<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="18289936" ns="0" title="Anna De Souza"><revisions><rev revid="447334603" parentid="415297048" user="Hammersoft" timestamp="2011-08-29T16:05:52Z" comment="rm ref to deleted article"><diff from="415297048" to="447334603" xml:space="preserve">&lt;tr&gt;
  &lt;td colspan=&quot;2&quot; class=&quot;diff-lineno&quot;&gt;Line 54:&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;td colspan=&quot;2&quot; class=&quot;diff-lineno&quot;&gt;Line 54:&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
  &lt;td class=&quot;diff-marker&quot;&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;td class=&quot;diff-context&quot;&gt;&lt;div&gt;Meanwhile, Matthew also tried to kiss Anna after they closed a successful business deal. However, she pulled away. She admitted that she wanted him but told him they could only have a business relationship, unaware that Carl had not dumped Lexi. Matthew asked if he was supposed to hide his feelings for her, and she replied he would have to if he wanted their current relationship to continue. Undeterred, Matthew continued to chase Anna, despite being turned down a second time.&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;td class=&quot;diff-marker&quot;&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;td class=&quot;diff-context&quot;&gt;&lt;div&gt;Meanwhile, Matthew also tried to kiss Anna after they closed a successful business deal. However, she pulled away. She admitted that she wanted him but told him they could only have a business relationship, unaware that Carl had not dumped Lexi. Matthew asked if he was supposed to hide his feelings for her, and she replied he would have to if he wanted their current relationship to continue. Undeterred, Matthew continued to chase Anna, despite being turned down a second time.&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
  &lt;td class=&quot;diff-marker&quot;&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;td class=&quot;diff-context&quot;&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;td class=&quot;diff-marker&quot;&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;td class=&quot;diff-context&quot;&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
  &lt;td class=&quot;diff-marker&quot;&gt;−&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;td class=&quot;diff-deletedline&quot;&gt;&lt;div&gt;Anna and Carl's rivalry was back, and nastier than ever, with them soon getting into a bidding war for &lt;span class=&quot;diffchange diffchange-inline&quot;&gt;[[List of residences in Emmerdale#Mill Cottage|Mill Cottage]]. &lt;/span&gt;Annoyed, Carl complained to Donald, who was incensed to discover Anna was out with Matthew, who he felt was a troublemaker and unsuitable for his daughter. In retaliation, Donald offered to buy Mill Cottage for Carl and Lexi.&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;td class=&quot;diff-marker&quot;&gt;+&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;td class=&quot;diff-addedline&quot;&gt;&lt;div&gt;Anna and Carl's rivalry was back, and nastier than ever, with them soon getting into a bidding war for &lt;span class=&quot;diffchange diffchange-inline&quot;&gt;Mill Cottage. &lt;/span&gt;Annoyed, Carl complained to Donald, who was incensed to discover Anna was out with Matthew, who he felt was a troublemaker and unsuitable for his daughter. In retaliation, Donald offered to buy Mill Cottage for Carl and Lexi.&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
  &lt;td class=&quot;diff-marker&quot;&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;td class=&quot;diff-context&quot;&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;td class=&quot;diff-marker&quot;&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;td class=&quot;diff-context&quot;&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
  &lt;td class=&quot;diff-marker&quot;&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;td class=&quot;diff-context&quot;&gt;&lt;div&gt;Later, Anna guessed that Carl had betrayed De Souza Enterprises by sending a rich client to King and Sons. Disappointed, Donald bought Carl out and he returned to King &amp;amp; Sons. Donald suffered a heart attack due to the stress and another argument with Anna. However, during his recovery in hospital, he and Anna made up, and Donald told Anna that he wanted to sign De Souza Enterprises over to her, even calling his [[Solicitor]] to bring the contract to the hospital. Much to his surprise, Anna tore the contract up and stated her intention to prove herself before taking ownership of the company. Reunited, Donald and Anna began to plot their revenge against the Kings.&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;td class=&quot;diff-marker&quot;&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;td class=&quot;diff-context&quot;&gt;&lt;div&gt;Later, Anna guessed that Carl had betrayed De Souza Enterprises by sending a rich client to King and Sons. Disappointed, Donald bought Carl out and he returned to King &amp;amp; Sons. Donald suffered a heart attack due to the stress and another argument with Anna. However, during his recovery in hospital, he and Anna made up, and Donald told Anna that he wanted to sign De Souza Enterprises over to her, even calling his [[Solicitor]] to bring the contract to the hospital. Much to his surprise, Anna tore the contract up and stated her intention to prove herself before taking ownership of the company. Reunited, Donald and Anna began to plot their revenge against the Kings.&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
  &lt;td colspan=&quot;2&quot; class=&quot;diff-lineno&quot;&gt;Line 62:&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;td colspan=&quot;2&quot; class=&quot;diff-lineno&quot;&gt;Line 62:&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
  &lt;td class=&quot;diff-marker&quot;&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;td class=&quot;diff-context&quot;&gt;&lt;div&gt;Anna and Matthew continued spending time together, and she soon had trouble with her feelings for him. Matthew was particularly touched when Anna got him a new watch after his old one was ruined and retrieved the engraving from the old one, as he explained that his father had given him the watch on his 21st birthday and it held a lot of sentimental value. No longer able to deny the chemistry between them, the pair finally slept together, and proceeded to start a secret relationship. Donald, unknowingly, offered Anna's services on a business trip to [[Warsaw]], as a Consultant, thinking Anna could get some valuable inside information about King &amp;amp; Sons for their revenge plan. What he didn't expect was Anna admitting to him that she had fallen in love with Matthew. A furious Donald shunned Anna, telling her he'd ruin the Kings with or without her help, and kept information that she thought she had destroyed. Matthew told Anna that he returned her feelings, telling her he loved her more than he imagined possible, and they agreed to start again. When Matthew returned to Warsaw to complete the business deal, Donald begged Anna to end her relationship with him and threatened to tell Matthew the reason why Anna got close to him in the first place.&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;td class=&quot;diff-marker&quot;&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;td class=&quot;diff-context&quot;&gt;&lt;div&gt;Anna and Matthew continued spending time together, and she soon had trouble with her feelings for him. Matthew was particularly touched when Anna got him a new watch after his old one was ruined and retrieved the engraving from the old one, as he explained that his father had given him the watch on his 21st birthday and it held a lot of sentimental value. No longer able to deny the chemistry between them, the pair finally slept together, and proceeded to start a secret relationship. Donald, unknowingly, offered Anna's services on a business trip to [[Warsaw]], as a Consultant, thinking Anna could get some valuable inside information about King &amp;amp; Sons for their revenge plan. What he didn't expect was Anna admitting to him that she had fallen in love with Matthew. A furious Donald shunned Anna, telling her he'd ruin the Kings with or without her help, and kept information that she thought she had destroyed. Matthew told Anna that he returned her feelings, telling her he loved her more than he imagined possible, and they agreed to start again. When Matthew returned to Warsaw to complete the business deal, Donald begged Anna to end her relationship with him and threatened to tell Matthew the reason why Anna got close to him in the first place.&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
  &lt;td class=&quot;diff-marker&quot;&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;td class=&quot;diff-context&quot;&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;td class=&quot;diff-marker&quot;&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;td class=&quot;diff-context&quot;&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
  &lt;td class=&quot;diff-marker&quot;&gt;−&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;td class=&quot;diff-deletedline&quot;&gt;&lt;div&gt;When Matthew returned, Anna knew she had to confess before Donald told Matthew. Angry, Matthew initially dumped her but listened when she insisted she would turn her back on Donald, and asked him to marry her. He happily accepted, and the news was broken to Donald, Jimmy, and Carl. The next day, Matthew proposed to Anna with an antique engagement ring as she moved her belongings to &lt;span class=&quot;diffchange diffchange-inline&quot;&gt;[[List of residences in Emmerdale#Home Farm|Home Farm]]. &lt;/span&gt;A party was planned, to celebrate both the engagement, and the successful deal with Polek Haulage. Donald crashed the party, announcing to everyone that Anna was only marrying Matthew to ruin the Kings from the inside. Matthew angrily retorted that Donald had tried to buy him off, and convinced his brothers that Donald was lying. Donald threatened Anna that he would disinherit her if she didn't break off the engagement, and she furiously insisted that she choose Matthew, and ordered him to leave. Hating to see his fiancee so upset, Matthew told Anna that the only thing that mattered was them, and planned to confront Donald alone.&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;td class=&quot;diff-marker&quot;&gt;+&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;td class=&quot;diff-addedline&quot;&gt;&lt;div&gt;When Matthew returned, Anna knew she had to confess before Donald told Matthew. Angry, Matthew initially dumped her but listened when she insisted she would turn her back on Donald, and asked him to marry her. He happily accepted, and the news was broken to Donald, Jimmy, and Carl. The next day, Matthew proposed to Anna with an antique engagement ring as she moved her belongings to &lt;span class=&quot;diffchange diffchange-inline&quot;&gt;Home Farm. &lt;/span&gt;A party was planned, to celebrate both the engagement, and the successful deal with Polek Haulage. Donald crashed the party, announcing to everyone that Anna was only marrying Matthew to ruin the Kings from the inside. Matthew angrily retorted that Donald had tried to buy him off, and convinced his brothers that Donald was lying. Donald threatened Anna that he would disinherit her if she didn't break off the engagement, and she furiously insisted that she choose Matthew, and ordered him to leave. Hating to see his fiancee so upset, Matthew told Anna that the only thing that mattered was them, and planned to confront Donald alone.&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
  &lt;td class=&quot;diff-marker&quot;&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;td class=&quot;diff-context&quot;&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;td class=&quot;diff-marker&quot;&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;td class=&quot;diff-context&quot;&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
  &lt;td class=&quot;diff-marker&quot;&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;td class=&quot;diff-context&quot;&gt;&lt;div&gt;Matthew's visit to Donald did not end well, as Donald had a heart attack after Matthew confronted him at Holdgate Farm. Donald began to suffer chest pains but Matthew, thinking he was making it up, refused to give him his medication until he agreed to attend the wedding. Donald made a final plea, and fell to the floor, dead. Matthew, panicked, fled the scene and Donald's body was found the next day by cleaners [[Betty Eagleton]] and [[Laurel Thomas]], who contacted Anna and the authorities.  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;td class=&quot;diff-marker&quot;&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;td class=&quot;diff-context&quot;&gt;&lt;div&gt;Matthew's visit to Donald did not end well, as Donald had a heart attack after Matthew confronted him at Holdgate Farm. Donald began to suffer chest pains but Matthew, thinking he was making it up, refused to give him his medication until he agreed to attend the wedding. Donald made a final plea, and fell to the floor, dead. Matthew, panicked, fled the scene and Donald's body was found the next day by cleaners [[Betty Eagleton]] and [[Laurel Thomas]], who contacted Anna and the authorities.  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
</diff></rev></revisions></page></pages></query><query-continue><revisions rvstartid="415297048" /></query-continue></api>
