<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="18737284" ns="0" title="Thomas Truax"><revisions><rev revid="411667976" parentid="411667948" user="Hammersoft" timestamp="2011-02-02T22:40:16Z" comment="Undid revision 411667948 by [[Special:Contributions/Tomtruax|Tomtruax]] ([[User talk:Tomtruax|talk]])"><diff from="411667948" to="411667976" xml:space="preserve">&lt;tr&gt;
  &lt;td colspan=&quot;2&quot; class=&quot;diff-lineno&quot;&gt;Line 21:&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;td colspan=&quot;2&quot; class=&quot;diff-lineno&quot;&gt;Line 21:&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
  &lt;td class=&quot;diff-marker&quot;&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;td class=&quot;diff-context&quot;&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;td class=&quot;diff-marker&quot;&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;td class=&quot;diff-context&quot;&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
  &lt;td class=&quot;diff-marker&quot;&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;td class=&quot;diff-context&quot;&gt;&lt;div&gt;==Biography==&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;td class=&quot;diff-marker&quot;&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;td class=&quot;diff-context&quot;&gt;&lt;div&gt;==Biography==&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
  &lt;td class=&quot;diff-marker&quot;&gt;−&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;td class=&quot;diff-deletedline&quot;&gt;&lt;div&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;diffchange diffchange-inline&quot;&gt;tom's hair makes babies cry. he uses moose sperm shampoo, which is &lt;/span&gt;a &lt;span class=&quot;diffchange diffchange-inline&quot;&gt;popular brand &lt;/span&gt;in &lt;span class=&quot;diffchange diffchange-inline&quot;&gt;sweden &lt;/span&gt;and &lt;/div&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;td class=&quot;diff-marker&quot;&gt;+&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;td class=&quot;diff-addedline&quot;&gt;&lt;div&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;diffchange diffchange-inline&quot;&gt;He first came to prominence as &lt;/span&gt;a &lt;span class=&quot;diffchange diffchange-inline&quot;&gt;solo performer &lt;/span&gt;in &lt;span class=&quot;diffchange diffchange-inline&quot;&gt;the 1990s in New York as one of a group of musicians and songwriters (including [[Lach]], [[Jeff Lewis]], [[Curtis Eller]], and [[Beck]]) who made up the [[antifolk]] movement based around the Sidewalk Cafe on the Lower East Side of Manhattan. Truax's emergence as a solo act came after years of fronting bands (most notably Like Wow).&amp;lt;ref&amp;gt;Aaron, P.&quot;Thomas Truax&quot; Allmusic [{{Allmusic|class=artist|id=p554775|pure_url=yes}}], 2004.&amp;lt;/ref&amp;gt; The move was in part to remove the need to rely on other people to perform and to embark in a new direction that would distinguish his act from the hundreds of bands and singer-songwriters active in New York. This new direction involved the construction and playing of unique instruments, as well as more traditional singer-songwriter style songs. The 'inventor' side of his musical act drew on his work as an animator on MTV's [[Celebrity Death Match]] and a fascination since early childhood with building objects out of whatever materials he had available. Thomas's use of 'primitive' technology, the often fantastical elements of his songs &lt;/span&gt;and &lt;span class=&quot;diffchange diffchange-inline&quot;&gt;gothic overtones (his website talks of his instruments 'as though plucked straight from the mind of Tim Burton') have led to him being linked to the subgenre of [[steampunk]].  &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
  &lt;td class=&quot;diff-marker&quot;&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;td class=&quot;diff-context&quot;&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;td class=&quot;diff-marker&quot;&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;td class=&quot;diff-context&quot;&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
  &lt;td colspan=&quot;2&quot;&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;td class=&quot;diff-marker&quot;&gt;+&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;td class=&quot;diff-addedline&quot;&gt;&lt;div&gt;Truax's first two instruments were the [[Cadillac Beatspinner Wheel]] and the [[Hornicator]], the former being a system of spinning wheels, metal spokes and small cymbals, which, through the use of various contact mics, 'beats out' through the PA a primitive drum beat that forms the backing to songs that Thomas then plays on guitar. Its large size made the Beatspinner Wheel unsuitable for touring, so Truax created a smaller version, entitled 'Sister Spinster' that he uses to this day. The Hornicator started life as an old gramophone record horn, before Truax added a set of strings, a kazoo and a microphone. Here Thomas beats out the rhythm on the horn's metal casing (using a ringed finger to create a 'click' and other fingers to create a contrastive 'thud') which is then repeated through the use of a looper pedal that records the beat and loops it over the PA, allowing Thomas to add more layers of other instrumentation (through the strings and other implements attached to the Hornicator). Finally Thomas sings a vocal through a microphone attached to the instrument. &lt;/div&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
  &lt;td colspan=&quot;2&quot;&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;td class=&quot;diff-marker&quot;&gt;+&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;td class=&quot;diff-addedline&quot;&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
  &lt;td colspan=&quot;2&quot;&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;td class=&quot;diff-marker&quot;&gt;+&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;td class=&quot;diff-addedline&quot;&gt;&lt;div&gt;Other instruments work as variations on automatic rhythms and looped beats: the [[Stringaling]] features a vaguely bongo-like drum at the top of a length of clothes' drier tubing to which is attached a variety of musical devices with pull-strings; Mary Poppins features a metal column attached to which are two arms that fly out to the side and spin, creating a train-like rhythm; the Backbeater, made up of several rotating spokes, straps on to Thomas' back and spins to create a low rhythm. Some songs do not feature any of his inventions, most notably 'Inside the Internet' which is played solely on guitar, and 'The Butterfly &amp;amp; The Entomologist', which is again played on a guitar, albeit with the use of a pocket fan that Thomas uses to hit the strings to produce an eerie effect.  Common themes in Thomas's songs include love, loneliness, travel, the animal kingdom, nature and technology.&amp;lt;ref&amp;gt;Baker, J.&quot;Toys, Bugs and Rock and Roll&quot; Nature Magazine [http://www.thomastruax.com/TruaxNATUREmag6-3-08.pdf] Vol 452, March 6, 2008.&amp;lt;/ref&amp;gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
  &lt;td colspan=&quot;2&quot;&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;td class=&quot;diff-marker&quot;&gt;+&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;td class=&quot;diff-addedline&quot;&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
  &lt;td colspan=&quot;2&quot;&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;td class=&quot;diff-marker&quot;&gt;+&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;td class=&quot;diff-addedline&quot;&gt;&lt;div&gt;Truax has once been challenged to show how the making of an instrument come about, given many items retrieved from a recycle bin within 15 minutes, he produced a rhythmic invention looped through effects with water and rubber bands.&amp;lt;ref&amp;gt;&quot;Weird Science V.03&quot; SUPERSWEET [http://www.supersweet.org/index.php?option=com_content&amp;amp;task=view&amp;amp;id=2044&amp;amp;Itemid=30] 19 June 2009&amp;lt;/ref&amp;gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
  &lt;td colspan=&quot;2&quot;&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;td class=&quot;diff-marker&quot;&gt;+&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;td class=&quot;diff-addedline&quot;&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
  &lt;td colspan=&quot;2&quot;&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;td class=&quot;diff-marker&quot;&gt;+&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;td class=&quot;diff-addedline&quot;&gt;&lt;div&gt;Though Truax usually only performs solo, his records contain songs with full band arrangements, along with his invented instruments. He has been featured in several music documentaries including Adam Clitheroe's 'One Man In The Band' (2008) and Gabriel Shalom's 'Instrumental'(2005).&amp;lt;ref&amp;gt;Howden, J. Kruger Magazine &quot;Q and A with Thomas Truax&quot; [http://www.krugermagazine.com/index.php?option=com_content&amp;amp;task=view&amp;amp;id=1424&amp;amp;Itemid=10994], February 2008&amp;lt;/ref&amp;gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
  &lt;td class=&quot;diff-marker&quot;&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;td class=&quot;diff-context&quot;&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;td class=&quot;diff-marker&quot;&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;td class=&quot;diff-context&quot;&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
  &lt;td class=&quot;diff-marker&quot;&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;td class=&quot;diff-context&quot;&gt;&lt;div&gt;==Singles==&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;td class=&quot;diff-marker&quot;&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;td class=&quot;diff-context&quot;&gt;&lt;div&gt;==Singles==&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
</diff></rev></revisions></page></pages></query><query-continue><revisions rvstartid="411667948" /></query-continue></api>
