<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="19389626" ns="0" title="Dave Harvey"><revisions><rev revid="420658833" parentid="420658268" user="Hammersoft" timestamp="2011-03-25T14:03:03Z" comment="Undid revision 420658268 by [[Special:Contributions/Harv24|Harv24]] ([[User talk:Harv24|talk]])"><diff from="420658268" to="420658833" xml:space="preserve">&lt;tr&gt;
  &lt;td colspan=&quot;2&quot; class=&quot;diff-lineno&quot;&gt;Line 1:&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;td colspan=&quot;2&quot; class=&quot;diff-lineno&quot;&gt;Line 1:&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
  &lt;td class=&quot;diff-marker&quot;&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;td class=&quot;diff-context&quot;&gt;&lt;div&gt;#REDIRECT [[David Harvey]]&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;td class=&quot;diff-marker&quot;&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;td class=&quot;diff-context&quot;&gt;&lt;div&gt;#REDIRECT [[David Harvey]]&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
  &lt;td class=&quot;diff-marker&quot;&gt;−&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;td class=&quot;diff-deletedline&quot;&gt;&lt;div&gt;David Michael Harvey (Dave Harvey) was born on Novemeber 15th, 1988 in Kingston ON. He grew up in Lyndhurst ON with his parents, Jack and Martha Harvey, and his two sisters, Laura and Louise Harvey. Harvey has lived in Ottawa from 2008 to present. Harvey graduated with honours from Algonquin College with a Police Foundations Diploma in 2009 and is currently going to Carleton University majoring in Pyschology and Minoring in Sociology. He plans on becomeing a Corrections Officer in British Columbia once he graduates in 2012, and later plans on becoming a Parole Officer. &lt;/div&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;td colspan=&quot;2&quot;&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
  &lt;td class=&quot;diff-marker&quot;&gt;−&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;td class=&quot;diff-deletedline&quot;&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;td colspan=&quot;2&quot;&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
  &lt;td class=&quot;diff-marker&quot;&gt;−&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;td class=&quot;diff-deletedline&quot;&gt;&lt;div&gt;Harvey has worked many different jobs in his life so far, such as two summers as a maintainance worker at Charleston Lake Provincial Park in 05 and 06, a constuction labourer from 07 to present, and other random jobs. He has also been a Canadian Forces reservist with the Brockville Rifles Primary Reserve Regiment from 07 to present. Harvey was a member of the security unit responsible for the G8 and G20 security in June of 2010 in Huntsville and Toronto. &lt;/div&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;td colspan=&quot;2&quot;&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
  &lt;td class=&quot;diff-marker&quot;&gt;−&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;td class=&quot;diff-deletedline&quot;&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;td colspan=&quot;2&quot;&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
  &lt;td class=&quot;diff-marker&quot;&gt;−&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;td class=&quot;diff-deletedline&quot;&gt;&lt;div&gt;In August 2010, Harvey hitchhicked across Canada in two separate phases. The first phase of Harvey's trip was from Joyceville ON to Victoria BC. He completed this phase in about 9 days, and spent some extra time at Lake Louise, Alberta. He stayed in Victora with his friend, Eric Dopson, for three days before flying across the counrty to St. John's NFLD. He then hitchhicked back to his then girl friends, Julie Patterson, house in Elgin ON. This phase of the trip took Harvey 5 days to complete. &lt;/div&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;td colspan=&quot;2&quot;&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
  &lt;td class=&quot;diff-marker&quot;&gt;−&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;td class=&quot;diff-deletedline&quot;&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;td colspan=&quot;2&quot;&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
  &lt;td class=&quot;diff-marker&quot;&gt;−&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;td class=&quot;diff-deletedline&quot;&gt;&lt;div&gt;Harvey is currently planing a second hitchhicking trip back to Victoria BC in May, 2011. This time, he plans on traveling down to New Orleans, visit the Grand Canyon in Arizona, and travel up the pacific coast to Dopsons place in Victoia again. &lt;/div&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;td colspan=&quot;2&quot;&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
  &lt;td class=&quot;diff-marker&quot;&gt;−&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;td class=&quot;diff-deletedline&quot;&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;td colspan=&quot;2&quot;&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
  &lt;td class=&quot;diff-marker&quot;&gt;−&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;td class=&quot;diff-deletedline&quot;&gt;&lt;div&gt;Harvey loves to play many different sports. His favourites are hockey, downhill skiing, golf, squash, badminton, and soccer. Harvey also enjoys playing Texas Holdem Poker.&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;td colspan=&quot;2&quot;&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
</diff></rev></revisions></page></pages></query><query-continue><revisions rvstartid="420658268" /></query-continue></api>
