<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="29218872" ns="0" title="Mara Clara (2010 TV series)"><revisions><rev revid="414677025" parentid="414676145" user="Hammersoft" timestamp="2011-02-18T21:02:11Z" comment=""><diff from="414676145" to="414677025" xml:space="preserve">&lt;tr&gt;
  &lt;td colspan=&quot;2&quot; class=&quot;diff-lineno&quot;&gt;Line 38:&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;td colspan=&quot;2&quot; class=&quot;diff-lineno&quot;&gt;Line 38:&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
  &lt;td class=&quot;diff-marker&quot;&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;td class=&quot;diff-context&quot;&gt;&lt;div&gt;===Story===&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;td class=&quot;diff-marker&quot;&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;td class=&quot;diff-context&quot;&gt;&lt;div&gt;===Story===&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
  &lt;td class=&quot;diff-marker&quot;&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;td class=&quot;diff-context&quot;&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;td class=&quot;diff-marker&quot;&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;td class=&quot;diff-context&quot;&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
  &lt;td class=&quot;diff-marker&quot;&gt;−&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;td class=&quot;diff-deletedline&quot;&gt;&lt;div&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;diffchange diffchange-inline&quot;&gt;Tenten Ramos &lt;/span&gt;and &lt;span class=&quot;diffchange diffchange-inline&quot;&gt;Pinong &lt;/span&gt;is a couple, but she breaks up with him, for a scholarship in America. Gary becomes heartbroken, and falls in love with Alvira's poor friend, Susan, in the thought that she may not return, but it was short lived. Upon Alvira's arrival after years of studying abroad, all his feelings for her came back and he sought to win her back, but was heartbroken to find out she's engaged to a wealthy businessman, Amante Del Valle. He became drunk with anger and impregnated Susan on a one-night stand. Lupe, Gary's mother, blamed Susan for everything, insisting she seduced him from getting back with Alvira. Alvira and Amante got married, with Gary's anger turning to total obsession for Alvira. Months passed, Susan and Alvira gave birth on the same date and hospital. Gary planned his revenge, and commands Karlo to kidnap Alvira's baby. He rejected at first, but a debt owed made him do otherwise. He became afraid when Gary was caught by the police and sent to jail, accidently switching Alvira's baby and Susan's baby. Susan's daughter, was brought up to the Del Valles and named '''Clara''' and Alvira's baby, brought to the Davids was named '''Mara'''. Years passed, Clara grows up in a loving environment, spoiled; and Mara, grew up as a loving and smart girl, though mistreated by Lupe, and Gary, in jail. Susan works hard for Mara just to give her a good life. Their lives suddenly entwine when Mara becomes a scholar to a private school where Clara studies. Because of her poor stature, many people make fun of her; but her nice personality and high grades put her on top of the class. At first, Clara becomes angry that someone is taking her spotlight in being the smartest of the class. Clara, the most popular in the school, is insecure inside. There Mara meets Christian, a boy she helped in the mall when he almost got caught; and she catches his eye. Through the school, they become good friends. But unbeknownst to all, he likes her. At first, Clara despises Mara and tries to put her down, but when they are partnered in a contest, they eventually become good friends even after they win. Even when their friends opposed their friendship, they remained friends. But changed when both of them ran for president in their school election. Mara won by popular vote. Clara couldn't accept her defeat, she became angry at Mara. Her jealousy turned to hatred, which added when she found out that Christian likes Mara. She grew up getting what she wanted. Gary, ambitious to take back Alvira worked for Lover Boy, a gang leader, until he killed Karlo, Gary's younger brother, who reported to the police about their job. Karlo wasn't able to reveal the truth when he got shot and died. Gary blamed Mara for Karlo's death, that Gary told Clara about his uncle keeping their secret for her, not knowing Karlo revealed this to Clara already. She couldn't accept this truth, she did things to make Mara's life a living hell, even embarrassing Susan in front of everybody. But the bond that Mara had with her mother, made Clara's deeds all to waste. On the other side, the truth of the diary's secret is starting to come out. Lupe's dream of Karlo; Clara's DNA test and her accident revealed the truth of the rightful owners. When Clara found out through the DNA test that she is the real David, she was devastated and sought to keep it to herself. But one day, when Lupe knew about Clara as her real granddaughter, visited her school which caused Clara's accident; and Mara was blamed and put to jail by Alvira. She needed blood transfusion, to their surprise that her blood didn't match theirs. Amante's curiosity went ahead of him when he saw Gary donated blood; and proved that Clara isn't their daughter through the DNA test and the diary Susan showed them. Alvira was shocked she jailed her own daughter, but couldn't accept the daughter she raised wasn't hers. But Gary would not leave without a fight for his daughter and  filed a case against the Del Valles, to claim what is his, and Mara and Clara was returned to their real families.&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;td class=&quot;diff-marker&quot;&gt;+&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;td class=&quot;diff-addedline&quot;&gt;&lt;div&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;diffchange diffchange-inline&quot;&gt;Alvira &lt;/span&gt;and &lt;span class=&quot;diffchange diffchange-inline&quot;&gt;Gary &lt;/span&gt;is a couple, but she breaks up with him, for a scholarship in America. Gary becomes heartbroken, and falls in love with Alvira's poor friend, Susan, in the thought that she may not return, but it was short lived. Upon Alvira's arrival after years of studying abroad, all his feelings for her came back and he sought to win her back, but was heartbroken to find out she's engaged to a wealthy businessman, Amante Del Valle. He became drunk with anger and impregnated Susan on a one-night stand. Lupe, Gary's mother, blamed Susan for everything, insisting she seduced him from getting back with Alvira. Alvira and Amante got married, with Gary's anger turning to total obsession for Alvira. Months passed, Susan and Alvira gave birth on the same date and hospital. Gary planned his revenge, and commands Karlo to kidnap Alvira's baby. He rejected at first, but a debt owed made him do otherwise. He became afraid when Gary was caught by the police and sent to jail, accidently switching Alvira's baby and Susan's baby. Susan's daughter, was brought up to the Del Valles and named '''Clara''' and Alvira's baby, brought to the Davids was named '''Mara'''. Years passed, Clara grows up in a loving environment, spoiled; and Mara, grew up as a loving and smart girl, though mistreated by Lupe, and Gary, in jail. Susan works hard for Mara just to give her a good life. Their lives suddenly entwine when Mara becomes a scholar to a private school where Clara studies. Because of her poor stature, many people make fun of her; but her nice personality and high grades put her on top of the class. At first, Clara becomes angry that someone is taking her spotlight in being the smartest of the class. Clara, the most popular in the school, is insecure inside. There Mara meets Christian, a boy she helped in the mall when he almost got caught; and she catches his eye. Through the school, they become good friends. But unbeknownst to all, he likes her. At first, Clara despises Mara and tries to put her down, but when they are partnered in a contest, they eventually become good friends even after they win. Even when their friends opposed their friendship, they remained friends. But changed when both of them ran for president in their school election. Mara won by popular vote. Clara couldn't accept her defeat, she became angry at Mara. Her jealousy turned to hatred, which added when she found out that Christian likes Mara. She grew up getting what she wanted. Gary, ambitious to take back Alvira worked for Lover Boy, a gang leader, until he killed Karlo, Gary's younger brother, who reported to the police about their job. Karlo wasn't able to reveal the truth when he got shot and died. Gary blamed Mara for Karlo's death, that Gary told Clara about his uncle keeping their secret for her, not knowing Karlo revealed this to Clara already. She couldn't accept this truth, she did things to make Mara's life a living hell, even embarrassing Susan in front of everybody. But the bond that Mara had with her mother, made Clara's deeds all to waste. On the other side, the truth of the diary's secret is starting to come out. Lupe's dream of Karlo; Clara's DNA test and her accident revealed the truth of the rightful owners. When Clara found out through the DNA test that she is the real David, she was devastated and sought to keep it to herself. But one day, when Lupe knew about Clara as her real granddaughter, visited her school which caused Clara's accident; and Mara was blamed and put to jail by Alvira. She needed blood transfusion, to their surprise that her blood didn't match theirs. Amante's curiosity went ahead of him when he saw Gary donated blood; and proved that Clara isn't their daughter through the DNA test and the diary Susan showed them. Alvira was shocked she jailed her own daughter, but couldn't accept the daughter she raised wasn't hers. But Gary would not leave without a fight for his daughter and  filed a case against the Del Valles, to claim what is his, and Mara and Clara was returned to their real families.&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
  &lt;td class=&quot;diff-marker&quot;&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;td class=&quot;diff-context&quot;&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;td class=&quot;diff-marker&quot;&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;td class=&quot;diff-context&quot;&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
  &lt;td class=&quot;diff-marker&quot;&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;td class=&quot;diff-context&quot;&gt;&lt;div&gt;===Book Two===&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;td class=&quot;diff-marker&quot;&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;td class=&quot;diff-context&quot;&gt;&lt;div&gt;===Book Two===&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
  &lt;td colspan=&quot;2&quot; class=&quot;diff-lineno&quot;&gt;Line 50:&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;td colspan=&quot;2&quot; class=&quot;diff-lineno&quot;&gt;Line 50:&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
  &lt;td class=&quot;diff-marker&quot;&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;td class=&quot;diff-context&quot;&gt;&lt;div&gt;*[[Julia Montes]] as Clara Del Valle/Clara David - Clara is a sassy, rich, beautiful and smart girl, but very insecure and ill-tempered. Because of her parents lack of attention, she grows up spoiled and brattish. She meets Mara and becomes friends with her until she felt threatened by Mara's popularity in the school, her parents and especially Christian, whom she liked since they were kids. The more she got jealous, the more she hated Mara, and sought various ways to destroy Mara's reputation and life. She is the first one to find out about the hidden secret of David Brothers (Gary and Karlo). Her life suddenly changed when she turned out to be a David, and blames Mara for her life. Until now, she still can't accept being Clara David and will find a way to take her life back from Mara.&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;td class=&quot;diff-marker&quot;&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;td class=&quot;diff-context&quot;&gt;&lt;div&gt;*[[Julia Montes]] as Clara Del Valle/Clara David - Clara is a sassy, rich, beautiful and smart girl, but very insecure and ill-tempered. Because of her parents lack of attention, she grows up spoiled and brattish. She meets Mara and becomes friends with her until she felt threatened by Mara's popularity in the school, her parents and especially Christian, whom she liked since they were kids. The more she got jealous, the more she hated Mara, and sought various ways to destroy Mara's reputation and life. She is the first one to find out about the hidden secret of David Brothers (Gary and Karlo). Her life suddenly changed when she turned out to be a David, and blames Mara for her life. Until now, she still can't accept being Clara David and will find a way to take her life back from Mara.&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
  &lt;td class=&quot;diff-marker&quot;&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;td class=&quot;diff-context&quot;&gt;&lt;div&gt;*[[Albie Casiño]] as Christian Torralba - Christian is the childhood friend of Clara. An only child, he has an alcoholic mother, Vanessa, when his father left them. He falls in love with Mara when he meets her as she changed his life. He secretly becomes her night in shining armor and helps Mara in everything becoming her closest camaraderie when she is in trouble. His affection to Mara made Clara jealous, destroying their friendship when she mistreated Mara. As time progresses, Christian confesses his feelings to Mara, but she rejects him. Clara takes the chance with the thought of slowly getting the things that what she believed was stolen by Mara from her.&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;td class=&quot;diff-marker&quot;&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;td class=&quot;diff-context&quot;&gt;&lt;div&gt;*[[Albie Casiño]] as Christian Torralba - Christian is the childhood friend of Clara. An only child, he has an alcoholic mother, Vanessa, when his father left them. He falls in love with Mara when he meets her as she changed his life. He secretly becomes her night in shining armor and helps Mara in everything becoming her closest camaraderie when she is in trouble. His affection to Mara made Clara jealous, destroying their friendship when she mistreated Mara. As time progresses, Christian confesses his feelings to Mara, but she rejects him. Clara takes the chance with the thought of slowly getting the things that what she believed was stolen by Mara from her.&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
  &lt;td class=&quot;diff-marker&quot;&gt;−&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;td class=&quot;diff-deletedline&quot;&gt;&lt;div&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;diffchange diffchange-inline&quot;&gt;*[[Art Glendale Ramos]] &lt;/span&gt;as Eris Guzman - Eris is Christian's friend. A poor boy working in the coffee shop owned by Christian's mom. A good friend, he listens and talks to Christian about anything, and even helps him with his problems. He becomes good friends with Mara. He is secretly in love with Clara, although she's very mean to him.&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;td class=&quot;diff-marker&quot;&gt;+&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;td class=&quot;diff-addedline&quot;&gt;&lt;div&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;diffchange diffchange-inline&quot;&gt;*[[John Manalo]] &lt;/span&gt;as Eris Guzman - Eris is Christian's friend. A poor boy working in the coffee shop owned by Christian's mom. A good friend, he listens and talks to Christian about anything, and even helps him with his problems. He becomes good friends with Mara. He is secretly in love with Clara, although she's very mean to him.&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
  &lt;td class=&quot;diff-marker&quot;&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;td class=&quot;diff-context&quot;&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;td class=&quot;diff-marker&quot;&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;td class=&quot;diff-context&quot;&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
  &lt;td class=&quot;diff-marker&quot;&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;td class=&quot;diff-context&quot;&gt;&lt;div&gt;===Supporting Cast===&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;td class=&quot;diff-marker&quot;&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;td class=&quot;diff-context&quot;&gt;&lt;div&gt;===Supporting Cast===&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
</diff></rev></revisions></page></pages></query><query-continue><revisions rvstartid="414676145" /></query-continue></api>
