<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="33482934" ns="0" title="Chakra Linux"><revisions><rev revid="456664188" parentid="456663895" user="SF007" timestamp="2011-10-21T11:43:32Z" comment="+ internal links"><diff from="456663895" to="456664188" xml:space="preserve">&lt;tr&gt;
  &lt;td colspan=&quot;2&quot; class=&quot;diff-lineno&quot;&gt;Line 29:&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;td colspan=&quot;2&quot; class=&quot;diff-lineno&quot;&gt;Line 29:&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
  &lt;td class=&quot;diff-marker&quot;&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;td class=&quot;diff-context&quot;&gt;&lt;div&gt;}}&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;td class=&quot;diff-marker&quot;&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;td class=&quot;diff-context&quot;&gt;&lt;div&gt;}}&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
  &lt;td class=&quot;diff-marker&quot;&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;td class=&quot;diff-context&quot;&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;td class=&quot;diff-marker&quot;&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;td class=&quot;diff-context&quot;&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
  &lt;td class=&quot;diff-marker&quot;&gt;−&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;td class=&quot;diff-deletedline&quot;&gt;&lt;div&gt;The Chakra Project is a &lt;span class=&quot;diffchange diffchange-inline&quot;&gt;semi-rolling release GNU/Linux distribution &lt;/span&gt;which was formerly based off on &lt;span class=&quot;diffchange diffchange-inline&quot;&gt;Arch Linux. &lt;/span&gt;Chakra GNU/Linux uses the KDE Desktop Manager and QT libraries for its graphics system. The Chakra Project grew out what was once the KDEmod group of packages which was a set of packages that were compiled from source code and were specifically optimized for Arch Linux. After a few years, the developers of the KDEmod project had the idea to create their own distribution which was primarily based off of Arch Linux and to use their KDEmod packages as the desktop manager instead of the default Arch built packages. As time progressed the developers wanted to introduce more radical changes to their base system, but this was becoming increasingly complex and painful since these modifications caused troubles with the Arch Linux package manager called &lt;span class=&quot;diffchange diffchange-inline&quot;&gt;Pacman, &lt;/span&gt;among other things. In early 2010, the developers decided that they would be moving away from the Arch Linux base and would create their own base, while still adhering to the Arch Linux philosophy and the &lt;span class=&quot;diffchange diffchange-inline&quot;&gt;KISS Principle &lt;/span&gt;(Keep It Simple Stupid). In May of 2010 the developers released the first edition of Chakra GNU/Linux, which was called Phoix and by the end of 2010 support for KDEmod was officially ended and full focus was given to the Chakra distribution. The newest release is entitled Aida and was released in April of this year.&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;td class=&quot;diff-marker&quot;&gt;+&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;td class=&quot;diff-addedline&quot;&gt;&lt;div&gt;The Chakra Project is a &lt;span class=&quot;diffchange diffchange-inline&quot;&gt;semi-[[rolling release]] [[GNU/Linux distribution]] &lt;/span&gt;which was formerly based off on &lt;span class=&quot;diffchange diffchange-inline&quot;&gt;[[Arch Linux]]. &lt;/span&gt;Chakra GNU/Linux uses the KDE Desktop Manager and QT libraries for its graphics system. The Chakra Project grew out what was once the KDEmod group of packages which was a set of packages that were compiled from source code and were specifically optimized for Arch Linux. After a few years, the developers of the KDEmod project had the idea to create their own distribution which was primarily based off of Arch Linux and to use their KDEmod packages as the desktop manager instead of the default Arch built packages. As time progressed the developers wanted to introduce more radical changes to their base system, but this was becoming increasingly complex and painful since these modifications caused troubles with the Arch Linux package manager called &lt;span class=&quot;diffchange diffchange-inline&quot;&gt;[[Pacman (package manager)|Pacman]], &lt;/span&gt;among other things. In early 2010, the developers decided that they would be moving away from the Arch Linux base and would create their own base, while still adhering to the Arch Linux philosophy and the &lt;span class=&quot;diffchange diffchange-inline&quot;&gt;[[KISS Principle]] &lt;/span&gt;(Keep It Simple Stupid). In May of 2010 the developers released the first edition of Chakra GNU/Linux, which was called Phoix and by the end of 2010 support for KDEmod was officially ended and full focus was given to the Chakra distribution. The newest release is entitled Aida and was released in April of this year.&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
  &lt;td class=&quot;diff-marker&quot;&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;td class=&quot;diff-context&quot;&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;td class=&quot;diff-marker&quot;&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;td class=&quot;diff-context&quot;&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
  &lt;td class=&quot;diff-marker&quot;&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;td class=&quot;diff-context&quot;&gt;&lt;div&gt;==External links==&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;td class=&quot;diff-marker&quot;&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;td class=&quot;diff-context&quot;&gt;&lt;div&gt;==External links==&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
</diff></rev></revisions></page></pages></query><query-continue><revisions rvstartid="456663895" /></query-continue></api>
