<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="638229" ns="0" title="Technical support"><revisions><rev revid="232907795" parentid="232907597" user="SF007" timestamp="2008-08-19T14:14:04Z" comment="reverting vandalism"><diff from="232907597" to="232907795" xml:space="preserve">&lt;tr&gt;
  &lt;td colspan=&quot;2&quot; class=&quot;diff-lineno&quot;&gt;Line 1:&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;td colspan=&quot;2&quot; class=&quot;diff-lineno&quot;&gt;Line 1:&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
  &lt;td class=&quot;diff-marker&quot;&gt;−&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;td class=&quot;diff-deletedline&quot;&gt;&lt;div&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;diffchange diffchange-inline&quot;&gt;WIKIPEDIA SUCKS!&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;td class=&quot;diff-marker&quot;&gt;+&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;td class=&quot;diff-addedline&quot;&gt;&lt;div&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;diffchange diffchange-inline&quot;&gt;[[Image:Attdevicesupportcenter.jpg|thumb|right|[[AT&amp;amp;T Mobility]] provides technical support for some of its [[mobile phone]]s through Device Support Centers.]]&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
  &lt;td colspan=&quot;2&quot;&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;td class=&quot;diff-marker&quot;&gt;+&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;td class=&quot;diff-addedline&quot;&gt;&lt;div&gt;'''Technical support''' (also ''tech support'') is a range of [[Customer service|services]] providing assistance with technology products such as mobile phones, televisions, [[computer]]s, or other electronic or mechanical goods. In general, technical support services attempt to help the user solve specific problems with a product—rather than providing training, customization, or other support services.&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
  &lt;td colspan=&quot;2&quot;&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;td class=&quot;diff-marker&quot;&gt;+&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;td class=&quot;diff-addedline&quot;&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
  &lt;td colspan=&quot;2&quot;&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;td class=&quot;diff-marker&quot;&gt;+&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;td class=&quot;diff-addedline&quot;&gt;&lt;div&gt;Most companies offer technical support for the products they sell, either freely available or for a fee.  Technical support may be delivered over the [[telephone]] or via various online media such as [[e-mail]] or a [[Web site]]. Larger organizations frequently have internal technical support available to their staff for computer related problem . The internet is also a good source for freely available tech support, where experienced users may provide advice and assistance with problems.  In addition, some fee-based service companies charge for premium technical support services. &amp;lt;ref&amp;gt; {{cite web|url=http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/uk_news/magazine/4387525.stm |title=Technical support for the neighbours |accessdate=2008-03-06 }}&amp;lt;/ref&amp;gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
  &lt;td colspan=&quot;2&quot;&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;td class=&quot;diff-marker&quot;&gt;+&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;td class=&quot;diff-addedline&quot;&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
  &lt;td colspan=&quot;2&quot;&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;td class=&quot;diff-marker&quot;&gt;+&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;td class=&quot;diff-addedline&quot;&gt;&lt;div&gt;&amp;lt;br /&amp;gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
  &lt;td colspan=&quot;2&quot;&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;td class=&quot;diff-marker&quot;&gt;+&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;td class=&quot;diff-addedline&quot;&gt;&lt;div&gt;==Coverage of support==&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
  &lt;td colspan=&quot;2&quot;&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;td class=&quot;diff-marker&quot;&gt;+&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;td class=&quot;diff-addedline&quot;&gt;&lt;div&gt;Technical support may be delivered by different technologies depending on the situation.  For example, [[direct question]]s can be addressed using [[Short message service|SMS]], email or fax; basic software problems can be addressed over the telephone or using remote support; while more complicated problems with equipment may need to be dealt with in person.&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
  &lt;td colspan=&quot;2&quot;&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;td class=&quot;diff-marker&quot;&gt;+&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;td class=&quot;diff-addedline&quot;&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
  &lt;td colspan=&quot;2&quot;&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;td class=&quot;diff-marker&quot;&gt;+&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;td class=&quot;diff-addedline&quot;&gt;&lt;div&gt;&amp;lt;br /&amp;gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
  &lt;td colspan=&quot;2&quot;&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;td class=&quot;diff-marker&quot;&gt;+&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;td class=&quot;diff-addedline&quot;&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
  &lt;td colspan=&quot;2&quot;&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;td class=&quot;diff-marker&quot;&gt;+&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;td class=&quot;diff-addedline&quot;&gt;&lt;div&gt;==Outsourcing Technical Support==&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
  &lt;td colspan=&quot;2&quot;&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;td class=&quot;diff-marker&quot;&gt;+&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;td class=&quot;diff-addedline&quot;&gt;&lt;div&gt;With the increasing use of technology in modern times, there is a growing requirement to provide technical support.  Many organizations locate their technical support departments or [[call centers]] in countries with lower costs.  There has also been a growth in companies specializing in providing technical support to other organizations.&amp;lt;ref&amp;gt; {{cite web|url=http://www.greatvoiceco.com/wp_maggiek.html |title=Call Centre Trends |accessdate=2008-05-02 |last=Berkley |first=Susan |coauthors=Maggie Klenke |work=The Great Voice Company }}&amp;lt;/ref&amp;gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
  &lt;td colspan=&quot;2&quot;&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;td class=&quot;diff-marker&quot;&gt;+&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;td class=&quot;diff-addedline&quot;&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
  &lt;td colspan=&quot;2&quot;&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;td class=&quot;diff-marker&quot;&gt;+&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;td class=&quot;diff-addedline&quot;&gt;&lt;div&gt;For businesses needing to provide technical support, [[outsourcing]] provides them with the ability to maintain a high availability of service. This comes as a result of peaks in call volumes during the day, periods of high activity due to the introduction of new products and maintenance service packs, and the necessity to provide consumers with a high level of service at a low cost to the business.&amp;lt;ref name=eHelp&amp;gt;{{cite web | url=http://www.e-help-desk.com/whitepaper0011.html | title= Outsourcing the Helpdesk | date= 2006| work= eHelp Desk Resource |accessdate= 2008-05-06 | }}&amp;lt;/ref&amp;gt; For businesses needing technical support assets, [[outsourcing]] enables their core employees to focus more on their work in order to maintain productivity.&amp;lt;ref name= perkins&amp;gt;{{cite web | author= Perkins, Bart | url=http://www.computerworld.com/printthis/2004/0,4814,97239,00.html | title= Outsourcing: First Ask Why?| date= 2004-11-08| work= [[Computerworld]] Management |accessdate= 2008-05-06 | }}&amp;lt;/ref&amp;gt;  It also enables them to utilize specialized personnel whose technical knowledge base and experience may exceed the scope of the business, thus providing a higher level of technical support to their employees. &lt;/div&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
  &lt;td colspan=&quot;2&quot;&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;td class=&quot;diff-marker&quot;&gt;+&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;td class=&quot;diff-addedline&quot;&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
  &lt;td colspan=&quot;2&quot;&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;td class=&quot;diff-marker&quot;&gt;+&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;td class=&quot;diff-addedline&quot;&gt;&lt;div&gt;&amp;lt;br /&amp;gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
  &lt;td colspan=&quot;2&quot;&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;td class=&quot;diff-marker&quot;&gt;+&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;td class=&quot;diff-addedline&quot;&gt;&lt;div&gt;==Multi-Tiered Technical Support==&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
  &lt;td colspan=&quot;2&quot;&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;td class=&quot;diff-marker&quot;&gt;+&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;td class=&quot;diff-addedline&quot;&gt;&lt;div&gt;Technical support is often subdivided into tiers, or levels, in order to better serve a business or customer base. The number of levels a business uses to organize their technical support group is dependent on a business’ need, want, or desire as it revolves around their ability to sufficiently serve their customers or users. The reason for providing a multi-tiered support system instead of one general support group is to provide the best possible service in the most efficient possible manner. Success of the organizational structure is dependent on the technicians’ understanding of their level of responsibility and commitments, their customer response time commitments, and when to appropriately escalate an issue and to which level.&amp;lt;ref name=walker&amp;gt;{{cite book | last= Walker| first =Gary |  title= IT Problem Management (Harris Kern’s Enterprise Computing Institute Series) | publisher = [[Prentice Hall]] | location=Upper Saddle River | date = 2001 | pages=85-113| isbn=013030770X |id=[[Google Book Search]]|access date = 2008-05-06 |}}&amp;lt;/ref&amp;gt; A common support structure revolves around a three-tiered technical support system. &lt;/div&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
  &lt;td colspan=&quot;2&quot;&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;td class=&quot;diff-marker&quot;&gt;+&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;td class=&quot;diff-addedline&quot;&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
  &lt;td colspan=&quot;2&quot;&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;td class=&quot;diff-marker&quot;&gt;+&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;td class=&quot;diff-addedline&quot;&gt;&lt;div&gt;&amp;lt;br /&amp;gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
  &lt;td colspan=&quot;2&quot;&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;td class=&quot;diff-marker&quot;&gt;+&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;td class=&quot;diff-addedline&quot;&gt;&lt;div&gt;'''Tier I''' – This is the initial support level responsible for basic customer issues. It is synonymous with first-line support, level 1 support, front-end support, support line 1, and various other headings denoting basic level technical support functions. The first job of a Tier I specialist is to gather the customer’s information and to determine the customer’s issue by analyzing the symptoms and figuring out the underlying problem.&amp;lt;ref name = walker/&amp;gt; When analyzing the symptoms, it is important for the [[technician]] to identify what the customer is trying to accomplish so that time is not wasted on “attempting to solve a symptom instead of a problem.” &amp;lt;ref name = walker/&amp;gt; Once identification of the underlying problem is established, the specialist can begin sorting through the possible solutions available. Technical support specialists in this group typically handle straightforward and simple problems while “possibly using some kind of knowledge management tool.” &amp;lt;ref name = windley&amp;gt;{{cite news | author= Windley, Phillip J. | title= “Delivering High Availability Services Using a Multi-Tiered Support Model” | date = 2002 | work=Windley’s Technometria | url=http://www.windley.com/docs/Tiered%20Support.pdf | access date = 2008-05-03}}&amp;lt;/ref&amp;gt; This includes troubleshooting methods such as verifying physical layer issues, resolving username and password problems, uninstalling/reinstalling basic [[software applications]], verification of proper [[hardware]] and [[software]] set up, and assistance with navigating around application menus. Personnel at this level have a basic to general understanding of the product or service and may not always contain the competency required for solving complex issues.&amp;lt;ref name=kajko&amp;gt;{{cite journal | author = Kajko-Mattsson, Mira | title=Problems within front-end support| journal=Journal of Software Maintenance and Evolution: Research and Practice| volume=16| issue=4/5| year=2004| month=July-October| pages=309–329 | doi=10.1002/smr.298}}&amp;lt;/ref&amp;gt; Nevertheless, the goal for this group is to handle 70%-80% of the user problems before finding it necessary to escalate the issue to a higher level.&amp;lt;ref name=kajko/&amp;gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
  &lt;td colspan=&quot;2&quot;&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;td class=&quot;diff-marker&quot;&gt;+&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;td class=&quot;diff-addedline&quot;&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
  &lt;td colspan=&quot;2&quot;&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;td class=&quot;diff-marker&quot;&gt;+&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;td class=&quot;diff-addedline&quot;&gt;&lt;div&gt;&amp;lt;br /&amp;gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
  &lt;td colspan=&quot;2&quot;&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;td class=&quot;diff-marker&quot;&gt;+&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;td class=&quot;diff-addedline&quot;&gt;&lt;div&gt;'''Tier II''' – This is a more in-depth technical support level than Tier I containing experienced and more knowledgeable personnel on a particular product or service. It is synonymous with level 2 support, support line 2, administrative level support, and various other headings denoting advanced technical [[troubleshooting]] and analysis methods. [[Technicians]] in this realm of knowledge are responsible for assisting Tier I personnel solve basic technical problems and for investigating elevated issues by confirming the validity of the problem and seeking for known solutions related to these more complex issues.&amp;lt;ref name=kajko/&amp;gt; However, prior to the [[troubleshooting]] process, it is important that the technician review the work order to see what has already been accomplished by the Tier I technician and how long the technician has been working with the particular customer. This is a key element in meeting both the customer and business needs as it allows the technician to prioritize the troubleshooting process and properly manage his or her time.&amp;lt;ref name = walker/&amp;gt; If a problem is new and/or personnel from this group cannot determine a solution, they are responsible for raising this issue to the Tier III technical support group. In addition, many companies may specify that certain troubleshooting solutions be performed by this group to help ensure the intricacies of a challenging issue are solved by providing experienced and knowledgeable technicians. This may include, but is not limited to onsite installations or replacements of various hardware components, software repair, diagnostic testing, and the utilization of remote control tools used to take over the user’s machine for the sole purpose of troubleshooting and finding a solution to the problem.&amp;lt;ref name = walker/&amp;gt;&amp;lt;ref name=nelson&amp;gt;{{cite journal | author = Leung, Nelson K. Y. | coauthors=Lau, Sim Kim | title=Information Technology Help Desk Survey: To Identify the Classification of Simple and Routine Enquiries| journal=Journal of Computer Information Systems | volume=47| issue=4| year=2007| month=Summer| pages=70–81}}&amp;lt;/ref&amp;gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
  &lt;td colspan=&quot;2&quot;&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;td class=&quot;diff-marker&quot;&gt;+&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;td class=&quot;diff-addedline&quot;&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
  &lt;td colspan=&quot;2&quot;&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;td class=&quot;diff-marker&quot;&gt;+&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;td class=&quot;diff-addedline&quot;&gt;&lt;div&gt;&amp;lt;br /&amp;gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
  &lt;td colspan=&quot;2&quot;&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;td class=&quot;diff-marker&quot;&gt;+&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;td class=&quot;diff-addedline&quot;&gt;&lt;div&gt;'''Tier III''' – This is the highest level of support in a three-tiered technical support model responsible for handling the most difficult or advanced problems. It is synonymous with level 3 support, back-end support, support line 3, high-end support, and various other headings denoting expert level troubleshooting and analysis methods. These individuals are experts in their fields and are responsible for not only assisting both Tier I and Tier II personnel, but with the research and development of solutions to new or unknown issues. Note that Tier III technicians have the same responsibility as Tier II technicians in reviewing the work order and assessing the time already spent with the customer so that the work is prioritized and time management is sufficiently utilized.&amp;lt;ref name = walker/&amp;gt; If it is at all possible, the [[technician]] will work to solve the problem with the customer as it may become apparent that the Tier I and/or Tier II technicians simply failed to discover the proper solution. Upon encountering new problems; however, Tier III personnel must first determine whether or not to solve the problem and may require the customer’s contact information so that the technician can have adequate time to troubleshoot the issue and find a solution.&amp;lt;ref name=kajko/&amp;gt; In some instances, an issue may be so problematic to the point where the product cannot be salvaged and must be replaced. Such extreme problems are also sent to the original developers for in-depth analysis. If it is determined that a problem can be solved, this group is responsible for designing and developing one or more courses of action, evaluating each of these courses in a test case environment, and implementing the best solution to the problem.&amp;lt;ref name=kajko/&amp;gt; Once the solution is verified, it is delivered to the customer and made available for future troubleshooting and analysis.&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
  &lt;td colspan=&quot;2&quot;&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;td class=&quot;diff-marker&quot;&gt;+&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;td class=&quot;diff-addedline&quot;&gt;&lt;div&gt;&amp;lt;br /&amp;gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
  &lt;td colspan=&quot;2&quot;&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;td class=&quot;diff-marker&quot;&gt;+&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;td class=&quot;diff-addedline&quot;&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
  &lt;td colspan=&quot;2&quot;&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;td class=&quot;diff-marker&quot;&gt;+&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;td class=&quot;diff-addedline&quot;&gt;&lt;div&gt;== Remote PC repair ==&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
  &lt;td colspan=&quot;2&quot;&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;td class=&quot;diff-marker&quot;&gt;+&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;td class=&quot;diff-addedline&quot;&gt;&lt;div&gt;'''Remote PC repair''' is troubleshooting common [[computer errors]] online via [[remote desktop]] connection which works by logging in to the remote PC with the username and password.&amp;lt;ref&amp;gt;{{cite news | first=Jack | last=Germain | coauthors= | title=Remote PC Repair, Part 1: The Warranty Alternative | date=[[2007-07-30]] | publisher= | url =http://www.technewsworld.com/story/60053.html | work =TechNewsWorld | pages = | accessdate = 2008-03-04 | language = }}&amp;lt;/ref&amp;gt; The person owning the computer uses it as himself, apart from the fact that it is being controlled over the Internet. The technology is being embraced by many people as it saves them from hauling their PCs to a shop and wait weeks to get it back. Another benefit is the lower cost. &lt;/div&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
  &lt;td colspan=&quot;2&quot;&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;td class=&quot;diff-marker&quot;&gt;+&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;td class=&quot;diff-addedline&quot;&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
  &lt;td colspan=&quot;2&quot;&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;td class=&quot;diff-marker&quot;&gt;+&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;td class=&quot;diff-addedline&quot;&gt;&lt;div&gt;Remote PC repair services are extremely cost effective and generally offered with a free policy which means that customers don’t have to pay if the issue is not resolved. These repairs are popular as technical support, online computer help, and onsite technical support. With an increase in online resources, there are many companies to get exclusive remote support at competitive prices. &lt;/div&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
  &lt;td colspan=&quot;2&quot;&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;td class=&quot;diff-marker&quot;&gt;+&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;td class=&quot;diff-addedline&quot;&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
  &lt;td colspan=&quot;2&quot;&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;td class=&quot;diff-marker&quot;&gt;+&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;td class=&quot;diff-addedline&quot;&gt;&lt;div&gt;Common repairs available with online computer support providers are [[computer virus]] and [[spyware]] removal, computer optimization, [[registry]] repair, [[device driver]] issues and [[Web]] related issues.&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
  &lt;td colspan=&quot;2&quot;&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;td class=&quot;diff-marker&quot;&gt;+&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;td class=&quot;diff-addedline&quot;&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
  &lt;td colspan=&quot;2&quot;&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;td class=&quot;diff-marker&quot;&gt;+&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;td class=&quot;diff-addedline&quot;&gt;&lt;div&gt;''Not all repairs can be fixed using remote PC repair''. It can be of no help to [[computer hardware]] with physical damage. Remote repair is ineffective for computers that are not able to [[reboot]].&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
  &lt;td colspan=&quot;2&quot;&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;td class=&quot;diff-marker&quot;&gt;+&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;td class=&quot;diff-addedline&quot;&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
  &lt;td colspan=&quot;2&quot;&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;td class=&quot;diff-marker&quot;&gt;+&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;td class=&quot;diff-addedline&quot;&gt;&lt;div&gt;&amp;lt;br /&amp;gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
  &lt;td colspan=&quot;2&quot;&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;td class=&quot;diff-marker&quot;&gt;+&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;td class=&quot;diff-addedline&quot;&gt;&lt;div&gt;==Technical Support Center Certification==&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
  &lt;td colspan=&quot;2&quot;&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;td class=&quot;diff-marker&quot;&gt;+&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;td class=&quot;diff-addedline&quot;&gt;&lt;div&gt;Technical support centers can be certified to help ensure a particular business is maintaining a high level of information technology service and support standards. Of the certifications available for support centers and technicians, there are two internationally recognized certifications geared specifically towards support centers as a whole – The [[Help Desk Institute]] (HDI) Support Center Certification and the Service Strategies Service Capability and Performance (SCP) Standards.&amp;lt;ref name=hdi&amp;gt;{{cite web | url=http://www.thinkhdi.com/ | title= Help Desk Institute | accessdate= 2008-05-06 | }}&amp;lt;/ref&amp;gt;&amp;lt;ref name=scp&amp;gt;{{cite web | url= http://www.servicestrategies.com/solutions/scp-standards/ | title= Service Capability &amp;amp; Performance (SCP) Standard | accessdate= 2008-05-06 | }}&amp;lt;/ref&amp;gt; Both certifications were developed by experts and organizations from around the world and both were developed under the premise of enhancing the quality of customer service and support.&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
  &lt;td colspan=&quot;2&quot;&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;td class=&quot;diff-marker&quot;&gt;+&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;td class=&quot;diff-addedline&quot;&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
  &lt;td colspan=&quot;2&quot;&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;td class=&quot;diff-marker&quot;&gt;+&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;td class=&quot;diff-addedline&quot;&gt;&lt;div&gt;&amp;lt;br /&amp;gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
  &lt;td colspan=&quot;2&quot;&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;td class=&quot;diff-marker&quot;&gt;+&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;td class=&quot;diff-addedline&quot;&gt;&lt;div&gt;==See also==	 	&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
  &lt;td colspan=&quot;2&quot;&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;td class=&quot;diff-marker&quot;&gt;+&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;td class=&quot;diff-addedline&quot;&gt;&lt;div&gt;* [[Help desk]]&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
  &lt;td colspan=&quot;2&quot;&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;td class=&quot;diff-marker&quot;&gt;+&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;td class=&quot;diff-addedline&quot;&gt;&lt;div&gt;* [[Information technology]]&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
  &lt;td colspan=&quot;2&quot;&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;td class=&quot;diff-marker&quot;&gt;+&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;td class=&quot;diff-addedline&quot;&gt;&lt;div&gt;* [[Help Desk Institute]]&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
  &lt;td colspan=&quot;2&quot;&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;td class=&quot;diff-marker&quot;&gt;+&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;td class=&quot;diff-addedline&quot;&gt;&lt;div&gt;* [[Tech Support Comedy]] - A popular website where tech support employees share humorous stories and provide support for each other.&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
  &lt;td colspan=&quot;2&quot;&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;td class=&quot;diff-marker&quot;&gt;+&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;td class=&quot;diff-addedline&quot;&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
  &lt;td colspan=&quot;2&quot;&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;td class=&quot;diff-marker&quot;&gt;+&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;td class=&quot;diff-addedline&quot;&gt;&lt;div&gt;&amp;lt;br /&amp;gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
  &lt;td colspan=&quot;2&quot;&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;td class=&quot;diff-marker&quot;&gt;+&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;td class=&quot;diff-addedline&quot;&gt;&lt;div&gt;== References ==&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
  &lt;td colspan=&quot;2&quot;&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;td class=&quot;diff-marker&quot;&gt;+&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;td class=&quot;diff-addedline&quot;&gt;&lt;div&gt;{{reflist}}&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
  &lt;td colspan=&quot;2&quot;&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;td class=&quot;diff-marker&quot;&gt;+&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;td class=&quot;diff-addedline&quot;&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
  &lt;td colspan=&quot;2&quot;&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;td class=&quot;diff-marker&quot;&gt;+&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;td class=&quot;diff-addedline&quot;&gt;&lt;div&gt;&amp;lt;br /&amp;gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
  &lt;td colspan=&quot;2&quot;&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;td class=&quot;diff-marker&quot;&gt;+&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;td class=&quot;diff-addedline&quot;&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
  &lt;td colspan=&quot;2&quot;&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;td class=&quot;diff-marker&quot;&gt;+&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;td class=&quot;diff-addedline&quot;&gt;&lt;div&gt;[[Category:Help desk]]&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
  &lt;td colspan=&quot;2&quot;&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;td class=&quot;diff-marker&quot;&gt;+&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;td class=&quot;diff-addedline&quot;&gt;&lt;div&gt;[[Category:Outsourcing]]&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
  &lt;td colspan=&quot;2&quot;&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;td class=&quot;diff-marker&quot;&gt;+&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;td class=&quot;diff-addedline&quot;&gt;&lt;div&gt;[[Category:Customer experience management]]&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
  &lt;td colspan=&quot;2&quot;&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;td class=&quot;diff-marker&quot;&gt;+&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;td class=&quot;diff-addedline&quot;&gt;&lt;div&gt;[[Category:Remote desktop]]&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
  &lt;td colspan=&quot;2&quot;&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;td class=&quot;diff-marker&quot;&gt;+&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;td class=&quot;diff-addedline&quot;&gt;&lt;div&gt;[[Category:Collaboration]]&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
  &lt;td colspan=&quot;2&quot;&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;td class=&quot;diff-marker&quot;&gt;+&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;td class=&quot;diff-addedline&quot;&gt;&lt;div&gt;[[Category:Groupware]]&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
  &lt;td colspan=&quot;2&quot;&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;td class=&quot;diff-marker&quot;&gt;+&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;td class=&quot;diff-addedline&quot;&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
  &lt;td colspan=&quot;2&quot;&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;td class=&quot;diff-marker&quot;&gt;+&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;td class=&quot;diff-addedline&quot;&gt;&lt;div&gt;[[ar:دعم فني]]&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
  &lt;td colspan=&quot;2&quot;&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;td class=&quot;diff-marker&quot;&gt;+&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;td class=&quot;diff-addedline&quot;&gt;&lt;div&gt;[[de:Support (Dienstleistung)]]&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
  &lt;td colspan=&quot;2&quot;&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;td class=&quot;diff-marker&quot;&gt;+&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;td class=&quot;diff-addedline&quot;&gt;&lt;div&gt;[[es:Soporte técnico]]&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
  &lt;td colspan=&quot;2&quot;&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;td class=&quot;diff-marker&quot;&gt;+&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;td class=&quot;diff-addedline&quot;&gt;&lt;div&gt;[[fr:Support technique]]&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
</diff></rev></revisions></page></pages></query><query-continue><revisions rvstartid="232907597" /></query-continue></api>
