<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="7475420" ns="0" title="MojoPac"><revisions><rev revid="218538840" parentid="205701192" user="SF007" timestamp="2008-06-11T02:27:03Z" comment="updated info, thinstall is now &quot;VMware ThinApp&quot;"><diff from="205701192" to="218538840" xml:space="preserve">&lt;tr&gt;
  &lt;td colspan=&quot;2&quot; class=&quot;diff-lineno&quot;&gt;Line 26:&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;td colspan=&quot;2&quot; class=&quot;diff-lineno&quot;&gt;Line 26:&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
  &lt;td class=&quot;diff-marker&quot;&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;td class=&quot;diff-context&quot;&gt;&lt;div&gt;[[U3]] requires modifications to the target applications to get them to run from the external device. This means that it doesn't support certain proprietary applications such as Microsoft Office and Adobe Photoshop. [[Ceedo]] can run target applications (including Microsoft Office and Adobe Photoshop 7&amp;lt;ref&amp;gt;[http://www.ceedoforum.com/forum/showthread.php?t=439] - User (post #5) running Photoshop 7 on Ceedo&amp;lt;/ref&amp;gt;) without modification but the user is required to purchase an add-on product called Argo that allows this functionality. Both U3 and Ceedo can run without Administrator privileges while MojoPac currently cannot. MojoPac has a virtualization layer that prevents applications from writing to the host machine; Ceedo can do this if the application is installed via Argo as mentioned above; and U3 requires the application to be &quot;unobtrusive&quot;.&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;td class=&quot;diff-marker&quot;&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;td class=&quot;diff-context&quot;&gt;&lt;div&gt;[[U3]] requires modifications to the target applications to get them to run from the external device. This means that it doesn't support certain proprietary applications such as Microsoft Office and Adobe Photoshop. [[Ceedo]] can run target applications (including Microsoft Office and Adobe Photoshop 7&amp;lt;ref&amp;gt;[http://www.ceedoforum.com/forum/showthread.php?t=439] - User (post #5) running Photoshop 7 on Ceedo&amp;lt;/ref&amp;gt;) without modification but the user is required to purchase an add-on product called Argo that allows this functionality. Both U3 and Ceedo can run without Administrator privileges while MojoPac currently cannot. MojoPac has a virtualization layer that prevents applications from writing to the host machine; Ceedo can do this if the application is installed via Argo as mentioned above; and U3 requires the application to be &quot;unobtrusive&quot;.&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
  &lt;td class=&quot;diff-marker&quot;&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;td class=&quot;diff-context&quot;&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;td class=&quot;diff-marker&quot;&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;td class=&quot;diff-context&quot;&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
  &lt;td class=&quot;diff-marker&quot;&gt;−&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;td class=&quot;diff-deletedline&quot;&gt;&lt;div&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;diffchange diffchange-inline&quot;&gt;[[Thinstall]] &lt;/span&gt;allows applications to run from external devices without application modifications and supports applications such as Microsoft Office and Photoshop. In addition &lt;span class=&quot;diffchange diffchange-inline&quot;&gt;Thinstall &lt;/span&gt;can run without Administrator privileges and does not use or require device drivers. &lt;span class=&quot;diffchange diffchange-inline&quot;&gt;Thinstall's &lt;/span&gt;virtualization can be configured to sandbox all changes the host PC from modifications, only allow modifications to the Desktop and &quot;My Documents&quot;, or allow full read/write access to the host PC's filesystem. &lt;span class=&quot;diffchange diffchange-inline&quot;&gt;Thinstall &lt;/span&gt;can startup from a USB device in less than a second on a new PC, Mojopac must reconfigure itself for new devices which typically takes several minutes. &lt;span class=&quot;diffchange diffchange-inline&quot;&gt;Thinstall &lt;/span&gt;requires a &quot;snapshot&quot; capture process using a clean Windows computer to create virtual applications and is optimized for use in ISV, corporate, and enterprise environments. Mojopac supplies a separate virtual environment for easier conversion for individual consumers. &lt;span class=&quot;diffchange diffchange-inline&quot;&gt;Thinstall &lt;/span&gt;supports all Windows operating systems and dynamically reconfigures applications to move from operating system to operating system. &lt;span class=&quot;diffchange diffchange-inline&quot;&gt;Thinstall &lt;/span&gt;occupies less than 500k on disk, while Mojopac requires at least 35MB of free disk space to install. &lt;span class=&quot;diffchange diffchange-inline&quot;&gt;Thinstall &lt;/span&gt;can run applications directly from the compressed state reducing disk space requirements in half and doubling loading times over USB. It should be noted that &lt;span class=&quot;diffchange diffchange-inline&quot;&gt;Thinstall &lt;/span&gt;is an extremely expensive piece of software, charging USD $4,995&amp;lt;ref&amp;gt;[http://www.thinstall.com/sales/purchase.php] - Thinstall fees as at February 2008&amp;lt;/ref&amp;gt; to do its work, placing it way out of reach of the general consumer.&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;td class=&quot;diff-marker&quot;&gt;+&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;td class=&quot;diff-addedline&quot;&gt;&lt;div&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;diffchange diffchange-inline&quot;&gt;[[VMware ThinApp]] &lt;/span&gt;allows applications to run from external devices without application modifications and supports applications such as Microsoft Office and Photoshop. In addition &lt;span class=&quot;diffchange diffchange-inline&quot;&gt;VMware ThinApp &lt;/span&gt;can run without Administrator privileges and does not use or require device drivers. &lt;span class=&quot;diffchange diffchange-inline&quot;&gt;VMware ThinApp's &lt;/span&gt;virtualization can be configured to sandbox all changes the host PC from modifications, only allow modifications to the Desktop and &quot;My Documents&quot;, or allow full read/write access to the host PC's filesystem. &lt;span class=&quot;diffchange diffchange-inline&quot;&gt;VMware ThinApp &lt;/span&gt;can startup from a USB device in less than a second on a new PC, Mojopac must reconfigure itself for new devices which typically takes several minutes. &lt;span class=&quot;diffchange diffchange-inline&quot;&gt;VMware ThinApp &lt;/span&gt;requires a &quot;snapshot&quot; capture process using a clean Windows computer to create virtual applications and is optimized for use in ISV, corporate, and enterprise environments. Mojopac supplies a separate virtual environment for easier conversion for individual consumers. &lt;span class=&quot;diffchange diffchange-inline&quot;&gt;VMware ThinApp &lt;/span&gt;supports all Windows operating systems and dynamically reconfigures applications to move from operating system to operating system. &lt;span class=&quot;diffchange diffchange-inline&quot;&gt;VMware ThinApp &lt;/span&gt;occupies less than 500k on disk, while Mojopac requires at least 35MB of free disk space to install. &lt;span class=&quot;diffchange diffchange-inline&quot;&gt;VMware ThinApp &lt;/span&gt;can run applications directly from the compressed state reducing disk space requirements in half and doubling loading times over USB. It should be noted that &lt;span class=&quot;diffchange diffchange-inline&quot;&gt;VMware ThinApp &lt;/span&gt;is an extremely expensive piece of software, charging USD $4,995&amp;lt;ref&amp;gt;[http://www.thinstall.com/sales/purchase.php] - Thinstall fees as at February 2008&amp;lt;/ref&amp;gt; to do its work, placing it way out of reach of the general consumer.&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
  &lt;td class=&quot;diff-marker&quot;&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;td class=&quot;diff-context&quot;&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;td class=&quot;diff-marker&quot;&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;td class=&quot;diff-context&quot;&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
  &lt;td class=&quot;diff-marker&quot;&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;td class=&quot;diff-context&quot;&gt;&lt;div&gt;===Alternative virtualization solutions===&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;td class=&quot;diff-marker&quot;&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;td class=&quot;diff-context&quot;&gt;&lt;div&gt;===Alternative virtualization solutions===&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
</diff></rev></revisions></page></pages></query><query-continue><revisions rvstartid="205701192" /></query-continue></api>
