<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="10025" ns="0" title="Flag of Europe"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{pp-move-vandalism|small=yes}}
{{Infobox Flag
| Name       = Europe
| Article    =
| Nickname   =
| Morenicks  =
| Image_size = 158px
| Image      = Flag of Europe.svg
| Use        = 111011&lt;!--Civil &amp; state flag and also used by military forces under EU command or mandate, however it is not used for civilian ships which must use national flags only - proposal to make it a civilian ensign were dropped in 2004 (I think it was that year)--&gt;
| Symbol     = {{FIAV|normal}}
| Proportion = 2:3
| Adoption   = 8 December 1955&lt;ref&gt;{{citation|last=Committee of Ministers of the Council of Europe|title=Resolution (55) 32 of the Committee of Ministers of the Council of Europe|date=8 December 1955|publisher=[[European Navigator]]|url=http://www.ena.lu/resolution_55_32_committee_ministers_council_europe_december_1955-020005258.html|accessdate=12 February 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt; ([[Council of Europe|CoE]])&lt;br /&gt;29 June 1985&lt;ref name=&quot;COE page&quot;/&gt; ([[European Economic Community|EEC]])
| Design     = A circle of 12 5-pointed gold (yellow) stars on a blue field.
| Type       = International
| Designer   = [[Arsène Heitz]] and [[Paul Michel Gabriel Levy|Paul Lévy]]
}}
The '''flag of Europe''' consists of a [[Circle of stars|circle of]] 12 golden (yellow) stars on an [[azure]] background. It is the [[flag]] and emblem of the [[European Union]] (EU) and [[Council of Europe]] (CoE).&lt;ref&gt;It is termed &quot;Flag of Europe&quot; or &quot;European Flag&quot; by both organisations, intended to represent the continent as a whole, but has no legal basis beyond use by the CoE. It is also known as the &quot;flag of the European Union&quot; excluding its relation to the CoE but the term &quot;flag of the Council of Europe&quot; is never used.&lt;/ref&gt; It is also often used to indicate [[eurozone]] countries, and, more loosely, to represent the continent of Europe or the countries of Europe independent of any of these institutions. The number of stars does not vary according to the members of either organisation as they are intended to represent all the peoples of Europe, even those outside [[European integration]].{{Citation needed|date=November 2010}}

The flag was designed by [[Arsène Heitz]] and [[Paul Michel Gabriel Levy|Paul Lévy]] in 1955 for the CoE as its symbol, and the CoE urged it to be adopted by other organisations. In 1985 the EU, which was then the [[European Economic Community]] (EEC), adopted it as its own flag (having had no flag of its own before) at the initiative of the [[European Parliament]]. The flag is not mentioned in the [[Treaties of the European Union|EU's treaties]], its incorporation being dropped along with the [[Treaty establishing a Constitution for Europe|European Constitution]], but it is formally adopted in law.

Despite it being the flag of two separate organisations, it is often more associated with the EU due to the EU's higher profile and heavy usage of the emblem. The flag has also been used to represent Europe in [[sporting event]]s and as a pro-[[democracy]] banner outside the Union.&lt;ref name=&quot;Mite&quot;&gt;{{citation|last=Mite|firstvalentinas=|title=Belarus: Scores Arrested, Opposition Leader Hospitalized After Minsk Protests|date=20 October 2004|publisher=rferl.org|url=http://www.rferl.org/featuresarticle/2004/10/340afaf0-ebf7-4a03-8a25-ebda21070598.html|accessdate=5 August 2007}}&lt;/ref&gt; It has partly inspired other flags, such as those of other European organisations and those of states where the EU has been heavily involved (such as [[Bosnia and Herzegovina]] and [[Republic of Kosovo|Kosovo]]).

== History ==
=== Creation ===
The Council of Europe's search for a symbol began in 1950 when it set up a committee to look into the question of a European flag. There were numerous proposals but a clear theme for stars and circles emerged.&lt;ref name=&quot;Levy&quot;&gt;{{Citation|last=|first=|title=Account by Paul M. G. Lévy on the creation of the European flag|publisher=[[European NAvigator]]|date=|url=http://www.ena.lu?lang=1&amp;doc=20734|accessdate=2008-07-15}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Count Richard Nikolaus von Coudenhove-Kalergi]] proposed that they adopt the flag of his [[International Paneuropean Union]], which was a blue, with a red cross inside an orange circle at the centre, which he had himself recently adopted for the [[European Parliamentary Union]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.coe.int/t/dgal/dit/ilcd/Historical_Content/flag/3.pdf Letter to the secretary general of the Council of Europe from Richard Coudenhove-Kalergi], Council of Europe {{Fr}}&lt;/ref&gt; Due to the cross symbolism, this was rejected by [[Turkey]] (a member of the Council of Europe since 1949).&lt;ref name=&quot;FOTW proposals&quot;&gt;[http://www.fahnenversand.de/fotw/flags/eu_ce.html Council of Europe] fahnenversand.de&lt;/ref&gt; Kalergi then suggested adding a crescent to the cross design, to overcome the [[Islam|Muslim]] objections.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.coe.int/t/dgal/dit/ilcd/Historical_Content/flag/f_d204.pdf Letter from Richard Coudenhove-Kalergi regarding a Muslim modification to the Pan-Europa flag design], Council of Europe {{Fr}}&lt;/ref&gt; Another organisation's flag was the [[European Movement]], which had a [[Federalist flag|large green E on a white background]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.crwflags.com/fotw/flags/eu%7Dmov.html European Movement] crwflags.com&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.crwflags.com/fotw/flags/eu!1.html Proposals for the European flag] crwflags.com&lt;/ref&gt; A further design was one based on the [[Olympic rings]]; eight silver rings on a blue background. It was rejected due to the rings' similarity with &quot;dial&quot;, &quot;chain&quot; and &quot;zeros&quot;. One proposal had a large yellow star on a blue background, but it was rejected due to its similarity with the so-called [[Flag of Texas#The Burnet Flag|Burnet flag]] and the [[Flag of the Democratic Republic of the Congo|flag of the Belgian Congo]].&lt;ref name=&quot;FOTW proposals&quot;/&gt;

The Consultative Assembly narrowed their choice to two designs. One was by [[Salvador de Madariaga]], the founder of the [[College of Europe]], who suggested a [[constellation]] of stars on a blue background&lt;ref name=&quot;ENA page&quot;&gt;{{Citation|last=|first=|title=The European flag: questions and answers|publisher=[[European NAvigator]]|date=|url=http://www.ena.lu?lang=2&amp;doc=21621|accessdate=2007-08-16}}&lt;/ref&gt; (positioned according to capital cities, with a large star for [[Strasbourg]], the seat of the Council). He had circulated his flag round many European capitals and the concept had found favour.&lt;ref name=&quot;Irish&quot;/&gt; The second was a variant on this by Arsène Heitz,&lt;ref name=&quot;ENA page&quot;/&gt; who worked at the Council's postal service and had submitted dozens of designs,&lt;ref&gt;{{Citation|last=|first=|title=Lettre d’Arsène Heitz à Filippo Caracciolo (Strasbourg, 5 janvier 1952)|publisher=[[European NAvigator]]|date=|url=http://www.ena.lu?lang=1&amp;doc=19530|accessdate=2008-07-15}}&lt;/ref&gt; The design of his that was accepted by the assembly was similar to Salvador de Madariaga's, but rather a constellation, the stars were arranged in a circle.&lt;ref name=&quot;ENA page&quot;/&gt; The Consultative Assembly favoured Heitz's design, however the flag the Assembly chose had fifteen stars, reflecting the number of states of the Council of Europe. The Consultative Assembly chose this flag and recommended that the Council adopt it.&lt;ref&gt;{{Citation|last=|first=|title=Recommendation 56(1) of the Consultative Assembly on the choice of an emblem for the Council of Europe (25 September 1953)|publisher=[[European NAvigator]]|date=|url=http://www.ena.lu?lang=2&amp;doc=18094|accessdate=2008-07-15}}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:European flag outside the Commission.jpg|thumb|The flag was created in 1955 and the [[European Economic Community|EEC]] adopted it in 1984.]]

The Committee of Ministers (the Council's main decision making body) agreed with the Assembly that the flag should be a circle of stars, but the number thirteen was a source of contention (see &quot;[[#Number of stars|Number of stars]]&quot; below).&lt;ref name=&quot;Levy&quot;/&gt; The number twelve was chosen and Paul M. G. Lévy drew up the exact design of the new flag as it is today.&lt;ref name=&quot;Levy&quot;/&gt; The [[Parliamentary Assembly of the Council of Europe]] approved it on 25 October 1955. Adopted on 8 December 1955, it was unveiled at the [[Château de la Muette]] in [[Paris]] on 13 December 1955.&lt;ref name=&quot;COE page&quot;&gt;{{Citation|last=|first=|title=Council of Europe's Emblems|publisher=[[Council of Europe]]|date=|url=http://www.coe.int/T/E/Com/About_Coe/flag.asp|accessdate=2007-08-16|archiveurl = http://web.archive.org/web/20070807045151/http://www.coe.int/T/E/Com/About_Coe/flag.asp |archivedate = August 7, 2007|deadurl=yes}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;ENA page&quot;/&gt;

=== European Communities ===
Following Expo '58 in [[Brussels]], the flag caught on and the Council of Europe lobbied for other European organisations to adopt the flag as a sign of European unity.&lt;ref name=&quot;ENA page&quot;/&gt; The European Parliament took the initiative in seeking a flag to be adopted by the European Communities. Shortly after the first [[European Parliament election, 1979|direct elections in 1979]] a draft resolution was put forward on the issue. The resolution proposed that the Communities' flag should be that of the Council of Europe&lt;ref name=&quot;COE page&quot;/&gt; and it was adopted by the Parliament on 11 April 1983.&lt;ref name=&quot;ENA page&quot;/&gt;

The June 1984 European Council (the Communities' leaders) summit in [[Fontainebleau]] stressed the importance of promoting a European image and identity to citizens and the world. The following year, meeting in [[Milan]], the 28–29 June European Council approved a proposal from the Committee on a People’s Europe (Adonnino Committee) in favour of the flag and adopted it. Following the permission of the Council of Europe,&lt;ref name=&quot;COE page&quot;/&gt; the Communities began to use it from 1986, with it being raised outside the [[Berlaymont building]] (the seat of the European Commission) for the first time on the 29 May 1986.&lt;ref&gt;{{Citation|title=Raising of the European flag in front of the Berlaymont (Brussels, 29 May 1986)|publisher=[[European Navigator]]|date=|url=http://www.ena.lu?lang=2&amp;doc=19888|accessdate=2009-01-21}}&lt;/ref&gt; The European Union, which was established by the [[Maastricht Treaty]] in 1992 to replace the EC and encompass its functions, also adopted the flag. Since then the use of the flag has been controlled jointly by the Council of Europe and the European Union.&lt;ref name=&quot;COE page&quot;/&gt;

=== Previous flags ===
{{See|Flag of the European Coal and Steel Community}}
[[File:Flag of the European Coal and Steel Community 12 Star Version.svg|thumb|[[File:FIAV historical.svg|23px]] [[Flag of the European Coal and Steel Community|Flag of the defunct ECSC]]]]

Prior to development of political institutions, flags representing Europe were limited to unification movements. The most popular were the [[European Movement]]'s [[Federalist flag|large green 'E' on a white background]], and the &quot;Pan European flag&quot; (see &quot;[[#Creation|Creation]]&quot; below).&lt;ref name=&quot;ENA page&quot;/&gt; With the development of institutions, aside from the Council of Europe, came other emblems and flags. None were intended to represent wider Europe and have since been replaced by the current flag of Europe.

The first major organisation to adopt one was the [[European Coal and Steel Community]] (ECSC), which merged into the [[European Communities]]. The ECSC was created in 1952 and the [[Flag of the European Coal and Steel Community|flag of the ECSC]] was unveiled in [[Expo '58|1958 Expo]] in [[Brussels]].&lt;ref name=&quot;FOTW ECSC&quot;&gt;{{Citation|last=|first=|title=The European Coal and Steel Community (ECSC)|publisher=Flags Of The World|date=2004-10-28|url=http://www.crwflags.com/fotw/flags/eu-ecsc.html|accessdate=2007-08-04}}&lt;/ref&gt;{{-}}

[[File:Flag of the European Parliament 1973-1983.svg|thumb|[[File:FIAV historical.svg|23px]] Former [[European Parliament|parliamentary]] flag]]

The flag had two stripes, blue at the top, black at the bottom with six gold (silver after 1973) stars, three on each stripe. Blue was for [[steel]], black for [[coal]] and the stars were the six member-states. The stars increased with the members until 1986 when they were fixed at twelve. When the [[Treaty of Paris (1951)|ECSC treaty]] expired in 2002, the flag was lowered outside the [[European Commission]] in Brussels and replaced with the European flag.&lt;ref name=&quot;FOTW ECSC&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.ena.lu?lang=2&amp;doc=19592 The ECSC flag 1986-2002], [[European NAvigator]]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.ena.lu?lang=1&amp;doc=19789 The ECSC flag 1978], [[European NAvigator]]&lt;/ref&gt;

The [[European Parliament]] also used its own flag from 1973, but never formally adopted it. It fell out of use with the adoption of the twelve star flag by the Parliament in 1983. The flag followed the yellow and blue colour scheme however instead of twelve stars there were the letters EP and PE (initials of the European Parliament in the then six [[Languages of the European Union|community languages]]) surrounded by a [[wreath]].&lt;ref&gt;{{Citation|last=|first=|title=European Parliament|publisher=Flags Of The World|date=2004-10-28|url=http://www.crwflags.com/fotw/flags/eu_ep.html|accessdate=2007-08-04}}&lt;/ref&gt;{{-}}

==== Barcode flag ====
{{See|Rem Koolhaas#European Flag proposal}}
[[File:Union-europea segun rem-koolhaas.svg|thumb|{{FIAV|proposal}}Koolhaas' flag proposal]]
In 2002, Dutch architect [[Rem Koolhaas]] and his architecture firm [[Office for Metropolitan Architecture]] (OMA) designed a new flag in response to [[President of the European Commission|Commission President]] [[Romano Prodi]]'s request to find ways of rebranding the Union in a way that represents Europe's &quot;diversity and unity&quot;. The proposed new design was dubbed the &quot;barcode&quot;, as it displays the colours of every European flag (of the then 15 members) as vertical stripes. As well as the [[barcode]] comparison, it had been compared unfavourably to wallpaper, a TV [[test card]] and [[deckchair]] fabric. Unlike the current flag, it would change to reflect the member states.&lt;ref name=&quot;BBC barcode&quot;&gt;{{Citation |title=Down with EU stars, run up stripes |date=8 May 2002   |publisher=BBC News   |url=http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/world/europe/1974721.stm}}&lt;/ref&gt;

It was never officially adopted by the EU or any organisation; however, it was used as the logo of the Austrian [[Presidency of the Council of the European Union|EU Presidency]] in 2006. It had been updated with the colours of the 10 members who had joined since the proposal, and was designed by Koolhaas's firm. Its described aim is &quot;to portray Europe as the common effort of different nations, with each retaining its own unique cultural identity&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{citation|title=Austrian EU Presidency Logo|date=|publisher=Dexigner|url=http://www.dexigner.com/database/design/austrian_eu_presidency_logo/|accessdate=}}&lt;/ref&gt; There were initially some complaints, as the stripes of the flag of [[Estonia]] were displayed incorrectly.{{-}}

=== Recent events ===
In April 2004, the flag was flown in space for the first time by [[European Space Agency]] astronaut [[André Kuipers]] while on board the [[International Space Station]].&lt;ref&gt;{{citation|title=Further steps towards a European space policy|publisher=[[European Space Agency]]|url=http://www.esa.int/esaCP/SEMJ0Z0DU8E_index_1.html#subhead3|accessdate=11 February 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt;

{{quote box|width=30em|quote = Belgium, Bulgaria, Germany, Greece, Spain, Italy, Cyprus, Lithuania, Luxemburg, Hungary, Malta, Austria, Portugal, Romania, Slovenia and the Slovak Republic declare that the flag with a circle of twelve golden stars on a blue background, the anthem based on the ‘Ode to Joy’ from the Ninth Symphony by Ludwig van Beethoven, the motto ‘United in diversity’, the euro as the currency of the European Union and Europe Day on 9 May will for them continue as symbols to express the sense of community of the people in the European Union and their allegiance to it.|source = Final Act, Official Journal of the European Union, 2007 C 306-2&lt;ref name=&quot;lisbon-symbols-declaration&quot;/&gt;}}
The flag was to have been given a formal status in the proposed [[Treaty establishing a Constitution for Europe|European Constitution]]. However since the ratification of that failed, the leaders removed the state-like elements such as the flag from the replacement [[Treaty of Lisbon]]. The European Parliament however had supported the inclusion of symbols, and in response backed a proposal to use the symbols, such as the flag more often in the Parliament. [[Jo Leinen]] MEP suggesting that the Parliament should again take the ''[[avant-garde]]'' in their use.&lt;ref&gt;{{Citation|last=Beunderman|first=Mark|title=MEPs defy member states on EU symbols|publisher=EU Observer|date=2007-07-11|url=http://euobserver.com/9/24464|accessdate=2007-07-12}}&lt;/ref&gt; Later, in September 2008, Parliament's [[Committee on Constitutional Affairs]] proposed a formal change in the institution's rules of procedure to make better use of the symbols. Specifically, the flag would be present in all meeting rooms (not just the hemicycle) and at all official events.&lt;ref&gt;{{Citation|title=EU Parliament set to use European flag, anthem|publisher=EU Business|date=2008-09-11|url=http://www.eubusiness.com/news-eu/1221140822.65|accessdate=2008-09-12}} {{Dead link|date=September 2010|bot=H3llBot}}&lt;/ref&gt; The proposal was passed on 8 October 2008 by 503 votes to 96 (15 abstentions).&lt;ref&gt;{{Citation|first=Lucia|last=Kubosova|title=No prolonged mandate for Barroso, MEPs warn|publisher=[[EU Observer]]|date=9 October 2008|url=http://euobserver.com/9/26899|accessdate=2008-10-09}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Additionally, a declaration by sixteen Member States on the symbols, including the flag, was included in the final act of the Treaty of Lisbon stating that the flag, the anthem, the motto and the currency and Europe Day &quot;will for them continue as symbols to express the sense of community of the people in the European Union and their allegiance to it.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;lisbon-symbols-declaration&quot;&gt;[http://eur-lex.europa.eu/LexUriServ/LexUriServ.do?uri=OJ:C:2007:306:0231:0271:EN:PDF Official Journal of the European Union, 2007 C 306-2 , p. 267]&lt;/ref&gt;

=====2011 dissent=====
In May 2011 on [[Europe Day]], MEPs from [[Denmark]], [[France]], the [[Netherlands]], and the [[United Kingdom]] protested the flag at a ceremony by raising their respective national flags.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.efdgroup.eu/news/256-eu-flag-raising-we-never-voted-for-this-ukips-farage.html &quot;EU flag raising - &quot;We never voted for this&quot; - UKIP's Farage&quot;], Europe of Freedom and Democracy. May 10, 2011. Accessed June 8, 2011&lt;/ref&gt; 

In June 2011, [[Greeks|Greek]] demonstrators covered the flag on the Finance Ministry with protest banners.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.thejakartaglobe.com/bisworld/unionists-storm-ministry-as-greek-pm-races-for-relief/444904 &quot;Unionists Storm Ministry as Greek PM Races for Relief&quot;], John Hadoulis. Jakata Globe. June 3, 2011. Accessed June 15, 2011&lt;/ref&gt;

== Usage ==
=== Council of Europe ===
The flag was originally designed by the Council of Europe,&lt;ref name=&quot;COE page&quot;/&gt; and as such the CoE holds the copyright for the flag. However, the Council of Europe agreed that the [[European Communities]] could use the flag and it had promoted its use by other regional organisations since it was created. The Council of Europe now shares responsibility with the [[European Commission]] for ensuring that use of the symbol respects the dignity of the flag—taking measures to prevent misuse of it.&lt;ref name=&quot;COE page&quot;/&gt;

Besides using the flag, the Council also uses a [[Defacement (flag)|defaced]] version of the flag as its emblem: it is the existing design with a stylised, green &quot;e&quot; over the stars.&lt;ref name=&quot;COE page&quot;/&gt;

=== European Union ===
[[Image:Euro banknotes.png|thumb|Euro banknotes]]

The flag symbolises the EU as a whole but it is also the sole emblem of the European Commission, the EU's executive arm.&lt;ref name=&quot;Europa history&quot;&gt;{{citation|title=The European Flag|publisher=[[Europa (web portal)]]|url=http://europa.eu/abc/symbols/emblem/index_en.htm|accessdate=4 August 2007}}&lt;/ref&gt; However, all other bodies and agencies, except for the [[European Agency for Reconstruction]], have their own emblem, albeit often inspired by the flag's design and colours.&lt;ref name=&quot;Europa logos&quot;&gt;{{citation|title=Emblems|date=|publisher=[[Europa (web portal)]]|url=http://publications.europa.eu/code/en/en-5000200.htm|accessdate=28 December 2007}}&lt;/ref&gt;

As part of the EU's usage, the flag appears on the [[euro banknotes]].&lt;ref&gt;{{citation|title=The euro|publisher=[[European Central Bank]]|url=http://www.ecb.int/bc/euro/html/index.en.html|accessdate=4 August 2007|archiveurl = http://web.archive.org/web/20070806010151/http://www.ecb.int/bc/euro/html/index.en.html |archivedate = August 6, 2007|deadurl=yes}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Euro coins]] also display the twelve stars of the flag on both the national and common sides&lt;ref&gt;{{citation|title=Euro coins|publisher=[[European Central Bank]]|url=http://www.ecb.int/bc/euro/coins/html/index.en.html|accessdate=28 December 2007|archiveurl = http://web.archive.org/web/20071224165324/http://www.ecb.int/bc/euro/coins/html/index.en.html |archivedate = December 24, 2007|deadurl=yes}}&lt;/ref&gt; and the flag is sometimes used as an indication of the currency or the [[eurozone]] (a collective name for those countries that use the Euro).
[[File:Plate-KA-PA777.JPG|thumb|left|The EU uses the flag in a number of ways, here on [[Vehicle registration plates of the European Union|vehicle licence plates]].]]
The flag appears also on many [[driving licence]]s and [[Vehicle registration plates of the European Union|vehicle registration plates]] issued in the Union.&lt;ref name=&quot;FOTW legal&quot;&gt;{{citation|title=European Union: Legal use of the flag|date=10 September 2005|publisher=[[Flags Of The World]]|url=http://www.allstates-flag.com/fotw/flags/eu_law.html|accessdate=29 November 2009}} {{dead link|date=June 2010| bot=DASHBot}}&lt;/ref&gt;
 
A proposal, soon to be discussed in the [[European Parliament]], stipulate that all national sports teams, including football, rugby, cricket and the European Olympic teams, should have the EU emblem appear on their jerseys.&lt;ref&gt;{{citation|title=England football team 'could be forced to wear EU flag'|publisher=The Telegraph|url=http://www.telegraph.co.uk/sport/football/teams/england/8623800/England-football-team-could-be-forced-to-wear-EU-flag.html|accessdate=1 August 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==== Protocol ====
It is mandatory for the flag to be used in every official speech made by the [[President of the European Council]] and it is often used at official meetings between the leaders of an EU state and a non-EU state (the national flag and European flag appearing together).&lt;ref name=&quot;FOTW legal&quot;/&gt; While normally the national flag takes precedence over the European flag in the national context, meetings between EU leaders sometimes differ. For example the Italian flag code expressly replaces the [[Flag of Italy|Italian flag]] for the European flag in precedence when dignitaries from other EU countries visit - for example the EU flag would be in the middle of a group of three flags rather than the Italian flag.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.governo.it/Presidenza/cerimoniale/onorificenze_araldica/documentazione/sistema_onorifico_rep_it.pdf The Rules of Protocol regarding national holidays and the use of the Italian flag] Presidency of the Council of Ministers, Department of Protocol (retrieved 5 October 2008)&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:Mrs. Laura Bush and daughter, Barbara Bush, are greeted by Italian Prime Minister Silvio Berlusconi.jpg|thumb| In Italy the European Flag must be displayed alongside the national flag in official ceremonies and over public buildings.]]

The flag is usually flown by the government of the country holding the [[Presidency of the Council of the European Union|rotating presidency]] [[Council of the European Union|Council of Ministers]], though in 2009 the [[President of the Czech Republic|Czech President]], a [[eurosceptic]], refused to fly the flag from his castle. In response, [[Greenpeace]] projected an image of the flag onto the castle and attempted to fly the flag from the building themselves.&lt;ref name=&quot;Czech&quot;&gt;{{citation|title=Greenpeace projects EU flag image on Prague Castle|date=7 January 2009|publisher=Ceske Noviny|url=http://www.ceskenoviny.cz/news/index_view.php?id=353387|accessdate=21 January 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Some members also have their own rules regarding the use of the flag alongside their national flag on domestic occasions, for example the obligatory use alongside national flags outside [[police stations]] or [[local government]] buildings. As an example according to the Italian laws it is mandatory for most public offices and buildings to hoist the European Flag alongside the Italian national Flag (Law 22/2000 and Presidential Decree 121/2000). Outside official use, the flag may not be used for aims incompatible with European values.&lt;ref name=&quot;FOTW legal&quot;/&gt;

In national usage, national protocol usually demands the national flag takes precedence over the European flag (which is usually displayed to the right of the national flag from the observer's perspective). On occasions where the European flag is flown alongside all national flags (for example, at a [[European Council]] meeting), the national flags are placed in alphabetical order (according to their name in the main [[Languages of the European Union|language]] of that state) with the European flag either at the head, or the far right, of the order of flags.&lt;ref name=&quot;Protocol IE&quot;&gt;{{citation|title=An Bhratach Náisiúnta / The National Flag|publisher=Department of the [[Taoiseach]]|url=http://www.taoiseach.gov.ie/attached_files/RTF%20files/The%20National%20Flag.rtf|format=RTF|accessdate=28 December 2007}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Protocol UK&quot;&gt;{{citation|title=A Guide to Flag Protocol in the United Kingdom|date=|publisher=[[Flag Institute]]|url=http://test2.leicester.gov.uk/EasySite/lib/serveDocument.asp?doc=79094&amp;pgid=89035|format=PDF|accessdate=28 December 2007}} {{dead link|date=June 2010| bot=DASHBot}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Extraordinary flying of the flag is common on the EU's [[flag day]], known as [[Europe Day]], which is celebrated annually on 9 May.&lt;ref&gt;{{citation|last=Rasmussen|first=Rina Valeur|title=Celebration of Europe Day 9 May 2007 in Denmar|publisher=Politeia|url=http://www.politeia.net/newsletter/politeia_newsletter_special_june_2007/celebration_of_europe_day_9_may_2007_in_denmark|accessdate=4 August 2007|archiveurl = http://web.archive.org/web/20070929003643/http://www.politeia.net/newsletter/politeia_newsletter_special_june_2007/celebration_of_europe_day_9_may_2007_in_denmark |archivedate = September 29, 2007|deadurl=yes}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{citation|title=Photo from Reuters Pictures|date=9 May 2008|publisher=[[Reuters]] Images, on [[Daylife]]|url=http://www.daylife.com/photo/0fic7mj4ujchD/European_Union|accessdate=9 May 2008}} {{dead link|date=June 2010| bot=DASHBot}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{citation|last=Rasmussen|first=Rina Valeur|title=London Eye lights up in colours of the European flag|date=9 May 2007|publisher=[[Europa (web portal)]]|url=http://ec.europa.eu/news/around/070509_uk_en.htm|accessdate=4 August 2007|archiveurl = http://web.archive.org/web/20070819214159/http://ec.europa.eu/news/around/070509_uk_en.htm |archivedate = August 19, 2007|deadurl=yes}}&lt;/ref&gt; On Europe Day 2008, the flag was flown for the first time above the German [[Reichstag (building)|Reichstag]].&lt;ref&gt;{{citation|title=Photo from Reuters Pictures|date=9 May 2008|publisher=[[Reuters]] Images, on [[Daylife]]|url=http://www.daylife.com/photo/058m1gweAF2Bh|accessdate=9 May 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt;{{-}}

==== Military and naval use ====
[[File:Pennant of the European Union Fishery Inspection.svg|thumb|[[Pennon|Pennant]] of fishery inspection vessels.]]
In addition to the flags use by the government and people, the flag is also used in EU military operations;&lt;ref&gt;{{citation|title=EUFOR Welcome Ceremony/Unfolding EU flag|publisher=[[NATO]]|url=http://www.nhqs.nato.int/multimedia/photoGallery/2003/NHQS/31%20March%20EUFOR%20Welcome%20Ceremony/pages/Unfolding%20EU%20flag%2001_jpg.htm|format=PDF|accessdate=14 April 2008|archiveurl = http://web.archive.org/web/20080611165130/http://www.nhqs.nato.int/multimedia/photoGallery/2003/NHQS/31%20March%20EUFOR%20Welcome%20Ceremony/pages/Unfolding%20EU%20flag%2001_jpg.htm |archivedate = June 11, 2008|deadurl=yes}}&lt;/ref&gt; however, it is not used as a [[civil ensign]]. In 2003, a [[member of the European Parliament]] tabled a proposal in a temporary [[Committees of the European Parliament|committee of the European Parliament]] that national civil ensigns be [[Defacement (flag)|defaced]] with the European flag. This proposal was rejected by Parliament in 2004, and hence the European flag is not used as a European civil ensign.&lt;ref&gt;{{citation|title=Rejected proposal of a European civil ensign|publisher=[[Flags of the World]]|url=http://areciboweb.50megs.com/fotw/flags/eu~eun.html#pro|accessdate=14 April 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Despite not having a civil ensign, the EU's Fishery Inspection teams display a blue and yellow [[Pennon|pennant]]. The pennant is flown by inspection vessels in [[Exclusive economic zone#European Union|EU waters]]. The flag is triangular and quartered blue and yellow and was adopted according to ''EEC Regulation #1382/87'' on 20 May 1978.&lt;ref&gt;{{citation|title=European Union Fishery Inspection|date=3 February 2008|publisher=[[Flags of the World]]|url=http://flagspot.net/flags/eu~fish.html|accessdate=15 July 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt; There are no other variants or alternative flags used by the EU (in contrast to countries which have presidential, naval and military variants).{{-}}

=== Wider use ===
[[File:Europe wins.jpg|thumb|European flag at victory of Europe over USA at the [[Ryder Cup]].]]
The flag has been intended to represent Europe in its wider sense. The Council of Europe covers all but three European countries, thereby representing much of Europe.&lt;ref name=&quot;COE page&quot;/&gt;

In particular the flag has become a banner for pro-Europeanism outside the Union, for example in [[Georgia (country)|Georgia]], where the flag is on most government buildings since the coming to power of [[Mikhail Saakashvili]],&lt;ref&gt;{{citation|last=Petersen|first=Alex|title=Comment - Georgia: Brussels on its mind|date=1 May 2007|publisher=[[EU Observer]]|url=http://euobserver.com/7/23969|accessdate=1 May 2007}}&lt;/ref&gt; who used it during his inauguration,&lt;ref&gt;{{citation|title=Saakashvili Sworn In as New President|publisher=Templeton Thorp|url=http://www.templetonthorp.com/en/news513|accessdate=4 August 2007}}&lt;/ref&gt; stating: &quot;[the European] flag is Georgia’s flag as well, as far as it embodies our civilisation, our culture, the essence of our history and perspective, and our vision for the future of Georgia.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{citation|last=Petersen|first=Alexandros|title=Georgia: Brussels on its mind|date=2 May 2007|publisher=Global Power Europe|url=http://www.globalpowereurope.eu/2007/05/georgia-brussels-on-its-mind.html|accessdate=25 August 2007}}&lt;/ref&gt; It was later used in 2008 by pro-western Serbian voters ahead of an election.&lt;ref&gt;{{citation|title=Photo from Reuters Pictures|date=9 May 2008|publisher=[[Reuters]] Images, on [[Daylife]]|url==http://www.daylife.com/photo/0aMZfuae7saPC/European_Union|accessdate=9 May 2008|archiveurl = http://web.archive.org/web/20080625171412/http://www.daylife.com/photo/0aMZfuae7saPC/European_Union |archivedate = June 25, 2008|deadurl=yes}}&lt;/ref&gt;

It is also used as a pro-democracy emblem in countries such as [[Belarus]], where it has been used on protest marches alongside the banned [[Flag of Belarus#The white-red-white flag|former national flag]] and flags of [[Zubr (political organization)|opposition movements]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Mite&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{citation|last=Myers|first=Steven Lee|title=Election is landslide for leader of Belarus|date=20 March 2006|publisher=[[International Herald Tribune]]|url=http://www.iht.com/articles/2006/03/19/news/belarus.php|accessdate=25 August 2007|coauthors=C.J. Chivers}}&lt;/ref&gt; The flag was used widely in a 2007 European March in [[Minsk]] as protesters rallied in support of democracy and accession to the EU.&lt;ref&gt;{{citation|title=Belarusians had European March in Mins|date=14 October 2007|publisher=charter97.org|url=http://www.charter97.org/en/news/2007/10/14/674/|accessdate=25 November 2007}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The flag is also used in certain sports arrangements where a unified [[Team Europe]] is represented. Following the [[2004 Summer Olympics]], [[President of the European Commission|President]] [[Romano Prodi]] pointed out that the combined [[2004 Summer Olympics medal table|medal total]] of the European Union was far greater than that of any other country and called for EU athletes to fly the European flag at the [[2008 Summer Olympics|following games]] alongside their own as a sign of solidarity (which did not happen).&lt;ref&gt;{{citation|last=Rachman|first=Gideon|title=The Ryder Cup and Euro-nationalism|date=22 September 2006|publisher=[[Financial Times]]|url=http://blogs.ft.com/rachmanblog/2006/09/the-ryder-cup-ahtml/|accessdate=17 August 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The flag, or features of it, are often used in the logos of organisations of companies which stress a pan-European element, for example European lobbyist groups or transnational shipping companies.{{-}}

The design of the European flag was displayed on the [[Eiffel Tower]] in [[Paris]] to celebrate the French presidency of the EU in the second half of 2008.

== Design ==
[[File:EU Flag specification.svg|right|300px|Construction Sheet]]
[[File:Flag of Europe (vertical).svg|thumb|70px|Vertical version, as shown where flying this flag format is common practice]]
The flag is rectangular with 2:3 proportions: its [[Flag terminology|fly]] (width) is one and a half times the length of its [[Flag terminology|hoist]] (height). Twelve [[gold (color)|gold]] (or [[yellow]]) stars are centered in a circle (the [[radius]] of which is a third of the length of the hoist) upon a [[blue]] background. All the stars are upright (one point straight up), have five points and are spaced equally according to the hour positions on the [[Clock face|face of a clock]].  Each star radius is equal to one-eighteenth of the height of the hoist.&lt;ref&gt;{{citation|title=Graphical specifications for the European flag|publisher=[[Council of Europe]]|url=http://www.coe.int/T/E/Com/About_Coe/flag_guide.asp#TopOfPage|accessdate=26 July 2008|archiveurl = http://web.archive.org/web/20080616035153/http://www.coe.int/T/E/Com/About_Coe/flag_guide.asp#TopOfPage |archivedate = June 16, 2008|deadurl=yes}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{citation|title=Graphical specifications for the European Emblem|publisher=[[Communication department of the European Commission]]|url=http://europa.eu/abc/symbols/emblem/graphics1_en.htm|accessdate=June 16, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The [[heraldic]] description given by the EU is: &quot;On an [[azure]] field a circle of twelve golden [[Mullet (heraldry)|mullets]], their points not touching.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{citation|title=Graphical specifications for the European Emblem|publisher=[[Europa (web portal)|European Commission]]|url=http://europa.eu/abc/symbols/emblem/graphics1_en.htm#symbol|accessdate=4 August 2004}}&lt;/ref&gt; The Council of Europe gives the flag a symbolic description in the following terms;

{{quote|Against the blue sky of the Western world, the stars represent the peoples of Europe in a circle, a symbol of unity. Their number shall be invariably set at twelve, the symbol of completeness and perfection.|Council of Europe. Paris, 7–9 December 1955&lt;ref name=&quot;36th&quot;&gt;{{Citation|title=Thirty-sixth meeting of the ministers' deputies: resolution (55) 32|publisher=Council of Europe|date=9 December 1955|url=http://www.coe.int/t/dgal/dit/ilcd/fonds/themes/flags/Res(55)32_en.pdf|accessdate=2008-02-02}}&lt;/ref&gt;}}

Just like the [[Zodiac#The twelve signs|twelve signs of the zodiac]] represent the whole universe, the twelve gold stars stand for all peoples of Europe – including those who cannot as yet take part.

&lt;gallery widths=&quot;150px&quot; heights=&quot;100px&quot;&gt;
File:Flag of Europe.svg|{{FIAV|normal}} '''Correct''' way to fly flag. Emblem is the right way up
File:European flag, upside down.svg|{{FIAV|noflag}} '''Incorrect''' way to fly flag. Emblem is upside down
File:European flag, incorrect star rotation.svg|{{FIAV|noflag}} '''Incorrect''' design of flag. Stars are not upright
File:European flag, incorrect star positions.svg|{{FIAV|noflag}} '''Incorrect''' design of  flag.  Stars are wrongly positioned in the circle
&lt;/gallery&gt;

=== Colours ===
{| class=&quot;wikitable&quot;
| rowspan=&quot;2&quot; style=&quot;border-top:2px solid white; border-left:2px solid white; background:white&quot; |
! rowspan=&quot;2&quot; | [[Pantone|PMS]]
! colspan=&quot;3&quot; | [[RGB]] approx.
! rowspan=&quot;2&quot; |[[Web colour|Hexadecimal]]
! colspan=&quot;4&quot; | [[CMYK]]
|-
! red
! green
! blue
! process cyan
! process magenta
! process yellow
! process black
|-
! {{Color box|#003399}} Blue
| Reflex blue || &lt;code&gt;0&lt;/code&gt; || &lt;code&gt;51&lt;/code&gt; || &lt;code&gt;153&lt;/code&gt; || &lt;code&gt;003399&lt;/code&gt; || 100% || 80% || 0% || 0%
|-
! {{Color box|#FFCC00}} Gold
| Yellow || &lt;code&gt;255&lt;/code&gt; || &lt;code&gt;204&lt;/code&gt; || &lt;code&gt;0&lt;/code&gt; || &lt;code&gt;FFCC00&lt;/code&gt; || 0% || 0% || 100% || 0%
|}

The base colour of the flag is a dark blue (reflex [[blue]], a mix of [[cyan]] and [[magenta]]), while the golden stars are portrayed in Yellow. The colours are regulated according to the [[Pantone]] colouring system (see table for specifications).

A large number of designs&lt;ref name=&quot;ENA page&quot;&gt;{{Citation|title=The European flag: questions and answers |editor=European NAvigator |url=http://www.ena.lu?lang=2&amp;doc=21621 |accessdate=09-10-2009}}&lt;/ref&gt; were proposed for the flag before the current flag was agreed. The rejected proposals are preserved in the [[Council of Europe Archives]]. One of these consists of a design of white stars on a light blue field, as a gesture to the peace and internationalism of the [[United Nations]].&lt;ref name=&quot;FOTW proposals&quot;/&gt; An official website makes a reference to blue and gold being the original colours of [[Count Richard Nikolaus von Coudenhove-Kalergi]], who proposed a [[International Paneuropean Union|Pan European Union]] in 1923, and was an active proponent of the early Community.&lt;ref name=&quot;FOTW ECSC&quot;&gt;{{citation|title=Do the Number of Stars on the European Flag Represent the Member States?|publisher=European Commission's delegation to Ukraine|url=http://www.delukr.ec.europa.eu/page6858.html|accessdate=11 July 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Citation|title=Do the Number of Stars on the European Flag Represent the Member States?|publisher=European Commission's delegation to Ukraine|url=http://www.delukr.ec.europa.eu/page6858.html|accessdate=2008-07-11}}&lt;/ref&gt;{{-}}

=== Number of stars ===
[[File:Olympians.jpg|thumb|upright|''The [[Twelve Olympians]]'' by [[Nicolas-André Monsiau|Monsiau]] (late 18th century)]]
The number of stars on the flag is fixed at 12, and is not related to the number of member states of the EU. This is because it originally was the flag of the [[Council of Europe]], and does not have a relationship with the EU.&lt;ref name=&quot;Europa history&quot;/&gt; In 1953, the Council of Europe had 15 members; it was proposed that the future flag should have one star for each member, and would not change based on future members. [[West Germany]] objected to this as one of the members was the disputed area of [[Saarland]], and to have its own star would imply [[sovereignty]] for the region.&lt;ref name=&quot;Irish&quot;&gt;{{citation|last=Murphy|first=Sean|title=Memorandum on the Role of Irish Chief Herald Slevin in the Design of the European Flag|date=25 January 2006|publisher=Centre for Irish Genealogical and Historical Studies|url=http://homepage.eircom.net/%7Eseanjmurphy/chiefs/euroflagmemo.html|accessdate=2 February 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[12 (number)|Twelve]] was eventually adopted as a number with no political connotations and as a symbol of perfection and completeness&lt;ref name=&quot;Europa history&quot;/&gt; because of the ubiquity of the number for groups in European cultures and traditions such as:

{{Colbegin}}
* 12 [[stars]] crowning the head of the [[Queen of Heaven]] in the book of Revelation, Chapter 12
* 12 [[Twelve Apostles|apostles]] of [[Jesus|Jesus Christ]]
* 12 [[Twelve Days of Christmas|days of Christmas]]
* 12 [[Jacob#Jacob.27s sons|sons of Jacob]]
* 12 [[tribes of Israel]]
* 12 [[Bible|Biblical]] [[minor prophet]]s
* 12 [[Twelve Tables|tables of Roman Law]]
* 12 [[Twelve Olympians|Olympian gods]]
* 12 [[labours of Hercules]]
* 12 [[Lives of the Twelve Caesars|Caesars]] chronicled by [[Suetonius]]
* 12 books of ''[[Paradise Lost]]'' and the ''[[Aeneid]]''
* 12 [[Astronomical symbols#Zodiac|symbols of the zodiac]]
* 12 [[hue]]s in the [[colour wheel]], star or sphere (western art)
* 12 [[hour]]s on a [[clock]]
* 12 [[month]]s in a [[year]]
* 12 [[ounces]] in a [[Troy weight|troy pound]]
* 12 [[semitones]] in an octave
{{Colend}}

While 12 is the correct number of stars, sometimes flags or emblems can be found that incorrectly show 15 (as of the rejected proposal) or 25 (as incorrectly suggested by some after the [[2004 enlargement of the European Union|expansion to 25 member states in 2004]]).&lt;ref name=&quot;flagspot page&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url=http://flagspot.net/flags/eu-eun.html#sta |title=Number of stars on the flag of the European Union |author=Sache, Ivan |date=17 July 2004 |accessdate=7 July 2010 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;flagboss page&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.flagboss.com/organization-flags/european-economic-community-flag-2-3-x-5.html | title=European Economic Community Flag 2  |accessdate=7 July 2010 }}&lt;/ref&gt;{{-}}

=== Biblical interpretation ===
[[File:Dolci Madonna p1070185.jpg|thumb|upright|''Madonna in Glory'' by [[Carlo Dolci]], c. 1670]]
One interesting aspect of the flag is the likeness to the twelve-star halo of the [[Blessed Virgin Mary|Virgin Mary]] seen in the sacred art of the [[Catholic Church]]. The flag's designer, Arsène Heitz, has acknowledged that the [[Book of Revelation]] (which is where the twelve-star halo of the Queen of Heaven was first mentioned) helped to inspire him.&lt;ref name=&quot;Economist religious&quot;&gt;{{citation|title=The European Commission and religious values|date=28 October 2004|publisher=[[The Economist]]|url=http://www.economist.com/printedition/PrinterFriendly.cfm?Story_ID=3332056|accessdate=4 August 2007}}&lt;/ref&gt; {{bibleref|Revelation|12:1}} is cited to explain the symbolism: &quot;A great sign appeared in heaven, a woman clothed with the sun, and the moon under her feet, and on her head a crown of twelve stars&quot; (a crown of stars can be interpreted as a &quot;[[Crown of Immortality]]&quot;). It has been noted that the date the flag was adopted, 8 December 1955, coincided with the Catholic [[Feast of the Immaculate Conception]] of the [[Blessed Virgin Mary]], a feast decreed in 1854 by [[Pope Pius IX]].&lt;ref name=&quot;origine&quot;&gt;{{citation|title=L'origine chrétienne du drapeau européen|publisher=www.atheisme.org|url=http://www.atheisme.org/drapeau.html|accessdate=21 January 2009}} {{Fr icon}} [http://translate.google.com/translate?u=http%3A%2F%2Fwww.atheisme.org%2Fdrapeau.html&amp;sl=fr&amp;tl=en&amp;hl=en&amp;ie=UTF-8 English translation by Google here]&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:Virgen estrasburgo UE.jpg|thumb|left|''Blessing Madonna'', stained glass window in [[Strasbourg Cathedral]] featuring the twelve stars.&lt;ref&gt;{{citation|title=Large full version of the window|date=|publisher=www.venez-chez-domi.fr|url=http://www.venez-chez-domi.fr/blog/wp-content/uploads/2007/07/32-abside-notre-dame-de-strasbourggrande.jpg|accessdate=28 January 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt;]]

A myth has evolved around [[Paul Michel Gabriel Lévy|Paul Lévy]], a [[Belgium|Belgian]] of [[Jewish]] descent, who vowed that if he should survive the war, he would convert to [[Christianity]]. He duly survived and became a [[Catholic]]. When the Council of Europe was established, Lévy became Chief of its Department of Culture. In 1952, when the idea of a European flag was being discussed, Lévy backed the flag of the Pan European Movement. However, the cross element in its design was rejected by Socialists and Turks as too Christian. Allegedly, Lévy one day passed a statue of the Virgin Mary with a halo of stars and was struck by the way the stars, reflecting the sun, glowed against the blue of the sky. Lévy later visited Count Benvenuti, a Venetian Christian democrat and then Secretary General of the Council of Europe, and suggested that he should propose twelve golden stars on a blue ground as motif for the flag of Europe. However, the idea for the flag's design came from [[Arsène Heitz]], not Lévy, and Lévy has stated that he was only informed of the connection to the Book of Revelation after it was chosen.&lt;ref name=&quot;Levy&quot;/&gt; Official authorities of the European Union disregard the biblical interpretation as myth.&lt;ref&gt;{{citation|title=European Union: Myths on the flag|date=4 February 2007|publisher=[[Flags Of The World]]|url=http://www.crwflags.com/fotw/flags/eu!myt.html|accessdate=4 August 2007}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Despite the formal rejection of biblical references, on 21 October 1956 the Council of Europe presented the city of [[Strasbourg]], its official seat, with a stained glass window for [[Strasbourg Cathedral]] by the [[Paris]]ian master Max Ingrand. It shows a blessing Madonna underneath a circle of 12 stars on dark blue ground.&lt;ref name=&quot;origine&quot;/&gt; The overall design of the Madonna is inspired by the [[banner]] of the cathedral's ''Congrégation Mariale des Hommes'', and the twelve stars are found on the statue venerated by this congregation inside the cathedral (twelve is also the number of members of the congregation's council).&lt;ref&gt;{{citation |title=Congrégation Mariale des Hommes |date=4 February 2004 |publisher=Cathédrale Notre-Dame de Strasbourg |url=http://www.cathedrale-strasbourg.fr/congregation_mariale.aspx |accessdate=24 January 2009 |language=French}}&lt;/ref&gt;{{-}}

== Derivative designs ==
{{Multiple image|direction=vertical|align=right|image1=Flag of Bosnia and Herzegovina.svg|image2=Flag of Kosovo.svg|width=150|caption2=The flags of Bosnia &amp; Herzegovina and Kosovo have references to the European flag}}
The design of the European flag has been used in a variation, such as that of the Council of Europe mentioned above, and also to a greater extent such as the [[flag of the Western European Union]] (WEU), which uses the same colours and the stars but has a number of stars based on membership and in a semicircle rather than a circle. It is also [[Defacement (flag)|defaced]] with the initials of the [[Western European Union]] in two languages.&lt;ref&gt;{{citation|title=Western European Union|publisher=[[Flags of the World]]|url=http://www.crwflags.com/fotw/flags/eu%5Eweu.html|accessdate=11 February 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The [[flag of Bosnia and Herzegovina]] does not have such a strong connection as the WEU flag, but was partly inspired by the European involvement in, and aspirations of, [[Bosnia and Herzegovina]]. It uses the same blue and yellow colours and the stars, although of a different number and colour, are a direct reference to those of the European flag.&lt;ref&gt;{{citation|title=Bosnia and Herzegovina - The 1998 Flag Change - Westendorp Commission - The Choice)|publisher=[[Flags of the World]]|url=http://www.crwflags.com/fotw/flags/ba-fccho.html|accessdate=11 February 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Likewise, [[Kosovo]] uses blue, yellow and stars in [[Flag of Kosovo|its flag]] in reference to the European flag, symbolising its European ambitions ([[Accession of Kosovo to the European Union|membership of the European Union]]). Kosovo has, like Bosnia and Herzegovina, seen heavy European involvement in its affairs, with the European Union assuming a supervisory role after its declared independence in 2008.&lt;ref&gt;{{citation|title=Kosovo's fiddly new flag|date=18 February 2008|publisher=[[The Economist]]|url=http://www.economist.com/blogs/certainideasofeurope/2008/02/kosovos_fiddly_new_flag.cfm|accessdate=11 February 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{citation|title=Kosovo's Flag Revealed|date=17 February 2008|publisher=Balkan Insight|url=http://www.balkaninsight.com/en/main/news/7950/|accessdate=11 February 2009}} {{Dead link|date=October 2010|bot=H3llBot}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Other labels take reference to the European flag such as the [[Organic_certification#Europe|EU organic food label]] that uses the twelve stars but reorders them into the shape of a leaf on a green background. The original logo of the [[European Broadcasting Union]] used the twelve stars on a blue background adding ray beams to connect the countries.

== See also ==
{{Portal box|Europe|European Union}}
* [[Circle of stars]]
* [[Flag of the European Coal and Steel Community]]
* [[Flag of the Western European Union]]
* [[Federalist flag]]
* [[Symbols of Europe]]

== References ==
{{Reflist|2}}

== External links ==
{{Commons|Flag of the European Union}}
* [http://www.coe.int/T/E/Com/About_Coe/flag.asp Council of Europe on the flag]
** [http://www.coe.int/t/dgal/dit/ilcd/Historical_Content/flag_en.asp Council of Europe historical files on the flag]
* [http://europa.eu/abc/symbols/emblem/graphics1_en.htm EU's graphical specifications for the flag]
* [http://www.ena.lu?lang=2&amp;doc=19575 Flag of the European Union] European Navigator
* [http://www.ena.lu?lang=2&amp;doc=23600 Ceremony to mark the expiry of the ECSC Treaty (Brussels, 23 July 2002)], [[European NAvigator]]
* [https://www.cia.gov/library/publications/the-world-factbook/flags/ee-flag.html CIA page]
* {{FOTW|id=eu-eun|title=European Union}}
* [http://homepage.eircom.net/%7Eseanjmurphy/chiefs/euroflagmemo.html Memorandum on design and designer of European flag]
* [http://www.flags.net/EUUN.htm World flag database]

{{EU symbols}}
{{Flag of Europe}}

{{Good article}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Europe}}
[[Category:International flags]]
[[Category:Council of Europe|Flag]]
[[Category:Symbols of the European Union|Flag]]

{{Link GA|sv}}

[[am:የአውሮፓ ሰንደቅ ዓላማ]]
[[ar:علم الاتحاد الأوروبي]]
[[an:Bandera Europeya]]
[[frp:Drapél eropèen]]
[[be:Сцяг Еўропы]]
[[bs:Zastava Evropske unije]]
[[bg:Знаме на Европа]]
[[ca:Bandera d'Europa]]
[[cs:Vlajka Evropské unie]]
[[cy:Baner Ewrop]]
[[da:Europaflaget]]
[[de:Europaflagge]]
[[et:Euroopa lipp]]
[[el:Ευρωπαϊκή σημαία]]
[[es:Bandera europea]]
[[eo:Flago de la Eŭropa Unio]]
[[fa:پرچم اتحادیه اروپا]]
[[fr:Drapeau européen]]
[[gv:Brattagh ny h-Oarpey]]
[[gl:Bandeira da Unión Europea]]
[[ko:유럽기]]
[[hr:Zastava Europske unije]]
[[id:Bendera Eropa]]
[[ia:Bandiera europee]]
[[is:Evrópufáninn]]
[[it:Bandiera europea]]
[[he:דגל האיחוד האירופי]]
[[jv:Gendéra Éropah]]
[[ka:ევროკავშირის დროშა]]
[[lb:Europafändel]]
[[lt:Europos Sąjungos vėliava]]
[[hu:Európai zászló]]
[[mk:Знаме на Европската Унија]]
[[ms:Bendera Eropah]]
[[nl:Vlag van Europa]]
[[ja:欧州旗]]
[[no:Det europeiske flagg]]
[[pl:Flaga europejska]]
[[pt:Bandeira europeia]]
[[ro:Drapelul Europei]]
[[ru:Флаг Европы]]
[[sco:Banner o Europe]]
[[sq:Flamuri i Evropës]]
[[sl:Evropska zastava]]
[[sr:Застава Европске уније]]
[[sh:Zastava Evropske Unije]]
[[fi:Euroopan lippu]]
[[sv:Europeiska flaggan]]
[[tt:АБ байрагы]]
[[tg:Парчами Аврупо]]
[[tr:Avrupa Birliği bayrağı]]
[[uk:Прапор Європи]]
[[wa:Drapea d' l' Union Uropeyinne]]
[[zh:欧盟旗帜]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
