<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="1004822" ns="0" title="Kenneth Bigley"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{No footnotes|date=March 2010}}

[[Image:Bigleyandwife.jpg|right|frame|Kenneth Bigley and his wife Sombat at their wedding in 1998.]]
'''Kenneth John Bigley''' (22 April 1942 - 7 October 2004), born [[Liverpool]], [[England]], was a [[civil engineer]] who was [[Kidnapping|kidnapped]] in the [[Mansour district|al-Mansour district]] of Baghdad, Iraq on 16 September 2004, along with his colleagues [[Jack Hensley]] and [[Eugene Armstrong]], both [[United States|U.S.]] citizens. The three men were working for Gulf Supplies and Commercial Services, a Kuwaiti company working on reconstruction projects in Iraq. They knew their house was being watched and that they were in grave danger because their Iraqi house guard told them he was quitting because he had been threatened by militias that knew he was protecting Americans and British workers, but Bigley and the two Americans decided it was worth it to live with the danger.  All were subsequently [[Decapitation|beheaded]].

On 18 September, the [[Jama'at al-Tawhid wal-Jihad|Tawhid and Jihad]] (&quot;Oneness of God and [[Jihad]]&quot;) [[Islamic extremist]] group, led by [[Jordan]]ian [[Abu Musab al-Zarqawi]], released a video of the three men kneeling in front of a Tawhid and Jihad banner. The kidnappers said they would kill the men within 48 hours if their demands for the release of Iraqi women prisoners held by [[Coalition of the willing|coalition forces]] were not met.

Armstrong was beheaded on 20 September when the deadline expired, Hensley 24 hours later, and Bigley over two weeks later, despite the intervention of the [[Muslim Council of Britain]] and the indirect intervention of the British government. Videos of the killings were posted on websites and blogs. Using voice-recognition technology, the [[Central Intelligence Agency]] (CIA) has claimed that al-Zarqawi personally carried out the beheading of Armstrong.

Before Bigley's death, it was claimed that the British [[Secret Intelligence Service]] (commonly known as MI6) had launched a rescue operation that had allowed Bigley to escape for a brief period, but he was recaptured at a roadblock, taken back to the Tawhid and Jihad safehouse, and beheaded shortly afterwards.
__TOC__
== Capture and negotiations for release ==
After Armstrong and Hensley were killed, the British government and media responded by turning Bigley's fate into Britain's major political issue during this period, leading to subsequent claims that the government had become a hostage to the situation, as [[President of the United States|President]] [[Jimmy Carter]] had arguably done during the 444-day [[Iran hostage crisis]] in 1979-81.

[[Secretary of State for Foreign and Commonwealth Affairs|British Foreign Secretary]] [[Jack Straw]] and [[Prime Minister of the United Kingdom|Prime Minister]] [[Tony Blair]] personally contacted the Bigley family several times to assure them that everything possible was being done, short of direct negotiation with the kidnappers. It was also reported that a [[Special Air Service]] (SAS) team had been placed on standby in Iraq in the event that a rescue mission might become possible.

The British government issued a statement saying it held no Iraqi women prisoners, and that the only two women known to be in U.S. custody were two so-called high-profile Iraqi scientists, British-educated Dr. [[Rihab Taha]] and U.S.-educated Dr. [[Huda Salih Mahdi Ammash]]. Both women participated in Iraq's biological-weapons program, according to the [[United Nations]] weapons inspectorate.
News reports had earlier suggested that other Iraqi women were indeed being held in U.S. custody, but it is not known to what extent these reports were out-of-date by the time of Bigley's kidnap.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news| url=http://www.guardian.co.uk/women/story/0,3604,1220673,00.html | location=London | work=The Guardian | first=Luke | last=Harding | title=The other prisoners | date=20 May 2004}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The Iraqi provisional government stated that Dr. Taha and Dr. Ammash could be released immediately, stressing that this was about to happen anyway, as no charges had been brought against the women.

=== Second and third videos ===
A second video was released on 22 September by Bigley's captors, this time showing Bigley pleading for his life and begging British Prime Minister Tony Blair to save him. Clearly exhausted and highly emotional, Bigley spoke directly to Blair: &quot;I need you to help me now, [Mr.] Blair, because you are the only person on God's earth who can help me.&quot; The video was posted on several websites, blogs and shown on [[al Jazeera]] television.

Around this time it emerged that Bigley's mother, Lil, 86 years old at the time of his abduction, had been born in [[Dublin]] and was therefore an Irish citizen; this meant Bigley himself was also an Irish citizen from birth. It was hoped this status would aid his release, as Ireland did not participate in the [[2003 invasion of Iraq]], and the Irish Government issued Bigley an Irish passport ''[[in absentia]]'', which was shown on al-Jazeera television. Irish Labour Party spokesman on foreign affairs Michael D. Higgins made an appeal on al-Jazeera. [[Sinn Féin]] leader [[Gerry Adams]] made two appeals, one on 30 September and a second on 7 October.

On 24 September 50,000 leaflets prepared by the [[Foreign and Commonwealth Office|British Foreign Office]], asking for information about Bigley's whereabouts, were distributed in al-Mansour, the wealthy district of Baghdad Bigley had been living in. In his home city of Liverpool, Christian and Muslim religious and civic leaders held joint prayer sessions for his safe return.

The [[Muslim Council of Britain]] condemned the kidnapping, saying it was contrary to the teachings of the [[Qur'an]] and sent a senior two-man delegation to Iraq to negotiate on Bigley's behalf. Bigley's family, particularly his brother Paul, was successful, with the help of the Irish government, in eliciting support for Bigley's release from Palestinian leader [[Yasser Arafat]], [[Abdullah II of Jordan|King Abdullah of Jordan]], and [[Muammar al-Gaddafi|Colonel Gadaffi of Libya]], who made public statements.

A third video was released on 29 September showing Bigley chained inside a small chicken-wire cage, wearing an orange boiler suit apparently intended to be reminiscent of those worn by inmates at the U.S. facility in [[Guantanamo Bay detainment camp|Guantanamo Bay]]. In the video, Bigley again begged for his life, saying, &quot;Tony Blair is lying. He doesn't care about me. I'm just one person.&quot;

On 1 October, another 100,000 leaflets asking for information about Bigley were distributed by the British Foreign Office in Baghdad.

== Death ==
Despite the efforts to save him, Bigley was [[Decapitation|beheaded]] on 7 October 2004. His death was first reported on [[Abu Dhabi]] television the following day.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.nytimes.com/2004/10/08/international/middleeast/08CND-IRAQ.html &quot;British Hostage Is Beheaded in Iraq&quot;]&lt;/ref&gt; A multi-faith [[funeral|memorial service]], attended by Tony Blair and his wife [[Cherie Blair|Cherie]], was held for him in Liverpool on 13 November. His body has not been recovered, although an alleged al-Qaeda militant awaiting trial for the [[2003 Istanbul bombings]] has claimed he is &quot;buried in a ditch at the entrance to [[Fallujah]]&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news| url=http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/uk/4933490.stm | work=BBC News | title=Bigley body claims investigated | date=22 April 2006}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The kidnappers made a film apparently showing Bigley's killing, and the tape was subsequently posted on Islamist websites and on one [[shock site|&quot;shock&quot; site]]. According to reporters who watched the film, Bigley was wearing an orange jumpsuit, and read out a statement, before one of the kidnappers stepped forward and cut off his head with a knife.

News reports published after Bigley's death suggested he had briefly managed to escape from the kidnappers with the help of two [[MI6]] agents of [[Syria]]n and Iraqi origin, who paid two of his captors to help him.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news| url=http://www.timesonline.co.uk/article/0,,2087-1302700,00.html | location=London | work=The Times | first1=Hala | last1=Jaber | title=Bigley beheaded after MI6 rescue backfired | date=10 October 2004}}&lt;/ref&gt; The captors attempted to drive Bigley, who was carrying a gun and was disguised, out of town, the reports said, but he was spotted and recaptured at an insurgent checkpoint. The two captors were said to have been beheaded.

After his death, the British [[mass media|media]] were criticized for the amount of [[news]] coverage his situation had been given. The same high-coverage news [[strategy]] was notably absent in the case of [[Margaret Hassan]], the Irish-born [[aid worker]], who held Irish, British and Iraqi citizenship, who was kidnapped on 19 October 2004 and killed two weeks later.

Columnist and author [[Mark Steyn]] had his column pulled from the British ''[[Daily Telegraph]]'' on 11 October 2004 when in it he stated that Bigley's last words &quot;Tony Blair has not done enough for me&quot; would not be high up on his list of final utterances.

In October 2004, during an 18-night stint at London's [[Hammersmith Apollo]], the Scottish comedian and actor [[Billy Connolly]] was criticised for making jokes about the hostage Bigley.&lt;ref&gt;[http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/england/merseyside/3717462.stm BBC News: Connolly blasted over Bigley joke]&lt;/ref&gt; Shortly after Connolly joked about the future killing of the hostage and touched on the subject of Bigley’s young Thai wife, Bigley was beheaded in Iraq. Connolly claims he was misquoted. He has declined to clarify what he actually said, claiming that the context was as important as the precise words used. However, it was reported that Connolly actually said &quot;When you hear about Bigley in the news, don't you wish they would just get on with, it?&quot; Connolly's routine has since been defended as an attack on the prurient media coverage of the incident, rather than a tasteless comment at the expense of the Bigleys.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/magazine-12775389|title=Why do people tell sick jokes about tragedies?|first=Jon|last=Kelly|work=BBC News website|date=18 March 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Torture-chamber discovery ==
The chicken-wire cage Bigley was filmed in was found in November 2004 by U.S. troops in a house in the Iraqi town of Fallujah during the [[Second Battle of Fallujah]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news| url=http://www.telegraph.co.uk/news/main.jhtml?xml=/news/2004/11/22/uhouses.xml&amp;sSheet=/portal/2004/11/22/ixportaltop.html | location=London | work=The Daily Telegraph}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news| url=http://www.guardian.co.uk/Iraq/Story/0,2763,1350982,00.html | location=London | work=The Guardian | title=The final battle | date=14 November 2004}}&lt;/ref&gt; The U.S. military stated that, in 20 houses, it found [[paraphernalia]] associated with hostage-holding and [[torture]], including shackles, blood-stained walls, and a torture chamber.

== See also ==
{{Portalbox|Biography|England|Terrorism}}
* [[2003 invasion of Iraq]]
* [[Human rights in post-invasion Iraq|Human rights situation in post-Saddam Iraq]]
* [[Decapitation]]
* [[Daniel Pearl]]
* [[Nick Berg]]
* [[Paul Marshall Johnson, Jr.]]
* [[Eugene Armstrong]]
* [[Margaret Hassan]]
* [[Jack Hensley]]
* [[Kim Sun-il]]
* [[Shosei Koda]]
* [[Fabrizio Quattrocchi]]
* [[Seif Adnan Kanaan]]
* [[Piotr Stańczak]]
{{-}}

==References==
{{Reflist}}

==External links==
* [http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/uk/3729158.stm Ken Bigley's wife mourns the loss of her husband] - [[BBC]]
* [http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/uk/3683182.stm ''Profile:Kenneth Bigley''], ''BBC News'', 10 October 2004
* [http://observer.guardian.co.uk/review/story/0,6903,1355798,00.html &quot;Theatre of terror&quot;], by Jason Burke, ''The Observer'', 21 November 2004
* [http://www.timesonline.co.uk/article/0,,2087-1302700,00.html &quot;Bigley beheaded after MI6 rescue backfired&quot;], by Hala Jaber and Ali Rifat, ''The Sunday Times'', 10 October 2004
* [http://www.guardian.co.uk/women/story/0,3604,1220673,00.html &quot;The other prisoners&quot;] by Luke Harding, ''The Guardian'', 20 May 2004
* [http://www.telegraph.co.uk/news/main.jhtml?xml=/news/2004/11/22/uhouses.xml&amp;sSheet=/portal/2004/11/22/ixportaltop.html &quot;Ken Bigley's hostage cage 'found'&quot;], no byline, ''The Daily Telegraph'', 22 November 2004
* [http://www.guardian.co.uk/Iraq/Story/0,2763,1350982,00.html &quot;The final battle&quot;] by Peter Beaumont, ''The Observer'', 14 November 2004
* [http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/uk/4933490.stm &quot;Bigley body claims investigated&quot;] ''BBC News'', 22 April 2006
* [http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/uk_politics/3749548.stm &quot;Spectator apology for 'disproportionate grief' for Mr Bigley&quot;] ''BBC News'', 16 October 2004
*&quot;[http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/talking_point/3726732.stm Ken Bigley killed: Your reaction].&quot; ''[[BBC]]''. Thursday 14 October 2004.

{{Persondata &lt;!-- Metadata: see [[Wikipedia:Persondata]]. --&gt;
| NAME              = Bigley, Kenneth
| ALTERNATIVE NAMES =
| SHORT DESCRIPTION =
| DATE OF BIRTH     = 22 April 1942
| PLACE OF BIRTH    =
| DATE OF DEATH     = 7 October 2004
| PLACE OF DEATH    =
}}
{{DEFAULTSORT:Bigley, Kenneth}}
[[Category:1942 births]]
[[Category:2004 deaths]]

[[Category:Murder in 2004]]
[[Category:Deaths by decapitation]]
[[Category:English civil engineers]]
[[Category:English murder victims]]
[[Category:Foreign hostages in Iraq]]
[[Category:People from Liverpool]]
[[Category:British people taken hostage]]
[[Category:British terrorism victims]]
[[Category:Terrorism deaths in Iraq]]
[[Category:Filmed executions in Iraq]]
[[Category:British people murdered abroad]]
[[Category:People murdered in Iraq]]
[[Category:Place of birth missing]]

[[ar:كينيث بجلي]]
[[fi:Kenneth Bigley]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
