<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="10106" ns="0" title="Earthquake"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{for}}
{{pp-semi-protected|small=yes}}
[[Image:Quake epicenters 1963-98.png|thumb|300px|Global earthquake [[epicenter]]s, 1963–1998]]
[[Image:Global plate motion 2008-04-17.jpg|thumb|300px|Global plate tectonic movement]]
An '''earthquake''' (also known as a '''quake''', '''tremor''' or '''temblor''') is the result of a sudden release of energy in the [[Earth|Earth's]] [[crust (geology)|crust]] that creates [[seismic wave]]s. The '''seismicity''', '''seismism'''  or '''seismic activity''' of an area refers to the frequency, type and size of earthquakes experienced over a period of time. Earthquakes are measured using observations from [[seismometer]]s. The [[Moment magnitude scale|moment magnitude]] is the most common scale on which earthquakes larger than approximately 5 are reported for the entire globe.  The more numerous earthquakes smaller than magnitude 5 reported by national seismological observatories are measured mostly on the local magnitude scale, also referred to as the [[Richter magnitude scale|Richter]] scale.  These two scales are numerically similar over their range of validity. Magnitude 3 or lower earthquakes are mostly almost imperceptible and magnitude 7 and over potentially cause serious damage over large areas, depending on their depth. The largest earthquakes in historic times have been of magnitude slightly over 9, although there is no limit to the possible magnitude. The most recent large earthquake of magnitude 9.0 or larger was a [[2011 Tōhoku earthquake and tsunami|9.0 magnitude earthquake in Japan in 2011]] (as of March 2011), and it was the largest Japanese earthquake since records began. Intensity of shaking is measured on the modified [[Mercalli intensity scale|Mercalli scale]]. The shallower an earthquake, the more damage to structures it causes, all else being equal.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.crustal.ucsb.edu/outreach/faq.php |title=Earthquake FAQ |publisher=Crustal.ucsb.edu |date= |accessdate=2011-07-24}}&lt;/ref&gt;

At the Earth's surface, earthquakes manifest themselves by shaking and sometimes displacement of the ground. When the [[epicenter]] of a large earthquake is located offshore, the seabed may be displaced sufficiently to cause a [[tsunami]]. Earthquakes can also trigger landslides, and occasionally volcanic activity.

In its most general sense, the word ''earthquake'' is used to describe any seismic event — whether natural or caused by humans — that generates seismic waves. Earthquakes are caused mostly by rupture of geological [[Fault (geology)|faults]], but also by other events such as volcanic activity, landslides, mine blasts, and [[Underground nuclear testing|nuclear tests]]. An earthquake's point of initial rupture is called its [[focus (earthquake)|focus]] or [[hypocenter]]. The [[epicenter]] is the point at ground level directly above the hypocenter.

==Naturally occurring earthquakes==
[[Image:Fault types.png|thumb|Fault types]]

Tectonic earthquakes occur anywhere in the earth where there is sufficient stored elastic strain energy to drive fracture propagation along a [[fault plane]]. The sides of a fault move past each other smoothly and [[Aseismic creep|aseismically]] only if there are no irregularities or [[Asperity (material science)|asperities]] along the fault surface that increase the frictional resistance. Most fault surfaces do have such asperities and this leads to a form of [[Stick-slip phenomenon|stick-slip behaviour]]. Once the fault has locked, continued relative motion between the plates leads to increasing stress and therefore, stored strain energy in the volume around the fault surface. This continues until the stress has risen sufficiently to break through the asperity, suddenly allowing sliding over the locked portion of the fault, releasing the [[Potential energy|stored energy]]. This energy is released as a combination of radiated elastic [[Strain (materials science)|strain]] [[seismic waves]], frictional heating of the fault surface, and cracking of the rock, thus causing an earthquake. This process of gradual build-up of strain and stress punctuated by occasional sudden earthquake failure is referred to as the [[elastic-rebound theory]]. It is estimated that only 10 percent or less of an earthquake's total energy is radiated as seismic energy. Most of the earthquake's energy is used to power the earthquake [[Fracture (geology)|fracture]] growth or is converted into heat generated by friction. Therefore, earthquakes lower the Earth's available [[elastic potential energy]] and raise its temperature, though these changes are negligible compared to the conductive and convective flow of heat out from the Earth's deep interior.&lt;ref name=&quot;USGS1&quot;&gt;{{cite web | last = Spence | first = William | coauthors = S. A. Sipkin, G. L. Choy | title = Measuring the Size of an Earthquake | publisher = [[United States Geological Survey]] | year= 1989 | url = http://earthquake.usgs.gov/learning/topics/measure.php|accessdate = 2006-11-03 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Earthquake fault types===
{{main|Fault (geology)}}
There are three main types of fault that may cause an earthquake: normal, reverse (thrust) and strike-slip. Normal and reverse faulting are examples of dip-slip, where the displacement along the fault is in the direction of [[Strike and dip|dip]] and movement on them involves a vertical component. Normal faults occur mainly in areas where the crust is being [[Extensional tectonics|extended]] such as a [[divergent boundary]]. Reverse faults occur in areas where the crust is being [[Thrust tectonics|shortened]] such as at a convergent boundary. Strike-slip faults are steep structures where the two sides of the fault slip horizontally past each other; transform boundaries are a particular type of strike-slip fault. Many earthquakes are caused by movement on faults that have components of both dip-slip and strike-slip; this is known as oblique slip.

Reverse faults, particularly those along [[Convergent boundary|convergent plate boundaries]] are associated with the most powerful earthquakes, including almost all of those of magnitude 8 or more. Strike-slip faults, particularly continental [[Transform boundary|transforms]] can produce major earthquakes up to about magnitude 8. Earthquakes associated with normal faults are generally less than magnitude 7.

This is so because the energy released in an earthquake, and thus its magnitude, is proportional to the area of the fault that ruptures&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | last1 = Wyss | first1 = M. | year = 1979 | title = Estimating expectable maximum magnitude of earthquakes from fault dimensions | url = | journal = Geology | volume = 7 | issue = 7| pages = 336–340 |bibcode = 1979Geo.....7..336W |doi = 10.1130/0091-7613(1979)7&lt;336:EMEMOE&gt;2.0.CO;2 }}&lt;/ref&gt; and the stress drop.  Therefore, the longer the length and the wider the width of the faulted area, the larger the resulting magnitude.  The topmost, brittle part of the Earth’s crust, and the cool slabs of the tectonic plates that are descending down into the hot mantle, are the only parts of our planet which can store elastic energy and release it in fault ruptures.  Rocks hotter than about 300 degrees Celsius flow in response to stress, they do not rupture in earthquakes.&lt;ref&gt;Sibson R. H. (1982) &quot;Fault Zone Models, Heat Flow, and the Depth Distribution of Earthquakes in the Continental Crust of the United States&quot;, Bulletin of the Seismological Society of America, Vol 72, No. 1, pp. 151–163&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Sibson, R. H. (2002) „Geology of the crustal earthquake source“ International handbook of earthquake and engineering seismology, Volume 1, Part 1, page 455, eds. W H K Lee, H Kanamori, P C Jennings, and C. Kisslinger, Academic Press, ISBN / ASIN: 0124406521&lt;/ref&gt;  The maximum observed lengths of ruptures and mapped faults, which may break in one go are approximately 1000&amp;nbsp;km.  Examples are the earthquakes in [[List of earthquakes in Chile|Chile, 1960]]; [[1957 Andreanof Islands earthquake|Alaska, 1957]]; [[2004 Indian Ocean earthquake and tsunami|Sumatra, 2004]], all in subduction zones.  The longest earthquake ruptures on strike-slip faults, like the [[San Andreas Fault]] (1857, 1906), the [[North Anatolian Fault]] in Turkey (1939) and the [[Denali Fault]] in Alaska (2002), are about half to one third as long as the lengths along subducting plate margins, and those along normal faults are even shorter.

The most important parameter controlling the maximum earthquake magnitude on a fault is however not the maximum available length, but the available width because the latter varies by a factor of 20.  Along converging plate margins, the dip angle of the rupture plane is very shallow, typically about 10 degrees.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.globalcmt.org/CMTsearch.html |title=Global Centroid Moment Tensor Catalog |publisher=Globalcmt.org |date= |accessdate=2011-07-24}}&lt;/ref&gt;  Thus the width of the plane within the top brittle crust of the Earth can become 50 to 100&amp;nbsp;km ([[2011 Tohoku earthquake and tsunami|Tohoku, 2011]]; [[1964 Alaska earthquake|Alaska, 1964]]), making the most powerful earthquakes possible.

Strike-slip faults tend to be oriented near vertically, resulting in an approximate width of 10&amp;nbsp;km within the brittle crust,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://wgcep.org/data-inst_eq_cat |title=Instrumental California Earthquake Catalog |publisher=WGCEP |date= |accessdate=2011-07-24}}&lt;/ref&gt;  thus earthquakes with magnitudes much larger than 8 are not possible.  Maximum magnitudes along many normal faults are even more limited because many of them are located along spreading centers, as in Iceland, where the thickness of the brittle layer is only about 6&amp;nbsp;km.&lt;ref&gt;Hjaltadóttir S., 2010, &quot;Use of relatively located microearthquakes to map fault patterns and estimate the thickness of the brittle crust in Southwest Iceland&quot;&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://en.vedur.is/earthquakes-and-volcanism/reports-and-publications/ |title=Reports and publications &amp;#124; Seismicity &amp;#124; Icelandic Meteorological office |publisher=En.vedur.is |date= |accessdate=2011-07-24}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In addition, there exists a hierarchy of stress level in the three fault types.  Thrust faults are generated by the highest, strike slip by intermediate, and normal faults by the lowest stress levels.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | last1 = Schorlemmer | first1 = D. | last2 = Wiemer | first2 = S. | last3 = Wyss | first3 = M. | year = 2005 | title = Variations in earthquake-size distribution across different stress regimes | url = | journal = Nature | volume = 437 | issue = 7058| pages = 539–542 |bibcode = 2005Natur.437..539S |doi = 10.1038/nature04094 | pmid = 16177788 }}&lt;/ref&gt;  This can easily be understood by considering the direction of the greatest principal stress, the direction of the force that ‘pushes’ the rock mass during the faulting.  In the case of normal faults, the rock mass is pushed down in a vertical direction, thus the pushing force ('''greatest''' principal stress) equals the weight of the rock mass itself.  In the case of thrusting, the rock mass ‘escapes’ in the direction of the least principal stress, namely upward, lifting the rock mass up, thus the overburden equals the '''least''' principal stress.  Strike-slip faulting is intermediate between the other two types described above.  This difference in stress regime in the three faulting environments can contribute to differences in stress drop during faulting, which contributes to differences in the radiated energy, regardless of fault dimensions.

===Earthquakes away from plate boundaries===
{{main|Intraplate earthquake}}
Where plate boundaries occur within [[Continental crust|continental lithosphere]], deformation is spread out over a much larger area than the plate boundary itself. In the case of the [[San Andreas fault]] continental transform, many earthquakes occur away from the plate boundary and are related to strains developed within the broader zone of deformation caused by major irregularities in the fault trace (e.g., the “Big bend” region). The [[Northridge earthquake]] was associated with movement on a blind thrust within such a zone. Another example is the strongly oblique convergent plate boundary between the [[Arabian plate|Arabian]] and [[Eurasian plate]]s where it runs through the northwestern part of the [[Zagros]] mountains. The deformation associated with this plate boundary is partitioned into nearly pure thrust sense movements perpendicular to the boundary over a wide zone to the southwest and nearly pure strike-slip motion along the Main Recent Fault close to the actual plate boundary itself. This is demonstrated by earthquake [[focal mechanism]]s.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal | last1 = Talebian | first1 = M | last2 = Jackson | first2 = J | doi = 10.1111/j.1365-246X.2004.02092.x | title = A reappraisal of earthquake focal mechanisms and active shortening in the Zagros mountains of Iran | journal = Geophysical Journal International | volume = 156 | issue = 3 | pages = 506–526 | year = 2004 | bibcode=2004GeoJI.156..506T}}&lt;/ref&gt;

All tectonic plates have internal stress fields caused by their interactions with neighbouring plates and sedimentary loading or unloading (e.g. deglaciation&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite doi|10.1146/annurev-earth-040809-152414}}&lt;/ref&gt;). These stresses may be sufficient to cause failure along existing fault planes, giving rise to [[intraplate earthquake]]s.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|last=Noson, Qamar, and Thorsen|year=1988|title=Washington State Earthquake Hazards: Washington State Department of Natural Resources|publisher=Washington Division of Geology and Earth Resources Information Circular 85}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Shallow-focus and deep-focus earthquakes===
{{Main|Depth of focus (tectonics)}}

The majority of tectonic earthquakes originate at the ring of fire in depths not exceeding tens of kilometers. Earthquakes occurring at a depth of less than 70&amp;nbsp;km are classified as 'shallow-focus' earthquakes, while those with a focal-depth between 70 and 300&amp;nbsp;km are commonly termed 'mid-focus' or 'intermediate-depth' earthquakes. In [[Subduction|subduction zones]], where older and colder [[oceanic crust]] descends beneath another tectonic plate, [[Deep focus earthquake|deep-focus earthquake]]s may occur at much greater depths (ranging from 300 up to 700&amp;nbsp;kilometers).&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
 | publisher = [[National Earthquake Information Center]]
 | title = M7.5 Northern Peru Earthquake of 26 September 2005
 | year=
 | pages =
 | date = 17 October 2005
 | url = ftp://hazards.cr.usgs.gov/maps/sigeqs/20050926/20050926.pdf
 | format= PDF
 | accessdate = 2008-08-01
}}&lt;/ref&gt; These seismically active areas of subduction are known as [[Wadati-Benioff zone]]s. Deep-focus earthquakes occur at a depth where the subducted [[lithosphere]] should no longer be brittle, due to the high temperature and pressure. A possible mechanism for the generation of deep-focus earthquakes is faulting caused by [[olivine]] undergoing a [[phase transition]] into a [[spinel]] structure.&lt;ref name=&quot;olivine&quot;&gt;{{cite journal
 | last = Greene II | first = H. W.
 | last2 = Burnley | first2 = P. C.
 | title = A new self-organizing mechanism for deep-focus earthquakes
 | journal = Nature
 | volume = 341
 | issue = 6244
 | pages = 733–737
 | date = October 26, 1989
 | doi = 10.1038/341733a0
 | bibcode=1989Natur.341..733G
}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Earthquakes and volcanic activity===
Earthquakes often occur in volcanic regions and are caused there, both by [[tectonic plates|tectonic]] faults and the movement of [[magma]] in [[volcano]]es. Such earthquakes can serve as an early warning of volcanic eruptions, as during the [[Mount St. Helens]] [[1980 eruption of Mount St. Helens|eruption of 1980]].&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|last=Foxworthy and Hill|year=1982|title=Volcanic Eruptions of 1980 at Mount St. Helens, The First 100&amp;nbsp;Days: USGS Professional Paper 1249}}&lt;/ref&gt; Earthquake swarms can serve as markers for the location of the flowing magma throughout the volcanoes. These swarms can be recorded by seismometers and [[tiltmeter]]s (a device that measures ground slope) and used as sensors to predict imminent or upcoming eruptions.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://pubs.usgs.gov/gip/earthq1/volcano.html|title=Volcanoes and Earthquakes|publisher=[[United States Geological Survey]]|date=January 7, 1998|author=Watson, John|coauthors=Watson, Kathie|accessdate=May 9, 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Rupture dynamics===
A tectonic earthquake begins by an initial rupture at a point on the fault surface, a process known as nucleation. The scale of the nucleation zone is uncertain, with some evidence, such as the rupture dimensions of the smallest earthquakes, suggesting that it is smaller than 100 m while other evidence, such as a slow component revealed by low-frequency spectra of some earthquakes, suggest that it is larger. The possibility that the nucleation involves some sort of preparation process is supported by the observation that about 40% of earthquakes are preceded by foreshocks. Once the rupture has initiated it begins to propagate along the fault surface. The mechanics of this process are poorly understood, partly because it is difficult to recreate the high sliding velocities in a laboratory. Also the effects of strong ground motion make it very difficult to record information close to a nucleation zone.&lt;ref name=&quot;NRS&quot;/&gt;

Rupture propagation is generally modelled using a [[fracture mechanics]] approach, likening the rupture to a propagating mixed mode shear crack. The rupture velocity is a function of the fracture energy in the volume around the crack tip, increasing with decreasing fracture energy. The velocity of rupture propagation is orders of magnitude faster than the displacement velocity across the fault. Earthquake ruptures typically propagate at velocities that are in the range 70–90 % of the S-wave velocity and this is independent of earthquake size. A small subset of earthquake ruptures appear to have propagated at speeds greater than the S-wave velocity. These [[supershear earthquake]]s have all been observed during large strike-slip events. The unusually wide zone of coseismic damage caused by the [[2001 Kunlun earthquake]] has been attributed to the effects of the [[sonic boom]] developed in such earthquakes. Some earthquake ruptures travel at unusually low velocities and are referred to as [[slow earthquake]]s. A particularly dangerous form of slow earthquake is the [[tsunami earthquake]], observed where the relatively low felt intensities, caused by the slow propagation speed of some great earthquakes, fail to alert the population of the neighbouring coast, as in the [[1896 Meiji-Sanriku earthquake]].&lt;ref name=&quot;NRS&quot;&gt;{{cite book|last=National Research Council (U.S.). Committee on the Science of Earthquakes|first=|title=Living on an Active Earth: Perspectives on Earthquake Science|url=http://www.nap.edu/openbook.php?record_id=10493&amp;page=282|accessdate=8 July 2010|year=2003|publisher=National Academies Press|location=Washington D.C.|isbn=9780309065627|page=418|chapter=5. Earthquake Physics and Fault-System Science }}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Tidal forces===
{{See also|Earthquake prediction#Earth tides as triggers}}
Research work has shown a robust correlation between small tidally induced forces and non-volcanic tremor activity.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal
 | last1 = Thomas
 | first1 = Amanda M.
 | last2 = Nadeau
 | first2 = Robert M.
 | last3 = Bürgmann
 | first3 = Roland
 | date = December 24, 2009
 | title = Tremor-tide correlations and near-lithostatic pore pressure on the deep San Andreas fault
 | journal = Nature
 | volume = 462
 | issue =7276
 | pages = 1048–51
 | pmid =20033046
 | doi = 10.1038/nature08654
 | bibcode=2009Natur.462.1048T
}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.spiegel.de/wissenschaft/natur/0,1518,669370,00.html &quot;Gezeitenkräfte: Sonne und Mond lassen Kalifornien erzittern&quot;] SPIEGEL online, 29.12.2009&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal
 | last = Tamrazyan
 | first = Gurgen P.
 | title = Tide-forming forces and earthquakes
 | journal = [[Icarus (journal)|Icarus]]
 | volume = 7
 | issue = 1–3
 | pages = 59–65
 | year = 1967
 | doi = 10.1016/0019-1035(67)90047-4
| bibcode=1967Icar....7...59T
}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal
 | last = Tamrazyan
 | first = Gurgen P.
 | title = Principal regularities in the distribution of major earthquakes relative to solar and lunar tides and other cosmic forces
 | journal = [[Icarus (journal)|Icarus]]
 | volume = 9
 | issue = 1–3
 | pages = 574–92
 | year = 1968
 | doi = 10.1016/0019-1035(68)90050-X
| bibcode=1968Icar....9..574T
}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Earthquake clusters===
Most earthquakes form part of a sequence, related to each other in terms of location and time.&lt;ref name=WAAFEC&gt;{{cite web|url=http://earthquake.usgs.gov/eqcenter/step/explain.php|title=What are Aftershocks, Foreshocks, and Earthquake Clusters?}}&lt;/ref&gt; Most earthquake clusters consist of small tremors that cause little to no damage, but there is a theory that earthquakes can recur in a regular pattern.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://earthquake.usgs.gov/research/parkfield/repeat.php|title=Repeating Earthquakes|publisher=[[United States Geological Survey]]|date=January 29, 2009|accessdate=May 11, 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt;

====Aftershocks====
{{Main|Aftershock}}
An aftershock is an earthquake that occurs after a previous earthquake, the mainshock. An aftershock is in the same region of the main shock but always of a smaller magnitude. If an aftershock is larger than the main shock, the aftershock is redesignated as the main shock and the original main shock is redesignated as a [[foreshock]]. Aftershocks are formed as the crust around the displaced [[fault plane]] adjusts to the effects of the main shock.&lt;ref name=WAAFEC/&gt;

====Earthquake swarms====
{{Main|Earthquake swarm}}
Earthquake swarms are sequences of earthquakes striking in a specific area within a short period of time. They are different from earthquakes followed by a series of [[aftershock]]s by the fact that no single earthquake in the sequence is obviously the main shock, therefore none have notable higher magnitudes than the other. An example of an earthquake swarm is the 2004 activity at [[Yellowstone National Park]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://volcanoes.usgs.gov/yvo/2004/Apr04Swarm.html|title=Earthquake Swarms at Yellowstone|publisher=[[United States Geological Survey]]|accessdate=2008-09-15}}&lt;/ref&gt;

====Earthquake storms====
{{Main|Earthquake storm}}
Sometimes a series of earthquakes occur in a sort of [[earthquake storm]], where the earthquakes strike a fault in clusters, each triggered by the shaking or stress redistribution of the previous earthquakes. Similar to [[aftershock]]s but on adjacent segments of fault, these storms occur over the course of years, and with some of the later earthquakes as damaging as the early ones. Such a pattern was observed in the sequence of about a dozen earthquakes that struck the [[North Anatolian Fault]] in Turkey in the 20th century and has been inferred for older anomalous clusters of large earthquakes in the Middle East.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | title = Poseidon's Horses: Plate Tectonics and Earthquake Storms in the Late Bronze Age Aegean and Eastern Mediterranean | journal = Journal of Archaeological Science | year = 2000 | author = Amos Nur | issn = 0305-4403 | volume = 27 | issue = 1 | pages = 43–63 | url = http://water.stanford.edu/nur/EndBronzeage.pdf | doi = 10.1006/jasc.1999.0431 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url = http://www.bbc.co.uk/science/horizon/2003/earthquakestorms.shtml | title = Earthquake Storms | work = [[Horizon (BBC TV series)|Horizon]] | date = 1 April 2003 | accessdate = 2007-05-02 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Size and frequency of occurrence==
It is estimated that around 500,000 earthquakes occur each year, detectable with current instrumentation. About 100,000 of these can be felt.&lt;ref name=&quot;usgsfacts&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://earthquake.usgs.gov/learn/facts.php|title=Earthquake Facts|publisher=[[United States Geological Survey]]|accessdate=2010-04-25}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;wp100414&quot;&gt;{{Cite news | first=Margaret Webb | last=Pressler | title=More earthquakes than usual? Not really. | url=| work=KidsPost | publisher= Washington Post| location=Washington Post | pages= C10 | date=14 April 2010 | id= | accessdate=}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;!----url does not contain box statistics that print edition does and is included for info only----&gt; Minor earthquakes occur nearly constantly around the world in places like [[California]] and [[Alaska]] in the U.S., as well as in [[Guatemala]], [[Chile]], [[Peru]], [[Indonesia]], [[Iran]], [[Pakistan]], the [[Azores]] in [[Portugal]], [[Turkey]], [[New Zealand]], [[Greece]], [[Italy]], and [[Japan]], but earthquakes can occur almost anywhere, including [[New York City]], [[London]], and [[Australia]].&lt;ref&gt;
{{cite web
 | url=http://earthquake.usgs.gov/
 | title=Earthquake Hazards Program
 | publisher=[[United States Geological Survey]]
 | accessdate=2006-08-14
}}&lt;/ref&gt; Larger earthquakes occur less frequently, the relationship being [[Gutenberg-Richter law|exponential]]; for example, roughly ten times as many earthquakes larger than magnitude 4 occur in a particular time period than earthquakes larger than magnitude 5. In the (low seismicity) United Kingdom, for example, it has been calculated that the average recurrences are:
an earthquake of 3.7–4.6 every year, an earthquake of 4.7–5.5 every 10&amp;nbsp;years, and an earthquake of 5.6 or larger every 100&amp;nbsp;years.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.quakes.bgs.ac.uk/hazard/Hazard_UK.htm |title=Seismicity and earthquake hazard in the UK |publisher=Quakes.bgs.ac.uk |date= |accessdate=2010-08-23}}&lt;/ref&gt; This is an example of the [[Gutenberg-Richter law]].
[[Image:Messina earthquake.jpg|thumb|The [[1908 Messina earthquake|Messina earthquake]] and tsunami took as many as 200,000 lives on December 28, 1908 in [[Sicily]] and [[Calabria]].&lt;ref&gt;&quot;[http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/low/europe/2381585.stm Italy's earthquake history].&quot; BBC News. October 31, 2002.&lt;/ref&gt;]]
The number of seismic stations has increased from about 350 in 1931 to many thousands today. As a result, many more earthquakes are reported than in the past, but this is because of the vast improvement in instrumentation, rather than an increase in the number of earthquakes. The [[United States Geological Survey]] estimates that, since 1900, there have been an average of 18 major earthquakes (magnitude 7.0–7.9) and one great earthquake (magnitude 8.0 or greater) per year, and that this average has been relatively stable.&lt;ref&gt;
{{cite web
 | title=Common Myths about Earthquakes
 | url=http://earthquake.usgs.gov/learning/faq.php?categoryID=6&amp;faqID=110
 | publisher=[[United States Geological Survey]]
 | accessdate=2006-08-14
}}&lt;/ref&gt; In recent years, the number of major earthquakes per year has decreased, though this is probably a statistical fluctuation rather than a systematic trend. More detailed statistics on the size and frequency of earthquakes is available from the [[United States Geological Survey]] (USGS).&lt;ref&gt;
{{cite web
 | title=Earthquake Facts and Statistics: Are earthquakes increasing?
 | url=http://neic.usgs.gov/neis/eqlists/eqstats.html
 | publisher=[[United States Geological Survey]]
 | accessdate=2006-08-14
}}&lt;/ref&gt;
Alternatively, some scientists suggest that the recent increase in major earthquakes could be explained by a cyclical pattern of periods of intense tectonic activity, interspersed with longer periods of low-intensity. However, accurate recordings of earthquakes only began in the early 1900s, so it is too early to categorically state that this is the case.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.australiangeographic.com.au/journal/the-10-biggest-earthquakes-in-recorded-history.htm/ The 10 biggest earthquakes in history], Australian Geographic, March 14, 2011.&lt;/ref&gt;

Most of the world's earthquakes (90%, and 81% of the largest) take place in the 40,000&amp;nbsp;km long, horseshoe-shaped zone called the circum-Pacific seismic belt, known as the [[Pacific Ring of Fire]], which for the most part bounds the [[Pacific Plate]].&lt;ref&gt;
{{cite web
 | title=Historic Earthquakes and Earthquake Statistics: Where do earthquakes occur?
 | url=http://earthquake.usgs.gov/learning/faq.php?categoryID=11&amp;faqID=95
 | publisher=[[United States Geological Survey]]
 | accessdate=2006-08-14
}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;
{{cite web
 | url=http://earthquake.usgs.gov/learning/glossary.php?termID=150
 | publisher=[[United States Geological Survey]]
 | title=Visual Glossary — Ring of Fire
 | accessdate=2006-08-14
}}&lt;/ref&gt; Massive earthquakes tend to occur along other plate boundaries, too, such as along the [[Himalayan Mountains]].&lt;ref&gt;Jackson, James, &quot;[http://rsta.royalsocietypublishing.org/content/364/1845/1911.full Fatal attraction: living with earthquakes, the growth of villages into megacities, and earthquake vulnerability in the modern world],&quot; ''[[Philosophical Transactions of the Royal Society]]'', doi: 10.1098/rsta.2006.1805 Phil. Trans. R. Soc. A 15 August 2006 vol. 364 no. 1845 1911–1925.&lt;/ref&gt;

With the rapid growth of [[Megacity|mega-cities]] such as [[Mexico City]], [[Tokyo]] and [[Tehran]], in areas of high [[seismic risk]], some seismologists are warning that a single quake may claim the lives of up to 3&amp;nbsp;million people.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;[http://cires.colorado.edu/~bilham/UrbanEarthquakesGlobal.html Global urban seismic risk].&quot; Cooperative Institute for Research in Environmental Science.&lt;/ref&gt;

==Induced seismicity==
{{main|Induced seismicity}}
While most earthquakes are caused by movement of the Earth's [[tectonic plate]]s, human activity can also produce earthquakes. Four main activities contribute to this phenomenon: storing large amounts of water behind a [[dam]] (and possibly building an extremely heavy [[building]]), drilling and injecting liquid into [[water well|well]]s, and by [[coal mining]] and [[oil well|oil drilling]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|author=Madrigal, Alexis|title=Top 5 Ways to Cause a Man-Made Earthquake|url=http://blog.wired.com/wiredscience/2008/06/top-5-ways-that.html|date=4 June 2008|work=Wired News|publisher=CondéNet|accessdate=2008-06-05}}&lt;/ref&gt; Perhaps the best known example is the [[2008 Sichuan earthquake]] in China's [[Sichuan Province]] in May; this tremor resulted in 69,227 fatalities and is the [[List of natural disasters by death toll#Earthquakes|19th deadliest earthquake of all time]]. The [[Zipingpu Dam]] is believed to have fluctuated the pressure of the fault {{convert|1650|ft|m|0|}} away; this pressure probably increased the power of the earthquake and accelerated the rate of movement for the fault.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://news.nationalgeographic.com/news/2009/02/photogalleries/humans-cause-earthquakes/photo2.html|title=How Humans Can Trigger Earthquakes|publisher=[[National Geographic]]|date=February 10, 2009|accessdate=April 24, 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt; The greatest earthquake in Australia's history is also claimed to be induced by humanity, through coal mining. [[Newcastle, Australia|The city of Newcastle]] was built over a large sector of coal mining areas. The earthquake has been reported to be spawned from a fault that reactivated due to the millions of tonnes of rock removed in the mining process.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.abc.net.au/am/content/2007/s1823833.htm |title=Researcher claims mining triggered 1989 Newcastle earthquake |author=Brendan Trembath |publisher=[[Australian Broadcasting Corporation]]|date=January 9, 2007 |accessdate=April 24, 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Measuring and locating earthquakes==
{{Main|Seismology}}
Earthquakes can be recorded by seismometers up to great distances, because [[seismic waves]] travel through the whole [[Earth's interior]]. The absolute magnitude of a quake is conventionally reported by numbers on the [[Moment magnitude scale]] (formerly Richter scale, magnitude 7 causing serious damage over large areas), whereas the felt magnitude is reported using the modified [[Mercalli intensity scale]] (intensity II–XII).

Every tremor produces different types of seismic waves, which travel through rock with different velocities:
* Longitudinal [[P-waves]] (shock- or pressure waves)
* Transverse [[S-waves]] (both body waves)
* [[Surface wave]]s — ([[Rayleigh wave|Rayleigh]] and [[Love wave|Love]] waves)
[[Propagation velocity]] of the seismic waves ranges from approx. 3&amp;nbsp;km/s up to 13&amp;nbsp;km/s, depending on the [[density]] and [[Elasticity (physics)|elasticity]] of the medium. In the Earth's interior the shock- or P waves travel much faster than the S waves (approx. relation 1.7 : 1). The differences in [[travel time]] from the [[epicentre]] to the observatory are a measure of the distance and can be used to image both sources of quakes and structures within the Earth. Also the depth of the [[hypocenter]] can be computed roughly.

In solid rock P-waves travel at about 6 to 7&amp;nbsp;km per second; the velocity increases within the deep mantle to ~13&amp;nbsp;km/s. The velocity of S-waves ranges from 2–3&amp;nbsp;km/s in light sediments and 4–5&amp;nbsp;km/s in the Earth's crust up to 7&amp;nbsp;km/s in the deep mantle. As a consequence, the first waves of a distant earth quake arrive at an observatory via the Earth's mantle.

'''Rule of thumb''': On the average, the kilometer distance to the earthquake is the number of seconds between the P and S wave '''times 8'''.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://hypertextbook.com/facts/2001/PamelaSpiegel.shtml |title=Speed of Sound through the Earth |publisher=Hypertextbook.com |date= |accessdate=2010-08-23}}&lt;/ref&gt; Slight deviations are caused by inhomogeneities of subsurface structure. By such analyses of seismograms the Earth's core was located in 1913 by [[Beno Gutenberg]].

Earthquakes are not only categorized by their magnitude but also by the place where they occur. The world is divided into 754 [[Flinn-Engdahl regions]] (F-E regions), which are based on political and geographical boundaries as well as seismic activity. More active zones are divided into smaller F-E regions whereas less active zones belong to larger F-E regions.

==Effects of earthquakes==
[[Image:1755 Lisbon earthquake.jpg|thumb|1755 copper engraving depicting [[Lisbon]] in ruins and in flames after the [[1755 Lisbon earthquake]], which killed an estimated 60,000 people. A [[tsunami]] overwhelms the ships in the harbor.]]

The effects of earthquakes include, but are not limited to, the following:

===Shaking and ground rupture===
Shaking and ground rupture are the main effects created by earthquakes, principally resulting in more or less severe damage to buildings and other rigid structures. The severity of the local effects depends on the complex combination of the earthquake [[Richter magnitude scale|magnitude]], the distance from the [[epicenter]], and the local geological and geomorphological conditions, which may amplify or reduce [[wave propagation]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.abag.ca.gov/bayarea/eqmaps/doc/contents.html |title=On Shaky Ground, Association of Bay Area Governments, San Francisco, reports 1995,1998 (updated 2003) |publisher=Abag.ca.gov |date= |accessdate=2010-08-23}}&lt;/ref&gt; The ground-shaking is measured by [[ground acceleration]].

Specific local geological, geomorphological, and geostructural features can induce high levels of shaking on the ground surface even from low-intensity earthquakes. This effect is called site or local amplification. It is principally due to the transfer of the [[seismic]] motion from hard deep soils to soft superficial soils and to effects of seismic energy focalization owing to typical geometrical setting of the deposits.

Ground rupture is a visible breaking and displacement of the Earth's surface along the trace of the fault, which may be of the order of several metres in the case of major earthquakes. Ground rupture is a major risk for large engineering structures such as [[dams]], bridges and [[nuclear power stations]] and requires careful mapping of existing faults to identify any likely to break the ground surface within the life of the structure.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.consrv.ca.gov/cgs/information/publications/cgs_notes/note_49/Documents/note_49.pdf|title=Guidelines for evaluating the hazard of surface fault rupture, California Geological Survey|publisher=California Department of Conservation|date=2002}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Landslides and avalanches===
{{main|Landslide}}
Earthquakes, along with severe storms, volcanic activity, coastal wave attack, and wildfires, can produce slope instability leading to landslides, a major geological hazard. Landslide danger may persist while emergency personnel are attempting rescue.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.usgs.gov/hazards/landslides/|title=Natural Hazards — Landslides|publisher=[[United States Geological Survey]]|accessdate=2008-09-15}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Fires===
[[Image:Sfearthquake3b.jpg|thumb|Fires of the [[1906 San Francisco earthquake]]]]
Earthquakes can cause [[fire]]s by damaging [[electric power|electrical power]] or gas lines. In the event of water mains rupturing and a loss of pressure, it may also become difficult to stop the spread of a fire once it has started. For example, more deaths in the [[1906 San Francisco earthquake]] were caused by fire than by the earthquake itself.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://earthquake.usgs.gov/regional/nca/1906/18april/index.php|title=The Great 1906 San Francisco earthquake of 1906|publisher=[[United States Geological Survey]]|accessdate=2008-09-15}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Soil liquefaction===
{{Main|Soil liquefaction}}
Soil liquefaction occurs when, because of the shaking, water-saturated [[granular]] material (such as sand) temporarily loses its strength and transforms from a [[solid]] to a [[liquid]]. Soil liquefaction may cause rigid structures, like buildings and bridges, to tilt or sink into the liquefied deposits. This can be a devastating effect of earthquakes. For example, in the [[1964 Alaska earthquake]], soil liquefaction caused many buildings to sink into the ground, eventually collapsing upon themselves.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://earthquake.usgs.gov/regional/states/events/1964_03_28.php|title=Historic Earthquakes — 1946 Anchorage Earthquake|publisher=[[United States Geological Survey]]|accessdate=2008-09-15}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Tsunami===
{{main|Tsunami}}
[[Image:2004-tsunami.jpg|thumb|left|The tsunami of the [[2004 Indian Ocean earthquake]]]]
Tsunamis are long-wavelength, long-period sea waves produced by the sudden or abrupt movement of large volumes of water. In the open ocean the distance between wave crests can surpass {{convert|100|km|mi|sp=us}}, and the wave periods can vary from five minutes to one hour. Such tsunamis travel 600-800&amp;nbsp;kilometers per hour (373–497 miles per hour), depending on water depth. Large waves produced by an earthquake or a submarine landslide can overrun nearby coastal areas in a matter of minutes. Tsunamis can also travel thousands of kilometers across open ocean and wreak destruction on far shores hours after the earthquake that generated them.&lt;ref name=Noson&gt;{{Cite book|last=Noson, Qamar, and Thorsen|publisher=Washington State Earthquake Hazards|year=1988|title=Washington Division of Geology and Earth Resources Information Circular 85}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Ordinarily, subduction earthquakes under magnitude 7.5 on the Richter scale do not cause tsunamis, although some instances of this have been recorded. Most destructive tsunamis are caused by earthquakes of magnitude 7.5 or more.&lt;ref name=Noson/&gt;

===Floods===
{{main|Flood}}
A flood is an overflow of any amount of water that reaches land.&lt;ref&gt;[[MSN Encarta]] Dictionary. [http://encarta.msn.com/encnet/features/dictionary/DictionaryResults.aspx?refid=1861612277 Flood]. Retrieved on 2006-12-28. [http://www.webcitation.org/5kwbTYD2X Archived] 2009-10-31.&lt;/ref&gt; Floods occur usually when the volume of water within a body of water, such as a river or lake, exceeds the total capacity of the formation, and as a result some of the water flows or sits outside of the normal perimeter of the body. However, floods may be secondary effects of earthquakes, if dams are damaged. Earthquakes may cause landslips to dam rivers, which collapse and cause floods.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.quakes.bgs.ac.uk/earthquakes/historical/historical_listing.htm|title=Notes on Historical Earthquakes|publisher=[[British Geological Survey]]|accessdate=2008-09-15}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The terrain below the [[Sarez Lake]] in [[Tajikistan]] is in danger of catastrophic flood if the [[landslide dam]] formed by the earthquake, known as the [[Usoi Dam]], were to fail during a future earthquake. Impact projections suggest the flood could affect roughly 5&amp;nbsp;million people.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/asia-pacific/3120693.stm|title=Fresh alert over Tajik flood threat|date=2003-08-03|work=[[BBC News]]|accessdate=2008-09-15}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Human impacts===
[[File:37 - Tremblement de terre - Août 2007.JPG|right|thumb|Damaged infrastructure, one week after the [[2007 Peru earthquake]]]]
An earthquake may cause injury and loss of life, road and bridge damage, general [[property damage]] (which may or may not be covered by [[earthquake insurance]]), and collapse or destabilization (potentially leading to future collapse) of buildings. The aftermath may bring [[disease]], lack of basic necessities, and higher insurance premiums.

==Major earthquakes==
{{Main|List of earthquakes}}

One of the most devastating earthquakes in recorded history occurred on 23 January 1556 in the [[Shaanxi]] province, China, killing more than 830,000 people (see [[1556 Shaanxi earthquake]]).&lt;ref&gt;&quot;[http://earthquake.usgs.gov/earthquakes/world/most_destructive.php Earthquakes with 50,000 or More Deaths]&quot;. U.S. Geological Survey&lt;/ref&gt; Most of the population in the area at the time lived in [[yaodong]]s, artificial caves in loess cliffs, many of which collapsed during the catastrophe with great loss of life. The [[1976 Tangshan earthquake]], with death toll estimated to be between 240,000 to 655,000, is believed to be the largest earthquake of the 20th century by death toll.&lt;ref&gt;Spignesi, Stephen J. [2005] (2005). Catastrophe!: The 100 Greatest Disasters of All Time. ISBN 0806525584&lt;/ref&gt;

The largest earthquake that has been measured on a seismograph reached 9.5 magnitude, occurring on 22 May 1960.&lt;ref name=&quot;usgsfacts&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;wp100414&quot;/&gt;&lt;!----url does not contain box statistics that print edition does and is included for info only----&gt;&lt;!---this figure is also contained in List of earthquakes but cannot retrieve material to copy directly here--&gt; Its epicenter was near Cañete, Chile. The energy released was approximately twice that of the next most powerful earthquake, the [[Good Friday Earthquake]], which was centered in [[Prince William Sound]], Alaska.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.gps.caltech.edu/uploads/File/People/kanamori/HKjgr77.pdf |title=The Energy Release in Great Earthquakes |author=Kanamori Hiroo |publisher=Journal of Geophysical Research |accessdate=2010-10-10}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://earthquake.usgs.gov/learn/topics/how_much_bigger.php |title=How Much Bigger? |author=USGS |publisher=[[United States Geological Survey]] |accessdate=2010-10-10}}&lt;/ref&gt; The ten largest recorded earthquakes have all been [[megathrust earthquake]]s; however, of these ten, only the [[2004 Indian Ocean earthquake]] is simultaneously one of the deadliest earthquakes in history.

Earthquakes that caused the greatest loss of life, while powerful, were deadly because of their proximity to either heavily populated areas or the ocean, where earthquakes often create [[tsunamis]] that can devastate communities thousands of kilometers away. Regions most at risk for great loss of life include those where earthquakes are relatively rare but powerful, and poor regions with lax, unenforced, or nonexistent seismic building codes.

==Prediction==
{{main|Earthquake prediction}}
Many different methods have been developed for predicting the time and place in which earthquakes will occur. Despite considerable research efforts by [[seismologist]]s, scientifically reproducible predictions cannot yet be made to a specific day or month.&lt;ref name=&quot;ludwin&quot;&gt;[http://www.geophys.washington.edu/SEIS/PNSN/INFO_GENERAL/eq_prediction.html Earthquake Prediction]. Ruth Ludwin, U.S. Geological Survey.&lt;/ref&gt; However, for well-understood faults the probability that a segment may rupture during the next few decades can be estimated.&lt;ref&gt;Working Group on California Earthquake Probabilities in the San Francisco Bay Region, 2003 to 2032, 2003, http://earthquake.usgs.gov/regional/nca/wg02/index.php.&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Earthquake warning system]]s have been developed that can provide regional notification of an earthquake in progress, but before the ground surface has begun to move, potentially allowing people within the system's range to seek shelter before the earthquake's impact is felt.

==Preparedness==
The objective of [[earthquake engineering]] is to foresee the impact of earthquakes on buildings and other structures and to design such structures to minimize the risk of damage. Existing structures can be modified by [[seismic retrofitting]] to improve their resistance to earthquakes. [[Earthquake insurance]] can provide building owners with financial protection against losses resulting from earthquakes.

[[Emergency management]] strategies can be employed by a government or organization to mitigate risks and prepare for consequences.

==Historical views==
[[Image:Lycosthène.jpg|thumb|An image from a 1557 book]]
From the lifetime of the Greek philosopher [[Anaxagoras]] in the 5th century BCE to the 14th century CE, earthquakes were usually attributed to &quot;air (vapors) in the cavities of the Earth.&quot;&lt;ref name=World&gt;{{cite encyclopedia| title =Earthquakes | encyclopedia =Encyclopedia of World Environmental History | volume =1 | pages =358–364| publisher =Encyclopedia of World Environmental History | year =2003 }}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Thales]] of Miletus, who lived from 625–547 (BCE) was the only documented person who believed that earthquakes were caused by tension between the earth and water.&lt;ref name=World/&gt; Other theories existed, including the Greek philosopher Anaxamines' (585–526 BCE) beliefs that short incline episodes of dryness and wetness caused seismic activity. The Greek philosopher Democritus (460–371 BCE) blamed water in general for earthquakes.&lt;ref name=World/&gt; [[Pliny the Elder]] called earthquakes &quot;underground thunderstorms.&quot;&lt;ref name=World/&gt;

==Earthquakes in culture==
===Mythology and religion===
In [[Norse mythology]], earthquakes were explained as the violent struggling of the god [[Loki]]. When Loki, [[Aesir|god]] of mischief and strife, murdered [[Baldr]], god of beauty and light, he was punished by being bound in a cave with a poisonous serpent placed above his head dripping venom. Loki's wife [[Sigyn]] stood by him with a bowl to catch the poison, but whenever she had to empty the bowl the poison dripped on Loki's face, forcing him to jerk his head away and thrash against his bonds, which caused the earth to tremble.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=[[Snorri Sturluson|Sturluson, Snorri]]|title=[[Prose Edda]]|year=1220|isbn=1156786215}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In [[Greek mythology]], [[Poseidon]] was the cause and god of earthquakes. When he was in a bad mood, he struck the ground with a [[trident]], causing earthquakes and other calamities. He also used earthquakes to punish and inflict fear upon people as revenge.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.pantheon.org/articles/p/poseidon.html|title=Poseidon|last=Sellers|first=Paige|date=1997-03-03|work=Encyclopedia Mythica|accessdate=2008-09-02}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In [[Japanese mythology]], '''[[Namazu (Japanese mythology)|Namazu]]''' (鯰) is a giant [[catfish]] who causes earthquakes. Namazu lives in the mud beneath the earth, and is guarded by the god [[Kashima (god)|Kashima]] who restrains the fish with a stone. When Kashima lets his guard fall, Namazu thrashes about, causing violent earthquakes.

===Popular culture===
In modern [[popular culture]], the portrayal of earthquakes is shaped by the memory of great cities laid waste, such as [[Great Hanshin earthquake|Kobe in 1995]] or [[1906 San Francisco earthquake|San Francisco in 1906]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Van Riper 60&quot;&gt;{{cite book|last=Van Riper|first=A. Bowdoin|title=Science in popular culture: a reference guide|publisher=[[Greenwood Press]]|location=Westport|year=2002|page=60|isbn=0313318220}}&lt;/ref&gt; Fictional earthquakes tend to strike suddenly and without warning.&lt;ref name=&quot;Van Riper 60&quot; /&gt; For this reason, stories about earthquakes generally begin with the disaster and focus on its immediate aftermath, as in ''Short Walk to Daylight'' (1972), ''[[A Wrinkle in the Skin|The Ragged Edge]]'' (1968) or ''[[Aftershock: Earthquake in New York]]'' (1998).&lt;ref name=&quot;Van Riper 60&quot; /&gt; A notable example is Heinrich von Kleist's classic novella, ''[[The Earthquake in Chile]]'', which describes the destruction of Santiago in 1647. [[Haruki Murakami]]'s short fiction collection [[After the Quake|after the quake]] depicts the consequences of the Kobe earthquake of 1995.

The most popular single earthquake in fiction is the hypothetical &quot;Big One&quot; expected of [[California]]'s [[San Andreas Fault]] someday, as depicted in the novels ''[[Richter 10]]'' (1996) and ''[[Goodbye California (novel)|Goodbye California]]'' (1977) among other works.&lt;ref name=&quot;Van Riper 60&quot; /&gt; Jacob M. Appel's widely anthologized short story, ''A Comparative Seismology'', features a con artist who convinces an elderly woman that an apocalyptic earthquake is imminent.&lt;ref&gt;JM Appel. A Comparative Seismology. Weber Studies (first publication), Volume 18, Number 2.&lt;/ref&gt; In ''Pleasure Boating in Lituya Bay'', one of the stories in [[Jim Shepard]]'s ''Like You'd Understand, Anyway'', the &quot;Big One&quot; leads to an even more devastating tsunami.

In the film ''[[2012 (film)|2012]]'' (2009), solar flares (geologically implausibly) affecting the Earth's core caused massive destabilization of the Earth's crust layers. This created destruction planet-wide with earthquakes and tsunamis, foreseen by the [[Maya civilization|Mayan]] culture and myth surrounding the last year noted in the ''[[Mesoamerican calendar]]'' — ''2012''.

Contemporary depictions of earthquakes in film are variable in the manner in which they reflect human psychological reactions to the actual trauma that can be caused to directly afflicted families and their loved ones.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | last1 = Goenjian | first1 = Najarian | last2 = Pynoos | first2 = Steinberg | last3 = Manoukian | first3 = Tavosian | last4 = Fairbanks | first4 =  AM| year = 1994 | title = Posttraumatic stress disorder in elderly and younger adults after the 1988 earthquake in Armenia | url = | journal = Am J Psychiatry | volume = 151 | issue = 6| pages = 895–901 | pmid = 8185000 | last5 = Manoukian | first5 = G | last6 = Tavosian | first6 = A | last7 = Fairbanks | first7 = LA }}&lt;/ref&gt; Disaster mental health response research emphasizes the need to be aware of the different roles of loss of family and key community members, loss of home and familiar surroundings, loss of essential supplies and services to maintain survival.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | last1 = Wang | first1 = Gao | last2 = Shinfuku | first2 = Zhang | last3 = Zhao | first3 = Shen | year = 2000 | title = Longitudinal Study of Earthquake-Related PTSD in a Randomly Selected Community Sample in North China | url = | journal = Am J Psychiatry | volume = 157 | issue = 8| pages = 1260–1266 | doi = 10.1176/appi.ajp.157.8.1260 | pmid = 10910788 | last4 = Zhang | first4 = H | last5 = Zhao | first5 = C | last6 = Shen | first6 = Y }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | last1 = Goenjian | first1 = Steinberg | last2 = Najarian | first2 = Fairbanks | last3 = Tashjian | first3 = Pynoos | year = 2000 | title = Prospective Study of Posttraumatic Stress, Anxiety, and Depressive Reactions After Earthquake and Political Violence | url = | journal = Am J Psychiatry | volume = 157 | issue = 6| pages = 911–895 | doi = 10.1176/appi.ajp.157.6.911 }}&lt;/ref&gt; Particularly for children, the clear availability of caregiving adults who are able to protect, nourish, and clothe them in the aftermath of the earthquake, and to help them make sense of what has befallen them has been shown even more important to their emotional and physical health than the simple giving of provisions.&lt;ref&gt;[[Susan Coates|Coates SW]], [[Daniel Schechter|Schechter D]] (2004). Preschoolers’ traumatic stress post-9/11: relational and developmental perspectives. Disaster Psychiatry Issue. Psychiatric Clinics of North America, 27(3), 473–489.&lt;/ref&gt; As was observed after other disasters involving destruction and loss of life and their media depictions, such as those of the 2001 World Trade Center Attacks or Hurricane Katrina—and has been recently observed in the [[2010 Haiti earthquake]], it is also important not to pathologize the reactions to loss and displacement or disruption of governmental administration and services, but rather to validate these reactions, to support constructive problem-solving and reflection as to how one might improve the conditions of those affected.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | last1 = Schechter | first1 = DS | authorlink = Daniel Schechter | authorlink2 = Susan Coates | last2 = Coates | first2 = SW | last3 = First | first3 = E | year = 2002 | title = Observations of acute reactions of young children and their families to the World Trade Center attacks | url = | journal = Journal of ZERO-TO-THREE: National Center for Infants, Toddlers, and Families | volume = 22 | issue = 3| pages = 9–13 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

==See also==
* [[Seismite]]
* [[Seismotectonics]]
* [[Submarine earthquake]]
* [[Triangle of Life]]
* [[Marine terrace]]

==References==
{{Reflist|colwidth=30em}}

==General references==
* {{cite book |title=Natural Hazards and Disasters |author=Donald Hyndman, David Hyndman |isbn=0495316679 |publisher=Brooks/Cole: Cengage Learning |year=2009 |edition=2nd |url=http://books.google.com/?id=8jg5oRWHXmcC&amp;pg=PT54&amp;q= |chapter=Chapter 3: Earthquakes and their causes}}

==External links==
{{commons}}
* [http://earthquake.usgs.gov/ U.S. Geological Survey Earthquake Hazards Program]
* [http://www.iris.edu/ Incorporated Research Institutions for Seismology]
** [http://www.iris.edu/dms/seismon.htm IRIS Seismic Monitor - Recent Earthquakes]
* [http://www.emsc-csem.org/#2 European-Mediterranean Seismological Centre]
* [http://www.dmoz.org/Science/Earth_Sciences/Geophysics/Earthquakes/ Open Directory - Earthquakes]

{{Geotechnical engineering|state=collapsed}}
{{Natural disasters}}
{{Disasters}} 

[[Category:Earthquakes| ]]
[[Category:Earthquake engineering]]
[[Category:Geological hazards]]
[[Category:Seismology]]

{{Link GA|sv}}
{{Link FA|bs}}
{{Link FA|sk}}
{{Link FA|tt}}

[[af:Aardbewing]]
[[als:Erdbeben]]
[[am:የመሬት መንቀጥቀጥ]]
[[ang:Eorþbeofung]]
[[ar:زلزال]]
[[an:Tierratremo]]
[[ast:Terremotu]]
[[az:Zəlzələ]]
[[bn:ভূমিকম্প]]
[[bjn:Lindu]]
[[zh-min-nan:Tē-tāng]]
[[be:Землетрасенне]]
[[be-x-old:Землятрус]]
[[bcl:Linog]]
[[bs:Potres]]
[[br:Kren-douar]]
[[bg:Земетресение]]
[[ca:Terratrèmol]]
[[cv:Çĕр чĕтренĕвĕ]]
[[cs:Zemětřesení]]
[[sn:Kundengenyeka kwenyika]]
[[co:Terramotu]]
[[cy:Daeargryn]]
[[da:Jordskælv]]
[[de:Erdbeben]]
[[nv:Kéyah haʼdéísná]]
[[et:Maavärin]]
[[el:Σεισμός]]
[[es:Terremoto]]
[[eo:Tertremo]]
[[ext:Terremotu]]
[[eu:Lurrikara]]
[[fa:زمین‌لرزه]]
[[fo:Jarðskjálvti]]
[[fr:Séisme]]
[[fy:Ierdskodding]]
[[ga:Crith talún]]
[[gd:Crith-thalmhainn]]
[[gl:Terremoto]]
[[gan:地震]]
[[gu:ધરતીકંપ]]
[[ko:지진]]
[[hy:Երկրաշարժ]]
[[hi:भूकंप]]
[[hr:Potres]]
[[io:Ter-tremo]]
[[id:Gempa bumi]]
[[ia:Seismo]]
[[iu:ᓴᔪᑉᐱᓛᕗᖅ]]
[[is:Jarðskjálfti]]
[[it:Terremoto]]
[[he:רעידת אדמה]]
[[jv:Lindhu]]
[[kn:ಭೂಕಂಪ]]
[[ka:მიწისძვრა]]
[[kk:Жер сілкіну]]
[[rw:Umutingito]]
[[sw:Tetemeko la ardhi]]
[[ht:Tranblemanntè]]
[[ku:Erdhej]]
[[la:Terrae motus]]
[[lv:Zemestrīce]]
[[lb:Äerdbiewen]]
[[lt:Žemės drebėjimas]]
[[li:Eerdsjók]]
[[ln:Moningí]]
[[hu:Földrengés]]
[[mk:Земјотрес]]
[[ml:ഭൂകമ്പം]]
[[mr:भूकंप]]
[[ms:Gempa bumi]]
[[mwl:Sismo]]
[[mn:Газар хөдлөлт]]
[[my:ငလျင်လှုပ်ခြင်း]]
[[nah:Tlālolīniliztli]]
[[nl:Aardbeving]]
[[ne:भुँइचालो]]
[[ja:地震]]
[[no:Jordskjelv]]
[[nn:Jordskjelv]]
[[oc:Tèrratrem]]
[[om:Chocho'a lafa]]
[[uz:Zilzila]]
[[pnb:بھونچال]]
[[pap:Terremoto]]
[[nds:Eerdbeven]]
[[pl:Trzęsienie ziemi]]
[[pt:Sismo]]
[[ksh:Äädbevve]]
[[ro:Cutremur]]
[[rm:Terratrembel]]
[[qu:Pacha kuyuy]]
[[ru:Землетрясение]]
[[sa:भूकंप]]
[[sq:Tërmeti]]
[[scn:Tirrimotu]]
[[si:භූමිකම්පාව]]
[[simple:Earthquake]]
[[sk:Zemetrasenie]]
[[sl:Potres]]
[[szl:Trzyńśyńy źymje]]
[[so:Dhulgariir]]
[[ckb:بوومەلەرزە]]
[[srn:Grontapubeyfi]]
[[sr:Земљотрес]]
[[sh:Potres]]
[[su:Lini]]
[[fi:Maanjäristys]]
[[sv:Jordbävning]]
[[tl:Lindol]]
[[ta:நிலநடுக்கம்]]
[[tt:Җир тетрәү]]
[[te:భూకంపం]]
[[th:แผ่นดินไหว]]
[[tg:Заминларза]]
[[tr:Deprem]]
[[uk:Землетрус]]
[[ur:زلزلہ]]
[[ug:يەر تەۋرەش]]
[[vec:Teremoto]]
[[vi:Động đất]]
[[fiu-vro:Maavärrin]]
[[wa:Tronnmint d' tere]]
[[vls:Eirdbevienge]]
[[war:Linog]]
[[yi:ערדציטערניש]]
[[zh-yue:地震]]
[[diq:Erdlerz]]
[[bat-smg:Žemės kustiejėms]]
[[zh:地震]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
