<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="1014770" ns="0" title="Shanty town"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">:''&quot;Shantytown&quot; redirects here. For the created gold-mining town in New Zealand, see [[Shantytown, New Zealand]].''
[[File:Soweto township.jpg|thumb|250px|Shanty town in [[Soweto]], South Africa, 2005]]A '''shanty town''' (also called a '''squatter settlement''') is a [[slum]] settlement (sometimes illegal or unauthorized) of impoverished people who live in improvised dwellings made from scrap materials: often [[plywood]], [[Corrugated galvanised iron|corrugated metal]] and sheets of plastic. Shanty towns, which are usually built on the periphery of cities, often do not have proper sanitation, electricity or telephone services.

Shanty towns are mostly found in developing nations, or partially developed nations with an [[economic inequality|unequal distribution of wealth]]. In extreme cases, shanty towns have populations approaching that of a city. {{asof|2005}}, one billion people, one-sixth of the world's population, live in shanty towns.&lt;ref&gt;David Whitehouse, [http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/science/nature/4561183.stm &quot;Half of humanity set to go urban&quot;], BBC News, May 19, 2005.&lt;/ref&gt;

==Features==
[[Image:Cite Soleil Haiti.jpg|left|thumb|250px|right|[[Cité Soleil]], [[Haiti]], 2002]]Since construction is informal and unguided by urban planning, there is a near total absence of formal [[Grid plan|street grids]], numbered streets, sewage network, [[electric power|electricity]], or [[telephone]]s. Even if these resources are present, they are likely to be disorganized, old or inferior. Shanty towns also tend to lack basic services present in more formally organized settlements, including policing, medical services and fire fighting. Fires are a particular danger for shanty towns not only for the lack of fire fighting stations and the difficulty fire trucks have traversing the absence of formal street grids,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.eluniversal.com/2009/07/04/ccs_art_solo-tres-unidades-d_1460015.shtml|title=Sólo tres unidades de bomberos atienden 2 mil barrios de Petare|author=Jorge Hernández|language=Spanish}}&lt;/ref&gt; but also because of the high density of buildings and flammability of materials used in construction&lt;ref&gt;See the report on shack fires in South Africa by Matt Birkinshaw [http://abahlali.org/files/Big_Devil_Politics_of_Shack_Fire.pdf] as well as the wider collection of articles in fires in shanty towns at [http://www.abahlali.org/taxonomy/term/841]&lt;/ref&gt; A sweeping fire on the hills of [[Shek Kip Mei]], Hong Kong, in late 1953 left 53,000 squatter dwellers homeless, prompting the colonial government to institute a resettlement estate system.

Shanty towns have high rates of [[crime]], [[suicide]], [[Recreational drug use|drug use]] and [[disease]]. However the observer [[Georg Gerster]] has noted (with specific reference to the ''invasões'' of [[Brasilia]]), &quot;squatter settlements [as opposed to slums], despite their unattractive building materials, may also be places of hope, scenes of a counter-culture, with an encouraging potential for change and a strong upward impetus.&quot; (1978)&lt;ref&gt;Georg Gerster, ''Flights of Discovery: The Earth from Above'', 1978, London: Paddington, p. 116&lt;/ref&gt; [[Stewart Brand]] has also written, more recently, that &quot;squatter cities are [[Green energy|Green]]. They have maximum density—­a million people per square mile in Mumbai—­and minimum energy and mate­rial use. People get around by foot, bicycle, rickshaw, or the universal [[shared taxi]] ... Not everything is efficient in the slums, though. In the Brazilian favelas where electricity is stolen and therefore free, Jan Chipchase from Nokia found that people leave their lights on all day. In most slums recycling is literally a way of life.&quot; (2010)&lt;ref&gt;Stewart Brand, &quot;[http://newurbannetwork.com/article/stewart-brand-new-urbanism-and-squatter-communities-13243 Stewart Brand on New Urbanism and squatter communities]&quot;, ''The New Urban Network'', reprinted from ''Whole Earth Discipline'', Penguin,&lt;/ref&gt;

==Examples==
Shanty towns are present in a number of countries. The largest shanty town in Asia is the [[Orangi Township]], in [[Karachi]], Pakistan.&lt;ref name=Natgeo&gt;[http://ngm.nationalgeographic.com/2007/05/dharavi-mumbai-slum/jacobson-text Dharavi - National Geographic Magazine]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;http://www.dawn.com/weekly/cowas/20071006.htm&lt;/ref&gt; while the largest in Africa is [[Khayelitsha]] in [[Cape Town]], [[South Africa]]{{Citation needed|date=September 2010}}. While shanty towns are less common in Europe, the growing influx of illegal immigrants have fueled shantytowns in cities commonly used as a points of entry into the EU, including [[Athens]] and [[Patras]] in Greece.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news| url=http://www.telegraph.co.uk/news/worldnews/europe/greece/6147072/Greek-immigration-crisis-spawns-shanty-towns-and-squats.html | location=London | work=The Daily Telegraph | first1=Nick | last1=Squires | first2=Paul | last2=Anast | title=Greek immigration crisis spawns shanty towns and squats | date=September 7, 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt;

{{anchor|bidonville}}In [[francophone]] countries, shanty towns are referred to as ''[[wikt:bidonville#French|bidonvilles]]'' (French for &quot;can town&quot;); such countries include [[Tunisia]], [[Haiti]], and France itself – see [[Poverty in France#Bidonvilles|bidonvilles in France]].

Other countries with shanty towns include India, [[South Africa]] (where they are often called ''[[squatter]] camps'') or imijondolo, the [[Philippines]] (often called ''squatter areas''), [[Venezuela]] (where they are known as [[barrio]]s), Brazil ([[favela]]s), [[Argentina]]       ([[villas miseria]]), [[West Indies]] such as [[Jamaica]] and [[Trinidad and Tobago]] (where they are known as Shanty town), and [[Peru]] (where they are known as [[pueblos jóvenes|&quot;young towns&quot;]]). There are also shanty town population in countries such as [[Bangladesh]]&lt;ref&gt;http://www.isuh.org/download/dhaka.pdf&lt;/ref&gt; and the [[People's Republic of China]].&lt;ref&gt;http://olympics.scmp.com/Article.aspx?id=1419&amp;section=insight&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;http://english.peopledaily.com.cn/200509/09/eng20050909_207472.html&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;http://www.isg-fi.org.uk/spip.php?article288&lt;/ref&gt;

===More Economically Developed Countries===
Although shantytowns are less common in first world countries, there are some cities that suffer from the shanty town condition. In [[Madrid]], Spain, a low-class neighborhood named La Cañada Real (which is considered a shanty town) has no schools, nurseries or health clinics. Some homes have no running water and rubble and trash is everywhere.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.blnz.com/news/2009/07/28/Madrid_calls_time_shameful_shanty_8445.html&lt;/ref&gt; In Portugal, shanty towns known as &quot;barracas&quot; are made up of immigrants from former Portuguese African colonies and Gypsies from Romania. The settlements are so bad that they can be compared to other shanty towns in third world countries.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.siloam.org.uk/002.htm&lt;/ref&gt; In the United States, some cities such as [[Newark, New Jersey#Poverty and lack of investment|Newark]] and [[Oakland#Demographics|Oakland]] suffer from high rates of poverty (28% in Newark and 17% in Oakland) and lead to the creation of [[Tent city|tent cities]]. Other settlements in developed countries that are comparable to shanty towns include the [[Colonia (United States)|Colonias]] on the border between the United States and Mexico, and [[Poverty in France#Bidonvilles|bidonvilles in France]], which may exist in the peripheries of some cities.

==Development==
While most shanty towns begin as precarious establishments haphazardly thrown together without basic social and civil services, over time many have undergone a significant amount of development.&lt;ref&gt;[http://cohaforum.org/2011/08/16/some-young-towns-in-lima-not-so-young-anymore/]&lt;/ref&gt; Often the residents themselves are responsible for the major improvements.&lt;ref name=&quot;cohaforum.org&quot;&gt;http://cohaforum.org/2011/08/16/some-young-towns-in-lima-not-so-young-anymore/&lt;/ref&gt;  Community organizations sometimes working alongside [[NGO]]'s, private companies, and the government, setup connections to the municipal water supply, pave roads, and build local schools.&lt;ref name=&quot;cohaforum.org&quot;/&gt;  Many of these shanties have become middle class [[suburbs]].  One such extreme example is the [[Los Olivos District|Los Olivos]] Neighborhood of [[Lima]], [[Peru]].   The Megaplaza shopping mall, one of Lima's largest, along with [[gated communities]], [[casinos]], and even plastic surgery clinics, are just a few of many developments that have transformed what used to be a decrepit shanty.&lt;ref name=&quot;cohaforum.org&quot;/&gt;  Brazilian [[favelas]] have also seen huge improvements in recent years, enough so to attract tourists who flock to catch a glimpse of the colorful lifestyle perched atop [[Rio de Janeiro]]'s highlands.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news| url=http://www.forbes.com/sites/megacities/2011/05/16/favela-tourism-provides-entrepreneurial-opportunuties-in-rio/ | work=Forbes}}&lt;/ref&gt;  Development occurs over a long period of time and newer towns still lack basic services.   Nevertheless there has been a general trend whereby shanties undergo gradual improvements, rather than relocation to even more distant parts of a metropolis and replacement by [[gated communities]] constructed over their ruins.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.crassh.cam.ac.uk/events/1324/87&lt;/ref&gt;

==See also==
===Regional names===
* [[Asentamiento]]s in [[Guatemala]]
* [[Campamento (Chilean term)|Campamentos]] in [[Chile]], another name is &quot;poblaciones callampa&quot;.
* [[Colonia (border settlement)|Colonias]]'' or ''Migrant camps'' on the [[Mexico – United States border]]
* [[Favela]]s in Brazil
* [[Cantegril]] in [[Uruguay]]
* [[Gecekondu]] in Turkey
* [[Hoovervilles]] in the United States (historical)
* [[Bidonville]]s in France (historical)
* [[Pueblos jóvenes]]'' (young towns) or ''barriadas'' in [[Peru]]
* [[Villa Miseria|Villas Miseria]]'' or just ''villas'' in [[Argentina]]
* [[Tent city|Tent cities]] in the United States.
* Barrios de invasión, in Colombia
* Invasiones in [[Puerto Rico]]
* Basti in India

===Specific places===
* [[Favela da Rocinha]] (Rio de Janeiro, Brazil)
**''see also [[List of favelas in Brazil]]''
* [[Cité Soleil]] (Haiti)
* [[Dharavi]] (India)
* [[Joe Slovo, Cape Town|Joe Slovo]] (Cape Town, South Africa)
* [[Kibera]] (Nairobi, Kenya)
* [[Khayelitsha]] (Cape Town, South Africa)

===People and organizations===
* [[Akhtar Hameed Khan]]
* [[CEIFAR]]
* [[Hernando de Soto (economist)]]
* [[Mike Davis (scholar)]]
* Chinese [[New Village]] (Malaysia)
* [[Orangi Pilot Project]]
* [[Slum Dwellers International]]
* [[Slum upgrading]]
* [[United Nations Human Settlements Programme]]
* [[Western Cape Anti-Eviction Campaign]]
* [[The Susso]], welfare in Australia originating in the Great Depression
* [[Occupy Wallstreet]]

===Related concepts===
* [[Ghetto]]
* [[Flophouse]]
* [[Favela]]
* [[Hobo]]
* [[Slumlord]]
* [[Poverty in France]]
* [[Refugee shelter]]
* [[Skid row]]
* ''[[Slumdog Millionaire]]'' (film)
* ''[[District 9]]'' (film)
* ''[[City of God]]'' (film)
* [[Squatting]]
* [[Tent city]]
* [[Trailer park]]
* [[Urban decay]]

==References==
{{Reflist|2}}

==External links==
{{Commons category|Shanty towns}}
* [http://www.slate.com/id/2140224/entry/2140206/ Slate article about an economist proposing New Orleans to be reconstructed with shanties]
* [http://www.flickr.com/photos/avaneeshbhatt/sets/ Photos of Dharavi, a shanty town in Mumbai, India.]

{{DEFAULTSORT:Shanty Town}}
[[Category:Homelessness]]
[[Category:Shanty towns| ]]
[[Category:Urban studies and planning]]
[[Category:Populated places by type]]

[[ar:مدن الصفيح]]
[[de:Informelle Siedlung]]
[[es:Asentamiento informal]]
[[fr:Bidonville]]
[[nl:Sloppenwijk]]
[[pt:Favela]]
[[sr:Divlja naselja]]
[[sv:Kåkstad]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
