<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="101568" ns="0" title="WAPA-TV"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Infobox_broadcast
| call_letters             = WAPA-TV 
| city                     =
| station_logo             = [[Image:WAPA-TV logo 2007 TAG spot.svg|200px|WAPA-TV]]       
| station_slogan           = Como tu... boricua! (Like you... Puerto Rican!)
| station_branding         = WAPA Television
| analog                   =
| digital                  = 27 ([[ultra high frequency|UHF]])&lt;br&gt;[[Virtual channel|Virtual]]: 4 ([[Program and System Information Protocol|PSIP]])
| other_chs                = [[WNJX-TV]] 4.1 [[Mayagüez, Puerto Rico|Mayagüez]]&lt;br /&gt;WTIN-TV 4.1 [[Ponce, Puerto Rico|Ponce]]
| affiliations             =
| subchannels              = 4.1 [[Independent station (North America)|Independent]]&lt;br&gt;4.2 [[Universal Sports]] &lt;br&gt;4.3 Canal del Tiempo
| network                  =
| founded                  =
| airdate                  = May 1, 1954
| location                 = [[San Juan, Puerto Rico]]
| callsign_meaning         = '''A'''sociación de&lt;br /&gt;'''P'''roductores de&lt;br /&gt;'''A'''zúcar
| former_callsigns         =
| former_channel_numbers   = '''Analog:'''&lt;br&gt;4 ([[Very high frequency|VHF]], 1954-2009)
| owner                    = [[InterMedia Partners]]
| licensee                 = {{nowrap|Televicentro of Puerto Rico, LLC}}
| sister_stations          =
| effective_radiated_power = 1000 [[kilowatt|kW]]
| HAAT                     = 794 m
| class                    =
| facility_id              = 52073
| coordinates              = {{Coord|18|6|33.8|N|66|3|2.5|W|type:landmark_scale:2000}}
| homepage                 = [http://www.wapa.tv/ www.wapa.tv]
}}

'''WAPA-TV''' is an [[Independent station (North America)|independent]] television station located in [[San Juan, Puerto Rico]] transmitting over digital channel 27, virtual channel 4. The station is owned by [[InterMedia Partners]] and is branded as WAPA Television.

WAPA-TV has two full-power satellite stations: '''WTIN-TV''', channel 4.1 in [[Ponce, Puerto Rico|Ponce]] and '''[[WNJX-TV]]''', channel 4.1 in [[Mayagüez, Puerto Rico|Mayagüez]]. Both stations are also owned by InterMedia Partners.

==History==
WAPA-TV was the second television station to be licensed to Puerto Rico and began broadcasting on May 1, 1954. Its call letters are a partial abbreviation of the station's original owners, the now-defunct ''Asociación de Productores de Azúcar'', or Puerto Rico Sugar Grower's Association. During its earliest years, the station was affiliated with [[NBC]], [[American Broadcasting Company|ABC]], [[DuMont Television Network|DuMont]], and the CMQ Television Network.&lt;ref name=&quot;Broadcasting&quot;&gt;[http://davidgleason.com/Broadcasting%201955%20Yearbook%20Page%20Range%20Guide_files/Broadcasting%20Yearbook%201955.pdf ''Broadcasting Yearbook'', 1955. p. 333]&lt;/ref&gt;

The station was the first to transition to color unceremoniously in 1966 on [[NTSC]], followed by [[WKAQ-TV]] in 1968. Popularly known in Puerto Rico by its assigned channel number, ''Canal Cuatro'', the station was also known by its animated cartoon mascot during the 1970s and 1980s, a bongo-playing cat (known commonly as ''el gato de WAPA'' in [[Spanish language|Spanish]]) and therefore its rhyming slogan is, ''Por el cuatro como el gato'' (colloquially &quot;on four like the cat&quot;), which rhymes in Spanish.  Similarly, another TV spot used the phrase, ''Hasta el gato, te-ve el cuatro'' and the cat itself was alternately known as ''el Gato de Cuatro.''

[[Image:Wapa80 ad2.jpg|thumb|left|WAPA-TV's &quot;Open 4&quot; logo in a 1980 newspaper advertisement for ''Decision '80''. The &quot;Open 4&quot; logo in this ad was used from 1968 to 1986, and again from 1996 to 1998.]]
Like other mascots, El Gato was seen in different situations in different TV spots.  Besides playing the bongos, he would also play the drums and was seen in one station ID as a matador.  Another spot had him interacting with a cat seen in a Telemundo ad.  El Gato would also sometimes be accompanied by his wife and children (one boy and one girl), where they appeared flying in a helicopter shaped like the channel's &quot;4&quot; logo and celebrated the holidays while playing musical instruments.

WAPA-TV's competitors include [[WKAQ-TV]] ([[Telemundo]]), [[WLII]] ([[Univision]] Puerto Rico), and [[WIPR-TV]]([[Public Broadcasting Service|PBS]]). WAPA-TV and WKAQ-TV have battled for the title of Puerto Rico's most-viewed station since the 1950s, with WLII entering the battle in the mid 80s.

During the 1980s and early 1990s, the station was very successful by mixing American shows translated to Spanish with locally produced sitcoms such as &quot;Cuqui&quot;, &quot;Cara o Cruz&quot;, &quot;Entrando por la Cocina&quot;, &quot;Carmelo y Punto&quot; and &quot;Barrio Cuatro Calles&quot;. But it was still trailing behind WKAQ-TV as the second major Puerto Rican station. In the early 90's, WAPA rebranded itself with the slogans &quot;WAPA'lla!&quot; (a catchy slang variation of &quot;Vamos pa'lla&quot; - Let's go!) and &quot;WAPA, aqui con la gente&quot; (WAPA, here with the people). These slogans were accompanied by a catchy score and vivid, colorful graphics depicting the channel's logo. In 1994, WAPA was the first television station in Puerto Rico to use high-end graphic animations to animate a new logo, created and animated by Pixel Light Studios in [[New York]]. This gave the channel a very &quot;American&quot; look. The logo, although graphically pleasing, was slowly dropped in favor of the classical number 4 logo. High end graphics were later altogether dropped for cheaper, in-house graphics.

[[Image:El Gato de Wapa TV by derictorres.jpg|thumb|right|El Gato, the mascot of WAPA-TV.]]
In 1997, under the helm of [[Miguel Banojian]] an Ex-Univision executive, WAPA-TV achieved the biggest rating increases in its History. During Mr. Banojian's tenure, the network was producing more local programming than ever, more local news production, several sporting events were produced by its Spots Division,including, Beisbol exclusive &quot;Serie Del Caribe&quot; [Caribe edition of the U.S Beisbol &quot;World Series], World Boxing championship events in partnership with Don King and many others.

In 1998, WAPA again rebranded itself with a new name and logo; &quot;Televicentro&quot; (used previously during the 70s and 80s). It has also regained its position as a major Puerto Rican TV station, mainly due to its new focus on locally produced programming. Its new slogan, &quot;Como tú, boricua&quot; highlights the fact that it is the only local commercial station left, with no foreign influence. Albeit the new name, locals still called it either &quot;el cuatro&quot; or simply &quot;WAPA&quot;.

In September 2004, WAPA-TV became the first Puerto Rican station, and the seventh TV station in the U.S. (including territories) to become a [[superstation]] and broadcast shows through the [[DirecTV]] [[satellite]] system to the [[United States]], under the name of '''WAPA America''' WAPA America's master control headquarters are located in [[Springfield, Massachusetts]] in the nearby suburb of Chicopee. &quot;WAPA America&quot; can also be seen in the U. S. through cable television service via companies like Comcast, RCN, Qwest Communications, and recently added to Cablevision subscribers in the greater New York City Metropolitan Area, and several surrounding communities. In reality, WAPA America isin't WAPA's first experiment outside Puerto Rico. In the 80's, it had WNJU-TV Channel 47 in New York City as a repeater and some other channels in the New York-New Jersey area, but due to financial problems, they sold Channel 47 and its others channels in that area to the Telemundo Network near the end of the 80's.

On October 19, 2006. LIN TV announced that it had entered into an agreement to sell its Puerto Rico television operations to [[InterMedia Partners]] for $130 million in cash.[http://www.corporate-ir.net/ireye/ir_site.zhtml?ticker=TVL&amp;script=410&amp;layout=-6&amp;item_id=918570 ] The sale was completed on March 30, 2007.

===WAPA (2007–present)===
On December 17, 2007, the station changed its branding from &quot;Televicentro&quot; to &quot;wapa&quot;, in lowercase letters. Following the rename, the channel began a developing a new format, changing the jingle and recreating their website.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web| url=http://www.primerahora.com/noticia/tv/espectaculos_asi/pegajosa_cancion_comojingle/210933| title=Pegajosa canción como“jingle”| publisher=Primera Hora| language=Spanish| date=2008-07-17| accessdate=2008-07-22}} {{Dead link|date=September 2010|bot=H3llBot}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web| url=http://www.primerahora.com/noticia/tv/espectaculos_asi/con_nuevo_formato_en_la_internet/212346| title=Con nuevo formato en la internet| publisher=Primera Hora| language=Spanish| date=2008-07-21| accessdate=2008-07-22}} {{Dead link|date=September 2010|bot=H3llBot}}&lt;/ref&gt; WAPA-TV signed a contract with [[Miss Puerto Rico|Miss Puerto Rico Universe]] to transmit a reality show titled &quot;Por la corona&quot;, beginning on August 15, 2008. The public will select via [[text messaging]], with five of the participants classifying directly to the pageant's semifinal.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web| url=http://www.primerahora.com/noticia/tv/espectaculos_asi/el_publico_elegira_a_la_nueva_reina/217740| title=El público elegirá a la nueva reina| publisher=''Primera Hora''| language=Spanish| date=2008-08-08| accessdate=2008-08-11}} {{Dead link|date=September 2010|bot=H3llBot}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Programming==
WAPA-TV for years has shown [[boxing]], [[Baloncesto Superior Nacional|BSN]] [[basketball]], [[telenovelas]], movies, comedies, sitcoms (both [[United States|American]] and domestic), [[baseball]], [[National Football League|NFL]] [[American football|football]], both [[World Wrestling Entertainment]] (WWE) and Puerto Rican (WWC) [[professional wrestling]], human interest shows and its news show, ''Noticentro''.

Current weekday programs:
{{col-begin}}
{{col-2}}
* ''Noticentro al Amanecer'' ([[news]])
* ''Entre Nosotras'' ([[talk show]])
* ''Amor en Custodia'' ([[telenovela]])
* ''Noticentro a las 5'' (news)
* ''SuperXClusivo'' (gossip show)
* ''[[Grey's Anatomy]]'' (series)
* ''[[CSI: Miami]]'' (series)
{{col-2}}
* [[Supernatural (TV series)|''Supernatural'' (TV series)]] (series)
* ''Super Cine'' (movies)
* ''Noticentro a las 10'' (news)
* ''Monica en confianza'' (talk show)
* ''Pegate al mediodia'' (variety)
* ''De Pelicula'' (movie news)
* ''Jangueo''
{{col-end}}

Weekend programs:
{{col-begin}}
{{col-2}}
* ''Chicola y la Ganga'' (children)
* ''Super Estrellas de la Lucha Libre (WWC)'' (wrestling)
* ''Noticentro Fin de Semana'' (news)
* ''SmackDown!'' (wrestling)
* ''Noticentro En Una Semana'' (news)
* ''[[Charmed]] (TV Series)
* [[House (TV series)|''House'' (TV series)]] (series)
{{col-2}}
* ''Battlestar Galactica''
* [[24 (TV series)|''24'' (TV series)]]
* ''Iglesia Católica'' (religious)
* ''[[Chiqui Chef]]'' (children)
* ''[[El Cartel (TV series)|El Cartel]]'' (telenovela)
* ''[[Desperate Housewives]] (TV Series)
* ''[[Al borde del deseo]]'' (telenovela)
{{col-end}}

==Noticentro==
'''Noticentro''' is the name of WAPA-TV's news division. The news operation began in 1967 with Cuban-born [[Evelio Otero]] as the sole anchorman at the 10&amp;nbsp;p.m. newscast. Soon thereafter Carlos Ruben Ortiz joined the news staff with the 6 p.m. broadcast. Evelio Otero remained by himself on camera until his departure from WAPA in 1980 to take the senior editor position at the Voice of America in Washington. Carlos Ruben Ortiz shared the anchor slot at 6 p.m. with then newcomer [[Guillermo José Torres]], a former radio announcer born in [[Juana Diaz, Puerto Rico]] who has since become the longest standing news announcer in the island, with a career spanning more than 36 years. The format predated the ''[[NewsCenter]]'' format which become popular in NBC owned stations in the 1970s.

In its beginnings, Noticentro 4 lasted only fifteen minutes in the afternoon, with a 30 minute edition at 10 in the evening. There was also a weekend edition. Gradually, the program's on-the-air time was increased to a full hour.

After Otero's departure, [[New York City]]-born William &quot;Bill&quot; Pérez became WAPA's news director (Torres held the post for a while but eventually asked to be left as an anchorperson only) In the late 1970s, [[Enrique Cruz Díaz]], [[Luz Nereida Vélez]], [[Sylvia Gómez]], [[Luis Rigual]], [[Cyd Marie Fleming]], [[José Esteves]], [[Luis Francisco Ojeda]] and others joined.

In 1980, ''Noticentro 4'' inaugurated a new studio. In 1981, [[Pedro Rosa Nales]] joined the team. In 1982, [[Enrique Cruz Díaz]], also known as ''Kike Cruz'', substituted Torres as show director. In 1983, Rigual died, being substituted as main sports anchor man by [[Rafael Bracero]]. [[Bobby Angleró]] joined the team of reporters as Bracero's main helper in 1984, year in which the ''[[Coquí]] Satellite'' was inaugurated by the station. ''Coquí Satellite'' helped the network deliver breaking news quicker, and it helped deliver the news on occasions such as the [[Space Shuttle Challenger|Challenger]] explosion, when Torres interrupted [[Angela Meyer]] on her [[Chanita Gobernadora]] comedy section to break the news to the public only minutes after it had happened.

In the early 2000s, WAPA-TV inaugurated the ''SuperCóptero'' (SuperChopper), the Noticentro 4 [[helicopter]]. The ''SuperCóptero'' is mostly used to report on traffic conditions in the metropolitan area on the 4:00 p.m. and 5:00 p.m. editions of Noticentro 4. WAPA-TV is the only local station to have a helicopter in the air, but soon they discontinued the SuperCoptero due to budget cuts, WAPA only uses the copter in speciel events and emergencies.

Noticentro runs a local cable channel, ''Wapa Tiempo'' . The channel broadcasts weather forecasts for Puerto Rico 24 hours a day. El Canal del Tiempo can be seen on all three cable companies serving Puerto Rico and on WAPA-TV [[digital subchannel]], WAPA-DT 27.3/4.3. The channel is now called Wapa Tiempo instead of El Canal del Tiempo to avoid confusion with The Weather Channel from NBCUniversal.

WAPA-TV uses it same  logo for Noticentro (formerly Noticentro 4), changing the word WAPA to Noticentro, but with the same red strips at the right. The previous music package Noticentro 4 used is called ''News Authority'' by 615 Music and has been used since 2004. In the past they've used ''Newswatch 24'', ''News One'', ''Impact'' among others. Noticentro now uses the same music for all its sections and bumpers except for its news resume En Una Semana (In One Week) which  used the Noticentro 4 graphics and music package from 1999, but now uses the current graphics and music package.

Wapa Tiempo for a time used the old Noticentro 4 graphics and logo, but recently the channel received new graphics and logo to go with the &quot;New WAPA&quot; upbringing. ''Noticentro'' currently airs about forty hours of local news coverage a week. In the next months to come, Noticentro will receive new graphics and studio redesign along with the &quot;New WAPA&quot; initiative.

===News/Station presentation===
====Newscast titles====
*''El Observador Kresto Denia'' (1954–1963)
*''El Noticiero'' (''The Newsroom'') (1963–1978)
*''Noticentro 4'' (''[[NewsCenter]] 4'') (1978–1995, 1996–1998, 2002–2007)
*''Noticentro'' (1995–1996, 1998–2002, 2007–present)

====Station slogans====
{{col-begin}}
{{col-2}}
*''Hasta el gato Te-Ve el 4'' (1968–1979)
*''Adelante en el 80'' (1980)
*''Arrasando en el 81'' (1981)
*''Insuperable'' (1982)
*''Tremendo'' (1983)
*''Pa' Encima'' (1983–1984)
*''La Pionera'' (1984)
*''Contigo Siempre'' (1985)
*''Siempre en Grande'' (1985–1986)
*''Esto es WAPA...Lo Mejor'' (1987)
{{col-2}}
*''Imagen Viva'' (1987)
*''Ven a Casa... Ven a WAPA'' (1988–1989)
*''Ponle el ojo al cuatro'' (1989–1990)
*''WAPA'lla!'' (1990–1992)
*''WAPA, Aqui con la Gente'' (WAPA, Here with the People) (1992–1994)
*''La Emocion!'' (1994–1995)
*''Lo nuestro siempre primero'' (1996)
*''Como tu... boricua!'' (1998–Present)
{{col-end}}
{{inc-video}}

==Broadcasting==
===Digital television===

{| class=&quot;wikitable&quot;
|-
! Channel
! Programming
|-
| 4.1 / 27.1 || Main WAPA-TV programming
|-
| 4.2 / 27.2 || WAPA2
|-
| 4.3 / 27.3 || Wapa Tiempo
|-
|}

===Satellite stations===
WAPA-TV can be seen across Puerto Rico on the following stations:
{| class=&quot;toccolours&quot; border=&quot;2&quot; cellpadding=&quot;4&quot; cellspacing=&quot;0&quot; style=&quot;margin: 1em 1em 1em 0; background: #f9f9f9; border: 1px #aaa solid; border-collapse: collapse&quot;
| '''Station'''
| '''[[City of license]]'''
| '''[[channel (broadcasting)|Channels]]&lt;br /&gt;''([[analog television|Analog]]/&lt;br /&gt;[[digital terrestrial television|Digital]])'''''
| '''First air date'''
| '''[[effective radiated power|ERP]]&lt;br /&gt;''(Analog/&lt;br /&gt;Digital)'''''
| '''[[height above average terrain|HAAT]]&lt;br /&gt;''(Analog/&lt;br /&gt;Digital)'''''
| '''[[Facility ID]]'''
| '''Transmitter Coordinates'''
|- style=&quot;vertical-align: top; text-align: left;&quot;
| '''WTIN'''
| [[Ponce, Puerto Rico|Ponce]]
| 14 ([[ultra high frequency|UHF]])&lt;br /&gt;15 ([[ultra high frequency|UHF]])
| 1985
| 1070 [[kilowatt|kW]]&lt;br /&gt;380.2&amp;nbsp;kW
| 861 m&lt;br /&gt;839 m
| 26681
| {{Coord|18|10|4.2|N|66|34|37.2|W|type:landmark_scale:2000|name=WTIN}} (analog)&lt;br /&gt;{{Coord|18|10|3|N|66|34|35|W|type:landmark_scale:2000|name=WTIN}} (digital)
|- style=&quot;vertical-align: top; text-align: left;&quot;
| '''[[WNJX-TV]]'''
| [[Mayagüez, Puerto Rico|Mayagüez]]
| 22 ([[ultra high frequency|UHF]])&lt;br /&gt;23 ([[ultra high frequency|UHF]])
| April 27, 1986
| 4201&amp;nbsp;kW&lt;br /&gt;400&amp;nbsp;kW
| 658 m&lt;br /&gt;693 m
| 73336
| {{Coord|18|8|52|N|66|58|59|W|type:landmark_scale:2000|name=WNJX-TV}}
|- style=&quot;vertical-align: top; text-align: left;&quot;
|}

==References==
{{Reflist}}

==External links and sources==
*[http://www.wapa.tv/ WAPA-TV]
*[http://www.wapaamerica.com/ WAPA America]
*[http://www.museum.tv/archives/etv/P/htmlP/puertorico/puertorico.htm The Museum of Broadcasting - Puerto Rico TV Profile]
*{{TVQ|WAPA-TV}}
*{{TVQ|WTIN}}
*{{BIA|WAPA|TV|TV}}
*{{BIA|WTIN|TV|TV}}

{{Puerto Rico TV}}
{{Superstations}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Wapa-Tv}}
[[Category:Independent television stations in the United States]]
[[Category:San Juan, Puerto Rico]]
[[Category:Superstations in the United States]]
[[Category:Channel 27 digital TV stations in the United States]]
[[Category:Channel 4 virtual TV stations in the United States]]
[[Category:Television channels and stations established in 1954]]
[[Category:Television stations in Puerto Rico]]
[[Category:Television pioneers]]

[[es:WAPA-TV]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
