<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="1016706" ns="0" title="Go Daddy"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Infobox dotcom company
| company_name = GoDaddy.com, Inc.
| company_logo = [[File:Go Daddy logo.svg|200px]]
| company_type = [[Private company]]
| foundation = 1997
| location = [[Scottsdale, Arizona]], USA
| founder = [[Bob Parsons]]
| industry = [[Domain Registrar]]
| products = Web services
| alexa = {{decrease}} 70 ({{as of|2011|11|2|alt=November 2011}})&lt;ref name=&quot;alexa&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url= http://www.alexa.com/siteinfo/godaddy.com |title= Godaddy.com Site Info | publisher= [[Alexa Internet]] |accessdate= 2011-11-02 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;!--Updated monthly by OKBot.--&gt;
| homepage= [http://www.godaddy.com/ godaddy.com]
}}

'''Go Daddy''' is an Internet [[Domain name registrar|domain registrar]] and [[Web hosting]] company that also sells e-business related [[software]] and services. In 2010, it reached more than 45 million [[domain name]]s under management.&lt;ref name=&quot;RegistrarStats&quot;&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.registrarstats.com |title=RegistrarStats |publisher=RegistrarStats |date= |accessdate=2009-04-20}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Domain Name Wire&quot;&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://domainnamewire.com/2010/03/09/go-daddy-set-to-hit-40-million-domains-milestone-on-wednesday/ |title=Domain Name Wire |publisher=Domain Name Wire |date=2010-03-09 |accessdate=2010-03-17}}&lt;/ref&gt; Go Daddy is currently the largest [[ICANN]]-accredited [[Domain name registrar|registrar]] in the world, and is four times the size of its closest competitor{{who?|date=October 2011}}.&lt;ref name=&quot;RegistrarStats&quot;/&gt;{{verification failed|date=October 2011}}&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://domainnamewire.com/2010/08/17/go-daddy-marches-toward-1-billion/ |title=Domain Name Wire |publisher=Domain Name Wire |date=2010-08-17 |accessdate=2010-08-24}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Go Daddy started advertising in the Super Bowl in 2005.  Since then, the company expanded its marketing to include sports sponsorships.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|url=http://money.cnn.com/2005/02/07/news/midcaps/superbowl_godaddy/index.htm |title=CNNMoney.com |publisher=CNNMoney.com |date=2005-02-07 |accessdate=2009-12-29 | first1=Krysten | last1=Crawford}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.sportsbusinessdaily.com/article/129006 |title=SportsBusinessDaily.com |publisher=SportsBusinessDaily.com |date=2009-04-03 |accessdate=2009-12-29}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Go Daddy filed for an [[IPO]] in 2006, but later canceled it, due to &quot;market uncertainties&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|url=http://www.usatoday.com/money/markets/us/2006-08-09-ipo-usat_x.htm?csp=34 |title=USAToday.com |publisher=USAToday.com |date=2006-10-08 |accessdate=2009-12-29 | first=Matt | last=Krantz}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In September 2010, Go Daddy put itself up for auction. Go Daddy called off the auction several weeks later, despite reports that bids exceeded the asking price of $1.5 billion to $2 billion.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |url=http://blogs.wsj.com/deals/2010/10/25/breaking-news-godaddycom-auction-is-scuttled/ |title=Breaking News: GoDaddy.com Auction Is Scuttled. |publisher=The Wall Street Journal |date=2010-10-25 |accessdate=2011-04-20 | first=Anupreeta| last=Das}}&lt;/ref&gt; On June 24, 2011, The Wall Street Journal reported that private-equity firms [[Kohlberg Kravis Roberts|KKR]] and [[Silver Lake Partners]], along with a third investor, are nearing a deal to buy the company for between $2-2.5 billion.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|url=http://online.wsj.com/article/SB10001424052702303339904576405610949743734.html |title=USAToday.com |publisher=WSJ.com |date=2011-06-24 |accessdate=2011-06-24 | first=Anupreeta | last=Das}}&lt;/ref&gt; On July 1, 2011 Go Daddy confirmed that [[Kohlberg Kravis Roberts|KKR]] and [[Silver Lake Partners]] and Technology Crossover Ventures closed the deal. Although the purchase price was not officially announced it was reported to be $2.25 billion.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://online.wsj.com/article/SB10001424052702304584004576420372308902058.html?mod=googlenews_wsj|title=GoDaddy Bought By KKR, Others|publisher=Wall Street Journal|date=July 1, 2011|accessdate=July 2, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==History==
Go Daddy was founded in 1997 as Jomax Technologies by [[Bob Parsons]], who previously founded the software development company Parsons Technology, Inc. The company changed its name to Go Daddy in 1999 when a group of employees were brainstorming on a more memorable name than Jomax Technologies. Someone said, &quot;How about Big Daddy?&quot; A quick check revealed that the Internet domain of that name was taken. Then Parsons said, &quot;How about Go Daddy?&quot; The name was available, so he bought it.&lt;ref name=&quot;BobParsons.me&quot;&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.bobparsons.me/9/how-godaddy-got-name-logo-mean.html |title=BobParsons.me |publisher=BobParsons.me |date=2004-12-16}}&lt;/ref&gt; CEO Bob Parsons states the company stuck with the name because it made people smile and remember it.&lt;ref name=&quot;BobParsons.me&quot;/&gt;

Go Daddy has grown to become the largest ICANN-accredited registrar on the Internet.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.web-hosting-top.com/web-hosting/news/articles/6359/go-daddy-top-registrar,-says-study |title=4/27/05 |publisher=Web-hosting-top.com |date=2005-04-27 |accessdate=2009-04-20}}&lt;/ref&gt;  In 2001, soon after [[Network Solutions]] was no longer the only place to register a domain, Go Daddy was approximately the same size as competitors Dotster and [[eNom]].&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.registrarstats.com/ |title=Registrarstats: Registrar and Domain Name Statistics |date= |accessdate=2009-06-28}}&lt;/ref&gt; In April 2005, it surpassed Network Solutions in market share in terms of total [[domain name]]s registered.

In 2002, Go Daddy sued [[VeriSign]] for [[domain slamming]]&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.theregister.co.uk/2003/09/25/verisign_slammed_for_domain_renewal TheRegister.co.uk]: VeriSign slammed for domain renewal scam&lt;/ref&gt; and again in 2003 over its [[Site Finder]] service.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.circleid.com/posts/go_daddy_sues_verisign_over_site_finder/ |title=CircleID 9/22/03 |publisher=Circleid.com |date=2003-09-22 |accessdate=2009-04-20}}&lt;/ref&gt; This latter suit caused controversy over VeriSign's role as the sole maintainer of the .com and the .net [[top-level domain]]s. VeriSign shut down Site Finder after receiving a letter from [[ICANN]] ordering it to comply with a request to disable the service.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.internetnews.com/ent-news/article.php/3087071 |title=10/3/03 |publisher=Internetnews.com |date= |accessdate=2009-04-20}}&lt;/ref&gt;  In 2006, Go Daddy was sued by [[Web.com]] for [[patent infringement]].&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|url=http://www.thestreet.com/tech/internet/10293025.html |title=GoDaddy Gets Sued |publisher=TheStreet.com |date=2006-06-21 |last=Berr |first=Jonathan}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|url=http://news.com.com/2110-1030_3-6085599.html |title=Domain registrars in court |publisher=News.com |last=Mills |first=Elinor |date=June 19, 2006}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In 2007 and 2008, the company lobbied in favor of legislation that would crack down on unscrupulous online pharmacies and child predators.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://domainnamewire.com/2006/09/27/godaddy-goes-to-washington/ |title=Domain Name Wire |publisher=Domain Name Wire |date= |accessdate=2009-04-20}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://news.clickfire.com/godaddy-joins-web-predator-fight/520/ |title=Clickfire 7/25/07 |publisher=News.clickfire.com |date=2007-07-25 |accessdate=2009-04-20}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In March 2010, Go Daddy stopped registering .CN domains (China) due to the high amount of personal information that is required to register in that country. Some called it a public relations campaign, since it closely followed Google's revolt in China.&lt;ref&gt;[http://ibnlive.in.com/news/after-google-godaddy-pulls-out-of-china/112139-11.html?from=webx After Google, Go Daddy pulls out of China].&lt;/ref&gt;

==Awards==
In 2010, Go Daddy ranked as one of three finalists in the BBB of Great Arizona Business Ethics Awards. BBB's Board of Directors and Foundation established the BBB Business Ethics Awards to recognize those firms whose business practices and related activities exemplify the BBB's mission and principles and to ensure the marketplace remains fair and honorable.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://central-northern-western-arizona.bbb.org/ethics/ |title=BBB |publisher=BBB.org |date=2010-04-10 |accessdate=2010-06-10}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In 2009, Go Daddy was voted &quot;Best Registrar&quot; Domain Name Wire annual survey for the 4th consecutive year.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://domainnamewire.com/2008/04/17/survey-godaddy-moniker-still-top-domain-registrars/ |title=Domain Name Wire |publisher=Domain Name Wire |date= |accessdate=2009-04-20}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://domainnamewire.com/2009/03/03/survey-go-daddy-top-domain-name-registrar/ |title=Domain Name Wire |publisher=Domain Name Wire |date= |accessdate=2009-04-20}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Marketing==
CEO Bob Parsons refers to the marketing as &quot;GoDaddy-esque&quot; which he describes as &quot;fun, edgy, and a bit inappropriate&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.bobparsons.me/GoDaddy-esqueMarketing.html|publisher=BobParsons.me|last=Parsons|first=Bob|title=Our GoDaddy-esque marketing. Why I keep it edgy. Our 2nd GoDaddy-esque video cast.|date=2007-03-30|accessdate=2007-04-10}}&lt;/ref&gt; Most of Go Daddy's early television ads starred former WWE Diva [[Candice Michelle]], in some sort of sexual-related theme. She has been referred to as &quot;Miss GoDaddy.com&quot; or &quot;The Go Daddy Girl&quot; by fans and on WWE television shows, where she also does the &quot;Go Daddy Dance&quot; (twirling her arms around her body while slowly turning) as part of her [[List of professional wrestling terms#G|wrestling gimmick]].

In 2006, Go Daddy began sponsoring [[IndyCar Series|IndyCar]] driver [[Danica Patrick]], who subsequently joined the &quot;Go Daddy Girl&quot; lineup and began playing a prominent role in the company's commercials. In March 2009, Go Daddy announced professional poker player [[Vanessa Rousso]] as the newest Go Daddy Girl.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://news.bluffmagazine.com/vanessa-rousso-newest-go-daddy-girl-2587/ |title=BluffMagazine.com |publisher=News.bluffmagazine.com |date= |accessdate=2009-04-20}}&lt;/ref&gt; Vanessa competed in the Go Daddy sponsored NBC National Heads-Up Poker Championship the same month, finishing second and making history by being the first woman to make it to the finals.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.vegasdeluxe.com/blogs/luxe-life/2009/mar/09/hollywood-and-poker-stars-battle-15-million-payday/ |title=VegasDeluxe.com |publisher=VegasDeluxe.com |date= |accessdate=2009-04-20}}&lt;/ref&gt; Also in March 2009, Go Daddy added pro-golfer [[Anna Rawson]], bringing the Go Daddy Girl spokeswomen count to four. ''She is edgy, she is fun, she is hotter than firecrackers, she is very clever and everything we look for in a Go Daddy Girl,'' CEO Bob Parsons said of Rawson at a news conference in Phoenix.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|author=By Elliot Harris Sun-Times Columnist |url=http://www.suntimes.com/sports/quickhits/1504650,CST-SPT-1hit01.article |title=Chicago Sun Times Online |publisher=Suntimes.com |date=2009-04-01 |accessdate=2009-04-20}}&lt;/ref&gt;  In August 2009, another Go Daddy Girl was announced.  A Russian native, [[Marina Orlova]] is an online linguist, explaining the origin of words on her HotforWords.com Web site.  A New Yorker magazine blogger called her the sexiest [[philologist]] in the world.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.azcentral.com/community/gilbert/articles/2009/08/05/20090805sr-godaddy0806.html |title=AZCentral.com |publisher=AZCentral.com |date=2009-08-05 |accessdate=2009-08-13}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.adrants.com/2009/08/marina-orlova-added-to-stable-of-godaddy.php |title=AdRants.com |publisher=AdRants.com |date=2009-08-04 |accessdate=2009-08-13}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In 2010, Go Daddy announced it is adding &quot;America's Toughest Trainer&quot; [[Jillian Michaels (personal trainer)|Jillian Michaels]] as a Go Daddy Girl. Michaels joins race car driver Danica Patrick as a Go Daddy Girl, a move that CEO Bob Parsons said should attract new customers.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.google.com/hostednews/ap/article/ALeqM5jF2VuXmgNG90ubXWif7HGanhg9fwD9I80AG80 |title=Associated Press |publisher=Associated Press |date=2010-09-14 |accessdate=2010-09-23}}&lt;/ref&gt; Michaels is a well-known celebrity, famous for her role as a health and wellnes coach on NBC's hit show, &quot;The Biggest Loser&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.usatoday.com/money/advertising/2010-09-15-godaddy15_ST_N.htm?csp=obinsite |title=USAToday.com |publisher=USAToday.com |date=2010-09-15 |accessdate=2010-09-23 | first=Bruce | last=Horovitz}}&lt;/ref&gt;

An order was placed{{When|date=August 2010}} with Orange County Choppers for a custom bike to raise contributions for charity and was revealed in Miami, Florida, and featured the models Candice and Danica. The episode was documented by the reality show ''[[American Chopper]]'' episode number 82.&lt;ref name=&quot;amchop82&quot;&gt;Discovery channel: American chopper episode 82&lt;/ref&gt;

===Super Bowl XLII advertisement===
====Development====
On August 13, 2007, Bob Parsons announced that Go Daddy may be sitting out [[Super Bowl XLII]]. &quot;There's always the possibility that we might not be able to get an appropriately edgy advertisement approved,&quot; he said. &quot;All things considered, there's a strong argument for staying on the sidelines this year and taking that Super Bowl advertising money and using it for other opportunities,&quot; he added.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.bobparsons.com/index.php?/archives/149-guid.html Super Bowl XLII. Why GoDaddy might sit this one out.&amp;nbsp;&amp;mdash; Hot Points], Monday, August 13. 2007&lt;/ref&gt;  However, on January 28, 2008, during a telecast of [[World Wrestling Entertainment]]'s [[WWE Raw|RAW]] program on [[USA Network]] in a reverse of field, it was disclosed by Go Daddy spokesperson (and WWE diva) [[Candice Michelle]] that there will be an advertisement during the game, which featured a &quot;behind the scenes&quot; look into that ad. Once again, Go Daddy went through more than a dozen submissions before it was able to get a commercial approved by Fox, the same network that had pulled its Super Bowl XXXIX advertisement before its second scheduled airing. Go Daddy had hoped to broadcast a spot called &quot;Exposure&quot; featuring Go Daddy Girl [[Danica Patrick]] and animatronics beavers. But Fox deemed the spot too racy for prime time television and told Parsons it would not air it unless he removed the word &quot;beaver&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.bobparson.com/SeeSB2008ad.html ] {{Dead link|date=December 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt; Parsons refused, and Go Daddy instead aired a completely different commercial, called &quot;Spot On&quot;. The spot was essentially an &quot;Ad to an Ad&quot; and told viewers to go to the company's Web site to see &quot;Exposure&quot;. &quot;Spot On&quot; aired in the first quarter of Super Bowl XLII, and the company quickly deemed it an enormous success. Go Daddy logged more than one million views of the &quot;Exposure&quot; advertisement before the game ended and reported 1.5 million visits to the GoDaddy.com Web site.
&lt;ref&gt;[https://www.godaddy.com/gdshop/news/release_view.asp?news%5Fitem%5Fid=143&amp;isc=superbowl&amp;app%5Fhdr= In Spite Of Fox&amp;nbsp;&amp;mdash; GoDaddy &quot;Beaver&quot; Builds Tremendous Web Traffic]. February 3, 2008 News Release&lt;/ref&gt;

====Reactions====
The 2008 Go Daddy advertisement has been both maligned and praised. Ad Week's Barbara Lippert described it a &quot;poorly produced scene in a living room where people are gathered to watch the Super Bowl. As we watch them watch, a guy at his computer in the corner of the room drags the crowd over to GoDaddy.com to view the banned ad instead.&quot; But Lippert, like others, also acknowledges the shrewdness of the public relations strategy, saying &quot;it will probably produce a Pavlovian response in getting actual viewers in their own living rooms to do the same.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.adweek.com/aw/magazine/article_display.jsp?vnu_content_id=1000652494 DIY Super Bowl Spots—So Bad, They're Good] - Adweek January 28, 2008 -Barbara Lippert&lt;/ref&gt; Go Daddy's Super Bowl XLI advertisement was criticized in ''[[The New York Times]]'' as being &quot;cheesy&quot;;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|title=Super Bowl Ads of Cartoonish Violence, Perhaps Reflecting Toll of War |last=Elliot |first=Stuart |publisher=The New York Times |url=http://www.nytimes.com/2007/02/05/business/media/05adcol.html?ei=5087&amp;en=4f83a99d6e414b2d&amp;ex=1186290000&amp;adxnnl=1&amp;mkt=bizphoto&amp;adxnnlx=1170812957-TA7YWpU7KaOUJFLOi9gqgw |date=February 5, 2007 |accessdate=2007-02-07 |quote=Another Super Bowl, another cheesy commercial for GoDaddy, the Web site registrar operated by the GoDaddy Group. This time, there was a wild party in the office of the GoDaddy marketing department. &quot;Everybody wants to work in marketing,&quot; a character says with a smirk. Hey, GoDaddy, go get Mommy — maybe she knows how to make a halfway decent Super Bowl spot. Agency: created internally.}}&lt;/ref&gt; in ''[[National Review]]'' as &quot;raunchy, '[[Girls Gone Wild|Girls-Gone-Wild]]' style&quot;;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|title=Not-So-Super Ads |publisher=The National Review |last=Nimouse (pseudonym) |first=Anna |date=February 6, 2007 |accessdate=2007-02-07 |url=http://article.nationalreview.com/?q=ODYyMGY4OTJkODhiYjczMmUwMzMwNThhZTY2ZjE2Yjk= |quote=The GoDaddy commercial that garnered enormous reaction (much negative) last year, with the buxom babe wearing a skimpy T-shirt with the logo across her chest, was tame in comparison to the raunchy, &quot;Girls-Gone-Wild&quot; style of this year's advertisement. The fact that the advertisement caused such a stir last year probably helped determine the content of this one.}}&lt;/ref&gt; and &quot;just sad&quot; by Barbara Lippert in ''[[Adweek]]'', who gave the advertisement a &quot;D&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|url=http://www.adweek.com/aw/search/article_display.jsp?vnu_content_id=1003541503 |title=Barbara Lippert's Critique: The Morning After  |last=Lippert |first=Barbara |date=February 5, 2007 |accessdate=2007-02-07 |publisher=Adweek |archiveurl = http://web.archive.org/web/20070308040456/http://www.adweek.com/aw/search/article_display.jsp?vnu_content_id=1003541503 |archivedate = March 8, 2007}}&lt;/ref&gt; However, Reprise Media, reviewing the success of Super Bowl advertising in getting potential customers online, listed the 2007 commercial as one of only eight &quot;Touchdown&quot;-worthy ads among the day's high-priced advertisers.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.reprisemedia.com/pdf/RepriseMedia_SearchMarketingScorecard_07.pdf |publisher=Reprise Media |title=Search Marketing Scorecard |accessdate=2007-02-07 |format=PDF}}&lt;/ref&gt; IAG Research, which rated the effectiveness of likeability and memorability of the ads, ranked Go Daddy's spot as second for most-recalled.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite press release |url=http://biz.yahoo.com/prnews/070207/nyw124.html?.v=83  |title=IAG Research Announces Top Super Bowl Ad |publisher=IAG Research |date=February 7, 2007 |accessdate=2007-02-07}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Super Bowl XLIII advertisements===
====Development====
Go Daddy purchased two Super Bowl spots for different commercials, both of which NBC approved. The commercials featured Go Daddy Girl and IndyCar Series driver [[Danica Patrick]]. In &quot;Shower&quot;, Danica takes a shower with Simona Fusco Stratten as three college students control the women's maneuvers from a computer. &quot;Baseball&quot; is a spoof of the steroids scandal.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|last=Reisinger |first=Don |url=http://news.cnet.com/8301-17939_109-10154867-2.html?tag=mncol/ |title=CNet.com |publisher=News.cnet.com |date=2009-02-02 |accessdate=2009-04-20}}&lt;/ref&gt; While &quot;Shower&quot; won Go Daddy's online vote, &quot;Baseball&quot; was the most popular of the Super Bowl. Both helped increase domain registrations 110 percent above 2008 post Super Bowl levels.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|last=Larson |first=Jane |url=http://www.azcentral.com/arizonarepublic/business/articles/2009/02/02/20090202biz-godaddy0203.html |title=GoDaddy a Super Bowl star |publisher=Azcentral.com |date=2009-02-03 |accessdate=2009-04-20}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|url=http://www.bizjournals.com/phoenix/stories/2009/02/02/daily6.html |title=GoDaddy scores with dual Super Bowl ads - Phoenix Business Journal: |publisher=Bizjournals.com |date=2009-02-02 |accessdate=2009-04-20 |first=Patrick |last=O'Grady}}&lt;/ref&gt; Go Daddy posted Internet-only versions of its commercials during the game. These are extended versions with more risque content.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|last=Boswell |first=Jeffrey |url=http://www.sports-central.org/sports/2009/02/06/sports_qa_super_bowl_edition.php/ |title=Sports-Central.org |publisher=Sports-Central.org |date=2009-02-06 |accessdate=2009-04-20}}&lt;/ref&gt;

====Reactions====
&quot;Baseball&quot; was the most watched Super Bowl commercial according to TiVo, Inc.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|author=4:15 p.m. ET |url=http://www.msnbc.msn.com/id/28978813/ |title=MSN.com |publisher=MSNBC |date=2009-02-02 |accessdate=2009-04-20}}&lt;/ref&gt; According to comScore, Go Daddy ranked first in advertiser Web site follow-through.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|author=The Earthtimes |url=http://www.earthtimes.org/articles/show/doritos-registers-highest-brand-improvement,706459.shtml/ |title=EarthTimes.org |publisher=EarthTimes.org |date=2009-02-05 |accessdate=2009-04-20}}&lt;/ref&gt; Rob Goulding, head of [[business-to-business]] markets for Google, offered an in-depth analysis of Super Bowl spots that aired during Sunday's championship game. He said the most successful were multichannel-oriented, driving viewers to Web sites and &quot;focusing on conversion as never before.&quot; Go Daddy experienced significant Web traffic and a strong &quot;hangover&quot; effect of viewer interest in the days that followed due to a provocative &quot;teaser&quot; advertisement pointing to the Web, Goulding said.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.btobonline.com/apps/pbcs.dll/article?AID=/20090209/FREE/302099981/1109/FREE/ |title=BtoBOnline.com |publisher=BtoBOnline.com |date=2009-02-09 |accessdate=2009-04-20}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===IndyCar===
In 2010, Go Daddy was again the presenting sponsor for the live race broadcast and the primary sponsor for IndyCar driver Danica Patrick. And, for the first time ever, Go Daddy broadcast user-generated commercials as part of its advertising strategy.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://nysportsjournalism.squarespace.com/daddy-does-indy-51110/2010/5/11/consumer-generated-ads-danica-patrick-drive-go-daddy-into-in.html |title=nysportsjournalism.squarespace.com |publisher=nysportsjournalism.squarespace.com |date=2010-05-11 |accessdate=2010-07-20}}&lt;/ref&gt; The top three winners of Go Daddy's &quot;Create Your Own Commercial&quot; contest had their ads air during the race broadcast.  Creators of the first place advertisement &quot;Go Momma&quot; received $100,000 in cash.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.thewhir.com/web-hosting-news/060110_Web_Host_Go_Daddy_Unveils_User_Generated_Commercial_Contest_Winner |title=TheWhir.com |publisher=David Hamilton |date=2010-06-01 |accessdate=2010-07-20}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.dotweekly.com/godaddy-com-video-contest-finalist-revealed |title=DotWeekly.com |publisher=DotWeekly.com |date=2010-05-17 |accessdate=2010-07-20}}&lt;/ref&gt;
The commercial features a mother who creates a Web site with Go Daddy in order to save time and still keep in touch with her family. In the thirty-second story, she posts her cherished family recipes on her Web site, even though she's not tech-savvy. The grand prize winner of the user-generated content contest is not only cleavage-free and smarm-free, it also celebrates an empowered woman of a certain age who uses Go Daddy to help her solve a family problem.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|url=http://mediadecoder.blogs.nytimes.com/2010/05/30/go-daddy-and-sin-no-more/?src=busln |title=Media Decoder Blog |publisher=Stuart Elliott |date=2010-05-30 |accessdate=2010-07-20}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In 2009, for a third consecutive year, Go Daddy was the presenting sponsor of the [[Indianapolis 500]] race broadcast on ABC.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.wtov9.com/sports/19532289/detail.html |title=WTOV9.com |publisher=Associated Press |date=2009-05-22 |accessdate=2009-06-02}}&lt;/ref&gt; Go Daddy also debuted a new commercial called &quot;Speeding&quot; during the Indy 500.  The commercial features Danica Patrick getting pulled over for speeding by a female cop wanting to be a &quot;Go Daddy Girl&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.edmunds.com/insideline/do/News/articleId=148927 |title=Edmunds.com |publisher=Edmunds.com |date=2009-05-26 |accessdate=2009-06-02}}&lt;/ref&gt; The advertisement teases to an edgier Web version that drove a 570% traffic increase to GoDaddy.com.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|url=http://www.usatoday.com/sports/motor/2009-05-27-danica-patrick-future_N.htm |title=USAToday.com |publisher=USAToday.com |date=2009-05-27 |accessdate=2009-06-02 | first=Gary | last=Graves}}&lt;/ref&gt;

For the Las Vegas race in 2011, Go Daddy launched the Go Daddy IndyCar Challenge where the only participent, driver Dan Wheldon, would have won $2.5m each for himself and randomly selected fan, Ann Babenco, if he won the race, starting from last place. A 15 car pile up 12 laps into the race injured 4 drivers and killed Wheldon.&amp;nbsp;&lt;ref name=GoDaddy&gt;
[http://webcache.googleusercontent.com/search?q=cache:xiGXy5ChJ_0J:indycarworldchampionships.com/Sweepstakes/+%22http://indycarworldchampionships.com/Sweepstakes/%22&amp;cd=1&amp;hl=en&amp;ct=clnk&amp;gl=uk&amp;client=firefox-a Go Daddy IndyCar Challenge]
&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=njonline&gt;
New Jersey On-Line - [http://www.nj.com/motorsports/index.ssf/2011/10/dan_wheldons_death_hits_home_with_high_bridge_family.html IndyCar driver Dan Wheldon's death hits home with High Bridge family], October 16 2011
&lt;/ref&gt;

===Super Bowl XLIV advertisements===
====Development====
In September 2009, Go Daddy announced it would be returning advertisers in the 2010 Super Bowl, purchasing two spots.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.azcentral.com/community/scottsdale/articles/2009/09/15/20090915sr-godaddy0916.html |title=AZCentral.com |publisher=AZCentral.com |date=2009-09-15 |accessdate=2010-03-17}}&lt;/ref&gt; The commercials &quot;Spa&quot; and &quot;News&quot; starred Go Daddy Girl and racecar driver Danica Patrick. In &quot;Spa,&quot; Patrick is getting a lavish massage when the masseuse breaks into a spontaneous Go Daddy Girl audition.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.tmcnet.com/usubmit/2010/02/06/4608753.htm |title=TMCNet.com |publisher=TMCNet.com |date=2010-02-06 |accessdate=2010-03-17}}&lt;/ref&gt; The second advertisement called &quot;News&quot; has news anchors conducting a 'gotcha' interview with Go Daddy Girl Danica Patrick about commercials known for being too hot for television.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.i4u.com/article30496.html |title=I4U.com |publisher=I4U.com |date=2010-02-02 |accessdate=2010-03-17}}&lt;/ref&gt;

====Reactions====
According to Akamai, there was a large spike in Internet traffic late in the fourth quarter of the game.  This spike was tied to Go Daddy's &quot;News&quot; advertisement airing. CEO Bob Parsons said Go Daddy had &quot;a tremendous surge in Web traffic, sustained the spike, converted new customers and shot overall sales off the chart.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.datacenterknowledge.com/archives/2010/02/08/go-daddy-ad-drives-huge-traffic-spike/ |title=DataCenterKnowledge.com |publisher=DataCenterKnowledge.com |date=2010-02-08 |accessdate=2010-03-17}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|url=http://www.usatoday.com/money/advertising/admeter/2010admeter.htm |title=USA Today AdMeter |publisher=USAToday.com |date=2010-02-08 |accessdate=2010-03-17 | first=Bruce | last=Horovitz}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===NASCAR and JR Motorsports===
A fourth spokesman, with commercials which are not sexually suggestive, has appeared in ads starting in 2008. These advertisements, which air in [[NASCAR]] broadcasts, feature NASCAR Nationwide Series owner [[Dale Earnhardt, Jr.]], who designed and owns and occasionally drives the #5 [[JR Motorsports]] [[Chevrolet]] in the series.  Go Daddy's sponsorship of the team includes five races in 2008 with [[Mark Martin (NASCAR)|Mark Martin]] and [[Ron Fellows]] (who won the [[NAPA Auto Parts 200]] in the Go Daddy Chevrolet), sharing duties in the races with Earnhardt Jr. Junior designed the paint scheme for the car, which in true Earnhardt tradition is dominated by black with green and orange (the colors of Go Daddy). GoDaddy.com also has sponsored the [[Randy Moss Motorsports]] (aka Morgan-Dollar Motorsports) truck when [[Landon Cassill]] drives it, both in the original #46 and later as #81, as Cassill is a Hendrick Motorsports Developmental Driver, which includes selected [[Nationwide Series]] races in Earnhardt's #5 car.

Go Daddy has also sponsored [[Brad Keselowski]] in the #25 for [[Hendrick Motorsports]] on a limited basis in the [[Sprint Cup]] series (owing to the &quot;part-time rookie exemption&quot; to a four-car limit). After a successful 2008 season, Go Daddy is expanding its 2009 NASCAR sponsorship with the [[JR Motorsports]] organisation, sponsoring 20 Nationwide Series races as primary sponsor, split between the #5 and #88 teams.  The #88 deal gave Keselowski a full 35-race NASCAR Nationwide Series sponsorship for 2009 split with [[Delphi]] and [[Unilever]].  Go Daddy will also be the primary sponsor for seven races in the [[Sprint Cup Series]] with Keselowski driving.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.hendrickmotorsports.com/news_detail.asp?id=2212&amp;bhcp=1/ |title=Hendrick Motorsports 2009 Sponsor Announcement |publisher=Hendrickmotorsports.com |date=2009-01-07 |accessdate=2009-04-20}}&lt;/ref&gt; GoDaddy.com signed a one-year deal with [[Darlington Raceway]] to sponsor the 53rd Annual [[Rebel 500]], the fifth-oldest race on the Sprint Cup circuit.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|author=6 days ago |url=http://www.google.com/hostednews/ap/article/ALeqM5gyxPWnsXMCR7Of3cOXO-eGhIwCdQD97HKFL81 |title=Associated Press |publisher=Google.com |date= |accessdate=2009-04-20}}{{Dead link|date=July 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|last=Fogle |first=Adam |url=http://www.palmettoscoop.com/2009/04/14/godaddy-gets-darlington-sponsorship/ |title=PalmettoScoop.com |publisher=PalmettoScoop.com |date=2009-04-14 |accessdate=2009-04-20}} {{Dead link|date=September 2010|bot=H3llBot}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|last=Iacobelli |first=Pete |url=http://www.usatoday.com/sports/motor/2009-04-13-1994942161_x.htm |title=USAToday.com |publisher=USAToday.com |date=2009-04-13 |accessdate=2009-04-20}}&lt;/ref&gt;  Keselowski got his third Nationwide victory at Dover - his first in the #88 GoDaddy.com Chevrolet.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.motorsport.com/news/article.asp?ID=330134 |title=Motorsport.com |publisher=Motorsport.com |date=2009-05-30 |accessdate=2009-06-02}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.nationalpost.com/sports/story.html?id=1647415 |title=NationalPost.com |publisher=NationalPost.com |date=2009-05-30 |accessdate=2009-06-02}} {{Dead link|date=September 2010|bot=H3llBot}}&lt;/ref&gt;  In the same season, Keselowski scored a second Nationwide victory in the #88 GoDaddy.com [[Chevrolet]] at the first ever [[NASCAR]] race at [[Iowa Speedway]]And then at Michigan.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.stltoday.com/stltoday/sports/stories.nsf/autoracing/story/0FD49FDC3266787D86257606000978CE?OpenDocument |title=STLToday.com |publisher=STLToday.com |date=2009-08-02 |accessdate=2009-08-13}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.nascar.com/2009/news/headlines/bg/08/01/post.race.bkeselowski.wins.iowa/index.html |title=NASCAR.com |publisher=NASCAR.com |date=2009-08-03 |accessdate=2009-08-13}}&lt;/ref&gt;

For 2010, the Hendrick/Go Daddy association will continue;[[Danica Patrick]] will drive a 12 race schedule in the #7 GoDaddy.com Chevrolet for JR Motorsports, and Mark Martin's #5 team will now have Go Daddy as its primary sponsor for the majority of the season.
&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.dalejr.com/#news/view/146 |title=DaleJR.com |publisher=DaleJR.com |date=2009-12-08 |accessdate=2010-03-17}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|url=http://www.usatoday.com/sports/motor/nascar/2009-12-15-danica-patrick-cover_N.htm?csp=34 |title=USAToday.com |publisher=USAToday.com |date=2009-12-17 |accessdate=2010-03-17 | first=Nate | last=Ryan}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Philanthropy===
In the last few years, Go Daddy has made many donations to local, regional, national, and international charities, including those that focus on [[domestic violence]], [[child abuse]], disabled children, teenage homelessness, Parkinson's research, breast cancer, and animal shelters. Major recipients of Go Daddy contributions over the past several years include the Juvenile Diabetes Research Foundation, Phoenix Children's Hospital, the Arizona Humane Society, the Phoenix Zoo, Chrysalis, HomeBase Youth Services, and the Salvation Army. Go Daddy's employees have also participated in a series of events to raise money for charitable causes. In 2009 Go Daddy donated $50,000 to the Lincoln Family Downtown YMCA in Arizona when the organization requested only $1,000.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.azcentral.com/arizonarepublic/local/articles/2009/07/08/20090708phxbriefs0709.html |title=AZCentral.com |publisher=AZCentral.com |date=2009-07-09 |accessdate=2009-08-13}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.webhostdir.com/news/showNews.aspx?ID=33132 |title=WebHostDir.com |publisher=WebHostDir.com |date=2009-06-10 |accessdate=2009-08-13}}&lt;/ref&gt;  Go Daddy also participated in the 11th Annual Arizona Humane Society Pet Telethon as the title sponsor.  The company matched online contributions and donated a check for $100,000.&lt;ref name=&quot;xxx&quot; &gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.thewhir.com/web-hosting-news/081009_Go_Daddy_Donates_100K_to_AZ_Humane_Society |title=TheWhir.com |publisher=TheWhir.com |date=2009-08-10 |accessdate=2009-08-13}}&lt;/ref&gt; In December 2009 at Go Daddy's annual Holiday Party, CEO Bob Parsons and Danica Patrick announced that Go Daddy would be donating $500,000 to the Phoenix-based UMOM New Day Center to fund the Danica Patrick Go Daddy.com Domestic Violence Center.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.azcentral.com/news/articles/2009/12/15/20091215sr-bigbash1216.html |title=AZCentral.com |publisher=AZCentral.com |date=2009-12-15 |accessdate=2010-03-17}}&lt;/ref&gt; In November 2008, more than 700 Go Daddy employees participated in the Juvenile Diabetes Research Foundation's Walk to Cure Diabetes in Tempe, AZ. Other Go Daddy employee efforts have included the annual Toys for Tots drive, as well as donations to St. Mary's Food Bank during the holiday season.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.thewhir.com/web-hosting-news/123008_Go_Daddy_Donates_%241.7M_to_Charities/ |title=TheWhir.com |publisher=TheWhir.com |date=2008-12-30 |accessdate=2009-04-20}}&lt;/ref&gt; In April 2006, the company donated $10,000 to the [[OpenSSH]] development program, which is managed by [[OpenBSD]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite pressrelease |url=http://www.thehostingnews.com/article2217.html |title=GoDaddy.com Donates $10K to Open Source Development Project }}&lt;/ref&gt; They have also donated $10,000 in March 2006 to Perverted-Justice.com in which volunteers pose online as minors to find child predators and report them to law enforcement.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite pressrelease |url=http://www.hostreview.com/news/news/060331GODADDY.html |title=Radio GoDaddy Rebranded to Life Online(TM) With Bob Parsons}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===GoDaddy.com Bowl===

Starting in 2010, Go Daddy is the sponsor of the [[GoDaddy.com Bowl]], a post season college football bowl game played in [[Mobile, Alabama]].  The game was previously known as the [[GMAC Bowl]].  The game currently matches teams from the [[Sun Belt Conference]] and the [[Mid-American Conference]], and will through 2013.

==Controversies==
===Suspension of Seclists.org===
&lt;!-- This section is linked from [[Seclists.org]] --&gt;
On January 24, 2007, Go Daddy deactivated the domain of computer security site, Seclists.org, taking 250,000 pages of security content offline.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|url=http://news.com.com/2100-1025-6153607.html?tag=tb |title=GoDaddy pulls security site after MySpace complaints |publisher=CNET's News.com |date=January 25, 2007 |last=McCullagh |first=Declan}}&lt;/ref&gt; The shutdown resulted from a complaint from [[MySpace]] to Go Daddy regarding 56,000 user names and passwords posted a week earlier to the full-disclosure mailing list and archived on the Seclists.org site as well as many other Web sites. Seclists.org administrator [[Gordon Lyon]], who goes by the handle &quot;Fyodor&quot;, provided logs to CNET News.com showing Go Daddy de-activated the domain 52 seconds after leaving him a voicemail, and he had to go to great lengths to get the site reactivated. Go Daddy general counsel Christine Jones stated that Go Daddy's terms of service &quot;reserves the right to terminate your access to the services at any time, without notice, for any reason whatsoever.&quot; The site seclists.org is now hosted with [[Linode]]. The suspension of seclists.org led Lyon to create NoDaddy.com, a [[Consumer activism|consumer activist]] web site where dissatisfied Go Daddy customers and [[whistleblower]]s from Go Daddy's staff share their experiences.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|last=Poulsen |first=Kevin |url=http://blog.wired.com/27bstroke6/2007/01/godaddy_meet_no.html |title=GoDaddy, Meet NoDaddy &amp;#124; Threat Level from Wired.com |publisher=Blog.wired.com |date=2007-01-29 |accessdate=2009-04-20}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|last=Newitz |first=Annalee |url=http://www.alternet.org/story/47669/ |title=The Self-Appointed Censors of GoDaddy |publisher=AlterNet |date=2007-02-05 |accessdate=2009-04-20}}&lt;/ref&gt; The No Daddy domain has since been sold to Go Daddy.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.theregister.co.uk/2011/07/12/godaddy_shuts_down_nodaddy/&lt;/ref&gt;

===Deletion of FamilyAlbum.com===
On December 19, 2006, Go Daddy received a third party complaint of invalid domain contact information in the [[WHOIS]] database for the domain FamilyAlbum.com.&lt;ref name=PCOLDomainnamewire&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://domainnamewire.com/2007/02/27/godaddy-deletes-domain-name-for-inaccurate-email-address/ |archiveurl=http://web.archive.org/web/20070302072828/http://domainnamewire.com/2007/02/27/godaddy-deletes-domain-name-for-inaccurate-email-address/ |archivedate=2007-03-02 |title=Domain Name Wire. &quot;GoDaddy Deletes Domain Name for Inaccurate Email Address.&quot; February 27, 2007. |publisher=Web.archive.org |date= |accessdate=2009-04-20}}&lt;/ref&gt; Go Daddy wrote a letter to the owner of FamilyAlbum.com saying, &quot;Whenever we receive a complaint, we are required by ICANN regulations to initiate an investigation as to whether the contact data displaying in the WHOIS database is valid data or not...&lt;ref name=PCOLDomainnamewire/&gt; On 12/19/2006 we sent a notice to you at the admin/tech contact email address and the account email address informing you of invalid data in breach of the domain registration agreement and advising you to update the information or risk cancellation of the domain. The contact information was not updated within the specified period of time and we canceled the domain.&quot;&lt;ref name=PCOLDomainnamewire/&gt; The editor of &quot;Domain Name Wire&quot; said that since domain names are valuable it was reasonable to expect that the registrar would try to contact the domain owner by phone or postal mail.&lt;ref name=PCOLDomainnamewire/&gt; On February 28, 2007, Go Daddy offered to get the domain name back for the previous owner if he would indemnify Go Daddy from legal action by the new registrant.&lt;ref name=PCOLDomainnamewire2&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://domainnamewire.com/2007/02/28/godaddy-responds-to-deletion-over-invalid-email-address/ |title=Domain Name Wire. &quot;GoDaddy Responds to Deletion Over Invalid Email Address.&quot; February 28, 2007. |publisher=Web.archive.org |date= |accessdate=2009-04-20 |archiveurl=http://web.archive.org/web/20070302072506/domainnamewire.com/2007/02/28/godaddy-responds-to-deletion-over-invalid-email-address/ |archivedate=2007-03-02}}&lt;/ref&gt; Go Daddy stated that the new owner paid $18.99 for the domain, the price of a backorder, not a regular registration.&lt;ref name=PCOLDomainnamewire2/&gt; On November 2, 2007, Domain Name Wire reported that it appears that Go Daddy no longer cancels domains for invalid WHOIS.&lt;ref name=PCOLDomainnamewire11022007/&gt; The editor on Domain Name Wire received a message from a reader who is trying to acquire a domain with obviously false WHOIS information.&lt;ref name=PCOLDomainnamewire11022007/&gt; The message from Go Daddy said, &quot;The domain has been suspended due to invalid WHOIS. The domain will remain in suspension through expiration, including the registry's redemption period, unless the owner updates the contact information before that time.&quot;&lt;ref name=PCOLDomainnamewire11022007&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://domainnamewire.com/2007/11/02/has-godaddy-done-a-180-on-invalid-whois/ |title=Domain Name Wire. &quot;Has GoDaddy Done a 180 on Invalid Whois?&quot; November 2, 2007 |publisher=Domainnamewire.com |date= |accessdate=2009-04-20}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Shutdown of RateMyCop.com===
On March 11, 2008, Go Daddy shut down RateMyCop.com&amp;nbsp;&amp;mdash; a [[RateMyProfessors.com|RateMyProfessors]]-type site where people would comment on their interactions with law enforcement officers. Some reports said there have been complaints from police. A Go Daddy spokeperson said, &quot;Basically, he was paying for compact car, when he really needed a semi-truck.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|last=Poulsen |first=Kevin |url=http://blog.wired.com/27bstroke6/2008/03/godaddy-silence.html |title=GoDaddy Silences Police-Watchdog Site RateMyCop.com - Update &amp;#124; Threat Level from Wired.com |publisher=Blog.wired.com |date=2008-03-11 |accessdate=2009-04-20}}&lt;/ref&gt; The registrar for the name, [[Name.com]], continued to allow the DNS to resolve, and is now hosted at Lunarpages. Go Daddy stated the reason for shutting down the Web site had nothing to do with censorship or complaints but that the site was receiving too many simultaneous connections.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|last=Nussenbaum |first=Evelyn |url=http://valleywag.com/367201/go-daddy-is-fightin-mad |title=Censorship: GoDaddy is fightin' mad |publisher=Valleywag.com |date=2008-03-12 |accessdate=2009-04-20}}&lt;/ref&gt; In 2006 Go Daddy locked access to the Irish Web site RateYourSolicitor.com after the Irish high court issued an order to remove offensive material about a barrister from the site.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|author=Trailer park |url=http://www.independent.ie/national-news/american-company-blocks-off-access-to-rate-your-lawyer-site-78642.html |title=American company blocks off access to 'rate your lawyer' site |publisher=Independent.ie |date=2006-09-16 |accessdate=2009-04-20}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Animal rights===
In 2011, [[animal rights groups]] including [[PETA]] complained&lt;ref&gt;http://animals.nationalgeographic.com/animals/mammals/african-elephant/&lt;/ref&gt; when a video of Go Daddy CEO [[Bob Parsons]] shooting and killing an elephant at night in [[Zimbabwe]] was made by Parsons and posted on his personal blog.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news| url=http://latimesblogs.latimes.com/technology/2011/04/peta-closes-godaddy-account-after-ceo-shoots-elephant.html | work=Los Angeles Times | title=Technology}}&lt;/ref&gt; In response, Parsons stated &quot;The tribal authorities request that I and others like me, patrol the fields before and during the harvest&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;ShowBizSpy&quot;&gt;{{cite web
 |year = 2011
 |month = March
 |title = GoDaddy CEO Embroiled in Controversy!  Bob Parsons Defends Elephant Murder!
 |work = Show Biz Spy
 |url = http://www.showbizspy.com/article/229616/go-daddy-ceo-embroiled-in-controversy-bob-parsons-defends-elephant-murder.html
 |access date - 2011 -30-03
}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;http://abcnews.go.com/Business/daddy-ceo-bob-parsons-africa-elephant-hunt-video/story?id=13279206&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;http://www.wired.com/epicenter/2011/04/godaddy-media-stampede/&lt;/ref&gt; PETA said they would be closing their account with Go Daddy.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Go Daddy CEO Named ‘Scummiest’.|url=http://www.peta.org/b/thepetafiles/archive/2011/03/29/go-daddy-ceo-named-scummiest-of-the-year.aspx|work=Go Daddy CEO Named ‘Scummiest’}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Domain Buy Practices===
Customers visiting Go Daddy's site to register a domain that has already been claimed may be directed to Go Daddy's Domain Buy Service. The Domain Buy service does not mean that a domain has been purchased; only that Go Daddy will serve as broker for the domain.&lt;ref&gt;http://help.godaddy.com/article/1699&lt;/ref&gt; In effect, Go Daddy Domain Buy customers are paying only to receive a price. Go Daddy has faced criticism that this practice may be misleading to some.&lt;ref&gt;http://blogigs.com/step-by-step-guide-to-buying-a-pre-owned-domain-part-one/&lt;/ref&gt;

===Go Daddy buys No Daddy===
On July 12, 2011, an article in the [[The Register]] reported that gripe site No Daddy was purchased by Go Daddy shortly after [[Bob Parsons]]' sale of the company. The Site had returned a top 5 result on [[Google]] for a search for Go Daddy.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|last=Murphy|first=Kevin|title=Go Daddy no-no means No Daddy is no-go|url=http://www.theregister.co.uk/2011/07/12/godaddy_shuts_down_nodaddy/|accessdate=12 July 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Implementation of Selective DNS Blackout policy===
In July, 2011, Go Daddy introduced a policy of blocking DNS queries from some outside DNS servers, in order to prevent other DNS queries from being too slow. Among other things, this prevents some [[bots]] from visiting websites, forcing some search engines to exclude domains hosted with Go Daddy. This policy has an impact on search engine ranking for various Go Daddy customer who have multiple domains with different registrars. GoDaddy has refused to comment on the policy or the perception that their servers can not handle the load or they are giving preference to their platinum level customers. It has also interfered with projects that collect Internet statistics.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last=Perry|first=R. Scott|title=GoDaddy's New &quot;Selective DNS Blackouts&quot; Policy|url=http://rscott.org/dns/GoDaddy_Selective_DNS_Blackouts.htm|accessdate=1 September 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

On August 16, after the policy was introduced, it appears that GoDaddy blocked recursive DNS servers in China, preventing Chinese visitors from reaching websites using Go Daddy DNS hosting.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last=Reid|first=Gerry|title=China Blocks GoDaddy|url=http://techpus.com/2011/china-blocks-godaddy/|publisher=Techpus|accessdate=10 September 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Canceled IPO==
On April 12, 2006, Marketwatch reported that GoDaddy.com, Inc., had hired [[Lehman Brothers]] to manage an initial stock offering that could raise more than $100 million and value the company at several times that amount.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.marketwatch.com/News/Story/Story.aspx?guid=%7BBE70F068%2D321F%2D4777%2D8640%2DECAACDBA077D%7D&amp;dist=WSJfeed&amp;siteid=WSJ&lt;/ref&gt; On May 12, 2006, Go Daddy filed an S-1 registration statement prior to an initial public offering.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.azcentral.com/community/gilbert/articles/0517gr-godaddy0517Z12.html |title=GoDaddy makes name for itself growing in Gilbert, going public |publisher=Azcentral.com |date=2006-05-17 |accessdate=2009-04-20}}&lt;/ref&gt; On August 8, 2006, [[Bob Parsons]], CEO of Go Daddy, announced that he had withdrawn the company's [[IPO]] filing.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.bobparsons.me/WhyIPOPulled.html |title=– A blog by Go Daddy CEO and founder Bob Parsons |publisher=Bobparsons.me |date= |accessdate=2009-04-20}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==See also==
*[[Domains by Proxy]]
*[[Warren Adelman]]

==References==
{{Reflist|2}}

==External links==
*[http://www.godaddy.com Go Daddy] official web site
*[http://www.bobparsons.me/index.html Go Daddy Founder and CEO Bob Parsons' personal blog]

{{Coord|33.617409|-111.90477|region:US_type:landmark|display=title}}

{{WebManTools}}

[[Category:Companies established in 1997]]
[[Category:Companies based in Scottsdale, Arizona]]
[[Category:Certificate authorities]]
[[Category:Domain registrars]]
[[Category:Go Daddy| ]]
[[Category:Web hosting]]

[[de:Go Daddy]]
[[es:Go Daddy]]
[[fr:Go Daddy]]
[[lv:Go Daddy]]
[[ml:ഗോ ഡാഡി]]
[[ja:Go Daddy]]
[[ru:Go Daddy]]
[[tr:Go Daddy]]
[[zh:Go Daddy]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
