<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="10219813" ns="0" title="List of Primeval characters"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Multiple issues
|in-universe=November 2010
|original research=January 2011
|primarysources=November 2010
}}
{{CompactTOC8
|name      = ''[[Primeval]]'' characters
|side      = yes
|center    = yes
|align     = left
|nobreak   = yes
|top       = yes
|num       = no
|sym       = no
|seealso   = no
|refs      = yes
|notes     = no
|extlinks  = yes
}}
[[File:Primeval cast.jpg|thumb|300px|right|The main characters of ''Primeval'' (Series 5)&lt;br/&gt; (l-r) Captain Becker, Jess Parker, Matt Anderson, Abby Maitland and Connor Temple]]
This is a '''list of characters in the [[ITV]] [[science fiction]] television series ''[[Primeval]]''''', including supporting characters.

The series originally features a cast of five main characters plus supporting cast who investigate time anomalies for the British government. The series 1 cast is made up of [[Douglas Henshall]] as [[#Nick Cutter|Professor Nick Cutter]], [[James Murray (English actor)|James Murray]] as [[#Stephen Hart|Stephen Hart]], [[Andrew-Lee Potts]] as [[#Connor Temple|Connor Temple]], [[Lucy Brown]] as [[#Claudia Brown|Claudia Brown]] and [[Hannah Spearritt]] as [[#Abby Maitland|Abby Maitland]], with [[Juliet Aubrey]] as [[#Helen Cutter|Helen Cutter]], [[Ben Miller]] as [[#James Lester|James Lester]] and [[Mark Wakeling]] as [[#Tom Ryan|Captain Tom Ryan]]. In the final episode of Series 1, Captain Tom Ryan is killed off, and Claudia Brown disappears. The rest of the cast carries over into Series 2. Lucy Brown plays a new character, [[#Jenny Lewis|Jenny Lewis]], a savvy PR person and a doppelgänger of Claudia, but unlike her, she has no romantic attachment to Cutter and resents him referring to her as &quot;Claudia&quot;. [[Karl Theobald]] as [[#Oliver Leek|Oliver Leek]], [[Naomi Bentley]] as [[#Caroline Steel|Caroline Steel]] and Tim Faraday as &quot;[[#The Cleaner|The Cleaner]]&quot; support. Stephen and Oliver Leek are killed off in the final episode of Series 2, and Caroline leaves. Series 3 sees the introduction of [[Laila Rouass]] as [[#Sarah Page|Sarah Page]], [[Ben Mansfield]] as [[#Captain Becker|Captain Becker]] and [[Jason Flemyng]] as [[#Danny Quinn|Danny Quinn]]. In the third episode Nick Cutter is killed, with Danny Quinn replacing him as team leader. Jenny Lewis leaves two episodes later. And in the finale of Series 3, Helen Cutter is knocked off a cliff by a Raptor. 
Sarah Page was killed offscreen prior to Series 4, and Danny Quinn returned only in the finale of Series 4. Joining the cast was [[Ciarán McMenamin]] as [[#Matt Anderson|Matt Anderson]], the new team leader, [[Ruth Kearney]] as [[#Jess Parker|Jess Parker]], team coordinator, [[Alexander Siddig]] as [[#Philip Burton|Philip Burton]], industrialist, who is put in charge of the ARC, [[Anton Lesser]] as [[#Gideon|Gideon]], [[Ruth Bradley]] as [[#Emily Merchant|Emily Merchant]] and Jonathyn Byrne as [[#Ethan Dobrowski|Ethan Dobrowski]].

As of the end of Series 5, the only original cast members remaining are [[Andrew-Lee Potts]], [[Hannah Spearritt]] and [[Ben Miller]].

== Character appearances ==
&lt;!-- &quot;Last&quot; appearance can be &quot;current&quot; while the show is airing, otherwise the last ep of the series they appear in. --&gt;
&lt;onlyinclude&gt;&lt;!-- transcluded to main Primeval article--&gt;
{| class= &quot;wikitable sortable&quot;
|-
! Character name !! Actor !! First appearance !! Last appearance
|-
| [[List of Primeval characters#Nick Cutter|Nick Cutter]] || [[Douglas Henshall]] || style= &quot;text-align: center; top&quot; | [[Episode 1 (Primeval)|1.1]] || style= &quot;text-align: center; top&quot; | 3.3
|-
| [[List of Primeval characters#Stephen Hart|Stephen Hart]] || [[James Murray (English actor)|James Murray]] || style= &quot;text-align: center; top&quot; | [[Episode 1 (Primeval)|1.1]] || style= &quot;text-align: center; top&quot; | 2.7
|-
| [[List of Primeval characters#Helen Cutter|Helen Cutter]] || [[Juliet Aubrey]] || style= &quot;text-align: center; top&quot; | [[Episode 1 (Primeval)|1.1]] || style= &quot;text-align: center; top&quot; | 3.10
|-
| [[List of Primeval characters#Connor Temple|Connor Temple]] || [[Andrew Lee Potts]] || style= &quot;text-align: center; top&quot; | [[Episode 1 (Primeval)|1.1]] || style= &quot;text-align: center; top&quot; | [[List of Primeval episodes#ep36|5.6]] 
|-
| [[List of Primeval characters#Abby Maitland|Abby Maitland]] || [[Hannah Spearritt]] || style= &quot;text-align: center; top&quot; | [[Episode 1 (Primeval)|1.1]] || style= &quot;text-align: center; top&quot; | [[List of Primeval episodes#ep36|5.6]] 
|-
| [[List of Primeval characters#Claudia Brown|Claudia Brown]] || [[Lucy Brown]] || style= &quot;text-align: center; top&quot; | [[Episode 1 (Primeval)|1.1]] || style= &quot;text-align: center; top&quot; | 1.6
|-
|[[#James Lester|James Lester]] || [[Ben Miller]] || style= &quot;text-align: center; top&quot; | [[Episode 1 (Primeval)|1.1]] || style= &quot;text-align: center; top&quot; | [[List of Primeval episodes#ep36|5.6]] 
|-
| [[List of Primeval characters#Tom Ryan|Captain Tom Ryan]] || [[Mark Wakeling]] || style= &quot;text-align: center; top&quot; | [[Episode 1 (Primeval)|1.1]] || style= &quot;text-align: center; top&quot; | 1.6
|-
| [[List of Primeval characters#Tom|Tom]] || Jake Curran || style= &quot;text-align: center; top&quot; | [[List of Primeval episodes#ep2|1.2]] || style= &quot;text-align: center; top&quot; | 1.4
|-
| [[List of Primeval characters#Duncan|Duncan]] || [[James Bradshaw (actor)|James Bradshaw]] || style= &quot;text-align: center; top&quot; | [[List of Primeval episodes#ep2|1.2]] || style= &quot;text-align: center; top&quot; | 4.2
|-
| [[List of Primeval characters#Oliver Leek|Oliver Leek]] || [[Karl Theobald]] || style= &quot;text-align: center; top&quot; | [[List of Primeval episodes#ep7|2.1]] || style= &quot;text-align: center; top&quot; | 2.7
|-
| [[List of Primeval characters#Jenny Lewis|Jenny Lewis]] || [[Lucy Brown]] || style= &quot;text-align: center; top&quot; | [[List of Primeval episodes#ep7|2.1]] || style= &quot;text-align: center; top&quot; | 4.6
|-
| [[List of Primeval characters#The Cleaner|The Cleaner]] || Tim Faraday || style= &quot;text-align: center; top&quot; | [[List of Primeval episodes#ep7|2.1]]|| style= &quot;text-align: center; top&quot; | 3.3
|-
| [[List of Primeval characters#Caroline Steel|Caroline Steel]] || [[Naomi Bentley]] || style= &quot;text-align: center; top&quot; | [[List of Primeval episodes#ep8|2.2]] || style= &quot;text-align: center; top&quot; | 2.7
|-
| [[List of Primeval characters#Mick Harper|Mick Harper]] || [[Ramon Tikaram]] || style= &quot;text-align: center; top&quot; | [[List of Primeval episodes#ep12|2.6]] || style= &quot;text-align: center; top&quot; | 3.4
|-
| [[List of Primeval characters#Captain Becker|Captain Becker]] || [[Ben Mansfield]] || style= &quot;text-align: center; top&quot; | [[List of Primeval episodes#ep14|3.1]] || style= &quot;text-align: center; top&quot; | [[List of Primeval episodes#ep36|5.6]] 
|-
| [[List of Primeval characters#Sarah Page|Sarah Page]] || [[Laila Rouass]] || style= &quot;text-align: center; top&quot; | [[List of Primeval episodes#ep14|3.1]] || style= &quot;text-align: center; top&quot; | 3.10
|-
| [[List of Primeval characters#Christine Johnson|Christine Johnson]] || [[Belinda Stewart-Wilson]] || style= &quot;text-align: center; top&quot; | [[List of Primeval episodes#ep14|3.1]] || style= &quot;text-align: center; top&quot; | 3.9
|-
| [[List of Primeval characters#Danny Quinn|Danny Quinn]] || [[Jason Flemyng]] || style= &quot;text-align: center; top&quot; | [[List of Primeval episodes#ep15|3.2]] || style= &quot;text-align: center; top&quot; | 4.7
|-
| [[List of Primeval characters#Katherine Kavanagh|Katherine Kavanagh]] || [[Ruth Gemmell]] || style= &quot;text-align: center; top&quot; | [[List of Primeval episodes#ep16|3.3]] || style= &quot;text-align: center; top&quot; | 3.4
|-
| [[List of Primeval characters#Captain Wilder|Captain Wilder]] || [[Alex McSweeney]] || style= &quot;text-align: center; top&quot; | [[List of Primeval episodes#ep17|3.4]] ||style= &quot;text-align: center; top&quot; | 3.9
|-
| [[List of Primeval characters#Jack Maitland|Jack Maitland]] || [[Robert Daniel Lowe]] || style= &quot;text-align: center; top&quot; | [[List of Primeval episodes#ep17|3.4]] || style= &quot;text-align: center; top&quot; | 3.8
|-
| [[List of Primeval characters#Matt Anderson|Matt Anderson]] || [[Ciarán McMenamin]] || style= &quot;text-align: center; top&quot; | [[List of Primeval episodes#ep24|4.1]] || style= &quot;text-align: center; top&quot; | [[List of Primeval episodes#ep36|5.6]] 
|-
| [[List of Primeval characters#Jess Parker|Jess Parker]] || [[Ruth Kearney]] || style= &quot;text-align: center; top&quot; | [[List of Primeval episodes#ep24|4.1]] || style= &quot;text-align: center; top&quot; | [[List of Primeval episodes#ep36|5.6]] 
|-
| [[List of Primeval characters#Philip Burton|Philip Burton]] || [[Alexander Siddig]] || style= &quot;text-align: center; top&quot; | [[List of Primeval episodes#ep24|4.1]] || style= &quot;text-align: center; top&quot; | [[List of Primeval episodes#ep36|5.6]]
|-
| [[List of Primeval characters#Gideon|Gideon]] || [[Anton Lesser]] || style= &quot;text-align: center; top&quot; | [[List of Primeval episodes#ep24|4.1]] || style= &quot;text-align: center; top&quot; | 4.6
|-
| [[List of Primeval characters#Emily Merchant|Emily Merchant]] || [[Ruth Bradley]] || style= &quot;text-align: center; top&quot; | [[List of Primeval episodes#ep26|4.3]] || style= &quot;text-align: center; top&quot; | [[List of Primeval episodes#ep36|5.6]] 
|-
| [[List of Primeval characters#Ethan Dobrowski|Ethan Dobrowski]] || Jonathyn Byrne || style= &quot;text-align: center; top&quot; | [[List of Primeval episodes#ep26|4.3]] || style= &quot;text-align: center; top&quot; | 4.7
|-
| [[List of Primeval characters#April Leonard|April Leonard]] || Janice Byrne || style= &quot;text-align: center; top&quot; | [[List of Primeval episodes#ep31|5.1]] || style= &quot;text-align: center; top&quot; | [[List of Primeval episodes#ep35|5.5]] 
|}
&lt;/onlyinclude&gt;

== A ==

=== Matt Anderson ===
{{Infobox character
| name        = Matt Anderson
| first       = [[List of Primeval episodes#ep24|Episode 4.1]]
| last        = 
| portrayer   = [[Ciarán McMenamin]]
| gender      = Male
| occupation  = Team Leader
| significantother = [[Emily Merchant]] (love interest)
| children    =   
| relatives   = [[Gideon]] (father, deceased)
| nationality = [[Irish people|Irish]] (possible in the future)
}}
'''Matt Anderson''' is portrayed by [[Ciarán McMenamin]]. He is a private man who guards the secrets of his past and the reason he has joined the ARC team. He is an ex-soldier and a zoologist, and can understand animal behaviour, demonstrating this ability in his first appearance by securing the escaped Dracorex inside of Lester's office by luring it with a water dispenser, as the dinosaur was thirsty.

He and Becker get along well enough, but neither misses the opportunity to make remarks of the other. In episode 4.2 Matt is unsure of Abby and Connor when they first return, and follows Abby out of suspicion, but this brings him to save both of their lives from a Kaprosuchus before he comes to accept them. In episode 4.3 a mysterious woman goes through an Anomaly, Matt went after her because he assumed she was from the present, but upon returning her learnt that Emily was from the Victorian era and had been living with other people throughout time. He was sympathetic towards her and kept her in his flat because he believed the ARC would treat her like a criminal and agrees to help her find her companion Ethan. But while he is dealing with another Anomaly she is kidnapped by Ethan so he goes to Lester, who helps him track her down and saves her life when she was trapped inside a coffin. In episode 4.6 he takes Emily to the anomaly site and admits to her that a disaster is going to happen because of the anomalies. He later saw Gideon, who was on the verge of death, and promised to use Emily as bait to catch Ethan since they suspected he was involved. As he died Matt wept and told Emily that Gideon was his father. In episode 4.7, he realises Ethan, in fact Danny Quinn's brother Patrick, is not involved as he and Gideon suspected. In the end he tells Emily that he is from the future, explaining that in his time everyone lives underground because the Earth is sterile and cannot support life. He and his father, Gideon, were sent back in time to help prevent that future from happening. At some point between the present time and Matt's time, an &quot;event&quot; happened which changed the way Anomalies appear and their effect on the Earth, making it a barren wasteland. At the end of the episode, he convinces Emily to return to 1867 so that he can focus on stopping &quot;the event&quot;.

In episode 5.1, he is caught by Abby trying to hack into Connor's computer to find out what he and Philip are up to. After showing his knowledge of the large burrowing insects from the future, Abby realised he was from the future and he asked for her to help in his mission. In 5.3 he goes to Victorian London to capture a raptor they sent through the anomaly, telling Abby to steal data from Connor in the meantime, and encounters Emily again. Having earlier learned that she would end up in an asylum because of her husband Henry, he attempted to convince her to come back to the present as he regretted telling her to go, and was thankful to Abby when she handed over a copy of Connor's hard drive. He wasn't happy when Connor opened his own anomaly in the ARC during episode 5.4, and worked with Connor to eradicate a swarm of Future Beetles. In episode 5.5 he explains his mission to the whole team, and after bringing down a Tyrannosaurus he heads to New Dawn to stop Philip, only to be restrained  as Philip activated his anomaly. In episode 5.6 he rescues Connor from  the future, and risks himself to close the anomaly. He somehow manages to survive the implosion and returns to the ARC. However he is confronted by another version of himself who tells him to return to his home.
{{clear}}

== B ==

=== Captain Becker ===
{{Infobox character
| name        = Captain Becker
| first       = [[List of Primeval episodes#ep14|Episode 3.1]]
| last        = 
| portrayer   = [[Ben Mansfield]]
| gender      = Male
| occupation  = Special Ops Captain
}}
'''Captain Hilary Becker''' is portrayed by [[Ben Mansfield]]. According to [[Tim Haines]], &quot;he is going to be a new military guy who comes onto the team to watch their backs so that none of them gets eaten&quot;. Becker hails from a military family and background, and is moved from special operations to the Primeval team. Mansfield has stated that he will have &quot;amiable friction&quot; with [[#Connor Temple|Connor]] and he sees himself as the person who &quot;looks after&quot; the team. 

James Lester assigned him to join the team in episode 3.1. Becker assisted the team in returning creatures, such as the Pristichampus and Diictodon, back home, and began to become more involved in the action when a Giganotosaurus and a fungus from the future appeared. He often questioned Danny Quinn's judgement, but was nevertheless loyal and obeys orders, even if he disagrees with them. In [[List of Primeval episodes#ep19|episode 3.6]] he appeared to be working with Christine Johnson after she took control the ARC from Lester, but this was later revealed to be a ploy between him and Lester to bring Johnson down. He helped Abby rescue the ''[[Dracorex]]'' in [[List of Primeval episodes#ep20|episode 3.7]], and accompanied the team into the future in [[List of Primeval episodes#ep21|episode 3.8]] (almost dying in a fight against a pack of [[List of creatures in Primeval#Future Predator|Future Predators]]) in order to keep them safe. In [[Primeval (Episode 23)|episode 3.10]] he and Sarah fought the Megopteran in the present day, and as a result was one of only three main cast members to be in the present at the end of Series 3 (the others being Sarah and Lester).

At the beginning of Series 4, Becker is still working for the ARC, despite wishing to resign before Lester convinced him to stay. It is shown in a [[List of Primeval episodes#epW1|prologue webisode]] that Becker went with Sarah to the future to try find Abby, Connor and Danny, during which Sarah was killed. This has left Becker shaken, feeling that Sarah's death was his fault. He did not get along with Matt at first but slowly came to accept him. He is friendly with Jess, but is unaware she has feelings for him. After having one of Matt's EMD weapons used on him to test their capabilities, Becker agrees to use them. He is greatly relieved when Abby and Connor return, jokingly asking if they bought him a souvenir. In episode 4.3 he is adamant about enforcing the new policy to not allow any expeditions through the anomaly when Matt is missing and finally relents, but blames him when Arboreal Raptors cause trouble later. In episode 4.4 he is bitten by a Therocephalian and poisoned by its venom, but recovers and is forced to go on sick leave. In episode 4.6 he searches for the psychopath Ethan Dobrowski who is causing problems for the ARC and gets caught in a trap rigged up to a bomb, but Jess saves him. In episode 4.7 he attempts to stop Ethan (Danny's brother Patrick) but is shot twice by an EMD, with his fate unrevealed.

In episode 5.1 it is shown that Becker did recover, and at one point was thrilled at the idea of being able to call in a tank if necessary. He allows Matt to go through an anomaly after accidentally sending a raptor to Victorian London, citing they had to make it right in episode 5.3. During 5.4 his fondness for Jess is more clearly shown when she has an allergic reaction to a Future Beetle bite and desperately tried to help her. He risked himself to radiation from a gamma ray after the beetles were killed, and though he found Jess some adrenaline, he made an excuse to leave. In the next episode he helped the rest of the ARC deal with several anomaly incursions, though was cut off at his last one. In the series finale he joins the others in trying to stop Philip's anomaly.

Mansfield was spotted for the role when auditioning for the future [[BBC]] series ''[[Merlin (TV series)|Merlin]]'', the casting director (who also works as the casting director for Primeval) suggested that he come along to audition for Captain Becker.
{{clear}}

=== Claudia Brown ===
{{Infobox character
| name        = Claudia Brown
| first       = [[Episode 1 (Primeval)|Episode 1.1]]
| last        = [[Episode 6 (Primeval)|Episode 1.6]]
| portrayer   = [[Lucy Brown]]
| gender      = Female
| occupation  = [[Home Office]] official
}}
'''Claudia Brown''' is played by [[Lucy Brown]]. According to the official ''Primeval'' website, Claudia Brown, (born in [[Oxford]]) joined the [[Civil Service]] after studying law at university. For two years, she was engaged to be married, but she broke it off a month before the wedding. She has had no significant relationships since. She has fallen in love with Nick Cutter after he defended her from the &quot;flying lizards&quot;.

Much like [[#James Lester|Lester]], her official role at the [[Home Office]] is unclear. Since the discovery of the first anomaly, she has worked alongside [[#Nick Cutter|Nick Cutter]] and his team, acting as a liaison with the Home Office and occasionally defending Cutter's actions to Lester, and vice versa, but is often stressed out by Cutter's methods and secrets. She is not happy when she learns Cutter's missing wife [[#Helen Cutter|Helen]] is alive and that he knew, since she could give them vital information. Claudia is in love with Nick Cutter with whom she shares a passionate kiss during [[List of Primeval episodes#ep5|episode 1.5]]. In episode 1.6, Claudia jokingly accuses Cutter of [[sexual harassment]], noting that it is a serious offence in the civil service. She began hallucinating, seeing anomalies and ''[[List of creatures in Primeval#Gorgonopsid|Gorgonopsid]]'' throughout the Home Office. 

When Cutter and Helen started to leave, she asked him not to go as she thought it was a mistake, but he assured her that it would be okay. 
She and Cutter then exchanged another kiss in front of Helen and the rest of the team, and rebuffed Lester's note of it being unprofessional. When Cutter returns from the past via an anomaly, Claudia has vanished and none of his colleagues have any knowledge of who she is or was, leading Cutter to believe that something he has done in the past has altered the present, eliminating Claudia's existence. The reason for her disappearance is not yet known, though probably due to the remaining Future Predators that managed to escape the Gorgonopsid.
Cutter is devastated by this, describing Claudia to co-worker [[#Abby Maitland|Abby]] as &quot;important to him&quot; and saying he cared about her. Her non-existence shakes his foundation to the core as she is the first woman he had loved in his life since the disappearance of his wife, Helen.

Claudia remained out of existence for the second series, although another woman who appears to be physically identical, [[#Jenny Lewis|Jenny Lewis]], first appears in [[List of Primeval episodes#ep7|episode 2.1]]. At the end of [[List of Primeval episodes#ep8|episode 2.2]], Cutter explains to Jenny as best he can about what could have happened to change the past. Claudia's job as Lester's assistant was changed to a man named [[#Oliver Leek|Oliver Leek]], who was revealed to be working for [[#Helen Cutter|Helen Cutter]]. It was implied that Helen was responsible for Claudia being replaced by Jenny, however Helen denies it. At the end of the finale, Cutter shreds Claudia's picture (although in Series 3 it is revealed that he repaired part of it). The writers alluded to Claudia's possible return in the future, but said that they had no plans at the time to rewrite Claudia into the [[timeline]].
{{clear}}

=== Philip Burton ===
{{Infobox character
| name        = Philip Burton
| first       = [[List of Primeval episodes#ep24|Episode 4.1]]
| last        = [[List of Primeval episodes#ep36|Episode 5.6]]
| portrayer   = [[Alexander Siddig]]
| gender      = Male
| occupation  = CEO, scientist
}}
'''Philip Burton''' is portrayed by [[Alexander Siddig]]. As a result of the last mission of the old ARC, he appears in a new public/private partnership with the government, making him Lester's boss after the minister. His company, Prospero Industries, is used as the new location for the new ARC. Philip is more interested by the Anomalies than the creatures. There is a secret project he is working on called New Dawn.

Neither Lester, Abby or Matt trust him, but Connor admits he is like a groupie to Philip. In episode 4.1 he debriefs Abby and Connor when they return and tells them they no longer have field positions, but in the next episode Lester rehires them despite his objections. In episode 4.3 he has Connor do minor work in the ARC to spite him after he was placed back on the team, but is thankful when Connor saves him from dying and sees his true potential. In episode 4.4 he attempts to have the creatures in the ARC killed because of their inconvenience, but Lester blackmails him in dropping the matter. In episode 4.5 he recruits Connor to head up his own team of anomaly researchers after they discover vital new data. In episode 4.7, Danny Quinn confronts Philip about knowing Helen Cutter and doing research with her after finding his name on a document on her body, and despite denying this all he is clearly agitated. Connor later tells Philip about a potential disaster to be caused by the anomalies; Philip assures him they will solve the issue themselves and do not need to tell the others. 

In episode 5.1, he shows Connor his project 'New Dawn,' with which he plans to use the anomalies as an energy source to provide the whole world with free, clean energy. He also gives Connor a lab assistant, April Leonard. He also told Connor about Danny's knowledge of him and Helen, though he convinced him that she only knew of Philip. In 5.4 he witnesses Connor's man-made anomaly and Prospero gains much information from it. He was prepared to sacrifice the lives of the team to keep New Dawn from being compromised by blowing up the ARC during a Future Beetle incursion, though this fails, and it was shown he had built a larger version of Connor's device. In episode 5.5 he abandons Connor when their car is attacked by a Kaprosuchus, and activates the New Dawn machine, creating a huge anomaly, ignoring Matt's desperate protests. In episode 5.6 the anomaly becomes unstable and he realises that Matt was right and that it is a threat to humanity, with Helen having tricked him into it. He sacrifices himself in an attempt to destroy the New Dawn installation, but the anomaly became self-sustaining and remained.
{{clear}}

== C ==

=== The Cleaner ===
{{Infobox character
| name        = The Cleaner
| first       = [[List of Primeval episodes#ep7|episode 2.1]]
| last        = [[List of Primeval episodes#ep15|episode 3.2]]
| portrayer   = [[Tim Faraday]]
| occupation  = Mercenary
| relatives   = Numerous clones
| gender      = Male
}}

&quot;The Cleaner&quot; is a character who is portrayed by [[Tim Faraday]]. 

He is introduced in [[List of Primeval episodes#ep7|episode 2.1]], under-cover as a cleaner in a mall, who was sliced in the neck by a baby ''[[Deinonychus]]''. He later mysteriously disappears. Later in [[List of Primeval episodes#ep8|episode 2.2]], [[#Connor Temple|Connor]] sees him as a soldier at the ARC, the scars from the raptor attack still visible. The mysterious cleaner is seen again by [[#Nick Cutter|Cutter]] in [[List of Primeval episodes#ep10|episode 2.4]]. Suspicious, he chases him, but is punched in the face by him, knocking him out. Later it is revealed that the man is working for [[#Oliver Leek|Oliver Leek]], who wants the team spied on — and Leek is working in cahoots with [[#Helen Cutter|Helen Cutter]]. It is also revealed that the Cleaner's real name (or at least his surname) is Sciswell. In [[List of Primeval episodes#ep11|episode 2.5]], he goes into an anomaly with two soldiers. When one of them protests about leaving a girl behind, the man responds, &quot;I'm not a bloody social worker!&quot;. This line was previously used by [[#Tom Ryan|Captain Tom Ryan]] in [[Episode 6 (Primeval)|episode 1.6]] before his death, possibly linking the two characters together. He travels through an anomaly into the [[Silurian]] where his team is attacked and killed by giant scorpions. Only he survives, injured, and left only with a gun. He finds Cutter, demanding him to hand over his water supplies, but is then attacked by another scorpion, being dragged off, yelling &quot;I'm a professional. I don't talk. Ever&quot; when he was asked who he worked for before being pulled under and killed.

However, at the end of [[List of Primeval episodes#ep13|episode 2.7]] many clones of him appear with Helen at [[#Stephen Hart|Stephen Hart's]] grave, presumably working for her. These clones would be revealed as the result of technology that Helen acquired from the future, though lack any real independent thought like the original and are programmed to obey her every command even if it meant killing themselves. The clones re-appear in Series 3 and make an appearance at the conclusion of [[List of Primeval episodes#ep14|episode 3.1]]. One clone is killed in [[List of Primeval episodes#ep15|episode 3.2]] while spying inside the ARC. Another dies when Helen orders him to jump off the roof of a tall building to test the clones' programmed loyalty, and many clones are killed when the ARC explodes. 
{{clear}}

=== Helen Cutter ===
{{Infobox character
| name        = Helen Cutter
| first       = [[Episode 1 (Primeval)|Episode 1.1]]
| last        = [[Primeval (Episode 23)|Episode 3.10]]
| portrayer   = [[Juliet Aubrey]]
| gender      = Female
| occupation  = [[Professor]] of at Central Metropolitan University
| title       = Professor
| spouse      = [[#Nick Cutter|Nick Cutter]] ([[wikt:estranged|estranged]] and deceased husband)
}}
'''Professor Helen Cutter''' is played by [[Juliet Aubrey]]. It is implied that she may be responsible for a string of [[Anomaly (Primeval)|anomalies in time and space]] through which [[List of creatures in Primeval|prehistoric and extinct animals]] are passing. At the very least, she clearly has an understanding of the phenomenon which exceeds that of any other character in the series and is able to use the anomalies for her own purposes, ranging from basic time travel and exploration to actively changing timelines and creating clones.

Before her disappearance, Helen had an [[affair]] with [[#Stephen Hart|Stephen Hart]], [[#Nick Cutter|Nick Cutter]]'s best friend and right-hand man. She led Nick to believe she was dead after passing through an anomaly eight years before the beginning of the series. She appears to have knowledge of most of the threats facing her husband and his team, but does not appear to wish to divulge this information. However, she did save the life of one of the members of Nick's team when [[piranha]]-like ''[[Anurognathus]]'' attacked. She is thought by the Home Office to hold clues into why the anomalies form, and is therefore one of the focuses of attention in the storyline. Helen Cutter has told Nick that she does know a fair amount about the anomalies, but has so far refused to divulge this information. Nick Cutter, her ex-husband, also has a personal wish for her to return, and for her to stop escaping. She also seems to disapprove of her husband's budding relationship with [[#Claudia Brown|Claudia Brown]] and it is hinted she may have had a hand in Claudia's disappearance.

At the end of [[List of Primeval episodes#ep10|episode 2.4]], Helen is shown directing the team that is spying on the ARC members. During [[List of Primeval episodes#ep11|episode 2.5]], Helen visits Stephen again and imparts some information about the group spying on the ARC members, but states it in a way to make it sound like Cutter is involved and Lester is in charge. In [[List of Primeval episodes#ep12|episode 2.6]] Helen starts showing her feelings about Stephen and they share a passionate kiss and is revealed to be working with Oliver Leek in attempting to experiment on the anomalies to see how they affect the future. In episode 2.7 she eavesdrops on a conversation in Nick's cell to Jenny about how Nick still cared for Helen. Although this is later revealed to be a ploy on Cutter's part, Helen still believes that he does care for her. She was aware of Claudia in the time before the change and denies being behind it. Despite being shown as the brains of the operation, Leek begins to challenge Helen and when their creatures are released, she calls Stephen and lies to him saying that she was kidnapped by Lester and that Cutter was killed. She asked Stephen to rescue her and not to trust Lester. When Stephen arrives, she attempts to convince him to leave into the Anomalies until it is safe but he is determined for revenge. He encounters Nick and learns that Helen lied to him. Stephen, Helen and Nick work to contain the predators contained in Leek's base by luring them into the centre where the cages are located by ringing the bell that they associated with feeding time, to trap the creatures together so they will kill each other but Stephen is killed. Helen appears at Stephen's gravesite  shortly after his funeral and states that the timeline can change, at which point several duplicates of  [[#The Cleaner|&quot;The Cleaner&quot;]] appear, the result of her obtaining future cloning technology to create loyal minions.

In [[List of Primeval episodes#ep14|episode 3.1]] she is seen in a future time period stealing an artifact from Christine Johnson's military force and barely escapes with her life as predators are in the building. At the conclusion of the episode, Helen sets up an operational headquarters in the present day, assisted by the clones. In [[List of Primeval episodes#ep16|episode 3.3]], after taking ARC with her clones, she attempts to explain herself to Nick that she can prevent future atrocities (such as the rise of the [[List of creatures in Primeval#Future Predator|Future Predators]]) by actively altering timelines in the past so that evolution and history take a different path. Nick rejects this, insisting that Helen has no right to meddle. Helen also seems to believe that Nick's work with the ARC is in some way responsible for the atrocities she has seen in the future and thus intended to kill him in order to avoid it once he translates the artifact for her. She is caught in the blast from the bomb in the ARC and Nick returns to rescue her only for her to shoot him and leave him to die. Donning the alias of Eve (played by [[Kate Magowan]]), she uses Danny to get into the new ARC headquarters to regain the artifact, now believing that the only means to ensure the Future Predators' timeline never occurs is by negating humanity itself. She attempts to do this in the finale of Series 3 and is responsible for the death of the so-called &quot;[[AL 333|First Family]]&quot;. She briefly confronts Danny Quinn in the Pliocene, stating that when humanity is gone, other species will be able to develop in peace with no war or pollution. Helen is killed by a raptor before she can complete her mission.

Her presence is still felt strongly in the fourth series, as the ARC team speculate her fate; when Danny returns in the finale, he confirms that Helen is dead 'as a dodo' to Lester, who responds happily: &quot;Excellent&quot;. Danny also tells Matt and Emily that Helen and Philip Burton worked together studying the anomalies, and that Burton is not to be trusted. In the fifth series, Connor discovered an audio of Helen encouraging Philip to find a way to make the future better by using the anomalies. However in the series finale Philip realised Helen had tricked him by stroking his ego, having intended for his attempt at making green energy with the anomalies to wipe out humans much like her later plan, likely done in case she failed in her attempt to wipe out early humans.
{{clear}}

=== Nick Cutter ===
{{Infobox character
| name        = Nick Cutter
| first       = [[Episode 1 (Primeval)|Episode 1.1]]
| last        = [[List of Primeval episodes#ep16|Episode 3.3]]
| portrayer   = [[Douglas Henshall]]
| gender      = Male
| occupation  = [[Professor]] of [[Palaeozoology]] at Central Metropolitan University&lt;br /&gt;Anomaly team member
| title       = Professor
| spouse      = [[#Helen Cutter|Helen Cutter]] ([[wikt:estranged|estranged]] and deceased wife)
}}
'''Professor Nick Cutter''' is played by [[Douglas Henshall]]. He is a Professor of [[Palaeozoology]] at the (fictional) Central Metropolitan University. He was one of a group of people who discover that [[List of creatures in Primeval|prehistoric and extinct animals]] are passing through [[Anomaly (Primeval)|anomalies in time and space]]. Due to his expertise in prehistoric creatures, he was assigned to tackling the problems these creatures cause for the present civilisation by the [[Home Office]], and was described as a &quot;rank amateur who was amazingly good at what he did&quot;. Cutter is an expert in Palaeontology and the identification of extinct species. While little is known about his early life, the Official site states that he was born in [[Edinburgh]] and graduated from his year at [[University College London]] with First Class Honours. At some point he met and quickly married his wife Helen. Their marriage proved to be a failure, however, as according to [http://www.douglashenshall.com/Primeval_introduction Douglas Henshall's web site], the relationship between them became ''as stormy as it was passionate''. They were estranged at the time of her disappearance, and this added to Nick's sense of guilt when she vanished. When the series begins it is established that he had a wife, fellow palaeontologist [[#Helen Cutter|Helen Cutter]], who went missing eight years prior to his first encounter with a time anomaly. He tells the others that she went missing sometime after the two of them had a fight.

At first, his insistence that his wife Helen is alive in the first two and a half episodes is seen by some members of the time as initially somewhat foolish and unrealistic, most notably Claudia. He then keeps the details of her visitations to himself, out of hurt pride that his wife could have left him alone for so long.&lt;ref name=&quot;epTwo&quot;&gt;{{cite episode|title=Episode 2|episodelink=List of Primeval episodes#ep2|series=Primeval|network=[[ITV]]|airdate=10 February 2007|seriesno=1|number=2|minutes= }}&lt;/ref&gt; This has terrible consequences later when the government found out. When the truth is known, not only does he lose the respect of Claudia but also brings the wrath of Lester down on himself. After being tricked into leading Lester's troops to his wife the relationship between the two of them hit a new low as she is adamant that he had set her up and he finally lost patience with her evasions and riddles. She later escapes, and his motives for trying to follow her through the Anomaly are open to question.&lt;ref name=&quot;epFour&quot;/&gt;

Nick started out as a somewhat aloof individual; for example he initially rather briskly brushes off [[#Connor Temple|Connor Temple]] who comes to him with suspicions of a prehistoric creature being loose in modern times, telling him to go and get a girlfriend instead. He also keeps his encounter with his long lost wife, [[#Helen Cutter|Helen]] to himself. He can be quite spiteful at times as his last words to [[#Stephen Hart|Stephen]] before heading through the anomaly in [[Episode 6 (Primeval)|episode 1.6]] are to push Lester through the nastiest anomaly he can find if he does not make it back. He withholds information from his friends and team mates and Connor notes in [[Episode 1 (Primeval)|episode 1.1]] that he never turns up for his own seminars. He also tries to make demands of Lester in [[List of Primeval episodes#ep3|episode 1.3]]&lt;ref name=&quot;epThree&quot;&gt;{{cite episode|title=Episode 3|episodelink=List of Primeval episodes#ep3|series=Primeval|network=[[ITV]]|airdate=24 February 2007|seriesno=1|number=3|minutes= }}&lt;/ref&gt; he is ordered to bring Helen back only to be shocked when Lester overrules his decision and brings his wife back by force. Nick's attitude towards the Home Office involvement was at first one of mild contempt, at least for the more bureaucratic members such as [[#James Lester|James Lester]]. He dislikes hiding things from the public, Helen says she thinks he wants to share the time anomalies with the rest of the world in [[List of Primeval episodes#ep3|episode 1.3]].

However Nick is not uncompassionate, and he has mellowed out over time. He's developed a grudging respect for Lester, despite his claims to the contrary, and his caring side is shown when he reassures Connor on several occasions, most notably when Connor's friend is killed by a parasite. He was also very trusting of Helen, despite her comments and the others' suspicions that she may have intentionally set the [[List of creatures in Primeval#Parasite|parasitic]] [[List of creatures in Primeval#Dodo|Dodos]] on mankind in [[List of Primeval episodes#ep4|episode 1.4]],&lt;ref name=&quot;epFour&quot;&gt;{{cite episode|title=Episode 4|episodelink=List of Primeval episodes#ep4|series=Primeval|network=[[ITV]]|airdate=3 March 2007|seriesno=1|number=4|minutes= }}&lt;/ref&gt; although he was angry to discover Helen's real reason for returning the baby Future Predators to their own time. After that, it's safe to assume whatever feelings he had left for her are now over. His relationship with [[#Claudia Brown|Claudia Brown]] was beginning to turn to romantic, as demonstrated when he rushes to her rescue and later kisses her in [[List of Primeval episodes#ep5|episode 1.5]] and she begs him not to leave her.&lt;ref name=&quot;epFive&quot;&gt;{{cite episode|title=Episode 5|episodelink=List of Primeval episodes#ep5|series=Primeval|network=[[ITV]]|airdate=3 March 2007|seriesno=1|number=5|minutes= }}&lt;/ref&gt; Before heading into the anomaly, the two share a passionate kiss - much to Helen's anger. After the catastrophic mission to the permian he returns to learn Helen and Stephen had had an affair and that Claudia no longer exists.

Due to alterations in the timeline, the cause of which is unknown, Nick remains one of two of the only currently identified characters (The second being Helen) to remain unaffected for reasons that are unknown. Nick himself is confused as to how this happened.&lt;ref name=&quot;epSix&quot;&gt;{{cite episode|title=Episode 6|episodelink=Episode 6 (Primeval)|series=Primeval|network=[[ITV]]|airdate=3 March 2007|seriesno=1|number=6|minutes= }}&lt;/ref&gt; Nick also immediately calls new P.R. guru Jennifer Lewis [[#Claudia Brown|Claudia Brown]] after her doppelgänger. This confuses the team a lot, and while Connor and Abby both show some sort of support they find it hard to accept what he is saying. Stephen and Nick are now both quietly cautious of one another after the revelation of the affair and are no longer in full agreement of their methods. Nick is not happy when he learns Stephen and Helen have been seeing each other in secret and punches him, showing he still has some feelings for Helen. In the series finale he learned Helen was working with traitor Oliver Leek on anomaly research and acts out that he still cares about Helen but instead reveals he's going to turn her over to Lester before she escapes. He frees Leek's Future Predators and when he meets up with Helen and Stephen they agree to put an end to the predators Leek's captured. He is willing to sacrifice himself to save others but he is punched by Stephen, who takes his place inside the predator-filled room. Stephen asks Nick to tell Connor and Abby to stay out of trouble, and is then killed. Having spent some time trying to get to know Jenny and learning she has a fiancé, but it is revealed they broke up and asked Cutter out for a drink but they were called away to an anomaly. Nick shreds the picture of Claudia Brown at the end of the episode, showing he's decided to move on.

In Series Three, Nick begins creating a matrix to predict anomalies with the help of Sarah Page after learning mythical beasts may be linked to anomalies and successfully predicts one. He also saw the Cleaner again despite witnessing his apparent death and realises Helen's back. In episode 3.3 he helps deliver a baby while trapped in a hospital room. When they return to the ARC he learns Helen created a clone in his image to take over the ARC. He learns of her intent to alter the timeline by killing him after learning he ordered the cloning of Future Predators in the ARC sometime in the future, but only once he translates the strange artifact from the future she possesses. Nick attempts to stall her until his friends neutralise the Cleaner clones, forcing Helen to order the Nick Clone to detonate a bomb in spite of the original's attempt to talk him out of it. Nick attempts to save Helen as the ARC goes up in flames, hiding the artifact from her, but she shoots him in the chest after saying the future was more important than he was and ran off. Connor then attempts to save Nick, but when he arrives, he is told to sit down and wait. As they are talking, Nick asks Connor to tell Jenny/Claudia something but, decides against it. Giving Connor the artifact, Nick charges him, as his dying wish, to find out what the artifact is, before dying on Connor's shoulder.&lt;ref name=&quot;epThree&quot;/&gt; Despite his death, the future did not change as Helen thought because he was not going to be the real reason the Future Predators appeared.

[[Douglas Henshall]] confirmed in TV Times that he would be leaving the show at the end of Series Three, quoting: &quot;It was one of those things that happened and I thought, 'Oh God, I've done it. I've left', he told David Hollingsworth. &quot;The show might miss me for five minutes, but then I think it will move on and be fine.&quot; &quot;There's a little bit of me that thinks, 'this is my show, what do you mean they're still doing it without me,&quot; he says. &quot;But it will be good for Primeval in the long term – it will have to reinvent itself.&quot;
{{clear}}

== D ==

=== Ethan Dobrowski&lt;!-- Leave as just &quot;Ethan Dobrowski&quot;, which was the name used throughout the series. His real name is OK for inclusion in the infobox and prose. --&gt; ===
{{Infobox character
| name        = Ethan Dobrowski &lt;br/&gt;(Patrick Quinn)
| image       = 
| caption     = 
| first       = [[List of Primeval episodes#ep26|Episode 4.3]]&lt;!--Not &quot;3.2&quot; when young Patrick was briefly shown in flashback. --&gt;
| last        = [[List of Primeval episodes#ep30|Episode 4.7]]&lt;!--If he comes back, update it then--&gt;
| portrayer   = Jonathyn Byrne
| gender      = Male
| occupation  = 
| title       = 
| significantother = Charlotte Cameron
| children    = 
| relatives   = [[#Danny Quinn|Danny Quinn]] (brother)
| nationality = [[English people|English]]
}}
Ethan Dobrowski, or Patrick Quinn as his original name, is a character played by Jonathyn Byrne.

Patrick Quinn was fourteen years old when he and two of his friends broke into a house, however they were caught off guard by a camouflage beast that had come through an anomaly, and Patrick's body was never found along with another one of his friends. Though presumed dead, and while his brother Danny spent years trying to find out what had happened to him, he had actually survived and gone through the anomaly to some point in the future. He is known to have killed several camouflage beasts in order to survive, and was left mentally damaged by the experience. At some point he discovered another anomaly which took him to the year 1902 where he took the name Ethan Dobrowski, and people assumed he was originally from Russia. He killed six people, gaining a police record, and eventually left through another anomaly. At some point he joined a group of time travellers along with [[#Emily Merchant|Emily Merchant]] and Charlotte Cameron. He became close to Charlotte, and she was able to calm him, as he was noticeably different to the other members of the group.

When Charlotte was sick Ethan accompanied her and Emily to find an anomaly leading to a place with medicine, and arrived in the present, but she died. Angered over her death, Ethan blamed Emily as he believed her rules had caused them to be too late. He soon followed Emily and took up residence across from Matt Anderson's flat, and when he left Ethan kidnapped her. In episode 4.5 he had decided that as the only two to have known Charlotte, they were going to have their own funeral. He drove them to a cemetery where he told Emily he also blamed his family for what had happened to him and was going to make them suffer, and bound and gagged Emily inside a coffin before he fled from Matt. During episode 4.6, and after laying a trap for anyone who might come looking for him in the flat, went to his old home to find that a neighbour recognised him and claimed to be someone else before leaving. In [[List of Primeval episodes#ep30|episode 4.7]], while attempting to leave through another anomaly, he was caught after he encountered his brother Danny, revealing to everyone that he was Patrick. Captured and taken to the ARC, he told Danny what had happened to make him disappear, but said he was unhappy in the modern era, and escaped, taking the still-alive Emily as a hostage. Before he went through an anomaly to the Pliocene he ignored Emily's attempts to get him to stop, and left her at the mercy of a terror bird. He was soon followed by Danny, who wanted to keep him from hurting anyone else.
{{clear}}

=== Duncan ===
{{Infobox character
| name        = Duncan
| first       = Episode 1.2
| last        = Episode 4.2
| portrayer   = [[James Bradshaw (actor)|James Bradshaw]]
| gender      = Male
}}
Duncan ([[James Bradshaw (actor)|James Bradshaw]]) is a friend of [[#Connor Temple|Connor Temple]] and [[#Tom|Tom]] and a fellow [[geek]]. He also seems to enjoy [[conspiracy theory|conspiracy theories]]. Despite this he does not believe Connor when he tries to tell him and Tom what he has been involved in without breaking the [[Official Secrets Act]],&lt;ref name=&quot;epTwo&quot;&gt;{{cite episode|title=Episode 2|episodelink=List of Primeval episodes#ep2|series=Primeval|network=[[ITV]]|airdate=17 February 2007|seriesno=1|number=2|minutes= }}&lt;/ref&gt; and he and Duncan devise their own conspiracy theories around the [[List of creatures in Primeval#Dodo|Dodo]] (which he names Dodie) that they capture.&lt;ref name=&quot;epFour&quot;/&gt; Duncan seems to be the more mellow of Connor's friends and is quite willing to follow the more [[proactive]] Tom.

Duncan returned in [[List of Primeval episodes#ep25|episode 4.2]], having gone into hiding for four years since Tom's passing and finding proof of creature attacks for himself since no one believed him. He lead Connor to the docks where homeless people had been going missing, and with Abby they discovered the Kaprosuchus that had been living there for years. After being chased into a maze of containers where the creature pursued him until it was killed, Connor returned him home, and asked that if he came across more creature reports that he tell him.
{{clear}}

== G ==

=== Gideon ===
{{Infobox character
| name        = Gideon &lt;!-- Surname is never stated in the series, up to 4.6. &quot;Anderson&quot; CANNOT BE STATED AS A FACT without some reference.--&gt;
| first       = [[List of Primeval episodes#ep24|Episode 4.1]]
| last        = [[List of Primeval episodes#ep29|Episode 4.6]]
| portrayer   = [[Anton Lesser]]
| gender      = Male
| significantother =
| children    =  [[#Matt Anderson|Matt Anderson]] 
| relatives   = 
| nationality = 

}}
'''Gideon''' is portrayed by [[Anton Lesser]]. 

Throughout the beginning of the fourth series it is implied that he and Matt Anderson were working on a secret mission involving the ARC. He seemed desperate that they achieve their goal, warning Matt to keep an eye on the other members of the ARC and be wary of everyone, particularly Abby and Connor when they returned after a year in the [[Cretaceous]]. In episode 4.3 he is revealed to be dying because of an undisclosed illness, but had accepted his fate and wanted Matt to forget about him as he wasn't important. He wasn't happy in 4.5 when Matt risked everything to rescue Emily Merchant from Ethan Dobrowski, and Gideon feared that Ethan was connected to their mission, and ordered Matt to use Emily as bait. By episode 4.6 he is close to death, and apologises to Matt for not allowing him to get close to anyone, as it was for everyone's own good, and before he died he asked Matt to complete their mission. Matt then revealed to Emily that Gideon was his father. In 4.7 it is revealed that he has travelled back in time from a sterile future Earth in order to prevent this future from happening.
{{clear}}

== H ==

=== Mick Harper ===
{{Infobox character
| name        = Mick Harper
| first       = Episode 2.6
| last        = Episode 3.4
| portrayer   = [[Ramon Tikaram]]
| gender      = Male
| occupation  = Journalist
}}
Mick Harper is a [[journalist]] who is played by [[Ramon Tikaram]]. He first appears in [[List of Primeval episodes#ep12|episode 2.6]], trying to interview a survivor of a [[Columbian mammoth|Columbian mammoth's]] rampage on the M25. Like everyone else he had been told it was an elephant, unaware that the creature was actually a mammoth. He was unable to complete the interview because [[#Jenny Lewis|Jenny]] disrupted him. She used a sarcastic tone about it being a mammoth to throw him off, but Mick suspected there was more to the operation, and vowed to find out what was going on. 

In episode 3.3, Mick convinced his boss, Katherine Kavanagh, to give him a chance to prove prehistoric creatures were alive in the present, and attempted to have Jenny tell him after tracking down her home, but she refused to comment. He followed the team to a hospital, and locked Nick, Abby and a pregnant woman in an operating theatre. He then found one of the Diictodons, taking a blurry picture which he showed Katherine, who thought he was playing games with her, but was allowed one last chance. In [[List of Primeval episodes#ep17|episode 3.4]] Mick stole an anomaly detector from Jenny's car and presented it to Katherine as it went off, and they decided to go to the location on it with a camera crew. At the airport site they found an anomaly, and Mick locked Jenny and Connor in another hanger after tricking them into believing they were attacked elsewhere. Mick and others filmed a juvenile velociraptor that comes through the anomaly while [[Nigel Marvin]] described it to them. A Giganotosaurus came through the anomaly and attacked, and the car Mick and Katherine hid in was flipped over. Danny and Connor pulled them out and both were locked in the other hanger as they were under arrest. Mick agreed to force the door open once Katherine agreed to give him a fair share of the merchandising once they had broke the story. They grabbed a camera to film the crisis, and Mick quit when Danny nearly hit him with a helicopter. Katherine frantically filmed the Giganotosaurus as it was heading towards the anomaly, and inadvertently pushed Mick backwards through the anomaly, where they are presumably killed as Mick is heard screaming.
{{clear}}

=== Stephen Hart ===
{{Infobox character
| name        = Stephen James Hart
| first       = [[Episode 1 (Primeval)|Episode 1.1]]
| last        = [[List of Primeval episodes#ep13|Episode 2.7]]
| portrayer   = [[James Murray (English actor)|James Murray]]
| gender      = Male
| occupation  = Lab technician
| significantother = Alison (ex-girlfriend), [[Helen Cutter]] (ex-lover)
| children    =   
| relatives   = 
| nationality = [[English people|English]]
}}
'''Stephen James Hart''' is played by [[James Murray (English actor)|James Murray]]. He is part of a team of five people, who investigate a series of [[Anomaly (Primeval)|anomalies in space and time]] through which [[List of creatures in Primeval|prehistoric and extinct creatures]] are travelling. Stephen is [[#Nick Cutter|Nick Cutter's]] lab technician and was the object of fellow team member [[#Abby Maitland|Abby Maitland's]] affections.

According to the official site Stephen is [[environmentalism|passionately committed to wildlife conservation]] and firmly believes that humanity is destroying its own environment through unchecked industrialisation. On average, he runs about 30 miles a week.

He remains a cold and aloof individual, but one with surprisingly loyal and brave tendencies as he willingly braves the jaws of a ''Gorgonopsid''&lt;ref name=&quot;epOne&quot;&gt;{{cite episode|title=Episode 1|episodelink=Episode 1 (Primeval)|series=Primeval|network=[[ITV]]|airdate=10 February 2007|seriesno=1|number=1|minutes= }}&lt;/ref&gt; and an Arthropleura&lt;ref name=&quot;epTwo&quot;/&gt; in order to save his friends and innocent bystanders. He is also not afraid to stand up to [[#Nick Cutter|Cutter]] as he confronts him about the way he withheld information about [[#Helen Cutter|his wife]] from them. In [[List of Primeval episodes#ep2|episode 1.2]], Cutter risks his life to get an anti-venom which will save Stephen's life.

While he tries not to show any emotion and keep his personal life secret, he does ask [[#Abby Maitland|Abby]] out for dinner&lt;ref name=&quot;epTwo&quot;/&gt; and later admitted that he has a girlfriend although their relationship appears to have broken down&lt;ref name=&quot;epThree&quot;/&gt; and the official site states that he &quot;''had his heart broken when he fell in love as a student and never really got over it.''&quot;

In the first series, Stephen seemed to act as a punchbag for the monsters, often being badly injured or stranded on his own. He also seems to have a big brother relationship with [[#Connor Temple|Connor]] whom he constantly puts down and yet looks out for at the same time.&lt;ref name=&quot;epThree&quot;/&gt; In [[List of Primeval episodes#ep13|episode 2.7]], Stephen is killed by a collection of animals that [[#Oliver Leek|Leek]] had captured. He was killed preventing the animals from escape, and his funeral was the only one in the history of the show. It is revealed that his middle name is James.

According to the official site, Stephen was once a junior fencing champion and also a junior shooting Olympic prospect. He later gave up both to study natural history. He appears to have had a long relationship with Nick Cutter going back at least eight years as he states that he knew [[#Helen Cutter|Helen]] himself, in the last episode it is revealed that he had an affair with her.&lt;ref name=&quot;epTwo&quot;/&gt; Whether or not she is the former girlfriend who broke his heart is unclear but it is shown in [[Episode 6 (Primeval)|episode 1.6]] that it was a short lived affair which he has regretted ever since, mainly because of his guilt over betraying his friend and partly because Helen is, as he calls her, ''&quot;a real bitch&quot;.''

When the series begins it is established that he is working alongside Nick as a teacher and lab assistant. He later follows both Nick and Connor and becomes ensnared with them in the sinister events unfolding in the Forest of Dean.&lt;ref name=&quot;epTwo&quot;/&gt; He then reveals that he has some training as a tracker and in stealth combat, as he vanishes under Connor's nose to begin the hunt for the Gorgonopsid personally. He later tracks it to a school and is wounded trying to lure it away from a teacher and her student.&lt;ref name=&quot;epTwo&quot;/&gt;

When brought into the anomaly team, he is then sent to the underground vaults and bunkers beneath Parsons Green Station. He is then attacked, poisoned and left for dead by an Arthroplura&lt;ref name=&quot;epTwo&quot;/&gt; while trying to find Cutter. It is during this time he is visited by Helen, although she also left him for dead, she gave him a message for her husband. He later remembers nothing of the incident, however. Subsequently his memory returns, he confronts Cutter and is angered by his unconcern for his wife, stating that if she was his wife he would have gone looking for her. He later helps prepare Cutter for his trip into the underwater anomaly, arming him with a spear gun. He also tries to make amends with Abby for asking her out and then forgetting about it.&lt;ref name=&quot;epThree&quot;/&gt;

He once again proves his concern for her welfare when he runs to her rescue in [[List of Primeval episodes#ep4|episode 1.4]] when she is captured by Connor's parasite-ridden friend.&lt;ref name=&quot;epFour&quot;&gt;{{cite episode|title=Episode 4|episodelink=List of Primeval episodes#ep4|series=Primeval|network=[[ITV]]|airdate=10 February 2007|seriesno=1|number=4|minutes= }}&lt;/ref&gt; However [[#Claudia Brown|Claudia]] (who is also angry for his running into trouble in the subway) and [[#James Lester|Lester]] appear to have lost patience with him during the hunt for the [[List of creatures in Primeval#Pteranodon|Pteranodon]].&lt;ref name=&quot;epFive&quot;/&gt;

Stephen appears to have undergone the least change of all the characters since the alterations in the timeline, with most of his history remaining the same including his affair with Helen. Thus he and Cutter still have a lot of issues to work through. In the final episode, he is called by Lester to handle the threat posed by a Silurian scorpion that was unleashed on a beach resort by Leek. He managed to spear the creature and left it for the ARC (or Leek as it is hinted later that Leek's collection includes the presumed dead [[List of creatures in Primeval#Smilodon|smilodon]] from [[List of Primeval episodes#ep9|episode 2.3]]) to deal with after which he received a call from Helen who told him her location, telling Stephen that Nick and the others were dead and that Lester had kidnapped her.

Stephen arrived at Leek's base only to discover that Helen had lied to him and that Nick was alive. Despite feeling betrayed by Helen, Stephen showed anger towards Nick as well believing that he was wrong on how he dealt with the Anomaly crisis. Stephen, Helen and Nick tried to deal with the freed creatures by luring them into the central chamber where they were all held, luring them by ringing the bell that the creatures associated with feeding time. While doing this, a Deinonychus (Raptor, also appeared in [[List of Primeval episodes#ep7|episode 2.1]]) attacked Helen which Stephen killed with his pistol but then Helen kicked the door mechanism which could only be closed from the inside. Nick attempted to sacrifice himself but Stephen punched his mentor and entered the chamber, sealing it from the inside. The last sight of him was being killed by the assembled predators who killed each other after feasting on him. Having been relieved of his ARC duties some time earlier, and being fed [[disinformation]] by Helen, it appears that Stephen died still believing James Lester to be the traitor in the ARC (though Cutter told him that Lester was not the enemy moments before his death), and unaware of both Leek's role and fate.

His funeral was held by the members of the ARC but after they left, Helen arrived to visit the grave and stated that there was nothing to worry as there were ways to return.
{{clear}}

== J ==

=== Christine Johnson ===
{{Infobox character
| name        = Christine Johnson
| first       = [[List of Primeval episodes#ep14|Episode 3.1]]
| last        = [[List of Primeval episodes#ep22|Episode 3.9]]
| portrayer   = [[Belinda Stewart-Wilson]]
| gender      = Female
| occupation  = Civil servant
}}
Christine (played by [[Belinda Stewart-Wilson]], ex-wife of [[Ben Miller]]) is the military liaison to the ARC in series three. Ostensibly, her role is to provide the assistance of the armed forces to deal with the problems caused by the anomalies. However, it is apparent she has other objectives.

In [[List of Primeval episodes#ep14|episode 3.1]], she revealed her new role to James Lester, both equally despising the other, and sent several soldiers through an anomaly into the future to retrieve a mysterious artifact. The mission failed, with only one soldier returning alive, and the artefact ultimately being stolen by [[#Helen Cutter|Helen Cutter]]. In [[List of Primeval episodes#ep17|episode 3.4]], it is revealed that she has her own facility, which contains an anomaly and a Future Predator which her team is running tests on. The anomaly that Christine has is normally cloaked from the ARC's Anomaly Detection Device (presumably by [[radio jamming]] on the frequency used by the detector), but denies the existence of the anomaly to the team when the cloaking device goes offline. In [[List of Primeval episodes#ep18|episode 3.5]] she visits the ARC and attempted to convince Lester to replace the dead Cutter with Captain Wilder so that she could control the ARC team, and blamed Lester when one of her men was killed by a fungus creature. She was annoyed even further when Lester led her to assume he would choose Wilder to be team leader, but instead appoints Danny Quinn.

In [[List of Primeval episodes#ep19|episode 3.6]], Christine's hidden cameras inside the ARC allowed her to learn they had the artefact, and had the Minister appoint to be in charge of the ARC, getting rid of Lester, but the team escaped with the artefact. She is forced to leave when Becker betrays her by recording her abusing the Minister, and Lester sent it to the Minister. She did so vowing &quot;It's not over&quot;, mirroring Lester from earlier. However she didn't give up trying to take control of the ARC, and in episode 3.8 she sent Wilder though her anomaly and he returned with a woman from the future called Eve. in [[List of Primeval episodes#ep22|episode 3.9]] her attempts to get information from her were interrupted by Danny, who escaped with Eve. Christine had a warrant for Danny's arrest, the return of Eve and the custody of the artefact when she arrived at the ARC, however Eve was revealed to be Helen, who kidnapped Christine and stole the artefact. Helen revealed Christine was the cause of the destruction in the future because of her ambitions, and Christine was killed when Helen let her be mauled by a Future Predator and was unable to be saved by the team.
{{clear}}

== K ==

=== Katherine Kavanagh ===
Katherine Kavanagh appeared in [[List of Primeval episodes#ep16|episode 3.3]] and [[List of Primeval episodes#ep17|episode 3.4]] played by [[Ruth Gemmell]]. She is Mick Harper's boss from Evening News HQ. She only gave his assistant one chance to find a Diictodon and when Mick gave the picture to her, she said &quot;No, not really, you bring me a blurry picture with a Gopher, a child of ten could've faked that. Get out of my sight!&quot; In [[List of Primeval episodes#ep17|episode 3.4]], Mick gave her an anomaly detector and they followed it. She got out from being locked in a building and while filming, Katherine was killed with Mick Harper by a Giganosaurus while it followed Danny Quinn in a helicopter.
{{clear}}

== L ==

=== Oliver Leek ===
{{Infobox character
| name        = Oliver Leek
| first       = [[List of Primeval episodes#ep7|Episode 2.1]]
| last        = [[List of Primeval episodes#ep13|Episode 2.7]]
| portrayer   = [[Karl Theobald]]
| gender      = Male
| occupation  = Assistant to [[#James Lester|James Lester]]
}}
'''Oliver Leek''' was the main antagonist of the second series. He is played by [[Karl Theobald]].

Leek works for the ARC (Anomaly Research Centre) which investigates [[Anomaly (Primeval)|time anomalies]] and stops [[List of creatures in Primeval|creatures of the past and future]] from coming through them. 

When Helen and Nick went to the Permian in [[Episode 1.6]], on their return the timeline had changed, Leek had replaced [[#Claudia Brown|Claudia Brown]] as [[#James Lester|James Lester's]] assistant.

According to the official ''Primeval'' website, Leek is &quot;slightly [[nerd]]y, intelligent and eager to please&quot;. He went as far as buying suits from exactly the same tailor as [[#James Lester|Lester]], a feeble attempt to impress his boss. At school Leek was overlooked and the last picked at sports.{{Citation needed|date= March 2008}} As an adult, he goes to the same restaurant every morning and eats at the same table, while the waiter still fails to recognise him. Apparently he is 33 years old, 170&amp;nbsp;cm (5&amp;nbsp;ft, 8 in) tall, and was born in [[Birmingham]].

According to the website &quot;There is more to Leek than meets the eye&quot;, pointing towards a sinister side of him.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.douglashenshall.com/2Primevalquestionsandanswers.html Primeval 2:Primeval ITV Series 2: ITV Publicity Q &amp; A&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt; This sinister side is first shown in episodes [[List of Primeval episodes#ep9|2.3]] and [[List of Primeval episodes#ep10|2.4]], where he appears to be employing at least two individuals ([[#The Cleaner|a mysterious cleaner]] and [[#Caroline Steel|Caroline Steel]]) to follow the team and find out as much as they can. He also appears to be consorting with Helen who seems to have placed her trust in him for some objective. In [[List of Primeval episodes#ep12|episode 2.6]] it is revealed that Leek is overseeing a private menagerie of animals, to establish a powerful place for himself in the future. Caroline eventually steals Rex, who is then used as bait to lure Cutter's team to Leek's secret facility.

Leek is highly adept at manipulating people, seeming very much in control in [[List of Primeval episodes#ep13|episode 2.7]], and is able to use this ability to engineer situations to his own advantage. In addition, although Cutter realises early in series two that there is a traitor within the ARC, Leek manages to avoid suspicion until he chooses to reveal himself in [[List of Primeval episodes#ep12|episode 2.6]], having set an elaborate trap for the team based on his knowledge of [[#Connor Temple|Connor Temple's]] working methods. He seems to dislike taking orders, and reminds Helen Cutter that he is in charge multiple times throughout [[List of Primeval episodes#ep13|episode 2.7]].

He seems to have a great disregard to other people's feelings and human lives - he finds the fight between Abby and Caroline entertaining, and does not seem to care when Cutter tells him that if a predator was to escape it could wipe out mankind. Lester and Connor both refer to him as a small, insignificant or irritating man because of his aloof nature.{{Citation needed|date= March 2008}}

His plan of releasing creatures to take control of mankind fails when a virus sends Lester all the information required. If Cutter had escaped with the others, then Leek would have almost certainly been arrested, but because Cutter remains Leek still seems to think he is unstoppable. He threatens to kill Cutter using his army of Future Predators, but before he can command the predators to kill him, Cutter throws a neural clamp used to control the predators into an electric box, which short-circuits all the other clamps. Cutter escapes and shuts the door to the room. The Future Predators descend to the floor of the room and kill Leek. Lester watches the death of Leek, before leaving.

Although he is never seen at a computer terminal, it is apparent that Leek has considerable hacking skills, which he has used to install [[spyware]] on Connor's &quot;anomaly detector&quot;, and to set a booby-trap which initiated the countdown on a bomb when Connor attempted to access Leek's personnel files.
{{clear}}

=== April Leonard ===
{{Infobox character
| name        = April Leonard
| first       = [[List of Primeval episodes#ep31|Episode 5.1]]
| last        =  [[List of Primeval episodes#ep35|Episode 5.5]]
| portrayer   = [[Janice Byrne]]
| gender      = Female
| occupation  = Prospero scientist
}}
'''April Leonard''' is played by [[Janice Byrne]], and is Connor's assistant following her appointment by Philip Burton. When around Connor and the rest of the ARC team she wears glasses, though she does not need them. 

She was first seen in episode 5.1 at the site of Philip's New Dawn facility, and Philip decided to have her assist Connor in helping work on New Dawn to create energy from the anomalies. She was later shown to be reporting to Philip on Connor's progress, as well as keeping and eye on anyone that Danny Quinn might have told about his connection with Helen Cutter. In 5.3 she subtly forces Connor to continue working, and later gives Abby 'friendly advice' about leaving Connor to finish his important work at the risk of losing him. 

In Episode 5.4 she assists Philip in watching their new data come in from Connor's anomaly, and convinced him to kill the people in the ARC by blowing in up during a future beetles incursion, saying that Philip's goals were worth more than them, however this did not come to pass. In episode 5.5, when the team is trying to prevent the New Dawn project going online, she has a confrontation with Abby, which ends when she is attacked and killed by a flock of [[List_of_creatures_in_Primeval#Anurognathus|Anurognathus]].
{{clear}}

=== James Lester ===
{{Infobox character
| name        = James Lester
| first       = [[Episode 1 (Primeval)|Episode 1.1]]
| last        = 
| portrayer   = [[Ben Miller]]
| gender      = Male
| occupation  = Senior [[UK government]] official
| title       = 
| spouse      = 1 (unnamed)
| children    = 3 (unnamed) 
| relatives   = 
| nationality = [[English people|English]]
}}
'''James Peregrine Lester''' is played by [[Ben Miller]] .

Lester works for the [[UK government|British government]], and is leader and ultimately responsible for the team of scientists, led by [[#Nick Cutter|Nick Cutter]], charged with investigating the appearance of [[Anomaly (Primeval)|time anomalies]]. A ruthless and sarcastic individual, he's been given the task of uncovering the secrets of the anomalies and to prevent mass panic and he intends to do that by whatever means are necessary.

According to the official site he is without any real political allegiances although he believes that [[the ends justify the means]] and has no problems with torture. He is also hinted to be a British patriot with a distrust of the [[EU]].&lt;ref name=&quot;epTwo&quot;/&gt; - &quot;And I thought the Common Agricultural Policy was far-fetched.&quot;

While remaining, for the most part, stubborn, [[paranoia|paranoid]], slow to face facts and wilfully ignorant, he has also displayed surprising bursts of astonishing foresight and knowledge as he guesses correctly that [[#Claudia Brown|his assistant]] has personal reasons for wanting Cutter to remain close by, and that Cutter was hiding something from them.&lt;ref name=&quot;epTwo&quot;/&gt; He also guesses that [[#Helen Cutter|Helen Cutter]] was lying in order to escape, &quot;I think I'd trust her just about as far as I can throw a ''[[Stegosaurus]]''&quot;, but is convinced otherwise by Claudia and Cutter, which proves to be a mistake on their part. He's usually right in the final analysis, especially on matters of human nature, when Cutter is usually wrong.&lt;ref name=&quot;epFour&quot;/&gt;

However, he has also shown a softer side when he promises to have the charges against a young girl dropped, when Claudia brings the matter to his attention, even though he can simply do nothing.&lt;ref name=&quot;epThree&quot;/&gt; In Series 3 he allowed Connor to stay with him when Abby asked him to move out of her flat when her brother Jack needed somewhere to stay, despite showing previous dislike towards him. Like Professor Cutter, Lester has slowly mellowed out over the course of the series and become far more active and reasonable when dealing with the team.&lt;ref name=&quot;epSix&quot;/&gt;

He is a snappy dresser as he owns over 50 suits, all made to measure, all dark colours with colourful ties because someone once told him it was trendy.&lt;ref name=&quot;Official Primeval website&quot;&gt;Character profile on [http://primeval.itv.com Official Primeval website]&lt;/ref&gt; He also plays squash and tennis as a hobby.&lt;ref name=&quot;Official Primeval website&quot;/&gt;

Little of Lester's background has been revealed, other than he has a family.&lt;ref name=&quot;Official Primeval website&quot;/&gt; While his exact role and position in the government is unclear, he has free run of [[UK government|Whitehall]] and command of intelligence and security forces. He has spent his entire career &quot;planning for just about every crisis imaginable&amp;mdash;up to and including [[alien invasion]].&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;epTwo&quot;/&gt; He describes himself as &quot;a trouble shooter without portfolio in the PM's office&quot; and agreed with Cutter's assessment that he is a &quot;government backed hatchet man.&quot;

For most episodes he remains a sedentary leader and problem-solver; everyone has to go to him at Whitehall, and he operates through agents like [[#Claudia Brown|Claudia Brown]] and [[#Tom Ryan|Tom Ryan]]. However this is apparently not due to any lack courage in the face of danger, he has no fear going out in the field and once met up with the team&lt;ref name=&quot;epThree&quot;/&gt; in order to confront Cutter personally and ensure the capture of Helen Cutter. During her later interrogation he is quite happy to use torture to gain information.

While having an intense dislike of Cutter, and believing his team members ([[#Connor Temple|Connor]] in particular) to be annoying,&lt;ref name=&quot;epThree&quot;/&gt; he remains professional except for regular sarcastic comments. Later in the series his relationship with Cutter did reach a breaking point; he questions Cutter's role in his wife's escape and the reason for his pursuit&lt;ref name=&quot;epFour&quot;/&gt; and claims he causes more problems than he solves, which is, as usual, an accurate assessment. By the end of the first series, however, he was prepared to forgive and forget and put his neck on the line for the Professor and, when push came to shove, was prepared to actively join in the effort to find a [[List of creatures in Primeval#Future Predator|Future Predator]] and the [[Anomaly (Primeval)|anomaly]] it came from.&lt;ref name=&quot;epSix&quot;/&gt;
James Lester's middle name is Peregrine, which he keeps a closely guarded secret.

Due to alterations in the timeline, the cause of which is unknown, Lester is now the agent in charge of the A.R.C. He now also has a personal assistant, [[#Oliver Leek|Oliver Leek]], who is apparently working for [[#Helen Cutter|Helen Cutter]]. [[#Connor Temple|Connor]] later discovered that his new girlfriend, [[#Caroline Steel|Caroline Steel]], is really working with Leek and Helen.&lt;ref name=s2qna&gt;[http://www.douglashenshall.com/2Primevalquestionsandanswers.html Primeval 2:Primeval ITV Series 2: ITV Publicity Q &amp; A]&lt;/ref&gt; In [[List of Primeval episodes#ep12|episode 2.6]], Lester is trapped alone inside the ARC by Oliver Leek, who attempts to kill him using a Future Predator controlled by &quot;neural clamp&quot; (some kind of external control) on its spinal column. Lester foils the attempt by releasing a Columbian mammoth which is being kept safe inside the ARC, which impales the predator on its tusks. Lester later jokingly suggests keeping the mammoth as a pet for his kids, if the team was unable to find the creature a home. This is the first time Lester mentions having a family. Lester then decides to take charge of the next anomaly investigation himself, however it turns out to be a false alarm, set up as a diversion by Leek while he lures Cutter's team to his secret facility. Lester arrives at the scene of the false alarm to find only a note reading &quot;BAD LUCK&quot;. In the final episode, Lester shows a lot much more support and concern for the team, and goes to the extent of calling Stephen to try and help out. However, he is set up by Helen, and portrayed as a bad guy throughout the final episode (by Stephen and Helen's perspective). He also sides with Cutter, who seems willing to die to prevent anyone else from being killed. When Cutter destroys the neural clamps, releasing the predators from Leek's control, Lester insists on watching Leek being devoured by his former pets and seems unfazed by it as opposed to the horrified reactions of the other people watching, including his assistant Lorraine Wickes. When the death of Leek is over, he casually tells Lorraine to: &quot;turn that off will you?&quot;. He also discovers the secret locations of Leek's menagerie, and mops them all up one by one. He also attends Stephen Hart's funeral, but has to leave early because of a &quot;high-priority anomaly&quot;.

In Series 3 Lester's fight become more personal when he discovers Christine Johnson working against him, who he has connections to. In [[List of Primeval episodes#ep16|episode 3.3]] he is rounded up and imprisoned with the rest of the ARC by Helen and her clones, and shows little surprise at Cutter's apparent betrayal &quot;So, Cutter's finally gone native&quot;. When Cutter lies dying after the ARC explosion, Lester yells desperately for an ambulance for him. In the following episode he makes Jenny team leader, and then assigns Danny Quinn to the same role the episode after. When he discovers Connor living in the ARC with the two Diictodon he offers him his spare apartment, although later appears to be annoyed at the mess Connor and his &quot;pets&quot; make. In [[List of Primeval episodes#ep19|episode 3.6]] he is stripped of command of the ARC by Christine Johnson, although with the help of Becker he regains it later in the episode, telling Johnson that she is &quot;sitting in his chair&quot; mirroring one of her lines earlier that episode. In [[List of Primeval episodes#ep22|episode 3.9]] Lester commands Danny NOT to invade Johnson's HQ to rescue Eve, and becomes annoyed at him when he does, and appears ready to hand Danny over to Johnson until Eve is revealed as Helen.

In Series 4 Lester is a subordinate to [[#Philip Burton|Philip Burton]], whom he dislikes greatly, after the government makes a deal for Burton's company to subsidise the ARC and anomaly research. He is somewhat pleased by Abby and Connor's return, though he has to follow orders and have them fired due to new policies, but later finds a loophole to get them back on the team. He defies Burton's plan to kill the creatures in the ARC's menagerie, by blackmailing him with the fact that when the anomalies inevitably go public he will expose Burton as &quot;the dinosaur killer&quot; in sympathy for an upset Abby. In 4.5 he helps Matt locate Victorian-era woman Emily Merchant, and in the next episode is informed of the Ethan Dobrowski situation before he marries Jenny and her fiancé with special power from the Prime Minister. In the series finale he couldn't been more happier when Danny returned with the news that Helen Cutter was as dead as a dodo.

Although he has previously been occasionally referred to in the credits as &quot;Sir&quot; James Lester, it is made clear in the first episode of Series 5 (when he thinks he is in line for one) that he does not actually have a knighthood. He was excited and thought that his interview would secure the knighthood, only to learn that it was for Philip and he had set aside any doubts. In episode 5.2, Lester is shown to have a large dislike of the Navy, especially when an admiral attempts to nuke the anomaly after the team's submarine had been pulled through, and is pleased when the admiral is berated by the Minister. When he returns in [[List of Primeval episodes#ep35|episode 5.5]] he learns Matt is from the future and Philip is responsible for the end of the world, and when several anomalies begin opening he encourages Jess to continue working, using polite words. When an anomaly opens in the ARC's carpark he goes to defend his new Jaguar from a tree creeper with an EMD. In the series finale he and Jess are attacked by mutated Future Predators in the ARC, and though he is heavily wounded, he survives.
{{clear}}

=== Jenny Lewis ===
{{Infobox character
| name        = Jennifer Lewis
| first       = [[List of Primeval episodes#ep7|Episode 2.1]]
| last        = [[List of Primeval episodes#ep18|Episode 4.6]]
| portrayer   = [[Lucy Brown]]
| gender      = Female
| occupation  = [[Public relations|PR]] official
| significantother = Michael (husband)
| children    =  
| relatives   = 
| nationality = [[English people|English]] 
}}
'''Jenny Lewis''' is played by [[Lucy Brown]] and replaced a physically identical but temperamentally different character, [[#Claudia Brown|Claudia Brown]], played by the same actress. She is 28 years old. At the end of the first series, Claudia disappeared off the timeline, much to the disappointment of Cutter, who found it difficult to adjust when Jenny appeared, looking exactly like Claudia.

Jenny's attitude contrasts with Claudia's. She is bossy and stubborn, ignoring [[#Nick Cutter|Cutter's]] order to take the stairs in [[List of Primeval episodes#ep8|episode 2.2]]. Cutter states in [[List of Primeval episodes#ep9|episode 2.3]] that Jenny is a &quot;real piece of work&quot; to which Jenny replies, &quot;Thank you, I'll take that as a compliment&quot;.

Jenny was engaged but in [[List of Primeval episodes#ep13|episode 2.7]], Jenny states that she no longer has a fiancé, as he broke up the engagement after he thought that she had met another man, although as Jenny says,
&quot;I couldn't really tell him that it wasn't another man, as much as a something-a-saurus.&quot;

Cutter explains to Jenny that he has not had luck with women - Helen disappeared eight years before, and he claims the last woman in his life (Claudia Brown) left him.

Jenny is initially employed by [[#James Lester|James Lester]] to create cover stories for the activities of the Anomaly Research Centre, without being told what the ARC is really doing. She only discovers that the centre is involved in dealing with prehistoric animals when she disobeys a direct order and accidentally comes face-to-face with one that has come through the office block anomaly in [[List of Primeval episodes#ep8|episode 2.2]]. However, once she has got over the initial shock, Jenny quickly adjusts and takes the unusual nature of the job in her stride. Although her job is officially just public relations, she has no difficulty in taking a leadership role when necessary. She led an armoured team to investigate the church anomaly in [[List of Primeval episodes#ep12|episode 2.6]] (though it is in fact a deliberate false alarm) and taking charge of the escape from Leek's secret facility in [[List of Primeval episodes#ep13|episode 2.7]]. In the latter she is also revealed to be a crack shot, shooting one of Leek's men from afar. She explains her ability by saying that her &quot;friends preferred pony riding, I preferred clay pigeon shooting&quot;. James Lester regards her as the most dependable member of the team, and makes her interim leader following the death of Nick Cutter.

One quirk of Jenny's character is that she always wears [[High-heeled footwear|high heeled shoes]], which are not necessarily appropriate or practical for the work she does and sometimes hamper her. It was her reluctance to climb stairs in her high heels that first led her, in [[List of Primeval episodes#ep8|episode 2.2]] to learn the truth about the ARC's purpose. In Series 3 she was more &quot;sensible&quot; in the way she dressed, wearing more suitable clothing, with her hair down, and less make-up, causing her to resemble Claudia much more.

Claudia remains out of existence for the rest of the series, although Jenny first appears in [[List of Primeval episodes#ep7|episode 2.1]]. At the end of [[List of Primeval episodes#ep8|episode 2.2]], Cutter explains to Jenny as best he can about what could have happened to change the past. Claudia's job as Lester's assistant was changed to a man named Oliver Leek, who was revealed to be working for [[#Helen Cutter|Helen Cutter]]. It was implied that Helen was responsible for Claudia being replaced by Jenny, however this is thought not to be the case when Helen explains that the first change was an accident. It is still possible that Helen intentionally messed with Claudia/Jenny's past in order to enact revenge or to, as her obsessing in [[List of Primeval episodes#ep13|episode 2.7]] would imply, re-set the stage for her and Nick to get together again.

in episode 3.3 Jenny confessed to [[#Sarah Page|Sarah Page]] that she has fallen in love with [[#Nick Cutter|Nick Cutter]]. When Cutter was preparing to go back inside the burning ARC to look for Helen in [[List of Primeval episodes#ep16|episode 3.3]], Jenny asked him not to go and thought it was a mistake, which is reference to what [[#Claudia Brown|Claudia Brown]] said the last time Cutter saw her before going through the Permian Anomaly. Later, as Cutter was dying in Connor's arms, he started to ask Connor to tell Claudia something, but then changed his mind and said nothing.
When Nick dies as the ARC explodes, Jenny bursts into tears along with Abby and Connor, while Sarah watches on silently. Jenny said there was something she wanted to tell Nick and that was that she loved him. Jenny is promoted by Lester temporarily to team leader in episode 3.4, though has difficulty dealing with Cutter's death. In the following episode, Jenny discovers a photograph of Claudia Brown amongst Cutter's remaining possessions, realising that she has in fact lived a double life. At the end of the episode, after dying within the ARC and then being resuscitated by the team, she makes the decision to leave her position for the Anomaly Research Centre.

Later though in Series 4 of Primeval an anomaly opens in a mansion where Jenny and a her fiancé are to be wed. Although she did not want to bump into them she invites them to the wedding. Connor then reopens the anomaly after locking it and releases two prehistoric wolves, Hyenadons, on the loose causing havoc. Fortunately Matt, Jenny, Abby and Emily take care of the creatures, and James Lester marries Jenny and her fiancé.
{{clear}}

== M ==

=== Abby Maitland ===
{{Infobox character
| name             = Abby Sarah Maitland
| first            = [[Episode 1 (Primeval)|Episode 1.1]]
| last             = 
| portrayer        = [[Hannah Spearritt]]
| gender           = Female
| occupation       = [[Zookeeper]]
| family           = [[#Jack Maitland|Jack Maitland]] (brother)
| significantother = [[#Connor Temple|Connor Temple]] (fiancé)
}}
'''Abby Sarah Maitland''' is played by [[Hannah Spearritt]].

ITV's official site says that while Abby has arachnophobia she developed a love of reptiles when her parents took her on holiday to the [[Galapagos Islands]] as a child and has had a love affair with lizards ever since. Although she started university she later left after only one term when she became a zookeeper. Always fit and athletic, her hobbies include gymnastics, [[Raja Yoga|Ashtanga]] yoga, karate, kick boxing, swimming and diving. She keeps gym equipment in her flat. Actress [[Hannah Spearritt]] also stated that Abby was [[child abuse|abused as a child]]. In Series 1 she seemed to be attracted to [[#Stephen Hart|Stephen Hart]], but in the second season she seems to be falling in love with [[#Connor Temple|Connor Temple]].

She openly admits to falling in love with the wrong type of men - moody and dangerous. She also appears to have her feelings hurt easily but struggles to remain upbeat and positive.&lt;ref name=&quot;epTwo&quot;/&gt; She can also be remarkably deceitful in order to get her own way as she lies to the government and to her team mates about her experiences with spiders so they will take her with them. She would not tell anyone that [[List of creatures in Primeval#Coelurosauravus|Rex]] came back through the anomaly with [[#Nick Cutter|Nick Cutter]].

She is a zookeeper who first appears in the series when a small boy called Ben who alerts the zoo she works at about an escaped lizard he misidentifies as a modern day lizard named [[Draco volans]].&lt;ref name=&quot;epTwo&quot; /&gt; She later angers Cutter when she and Connor go off to find an anomaly by themselves but is allowed to stay because he admits he needs her skills. She later allows Connor to move into her flat on a purely platonic basis. She remains as the team lab assistant and sidekick up until [[List of Primeval episodes#ep4|episode 1.4]] when she is almost contaminated by a deadly parasite by a student friend of work/flatmate Connor Temple.&lt;ref name=&quot;epFour&quot;/&gt;

Her love/hate relationship with Connor reaches a peak in [[List of Primeval episodes#ep5|episode 1.5]]&lt;ref name=&quot;epFive&quot; /&gt; when she is enraged that he let everyone know that she's been keeping Rex in secret but later says that if he makes her breakfast on the weekends and does the washing up for a month then he can stay. She admits that this compromise is really because she actually likes having him around. Connor hugs her, prompting Abby to say she likes having him around as a friend, hinting that she is beginning to fall in love with him. How Abby has been changed by the alterations in the timeline is unknown. Connor now has a [[#Caroline Steel|girlfriend]] in this new timeline but how this affects their relationship is unknown. Connor's girlfriend, much to Abby's horror, hates lizards, and the two do not get along.&lt;ref name=s2qna /&gt; Also, her crush on Stephen, and their closeness because of it, seems to have completely disappeared in the second season.

In [[List of Primeval episodes#ep7|episode 2.1]], Abby and Connor seem to have a much closer relationship than they did previously. This comes to the extent that Abby pays for Connor's slushie and lets Connor use her gun, even though there is a pack of ''[[Deinonychus]]'' on the loose. Abby has a much better flat in the second series, and the reptile species that she keeps includes Rex the [[Coelurosauravus]], a [[corn snake]], a [[milk snake]], [[leopard gecko]]s, [[bearded dragon]]s and a [[boa constrictor]]. In [[List of Primeval episodes#ep8|episode 2.2]], Abby is quietly jealous of Caroline Steel who Connor seems to have a relationship with. It is clear that Abby disapproves however, as she shows no sympathy when Connor has to leave for work or when he accidentally washes his number off. In [[List of Primeval episodes#ep10|episode 2.4]], Abby is attacked by a [[List of creatures in Primeval#Mer|futuristic Mer]], and dragged through an anomaly to the future. Connor runs through, despite being injured, alone to help her, and tries to pull her over an overhang, and as he appears to be able to get her over, a massive Mer looms over them, preparing to kill them. Abby begs him to let her go and escape, but he refuses, finally bursting out, 'I can't! I love you!' She would later confront him about the matter but at this point Caroline Steel comes for her date with Connor. Ironically, at one point Abby defeats a Mer using a kickboxing move that Caroline showed her, thus Caroline probably indirectly and unknowingly saved Abby's life.

In the Series 2 finale, Abby is captured with the rest of the team and held captive. When Caroline is thrown into the cell with Connor and Abby, the two girls fight, punching and kicking each other. Eventually Abby slams Caroline against a wall, but Caroline uses her superior strength to pin Abby down. Abby bites her and she lets go, and the two continue to grapple briefly, much to Connor's shock and Leek's amusement. Connor succeeds in breaking up the fight but when Caroline thanks him, he says &quot;I didn't do it for you&quot; and seems to remain close to Abby throughout the episode. Surprisingly, she later forgives Caroline and even saves her life when they are kept in a room with a [[List of creatures in Primeval#Smilodon|smilodon]]. Abby splits off from the group as a distraction, and inadvertently turns off the power system and releases the creatures. Rex is shot in the episode, and Abby looks after him (but not before thanking Caroline for saving him). At the end of the episode, Abby and the rest of the team are at Stephen's funeral, where Abby lays flowers for him. As they leave, Abby reaches to hold Connor's hand, but the team get called out to an anomaly.

In series 3, she and Connor continued to grow closer, though they were reluctant to do anything about their attraction. In episode 3.4 she is revealed to have a brother, Jack, who stays with her and forces Connor to move out temporarily. During episode 3.8 Abby desperately went through an anomaly to rescue Jack after he went through accidentally, risking her own life and the others because she didn't want to lose him. At the end of the episode she and Connor kissed after Jack admitted to her that Connor had helped him get Rex back and losing him in a poker game, thankful that he hadn't made Jack look bad. At the start of episode 3.9, Abby visits Connor and explains that she does not want things to be 'weird' between them, making their relationship indefinite. However when the pair are trapped in the Cretaceous while chasing Helen with new team leader Danny Quinn, she helps him to relax, and agrees to let him move back into her flat once they return home.

The [[List of Primeval episodes#ep24|episode 4.1]], Connor and Abby have been living in the Cretaceous period for a year and by this time, Abby had lost all faith in getting back to the present. However, after finding an anomaly device they do manage to get back to the present, and both are told by the ARC that they are fired, due to new regulations stating that employees must be from a military/police background; although Lester later reinstates them in [[List of Primeval episodes#ep25|episode 4.2]]. The opening episodes also show that Connor and Abby are a couple, this is shown by the two kissing at the end of 4.1, and Abby telling Duncan that she is Connor's girlfriend. However their relationship becomes strained as they readjust to their jobs, particularly when Connor doesn't stay to support her as she tries to stop Philip Burton from killing the Rex and the other creatures in the ARC in episode 4.4, and when he blurts out about the possibility of getting married in episode 4.6.

In the fifth series she learned of Matt's mission and lent her help, though her relationship with Connor became strained as she couldn't tell him why she was trying to stop his obsessive work for Philip. In episode 5.3 she wasn't happy when Connor's new assistant April Leonard suggested that she was nothing but a distraction for him, and this emboldened her to copy Connor's hard drive, despite refusing Matt's earlier requests. When he caught her near his lab she tried to appeal to him by revealing Helen and Philip's association, though his apparent knowledge made him adamant she only wanted him away from Philip, creating further tension between them. She was furious at him when he opened his own anomaly in the ARC in episode 5.4, and set out to find Rex when he was loose in the ARC with an imminent gamma ray to kill a swarm of future beetles. In episode 5.5 she rescued Connor from a Kaprosuchus after he had been abandoned by Philip, and the two made up as Connor had realised he should have trusted Abby over Philip. At the New Dawn facility she threatened April with her EMD, and tried to go after Connor when he was pulled through the anomaly as it opened. In the series finale she and Matt go to rescue him from a pack of mutated Future Predators, and encourages Connor to return when he gives up hope, whispering something in his ear. After returning she comes up with a plan to paralyse the Predators in the ARC by using high frequency sounds, and once the crisis is over she asks Connor to marry her (what she told him in the future), which he agreed to.
{{clear}}

=== Jack Maitland ===
{{Infobox character
| name        = Jack Maitland
| first       = Episode 3.4
| last        = Episode 3.8
| portrayer   = [[Robert Lowe]]
| gender      = Male
}}
Jack Maitland is the brother of Abby Maitland, played by Robert Lowe. He first appears in [[List of Primeval episodes#ep17|episode 3.4]], when Connor mistakenly believes that Jack is Abby's boyfriend after he answers Abby's phone while she's out of the room. At the end of the episode Abby explains that Jack is her brother but asks Connor to move out for a couple of days so that Jack can stay with her. In [[List of Primeval episodes#ep19|episode 3.6]], he invited his friends for a game of poker and used Rex. He gambled Rex and put him up for auction and neither Connor or Abby were happy with him. Connor felt he could've made Jack feel bad after he got Rex back from his friend, Tony, but he did not. In [[List of Primeval episodes#ep21|episode 3.8]], he stole Abby's anomaly detector and found out she worked in a dangerous place and while playing around in a sports car, he went through the anomaly. He fell in a trap underground and broke his arm. He shouted &quot;Help!&quot; and Abby heard him. They got him safe and they all shouted at him for nearly killing Becker (and almost himself). Jack moved out at the end of series three, and it was implied that Connor then moved back in with Abby. It is unknown if he knew of Abby's year-long disappearance.
{{clear}}

===Emily Merchant===
{{Infobox character
| name             = Emily Merchant
| first            = [[List of Primeval episodes#ep26|Episode 4.3]]
| last             = 
| portrayer        = [[Ruth Bradley]]
| gender           = Female
| occupation       = 
| spouse = Henry Merchant (deceased)
| significantother = Matt
| nationality      = English 
}}
Emily Merchant is a 28-year-old English woman&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.itv.com/drama/primeval/theteam/emilymerchant/ Primeval - The Team]&lt;/ref&gt; who appeared in a theatre via an anomaly in [[List of Primeval episodes#ep26|episode 4.3]]. Born in London in 1840, she is familiar with travelling in time and was previously living with a group in the Cretaceous. She carries a [[stiletto]] and is capable of holding her own in a fight with humans or creatures.

She and Ethan Dobrowski brought a sick woman, their friend Charlotte Cameron, to modern London in the hope of finding medical treatment. After Charlotte died she returned to the Cretaceous, but Matt brought her back thinking she was from the present and been attacked by a [[List of creatures in Primeval#Tree Creeper|tree creeper]]. She then asked him to keep her presence secret while she tried to find Ethan Dobrowski. In [[List of Primeval episodes#ep27|episode 4.4]] she was kidnapped by Ethan from Matt's flat. In [[List of Primeval episodes#ep28|episode 4.5]] Ethan took her to a cemetery and left her tied and gagged in a coffin, until she was rescued by Matt. She forms a close relationship with Matt Anderson, but in episode 4.6 she is revealed to have been married before she went through the anomalies, but told Matt that she had only married out of her father's wishes and had never loved him. In [[List of Primeval episodes#ep30|episode 4.7]] she returns to the 19th Century so as not to distract Matt from his mission to save humanity, which he admitted after she figured out he wasn't from the present day.

She features in episode 5.3, where she has been trying to find a creature that has been killing people in  19th C London, while being forced back into a subservient role by her husband Henry. She reunites with Matt, and refuses to hear what Matt has learned about her future until Henry arrives. Abby and Matt had discovered that Henry would institutionalise her for apparent insanity, though mostly for the position she has been putting him in lately. After capturing the raptor she initially refuses to return with him to the present, but does so when Henry arrives and threatens Matt at gunpoint, and after he is killed by the raptor she decides to stay. During the next few episodes she becomes part of the ARC team, helping with creature incursions.
{{clear}}

== P ==

=== Sarah Page ===
{{Infobox character
| name        = Sarah Page
| first       = [[List of Primeval episodes#ep14|episode 3.1]]
| last        = [[Primeval (Episode 23)|Episode 3.10]]
| portrayer   = [[Laila Rouass]]
| gender      = Female
| occupation  = Egyptologist
}}
Sarah Page studies Egyptology before joining the Primeval team in Series 3. She joins after witnessing a creature attack the British History Museum in the first episode. Cutter is impressed with her skills and asks her to join the team, which she accepts. after she makes a remark, Cutter sets her the task of finding out if the old myths and legends of the past could have a link with the anomalies. Sarah is shown to have a brother and sister type relationship with Connor.
When the ARC is attacked by Helen's Cleaner Clones in [[List of Primeval episodes#ep16|episode 3.3]], she is captured along with Jenny and Lester. She is the one who makes the audio tape that eventually stops Helen's clones. Sarah makes it out of the fire raging inside the ARC and watches on in shock while Cutter is lying dead on the floor after Connor has brought him from the exploding building.

In [[List of Primeval episodes#ep17|episode 3.4]], Sarah works with Connor on cleaning up the 'artifact' that Cutter took from Helen and finds out that it contains a map of the matrix of anomalies that Cutter had created at the beginning of the series.
In [[List of Primeval episodes#ep19|episode 3.6]], she is forced to go into hiding with Danny, Connor and Abby after Christine Johnson takes over the ARC, she and the rest of the team are forced to take refuge in an old abandoned cabin. When Lester is reinstated to the ARC thanks to Becker, Sarah kisses Becker on the cheek as a reward. After episode 3.6, she takes a more hands on approach and goes out with the team to the anomaly sites, she goes back in time to find out information about the knight who came through an anomaly. In [[List of Primeval episodes#ep22|episode 3.9]], she finds out that the woman who Danny is with is actually Helen Cutter in disguise, but she is too late to stop her from taking Christine Johnson hostage. In [[Primeval (Episode 23)|episode 3.10]], she and Becker are the only two members of the team to be in the present day, with Connor, Abby and Danny stuck on the other sides of different anomalies. She ends by saying she has an idea although it is unexplained what this is.

Sarah Page did not return in series 4. Her death was implied through Becker's flashback in a [[List of Primeval episodes#epW1|series 4 webisode]]. Becker and Sarah are known to have led rescue missions to try and find the others by going through the future anomaly. During their last attempt, Sarah was killed by an unknown creature, though it is implied to be a Future Predator as her cries to Becker are heard over a visual of a Predator attacking a the car she was probably in.
{{clear}}

=== Jess Parker ===
{{Infobox character
| name        = Jess Parker
| first       = [[List of Primeval episodes#ep24|Episode 4.1]]
| last        = 
| portrayer   = [[Ruth Kearney]]
| gender      = Female
| occupation  = Field Coordinator
}}
Jess Parker is the team's field coordinator, using her skills to help the team and direct their movements, all from her control station at the ARC. Although only 19,&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.itv.com/drama/primeval/theteam/jessparker/ Primeval - The Team]&lt;/ref&gt; Jess displays an outstanding level of organisation and efficiency, providing a stable environment for the team during their missions, and also has a crush on Becker.

Jess accidentally released the Dracorex from the ARC's containment in the beginning of Series 4, and later coordinated the team as they dealt with a Spinosaurus that had followed Connor and Abby through the Anomaly. She was sympathetic towards Connor as his job had been rendered unnecessary since his disappearance, and offered for him and Abby to stay at her flat. When Matt was gone she asked him to get her some chocolates but he forgot, however Becker got her some, leaving her flustered as she later asked about the old team and Becker. She didn't seem to realise the seriousness of the job until she witnessed a teenager being killed on CCTV footage in episode 4.4. She was afraid when Becker was poisoned by a creature, but relieved when he recovered and tried comforting him. In episode 4.6 she joins Becker on his stakeout to catch Ethan Dobrowski, and instead of fleeing a trap that Becker was caught in stayed to disarm the bomb, and she hugged him in relief.

She is allergic to insect bites and keeps an epi pen, as shown in episode 5.4 when she is bitten by a future beetle and almost dies. Becker takes care of her throughout this ordeal, determined to get her help, showing her feelings may be returned.
{{clear}}

== Q ==

=== Danny Quinn ===
{{Infobox character
| name        = Danny Quinn
| first       = [[List of Primeval episodes#ep15|Episode 3.2]]
| last        = 
| portrayer   = [[Jason Flemyng]]
| gender      = Male
| occupation  = Former Police Officer
                Team Leader
| significantother = 
| children    =   
| relatives   = [[#Ethan Dobrowski|Patrick Quinn (Ethan Dobrowski)]] (brother)
| nationality = [[English people|English]] 
}}
Danny Quinn is a former Police officer and team leader, and is played by [[Jason Flemyng]]

He was investigating the death of two teenagers (one being his brother, Patrick) in a house believed to be haunted. He suspected Ryan Mason as the murderer, as he was the third teenager in the house, who escaped. Danny frequently went to the house to arrest trespassers, and at first thought the team were breaking in. He then arrests Connor and discovers a futuristic camouflaging creature, as well as the anomalies. He discovers that the creature was the one that murdered his brother. He shoots the creature back through the anomaly. He returns, following the team on his motorbike when they arrive in an airport and pilots a helicopter through the anomaly so the Giganotosaurus that had come through followed him back. He is lucky to escape, as when he returns to the present he is being hunted by a pack of creatures, and Connor locks the anomaly just in time. In the next episode he breaks into the ARC and, armed with flamethrowers, searches for a fungus creature in the London underground with the team. He plans to burn it but Sarah phones Jenny to warn him not to use the flamethrowers. The team manage to get the creature into a van, then he drives it back into the ARC. They then lose the creature briefly, but it appears in the communications room, while Jenny is still there. He risks his life to go in the frozen room to distract the creature, thus saves Jenny's life. Lester decides he will be the new team leader, as suggested by Jenny, who decided to leave. It was implied that he fancied Jenny, but she left the team too soon for any relationship to occur between them.

While checking security in the ARC he breaks through the ventilation shafts and then battles the titanis tricking them into the anomaly by using a loud speakerphone recording of their calling. He later battles Sir William, a medieval knight, and is almost run through by his sword. He is revealed to know Latin fairly fluently. During a trip to the future in [[List of Primeval episodes#ep21|episode 3.8]] he witnessed Eve (Helen Cutter in disguise) enter the present, and in the following episode rescued her from Christine Johnson's base, returning her to the ARC before realising who she really was. Along with Connor, Abby, Sarah and Becker he follows her back to Johnson's HQ and witnesses the death of Christine at the hands of a Future Predator. In the following episode he travels back to the future with Connor and Abby, only to chase Helen into the past, and onwards into the deeper past alone, after Connor is injured. Danny witnesses the death of Helen in the deep past, and assures that the human race survives, before finding himself stranded when the anomaly closes. Trapped, alone in the past, Danny cries out in anger as Series 3 draws to a close.

Danny returned in the episode 4.7, having survived his time in the [[Pliocene]]. However as he came through the anomaly he was shot by Matt Anderson with an EMD. He woke up sometime later, relieved to be back. While the team were also dealing with a man named Ethan, Danny helped Abby and Connor in sending a Terror Bird through a satellite anomaly. When Ethan held Danny at gunpoint, he recognised him as his brother Patrick, who had survived his encounter with the camouflage beast and had been driven mad while going through the anomalies. He reported Helen's death to a pleased Lester, and was suspicious of Philip Burton when they met, having found a document on Helen's body with Philip's name on it. While speaking with Patrick he pleaded to be allowed to go through the anomaly, only to be knocked out. He and Matt went after Patrick, who escaped into the Pliocene. Danny decided to follow him, unwilling to risk Patrick making it to another human inhabited era. Before he departed he left a warning to Matt that Philip couldn't be trusted, asking him to warn the others.
&lt;!--Please don't make statements about Danny in future episodes without citing a source--&gt;
{{clear}}

== R ==

=== Tom Ryan ===
{{Infobox character
| name        = Tom Ryan
| first       = [[Episode 1 (Primeval)|Episode 1.1]]
| last        = [[Episode 6 (Primeval)|Episode 1.6]]
| portrayer   = [[Mark Wakeling]]
| gender      = Male
| occupation  = Special Ops Captain
| title       = Captain
}}
'''Captain Tom Ryan''' is played by Mark Wakeling. He was the leader of the [[special forces]] unit that supported [[#Nick Cutter|Nick Cutter]] and his team. Ryan was said to have joined the army at 17, saw active service in both Gulf wars, joined the SAS, then transferred to a special elite unit engaged in top secret operations. He had led an army walking team to the South Pole and back in record time and commented that it was chilly on his return. He was attacked by a Future Predator at the end of series one and died shortly afterwards.&lt;ref name=tomryan&gt;[http://www.douglashenshall.com/Primeval_facts_Tom_Ryan.html Primeval ITV:Tom Ryan Factfile&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt; He was replaced in Series 3, by [[#Captain Becker|Captain Becker]].

Ryan was a background character who was in charge of the military support, but generally followed Cutter's orders, whilst deferring to the government officials. When told to shoot the flying creature on the golf course he does so despite Cutter's protests, and in [[List of Primeval episodes#ep3|episode 1.3]] he is willing to capture Helen Cutter when ordered to, despite Cutter's disapproval. In general, he does not appear to have a close relationship with the rest of the team.

In his final scene he attempts to save Cutter by opening fire on the futuristic beast, knowing full well it will give his position away and he is mortally wounded. Cutter rushes to him after the beast is killed by a gorgonopsid, and Captain Ryan reminisces
about their first trip through the anomaly.&lt;ref name=tomryan/&gt; It soon becomes clear that Ryan's role in the series is as a catalyst for the change in the timeline that occurs at the end of Series 1.

In [[Episode 1 (Primeval)|episode 1.1]] he first appears towards the end as they are about to perform an expedition into the anomaly. It is said he has seen action in the first gulf war and has had experience in desert combat. When Cutter refuses to leave towards the end of the expedition he knocks Cutter out with the handle of his pistol. When Cutter comes round he hits him but Ryan hits him back harder and tells him not to do that, he says he will stay with Cutter if he refuses to leave but both decide to leave. In episode 1.2 he leads the special forces unit into the London underground where they come into contact with Prehistoric spiders the team cannot fire in enclosed spaces and try to fight them off with their fists but are forced back because of the sheer number of them. He then later accompanies Connor and Cutter to collect venom from the giant centipede in the tube station, once the venom has been collected Cutter tells him to finish off the centipede but despite initial success shooting him the centipede disarms him but Connor comes in with a chair forcing him in to a generator electrocuting and killing it. In episode 1.3 he firstly helps operate the rope on Cutter when he dives through the underwater anomaly and helps pull him out when a mosasaur destroys his oxygen tank then leads the special forces into the anomaly to capture Helen Cutter and forcibly bring her back.

In episode 1.4 his team accompany Helen Cutter to an anomaly where a pack of saber tooth tigers are supposed to be, and when she escapes he pursues her but she escapes through a series of anomalies on the other side. Then a flock of dodos come through the anomaly. Cutter and his team, with difficulty, round up all but one of the dodos and send them back through the anomaly. When an infected Tom, Connor's friend, attacks Abby he and his special forces team arrive and fix their laser sights on him but before they can shoot him Connor blocks the way and despite his protest he is forced not to shoot and Connor talks Tom out of his rage. In episode 1.5 his team accompany Cutter to a golf course where a flying creature is killing people, when ordered to shoot it he obeys but Cutter pushes him making his shot miss. He looks at Cutter resentfully. At the end when the creature flies back into the void while everyone else in Cutters team are cheering he simply lowers his gun and appears happy. In [[Episode 6 (Primeval)|episode 1.6]] when pursuing the futuristic creature he says to Cutter he is happy that the team is allowed to kill this one as he was starting to feel &quot;like a bloody social worker.&quot; He is mortally wounded by the futuristic predator, and correctly predicts himself to be the skeleton they found in the first episode

The BBC America website revealed that initially Captain Ryan was going to be killed off in the first episode, but Mark Wakeling acted so well that they commissioned him for the entire series. Henshall also stated that he would have wanted Ryan to be like the character of [[Kenny McCormick]] in [[South Park]], being killed and resurrected throughout the different series.
{{clear}}

== S ==

=== Caroline Steel ===
{{Infobox character
| name        = Caroline Steel
| first       = [[List of Primeval episodes#ep8|Episode 2.2]]
| last        = [[List of Primeval episodes#ep13|Episode 2.7]]
| portrayer   = Naomi Bentley
| gender      = Female
| occupation  = 
}}
'''Caroline Steel''' is a supporting villain played by [[Naomi Bentley]]. Steel meets [[#Connor Temple|Connor Temple]] in [[List of Primeval episodes#ep8|episode 2.2]] in a local DVD store where Connor was looking for science fiction DVDs.&lt;ref name=&quot;epSeven&quot;&gt;{{cite episode|title=Episode 1|episodelink=List of Primeval episodes#ep7|series=Primeval|network=[[ITV]]|airdate=10 February 2008|seriesno=2|number=1|minutes= }}&lt;/ref&gt;

She loves cats and dogs, but is scared of lizards (possibly all reptiles) much to the shock of [[#Abby Maitland|Abby Maitland]]. It is eventually revealed that Steel is working for [[#Oliver Leek|Oliver Leek]] (though she is largely ignorant of Leek's plans), and is using Connor to get to the team. Caroline has plans to appear on television, but so far has failed to appear upon ''[[Big Brother (UK)|Big Brother]]'' and ''[[The X Factor (UK)|X Factor]]''. Apparently she is 22 years old, 157 centimetres tall and was born in Hackney, London. She enjoys running, dancing, [[fencing]], squash, kick boxing, [[paintball]]ing and &quot;[[Metal detector#As a hobby|metal detector]]&quot;. Her bitter rivalry with Abby arises from Abby's suspicions that Caroline's interest in Connor is not genuine.

In [[List of Primeval episodes#ep11|episode 2.5]], furious about being dumped by Connor, Caroline attacks [[List of creatures in Primeval#Coelurosauravus|Rex]], so as to avenge herself against Abby. She takes Rex to Leek, who pays a substantial bounty. When Caroline asks what the job was about, Leek offers to show her and takes her to see his secret facility, knowing that Cutter's team will attempt to retrieve Rex by triangulating the signal from Caroline's mobile phone - thereby leading them into Leek's trap.&lt;ref name=&quot;epTwelve&quot;&gt;{{cite episode|title=Episode 6|episodelink=List of Primeval episodes#ep12|series=Primeval|network=[[ITV]]|airdate=25 March 2008|seriesno=2|number=6|minutes= }}&lt;/ref&gt;

In [[List of Primeval episodes#ep13|episode 2.7]], Caroline arrives to look at what Leek is actually doing with Rex. She is immediately repulsed, and keeps asking Leek why she cannot go home. Leek takes her and the rest of the team hostage. In their cell, she is threatened by Abby, and the two of them fight, punching and kicking each other. Connor splits them up, and Caroline thanks him. Connor replies &quot;I didn't do it for you&quot;. She explains that she was money-driven and asks Connor for forgiveness. Not only does Connor accept her apology, but Abby saves Caroline's life from a [[List of creatures in Primeval#Smilodon|sabre-toothed cat]]. Later on, as they escape, Caroline even shows sympathy to Rex, rescuing him after he is injured.&lt;ref name=&quot;epThirteen&quot;&gt;{{cite episode|title=Episode 7|episodelink=List of Primeval episodes#ep13|series=Primeval|network=[[ITV]]|airdate=31 March 2008|seriesno=2|number=7|minutes= }}&lt;/ref&gt;

Later on, Caroline is seen briefly at Stephen's funeral, despite the two characters never meeting on screen, and tries to remind Connor that he still has her mobile number.&lt;ref name=&quot;epThirteen&quot;/&gt; She then leaves and does not return to the series.
{{clear}}

== T ==

=== Connor Temple ===
{{Infobox character
| name        = Connor Temple
| first       = [[Episode 1 (Primeval)|episode 1.1]]
| last        = 
| portrayer   = [[Andrew-Lee Potts]]
| gender      = Male
| occupation  = 
| significantother = [[Abby Maitland]] (fiancée)
| children    =   
| relatives   = 
| nationality = [[English people|English]] 
}}
'''Connor Temple''' is played by [[Andrew-Lee Potts]], who relates strongly to his character.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.radiotimes.com/content/show-features/primeval/andrew-lee-potts-on-primeval Radio Times interview with Andrew-Lee Potts]&lt;/ref&gt; He is one of the main characters, a student of [[Palaeontology]] at the (fictional) Central Metropolitan University. He is one of a group of people who discover that [[List of creatures in Primeval|prehistoric and extinct animals]] are passing through [[Anomaly (Primeval)|anomalies in time and space]]. When the [[Home Office]] assigns his professor [[#Nick Cutter|Nick Cutter]] to tackling the problems these creatures cause, Connor tags along and is accepted as an aid to the rest of the team.

Connor is seen as a [[geek]], he enjoys [[science fiction on television|science fiction television]] and [[science fiction film|film]]s such as ''[[Blake's 7]]'', ''[[Battlestar Galactica (1978 TV series)]]'' and ''[[Star Wars]]''.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.thetelegraphandargus.co.uk/leisure/theatre/theatrefeatures/display.var.1167309.0.primetime_andrew.php Telegraph and Argus interview with Andrew-Lee Potts]&lt;/ref&gt; He has an enormous interest in dinosaurs and other prehistoric animals, and has created a database of prehistoric creatures. He is also interested in [[conspiracy theory|conspiracy theories]] and [[cryptozoology]]. It is this interest in these that piques his interest in a reported monster sighting (of a [[List of creatures in Primeval#Gorgonopsid|Gorgonopsid]] near the [[Forest of Dean]]), which he takes to Nick Cutter and eventually leads him and the others into discovering a [[Anomaly (Primeval)]] over the course of [[Episode 1 (Primeval)|episode 1.1]]. At the beginning of series one, Connor is seen as a student of [[#Nick Cutter|Nick Cutter]], but one who does not attend many lectures, although he has already completed his dissertation. Later in [[Episode 1 (Primeval)|episode 1.1]], he claims he has 'sinus issues and allergies', but his database proves invaluable and he becomes part of the team. In [[List of Primeval episodes#ep2|episode 1.2]], he admits he started the [[Duke of Edinburgh's Award]], but did not complete it, due to a sprained ankle.

While Connor finds the idea of the time anomalies exciting, he questions his own usefulness after he leads [[#Abby Maitland|Abby Maitland]] on a wild goose chase in [[List of Primeval episodes#ep2|episode 1.2]], especially after being reprimanded for it. He is also admittedly unsettled and afraid of some of the more dangerous creatures. Later, he almost leaves the team after one of his friends is killed by a [[List of creatures in Primeval#Parasite|parasite]] from the past in [[List of Primeval episodes#ep4|episode 1.4]], but is persuaded to stay by Cutter. He has a well known crush on Abby, who he is currently living with. Although, he ended up dating a girl named [[#Caroline Steel|Caroline Steel]] in the alternate timeline.

Connor Temple still lives in Abby's flat in Series 2, and the pair still have a close bond. In [[List of Primeval episodes#ep7|episode 2.1]] Abby and Connor seem to spend a lot more time together than they did in the previous series. Connor is also irritated by the fact that the rest of the team do not trust him with firearms. In [[List of Primeval episodes#ep7|episode 2.1]] he accidentally shoots Abby with a tranquilliser dart intended for a baby ''[[Deinonychus]]'' and in [[List of Primeval episodes#ep9|episode 2.3]] he shoots a costumed man playing the furry mascot of an adventure park, mistaking him for a [[List of creatures in Primeval#Smilodon|sabre-toothed cat]] (though being such a poor shot, he fortunately does no real damage). Connor makes himself useful to the team by building, programming and operating the Anomaly Detection Device, based on Cutter's discovery that anomalies cause radio interference. Connor is also the first character to notice that the team is being followed by a mysterious man, who later turns out to have been working for [[#Oliver Leek|Oliver Leek]].

In the second series, Connor also gets a new girlfriend called [[#Caroline Steel|Caroline Steel]]. Caroline and Connor meet in a DVD store and he invites her back to Abby's flat with him. After Connor nearly gets eaten by a [[List of creatures in Primeval#Worm|giant worm]] in the episode and gets covered in giant worm slime, he accidentally wipes Caroline's number off his hand. Connor clearly worries about Caroline, and by the end of the episode seems to put her ahead of Abby, much to the latter's confusion. In [[List of Primeval episodes#ep10|episode 2.4]], Connor is distraught when Abby is mistaken as dead, and searches for her. He does eventually find her, but is dragged into the future by a creature. When Abby is dangling from the side of a cliff, Connor tells her that he loves her. Abby later confronts Connor about this, but due to embarrassment, did not re-approach the matter, and went on a date with Caroline, leaving Abby upset and confused. In [[List of Primeval episodes#ep11|episode 2.5]], Connor dumps Caroline after he believes that the two are not ideal for one another. (In fact, unknown to him, Caroline has been paid by [[#Oliver Leek|Oliver Leek]] to spy on Connor.) This now opens him up to Abby, and seeks [[#Stephen Hart|Stephen's]] help as he is still unsure of whether Abby is interested in him. Connor remained faithful to Abby throughout the final episode of the season, and drags her out of a fight with Caroline. Connor was shocked to find out that Caroline only went out with him because she was getting paid. Leek says that he and Connor are similar, saying that they are both &quot;Uncool, nerdy and never get the attractive girls&quot;. To this Connor makes another sarcastic remark, saying &quot;Speak for yourself&quot;. Connor is very caring towards Jenny, Abby and Caroline, whom he makes sure all climb the ladder to escape before he does. Finally, Connor is seen at the end of the episode at Stephen's funeral. He seems close to Abby, but surprisingly Caroline is invited to the funeral, despite the fact the two characters never met. Caroline reminds Connor he has her mobile number and then quickly leaves. As Connor and Abby themselves leave, Abby makes to hold Connor's hand, but Cutter receives an urgent call of a high-priority anomaly. In one of the final scenes, Connor is seen in the back of Cutter's car with a gun, suggesting that Cutter is trusting him with guns.

In the third season his and Abby's relationship continues to grow stronger, though neither continue to do anything about it. In episode 3.3 he adopts a pair of Diictodon trapped in the present, naming them Sid and Nancy. After the ARC exploded Connor ran back into the building to find Cutter. When he did he found that he had been shot. Connor wants to help him, but Cutter tells him to sit down and they start to talk. Cutter tells him that he is now in charge and has to carry on his work of tracking and exploring the anomalies. He then gives him the mysterious artefact that Helen was trying to work out what it was. Connor is then seen carrying Cutter's body out of the burning building and then after everyone realises he is dead he is seen crying and comforting a crying Abby. In [[List of Primeval episodes#ep18|episode 3.4]] Connor was still distraught over his death, and set about creating a device to lock anomalies, and was worried when he heard Abby was hanging out with someone else. However it was only Abby's baby brother Jack, who was going to be staying at her flat, forcing him to move out for a while. He eventually moves in with James Lester after a short time staying in the ARC. In episode 3.6 he and Sarah Page get the artefact to open for a short while, revealing that it predicted anomalies and that Cutter  had been right about its importance, and did his best to keep it safe when the team was hiding from Christine Johnson and a flock of terror birds. At the end of [[List of Primeval episodes#ep21|episode 3.8]], Abby kisses Connor after she finds out from Jack, that Connor got Rex back after Jack lost him in a game of poker which he did as he didn't want to hurt Abby when she was already distraught. In episode 3.9 they agree to try and not make things weird between them, and realised Helen had invaded the ARC with Sarah. In the Series 3 finale he, Abby and Danny go in pursuit of Helen and he discovers that Helen will be the cause of Site 333, the location of the [[AL 333|First Family]], a group of thirteen homonids who all died mysteriously at once, from Helen poisoning them. Connor was injured while fighting a pack of raptors in the Cretaceous, and Abby stays with him in the while Danny pursues Helen. They are last seen hiding in a tree as night falls, talking about going home.

In [[List of Primeval episodes#ep24|episode 4.1]], it is highlighted that Connor and Abby have been living in the Cretaceous period for a year. After a Velociraptor steals Abby's blanket, Connor goes to retrieve it from a Raptor's nest and finds Helen's anomaly device that she dropped in the series 3 finale. After using it to get back to the present, both are told by the ARC that they are fired, due to new regulations stating that employees must be from a military/police background (which neither are). Connor and Abby are a couple at this point, shown by the two kissing at the end of [[List of Primeval episodes#ep24|episode 4.1]], and Abby saying that she is &quot;his&quot; (Connor's) girlfriend to Duncan in [[List of Primeval episodes#ep25|episode 4.2]]. In the same episode Connor decided to track down his old friend after not being reinstated like Abby, and came to learn of a Kaprosuchus that had been causing trouble, and after helping deal with the creature got his old job back. Connor accidentally trapped Philip and Rex in a room with the oxygen being sucked out in episode 4.3, and after rectifying the situation Philip thanked him, seeing his talent. In episode 4.4 he saved two students from Therocephalians, and didn't support Abby's campaign to save the menagerie creatures following Philip's plan to kill them all. In episode 4.5, Philip asked Connor to work for him at Prospero studying the anomalies, and Connor was unsure, not wanting to abandon the team. After learning that acid was what was affecting an unstable anomaly, he believed that a Labyrinthodont had killed Abby he attacked it in a rage, only to learn she was okay and asked her not to make him worry like that again. He then agreed to work for Philip, but only in his spare time. In episode 4.6 he and Abby meet up with Jenny when she is getting married, and Connor blurted out the possibility of him and Abby getting married, which helped to create more tension in the relationship, particularly after he hadn't supported Abby. In episode 4.7 he became worried after figuring out two anomalies had opened on the same spot, and began to look into the ARC's anomaly data, discovering they were going to continue multiplying. After telling Philip, he asked they keep it between them until they found a solution.

In episode 5.1 Philip shows him his machine called New Dawn, from which he hopes to take energy from anomalies and turn it into green energy, and assigned Connor an assistant named April Leonard when he agreed to help. He was later taken by a burrowing creature from the future, but survived, and came up with a plan to blow up the rest of the creatures in a warehouse. In episode 5.3 Connor was kept busy by April, and when he caught Abby near his lab she tried to appeal to him by revealing Helen and Philip's association, though Philip had told him this already (having made him believe Helen had only known of Philip), and was adamant Abby only wanted him away from Philip, creating further tension between them. At the end of the episode he created his own anomaly in the ARC, and in episode 5.4 told Abby he only wanted to do what he thought what would make Cutter proud, and his anomaly caused a swarm of future beetles to invade the ARC. Connor tried to make up for what he had done, and came up with a plan to kill all the beetles by closing his anomaly and unleashing a gamma ray, though only after Matt and Abby revealed they possessed a copy of his laptop's hard drive (which Matt had earlier blasted) in order to allow this. He later learned that Philip had tried to blow the building up, and then went through Prospero's files, learning of Philip and Helen's  partnership and that Philip had created a larger version of his machine. In episode 5.5 he attempted to slow down Philip on the way to New Dawn, but when a Kaprosuchus attacked Philip refused to believe Connor's claims that New Dawn would destroy the world and was left behind. After being rescued by Abby, the two made up as Connor realised he should have trusted Abby over Philip. At the New Dawn facility he tried to go sabotage New Dawn, only to fail and fall  through the anomaly as it opened. In the series finale he is rescued from a pack of  Future Predators by Abby and Matt. He gave up hope until Abby whispered something in his ear which convinced him to continue. After returning he came up with a plan to merge his anomaly with the New Dawn one, which succeeded as it imploded. Once the crisis was over, it was revealed Abby had asked Connor to marry her while they had been in the future), which he agreed to.
{{clear}}

=== Tom ===
Tom (Jake Curran) should not be confused with [[#Tom Ryan|Tom Ryan]], an SAS soldier. He is a friend of [[#Connor Temple|Connor]] and [[#Duncan|Duncan]] and a fellow [[geek]]. He appears to be the bossier 'leader' of Connor's friends and is the one that seems to come up with the 'plans' whereas Duncan is quite happy to follow, he also seems to be slightly more aggressive than Duncan, both with and without the parasite infecting him.

He also seems to enjoy conspiracy theories. Despite this he does not believe Connor when he tries to tell he and Duncan what he has been involved in without breaking the [[Official Secrets Act]],&lt;ref name=&quot;epTwo&quot;/&gt; and he and Duncan devise their own conspiracy theories around the dodo that they capture (none of which are particularly rational).&lt;ref name=&quot;epFour&quot;/&gt;

He is infected by a prehistoric [[List of creatures in Primeval#Parasite|parasite]] which makes him more aggressive, [[Photophobia|photophobic]], and he attempts to pass on the parasite. He manages to avoid biting anyone apart from a doctor who was examining him. The team did not find him in time to save him which resulted in his death with his last words being &quot;I'm a hero.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;epFour&quot; /&gt;
{{clear}}

== W ==

=== Captain Wilder ===
{{Infobox character
| name        = Captain Wilder
| first       = [[List of Primeval episodes#ep17|Episode 3.4]]
| last        = [[List of Primeval episodes#ep22|Episode 3.9]]
| portrayer   = [[Alex McSweeney]]
| gender      = Male
| occupation  = Security
}}
Captain Wilder, played by [[Alex McSweeney]], is Christine Johnson's head of security in series 3. He takes an active role in several episodes and is Johnson's choice to succeed Nick Cutter as leader of the anomaly response team, as part of her plot to seize control of the ARC from James Lester. This fails, and Lester appoints Danny Quinn instead. It is also revealed that Captain Becker from the ARC knew Wilder at [[Royal Military Academy Sandhurst|Sandhurst]]. Later Wilder is recognised by Danny at a distance, leading to the discovery that Wilder and Johnson have captured Eve (actually the disguised Helen Cutter) from the future. In [[List of Primeval episodes#ep22|episode 3.9]] he points his gun at Helen who threatens to kill Johnston if the artifact is not given to her. In 3.10 a severed arm is seen and it is presumed to be his.
{{clear}}

== References ==
{{reflist}}

{{Primeval}}

{{Use dmy dates|date=January 2011}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:List Of Primeval Characters}}
[[Category:Primeval|Characters]]
[[Category:Lists of television characters|Primeval characters]]

[[fr:Personnages de Nick Cutter et les Portes du temps]]
[[no:Liste over rollefigurer i Portalen]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
