<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="10216818" ns="0" title="History of massively multiplayer online games"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Generalize|date=February 2010}}
{{Video RPG}}

The '''history of massively multiplayer online games''' spans over thirty years and hundreds of [[massively multiplayer online games]] (MMOG) titles.  The origin and influence on MMOG  games stems from [[MUD]]s, [[Dungeons and Dragons]] and earlier social games.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
 | url       = http://radoff.com/blog/2010/05/24/history-social-games/
 | author    = [[Jon Radoff]]
 | title     = History of Social Games
}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== The first virtual worlds ==

In 1974, ''[[Mazewar]]'' introduced the first graphic virtual world, providing a first-person perspective view of a maze in which players roamed around shooting at each other.  It was also the first networked game, in which players at different computers could visually interact in a virtual space. The initial implementation was over a [[serial cable]], but when one of the authors began attending [[Massachusetts Institute of Technology|MIT]] in 1974, the game was enhanced so that it could be played across the [[ARPAnet]], forerunner of the modern Internet.

[[Image:ADVENT -- Will Crowther's original version.png|thumb|[[Will Crowther]]'s ''Adventure''.]]
[[Image:MUDscreen.jpg|thumb|You haven't lived until you've died in MUD. -- The [[MUD1]] Slogan.]]

''[[Colossal Cave Adventure|Adventure]]'', created in 1975 by [[Will Crowther]] on a [[Digital Equipment Corporation|DEC]] [[PDP-10]] computer, was the first widely used [[adventure game]]. The game was significantly expanded in 1976 by [[Don Woods]]. ''Adventure'' contained many D&amp;D features and references, including a computer controlled [[dungeon master]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book
 | author    = [[Nick Montfort]]
 | title     = Twisty Little Passages: An Approach to Interactive Fiction
 | publisher = [[MIT Press]]
 | year      = 2003
 | isbn      = 354063293X
 | url       = http://books.google.com/?id=XiJFORKEm0oC
 | quote     =
}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
 | url       = http://www.livinginternet.com/d/di_major.htm
 | author    = Bill Stewart
 | title     = Summary MUD History
 | quote     = Containing many of the features of a D&amp;D game, it added an interesting twist -- the dungeon master, the person who set-up and ran a D&amp;D world, was played by the Adventure computer program itself.
}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Inspired by ''Adventure'', a group of students at [[MIT]], in the summer of 1977 wrote a game called ''[[Zork]]'' for the PDP-10.  It became quite popular on the [[ARPANET]]. ''Zork'' was [[ported]] under the name ''Dungeon'' to [[FORTRAN]] by a programmer working at [[Digital Equipment Corporation|DEC]] in 1978.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
 | url       = http://www.csd.uwo.ca/Infocom/Articles/NZT/zorkhist.html
 | author    = Tim Anderson
 | coauthor  = [[Stu Galley]]
 | title     = The History of Zork
 | quote     = Zork was too much of a nonsense word, not descriptive of the game, etc., etc., etc. Silly as it sounds, we eventually started calling it Dungeon. (Dave admits to suggesting the new name, but that's only a minor sin.) When Bob the lunatic released his FORTRAN version to the DEC users' group, that was the name he used.
 | authorlink     = Tim Anderson (Zork)
}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In 1978 [[Roy Trubshaw]], a student at [[Essex University]] in the UK, started working on a multi-user adventure game in the MACRO-10 assembly language for a DEC PDP-10. He named the game ''MUD'' (''Multi-User Dungeon''), in tribute to the ''Dungeon'' variant of ''Zork'', which Trubshaw had greatly enjoyed playing.&lt;ref name=&quot;wired-article&quot;&gt;{{cite journal
 |author=[[Kevin Kelly (editor)|Kevin Kelly]], [[Howard Rheingold]]
 |year=1993
 |title=The Dragon Ate My Homework
 |journal=[[Wired (magazine)|Wired]]
 |volume=1
 |issue=3
 |url=http://www.wired.com/wired/archive/1.03/muds.html
 |quote=In 1980, Roy Traubshaw, a British fan of the fantasy role-playing board game Dungeons and Dragons, wrote an electronic version of that game during his final undergraduate year at Essex College. The following year, his classmate Richard Bartle took over the game, expanding the number of potential players and their options for action. He called the game MUD (for Multi-User Dungeons), and put it onto the Internet.
}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;bartle-acronym&quot;&gt;{{cite book
 | last = Bartle | first = Richard | authorlink = Richard Bartle
 | title = [[Designing Virtual Worlds]]
 | publisher = New Riders
 | year = 2003
 | isbn = 0-1310-1816-7
 | page = 741
 | quote = The &quot;D&quot; in MUD stands for &quot;Dungeon&quot; [...] because the version of ZORK Roy played was a Fortran port called DUNGEN.
}}&lt;/ref&gt; Trubshaw converted MUD to [[BCPL]] (the predecessor of [[C (Programming Language)|C]]), before handing over development to [[Richard Bartle]], a fellow student at Essex University, in 1980.&lt;ref name=&quot;bartle-history-email&quot;&gt;{{cite web
| url=http://www.mud.co.uk/richard/mudhist.htm
| title=Early MUD History 
| year=1990
| quote=The program was also becoming unmanageable, as it was written in assembler. Hence, he rewrote everything in BCPL, starting late 1979 and working up to about Easter 1980. The finished product was the heart of the system which many people came to believe was the &quot;original&quot; MUD. In fact, it was version 3.
}}&lt;/ref&gt;

''[[MUD1|MUD]]'', better known as ''Essex MUD'' and ''MUD1'' in later years, ran on the Essex University network until late 1987.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
 | url=http://www.mud.co.uk/richard/incarns.htm
 | title=Incarnations of MUD
 | author=[[Richard Bartle]]
 | quote=This is the &quot;classic&quot; MUD, played by many people both internal and external to the University. Although eventually available only during night-time due to the effects of its popularity on the system, its impact on on-line gaming has been immense. I eventually closed it down on 30/9/87 upon leaving Essex University to work for MUSE full time.
}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The popularity of MUDs of the Essex University tradition escalated in the USA during the 1980s when affordable [[personal computers]] with 300 to 2400 bit/s [[modems]] enabled role-players to log into multi-line [[Bulletin Board Systems]] and [[online service providers]] such as [[CompuServe]]. During this time it was sometimes said that MUD stands for &quot;Multi Undergraduate Destroyer&quot; due to their popularity among college students and the amount of time devoted to them.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
| url=http://www.mud.co.uk/dvw/mudsasasociety.html
| title=A Study of MUDs as a Society
| year=1998
| quote=Some would insist however that 'MUD' does in fact stand for Multi Undergraduate Destroyer, in recognition of the number of students who may have failed their classes due to too much time spent MUDding!
}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Many [[MUD]]s are still active and a number of influential MMORPG designers, such as [[Raph Koster]], [[Brad McQuaid]],&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
 | last = Nelson | first = Mike
 | url = http://www.guru3d.com/gamereviews/brad-mcquaid-interview/index1.shtml
 | title = Interview: Brad McQuaid
 | work = The guru of 3D
 | date = 2002-07-02
 | accessdate = 2007-03-03
}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Matt Firor]], [[Mark Jacobs (video game designer)|Mark Jacobs]], [[Brian Green (game developer)|Brian Green]],&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
 | last = Carter | first = Randolph
 | url = http://grindingtovalhalla.wordpress.com/2009/04/23/psychochild/
 | title = Psychochild
 | work = Grinding to Valhalla
 | date = 2009-04-23
 | accessdate = 2010-04-19
 | quote = The MUDs I played extensively: Genocide (where I first used the name &quot;Psychochild&quot;), Highlands, Farside, Kerovnia, and Astaria.
}}&lt;/ref&gt; and [[J. Todd Coleman]], began as [[:Category:MUD developers|MUD developers]] and/or players.  The history of MMORPGs grows directly out of the history of MUDs.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book
 | last = Castronova | first = Edward | authorlink = Edward Castronova
 | title = Synthetic Worlds: The Business and Culture of Online Games
 | publisher = University Of Chicago Press
 | year = 2006
 | isbn = 0226096270
 | pages = 10, 291
 | quote = [pp. 10] The ancestors of MMORPGS were text-based multiuser domains (MUDs) [...] [pp. 291] Indeed, MUDs generate perhaps the one historical connection between game-based VR and the traditional program [...]
}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book
 | last = Bainbridge | first = William Sims | authorlink = William Sims Bainbridge
 | title = Berkshire Encyclopedia of Human-Computer Interaction
 | publisher = Berkshire Publishing Group
 | year = 2004
 | isbn = 0974309125
 | volume = 2
 | page = 474
 | quote = Developers had long considered writing a graphical MUD. [...] the last major 2D virtual environment in the West marked the true beginning of the fifth age of MUDs: Origin Systems' 1997 Ultima Online (UO).
}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== PLATO ==
Meanwhile, the [[PLATO system]], an educational computer system based on [[Mainframe computer|mainframe]] computers with graphical terminals, was pioneering many areas of multiuser computer systems. By the middle of 1974, there were graphical multiplayer games such as ''[[Spasim]]'', a space battle game which could support 32 users,  and the ''[[Talkomatic]]'' multi-user chat system.

''Oubliette'', written by Jim Schwaiger, and published on the PLATO system predated ''MUD1'' by about a year. It was so difficult that one could not play it alone: in order for players to survive, they had to run in groups. While ''Oubliette'' was a multi-player game, there was no persistence to the game world. Following it, also on PLATO, was a game called ''[[Moria (PLATO)|Moria]]'' written in 1977, copyright 1978. Again, players could run in parties but in this game it was also possible to effectively play while only running one character.&lt;ref name=&quot;oubliette&quot;&gt;{{cite book
 | last = Bartle | first = Richard | authorlink = Richard Bartle
 | title = [[Designing Virtual Worlds]]
 | publisher = New Riders
 | year = 2003
 | isbn = 0-1310-1816-7
 | page = 741
 | quote = Jim Schwaiger's 1977 game ''Oubliette'' (inspired by ''Dungeons &amp; Dragons'' and Chuck Miller's earlier multiplayer game, ''Mines of Moria'') had a first-person point of view and used line graphics to render the scene ahead. It had persistent characters, but was not a persistent world. Also, the interaction it allowed between characters was very limited; it was almost there, but not quite.
}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Another early PLATO game was ''[[Avatar (computer game)|Avatar]]'', begun around 1977 and opened in 1979, written by Bruce Maggs, Andrew Shapira, and Dave Sides, all high school students using the PLATO system at the [[University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign|University of Illinois]]. This [[2.5-D]] game was running on 512x512 [[plasma display|plasma panels]] of the PLATO system, and groups of up to 15 players could enter the dungeon simultaneously and fight monsters as a team.

These games were graphical in nature and very advanced for their time, but were proprietary programs that were unable to spread beyond PLATO. Textual worlds, which typically ran on [[Unix]], [[OpenVMS|VMS]], or [[DOS]], were far more accessible to the public.

== Early commercial development==

&lt;!-- Please DO NOT ADD a game to the history section unless you intend to assert notability AND provide a source to support its release dates and/or other assertions. --&gt;

The first commercial MMORPG (although what constitutes &quot;massive&quot; requires qualification when discussing mid-1980s [[Mainframe computer|mainframe]]s) was ''[[Island of Kesmai]]'' designed by [[Kelton Flinn]] and John Taylor. Still [[roguelike]], this game became available in 1985 for $12.00 per hour via the [[CompuServe]] online service and supported up to one hundred players.&lt;ref name=&quot;Online World Timeline&quot;&gt;Koster, Raph (2002) &quot;Online World Timeline,&quot; http://www.raphkoster.com/gaming/mudtimeline.shtml&lt;/ref&gt;

The first graphical character-based interactive environment, though not actually an RPG, was ''[[Club Caribe]]''.  Although first released as ''[[Habitat (video game)|Habitat]]'' in 1988, Club Caribe was introduced by [[LucasArts]] for [[Quantum Link|Q-Link]] customers on their [[Commodore 64]] computers. Users could interact with one another, chat and exchange items.&lt;ref&gt;Ferrell, Keith. (November 1987), &quot;The Future Of Computer Games: Ten Industry Leaders Speak Out,&quot; http://www.atarimagazines.com/compute/issue90/Future_Of_Computer_Games.php&quot;. [[COMPUTE!]]&lt;/ref&gt; Although very basic, its use of online [[Avatar (computing)|avatars]] (already well established off-line by ''[[Ultima (video game series)|Ultima]]'' and other games) and combining [[Online chat|chat]] and graphics was revolutionary.

&lt;!-- Deleted image removed: [[Image:NeverwinterNightsAOL.gif|thumb|260px|right|''Neverwinter Nights'' on AOL, the first truly graphical multi-user game.]] --&gt;
The first graphical MMORPG was ''[[Neverwinter Nights (AOL game)|Neverwinter Nights]]'' by designer [[Don Daglow]] and programmer [[Cathryn Mataga]] (not to be confused with ''[[Neverwinter Nights]]'' by [[BioWare]]). &quot;Neverwinter Nights&quot; went live on AOL for [[Personal computer|PC]] owners in 1991 and ran through 1997. This project was personally championed and green-lighted by AOL President [[Steve Case]]. Both ''Club Caribe'' and ''Neverwinter Nights'' cost $6.00 per hour to play.

During the early-1990s, commercial use of the internet was limited by [[NSFNET]] acceptable use policies.  Consequently, early online games like ''[[Legends of Future Past]]'', ''Neverwinter Nights'', ''[[GemStone IV|GemStone III]]'', ''[[Dragon's Gate]]'', and ''Federation'' relied heavily on proprietary services such as [[CompuServe]], [[America Online]], and [[GEnie]] for distribution. 

[[Air Warrior]] was an early multiplayer game as players could battle each other flying virtual fighter planes. The game was first introduced in 1986 and ran on the GEnie network. In 1993 the game was revised to run over the internet.

Following ''Neverwinter Nights'' was ''[[The Shadow of Yserbius]]'', an MMORPG on [[The Sierra Network]] (TSN), which ran from 1992 through 1996. The game was produced by [[Joe Ybarra]]. ''The Shadow of Yserbius'' was an hourly service, although it also offered unlimited service for $119.99 per month, until [[AT&amp;T]] acquired TSN and rendered it strictly an hourly service. The name was then changed from TSN to the [[ImagiNation Network]].

== Commercial MMORPGs on the Internet ==
&lt;!--This use of this image has no rationale on the image's page. Please read [[Wikipedia:NFCC#10c]] [[Image:UOPlayerInteraction.jpg|thumb|300px|right|Players interacting in ''[[Ultima Online]]''.]]--&gt;
As [[NSFNET]] restrictions were relaxed, traditional game companies and online services began deploying games on the [[internet]]. The first commercial text-based MMORPG to make this transition to the Internet from a proprietary network provider (CompuServe, in this case) was ''[[Legends of Future Past]]''.  ''Legends'' was also notable for being one of the first titles to have featured professional Game Masters who conducted online events.&lt;ref name=&quot;lombardi&quot;&gt;Chris Lombardi (1992), &quot;Legends in their Own Minds,&quot; Computer Gaming World, http://static.filefront.com/cgw/1992_08_issue97.pdf&lt;/ref&gt;

The term MMORPG was coined by [[Richard Garriott]], the creator of [[Ultima Online]], in 1997.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book
 | last1 = Safko | first1 = Ron
 | last2 = Brake | first2 = David
 | title = The Social Media Bible: Tactics, Tools, and Strategies for Business Success
 | publisher = Wiley
 | year = 2009
 | isbn = 0470411554
 | quote = Richard Garriott first coined the term ''MMORPG'' in 1997.
}}&lt;/ref&gt;  The term probably derives from &quot;MMOG&quot;, which can be traced back to the 1993 E3 Convention, when [[Aces High (computer game)|Dale Addink]] used it to describe the AirWarrior franchise.{{Citation needed|date=October 2009}}

''[[The Realm Online]]'' was another successful early Internet MMORPG, launched by [[Sierra Entertainment|Sierra Online]]. Although released just after ''Meridian 59'', the [[Development stage|beta]] was active several months before.  ''The Realm Online'' had fully animated 2D graphics, both in and out of combat situations, which made it accessible to a wider audience compared to more text-based games or the graphical MUDs on which it was based.  Also, its gameplay and interface were already familiar to those accustomed to the graphical adventure games earlier popularised by Sierra.  Like many of its predecessors, ''The Realm Online'' only featured simple turn-based combat, however, it did feature a huge number (for the time) of visual character customization options.  It, too, is still running.

''[[Nexus: The Kingdom of the Winds]]'', whose beta was released to Korean audiences in 1996 was one of the first mmorpgs.  Not only that, but it is still an active game today with over 1000 subscribers. 

''[[Meridian 59]]'', launched  by [[The 3DO Company|3DO]] in late 1996, was one of the first Internet MMORPGs.  It was one of the first Internet game from a major publisher, the one of first to be covered in the major game magazines and  the first MMPOG to introduce the flat monthly subscription fee. Perhaps most significantly, was its [[Game engine|3D engine]], allowing players to experience the game world through the eyes of their characters. A cult following quickly grew for ''Meridian 59'' that still exists today.

''[[Ultima Online]]'', released in September 1997, is now credited with popularizing the genre.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.ge-eu.com/games.html Game Entertainment Europe&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://pc.ign.com/articles/759/759391p1.html IGN: Ultima Online: Kingdom Reborn Preview&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt; It featured 3D [[Isometric projection|isometric]]/third-person graphics, and was set in the already popular ''Ultima'' universe.  It was also a more involved, complex game than many of its predecessors.

Two years after ''[[Ultima Online]]'', [[The 4th Coming|The Fourth Coming]] was released, an MMORPG in 3D [[Isometric projection|isometric]]. It was launched in France under the name La 4ème Prophétie and contributed to spread the MMORPG culture in Europe as one of the first graphical MMORPG. It became very popular through the website [[GOA (portail web)|GOA]] until its close in 2001. This MMORPG featured a unique communication system. The game has lost its popularity, however it is still a subject of nostalgia for its old players and some servers continue to host players.

Meanwhile, commercial online gaming was becoming extraordinarily popular in [[South Korea]]. ''[[Nexus: The Kingdom of the Winds]]'', designed by [[Jake Song]], was commercially released in 1996 and eventually gained over one million subscribers. Song's next game, ''[[Lineage (computer game)|Lineage]]'' (1998), enjoyed even greater success gaining millions of subscribers in Korea and [[Taiwan]].  This helped to secure developer [[NCsoft]]'s dominance in the global MMORPG market for several years.
NCSoft has released ''[[Lineage 2]]'', ''[[City of Heroes]]'', ''[[Guild Wars]]'', ''[[Exteel]]'', and ''[[Aion: The Tower of Eternity]]''. And titles like ''[[Blade &amp; Soul]]'' and ''[[Guild Wars 2]]'' are expected to be released in late 2011 to early 2012.&lt;!--This would be a good place to throw 1 or 2 sentences listing NCSoft's other MMORPG achievements and the years they went live--&gt;

''[[EverQuest]]'', launched in March 1999 by Verant Interactive (later acquired by [[Sony Online Entertainment]]), brought fantasy MMORPGs into the Western mainstream. It was the most commercially successful MMORPG in the [[United States]] for five years, and was the basis for 16 expansions (as of December 2009) and several derivative games. 

In 1999, following ''Ultima Online'' and ''EverQuest'', was another hit, ''[[Asheron's Call]]''. Together, these three games are sometimes referred to as the original &quot;big three&quot; of the late 1990s.

== Second generation MMORPGs ==
[[File:Anarchy Online Land Control Area.png|thumb|250px|''[[Anarchy Online]]'' is a 2001 massively multiplayer online role-playing game]]
By the turn of the century, game companies were eager to capitalize on the new market.  The concept of [[massively multiplayer online game]]s expanded into new [[video game genre]]s around this time, though RPGs, with their ability to &quot;suck in&quot; the player, were (and still are) the most financially promising.

The next generation of MMORPGs, following the &quot;big three&quot; of the previous decade, was to include the medieval [[player versus player|PvP]]-oriented ''[[Dark Age of Camelot]]'', the sci-fi ''[[Anarchy Online]]'', and ''[[Ultima Worlds Online: Origin|Ultima Online 2]]''. ''Anarchy Online'', released first in June 2001, was saddled with crippling technical problems upon its release, mostly due to an inability to handle the huge playerbase. ''Dark Age of Camelot'' launched smoothly four months later, introducing &quot;Realm vs. Realm&quot; [[player versus player|PvP]] and other innovations, and quickly passed ''Ultima Online'' and ''Asheron's Call'' in popularity, and became ''EverQuest'' 's main rival.  ''Ultima Online 2'' was cancelled by [[Electronic Arts]] in March 2001, as they had decided that the market was becoming saturated and that it would be more profitable to divert resources to the original ''Ultima Online''. ''[[RuneScape]]'' by Jagex was also released in 2001.  2001 also saw MMORPGs move off of PCs and onto home consoles in a limited form with the release of ''[[Phantasy Star Online]]'';&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
 | url=http://www.acegamez.co.uk/reviews_x360/Phantasy_Star_Universe_Preview_X360.htm
 | title=''AceGamez,'' &quot;Phantasy Star Universe Preview Microsoft Xbox 360&quot;
 | author=Tony Peters (2006)
 | quote=Phantasy Star Online was the console gamer's first MMORPG. When it first saw release on the Dreamcast back in the winter of 2001, it was to be the crowning feather in Sega's online gaming hat.
}}&lt;/ref&gt; however, due to platform limitations, it would not be until ''[[Final Fantasy XI]]'''s release that 'massive' features found their way outside of non-combat areas on consoles.

In 2002 the sprite-based ''[[Ragnarok Online]]'', produced by Korean company [[Gravity Corp]], was released.  Though unknown to many Western players, the game took Asia by storm as ''Lineage'' had done.  The publisher has claimed in excess of 25 million subscribers of the game, although this number is based upon a quantity of registered users (rather than active subscribers).&lt;ref&gt;Michael Kanellos (2004), &quot;Gaming their Way to Growth,&quot; [http://news.com.com/Consumers+Gaming+their+way+to+growth+-+Part+3+of+South+Koreas+Digital+Dynasty/2009-1040_3-5239555.html CNET News]&lt;/ref&gt;  2002 also saw the release of ''[[MapleStory]]'', another sprite-based title, which was completely [[free-to-play]] - instead of charging a monthly fee, it generated revenue by selling in-game &quot;enhancements&quot;. ''MapleStory'' would go on to become a major player in the new market for free-to-play MMORPGs (generating huge numbers of registered accounts across its many versions), if it did not introduce the market by itself.

In September 2002, ''[[Earth &amp; Beyond]]'' was released.  Having been in development since 1997, this was the first 3D sci-fi space-ship based MMORPG. ''Earth and Beyond'' only lasted two years before being shut down by developer [[Westwood Studios]]' owners, [[Electronic Arts]].

In November 2002, ''[[Final Fantasy XI]]'' by [[Square-Enix]] became the first MMOG to provide clients for different platforms using a single set of servers,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Xbox.com FINAL FANTASY XI - Game Detail Page|publisher=[[Xbox.com]]|date=2010-04-30|url= http://www.xbox.com/en-US/games/f/finalfantasyXI/|accessdate=2010-04-30}} {{Dead link|date=November 2010|bot=H3llBot}}&lt;/ref&gt; in addition to being the first 'true' MMOG to appear on a [[video game console]] due to its initial release in Japan in May of the same year on the [[PlayStation 2]].  It would go on to provide a client for a third platform, the [[Xbox 360]], in 2006.

In March 2003, [[Ubisoft]] launched their first MMORPG: ''[[Shadowbane]]''.  Shadowbane was notable for featuring no quests, and instead relying on player warfare to provide immersion.  To support this goal it featured player-built, player-owned, and player-razed cities and capitals, and a system for player government.

Also in March 2003 [[Sony Online Entertainment]] launched ''[[EverQuest Online Adventures]]'', a [[Playstation 2]] spin-off of the successful ''[[EverQuest]]'' MMO. This game is only accessible to Playstation 2 players and it's still running.

May 2003 saw the release of ''[[Eve Online]]'', produced by [[Crowd Control Productions]], which had players taking the role of spaceship pilots and had gameplay similar to the series ''[[Star Control]]''. Though not the first space MMO (''[[Microsoft Allegiance]]'' was the first space MMO and was released in 1999), ''Eve'' was able to achieve lasting success.  One of the reasons for its success may have been the game's design, in which all subscribers play in one shared universe as a result the natural partitioning of the game universe into solar systems connected by stargates. This partitioning allows the world to be divided up in such a way that one or more solar systems run on different servers, while still maintaining a single coherent world.

In October 2003, ''[[Lineage II]]'' (NCsoft's sequel to ''Lineage'') became the latest MMORPG to achieve huge success across Asia. It received the Presidential Award at the 2003 Korean Game awards, and is now the second most popular MMORPG in the world. As of the first half of 2005 ''Lineage II'' counted over 2.25 million subscribers worldwide, with servers in Japan, China, North America, Taiwan, and Europe, once the popularity of the game had surged in the West.

2003 also saw the appearance of ''[[Second Life]]''.  While not primarily a role playing game, it is clearly multiplayer and online, and it is used as a platform where people construct role playing games based on Gor, ''Star Trek'', vampires, and other genres.

In April 2004, NCSoft produced another significant title, ''[[City of Heroes]]''.  It introduced several major innovations in gameplay and also featured an extreme number of possible visual character appearances, and its comic-book [[superhero]] theme made it stand out.

==Current-generation MMORPGs==

&lt;!-- Deleted image removed: [[Image:Horderaid.jpg|thumb|260px|right|A Horde raid group in ''World of Warcraft'']] --&gt;
The most recent generation of MMORPGs, based on arbitrary standards of graphics, gameplay, and popularity, is said to have launched in November 2004 with [[Sony Online Entertainment]]'s ''[[EverQuest II]]'' and [[Blizzard Entertainment|Blizzard Entertainment's]] ''[[World of Warcraft]]'' (''WoW''). At the time, Sony expected to dominate the market, based on the success of the first ''EverQuest'', and decided to offer a flat monthly rate to play all of their MMORPGs including ''EverQuest'', ''EverQuest II'', and ''[[Star Wars Galaxies]]'', to keep from competing with itself.  While ''EverQuest II'' was a commercial success as predicted, ''World of Warcraft'' immediately overtook all of these games upon release, and indeed became so popular that it dwarfed all previous monthly-fee MMORPGs. At present, [[World of Warcraft|''WoW'']] is one of the most played games in North America, and the most subscribed to MMORPG worldwide, with a total of over 10 million&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/technology-15672416|}}&lt;/ref&gt; customers. The closest MMORPG to ''World of Warcraft'' is in terms of paying subscribers is ''[[RuneScape]]'' with more than one million subscribers and even more free players. ''RuneScape'' is also the world's largest free MMORPG,&lt;ref name=&quot;Guiness Records&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://news.runescape.com/newsitem.ws?id=1386| title=RuneScape in Guinness World Records! |publisher=Jagex |date =2008-08-22| accessdate=2008-08-22}}&lt;/ref&gt; though it receives less media attention than ''WoW''. With the release of these newer games, subscriptions began to decline for many older MMORPGs, even the year-old ''[[Lineage II]]'', and in particular ''Everquest''.  The current MMORPG market has ''World of Warcraft'' in a position similar to the position of [[Dungeons &amp; Dragons]] in the tabletop RPG market, with both games' market share being greater than 50% of the overall market.

In August 2005 Sony Online Entertainment acquired ''[[The Matrix Online]]'', and the game was shut down at 11:59pm, 31 July 2009.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://thematrixonline.station.sony.com/sunset/bluePill/8-FinalChapter-Closing-Credits-Cover_printable.pdf| title=The Final Chapter}}&lt;/ref&gt; It is the first game Sony has ended.

On April 25, [[ArenaNet]] (a subsidiary of [[NCSoft]]) successfully launched ''[[Guild Wars]]'', introducing a new financial model which might have been partly responsible for the game's success.  Though definitely an online RPG, and technically having a persistent world (despite most of the game's content being [[instance dungeon|instanced]]), it requires only a one-time purchasing fee.  It was also designed to be &quot;winnable&quot;, more or less, as developers would not profit from customers' prolonged playtime.  Other differences compared to traditional MMORPGs include strictly PvP-only areas, a relatively short playtime requirement to access end-game content, instant world travel, and strategic PvP.  The game is designed around the max level cap of level 20, so players will not run into the level-spreading problem when grouping.  For these differences it was termed instead a &quot;Competitive Online Role-Playing Game&quot; (CORPG) by its developers.  With five million games purchased as of April '09,&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.guildwars.com/events/press/releases/pressrelease-2008-02-26.php News story from GW official site]&lt;/ref&gt; Guild Wars is still continuously profitable (due to several stand-alone games) but is still not viewed by some as a serious competitor to ''WoW'' in terms of profit and number of players. However, the alternative nature of the payment system in Guild Wars means that the game does not aim to &quot;compete&quot; with WoW rather than exist along-side it, and in that sense it can still be considered a large success.

There has also been significant competition (and potential for profit) among [[free-to-play]] MMORPGs. A few of the most successful of these are ''[[Silkroad Online]]'' by the publisher [[Joymax]], the 3D sprite based MMORPG ''[[Flyff]]'' by Aeonsoft, ''Rappelz'' by nFlavor, (with Aeonsoft and nFlavor merging in 2010 to become Gala Lab Corp) ''[[Perfect World]]'' by ''[[Beijing Perfect World]]'', the 2D scrolling MMORPG ''[[MapleStory]]'' by [[Wizet]] and finally the free-to-play converted ''[[Shadowbane]]'' by [[Ubisoft]]. Most of these games generate revenue by selling in-game &quot;enhancements&quot;, and due to their free nature have accumulated huge numbers of registered accounts over the years, with a majority of them from East Asia.

On July 1, 2009, [[Ubisoft]] shut down the [[Shadowbane]] servers.

Many of the most recent big-budget contributions to the market have focused on giving players visually stunning graphics.  In 2007, ''[[The Lord of the Rings Online: Shadows of Angmar]]'' (LOTRO) was one of the first of these to meet with commercial success, followed by the problematic 2008 launch of ''[[Age of Conan: Hyborian Adventures]]'' and the [[Player versus player]] focused ''[[Warhammer Online: Age of Reckoning]]''.  Much like LOTRO, many of the games in development with big expectations have multi-media tie-ins, such as ''[[Star Wars: The Old Republic]]'', ''[[Star Trek Online]]'' and ''[[Stargate Worlds]]''.

==Upcoming MMORPGs==
Although no competitor has been able to garner a subscription base to rival ''World of Warcraft'', there are some promising games in development. ''[[ArcheAge]]'' currently in beta stage for korea player base is developed by [[XL_Games]] and looks the most promising yet where [[Tencent]] reportedly paid in the neighborhood of 40 million US dollars to publish the game in [[China]]. Followed by ''[[Aion: The Tower of Eternity]]'', developed by [[NCsoft]], has gathered a respectable subscription base (NCSoft's previous titles include ''[[Guild Wars]]'' and ''[[Lineage II]]'').  Upcoming titles also include ''[[Dungeons &amp; Dragons: Neverwinter]]'', ''[[Star Wars: The Old Republic]]'', and ''[[Warhammer 40,000 Online]]''. ''[[Stellar Dawn]]'', an upcoming multiplayer sci-fi game by Jagex - the maker of RuneScape - is supposed to be a rival of ''[[WoW]]'': [[Mark Gerhard]], the CEO of Jagex, has stated in an interview with [[Eurogamer]] that he suspects that the players of ''Stellar Dawn'' are the same players who play ''[[WoW]]''.&lt;ref&gt;http://stellardawnmaniacs.com/index.php?option=com_content&amp;view=article&amp;id=52:mmg-interview-with-eurogamer&amp;catid=47:interviews&amp;Itemid=62&lt;/ref&gt;
On December 2010, Blizzard confirmed that they're working on ''Titan'', a new MMO.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.crunchgear.com/2010/12/17/titan-blizzard-reluctantly-confirms-next-gen-mmo/]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.destructoid.com/vgas-interviews-mortal-kombat-and-blizzard-189714.phtml]&lt;/ref&gt;  Lastly much hype has been surrounding ''[[Guild Wars 2]]'' which features many innovative new systems that aim to drastically alter the way people play MMORPGs. It will have the same Buy-to-play purchase model as the original.

==See also==
*[[List of MMORPGs]]
* [[Multiplayer online game|MOG]]
* [[MMORPG]]
* [[Virtual world]]

==References==
{{Reflist|2}}
{{Multiplayer online games}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:History Of Massively Multiplayer Online Games}}
[[Category:Massively multiplayer online role-playing games| ]]
[[Category:History of video games]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
