<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="10284834" ns="0" title="Frenkie"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{BLP sources|date=August 2009}}
{{Infobox musical artist
|name = Frenkie
|image =
|caption = Frenkie
|background = solo_singer
|birth_name = Adnan Hamidović
|alias = Frenk the Tenk, Frenkoza, Frenkzilla, Charlie, Frenkie
|Born = [[Bijeljina]], [[SFR Yugoslavia]]
|genre = [[Bosnian hip-hop]]
|occupation = [[Rapper]]
|years_active = 1997-present
|label = ''[[Fmjam]]'', ''[[Menart Records|Menart]]''
|associated_acts = [[Edo Maajka]], HZA, [[Disciplinska Komisija]],
}}

'''Adnan  Hamidović''' (born May 31, 1982), better known by his stage name '''Frenkie''', is a [[Bosnia and Herzegovina|Bosnian]] [[rapper]]&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |title=Balkan rappers speak out on peace and justice |url=http://www.reuters.com/article/inDepthNews/idUSL2329247820061124 |work=[[Reuters]] |date=24 November 2006 |accessdate=4 November 2009 }}&lt;/ref&gt; from [[Bijeljina]], [[Bosnia]]. The themes present in his music are often concerned with the political situation in Bosnia,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |title=Bosnians say 'enough' to politics |url=http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/world/europe/5045246.stm |work=[[BBC News]] |date=4 June 2006 |accessdate=4 November 2009 }}&lt;/ref&gt; as well as traditional hip-hop subject matter such as battle rapping and pop culture. He has recorded three successful full-length albums to date: Odličan CD,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |title=Bosnia: Frenkie e l'hip hop impegnato |url=http://www.osservatoriobalcani.org/article/articleview/6383/1/42/ |work=Osservatorio Balcani |date=7 November 2006 |accessdate=4 November 2009 }}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Dosta album|DOSTA]]&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |title=Frenk: U prodaji album Dosta |url=http://www.nezavisne.com/muzika/vijesti/914/Frenk-U-prodaji-album-Dosta.html |work=[[Nezavisne novine]] |date=8 October 2006 |accessdate=4 November 2009 }}&lt;/ref&gt; and [[Povratak Cigana]].,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |title=Povratak cigana zagrijao atmosferu u Ksetu |url=http://www.javno.com/home/hr-trach/foto--povratak-cigana-zagrijao-atmosferu-u-ksetu_86566 |work=Javno |date=3 October 2007 |accessdate=4 November 2009 }}&lt;/ref&gt; a EP album, [[Pokreni Se EP]] and is releasing his 4th studio and 5th album in December 2009 named [[Protuotrov]]. Frenkie is also a member of the crew [[Disciplinska Komisija]] which includes [[Edo Maajka]] and HZA.

==Life and music career==
===Early life===
Adnan Hamidović was born in Bijeljina on May 31, 1982, where he lived until 1992. After escaping the Bosnian war, he settled with his family in [[Nürnberg]], [[Germany]] until 1998. There he was first introduced to hip-hop culture. Along with starting to make hip-hop, he started to do graffiti. His first rap lyrics were in German. German hip-hop directed his style of rap, even to this day he is paying attention to [[German hip-hop]] culture. After returning to Bosnia, he went to [[Tuzla]] and continued with his graffiti, making him one of the first to make hip-hop related graffiti art after the war.

===Early career===
In 1999, with the beginning of the station &quot;[[Fmjam]]&quot; on radio &quot;[[Kameleon]]&quot;, he befriended DJ Soul and Erol, who started Fmjam and the first hip-hop demo singles. Frenkie, Koma, Ady started the group &quot;Prljavi Andeli&quot; (Dirty Angels).
Then later in 1999, &quot;Disciplinska Komisija&quot;(DK) was formed. At the time of the formation the members were: spearhead of the group [[Edo Maajka]], Frenkie, Hamaz, Mire, Koma and their DJ Soul. Edo Maajka released his popular album &quot;[[Slusaj Mater]]&quot; and started tours and concerts, which he was joined by Frenkie, doing the people got to know him that way. Frenkie is known for his fast rapping and energy, never before seen in rap. On Edo Maajka's second studio album &quot;[[No Sikiriki]]&quot;, Frenkie is featured on two songs, establishing himself even more.

=== Fine ===
In 2007, radio station 202 was fined 5000 euros by the BIH organization RAK for Frenkie's song &quot;Mr. Policeman&quot;, a song talking about corrupt police forces. After that fine, Frenkie released a song in response to RAK on FMJam called &quot;Massiv&quot;, which criticizes and mocks this institution.

== Discography ==
{{Main|Frenkie discography}}
Frenkie's album &quot;[[Odličan CD]]&quot; was released in 2005. It included the singles &quot;Bruce Lee Rap&quot; with Baby Dooks and &quot;Raise&quot; with Defence. Frenkie's second album, &quot;DOSTA&quot; (Enough) featuring his beat maker King Mire from [[Brčko (city)|Brčko]], was released in June 2006 and was dedicated to the movement [[Dosta]] which is gaining popularity in Bosnia. Singles from the album include &quot;Rat Savezu&quot; which was dedicated to the Bosnian Soccer Fans &quot;BHFANATICOS&quot; in their war against the corrupt Bosnian Football Federation; Frenkie has released a video clip for this hit song. He has also released a video for &quot;Mr Policeman&quot;, The first single, the title track, from his new album Povratak Cigana (released in 2007), has already been released on FMJAM's website. It features Hamza, Frenkie's long time friend who recently released his own album, entitled &quot;Opusten Ko Leksaurin&quot;.

In addition to his solo work, Frenkie has featured on many Disciplinska Komisija songs such as &quot;America 2&quot; and &quot;Ustaj&quot;, and on Edo Maajka's albums on &quot;Ozezi&quot;, &quot;Ne-Mo-Zes&quot; and &quot;Stvoren Za Rep&quot;.

In the summer of 2008, Frenkie's song 'Soundtrack' (from the album Odlican CD) was used in the movie [[The Incredible Hulk (film)|The Incredible Hulk]]. The song was used in during a very rough cab driving scene featuring [[Edward Norton]] and [[Liv Tyler]].

Frenkie recorded a song with [[Masta Ace]] called ''Živili''. It was released on Frenkie's 2009 album [[Protuotrov]].

Frenkie is part of the Diversidad crew. Diversidad: A Unique European Urban Experience has a collective album gathering twenty rappers, beatmakers and DJ’s, which includes Frenkie.

=== Studio albums ===
* 2005 - ''Odličan CD''
* 2007 - ''[[Povratak Cigana]]''
* 2009 - ''[[Protuotrov]]''

=== Ep-s, regional and other releases ===
* 2006 - ''[[Dosta album|DOSTA]]'' (released only in Bosnia)
* 2008 - ''[[Pokreni Se EP]]''
* 2010 - ''[[Featuring mixtape]]
* 2011 - ''[[Diversidad - The Experience Album]]''

==Filmography==
=== Documentaries ===
* 2009 - ''Who the fuck is Frenkie'' (came out with the album [[Protuotrov]])

==References==
{{Reflist}}

== External links ==
* ''Official Website [http://www.frenkozza.com/]''
* ''News Magazine [http://www.nme.com/artists/frenkie Frenkie - news, lyrics, pictures, reviews, biography, videos, best songs, discography, concerts, gossip, pictures and tour dates]''
* ''Twitter [http://twitter.com/Frenkozza]''
* ''Interview [http://www.tip.ba/2009/07/07/intervju-frenki-hip-hop-je-moj-stil-zivota-2/]''
* ''Amazon Album [http://www.amazon.com/Odlican-CD/dp/B000RGJC3I Amazon.com: Odlican CD: Frenkie: MP3 Downloads]''
* ''Interview in English [http://www.facebook.com/topic.php?uid=23781850948&amp;topic=8403 Frenkie Interview for hip-Hopkings.com &amp;#124; Facebook]''

{{Persondata &lt;!-- Metadata: see [[Wikipedia:Persondata]]. --&gt; 
| NAME              =Hamidovic, Adnan
| ALTERNATIVE NAMES =
| SHORT DESCRIPTION =
| DATE OF BIRTH     = 31 May 1982
| PLACE OF BIRTH    =
| DATE OF DEATH     =
| PLACE OF DEATH    =
}}
{{DEFAULTSORT:Hamidovic, Adnan}}
[[Category:Bosnia and Herzegovina rappers]]
[[Category:1982 births]]
[[Category:Living people]]
[[Category:People from Bijeljina]]

[[bs:Frenkie]]
[[de:Frenkie]]
[[hr:Frenkie]]
[[sr:Френки]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
