<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="1030851" ns="0" title="Nazi salute"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{About|the fascist salute used in Germany|fascist salutes in other countries|Roman salute}}
{{Use dmy dates|date=October 2011}}
[[File:Bundesarchiv Bild 183-H13160, Beim Einmarsch deutscher Truppen in Eger.jpg|300px|thumb|right|People of [[Cheb|Eger]], in the [[Sudetenland]] (now [[Cheb]], Czech Republic), greet German soldiers with the Hitler salute in October 1938]]

The '''Nazi salute''', or '''Hitler salute''' ({{lang-de|link=no|Hitlergruß}}, literally Hitler Greeting or ''Deutscher Gruß'', German Greeting), was a [[gesture]] of greeting in [[Nazi Germany]] usually accompanied by saying, ''Heil Hitler!'' [&quot;Hail Hitler!&quot;], ''Heil, mein [[Führer]]'' [&quot;Hail, my leader!&quot;], or ''Sieg Heil!'' [&quot;Hail victory!&quot;]. Characteristic of a [[cult of personality]], it was adopted in the 1930s by the Nazi Party to signal obedience to the party's leader [[Adolf Hitler]] and to glorify the German nation and later the war effort. The salute was mandatory for civilians&lt;ref name=&quot;Myth60&quot; /&gt; but optional for [[Wehrmacht|military personnel]], where the traditional [[salute|military salute]] was retained until shortly after the [[20 July plot|failed assassination attempt on Hitler]] in 1944.&lt;ref&gt;Büchner, Alex (1991). ''German Infantry Handbook, 1939–1945: Organization, Uniforms, Weapons, Equipment, Operations''. Schipper Publishing. ISBN 978-0887402845&lt;/ref&gt; Currently,  use of this form of greeting constitutes a criminal offense in Germany, Austria and the Czech Republic.&lt;ref&gt;[http://globalvoicesonline.org/2008/08/15/czech-republic-a-german-put-in-jail-for-nazi-salute/ Czech Republic: A German put in jail for Nazi salute] Global Voices, 15 August 2008&lt;/ref&gt; Depending on the circumstances, the greeting might constitute a criminal offense in Sweden as a [[hate speech]] act.{{Citation needed|date=August 2011}}

==Description==
To perform the salute, it was customary to extend one's right arm straight in front of oneself, raise it at least to eye level, straighten the hand so that it is parallel to the arm&lt;ref name=&quot;Grunberger&quot; /&gt; and say emphatically, ''Heil Hitler!'', or at least ''Heil!'' If one saw an acquaintance at a distance, it sufficed to simply raise the right hand.&lt;ref name=&quot;Grunberger&quot; /&gt; If one encountered a superior, one would also say, ''Heil Hitler''.&lt;ref name=&quot;Grunberger&quot;&gt;{{cite book |last=Grunberger |first=Richard |title=The 12-year Reich: a social history of Nazi Germany, 1933–1945 |publisher=Da Capo Press |year=1995 |edition=illustrated |isbn=0306806606, 9780306806605}}&lt;/ref&gt; If physical disability prevented raising the right arm, it was acceptable to raise the left.&lt;ref name=&quot;Myth&quot; /&gt;
The form ''Heil, mein Führer!'' was for direct address to Hitler.&lt;ref name=&quot;Lepage&quot;&gt;{{cite book |last=Lepage |first= Jean-Denis G. G. |title=Hitler Youth, 1922–1945: An Illustrated History |publisher=McFarland |year=2008 |edition=illustrated |page=70 |isbn=0786439351, 9780786439355}}&lt;/ref&gt; ''Sieg Heil'' was repeated as a chant on public occasions.&lt;ref name=&quot;Lepage&quot; /&gt; Written communications would be concluded with either ''Mit deutschem Gruß'' [With German greeting], or, simply, ''Heil Hitler''.&lt;ref&gt;Tilman (2009), p. 15.&lt;/ref&gt;

In later periods Hitler himself used a modified German salute, not stretching his full right arm, but bending it while holding an open hand towards the greeted at shoulder's height.

==Origins and adoption==
{{See also|Roman salute}}
[[Image:Hitler 1928 crop.jpg|thumb|upright|[[Adolf Hitler]] and [[Hermann Göring]] performing the salute at a Nazi party rally in [[Nuremberg Rally|Nuremberg]] (ca. 1928)]]
The [[greeting|oral greeting]] ''Heil'' became popular in the [[Pan-Germanism|pan-German]] movement around 1900.&lt;ref name=&quot;Mommsen&quot;&gt;{{cite book
|last=Mommsen
|first=Hans
|title=The Third Reich Between Vision and Reality: New Perspectives on German History 1918–1945
|publisher=Berg Publishers
|year=2003
|series=German Historical Perspectives
|volume=Volume 12
|page=28
|isbn=859736270, 9781859736272}}&lt;/ref&gt; Hitler introduced the greeting ''Heil'' .&lt;ref&gt;http://de.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hitlergru%C3%9F&lt;/ref&gt;

As a [[Style (manner of address)|manner of address]], ''Führer'' was introduced by [[Georg Ritter von Schönerer]], who considered himself leader of the Austrian Germans.&lt;ref name=&quot;Mommsen&quot; /&gt; The salute gesture is widely believed to be based on an [[ancient Rome|ancient Roman]] custom.&lt;ref name=&quot;Winkler&quot;&gt;Winkler (2009) p. 2&lt;/ref&gt; However, no [[Roman art|Roman work of art]] depicts it, nor does any [[Roman literature|Roman text]] describe it.&lt;ref name=&quot;Winkler&quot; /&gt; [[Jacques-Louis David]]'s painting ''[[Oath of the Horatii]]'' (1784) seems to be the starting point for the gesture that became known as the Roman Salute.&lt;ref name=&quot;Winkler55&quot;&gt;Winkler (2009), p. 55.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Boime87&quot;&gt;{{cite book |last=Boime |first=Albert |title=Art in an age of revolution, 1750–1800 |publisher=University of Chicago Press |year=1987 |series=Social history of modern art |volume=Volume 1 |pages=400–401 |isbn=0226063348, 9780226063348}} Boime states &quot;''The brothers stretch out their arms in a salute that has since become associated with tyranny. The &quot;Hail Caesar&quot; of antiquity (although at the time of the Horatti a Caesar had yet to be born) was transformed into the &quot;Heil Hitler&quot; of the modern period. The fraternal intimacy brought about by the Horatii's dedication to absolute principles of victory or death ... is closely related to the establishment of the fraternal order ... In the total commitment or blind obedience of a single, exclusive group lies the potentiality of the authoritarian state.''&quot;&lt;/ref&gt; The gesture and its identification with [[Culture of ancient Rome|ancient Rome]] was advanced in other [[Neoclassicism|French neoclassic art]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Boime93&quot;&gt;{{cite book |last=Boime |first=Albert |title=Art in an age of Bonapartism, 1800–1815 |publisher=University of Chicago Press |year=1993 |edition=reprint, illustrated |series=Social history of modern art|volume=2 |page=46}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Winkler51&quot;&gt;Winkler (2009), p. 51.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Winkler40&quot;&gt;Winkler (2009), p. 40.&lt;/ref&gt; This was further elaborated upon in [[popular culture]] during the late 19th and early 20th centuries in plays and films that portrayed the salute as an ancient Roman custom.&lt;ref name=&quot;Winkler79&quot;&gt;Winkler (2009), pp. 70–101.&lt;/ref&gt; This  included the [[silent film]] ''[[Cabiria]]'' (1914), whose screenplay was written by the Italian [[nationalism|ultra-nationalist]] [[Gabriele d'Annunzio]], arguably the forerunner of [[Benito Mussolini]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Winkler94&quot; &gt;Winkler (2009), pp. 74–101.&lt;/ref&gt; In 1919, when he led the [[Italian Regency of Carnaro|occupation of Rijeka]], d'Annunzio adopted the style of salute depicted in the film as a [[Neocolonialism|neo-Imperialist]] ritual;&lt;ref name=&quot;Falasca-Zamponi&quot;&gt;{{cite book |last=Falasca-Zamponi |first=Simonetta |title=Fascist spectacle: the aesthetics of power in Mussolini's Italy|publisher=University of California Press |year=2000 |edition=illustrated |pages=110–113 |series=Studies on the history of society and culture |volume=28 |isbn=0520226771, 9780520226777}}&lt;/ref&gt; and it was quickly adopted by the [[Italian Fascist]] Party.&lt;ref name=&quot;Falasca-Zamponi&quot; /&gt;

By autumn 1923, some members of the [[National Socialist German Workers Party|Nazi Party]] were using the rigid, outstretched right arm salute to greet their leader; and the leader responded by raising his own right hand crooked back at the elbow, palm opened upwards, in a gesture of acceptance.&lt;ref name=&quot;Evans&quot;&gt;{{cite book |last=Evans |first=Richard J. |title=The Coming of the Third Reich |publisher=Penguin Group |year=2005 |edition=reprint, illustrated |pages=184–185 |chapter=The Rize of Nazism |isbn=0143034693, 9780143034698}}&lt;/ref&gt; In 1926, the ''Heil Hitler'' salute was made compulsory.&lt;ref name=&quot;Myth&quot;&gt;Kershaw (2001), p. 26.&lt;/ref&gt; It functioned as a display of commitment to the Party and a [[declaration]] of principle to the outside world.&lt;ref name=&quot;Tilman55&quot;&gt;Tilman (2009), p. 55.&lt;/ref&gt; Yet, the drive to gain acceptance did not go unchallenged.&lt;ref name=&quot;Tilman55&quot; /&gt;

Some party members challenged the legitimacy of the so-called Roman salute employed by Fascist Italy, as not [[German folklore|Germanic]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Tilman55&quot; /&gt; In response, efforts were made to establish its pedigree by inventing a tradition after the fact.&lt;ref name=&quot;Tilman55&quot; /&gt; In June 1928, [[Rudolph Hess]] published an article titled &quot;The Fascist Greeting&quot;, which claimed the gesture was used in Germany as early as 1921, before the Nazis had heard about the Italian Fascists.&lt;ref name=&quot;Tilman556&quot;&gt;Tilman (2009), pp.55–56&lt;/ref&gt; He admits in the article: &quot;The NSDAP's introduction of the raised-arm greeting approximately two years ago still gets some people's blood boiling.  Its opponents suspect the greeting of being un-Germanic. They accuse it of merely aping the (Italian) Fascists&quot;,&lt;ref name=&quot;Tilman56&quot;&gt;Tilman (2009), p. 56.&lt;/ref&gt; but goes on to ask, &quot;and even if the decree from two years ago (Hess's order that all party members use it) is seen as an adaption of the Fascist gesture, is that really so terrible&quot;?&lt;ref name=&quot;Tilman56&quot; /&gt; [[Ian Kershaw]] points out that Hess did not deny the likely influence from Fascist Italy, even if indeed the salute had been used sporadically in 1921 as Hess claimed.&lt;ref name=&quot;Kershaw&quot;&gt;{{cite book |last=Kershaw |first=Ian |title=Hitler, 1889–1936: hubris |publisher=W. W. Norton &amp; Company |year=2000 |pages=294, 689 |edition=illustrated |isbn=0393320359, 9780393320350}}&lt;/ref&gt;

On the night of 3 January 1942, Hitler said of the origins of the salute:&lt;ref name=&quot;tabletalk&quot;&gt;{{cite book |
title=Hitler's Table Talk 1941–1944 |
last1=Hitler |
first1=Adolf |
authorlink1=Adolf Hitler |
last2=|
first2=|
authorlink2=Hugh Trevor-Roper |
others = trans. Cameron, Norman; Stevens, R.H. Preface and Introduction: The Mind of Adolf Hitler by H.R. Trevor-Roper |
editor-first= Martin |
editor-last = Bormann |
editor-link=Martin Bormann |
date= 1 October 2000 |
publisher=Enigma Books |
edition=3rd |
location=London |
isbn=1929631057|
pages=172–173 |
ref=TableTalk2000
}}&lt;/ref&gt; {{quote|I made it the salute of the Party long after the [[Duce]] had adopted it. I'd read the description of the sitting of the [[Diet of Worms]], in the course of which [[Martin Luther|Luther]] was greeted with the German salute.  It was to show him that he was not being confronted with arms, but with peaceful intentions.  In the days of [[Frederick the Great]], people still saluted with their hats, with pompous gestures.  In the [[Middle Ages]] the serfs humbly doffed their bonnets, whilst the noblemen gave the German salute. It was in the [[The Ratskeller in Bremen|Ratskeller at Bremen]], about the year 1921, that I first saw this style of salute.  It must be regarded as a survival of an ancient custom, which originally signified: &quot;See, I have no weapon in my hand!&quot; I introduced the salute into the Party at our first meeting in [[Weimar]].  The [[Schutzstaffel|SS]] at once gave it a soldierly style.  It's from that moment that our opponents honored us with the epithet &quot;dogs of Fascists&quot;.|Adolf Hitler|''[[Hitler's Table Talk]]}}

==From 1933 to 1945==
[[Image:Briefmark Reichsparteitag 1936.jpg|thumb|upright|Raised hands in a [[salute]] to the [[swastika]] on a German stamp commemorating the 1936 [[Nuremberg Rally]].]]

The compulsory use of the Hitler salute for all public employees followed a directive issued by Reich [[Minister of the Interior]] [[Wilhelm Frick]] on 13 July 1933, one day before the ban on all non-Nazi parties.&lt;ref name=&quot;Myth60&quot; &gt;Kershaw (2001) p.60&lt;/ref&gt; The decree also required the salute during the singing of the national anthem and the ''[[Horst-Wessel-Lied]]''.&lt;ref name=&quot;Myth60&quot; /&gt; It stipulated that &quot;anyone not wishing to come under suspicion of behaving in a consciously negative fashion will therefore render the Hitler Greeting&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;Myth60&quot; /&gt; A rider to the decree, added two weeks later, stipulated that if physical disability prevented raising of the right arm, &quot;then it is correct to carry out the Greeting with the left arm.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;Myth&quot; /&gt; On 27 September, prison inmates were forbidden to use the salute,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://select.nytimes.com/mem/archive/pdf?res=F60B10FC3E541A7A93C5AB1782D85F478385F9 |title=Nazi Salute Banned in Prisons |last=Wireless to THE NEW YORK TIMES |date=27 September 1933 |work=The New York Times |page=12 |accessdate=26 February 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; as were Jews by 1937.&lt;ref&gt;Tilman (2009), p. 51.&lt;/ref&gt;

By the end of 1934, special courts were established to punish those who refused to salute.&lt;ref name=&quot;Tilman61&quot;&gt;Tilman (2009), p. 61.&lt;/ref&gt; Offenders, such as Protestant preacher [[Paul Schneider (pastor)|Paul Schneider]], faced the possibility of being sent to a concentration camp.&lt;ref name=&quot;Tilman61&quot; /&gt; Foreigners were not exempt from intimidation. For example, the Portuguese [[Consul (representative)|Consul General]] was beaten by members of the [[Sturmabteilung]] for remaining seated in a car and not saluting a procession in [[Hamburg]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Shore&quot;&gt;{{cite book |last=Shore |first=Zachary |title=What Hitler knew: the battle for information in Nazi foreign policy |publisher=Oxford University Press US |year=2003 |edition=illustrated |page=33 |isbn=0195154592, 9780195154597}}&lt;/ref&gt; Reactions to inappropriate use were not merely violent but sometimes bizarre.&lt;ref name=&quot;Tilman60&quot;&gt;Tilman (2009), p. 60.&lt;/ref&gt; For example, a memo dated 23 July 1934 sent to local police stations stated: &quot;There have been reports of traveling vaudeville performers training their monkeys to give the German Greeting....see to it that said animals are destroyed&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;Tilman60&quot; /&gt;

[[File:SauckelAufruf.jpg|thumb|left|upright|Appeal by [[Fritz Sauckel]] to show gratitude by using the Hitler salute (ca. 1934)]]
The salute became an ordinary way of life.&lt;ref name=&quot;Tilman33&quot;&gt;Tilman (2009), p. 33&lt;/ref&gt; Postmen used the greeting when they knocked on people's doors to deliver packages or letters.&lt;ref name=&quot;Tilman33&quot; /&gt; Small metal signs that reminded people to use the Hitler salute were displayed in public squares and on telephone poles and street lights throughout Germany.&lt;ref name= &quot;Tilman34&quot;&gt;Tilman (2009), p. 34.&lt;/ref&gt; Department store clerks greeted customers with “Heil Hitler, how may I help you?”&lt;ref name=&quot;Tilman33&quot; /&gt; Dinner guests brought glasses etched with the words &quot;Heil Hitler&quot; as house gifts.&lt;ref name=&quot;Tilman33&quot; /&gt;
[[File:Bundesarchiv Bild 183-2007-0329-501, Reichsgründungsfeier, Schulklasse.jpg|thumb|upright|right|The Nazi salute in school, 1934]]
Children were indoctrinated at an early age.&lt;ref name=&quot;Tilman35&quot;&gt;Tilman (2009), p. 35.&lt;/ref&gt; Kindergarten children were taught to raise their hand to the proper height by hanging their lunch bags across the raised arm of their teacher.&lt;ref name=&quot;Tilman35&quot; /&gt; At the beginning of first grade primers was a lesson on how to use the greeting.&lt;ref name=&quot;Tilman35&quot; /&gt; The greeting found its way into fairy tales, including classics like ''[[Sleeping Beauty]]''.&lt;ref name=&quot;Tilman35&quot; /&gt; Students and teachers would salute each other at the beginning and end of the school day, between classes, or whenever an adult entered the classroom.&lt;ref&gt;Tilman (2009), p. 38.&lt;/ref&gt;

Some athletes used the Nazi salute in the opening ceremony of the [[1936 Summer Olympics|1936 Berlin Olympics]] as they passed by Adolf Hitler in the reviewing stand.&lt;ref name=&quot;Schaap&quot;&gt;
{{cite book
|last=Schaap
|first=Jeremy
|title=Triumph: the untold story of Jesse Owens and Hitler's Olympics|publisher=Houghton Mifflin Harcourt
|year=2007
|pages=163–166
|isbn=0618688226, 9780618688227}}&lt;/ref&gt; This was done by delegates from Afghanistan, [[Bermuda]], Bulgaria, Bolivia, France, Greece, Iceland, Italy and Turkey.&lt;ref name=&quot;Schaap&quot; /&gt; The Bulgarian athletes performed the Nazi salute and broke into a [[goose-step]];&lt;ref name=&quot;Schaap&quot; /&gt; Turkish athletes maintained the salute all around the track.&lt;ref name=&quot;Mandell&quot; /&gt; There is some confusion over the use of the salute, since the stiff-arm Nazi salute could have been mistaken for an [[Olympic_symbols#Olympic_salute|Olympic salute]], with the right arm held out at a slight angle to the right from the shoulder.&lt;ref name=&quot;Schaap&quot; /&gt; According to the American sportswriter [[Jeremy Schaap]], only half of the athletes from Austria performed a Nazi salute, while the other half gave an Olympic salute. According to the historian Richard Mandell, there are conflicting reports on whether athletes from France performed a Nazi salute or an Olympic Salute.&lt;ref name=&quot;Mandell&quot;&gt;
{{cite book
|last=Mandell
|first=Richard D.
|title=The Nazi Olympics
|publisher=University of Illinois Press
|year=1987
|edition=illustrated, reprint
|series=Sports and society
|page=149
|isbn=0252013255, 9780252013256}}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:Bundesarchiv Bild 101I-030-0787-10, Polen, General Karl Heinrich v. Stülpnagel.jpg|thumb|upright|General [[Carl-Heinrich von Stülpnagel|von Stülpnagel]] saluting in customary [[Wehrmacht]] style, January 1941]]
The [[Wehrmacht]] refused to adopt the Hitler salute and was able for a time to maintain its own customs.&lt;ref name=&quot;Tilman80&quot;&gt;Tilman (2009) pp. 80–82.&lt;/ref&gt; A compromise edict from the Reich Defense Ministry, released on 19 September 1933, required the Hitler salute of soldiers and uniformed civil servants while singing the ''[[Horst Wessel Lied]]'' and [[Deutschlandlied|national anthem]], and in non-military encounters both within and outside the Wehrmacht (for example, when greeting members of the civilian government). At all other times they were to use their traditional salutes.&lt;ref name=&quot;Tilman80&quot; /&gt; Only after the [[20 July Plot]] in 1944 were the military forces of the Third Reich ordered to replace the standard military salute with the Hitler salute.&lt;ref name=&quot;Tilman82&quot; /&gt; The order went into effect on 24 July 1944, four days after the attempt on Hitler's life in [[Kętrzyn|Rastenburg]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Tilman82&quot;&gt;Tilman (2009), p. 82.&lt;/ref&gt;

On the night of 3 January 1942, Hitler stated the following about the compromise edict of 1933:&lt;ref name=&quot;tabletalk&quot; /&gt; {{quote|I imposed the German salute for the following reason. I'd given orders, at the beginning, that in the Army I should not be greeted with the German salute. But many people forgot. [[Werner von Fritsch|Fritsch]] drew his conclusions, and punished all who forgot to give me the military salute, with fourteen days' confinement to barracks. I, in turn, drew my conclusions and introduced the German salute likewise into the Army.|Adolf Hitler|''[[Hitler's Table Talk]]}}

Despite indoctrination and punishment, the salute was ridiculed by some people. Since &quot;heil&quot; is also the imperative of the German verb &quot;heilen&quot; (&quot;to heal&quot;), a common joke in Nazi Germany was to reply with &quot;Is he sick?&quot;, &quot;Am I a doctor?&quot;, or &quot;You heal him!&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;Tilman44&quot;&gt;Tilman (2009), p. 44.&lt;/ref&gt; Jokes were also made by distorting the phrase. So for example ''Heil Hitler'' might become ''Ein Liter'' (&quot;One liter&quot;).&lt;ref name=&quot;Tilman44&quot; /&gt; Cabaret performer [[Karl Valentin]] would quip, &quot;It's lucky that Hitler's name wasn't 'Kräuter'. Otherwise, we'd have to go around yelling Heilkräuter ('medicinal herbs')&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;Tilman44&quot; /&gt;

Satirical use of the salute dates back to anti-Nazi propaganda in Germany before 1933. In 1932, [[photomontage]] artist [[John Heartfield]] used Hitler's modified version, with the hand bent over the shoulder, in a poster that linked Hitler to [[Big Business]]. A giant figure representing [[Right-wing politics|right-wing]] capitalists stands behind Hitler, placing money in his hand, suggesting 'backhand' donations. The caption is, &quot;the meaning of the Hitler salute&quot; and &quot;Millions stand behind me&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;Jay&quot;&gt;
{{cite book
|last=Jay
|first=Martin
|title=The Oxford illustrated history of modern Europe
|editor=T. C. W. Blanning
|publisher=Oxford University Press
|year=2001
|edition=illustrated, reissue
|series=Oxford Illustrated Histories
|page=261
|chapter=From Modernism to Post-Modernism
|isbn=0192854267, 9780192854261}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Sieg Heil==

[[File:Bundesarchiv Bild 102-04481B, Berlin, Maifeier auf dem Tempelhofer Feld.jpg|thumb|upright|A mass rally on [[Tempelhof]] field, 1 May 1935]]
''Sieg Heil'' was a ritualistic chant used at mass rallies, where enthusiastic crowds answered ''Heil'' to the call of ''Sieg'' (&quot;victory&quot;).&lt;ref&gt;Tilman (2009), p. 32.&lt;/ref&gt; For example, at the 1934 Nuremberg Rally, Rudolf Hess ends his climactic speech with, &quot;The Party is Hitler. But Hitler is Germany, just as Germany is Hitler. Hitler! Sieg Heil!&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Kershaw (2001), p. 69.&lt;/ref&gt; At his [[Sportpalast speech|total war speech]] delivered in 1943, audiences shouted ''Sieg Heil'' as [[Joseph Goebbels]] solicited from them &quot;a kind of plebiscitary 'Ja' to self destruction in a war which Germany could by now neither win nor end through negotiated peace&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;Kershaw
N561&quot;&gt;Kershaw (2000), pp. 561–562.&lt;/ref&gt;
In correspondence with high-ranking nazi officials, letters were usually signed with &quot;Heil Hitler&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;Klee, Kulturlexikon, S. 227.&lt;/ref&gt;

On 11 March 1945, less than two months before the [[Victory Day (9 May)|capitulation of Nazi Germany]], a memorial for the dead of the war was held in [[Marktschellenberg]], a small town near Hitler's [[Berghof (residence)|Berghof residence]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Kershaw Nemesis&quot;&gt;Kershaw (2000), p. 766.&lt;/ref&gt; The historian [[Ian Kershaw]] reports, &quot;When the leader of the Wehrmacht unit at the end of his speech called for a ''Sieg Heil'' for the Fuhrer, it was returned neither by the Wehrmacht present, nor by the [[Volkssturm]], nor by the spectators of the civilian population who had turned up. This silence of the masses... probably reflects better than anything else, the attitudes of the population.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;Kershaw Nemesis&quot; /&gt;

The [[Swing Kids]] ({{lang-de|link=no|Swing Jugend}}) were a group of middle-class teenagers who consciously separated themselves from Nazism and its culture, greeting each other with 'Swing-Heil!' and addressing one another as 'old-hot-boy'.&lt;ref name=&quot;Willet&quot;&gt;{{cite journal |last=Willett |first=Ralph |date=May 1989|title=Hot Swing and the Dissolute Life: Youth, Style and Popular Music in Europe 1939–49 |journal=Popular Music |publisher=Cambridge University Press |volume= 8 |issue=2 |page=161 |jstor=853465}}&lt;/ref&gt; This playful behaviour was dangerous for participants in the subculture; on 2 January 1942, [[Heinrich Himmler]] ordered that the leaders be put in concentration camps to be drilled and beaten.&lt;ref name=&quot;Willet&quot; /&gt;

==Reactions outside Nazi Germany==
[[File:They salute with both hands now 1934-DLow.png|thumb|left|150px|&quot;They salute with both hands now&quot; A political cartoon in the ''[[Evening Standard|London Evening Standard]]'' 3 July 1934, depicting the SA surrendering to Hitler after the [[Night of the Long Knives]].]]
[[File:Dictator charlie2.jpg|thumb|upright|[[Charlie Chaplin]] in ''[[The Great Dictator]]'' (1940)]]

In England, the cartoonist [[David Low (cartoonist)|David Low]] caricatured members of the [[Sturmabteilung]] during [[Night of the Long Knives]] in 1934 –with their hands raised to surrender– with the caption &quot;They salute with both hands now&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |last= Kelly |first=Nigel |coauthors= Martyn J. Whittock |title=The twentieth century world |publisher=Heinemann|year=1995 |edition=illustrated |series=Heinemann History Study Units Series |page=46 |isbn=0435312928, 9780435312923}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In the United States, [[Charlie Chaplin]] produced and directed a [[comedy film]] called ''[[The Great Dictator]]'' that satirised Adolf Hitler and Nazism and portrayed the protagonist, Adenoid Hynkel, as ridiculously obsessed with the salute. For instance, when he passes the famous statues of ''[[The Thinker]]'' and ''[[Venus de Milo]]'', they appear in a saluting posture.&lt;ref&gt;
{{cite book
|last=Schechter
|first=Joel
|title=Satiric impersonations: from Aristophanes to the Guerrilla Girls
|publisher=SIU Press
|year=1994
|edition=illustrated
|page=67
|isbn=0809318687, 9780809318681}}&lt;/ref&gt; At the film's first release in October 1940, the United States was still formally at peace with Nazi Germany. After America entered the war, [[Spike Jones]] released the derisory song &quot;[[Der Führer's Face]]&quot;, in which ''Heil'' was accompanied throughout by [[blowing a raspberry]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Taruskin&quot;&gt;
{{cite book
|last=Taruskin
|first=Richard
|title=Music in the Late Twentieth Century
|publisher=Oxford University Press US
|year=2009|edition=illustrated
|series=Oxford History of Western Music
|volume=5
|page=505
|isbn=0195384857, 9780195384857}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Because of the similarity between the [[Bellamy salute]] in the United States and the Nazi salute, President [[Franklin D. Roosevelt]] instituted the hand-over-the-heart gesture as the salute to be rendered by civilians during the [[Pledge of Allegiance]] and the [[The Star-Spangled Banner|national anthem]] in the United States, instead of the Bellamy salute.&lt;ref name=&quot;Bishop&quot;&gt;
{{cite book
|last=Bishop
|first=Ronald
|title=Taking on the Pledge of Allegiance: the news media and Michael Newdow's Constitutional challenge|
publisher=SUNY Press
|year=2007
|page=27
|chapter=A Case of First Impression
|isbn=0791471810, 9780791471814}}&lt;/ref&gt; This was done when [[United States Congress|Congress]] officially adopted the [[United States Flag Code|''Flag Code'']] on 22 June 1942.&lt;ref&gt;
{{cite book
|last=Leepson
|first=Marc
|title=Flag: An American Biography
|publisher=Macmillan
|year=2006
|page=171
|isbn=0312323093}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Post-1945==
[[File:Producer spngtim 4.jpg|thumb|right||upright|Dancing stormtroopers in ''[[Springtime for Hitler]]'' (1968)]]
Today in Germany, Nazi salutes in written form, vocally, and even straight-extending the right arm with or without the phrase, are forbidden.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
 |url= http://www.hagalil.com/deutschland/rechts/erkennungszeichen/rechtsextremismus.htm
 |title=Rechtsextremismus – Straftaten
 |work=hagalil.com
 |accessdate=24 February 2010
}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=Tilman945&gt;Tilman (2009), pp. 94–95.&lt;/ref&gt; It is a criminal offence punishable by up to three years of prison ([[Strafgesetzbuch section 86a]]).&lt;ref name=&quot;Tilman945&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;StGB&quot;&gt;{{cite web
|url=http://www.iuscomp.org/gla/statutes/StGB.htm#86aSection
|title=Criminal Code (Strafgesetzbuch, StGB)
|date=13 November 1998
|work=Federal Law Gazette I,
|pages=945, p. 3322
|accessdate=14 February 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; Usage for art, teaching and science is exempt from punishment unless &quot;the existence of an insult results from the form of the utterance or the circumstances under which it occurred&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;StGB&quot; /&gt; Use of the salute has also been forbidden by law in Austria since the end of World War II.

Usage that is &quot;ironic and clearly critical of the Hitler Greeting&quot; is exempt, and this exemption has led to legal debates as to what constitutes ironic use of the salute.&lt;ref name=&quot;Tilman95&quot;&gt;Tilman (2009), p. 95.&lt;/ref&gt; One recent case involved [[Ernst August, Prince of Hanover (b. 1954)|Prince Albrecht of Hanover]], who was brought to court after using the gesture as a commentary on the behavior of an overly zealous airport baggage inspector.&lt;ref name=&quot;Tilman95&quot; /&gt; On 23 November 2007, the [[Amtsgericht]] [[Cottbus]] sentenced [[Horst Mahler]] to six months of imprisonment without parole for having, according to his own claims, ironically performed the Hitler salute when reporting to prison for a nine-month term a year earlier.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |date=23 November 2007 |title=Sechs Monate für Hitlergruß |language=German|publisher=[[Die Zeit]]/[[dpa]] |url=http://www.zeit.de/online/2007/48/mahler-urteil}}&lt;/ref&gt; The following month, a pensioner named Roland T was given a prison term of five months for, amongst other things, training his dog Adolf to raise his right paw in a Nazi salute every time the command &quot;Heil Hitler!&quot; was uttered.&lt;ref name=&quot;Paterson &quot;&gt;{{cite news |url=http://www.independent.co.uk/news/world/europe/dogs-nazi-salute-lands-owner-in-jail-for-five-months-766438.html |title=Dog's Nazi salute lands owner in jail for five months |last=Paterson |first=Tony |date=21 December 2007 |work=The Independent |location=UK |accessdate=1 March 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Versions of the salute are used by [[neo-Nazis]], who also use the number '''88''' to stand for &quot;Heil Hitler&quot; (the [[8 (number)|8]] standing for [[H]], the eighth letter of the alphabet).&lt;ref name=&quot;Tilman94&quot;&gt;Tilman (2009), p. 94.&lt;/ref&gt; One version is the so-called [[Michael Kühnen|Kühnen]] salute with extended thumb, [[index finger|index]] and [[middle finger]], also forbidden in Germany.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news
|url=http://www.kleinezeitung.at/nachrichten/politik/1989141/index.do
|title=Kühnengruß oder sechs Bier bei FPÖ-Parteitag?
|date=27 May 2009
|publisher=Kleine Zeitung
|language=German
|accessdate=27 August 2009}} Second paragraph: &quot;The Kühnengruß is regarded as a variation of the Hitler salute. In it the right arm is extended with three fingers spread. In Austria, unlike Germany, the salute is not prohibited&quot;.&lt;/ref&gt; In Switzerland, Neo-Nazis are usually seen to perform this salute. The Swiss [[Rütlischwur]], the traditional oath of pledge sworn at the founding of Switzerland in 1291, was also made with the three fingers extended, although the arm was not fully extended as in the Hitler pledge.

Satirical displays of the salute continued after the war. A notable example is [[Mel Brooks]]' comedy film ''[[The Producers]]'', in which the Hitler salute is performed as a [[can-can]] dance in the [[Play within a play|fictional musical]] ''[[Springtime for Hitler]]''.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book
|last=Finney
|first=Gail
|title=Visual culture in twentieth-century Germany: text as spectacle
|publisher=Indiana University Press
|year=2006
|page=237
|isbn=0253347181, 9780253347183}}&lt;/ref&gt; Another example is [[Stanley Kubrick]]'s ''[[Dr. Strangelove]]'', whose eponymous character played by [[Peter Sellers]] had a 'possessed' arm which would [[Alien hand syndrome|independently spring]] into a Nazi salute (when not attempting to strangle its owner).&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book
|last=Goodchild
|first=Peter
|title=Edward Teller, the real Dr. Strangelove
|publisher=Harvard University Press
|year=2004
|edition=illustrated
|page=xxi
|isbn=0674016696, 9780674016699}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The border between satirical and offensive usage of the term &quot;Sieg Heil&quot; is sometimes ambiguous. On 1 December 2003, [[Dieudonné M'bala M'bala]] appeared live on a television show, disguised as a [[Haredi Judaism|Haredi]] (Orthodox) Jew making the Hitler salute and bellowing &quot;Isra-Heil&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.24heures.ch/actu/culture/dieudonne-promo-pire-2009-01-06 ''Dieudonné, la promo par le pire''], [[24 heures]], 7 January 2009.&lt;/ref&gt; He was cleared of charges of antisemitism in a Paris court after the judge said this was not an attack against Jews in general but against a type of person &quot;distinguished by their political views&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news
 |title = French comic 'not anti-Semitic'
 |publisher=BBC 
 |date = 27 May 2004
 |url = http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/world/europe/3755013.stm
 |accessdate =7 May 2009 }}&lt;/ref&gt; At the [[European Parliament election, 2004]], Dieudonné was candidate of the extreme left-wing party &quot;Euro-Palestine&quot;, but left a few months after the election because of disagreements with its Jewish leaders.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.europalestine.com/article.php3?id_article=1410 ''Dieudonné sur une pente très glissante''], Euro-Palestine, 29 October 2004.&lt;/ref&gt;

==Notes==
{{Reflist|2}}

==References==
* {{cite book |last=Kershaw |first=Ian |title=Hitler: 1936–45 : Nemesis |publisher=W. W. Norton &amp; Company |year=2000 |edition=illustrated |isbn=0393049949, 9780393049947}}
* {{cite book |last=Kershaw |first=Ian |title=The &quot;Hitler myth&quot;: image and reality in the Third Reich |publisher=Oxford University Press |year=2001 |edition=2, reissue |isbn=0192802062, 9780192802064}}
* {{cite book |last=Allert |first=Tilman |coauthors=Translated by Jefferson Chase |title=The Hitler Salute: On the Meaning of a Gesture |publisher=Picador |date=April 2009 |edition=Picador |isbn=0312428308, 9780312428303}}
* {{cite book |last=Winkler |first=Martin M. |title=The Roman Salute: Cinema, History, Ideology |publisher=Ohio State University Press |location=Columbus |year=2009 |isbn=0814208649, 9780814208649}}

{{Nazism}}
{{Fascism}}
{{Gestures}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Nazi Salute}}
[[Category:Nazism]]
[[Category:Greetings]]
[[Category:Gestures]]
[[Category:Adolf Hitler]]
[[Category:Symbols of Nazi Germany]]

[[ar:هايل (مصطلح)]]
[[bg:Хитлеров поздрав]]
[[cs:Heil Hitler]]
[[da:Heil]]
[[de:Hitlergruß]]
[[es:Saludo fascista]]
[[eo:Heil Hitler]]
[[fa:درود نازی]]
[[fr:Salut fasciste]]
[[hr:Hitlerov pozdrav]]
[[it:Saluto nazista]]
[[lv:Hitlera sveiciens]]
[[hu:Náci karlendítés]]
[[nl:Hitlergroet]]
[[ja:ナチス式敬礼]]
[[no:Hitlerhilsen]]
[[pl:Heil Hitler]]
[[pt:Saudação nazista]]
[[ro:Salutul nazist]]
[[ru:Нацистское приветствие]]
[[sh:Hitlerov pozdrav]]
[[fi:Natsitervehdys]]
[[sv:Hitlerhälsning]]
[[th:การสดุดีฮิตเลอร์]]
[[tr:Hitler selamı]]
[[uk:Нацистське вітання]]
[[zh:納粹禮]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
