<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="1030917" ns="0" title="Wire Fox Terrier"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Refimprove|date=May 2007}}
{{Infobox Dogbreed 
&lt;!-- Put article text AFTER this infobox markup. See: --&gt;
&lt;!-- Wikipedia:WikiProject Dog breeds/Templates for more info.--&gt;
|name= Wire Fox Terrier
|image= Elias1červen2006.jpg|image_caption= A Wire Fox Terrier (Ginger)
|altname= Wire Hair Fox Terrier &lt;br&gt; Wirehaired Terrier&lt;br&gt; Fox Terrier
|nickname= Foxie
|country= [[England]]
|fcigroup= 3
|fcisection= 1
|fcinum= 169
|fcistd= http://www.dogdomain.com/FCI/fcistandards/fci-169.htm
|akcgroup= Terrier
|akcstd= http://www.akc.org/breeds/wire_fox_terrier/index.cfm 
|ankcgroup= Group 2 (Terriers)
|ankcstd= http://ankc.org.au/home/breeds_details.asp?bid=57
|ckcgroup= Group 4 - Terriers
|ckcstd= http://www.ckc.ca/en/Default.aspx?tabid=99&amp;BreedCode=FTW
|kcukgroup= Terrier
|kcukstd=http://www.thekennelclub.org.uk/item/74
|nzkcgroup=Terrier
|nzkcstd=http://www.nzkc.org.nz/br240.html
|ukcgroup= Terrier
|ukcstd= http://mail.ukcdogs.com/UKCweb.nsf/80de88211ee3f2dc8525703f004ccb1e/70036e402093b7cc8525704d006abb1c?OpenDocument
|}}  
The '''Wire Fox Terrier'''  is a [[dog breed|breed]] of [[dog]], one of many [[terrier]] breeds. It is an instantly recognizable [[fox terrier]] breed.  Although it bears a resemblance to the [[Fox Terrier (Smooth)|Smooth Fox Terrier]], they are believed to have been developed separately.

==Appearance==
[[Image:P1030547 (Medium).jpg|thumb|left|A hand stripped British wire haired fox terrier]]
The wire fox terrier is a sturdy, balanced dog weighing between 7 and 9.5&amp;nbsp;kg (15 and 21&amp;nbsp;lb).  It should not be more than 15 1/2 in (39.37 cm) in height. Its rough, broken coat is distinctive.  Coat color consists of a predominant white base with brown markings of the face and ears, and usually a black saddle or large splotch of color; there may be other black or brown markings on the body.
The wire in the photo at left sports the traditional white, black and buff tri-color coat. The wire in the upper right hand photo appears to be a ginger, a wire without black markings.

==Temperament==
Two of the Wire Fox Terriers' most distinctive traits are their enormous amount of energy and intelligence. They have a low threshold for boredom and require stimulation, exercise and attention. Indeed, once absorbed into the family, they are an inquisitive pet with a nose for everybody's business. They particularly enjoy comfort time on the couch or in bed in the evening, the wirefox is a true companion animal. Most of them truly love water and are always up for a swim. A life jacket is recommended for them.
The Wire Fox Terrier should be alert, quick and ready to respond swiftly with enthusiasm. However they should also be friendly, communicative and exceedingly playful if they receive the proper care and exercise. Bred to be independent thinkers, they are capable of tactical maneuvering for vermin and other sport. Their stamina, energy and level of intelligence is unusually high. 
But before being seduced by these clever antics and independent ways, prospective owners should attempt to understand the breed's willful nature. 
Often, Wire Fox Terriers are abandoned or surrendered for reasons that may include running away instead of coming on command, chasing cars, bicycles, etc., taunting and then attacking other animals, including a household's cats and other dogs -- and they are sufficiently strong with more than enough bite pressure to do serious damage. 
But these are actually [http://www.wirefoxrescue.org/Breed_desc.htm normal behaviors] for a breed designed to hunt not only foxes but badgers and boars, with no more fear of cows or buses than they have for small prey. With a firm owner to control and redirect these prey instincts and provide them with enough exercise and diversion, Fox Terriers are amusing, exciting, long-lived companion animals -- but they are not for everyone. 

==Grooming==
Wire Hair Fox Terriers are hand stripped; if the hair becomes too long, their hair should be taken out by hand in order to preserve the colors and the glossiness of the coat.  Many Wire Fox pets are clipped 3 - 4 times a year by a groomer.  Clipping dulls the colors and makes the coat soft, curly and more difficult to keep clean, but is considered acceptable and comfortable by many owners. [[Image:Beam.JPG|thumb|left|Clipped four year old male British Wire-Hair Fox Terrier]]

==History==
The wire fox terrier was [[selective breeding|developed]] in England by [[fox hunting]] enthusiasts and is believed to be descended from a now-extinct rough-coated, [[Black and Tan Terrier|black-and-tan working terrier]] of Wales, Derbyshire, and Durham. The breed was also thought to have been bred to chase foxes into their underground burrows; the dogs' short, strong, usually docked tails were used as handles by the hunter to pull them back out.
[[File:Fox Terrier (wire-hair) from 1915.JPG|thumb|Wire-hair Fox Terrier circa 1915]]
Although it is said [[Queen Victoria]] owned one, and her son and heir, King Edward VII of Great Britain did own the wire fox terrier, Caesar, the wire fox terrier was not popular as a family [[pet]] until the 1930s, when ''[[The Thin Man (film)|The Thin Man]]'' series of [[feature film]]s was created.  [[Skippy (dog)|Asta]], the canine member of the [[Nick and Nora Charles|Charles]] family, was a Wire-Haired Fox Terrier, and the popularity of the breed soared. Milou ([[Snowy (character)|Snowy]]) from ''[[The Adventures of Tintin]]'' comic strip is also a Wire Fox Terrier. 

In the late 20th century, the popularity of the breed declined again, most likely due to changing living conditions in the Western world and the difficulty of keeping hunting terriers in cities due to their strong prey instincts.  

As of 2010, the wire fox terrier has the distinction of having received more [[List of Best in Show winners of the Westminster Kennel Club Dog Show|Best in Show]] titles at Westminster Kennel Club dog shows (currently 13) than any other breed.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.westminsterkennelclub.org/history/biswinners.html |title=Best in Show Winners |author= |date= |work=The Westminster Kennel Club |publisher= |accessdate=2011-01-20}}&lt;/ref&gt;  Wire fox terriers kept as pets show the loyalty, intelligence, independence, playfulness and breeding befitting such a storied breed.

Ch. [[Matford Vic]], a Wire Fox Terrier, is one of only five dogs to have won the [[Westminster Kennel Club Dog Show]] on more than one occasion. He won the competition twice, in 1915 and 1916. The only dog to win it on more occasions was Ch. Warren Remedy, a [[Smooth Fox Terrier]], who won it on three occasions between 1907 and 1909.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.westminsterkennelclub.org/history/biswinners.html |title=Best in Show Winners |author= |date= |work=The Westminster Kennel Club |publisher= |accessdate=2009-12-28}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Noteworthy Wire Fox Terriers==
*Archie, owned by Gill Raddings [[Stunt Dogs]] starred in ITV's Catwalk Dogs.
*[[Skippy (dog)|Asta]], from ''[[The Thin Man (film)|The Thin Man films adaptation]]'' (the novel's breed was a [[Schnauzer]])
*Bob, from the ''[[Hercule Poirot]]'' episode ''[[Dumb Witness]]''
*Bunny, from ''[[Hudson Hawk]]''
*Caesar, the companion of [[King Edward VII]] of the United Kingdom
*Charles, brought to Ceylon by Leonard Woolf in 1905
*Chester, in the film [[Jack Frost]]
*Dášeňka, the dog of Czechoslovak writer and journalist [[Karel Čapek]] - also featured as main hero of &quot;Dášeňka čili život štěněte&quot; book.
*George, from ''[[Bringing Up Baby]]''
*Ike Larue, from the ''Ike Larue'' series, written and illustrated by [[Mark Teague]]
*Moll, from the book &quot;Memoirs of a Fox Hunting Man&quot;
*Montmorency, from the book ''[[Three Men in a Boat]]'' by [[Jerome K. Jerome]]
*Mr. Atlas, from ''[[Topper Takes a Trip]]'' (played by [[Skippy (dog)|Skippy]])
*Mr. Smith, from ''[[The Awful Truth]]''
*Nellie, inspiration for ''Nellie the Lighthouse Dog'' (Nellie was formerly known as Hockney) by Jane Scarpino; Nellie's owner, Robert Ensor, illustrated
*Pan, the companion of A.L. Westgard, AAA pathfinder. Pan was the mascot of the dedication tour for the [[National Park to Park Highway]] in 1920.
*Polly, a white rough terrier companion to  [[Charles Darwin]]
*[http://www.tvacres.com/dogs_terriers_scruffy.htm Scruffy], the Muirs' Wire Fox Terrier on [[The Ghost and Mrs. Muir]]
*[[Skippy (dog)|Skippy]], starred as Asta in ''The Thin Man'', and other movies
*[[Snowy (character)|Snowy]] (''[[French language|French]]: Milou''), companion of [[Tintin (character)|Tintin]]
*&quot;The dog,&quot; from the Selchow and Righter board game &quot;Mr. Doodle's Dog&quot;
*Van Gogh, [[Paul Meltsner|Paul Meltsner's]] dog featured in his famous painting ''Paul, Marcella and Van Gogh''
*Wessex, the wire of British novelist (&quot;Tess of the d'Ubervilles&quot;) [[Thomas Hardy]]
*Willy, from ''[[Ask the Dust (film)|Ask the Dust]]''
*Wuffles, the [[Havelock Vetinari|Patrician]]'s dog in the ''[[Discworld]]'' Series

Asta, George, Mr. Smith and Skippy were all played by the canine actor, Skippy.

==See also==
*[[Fox Terrier]], for additional details on history, genetics, coat color, and so on.

==External links==
{{commons|Fox Terrier}}
*[http://www.wirefoxterrierassociation.co.uk/ The Wire Fox Terrier Association]
*[http://www.aftc.org/ American Fox Terrier Club, Inc.]

==References==
{{reflist}}

{{Terriers}}

[[Category:Dog breeds]]
[[Category:Terriers]]
[[Category:Dog breeds originating in England]]

[[cs:Foxteriér drsnosrstý]]
[[fr:Fox-terrier à poil dur]]
[[ja:ワイアーヘアード・フォックス・テリア]]
[[pl:Foksterier szorstkowłosy]]
[[pt:Fox terrier de pelo duro]]
[[ro:Fox Terrier sârmos]]
[[ru:Жесткошёрстный фокстерьер]]
[[sl:Resasti foksterier]]
[[fi:Karkeakarvainen kettuterrieri]]
[[sv:Strävhårig foxterrier]]
[[uk:Жорсткошерстий фокстер'єр]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
