<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="103549" ns="0" title="The Big Bopper"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Infobox musical artist
|name           = The Big Bopper
|background     = solo_singer
|image            =
|caption       = 
|birth_name     = Jiles Perry Richardson, Jr.
|Born           = {{birth date|1930|10|24}}&lt;br /&gt;[[Sabine Pass, Texas|Sabine Pass]], [[Texas]]&lt;br /&gt;[[United States|U.S.]]
|Died           = {{death date and age|1959|2|3|1930|10|24}}&lt;br/&gt; [[Grant Township, Cerro Gordo County, Iowa|Grant Township]], [[Iowa]], U.S.
|genre          = [[Rock and roll]], [[rockabilly]], [[Country music|country]] 
|occupation     = [[Musician]], [[songwriter]] 
|instrument     = [[Singer|Vocals]], [[guitar]]
|years_active   = 1954–59
|First_album    = 
|Latest_album   = 
|Notable_albums = 
|Notable_songs  = &quot;[[Chantilly Lace (song)|Chantilly Lace]]&quot; &quot;[[Chantilly Lace (song)|Big Bopper's Wedding]]&quot; 
|label          = [[Mercury Records]]
}}

'''Jiles Perry &quot;J. P.&quot; Richardson, Jr.''' (October 24, 1930 &amp;ndash; February 3, 1959) also commonly known as '''The Big Bopper''', was an [[United States|American]] [[disc jockey]], [[singing|singer]], and [[songwriter]] whose big voice and exuberant personality made him an early [[rock and roll]] star. He is best known for his recording of &quot;[[Chantilly Lace (song)|Chantilly Lace]]&quot;. 

On February 3, 1959, a day that has become known as [[The Day the Music Died]] (from [[Don McLean]]'s song &quot;[[American Pie (song)|American Pie]]&quot;),&lt;ref name = &quot;BBC&quot;&gt;{{cite news|title = 1959: Buddy Holly killed in air crash|publisher = BBC|url = http://news.bbc.co.uk/onthisday/hi/dates/stories/february/3/newsid_2802000/2802541.stm|work = On This Day|accessdate = 2008-11-02 | date=February 3, 1959 | location=London}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name = &quot;Thimou&quot;&gt;{{cite web|last = Thimou|first = Theodore|title = Preview: The Twice-Famous Don McLean Plays Rams Head|work = Bay Weekly|date = December 28, 2006|url = http://www.bayweekly.com/musicscene.html|accessdate = 2008-09-11 |archiveurl = http://web.archive.org/web/20080613224425/http://www.bayweekly.com/musicscene.html &lt;!-- Bot retrieved archive --&gt; |archivedate = 2008-06-13}}&lt;/ref&gt; Richardson was killed in a plane crash in [[Iowa]], along with [[Buddy Holly]] and [[Ritchie Valens]].

==Early years==
Richardson was born in [[Sabine Pass, Texas]], the oldest son of Jiles Perry Richardson, Sr. and his wife Elise (Stalsby) Richardson. His father was an oil field worker. Richardson had two younger brothers, Cecil and James. The family soon moved to [[Beaumont, Texas]]. Richardson graduated from Beaumont High School in 1947 and played on the &quot;Royal Purple&quot; football team as a defensive lineman, wearing number 85&lt;ref&gt;''Big Bopper: From Head Waiter To Rock'N'Roll Hero''. T Knight - Goldmine, 1989&lt;/ref&gt;. Richardson later studied pre-law at [[Lamar University|Lamar College]], and was a member of the band and chorus. He sometimes played with the Johnny Lampson Combo.

==Radio==
He worked part time at [[Beaumont, Texas]] radio station KTRM (now [http://www.kzzbradio.com/ KZZB]). He was hired by the station full-time in 1949 and quit college. Richardson married Adrianne Joy Fryou on April 18, 1952. In December 1953, their daughter, Debra Joy, was born. Earlier that year Richardson had been promoted to Supervisor of Announcers at KTRM.

In March 1955, he was [[conscription in the United States|drafted]] into the [[United States Army]] and did his basic training at [[Fort Ord]], [[California]]. He spent the rest of his two years service as a radar instructor at [[Fort Bliss]], near [[El Paso, Texas]]. 

Following his discharge as a [[corporal]] in March 1957, Richardson returned to KTRM radio, where he held down the &quot;Dishwashers' Serenade&quot; shift from 11 AM to 12:30 PM, Monday through Friday. One of the station's sponsors wanted Richardson for a new time slot and suggested an idea for a show. Richardson had seen the college students doing a dance called The Bop, and he decided to call himself &quot;The Big Bopper&quot;. His new radio show ran from 3 to 6 p.m. Richardson soon became the station's program director.

In May 1957, he broke the record for continuous on-the-air broadcasting by eight minutes.  From a remote set-up in the lobby of the [[Jefferson Theatre]] in downtown Beaumont, Richardson performed for a total of five days, two hours and eight minutes, playing 1,821 records&lt;ref name=accuracy/&gt; and taking showers during five-minute newscasts.

Richardson is credited with coining the term ''[[music video]]'' in 1959, and recorded an early example himself.&lt;ref name=accuracy&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.accuracyproject.org/cbe-Richardson,J.P.TheBigBopper.html|title=J.P. &quot;The Big Dipper&quot; Richardson|publisher=Internet Accuracy Project|accessdate=2007-01-21}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Singer and songwriter==
Richardson — who played [[guitar]] — began his musical career as a songwriter. [[George Jones]] later recorded Richardson's &quot;[[White Lightning (George Jones song)|White Lightning]]&quot;, which became Jones' first #1 country hit in 1959 (#73 on the pop charts). Richardson also wrote &quot;[[Running Bear]]&quot; for [[Johnny Preston]], his friend from [[Port Arthur, Texas]]. The inspiration for the song came from Richardson's childhood memory of the [[Sabine River (Texas-Louisiana)|Sabine River]], where he heard stories about [[Native Americans in the United States|Indian]] tribes. Richardson sang background on &quot;Running Bear&quot;, but the recording wasn't released until September 1959, after his death. Within several months it became #1.

The man who launched Richardson as a recording artist was [[Pappy Daily|Harold &quot;Pappy&quot; Daily]] from [[Houston, Texas]]. Daily was promotion director for [[Mercury Records|Mercury]] and [[Starday Records]] and signed Richardson to Mercury. Richardson's first single, &quot;Beggar To A King&quot;, had a country flavor, but failed to gain any chart action. He soon cut &quot;[[Chantilly Lace (song)|Chantilly Lace]]&quot; as &quot;The Big Bopper&quot; for Pappy Daily's [[D (record label)|D label]]. Mercury bought the recording and released it in the summer of 1958. It reached #6 on the pop charts and spent 22 weeks in the national Top 40. It also inspired an [[answer record]] by [[Jayne Mansfield]] titled &quot;That Makes It&quot;. In &quot;Chantilly Lace&quot;, Richardson pretends to have a flirting phone conversation with his girlfriend; the Mansfield record suggests what his girlfriend might have been saying at the other end of the line.  Later that year, he scored a second hit, a raucous novelty tune entitled &quot;The Big Bopper's Wedding&quot;, in which Richardson pretends to be getting cold feet at the altar. He was known for his &quot;Hello baby!&quot;

==Death==
{{Main|The Day the Music Died}}
With the success of &quot;Chantilly Lace&quot;, Richardson took time off from KTRM radio and joined [[Buddy Holly]], [[Ritchie Valens]] and [[Dion and the Belmonts]] for a &quot;Winter Dance Party&quot; tour.  On the eleventh night of the tour, Holly chartered an airplane to fly them to the next show in Moorhead, Minnesota.  The musicians had been traveling by bus for over a week, and it had already broken down once. They were tired, they had not been paid yet and all of their clothes were dirty. With the airplane, Holly could arrive early, do everyone's laundry and get some rest.

21-year old pilot [[Roger Peterson (pilot)|Roger Peterson]] had agreed to take the singers to Fargo, North Dakota, where the airport serves the cities of Moorhead and Fargo.  A snowstorm was inbound, and the pilot was fatigued from a 17-hour workday, but agreed to fly the trip.  The musicians packed up their instruments and finalized the flight arrangements.  Buddy Holly's bass player, [[Waylon Jennings]], was scheduled to fly on the plane, but gave his seat up to the Big Bopper, who was suffering from influenza.  Holly's guitarist, [[Tommy Allsup]], agreed to flip a coin with Ritchie Valens for the remaining seat; Valens won.  The three musicians boarded the red and white single-engine [[Beech Bonanza]] around 12:30 AM on February 3. Snow blew across the runway, but the sky was clear.  Peterson received clearance from the control tower, taxied down the runway and took off.  He was never told of two weather advisories that warned of an oncoming blizzard ahead. 

The plane remained airborne only a few minutes; no one is sure what went wrong.  The best guess is Peterson flew directly into the blizzard, lost visual reference and accidentally flew down instead of up.  The four-passenger plane plowed into a cornfield at over 170&amp;nbsp;mph, flipping over on itself and tossing the passengers into the air.  Their bodies landed yards from the wreckage and remained there for ten hours as snowdrifts formed around them.  Because of the weather, no one reached the crash site until later in the morning.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | title = The Day the Music Died | journal = Time Magazine | id = | accessdate = 2010-05-19}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Son==
Richardson was survived by his wife and four-year-old daughter. His son, Jay Perry Richardson, was born two months later in April 1959. At the time of his death, Richardson had been building a recording studio in his home in [[Beaumont, Texas]], and was also planning to invest in the ownership of a radio station. He had written 20 new songs he planned to record himself or with other artists.

Jay Perry Richardson took up a musical career and is known professionally as &quot;The Big Bopper, Jr.,&quot; and has performed around the world. He has toured on the &quot;Winter Dance Party&quot; tour with Buddy Holly impersonator John Mueller on some of the stages where his father performed.

In January 2007, Jay requested that his father's body be [[exhumed]] and an [[autopsy]] be performed to settle the rumors that a gun was fired or that Richardson initially survived the crash.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title=Autopsy of 'Big Bopper' to Address Rumors About 1959 Plane Crash|url=http://www.washingtonpost.com/wp-dyn/content/article/2007/01/17/AR2007011701976.html|publisher=Associated Press|date=2007-01-18}}&lt;/ref&gt; The autopsy was performed by Dr. [[Bill Bass]], a [[forensic anthropologist]] at the [[University of Tennessee]], [[Knoxville, Tennessee|Knoxville]]. Jay was present with Dr. Bass throughout the autopsy and observed as the casket was opened; both men were surprised to find the remains well enough preserved to be recognizable as those of the late rock star. &quot;Dad still amazes me 48 years after his death, that he was in remarkable shape,&quot; Richardson told the Associated Press. &quot;I surprised myself. I handled it better than I thought I would&quot;.&lt;ref name = &quot;Rumors&quot;/&gt; Dr. Bass' findings indicated there were no signs of foul play. He was quoted as saying, &quot;There are fractures from head to toe. Massive fractures. ...(Richardson) died immediately. He didn't crawl away. He didn't walk away from the plane&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;Rumors&quot;&gt;{{cite news|last=Davis|first=Elizabeth A.|title=48 Years Later, Big Bopper Rumors Buried|work=Associated Press| date=2007-03-07|url=http://news.yahoo.com/s/ap/20070307/ap_en_mu/big_bopper_autopsy;_ylt=AiuEThYrYavV4isgGgMkAfEDW7oF| accessdate=2007-03-08}} {{Dead link|date=October 2010|bot=H3llBot}}&lt;/ref&gt;

After the autopsy, Richardson's body was placed in a new casket made by the same company as the original, then was re-buried next to his wife in Beaumont's Forest Lawn Cemetery. Jay then allowed the old casket to be put on display at the [[Texas Musicians Museum]]. In December 2008, Jay Richardson announced that he would be placing the old casket up for auction on [[eBay]], giving a share of the proceeds to the Texas Musicians Museum,&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.beaumontenterprise.com/news/local/36759549.html Big Bopper's casket a macabre marketable on eBay], The Beaumont Enterprise, December 27, 2008&lt;/ref&gt; but downplayed the suggestion in later interviews.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.beaumontenterprise.com/news/local/big_bopper_s_casket_may_not_appear_on_ebay_01-14-2009.html Big Bopper's casket appears on eBay, but it's not for sale], The Beaumont Enterprise, January 14, 2009&lt;/ref&gt;

==Awards/honors==
* Rockabilly Hall of Fame (1997)
* Texas Country Hall of Fame (2004)
* Texas Radio Hall of Fame (2008)

==Compositions==
Songs Richardson composed and recorded include:

* [[Chantilly Lace (song)|Chantilly Lace]]
* Big Bopper's Wedding
* [[White Lightning (George Jones song)|White Lightnin']], #1 hit for George Jones
* [[Running Bear]], #1 hit for Johnny Preston
* [[Purple People Eater]] Meets the [[Witch Doctor (song)|Witch Doctor]]
* Little Red Riding Hood
* Walking Through My Dreams (two versions, one on 45-RPM only, the other on LP)
* Beggar to a King (recorded under his real name)
* Crazy Blues (recorded under his real name)
* Bopper's Boogie Woogie
* That's What I'm Talking About
* Pink Petticoats
* Monkey Song (You Made a Monkey out of Me) (Richardson's attempt to imitate Buddy Holly)
* It's the Truth, Ruth (two versions, one on 45-RPM only, the other on LP)
* [[Preacher and the Bear]]
* Someone Watching Over You
* Old Maid
* Strange Kisses
* Teenage Moon
* The Clock

==Tributes==
[[Image:HollyMonument.jpg|thumb|right|Monument at Crash Site, September 16, 2003]]
In 1988, Ken Paquette, a Wisconsin fan of the 1950s era, erected a stainless steel monument depicting a steel guitar and a set of three records bearing the names of each of the three performers. It is located on private farmland, about one quarter mile west of the intersection of 315th Street and Gull Avenue, approximately eight miles north of Clear Lake; this is where the plane crash occurred. He also created a similar stainless steel monument to the three near the Riverside Ballroom in [[Green Bay, Wisconsin]]. The memorial was unveiled on July 17, 2003.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.articlestree.com/music/the-day-the-music-died-tx390707.html The Day the Music Died - Music Articles]&lt;/ref&gt;

J.P. Richardson's pioneering contribution to the genre has been recognized by the [[Rockabilly Hall of Fame]]. The Big Bopper is fondly remembered not only for his distinctive singing and songwriting, but also as a humorist who combined the best elements of country, R&amp;B and rock 'n' roll.

His name is mentioned as one of the upcoming musical acts in both the print and television versions of [[Stephen King]]'s [[short story]] ''[[You Know They Got a Hell of a Band]]'' about a town inhabited by late musical legends. Buddy Holly is subsequently featured in the story.

The Canadian television comedy show ''[[Second City Television|SCTV]]'' featured a character named &quot;Sue Bopper-Simpson&quot;, a fictional daughter of the Big Bopper, played by [[Catherine O'Hara]]. The character was a part-time real estate agent who appeared in a [[musical theatre|musical]] entitled ''I'm Taking My Own Head, Screwing It On Right, and No Guy's Gonna Tell Me That It Ain't''.

Shortly after the fatal plane crash, Tommy Dee wrote and recorded a song entitled ''[[Three Stars]]'' in tribute to the three singers. It was recorded by others, including [[Eddie Cochran]], a good friend of all three.

==Film and stage==
Richardson was portrayed by [[Gailard Sartain]] in ''[[The Buddy Holly Story]]'', Stephen Lee in ''[[La Bamba (film)|La Bamba]]'', and [[John Ennis (actor)|John Ennis]] in ''[[Walk Hard: The Dewey Cox Story]]''.

On the London stage, Richardson has been portrayed by John Simon Rawlings in the musical ''Buddy - The Buddy Holly Story'', and is currently being portrayed by Steve Dorsett in the 2011 UK National Tour.

Both a movie project and a stage musical about Richardson are currently in development. (See [http://www.bigboppermovie.com www.bigboppermovie.com] and [http://www.chantillylace.com www.chantillylace.com])

The song Chantilly Lace is used in the movie [[True Romance]]&lt;ref&gt;''Lyrical commentaries: Learning from popular music''. BL Cooper - Music Educators Journal, 1991 - JSTOR
&lt;/ref&gt;.

==References==
{{Reflist}}

*Escott, Colin (1998). &quot;The Big Bopper (J.P. Richardson)&quot;. In ''The Encyclopedia of Country Music''. Paul Kingsbury, Editor. New York: Oxford University Press. p.&amp;nbsp;35.
* [http://www.angelfire.com/music5/archives/tribute.html ''Tribute: The Day the Music Died'' at The Death of Rock: The Archive]

==External links==
*{{Handbook of Texas|id=RR/fri40|name=Richardson, Jiles Perry}}
*{{discogs artist|artist=J.P. Richardson|name=J.P. Richardson}}
*[http://www.findagrave.com/cgi-bin/fg.cgi?page=gr&amp;GRid=1705 J. P. &quot;Big Bopper&quot; Richardson, Jr] at [[Find A Grave]]

{{Persondata
|NAME=Richardson, Jiles Perry
|ALTERNATIVE NAMES=The Big Bopper, Jape, J.P.
|SHORT DESCRIPTION=American singer
|DATE OF BIRTH=October 24, 1930
|PLACE OF BIRTH=[[Sabine Pass, Texas]]
|DATE OF DEATH=February 3, 1959
|PLACE OF DEATH=[[Clear Lake, Iowa]]
}}
{{DEFAULTSORT:Big Bopper, The}}
[[Category:1930 births]]
[[Category:1959 deaths]]
[[Category:American male singers]]
[[Category:American novelty song performers]]
[[Category:American DJs]]
[[Category:American rock singers]]
[[Category:People from Beaumont, Texas]]
[[Category:People from Port Arthur, Texas]]
[[Category:Musicians from Texas]]
[[Category:Victims of aviation accidents or incidents in the United States]]
[[Category:Rockabilly Hall of Fame inductees]]
[[Category:Mercury Records artists]]
[[Category:Accidental deaths in Iowa]]
[[Category:Lamar University alumni]]

[[da:The Big Bopper]]
[[de:The Big Bopper]]
[[es:The Big Bopper]]
[[fr:The Big Bopper]]
[[is:The Big Bopper]]
[[it:The Big Bopper]]
[[nl:The Big Bopper]]
[[no:The Big Bopper]]
[[pl:Jiles Perry Richardson]]
[[pt:The Big Bopper]]
[[ro:The Big Bopper]]
[[ru:Биг Боппер]]
[[fi:The Big Bopper]]
[[sv:The Big Bopper]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
