<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="1043143" ns="0" title="Single-payer health care"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Use mdy dates|date=November 2011}}
[[File:PNHP poster.jpg|right|thumb|An analysis of the [[United States National Health Care Act]] by [[Physicians for a National Health Program]] who estimated the savings at $350 billion per year in 2008.&lt;ref&gt;[[Physicians for a National Health Program]] (2008) [http://www.pnhp.org/facts/single_payer_system_cost.php?page=all &quot;Single Payer System Cost?&quot;] ''PNHP.org''&lt;/ref&gt; Others have estimated a 40% savings&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | doi = 10.1186/1472-6963-5-20 | last1 = Hogg | first1 = W. | last2 = Baskerville | year = 2005 | first2 = N | last3 = Lemelin | first3 = J | title = Cost savings associated with improving appropriate and reducing inappropriate preventive care: cost-consequences analysis | journal = BMC Health Services Research | volume = 5 | issue = 1| page = 20 | pmid = 15755330 | pmc = 1079830 }}&lt;/ref&gt; due to elimination of insurance company overhead costs.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | author = Levy A.R. ''et al.'' | year = 2010 | title = International comparison of comparative effectiveness research in five jurisdictions: insights for the US | url = http://www.ingentaconnect.com/content/adis/pec/2010/00000028/00000010/art00004 | journal = Pharmacoeconomics | volume = 28 | issue = 10| pages = 813–30 | pmid = 20831289 | doi = 10.2165/11536150-000000000-00000 }}&lt;/ref&gt;]]

'''Single-payer health care''' is [[health care|medical care]] funded from a single insurance pool, run by the [[state (polity)|state]]. Under a single-payer system, [[universal health care]] for an entire population can be financed from a pool to which many parties {{ndash}} employees, employers, and the state {{ndash}} have contributed. Single-payer is form of [[monopsony]]: a market in which one buyer faces many sellers; in all existing and proposed cases that buyer is the state or large organization.{{Citation needed|date=July 2011}}

Single-payer health insurance collects all medical fees, and then pays for all services, through a &quot;single&quot; government (or government-related) source.&lt;ref name=&quot;MedicalSubject&quot;&gt;Medical Subject Headings thesaurus, National Library of Medicine.[http://www.nlm.nih.gov/cgi/mesh/2008/MB_cgi?mode=&amp;index=17627&amp;field=all&amp;HM=&amp;II=&amp;PA=&amp;form=&amp;input= &quot;Single-Payer System&quot;] Year introduced: 1996, (From Slee and Slee, Health Care Reform Terms, 1993, p106)&lt;/ref&gt; In wealthy nations, this kind of publicly managed insurance is typically extended to all citizens and legal residents. Examples include the United Kingdom's [[Healthcare in the United Kingdom|National Health Service]], Australia's [[Medicare (Australia)|Medicare]], Canada's [[Medicare (Canada)|Medicare]], and Taiwan's [[healthcare in Taiwan|National Health Insurance]]. [[Medicare (United States)|Medicare in the United States]] is an example of a single-payer system for a specified, limited group of persons.

Single-payer systems may contract for healthcare services from private organizations (as is the case in Canada) or may own and employ healthcare resources and personnel (as is the case in the UK). The term &quot;single-payer&quot; thus only describes the funding mechanism—referring to health care financed by a single public body from a single fund—and does not specify the type of delivery, or for whom doctors work. Although the fund holder is usually the state, some forms of single-payer use a mixed public-private system.

==Types and variations==
Canada, Australia, Taiwan, and the United Kingdom have single-payer health insurance programs. These programs provide universal health care. Single-payer healthcare may be operated in a number of ways. In some cases doctors may be employed, and hospitals run by, the government as in the United Kingdom. Alternatively the government may purchase healthcare services from outside organizations. This is the approach taken in Canada.

Some writers describe publicly administered health care systems as &quot;single-payer plans.&quot; Some writers have described any system of health care which intends to cover the entire population, such as voucher plans, as &quot;single-payer plans,&quot;&lt;ref&gt;A Health Care Plan So Simple, Even Stephen Colbert Couldn’t Simplify It, By ROBERT H. FRANK, New York Times, February 15, 2007
[http://www.nytimes.com/2007/02/15/business/15scene.html] Fuchs [http://www.robert-h-frank.com/PDFs/Emanuel-Fuchs.NEJM.3-24-05.pdf]&lt;/ref&gt; although this is an uncommon usage. The standard usage refers to health insurance, as opposed to healthcare delivery, operating as a public service,
like fire departments, community libraries, and other publicly-funded
services, offered to citizens and legal residents towards providing near-universal or [[universal health care]]. The fund can be managed by the government directly or as a publicly owned and regulated agency.&lt;ref name=&quot;MedicalSubject&quot; /&gt;

===Canada===
{{Main|Medicare (Canada)}}
{{See also|Canadian and American health care systems compared}}

[[Health care in Canada]] is an example of single-payer health care.&lt;ref name=&quot;Chua&quot;/&gt; The national government provides part of the funding, provincial governments manage the hospitals and provide the bulk of the funding, and doctors in private practice contract with the government for fee-for-service payments. Although many Canadian citizens have supplemental private insurance from their employers, this covers non-[[medically necessary]] expenses not covered by Canadian Medicare, and accounts for 12% of national health care spending.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.chepa.org/Libraries/PDFs/CHEPA_WP_08-04.sflb.ashx Private Health Insurance in Canada], Centre for Health Economics and Policy Analysis, [[McMaster University]]&lt;/ref&gt;

Fees for doctors, hospitals and other providers are set by negotiations among doctors' associations, provincial or regional governments, and the national government.{{Citation needed|date=August 2009}} Global budgets eliminate the high potential costs (as is the case in the U.S.) of billing individually for huge numbers of products and services.{{Citation needed|date=August 2009}}

Health care provision in Canada is a mix of private and public services, although most hospitals are public.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |title=Recent Social Trends in Canada, 1960–2000 |last=Lance |first=Roberts |year=2005 |publisher=McGill Queen's University Press |isbn=0773529551 | url=http://books.google.com/?id=qnPOqwsR5UsC&amp;pg=PA317&amp;vq=private+hospitals&amp;dq=private+hospitals+in+canada |page=317 }}&lt;/ref&gt; Patients may go to any doctor or hospital in the country.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url= http://bcn.boulder.co.us/health/healthwatch/canada.html|title=Single Payer Health Care System&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Canadians do wait for some treatments and diagnostic services. Survey data show that the median wait time to see a special physician is a little over four weeks with 89.5% waiting less than three months. The median wait time for diagnostic services such as MRI and CAT scans&lt;ref&gt;Diagnostic tests defined as the following: non-emergency magnetic resonance imaging (MRI) devices; computed tomography (CT or CAT) scans; and angiographies that use X-rays to examine the inner opening of blood-filled structures such as veins and arteries.&lt;/ref&gt; is two weeks, with 86.4% waiting less than three months.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.hc-sc.gc.ca/hcs-sss/pubs/system-regime/2006-fed-comp-indicat/2006-fed-comp-indicat-3-eng.php#a1 Section from Healthy Canadians: A Federal report on Comparable Health Indicators] {{dead link|date=November 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; The median wait time for surgery is four weeks, with 82.2% waiting less than three months. In addition, there is concern of a &quot;brain drain&quot; as high-quality medical graduates leave Canada for better-paying careers in the U.S.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.cmaj.ca/cgi/content/full/161/8/1028], ''Canadian Medical Association Journal''&lt;/ref&gt;

===Taiwan===
{{Main|Health care in Taiwan}}
Taiwan instituted a single-payer system, called the National Health Insurance (NHI), in 1995. In a 2009 interview, Dr. Michael Chen, Vice President and CFO of Taiwan's National Health Insurance Bureau, explained that before NHI was instituted, Taiwan &quot;sent our people around the world to learn their programs, including the United States&quot; to compare models. Dr. Chen indicated that Taiwan's single-payer NHI program &quot;is modeled after (U.S.) Medicare. And there are so many similarities&amp;nbsp;— other than that our program covers all of the population, and Medicare covers only the elderly. &quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web| url=http://www.pnhp.org/news/2009/april/jonathan_cohn_interv.php|title=Jonathan Cohn interviews Taiwan's Dr. Michael Chen: The Case for Single-Payer Health Care (Transcript)}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web  |title=TRNtv:Jonathan Cohn interviews Taiwan's Dr. Michael Chen (Video)|url=http://player.theplatform.com/ps/player/pds/Knmmuhlp3e?pid=Vq2Q_9LKk_AhPrGSWCgdcBmcX6CwnZQn |accessdate=September 11, 2009}} {{Dead link|date=September 2010|bot=H3llBot}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Proposals in the United States==
{{Health care reform in the United States}}
{{Main|United States National Health Care Act}}
{{See also|Health care reform in the United States|Health care in the United States|Public opinion on health care reform in the United States|Medicare for All}}

A number of proposals have been made for a universal single-payer healthcare system in the United States, none of which has achieved significant political support, with polling showing support for various levels of government involvement depending on wording.&lt;ref name=&quot;wpasinglepayer.org&quot;&gt;http://www.wpasinglepayer.org/PollResults.html&lt;/ref&gt; Proposers include [[Physicians for a National Health Program]],&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.pnhp.org/|title=Physicians for a National Health Program&amp;nbsp;— Health Care is a Human Right}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[American College of Physicians|The American College of Physicians]]&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.entrepreneur.com/tradejournals/article/179007449.html|title=ACP issues call for mandated universal coverage}}&lt;/ref&gt; and the American Medical Student Association.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.amsa.org/uhc/HFA.cfm]{{dead link|date=January 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In Congress, Rep. [[John Conyers]], Jr. (D-MI), and Rep. [[Dennis Kucinich]] (D-OH) have introduced the [[United States National Health Care Act]] (HR 676). The bill has been introduced in every term of Congress under the same name since it was first introduced in 2003 in the 108th Congress with 38 cosponsors.&lt;ref&gt;GovTrack. [http://www.govtrack.us/congress/bill.xpd?bill=h108-676 Expanded and Improved Medicare for All Act].&lt;/ref&gt;

===Current programs===
{{hus}}
[[Medicare (United States)|Medicare in the United States]] is a single-payer healthcare system, but is restricted to only senior citizens and certain other classes of people.&lt;ref name=&quot;Chua&quot;/&gt; Government is increasingly involved in [[Health care in the United States|U.S. health care]] spending, paying about 45% of the $2.2 trillion the nation spent on individuals' medical care in 2004.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |first=Julie |last=Appleby |title=Universal care appeals to USA |url=http://www.usatoday.com/money/industries/health/2006-10-15-universal-usat_x.htm |work=USA Today |date=2006-10-16 |accessdate=2007-05-22 }}&lt;/ref&gt; However, studies have shown that the publicly-administered share of health spending in the U.S. is closer to 60%.&lt;ref&gt;Health Affairs, July 2002. Woolhandler, Steffi&lt;/ref&gt;

According to [[Princeton University]] health economist Uwe E. Reinhardt, U.S. Medicare, [[Medicaid]], and [[State Children's Health Insurance Program]] (SCHIP) represent &quot;forms of '[[social insurance]]' coupled with a largely private health-care delivery system&quot; rather than forms of &quot;[[socialized medicine]].&quot; In contrast, he describes the [[Veterans Health Administration|Veterans Administration healthcare system]] as a pure form of socialized medicine because it is &quot;owned, operated and financed by government.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;[http://online.wsj.com/article/SB118411829790962883.html &quot;Letters: For Children's Sake, This 'Schip' Needs to Be Relaunched&quot;], Wall Street Journal, July 11, 2007, Uwe E. Reinhardt and others.&lt;/ref&gt;

The [[United States Department of Veterans Affairs|Veterans Administration]] is a single-payer system and provides excellent quality, said Reinhardt. In a peer-reviewed paper published in the Annals of Internal Medicine, researchers of the [[RAND]] Corp. reported that the quality of care received by Veterans Administration patients scored significantly higher overall than did comparable metrics for patients currently using U.S. Medicare.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |author=Asch SM, McGlynn EA, Hogan MM, ''et al.'' |title=Comparison of quality of care for patients in the Veterans Health Administration and patients in a national sample |journal=Ann. Intern. Med. |volume=141 |issue=12 |pages=938–45 |year=2004 |month=December |pmid=15611491 |url=http://www.annals.org/cgi/reprint/141/12/938}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===State proposals===
Several single-payer state referendums and bills from state legislatures have been proposed, but so far all have either failed to pass both legislatures or were vetoed by the governor, including (states where the debate is also current) California as early as 1994,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.kff.org/statepolicy/1075-index.cfm |title=The California Single-Payer Debate, The Defeat of Proposition 186 – Kaiser Family Foundation |publisher=Kff.org |accessdate=November 20, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Massachusetts]] in 2000, and [[Oregon Ballot Measure 23 (2002)|Oregon]] in 2002.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.heartland.org/Article.cfm?artId=10803 |title=Free-Market Reformers Are Winners in Election 2002 – by Joe Moser – The Heartland Institute |publisher=Heartland.org |accessdate=November 20, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In 2009 the House of Representatives Education and Labor Committee approved an amendment to the House health care bill, which would allow individual states to adopt a single-payer Medicare-for-all-style health plan. The amendment was proposed by Democratic Congress member Dennis Kucinich of Ohio. The [[Kucinich Amendment]] received support from some conservatives supporting [[states rights]] as it would allow states more freedom to explore various models including, but not limited to, single payer.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.democracynow.org/2009/7/21/as_obama_continues_push_for_healthcare|title=As Obama Continues Push for Healthcare Reform, House Committee Approves Kucinich-Sponsored Measure to Keep Single-Payer Option Alive}}&lt;/ref&gt;

====Minnesota====
In Minnesota, the Minnesota Health Act, which would establish a state-wide single payer health plan, has been presented to the Senate as SF118 and to the House as HF135, in identical language. This bill was passed by several critical committees in both houses, has been designated as a two-year bill, and awaits a second reading in the House Health Care and Human Services Policy &amp; Oversight Committee.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://muhcc.org/minnesotahealthplan/billstatus|title=Status of the MN Health Act SF118 / HF135}}&lt;/ref&gt;  Two out of three of the 2010 [[Democratic-Farmer-Labor Party]] candidates for governor have indicated they would sign the bill, if passed; the [[Republican Party of Minnesota|Republican Party]] candidate does not support such a measure (two of the candidates interviewed that indicated they would not have since left the race).&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://muhcc.org/sites/default/file/MUHCC%20Survey%20Responses%20-%20short.pdf|title=Gubernatorial Candidate Survey}}{{dead link|date=January 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

====California====
The [[California State Legislature]] has twice passed a state-level single payer bill, SB 840, &quot;The California Universal Healthcare Act&quot; (authored by [[Sheila Kuehl]]), in 2006 and again in 2008.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.eastcountymagazine.org/?q=health_care_for_all|title=Healthcare for All Bill Passes&amp;nbsp;— Governor Threatens Veto}}&lt;/ref&gt; Both times, Governor Arnold Schwarzenegger vetoed the bill.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.calnurses.org/media-center/press-releases/2008/september/rns-say-governor-harming-economy-and-californians-health-with-sb-840-veto.html|title=RNs Say Governor Harming Economy and Californians' Health with SB 840 Veto}}&lt;/ref&gt; State Senator Mark Leno later re-introduced &quot;The California Universal Healthcare Act&quot; in March 2009, newly renumbered as SB 810,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://singlepayernow.net/archive/dec-14-holiday-potluck-with-mark-leno/|title=Healthcare Potluck}}{{dead link|date=January 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; and in January 2010, the California Senate passed SB 810. On the last day of the 2010 legislative session, the Democrats pulled SB 810 from the Assembly floor as Governor Arnold Schwarzenegger said he would veto it a third time, with Senator [[Mark Leno]] announcing he would reintroduce the bill again in January of the 2011 legislative session as [[Jerry Brown]] is sworn in as the new Governor of California.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://pnhp.org/blog/2010/09/01/democrats-block-california-single-payer-bill/|title=Democrats Block California Single Payer Bill}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.opednews.com/articles/CALIFORNIA-LIBERALS-VICTOR-by-Ruth-Hull-101104-999.html|title=CALIFORNIA LIBERALS VICTORIOUS; AMERICANS MOURN THE LOSS OF THEIR ADVOCATE IN U.S. SENATE}}&lt;/ref&gt; The bill has received support from the [[California Nurses Association]]/National Nurses United.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.medicalnewstoday.com/articles/177552.php |title=Major Advance For California Healthcare Reform As Senate Passes Medicare For All Legislation |publisher=Medicalnewstoday.com |accessdate=November 20, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

====Illinois====
In April 2008, the Illinois House of Representatives' Health Availability Access Committee passed the single-payer bill HB 311, &quot;The Health Care for All Illinois Act,&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.healthcareil.org/|title=Health Care for All Illinois}}&lt;/ref&gt; favorably out of committee by an 8–4 vote.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.ilga.gov/legislation/BillStatus.asp?DocNum=311&amp;GAID=9&amp;DocTypeID=HB&amp;LegId=27071&amp;SessionID=51|title=Illinois General Assembly Bill Status: HB 311}}&lt;/ref&gt;

====Pennsylvania====
In February 2010, the 301-member Pennsylvania Democratic State Committee unanimously endorsed a resolution calling for passage of single payer healthcare, Senate Bill 400 and House Bill 1660, also known as the &quot;Family and Business Healthcare Security Act.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.pnhp.org/news/2010/february/pennsylvania-democrats-unanimously-endorse-single-payer-senate-bill-400-and-house |title=Pennsylvania Democrats Unanimously Endorse Single Payer Senate Bill 400 and House Bill 1660 |publisher=Pnhp.org |date=February 8, 2010 |accessdate=November 20, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

====Montana====
In September 2011, Governor Brian Schweitzer did a news interview discussing his desire to obtain a waiver from the federal government similar to the waiver Vermont used, and set up their own universal health care system similar to what was established in the Canadian provence of Saskatchewan.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last=Jilani |first=Zaid |url=http://thinkprogress.org/health/2011/09/29/332031/montana-governor-waiver-for-single-payer/ |title=Montana Gov. Brian Schweitzer Will Seek Health Care Law Waiver To Establish Single Payer In His State |publisher=ThinkProgress |date=September 29, 2011 |accessdate=November 20, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

====Massachusetts====
In Massachusetts, Question 4, a nonbinding referendum was on the ballot in 14 districts in November 2010, asking voters, &quot;Shall the representative from this district be instructed to support legislation that would establish health care as a [[right to health|human right]] regardless of age, state of health or employment status, by creating a single payer health insurance system like Medicare that is comprehensive, cost effective, and publicly provided to all residents of Massachusetts?&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://pnhp.org/blog/2010/09/22/insurers-continue-health-care-rip-off/ |title=Insurers continue health care rip-off |publisher=Pnhp.org |date=September 22, 2010 |accessdate=November 20, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; With 222 of 228 precincts reporting, in all 14 districts, including five in which majorities had voted for Republican Senator [[Scott Brown]], Question 4 passed, with 63.5% of the overall votes being cast in favor of the  ballot referendum for establishing a Massachusetts single payer system.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://pnhp.org/blog/2010/11/03/single-payer-ballot-questions-pass-in-all-fourteen-massachusetts-districts/ |title=Single payer ballot questions pass in all fourteen Massachusetts districts! |publisher=Pnhp.org |date=November 3, 2010 |accessdate=November 20, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.boston.com/news/special/politics/2010/ballot_questions/results/ |title=Boston Globe: Ballot Questions (2010) |work=Boston Globe  |accessdate=November 20, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

====Vermont====
{{main|Vermont health care reform}}
The legislature of [[Vermont]], including both the Democratic and [[Vermont Progressive Party|Progressive Party]], endorses single payer health care and has hired [[William Hsiao]], the designer of Taiwan's single payer health care system, to design three possible systems of universal health care, one being a single payer model. Governor [[Peter Shumlin]] supports this move.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.pnhp.org/news/2010/december/in-vermont-single-payer-health-care-in-a-single-state |title=In Vermont, single-payer health care in a single state &amp;#124; Physicians for a National Health Program |publisher=Pnhp.org |date=December 14, 2010 |accessdate=November 20, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.burlingtonfreepress.com/article/20101227/NEWS03/12270311/Expect-strong-push-in-the-Vermont-Legislature-for-health-reforms-in-2011 Expect strong push in the Vermont Legislature for health reforms in 2011 | The Burlington Free Press | Burlington, Vermont]{{dead link|date=November 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The Vermont health bill, H.202, has led to the creation of Green Mountain Care, a private/public single payer exchange system that will give universal coverage to Vermonters and create an electronic system of medical records in an effort to make the system efficient and accessible.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.pnhp.org/news/2011/february/pnhp-commentary-on-the-vermont-health-reform-bill |title=PNHP commentary on the Vermont health reform bill &amp;#124; Physicians for a National Health Program |publisher=Pnhp.org |date=February 15, 2011 |accessdate=November 20, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; In April 2011, it passed the Vermont Senate.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.wcax.com/story/14518224/vt-senate-approves-single-payer-plan |title=Vt. Senate approves single-payer plan – WCAX.COM Local Vermont News, Weather and Sports |publisher=Wcax.com |date=April 26, 2011 |accessdate=November 20, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; In May 2011, the governor signed it into law, making Vermont the first state to have a single payer health care system.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.pnhp.org/news/2011/may/vermont-poised-to-become-1st-state-to-enact-single-payer-healthcare |title=Vermont Poised to Become 1st State to Enact Single-Payer Healthcare &amp;#124; Physicians for a National Health Program |publisher=Pnhp.org |date=May 26, 2011 |accessdate=November 20, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Other proposals===
[[Physicians for a National Health Program]]&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
| url = http://www.pnhp.org/publications/proposal_of_the_physicians_working_group_for_singlepayer_national_health_insurance.php| title = Proposal of the Physicians' Working Group for Single-Payer National Health Insurance| publisher = Physicians for a National Health Program}}&lt;/ref&gt; the [[American Medical Student Association]]&lt;ref name=&quot;Chua&quot;&gt;Chua, Kao-Ping. [http://www.amsa.org/uhc/SinglePayer101.pdf &quot;Single Payer 101&quot;.]{{dead link|date=January 2011}} February 10, 2006&lt;/ref&gt; and the [[California Nurses Association]]&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.calnurses.org/media-center/in-the-news/2007/september/page.jsp?itemID=32125992 Single-payer, or Medicare for all, is the way to go]{{dead link|date=January 2011}} from the California Nurses Association / National Nurses Organizing Committee.&lt;/ref&gt; are among those that have called for the introduction of a single payer health care program. In Congress, Rep. [[John Conyers]], Jr. (D-MI) has repeatedly introduced The [[United States National Health Care Act]] (HR 676). As of August 2008, HR 676 had 91 co-sponsors.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://thomas.loc.gov/cgi-bin/bdquery/z?d110:HR00676:@@@P |title=H.R. 676 |accessdate=2008-08-26 |work=Library of Congress THOMAS }}&lt;/ref&gt;

The [[Congressional Budget Office]] and related government agencies scored the cost of a universal health care system several times since 1991, and have uniformly predicted cost savings,&lt;ref&gt;Physicians for a National Health Program (January, 2008) [http://www.pnhp.org/facts/single_payer_system_cost.php?page=all &quot;Single Payer System Cost?&quot;] ''pnhp.org''&lt;/ref&gt; probably because of the 40% cost savings associated with universal preventative care.&lt;ref&gt;Hogg, W., ''et al.'' (2005) [http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC1079830/ &quot;Cost savings associated with improving appropriate and reducing inappropriate preventive care: cost-consequences analysis&quot;] ''BMC Health Services Research'' '''5''':20&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Image:Single Payer Protester.JPG|thumb|left|Costumed supporter of single-payer at an April 2009 protest in New York City]]

The issue has often been debated, most recently in the 2008 presidential elections. A CBS News/''[[New York Times]]'' poll published in February 2009 reported that 59% say the government should provide national health insurance (up from 40% thirty years earlier)&lt;ref&gt;{{cite press release| title = CBS NEWS/NEW YORK TIMES POLL| publisher = CBS NEWS| date = Sunday, February 1, 2009| url = http://www.cbsnews.com/htdocs/pdf/SunMo_poll_0209.pdf
 | quote = Americans are more likely today to embrace the idea of the government providingealth insurance than they were 30 years ago.}}&lt;/ref&gt; A study published in the Annals of Internal Medicine concluded that 59% of physicians &quot;supported legislation to establish national health insurance&quot; while 9% were neutral on the topic, and 32% opposed it.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |author=Carroll AE, Ackerman RT |title=Support for National Health Insurance among U.S. Physicians: 5 years later |journal=Ann. Intern. Med. |volume=148 |issue=7 |pages=566–7 |year=2008 |month=April |pmid=18378959 |url=http://www.annals.org/cgi/reprint/148/7/566}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Public opinion in the United States===

According to the media criticism organization [[Fairness and Accuracy in Reporting]], a 1987 ''New York Times''/CBS poll showed 78% of people saying that the &quot;government should guarantee medical care to everyone.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.fair.org/index.php?page=3633 |title=Fear &amp; Loathing at the Democratic Convention |publisher=Fair.org |accessdate=November 20, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;  Between 2003 to 2009, 17 opinion polls showed a majority of the public supports various levels of government involvement in health care in the United States.&lt;ref name=&quot;wpasinglepayer.org&quot;/&gt; Many polls, such as ones administered through CNN,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.pnhp.org/news/2007/may/new_polls_on_univers.php |title=New polls on universal, tax-supported health care &amp;#124; Physicians for a National Health Program |publisher=Pnhp.org |accessdate=November 20, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; AP-[[Yahoo]],&lt;ref&gt;http://l.yimg.com/a/i/us/nws/elections/2008/yahoo2topline.pdf&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.pnhp.org/news/2007/december/where_are_we_on_refo.php |title=Where are we on reform? &amp;#124; Physicians for a National Health Program |publisher=Pnhp.org |accessdate=November 20, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[New York Times]]/[[CBS News|CBS News Poll]],&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last=Sack |first=Kevin |url=http://www.nytimes.com/2009/06/21/health/policy/21poll.html |title=In Poll, Wide Support for Government-Run Health |work=The New York Times  |date=June 20, 2009 |accessdate=November 20, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news| url=http://www.cbsnews.com/htdocs/pdf/SunMo_poll_0209.pdf | work=CBS News}}&lt;/ref&gt; and [[Washington Post]]/[[ABC News|ABC News Poll]],&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://abcnews.go.com/images/pdf/935a3HealthCare.pdf |title=Question 49 |format=PDF |accessdate=November 20, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Kaiser Family Foundation]]&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.kff.org/kaiserpolls/upload/7943.pdf |title=Kaiser Health Tracking Poll: July 2009 – Topline |format=PDF |accessdate=November 20, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; showed a majority in favor of a form of national health insurance, often compared to Medicare.  The Civil Society Institute&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news| url=http://findarticles.com/p/articles/mi_hb6366/is_6_16/ai_n29141381/ | work=Dermatology Nursing | title=Health care survey: 2 out of 3 Americans now favor government-guaranteed coverage | year=2004}}&lt;/ref&gt; and Physicians for a National Health Program&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.pnhp.org/news/2007/march/public_opinion_on_he.php |title=Public opinion on health care reform &amp;#124; Physicians for a National Health Program |publisher=Pnhp.org |date=March 2, 2007 |accessdate=November 20, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; have both found majorities in favor of the government offering guaranteed insurance, and a [[Quinnipiac]] poll in three states in 2008 found majority support for the government ensuring &quot;that everyone in the United States has adequate health-care&quot; among likely Democratic primary voters.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|author=Quinnipiac University – Office of Public Affairs |url=http://www.quinnipiac.edu/x2882.xml?ReleaseID=1164 |title=Question 9: &quot;Do you think it's the government's responsibility to make sure that everyone in the United States has adequate health-care, or don't you think so?&quot; |publisher=Quinnipiac.edu |date=April 2, 2008 |accessdate=November 20, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In contrast, a October 2011 [[Rasmussen Reports]] poll of registered voters showed only 35% of respondents in favor of single-payer health care, with a plurality (49%) opposed.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.rasmussenreports.com/public_content/politics/current_events/healthcare/october_2011/49_oppose_single_payer_health_care_system |title=Rasmussen Reports |publisher=Rasmussen Reports |date=January 1, 2010 |accessdate=November 20, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;  [[Politifact]] rated a statement by [[Michael Moore]] &quot;false&quot; when he stated that &quot;[t]he majority actually want single-payer health care.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;politifact1&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.politifact.com/truth-o-meter/statements/2009/oct/01/michael-moore/michael-moore-claims-majority-favor-single-payer-h/ |title=Michael Moore claims a majority favor a single-payer health care system |publisher=PolitiFact |accessdate=November 20, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;  Responses on these polls largely depend on the wording. For example, people respond more favorably when they are asked if they want a system &quot;like Medicare,&quot; less favorably when stated as &quot;socialized.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;politifact1&quot;/&gt;

==See also==
&lt;!-- Please maintain in alphabetical order --&gt;
* [[Health care compared]] – tabular comparisons of the US, Canada, and other countries not shown above.
* [[Health care reform debate in the United States]]
* [[Kucinich Amendment]] to Health Care Bill [[HR 3200]] grants [[states rights]] to [[single payer]] health care at the state level.
* [[Monopsony]]
* [[National health insurance]]
* [[Publicly funded health care]]
* [[Public opinion on health care reform in the United States]]
* [[Public health insurance option]]

==References==

{{Reflist|30em}}

==External links==
;Citizen action or resource groups
&lt;!-- Please maintain in alphabetical order --&gt;
*[http://docs.google.com/View?id=dfjfmkw7_659c5rt7fq Single-Payer Healthcare Resources].  A collection of links to primers, national/state resources, comparisons to other nations, bills/terminology, etc.
*[http://www.healthcare-now.org/ Healthcare-NOW!]. A nonprofit advocacy group for single-payer healthcare.
*[http://www.pdamerica.org/ Progressive Democrats of America] Advocates for single-payer system.
*[http://pnhp.org/ Physicians for a National Health Program]. Advocates for single-payer system. Extensive source material from peer-reviewed journals.
*[http://singlepayeraction.org/ Single Payer Action]. Activist nonprofit organization supporting single-payer universal healthcare.
*[http://www.singlepayercentral.com/ Single Payer Central]. An independent/unaffiliated central clearing house of information (groups, legislation, etc.), for single-payer.

;Articles, books, and broadcast programs
*[http://www.oregonlive.com/opinion/index.ssf/2009/08/five_myths_about_health_care_a.html Five myths about health care around the world] &quot;For people over 65, we're Canada ... for the tens of millions without insurance coverage, we're Burundi or Burma&quot; by T.R. Reid, a former Washington Post reporter.
*[http://www.nap.edu/catalog/10719.html Institute of Medicine Committee on the Consequences of Uninsurance]. Hidden costs, value lost: uninsurance in America. Washington, D.C.: National Academies Press, 2003. Frequently-cited monograph.
*[http://www.pbs.org/wgbh/pages/frontline/sickaroundtheworld/ Sick Around the World: Can the U.S. learn anything from the rest of the world about how to run a health care system?] from Frontline, PBS.
*[http://www.singlepayerhealthcarenow.com/ Single Payer Healthcare Now]. An activist blog supporting single payer healthcare
*[http://www.kff.org/uninsured/kcmu_statehealthreform.cfm States Moving Towards Comprehensive Health Care Reform in the U.S.], The Henry J. Kaiser Family Foundation.
*[http://cthealth.server101.com/the_case_for_universal_health_care_in_the_united_states.htm The Case For Single Payer, Universal Health Care For The United States]
*[http://www.nytimes.com/2007/09/28/opinion/28fri4.html?_r=2&amp;oref=slogin&amp;oref=slogin ''The Socialists Are Coming! The Socialists Are Coming!''] by Phillip Boffey. Editorial on U.S. &quot;socialized medicine&quot; in the military, the Veterans Health Administration, and Medicare, The New York Times, September 28, 2007.
*[http://www.businessweek.com/archives/1994/b336351.arc.htm ''Whither a health-care solution? Oh Canada''] BusinessWeek, March 21, 1994 by William C. Symonds, article in a business journal writing favorably about single payer.

;FAQ and summaries by NGOs favoring single payer
*[http://action.citizen.org/t/6693/content.jsp?content_KEY=5722 Get the Facts on Health Care Reform] Single-payer solution myths and facts from Public Citizen.
*[http://www.healthcare-now.org/docs/spreport.pdf Report Card on Single-Payer and Public Option] from PDA and Healthcare-now comparing, contrasting, and grading the two proposals.
*[http://www.pnhp.org/facts/singlepayer_myths_singlepayer_facts.php Single-Payer Myths; Single-Payer Facts] summary from PNHP.
*[http://www.healthcare-now.org/hr-676/whats-single-payer/ What is Single-Payer Healthcare?] from Healthcare-Now.org (expanded from PNHP with additional information)

{{DEFAULTSORT:Single-Payer Health Care}}
[[Category:Health economics]]
[[Category:Healthcare reform]]
[[Category:Universal healthcare]]

[[de:Bürgerversicherung]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
