<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="1049666" ns="0" title="Magnussoft ZETA"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Infobox OS
|name = magnussoft ZETA
|screenshot = &lt;!-- Deleted image removed: [[Image:Zeta2.png|250px]] --&gt;
|caption = The desktop running on Zeta RC2
|developer = [[yellowTAB]] / [[magnussoft]]
|family = [[BeOS]]
|source_model = [[Closed source]]
|frequently_updated = yes
|working_state = Discontinued
|kernel_type = [[Modular (programming)|Modular]] [[microkernel]]
|license = [[Proprietary software|Proprietary]]
|website = [http://www.zeta-os.com/ magnussoft ZETA]
}}
{{lowercase}}
'''magnussoft ZETA''', earlier '''yellowTAB ZETA''', was an [[operating system]] formerly developed by [[yellowTAB]] of [[Germany]] based on the [[BeOS|Be Operating System]] developed by [[Be Inc.]]; because of yellowTAB's insolvency, ZETA was later being developed by an independent team of which little was known, and distributed by [[magnussoft]]. As of February 28, 2007 the current version of ZETA is 1.5. On March 28, 2007, magnussoft announced that it has discontinued funding the development of ZETA by March 16, because the sales figures had fallen far short of the company's expectations, so that the project was no longer economically viable.&lt;ref name=magnussoft_discontinues_zeta_funding&gt;ZETA-os.com: ''[http://www.zeta-os.com/cms/news.php?extend.49 Continuity of magnussoft Zeta]'', March 26, 2007&lt;/ref&gt; A few days later, the company also stopped the distribution of ZETA in reaction to allegations that ZETA constituted an illegal unlicensed derivative of the BeOS source code and binaries.&lt;ref name=verkaufsstop&gt;ZETA-OS.com: ''[http://www.zeta-os.com/cms/news.php?extend.50 Magnussoft cease distribution of Zeta]'', April 5, 2007&lt;/ref&gt;

==Development==
ZETA was an effort to bring BeOS up to date, adding support for newer hardware, and features that had been introduced in other operating systems in the years since Be Incorporated ceased development in 2001. Among the new features were [[USB 2.0]] support, [[SATA]] support, [[Samba (software)|samba]] support, a new media player, and enhanced localization of system components. Unlike [[Haiku (operating system)|Haiku]] and other open source efforts to recreate some or all of BeOS's functionality from scratch, ZETA was based on the actual BeOS code base, and it is closed source.

ZETA contributed to an increase in activity in the BeOS commercial software market, with a number of new products for both ZETA and the earlier BeOS being released.

However, some critics point to a list of goals for the first release that do not appear to have been met (including [[Java (programming language)|Java]] 1.4.2 and [[ODBC]] support). Other reviewers point to bugs that still exist from BeOS, and question whether yellowTAB has the complete access to the source code they would need to make significant updates.

The system also came under heavy criticism from BeOS developers for undocumented changes in the system messaging system{{Citation needed|date=January 2010}}. These changes could break compilation of code, and in some cases (most notably [[Mozilla]]), break the actual application if any code optimizations are applied, resulting in much slower builds.&lt;ref name=lifejournal&gt;[http://www.livejournal.com/community/bezilla/64711.html bezilla: Is O3 too much? or where is Zeta users feedback?&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;

Additional controversy has come from their bundling of [[Gobe Productive]] in a licensing deal which [[Gobe]] had disputed.{{Citation needed|date=March 2007}}

YellowTAB promoted ZETA mainly in the German market, where it used to be sold through [[infomercial]]s and on [[RTL Shop]], and in [[Japan]] still being a beta version. Prior to Magnussoft stopping the distribution of ZETA, it was mainly distributed directly by magnussoft.

== Versions ==
{| class=&quot;wikitable&quot;
! Zeta version
! Release date
! Description
|-
| Release Candidates RC1-RC4 || October 15, 2004 || 

The operating system ZETA was published before the appearance of the final version 1,0 as Release Candidates (RC). The release began with RC1, and the following RC2 showed clear development progress since BeOS R5 was on the market.
Among other things new hardware was supported, as well as USB devices. Starting from June 9, 2004 the third release Candidate of the system was available.

On 15 October 2004 the fourth release candidate appeared under the name '''Neo'''. This brought among other things a better hardware support by more drivers and a new Media Player.
|-
| Zeta 1.0 || June 24, 2005 ||

ZETA 1.0 became the final version of the operating system and presented at [[CeBIT]] (10. - 16. March 2005 in Hanover). ZETA has, like Windows XP, for the first time, a [[product activation]]. One gets a registration key by post and must afterwards enter these and the CD serial number in a window under ZETA, so that one may use it further.

Starting from 24 June ZETA 1.0 was in the distribution; on the company-owned Website the spreading of the version 1.0 was officially confirmed on 1 July 2005.
|-
| Zeta 1.1 || October 17, 2005 || 

On 17 October 2005 a substantial update was released, bumping the version number to 1.1. With this new version it is possible to boot ZETA from a USB drive as well as a normal hard drive install. This release of ZETA also supports dual core processors.
|-
| Zeta 1.2 || April 22, 2006 || 

Briefly after the publication of the insolvency request from April 2006, the manufacturer released version 1.2. On 22 April, RTL Shop became a selling partner. This version brings some innovations, such as full [[SATA]] support and a [[Yahoo! Messenger]] is available.
|-
| Zeta 1.21 ||  || 

Based on the [http://zeta-os.com/cms/custom/zeta/indexe.php product information from magnussoft], ZETA 1.21 a minor upgrade to ZETA 1.2. This is also the first version of the product to be labeled &quot;magnussoft ZETA&quot; and to be sold by [[magnussoft]].

Since September 7, 2006, [http://zeta-os.com/cms/plugins/content/content.php?content.15 magnussoft is taking pre-orders of ZETA 1.21]; on September 25, 2006 a downloadable [[Live CD]] of ZETA 1.21 was released. Existing ZETA users are able to upgrade by ordering an upgrade CD for 10 [[euro]]s. It is not known whether magnussoft will provide updates to 1.21 via software download.

According to an [http://osnews.com/story.php?news_id=15802 interview with Rene Weinert of magnussoft], magnussoft owns only the rights to sell ZETA, and development is being done by an independent developing team which includes Mr. Bernd Korz (the former CEO of the now bankrupt yellowTAB). This confirms that, contrary to the widespread belief, prior to this interview, ZETA is not being developed by magnussoft, but by an independent development team, of which little is known so far.
|-
| Zeta 1.5 || February 28, 2007 || 

The version included
Samba-Client / WilmaCon, AudioTagger, PeopleEditor, multi-user support, Intel Extreme x9xx support and other drivers and fixes.

It was announced  an upgrade to R1.21 only, and began shipping February 28, 2007. On April 5, 2007 distribution was discontinued.
|}

==Criticism==
{{Ref improve section|date=September 2006}}
ZETA and yellowTAB have been surrounded by controversy. Critics of yellowTAB questioned for a long time the legality of ZETA, and whether yellowTAB had legal access to the sources of BeOS;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.osnews.com/comment.php?news_id=4734&amp;limit=no#150413 YellowTAB Zeta RC1 Review at ZetaNews &gt; Comments&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.bitsofnews.com/content/view/5496/44/#comments Bits of News - Zeta Officially a Dead Fish&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt; it is now known that yellowTAB could not have developed ZETA to the extent that they did without access to the source code, but doubts remain as to whether yellowTAB actually had legal access to the code or not.

Furthermore, critics did not see ZETA as real advancement of BeOS, but rather as an unfinished and buggy operating system loaded with third party applications that were either obsolete, unsupported, or non-functional. This was particularly true in the initial releases of ZETA, and it was in clear conflict with the attention to detail that BeOS used to stand for, disappointing the BeOS community who at one point had high expectations for ZETA. While yellowTAB did clean up the selection of bundled applications in following versions, ZETA remains somewhat unstable when compared to other modern desktop operating systems.

But perhaps the most criticized practice by yellowTAB was its tendency to make claims that turned out to be either half truths or vague enough that they could not be confirmed. Not only did yellowTAB announce certain developments that never materialized (such as Java, and ODBC among others), but it would also support certain capabilities beyond what ZETA was actually capable of (e.g., compatibility with MS Office). According to sources close to yellowTAB, this is believed to have led to a high return rate from customers that bought ZETA from the German [[RTL Shop|RTL]] TV shopping channel, and the reason for which RTL eventually stopped selling the product.

Another issue that has been brought up by the BeOS community is the fact that magnussoft has never released any free-of-charge versions of Zeta. Be Inc. used to offer BeOS Personal Edition free of charge, which was of great help to those who wanted to test BeOS. The lack of a similar personal installable version saw Zeta seriously confined to the limits of the older BeOS community. Nevertheless, a LiveCD version, which could be downloaded from the ZetaOS web site, allowed one to test hardware compatibility and get a flavor of the experience for little cost.  However, the modifications made to render this version not-installable, crippled it as a potential BeOS/Zeta system recovery tool; the BFS (Be File System)could not mount an existing BFS partition on the harddrive.  There was also a Students Edition, which could be obtained, at the price of 49 Euro, from [http://www.zeta-os.com Zeta-OS.com].

{{cquote|Zeta had no legal rights to distribute the BeOS software, much less open source any of it, as the rumours had it.&lt;br&gt;[...]&lt;br&gt;The main reason that there hasn't been a public statement previously is that dealing with this matter legally, in Germany, is an expensive undertaking and--given the apparently small amount of funding behind Zeta in its various incarnations--we'd only be in a position to spend significant money and legal time to make a point.&lt;br&gt;[...]&lt;br&gt;We have sent &quot;cease and desist&quot; letters to YellowTab on a number of occasions, which have been uniformly ignored. If Mr. Bernd Korz(Former CEO of yellowTAB) feels that he holds a legitimate license to the BeOS code he's been using, we're completely unaware of it, and I'd be fascinated to see him produce any substantiation for that claim.|author=David Schlesinger, Director, Open Source Technologies. ACCESS Co., Ltd.|source=''http://www.bitsofnews.com/content/view/5498/44/'' (2007-04-04)}}

==Cease of distribution==
A cease of distribution letter was posted by Magnussoft at 5 April 2007.&lt;ref name=verkaufsstop /&gt;

==See also==
*[[Comparison of operating systems]]
*[[Haiku (operating system)|Haiku]]

== References ==
{{reflist}}

== External links ==
* [http://www.zeta-os.com/ magnussoft ZETA] – Official product website
* [http://www.osnews.com/story.php/17518/Review-Zeta-1.5/page1/ ZETA 1.5 Review] - Reviewed by Thom Holwerda for OSNews
* [http://members.shaw.ca/guis/zeta.html ZETA 1.21 Live CD screenshot gallery]
{{BeOS}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Magnussoft Zeta}}
[[Category:BeOS]]
[[Category:Proprietary operating systems]]

[[de:ZETA]]
[[es:Zeta (sistema operativo)]]
[[fr:ZETA]]
[[nl:Magnussoft ZETA]]
[[ja:ZETA]]
[[no:Zeta (operativsystem)]]
[[pl:YellowTAB Zeta]]
[[pt:Zeta (sistema operacional)]]
[[ru:Zeta (операционная система)]]
[[sv:Zeta (operativsystem)]]
[[uk:Magnussoft ZETA]]
[[zh:Magnussoft ZETA]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
