<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="10514539" ns="0" title="List of xxxHolic characters"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">[[File:Holiccharac.jpg|thumb|250pxs|Promotional image of the series featuring Yūko at the top left, Kohane below, Domeki in the middle at the top, Himawari below and Watanuki in the right at the bottom.]]
The [[Character (arts)|fictional character]]s appearing in the [[manga]] and [[anime]] series ''[[xxxHolic]]'' were developed by [[Clamp (manga artists)|Clamp]], a group of four [[mangaka|manga artists]]. Taking place in a modern Japan, the series focuses on various [[supernatural]] themes, leading to various of the characters being spirits or mysterious creatures. Published at the same time of Clamp's ''[[Tsubasa: Reservoir Chronicle]]'' manga, ''xxxHolic'' often makes [[Fictional crossover|crossover]]s with it, leading to the appearances of various of its characters in the series.

The series' [[protagonist]] is [[#Kimihiro Watanuki|Kimihiro Watanuki]], a high school student plagued by [[yōkai]] and [[ayakashi (monster)|ayakashi]], spirits with a strong attraction to him. When bothered by them, Watanuki accidentally enters into a shop that grants wish where he meets the witch [[#Yūko Ichihara|Yūko Ichihara]]. Yūko decides to grant his wish of making his demons go away in exchange of having him work as her assistant in her shop. Working at Yūko's shop, Watanuki comes to encounter various spirits as well as knowing more of his classmates [[#Shizuka Dōmeki|Shizuka Dōmeki]], a teenager who repels spirits and Watanuki dislikes, and [[#Himawari Kunogi|Himawari Kunogi]], Watanuki's crush who is said to give bad luck to people. Watanuki also meets various ghosts and other spiritual being that take the form of animals or people. Although Watanuki becomes happy with the new friendships he makes, he becomes concerned about Yūko, promising he will try to grant her wish.

The characters from ''xxxHolic'' were designed by Clamp's members [[Mokona]] and [[Tsubaki Nekoi]] with some of their designs being inspired by [[Ukiyo-e]] art style. Positive critical reception has been given to the series' characters based on their interactions and personalities. The designs have also been well-received most notably in the manga, where Clamp's work was praised. On the other hand, the designs featured in the animated adaptations have received mixed criticism.
==Creation and conception==
As the artwork of ''xxxHolic'' is influenced by [[Ukiyo-e]] art style, it leads to the characters having longer limbs in various illustrations. However, Clamp pointed the Clamp also often uses one-eyed characters or people who lost their sight which is meant to express the feelings from them. This is also meant to serve as a connection with ''Tsubasa: Reservoir Chronicle'', another Clamp's series which uses this method as well as the artwork influenced by Ukiyo-e.&lt;ref name=&quot;animexpointer&quot;&gt;{{Cite web |title=Anime Expo 15 Cosplay 2006 |publisher=John (Phoenix) Brown |date=January 11, 2009 |url=http://www.phoenixanime.com/ax06/page5.htm |accessdate=April 21, 2009 |archiveurl=http://www.webcitation.org/5unxRgAvf |archivedate=December 7, 2010 |deadurl=no }}&lt;/ref&gt; The series' female characters are designed by [[Mokona]] while [[Tsubaki Nekoi]] draws the male ones and all the spirits featured.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |last=Clamp |authorlink=Clamp (manga artists) |others=translanted and adapted by William Flanagan |title=The Official xxxHOLiC Guide |publisher=[[Del Rey Manga]] |year=2009|location=[[New York]] |pages=154–163 |isbn=978-0-345-51000-6}}&lt;/ref&gt; The characters' names were made so that people would find different meanings to each of them.&lt;ref name=&quot;finalinter&quot;&gt;{{cite web |title=CLAMP ：「想像以上に大変でした」&quot;×××HOLiC&quot;&quot;ツバサ&quot;異例の並行連載7年を振り返る|language=Japanese|publisher=[[Mainichi Shimbun]]|date=March 5, 2011|url=http://mantan-web.jp/2011/03/05/20110305dog00m200014000c.html|trans_title=CLAMP: &quot;It was hard to imagine more &quot;×××HOLiC&quot; &quot;Tsubasa&quot; looking back on an unprecedented 7 year simultaneous serialization|accessdate=March 9, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Main characters==
===Kimihiro Watanuki===
{{nihongo|Kimihiro Watanuki|四月一日 君尋|Watanuki Kimihiro}} is a high school student plagued daily by spirits who are constantly attracted to him. After meeting [[#Yūko Ichihara|Yūko Ichihara]], she promises to remove this unwanted ability in exchange for working part-time in her shop until it equals the worth of his wish. He lives by himself due to his parents no longer being around, so he excels in cooking and cleaning, much to Yūko's pleasure.&lt;ref name=&quot;ch1&quot;&gt;{{cite book |title= xxxHolic, Volume 1 |year= 2004|author=Clamp |publisher= [[Del Rey Manga]] |chapter=Chapter 1|isbn= 978-0-345-47058-4}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;ch2&quot;&gt;{{cite book |title= xxxHolic, Volume 1 |year= 2004|author=Clamp |publisher= [[Del Rey Manga]] |chapter=Chapter 2|isbn= 978-0-345-47058-4}}&lt;/ref&gt; She also sends him on various jobs that often have a spiritual nature. Watanuki is known for a having both a volatile and caring nature to him. While around [[#Himawari Kunogi|Himawari Kunogi]], he is very excited and speaks in a high-pitched voice,&lt;ref name=&quot;ch3&quot;&gt;{{cite book |title= xxxHolic, Volume 1 |year= 2004|author=Clamp |publisher= [[Del Rey Manga]] |chapter=Chapter 3|isbn= 978-0-345-47058-4}}&lt;/ref&gt; while he expresses irritation while speaking to [[#Shizuka Dōmeki|Shizuka Dōmeki]].&lt;ref name=&quot;ch13&quot;&gt;{{cite book |title= xxxHolic, Volume 2 |year= 2004|author=Clamp |publisher= [[Del Rey Manga]] |chapter=Chapter 13|isbn= 978-0-345-47119-2}}&lt;/ref&gt; He generally gets enraged at the often insane requests of Yūko, though he will pay close attention whenever she is serious with him.&lt;ref name=&quot;ch13&quot;&gt;{{cite book |title= xxxHolic, Volume 8 |year= 2006|author=Clamp |publisher= [[Del Rey Manga]] |chapter=Chapter 49|isbn= 978-0-345-48336-2 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

Watanuki is essentially an alternate self of the [[List of Tsubasa: Reservoir Chronicle characters#Tsubasa (Syaoran)|second Syaoran]] who appeared in the series, having been created to fill the gap left by Syaoran after he decided to turn back time and be imprisoned by the sorcerer [[Fei-Wang Reed]] as a payment. Watanuki became the child of Syaoran's parents, and fills all of the relationships Syaoran would have made.&lt;ref name=&quot;ch90&quot;&gt;{{cite book |title= xxxHolic, Volume 14 |year= 2009|author=Clamp |publisher= [[Del Rey Manga]] |chapter=Chapter 90|isbn= 978-0-345-51843-9}}&lt;/ref&gt; Before the series' start, Watanuki gave up the memories of his past in order to help Yūko find Fei-Wang, and help Syaoran. As he then could not remember his parents, Watanuki developed a strong guilt, thinking his parents died due to his fault, and it led to the attraction of spirits.&lt;ref name=&quot;ch90&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;ch84&quot;/&gt;  

After Yūko's death, Watanuki resolves to stay and take care of the shop until he sees her again.&lt;ref name=&quot;ch95&quot;&gt;{{cite book |title= xxxHolic, Volume 15 |year= 2010|author=Clamp |publisher= [[Del Rey Manga]] |chapter=Chapter 95|isbn= 978-0-345-52112-5}}&lt;/ref&gt; In order to both stabilize the shop and break free of Fei-Wang's dying curse with the second Syaoran, Watanuki offers up the remainder of his &quot;existence&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;tsu233&quot;&gt;{{cite book |title=Tsubasa: Reservoir Chronicle, Volume 28 |year= 2010|author=Clamp |publisher= [[Del Rey Manga]] |chapter=Chapitre 233|isbn= 978-0-345-52164-4}}&lt;/ref&gt; As a result, Watanuki can no longer leave the shop. He becomes the new master of the shop and takes up Yūko's role of granting wishes to those who come to the shop.&lt;ref name=&quot;ch96&quot;&gt;{{cite book |title= xxxHolic, Volume 16 |year= 2010|author=Clamp |publisher= [[Del Rey Manga]] |chapter=Chapter 96|isbn= 978-0-345-52412-6}}&lt;/ref&gt; Over the next several years, Watanuki's powers become stronger thanks to the fact he did not remove his ability to see spirits.&lt;ref name=&quot;ch101&quot;&gt;{{cite book |title= xxxHolic, Volume 16 |year= 2010|author=Clamp |publisher= [[Del Rey Manga]] |chapter=Chapter 101|isbn= 978-0-345-52412-6}}&lt;/ref&gt; His lifespan also increases and retains the appearance of a teenager for over a hundred years. Over a hundred years after taking over the shop, Watanuki's powers grow strong enough to allow him leave the shop, but decides to remain there.&lt;ref name=&quot;final&quot;/&gt;

{{anime voices2|Watanuki|[[Jun Fukuyama]]|[[Todd Haberkorn]]}}&lt;ref name=&quot;holicstaff&quot;&gt;{{Cite web |title=xxxHOLiC&amp;gt; STAFF &amp; CAST |url=http://www.productionig.com/contents/works_sp/43_/s03_/index.html |publisher=Production I.G |accessdate=January 17, 2011 |archiveurl=http://www.webcitation.org/5vnxeBAVF |archivedate=January 17, 2011 |deadurl=no }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;OVAengcast&quot;&gt;{{cite web |title=Tsubasa OVAs English Cast Revealed|date=January 3, 2011 |url=http://www.mania.com/tsubasa-ovas-english-cast-revealed_article_127444.html|author=Beveridge, Chris|accessdate=January 4, 2011|publisher=Mania Entertainment}}&lt;/ref&gt; Director Tsutomu Mizushima referred to Watanuki as his favorite character from the series due to his personality and that he identifies himself with him.&lt;ref name=&quot;holicstaff&quot;&gt;{{cite web|title =Interview: Tsutomu Mizushima|url = http://www.productionig.com/contents/works_sp/22_/s08_/000063.html|publisher=Production I.G| accessdate = February 22, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; In a ''xxxHolic'' poll, Watanuki was voted as the most popular character from the series.&lt;ref name=&quot;holicpoll&quot;&gt;{{cite book |last=Clamp |authorlink=Clamp (manga artists) |others=translanted and adapted by William Flanagan |title=The Official xxxHOLiC Guide |publisher=[[Del Rey Manga]] |year=2009|location=[[New York]] |pages=139 |isbn=978-0-345-51000-6}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Yūko Ichihara===
{{nihongo|Yūko Ichihara|壱原 侑子|Ichihara Yūko}} is a woman who runs a shop that deals in granting wishes in exchange for something of equal value to the wish; sometimes this is referred to as a soul. She can take anything from a precious object to abstract concepts, such as love and luck in exchange.&lt;ref name=&quot;ch1&quot;/&gt; She usually displays an immature and free-spirited attitude, drinking saké at all hours of the day and forcing difficult tasks upon Watanuki.&lt;ref name=&quot;ch4&quot;&gt;{{cite book |title= xxxHolic, Volume 1 |year= 2004|author=Clamp |publisher= [[Del Rey Manga]] |chapter=Chapter 4|isbn= 978-0-345-47058-4}}&lt;/ref&gt; While dealing with customers or giving Watanuki advice, she is much more stern and offers cryptic messages to warn him and others of impending danger. She constantly speaks of inevitability and how nothing is a coincidence.&lt;ref name=&quot;ch1&quot;/&gt;

Yūko had a past relationship with the sorcerer [[Clow Reed]] and both created the two [[Mokona Modoki]] creatures in anticipation for the series' events.&lt;ref name=&quot;ch9&quot;&gt;{{cite book |title= xxxHolic, Volume 2 |year= 2004|author=Clamp |publisher= [[Del Rey Manga]] |chapter=Chapter 9|isbn= 978-0-345-47119-2}}&lt;/ref&gt; While she was on the verge of dying, Clow Reed accidentally used his powers to freeze time for her just by wishing for her to open her eyes. After that point, she opposes the sorcerer Fei-Wang Reed who controls the events happening in ''Tsubasa: Reservoir Chronicle''.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |title=Tsubasa: Reservoir Chronicle, Volume 9 |year= 2006|author=Clamp |publisher= [[Del Rey Manga]] |chapter=Chapitre 64|isbn= 978-0-345-48429-1}}&lt;/ref&gt; Near the end of ''Tsubasa: Reservoir Chronicle'', Yūko is revived by Fei-Wang and gives her life as a price to enable the clones of [[Syaoran (Tsubasa: Reservoir Chronicle)|Syaoran]] and [[Sakura (Tsubasa: Reservoir Chronicle)|Sakura]] be reborn as normal humans.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |title=Tsubasa: Reservoir Chronicle, Volume 27 |year= 2010|author=Clamp |publisher= [[Del Rey Manga]] |chapter=Chapitre 215|isbn= 978-0-345-52071-5 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |title=Tsubasa: Reservoir Chronicle, Volume 28 |year= 2010|author=Clamp |publisher= [[Del Rey Manga]] |chapter=Chapitre 220|isbn= 978-0-345-52164-4}}&lt;/ref&gt; Following this, Yūko finds Watanuki and tells him her wish is or for him to continue existing just before her death as she is covered by shadows from the Dream World.&lt;ref name=&quot;ch95&quot;/&gt;

Over a hundred years later after her death and Watanuki has become the shop's owner, Yūko appears as part of a dream she left to Watanuki, telling him he has stayed in the shop for a long time and now is able to leave it.&lt;ref name=&quot;final&quot;/&gt; In the ''Holic Rō'' OVA, Watanuki receives a recorded tape from a girl. When Watanuki plays the tape, Yūko's voice is heard saying &quot;I'm home,&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite video |date = June 2010|title = xxxHolic Rō|format = [[DVD]] |publisher = Kodansha}}&lt;/ref&gt; {{anime voices2|Yūko|[[Sayaka Ohara]]|[[Colleen Clinkenbeard]]}}&lt;ref name=&quot;holicstaff&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;OVAengcast&quot;/&gt; Yūko's character has well-received by Japanese readers of the series. In two popularity polls held by ''[[Weekly Shōnen Magazine]]'', she placed seventh among all the characters in ''Tsubasa: Reservoir Chronicle''.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |last=Clamp |authorlink=Clamp (manga artists) |others=translanted and adapted by William Flanagan|title=Tsubasa CHARACTer GuiDE |publisher=[[Del Rey Manga]] |year=2005 |location=[[New York]] |page=151 |isbn=978-4063720013}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |last=Clamp |authorlink=Clamp (manga artists) |others=translanted and adapted by William Flanagan|title=Tsubasa CHARACTer GuiDE 2|publisher=[[Del Rey Manga]] |year=2006 |location=[[New York]] |page=147|isbn=978-4063722161}}&lt;/ref&gt; In the ''[[Animage]]''{{'}}s [[Anime Grand Prix]] poll from 2007, Yūko was voted as the thirteenth most popular female anime character.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | journal=[[Animage]] | publisher=[[Gakken]] |issue=6| title=Anime Grand Prix 2006-2007| date=May 2007 | language=Japanese}}&lt;/ref&gt; In a ''xxxHolic'' poll, Yūko was featured as the third most popular character from the series.&lt;ref name=&quot;holicpoll&quot;&gt;{{cite book |last=Clamp |authorlink=Clamp (manga artists) |others=translanted and adapted by William Flanagan |title=The Official xxxHOLiC Guide |publisher=[[Del Rey Manga]] |year=2009|location=[[New York]] |pages=139 |isbn=978-0-345-51000-6}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Shizuka Dōmeki===
{{nihongo|Shizuka Dōmeki|百目鬼 静|Dōmeki Shizuka}} is a schoolmate of Watanuki. He lives in a shrine owned by his late grandfather, [[#Haruka Dōmeki|Haruka Dōmeki]], a [[Shinto]] priest who taught Dōmeki about folklore and shinto practices during his childhood. However, despite his heritage, Dōmeki has a nearly null ability of seeing ghosts or spirits, though he can sense them, and he has a natural ability to exorcise them.&lt;ref name=&quot;ch22&quot;&gt;{{cite book |title= xxxHolic, Volume 2 |year= 2004|author=Clamp |publisher= [[Del Rey Manga]] |chapter=Chapter 22|isbn= 978-0-345-47119-2 }}&lt;/ref&gt; He is part of the school's [[kyūdō]] club and often tops school competitions. Dōmeki barely speaks unless explaining folklore or asking Watanuki various of his meals which infuriates him.&lt;ref name=&quot;ch19&quot;&gt;{{cite book |title= xxxHolic, Volume 3 |year= 2004|author=Clamp |publisher= [[Del Rey Manga]] |chapter=Chapter 19|isbn= 978-0-345-47181-9 }}&lt;/ref&gt; {{anime voices2|Dōmeki|[[Kazuya Nakai]]|[[J. Michael Tatum]]}}&lt;ref name=&quot;holicstaff&quot;/&gt;

Despite Watanuki's hatred for him, Yūko often makes Dōmeki join Watanuki in his jobs as his ability to exorcise spirits annulate the attraction that Watanuki has towards them.&lt;ref name=&quot;ch22&quot;/&gt; Utilizing Yūko's shop, Dōmeki gives Watanuki half of his eye after he loses his right eye's vision to the spirits, which allows Dōmeki to see and experience what Watanuki goes through.&lt;ref name=&quot;ch49&quot;&gt;{{cite book |title= xxxHolic, Volume 8 |year= 2006|author=Clamp |publisher= [[Del Rey Manga]] |chapter=Chapter 49|isbn= 978-0-345-48336-2  }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;ch50&quot;&gt;{{cite book |title= xxxHolic, Volume 8 |year= 2006|author=Clamp |publisher= [[Del Rey Manga]] |chapter=Chapter 50|isbn= 978-0-345-48336-2  }}&lt;/ref&gt; He also gives Watanuki a large amount of his blood, which Yūko states is changing their personalities. Yūko gives Domeki a magic egg obtained by Sakura while working for her, however Dōmeki does not know what it does or when he should use it.&lt;ref name=&quot;ch67&quot;&gt;{{cite book |title= xxxHolic, Volume 11 |year= 2008|author=Clamp |publisher= [[Del Rey Manga]] |chapter=Chapter 68|isbn= 978-0-345-50163-9 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;ch96&quot;/&gt;

Four years after Yūko's death, Dōmeki is a university student studying ancient history and often visits Watanuki in the shop. Because Watanuki cannot leave the shop, Domeki provides assistance both with Watanuki's work and by providing essentials, such as food.&lt;ref name=&quot;ch97&quot;&gt;{{cite book |title= xxxHolic, Volume 16 |year= 2010|author=Clamp |publisher= [[Del Rey Manga]] |chapter=Chapter 97|isbn= 978-0-345-52412-6}}&lt;/ref&gt; After six more years, Dōmeki graduates and has become an assistant to one of his professors at the university.&lt;ref name=&quot;ch106&quot;&gt;{{cite book |title= xxxHolic, Volume 18 |year= 2010|author=Clamp |publisher= [[Kodansha]] |chapter=Chapter 106|isbn= 978-4-06-375979-2}}&lt;/ref&gt; In the ''xxxHolic Rō Adayume'' OVA it is revealed that Dōmeki is engaged with [[#Kohane Tsuyuri|Kohane Tsuyuri]], having delivered his wedding's invitation to Watanuki.&lt;ref name=&quot;adayum&quot;&gt;{{cite video |date = March 2011|title = xxxHolic Rō Adayume|format = [[DVD]] |publisher = Kodansha}}&lt;/ref&gt; After it has been over a hundred years since Watanuki inherited the shop, Dōmeki's great grandson is Watanuki's new assistant, keeping the egg Yūko gave to Dōmeki.&lt;ref name=&quot;final&quot;&gt;{{cite book |title= xxxHolic, Volume 19 |year= 2011|author=Clamp |publisher= [[Kodansha]]|isbn= 978-4-06-376039-2}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Himawari Kunogi===
{{nihongo|Himawari Kunogi|九軒 葵|Kunogi Himawari}} is Watanuki's [[love interest]] and classmate. She has a cheerful attitude and is very friendly around Watanuki and Dōmeki.&lt;ref name=&quot;ch3&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;ch13&quot;&gt;{{cite book |title= xxxHolic, Volume 8 |year= 2006|author=Clamp |publisher= [[Del Rey Manga]] |chapter=Chapter 49|isbn= 978-0-345-48336-2 }}&lt;/ref&gt; Despite the fact that Watanuki is very open in showing his feelings and admiration for her, she seems very oblivious to the fact that he likes her. Watanuki always thinks that Dōmeki is more favored. Watanuki often invited her to join him for various outings, but Himawari characteristically has a prior engagement, comically and inadvertently leaving Watanuki with Dōmeki. {{anime voices2|Himawari|[[Shizuka Itō]]|[[Cherami Leigh]]}}&lt;ref name=&quot;holicstaff&quot;/&gt;

Watanuki originally believes that she is his &quot;goddess of good luck&quot;, though Yūko states the opposite, often leaving cryptic statements about Himawari's true nature.&lt;ref name=&quot;ch3&quot;/&gt; It is eventually revealed that Himawari emanates misfortune that affects everyone around her except her parents, as they brought her into the world, and those with spiritual abilities, such as Dōmeki and Yūko.&lt;ref name=&quot;ch60&quot;&gt;{{cite book |title= xxxHolic, Volume 10 |year= 2008|author=Clamp |publisher= [[Del Rey Manga]] |chapter=Chapter 60|isbn= 978-0-345-49683-6 }}&lt;/ref&gt; Her luck causes Watanuki fall from a second story window and is severely cut by the shattered window glass, nearly dying.&lt;ref name=&quot;ch62&quot;&gt;{{cite book |title= xxxHolic, Volume 10 |year= 2008|author=Clamp |publisher= [[Del Rey Manga]] |chapter=Chapter 62|isbn= 978-0-345-49683-6 }}&lt;/ref&gt; Yūko has them rush Watanuki to her shop, where they manage to save his life. After revealing her secret to Watanuki, she attempts to cut all connections with him. Watanuki, however, states that he is truly happy around her no matter what and refuses to stop seeing her.&lt;ref name=&quot;ch63&quot;&gt;{{cite book |title= xxxHolic, Volume 10 |year= 2008|author=Clamp |publisher= [[Del Rey Manga]] |chapter=Chapter 63|isbn= 978-0-345-49683-6 }}&lt;/ref&gt; Watanuki later gives her a small bird he names {{nihongo|Tanpopo|タンポポ||lit. &quot;Dandelion&quot;}} that is immune to her bad luck.&lt;ref name=&quot;ch65&quot;&gt;{{cite book |title= xxxHolic, Volume 11 |year= 2008|author=Clamp |publisher= [[Del Rey Manga]] |chapter=Chapter 65|isbn= 978-0-345-50163-9 }}&lt;/ref&gt; The small bird comes from an egg that was retrieved by Sakura from an alternate Tokyo.&lt;ref name=&quot;ch66&quot;&gt;{{cite book |title= xxxHolic, Volume 11 |year= 2008|author=Clamp |publisher= [[Del Rey Manga]] |chapter=Chapter 66|isbn= 978-0-345-50163-9 }}&lt;/ref&gt; After Watanuki tells Himawari that he loves her and is glad to met her, Himawari starts developing feelings for Watanuki.

She is the only one of the main cast not seen visiting Watanuki after he inherits the shop. She is attending a university far away from Watanuki's store.  Because her natural misfortune causes problems with the shop's magic, she has promised only to enter the shop once a year, always on Watanuki's birthday, though she calls occasionally. Himawari is married to a businessman whose identity is unknown.&lt;ref name=&quot;ch104&quot;&gt;{{cite book |title= xxxHolic, Volume 17 |year= 2010|author=Clamp |publisher= [[Kodansha]] |chapter=Chapter 104|isbn= 978-0-345-53071-4}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Kohane Tsuyuri===
{{nihongo|Kohane Tsuyuri|五月七日小羽|Tsuyuri Kohane}} is a young girl known publicly as a [[child prodigy]], [[Mediumship|medium]] and [[exorcist]], having been featured on many paranormal-based TV shows.&lt;ref name=&quot;ch55&quot;&gt;{{cite book |title= xxxHolic, Volume 9 |year= 2008|author=Clamp |publisher= [[Del Rey Manga]] |chapter=Chapter 55|isbn= 978-0-345-49639-3 }}&lt;/ref&gt; After first developing her powers, she helped her mother learn that her father was having an affair, causing a drastic change in her mother's personality. She soon stopped touching Kohane, does not refer to her by name, takes away any objects or food not considered &quot;pure&quot;, and cuts off all contact with other people. Nevertheless, Kohane states her mother's treatment is her fault for developing her powers.&lt;ref name=&quot;ch83&quot;&gt;{{cite book |title= xxxHolic, Volume 13 |year= 2009|author=Clamp |publisher= [[Del Rey Manga]] |chapter=Chapter 83|isbn= 978-0-345-50566-8}}&lt;/ref&gt; She focuses on having Kohane on as many television shows as possible, and buys large amounts of extravagant items. This treatment causes Kohane to have a quiet and lonely demeanor, though she attempts to stay strong for her mother's sake, blaming everything on herself.&lt;ref name=&quot;ch55&quot;/&gt; {{anime voices2|Kohane|[[Rina Hidaka]]}}

She eventually meets Watanuki, and forms a bond with him.&lt;ref name=&quot;ch56&quot;&gt;{{cite book |title= xxxHolic, Volume 9 |year= 2008|author=Clamp |publisher= [[Del Rey Manga]] |chapter=Chapter 56|isbn= 978-0-345-49639-3 }}&lt;/ref&gt; Despite constant protest from her mother, he keeps in contact with her, all while trying to make her feel happy.&lt;ref name=&quot;ch81&quot;&gt;{{cite book |title= xxxHolic, Volume 13 |year= 2009|author=Clamp |publisher= [[Del Rey Manga]] |chapter=Chapter 81|isbn= 978-0-345-50566-8}}&lt;/ref&gt; Her powers of exorcism develop from a magical feather embodied from Sakura, though her ability to see spirits is natural. She asks Yūko to grant her happiness, which Yūko does by fixing the various external problems in her life, such as her reputation, in exchange for her exorcism ability. Yūko cannot fix her issues with her mother, as a person's true character can only be changed by their own will.&lt;ref name=&quot;ch84&quot;&gt;{{cite book |title= xxxHolic, Volume 13 |year= 2009|author=Clamp |publisher= [[Del Rey Manga]] |chapter=Chapter 84|isbn= 978-0-345-50566-8}}&lt;/ref&gt; Four years after Yūko's death, Kohane is a student at Tsuji Academy and often visits Watanuki in his shop.&lt;ref name=&quot;ch97&quot;/&gt; She continues to live with the grandmother fortune teller. After six years, she studies folklore at the same university as Domeki, with whom she also bonded.&lt;ref name=&quot;ch106&quot;/&gt; In the ''xxxHolic Rō Adayume'' OVA it is revealed that Kohane is engaged with Dōmeki, who states that nevertheless Watanuki is Kohane's most important person.&lt;ref name=&quot;adayum&quot;/&gt;

==Secondary characters==
===Zashiki-warashi===
{{nihongo|[[Zashiki-warashi]]|座敷童||lit. &quot;Vestal Sprite&quot;}} is a spirit girl who lives on a mountain with pure spiritual energy. She is very shy and prone to crying, which causes her Karasu-[[Tengu]] Guardians. small guardians, to defend her. Ironically, the guardians will come to her aid even if she weeps tears of joy. Zashiki-warashi develops a crush on [[#Kimihiro Watanuki|Kimihiro Watanuki]] as his exploits become known among spirits, and she first meets him when she accidentally steals [[#Shizuka Dōmeki|Shizuka Dōmeki]]'s soul while attempting to get a good Valentine's Day gift for Watanuki.&lt;ref name=&quot;ch23&quot;&gt;{{cite book |title= xxxHolic, Volume 4 |year= 2006|author=Clamp |publisher= [[Del Rey Manga]] |chapter=Chapter 23|isbn= 978-0-345-47788-0 }}&lt;/ref&gt; He later sees her while giving her a [[White Day]] present, while restoring the pipe fox spirit to his smaller form. Watanuki later rescues her from [[Jorōgumo|Lady Jorōgumo]] who captures her after a failed attempt to recover Watanuki's eye,&lt;ref name=&quot;ch49&quot;/&gt; and she appears again briefly with her friend, [[#Ame-warashi|Ame-warashi]], after Watanuki recovers from a near death experience. {{anime voices2|Zashiki-warashi|[[Sumi Mutoh]]|[[Brina Palencia]]}}

===Ame-warashi===
{{nihongo|Ame-warashi|雨童女||lit. &quot;Rain Sprite&quot;}} is a high ranking rain spirit, who has a very hostile attitude toward humans due to the fact that &quot;humans have no care or regard whatsoever with living nature&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;ch29&quot;&gt;{{cite book |title= xxxHolic, Volume 5|year= 2006|author=Clamp |publisher= [[Del Rey Manga]] |chapter=Chapter 29|isbn= 978-0-345-47789-7 }}&lt;/ref&gt; She is somewhat close and protective of Zashiki-warashi, and greatly teases Watanuki, despite him helping to fulfill her request. She owned the creature [[#Kudagitsune|Kudagitsune]] which later becomes Watanuki's guardian. She gives it to [[#Yūko Ichihara|Yūko Ichihara]] as a compensation for fulfilling her wish to retrieve the sick hydrangea.&lt;ref name=&quot;ch30&quot;&gt;{{cite book |title= xxxHolic, Volume 5|year= 2006|author=Clamp |publisher= [[Del Rey Manga]] |chapter=Chapter 30|isbn= 978-0-345-47789-7 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;ch31&quot;&gt;{{cite book |title= xxxHolic, Volume 5|year= 2006|author=Clamp |publisher= [[Del Rey Manga]] |chapter=Chapter 31|isbn= 978-0-345-47789-7 }}&lt;/ref&gt; {{anime voices2|Ame-warashi|Akiko Yajima|[[Kate Oxley]]}}

===Kudagitsune===
{{nihongo|Kudagitsune|管狐||lit. &quot;Pipe Fox&quot;}}, later named  {{nihongo|Mugetsu|無月||lit. &quot;moonless&quot; or &quot;no moon&quot;}} by Watanuki,&lt;ref name=&quot;ch67&quot;/&gt; is a [[Kudagitsune|tube fox spirit]] given to Yūko as payment by Ame-warashi for Watanuki's help. It quickly becomes attached to Watanuki, and protects him during dangerous situations.&lt;ref name=&quot;ch31&quot;/&gt; It is generally a small snake-like being with a fox head, but it can transform into a traditional [[Kitsune|nine-tailed fox]] when it reveals its true power. It is able to create &quot;Foxfire&quot; in the form of large fireballs, and it can detect evil spirits.&lt;ref name=&quot;ch32&quot;&gt;{{cite book |title= xxxHolic, Volume 5|year= 2006|author=Clamp |publisher= [[Del Rey Manga]] |chapter=Chapter 32|isbn= 978-0-345-47789-7 }}&lt;/ref&gt; It takes a large amount of pure spiritual energy to revert it to its initial form.&lt;ref name=&quot;ch34&quot;&gt;{{cite book |title= xxxHolic, Volume 5|year= 2006|author=Clamp |publisher= [[Del Rey Manga]] |chapter=Chapter 34|isbn= 978-0-345-47789-7 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Maru &amp; Moro===
{{nihongo|Maru|マル}} and {{nihongo|Moro|モロ}}, whose respective real names are {{nihongo|Marudashi|マルダシ}} and {{nihongo|Morodashi|モロダシ}}, are two artificial beings that keep Yūko's shop in existence.&lt;ref name=&quot;ch32&quot;/&gt; They are two energetic small girls, who often speak in unison and repeat the words of others.&lt;ref name=&quot;ch1&quot;/&gt; They cannot leave the shop, as they have no souls.&lt;ref name=&quot;ch32&quot;/&gt; They help Yūko around the shop most of the time, but often go into long periods of hibernation due to the strain from keeping the shop in existence. Yuko uses the last bit of her power to revive Maru and Moro and send them back to the shop.&lt;ref name=&quot;ch96&quot;/&gt; After Watanuki becomes the new shop's owner, Maru and Moro become his assistants. Later it is shown that they have developed a very close bond with Watanuki similar to the one they had with Yūko.&lt;ref name=&quot;ch97&quot;/&gt; {{anime voices2|Maru|[[Kazuko Kojima]]|[[Leah Clark]]}} {{Anime voices2|Moro|[[Hisayo Mochizuki]]|[[Brina Palencia]]}}&lt;ref name=&quot;holicstaff&quot;/&gt;

===Mokona Modoki===
{{nihongo|Mokona Modoki|モコナ＝モドキ}} refers to a pair of two rabbit-like creatures created by Yūko and [[Clow Reed]] in preparation for the events in ''[[Tsubasa: Reservoir Chronicle]]'' and ''xxxHolic'', as well as to save &quot;two futures&quot;. The [[List of Tsubasa: Reservoir Chronicle characters#Mokona Modoki|white Mokona]] travels with [[Syaoran (Tsubasa: Reservoir Chronicle)|Syaoran]]'s group, while the black Mokona stays in Yūko's shop.&lt;ref name=&quot;ch9&quot;/&gt; Both are based upon the original [[List of Magic Knight Rayearth characters#Mokona|Mokona]], who Yūko and Clow encountered while Mokona was traveling through different worlds. Mokona provided Yūko and Clow with the knowledge of alternate dimensions.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |author=Clamp|title=ソエルとラーグ―モコナ=モドキの冒険|publisher=[[Kodansha]] |year=2004 |pages=|isbn=978-4063645958|trans_title=Soel and Larg: The Adventures of Mokona=Modoki}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The black Mokona, whose real name is {{nihongo|Larg|ラーグ|Rāgu}}, acts as a liaison between the ''Tsubasa: Reservoir Chronicle'' protagonists and Yūko.&lt;ref name=&quot;ch16&quot;&gt;{{cite book |title= xxxHolic, Volume 3|year= 2004|author=Clamp |publisher= [[Del Rey Manga]] |chapter=Chapter 15|isbn= 978-0-345-47181-9 }}&lt;/ref&gt; Mokona likes to be around Yūko, who treats Mokona as a &quot;drinking buddy.&quot; He also likes to be around Watanuki and play with Maru and Moro.&lt;ref name=&quot;ch106&quot;/&gt; While allowing the two groups to speak, Mokona can also teleport and receive items from the white Mokona by swallowing them. Like the white Mokona, he has a single earring. It is a blue gem made by Clow Reed and has the ability to seal magical power, and it also holds [[Sakura (Tsubasa: Reservoir Chronicle)|Sakura]]'s memories of Syaoran and Watanuki's memory of his past.&lt;ref name=&quot;ch84&quot;/&gt; {{Anime voices2|Mokona|[[Mika Kikuchi]]|[[Carrie Savage]]}}&lt;ref name=&quot;holicstaff&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;OVAengcast&quot;/&gt;

===Haruka Dōmeki===
{{nihongo|Haruka Dōmeki|百目鬼 遥|Dōmeki Haruka}} is the deceased grandfather of Dōmeki, and a former Shinto priest who taught Shizuka Dōmeki many of his practices. He has the ability to destroy evil spirits, cross into dreams and often appears to Watanuki's dream, taking on the appearance of a teenager. As a teenager, he looks exactly like Dōmeki, though he has a somewhat more cheerful and outgoing personality than his grandson, and he is always smoking.&lt;ref name=&quot;ch53&quot;&gt;{{cite book |title= xxxHolic, Volume 9 |year= 2008|author=Clamp |publisher= [[Del Rey Manga]] |chapter=Chapter 53|isbn= 978-0-345-49639-3 }}&lt;/ref&gt; He acts like a guide to Watanuki as Yūko does, often giving him advice, telling him about Dōmeki, and helping him work out problems. Before Yūko's death, Haruka is visited by her in a dream, requesting him to keep protecting Watanuki.&lt;ref name=&quot;ch101&quot;/&gt; In the ''xxxHolic Rō Adayume'' OVA, Haruka becomes Watanuki's client as he wants him to free Dōmeki from nightmares.&lt;ref name=&quot;adayum&quot;/&gt; {{anime voices2|Haruka|[[Kazuya Nakai]]}}

===Syaoran===
{{main|Syaoran (Tsubasa: Reservoir Chronicle)|List of Tsubasa: Reservoir Chronicle characters#Tsubasa (Syaoran)}}
{{nihongo|Syaoran|小狼|Shaoran}} refers to two identical teenagers who appear across the series. The first one is from a parallel dimension and visits Yūko's shop to help him save his childhood friend Sakura. He gains the ability to travel across dimension with the white Mokona in order to recover the memories Sakura lost and remains in contact with Yūko.&lt;ref name=&quot;ch9&quot;/&gt; The [[List of Tsubasa: Reservoir Chronicle characters#Tsubasa (Syaoran)|second Syaoran]] shortly visits Yūko, as he is sent to another world.&lt;ref name=&quot;ch57&quot;&gt;{{cite book |title= xxxHolic, Volume 9 |year= 2008|author=Clamp |publisher= [[Del Rey Manga]] |chapter=Chapter 57|isbn= 978-0-345-49639-3 }}&lt;/ref&gt; While Watanuki does not know him, Syaoran paid a price to save Watanuki from dying after being affected by Himawari's bad luck,&lt;ref name=&quot;ch63&quot;/&gt; and constantly he can hear him yelling him not to die.&lt;ref name=&quot;ch76&quot;/&gt; It is later revealed that the second Syaoran was responsible for creating Watanuki when he wished turn back time, but at the price of losing his freedom to the sorcerer [[Fei-Wang Reed]]. Watanuki was used to replace Syaoran in his world, sharing the same parents, but forgot all of this, when he paid Yūko with his memories to locate Fei-Wang.&lt;ref name=&quot;ch90&quot;/&gt; Watanuki later learns of their relationship in the ending of ''Tsubasa'' when both are imprisoned by Fei-Wang's curse. To free each other Syaoran has to travel across dimensions forever.&lt;ref name=&quot;tsu233&quot;/&gt; Both Syaorans are voiced by [[Miyu Irino]].

===Sakura===
{{main|Sakura (Tsubasa: Reservoir Chronicle)}}
{{nihongo|Sakura|サクラ}} is a girl coming from another dimension in catatonic state under the care of the teenager Syaoran. As Sakura is about to die due to losing her soul, Syaoran goes on a search across dimension to save her. However, the usage of the white Mokona Modoki to travel across dimension requires Sakura to pay to Yūko with all her memories regarding Syaoran, her most important person.&lt;ref name=&quot;ch9&quot;/&gt; As the series continues, Sakura recovers and gives Yūko an egg as part of a job which then becomes two and are given to Watanuki and Domeki. Her soul is later separated from her body and appears in the Dream World where she meets Watanuki.&lt;ref name=&quot;ch73&quot;&gt;{{cite book |title= xxxHolic, Volume 12 |year= 2008|author=Clamp |publisher= [[Del Rey Manga]] |chapter=Chapter 73|isbn= 978-0-345-50565-1}}&lt;/ref&gt; Befriending him, Sakura finds Watanuki similar to the other Syaoran, and later disappears from the Dream World.&lt;ref name=&quot;ch76&quot;&gt;{{cite book |title= xxxHolic, Volume 12 |year= 2008|author=Clamp |publisher= [[Del Rey Manga]] |chapter=Chapter 76|isbn= 978-0-345-50565-1}}&lt;/ref&gt;  She is voiced by [[Yui Makino]].

==Reception==
The characters from ''xxxHolic'' have been well-received by publications from manga and anime. Although Watanuki's character was initially seen &quot;a little bit weak to be the lead character&quot;,&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web |first=Dan |last=Polley |url=http://www.mangalife.com/reviews/xxxHolicv10.htm |title=xxxHOLiC v10 |publisher=Manga Life |date=November 25, 2007 |accessdate=November 18, 2010 |archiveurl=http://web.archive.org/web/20071127150153/www.mangalife.com/reviews/xxxHolicv10.htm |archivedate=November 27, 2007 |deadurl=yes }}&lt;/ref&gt; his interactions with other characters and his development across the series has been praised.&lt;ref name=&quot;volelven&quot;&gt;{{Cite web |first=Joy |last=Kim |url=http://www.mangalife.com/reviews/xxxHOLiCv11-12.htm |title=xxxHOLiC v11-12 Review |publisher=Manga Life |date=August 13, 2008 |accessdate=November 18, 2010 |archiveurl=http://web.archive.org/web/20080815224220/www.mangalife.com/reviews/xxxHOLiCv11-12.htm |archivedate=August 15, 2008 |deadurl=yes }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;maniatwelve&quot;&gt;{{cite web |first=Matthew |last=Alexander |url=http://www.mania.com/xxxholic-vol-12_article_83873.html|title=XXXHolic Vol.#12|date=September 6, 2008 |publisher=Mania Entertainment|accessdate=November 18, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; Todd Douglass Jr. from DVD Talk agreed, focusing in the characters in general and how they were developed across the anime.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |first=Todd|last=Douglass Jr.|url=http://www.dvdtalk.com/reviews/34614/xxxholic-fifth-collection/|title=xxxHOLiC: Fifth Collection |date=September 9, 2008|publisher=DVD Talk |accessdate=November 18, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; The emotional focus on the series has also been well-received due to its comedy and the way characters deal supernatural elements.&lt;ref name=&quot;activeone&quot;&gt;{{Cite web |first=Holly |last=Ellingwood |url=http://activeanime.com/html/2008/04/16/xxxholic-vol-1-starter-set/ |title=XXXHOLIC VOL. 1 STARTER SET |date=April 16, 2010 |publisher=Active Anime |accessdate=November 18, 2010 }}&lt;!-- http://www.activeanime.com/html/content/view/3000/57/ --&gt;&lt;/ref&gt; Yuko has also been called the &quot;star performer&quot; from the series, and her death has received mixed feelings; although writers found events following her death to lack the main characters' comedy, the way Watanuki dealed with her role was enjoyed.&lt;ref name=&quot;rosixteen&quot;&gt;{{cite web |first=Carlo |last=Santos |url=http://www.animenewsnetwork.com/review/xxxholic/gn-16|title=xxxHOLic GN 16 |date=November 4, 2010|publisher=Anime News Network |archiveurl= |archivedate= |accessdate=November 18, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |first=Matthew |last=Alexander |url=http://www.mania.com/xxxholicvol-16_article_125647.html|title=XXXHolic Vol.#16|date=November 24, 2010 |publisher=Mania Entertainment |archiveurl= |archivedate= |accessdate=November 28, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; The connections between the characters from ''xxxHolic'' and ''Tsubasa: Reservoir Chronicle'' has also received positive comments as how in both series, an important connection between two characters from the two series is hinted.&lt;ref name=&quot;animenewsnetwork.com&quot;&gt;{{cite web |first=Carlo |last=Santos |url=http://www.animenewsnetwork.com/review/xxxholic/gn-12 |title=xxxHOLic GN12 |date=September 26, 2008 |publisher=Anime News Network |archiveurl= |archivedate= |accessdate=February 12, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; However, the lack of reading the other series would confuse the readers or it would persuade them to read the other series.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |first=Megan |last=Lavey |url=http://www.mania.com/xxxholic-vol-01_article_81617.html|title=XXXHolic Vol.#01|date=June 23, 2004 |publisher=Mania Entertainment |archiveurl= |archivedate= |accessdate=November 13, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;maniatwelve&quot;&gt;{{cite web |first=Matthew |last=Alexander |url=http://www.mania.com/xxxholic-vol-12_article_83873.html|title=XXXHolic Vol.#12|date=September 6, 2008 |publisher=Mania Entertainment|accessdate=November 18, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; 

The manga's character designs have been labelled as &quot;striking&quot;, with focus on the notable traits that Clamp gives to all their characters.&lt;ref name=&quot;activeeight&quot;&gt;{{Cite web |first=Christopher |last=Seaman |url=http://www.activeanime.com/html/content/view/69/57/ |title=XXX HOLIC (VOL. 8) |date=January 10, 2007 |publisher=Active Anime |accessdate=November 18, 2010 |archiveurl=http://web.archive.org/web/20080828032553/www.activeanime.com/html/content/view/69/57/ |archivedate=August 28, 2008 |deadurl=yes }}&lt;/ref&gt; Additionally, the large number of outfits characters tend to wear was praised for being notable from each other.&lt;ref name=&quot;rosixteen&quot;/&gt; Critics have found issues with anime's character designs due to how the limbs were notably extended in most episodes, leading to superdeformed.&lt;ref name=&quot;dvdbox&quot;&gt;{{cite web |first=Carlo|last=Santos |url=http://www.animenewsnetwork.com/review/xxxholic-dvd-box-set-hyb/dvd|title=xxxHolic DVD Box Set (Hyb)|date=August 16, 2009|publisher=Anime News Network |accessdate=November 18, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |first=Jeff|last=Harris Jr.|url=http://dvd.ign.com/articles/876/876603p2.html|title=xxxHolic: First Collection DVD Review|publisher=IGN |accessdate=November 18, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; Nevertheless, such designs have been found comical with every character still noted to be distinctive.&lt;ref name=&quot;activeone&quot;/&gt; The voice casting for the English release of the series has been found remarkable with comments focused on the work from [[Colleen Clinkenbeard]] as Yuko and [[Todd Haberkorn]] as Watanuki; although the former was enjoyed, the latter received mixed responses.&lt;ref name=&quot;dvdbox&quot;/&gt;

==References==
{{reflist|2}}

{{XxxHolic}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:List Of Xxxholic Characters}}
[[Category:Lists of anime and manga characters|XxxHolic]]
[[Category:Clamp characters]]

[[it:Personaggi di xxxHOLiC]]
[[ms:Watak-watak dalam xxxHolic]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
