<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="1053447" ns="0" title="Physical attractiveness"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{double image|right|Venus de Milo Louvre Ma399 n4.jpg|180|Adonis Mazarin Louvre MR239.jpg|150|[[Venus de Milo]] at the [[Louvre]] has been described as a &quot;classical vision of beauty&quot;.&lt;ref name=twsE17&gt;{{cite news |title= People: Just Deserts |publisher= ''Time Magazine''|quote= ... &quot;the most perfect all-over beauty of all time.&quot; Runner-up: the Venus de Milo. |date= May 28, 1945 |url= http://www.time.com/time/magazine/article/0,9171,775696,00.html |accessdate= 2011-08-05}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=twsE18&gt;{{cite news |title= SAYS VENUS DE MILO WAS NOT A FLAPPER; Osteopath Says She Was Neurasthenic, as Her Stomach WasNot is Proper Place. |publisher= ''The New York Times'' |quote= Venus de Milo ... That lady of renowned beauty... |date= April 29, 1922 |url= http://query.nytimes.com/mem/archive-free/pdf?res=F50B14F6355810738DDDA00A94DC405B828EF1D3 |accessdate= 2011-08-05}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=twsE19&gt;{{cite news |author= CBS News Staff |title= Venus |publisher= ''CBS News'' |quote= The classical vision of beauty exemplified in Greek art, such as the 2nd century B.C. Venus de Milo (a.k.a. Aphrodite of Milos), was an ideal carried through millennia, laying the basis for much of Western art's depictions of the human form. |date= 2011-08-05 |url= http://www.cbsnews.com/2300-3445_162-5417565.html |accessdate= 2011-08-05
}}&lt;/ref&gt; However, one expert claimed her &quot;almost matronly&quot; &quot;representation&quot; was meant to convey an &quot;impressive appearance&quot; rather than &quot;ideal female beauty&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |author=Kousser R |title=Creating the Past: The Vénus de Milo and the Hellenistic Reception of Classical Greece|journal=American Journal of Archaeology |volume=109 |issue=2 |pages=227–250 |year=2005 |doi=10.3764/aja.109.2.227 }}&lt;/ref&gt;|''[[Adonis]]'' restored and completed by [[François Duquesnoy]], formerly in the collection of [[Cardinal Mazarin]] ([[Louvre Museum]]).}}
'''Physical attractiveness''' refers to a person's physical traits which are perceived to be [[aesthetic]]ally pleasing or [[beauty|beautiful]]. The term often implies [[sexual attraction|sexual attractiveness]] or desirability, but can also be distinct from the two; for example, humans may regard the young as attractive for various reasons, but without sexual attraction. There are many factors which influence one person's attraction to another, with physical aspects being one of them. In many cases, humans attribute positive characteristics, such as intelligence and honesty, to physically attractive people without consciously realizing it.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |author=Dion K, Berscheid E, Walster E |title=What is beautiful is good |journal=J Pers Soc Psychol |volume=24 |issue=3 |pages=285–90 |year=1972 |month=December |pmid=4655540 |doi=10.1037/h0033731 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

Men, on average, tend to be attracted by women who are shorter than they are, have a youthful appearance and exhibit features such as a [[facial symmetry|symmetrical face]],&lt;ref name=twsO66f2/&gt; full breasts, full lips, and a low waist-hip ratio.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.staff.ncl.ac.uk/daniel.nettle/procroysoc.pdf Daniel Nettle: Women’s height, reproductive success and the evolution of sexual dimorphism in modern humans. The Royal Society.] Retrieved 15 October 2009.&lt;/ref&gt; Women, on average, tend to be more attracted to men who are taller than they are, display a high-degree of facial symmetry, masculine facial dimorphism,&lt;ref name=Glassenberg10&gt;{{cite journal |author=Glassenberg AN, Feinberg DR, Jones BC, Little AC, Debruine LM |title=Sex-dimorphic face shape preference in heterosexual and homosexual men and women |journal=Arch Sex Behav |volume=39 |issue=6 |pages=1289–96 |year=2010 |month=December |pmid=19830539 |doi=10.1007/s10508-009-9559-6 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=Perrett98/&gt; and who have broad shoulders, a relatively narrow waist and V-shaped torso. 

== General contributing factors ==
Generally, physical attraction can be studied from a number of perspectives, including universal perceptions common to all human [[culture]]s, cultural and [[society|social]] aspects, and individual subjective preferences. Additionally, the perception of attractiveness can have a significant effect on how people are judged in terms of employment or social opportunities, friendship, sexual behavior, and marriage.&lt;ref&gt;Lorenz, Kate. (2005). &quot;[http://www.cnn.com/2005/US/Careers/07/08/looks/ Do Pretty People Earn More?]&quot; www.CNN.com.&lt;/ref&gt;

Some physical features are attractive in both men and women, particularly bodily&lt;ref name=twsO66f1&gt;{{cite news |author= Guy Dammann |title= Rules of attraction |publisher= ''The Guardian'' |quote= scientists from Brunel University have revealed that physical attraction is all down to bodily symmetry. |date= 20 August 2008 |url= http://www.guardian.co.uk/commentisfree/2008/aug/20/beauty |accessdate= 2011-07-15}}&lt;/ref&gt; and facial symmetry,&lt;ref name=twsO52&gt;{{cite news|author= SARAH KERSHAW |title= The Sum of Your Facial Parts |publisher= ''The New York Times''|date= October 8, 2008 |url= http://www.nytimes.com/2008/10/09/fashion/09skin.html?pagewanted=all |accessdate= 2011-07-15}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=twsO54/&gt;&lt;ref name=twsO66e&gt;{{cite news |author= Edward Willett |title= A person's face can say a lot: Helen's face is said to have launched a thousand ships, while Medusa's could turn men to stone. And even today we talk about individuals with &quot;a face that can stop a clock.&quot; |publisher= ''The Leader-Post (Regina)'' |quote= &quot;people preferentially mate with, date, associate with, employ, and even vote for physically attractive individuals.&quot; ... Symmetry is one trait we find attractive (but only if the face is right-side up: your symmetric face will, alas, do nothing to help you attract a mate if you constantly stand on your head. |date= October 29, 2008 |url= http://www.canada.com/reginaleaderpost/news/arts_life/story.html?id=89cfe85e-664a-4abf-ba93-faed9fd7704b |accessdate= 2011-07-15}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=twsO53/&gt; although one contrary report suggests that &quot;absolute flawlessness&quot; with perfect symmetry can be &quot;disturbing&quot;.&lt;ref name=twsO66d&gt;{{cite news |author= Oliver Burkeman |title= This column will change your life: The beauty in imperfection |publisher= ''The Guardian'' |quote= Absolute flawlessness, it's long been observed, is disturbing. It offers no point of connection, and may help explain the &quot;uncanny valley&quot; effect, where almost-lifelike robots trigger revulsion in humans. ... |date= 24 April 2010 |url= http://www.guardian.co.uk/lifeandstyle/2010/apr/24/change-your-life-beauty-imperfection |accessdate= 2011-07-15}}&lt;/ref&gt; Symmetry may be evolutionarily beneficial as a sign of health because asymmetry &quot;signals past illness or injury&quot;.&lt;ref name=twsO66c&gt;{{cite news|author= S McKeen |title= A beauty fix plumps up psyche and overall health |publisher= ''The Edmonton Journal'' |quote= Evolution taught us to lust after symmetry — a nicely balanced body and face — because asymmetry signals past illness or injury. We therefore define beauty quite elegantly, right down to the most ideal ratio of hips to breasts and upper lip to lower lip. Singh says one study showed that people were able to gauge beauty at a subliminal level, when shown pictures for a mere one-hundredth of a second. Another study showed babies prefer pretty faces. |date= February 10, 2006
 |url= http://www.canada.com/story_print.html?id=80528414-59df-4167-b5fb-fca13919d345&amp;sponsor=
 |accessdate= 2011-07-15}}&lt;/ref&gt; One study suggested people were able to &quot;gauge beauty at a subliminal level&quot; by seeing only a glimpse of a picture for one-hundredth of a second.&lt;ref name=twsO66c/&gt; Other important factors include youthfulness, skin clarity and smoothness of skin; and &quot;vivid color&quot; in the eyes and hair.&lt;ref name=twsO52/&gt; But there are numerous differences based on gender.

==Male physical attractiveness==
Women, on average, tend to be more attracted to men who have a relatively narrow waist, a V-shaped torso, and broad shoulders, are taller than they are, and display a high-degree of [[facial symmetry]], and relatively masculine facial dimorphism.&lt;ref  name=Glassenberg10/&gt;&lt;ref name=Perrett98&gt;{{cite journal | doi = 10.1038/29772 | last1 = Perrett | first1 = D.I. | last2 = Lee | first2 = K.J. | last3 = Penton-Voak | first3 = I.S. | last4 = Rowland | first4 = D.R. | last5 = Yoshikawa | first5 = S. | last6 = Burt | first6 = D.M. | last7 = Henzi | first7 = S.P. | last8 = Castles | first8 = D.L. | last9 = Akamatsu | first9 = S. ''et al.'' | year = 1998 | title = Effects of sexual dimorphism on facial attractiveness | url = http://www.nature.com/nature/journal/v394/n6696/full/394884a0.html | journal = Nature | volume = 394 | issue = 6696| pages = 884–7 | pmid = 9732869 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

According to one source, the most important factor that attracts gay men to other males is the man's physical attractiveness.&lt;ref&gt;Voon, C.P. The Crossroads of Race and Sexuality
Date Selection Among Men in Internet “Personal” Ads. CUNY Graduate School.&lt;/ref&gt;

===Facial attractiveness===
====Sexual dimorphism====
Studies have shown that ovulating heterosexual women (and homosexual men) prefer faces with masculine traits associated with increased exposure to testosterone during key developmental stages, such as prominent and broad cheekbones,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |author=Scheib JE, Gangestad SW, Thornhill R |title=Facial attractiveness, symmetry and cues of good genes |journal=Proc. Biol. Sci. |volume=266 |issue=1431 |pages=1913–7 |year=1999 |month=September |pmid=10535106 |pmc=1690211 |doi=10.1098/rspb.1999.0866 |url=http://rspb.royalsocietypublishing.org/cgi/pmidlookup?view=long&amp;pmid=10535106}}&lt;/ref&gt; a relatively longer lower face, developed brows, and chiseled jawlines. The masculinity of male faces (and the femininity of female faces) is described as a [[sexual dimorphism]]. Female respondents in the follicular phase of their menstrual cycle (n = 55) were significantly more likely to choose a masculine face than those in menses and luteal phases (n = 84),&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |author=Penton-Voak IS, Perrett DI |title=Female preference for male faces changes cyclically: Further evidence |journal=Evol Hum Behav |volume=21  |issue=1 |pages=39–48 |date=January 2000 |doi=10.1016/S1090-5138(99)00033-1 |url=http://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S1090513899000331}}&lt;/ref&gt; (or in those taking [[hormonal contraception]]).&lt;ref name=Glassenberg10/&gt;&lt;ref name=Perrett98/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | doi = 10.1146/annurev.psych.57.102904.190208 | author = Rhodes G | year = 2006 | title = The evolutionary psychology of facial beauty | url = | journal = Annu Rev Psychol | volume = 57 | issue = | pages = 199–226 | pmid = 16318594 }}&lt;/ref&gt; It is suggested that the masculinity of facial features is a reliable indication of good health, or, alternatively, that masculine-looking males are more likely to achieve high status.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | doi = 10.1002/ajhb.20583 | author = Fink B, Neave N, Seydel H | year = 2007 | title = Male facial appearance signals physical strength to women | url = | journal = Am J Hum Biol. | volume = 19 | issue = 1| pages = 82–7 | pmid = 17160983 }}&lt;/ref&gt; However, the correlation between attractive facial features and health has been questioned.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | doi = 10.1098/rsbl.2003.0023 | author = Rhodes G., Chan J., Zebrowitz L.A., Simmons L.W. | year = 2003 | title = Does sexual dimorphism in human faces signal health? | url = | journal = Proc Biol Sci. | volume = 270 | issue = Suppl 1| pages = S93–5 | pmid = 12952647 | pmc = 1698019 }}&lt;/ref&gt; Also, females tend to prefer masculine facial traits more for short-term partners than for long-term partners. Sociocultural factors, such as self-perceived attractiveness, status in a relationship and degree of gender-conformity, have been reported to play a role in female preferences for male faces.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | author = Cellerino A | year = 2003 | title = Psychobiology of facial attractiveness | url = | journal = J Endocrinol Invest | volume = 26 | issue = 3 Suppl | pages = 45–8 | pmid = 12834020 }}&lt;/ref&gt; Studies have found that women who perceive themselves as physically attractive are more likely to choose men with masculine facial dimorphism, than are women who perceive themselves as physically unattractive.&lt;ref name=&quot;Proc Biol Sci 1462&quot;&gt;{{cite journal | author = Little AC, Burt DM, Penton-Voak IS, Perrett DI | year = 2001 | title = Self-perceived attractiveness influences human female preferences for sexual dimorphism and symmetry in male faces | url = | journal = Proc Biol Sci. | pmid = 12123296 | volume = 268 | issue = 1462 | pmc = 1087598| pages = 39–44 | doi = 10.1098/rspb.2000.1327 }}&lt;/ref&gt; In men, facial masculinity significantly correlates with facial symmetry—it has been suggested that both are signals of developmental stability and genetic health.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |author=Gangestad SW, Thornhill R |title=Facial masculinity and fluctuating asymmetry |journal=Evol Hum Behav |volume=24 |issue=4 |pages=231–241 |date=July 2003 |doi=10.1016/S1090-5138(03)00017-5 |url=http://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S1090513803000175}}&lt;/ref&gt; One study called into question the importance of facial masculinity in physical attractiveness in men arguing that when perceived health, which is factored into facial masculinity, is discounted it makes little difference in physical attractiveness.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.plosone.org/article/info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0013585&lt;/ref&gt; In a cross-country study involving 4,794 women in their early twenties, a difference was found in women's [[mean|average]] &quot;masculinity preference&quot; between countries.&lt;ref&gt;DeBruine, L. M., Jones, B. C., Crawford, J. R., Welling, L. L. M. &amp; Little, A. C. (2010). The health of a nation predicts their mate preferences: cross-cultural variation in women’s preferences for masculinized male faces. Proceedings of the Royal Society. B 277, 2405–2410. (doi:10.1098/rspb.2009.2184)&lt;/ref&gt;

====Symmetry====
Symmetrical faces and bodies may be signs of good inheritance to women of child-bearing age seeking to create healthy offspring. Studies suggest women are more attracted to men with symmetrical faces,&lt;ref name= tws19janbc&gt;{{Cite news |author=Stephen Khan and Roger Dobson |title=A symmetrical face isn't just prettier – it's healthier too |quote=For the perfectly proportioned face is also an indication that the body it sits atop is well prepared to fight off infection. The common cold, asthma and flu are all more likely to be combated efficiently by those whose left side matches their right. |work=The Independent: Science |date=2 October 2005 |url=http://www.independent.co.uk/news/science/a-symmetrical-face-isnt-just-prettier--its-healthier-too-509285.html |accessdate=2010-01-19 |location=London}}&lt;/ref&gt; and symmetrical faces correlate with long term mental performance&lt;ref name=twsO66a&gt;{{cite news
 |title= Face shape clue to mental decline: Men with symmetrical faces are less likely to lose their memory and intelligence in later life, according to researchers.
 |publisher= ''BBC News''
 |quote= Psychologists at the University of Edinburgh found a link between facial symmetry and mental performance between the ages of 79 and 83. ...
 |date= 9 August 2009
 |url= http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/uk_news/scotland/edinburgh_and_east/8192193.stm
 |accessdate= 2011-07-15
}}&lt;/ref&gt; and are an indication that a man has experienced &quot;fewer genetic and environmental disturbances such as diseases, toxins, malnutrition or genetic mutations&quot; while growing.&lt;ref name=twsO66a/&gt; Since achieving symmetry is a difficult task during human growth, requiring literally billions of cell reproductions while maintaining a parallel structure, achieving symmetry is a visible signal of genetic health.

Studies have also suggested that women at peak [[fertility]] were more likely to fantasize about men with greater facial symmetry,&lt;ref name=tws19janab&gt;{{Cite news |author=Tim Radford |title=How women dream of symmetrical men |quote=The research once again confirms a hypothesis that beauty is not merely in the eye of the beholder: it is an indicator of genetic fitness. From a choice of computer-generated faces, volunteers routinely choose the most symmetrical as the most attractive. Physical symmetry is interpreted as a sign of good inheritance. And therefore, the theory goes, women in a position to conceive would be more attracted to someone more likely to engender the healthiest offspring. |work=The Guardian |date=17 August 2005 |url=http://www.guardian.co.uk/science/2005/aug/17/genderissues.research |accessdate= 2010-01-19 |location=London}}&lt;/ref&gt; and other studies have found that male symmetry was the only factor that could significantly predict the likelihood of a woman experiencing orgasm during sex. Women with partners possessing greater symmetry reported significantly more copulatory female orgasms than were reported by women with partners possessing low symmetry, even with many potential confounding variables controlled.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |author=Thornhill R, Gangestad SW, Comer R |title=Human female orgasm and mate fluctuating asymmetry |journal=Animal Behaviour |volume=50 |issue=6 |pages=1601–15 |year=1995 |doi=10.1016/0003-3472(95)80014-X |url=http://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/000334729580014X}}&lt;/ref&gt; This finding has been found to hold across different cultures. It has been argued that masculine facial dimorphism (in men) and symmetry in faces are signals advertising genetic quality in potential mates.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |author=Little AC, Jones BC, Waitt C, ''et al.'' |title=Symmetry Is Related to Sexual Dimorphism in Faces: Data Across Culture and Species |journal=PLoS ONE |volume=3 |issue=5 |pages=e2106 |year=2008 |pmid=18461131 |pmc=2329856 |doi=10.1371/journal.pone.0002106 |url=http://dx.plos.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0002106 |editor1-last=Reimchen |editor1-first=Thomas}}&lt;/ref&gt; Low facial and body [[fluctuating asymmetry]] may indicate good health and intelligence, which are desirable features.&lt;ref name=tws19janbc/&gt; Studies have found that women who perceive themselves as being more physically attractive are more likely to favor men with a higher degree of facial symmetry, than are women who perceive themselves as being less physically attractive.&lt;ref name=&quot;Proc Biol Sci 1462&quot;/&gt; It has been found that symmetrical men (and women) have a tendency to begin to have [[sexual intercourse]] at an earlier age, to have more sexual partners, and to have more [[one-night stand]]s. They are also more likely to be prone to [[infidelity]].&lt;ref name=Etcoff00&gt;{{cite book |author=Nancy Etcoff |title=Survival of the Prettiest: The Science of Beauty |publisher= |location= |year=2000 |isbn= |pages=50–3, 185–7 }}&lt;/ref&gt; A study of quarterbacks in the National Football League found a positive correlation between facial symmetry and salaries.&lt;ref name=twsO54&gt;{{cite news
 |author= DAVID J. BERRI
 |title= Do Pretty-Boy Quarterbacks Make More Money?
 |publisher= ''The New York Times''
 |quote= Research, though, has indicated that what we think of as facial attractiveness is really just facial symmetry.
 |date= September 16, 2008
 |url= http://www.nytimes.com/2008/09/14/sports/playmagazine/0914play-FBALL-QBS.html
 |accessdate= 2011-07-15
}}&lt;/ref&gt;

====Body scent====
A number of double-blind studies have found that women prefer the scent of men who are rated as facially attractive.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |author=Haselton MG, Gangestad SW |title=Conditional expression of women's desires and men's mate guarding across the ovulatory cycle |journal=Horm Behav |volume=49 |issue=4 |pages=509–18 |year=2006 |month=April |pmid=16403409 |doi=10.1016/j.yhbeh.2005.10.006 |url=http://linkinghub.elsevier.com/retrieve/pii/S0018-506X(05)00256-4}}&lt;/ref&gt; For example, a study by Anja Rikowski and Karl Grammer had individuals rate the scent of t-shirts slept in by test subjects. The photographs of those subjects were independently rated, and Rikowski and Grammar found that both males and females were more attracted to the natural scent of individuals who had been rated by consensus as facially attractive.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |author=Rikowski A, Grammer K |title=Human body odour, symmetry and attractiveness |journal=Proc. Biol. Sci. |volume=266 |issue=1422 |pages=869–74 |year=1999 |month=May |pmid=10380676 |pmc=1689917 |doi=10.1098/rspb.1999.0717 |url=http://rspb.royalsocietypublishing.org/cgi/pmidlookup?view=long&amp;pmid=10380676}}&lt;/ref&gt; Additionally, it has also been shown that women have a preference for the scent of men with more symmetrical faces, and that women's preference for the scent of more symmetrical men is strongest during the most fertile period of their menstrual cycle. Within the set of normally cycling women, individual women's preference for the scent of men with high facial symmetry correlated with their probability of conception.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |author=Gangestad SW, Thornhill R |title=Menstrual cycle variation in women's preferences for the scent of symmetrical men |journal=Proc. Biol. Sci. |volume=265 |issue=1399 |pages=927–33 |year=1998 |month=May |pmid=9633114 |pmc=1689051 |doi=10.1098/rspb.1998.0380 |url=http://rspb.royalsocietypublishing.org/cgi/pmidlookup?view=long&amp;pmid=9633114}}&lt;/ref&gt;

====Genetics====
{{See also|Heterozygote advantage|Major Histocompatibility Complex and Sexual Selection}}
New studies are exploring the genetic basis behind such issues as facial symmetry and body scent and how they influence physical attraction. In one study in which women wore men's T-shirts, researchers found that women were more attracted to the bodily scents in shirts of men who had a different type of gene section within the DNA called [[Major histocompatibility complex|Major histocompatibility complex (MHC)]].&lt;ref name=twsYuiu&gt;{{cite news
 |title= The laws of sexual attraction
 |publisher= ''CNN''
 |quote= ... when women are ovulating, they produce copulins, a scent that attracts men....
 |date= April 13, 2009
 |url= http://articles.cnn.com/2009-04-13/living/o.laws.of.sex.attraction_1_attraction-mhc-testosterone-levels?_s=PM:LIVING
 |accessdate= 2011-07-25
}}&lt;/ref&gt; MHC is a large gene area within the DNA of [[vertebrate]]s which encodes proteins dealing with the [[immune system]]&lt;ref name=twsYc1/&gt; and which influences individual bodily odors.&lt;ref name=twsJunY454&gt;{{cite news
 |author= Razib Khan in Genetics
 |title= Taking the pill might make your brother hawt?
 |publisher= ''Discover Magazine''
 |quote= Previous studies in animals and humans show that genes in the major histocompatibility complex (MHC) influence individual odours and that females often prefer odour of MHC-dissimilar males, perhaps to increase offspring heterozygosity or reduce inbreeding. Women using oral hormonal contraceptives have been reported to have the opposite preference, raising the possibility that oral contraceptives alter female preference towards MHC similarity, with possible fertility costs.
 |date= August 16, 2008
 |url= http://blogs.discovermagazine.com/gnxp/2008/08/taking-the-pill-might-make-your-brother-hawt/
 |accessdate= 2011-07-25
}}&lt;/ref&gt; One hypothesis is that humans are naturally attracted by the sense of smell and taste to others with ''dissimilar'' MHC sections, perhaps to avoid subsequent [[inbreeding]] while increasing the genetic diversity of offspring.&lt;ref name=twsYc1&gt;{{cite news
 |title= Google Science Fair semi-finalist: I can taste your DNA
 |publisher= ''The Guardian''
 |quote= the Major Histocompatibility Complex (MHC) is a large gene family found in most vertebrates....
 |date= 2011-07-25
 |url= http://www.guardian.co.uk/science/punctuated-equilibrium/2011/may/11/2
 |accessdate= 2011-07-25
}}&lt;/ref&gt; Further, there are studies showing that women's natural attraction for men with dissimilar immune profiles can be distorted with use of birth control pills.&lt;ref name=twsJunY454/&gt; Other research findings involving the genetic foundations of attraction suggest that MHC heterozygosity positively correlates with male facial attractiveness.  Women judge the faces of men who are heterozygous at all three MHC loci to be more attractive than the faces of men who are homozygous at one or more of these loci. Additionally, a second experiment with genotyped women raters, found these preferences were independent of the degree of MHC [[Interpersonal attraction#Similarity (like-attracts-like)|similarity]] between the men and the female rater. With MHC heterozygosity independently seen as a genetic advantage, the results suggest that facial attractiveness in men may be a measure of genetic quality.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |author=Roberts SC, Little AC, Gosling LM, Perrett DI, Carter V, Jones BC, Penton-Voak I, Petrie M |title=MHC-heterozygosity and human facial attractiveness |journal=Evol Hum Behav |volume=26 |issue=3 |pages=213–226 |date=May 2005 |doi=10.1016/j.evolhumbehav.2004.09.002 |url=http://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S1090513804000789}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |author=Penn DJ, Damjanovich K, Potts WK |title=MHC heterozygosity confers a selective advantage against multiple-strain infections |journal=Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. U.S.A. |volume=99 |issue=17 |pages=11260–4 |year=2002 |month=August |pmid=12177415 |pmc=123244 |doi=10.1073/pnas.162006499 |url=http://www.pnas.org/cgi/pmidlookup?view=long&amp;pmid=12177415}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Youth===
For the Romans especially, &quot;beardlessness&quot; and &quot;smooth young bodies&quot; were considered beautiful to both men and women.&lt;ref name=&quot;Williams&quot;&gt;Williams, C. A. (1999). Roman homosexuality: ideologies of masculinity in classical antiquity. Oxford University Press, USA.&lt;/ref&gt; For Greek and Roman men, the most desirable traits of boys were their &quot;youth&quot; and &quot;hairlessness&quot;. Pubescent boys were considered a socially appropriate object of male desire, while post-pubescent boys were considered to be &quot;ἔξωροι&quot; or &quot;past the prime&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;Williams&quot;/&gt; This was largely in the context of [[pederastry]] (adult male interest in adolescent boys).

Today, men and women's attitudes towards male beauty has changed. For example, body hair on men may even be preferred (see below).

===Waist-to-chest ratio===
The [[mesomorphic]] physique of a slim waist, broad shoulders and muscular chest are often found to be attractive.&lt;ref name=&quot;Archives of Sexual Behavior&quot;&gt;{{cite journal |author=Horvath T |title=Physical attractiveness: the influence of selected torso parameters |journal=Arch Sex Behav |volume=10 |issue=1 |pages=21–4 |year=1981 |month=February |pmid=7212994 | doi=10.1007/BF01542671 }}&lt;/ref&gt; When asked to rate other men, both heterosexual and homosexual men found low waist-to-chest ratios (WCR) to be more attractive on other men with the gay men showing a preference for lower WCR (more V-shaped) than the straight men.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |author=Swami V, Tovée MJ |title=The Muscular Male: A Comparison of the Physical Attractiveness Preferences of Gay and Heterosexual Men |journal=International Journal of Men's Health |volume=7 |issue=1 |pages=59–71 |year=2008 |doi=10.3149/jmh.0701.59 |url=http://mensstudies.metapress.com/content/82q0r82475q38h50/}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Genitalia===
Studies based in China, England, the United States, Italy, New Zealand, Sweden, Spain, and France have suggested that women consider men more attractive whose erect [[penis]] is longer and thicker.&lt;ref name=MPaley&gt;{{Cite book |last=Paley |first=Maggie |title=The Book of the Penis |origyear=2000 |edition=first |year=2000 |publisher=Grove Press |location=New York |pages=232, 16–19 |isbn= 0802116485}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Height and erect posture===
Females' sexual attraction towards males may be determined by the [[Human height|height]] of the man.&lt;ref name=&quot;Pierce&quot;&gt;Pierce, C.A. 1996; Cunningham, M.R. 1990; Pawlowski B, Dunbar RI, Lipowicz A 2000.&lt;/ref&gt; Height in men is associated with status or wealth in many cultures (in particular those where malnutrition is common),&lt;ref name=&quot;height&quot;/&gt; which is beneficial to women romantically involved with them. One study conducted of women's personal ads support the existence of this preference; the study found that in ads requesting height in a mate, 80% requested a height of {{convert|6.00|ft|m}}  or taller.&lt;ref name=&quot;height&quot;/&gt; However, this percentage was only of ads specifying height, and therefore possibly self-selected and/or biased by a third factor such as female height. Recent studies have shown that heterosexual women often prefer men taller than they are, rather than a man with above average height. While women usually desire men to be at least the same height as themselves or taller, several other factors also determine male attractiveness, and the male-taller norm is not universal.&lt;ref name=Sear09&gt;{{cite journal |author=Sear R, Marlowe FW |title=How universal are human mate choices? Size does not matter when Hadza foragers are choosing a mate |journal=Biol. Lett. |volume=5 |issue=5 |pages=606–9 |year=2009 |month=October |pmid=19570778 |pmc=2781963 |doi=10.1098/rsbl.2009.0342 |url=http://rsbl.royalsocietypublishing.org/cgi/pmidlookup?view=long&amp;pmid=19570778}}&lt;/ref&gt; In certain non-Western cultures, the relative heights of partners have been shown to be irrelevant in their choice of mate, which suggests that Western height preferences may be sociocultural, rather than genetic, in nature.&lt;ref name=Sear09/&gt; Professor Adam Eyre-Walker, from the [[University of Sussex]], stated that there is, as yet, no evidence that these preferences are evolutionary preferences, as opposed to merely cultural preferences.&lt;ref&gt;[http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/health/2190461.stm Tall men 'top husband stakes']. BBC News. Retrieved 15 October 2009.&lt;/ref&gt;

Additionally, women seem more receptive to an erect posture than men, though both prefer it as an element of [[beauty]].&lt;ref name=&quot;height&quot;&gt;{{Cite book |last=Buss |first=David |title=The Evolution of Desire |origyear=1994 |edition=second |year=2003 |publisher=Basic Books |location=New York |pages=38–40 |isbn=0465077501}}&lt;/ref&gt; According to one study (Yee N., 2002), gay men who identify as &quot;Only [[Top, bottom and versatile#Top|Tops]]&quot; tend to prefer shorter men, while gay men who identify as &quot;Only [[Top, bottom and versatile#Bottom|Bottoms]]&quot; tend to prefer taller men.&lt;ref name=&quot;Yee&quot;&gt;Yee, N. (2002). Beyond Tops and Bottoms Correlations between Sex-Role Preference and Physical Preferences for Partners among Gay Men&lt;/ref&gt;

===Hairiness===
Studies based in the United States, New Zealand, and China have shown that women rate men with no body hair as most attractive, and that attractiveness ratings decline as [[hirsutism]] increases.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |author=Dixson BJ, Dixson AF, Bishop PJ, Parish A |title=Human Physique and Sexual Attractiveness in Men and Women: A New Zealand-U.S. Comparative Study |journal=Arch Sex Behav |volume=39 |issue=3 |pages=798–806 |year=2010 |doi=10.1007/s10508-008-9441-y |url=http://www.springerlink.com/content/y520080w61511h1m/ |pmid=19139985}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |author=Dixson BJ, Dixson AF, Li B, Anderson MJ |title=Studies of human physique and sexual attractiveness: sexual preferences of men and women in China |journal=Am. J. Hum. Biol. |volume=19 |issue=1 |pages=88–95 |year=2007 |pmid=17160976 |doi=10.1002/ajhb.20584 |url=http://www3.interscience.wiley.com/journal/113509376/abstract}}&lt;/ref&gt; Another study, however, found that moderate amounts of trunk hair on men was most attractive, to the sample of British and Sri Lankan women.&lt;ref name=hirsute/&gt; Further, a degree of hirsuteness (hairiness) and a waist-to-shoulder ratio of 0.6 is often preferred, when combined with a mesomorphic physique.&lt;ref name=hirsute&gt;{{cite journal |author=Dixson AF, Halliwell G, East R, Wignarajah P, Anderson MJ |title=Masculine somatotype and hirsuteness as determinants of sexual attractiveness to women |journal=Arch Sex Behav |volume=32 |issue=1 |pages=29–39 |year=2003 |month=February |pmid=12597270 |url=http://www.kluweronline.com/art.pdf?issn=0004-0002&amp;volume=32&amp;page=29 |doi=10.1023/A:1021889228469}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In a study using Finnish women, women with hairy fathers were more likely to prefer hairy men, suggesting that preference for hairy men is either the result of genetics or imprinting.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |author=Rantala MJ, Pölkki M, Rantala LM |title=Preference for human male body hair changes across the menstrual cycle and menopause |journal=Behavioral Ecology |volume=21 |issue=2 |pages=419–423 |year=2010 |doi=10.1093/beheco/arp206 |url=http://beheco.oxfordjournals.org/content/21/2/419.abstract}}&lt;/ref&gt; Among gay men, another study (Yee N., 2002) reported gay males who identify as  &quot;Only [[Top, bottom and versatile#Top|Tops]]&quot; prefer less hairy men, while gay males who identify as &quot;Only [[Top, bottom and versatile#Bottom|Bottoms]]&quot; prefer hairier men.&lt;ref name=&quot;Yee&quot; /&gt;

===Skin color===
Testosterone has been shown to darken skin color in laboratory experiments.&lt;ref&gt;Robins, A.H. (1991). Biological perspectives on human pigmentation. Cambridge University Press&lt;/ref&gt; In his foreword to [[Peter Frost (anthropologist)|Peter Frost]]'s 2005 ''Fair Women, Dark Men'', [[University of Washington]] sociologist Pierre L. van den Berghe writes: &quot;Although virtually all cultures express a marked preference for fair female skin, even those with little or no exposure to European imperialism, and even those whose members are heavily pigmented, many are indifferent to male pigmentation or even prefer men to be darker.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;Sailer&quot;/&gt;

According one study (Yee N., 2002), gay men who identify as &quot;Only Tops&quot; tend to prefer lighter-skinned men while gay men who identify as &quot;Only Bottoms&quot; tend to prefer darker-skinned men.&lt;ref name=&quot;Yee&quot; /&gt;

More recent research has suggested that redder and yellower skin tones,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|last=Stephen|first=Ian|coauthors=Law Smith, M.J., Stirrat, M.R., Perrett, D.I.|title=Facial skin coloration affects perceived health of human faces|journal=International Journal of Primatology|year=2009|volume=30|issue=6|pages=845-857|doi=10.1007/s10764-009-9380-z}}&lt;/ref&gt; reflecting higher levels of oxygenated blood&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|last=Stephen|first=Ian|coauthors=Coetzee, V., Law Smith, M.J., Perrett, D.I.|title=Skin blood perfusion and oxygenation affect perceived human health|journal=PLoS ONE|year=2009|volume=4|pages=e5083|doi:10.1371/journal.pone.0005083}}&lt;/ref&gt;, melanin pigment and net dietary intakes of fruit and vegetables,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|last=Stephen|first=Ian|coauthors=Coetzee, V., Perrett, D.I.|title=Carotenoid and melanin pigment coloration affect perceived human health|journal=Evolution and Human Behavior|year=2011|volume=32|pages=216-227|doi:10.1016/j.evolhumbehav.2010.09.003}}&lt;/ref&gt; appears healthier, and therefore more attractive.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|last=Jones|first=Ben|coauthors=Little, A.C., Burt, D.M., Perrett, D.I.|title=When facial attractiveness is only skin deep|journal=Perception|year=2004|volume=33|pages=569-576|doi=10.1068/p3463}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Female physical attractiveness==
{{double image|right|Betty_Boop_patent_fig1.jpg|100|Betty_Boop_patent_fig2.jpg|100|Physical anthropologist [[Barry Bogin]] considers [[Betty Boop]] to be an example of neoteny.&lt;ref name=&quot;Bogin&quot;&gt;Bogin, B. (1999). Patterns of Human Growth. Cambridge University Press, NY.&lt;/ref&gt;}}
Attractiveness research indicates that men tend to be attracted to young&lt;ref name=&quot;youth&quot;&gt;{{Cite book |last=Buss |first=David |title=The Evolution of Desire |origyear=1994 |edition=second |year=2003 |publisher=Basic Books |location=New York |pages=51–4 |isbn=0465077501}}&lt;/ref&gt; and beautiful women&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |author=Browne KR |title=Sex, Power, and Dominance: The Evolutionary Psychology of Sexual Harassment |journal=Managerial and Decision Economics |volume=27 |pages=145–158 |year=2006 |doi=10.1002/mde.1289 |issue=2–3 }}&lt;/ref&gt; with bodily symmetry.&lt;ref name=twsO66f4b&gt;{{cite news
 |author= IAN TATTERSALL (book reviewer) Geoffrey Miller (author)
 |title= Whatever Turns You On: A psychologist looks at sexual attraction and what it means for humankind.
 |publisher= ''The New York Times: Book Review''
 |quote= it turns out that symmetry of bodily structure is a fitness indicator, and symmetry is more easily detectable among large breasts than small ones.
 |date= June 11, 2000
 |url= http://www.nytimes.com/books/00/06/11/reviews/000611.11tattert.html
 |accessdate= 2011-07-15
}}&lt;/ref&gt; Rather than decreasing it, modernity has only increased the emphasis men place on women's looks.&lt;ref name=&quot;Jackson&quot;&gt;Jackson, L. B. (1992). Physical appearance and gender: sociobiological and sociocultural perspectives. State University of New York Press.&lt;/ref&gt; [[Evolutionary psychology|Evolutionary psychologist]]s attribute such attraction to an evaluation of the [[fertility]] potential in a prospective mate.&lt;ref name=&quot;youth&quot;/&gt;

===Facial features===
[[File:Jessica Alba Face Proportions.png|thumb|right|A [[University of Toronto]] study found that ideal facial proportions were close to the average of all female profiles.&lt;ref name=twsZE23&gt;{{cite news
 |author= Fiona Macrae
 |title= Skin deep: Beautiful faces have Miss Average proportions
 |publisher= ''Daily Mail''
 |quote= All were head shots of the same person with different distances from eyes to mouth or between the eyes. She was at her most attractive when the space between her pupils was just under half, or 46 per cent, of the width of her face from ear to ear. The other perfect dimension was when the distance between her eyes and mouth was just over a third, or 36 per cent, of the overall length of her face from hairline to chin. ...
 |date= 27 December 2009
 |url= http://www.dailymail.co.uk/sciencetech/article-1236636/Skin-deep-Beautiful-faces-Miss-Average-proportions.html
 |accessdate= 2011-07-31
}}&lt;/ref&gt;]]
{{See also|Cuteness|Koinophilia}}

Attractiveness research has attempted to determine which facial aspects communicate attractiveness. Facial symmetry has been shown to be considered attractive in women,&lt;ref name=&quot;Berscheid&quot;&gt;Berscheid and Reis, 1998&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Fink&quot;&gt;{{cite journal |author=Fink B, Penton-Voak IS |title=Evolutionary Psychology of Facial Attractiveness |journal=Current Directions in Psychological Science |volume=11 |issue=5 |pages=154–8 |year=2002 |doi=10.1111/1467-8721.00190 |url=http://cdp.sagepub.com/content/11/5/154}}&lt;/ref&gt; and men have been found to prefer full lips,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|first=Louann |last=Brizendine|title=The female brain|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=dGfQ2TMB1lIC&amp;pg=PA63 |year=2006|publisher=Random House Digital, Inc.|isbn=978-0-7679-2010-0|pages=63}}&lt;/ref&gt; clear smooth skin, and clear eyes.&lt;ref name=&quot;youth&quot;/&gt; The shape of the face in terms of &quot;how everything hangs together&quot; is an important determinant of beauty.&lt;ref name=twsO66f4a/&gt; A [[University of Toronto]] study found correlations between facial measurements and attractiveness; researchers varied the distance between eyes, and between eyes and mouth, in different drawings of the same female face, and had the drawings evaluated; they found there were ideal proportions perceived as attractive (see photo).&lt;ref name=twsZE23/&gt; These proportions (46% and 36%) were close to the average of all female profiles.&lt;ref name=twsZE23/&gt; Women with thick, dark [[limbal ring]]s in their eyes have also been found to be more attractive. The explanation given is that because the ring tends to fade with age and medical problems, a prominent limbal ring gives an honest indicator of youth.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.psychologytoday.com/blog/love-sex-and-babies/201104/how-big-is-your-limbal-ring How Big Is Your Limbal Ring? | Psychology Today&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt; 

In another cross-cultural study, more [[Neoteny|neotenized]] (i.e., youthful looking) female faces were found to be most attractive to men while less neotenized female faces were found to be less attractive to men, regardless of the females' actual age.&lt;ref&gt;Jones, D. Sexual Selection, Physical Attractiveness and Facial Neoteny: Cross-Cultural Evidence and Implications. p.723&lt;/ref&gt; One of these desired traits was a small jaw.&lt;ref name=&quot;Kohl&quot;&gt;{{cite journal |author=Kohl JV |title=The Mind's Eyes: Human Pheromones, Neuroscience, and Male Sexual Preferences |journal=Psychology &amp; Human Sexuality |volume=18 |issue=4 |pages=313–369 |year=2006 |doi= |url=http://www2.hu-berlin.de/sexology/BIB/kohl.htm}}&lt;/ref&gt; In a study of Italian women who have won beauty competitions, it was found that their faces had more &quot;babyness&quot; traits than those of the &quot;normal&quot; women used as a reference.&lt;ref name=&quot;Chiarella&quot;&gt;{{cite journal |author=Sforza C, Laino A, D'Alessio R, Grandi G, Binelli M, Ferrario VF |title=Soft-tissue facial characteristics of attractive Italian women as compared to normal women |journal=Angle Orthod |volume=79 |issue=1 |pages=17–23 |year=2009 |month=January |pmid=19123721 |doi=10.2319/122707-605.1 |url=http://www.angle.org/doi/full/10.2319/122707-605.1}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Michael R. Cunningham of the Department of Psychology at the [[University of Louisville]] found, using a panel of &quot;Asian&quot;, &quot;Hispanic&quot; and &quot;White&quot; judges, that the &quot;Asian&quot;, &quot;Hispanic&quot; and &quot;White&quot; female faces found most attractive were those that had &quot;neonate large eyes, greater distance between eyes, and small noses&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;Cunningham&quot; /&gt; and his study led him to conclude that &quot;large eyes&quot; were the most &quot;effective&quot; of the &quot;neonate cues&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;Cunningham&quot; /&gt; Cunningham also said that &quot;shiny&quot; hair may be indicative of &quot;neonate vitality&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;Cunningham&quot; /&gt; Using a panel of &quot;Blacks&quot; and &quot;Whites&quot; as judges, Cunningham found more neotenous faces were perceived as having both higher &quot;femininity&quot; and &quot;sociability&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;Cunningham&quot; /&gt; In contrast, Cunningham found that faces that were &quot;low in neoteny&quot; were judged as &quot;intimidating&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;Cunningham&quot; /&gt; Cunningham noted a &quot;difference&quot; in the preferences of &quot;Asian&quot; and &quot;White&quot; judges with &quot;Asian&quot; judges preferring women with &quot;less mature faces&quot; and smaller mouths than the &quot;White&quot; judges.&lt;ref name=&quot;Cunningham&quot; /&gt; Cunningham hypothesized that this difference in preference may stem from &quot;ethnocentrism&quot; since &quot;Asian faces possess those qualities&quot;, so Cunningham re-analyzed the data with &quot;11 Asian targets excluded&quot; and concluded that &quot;ethnocentrism was not a primary determinant of Asian preferences.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;Cunningham&quot; /&gt; Rather than finding evidence for purely &quot;neonate&quot; faces being most appealing, Cunningham found faces with &quot;sexually-mature&quot; features at the &quot;periphery&quot; of the face combined with &quot;neonate&quot; features in the &quot;center of the face&quot; most appealing in men and women.&lt;ref name=&quot;Cunningham&quot; /&gt; Upon analyzing the results of his study Cunningham concluded that preference for &quot;neonate features may display the least cross-cultural variability&quot; in terms of &quot;attractiveness ratings&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;Cunningham&quot;/&gt; and, in another study, Cunningham concluded that there exists a large agreement on the characteristics of an attractive face.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |author=Cunningham MR |title=Measuring the Physical in Physical Attractiveness: Quasi-Experiments on the Sociobiology of Female Facial Beauty |journal=Journal of Personality and Social Psychology |volume=50 |issue=5 |pages=925–935 |year=May 1986 |doi=10.1037/0022-3514.50.5.925 |url=}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;From Cunningham (1986) Research with Western subjects disclosed significant consistency in evaluating attractiveness (Hatfield &amp; Sprecher, 1986; Iliife, 1960). The females judged to be most attractive may have such similar facial features that they were hard to distinguish one from another (Light, Hollander, &amp; Kayra-Stuart, 1981). Cross-cultural investigations on the judgment of facial attractiveness tended to highlight societal differences, but rough agreements in facial aesthetic preferences were shown by Asian-American and Caucasian females (Wagatsuma &amp; Kleinke, 1979), Chinese, Indian, and English females judging Greek males (Thakerar &amp; Iwawaki, 1979), South African and American males and females (Morse, Gruzen, &amp; Reis, 1976), and blacks and whites judging males and females from both races (Cross &amp; Cross, 1971).&lt;/ref&gt;

In computer face averaging tests, women with [[Averageness|averaged]] faces have been shown to be considered more attractive.&lt;ref name=twsO53&gt;{{cite news
 |author= Clare Murphy
 |title= In the eye of the beholder?
 |publisher= ''BBC News''
 |quote= Art historians, anthropologists and human psychologists in general agree that it is the symmetry of a face, its perfect proportion, or indeed its averageness — where no feature stands out — that has consistently down the ages been deemed attractive. ...
 |date= 4 December 2003
 |url= http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/3291271.stm
 |accessdate= 2011-07-15
}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;evolution&quot;&gt;{{Cite book |last=Buss |first=David |title=The Evolution of Desire |origyear=1994 |edition=second |year=2003 |publisher=Basic Books |location=New York |pages=54, 55 |isbn=0465077501}}&lt;/ref&gt; This is possibly due to average features being more familiar and, therefore, more comfortable.&lt;ref name=&quot;Berscheid&quot;/&gt;

Commenting on the prevalence of whiteness in supposed beauty ideals in his book ''White Lies: Race and the Myth of Whiteness'', [[Maurice Berger]] notes that the schematic rendering in the idealized face of a notable study conducted with American subjects had &quot;straight hair,&quot; &quot;light skin,&quot; &quot;almond-shaped eyes,&quot; &quot;thin, arched eyebrows,&quot; &quot;a long, thin nose, closely set and tiny nostrils&quot; and &quot;a large mouth and thin lips&quot;,&lt;ref name=&quot;Berger&quot;&gt;Berger, M. (1999). White lies: race and the myths of whiteness. Farrar, Strous and Giroux, Canada.&lt;/ref&gt; though the author of the study noted the consistency between his results and those conducted on other races.

One psychologist speculated there were two opposing principles of female beauty: prettiness and rarity. So on average, symmetrical features are one ideal, while unusual, stand-out features are another.&lt;ref name= tws6nov09&gt;{{Cite news |author=John Tierney |title=The Waif From Ipanema |quote=women's aesthetic judgments are so influenced by other women. Men prefer the wider hips, and most likely could care less about high heels and handbags. Yet for many women all these things are essential to marking their beauty status with other women |work=New York Times |date=January 18, 2007 |url=http://tierneylab.blogs.nytimes.com/2007/01/18/the-waif-from-ipanema/ |accessdate=2009-11-06}}&lt;/ref&gt; A study performed by the University of Toronto found that the most attractive facial dimensions were those found in the average female face. However, that particular University of Toronto study looked only at white women.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news |url=http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/health/8421076.stm |work=BBC News |title=Perfect face dimensions measured |date=2009-12-18 |accessdate=2010-05-22}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Youthfulness===

Cross-cultural data shows that the reproductive success of women is tied to their youth and physical attractiveness&lt;ref&gt;Hechter, M. (2011). Social Norms. Russell Sage Foundation. pp. 300&lt;/ref&gt; such as the pre-industrial [[Sami people|Sami]] where the most reproductively successful women were 15 years younger than their man.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |author=Biello D |title=What is the Best Age Difference for Husband and Wife? |date=5 December 2007 |publisher=Scientific American |url=http://www.scientificamerican.com/article.cfm?id=what-is-the-best-age-difference-for-husband-and-wife}}&lt;/ref&gt; One study covering 37 cultures showed that, on average, a woman was 2.5 years younger than her male partner, with the age difference in Nigeria and Zambia being at the far extreme of 6.5 to 7.5 years. As men age, they tend to seek a mate who is even younger.&lt;ref name=&quot;youth&quot;/&gt; The common explanation for this preference is that men have evolved to be attracted to women with high child-bearing potential and therefore prefer young women. In a study performed in the United States using male college students, the mean age expressed as ideal for a wife was to be 16.87 years old, while 17.76 was the mean ideal age for a brief sexual encounter.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |author=Young JA, Critelli JW, Keith KW |title=Male age preferences for short-term and long-term mating  |journal=Sexualities, Evolution &amp; Gender |volume=7 |issue=2 |pages=83–93 |year=2005 |doi=10.1080/14616660500035090 |url=http://www.tandfonline.com/doi/abs/10.1080/14616660500035090}}&lt;/ref&gt; In a study of male penile tumescence, men were found most aroused by pictures of young adult females.&lt;ref name=&quot;Quinsey&quot;&gt;Quinsey, V.L. The Etiology of Anomalous Sexual Preferences in Men. Queen's University Department of Psychology.&lt;/ref&gt; According to cultural anthropologist Dr. Paula E. Drew who has held tenured positions at two universities in Iran, &quot;Many (Iranian men) speak openly, with disgust and derision, of the effects of pregnancy and the aging process on the female body.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Drew, P.E. Iran. Jomhoori-Islam-Iran. Retrieved June 12, 2011, from http://www2.hu-berlin.de/sexology/IES/iran.html&lt;/ref&gt;

===Breasts===

Research has shown some that men enjoy viewing women's [[breasts]],&lt;ref name=dailytelegraph&gt;[http://www.dailytelegraph.com.au/lifestyle/scientific-proof-that-men-look-at-womens-breasts-first-and-their-face-is-almost-last/story-e6frf00i-1225770286482 Scientific proof that men look at women's breasts first and their face is almost last ] ''[[The Daily Telegraph]]''&lt;/ref&gt; and another study showed that men prefer symmetrical breasts&lt;ref name=twsO66f4b/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|author=Joann Ellison Rodgers|title=Sex: A Natural History|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=eJutAwmKCPEC&amp;pg=PA102 |year=2003|publisher=Macmillan|isbn=978-0-8050-7281-5|pages=102}}&lt;/ref&gt; but some studies show men preferring large, firm breasts,&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.uoregon.edu/~sugiyama/docs/LSsugiyama-buss_c09CEforrequests.pdf ''Physical Attractiveness in Adaptationist Perspective''] in ''Evolutionary Psychology Handbook'', Lawrence S. Sugiyama (2005).&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Buss, David M.''The Handbook of Evolutionary Psychology'', John Wiley and Sons, 2005, pg. 325 ISBN 0-471-26403-2, 9780471264033&lt;/ref&gt; while a contradictory study of British undergraduates found men preferring small breasts on women.&lt;ref name=&quot;Furnham&quot;&gt;{{cite journal |author=Furnham A, Swami V |title=Perception of female buttocks and breast size in profile |journal=Soc Behav Pers |volume=35 |issue=1 |pages=1–8 |year=2007 |doi= 10.2224/sbp.2007.35.1.1|url=http://www.sbp-journal.com/default.aspx?pageid=46&amp;JournalArticleID=1657}}&lt;/ref&gt; Cross-culturally, another study found &quot;high variability&quot; regarding the ideal breast size.&lt;ref name=&quot;Furnham&quot; /&gt; Some researchers have speculated that a preference for larger breasts may have developed in Western societies, because women with larger breasts tend to have higher levels of the hormones [[Estradiol|oestradial]] and [[progesterone]], which both promote fertility.&lt;ref&gt;[http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/health/3682657.stm Hourglass figure fertility link - BBC News]&lt;/ref&gt;

Breast symmetry may be particularly sensitive to developmental disturbances and the symmetry differences for breasts are large compared to other body parts. Women who have more symmetrical breasts tend to have more children.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite doi|10.3390/sym2021081}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Buttocks===
Biological anthropologist, [[Helen Fisher (anthropologist)|Helen B. Fisher]] of the Center for Human Evolution Studies in the Department of Anthropology of [[Rutgers University]], said that, &quot;perhaps&quot;, &quot;the fleshy, rounded [[buttocks]]... attracted males during [[Sex positions#Penetrating from behind|rear-entry intercourse]].&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Fisher, H.B. (1982). The Sex Contract - The Evolution of Human Behavior. New York: William Morrow &amp; Company, Inc.&lt;/ref&gt; Bobbi S. Low et al. of the School of Natural Resources and Environment at the [[University of Michigan]], said the female &quot;buttocks evolved in the context of females competing for the attention and parental commitment of powerful resource-controlling males&quot; as an &quot;honest display of fat reserves&quot; that could not be confused with another type of tissue,&lt;ref name=&quot;Caro&quot; /&gt; although T. M. Caro, professor in the Center for Population Biology and the Department of Wildlife, Fish, and Conservation Biology, at [[University of California, Davis]], rejected that as being a necessary conclusion, stating that female fatty deposits on the hips improve &quot;individual [[Fitness (biology)|fitness]] of the female&quot;, regardless of [[sexual selection]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Caro&quot;&gt;Caro, T.M. &amp; D. W. Sellen, D.W. (1990). The Reproductive Advantages of Fat in Women. Ethology and Sociobiology. (11)5 1-66 0162-3095&lt;/ref&gt;

===Body mass===
[[File:Betty Grable 20th Century Fox.jpg|200px|left|thumb|[[Betty Grable]]'s iconic [[pin-up girl]] photo, popular among [[G.I. (military)|GIs]] fighting in [[World War II]]]]
[[Body Mass Index]] (BMI) is an important determinant to the perception of beauty.&lt;ref name=&quot;Toove&quot;&gt;{{cite journal |author=Tovée MJ, Reinhardt S, Emery JL, Cornelissen PL |title=Optimum body-mass index and maximum sexual attractiveness |journal=Lancet |volume=352 |issue=9127 |pages=548 |year=1998 |month=August |pmid=9716069 |doi=10.1016/S0140-6736(05)79257-6 }}&lt;/ref&gt; Even though the Western ideal is for a thin woman, some cultures prefer plumper women,&lt;ref name=&quot;Cunningham&quot;&gt;{{cite journal |author=Cunningham MR, Roberts, AR, Barbee, AP, Druen, PB, Wu, CH |title=Their ideas of beauty are, on the whole, the same as ours&quot;: Consistency and variability in the cross-cultural perception of female physical attractiveness |journal=Journal of Personality and Social Psychology |volume=68 |issue=2 |pages=261–279 |date=February 1995 |doi=10.1037/0022-3514.68.2.261 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;build&quot;&gt;{{Cite book |last=Buss |first=David |title=The Evolution of Desire |origyear=1994 |edition=second |year=2003 |publisher=Basic Books |location=New York |pages=55, 56 |isbn=0465077501}}&lt;/ref&gt; so attraction for a particular BMI appears to be merely a cultural artifact.&lt;ref name=&quot;build&quot;/&gt;  The attraction for a proportionate body also influences an appeal for [[Human positions|erect posture]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Furnham&quot;&gt;Furnham, Adrian, Gianna Caroline Fischer, Lauren Tanner, Melanie Dias, and Alastair McClelland 1998.&lt;/ref&gt;

In the United States, women overestimate men's preferences for thinness in a mate. In one study, American women were asked to choose what their ideal build was and what they thought the build most attractive to men was. Women chose slimmer than average figures for both choices. When American men were independently asked to choose the female build most attractive to them, the men chose figures of average build. This indicates that women may be misled as to how thin men prefer women to be.&lt;ref name=&quot;build&quot;/&gt; Some speculate that thinness as a beauty standard is one way in which women judge each other.&lt;ref name=tws6nov09&gt;{{Cite news
| author = John Tierney
| title = The Waif From Ipanema
| quote = women’s aesthetic judgments are so influenced by other women. Men prefer the wider hips, and most likely could care less about high heels and handbags. Yet for many women all these things are essential to marking their beauty status with other women
| publisher = New York Times
| date = January 18, 2007
| url = http://tierneylab.blogs.nytimes.com/2007/01/18/the-waif-from-ipanema/
| accessdate = 2009-11-06
}}&lt;/ref&gt; A reporter surmised that thinness is prized among women as a &quot;sign of independence, strength and achievement.&quot;&lt;ref name=tws6nov09/&gt; Some implicated the fashion industry for the promulgation of the notion of thinness as attractive.&lt;ref name=tws6nov20&gt;{{Cite news
| author = Nanci Hellmich
| title = Do thin models warp girls' body image?
| quote = The widespread concern that model thinness has progressed from willowy to wasted has reached a threshold as evidenced by the recent actions of fashion show organizers.
| publisher = USA TODAY
| date = 2006-09-26
| url = http://www.usatoday.com/news/health/2006-09-25-thin-models_x.htm
| accessdate = 2009-11-06
}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Waist–hip ratio{{anchor|Waist-hip ratio}}===
{{Main|Waist–hip ratio}}
Ethnic groups vary with regard to their ideal waist-to-hip ratio for women,&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal |journal=J Cosmet Dermatol |date=June 2006 |volume=5 |issue=2 |pages=190–4 |title=The shape of beauty: determinants of female physical attractiveness |last=Fisher |first=M.L. |coauthors=Voracek M.|pmid=17173598 |doi=10.1111/j.1473-2165.2006.00249.x}}&lt;/ref&gt; ranging from 0.6 in China,&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal |journal=Am J Hum Biol |date=January 2007 |volume=19 |issue=1 |pages=88–95 |pmid=17160976 |title=Studies of human physique and sexual attractiveness: sexual preferences of men and women in China |last=Dixson |first=B.J. |coauthors=Dixson A.F., Li B., Anderson M.J.|doi=10.1002/ajhb.20584}}&lt;/ref&gt; to 0.8 or 0.9 in parts of South America and Africa,&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal |journal=Personality and Individual Differences |last=Marlowe |first=F. |coauthors=Wetsman, A. |year=2001 |title=Preferred waist-to-hip ratio and ecology |volume=30 |issue=3 |pages=481–489 |accessdate=2007-08-04 |url=http://www.fas.harvard.edu/%7Ehbe-lab/acrobatfiles/preferred%20waist.pdf |doi=10.1016/S0191-8869(00)00039-8 |format=PDF}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |author=Marlowe F, Apicella C, Reed D |title=Men's preferences for women's profile waist-to-hip ratio in two societies |journal=Evol Hum Behav |volume=26 |issue=6 |pages=458–468 |date=November 2005 |doi=10.1016/j.evolhumbehav.2005.07.005 |url=http://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S1090513805000620}} [http://www.fas.harvard.edu/~hbe-lab/acrobatfiles/profilewhr.pdf as PDF]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal |journal=Arch Sex Behav |date=June 2007 |volume=36 |issue=3 |pages=369–75 |title=Human physique and sexual attractiveness: sexual preferences of men and women in Bakossiland, Cameroon |last=Dixson |first=B.J. |coauthors=Dixson A.F., Morgan B., Anderson M.J.|pmid=17136587 |doi=10.1007/s10508-006-9093-8}}&lt;/ref&gt; and divergent preferences based on ethnicity, rather than nationality, have also been noted.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal |journal=Eat Behav |date=August 2007 |volume=8 |issue=3 |pages=319–33 |title=Do men hold African-American and Caucasian women to different standards of beauty? |last=Freedman |first=R.E. |coauthors=Carter M.M., Sbrocco T., Gray JJ.|pmid=17606230 |doi=10.1016/j.eatbeh.2006.11.008 |pmc=3033406}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal |journal=Eat Behav. |date=July 2004 |volume=5 |issue=3 |pages=191–8 |title=Ethnic differences in preferences for female weight and waist-to-hip ratio: a comparison of African-American and White American college and community samples |last=Freedman |first=R.E. |coauthors=Carter M.M., Sbrocco T., Gray J.J.|pmid=15135331 |doi=10.1016/j.eatbeh.2004.01.002}}&lt;/ref&gt; A cross-cultural analysis that found isolated peoples preferring high WHR (0.9) over a low WHR (0.7) suggested that many such &quot;cross-cultural&quot; tests &quot;may have only reflected the pervasiveness of Western media&quot;;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |author=Yu DW, Shepard GH |title=Is beauty in the eye of the beholder? |journal=Nature |volume=396 |issue=6709 |pages=321–2 |year=1998 |month=November |pmid=9845067 |doi=10.1038/24512 |url=http://www.nature.com/nature/journal/v396/n6709/full/396321a0.html}}&lt;/ref&gt; however many evolutionary psychologists believe preference for low WHR is a signal for fertility and biologically based.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |last=Buss |first=David |title=The Evolution of Desire |origyear=1994 |edition=second |year=2003 |publisher=Basic Books |location=New York |page=56 |isbn=0465077501}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Height===

Most men tend to be taller than their female partner.&lt;ref name=autogenerated2&gt;http://www.staff.ncl.ac.uk/daniel.nettle/procroysoc.pdf&lt;/ref&gt; It has been found that, in Western societies, most men prefer shorter women, tend to view taller women as less attractive.&lt;ref name=&quot;Scar&quot;&gt;Scar, R. Height and Reproductive Success: How a Gambian Population Compares to the West. Human Nature Winter 2006.&lt;/ref&gt; and people view couples where the woman is taller to be less ideal.&lt;ref name=&quot;Scar&quot;/&gt; Women who are 0.7 to 1.7 [[standard deviations]] below the mean female height have been reported to be the most reproductively successful,&lt;ref name=autogenerated1&gt;[http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/health/2190461.stm ''BBC News'': &quot;Tall men 'top husband stakes{{'&quot;}}]&lt;/ref&gt; since fewer tall women get married compared to shorter women.&lt;ref name=&quot;Scar&quot; /&gt;

However, in some non-Western cultures, height is irrelevant in choosing a mate, which suggests that the preference among Western men for women shorter than themselves may be sociocultural in nature.&lt;ref name=Sear09/&gt;

===Leg-to-body ratio===

A study using Polish participants by Sorokowski found 5% longer legs than an individual used as a reference was considered most attractive.&lt;ref name=tws19jan&gt;{{cite journal |author=Sorokowskia P, Pawlowskib B |title=Adaptive preferences for leg length in a potential partner |journal=Evol Hum Behav |volume=29 |issue=2 |pages=86–91 |date=March 2008 |doi=10.1016/j.evolhumbehav.2007.09.002 |url=http://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S1090513807000906}}&lt;/ref&gt; The study concluded this preference might stem from the influence of leggy runway models.&lt;ref name=&quot;Sorokowski&quot;&gt;{{cite journal |author=Sorokowski P |title=Attractiveness of Legs Length in Poland and Great Britain |journal=J Hum Ecol |volume=31 |issue=3 |pages=148 |year=2010 |url=http://www.krepublishers.com/02-Journals/JHE/JHE-31-0-000-10-Web/JHE-31-3-000-10-Abst-PDF/JHE-31-3-145-10-1996-Sorokowski-P/JHE-31-3-145-10-1996-Sorokowski-P-Tt.pdf |format=PDF}}&lt;/ref&gt; The Sorokowski study was criticized for using a picture of the same person with digitally altered leg lengths which Dr. Marco Bertamini felt were unrealistic.&lt;ref name=&quot;Bertamini&quot; /&gt;

Another study using British and American participants, found &quot;mid-ranging&quot; leg-to-body ratios to be most ideal.&lt;ref name=&quot;Frederick&quot;&gt;{{cite journal |author=Frederick DA, Hadji-Michael M, Furnham A, Swami V |title=The influence of leg-to-body ratio (LBR) on judgments of female physical attractiveness: assessments of computer-generated images varying in LBR |journal=Body Image |volume=7 |issue=1 |pages=51–5 |year=2010 |month=January |pmid=19822462 |doi=10.1016/j.bodyim.2009.09.001 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

A study by Swami et al. of British male and female undergraduates showed a preference for men with legs as long as the rest of their body and women with 40% longer legs than the rest of their body.&lt;ref name=&quot;Swami&quot;&gt;{{cite journal |author=Swami V, Einon D, Furnham A |title=The leg-to-body ratio as a human aesthetic criterion |journal=Body Image |volume=3 |issue=4 |pages=317–23 |year=2006 |month=December |pmid=18089235 |doi=10.1016/j.bodyim.2006.08.003 }}&lt;/ref&gt; The researcher concluded that this preference might be influenced by American culture where long legged women are portrayed as more attractive.&lt;ref name=&quot;Swami&quot; /&gt; The Swami et al. study was criticized for using a picture of the same person with digitally altered leg lengths which Marco Bertamini felt were unrealistic.&lt;ref name=&quot;Bertamini&quot;&gt;{{cite journal |author=Bertamini M, Bennet KM |title=The effect of leg length on perceived attractiveness of simplified stimuli |journal=Journal of Social, Evolutionary, and Cultural Psychology |volume=3 |issue=3 |pages=233–250 |year=2009 |doi= |url=http://www.liv.ac.uk/vp/Publications/BertaminiBennett2009.pdf |format=PDF}}&lt;/ref&gt; Bertamini also criticized the Swami study for only changing the leg length while keeping the arm length constant.&lt;ref name=&quot;Bertamini&quot; /&gt; Bertamini's own study which used stick figures mirrored Swami's study, however, by finding a preference for leggier women.&lt;ref name=&quot;Bertamini&quot; /&gt;

According to some studies, most men prefer women with small feet,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |author=Barber N |title=The evolutionary psychology of physical attractiveness: Sexual selection and human morphology |journal=Ethology &amp; Sociobiology |volume=19 |issue=5 |pages=395–424 |date=September 1995 |doi=10.1016/0162-3095(95)00068-2 |url=}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |author=Voracek M, Fisher ML, Rupp B, Lucas D, Fessler DM |title=Sex differences in relative foot length and perceived attractiveness of female feet: relationships among anthropometry, physique, and preference ratings |journal=Percept Mot Skills |volume=104 |issue=3 Pt 2 |pages=1123–38 |year=2007 |month=June |pmid=17879647 }}&lt;/ref&gt; such as in ancient China where [[foot binding]] was practiced.&lt;ref&gt;Berman, J.E. (1993). Female Genital Mutilation, Yes, but Don't Condone It. Accessed date November 6, 2009, from http://www.nytimes.com/1993/11/30/opinion/l-understand-female-genital-mutilation-yes-but-don-t-condone-it-015393.html&lt;/ref&gt;

===Hair===
Men have been found to prefer long-haired women.&lt;ref name=&quot;youth&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|first=David M. |last=Buss|title=The handbook of evolutionary psychology|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=esDW3xTKoLIC&amp;pg=PA309 |year=2005|publisher=John Wiley and Sons|isbn=978-0-471-26403-3|pages=309}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Bereczkei&quot;&gt;Bereczkei, T. Hair length, facial attractiveness, personality attribution; A multiple fitness model of hairdressing&lt;/ref&gt; An [[evolutionary psychology]] explanation for this is that malnutrition and deficiencies in minerals and vitamins causes loss of hair or hair changes. Hair therefore indicates health and nutrition during the last 2–3 years. Lustrous hair is also often a cross-cultural preference.&lt;ref name=EPHandbook2005&gt;The Handbook of Evolutionary Psychology, edited by David M. Buss, John Wiley &amp; Sons, Inc., 2005. Chapter 10 &quot;Physical Attractiveness in Adaptationist Perspective&quot; by Lawrence S. Sugiyama.&lt;/ref&gt;

One study reported non-Asian men to prefer blondes and Asian men to prefer black-haired women.&lt;ref name=&quot;Bereczkei&quot; /&gt;

=== Movement patterns ===
The way an individual moves can indicate health and even age and influence attractiveness.&lt;ref name=EPHandbook2005/&gt;

===Skin tone and skin radiance===
{{main|Human skin color#Social status and racism}} 
A preference for lighter-skinned women has remained prevalent over time, even in cultures without European contact, though exceptions have been found.&lt;ref name=&quot;Frost&quot;&gt;Peter Frost &quot;Fair Women, Dark Men: The Forgotten Roots of Color Prejudice,&quot; (2005).&lt;/ref&gt; Anthropologist Peter Frost stated that since higher-ranking men were allowed to marry the perceived more attractive women, who tended to have fair skin, the upper classes of a society generally tended to develop a lighter complexion than the lower classes by [[sexual selection]] (see also [[Fisherian runaway]]).&lt;ref name=&quot;Sailer&quot;&gt;see Steve Sailer, [http://vdare.com/sailer/050612_blondes.htm Blondes Have Deeper Roots] (2005)&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Frost&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=Dixson&gt;Dixson, Barnaby. Human Physique and Sexual Attractiveness: Sexual Preferences of Men and Women in Bakossiland, Cameroon http://www.springerlink.com/content/b74147t360040220/fulltext.pdf&lt;/ref&gt;  In contrast, one study on men of the Bikosso tribe in Cameroon found no preference for attractiveness of females based on lighter skin color, bringing into question the universality of earlier studies that had exclusively focused on skin color preferences among non-African populations.&lt;ref name=Dixson/&gt;

Today, [[skin bleaching]] is not uncommon in parts of the world such as Africa,&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news |url=http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/africa/718359.stm |title=The Heavy Cost of Light Skin |work=BBC News |date=2000-04-18 |accessdate=09-08-2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; and a preference for lighter-skinned women generally holds true for African Americans,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://northbysouth.kenyon.edu/2000/Beauty/goodlooks.htm |title=What Are &quot;Good Looks&quot;? |publisher=Kenyon College |accessdate=09-08-2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; Latin Americans,&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news |url=http://www.boston.com/news/globe/living/articles/2004/08/19/pride_or_prejudice/?page=2 |title=Pride or Prejudice? |publisher=Boston.com |date=2004-08-19 |accessdate=09-08-2010 |first=Vanessa E. |last=Jones}}&lt;/ref&gt; and Asians.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.pri.org/world/asia/skin-whitening-big-business-asia.html Skin whitening big business in Asia | PRI.ORG&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt; One exception to this has been in contemporary Western culture, where tanned skin used to be associated with the sun-exposed manual labor of the lower-class, but has generally been [[Sun tanning#Cultural history|considered more attractive and healthier]] since the mid-20th century.&lt;ref name=&quot;Singer&quot;&gt;{{Cite book |last=Singer |first=Merrill |authorlink=Merrill Singer |coauthors=Hans Beyer |title=Killer Commodities: Public Health and the Corporate Production of Harm |url=http://books.google.com/?id=64xpa-rhHLgC&amp;pg=PA151&amp;dq=sun+tan+lower+class&amp;q= |date=28 July 2008 |publisher=[[AltaMira Press]]|isbn=0759109796 |page=151 |quote=Harris investigated the history of the parasol... everywhere ordinary people were forbidden to protect themselves with such devices &quot;pallid skin became a marker of upper-class status&quot;. At the beginning of the 20th Century, in the United States, lighter-skinned people avoided the sun... Tanned skin was considered lower class.}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;pediatrics.aappublications.org&quot;&gt;{{cite journal |doi=10.1542/peds.109.6.1009 |last1=Geller |first1=AC |last2=Colditz |first2=G |last3=Oliveria |first3=S |last4=Emmons |first4=K |last5=Jorgensen |first5=C |last6=Aweh |first6=GN |last7=Frazier |first7=AL |title=Use of Sunscreen, Sunburning Rates, and Tanning Bed Use Among More Than 10 000 US Children and Adolescents |date=2002-06-06 |work=Pediatrics |volume=109 |journal=Pediatrics |issue=6 |pages=1009–14 |url=http://pediatrics.aappublications.org/cgi/content/full/109/6/1009 |pmid=12042536}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |author=Broadstock M, Borland R, Gason R |title=Effects of Suntan on Judgements of Healthiness and Attractiveness by Adolescents |journal=J Appl Soc Psychol |volume=22 |issue=2 |pages=157–172 |date=January 1992 |doi=10.1111/j.1559-1816.1992.tb01527.x}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |author=Leary MR, Jones JL |title=The Social Psychology of Tanning and Sunscreen Use: Self-Presentational Motives as a Predictor of Health Risk |journal=J Appl Soc Psychol |volume=23 |issue=17 |pages=1390–1406 |date=September 1993 |doi=10.1111/j.1559-1816.1993.tb01039.x |url=http://www3.interscience.wiley.com/journal/119292742/abstract}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.physorg.com/news78679968.html Tan is 'In': Study Finds Light Brown More Attractive than Pale or Dark Skin&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;

More recent work has extended skin color research beyond preferences for lightness, finding that redder (higher a* in the CIELab colour space) and yellower (higher b*) skin has healthier appearance.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|last=Stephen|first=Ian|coauthors=Law Smith, M.J., Stirrat, M.R., Perrett, D.I.|title=Facial skin coloration affects perceived health of human faces|journal=International Journal of Primatology|year=2009|volume=30|issue=6|pages=845-857|doi=10.1007/s10764-009-9380-z}}&lt;/ref&gt; These preferences have been attributed to higher levels of red oxygenated blood in the skin, which is associated with aerobic fitness and lack of cardiac and respiratory illnesses,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|last=Stephen|first=Ian|coauthors=Coetzee, V., Law Smith, M.J., Perrett, D.I.|title=Skin blood perfusion and oxygenation affect perceived human health|journal=PLoS ONE|year=2009|volume=4|pages=e5083|doi:10.1371/journal.pone.0005083}}&lt;/ref&gt; and to higher levels of yellow-red antioxidant carotenoids in the skin, indicative of more fruit and vegetables in the diet and, possibly more efficient immune and reproductive systems.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|last=Stephen|first=Ian|coauthors=Coetzee, V., Perrett, D.I.|title=Carotenoid and melanin pigment coloration affect perceived human health|journal=Evolution and Human Behavior|year=2011|volume=32|pages=216-227|doi:10.1016/j.evolhumbehav.2010.09.003}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Research has additionally shown that skin radiance or glowing skin indicates health, thus skin radiance influences perception of beauty and physical attractiveness.&lt;ref name=&quot;Bernhard&quot;&gt;{{cite journal | author = Fink B., Grammer K., Thornhill R. | year = 2001 | title = Human (Homo sapiens) facial attractiveness in relation to skin texture and color | url = | journal = Journal of Comparative Psychology | volume = 115 | issue = 1| pages = 92–99 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Fink2&quot;&gt;Fink, B. &amp; Matts, P.J. (2008). The effects of skin colour distribution and topography cues on the perception of female facial age and health. Journal of the European Academy of Dermatology and Venerology, 22(4), 493-498.&lt;/ref&gt; 

===Other determinants===
There has been research suggesting that women at the &quot;fertile stage&quot; of the menstrual cycle appear more attractive to single unattached men, but it is not clear exactly how this process works.&lt;ref name=twsO66b&gt;{{cite news
 |author= JOHN TIERNEY
 |title= The Threatening Scent of Fertile Women
 |publisher= ''The New York Times''
 |quote= Previous research had shown that a woman at the fertile stage of her menstrual cycle seems more attractive, and that same effect was observed here — but only when this woman was rated by a man who wasn’t already involved with someone else.
 |date= February 21, 2011
 |url= http://www.nytimes.com/2011/02/22/science/22tier.html
 |accessdate= 2011-07-15
}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Possible gender differences for preferences==
For both men and women, there appear to be universal criteria of attractiveness both within and across cultures and ethnic groups.&lt;ref name=twsO66f2&gt;{{cite news |author= Joanna Briscoe |title= Haven't I seen you somewhere before? |publisher= ''The Guardian'' |quote= Evolutionary psychologists claim there is an underlying standard script for beauty — a foundation for what we find appealing that transcends culture and ethnicity. There are various absolutes. For instance, to judge someone beautiful, the eye requires symmetry. |date= 17 January 2004 |url=http://www.guardian.co.uk/theguardian/2004/jan/17/weekend7.weekend2 |accessdate= 2011-07-15}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |author=Langlois JH, Kalakanis L, Rubenstein AJ, Larson A, Hallam M, Smoot M |title=Maxims or myths of beauty? A meta-analytic and theoretical review |journal=Psychol Bull |volume=126 |issue=3 |pages=390–423 |year=2000 |month=May |pmid=10825783 |url=http://content.apa.org/journals/bul/126/3/390 |doi=10.1037/0033-2909.126.3.390}} [http://www2.psych.purdue.edu/~kip/392F/Langlois.pdf as PDF]&lt;/ref&gt; Some studies have concluded that, in particular with regard to long-term relationships, men place a higher emphasis on physical attractiveness in a partner than women do.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite pmid|6008393}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Cowley, Geoffrey. &quot;The Biology of beauty&quot;. ''Newsweek''. June 3, 1996&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=BussBook&gt;{{Cite book |last=Buss |first=David |title=The Evolution of Desire |origyear=1994 |edition=second |year=2003 |publisher=Basic Books |location=New York |pages=57, 58, 60–63 |isbn=0465077501}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite doi|10.1007/BF00287245}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite doi|10.1007/BF00287468}}&lt;/ref&gt; On the other hand, some studies have found little difference between men and women in terms of the weight they place on physical characteristics when choosing partners for short-term relationships,&lt;ref&gt;Li, N. P., &amp; Kenrick, D. T. (2006). ''Sex similarities and differences in preferences for short-term mates: What, whether,and why.'' Journal of Personality and Social Psychology, 90, 468–489.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;''Sex differences in mate preferences revisited: Do people know what they initially desire in a romantic partner''?, By Eastwick, Paul W.; Finkel, Eli J. Journal of Personality and Social Psychology, Vol 94(2), Feb 2008, 245-264, Norman P. Lia, , , Katherine A. Valentinea and Lily Patel&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;''Mate preferences in the US and Singapore: A cross-cultural test of the mate preference priority model'', Personality and Individual Differences
Volume 50, Issue 2, January 2011, Pages 291-294&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Feingold, A. (1990). ''Gender differences in effects of physical attractiveness
on romantic attraction: A comparison across five research paradigms.''
Journal of Personality and Social Psychology, 59, 981–993.
doi:10.1037/0022-3514.59.5.981&lt;/ref&gt; in particular with regard to their implicit, as opposed to explicitly articulated, preferences.&lt;ref&gt;Implicit and explicit preferences for physical attractiveness in a romantic partner: A double dissociation in predictive validity'', Eastwick, Paul W.; Eagly, Alice H.; Finkel, Eli J.; Johnson, Sarah E. Journal of Personality and Social Psychology, Jul 18, 2011&lt;/ref&gt; Other recent studies continue to find sex differences for long-term relationships.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite doi|10.1007/s00265-006-0325-7}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite doi|10.1556/JEP.2008.1001}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite doi|10.1348/000712609X417319}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite doi|10.1016/j.paid.2010.10.005}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Some evolutionary psychologists, including David Buss, have argued that this long-term relationship difference may be consequence of ancestral humans who selected partners based on [[secondary sexual characteristics]], as well as general indicators of fitness which allowed for greater reproductive success as a result of higher fertility in those partners,&lt;ref&gt;Symons D. 1995. Beauty is in the adaptations of the beholder: the evolutionary psychology of human female sexual attractiveness. In ''Sexual Nature, Sexual Culture: Chicago Series on Sexuality, History, and Society'', ed. P.R. Abramson, S.D. Pinkerton, pp. 80–119. Chicago: Univ. Chicago Press&lt;/ref&gt; although a male's ability to provide resources for offspring was likely signaled less by physical features.&lt;ref name=BussBook/&gt; It is argued that the most prominent indicator of fertility in women is youth,&lt;ref name=&quot;Mealey and Hardy&quot;&gt;''Sex Differences: Developmental and Evolutionary Strategies'' by Linda Mealey and ''Mother Nature'' by Sarah Hardy.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=tws6nov13&gt;{{Cite news |author=Abigail Trafford, Andrew Cherlin |title= Second Opinion: Men's Health &amp; Marriage |quote=The major reason for the imbalance between men and women in the later decades of life is because men tend to marry younger women as they get older. |work= Washington Post |date=March 6, 2001 |url=http://www.washingtonpost.com/wp-srv/liveonline/01/health/health0306.htm |accessdate=2009-11-06}}&lt;/ref&gt; while the traits in a man which enhance reproductive success are proxies for his ability to accrue resources and protect.&lt;ref name=tws6nov13/&gt;

Studies have shown that women pay greater attention to physical traits than they do directly to earning capability or potential to commit,&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.reuters.com/article/2007/07/10/us-sex-muscles-idUSEIC04599320070710?feedType=RSS Women drawn to men with muscles]&lt;/ref&gt; including muscularity, fitness and masculinity of features; the latter preference was observed to vary during a woman's period, with women preferring more masculine features during the late-follicular (fertile) phase of the menstrual cycle.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite doi|10.1016/j.yhbeh.2005.07.004}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/376321.stm Women's choice of men goes in cycles]&lt;/ref&gt; Additionally, women process physical attractiveness differently, paying attention to both individual features and the aesthetic effect of the whole face.&lt;ref&gt;[http://healthland.time.com/2009/08/26/how-ladies-size-up-facial-attractiveness/ How Ladies Size Up Facial Attractiveness]&lt;/ref&gt; A 2003 study in the area concluded that heterosexual women are about equally aroused when viewing men or women. Heterosexual men were only aroused by women. This study verified arousal in the test subjects by connecting them to brain imaging devices.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.futurepundit.com/archives/001393.html Study on differences in Male, Female sexuality. June 2003]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://faculty.wcas.northwestern.edu/JMichael-Bailey/The%20Washington%20Times.htm Federally funded study measures arousal]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.nytimes.com/2009/01/25/magazine/25desire-t.html ''New York Times''. &quot;What do women want?&quot; Study on human sexuality]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;ScienceDaily. &quot;Study Suggests Difference Between Female And Male Sexuality&quot;[http://www.sciencedaily.com/releases/2003/06/030613075252.htm]&lt;/ref&gt; Notably, the same study reported arousal for women upon viewing animals mating.

It has been shown that women prefer men with a more masculine facial dimorphism during the fertile period of the menstrual cycle and men with a more feminine facial dimorphism during other parts of the cycle.&lt;ref name=&quot;fertility&quot;&gt;{{Cite news |url=http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/sci/tech/376321.stm |title=Women's choice of men goes in cycles |work=BBC News |accessdate=30 November 2006 |date=1999-06-24}}&lt;/ref&gt; This distinction supports the [[sexy son hypothesis]], which posits that it is evolutionarily advantageous for women to select potential fathers who are more genetically attractive,&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.amazon.com/Selfish-Gene-Richard-Dawkins/dp/0192860925 The Selfish Gene]&lt;/ref&gt; rather than the best caregivers.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.umich.edu/news/index.html?Releases/2003/Oct03/r102203 University of Michigan.&lt;!--Bot generated title--&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;

According to strategic pluralism theory, men may have correspondingly evolved to pursue reproductive strategies that are contingent on their own physical attractiveness. More physically attractive men accrue reproductive benefits from spending more time seeking multiple mating partners and relatively less time investing in offspring. In contrast, the reproductive effort of physically less attractive men, who therefore will not have the same mating opportunities, is better allocated either to investing heavily in accruing resources, or investing in their mates and offspring and spending relatively less time seeking additional mates.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite doi|10.1177/0146167207303022}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Facial similarity and racial bias ==
{| class=&quot;wikitable&quot;  border=&quot;1&quot; width=&quot;100%&quot;
|-
!colspan=&quot;5&quot; scope=&quot;col&quot; class=&quot;unsortable&quot; |Leslie A. Zebrowitz et al. professor of psychology at [[Brandeis University]] used 20 white faces, 24 black faces and 24 Korean faces in an experiment to determine that there was a greater average preference for &quot;within race&quot; faces (0.78) than &quot;between race&quot; faces (0.64).&lt;ref&gt;Zebrowitz, Leslie A.; Montepare, Joann M.; Lee, Hoon Koo
Journal of Personality and Social Psychology, Vol 65(1), Jul 1993, 85-101.&lt;/ref&gt;
|-
!Judging Group
!own race&lt;/br&gt; face
!White-Black&lt;/br&gt;mixed face
!White-Korean&lt;/br&gt;mixed face
!Black-Korean&lt;/br&gt;mixed face
|-
|[[White people|White]]||style=&quot;background: #48FF48&quot;|0.72||style=&quot;background: #CDFF00&quot;|0.69||style=&quot;background: #FFC400&quot;|0.47||style=&quot;background: #FF0000&quot;|0.23
|-
|[[Black people|Black]]||style=&quot;background: #66FF00&quot;|0.77||style=&quot;background: #66FF00&quot;|0.74||style=&quot;background: #CDFF00&quot;|0.69||style=&quot;background: #66FF00&quot;|0.75
|-
|[[Korean people|Korean]]||style=&quot;background: #00FF91&quot;|0.85||style=&quot;background: #66FF00&quot;|0.79||style=&quot;background: #5DFF48&quot;|0.72||style=&quot;background: #CDFF00&quot;|0.69
|}
Several studies have suggested that people are generally attracted to people who [[Interpersonal attraction#Similarity (like-attracts-like)|look like them]]&lt;ref&gt;(Locke &amp; Horowitz, 1990).&lt;/ref&gt; and they generally evaluate faces that exhibit features of their own ethnic or racial group as being more attractive.&lt;ref name=&quot;Bereczkei&quot; /&gt; Although both men and women use children's &quot;facial resemblance&quot; to themselves in &quot;attractiveness judgments,&quot; a greater percentage of women in one study (37% n=30) found hypothetical children whose faces were &quot;self-morphs&quot; of themselves as most attractive when compared to men (30% n=23).&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |author=DeBruine LM |title=Resemblance to self increases the appeal of child faces to both men and women |journal=Evol Hum Behav |volume=25 |issue=3 |pages=142–154 |date=May 2004 |doi=10.1016/j.evolhumbehav.2004.03.003 |url=http://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S1090513804000194}}&lt;/ref&gt; However, one report in ''[[The Guardian]]'' suggested there was a &quot;Caucasian beauty standard&quot; spreading worldwide because of the proliferation of the Western entertainment industry.&lt;ref name=twsO66f2/&gt;

The more similar a judged person is toward the judging person, the more the former is liked. However, this effect can be reversed. This might depend on how attractivity is conceptualized: similar members (compared to dissimilar ones) of the opposite sex are judged as more likeable in a prosocial sense. Again, findings are more ambiguous when looking for the desiring, pleasure related component of attractivness.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | doi = 10.1098/rspb.2004.3003 | last1 = DeBruine | first1 = L.M. |year = 2005 | title = Trustworthy but not lust-worthy: context-specific effects of facial resemblance | journal = Proceedings of the Royal Society. B, Biological sciences | volume = 272 | issue = 1566| pages = 919–922 | pmid = 16024346 | last2 = Deuter | first2 = C. E. | last3 = Kuehl | first3 = L. K. | last4 = Schulz | first4 = A. | last5 = Blumenthal | first5 = T. D. | last6 = Schachinger | first6 = H. | pmc = 1564091 }}&lt;/ref&gt; This might be influenced by the measure one uses (subjective ratings can differ from the way one actually reacts) and by situational factors: while men usually prefer women whose face resembles their own, this effect can reverse under stress, when dissimilar females are preferred.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | doi = 10.1098/rspb.2010.0258 | last1 = Lass-Hennemann | first1 = J. | last2 = Deuter | first2 = C.E. | last3 = Kuehl | first3 = L.K. | last4 = Schulz | first4 = A. | last5 = Blumenthal | first5 = T.D.. | last6 = Schachinger | first6 = H. |year = 2010 | title = Effects of stress on human mating preferences: stressed individuals prefer dissimilar mates | journal = Proceedings of the Royal Society. B, Biological sciences | volume = 277 | issue = 1691| pages = 2175–2183 | pmid = 20219732 | pmc=2880157}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Social effects==
Perceptions of physical attractiveness contribute to generalized assumptions based on those attractions. Across cultures, what is beautiful is assumed to be good; attractive people are assumed to be more extroverted, popular, and happy. This could lead to a [[self-fulfilling prophecy]], as from a young age, attractive people receive more attention that helps them develop these characteristics.&lt;ref name=&quot;Cash&quot;&gt;{{cite journal |author=Cash TF, Gillen B, Burns DS |title=Sexism and beautyism in personnel consultant decision making |journal=Journal of Applied Psychology |volume=62 |issue=3 |pages=301–310 |date=June 1977 |doi=10.1037/0021-9010.62.3.301 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Clark&quot;&gt;Clark, M.S.; &amp; Mills, J. (1979)&lt;/ref&gt; In one study, beautiful people were found to be generally happier than less beautiful or plain people, perhaps because beauty led to increased economic benefits which partially explained the increased happiness.&lt;ref name=twsO66f4a/&gt;

However, attractiveness varies by society; in ancient China, a small foot was considered attractive, so [[foot binding]] was practiced by confining young girls' feet in tightly bound shoes to prevent the feet from growing to normal size.&lt;ref name=tws6nov02&gt;{{Cite news |author=Jonathan E. Berman (letter to the editor) |title= Understand Female Genital Mutilation, Yes, but Don't Condone It |quote=The desired mark of beauty, put in plain language, was a set of withered or amputated toes at the end of crippled feet, which were jammed into the smallest possible slipper. |work=New York Times |date=November 30, 1993 |url=http://www.nytimes.com/1993/11/30/opinion/l-understand-female-genital-mutilation-yes-but-don-t-condone-it-015393.html |accessdate=2009-11-06}}&lt;/ref&gt; In England, women used to wear corsets that severely constricted their breathing and damaged vital internal organs, in order to achieve a visual effect of an exaggeratedly low Waist-to-Hip ratio.

People make judgments of physical attractiveness based on what they see, but also on what they know about the person. Specifically, perceptions of beauty are malleable such that information about the person's personality traits can influence one's assessment of another person's physical beauty. A 2007 study had participants first rate pictures for attractiveness. After doing distracting math problems, participants saw the pictures again, but with information about the person's personality. When participants learned that a person had positive personality characteristics (e.g., smart, funny, kind), that person was seen as more physically attractive.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal |title=Personality goes a long way: The malleability of opposite-sex physical attractiveness |first=Gary |last=Lewandowski |first2=Art |last2=Aron |first3=Julie |last3=Gee |journal=Personal Relationships |volume=14 |issue=4 |year=2007 |pages=571–585 |doi=10.1111/j.1475-6811.2007.00172.x}}&lt;/ref&gt; Conversely, a person with negative personality characteristics (e.g., materialistic, rude, untrustworthy) was seen as less physically attractive. This was true for both females and males.

Physical attractiveness can have various effects. A survey conducted by [[London Guildhall University]] of 11,000 people showed that those who subjectively describe themselves as physically attractive earn more income than others who would describe themselves as less attractive.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.cnn.com/2005/US/Careers/07/08/looks/ Do Pretty People Earn More from cnn.com&lt;/ref&gt; People who described themselves as less attractive earned, on average, 13% less than those who described themselves as more attractive, while the penalty for being overweight was around 5%. It is important to note that other factors such as self-confidence may explain or influence these findings as they are based on self-reported attractiveness as opposed to any sort of objective criteria; however, as one's self-confidence and [[self-esteem]] are largely learned from how one is regarded by his/her peers while maturing, even these considerations would suggest a significant role for physical appearance. One writer speculated that &quot;the distress created in women by the spread of unattainable ideals of female beauty&quot; might possibly be linked to increasing incidence of [[Depression (mood)|depression]].&lt;ref name=tws6nov18&gt;{{Cite news |author=Daniel Goleman |title=A Rising Cost Of Modernity: Depression |quote=Competing explanations range from a loss of beliefs in God or an afterlife that can buffer people against life's setbacks, to the stresses of industrialization, to the distress created in women by the spread of unattainable ideals of female beauty, to exposure to toxic substances. |work=New York Times |date=December 8, 1992 |url=http://www.nytimes.com/1992/12/08/science/a-rising-cost-of-modernity-depression.html |accessdate=2009-11-06}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Many have asserted that certain advantages tend to come to those who are perceived as being more attractive, including the ability to get better jobs and promotions; receiving better treatment from authorities and the [[legal system]]; having more choices in romantic partners and, therefore, more power in relationships; and marrying into families with more money.&lt;ref name=twsO66e/&gt;&lt;ref name=twsO66f4a&gt;{{cite news
 |author= Sharon Jayson
 |title= Study: Beautiful people cash in on their looks
 |publisher= ''USA Today''
 |quote= Numerous studies, including his earlier research, have concluded that beauty helps the budget by providing greater wealth in several ways: Better-looking people generally earn more money and marry those who are better-looking and higher-earning, he says.
 |date= March 31, 2011
 |url= http://yourlife.usatoday.com/your-look/story/2011/03/Beautiful-people-are-happier-study-finds/45500558/1
 |accessdate= 2011-07-15
}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Cash&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Clark&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name= &quot;DeSantis&quot;&gt;De Santis, A; and Kayson, W.A. 1999&lt;/ref&gt; Men and women use physical attractiveness as a measure of how &quot;good&quot; another person is.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.sensualism.com/beauty/attraction.html Science rewrites the rules of attraction]&lt;/ref&gt; Discrimination against or prejudice towards others based on their appearance is sometimes referred to as [[lookism]].

Some researchers conclude that little difference exists between men and women in terms of [[Human sexual activity|sexual behavior]].&lt;ref&gt;Cowley, Geoffrey. &quot;The Biology of beauty.&quot; ''Newsweek''. June 3, 1996&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.psychdaily.com/article/613 Sexual atrractiveness predicted by voice attractiveness]&lt;/ref&gt; [[Symmetry (physical attractiveness)|Symmetrical]] men and women have a tendency to begin to have [[sexual intercourse]] at an earlier age, to have more sexual partners, to engage in a wider variety of [[sexual activities]], and to have more [[one-night stand]]s. They are also prone to [[infidelity]] and are more likely to have [[open relationships]].&lt;ref name=Etcoff00/&gt; Additionally, they have the most [[reproductive success]]. Therefore, their physical characteristics are most likely to be inherited by future generations.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book |last=Rhodes |first=Gillian |coauthors=Zebrowitz, Leslie, A. |title=Facial Attractiveness – Evolutionary, Cognitive, and Social Perspectives |publisher=Ablex |year=2002 |isbn=1567506364}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |author=Edler RJ |title=Background considerations to facial aesthetics |journal=J Orthod |volume=28 |issue=2 |pages=159–68 |year=2001 |month=June |pmid=11395532 |url=http://jorthod.maneyjournals.org/cgi/pmidlookup?view=long&amp;pmid=11395532 |doi=10.1093/ortho/28.2.159}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |author=Zaidel DW, Aarde SM, Baig K |title=Appearance of symmetry, beauty, and health in human faces |journal=Brain Cogn |volume=57 |issue=3 |pages=261–3 |year=2005 |month=April |pmid=15780460 |doi=10.1016/j.bandc.2004.08.056 |url=http://linkinghub.elsevier.com/retrieve/pii/S0278-2626(04)00269-6}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.news.com.au/story/0,27574,25845304-36398,00.html Evolution producing more 'beautiful' women]&lt;/ref&gt;

Concern for improving physical attractiveness has led many persons to consider alternatives such as [[cosmetic surgery]]. It has led scientists working with related disciplines such as [[computer imaging]] and [[mathematics]] to conduct research to suggest ways to surgically alter a face in terms of distances between facial features, to make it closer to an ideal face with &quot;agreed-upon standards of attractiveness&quot;, by using algorithms to suggest an alternative which still resembles the current face.&lt;ref name=twsO52&gt;{{cite news
 |author= SARAH KERSHAW
 |title= The Sum of Your Facial Parts
 |publisher= ''The New York Times''
 |quote= Scientists ... trained a computer to determine, for each individual face, the most attractive set of distances and then choose the ideal closest to the original face. ...
 |date= October 8, 2008
 |url= http://www.nytimes.com/2008/10/09/fashion/09skin.html?pagewanted=all
 |accessdate= 2011-07-15
}}&lt;/ref&gt; One research study found that cosmetic surgery as a way to &quot;boost earnings&quot; was &quot;not profitable in a monetary sense.&quot;&lt;ref name=twsO66f4a/&gt;

==See also==
* [[Adornment]]
* [[Body proportions]]
* [[Body shape]]
* [[Erotic capital]]
* [[Female body shape]]
*[[Halo effect]]
* [[Human physical appearance]]
*[[Matching hypothesis]]
* [[Sexual attraction]]
* [[Sexual fetishes]]
* [[Sexual objectification]]

==References==
;Notes
{{Reflist|2}}

{{Aesthetics}}
{{Human sexuality}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Physical Attractiveness}}
[[Category:Physical attractiveness| ]]
[[Category:Social psychology]]
[[Category:Human sexuality]]
[[Category:Seduction]]

[[de:Attraktivität]]
[[ko:매력]]
[[iu:ᐃᓄᒃᑦᓯᐊᖅ/inuktsiaq]]
[[lt:Lytinis patrauklumas]]
[[pt:Beleza humana]]
[[ru:Физическая привлекательность]]
[[simple:Physical attractiveness]]
[[sv:Fysisk attraktivitet]]
[[tl:Kaaya-ayang pangangatawan]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
