<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="10550768" ns="0" title="Eelam War IV"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Infobox Military Conflict
| conflict = Eelam War IV
| partof = the [[Sri Lankan civil war]]
| date = 26 July 2006 – 18 May 2009
| place = [[Sri Lanka]]
| casus =
| result = [[Decisive victory|Decisive]] Sri Lankan Armed Forces victory. End of LTTE conventional military capabilities inside Sri Lanka.
| combatant1 = [[Image:Coat of arms of Sri Lanka.svg|18px]] [[Military of Sri Lanka]]
| combatant2 = [[Liberation Tigers of Tamil Eelam]]
| commander1 = [[Mahinda Rajapakse]], President
| commander1 = [[Sarath Fonseka]], Commander of the Army
| commander2 = [[Velupillai Prabhakaran]] [[Killed in Action|†]]
| strength1 = 150,000 (approx.)
| strength2 = 18,000 (approx.)
| casualties1 =6,261 killed (government claim&lt;ref name=&quot;english.aljazeera.net&quot;&gt;http://english.aljazeera.net/news/asia/2009/05/20095223465894713.html&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;news.bbc.co.uk&quot;&gt;{{cite news| url=http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/world/south_asia/8062922.stm | work=BBC News | title=Sri Lankan army deaths revealed | date=2009-05-22 | accessdate=2010-05-01}}&lt;/ref&gt;)&lt;br&gt; 29,551 wounded(government claim&lt;ref name=&quot;english.aljazeera.net&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;news.bbc.co.uk&quot;/&gt;)
| casualties2 =15,000 to 22,000 killed (government claim&lt;ref name=&quot;english.aljazeera.net&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;news.bbc.co.uk&quot;/&gt;)
}}
{{Campaignbox Eelam War IV}}
{{Campaignbox Sri Lankan Civil War}}
{{main|Sri Lankan Civil War}}
{{Sri Lankan Conflict}}

'''Eelam War IV''' is the name given to the fourth phase of armed conflict between the Sri Lankan military and the separatist [[Liberation Tigers of Tamil Eelam]], which is currently [[proscription|proscribed]] as a [[terrorist organisation]] by 32 countries (see [[Liberation Tigers of Tamil Eelam#Proscription as a terrorist group|list]]). Renewed hostilities began on the July 26, 2006 when [[Sri Lanka Air Force]] [[fighter jet]]s bombed several [[LTTE]] camps around [[Mavil Aru]] [[anicut]]. The government's [[casus belli]] was that the LTTE had cut-off the water supply to surrounding [[paddy field]]s in the area. The fighting resumed after a four-year ceasefire, between the [[Government of Sri Lanka]] (GoSL) and LTTE. Continued fighting lead to several territorial gains for the Sri Lankan Army, including the capture of Sampur, Vakarai and other parts of the east. The war took on an added dimension when the LTTE [[Air Tigers]] bombed [[Katunayake]] airbase on March 26, 2007, the first rebel air attack without external assistance in history.

==Peace process 2002==
The [[Sri Lankan parliamentary election, 2001|elections, held on 5 December 2001]] saw a sweeping victory for the [[United National Front]], led by [[Ranil Wickremasinghe]], who campaigned on a pro-peace platform and pledged to find a negotiated settlement to the conflict.

On 19 December, amidst efforts by Norway to bring the government and the Tamil Tigers to the negotiating table, the LTTE announced a 30 day ceasefire with the Sri Lankan government and pledged to halt all attacks against government forces.&lt;ref name=&quot;bbc1&quot;&gt;{{cite news | url= http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/world/south_asia/1719133.stm | title =Sri Lanka rebels announce truce| work =|publisher = BBC News|date = 19 December 2001 | accessdate=2010-01-03}}&lt;/ref&gt; The new government welcomed the move, and reciprocated it 2 days later, announcing a month long ceasefire and agreeing to lift a long standing economic [[embargo]] on rebel-held territory.&lt;ref name=&quot;bbc2&quot;&gt;{{cite news | url=http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/world/south_asia/1723419.stm | title =Sri Lanka enters truce with rebels|
work =|publisher = BBC News|date = 21 December 2001 | accessdate=2010-01-03}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Signing of MoU===
The two sides formalized a Memorandum of Understanding (MoU) on February 22, 2002 and signed a permanent ceasefire agreement (CFA). Norway was named [[mediation|mediator]], and it was decided that they, together with the other Nordic countries, monitor the ceasefire through a committee of experts named the [[Sri Lanka Monitoring Mission]].&lt;ref name=&quot;bbc3&quot;&gt;{{cite news | url= http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/world/south_asia/1835737.stm | title =Sri Lanka seals truce deal| work =|publisher = BBC News|date = 22 February 2002 | accessdate=2010-01-03}}&lt;/ref&gt; In August, the government agreed to lift the ban on the LTTE and paved the way for the resumption of direct negotiations with the LTTE.&lt;ref name=&quot;bbc4&quot;&gt;{{cite news | url= http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/world/south_asia/2217189.stm | title =Colombo lifts ban on Tamil Tigers| work =|publisher = BBC News|date = 26 August 2002 | accessdate=2010-01-03}}&lt;/ref&gt;
[[Image:Sea Tiger Fast Attack boat.jpg|thumb|right|200px|LTTE Sea Tiger boat patrolling during the peace.]]
Following the signing of the ceasefire agreement, commercial air flights to Jaffna began and the LTTE opened the key A9 highway, which linked government controlled area in the south with Jaffna and ran through LTTE territory, allowing civilian traffic through the Vanni region for the first time in many years. Many foreign countries also offered substantial financial support if peace was achieved and optimism grew that an end to the decades long conflict was in sight.

The much anticipated peace talks began in [[Phuket Province|Phuket]], [[Thailand]] on the September 16 and 5 further rounds followed in Phuket, Norway and [[Berlin]], [[Germany]].&lt;ref name=&quot;bbc5&quot;&gt;{{cite news | url= http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/world/south_asia/2260047.stm | title =Upbeat opening for Sri Lanka talks| work =|publisher = BBC News|date = 16 September 2002 | accessdate=2010-01-03}}&lt;/ref&gt; During the talks, both sides agreed to the principle of a federal solution and the Tigers dropped their long standing demand for separate state. This was a key compromise from the LTTE, which had always insisted on an independent Tamil state and it also represented a compromise from the government, which had seldom agreed to more than minimal devolution. Both sides also exchanged prisoners of war for first time.&lt;ref name=&quot;bbct&quot;&gt;''BBC News'', [http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/world/south_asia/country_profiles/1166237.stm Timeline: Sri Lanka]&lt;/ref&gt;

==Beginning of the war==
A new crisis leading to the first large-scale fighting since signing of the ceasefire occurred when the LTTE closed the [[sluice gate]]s of the [[Mavil Aru]] [[reservoir]] on July 21 and cut the [[water supply]] to 15,000 villages in government controlled areas.&lt;ref name=&quot;bbc12&quot;&gt;{{cite news | url = http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/south_asia/5249884.stm | title = Sri Lanka forces attack reservoir|work =|publisher = BBC News|date=2006-08-06 | accessdate=2010-01-03}}&lt;/ref&gt; After initial negotiations and efforts by the SLMM to open the gates failed, the Air Force attacked LTTE positions on July 26, and ground troops began an operation to open the gate.&lt;ref name=&quot;dm1&quot;&gt;{{cite news | url = http://www.dailymirror.lk/2006/07/27/front/6.asp | title = Air Force jets hit LTTE targets|work =Sunil Jayasiri|publisher = The Daily Mirror|date=2006-07-27}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Palitha Kohona]], a government spokesman, stated that the government remained committed to the cease-fire.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.lankanewspapers.com/news/2006/12/05/lankanews.html Sri Lanka Newspapers - Sri Lanka News Updates around the clock&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt; Likewise, the LTTE also claimed that they were committed to the ceasefire &lt;ref&gt;{{cite news| url=http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/south_asia/5237114.stm | work=BBC News | title='Muslims flee' Sri Lanka fighting | date=2006-08-02 | accessdate=2010-05-01}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The sluice gates were eventually reopened on August 8, with conflicting reports as to who actually opened them. Initially, the SLMM claimed that they managed to persuade the LTTE to lift the waterway blockade conditionally.&lt;ref name=&quot;fline1&quot;&gt;{{cite news |url =http://www.hinduonnet.com/fline/fl2316/stories/20060825001405400.htm |title = Water war |work = B. Muralidhar Reddy |publisher = The Hindu |date = August 12, 2006}}&lt;/ref&gt; However a government spokesman said that &quot;utilities could not be used as bargaining tools&quot; by the rebels&lt;ref name=&quot;bbc12&quot;/&gt; and government forces launched fresh attacks on LTTE positions around the reservoir. These attacks prompted condemnation from SLMM Chief of Staff, who stated &quot;(The government) have the information that the LTTE has made this offer.&quot; &quot;It is quite obvious they are not interested in water. They are interested in something else.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;bbc12&quot;/&gt; The LTTE then claimed they opened the sluice gates &quot;on humanitarian grounds&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;bbc12&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;st2&quot;&gt;''The Sunday Times Situation Report'', [http://sundaytimes.lk/060813/index.html Eelam war IV rages on several fronts]&lt;/ref&gt; Eventually, following heavy fighting with the rebels, government troops gained full control of the Mavil Aru reservoir on August 15.&lt;ref name=&quot;jw1&quot;&gt;''Iqbal Athas, Janes Defence Weekly,'' [http://www.janes.com/defence/news/jdw/jdw060817_1_n.shtml Full-scale fighting flares in Sri Lanka]&lt;/ref&gt;

==War in east==
{{main|Eastern Theater of Eelam War IV}}
{{See also|Operation Definite Victory}}
[[Image:Eastern peoples' victory monument.JPG|thumb|left|160px|Eastern peoples' victory monument at Karadiyanaru junction. This was erected after the Sri Lankan government military forces' victory over LTTE in the Eastern theatre.]]

The war between LTTE and Sri Lankan government started after the failure of Norway brokered cease fire on July 21, 2006, when LTTE cut off the water supply to the rice growing fields in the Mavil aru area in eastern Trincomalee district. The government military claimed the total control of the eastern province after capturing the Thoppigala (Baron's cap) on July 11, 2007 nearly a year of fighting.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/world/south_asia/6895809.stm|title='War victory party' in Sri Lanka|publisher=BBC News|date=2007-07-12 | accessdate=2010-01-03}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The TMVP contested Batticaloa district local council election on March 10, 2008 and won all 9 councils with a high majority 70% of votes.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/south_asia/7288942.stm|title=Ex-Tamil Tigers win local polls|publisher=BBC News|date=2008-03-11 | accessdate=2010-01-03}}&lt;/ref&gt; The party also contested in Eastern Provincial Council election May 10, 2008 under the ruling [[UPFA]] banner and UPFA won the election.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/south_asia/7394488.stm|title=Sri Lankan government wins vote|publisher=BBC News|date=2008-05-11 | accessdate=2010-01-03}}&lt;/ref&gt; TMVP's current leader [[Sivanesathurai Chandrakanthan]] sworn as the Chief Minister of Eastern Provincial Council on May 16, 2008.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.bbc.co.uk/sinhala/news/story/2008/05/080516_pillayan_cm.shtml|title=CM appointment illegal - Hisbullah|publisher=BBC News|date=2008-05-16}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Political situation in North and East==
Karuna has also been accused of gross human rights violations such as forming [[death squads]],&lt;ref name=&quot;rsf.org&quot;&gt;[http://www.rsf.org/article.php3?id_article=10956 Nine recommendations for improving the state of press freedom, Reporters Without Borders] (July 19, 2004)&lt;/ref&gt; harassing journalists,&lt;ref name=&quot;rsf.org&quot;/&gt; extrajudicial killings,&lt;ref&gt;U.S. Department of State, [http://www.state.gov/g/drl/rls/hrrpt/2005/61711.htm 2005 Human Rights Report], March 8, 2006&lt;/ref&gt; abductions,&lt;ref&gt;Denyer, Simon. &quot;[http://www.boston.com/news/world/asia/articles/2006/09/14/disappearances_on_rise_in_sri_lankas_dirty_war/ &quot;Disappearances&quot; on rise in Sri Lanka's dirty war]&quot;. Reuters, September 14, 2006. Retrieved April 5, 2007&lt;/ref&gt; and the use of child soldiers against the LTTE.&lt;ref&gt;UNICEF, [http://www.unicef.org/srilanka/media_2514.htm Statement on Sri Lanka from the UN Special Adviser on Children and Armed Conflict], November 13, 2006. Retrieved April 6, 2007&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal | title =Complicit in Crime: State Collusion in Abductions and Child Recruitment by the Karuna Group | journal =Human Rights Watch | volume =19 | issue =1(C) |date = January 2007| url =http://www.hrw.org/reports/2007/srilanka0107/}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Ross, James. &quot;[http://www.fpif.org/fpiftxt/3512 When Ceasefire Fails]&quot;, Foreign Policy in Focus, September 15, 2006. Retrieved April 6, 2007&lt;/ref&gt; Apart from that his group has split due to alleged financial corruption issues.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;[http://www.hindustantimes.com/StoryPage/StoryPage.aspx?id=28a57907-17be-425e-90fd-fd4f2313e325&amp;&amp;Headline=Split+in+Karuna+group+reported Split in Karuna group reported]&quot;. Hindustan Times, May 6, 2007. Retrieved January 4, 2008&lt;/ref&gt; Karuna, with the help of the Government of Sri Lanka, was smuggled into [[Great Britain]] for refuge.&lt;ref&gt;Balachandran, PK&quot;[http://www.hindu.com/2007/11/03/stories/2007110358400100.htm Colonel’ Karuna arrested in London]&quot;. The Hindu, November 3, 2007. Retrieved January 4, 2008&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;&quot;[http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/south_asia/7076248.stm &quot;UK detains breakaway Tamil leader]&quot;. BBC, November 3, 2007. Retrieved January 4, 2008&lt;/ref&gt; He was later arrested by British authorities for [[illegal entry]] and is being probed for war crimes.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;[http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/world/south_asia/7082299.stm Calls to prosecute ex-Tamil Tiger]&quot;. BBC.co.uk, 7 November 2007. Retrieved January 12, 2009&lt;/ref&gt;

==Sri Lanka pulls out of ceasefire==
On January 2, 2008, The Sri Lankan government unanimously decided to formally withdraw from the ceasefire with the separatist Tamil Tiger rebels, which had existed only on paper over the past two years. Prime Minister Ratnasiri Wickramanayake had proposed that the cabinet annul the truce after yet another bomb blast went off on January 2 in the capital, Colombo, killing five and injuring over 28.
&lt;ref name=&quot;aki&quot;&gt;{{cite news | url= http://www.adnkronos.com/AKI/English/Politics/?id=1.0.1730419377| title='Sri Lanka: Government ends ceasefire with Tamil Tiger rebels'| work =|publisher = AKI - Adnkronos International | date = 2008-01-10}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;&quot;The Government of Sri Lanka yesterday (3rd January 2008) formally notified the Norwegian Government of its decision to terminate the Agreement on a “Ceasefire (CFA) between the Government of the Democratic Socialist Republic of Sri Lanka and the Liberation Tigers of Tamil Eelam” concluded on 22nd February 2002. This notification was in terms of Article 4:4 of this Agreement and will take effect 14 days from the date of this notice i.e. 16th January 2008.

Accordingly, the Status of Mission Agreement (SOMA) on the Establishment and the Management of the Sri Lanka Monitoring Mission (SLMM) dated 18th March 2002 between the Royal Norwegian Government and the Government of the Democratic Socialist Republic of Sri Lanka will also stand terminated with effect from 16th January 2008.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;psl&quot;&gt;{{cite news | url= http://www.peaceinsrilanka.org/peace2005/Insidepage/PressRelease/WebRel/January/WebRel040108.asp | title = Statement by Hon. Rohitha Bogollagama, Minister of Foreign Affairs, at the Ministry on 4 January 2008| work =|publisher = Secretariat for Coordinating the Peace Process (SCOPP) | date = 2008-01-04}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

This was amidst the demands of the defense secretary [[Gotabhaya Rajapaksa]] on December 29, 2007.&lt;ref name=&quot;Daily&quot;&gt;{{cite news | url= http://www.dailynews.lk/2007/12/29/sec01.asp | title = Ban LTTE, end truce| work =|publisher = Daily News|date = 29 December 2007}}&lt;/ref&gt; Donor countries such as the United States,&lt;ref name=&quot;State&quot;&gt;{{cite news | url= http://www.state.gov/r/pa/prs/ps/2008/jan/98381.htm/ | title = Government of Sri Lanka’s Withdrawal from Ceasefire Agreement| work =|publisher = U.S. Department of State|date = 3 January 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt; Canada,&lt;ref name=&quot;Foreign&quot;&gt;{{cite news | url= http://w01.international.gc.ca/MinPub/Publication.aspx?isRedirect=True&amp;Language=E&amp;publication_id=385729&amp;docnumber=2 | title = STATEMENT ON THE POSSIBLE ESCALATION OF VIOLENCE IN SRI LANKA| work =|publisher = Foreign Affairs and International Trade Canada|date = 3 January 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt; and Norway&lt;ref name=&quot;Ministry&quot;&gt;{{cite news | url= http://www.regjeringen.no/en/dep/ud/Press-Contacts/News/2008/Norway-regrets-the-Government-of-Sri-Lan.html?id=495581 | title = Norway regrets the Government of Sri Lanka’s decision to terminate the 2002 ceasefire agreement| work =|publisher = Ministry of Foreign Affairs|date = 2 January 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt; have shown deep regrets on this decision by the Sri Lankan government. Neighboring India has also shown is dismay of Sri Lanka's abrogation of the ceasefire&lt;ref name=&quot;India&quot;&gt;{{cite news | url= http://mea.gov.in/pressbriefing/2008/01/04pb01.htm | title = In response to questions about Sri Lankan Government’s abrogation of Ceasefire Agreement of 2002, Official Spokesperson said:| work =|publisher = Ministry of External Affairs, India|date = 4 January 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==War in north==
{{main|Northern Theater of Eelam War IV}}
{{update|date=November 2010}}
Meanwhile, in the north of the country, some of the bloodiest fighting since 2001 took place after the LTTE launched massive attacks on [[Sri Lanka Army]] defence lines in the Jaffna peninsula on August 11. The LTTE used a force of 400 to 500 fighters in the attacks which consisted of land and amphibious assaults, and also fired a barrage of artillery at government positions, including the key military airbase at [[Palali]].&lt;ref name=&quot;hindu3&quot;&gt;{{cite news | url = http://www.hindu.com/thehindu/holnus/000200608121801.htm | title = At least 127 combatants killed in Lanka fighting: military |work =|publisher = The Hindu| date =August 12, 2006 | location=Chennai, India | deadurl=yes}} {{Dead link|date=December 2010|bot=RjwilmsiBot}}&lt;/ref&gt; Initially, the Tigers broke through army defense lines around Muhamalai, and advanced further north,&lt;ref name=&quot;oi1&quot;&gt;{{cite news | url = http://news.oneindia.in/2006/08/12/sri-lanka-rebels-say-destroy-northern-defences-advance-1155353635.html | title = Lanka rebels destroy northern defenses, advance |work =|publisher = One India| date =August 12, 2006}}&lt;/ref&gt; but they were halted after 10 hours of fierce fighting. Isolated battles continued over the next few days, but the LTTE was forced to give up its offensive due to heavy casualties.&lt;ref name=&quot;ht1&quot;&gt;{{cite news | url = http://www.hindustantimes.com/news/7598_1883909,000500020002.htm | title = Lanka's chilling 2006 timeline |work =PK Balachandran|publisher = [[Hindustan Times]]| date =December 30, 2006}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;ht1&quot;/&gt;

Sporadic fighting in the North has been going on for months, but the intensity of the clashes has increased since September 2007. During clashes in the Forward Defence Lines, separating their forces, both sides exchange heavy artillery fire, after which military incursions follow. By December 22, 2007 the LTTE defences at Uyilankulama and Thampanai were lost to advancing troops of the Sri Lanka Army. On December 29, 2007 the Army overran the LTTE stronghold at Parappakandal, Mannar.

In an interview with the 'Sunday Observer' the Sri Lankan Army  Commander Lt. Gen. Sarath Fonseka said that the Army had occupied the LTTE's Forward Defence Lines and surrounded the Wanni LTTE bases from all directions. He also said that there are around 3,000 Tigers remaining and that the military targets to annihilate them within the first six months of 2008. A day later there were less optimistic statements by Army, Air Force and Navy Commanders.   Lt. Gen. Fonseka's believed it was possible to defeat the LTTE in 2008.

The military of Sri Lanka claims that the leader of the LTTE Velupillai Prabhakaran was seriously injured during air strikes carried out by the Sri Lanka Air Force on a bunker complex in Jayanthinagar on November 26, 2007. Earlier, on November 2, 2007 S. P. Thamilselvan, who was the head of the rebels' political wing, was killed during another government air raid. The Sri Lanka Air Force has openly vowed to destroy the entire leadership of the LTTE. On January 5, 2008 Col. Charles, Head of LTTE Military Intelligence, was killed in claymore ambush by a suspected Sri Lanka Army Deep Penetration Unit according to a Pro-LTTE website.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news| url=http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/south_asia/7173679.stm | work=BBC News | title=Tamil intelligence chief killed | date=2008-01-06 | accessdate=2010-05-01}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Before the government offensive, the war in the Northern front was in a stalemate due to the unique topology of the two major Forward Defence Lines, The [[Nagarcoil Forward Defence Line|Nagarcoil FDL]] and The [[Muhamalai Forward Defence Line|Muhamalai FDL]].

==Capture of Mannar District==
On 2 August 2008 the Sri Lankan army captured the town of Vellankulam which was the last bastion of Tigers in the [[Mannar district]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news| url=http://www.hindu.com/2008/08/03/stories/2008080356141400.htm | location=Chennai, India | work=The Hindu | title=LTTE's last bastion in Mannar captured | date=3 August 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt; This marked the capture of the entire Mannar district by the Army which took eight months.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.asiantribune.com/?q=node/12554&lt;/ref&gt;

==Battles at sea==
On March 22, 2008, a Navy fast attack boat was destroyed after it hit a suspected sea mine laid by Tamil Tiger rebels off the country's north-east coast.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.gulfnews.com/World/Sri_Lanka/10199382.html&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;http://www.abc.net.au/news/stories/2008/03/22/2196752.htm&lt;/ref&gt;

==The air war==
The battle in air is significant for both sides (GoSL and LTTE) in this phase of war. The [[Sri Lankan Air Force]] used its attack aircraft to carry out a bombing campaign against identified LTTE targets. The LTTE Air Tigers also used its light aircraft to carry out bombing on the Sri Lankan military.

===Major air strikes of SLAF===
* On August 14, 2006 the SLAF [[Chencholai airstrike|bombed a facility in the rebel-held Mullaitivu area]]. The LTTE claimed 61 girls were killed, the SLMM stated they were able to count just 19 bodies.&lt;ref name=&quot;mc1&quot;&gt;{{cite news |url = http://news.monstersandcritics.com/southasia/article_1190181.php/61_girls_killed_in_airstrike_8_dead_in_Colombo_blast__2nd_Roundup_|title = SLMM counted 19 Bodies|work = |publisher = monstersandcritics.com |date = 13 August 2006}}&lt;/ref&gt; The government claimed that it was an LTTE training facility and that the children were LTTE child soldiers,&lt;ref name=&quot;mg1&quot;&gt;{{cite news |url = http://www.mg.co.za/articlepage.aspx?area=/breaking_news/breaking_news__international_news/&amp;articleid=280855|title = Unicef: Bombed orphans were not Tamil Tigers |work = |publisher = [[Mail and Guardian Online]] |date = 15 August 2006}}&lt;/ref&gt; although the LTTE claimed the victims were schoolgirls attending a course on first aid at an orphanage. A team from [[UNICEF]] and the Swedish-led Sri Lanka Monitoring Mission (SLMM) visited the bombed site and said they had found no evidence to support claims the rebels had been using the facility as a military training centre.
* On May 7, 2007 at about 0725 supersonic fighter jets of the SLAF bombed a strategic LTTE base and a large fuel storage at Ramanatpuram East of [[Iranamadu]].
* In November 2007, Thamilselvan, along with five other high ranking Tamil rebels were killed by a precision air strike carried out by the SLAF on an undisclosed location near the rebels's stronghold town of Kilinochchi.

===LTTE air strikes===
* LTTE air strikes occurred for the first time in history on March 26, 2007 on a SLAF base at [[Katunayake]], killing three Air Force personnel and wounding several.
* LTTE aircraft attacked [[Palali]] military complex by dropping bombs on April 23, 2007, killing six soldiers and wounding 13.
* The LTTE attacked Katunayake air base for the second time on April 26, 2007, one month after their first attack on the same location.
* in the early hours of April 29, 2007, LTTE aircraft bombed two fuel tanks at [[Kolonnawa]] and [[Muthurajawela]] close to [[Colombo]].

;Palali raid
On April 23, the Air Tigers conducted their second raid. One aircraft flew toward the Palali Air Base near Jaffna, which is the main military complex in the region. Anti‐aircraft fire prevented the aircraft from bombing the runways, but it instead dropped its bombs on a nearby military bunker, killing six soldiers.

;Colombo raids
On April 26, Sri Lanka’s air defenses in Colombo fired into the sky following reports that unidentified aircraft had been spotted on radar. No attack was reported.

However, a few days later on the early morning of April 29, while the entire nation was watching the Cricket World Cup Final a Tiger aircraft bombed two fuel storage facilities outside Colombo. Chaos followed and electricity in the capital was shut off for nearly an hour. There were no casualties and minimal damage. The security forces were unable to bring down the aircraft prompting much criticism from the public and opposition political parties.

Although the government played down the attack, Shell's Sri Lankan country director, Hassan Madan, told the AFP &quot;There was big damage to our fire-fighting facility and we estimate it will cost us in excess of 75 m rupees ($700,000) to put things back&quot;.

On October 22, 2007, Air Tigers launched a [[Raid on Anuradhapura Air Force Base|pre-dawn combined arms assault]] on a SLAF airbase at [[Anuradhapura]], about {{convert|212|km|mi|sp=us}} north of the capital, Colombo.

According to the [[Ministry of Defence (Sri Lanka)|Ministry of Defence]], the assault started at around 3:20 am, with LTTE ground forces attacking the airbase and overrunning key positions, including an anti-aircraft position, before Air Tiger ultralights dropped bombs on government positions. This resulted in the destruction of eight aircraft and damage to several others.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.defence.lk/new.asp?fname=20071024_07 Ministry of Defence, Sri Lanka]&lt;/ref&gt; The attack only affected the SLAF's training element.

==The conclusion of the war==
On 19 May 2009, the Sri Lankan military effectively concluded its 26 year operation against the [[LTTE]]. The [[58 Division (Sri Lanka)|58 Division]] of the Sri Lankan Army led by Brig. Shavendra Silva, [[59 Division (Sri Lanka)|59 Division]] led by Brig. Prasanna de Silva and the [[53 Division (Sri Lanka)|53 Division]] commanded by Gen. Kamal Gunaratne, after having boxed in the remaining LTTE cadres into a small area of territory near [[Nanthi Kadal|Nandhikkadal lagoon]], linked up and eliminated the remaining cadres. This final battle claimed the lives of several top LTTE leaders, including Jeyam, Bhanu, Lawrence, Pappa, Laxamanan, Balasingham Nadesan, Pottu Amman, Soosai and [[Velupillai Prabhakaran]] who was reported to have attempted to flee.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.dailymirror.lk/DM_BLOG/Sections/frmNewsDetailView.aspx?ARTID=49739, The Last Day of Prabhakaran, D.B.S. Jeyaraj, Daily Mirror]&lt;/ref&gt; On the morning of the 19th, soldiers of the 4th Vijayabahu infantry regiment led by Lt. Col Rohitha Aluvihare claimed to have found the body of Prabhakaran, and so militarily ending a separatist war that had defined Sri Lanka's history for three decades.

On 22 May 2009, Sri Lankan Secretary of Defence [[Gotabhaya Rajapaksa]] confirmed that 6,261 personnel of the Sri Lankan Armed Forces had lost their lives and 29,551 were wounded during Eelam War IV since July 2006. Brig. Udaya Nanayakkara added that approximately 22,000 [[LTTE]] cadres had died during this time.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.reuters.com/article/latestCrisis/idUSSP463682, Reuters article citing Gotabhaya Rajapaksa]&lt;/ref&gt;

==Chronology of towns captured by the government of Sri Lanka==

{| width=100% class=&quot;wikitable&quot; border=&quot;1&quot;
! Area Liberated&lt;ref&gt;http://defence.lk/new.asp?fname=20090117_03&lt;/ref&gt;
! Division/Task Force
! Date
|-
|[[Silawaturai]]
|
|2 September 2007
|-
|[[Madhu church]] complex
|[[57 Division (Sri Lanka)|57 Division]]
|24 April 2008
|-
|[[Adampan town]]
|[[58 Division (Sri Lanka)|58 Division]]
|9 May 2008
|-
|[[Palampiddi]] Town
|[[57 Division (Sri Lanka)|57 Division]]
|16 May 2008
|-
|[[Mundumurippu]] Village
|[[57 Division (Sri Lanka)|57 Division]]
|23 May 2008
|-
|[[Munagam Base]]
|[[59 Division (Sri Lanka)|59 Division]]
|30 May 2008
|-
|[[Periyamadhu]] Village
|[[57 Division (Sri Lanka)|57 Division]]
|15 June 2008
|-
|[[Mullikkandal]], [[Minnaniranchan]] and [[Marattikannaddi]] Villages
|[[58 Division (Sri Lanka)|58 Division]]
|24 June 2008
|-
|&quot;[[The Mannar Rice Bowl]]&quot;: [[Alankulama]], [[Andankulama]], [[Alakaddiveli]], [[Parappakandal]], [[Parappukadatan]],&lt;br&gt;[[Papamoddai]], [[Odupallam]], [[Neduvarampu]], [[Kannaputtukulama]] and [[Vannakulama]] Villages
|[[58 Division (Sri Lanka)|58 Division]]
|29 June 2008
|-
|[[Uyilankulam]]
|
|29 June 2008
|-
|Linked up with [[57 Division (Sri Lanka)|57 Division]] - south west of [[Periyamadhu]]
|[[58 Division (Sri Lanka)|58 Division]]
|30 June 2008
|-
|[[Michael Base]]
|[[59 Division (Sri Lanka)|59 Division]]
|4 July 2008
|-
|[[Naddankandal]] Village
|[[57 Division (Sri Lanka)|57 Division]]
|11 July 2008
|-
|[[Navvi]] village
|[[Task Force 2]]
|11 July 2008
|-
|[[Vidattaltivu]] Town
|[[58 Division (Sri Lanka)|58 Division]]
|16 July 2008
|-
|[[Iluppaikkadavai]]
|
|20 July 2008
|-
|[[Suganthan camp]]
|[[59 Division (Sri Lanka)|59 Division]]
|27 July 2008
|-
|[[Illuppaikkadavai]] Town
|[[58 Division (Sri Lanka)|58 Division]]
|2 August 2008
|-
|[[Vellankulam]] Town, [[Mulankavil]] and [[Pallavarayankaddu]] areas
|[[58 Division (Sri Lanka)|58 Division]]
|12 August 2008
|-
|[[Kalvilan]] Village
|[[57 Division (Sri Lanka)|57 Division]]
|13 August 2008
|-
|[[Jeevan Base]]
|[[59 Division (Sri Lanka)|59 Division]]
|16 August 2008
|-
|[[West of Nayaroo lagoon]]
|[[59 Division (Sri Lanka)|59 Division]]
|21 August 2008
|-
|[[Nachchikudha]]
|[[58 Division (Sri Lanka)|58 Division]]
|21 August 2008
|-
|[[Thunukkai]] and [[Uilankulam]] Towns
|[[57 Division (Sri Lanka)|57 Division]]
|22 August 2008
|-
|[[Mallavi]] Town
|[[57 Division (Sri Lanka)|57 Division]]
|2 September 2008
|-
|[[Maniyankulama]]
|[[58 Division (Sri Lanka)|58 Division]]
|16 October 2008
|-
|[[Vannerikkulama]]
|[[58 Division (Sri Lanka)|58 Division]]
|20 October 2008
|-
|[[Gajabapura]]
|[[59 Division (Sri Lanka)|59 Division]]
|23 October 2008
|-
|[[Nochchimodai]]
|[[58 Division (Sri Lanka)|58 Division]]
|28 October 2008
|-
|[[Jeyapuram]] and [[Nachchikuda]]
|[[58 Division (Sri Lanka)|58 Division]]
|29 October 2008
|-
|[[Akkarayankulam tank bund]]
|[[57 Division (Sri Lanka)|57 Division]]
|29 October 2008
|-
|[[Akkarayankulam]] built-up
|[[57 Division (Sri Lanka)|57 Division]]
|5 November 2008
|-
|[[Kiranchi]]
|[[58 Division (Sri Lanka)|58 Division]]
|10 November 2008
|-
|[[Kumulamunai village]]
|[[59 Division (Sri Lanka)|59 Division]]
|11 November 2008
|-
|[[Palavi]]
|
|11 November 2008
|-
|[[Valaippadu]]
|
|13 November 2008
|-
|[[Devil's Point]] and [[Vallaipadu]]
|[[58 Division (Sri Lanka)|58 Division]]
|13 November 2008
|-
|[[Pooneryn]]
|[[58 Division (Sri Lanka)|58 Division]]
|15 November 2008
|-
|[[Mankulama]]
|[[Task Force 3]]
|17 November 2008
|-
|[[Mankulam]]
|
|17 November 2008
|-
|[[Olumadu]]
|[[Task Force 3]]
|25 November 2008
|-
|[[Otiyamalai]]
|[[59 Division (Sri Lanka)|59 Division]]
|29 November 2008
|-
|[[Kokavil]] Town
|[[57 Division (Sri Lanka)|57 Division]]
|1 December 2008
|-
|[[Puliyankulam]]
|[[Task Force 2]]
|4 December 2008
|-
|[[Kanakarayankulam]]
|[[Task Force 2]]
|5 December 2008
|-
|[[Terumurikandy]] junction
|[[57 Division (Sri Lanka)|57 Division]]
|10 December 2008
|-
|[[Ampakamam]]
|[[Task Force 3]]
|15 December 2008
|-
|[[Nadunkerni]]
|[[Task Force 4]]
|20 December 2008
|-
|[[Sinna-Paranthan]]
|[[58 Division (Sri Lanka)|58 Division]]
|23 December 2008
|-
|[[Nalanawakulam]] Village
|[[58 Division (Sri Lanka)|58 Division]]
|26 December 2008
|-
|[[Mulliyawalai]]
|[[59 Division (Sri Lanka)|59 Division]]
|26 December 2008
|-
|[[Iranamadu]]
|
|1 January 2009
|-
|[[Paranthan]]
|[[58 Division (Sri Lanka)|58 Division]]
|1 January 2009
|-
|[[Kilinochchi]] Town
|[[57 Division (Sri Lanka)|57 Division]]
|2 January 2009
|-
|[[Oddusuddan]]
|[[Task Force 4]]
|4 January 2009
|-
|[[Ramanathapuram]]
|[[57 Division (Sri Lanka)|57 Division]]
|7 January 2009
|-
|[[Murasumoddai]]
|[[58 Division (Sri Lanka)|58 Division]]
|8 January 2009
|-
|[[Elephant Pass]]
|
|9 January 2009
|-
|[[Keridattadu]]
|[[Task Force 4]]
|12 January 2009
|-
|[[Jaffna peninsula]]
|
|14 January 2009
|-
|[[Dharmapuram]]
|[[58 Division (Sri Lanka)|58 Division]]
|15 January 2009
|-
|[[Udayarkattukulam Tank Bund]]
|[[Task Force 2]]
|2114 January 2009
|-
|[[Mullaittivu Town]]
|[[59 Division (Sri Lanka)|59 Division]]
|25 January 2009
|-
|[[Visuamadu]] Town
|[[57 Division (Sri Lanka)|57 Division]]
|28 January 2009
|-
|[[Visuamadu]] Town
|[[58 Division (Sri Lanka)|58 Division]]
|28 January 2009
|-
|[[Chalai]]
|[[55 Division (Sri Lanka)|55 Division]]
|5 February 2009
|-
|[[Thevipuram]]
|[[58 Division (Sri Lanka)|58 Division]]
|20 February 2009
|-
|[[Iranapalai]] Junction
|[[58 Division (Sri Lanka)|58 Division]]
|17 March 2009
|-
|[[Pachchapulmuddai]]
|[[58 Division (Sri Lanka)|58 Division]]
|1 April 2009
|-
|[[Puthukkudiyiruppu]]
|[[58 Division (Sri Lanka)|58 Division]]
|5 April 2009
|-
|[[Puthukkudiyirippu Hospital]]
|[[53 Division (Sri Lanka)|53 Division]]
|12 March 2009
|-
|[[Pachchapulmuddai]]
|[[53 Division (Sri Lanka)|53 Division]]
|1 April 2009
|-
|[[Puthukkudiyiruppu (Mullaitivu)|Puthukkudiyiruppu]]
|[[53 Division (Sri Lanka)|53 Division]]
|5 April 2009
|}

==Killings LTTE Leaders==
* [[Velupillai Prabhakaran]] was killed by government troops. His body was identified through [[DNA testing]] on May 19, 2009.
* [[Soosai]], leader of the [[Sea Tigers]], and [[Pottu Amman]], head of the LTTE intelligence wing, were killed along with Prabhakaran.
* [[Charles Anthony (LTTE)|Charles Anthony]] was confirmed dead on May 18, 2009. SL Army has confirmed that the body found in [[Vellamullivaikkal]] is that of LTTE chief's son.
* Three bodies recovered by SL troops have been identified as those of Nadesan, Puleethevan and Ramesh on May 18, 2009.

==Assassinations==
* Then Sri Lankan Foreign Minister [[Lakshman Kadirgamar]], a Tamil who was highly respected by foreign diplomats and who had been sharply critical of the LTTE, was assassinated at his home on August 12, 2005, allegedly by an LTTE sniper.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |url=http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/south_asia/4147196.stm |title=Senior Sri Lanka minister killed |accessdate=2005-08-13|format= |work=BBC News  | date=2005-08-13}}&lt;/ref&gt; His assassination led to the marginalisation of the LTTE from the international community.
* The assassination of well renowned Tamil diplomat the Deputy Peace Secretariat General for Co-ordinating the Peace Process (SCOPP) Mr. [[Kethesh Loganathan]] on August 12, 2006 at [[Dehiwala]] by shooting at around 9:30 PM. He has been very keen to bring peace to the country also participated in [[Thimphu]] peace talks in 1980's. Rajapakse condemned the murder and blamed the LTTE. &lt;!--This section already referred to cited main article in Wikipedia--&gt;
* The assassination of the head Priest of the [[Santhiveli Pilleyar Kovil]] Rev [[Selliah Parameswaran Kurukkal]] on February 7, 2007 in his home [[Batticaloa]]. The LTTE and the Sri Lankan Government blamed each other for this murder.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news| url=http://www.hindu.com/2007/02/09/stories/2007020902671500.htm | location=Chennai, India | work=The Hindu | title=Hindu priest shot dead | date=9 February 2007}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.ltteps.org/?view=1857&amp;folder=2 LTTE PS: Another Hindu priest murdered by paramilitary&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;
* UNP Parliamentarian T. Maheshwaran&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news | url=http://timesofindia.indiatimes.com/Sri_Lankan_Tamil_MP_shot_dead_at_Hindu_temple_in_Colombo/articleshow/2666314.cms| title=Sri Lankan Tamil MP shot dead at Hindu temple in Colombo [Updated]| work =The Times Of India|publisher = | date = 2008-03-16| deadurl=yes}} {{Dead link|date=April 2011|bot=RjwilmsiBot}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* A roadside bomb killed Non-cabinet Nation Building Minister, [[D. M. Dassanayake]] on January 8, 2008 at [[Ja-ela]] town located 19&amp;nbsp;km north of Colombo city.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/south_asia/7176207.stm|title=Sri Lankan minister dies in blast|publisher=BBC News|date=2008-01-08 | accessdate=2010-01-03}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news | url=http://www.defence.lk/new.asp?fname=20080108_06| title=Minister D.M Dassanayake and his body guard succumb to injuries- Ragama| work =|publisher = Ministry of Defence, Public Security, Law &amp; Order - Democratic Socialist Republic of Sri Lanka| date = 2008-01-10}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* A suspected LTTE suicide bomber killed cabinet Minister of Highways &amp; Road Development [[Jeyaraj Fernandopulle]] on April 6, 2008 at Weliveriya [[Gampaha]] district.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/south_asia/7332952.stm|title=Blast 'kills Sri Lankan minister'|publisher=BBC News|date=2008-04-06 | accessdate=2010-01-03}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Impact of war into civilian life==
Since the latest upsurge in violence in April, nearly 40,000 people have been displaced in Sri Lanka. This comes amidst the governments air strikes on civilian populated areas of the East.&lt;ref name=&quot;BBC&quot;&gt;{{cite news |url=http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/south_asia/4946730.stm | title = Thousands flee Sri Lanka strikes| work =|publisher = BBC|date = 26 April 2006}}&lt;/ref&gt; Amnesty International quoted UN figures to say that a total of 39,883 people had been displaced in the north and east since April 7 adding that a total of 314,378 people were displaced by the conflict while around 325,000 people were estimated to have been displaced by the tsunami.&lt;ref name=&quot;Ganguly&quot;&gt;{{cite news | url= http://www.washingtonpost.com/wp-dyn/content/article/2006/04/26/AR2006042600335.html | title = 40,000 Flee Sri Lanka Violence| work =|publisher = Washington Post|date = 26 April 2006 | first=Dilip | last=Ganguly | accessdate=2010-05-01}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;CTV&quot;&gt;{{cite news |url=http://www.ctv.ca/servlet/ArticleNews/story/CTVNews/20060426/sri_lanka_bombing_060427/20060427?hub=World&amp;s_name= | title = At least 40,000 civilians flee Sri Lanka violence| work =|publisher = CTV|date = 27 April 2006}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Jazeera&quot;&gt;{{cite news |url=http://english.aljazeera.net/English/archive/archive?ArchiveId=22334 | title = Thousands flee Sri Lanka air raids| work =|publisher = CTV|date = 29 April 2006}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Amnesty International has also stated that increasing violence was forcing many Sri Lankans to flee the country and that more than 2,800 people had sought shelter in India this year. The state's failure to provide adequate security and to ensure that attacks against civilians are prosecuted has resulted in widespread fear and panic.&lt;ref name=&quot;CTV&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Lanka&quot;&gt;{{cite news | url= http://www.lankanewspapers.com/news/2006/6/7542.html | title = Nowhere people - 40,000 more| work =|publisher = LankaNewspapers|date = 1 July 2006}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Amnesty international also accused the LTTE of breaking the international law by using civilians as buffers against the army. A researcher for the organisation stated that there were cases where militants had forced people to stay in rebel-held areas to hamper army operations.&lt;ref name=&quot;BBC news&quot;&gt;{{cite news | url= http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/world/south_asia/7564089.stm | title = Tamil rebels 'breaking the law'| work =|publisher = BBC.co.uk|date = 15 August 2008|accessdate = 14 January 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt; The United Nations reported more than 20,000 civilians were killed in this recent war.&lt;ref&gt;[http://abcnews.go.com/International/wireStory?id=7704790 Estimation report]&lt;/ref&gt; [http://www.telegraph.co.uk/news/worldnews/asia/srilanka/5405085/Sri-Lankan-army-accused-of-massacring-20000-Tamil-civilians-in-final-assault.html] CNN report [http://www.cnn.com/2009/WORLD/asiapcf/05/29/srilanka.death.toll/index.html]

After the International Council of Red Cross, doctors and government officials left the war zone, only the Catholic priests remained with people until the end. One of the priests, [[Rev. Fr. Mariampillai Sarathjeevan]] who was leading the refugees to safety, also died in the war zone.&lt;ref&gt;http://fathersara.info&lt;/ref&gt; The people and the priest did not have food for five days, and exhausted by months of hardship.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.indcatholicnews.com/news.php?viewStory=14398&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;http://www.asianews.it/index.php?l=en&amp;art=15356&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;http://omiusajpic.org/2009/05/26/tribute-to-fr-mariampillai/&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;http://www.archdioceseofcolombo.com/FrSarathjeevan_Tributes.php&lt;/ref&gt; Unconfirmed reports indicate that the priest was assaulted by soldiers when he approached them for help.

Stephen Rapp, the U.S. ambassador at large for war crimes issues, called for war crimes investigation on October 2009. His department submitted a detailed report to Congress about the incidents happened during the recent conflict in Sri Lanka.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.state.gov/documents/organization/131025.pdf&lt;/ref&gt;  On October 25, 2009 The Office of the High Commissioner for Human Rights of the United Nations called for an  independent, international investigation of possible war crimes committed during the last few months of the war in Sri Lanka.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.voanews.com/english/2009-10-25-voa7.cfm&lt;/ref&gt; Internal Displacement Monitoring Center of the Norwegian Refugee Council reported that the government of Sri Lanka was holding nearly 300,000 displaced people in military-run internment camps under questionable humanitarian conditions.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.internal-displacement.org/8025708F004BE3B1/(httpInfoFiles)/E52F8EDB6EC95876C125766A0045F597/$file/SriLanka_Overview_Nov09.pdf&lt;/ref&gt;

==See also==
* [[Sri Lankan Civil War]]
* [[Eelam War I]]
* [[Eelam War II]]
* [[Eelam War III]]
* [[Eastern Theater of Eelam War IV]]
* [[Northern Theater of Eelam War IV]]

==References==
{{reflist|2}}
56. Recapture Of Poonaryn by SL Army : http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/world/south_asia/7730850.stm

==External links==
* [http://www.defence.lk/ Ministry of Defence, Sri Lanka]
* [http://www.cyberlk.com/defencemap/ Interactive Defence Map of Sri Lanka, explains current progress of the battle fronts visually.]
* [http://www.peaceinsrilanka.org/ GoSL Peace Secretariat]
* [http://www.ltteps.org/ LTTE Peace Secretariat]
* [http://www.slmm.lk/ Sri Lanka Monitoring Mission]
* [http://www.theacademic.org/ Lanka Academic, news site sponsored by Sri Lankan academics worldwide]
* [http://www.sangam.org/ Sangam.org]
* [http://www.c-r.org/our-work/accord/sri-lanka/key-texts.php Texts of key agreements in the peace process and an analysis of the process by Conciliation Resources]
* [http://www.asiafoundation.org/Locations/srilanka_publications.html Report on the Sri Lankan peace process by Asiafoundation]
* [http://www.hweb.org.uk/content/view/27/4/ hWeb - Sri Lanka’s recent history of ethnic conflict and political crisis originates from its colonial legacy]
* [http://nesohr.org/human-rights-reports/StatisticsOnCiviliansAffectedByWar.pdf?PHPSESSID=8204ff9bfa58e205f71a95c3899f8835 NorthEast Secretariat report on Human rights 1974-2004]
* [http://www.hweb.org.uk/content/view/27/4/ hWeb - Sri Lanka’s recent history of ethnic conflict originates from its colonial legacy]
* [http://www.peaceandwar-ha.blogspot.com/ Peace&amp;War: Humanity Ashore Pictorial]
* [http://www.lakdiva.org/army/digital_globe.html Final Conflict Zone Maps]

{{DEFAULTSORT:Eelam War Iv}}
[[Category:21st-century conflicts]]
[[Category:History of Sri Lanka]]
[[Category:Military history of Sri Lanka]]
[[Category:Tamil Eelam]]
[[Category:Guerrilla wars]]
[[Category:Counter-terrorism in Sri Lanka]]
[[Category:Sri Lankan Civil War]]
[[Category:Eelam War IV|*]]
[[Category:Wars involving Sri Lanka]]

[[de:Bürgerkrieg in Sri Lanka]]
[[nl:Conflict in Sri Lanka]]
[[no:Etnisk konflikt i Sri Lanka]]
[[fi:Sri Lankan sisällissota]]
[[sv:Inbördeskonflikten i Sri Lanka]]
[[ta:நான்காம் ஈழப்போர்]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
