<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="1060872" ns="0" title="Coppin State University"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Infobox university
 |name              = Coppin State University
 |native_name       = 
 |image_name        = Coppin State University Logo.svg
 |image_size        = 150px
 |caption           = 
 |latin_name        = 
 |motto             = ''Nurturing Potential... Transforming Lives''
 |mottoeng          = 
 |established       = 1900
 |closed            = 
 |type              = [[Public university|Public]], [[HBCU]]
 |affiliation       = 
 |endowment         = 
 |officer_in_charge = 
 |chairman          = 
 |chancellor        = 
 |president         = Dr. Reginald S. Avery  
 |vice-president    = 
 |superintendent    = 
 |provost           = Dr. Cynthia Hammond
 |vice_chancellor   = 
 |rector            = 
 |principal         = 
 |dean              = 
 |director          = 
 |head_label        = 
 |head              = 
 |faculty           =  
 |staff             = 
 |students          = 4,000
 |undergrad         = 
 |postgrad          = 
 |doctoral          = 
 |other             = 
 |city              = [[Baltimore]]
 |state             = [[Maryland]]
 |country           = [[United States]]
 |coor              = 
 |campus            = Urban, 52 acres (154,000&amp;nbsp;m²) 
 |former_names      = 
 |free_label        = 
 |free              = 
 |sports            = 
 |colors            = 
 |colours           = 
 |nickname          = [[Eagle]]s 
 |mascot            = 
 |athletics         = 
 |affiliations      = 
 |website           = [http://www.coppin.edu www.coppin.edu]
 |logo              = 
 |footnotes         = 
}}
'''Coppin State University''' is a [[historically black college]] located in [[Baltimore]], [[Maryland]], [[United States]]. It is part of the [[University System of Maryland]]. {{Coord|39.31028|-76.65861|display=title}}

==History==
Coppin State University was founded in 1900 at what was then called ''Colored High School'' (later named ''Douglass High School'') on Pennsylvania Avenue by the Baltimore City School Board who initiated a one-year training course for the preparation of [[African-American]] elementary school teachers. By 1902, the training program was expanded to a two-year Normal Department within the high school, and seven years later it was separated from the high school and given its own principal.

In 1926, this facility for teacher training was named ''Fanny Jackson Coppin Normal School'' in honor of an African-American woman who was a pioneer in teacher education, [[Fanny Jackson Coppin]].

By 1938 the curriculum of the normal school was lengthened to four years, authority was given for the granting of the Bachelor of Science degree, and the name of the Normal School was changed to ''Coppin Teachers College''. In 1950, Coppin became part of the higher education system of Maryland under the State Department of Education, and renamed ''Coppin State Teachers College''. Two years later Coppin moved to its present {{convert|38|acre|m2|sing=on}} site on West North Avenue.

In acknowledgment of the goals and objectives of the college, the Board of Trustees ruled in 1963 that the institution's degree-granting authority would no longer be restricted to teacher education. Following this ruling, Coppin was officially renamed ''Coppin State College'', and in 1967 the first Bachelor of Arts degree was conferred. In 1988, the College became part of the newly organized University of Maryland System (now the University System of Maryland.) 

Coppin's first president (1930–1956) was Dr. [[Miles Connor]]. He was succeeded by Dr. Parlett Moore in 1956, who served until Dr. [[Calvin W. Burnett]] took over as Coppin's third president in 1970. Burnett served the institution for thirty-three years, until Coppin's fourth president, Dr. [[Stanley F. Battle]], was appointed on March 3, 2003. After Dr. Battle departed for [[North Carolina A&amp;T State University]] in 2007, Coppin's fifth president, [[Dr. Reginald Avery]] was hired.

==Coppin Facts==
*Coppin supplies education to some of the most historically oppressed populations in the United States.  Partly for this reason, the school historically has low rates of retention and graduation, with many students taking more than six years to complete BA or BS degrees. Coppin suffers one of the lowest graduation rates among U.S. colleges and universities, with some studies finding that only 19% of freshmen earn their degree.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news| url=http://www.forbes.com/2009/08/07/college-graduation-rate-opinions-colleges-09-aei.html | work=Forbes | first=Frederick M. | last=Hess | title=What's Your School's Graduation Rate? | date=2009-08-07}}&lt;/ref&gt;

*In its [http://ticas.org/pub_view.php?idx=791  2010 report], &quot;Student Debt and the Class of 2010,&quot; The Project on Student Debt at the Institute of College Access and Success (TICAS) recognized Coppin as one of 20 schools whose students graduated with low school debt. Coppin was the only University in the state of Maryland to be recognized in the report.

==Student activities==
===Student life===
Organizations participate in the Student Senate at Coppin State. There is currently a board called the SAPB (Student Activities Planning Board) which plans students events for and by the student body.

===Athletics===
[[File:CoppinStateEagles.png|thumb|right|Athletics logo]]
The Coppin State Eagles play in the [[Mid-Eastern Athletic Conference]] and in the [[NCAA]]'s Division I.  The school has men's teams in [[baseball]], [[basketball]], [[Cross country running|cross country]], [[tennis]] and [[Track and field|track]], and women's teams in basketball, [[bowling]], cross country, [[softball]], tennis, track and [[volleyball]].

In 1997, the Coppin State Men's Basketball team defeated the [[University of South Carolina]] in the opening round of the [[NCAA Men's Division I Basketball Championship]] becoming just the third #15 seed to defeat a #2 seed. In the 2007-08 season, Coppin State became the first team in NCAA [[College Basketball]] history to reach the NCAA Tournament with 20 losses.

==Community outreach==
Coppin took over nearby Rosemont Elementary School in 1998. Coppin is the only higher education institution in Maryland to manage a public school. Rosemont Elementary is in the Greater Rosemont Community, an area adjacent to the university. In 1997, the Maryland Department of Education (MSDE) had declared Rosemont to be &quot;below acceptable standards.&quot; As operator of Rosemont, Coppin hired staff and developed the school's educational program. In 2000, Rosemont Elementary first-graders led Baltimore City in largest percentile gains in first grade reading.{{Citation needed|date=August 2010}} In 2003, Rosemont was removed from MSDE's &quot;watch list&quot; citing that Rosemont has &quot;made enough progress to exit the school improvement program.&quot;{{Citation needed|date=March 2010}}

Coppin operates the Coppin State University Community Nursing Center, a fully equipped medical clinic that offers affordable health care for children and adults that is across the street from the university's campus.{{Citation needed|date=March 2010}} Coppin formed The Coppin Academy, a public charter high school for students in grades 9-12. The goal is to encourage young people to attend college.

==Accreditation==

Coppin is accredited by the Middle States Association of Colleges and Schools. In addition, the undergraduate and graduate academic programs are accredited by a number of specialized agencies. Teacher education programs are accredited by the National Council for the Accreditation of Teacher Education and are approved by the Maryland State Department of Education.

The nursing program is approved by the Maryland State Board of Examiners of Nurses and accredited by the National League of Nursing. The Social Work and Rehabilitation Counseling Education programs are accredited by the Council on Social Work Education and the Council of Rehabilitation Counseling Education, respectively.

==Notable alumni==
{{AlumniStart}}

{{Alum|name=[[Roshanda Duncan]]|year=|nota=music and film producer and independent record label CEO|ref=&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.bubblelistic.com/|title=Bubblelistic Music|publisher=bubblelistic.com|accessdate=2011-01-26}}&lt;/ref&gt;}}

{{Alum|name=[[Bishop L. Robinson]]|year=|nota=first [[African American]] Police Commissioner of Baltimore City, 1984-1987|ref}}
{{Alum|name=[[Stephanie Ready]]|year=1998|nota=first female coach in professional men's basketball|ref=&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.nba.com/news/nbdl_ready_greenville_010815.html?nav=ArticleList|title=NBDL Makes History With Female Coach|publisher=nba.com|accessdate=2011-01-26}}&lt;/ref&gt;}}

{{Alum|name=[[Larry Stewart (basketball)|Larry Stewart]]|year=|nota=former NBA player for the Washington Bullets and Seattle SuperSonics|ref}}
{{Alum|name=[[Raheem DeVaughn]]|year=|nota=R&amp;B and Neo-Soul artist|ref}}
{{Alum|name=[[Tywain McKee]]|nota= professional basketball player in [[Australian National Basketball League|Australia]] for the [[Wollongong Hawks]]|}}
{{Alum|name=[[Margaret &quot;Peggy&quot; Murphy]]|year=|nota=first black woman to chair the [[Baltimore City Delegation]]|ref}}
{{Alum|name=Cyrus|year=|nota=R&amp;B Neo-Soul artist|ref}}
{{Alum|name=[[Rafi Reavis]]|year=|nota=Philippine Basketball Association Player, [[Derby Ace Llamados]]|ref}}
{{Alum|name=[[Dorian Peña]]|year=|nota=[[Philippine Basketball Association|Philippine Basketball Association Player]], [[San Miguel Beermen]]|ref}}
{{Alum|name=[[Verda Welcome]]|year=|nota=Maryland politician and educator|ref}}
{{Alum|name=Mike Malachi|nota= Socially Conscience underground Hip-Hop Artist from Baltimore|}}
{{AlumniEnd}}

==References==
&lt;references/&gt;

==External links==
*[http://www.coppin.edu/ www.coppin.edu] - Official web site
*[http://www.coppinstatesports.com/ www.coppinstatesports.com] - Official athletics site
*[http://westsidenews.org/] Coppin's Online Student Newspaper
*[http://maps.google.com/maps?f=q&amp;hl=en&amp;geocode=&amp;q=Smith+Ave+%26+Newbury+St,+Baltimore,+MD+21209&amp;sll=37.926868,-95.712891&amp;sspn=31.365626,61.787109&amp;ie=UTF8&amp;ll=39.313449,-76.661439&amp;spn=0.015904,0.030169&amp;z=15&amp;layer=c&amp;cbll=39.309385,-76.658354&amp;panoid=Q5IH_1GG0LgBWI0wZuPqPg&amp;cbp=12,351.309681652013,,0,-1.8681427215881392 Coppin State campus on Google Street View]

{{Colleges and Universities in Maryland}}
{{HBCU}}
{{Thurgood Marshall Scholarship Fund}}
{{Mid-Eastern Athletic Conference}}
{{Maryland Sports}}

[[Category:Coppin State University| ]]
[[Category:Historically black universities and colleges in the United States]]
[[Category:American Association of State Colleges and Universities]]
[[Category:Middle States Association of Colleges and Schools]]
[[Category:Universities and colleges in Baltimore, Maryland]]
[[Category:Educational institutions established in 1900]]
[[Category:Coalition of Urban and Metropolitan Universities]]

[[no:Coppin State University]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
