<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="10638" ns="0" title="Free-software movement"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">The '''free software movement''' is a [[social movement|social]] and [[political movement]]&lt;ref&gt;[http://lists.gnu.org/archive/html/emacs-devel/2008-03/msg00635.html Richard Stallman on the nature of the Free software movement] in 2008 on emacs-devel mailing list.&lt;/ref&gt; with the goal of ensuring software users' four basic freedoms: the freedom to run their software, to study and change their software, and to redistribute copies with or without changes. The [[alternative terms for free software|alternative terms]] &quot;software libre&quot;, &quot;open source&quot;, and &quot;FOSS&quot; are associated with the free software movement.  Although drawing on traditions and philosophies among members of the 1970s [[hacker (programmer subculture)|hacker culture]], [[Richard Stallman]] founded and launched the movement in 1983 by founding the [[GNU Project]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
|title=Announcement of the GNU project
|url=http://www.gnu.org/gnu/initial-announcement.html
}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The '''free software philosophy''' at the core of the movement drew on the essence and incidental elements of what was called ''hacker culture'' by many computer users in the 1970s, among other sources.

Stallman founded the [[Free Software Foundation]] in 1985 to support the movement. 

== Philosophy ==
The philosophy of the movement is to give freedom to computer users by replacing [[proprietary software]] under restrictive licensing terms with [[free software]],&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
|title=Use Free Software
|publisher=gnu.org
|url=http://www.gnu.org/philosophy/use-free-software.html
}}&lt;/ref&gt; with the ultimate goal of liberating everyone &quot;in cyberspace&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
|title=Stallman interviewed by Sean Daly
|url=http://www.groklaw.net/article.php?story=20060625001523547
|publisher=Groklaw
|date=2006-06-23
}}&lt;/ref&gt; – that is, every computer user. Stallman notes that this action will promote rather than hinder the progression of technology, since &quot;it means that much wasteful duplication of system programming effort will be avoided. This effort can go instead into advancing the state of the art&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;Wardrip-Fruin, Noah 2003&quot;&gt;Wardrip-Fruin, Noah, and Nick Montfort, eds. ''The New Media Reader''. Cambridge: MIT Press, 2003.&lt;/ref&gt;

Members of the free software movement believe that all users of software should have the freedoms listed in the [[free software definition]]. Many of them hold that it is [[morality|immoral]] to prohibit or prevent people from exercising these freedoms and that these freedoms are required to create a decent society where software users can help each other, and to have control over their computers.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
|title=Why free software?
|url=http://www.gnu.org/philosophy/why-free.html
|publisher=gnu.org
}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Some adherents to the free software movement do not believe that [[proprietary software]] is strictly immoral.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
|title=Copyleft: Pragmatic Idealism
|publisher=gnu.org
|url=http://www.fsf.org/licensing/essays/pragmatic.html
}}&lt;/ref&gt; They argue freedom is valuable (both socially and pragmatically) as a property of software in its own right, separate from technical quality in a narrow sense.

The Free Software Foundation also believes all software needs free [[documentation]] (in particular because conscientious programmers should be able to update manuals to reflect modification that they made to the software), but deems the freedom to modify less important for other types of written works.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
|title=Free Software and Free Manuals
|url=http://www.gnu.org/philosophy/free-doc.html
|publisher=gnu.org
}}&lt;/ref&gt; Within the free software movement, the [[Floss manuals]] foundation specializes on the goal of providing such documentation. Members of the free software movement advocate that works which serve a practical purpose should also be free.{{Citation needed|date=September 2008}}

== Actions ==
=== Writing and spreading free software ===
The core work of the free software movement focused on software development. The free software movement also rejects proprietary software, refusing to install software that does not give them the freedoms of free software. According to Stallman, &quot;The only thing in the software field that is worse than an unauthorised copy of a proprietary program, is an authorised copy of the proprietary program because this does the same harm to its whole community of users, and in addition, usually the developer, the perpetrator of this evil, profits from it.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
|title=Transcript of Stallman on Free Software
|date=2006-03-09
|url=http://fsfeurope.org/documents/rms-fs-2006-03-09.en.html
|publisher=FSFE
}}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Building awareness ===
Some supporters of the free software movement take up [[public speaking]], or host a stall at software-related conferences to raise awareness of software freedom. This is seen as important since people who receive free software, but who are not aware that it is free software, will later accept a non-free replacement or will add software which is not free software.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
|title=Transcript of Stallman speaking at WSIS
|url=http://fsfe.org/en/fellows/ciaran/ciaran_s_free_software_notes/transcript_of_rms_at_wsis_on_is_free_open_source_software_the_answer#wsis--importance-of-awareness
|publisher=[[Ciarán O'Riordan]]
}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Legislation ==
A lot of lobbying work has been done against [[software patent]]s and expansions of copyright law.

The [[Venezuela]]n government implemented a free software law in January 2006. Decree No. 3,390 mandated all government agencies to migrate to free software over a two-year period.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
|url=http://www.freesoftwaremagazine.com/articles/professional_services_venezuela/
|title=Free software liberates Venezuela
|publisher=[[Free Software Magazine]] n°10
|date=2006-02-08
}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Congressmen Dr [[Edgar David Villanueva]] and Jacques Rodrich Ackerman have been instrumental in introducing in Republic of Peru bill 1609 on &quot;Free Software in Public Administration&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
|url=http://en.wikisource.org/wiki/Free_Software_in_Public_Agencies
|title=An English translation of the Free Software bill proposed in Peru
}}{{dead link|date=November 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;  The incident immediately invited the attention of Microsoft Inc, Peru, whose General Manager wrote a letter to Dr Edgar David Villanueva. Dr Villanueva's response received worldwide attention and is still seen as a classical piece of argumentation favouring use of Free Software in Governments.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.gnu.org.pe/resmseng.html|archiveurl=http://web.archive.org/web/20070829215908/http://www.gnu.org.pe/resmseng.html|archivedate=2007-08-29|title=Peruvian Congressman Edgar Villanueva writing to Microsoft about free software.}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In the USA, there have been efforts to pass legislation at the state level encouraging use of free software by state government agencies.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
|url=http://news.cnet.com/2100-1001-949241.html
|title=Open source's new weapon: The law?
}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Internal conflict ==
Like many social movements, the free software movement has ongoing internal conflict between personalities and between supporters of compromise versus strict adherence to values.

=== Open source ===
In 1998, some companies {{who|date=November 2011}} met to create a marketing campaign for free software which would focus on technology rather than ethics{{Citation needed|date=February 2008}}. After this [[Eric Raymond]] and [[Bruce Perens]] founded the [[Open Source Initiative]] (OSI), to promote the term &quot;[[open-source software]]&quot; as an [[alternative term for free software]]. OSI did not agree with the free software movement's position that non-free software is a social problem or that it is unethical,&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.urbanophile.com/arenn/hacking/fsvos.html &quot;Free&quot;, &quot;Open Source&quot;, and Philosophies of Software Ownership&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]{{dead link|date=November 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; arguing instead that it is a superior model for software development.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
|publisher=gnu.org
|url=http://www.gnu.org/philosophy/open-source-misses-the-point.html
|title=Open Source misses the point
}}&lt;/ref&gt;  

By 2005, Richard Glass considered the differences to be a &quot;serious fracture&quot; but &quot;vitally important to those on both sides of the fracture&quot; and &quot;of little importance to anyone else studying the movement from a software engineering perspective&quot; since they have had &quot;little effect on the field&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{Citation
 | author = Richard Glass
 | chapter = Standing in Front of the Open Source Steamroller
 | title = Perspectives on Free and Open Source Software
 | editor = Joseph Feller, Brian Fitzgerald, Scott A. Hissam, Karim R. Lakahani
 | publisher = MIT Press
 | year = 2005
 | isbm = 0262062461
 | pages = 89}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Some free software advocates use the term [[Free and Open Source Software]] (FOSS) as an inclusive compromise, drawing on both philosophies to bring both free software advocates and open source software advocates together to work on projects with more cohesion. Some users believe that a compromise term encompassing both aspects is ideal, to promote both the user's freedom with the software and also to promote the perceived superiority of an open source development model.

=== Stallman and Torvalds ===
The two most prominent people attached to the movement, [[Richard Stallman]] and [[Linus Torvalds]], may be seen as representatives of the value based versus apolitical philosophies, as well as the Gnu versus Linux [[coding style]]s. Paradoxically as it seems, it is the [[symbiosis]] of their works that make up a complete [[operating system]] known as [[GNU/Linux|GNU/Linux, or just Linux]].

== Measures of progress ==
[[Ohloh]], a [[web service]] founded in 2004 and launched in 2006, monitors the development activity in the [[free software community]], providing detailed [[Software metric|metrics]] and [[Quantitative analysis (finance)|quantitative analyses]] on the growth and popularity of projects and [[programming language]]s.

In January 2010, [[Global Graphics]] completed a survey [http://www.computerworlduk.com/toolbox/open-source/applications/news/index.cfm?newsid=18518] with 400 Chief Information Officers from organisations with over 1000 employees across the US and the UK that showed three quarters (76 per cent) of large organisations use free software across the enterprise with over half (51 per cent) planning to deploy more free software in 2010.

== Criticism and controversy ==
=== Is something impeding progress? ===
Some, such as [[Eric Raymond]], criticise the speed at which the free software movement is progressing, suggesting that temporary compromises should be made for long-term gains. Raymond argues that this could raise awareness of the software and thus increase the free software movement's influence on relevant standards and legislation.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.catb.org/~esr/writings/world-domination/world-domination-201.html|title=ESR's &quot;World Domination 201&quot;, on the need for more compromise by the free software movement}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Others, such as Richard Stallman, see the current level of compromise to be the bigger worry.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.gnu.org/philosophy/use-free-software.html|title=RMS on the progress of the movement and his worry about compromise}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.libervis.com/article/richard_stallman_on_world_domination_201|title=Richard Stallman on &quot;World Domination 201&quot;|quote=I cannot agree to that compromise, and my experience teaches me that it won't be temporary. ... What our community needs most is more spine in rejection of non-free software. It has far too much willingness to compromise. ... To &quot;argue&quot; in favor of adding non-free software in GNU/Linux distros is almost superfluous, since that's what nearly all of them have already done.}}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Shouldn't a programmer deserve or ask for rewards for their creativity? ===
Stallman said that this is where people get the misconception of &quot;free&quot;: there is no wrong in programmers' requesting rewards for their works. Restricting and controlling the user's decisions on use is the actual violation of freedom. Stallman defends that in some cases, monetary incentive is not necessary for motivation since the pleasure in expressing creativity is a reward in itself (such as music and art).&lt;ref name=&quot;Wardrip-Fruin, Noah 2003&quot; /&gt;

== See also ==
{{Portal|Free software}}
* [[Digital rights management]]
* [[Free Culture Movement]]
* [[Free software community]]
* [[Free Software Foundation]]
* [[GNU Manifesto]]
* [[Linux adoption]]
* [[Open Source Initiative]]
* [[Open source governance]]
* [[Open source movement]]
* Projects
** [[BadVista]]
** [[Defective by Design]]
 
==References==
{{Reflist|2}}

== Further reading ==
* David M. Berry, ''Copy, Rip, Burn: The Politics of Copyleft and Open Source'', Pluto Press, 2008, ISBN 0745324142
* Johan Soderberg, ''Hacking Capitalism: The Free and Open Source Software Movement'', Routledge, 2007, ISBN 0415955432

==External links==
* [http://www.onlamp.com/pub/a/onlamp/2005/09/29/what-is-free-software.html What is Free Software?] - Essay by Karl Fogel.
* [http://fsfeurope.org/documents/rms-fs-2006-03-09.en.html The Free Software Movement and the Future of Freedom], a 2006 lecture by Richard Stallman
* [http://www.gnu.org/philosophy/free-software-intro.html Free Software Movement intro by FSF]
* [http://www.gnu.org/philosophy/ The GNU Project Philosophy Directory], containing many defining documents of the free software movement
* [http://www.zmag.org/znet/viewArticle/4795 An interview with Stallman, &quot;Free Software as a social movement&quot;]
* Christian Imhorst, [http://www.imhorst.net/translations/anarchy-and-source-code/ ''Anarchy and Source Code - What does the Free Software Movement have to do with Anarchism?]'', (license: [[GFDL]]), 2005
* [http://www.zeuux.org/law/billxu-rms-drm.html An anti-DRM campaign] - by Bill Xu and Richard Stallman
* [http://www.apdip.net/news/fossdoc The Codebreakers - a freely redistributable movie]
* [http://www.gnu.org/music/free-software-song.html Stallman's Free Software Song]

{{FLOSS}}
{{Intellectual property activism}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Free Software Movement}}
[[Category:Copyleft media]]
[[Category:Free software culture and documents]]
[[Category:Free Software Foundation]]
[[Category:GNU Project|*]]
[[Category:Social movements]]

[[bn:মুক্ত সফটওয়্যার আন্দোলন]]
[[es:Movimiento del software libre]]
[[fa:جنبش نرم‌افزار آزاد]]
[[fr:Mouvement du logiciel libre]]
[[ko:자유 소프트웨어 운동]]
[[hr:Pokret slobodnih programa]]
[[id:Gerakan perangkat lunak bebas]]
[[ja:フリーソフトウェア運動]]
[[si:නිදහස් මෘදුකාංග ව්‍යාපාරය]]
[[simple:Free software movement]]
[[zh:自由软件运动]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
