<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="10673182" ns="0" title="Whitacre College of Engineering"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Infobox university
|name            = Edward E. Whitacre Jr. College of Engineering
|native_name     =
|latin_name      =
|image_name      = Texas Tech Red Raiders Logo.svg
|image_size      = 125px
|established     = 1925
|endowment       = $100 million
|faculty         = 155
|dean            = [[Albert Sacco|Dr. Albert Sacco, Jr.]]
|students        = 5,033
|undergrad       = 4,308
|postgrad        = 725 
|city            = [[Lubbock, Texas|Lubbock]]
|state           = [[Texas]]
|country         = [[United States|U.S.]]
|website         = [http://www.coe.ttu.edu/ Whitacre College of Engineering]
}}
[[Image:TTeng.jpg|thumb|right|228px|Engineering Key]]
The '''Edward E. Whitacre Jr. College of Engineering''' is the college of [[engineering]] at [[Texas Tech University]] in [[Lubbock, Texas]]. The engineering program has existed at Texas Tech University since 1925. Additionally, the Whitacre College of Engineering administers graduate engineering degree programs at the university's campus in [[Texas Tech University at Amarillo|Amarillo]], Texas. Many of the college's degree programs are accredited by [[ABET]]. The Whitacre College of Engineering is the first and, presently, only school in the world to offer a doctor of philosophy degree in wind science and engineering.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url=http://today.ttu.edu/2007/08/coordinating-board-approves-first-wind-science-and-engineering-doctorate/ | title=Coordinating Board Approves First Wind Science and Engineering Doctorate - News | publisher=Texas Tech University }}&lt;/ref&gt;

In August 2008, the Whitacre College of Engineering announced that it would rename its petroleum engineering department the Bob L. Herd Department of Petroleum Engineering. Herd, a Texas Tech petroleum engineering alumnus and [[Tyler, Texas]] oil man, donated $15 million to the college.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Petroleum Engineering Receives $15 Million Gift | publisher=Texas Tech University|url=http://today.ttu.edu/2008/08/petroleum-engineering-receives-15-million-gift/|accessdate=2008-08-29}}&lt;/ref&gt; The department was ranked tenth in the nation in the April 2008 edition of ''U.S. News &amp; World Report.''&lt;ref name=&quot;4-tech-grad-programs-top-100&quot;&gt;{{cite web | url=http://today.ttu.edu/2008/04/us-news-world-report-ranks-texas-tech-graduate-programs-among-best/. | title=U.S. News &amp; World Report Ranks Texas Tech Graduate Programs Among Best&quot;  | publisher=Texas Tech University}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== History ==
The Texas Technological College, present day Texas Tech University, School of Engineering was created in the fall of 1925. At that time the school consisted of 313 students and two faculty members, and was housed in the textile engineering building, now the industrial engineering building.&lt;ref name=History&gt;{{cite web | title=About the College :: History | publisher=Texas Tech University College of Engineering | url=http://www.depts.ttu.edu/coe/about/history.php | accessdate=2008-09-20}}&lt;/ref&gt; In 1928, the School of Engineering expanded and opened the west engineering building, now the electrical and computer engineering building.&lt;ref name=&quot;History&quot; /&gt; The school's civil, electrical, industrial, mechanical, and textile engineering programs were accredited by the Engineering Council for Professional Development in 1933. The chemical engineering and petroleum engineering programs were accredited in 1959 and 1960 respectively.&lt;ref name=&quot;History&quot; /&gt; The chemical engineering building opened for classes in 1960. In the early 1970s the Pulsed Power Research Center was created for the purpose of plasma research.&lt;ref name=&quot;History&quot; /&gt;

On November 12, 2008, Texas Tech announced that they received a $25 million gift from AT&amp;T and friends of Ed Whitacre in honor of former CEO and Texas Tech alumnus Edward E. Whitacre Jr.  Additionally, the college announced that it will be renamed the Edward E. Whitacre Jr. College of Engineering.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.streetinsider.com/Press+Releases/Texas+Tech+Names+College+of+Engineering+After+Former+Regent+and+AT%26amp%3BT+CEO+Edward+E.+Whitacre+Jr./4149495.html&lt;/ref&gt;

== Recognitions ==

In 2011, Texas Tech’s Whitacre College of Engineering was ranked 78th in the nation by ''U.S. News &amp; World Report''&lt;ref name=Recognitions&gt;{{cite web | publisher=Texas Tech University | url=http://www.depts.ttu.edu/coe/publications/COE_Today/COE_Today_August2010.htm |title=Whitacre College of Engineering Among America's Best| accessdate=2010-12-17}}&lt;/ref&gt;. In the magazine's 2010 graduate engineering rankings, the overall graduate engineering program moved up to 99th among 198 programs nationwide. The Department of Industrial Engineering ranked 29th in the industrial/manufacturing category.

Texas Tech University recently made the top ten in [[Forbes.com]] survey of the &quot;Best Colleges for Women and Minorities in STEM.&quot;  Texas Tech ranked the No. 7 &quot;Best Colleges for Minorities in STEM.&quot;&lt;ref name=Recognitions&gt;{{cite news | publisher=Forbes Magazine | url=http://www.forbes.com/2010/12/10/best-colleges-minorities-women-science-lifestyle-education-stem.html | accessdate=2010-12-17 | first=Natalie | last=Doss | title=Best Colleges For Women And Minorities In STEM | date=2010-12-15}}&lt;/ref&gt;

''Hispanic Business'' magazine's September 2007 issue ranked the Whitacre College of Engineering as the 14th best in the United States for [[Hispanic]] students. The college focused on enrolling students from minority backgrounds and from 2006 to 2007, freshman Hispanic enrollment increased by 23 percent.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url=http://www.depts.ttu.edu/communications/news/stories/07-10-engineering-ranking.php |title=&quot;Tech College of Engineering ranks high for Hispanic students&quot; - News | publisher=Texas Tech University}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Academic departments ==
* [[Chemical engineering|Chemical Engineering]]
* [[Civil engineering|Civil]] and [[Environmental engineering|Environmental]] Engineering
* [[Computer science|Computer Science]]
* [[Electrical engineering|Electrical]] and [[Computer engineering|Computer]] Engineering
* [[Engineering technology|Construction Engineering and Engineering Technology]]
* [[Industrial engineering|Industrial Engineering]]
* [[Mechanical engineering|Mechanical Engineering]]
* [[Petroleum engineering|Petroleum Engineering]]
[[Image:TTUcivilengineering.jpg|thumb|right|228px|Civil engineering building]]
== Research centers ==
=== Center for Advanced Intelligent Systems ===

The Center for Advanced Intelligent Systems is an interdisciplinary laboratory in the computer science department.&lt;ref name=&quot;about-cais&quot; /&gt; Currently the center conducts research in the fields of [[metadata discovery|data understanding]], [[human-centered computing]], [[computational mechanics|computational mechanics and materials]], [[declarative programming|declarative languages]] and [[software engineering]].&lt;ref name=&quot;about-cais&quot;&gt;{{cite web | url=http://www.cs.ttu.edu/~cais/about/ | title=About the Center for Advanced Intelligent Systems | publisher = Texas Tech University Center for Advanced Intelligent Systems | accessdate = 2008-09-20}}&lt;/ref&gt; The center's research on data understanding is focused on data and knowledge representation, finding causal links, and mining of large databases containing macro and micro data.&lt;ref name=&quot;about-cais&quot; /&gt; The center also researches seamless interaction of dry and wet [[intelligent agent]]s in the field of human-centered computing.&lt;ref name=&quot;about-cais&quot; /&gt; Its declarative languages research aims to develop intuitive abstractions for the construction of symbolic and numerical computations.&lt;ref name=&quot;about-cais&quot; /&gt; In the field of software engineering, the center is also conducting research on the impact of [[software architecture]], classifications of software, and [[technology transfer]] considerations on the process of [[software development]].&lt;ref name=&quot;about-cais&quot; /&gt;

=== Center for Engineering Outreach ===
The principal goal of the Center of Engineering Outreach is to promote integration of engineering education in [[K-14 education]] at the regional and state level.&lt;ref name=&quot;about-cfeo&quot;&gt;{{cite web | url=http://www.engineeringoutreach.ttu.edu/about/ | title=About the Center | publisher = Texas Tech University Center for Engineering Outreach | accessdate = 2008-09-20}}&lt;/ref&gt; The center aims to accomplish this by developing [[curriculum|curricula]], teacher training, and other academic resources designed to help K-14 educators and institutions engage students in the fields of engineering.&lt;ref name=&quot;about-cfeo&quot; /&gt; To work towards this goal, the center provides experiences that reinforce interest and learning about engineering at the K-14 level through competitions, mentoring, campus visits and early admission.&lt;ref name=&quot;about-cfeo&quot; /&gt;

=== Center for Multidisciplinary Research in Transportation ===
The Center for Multidisciplinary Research in Transportation (TechMRT) was established in 1997 to serve as a focal point between Texas Tech and the various transportation research funding organizations and programs.&lt;ref name=&quot;about-techmrt&quot;&gt;{{cite web | url=http://www.techmrt.ttu.edu/ | title=Center for Multidisciplinary Research in Transportation  | publisher=Texas Tech Center for Multidisciplinary Research in Transportation | accessdate=2008-09-20}}&lt;/ref&gt; In the area of [[pavement engineering]] and construction, the center has conducted research on constructability and material selection for surface treatments,  [[asphalt|asphalt binder]] quality assurance and best practices for pavement edge maintenance and repair.&lt;ref name=&quot;techmrt-brochure&quot;&gt;{{cite paper | author = Nash, Phillip T. | title = Multidisciplinary Research in Transportation | url=http://www.techmrt.ttu.edu/Includes/TechMRT_brochure.pdf  | format = [[PDF]]  | accessdate = 2008-09-20 }}&lt;/ref&gt; TechMRT's research in environmental and [[Right-of-way (transportation)|right-of-way]] issues has included projects on developing an integrated roadside management system for [[TxDOT]] and addressing [[fire ant]] dispersal along [[Texas]] highways.&lt;ref name=&quot;techmrt-brochure&quot; /&gt; In the field of [[geotechnical engineering]], the center also conducts research in the area of expansive solids, [[pavement (material)|pavements]] and [[foundation (engineering)|foundations]], as well as in the areas of design, construction, and performance of geotechnical systems including earth retention systems, bridge foundations and bridge approaches.&lt;ref name=&quot;techmrt-brochure&quot; /&gt; TechMRT also conducts research in the area of transportation structures including projects in innovative design and construction methods for off-system bridges, controlling [[vibration]] in [[cable-stayed bridges]], rapid bridge replacement and live load testing of a [[sandwich plate system]].&lt;ref name=&quot;techmrt-brochure&quot; /&gt; The [[traffic engineering]] branch of TechMRT was created in 2004 and has conducted research in ways to make highways and intersections safer from aggressive drivers, as well as methods to make roadways safer during [[severe weather|weather events]].&lt;ref name=&quot;techmrt-brochure&quot; /&gt;

=== Center for Nanophotonics ===	
The Center for Nanophotonics at Texas Tech is a focal point in Texas for conducting innovative research and development on active nano-scale photonic materials and devices (devices that convert light to electricity or vice versa). The center’s research areas cover a broad spectrum, ranging from basic to applied, and dealing with state-of-the-art{{Fact|date=April 2011}} nano-scale material synthesis, device processing and fundamental physics. In particular, the center’s research works have significantly advanced the fundamental understanding of III-nitride wide bandgap semiconductors (GaN, AlN, AlGaN, InGaN, and InAlGaN) and their applications (these materials promise to be effective in producing renewable energy and light more efficiently).

=== Center For Pulsed Power and Power Electronics (P&lt;sup&gt;3&lt;/sup&gt;E) ===
The Center For Pulsed Power and Power Electronics (P&lt;sup&gt;3&lt;/sup&gt;E) conducts interdisciplinary research in [[plasma (physics)|plasma]], [[pulsed power]], and [[power electronics]].&lt;ref name=&quot;P3E-homepage&quot;&gt;{{cite web | title=Center For Pulsed Power and Power Electronics | publisher=Texas Tech Center For Pulsed Power and Power Electronics | url=http://www.p3e.ttu.edu/index.asp | accessdate=2008-09-21}}&lt;/ref&gt; Plasma research at Texas Tech started in 1966, and was focused on harmonic [[ion cyclotron resonance]]s in small mirror machines, [[laser]] heating of magnetized plasmas, and pellet injection in hot dense plasmas.&lt;ref name=&quot;P3E-homepage&quot; /&gt; In 1977 a small [[Tokamak]] was constructed for the purpose of [[wave propagation]] studies in the ion cyclotron range of frequencies.&lt;ref name=&quot;P3E-homepage&quot; /&gt; In recent years, the emphasis of P&lt;sup&gt;3&lt;/sup&gt;E has shifted to theoretical wave propagation and [[turbulence]] studies, as well as applications of plasma technology to pulsed power devices, plasma synthesis of thin films, high power microwave generation, and electric space propulsion engines.&lt;ref name=&quot;P3E-homepage&quot; /&gt;

Pulsed power research at Texas Tech began in the early 1970s with studies in [[Nuclear fusion|high beta controlled thermonuclear fusion]].&lt;ref name=&quot;P3E-homepage&quot; /&gt; Based on this initial research and other research in the field the need to understand the [[Phenomenon|physical phenomena]] of pulsed power technology.&lt;ref name=&quot;P3E-homepage&quot; /&gt; Today the Texas Tech pulsed power research program at P&lt;sup&gt;3&lt;/sup&gt;E focuses on high power switching, materials studies, and high power [[microwaves]].&lt;ref name=&quot;P3E-homepage&quot; /&gt;

P&lt;sup&gt;3&lt;/sup&gt;E's power electronics research is focused on the usage of very large power [[insulated-gate bipolar transistor]]s (IGBT) for intermittent and steady state operation, the use of ultra high power [[silicon-controlled rectifier]]s (SCR) for pulsed power applications, research into advanced electrical and thermal packaging, robust controls to supply nonlinear loads such as plasma arcs, and high bandwidth monitoring and control of electric machines.&lt;ref name=&quot;P3E-homepage&quot; /&gt; The program is also working collaboratively with the [[University of Minnesota]] to develop a power electronics curriculum at the national level.&lt;ref name=&quot;P3E-homepage&quot; /&gt;

=== Nano Tech Center ===
In the Fall of 1999, the Texas Tech Nano Tech Center was formed to capitalize on the growing interest in [[sensor|microsensors]] and [[microanalysis]] systems.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url=http://www.depts.ttu.edu/ntc/About/history.php | title=Nano Tech Center History | publisher=Texas Tech Nano Tech Center | accessdate=2008-09-21}}&lt;/ref&gt; Currently the center is focused on the fundamental science and growth of advanced semiconductor materials for [[optoelectronic]] and [[CMOS]] applications, and the design, fabrication, characterization and implementation of [[microelectromechanical systems]] (MEMS).&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url=http://www.depts.ttu.edu/ntc/index.php | title=Nano Tech Center | publisher=Texas Tech Nano Tech Center | accessdate=2008-09-21}}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Murdough Center for Engineering Professionalism (National Institute for Engineering Ethics)===
The Murdough Center for Engineering Professionalism/National Institute for Engineering Ethics provides engineering ethics and professionalism education, research, and communications to students, faculty, staff, and engineers in industry, government and private practice, other professionals, and citizens in the community, state, and nation. The goal of the center is to increase the awareness of the professional and ethical obligations and responsibilities entrusted to individuals who practice engineering, and encourage cooperation among individuals, universities, professional and technical societies and business organizations with regard to engineering ethics and professionalism issues.

=== Water Resources Center===
The Water Resources Center (WRC) was established by the Texas Tech Board of Regents in 1965. Since its inception, the WRC has encouraged, conducted, and coordinated water resources research and related activities. To accomplish this purpose, WRC has adopted a multiphase approach, encompassing research, education, and public service. The WRC also provides public services, both locally and statewide, through its publications, seminars, workshops, and as a resources contact with access to water-related experts throughout the campus.

=== Wind Science and Engineering Research Center ===
The Wind Science and Engineering (WISE) Research Center at Texas Tech is an interdisciplinary research center focused on education and information outreach. Its goals are to exploit the useful qualities of wind and to mitigate its detrimental effects. The Center offers an education in wind science and engineering to develop professionals who are experts in design for windstorms and wind-induced effects. Currently WISE is composed of approximately 25 faculty associates from seven academic departments, four research associates, eight professional staff and 40 graduate students. It is also the home to the only wind science and engineering doctorate program.

==Degrees offered==
&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url=http://www.depts.ttu.edu/coe/about/degrees.php | title=Texas Tech University Whitacre College of Engineering Degree Listing | publisher=Texas Tech University Whitacre College of Engineering | accessdate=2009-09-30}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url=http://www.depts.ttu.edu/coe/academics/undergraduate.php | title=Texas Tech University Whitacre College of Engineering Undergraduate Programs | publisher=Texas Tech University College of Engineering | accessdate=2009-09-30}} {{Dead link|date=October 2010|bot=H3llBot}}&lt;/ref&gt;

*'''Bachelor of Science'''
**Chemical Engineering - B.S.Ch.E.
**Civil Engineering - B.S.C.E.
**Computer Engineering - B.S.Cmp.E.
**Computer Science - B.S.C.S.
**Construction Engineering - B.S.Con.E.
**Electrical Engineering - B.S.E.E.
**Engineering Physics - B.S.E.P.
**Environmental Engineering – BS.Env.E.
**Construction Engineering Technology - B.S.E.T.
**Mechanical Engineering Technology - B.S.E.T.
**Electrical Engineering Technology- B.S.E.T.
**Engineering Technology – B.S.E.T.
**Industrial Engineering - B.S.I.E.
**Mechanical Engineering - B.S.M.E.
**Petroleum Engineering - B.S.P.E.
**Dual degrees (offered in cooperation with other Texas Tech University colleges) 
***Architecture and Civil Engineering - B.S.
***Chemical Engineering and Computer Science - B.S.
***Electrical Engineering and Computer Science - B.S.
***Mathematics and Computer Science - B.S.

*'''Master of Science'''
**Bioengineering - M.S.Bio.
**Chemical Engineering - M.S.Ch.E.
**Civil Engineering - M.S.C.E.
**Computer Science - M.S.C.S.
**Electrical Engineering - M.S.E.E.
**Industrial Engineering - M.S.I.E.
**Manufacturing Systems Engineering - M.S.M.S.E.
**Mechanical Engineering - M.S.M.E.
**Petroleum Engineering - M.S.P.E.
**Software Engineering - M.S.S.E.
**Systems and Engineering Management - M.S.S.E.M.

*'''Master's degrees'''
**Engineering - M.Engr.
**Environmental Engineering - M.Env.E.

*'''Doctor of Philosophy'''
**Chemical Engineering - Ph.D.
**Civil Engineering - Ph.D.
**Computer Science - Ph.D.
**Electrical Engineering - Ph.D.
**Industrial Engineering - Ph.D.
**Mechanical Engineering - Ph.D.
**Petroleum Engineering - Ph.D.
**Systems and Engineering Management - Ph.D.
**Wind Science and Engineering - Ph. D.

== Notable organizations ==
[[Image:Tau Beta Pi Association seal.png|thumb|right|140px|Tau Beta Pi seal]]
* [[Alpha Omega Epsilon]] Beta Alpha chapter [http://ttu.orgsync.com/org/alphaomegaepsilon/home]
* Alpha Pi Mu chapter (Industrial Engineering Honor Society)
* [[American Institute of Chemical Engineers]] chapter
* [[American Society of Civil Engineers]] chapter
* American Society of Heating, Refrigeration and Air Conditioning Engineers
* [[American Society of Mechanical Engineers]] chapter
* [[Associated General Contractors]] chapter
* [[Association for Computing Machinery]] chapter
* Association of Women in Electrical Engineering chapter
* [[Chi Epsilon]] chapter (Civil Engineering Honor Society)
* [[Construction Specifications Institute]] chapter
* [[Engineers Without Borders]] chapter [http://www.ewb-ttu.org]
* [[Eta Kappa Nu]] Gamma Nu chapter (Electrical Engineering Honor Society)
* Human Factors and Ergonomics Society chapter
* [[Institute of Electrical and Electronic Engineers]] chapter
* [[Institute of Industrial Engineers]] chapter
* [[National Society of Black Engineers]] chapter
* [[Omega Chi Epsilon]] Alpha Omicron chapter (Chemical Engineering Honor Society)
* Pi Epsilon Tau Gamma chapter (Petroleum Engineering Honor Society)
* [[Pi Tau Sigma]] Sigma Epsilon chapter (Mechanical Engineering Honor Society)
* [[Society of Automotive Engineers]] chapter
* [http://www.techset.org/ Society of Engineering Technologists] founding chapter
* [[Society of Hispanic Professional Engineers]] chapter
* [[Society of Manufacturing Engineers]] chapter
* [[Society of Petroleum Engineers]] chapter
* [[Society of Plastics Engineers]] chapter
* [[Society of Women Engineers]] chapter
* Tau Alpha Pi chapter (Engineering Technology Honor Society)
* [[Tau Beta Pi]] Texas Beta chapter (Engineering Honor Society)
* Texas Society of Professional Engineers chapter
* [[Upsilon Pi Epsilon]] Beta chapter (Computer Science Honor Society)

==Notable people==
{{main|List of Texas Tech University people}}
=== Faculty ===
* [[M. M. Ayoub]]
* [[Kishor C. Mehta]]

==References==
{{reflist}}

==External links==
* [http://www.coe.ttu.edu/ Texas Tech University Whitacre College of Engineering website]
* [http://www.cs.ttu.edu/~cais/ Center for Advanced Intelligent Systems (CAIS)]
* [http://www.engineeringoutreach.ttu.edu/ Center for Engineering Outreach]
* [http://www.techmrt.ttu.edu/ Center for Multidisciplinary Research in Transportation (TechMRT)]
* [http://www.p3e.ttu.edu/ Center for Pulsed Power and Power Electronics (P&lt;sup&gt;3&lt;/sup&gt;E)]
* [http://www.depts.ttu.edu/ntc/index.php Nano Tech Center]
{{Texas Tech University|show=yes}}
{{coord missing|Texas}}

[[Category:Educational institutions established in 1925]]
[[Category:Engineering universities and colleges in Texas]]
[[Category:Texas Tech University colleges and schools|Engineering]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
