<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="1070309" ns="0" title="Competitive Enterprise Institute"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">
{{infobox Organization
|name         = Competitive Enterprise Institute 
|image        = CompetitiveEnterpriseInstitutelogo.png
|caption      = 
|abbreviation = CEI
|motto        = Free Markets and Limited Government
|formation    = 1984
|type         = Public Policy Think Tank
|headquarters = 1899 L St NW,&lt;br /&gt;Washington, DC 20036
|location     = [[Washington, D.C.]]
|leader_title = President
|leader_name  = [[Fred L. Smith]], Jr.
|website      = http://cei.org
}}
{{Libertarianism sidebar}}

The '''Competitive Enterprise Institute''' (CEI) is a [[non-profit]] [[think tank]] founded on March 9, 1984 in [[Washington, D.C.]] by lobbyist [[Fred L. Smith|Fred L. Smith, Jr]] to advance economic liberty and fight over-regulation by [[big government]]. CEI's stated belief is that people are best helped not by [[government regulation]] of [[commerce|commercial]] interests, but by a [[free market]]place in which entrepreneurship and innovation to truly thrive.  CEI states that it &quot;promotes liberal ideals through analysis, education, coalition-building, advocacy,&quot; and when appropriate, &quot;litigation.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Self-description on [http://www.cei.org/pdf/2987.pdf National Survey of Oncologists]&lt;/ref&gt; CEI offers or has offered analysis and advocacy on public policy issues such as energy, environment, [[biotechnology]], pharmaceutical regulation, chemical risk, telecommunications, insurance, transportation, tobacco regulation, constitutional issues, economic policy and [[securities]] law.&lt;ref&gt;[http://cei.org/issues Issues]&lt;/ref&gt;


==General activity==
CEI cites its major issues of concern as [[environmental policy]], [[regulation]] and economic liberty, [[Law|legal]] and [[constitutional]] matters, and [[health and safety]]. Among the methods used to implement the organization's agenda are various press releases and policy papers, testifying at [[government hearing|governmental hearings]], paid advertising, [[editorial]] and [[op-ed]] pieces, [[open letter]]s, books, [[NGO]] operations, and &quot;when appropriate,&quot; litigations. Their legal actions have included lawsuits challenging the constitutionality of statutes, interstate agreements, and onerous regulations, and suing government agencies to force the disclosure of public information.&lt;ref name=About&gt;{{cite web|title=About CEI|url=http://cei.org/about-cei|publisher=The Competitive Enterprise Institute|accessdate=27 November 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; 

CEI's last television ad campaign (to date), entitled ''A Bright Future For Some'',&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=rpWScO4-OH8|title=A Bright Future For Some|format=Video}}&lt;/ref&gt; focused on energy policy and global warming, criticizing policies advocated by former Vice President [[Al Gore]]. The CEI ad aired nation-wide in March and April, 2008.

==Policy areas==
===Environmental policy===
CEI is an outspoken [[anthropogenic climate change]] skeptic and an opponent of government action that would require limits on [[greenhouse gas]] emissions. It favors [[free-market environmentalism]], and supports the idea that market institutions are more effective in protecting the environment than is [[government]].

In March 1992, CEI’s founder Fred Smith said of anthropogenic climate change: &quot;Most of the indications right now are it looks pretty good. Warmer winters, warmer nights, no effects during the day because of clouding, sounds to me like we’re moving to a more benign planet, more rain, richer, easier productivity to agriculture.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.nrdc.org/globalwarming/fcons.asp |title=Consequences of Global Warming |publisher=NRDC |date= |accessdate=2011-08-25}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In May 2006, CEI's global warming policy activities attracted attention as it embarked upon an ad campaign with two television commercials [http://streams.cei.org/]. These ads promote [[carbon dioxide]] as a positive factor in the environment and argue that [[global warming]] is not a concern. One ad focuses on the message that CO&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt; is misrepresented as a [[pollutant]], stating that &quot;it’s essential to life. We breathe it out. Plants breathe it in... They call it pollution. We call it life.&quot;&lt;ref name=factcheck /&gt; The other states that the world's glaciers are &quot;growing, not melting... getting thicker, not thinner.&quot;&lt;ref name=factcheck&gt;{{cite web| last = Bank| first = Justin| date = 2006-05-26| url = http://www.factcheck.org/article395.html| title = Scientist to CEI: You Used My Research To &quot;Confuse and Mislead&quot;| publisher = FactCheck.org| accessdate = 2006-05-30}}&lt;/ref&gt; It cites ''[[Science (journal)|Science]]'' articles to support its claims. However, the editor for ''Science'' stated that the ad &quot;misrepresents the conclusions of the two cited ''Science'' papers... by selective referencing&quot;. The author of the articles, [[Curt Davis]], director of the Center for Geospatial Intelligence at the University of Missouri-Columbia, said CEI was misrepresenting his previous research to inflate their claims. &quot;These television ads are a deliberate effort to confuse and mislead the public about the global warming debate,&quot; Davis said.&lt;ref&gt;[https://cf.iats.missouri.edu/news/NewsBureauSingleNews.cfm?newsid=9842]{{dead link|date=August 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In 2009, CEI's director of energy and global warming policy told ''The Washington Post'', &quot;The only thing that's been demonstrated to reduce emissions is economic collapse&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.washingtonpost.com/wp-dyn/content/article/2009/03/05/AR2009030503293.html Europe Advises U.S. Officials on Climate] By Juliet Eilperin, Staff Writer (March 6, 2009); Page A04 - Washington Post&lt;/ref&gt;

Some of CEI's work on global warming policy includes:
* Participating in and reporting on&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|author= |url=http://www.cei.org/gencon/020,05031.cfm |title=Dispatches from the Montreal U.N. Climate Conference &amp;#124; Competitive Enterprise Institute |publisher=Cei.org |date= |accessdate=2011-08-25}}&lt;/ref&gt; the [[UNFCCC]] negotiations in [[Montreal]] as an NGO in December 2005.
* [http://cei.org/pdf/rowan_cantuar.pdf A letter] to the [[Archbishop of Canterbury]] in 2006, after the Archbishop urged Christians to take action to reduce greenhouse gas emissions. The CEI wrote that reducing these levels, even in &quot;baby steps,&quot; would &quot;result in the deaths of more people in the U.S. than global warming would worldwide.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.cei.org/gencon/003,05235.cfm |title=Leader of Anglican Church Should Consider Effects of His Comments on World's Poor &amp;#124; Competitive Enterprise Institute |publisher=Cei.org |date=2006-03-28 |accessdate=2011-08-25}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* The book ''Blue Planet in Green Shackles: What is Endangered, Climate or Freedom?''. Published in May 2008, it was written by [[Václav Klaus]], President of the [[Czech Republic]] and keynote speaker at CEI's annual dinner in 2008. Klaus argues that the politics of global warming policy are about human freedom, not the environment.
* The [[Cooler Heads Coalition]], which operates the website globalwarming.org.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.globalwarming.org |title=— Climate Change News &amp; Analysis |publisher=Globalwarming.org |date= |accessdate=2011-08-25}}&lt;/ref&gt; The chairman is [[Myron Ebell]], the Director of Energy and Global Warming Policy at CEI.

In 2010, coincident with CEI's financial ills, the pace of CEI's work on climate change slowed significantly: national advertising campaigns ceased and, through the first half of the year, CEI's only studies on the topic were two letters written to regulators.&lt;ref name=&quot;autogenerated1&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.cei.org/publications/studies |title=Studies &amp;#124; Publications &amp;#124; Competitive Enterprise Institute |publisher=Cei.org |date= |accessdate=2011-08-25}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Government regulation===
CEI uses think tank and [[advocacy]] methods to support activities in various areas, such as [[antitrust]] and [[government regulation]], in matters including [[corporate welfare]], [[Internet]] and [[Ecommerce|E-Commerce]], and [[Privacy]] and [[Security]]. They have written comments involving [[Corporate Average Fuel Economy]] (CAFE), [[rent control]], the [[Food and Drug Administration (United States)|U.S. Food and Drug Administration]] (FDA) proposals, and the [[Federal Trade Commission]] (FTC). CEI publishes an annual report on the cost burden imposed by government regulations, entitled &quot;10,000 Commandments: An Annual Snapshot of the Federal Regulatory State&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://cei.org/node/20855 |title=Ten Thousand Commandments &amp;#124; Competitive Enterprise Institute |publisher=Cei.org |date=2008-07-10 |accessdate=2011-08-25}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Legal and constitutional===
CEI has also been active in the legal aspects of antitrust and government regulation. As part of its &quot;Control Abuse of Power&quot; (CAP) project,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.controlabuseofpower.org/ |title=Controlled Power &amp;#124; Not another 1984 please |publisher=Controlabuseofpower.org |date= |accessdate=2011-08-25}}&lt;/ref&gt; CEI launched lawsuits challenging the constitutionality of the 1998 tobacco [[Master Settlement Agreement]] and the [[Public Company Accounting Oversight Board]] (PCAOB), respectively. The project's web page has been dormant since 2008.

The ''Project on Technology &amp; Innovation,'' during the period of its existence, extended CEI's efforts into new areas, including antitrust in high tech and network industries, privacy, e-commerce, intellectual property, and telecommunications.

CEI has opposed a range of regulatory intervention into commercial activities including bans on [[alcohol advertising]], fuel economy mandates and proposals to mitigate global warming. CEI supports constitutional checks over government's power over corporations.

===Health and safety===
CEI previously criticized health and safety regulation and argued through its ''Death by Regulation'' project that overregulation itself can be deadly. Previously, CEI has claimed that automotive downsizing due to federal fuel economy standards increased road accident deaths, and criticized the delayed availability of new medical therapies due to Food and Drug Administration rules. CEI scholars have also claimed that the health risks of [[secondhand smoke]] have not been adequately proven, and thus restrictions on smoking are unwarranted.&lt;ref&gt;Jerome C. Arnett, [http://www.skinandallergynews.com/article/PIIS0037633707700189/fulltext Is the public health message on secondhand smoke based on science?]{{dead link|date=August 2011}} ''Skin and Allergy News,'' 38(2):13, 2007.&lt;/ref&gt;

==CEI events==
===Annual dinner===
Every year CEI hosts an annual dinner gala and presents the [[Julian L. Simon]] Memorial Award. The Simon award honors the work of the late economist, winner of the [[Simon–Ehrlich wager]].

Award winners include:
* 2011: [[Robert J. Smith]]
* 2010: Stephen McIntyre and Ross McKitrick (joint award)
* 2009: [[Richard Tren]]
* 2008: [[Václav Klaus]]
* 2007: Indur Goklany
* 2006: [[John Stossel]]
* 2005: Barun Mitra
* 2003: [[Bjorn Lomborg]]
* 2002: Robert L. Bradley
* 2001: [[Stephen Moore (economist)|Stephen Moore]]

==CEI projects==
===Warren T. Brookes Journalism Fellowship===
In 1991, CEI established the Warren T. Brookes Fellowship to identify and train journalists who wish to improve their knowledge of environmental issues and free market economics. In this manner, the program seeks to perpetuate the legacy of Warren Brookes, who was a longtime journalist with the ''[[Boston Herald]]'' and the ''[[Detroit News]]'' and a nationally syndicated columnist.

Former and current fellows:
{| class=&quot;wikitable&quot;
|-
| '''1993-1994''' || [[Ronald Bailey]]|| '''2003-2004'''|| [[Neil Hrab]]
|-
| '''1994-1995''' || [[Michael Fumento]]|| '''2004-2005'''|| [[John Berlau]]
|-
| '''1995-1996''' || [[Michelle Malkin]]|| '''2005-2006'''|| [[Timothy Carney]]
|-
| '''1996-1997''' || [[James Bovard]]|| '''2006-2007'''|| [[Jeremy Lott]]
|-
| '''1997-1998''' || [[Jesse Walker]]|| '''2007-2008'''|| [[Lene Johansen]]
|-
| '''1999-2000''' || [[Brian Doherty (journalist)|Brian Doherty]]|| '''2008-2009'''|| [[Silvia Santacruz]]
|-
| '''2000-2001''' || [[Sean Paige]]|| '''2009-2010'''|| Ryan Young
|-
| '''2001-2002''' || [[Eileen Ciesla-Norcross]]|| '''2010-2011'''|| [[Kathryn Ciano]]
|-
| '''2002-2003''' || [[Hugo Gurdon]]||  
|}


===Bureaucrash===
[[Bureaucrash]], a special outreach and activist project of CEI, is described as an international network of pro-freedom activists working to promote a political ideology based on personal and economic freedom. Bureaucrash conducts political activism using new media, creative marketing, and education campaigns. Bureaucrash maintains a website (bureaucrash.com) and a channel on YouTube, Bureaucrash TV,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.youtube.com/user/bureaucrash |title=Канал користувача bureaucrash |publisher=YouTube |date= |accessdate=2011-08-25}}{{dead link|date=August 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; which features short videos on political topics. Begun as an independent organization, Bureaucrash was absorbed into CEI and, for a time, maintained full-time staff as part of CEI's staff. In mid-2010, coincident with CEI's financial ills, Bureaucrash transferred its only full time staffer to an open position on CEI's communications staff leaving Bureaucrash itself without any full-time staff.

===CEI Studios===
CEI Studios was the organization's video project. It produced short-format videos on current public policy issues, from the 2008 financial crisis to flood insurance to global warming and many other topics. It stopped producing original videos in 2011, using its site instead as a repository for videos of CEI events and occasional TV appearances by CEI fellows.&lt;ref&gt;[http://ceiondemand.org/ CEI On Demand]&lt;/ref&gt;

==CEI staff==
===Governance===
The organization is governed by a [[board of directors]]. The current board of directors consists of: James Curley, William Dunn, [[Michael Greve]], [[Leonard Liggio]], Thomas Gale Moore, [[Frances Smith]] (the wife of Fred L. Smith), and [[Fred L. Smith|Fred Smith]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://cei.org/board ]{{dead link|date=August 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Scholars and affiliates===
CEI lists its adjunct scholars as well as full and part-time staff members on its website and major area of responsibility on its website.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.cei.org/dyn/staff_list.cfm ]{{dead link|date=August 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; Some notable full-time staff working out of CEI's Washington, D.C. offices include:
* [[Fred L. Smith|Fred Smith]] (director) - Founder and president
* [[Myron Ebell]] (since 1999) - specializes in climate change*
* [[Sam Kazman]] General counsel

Other individuals affiliated with CEI include:
* [[Michael Greve]] (director) - [[American Enterprise Institute]]
* [[Leonard Liggio]] (director since 1994) - [[Atlas Economic Research Foundation]]
* [[Christopher C. Horner]] - attorney and author, part time staffer
* [[Steven Milloy]] - editor of JunkScience.com and FoxNews.com columnist, adjunct fellow

==Funding==
CEI is funded by donations from individuals, foundations and corporations. Past and present funders include the [[Scaife Foundations]], [[Exxon Mobil]], the [[Ford Motor Company]] Fund, [[Pfizer]], and the [[Earhart Foundation]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.washingtonpost.com/wp-dyn/content/article/2006/05/23/AR2006052301305_pf.html The Tempest] Washington Post, by Joel Achenbach, May 28, 2006&lt;/ref&gt;

In its IRS Form 990 for the fiscal year ending September 30, 2007,&lt;ref&gt;http://www.guidestar.org/FinDocuments/2007/521/351/2007-521351785-04467a1e-9.pdf&lt;/ref&gt; CEI reported revenues totaling $3,650,461, including donations from individuals, foundations and corporations. Its net assets were $2,012,478. Salaries and benefits to its top employees were reported as:
* Fred L. Smith, President, $208,935
* Marlo Lewis, Senior Fellow, $104,974
* Sam Kazman, General Counsel, $132,152

According to the website Charity Navigator, Smith's salary—at about 5 percent of CEI's budget—constitutes a larger percentage of revenues than the salaries of the heads of think tanks such as the Heritage Foundation, American Enterprise Institute, Cato Institute, and Reason Foundation.

According to page nine of a &lt;ref&gt;[http://legacy.library.ucsf.edu/cgi/getdoc?tid=jot72e00&amp;fmt=pdf&amp;ref=results report]&lt;/ref&gt; from the CEI contained on the [[University of California, San Francisco]]'s ''Legacy Tobacco Documents Library'' (LTDL), the following companies and foundations were among those listed as supporting CEI's work with annual contributions of at least $10,000, currently the CEI's &quot;Entrepreneurs&quot; level:

[[Aequus Institute]], [[Amoco]] Foundation, Inc., [[Lynde and Harry Bradley Foundation]], [[Coca-Cola Company]], [[E.L. Craig Foundation]], [[CSX Corporation]], [[Earhart Foundation]], Fieldstead and Co., FMC Foundation, [[Ford Motor Company]] Fund, [[Gilder Foundation]], [[Koch Family Foundations]] (including the [[Charles G. Koch Charitable Foundation]], David H. Koch Charitable Foundation, and [[Claude R. Lambe Charitable Foundation]]), [[Philip M. McKenna Foundation, Inc.]], [[Curtis and Edith Munson Foundation]], [[Altria Group|Philip Morris]] Companies, Inc., [[Pfizer]] Inc., [[Precision Valve Corporation]], [[Prince Foundation]], [[Rodney Fund]], [[Sheldon Rose]], [[Scaife Foundations]] ([[Carthage Foundation]] and [[Sarah Scaife Foundation]]), and [[Texaco]], Inc. ([[Texaco Foundation]]).

Other documents in the LTDL show that CEI has received funding directly from various tobacco companies.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://legacy.library.ucsf.edu/tid/qlh36e00/pdf |title=(qlh36e00) |publisher=Legacy.library.ucsf.edu |date= |accessdate=2011-08-25}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;http://legacy.library.ucsf.edu/tid/yzj60d00/pdf],[http://legacy.library.ucsf.edu/tid/pot72e00/pdf&lt;/ref&gt; For example, the listing on the Philip Morris Glossary of Names: C&lt;ref&gt;[http://legacylibrary.u.csf.edu/pm_gloss.C.html]{{dead link|date=August 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; gives the note &quot;Received public policy grant from Philip Morris (1995); Pro-market public interest group dedicated to advancing the principles of free enterprise and limited government.&quot;

[[ExxonMobil]] Corporation was a major donor to CEI, with over $2 million in contributions between 1998 and 2005. In 2002 the company gave $405,000;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www2.exxonmobil.com/files/corporate/public_policy1.pdf ]{{dead link|date=August 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; in 2004 it gave CEI $180,000 that was earmarked for &quot;global climate change and global climate change outreach.&quot; &lt;ref&gt;Exxon-Mobil 2005 annual giving (donations) report: Competitive Enterprise Institute, Washington, D.C., General Operating Support 90,000, General Operating Support* 180,000 ,Total 270,000 [http://exxonmobil.com/Corporate/Files/Corporate/giving05_policy.pdf 2005 annual giving report]{{dead link|date=August 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; In 2006, the company announced that it had ended its funding for the group.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.post-gazette.com/pg/07011/753072-28.stm |title=Exxon Mobil softens its climate-change stance |publisher=Post-gazette.com |date=2007-01-11 |accessdate=2011-08-25}}&lt;/ref&gt;{{Competitive Enterprise Institute/IRS form 990 table}}

===Financial Ills===
In late 2009, the Competitive Enterprise Institute reported a budget gap of at least $450,000&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last=Newlin |first=Eliza |url=http://undertheinfluence.nationaljournal.com/2009/11/cei-losing-money-and-a-profit.php |title=CEI Losing Money and a 'Profit Center' - Under The Influence - Under the Influence |publisher=Undertheinfluence.nationaljournal.com |date= |accessdate=2011-08-25}}&lt;/ref&gt; and the loss of its profitable Center for Risk, Regulation and Markets to the [[Heartland Institute]]. Shortly thereafter, CEI reported a year-over-year decline in its program spending coupled with a large increase in its fund-raising spending. As a result, the website [[Charity Navigator]] cut CEI's four star rating to two stars.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.charitynavigator.org/index.cfm?bay=search.summary&amp;orgid=7847 |title=Charity Navigator Rating - Competitive Enterprise Institute |publisher=Charitynavigator.org |date= |accessdate=2011-08-25}}&lt;/ref&gt; CEI also contracted its web presence significantly in the wake of its financial ills leaving sites including [[controlabuseofpower.org]], [[ethanolfacts.org]], and [[enjoybottledwater.org]] dormant. In 2010, furthermore, CEI's production of reports and papers dropped significantly. Whereas the think tank had produced 20 studies during the first six months of 2009, it produced only 10 during the first six months of 2010.&lt;ref name=&quot;autogenerated1&quot;/&gt;

==References==
{{Reflist|30em|refs=
}}

==External links==
* [http://www.cei.org/ CEI homepage]
* [http://www.ceiopenmarket.org/ CEI Open Market] Official blog
** [http://www.globalwarming.org/ GlobalWarming.org] Cooler Heads Coalition homepage
** [http://ceiondemand.org/ CEI Studios] a CEI project
** [http://bureaucrash.com/ Bureaucrash] a CEI project
** [http://www.youtube.com/user/bureaucrash Bureaucrash TV]{{dead link|date=August 2011}} a CEI project

[[Category:Organizations of environmentalism skeptics and critics]]
[[Category:Think tanks established in 1984]]
[[Category:Non-profit organizations based in Washington, D.C.]]
[[Category:Political advocacy groups in the United States]]
[[Category:Political and economic think tanks in the United States]]
[[Category:Libertarian think tanks]]
[[Category:Libertarian organizations based in the United States]]
[[rw:Competitive Enterprise Institute]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
