<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="10758727" ns="0" title="List of Epcot attractions"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">'''[[Epcot]]''' is a [[theme park]] located at the [[Walt Disney World Resort]]. The term &quot;attractions&quot; is used by [[The Walt Disney Company|Disney]] as a catch-all term for rides, shows, and exhibits.

==Future World==
===Current Future World attractions===
* '''[[Spaceship Earth (Epcot)|Spaceship Earth]]''' (Sponsored by [[Siemens AG]]) is a ride through an eighteen-story-tall [[Geodesic dome|geodesic sphere]], located at the front entrance of Epcot. The ride tells the history of communication, with a focus on the development of cultures and the future of technologies.
** '''[[Spaceship Earth (Epcot)#Project Tomorrow: Inventing the Wonders of the Future|Project Tomorrow: Inventing the Wonders of the Future]]''' is an interactive post show following Spaceship Earth showcasing many &quot;[[virtual reality]]&quot; games.

* '''[[Innoventions (Epcot)|Innoventions]]''', located in two pavilions ('''Innoventions East''' and '''Innoventions West'''), houses hands-on exhibitions from various science-and-technology oriented companies.

* '''[[Universe of Energy#Ellen's Energy Adventure|Universe of Energy: Ellen's Energy Adventure]]''' is a show about [[energy]] and how people generate and harvest it. The show is named for its star, [[Ellen DeGeneres]].

* '''[[Mission: SPACE]]''' (Sponsored by [[Hewlett-Packard]]) is a [[centrifuge]]-based ride that simulates the training required to be a member of the [[NASA|space program]].

* '''[[Test Track]]''' (Sponsored by [[General Motors]]) is a high-speed ride that takes guests through an automotive factory's testing grounds.

* '''[[Imagination!]]''' is a pavilion that contains attractions that highlight imagination.
** '''[[Journey into Imagination with Figment]]''' is a ride that encourages guests to use their senses and their imagination.
** '''[[ImageWorks (Disney)|ImageWorks]]''' is an interactive post show following Journey into Imagination.
** '''[[Captain EO Tribute]]''' is a 3-D show starring Michael Jackson as a commander of a lovable crew of misfits on a special mission in this 17&amp;nbsp;minute space fantasy adventure.

* '''[[The Land (Disney)|The Land]]''' is a pavilion that contains attractions that detail how we interact with our natural environment.
** '''[[Living with the Land]]''' takes visitors on a boat tour through a working [[greenhouse]].
** '''[[Soarin' Over California#Epcot's version|Soarin']]''' is a [[hang glider]] simulator that &quot;flies&quot; over various areas of California.
** '''[[Circle of Life: An Environmental Fable]]''' is a movie that shows [[symbiosis]].

* '''[[The Seas with Nemo &amp; Friends]]''' is one of the largest [[aquariums]] in the world. The pavilion contains two attractions:
** '''The Seas with Nemo &amp; Friends''', a new ride chronicling Nemo's epic journey, featuring projection technology that makes it appear as though Nemo, Dory, and Marlin are swimming with the live fishes.
** '''[[Turtle Talk with Crush]]''', an interactive show starring Crush, the Sea Turtle, from [[Walt Disney Pictures|Disney]]/[[Pixar]]'s film ''[[Finding Nemo]]''.

* The '''Odyssey Restaurant''' in Showcase Plaza. Used for conferences, and previously a fast-food location.

===Initial Future World Attractions===
{|class=&quot;wikitable&quot;
|-
! Name
! Opening- Closing Date
! Description
! Current Attraction
! Notes
|-
| '''[[Spaceship Earth (Epcot)|Spaceship Earth]]'''|| 1982–present || || 
 || 
|-
| '''[[CommuniCore]]''' || 1982–1994 ||The pavilion served as [[Epcot|EPCOT Center]]'s version of [[Main Street, U.S.A.]], as it brought together nearly all of the sponsors in the surrounding pavilions under one roof to serve as a supplemental experience to the overall visit to [[Future World]].|| [[Innoventions]] || The pavilions were renamed [[Innoventions]] in 1994 when all new exhibits were installed. In [[2007]] all signage was changed to incorporate a new Innoventions logo.
|-
| '''[[Horizons (Epcot attraction)|Horizons]]'''  || 1983–1999 || Guests visiting the pavilion were advised that, &quot;If we can dream it, we can do it.&quot; Featuring a series of scenes incorporating [[Animatronic]] figures in futuristic endeavors and its vision of how the future might develop technologically || [[Mission: Space]]  || The building was later demolished and the site is now home to [[Mission: Space]].
|-
| '''[[Journey Into Imagination#Journey Into Imagination (1983-1998)|Journey Into Imagination]]'''   || 1983–1999 || A ride that encouraged guests to use their imagination, as led by the [[Animatronic]] characters Dreamfinder and Figment. || [[Journey into Imagination with Figment]]  || It has been through three incarnations over the years, two of them featuring Figment, a small purple dragon, as a character.
|-
| '''[[The Seas with Nemo and Friends|The Living Seas]]'''   || 1986–2006 || The concept of the building was to take visitors under the ocean to 'Sea Base Alpha'. They would then disembark into the main exhibit area where they could interact with various multimedia displays. || [[The Seas with Nemo &amp; Friends]]   || It was changed dramatically after the 2006 rehab. The queue, Hydrolators, The Seas film and Seacab ride were removed for a theme based on Finding Nemo, and the attraction renamed [[The Seas with Nemo and Friends]].
|-
| '''[[World of Motion]]'''   || 1982–1996 || It was a whimsical look at the history and achievements in transportation ranging from cavemen having to use foot power, the invention of the wheel, [[Leonardo da Vinci]]'s plans for gliders and flying machines, [[Christopher Columbus]] setting sail for [[Americas|America]], and the first automobiles. || [[Test Track]]  || The building was kept but was replaced by Test Track
|-
| '''[[The Land (Disney)|The Land]]'''  || 1982–1995 || It explored how humans can both use the land for their benefit, and how they can also destroy it. Future Technology in better preserving the land was also explored in the pavilion, along with a focus on the celebration of the land itself. || [[The Land (Epcot)|Living with the Land]] || Although the building and the focus has largely stayed the same, the initial attractions were all removed by 1995.
|-
| '''[[Universe of Energy#Original attraction|Universe of Energy]]''' ||  1982–1996 || The original attraction featured numerous films that presented information on the subject of energy in a serious fashion as well as a ride through a primeval diorama complete with animatronic dinosaurs. || [[Universe of Energy|Ellen's Energy Adventure]]  || The current show stars Ellen DeGeneres, Bill Nye 'The Science Guy,' and Alex Trebek. It deals with energy, how energy is produced, the history of energy production, and the search for new energy resources. In particular it focuses on the origins of fossil fuels such as petroleum, coal and natural gas.
|-
| '''[[Wonders of Life]]''' || 1989–2007 || The pavilion was devoted to health and body related attractions. It is located inside a golden colored dome between Mission: SPACE and the Universe of Energy. || ''N/A'' || As of March 2010, the pavilion hasn't operated regularly for over 6 years, and although the space is sometimes used for special events, the attractions within have remained closed, and since been partially removed.
|}

===Other Past Attractions===
{|class=&quot;wikitable&quot;
|-
! Name
! Opening-Closing Date
! Description
|-
| '''[[Journey Into Imagination#Journey Into Your Imagination (1999-2001)|Journey Into Your Imagination]]''' || 1999–2001 || this version of the ride removed Dreamfinder and downplayed Figment's role. The ride was more closely tied to the film [[Honey, I Shrunk the Audience]] (which played in the pavilion's theater), by re-theming the ride as a trip to the Imagination Institute and casting [[Eric Idle]] as his character from the 3D film.
|-
| '''[[Millennium Village]]''' || 1999–2001 || It was the centerpiece of Disney's Millennium Celebration. The 60,000-square-foot (5,600 m2) pavilion opened up its doors to the public on October 1, 1999 and was closed down on January 1, 2001. It is, however, used on occasion. Along with the Odyssey Restaurant, the Millennium Village (now named &quot;World ShowPlace&quot;) is used in the Epcot Food and Wine Festival.
|-
| '''[[Honey, I Shrunk the Audience!]]''' || 1994–2010 || This was a 3D movie that was part of the [[Honey, I Shrunk the Kids (franchise)|''Honey, I Shrunk the Kids'' franchise]]. It closed in June 2010 to make way for [[Captain EO]].
|}

===Future World entertainment===
* '''[[Fountain of Nations]]''' (Original:1982-1992/Refurbished 1993–present), an elaborate [[Musical fountain|fountain that performs to music]] every 15&amp;nbsp;minutes. Shows are presented in no particular order and include music by [[John Tesh]], [[Yanni]], and from Disney movies such as ''[[The Rescuers Down Under]]'' and ''[[The Rocketeer (film)|The Rocketeer]]''.
''
* '''Splashtacular'''- A show that debuted in 1994 and included the [[Fountain of Nations]] and ended a few months later. The attraction was closed due to the water from the fountain blowing onto the stage, soaking the performers and the guests. It also would cause the walkways to get very crowded, making it hard for people to get through.

* '''EPCOT Computer Central''', an area in [[CommuniCore]] that featured two shows:
** '''The Astuter Computer Revue''' (1982–1984), presented by [[Sperry Corporation]].
** '''Backstage Magic''' (1984–1994), a show about how computers controlled park operations around Walt Disney World. Presented by [[Unisys]].

* '''Disney Vision Adventure: In Virtual Reality''', a show that took place in [[Innoventions]] about how Disney movies are made using CGI technology featuring [[Iago]] from ''[[Aladdin (1992 Disney film)|Aladdin]]''.

* '''[[Future Corps]]''' was a drum and bugle corps band which entertained guests with a high energy instrumental show. The group performed at Epcot from 1982-2006.

* '''Future World Brass''', a high energy brass and percussion ensemble that performed at Epcot from 1982-2000.

* '''JAMMitors''', trashcan percussion band that plays daily.

==World Showcase==
===Current World Showcase attractions===
* '''[[IllumiNations: Reflections of Earth]]''': A nightly fireworks and laser show that tells a story encompassing the creation of Earth to celebrating the people of the world.

[[File:Flag of Mexico.svg|right|50px|border]]
* '''[[Mexico (Epcot)|Mexico]]'''
** '''[[Gran Fiesta Tour Starring The Three Caballeros]]''' a boat ride adventure with Jose Carioca, Panchito Pistoles, and Donald Duck.
** '''[[Kim Possible World Showcase Adventure]]'''

[[File:Flag of Norway.svg|right|50px|border]]
* '''[[Norway (Epcot)|Norway]]'''
** '''[[Maelstrom (ride)|Maelstrom]]''' is a boat ride into Norway's past and present.
** '''Kim Possible World Showcase Adventure'''

[[File:Flag of the People's Republic of China.svg|right|50px|border]]
* '''[[China (Epcot)|China]]'''
** '''[[Reflections of China]]''' is a [[Circle-Vision 360°]] movie exploring China's history and scenery.
** '''Kim Possible World Showcase Adventure'''

[[File:Flag of Germany.svg|right|50px|border]]
* '''[[Germany (Epcot)|Germany]]'''
** '''Kim Possible World Showcase Adventure'''

[[File:Flag of Italy.svg|right|50px|border]]
* '''[[Italy (Epcot)|Italy]]'''

[[File:Flag of the United States.svg|right|50px|border]]
* '''[[The American Adventure (Epcot)|The American Adventure]]'''
** '''[[The American Adventure]]''' is a stage show about American history using [[audio-animatronic]]s.

[[File:Flag of Japan.svg|right|50px|border]]
* '''[[Japan (Epcot)|Japan]]'''
** '''Kim Possible World Showcase Adventure'''

[[File:Flag of Morocco.svg|right|50px|border]]
* '''[[Morocco (Epcot)|Morocco]]'''

[[File:Flag of France.svg|right|50px|border]]
* '''[[France (Epcot)|France]]'''
** '''[[Impressions of France|Impressions de France]]''' is a panoramic movie which visits many of France's cities and historical structures.
** '''Kim Possible World Showcase Adventure'''

[[File:Flag of the United Kingdom.svg|right|50px|border]]
* '''[[United Kingdom (Epcot)|United Kingdom]]'''
** '''Kim Possible World Showcase Adventure'''

[[File:Flag of Canada.svg|right|50px|border]]
* '''[[Canada (Epcot)|Canada]]'''
** '''[[O Canada! (Disney)|O Canada!]]''' is a [[Circle-Vision 360°]] movie of Canada's cities and scenery.

===Past World Showcase attractions===
* '''[[Mexico (Epcot)|Mexico]]'''
** '''[[El Rio del Tiempo]] (The River of Time)''' (October 1, 1982–2007), was a boat ride that shows many aspects of Mexican life, history, and celebrations.

* '''[[Canada (Epcot)|Canada]]'''
** '''Portraits of Canada''', this film from [[Expo 86]] in Canada was played temporarily instead of &quot;O Canada&quot;
** '''Canada 67'''
** '''[[O Canada! (Disney)|O Canada!]]''' (October 1, 1982–2007), the [[Circle-Vision 360°]] film was updated in 2007.

* '''[[China (Epcot)|China]]'''
** '''Wonders of China''' ( October 1, 1982–March 26, 2003), the [[Circle-Vision 360°]] film was updated in 2003.

* '''[[Millennium Village]]''' (October 1, 1999–2000), a large building built for the [[Millennium Celebration]] with many small attractions that represent countries not in World Showcase.

===World Showcase entertainment===
====Fireworks Shows====
* '''[[IllumiNations#Carnival de Lumiere|Carnival de Lumiere]]''' (premiered October 23, 1982)
* '''[[A New World Fantasy]]''' (premiered [[1983]])
* '''[[Laserphonic Fantasy]]''' (premiered June 9, 1984)
* '''[[IllumiNations]]''' (January 30, 1988 - September 20, 1996)
* '''[[IllumiNations#IllumiNations 25 (A)|IllumiNations 25 (A)]]''' (September 21, 1996 - May 18, 1997)
* '''[[IllumiNations#IllumiNations 25 (B)|IllumiNations 25 (B)]]''' (May 19, 1997 - January 31, 1998)
* '''[[IllumiNations#IllumiNations (98)|IllumiNations (98)]]''' (February 1, 1998 - September 21, 1999)
* '''Surprise in the Skies''' (1991–1992) &lt;ref name=&quot;Surprise&quot;&gt;http://allears.net/tp/ep/e_sky1.htm&lt;/ref&gt;
* '''Skylaidescope''' (1985–1987) &lt;ref name=&quot;Skyleidoscope&quot;&gt;http://allears.net/tp/ep/skyleido.htm&lt;/ref&gt; Planes were launched from the [[Epcot Center Ultralight Flightpark]].
* '''[[IllumiNations: Reflections of Earth]]''' (1999–present), previously &quot;IllumiNations 2000: Reflections of Earth&quot;, created for the Millennium Celebration

====Parades====
* '''[[Tapestry of Nations]]''' (1999–2001), a parade created for the Millennium Celebration
* '''[[Tapestry of Nations|Tapestry of Dreams]]''' (2001–2003), a refurbished version of Tapestry of Nations replacing the Sage of Time, the parade's original host/narrator with three Dreamseekers

====Live and Musical Entertainment====
Acts with * are no longer performing

* '''[[Mexico (Epcot)|Mexico]]'''
** '''[[Mariachi Cobre]]''', mariachi band

* '''[[Norway (Epcot)|Norway]]'''
** '''[[Spelmanns Gledje]]''', Norwegian folk music *

* '''[[China (Epcot)|China]]'''
** '''[[Si Xian]]''', traditional Chinese music played on authentic instruments
** '''[[Dragon Legend Acrobats]]''' group of young Chinese acrobats

* '''[[Germany (Epcot)|Germany]]'''
** '''[[Oktoberfest Musikanten]]''', dinner theater

* '''[[Italy (Epcot)|Italy]]'''
** '''[[Sergio (Epcot)|Sergio]]''', juggler
** '''[[Lou E. G.]]*''', mime, comedian, magician, street performer
** '''[[Rondo Veneziano]]*''', Electronic Classical Music Group
** '''[http://www.novaeramusic.com Nova Era]*''', Electronic Classical Music group (now at Downtown Disney)
** '''[[Imaginum A statue Act]]*''' Living statue act

* '''[[The American Adventure (Epcot)|The American Adventure]]'''
** '''[[Voices of Liberty]]''', [[a cappella]] choir singing traditional American songs
** '''[[Spirit of America Fife &amp; Drum Corps]]'''
** '''[[American Vybe]]*''' contemporary a capella group performing American R&amp;B, Jazz, and Swing

* '''[[Japan (Epcot)|Japan]]'''
** '''[[Matsuriza]]''', [[Taiko]] drummers
** '''[[Miyuki (Epcot)|Miyuki]]''', candy artist

* '''[[Morocco (Epcot)|Morocco]]'''
** '''[[MoRockin]]''', Arabic rhythms fused with rock n' roll
** '''[[Restaurant Marrakesh]]''', Traditional Moroccan music and dance inside restaurant

* '''[[France (Epcot)|France]]'''
** '''[[Serveur Amusant]]''', the comical waiter

* '''[[United Kingdom (Epcot)|United Kingdom]]'''
** '''[[The British Invasion (Epcot)|The British Invasion]]''', a '60s British rock-and-roll revival
** '''[[The Hat Lady]]''', pianist in the Rose 'n Crown Pub
** '''[[Jason Wethington]]''', Magician, appearing at the Rose and Crown Pub

* '''[[Canada (Epcot)|Canada]]'''
** '''[[Off Kilter]]''', a Celtic rock band

==EPCOT celebrations==
* '''[[Millennium Celebration]]''' (1999–2000), this included:
** A [[Mickey Mouse]] hand holding a wand over [[Spaceship Earth (Epcot)|Spaceship Earth]] with the text &quot;2000&quot; (wand then changed to say &quot;Epcot&quot;; 1999–2007)
** Millennium Central: a rethemed area in front of the Fountain of Nations. Includes the Pin Station.
** '''[[IllumiNations: Reflections of Earth|IllumiNations 2000: Reflections of Earth]]''', the new nightly fireworks show. Its name was changed to IllumiNations: Reflections of Earth after the Millennium Celebration.
** '''[[Tapestry of Nations]]''' (1999–2001): a new parade about unity and world peace featuring large puppets.
** '''[[Millennium Village]]''' (1999–2000): a large building with many small attractions that represent other countries that are not in World Showcase.

* '''100 Years of Magic''' (2001), part of the [[Walt Disney World Resort]] celebration.
** '''[[Tapestry of Nations|Tapestry of Dreams]]''' (2001–2002), a refurbished version of Tapestry of Nations replacing the Sage of Time, the parade's original host/narrator with three Dreamseekers.

* '''25th Anniversary''' (October 1, 2007): included a re-dedication of the park, presentations by [[Marty Sklar]], an exhibit showing the history of EPCOT, fan gatherings, and was concluded by a special IllumiNations: Reflections of Earth which added an extra few minutes of fireworks. Classic Epcot songs ranging from ''We've Just Begun to Dream'' from opening day to ''Celebrate the Future Hand in Hand'' from the Millennium Celebration were played around the entrance and around the park all day.

==See also==
* [[List of Disney theme park attractions]]
* [[List of lands at Disney theme parks]]
* [[List of Magic Kingdom attractions]]
* [[List of Disney's Hollywood Studios attractions]]
* [[List of Disney's Animal Kingdom attractions]]

==References==
{{reflist}}

==External links==
* [http://disneyworld.disney.go.com/parks/epcot/ Walt Disney World Resort - Epcot]
* [http://disneyworld.disney.go.com/parks/epcot/attractions Walt Disney World Resort - Epcot Attractions]
* [http://disneyworld.disney.go.com/parks/epcot/dining Walt Disney World Resort - Epcot Dining]
* [http://pages.prodigy.net/stevesoares/EPCOT.htm Epcot Live Entertainment] Frequently updated list of Live Entertainment for Epcot. Includes Schedules.

{{Epcot attractions}}

[[Category:Lists of Disney attractions|Epcot]]
[[Category:Epcot|*]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
