<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="107597" ns="0" title="Altadena, California"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Refimprove|date=December 2007}}
{{Infobox settlement
&lt;!-- Basic info  ----------------&gt;
|name            = Altadena
|other_name               =
|native_name              = &lt;!-- for cities whose native name is not in English --&gt;
|nickname                 =
|settlement_type          = [[census-designated place]]
|motto                    =
&lt;!-- images and maps  -----------&gt;
|image_skyline            =Eaton canyon from the air.jpg
|imagesize                = 
|image_caption            =Aerial view of Altadena and [[Eaton Canyon]]
|image_flag               =
|flag_size                =
|image_seal               =
|seal_size                =
|image_shield             =
|shield_size              =
|image_blank_emblem       =
|blank_emblem_size        =
|image_map                = LA County Incorporated Areas Altadena highlighted.svg
|mapsize                  = 250x200px
|map_caption              = Location of Altadena in [[Los Angeles County, California|Los Angeles County]], [[California]]
|image_map1               =
|mapsize1                 =
|map_caption1             =
|image_dot_map            =
|dot_mapsize              =
|dot_map_caption          =
|dot_x                    =
|dot_y                    =
|pushpin_map              =California &lt;!-- the name of a location map as per http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Template:Location_map --&gt;
|pushpin_label_position   = &lt;!-- the position of the pushpin label: left, right, top, bottom, none --&gt;
|pushpin_map_caption      =Location in California
|pushpin_mapsize          =
&lt;!-- Location ------------------&gt;
|coordinates_region       = US-CA
|subdivision_type         = [[List of countries|Country]]
|subdivision_name         = {{USA}}
|subdivision_type1        = [[Political divisions of the United States|State]]
|subdivision_name1        = {{flag|California}}
|subdivision_type2        = [[List of counties in California|County]]
|subdivision_name2        = [[Los Angeles County, California|Los Angeles]]
|subdivision_type3        =
|subdivision_name3        =
|subdivision_type4        =
|subdivision_name4        =
&lt;!-- Politics -----------------&gt;
|government_footnotes     =
|government_type          =
|leader_title             =
|leader_name              =
|leader_title1            = &lt;!-- for places with, say, both a mayor and a city manager --&gt;
|leader_name1             =
|leader_title2            =
|leader_name2             =
|leader_title3            =
|leader_name3             =
|leader_title4            =
|leader_name4             =
|established_title        = &lt;!-- Settled --&gt;
|established_date         =
|established_title2       = &lt;!-- Incorporated (town) --&gt;
|established_date2        =
|established_title3       = &lt;!-- Incorporated (city) --&gt;
|established_date3        =
&lt;!-- Area------------------&gt;
|area_magnitude           =
| unit_pref               =US
| area_footnotes          = &lt;ref&gt;[http://www.census.gov/geo/www/gazetteer/files/Gaz_places_national.txt U.S. Census]&lt;/ref&gt;
| area_total_sq_mi        = 8.729
| area_land_sq_mi         = 8.713
| area_water_sq_mi        = 0.016
| area_total_km2          = 22.609
| area_land_km2           = 22.566
| area_water_km2          = 0.043
| area_water_percent      = 0.19
| area_note               = 
|area_urban_km2           =
|area_urban_sq_mi         =
|area_metro_km2           =
|area_metro_sq_mi         =
|area_blank1_title        =
|area_blank1_km2          =
|area_blank1_sq_mi        =
&lt;!-- Population   -----------------------&gt;
|population_as_of         = 2010
|population_footnotes     =
|population_note          =
|population_total         = 42777
|population_density_km2   = auto
|population_density_sq_mi = auto
|population_metro         =
|population_density_metro_km2     =
|population_density_metro_sq_mi   =
|population_urban                 =
|population_density_urban_km2     =
|population_density_urban_sq_mi   =
|population_blank1_title          =
|population_blank1                =
|population_density_blank1_km2    =
|population_density_blank1_sq_mi  =
&lt;!-- General information  ---------------&gt;
|timezone                 = [[Pacific Time Zone|PST]]
|utc_offset               = -8
|timezone_DST             = PDT
|utc_offset_DST           = -7
|coordinates_display      = inline,title
|coordinates_type         = region:US_type:city
|latd = 34 |latm = 11 |lats = 19 |latNS = N
|longd = 118 |longm = 8 |longs = 5 |longEW = W
|elevation_footnotes      = &lt;!--for references: use &lt;ref&gt; &lt;/ref&gt; tags--&gt;
|elevation_m              = 414
|elevation_ft             = 1358
&lt;!-- Area/postal codes &amp; others --------&gt;
|postal_code_type         = [[ZIP code]]s
|postal_code              = 91001, 91003
|area_code                = [[Area code 626|626]]
|blank_name               = [[Federal Information Processing Standard|FIPS code]]
|blank_info               = 06-01290
|blank1_name              = [[Geographic Names Information System|GNIS]] feature ID
|blank1_info              = 1652662
|website                  =
|footnotes                =
}}
'''Altadena''' is an [[unincorporated area|unincorporated]]&lt;ref&gt;Los Angeles County publication: “Unincorporated Areas within the County of Los Angeles”, [http://ceo.lacounty.gov/forms/Unincorp%20Alpha%20Web.pdf Altadena listed by Los Angeles County government office, as an unincorporated area], “Los Angeles County publication: ‘Unincorporated Areas within the County of Los Angeles’”, verified September 27, 2010&lt;/ref&gt; area&lt;ref&gt;Los Angeles County Office of Unincorporated Area Services, [http://ceo.lacounty.gov/OUAS/ Altadena listed by Los Angeles County government office, as an unincorporated area], “Los Angeles County Office of Unincorporated Area Services”, verified September 27, 2010&lt;/ref&gt; and [[census-designated place]] in [[Los Angeles County, California|Los Angeles County]], [[California]], [[United States]], approximately {{convert|14|mi|km}} from the [[downtown Los Angeles]] Civic Center, and directly north of the city of [[Pasadena, California]].  The population was 42,777 at the 2010 census, up from 42,610 at the 2000 census.

==History==
[[Benjamin Eaton]] first developed water sources from the [[Arroyo Seco]] and [[Eaton Canyon]] from the mid-1860s from his vineyard near the edge of Eaton Canyon. This made development of Altadena, Pasadena, and South Pasadena possible. He did the work for [[Benjamin Davis Wilson|B.D. Wilson]] and Dr. John Griffin, who jointly owned the Mexican land grant of the [[Rancho San Pascual]], about {{convert|14000|acre|km2}} that comprised the future sites of the three communities. They hoped to develop and sell part of this in a real estate scheme called the San Pasqual Plantation. It failed by 1870 despite the irrigation ditch Eaton engineered for the partners that drew water from around the site of present day [[Jet Propulsion Laboratory]] in the Arroyo Seco. The failure had two main causes: few believed citrus or other crops could thrive so close to the mountains, and the land was relatively inaccessible.

Eaton then tried to sell the land for the partners, and in late 1873 helped broker a deal with [[Daniel Berry]], who represented a group of investors from Indiana to purchase {{convert|4000|acre|km2}} of the rancho. Although this included the land of present day Altadena, they developed the {{convert|2500|acre|km2}} section further south into Pasadena. In 1881, the land that became Altadena was sold to the Woodbury brothers, John and Fred, who launched the subdivision of Altadena in 1887 just as Southern California's great land boom busted. The land remained mostly agricultural. However, several millionaires (mainly from Chicago) built mansions along [[Mariposa Street]], and a small community slowly developed through the 1890s and into the new century.

{{USCensusPop
| 1960=40568
| 1970=42415
| 1980=40983
| 1990=42658
| 2000=42610
| 2010=42777
| footnote=sources:&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
  |url=http://www.census.gov/prod/www/abs/decennial/index.html
  |title=CENSUS OF POPULATION AND HOUSING (1790-2000)
  |publisher=[[U.S. Census Bureau]]
  |accessdate=2010-07-17}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;http://factfinder2.census.gov/faces/tableservices/jsf/pages/productview.xhtml?pid=DEC_10_PL_GCTPL1.ST13&amp;prodType=table US Census Bureau&lt;/ref&gt;
}}
[[Image:woodburys.jpg|frame|right|[[Woodbury-Story House|Home of Capt. John Woodbury, built 1882, still standing and occupied]].]]

In 1880, Capt. Frederick Woodbury and his brother John Woodbury of [[Marshalltown, Iowa]], purchased {{convert|937|acre|km2}} known as the Woodbury Ranch.  John Woodbury established the Pasadena Improvement Company in 1887 with a plot plan of residential development referred to as the Woodbury Subdivision.  They contacted Byron O. Clark who established a nursery in the foothills in 1875 and had since moved away.  He called his nursery &quot;Altadena Nursery&quot;, a name he coined from the Spanish &quot;alta&quot; meaning &quot;upper&quot; and &quot;dena&quot; from Pasadena.  Woodbury asked if he could use the name &quot;Altadena&quot; for his subdivision and Clark agreed.

The newly sprouted community of Altadena immediately began to attract millionaires from the East. In 1887 [[Andrew McNally]], the printing magnate from Chicago and his good friend Col. [[George Gill Green|G. G. Green]] had built mansions on what was to become Millionaire's Row, Mariposa Street near Santa Rosa. Newspaper moguls William Armiger Scripps and William Kellogg built side by side just east of [[Fair Oaks Avenue]]. The grandson of Andrew McNally, [[Wallace Neff]], became a famous Southern California architect. He started his career in Altadena with the design and construction of St. Elizabeth of Hungary Catholic Church ( parish est.1918) which was dedicated in October 1926.

Over the years Altadena has been subject to attempted annexation by Pasadena. Annexation was stopped in 1956 by community campaigns though it has been resurrected several times since by Pasadena without success. Had the annexation succeeded, Pasadena would be the [[Largest cities in the US|108th largest city]] in the United States.

While Altadena long refused wholesale annexation by neighboring [[Pasadena, California|Pasadena]], the larger community nibbled at its edges in several small annexations of neighborhoods through the 1940s. With early 1960s redevelopment in Pasadena, the routing of extensions of 134 and 210 freeways, and lawsuits over the desegregation of Pasadena Unified School District, there was white flight and convulsive racial change in Altadena. In 1960, its black population was under four percent; over the next 15 years, half the Caucasian population left and was replaced by people of color — many of whom settled on the west side of town after being displaced by Pasadena's redevelopment and freeway projects.

The name Altadena derives from the [[Spanish language|Spanish]] ''alta'', meaning &quot;upper&quot;, and ''dena'' from Pasadena; the area is adjacent to, but at a higher elevation than, Pasadena.&lt;ref name=&quot;naming&quot;&gt;Manning, Mike. The word Altadena was first used by Byron Clark, who coined it for his nursery located south of present-day Woodbury on the west side of town. When he moved his nursery to Linda Vista, he agreed to let the Woodburys take the name for their new subdivision. &quot;[http://www.altadenatowncouncil.org/altadenahistory/ald_history.html ALTADENA, CALIFORNIA: an abbreviated history for the internet].&quot; ''[http://www.altadenatowncouncil.org/ Altadena Town Council].'' Retrieved on March 18, 2007.&lt;/ref&gt;

==Geography==
According to the [[United States Census Bureau]], the CDP has a total area of {{convert|8.7|sqmi|km2}}, over 99% of it land.

==Demographics==
===2010===
The [[2010 United States Census]]&lt;ref&gt;{{USCensus-2010CA}}&lt;/ref&gt; reported that Altadena had a population of 42,777. The [[population density]] was 4,900.4 people per square mile (1,892.1/km²). The racial makeup of Altadena was 22,569 (52.8%) [[White (U.S. Census)|White]], 10,136 (23.7%) [[African American (U.S. Census)|African American]], 300 (0.7%) [[Native American (U.S. Census)|Native American]], 2,307 (5.4%) [[Asian (U.S. Census)|Asian]], 71 (0.2%) [[Pacific Islander (U.S. Census)|Pacific Islander]], 4,852 (11.3%) from [[Race (United States Census)|other races]], and 2,542 (5.9%) from two or more races.  [[Hispanic (U.S. Census)|Hispanic]] or [[Latino (U.S. Census)|Latino]] of any race were 11,502 persons (26.9%). 

The Census reported that 42,276 people (98.8% of the population) lived in households, 234 (0.5%) lived in non-institutionalized group quarters, and 267 (0.6%) were institutionalized.  

There were 15,212 households, out of which 5,170 (34.0%) had children under the age of 18 living in them, 7,684 (50.5%) were [[marriage|opposite-sex married couples]] living together, 2,210 (14.5%) had a female householder with no husband present, 814 (5.4%) had a male householder with no wife present.  There were 661 (4.3%) [[POSSLQ|unmarried opposite-sex partnerships]], and 271 (1.8%) [[same-sex partnerships|same-sex married couples or partnerships]]. 3,489 households (22.9%) were made up of individuals and 1,318 (8.7%) had someone living alone who was 65 years of age or older. The average household size was 2.78.  There were 10,708 [[family (U.S. Census)|families]] (70.4% of all households); the average family size was 3.26.

The population was spread out with 9,507 people (22.2%) under the age of 18, 3,286 people (7.7%) aged 18 to 24, 10,622 people (24.8%) aged 25 to 44, 13,298 people (31.1%) aged 45 to 64, and 6,064 people (14.2%) who were 65 years of age or older.  The median age was 41.8 years. For every 100 females there were 93.1 males.  For every 100 females age 18 and over, there were 89.2 males.

There were 15,947 housing units at an average density of 1,826.8 per square mile (705.4/km²), of which 10,889 (71.6%) were owner-occupied, and 4,323 (28.4%) were occupied by renters. The homeowner vacancy rate was 0.9%; the rental vacancy rate was 4.9%.  30,319 people (70.9% of the population) lived in owner-occupied housing units and 11,957 people (28.0%) lived in rental housing units.

===2000===
As of the [[census]]{{GR|2}} of 2000, there were 42,610 people, 14,780 households, and 10,671 families residing in the CDP.  The [[population density]] was 4,898.9 people per square mile (1,891.0/km²).  There were 15,250 housing units at an average density of 1,753.3 per square mile (676.8/km²).  The racial makeup of the CDP was 47.30% [[Race (United States Census)|White]], 31.42% [[Race (United States Census)|Black]] or [[Race (United States Census)|African American]], 0.58% [[Race (United States Census)|Native American]], 4.24% [[Race (United States Census)|Asian]], 0.13% [[Race (United States Census)|Pacific Islander]], 10.19% from [[Race (United States Census)|other races]], and 6.14% from two or more races.  20.39% of the population were [[Hispanics in the United States|Hispanic]] or [[Race (United States Census)|Latino]] of any race.

There were 14,780 households out of which 34.1% had children under the age of 18 living with them, 52.3% were [[Marriage|married couples]] living together, 15.2% had a female householder with no husband present, and 27.8% were non-families. 21.8% of all households were made up of individuals and 7.1% had someone living alone who was 65 years of age or older.  The average household size was 2.82 and the average family size was 3.29.

In the CDP the population was spread out with 26.6% under the age of 18, 6.4% from 18 to 24, 30.1% from 25 to 44, 24.6% from 45 to 64, and 12.3% who were 65 years of age or older.  The median age was 38 years. For every 100 females there were 91.8 males.  For every 100 females age 18 and over, there were 86.6 males.

The median income for a household in the CDP was $60,549, and the median income for a family was $66,800 (these figures had risen to $77,020 and $86,778 respectively as of a 2007 estimate). Males had a median income of $49,098 versus $38,054 for females. The [[per capita income]] for the CDP was $27,604.  About 7.4% of families and 10.6% of the population were below the [[poverty line]], including 14.1% of those under age 18 and 8.3% of those age 65 or over.

== Government and politics ==

Altadena is part of the County of Los Angeles and is politically run by the Los Angeles County Board of Supervisors who have executive, legislative and judicial powers. There are five members of the Board of Supervisors, elected by geographic district. Altadena is in District five, presently represented by Supervisor [[Michael D. Antonovich]].  In 1975, a  group of Altadenans formed [http://www.altadenatowncouncil.org The Altadena Town Council] with the help of Los Angeles County Supervisor [[Baxter Ward]] and the Pasadena Chapter of the [[League of Women Voters]].

The Altadena Town Council acts as an [[ombudsman]] group to express to county, state and federal agencies the will and wishes of the Altadena community.  Altadena is identified collectively by eight census tract, ([[U.S. Census Bureau]]) from each of which two resident census tract representatives are elected.  The Altadena Town Council meets monthly at the Altadena Community Center to provide a forum for residents and government officials to convene.  The council has no legislative powers and makes no legal decisions for the community; it only operates to express consensus to governmental officials.

===Politics===
In the [[California State Legislature|state legislature]] Altadena is located in the 21st [[California State Senate|Senate]] District, represented by Democrat [[Carol Liu]], and in the 44th [[California State Assembly|Assembly]] District, represented by Democrat [[Anthony J. Portantino]]. Federally, Altadena is located in California's [[California's 26th congressional district|26th]] and [[California's 29th congressional district|29th]] congressional districts, which have [[Cook Partisan Voting Index|Cook PVIs]] of R +4 and D +12 respectively&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | title = Will Gerrymandered Districts Stem the Wave of Voter Unrest? | publisher = Campaign Legal Center Blog | url=http://www.clcblog.org/blog_item-85.html | accessdate = 2008-02-10}}&lt;/ref&gt; and are represented by Republican [[David Dreier]] and Democrat [[Adam Schiff]] respectively.

===Government and infrastructure===
The [[Los Angeles County Sheriff's Department]] (LASD) operates the Altadena Station in Altadena.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;[http://www.lasd.org/stations/for1/altadena/index.html Altadena Station].&quot; [[Los Angeles County Sheriff's Department]]. Retrieved on January 21, 2010.&lt;/ref&gt;

The [[Los Angeles County Department of Health Services]] operates the Monrovia Health Center in [[Monrovia, California|Monrovia]], serving Altadena.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;[http://publichealth.lacounty.gov/phn/docs/HealthCenter/monrovia.pdf Monrovia Health Center].&quot; [[Los Angeles County Department of Health Services]]. Retrieved on March 27, 2010.&lt;/ref&gt;

==Official tree and flower==
[[Image:Cedrus-deodare-habit.JPG|thumb|left|Deodar Cedar (''Cedrus deodara'')]]
[[Image:California poppy.jpg|thumb|right|Golden poppy ''(Eschscholzia californica)'']]

'''Official tree:''' The [[Deodar Cedar]] (Cedrus deodara). Indigenous to the Himalayas, the deodar was brought as seeds to Altadena in 1883 by Founder John Woodbury who saw the beautiful trees in Italy.  After growing the trees for two years, the trees were transplanted to Santa Rosa Avenue where they now stand majestically as [[Christmas Tree Lane]].

'''Official flower:''' The [[California Poppy|California Golden Poppy]] (Eschscholzia californica). Indigenous to the southland, the golden poppy was a landmark to Spanish sailors who recognized the area by a sweeping gold carpet.  The sailors referred to the marvelous vision as ''sabanilla de oro,'' or, &quot;altar cloth of gold.&quot;
{{-}}

==Points of interest==
[[File:Christmas Tree Lane.jpg|thumb|right|[[Christmas Tree Lane]]]]
[[Christmas Tree Lane]] is a {{convert|0.7|mi|km|sing=on}} stretch of Santa Rosa Avenue from Woodbury Road to [[Altadena Drive (California)|Altadena Drive]].  It has been a holiday attraction since 1920 and it is the oldest large-scale outdoor Christmas lighting venue in the world.  Each December, members of the Christmas Tree Lane Association [http://www.christmastreelane.net/] festoon the 110 still standing giant [[Deodar Cedar|deodars]] that line the street with thousands of Christmas lights.  Christmas Tree Lane was placed on the [[National Register of Historic Places]] in 1990, and is a [[California Historical Landmark]].

Among Altadena's Christmas lighting attractions is the Balian Mansion, which collects worldwide tours for its Christmas lighting display.  The Balian Mansion has been lighted since 1955 and is arguably the pioneer of home holiday lighting.  The Balian Mansion is located at the 5-point junction of Mendocino Street, Mendocino Lane, Allen Avenue, and East Glenview Terrace.

The historic [[Mount Lowe Railway]] was once a scenic railway that carried passengers to any four resort hotels high in the San Gabriel Mountains above Altadena and Pasadena.  Although the mountains and the remains of the railway are not strictly in Altadena, the most direct trail to the sites, the [[Sam Merrill Trail]], starts in Altadena at the top of [[Lake Avenue (Pasadena)|Lake Avenue]] and leads to Mount Echo, about {{convert|3|mi|km}}.  Chaney Trail, just west of the intersection at Fair Oaks Avenue and Loma Alta Street, is a forestry service road leading to the old right of way.  The Mount Lowe Railway was placed on the [[National Register of Historic Places]] in 1993.

The Cobb Estate at the top of Lake Avenue is now a free [[botanical garden]] of the [[United States Forest Service]].  It is guarded by its historic gates which are easily bypassed to allow visitors and hikers to ascend its long and winding paved driveway to the site of what was once one of Altadena's premier mansions. This is found alongside the Sam Merrill Trail which accesses Las Flores Canyon on the way to [[Echo Mountain]].

[[Farnsworth Park]] located on Lake Avenue is a large county park that offers picnic grounds, play areas, and a club house and amphitheater. It was placed in the National Register of Historic Places in 1997.

==Education==
Residents are zoned to [[Pasadena Unified School District]] schools. Zoned elementary schools include Altadena Elementary School, [[Burbank Elementary School (Altadena, California)|Burbank Elementary School]], Edison Elementary School, Franklin Elementary School, Jackson Elementary School, Loma Alta Elementary School, Webster Elementary School, [http://aveson.org Aveson School of Leaders], [[Charles W. Eliot Middle School|Eliot Middle School]], [[John Muir High School (Pasadena, California)|Muir High School]], [[Pasadena High School (California)|Pasadena High School]], [[Marshall Fundamental Secondary School|John Marshall Fundamental]] and Blair High School.

Private schools include Sahag-Mesrob Armenian Christian School, St. Elizabeth Catholic School, Saint Mark's, [[Pasadena Waldorf School]], [[Walden School (Altadena, California)|Walden School]] and [[Jane Warner's School]]

==Notable residents==
* [[Al Boeke]], architect and developer of [[Sea Ranch, California]].&lt;ref name=nytimes&gt; {{cite news|first=Dennis|last=Hevesi|title=Al Boeke, Architect Who Sought Ecological Harmony, Is Dead at 88 |url=http://www.nytimes.com/2011/11/17/us/al-boeke-88-dies-architect-sought-ecological-harmony.html |work=[[New York Times]] |publisher= |date=2011-11-16 |accessdate=2011-12-03}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[Bob Lillis]], [[Major League Baseball]] player and coach

== See also ==
{{Portal|Los Angeles}}

*[[Altadena Drive (California)]]

==References==
{{Reflist}}

==Further reading==
*The Altadena Historical Society
*Altadena Town Council
*Ives, Sarah Noble, ''Altadena''.  Pasadena, California: The Star-News Publishing Co., 1938. Out of print.
*Peterson, Robert H. ''Altadena's Golden Years''. Alhambra, California: Sinclair Printing and Litho, Inc., 1976.
*Zack, Michele. ''Altadena: Between Wilderness and City''. Altadena, California: Altadena Historical Society, 2004. ISBN 0-9747257-0-6

==External links==
{{Commons category}}
*[http://www.altadenatowncouncil.org/ Altadena Town Council]
*[http://www.abacus-es.com/altadena/ Altadena Chamber of Commerce]
*[http://www.altadenahistoricalsociety.org/ Altadena Historical Society]
*[http://www.mraltadena.com/altadena%20history/ald_history.html Altadena history]
*[http://www.altadenatowncouncil.org/altadenahistory/timeline.html  Official Altadena timeline]
*[http://www.library.altadena.ca.us/ Altadena Library District]

{{Los Angeles County, California}}
{{Greater Los Angeles Area}}

[[Category:Altadena, California| ]]
[[Category:San Gabriel Valley]]
[[Category:Census-designated places in Los Angeles County, California]]
[[Category:Unincorporated communities in Los Angeles County, California]]
[[Category:Populated places established in 1887]]

[[ca:Altadena]]
[[de:Altadena]]
[[es:Altadena]]
[[fr:Altadena]]
[[nl:Altadena]]
[[pt:Altadena]]
[[simple:Altadena, California]]
[[sv:Altadena]]
[[vo:Altadena]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
