<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="107594" ns="0" title="Agoura Hills, California"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{For|the unincorporated community|Agoura, California|}}
{{Infobox settlement
|official_name            = Agoura Hills
|other_name               =
|native_name              = &lt;!-- for cities whose native name is not in English --&gt;
|nickname                 =
|motto                    =
|image_skyline            = 	Agouravista.jpg
|imagesize                =
|image_caption            =View of Agoura Hills looking from southern edge of the Historic Quarter.
|image_flag               =
|flag_size                =
|image_seal               =
|seal_size                =
|image_shield             =
|shield_size              =
|image_blank_emblem       =
|blank_emblem_size        =
|image_map                = LA County Incorporated Areas Agoura Hills highlighted.svg
|mapsize                  =
|map_caption              = Location of Agoura Hills in California
|image_map1               =
|mapsize1                 =
|map_caption1             =
|pushpin_map=USA California
|coordinates_region       = US-CA
|subdivision_type         = [[List of countries|Country]]
|subdivision_name         = {{USA}}
|subdivision_type1        = [[Political divisions of the United States|State]]
|subdivision_name1        = {{flag|California}}
|subdivision_type2        = [[List of counties in California|County]]
|subdivision_name2        =  [[Los Angeles County|Los Angeles]]
|subdivision_type3        =
|subdivision_name3        =
|subdivision_type4        =
|subdivision_name4        =
|government_type          =
|leader_title             = [[Mayor]]
|leader_name              = Harry Schwarz &lt;ref name=&quot;cityc&quot;&gt;{{cite web | url = http://www.ci.agoura-hills.ca.us/index.aspx?page=24 | title = City of Agoura Hills : Council Members | accessdate = 2010-04-25}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|leader_title1            = Mayor Pro Tem &lt;!-- for places with, say, both a mayor and a city manager --&gt;
|leader_name1             = Dan Kuperberg &lt;ref name=&quot;cityc&quot; /&gt;
|leader_title2            =
|leader_name2             =
|leader_title3            =
|leader_name3             =
|established_title        = Settled by Spanish
|established_date         = 1700s
|established_title2       = &lt;!-- Incorporated (town) --&gt;
|established_date2        =
|established_title3       = Incorporated (city)
|established_date3        = December 8, 1982&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url = http://www.cacities.org/resource_files/20457.IncorpDateLO.doc |  title = Incorporation Dates of California Cities | accessdate = 2007-01-18}}&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;!-- Area------------------&gt;
|area_magnitude           =
| unit_pref               =US
| area_footnotes          = &lt;ref&gt;[http://www.census.gov/geo/www/gazetteer/files/Gaz_places_national.txt U.S. Census]&lt;/ref&gt;
| area_total_sq_mi        = 7.822
| area_land_sq_mi         = 7.793
| area_water_sq_mi        = 0.029
| area_total_km2          = 20.260
| area_land_km2           = 20.184
| area_water_km2          = 0.076
| area_water_percent      = 0.37
| area_note               = 
|area_urban_km2           =
|area_urban_sq_mi         =
|area_metro_km2           =
|area_metro_sq_mi         =
|population_as_of         = 2010
|population_note          =
|population_footnotes     =
|settlement_type          = [[City]]
|population_total         = 20330
|population_density_km2   = auto
|population_density_sq_mi = auto
|population_metro         =
|population_density_metro_km2     =
|population_density_metro_sq_mi   =
|population_urban                 =
|population_density_urban_km2     =
|population_density_urban_sq_mi   =
|timezone                 = [[Pacific Time Zone|PST]]
|utc_offset               = -8
|timezone_DST             = PDT
|utc_offset_DST           = -7
|coordinates_display      = inline,title
|coordinates_type         = region:US_type:city
|latd = 34 |latm = 9 |lats = 12 |latNS = N
|longd = 118 |longm = 45 |longs = 42 |longEW = W
|elevation_m              = 281
|elevation_ft             = 922
|postal_code_type         = [[ZIP Code]]
|postal_code              = 91301, 91376, 91377&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url = http://zip4.usps.com/zip4/zcl_1_results.jsp?visited=1&amp;pagenumber=0&amp;state=ca&amp;city=Agoura%20Hills | title = USPS - ZIP Code Lookup - Find a ZIP+ 4 Code By City Results | accessdate = 2007-01-17}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|area_code                = [[Area code 818|818]]&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url = http://www.nanpa.com/nas/public/npa_city_query_step2.do?method=displayData&amp;cityToNpaModel.stateAbbr=CA&amp;cityToNpaModel.city=Agoura%20Hills | title = Number Administration System - NPA and City/Town Search Results | accessdate = 2007-01-18}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|website                  = [http://www.ci.agoura-hills.ca.us/ http://www.ci.agoura-hills.ca.us/]
|blank_name               = [[Federal Information Processing Standard|FIPS code]]
|blank_info               = 06-00394
|blank1_name              = [[Geographic Names Information System|GNIS]] feature ID
|blank1_info              = 1667896
|footnotes                =
}}
&lt;!-- Infobox ends --&gt;

'''Agoura Hills''' is a city in [[Los Angeles County, California|Los Angeles County]], [[California]], and has the [[ZIP code]] 91301.  The population was 20,330 at the 2010 census, down from 20,537 at the 2000 census. It is located in the eastern [[Conejo Valley]] between the [[Simi Hills]] and the [[Santa Monica Mountains]]. This city on the [[Ventura Freeway]] ([[U.S. Route 101]]) straddles the border between the county of Los Angeles to the east, west and south and [[Ventura County, California|Ventura County]] to the north. It is approximately {{convert|30|mi|km|}} northwest of [[Downtown Los Angeles]] and less than {{convert|10|mi|km|}} west of the Los Angeles City limits (Woodland Hills).  Agoura Hills and unincorporated [[Agoura, California|Agoura]] are also situated next to Calabasas, Malibu, Oak Park, and Westlake Village.

==History==

The area was first settled by the [[Chumash (tribe)|Chumash]] Native Americans around 10,000 years before present.&lt;ref&gt;C. M. Hogan, 2008&lt;/ref&gt; As the [[Alta California]] (Upper California) coast was settled by [[Spaniard|Spanish]] [[Franciscan]] missionaries in the late 18th century, the [[El Camino Real (California)|El Camino Real]] (the Royal Road or King's Highway), a road from [[Loreto, Baja California Sur|Loreto, Baja California]], [[Mexico]] to [[Sonoma, California]], and connecting the [[Spanish missions in California]], was established through the heart of what would later be known as Agoura Hills.

In about 1800, Miguel Ortega was granted a Spanish grazing concession called [[Rancho Las Virgenes]] or El Rancho de Nuestra Señora La Reina de Las Virgenes.  The grant was abandoned after Ortega's death in 1810, and José Maria Dominguez was given Rancho Las Virgenes as a Mexican land grant in 1834.  [[Juan Francisco Reyes (soldier)#Jose Jacinto Reyes|Maria Antonia Machado de Reyes]] purchased the rancho from Dominguez in 1845.  The &quot;Reyes Adobe&quot; ranch headquarters can still be found today in a museum along Reyes Adobe Rd. in central Agoura Hills.  The historic Reyes Adobe Museum, owned by the Los Angeles County Parks and Recreation Department, was built in the mid-first decade of the 21st century around the site of the old [[adobe]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.laokay.com/halac/ReyesAdobe.htm Reyes Adobe]&lt;/ref&gt;

By 1900, Agoura Hills was being used as a popular stage stop for travelers along the [[El Camino Real (California)|Camino Real]] because of its natural spring at the foothills of [[Ladyface Mountain]], one of Agoura Hills' defining geographic features.

In the 1920s, the community was briefly known as Picture City, as [[Paramount Pictures]] owned a ranch in the area used for filming [[Western movies|Westerns]].  To obtain a post office of its own the residents were required to choose a one word name, and in 1927 chose a misspelling of the last name of [[Pierre Agoure]], a local Basque man and [[France|French]] immigrant who had settled in the area in 1871 to live the lifestyle of the Mexican rancher and styled himself Don Pierre Agoure,&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.findagrave.com/cgi-bin/fg.cgi?page=gr&amp;GSvcid=9332&amp;GRid=14344192&amp; http://www.findagrave.com/cgi-bin/fg.cgi?page=gr&amp;GSvcid=9332&amp;GRid=14344192&amp;] ''findagrave.com''&lt;/ref&gt; accordingly. Agoure was a successful sheep herder and had a reputation as a swashbuckler. His name was chosen for the post office as it was the shortest name proposed.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.colapublib.org/history/agourahills/faq.html http://www.colapublib.org/history/agourahills/faq.html] ''colapublib.org''&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Image:agouraestate.jpg|left|thumb|200px|An estate in [[Old Agoura]]]]

Rapid growth occurred in the Agoura Hills area starting in the late 1960s, in the wake of the construction of the [[Ventura Freeway]] section of  [[U.S. Route 101]] through the city's heart, an action that isolated the northern half of the city from the south. The first housing tracts started in Agoura were [[Hillrise]], Liberty Canyon and [[Lake Lindero]]. Growth continued at a rapid pace during the 1970s. Schools were built and much of downtown was erected.

In 1978, residents of the Agoura Hills area banded together to lobby [[Sacramento]] to widen the Kanan Bridge. Legislation was introduced and passed requiring the State [[California Department of Transportation|Department of Transportation]] to award contracts for widening of the Kanan Road bridge overpass, over the [[Ventura Freeway]], from two lanes to four lanes.

In 1982, the residents of the City of Agoura Hills voted in favor of cityhood by a 68% majority. Agoura Hills became the 83rd City in [[Los Angeles County]]. Elected to the first City Council were Mayor [[Fran Pavley]], Mayor Pro Tem Carol Sahm, Councilmembers Ernest Dynda, John Hood and Vicky Leary.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.ci.agoura-hills.ca.us/history.html http://www.ci.agoura-hills.ca.us/history.html] ''ci.agoura-hills.ca.us''&lt;/ref&gt; Incorporating a year after neighboring [[Westlake Village]], the drive for cityhood in the region was largely based on public discontent with the county's failure to limit residential development of the area, motives that influenced [[Malibu, California|Malibu]] and [[Calabasas]] to follow suit in 1991.&lt;ref&gt;[http://desperado.scvnet.com/~philh/scope/articles/inthenews/lat-smm-1.html http://desperado.scvnet.com/~philh/scope/articles/inthenews/lat-smm-1.html] ''desperado.scvnet.com''&lt;/ref&gt;

The 1980s was a period of tremendous growth, with large land areas being subdivided into [[housing tract]]s and a great wave of migration of people into the city. In the 1990s numerous businesses also set up shop in the city, and the downtown area was filled with shops and restaurants.

[[Image:Agoura2.JPG|right|thumb|250px|Map showing Agoura Hills Districts]]

In 1996, however, the murder of Jimmy Farris (the infamous [[Brandon Hein]] case) shook the city and awakened it to a rising [[drug]] problem and [[petty theft]] crime wave among its young. As a result, the city began sponsoring live music competitions and concerts in local parks (see Music).

==Geography==

{{Main|Neighborhoods of Agoura Hills, California}}
According to the [[United States Census Bureau]], the city has a total area of {{convert|8.2|sqmi|km2}}.  {{convert|8.2|sqmi|km2}} of it is land and {{convert|0.04|sqmi|km2}} of it (0.37%) is water

Agoura Hills has a mountain called Ballard Mountain named after pioneer settler and freed slave John Ballard.   The name of the mountain was officially changed from Negrohead to Ballard in a ceremony on February 20, 2010.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.newsvine.com/_news/2010/02/20/3927658-califs-negrohead-mountain-renamed-for-pioneer |title=Calif.'s Negrohead Mountain renamed for pioneer |author=Associated Press |date=February 20, 2010 |publisher=Newsvine |accessdate=2010-02-21}}&lt;/ref&gt;

{{wide image|Westlake Village and Agoura Hills California USA.jpg|700px|Panorama of Agoura Hills and Westlake Village with Ballard Mountain prominent as the leftmost peak in the image.}}

Agoura Hills is called the &quot;Gateway to the [[Santa Monica Mountains National Recreation Area]]&quot;{{Citation needed|date=July 2007}}. The city is unofficially divided into a number of varied districts centered on the modern Downtown area of the city. The most notable of these districts include '''[[Downtown, Agoura Hills, California|Downtown]]''', '''[[Forest Cove, Agoura Hills, California|Forest Cove]]''', '''[[South End, Agoura Hills, California|South End]]''', '''[[Malibu Junction, Agoura Hills, California|Malibu Junction]]''', '''[[East Agoura, Agoura Hills, California|East Agoura]]''', and '''[[Old Agoura, Agoura Hills, California|Old Agoura]]'''.

==Environment==
{{See|Santa Monica Mountains}}

Natural areas of Agoura Hills are part of the [[California chaparral and woodlands]] ecoregion and are covered by hundreds of local plant species, some of which are very rare, and others of which have become popular ornamentals. The range is host to an immense variety of wildlife, from [[mountain lion]]s to the endangered [[rainbow trout|steelhead]]. The [[Mountain lion]] population within the Santa Monica Mountains (which includes the Simi Hills &amp; Santa Susana Pass) is severely depleted with only seven known living adult individuals. The primary cause of the decline is due to a combination of traffic related mortality (three from the area were killed within a matter of months,) anti-coagulants ingested from human poisoned prey (two individuals within the Simi Hills) and attacks by other, more dominant mountain lions (an elder male, known as P1, killed both his son and his mate, this is though to be due to a lack of space available.) Snakes are common but only occasionally seen- the [[Southern Pacific Rattlesnake]] (the only venomous species), Mountain Kingsnake, [[California Kingsnake]], [[Gopher snake]], and [[Garter snake]]. The mountains are also home to the [[Western fence lizard]].

===Invasive species===
In 2010, the ''[[Los Angeles Times]]'' reported that the [[New Zealand mud snail]] had infested watersheds in the Santa Monica Mountains, posing serious threats to native species and complicating efforts to improve stream-water quality for the endangered [[steelhead trout]]. According to the article, the snails have expanded &quot;from the first confirmed sample in Medea Creek in Agoura Hills to nearly 30 other stream sites in four years.&quot; Researchers at the Santa Monica Bay Restoration Commission believe that the snails' expansion may have been expedited after the mollusks traveled from stream to stream on the gear of contractors and volunteers.&lt;ref name=latmudsnail&gt;[http://www.latimes.com/news/la-me-snail30-2010mar30,0,2859185.story Hard-to-kill snails infest Santa Monica Mountain watersheds] Even Formula 409 has proven ineffective at destroying the New Zealand mudsnail, an asexually reproducing invasive species that poses a threat to steelhead restoration efforts and native creatures.&lt;/ref&gt;

==Music==

Agoura Hills is known regionally for its live music scene and originality in the nu metal scene, a fame that has given rise to such acts as [[Linkin Park]], [[Incubus (band)|Incubus]], [[Hoobastank]], [[Dead By Sunrise]], and [[Fort Minor]].

This music scene was born amid the coming of age of the children of the first wave of migration into Agoura Hills, those that settled in the 1960s. The 1980s was the first boom in the music scene, but by the late 1980s, as many of these original rockers moved off to [[college]] or aged, the scene quietly began to slip away.

[[Image:MorrisonRanch.jpg|250px|thumb|left|Western Agoura Hills from the hills north of [[Morrison Ranch]]]]

However, in the mid-1990s the music scene began to take off again, energized by the coming of age of the children of those who had settled in the early 1980s. The 1996 [[Jimmy Farris]] murder case (popularized by defendant [[Brandon Hein]]) spurred many city leaders to action in promoting the arts among teenagers, hoping to ward off a rising [[Crime|crime wave]]. This patronage helped re-popularize live music among teenagers, and created the fertile ground that led to the take off of Linkin Park and Hoobastank.

However, by the first decade of the 21st century, much of this wave of teenagers had aged or gone to college, leaving the scene with only a shell of the energy it once had. Although the scene lives on, pushed forward by various [[Battle of the Bands]] competitions and garage concerts, the lack of a third major wave of migration to Agoura Hills (construction having been relatively maxed out in the second migration) makes a major renaissance seem doubtful as of early 2007. Demographic  data suggests a possible resurgence within the coming years, but current data shows that the majority of young people in the city are in the 10 to 14 years old age group, leaving a comeback to some years in the future.   With mean house prices in Agoura at $1.03 million, families with younger children (age 0-9) are probably not expected for a generation.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www4.onboardnavigator.com/webcontent/OBWC_report.aspx&amp;AID=108&amp;CD_SID=CO001&amp;RTID=1&amp;RID=10815&amp;Frame=0&amp;Height=600&amp;Width=600&amp;AgentEmail=&amp;AgentID=&amp;SearchID=1&amp;LSID=6&amp;STEXT=91301&amp;STYPE=3&amp;STEXTOPT=&amp;STYPEOPT=-1&amp;STEXTOPT2=&amp;STYPEOPT2=-1&amp;ITID=-1&amp;SITID=-1&amp;PassBackValues=&amp;NHood=&amp;Market=&amp;PropertyType=-1&amp;TransactionType=-1] ''ww4.onboardnavigator.com''&lt;/ref&gt;

As a result of this decline, it has become equally common to hear [[alt-rock]] blaring from stereos in Agoura as to hear [[reggaeton]], a fact evidenced by radio station [[KXOL-FM|Latino 96.3]]'s advertising campaign and runaway popularity in Agoura Hills.

Agoura Hills is home to The Canyon Club, a highly regarded concert venue that hosts national and regional touring acts such as [[Peter Frampton]], [[Pat Benetar]], [[Cyndi Lauper]], [[REO Speedwagon]], [[X (American band)|X]], [[Steel Pulse]], [[The New Cars]], [[Asia (band)|Asia]], [[Boyz II Men]], [[Alan Parsons]], and [[The Smithereens]].

==Demographics==
[[File:StrawberryHillApartments.jpg|thumb|right|&quot;The Gateway to the Santa Monica Mountains National Recreational Area&quot;]]
===2010===
The [[2010 United States Census]]&lt;ref&gt;{{USCensus-2010CA}}&lt;/ref&gt; reported that Agoura Hills had a population of 20,330. The [[population density]] was 2,599.0 people per square mile (1,003.5/km²). The racial makeup of Agoura Hills was 17,147 (84.3%) [[White (U.S. Census)|White]], 267 (1.3%) [[African American (U.S. Census)|African American]], 51 (0.3%) [[Native American (U.S. Census)|Native American]], 1,521 (7.5%) [[Asian (U.S. Census)|Asian]], 24 (0.1%) [[Pacific Islander (U.S. Census)|Pacific Islander]], 590 (2.9%) from [[Race (United States Census)|other races]], and 730 (3.6%) from two or more races.  [[Hispanic (U.S. Census)|Hispanic]] or [[Latino (U.S. Census)|Latino]] of any race were 1,936 persons (9.5%). 

The Census reported that 20,242 people (99.6% of the population) lived in households, 15 (0.1%) lived in non-institutionalized group quarters, and 73 (0.4%) were institutionalized.  

There were 7,327 households, out of which 2,799 (38.2%) had children under the age of 18 living in them, 4,565 (62.3%) were [[marriage|opposite-sex married couples]] living together, 726 (9.9%) had a female householder with no husband present, 302 (4.1%) had a male householder with no wife present.  There were 263 (3.6%) [[POSSLQ|unmarried opposite-sex partnerships]], and 36 (0.5%) [[same-sex partnerships|same-sex married couples or partnerships]]. 1,346 households (18.4%) were made up of individuals and 438 (6.0%) had someone living alone who was 65 years of age or older. The average household size was 2.76.  There were 5,593 [[family (U.S. Census)|families]] (76.3% of all households); the average family size was 3.15.

The population was spread out with 4,904 people (24.1%) under the age of 18, 1,582 people (7.8%) aged 18 to 24, 4,465 people (22.0%) aged 25 to 44, 7,089 people (34.9%) aged 45 to 64, and 2,290 people (11.3%) who were 65 years of age or older.  The median age was 42.4 years. For every 100 females there were 97.2 males.  For every 100 females age 18 and over, there were 94.6 males.

There were 7,585 housing units at an average density of 969.7 per square mile (374.4/km²), of which 5,715 (78.0%) were owner-occupied, and 1,612 (22.0%) were occupied by renters. The homeowner vacancy rate was 0.5%; the rental vacancy rate was 6.8%.  16,111 people (79.2% of the population) lived in owner-occupied housing units and 4,131 people (20.3%) lived in rental housing units.

===2000===
As of the [[census]]{{GR|2}} of 2000, there were 20,537 people, 6,874 households, and 5,588 families residing in the city.  The [[population density]] was 2,511.8 inhabitants per square mile (969.4/km&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt;).  There were 6,993 housing units at an average density of 855.3 per square mile (330.1/km&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt;).  The racial makeup of the city was 86.96% [[Race (United States Census)|White]], 1.32% [[Race (United States Census)|Black]] or [[Race (United States Census)|African American]], 0.25% [[Race (United States Census)|Native American]], 6.50% [[Race (United States Census)|Asian]], 0.10% [[Race (United States Census)|Pacific Islander]], 2.09% from [[Race (United States Census)|other races]], and 2.78% from two or more races.  6.85% of the population were [[Hispanics in the United States|Hispanic]] or [[Race (United States Census)|Latino]] of any race.

There were 6,874 households out of which 47.3% had children under the age of 18 living with them, 67.7% were married couples living together, 9.9% had a female householder with no husband present, and 18.7% were non-families. 13.8% of all households were made up of individuals and 3.0% had someone living alone who was 65 years of age or older.  The average household size was 2.98 and the average family size was 3.30.

In the city the population was spread out with 30.5% under the age of 18, 6.3% from 18 to 24, 27.6% from 25 to 44, 29.4% from 45 to 64, and 6.2% who were 65 years of age or older.  The median age was 38 years. For every 100 females there were 99.1 males.  For every 100 females age 18 and over, there were 94.0 males.

[[Image:oldagoura.jpg|right|thumb|200px|A ranch in [[Old Agoura]]]]

==Economy==
There are 14,899 people at least 16 years old, of which 10,645 are in the Civilian Labor Group and 11 are in the [[Armed Force]]s. 360 are [[unemployment|unemployed]].

Of 7,660 females that are at least 16 years old, 4,865 are in the Civilian Labor Group and 0 are in the Armed Forces. 4,715 are employed, and 150 are unemployed.

Of 10,166 out of the 10,285 workers 16 years or older, 8,454 drive to work alone in a [[motor vehicle]], 793 [[carpool]], 90 use public transportation (including taxicabs), 76 walk, and 82 use other means of transportation to commute to work. 671 workers work at home.

The mean time to commute to work (one-way) is 30.5 minutes.

Of the 10,285 workers, 7,900 are privately employed, 1,124 are [[government]] workers, 1,211 are [[self-employment|self-employed]], and 50 are unpaid family workers.

Gaming company [[NovaLogic]] has their headquarters in Agoura Hills.

===Top employers===
According to the City's 2009 Comprehensive Annual Financial Report,&lt;ref name=&quot;cafr2009&quot;&gt;[http://www.ci.agoura-hills.ca.us/Modules/ShowDocument.aspx?documentid=7810 City of Agoura Hills CAFR]&lt;/ref&gt; the top employers in the city are:

{| class=&quot;wikitable&quot; border=&quot;1&quot;
|-
! #
! Employer
! # of Employees
|-
| 1
|[[Bank of America]]
|755
|-
| 2
|[[THQ]]
|505
|-
| 3
|[[Las Virgenes Unified School District]]
|503
|-
| 4
|TouchCommerce
|256
|-
| 5
|[[Teradyne]]
|205
|-
| 6
|[[PacificComp]]
|211
|-
| 7
|[[Farmers Insurance Group|Farmers]] Financial Solutions
|200
|-
| 8
|Community Medical Group Of The West Valley
|160
|-
| 9
|[[Renaissance Hotels|Renaissance Hotel]]
|120
|-
| 10
|[[DTS (sound system)|DTS]]
|130
|-
| 11
|Wood Ranch BBQ &amp; Grill
|100
|-
| 12
|[[Vons]]
|86
|-
|}

==Government and infrastructure==
Agoura Hills is governed by a [[Council–manager government|City Council/City Manager]] form of government. A five-member [[City Council]] is elected by the residents to oversee city operations and guide the development of the community. Councilmembers are elected to four-year terms.&lt;ref name=&quot;ci.agoura-hills.ca.us&quot;&gt;City of Agoura Hills Website: Local Election Information. http://ci.agoura-hills.ca.us/Modules/ShowDocument.aspx?documentid=6913&lt;/ref&gt; The terms are staggered so that a measure of continuity is maintained from one Council to the next. The role of [[Mayor]] rotates among the Councilmembers. The Mayor is chosen by the City Councilmembers to serve a one-year term.&lt;ref name=&quot;ci.agoura-hills.ca.us&quot;/&gt; The City Manager is appointed by the City Council to supervise the administrative personnel and contract services.&lt;ref&gt;City of Agoura Hills Website. http://ci.agoura-hills.ca.us/Index.aspx?page=24&lt;/ref&gt; As of August 2010, the Agoura Hills City Council consists of William D. Koehler (Mayor), Harry Schwarz (Mayor Pro Tem) and councilmembers John M. Edelston, Dan Kuperberg and Denis Weber. The City Manager is Greg Ramirez and the city attorney is Craig Steele.

In the [[California State Legislature|state legislature]] Agoura Hills is located in the 23rd [[California State Senate|Senate]] District, represented by Democrat [[Fran Pavley]], and in the 41st [[California State Assembly|Assembly]] District, represented by Democrat [[Julia Brownley]]. Federally, Agoura Hills is located in [[California's 30th congressional district]], which has a [[Cook Partisan Voting Index|Cook PVI]] of D +20&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | title = Will Gerrymandered Districts Stem the Wave of Voter Unrest? | publisher = Campaign Legal Center Blog | url=http://www.clcblog.org/blog_item-85.html | accessdate = 2008-02-10}}&lt;/ref&gt; and is represented by Democrat [[Henry Waxman]].

In the 2004 presidential election [[John Kerry]] won 52% of the vote, whereas [[George W. Bush]] won 46% of the vote. In the 2006 state governor election, [[Arnold Schwarzenegger]] got just over 62% of the vote, while Democratic opponent [[Phil Angelides]] got over 34%.

The [[Los Angeles County Sheriff's Department]] (LASD) operates the Malibu/Lost Hills Station in [[Calabasas, California|Calabasas]], serving Agoura Hills.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;[http://www.lasd.org/stations/for1/malibu_lhill/index.html Malibu/Lost Hills Station].&quot; [[Los Angeles County Sheriff's Department]]. Retrieved on January 21, 2010.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;&quot;[http://factfinder.census.gov/servlet/MapItDrawServlet?geo_id=16000US0609598&amp;_bucket_id=50&amp;tree_id=420&amp;context=saff&amp;_lang=en&amp;_sse=on Calabasas city, California].&quot; [[U.S. Census Bureau]]. Retrieved on January 21, 2010.&lt;/ref&gt;

The [[United States Postal Service]] Agoura Hills Post Office is located at 5158 Clareton Drive.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;[http://usps.whitepages.com/service/post_office/56010?p=4&amp;s=CA&amp;service_name=post_office&amp;z=Agoura+Hills Post Office Location - AGOURA HILLS].&quot; ''[[United States Postal Service]]''. Retrieved on December 6, 2008.&lt;/ref&gt;

==Education==
[[File:Agoura high.jpg|thumb|[[Agoura High School]]]]
The [[Las Virgenes Unified School District]] serves Agoura Hills.
* Lupin Hill Elementary School
* Sumac Elementary School
* Willow Elementary School
* Yerba Buena Elementary School
* [[A.E. Wright Middle School]]
* [[Lindero Canyon Middle School]]
* [[Agoura High School]]

==Notable residents==

Notable current and former residents of Agoura Hills include:
{{div col|3}}
* [[Ron Goldman]], waiter and deceased friend of [[Nicole Brown Simpson]]
* [[Rainn Wilson]], actor
* [[Erin Brockovich]], environmental activist
* [[Mike Shinoda]], musician
* [[Doug Robb]], singer
* [[Heather Graham]], actress
* [[Todd Steussie]] 
* [[Brad Garrett]], actor/comedian
* [[Clay Matthews III|Clay Matthews]], NFL Linebacker for the [[Green Bay Packers]]
* [[Casey Matthews]], NFL Linebacker for the [[Philadelphia Eagles]]
* [[Guillermo del Toro]], Mexican film director
* [[Rob Paulsen]], American voice actor
{{div col end}}

==References==
{{Reflist|colwidth=30em}}

==External links==
{{Portal|Los Angeles|Greater Los Angeles|Southern California}}
* [http://www.ci.agoura-hills.ca.us/ Agoura Hills official website]
* [http://www.visitagourahills.com/ Local Guide of City]
* [http://www.agourachamber.org/ Agoura area chamber of commerce]
* [http://www.colapublib.org/history/agourahills/ Agoura Hills community History] LA County library
* [http://www.theacorn.com/current/front_page/ The Acorn local newspaper]
* [http://www.conejopost.com - Conejo Post - News, Issues, History and Outdoors in the Conejo Valley, including Agoura Hills]

{{Los Angeles County, California}}
{{Greater Los Angeles Area}}

[[Category:Neighborhoods in Agoura Hills| Agoura Hills]]
[[Category:Cities in Los Angeles County, California]]
[[Category:Incorporated cities and towns in California]]
[[Category:Populated places established in 1982]]

[[ar:أغورا هيلز، كاليفورنيا]]
[[bg:Агура Хилс]]
[[ca:Agoura Hills]]
[[cs:Agoura Hills (Kalifornie)]]
[[de:Agoura Hills]]
[[es:Agoura Hills]]
[[fa:آگورا هیلز]]
[[fr:Agoura Hills (Californie)]]
[[it:Agoura Hills]]
[[pam:Agoura Hills, California]]
[[sw:Agoura Hills, California]]
[[ht:Agoura Hills, Kalifòni]]
[[nl:Agoura Hills]]
[[no:Agoura Hills]]
[[pt:Agoura Hills]]
[[ru:Агура-Хиллз]]
[[fi:Agoura Hills]]
[[tl:Agoura Hills, Kaliporniya]]
[[vi:Agoura Hills, California]]
[[vo:Agoura Hills]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
