<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="107682" ns="0" title="Signal Hill, California"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Infobox settlement
|official_name            = City of Signal Hill
|settlement_type          = [[City]]
|nickname                 =
|motto                    =
|image_skyline            =
|imagesize                =
|image_caption            =
|image_flag               =
|image_seal               =
|image_map                = LA County Incorporated Areas Signal Hill highlighted.svg
|mapsize                  = 250x200px
|map_caption              = Location of Signal Hill in [[Los Angeles County, California|Los Angeles County]], [[California]]
|image_map1               =
|mapsize1                 =
|map_caption1             =
|coordinates_region       = US-CA
|subdivision_type         = [[List of countries|Country]]
|subdivision_name         = [[United States]]
|subdivision_type1        = [[Political divisions of the United States|State]]
|subdivision_name1        = [[California]]
|subdivision_type2        = [[List of counties in California|County]]
|subdivision_name2        = [[Los Angeles County, California|Los Angeles]]
|government_type          =
|leader_title             = [[Mayor]]
|leader_name              = Ed Wilson
|established_title        = Incorporated
|established_date         = 1924
&lt;!-- Area------------------&gt;
|area_magnitude           =
| unit_pref               =US
| area_footnotes          = &lt;ref&gt;[http://www.census.gov/geo/www/gazetteer/files/Gaz_places_national.txt U.S. Census]&lt;/ref&gt;
| area_total_sq_mi        = 2.191
| area_land_sq_mi         = 2.189
| area_water_sq_mi        = 0.002
| area_total_km2          = 5.673
| area_land_km2           = 5.669
| area_water_km2          = 0.004
| area_water_percent      = 0.08
| area_note               = 

|area_urban_sq_mi         =
|area_urban_km2           =
|area_metro_sq_mi         =
|area_metro_km2           =
|population_as_of         = 2010
|population_note          =
|population_total         = 11016
|population_footnotes     =
|population_metro         =
|population_urban                 =
|population_density_km2   = auto
|population_density_sq_mi = auto
|timezone                 = [[Pacific Time Zone|PST]]
|utc_offset               = -8
|timezone_DST             = PDT
|utc_offset_DST           = -7
|latd = 33.79935 |latm =  |lats = |latNS = N  
|longd = 118.16558 |longm = |longs = |longEW = W
|elevation_m              = 45
|elevation_ft             = 148
|website                  = http://www.cityofsignalhill.org/
|postal_code_type         = [[ZIP code]]
|postal_code              = 90755
|area_code                = [[Area code 562|562]]
|blank_name               = [[Federal Information Processing Standard|FIPS code]]
|blank_info               = 06-71876
|blank1_name              = [[Geographic Names Information System|GNIS]] feature ID
|blank1_info              = 1661443
|footnotes                =
}}
'''Signal Hill''' is a small [[city]] (2.2&amp;nbsp;mi², 5.7&amp;nbsp;km²) in [[California]] located in the [[Greater Los Angeles area]]. Signal Hill, completely surrounded by the city of [[Long Beach, California|Long Beach]], was [[Municipal corporation|incorporated]] on April 22, 1924, roughly three years after oil was discovered in Signal Hill. As of the 2010 census, the city population was 11,016.

Signal Hill lies in the [[Area code 562|562 area code]]. The city once shared three different postal [[ZIP code]]s with the city of Long Beach but in July 2002, the city of Signal Hill received its own ZIP code, 90755.

==History==
The hill that the city is named after is 365 feet (110 m) above the surrounding town of Long Beach. Because of this height, it was used by the local [[Tongva people|Tongva]] [[American Indians in the United States|Indian]]s for [[Smoke signal|signal fire]]s that could be seen throughout the surrounding area and even out to [[Santa Catalina Island, California|Catalina Island]], {{convert|26|mi|km}} away.

After the Spanish discovered  ''[[Alta California]]'' (&quot;Upper California,&quot; or what is now the state of California), Signal Hill eventually became part of the first large rancho grant to be allotted under Spanish rule in Alta California. The [[Rancho San Pedro]] (Dominguez Rancho) land grant exceeded {{convert|74000|acre|km2}} as granted to a soldier, [[Manuel Dominguez#Juan Jose Dominguez|Juan Jose Dominguez]], who accompanied Junipero Serra, by Governor Fages through authority of [[Charles III of Spain|King Carlos III]] of [[Spain]] in 1784.

Between 1913 and 1923 an early California movie studio, Balboa Amusement Producing Company (also known as Balboa Studios), was located in Long Beach and used 11 acres (45,000&amp;nbsp;m²) on Signal Hill for outdoor locations. [[Buster Keaton]] and [[Fatty Arbuckle]] were two of Balboa Studio actors who had films shot on Signal Hill.

Before oil was discovered in Signal Hill, there were large homes built on the hill itself, and in the lower elevations was an agricultural area where fruits, vegetables, and flowers were grown. Many of the truck farmers were Japanese.

===Oil is discovered on Signal Hill===
{{Wide image|Signal Hill California 1923.jpg|1000px|Signal Hill c1923}}
Signal Hill changed forever when oil was discovered. The hill would soon become part of the [[Long Beach Oil Field]], one of the most productive [[oil fields]] in the world.&lt;ref name=&quot;MMS&quot;&gt;Schmitt, R. J., Dugan, J. E., and M. R. Adamson. &quot;Industrial Activity and Its Socioeconomic Impacts:
Oil and Three Coastal California Counties.&quot; MMS OCS Study 2002-049. Coastal Research Center, Marine Science Institute, University of California, Santa Barbara, California. MMS Cooperative Agreement Number 14-35-01-00-CA-31603. 244 pages; p. 47.&lt;/ref&gt; On June 23, 1921, [[Shell Oil Company]]'s Alamitos #1 well erupted. The [[natural gas|gas]] pressure was so great the [[oil gusher|gusher]] rose 114&amp;nbsp;ft (35 m) in the air. Soon Signal Hill was covered with over 100 [[Oil_derrick#Oil_derrick|oil derrick]]s, and because of its prickly appearance at a distance became known as &quot;Porcupine Hill&quot;.

The city was incorporated on April 22, 1924. Among the reasons for incorporating was avoiding annexation by Long Beach with its zoning restrictions and per-barrel oil tax. Signal Hill's first mayor, Jessie Nelson, was also California's first female mayor.

===Later years===
One of the city's more colorful residents was the boxer [[Kid Mexico]] (real name, Tod Faulkner) who was the state's [[bantamweight]] champion in 1914 (at age 14&amp;mdash;he had lied about his age) and the state's [[welterweight]] champion in 1925. He put his earnings into businesses and real estate in Signal Hill, including an eight lane [[bowling alley]], restaurant, cocktail lounge, auditorium, and movie house. He also had a [[Bingo (US)|bingo parlor]] that was ignored by the local police for many years. He was well-known for his large annual Christmas parties for children from Signal Hill and Long Beach. Besides his bowling alley, he also had a single lane for bowling in his nearby home. Eventually he was arrested for [[gambling]], [[tax evasion]], and [[election fraud]] (Davis, 2006, p.&amp;nbsp;62-64).

Today, many of the oil wells and [[nodding donkey]] oil pumps are gone, although some remain. Signal Hill is now a mix of residential and commercial areas.

==Government and infrastructure==
{{Ref improve section|date=December 2008}}

===Local government===
The Signal Hill Police Department provides law enforcement.

===County, state, and federal representation===
For sixteen years, Signal Hill contracted for their fire protection services from the City of Long Beach. On November 6, 2003, Signal Hill returned to [[Los Angeles County Fire Department]] protection as Station 60.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;[http://lacountyfire.com/modules.php?name=News&amp;file=article&amp;sid=132 Misc.: LA County FD ''Signals'' a new station opening on the ''Hill''].&quot; ''[[Los Angeles County Fire Department]]''. Wednesday January 7, 2004.&lt;/ref&gt; Ambulance transport is provided by [[Care Ambulance Service]].

The [[Los Angeles County Department of Health Services]] operates the Whittier Health Center in [[Whittier, California|Whittier]], serving Signal Hill.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;[http://publichealth.lacounty.gov/phn/docs/HealthCenter/whittier.pdf Whittier Health Center].&quot; [[Los Angeles County Department of Health Services]]. Retrieved on March 18, 2010.&lt;/ref&gt;

Signal Hill is in the 4th Supervisorial District of Los Angeles County, with [[Don Knabe]] the current Supervisor. Signal Hill is in the 37th [[Congressional District]] of the U.S. Congress, represented by Congresswoman [[Laura Richardson]] (D). It is in the 27th California State Senate District, represented by [[Alan Lowenthal]], and the 54th California Assembly District, represented by [[Bonnie Lowenthal]].{{Citation needed|date=April 2010}}

==Economy==
Prior to its dissolution, the airline [[Jet America Airlines]] was headquartered in Signal Hill.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;World Airline Directory.&quot; ''Flight International''. March 30, 1985. [http://www.flightglobal.com/pdfarchive/view/1985/1985%20-%200948.html 88].&quot; Retrieved on July 23, 2009.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;&quot;[http://www.cityofsignalhill.org/community_development/upper_rightc4.jpg upper_rightc4.jpg].&quot; City of Signal Hill. Retrieved on July 23, 2009.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;&quot;[http://idea.sec.gov/news/digest/1984/dig021784.pdf SEC News Digest Issue 84-34].&quot; ''[[Securities and Exchange Commission]]''. February 17, 1984. 2/4. Retrieved on July 23, 2009.&lt;/ref&gt; The diner chain [[Hof's Hut]] is headquartered in Signal Hill.

===Top employers===
According to the City's 2009 Comprehensive Annual Financial Report, the top employers in the city are:&lt;ref name=&quot;cafr2009&quot;&gt;[http://www.cityofsignalhill.org/DocumentView.aspx?DID=83 City of Signal HillCAFR]&lt;/ref&gt;

{| class=&quot;wikitable&quot; border=&quot;1&quot;
|-
! #
! Employer
! # of Employees
|-
| 1
|[[Office Depot]]
|551
|-
| 2
|[[The Home Depot]]
|303
|-
| 3
|[[Costco]]
|292
|-
| 4
|Universal Care
|272
|-
| 5
|Telestranger Productions
|230
|-
| 6
|Oil Well Service Company
|225
|-
| 7
|[[Target Corporation|Target]]
|202
|-
| 8
|[[The Home Depot]]
|165
|-
| 9
|[[Crane Co.|Crane]]
|143
|-
| 10
|Alliance Spacesystems
|129
|-
|}

==Education==
===Primary and secondary school===
====Public schools====
Signal Hill is served by [[Long Beach Unified School District]].

There are three elementary schools within the city limits:
*[[Signal Hill Elementary School (Signal Hill, California)|Signal Hill Elementary School]]
*Juan Bautista Alvarado Elementary School
*Burroughs Elementary School (A Teacher Resource Center is adjacent to the Burroughs campus).

The three areas have separate attendance zones.

In addition, Robinson School in Long Beach takes some students in Signal Hill for elementary school and middle school.

Some residents attend [[Long Beach Unified School District|Butler School]], a K-8 school, for middle school only. Some other residents attend [[Hughes Middle School (Long Beach, California)|Hughes Middle School]]. Some attend the [[Jefferson Leadership Academies]]. Areas within the city are zoned, for middle school, to either Butler, Hughes, Jefferson, or Robinson.

High school students usually go to [[Long Beach Polytechnic High School]] (usually referred to as Long Beach Poly); most of the city is zoned to Long Beach Polytechnic.

Some students choose to go to [[Wilson Classical High School|Long Beach Wilson Classical High School]]; small portions are zoned to Wilson Classical High School.

Signal Hill Elementary School has earned the California Achieving Schools Award, and the National Achieving Schools Award. Signal Hill and Alvarado are both California Distinguished Schools.

Juan Bautista Alvarado Elementary School is located on the site of the former all male boarding school, the [[Southern California Military Academy]].

===Colleges and universities===
Community college students attend one of the two nearby campuses for [[Long Beach City College]].

[[California State University, Long Beach]] is located less than five miles (8&amp;nbsp;km) away.

==City parks==
[[Image:SignalHill.jpg|thumb|300px|right|Hilltop Park]]
Although a small town, Signal Hill has several parks. The largest is ''Signal Hill Park'' at {{convert|10|acre|m2}}. It is adjacent to City Hall, the Police Department, the Community Center and the Library. The park has picnic tables, a playground, a horseshoe pit, basketball courts, a softball field, and restrooms. There is also an amphitheater where there are weekly outdoor concerts during the summer.

''Hilltop Park''  {{convert|3.2|acre|m2}} is at the top of Signal Hill and is very popular for its great views. There are several telescopes in the park. There is also some public artwork in the park and a mist tower. This park is a popular location for hiding [[geocache]]s.

''Reservoir Park''  {{convert|2.8|acre|m2}} near the [[California Heights, Long Beach, California|California Heights]] neighborhood of Long Beach is a large grassy area with picnic tables next to a 4.7 million gallon water reservoir.

''Discovery Well Park''  {{convert|4.9|acre|m2}},    {{convert|1.8|acre|m2}}  flat is near the original well on Signal Hill.

There are also six [[pocket park]]s of roughly {{convert|0.5|acre|m2}} or less, including ''Calbrisas Park'', ''Hillbrook Park'', ''Panorama Promenade'', ''Raymond Arbor Park'', ''Sunset View Park'', and ''Temple View Park''.

Near the ''Panorama Promenade'', there is the ''Unity Sculpture'', a 12' height sculpture atop a 4' pedestal with a seating courtyard that is dedicated in memory of the victims of September 11.

There are also several pedestrian-only [[trail]]s that travel between various parks and roadways. Hiking along these trails, as well as on the sidewalks in Signal Hill is very popular. Some sections can be found that are between a 15% and 25% grade.

===Proposed nature preserve===
On the north slope of Signal Hill is a large area that is currently used for oil operations. This area has been proposed as a [[nature preserve]].

==Sports==
There used to be a popular [[Ford Model T|Model T]] Hill Climb up Hill Street on the east side of Signal Hill.

In 1975 the first professional [[street luge]] race was held at Signal Hill. By 1978, however, the races were canceled because of injuries to racers and spectators.

The Long Beach chapter of the [[Sierra Club]] does conditioning hikes twice a week in Signal Hill.

The [[Long Beach Sports Park]] is scheduled to be built on a parcel of Long Beach that is almost completely surrounded by the city of Signal Hill.

==Geography==
According to the [[United States Census Bureau]], the city has a total area of {{convert|2.2|sqmi|km2}}, virtually all land.

The city is surrounded on all sides by the city of [[Long Beach, California]].

==Demographics==
{{USCensusPop
|1990= 8371
|2000= 9333
|2010=11016
}}
===2010===
The [[2010 United States Census]]&lt;ref&gt;{{USCensus-2010CA}}&lt;/ref&gt; reported that Signal Hill had a population of 11,016. The [[population density]] was 5,029.0 people per square mile (1,941.7/km²). The racial makeup of Signal Hill was 4,650 (42.2%) [[White (U.S. Census)|White]], 1,502 (13.6%) [[African American (U.S. Census)|African American]], 83 (0.8%) [[Native American (U.S. Census)|Native American]], 2,245 (20.4%) [[Asian (U.S. Census)|Asian]], 135 (1.2%) [[Pacific Islander (U.S. Census)|Pacific Islander]], 1,778 (16.1%) from [[Race (United States Census)|other races]], and 623 (5.7%) from two or more races.  [[Hispanic (U.S. Census)|Hispanic]] or [[Latino (U.S. Census)|Latino]] of any race were 3,472 persons (31.5%). 

The Census reported that 10,970 people (99.6% of the population) lived in households, 2 (0%) lived in non-institutionalized group quarters, and 44 (0.4%) were institutionalized.  

There were 4,157 households, out of which 1,419 (34.1%) had children under the age of 18 living in them, 1,580 (38.0%) were [[marriage|opposite-sex married couples]] living together, 660 (15.9%) had a female householder with no husband present, 258 (6.2%) had a male householder with no wife present.  There were 302 (7.3%) [[POSSLQ|unmarried opposite-sex partnerships]], and 156 (3.8%) [[same-sex partnerships|same-sex married couples or partnerships]]. 1,128 households (27.1%) were made up of individuals and 245 (5.9%) had someone living alone who was 65 years of age or older. The average household size was 2.64.  There were 2,498 [[family (U.S. Census)|families]] (60.1% of all households); the average family size was 3.33.

The population was spread out with 2,624 people (23.8%) under the age of 18, 1,034 people (9.4%) aged 18 to 24, 3,476 people (31.6%) aged 25 to 44, 2,970 people (27.0%) aged 45 to 64, and 912 people (8.3%) who were 65 years of age or older.  The median age was 36.0 years. For every 100 females there were 97.3 males.  For every 100 females age 18 and over, there were 94.9 males.

There were 4,389 housing units at an average density of 2,003.7 per square mile (773.6/km²), of which 2,141 (51.5%) were owner-occupied, and 2,016 (48.5%) were occupied by renters. The homeowner vacancy rate was 1.9%; the rental vacancy rate was 5.7%.  5,253 people (47.7% of the population) lived in owner-occupied housing units and 5,717 people (51.9%) lived in rental housing units.

===2000===
As of the [[census]]{{GR|2}} of 2000, there were 9,333 people, 3,621 households, and 2,096 families residing in the city.  The [[population density]] was 4,182.0 inhabitants per square mile (1,615.9/km²).  There were 3,797 housing units at an average density of 1,701.4 per square mile (657.4/km²).  The racial makeup of the city was 45.48% [[White (U.S. Census)|White]], 12.99% [[African American (U.S. Census)|African American]], 0.59% [[Native American (U.S. Census)|Native American]], 16.49% [[Asian (U.S. Census)|Asian]], 2.08% [[Pacific Islander (U.S. Census)|Pacific Islander]], 16.18% from [[Race (United States Census)|other races]], and 6.19% from two or more races. [[Hispanic (U.S. Census)|Hispanic]] or [[Latino (U.S. Census)|Latino]] of any race were 29.00% of the population.

There were 3,621 households out of which 31.0% had children under the age of 18 living with them, 36.8% were [[Marriage|married couples]] living together, 14.5% had a female householder with no husband present, and 42.1% were non-families. 30.6% of all households were made up of individuals and 5.2% had someone living alone who was 65 years of age or older.  The average household size was 2.56 and the average family size was 3.34.

In the city the population was spread out with 26.4% under the age of 18, 9.1% from 18 to 24, 35.3% from 25 to 44, 22.0% from 45 to 64, and 7.2% who were 65 years of age or older.  The median age was 33 years. For every 100 females there were 97.1 males.  For every 100 females age 18 and over, there were 96.1 males.

The median income for a household in the city was $48,938, and the median income for a family was $46,439. Males had a median income of $41,487 versus $36,460 for females. The [[per capita income]] for the city was $24,399.  About 13.6% of families and 17.2% of the population were below the [[poverty line]], including 31.1% of those under age 18 and 3.9% of those age 65 or over.

==Politics==
In the [[California State Legislature|state legislature]] Signal Hill is located in the 27th [[California State Senate|Senate]] District, represented by Democrat [[Alan Lowenthal]], and in the 54th [[California State Assembly|Assembly]] District, represented by Democrat [[Bonnie Lowenthal]]. Federally, Signal Hill is located in [[California's 37th congressional district]], which has a [[Cook Partisan Voting Index|Cook PVI]] of D +27&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | title = Will Gerrymandered Districts Stem the Wave of Voter Unrest? | publisher = Campaign Legal Center Blog | url=http://www.clcblog.org/blog_item-85.html | accessdate = 2008-02-10}}&lt;/ref&gt; and is represented by Democrat [[Laura Richardson]].

==See also==
{{Portal|Los Angeles}}
*[[Signal Hill (disambiguation)]] for other Signal Hills

==References==
{{Reflist}}
&lt;div class=&quot;references-small&quot;&gt;
*{{cite book
  | last = Davis
  | first = Ken
  | authorlink =
  | coauthors = the Signal Hill Historical Society
  | title = Signal Hill: Images of America
  | publisher = [[Arcadia Publishing]]
  | year = 2006
  | isbn =  0-7385-3073-5
}}
&lt;/div&gt;

==External links==
*[http://www.cityofsignalhill.org/ Signal Hill official website]
* [http://www.signalhillchamber.com/ Signal Hill Chamber of Commerce website]
* [http://www.signalhillautocenter.com Signal Hill Auto Center]
*[http://www.priweb.org/ed/pgws/history/signal_hill/signal_hill2.html The Story of Oil in California - Signal Hill] at [http://www.priweb.org The Paleontological Research Institution]
*[http://www.letsgoseeit.com/index/county/la/signal_hill/loc02/oilwell.htm DISCOVERY WELL - SIGNAL HILL FIELD - SHELL OIL COMPANY - ALAMITOS NO. 1 JUNE 25, 1921]
*[http://www.longbeachfilmfestival.com/history.htm The Balboa Amusement Producing Company: The Unforgotten Studio of Long Beach]

{{Coord|33.79935|-118.16558|region:US_type:landmark|display=title}}

{{Cities of Los Angeles County, California}}
{{Greater Los Angeles Area}}

[[Category:Cities in Los Angeles County, California]]
[[Category:Geography of Long Beach, California]]
[[Category:Hills of California]]
[[Category:Incorporated cities and towns in California]]
[[Category:Populated places established in 1924]]

[[ar:سيغنال هيل، لوس أنجليس، كاليفورنيا]]
[[bg:Сигнал Хил (град, Калифорния)]]
[[ca:Signal Hill]]
[[de:Signal Hill]]
[[es:Signal Hill]]
[[fr:Signal Hill (Californie)]]
[[sw:Signal Hill, California]]
[[ht:Signal Hill, Kalifòni]]
[[nl:Signal Hill]]
[[pt:Signal Hill]]
[[ru:Сигнал-Хилл (Калифорния)]]
[[sv:Signal Hill]]
[[tl:Signal Hill, California]]
[[vo:Signal Hill]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
