<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="107660" ns="0" title="Monrovia, California"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Infobox settlement
|official_name            = City of Monrovia
|settlement_type          = [[City]]
|image_skyline            =Monrovia CA San Gabriel Mountains i210.JPG 
|imagesize                =
|image_caption            =[[Interstate 210|I210]] in Monrovia with San Gabriel Mountains in the background.
|image_seal               =
|image_map                = LA County Incorporated Areas Monrovia highlighted.svg
|mapsize                  = 250x200px
|map_caption              = Location of Monrovia in [[Los Angeles County, California|Los Angeles County]], [[California]].
|image_map1               =
|mapsize1                 =
|map_caption1             =
|subdivision_type         = [[List of countries|Country]]
|subdivision_name         = [[United States]]
|subdivision_type1        = [[Political divisions of the United States|State]]
|subdivision_name1        = [[California]]
|subdivision_type2        = [[List of counties in California|County]]
|subdivision_name2        = [[Los Angeles County, California|Los Angeles]]
|government_type          =
|leader_title             = [[City council]]
|leader_name              =
&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;[[Mayor]] [[Mary Ann Lutz]]&lt;br /&gt;
&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;Mayor Pro Tem Tom Adams&lt;br /&gt;
&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;Dan Kirby&lt;br /&gt;
&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;Joe Garcia&lt;br /&gt;
&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;Tom Adams|
|leader_title1             = [[City Treasurer]]
|leader_name1              = Stephen Baker&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.cacities.org/resource_files/24827.Electedcitytreasurers06.rtf California League of Cities, Elected City Treasurers]&lt;/ref&gt;
|established_date         =
&lt;!-- Area------------------&gt;
|area_magnitude           =
| unit_pref               =US
| area_footnotes          = &lt;ref&gt;[http://www.census.gov/geo/www/gazetteer/files/Gaz_places_national.txt U.S. Census]&lt;/ref&gt;
| area_total_sq_mi        = 13.714
| area_land_sq_mi         = 13.605
| area_water_sq_mi        = 0.109
| area_total_km2          = 35.519
| area_land_km2           = 35.237
| area_water_km2          = 0.282
| area_water_percent      = 0.79
| area_note               = 
|elevation_m              = 174
|elevation_ft             = 571
|coordinates_display      = inline,title
|coordinates_type         = region:US_type:city
|latd = 34 |latm = 8 |lats = 39 |latNS = N
|longd = 118 |longm = 0 |longs = 7 |longEW = W
|population_as_of         = 2010
|population_total         = 36590
|population_density_km2   = auto
|timezone                 = [[Pacific Time Zone|PST]]
|utc_offset               = -8
|timezone_DST             = PDT
|utc_offset_DST           = -7
|latitude = 34°08'39&quot; N
|longitude = 118°00'07&quot; W
|website                  = [http://www.ci.monrovia.ca.us/ ci.monrovia.ca.us]
|postal_code_type         = [[ZIP code]]s
|postal_code              = 91016, 91017
|area_code                = [[Area code 626|626]]
|blank_name               = [[Federal Information Processing Standard|FIPS code]]
|blank_info               = 06-48648
|blank1_name              = [[Geographic Names Information System|GNIS]] feature ID
|blank1_info              = 1661049
|footnotes                =
}}
'''Monrovia''' is a city located in the foothills of the [[San Gabriel Mountains]] in the [[San Gabriel Valley]] of [[Los Angeles County, California|Los Angeles County]], [[California]], [[United States]].  The population was 36,590 at the 2010 census, down from 36,929 at the 2000 census. Monrovia has been used extensively for filming many TV shows, movies and commercials.

==History==
[[Image:Monrovia-1886.jpg|250px|left|thumb|Monrovia, 1886 (Myrtle Ave., looking north).]]
Monrovia is the fourth oldest general law city in Los Angeles County and the [[Los Angeles Basin|L.A. Basin]] (after [[Los Angeles]], [[Santa Monica, California|Santa Monica]], and [[Pasadena, California|Pasadena]]). Incorporated in 1887, Monrovia has grown from a sparse community of orange ranches to a residential community of 37,000.

Around 500 BC, a band of Shoshonean-speaking Indians established settlements in what is now the San Gabriel Valley. These native Americans came to be called the Gabrieliño Indians by early Spanish explorers, and are now referred to as the [[Tongva people|Tongva]]. The Tongva were not farmers; they gathered wild seeds, berries, and plants along rivers and in marshlands. Abundant oaks in the Valley, such as [[Coast live oak|Coast Live Oak]] and [[Interior live oak|Interior Live Oak]] provided a staple of the Tongva diet:  [[acorn]] mush made of boiled acorn flour.
[[Image:Monrovia-1892.jpg|250px|left|thumb|Monrovia, 1892 (Myrtle Ave., looking north).]]
In 1769, when all [[California]] was claimed by the [[Spanish monarchy|King of Spain]], Europeans first visited the San Gabriel Valley, including Monrovia.  An expedition from [[San Diego, California|San Diego]] passed through en route to [[Monterey Bay]], commanded by [[Gaspar de Portolà|Don Gaspar Portola]]. Accompanying Portola were a [[Franciscan]] Father from [[Junípero Serra|Father Junipero Serra's]] Franciscan order of Mexico, and [[Juan Crespi]], the expedition's diarist. Much of what is known of early California is known only from Crespi's detailed descriptions.

In 1771, the Franciscans established the [[Mission San Gabriel Arcangel]] in the San Gabriel Valley. The mission was a resting point for early California travelers and gathered most of the native Tongva into an agricultural lifestyle. Following the [[Mexican Revolution]] in 1839, the mission lands were nationalized.

In 1841, California Governor [[Juan Alvarado]] gave [[Rancho Azusa de Duarte]] to [[Andres Duarte]], a Mexican soldier, and he gave [[Rancho Santa Anita]] to [[Hugo Reid]], a naturalized Mexican citizen of Scottish birth. Monrovia is made of parts of these two ranchos.

In the mid-19th century, most of Rancho Azusa de Duarte was subdivided and sold by Duarte to settle his debts. Some of those parcels would eventually end up as part of the ranch of [[William N. Monroe]], Monrovia's namesake.
[[Image:Monrovia-1903.jpg|250px|left|thumb|Pacific Electric in Monrovia, 1903.]]
Rancho Santa Anita changed hands several times before the famous multimillionaire, silver baron and rancher, [[Elias Jackson Baldwin|E.J. &quot;Lucky&quot; Baldwin]] acquired it in 1875. That same year his Los Angeles Investment Company began subdividing and selling parcels from many of his ranchos. In 1883, 240 acres (970,000 m²) of Rancho Santa Anita were sold to Monroe for $30,000. Additional parcels of Rancho Santa Anita were sold to Edward F. Spence, [[John Dustin Bicknell|John D. Bicknell]], James F. Crank, and J.F. Falvey.

The completion of the [[Santa Fe Railroad|Santa Fe]] (which would run through Monrovia) and [[Southern Pacific Railroad|Southern Pacific]] railroads to Southern California would bring new people looking for homes and investment opportunities. With this in mind, Monroe, Spence, Bicknell, Crank, and Falvey decided to combine their land under the business name of the Monrovia Land and Water Company in 1886. The combined lots formed the Town of Monrovia Subdivision. The original borders of the Town of Monrovia Subdivision were Canyon Blvd. to the east, Walnut Ave. to the south, Magnolia Ave. to the west, and Lime Ave. to the north. The subdivision was then itself quickly subdivided into 600 {{convert|500|ft|m|sing=on}} by {{convert|160|ft|m|sing=on}} lots and sold. Some lucky buyers of these lots turned around and sold them very quickly. Those who chose to hold on to their property saw its value fall to a fraction of its 1886-1887 value.

The town was incorporated in 1887 under the leadership of prohibitionists who wished to control the arrival of an unwelcome saloon. The first order of business for the newly formed government was to pass a tippler's law, prohibiting the sale of alcohol.

In 1903 the Monrovia News was established. In the same year, the [[Pacific Electric]] was opened providing transportation to and from Los Angeles, making it possible for Monrovian homeowners to work in Los Angeles.
[[Image:Monrovia-May-16-1914.jpg|350px|right|thumb|Monrovia, 1914 (Myrtle Ave., looking north).]]
In 1905 [[Andrew Carnegie|Carnegie]] funds became available and with the help of the Board of Trade (forerunner to the [[Chamber of Commerce]]), and the Monrovia Women's Club, a bond issue was passed to purchase the Granite Bank Building to be used as a City Hall, and to acquire property for a public park.  The Granite Building serves as the city hall, fire and police department facilities in 1961 and the fire department in 1974. In 1956, the old [[Carnegie library]] building was torn down and the present library constructed. The library now boasts a book collection of 95,000 volumes.As of March 2007, the city's residents were asked to vote on a new, upgraded library which is ADA-compliant and has twice as much room for books and computer usage as the current one(the measure passed with at least 70% of the vote.).

A [[Council-manager government|city council-manager]] type government was instituted in 1923.

In 1937, Patrick McDonald opened a simple restaurant on Huntington Drive (Route 66) near the old Monrovia Airport called &quot;The Airdrome&quot; (hamburgers were ten cents, and all-you-can-drink orange juice was five cents); the restaurant remained there until 1940, when he and his two sons, [[Richard and Maurice McDonald|Maurice and Richard]], moved the entire building {{convert|40|mi|km}} east to [[San Bernardino, California|San Bernardino]] to the corner of West 14th Street and 1398 North E Street renaming it &quot;[[McDonald's]]&quot;. In 1955, milkshake machine salesman [[Ray Kroc]] made a franchising deal with the McDonald brothers.  In 1961 Kroc purchased the business rights for $2.7 million.  For years after the [[McDonald's Corporation]] claimed the 1955 Des Plaines, Illinois Mcdonald's to be the first (it was the first location franchised through Ray Kroc), and only recently has recognized [[San Bernardino, California|San Bernardino]].  Some though claim Monrovia to be the &quot;real&quot; birthplace, but that's subjective since McDonald's as it was first franchised in 1953 (in Phoenix, Arizona and Downey, California) came into being following the development of the &quot;[[Speedee|Speedee Service System]]&quot; in 1948.
[[File:UptonSinclairHouse-186-sm.jpg|thumb|right|[[Upton Sinclair House]]]]
The [[Upton Sinclair House]], home to activist and author [[Upton Sinclair]], is located in Monrovia and is a [[National Historic Landmark]]. In 1995 Monrovia received the [[All America City]] Award from the [[National Civic League]].

Monrovia operates its own Fire &amp; Police Departments led by Fire Chief Christopher Donovan and Chief of Police Roger W. Johnson

==Geography==
According to the [[United States Census Bureau]], the city has a total area of {{convert|35.5|km2|mi2|1|sp=us}}.  {{convert|13.6|sqmi|km2}} of it is land and {{convert|0.1|sqmi|km2}} of it (0.79%) is water.

==Demographics==
===2010===
The [[2010 United States Census]]&lt;ref&gt;{{USCensus-2010CA}}&lt;/ref&gt; reported that Monrovia had a population of 36,590. The [[population density]] was 2,668.1 people per square mile (1,030.2/km²). The racial makeup of Monrovia was 21,932 (59.9%) [[White (U.S. Census)|White]], 4,107 (11.2%) [[Asian (U.S. Census)|Asian]], 2,500 (6.8%) [[African American (U.S. Census)|African American]], 279 (0.8%) [[Native American (U.S. Census)|Native American]], 76 (0.2%) [[Pacific Islander (U.S. Census)|Pacific Islander]], 5,818 (15.9%) from [[Race (United States Census)|other races]], and 1,878 (5.1%) from two or more races.  [[Hispanic (U.S. Census)|Hispanic]] or [[Latino (U.S. Census)|Latino]] of any race were 14,043 persons (38.4%). 

The Census reported that 36,434 people (99.6% of the population) lived in households, 61 (0.2%) lived in non-institutionalized group quarters, and 95 (0.3%) were institutionalized.  

There were 13,762 households, out of which 4,725 (34.3%) had children under the age of 18 living in them, 6,295 (45.7%) were [[marriage|opposite-sex married couples]] living together, 2,073 (15.1%) had a female householder with no husband present, 778 (5.7%) had a male householder with no wife present.  There were 793 (5.8%) [[POSSLQ|unmarried opposite-sex partnerships]], and 131 (1.0%) [[same-sex partnerships|same-sex married couples or partnerships]]. 3,649 households (26.5%) were made up of individuals and 1,276 (9.3%) had someone living alone who was 65 years of age or older. The average household size was 2.65.  There were 9,146 [[family (U.S. Census)|families]] (66.5% of all households); the average family size was 3.24.

The population was spread out with 8,514 people (23.3%) under the age of 18, 3,084 people (8.4%) aged 18 to 24, 10,733 people (29.3%) aged 25 to 44, 10,018 people (27.4%) aged 45 to 64, and 4,241 people (11.6%) who were 65 years of age or older.  The median age was 37.9 years. For every 100 females there were 91.6 males.  For every 100 females age 18 and over, there were 87.0 males.

There were 14,473 housing units at an average density of 1,055.4 per square mile (407.5/km²), of which 6,809 (49.5%) were owner-occupied, and 6,953 (50.5%) were occupied by renters. The homeowner vacancy rate was 1.3%; the rental vacancy rate was 4.9%.  18,478 people (50.5% of the population) lived in owner-occupied housing units and 17,956 people (49.1%) lived in rental housing units.

===2000===
As of the [[census]]{{GR|2}} of 2000, there were 36,929 people, 13,502 households, and 9,086 families residing in the city.  The [[population density]] was 2,686.5 inhabitants per square mile (1,037.0/km²).  There were 13,957 housing units at an average density of 1,015.3 per square mile (391.9/km²).  The racial makeup of the city was 62.92% [[White (U.S. Census)|White]], 8.67% [[African American (U.S. Census)|African American]], 7.02% [[Asian (U.S. Census)|Asian]], 0.87% [[Native American (U.S. Census)|Native American]], 0.13% [[Pacific Islander (U.S. Census)|Pacific Islander]], 15.61% from [[Race (United States Census)|other races]], and 4.77% from two or more races. [[Hispanic (U.S. Census)|Hispanic]] or [[Latino (U.S. Census)|Latino]] of any race were 35.24% of the population.

There were 13,502 households out of which 35.4% had children under the age of 18 living with them, 46.4% were [[Marriage|married couples]] living together, 15.4% had a female householder with no husband present, and 32.7% were non-families. 26.0% of all households were made up of individuals and 8.8% had someone living alone who was 65 years of age or older.  The average household size was 2.71 and the average family size was 3.29.

In the city the population was spread out with 27.4% under the age of 18, 8.0% from 18 to 24, 34.0% from 25 to 44, 20.2% from 45 to 64, and 10.4% who were 65 years of age or older.  The median age was 34 years. For every 100 females there were 92.2 males.  For every 100 females age 18 and over, there were 87.6 males.

The median income for a household in the city was $45,375, and the median income for a family was $49,703. Males had a median income of $41,039 versus $32,259 for females. The [[per capita income]] for the city was $21,686.  About 9.7% of families and 13.1% of the population were below the [[poverty line]], including 18.3% of those under age 18 and 9.7% of those age 65 or over.

==Government and infrastructure==
In the [[California State Legislature|state legislature]] Monrovia is located in the 29th [[California State Senate|Senate]] District, represented by Republican [[Bob Huff]], and in the 44th and 59th [[California State Assembly|Assembly]] Districts, represented by Democrat [[Anthony J. Portantino]] and Republican [[Tim Donnelly (politician)|Tim Donnelly]] respectively. Federally, Monrovia is located in [[California's 26th congressional district]], which has a [[Cook Partisan Voting Index|Cook PVI]] of R +4&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | title = Will Gerrymandered Districts Stem the Wave of Voter Unrest? | publisher = Campaign Legal Center Blog | url=http://www.clcblog.org/blog_item-85.html | accessdate = 2008-02-10}}&lt;/ref&gt; and is represented by Republican [[David Dreier]].

The [[Los Angeles County Department of Health Services]] operates the Monrovia Health Center in Monrovia.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;[http://publichealth.lacounty.gov/phn/docs/HealthCenter/monrovia.pdf Monrovia Health Center].&quot; [[Los Angeles County Department of Health Services]]. Retrieved on March 27, 2010.&lt;/ref&gt;

==Education==
[[File:Monrhs.JPG|thumb|right|[[Monrovia High School]]]]
[[Monrovia Unified School District]] operates public schools.

[[Monrovia High School]] gained a creditable rating in its early history. The first school in Monrovia was built in 1887. It was located where Monroe School now stands, and housed the entire elementary and high school student body. A new high school on the property now occupied by Clifton Middle School was erected in 1905, and in 1912 was greatly expanded by the addition of new buildings. In 1928 a high school to serve the communities of Monrovia, [[Arcadia, California|Arcadia]] and [[Duarte, California|Duarte]] was built. The same structure now serves only Monrovia students, as the elementary and high school district were unified into one district in 1961. The district now has one high school, one continuation school, two middle schools and five elementary schools, and is part of the [[Citrus Community College District]]. There are also three parochial schools in Monrovia.

Monrovia, California's schools are:
*Bradoaks Elementary School,  K-5, 930 E. Lemon
*Calvary Road Baptist Academy, K-12, 319 W. Olive
*Canyon Early Learning Center, public pre-K, 1000 South Canyon
*Canyon Oaks High School (public alternative), 7-12, 930 Royal Oaks Drive
*Carden of the Foothills, K-8, 429 Wild Rose
*Church of the Nazarene, K-6 303 W. Colorado
* Clifton Middle School,  6-8, 226 S. Ivy
*First Lutheran School, pre-K-8, 1323 South Magnolia
*First Presbyterian Church Preschool, 101 E. Foothill Blvd.
*Immaculate Conception School, K-8, 726 Shamrock
*Joe Ferrante Music Academy, K-12, 126 E. Colorado Blvd.
* Mayflower Elementary School,  K-5, 210 North Mayflower
* Monroe Elementary School,  K-5, 402 W. Colorado
* Monrovia Community Adult School] 920 South Mountain
* Monrovia High School 9-12, 845 W. Colorado Boulevard
*Monrovia Mountain School, public Alternative K-8, 950 S. Mountain Avenue
* Mt. Sierra College Trade College
* Plymouth Elementary K-5, 1300 Boley Street
* Santa Fe Middle School 6-8, 148 W. Duarte Road
*Serendipity Early Care and Education Center, K, 940 W. Duarte Road
* Wild Rose Elementary, A California Distinguished School K-5, 232 Jasmine
* Vista Ridge Academy, 1311S. Shamrock

Monrovia Public Library is located at Library Park, at the corner Myrtle Avenue and Lime Avenue.

==Transportation==
[[File:Monrovia trolley bus.jpg|thumb|right|Monrovia Trolley Bus in front of the landmark Krikorian Theater]]
Monrovia has several main roads, including [[Foothill Boulevard (Southern California)|Foothill Boulevard]] and [[Huntington Drive]] (historic [[U.S. Route 66|Route 66]]).  It is also served by the [[Interstate 210 and State Route 210 (California)|Foothill Freeway]] (I-210).

In 2014, [[Los Angeles County Metropolitan Transportation Authority|Metro]] will open a new [[light-rail]] station in Monrovia.  [[Monrovia (Los Angeles Metro station)|Monrovia Station]] will be located at the intersection of Myrtle Avenue and Duarte Road, and will be served by the [[Gold Line (Los Angeles Metro)|Metro Gold Line]].&lt;ref&gt;http://www.foothillextension.org/city_monrovia.html&lt;/ref&gt; It will be at the same location of the former [[Santa Fe Railway]] depot, which still stands.

==Economy==
[[Original Tommy's]], [[Trader Joe's]], [[Green Dot Corporation|Green Dot]] and [[Naked Juice]] are based in Monrovia.

===Top employers===
According to the City's 2010 Comprehensive Annual Financial Report,&lt;ref name=&quot;cafr2009&quot;&gt;[http://www.ci.monrovia.ca.us/images/content/city_government/departments/AdminServices/cafr_09-10.pdf City of Monrovia CAFR]&lt;/ref&gt; the top employers in the city are:

{| class=&quot;wikitable&quot; border=&quot;1&quot;
|-
! #
! Employer
! # of Employees
|-
| 1
|Monrovia Unified School District
|488
|-
| 2
|[[Ducommun]] AeroStructures 
|463
|-
| 3
|[[WorleyParsons]]
|452
|-
| 4
|[[The Home Depot]]
|364
|-
| 5
|[[Oracle Corporation|Oracle]]
|315
|-
| 6
|[[AeroVironment]]
|267
|-
| 7
|Vinyl Technology
|251
|-
| 8
|[[City of Hope National Medical Center|City of Hope]]
|250
|-
| 9
|[[ITT Corporation|ITT]] Systems
|240
|-
| 10
|City of Monrovia
|240
|-
|}

==Trivia==

The House to the 1986 horror-comedy cult film [[House (1986 film)]] is located at 329 Melrose Avenue in Monrovia.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.movie-locations.com/movies/h/House.html&lt;/ref&gt;

==Notable residents==
{{div col|2}}
* [[Kenny Baker (entertainer)|Kenny Baker]], singer and actor
* [[Dicky Barrett]], frontman, [[Mighty Mighty Bosstones]], late night TV announcer
* [[Ron Brown]], actor
* [[Mary Ford]], vocalist and guitarist
* [[Jim Fuller (musician)|Jim Fuller]], guitarist for [[The Surfaris]] (of &quot;Wipeout&quot; fame)
* [[Prince Gomolvilas]], playwright
* [[Dean R. Hirsch]], president of [[World Vision International]]
* [[Corky King]], founder of [[Summum]]
* [[Scott Land]], puppeteer/actor
* [[Francis M. Pottenger, Jr.]], nutrition researcher
* [[Upton Sinclair]] and [[Mary Craig Sinclair]], authors and producers
* [[Jacob Smith (actor)|Jacob Smith]], actor
* [[William A. Spinks]] (1865&amp;ndash;1933), champion [[carom billiards]] pro, co-inventor of modern [[Cue sports#Chalk|billiards cue chalk]], oil investor, and flower and [[avocado]] farmer (developer of the Spinks avocado [[cultivar]]); also maintained a home and farm in nearby Duarte
*[[The Fabulous Wonder Twins]], entertainers
* [[Jason Earles]], actor, [[Hannah Montana]]
* [[Henry Alonzo]], Entertainment Entrepreneur 
*[[Bill Cormalis]], visual artist
* [[Michael Lee (keyboardist)|Michael Lee]], keyboardist for [[Meredith Brooks]] and [[Melissa Etheridge]]
{{div col end}}

==References==
{{Reflist}}

==External links==
{{Portal|Los Angeles|Greater Los Angeles|Southern California}}
{{Commons category}}
*[http://www.ci.monrovia.ca.us/ Monrovia official website]
*{{Cite Americana|year=1920|Monrovia (California)|display=Monrovia, Cal.}}

{{Cities of Los Angeles County, California}}
{{Greater Los Angeles Area}}

[[Category:Communities in the San Gabriel Valley]]
[[Category:Cities in Los Angeles County, California]]
[[Category:Communities on U.S. Route 66]]
[[Category:Incorporated cities and towns in California]]
[[Category:Populated places established in 1887]]

[[ar:مونروفيا، لوس أنجليس، كاليفورنيا]]
[[bg:Монровия (Калифорния)]]
[[ca:Monrovia (Califòrnia)]]
[[de:Monrovia (Kalifornien)]]
[[es:Monrovia (California)]]
[[fr:Monrovia (Californie)]]
[[sw:Monrovia, California]]
[[ht:Monrovia, Kalifòni]]
[[nl:Monrovia (Californië)]]
[[pt:Monrovia (Califórnia)]]
[[ru:Монровия (Калифорния)]]
[[simple:Monrovia, California]]
[[tl:Monrovia, California]]
[[vo:Monrovia (California)]]
[[zh:蒙诺维亚]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
