<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="107659" ns="0" title="Maywood, California"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Infobox settlement
|official_name            = Maywood
|other_name               =
|native_name              = &lt;!-- for cities whose native name is not in English --&gt;
|nickname                 =
|motto                    =
|image_skyline            = MaywoodMontageCA.jpg
|imagesize                =
|image_caption            = Images, from top, left to right: Maywood Skyline, Aquatic Center, Maywood Villas, Maywood Academy
|image_flag               =
|flag_size                =
|image_seal               = Seal_maywood_ca.png
|seal_size                =
|image_shield             =
|shield_size              =
|image_blank_emblem       =
|blank_emblem_size        =
|image_map                = LA County Incorporated Areas Maywood highlighted.svg
|mapsize                  = 250x200px
|map_caption              = Location of Maywood in [[Los Angeles County, California|Los Angeles County]], [[California]]
|image_map1               =
|mapsize1                 =
|map_caption1             =
|subdivision_type         = [[List of countries|Country]]
|subdivision_name         = [[United States]]
|subdivision_type1        = [[Political divisions of the United States|State]]
|subdivision_name1        = [[California]]
|subdivision_type2        = [[List of counties in California|County]]
|subdivision_name2        =  [[Los Angeles County, California|Los Angeles]]
|subdivision_type3        =
|subdivision_name3        =
|subdivision_type4        =
|subdivision_name4        =
|government_type          =
|leader_title             = [[Mayor]]
|leader_name              = Ana Rosa Rizo &lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url = http://www.pantagraph.com/articles/2008/02/04/money/doc47a6a2243022c281997132.txt | title = Maywood Mayor Felipe Aguirre holds a bottle of discolored tap water | accessdate = 2008-06-02}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|leader_title1            = &lt;!-- for places with, say, both a mayor and a city manager --&gt;
|leader_name1             =
|leader_title2            =
|leader_name2             =
|leader_title3            =
|leader_name3             =
|established_title        = &lt;!-- Settled --&gt;
|established_date         =
|established_title2       = &lt;!-- Incorporated (town) --&gt;
|established_date2        =
|established_title3       = Incorporated (city)
|established_date3        = 1924-09-02&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url = http://www.cacities.org/resource_files/20457.IncorpDateLO.doc |  title = Incorporation Dates of California Cities | accessdate = 2007-01-18}}&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;!-- Area------------------&gt;
|area_magnitude           =
| unit_pref               =US
| area_footnotes          = &lt;ref&gt;[http://www.census.gov/geo/www/gazetteer/files/Gaz_places_national.txt U.S. Census]&lt;/ref&gt;
| area_total_sq_mi        = 1.178
| area_land_sq_mi         = 1.178
| area_water_sq_mi        = 0
| area_total_km2          = 3.052
| area_land_km2           = 3.052
| area_water_km2          = 0
| area_water_percent      = 0
| area_note               = 
|area_urban_km2           =
|area_urban_sq_mi         =
|area_metro_km2           =
|area_metro_sq_mi         =
|population_as_of         = 2010
|population_note          =
|population_footnotes     =
|settlement_type          = [[City]]
|population_total         = 27395
|population_density_km2   = auto
|population_metro         =
|population_density_metro_km2     =
|population_density_metro_sq_mi   =
|population_urban                 =
|population_density_urban_km2     =
|population_density_urban_sq_mi   =
|timezone                 = [[Pacific Time Zone|PST]]
|utc_offset               = -8
|timezone_DST             = PDT
|utc_offset_DST           = -7
|coordinates_display      = inline,title
|coordinates_type         = region:US_type:city
|latd = 33 |latm = 59 |lats = 16 |latNS = N
|longd = 118 |longm = 11 |longs = 12 |longEW = W
|elevation_m              = 46
|elevation_ft             = 151
|postal_code_type         = [[ZIP Code]]
|postal_code              = 90270&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url = http://zip4.usps.com/zip4/zcl_1_results.jsp?visited=1&amp;pagenumber=0&amp;state=ca&amp;city=Maywood | title = USPS - ZIP Code Lookup - Find a ZIP+ 4 Code By City Results | accessdate = 2007-01-18}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|area_code                = [[Area code 323|323]]&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url = http://www.nanpa.com/nas/public/npa_city_query_step2.do?method=displayData&amp;cityToNpaModel.stateAbbr=CA&amp;cityToNpaModel.city=Maywood | title = Number Administration System - NPA and City/Town Search Results | accessdate = 2007-01-18}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|website                  = [http://www.cityofmaywood.com/ cityofmaywood.com]
|blank_name               = [[Federal Information Processing Standard|FIPS code]]
|blank_info               = 06-46492
|blank1_name              = [[Geographic Names Information System|GNIS]] feature ID
|blank1_info              = 1661000
}}
&lt;!-- Infobox ends --&gt;

'''Maywood''' is a small city in [[Gateway Cities|southeast Los Angeles County, California]].&lt;ref name=&quot;money.cnn.com&quot;&gt;{{cite news|last=Luhby|first=Tami|url=http://money.cnn.com/2010/06/29/news/economy/city_fires_employees/index.htm|title=Maywood, California, lays off all employees - July 1, 2010|publisher=Money.cnn.com|date=2010-07-01|accessdate=2010-08-17}}&lt;/ref&gt; At {{convert|1.18|sqmi|km2}},&lt;ref name=&quot;cityofmaywood.com&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.cityofmaywood.com/index.php?option=com_content&amp;view=article&amp;id=50&amp;Itemid=73|title=City History &amp; Facts|publisher=Cityofmaywood.com|date=1924-09-02|accessdate=2010-08-17}}&lt;/ref&gt; Maywood is the third-smallest incorporated city in Los Angeles County.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.maywoodcalifornia.us|title=www.maywoodcalifornia.us|publisher=www.maywoodcalifornia.us|date=2010-07-22|accessdate=2010-08-17}}&lt;/ref&gt; 

As of July 1, 2010, Maywood became the first municipality in [[California]]&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.economist.com/node/16541692?story_id=16541692&amp;fsrc=rss|title=Municipal finances: There goes everybody|publisher=The Economist|date=2010-07-08|accessdate=2010-08-17}}&lt;/ref&gt; to dismantle its police department, lay off all city employees, except for the city manager, city attorney and elected officials,&lt;ref name=&quot;finance.yahoo.com&quot;&gt;{{cite web|author=Tami Luhby, senior writer|url=http://finance.yahoo.com/news/Maywood-California-lays-off-cnnm-2024697265.html?x=0|title=Maywood, California, lays off all employees|publisher=Finance.yahoo.com|date=2010-07-01|accessdate=2010-08-17}} {{dead link|date=September 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; and contract with outside agencies for the provision of all municipal services, an unprecedented action among California cities.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;lat_jun23&quot;&gt;{{cite news|url=http://articles.latimes.com/2010/jun/23/local/la-me-0623-maywood-20100623|title=Maywood to hire others to run the city|author=Ruben Vives, Jeff Gottlieb and Hector Becerra|date=June 23, 2010|publisher=Los Angeles Times|accessdate=July 18, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; Maywood is now billing itself as the first American city to outsource all of its city services.&lt;ref name=&quot;finance.yahoo.com&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;bloomberg1&quot;&gt;{{cite web|last=Palmeri|first=Christopher|url=http://www.bloomberg.com/news/2010-08-03/california-city-that-outsourced-everyone-is-snared-by-pay-scandal-in-bell.html|title=California City That Outsourced Everyone Is Snared by Pay Scandal in Bell|publisher=Bloomberg|date=2010-08-03|accessdate=2010-08-17}}&lt;/ref&gt; The population was 27,395 at the [[United States 2010 Census|2010 census]].

==History==
The land on which Maywood now stands had been populated by Native American tribes for centuries. The area that would later become Maywood was deeded in 1781 by the [[Spanish Empire|Spanish]] monarchy to Spanish War veteran Manuel Nieto. When the settlement of Pueblo de Nuestra Senora de Los Angeles was recorded, it included the cow pasture (now Maywood) that eventually turned into a rancho.&lt;ref&gt;Ahrens, Edward A. &quot;City of Maywood&quot; pg. 1&lt;/ref&gt;

In 1919, May Wood, a popular young woman who worked for the real estate corporation developing the {{convert|2,300|acre|km2}} ranch into home tracts, agreed to lend her name to the property. The development of Maywood later survived a bitter challenge to dissolve the prospective city in early 1924.&lt;ref&gt;Ahrens, Edward A., &quot;City of Maywood&quot;&lt;/ref&gt;

On September 2, 1924, Maywood's citizens voted to incorporate and about 300 people turned out for the dedication, including Miss May Wood. By 1924, the population of Maywood had reached 1,000. The city featured homes, stores and a movie theater. In the 1930s, gamblers were successfully removed from the city. Maywood Parks and Recreation built Maywood Park, had its beginnings in the 1930s, when a large meadow was turned into the present day baseball field. The Golden State Baseball Association made Maywood Park its home in the early 1950s.

The [[Chrysler Corporation]] had an auto assembly plant in Maywood from the 1920s until its closing in July 1971. It was located at 5800 Eastern Avenue at Slauson, and was generally referred to as the &quot;Los Angeles&quot; Plant.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|title=Chrysler Heritage: A Photographic History|last=Davis|first=Michael W.R.|year=2001|publisher=|isbn=0-7385-0779-2|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=btNBJdkw4joC&amp;dq=chrysler+history&amp;printsec=frontcover&amp;source=in&amp;hl=en&amp;ei=AvMpTLCUDIyJnQfymtR2&amp;sa=X&amp;oi=book_result&amp;ct=result&amp;resnum=12&amp;ved=0CFQQ6AEwCw#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false|accessdate=July 19, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; When the city of Commerce was incorporated in 1961, that corner was annexed as were several in the surrounding area.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.varley.net/Pages/VarleyYarns/2%20Down%20a%20lazy%20concrete%20river/6%20Down%20a%20lazy%20concrete%20river%20-%20Five%20Towns.htm|title=Books|publisher=Varley.net|date=2007-07-23|accessdate=2010-08-17}}&lt;/ref&gt; Lockheed A-29 Hudson

[[File:RAF Lockheed Hudson.jpg|thumb|right|Lockheed Hudson Mk IIIA (T9422) at the North Atlantic Aviation Museum]]
[[Willys]]-Overland  built its California factory in Maywood, California, in 1929.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://blog.hemmings.com/index.php/2009/02/13/factories-and-dealerships-of-historical-los-angeles|title=Factories and dealerships of historical Los Angeles at Hemmings Blog – Classic and collectible cars and parts|publisher=Blog.hemmings.com|accessdate=2010-08-17}}&lt;/ref&gt; Over 900 people were employed at the new $1.5 million assembly plant. Willys-Overland became the second automobile manufacturer to build a major plant in the city. After the United States entered World War II, automobile production for civilians was phased out and in November 1941, automobile assembly at Maywood was stopped. A great many automobile plants were retooled to manufacture war machinery and for three years during the war, the [[Lockheed Aircraft Corporation]] rented the plant building from Willys-Overland for that purpose. Equipment was installed for the manufacture of sub-assemblies for Hudson Bombers &lt;ref name=&quot;cj3a&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.cj3a.info/cj3a/maywood.html|title=The Maywood Assembly Plant|publisher=Cj3a.info|accessdate=2010-08-17}}&lt;/ref&gt; until the war ended. Willys-Overland began to manufacture the first Jeeps (CJ-2As) for civilians in 1945. As the demand for Jeeps increased, the reconditioning of the plant back to automobile assembly began early in 1947 and by November, Willys was building &quot;West Coast&quot; CJ-2As. By the end of November, 108 Jeeps had been assembled.&lt;ref&gt;Toledo Times&lt;/ref&gt; Jeep Trucks and Station Wagons were incorporated into the West Coast Division's &quot;final assemblies&quot; production lines in 1948. The Maywood plant produced the entire CJ-3A model production duration and about 5% of all CJ-3As were assembled in California. In 1952, Willys-Overland introduced a new post-war model car, the Aero, and they were assembled in both Maywood and Toledo. The entire plant was shut down in 1954.&lt;ref name=&quot;cj3a&quot;/&gt;

Postwar Maywood was a flourishing blue-collar, multi-ethnic suburb of Los Angeles. There were plenty of industrial jobs in aerospace, food processing, auto and furniture manufacturing. But, the early 1970s saw these jobs disappear with the pressure of higher taxes, increased local and state regulation, and the desirability of cheaper land and labor in other markets. Maywood would change over the next two decades by the influx of Hispanic immigrants.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.humanevents.com/article.php?id=37671|title=Welcome to Maywood, Mexico|publisher=Human Events|date=2010-06-25|accessdate=2010-08-17}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===2010 city layoffs===
Maywood officials were given notice in June 2009,&lt;ref name=&quot;lat_jun25&quot;&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.latimes.com/news/local/la-me-maywood-20100625,0,3217996.story|title=Maywood didn't meet insurer's conditions|author=Jeff Gottlieb and Ruben Vives|publisher=Los Angeles Times|date=June 25, 2010|accessdate=July 19, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; that the city would lose its insurance coverage unless they implemented a 20-point performance plan. Maywood also owed the California Insurance Authority $927,135 and had been making interest-only payments. Mainly because of the troubled history, including multiple lawsuits, and the dubious reputation of the Maywood Police Department,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://articles.latimes.com/2007/apr/01/local/me-maywood1|title=Maywood employs police officers with a history of trouble|author=Matt Lait and Scott Glover|date=April 1, 2007|publisher=Los Angeles Times|accessdate=July 19, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; the city’s Liability and Workers Compensation insurer, notified the city in August 2009, that it would cancel its coverage effective July 1, 2010. When the city was unable to find coverage elsewhere, it disbanded its police department, laid off all city employees, except for the city manager, city attorney and elected officials, and contracted with other agencies to provide all municipal services.&lt;ref name=&quot;lat_jun23&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Mayme&quot;&gt;{{cite news|last=Becerra|first=Hector|url=http://www.latimes.com/la-me-maywood-20100810,0,7786763.story|title=Bell salary scandal: Maywood leaders may try to fire Bell|publisher=latimes.com|date=2010-08-10|accessdate=2010-08-17}}&lt;/ref&gt;

An outside audit found that Maywood was losing approximately $620,000 annually from its $10 million general fund budget &lt;ref name=&quot;lat_jun23&quot;/&gt; under the previous seven-year contract with nearby [[Cudahy, California|Cudahy]],&lt;ref name=&quot;finance.yahoo.com&quot;/&gt; because they had neglected to bill Cudahy for administration, vehicle maintenance or insurance. The firm concluded that Maywood was losing about $620,000 a year, or a total of about $4 million in the last six years.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|author=June 25, 2010&amp;nbsp;|&amp;nbsp; 5:52 pm |url=http://latimesblogs.latimes.com/lanow/2010/06/cudahy-to-contract-police-services-with-sheriffs.html|title=Cudahy to contract with the Sheriff’s Department &amp;#124; L.A. NOW &amp;#124; Los Angeles Times|publisher=Latimesblogs.latimes.com|date=2010-06-25|accessdate=2010-08-17}}&lt;/ref&gt; George Perez, Cudahy's city manager, said Maywood's &quot;politics have been getting in the way.&quot; Perez said that he and then-acting Maywood City Manager, Paul Philips would  agree on a new contract, but the Maywood City Council would then send Philips back for further negotiation. Perez said that negotiations disintegrated in February, after Philips resigned.&lt;ref name=&quot;lat_jun25&quot;/&gt;
[[Image:Maywood CA CityHall.jpg|left|thumb|200px|City Hall]]
Councilman Felipe Aguirre said, &quot;We don't want to file for bankruptcy. We don't want to disappear as a city.&quot; Aguirre said filing for bankruptcy was not an option for Maywood because its problems were related specifically to insurance coverage.&lt;ref name=&quot;lat_jun23&quot;/&gt;  Several cities in the state have said that they are close to bankruptcy because of the sharp drop in sales and property tax revenues caused by the deepest recession in decades.&lt;ref name=&quot;lat_jun23&quot;/&gt; During a heated City Council meeting in June 2010, opponents of the plan accused council members of mismanaging the city by failing to maintain insurance coverage.&lt;ref name=&quot;lat_jun23&quot;/&gt;  Under the plan adopted by the City Council that night, council members would continue to be paid to set policy, but all services would be contracted out. &quot;You single-handedly destroyed the city,&quot; Lizeth Sandoval, the city treasurer, told the City Council. Sandoval, a city employee spoke out as a private citizen, and was laid off as part of the cuts.&lt;ref name=&quot;lat_jun23&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.chicagotribune.com/news/la-maywood-m,0,1212634.story |title=Maywood (Los Angeles, California): Maywood (Los Angeles, California) News and Photos|publisher=chicagotribune.com|accessdate=2010-08-17}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Though Maywood officials stopped short of filing for bankruptcy or even giving up the city's municipal status, the city still faces a serious problem with a huge deficit.&lt;ref name=&quot;http://www.cityofmaywood.com&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.cityofmaywood.com|title=City of Maywood|publisher=City of Maywood|accessdate=2010-08-17}}&lt;/ref&gt; The city did keep a few employees as independent contractors when they outsourced most city functions to Bell and police duties to the [[Los Angeles County Sheriff's Department]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Mayme&quot;/&gt; In September 2010, the troubled nearby city of [[Bell, California|Bell]] agreed to cancel the contract to handle the day-to-day operations of neighboring Maywood.&lt;ref&gt;[http://outside.in/maywood-ca/tags/Bell%20Fallout#881175176 Bell Fallout news in Maywood, California|Outside.in local topics|alt4&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt; Maywood has been overrun with political crises — from recalls to a city clerk accused of trying to contract a hit man to kill Councilman Aguirre. In early 2006, a newly-elected Aguirre called Maywood a &quot;sanctuary city&quot; for illegal immigrants.&lt;ref name=&quot;Mayme&quot;/&gt; {{Clarify|date=June 2011}}

==Geography==
Maywood is located at {{Coord|33|59|16|N|118|11|12|W|city}} (33.987864, -118.186553).{{GR|1}} According to the [[United States Census Bureau]], the city has a total area of 1.2 square miles (3.1&amp;nbsp;km²), all land.

It is {{convert|8|mi|km}} southeast from [[Downtown Los Angeles]] [[Financial District, Los Angeles, California|Financial District]] and only {{convert|2|mi|km}} miles east of the [[Los Angeles]] city limit on Slauson Ave and Alamada St in the Central-Alameda neighborhood.&lt;ref name=&quot;Central Alameda Neighborhood of Los Angeles&quot;&gt;[http://projects.latimes.com/mapping-la/neighborhoods/neighborhood/central-alameda/ Los Angeles City Limit]&lt;/ref&gt; Maywood is part of the [[Gateway Cities]] region of southeastern Los Angeles County area. Maywood is bordered by the city of [[Bell, California|Bell]] on the south, [[Vernon, California|Vernon]] on the north and west, [[Huntington Park, California|Huntington Park]] on the southwest, and [[Commerce, California|Commerce]] on the east.

===Climate===
The climate in the city of Maywood is very warm during summer when temperatures tend to be in the 80's and cool during winter when temperatures tend to be in the 50's.&lt;ref name=&quot;cityofmaywood.com&quot;/&gt; The warmest month of the year is August with an average maximum temperature of {{convert|89.40|°F|°C}}, while the coldest month of the year is December with an average minimum temperature of {{convert|47.30|°F|°C}}.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.city-data.com/city/Maywood-California.html |title=Maywood, California (CA 90270) profile: population, maps, real estate, averages, homes, statistics, relocation, travel, jobs, hospitals, schools, crime, moving, houses, sex offenders, news, sex offenders |publisher=City-data.com |date= |accessdate=2010-08-30}}&lt;/ref&gt;  Temperature variations between night and day tend to be moderate during summer with a difference that can reach {{convert|24|°F|°C}}, and moderate during winter with an average difference of {{convert|22|°F|°C}}. The annual average precipitation at Maywood is {{convert|15.07|in|mm}}. The wettest month of the year is February with an average rainfall of {{convert|3.75|in|mm}}.&lt;ref name=&quot;Maywood Average Annual Climate&quot;&gt;[http://www.idcide.com/weather/ca/maywood.htm  Maywood Annual Climate]&lt;/ref&gt; Maywood-area historical tornado activity is significantly above California state average. It is 75% smaller than the overall U.S. average.  On November 7, 1966, a category 2 (max. wind speeds 113-157&amp;nbsp;mph) tornado {{convert|6.2|mi|km}} away from the Maywood city center injured 10 people and caused between $50,000 and $500,000 in damages.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.city-data.com/city/Maywood-California.html#ixzz0y4JAaNbD |title=Maywood, California (CA 90270) profile: population, maps, real estate, averages, homes, statistics, relocation, travel, jobs, hospitals, schools, crime, moving, houses, sex offenders, news, sex offenders |publisher=City-data.com |date= |accessdate=2010-08-30}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Demographics==
{{USCensusPop
| 1930=6794
| 1940=10731
| 1950=13292
| 1960=14588
| 1970=16996
| 1980=21810
| 1990=27850
| 2000=28083
| 2010=27395
| footnote=source:&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
  |url=http://www.census.gov/prod/www/abs/decennial/index.html
  |title=CENSUS OF POPULATION AND HOUSING (1790–2000)
  |publisher=[[U.S. Census Bureau]]
  |accessdate=2010-07-30}}&lt;/ref&gt;
}}
===2010===
The [[2010 United States Census]]&lt;ref&gt;{{USCensus-2010CA}}&lt;/ref&gt; reported that Maywood had a population of 27,395. The [[population density]] was 23,247.5 people per square mile (8,975.9/km²). The racial makeup of Maywood was 14,244 (52.0%) [[White (U.S. Census)|White]], 166 (0.6%) [[African American (U.S. Census)|African American]], 208 (0.8%) [[Native American (U.S. Census)|Native American]], 87 (0.3%) [[Asian (U.S. Census)|Asian]], 20 (0.1%) [[Pacific Islander (U.S. Census)|Pacific Islander]], 11,495 (42.0%) from [[Race (United States Census)|other races]], and 1,175 (4.3%) from two or more races.  [[Hispanic (U.S. Census)|Hispanic]] or [[Latino (U.S. Census)|Latino]] of any race were 26,696 persons (97.4%). 

The Census reported that 27,276 people (99.6% of the population) lived in households, 0 (0%) lived in non-institutionalized group quarters, and 119 (0.4%) were institutionalized.  

There were 6,559 households, out of which 4,120 (62.8%) had children under the age of 18 living in them, 3,721 (56.7%) were [[marriage|opposite-sex married couples]] living together, 1,254 (19.1%) had a female householder with no husband present, 717 (10.9%) had a male householder with no wife present.  There were 595 (9.1%) [[POSSLQ|unmarried opposite-sex partnerships]], and 32 (0.5%) [[same-sex partnerships|same-sex married couples or partnerships]]. 599 households (9.1%) were made up of individuals and 231 (3.5%) had someone living alone who was 65 years of age or older. The average household size was 4.16.  There were 5,692 [[family (U.S. Census)|families]] (86.8% of all households); the average family size was 4.30.

The population was spread out with 8,925 people (32.6%) under the age of 18, 3,402 people (12.4%) aged 18 to 24, 8,619 people (31.5%) aged 25 to 44, 4,807 people (17.5%) aged 45 to 64, and 1,642 people (6.0%) who were 65 years of age or older.  The median age was 27.9 years. For every 100 females there were 104.5 males.  For every 100 females age 18 and over, there were 102.9 males.

There were 6,766 housing units at an average density of 5,741.6 per square mile (2,216.9/km²), of which 1,980 (30.2%) were owner-occupied, and 4,579 (69.8%) were occupied by renters. The homeowner vacancy rate was 1.2%; the rental vacancy rate was 2.6%.  9,245 people (33.7% of the population) lived in owner-occupied housing units and 18,031 people (65.8%) lived in rental housing units.

===2000===
As of the [[census]]{{GR|2}} of 2000, there were 28,083 people, 6,469 households, and 5,699 families residing in the city.  The [[population density]] was 23,887.2 inhabitants per square mile (9,188.9/km²).  There were 6,701 housing units at an average density of 5,699.8 per square mile (2,192.6/km²).  The racial makeup of the city was 42.99% [[White (U.S. Census)|White]], 0.36% [[African American (U.S. Census)|African American]], 1.14% [[Native American (U.S. Census)|Native American]], 0.36% [[Asian (U.S. Census)|Asian]], 0.13% [[Pacific Islander (U.S. Census)|Pacific Islander]], 50.48% from [[Race (United States Census)|other races]], and 4.53% from two or more races. [[Hispanic (U.S. Census)|Hispanic]] or [[Latino (U.S. Census)|Latino]] of any race were 96.33% of the population.

There were 6,469 households out of which 62.9% had children under the age of 18 living with them, 60.8% were [[Marriage|married couples]] living together, 16.9% had a female householder with no husband present, and 11.9% were non-families. 8.4% of all households were made up of individuals and 3.2% had someone living alone who was 65 years of age or older.  The average household size was 4.33 and the average family size was 4.47.

In the city the population was varied, with 37.0% under the age of 18, 13.2% from 18 to 24, 32.6% from 25 to 44, 13.0% from 45 to 64, and 4.2% who were 65 years of age or older.  The median age was 25 years. For every 100 females there were 104.1 males.  For every 100 females age 18 and over, there were 105.4 males.

The median income for a household in the city was $30,480, and the median income for a family was $30,361. Males had a median income of $20,646 versus $16,397 for females. The [[per capita income]] for the city was $11,935.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.city-data.com/city/Maywood-California.html |title=Maywood, California (CA 90270) profile: population, maps, real estate, averages, homes, statistics, relocation, travel, jobs, hospitals, schools, crime, moving, houses, sex offenders, news, sex offenders |publisher=City-data.com |date= |accessdate=2010-08-17}}&lt;/ref&gt; About 23.1% of families and 24.5% of the population were below the [[poverty line]], including 29.3% of those under age 18 and 11.7% of those age 65 or over.

=== Immigrant population===
Several news accounts have said Maywood's official population reaches approximately 40,000&amp;nbsp;persons when illegal immigrants are counted. A significant percentage of its residents work in the factories at nearby [[Vernon, California|Vernon]] and [[Commerce, California|Commerce]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://factfinder.census.gov/ http://factfinder.census.gov/] ''factfinder.census.gov''&lt;/ref&gt; The city has been at the forefront of illegal immigration debates.  It is speculated that one- third of Maywood's residents population lives in the U.S. illegally.&lt;ref name=&quot;msnbc.msn.com&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.msnbc.msn.com/id/11964275/ |title=Sanctuary for illegal immigrants - msnbc tv - The Ed Show - msnbc.com |publisher=MSNBC |date=2006-03-27 |accessdate=2010-08-17}}&lt;/ref&gt; The city, 96% of which is Latino, and more than half are foreign-born, has declared itself as a &quot;Sanctuary City&quot; for illegal immigrants.&lt;ref name=&quot;msnbc.msn.com&quot;/&gt;  Councilman Felipe Aguirre stated: &quot;I think we needed to amplify the debate by saying that no human being is illegal. These people are here ... making your clothes, shining your shoes and taking care of your kids. And now you want to develop this hypocritical policy?&quot; &lt;ref name=&quot;latimes.com&quot;&gt;{{cite news| url=http://www.latimes.com/news/printedition/la-me-maywood21mar21,0,4897086.story?coll=la-headlines-business }}{{dead link|date=November 2010}} {{Dead link|date=August 2010|bot=RjwilmsiBot}}&lt;/ref&gt;
But Maywood's actions have made the town a lightning rod for criticism on conservative radio shows and websites. &lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://articles.latimes.com/2006/mar/21/local/me-maywood21 |title=Welcome to Maywood, Where Roads Open Up for Immigrants - Los Angeles Times |publisher=Articles.latimes.com |date=2006-03-21 |accessdate=2010-08-17 | first=Hector | last=Becerra}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Government and infrastructure==
===City government===
Maywood City Hall is located at 4319 E Slauson Avenue. The City Council of Maywood is constituted by Veronica Guardado, Oscar Magana, Felipe Aguirre, Edward Varela, and Thomas Martin.
===WiFi Internet access===
The City of Maywood offers a free WiFi network service to residents, businesses and visitors. Maywood originally provided free WiFi internet access only along the business corridors of [[Slauson Avenue]] and [[Atlantic Boulevard (Los Angeles County)|Atlantic Boulevard]]. It is now city-wide. The coverage is highly dependent upon location and proximity to wireless access points along Atlantic Boulevard and Slauson Avenue. Indoor coverage is severely limited due to the inherent nature of WiFi coverage.  Netlogix is the provider of the service.  The city is the only one in the Southeast Los Angeles area with free WiFi.&lt;ref name=&quot;Programs &amp; Services&quot;&gt;Maywood Free WiFi [http://www.cityofmaywood.com/index.php?option=com_content&amp;view=category&amp;layout=blog&amp;id=111&amp;Itemid=195]. Retrieved 2-24-10.&lt;/ref&gt;

===Emergency services===
[[Image:MaywoodPDandCityHall.JPG|thumb|180jpg|left|alt=Maywood City Hall and Former Police Station.|''Maywood City Hall and Former Police Station'']]
Due to financial crisis the city officials in Maywood  disbanded the Maywood Police Department and contracted with the [[Los Angeles County Sheriff's Department]] for law enforcement services.   In August  2010, the  Sheriff's Department went out walking  in Maywood streets and knocking on residents' doors  to survey the safety and policing needs in the community.  The nearby East Los Angeles Sheriff’s Station will address non-emergency police questions and concerns including requests for police reports.&lt;ref name=&quot;cityofmaywood1&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.cityofmaywood.com/ |title=City of Maywood |publisher=City of Maywood |date= |accessdate=2010-08-30}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Fire protection in Maywood is provided by the [[Los Angeles County Fire Department]]. Ambulance transport is provided by [[Care Ambulance Service]]. The [[Los Angeles County Sheriff's Department]] will continue to provide police and aerial support to the city of Maywood.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.cityofmaywood.com/index.php?option=com_content&amp;view=article&amp;id=87&amp;Itemid=111 |title=Fire Services |publisher=Cityofmaywood.com |date= |accessdate=2010-08-30}}&lt;/ref&gt;


===County government===
The [[Los Angeles County Department of Health Services]] operates the Whittier Health Center in [[Whittier, California|Whittier]], serving Maywood.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;[http://publichealth.lacounty.gov/phn/docs/HealthCenter/whittier.pdf Whittier Health Center].&quot; [[Los Angeles County Department of Health Services]]. Retrieved on March 18, 2010.&lt;/ref&gt;
[[Image:MaywoodPostOffice.jpg|thumb|alt=Maywood's United States Post Office|''Maywood Post Office'']]

===State and federal===
In the [[California State Legislature|state legislature]] Maywood is located in the 22nd [[California State Senate|Senate]] District, represented by Democrat [[Gil Cedillo]], and in the 46th [[California State Assembly|Assembly]] District, represented by Democrat [[John A. Perez]]. Federally, Maywood is located in [[California's 34th congressional district]], which has a [[Cook Partisan Voting Index|Cook PVI]] of D +23&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | title = Will Gerrymandered Districts Stem the Wave of Voter Unrest? | publisher = Campaign Legal Center Blog | url=http://www.clcblog.org/blog_item-85.html | accessdate = 2008-02-10}}&lt;/ref&gt; and is represented by Democrat [[Lucille Roybal-Allard]]. Supervisor Gloria Molina represents Maywood.

The [[United States Postal Service]] Maywood Post Office is located at 4357 Slauson Avenue.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;[http://usps.whitepages.com/service/post_office/67354?p=2&amp;s=CA&amp;service_name=post_office&amp;z=Maywood Post Office Location - MAYWOOD].&quot; ''[[United States Postal Service]]''. Retrieved on December 6, 2008.&lt;/ref&gt;

===Transportation===
[[Image:MaywoodExpress.JPG|thumb|left|''Maywood Express'' bus]]
The city can be reached by Atlantic Boulevard which runs north and south through the city and Slauson Avenue which runs east and west through the city. Maywood is also accessible via the [[Interstate 710]] on Atlantic Boulevard. [[Los Angeles County Metropolitan Transportation Authority]] (Metro) provides bus services to the city, Metro Local Line 108 and Metro Rapid Line 358 on Slauson Avenue.&lt;ref name=&quot;metro.net 108&quot;&gt;[http://www.metro.net/riding_metro/bus_overview/images/108-358.pdf Metro Line 108/358]&lt;/ref&gt; Metro Local Line 260&lt;ref name=&quot;metro.net 260&quot;&gt;[http://www.metro.net/riding_metro/bus_overview/images/260.pdf Metro Local Line 260]&lt;/ref&gt; and Metro Rapid Line 762&lt;ref name=&quot;metro.net 762&quot;&gt;[http://www.metro.net/riding_metro/bus_overview/images/762.pdf Metro Rapid 762]&lt;/ref&gt; on Atlantic Boulevard. Metro Shuttle Line 611 runs through the westside and northside of the city.&lt;ref name=&quot;metro.net 611&quot;&gt;[http://www.metro.net/riding_metro/bus_overview/images/611.pdf Metro Shuttle 611]&lt;/ref&gt;

The city of Maywood also operates a local bus service to its residents called ''Dial-a-Ride''. The shuttles pick up residents at their location and transports them within the city limits for a one way fee of $1.00. The service is free to senior citizens, age 62 and over, and handicapped individuals. Seniors and the handicapped must come to City Hall to pick up their free pass.&lt;ref name=&quot;Maywood Dial-a-Ride&quot;&gt;[http://www.cityofmaywood.com/index.php?option=com_content&amp;view=article&amp;id=89&amp;Itemid=107 Maywood Dial-a-Ride Serivce]&lt;/ref&gt;

==Education==
===K–12 schools===
Maywood is a part of the [[Los Angeles Unified School District]]. The city has also joined
[[South Gate, California|South Gate]], [[Huntington Park, California|Huntington Park]], [[Cudahy, California|Cudahy]], [[Vernon, California|Vernon]], and [[Bell, California|Bell]] in the Southeast Cities School Coalition to improve the education of the children of the Southeast.&lt;ref name=&quot;Southeast Cities Schools Coalition&quot;&gt;[http://southeastschools.net/  Southeast Cities Schools Coalition]&lt;/ref&gt; Several council members from each city are part of this group. The city is offering scholarships to students planning to attend Community Colleges and Universities. This may change with the city reorganization.
[[Image:MaywoodElementarySchool(2).JPG|thumb|alt=Maywood Elementary School.|''Maywood Elementary School'']]

====Public primary schools====
Maywood is served by several public elementary schools, including:
* Fishburn Avenue Elementary School (Maywood)
* [http://www.lausd.k12.ca.us/Heliotrope_EL/ Heliotrope Elementary School] (Maywood)
* [http://www.lausd.k12.ca.us/Loma_Vista_EL Loma Vista Elementary School] (Maywood)
* Maywood Elementary School (Maywood) (opened 2005&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.laschools.org/project-status/one-project?project_number=55.98005 http://www.laschools.org/project-status/one-project?project_number=55.98005] ''laschools.org''&lt;/ref&gt;)
* Nueva Vista Elementary School ([[Bell, California|Bell]])

====Public middle schools====
Maywood is served by several public middle schools, including:
* [http://www.lausd.net/Nimitz_MS/ Nimitz Middle School]  ([[Huntington Park, California|Huntington Park]])
* [http://www.laschools.org/project-status/one-project?project_number=56.40022/ South Region MS #2]  ([[Bell, California|Bell]]) Opens September 2010

====Public secondary schools====
Maywood is served by several public secondary schools, including:
* [[Bell High School (Bell, California)|Bell High School]]  ([[Bell, California|Bell]])
* [[Huntington Park High School]] ([[Huntington Park, California|Huntington Park]])
* [[Maywood Academy High School]] (Maywood)

Most of Maywood is zoned to Bell High School, while a portion is zoned jointly to Bell and Huntington Park high schools.&lt;ref name=&quot;SEHSchanges&quot;&gt;&quot;[http://web.archive.org/web/20060409044938/laschools.org/employee/mpd/fs-mpd/download/map_booklets/Project22.pdf Proposed Changes to South East HS Area Schools].&quot; [[Los Angeles Unified School District]]. Retrieved on June 24, 2010.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;&quot;[http://factfinder.census.gov/servlet/MapItDrawServlet?geo_id=16000US0646492&amp;_bucket_id=50&amp;tree_id=420&amp;context=saff&amp;_lang=en&amp;_sse=on Maywood city, California].&quot; [[U.S. Census Bureau]]. Retrieved on July 2, 2010.&lt;/ref&gt; Any student who lives in the Bell or Huntington Park zones may apply to Maywood Academy High School; Maywood Academy, which opened in 2005 and moved into its permanent campus in 2006, does not have its own attendance boundary because it lacks American football, track and field, and tennis facilities.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;[http://www.maywoodacademy.org/apps/pages/index.jsp?uREC_ID=52515&amp;type=d School History].&quot; [[Maywood Academy High School]]. Retrieved on July 2, 2010.&lt;/ref&gt;  Maywood Academy is a showcase &quot;green&quot; school in the [[Los Angeles Unified School District]] (LAUSD). In the time since its opening, it has made the case that, aside from reducing environmental impact,  sustainable design can dramatically improve a school's learning environment, and hopefully, even its attendance rates. Data is being gathered; it is too soon to demonstrate that this &quot;green school&quot; is fulfilling its goals.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.green-technology.org/green_technology_magazine/maywood.htm |title=Green Technology News |publisher=Green-technology.org |date= |accessdate=2010-08-30}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In November 2009, the voters in Maywood, in an advisory vote, voted against the acquisition and demolition of properties to build a new high school.  The construction of the new school would demolish the homes of over 200 families in Maywood.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.ballotpedia.org/wiki/index.php/Annexation_of_City_of_Maywood_properties_by_LAUSD,_Measure_MS,_November_2009 |title=Annexation of City of Maywood properties by LAUSD, Measure MS, November 2009 |publisher=Ballotpedia |date= |accessdate=2010-08-30}}&lt;/ref&gt;  The voters also voted to have more studies to find an alternative site for the school.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.ballotpedia.org/wiki/index.php/City_of_Maywood_Alternate_LAUSD_School_Site_Selection,_Measure_SC,_November_2009 |title=City of Maywood Alternate LAUSD School Site Selection, Measure SC, November 2009 |publisher=Ballotpedia |date= |accessdate=2010-08-30}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Private schools===
Private schools include Maywood Christian School (K–12), an independent private school,&lt;ref&gt;&quot;[http://www.maywoodchristian.com/1.html Welcome to Maywood Christian School].&quot; ''Maywood Christian School''. Retrieved on December 6, 2008.&lt;/ref&gt; Betania Christian School (1-12), an independent private school,&lt;ref&gt;&quot;[http://www.greatschools.org/california/maywood/23833-Betania-Christian-School/ Betania Christian School].&quot; ''Betania Christian School''. Retrieved on December 6, 2008.&lt;/ref&gt; and St. Rose of Lima School (K-8) of the [[Roman Catholic Archdiocese of Los Angeles]].&lt;ref&gt;&quot;[http://www.archdiocese.la/directories/schools/info.php?school_id=265 St. Rose of Lima School].&quot; ''[[Roman Catholic Archdiocese of Los Angeles]]''. Retrieved on December 6, 2008.&lt;/ref&gt;

==Parks and recreation==
[[Image:MYWDAquaticCenter.JPG|thumb|left|Maywood Park and Aquatic Center]]

Maywood has two major parks and one small pocket park. The existing Maywood Park at 4801 E 58th Street and the new Maywood Riverfront Park at 5000 Slauson Avenue are currently the largest parks in the city, both are in the east side of the city.  Maywood Park has a baseball field and the Maywood Activity Center, which opened in 1999. The Parks and Recreation Department currently maintains all of the parks in the city and offers many activities for all ages, seniors, adults and youth.  Mr. Aldo Perez is Director of Parks and Recreation.&lt;ref name=&quot;http://www.cityofmaywood.com&quot;/&gt;

The Maywood Activities Center (M.A.C.), is available for general public use and offers a wide variety of classes, specialty rooms, indoor basketball court, gymnasium, pool and place for clubs and classes to meet.&lt;ref name=&quot;Parks &amp; Recreation&quot;&gt;Maywood Parks &amp; Recreation Description [http://www.cityofmaywood.com/index.php?option=com_content&amp;view=article&amp;id=162&amp;Itemid=69]. Retrieved 2-24-10.&lt;/ref&gt;
[[Image:LAbikePathMaywood.JPG|thumb|Access to LA River Bike Path at ''Riverfront Park'']]
The new Riverfront Park is located next  to the Los Angeles River and has handball courts,a  basketball court, and soccer field. It also includes an access pathway to the [[Los Angeles River bicycle path|LA River Bike Path]] that travels through {{convert|40|mi|km}} of Los Angeles County, including [[Griffith Park]] and [[Long Beach, California|Long Beach]]
A small pocket park is located in the west side of the city, Pixley Park at 3626 56th Street. Two small pocket parks were proposed to the city in 2008, Maywood Avenue Park and Pine Avenue Park are to be built in the future in the west side of the city. As the city reorganizes, future plans are on hold.

The only sports team located in the city is the [[Maywood Buzz]], which features former NBA star [[Cedric Ceballos]]. The team plays in the '''Maywood Activities Center''', also known as the M.A.C. They are an ABA (American Basketball Association) team. Several famous baseball players have played at Maywood Park including former MLB player [[Marvin Benard]], who attended local rival, [[Bell High School (Bell, California)|Bell High School]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.baseball-reference.com/players/b/benarma01.shtml |title=Marvin Benard Statistics and History |publisher=Baseball-Reference.com |date= |accessdate=2010-08-30}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The [[American Basketball Association (21st century)|ABA]] team, the [[Beijing Aoshen Olympians]] played their inaugural season at the M.A.C. during the 2005–2006 season.  They reached the playoffs, but lost to the [[SoCal Legends]] in the [[Great Eight Tournament]] in [[Rochester, New York|Rochester]]. After the season, the Olympians relocated, and now play on the campus of [[Azusa Pacific University]].

{{-}}

==&quot;Maywood Street Fair&quot;==
&lt;gallery perrow=5&gt;
Image:FoodStandsMaywood.jpg
Image:Maywood Fair Rides.jpg
Image:MaywoodMemorialDayStreetFairs.jpg
Image:Maywood Fair Live Music.jpg
Image:Maywood2010StreetFair.jpg
&lt;/gallery&gt;
Every Memorial Day weekend the City of Maywood holds their annual Street Fair.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.cityofmaywood.com/index.php?option=com_content&amp;view=article&amp;id=151:maywood-street-fair&amp;catid=61:citywide-events&amp;Itemid=120 |title=Maywood Street Fair |publisher=Cityofmaywood.com |date= |accessdate=2010-08-30}}&lt;/ref&gt; It is a place where families, friends, and neighbors get together to experience a variety of food, music, games, rides, and multi-cultural activities. Street fair presale ride tickets will be available at City Hall  until sold out. Location : On Slauson between Pine Avenue and Loma Vista Avenue &lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.cityofmaywood.com/index.php?option=com_jevents&amp;task=icalrepeat.detail&amp;evid=89&amp;Itemid=0&amp;year=2010&amp;month=09&amp;day=05&amp;uid=457d75bf4e2ccf60ff32e48790571f1d |title=Street Fair - Labor Day Weekend |publisher=Cityofmaywood.com |date= |accessdate=2010-08-17}}&lt;/ref&gt; In July, 2010,  Over 600 people attended the  First Annual 4 July Family Fun Day Celebration at the Maywood Activities Center, to honor our nation’s birthday.&lt;ref name=&quot;cityofmaywood1&quot;/&gt;

==Places of worship==
{{columns|width=305px
|col1=
'''First Baptist Church '''
*3759 East 57th Street, Maywood, CA


'''Maywood Apostolic Christian Church  '''
*5001 East 60th Street, Maywood, CA


'''Maywood Church of the Nazarene '''
*4756 Slauson Avenue, Maywood, CA


'''Maywood United Methodist Church'''
*4535 Randolph Street, Maywood, CA


'''Saint Rose of Lima Catholic Church'''
*4450 East 60th Street, Maywood, CA


'''Iglesia Betania'''
*3801 East Slauson Ave, Maywood, CA


'''Bab UL Lim Islamic'''
*5950 Heliotrope Circle, Maywood, CA


'''Zion Lutheran Church'''
*4421 East 61st Street, Maywood, CA


'''Church of Jesus Christ of Latter Day Saints '''
*4407 Randolph Street, Maywood, CA
|col2=
&lt;gallery perrow=3&gt;
Image:Church of Jesus Christ.JPG|Church of Jesus Christ of LDS
Image:Saint Rose of Lima Catholic Church.JPG|Saint Rose of Lima Catholic Church
Image:ZionLutheranChurch.JPG|Zion Lutheran Church
Image:MaywoodIslamicCenter.jpg|Bab UL Lim Islamic Center
&lt;/gallery&gt;
}}

==Notable natives and residents==
[[Dana Plato]] from ''[[Diff'rent Strokes]]'' was born on November 7, 1964, in Maywood, CA&lt;ref name=&quot;Dana Plato IMDB&quot;&gt;[http://www.imdb.com/name/nm0686818/  Dana Plato Profile on imdb.com]&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Jim Messina (musician)|Jim Messina]], ''[[Loggins and Messina]]''

[[Christie Repasy]], American floral artist

==References==
{{Reflist|2}}

==External links==
{{Portal|Los Angeles|Greater Los Angeles|Southern California}}
* [http://www.cityofmaywood.com/ Maywood official website]
* [http://abclocal.go.com/kabc/areaweather?cityId=90270 Maywood Local 24-Hour Weather]
* [http://www.chps.net/chps_schools/Maywood.htm Profile on Maywood Academy High School]
* [http://www.ibm12.com/ Maywood First Baptist Church]
* [http://www.cityofmaywood.com/index.php?option=com_content&amp;view=article&amp;id=50&amp;Itemid=73/ Maywood History and Fun Facts]
* [http://www.flickr.com/groups/maywood_california/ Photography of Maywood California]
*{{cite web|last=Hedgecock|first=Roger|title=Welcome to Maywood, Mexico|url=http://www.humanevents.com/article.php?id=37671|publisher=''[[Human Events]]''|date=2010-06-25}}

{{Cities of Los Angeles County, California}}
{{Greater Los Angeles Area}}

[[Category:Cities in Los Angeles County, California]]
[[Category:Populated places in California with Hispanic majority populations]]
[[Category:Maywood, California]]
[[Category:Incorporated cities and towns in California]]
[[Category:Populated places established in 1924]]

[[ar:مايووود، لوس أنجليس، كاليفورنيا]]
[[bg:Мейуд (град, Калифорния)]]
[[ca:Maywood (Califòrnia)]]
[[de:Maywood (Kalifornien)]]
[[es:Maywood (California)]]
[[fr:Maywood (Californie)]]
[[sw:Maywood, California]]
[[ht:Maywood, Kalifòni]]
[[nl:Maywood (Californië)]]
[[pt:Maywood (Califórnia)]]
[[tl:Maywood, California]]
[[vo:Maywood (California)]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
