<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="107636" ns="0" title="Hermosa Beach, California"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">&lt;!-- Infobox begins --&gt;{{Infobox settlement
|official_name            = City of Hermosa Beach
|other_name               =
|native_name              = &lt;!-- for cities whose native name is not in English --&gt;
|nickname                 =
|motto                    =
|image_skyline            = Hermosa beach summer day.jpg
|imagesize                = 200px
|image_caption            = The Hermosa Beach pier on a hot summer day.
|image_flag               =
|flag_size                =
|image_seal               = Hermosa_Beach_Seal.jpg
|seal_size                =
|image_shield             =
|shield_size              =
|image_blank_emblem       =
|blank_emblem_size        =
|image_map                = LA County Incorporated Areas Hermosa Beach highlighted.svg
|mapsize                  = 250x200px
|map_caption              = Location of Hermosa Beach in [[Los Angeles County, California|Los Angeles County]], [[California]]
|image_map1               =
|mapsize1                 =
|map_caption1             =
|coordinates_display      = inline,title
|coordinates_region       = US-CA
|subdivision_type         = [[List of countries|Country]]
|subdivision_name         = [[United States]]
|subdivision_type1        = [[Political divisions of the United States|State]]
|subdivision_name1        = [[California]]
|subdivision_type2        = [[List of counties in California|County]]
|subdivision_name2        =  [[Los Angeles County, California|Los Angeles]]
|subdivision_type3        =
|subdivision_name3        =
|subdivision_type4        =
|subdivision_name4        =
|government_type          =
|leader_title             = [[Mayor]]&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url = http://www.hermosabch.org/index.aspx?page=99 | title = City Council - City of Hermosa Beach, CA| accessdate = 2009-03-14}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|leader_name              = Howard Fishman
|leader_title1            = [[Mayor]] [[Pro Tempore]]
|leader_name1             = Jeff Duclos
|leader_title2            = Councilmembers
|leader_name2             = Peter Tucker, Michael DiVigrilio, Patrick &quot;Kit&quot; Bobko
|leader_title3            = [[City Treasurer]]
|leader_name3             = David Cohn
|leader_title4            = City Clerk (elected)
|leader_name4             = Elaine Doerfling 
|established_title        = &lt;!-- Settled --&gt;
|established_date         =
|established_title2       = &lt;!-- Incorporated (town) --&gt;
|established_date2        =
|established_title3       = Incorporated (city)
|established_date3        = 1907-01-14&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url = http://www.cacities.org/resource_files/20457.IncorpDateLO.doc |  title = Incorporation Dates of California Cities | accessdate = 2007-01-18}}&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;!-- Area------------------&gt;
|area_magnitude           =
| unit_pref               =US
| area_footnotes          = &lt;ref&gt;[http://www.census.gov/geo/www/gazetteer/files/Gaz_places_national.txt U.S. Census]&lt;/ref&gt;
| area_total_sq_mi        = 1.427
| area_land_sq_mi         = 1.427
| area_water_sq_mi        = 0
| area_total_km2          = 3.695
| area_land_km2           = 3.695
| area_water_km2          = 0
| area_water_percent      = 0
| area_note               = 
|area_urban_km2           =
|area_urban_sq_mi         =
|area_metro_km2           =
|area_metro_sq_mi         =
|population_as_of         = 2010
|population_note          =
|population_footnotes     =
|settlement_type          = [[City]]
|population_total         = 19506
|population_density_km2   = auto
|population_density_sq_mi = auto
|population_metro         =
|population_density_metro_km2     =
|population_density_metro_sq_mi   =
|population_urban                 =
|population_density_urban_km2     =
|population_density_urban_sq_mi   =
|timezone                 = [[Pacific Time Zone|PST]]
|utc_offset               = -8
|timezone_DST             = PDT
|utc_offset_DST           = -7
|latd = 33 |latm = 51 |lats = 59 |latNS = N
|longd = 118 |longm = 23 |longs = 59 |longEW = W
|elevation_m              = 8
|elevation_ft             = 26
|postal_code_type         = [[ZIP Code]]
|postal_code              = 90254&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url = http://zip4.usps.com/zip4/zcl_1_results.jsp?visited=1&amp;pagenumber=0&amp;state=ca&amp;city=Hermosa%20Beach | title = USPS - ZIP Code Lookup - Find a ZIP+ 4 Code By City Results | accessdate = 2007-01-18}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|area_code                = [[Area code 310|310]] and [[Area code 424|424]]
|website                  = [http://www.hermosabch.org/ www.hermosabch.org/]
|blank_name               = [[Federal Information Processing Standard|FIPS code]]
|blank_info               = 06-33364
|blank1_name              = [[Geographic Names Information System|GNIS]] feature ID
|blank1_info              = 1652719
|footnotes                =
}}
&lt;!-- Infobox ends --&gt;

'''Hermosa Beach''' is a beachfront city in [[Los Angeles County, California|Los Angeles County]], [[California]], [[United States]]. Its population was 19,506 at the 2010 census, up from 18,566 at the 2000 census.

The city is located in the [[South Bay, Los Angeles|South Bay]] region of the [[Greater Los Angeles Area|greater Los Angeles area]] and is one of the three [[Beach Cities]]. Hermosa Beach is bordered by the other two, [[Manhattan Beach, California|Manhattan Beach]] to the north and [[Redondo Beach, California|Redondo Beach]] to the south and east.

The city's beach is popular for [[sunbathing]], [[beach volleyball]], [[surfing]] and [[paddleboarding]]. The city itself extends only about 15 blocks from east to west and 40 blocks from north to south, with the [[Pacific Coast Highway (US)|Pacific Coast Highway]] running down the middle. Situated on the [[Pacific Ocean]], Hermosa's average temperature is 70 degrees in the summer and 55 degrees in the winter. Westerly [[sea]] breezes lessen what can be high summertime temperatures in [[Los Angeles]] and elsewhere in the county and help keep the [[smog]] away 360 days of the year.

A paved path, called [[The Strand (bicycle path)|The Strand]], runs along Hermosa's beach from Torrance Beach in the south approximately twenty miles north to [[Santa Monica, California|Santa Monica]] and the [[Hermosa Beach pier]] is at the end of Pier Avenue, which is one of the beach community's main and shopping, eating and partying areas.

== History ==
Hermosa Beach was originally part of the 1884 [[Rancho San Pedro]] [[Spain|Spanish]] land grant that later became the ten-mile (16&amp;nbsp;km) Ocean frontage of [[Rancho Sausal Redondo]]. In 1900 a tract of {{convert|1,500|acre|km2}} was purchased for $35 per acre from A. E. Pomroy, then owner of the greater part of Rancho Sausal Redondo. Messrs. Burbank and Baker, agents, bought this land for [[Moses Sherman|Sherman]] and Clark who organized and retained the controlling interest in the Hermosa Beach Land and Water Company,

In early days, Hermosa Beach — like so many of its neighboring cities ([[Inglewood, California|Inglewood]], [[Lawndale, California|Lawndale]], [[Torrance, California|Torrance]]) — was one vast sweep of rolling hills covered with [[field (agriculture)|fields]] of [[grain]], mostly [[barley]]. During certain seasons of the year large herds of [[sheep]] were grazed over this land, and corrals and large [[barn]]s for storing the grain, as well as providing shelter for [[horse]]s and farm implements were located on the [[ranch]] between Hermosa and Inglewood. The Spanish words ''Rancho Sausal Redondo'' mean a large circular ranch of [[pasture]] of [[grazing]] land, with a grove of [[willow]] on it.

[[Image:Hermosa beach pier statue.jpg|thumb|right|[[Tim Kelly (surfer)|Tim Kelly]] Lifeguard Memorial Statue at Hermosa Beach Pier &amp; Volleyball courts]]The first official survey was made in the year 1901 for the board walk on the Strand, Hermosa Avenue and Santa Fe Avenue; work on these projects commenced soon after. In 1904 the first pier was built. It was constructed entirely of wood even to the [[piling]]s and it extended five hundred feet out into the ocean. The pier was constructed by the Hermosa Beach Land and Water Company. In 1913 this old pier was partly washed away and later torn down and a new one built to replace it. This pier was built of [[concrete]] {{convert|1000|ft|m|-2}} long, and paved with [[asphalt]] its entire length. Small tiled pavilions were erected at intervals along the sides to afford shade for [[fishermen]] and [[picnic]] parties. A [[bait (luring substance)|bait]] stand was built eventually out on the end. Soon after, about 1914, an [[auditorium]] building was constructed; it has housed various enterprises and at present the public [[rest room]]s, the Los Angeles [[Life Guard]] Service, and the local branch of the [[Los Angeles County Public Library]] occupy rooms in the building. This pier is municipally owned.

The [[Santa Fe Railway]] was the only [[transportation]] system through Hermosa Beach. It was seven blocks from the beach. The street that led to the tracks was called Santa Fe Avenue, but was later renamed Pier Avenue. There was no [[railway station]] for Hermosa, but Burbank and Baker built a [[railway platform]] on the west side of the tracks near Santa Fe Avenue, and later the Railroad Company donated an old [[boxcar]] to be used as a storage place for freight. In 1926, the Santa Fe Company built a modern [[stucco]] depot and installed [[Western Union]] [[telegraph]] service in it.

The first city election for city officers was held December 24, 1906. On January 14, 1907, Hermosa Beach became the nineteenth incorporated city of Los Angeles County.

The name ''Hermosa'' comes from [[Spanish language|Spanish]] and means &quot;beautiful.&quot;

== Parks and recreation ==
The wide flat beach makes Hermosa Beach one of the most popular places to play beach volleyball, from professional to amateur.  Hermosa Beach is home to the [[Association of Volleyball Professionals|AVP]] Hermosa Beach Open tournament, and several amateur CBVA tournaments during the year. [[The Strand (bicycle path)|The Strand]] stretches north into [[Manhattan Beach, California|Manhattan Beach]] and south into [[Redondo Beach, California|Redondo Beach]] and is a popular place for walkers, joggers and biking. Of the three Beach Cities, only Hermosa Beach owns its own beach. The other two cities' beaches are owned by the county of [[Los Angeles]].

Running parallel to The Strand is a lovely linear trail known today as the Hermosa Valley Greenbelt.  Once part of a railroad easement, this narrow {{convert|24|acre|m2|adj=on}} strip had long been the subject of heated controversy and pressure from various commercial interests.  After years of litigation and wrangling, the city was poised to permit intensive retail and condominium development in the mid-1980s when a grassroots group spearheaded by activist Rosamond Fogg forced the matter to a vote.  The City Council at the time was divided over whether the matter was of much importance but after an energetic and passionate campaign, the citizens found that the greenbelt was a vital recreational resource and mandated its preservation for the use and enjoyment of residents and visitors.  This ballot initiative passed by almost 87%, the highest in California history.  {{Citation needed|date=July 2007}} The public also substantiated this effort by taxing themselves millions of dollars in order to purchase the lands.{{Citation needed|date=July 2007}}  As a result, the Hermosa Valley Greenbelt has the quality of a rural country lane, home to butterflies and many bird and animal species.  At any time of day or night joggers and walkers enjoy its soft woodchip trails and graceful landscaping.  The Greenbelt is also now part of the Federal [[Rails to Trails]] network.  RUDAT (an urban architectural planning group) found that Hermosa Beach, thanks in large part to the existence of the Greenbelt, was a &quot;world class pedestrian city&quot;.

The city also has eight other parks:
* Cypress Park, also known as Clark Field (9th Street &amp; Ardmore Avenue) - [[Baseball]]/[[Softball]] Diamond, [[Basketball]] and [[Tennis]] Courts
* South Park (Valley Drive &amp; 4th Street) - Children's play area, [[Roller Hockey]] Rink, Large open field for [[Soccer]] and [[American Football|Football]]
* Bi-Centennial Park (4th Street &amp; Ardmore)
* Fort Lots-o-Fun (6th Street  &amp; Prospect)
* Noble Park (The Strand &amp; 14th Street)
* Edith Rodaway Friendship Park (Prospect Avenue between Gentry &amp; Hollowell)
* Valley Park (Valley Drive &amp; Gould Avenue)
* Kay Etow Park (Herondo Street and Monterey Boulevard)

Other facilities:
* Skateboard Park - Pier Avenue and Ardmore Avenue
* [[Roller Hockey]] rink (South Park) - 4th and Valley Drive is frequently used for friendly pick-up games and league matches.
* [[Basketball]] (Cypress Park) - Two outdoor courts on 9th and Valley Drive
* [[Baseball]]/[[Softball]] (Cypress Park)- Lighted field with lights on 9th and Valley Drive behind the basketball and tennis courts
* [[Tennis]] - Lighted courts on 10th and Valley / Ardmore
* Skateboarding Park - Lighted park behind the Hermosa Beach Playhouse
* [http://www.hermosabch.org/about/history/lawnhist.html Lawn Bowling Club] is located next to Clark Building at 861 Valley Drive, Hermosa Beach. Open to the public and they furnish equipment and instruction to beginners.  The club was founded in 1936, when Mayor John Clark obtained the approval of the City Council to install a green at his own expense. In 1958, a clubhouse was donated and in 1963 a second green was laid. In the 1960s, over 150 bowlers could be seen all dressed in white. When membership waned, the second green was lost to the basketball court. The club is informal and seeks new members.

== Demographics ==
===2010===
The [[2010 United States Census]]&lt;ref&gt;{{USCensus-2010CA}}&lt;/ref&gt; reported that Hermosa Beach had a population of 19,506. The [[population density]] was 13,673.6 people per square mile (5,279.4/km²). The racial makeup of Hermosa Beach was 16,928 (86.8%) [[White (U.S. Census)|White]], 229 (1.2%) [[African American (U.S. Census)|African American]], 49 (0.3%) [[Native American (U.S. Census)|Native American]], 1,111 (5.7%) [[Asian (U.S. Census)|Asian]], 46 (0.2%) [[Pacific Islander (U.S. Census)|Pacific Islander]], 325 (1.7%) from [[Race (United States Census)|other races]], and 818 (4.2%) from two or more races.  [[Hispanic (U.S. Census)|Hispanic]] or [[Latino (U.S. Census)|Latino]] of any race were 1,632 persons (8.4%). 

The Census reported that 19,491 people (99.9% of the population) lived in households, 11 (0.1%) lived in non-institutionalized group quarters, and 4 (0%) were institutionalized.  

There were 9,550 households, out of which 1,878 (19.7%) had children under the age of 18 living in them, 3,254 (34.1%) were [[marriage|opposite-sex married couples]] living together, 460 (4.8%) had a female householder with no husband present, 325 (3.4%) had a male householder with no wife present.  There were 710 (7.4%) [[POSSLQ|unmarried opposite-sex partnerships]], and 64 (0.7%) [[same-sex partnerships|same-sex married couples or partnerships]]. 3,644 households (38.2%) were made up of individuals and 606 (6.3%) had someone living alone who was 65 years of age or older. The average household size was 2.04.  There were 4,039 [[family (U.S. Census)|families]] (42.3% of all households); the average family size was 2.80.

The population was spread out with 3,093 people (15.9%) under the age of 18, 1,242 people (6.4%) aged 18 to 24, 8,516 people (43.7%) aged 25 to 44, 4,898 people (25.1%) aged 45 to 64, and 1,757 people (9.0%) who were 65 years of age or older.  The median age was 37.0 years. For every 100 females there were 111.3 males.  For every 100 females age 18 and over, there were 112.1 males.

There were 10,162 housing units at an average density of 7,123.5 per square mile (2,750.4/km²), of which 4,255 (44.6%) were owner-occupied, and 5,295 (55.4%) were occupied by renters. The homeowner vacancy rate was 1.0%; the rental vacancy rate was 4.4%.  10,083 people (51.7% of the population) lived in owner-occupied housing units and 9,408 people (48.2%) lived in rental housing units.

===2000===
As of the [[census]]{{GR|2}} of 2000, there were 18,566 people, 9,476 households, and 3,553 families residing in the city.  The [[population density]] was 12,982.4 inhabitants per square mile (5,012.8/km²).  There were 9,840 housing units at an average density of 6,880.7 per square mile (2,656.8/km²).  The racial makeup of the city was 89.58% [[Race (United States Census)|White]], 0.80% [[Race (United States Census)|Black]] or [[Race (United States Census)|African American]], 0.40% [[Race (United States Census)|Native American]], 4.40% [[Race (United States Census)|Asian]], 0.22% [[Race (United States Census)|Pacific Islander]], 1.68% from [[Race (United States Census)|other races]], and 2.91% from two or more races.  4.82% of the population were [[Hispanics in the United States|Hispanic]] or [[Race (United States Census)|Latino]] of any race.

There were 9,476 households out of which 14.1% had children under the age of 18 living with them, 30.6% were [[Marriage|married couples]] living together, 4.5% had a female householder with no husband present, and 62.5% were non-families. 39.4% of all households were made up of individuals and 3.9% had someone living alone who was 65 years of age or older.  The average household size was 1.95 and the average family size was 2.65.

In the city the population was spread out with 12.0% under the age of 18, 6.1% from 18 to 24, 55.0% from 25 to 44, 20.1% from 45 to 64, and 6.8% who were 65 years of age or older.  The median age was 34 years. For every 100 females there were 112.9 males.  For every 100 females age 18 and over, there were 113.8 males.

The median income for a household in the city was $81,153, and the median income for a family was $104,645. Males had a median income of $67,407 versus $50,295 for females. The [[per capita income]] for the city was $54,244.  About 1.7% of families and 4.6% of the population were below the [[poverty line]], including 3.1% of those under age 18 and 3.0% of those age 65 or over.

There are eight hotels and one [[youth hostel]] in the city.

== Government ==
=== Local Government ===

According to the city’s most recent Comprehensive Annual Financial Report, the city’s various funds had $32.4 million in Revenues, $33.9 million in expenditures, $93.8 million in total assets, $12.2 million in total liabilities, and $23.0 million in cash and investments.&lt;ref name=&quot;City of Hermosa Beach CAFR&quot;&gt;[http://www.hermosabch.org/departments/finance/docs/CAFR2008_FINAL.pdf City of Hermosa Beach CAFR] Retrieved 2009-08-18&lt;/ref&gt;

The structure of the management and coordination of city services is:&lt;ref name=&quot;City of Hermosa Beach CAFR&quot;/&gt;

{| class=&quot;wikitable&quot; border=&quot;1&quot;
|-
! City Department
! Director
|-
|Administration
|(City Manager) Stephen Burrell
|-
|Finance
|Viki Copeland
|-
|Community Development
|Ken Robertson
|-
|Community Resources
| (open)
|-
|Personnel and Risk Manager
| (open)
|-
|Police Chief
|Gregory Savelli
|-
|Public Works
|Frank Senteno
|-
|Fire Chief
|David Lantzer
|}

The [[Beach Cities Health District]],&lt;ref&gt;[http://bchd.org Beach Cities Health District]&lt;/ref&gt; provides [[health]] and wellness services to the residents of Hermosa Beach, [[Manhattan Beach, California|Manhattan Beach]], and [[Redondo Beach, California|Redondo Beach]]. The voters of the three beach cities elect the 5-member [[Board of Directors]] to 4-year terms. One of 78 California Health Districts,&lt;ref&gt;[[List of California Health Districts]]&lt;/ref&gt; it was created in 1955 as South Bay Hospital and took on its current name in 1993.  Beach Cities Health District opened AdventurePlex,&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.adventureplex.org/ AdventurePlex]&lt;/ref&gt; a Manhattan Beach fitness center for kids and their families, in 2002.  Filled with [[mazes]], tunnels, outdoor [[rock climbing]] walls, complex [[ropes courses]], and an indoor [[gym]], AdventurePlex challenges children physically and intellectually in health-focused [[recreational activities]].

The [[United States Postal Service]] Hermosa Beach Post Office is located at 565 Pier Avenue.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;[http://usps.whitepages.com/service/post_office/61915?p=1&amp;s=CA&amp;service_name=post_office&amp;z=Hermosa+Beach Post Office Location - HERMOSA BEACH].&quot; ''[[United States Postal Service]]''. Retrieved on December 6, 2008.&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Politics ===
In the [[California State Legislature|state legislature]] Hermosa Beach is located in the 28th [[California State Senate|Senate]] District, represented by Democrat [[Ted Lieu]], and in the 53rd [[California State Assembly|Assembly]] District, represented by Democrat [[Betsy Butler]]. Federally, Hermosa Beach is located in [[California's 36th congressional district]], which has a [[Cook Partisan Voting Index|Cook PVI]] of D +11&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | title = Will Gerrymandered Districts Stem the Wave of Voter Unrest? | publisher = Campaign Legal Center Blog | url=http://www.clcblog.org/blog_item-85.html | accessdate = 2008-02-10}}&lt;/ref&gt; and is represented by Democrat [[Janice Hahn]].

In the [[2008 presidential election]], [[Barack Obama]] won 61% of the vote compared to 36% for [[John McCain]].&lt;ref&gt;http://www.lavote.net/VOTER/PDFS/STATEMENT_VOTES_CAST/11042008_COM.pdf&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Education ===
&lt;!-- Deleted image removed: [[Image:Hermosa elementary school.JPG|thumb|right|Hermosa Beach Elementary API Scores and Demographics|400px]] --&gt;

Hermosa Beach has its own elementary school and middle school but high school students are served by either [[Manhattan Beach, California|Manhattan Beach]] or [[Redondo Beach, California|Redondo Beach]] where rankings are in the 80 to 90th percentiles. Hermosa Beach residents are zoned to [[Hermosa Beach City School District]] for grades ([[Kindergarten]] through 8).

In 2005, Hermosa Valley and Hermosa View schools were honored as [[U.S. Department of Education]] National [[Blue Ribbon School]]s, along with 33 California schools and less than 300 schools across the nation. The award was based on academic achievement.  Hermosa schools are among the top 10% of schools in the state with students scoring at or above the 90% in the highest grade tested in reading and math.  For the award, the Department of Education reviewed growth in scores over a three-year period.

The district has two schools:
* [http://hbcsd.org/view/ Hermosa View Elementary] ([[Kindergarten]] to Grade 2)
* Hermosa Valley Elementary (Grades 3 through 8)
* [[Mira Costa High School]] of [[Manhattan Beach Unified School District]] or
* [[Redondo Union High School]] of the [[Redondo Beach Unified School District]] 

The [[Hermosa Beach City School District]] as a whole received a score of 915&lt;ref&gt;[http://api.cde.ca.gov/APIBase2006/2006Grth_Dst.aspx?cYear=2005-06&amp;allcds=1964600&amp;cChoice=2004BApiD http://api.cde.ca.gov/APIBase2006/2006Grth_Dst.aspx?cYear=2005-06&amp;allcds=1964600&amp;cChoice=2004BApiD] ''api.cde.ca.gov''&lt;/ref&gt; on the 2006 California [[Academic Performance Index]], neighboring [[Manhattan Beach Unified School District]] scored just below at 906&lt;ref&gt;[http://api.cde.ca.gov/APIBase2006/2006Grth_dst.aspx?cYear=&amp;allcds=1975333&amp;cChoice=2006GDst1 http://api.cde.ca.gov/APIBase2006/2006Grth_dst.aspx?cYear=&amp;allcds=1975333&amp;cChoice=2006GDst1] ''api.cde.gov''&lt;/ref&gt; making it one of California's best performing districts.  Each individual school also ranks at the top of its respective category.

{| class=&quot;wikitable&quot;
!- |School||2006 API Score
|-
|Hermosa View Elementary||950
|-
|Hermosa Valley Elementary||910
|-
|[[Mira Costa High School]]||852
|}

Hermosa Beach also has a [[private school]]:
* [[Our Lady of Guadalupe]], a [[Catholic school]] with classes up to the eighth grade. Although it is a religious school, there is no convent so most classes are taught by lay persons. Religious studies and services are provided by Franciscan friars and priests.

== Geography ==
[[Image:Hermosa beach plaza 100.jpg|thumb|right|200px|Pier Plaza in downtown Hermosa Beach]]

Hermosa Beach is located at {{Coord|33|51|59|N|118|23|59|W|type:city}} (33.866314, -118.399681).{{GR|1}}

According to the [[United States Census Bureau]], the city has a total area of {{convert|1.4|sqmi|km2}}, all of it land.

== Climate ==
{{climate chart
|Hermosa Beach, California
|49|66|2.98
|50|66|3.11
|51|65|2.40
|54|68|0.63
|57|69|0.24
|60|75|0.08
|63|77|0.03
|65|77|0.14
|64|74|0.26
|59|74|0.36
|53|70|1.13
|48|67|1.79
|source=Weather.com / NWS
|float=right
|clear=right
|units=imperial
}}
Average air temperature - (Summer 74 °F (23.3 °C)/ Winter, 55 °F (12.7 °C))

Average water temperature - 60 °F (15.5 °C) (Summer 68 °F (20 °C)/ Winter 50 °F (10 °C))

Hermosa Beach has an average of 325 days of sunshine a year.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.weatherbase.com/weather/weather.php3?s=159227&amp;refer=| title=Weatherbase: Historical Weather for Los Angeles, California, United States of America| publisher=Weatherbase.com| date=| accessdate=2009-08-13}}&lt;/ref&gt; Because of its location, nestled on a vast open bay ([[Santa Monica Bay]]), morning fog and haze is a common phenomenon in May, June and early July (caused by ocean temperature variations and currents). Locals have a particular terminology for this phenomenon: the &quot;May Gray&quot; and the &quot;[[June Gloom]]&quot;. Overcast skies are common for June mornings, but usually the strong sun burns the fog off by noon.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.santabarbara.com/community/weather/junegloom.asp| title = Santa Barbara.com: June Gloom| publisher=SantaBarbara.com| date=| accessdate=2009-08-13}}&lt;/ref&gt;  Nonetheless, it will sometimes stay cloudy and cool all day during June, even as other parts of the Los Angeles area will enjoy sunny skies and warmer temperatures. At times, the sun shines east of PCH, while the beach area is overcast.

As a general rule, the temperature is from 5 to 10 degrees Fahrenheit (3 to 5.5 degrees Celsius) cooler than it is inland. A typical spring day (mid-April) is sunny, pleasant and about 68 °F (20 °C). In the summer, which stretches basically from May to late October, temperatures can reach to the mid-80's Fahrenheit (about 30 °C) at the beach. In early November, it is about 68 °F (20 °C). In late January, temperatures are around 63 °F (17 °C). It is winter, however, when the hot, dry [[Santa Ana wind]]s are most common. In mid-December 2004, temperatures soared to 84 °F (28 °C) in Santa Monica, for a few straight days, with perfectly sunny skies.

The rainy season is from late October through late March. Winter storms usually approach from the northwest and pass quickly through the Southland. There is very little rain during the rest of the year.

Hermosa Beach usually enjoys a cool breeze blowing in from the ocean, keeping the air fresh and clean. Therefore, [[smog]] is less a problem for Hermosa Beach than elsewhere around Los Angeles.

== Economy ==

According to the City's 2009 Comprehensive Annual Financial Report,&lt;ref name=&quot;City of Hermosa Beach CAFR&quot;&gt;[http://www.hermosabch.org/departments/finance/docs/CAFR2009_FINAL.pdf City of Hermosa Beach CAFR]&lt;/ref&gt; the top employers in the city are:

{| class=&quot;wikitable&quot; border=&quot;1&quot;
|-
! #
! Employer
! # of Employees
! % of Total City Employment
|-
|1
|24 Hour Fitness 
|187
|4.64%
|-
|2
|City of Hermosa Beach
|183
|4.54%
|-
|3
|[[Vons]]
|131
|3.25%
|-
|4
|[[International Church of the Foursquare Gospel|Hope Chapel]] Shorewood Realtors, Incorporated
|92
|2.28%
|-
|5
|Shorewood Realtors
|87
|2.16%
|-
|6
|[[Ralphs]]
|64
|1.59%
|-
|7
|Hermosa Beach School District
|62
|1.54%
|-
|8
|Patrick Molloy's
|58
|1.44%
|-
|9
|Intensive Behavior Intervention
|55
|1.37%
|-
|10
|[[The Comedy &amp; Magic Club]]
|52
|1.29%
|}

=== Cost of living ===
[[Image:6th street and hermosa beach strand.JPG|thumb|right|6th and The Strand Hermosa Beach|175px]]

The beautiful beach lifestyle comes at a price: according to public data from the ''[[LA Times]]'', real estate prices increased almost 20% per year between 1999 and 2005.{{Citation needed|date=July 2007}} Properties within short walking distance of the ocean routinely sell for well over US$1.5 million. Those with direct, unhindered views routinely ask in excess of $2 million. ''[[Money Magazine]]'' ranks communities in the area as some of the most expensive places to live in America.  Homes located on The Strand frequently sell for $3–10 million.  The home pictured to the right sold in 2003 for $8,100,000.  The average 3-bed 2-bath home costs about $649 per square foot or $1,500,000 as of 2006.{{Citation needed|date=July 2007}}

West of PCH single homes mix with apartments, some have sunset views. East of PCH, the hills rise into upper middle class neighborhoods of tract homes with custom touches. Since the 1980s gentrification has set in, and many single-family dwellings and apartment buildings have been razed for condominiums. Multiple housing units dominate slightly over single family homes.

== Events ==
[[File:Hermosa Beach Pier Surfer Statue.jpg|thumb|Hermosa Beach Pier Surfer Statue|left]][[Image:Hermosa Beach sunset concert.JPG|thumb|right|Hermosa Beach Sunset Concert|175px]]
* [http://www.hermosabch.org/about/calendar HermosaBeach.org] City of Hermosa Beach Event Calendar
* [http://www.fiestahermosa.com Fiesta Hermosa] Arts and crafts festival which has taken place for the last 35 years every Memorial Day and Labor Day weekend
* [http://www.southbayevents.com SouthBayEvents.com] The locals' weekly entertainment and activities guide to Hermosa Beach.
* [http://www.lataco.com/taco/ironman-hermosa-beach Hermosa Ironman] Unofficial triathlon every July 4, consisting of running a mile in the sand, paddling a mile on a surfboard, and downing a 6-pack of beer. Then keeping it down for 20 minutes.
* [http://www.avp.com AVP Hermosa Beach Open]  Started in 1969 and typically in June. Attracts combinations of pros and near pros.  It's best to know a local to get in.
* [http://www.hermosashorts.com Hermosa Beach Film Festival] Started in 2005 and typically in August.  Short films from each year are chosen to be screened at the [http://www.hermosabeachplayhouse.com Hermosa Beach Playhouse]
* [http://www.surffestival.org International Surf Festival] Surfing, [[Paddleboarding]], Pier to Pier [[Swimming (sport)|Swim]] Events.  Beginning of August
* [http://www.hennesseyspaddleboarding.com/2007/hpf.php Hennessey's Paddle Board Festival] U.S. Paddleboard Championships. Typically in July.
* Hermosa Beach Sunset Concert free concert series from bands who perform on the beach. Starts July 31 - Aug. 21 (4 Weeks)
* [[Farmers' Market]] Every Friday from 12 noon to 4 pm, rain or shine. (Valley Drive between 8th and 10th Streets)
* Sand and Strand Run The second oldest standing run in the L.A. area. Unique is its course design, with 45% of the run on the Strand and 55% on the beach.  February during low tide.
* [[Shakespeare by the Sea, Los Angeles|Shakespeare by the Sea]]- the South Bay's ''free Shakespeare in the Park company''.  Performances run June through August in a variety of venues in Los Angeles and Orange County. [http://www.shakespearebythesea.org Shakespeare by the Sea]
* The [[Lighthouse Cafe]], a seminal [[West Coast jazz]] venue, is located in Hermosa Beach.

== Notable residents ==
* [[Lauren Mayhew]]: Superstar
* [[Adrianne Curry]]: First winner of'' America's Next Top Model'' who appeared on ''[[My Fair Brady]]'', ''[[The Surreal Life]]'', and was featured on the cover of ''Playboy'' twice
* [[Christopher Knight (actor)|Christopher Knight]]: Actor, [[The Brady Bunch]], [[The Surreal Life]], and [[My Fair Brady]]
* [[A. J. Cook (actress)|A. J. Cook]] - actress on [[Criminal Minds]]
* [[Bill Butler (cinematographer)|Bill Butler]] - cinematographer
* [[Bill Simpson]] - racecar driver (retired)
* [[Brent Barry]] - professional [[NBA]] basketball player
* [[Carson Daly]] - television personality
* [[Daniel Tosh]] - comedian
* [[Descendents]] - punk band
* [[Dylan O'Brien]] - actor; Stiles on [[Teen Wolf (2011 TV series)]]
* [[Eric Fonoimoana]] - professional [[Association of Volleyball Professionals|AVP]] volleyball player
* [[Jack Black]] - actor who grew up in Hermosa
* [[Jacqueline Frank DeLuca]] - water polo goalie; [[Water polo at the 2004 Summer Olympics|bronze medalist, 2004 Summer Olympics]]
* [[Jason Acuna]] - ''[[Jackass (TV series)|Jackass]]'' personality, actor and professional skateboarder
* [[Jim Finn]] - professional [[NFL]] football player
* [[Jimmy Kimmel]] - television host  [[Jimmy Kimmel Live!]] and comedian
* [[Kerri Walsh]] - [[Gold medalist]] and professional [[Association of Volleyball Professionals|AVP]] volleyball player
* [[Kyle Harrison]] - professional [[lacrosse]] player and 2005 [[Tewaaraton Trophy]] winner
* [[LeRoy Grannis]] co-founder of Surfing magazine. Legendary surf photographer
* [[Leonard  Wibberley]] - Author of ''The Mouse that Roared''
* [[Ozzie Nelson|Ozzie]] and [[Harriet Nelson]]- Actors on the [[The Adventures of Ozzie and Harriet]] 
* [[Pennywise (band)|Pennywise]] - punk band 
* [[Rachel Hunter]] and LA Kings [[Jarret Stoll]]&lt;ref&gt;http://www.bergproperties.com/blog/rachel-hunter-and-jarrett-stoll-pay-3645m-for-a-house-in-hermosa-beach-ca/1964/celebrities &quot;Rachel Hunter and Jarret Stoll pay $3.645M for a house in Hermosa Beach, CA&quot;, September 21, 2007&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news| url=http://www.dailymail.co.uk/tvshowbiz/article-1043224/After-Hot-Legs-Rod-Rachel-looks-set-marry-younger-ice-man.html | location=London | work=Daily Mail | title=After 'Hot Legs' Rod, Rachel looks set to marry her much younger ice man | date=2008-08-10}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[Mae Marsh]] - former actress
* [[Michael Strahan]] - professional [[NFL]] football player
* [[Misty May-Treanor]] - [[Gold medalist]] and professional [[Association of Volleyball Professionals|AVP]] volleyball player
* [[Morgan Ensberg]]- professional [[Major League Baseball|MLB]] baseball player
* [[Raymond Pettibon]]- Contemporary American artist largely associated with the LA Punk scene; notably Black Flag.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.pbs.org/art21/artists/pettibon/index.html&lt;/ref&gt; Also the brother of Greg Ginn of Black Flag.
* [[Rodney Mullen]] - professional skateboarder
* [[Ryan Starr]] - On [[American Idol]]
* [[Steve Lyons (baseball)|Steve Lyons]] - former professional [[Major League Baseball|MLB]] baseball player, [[Fox Broadcasting Company|Fox]] sportcaster and current [[Dodgers]] broadcast team
* [[Ted Coombs]] - Author of &quot;For Dummies&quot; computer books series
* [[Ty Page]] - Professional skateboarder
* [[Peter Revson]] - race car driver
* [[Kim Lyons]] - personal trainer on [[The Biggest Loser]] and [[Dr. Phil (TV series)|Dr. Phil]]
* [[Teri Polo]] - Actress &quot;Meet the Fockers&quot;, &quot;Meet the Parents&quot;
* [[Warren Miller (director)|Warren Miller]] - Warren Miller Films made over 50 feature length documentary films on extreme sports

== Media ==
In addition to the ''[[Los Angeles Times]]'', Hermosa Beach is served by local daily the ''[[Daily Breeze]]'' and local weeklies the ''[[Beach Reporter]]'' and the ''[[Easy Reader]]''. One of the main online references for locals and visitors is the online home of the venerable [[Easy Reader]] at [http://www.easyreadernews.com EasyReaderNews.com] and [http://www.SouthBayEvents.com SouthBayEvents.com], which offers a weekly entertainment guide, as well as a full local business listing. The TV show ''[[Summerland (TV series)|Summerland]]'' was partly filmed here.

== Trivia ==

Segments of the [[television show]] ''[[The O.C.]]'' were filmed in Hermosa Beach (and more in neighboring Redondo Beach), not [[Newport Beach, California|Newport Beach]].  This was necessary because of [[trade union|union]] rules that make it expensive to film outside of Los Angeles County.&lt;ref name=&quot;OC&quot;&gt;[http://www.seeing-stars.com/OC/ByLocation.shtml The O.C. Filming Locations]&lt;/ref&gt;

In the late 1970s the [[hardcore punk]] band [[Black Flag (band)|Black Flag]] emerged from Hermosa Beach, and played their first show at Valley Park. The infamous &quot;church&quot; profiled in ''[[The Decline of Western Civilization]]'' was on Pier Avenue, though it has since been torn down.

The [[melodic hardcore]] band [[Descendents]] also appered in Hermosa Beach in 1978. It paved the way to two other well known punk bands, the [[Circle Jerks]] in 1979 and [[Pennywise (band)|Pennywise]] in 1988.

An episode of [[Gilmore Girls]] (Season 4, Episode 17: Girls in Bikinis, Boys Doin' the Twist) was filmed at the Sea Sprite Inn where Rory went to &quot;Florida&quot; for spring break.

Hermosa Beach has been the sister city of [[Loreto, Baja California Sur]], since 1967.

In the film &quot;[[Jackie Brown]]&quot; by [[Quentin Tarantino]] the arms dealer Ordell Robbie, played by [[Samuel Jackson]], kept his mistress Melanie, played by [[Bridget Fonda]], in a beachfront condo in Hermosa Beach.

== Gallery ==
{{cleanup-gallery}}
&lt;gallery&gt;
Image:Hermosa beach summer sunset surf.jpg|Hermosa Beach Pier sunset wave looking north
Image:Hermosabeachpier.jpg|The municipal pier in downtown Hermosa Beach
Image:Hermosa_beach_chip_trail.jpg|4 mile chip running trail running through Hermosa &amp; Manhattan Beach
Image:Hermosa_beach_in_winter.jpg|Looking North from the Hermosa Pier
Image:Hermosa beach in winter looking south.jpg|Looking South from the Hermosa Pier
Image:Hermosa_Beach_Strand.JPG|Looking North up The Strand from South Hermosa
&lt;/gallery&gt;

==References==
{{Reflist}}

==External links==
{{Portal|Los Angeles|Greater Los Angeles|Southern California}}
* [http://www.hermosabch.org/ Official website]
* [http://www.hbchamber.net/ Hermosa Beach Chamber of Commerce]
* [http://www.hermosabeachhistoricalsociety.org/ Hermosa Beach Historical Society website]
* {{dmoz|Regional/North_America/United_States/California/Localities/H/Hermosa_Beach}}

{{Cities of Los Angeles County, California}}
{{Greater Los Angeles Area}}

[[Category:Beaches of Southern California]]
[[Category:Cities in Los Angeles County, California]]
[[Category:Populated coastal places in California]]
[[Category:Surfing locations in California]]
[[Category:Incorporated cities and towns in California]]
[[Category:Populated places established in 1907]]

[[ar:هيرموسا بيتش، لوس أنجليس، كاليفورنيا]]
[[bg:Хермоса Бийч (Калифорния)]]
[[ca:Hermosa Beach]]
[[cs:Hermosa Beach]]
[[de:Hermosa Beach]]
[[es:Hermosa Beach]]
[[fr:Hermosa Beach]]
[[id:Hermosa Beach, California]]
[[it:Hermosa Beach]]
[[sw:Hermosa Beach, California]]
[[ht:Hermosa Beach, Kalifòni]]
[[nl:Hermosa Beach]]
[[no:Hermosa Beach]]
[[pt:Hermosa Beach]]
[[sv:Hermosa Beach]]
[[tl:Hermosa Beach, California]]
[[vo:Hermosa Beach]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
