<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="107681" ns="0" title="Sierra Madre, California"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Infobox settlement
|official_name            = City of Sierra Madre
|other_name               =
|native_name              = &lt;!-- for cities whose native name is not in English --&gt;
|nickname                 =
|motto                    =
|image_skyline            =
|imagesize                =
|image_caption            =
|image_flag               =
|flag_size                =
&lt;!--  Commented out because image was deleted: |image_seal               = Seal_sierra_madre.png --&gt;
|seal_size                = 100
|image_shield             =
|shield_size              =
|image_blank_emblem       =
|blank_emblem_size        =
|image_map                = LA County Incorporated Areas Sierra Madre highlighted.svg
|mapsize                  = 250x200px
|map_caption              = Location of Sierra Madre in [[Los Angeles County, California|Los Angeles County]], [[California]]
|image_map1               =
|mapsize1                 =
|map_caption1             =
|subdivision_type         = [[List of countries|Country]]
|subdivision_name         = [[United States]]
|subdivision_type1        = [[Political divisions of the United States|State]]
|subdivision_name1        = [[California]]
|subdivision_type2        = [[List of counties in California|County]]
|subdivision_name2        = [[Los Angeles County, California|Los Angeles]]
|subdivision_type3        =
|subdivision_name3        =
|subdivision_type4        =
|subdivision_name4        =
|government_type          =
|leader_title             =
|leader_name              =
|leader_title1            = &lt;!-- for places with, say, both a mayor and a city manager --&gt;
|leader_name1             =
|leader_title2            =
|leader_name2             =
|leader_title3            =
|leader_name3             =
|established_title        = &lt;!-- Settled --&gt;
|established_date         =
|established_title2       = &lt;!-- Incorporated (town) --&gt;
|established_date2        =
|established_title3       = Incorporated (city)
|established_date3        = 1907-02-02&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url = http://www.cacities.org/resource_files/20457.IncorpDateLO.doc |  title = Incorporation Dates of California Cities | accessdate = 2007-01-18}}&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;!-- Area------------------&gt;
|area_magnitude           =
| unit_pref               =US
| area_footnotes          = &lt;ref&gt;[http://www.census.gov/geo/www/gazetteer/files/Gaz_places_national.txt U.S. Census]&lt;/ref&gt;
| area_total_sq_mi        = 2.957
| area_land_sq_mi         = 2.953
| area_water_sq_mi        = 0.004
| area_total_km2          = 7.659
| area_land_km2           = 7.647
| area_water_km2          = 0.012
| area_water_percent      = 0.15
| area_note               = 
|area_urban_km2           =
|area_urban_sq_mi         =
|area_metro_km2           =
|area_metro_sq_mi         =
|population_as_of         = 2010
|population_note          =
|population_footnotes     = 
|settlement_type          = [[City]]
|population_total         = 10917
|population_density_km2   = auto
|population_density_sq_mi = auto
|population_metro         =
|population_density_metro_km2     =
|population_density_metro_sq_mi   =
|population_urban                 =
|population_density_urban_km2     =
|population_density_urban_sq_mi   =
|timezone                 = [[Pacific Time Zone|PST]]
|utc_offset               = -8
|timezone_DST             = PDT
|utc_offset_DST           = -7
|coordinates_display      = inline,title
|coordinates_type         = region:US_type:city
|latd = 34 |latm = 9 |lats = 53 |latNS = N
|longd = 118 |longm = 3 |longs = 3 |longEW = W
|elevation_m              = 252
|elevation_ft             = 827
|postal_code_type         = [[ZIP Code]]
|postal_code              = 91024, 91025&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url = http://zip4.usps.com/zip4/zcl_1_results.jsp?visited=1&amp;pagenumber=0&amp;state=ca&amp;city=Sierra%20Madre | title = USPS - ZIP Code Lookup - Find a ZIP+ 4 Code By City Results | accessdate = 2007-01-18}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|area_code                = [[Area code 626|626]]
|website                  = [http://www.cityofsierramadre.com/ cityofsierramadre.com/]
|blank_name               = [[Federal Information Processing Standard|FIPS code]]
|blank_info               = 06-71806
|blank1_name              = [[Geographic Names Information System|GNIS]] feature ID
|blank1_info              = 1661439
|footnotes                =
}}
&lt;!-- Infobox ends --&gt;

The city of '''Sierra Madre''' is a municipality in [[Los Angeles County, California]] whose population was 10,917 at the 2010 census, up from 10,580 at the time of the 2000 census. The city is located in the [[Foothills of California|Foothills]] of the [[San Gabriel Mountains]] below the southern edge of the [[Angeles National Forest]].  [[Pasadena, California|Pasadena]] and [[Altadena, California|Altadena]] are to its west, with [[Arcadia, California|Arcadia]] to its south and east.  Sierra Madre is known as &quot;Wistaria City&quot;, and its city seal is decorated with a drawing of the now widely known {{convert|500|ft|m|adj=on}} vine.&lt;ref name=&quot;Times1&quot;&gt;{{cite news| url=http://articles.latimes.com/1990-01-25/news/ga-767_1_sierra-madre | work=Los Angeles Times | title=Sierra Madre : Wisteria Vine Event Set - Los Angeles Times | date=January 25, 1990}}&lt;/ref&gt; It is also called the &quot;Village of the Foothills&quot; and was an [[All-America City Award|All-America City]] in 2007.&lt;ref name=&quot;city&quot;&gt;[http://cityofsierramadre.com/ The Official Site of the City of Sierra Madre:&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;

==History==
===Early history===	
In approximately 500 A.D., [[Tongva people|Tongva Indians]],&lt;ref&gt;[http://tongva.com/ Gabrieleno/Tongva of San Gabriel&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt; the aborigines migrated from the [[Mojave, California|Mojave]] area to what would become the [[Los Angeles County]], (including the [[San Gabriel Valley]]). Their name means &quot;People of the Earth&quot;. Their primary  language was  Uto-Aztecan Shoshonean, exemplifying their roots in the [[Aztec]] empire. In the 16th century there were about 25 Tongva villages, with  population of approximately 400 native people.&lt;ref name=&quot;history&quot;&gt;[http://cityofsierramadre.com/departments/library/106-headline-history-of-sierra-madre City of Sierra Madre: Headline History]&lt;/ref&gt; By 1769, the first Spanish settlers arrived in the region, finding an estimated 5,000 Tongva living in 31 villages. Two years later, [[Mission San Gabriel Arcangel]] was founded in today's [[Montebello, California|Montebello]], causing the Tongva communities to rapidly dwindle. The mission was later moved to [[San Gabriel, California|San Gabriel]] because of severe flooding from the [[Rio Hondo (California)|Rio Hondo]] River, which ruined their crops. The original mission site is now marked by a [[California Historical Landmark]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | title =Los Angeles | work =California Historical Landmarks  | publisher =California Department of Parks &amp; Recreation Office of Historic Preservation | year =2004 | url =http://ohp.parks.ca.gov/default.asp?page_id=21427 | accessdate =2007-07-30}}&lt;/ref&gt; Tongvas were integrated into the culture of the mission, and the tribe were renamed [[Gabrielino Indians]] by the Spaniards.&lt;ref name=&quot;history&quot;/&gt; The first Mount Wilson trail was carved by the Gabrielino Indians which was used by them when they carried timber down from the mountains for  the construction of the San Gabriel Mission in 1771.&lt;ref name=&quot;race&quot;&gt;[http://www.sierramadrenews.net/trail.htm#history Mt. Wilson Trail Race&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;
 
Using Mexican and Chinese laborers, [[Benjamin Davis Wilson|Benjamin &quot;Don Benito&quot; Wilson]] expanded the [[Mount Wilson (California)|Mount Wilson]] Trail in 1864.&lt;ref name=&quot;race&quot;/&gt; Nathaniel Carter purchased the original {{convert|1103|acre|km2}} that comprise Sierra Madre in 1881: {{convert|845|acre|km2}} from &quot;[[Lucky Baldwin]]&quot;, {{convert|108|acre|km2}} from the Southern Pacific Railroad Company; and {{convert|150|acre|km2}} from Levi Richardson.  In 1888, The Santa Anita railroad station was built.&lt;ref name=&quot;history&quot;/&gt;  The first of the year brought Pacific Electric Railway Red Car passenger service to Sierra Madre. Later that year the first electric lights were installed by the Edison Electric Company. In December 1906, the first telephones were installed, 250 of them, by the Home Telephone Company of Monrovia.&lt;ref name=&quot;history&quot;/&gt; On February 2, 1907, the first citywide election was held and 96 citizens voted 71-25 to officially incorporate Sierra Madre, the population was about 500. Eighteen days later, Sierra Madre became incorporated as a California city. Charles Worthington Jones served as the first mayor.&lt;ref name=&quot;history&quot;/&gt;
[[Image:SierraMadreVillaHotel-1884.jpg|thumb|left|250px|The Sierra Madre Villa Hotel, 1884.]]

===The new century===	
Sierra Madre is historically linked to the old mountain resorts of the San Gabriel Mountains and Valley.  The Sierra Madre Villa Hotel was a pioneer of summer resorts that populated the [[San Gabriel Valley]] in the late-19th century.&lt;ref name = &quot;headline_history&quot;&gt;[http://cityofsierramadre.com/index.php?mod=headline_history The Official Site of the City of Sierra Madre: Headline History of Sierra Madre&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt; The municipality also operated and maintained the landmark &quot;Lizzie's Trail&quot; inn at the head of Old Mount Wilson Trail.&lt;ref name = &quot;headline_history&quot;/&gt;

[[Harvard College]] established the first [[Mount Wilson Observatory]] in 1889.&lt;ref name=&quot;history&quot;/&gt; The installation of the Harvard telescope in 1889, which brought its own problems of transporting the instrument up the old Wilson trail, caused an interest in a Mt. Wilson roadway, something more than a trail.  The Harvard telescope was removed and in July the new toll road was officially opened to the public.  The toll was set by the Los Angeles County Board of Supervisors at 25 cents for hikers and 50 cents for horseback. The new road was called the &quot;New Mt. Wilson Trail&quot; and it was more popular at the time than the old Sierra Madre trail. Foot and pack animal traffic became so heavy that in June 1893 the trail was widened to six feet. The Pacific Electric &quot;Red Cars&quot; established their route to Sierra Madre from 1906 until 1950. Literally thousands of people rode the cars to Sierra Madre to hike the original Mt. Wilson Trail.&lt;ref name=&quot;race&quot;/&gt;
[[Image:Mt Wilson trl.jpg|thumb|right|Horse and buggy passage on the Mount Wilson Trail.]]	

In 1908, the first Mt. Wilson Trail Race was run. This popular annual event race was discontinued during WWII and reestablished in 1966.&lt;ref name=&quot;history&quot;/&gt; The 102nd anniversary of the first running of the Mount Wilson Trail Race was also The 44th annual running of the race, was run in May 2010.  Because with rain, mudslides, falling trees and rockslides, the regularly monitored trail course changes almost every year, due to soil erosion and wear and tear, no official records are kept of running times are kept.&lt;ref name=autogenerated1&gt;[http://www.sierramadrenews.net/trail.htm Mt. Wilson Trail Race&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;  The {{convert|8.6|mi|km|adj=on}} course, starts and ends on pavement, the majority of the race is run on a  dirt path about three foot wide and the Mt. Wilson Trail has occasionally steep vertical drops of hundreds of feet.  Due to the narrow and steep qualities of the trail, the race is limited to 300 male and female runners.&lt;ref name=&quot;race&quot;/&gt; The path  gains elevation  to more than {{convert|2100|ft|m}} and, at {{convert|4.3|mi|km}} from the start of the race, is Orchard Camp, the turnaround point.  Scout troops hike up to provide water at two locations, the {{convert|2.3|mi|km|adj=on}} point and at the Orchard Camp turnaround. The Sierra Madre Search and Rescue Team provides emergency support on race day. The special feature of the Mt. Wilson Trail Race, is its traditional and historical value to the community.&lt;ref name=&quot;race&quot;/&gt;
	
A year after the city's incorporation, Roman Catholic families contacted a priest from Chicago, Fr. M. W. Barth, who had moved west for his health, to ask if he could celebrate Mass for them.&lt;ref name=&quot;Rita&quot;&gt;[http://st-rita.org/about-st-rita/parish-history Parish History&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt; The construction of the first very small church of St. Rita's parish, founded by Father Barth in 1908, was completed in 1910.&lt;ref name=&quot;history&quot;/&gt;  In 1922, St. Rita's Catholic Church parochial school opened.  During the first 100 years of St. Rita Parish, it has on record: 4,075 Baptisms, 3,590 Confirmations, 1,334 Marriages and 1,469 funerals.&lt;ref&gt;http://st-rita.org/about-st-rita/parish-history&lt;/ref&gt; The scattering of families that began with Fr. Barth in 1908, has grown to more than 1,200 Catholic parish homes today,&lt;ref name=&quot;Rita&quot;/&gt; in a city whose entire population is now approximately 10,580 people.

In 1914, after a long legal battle, the city acquired title to all water rights, lands, and distributing systems of the Baldwin Estate and the Sierra Madre Water Company.&lt;ref name=&quot;history&quot;/&gt;

====1920s and 1930s====
In 1921, a disastrous bakery fire at Windsor Lane and Montecito Court, prompted the official organization of the Sierra Madre Volunteer Fire Department. The town is still home to the only remaining [[volunteer fire department]] in [[Greater Los Angeles area|greater Los Angeles]] today.&lt;ref name=&quot;history&quot;/&gt;

On January 1, 1922, Bethany Temple was dedicated, the now historical domed cobblestone church was designed and built by the nearly-blind Louis D. Corneulle. The new Congregational Church structure was completed on Sierra Madre Ave; the Romanesque Revival building was designed by Marsh, Smith, &amp; Powell.  On April 21, 1931, the first meeting of the Sierra Madre Historical Society took place, in conjunction with the city's fiftieth anniversary celebration.&lt;ref name=&quot;history&quot;/&gt; In 1936, a city ordinance officially changed the name of Central Avenue to Sierra Madre Blvd.&lt;ref name=&quot;history&quot;/&gt;  In March 1938, a disastrous storm and the resulting flood destroyed many resorts in the local mountains, also ravaged the (John) Muir Lodge in Big [[Santa Anita Canyon]] above Sierra Madre. No trace remains of it today.&lt;ref&gt;http://angeles.sierraclub.org/about/MuirLodge.asp&lt;/ref&gt;  In 1939 the city purchased {{convert|760|acre|km2}} of land in San Gabriel Mountains near Orchard Camp to avoid contamination of water supply.&lt;ref name=&quot;history&quot;/&gt;
	
A six week Wistaria event took place in the 1930s. The crowds that traveled to see the giant Wisteria vine were estimated at over 100,000. With so many visitors, Extra &quot;Red Cars&quot; were put on the Pacific Electric route to Sierra Madre.&lt;ref name=autogenerated2&gt;[http://www.sierramadrenews.net/wistaria.htm Sierra Madre Wistaria Festival&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;

====1940s====	
[[Image:Arrivals.gif|left|thumb|300px|Japanese Americans arrive at the Internment Camp.]]
 	
On May 14, 1942, The whole of Sierra Madre's Japanese population, including U.S. citizens, was required to depart for the assembly center in Tulare, California. During the decade, Sierra Madre Civic Club and the Sierra Madre Lion's Club are organized. The Sierra Madre Community Nursery School also opened. In May 1947 the first Pioneer Days Parade was held. The heaviest recorded snow falls on Sierra Madre in 1949, blanketing the town with 3-4&amp;nbsp;inches of snow overnight.&lt;ref name=&quot;history&quot;/&gt;

====Mid-century====
On October 6, 1950, the last Pacific Electric train left from Sierra Madre.&lt;ref name=&quot;history&quot;/&gt;  In 1951, Sierra Madre Search and Rescue Team was established by Larry Shepherd and Fred LaLone.&lt;ref name=&quot;history&quot;/&gt;  Sierra Madre joined the [[Pasadena Unified School District]] In 1961.&lt;ref name=&quot;history&quot;/&gt;  In 1967, Britains's Princess Margaret visited the British Home in Sierra Madre.&lt;ref name=&quot;history&quot;/&gt; The Cultural Heritage Committee was established in 1969 by the Sierra Madre City Council with the intent of &quot;defining cultural and aesthetic landmarks throughout the City of Sierra Madre and to recommend how such landmarks be preserved.&quot;  In 1969, the city purchased the Woman's Clubhouse to be demolished and become the site of a new City Hall building.&lt;ref name=&quot;history&quot;/&gt;
 	
Predominately through the efforts of a few dedicated  Sierra Madre residents, the Sierra Madre Historical Wilderness Area was established by declaration of the City Council on January 24, 1967. When it was dedicated on January 27, 1968, Sierra Madre was the first city in [[Southern California]] to own a wilderness preserve.&lt;ref name=&quot;race&quot;/&gt; The Sierra Madre City Council added the Mt. Wilson Trail to the Sierra Madre Register of Historic Cultural Landmarks, on October 12, 1993,.&lt;ref name=&quot;race&quot;/&gt;

====1970s====	
In January 1971, the Sierra Madre Environmental Action Council was formed. In 1974, the Bell Tower in Kersting Court was dedicated; this bell tower houses the original school bell from the 1885 schoolhouse. In 1976 the &quot;Sierra Madre Vistas&quot; was published by the Sierra Madre Historical Preservation Society.	On March 19, 1976, the Bicentennial time capsule was buried beneath flagpole at the new Fire and Police Department Facility, and dedicated in May. The New City Hall building was dedicated on Sierra Madre Boulevard in 1977&lt;ref name=&quot;history&quot;/&gt;
 	
====1980s and 1990s====	
In 1981, Sierra Madre celebrated the centennial of its founding, complete with a Centennial Royal Court and dance, a special Historical Society dinner, and rides on a Pacific Electric red car brought back to town Independence Day weekend.&lt;ref name=&quot;history&quot;/&gt;  On February 28, 1983, Queen Elizabeth visited the British Home and greeted each and every resident of the small town. In April 1999, &quot;The Weeping Wall Veterans' Memorial&quot;, designed by Lew Watanabe, is dedicated in Memorial Park.&lt;ref name=&quot;history&quot;/&gt;

====Recent history====
The groundbreaking ceremony for the Senior Housing Project on Esperanza Avenue was held, the affordable housing project includes 46 units designed by PBWS Architects and developed by the Foundation for Quality Housing in 2003. Later that year the Veterans' Photo Wall, spearheaded by John Grijalva, is dedicated in Memorial Park. In 2007, Sierra Madre celebrated the centennial of its incorporation as a Californian city. Sierra Madre also won the [[All-America City Award]], the prestigious award is given by the [[National Civic League]]. That same year, the refurbished World War I cannon in Memorial Park was dedicated.&lt;ref name=&quot;history&quot;/&gt;
 	
In March 2008, Goldberg Park was dedicated. It is the city's first new park in over thirty years. In 2009, the Sierra Madre Historical Preservation Society published &quot;Southern California Story: Seeking the Better Life in Sierra Madre&quot;, by Michele Zack.&lt;ref name=&quot;history&quot;/&gt; In the northern and northeastern portions of the city are the Lower and Upper Sierra Madre Canyons. These small communities are noted for their narrow and winding roads, lush vegetation, views of the [[San Gabriel Valley]], and small bungalows or cabins.

==Government and infrastructure==
In the [[California State Legislature|state legislature]] Sierra Madre is located in the 29th [[California State Senate|Senate]] District, represented by Republican [[Bob Huff]], and in the 59th [[California State Assembly|Assembly]] District, represented by Republican [[Anthony Adams (politician)|Anthony Adams]]. Federally, Sierra Madre is located in [[California's 26th congressional district]], which has a [[Cook Partisan Voting Index|Cook PVI]] of R +4&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | title = Will Gerrymandered Districts Stem the Wave of Voter Unrest? | publisher = Campaign Legal Center Blog | url=http://www.clcblog.org/blog_item-85.html | accessdate = 2008-02-10}}&lt;/ref&gt; and is represented by Republican [[David Dreier]].

===County===

The [[Los Angeles County Department of Health Services]] operates the Monrovia Health Center in [[Monrovia, California|Monrovia]], serving Sierra Madre.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;[http://publichealth.lacounty.gov/phn/docs/HealthCenter/monrovia.pdf LA County Department of Health Services Monrovia Health Center]. Retrieved on March 27, 2010.&lt;/ref&gt;
[[Image:210Freeway.JPG|thumb|right|250px|[[Interstate 210 and State Route 210 (California)|Foothill Freeway (I-210)]] as seen from the Metro Gold Line [[Sierra Madre Villa (LACMTA station)|Sierra Madre Villa Station]]]]

===City services===
The town is also home to the only remaining [[volunteer fire department]] in the [[Greater Los Angeles area|Greater Los Angeles]] area and has no traffic signals within its town limits.&lt;ref name=&quot;history&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://abclocal.go.com/kabc/story?section=seenon&amp;id=4385517 abc7.com: On The Road With Garth Kemp: Sierra Madre 7/27/06&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt; In 1928,  Gordon MacMillan was inaugurated as first Chief of Police, the beginning of the city's police system as we know it today.  With the appointment of former [[Pasadena Police Department]] Cmdr. Marilyn Diaz as Police Chief on March 14, 2006, the Sierra Madre Police Department became the first municipal police department in [[Los Angeles County]] to have a female Chief.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.cityofsierramadre.com/index.php?mod=city_article&amp;id=34 The Official Site of the City of Sierra Madre: City of Sierra Madre&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt; As reported by KCAL television in 2006, there were 17 sworn members of the Sierra Madre Police Department.

A plaque honoring our fallen firefighters from 9/11, was installed in front of the fire station in October 2001.
In July 2003, the MTA begins operation of the Gold line from Union Station to Sierra Madre Villa. Sierra Madre expanded local transit service as part of the new operation.  In March 2005, Marilyn Diaz was named Sierra Madre Chief of Police, the first female police chief in Los Angeles County.

In June 2007, the Paramedic  was  begun. It was funded by the sale of an unused fire station in the canyon. Sierra Madre is the last city in Los Angeles County to provide paramedic service to its residents.&lt;ref name=&quot;history&quot;/.

Sierra Madre is considering contracting out law enforcement and paramedic services. The City Council authorized a formal request to Arcadia, Pasadena, and LA County on Tuesday July 14 at the City Council meeting.
&lt;ref&gt;[http://sierramadreweekly.com/featured/city-council-might-contract-out-public-safety-services/ City Council Might Contract Out Public Safety Services | Sierra Madre Weekly&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;

====City Council====
The Sierra Madre City Council has five members elected to four-year terms. The Council is responsible for general city policy, as well as for the appointment of the City Manager, City Attorney, and members of the city's boards and commissions. It also serves as the governing body for the Community Redevelopment Agency and Public Financing Authority.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.cityofsierramadre.com/index.php?mod=city_council The Official Site of the City of Sierra Madre: City Council&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;

;City Council members
*John Buchanan, Mayor
*Josh Moran, Mayor Pro Tem
*MaryAnn MacGillivray, Council Member
*Joseph M. Mosca, Council Member
*Nancy Walsh, Council Member

==Unique culture==
Downtown Sierra Madre has small restaurants and shops. There is also a historic company that makes gourmet and specialty olives, jams, jellies, and syrups (sold to the public) from its own citrus groves.  The company, E. Waldo Ward and Son, was founded over 120 years ago, when most of Sierra Madre was mainly agricultural in its zoning; the first [[Sevilla orange]] trees in the U.S. were planted on the grounds (now, due to re-zoning, the original trees are on private property, however the Ward family still owns {{convert|3|acre|m2}} of oranges at 273 East Highland Avenue as well as having a barn.)

Sierra Madre hosts a locally famous [[Independence Day (United States)|Independence Day]] parade and three days of festivities each year. The date of the parade varies from year to year, dependent on when the Monday of the holiday weekend falls. Residents like to call it a &quot;Star Spangled Weekend.&quot; The old tradition of water-filled squirt guns during the parade has been scrapped for &quot;confetti eggs&quot; to throw at parade participants and viewers. Concerts, food and game booths and the ubiquitous Beer booth are all a part of the firework-free weekend.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.cityofsierramadre.com/index.php?mod=news_detail&amp;id=534 The Official Site of the City of Sierra Madre: News from the City of Sierra Madre&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;

In the northern and northeastern portions of the city are the Lower and Upper Sierra Madre Canyons.  These small communities are noted for their narrow and winding roads, lush vegetation, views of the [[San Gabriel Valley]], and small bungalows or cabins.&lt;ref name=&quot;history&quot;/&gt;  Bailey Canyon Wilderness Park has these resources and hiking trail entrances are available to the public: Sierra Madre Wilderness Trail,  Live Oak Nature Trail, and Canyon View Nature Trail. The park itself has a Native Botanical Area  and picnic area barbecues and fire rings&lt;ref&gt;[http://cityofsierramadre.com/index.php?mod=bailey_canyon The Official Site of the City of Sierra Madre: Bailey Canyon&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;

===Wisteria vine===
Sierra Madre is known for its annual Wistaria Festival (an alternative spelling of [[Wisteria]]), which celebrates its 114-year-old, {{convert|1|acre|m2}} Chinese wisteria (''[[Wisteria sinensis]]'') vine.&lt;ref name=&quot;Times1&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://landscaping.about.com/od/vineplants1/p/wisteria_plants.htm Chinese Wisteria Plants | Wistaria Vines&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;  The plant was named by the ''[[Guinness Book of World Records]]''&lt;ref&gt;as the largest flowering plant and one of the seven horticultural wonders of the world.&lt;/ref&gt; The annual festival is the one day a year the 115-year-old vine on private property can be viewed.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;Now the largest blossoming plant in the world, Sierra Madre's 250-ton wistaria vine fit in a one-gallon can when it was purchased for 75 cents at Monrovia nursery in 194.&quot; March/April 2009 page 52 AAA Westways magazine&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Sierramadrewistariafestival.com&lt;/ref&gt; The city's more than {{convert|500|ft|m|adj=on}}-long Wisteria Vine, was purchased in 1894 by Mrs. William (Alice) Brugman from the old Wilson nursery, in [[Monrovia, California|Monrovia]], for seventy-five cents.&lt;ref name=autogenerated2 /&gt;  Over time, the vine, with its lavender flowers, grew so large that it crushed the house. Now the vine spans two back yards in the 500 block of North Hermosa Avenue.&lt;ref name=&quot;Times1&quot;/&gt; The vine measures more than {{convert|1|acre|m2}} in size and weighs 250 tons.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.gardendecor-and-decorativeaccessories.com/wisteria-and-trumpet-vines-friend-or-foe/ Wisteria /Trumpet Vine | Garden Decor&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;

===&quot;Rose Parade&quot;===	
On January 1, 1917, Sierra Madre made its first entry in the Pasadena Tournament of Roses parade.&lt;ref name=&quot;history&quot;/&gt; Since 1954, the year it was founded, the Sierra Madre Rose Float Association has organized  all of the volunteers that decorate the self made floats every year, and receives no funds from the city. In 2010, the Sierra Madre Rose Float Association and float designer Charles Meier won their fourth award in a row, the ''&quot;Lathrop K. Leishman Award&quot; for Most Beautiful Non-Commercial Float.''&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.sierramadrerosefloat.us/ Sierra Madre Rose Float Association&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;

===Jailhouse Inn===
Sierra Madre's &quot;JailHouse Inn&quot; is located in the Historic City Hall, and its &quot;suite&quot; is actually located at the genuine old jail. There is only one cell, so it can only &quot;incarcerate&quot; just one or two people per night. It is about {{convert|200|sqft|m2}} and is regarded as the smallest, and perhaps most unique, [[bed &amp; breakfast]] in the United States.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.jailhouseinn.net/ Jailhouse Inn Home Page&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;

==Mater Dolorosa Monastery==
In the foothills of Sierra Madre is an {{convert|80|acre|m2}} retreat with a bubbling fountain and verdant gardens. Mater Dolorosa Monastery's first permanent structure was built in 1931.  In 1949, the new retreat house was built and dedicated. The Mater Dolorosa Retreat Center ( Mater Dolorosa means &quot;Mother of Sorrows&quot;) has provided an environment of peace for monks as well as [[Methodist]]s, [[Presbyterians]] and even movie crews.&lt;ref name=&quot;retreat&quot;&gt;{{cite news| url=http://articles.latimes.com/1993-06-21/local/me-5401_1_mater-dolorosa-retreat-center | work=Los Angeles Times | first=Cecilia | last=Rasmussen | date=June 21, 1993}}&lt;/ref&gt;  It is a place where, for almost a century, [[Roman Catholic]] monks and their faithful, have sought tranquillity, and where [[Rose Bowl (stadium)|Rose Bowl]]-bound football teams have found a good night's rest away from the wicked temptations of the cities of Los Angeles and [[Pasadena, California|Pasadena]].

Shortly before the Rose Bowl game in 1958, Ohio State Coach [[Woody Hayes]] started looking for a place to sequester his team from the wicked temptations of [[Los Angeles]]. The Mater Dolorosa monastery in Sierra Madre offered secluded serenity, along with a small company of black-robed friars to make sure the team didn't get into any mischief. The [[1957 Ohio State Buckeyes football team|Buckeyes]] won the game.&lt;ref name=&quot;retreat&quot; /&gt; Other team coaches have followed suit.  [[Bobby Bell]], a [[Minnesota]] linebacker, remembered the team bus pulling into the monastery one late  night, with only the headlights and police escort lights shining against the religious statues. He remarked to his coach: &quot;You don't have to worry about bed-check tonight, Coach.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;retreat&quot;/&gt;

==Historical films produced in Sierra Madre==
*In 1910, New York filmmaker [[D. W. Griffith]] began producing movies in town, using townspeople as extras.{{cn|date=October 2011}}
*''[[The Great Man's Lady]]'', based on the short story &quot;The Human Side&quot; by [[Viña Delmar]], was filmed in 1941, at the Pinney House, starring [[Barbara Stanwyck]], [[Joel McCrea]], and [[Brian Donlevy]].
*[[Eddie Foy, Jr.]] and ''[[The Seven Little Foys]]'' was also filmed at the Pinney House, starring [[Bob Hope]] and [[Milly Vitale]] in 1954.
*In 1976, [[Alfred Hitchcock]] filmed segments of ''A Family Plot'' in Sierra Madre's &quot;Pioneer Cemetery&quot;.
*The 1956 version of ''[[The Invasion of the Body Snatchers]]'' was filmed in town; it starred [[Kevin McCarthy (actor)|Kevin McCarthy]], [[Dana Wynter]], and [[Larry Gates]].
**In 1993, ''Invasion of the Body Snatchers'' was selected for preservation in the United States [[National Film Registry]] by the [[Library of Congress]] as being &quot;culturally, historically, or aesthetically significant&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.imdb.com/title/tt0049366/awards |title= ''Invasion of the Body Snatchers'': Award Wins and Nominations |publisher=[[IMDb|IMDb.com]] |date= |accessdate= June 19, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Numerous other movies have been filmed at Mater Dolorosa Monastery.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.sierramadrenews.net/happyjacks2.htm Movies and TV Shot in Sierra Madre&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;

==Newspaper==
Sierra Madre's local newspaper is the ''[[Mountain Views News]]''.&lt;ref&gt;[http://mtnviewsnews.com/ p1 -- Home Page -- Mountain Views News&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;

==Geography==
Sierra Madre is located at {{Coord|34|9|53|N|118|3|3|W|city}} (34.164806, -118.050907).{{GR|1}}

According to the [[United States Census Bureau]], the town has a total area of 3.0 square miles (7.7&amp;nbsp;km²). 3.0 square miles (7.7&amp;nbsp;km²) of it is land and 0.15% is water.

==Demographics==
===2010===
The [[2010 United States Census]]&lt;ref&gt;{{USCensus-2010CA}}&lt;/ref&gt; reported that Sierra Madre had a population of 10,917. The [[population density]] was 3,692.0 people per square mile (1,425.5/km²). The racial makeup of Sierra Madre was 8,967 (82.1%) [[White (U.S. Census)|White]], 201 (1.8%) [[African American (U.S. Census)|African American]], 44 (0.4%) [[Native American (U.S. Census)|Native American]], 835 (7.6%) [[Asian (U.S. Census)|Asian]], 9 (0.1%) [[Pacific Islander (U.S. Census)|Pacific Islander]], 390 (3.6%) from [[Race (United States Census)|other races]], and 471 (4.3%) from two or more races.  [[Hispanic (U.S. Census)|Hispanic]] or [[Latino (U.S. Census)|Latino]] of any race were 1,628 persons (14.9%).

The Census reported that 10,916 people (100% of the population) lived in households, 1 (0%) lived in non-institutionalized group quarters, and 0 (0%) were institutionalized.

There were 4,837 households, out of which 1,205 (24.9%) had children under the age of 18 living in them, 2,291 (47.4%) were [[marriage|opposite-sex married couples]] living together, 442 (9.1%) had a female householder with no husband present, 139 (2.9%) had a male householder with no wife present.  There were 217 (4.5%) [[POSSLQ|unmarried opposite-sex partnerships]], and 54 (1.1%) [[same-sex partnerships|same-sex married couples or partnerships]]. 1,596 households (33.0%) were made up of individuals and 588 (12.2%) had someone living alone who was 65 years of age or older. The average household size was 2.26.  There were 2,872 [[family (U.S. Census)|families]] (59.4% of all households); the average family size was 2.89.

The population was spread out with 2,095 people (19.2%) under the age of 18, 539 people (4.9%) aged 18 to 24, 2,524 people (23.1%) aged 25 to 44, 3,864 people (35.4%) aged 45 to 64, and 1,895 people (17.4%) who were 65 years of age or older. The median age was 46.6 years. For every 100 females there were 89.8 males. For every 100 females age 18 and over, there were 86.3 males.

There were 5,113 housing units at an average density of 1,729.1 per square mile (667.6/km²), of which 2,988 (61.8%) were owner-occupied, and 1,849 (38.2%) were occupied by renters. The homeowner vacancy rate was 1.0%; the rental vacancy rate was 5.0%.  7,390 people (67.7% of the population) lived in owner-occupied housing units and 3,526 people (32.3%) lived in rental housing units.

===2000===
As of the [[census]]{{GR|2}} of 2000, there were 10,578 people, 4,756 households, and 2,739 families residing in the town.  The [[population density]] was 3,522.9 inhabitants per square mile (1,361.4/km²).  There were 4,923 housing units at an average density of 1,639.5 per square mile (633.6/km²).  The racial makeup of the town was 85.8% [[White (U.S. Census)|White]], 1.1% [[African American (U.S. Census)|African American]], 0.4% [[Native American (U.S. Census)|Native American]], 5.6% [[Asian (U.S. Census)|Asian]], 0.1% [[Pacific Islander (U.S. Census)|Pacific Islander]], 3.0% from [[Race (United States Census)|other races]], and 4.0% from two or more races. [[Hispanic (U.S. Census)|Hispanic]] or [[Latino (U.S. Census)|Latino]] of any race were 6.0% of the population.

There were 4,756 households out of which 23.1% had children under the age of 18 living with them, 47.4% were married couples living together, 7.7% had a female householder with no husband present, and 42.4% were non-families. 35.0% of all households were made up of individuals and 9.7% had someone living alone who was 65 years of age or older. The average household size was 2.20 and the average family size was 2.87.

In the town, the population was spread out with 18.9% under the age of 18, 4.9% from 18 to 24, 30.8% from 25 to 44, 29.7% from 45 to 64, and 15.7% who were 65 years of age or older. The median age was 43 years. For every 100 females there were 89.5 males. For every 100 females age 18 and over, there were 86.5 males.

The median income for a household in the town was $65,900, and the median income for a family was $79,588. Males had a median income of $61,635 versus $42,527 for females. The [[per capita income]] for the town was $41,104. About 1.9% of families and 3.7% of the population were below the [[poverty line]], including 2.2% of those under age 18 and 1.7% of those age 65 or over.

==References==
{{reflist|2}}

==External links==
{{Portal|Los Angeles}}
*[http://www.ci.sierra-madre.ca.us/ Sierra Madre official website]
*[http://www.sierramadre.lib.ca.us/ Sierra Madre Public Library]
*[http://mtnviewsnews.com/ Mountain Views News- The city's legal adjudicated newspaper]
{{Geographic Location
 | Centre =Sierra Madre
 | North =[[San Gabriel Mountains]]
 | Northeast =
 | East =[[Arcadia, California|Arcadia]]
 | Southeast =
 | South = [[Arcadia, California|Arcadia]]
 | Southwest =
 | West = [[Pasadena, California|Pasadena]], ([[East Pasadena, California|East Pasadena]])
 | Northwest =
 | image =
}}

{{Cities of Los Angeles County, California}}
{{Greater Los Angeles Area}}

[[Category:Communities in the San Gabriel Valley]]
[[Category:Cities in Los Angeles County, California]]
[[Category:Incorporated cities and towns in California]]
[[Category:Populated places established in 1907]]

[[ar:سيررا مادري، لوس أنجليس، كاليفورنيا]]
[[bg:Сиера Мадре (окръг, Калифорния)]]
[[de:Sierra Madre (Kalifornien)]]
[[es:Sierra Madre (California)]]
[[fr:Sierra Madre (Californie)]]
[[sw:Sierra Madre, California]]
[[ht:Sierra Madre, Kalifòni]]
[[nl:Sierra Madre (Californië)]]
[[pt:Sierra Madre (Califórnia)]]
[[tl:Sierra Madre, California]]
[[vo:Sierra Madre]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
