<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="107662" ns="0" title="Monterey Park, California"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Infobox settlement
|official_name            = City of Monterey Park
|settlement_type          = [[City]]
|nickname                 =
|website                  = [http://ci.monterey-park.ca.us/ http://ci.monterey-park.ca.us]
|image_skyline            = Cascadeswaterfallmontereypa.jpg
|imagesize                =
|image_caption            = Cascades Waterfall on Atlantic Boulevard
|image_flag               =
|image_seal               = Monterreypark_seal.jpg
|image_map                = LA County Incorporated Areas Monterey Park highlighted.svg
|mapsize                  = 250x200px
|map_caption              = Location of Monterey Park in [[Los Angeles County, California|Los Angeles County]], [[California]]
|image_map1               =
|mapsize1                 =
|map_caption1             =
|coordinates_region       = US-CA
|subdivision_type         = [[List of countries|Country]]
|subdivision_name         = [[United States]]
|subdivision_type1        = [[Political divisions of the United States|State]]
|subdivision_name1        = [[California]]
|subdivision_type2        = [[List of counties in California|County]]
|subdivision_name2        =  [[Los Angeles County, California|Los Angeles]]
|government_type          =
|leader_title             = [[Mayor]]
|leader_name              = Anthony Wong
|established_date         =
&lt;!-- Area------------------&gt;
|area_magnitude           =
| unit_pref               =US
| area_footnotes          = &lt;ref&gt;[http://www.census.gov/geo/www/gazetteer/files/Gaz_places_national.txt U.S. Census]&lt;/ref&gt;
| area_total_sq_mi        = 7.733
| area_land_sq_mi         = 7.672
| area_water_sq_mi        = 0.061
| area_total_km2          = 20.029
| area_land_km2           = 19.870
| area_water_km2          = 0.158
| area_water_percent      = 0.79
| area_note               = 
|population_as_of         = 2010
|population_total         = 60269
|population_urban                 =
|area_urban_km2           =
|area_urban_sq_mi         =
|population_metro         =
|population_density_km2   = auto
|population_density_sq_mi = auto
|timezone                 = [[Pacific Time Zone|PST]]
|utc_offset               = -8
|timezone_DST             = PDT
|utc_offset_DST           = -7
|coordinates_display = display=inline,title
|latd = 34 |latm = 2 |lats = 57 |latNS = N
|longd = 118 |longm = 8 |longs = 8 |longEW = W
|elevation_m              = 117
|elevation_ft             = 384
|postal_code_type         = [[ZIP code]]s
|postal_code              = 91754-91756
|area_code                = [[Area code 323|323]], [[Area code 626|626]]
|blank_name               = [[Federal Information Processing Standard|FIPS code]]
|blank_info               = 06-48914
|blank1_name              = [[Geographic Names Information System|GNIS]] feature ID
|blank1_info              = 1652753
|footnotes                =
}}
'''Monterey Park''' is a city in [[Los Angeles County, California|Los Angeles County]], [[California]], [[United States]], {{convert|10|mi|km}} east of [[downtown Los Angeles]]. The city's motto is &quot;Pride in the past, Faith in the future&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;CMP&quot;&gt;http://www.ci.monterey-park.ca.us/&lt;/ref&gt; Monterey Park is part of a cluster of cities, along with [[Arcadia, California|Arcadia]], [[Temple City, California|Temple City]], [[Rosemead, California|Rosemead]], [[San Marino, California|San Marino]], and [[San Gabriel, California|San Gabriel]] in the west [[San Gabriel Valley]], with a growing [[Asian American]] population, making up 66.9% of its resident population at 2010; 47.7% of its residents are of [[Chinese people|Chinese descent]], the largest concentration of [[Chinese American]]s of any [[municipality]] in the United States.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.pacsla.org/API_demographics.html |title=PACS &amp;#124; Asian Pacific Family Center &amp;#124; Asian Youth Center &amp;#124; Chinatown Service Center &amp;#124; Korean Youth and Community Center &amp;#124; Search to Involve Pilipino Americans |publisher=Pacsla.org |date=2005-04-26 |accessdate=2010-08-17}}&lt;/ref&gt; According to the [[2010 United States Census|2010 Census]], the city had a total population of 60,269.&lt;ref name=&quot;CMP&quot;/&gt;

==History==
===Early history===
For at least seven thousand years &lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.lausd.k12.ca.us/Verdugo_HS/classes/multimedia/intro.html |title=introduction |publisher=Lausd.k12.ca.us |date= |accessdate=2010-08-17}}&lt;/ref&gt; the land was populated by the [[Tongva people|Tongva]] ([[Gabrielino]]) Native Americans.   The Tongva lived in dome like structures with thatched exteriors, an open smoke hole for ventilation and light at the top.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.lausd.k12.ca.us/Verdugo_HS/classes/multimedia/house.htm |title=Housing |publisher=Lausd.k12.ca.us |date= |accessdate=2010-08-17}}&lt;/ref&gt;  Both sexes wore long hair styles and tattooed their bodies. During warm weather the men wore little clothes but the women would wear minimal skirts made of animal hides. During the cold weather they would wear animal skin capes and occasionally wore sandals made from hide of yucca fiber.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.lausd.k12.ca.us/Verdugo_HS/classes/multimedia/cloth.html |title=clothing |publisher=Lausd.k12.ca.us |date= |accessdate=2010-08-17}}&lt;/ref&gt;  With the arrival of the Spaniards, [[Old World]] diseases killed off many of the Tongva, and by 1870 very few Native-Americans had survived. In the early 19th century the area was part of the [[Mission San Gabriel Arcángel]] mission system and later, the [[Rancho San Antonio (Lugo)|Rancho San Antonio]].

===1860s–1960s===
Following the Civil War, an Italian, Alessandro Repetto, purchased {{convert|5,000|acre|km2}} of the rancho and built his ranch house on the hill overlooking his land, about a half-mile north of where Garfield Avenue crosses the Pomona Freeway,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.cityofmontebello.com/about/default.asp |title=About Montebello |publisher=City of Montebello |date=1920-10-19 |accessdate=2010-08-17}}&lt;/ref&gt; not far from where the [[Southern California Edison|Edison]] substation is now located on Garfield Avenue.&lt;ref name=&quot;ci.monterey-park.ca.us&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.ci.monterey-park.ca.us/index.aspx?page=1079 |title=City of Monterey Park : History of Monterey Park |publisher=Ci.monterey-park.ca.us |date= |accessdate=2010-08-17}}&lt;/ref&gt;

It was at this time, Richard Garvey, a mail rider for the U.S. Army whose route took him through [[Monterey Pass]], a trail that is now Garvey Avenue, settled down in the King's Hills.  Garvey began developing the land by bringing in spring water from near the Hondo River and by constructing a {{convert|54|ft|m|adj=mid|-high|0}} dam to form Garvey Lake located where  Garvey Ranch Park is now.  To pay for his development and past debts, Garvey began selling portions of his property.  In 1906, the first subdivision in the area, Ramona Acres (named after the developer's daughter, who would also later inspire the title of the novel ''[[Ramona]]''&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://articles.latimes.com/1994-01-17/local/me-12794_1_san-bernardino-freeway|title=L.A. Scene / The City Then and Now|last=Cecilia|first=Rasmussen|date=January 17, 1994|work=[[Los Angeles Times]]|accessdate=19 July 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;), was developed north of Garvey and east of Garfield Avenues.&lt;ref name=&quot;ci.monterey-park.ca.us&quot;/&gt;

In 1916, the new residents of the area initiated action to become a city when the cities of [[Pasadena, California|Pasadena]], [[South Pasadena, California|South Pasadena]], and [[Alhambra, California|Alhambra]] proposed to put a large sewage treatment facility in the area.  The community voted itself into cityhood on May 29, 1916, by a vote of 455 to 33.  The City's new Board of Directors immediately outlawed sewage plants within city boundaries and named the new city [[Monterey Park]].  The name was taken from an old government map showing the oak-covered hills of the area as Monterey Hills.  In 1920, a large area on the south edge of the city broke away and the separate city of [[Montebello, California|Montebello]] was established.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.montebellochamber.org/History.aspx |title=Chamber History |publisher=Montebellochamber.org |date= |accessdate=2010-08-17}}&lt;/ref&gt;

By 1920, the white and Spanish-surname settlers were joined by Asian residents who began farming potatoes and flowers and developing nurseries in the Monterey Highlands area.  They improved the Monterey Pass Trail with a road to aid in shipping their produce to Los Angeles.  The nameless pass, which had been a popular location for western movies, was called Coyote Pass by Pioneer Masami Abe.&lt;ref name=&quot;ci.monterey-park.ca.us&quot;/&gt;

In 1926, near the corner of Atlantic and Garvey Boulevards, [[Laura Scudder]] invented the first sealed bag of potato chips. In an effort to maintain quality and freshness, Laura's team would iron sheets of wax paper together to form a bag. They would fill these bags with potato chips; iron the top closed, and then deliver them to various retailers.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.laurascudders.com/History |title=Laura Scudder's |publisher=Laurascudders.com |date= |accessdate=2010-08-17}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Real estate became a thriving industry during the late 1920s with investors attracted to the many subdivisions under development and increasing commercial opportunities. One such development was the Midwick View Estates by Peter N. Snyder, a proposed garden community that was designed to rival [[Bel Air, California|Bel Air]] and [[Beverly Hills, California|Beverly Hills]].  Known as the &quot;Father of the East Side&quot;, Mr. Snyder was a key player in the vast undertaking in the 1920s of developing the East Side as part of the industrial base of Los Angeles.  His efforts to build Atlantic Boulevard, his work with the East Side organization to bring industry to the East Side, and his residential and commercial development projects along Atlantic Boulevard (Gardens Square, Golden Gate Square, and the Midwick View Estates) were a major influence to the surrounding communities.  The focal point of the Midwick View Estates was &quot;Jardin del Encanto&quot;, otherwise known as &quot;El Encanto,&quot; a Spanish style building that was to serve as the administration building and community center for Midwick View Estates, and an amphitheater to be nestled into the hillside above Kingsford Street.  Although the amphitheater was never built, the observation terrace from which viewers could look down to Jardin del Encanto and the fountain with cascading water going down the hillside in stepped pools to De La Fuente remains and is now known as Heritage Falls Park or &quot;the Cascades.&quot;  The Great Depression brought an abrupt end to the real estate boom, as well as the Midwick proposal.  From the late 1920s, the City had little development for nearly two decades.&lt;ref name=&quot;ci.monterey-park.ca.us&quot;/&gt;

The end of World War II resulted in a revived growth trend with explosive population gains during the late 1940s and 1950s.  Until this time, the population was concentrated in the northern and southern portions of the city, with the Garvey and Monterey Hills forming a natural barrier.  With the renewed growth, many new subdivisions were developed, utilizing even the previously undeveloped central area to allow for maximum growth potential.  A series of annexations of surrounding land also occurred.&lt;ref name=&quot;ci.monterey-park.ca.us&quot;/&gt;

===1970s–present===
[[Image:Montereypark.jpg|250px|right|thumb|Downtown Monterey Park, California]]
Beginning in the 1970s, well-educated and affluent [[Asian Americans]] began settling in the west [[San Gabriel Valley]], primarily to Monterey Park.&lt;ref&gt;Horton, John. ''The Politics of Diversity: Immigration, Resistance, and Change in Monterey Park, California ''. Temple University Press, 195. p. 80.Chapter 4&lt;/ref&gt; The city council subsequently tried and failed to pass English-only ordinances.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.asianweek.com/052496/LittleTaipei.html&lt;/ref&gt;  In 1985 the City Council of Monterey Park approved drafting of a proposal that would require all businesses in Monterey Park to display [[English language]] identification on business signs.&lt;ref&gt;Arax, Mark. &quot;Stronger Rules on English in Signs Pushed by Council.&quot; ''[[Los Angeles Times]]''. December 5, 1985. [http://articles.latimes.com/1985-12-05/news/ga-633_1_sign-ordinance 1]. Retrieved on March 29, 2010.&lt;/ref&gt; 

In the 1980s, Monterey Park was also referred to as &quot;[[Little Taipei]]&quot; or affectionately,  &quot;The Chinese Beverly Hills&quot; by a local Chinese-language newspaper, &quot;Asian Week&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;http://asianweek.com/052496/LittleTaipei.html&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;asian&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;at-usa.com&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.at-usa.com/California/Localities/M/Monterey_Park/ |title=Monterey Park, California (CA) @USA |publisher=At-usa.com |date= |accessdate=2010-08-17}}&lt;/ref&gt; Many businesses from [[Chinatown, Los Angeles]] began to open up stores in Monterey Park.  In the 1970s and 1980s, many affluent ''[[Mainlander#Chinese mainlanders (Taiwan)|waisheng ren]]'' [[Taiwan]]ese immigrants moved abroad from Taiwan and began settling into Monterey Park. [[Mandarin Chinese]] dialect was predominant in the city during that time.&lt;ref name=&quot;temple.edu&quot;&gt;{{cite book|first=Timothy P. |last=Fong |url=http://www.temple.edu/tempress/titles/997_reg_print.html |title=The First Suburban Chinatown |publisher=Temple University|isbn=9781566392624 |year=1994}}&lt;/ref&gt; By the late 1980s, immigrants from [[Mainland China]] and [[Vietnam]] began moving into Monterey Park.  By the 1990 census, Monterey Park became the first city with an Asian descent majority population in the continental United States.&lt;ref name=&quot;at-usa.com&quot;/&gt; Timothy P. Fong, a professor and director of Asian American studies at [[California State University, Sacramento]], describes Monterey Park as the &quot;First Suburban Chinatown&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;temple.edu&quot;/&gt;

In the 1980s, the second generation Chinese Americans generally moved out of the old Chinatown and into the San Gabriel Valley suburbs, joining the new immigrants from Taiwan and Mainland China.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.raulareyes.com/Site/Monterey_Park.html/ San Gabriel Valley Tribune&lt;/ref&gt;
From that time, with a combined influx of Vietnamese, Taiwanese and Hong Kong immigrant students at the time, [[Mark Keppel High School]], constructed during the [[New Deal]] era and located in [[Alhambra, California|Alhambra]], but also serving most of [[Monterey Park]] and portions of [[Rosemead]], felt the impact of this new immigration as the student population increased dramatically, leading  to overcrowding.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.mkhs.org/apps/pages/index.jsp?uREC_ID=62613&amp;type=d&amp;termREC_ID=&amp;pREC_ID=97013 |title=Mark Keppel High School |publisher=Mkhs.org |date=1999-12-31 |accessdate=2010-08-17}}&lt;/ref&gt; Today, many students are second- or third-generation Asian Americans.&lt;ref&gt;www.hks.harvard.edu/aapr/doc/tsai76-98.pdf&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;/ref&gt; In the Japanese community called: Nisei, (second-generation), Sansei,  (third-generation).&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|pmid=7859632}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In 1988, the City of Monterey Park passed an ordinance declaring a moratorium on new building, in an attempt to regulate the rapid growth the city experienced as a result of the influx of Asian immigrants.&lt;ref name=&quot;asian&quot;&gt;{{cite web|author=Alfred Pong |url=http://www.asianweek.com/052496/LittleTaipei.html |title=The Chinese Beverly Hills |publisher=Asianweek.com |date= |accessdate=2010-08-17}}&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://articles.latimes.com/1988-05-12/local/me-4230_1_building-permits |title=Local News in Brief : Building Bans Imposed - Los Angeles Times |publisher=Articles.latimes.com |date=1988-05-12 |accessdate=2010-08-17}}&lt;/ref&gt;  This moratorium was challenged and defeated in 1989 &lt;ref name=&quot;sfgate.com&quot;&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.sfgate.com/cgi-bin/article.cgi?f=/c/a/2010/06/05/MNSG1DQ1BL.DTL |title=Whites in state 'below the replacement' level |publisher=Sfgate.com |date=2010-06-05 |accessdate=2010-08-17 | first=Justin | last=Berton}}&lt;/ref&gt; This controversial move caused many Asian residents and businesses to shift locus, establishing themselves in the neighboring city of [[Alhambra, California|Alhambra]].  When the potential loss of business revenue was recognized,&lt;ref&gt;http://www.docstoc.com/docs/48018067/The-First-Suburban-Chinatown&lt;/ref&gt;  &quot;Monterey Park went through a lot of upheaval that a lot of people regret.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Quan, Douglas. &quot;[http://www.pe.com/localnews/rivcounty/stories/PE_News_Local_D_asian07.25558b4.html Some in Chino Hills nervous about ethnic shift].&quot; ''[[The Press-Enterprise]]''. Tuesday February 6, 2007. Retrieved on January 21, 2010.&lt;/ref&gt; and relocation back to Monterey Park was highly encouraged in the [[Asian American]] community.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|author=By DOUGLAS QUANThe Press-Enterprise |url=http://www.pe.com/localnews/rivcounty/stories/PE_News_Local_D_asian07.25558b4.html |title=Riverside County &amp;#124; PE.com &amp;#124; Southern California News &amp;#124; News for Inland Southern California |publisher=PE.com |date=2007-02-06 |accessdate=2010-08-17}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Since early 1990s, the Taiwanese are no longer the majority in the city,&lt;ref name=&quot;at-usa.com&quot;/&gt; and [[Mandarin Chinese|Mandarin]], the national language of China,  is now rapidly displacing [[Cantonese]] as the most widely spoken dialect in many Chinese businesses of Monterey Park. Cantonese, a dialect from southern China  has dominated the Chinatowns of North America for decades, but Mandarin is the  most common language of the latest Chinese immigrants.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news| url=http://www.nytimes.com/2009/10/22/nyregion/22chinese.html?_r=1 | work=The New York Times | first=Kirk | last=Semple | title=In Chinatown, Sound of the Future Is Mandarin | date=2009-10-22}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;http://www.howardwfrench.com/archives/2006/01/07/cantonese_is_losing_its_voice_speakers_of_the_spicy_tongue_that_can_make_words_of_love_sound_like_a_fight_are_having_to_learn_its_linguistic_kin_the_mellower_mandarin/&lt;/ref&gt; The construction boom of shopping centers has declined, but recent plans for redevelopment may change that. High property values and overcrowding in Monterey Park &lt;ref&gt;http://www.ci.monterey-park.ca.us/index.aspx?page=726&lt;/ref&gt; have contributed to a secondary movement away from Monterey Park. Furthermore, a great many established, wealthy Taiwanese immigrants have since relocated out of Monterey Park and northward to wealthier cities of [[San Marino, California|San Marino]], [[Arcadia, California|Arcadia]], [[Temple City, California|Temple City]], [[South Pasadena, California|South Pasadena]], and eastward to [[Diamond Bar, California|Diamond Bar]], [[Hacienda Heights, California|Hacienda Heights]],  [[Walnut, California|Walnut]] and  [[Rowland Heights, California|Rowland Heights]], sometimes  called the &quot;New Little Taipei&quot;  &lt;ref&gt;http://www.theatlantic.com/past/issues/99jan/chinese.htm&lt;/ref&gt; Many Chinese-speaking businesses were established in these suburbs to accommodate this shift in demographics. This path follows the [[White Flight]] of the late 1970s.&lt;ref name=&quot;sfgate.com&quot;/&gt; Development of new buildings in Monterey Park had come to a virtual standstill,  there are still numerous Chinese-oriented businesses in Monterey Park and  there are significant redevelopment plans, now in process.

==Business==
The Chinese-dominated business district, between Garfield Avenue and Garvey Avenue, is called &quot;Downtown Monterey Park&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.ci.monterey-park.ca.us/index.aspx?page=1811&lt;/ref&gt; In the mid-1980s, Lincoln Plaza Hotel was built to predominately service tourists from Taiwan and Hong Kong.  Monterey Park has many choices of Hong Kong fusion cafes, there are several Cantonese seafood restaurants, as well as  restaurants offering [[Mainland Chinese]] fare.  As the activity of Taiwanese immigrant activity shifted to [[San Gabriel, California|San Gabriel]], [[Arcadia, California|Arcadia]] and [[Rowland Heights, California|Rowland Heights]] in the 1980s and 1990s, few Taiwanese restaurants have opened in the city.

The city's business interests are represented by the local [[Chamber of Commerce]]. The Chamber offices are located in the historic [[El Encanto]] - a building originally intended to be used as a land sales office. The Chamber is staffed during regular business hours and offers a variety of services for its members and the public. The Chamber is run by a [[Board of directors]]. The current president of the chamber is Vincent D. Chang, an attorney. The immediate past-president was Ronald Lee, a jeweler. The Chamber host regular networking opportunities such as a monthly Business-to-Business luncheon. Recently, the Chamber revived the &quot;Miss Monterey Park&quot; Pageant.

===Top employers===
According to the City's 2010 Comprehensive Annual Financial Report,&lt;ref name=&quot;cafr&quot;&gt;[http://www.ci.monterey-park.ca.us/Modules/ShowDocument.aspx?documentid=11078 City of Monterey Park CAFR]&lt;/ref&gt; the top employers in the city are:

{| class=&quot;wikitable&quot; border=&quot;1&quot;
|-
! #
! Employer
! # of Employees
|-
| 1
|[[East Los Angeles College]]
|1,969
|-
| 2
|[[AHMC|Garfield Medical Center]]
|970
|-
| 3
|[[Los Angeles County Sheriff's Department]]
|791
|-
| 4
|[[Superior Court of Los Angeles County]] - Edmund D. Edelman Children's Court
|736
|-
| 5
|City of Monterey Park
|440
|-
| 6
|[[AHMC|Monterey Park Hospital]]
|362
|-
| 7
|Care1st Health Plan 
|315
|-
| 8
|[[Southern California Gas Company]]
|279
|-
| 9
|[[Pacific Bell|AT&amp;T]]
|228
|-
| 10
|SynerMed
|217
|-
| 11
|[[Ralphs]]
|158
|-
| 12
|[[First Data]]
|133
|-
| 13
|[[California Highway Patrol]]
|131
|-
| 14
|''[[World Journal]]''
|128
|-
| 15
|[[Southern California Edison]]
|125
|-
| 16
|Camino Real [[Chevrolet]]
|121
|-
| 17
|[[CVS/pharmacy]]
|117
|-
|}

==Redevelopment==
The recently opened commercial developments include Atlantic Times Square,&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.ci.monterey-park.ca.us/index.aspx?page=1403 Atlantic Times Square]&lt;/ref&gt; which has {{convert|215000|sqft|m2|-2}} . The oldest shopping center in the region  is being rebuilt as a neighborhood center with anchors such as [[Ralph's]] Grocery, [[Rite Aid]], [[Foot Locker]], and [[Radio Shack]].  The new center will create over 400 jobs when completed.&lt;ref name=&quot;MP&quot;&gt;http://www.ci.monterey-park.ca.us/Index.aspx?page=286&lt;/ref&gt;

Monterey Park Village is a 40,000 sq. ft. shopping center on South Atlantic Boulevard commercial corridor.  Tenants include: [[Staples Inc.|Staples]], [[Walgreens]] and Togo’s eatery.  100 jobs are created.&lt;ref name=&quot;MP&quot;/&gt;

The CVS Center is on South Garfield Avenue.  This is a redevelopment of infill site into a 17,000 sq. ft.   neighborhood convenience center.  Anchor tenant [[CVS Pharmacy]] brings a full-service drug store back to the downtown project.&lt;ref name=&quot;MP&quot;/&gt;

The &quot;Merged Project Area&quot; encompasses a total of 620 acres for development of a commercial, industrial, office park, residential, public improvements
Projected are the Monterey Park Market Place, Los Angeles Corporate Center Hotel, and [[Sav-on]].&lt;ref name=&quot;MP&quot;/&gt;

The Monterey Park Towne Centre will be located at Garvey Avenue and Garfield Avenue, and is the future site of {{convert|500000|sqft|m2|-4|sing=on}} the {{convert|45|acre|m2|adj=on}} Monterey Park Market Place center.  The Monterey Park Towne Centre will offer {{convert|71366|sqft|m2|0}} of retail space in the heart of Monterey Park's Downtown revitalization.  Plans for  the multi-use development include 109  condominiums.  The Towne Centre will feature a palm court entry surrounded by major anchors, specialty shops and outdoor dining.  Residents will enjoy such amenities as a community clubhouse, recreation facilities and private, secured parking&lt;ref&gt;http://www.ci.monterey-park.ca.us/index.aspx?page=1287&lt;/ref&gt;

Cascades Market Place
The {{convert|507000|sqft|m2|adj=on}} Center will be the largest shopping center in the city.  Located along the Pomona 60 Freeway, west of Paramount Boulevard, this  center proposes to be a major regional shopping center for the San Gabriel Valley. The project manager says &quot;This 45 plus acre project has grade level visibility from the freeway unmatched by any retail project in the region.&quot; &lt;ref&gt;http://www.ci.monterey-park.ca.us/index.aspx?page=1284&lt;/ref&gt;

&quot;The Garvey Villas Project&quot;, part of the Monterey Park Redevelopment plan, will be at the southwest corner of Atlantic Boulevard and Garvey Avenue.  The project involves displacement and relocation of two separate family homes.  The Agency pledges to appropriate, on a timely basis, the funds necessary to ensure the successful completion of the relocation activities associated with this Project.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.ci.monterey-park.ca.us/Modules/ShowDocument.aspx?documentid=3858&lt;/ref&gt;

==Places of interest==
Monterey Park is home to the Garvey Ranch Observatory, located in Garvey Ranch Park, which is operated by the Los Angeles Astronomical Society (LAAS). It adjoins a telescope construction workshop, a historical museum and a library. The observatory houses an {{convert|8|in|mm|sing=on}} refractor, and the grounds are open to the public for astronomical observation on Wednesday evenings, hosted by LAAS members.&lt;ref&gt;
{{cite web
|url=http://www.laas.org/joomlasite/index.php?option=com_content&amp;view=article&amp;id=86&amp;Itemid=99
|title=Garvey Ranch
|accessdate=2011-08-10
}}&lt;/ref&gt;
The [[Sybil Brand Institute]], the [[county jail]] for women, was located in the city, but closed in 1994 after the facility had been damaged in the [[Northridge earthquake]].&lt;ref name=&quot;at-usa.com&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.whittierdailynews.com/ci_8608567 |title=County may replace jail |publisher=Whittier Daily News |date= |accessdate=2010-08-17}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Transportation==
Monterey Park is served by the [[Interstate 710 (California)|I-710]], the [[San Bernardino Freeway]] ([[Interstate 10 (California)|I-10]]), and the [[Pomona Freeway]], [[California State Route 60|SR 60]].

Public transportation is provided by the city government, [[Monterey Park Spirit Bus|Spirit bus service]] and [http://www.ci.monterey-park.ca.us/docs/schedule.pdf Metrolink feeder bus], the [http://www.cityofmontebello.com/depts/transit/bus/default.asp City of Montebello] and the [[Los Angeles County Metropolitan Transportation Authority]].

==Geography==
Monterey Park is located at {{Coord|34.049199|-118.135561|type:city_region:US|format=dms|display=inline}}.{{GR|1}}
According to the [[United States Census Bureau]], the city has a total area of {{convert|7.7|sqmi|km2}}, of which, {{convert|7.6|sqmi|km2}} is land, and {{convert|0.04|sqmi|km2}} (0.39%) is water.

The city boundaries include [[Los Angeles]] to the west, unincorporated [[East Los Angeles, California|East Los Angeles]] to the south, [[Alhambra, California|Alhambra]] to the north, [[Rosemead, California|Rosemead]] to the northeast, [[Montebello, California|Montebello]] to the south, and unincorporated [[South San Gabriel, California|South San Gabriel]] to the southeast.

==Demographics==
===2010===
The [[2010 United States Census]]&lt;ref&gt;{{USCensus-2010CA}}&lt;/ref&gt; reported that Monterey Park had a population of 60,269. The [[population density]] was 7,793.7 people per square mile (3,009.2/km²). The racial makeup of Monterey Park was 11,680 (19.4%) [[White (U.S. Census)|White]], 252 (0.4%) [[African American (U.S. Census)|African American]], 242 (0.4%) [[Native American (U.S. Census)|Native American]], 40,301 (66.9%) [[Asian (U.S. Census)|Asian]] (47.7% Chinese, 5.8% Japanese, 4.4% Vietnamese, 1.9% Filipino, 1.3% Korean, 0.9% Thai, 0.8% Cambodian, 0.4% Burmese, 0.4% Indonesian, 0.3% Indian), 28 (0.0%) [[Pacific Islander (U.S. Census)|Pacific Islander]], 6,022 (10.0%) from [[Race (United States Census)|other races]], and 1,744 (2.9%) from two or more races.  [[Hispanic (U.S. Census)|Hispanic]] or [[Latino (U.S. Census)|Latino]] of any race were 16,218 persons (26.9%). 

The Census reported that 60,039 people (99.6% of the population) lived in households, 41 (0.1%) lived in non-institutionalized group quarters, and 189 (0.3%) were institutionalized.  

There were 19,963 households, out of which 6,315 (31.6%) had children under the age of 18 living in them, 10,538 (52.8%) were [[marriage|opposite-sex married couples]] living together, 3,243 (16.2%) had a female householder with no husband present, 1,460 (7.3%) had a male householder with no wife present.  There were 651 (3.3%) [[POSSLQ|unmarried opposite-sex partnerships]], and 85 (0.4%) [[same-sex partnerships|same-sex married couples or partnerships]]. 3,641 households (18.2%) were made up of individuals and 2,025 (10.1%) had someone living alone who was 65 years of age or older. The average household size was 3.01.  There were 15,241 [[family (U.S. Census)|families]] (76.3% of all households); the average family size was 3.37.

The population was spread out with 10,932 people (18.1%) under the age of 18, 5,180 people (8.6%) aged 18 to 24, 15,597 people (25.9%) aged 25 to 44, 16,904 people (28.0%) aged 45 to 64, and 11,656 people (19.3%) who were 65 years of age or older.  The median age was 43.1 years. For every 100 females there were 92.2 males.  For every 100 females age 18 and over, there were 89.4 males.

There were 20,850 housing units at an average density of 2,696.2 per square mile (1,041.0/km²), of which 11,058 (55.4%) were owner-occupied, and 8,905 (44.6%) were occupied by renters. The homeowner vacancy rate was 0.5%; the rental vacancy rate was 4.1%.  33,073 people (54.9% of the population) lived in owner-occupied housing units and 26,966 people (44.7%) lived in rental housing units.

===2009===
According to the 2009 [[American Community Survey]], Monterey Park is 43.7% [[Chinese American]], and is the city in the United States with the largest concentration of people of Chinese descent.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.asian-nation.org/taiwanese.shtml&lt;/ref&gt; The Chinese American population in Monterey Park and San Gabriel Valley is relatively diverse in socio-economics and region of origin. The city has attracted immigrants from [[Taiwan]], as well as [[Mainland Chinese]] and the [[overseas Chinese]] from [[Southeast Asia]]. There are also significant [[Japanese American|Japanese]], [[Vietnamese American|Vietnamese]], [[Korean American|Korean]], and [[Filipino American|Filipino]] communities living within Monterey Park. 

While the multi-generational American-born Latino population was generally declining in Monterey Park, there has been a small new influx of Mexican immigrants (about one percent increase in the population).&lt;ref&gt;http://factfinder.census.gov/servlet/SAFFFacts?_event=Search&amp;_geoContext=&amp;_street=&amp;_county=monterey+park&amp;_cityTown=monterey+park&amp;_state=04000US06&amp;_zip=&amp;_lang=en&amp;_sse=on&amp;pctxt=fph&amp;pgs1=010&amp;show_2003_tab=&amp;redirect=Y&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;ttp://factfinder.census.gov/servlet/ACSSAFFFacts?_event=&amp;geo_id=16000US0648914&amp;_geoContext=01000US|04000US06|16000US0648914&amp;_street=&amp;_county=monterey+park&amp;_cityTown=monterey+park&amp;_state=04000US06&amp;_zip=&amp;_lang=en&amp;_sse=on&amp;ActiveGeoDiv=&amp;_useEV=&amp;pctxt=fph&amp;pgsl=160&amp;_submenuId=factsheet_1&amp;ds_name=DEC_2000_SAFF&amp;_ci_nbr=null&amp;qr_name=null&amp;reg=&amp;_keyword=&amp;_industry=&lt;/ref&gt;

===2000===
There were 19,564 households out of which 31.3% had children under the age of 18 living with them, 55.4% were married couples living together, 15.8% had a female householder with no husband present, and 22.1% were non-families. 17.3% of all households were made up of individuals and 8.7% had someone living alone who was 65 years of age or older.  The average household size was 3.06 and the average family size was 3.43.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.laalmanac.com/cities/ci56.htm&lt;/ref&gt;

In the city the population was spread out with 21.3% under the age of 18, 8.4% from 18 to 24, 30.2% from 25 to 44, 22.2% from 45 to 64, and 17.9% who were 65 years of age or older.  The median age was 38 years. For every 100 females there were 92.4 males.  For every 100 females age 18 and over, there were 89.3 males.

The median [[income]] for a household in the city was $40,724, and the median income for a family was $43,507. Males had a median income of $32,463 versus $29,057 for females. The [[per capita income]] for the city was $17,661.  About 12.4% of families and 15.6% of the population were below the [[poverty line]], including 22.6% of those under age 18 and 9.2% of those age 65 or over.

==Government==
In the [[California State Legislature|state legislature]] Monterey Park is located in the 24th [[California State Senate|Senate]] District, represented by Democrat [[Gloria J. Romero|Gloria Romero]], and in the 49th [[California State Assembly|Assembly]] District, represented by Democrat [[Mike Eng]],also a former mayor of Monterey Park. Federally, Monterey Park is located in California's [[California's 29th congressional district|29th]] and [[California's 32nd congressional district|32nd]] congressional districts, which have [[Cook Partisan Voting Index|Cook PVIs]] of D +12 and D +17&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | title = Will Gerrymandered Districts Stem the Wave of Voter Unrest? | publisher = Campaign Legal Center Blog | url=http://www.clcblog.org/blog_item-85.html | accessdate = 2008-02-10}}&lt;/ref&gt; and is represented by Democrats [[Adam Schiff]] and [[Judy Chu]]. Chu previously served as mayor and city council member of Monterey Park.

===City===
Monterey Park City Municipal Elections are held every two  years in odd numbered years, on the first Tuesday in March. The five  Council Members serve four  year terms with overlapping terms in bi-annual elections:  the three seats elected in one election and two  seats in the next election, at which time the City Clerk and City Treasurer are also elected.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.ci.monterey-park.ca.us/index.aspx?page=3&lt;/ref&gt; The current members of the City Council are:

*Betty Tom Chu
*David T. Lau, Mayor
*Mitchell Ing
*Teresa Real Sebastian&lt;ref name=&quot;mpk1&quot;&gt;[http://www.pasadenastarnews.com/news/ci_17522324&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;
*Anthony Wong

===County services===
The [[Los Angeles County Sheriff's Department]] has its central headquarters in Monterey Park. [[Los Angeles County Sheriff's Department]]&lt;ref&gt;&quot;[http://www.lasd.org/divisions/leadership-training-div/bureaus/ebd/assets/sb-579.pdf Education-Based Discipline].&quot; [[Los Angeles County Sheriff's Department]]. April 29, 2009. Retrieved on March 12, 2010.&lt;/ref&gt;
The [[Edmund D. Edelman]] Children's Court,  Central Juvenile District, (Dependency) is located in  Monterey Park.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.lasuperiorcourt.org/locations/ui/location.aspx?loc=CCJ&amp; |title=Court Location General Tab |publisher=Lasuperiorcourt.org |date= |accessdate=2010-08-17}}&lt;/ref&gt;
The [[Los Angeles County Department of Health Services]] operates the Monrovia Health Center in [[Monrovia, California|Monrovia]], serving Monterey Park.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;[http://publichealth.lacounty.gov/phn/docs/HealthCenter/monrovia.pdf Monrovia Health Center].&quot; [[Los Angeles County Department of Health Services]]. Retrieved on March 27, 2010.&lt;/ref&gt;

==Education==

[[Image:MKHSauditoriumSouthernFace.jpg|thumb|[[Mark Keppel High School]]]]

===Colleges and universities===
[[East Los Angeles College]] is a community college that is located in Monterey Park in an area that was once part of [[East Los Angeles, California|East Los Angeles]] (unincorporated). In addition [[California State University, Los Angeles]] is in proximity.&lt;ref name=&quot;SchoolsMP&quot;&gt;&quot;[http://www.ci.monterey-park.ca.us/index.aspx?page=866 School districts serving Monterey Park].&quot; City of Monterey Park. Retrieved on July 3, 2010.&lt;/ref&gt;

===Primary and secondary schools===
Four school districts all serve different areas of Monterey Park. They include [[Alhambra Unified School District]], [[Garvey School District]], [[Los Angeles Unified School District]], and [[Montebello Unified School District]].&lt;ref name=&quot;SchoolsMP&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.latimes.com/classified/realestate/news/la-re-guide5mar05,1,4455622.story http://www.latimes.com/classified/realestate/news/la-re-guide5mar05,1,4455622.story] ''latimes.com''&lt;/ref&gt;

====Public schools====
=====Alhambra Unified School District=====
[[Image:MontereyHighlandsMarquee.jpg|thumb|Monterey Highlands School]]
K-8 schools serving AUSD in Monterey Park include:
* [[Brightwood School]]
* [[Monterey Highlands School]]
* Repetto School [http://alhambra.k12.ca.us/]
* Ynez School [http://alhambra.k12.ca.us/]

[[Mark Keppel High School]], [http://www.mkhs.org/], located in [[Alhambra, California|Alhambra]], also serves Monterey Park.

=====Garvey School District=====
Two elementary schools, [http://www.garvey.k12.ca.us/education/school/school.php?sectionid=14 Hillcrest] and [http://www.garvey.k12.ca.us/education/school/school.php?sectionid=16 Monterey Vista] (both are in Monterey Park), serve this part of the city. Monterey Vista is a Blue Ribbon School.

[http://www.garvey.k12.ca.us/education/components/scrapbook/default.php?sectionid=17 Garvey Intermediate School] (Rosemead) also serves this portion.

Once students graduate from eighth grade, they attend Alhambra's Mark Keppel High School [http://www.mkhs.org/].

=====Los Angeles Unified School District=====
[http://www.lausd.k12.ca.us/Lane_EL/ Robert Lane Elementary School] (Monterey Park), Griffith Middle School (Unincorporated Los Angeles County), and [[Garfield High School (Los Angeles County, California)|Garfield High School]] (Unincorporated Los Angeles County) serve the LAUSD part of the city.

=====Montebello Unified School District=====
[http://www.bve.montebello.k12.ca.us/ Bella Vista Elementary School], Monterey Park, [http://www.phe.montebello.k12.ca.us/ Potrero Heights Elementary School], South San Gabriel, [http://www.mai.montebello.k12.ca.us/ Macy Intermediate School], Monterey Park, and [[Schurr High School]], Montebello, serve the Montebello MUSD portion.

====Private schools====
Saint Stephen Martyr  School:  opened  in 1926 to provide the families of Monterey Park with an opportunity for their children to receive a Catholic School education.  K--Grade 8
[http://stsmc.org/]

Meher Montessori School: preschool, lower and upper elementary classes &lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://mehermontessori.org/pages/info.html |title=info |publisher=Mehermontessori.org |date= |accessdate=2010-08-17}}&lt;/ref&gt;

St Thomas Aquinas School: A Catholic parish school, serving economically and ethnically diverse students in grades Kindergarten through eighth.  Founded in 1963, the Church is in the center of our school both physically and spiritually.  The school is accredited by the Western Association of Schools and Colleges and the Western Catholic Educational Association.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.stacatholicschool.org/information.html |title=Information - St. Thomas Aquinas Catholic School |publisher=Stacatholicschool.org |date= |accessdate=2010-08-17}}&lt;/ref&gt;

New Avenue School
PreKindergarten—Kindergarten through 8th grade. New Avenue school was founded in 1961.
[http://www.elocallink.tv/profiles/ca/alhambra/11/]

Alpha-Shen Preschool and Kindergarten

Esther's Nest Children's School
PreKindergarten—Kindergarten

Graceland Christian Day Care Center
PreKindergarten—Kindergarten

Monterey Park Christian School
PreKindergarten—Kindergarten

===Public library===
The Monterey Park Bruggemeyer Library serves Monterey Park.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;[http://montereyparklibrary.llwip.org/ Welcome!]&quot; Monterey Park Bruggemeyer Library. Retrieved on October 28, 2010.&lt;/ref&gt;

==Notable residents==
* [[Judy Chu]], Congresswoman; former City Councilwoman
*[[Esther Salas]], the first Hispanic woman to serve as a United States magistrate judge in the District of New Jersey, and the first Hispanic woman to be appointed a U.S. District Court judge in New Jersey.&lt;ref name=LocalRoots&gt;Sanabria, Santo. &quot;Local roots&quot;. ''[[The Union City Reporter]]''. July 24, 2011. pages 1 and 12&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[Michael Woo]], former [[Los Angeles City Council]]man (1985–1994); Dean, [[Cal Poly Pomona College of Environmental Design]]

==References==
{{Reflist|2}}

==Further reading==
* Saito, Leland T. ''[http://books.google.com/books?id=pEDlhVFcqh4C&amp;source=gbs_navlinks_s Race and Politics: Asian Americans, Latinos, and Whites in a Los Angeles Suburb]''. ''[[University of Illinois Press]]'', 1980. ISBN 0252067207, 9780252067204.

==External links==
{{Commons category}}
{{Portal|Los Angeles|Greater Los Angeles|Southern California}}
*[http://ci.monterey-park.ca.us/ City of Monterey Park]
*[http://ci.monterey-park.ca.us/Library/ Monterey Park Bruggemeyer Library]
*[http://www.montereyparkchamber.org/ Monterey Park Chamber of Commerce]
*[http://www.temple.edu/tempress/titles/997_reg_print.html The First Suburban Chinatown]
*[http://www.temple.edu/tempress/asam_history.html/ Asian American History and Culture, edited by Sucheng Chan, David Palumbo-Liu, Michael Omi, K. Scott Wong, and Linda Trinh Võ.]

{{Cities of Los Angeles County, California}}
{{Greater Los Angeles Area}}

[[Category:Communities in the San Gabriel Valley]]
[[Category:Cities in Los Angeles County, California]]
[[Category:Populated places in the United States with Asian American majority populations]]
[[Category:Incorporated cities and towns in California]]

[[ar:مونتيري بارك، لوس أنجليس، كاليفورنيا]]
[[bg:Монтерей Парк]]
[[ca:Monterey Park]]
[[de:Monterey Park]]
[[es:Monterey Park (California)]]
[[fr:Monterey Park]]
[[it:Monterey Park]]
[[sw:Monterey Park, California]]
[[ht:Monterey Park, Kalifòni]]
[[nl:Monterey Park]]
[[pt:Monterey Park]]
[[tl:Monterey Park, California]]
[[vi:Monterey Park, California]]
[[vo:Monterey Park]]
[[zh:蒙特利公园]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
