<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="107655" ns="0" title="Malibu, California"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Redirect|Malibu Beach|the beach in Boston, Massachusetts|Savin Hill}}
{{Redirect|Malibu, CA|the U.S. [[broadcast syndication|syndicated]] television series than ran from 1998-2000|Malibu, CA (TV series)}}
{{Refimprove|date=March 2011}}
{{Infobox settlement
|name            = Malibu
|other_name               =
|nickname                 = The BU{{Citation needed|date=March 2011}}
|motto                    =
|image_skyline            = MalibuAir.jpg
|imagesize                =
|image_caption            = Aerial view of Downtown Malibu and surrounding neighorhoods
|image_flag               =
|flag_size                =
|image_seal               = Seal_malibu_ca.png
|seal_size                = 94px
|image_shield             =
|shield_size              =
|image_blank_emblem       =
|blank_emblem_size        =
|image_map                = LA County Incorporated Areas Malibu highlighted.svg
|mapsize                  = 250x200px
|map_caption              = Location of Malibu in [[Los Angeles County, California|Los Angeles County]], [[California]]
|image_map1               =
|mapsize1                 =
|map_caption1             =
|pushpin_map              = 
|pushpin_map_caption      = 
|subdivision_type         = [[List of countries|Country]]
|subdivision_name         = [[United States]]
|subdivision_type1        = [[Political divisions of the United States|State]]
|subdivision_name1        = [[California]]
|subdivision_type2        = [[List of counties in California|County]]
|subdivision_name2        = [[Los Angeles County, California|Los Angeles]]
|subdivision_type3        =
|subdivision_name3        =
|subdivision_type4        =
|subdivision_name4        =
|government_type          =
|leader_title             = [[Mayor]]
|leader_name              = John Sibert&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url = http://www.ci.malibu.ca.us/index.cfm/fuseaction/detail/navid/14/cid/12061/ | title = John Sibert - Mayor | publisher = City of Malibu | location = Malibu, California | accessdate = 2011-03-28}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|leader_title1            = &lt;!-- for places with, say, both a mayor and a city manager --&gt;
|leader_name1             =
|established_title        = &lt;!-- Settled --&gt;
|established_date         =
|established_title2       = &lt;!-- Incorporated (town) --&gt;
|established_date2        =
|established_title3       = Incorporated (city)
|established_date3        = {{start date|1991|3|28}}&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url = http://www.cacities.org/resource_files/20457.IncorpDateLO.doc |  title = Incorporation Dates of California Cities | accessdate = 2007-01-18}}&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;!-- Area------------------&gt;
|area_magnitude           =
| unit_pref               =US
| area_footnotes          = &lt;ref&gt;[http://www.census.gov/geo/www/gazetteer/files/Gaz_places_national.txt U.S. Census]&lt;/ref&gt;
| area_total_sq_mi        = 19.828
| area_land_sq_mi         = 19.785
| area_water_sq_mi        = 0.043
| area_total_km2          = 51.354
| area_land_km2           = 51.242
| area_water_km2          = 0.113
| area_water_percent      = 0.22
| area_note               = 
|area_urban_km2           =
|area_urban_sq_mi         =
|area_metro_km2           =
|area_metro_sq_mi         =
|population_as_of         = 2010
|population_note          =
|population_footnotes     =&lt;ref&gt;
|settlement_type          = [[City]]
|population_total         = 12645
|population_density_km2   = auto
|population_density_sq_mi = auto
|population_metro         =
|population_density_metro_km2     =
|population_density_metro_sq_mi   =
|population_urban                 =
|population_density_urban_km2     =
|population_density_urban_sq_mi   =
|timezone                 = [[Pacific Time Zone|PST]]
|utc_offset               = -8
|timezone_DST             = PDT
|utc_offset_DST           = -7
|coordinates_display      = inline,title
|coordinates_type         = region:US-CA_type:city_dim:31200_source:GoogleEarth-eyeball
|coordinates_format       =
&lt;!-- city hall coordinates: 34.037065,-118.688988 --&gt;
|latd = 34.03
|longd = -118.75
|elevation_m              = 32
|elevation_ft             = 105
|postal_code_type         = [[ZIP Code]]
|postal_code              = 90263, 90264, 90265&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url = http://zip4.usps.com/zip4/zcl_1_results.jsp?visited=1&amp;pagenumber=0&amp;state=ca&amp;city=Malibu | title = USPS – ZIP Code Lookup – Find a ZIP+ 4 Code By City Results | accessdate = 2007-01-18}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|area_code                = [[Area code 310|310]]
|website                  = [http://www.ci.malibu.ca.us/ http://www.ci.malibu.ca.us/ City of Malibu]
|blank_name               = [[Federal Information Processing Standard|FIPS code]]
|blank_info               = 06-45246
|blank1_name              = [[Geographic Names Information System|GNIS]] feature ID
|blank1_info              = 1668257
|footnotes                =
}}&lt;!-- Infobox ends --&gt;
[[Image:HALLOWEENDAWN CA18.jpg|thumb|260px|Dawn in the [[Santa Monica Mountains]].]]
'''Malibu''' ({{IPA-en|ˈmælɨbuː|pron}}) is an affluent, beachfront city in northwestern [[Los Angeles County, California|Los Angeles County]], [[California]], [[United States]]. As of the 2010 census, the city population was 12,645. Malibu consists of a {{convert|21|mi|km|sing=on}}&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.ci.malibu.ca.us/index.cfm?fuseaction=nav&amp;navid=3 Length of City of Malibu (Malibu before incorporation was {{convert|27|mi|km}}] from the City of Malibu's website&lt;/ref&gt; strip of prime Pacific coastline. The community is famous for its warm, sandy beaches, and for being the home of many Hollywood movie stars and others associated with the entertainment industry. Signs around the city proclaim &quot;27 miles of scenic beauty&quot;, referring to Malibu's original length of {{convert|27|mi|km}} before the city was incorporated in 1991.

Most Malibu residents live within a few hundred yards of [[Pacific Coast Highway (California)|Pacific Coast Highway]] ([[California State Route 1|State Route 1]]), which traverses the city, with some residents living up to a mile away from the beach up narrow canyons, and many more residents of the unincorporated canyon areas identifying Malibu as their hometown.  The city is also bounded (more or less) by [[Topanga, California|Topanga Canyon]] to the East, the [[Santa Monica Mountains]] consisting of [[Agoura Hills]], [[Calabasas]], and [[Woodland Hills]] to the North, the [[Pacific Ocean]] to the South, and [[Ventura County, California|Ventura County]] to the West.

Malibu's beaches include Surfrider Beach, [[Zuma Beach]], Malibu State Beach, Topanga State Beach, Point Dume State Beach and Dan Blocker Beach; its local parks include Malibu Bluffs Park&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.ci.malibu.ca.us/index.cfm?fuseaction=detailgroup&amp;navid=174&amp;cid=3826 Malibu Bluffs Park (local)] from the City of Malibu's website&lt;/ref&gt; (formerly Malibu Bluffs State Park), Trancas Canyon Park, Las Flores Creek Park, and Legacy Park,&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.malibulegacy.org/ Malibu Legacy Park (local)]&lt;/ref&gt; with neighboring parks [[Malibu Creek State Park]], [[Leo Carrillo State Park|Leo Carrillo State Beach and Park]],&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.parks.ca.gov/?page_id=616 Leo Carrillo SB]&lt;/ref&gt; [[Point Mugu State Park]],&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.parks.ca.gov/default.asp?page_id=630 Pt. Mugu SP]&lt;/ref&gt; and the [[Santa Monica Mountains National Recreation Area]], and neighboring state beach Robert H. Meyer Memorial State Beach,&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.parks.ca.gov/default.asp?page_id=633 Robert H. Meyer Memorial SB]&lt;/ref&gt; that was once part of Old Malibu (before Malibu became a city), and better known as pristine beaches, El Pescador, La Piedra and El Matador.

==History==
Malibu was originally settled by the [[Chumash (tribe)|Chumash]], [[Native Americans in the United States|Native Americans]] whose territory extended loosely from the [[San Joaquin Valley]] to [[San Luis Obispo]] to Malibu, as well as several islands off the southern coast of California. They named it &quot;''Humaliwo''&quot;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.parks.ca.gov/default.asp?page_id=24435 Humaliwo: An Ethnographic Overview of the Chumas in Malibu]&lt;/ref&gt; or &quot;the surf sounds loudly.&quot; The city's name derives from this, as the &quot;Hu&quot; syllable is not stressed.

[[Spain|Spanish]] explorer [[Juan Cabrillo]] is believed to have moored at Malibu Lagoon, at the mouth of Malibu Creek, to obtain fresh water in 1542. The Spanish presence returned with the [[Spanish Missions of California|California mission]] system, and the area was part of [[Rancho Topanga Malibu Sequit]] — a {{convert|13000|acre|km2|sing=on}} [[land grant]] — in 1802. That ranch passed intact to [[Frederick Hastings Rindge]] in 1891. He and his widow, Rhoda May Rindge, guarded their privacy zealously by hiring guards to evict all trespassers and fighting a lengthy court battle to prevent the building of a [[Southern Pacific Railroad|Southern Pacific]] railroad line. Few roads even entered the area before 1929, when the state won another court case and built what is now known as the [[Pacific Coast Highway (California)|Pacific Coast Highway]]. By then May Rindge was forced to subdivide her property and begin selling and leasing lots. The Rindge house, known as the [[Adamson House]]&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.parks.ca.gov/default.asp?page_id=672 Adamson House]&lt;/ref&gt; (a [[National Register of Historic Places]] site and [[California Historical Landmark]]), is now part of Malibu Creek State Park and is situated between [[Malibu Lagoon State Beach]]&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.parks.ca.gov/default.asp?page_id=835 Malibu Lagoon State Beach]&lt;/ref&gt; and Surfrider Beach, beside the Malibu Pier&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.parks.ca.gov/default.asp?page_id=24409 Malibu Pier]&lt;/ref&gt; that was originally built for the family yacht.

In 1926, in an effort to avoid selling land to stave off insolvency, Rhoda May Rindge created a small ceramic tile factory. At its height, Malibu Potteries employed over 100 workers, and produced decorative tiles which furnish many [[Los Angeles, California|Los Angeles]]-area public buildings and [[Beverly Hills]] residences. The factory, located one-half mile east of the pier, was ravaged by a fire in 1931. Although the factory partially reopened in 1932, it could not recover from the effects of the [[Great Depression]] and a steep downturn in Southern California construction projects. A distinct hybrid of [[Moorish]] and [[Arts and crafts]] designs, Malibu tile is considered highly collectible. Fine examples of the tiles may be seen at the Adamson House and Serra Retreat, a fifty-room mansion that was started in the 1920s as the main Rindge home on a hill overlooking the lagoon. The unfinished building was sold to the [[Franciscan]] Order in 1942&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.serraretreat.com/about/index.htm Rindge House sold to Franciscans] from serraretreat.com&lt;/ref&gt; and is operated as a [[Retreat (spiritual)|retreat]] facility,&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.serraretreat.com/ Serra Retreat]&lt;/ref&gt; Serra Retreat. It burned in the 1970 fire and was rebuilt using many of the original tiles.

'''Malibu Colony''' was one of the first areas inhabited after Malibu was opened to the public in 1929 and it is one of Malibu's most famous districts.&lt;ref&gt;[http://malibuca.org/ MalibuCa.org&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;  It is located south of Malibu Road and the Pacific Coast Highway, west of Malibu Lagoon State Beach, and east of Malibu Bluffs Park (formerly a state park). Initially May Rindge kept control of Malibu Beach, allowing a few wealthy Hollywood stars to build vacation homes. Nearly a decade later, money woes forced Rindge to sell the land, and the Colony was born. Long known as a popular private enclave for wealthy celebrities,&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.seeing-stars.com/Live/Malibu.shtml Celebrities living in Malibu Colony] from seeing-stars.com&lt;/ref&gt; the Malibu Colony today is a [[gated community]], with multi-million dollar homes on small lots. The Colony commands breathtaking views of the Pacific Ocean, affording a spectacular coastline view stretching from [[Santa Monica]] to [[Rancho Palos Verdes]] to the south (known locally as the ''Queen's Necklace''&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.trails.com/rentals/propertyna.asp?vacation=01044_Thousand+Oaks_California Malibu to RPV: Queen's Necklace] from trails.com&lt;/ref&gt;) and the bluffs of [[Point Dume]] to the north.

'''High technology in Malibu''': the first working model of a [[laser]] was demonstrated by Dr. Theodore Maiman in 1960 in Malibu at then [[Hughes Research Laboratories|Hughes Research Laboratory]]&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.seattlepi.com/local/6420AP_WA_Obit_Maiman.html Dr. Maiman's laser, the world's first] from seattlepi.nwsource.com&lt;/ref&gt; (now known as HRL Laboratories LLC). In the 1990s HRL Laboratories developed the FastScat computer code,&lt;ref&gt;[http://hrl.com/media/anlRprts/05_AR.pdf HRL's FastScat] from the HRL Laboratories website&lt;/ref&gt; for frequency domain algorithms and implementation, recognized as perhaps the most accurate code in the world for radar cross-section calculations.{{Citation needed|date=July 2009}} [[TRW]] built a laboratory in Solstice Canyon without any structural steel to test magnetic detectors for satellites and medical devices.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title=Historic Buildings in Solstice Canyon Are Burned: Park Is Closed: Matthew Keller House and TRW Aerospace Research Buildings Destroyed by Corral Fire|title=Malibu Surfside News|first= ANNE |last=SOBLE|date=November 29, 2007|url=http://www.malibusurfsidenews.com/stories/200711/20071129001.html|accessdate=December 1, 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt;

'''Incorporation''': in 1991 most of the old Malibu land grant was incorporated as a city to allow local control of the area (as cities, unlike townships, are not subject to the same level of county government oversight). Prior to achieving municipal status, the local residents had fought several county-proposed developments, including an offshore [[freeway]], a [[nuclear power plant]], and several plans to replace septic tanks with [[sanitary sewer|sewer]] lines. The incorporation drive gained impetus in 1986, when the Los Angeles County Board of Supervisors approved plans for a regional sewer that would have been large enough to serve 400,000 people in the western Santa Monica Mountains. Residents were incensed that they would be assessed taxes and fees to pay for the oversized sewer project, and feared that the already-capacity Pacific Coast Highway would need to be widened into a freeway to accommodate growth that they did not want. The Supervisors fought the incorporation drive and prevented the residents from voting, a decision that was overturned in courts.

The city councils that were elected in the 1990s were unable to write a Local Coastal Plan (LCP) that preserved enough public access to satisfy the California Coastal Commission, as required by the California Coastal Act. The state Legislature eventually passed a Malibu-specific law that allowed the Coastal Commission to write an LCP for Malibu, thus neutering the city's ability to control many aspects of land use. Because of the failure to adequately address sewage disposal problems in the heart of the city, the local water board ordered Malibu in November 2009 to build a sewage plant for the Civic Center area. The city council has objected to that solution.
[[Image:Malibupacificcoasthighway.jpg|thumb|260px|left|The Pacific Coast Highway (PCH) in central Malibu]]

== Geography ==
[[Image:Paradise cove.JPG|thumb|250px|The Paradise Cove pier in Malibu]]
Malibu is located at {{Coord|34|1|50|N|118|46|43|W|region:US-CA_type:landmark_source:GNIS|name=Malibu, California (GNIS point)}} (34.030450, −118.778612).{{GR|1}}

According to the [[United States Census Bureau]], the city has a total area of {{convert|19.8|sqmi|km2}}, over 99% of it land.

Malibu's dry brush and steep clay slopes make it susceptible to fires, floods, and mudslides. Poor grading practices and over-irrigation or leaking pipes exacerbate the tendency for landslides.{{Citation needed|date=July 2009}}

Carbon Beach, Paradise Cove, Escondido Beach, Surfrider Beach, Broad Beach, Pirate's Cove, Westward Beach, Zuma Beach, and Trancas are places along the coast in Malibu. Point Dume forms the northern end of the [[Santa Monica Bay]], and Point Dume Headlands Park affords a vista of stretching to the [[Palos Verdes Peninsula]] and [[Santa Catalina Island, California|Santa Catalina Island]]. Directly below the park, on the western side of the point, is Pirates Cove, named for rum-runners during [[Prohibition in the United States|Prohibition]] who liked the secluded beach for offloading their cargo.{{Citation needed|date=July 2009}}  Because of its relative seclusion, Pirate's Cove was previously used as a [[nude beach]], but because nudity is now illegal on all [[Los Angeles County]] beaches, nude sunbathers are subject to fines and/or arrest. On the eastern side of the point is &quot;Little Dume&quot;, a surf spot which is accessible only by an unmarked trail below Wildlife Drive which has a locked gate.{{Citation needed|date=July 2009}}  Surfers often paddle out from Paradise Cove to the area when the waves are breaking.

Like all California beaches, Malibu beaches are technically public land below the mean high tide line. Many large public beaches (Zuma Beach, Surfrider Beach) are easy to access, but such access is sometimes limited in some of the smaller and more remote beaches. Some Malibu beaches are private, such as Paradise Cove, which charges an entrance fee to keep the crowds at bay.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.ruba.com/place/Paradise_Cove_Beach-anon Review of Paradise Cove] Retrieved November 5, 2009. {{Dead link|date=October 2010|bot=H3llBot}}&lt;/ref&gt; Although access to most all Malibu beaches can be obtained after a bit of a walk, the issue of expanded public access is continuously addressed and debated by the City. Many Malibu homeowners{{Who|date=July 2009}} favor limited public access expansions to some beaches, claiming that many visitors are less likely than residents to respect the beaches or private property.

==Natural disasters==
[[Image:Malibu Bluffs State Park IMG 0986 060826 140616.jpg|thumb|250px|View from Malibu Bluffs State Park. Camera facing West toward Point Dume.]]
Malibu lies on the fringe of an extensive [[chaparral]] wilderness area, the Santa Monica Mountains National Recreation Area.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.nps.gov/samo Santa Monica Mountains National Recreation Area] from the [[National Park Service]] website&lt;/ref&gt; Various environmental elements collectively create a recipe for natural disasters: the mountainous and geologically unstable terrain; seasonal rainstorms that result in dense vegetation growth; seasonal dry [[Santa Ana winds]]; and a naturally dry topography and climate.

===Wildfire===
{{See also|California wildfires of October 2007}}

Malibu has seen dozens of wildfire over the course of its history, before and after incorporation.
Notably:&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.malibutimes.com/articles/2007/11/24/news/news2.prt Malibu Times Article]&lt;/ref&gt;

*{{date|1929-10-26}} – Malibu Colony, 13 homes burned.&lt;ref name=&quot;hazards&quot;&gt;[http://www.malibucomplete.com/mc_hazards_fires.php Malibu Fires], MalibuComplete.com&lt;/ref&gt;
*1930 – &quot;Potrero,&quot; Decker Canyon Road Corridor, {{convert|15000|acre|km2}}, accidental blaze caused by walnut pickers in Thousand Oaks area.&lt;ref name=&quot;hazards&quot; /&gt;
*{{date|1935-10-23}} – &quot;Malibu&quot; or &quot;Latigo/Sherwood,&quot; Kanan/Decker Corridor, {{convert|30000|acre|km2}}.&lt;ref name=&quot;hazards&quot; /&gt;
*{{date|1938-11-23}} – &quot;Topanga,&quot; Topanga Canyon, {{convert|14500|acre|km2}}.&lt;ref name=&quot;hazards&quot; /&gt;
*{{date|1943-10-20}} – &quot;Las Flores,&quot; Malibu Canyon, {{convert|5800|acre|km2}}.&lt;ref name=&quot;hazards&quot; /&gt;
*{{date|1943-11-06}} – &quot;Woodland Hills (Las Virgenes),&quot; Kanan/Decker Corridor, {{convert|15000|acre|km2}}.&lt;ref name=&quot;hazards&quot; /&gt;
*{{date|1956-12-26}} – &quot;Newton,&quot; Kanan/Decker Corridor, {{convert|26000|acre|km2}}, 100 homes, one death, Frank Dickover.&lt;ref name=&quot;hazards&quot; /&gt;
*{{date|1958-12-02}} – &quot;Liberty,&quot; Malibu Canyon, {{convert|18000|acre|km2}}, eight firefighters injured, 74 homes destroyed (17 in Corral Canyon).&lt;ref name=&quot;hazards&quot; /&gt;
*{{date|1961-11-06}} – &quot;Topanga,&quot; Topanga Canyon, {{convert|8000|acre|km2}}.&lt;ref name=&quot;hazards&quot; /&gt;
*{{date|1970-09-25}} – &quot;Wright,&quot; Malibu Canyon, {{convert|28000|acre|km2}}, 10 deaths, 403 homes destroyed.&lt;ref name=&quot;la208946&quot;&gt;[http://la.indymedia.org/news/{{date|2007-10-208946}}.php Let Malibu Burn: A political history of the Fire Coast Mike Davis], by repost publish in LA Weekly 1996 Wednesday, Oct. 24, 2007, Los Angeles Independent Media Center&lt;/ref&gt;
*{{date|1973-10-30}} – &quot;Topanga,&quot; Topanga Canyon, {{convert|2800|acre|km2}}.&lt;ref name=&quot;hazards&quot; /&gt;
*{{date|1978-10-23}} – &quot;Kanan,&quot; Kanan/Decker Corridor, {{convert|25000|acre|km2}}, 2 deaths, 230 homes.&lt;ref name=&quot;la208946&quot; /&gt;
*{{date|1982-10-09}} – &quot;Dayton,&quot; Malibu Canyon Corridor, {{convert|44000|acre|km2}}, 15 homes in Paradise Cove destroyed.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.malibucomplete.com/mc_history_dev_1970s-91_disasters.php MALIBU HISTORY: 1970 TO CITYHOOD IN 1991&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;
*{{date|1985-10-14}} – &quot;Piuma,&quot; Las Flores area, Topanga Canyon, {{convert|4700|acre|km2}}.&lt;ref name=&quot;hazards&quot; /&gt;
*{{date|1985-10-14}} – &quot;Decker,&quot; Kanan/Decker Corridor, {{convert|6600|acre|km2}}. Both arson-caused; six homes destroyed; $1 million damage.&lt;ref name=&quot;hazards&quot; /&gt;

Malibu incorporated as a city.

*{{date|1993-11-02}} – &quot;Old Topanga / North Malibu.&quot;  In 1993, from November 2 to 11, Malibu experienced one of the largest fires in its history, which burned more than {{convert|16516|acre|km2|0}}.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.lafire.com/famous_fires/931102_OldTopangaFire/110293_official_report_old_topanga_inci.htm 1993 Fire], LACFD official report&lt;/ref&gt; The 1993 fire storm was composed of two separate fires, one ravaging most of central Malibu/Old Topanga, and another, larger fire affecting areas north of Encinal Canyon. Three lives were lost and 739 homes destroyed in the central Malibu/Old Topanga blaze. {{convert|18949|acre|km2|0}} were torched in the north Malibu fire, with zero lives taken and few homes lost in the less densely populated region. Los Angeles County Fire Department officials announced suspicions that the fire was started by arson.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.coastal.ca.gov/fire/firerept.html Malibu: Public Safety] from coastal.ca.gov&lt;/ref&gt; The fire and widespread damage to properties and infrastructure resulted in the City of Malibu adopting the strictest fire codes in the country.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.npr.org/templates/story/story.php?storyId=1145994 Malibu Lessons] from [[National Public Radio]]&lt;/ref&gt;
*{{date|1996-10-28}} – &quot;Calabasas,&quot; Malibu Canyon Corridor, Brush fire ignited by arcing power line, {{convert|13000|acre|km2}}; 10 houses destroyed.&lt;ref name=&quot;hazards&quot; /&gt;
*{{date|2003-01-06}} – &quot;Trancas&quot;, Trancas Canyon, {{convert|759|acre|km2}}.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.malibutimes.com/articles/{{date|2003-01-10}}/news/export4751.txt]&lt;/ref&gt;
*{{date|2007-01-08}} – On January 8, 2007 at approximately 5:00 p.m. a fire started in the vicinity of Bluffs Park, south of [[Pacific Coast Highway (California)|Pacific Coast Highway]] in Malibu. The fire hit near the Colony area, burning down four houses on Malibu Road, including the oceanfront home of ''[[Step by Step (TV series)|Step By Step]]'' star [[Suzanne Somers]]. [[Los Angeles County Fire Department]] officials announced that a discarded cigarette stub started the blaze.
*{{date|2007-10-21}} – On October 21, 2007 at approximately 5:00 a.m. a fire started off of Malibu Canyon Road. As of 1:00pm there were 500+ personnel on scene. {{convert|1200|acre|km2}} burned with no containment. 200+ homes have been evacuated. Five homes confirmed to have been destroyed, with at least nine others damaged. Two commercial structures were completely destroyed.  [[Castle Kashan]] and the Malibu Presbyterian Church have both been destroyed. Los Angeles County Fire Department officials announced that the fire is still under investigation.
*{{date|2007-11-24}} – &quot;Corral.&quot;  On November 24, 2007, the Corral Fire destroyed 53 homes, damaged 35, and burned over {{convert|4720|acre|km2}}, forcing as many as 14,000 people to evacuate. Damages from the fire were expected to reach more than $100 million. The blaze originated at the top of Corral Canyon, where a group of young people who were in closed parkland after dusk had started a bonfire despite the presence of high Santa Ana winds.  The individuals responsible for starting the fire were later identified, and are the subject of ongoing civil and criminal litigation.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.malibutimes.com/articles/{{date|2008-08-28}}/news/news5.txt&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://news.monstersandcritics.com/usa/news/article_1376494.php/Malibu_Thanksgiving_weekend_blaze_claims_53_homes Malibu gossip] from monstersandcritics.com&lt;/ref&gt;

===Mudslides===
One of the most problematic side-effects of the fires that periodically rage through Malibu is the destruction of vegetation, which normally provides some degree of topographical stability to the loosely packed shale and sandstone hills during periods of heavy precipitation. Rainstorms following large wildfires can thus cause a phenomenon known as mudslides, in which water-saturated earth and rock moves quickly down mountainsides, or entire slices of mountainside abruptly detach and fall downward.

After the 1993 wildfire stripped the surrounding mountains of their earth-hugging [[chaparral]], torrential rainstorms in early 1994 caused a massive mudslide near Las Flores Canyon that closed down the main coastal transport artery, Pacific Coast Highway, for months. Thousands of tons of mud, rocks, and water rained down on the Pacific Coast Highway like it was a sluicebox. The destruction to property and infrastructure was exacerbated by the narrow constriction of the road at that point, with beachside houses buttressing the highway with little or no frontage land acting as a buffer to the mudslide.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.colorado.edu/hazards/research/qr/qr107.html Mudslides in Malibu, etc.]&lt;/ref&gt;  Another large mudslide occurred on Malibu Canyon Road, between the Pepperdine University campus and HRL Laboratories LLC, closing down Malibu Canyon for two months.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.wrh.noaa.gov/sgx/document/weatherhistory.pdf Malibu Mudslides] from noaa.gov&lt;/ref&gt;  Yet another behemoth slide occurred on another main canyon road, Kanan-Dume Road about one mile (1.6&amp;nbsp;km) up the canyon from the Pacific Coast Highway. This last road closure lasted over a period of many months, with Kanan finally fixed by the California Department of Transportation (Cal-Trans)&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.dot.ca.gov/ Cal-Trans official web site]&lt;/ref&gt; over a year after the road collapse.

Mudslides can and do happen at any time in Malibu, whether or not there has been a recent fire or rainstorm. Pacific Coast Highway, Kanan-Dume Road, and Malibu Canyon road (as well as many other local roads) have all been subject to many subsequent mudslide-related closures.  During any period of prolonged or intense rain, Caltrans snowplows will patrol most canyon roads in the area, clearing mud, rocks, and other fallen debris from the roadways.  Such efforts keep most roads passable, but it is nevertheless common for one or more of the major avenues in and out of Malibu to be temporarily shut down during the rainy season.

===Storms===
Malibu is periodically subjected to intense coastal storms, although its Mediterranean climate means that such occurrences are relatively infrequent.

Friday, January 25, 2008, during a storm which was unusually large for the Southern California area, a tornado came ashore and struck a naval base's hangar, ripping off the roof. It was the first tornado to strike Malibu's shoreline in recorded history.{{Citation needed|date=July 2009}}

===Earthquakes===
Malibu lies fairly close to the [[San Andreas Fault]], and is subject to the same regional geological unrest as the rest of the Los Angeles Basin.

==Demographics==
===2010===
The [[2010 United States Census]]&lt;ref&gt;{{USCensus-2010CA}}&lt;/ref&gt; reported that Malibu had a population of 12,645. The [[population density]] was 637.7 people per square mile (246.2/km²). The racial makeup of Malibu was 11,565 (91.5%) [[White (U.S. Census)|White]], 148 (1.2%) [[African American (U.S. Census)|African American]], 20 (0.2%) [[Native American (U.S. Census)|Native American]], 328 (2.6%) [[Asian (U.S. Census)|Asian]], 15 (0.1%) [[Pacific Islander (U.S. Census)|Pacific Islander]], 182 (1.4%) from [[Race (United States Census)|other races]], and 387 (3.1%) from two or more races.  [[Hispanic (U.S. Census)|Hispanic]] or [[Latino (U.S. Census)|Latino]] of any race were 769 persons (6.1%). 

The Census reported that 12,504 people (98.9% of the population) lived in households, 126 (1.0%) lived in non-institutionalized group quarters, and 15 (0.1%) were institutionalized.  

There were 5,267 households, out of which 1,379 (26.2%) had children under the age of 18 living in them, 2,571 (48.8%) were [[marriage|opposite-sex married couples]] living together, 403 (7.7%) had a female householder with no husband present, 222 (4.2%) had a male householder with no wife present.  There were 269 (5.1%) [[POSSLQ|unmarried opposite-sex partnerships]], and 49 (0.9%) [[same-sex partnerships|same-sex married couples or partnerships]]. 1,498 households (28.4%) were made up of individuals and 501 (9.5%) had someone living alone who was 65 years of age or older. The average household size was 2.37.  There were 3,196 [[family (U.S. Census)|families]] (60.7% of all households); the average family size was 2.87.

The population was spread out with 2,366 people (18.7%) under the age of 18, 1,060 people (8.4%) aged 18 to 24, 2,291 people (18.1%) aged 25 to 44, 4,606 people (36.4%) aged 45 to 64, and 2,322 people (18.4%) who were 65 years of age or older.  The median age was 47.8 years. For every 100 females there were 100.6 males.  For every 100 females age 18 and over, there were 97.0 males.

There were 6,864 housing units at an average density of 346.2 per square mile (133.7/km²), of which 3,716 (70.6%) were owner-occupied, and 1,551 (29.4%) were occupied by renters. The homeowner vacancy rate was 2.8%; the rental vacancy rate was 11.9%.  9,141 people (72.3% of the population) lived in owner-occupied housing units and 3,363 people (26.6%) lived in rental housing units.

===2000===
As of the [[census]]{{GR|2}} of 2000,&lt;ref&gt;[http://factfinder.census.gov/servlet/SAFFFacts?_event=Search&amp;geo_id=&amp;_geoContext=&amp;_street=&amp;_county=&amp;_cityTown=Malibu%20city&amp;_state=04000US06&amp;_zip=&amp;_lang=en&amp;_sse=on&amp;pctxt=fph&amp;pgsl=010&amp;show_2003_tab=&amp;redirect=Y U.S. Census, Malibu, CA] from the U.S. Census website&lt;/ref&gt; there were 12,575 people, 5,137 households, and 3,164 families residing in the city. The [[population density]] was 632.9 inhabitants per square mile (244.4/km²). There were 6,126 housing units at an average density of 308.3 per square mile (119.0/km²). The racial makeup of the city was 91.91% [[White (U.S. Census)|White]],  8.49% [[Asian (U.S. Census)|Asian]], 0.90% [[African American (U.S. Census)|African American]], 0.21% [[Native American (U.S. Census)|Native American]], 0.10% [[Pacific Islander (U.S. Census)|Pacific Islander]], 1.67% from [[Race (United States Census)|other races]], and 2.72% from two or more races. [[Hispanic (U.S. Census)|Hispanic]] or [[Latino (U.S. Census)|Latino]] of any race were 1.48% of the population.

There were 5,137 households out of which 25.3% had children under the age of 18 living with them, 51.5% were [[Marriage|married couples]] living together, 6.7% had a female householder with no husband present, and 38.4% were non-families. 27.3% of all households were made up of individuals and 6.7% had someone living alone who was 65 years of age or older. The average household size was 2.39 and the average family size was 2.86.

The age distribution was 19.6% under the age of 18, 7.9% from 18 to 24, 26.4% from 25 to 44, 32.0% from 45 to 64, and 14.0% who were 65 years of age or older. The median age was 43 years. For every 100 females there were 97.8 males. For every 100 females age 18 and over, there were 95.6 males.

The median income for a household in the city was $102,031, and the median income for a family was $123,293. Males had a median income of $100,000+ versus $46,919 for females. The [[per capita income]] for the city was $74,336. About 3.2% of families and 7.6% of the population were below the [[poverty line]], including 6.8% of those under age 18 and 1.1% of those age 65 or over.

==Government and infrastructure==
===Local government===
Malibu is a general law city governed with a five-member City Council including the mayor and mayor pro tem. The City Council hires a city manager to carry out policies and serve as executive officer. Every even-numbered year either two or three members are elected by the people to serve a four-year term. Usually, the City Council meets in April and chooses one of its members as mayor and one as mayor-pro-tem. In 2006, this pattern was deviated from when the council decided to have a cycle of three mayors and mayor pro-tems in the coming two years.

Fire protection is served by the [[Los Angeles County Fire Department]].

The [[Los Angeles County Sheriff's Department]] (LASD) operates the Malibu/Lost Hills Station in [[Calabasas, California|Calabasas]], serving Malibu under contract with the City.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;[http://www.lasd.org/stations/for1/malibu_lhill/index.html Malibu/Lost Hills Station].&quot; [[Los Angeles County Sheriff's Department]]. Retrieved on January 21, 2010.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;&quot;[http://factfinder.census.gov/servlet/MapItDrawServlet?geo_id=16000US0609598&amp;_bucket_id=50&amp;tree_id=420&amp;context=saff&amp;_lang=en&amp;_sse=on Calabasas city, California].&quot; [[U.S. Census Bureau]]. Retrieved on January 21, 2010.&lt;/ref&gt;

===County, state, and federal representation===
In the [[California State Legislature|state legislature]] Malibu is located in the 23rd [[California State Senate|Senate]] District, represented by Democrat [[Fran Pavley]], and in the 41st [[California State Assembly|Assembly]] District, represented by Democrat [[Julia Brownley]]. Federally, Malibu is located in [[California's 30th congressional district]], which has a [[Cook Partisan Voting Index|Cook PVI]] of D +20&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | title = Will Gerrymandered Districts Stem the Wave of Voter Unrest? | publisher = Campaign Legal Center Blog | url=http://www.clcblog.org/blog_item-85.html | accessdate = 2008-02-10}}&lt;/ref&gt; and is represented by Democrat [[Henry Waxman]].

Malibu residents tend to be [[politics|politically]] [[Left-wing politics|left of center]], like much of [[Los Angeles County, California|Los Angeles County]].{{Citation needed|date=July 2009}}  60% of Malibu voters chose presidential candidate [[John Kerry]] in the [[United States presidential election, 2004|2004 election]], compared to 39% for incumbent President [[George W. Bush]].

The [[Los Angeles County Department of Health Services]] SPA 5 West Area Health Office serves Malibu.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;[http://publichealth.lacounty.gov/phcommon/public/aboutus/aboutdisplay.cfm?ou=ph&amp;prog=chs&amp;unit=spa5 About Us].&quot; [[Los Angeles County Department of Health Services]]. Retrieved on March 18, 2010.&lt;/ref&gt; The department operates the Simms/Mann Health and Wellness Center in [[Santa Monica, California|Santa Monica]], serving Malibu.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;[http://publichealth.lacounty.gov/phn/docs/HealthCenter/santamonica.pdf Simms/Mann Health and Wellness Center].&quot; [[Los Angeles County Department of Health Services]]. Retrieved on March 17, 2010.&lt;/ref&gt;

The [[United States Postal Service]] operates the Malibu Post Office at 23838 Pacific Coast Highway,&lt;ref&gt;&quot;[http://usps.whitepages.com/service/post_office/7368?p=1&amp;s=CA&amp;service_name=post_office&amp;z=Malibu Post Office Location – MALIBU].&quot; ''[[United States Postal Service]]''. Retrieved on December 6, 2008.&lt;/ref&gt; the Colony Annex at 23648 Pacific Coast Highway, adjacent to the Malibu Post Office,&lt;ref&gt;&quot;[http://usps.whitepages.com/service/post_office/56662?p=1&amp;s=CA&amp;service_name=post_office&amp;z=Malibu Post Office Location – COLONY ANNEX].&quot; ''[[United States Postal Service]]''. Retrieved on December 6, 2008.&lt;/ref&gt; and the La Costa Malibu Post Office at 21229 Pacific Coast Highway.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;[http://usps.whitepages.com/service/post_office/67263?p=1&amp;s=CA&amp;service_name=post_office&amp;z=Malibu Post Office Location – LA COSTA MALIBU].&quot; ''[[United States Postal Service]]''. Retrieved on December 6, 2008.&lt;/ref&gt;

== Education ==
===Schools===
The [[Santa Monica-Malibu Unified School District]] serves Malibu with three elementary schools: [[John L. Webster Elementary School]] (grades K-5, located in central Malibu), [[Juan Cabrillo Elementary School]] (grades K-5, located in northwestern Malibu's Malibu Park district), and [[Point Dume Elementary School]] (grades K-5, located in northwestern Malibu's Pt. Dume district).

Private schools include: Calmont,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
|url=http://www.calmontschool.org/
|title=Calmont School for preschool through seventh grade
|publisher=CalmontSchool.org
|archiveurl=http://replay.web.archive.org/19991014015838/http://www.calmontschool.org/
|archivedate=14 October 1999
|accessdate=2011-05-07
|deadurl=no}}&lt;/ref&gt; Our Lady Of Malibu (Catholic),&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
|url=http://www.olmalibu.org/
|title=Our Lady of Malibu
|publisher=Our Lady of Malibu
|accessdate=2011-05-07}}&lt;/ref&gt; Colin McEwen High School, New Roads,&lt;ref&gt;[{{cite web
|url=http://www.newroads.org/
|title=New Roads School
|publisher=New Roads School
|accessdate=2011-05-07}}]&lt;/ref&gt; and St. Aidan's School.

[[Malibu High School]] (MHS) provides secondary public education for both middle school (grades 6–8) and high school (grades 9–12). MHS is located in the northwestern region of Malibu.

[[Pepperdine University]], a private college affiliated with the [[Churches of Christ|Church of Christ]], which is located in central Malibu, north of the Malibu Colony at the intersection of the Pacific Coast Highway and Malibu Canyon Road. Malibu is also served by [[Santa Monica College]], a [[community college]] in the neighboring city of [[Santa Monica]] to the south.

===Library===
Malibu Public Library, a {{convert|16530|sqft|sqm}} branch of the [[County of Los Angeles Public Library]], is in the Malibu Civic Center Complex. The branch has an adult reading area, a children's reading area, a 125 person meeting room, and free parking. The library opened in 1970. Prior to 1970 residents were served by a bookmobile.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;[http://www.colapublib.org/libs/malibu/ Maliby Library].&quot; [[County of Los Angeles Public Library]]. Retrieved on March 17, 2010.&lt;/ref&gt;

The Library is currently undergoing an extensive renovation, for the duration of which the library staff and a subset of its collections have been temporarily relocated to a small building on the opposite side of the Civic Center Complex from the main Library building.

==Arts and culture==
[[Getty Villa]], an art museum that is part of the [[J. Paul Getty Museum]], is located just outside the city limits in the adjacent [[Pacific Palisades, Los Angeles|Pacific Palisades]] neighborhood of [[Los Angeles]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.getty.edu/visit/events/villa.html Getty Villa.] Retrieved August 28, 2008.&lt;/ref&gt; It is owned and operated by the [[J. Paul Getty Trust]], which also oversees the [[Getty Center]] in West Los Angeles.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.getty.edu/museum/about.html About the J. Paul Getty Museum.] Retrieved August 28, 2008.&lt;/ref&gt; The Museum at the Getty Villa houses Getty's collections of antiquities, sculptures, art pieces and cultural artifacts of ancient Greece, Rome, and Etruria.

The Malibu Art Association, a non-profit organization to foster the arts in Malibu produces shows, demonstrations and workshops for its members, and offers art for public display throughout the community.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.malibuart.org/ Malibu Art Association website]&lt;/ref&gt;

The Malibu Garden Club holds an annual garden tour of private, residential gardens.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.malibugardenclub.com/tour-info.htm Malibu Garden Club, Tour]&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Malibu High School]] offers musicals every spring and instrumental and vocal musical concerts every winter and spring.{{Citation needed|date=July 2009}}

Smothers Theatre of [[Pepperdine University]]'s Theatrical Drama Department offers concerts, plays, musicals, opera, and dance.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.pepperdine.edu/arts/performances/ Smothers Theatre, Pepperdine]&lt;/ref&gt;

== Beaches, parks, and other attractions ==
[[Image:Malibu pier.JPG|thumb|250px|right|The Malibu pier near the famous [[Surfrider Beach]]]]
The beaches of Malibu are well regarded locally, with Zuma Beach drawing over 800,000 visitors over Labor Day Weekend in 2007.{{Citation needed|date=June 2008}} The long waves of Surfrider Beach, adjacent to the Adamson's House and Malibu Lagoon, draw a steady beach and surfer crowd.

California State Parkland carpets the hills behind Malibu, and provides extensive horseback-riding, hiking, running, and mountain-biking options, affording many different views of the [[Santa Monica Mountains]], the curve of the [[Santa Monica Bay]], [[Santa Catalina Island, California|Santa Catalina Island]], and the [[San Fernando Valley]].  There are many points of access to the [[Backbone Trail System]] scattered throughout the local canyons, as well as a variety of smaller, local trail-heads.

[[Pacific Coast Highway (California)|Pacific Coast Highway]] is popular with road cycling enthusiasts for its vistas.  The route also has a reputation for being quite dangerous for cyclists, a fact which inspired the creation of the Dolphin Run, an annual community event commemorating local victims of reckless driving.  The Dolphin Run was held each Autumn from 1990 to 2004.

[http://www.adamsonhouse.org Adamson's House], the unused homesite of the 19th century original owners of Malibu, the Rindge Family, draws some visitors.

In late June 2008, the Malibu Pier reopened after $10 million in renovations.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |last=Groves |first=Martha |title=Reopening marks new chapter in Malibu Pier's history book |date=June 28, 2008 |publisher=[[The Los Angeles Times]] |url=http://www.latimes.com/news/local/la-me-pier29-2008jun29,0,1691155.story |accessdate= 2008-06-29}}&lt;/ref&gt;

There are several shopping centers in the Malibu Civic Center area including the [[Malibu Country Mart]] and the newly opened Malibu Lumberyard, so named for the community Lumberyard that used to occupy that space.  The Malibu Civic Center is well known for being frequented by paparazzi and tourists looking to catch a glimpse of local celebrities.

Chartered buses filled with tourists pass through Malibu infrequently. Unlike Beverly Hills or Hollywood, Malibu's celebrity homes are often in remote locations, inaccessible by bus.{{Citation needed|date=July 2009}}

=== Malibu Bluffs Community Park and Malibu Bluffs Recreation Area ===

The former '''Malibu Bluffs State Park''' ownership changed hands in 2006 after the California Department of Parks and Recreation transferred the park's {{convert|93|acre|m2}} control to the Santa Monica Mountains Conservancy,&lt;ref&gt;[http://smmc.ca.gov/ Santa Monica Mountains Conservancy website]&lt;/ref&gt; They established the '''Malibu Bluffs Recreation Area''', an Open Space Preserve of {{convert|90|acre|m2}} on the bluffs between the Pacific Coast Highway and Malibu Road, directly opposite Pepperdine University and Malibu Canyon Road.  The {{convert|100|ft|m|adj=on}} bluffs rise above Amarillo Beach and Puerco Beach across Malibu Road. Five public stairways (which adjoin private property) lead down to the shoreline from the base of the bluffs. The trails begin from the spacious lawns in Malibu Bluffs Community Park

The Malibu Bluffs Recreation Area surrounds the {{convert|6|acre|m2|adj=on}} '''Malibu Bluffs Community Park''', whose {{convert|10|acre|m2|sing=on}} parcel the Santa Monica Mountains Conservancy sold to the city.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.malibutimes.com/articles/2005/03/04/news/news4.txt MLL's 50th year]  from the ''Malibu Times''&lt;/ref&gt; It consists of the Michael Landon Community Center, baseball diamonds, and soccer fields. Home of the Malibu Little League&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.malibulittleleague.org/ Malibu Little League's official website]&lt;/ref&gt; (MLL), once the largest youth team sports organization in Malibu.  (That honor was wrested in the 1990s by Malibu AYSO,&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.malibuayso.org/ Malibu AYSO official website]&lt;/ref&gt; a youth soccer organization that shares park space (practice fields).)  For over 20 years, the State Parks had tried to kick out Malibu Little League's baseball diamonds and tall baseball fences, with the intention of returning the land to its native wetlands and vegetation.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.malibutimes.com/articles/2006/09/21/news/news3.txt Bluffs Park under local control] from the ''Malibu Times''&lt;/ref&gt;  A rider to a California state law was written specifically in the 1950s to allow baseball, with its attendant field accoutrements, to continue being played in the state park.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.malibutimes.com/articles/2005/01/27/news/news2.txt 20-yr conflict over Malibu Bluffs Park] from the ''Malibu Times''&lt;/ref&gt;  Several generations of Malibuites worked to keep Malibu Bluffs Park for baseball and soccer.

=== Malibu Legacy Park Project ===
Adjacent to the [[Malibu Country Mart]] was a vacant, {{convert|20|acre|m2|sing=on}} plot of land owned by billionaire [[Jerry Perenchio]] and sold to the City of Malibu in 2005 with strict deed restrictions prohibiting any further commercial use.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.malibucomplete.com/mc_people_wealthy_perenchio.php Malibu'S Wealthy: A. Jerrold Perenchio&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news| url=http://www.forbes.com/lists/2006/54/biz_06rich400_A-Jerrold-Perenchio_J3C6.html | work=Forbes | title=#85 A Jerrold Perenchio}}&lt;/ref&gt;

This site is now home to Malibu Legacy Park, an ongoing restoration project undertaken by the City, with broad community support. The City hopes that a state-of-the-art water treatment plant already built will use stormwater runoff that accumulates in the park, making it into an environmental cleaning machine that will end the City's stormwater pollution contribution to Malibu Creek, Malibu Lagoon, and the world-famous Surfrider Beach.  The Malibu Legacy Park Project responds to critical issues: (1) bacteria reduction by stormwater treatment, (2) nutrient reduction in wastewater management, (3) restoration and development of riparian habitats, and (4) the development of an open space area for passive recreation and environmental education. In addition, the Project will be linked by a “linear park” to neighboring Surfrider Beach, Malibu Pier, Malibu Lagoon, and Malibu Bluffs Park.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.annenbergfoundation.org/news/news_show.htm?doc_id=635503 Annenberg Foundation | News | City of Malibu Announces $2 Million Matching Grant from the Annenberg Foundation&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;

The park is located east of Webb Way, and between Civic Center Way on the north and PCH to the south. It was the site of the annual Labor Day Weekend Kiwanis Club Chili Cook-Off from 1982–2009 (the fair will be moved to nearby streets and parking lots in 2010,  the city says). Further back, it was agricultural land, planted in geraniums, other flowers and vegetables by the Takahashi family since 1924.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.malibucomplete.com/mc_history_malibucity_chilicookoffland.php Malibu Chili Cook-Off Land Purchase&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;

As of now, &quot;Legacy Park&quot; stands in the lot adjacent to the Malibu Public Library, many citizens of Malibu feel the project was a large waste of money because the park does not contain grass areas, only many walkways and plants.

==Businesses and organizations==
The Malibu Chamber of Commerce was formed in 1949 to provide support to local Malibu business, and now has over 500 members.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.malibu.org&lt;/ref&gt;

[[HRL Laboratories]], the research arm of the former [[Hughes Aircraft Company]], was established in 1960 in Malibu. Among its research accomplishments was the first working [[laser]]. Despite aerospace industry downsizing in the 1990s, HRL is the largest employer in Malibu.

[[Jakks Pacific]] is based in Malibu.

Established in 1937 in south-central Los Angeles, [[Pepperdine University]] moved to its Malibu campus in 1972. However, when Malibu incorporated as a city the boundaries were drawn to exclude Pepperdine, at the college's insistence.{{Citation needed|date=July 2009}}

The [[Surfrider Foundation]] was formed in 1984 by a group of surfers gathered to protect {{convert|31|mi|km}} of coastal waters from Marina Del Rey through Malibu to Ventura County, and represent the surfing community.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.surfrider.org/malibu/history.htm History] from the Surfrider Foundation website&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Heal the Bay]], a non-profit organization for environmental advocacy, was formed in 1985 to protect [[Santa Monica Bay]], which extends from Malibu's [[Point Dume]] along the entire coastline of Malibu past [[Santa Monica]] to the Palos Verdes Peninsula.

==Events==

The Malibu Arts Festival is held annually on the last weekend in July by the Malibu Chamber of Commerce.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.malibuartsfestival.com/ Malibu Arts Festival]&lt;/ref&gt;

The Malibu International Film Festival is held every year showcasing new films and filmmakers from around the world.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.malibufilmfestival.com Malibu Film Festival 2011&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;

The Malibu Chili Cookoff, held every Labor Day weekend, is sponsored by the Kiwanis Club of Malibu. Proceeds benefit children and youth organizations.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.malibukiwanis.com/ChiliCookOff.html Malibu Chili Cookoff] from malibukiwanis.com&lt;/ref&gt;

The Malibu Nautica Triathlon is held every September. In 2007, it raised $718,000 to benefit [[Children's Hospital Los Angeles]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.nauticamalibutri.com/ Malibu Nautica Press Release] from nauticamalibutri.com&lt;/ref&gt;

The Polar Plunge (Los Angeles) is held each year in February at [[Zuma Beach]] to help raise funds for the [[Special Olympics]] in Southern California.&lt;ref&gt;[http://sosc.kintera.org/laplunge Polar Plunge (Los Angeles)] from sosc.kintera.org&lt;/ref&gt;

National Get Organized Month is Provided by Bee Organized&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.beeorganized.la/services Bee Organized] from beeorganized.la&lt;/ref&gt;

Malibu International Marathon is a half and full marathon race held every November.

==Filming location==
Malibu has been used as a location or setting for many films, television programs and music videos.

[[Surfrider Beach]]  was home to ''[[Gidget]]'', and [[surfing]] movies of the 1960s. [[Jill Munroe]] and her sister [[Kris Munroe]]'s  [[Charlie's Angels]] beach house was located in Malibu. The residence can also be seen in the first scene after the opening theme song of [[Beach Blanket Bingo]].  Important scenes in the ''[[Planet of the Apes (1968 film)|Planet of the Apes]]'' series were filmed at Point Dume. For an entire summer during the filming, the scale replica of the Statue of Liberty from the famous closing scene lay buried at the Southern end of Pirate's Cove. The hero's trailer in ''[[The Rockford Files]]'' was parked by the Paradise Cove Pier. ''[[Love American Style]]'' and ''[[The Mod Squad]]'' are among many TV series and commercials filmed in Paradise Cove. A 1978 film starring [[Suzanne Somers]] was entitled ''Zuma Beach''.&lt;ref&gt;[http://imdb.com/title/tt0078531/ http://imdb.com/title/tt0078531/] ''imdb.com''&lt;/ref&gt; In the 1990s and 2000s it was the setting for ''MTV Beach House'', ''[[Malibu's Most Wanted]]'', and [[Nickelodeon (TV channel)|Nickelodeon]]'s ''[[Zoey 101]]''. In the [[Coen Brothers]] 1998 motion picture ''[[The Big Lebowski]]'', the fictional chief of police describes it thus: &quot;We've got a nice, quiet beach community here, and I aim to keep it nice and quiet&quot;. In the 2008 movie ''[[Iron Man (film)|Iron Man]]'', [[Iron Man|Tony Stark]]'s home is located in Malibu.  In [[George Cukor]]'s 1981 film ''[[Rich and Famous (1981 film)|Rich and Famous]]'', [[Candice Bergen]]'s character, Merry Noel Blake, resides in Malibu, during a portion of the film.

Malibu is setting for the television series ''[[Two and a Half Men]]''. The television series ''[[So Little Time]]'' (2001) portrayed two Malibu teens ([[Mary-Kate and Ashley Olsen]]) who attend the fictional school West Malibu High. Fictional teen star [[Miley Stewart|Hannah Montana / Miley Stewart]] (portrayed by [[Miley Cyrus]]) and her father [[Robbie Ray Stewart]] (portrayed by [[Billy Ray Cyrus]]) live in Malibu on the [[Disney Channel]] Original Series, [[Hannah Montana]]. In the Fox TV series, &quot;The O.C.&quot;, both the Cohen house and the Cooper homes were actually located in Malibu.&lt;ref name=&quot;OC&quot;&gt;[http://www.seeing-stars.com/OC/ByLocation.shtml The O.C. Filming Locations] from seeing-stars.com&lt;/ref&gt; ''[[Malibu Shores]]'', a teen drama that aired on NBC, was set in Malibu. Some scenes from ''[[The Even Stevens Movie]]'' were filmed on Westward Beach in Point Dume. The small hit TV show ''Summerland'' was also filmed and set in Malibu.

In 2006, [[Bravo (US TV channel)|Bravo]] television aired ''[[Million Dollar Listing]]'', a real-estate related show based on million dollar listings in Malibu, as well as [[Hollywood]], including real-life Malibu agents such as Chris Cortazzo, Scotty Brown, Madison Hildebrand, and Lydia Simon.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.bravotv.com/Million_Dollar_Listing//index.shtml http://www.bravotv.com/Million_Dollar_Listing//index.shtml] ''bravotv.com''&lt;/ref&gt;

The MTV reality show ''[[Buzzin' (TV series)|Buzzin']]'' starring [[Shwayze]] and [[Cisco Adler]] is mostly filmed in Malibu, at locations including Westward Beach, Malibu Courthouse, Pacific Coast Highway, Point Dume Trailer Park, Malibu Inn, and the outside of PC Greens.

Malibu was the setting of the 52nd installment in the ''[[Goosebumps]]'' series of books: ''How I Learned to Fly'', it was also the setting of Alex Duval's ''Vampire Beach'' series.

There are also many [[music video]]s filmed on Malibu's beaches. [[Mariah Carey]]'s video for her 2009 single [[H.A.T.E.U.]] was filmed there.  [[Selena Gomez]]'s &quot;[[Love You Like a Love Song]]&quot; video was partly filmed in Malibu. Music videos for &quot;[[Survivor (Destiny's Child song)|Survivor]]&quot; by [[Destiny's Child]], &quot;Sunshine&quot; by [[Lil Flip]], &quot;[[Natural (S Club 7 song)|Natural]]&quot; by [[S Club 7]], &quot;[[Feel It Boy]]&quot; by [[Beenie Man]] featuring [[Janet Jackson]], and many others were filmed on Westward Beach such as [[Shania Twain]]'s &quot;[[You're Still the One]]&quot;. [[Linda Ronstadt]] who lived in the Colony is photographed in front of her home for her 1976 [[Grammy]] award winning album ''[[Hasten Down The Wind]]''. [[Girls Aloud]] filmed their video &quot;[[Call the Shots]]&quot; on the beach at Malibu. In spring 1999, [[Britney Spears]] shot the video for the song &quot;[[Sometimes (Britney Spears song)|Sometimes]]&quot; directed by [[Nigel Dick]] on the pier at Paradise Cove. Also in late 1998, Madonna shot her video for &quot;[[The Power of Good-Bye]]&quot; near Silver Top mansion. The most recent music video filmed on Malibu Beach was &quot;[[What Makes You Beautiful]]&quot;, the debut single from British boyband [[One Direction]] in July [[2011]].

==Local media==
[[Pepperdine University]]'s TV-32 is fed on [[Distance Learning|Educational-access television]] [[cable TV]] channel 32, and was previously on channel 26.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news | url = http://www.pepperdine-graphic.com/sports/alumn-sports-broadcaster-heads-to-maui-1.2341044 | title = Alumn sports broadcaster heads to Maui | publisher = [[Pepperdine University]] | location = Malibu, California | date = 2010-09-23 | accessdate = 2011-03-28 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news | url = http://graphic.pepperdine.edu/ane/2005/2005-03-24-redcarpet.htm | title = TV-26 strolls down the red carpet | first = Karin | last = Sabin | work = Graphic | publisher = [[Pepperdine University]] | location = Malibu, California | date = 2005-03-24 | accessdate = 2011-03-28 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

Broadcast radio stations licensed for Malibu include 101.5 [[KWVS-LP]] of [[Pepperdine University]] and FM [[booster station]] KPFK-FM1 for 90.7 [[KPFK]] Los Angeles.  92.7 [[KHJL]], Thousand Oaks, has a booster KHJL-FM1 with a city of license of &quot;Malibu Vista&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url = http://www.fccinfo.com/CMDProFacLookup.php?sCurrentService=FM&amp;sCity=Malibu&amp;sState=CA&amp;tabSearchType=City+State+Search | title = FM Records With Principal Community of Malibu, CA | work = FCCInfo.com | publisher = Cavell Mertz &amp; Associates, Inc. | location = Manassas, Virginia | date = 2011-03-23 | accessdate = 2011-03-28 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

Malibu has three local newspapers: ''[[The Malibu Times]]'', founded in 1946, the ''[http://www.malibusurfsidenews.com/ Malibu Surfside News]'', and Pepperdine University's student newspaper, the ''[http://www.pepperdine-graphic.com/ Graphic]''.

There are also three magazines in Malibu: ''[http://www.malibuartsjournal.com/ Malibu Arts Journal]'', ''[http://www.malibumag.com/ Malibu Magazine]'', and ''[http://www.malibutimes.com/ Malibu Times Magazine]''.

==Notable residents==
{{main|List of people from Malibu, California}}

==See also==

*[[Rindge Co. v. County of Los Angeles]]

==References==
{{Reflist|colwidth=30em}}

==External links==
{{Commons category}}
{{Portal|Los Angeles|Greater Los Angeles|Southern California}}
*[http://www.ci.malibu.ca.us/ City of Malibu, official website]
*[http://www.malibu.org/ Malibu Chamber of Commerce]
*{{dmoz|Regional/North_America/United_States/California/Localities/M/Malibu/|Malibu, California}}

{{Cities of Los Angeles County, California}}
{{Greater Los Angeles Area}}
{{Use mdy dates|date=March 2011}}

[[Category:Malibu, California| ]]
[[Category:1991 establishments in the United States]]
[[Category:Beaches of Southern California]]
[[Category:Cities in Los Angeles County, California]]
[[Category:Populated coastal places in California]]
[[Category:Seaside resorts in the United States]]
[[Category:Incorporated cities and towns in California]]
[[Category:Populated places established in 1991]]

[[ar:ماليبو، كاليفورنيا]]
[[bg:Малибу (Калифорния)]]
[[ca:Malibú (Califòrnia)]]
[[cs:Malibu]]
[[de:Malibu (Kalifornien)]]
[[es:Malibú (California)]]
[[eo:Malibu]]
[[eu:Malibu (Kalifornia)]]
[[fa:ملیبو، کالیفرنیا]]
[[fr:Malibu (Californie)]]
[[id:Malibu, California]]
[[it:Malibù]]
[[he:מליבו]]
[[sw:Malibu, California]]
[[ht:Malibu, Kalifòni]]
[[lt:Malibu]]
[[hu:Malibu]]
[[nl:Malibu (Californië)]]
[[ja:マリブ (カリフォルニア州)]]
[[no:Malibu (California)]]
[[pl:Malibu]]
[[pt:Malibu]]
[[ro:Malibu, California]]
[[ru:Малибу (Калифорния)]]
[[sah:Малибу]]
[[simple:Malibu, California]]
[[sk:Malibu (Kalifornia)]]
[[sr:Малибу]]
[[fi:Malibu (Kalifornia)]]
[[sv:Malibu]]
[[tl:Malibu, California]]
[[vo:Malibu]]
[[zh:马利布 (加利福尼亚州)]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
