<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="107678" ns="0" title="San Gabriel, California"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">&lt;!-- Infobox begins --&gt;{{Infobox settlement
|official_name            = City of San Gabriel
|other_name               =
|native_name              = &lt;!-- for cities whose native name is not in English --&gt;
|nickname                 =
|motto                    =
|image_skyline            =
|imagesize                =
|image_caption            =
|image_flag               =
|flag_size                =
|image_seal               = Seal_san_gabriel_ca.png
|seal_size                = 105
|image_shield             =
|shield_size              =
|image_blank_emblem       =
|blank_emblem_size        =
|image_map                = LA County Incorporated Areas San Gabriel highlighted.svg
|mapsize                  = 250x200px
|map_caption              = Location of San Gabriel in [[Los Angeles County, California|Los Angeles County]], [[California]]
|image_map1               =
|mapsize1                 =
|map_caption1             =
|coordinates_display      = inline,title
|coordinates_region       = US-CA
|subdivision_type         = [[List of countries|Country]]
|subdivision_name         = [[United States]]
|subdivision_type1        = [[Political divisions of the United States|State]]
|subdivision_name1        = [[California]]
|subdivision_type2        = [[List of counties in California|County]]
|subdivision_name2        = [[Los Angeles County, California|Los Angeles]]
|subdivision_type3        =
|subdivision_name3        =
|subdivision_type4        =
|subdivision_name4        =
|government_type          =
|leader_title             = [[Mayor]]
|leader_name              = David Gutierrez 
|leader_title1            = &lt;!-- for places with, say, both a mayor and a city manager --&gt;
|leader_name1             =
|leader_title2            =
|leader_name2             =
|leader_title3            =
|leader_name3             =
|established_title        = &lt;!-- Settled --&gt;
|established_date         =
|established_title2       = &lt;!-- Incorporated (town) --&gt;
|established_date2        =
|established_title3       = Incorporated (city)
|established_date3        = 1913-04-24&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url = http://www.cacities.org/resource_files/20457.IncorpDateLO.doc |  title = Incorporation Dates of California Cities | accessdate = 2007-01-18|format=DOC}}&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;!-- Area------------------&gt;
|area_magnitude           =
| unit_pref               =US
| area_footnotes          = &lt;ref&gt;[http://www.census.gov/geo/www/gazetteer/files/Gaz_places_national.txt U.S. Census]&lt;/ref&gt;
| area_total_sq_mi        = 4.146
| area_land_sq_mi         = 4.145
| area_water_sq_mi        = 0.001
| area_total_km2          = 10.736
| area_land_km2           = 10.734
| area_water_km2          = 0.002
| area_water_percent      = 0.02
| area_note               = 
|area_urban_km2           =
|area_urban_sq_mi         =
|area_metro_km2           =
|area_metro_sq_mi         =
|population_as_of         = 2010
|population_note          =
|population_footnotes     =
|settlement_type          = [[City]]
|population_total         = 39718
|population_density_km2   = auto
|population_density_sq_mi = auto
|population_metro         =
|population_density_metro_km2     =
|population_density_metro_sq_mi   =
|population_urban                 =
|population_density_urban_km2     =
|population_density_urban_sq_mi   =
|timezone                 = [[Pacific Time Zone|PST]]
|utc_offset               = -8
|timezone_DST             = PDT
|utc_offset_DST           = -7
|latd = 34 |latm = 5 |lats = 39 |latNS = N
|longd = 118 |longm = 5 |longs = 54 |longEW = W
|elevation_m              = 128
|elevation_ft             = 420
|postal_code_type         = [[ZIP Code]]
|postal_code              = 91775, 91776, 91778&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url = http://zip4.usps.com/zip4/zcl_1_results.jsp?visited=1&amp;pagenumber=0&amp;state=ca&amp;city=San%20Gabriel | title = USPS - ZIP Code Lookup - Find a ZIP+ 4 Code By City Results | accessdate = 2007-01-18}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|area_code                = [[Area code 626|626]]&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url = http://www.nanpa.com/nas/public/npa_city_query_step2.do?method=displayData&amp;cityToNpaModel.stateAbbr=CA&amp;cityToNpaModel.city=San%20Gabriel | title = Number Administration System - NPA and City/Town Search Results | accessdate = 2007-01-18}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|website                  = [http://www.sangabrielcity.com/ http://www.sangabrielcity.com/]
|blank_name               = [[Federal Information Processing Standard|FIPS code]]
|blank_info               = 06-67042
|blank1_name              = [[Geographic Names Information System|GNIS]] feature ID
|blank1_info              = 1656614
|footnotes                =
}}
&lt;!-- Infobox ends --&gt;

'''San Gabriel''' is a city in [[Los Angeles County, California|Los Angeles County]], California, [[United States]].  It is named after the [[Mission San Gabriel Arcángel]], founded by [[Junipero Serra]].  The city grew outward from the mission and in 1852 became the original  township of [[Los Angeles County]].  San Gabriel was incorporated in 1913. The city's  motto is &quot;A city with a Mission&quot; and it is often called the &quot;Birthplace&quot; of the Los Angeles metropolitan area. At the 2010 census, the population was 39,718.

==History==
Prior to the arrival of the Spanish to Alta California, the area that is now  San Gabriel was inhabited by the [[Tongva people|Tongva]] Native Americans, whom the Spanish called the ''Gabrieleno.''  The Tongva name for the San Gabriel region was ''Shevaa''.&lt;ref&gt;Munro, Pamela, et al. ''Yaara' Shiraaw'ax 'Eyooshiraaw'a. Now You're Speaking Our Language: Gabrielino/Tongva/Fernandeño''. Lulu.com: 2008.&lt;/ref&gt;
[[Image:JarabeTapatio.jpg|frame|left|[[Folk Dance]]rs in traditional Mexican dress.]]
Today a center for culture and art, the Mission San Gabriel Arcángel, founded by Father [[Junipero Serra]], is the fourth of twenty-one California Missions, and is known as the &quot;Pride of the California Missions.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.sangabrielcity.com/cityhall/documents/SanGabrielCAFR.pdf |title=City of San Gabriel, California, Comprehensive Annual Financial Report, Year ended June 30, 2009 |publisher=sangabrielcity.com |accessdate=27 November 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The [[Mission San Gabriel Arcángel]] served a pivotal role in the colonial Spanish society, with many of the area's first Mexican settlers being baptized at the mission, including future governor [[Pio Pico]], who was born in 1801 at the mission and baptized there the same year. He was appointed twice as California's governor twice, serving briefly in 1832 and again from 1845 through the Mexican-American War. Later in life, he was elected as a Los Angeles City councilman.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.laalmanac.com/history/hi05s.htm |title=Pio Pico - Last Governor of Mexican California |publisher=laalmanac.com }}&lt;/ref&gt; The city of [[Pico Rivera]] was named to honor him as the last governor of California to be born in [[Mexico]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.colapublib.org/history/picorivera/faq.html#q4 |title=Frequently Asked Questions: Pico Rivera |publisher=colapublib.org }}&lt;/ref&gt;

In 1853, a company of Army Engineers, who included the geologist William P. Blake, passed by the mission in search of the best route for a intercontinental railroad. Blake observed that the once great vineyards had fallen into wild disarray. Fences were in disrepair, and animals roamed freely through the property. But, the mission bells were ringing, and the church was still in use.  Blake predicted, &quot;I believe that when the adaptation of that portion of California to the culture of the grape and the manufacture of wine becomes known and appreciated, the state will become celebrated not only for its gold and grain, but (also) for its fruits and wines.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last=Gally |first=Sid |url=http://www.pasadenastarnews.com/ci_15440867?source=rss |title=Past on Parade: What was the San Gabriel Valley like in 1853? |publisher=Pasadena Star-News |date=2010-03-09 |accessdate=2010-08-03}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In the first United States census made in California in 1860, 586 people lived in San Gabriel. By the time of General Law Incorporation on April 24, 1913, the city's population had grown to 1,500.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite new |url=http://www.pasadenastarnews.com/ci_15440867?source=rss |title=Past on Parade: What was the San Gabriel Valley like in 1853? |publisher=Pasadena Star-News }}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Geography==
San Gabriel is located at {{Coord|34|5|39|N|118|5|54|W|city}} (34.094176, -118.098449).{{GR|1}}

According to the [[United States Census Bureau]], the city has a total area of {{convert|4.1|sqmi|km2}}, virtually all of it land.

The city is bordered on the north by [[San Marino, California|San Marino]], on the east by [[Temple City]] and [[Rosemead]], to the south by [[Rosemead]] and to the west by [[Alhambra, California|Alhambra]].

==Demographics==
===2010===
The [[2010 United States Census]]&lt;ref&gt;{{USCensus-2010CA}}&lt;/ref&gt; reported that San Gabriel had a population of 39,718. The [[population density]] was 9,581.5 people per square mile (3,699.4/km²). The racial makeup of San Gabriel was 10,076 (25.4%) [[White (U.S. Census)|White]], 388 (1.0%) [[African American (U.S. Census)|African American]], 220 (0.6%) [[Native American (U.S. Census)|Native American]], 24,091 (60.7%) [[Asian (U.S. Census)|Asian]], 43 (0.1%) [[Pacific Islander (U.S. Census)|Pacific Islander]], 3,762 (9.5%) from [[Race (United States Census)|other races]], and 1,138 (2.9%) from two or more races.  [[Hispanic (U.S. Census)|Hispanic]] or [[Latino (U.S. Census)|Latino]] of any race were 10,189 persons (25.7%). 

The Census reported that 39,266 people (98.9% of the population) lived in households, 34 (0.1%) lived in non-institutionalized group quarters, and 418 (1.1%) were institutionalized.  

There were 12,542 households, out of which 4,542 (36.2%) had children under the age of 18 living in them, 6,668 (53.2%) were [[marriage|opposite-sex married couples]] living together, 1,961 (15.6%) had a female householder with no husband present, 965 (7.7%) had a male householder with no wife present.  There were 481 (3.8%) [[POSSLQ|unmarried opposite-sex partnerships]], and 76 (0.6%) [[same-sex partnerships|same-sex married couples or partnerships]]. 2,121 households (16.9%) were made up of individuals and 800 (6.4%) had someone living alone who was 65 years of age or older. The average household size was 3.13.  There were 9,594 [[family (U.S. Census)|families]] (76.5% of all households); the average family size was 3.47.

The population was spread out with 7,866 people (19.8%) under the age of 18, 3,555 people (9.0%) aged 18 to 24, 11,335 people (28.5%) aged 25 to 44, 11,388 people (28.7%) aged 45 to 64, and 5,574 people (14.0%) who were 65 years of age or older.  The median age was 40.3 years. For every 100 females there were 93.2 males.  For every 100 females age 18 and over, there were 90.6 males.

There were 13,237 housing units at an average density of 3,193.3 per square mile (1,232.9/km²), of which 6,168 (49.2%) were owner-occupied, and 6,374 (50.8%) were occupied by renters. The homeowner vacancy rate was 1.0%; the rental vacancy rate was 5.7%.  19,974 people (50.3% of the population) lived in owner-occupied housing units and 19,292 people (48.6%) lived in rental housing units.

===2000===
As of the [[census]]{{GR|2}} of 2000, there were 39,804 people, 12,587 households, and 9,566 families residing in the city.  The [[population density]] was 9,639.3 inhabitants per square mile (3,721.2/km²).  There were 12,909 housing units at an average density of 3,126.2 per square mile (1,206.8/km²).  The racial makeup of the city was 33.40% [[White (U.S. Census)|White]], 1.06% [[African American (U.S. Census)|African American]], 0.83% [[Native American (U.S. Census)|Native American]], 48.91% [[Asian people|Asian]], 0.10% [[Pacific Islander (U.S. Census)|Pacific Islander]], 12.36% from [[Race (United States Census)|other races]], and 3.34% from two or more races. Those identifying as [[Hispanic (U.S. Census)|Hispanic]] or [[Latino (U.S. Census)|Latino]] (of any race) were 30.71% of the population.

There were 12,587 households out of which 35.7% had children under the age of 18 living with them, 54.1% were [[Marriage|married couples]] living together, 15.2% had a female householder with no husband present, and 24.0% were non-families. 18.2% of all households were made up of individuals and 6.4% had someone living alone who was 65 years of age or older.  The average household size was 3.10 and the average family size was 3.52.

In the city the population was spread out with 23.5% under the age of 18, 8.6% from 18 to 24, 33.3% from 25 to 44, 21.1% from 45 to 64, and 13.4% who were 65 years of age or older.  The median age was 36 years. For every 100 females there were 92.2 males.  For every 100 females age 18 and over, there were 88.5 males.

The median income for a household in the city was $85,807, and the median income for a family was $96,262. Males had a median income of $61,642 versus $59,302 for females. The [[per capita income]] for the city was $46,807.  About 9.5% of families and 12.9% of the population were below the [[poverty line]], including 17.4% of those under age 18 and 9.5% of those age 65 or over.

===Ethnic culture===

The city boasts a mixture of Asian, European, and North American cultures.&lt;ref name=&quot;SG&quot;&gt;[http://www.sangabrielcity.com/pointsofinterest/valley.shtml City of San Gabriel&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt; Second- and third-generation Chinese Americans patronize its diverse array of stores and eateries.&lt;ref name=&quot;dragon&quot;&gt;{{cite news| url=http://articles.latimes.com/2006/mar/31/local/me-sangabriel31 | work=Los Angeles Times | first=David | last=Pierson | title=Dragon Roars in San Gabriel - Los Angeles Times | date=2006-03-31}}&lt;/ref&gt; There is the 12-acre &quot;San Gabriel Square&quot; mall, sometimes referred to as the &quot;Chinese Disneyland”.&lt;ref name=&quot;SG&quot;/&gt; It was also nicknamed by the [[Los Angeles Times]] as &quot;the great mall of China.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.sangabrielsquare.com/ Welcome To The San Gabriel Square]&lt;/ref&gt; This stretch of exotic Chinese shops and bold architecture,  with roofs of  Spanish-style tile, is the model for the new [[ethnoburb]]s recently recognized in cities like [[Las Vegas metropolitan area|Las Vegas]] and [[Houston]].&lt;ref name=&quot;SG&quot;/&gt; The conglomeration of restaurants and cafes,  shops, markets, hair and nail salons, Asian video stores,health services, department stores, plus an extensive jewelry mart, provides 'something for everyone', from purchasing an expensive diamond and shopping for designer suits, to buying soy milk or a travel package to Las Vegas or China.&lt;ref name=&quot;SG&quot;/&gt;

==Government and infrastructure==
In the [[California State Legislature|state legislature]] San Gabriel is located in the 21st [[California State Senate|Senate]] District, represented by Democrat [[Carol Liu]], and in the 49th [[California State Assembly|Assembly]] District, represented by Democrat [[Mike Eng]]. Federally, San Gabriel is located in [[California's 29th congressional district]], which has a [[Cook Partisan Voting Index|Cook PVI]] of D +12&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | title = Will Gerrymandered Districts Stem the Wave of Voter Unrest? | publisher = Campaign Legal Center Blog | url=http://www.clcblog.org/blog_item-85.html | accessdate = 2008-02-10}}&lt;/ref&gt; and is represented by Democrat [[Adam Schiff]].

===City government===

Five Councilmembers are elected  by the voters to serve a four-year term. The Mayor is appointed annually by the Council in a rotation among its members. The City Council is also the Redevelopment Agency Board of Directors. 
The current members of the City Council are:
   
*David R. Gutierrez—Mayor
*Kevin B. Sawkins—Vice-Mayor
*Juli Costanzo—Council member
*Mario De La Torre—Council member
*'John Harrington—Council member&lt;ref name=&quot;sangabrielcity1&quot;&gt;[http://www.sangabrielcity.com/cityhall/electcitycouncil.shtml City of San Gabriel&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;

The city's first Chinese American mayor was Chi Mui in 2006. He symbolized San Gabriel's rise as the new center of the region's Chinese community. He died of cancer three months later.&lt;ref name=&quot;dragon&quot;&gt;{{cite news |url=http://articles.latimes.com/2006/mar/31/local/me-sangabriel31 |title= Dragon Roars in San Gabriel |news=[[Los Angeles Times]] | first=David |last=Pierson |date=2006-03-31}}&lt;/ref&gt; Mui was replaced by Albert Y. M. Huang, who served as mayor during his term. Huang submitted his resignation October 19, 2010 following a late-night domestic dispute with his girlfriend and subsequent arrest. Huang has since been cleared of all charges.&lt;ref name=&quot;sangabrielcity1&quot;/&gt;

===City services===

[[Image:Mission San Gabriel conceptual elevation - Rexford Newcomb 1916.jpg|thumb|250px|right|Artist Rexford Newcomb's rendition of Mission San Gabriel Arcángel's original ''campanile'', or &quot;[[bell tower]].&quot;]]

San Gabriel won a record $4.6 million park grant that will fund San Gabriel’s first new park in this century, for the proposed Marshall Community Park project.  This the first time a joint venture between the City and Garvey School District has been planned.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://sangabrielcity.com/ |title=San Gabriel City homepage }}&lt;/ref&gt;

*Adult Recreation Center and Senior Center, 324 South Mission Drive
*Bovard-Wilson-Hayes House and Jail
*Grapevine Park and Arbor, 324 South Mission Drive
*Parks Office, The Parks and Recreation Department offers an after school sports program and a summer playground program for San Gabriel youth. Along with these programs, the Department provides a variety of trips and special events throughout the year for youth of all ages.
*San Gabriel Historical Association
*San Gabriel Mission Playhouse
*Smith Park and Pool, 232 West Broadway,
*Vincent Lugo Park, Corner of Wells and Ramona Streets

===County services===

The [[Los Angeles County Department of Health Services]] operates the Monrovia Health Center in [[Monrovia, California|Monrovia]], serving San Gabriel.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;[http://publichealth.lacounty.gov/phn/docs/HealthCenter/monrovia.pdf Monrovia Health Center].&quot; [[Los Angeles County Department of Health Services]]. Retrieved on March 27, 2010.&lt;/ref&gt;

===Scandal===

On Friday October 15, 2010, Mayor Albert Y.M. Huang was arrested on suspicion of battery, robbery and assault, two felonies and a misdemeanor. He was released on $100,000 bail. He resigned from the office of Mayor and from the council on October 19, 2010, at the city council meeting that evening. He declared his innocence even though he was observed driving away from the scene of the altercation at approximately 45&amp;nbsp;mph, with a woman clinging to his car.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.pasadenastarnews.com/news/ci_16342750#ixzz12Seo70On San Gabriel Mayor Huang arrested on suspicion of assault, robbery - Pasadena Star-News&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;KCal news, October 19, 2010.&lt;/ref&gt; According to the police, a security guard from a nearby business saw Huang and the female subject fighting and detained them until police could arrive.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.alhambrasource.org/news/san-gabriel-mayor-arrested-alleged-robbery-assault-battery San Gabriel mayor arrested for alleged robbery, assault, battery | Alhambra Source&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;
Huang resigned after he was arrested and posted bail.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.huffingtonpost.com/2010/10/19/san-gabriel-mayor-albert-_n_768540.html San Gabriel Mayor Albert Y.M. Huang Resigns After Purse-Snatching Arrest&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;
Huang has since been cleared of all charges.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.pasadenastarnews.com/ci_17570639]&lt;/ref&gt;

==Economy==
===Top employers===
According to the City's 2009 Comprehensive Annual Financial Report, the top employers in the city are:&lt;ref name=&quot;cafr2009&quot;&gt;[http://www.sangabrielcity.com/cityhall/documents/SanGabrielCAFR.pdf City of San Gabriel CAFR]&lt;/ref&gt;

{| class=&quot;wikitable&quot;
|-
! #
! Employer
! # of Employees
|-
| 1
|San Gabriel Valley Medical Center
|860
|-
| 2
|[[99 Ranch Market]]
|180
|-
| 3
|Landwin
|180
|-
| 4
|[[Shun Fat Supermarket]]
|143
|-
| 5
|Live Oak Rehabilitation Center
|136
|-
| 6
|Hawaii Supermarket
|120
|-
| 7
|Alderwood Manor Convalescent Hospital
|101
|-
| 8
|Park Uniform Rental
|100
|-
| 9
|Vista Cove Care Center
|99
|-
| 10
|Mission Lodge Sanitarium
|98
|-
| 11
|Fernview Convalescent Hospital
|88
|-
| 12
|Country Villa Broadway
|76
|-
| 13
|Marco's Auto Body
|70
|-
| 14
|O'Donnell [[Chevrolet]]-[[Buick]]
|67
|-
| 15
|China Times Printing 
|53
|-
| 16
|San Gabriel Nursery &amp; Florist
|52
|}

==Transportation==
[[Image:Old PE car at San Gabriel Mission circa 1905.jpg|thumb|300px|left|A [[streetcar]] of the [[Pacific Electric Railway]] makes a stop at Mission San Gabriel Arcángel ''circa'' 1905.]]
In 2008, voters approved the measure, proposition 1A for the California High Speed Rail Project from San Diego to San Francisco.&lt;ref name=&quot;rail&quot;&gt;http://www.pasadenastarnews.com/news/ci_16391198&lt;/ref&gt; The project will be constructed in two segments. The [[San Francisco]] to [[Los Angeles]]/[[Anaheim]] project is scheduled to be built first, at a cost of $43 billion, with a completion date in 2020.&lt;ref name=&quot;rail&quot;/&gt; The second phase of the proposed railway, from Los Angeles to stations in [[San Diego]] will not begin construction until after phase one is completed.

Conceptually, the voters were very enthusiastic about a high speed railway. The reality of the possibility that it could impact their neighborhood and their homes is being met with steadfast disapproval.  When the [[California High Speed Rail Authority]] recently met with the city councils and residents of [[San Gabriel]], [[El Monte]], [[Rosemead]] &lt;ref name=&quot;SM&quot;&gt;http://www.sanmarinotribune.com/article/Politics/Politics/Residents_Oppose_HighSpeed_Railway_in_Alhambra_Monday_Night/2288&lt;/ref&gt; and [[Alhambra]], to discuss the  four proposed routes for phase two, the councils expressed that residents were very concerned that the railway could possibly end up in their backyards.&lt;ref name=&quot;rail&quot;/&gt;   Mayor David Gutierrez said  &quot;We made a promise to the community that the city of San Gabriel will never allow anything like this to happen if there is any consideration that people might lose their home.&quot; 
&lt;ref name=&quot;rail&quot;/&gt; No decisions will be made until environmental impact and evaluation of the various proposed routes are completed in 2014.&lt;ref name=&quot;rail&quot;/&gt; Alhambra city councilwoman, Jessica Keating,
maintained  that city representatives, who had appeared to agree with the proposal, admitted they were “caught asleep at the wheel.”&lt;ref name=&quot;SM&quot;/&gt;

==Education==
The city of San Gabriel is served by the [[San Gabriel Unified School District]].  They state: &quot;It is the mission of the San Gabriel School District, in partnership with the Community, to prepare its students for their future as productive citizens and lifelong learners...&quot;  &lt;ref&gt;http://www.sgusd.k12.ca.us/&lt;/ref&gt;
The 2009 [[API]] school reports has recognized the San Gabriel Unified school district as one of the top school districts in California.  [[Gabrielino High School]] consistently ranks as one of the highest achieving  schools, as it ranks with some of the highest scores possible among public high schools in [[California]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://education.usnews.rankingsandreviews.com/listings/high-schools/california/gabrielino_high_school Gabrielino High School: Best High Schools - USNews.com&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;

===Elementary schools===

There are five public elementary schools in San Gabriel, all of which are named after former Presidents.: 
:Calvin Coolidge Elementary School.
:McKinley Elementary School
:Roosevelt Elementary School
:Washington Elementary School
:Wilson Elementary School
Each of its public schools have been  honored as a [[California Distinguished School]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.sgusd.k12.ca.us/site_listing.aspx?categoryid=c477ca4c-1c91-443c-bf7a-533e94c543f6&amp;catName=Elementary&amp;type=post&amp;schoolAffiliatedCatLink=0 |title=San Gabriel Unified School District Listing |publisher=sgusd.k12.ca.us |accessdate=27 November 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;
Two other elementary schools within the city limits, Dewey Elementary, and Marshall Elementary, are operated by the [[Garvey School District]], in the southern portion of San Gabriel.

===Middle school===

[[Image:Gabrielino High School entrance.JPG|thumb|right|Entrance to Gabrielino High School]]
[[Jefferson Middle School (San Gabriel, California)|Jefferson Middle School]] is located in the [[San Gabriel Unified School District]]. In 1968 the school was converted to the only intermediate school in the elementary school district with seventh and eighth grade  students.  Jefferson became part of the San Gabriel Unified School District in 1993-94.  The five K-6 elementary schools  feed into the middle school. Jefferson is recognized as a [[California Distinguished School]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.jefferson.sgusd.k12.ca.us/site_res_view_template.aspx?id=d9b351c7-5681-4490-bb91-858468e1d24f |title=Jefferson Middle School |publisher=Jefferson.sgusd.k12.ca.us |date= |accessdate=2010-08-03}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===High schools===

[[Gabrielino High School]] has been named by [[US News and World Report]] as one of &quot;America's Best Public High Schools&quot;. This puts it in the top 2.8% of the schools in the nation.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.gabrielino.sgusd.k12.ca.us/home |title=Gabrielino High School - Homepage |publisher=Gabrielino.sgusd.k12.ca.us |date= |accessdate=2010-08-03}}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Del Mar High School]] opened in September 2010, is newly built alternative school, &quot;Where Second Chances Happen&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.delmar.sgusd.k12.ca.us/ |title=Del Mar High School, Daly Announcements |publisher=delmar.sgusd.k12.ca.us |accessdate=27 November 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[San Gabriel High School]] is located in the [[Alhambra Unified School District]], which serves residents from [[Alhambra]], [[Rosemead]], [[San Gabriel]], and [[San Marino, California|San Marino]].

[[San Gabriel Mission High School]], a Catholic, private, all girls high school, grades 9-12.  It was named after and  is located in the same block as the historical [[Mission San Gabriel Arcángel]].

===Private schools===

There are several private schools in the City of San Gabriel including: 
:Saint Anthony School, Grades Pre-K through 8th.  A Tradition of Excellence in Catholic education since 1948.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://stanthonysangabriel.org/index.html |title=Saint Anthony Catholic School. A Tradition of Excellence Since 1948 |publisher=stanthonysangabriel.org |accessdate=27 November 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;
:San Gabriel Mission Elementary School&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://sangabrielmission.org/schools/ |title=San Gabriel Mission High School homepage |publisher=sangabrielmission.org |accessdate=27 November 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;
:San Gabriel Academy is a coeducational Seventh-day Adventist college preparatory school, grades K-12.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.sangabrielacademy.org/article.php?id=23 |title=Mission |publisher=Sangabrielacademy.org |accessdate=27 November 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;
:Clairbourn School is a coeducational preparatory day school, pre-K through 8th grade in an environment harmonious with the teachings of Christian Science.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.clairbourn.org/overview.php |title=School Overview  |publisher=clairbourn.org |accessdate=27 November 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;
:Little Flower Montessori School, Grades Pre-K through 5th.
:San Gabriel Christian School-- Is an accredited member of the Association of Christian Schools International (ACSI) and the Western Association of Schools and Colleges (WASC).  The school provides a strong Christian education program for over 600 students in grades kindergarten through eighth grade.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.sgucandcs.org/#/s-g-christian-school |title=Welcome to San Gabriel Christian School |publisher=sgucandcs.org |accessdate=27 November 2010 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Famous natives and notable residents==
*[[Hank Aguirre]], Major League Baseball pitcher &lt;ref name=&quot;baseball&quot;&gt;http://www.insidesocal.com/tribpreps/2009/02/mcconnell-names.html&lt;/ref&gt;
*[[Susan Atkins]]
*[[Judge Roy Bean]]
*[[Francisco Dumetz]]
*[[Mike Garcia (AL pitcher)|Mike Garcia]]&lt;ref name=&quot;baseball&quot;/&gt;
*[[Ken Gushi]]
*[[Curly Howard]]
*[[Ward Kimball]]
*[[Mike Krukow]]&lt;ref name=&quot;baseball&quot;/&gt;
*[[Dee Luong]]
*[[Bill Mumy]]&lt;ref&gt;http://www.filmreference.com/film/10/Bill-Mumy.html&lt;/ref&gt;
*[[Danny Patterson]]
*[[George Patton|General George S. Patton]]
*[[Pio Pico]] last Mexican Governor of California
*[[Allan Sandage]]
*[[Luis J. Rodriguez]]
*[[Kurt Vollers]]
*[[Max Padilla]] 
*[[Joanna Wang]] &lt;ref&gt;http://www.sweetslyrics.com/Joanna%20Wang.html&lt;/ref&gt;

==External links==
{{Portal|Los Angeles}}
*[http://www.sangabrielcity.com/ San Gabriel official website]
*[http://www.missionplayhouse.org/ San Gabriel Mission Playhouse website]

==References==
{{Reflist}}
{{Cities of Los Angeles County, California}}
{{Greater Los Angeles Area}}

[[Category:San Gabriel, California|*]]
[[Category:Populated places in the United States with Asian American majority populations]]


[[ar:سان غابريل، لوس أنجليس، كاليفورنيا]]
[[bg:Сан Габриел (град, Калифорния)]]
[[cs:San Gabriel]]
[[de:San Gabriel (Kalifornien)]]
[[es:San Gabriel (California)]]
[[fr:San Gabriel (Californie)]]
[[sw:San Gabriel, California]]
[[ht:San Gabriel, Kalifòni]]
[[nl:San Gabriel (Californië)]]
[[pt:São Gabriel (Califórnia)]]
[[ru:Сан-Габриэль (Калифорния)]]
[[tl:San Gabriel, California]]
[[vo:San Gabriel]]
[[zh:圣盖博]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
