<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="107615" ns="0" title="Compton, California"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Infobox settlement
|official_name            = City of Compton 
|settlement_type          = [[City]]
|nickname                 = CPT, The Hub City, The Shopping City
|motto                    = Birthing a New Compton
|image_skyline            = Compton martin luther king monument.jpg
|imagesize                =
|image_caption            = The Martin Luther King Monument in front of the Compton City Hall and the Superior Court building. The monument is the logo for the city and is featured on signage.
|image_seal               = ComptonSeal.png
|seal_size                =
|image_map                = LA County Incorporated Areas Compton highlighted.svg
|mapsize                  = 250px
|map_caption              = Location of Compton in [[Los Angeles County, California|Los Angeles County]], [[California]]
|image_map1               =
|mapsize1                 =
|map_caption1             =
|coordinates_region       = US-CA
|subdivision_type         = [[List of countries|Country]]
|subdivision_name         = {{Flagicon|USA}} [[United States]]
|subdivision_type1        = [[Political divisions of the United States|State]]
|subdivision_name1        = {{Flagicon|California}} [[California]]
|subdivision_type2        = [[List of counties in California|County]]
|subdivision_name2        =  [[Los Angeles County|Los Angeles]]
|government_type          = [[Council-manager government|Council-Manager]]
|leader_title             = [[City Council]] &lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.comptoncity.org/ |title=Home |publisher=Comptoncity.org |date=2009-04-11 |accessdate=2011-02-07}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|leader_name              = [[Mayor]]: [[Eric Perrodin]] &lt;br /&gt; Barbara J. Calhoun &lt;br /&gt; Lillie Dobson &lt;br /&gt; [[Yvonne Arceneaux]] &lt;br /&gt; Dr.Willie O Jones
|leader_title1             = City Council
|leader_name1              = Craig J. Cornwell
|leader_title2             = [[City Treasurer]]
|leader_name2              = Douglas Sanders
|leader_title3             = City Clerk
|leader_name3              = Alita Godwin
|established_title         = Incorporated
|established_date         = May 11, 1888
&lt;!-- Area------------------&gt;
|area_magnitude           =
| unit_pref               =US
| area_footnotes          = &lt;ref&gt;[http://www.census.gov/geo/www/gazetteer/files/Gaz_places_national.txt U.S. Census]&lt;/ref&gt;
| area_total_sq_mi        = 10.116
| area_land_sq_mi         = 10.012
| area_water_sq_mi        = 0.104
| area_total_km2          = 26.202
| area_land_km2           = 25.932
| area_water_km2          = 0.270
| area_water_percent      = 1.03
| area_note               = 

|elevation_m              = 18–24
|elevation_ft             = 60–79
|coordinates_display      = inline,title
|coordinates_type         = region:US_type:city
|latd = 33 |latm = 53 |lats = 48 |latNS = N
|longd = 118 |longm = 13 |longs = 30 |longEW = W
|population_as_of         = 2010
|population_total         = 96455
|population_density_km2   = auto
|timezone                 = [[Pacific Time Zone|PST]]
|utc_offset               = -8
|timezone_DST             = PDT
|utc_offset_DST           = -7
|latitude = 33.896715° N
|longitude = -118.225078° E
|website                  = [http://www.comptoncity.org/ www.comptoncity.org]
|postal_code_type         = [[ZIP code]]s
|postal_code              = 90220-90224
|area_code                = [[Area code 310|310]]/[[Area code 424|424]], [[Area code 323|323]], [[Area code 562|562]]
|blank_name               = [[Federal Information Processing Standard|FIPS code]]
|blank_info               = 06-15044
|blank1_name              = [[Geographic Names Information System|GNIS]] feature ID
|blank1_info              = 1652689
|footnotes                =
}}

'''Compton''' is a city in southern [[Los Angeles County, California|Los Angeles County]], [[California]], [[United States]],&lt;ref name=&quot;city&quot;&gt;{{cite web | url=http://www.comptoncity.org/ |title=Comptoncity.org | accessdate=2010-08-29}}&lt;/ref&gt; southeast of downtown [[Los Angeles, California|Los Angeles]]. The city of Compton is one of the oldest cities in the county and on May 11, 1888, was the eighth city to incorporate. The city is considered part of the [[South Los Angeles|South side]] by residents of Los Angeles.&lt;ref name=&quot;streetgangs.com&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.streetgangs.com/maps/southla_turf.html |title=Gang Maps – Gang Territory Map – South Central Los Angeles |publisher=Streetgangs.com |accessdate=2010-08-30}}&lt;/ref&gt; As of the [[2010 United States Census|2010 census]], the city had a total population of 96,455.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://factfinder.census.gov/servlet/SAFFPopulation?_event=ChangeGeoContext&amp;geo_id=16000US0615044&amp;_geoContext=01000US%7C04000US06%7C16000US0615044&amp;_street=&amp;_county=compton%2C+california&amp;_cityTown=compton%2C+california&amp;_state=&amp;_zip=&amp;_lang=en&amp;_sse=on&amp;ActiveGeoDiv=geoSelect&amp;_useEV=&amp;pctxt=fph&amp;pgsl=010&amp;_submenuId=population_0&amp;ds_name=null&amp;_ci_nbr=null&amp;qr_name=null&amp;reg=null%3Anull&amp;_keyword=&amp;_industry= |title=Compton city, California – Population Finder – American FactFinder |publisher=Factfinder.census.gov |accessdate=2011-02-07}}&lt;/ref&gt;  It is known as the &quot;Hub City&quot; due to its geographic centrality in Los Angeles County.&lt;ref name=&quot;city&quot;/&gt;  Neighborhoods in Compton include: Sunny Cove, Leland, Downtown Compton, and the Richland Farms.

==History==
[[Image:Comption-1914.jpg|thumb|left|Compton, 1914]]
In 1784, the [[Spain|Spanish]] Crown deeded a tract of over {{convert|75,000|acre|km2}} to [[Juan Jose Dominguez]] in this area.  The tract was named [[Rancho San Pedro]].  Dominguez's name was later applied to the [[Dominguez Hills]] community south of Compton.  The tree that marked the original northern boundary of the rancho still stands at the corner of Poppy and Short streets.  The rancho was sub-divided and parcels were sold within the [[Californios]] of [[Alta California]] until the lands were ceded after the [[Mexican-American war]] in 1848. [[United States|American]] [[immigrants]] acquired most of the rancho lands after 1848.

In 1867, Griffith Dickenson Compton led a group of thirty pioneers to the area. These families had traveled by wagon train south from [[Stockton, California|Stockton]], California in search of ways to earn a living other than in the rapid exhaustion of gold fields.  Originally named Gibsonville, after one of the tract owners, it was later called Comptonville.  However, to avoid confusion with the Comptonville located in [[Yuba County]], the name was shortened to Compton.&lt;ref name=&quot;city&quot;/&gt;  Compton’s earliest settlers were faced with terrible hardships as they farmed the land in bleak weather to get by with just the barest subsistence.  The weather continued to be harsh, rainy and cold, and fuel was difficult to find.  To gather firewood  it was necessary to travel  to mountains close to [[Pasadena, California|Pasadena]].  The round trip took almost a week.  Many in the Compton party wanted to relocate to  a friendlier climate and settle down.  But there were only two general stores within traveling distance, one in the pueblo of [[Los Angeles]], the other in [[Wilmington, Los Angeles, California|Wilmington]],  so they eventually made the decision to stay put.&lt;ref name=&quot;city&quot;/&gt;

By 1887, the settlers realized it was time to make improvements to the local government.  A series of town meetings were held to discuss incorporation of their little town. Griffith D. Compton donated his land to incorporate and create the city of Compton in 1889, but he did stipulate that a certain acreage be zoned solely for agriculture and named Richland Farms &lt;ref name=&quot;Comp&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.kcet.org/socal/departures/richland-farms/the-past/ |title=1 The Past &amp;#124; Departures |publisher=KCET |date=2010-07-23 |accessdate=2010-08-29}}&lt;/ref&gt;  In January 1888, they forwarded a petition supporting the incorporation of Compton to the Los Angeles County Board of Supervisors, who in turn forwarded the petition to the State Legislature. On May 11, 1888 the city of Compton was incorporated, it had a total  population of 500 people.  The first City Council meeting was held on May 14, 1888.&lt;ref name=&quot;city&quot;/&gt;

The ample residential lots of Richland Farms gave residents enough space to raise a family, and food to feed them, along with building a barn, and caring for livestock. The farms attracted the  black families who had begun migrating from the rural South in the 1950s,  there they found their 'home away from home' in this small community. Compton couldn't support large-scale agricultural business, but it did give the residents the opportunity to work the land for their families and for the welfare of the new community.&lt;ref name=&quot;Comp&quot;/&gt;

The 1920s saw the opening of the Compton Airport. Compton Junior College was founded and city officials moved to a new City Hall on Alameda Street.&lt;ref name=&quot;city&quot;/&gt; On March 10, 1933, a devastating earthquake  caused many casualties,  schools were destroyed and there was major damage to the central business district.&lt;ref name=&quot;city&quot;/&gt;  While it would eventually be home to a large number of [[African Americans]], in 1930 there was only one black resident.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book | last = Horne | first = Gerald | authorlink = | coauthors = | title = Fire This Time: The Watts Uprising and the 1960s | publisher = Da Capo Press | year = 1997 | location = New York, New York | page = 27 | url = | doi = | id = | isbn = 978-0-306-80792-3 }}&lt;/ref&gt; In the late 1940s, middle class African-Americans began moving into the area, mostly on the west side. Compton grew quickly in the 1950s.  One reason for this was Compton was close to [[Watts, Los Angeles, California|Watts]], where there was an established community  of African Americans.  The eastern side of the city was predominately white until the 1970s.  Despite being located in the middle of a major metropolitan area, thanks to the legacy of Griffith D. Compton, there still remains one small pocket of agriculture from its earliest years.&lt;ref name=&quot;Comp&quot;/&gt;

During the 1950s and 1960s, after the Supreme Court declared all racially exclusive housing covenants (title deeds) unconstitutional in the case [[Shelley v. Kraemer]], the first African American families moved to the area. &lt;ref Name=&quot;black&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.comptoncity.org/index.php/About-Compton/history-of-the-city.htm |title=History of the City &amp;#124; About Compton |publisher=Comptoncity.org |date=1933-03-10 |accessdate=2010-08-29}}&lt;/ref&gt; Compton's growing African American population was still largely ignored and neglected by the city's elected officials.  [[Centennial High School (Compton, California)|Centennial High School]] was finally built to accommodate a burgeoning student population. &lt;ref Name=&quot;black&quot;/&gt; At one time, the City Council even discussed dismantling the Compton Police Department in favor of the [[Los Angeles County Sheriff's Department]] in an attempt to exclude blacks from law enforcement jobs.   This slowly began to change when, in 1958, the first African-American ran for a City Council seat. However, it would be another three years before an African-American would actually be elected to the City Council in 1961. &lt;ref Name=&quot;black&quot;/&gt;
[[Image:Comption-1920.jpg|thumb|right|Aerial view of Compton, 1920]]

[[Douglas Dollarhide]] made history in Compton in 1969 when he became [[California]]'s first African-American mayor of a metropolitan city. &lt;ref Name=&quot;black&quot;/&gt;  Two African-Americans and one Mexican-American were also elected to the local school board. &lt;ref Name=&quot;black&quot;/&gt; Four years later, in 1973, [[Doris A. Davis]] defeated Dollarhide's bid for re-election to become the first [[African-American]] female mayor of a metropolitan city in the [[United States]]. By the early 1970s, the city had one of the largest concentrations of African-Americans in the country with over ninety percent.{{Citation needed|date=January 2010}}

For many years, Compton was a much sought after neighborhood for the black middle class of Los Angeles. Now, only a few areas of Compton are still middle class communities. This past affluence is reflected in the area's appearance — Compton's streets are lined with relatively spacious and attractive single family homes. However, several factors have contributed to Compton's decline. One of the most significant factors was a steady erosion of its tax base. First by [[white flight|whites who fled]] to the newly incorporated cities of [[Artesia, California|Artesia]], [[Bellflower, California|Bellflower]], [[Cerritos, California|Cerritos]], [[Paramount, California|Paramount]] and [[Norwalk, California|Norwalk]] in the late 1950s. These nearby communities remained largely white early on despite [[Racial integration|integration]].&lt;ref&gt;Scott, Allen John and Edward Soja (1996). ''The City: Los Angeles and Urban Theory at the End of the Twentieth Century'' Berkeley: University of California Press. 10.&lt;/ref&gt; This move was even further precipitated after the [[Watts Riots]] in 1965 and [[1992 Los Angeles riots]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|author=Post Store |url=http://www.washingtonpost.com/wp-dyn/content/discussion/2005/08/12/DI2005081201348.html |title=Outlook: The Negative Impact of the Watts Riots |publisher=washingtonpost.com |date= 2005-08-15|accessdate=2010-08-29}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Soon, middle class blacks also found other areas more attractive to them. Some were unincorporated areas of [[Los Angeles County, California|Los Angeles County]] such as [[Ladera Heights, California|Ladera Heights]], [[View Park-Windsor Hills, California|View Park]] and [[View Park-Windsor Hills, California|Windsor Hills]]; and others were cities such as [[Inglewood, California|Inglewood]] and, particularly, [[Carson, California|Carson]]. The latter was significant because it had successfully thwarted attempts at [[annexation]] by neighboring Compton. The city of Carson opted instead for incorporation in 1968, which is notable because its black population was actually more affluent than its white population. As a newer city, it also offered more favorable tax rates and lower crime.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://ci.carson.ca.us/content/department/about_carson/growing_pains.asp |title=Growing Pains of a Young City – City of Carson, CA |publisher=Ci.carson.ca.us |accessdate=2010-08-29}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Culture==
Although Compton is still often thought of as a primarily black community, [[Latinos]] are the largest ethnic group in the city. A possible reason for this misconception is, despite the shift in population, many [[African American]] professional athletes and rappers are originally from Compton. Also, African Americans continue to dominate local politics, holding most elected positions in the city. Although an [[Inner suburbs|inner suburb]] of Los Angeles, Compton has seen an increase of middle-class residents in the last few years, due to its affordable housing and a reduction in crime. With the influx of immigrants and the demographic shift in ethnic population, it was after the 2000 [[U.S. Census]] Latinos were recognized as the majority.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.comptoncity.org/index.php/About-Compton/history-of-the-city.htm |title=History of the City &amp;#124; About Compton |publisher=Comptoncity.org |date=1933-03-10 |accessdate=2010-08-30}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Compton has been referenced on numerous occasions in [[gang]] affiliation, [[gangsta rap]] and [[g-funk]] songs, especially in the late 1980s and early 1990s, and so has attained an association not only with gang violence and crime, but with [[hip hop music]] as well. The city is known as the home of many famous rappers. (see list [[List of people from Compton, California#Arts and entertainment]])  Compton has evolved into a younger community, the median age of people living in Compton, was 25 at the time of the last full census survey; the United States average at the time was 35.3.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.americantowns.com/ca/compton-information |title=Compton California (CA) Census and detailed community profile |publisher=AmericanTowns.com |accessdate=2010-08-30}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Some episodes of the [[sitcom]] ''[[The Fresh Prince of Bel-Air]]'' took place in Compton because [[Will Smith]]'s friend Jazz lived there.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.answers.com/topic/the-fresh-prince-of-bel-air |title=The Fresh Prince of Bel-Air: Information from |publisher=Answers.com |accessdate=2010-08-30}}&lt;/ref&gt;
Many well-known [[NBA]] players attended high school in the city as well. [[DeMar DeRozan]] attended Compton High School, and [[Tayshaun Prince]], [[Tyson Chandler]] and [[Brandon Jennings]] attended Dominguez High.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
| title = American Experience, George H. W. Bush, PBS
| work = pbs.org
| accessdate = 2008-06-12
| url = http://www.pbs.org/wgbh/amex/bush41/timeline/
}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Compton has a growing [[Pacific Islander American|Pacific Islander]], [[Filipino American|Filipino]], and [[Vietnamese people|Vietnamese]] community. West Compton and unincorporated Willowbrook have more middle class [[African American]]s than the central city (west of Alameda St.) and unincorporated East Compton, the latter of which has a higher number of Hispanics and working-class African Americans. Lower-income subsections on Compton Boulevard have many businesses owned by Latinos.

==Crime==
Compton's violent reputation was popularized in the late 1980s by the rise to prominence of local [[gangsta rap]] groups [[Compton's Most Wanted]] and especially [[N.W.A.]], who released the famous album ''[[Straight Outta Compton]]'' in 1988.  The city used to be notorious for [[gang violence]], primarily caused by the [[Bloods]], the [[Crips]], and [[Sureños]] gangs that are allied with the Mexican [[drug cartels]].  Crime rates had been falling for years following the [[crack epidemic]] of the 1980s and early 1990s.

Crime, though present in lesser degrees beforehand, worsened significantly with the introduction of [[crack (cocaine)|crack cocaine]] in the latter part of the 20th century. The neighborhood lost wealthy residents, with the worsening safety problems, and, after the [[1992 Los Angeles riots|1992 riots]] in the [[Los Angeles, California|Los Angeles metropolitan area]], many [[African Americans]] left the city. Meanwhile, many Latino and other immigrant families moved into Compton, including [[Samoans]], [[Tongans]], [[Koreans]], [[Filipino American|Filipinos]], [[Belizeans]] and [[East Africa]]ns.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.comptoncity.org/index.php/About-Compton/demographic-information.htm |title=Demographic Information &amp;#124; About Compton |publisher=Comptoncity.org |date=1991-12-03 |accessdate=2010-08-30}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Compton had 76 murders in 2005, which is significantly higher than the national average on a per capita basis. That same year, in an effort to combat [[gun violence]], the citizens of Compton were given the option to hand over their guns to the police and receive a $50–$100 check for various goods, called the Gifts for Guns Program.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://articles.latimes.com/2008/dec/09/local/me-gifts-for-guns9 |title=Residents turn in guns in Compton – Los Angeles Times |publisher=Articles.latimes.com |date=2008-12-09 |accessdate=2010-08-12 | first=Kate | last=Linthicum}}&lt;/ref&gt; People have turned in about 7,000 guns over the last few years, [[KABC-TV]] reported. The program's success has prompted the [[Los Angeles County Sheriff's Department|LASD]] to expand the program county-wide.&lt;ref name=&quot;SD&quot;&gt;Compton Sheriff's Station 2009 Year in review publication&lt;/ref&gt;

During 2006, Compton deployed twice as many [[sheriff|sheriff's deputies]] and the murder rate has steadily decreased in the last decade.&lt;ref name=autogenerated1&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.idcide.com/citydata/ca/compton.htm |title=Compton Profile &amp;#124; Compton CA &amp;#124; Population, Crime, Map |publisher=Idcide.com |accessdate=2011-02-07}}&lt;/ref&gt; Compton's [[property crime]] levels tend to be about the same as the average California city. The same data shows [[violent crime]], including arson, levels in Compton tend to be higher than California's average level.&lt;ref name=autogenerated1 /&gt; However, recent reports show that Compton's violent crime rate has been reduced by 30% over the last ten years.&lt;ref&gt;NBC News, 12-11-02&lt;/ref&gt;  

Although the [[U.S. News &amp; World Report]] does not even list Compton in the &quot;The 11 Most Dangerous Cities&quot; for overall crime rates in the United States,&lt;ref&gt; http://www.usnews.com/news/articles/2011/02/16/the-11-most-dangerous-cities &lt;/ref&gt;, it contrasts the CQ Press, using data from the [[Crime in the United States|FBI's annual report of crime statistics]] &quot;Crime in the United States 2010,&quot; ranked Compton as the 8th most dangerous city in the country.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://os.cqpress.com/citycrime/2010/City_crime_rate_2010-2011_hightolow.pdf |title=AMSAFC2.WK4 |format=PDF |accessdate=2011-07-31}}&lt;/ref&gt;  Statistics will vary depending on how property crimes and violent crimes are weighted in each statistical survey.  See [[Statistical variability]]

In 2010, Compton Station area homicides were reduced by about 38 percent, with 26 homicides in 2010, compared with 42 homicides in 2009.&lt;ref name=&quot;CBS1&quot;&gt;http://losangeles.cbslocal.com/2011/01/17/homicides-dip-16-percent-in-compton-la-county/&lt;/ref&gt;   This number is a 53 percent decrease from five years ago, and was the lowest number of homicides since 1972.  The sheriff’s department reported: Taking into consideration the population changes, last year showed the lowest homicide rate since 1965.  Property crimes also decreased.&lt;ref name=&quot;CBS1&quot;/&gt;

==Compton Cricket Club==
{{Main|Compton Cricket Club}}
[[Image:UmbroCCC.jpg|thumb|right|Umbro photographs The Compton CC in South Central LA, February 2009]]
The [[Compton Cricket Club]] (CCC), nicknamed &quot;The Homies &amp; the POPz&quot;, has also been christened &quot;America's Team&quot; and the &quot;US Ambassadors of Good Will and Peace in the sporting world of [[Cricket]].&quot;  At this time, the CCC is the only exhibition cricket team in the world that totally consists of North American-born players. 

&quot;The aim of playing cricket is to teach people how to respect themselves and respect authority, so they stop killing each other,&quot; says team founder, Ted Hayes. Their mission is &quot;to curb the negative effects of gang activities amongst the youth of Compton, [[South Central Los Angeles]], and all inner cities, and to address homelessness through the principles and ethics of cricket.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;http://www.comptoncricketclub.org/&lt;/ref&gt;  

The team has traveled to [[England]] and [[Australia]] and has collaborated with several charities during its exhibition tour raising money for Australian flood victims. Due to financial difficulties in building a [[cricket pitch]] in Compton, the team utilizes various fields in the [[Greater Los Angeles Area]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news| url=http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/world-us-canada-12382224 | work=BBC News | title=LA cricket: Club helps tame Compton's mean streets | date=2011-02-10}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Government and infrastructure==
===City government===
Elected Officials:
See info box.
*City Manager, Charles Evans, The City Manager is responsible for the administration of city services and programs, enforcement of the city's Municipal Code and ordinances, and preparation of the annual budget.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.comptoncity.org/ |title=Home |publisher=Comptoncity.org |accessdate=2010-08-30}}&lt;/ref&gt;

After [[Lionel Cade]], an accountant, assumed the mayor's office in 1977, one of the first orders of business was to conduct an audit of the city's finances. It was discovered that the city was $2 million in debt. The administration was able to eliminate the huge deficit in one year by making cuts in every department. It also aggressively sought federal funding to help pay for essential services, which was at least partially effective. However, with the passage of the property tax cutting initiative [[Proposition 13]] by California voters, Compton was one of the cities hardest hit, since it had already eliminated most of the fat from its budget.&lt;ref&gt;William A. Fischel [http://www.dartmouth.edu/~wfischel/Papers/Martin%20comment%20feb09.pdf Serrano and Proposition 13: Comment on Isaac Martin, “Does School Finance Litigation Cause Taxpayer Revolt”], Dartmouth College, 2009&lt;/ref&gt;

===County, state and federal representation===

The [[Los Angeles County Department of Health Services]] operates the South Health Center in [[Watts, Los Angeles, California|Watts]], [[Los Angeles]], serving Compton.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;[http://publichealth.lacounty.gov/phn/docs/HealthCenter/southla.pdf South Health Center].&quot; [[Los Angeles County Department of Health Services]]. Retrieved on March 18, 2010.&lt;/ref&gt;

In the [[California State Legislature|state legislature]] Compton is located in the 25th [[California State Senate|Senate]] District, represented by Democrat [[Edward Vincent]], and in the 52nd [[California State Assembly|Assembly]] District, represented by Democrat [[Isadore Hall, III]]. Federally, Compton is located in [[California's 37th congressional district]], which has a [[Cook Partisan Voting Index|Cook PVI]] of D +27&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | title = Will Gerrymandered Districts Stem the Wave of Voter Unrest? | publisher = Campaign Legal Center Blog | url=http://www.clcblog.org/blog_item-85.html | accessdate = 2008-02-10}}&lt;/ref&gt; and is represented by Democrat [[Laura Richardson]].

The [[United States Postal Service]] operates the Compton Post Office at 701 South Santa Fe Avenue&lt;ref&gt;&quot;[http://usps.whitepages.com/service/post_office/14296?p=1&amp;s=CA&amp;service_name=post_office&amp;z=Compton Post Office Location – COMPTON].&quot; ''[[United States Postal Service]]''. Retrieved on December 6, 2008.&lt;/ref&gt; the Hub City Post Office at 101 South Willowbrook Avenue,&lt;ref&gt;&quot;[http://usps.whitepages.com/service/post_office/27401?p=1&amp;s=CA&amp;service_name=post_office&amp;z=Compton Post Office Location – HUB CITY].&quot; ''[[United States Postal Service]]''. Retrieved on December 6, 2008.&lt;/ref&gt; and the Fashion Square Post Office at 2100 North Long Beach Boulevard.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;[http://usps.whitepages.com/service/post_office/64676?p=1&amp;s=CA&amp;service_name=post_office&amp;z=Compton Post Office Location – FASHION SQUARE].&quot; ''[[United States Postal Service]]''. Retrieved on December 6, 2008.&lt;/ref&gt; &lt;!--The Willowbrook PO is NOT in Compton - it is in Willowbrook, uninc. LA County, California--&gt;

====LASD====
The [[Los Angeles County Sheriff's Department]] operates the Compton Station in Compton.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;[http://www.lasd.org/stations/for2/compton/index.html Compton Station].&quot; [[Los Angeles County Sheriff's Department]]. Retrieved on January 21, 2010.&lt;/ref&gt; When the LASD replaced the Compton Police Department in 2000, they increased patrol service hours from 127,410, to 141, 692.  Compton Station is centrally located in the Los Angeles area. The station is easily accessible from the (105) Century freeway to the north, the (91) Riverside/Artesia freeway to the south, the (110) Harbor freeway to the west, and the (710) Long Beach freeway to the east.  Diane Walker, a 30-year veteran of the Los Angeles County Sheriff's Department, was promoted to the rank of Captain by Sheriff [[Lee Baca]], and  is now Commander of Compton Station.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.la-sheriff.org/stations/for2/compton/index.html |title=Los Angeles County Sheriff's Dept. – Compton Station |publisher=La-sheriff.org |accessdate=2010-08-30}}&lt;/ref&gt; There is also a LASD substation located in  the Gateway Towne Center.&lt;ref name=&quot;SD&quot; /&gt;

==City government controversies==
Civic [[Political corruption|corruption]] has also been a widespread problem in Compton.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news| url=http://articles.latimes.com/1990/oct/25 | work=The Los Angeles Times | title=Popular Articles &amp; Stories for October 25, 1990 – Los Angeles Times}}&lt;/ref&gt; In the early 1990s, United States Attorney [[Joey Chin]] conducted a series of investigations, centered on a phony [[waste-to-energy]] scheme, that ultimately ensnared a number of prominent elected officials.

In 2000, the [[Compton Police Department]] was disbanded amidst controversy and charges of corruption.  The police department claims it was disbanded after investigations of gang activity led to then-Compton Mayor [[Omar Bradley (California politician)|Omar Bradley]].  Once this became public, the mayor charged it was the police who were themselves corrupt, and he disbanded the police department.  Omar Bradley has since faced serious corruption charges.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.blackpressusa.com/news/Article.asp?SID=3&amp;Title=National+News&amp;NewsID=2776 Former Compton Mayor among Five Officials Arrested after Probe]. ''BlackPressUSA''&lt;/ref&gt; Regardless of the situation, an alternative form of law enforcement was sought. Compton's policing needs are currently served by the [[Los Angeles County Sheriff's Department]].

Eric J. Perrodin, the city's current mayor, was investigated in 2007 by the California State Bar for threatening to violate a local newspaper's first amendment rights after the paper printed an investigative report relative to a contract granted to one of Perrodin's associates. Following the report, Perrodin threatened to yank the city's advertising contract with the paper&lt;ref&gt;([http://www.metnews.com/articles/2006/bull063006.htm District Attorney’s Office Probing Prosecutor Over Alleged Threats]. &quot;Metropolitan News-Enterprise&quot;.&lt;/ref&gt;  A Times review of city records shows Perrodin was absent from city board and commission meetings nearly two-thirds of the time between July 2009 and July 2010.&lt;ref name=AP &gt;[http://www.cbs47.tv/news/state/story/Compton-council-fires-city-manager-again/4Nq3ekEo_0OkZND1KLIGAw.cspx?rss=154 Compton council fires city manager again – KGPE CBS47 News, Sports &amp; Weather for the Central Valley]{{dead link|date=February 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Current recall efforts are a direct response from residents of the accusations of corruption of the city's mayor and council. Some of the accusations involve the issuing of city contracts to personal donors and friends. One particular accusation involved the trash and recycling contract of the city to Pacific Coast Waste and Recycling LLC in 2007,&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.thecomptonbulletin.com/series1/index.html The Compton Bulletin Online – LOCAL NEWS&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]{{dead link|date=February 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; whose leadership donated large amounts of money to Perrodin's political coffers.

Notices of intent to circulate recall petitions against four Compton city officials are expected to be filed  in August 2010, by a group of citizens who claim corruption in Compton is being ignored by the same authorities who were shocked  by the recent salary controversy  in the city of [[Bell, California|Bell]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|author=By BETTY PLEASANT, Contributing Editor |url=http://www.wavenewspapers.com/opinion/Bottom-Line-In-Compton-recall-paperwork-soon-to-land-on-the-desks-of-top-city-officials-101040384.html |title=Bottom Line: In Compton, recall paperwork soon to land on the desks of top city officials &amp;#124; Los Angeles Wave – Community News, Sports &amp; Entertainment &amp;#124; Opinion |publisher=Wavenewspapers.com |date=2010-08-18 |accessdate=2010-08-30}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Compton has discharged its city manager for the second time in three years. ''The Los Angeles Times'' says the City Council voted in a closed meeting, September 9, 2010, to fire Charles Evans. ''The Times'' says council members refused to discuss the reasons for their decision. Evans took office in 2007, after the dismissal of previous City Manager Barbara Kilroy. City Controller Willie Norfleet will take over until a permanent manager can be named.&lt;ref name=AP/&gt;

==Geography==
{{Geographic Location 2
 | Center    = [[Downtown Compton]]
 | North     = [[Willowbrook, California]]
 | Northeast = [[Lynwood, California]]
 | East      = [[East Rancho Dominguez, California]]
 | ESE       =
 | Southeast = [[Long Beach, California]]
 | Southwest = [[Carson, California]]
 | South     = [[Rancho Dominguez, California]]
 | WSW       =
 | West      = [[West Compton, California]]
 | WNW       =
 | Northwest = [[Willowbrook, California]]
}}

Compton is located at {{Coord|33|53|48|N|118|13|30|W|type:city}} (33.896715, −118.225078).{{GR|1}} According to the [[United States Census Bureau]], the city has a total area of {{convert|10.1|sqmi|km2}}. {{convert|10.0|sqmi|km2}} of it is land and {{convert|0.1|sqmi|km2}} of it (1.03%) is water.

It is bordered by the unincorporated [[Willowbrook, California|Willowbrook]] on the north and northwest, the unincorporated [[West Compton, California|West Compton]] on the west, the city of [[Carson, California|Carson]] on the southwest, the unincorporated [[Rancho Dominguez, California|Rancho Dominguez]] on the south, the city of [[Long Beach, California|Long Beach]] on the southeast, the city of [[Paramount, California|Paramount]] and the unincorporated [[East Compton, California|East Compton]] on the east, and by the city of [[Lynwood, California|Lynwood]] on the northeast.

===East Compton===
[[East Compton, California|East Compton]], also known as '''East Rancho Dominguez''', is a mostly industrial  [[unincorporated community]] and [[census-designated place]] (CDP). The population was 9,286 at the 2000 census. East Rancho Dominguez is an accepted city name according to the [[United States Postal Service|USPS]], and shared the 90221 [[ZIP Code]] with Compton.&lt;ref&gt;[http://zip4.usps.com/zip4/zcl_3_results.jsp ZIP Code Lookup]&lt;/ref&gt; Its [[sphere of influence#California|sphere of influence]] is the city of Compton, which has tried to annex East Rancho Dominguez, but business and property owners in the area have opposed the annexation.&lt;ref&gt;[http://web.archive.org/web/20071008051455/http://www.thecomptonbulletin.com/news04_012506/index.html The Compton Bulletin Online – LOCAL NEWS]. Web.archive.org (2007-10-08). Retrieved on 2011-02-10.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.lalafco.org/Agendas/2006/030806a.pdf#search=%22%22East%20Rancho%20Dominguez%22%20Compton%22 City of Carson SOI Update Resolution], March 8, 2006&lt;/ref&gt; &lt;!-- LOCAL AGENCY FORMATION COMMISSION REGULAR MEETING AGENDA 3/8/2006--&gt;

==Demographics==
===2010===
The [[2010 United States Census]]&lt;ref&gt;{{USCensus-2010CA}}&lt;/ref&gt; reported that Compton had a population of 96,455. The [[population density]] was 9,534.3 people per square mile (3,681.2/km²). The racial makeup of Compton was 24,942 (25.9%) [[White (U.S. Census)|White]], 31,688 (32.9%) [[African American (U.S. Census)|African American]], 655 (0.7%) [[Native American (U.S. Census)|Native American]], 292 (0.3%) [[Asian (U.S. Census)|Asian]], 718 (0.7%) [[Pacific Islander (U.S. Census)|Pacific Islander]], 34,914 (36.2%) from [[Race (United States Census)|other races]], and 3,246 (3.4%) from two or more races.  [[Hispanic (U.S. Census)|Hispanic]] or [[Latino (U.S. Census)|Latino]] of any race were 62,669 persons (65.0%). 

The Census reported that 95,700 people (99.2% of the population) lived in households, 643 (0.7%) lived in non-institutionalized group quarters, and 112 (0.1%) were institutionalized.  

There were 23,062 households, out of which 13,376 (58.0%) had children under the age of 18 living in them, 10,536 (45.7%) were [[marriage|opposite-sex married couples]] living together, 6,373 (27.6%) had a female householder with no husband present, 2,354 (10.2%) had a male householder with no wife present.  There were 1,725 (7.5%) [[POSSLQ|unmarried opposite-sex partnerships]], and 158 (0.7%) [[same-sex partnerships|same-sex married couples or partnerships]]. 2,979 households (12.9%) were made up of individuals and 1,224 (5.3%) had someone living alone who was 65 years of age or older. The average household size was 4.15.  There were 19,263 [[family (U.S. Census)|families]] (83.5% of all households); the average family size was 4.41.

The population was spread out with 31,945 people (33.1%) under the age of 18, 11,901 people (12.3%) aged 18 to 24, 26,573 people (27.5%) aged 25 to 44, 18,838 people (19.5%) aged 45 to 64, and 7,198 people (7.5%) who were 65 years of age or older.  The median age was 28.0 years. For every 100 females there were 94.8 males.  For every 100 females age 18 and over, there were 90.7 males.

There were 24,523 housing units at an average density of 2,424.0 per square mile (935.9/km²), of which 12,726 (55.2%) were owner-occupied, and 10,336 (44.8%) were occupied by renters. The homeowner vacancy rate was 2.9%; the rental vacancy rate was 5.9%.  53,525 people (55.5% of the population) lived in owner-occupied housing units and 42,175 people (43.7%) lived in rental housing units.

===2000===
As of the [[census]]{{GR|2}} of 2000, there were 93,692 people, (A 2006 city census showed a growth to 95,701 people), 22,327 households, and 18,620 families residing in the city. The [[population density]] was 9,225.6 inhabitants per square mile (3,563.5/km²). There were 23,795 housing units at an average density of 2,348.0 per square mile (906.9/km²). 

As of 2000, the racial makeup of the city was: 
*[[Race (United States Census)|White]] 16.7%
*[[Race (United States Census)|Black]] or [[Race (United States Census)|African American]] 40.3%
*[[Race (United States Census)|Native American]] and [[Alaska Native]] 0.7%
*[[Asian people|Asian]]  0.3%
*[[Race (United States Census)|Pacific Islander]] 1.1%
*Other Race 37.3%
*[[(U.S. Census)|Two or more races]] 3.6%
*[[Hispanic (U.S. Census)|Hispanic]] or [[Latino (U.S. Census)|Latino]] (of any race) 56.8% &lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://factfinder.census.gov/servlet/ACSSAFFFacts?_event=&amp;geo_id=16000US0615044&amp;_geoContext=01000US%7C04000US06%7C16000US0615044&amp;_street=&amp;_county=compton%2C+california&amp;_cityTown=compton%2C+california&amp;_state=&amp;_zip=&amp;_lang=en&amp;_sse=on&amp;ActiveGeoDiv=geoSelect&amp;_useEV=&amp;pctxt=fph&amp;pgsl=160&amp;_submenuId=factsheet_1&amp;ds_name=null&amp;_ci_nbr=null&amp;qr_name=null&amp;reg=null%3Anull&amp;_keyword=&amp;_industry= |title=Compton city, California – Fact Sheet – American FactFinder |publisher=Factfinder.census.gov |accessdate=2011-02-07}}&lt;/ref&gt;
There were 23,665 households out of which 49.1% had children under the age of 18 living with them, 43.9% were [[Marriage|married couples]] living together, 29% had a female householder with no husband present, and 17.7% were non-families. 14.6% of all households were made up of individuals and 5.6% had someone living alone who was 65 years of age or older. The average household size was 4.16 and the average family size was 4.57.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|author=American FactFinder, United States Census Bureau |url=http://factfinder.census.gov/servlet/ADPTable?_bm=y&amp;-geo_id=16000US0615044&amp;-qr_name=ACS_2009_5YR_G00_DP5YR2&amp;-ds_name=ACS_2009_5YR_G00_&amp;-_lang=en&amp;-_sse=on= |title=Compton city, California – Selected Social Characteristics in the United States: 2005–2009 |publisher=Factfinder.census.gov |accessdate=2011-02-07}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In the city the population was spread out with 38.5% under the age of 18, 11.5% from 18 to 24, 28.7% from 25 to 44, 14.4% from 45 to 64, and 6.9% who were 65 years of age or older. The median age was 25 years. For every 100 females there were 96.3 males. For every 100 females age 18 and over, there were 91.2 males.&lt;ref name=&quot;alm1&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.laalmanac.com/population/po09a.htm |title=Population by City by Age |publisher=Laalmanac.com |accessdate=2011-02-07}}&lt;/ref&gt;
The median income for a household in the city was $33,021, and the median income for a family was $40,021. Males had a median income of $22,698 versus $24,692 for females. The [[per capita income]] for the city was $13,382
. About 21.6% of families and 23.7% of the population were below the [[poverty line]], including 33.5% of those under age 18 and 14.1% of those age 65 or over.&lt;ref name=&quot;alm1&quot;/&gt;

==Education==	
[[File:Compton High School billboard.jpg|thumb|[[Compton High School]]]]
The city is served by [[Compton Unified School District]]. &lt;ref Name=&quot;education&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.comptoncity.org/index.php/About-Compton/education-system.htm |title=Education System &amp;#124; About Compton |publisher=Comptoncity.org |accessdate=2010-08-29}}&lt;/ref&gt; The district is a participant of the FOCUS program conducted by the [[University of California, Irvine]]. The goals of the program are to improve mathematics and science achievement by uniting the efforts of mathematics, science, education and research library faculty and staff with educators of the school district.&lt;ref&gt;[http://focus.web.uci.edu/smarts/participants.php FOCUS Progam Participants]. ''FOCUS at UCI''&lt;/ref&gt;
 	
The CUSD provides public education for grades K-12. The district operates 24 elementary schools, eight middle schools, three high schools, and one adult school, which also serves as an alternative school. The district maintains five alternative learning schools.&lt;ref Name=&quot;education&quot;/&gt;
 	
The three high schools that are part of CUSD, are [[Centennial High School (Compton, California)|Centennial High School]], [[Dominguez High School]], and [[Compton High School]].&lt;ref Name=&quot;education&quot;/&gt;
 	
The city is also served by [[El Camino College]] Compton Education Center, which offers community college courses for those planning to enter a four-year degree program, as well as those seeking further education in specific trade fields.&lt;ref Name=&quot;education&quot;/&gt;
 
Reed Christian College is a non-profit private institution, located in Compton. The program lasts for less than one year, and total enrollment is approximately 120 students.	 
	
The Compton Library offers adult, children’s and Spanish language materials; reference services; a Literacy Center and a Homework Center; public computers with Internet access and word processing capabilities; public typewriters; and a bilingual story time every Saturday at 12:00 noon.&lt;ref Name=&quot;education&quot;/&gt;
 	
Occidental’s Center for Food and Justice and its Compton Farm-to-School project were featured in a segment of “Life and Times,” a half-hour news program on public television’s KCET in Los Angeles.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.oxy.edu/x2948.xml |title=Occidental College :: Oxy in the News |publisher=Oxy.edu |date=2005-06-22 |accessdate=2011-02-07}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Economy==
Compton was recently designated as an “Entrepreneurial Hot Spot” by Cognetics, Inc., an independent economic research firm. Compton made the national list for best places to start and grow a business, and ranked #2 in [[Los Angeles County]] out of a field of 88 cities.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.simplyhired.com/a/local-jobs/city/l-Compton,+CA |title=Compton Jobs (CA) |publisher=Simply Hired |accessdate=2010-08-30}}&lt;/ref&gt; The city's Planning and Economic Development department provides a business assistance program consisting of a comprehensive mix of resources to small business owners and entrepreneurs. The grocery chains [[Ralphs]] and [[Food 4 Less]], subsidiaries of [[Krogers]], is headquartered in Compton.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;[http://www.kroger.com/company_information/careers/Pages/contact_us.aspx Contact Us].&quot; ''[[Kroger]]''. Retrieved on April 30, 2009.&lt;/ref&gt;  Gelson's Market, a subsidiary of Arden Group, Inc., a holding company, is also based there.
&lt;ref&gt;http://www.gelsons.com/about/company/index.asp&lt;/ref&gt;

Compton is surrounded by multiple freeways which provide access to destinations throughout the region. The Long Beach and Los Angeles Ports are less than 20 minutes from downtown Compton, providing access to international destinations for customers and suppliers.  The [[Alameda Corridor]], a passageway for 25% of all U.S. waterborne international trade, runs directly through Compton from north to south.{&lt;ref name=&quot;comptoncity.org&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.comptoncity.org/index.php/About-Compton/hub-city.htm |title=Hub City &amp;#124; About Compton |publisher=Comptoncity.org |accessdate=2010-08-30}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Gateway Towne Center===
The Gateway Towne Center is a large [[power center]] and represents a new trend in investing in inner cities. Opened in October, 2007, it brought over 1,000 local jobs to the city and helped address a need for increased local services. The city's tax revenues have increased about 30% since the center's opening. Phase one of the mega-shopping center includes several [[big box]] retailers, several restaurants, banks, supply stores and fitness centers.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://gatewaytownecenter.com/ |title=Gateway Towne Center |publisher=Gateway Towne Center |accessdate=2011-02-07}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Historical landmarks==
&quot;Angeles Abbey Cemetery&quot; contains examples of [[Byzantine]], [[Moorish]] and Spanish architectural style. The cemetery was built in 1923 and survived the 1933 Long Beach Earthquake.&lt;ref name=&quot;history&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.comptoncity.org/index.php/Historical-Landmarks/heritage-house.htm |title=Heritage House &amp;#124; Historical Landmarks |publisher=Comptoncity.org |accessdate=2010-08-29}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The &quot;Compton Airport&quot; opened on May 10, 1924.  Located on Alondra Boulevard, the airport offers flight training, has accommodations for more than 200 planes, and is home to several aviation clubs.&lt;ref name=&quot;history&quot;/&gt;

&quot;Dr. Martin Luther King, Jr. Memorial&quot;: This Civic Center monument is dedicated to the memory of Dr. Martin Luther King, Jr. It is surrounded by the Civic Center, Compton Court House, Compton City Hall, and Compton Public Library.&lt;ref name=&quot;history&quot;/&gt;

The &quot;Eagle Tree&quot; is a natural boundary marker of [[Rancho San Pedro]] dating back to 1858. It contains an historic marker and plaque placed by the Daughters of the Golden West in 1947.&lt;ref name=&quot;history&quot;/&gt;

The &quot;'Heritage House'&quot; was built in 1869 and is a State Historic Landmark.  The oldest house in Compton, it was restored as a tribute to early settlers.  It serves as an important landmark of Compton's rich history. Located at the corner of Myrrh and Willowbrook near the Civic Center Plaza, the Heritage House is a rustic-looking home that will eventually house a museum detailing early life in Compton. For now it demarks the stark difference between the simple life of the 19th century and the fast-paced urban environment of the 21st century.&lt;ref name=&quot;history&quot;/&gt;

&quot;Woodlawn Cemetery&quot; is the final resting place of 18 Civil War Veterans.  It has been a Los Angeles County Historic Landmark since 1946.&lt;ref name=&quot;history&quot;/&gt;

==Transportation==
Four freeways are near the city's boundaries and provide access to destinations throughout the region. These include Interstate Highways [[Interstate 105 (California)|105]], [[Interstate 110 (California)|110]], [[Interstate 710 (California)|710]], and [[California State Route 91|State Route 91]].

The [[LACMTA Blue Line|Metro Blue Line]] [[light rail]] runs north-south through the city; [[Compton (LACMTA Station)|Compton Station]] is in the heart of the city, adjacent to the Renaissance Shopping Center. The Blue Line connects Compton to [[downtown Los Angeles]] and downtown Long Beach.

There is also a [[List of small Southern California transit agencies#Compton Renaissance Transit|Compton Renaissance Transit System]] that serves the local community.

[[Compton/Woodley Airport]] is a small [[general aviation]] [[airport]] located in the city. The airport lies within busy airspace, as it is situated within a few miles of both [[Los Angeles International Airport]] and [[Long Beach Airport]].

[[Greyhound Lines]] operates the Compton Station.

Collectively, these multi–faceted transportation links lend justification to the city's familiar name of &quot;the Hub City.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;comptoncity.org&quot;/&gt;

==City sites==
* The '''[[Major League Baseball Academy]]''' '&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Major_League_Baseball_Academy |title=Major League Baseball Urban Youth Academy – Wikipedia, the free encyclopedia |publisher=En.wikipedia.org |accessdate=2010-08-29}}&lt;/ref&gt; &quot;'is a youth baseball academy providing free baseball and softball instruction to Southern California youth.
* '''[http://www.TAMuseum.org/ Tomorrow’s Aeronautical Museum]''' is a non-traditional compilation of a living interactive museum, after-school programs, gang intervention programs and flight school.

===Noted people===
{{Main|List of people from Compton, California}}

== See also ==

* [[List of California public officials charged with crimes#Commerce|List of California public officials charged with crimes, Compton]]
* [[South Los Angeles]]
{{-}}

==References==
{{Reflist|colwidth=30em}}

==Further reading==
*Adams, Emily, &quot;Bush's Compton Roots Raise Thorny Issue&quot;, ''Los Angeles Times'', August 3, 1992, page B-1
*Miller, Gary J., ''Cities by Contract: The Politics of Municipal Incorporation'', The MIT Press, Cambridge, Massachusetts and London, England, 1981
*Gould, Lewis L. (editor), ''American First Ladies: Their Lives and Their Legacy'', Garland Publishing, New York and London, 1996. See pages 612–613 regarding the Bush family's &quot;nomadic&quot; existence in the cities of [[Huntington Park, California|Huntington Park]], [[Bakersfield, California|Bakersfield]], [[Whittier, California|Whittier]], [[Ventura, California|Ventura]] and Compton, [[California]].
*The George Bush Presidential Library web site states that during the period from 1948 to 1951, &quot;Bush and his family moved several times, living successively in Odessa, Texas; Ventura, Bakersfield, and Compton, California; and Midland, Texas.&quot; The web site also includes a [http://bushlibrary.tamu.edu/image.php?id=2175 photograph] of [[George W. Bush]]  in Compton, dated 1949.

==External links==
{{Portal|Los Angeles|Greater Los Angeles|Southern California}}
{{Commons category|Compton, California}}
*[http://www.comptoncity.org/ City of Compton – official city website]
*[http://www.lasd.org/stations/for2/compton/index.html LASD in Compton]
*[http://www.lasgrwc.org/ComptonCreek.htm Compton Creek Watershed Management Plan]
*[http://www.bncompton.blogspot.com/ Birthing A New Compton]
*[http://www.newsweek.com/id/190871/page/1 How Compton got its groove back, ''Newsweek'' 2009]
*[https://humanexperience.stanford.edu/camarillocompton Going Back to Compton]

{{Cities of Los Angeles County, California}}
{{Greater Los Angeles Area}}

[[Category:California Enterprise Zones]]
[[Category:Incorporated cities and towns in California]]
[[Category:Cities in Los Angeles County, California]]
[[Category:Populated places in California with Hispanic majority populations]]
[[Category:Populated places established in 1888]]

[[ar:كومبتون، كاليفورنيا]]
[[bg:Комптън (Калифорния)]]
[[ca:Compton (Califòrnia)]]
[[cs:Compton]]
[[da:Compton]]
[[de:Compton (Kalifornien)]]
[[es:Compton]]
[[fr:Compton (Californie)]]
[[hr:Compton, Kalifornija]]
[[it:Compton (California)]]
[[sw:Compton, California]]
[[ht:Compton, Kalifòni]]
[[hu:Compton]]
[[nl:Compton (Californië)]]
[[ja:コンプトン (カリフォルニア州)]]
[[no:Compton]]
[[pnb:کیمپٹن]]
[[pl:Compton (Kalifornia)]]
[[pt:Compton (Califórnia)]]
[[ro:Compton, California]]
[[ru:Комптон (Калифорния)]]
[[simple:Compton, California]]
[[sk:Compton]]
[[sr:Комптон (град)]]
[[fi:Compton]]
[[sv:Compton, Kalifornien]]
[[tl:Compton, California]]
[[vi:Compton, California]]
[[vo:Compton (California)]]
[[zh:康普顿 (加利福尼亚州)]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
