<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="107661" ns="0" title="Montebello, California"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Infobox settlement
|official_name            = Montebello
|settlement_type          = [[City]]
|nickname                 =
|website                  = [http://www.cityofmontebello.com/ www.cityofmontebello.com]
|image_skyline            =
|imagesize                =
|image_caption            = War memorial for the Battle of Rio San Gabriel overlooking the Rio Hondo river
|image_flag               =
|image_seal               = Montebello_ca_usa_logo.png
|seal_size                = 97px
|image_map                = LA County Incorporated Areas Montebello highlighted.svg
|mapsize                  = 250x200px
|map_caption              = Location of Montebello in [[Los Angeles County, California|Los Angeles County]], [[California]]
|image_map1               =
|mapsize1                 =
|map_caption1             =
|pushpin_map=USA California
|pushpin_map_caption=Location in California
|subdivision_type         = [[List of countries|Country]]
|subdivision_name         = [[United States]]
|subdivision_type1        = [[Political divisions of the United States|State]]
|subdivision_name1        = [[California]]
|subdivision_type2        = [[List of counties in California|County]]
|subdivision_name2        = [[Los Angeles County, California|Los Angeles]]
|government_type          =
|leader_title             = [[Mayor]]
|leader_name              = Art Barajas
|established_date        = October 19, 1920
&lt;!-- Area------------------&gt;
|area_magnitude           =
| unit_pref               =US
| area_footnotes          = &lt;ref&gt;[http://www.census.gov/geo/www/gazetteer/files/Gaz_places_national.txt U.S. Census]&lt;/ref&gt;
| area_total_sq_mi        = 8.373
| area_land_sq_mi         = 8.333
| area_water_sq_mi        = 0.040
| area_total_km2          = 21.685
| area_land_km2           = 21.581
| area_water_km2          = 0.104
| area_water_percent      = 0.48
| area_note               = 
|population_as_of         = 2010
|population_total         = 62500
|population_urban                 =
|area_urban_km2           =
|area_urban_sq_mi         =
|population_metro         =
|population_density_km2   = auto
|population_density_sq_mi = auto
|timezone                 = [[Pacific Time Zone|PST]]
|utc_offset               = -8
|timezone_DST             = PDT
|utc_offset_DST           = -7
|coordinates_display      = inline,title
|coordinates_type         = region:US_type:city
|latd = 34 |latm = 0 |lats = 52 |latNS = N
|longd = 118 |longm = 6 |longs = 52 |longEW = W
|elevation_m              = 61
|elevation_ft             = 200
|postal_code_type         = [[ZIP code]]
|postal_code              = 90640
|area_code                = [[Area code 323|323]]
|blank_name               = [[Federal Information Processing Standard|FIPS code]]
|blank_info               = 06-48816
|blank1_name              = [[Geographic Names Information System|GNIS]] feature ID
|blank1_info              = 1656573
|footnotes                =
}}

'''Montebello'''  is a city in [[Los Angeles County, California|Los Angeles County]], [[California]], [[United States]], in the southwestern part of the [[San Gabriel Valley]]. It is located on {{convert|8.4|sqmi|abbr=on}} of land just {{convert|8|mi|abbr=on}} east of downtown Los Angeles. It is considered part of the [[Gateway Cities]], and the city is a member of the Gateway Cities Council of Governments. The name, Montebello, means “Beautiful mountain” in both Italian and Spanish.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.spanishdict.com/translate/monte&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;http://www.spanishdict.com/translate/bello&lt;/ref&gt;  In the early 20th century, Montebello was a well-known source for oil reserves.  The population was 62,500 at the 2010 census; according to the [[California Department of Finance]], the estimated population of Montebello on January 1, 2011, was 62,789.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.dof.ca.gov/research/demographic/reports/estimates/e-1/documents/E-1_2011_Press_Release.pdf&lt;/ref&gt;

==History==
Before the arrival of the [[Spain|Spaniards]], the land along the [[Rio Hondo (California)|Rio Hondo River]] was populated by the [[Tongva people|Tongva]] (Gabrielino) part of the [[Uto-Aztecan languages|Uto-Aztecan]] family [[Native Americans in the United States|Native Americans]]. The Tongva occupied much of the Los Angeles basin and the islands of [[Santa Catalina Island, California|Santa Catalina]], [[San Nicolas Island|San Nicolas]], [[San Clemente Island|San Clemente]] and [[Santa Barbara Island|Santa Barbara]]. When the Spanish explorer [[Juan Rodrigues Cabrillo]] arrived off the shores of Santa Catalina, the Tongva came out in their canoes to meet with him in 1542. The language of the Tongva was different from the neighboring Indian tribes and it was called Gabrielino by the Spanish.  The Gabrielinos lived in dome-like structures with thatched exteriors.  Both sexes wore long hair styles and tattooed their bodies.  During warm weather the men wore little clothing, but the women would wear minimal skirts made of animal hides.  During the cold weather they would wear animal skin capes.  European diseases killed many of the Tongva and by 1870 the area had few remaining native inhabitants.&lt;ref name=&quot;Fred&quot;&gt;[http://www.datarecoverypomona.com/data-recovery-montebello.html Data Recovery Montebello California (CA) - Data Retrieval Montebello California (CA) - Data Restoration Montebello California (CA)&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;

Franciscan Missionaries, Fathers Angel Somera and Pedro Cambon, founded the original [[Mission San Gabriel Arcangel]] on September 8, 1771 near where San Gabriel Boulevard intersects the Rio Hondo River. Additionally, it is also close to the present day Sanchez Adobe Mansion.  This marked the beginning of the Los Angeles region's settlement by Spaniards.  The San Gabriel Mission is the fourth of twenty-one &lt;ref name=&quot;cityofmontebello1&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.cityofmontebello.com/about/history_/default.asp |title=History |publisher=City of Montebello |date=1920-10-19 |accessdate=2010-08-03}}&lt;/ref&gt; missions that would ultimately be established along California's [[El Camino Real (California)|El Camino Real]]. The San Gabriel mission did well as a cattle ranch and farm, but six years after its founding a destructive flood led the mission fathers to relocate the establishment to its current location farther north in present day city of [[San Gabriel, California|San Gabriel]]. The original mission site is now marked by a [[California Historical Landmark]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | title =Los Angeles | work =California Historical Landmarks  | publisher =California Department of Parks &amp; Recreation Office of Historic Preservation | year =2004 | url =http://ohp.parks.ca.gov/default.asp?page_id=21427 | accessdate =2007-07-30}}&lt;/ref&gt;

During the early years of the mission, the region operated under a Rancho system.  The lands which now compose the city of Montebello were originally parts of [[Rancho San Antonio (Lugo)|Rancho San Antonio]], [[Rancho La Merced]], and [[Rancho Paso de Bartolo]]. The Juan Matias Sanchez Adobe, built in 1844, still stands at the center of old Rancho La Merced in East Montebello. Recently restored, is the city's oldest structure.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.cityofmontebello.com/about/history_/default.asp City of Montebello - History&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt; The [[Battle of Rio San Gabriel]] took place in Montebello on January 8, 1847. This battle that gave the control of Los Angeles and Alta California to the United States, and was an important decisive factor in  winning the [[Mexican-American war]].  Today the site is California State Historical Landmark #385, and there are two old cannons and a plaque commemorating the battle overlooking the river on Bluff Rd. and Washington Blvd.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book | author=Bauer, K. Jack  | title=The Mexican War, 1846–1848 | publisher=Macmillan | location=New York | year=1974 | isbn=0-8032-6107-1}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Following the [[American Civil War]], some {{convert|5000|acre|abbr=on}} of the [[East Los Angeles (region)|East Los Angeles region]] was owned by an Italian settler from [[Genoa]], Alessandro Repetto. After Repetto's death in 1885, his brother sold his rancho to  a consortium of five Los Angeles businessmen including banker [[Isaias Hellman]] and wholesale grocer/historian [[Harris Newmark]] for $60,000, or about $12 per acre.&lt;ref name=&quot;cityofmontebello1&quot;/&gt;

Later the land was divided among the partners, one large parcel of approximately {{convert|2000|acre|abbr=on}} going to a partnership of Newmark and his nephew, banker Kaspare Cohn. It was out of the Newmark and Cohn share of {{convert|1200|acre|abbr=on}} that Montebello had its beginnings in May 1899.  After seeking the advice of [[hydraulic engineer]] [[William Mulholland]] in drafting the design and building a water system,  the land was subdivided.  In 1900 the completed water system was incorporated as the Montebello Land and Water Company.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | title =Sixty years in Southern California, 1853–1913, containing the reminiscences of Harris Newmark | work =American Memory | publisher =Library of Congress | url =http://memory.loc.gov/cgi-bin/query/r?ammem/calbk:@field(DOCID+@lit(calbk023div45)) | accessdate =2007-07-30}}&lt;/ref&gt;

An area of {{convert|200|acre|abbr=on}}, adjacent to the tracks of the [[Los Angeles and Salt Lake Railroad|San Pedro, Los Angeles &amp; Salt Lake Railroad]] (now part of the [[Union Pacific Railroad]]) were developed into a townsite called Newmark, and the remainder of the land was subdivided into {{convert|5|acre|abbr=on}} lots suitable for small-scale agriculture. On Mulholland's suggestion, Montebello, was adopted as the city's name, replacing the original name Newmark.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news | last =Rasmussen | first =Cecilia | title =City names stem from trees, ranches - even a goddess | work =Los Angeles Times | pages =B2 | date =July 29, 2007 | accessdate =2007-07-30}}&lt;/ref&gt; The name, Montebello, which means ''beautiful mountain'' in both Italian and Spanish, is shared with several other communities in Europe and the Americas.

Originally an agricultural community in the early 20th century, Montebello was known for its prolific production of flowers, berries, fruits, and vegetables.  The first flower show was sponsored by the Montebello Woman’s Club and held in the [[Montebello High School]] auditorium on Whittier Boulevard in 1912.&lt;ref name=&quot;cityofmontebello1&quot;/&gt;  The Montebello – El Carmel (South Montebello) Improvement Association, the predecessor of the Montebello Chamber of Commerce, operated from September 1907 to April 1912. Its purpose was “to improve and beautify the community.” Some of its achievements were: Whittier Boulevard was paved, trees planted along the streets, laid the groundwork and established the first high school,  strived to have the name of Newmark dropped and to have the entire area incorporated as the City of Montebello.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.montebellochamber.org/History.aspx |title=Chamber History |publisher=Montebellochamber.org |date= |accessdate=2010-08-03}}&lt;/ref&gt;  On October 19, 1920, the city's name was officially changed to Montebello and it was incorporated as the 35th of the present cities in Los Angeles County, and the official seal contained a red poinsettia in the center.&lt;ref name=&quot;cityofmontebello1&quot;/&gt;

The [[Standard Oil Company]] discovered oil in the Montebello hills in 1917, on the [[Baldwin]] and Temple properties.  This discovery revolutionized the face of Montebello. The formerly agricultural hills became oil fields, and were eventually producing one-eighth of California's crude oil.&lt;ref name=&quot;MTB1&quot;/&gt; For sixty years, the Montebello hills were dotted with nodding oil wells.&lt;ref name=&quot;cityofmontebello1&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;http://www.mkhs.org/apps/pages/index.jsp?uREC_ID=62613&amp;type=d&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Image:Armenian Genocide Memorial, Montebello, California.jpg|thumb|right|200px|none|[[Armenian Genocide]] Memorial in Montebello]]

Montebello is home to the oldest Armenian Community in Los Angeles County and home to the only Armenian [[Cathedral]] in California, [[Holy Cross Armenian Apostolic Cathedral]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.cathedralsofcalifornia.com/?tag=armenian |title=Armenian |publisher=Cathedrals of California |date= |accessdate=2010-08-03}}&lt;/ref&gt;  The [[Armenian Martyrs Monument]] at Bicknell Park commemorating the victims of the Armenian Genocide by the Ottoman Turks is the largest monument found on public property in the World.&lt;ref name=&quot;MTB1&quot;&gt;[http://www.streetgangs.com/hispanic/montebello Montebello, California – Hispanic Gangs | Street Gangs Resource Center&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.armenian-genocide.org/Memorial.118/current_category.75/offset.10/memorials_detail.html |title=Monument at Bicknell Park in Montebello, California |publisher=Armenian-genocide.org |date=1965-04-24 |accessdate=2010-08-03}}&lt;/ref&gt;
[[Armenian Apostolic Church|Armenian Church]] in Montebello  It is inscribed:
:''This Monument Erected By Americans Of Armenian Decent, Is Dedicated To The 1,500,000 Armenian Victims Of The [[Genocide]] Perpetrated By The Turkish Government 1915–1921, And To Men Of All Nations Who Have Fallen Victim To Crimes Against Humanity.&quot;
::(Script is also is Armenian).''  ''The Annual Armenian Food Fair is  hosted in May every year at Holy Cross Cathedral in Montebello.''
Montebello was also home to a significant Japanese community. The city's Japanese residents operated the four nurseries in town, but were sent to internment camps during [[World War II]].  Japanese-Peruvian and Japanese-Hawaiian communities later settled in the area after WWII.&lt;ref name=&quot;Fred&quot;/&gt; When the Japanese citizens returned from the internment camps after the war, most found they had lost their property.  One of the nurseries had been taken over and cared for by a loyal employee, a young French-American, named Fred Sarrazin.&lt;ref name=fred&gt;http://www.docstoc.com/docs/23500751/Sending-Flowers-to-America&lt;/ref&gt;  After the war, he returned the nursery to its rightful owner, George Mori.  In turn, Mr. Mori gave Sarrazin employment at the nursery for his lifetime, and the Mori Nursery was able to continue under its original name.&lt;ref name=fred/&gt; Today, the Japanese population in Montebello is over 11% of the total population.&lt;ref name=&quot;cityofmontebello1&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;MTB1&quot;/&gt;

==Demographics==
{{USCensusPop
| 1930=5498
| 1940=8016
| 1950=21735
| 1960=32097
| 1970=42807
| 1980=52929
| 1990=59564
| 2000=62150
| 2010=62500
| footnote=source:&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web  |url=http://www.census.gov/prod/www/abs/decennial/index.html  |title=Census of Population and Housing (1790–2000) |publisher=[[U.S. Census Bureau]]  |accessdate=2010-07-30}}&lt;/ref&gt;
}}

===2010===
The [[2010 United States Census]]&lt;ref&gt;{{USCensus-2010CA}}&lt;/ref&gt; reported that Montebello had a population of 62,500. The [[population density]] was 7,464.7 people per square mile (2,882.1/km²). The racial makeup of Montebello was 33,633 (53.8%) [[White (U.S. Census)|White]], 567 (0.9%) [[African American (U.S. Census)|African American]], 634 (1.0%) [[Native American (U.S. Census)|Native American]], 6,850 (11.0%) [[Asian (U.S. Census)|Asian]], 58 (0.1%) [[Pacific Islander (U.S. Census)|Pacific Islander]], 18,431 (29.5%) from [[Race (United States Census)|other races]], and 2,327 (3.7%) from two or more races.  [[Hispanic (U.S. Census)|Hispanic]] or [[Latino (U.S. Census)|Latino]] of any race were 49,578 persons (79.3%). 

The largest percentage of residents who reside in Montebello are Mexican-American. Montebello is the neighboring city just east of East Los Angeles, and is well known for its Mexican-American history and culture.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.drugrehabmontebello.com/ |title=Drug Rehab, Montebello, Alcohol Treatment, Drug Rehab, Drug Addiction Recovery And Rehab Programs |publisher=Drugrehabmontebello.com |date= |accessdate=2010-08-03}}&lt;/ref&gt;  Montebello also has a significant contingent of Armenian-Americans.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://sinosoul.com/2010/05/a-goat-roast-at-chic-la-wine-festival-armenian-food-fair-on-the-lamb-high-tea/ |title=A Goat Roast at Chic, LA Wine Festival, Armenian Food Fair, On the Lamb High Tea |publisher=sinosoul.com |date=2010-05-05 |accessdate=2010-08-03}}&lt;/ref&gt; 38.3% of residents are foreign born, and 75.6% speak a language other than English in the home.&lt;ref name=&quot;MTB1&quot; /&gt;

The Census reported that 62,100 people (99.4% of the population) lived in households, 39 (0.1%) lived in non-institutionalized group quarters, and 361 (0.6%) were institutionalized.  

There were 19,012 households, out of which 8,168 (43.0%) had children under the age of 18 living in them, 9,088 (47.8%) were [[marriage|opposite-sex married couples]] living together, 4,031 (21.2%) had a female householder with no husband present, 1,651 (8.7%) had a male householder with no wife present.  There were 1,302 (6.8%) [[POSSLQ|unmarried opposite-sex partnerships]], and 134 (0.7%) [[same-sex partnerships|same-sex married couples or partnerships]]. 3,350 households (17.6%) were made up of individuals and 1,640 (8.6%) had someone living alone who was 65 years of age or older. The average household size was 3.27.  There were 14,770 [[family (U.S. Census)|families]] (77.7% of all households); the average family size was 3.67.

The population was spread out with 16,142 people (25.8%) under the age of 18, 6,414 people (10.3%) aged 18 to 24, 17,567 people (28.1%) aged 25 to 44, 13,857 people (22.2%) aged 45 to 64, and 8,520 people (13.6%) who were 65 years of age or older.  The median age was 34.7 years. For every 100 females there were 93.3 males.  For every 100 females age 18 and over, there were 89.5 males.

There were 19,768 housing units at an average density of 2,361.0 per square mile (911.6/km²), of which 8,766 (46.1%) were owner-occupied, and 10,246 (53.9%) were occupied by renters. The homeowner vacancy rate was 0.9%; the rental vacancy rate was 4.1%.  29,095 people (46.6% of the population) lived in owner-occupied housing units and 33,005 people (52.8%) lived in rental housing units.

===2000===
As of the [[census]] of 2000, there were 62,150 people, 18,844 households, and 14,867 families residing in the city.{{GR|2}} The [[population density]] was 7,536.9 people per square mile (2,908.6/km²). There were 19,416 housing units at an average density of 2,354.6 per square mile (908.7/km²). The racial makeup of the city was 46.82% [[White (U.S. Census)|White]], 0.90% [[African-American (U.S. Census)|African-American]], 1.23% [[Native American (U.S. Census)|Native American]], 11.64% [[Asian (U.S. Census)|Asian]], 0.08% [[Pacific Islander (U.S. Census)|Pacific Islander]], 33.85% from [[Race (United States Census)|other races]], and 5.48% from two or more races. [[Hispanic (U.S. Census)|Hispanic]] or [[Latino (U.S. Census)|Latino]] of any race were 74.57% of the population, some of which are also included in the census of the white population.&lt;ref name=&quot;epodunk1&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.epodunk.com/cgi-bin/popInfo.php?locIndex=10538 |title=Montebello - Montebello - Population overview |publisher=Epodunk.com |date= |accessdate=2010-08-03}}&lt;/ref&gt;

There were 18,844 households out of which 40.2% had children under the age of 18 living with them, 51.5% were [[Marriage|married couples]] living together, 20.1% had a female head of household and 21.1% were unrelated individuals. 17.1% of all households consisted of a single individual and 8.0% had persons who were 65 years of age or older living alone.  The average household size was 3.28 and the average family size was 3.67.

The 2000 census data counted persons as 28.6% under the age of 18, 10.4% from 18 to 24, 30.3% from 25 to 44, 18.2% from 45 to 64, and 12.4% who were 65 years of age or older.  The median age was 34.32 years. For every 100 females there were 92.4 males.  For every 100 females age 18 and over, there were 88.3 males.

The median [[income]] for a household in the city was $38,805, and the median income for a family was $41,257. Males had a median income of $30,423 versus $26,590 for females. The [[per capita income]] for the city was $15,125.  16.3% of residents have a bachelor’s degree or higher and 69% of residents have a high school degree.  About 14.2% of families and 13.2% of the population were living below the [[poverty line]], including 24.3% of those under age 18 and 10.7% of those age 65 or over.

==Government and infrastructure==
In the [[California State Legislature|state legislature]] Montebello is located in the 30th [[California State Senate|Senate]] District, represented by Democrat [[Ronald S. Calderon]], and in the 58th [[California State Assembly|Assembly]] District, represented by Democrat [[Charles M. Calderon]]. Federally, Montebello is located in [[California's 38th congressional district]], which has a [[Cook Partisan Voting Index|Cook PVI]] of D +20 and is represented by Democrat [[Grace Napolitano]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | title = Will Gerrymandered Districts Stem the Wave of Voter Unrest? | publisher = Campaign Legal Center Blog | url=http://www.clcblog.org/blog_item-85.html | accessdate = 2008-02-10}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Montebello utilizes a City Council/City Administrator form of government. The City Council provides political leadership and policy direction.  The City Administrator provides the leadership and management of the city and the department heads.  Montebello has six department heads and some oversee more than one division.

Montebello Redevelopment Agency has  three project areas:
* Montebello Hills Redevelopment Project Area
* Montebello Economic Revitalization Project Area
* South Montebello Industrial Redevelopment Project Area

The [[Los Angeles County Department of Health Services]] operates the Whittier Health Center in [[Whittier, California|Whittier]], serving Montebello.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;[http://publichealth.lacounty.gov/phn/docs/HealthCenter/whittier.pdf Whittier Health Center].&quot; Los Angeles County Department of Health Services. Retrieved on March 18, 2010.&lt;/ref&gt;

The [[United States Postal Service]] operates the Montebello Post Office at 145 North 5th Street and the Montebello Hills Post Office at 2547 Via Campo.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;[http://usps.whitepages.com/service/post_office/46471?p=1&amp;s=CA&amp;service_name=post_office&amp;z=Montebello Post Office Location - MONTEBELLO].&quot; ''[[United States Postal Service]]''. Retrieved on December 6, 2008.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;&quot;[http://usps.whitepages.com/service/post_office/69011?p=1&amp;s=CA&amp;service_name=post_office&amp;z=Montebello Post Office Location - Montebello Hills].&quot; ''[[United States Postal Service]]''. Retrieved on December 6, 2008.&lt;/ref&gt;

==Economy==
===Budget crisis===	
The City of Montebello has some difficult choices ahead of them as they have a projected $2 million deficit, and also Federal officials are asking for the return of $1.3 million in housing money they allege the city mismanaged.  The city is also being sued by a businessman who alleges Montebello unlawfully borrowed approximately $19 million from its redevelopment agency late in 2010.
&lt;ref name=&quot;sfgate.com&quot;&gt;{{cite news| url=http://www.sfgate.com/cgi-bin/article.cgi?f=/n/a/2011/02/23/state/n151004S04.DTL | work=The San Francisco Chronicle | title=Montebello probed over mystery bank accounts | date=2011-02-25}} {{Dead link|date=May 2011|bot=RjwilmsiBot}}&lt;/ref&gt;

There are also more difficult issues being addressed: &quot;How much does it cost to rebuild a street? A mile-long length of street costs $1.6 million.&quot; &quot;How much does a bus cost? $560,000, but its value becomes $5,000 once they’re done with it later, after many years of service.&quot;  &quot;How many of the city's ancient computers need to be replaced?  Last year, the city laid off 26 employees, and closed a fire station. In light of the scandals happening in nearby cities in Southern California, Councilman Frank Gomez immediately asked the onerous question: &quot;Has the city been mis-managed for the last quarter century?” &lt;ref&gt;http://egpnews.com/?p=17636&lt;/ref&gt;
 	
Avoiding a definite answer, Randy Narramore replied, “I don’t think it’s one thing. It’s been happening for a number of years, the city “cannot keep borrowing”.  Narramore stated that  “Overtime is a major issue.&quot;  He then posted a chart that demonstrated that fire and police personnel are sometimes getting as much in overtime and benefits, as they do in salaries, i.e., there was one captain that received more in overtime, $105,000, than he did in salary, $91,000.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://egpnews.com/?p=17636 |title=Montebello Budget Crisis Likely to Affect Police, Fire : Eastern Group Publications |publisher=Egpnews.com |date=2010-04-22 |accessdate=2010-08-06}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Missing funds===	
In addition to the shortfall, there is the mystery of how the city of Montebello has misplaced the records explaining the fate of more than $1 million that were sitting in some of &quot;off-the-books&quot; accounts.  City officials said that only $5,000 was left in an &quot;off-the-books&quot; Union Bank  account that had once had about $900,000.  The discovery was made shortly after an unofficial city account that held $240,000 was discovered at Banco Popular.  An investigation will be handled by the District Attorney's public integrity unit.
&lt;ref name=&quot;sfgate.com&quot;/&gt;  &lt;ref name=Whit&gt;http://www.whittierdailynews.com/ci_17444887&lt;/ref&gt;

Prosecutors in Los Angeles County Dist. Atty. Steve Cooley's Public Integrity Division  said they are in the process of examining what happened with those funds.  Furthermore, the federal [[Department of Housing and Urban Development]] has told Montebello to return more than $1.3 million that HUD says was improperly spent.
&lt;ref name=&quot;funds&quot;&gt;{{cite news| url=http://latimesblogs.latimes.com/lanow/2011/04/montebello-city-manager-abruptly-resigns-amid-fiscal-crisis.html?utm_source=feedburner&amp;utm_medium=feed&amp;utm_campaign=Feed%3A+lanowblog+%28L.A.+Now%29 | work=Los Angeles Times | title=L.A. Now}}&lt;/ref&gt;	The city has also been sued by a businessman who claims it  borrowed up to $19 million in unsanctioned funds from its redevelopment agency in 2010.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news| url=http://articles.latimes.com/2011/feb/19/local/la-me-montebello-20110219 | work=Los Angeles Times | first1=Jessica | last1=Garrison | first2=Richard | last2=Winton | date=2011-02-19 | title=Fiscal mess fuels crisis in Montebello}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Until the DA's office stepped in, the City Attorney, former City Administrator Richard Torres, members of the City Council, and [[Union Bank]], where the biggest mystery account had been held, have offered little or no explanation or had shown any signs of an investigation. City officials have said they have no idea why the accounts weren't on the Montebello's books or where the money had gone.  Former seven-time mayor and current councilman Bill Molinari stated he thinks an accounting from the city will be forthcoming shortly. &quot;Most likely the Union Bank fund was a Money market account, which held redevelopment funds that were drawing interest in line with state law,&quot; Molinari said. Commenting further, he said, &quot;Quite frankly, there's nothing going on over here, that's the gospel truth.&quot; &lt;ref name=Whit/&gt;

Two weeks after Interim City Manager Peter Cosentini warned council members that they needed to take &quot;immediate corrective action&quot; and need to call a special meeting or the city would not be able to make payroll or pay its bills by the end of the year.  &quot;We need to move quickly because clearly the wall is in front of us,&quot; &lt;ref&gt;http://www.topix.com/city/montebello-ca/2011/04/montebello-weighs-fee-and-tax-increase-to-deal-with-looming-fiscal-crisis&lt;/ref&gt;  Interim City Administrator Peter Cosentini said. &quot;It is in view.&quot;  Cosentini was ignored and resigned effective immediately. He stated that he was stepping down because he was &quot;no longer comfortable with our progress toward a balanced budget.&quot; &lt;ref name=&quot;funds&quot;/&gt;

==Top employers==
According to the City's 2009 Comprehensive Annual Financial Report, the top employers in the city are:&lt;ref name=&quot;cafr2009&quot;&gt;[http://www.cityofmontebello.com/civica/filebank/blobdload.asp?BlobID=2851#page= City of Montebello CAFR]&lt;/ref&gt;

{| class=&quot;wikitable&quot;
|-
! #
! Employer
! # of Employees
|-
| 1
|[[Kaiser Permanente]]
|4,496
|-
| 2
|[[Montebello Unified School District]]
|3,577
|-
| 3
|Monarch Litho
|2,865
|-
| 4
|[[Montebello Town Center]]
|1,897
|-
| 5
|Beverly Hospital
|860
|-
| 6
|[[Bimbo Bakeries USA]]
|750
|-
| 7
|Minson
|633
|-
| 8
|City of Montebello
|601
|-
| 9
|[[Costco]]
|300
|-
| 10
|Royal Paper Box
|170
|}

==Police department==
The City of Montebello has its own police department. The department consists of 87 sworn officers and 10 sergeants.  The department also employs 59 civilian personnel organized into three divisions: Field Services, Investigative Services, and Support Services.  Augmenting the department are a Reserve Officer Corps, a Police Explorer Program, a Police Chaplain Corps and a civilian Citizen’s on Patrol program.

The department provides a  variety of services including Neighborhood Watch, the Citizen’s Academy and a child seat loan program. The Crime prevention Bureau provides free security inspections to local businesses and residents.  The department upholds five core values: Quality, Integrity, Service, Compassion, and Pride.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.cityofmontebello.com/depts/police/mission.asp |title=Mission Statement |publisher=City of Montebello |date= |accessdate=2010-08-03}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://cityofmontebello.com/depts/police/default.asp |title=Police |publisher=City of Montebello |date= |accessdate=2010-08-03}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Education==
The city is served by the [[Montebello Unified School District]]. M.U.S.D. serves the city of Montebello, portions of the cities of Bell Gardens, Commerce, Downey, Rosemead, Pico Rivera, and Monterey Park, as well as the unincorporated community of South San Gabriel, and a part of the unincorporated community of East Los Angeles.  The District is one of the largest and most diverse in Los Angeles County with an enrollment of more than 35,000 K–12 students and 30,000 adults enrolled in Adult Education.  There are eighteen elementary schools, six intermediate schools, four high schools,  and four adult schools.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.montebello.k12.ca.us/schools/default.htm |title=Montebello Unified School District &amp;#124; Schools |publisher=Montebello.k12.ca.us |date= |accessdate=2010-08-03}}&lt;/ref&gt; The four high schools in the [[Montebello Unified School District]] are the historic [[Montebello High School]], founded in 1909,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.mhs.montebello.k12.ca.us/ |title=Montebello High School &amp;#124; Home |publisher=Mhs.montebello.k12.ca.us |date= |accessdate=2010-08-03}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Bell Gardens High School]], [[Schurr High School]] and [[Vail High School]], an [[alternative high school]] (grades 10–12).

Saint Benedict School, a private parochial grammar school, K-8, is operated on Saint Benedict Church property. It opened in September 1941 and was formally dedicated on Pearl Harbor Day, December 7, 1941.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.st-benedict.com/ Home&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;

A private parochial high school, [[Cantwell-Sacred Heart of Mary High School]], is  also located in Montebello. Originally two separate gender-segregated High Schools, they merged in the 1991, the Sacred Heart of Mary campus moving to the Cantwell campus.  This monumental endeavor has taken and incorporated the very best from each of the these two educational traditions.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.cshm.org/a_ourhistory.html |title=History of CSHM |publisher=Cshm.org |date= |accessdate=2010-08-03}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===New high school===
A $30 million high school, Applied Technology Center is scheduled to open in Fall, 2011. The new facility will offer high school students college-focused instruction with state-of-the-art technical training. Located on the corner of Mines and Maple avenues, the campus will open to 720 students.  &quot;It's an integrated education, with all the classes related to an academic academy,&quot; an official said.  The campus can accommodate 750 students, all of whom had to apply to qualify to attend the new technical school.&lt;ref name=&quot;new&quot;&gt;http://www.whittierdailynews.com/ci_17386593?source=rss_viewed&lt;/ref&gt;

Board of education President Edwin Chau said the ATC will offer students a &quot;rigorous academic curriculum and career technical education within a full-day schedule.&quot;  At Montebello Unified, we have made it our goal to ensure our students graduate from our district career-ready and college prepared,&quot; Chau said. &quot;The new Applied Technology Center is truly taking our efforts to the next level.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;new&quot;/&gt;
The project is being paid for with a $98 million Measure M bond, which voters passed in November 2004.&lt;ref name=&quot;new&quot;/&gt;

==Montebello city parks==
[[Image:Montebello Barnyard Zoo.JPG|thumb|200px|left|none|Grant Rea Park Sign / Montebello Barnyard Zoo]]
[[Image:MontebelloHorseTrailGrantReaPark.JPG|thumb|200px|left|none|Horses on the trails]]

The Montebello Parks and Recreation Division provides recreational services for all age groups, from small children to the growing senior citizen community. Their Mission Statement is: “Creating Community Through People, Parks &amp; Recreation”.

*The popular Grant Rea Park, is home to the Montebello Barnyard Zoo, Pony Rides, Train Rides and a Merry Go Round.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.montebellobarnyardzoo.com/about.html :: Montebello Barnyard Zoo ::&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;
*Bicknell Park, where the [[Montebello Genocide Memorial]] is located.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://armenian-genocide.org/Memorial.118/.../memorials_detail.html |title=Monument at Bicknell Park in Montebello, California |publisher=Armenian-genocide.org |date=1965-04-24 |accessdate=2010-08-03}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*The oldest park is Montebello City Park, 1300 W Whittier Blvd. which is now home to Montebello Skateboard Park located where, in the 1950s, were quiet fishponds. The skateboard park is highly rated by local skateboarders, was opened in 2002.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.socalskateparks.com/park/Montebello |title=Montebello Montebello Skateboard Park Montebello, CA Southern California Skateboard Parks Montebello Skatepark |publisher=Socal Skateparks .Com |date= |accessdate=2010-08-03}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*The Sanchez Adobe Park is home to the Juan Matias Sanchez Adobe, the oldest standing structure in the City of Montebello, built in 1845.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.letsgoseeit.com/index/county/la/montebello/loc02/sanchez_adobe.htm |title=Juan Sanchez Adobe |publisher=LetsGoSeeIt.com |date= |accessdate=2010-08-03}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*Ashiya Park, named for Montebello's sister city in Japan.
*Henry Acuna Park, named in honor of the only Montebello Police Department Officer killed while on duty.  In Henry's memory a Marker of Honor and Tree of Life was placed at the entrance of Acuna Park.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.mtbpoa.com/Memorial.htm |title=MPOA ~ Memorial Page |publisher=Mtbpoa.com |date= |accessdate=2010-08-03}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*Reggie Rodriquez Park is named for a [[Vietnam War]] hero&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.virtualwall.org/dr/RodriguezRJ01a.htm Reginald Rodriguez, LCPL, Marine Corps, Montebello CA, 17Feb69 32W052 - The Virtual Wall&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt; and is a {{convert|11|acre|abbr=on}} area on which is located the Reggie Rodriguez Community Center, noted for its unique architecture and providing a central location for activities for the at-risk youth population in the city.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://archrecord.construction.com/projects/BTS/archives/public/ReggieRodriguez/overview.asp |title=Architectural Record Building Types Study &amp;#124; Reggie Rodriguez Community Center |publisher=Archrecord.construction.com |date= |accessdate=2010-08-03}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*Chet Holifield Park, which is home to the Chet Holifield Branch Library in south Montebello. The name of the library and park honors  Congressman Chet Holifield, 19th District (served 1943–1974).&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.americantowns.com/ca/montebello/organization/chet_holifield_library Chet Holifield Library - Montebello California CA - AmericanTowns.com&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;
*Potrero Heights Park is located at the northern-most point in Montebello.

==Golf course==
Montebello Municipal Golf Course's history that dates back to 1928, when it was built as an enterprising country club designed by Max Behr, (Golf Course Architect). The City of Montebello purchased the course in 1941.&lt;ref name=&quot;golf&quot;&gt;[http://www.cityofmontebello.com/depts/golf_course/default.asp City of Montebello - Golf Course&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt; The 120 acre, 18-hole public championship course was remodeled in 1998-99 reopening on May 7, 1999. The remodel included the addition of 3 lakes all new greens, tees, bunkers and cart paths. Architects for the remodel were David Rainville and Gary Bye. Montebello Country Club is now recognized as one of the best municipal golf courses in Southern California.&lt;ref name=&quot;golf&quot;/&gt; Golf lessons are available at The Montebello Country Club. These lessons are available for the beginners to advanced golfers. Lessons are given by appointment. There are 4 golf instructors available, 2 of which are bilingual in Korean and Spanish.&lt;ref name=&quot;golf&quot;/&gt;

Located in the Golf Course grounds is the &quot;Quiet Cannon&quot; and conference center. The banquet room holds up to 500 people. There is over {{convert|30000|sqft|m2|abbr=on}} of private event space to accommodate groups of 25 or more guests.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.quietcannon.com/&lt;/ref&gt;

===Tree division===

The Tree Division is in charge of maintaining the trees throughout the City located in the parkways, street medians, parks and golf course. There are an estimated total of 20,000 trees on city property. The Tree Division has been recognized by the National Arbor Day Foundation for the outstanding management of the city’s urban forest, and has been a recipient of the Tree City U.S.A. award for the past 19 years.&lt;ref name=&quot;golf&quot;/&gt;

==Geography and climate==
{{Weather box
|location = Montebello, CA
|single line = yes
|Jan record high F = 91
|Feb record high F = 95
|Mar record high F = 100
|Apr record high F = 104
|May record high F = 105
|Jun record high F = 108
|Jul record high F = 108
|Aug record high F = 106
|Sep record high F = 113
|Oct record high F = 106
|Nov record high F = 100
|Dec record high F = 88
|year record high F = 113
|Jan high F = 69.7
|Feb high F = 71.3
|Mar high F = 72.6
|Apr high F = 77.4
|May high F = 79.2
|Jun high F = 84.2
|Jul high F = 88.9
|Aug high F = 89.4
|Sep high F = 87.5
|Oct high F = 82.2
|Nov high F = 75.2
|Dec high F = 70.7
|year high F = 79.0
|Jan mean F = 58.8
|Feb mean F = 60.0
|Mar mean F = 61.6
|Apr mean F = 65.3
|May mean F = 68.1
|Jun mean F = 72.6
|Jul mean F = 76.6
|Aug mean F = 77.4
|Sep mean F = 75.7
|Oct mean F = 70.3
|Nov mean F = 63.6
|Dec mean F = 59.0
|year mean F = 67.4
|Jan low F = 47.9
|Feb low F = 48.7
|Mar low F = 50.5
|Apr low F = 53.1
|May low F = 56.9
|Jun low F = 60.9
|Jul low F = 64.3
|Aug low F = 65.4
|Sep low F = 63.8
|Oct low F = 58.4
|Nov low F = 52.0
|Dec low F = 47.3
|year low F = 55.8
|Jan record low F = 30
|Feb record low F = 29
|Mar record low F = 33
|Apr record low F = 39
|May record low F = 30
|Jun record low F = 30
|Jul record low F = 38
|Aug record low F = 44
|Sep record low F = 50
|Oct record low F = 44
|Nov record low F = 37
|Dec record low F = 30
|year record low F = 29
|Jan precipitation inch = 3.53
|Feb precipitation inch = 3.60
|Mar precipitation inch = 2.94
|Apr precipitation inch = 0.90
|May precipitation inch = 0.23
|Jun precipitation inch = 0.06
|Jul precipitation inch = 0.01
|Aug precipitation inch = 0.02
|Sep precipitation inch = 0.17
|Oct precipitation inch = 0.31
|Nov precipitation inch = 1.00
|Dec precipitation inch = 1.67
|year precipitation inch = 14.44
|source 1 = http://www.wrcc.dri.edu/cgi-bin/cliMAIN.pl?ca5790 &lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | author=WRCC | title=Western U.S. Climate Historical Summaries Weather | url=http://www.wrcc.dri.edu/cgi-bin/cliMAIN.pl?ca5790 | publisher=Desert Research Institute | date= | accessdate=2011-02-12}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|date=February 2011
}}

Montebello is located {{convert|8|mi|abbr=on}} east of [[downtown Los Angeles]] at the southwestern part of the San Gabriel Valley. The surrounding cities are [[Monterey Park, California|Monterey Park]], [[South San Gabriel, California|South San Gabriel]], and [[Rosemead, California|Rosemead]] to the north, [[Commerce, California|Commerce]] to the south, [[Pico Rivera, California|Pico Rivera]] to the east, and [[Los Angeles]] and [[East Los Angeles, California|East Los Angeles]] to the west. It is also sometimes considered part of the [[Gateway Cities]], and the city is a member of the Gateway Cities Council of Governments.

According to the [[United States Census Bureau]], the city has a total area of {{convert|8.4|m²|abbr=on}}, of which {{convert|8.2|m2|abbr=on}} are land and {{convert|0.1|m²|abbr=on}} or 1.32% is water.

The city is easily accessible to the [[Long Beach Freeway|Long Beach-]] (I-710), [[Interstate 605|San Gabriel River-]] (I-605), [[Pomona Freeway|Pomona-]] (SR 60) and [[Santa Ana Freeway|Santa Ana-]] (I-5) freeways.

==Transportation==

Public transportation is provided by the city government's [[Montebello Bus Lines]] &lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.cityofmontebello.com/depts/transit/bus/default.asp |title=Bus Lines |publisher=City of Montebello |date= |accessdate=2010-08-03}}&lt;/ref&gt;  Montebello Bus Lines is the third largest municipal bus system in Los Angeles County with 9.1 million people riding the  buses each year.  Its peak period fleet of 67 buses has been enhanced with the addition of five hybrid gasoline-electric buses. Montebello Bus Lines has plans to purchase 25 more hybrid buses in the next three years, replacing 15 of its diesel fuel buses &lt;ref&gt;Author:Sandra T. Molina Staff Writer|Date: July 22, 2007|
Publication: Whittier Daily News, The (CA)&lt;/ref&gt;  In 2011 it celebrated 80 years of service. It started with four buses but now has a fleet of 66 with service  to 14 communities. &lt;ref&gt;http://www.whittierdailynews.com/ci_18581970&lt;/ref&gt;

[[LINK]], which offers a curb-to-curb shuttle to and from the [[Montebello/Commerce (Metrolink station)|Montebello/Commerce]] Metrolink station.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.cityofmontebello.com/depts/transit/default.asp |title=Transportation |publisher=City of Montebello |date= |accessdate=2010-08-03}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The City of Montebello also operates Montebello Dial-a-Taxi, a program which offers transportation for senior residents and qualified disabled persons of any age and their attendants.  15,000 residents utilize this service.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.cityofmontebello.com/depts/transit/dialtaxi.asp |title=Dial-A-Taxi |publisher=City of Montebello |date=2007-06-04 |accessdate=2010-08-03}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Notable people==
*Eddie Alvarado  actor,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news| url=http://articles.latimes.com/2001/nov/07/local/me-1195 | work=Los Angeles Times | first=Erika | last=Hayasaki | title=A Leading Role for Learning - Los Angeles Times | date=2001-11-07}}&lt;/ref&gt; founder of the blog Hollywood Teen TV,&lt;ref&gt;http://gimmemo.com/12/2010/teen-takes-hollywoods-list&lt;/ref&gt; Schurr High School Class of 2009
* [[Alan Bannister]], born in Montebello, was a former [[MLB]] player.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.baseball-almanac.com/players/player.php?p=bannial01 Alan Bannister Baseball Stats by Baseball Almanac&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[Ken Davitian]], Actor, number of movies most notably played the role of Azamat in the movie &quot;Borat&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.reporter.am/pdfs/C0614.pdf&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[John DeCuir]], Oscar Winning Art Director. Montebello High School Class of 1936. DeCuir earned eleven Oscar nominations, winning three: The King and I (1956), Cleopatra (1963), and Hello, Dolly! (1969).&lt;ref name=&quot;MHS&quot;&gt;[http://www.mhs.montebello.k12.ca.us/ Montebello High School | Home&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;
*[[Oscar De La Hoya]], 10-time boxing world champion &lt;ref&gt;[http://www.infoplease.com/biography/var/oscardelahoya.html#axzz0xiFkUQQf Oscar De La Hoya Biography (Boxer) — Infoplease.com&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.answers.com/topic/oscar-de-la-hoya-1 Oscar De La Hoya: Biography from Answers.com&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[Rodney Eastman]], Actor, A Nightmare on Elm Street 3 &amp; 4.  Graduate of Schurr High School Class of 1985.
* [[Darlene Hard]], (tennis player) 2-time U.S. Nationals Champion (1960, 1961), 1960 French Champion, Fed Cup Champ 1963. Won 18 grand slam titles in doubles and mixed doubles. Born in Montebello and a 1953 graduate of Montebello High.&lt;ref name=&quot;MHS&quot; /&gt;
* [[Jay Hernandez]], actor, he has since appeared in several major Hollywood films, including playing the lead role in the 2005 horror film ''Hostel''.
* [[Bobby Knoop]] Major league Baseball player. MHS Class of 1956 &lt;ref name=&quot;MHS&quot; /&gt;
* [[Jack Kramer]], 3-time Wimbledon Champ, 7-time U.S. Champ, 3-time Davis Cup Champ&lt;ref name=&quot;MHS&quot; /&gt;
* [[Judi Evans|Judi Evans Luciano]]&lt;ref&gt;[http://daysofourlives.about.com/gi/dynamic/offsite.htm?site= http://daysofourlives.about.com/gi/dynamic/offsite.htm?site=] ''daysofourlives.about.com''&lt;/ref&gt; was born in Montebello, star on ''Days of Our Lives''.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web  | title =Judi Evans' Biography | work =Judi Evans Official Website  | url =http://www.judievans.net/site/biography.htm | accessdate =2007-07-30 |archiveurl = http://web.archive.org/web/20080302032815/http://www.judievans.net/site/biography.htm &lt;!-- Bot retrieved archive --&gt; |archivedate = 2008-03-02}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* Dr. [[Bruce Merrifield]], Montebello High School class of 1939, Nobel Prize Winner.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web  | title =Bruce Merrifield - Biography  | publisher =The Nobel Foundation | url =http://nobelprize.org/nobel_prizes/chemistry/laureates/1984/merrifield-bio.html  | accessdate =2007-07-30}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[Edward James Olmos]] was a graduate of Montebello High School.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news | last =Aldama | first =Frederick Luis | title =Edward James Olmos | work =St. James Encyclopedia of Pop Culture | url =http://www.findarticles.com/p/articles/mi_g1epc/is_bio/ai_2419200908 | accessdate =2007-07-30 | year=2002}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*[[Jerry Pimm]]  Men's Basketball Coach , MHS Class of 1956,&lt;ref name=&quot;MHS&quot;/&gt;
*[[Carl Renezeder]], off-road racing champion
* [[Jack Russell (musician)|Jack Russell]], born in Montebello, lead vocalist for [[Great White]].
*[[Mark Salas]], born in Montebello, Major League Baseball player.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|title=The ESPN Baseball Encyclopedia|year=2007|publisher=Sterling Publishing|isbn=1-4027-4771-3|pages=874}}&lt;/ref&gt; 
* [[Hagop Sandaldjian]], microminiature [[sculpture|sculptor]], lived and worked in Montebello after emigrating from [[Yerevan, Armenia]] (then part of the [[Soviet Union]]) in 1980.&lt;ref&gt;[[Lawrence Weschler]], ''[[Mr. Wilson's Cabinet of Wonder]]'' (Pantheon Books, 1995), ISBN 978-0-679-43998-1, pp. 58–60.&lt;/ref&gt;
*[[Catherine Sandoval]], first Latina Rhodes scholar, professor of law, California Public Utilities Commissioner
* Tes Santo Syzonenko, Sacred Heart of Mary Class of 1976, the only young woman to be selected as City of Montebello's Rose Queen, Student Ambassador to Sister City Ashiya, Japan and Ambassador to Sister City in Ensenada, Mexico.&lt;ref&gt;Montebello Messenger News, August, 1977&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;http://www.lacp.org/Links-Tools/LA%20County%20Newspapers.html&lt;/ref&gt;
*[[Tom Tellez Track at Carl Lewis International Complex|Tom Tellez]], Track star. Montebello High School Class of 1951, [[Tom Tellez Track at Carl Lewis International Complex]]&lt;ref name=&quot;MHS&quot;/&gt;
* [[Nosaj Thing]] (aka Jason Chung), hip-hop recording artist,  is a native of Montebello.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.residentadvisor.net/feature.aspx?1111&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[Art Torres]]  Politician. MHS Class of 1964 &lt;ref name=&quot;MHS&quot;/&gt;
* [[Eduardo Xol]] Television Personality. Graduate of Schurr High School Class of 1984

==Sister cities==
*{{flagicon|Japan}} '''[[Ashiya]]''', [[Japan]]
The City of Montebello has been affiliated with the City of Ashiya, Japan since the inception of the Sister City Program in 1961. Student Ambassadors are chosen to travel  to Ashiya every year.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.cityofmontebello.com/about/sister_cities_of_montebello/ashiya_japan/default.asp |title=Ashiya, Japan |publisher=City of Montebello |date= |accessdate=2010-08-03}}&lt;/ref&gt;

* {{flagicon|Nagorno-Karabakh}}({{flagicon|Azerbaijan}})'''[[Stepanakert]]''', [[Nagorno-Karabakh Republic]] ([[Azerbaijan]])
The City of Montebello has been affiliated with the City of Stepanakert, the capital of the unrecognized Nagorno-Karabagh Republic, since  2005, when a much controversial move to facilitate the sister city relationship was made by the Armenian National Committee of the San Gabriel Valley and unanimously approved by the City Council.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.anca.org/press_releases/press_releases.php?prid=834 |title=Despite Azeri Meddling, Montebello City Council Ok’S Sister-City Ties With Stepanakert |publisher=Anca.org |date= |accessdate=2010-08-03}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==References ==
{{Reflist|2}}

==External links==
{{Portal|Los Angeles|Greater Los Angeles|Southern California}}
*[http://www.cityofmontebello.com/ City of Montebello official website]
{{Cities of Los Angeles County, California}}
{{Greater Los Angeles Area}}

[[Category:Communities in the San Gabriel Valley]]
[[Category:Cities in Los Angeles County, California]]
[[Category:Populated places in California with Hispanic majority populations]]
[[Category:Mid-importance Southern California articles]]
[[Category:Incorporated cities and towns in California]]
[[Category:Populated places established in 1771]]

[[ar:مونتيبيلو، لوس أنجليس، كاليفورنيا]]
[[bg:Монтебело (Калифорния)]]
[[ca:Montebello (Califòrnia)]]
[[de:Montebello (Kalifornien)]]
[[es:Montebello (California)]]
[[fr:Montebello (Californie)]]
[[it:Montebello (California)]]
[[sw:Montebello, California]]
[[ht:Montebello, Kalifòni]]
[[nl:Montebello (Californië)]]
[[ja:モンテベロ (カリフォルニア州)]]
[[pt:Montebello (Califórnia)]]
[[ru:Монтебелло (Калифорния)]]
[[vi:Montebello, California]]
[[vo:Montebello (California)]]
[[zh:蒙特贝洛 (加利福尼亚州)]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
