<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="107685" ns="0" title="South Pasadena, California"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Multiple issues
 | POV=December 2007
 | refimprove=December 2007
 | tone=December 2007
}}
{{Infobox settlement
|official_name            = City of South Pasadena
|other_name               =
|native_name              = &lt;!-- for cities whose native name is not in English --&gt;
|nickname                 =
|motto                    =
|image_skyline            =
|imagesize                =
|image_caption            =
|image_flag               =
|flag_size                =
|image_seal               = South Pasadena seal.jpg
|seal_size                =
|image_shield             =
|shield_size              =
|image_blank_emblem       =
|blank_emblem_size        =
|image_map                = LA County Incorporated Areas South Pasadena highlighted.svg
|mapsize                  = 250x200px
|map_caption              = Location of South Pasadena in [[Los Angeles County, California|Los Angeles County]], [[California]]
|image_map1               =
|mapsize1                 =
|map_caption1             =
|subdivision_type         = [[List of countries|Country]]
|subdivision_name         = [[United States]]
|subdivision_type1        = [[Political divisions of the United States|State]]
|subdivision_name1        = [[California]]
|subdivision_type2        = [[List of counties in California|County]]
|subdivision_name2        = [[Los Angeles County, California|Los Angeles]]
|subdivision_type3        =
|subdivision_name3        =
|subdivision_type4        =
|subdivision_name4        =
|government_type          =
|leader_title             = [[City Council]]&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url = http://www.ci.south-pasadena.ca.us/government/citycouncil.html | title = City of South Pasadena: City Council | accessdate = 2008-12-15}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|leader_name              =  David Sifuentes, [[Mayor]]  &lt;br /&gt; Richard D. Schneider, MD
&lt;br /&gt; Michael A. Cacciotti &lt;br /&gt; Philip C. Putnam &lt;br /&gt; Mike Ten
|leader_title1            =[[City Treasurer]]
|leader_name1             =Victor Robinette, [[Certified California Municipal Treasurer|CCMT]], [[Certified Public Accountant|CPA]]
|leader_title2            =[[City Attorney]]
|leader_name2             = Richard L. Adams II
|leader_title3            =[[City Clerk]]
|leader_name3             =Sally Kilby
|established_title        = &lt;!-- Settled --&gt;
|established_date         =
|established_title2       = &lt;!-- Incorporated (town) --&gt;
|established_date2        =
|established_title3       = Incorporated (city)
|established_date3        = March 2, 1888&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url = http://www.cacities.org/resource_files/20457.IncorpDateLO.doc |  title = Incorporation Dates of California Cities | accessdate = 2007-01-18}}&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;!-- Area------------------&gt;
|area_magnitude           =
| unit_pref               =US
| area_footnotes          = &lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.census.gov/geo/www/gazetteer/files/Gaz_places_national.txt |title=U.S. Census |date= |accessdate=2011-11-18}}&lt;/ref&gt;
| area_total_sq_mi        = 3.417
| area_land_sq_mi         = 3.405
| area_water_sq_mi        = 0.012
| area_total_km2          = 8.851
| area_land_km2           = 8.820
| area_water_km2          = 0.031
| area_water_percent      = 0.35
| area_note               = 
|area_urban_km2           =
|area_urban_sq_mi         =
|area_metro_km2           =
|area_metro_sq_mi         =
|population_as_of         = 2010
|population_note          =
|population_footnotes     =
|settlement_type          = [[City]]
|population_total         = 25619
|population_density_km2   = auto
|population_density_sq_mi = auto
|population_metro         =
|population_density_metro_km2     =
|population_density_metro_sq_mi   =
|population_urban                 =
|population_density_urban_km2     =
|population_density_urban_sq_mi   =
|timezone                 = [[Pacific Time Zone|PST]]
|utc_offset               = -8
|timezone_DST             = PDT
|utc_offset_DST           = -7
|coordinates_display      = inline,title
|coordinates_type         = region:US_type:city
|latd = 34 |latm = 6 |lats = 47 |latNS = N
|longd = 118 |longm = 9 |longs = 21 |longEW = W
|elevation_m              = 201
|elevation_ft             = 659
|postal_code_type         = [[ZIP code]]
|postal_code              = 91030/91031 &lt;small&gt;([[Post office box|PO box]])&lt;/small&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url = http://zip4.usps.com/zip4/zcl_1_results.jsp?visited=1&amp;pagenumber=0&amp;state=ca&amp;city=South%20Pasadena | title = USPS&amp;nbsp;— ZIP Code Lookup&amp;nbsp;— Find a ZIP+ 4 Code By City Results | accessdate = 2007-01-18}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|area_code                = [[Area code 323|323]]/[[Area code 626|626]]&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url = http://www.nanpa.com/nas/public/npa_city_query_step2.do?method=displayData&amp;cityToNpaModel.stateAbbr=CA&amp;cityToNpaModel.city=South%20Pasadena | title = Number Administration System&amp;nbsp;— NPA and City/Town Search Results | accessdate = 2007-01-18}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|website                  = [http://www.ci.south-pasadena.ca.us/ http://www.ci.south-pasadena.ca.us/]
|blank_name               = [[Federal Information Processing Standard|FIPS code]]
|blank_info               = 06-73220
|blank1_name              = [[Geographic Names Information System|GNIS]] feature ID
|blank1_info              = 1661479
|footnotes                =
}}
&lt;!-- Infobox ends --&gt;

[[File:Southpasadena ca cityhall.jpg|thumb|280px|right|South Pasadena [[City Hall]]]]
'''South Pasadena''' is a [[city]] in [[Los Angeles County, California|Los Angeles County]], [[California]],  [[United States]]. As of the 2010 census, it had a population of 25,619, up from 24,292 at the 2000 census. It is located in in the West [[San Gabriel Valley]]. It is less than 3 1/2 square miles in in area and lies between the far larger City of [[Pasadena, California|Pasadena]], of which it was once part, and the metropolis of [[Los Angeles]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.ci.south-pasadena.ca.us/about/index.html |title=City of South Pasadena, California - About South Pasadena |publisher=Ci.south-pasadena.ca.us |date= |accessdate=2011-11-18}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Geography==
South Pasadena is located at the western end of the [[San Gabriel Valley]], north of the [[San Rafael Hills]], east of the [[Arroyo Seco (Los Angeles County)|Arroyo Seco]] seasonal river, and south of the separate city of [[Pasadena, California]]. Adjacent cities are Los Angeles to the west and south, Pasadena to the north, [[San Marino, California|San Marino]] to the east, and [[Alhambra, California|Alhambra]] to the southeast. 

South Pasadena is located at {{Coord|34|6|47|N|118|9|21|W|city}} (34.112958, -118.155778).{{GR|1}}

According to the [[United States Census Bureau]], the city has a total area of {{convert|3.42|sqmi|km2}}, virtually all land.

==History==
The original inhabitants of South Pasadena and surrounding areas were members of the Native American [[Hahamog-na]] tribe, a branch of the [[Tongva people|Tongva]] Nation (part of the [[Shoshone]] language group) that occupied the [[Los Angeles Basin]]. The Tongva name for the area that covers modern day South Pasadena and much of Alhambra was Vaytsuung'xuilhoor pronounced /ʋaitsyŋ sʐuilχøɛr/. Tongva dwellings lined the [[Arroyo Seco (Los Angeles County)]] in South Pasadena and south to where it joins the [[Los Angeles River]] and along other natural waterways in the city. They lived in thatched, dome-shape lodges characteristic for their use of carved wood decorations in the [[Nahua peoples|Nava]] style. For food, they lived on a diet of corn meal, seeds and herbs, venison, berries, fruits and other small animals. They traded for ocean fish with the coastal Tongva on a daily basis. They made cooking vessels from steatite [[soapstone]] from [[Santa Catalina Island, California|Catalina Island]]. South Pasadena also has a strong claim to having the oldest and most historic sites in the San Gabriel Valley. For many centuries, its adjacency to a natural fording place along the Arroyo Seco had served as a gateway to travel and commerce for aboriginal peoples here and along the coast. It was here that Hahamognas greeted Portola and the missionaries who later established the [[San Gabriel Mission]] a few miles to the west.  When the Spanish occupied the Los Angeles Basin they built the San Gabriel Mission and renamed the local Tongva people &quot;Gabrielino Indians,&quot; after the name of the mission. Today, several bands of Tongva people live in the Los Angeles area.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://tongva.com/ |title=Gabrieleno/Tongva of San Gabriel |publisher=Tongva.com |date= |accessdate=2011-11-18}}&lt;/ref&gt; While ethnic Tongva survive in South Pasadena, their culture had already been mostly assimilated into the Mexican Hispanic culture by the 1830s making them largely undistinguishable between contemporary Hispanic peoples.

The initial buildings on the [[Rancho San Pascual]], were built on the land  which eventually gave birth to the Cities of Pasadena, South Pasadena and Altadena. The first of these adobe structures became headquarters for General Flores and his staff in 1847 where they agreed to surrender to American forces, ending [[Mexican Colonial rule]] in California.In 1875 the landowners of the area encompassing present-day [[Pasadena, California|Pasadena]] and South Pasadena voted to rename their association, Pasadena. In February 1888, members of the southern portion of Pasadena attempted to gain more control over their own property and a vote for incorporation was made. In 1888, South Pasadena incorporated the southern portion of the Indiana Colony and land south and eastward to the Los Angeles border. On 2 March 1888, the city of South Pasadena was incorporated with a population slightly over 500 residents, becoming the sixth municipality in Los Angeles County.  It was chartered with roughly the same area as the current South Pasadena, about 3.44 square miles (8.91 square kilometers).

South Pasadena's first mayor was William Collier, whose sister, Margaret(a local socialite), later moved with him in the early 1890s to move to what's now south-central Riverside County(and the [[Lake Elsinore]] Valley) to establish a small town with her husband, local businessman Donald Collier;thus the [[Wildomar]] area was founded, now the 25th(and newest) incorporated City in Riverside County(the name &quot;Wildomar&quot; comes from an anagram of their first names:WIL(liam) Collier, DO(nald) Graham and (MAR)garet Collier Graham).

South Pasadena's history is commonly associated with that of the [[Cawston Ostrich Farm]], [[Fair Oaks Pharmacy and Soda Fountain]], and the [[Rialto Theatre (South Pasadena, California)|Rialto Theatre]], as they played major roles in the past of the city.  With completion of the Pacific Electric Short Line, putting the entire city within easy walking distance of the “red car” stations, South Pasadena also became a one of the first suburbs of Los Angeles.

==Modern South Pasadena==
South Pasadena's streets are lined with numerous species of native California trees. These include [[redwood]], [[Sequoia sempervirens|sequoia]], [[Fraxinus|ash]], [[walnut]], and [[sycamore]]. Some non-native trees, such as [[Liquidambar|sweetgum]], are also seen. Because there are very few [[stucco]]-clad [[Spanish Colonial Revival Style architecture|Spanish Colonial]] houses and virtually no palm trees in some parts of the city, South Pasadena is a popular stand-in for Midwestern and Northeastern towns in [[motion picture]] and [[television]] productions.  South Pasadena sits less than {{convert|10|mi|km}} from [[Downtown Los Angeles]]; substantial numbers of residents work either in [[Bunker Hill, Los Angeles, California|Bunker Hill]] or as professors and staff at the [[University of Southern California]].

&quot;Mom and Pop&quot; merchants populate the business district, and the Mission West area is a part of the original [[U.S. Route 66]]. Of note are the historic [[Fair Oaks Pharmacy and Soda Fountain]] and the Rialto Theater in downtown South Pasadena; the theater is a unique blend of Spanish Baroque and Egyptian stylings and was built in 1925. It is one of the last remaining single screen cinemas in the country. The Rialto was added to the [[National Register of Historic Places]] in 1978, having narrowly missed the wrecking ball that year. Unfortunately, it went out of business on August 19, 2007 because of low profits. It has been featured in many films and commercials, most notably Robert Altman's ''[[The Player]]'' and more recently in ''[[Scream 2]]''.

The Farmer's Market has become a fast tradition in the historic Mission-West District of South Pasadena.  Every Thursday from 4pm to 8pm. On the first Saturday of December every year, South Pasadena hosts an annual 5K/10K run around South Pasadena known as the Tiger Run. The 5K has no elevation changes and the 10K has elevation changes on the second half.

South Pasadena can often be seen in motion picture productions with its beautiful tree-lined streets and &quot;anywhere in America&quot; feel. Such movies as ''[[Freaky Friday (1976 film)|Freaky Friday]]'', ''[[The Terminator]]'', ''[[Gone with the Wind (film)|Gone with the Wind]]'', ''[[Halloween (1978 film)|Halloween]]'', ''[[Pee-Wee's Big Adventure]]'', ''[[American Pie (film)|American Pie]]'',''[[The Girl Next Door (2004 film)|The Girl Next Door]]'', ''[[Legally Blonde]]'', ''[[13 Going on 30]]'', ''[[Back to the Future]]'', ''[[Mr. Deeds]]'', ''[[Bruce Almighty]]'', ''[[The Ugly Truth (film)|The Ugly Truth]]'', and ''[[License to Wed]]'' are just a few of the notable films shot on location in South Pasadena. Notable television series that have been filmed there include ''[[Parenthood (2010 TV series)|Parenthood]]'', ''[[Family (TV series)|Family]]'', ''[[Boston Public]]'', ''[[Nip/Tuck]]'', ''[[Desperate Housewives]]'', ''[[Cold Case (TV series)|Cold Case]]'', ''[[Bones (TV series)|Bones]]'', ''[[Modern Family]]'', ''[[No Ordinary Family]]'', ''[[Big Love]]', and CSI: Crime Scene Investigation'.

South Pasadena is the oldest self-builder of floats in the [[Tournament of Roses Parade]].

[[File:Myershouse10.jpg|thumb|280px|right|The house used in the film ''[[Halloween (1978 film)|Halloween]] on Mission Street in South Pasadena.]]

==Interstate 710 extension controversy==
South Pasadena, together with a broad coalition of national, state and local organizations, has opposed the 710 Freeway  [[Long Beach Freeway]] ([[Interstate 710 (California)|I-710]]) extension from Alhambra's Valley Blvd. to the [[Foothill Freeway]] ([[Interstate 210 (California)|I-210]]) in [[Pasadena, California|Pasadena]] at California Blvd. The proposed 1960's route would have sliced through the middle of the city, as well as through neighborhoods in El Sereno and Pasadena impacting nearly 1,000 homes in its path.
On July 19, 1999, United States District Court Judge Pregerson issued a preliminary injunction prohibiting defendants Caltrans, et al., from proceeding with the 710 Freeway Project.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.ci.south-pasadena.ca.us/transportation/710.html |title=City of South Pasadena, California - 710 Freeway |publisher=Ci.south-pasadena.ca.us |date= |accessdate=2011-11-18}}&lt;/ref&gt;
Moral and financial support for the fight against a major highway project through the city has come from all across the country{{Citation needed|date=July 2007}}; however, the bulk of it comes from the residents themselves, who pay legal bills incurred by the city in the freeway fight from their general fund (no special taxes are used), making the fight an ongoing local election issue. South Pasadena has been cited five times on the [[National Trust for Historic Preservation's]] list of &quot;Most Endangered Places.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.preservationnation.org/travel-and-sites/sites/western-region/south-pasadena-el-sereno.html |title=South Pasadena/El Sereno |publisher=Preservationnation.org |date= |accessdate=2011-11-18}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Litigation over the 710 extension has run for  three to four decades. [[Caltrans]] (the California Department of Transportation) proposed a compromise route of boring a tunnel beneath the city. Having purchased hundreds of properties along the proposed right-of-way in the 1960s, Caltrans proposed selling these in order to partially finance the tunnel. The Southern California real estate boom of the early 2000s caused those properties in South Pasadena alone to appreciate to a combined value of over $300 million{{Citation needed|date=February 2011}}.  The City of South Pasadena has filed a federal lawsuit citing failure to protect clean air, the environment and historic properties, and until the California Department of Transportation (Caltrans) completes a comprehensive new environmental study, bringing additional delays to the 40-year-old project.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.ci.south-pasadena.ca.us/transportation/fedpull710.html |title=City of South Pasadena, California -710 Freeway Information |publisher=Ci.south-pasadena.ca.us |date= |accessdate=2011-11-18}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Arroyo Seco==
The [[Arroyo Seco (Los Angeles County)|Arroyo Seco]] (canyon, stream, and cultural landscape) offers a diverse range of experiences for walkers and more experienced hikers. 

The Arroyo Seco stream begins at Red Box near Mount Wilson in the [[San Gabriel Mountains]] and proceeds through steep mountain canyons for eleven miles (18&amp;nbsp;km) until it enters the urban plain of Southern California at the [[Jet Propulsion Laboratory]].  The stream, largely channelized south of Devil's Gate Dam, proceeds in the Arroyo Seco canyon for eleven miles (18&amp;nbsp;km) more: through Pasadena, South Pasadena and Northeast Los Angeles to the confluence with the [[Los Angeles River]] near Elysian Park, Chinatown and downtown Los Angeles.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.arroyoseco.org/HikingAS.htm |title=Arroyo Seco Foundation |publisher=Arroyoseco.org |date= |accessdate=2011-11-18}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Transportation==
[[File:LACMTA Metro Gold Line at South Pasadena.jpg|thumb|The [[Gold Line (Los Angeles Metro)|Los Angeles Metro Gold Line]] passing through South Pasadena.]]
[[Fair Oaks Avenue (Pasadena)|Fair Oaks Avenue]], Huntington Drive, and Mission Street are the main thoroughfares through South Pasadena.

The [[Pasadena Freeway]] has two exits in South Pasadena--[[Orange Grove Avenue]] and [[Fair Oaks Avenue (Pasadena)|Fair Oaks Avenue]].

[[LACMTA]] operates six bus lines (79, 176, 256, 260, 485, 762) through South Pasadena. The [[Gold Line (Los Angeles Metro)|Metro Gold Line]] Mission Station is in the heart of South Pasadena, located at the corner of Mission and Meridian.

South Pasadena operates their own public transportation system. Since 2003, South Pasadena has been operating the City of South Pasadena Community Transit to connect with the Mission Gold Line Station, it schedule is linked to the Gold Line schedule. The system was originally called &quot;South Pasadena Gold Link.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.ci.south-pasadena.ca.us/transportation/goldlink.html |title=City of South Pasadena: Gold Link |publisher=Ci.south-pasadena.ca.us |date= |accessdate=2010-08-04}}&lt;/ref&gt;  Additionally South Pasadena has a transit shuttle that operates around the city. As of 2007, many old and outdated traffic signals have been replaced throughout South Pasadena.

==Schools==
[[File:Spjhs.JPG|thumb|South Pasadena Middle School before the 2009 renovations.]]
The [[South Pasadena Unified School District]] includes five schools: three elementary schools (Monterey Hills, Marengo and Arroyo Vista), [[South Pasadena Middle School]], and [[South Pasadena High School]]. Former elementary schools now closed or renamed are Lincoln (now Arroyo Vista), El Centro (now the School District headquarters, closed), Las Flores (limited grades, near [http://www.laokay.com/halac/FloresAdobe.htm Flores Adobe], historic landmark), &amp; Oneonta (later a private Montessori school).

South Pasadena and the neighboring city of [[San Marino, California|San Marino]] have had a long-standing rivalry. In the early 1900s, these two cities shared the same high school, which was adjacent to the South Pasadena Public Library. Every year, the schools meet during football season to struggle for a victor's plaque that has been passed back and forth for many years. As of 2010, the South Pasadena team has won 28 times and 8 of the last 11 meetings. San Marino has won 25 times, and there have been three ties.

SPEF ([http://www.spef4kids.com/ South Pasadena Educational Foundation]) is a [[501(c)]](3) charity designated by the SPUSD as the official private fund-raising organization for the support of the district's educational programs.&lt;ref&gt;SPEF website&lt;/ref&gt;  They work to help keep the quality of the schools high. Many of SPHS team have won [http://www.cifstate.org/ CIF] titles over the years.

==Demographics==
===2010===
The [[2010 United States Census]]&lt;ref&gt;{{USCensus-2010CA}}&lt;/ref&gt; reported that South Pasadena had a population of 25,619. The [[population density]] was 7,496.4 people per square mile (2,894.4/km²). The racial makeup of South Pasadena was 13,922 (54.3%) [[White (U.S. Census)|White]], 771 (3.0%) [[African American (U.S. Census)|African American]], 107 (0.4%) [[Native American (U.S. Census)|Native American]], 7,973 (31.1%) [[Asian (U.S. Census)|Asian]], 9 (0.0%) [[Pacific Islander (U.S. Census)|Pacific Islander]], 1,422 (5.6%) from [[Race (United States Census)|other races]], and 1,415 (5.5%) from two or more races.  [[Hispanic (U.S. Census)|Hispanic]] or [[Latino (U.S. Census)|Latino]] of any race were 4,767 persons (18.6%). 

The Census reported that 25,456 people (99.4% of the population) lived in households, 8 (0%) lived in non-institutionalized group quarters, and 155 (0.6%) were institutionalized.  

There were 10,467 households, out of which 3,621 (34.6%) had children under the age of 18 living in them, 4,904 (46.9%) were [[marriage|opposite-sex married couples]] living together, 1,264 (12.1%) had a female householder with no husband present, 451 (4.3%) had a male householder with no wife present.  There were 501 (4.8%) [[POSSLQ|unmarried opposite-sex partnerships]], and 107 (1.0%) [[same-sex partnerships|same-sex married couples or partnerships]]. 3,073 households (29.4%) were made up of individuals and 802 (7.7%) had someone living alone who was 65 years of age or older. The average household size was 2.43.  There were 6,619 [[family (U.S. Census)|families]] (63.2% of all households); the average family size was 3.06.

The population was spread out with 5,998 people (23.4%) under the age of 18, 1,576 people (6.2%) aged 18 to 24, 7,431 people (29.0%) aged 25 to 44, 7,510 people (29.3%) aged 45 to 64, and 3,104 people (12.1%) who were 65 years of age or older.  The median age was 40.1 years. For every 100 females there were 90.3 males.  For every 100 females age 18 and over, there were 85.5 males.

There were 11,118 housing units at an average density of 3,253.2 per square mile (1,256.1/km²), of which 4,787 (45.7%) were owner-occupied, and 5,680 (54.3%) were occupied by renters. The homeowner vacancy rate was 1.1%; the rental vacancy rate was 6.1%.  13,185 people (51.5% of the population) lived in owner-occupied housing units and 12,271 people (47.9%) lived in rental housing units.

===2000===
As of the [[census]]{{GR|2}} of 2000, there were 24,292 people, 10,477 households, and 6,003 families residing in the city. The [[population density]] was 7,064.4 inhabitants per square mile (2,726.5/km²). There were 10,850 housing units at an average density of 3,155.3 per square mile (1,217.8/km²). The racial makeup of the city was 60.32% [[White (U.S. Census)|White]], 3.04% [[African American (U.S. Census)|African American]], 0.34% [[Native American (U.S. Census)|Native American]], 26.58% [[Asian (U.S. Census)|Asian]], 0.08% [[Pacific Islander (U.S. Census)|Pacific Islander]], 5.17% from [[Race (United States Census)|other races]]. [[Hispanic (U.S. Census)|Hispanic]] or [[Latino (U.S. Census)|Latino]] of any race were 16.07% of the population.  4.47% from two or more races.  (explaining why these percentages sum to about 116%)

There were 10,477 households out of which 29.4% had children under the age of 18 living with them, 42.4% were [[Marriage|married couples]] living together, 11.4% had a female head of household, and 42.7% were non-related families. 34.9% of all households were made up of individuals and 7.4% had someone living alone who was 65 years of age or older. The average household size was 2.30 and the average family size was 3.05.

In the city the population was spread out with 22.6% under the age of 18, 6.8% from 18 to 24, 34.7% from 25 to 44, 24.5% from 45 to 64, and 11.4% who were 65 years of age or older. The median age was 37 years. For every 100 females there were 86.6 males. For every 100 females age 18 and over, there were 83.3 males.

As of a 2009 estimate, the median household income is $80,412 and the median family income $102,412. Males had a median income of $67,062 versus $54,445 for females. The [[per capita income]] for the city was $47,367. About 6.1% of families and 7.6% of the population were below the [[poverty line]], including 7.7% of those under age 18 and 4.9% of those age 65 or over. Approximately 40% of all households in South Pasadena have an income of at least $100,000.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://factfinder.census.gov/servlet/ADPTable?_bm=y&amp;-geo_id=16000US0673220&amp;-qr_name=ACS_2009_5YR_G00_DP5YR3&amp;-ds_name=ACS_2009_5YR_G00_&amp;-_lang=en&amp;-redoLog=false&amp;-_sse=on|title=South Pasadena city, California - Fact Sheet - American FactFinder |publisher=Factfinder.census.gov |date= |accessdate=2011-01-03}}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Adjacent localities ===
Diagram showing South Pasadena's location in relation to other cities in a {{convert|16|km|mi|sp=us|adj=on}} radius.
&lt;div style=&quot;position: relative; float:left; width:500px;&quot;&gt;
[[File:Blank map.svg|400px|left|Localidades cercanas]]  
{{Image label|x=0.5|y=0.5|scale=400|text=[[File:Map pointer black.svg|20px|South Pasadena]]'''South Pasadena'''}} 
{{Image label|x=0.607|y=0.694|scale=400|text=[[File:Dot-yellow.svg|20px|Localidad con 85804 habitantes (2000).]] &lt;small&gt;[[Alhambra, California|Alhambra]] (4 km) &lt;/small&gt;}} 
{{Image label|x=0.905|y=0.330|scale=400|text=[[File:Small-city-symbol.svg|16px|Localidad con 6045 habitantes (2000).]] &lt;small&gt;[[East Pasadena, California|East Pasadena]] (8 km) &lt;/small&gt;}} 
{{Image label|x=0.882|y=0.462|scale=400|text=[[File:Small-city-symbol.svg|18px|Localidad con 14512 habitantes (2000).]] &lt;small&gt;[[East San Gabriel, California|East San Gabriel]] (7 km) &lt;/small&gt;}} 
{{Image label|x=0.604|y=0.898|scale=400|text=[[File:Dot-yellow.svg|20px|Localidad con 60051 habitantes (2000).]] &lt;small&gt;[[Monterey Park, California|Monterey Park]] (7 km) &lt;/small&gt;}} 
{{Image label|x=0.624|y=0.231|scale=400|text=[[File:Dot-yellow.svg|20px|Localidad con 133936 habitantes (2000).]] &lt;small&gt;[[Pasadena, California|Pasadena]] (5 km) &lt;/small&gt;}} 
{{Image label|x=0.880|y=0.766|scale=400|text=[[File:Dot-yellow.svg|20px|Localidad con 53505 habitantes (2000).]] &lt;small&gt;[[Rosemead, California|Rosemead]] (8 km) &lt;/small&gt;}} 
{{Image label|x=0.797|y=0.616|scale=400|text=[[File:Dot-yellow.svg|20px|Localidad con 39804 habitantes (2000).]] &lt;small&gt;[[San Gabriel, California|San Gabriel]] (6 km) &lt;/small&gt;}} 
{{Image label|x=0.722|y=0.439|scale=400|text=[[File:Small-city-symbol.svg|18px|Localidad con 12945 habitantes (2000).]] &lt;small&gt;[[San Marino, California|San Marino]] (4 km) &lt;/small&gt;}} 
&lt;/div&gt;{{clearleft}}

==Government and infrastructure==
In the [[California State Legislature|state legislature]] South Pasadena is located in the 22nd [[California State Senate|Senate]] District, represented by Democrat [[Gilbert Cedillo]], and in the 44th [[California State Assembly|Assembly]] District, represented by Democrat [[Anthony J. Portantino]]. Federally, South Pasadena is located in [[California's 29th congressional district]], which has a [[Cook Partisan Voting Index|Cook PVI]] of D +12&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | title = Will Gerrymandered Districts Stem the Wave of Voter Unrest? | publisher = Campaign Legal Center Blog | url=http://www.clcblog.org/blog_item-85.html | accessdate = 2008-02-10}}&lt;/ref&gt; and is represented by Democrat [[Adam Schiff]].

The [[Los Angeles County Department of Health Services]] operates the Monrovia Health Center in [[Monrovia, California|Monrovia]], serving South Pasadena.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;[http://publichealth.lacounty.gov/phn/docs/HealthCenter/monrovia.pdf Monrovia Health Center].&quot; [[Los Angeles County Department of Health Services]]. Retrieved on March 27, 2010.&lt;/ref&gt;

==Economy==
===Top employers===
According to the City's 2009 Comprehensive Annual Financial Report, the top employers in the city are:&lt;ref name=&quot;cafr2009&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.ci.south-pasadena.ca.us/finance/PDFs/CAFR%202008-09.pdf |title=City of South Pasadena CAFR |format=PDF |date= |accessdate=2011-11-18}}&lt;/ref&gt;

{| class=&quot;wikitable&quot;
|-
! #
! Employer
! # of Employees
|-
| 1
| The Vons Companies
|185
|-
| 2
|South Pasadena Convalescent Hospital
|159
|-
| 3
|[[Bristol Farms]]
|135
|-
| 4
|WNC Insurance Services
|101
|-
| 5
|[[Abbott Laboratories|Abbott]]
|78
|-
| 6
|[[Trader Joe's]]
|77
|-
| 7
|Mission Hospice
|69
|-
| 8
|[[Ralphs]]
|65
|-
| 9
|[[Orchard Supply Hardware]]
|63
|-
| 10
|[[Stargate Studios]]
|62
|}

==Notable people==
*[[Meredith Baxter]], actor, born here
*[[Alison Brie]], award-winning actor, Community and Mad Men
*[[Michael Catherwood]], radio and television personality
*[[Kristinia DeBarge]], singer.
*[[John de Lancie]], theater and TV and film actor, Q on ''[[Star Trek: The Next Generation]]''
*[[Andy Dick]], actor and comedian
*[[Thomas Francis Ford]] (1873–1958), member of Congress, editor, specialist in international trade and the only person ever sent to the Los Angeles City Council by a write-in vote
*[[Victoria Forester]], New York Times Best Selling children's book author
*[[Eddie Furlong]], actor, moved
*[[Lucretia Garfield]], wife of [[James A. Garfield]]
*[[William Holden]], Academy-Award winning actor, deceased
*[[Dave King (Irish singer)|Dave King]], musician, member of [[Flogging Molly]]
*[[Federico Mena]], Mexican programmer, creator of the [[GNOME]] operating system.
*[[Sparky Marcus]] (real name Marcus Issoglio), child actor, moved
*[[Carlos Slim|Carlos Helu]], Mexican businessman, owner of [[Telmex]] and [[Grupo Carso|Carso Conglomerate]] owned a house in South Pasadena in the 1990s before he was the richest man in the world.
*[[Cody McMains]], actor, moved
*[[Joel McCrea]], actor, deceased
*[[Jack McGrath]], auto racer.
*[[Rich Moore]], [[Emmy]]-winning animation director (''[[The Simpsons]]'', ''[[Futurama]]''), and partner in [[Rough Draft Studios]], Inc. ([[Glendale, California|Glendale, CA]])
*[[Kim Soon-kwon]], Korean born biochemist, specializing in the fields of hybrid and engineered corn to combat starvation in poor countries and three time nobel peace prize nominee.
*[[Bronson Pinchot]], actor, moved
*[[David Lee Roth]], singer, member of [[Van Halen]]
*[[Hilary Swank]], Academy-Award winning actor, moved
*[[Juan Francisco Azcárate]], aircraft designer and Mexico's military attache to Germany and later to the United States during [[World War II]].
*[[Jaleel White]], iconic TV comedic actor, moved
*[[Lisa Yee]], children's book author
*[[Wang You-theng]], Taiwanese born CEO and founder of the [[Rebar (Taiwan)|Rebar Group]], wanted in Taiwan for criminal charges

==See also==
{{Portal|Los Angeles}}
*[[Baranger Studios]]
*[[History of Pasadena, California]]
*[[Rancho San Pascual]]
*[[Tongva people]]

==References==
{{reflist|colwidth=35em}}

==External links==
*[http://www.ci.south-pasadena.ca.us/ South Pasadena official website]
*[http://www.southpaschamber.com/ South Pasadena Chamber of Commerce official website]
*[http://southpas.wikicities.com South Pas Wiki]
*[http://www.sptor.com/ Official site of South Pasadena Rose Parade Float]
{{Cities of Los Angeles County, California}}
{{Greater Los Angeles Area}}

[[Category:Cities in Los Angeles County, California]]
[[Category:Communities on U.S. Route 66]]
[[Category:South Pasadena, California| ]]
[[Category:Incorporated cities and towns in California]]
[[Category:Communities in the San Gabriel Valley]]
[[Category:Populated places established in 1888]]

[[ar:سووث باسادينا، لوس أنجليس، كاليفورنيا]]
[[bg:Южна Пасадина (Калифорния)]]
[[ca:South Pasadena (Califòrnia)]]
[[de:South Pasadena]]
[[es:South Pasadena]]
[[fr:South Pasadena (Californie)]]
[[sw:South Pasadena, California]]
[[ht:South Pasadena, Kalifòni]]
[[nl:South Pasadena (Californië)]]
[[pl:South Pasadena (Kalifornia)]]
[[pt:South Pasadena (Califórnia)]]
[[sv:South Pasadena]]
[[tl:South Pasadena, California]]
[[vo:South Pasadena (California)]]
[[zh:南帕萨迪纳 (加利福尼亚州)]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
