<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="107600" ns="0" title="Avalon, California"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Infobox settlement
|name                     = Avalon
|other_name               =
|native_name              = &lt;!-- for cities whose native name is not in English --&gt;
|nickname                 =
|motto                    =
|image_skyline            = Lightmatter Avalon Bay.jpg
|imagesize                = 300px
|image_caption            = Avalon Harbor
|image_flag               =
|flag_size                =
|image_seal               = Seal_avalon_ca.png
|seal_size                = 92px
|image_shield             =
|shield_size              =
|image_blank_emblem       =
|blank_emblem_size        =
|image_map                = LA County Incorporated Areas Avalon highlighted.svg
|mapsize                  = 250x200px
|map_caption              = Location of Avalon within [[Los Angeles County]]
|image_map1               =
|mapsize1                 =
|map_caption1             =
|pushpin_map              = California
|pushpin_label_position   = left
|pushpin_mapsize          =
|pushpin_map_caption      = Location in California
|coordinates_region       = US-CA
|subdivision_type         = [[List of countries|Country]]
|subdivision_name         = {{USA}}
|subdivision_type1        = [[Political divisions of the United States|State]]
|subdivision_name1        = {{flag|California}}
|subdivision_type2        = [[List of counties in California|County]]
|subdivision_name2        = [[Los Angeles County|Los Angeles]]
|subdivision_type3        =
|subdivision_name3        =
|subdivision_type4        =
|subdivision_name4        =
|government_type          = [[Council-manager government|Council-Manager]]
|leader_title             = [[Mayor]]
|leader_name              = Bob Kennedy &lt;ref name=&quot;City Council&quot;/&gt;
|leader_title1            = [[City Manager]]
|leader_name1             = Steve Hoefs
|leader_title2            =
|leader_name2             =
|leader_title3            =
|leader_name3             =
|established_title        = &lt;!-- Settled --&gt;
|established_date         =
|established_title2       = &lt;!-- Incorporated (town) --&gt;
|established_date2        =
|established_title3       = Incorporated (city)
|established_date3        = June 26, 1913 &lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url = http://www.cacities.org/resource_files/20457.IncorpDateLO.doc | title = Incorporation Dates of California Cities |publisher = League of California Cities |accessdate = January 18, 2007}}&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;!-- Area------------------&gt;
|area_magnitude           =
| unit_pref               =US
| area_footnotes          = &lt;ref&gt;[http://www.census.gov/geo/www/gazetteer/files/Gaz_places_national.txt U.S. Census]&lt;/ref&gt;
| area_total_sq_mi        = 2.937
| area_land_sq_mi         = 2.935
| area_water_sq_mi        = 0.002
| area_total_km2          = 7.607
| area_land_km2           = 7.602
| area_water_km2          = 0.005
| area_water_percent      = 0.07
| area_note               = 
|area_urban_km2           =
|area_urban_sq_mi         =
|area_metro_km2           =
|area_metro_sq_mi         =
|population_as_of         = 2010
|population_footnotes     = 
|population_note          =
|settlement_type          = [[City]]
|population_total         = 3728
|population_density_km2   = auto
|population_density_sq_mi = auto
|population_metro         =
|population_density_metro_km2     =
|population_density_metro_sq_mi   =
|population_urban                 =
|population_density_urban_km2     =
|population_density_urban_sq_mi   =
|timezone                 = [[Pacific Time Zone|PST]]
|utc_offset               = -8
|timezone_DST             = PDT
|utc_offset_DST           = -7
|coordinates_type       = type:landmark_region:US
|coordinates_display      = inline,title
|latd = 33 |latm = 20 |lats = 27 |latNS = N
|longd = 118 |longm = 19 |longs = 40 |longEW = W
|elevation_m              = 9
|elevation_ft             = 30
|postal_code_type         = [[ZIP Code]]
|postal_code              = 90704 &lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url = http://zip4.usps.com/zip4/zcl_1_results.jsp?visited=1&amp;pagenumber=0&amp;state=ca&amp;city=Avalon | title = USPS - ZIP Code Lookup - Find a ZIP+ 4 Code By City Results | accessdate = January 17, 2007}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|area_code                = [[Area code 310|310]]/[[Area code 424|424]]
|website                  = [http://www.cityofavalon.com/ cityofavalon.com]
|blank_name               = [[Federal Information Processing Standard|FIPS code]]
|blank_info               = 06-03274
|blank1_name              = [[Geographic Names Information System|GNIS]] feature ID
|blank1_info              = 1660283
|footnotes                =
}}
&lt;!-- Infobox ends --&gt;

'''Avalon''', or '''Avalon Bay''', is the only [[city|incorporated city]] on [[Santa Catalina Island, California|Santa Catalina Island]] of the [[Channel Islands of California|California Channel Islands]], and the southernmost city in [[Los Angeles County]]. Besides Avalon, the only other center of population on the island is the small [[unincorporated area|unincorporated]] town of [[Two Harbors, California|Two Harbors]]. The population was 3,728 at the 2010 census.

Avalon was first settled in pre-modern times by members of the [[Tongva people|Gabrielino/Tongva]] tribe. From the late 19th century to the early 20th century, several different developers tried to develop Avalon into a [[Resort town|resort destination community]], but most went bankrupt. In 1919, [[William Wrigley, Jr.]] gained control of Avalon. Wrigley oversaw much of the development of Avalon, including the construction of the landmark [[Catalina Casino]].

The city remains primarily a [[Resort town|resort community]]. Most of the waterfront is dominated by tourism-oriented businesses. The older parts of the town on the valley floor consist primarily of small houses and two and three-story buildings in various traditional architectural styles.  There are also several large apartment complexes nestled in the hills on either side of the valley, so that they are not obvious in most postcard photos of Avalon.

==History==
===Pre-European settlement===
Prior to the modern era, Avalon Bay was inhabited by people of the [[Tongva people|Gabrielino/Tongva]] tribe. In addition to Catalina Island, the Tongva occupied present-day Los Angeles County, northern Orange County, and San Clemente Island. The island was a major source of [[soapstone]] to the Tongva, who used the material to make stone vessels for cooking.&lt;ref name=Kroeber&gt;{{cite book
  | last = Kroeber
  | first = Alfred Louis
  | authorlink = Alfred L. Kroeber
  | title = Handbook of the Indians of California, Volume 2
  | publisher = Kessinger Publishing, LLC
  | date = July 9, 2006
  | pages = 620&amp;ndash;635
  | url = http://books.google.com/?id=z03qwZoErPkC&amp;pg=PA620&amp;lpg=PA620&amp;dq=gabrielino+catalina+island&amp;q=gabrielino%20catalina%20island
  | isbn = 978-1428644939}}&lt;/ref&gt; The Tongva called the island ''Pimu'' or ''Pimugna'' and referred to themselves as the ''Pimugnans''.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | author = Belanger, Joe | year = 2007 | title = History | url = http://www.visitingcatalina.com/history.html | work = Catalina Island - All You Need to Know | publisher  = | accessdate = August 28, 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt; The Pimugnans had settlements all over the island at one time or another. Their biggest villages, most likely, were located at Avalon Bay, as well as at the Isthmus and Emerald Bay.{{Citation needed|date=September 2009}}  By the 1830s, the entire island's native population had either died off, or had migrated to the mainland to work in the missions or as ranch hands for the many private land owners.&lt;ref name=otte&gt;{{cite web | last= Otte |first = Stacey |last2 = Pedersen |first2 = Jeannine | year = 2004 | title = Catalina Island History | url = http://www.catalinamuseum.org/history.html | work = A Catalina Island History in Brief | publisher  =Catalina Island Museum | accessdate = January 28, 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Early developers===
In the 1840s, the Mexican governor [[Pio Pico]] gave the island of Catalina as a grant to Don Jose Corruvias of Santa Barbara. The island traded hands dozens of times in the ensuing years. In 1864, during the Civil War, it was occupied by Union troops, who built and occupied [[Camp Santa Catalina Island]] for most of that year. Federal commanders planned to use the island as an Indian reservation for the tribes they were fighting in northwestern California and as a coastal fortification. It was finally acquired in the 1860s by [[James Lick]], whose estate maintained control of the island for approximately the next 25 years.&lt;ref name=Williamson&gt;{{cite journal
  | last = Williamson
  | first = M. Burton
  | title = History of Santa Catalina Island
  | journal = The Historical Society of Southern California
  | volume =
  | issue =
  | pages = 14–31
  | publisher = George Rice &amp; Sons
  | location = Los Angeles
  | date = December 7, 1903
  | url = http://books.google.com/?id=qcE1AAAAIAAJ&amp;pg=PA30&amp;q=
  | issn =
  | doi =
  | id =
  | accessdate = }}&lt;/ref&gt;

The first owner to try to develop Avalon Bay into a resort destination was [[George Shatto]], a real estate speculator from [[Grand Rapids, Michigan]]. Shatto purchased the island for $200,000 from the Lick estate at the height of a [[real estate]] [[Boom and bust|boom]] in [[Southern California]] in 1887. Shatto created the settlement that would become Avalon, and can be credited with building the town's first hotel, the original Hotel Metropole, and pier.&lt;ref name=Gelt&gt;{{cite news
  | last = Gelt
  | first = Jessica
  | title = A Day In; 90704; Pleasure Cruising in Avalon
  | newspaper = Los Angeles Times
  | pages = I.9
  | date = January 7, 2007
  | url = http://pqasb.pqarchiver.com/latimes/access/1190443921.html?dids=1190443921:1190443921&amp;FMT=ABS&amp;FMTS=ABS:FT&amp;type=current&amp;date=Jan+7%2C+2007&amp;author=Jessica+Gelt&amp;pub=Los+Angeles+Times&amp;edition=&amp;startpage=I.9&amp;desc=A+DAY+IN%3B+90704%3B+Pleasure+Cruising+in+Avalon
  | accessdate = September 12, 2009}}
&lt;/ref&gt; His sister-in-law Etta Whitney came up with the name ''Avalon'', which was pulled as a reference from [[Alfred, Lord Tennyson]]'s poem &quot;[[Idylls of the King]]&quot;, about the legend of [[King Arthur]]. {{quote|Mr. and Mrs. Shatto and myself were looking for a name for the new town, which in its significance should be appropriate to the place, and the names which I was looking up were 'Avon' and 'Avondale,' and I found the name 'Avalon,' the meaning of which, as given in Webster's unabridged, was 'Bright gem of the ocean,' or Beautiful isle of the blest.'|Etta Whitney&lt;ref name=Williamson/&gt;}} Shatto laid out Avalon's streets, and introduced it as a vacation destination to the general public. He did this by hosting a real estate auction in Avalon in 1887, and purchasing a steamer ship for daily access to the island. In the summer of 1888, the small pioneer village kicked off its opening season as a booming little resort town. Despite Shatto's efforts, in a few years he had to default on his loan and the island went back to the Lick estate.{{Citation needed|date=September 2009}}

[[Image:Avalonbaybig.jpg|thumb|left|Avalon Bay around 1910, before the construction of the casino]]The sons of [[Phineas Banning]] bought the island in 1891 from the Lick estate and established the Santa Catalina Island Company to develop it as a resort. The Banning brothers fulfilled Shatto's dream of making Avalon a resort community. They built a dance pavilion in the center of town, made additions to the Hotel Metropole and steamer-wharf, built an aquarium, created the Pilgrim Club (a gambling club for men only). They also improved the standard of Avalon's beach by erecting a sea-wall and adding &quot;spoonholders&quot; or covered benches, building a bath house. For additional habitation, the Bannings erected close to one hundred tents throughout Avalon's canyon (often called &quot;tent cities&quot;). These tents were created so that if the expense of a hotel was too much, a visitor could rent out a tent for the bargain price of $7.50 per week. To this day, many homes in Avalon are still in possession of the same tents that stood in that spot over a century ago.{{Citation needed|date=September 2009}}

Just as the Bannings were anticipating the construction of a new, Hotel Saint Catherine, their efforts were set back on November 29, 1915, when a fire burned half of Avalon's buildings, including six hotels and several clubs.{{Citation needed|date=September 2009}} The Bannings refused to sell the island in hopes of rebuilding the town, starting with the Hotel Saint Catherine. The hotel would be located on Sugarloaf Point, the unique, picturesque, cliff bound peninsula at the north end of Avalon's harbor. It was blasted away to begin the construction of the hotel with its annex being in Descanso Canyon. These plans failed due to lack of funding and, in the end, the hotel was built in Descanso Canyon. Due to debt related to the 1915 fire and a decline in tourism due to [[World War I]], the Bannings were forced to sell the island in 1919 in shares.&lt;ref name=otte/&gt;

===Wrigley ownership===
[[image:WM. Wrigley, Jr. LC-DIG-ggbain-29898.jpg|thumb|William Wrigley, Jr. took control of Avalon in 1919]]
In February 1919, chewing gum magnate [[William Wrigley, Jr.]] bought a controlling interest in Santa Catalina Island and its associated properties from the Banning Brothers.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news
  | title = Wrigley Buys Catalina Island
  | newspaper = [[Los Angeles Times]]
  | pages = II1
  | date = February 13, 1919
  | url = http://pqasb.pqarchiver.com/latimes/access/331601052.html?dids=331601052:331601052&amp;FMT=ABS&amp;FMTS=ABS:AI&amp;type=historic&amp;date=Feb+13%2C+1919&amp;author=&amp;pub=Los+Angeles+Times&amp;desc=WRIGLEY+BUYS+CATALINA+ISLAND.&amp;pqatl=google
  | accessdate = September 16, 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt; Before his purchase, he had traveled to Catalina with his wife, Ada, and son, Philip, and immediately fell in love with the island.&lt;ref name=otte/&gt; Wrigley devoted himself to preserving and promoting it, investing millions in needed infrastructure and attractions.  When Wrigley bought the island, the ''Hermosa II'' and the ''[[S.S. Cabrillo]]'' were the only steamships that provided access to the island. In order to encourage growth, Wrigley purchased an additional steamship, the ''S.S. Virginia''. With some adjustments, it was renamed the ''S.S. Avalon''. He also foresaw the design of another steamship, the ''[[S.S. Catalina]]'' which was launched on the morning of May 3, 1924. These steamships would deliver passengers to Catalina for many years.{{Citation needed|date=September 2009}}

In the 1920s, in an effort to generate tourism in Avalon, Wrigley tried to convince [[Gertrude Ederle]], who had just become famous as the first woman to swim across the [[English Channel]], to swim from Catalina to the mainland.  She declined, so he launched the 1927 Wrigley Ocean Marathon: offering $25,000 to the first person to cross the channel and $15,000 for the first finisher of &quot;the fair sex.&quot;  Out of a field of 102, only one man completed the swim, Canadian swimmer George Young, who finished 15 hours and 44 minutes after the start.  The two women who came the closest were awarded $2,500 each.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news
  | last = Rainey
  | first = James
  | title = Crossing the icy waters for posterity
  | work = [[Los Angeles Times]]
  | pages = F5
  | date = October 18, 2005
  | url = http://pqasb.pqarchiver.com/latimes/access/912678821.html?dids=912678821:912678821&amp;FMT=ABS&amp;FMTS=ABS:FT&amp;type=current&amp;date=Oct+18%2C+2005&amp;author=James+Rainey&amp;pub=Los+Angeles+Times&amp;edition=&amp;startpage=F.5&amp;desc=BACK+STORY%3B+Crossing+the+icy+waters+for+posterity%3B+William+Wrigley+Jr.+planned+the+first+channel+swim+in+1927+with+fanfare.+But+the+event%27s+popularity+waned+until+the+1970s.
  | accessdate = September 24, 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt; Wrigley also brought attention to the town of Avalon by having his [[Chicago Cubs]] use the island for the team's [[spring training]] from 1921–1951, absent the war years of 1942-45.&lt;ref name=otte/&gt; In 1929, Wrigley built the [[Catalina Casino]] over the site of a previous dance hall known as the Sugarloaf Casino. Throughout the 1930s the Casino Ballroom hosted many of the biggest names in entertainment, including Benny Goodman, Stan Kenton, Woody Herman, and Gene Autry.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news
  | last = McClure
  | first = Rosemary
  | title = Backstage at Catalina Island's Avalon Casino
  | work = [[Los Angeles Times]]
  | date = June 19, 2009
  | url = http://travel.latimes.com/articles/la-trw-catalina21-2009jun21
  | accessdate = August 30, 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt; Following the death of William Wrigley, Jr. in 1932, his son [[Philip K. Wrigley]] took over the Santa Catalina Island Company. Philip continued his father's work in the improvement of the infrastructure of the City of Avalon.{{Citation needed|date=September 2009}}

During [[World War II]], the island was closed to tourists and used for military training facilities.&lt;ref name=&quot;CatalinaWWII&quot;&gt;
{{cite web
  | last = Pedersen
  | first = Jeannine
  | title = Catalina Island Life During WWII
  | publisher = eCatalina.com
  | url = http://www.ecatalina.com/article_ww2.cfm
  | accessdate = August 30, 2009}}
&lt;/ref&gt;  Catalina's steamships were expropriated for use as troop transports, the U.S. Maritime Service set up a training facility in Avalon, the Coast Guard had training at Two Harbors, the Army Signal Corp maintained a radar station in the interior, and the [[Office of Strategic Services]] (a precursor to the [[CIA]]) did training at Toyon Bay.&lt;ref name=otte/&gt;

In September 1972, 26 members of the [[Brown Berets]], a group of [[Chicano]] activists, travelled to Catalina and planted a Mexican flag, claiming the island for all Chicanos. They asserted that the [[Guadalupe Hidalgo Treaty]] between [[Mexico]] and the [[USA]] did not specifically mention the Channel Islands. The group camped outside of Avalon and were viewed as a new tourist attraction. Local Mexican-Americans provided them with food after they used up their own supplies. After 24 days a municipal judge visited the camp to ask them to leave. They departed peaceably on the tourist boat, just as they had arrived.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news | issn = 04583035 | pages = B1 | last = Martinez | first = Al
| title = Judge Asks Berets to Leave--They Do | work = [[Los Angeles Times]] | accessdate = October 4, 2008 | date = September 23, 1972}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Post-Wrigley era===
[[Image:Catalina Island Casino.jpg|thumb|right|The Catalina Casino, 2007]]
In 1975, [[Philip Wrigley]] deeded the Wrigley shares in the Santa Catalina Island Company to the [[Catalina Island Conservancy]] that he had helped create. The Conservancy now stewards 88 percent of the island, primarily outside of the City of Avalon. The mission of the Catalina Island Conservancy is to be a responsible steward of its lands through a balance of conservation, education and [[recreation]].{{Citation needed|date=September 2009}} So far, the successes include the opening of California's first permanent [[desalination plant]] in 1991.{{Citation needed|date=September 2009}} The Santa Catalina Island Company maintains control of much of its resort properties and operations within the City of Avalon.  It still owns and operates many of the main tourist draws to Avalon, including the Catalina Visitors Country Club, Catalina Island Golf Course, Descanso Beach Club and the Casino Ballroom.&lt;ref name=SCICo&gt;{{cite web
  | title = About Us
  | publisher = Santa Catalina Island Company
  | url = http://www.visitcatalinaisland.com/avalon/AboutUs.php
  | accessdate = August 29, 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In May 2007, the [[2007 Island Fire|Island Fire]] ripped through {{convert|4750|acre|km2|sp=us}} of land just outside of Avalon's City Limits. Over 200 fire fighting recruits were brought over by Marine hovercraft and helicopter to protect the city. Ultimately, only one residence and six commercial structures were destroyed.&lt;ref&gt;
{{cite news
  | last = Sahagun
  | first = Louis
  | last2 = Quinones
  | first2 = Sam
  | title = Catalina fire lays siege to Avalon: Hundreds of residents and tourists are forced to flee the island
  | work = [[Los Angeles Times]]
  | date = May 11, 2007
  | url = http://www.latimes.com/news/printedition/front/la-me-catalina11may11,1,682119.story?coll=la-headlines-frontpage
  | accessdate = August 30, 2009}} {{Dead link|date=September 2010|bot=H3llBot}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news
  | last = Seema
  | first = Mehta
  | last2 =Rosenblatt
  | first2 = Susannah
  | title = Catalina Fire: A New Day; After such a huge threat, Avalon's loss is small
  | newspaper = Los Angeles Times
  | pages = A.1
  | date = May 12, 2007
  | url = http://pqasb.pqarchiver.com/latimes/access/1269512931.html?dids=1269512931:1269512931&amp;FMT=ABS&amp;FMTS=ABS:FT&amp;type=current&amp;date=May+12%2C+2007&amp;author=Seema+Mehta%3BSusannah+Rosenblatt&amp;pub=Los+Angeles+Times&amp;edition=&amp;startpage=A.1&amp;desc=CATALINA+FIRE%3A+A+NEW+DAY%3B+After+such+a+huge+threat%2C+Avalon%27s+loss+is+small
  | accessdate = September 8, 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Geography and climate==
Avalon is located on [[Santa Catalina Island, California|Santa Catalina Island]], approximately {{convert|22|mi|km|sp=us}} south-by-southwest of the [[Port of Los Angeles|Los Angeles Harbor]] [[Breakwater (structure)|breakwater]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
| title = Avalon Living
| publisher = City of Avalon
| url=http://www.cityofavalon.com/content/2497/2505/default.aspx
| accessdate = August 29, 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt; It is the only incorporated city to be located on one of the eight [[Channel Islands of California]].  Due to its location on Catalina Island, it is the southern-most city in [[Los Angeles County]]. According to the [[United States Census Bureau]], the city has a total area of {{convert|3|sqmi|km2|0|abbr=on}}, {{convert|2.8|sqmi|km2|0|abbr=on}} on land and {{convert|.3|sqmi|km2|0|abbr=on}} on water.{{Citation needed|date=September 2009}}

Avalon has a very mild subtropical climate with warm temperatures year-round.  The [[National Weather Service]] maintained a cooperative station at the Avalon Pleasure Pier from 1909 through 1988.  Based on those records, average January temperatures are a maximum of {{convert|61.9|F|C|sp=us}} and a minimum of {{convert|46.6|F|C|sp=us}} and average July temperatures are a maximum of {{convert|72.1|F|C|sp=us}} and a minimum of {{convert|60.3|F|C|sp=us}}.  The temperature reaches {{convert|90|F|C|sp=us}} or higher on an average of only 1.0 day and drops to {{convert|32|F|C|sp=us}} or lower on an average of only 0.1 day annually. The highest recorded temperature was {{convert|104|F|C|sp=us}} on September 28, 1963, and the lowest recorded temperature was {{convert|29|F|C|sp=us}} on January 2, 1973.&lt;ref name=climate/&gt;

Annual average precipitation is {{convert|11.9|in|cm|sp=us}} and there are 34 days with measurable precipitation.  The wettest year was 1983 with {{convert|34.54|in|cm|sp=us}} and the driest year was 1953 with {{convert|4.10|in|cm|sp=us}} inches.  The most rainfall in one month was {{convert|11.68|in|cm|sp=us}} in May 1921.  The most rainfall in 24 hours was {{convert|6.75|in|cm|sp=us}} on October 22, 1941. Weather records are still maintained at the Santa Catalina airport.&lt;ref name=climate/&gt;

{{Weather box
|location = Avalon, CA
|single line = sl
|Jan high F = 61.9
|Feb high F = 62.9
|Mar high F = 63.3
|Apr high F = 65.3
|May high F = 66.9
|Jun high F = 69.2
|Jul high F = 72.1
|Aug high F = 73.5
|Sep high F = 73.0
|Oct high F = 70.7
|Nov high F = 67.1
|Dec high F = 63.2
|year high F = 67.4
|Jan low F = 46.6
|Feb low F = 47.6
|Mar low F = 48.4
|Apr low F = 51.2
|May low F = 53.8
|Jun low F = 56.9
|Jul low F = 60.3
|Aug low F = 61.4
|Sep low F = 59.9
|Oct low F = 56.4
|Nov low F = 51.0
|Dec low F = 47.4
|year low F = 53.4
|Jan precipitation inch = 2.65
|Feb precipitation inch = 2.37
|Mar precipitation inch = 1.90
|Apr precipitation inch = 0.97
|May precipitation inch = 0.18
|Jun precipitation inch = 0.02
|Jul precipitation inch = 0.00
|Aug precipitation inch = 0.07
|Sep precipitation inch = 0.29
|Oct precipitation inch = 0.18
|Nov precipitation inch = 1.35
|Dec precipitation inch = 1.90
|year precipitation inch = 11.90
|source 1 = Western Regional Climate Center&lt;ref name=climate&gt;{{cite web
|url = http://www.wrcc.dri.edu/cgi-bin/cliMAIN.pl?caaval+sca Western Regional Climate Center| title = Avalon Pleasure Pier, California| accessdate = August 29, 2009
|publisher = Western Regional Climate Center}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|date=August 2010
}}

==Cityscape==
[[Image:Avalon-Catalina-Island.jpg|thumb|left|Avalon harbor, 2004]]
The City of Avalon is oriented around Avalon Bay. Being a [[Resort town|resort community]], much of the city infrastructure is oriented toward a tourist-based economy. The harbor and beaches form the center of the town's activity. The Cabrillo Mole, located at the south end of the harbor, acts both as a breakwater and the main docks for the cross-channel passenger boats.{{Citation needed|date=September 2009}} Many of the commercial businesses dedicated to serving visitors are located along the Crescent Street [[pedestrian mall]], which runs just behind the three main beaches of Avalon Bay. The pedestrian walkway is adorned throughout with decorative pavers, fountains, palm trees, and a decorative serpentine [[seawall]]. Many of these features were introduced to Avalon during an extensive re-design undertaken by [[Philip K. Wrigley]] in 1934.&lt;ref name=otte/&gt; Extending out into the center of the harbor is the green Pleasure Pier. The north end of the harbor is dominated by the [[Catalina Casino]]. Built in a style described as a cross between [[Art Deco]] and [[Mediterranean Revival]], the Casino serves as Avalon's most distinctive landmark.{{Citation needed|date=September 2009}}

Outside of the bay and just north of the Casino is Descanso Beach, a private beach run by the Santa Catalina Island Company. At the farthest north end of town are the Hamilton Cove condominiums, a gated community consisting mostly of second homes. South of the bay is Lovers Cove dive park, a marine reserve frequented by both snorkelers and the classic [[glass-bottom boat]] tours. Further south still is Pebbly Beach, an industrial area home to the heliport and Pebbly Beach Generating Station where Avalon gets its power.{{Citation needed|date=September 2009}}

Most of the residential units in Avalon are tucked away off of the beachfront, either in the flat lands further back into the canyon or on the hills that constitute the sides of Avalon Valley. Many of the major municipal amenities are located even further into the canyon, including City Hall, the fire station, the Catalina Island Medical Center, and Avalon Schools. The [[Wrigley Botanical Gardens|Wrigley Memorial and Botanical Gardens]] are located at the farthest end of town away from the bay.&lt;ref&gt;
{{cite web
| year = 2006
| title = Catalina Island Life
| url = http://www.catalina.com/memorial.html
| work = The Wrigley Memorial and Botanical Gardens
| publisher = Catalina Island Chamber of Commerce
| accessdate = August 28, 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt; The Memorial prominently features native Catalina Island building materials, including the famous pottery and tile that were made on the island from 1927 through 1937.&lt;ref&gt;
{{cite book
  | last = Coates
  | first = Carole
  | title = Catalina Island Pottery &amp; Tile: Island Treasures 1927-1937
  | publisher = Schiffer Publishing
  | date = July 2007
  | location = Atglen, PA
  | url = http://catalinacollectors.org/blog/articles/carole_coates.html
  | isbn = 9780764314018
  | accessdate = August 28, 2009}}
&lt;/ref&gt;

In February 2011, water regulators cited the city for letting tens of thousands of gallons of sewage reach the ocean in six spills since 2005. A report in June 2011 by the [[Natural Resources Defense Council]] listed Avalon as having one of the 10 most chronically polluted beaches in the United States.The beach fails state health standards so often that warning signs are posted much of the summer. The pollution is caused by the city's sewer system, made of century-old clay and metal pipes.  By 2011, city had spent $3.5 million testing and rehabilitating sewer lines, but the water was no cleaner. It is now planning a $5.1 million project to clean, repair and replace miles of sewer lines and make improvements at its sewer plant.{&lt;ref&gt;{cite news |url=http://www.latimes.com/news/local/la-me-avalon-water-20110710,0,4895779,full.story |work=Los Angeles Times |title=Avalon's dirty little secret: its beach is health hazard |author=Tony Barboza |date=July 10, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Government==
[[image:Avalon City Hall.JPG|thumb|Avalon City Hall]]The municipal government of the City of Avalon is of the [[Council-manager government|council-manager]] type. The Mayor is elected to serve a two-year term while the City Councilors are elected to four-year terms. The City Manager is the executive officer of the city and is appointed directly by the City Council.  The new City Hall was completed June 8, 2004. It contains local government offices as well as the council chambers.&lt;ref name=&quot;City Council&quot;&gt;{{cite web |title=City Council |publisher=City of Avalon |url=http://www.cityofavalon.com/content/2517/2520/default.aspx |accessdate=August 29, 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt; In the [[California State Legislature|state legislature]], Avalon is located in the 27th [[California State Senate|Senate]] District, represented by Democrat [[Alan Lowenthal]], and in the 54th [[California State Assembly|Assembly]] District, represented by Democrat [[Bonnie Lowenthal]]. Federally, Avalon is located in [[California's 46th congressional district]], which has a [[Cook Partisan Voting Index|Cook PVI]] of R +6&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
| title = Will Gerrymandered Districts Stem the Wave of Voter Unrest?
| publisher = Campaign Legal Center Blog
| url=http://www.clcblog.org/blog_item-85.html
| accessdate = February 10, 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt; and is represented by Republican [[Dana Rohrabacher]].

The [[Los Angeles County Sheriff's Department]] (LASD) operates the Avalon Station in Avalon.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;[http://www.lasd.org/stations/for3/avalon/index.html Avalon Station].&quot; [[Los Angeles County Sheriff's Department]]. Retrieved on January 21, 2010.&lt;/ref&gt; A few deputies are stationed on the island full-time with additional units brought from the mainland on an as-needed and seasonal basis. The city has its own full-time and volunteer fire departments for incidents within the city limits, while the [[Los Angeles County Fire Department]] serves the rest of the island.&lt;ref name=&quot;City Council&quot;/&gt;
&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
| title = LA County Fire Helicopters: Firehawks and Hueys
| work= [[KCBS-TV]]
| url=http://cbs2.com/amelia/LA.County.Fire.2.1133683.html
| accessdate = August 29, 2009}} {{Dead link|date=September 2010|bot=H3llBot}}&lt;/ref&gt; The [[Los Angeles County Department of Health Services]] operates the Torrance Health Center in [[Harbor Gateway, Los Angeles, California|Harbor Gateway]], [[Los Angeles]], near [[Torrance, California|Torrance]] and serving Avalon.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;[http://publichealth.lacounty.gov/phn/docs/HealthCenter/torrance.pdf Torrance Health Center].&quot; [[Los Angeles County Department of Health Services]]. Retrieved on March 18, 2010.&lt;/ref&gt;

The [[United States Postal Service]] Avalon Post Office is located at 118 Metropole Street.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
  | title = Post Office Location - Avalon
  | publisher = [[United States Postal Service]]
  | url = http://usps.whitepages.com/service/post_office/3791?p=1&amp;s=CA&amp;service_name=post_office&amp;z=Avalon
  | accessdate = August 30, 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Demographics==
{{USCensusPop
| title= Historical Population
| 1920=586
| 1930=1897
| 1940=1037
| 1950=1506
| 1960=1536
| 1970=1520
| 1980=2022
| 1990=2918
| 2000=3127
| 2010=3728
| footnote=&lt;ref name=census&gt;{{cite web
  | title = Avalon City, California - Fact Sheet - American FactFinder
  | publisher = US Census
  | url = http://factfinder.census.gov/servlet/ACSSAFFFacts?_event=Search&amp;geo_id=&amp;_geoContext=&amp;_street=&amp;_county=&amp;_cityTown=Avalon&amp;_state=04000US06&amp;_zip=&amp;_lang=en&amp;_sse=on&amp;pctxt=fph&amp;pgsl=010
  | accessdate = August 30, 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Historical Populations&quot;&gt;Census years 1930 through 2000 are as follows
* {{Cite web
  | title = Vol. 1. Number and distribution of inhabitants. Total population for states, counties, and townships or other minor civil divisions; for urban and rural areas; and for cities and other incorporated places.
  | work = 1930 Census | year = 1931
  | publisher = [[US Census Bureau]]
  | url = http://www.census.gov/prod/www/abs/decennial/1930.htm
  | page = 138 | location = Washington D.C.
  | accessdate = August 30, 2009}}
* {{Cite web
  | title = Vol. I. Number of Inhabitants.
  | work = 1950 Census | year = 1951
  | publisher = [[US Census Bureau]]
  | url = http://www.census.gov/prod/www/abs/decennial/1950.htm
  | pages = 1–48 | location = Washington D.C.
  | accessdate = August 30, 2009}}
* {{Cite web
  | title = California - Ch. A, B
  | work = 1980 Census | year = 1981
  | publisher = [[US Census Bureau]]
  | url = http://www.census.gov/prod/www/abs/decennial/1980cenpopv1.htm
  | pages = 6–15 | location = Washington D.C.
  | accessdate = August 30, 2009}}
&lt;/ref&gt;
}}
===2010===
The [[2010 United States Census]]&lt;ref&gt;{{USCensus-2010CA}}&lt;/ref&gt; reported that Avalon had a population of 3,728. The [[population density]] was 1,269.2 people per square mile (490.0/km²). The racial makeup of Avalon was 2,313 (62.0%) [[White (U.S. Census)|White]], 20 (0.5%) [[African American (U.S. Census)|African American]], 22 (0.6%) [[Native American (U.S. Census)|Native American]], 49 (1.3%) [[Asian (U.S. Census)|Asian]], 13 (0.3%) [[Pacific Islander (U.S. Census)|Pacific Islander]], 1,137 (30.5%) from [[Race (United States Census)|other races]], and 174 (4.7%) from two or more races.  [[Hispanic (U.S. Census)|Hispanic]] or [[Latino (U.S. Census)|Latino]] of any race were 2,079 persons (55.8%). 

The Census reported that 3,721 people (99.8% of the population) lived in households, 0 (0%) lived in non-institutionalized group quarters, and 7 (0.2%) were institutionalized.  

There were 1,473 households, out of which 488 (33.1%) had children under the age of 18 living in them, 641 (43.5%) were [[marriage|opposite-sex married couples]] living together, 160 (10.9%) had a female householder with no husband present, 90 (6.1%) had a male householder with no wife present.  There were 110 (7.5%) [[POSSLQ|unmarried opposite-sex partnerships]], and 5 (0.3%) [[same-sex partnerships|same-sex married couples or partnerships]]. 461 households (31.3%) were made up of individuals and 125 (8.5%) had someone living alone who was 65 years of age or older. The average household size was 2.53.  There were 891 [[family (U.S. Census)|families]] (60.5% of all households); the average family size was 3.25.

The population was spread out with 960 people (25.8%) under the age of 18, 316 people (8.5%) aged 18 to 24, 953 people (25.6%) aged 25 to 44, 1,093 people (29.3%) aged 45 to 64, and 406 people (10.9%) who were 65 years of age or older.  The median age was 37.7 years. For every 100 females there were 102.8 males.  For every 100 females age 18 and over, there were 98.6 males.

There were 2,266 housing units at an average density of 771.5 per square mile (297.9/km²), of which 383 (26.0%) were owner-occupied, and 1,090 (74.0%) were occupied by renters. The homeowner vacancy rate was 4.7%; the rental vacancy rate was 10.7%.  801 people (21.5% of the population) lived in owner-occupied housing units and 2,920 people (78.3%) lived in rental housing units.

===2000===
As of the [[census]]&lt;ref name=census/&gt; of 2000, there were 3,127 people, 1,158 households, and 719 families residing in the city.  The [[population density]] was 1,112.4 inhabitants per square mile (429.7/km&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt;).  There were 1,839 housing units at an average density of 654.2 per square mile (252.7/km&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt;).  The racial makeup of the city was 71.63% [[Race (United States Census)|White]], 0.74% [[Race (United States Census)|Black]], 1.02% [[Race (United States Census)|Native American]], 0.61% [[Race (United States Census)|Asian]], 0.22% [[Race (United States Census)|Pacific Islander]], 20.37% from [[Race (United States Census)|other races]], and 5.40% from two or more races.  45.95% of the population were [[Hispanics in the United States|Hispanic]] or [[Race (United States Census)|Latino]] of any race.&lt;ref name=census/&gt;

There were 1,158 households out of which 38.3% had children under the age of 18 living with them, 44.0% were [[Marriage|married couples]] living together, 11.2% had a female householder with no husband present, and 37.9% were non-families. 31.3% of all households were made up of individuals and 10.3% had someone living alone who was 65 years of age or older.  The average household size was 2.65 and the average family size was 3.38.&lt;ref name=census/&gt;

In the city the population was spread out with 30.3% under the age of 18, 7.7% from 18 to 24, 30.2% from 25 to 44, 21.7% from 45 to 64, and 10.1% who were 65 years of age or older.  The median age was 34 years. For every 100 females there were 99.4 males.  For every 100 females age 18 and over, there were 98.2 males.&lt;ref name=census/&gt;

The median income for a household in the city was $39,327, and the median income for a family was $46,406. Males had a median income of $30,789 versus $24,643 for females. The [[per capita income]] for the city was $21,032.  About 9.2% of families and 10.4% of the population were below the [[poverty line]], including 11.5% of those under age 18 and 4.6% of those age 65 or over.&lt;ref name=census/&gt;

==Education==
[[image:Avalon Schools Logo.jpg|thumb|The Lancer, Avalon Schools' mascot]]
There are two [[preschool education|preschools]] within the City of Avalon, Catalina Kid Ventures and Pre-School Learning for Avalon Youth (P.L.A.Y.). Kid Ventures is located next to City Hall and is funded through the city support, tuition payments, and charitable donations.&lt;ref name=&quot;Kid Ventures&quot;&gt;{{cite web
  | title =  Catalina Kid Ventures Open House Celebrating 20 years
  | publisher = eCatalina.com
  | url = http://www.ecatalina.com/news-article-1295.html
  | accessdate = September 4, 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt; P.L.A.Y. is a [[cooperative]] preschool that is tucked further back into the canyon at 4 Bird Park Canyon Road. It is located at the site of the former Bird Park, which itself was built from materials left over from the demolition of the original Sugarloaf Casino.&lt;ref name=&quot;Bird Park&quot;&gt;{{cite web
  | last = Pedersen
  | first = Jeannine
  | title =  Catalina Island's Bird Park
  | publisher = eCatalina.com
  | url = http://www.ecatalina.com/catalina-history-bird-park.html
  | accessdate = September 4, 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt;

For [[K–12 (education)|K-12 education]], children attend Avalon Schools. Avalon Schools are part of the [[Long Beach Unified School District]].  It is divided into an elementary, middle, and high school, but a single principal administers all three levels of education.&lt;ref name=&quot;Avalon Schools&quot;&gt;{{cite web
  | title = Avalon Schools Home Page
  | publisher = Avalon Schools
  | year = 2009
  | url = http://lbavalon.schoolloop.com/
  | accessdate = September 4, 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt; The campus is composed of three [[Mission Revival Style architecture|Mission Style]] buildings, a gymnasium, four secondary bungalows, and sixteen elementary bungalows.&lt;ref name=&quot;Avalon Schools&quot;/&gt; For high school sports, Avalon is a member of the [[CIF Southern Section]].&lt;ref name=&quot;CIF&quot;&gt;{{cite web
  | title = CIF Southern Section Home Page
  | publisher = CIF Southern Section
  | url = http://www.cifss.org/
  | accessdate = September 4, 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt; The school mascot is the [[Lancer]]. The teams are referred to either as the &quot;Avalon Lancers&quot; or &quot;Lancers&quot;. Home games are played in Avalon, and visiting teams must travel by boat to the island in order to make the games. In turn, the Lancers travel to the mainland for away games.&lt;ref name=football&gt;{{cite news
  | last = Wride
  | first = Nancy
  | title = Keeping Football Season Afloat; Catalina Island team travels for hours by boat and bus to reach its away games.
  | newspaper = Los Angeles Times
  | pages = B.1
  | date = October 25, 2002
  | url = http://pqasb.pqarchiver.com/latimes/access/223411231.html?dids=223411231:223411231&amp;FMT=ABS&amp;FMTS=ABS:FT&amp;type=current&amp;date=Oct+25%2C+2002&amp;author=Nancy+Wride&amp;pub=Los+Angeles+Times&amp;edition=&amp;startpage=B.1&amp;desc=Keeping+Football+Season+Afloat%3B+Catalina+Island+team+travels+for+hours+by+boat+and+bus+to+reach+its+away+games.
  | accessdate = September 4, 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Children in Avalon have two other options for elementary education. LBUSD has a [[one-room school]], Two Harbors Elementary School, at [[Two Harbors, California|Two Harbors]] in unincorporated [[Los Angeles County, California|Los Angeles County]]. Children may also study at the private Avalon Christian School, located on 346 Catalina Avenue.&lt;ref name=community&gt;{{cite web
  | title =  Avalon Community Organizations
  | publisher = eCatalina.com
  | url = http://www.ecatalina.com/catalina-organizations.html
  | accessdate = September 4, 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt; Students from both these schools attend Avalon Schools for junior high and high school education.

==Transportation==
===Intercity===
[[Image:Catalina Express.jpg|thumb|left|Catalina Express leaving Long Beach for Avalon, 2008]]The city is served by several high-speed passenger boats such as the [[Catalina Flyer]] with regular daily service to [[Newport Beach, California|Newport Beach]]. [[San Pedro, California|San Pedro]], [[Long Beach, California|Long Beach]], and [[Dana Point, California|Dana Point]] are served by [[Catalina Express]],and [[Marina del Rey, California|Marina del Rey]] is served by the [[Catalina-Marina Del Rey Flyer]]. Most of these cross-channel carriers dock at the Cabrillo Mole, located at the south end of the bay.{{Citation needed|date=September 2009}} Private vessels that come to Avalon Harbor are assigned a [[mooring (watercraft)|mooring]] by the Avalon Harbor Patrol on a first-come, first-serve basis. Boaters can get from their vessels to shore either by mooring their [[dinghy|dinghies]] at one of the dinghy docks, or by catching a ride on a private shoreboat.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
  | title = Welcome to Avalon
  | publisher = City of Avalon
  | date = July 1, 2008
  | url = http://www.cityofavalon.com/filestorage/2542/2566/2572/Brochure_July_2008.pdf
  | accessdate = September 3, 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt; 

[[Catalina Airport]] (FAA Identifier: AVX), also known as Airport-in-the-Sky, was built in 1946 and is located at (NAD83 rounded from FAA-provided coordinates): {{Coord|33|24|17|N|118|24|59|W}}, {{convert|7|mi|km}} northwest of Avalon. The {{convert|3250|ft|m|sp=us}} runway sits on a mountaintop, {{convert|1602|ft|m|sp=us}} above sea level.  Until the time of the airport's construction, the only air service to the island was provided by [[seaplane]]s.  Fixed-wing flights pay a $25 landing fee as of January 1, 2009.{{Citation needed|date=September 2009}} Several [[helicopter]] companies serve the city, with the most landing at the Pebbly Beach Heliport, located south of Avalon Bay.{{Citation needed|date=September 2009}}

===Intracity===
[[image:Avalon houses.jpg|thumb|Two examples of &quot;autoettes&quot; in Avalon, a [[Mini]] and a [[golf cart]] ]]

There is no regular vehicle ferry service to Avalon. Instead, the main method of transportation within the city is by small gasoline or electric powered motorcars referred to as &quot;autoettes.&quot; These include numerous [[golf carts]] and similarly sized vehicles. Vehicles under {{convert|55|in|cm|sp=us}} wide, {{convert|120|in|cm|sp=us}} long, and less than {{convert|1800|lbs|kg|sp=us}} may qualify as an autoette.  Any resident may acquire an autoette permit with the restriction of one permit per household. It is very difficult for a private citizen to get a permit to have a [[full-size vehicle]] in Avalon. The permit is issued to the individual as opposed to a specific vehicle, is surrendered when residency on the island ends, and is not transferable except through petition before the city council. Only one new vehicle permit is issued for every two permits that become ineligible to be renewed or are voluntarily surrendered. For purposes of vehicle registration, [[Santa Catalina Island, California|Catalina Island]] is divided into two classifications: within Avalon and &quot;Interior&quot; (areas outside the city limits). The city has its own strict permit program with which local vehicle owners must comply, in addition to the usual requirements imposed by the [[California Department of Motor Vehicles]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
| title = F.A.Q.
| publisher = City of Avalon
| url = http://www.cityofavalon.com/content/2542/2582/2586/default.aspx
| accessdate = August 29, 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==See also==

* [[Membership discrimination in California social clubs#Avalon|Membership discrimination in California social clubs]]

==References==
{{Reflist|2}}

==External links==
{{Portal|Los Angeles|Greater Los Angeles|Southern California}}
{{Commons category|Avalon, California}}
* [http://www.cityofavalon.com The City of Avalon]
* [http://www.smalltownpapers.com/listCAT.htm The Catalina Islander - Local newspaper]
* [http://www.catalinachamber.com/ The Catalina Island Chamber of Commerce]
* [http://www.lacdcs.com/station-end-page-18.html LA County Disaster Communications Service ( DCS ) Avalon Sheriff Station]
* {{Wikitravel|Avalon}}

{{Cities of Los Angeles County, California}}
{{Greater Los Angeles Area}}

[[Category:Populated coastal places in California]]
[[Category:Cities in Los Angeles County, California]]
[[Category:Channel Islands of California]]
[[Category:Populated places established in 1913]]
[[Category:Incorporated cities and towns in California]]
[[Category:Populated places in California with Hispanic majority populations]]

[[ar:أفالون، لوس أنجليس، كاليفورنيا]]
[[bg:Авалон (Калифорния)]]
[[ca:Avalon (Califòrnia)]]
[[de:Avalon (Kalifornien)]]
[[es:Avalon (California)]]
[[fo:Avalon]]
[[fr:Avalon (Californie)]]
[[it:Avalon (California)]]
[[sw:Avalon, California]]
[[ht:Avalon, Kalifòni]]
[[nl:Avalon (Californië)]]
[[pl:Avalon (Kalifornia)]]
[[pt:Avalon (Califórnia)]]
[[ru:Авалон (Калифорния)]]
[[sv:Avalon, Kalifornien]]
[[tl:Avalon, California]]
[[vo:Avalon (California)]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
