<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="107622" ns="0" title="Downey, California"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Infobox settlement
|official_name            = City of Downey
|settlement_type          = [[City]]
|nickname                 =
|motto                    =
|image_skyline            = DowntownDowney.JPG
|imagesize                = 250px
|image_caption            = Downtown Downey
|image_flag               = Flag of Downey California.svg
|image_seal               = City of Downey Seal.svg
|image_map                = LA County Incorporated Areas Downey highlighted.svg
|mapsize                  = 250x200px
|map_caption              = Location of Downey in [[Los Angeles County, California|Los Angeles County]], [[California]]
|image_map1               =
|mapsize1                 =
|map_caption1             =
|subdivision_type         = [[List of countries|Country]]
|subdivision_name         = {{USA}}
|subdivision_type1        = [[Political divisions of the United States|State]]
|subdivision_name1        = {{flag|California}}
|subdivision_type2        = [[List of counties in California|County]]
|subdivision_name2        =  [[Los Angeles County, California|Los Angeles]]
|government_type          = [[Council-manager government|Council-Manager]]
|leader_title             = [[City Council]]
|leader_name              = [[Mayor]] Luis H. Marquez &lt;br /&gt; David R. Gafin &lt;br /&gt; Roger Brossmer &lt;br /&gt; Mario Guerra &lt;br /&gt; Fernando Vasquez
|leader_title1             = [[City Manager]]
|leader_name1              = Gerald Caton
|leader_title2             = Finance Director
|leader_name2              = John Michicoff
|established_title        = Founded
|established_title2       = Incorporated
|established_date         = October 23, 1873
|established_date2        = December 17, 1956
&lt;!-- Area------------------&gt;
|area_magnitude           =
| unit_pref               =US
| area_footnotes          = &lt;ref&gt;[http://www.census.gov/geo/www/gazetteer/files/Gaz_places_national.txt U.S. Census]&lt;/ref&gt;
| area_total_sq_mi        = 12.568
| area_land_sq_mi         = 12.408
| area_water_sq_mi        = 0.160
| area_total_km2          = 32.551
| area_land_km2           = 32.137
| area_water_km2          = 0.414
| area_water_percent      = 1.27
| area_note               = 
|area_urban_sq_mi         =
|area_urban_km2           =
|area_metro_sq_mi         =
|area_metro_km2           =
|population_as_of         = 2010
|population_note          = 
|population_total         = 111772
| population_rank  =[[List of cities in Los Angeles County, California|11th]] in Los Angeles County&lt;br/&gt;[[List of largest California cities by population|53rd]] in California&lt;br/&gt;[[List of United States cities by population|232nd]] in the United States
|population_metro         =
|population_urban                 =
|population_density_km2   = auto
|population_density_sq_mi = auto
|timezone                 = [[Pacific Time Zone|PST]]
|utc_offset               = -8
|timezone_DST             = PDT
|utc_offset_DST           = -7
|coordinates_display      = inline,title
|coordinates_type         = region:US_type:city
|latd = 33 |latm = 56 |lats = 17 |latNS = N
|longd = 118 |longm = 07 |longs = 51 |longEW = W
|elevation_m              = 36
|elevation_ft             = 118
|website                  = [http://www.downeyca.org/ www.downeyca.org]
|postal_code_type         = [[ZIP code]]s
|postal_code              = 90239-90242
|area_code                = [[Area code 562|562]]
|blank_name               = [[Federal Information Processing Standard|FIPS code]]
|blank_info               = 06-19766
|blank1_name              = [[Geographic Names Information System|GNIS]] feature ID
|blank1_info              = 1652698
|footnotes                =
}}
'''Downey''' is a city located in southeast [[Los Angeles County, California]], [[United States]], {{convert|21|km|mi|abbr=on}} southeast of downtown [[Los Angeles]].  The city is best known as the birthplace of the [[Apollo program|Apollo space program]], and is the city where folk singer [[Karen Carpenter]] lived and died.  As of the 2010 census, the city had a total population of 111,772, up from 107,323 at the 2000 census.

==History==
Prior to the arrival of the [[Spanish Empire|Spanish]] in [[Alta California]], the area that now comprises Downey was inhabited by the [[Tongva people|Tongva]] ethnic group, which came to be called the [[Gabrielino]] by the Spanish.  The nearest Tongva settlements appear to have been just north and northeast of present-day Downey, although there is difficulty is locating them very precisely.&lt;ref name=&quot;McCawley&quot;&gt;McCawley, William (1996). ''The First Angelinos: the Gabrielino Indians of Los Angeles.''  Banning, CA: Malki Museum Press/Ballena Press.&lt;/ref&gt; The villages of ''Naxaaw’nga'' and ''Sehat'' seem to have been situated near the present-day community of Los Nietos, or perhaps farther west on sites that were lost to floods of the San Gabriel River.  ''Chokiishnga'' and ''Huutnga'' are other Tongva  place names that may have referred to villages in the general area north of Downey between the San Gabriel River and Rio Hondo.&lt;ref name=&quot;Reid&quot;&gt;Reid, Hugo (1852). &quot;Los Angeles County Indians.&quot; ''Los Angeles County Star'', '''1'''(41)–'''2'''(11) (24 February-24 July 1852).&lt;/ref&gt;  In all four cases, it is difficult to relate the original location descriptions, based on ranchos and land grants, to more specific sites identifiable by today’s landmarks. [[Mission San Gabriel Arcangel]] was initially founded on September 8, 1771, near these concentrations of Tongva population, at a site in the Whittier Narrows on a bluff overlooking the Rio Hondo near the intersection of today’s San Gabriel Blvd and Lincoln Avenue.&lt;ref name=&quot;Kyle&quot;&gt;Kyle, Douglas E. (1990). ''Historic Spots in California'', 4th ed. Stanford, CA: Stanford University Press.&lt;/ref&gt;  After five years, flooding forced the relocation of the mission to its present site in [[San Gabriel, California|San Gabriel]].

In 1784, Governor [[Pedro Fages]] granted to former soldier [[Manuel Nieto]] (1734–1804) the largest of the land concessions made during the Spanish control of California.  Its {{convert|300,000|acre|km2}} stretched from the [[Santa Ana River]] on the east to the Old [[San Gabriel River (California)|San Gabriel River]] (now the [[Rio Hondo (California)|Rio Hondo]] and [[Los Angeles River]]) on the west, and from the mission highway (approximately [[Whittier Boulevard]]) on the north to the ocean on the south.  Its acreage was slightly reduced later at the insistence of [[Mission San Gabriel]] on whose lands it infringed. The Spanish concessions, of which 25 were made in California, were unlike the later Mexican land grants in that title was not transferred, but were similar to grazing permits, with the title remaining with the Spanish crown.&lt;ref&gt;Beck, Warren A., Haase, Ynez D. (1974). ''Historical Atlas of California''. Norman: University of Oklahoma Press.&lt;/ref&gt;

The [[Rancho Los Nietos]] passed to Manuel Nieto's four children upon his death and remained intact until, in 1833, his heirs petitioned Mexican Governor [[José Figueroa]] to partition the property.  The northwestern portion of the original rancho, comprising the Downey-Norwalk area, was granted as [[Rancho Santa Gertrudes]] to Josefa Cota, the widow of Manuel's son, Antonio Nieto.  At approximately {{convert|21,000|acre|km2}}, Santa Gertrudes was itself a sizable rancho and contained the old Nietos homestead, which was a center of social life east of the pueblo of Los Angeles.&lt;ref&gt;Quinn, Charles Russell (1973). ''The History of Downey, California'' Published by Elena Quinn; copyright by City of Downey, California.&lt;/ref&gt;  After the [[Mexican-American war]] concluded in 1848, many of the [[Californio]] ranchos were obtained by affluent [[English-American|Anglo-Americans]] who were immigrating west under the [[United States]] [[manifest destiny]] doctrine, and marrying into established [[Californio]] Spanish families.
[[File:John G Downey by William F Cogswell, 1879.jpg|thumb|200px|left|Governor Downey by [[William F. Cogswell]]]]
Unlike most Southern California towns, Downey can claim some of its roots came from [[Ireland]].&lt;ref name=Ireland&gt;[http://www.jdcjr.us/irish.html jdcjr's Irish History Page&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt; Downey was founded by and named for the former and youngest ever [[governor]] of [[California]], [[John G. Downey|John Gately Downey]], who was born in Ireland.  Although he was an Irish Democrat, he supported the Republican Lincoln in his efforts to keep the Union intact during the [[Civil War]]. He pioneered the modern subdivision with land he acquired between the [[Rio Hondo (California)|Rio Hondo]] and the [[San Gabriel River (California)|San Gabriel River]], in about 1865.  Downey was convinced that oranges would flourish in Southern California, so he imported several varieties, and therefore set in motion what became one of the state's biggest cash crops.&lt;ref name=Ireland/&gt;  In 1935 Downey was described as an &quot;orange-grove town&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;Romance &amp; History of California Ranchos. Myrtle Garrison. 1935. page 11. Harr Wagner Publishing Company, San Francisco, CA.&lt;/ref&gt;  The [[Southern Pacific Railroad]] arrived in 1873, and farmers in the area grew grain, corn, castor beans and fruit until around 1940.

Downey was incorporated in 1956, and instituted a charter form of government in 1964.  Suburban homes and factories replaced the farms after World War II.  The largest employer was originally [[Vultee Aircraft]], then [[North American Aviation]], (later [[North American Rockwell]], then [[Rockwell International]] which was then bought by the [[Boeing]] company) whose facilities  were the birthplace of the systems for the [[Apollo program|Apollo space program]] as well as the [[Space Shuttle]].  For over 70 years, Downey's Rockwell [[NASA]] plant produced and tested many of the 20th century's greatest aviation, missile, and space endeavors.  By the early 1970s, the facilities encompassed some {{convert|1700000|sqft|m2}} of enclosed area over more than 200 acres. But, by the early 1990s, Downey  was brutally hit by cutbacks in the defense budget. Rockwell International, who once had over 30,000 employees, had less than 5,000 in 1992. {{Citation needed|date=February 2011}} The seventy year history of airplane and space vehicle manufacturing in Downey came to an end when the Rockwell plant closed in 1999.  The former Rockwell plant has been converted to the Downey Landing shopping complex, a [[Kaiser Permanente]] hospital, a park, a space museum and [[Downey Studios]].

Near the center of the city lies what was once one of the busiest intersections in the world, the intersection of Lakewood Boulevard (State Route 19) and Firestone Boulevard (former State Route 42).  Route 19 was a major thoroughfare between [[Pasadena, California|Pasadena]] and the port at [[Long Beach, California|Long Beach]], and Route 42 was part of the old Spanish Trail system that connected Los Angeles to [[San Diego]].  In the 1960s the town's Downey Records achieved a small notoriety with recordings like [[The Chantays]]' surfing instrumental &quot;[[Pipeline (song)|Pipeline]]&quot;. Downey's two main public [[high school]]s are named for [[John G. Downey|Governor Downey]] and [[Earl Warren|Governor (and later, Chief Justice) Earl Warren]].  Downey is home to [[Rancho Los Amigos National Rehabilitation Center]], which is the main public rehabilitation hospital for [[Los Angeles County, California|Los Angeles County]].  Rancho Los Amigos is renowned worldwide for its innovative contributions to the care of [[Spinal cord injury|spinal cord injuries]] and [[post-polio syndrome]].{{Citation needed|date=February 2011}}

Downey was featured in the 2008 American action comedy film ''[[Pineapple Express (film)|Pineapple Express]]''.  Many of the buildings along Florence Ave. can be viewed in a driving scene early in the film. {{Citation needed|date=February 2011}}

==Geography==
[[Image:CAMap-doton-Downey.PNG|right|167px|Location of Downey, California]]
Downey is located at {{Coord|33|56|17|N|118|7|51|W|type:city}} (33.938164, -118.130801).{{GR|1}}

According to the [[United States Census Bureau]], the city has a total area of {{convert|12.6|sqmi|km2}}. {{convert|12.4|sqmi|km2}} of it is land and {{convert|0.2|sqmi|km2}} of it (1.27%) is water.

The cities of [[South Gate, California|South Gate]] and [[Bell Gardens, California|Bell Gardens]] are adjacent to the west and northwest, [[Pico Rivera, California|Pico Rivera]] lies to the northeast, [[Santa Fe Springs, California|Santa Fe Springs]] and [[Norwalk, California|Norwalk]] to the east, and [[Paramount, California|Paramount]] and [[Bellflower, California|Bellflower]] are to the south.

==Demographics==
{{USCensusPop
| 1960=82505
| 1970=88573
| 1980=82602
| 1990=91444
| 2000=107323
| 2010=111772
| footnote=source:&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
  |url=http://www.census.gov/prod/www/abs/decennial/index.html
  |title=CENSUS OF POPULATION AND HOUSING (1790-2000)
  |publisher=[[U.S. Census Bureau]]
  |accessdate=2010-07-30}}&lt;/ref&gt;
}}

===2010===
The [[2010 United States Census]]&lt;ref&gt;{{USCensus-2010CA}}&lt;/ref&gt; reported that Downey had a population of 111,772. The [[population density]] was 8,893.3 people per square mile (3,433.7/km²). The racial makeup of Downey was 63,255 (56.6%) [[White (U.S. Census)|White]], 4,329 (3.9%) [[African American (U.S. Census)|African American]], 820 (0.7%) [[Native American (U.S. Census)|Native American]], 7,804 (7.0%) [[Asian (U.S. Census)|Asian]] (2.2% Korean, 2.2% Filipino, 0.6% Indian, 0.5% Chinese, 0.3% Vietnamese, 0.3% Japanese, 0.2% Thai, 0.1% Cambodian, 0.1% Pakistani), 221 (0.2%) [[Pacific Islander (U.S. Census)|Pacific Islander]], 30,797 (27.6%) from [[Race (United States Census)|other races]], and 4,546 (4.1%) from two or more races.  [[Hispanic (U.S. Census)|Hispanic]] or [[Latino (U.S. Census)|Latino]] of any race were 78,996 persons (70.7%); 54.0% of Downey is Mexican, 3.9% Salvadoran, 2.0% Cuban, 2.0% Guatemalan, 1.1% Peruvian, 1.0% Nicaraguan, 0.7% Colombian, 0.7% Puerto Rican, 0.6% Peruvian, 0.5% Honduran, 0.4% Argentinean, and 0.2% Costa Rican. 

The Census reported that 111,089 people (99.4% of the population) lived in households, 122 (0.1%) lived in non-institutionalized group quarters, and 561 (0.5%) were institutionalized.  

There were 33,936 households, out of which 15,697 (46.3%) had children under the age of 18 living in them, 17,405 (51.3%) were [[marriage|opposite-sex married couples]] living together, 6,289 (18.5%) had a female householder with no husband present, 2,796 (8.2%) had a male householder with no wife present.  There were 2,357 (6.9%) [[POSSLQ|unmarried opposite-sex partnerships]], and 225 (0.7%) [[same-sex partnerships|same-sex married couples or partnerships]]. 5,721 households (16.9%) were made up of individuals and 2,211 (6.5%) had someone living alone who was 65 years of age or older. The average household size was 3.27.  There were 26,490 [[family (U.S. Census)|families]] (78.1% of all households); the average family size was 3.68.

The population was spread out with 29,972 people (26.8%) under the age of 18, 12,108 people (10.8%) aged 18 to 24, 33,056 people (29.6%) aged 25 to 44, 25,057 people (22.4%) aged 45 to 64, and 11,579 people (10.4%) who were 65 years of age or older.  The median age was 33.3 years. For every 100 females there were 94.1 males.  For every 100 females age 18 and over, there were 90.4 males.

There were 35,601 housing units at an average density of 2,832.7 per square mile (1,093.7/km²), of which 17,135 (50.5%) were owner-occupied, and 16,801 (49.5%) were occupied by renters. The homeowner vacancy rate was 1.4%; the rental vacancy rate was 4.9%.  59,555 people (53.3% of the population) lived in owner-occupied housing units and 51,534 people (46.1%) lived in rental housing units. 

30-40 Homeless (Reference: City of Downey, 3685.pdf; Sec. 3, Consolidated Plan 2010-2015

===2000===
As of the [[census]]{{GR|2}} of 2000, there were 107,323 people, 33,989 households, and 26,001 families residing in the city.  The [[population density]] was 8,641.7 inhabitants per square mile (3,336.4/km&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt;).  There were 34,759 housing units at an average density of 2,798.8 per square mile (1,080.6/km&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt;).  The racial makeup of the city was 53.48% [[Race (United States Census)|White]], 3.75% [[Race (United States Census)|Black]] or [[Race (United States Census)|African American]], 0.87% [[Race (United States Census)|Native American]], 7.74% [[Race (United States Census)|Asian]], 0.22% [[Race (United States Census)|Pacific Islander]], 29.05% from [[Race (United States Census)|other races]], and 4.89% from two or more races.  57.85% of the population were [[Hispanics in the United States|Hispanic]] or [[Race (United States Census)|Latino]] of any race.

There were 33,989 households out of which 41.8% had children under the age of 18 living with them, 54.1% were married couples living together, 15.8% had a female householder with no husband present, and 23.5% were non-families. 19.1% of all households were made up of individuals and 8.1% had someone living alone who was 65 years of age or older.  The average household size was 3.11 and the average family size was 3.55.
[[Image:DowneyGingerBread.JPG|thumb|Typical Downey [[Gingerbread house]]s]]

In the city the population was spread out with 29.2% under the age of 18, 9.8% from 18 to 24, 31.2% from 25 to 44, 18.8% from 45 to 64, and 11.0% who were 65 years of age or older.  The median age was 32 years. For every 100 females there were 94.6 males.  For every 100 females age 18 and over, there were 89.8 males.

The median income for a household in the city was $46,000 and the median income for a family was $50,017. Males had a median income of $35,991 versus $28,768 for females. The [[per capita income]] for the city was $18,197.  About 9.3% of families and 11.1% of the population were below the [[poverty line]], including 14.4% of those under age 18 and 7.6% of those age 65 or over.

Downey has the second highest percentage of Cubans and Cuban Americans in the Western United States at 1.96% of the population.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.epodunk.com/ancestry/Cuban.html Cuban Ancestry Search - Cuban Genealogy by City - ePodunk.com&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;

==Government and infrastructure==
[[Image:Downey City Hall.jpg|thumb|left|Downey City Hall]]
In the [[California State Legislature|state legislature]] Downey is located in the 27th [[California State Senate|Senate]] District, represented by Democrat [[Alan Lowenthal]], and in the 50th and 58th [[California State Assembly|Assembly]] Districts, represented by Democrats [[Ricardo Lara]] and [[Charles M. Calderon]] respectively. Federally, Downey is located in [[California's 34th congressional district]], which has a [[Cook Partisan Voting Index|Cook PVI]] of D +23&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | title = Will Gerrymandered Districts Stem the Wave of Voter Unrest? | publisher = Campaign Legal Center Blog | url=http://www.clcblog.org/blog_item-85.html | accessdate = 2008-02-10}}&lt;/ref&gt; and is represented by Democrat [[Lucille Roybal-Allard]].

The [[Los Angeles County Department of Health Services]] operates the Whittier Health Center in [[Whittier, California|Whittier]], serving Downey.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;[http://publichealth.lacounty.gov/phn/docs/HealthCenter/whittier.pdf Whittier Health Center]{{dead link|date=November 2011}}.&quot; [[Los Angeles County Department of Health Services]]. Retrieved on March 18, 2010.&lt;/ref&gt;

The [[United States Postal Service]] operates the Downey Post Office at 8111 Firestone Boulevard,&lt;ref&gt;&quot;[http://usps.whitepages.com/service/post_office/4693?p=2&amp;s=CA&amp;service_name=post_office&amp;z=Downey Post Office Location - DOWNEY].&quot; ''[[United States Postal Service]]''. Retrieved on December 6, 2008.&lt;/ref&gt; the North Downey Post Office at 10409 Lakewood Boulevard,&lt;ref&gt;&quot;[http://usps.whitepages.com/service/post_office/58854?p=4&amp;s=CA&amp;service_name=post_office&amp;z=Downey Post Office Location - NORTH DOWNEY].&quot; ''[[United States Postal Service]]''. Retrieved on December 6, 2008.&lt;/ref&gt; and the South Downey Post Office at 7911 Imperial Highway.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;[http://usps.whitepages.com/service/post_office/59796?p=2&amp;s=CA&amp;service_name=post_office&amp;z=Downey Post Office Location - SOUTH DOWNEY].&quot; ''[[United States Postal Service]]''. Retrieved on December 6, 2008.&lt;/ref&gt;

==Economy==

According to the City's 2009 Comprehensive Annual Financial Report,&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.downeyca.org/_blobcache/0000/0004/3528.pdf City of Downey CAFR]&lt;/ref&gt; the top employers in the city are:

{| class=&quot;wikitable&quot;
|-
! #
! Employer
! # of Employees
|-
| 1
|[[Kaiser Permanente]]
|3,000
|-
|2
| [[Downey Unified School District]]
|2,000
|-
|3
|[[Stonewood Center]]
|1,750
|-
|4
|[[Rancho Los Amigos National Rehabilitation Center]]
|1,374
|-
|5
|Downey Regional Medical Center
|955
|-
|6
|[[The Coca-Cola Company]]
|920
|-
|7
|Office of Education, [[Los Angeles County, California|County of Los Angeles]]
|900
|-
|8
|Lakewood Park Health Center
|325
|-
|9
|[[International Paper|Xpedex]]
|250
|-
|10
|[[Do It Best|All American Home Center]]
|180
|}

==Historic restaurants ==
=== McDonald's restaurant===
{{main|Oldest McDonald's restaurant}}
[[Image:DowneyMcdonalds.jpg|thumb|250px|right|Oldest operating McDonald's restaurant on Lakewood and Florence in Downey, California]]
The 1953 [[McDonald's]] restaurant at 10207 [[Lakewood Blvd.]] (at Florence Ave.) was the third  McDonald's built and is the oldest surviving McDonald's. It was listed on the [[National Trust for Historic Preservation]]'s [[America's Most Endangered Places|1994 list of the 11 Most Endangered Historic Places]]. It was the second restaurant franchised by [[Richard and Maurice McDonald]], prior to the involvement of [[Ray Kroc]] in the company, and it still has the two original {{convert|30|ft|m|adj=on}} &quot;[[Golden arches]]&quot; and a {{convert|60|ft|m|adj=on}} animated neon &quot;[[Speedee]]&quot; sign.

With low sales, damage from the 1994 [[Northridge earthquake]], and the lack of a drive-up window and indoor seating, the restaurant was closed. However with both the public and preservationists demanding the restaurant be saved, McDonald's spent two years restoring the restaurant and reopened it. Customers today can visit the original restaurant and an adjoining gift shop and museum.
&lt;!--Ray Kroc DID NOT franchise this restaurant!--&gt;

===Harvey's/Johnie's Broiler===
[[Johnie's Broiler]] (originally Harvey's Broiler) was a drive-in restaurant and coffee shop, which has been in movies and sitcoms as well as TV commercials and music videos. Completed in 1958, it is an example of [[Googie]] architecture. Johnie's was well known to [[Southern California]] locals, many of which drove miles to cruise through its massive lot. In the mid-1960s, renowned author [[Tom Wolfe]] immortalized the cruising, car and fashion scene that surrounded Harvey's Broiler at the time; The article, &quot;The Hair Boys,&quot; appears in a bestselling 1968 collection of his articles titled, ''[[The Pump House Gang]]''. He made drawings of the denizens of Harvey's that appear in a later book, ''[[The Purple Decades]]''. The Broiler was a regular commercial and movie location for films such as ''[[Heat (movie)|Heat]]'', ''[[What's Love Got to Do with It (film)|What's Love Got to Do with It]]'', ''[[Unstrung Heroes]]'', ''[[Reality Bites]]'', ''[[Can't Hardly Wait]]'', ''[[Jawbreaker (movie)|Jawbreaker]]'', as well as a television episode of ''[[The X-Files]]''. Lily Tomlin played a waitress who worked at Johnie's in ''[[Short Cuts]]''. The last film shot at Johnie's was ''[[The Country Bears]]''.&lt;ref name=&quot;john&quot;&gt;[http://www.johniesbroiler.net/history.htm History&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;

The restaurant was closed in 2001, and a used car dealership leased the property. In January 2007, the leasees of Johnie's started to illegally tear it down.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.thedowneypatriot.net/pdfs/1-12-07.pdf]{{dead link|date=November 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; The destruction of the building was halted, with extreme damage to the building, though the sign is intact.&lt;ref name=&quot;john&quot;/&gt; Tenants made significant alterations to the dining room without permits, and the City of [[Downey]] had to issue several stop work orders and citations.&lt;ref name=&quot;john&quot;/&gt;

===Bob's Big Boy===
In April 2008, Jim Louder, owner of the [[Bob's Big Boy]] restaurant in Torrance, California, entered into a long-term lease agreement with the owner of Johnie's Broiler.&lt;ref name=&quot;Long Beach Press Telegram&quot;&gt;{{cite web | last = Gonzaga| first = Samantha| title = Bob's Big Boy to Replace Johnie's| publisher = [[Long Beach Press-Telegram]]| date = 2008-04-08| url = http://www.presstelegram.com/ci_8857848| accessdate = 2008-09-07 }}&lt;/ref&gt;  The restaurant was rebuilt as a Bob's Broiler and incorporated the surviving architectural elements of the old structure into the new restaurant.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |last = Gonzaga| first = Samantha | title = New Future for Johnie's | publisher = [[Long Beach Press-Telegram]] | date = 2008-11-08 | url=http://www.presstelegram.com/lifestyle/dining/ci_10172183 | accessdate = 2008-09-07}}&lt;/ref&gt; Bob's Big Boy Broiler is now open for business.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.bobsbigboybroiler.com/ Bob's Big Boy Broiler, Downey, California - Restaurant - Downey | Facebook&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;

===First Taco Bell===
[[Glen Bell]] opened the first [[Taco Bell]] restaurant on March 21, 1962, in Downey. The building, at 7112 Firestone Boulevard, is largely unchanged from its original appearance, but it is no longer a Taco Bell.&lt;!--note:the date originally came from the Taco Bell website, but it's now all flash-based, so you can't reference a specific page anymore.--&gt;

==Downey Farmers' Market==
The Downtown Downey Farmers' Market was approved by the Downey City Council in 2008.  It has rapidly blossomed into a community main attraction, with the standard fruit and vegetable stands and a growing number of food booths. It is open every Saturday from 9 AM to 1 PM on Second Street between New St. and La Reina.  The market is intended to be a community gathering place, an opportunity to purchase California-grown products, homemade tamales and a vehicle to  improve and finance Downtown Downey.
&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.downeyca.org/thingstodo/market.asp City of Downey - Farmers' Market&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;

==Crime==
While reports of robberies, aggravated assaults and petty thefts in Downey dropped in 2008, auto thefts reached a 10-year high. In 2008, 1,231 vehicles were reported stolen in Downey. Other crimes recorded by the FBI Crime Index for the year 2008 include 252 robberies, 172 aggravated assaults, 24 rapes, 711 burglaries and 2,038 acts of larceny/thefts.&lt;ref&gt;[http://thedowneypatriot.com/view/full_story/2876155/article-Auto-theft-climbs-to-10-year-high The Downey Patriot - Auto theft climbs to 10 year high&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;

'''Anti-gang activities'''

In the late 1980s and early 1990s, Downey saw an increase in gang activity.  Today there is still gang activity going in the south area of Downey.  In response, Downey formed [[GOOD (Gangs Out Of Downey)]], a community-based organization that helps encourage young people between the ages of 10-20 to stay away from gangs. GOOD is also responsible for organizing many community events and programs such as various sports, after school care, scholarship programs for at-risk students looking to attend college, and counseling for both young people and their parents. GOOD has kept a close partnership with [[Downey Police]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.pointsoflight.org/downloads/pdf/awards/dpol/DailyPOLF2002.pdf#search=%22gangs%20out%20of%20downey%22]{{dead link|date=November 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Transportation==
The city can be conveniently reached by any of four freeways: [[Interstate 105 (California)|Interstate 105]] with its [[Metro Green Line (LACMTA)|Metro rail line]] passes through the southern part of the city, [[Interstate 5 (California)|Interstate 5]] passes through the northern part, [[Interstate 605 (California)|Interstate 605]] passes along the eastern side, and [[Interstate 710 (California)|Interstate 710]] passes just west of the city.

[[Los Angeles County Metropolitan Transportation Authority]] (Metro) provides bus services to the city. The city also operates a local bus service called [[List of small Southern California transit agencies#DowneyLINK|DowneyLINK]].

==Education==
===Primary and secondary schools===
[[Image:OLPH.JPG|thumb|150px|right|Our Lady of Perpetual Help, serving the Catholic Community of Downey]]
Downey is within the [[Downey Unified School District]].
Public schools include:
* [[Downey High School]]
* Alameda Elementary School
* [[Warren High School (Downey, California)]] Named after the 14th Chief Justice of the United States [[Earl Warren]].
* Columbus High School
* West Middle School
* East Middle School
* Griffiths Middle School (formerly [North Junior High School])
* Sussman Middle School (formerly [South Middle School])
* Carpenter Elementary School
* Gallatin Elementary School
* Gauldin Elementary School
* Imperial Elementary School
* Lewis Elementary School
* Old River Elementary School
* Price Elementary School
* Rio Hondo Elementary School
* Rio San Gabriel Elementary School
* Unsworth Elementary School
* Ward Elementary School
* Williams Elementary School
[[Image:NewDowneyHomes.JPG|thumb|185px|right|New Homes in Downey]]
Private schools include:
* Our Lady of Perpetual Help School: pre K-8
* Calvary Chapel, Downey: pre K-12
* [[St. Matthias High School]]: 9-12
* Saint Raymond's Catholic School: pre K-8
* Saint Mark's Episcopal School: pre K-8

===Public libraries===
The Downey City Library serves the city. The first library in Downey was established in 1901 by a women's social club that was founded in 1898. The [[County of Los Angeles Public Library]] opened a branch in Downey in September 1915. The county branch moved several times; its final location was in the County Civic Center. In 1958 the Downey City Council voted to establish its own library and withdraw from the county system. The city library services were originally provided out of the back of a bookstore. The city library opened in the former cafeteria of the former Downey Elementary School, then being used as the city hall and police station, on July 1, 1958. A permanent library building was built on December 7, 1959. It had almost {{convert|16000|sqft|sqm}} and it was built for $186,200, costing $11.97 per square foot. It was dedicated on December 17 and opened on December 18. In February 1984 an addition of almost {{convert|12000|sqft|sqm}} was completed and dedicated.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;[http://www.downeylibrary.org/about/ About the Library].&quot; Downey Public Library. Retrieved on March 5, 2010.&lt;/ref&gt;

In addition the headquarters of the County of Los Angeles Public Library are located in Downey.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;[http://www.colapublib.org/aboutus/publicinfo.html Public Records].&quot; [[County of Los Angeles Public Library]]. Retrieved on March 5, 2010.&lt;/ref&gt;

== Notable citizens ==

* [[Alanna Ubach]], actress, was born in Downey.
* [[Allison Iraheta]], musician and [[American Idol (season 8)|American Idol season eight]] contestant, raised in Downey.
* [[Aimee Teegarden]], actress (''[[Friday Night Lights (TV series)|Friday Night Lights]]'') and fashion model
*The brother and sister music duo [[The Carpenters]] moved to Downey from [[New Haven, Connecticut|New Haven]] in 1963 with their family. When they hit it big in the 1970s they built two apartment buildings there that still operate today. They stand across the street from each other on 5th St. and are named after their two biggest hits &quot;[[We've Only Just Begun]]&quot; and &quot;[[(They Long to Be) Close to You|Close To You]]&quot;. The Carpenter's family house still stands today in Newville Avenue as well. The house can be seen on the cover of their album, ''[[Now &amp; Then (The Carpenters album)|Now &amp; Then]]''.
* Rock and country musician [[Dave Alvin]] was born and raised in Downey. He formed the early Downey based [[rockabilly]] band [[The Blasters]] with his brother Phil, and later started a solo career as a country musician. He wrote a song called ''Downey Girl'' released on his 2009 album ''Dave Alvin &amp; The Guilty Women''.
*Thrash metal band [[Dark Angel (band)|Dark Angel]] formed in Downey.
*Surfer and acoustic rock musician [[Donavon Frankenreiter]] was born in Downey.
*[[Dan Henderson]], a mixed martial artist, was born in Downey.
* [[Metallica]] frontman [[James Hetfield]] was born and raised in Downey.  Also, original Metallica bassist Ron McGovney attended Downey Elementary, East Middle School, and graduated from [[Downey High School]] in 1981.
*[[Miranda Cosgrove]], actress and singer starring in the Nickelodeon show [[iCarly]] was raised in Downey.
*[[Evan Longoria]], an All-Star 3rd baseman for the [[Tampa Bay Rays]], who was born in, and raised as, a Downey resident.
*[[Kimmy Robertson]], best known for her role as [[Lucy Moran]] in the TV series [[Twin Peaks]], was raised in Downey.
*[[Wayne Rainey]], three-time world champion [[Grand Prix motorcycle racing|motorcycle]] [[road racing|road racer]]
* [[Weird Al Yankovic]] the [[polka]] parody artist was born in Downey in 1959.
*Olympians [[JoJo Starbuck]] and [[Kenneth Shelley]] were raised in Downey.
*[[Dennis Sproul]], [[NFL]] player, was born in Downey.
* [[Ira J. McDonald]], Los Angeles City Council member, 1941–43, Downey civic leader
* [[William Bonin]], serial killer was Downey resident during his crime spree

==References==
{{Reflist|30em}}

==External links==
{{Portal|Los Angeles|Greater Los Angeles|Southern California}}
*[http://www.downeyca.org/ Downey official website]
*[http://www.thedowneypatriot.com/ The Downey Patriot newspaper]
*[http://www.downeyhistoricalsociety.org/ Downey Historical Society]
*[http://www.preservationnation.org/travel-and-sites/sites/western-region/oldest-surviving-mcdonalds.html National Trust for Historic Preservation article on the oldest surviving McDonald's]
*[http://www.downeyca.org/visitors/attractions/mcdonalds.asp World's Oldest McDonald's]
*[http://downey.fewblocks.com/ Downey local portal]

{{Geographic Location 2
 | Center    = Downey
 | North     = [[Commerce, California|Commerce]]
 | Northeast = [[Pico Rivera, California|Pico Rivera]]
 | East      = [[Santa Fe Springs, California|Santa Fe Springs]]
 | Southeast = [[Norwalk, California|Norwalk]]
 | Southwest = [[Paramount, California|Paramount]]
 | South     = [[Bellflower, California|Belllflower]]
 | West      = [[South Gate, California|South Gate]]
 | Northwest = [[Bell Gardens, California|Bell Gardens]]
}}

{{Cities of Los Angeles County, California}}
{{Greater Los Angeles Area}}
{{California cities and mayors of 100,000 population}}

[[Category:Cities in Los Angeles County, California]]
[[Category:Populated places in California with Hispanic majority populations]]
[[Category:Incorporated cities and towns in California]]

[[ar:داوني، لوس أنجليس، كاليفورنيا]]
[[bs:Downey, California]]
[[bg:Дауни (Калифорния)]]
[[ca:Downey (Califòrnia)]]
[[de:Downey]]
[[es:Downey (California)]]
[[fr:Downey]]
[[hr:Downey, Kalifornija]]
[[it:Downey (California)]]
[[sw:Downey, California]]
[[ht:Downey, Kalifòni]]
[[nl:Downey]]
[[ja:ダウニー (カリフォルニア州)]]
[[no:Downey]]
[[pnb:ڈاؤنی]]
[[pl:Downey (Kalifornia)]]
[[pt:Downey (Califórnia)]]
[[ro:Downey, California]]
[[ru:Дауни (Калифорния)]]
[[sv:Downey, Kalifornien]]
[[tl:Downey, California]]
[[vi:Downey, California]]
[[vo:Downey (California)]]
[[war:Downey, California]]
[[zh:唐尼 (加利福尼亞州)]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
