<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="107640" ns="0" title="Inglewood, California"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Infobox settlement
|official_name            = Inglewood
|image_seal              = SealInglewood.jpg
|nickname                =
|motto                   =  Harbor of the Air (undated)[http://articles.latimes.com/1995-05-19/local/me-3427_1_jack-nicholson]
|settlement_type         = City
|seal_size               =
|image_map                = LA County Incorporated Areas Inglewood highlighted.svg
|mapsize                  = 250x200px
|map_caption              = Location of Inglewood in [[Los Angeles County, California|Los Angeles County]], [[California]]
|coordinates_region       = US-CA
|subdivision_type         = [[List of countries|Country]]
|subdivision_name         = [[United States]]
|subdivision_type1        = [[Political divisions of the United States|State]]
|subdivision_name1        = [[California]]
|subdivision_type2        = [[List of counties in California|County]]
|subdivision_name2        = [[Los Angeles County, California|Los Angeles]]
|government_type          = [[Council-manager government|Council-Manager]]
|leader_title             = [[Mayor]]
|leader_name              = [[James T Butts Jr|James Butts]]&lt;ref&gt;http://www.cityofinglewood.org/city_hall/mayor/default.asp&lt;/ref&gt;
|established_title        = Established
|established_title2       = Incorporated
|established_date         = 1888
|established_date2        = February 14, 1908&lt;ref name=&quot;inc&quot;/&gt;
&lt;!-- Area------------------&gt;
|area_magnitude           =
| unit_pref               =US
| area_footnotes          = &lt;ref&gt;[http://www.census.gov/geo/www/gazetteer/files/Gaz_places_national.txt U.S. Census]&lt;/ref&gt;
| area_total_sq_mi        = 9.093
| area_land_sq_mi         = 9.068
| area_water_sq_mi        = 0.025
| area_total_km2          = 23.549
| area_land_km2           = 23.486
| area_water_km2          = 0.064
| area_water_percent      = 0.27
| area_note               =
|area_urban_sq_mi         =
|area_urban_km2           =
|area_metro_sq_mi         =
|area_metro_km2           =
|population_as_of         = 2010
|population_note          = [[2010 United States Census]]
|population_total         = 109673
| population_rank  =[[List of cities in Los Angeles County, California|12th]] in Los Angeles County&lt;br/&gt;[[List of largest California cities by population|55th]] in California&lt;br/&gt;[[List of United States cities by population|237th]] in the United States
|population_metro         =
|population_urban         =
|population_density_km2   = auto
|population_density_sq_mi = auto
|timezone                 = [[Pacific Standard Time|PST]]
|utc_offset               = -8
|timezone_DST             = PDT
|utc_offset_DST           = -7
|latd = 33 |latm = 57 |lats = 27 |latNS = N
|longd = 118 |longm = 20 |longs = 46 |longEW = W
|coordinates_display      = display=inline,title
|elevation_m              = 40
|elevation_ft             = 131
|website                  = [http://www.cityofinglewood.org/ cityofinglewood.org]
|postal_code_type         = [[ZIP code]]s
|postal_code              = 90301-90313, 90397-90398
|area_code                = [[Area code 310|310]]
|blank_name               = [[Federal Information Processing Standard|FIPS code]]
|blank_info               = 06-36546
|blank1_name              = [[Geographic Names Information System|GNIS]] feature ID
|blank1_info              = 1660799
}}
'''Inglewood''' is a city in southwestern [[Los Angeles County, California]], southwest of downtown [[Los Angeles, California|Los Angeles]]. It was incorporated on February 14, 1908.&lt;ref name=&quot;inc&quot;&gt;{{cite news |title=City History |work=City of Inglewood |url=http://www.cityofinglewood.org/about/city_history.asp }}&lt;/ref&gt; Its population stood at 109,673 as of the [[2010 United States Census|2010 Census]].  The city is in the [[South Bay, Los Angeles|South Bay]] region of the [[Greater Los Angeles Area|greater Los Angeles area]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.chooselacounty.com/images/doingbusiness/la-county-map.jpg  Choose LA County ]&lt;/ref&gt;

== History ==
===Pre-American era===
The earliest residents of what is now  Inglewood were [[indigenous people]] who used the natural springs in today's Edward Vincent Jr. Park (known for most of its history as Centinela Park). Local historian [[Gladys Waddingham]] wrote that these springs took the name ''Centinela'' from the hills that rose gradually around them and which allowed ranchers to watch over their herds &quot;(thus the name centinelas or sentinels).&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;GW&quot;&gt;{{cite book|last=Waddingham|first=Gladys|title=The History of Inglewood|publisher=The Historical Society of Centinela Valley|location=Inglewood|year=1994|isbn=none}}&lt;/ref&gt;{{Rp|unpaged [xiv]|date=May 2009}}

Waddingham traced the written history of Inglewood back to the original settlers of Los Angeles in 1781, one of whom was the Spanish soldier [[Rancho La Ballona#Machado family|Jose Manuel Orchado Machado]], &quot;a 23-year-old muleteer from Los Alamos in  Sinaloa.&quot; These settlers, she wrote, were ordered by the officials of the San  Gabriel Mission &quot;to graze their animals on the ocean side of Los Angeles in order not to infringe on Mission lands.&quot; As a result, the settlers, or ''pobladores,'' drove some of their cattle to the &quot;lush pasture lands near Centinela Springs,&quot; and the first construction there was done by one [[Cornelio Avila#Antonio Ygnacio Avila|Ygnacio Avila]], who received a permit in 1822 to build a &quot;corral and hut for his herders.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;GW&quot;/&gt;{{Rp|unpaged [xiv]|date=May 2009}}
[[Image:CentinelaAdobe-1890.jpg|thumb|left|Rancho Aguaje de la Centinela Adobe, 1889]]
Later Avila constructed a three-room adobe on a slight rise overlooking the creek that ran from Centinela Springs all the way to the ocean. According to the LAOkay web site,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |title=Things To Do In Los Angeles |work=LAOkay.com |url=http://www.laokay.com/AdobeSites.htm#Inglewood }}&lt;/ref&gt; this adobe was built where the present baseball field is in the park. It no longer exists.

In 1834 Ygnacio Machado, one of the sons of Jose Machado, built the [[Centinela Adobe]],&lt;ref name=&quot;GW&quot;/&gt;{{Rp|unpaged [xv]|date=May 2009}} which sits on a rise above the present 405 [[Interstate 405 (California)|San Diego Freeway]] and is used as the headquarters of the Centinela Valley Historical Society. [http://www.cityofinglewood.org/depts/rec/centinela_adobe/default.asp] Two years later, Waddingham writes, Ygnacio&lt;ref&gt;Waddingham used the spelling ''Ignacio'' for both Avila and Machado.&lt;/ref&gt; was granted the {{convert|2220|acre|km2|sing=on}} [[Rancho Aguaje de la Centinela]] even though this land had already been claimed by Avila.&lt;ref name=&quot;GW&quot;/&gt;{{Rp|unpaged [xv]|date=May 2009}}

===American era===
[[Image:Inglewood-1890.jpg|thumb|right|Inglewood, about 1894]]
[[Image:Inglewood-1910.jpg|thumb|right|Commercial Street (later [[La Brea Avenue]]) in Inglewood, sometime around 1910]]
[[File:KHJ-AM,1927.jpg|thumb|right|Radio engineer Ernest G. Underwood sitting at desk of his [[KHJ (AM)|KHJ]] broadcasting station in Inglewood, 1927]]
[[Image:Aircraft workers on lunch break 1942.gif|thumb|Aircraft workers on lunch break in Inglewood aircraft factory of [[North American Aviation]], 1942.]]

====Through the years====
[[Inglewood Park Cemetery]], a widely used cemetery for the entire region, was founded in 1905,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |title=Inglewood Park Cemetery: Living Heritage |work=Inglewood Park Cemetery |url=http://www.inglewoodparkcemetery.org/heritage.html }}&lt;/ref&gt; and the city has been home to the [[Hollywood Park Racetrack]] since 1938.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |title=Hollywood Park: About |work=Hollywood Park |url=http://www.hollywoodpark.com/about/history.html }}&lt;/ref&gt;
[[Fosters Freeze]], the first [[Soft Serve]] ice cream chain in California, was founded by George Foster  in 1946 in Inglewood.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |title=Fosters Freeze: Company History |work=Fosters Freeze |url=http://www.fostersfreeze.com/Company.html }}&lt;/ref&gt; Inglewood was named an [[All-America City]] by the [[National Civic League]] in 1989 and yet again recently in 2009 for its visible progress.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |title=Past Winners of the All-America City Award |work=National Civic League |url=http://www.ncl.org/aac/past_winners/past_winners_1980s.html }}&lt;/ref&gt;

====Ku Klux Klan====
{{Main|Ku Klux Klan in Inglewood, California}}

Ku Klux Klan activities in Inglewood during the 20th century were highlighted by the 1922 arrest and trial of 37 men, most of them masked, for a night-time raid on a suspected [[rum-running|bootlegger]] and his family. The raid led to the shooting death of one of the culprits, an Inglewood police officer.  A jury returned a &quot;not guilty&quot; verdict for all defendants who completed the trial. It was this scandal, according to the ''Los Angeles Times,'' that eventually led to the outlawing of the [[Ku Klux Klan|Klan]] in California.&lt;ref name=LAT19490521&gt;[http://proquest.umi.com.ezproxy.lapl.org/pqdweb?did=418321431&amp;sid=4&amp;Fmt=10&amp;clientId=13322&amp;RQT=309&amp;VName=HNP &quot;Ex-Klan Chief Dies After Traffic Row; Knife Fight With Truck Driver Following Collision Proves Fatal for Gus Price, 64.&quot; ''Los Angeles Times,'' May 21, 1949]&lt;/ref&gt; The Klan had a chapter in Inglewood as late as October 1931.

====African-American influence====
“No blacks had ever lived in Inglewood,” Gladys Waddingham wrote,&lt;ref name=&quot;GW&quot;/&gt;{{Rp|59|date=May 2009}}  but by 1960, “they lived in great numbers along its eastern borders. This came to the great displeasure of the predominantly white residents already residing in Inglewood. In 1960, the census counted only 29 'Negroes' among Inglewood's 63,390 residents. Not a single black child attended the city's schools. Real estate agents refused to show homes to blacks. A rumored curfew kept blacks off the streets at night. Inglewood was a prime target because of its [previous] history of restrictions.” “Fair housing and school busing were the main problems of 1964. The schools were not prepared to handle racial incidents, even though any that occurred were very minor. Adults held many heated community meetings, since the Blacks objected to busing as much as did the Whites.”&lt;ref name=&quot;GW&quot;/&gt;{{Rp|61|date=May 2009}} In 1969, an organization called “Morningside Neighbors” changed its name to “Inglewood Neighbors&quot; &quot;in the hope of promoting more integration.”&lt;ref name=&quot;GW&quot;/&gt;{{Rp|63|date=May 2009}}

On July 22, 1970, Los Angeles Superior Court Judge Max F. Deutz ordered Inglewood schools to desegregate in response to a suit filed by 19 parents.&lt;ref name=LAT19700902&gt;&quot;Parents Lose Plea in Inglewood Suit,&quot; ''Los Angeles Times,'' September 2, 1970, page D-2&lt;/ref&gt; At least since 1965, said Deutz, the Inglewood school board had been aware of a growing influx of black families into its eastern areas but had done nothing about the polarization of its pupils into an eastern black area and a western white one.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;Inglewood Order,&quot; ''Los Angeles Times,'' July 26, 1970, page F-5&lt;/ref&gt; On August 31, he rejected an appeal by four parents who said the school board was not responsible for the segregation but that the blacks &quot;selected their places of residence by voluntary choice.&quot;&lt;ref name=LAT19700902/&gt;

The first black principal among the 18 Inglewood schools was Peter Butler at La Tijera Elementary,&lt;ref name=&quot;GW&quot;/&gt;{{Rp|66|date=May 2009}} and in 1971, Waddingham wrote, “Stormy racial meetings in 1971” included a charge by “some [[real estate]] men in the overflowing Crozier Auditorium” that the Human Relations Commission was acting like “the Gestapo.”&lt;ref name=&quot;GW&quot;/&gt;{{Rp|67|date=May 2009}} In that year, Loyd Sterling Webb, president of ''Inglewood Neighbors'', became the first black officeholder when voters elected him to the school board.&lt;ref&gt;[http://proquest.umi.com.ezproxy.lapl.org/pqdweb?did=601423232&amp;sid=1&amp;Fmt=10&amp;clientId=13322&amp;RQT=309&amp;VName=HNP &quot;Negro Elected to Inglewood Public Office,&quot; ''Los Angeles Times,'' April 7, 1971, page 18]&lt;/ref&gt;

In 1972 Curtis Tucker Sr. was appointed as the first black City Council member.&lt;ref name=&quot;GW&quot;/&gt;{{Rp|69|date=May 2009}} That year composer LeRoy Hurte, an [[African American|African-American]], took the baton of the Inglewood Symphony Orchestra and continued to work with it for 20 years.&lt;ref name=&quot;GW&quot;/&gt;{{Rp|75|date=May 2009}}  [[Edward Vincent]] became Inglewood’s first black mayor in 1980. In that decade Inglewood became the first city in California to declare the birthday of [[Martin Luther King, Jr.]] as a holiday.&lt;ref name=&quot;GW&quot;/&gt;{{Rp|76|date=May 2009}}

====Rise of Latino population====

The 1990 census showed that Hispanics in Inglewood had increased by 134 percent since 1980, the largest jump in the South Bay. Economic factors apparently played a role in where new arrivals settled, said David Heer, a USC professor of sociology and associate director of the university's Population Research Laboratory. &quot;Housing is generally less expensive here than elsewhere . . . and I would say that they receive a warmer welcome here,&quot; said Norm Cravens, assistant city manager in Inglewood, where the Anglo population dropped from nearly 21 percent in 1980 to 8.5 percent in 1990.&lt;ref&gt;[http://proquest­.umi­.com­.ezproxy­.lapl­.org/pqdweb­?did=61104958­&amp;sid=3­&amp;Fmt=3­&amp;clientId=13322­&amp;RQT=309­&amp;VName=PQD Janet-Rae Dupree, “Census Shows Influx of Asians on Peninsula,” ''Los Angeles Times,'' February 28, 1991, page 3]&lt;/ref&gt;

In the 2000 census, blacks made up 47 percent of the city's residents (53,060 people), and Hispanics made up 46 percent (51,829), but the Census Bureau estimated that in 2007 the percentage of blacks had declined to 41 percent (48,252) and that of Hispanics of any race were at 52.5 percent (61,847). The white population declined from 19 percent (21,505) to 17.7 percent (20,853).&lt;ref&gt;[http://factfinder.census.gov/servlet/SAFFFacts?_event=Search&amp;geo_id=01000US&amp;_geoContext=01000US&amp;_street=&amp;_county=Inglewood&amp;_cityTown=Inglewood&amp;_state=04000US06&amp;_zip=&amp;_lang=en&amp;_sse=on&amp;ActiveGeoDiv=geoSelect&amp;_useEV=&amp;pctxt=fph&amp;pgsl=010&amp;_submenuId=factsheet_1&amp;ds_name=DEC_2000_SAFF&amp;_ci_nbr=null&amp;qr_name=null&amp;reg=null%3Anull&amp;_keyword=&amp;_industry=  U.S. Census Bureau, American FactFinder figures for 2000]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://factfinder.census.gov/servlet/ACSSAFFFacts?_event=&amp;geo_id=16000US0636546&amp;_geoContext=01000US%7C04000US06%7C16000US0636546&amp;_street=&amp;_county=Inglewood&amp;_cityTown=Inglewood&amp;_state=04000US06&amp;_zip=&amp;_lang=en&amp;_sse=on&amp;ActiveGeoDiv=geoSelect&amp;_useEV=&amp;pctxt=fph&amp;pgsl=160&amp;_submenuId=factsheet_1&amp;ds_name=DEC_2000_SAFF&amp;_ci_nbr=null&amp;qr_name=null&amp;reg=null%3Anull&amp;_keyword=&amp;_industry= U.S. Census Bureau, American FactFinder estimates for 2007]&lt;/ref&gt;

But in that year, only one of the city's five City Council members was Latino, Jose Fernandez. There were no Latinos on the five-member Board of Education.&lt;ref&gt;[http://proquest.umi.com.ezproxy.lapl.org/pqdweb?did=62342343&amp;sid=1&amp;Fmt=3&amp;clientId=13322&amp;RQT=309&amp;VName=PQD Hugo Martin, &quot;Latino Revolution Leaves Some City Councils Untouched,&quot; ''Los Angeles Times,'' October 9, 2000, page 1]&lt;/ref&gt;

==Geography==
[[Image:2008-0914-RandysDonuts.jpg|thumb|right|upright|[[Randy's Donuts]] is a landmark in Inglewood, near the [[Interstate 405 (California)|405 Freeway]].]]

===Location and area===
According to the [[United States Census Bureau]], the city has a total area of {{convert|9.1|sqmi|km2}}. Downtown Inglewood is {{convert|4.15|mi|km}} from [[Los Angeles International Airport]] (LAX).

==Neighborhoods==
===Crenshaw-Imperial===
The Crenshaw-Imperial district was a later annexation to Inglewood. It has its own branch public library and an important shopping center for the area.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |title=City of Inglewood: Departments - Library |work=City of Inglewood |url=http://www.cityofinglewood.org/depts/library/default.asp }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |title=Crenshaw Imperial Shopping Center (includes a map)|work=LoopNet |publisher=LoopNet, Inc. |url=http://www.loopnet.com/xNet/MainSite/Listing/Profile/ProfileSE.aspx?LID=13568669&amp;linkcode=1070&amp;sourcecode=1lww2t006a00001 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Morningside Park===
Morningside Park is a district in the eastern part of the city. Though the city of Inglewood does not define the district's boundaries, it may be delineated by [[Hyde Park, Los Angeles, California|Hyde Park]] on the north, [[South Los Angeles]] on the east, [[Century Boulevard]] on the south and Prairie Avenue on the west. The major streets that run through the area are Manchester and Crenshaw boulevards. It is six miles (10&amp;nbsp;km) from [[Los Angeles International Airport]] and about two miles (3&amp;nbsp;km) from the [[Hollywood Park Racetrack]] and [[The Forum (Inglewood, California)|The Forum]] where for 31 years the [[Los Angeles Lakers]] and [[Los Angeles Kings]] played.

===North Inglewood and Fairview Heights===

North Inglewood is the area north of the Santa Fe railroad tracks. In 2009, it was reported to be the site of a &quot;burgeoning arts scene&quot; centered at East Hyde Park Boulevard and [[La Brea Avenue]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.latimes.com/news/local/la-me-inglewood16-2009nov16,0,1996026.story  Alejandro Lazo, &quot;Inglewood art studio tour a stroke of genius,&quot; ''Los Angeles Times,'' November 16, 2009]&lt;/ref&gt;  Fairview Heights is a signed area north of Florence and east of La Brea.

==Demographics==
===2010 census===
The [[2010 United States Census]]&lt;ref&gt;{{USCensus-2010CA}}&lt;/ref&gt; reported that Inglewood had a population of 109,673. The [[population density]] was 12,062.1 people per square mile (4,657.2/km²). The racial makeup of Inglewood was 25,562 (23.3%) [[White (U.S. Census)|White]], 48,164 (43.9%) [[African American (U.S. Census)|African American]], 751 (0.7%) [[Native American (U.S. Census)|Native American]], 1,484 (1.4%) [[Asian (U.S. Census)|Asian]], 350 (0.3%) [[Pacific Islander (U.S. Census)|Pacific Islander]], 28,860 (26.3%) from [[Race (United States Census)|other races]], and 4,502 (4.1%) from two or more races. There were 55,449 people classifying themselves as  [[Hispanic (U.S. Census)|Hispanic]] or [[Latino (U.S. Census)|Latino]] — 50.6% of the population.{{Clarify|date=August 2011}}

The Census reported that 108,171 people (98.6% of the population) lived in households, 987 (0.9%) lived in non-institutionalized group quarters, and 515 (0.5%) were institutionalized.

There were 36,389 households, out of which 15,315 (42.1%) had children under the age of 18 living in them, 13,095 (36.0%) were [[marriage|opposite-sex married couples]] living together, 8,987 (24.7%) had a female householder with no husband present, 2,937 (8.1%) had a male householder with no wife present.  There were 2,318 (6.4%) [[POSSLQ|unmarried opposite-sex partnerships]], and 234 (0.6%) [[same-sex partnerships|same-sex married couples or partnerships]]. 9,346 households (25.7%) were made up of individuals and 2,776 (7.6%) had someone living alone who was 65 years of age or older. The average household size was 2.97.  There were 25,019 [[family (U.S. Census)|families]] (68.8% of all households); the average family size was 3.59.

The population was spread out with 29,293 people (26.7%) under the age of 18, 11,853 people (10.8%) aged 18 to 24, 31,650 people (28.9%) aged 25 to 44, 26,621 people (24.3%) aged 45 to 64, and 10,256 people (9.4%) who were 65 years of age or older.  The median age was 33.4 years. For every 100 females there were 90.6 males.  For every 100 females age 18 and over, there were 86.8 males.

There were 38,429 housing units at an average density of 4,226.5 per square mile (1,631.9/km²), of which 13,447 (37.0%) were owner-occupied, and 22,942 (63.0%) were occupied by renters. The homeowner vacancy rate was 1.5%; the rental vacancy rate was 5.5%.  43,040 people (39.2% of the population) lived in owner-occupied housing units and 65,131 people (59.4%) lived in rental housing units.

===2006 survey===
&lt;blockquote&gt;''Source for this section is the American Community Survey conducted by the U.S. Census Bureau in 2006. Numbers may be rounded to the nearest whole figure.''&lt;ref name=2006Estimate&gt;[http://www.factfinder.census.gov/servlet/ACSSAFFFacts?_event=&amp;geo_id=16000US0636546&amp;_geoContext=01000US%7C04000US06%7C16000US0636546&amp;_street=&amp;_county=Inglewood&amp;_cityTown=Inglewood&amp;_state=04000US06&amp;_zip=&amp;_lang=en&amp;_sse=on&amp;ActiveGeoDiv=&amp;_useEV=&amp;pctxt=fph&amp;pgsl=160&amp;_submenuId=factsheet_1&amp;ds_name=DEC_2000_SAFF&amp;_ci_nbr=null&amp;qr_name=null&amp;reg=null%3Anull&amp;_keyword=&amp;_industry= &quot;2006 American Community Survey,&quot; ''American Fact Finder,'' U.S. Census Bureau]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

Inglewood’s population of 129,900 in 2006 was relatively youthful, with a median age of 31, compared to 36 in the nation as a whole. Eleven percent of its residents were under 5 years of age, as against 7 percent in the rest of the country. Some 8 percent were 65 or older, versus 12 percent elsewhere.

It was a city of renters squeezing into a limited amount of space. Of Inglewood’s 37,562 occupied housing units (houses and apartments), just 39 percent were owned by the people who lived in them (compared to 67 percent in the U.S. as  whole). The other units were rented out. Only 5 percent of its housing units were vacant, much less than the 12 percent across the country. The number of people living in each unit was about 3.7 persons, versus 2.7 elsewhere. Family size was 3.9 people, compared to 3.2.

It was estimated that 18 percent of Inglewood families had incomes below the [[Poverty threshold|poverty level]], about twice that of the country at large (9 percent).

About 17 percent of Inglewood’s residents had earned a [[Bachelor's degree|bachelor’s degree]] or higher (versus 27 percent across the country).

Twenty-nine percent of the city's population were foreign-born, compared to 13 percent in the nation as a whole.

===Mapping L.A.===

In 2009, the ''Los Angeles Times'''s &quot;Mapping L.A.&quot; project supplied these neighborhood statistics based on the 2000 census.&lt;ref name=LATMapping&gt;[http://projects.latimes.com/mapping-la/neighborhoods/neighborhood/inglewood/  &quot;Inglewood&quot; entry on the ''Los Angeles Times'' &quot;Mapping L.A.&quot; website]&lt;/ref&gt;

The population was 112,482, or 12,330 people per square mile, among the highest densities for the [[South Bay]] and among the highest densities for the county. The percentage of black people was high for the county, and the population was moderately diverse. Median household income was $46,574, low for both the South Bay and for the county. The median age was 29, young for the county; the percentage of residents aged 10 or under was among the county's highest. Three people, on the average, lived in each household — high for the South Bay but about average for the county. There was a higher percentage of families headed by single parents than elsewhere in the county. The percentage of veterans who served during 1975-89 and 1990-99 was among the county's highest.
{| class=&quot;wikitable&quot;
|-
! Inglewood&lt;br&gt;and nearby&lt;br&gt;areas
! Inglewood&lt;ref name=LATMapping/&gt;
! Hyde Park&lt;ref&gt;[http://projects.latimes.com/mapping-la/neighborhoods/neighborhood/hyde-park &quot;Hyde Park&quot; entry on the ''Los Angeles Times'' &quot;Mapping L.A.&quot; website]&lt;/ref&gt;
! Ladera&lt;br&gt;Heights&lt;ref&gt;[http://projects.latimes.com/mapping-la/neighborhoods/neighborhood/ladera-heights/ &quot;Ladera Heights&quot; entry on the ''Los Angeles Times'' &quot;Mapping L.A.&quot; website]&lt;/ref&gt;
! Westchester&lt;ref&gt;[http://projects.latimes.com/mapping-la/neighborhoods/neighborhood/westchester/ &quot;Westchester&quot; entry on the ''Los Angeles Times'' &quot;Mapping L.A.&quot; website]&lt;/ref&gt;
! Hawthorne&lt;ref&gt;[http://projects.latimes.com/mapping-la/neighborhoods/neighborhood/hawthorne/ &quot;La Crescenta-Montrose&quot; entry on the ''Los Angeles Times'' &quot;Mapping L.A.&quot; website]&lt;/ref&gt;
|-
| '''Population'''
| 112,482
| 38,635
|  6,509
| 41,500
| 86,265
|-
| '''White'''
|  4%
|  2%
| 19%
| 52%
| 13%
|-
| '''Latino'''
| 46%
| 27%
|  3%
| 17%
| 44%
|-
| '''Asian'''
|  1%
|  1%
|  3%
|  10%
|  8%
|-
| '''Black'''
| 46%
| 66%
| 71%
| 17%
| 32%
|-
| '''Household income'''
| $46,574
| $39,460
| $117,925
| $77,473
| $43,602
|-
| '''College degree'''
| 13%
| 12%
| 53%
| 42%
| 13%
|-
| '''Median age'''
| 29
| 31
| 43
| 35
| 27
|-
| '''Single parents'''
| 27%
| 29%
| 10%
| 15%
| 27%
|-
| '''Veteran'''
|  8%
|  9%
| 13%
|  9%
|  7%
|-
| '''Foreign born'''
| 30%
| 20%
|  7%
| 21%
| 33%
|-
|    '''Where?'''
| Mexico,&lt;br&gt;El Salvador
| Mexico,&lt;br&gt;El Salvador
| Trinidad,&lt;br&gt;Canada
| Mexico,&lt;br&gt;Philippines
| Mexico,&lt;br&gt;Guatemala
|-
| '''Ethnic diversity''' (*)
| Moderate .571
| Moderate .488
| Moderate .446
| High .660
| High .676
|-
| '''Home ownership'''
| 36%
| 47%
| 77%
| 52%
| 26%
|-
|}

&lt;small&gt;(*) &quot;The diversity index measures the probability that any two residents, chosen at random, would be of different ethnicities. If all residents are of the same ethnic group it's zero. If half are from one group and half from another it's .50.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;[http://projects.latimes.com/mapping-la/neighborhoods/diversity/neighborhood/list/#inglewood  Definition of &quot;diversity index&quot; from Mapping L.A.] The most diverse area is [[Mid-Wilshire]], and the least diverse is [[East Los Angeles]]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;/small&gt;

==Politics==
''See also [[Roosevelt Dorn]].''

Inglewood has the highest percentage of registered Democrats of any city in California, with 75.6 percent of its 48,615 voters registered in May 2009 as Democrats. Seven percent were registered as Republicans, and 14.1 percent declined to state a preference.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.sos.ca.gov/elections/ror/ror-pages/15day-stwdsp-09/politicalsub.pdf&lt;/ref&gt;

In 2005, the [[Bay Area Center for Voting Research]], a nonpartisan organization in [[Berkeley, California|Berkeley]], ranked Inglewood as the sixth-most-liberal city in the United States, after [[Oakland, California]], and just ahead of [[Newark, New Jersey]].   Researchers examined voting patterns of 237 American cities with populations over 100,000 and ranked them on liberal and conservative scales.&lt;ref&gt;[http://govpro.com/content/gov_imp_31439/ &quot;Study Ranks America's Most Liberal and Conservative Cities,&quot; ''Govpro.com,'' August 16, 2005]&lt;/ref&gt;

The city is within [[California's 35th congressional district]], which in February 2008 had a [[Cook Partisan Voting Index]] of D +33, which meant that recent Democratic presidential candidates received 33 percentage points more votes than the national average.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | title = Will Gerrymandered Districts Stem the Wave of Voter Unrest? | publisher = Campaign Legal Center Blog | url=http://www.clcblog.org/blog_item-85.html | accessdate = 2008-02-10}}&lt;/ref&gt; It is represented by Democrat [[Maxine Waters]].

In the [[California State Legislature|California Legislature]], Inglewood is in the 25th [[California State Senate|Senate]] District, represented by Democrat [[Rod Wright]] and in the 51st [[California State Assembly|Assembly]] District, represented by Democrat [[Steve Bradford]].

==Government and infrastructure==
The [[Los Angeles County Department of Health Services]] operates the Curtis Tucker Health Center in Inglewood.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;[http://publichealth.lacounty.gov/phn/docs/HealthCenter/inglewood.pdf Curtis Tucker Health Center].&quot; [[Los Angeles County Department of Health Services]]. Retrieved on March 18, 2010.&lt;/ref&gt;

The [[United States Postal Service]] operates the Hillcrest Inglewood Post Office at 300 East Hillcrest Boulevard,&lt;ref&gt;&quot;[http://usps.whitepages.com/service/post_office/72239?p=1&amp;s=CA&amp;service_name=post_office&amp;z=Inglewood Post Office Location - HILLCREST INGLEWOOD].&quot; ''[[United States Postal Service]]''. Retrieved on December 6, 2008.&lt;/ref&gt; the North Inglewood Post Office at 811 North La Brea Avenue,&lt;ref&gt;&quot;[http://usps.whitepages.com/service/post_office/67511?p=1&amp;s=CA&amp;service_name=post_office&amp;z=Inglewood Post Office Location - NORTH INGLEWOOD].&quot; ''[[United States Postal Service]]''. Retrieved on December 6, 2008.&lt;/ref&gt; and the Morningside Park Post Office at 3212 West 85th Street.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;[http://usps.whitepages.com/service/post_office/69024?p=1&amp;s=CA&amp;service_name=post_office&amp;z=Inglewood Post Office Location - MORNINGSIDE PARK].&quot; ''[[United States Postal Service]]''. Retrieved on December 6, 2008.&lt;/ref&gt;

The city is a member of the [[South Bay, Los Angeles|South Bay Cities]] [[Council of Governments]].&lt;ref&gt;http://www.southbaycities.org/node/2&lt;/ref&gt;

The City of Inglewood has a mayor-council type of government.  The mayor is an elected office and is the chief executive officer of the city.

===Public libraries===
The City of Inglewood operates a main library in the city Civic Center, in addition to a branch in the southeastern corner of the city, near the intersection of Crenshaw and Imperial.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.cityofinglewood.org/depts/library/default.asp City of Inglewood Public Library] ''http://www.cityofinglewood.org/''&lt;/ref&gt;

==Education==
[[Image:Inglewood-California-Mural.jpg|thumb|right|400px|Inglewood High School students portrayed historic characters when the restored mural behind them was dedicated in August 2007.]]

===Public and private schools===
Most of Inglewood is served by the [[Inglewood Unified School District]]. The district has two zoned high schools, [[Inglewood High School (California)|Inglewood High School]] and [[Morningside High School]], and an alternative high school, [[City Honors High School]].

Some of it is in the [[Los Angeles Unified School District]]

Public charter schools include:
* [[Ánimo Inglewood Charter High School]] of [[Green Dot Public Schools]]&lt;ref&gt;&quot;[http://www.greendot.org/inglewood/ Home].&quot; [[Ànimo Inglewood Charter High School]]. Retrieved on February 20, 2011. &quot;Copyright © 2007 Animo Inglewood Charter High School - All Rights Reserved 3425 Manchester Blvd. Inglewood, CA 90305.&quot;&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[Ánimo Leadership Charter High School]] of Green Dot&lt;ref&gt;&quot;[http://www.greendot.org/leadership/about_us/contact_us Contact Us].&quot; [[Ánimo Leadership Charter High School]]. Retrieved on February 20, 2011. &quot;Animo Leadership Charter High School 1155 West Arbor Vitae St. Inglewood, CA 90301.&quot;&lt;/ref&gt;

Private schools include:
*St John Chrysostom Elementary School is a private [[Catholic school]].
*[[St. Mary's Academy (Inglewood, California)|St. Mary's Academy]], &quot;In 1966 St. Mary's Academy left its home of many years on [[Slauson Avenue]] [at Crenshaw Boulevard] in Los Angeles for a new building on Grace Avenue across from [Daniel] Freeman Hospital&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;GW&quot;/&gt;{{Rp|62|date=May 2009}}

'''See also'''

*[[Good Shepherd Lutheran School]], 1936–2003

===Schools history===
In 1888, a school district was organized, trustees were elected and a building was chosen. The school opened on May 21 that year on the second floor of a [[livery stable]] on Grevillea Avenue between Regent Street and Orchard (today's Florence Avenue), with 17 boys and 16 girls. The first teacher was Minnie Walker, a graduate of Los Angeles State Normal  School. The schoolroom, named Bucephalus Hall, after a horse belonging to town founder Daniel Freeman, was also used for community meetings.&lt;ref name=&quot;GW&quot;/&gt;{{Rp|6|date=May 2009}}

Meanwhile, a permanent school building was erected on Grevillea Avenue a block to the south, between Regent and Queen. It remained Inglewood's only school until 1911.  It was destroyed by an earthquake in 1920.&lt;ref name=&quot;GW&quot;/&gt;{{Rp|6 and 26|date=May 2009}}

The [[Centinela Valley Union High School District]] was organized in 1904 to bring [[secondary education]] to the town. Inglewood High opened in two rooms of the school building with 15 students taught by Nina Martin, principal, and Anna McClelland. Four years later, a new building rose on {{convert|9.5|acre|m2}} of land, and the first graduation of one boy and four girls took place in 1908.&lt;ref name=&quot;GW&quot;/&gt;{{Rp|13–14|date=May 2009}}
Until 1912 there was a new principal every year at the [[grammar school]], but on May 8 of that year George W. Crozier was named principal, and he held the post for 20 years. The school was renamed in his honor in 1932.&lt;ref name=&quot;GW&quot;/&gt;{{Rp|20|date=May 2009}} In 1913, George M. Green was appointed principal of Inglewood Union High School; he retired from that position in 1939.&lt;ref name=&quot;GW&quot;/&gt;{{Rp|22|date=May 2009}}

In 1914 voters approved bonds for high school improvement. Four more buildings and a [[Power station|power plant]] were erected, &quot;joined by walks and arcades.&quot; The improvement included a &quot;five-room model flat in the Home Economics Building.&quot; Nine acres of land were bought at Kelso Avenue and Damask (now Inglewood Avenue) for an experimental agricultural statement, thenceforth known as &quot;The Farm.&quot; There were gardens, an orchard and an alfalfa field. In 1915 Inglewood High won a first-place Los Angeles County prize for its beautiful ivy-covered brick buildings.&lt;ref name=&quot;GW&quot;/&gt;{{Rp|24|date=May 2009}} These buildings were destroyed in 1953 to make room for new ones.&lt;ref name=&quot;GW&quot;/&gt;{{Rp|unpaged [58c]|date=May 2009}}

In the mid-1920s, the high school district stretched all the way south to El Segundo, so two women teachers were asked to live in El Segundo and ride the school buses with the students every day to and from that city — for an extra dollar a day in pay. In 1923 girls adopted a school uniform, &quot;a dark blue skirt with a white middy.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;GW&quot;/&gt;{{Rp|30|date=May 2009}}

In 1925 a new fine arts building for the high school was erected on the southwest corner of Grevillea and Manchester, replacing the Truax Candy Kitchen,&lt;ref name=&quot;GW&quot;/&gt;{{Rp|34|date=May 2009}} but it was severely damaged by the [[1933 Long Beach earthquake|Long Beach earthquake]] of 1933. It was &quot;later rebuilt with  WPA help but lost its magnificent stairway and all its fireplaces.&quot; Temporary classrooms were built on Olive Street, &quot;all too cold in winter and too hot most of the time.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;GW&quot;/&gt;{{Rp|41|date=May 2009}}

The athletic field on the west side of the campus, later called Badenoch Field, was used for physical education and sporting events. In 1937, agricultural classes were ended at the Farm and Sentinel Field was dedicated there for sports activities.&lt;ref name=&quot;GW&quot;/&gt;{{Rp|30|date=May 2009}} By 1938 there were more than 3,000 students and 141 teachers at the high school.&lt;ref name=&quot;GW&quot;/&gt;{{Rp|43|date=May 2009}}

The &quot;startling news&quot; of 1948 was the dismissal &quot;of the entire administrative staff at Inglewood High School, beginning with Principal James R. Haines.&quot; He was replaced by Forrest Murdoch of Everett, Washington, as superintendent and Fred Heisner as principal.&lt;ref name=&quot;GW&quot;/&gt;{{Rp|49|date=May 2009}}

In 1952, another secondary school campus in Inglewood was opened in the east side neighborhood of Morningside Park as [[Morningside High School]].&lt;ref name=&quot;GW&quot;/&gt;{{Rp|55|date=May 2009}} Center Park School of Los Angeles became part of the Inglewood School District in 1961 when its area (Crenshaw-Imperial) was annexed to the city.&lt;ref name=&quot;GW&quot;/&gt;{{Rp|59|date=May 2009}} In the 1970s, its name was changed to Worthington School to honor Frances and William Worthington.&lt;ref name=&quot;GW&quot;/&gt;{{Rp|74|date=May 2009}}

==Religion==
In 2007 the area served by the Inglewood post office (including Lennox) had 98 churches, temples, mosques, chapels and other houses of worship, according to the AreaConnect.com Web site.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |title=Inglewood Churches and Religion (Inglewood, CA) |work=areaConnect |publisher=MDNH, Inc. |url=http://inglewood.areaconnect.com/churches.htm }}&lt;/ref&gt;

The first church service was held on April 22, 1888, in the Inglewood House hotel on  Commercial Street (today's La Brea Boulevard), popularly called Mrs. Belden's Boarding House, when Inglewood had only 300 residents and 112 registered voters. Later services were in Bucephalus Hall, but eventually the congregation moved to Hyde Park, which left Inglewood with no church. On January 19, 1890, Inglewood's first permanent church — Presbyterian — was established on Market Street. A bit later the [United] Brethren constructed a building on South Market Street.&lt;ref name=&quot;GW&quot;/&gt;{{Rp|6, 10, and 17|date=May 2009}}

In 1907, a group of Episcopalians began services in a private home, and a few years later the first Catholic services were held in Bank Hall.  In 1910 the Presbyterians moved their two buildings, a sanctuary and a manse,  to the corner of Grevillea and Nutwood &quot;because the streetcars [on Market Street] were so noisy and threw so much dust and sand fleas in the windows.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;GW&quot;/&gt;{{Rp|14 and 17|date=May 2009}}

In 1923 St. John Chrysostom Catholic Church was founded.  The current church at the intersection of Centinela and Florence was built in 1959 and is the tallest point in the city.  It is the largest congregation in the city, consisting of almost 10,000 registered families.  Next door is St. John Chrysostom School, educating children since 1927 from Pre-K through 8th grade.{{Citation needed|date=May 2011}}

By 1940, the Methodists had built a structure at Manchester and La Brea, but in that year they moved to a new building at Kelso and Spruce. &lt;ref name=&quot;GW&quot;/&gt;{{Rp|46 and 57|date=May 2009}}

==Community resources==
[[D.A.R.E. America]], an international education program that seeks to prevent use of controlled drugs, membership in gangs and violent behavior, has its headquarters in Inglewood.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;[http://www.dare.com/home/about_dare.asp About D.A.R.E.]&quot; Drug Abuse Resistance Education. Retrieved on July 24, 2010. &quot;D.A.R.E. America 9800 La Cienega Blvd. Suite 401 Inglewood, CA 90301&quot;&lt;/ref&gt;

==Cultural resources==
===Symphony===
The [[Southeast Symphony]] Association is a non-profit, musical and cultural association located in Inglewood, California founded in 1948 whose goal continues to be to create an orchestra that welcomes African-American musicians.[http://www.southeastsymphony.org/index.html]

===Open Studios===

The annual Open Studios event features &quot;drawing, painting, photography and more,&quot; under the general supervision of the Inglewood Cultural Arts organization, aided by the number of artists moving into the community.  The first year of the event saw six artists featured, but at the November 2011 event &quot;more than 30&quot; were expected, said Renee Fox, gallery director at the Beacon Arts Building on North La Brea Avenue. The structure has been turned into 14 artists' studios, with 16 more to be added by the end of 2011. A nearby former auto showroom has also been turned over to artsts.&lt;ref&gt;Barbara Thornburg, &quot;Open Studios Blossoms With Promise,&quot; ''Los Angeles Times,'' November 5, 2011, page E-2&lt;/ref&gt;

==Newspapers==

The ''Inglewood News'' and ''Inglewood Today'' circulate in the city.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.manta.com/c/mtk9c4b/inglewood-news ''Inglewood News'' website]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.inglewoodtodaynews.com/ ''Inglewood Today'' website]&lt;/ref&gt;

==Sister cities==
{{div col|cols=2}}
* {{flagicon|Sierra Leone}}  [[Bo, Sierra Leone]]&lt;ref&gt;[http://articles.latimes.com/1994-06-02/news/cb-64908_1_city-officials Jon  Garcia, &quot;Officials Study Finances of Sister-City Panel,&quot; ''Los Angeles Times,'' June 2, 1994]&lt;/ref&gt;
* {{flagicon|Italy}}  [[Pedavena|Pedavena, Italy]]&lt;ref&gt;[http://articles.latimes.com/1989-09-24/local/me-483_1_sister-city-program Marc Lacey, &quot;Inglewood, Jamaican  City Plan to Become 'Sisters,'&quot; ''Los Angeles Times,'' September 24, 1989]&lt;/ref&gt;
* {{flagicon|Jamaica}}  [[Port Antonio, Jamaica]]&lt;ref&gt;[http://articles.latimes.com/1990-06-15/local/me-140_1_port-antonio &quot;Inglewood Aids City in Jamaica,&quot; ''Los Angeles Times,'' June 15, 1990]&lt;/ref&gt;
* {{flagicon|Mexico}} [[Tijuana, Mexico]]&lt;ref&gt;[http://articles.latimes.com/1991-03-21/local/me-694_1_sister-city-tuesday &quot;Tijuana Adopted as Sister City,&quot; ''Los Angeles Times,'' March 21, 1991]&lt;/ref&gt;
{{div col end}}

==Born in Inglewood==
*[[Paul Pierce]], basketball player for the [[Boston Celtics]]
*[[Don August]], baseball player&lt;ref&gt;http://www.baseball-almanac.com/players/player.php?p=augusdo01&lt;/ref&gt;
*[[Scott Eyre]], baseball player&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.baseball-almanac.com/players/player.php?p=eyresc01 ''Baseball Almanac'']&lt;/ref&gt;
*[[Tyra Lynne Banks|Tyra Banks]], supermodel, television personality, talk show host and actress&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |title=Tyra Banks: Snapshot |work=People Magazine |url=http://www.people.com/people/tyra_banks }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.imdb.com/name/nm0004723 Internet Movie Data Base]&lt;/ref&gt;
*[[Dottie Wiltse Collins]], [[All-American Girls Professional Baseball League]] pitcher&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.aagpbl.org/players/index.cfm?do=player.details&amp;playerid=2 |title=Dorothy Collins |publisher=[[All-American Girls Professional Baseball League|AAGPBL]] |accessdate=2008-08-15}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*[[Maureen Flannigan]], actress
*[[Tanedra Howard]], 2008 winner of ''[[Scream Queens]] (TV series)'' and ''[[Saw VI]]'' star&lt;ref&gt;http://clutchmagonline.com/lifeculture/feature/tanedra-howard-a-dream-deferred-no-more/#2&lt;/ref&gt;
*[[Flo Hyman]], American volleyball player, Morningside High School graduate&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |title=Flo Hyman |work=Microsoft Encarta Online Encyclopedia 2007 |url=http://encarta.msn.com/encyclopedia_761582312/Flo_Hyman.html |archiveurl=http://www.webcitation.org/5kwrN0iIW|archivedate=2009-10-31|deadurl=yes}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*Comedian [[Vicki Lawrence]]&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |title=Vicki Lawrence |work=Richard De La Font Agency, Inc. |url=http://delafont.com/specialty_acts/Vicki-Lawrence.htm }}&lt;/ref&gt;
*[[Jim Lefebvre]], major league baseball manager&lt;ref&gt;http://www.baseball-almanac.com/players/player.php?p=lefebji01&lt;/ref&gt;
*[[Mack 10]], rapper&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |title=Mack 10 |work=IMDb |url=http://www.imdb.com/name/nm0532924/ }}&lt;/ref&gt;
*[[Bishop Lamont|Philip &quot;Bishop Lamont&quot; Martin]], rapper&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |title=Interview with Bishop Lamont |date=January 2006 |work=Aftermath Music |publisher=MRF Entertainment |url=http://www.aftermathmusic.com/_interviews/bishoplamont_january_2006.html }}&lt;/ref&gt;
*[[Len Maxwell]], voice actor and announcer&lt;ref&gt;{{IMDb name|id=0561752 |name=Len Maxwell }}&lt;/ref&gt;
*[[Scott McGregor (baseball)|Scott McGregor]], baseball player with [[Baltimore Orioles]]&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |title=Scott McGregor Baseball Stats |work=Baseball Almanac |url=http://www.baseball-almanac.com/players/player.php?p=mcgresc01 }}&lt;/ref&gt;
*[[Lisa Moretti]], professional wrestler&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |title=Lisa Moretti |work=IMDb |url=http://www.imdb.com/name/nm0604324/ }}&lt;/ref&gt;
*[[Marcel Reece]], professional football player&lt;ref&gt;http://www.raiders.com/media-vault/videos/Behind-the-Shield-Online-October-12th/5a3d083d-5f0c-4d72-8a0c-942027a4cc90&lt;/ref&gt;
*[[Jamal Sampson]], professional basketball player&lt;ref&gt;http://sports.espn.go.com/nba/players/profile?playerId=1780&lt;/ref&gt;
*[[Shade Sheist]], recording artist, singer-songwriter, actor
*Jazz saxophonist [[Zoot Sims]]&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |title=Zoot Sims |work=All About Jazz |url=http://www.allaboutjazz.com/php/musician.php?id=4362 }}&lt;/ref&gt;
*[[Esther Williams]], swimmer and motion picture actress (August 8, 1923).&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |title=Esther Williams |work=BrainyMedia.com |url=http://www.brainyhistory.com/events/1923/august_8_1923_83369.html }}&lt;/ref&gt;
*[[Brian Wilson]] of [[The Beach Boys]]&lt;ref name=&quot;Gaines&quot;&gt;{{cite book|last=Gaines|first=Steven|title=Heroes and Villains: the true story of the Beach Boys|publisher=[[New American Library]]|location=New York|year=1986|page=40|isbn=0 306 80647 9|accessdate=February 18, 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt; (June 20, 1942)
*[[Shawn Chrystopher (Rapper)|Shawn Chrystopher]], recording artist, producer

==Notable residents==
&lt;!-- Please keep this list pristine. You must have a reliable source for anybody you add. ---&gt;
*[[Sonny Bono|Salvatore (Sonny) Bono]] singer, actor, and congressman, attended Inglewood High School&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news| url=http://articles.latimes.com/1998/jan/07/news/mn-5814 | work=Los Angeles Times | first=Nona | last=Yates | date=January 7, 1998 | title=Sonny Bono, a Chronology}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*[[Jeanne Crain]], actress &lt;ref&gt;http://www.hollywood.com/celebrity/Jeanne_Crain/198514&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;http://www.seeing-stars.com/schools/otherschools.shtml&lt;/ref&gt;
*[[Cali Swag District]], hip hop group&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.theboombox.com/2010/06/01/cali-swag-district-bring-the-party-back-to-inglewood/ Nadeska Alexis, &quot;Cali Swag District Bring the Party Back to Inglewood,&quot; ''The Boombox,'' June 1, 2010]&lt;/ref&gt;
*[[Lisa Leslie]], basketball player&lt;ref&gt;[http://sportsillustrated.cnn.com/vault/article/magazine/MAG1135992/index.htm Shelley Smith, &quot;She Was Truckin',&quot; ''Sports Illustrated,'' February 19, 1990]&lt;/ref&gt;
*[[Frank D. Parent]], municipal court judge&lt;ref&gt;(1960, June 20). ''Los Angeles Times'' (1886-Current File), Page B1.  Retrieved November 24, 2009, from ProQuest Historical Newspapers Los Angeles Times (1881-1986). (Document ID: 446603572).&lt;/ref&gt;
*[[Paul Pierce]], basketball player&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.nytimes.com/2008/06/10/sports/basketball/10pierce.html?_r=1 Billy Witz, &quot;Pierce's Road From Inglewood Could Hit Its Summit Nearby,&quot; ''New York Times,'' June 10, 2008]&lt;/ref&gt;
*[[Chastin West]], football player&lt;ref&gt;http://www.packers.com/team/roster/Chastin-West/e69c9b58-ac01-497b-b355-78ace6ce9c8d&lt;/ref&gt;

==Filming locations==
*The city was a filming location for ''[[The Wood]]'', a 1999 movie about three African-American men recalling their childhood in 1980s Inglewood.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |title=The Wood |work=IMDb |url=http://www.imdb.com/title/tt0161100/ }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |title=Plot summary for The Wood |work=IMDb |url=http://www.imdb.com/title/tt0161100/plotsummary }}&lt;/ref&gt;
*Scenes from ''[[Boyz n the Hood]]'', ''[[Training Day]]'' and ''[[Wayne's World]]'' were filmed in Inglewood.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |title=Filming locations for Boyz n the Hood |work=IMDb |url=http://www.imdb.com/title/tt0101507/locations }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |title=Filming locations for Training Day |work=IMDb |url=http://www.imdb.com/title/tt0139654/locations }}&lt;/ref&gt;

==References in popular culture==
*[[Jules Winnfield]], a lead-role gangster played by [[Samuel L. Jackson|Samuel Jackson]] in [[Quentin Tarantino|Quentin Tarantino's]] 1994 film'' [[Pulp Fiction (film)|Pulp Fiction]],'' told another character he lived in Inglewood.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |title=Memorable quotes for Pulp Fiction |work=IMDb |url=http://www.imdb.com/title/tt0110912/quotes }}&lt;/ref&gt;
*The lead character in the movie ''Soul Plane'' (Kevin Hart) stated that he grew up in Inglewood.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |title=Soul Plane Movie Review |work=Netkushi.com |publisher=Web Logix, Inc. |url=http://www.netkushi.com/movies/hollywood_movie_reviews/soul-plane.php }}&lt;/ref&gt;
* In the 1996 song &quot;[[California Love]]&quot;,  [[Dr. Dre]] raps that Inglewood is &quot;always up to no good&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;[[2Pac]]'s [[California Love]], sung by [[Dr. Dre]], 1995&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title=Pierce's Road From Inglewood Could Hit Its Summit Nearby|last=Witz|first=Billy|date=10 June 2008|work=[[The New York Times]]|page=D1|accessdate=11 March 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* A music video from [[Mack 10]] featured Inglewood.&lt;ref name=&quot;Keyes2002&quot;&gt;{{cite book|last=Keyes|first=Cheryl Lynette|title=Rap music and street consciousness|year=2002|publisher=University of Illinois Press|location=Urbana|isbn=0-252-07201-4|page=220}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==See also==
* [[List of California public officials charged with crimes#Inglewood|List of California public officials charged with crimes, Inglewood]]

* [[Los_Angeles_Times_suburban_sections#Suburbs_and_neighborhoods|''Los Angeles Times'' suburban sections]], for a time capsule placed in the Inglewood City Hall
{{-}}

==Notes and references==
{{Reflist|colwidth=30em}}

==Further reading==
* Constance Zillgitt Snowden, ''Men of Inglewood,'' 1924.
* Roy Rosenberg, ''The History of Inglewood'', published by Arthur Cawston, 1938.[http://www.urbanwildlands.org/cited.htm]
* Lloyd Hamilton, ''Inglewood Community Book,'' 1947.

==External links==
{{Portal|Los Angeles|Greater Los Angeles|Southern California}}
*[http://www.cityofinglewood.org/ City of Inglewood official website]
*&quot;[http://www.laweekly.com/2005-07-21/news/welcome-to-inglewood-leave-your-aspirations-behind/ Welcome to Inglewood - Leave Your Aspirations Behind],&quot; ''[[Los Angeles Weekly]]''
* [http://www.wikimapia.org/#lat=33.9575&amp;lon=-118.346111&amp;z=11&amp;l=0&amp;m=m WikiMapia]
* [http://content.cdlib.org/search?style=oac-img&amp;sort=title&amp;relation=ark:/13030/kt9g5029q0 Images of Inglewood in the Online Archive of California]

{{Commons category}}

{{Cities of Los Angeles County, California}}
{{Greater Los Angeles Area}}
{{California cities and mayors of 100,000 population}}

[[Category:Cities in Los Angeles County, California]]
[[Category:Inglewood, California| ]]
[[Category:Incorporated cities and towns in California]]
[[Category:Populated places in California with Hispanic majority populations]]
[[Category:Populated places established in 1888]]

[[ar:إنغليووود، لوس أنجليس، كاليفورنيا]]
[[bg:Ингълуд (Калифорния)]]
[[ca:Inglewood (Califòrnia)]]
[[cs:Inglewood]]
[[de:Inglewood]]
[[es:Inglewood (California)]]
[[fr:Inglewood]]
[[hr:Inglewood, Kalifornija]]
[[it:Inglewood]]
[[he:אינגלווד]]
[[sw:Inglewood, California]]
[[ht:Inglewood, Kalifòni]]
[[nl:Inglewood (Californië)]]
[[ja:イングルウッド (カリフォルニア州)]]
[[no:Inglewood]]
[[pnb:انگل ووڈ]]
[[pl:Inglewood (Kalifornia)]]
[[pt:Inglewood (Califórnia)]]
[[ro:Inglewood, California]]
[[ru:Инглвуд (округ Лос-Анджелес, Калифорния)]]
[[fi:Inglewood (Kalifornia)]]
[[sv:Inglewood]]
[[tl:Inglewood, California]]
[[vi:Inglewood, California]]
[[vo:Inglewood (California)]]
[[war:Inglewood, California]]
[[zh:英格爾伍德 (加利福尼亞州)]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
