<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="107656" ns="0" title="Manhattan Beach, California"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Coord|33|53|20|N|118|24|19|W|display=title}}
&lt;!-- Infobox begins --&gt;{{Infobox settlement
|official_name                  = City of Manhattan Beach
|native_name                    = &lt;!-- for cities whose native name is not in English --&gt;
|nickname                       =
|motto                          =
|image_skyline                  =
|imagesize                      =
|image_caption                  = Manhattan Beach Pier
|image_flag                     =
|flag_size                      =
|image_seal                     = Manhattan_Beach_Seal.jpg
|seal_size                      =
|image_shield                   =
|shield_size                    =
|image_blank_emblem             =
|blank_emblem_size              =
|image_map                      = LA County Incorporated Areas Manhattan Beach highlighted.svg
|mapsize                        = 250x200px
|map_caption                    = Location of Manhattan Beach in [[Los Angeles County, California|Los Angeles County]], [[California]]
|image_map1                     =
|mapsize1                       =
|map_caption1                   =
|coordinates_region             = US-CA
|subdivision_type               = [[List of countries|Country]]
|subdivision_name               = [[United States]]
|subdivision_type1              = [[Political divisions of the United States|State]]
|subdivision_name1              = [[California]]
|subdivision_type2              = [[List of counties in California|County]]
|subdivision_name2              = [[Los Angeles County, California|Los Angeles]]
|subdivision_type3              =
|subdivision_name3              =
|subdivision_type4              =
|subdivision_name4              =
|government_type                = [[Council-manager government|Council-Manager]]
|leader_title                   = [[City Council]]
|leader_name                    = Mayor Nicholas Tell &lt;ref&gt;[http://www.citymb.info/Index.aspx?page=721 City of Manhattan Beach : Mayor's Welcome&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt; &lt;br /&gt; Vice-Mayor Wayne Powell &lt;br /&gt; David Lesser &lt;br /&gt; Amy Howorth &lt;br /&gt; Richard Montgomery |
|leader_title1                  = [[Treasurer|City Treasurer]]
|leader_name1                   = Tim Lilligren, [[Certified California Municipal Treasurer|CCMT]]&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.cacities.org/resource_files/24827.Electedcitytreasurers06.rtf California League of Cities, Elected City Treasurers]&lt;/ref&gt;|
|leader_title2                  =
|leader_name2                   =
|leader_title3                  =
|leader_name3                   =
|established_title              = &lt;!-- Settled --&gt;
|established_date               =
|established_title2             = &lt;!-- Incorporated (town) --&gt;
|established_date2              =
|established_title3             = Incorporated (city)
|established_date3              = December 12, 1912&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url = http://www.cacities.org/resource_files/20457.IncorpDateLO.doc |  title = Incorporation Dates of California Cities | accessdate = 2007-01-18}}&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;!-- Area------------------&gt;
|area_magnitude           =
| unit_pref               =US
| area_footnotes          = &lt;ref&gt;[http://www.census.gov/geo/www/gazetteer/files/Gaz_places_national.txt U.S. Census]&lt;/ref&gt;
| area_total_sq_mi        = 3.941
| area_land_sq_mi         = 3.937
| area_water_sq_mi        = 0.004
| area_total_km2          = 10.208
| area_land_km2           = 10.197
| area_water_km2          = 0.010
| area_water_percent      = 0.1
| area_note               = 
|area_urban_km2                 =
|area_urban_sq_mi               =
|area_metro_km2                 =
|area_metro_sq_mi               =
|population_as_of               = 2010
|population_note                =
|population_footnotes           = 
|settlement_type                = [[City]]
|population_total               = 35135
|population_density_km2         = auto
|population_density_sq_mi       = auto
|population_metro               =
|population_density_metro_km2   =
|population_density_metro_sq_mi =
|population_urban               =
|population_density_urban_km2   =
|population_density_urban_sq_mi =
|timezone                       = [[Pacific Time Zone|PST]]
|utc_offset                     = -8
|timezone_DST                   = PDT
|utc_offset_DST                 = -7
|latd                           = 33 |latm = 53 |lats = 20 |latNS = N
|longd                          = 118 |longm = 24 |longs = 19 |longEW = W
|elevation_m                    = 20
|elevation_ft                   = 66
|postal_code_type               = [[ZIP Code]]
|postal_code                    = 90266, 90267&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url = http://zip4.usps.com/zip4/zcl_1_results.jsp?visited=1&amp;pagenumber=0&amp;state=ca&amp;city=Manhattan%20Beach | title = USPS - ZIP Code Lookup - Find a ZIP+ 4 Code By City Results | accessdate = 2007-01-18}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|area_code                      = [[Area code 310|310]]/[[Area code 424|424]]&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url = http://www.nanpa.com/nas/public/npa_city_query_step2.do?method=displayData&amp;cityToNpaModel.stateAbbr=CA&amp;cityToNpaModel.city=Manhattan%20Beach | title = Number Administration System - NPA and City/Town Search Results | accessdate = 2007-01-18}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|website                        = [http://www.citymb.info/ www.citymb.info]
|blank_name                     = [[Federal Information Processing Standard|FIPS code]]
|blank_info                     = 06-45400
|blank1_name                    = [[Geographic Names Information System|GNIS]] feature ID
|blank1_info                    = 1660985
|footnotes                      =
}}
&lt;!-- Infobox ends --&gt;
'''Manhattan Beach''' is the wealthiest beachfront city located in southwestern [[Los Angeles County, California]], [[United States|USA]].  The city is on the [[Pacific Ocean|Pacific]] coast, south of [[El Segundo, California|El Segundo]], and north of [[Hermosa Beach, California|Hermosa Beach]]. Manhattan Beach is the home of both beach and indoor volleyball, and surfing. During the winter, the waves can get as big as {{convert|12|ft|m}}.  It is one of the three [[Beach Cities]] in the [[South Bay, Los Angeles|South Bay]].  Manhattan Beach is known for its homes with prices averaging above 9 million dollars.  In the past 15 years, it has become home to professional athletes such as Maria Sharapova, Tiger Woods, and Blake Griffin.  The average income of a typical Manhattan Beach household is 3.4 million dollars annually. 

Manhattan Beach is an affluent beach town within commuting distance of [[Los Angeles]] and therefore it is one of the most expensive coastal towns in which to live in America, according to the most recent ''[[Fortune Magazine]]'' rankings. The median price of a single family dwelling greatly exceeds the already high Los Angeles County median price by well over 100%.  Property in Manhattan Beach is exceptionally expensive when considering the size of land for sale.  In comparison, a half acre of land in Bel-Air is valued at $20 million, while a half acre of land on the Strand in Manhattan Beach is valued at $35 million.&lt;ref&gt;[http://manhattanbeach.patch.com/articles/the-most-expensive-homes-in-america]&lt;/ref&gt;  Homes with an ocean view often exceed $5 million in cost.

Manhattan Beach and the local high school, [[Mira Costa High School]], were the real-life film locations for the popular TV show ''[[The O.C.]]''&lt;ref&gt;http://www.seeing-stars.com/oc/&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;http://digitalcontentproducer.com/digitalfilm/video_production_meets_post/&lt;/ref&gt;

==History==
[[Image:Manhattan Pier.jpg|thumb|left|The [[Manhattan Beach pier]] in downtown Manhattan Beach on a typical fall afternoon.]]

In 1863, a Scottish immigrant, Sir Robert Burnett, purchased [[Rancho Sausal Redondo]] and [[Rancho Aguaje de la Centinela]] from [[Cornelio Avila#Antonio Ygnacio Avila|Avila]]'s heirs for $33,000.  Ten years later in 1873, Burnett leased the ranch to a Canadian, Daniel Freeman (not the American [[Daniel Freeman]], who was the first to file a claim under the [[Homestead Act]] of 1862).  Burnett returned to Scotland.  Freeman moved his wife and three children onto the ranch and started growing various crops.  On May 4, 1885 Freeman bought the ranch from Burnett for $140,000.

[[George H. Peck (1856-1940)|George H. Peck]] owned a lot of the land that became part of the north section of Manhattan Beach. Supposedly, a coin flip decided the town's name.  Around 1902, the beach suburb was named &quot;Manhattan Beach&quot; after the developer's home town, [[Manhattan Beach, Brooklyn|Manhattan Beach]], Brooklyn, New York.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web| title = History of Manhattan Beach| author = Bonnie Beckerson| url = http://history90266.org/HistoryMB.htm| accessdate = 2008-09-25|archiveurl = http://web.archive.org/web/20080606024945/http://history90266.org/HistoryMB.htm |archivedate = 2008-06-06}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Geography==
The city has a total area of {{convert|4.9|sqmi|km2}}. 
Manhattan Beach features {{convert|2.1|mi|km}} of ocean frontage.  Much of Manhattan Beach was once sand dunes.  The city is quite hilly, but the only remaining sand dune is at Sand Dune Park.

===Neighborhoods===
[[Image:Manhattan Beach houses.jpg|thumb|A view of the ocean in Manhattan Beach.]]
Residents have divided the city into several distinct neighborhoods, including &quot;The Village&quot;, &quot;Sand Section&quot;, &quot;Hill Section&quot;, &quot;Tree Section&quot;, &quot;Gas Lamp&quot; section, Manhattan Heights, East Manhattan Beach, Liberty Village, &quot;Poet's Section&quot; (Shelley, Tennyson, Longfellow), and El Porto (North Manhattan Beach).

The Hill Section includes higher priced homes where many of the residences are remodeled and situated on steep hills allowing panoramic ocean and city views. 

The nearby Sand Section is notable for its pockets of quiet neighborhoods adjacent to the ocean.  Multi-million dollar ocean-front homes line the bike path and walking lane along The Strand.

====Downtown====
&quot;Downtown&quot; Manhattan Beach runs along Manhattan Beach Boulevard and the streets perpendicular to it in the area near the [[Manhattan Beach Pier]] up to Valley Drive. There are restaurants and stores and a mixed-use center, where once the [[Metlox Pottery|pottery factory]], famous for its colorful plates, stood for decades.  The Metlox site closed in the early 1990s, and it took several years for the contaminated soil to be removed.  The new &quot;Metlox&quot; site includes a boutique hotel and a few restaurants and shops. 

The Manhattan Beach Library is near downtown on Highland Avenue two blocks north of Manhattan Beach Boulevard. The library is part of the [[County of Los Angeles Public Library]] system, and includes internet accessible computers, WiFi, and access to the six million items in the county library collection.

====Rosecrans Strip====
The Rosecrans strip is located on the south side of Rosecrans Avenue, east of Sepulveda, and west of Aviation.  

The area includes the small Manhattan Village Mall, which is located on the southeast corner of Sepulveda Boulevard and Rosecrans Avenue.  The mall, built in the early 1980s, was once anchored by the department stores [[Bullock's]] and [[Buffums]], which both went bankrupt in the early 1990s.  Most of the original stores in the mall also went bankrupt in the 1980s and 1990s (Miller's Outpost, Contempo Casuals, [[Music Plus]], Orange Julius, Tequila Willies, Kinney Shoes, [[B. Dalton]] bookstore).  The mall was remodeled in the late 1990s and early 2000s, and is now anchored by [[Macy's]] on both ends.  It also has higher-end stores such as [[Pottery Barn]], [[Pottery Barn Kids]], and [[Williams and Sonoma]].   

The Manhattan Beach Country Club, the Marriott Hotel and Golf Course, restaurants, retail stores, supermarkets, and shopping centers are along the strip between the Manhattan Mall and Aviation Boulevard.

====Sepulveda Strip====
The &quot;Sepulveda Strip&quot; occupies the commercial zone, which runs north-south through the city.  There is often very heavy traffic on this main thoroughfare.

====Aviation Strip====
The Aviation Strip is located along Aviation Boulevard (the city's eastern boundary), south of Rosecrans Avenue, and north of Marine Avenue.  Aviation High School once stood there until it was closed in the early 1980s.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web| title = Manhattan Beach Studios| author =| url = http://www.raleighstudios.com/index_manhattan.aspx
| accessdate = 2008-12-28}}&lt;/ref&gt;  The zone includes several major complexes, including the Manhattan Beach Film Studios and the Northrop Grumman Space Technology Plant (where TRW once stood).&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web| title = Northrop Grumman Space Technology| author =| url = http://www.st.northropgrumman.com/index.html| accessdate = 2008-12-28}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Parks and recreation==
The Strand path and bikeway along the beach is popular for [[biking]], [[jogging]], [[roller blading]], and [[skateboarding]]. Volleyball nets are set up along the beach, and swimming, [[body boarding]] and [[surfing]] are popular among residents and visitors. At Manhattan Beach you are allowed to surf at the [[Manhattan Beach Pier]], and North Manhattan Beach (El Porto).

==Demographics==
===2010===
The [[2010 United States Census]]&lt;ref&gt;{{USCensus-2010CA}}&lt;/ref&gt; reported that Manhattan Beach had a population of 35,135. The [[population density]] was 8,914.7 people per square mile (3,442.0/km²). The racial makeup of Manhattan Beach was 29,686 (84.5%) [[White (U.S. Census)|White]], 290 (0.8%) [[African American (U.S. Census)|African American]], 59 (0.2%) [[Native American (U.S. Census)|Native American]], 3,023 (8.6%) [[Asian (U.S. Census)|Asian]], 49 (0.1%) [[Pacific Islander (U.S. Census)|Pacific Islander]], 409 (1.2%) from [[Race (United States Census)|other races]], and 1,619 (4.6%) from two or more races.  [[Hispanic (U.S. Census)|Hispanic]] or [[Latino (U.S. Census)|Latino]] of any race were 2,440 persons (6.9%). 

The Census reported that 35,107 people (99.9% of the population) lived in households, 28 (0.1%) lived in non-institutionalized group quarters, and 0 (0%) were institutionalized.  

There were 14,038 households, out of which 4,735 (33.7%) had children under the age of 18 living in them, 7,583 (54.0%) were [[marriage|opposite-sex married couples]] living together, 892 (6.4%) had a female householder with no husband present, 438 (3.1%) had a male householder with no wife present.  There were 695 (5.0%) [[POSSLQ|unmarried opposite-sex partnerships]], and 85 (0.6%) [[same-sex partnerships|same-sex married couples or partnerships]]. 3,627 households (25.8%) were made up of individuals and 1,078 (7.7%) had someone living alone who was 65 years of age or older. The average household size was 2.50.  There were 8,913 [[family (U.S. Census)|families]] (63.5% of all households); the average family size was 3.10.

The population was spread out with 8,725 people (24.8%) under the age of 18, 1,740 people (5.0%) aged 18 to 24, 9,532 people (27.1%) aged 25 to 44, 10,681 people (30.4%) aged 45 to 64, and 4,457 people (12.7%) who were 65 years of age or older.  The median age was 40.9 years. For every 100 females there were 100.4 males.  For every 100 females age 18 and over, there were 99.2 males.

There were 14,929 housing units at an average density of 3,787.9 per square mile (1,462.5/km²), of which 9,420 (67.1%) were owner-occupied, and 4,618 (32.9%) were occupied by renters. The homeowner vacancy rate was 0.8%; the rental vacancy rate was 5.3%.  25,587 people (72.8% of the population) lived in owner-occupied housing units and 9,520 people (27.1%) lived in rental housing units.

===2000===
As of the [[census]]{{GR|2}} of 2000, there were 33,854 people, 14,474 households, and 8,394 families residing in the city.  The [[population density]] was 8,606.7 inhabitants per square mile (3,325.8/km²).  There were 15,034 housing units at an average density of 3,822.3 per square mile (1,477.0/km²).  The racial makeup of the city was 88.99% [[White (U.S. Census)|White]], 6.04% [[Asian (U.S. Census)|Asian]], 0.61% [[African American (U.S. Census)|African American]], 0.21% [[Native American (U.S. Census)|Native American]], 0.12% [[Pacific Islander (U.S. Census)|Pacific Islander]], 1.23% from [[Race (United States Census)|other races]], including 2.81% from two or more races. 5.19% of the population was [[Hispanic (U.S. Census)|Hispanic]] or [[Latino (U.S. Census)|Latino]] of any race.{{Citation needed|date=August 2009}}

There were 14,474 households, of which 28.1% had children under the age of 18, 49.8% were [[Marriage|married couples]] living together, 5.8% had a female householder with no husband present, 42.0% were non-families, 29.3% were individuals living alone, and 6.5% were individuals living alone who were 65 years of age or older.  The average household size was 2.34, and the average family size was 2.98.

Other census data showed that the age distribution in the city was 22.3% who were under the age of 18, 4.1% from 18 to 24, 37.5% from 25 to 44, 25.7% from 45 to 64, and 10.4% who were 65 years of age or older.  The median age was 38 years.  For every 100 females, there were 101.5 males, and for every 100 females age 18 and over, there were 101.6 males.

The median income for a household in the city was $100,750, and the median income for a family was $122,686 (these figures had risen to $124,048 and $149,396 respectively as of a 2007 estimate&lt;ref&gt;[http://factfinder.census.gov/servlet/ACSSAFFFacts?_event=Search&amp;geo_id=16000US0644112&amp;_geoContext=01000US%7C04000US06%7C16000US0644112&amp;_street=&amp;_county=manhattan+beach&amp;_cityTown=manhattan+beach&amp;_state=04000US06&amp;_zip=&amp;_lang=en&amp;_sse=on&amp;ActiveGeoDiv=geoSelect&amp;_useEV=&amp;pctxt=fph&amp;pgsl=160&amp;_submenuId=factsheet_1&amp;ds_name=ACS_2007_3YR_SAFF&amp;_ci_nbr=null&amp;qr_name=null&amp;reg=null%3Anull&amp;_keyword=&amp;_industry= factfinder.census.gov]&lt;/ref&gt;).  Males had a median income of $84,256 versus $54,142 for females. The [[per capita income]] for the city was $61,136.  About 2.0% of families and 3.2% of the population were below the [[poverty line]], including 2.3% of those under age 18 and 4.9% of those age 65 or over.

In February 2006, the median price of Manhattan Beach home sales was $1,925,000.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.dqnews.com/ZIPCAR.shtm dqnews.com]&lt;/ref&gt;  In its &quot;Best Places to Live&quot; 2005 feature, ''[[Money Magazine]]'' ranked Manhattan Beach as the fourth most expensive beach town in America.&lt;ref&gt;[http://money.cnn.com/best/bplive/topten/homes.html money.cnn.com]&lt;/ref&gt;  Additionally, in 2005 it ranked 2nd in California for the number of million-dollar homes sold.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.dqnews.com/RRMDH0106.shtm dqnews.com]&lt;/ref&gt; ''[[Forbes]]'' has also ranked the local ZIP code 90266 as the 29th most expensive ZIP code in [[North America]].

==Economy==
===Top Employers===
According to the City's 2010 Comprehensive Annual Financial Report,&lt;ref name=&quot;cafr&quot;&gt;[http://www.citymb.info/Modules/ShowDocument.aspx?documentid=7586 City of Manhattan Beach Comprehensive Annual Financial Report, Fiscal Year Ended June 30, 2010]. Retrieved 2010-09-26.&lt;/ref&gt; the top employers in the city are:

{| class=&quot;wikitable&quot;
|-
! #
! Employer
! # of Employees
|-
|1
| [[Target Corporation|Target]]
| 405
|-
|2
| [[Skechers]]
|362
|-
|3
| [[Macy's]]
|271
|-
|4
| [[Fry's Electronics]]
|251
|-
|5
| [[Marriott International|Marriott]]
|208
|-
|6
| [[Ralphs]]
|146
|-
|7
| [[Olive Garden]]
|143
|-
|8
| [[24 Hour Fitness]]
|133
|-
|9
| [[Bristol Farms]]
|130
|-
|10
| Shade Hotel
|113
|-
|11
| Manhattan Beach [[Toyota]]
|99
|-
|12
| Houston's Restaurants
|97
|-
|13
| [[California Pizza Kitchen]]
|85
|-
|14
| [[Chili's]]
|81
|-
|15
| Belamar Hotel
|79
|-
|16
| [[Islands (restaurant)|Islands]]
|75
|-
|17
| [[Recreational Equipment Incorporated|REI]]
|62
|}

==Government==
===Local government===
The city of Manhattan Beach is governed by a five-member City Council. City Council members are elected every four years. The office of the Mayor of Manhattan Beach rotates every nine months among the members of the City Council, so that each City Council member serves one term as Mayor.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web| title = City Council of the City of Manhattan Beach| url = http://www.citymb.info/Index.aspx?page=721| accessdate = 2008-09-25}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===State government===
The residents of the city of Manhattan Beach are represented in [[California State Legislature|state legislature]] by both a California State Senator and a California State Assemblyman.

In the [[California State Senate]], Manhattan Beach is located in the 28th District. The current State Senator is Ted Lieu.

In the [[California State Assembly]], Manhattan Beach is located in 53rd District. The current State Assemblyman from the District is Democrat [[Betsy Butler]].

=== Education ===
==== Primary and secondary schools ====
{| class=&quot;wikitable&quot; style=&quot;float:right;&quot;
!- |School||2010 [[Academic Performance Index|API]] Score
|-
|Grandview Elementary
| style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;|957
|-
|Meadows Elementary
| style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;|946
|-
|Pacific Elementary
| style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;|960
|-
|Pennekamp Elementary
| style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;|948
|-
|Robinson Elementary
| style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;|962
|-
|Manhattan Beach Middle
| style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;|945
|-
|[[Mira Costa High School]]
| style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;|911
|}

Public education in Manhattan Beach is provided by the [[Manhattan Beach Unified School District]], which oversees five elementary schools (Grandview, Meadows, Pacific, Pennekamp, Robinson), one middle school, and one high school (Mira Costa). 

The district as a whole received a score of 926 on the 2010 California Academic Performance Index, making it California's 3rd best performing district.&lt;ref&gt;[http://easyreader.hermosawave.net/news2002/storypage.asp?StoryID=20030003&amp;IssuePath=news2006/1026/ http://easyreader.hermosawave.net/news2002/storypage.asp?StoryID=20030003&amp;IssuePath=news2006/1026/] ''eastreader.hermosawave.net''&lt;/ref&gt; Each individual school also ranks at the top of its respective category.&lt;ref&gt;[http://api.cde.ca.gov/APIBase2006/2006Grth_dst.aspx?cYear=&amp;allcds=1975333&amp;cChoice=2006GDst1 http://api.cde.ca.gov/APIBase2006/2006Grth_dst.aspx?cYear=&amp;allcds=1975333&amp;cChoice=2006GDst1] ''api.cde.ca.gov''&lt;/ref&gt;

==Private schools==
Private schools located in Manhattan Beach include [[American Martyrs Catholic School]], [[Manhattan Academy]], [[Montessori School of Manhattan Beach]] and [[Journey of Faith Christian School]].

== Newspapers ==
Manhattan Beach is served by [http://www.easyreadernews.com/manhattan-beach-news ''Easy Reader Manhattan Beach News''], [http://www.easyreadernews.com/beach-magazine ''Beach Magazine''], the ''[[Daily Breeze]]'', the ''[[Beach Reporter]]'' and the ''[[Manhattan Beach Sun]]''.

==In popular culture==
===Filming location===
*Filming location of ''1408'' (2007).  [[John Cusack]]'s character surfs in El Porto waves.
*Filming location of ''2012'' (2009).  Cracks appear down the middle of 45th Street.
*Scenes from the 1983 Taylor Hackford film, ''[[Against All Odds (film)|Against All Odds]]'', were filmed along The Strand and on the beach.
*Film and real life location of [[George Jung]] of ''[[Blow (film)|Blow]]'' fame.
*Home to the filming of the [[CBS]] series ''[[CSI: Miami]]'' Manhattan Beach Studios.
*Establishing shots of the TV show, ''[[Hannah Montana]]'' are filmed at Mira Costa High School.
*Film location of ''[[Jerry Maguire]]'' (1996). In the movie, Dorothy's ([[Rene Zellwegger]]) house is in the Sand Section on 23rd Street.
*Home to the filming of the [[Fox Network]] series, ''[[The O.C.]]''
*Filming location of ''[[Point Break]]'' (1991). In the movie, [[Keanu Reeves]] buys his [[surfboard]] from a shop located on the Manhattan Beach pier.
*Filming location of ''[[Starsky and Hutch (film)|Starsky and Hutch]]'' (2004). In the movie, Starsky (Ben Stiller), can be seen stretching under the pier.
*Filming location of ''[[Tequila Sunrise (film)|Tequila Sunrise]]'' (1988). [[Mel Gibson]]'s character lives on the beach near the pier.
*Home to the filming of some of the [[The CW Television Network]]/Ex-[[UPN]] series, ''[[Veronica Mars]]''.
*Filming location for the TV show, ''[[Weeds (TV series)|Weeds]]''.
*Filming location for the TV show, &quot;[[90210 (TV series)|90210]]&quot;

===Music===
*Mentioned in the song, &quot;[[Surfin' USA]]&quot;, by the [[Beach Boys]].  The Beach Boys, who surfed in Manhattan Beach, grew up in nearby Hawthorne.

===Sports===
*The Manhattan Beach Open volleyball tournament in Manhattan Beach is known as &quot;The Championships, Wimbledon of Beach Volleyball.&quot; The names of the tournament champions are inscribed in plaques along Manhattan Beach Pier. This event usually takes place in August and is aired on national TV.

===Other===
*[[CNN Money]] named Manhattan Beach #1 as the &quot;2011 Best Places For the Rich and Single&quot;. &lt;ref&gt;http://money.cnn.com/galleries/2011/moneymag/1108/gallery.best_places_rich_single.moneymag/index.html&lt;/ref&gt;
*[[The Travel Channel]] named Manhattan Beach the 9th sexiest beach on earth for its 2008 &quot;21 Sexiest Beaches&quot; show.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=Ej5nTkad0Cg]&lt;/ref&gt;
*Manhattan Beach has been nicknamed the &quot;Pearl of the South Bay&quot; for its beauty and desirability.
*Much of the sand on [[Waikīkī Beach]] was purchased from Manhattan Beach by Hawaiʻian developers in the late 1920s. The developers negotiated a deal with the Kuhn Brothers Construction Company to ship the city's sand across the [[Pacific Ocean]] from Manhattan Beach to Waikiki Beach for over 10 years.[1] The remaining sand that resembles Manhattan Beach's original landscape can be found at [[Sand Dune Park]].

==Notable residents==
&lt;!-- Note:
· Only people who already have a Wikipedia article may appear here. This establishes notability.
· The biographical article must mention how they are associated with &lt;city name&gt;, whether born, raised, or residing.
· The fact of their association should have a reliable source cited.
· Alphabetical by last name please
· All others will be deleted without further explanation
--&gt;
  
===Entertainment===

*[[Brad Bird]]: Creator, ''The Incredibles'' and Oscar winner for ''Ratatouille''
*[[Dave Coulier]]: Uncle Joey in TV's ''Full House''
*[[Don Dokken]]: Founder and lead singer of 1980s Heavy Metal band Dokken
*[[Jane Elliot]]: Actress, ''General Hospital'' and ''Days of Our Lives''
*[[Bill Engvall]]: Comedian with the Blue Collar Comedy group
*[[Matthew Fox (actor)|Matthew Fox]]: Actor ''Lost'' and ''Party of Five''
*[[Neal Israel]]: Director of ''Surf Ninjas'' and nationally ranked falconer
*[[Kevin James (actor)|Kevin James]]: Actor on the sitcom ''King of Queens''
*[[Wally Kurth]]: Actor, ''General Hospital'' and ''Days of Our Lives''
*[[Jim Lindberg]]: Singer of the South Bay Punk Rock Band [[Pennywise (band)|Pennywise]]
*[[Benjamin McKenzie|Ben McKenzie]]: Actor, ''The O.C.'', ''Southland''
*[[Mike Mignola]]: Creator of ''Hellboy'' [9]
*[[Maria Sansone]]: American television host for ''TV Guide Network''
*[[Marisa Miller]]: ''Sports Illustrated'' Swimsuit Edition cover page model
*[[Kevin Nealon]]: Actor/Comedian from ''Saturday Night Live'' fame
*[[Ryan Newman (actress) ]]: Actress in the movie ''Zoom''
*[[Liz Phair]]: Singer/songwriter and guitarist
*[[Teri Polo]]: Actress, Pam in ''Meet the Parents''
*[[Thomas Pynchon]]: Author of ''The Crying of Lot 49'' and ''Gravity's Rainbow''
*[[Tara Reid]]: Actress and model
*[[J.D. Roth]]: Host of the reality TV show ''Endurance''
*[[Pat Sajak]]: ''Wheel of Fortune'' host
*[[Max Thieriot]]: Actor, ''The Pacifier''
*[[Owen Wilson]]: Actor, ''Wedding Crashers'', ''Behind Enemy Lines''
*[[Jenn Brown]]: [[ESPN]] reporter

===Public service===

* [[George P. Cronk]],  Manhattan Beach Board of Education. 1939–42, and Los Angeles City Council, 1945–52

===Journalists and writers===

*[[John Bollinger]]: Creator [[Bollinger Bands]]
*[[Richard Foss]]: Journalist and Science Fiction Writer

===Athletes===

'''Basketball'''
*[[Blake Griffin]]: First round draft pick and star of the Los Angeles Clippers&lt;ref&gt;http://sports.espn.go.com/los-angeles/nba/news/story?id=6039550&lt;/ref&gt;
*[[Brian Cook]]: Power forward for the Orlando Magic
*[[Robbie Davis]]: Lakers team trainer.
*[[Devean George]]: Small forward for the Dallas Mavericks
*[[Shaun Livingston]]: Point Guard for the Charlotte Bobcats
*[[Slava Medvedenko]]: Basketball player, former power forward for the Los Angeles Lakers
*[[Chris Mihm]]: Former Center for the Los Angeles Lakers
*[[Michael Olowokandi]]: Retired basketball player
*[[Kurt Rambis]]: Head Coach of the Minnesota Timberwolves
*[[Zeljko Rebraca]]: Former Center for the Los Angeles Clippers
*[[Brian Shaw]]: Former Point/Shooting guard in the NBA, now an assistant coach for the Los Angeles Lakers
*[[Luke Walton]]: Small forward for the Los Angeles Lakers
*[[Sasha Vujacic]]: Shooting guard for the New Jersey Nets

'''Football'''
*[[Tim Brown (American football)|Tim Brown]]: 1987 Heisman winner and Raider player
*[[Jeff Garcia]]: Former NFL quarterback
*[[Tony Gonzalez (tight end)|Tony Gonzalez]]: Tight end for the Atlanta Falcons
*[[Don Mosebar]]: Played for the Los Angeles Raiders for 13 years
*[[Michael Strahan]]: Former defensive end for the New York Giants
*[[Pete Carroll]]: Head coach of the Seattle Seahawks NFL football team

'''Baseball'''
*[[Nomar Garciaparra]]: Former MLB shortstop for the Boston Red Sox, Chicago Cubs, Los Angeles Dodgers, and Oakland A's
*[[Jason Kendall]]: Catcher for the Kansas City Royals
*[[Paul LoDuca]]: Retired Catcher formerly of the Los Angeles Dodgers and the Washington Nationals

'''Soccer'''
*[[Bob Bradley]]: Head coach of the US Men's National Soccer Team
*[[Landon Donovan]]: Soccer player for the Los Angeles Galaxy, U.S. National Team forward
*[[Mia Hamm]]: Former Olympic Soccer player [13]
*[[Cobi Jones]]: Soccer player for the Los Angeles Galaxy

'''Hockey'''
*[[Rob Blake]]: Defenseman for the Los Angeles Kings
*[[Marc Crawford]]: Head coach for the Los Angeles Kings
*[[Pavol Demitra]]: Forward for the Minnesota Wild
*[[Alexander Frolov]]: Hockey player for the Los Angeles Kings
*[[Tim Gleason]]: Defensman for the Carolina Hurricanes
*[[Ron Hextall]]: Former goaltender for the Philadelphia Flyers, current Assistant GM for the Los Angeles Kings
*[[Anze Kopitar]]: Center and Western Conference all-star for the Los Angeles Kings
*[[Shane McColgan]]: Right Winger for the WHL Kelonwa Rockets
*[[Glen Murray (ice hockey)|Glen Murray]]: Right Winger for the Boston Bruins
*[[Lubomir Visnovsky]]: Defensman for the Los Angeles Kings

'''Other'''
*[[Michael Lambert (volleyball)|Mike Lambert]]: Former professional beach volleyball player
*[[Stein Metzger]]: Former professional beach volleyball player
*[[Maria Sharapova]]: Professional tennis player [14]
*[[Pearl Sinn]]: Former LPGA golfer

==References==
{{reflist|colwidth=30em}}

==External links==
{{Commons category|Manhattan Beach, California}}
{{Portal|Los Angeles|Greater Los Angeles|Southern California}}
*[http://www.citymb.info/ Manhattan Beach official website]
*[http://www.manhattanbeachhistorical.org/ Manhattan Beach Historical Society]
*[http://www.leadershipmb.org/ Leadership Manhattan Beach]
*[http://www.mb-chamber.com/ Manhattan Beach Chamber of Commerce]
*[http://www.manhattan.k12.ca.us/ Manhattan Beach School District]
*[http://sites.google.com/site/WaynePowell4MB/ Manhattan Beach City Councilmember Wayne Powell]
*[http://archives.csudh.edu:2006/cdm4/RanchoSanPedro.php Map of original Rancho San Pedro, 1784, reflecting Rancho Sausal Redondo within its domain]

{{Cities of Los Angeles County, California}}
{{Greater Los Angeles Area}}

[[Category:Cities in Los Angeles County, California]]
[[Category:Populated coastal places in California]]
[[Category:Incorporated cities and towns in California]]
[[Category:Populated places established in 1912]]

[[ar:مانهاتان بيتش، لوس أنجليس، كاليفورنيا]]
[[bg:Манхатън Бийч (Калифорния)]]
[[ca:Manhattan Beach (Califòrnia)]]
[[cs:Manhattan Beach]]
[[de:Manhattan Beach]]
[[es:Manhattan Beach (California)]]
[[fr:Manhattan Beach (Californie)]]
[[ko:맨해튼비치]]
[[it:Manhattan Beach (California)]]
[[sw:Manhattan Beach, California]]
[[ht:Manhattan Beach, Kalifòni]]
[[nl:Manhattan Beach (Californië)]]
[[pt:Manhattan Beach (Califórnia)]]
[[fi:Manhattan Beach]]
[[sv:Manhattan Beach]]
[[tl:Manhattan Beach, Kaliporniya]]
[[vo:Manhattan Beach (California)]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
