<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="107706" ns="0" title="Whittier, California"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Infobox settlement
|official_name = City of Whittier
|settlement_type = [[City]]
|image_skyline = Pio Pico Casa, Whittier.JPG
|imagesize =
|image_caption = Pio Pico Casa in Whittier
|image_seal =
|image_map = LA County Incorporated Areas Whittier highlighted.svg
|mapsize = 250x200px
|map_caption = Location of Whittier in [[Los Angeles County, California|Los Angeles County]], [[California]]
|image_map1 =
|mapsize1 =
|map_caption1 =
|subdivision_type         = [[List of countries|Country]]
|subdivision_name         = [[United States]]
|subdivision_type1        = [[Political divisions of the United States|State]]
|subdivision_name1        = [[California]]
|subdivision_type2        = [[List of counties in California|County]]
|subdivision_name2        = [[Los Angeles County, California|Los Angeles]]
|government_type =
|leader_title = [[Mayor]]
|leader_name = Greg Nordbak
|established_date =
&lt;!-- Area------------------&gt;
|area_magnitude           =
| unit_pref               =US
| area_footnotes          = &lt;ref&gt;[http://www.census.gov/geo/www/gazetteer/files/Gaz_places_national.txt U.S. Census]&lt;/ref&gt;
| area_total_sq_mi        = 14.7
| area_land_sq_mi         = 14.7
| area_water_sq_mi        = 0.016
| area_total_km2          = 37.983
| area_land_km2           = 37.942
| area_water_km2          = 0.041
| area_water_percent      = 0.11
| area_note               =
|population_as_of = 2010
|population_total = 85331
|population_footnotes =
|population_density_km2 = auto
|population_demonym = Whittierite
|timezone = [[Pacific Time Zone|PST]]
|utc_offset = -8
|timezone_DST = PDT
|utc_offset_DST = -7
|latitude = 33°57'56&quot; N
|longitude = 118°1'28&quot; W
|area_water_sq_mi = 0.0
|elevation_m = 112
|elevation_ft = 367
|coordinates_display = inline,title
|coordinates_type = region:US_type:city
|latd = 33 |latm = 57 |lats = 56 |latNS = N
|longd = 118 |longm = 1 |longs = 28 |longEW = W
|postal_code_type = [[ZIP code]]s
|postal_code = 90601-90606
|area_code = [[Area code 562|562]]
|blank_name = [[Federal Information Processing Standard|FIPS code]]
|blank_info = 06-85292
|blank1_name = [[Geographic Names Information System|GNIS]] feature ID
|blank1_info = 1652813
|footnotes =
|website = http://www.cityofwhittier.org/
}}
'''Whittier''' is a city in [[Los Angeles County, California]] about {{convert|12|mi|km|0}} southeast of [[Los Angeles, California|Los Angeles]]. The city had a population of 85,331 at the 2010 census, up from 83,680 as of the 2000 census, and encompasses 14.7 square miles (38.0 square kilometers). Like nearby [[Montebello, CA|Montebello]], the city constitutes part of the [[Gateway Cities]]. Whittier was incorporated in February 1898, although it was first settled in 1887, and became a [[charter city]] in 1955.&lt;ref name=&quot;city&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.cityofwhittier.org/ |title=Whitter Web - Homepage |publisher=Cityofwhittier.org |date= |accessdate=2011-03-16}}&lt;/ref&gt; The city is named for the poet [[John Greenleaf Whittier]] and is home to [[Whittier College]].

==History==
Whittier's roots can be traced to Spanish soldier [[Manuel Nieto]].&lt;ref name=&quot;History&quot;&gt;[http://www.cityofwhittier.org/content/AW01.html ]{{dead link|date=March 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;  In 1784, Nieto received a [[Spain|Spanish]] land grant of {{convert|300,000|acre|km2}}, [[Rancho Los Nietos]], as a reward for his military service and to encourage settlement in California.&lt;ref name=&quot;city&quot;/&gt; The area of Nieto's land grant was reduced in 1790 as the result of a dispute with [[Mission San Gabriel]].  Nonetheless, Nieto still had claim to {{convert|167000|acre|km2|-1}} stretching from the hills north of Whittier, [[Fullerton, California|Fullerton]] and [[Brea, California|Brea]], south to the Pacific ocean, and from what is known today as the [[Los Angeles River]] east to the [[Santa Ana River]]. Nieto built a rancho for his family near  Whittier, and purchased cattle and horses for his ranch and also planted cornfields. When Nieto died in 1804,  his children inherited their father's property.
[[Image:Whittier old.jpg|thumb|right|300px|Whittier, California, late 19th century]]
At the time of the [[Mexican-American War]], much of Whittier was owned by [[Pio Pico]], a rancher and the last Mexican governor of California.&lt;ref name=&quot;city&quot;/&gt; Pio Pico built an hacienda in Whittier on the San Gabriel River, which today is known as [[Pio Pico State Historic Park]]&lt;ref name=&quot;city&quot;/&gt;  Following the Mexican-American war, German immigrant [[Jacob F. Gerkens]] paid $234 to the U.S. government to acquire {{convert|160|acre|km2|1}} of land under the [[Homestead Act]] and built a cabin  known today as the Jonathan Bailey House. Gerkens would later become the first chief of police of the [[Los Angeles Police Department]]. Gerkens' land was owned by several others before a group of Quakers purchased it and expanded it to {{convert|1259|acre|km2|0}}, with the intent of founding a Quaker community. The area soon became known as a thriving citrus ranching region, with &quot;Quaker Brand&quot; fruit being shipped all over the United States. Later, walnut trees were also planted, and Whittier became the largest walnut grower in the United States.&lt;ref name=&quot;city&quot;/&gt;  In addition to walnuts and citrus, Whittier was also a major producer of [[pampas grass]].

[[Southern Pacific Railroad]] built the first railroad spur to Whittier in 1887.&lt;ref name=&quot;History&quot;/&gt; The railroad spur helped promote the boom of the 1880s. By 1906, 650 carloads of oranges and 250 carloads of lemons were shipped annually by rail.  In 1904, the [[Pacific Electric]] opened the trolley line known as &quot;Big Red Cars&quot; from Los Angeles to Whittier. In the first two decades over a million passengers a year rode to and from Los Angeles on the Whittier line.&lt;ref name=&quot;city&quot;/&gt; Groves of walnuts were planted  in 1887 and  eventually Whittier was known as the primary walnut growing town in the United States.&lt;ref name=&quot;History&quot;/&gt;
After [[World War II]] Whittier grew rapidly and the sub-dividing of orange groves began, driven by housing shortages in southern California. In 1955 the new Civic Center complex was completed and the City Council met in new chambers for the first time on March 8, 1955. The City continued to grow as the City annexed portions of Whittier Boulevard and East Whittier, the 1961 annexation added over 28,000 people to the population, bringing the total to about 67,000.&lt;ref name=&quot;city&quot;/&gt;

===Origin of name===
[[Image:Jonathan Bailiey House, Whittier.JPG|thumb|left|150px|Jonathan Bailey House]]
In the founding days of Whittier, when it was a small isolated town, Jacob Bailey and his wife, Rebecca, were among the first residents. They followed the [[Quaker]] religion, and held religious meetings on their porch. As the city grew, the citizens named it after [[John Greenleaf Whittier]], a respected Quaker [[poet]]. Whittier wrote a dedication poem, and is honored today with statues and a small exhibit at the Whittier museum; a statue of him sits in the park, and another representing his poem ''The Barefoot Boy'' used to reside by the City Hall.   Whittier never set foot there, but the city still bears his name and is rooted in the Quaker tradition.&lt;ref name=&quot;city&quot;/&gt;

===College history===
In 1887 the Pickering Land and Water Company set aside a {{convert|20|acre|m2|adj=on}} parcel of land for the development of a college, but a collapse in the land boom stalled construction. Progress on developing a college was sporadic, but on July 30, 1896 the Whittier Academy, operating since 1891, officially changed its name to [[Whittier College]] with 100 students enrolled.  The school mascot is &quot;The Poet.&quot;  By 1906, Whittier College was an educational institution with laboratories, boarding halls, a large gymnasium and athletic fields. Due to an economic depression in the 1890s, the first bachelors degrees were not awarded at the college for 17 years.&lt;ref name=&quot;city&quot;/&gt;

The Mendenhall Building at Whittier College was donated by Leona May Mendenhall in honor of her husband Oscar. The Mendenhalls were among the founding families of Whittier. Oscar's brother, Samuel Mendenhall, helped bring in the water system and post office. The Mendenhalls were large growers for [[Sunkist Growers, Incorporated|Sunkist]] oranges and [[Blue Diamond Growers|Blue Diamond]] walnuts.

===Quaker history in Whittier===
The first Quaker meeting house was built on the corner of Comstock Avenue and Wardman Street in 1887. The meeting soon outgrew this 100 seat meeitng house and new, larger building was erected on the corner of Philadelphia Street and Washington Avenue in 1902. By 1912, membership had grown to 1,200 and a third building was dedicated on the same site in 1917. With a capacity of 1,700, the 1917 meeting house featured a balcony and was constructed of brick with mahogany paneling and pews. The present meeting house, dedicated in 1975, features many architectural elements and materials from the 1917 building including the stained glass windows and mahogany interior.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Nelson|first=Carl|title=Whittier Friends Church: Eighty-Eight Years of Service|year=1975|publisher=First Friends Church|location=Library of William Wright|pages=2–9}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Whittier Narrows earthquake===
On Oct. 1, 1987, at 7:42 a.m., the [[Whittier Narrows earthquake]] struck, the epicenter six miles (10&amp;nbsp;km) north by northwest of Whittier. The seismic event, which registered 5.9 on the Richter scale, resulted in eight casualties and massive damage to uptown Whittier's historic buildings. Three days later , on 4th Oct 1987 , @ 03:59 , a major aftershock ( 5.2 ) hit causing further damage . Buildings and residential structures which were already borderline unsafe were now deemed unsafe / uninhabitable . In the years following the earthquake, the city's deteriorating uptown business district, which suffered substantial damage in the earthquake, became the focus of renewed development, which met with opposition from many Whittier citizens. Out of the rubble of the earthquake the [[Whittier Conservancy]] was formed in 1987 in an effort to stop the demolition of many historic buildings and residences after the disaster. The city also created a [[Historic Resources Commission]] to oversee the approval of historic designations, historic districts and [[Mills Act]] proposals.

==Geography==
Whittier is located at {{Coord|33|57|56|N|118|1|28|W|city}} (33.5756, -118.128).{{GR|1}}

According to the [[United States Census Bureau]], the city has a total area of {{convert|14.7|sqmi|km2}}, virtually all land.

Whittier is bordered by the community of [[Hacienda Heights]] to the northeast, [[City of Industry, CA|City of Industry]] to the north, and several other unincorporated communities in the [[San Gabriel Valley]] mostly along its northern sections. [[Pico Rivera, CA|Pico Rivera]] lies at the west, [[La Habra Heights, CA|La Habra Heights]] to the east, [[La Habra, CA|La Habra]] to the southeast and [[Santa Fe Springs, CA|Santa Fe Springs]] to the south.

===Neighborhoods===
There are several neighborhoods in Whittier.  The area centered around Philadelphia Street and Greenleaf Avenue is known as Uptown Whittier and contains the traditional central business core.  Just north of Uptown Whittier are the neighborhoods known as Central Park and Hadley-Greenleaf.  They have been designated historic districts by the city Historic Resources Commission, and together comprise most of the area of the Whittier Historic Neighborhood Association.  These districts contain many Craftsman and Spanish Colonial Revival homes.  In and abutting the hills north of the historic districts is Starlite Estates, an upscale neighborhood.  The area surrounding Whittier College is known as College Hills and was also recently designated a historic district.  The area east of College Avenue is referred to as '''East Whittier'''.  East Whittier was a separate agricultural community until the postwar era.  The eastern parts of East Whittier, developed in the 1950s and 60s, are Friendly Hills, Murphy Ranch and Leffingwell Ranch.

==Demographics==
[[Image:C.W. Harvey Home, Whittier.JPG|thumb|left|175px|C.W.Harvey Home]]
===2010===
The [[2010 United States Census]]&lt;ref&gt;{{USCensus-2010CA}}&lt;/ref&gt; reported that Whittier had a population of 85,331. The [[population density]] was 5,818.6 people per square mile (2,246.6/km²). The racial makeup of Whittier was 55,117 (64.6%) [[White (U.S. Census)|White]], 1,092 (1.3%) [[African American (U.S. Census)|African American]], 1,093 (1.3%) [[Native American (U.S. Census)|Native American]], 3,262 (3.8%) [[Asian (U.S. Census)|Asian]], 123 (0.1%) [[Pacific Islander (U.S. Census)|Pacific Islander]], 20,848 (24.4%) from [[Race (United States Census)|other races]], and 3,796 (4.4%) from two or more races.  [[Hispanic (U.S. Census)|Hispanic]] or [[Latino (U.S. Census)|Latino]] of any race were 56,081 persons (65.7%). 

The Census reported that 83,696 people (98.1% of the population) lived in households, 1,083 (1.3%) lived in non-institutionalized group quarters, and 552 (0.6%) were institutionalized.  

There were 28,273 households, out of which 11,289 (39.9%) had children under the age of 18 living in them, 14,152 (50.1%) were [[marriage|opposite-sex married couples]] living together, 4,566 (16.1%) had a female householder with no husband present, 1,896 (6.7%) had a male householder with no wife present.  There were 1,770 (6.3%) [[POSSLQ|unmarried opposite-sex partnerships]], and 247 (0.9%) [[same-sex partnerships|same-sex married couples or partnerships]]. 6,096 households (21.6%) were made up of individuals and 2,495 (8.8%) had someone living alone who was 65 years of age or older. The average household size was 2.96.  There were 20,614 [[family (U.S. Census)|families]] (72.9% of all households); the average family size was 3.46.

The population was spread out with 21,686 people (25.4%) under the age of 18, 9,198 people (10.8%) aged 18 to 24, 23,627 people (27.7%) aged 25 to 44, 20,819 people (24.4%) aged 45 to 64, and 10,001 people (11.7%) who were 65 years of age or older.  The median age was 35.4 years. For every 100 females there were 94.0 males.  For every 100 females age 18 and over, there were 90.5 males.

There were 29,591 housing units at an average density of 2,017.8 per square mile (779.1/km²), of which 16,207 (57.3%) were owner-occupied, and 12,066 (42.7%) were occupied by renters. The homeowner vacancy rate was 1.3%; the rental vacancy rate was 5.1%.  49,393 people (57.9% of the population) lived in owner-occupied housing units and 34,303 people (40.2%) lived in rental housing units.

===2000===
As of the [[census]]{{GR|2}} of 2000, there were 83,680 people, 28,271 households, and 20,468 families residing in the city. The [[population density]] was 5,719.4 inhabitants per square mile (2,208.4/km²). There were 28,977 housing units at an average density of 1,980.5 per square mile (764.7/km²). The racial makeup of the city was 43.2% [[White (U.S. Census)|White]], 1.2% [[African American (U.S. Census)|African American]], 1.3% [[Native American (U.S. Census)|Native American]], 3.3% [[Asian (U.S. Census)|Asian]], 0.2% [[Pacific Islander (U.S. Census)|Pacific Islander]], 25.8% from [[Race (United States Census)|other races]], and 5.0% from two or more races. [[Hispanic (U.S. Census)|Hispanic]] or [[Latino (U.S. Census)|Latino]] of any race were 65.9% of the population.&lt;ref&gt;[http://factfinder.census.gov/servlet/QTTable?_bm=y&amp;-geo_id=16000US0685292&amp;-qr_name=DEC_2000_SF1_U_QTP3&amp;-ds_name=D&amp;-_lang=en&amp;-redoLog=false http://factfinder.census.gov/servlet/QTTable?_bm=y&amp;-geo_id=16000US0685292&amp;-qr_name=DEC_2000_SF1_U_QTP3&amp;-ds_name=D&amp;-_lang=en&amp;-redoLog=false] ''factfinder.census.gov''&lt;/ref&gt;

There were 28,271 households out of which 37.8% had children under the age of 18 living with them, 52.5% were [[Marriage|married couples]] living together, 14.3% had a female householder with no husband present, and 27.6% were non-families. 22.4% of all households were made up of individuals and 9.4% had someone living alone who was 65 years of age or older. The average household size was 2.88 and the average family size was 3.38.

In the city the population was spread out with 28.3% under the age of 18, 10.0% from 18 to 24, 30.6% from 25 to 44, 18.6% from 45 to 64, and 12.5% who were 65 years of age or older. The median age was 33 years. For every 100 females there were 94.6 males. For every 100 females age 18 and over, there were 90.1 males.

The median income for a household in the city was $49,256, and the median income for a family was $55,726. Males had a median income of $40,394 versus $34,223 for females. The [[per capita income]] for the city was $21,409. About 7.8% of families and 10.5% of the population were below the [[poverty line]], including 13.7% of those under age 18 and 8.0% of those age 65 or over.

==Politics==
{{Citation needed|date=June 2011}}

In the [[California State Legislature|state legislature]] Whittier is located in the 30th [[California State Senate|Senate]] District, represented by Democrat [[Ronald S. Calderon]], and in the 56th 58th and 60th [[California State Assembly|Assembly]] Districts, represented by Democrats [[Tony Mendoza (politician)|Tony Mendoza]], [[Charles M. Calderon]] and Republican [[Curt Hagman]] respectively. Federally, Whittier is located in California's [[California's 38th congressional district|38th]], [[California's 39th congressional district|39th]], and [[California's 42nd congressional district|42nd]] congressional districts, which have [[Cook Partisan Voting Index|Cook PVIs]] of D +20, D +13, and R +10 respectively&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | title = Will Gerrymandered Districts Stem the Wave of Voter Unrest? | publisher = Campaign Legal Center Blog | url=http://www.clcblog.org/blog_item-85.html | accessdate = 2008-02-10}}&lt;/ref&gt; and are represented by Democrats [[Grace Napolitano]] and [[Linda Sánchez]] and Republican [[Gary Miller]] respectively.

The [[Los Angeles County Department of Health Services]] operates the Whittier Health Center in Whittier.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;[http://publichealth.lacounty.gov/phn/docs/HealthCenter/whittier.pdf Whittier Health Center].&quot; [[Los Angeles County Department of Health Services]]. Retrieved on March 18, 2010.&lt;/ref&gt;

At one time the [[California Youth Authority]] operated the [[Fred C. Nelles Youth Correctional Facility]].&lt;ref&gt;&quot;[http://web.archive.org/web/19980125182015/www.cya.ca.gov/locations/instcamp.htm Institutions &amp; Camps].&quot; [[California Youth Authority]]. January 25, 1998. Retrieved on August 10, 2010.&lt;/ref&gt; The center, which started operations in 1890, closed.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;[http://www.parentdish.com/2010/06/07/states-closing-youth-prisons-as-arrests-plunge/ States Closing Youth Prisons as Arrests Plunge].&quot; ''[[Associated Press]]''. June 7, 2010. Retrieved on August 10, 2010.&lt;/ref&gt;

==Business==
Whittier's Redevelopment Agency has numerous projects underway to revitalize the community. This includes a $7 million dollar project near historic '''Hoover Hotel'''.

The Whittwood Town Center (formerly the Whittwood Mall) anchored by [[JC Penney]], [[Target Corporation|Target]], [[Sears, Roebuck and Company|Sears]], [[Vons]], and [[Kohl's]] has made way for [[Red Robin]] and [[Black Angus]]. The city still waits to attract more well known businesses and open new residential town homes with the revival of its Uptown district.

In addition, the agency is working on developing a {{convert|480|acre|km2|1|sing=on}} project area near Whittier Blvd. The master plan was adopted in June 2005 by the City Council.

===Media===
The local newspaper is the ''[[Whittier Daily News]]''. Other area papers include the ''[[San Gabriel Valley Tribune]]'', the parent paper of the Whittier Daily News, ''[[Los Angeles Times]]'' and the ''[[Orange County Register]]''.

===Top employers===
According to the City's 2009 Comprehensive Annual Financial Report,&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.cityofalhambra.org/government/finance/downloads/AlhambraCAFR09-final.pdf City of Alhambra CAFR]&lt;/ref&gt; the top employers in the city are:

{| class=&quot;wikitable sortable&quot;
|-
! #
! Employer
! # of Employees
|-
|1
|[[AHMC Healthcare|Presbyterian Intercommunity Hospital]]
|2,600
|-
|2
|[[Whittier Hospital Medical Center]]
|850
|-
|3
|City of Whittier
|702
|-
|4
|[[Whittier Union High School District]]
|412
|-
|5
|[[Whittier College]]
|325
|-
|6
|[[United States Postal Service]]
|315
|-
|7
|Bright Health Physicians
|300
|-
|8
|[[Johnson Controls]]
|250
|-
|9
|[[Southern California University of Health Sciences]]
|220
|-
|10
|[[Whittier City School District]]
|200
|}

==Transportation==
[[Image:Southern Pacific Railroad Depot, Whittier.JPG|thumb|rightt|200px|Southern Pacific Railroad Depot]]
There are a variety of bus routes operating within the city with [[Foothill Transit]], [[Montebello Bus Lines]] and the [[Norwalk Transit]] being the leading bus lines used within the city. Other bus routes operating in the city include the [[LACMTA|Metro]], The Sunshine Shuttle starting at Beaty Ave all the way through The Whitwood Town Center, Line 121 Whitwood starting at Aviation Station (Metrorail Green Line) and ending at the Whittwood Town Center. The city also has a variety of freeways with the [[San Gabriel River Freeway]] ([[I-605]]) running right along the northern end of the city. [[California State Route 72|State Route 72]] runs via Whittier Boulevard and forms part of [[El Camino Real (California)|El Camino Real]].

==Police and fire departments==
===Police===
The Whittier Police Department provides patrol service to the communities of Whittier and Santa Fe Springs. Currently, over 100&lt;ref name=&quot;Whit&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.whittierdailynews.com/ci_16442382 |title=New era for Police Department |publisher=Whittier Daily News |date= |accessdate=2011-03-16}}&lt;/ref&gt; officers are assigned to patrol the city streets.  The Patrol Division includes the Traffic Bureau, Special Enforcement Team, Code Enforcement, and School Resource Officers.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.whittierpd.org/aboutpatrol.htm&lt;/ref&gt; The Police Services Division consists of the Records Bureau, [[9-1-1]] Communications Center, Property and Evidence, and the Jail. The Services Division operates 24 hours a day, 365 days a year, staffing communications and records functions around the clock.  This permits continuous support to patrol and investigational activities.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.whittierpd.org/aboutservices.htm&lt;/ref&gt;

In October 2010, the dedication of the new, spacious police station was held. It is a {{convert|53000|sqft|m2|adj=on}} facility, built at a cost of $35 million.  Police Chief David Singer said he has been working towards a new station since 2002, but the project has been in the works for three decades, because the old station, built in 1955, at only {{convert|20000|sqft|m2}}  was so small. Voters had previously rejected a raise in their utility tax, so the delay in building was a matter of finding funding. Included in the new station is a more modern jail, air conditioning, upgraded radio and 9-1-1 communications systems and more space for the department offices and private interview rooms.  Chief Singer celebrated his efforts by retiring that day, and leaving behind the attractive new building for his officers and  community.&lt;ref name=&quot;Whit&quot;/&gt;

===Fire===
[[Los Angeles County Fire Department]] Station 28 (Engine, [[Quint (fire apparatus)|Quint]], [[Paramedic]] Squad, Mobile Aid, and the Battalion Chief), Station 17 (Engine), Station 59 (Engine and [[EST]]) serve the community of Whittier. The Los Angeles County Fire Department, Battalion 8 services the unincorporated area of Whittier.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://whittier.lacounty.info/Fire.htm |title=Unincorporated Area of Whittier |publisher=Whittier.lacounty.info |date= |accessdate=2011-03-16}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Library==
On April 17, 1900, the Whittier Public Library Board of Trustees held its first meeting in Landrum Smith's drugstore. With an initial collection of 60 books and 200 magazines, the library facilities began in the Woody Building as a reading room, maintained by Mr. Hester in exchange for space for his telegraph office. In 1907, a Carnegie grant funded the construction of the building at Bailey and Greenleaf that many Whittierites fondly remember. As the city expanded, a larger library was needed, and the Friends of the Library organized in 1956 to raise money for a new building. Through their efforts, and those of the board members, librarians, and citizen fund raising groups, the new library was completed at the Washington Avenue site in May 1959. In 1968, service was further expanded with the construction of the Whittwood Branch Library on Santa Gertrudes.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.whittierlibrary.org/about_the_library.html ]{{dead link|date=March 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Education==
[[Image:Lou Henry Hoover School, Whittier.JPG|thumb|195px|right|Lou Henry Hoover School]]
[[Image:Frieze at Lou Henry Hoover School, Whittier.JPG|thumb|195px|right|Frieze at Hoover School, designed by Bartholomew Mako]]
The city of Whittier is served by the [[Whittier Union High School District]], [[East Whittier City School District]], [[Whittier City School District]], [[Lowell Joint School District]] and the [[Fullerton Joint Union High School District]].{{citation needed|date=December 2010}}

Five high schools, [[California High School (Whittier, California)|California High School]], [[La Serna High School]], [[Pioneer High School (Whittier, California)|Pioneer High School]], [[Santa Fe High School (California)|Santa Fe High School]], and [[Whittier High School]] comprise the Whittier Union High School District. There is one alternative continuation high school Sierra Vista High School, and [[Frontier High School (Whittier, California)|Frontier High School]]. Although they still have Whittier postal addresses, both California High School and Pioneer High School lie outside the city limits in unincorporated Los Angeles County. Santa Fe High School is located within the City of Santa Fe Springs. Adults may attend the Whittier Adult School, which belongs to the [[Whittier Union High School District]].
The city also has three private Catholic elementary schools, K-8
* St. Bruno's Parish School&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://saintbrunoschool.com/default.aspx |title=Home |publisher=Saintbrunoschool.com |date= |accessdate=2011-03-16}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* St Gregory The Great Parish School&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.stgregorywhittier.org/]&lt;/ref&gt;
* St. Mary of the Assumption School&lt;ref&gt;[http://saintmaryoftheassumptionschool.com/]&lt;/ref&gt;

The schools are operated by the [[Roman Catholic Archdiocese of Los Angeles]] with one (St. Mary of the Assumption School) being one of the largest Catholic elementary schools in [[Los Angeles County]]. St Gregory The Great School has been Number One in their deanery for the Academic Decathlon two years in a row.

Trinity Lutheran School,&lt;ref&gt;[http://trinitywhittier.ctsmemberconnect.net/ Trinity Lutheran School]&lt;/ref&gt; a ministry of Trinity Lutheran Church, serves Pre-K through eighth grade and is accredited by [[Western Association of Schools and Colleges]]. Whittier Christian School,&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.whittierchristian.org/ Whittier Christian School]&lt;/ref&gt; a ministry of Calvary Baptist Church, [[Association of Christian Schools International]] serves grades K–8 in the Whittier community.

Higher education institutions in the area include [[Rio Hondo College]], which lies just outside the city, and historic [[Whittier College]].

==Fred C. Nelles Youth Correctional Facility==
{{Main|Fred C. Nelles Youth Correctional Facility}}
The Fred C. Nelles Youth Correctional Facility is located on a highly visible sector of Whittier Blvd.  Nelles' 74-acres Nelles has been added to the list of state historical landmarks. Taken separately, the administration building that was constructed in 1928-29, has its own historical designation and must be protected, according to the State of California. On the campus there 6-8 historical buildings to be considered. The San Gabriel Valley Tribune, in its 2010 Thanksgiving edition, gave thanks for &quot;The plans to revitalize Whittier Boulevard and properly develop the former Fred C. Nelles Youth Correctional Facility.&quot;{{Citation needed|date=June 2011}}

==Historical landmarks and entertainment locations==
===Places===
[[Image:Hoover Hotel, Whittier.JPG|thumb|right|120px|Hoover Hotel]]
[[Image:National Bank of Whittier Building.JPG|thumb|right|120px|National Bank of Whittier Building]]
[[Image:Whittier Village Clock.JPG|thumb|right|120px|Whittier Village Clock]]
[[Image:Standard Oil Building, Whittier.JPG|thumb|right|150px|Standard Oil Building]]
[[Image:Whittier Village Cinemas, Whittier.JPG|thumb|right|150px|Whittier Village Cinemas]]
* [[Rose Hills Memorial Park]], the largest single-location cemetery in the world, is located at the western edge of the city limits.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.rosehills.com/locationsContent/Default.aspx |title=Home |publisher=Rose Hills |date= |accessdate=2011-03-16}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* The [[Principia Discordia]] was revealed to its authors in the city's local bowling alley.
* Whittier is home to the following [[California Historical Landmark]]s&lt;ref&gt;[http://ohp.parks.ca.gov/default.asp?page_id=21427]&lt;/ref&gt;
** [[Pio Pico State Historic Park]], [[List of California Historical Landmarks#Los Angeles County|California Historical Landmark No. 127]]: The ''Casa de Governor Pío Pico''/Home of Governor [[Pío Pico]], home of the last Mexican [[Governors of California|Governor of California]].
** California Historical Landmark No. 646: Grave of [[Yiorgos Caralambo|George Caralambo]], (Greek George):
** California Historical Landmark No. 681: Paradox Hybrid Walnut Tree:
** California Historical Landmark No. 947: Reform School for Juvenile Offenders ([[Fred C. Nelles Youth Correctional Facility|Fred C. Nelles School]]&amp;nbsp; &amp;mdash; Closed May 27, 2004 and currently being redeveloped for business and residential use)
* Whittier Museum - 6755 Newlin Ave, Whittier 90601. Open to the public Saturdays and Sundays from 1 to 4 p.m. and is free of charge
* Whittier is the home to the following places listed in the [[National Register of Historic Places]]:
** [[Pio Pico State Historic Park|Pio Pico House]], 6003 Pioneer Blvd.
** [[Hoover Hotel]], 7035 Greenleaf Ave.
** [[Southern Pacific Railroad Depot, Whittier|Southern Pacific Railroad Depot]], 7333 Greenleaf Ave.
** [[Standard Oil Building (Whittier, California)|Standard Oil Building]], 7257 Bright Ave.
** [[Jonathan Bailey House (Whittier, California)|Jonathan Bailey House]], 13421 E. Camilla St.
** [[National Bank of Whittier Building]], 13002 E. Philadelphia
** [[Orin Jordan House]], 8310 S. Comstock Ave.

===Film and television locations===
{{Unreferenced|section|date=June 2011}}
* Various movies and television shows have been filmed in the city including:
:''[[Amish Grace]]'' (2010) - Television film. The carriage procession was filmed on Greenleaf St. in Uptown Whittier and funeral home scene was filmed at The Good Shepherd Family Bible Church, across the street from the post office on Bailey St.
:''[[Back to the Future]]''/''[[Back to the Future Part II]]'' - Films starring [[Michael J. Fox]]. [[Whittier High School]] was used as the setting for Hill Valley High School.
:''[[Hocus Pocus (1993 film)|Hocus Pocus]]'' - Film starring [[Bette Midler]], [[Sarah Jessica Parker]], [[Thora Birch]] and [[Vinessa Shaw]]. Parts were filmed in Uptown Whittier and East Whittier Middle School.
:''[[Father of the Bride Part II]]'' - Film starring [[Steve Martin]]. Parts were filmed in uptown Whittier.
:''[[The Wonder Years]]'' - Television series starring [[Fred Savage]]. The parade scene in the last episode was filmed in uptown Whittier.
:''[[The Next Best Thing]]'' - Film starring [[Madonna (entertainer)|Madonna]] and [[Rupert Everett]] was filmed in the Whittier Hills.
:''[[Bringing Down the House (film)|Bringing Down the House]]'' - Film starring [[Queen Latifah]] and [[Steve Martin]] was filmed at the Friendly Hills Country Club, in East Whittier.
:''[[Terminator 3: Rise of the Machines]]'' (2003) - Film starring [[Arnold Schwarzenegger]]. Various parts were shot in Whittier including in [[Rose Hills Memorial Park]].
:''[[Blow (film)|Blow]]'' - Film starring [[Johnny Depp]] and [[Penelope Cruz]]. Scenes were filmed at the [[Fred C. Nelles Youth Correctional Facility]], which closed in January 2004, and in a residential neighborhood.
:''[[Ali (film)|Ali]]'' - directed by Michael Mann, portions of which were filmed at a residence in the historic neighborhood near the uptown village.
:''[[Disturbia (film)|Disturbia]]'' (2007)- Film starring [[Shia LaBeouf]], [[Carrie Anne Moss]], and [[Amanda Walsh]]. Was shot on Painter Ave, the deli scenes were filmed at &quot;Our Cleaners&quot; on Comstock Ave. in uptown Whittier.
:''[[Moonlight (TV series)|Moonlight]]'' - Television series starring [[Alex O'Loughlin]] and [[Sophia Myles]]. Exteriors of a state execution facility were filmed at the [[Fred C. Nelles Youth Correctional Facility]], the facility name being clearly shown in multiple shots.
:''[[What Just Happened?]]'' (2008) - Film starring [[Robert De Niro]], [[Bruce Willis]], [[Sean Penn]] and [[Robin Wright (actress)|Robin Wright Penn]]. Scenes were filmed in Rose Hills Memorial Park.
:''[[Red State (2011 film)|Red State]]'' (2011) - Film directed by [[Kevin Smith]] and starring [[Michael Parks]]. Scenes were filmed at the [[Fred C. Nelles Youth Correctional Facility]].

===John Greenleaf Whittier's dedication poem===
Although John Greenleaf Whittier never visited the city, he did write a poem in honor of it:

'''&quot;My Name I Give To Thee&quot;'''&lt;br /&gt;
''Dear Town, for whom the flowers are born,&lt;br /&gt;
''Stars shine, and happy songbirds sing,&lt;br /&gt;
''What can my evening give to thy morn,&lt;br /&gt;
''My Winter to Thy Spring?&lt;br /&gt;
''A life not void of pure intent&lt;br /&gt;
''With small desert of praise or blame;&lt;br /&gt;
''The Love I felt, the Good I meant,&lt;br /&gt;
''I leave Thee with My Name.

==Notable residents==
{{Main|List of people from Whittier, California}}
*[[M.F.K. Fisher]], American food writer, grew up in Whittier.&lt;ref name=poet_app&gt;{{cite book|last=Reardon|first=Joan|title=Poet of the Appetites: The Lives and Loves of M.F.K. Fisher [Hardcover]|year=2004|publisher=North Point Press|isbn=0865475628|pages=5}}&lt;/ref&gt; 
*[[Lou Henry Hoover]], wife of  U.S. president [[Herbert Hoover]] grew up in Whittier.&lt;ref name=&quot;home&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.usacitiesonline.com/cacountywhittier.htm |title=Whittier California Profile and Resource Guide, City or community of Whittier, California Facts, Information, Relocation, Real Estate, Advertising |publisher=Usacitiesonline.com |date=2011-02-28 |accessdate=2011-03-16}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*[[Tinker Juarez]], Professional Cyclist: Two-time Olympian, MTB Hall of Fame, BMX Hall of Fame, National Champion, World Master MTB Champion,&lt;ref name=&quot;home&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.tinkerjuarez.com |title=home |publisher=Tinkerjuarez.com |date=1961-03-04 |accessdate=2011-03-16}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*[[Richard Nixon]], 37th President of the United States played football at Whittier High School and Whittier College.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.whitehouse.gov/about/presidents/richardnixon |title=Richard M. Nixon &amp;#124; The White House |publisher=Whitehouse.gov |date=2011-03-11 |accessdate=2011-03-16}}&lt;/ref&gt; Whittier was his childhood home, and he is buried in [[Yorba Linda, California]] in nearby [[Orange County, California|Orange County]], where he was born.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|author=By R. W. Apple Jr. |url=http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A06E0D71031F930A15757C0A962958260 |title=THE 37th PRESIDENT - RICHARD NIXON, 81, DIES - A MASTER OF POLITICS UNDONE BY WATERGATE - Obituary; Biography - NYTimes.com |publisher=New York Times |date=1994-04-23 |accessdate=2011-03-16}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*[[Jessamyn West]], Author of ''Friendly Persuasion'',&lt;ref name=&quot;home&quot;/&gt;
*[[Taylor Gray]], an actor on [[Nickelodeon (TV channel)|Nickelodeon]] on the new series [[Bucket and Skinner's Epic Adventures]]
*[[Gabriel Iglesias]], a [[stand-up]] comedian and actor

==Sister cities==
*{{flagicon|People's Republic of China}} [[Changshu]], P.R. China &lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.socalsistercities.org/Directory.html |title=Directory |publisher=SOCAL Sister Cities |date= |accessdate=2010-08-17}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*{{flagicon|Alaska}} [[Whittier, Alaska]] {{Citation needed|date=May 2010}}

==See also==
{{Portal|Greater Los Angeles}}
* [[South Whittier, California]] ''(an unincorporated area south of the city limits)''
* [[West Whittier-Los Nietos, California]]
* [[Los Angeles]]
* [[Whittier Narrows earthquake]]
* [[List of people from Whittier, California]]

==References==
{{reflist}}

==External links==
* [http://www.cityofwhittier.org/ City of Whittier]
* [http://www.whittierlibrary.org/ Whittier Public Library]
* [http://www.whittierchamber.com/ Whittier Chamber of Commerce]
* [http://www.whittier.edu/ Whittier College]
{{Refimprove|date=January 2008}}
{{Cities of Los Angeles County, California}}
{{Greater Los Angeles Area}}

[[Category:Whittier, California| ]]
[[Category:Cities in Los Angeles County, California]]
[[Category:Populated places in California with Hispanic majority populations]]
[[Category:Incorporated cities and towns in California]]
[[Category:Populated places established in 1784]]

[[ar:ويتير، لوس أنجليس، كاليفورنيا]]
[[bg:Уитиър]]
[[ca:Whittier (Califòrnia)]]
[[de:Whittier]]
[[es:Whittier (California)]]
[[fr:Whittier (Californie)]]
[[sw:Whittier, California]]
[[ht:Whittier, Kalifòni]]
[[nl:Whittier (Californië)]]
[[pnb:وائٹئر]]
[[pt:Whittier (Califórnia)]]
[[simple:Whittier, California]]
[[sv:Whittier, Kalifornien]]
[[tl:Whittier, California]]
[[vi:Whittier, California]]
[[vo:Whittier (California)]]
[[zh:惠提尔]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
