<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="10772582" ns="0" title="Comparison of the Java and .NET platforms"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">==Legal issues==
=== Standardization ===

The two platforms, their programming libraries, their binary formats, and their runtime environments have largely been governed by very different means.

The .NET platform as a whole has not been standardized. International standards organizations [[Ecma International]] and [[ISO]]/[[International Electrotechnical Commission|IEC]] define the standard for the .NET executable environment (known as the Common Language Infrastructure, or CLI), and .NET executable format (known as Common Intermediate Language, or CIL), but excluding most of the foundation classes (the Base Class Library, or BCL).  This formal committee-based standardization process is in keeping with the way very popular languages like [[COBOL]], [[Fortran]] and [[C programming|C]] have been standardized in the past.  The standards do not include many new libraries that Microsoft has implemented on top of the standard framework, such as those for accessing databases, or building GUI and Web applications, such as [[Windows Forms]], [[ASP.NET]] and [[ADO.NET]].

&lt;!-- Do we really need to list each standards authority? Surely &quot;has not been standardized by any third-party standards organization&quot; would be stronger? --&gt;
To date, no part of Java has been standardized by [[Ecma International]], [[ISO]]/[[International Electrotechnical Commission|IEC]], [[ANSI]], or any other third-party standards organization.  While [[Sun Microsystems]] has unlimited and exclusive legal rights to modify and license its Java trademarks, Sun voluntarily participates in a process called the [[Java Community Process]] (JCP) that allows interested parties to propose changes to any of Sun's Java technologies (from language and tools to API) via forums, consultation exercises and expert groups.  The JCP requires a membership fee for commercial contributors, while non-commercial contributors and individuals can join for free.

Within the rules of the JCP anyone can bring forward a proposal for a new Platform Edition Specifications or suggest changes to the Java language.  All proposals are reviewed and voted on by interested JCP members at various stages throughout their lifecycle, however when it comes to including changes into the standard reference implementations (Java SE, Java EE and Java ME) modifications may be subject to rejection by Sun, who retain ultimate power of veto.

Java standards are maintained by a suite of test applications which examine every aspect of a given Java implementation against a rigorous specification.  Only if an implementation passes the tens of thousands of individual tests can it use the trademarked name &quot;Java&quot;, and associated logos and brands.

=== License ===
====Java====
The primary implementation of the Java platform is available as an Open Source implementation called [http://openjdk.java.net/ OpenJDK].

While &quot;Java&quot; is an Oracle trademark, and only Oracle can license the name &quot;Java&quot;, numerous free software projects exist that are compatible with Oracle Java.  Most notably, [[GNU Classpath]] and [[GNU Compiler for Java|GCJ]] provide a free software class library and a compiler that are partially compatible with the current version of OracleJava.&lt;ref name=&quot;classpathjdk15compat&quot;&gt;[http://www.kaffe.org/~stuart/japi/htmlout/h-jdk15-classpath Results of comparison between jdk15 and classpath]&lt;/ref&gt;  Sun announced on November 13, 2006 that all Java source code, excluding [[closed-source]] code for which they do not retain rights, will be released under a modified version of the [[GNU General Public License|GPL]],&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.sun.com/software/opensource/java/project_overview.jsp Free and Open Source Java - Project Overview&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt; and released two fundamental parts of the [[JRE]] and [[JDK]]: [[HotSpot]] and the [[javac]] compiler under the [[GNU General Public License|GPL]].&lt;ref name=&quot;openjdk&quot;&gt;[http://openjdk.java.net/ Sun openjdk: Home]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;sunj2relicense&quot;&gt;[http://java.sun.com/j2se/1.4.2/j2re-1_4_2_13-license.txt Sun Java 2 Runtime License Agreement]&lt;/ref&gt;

Following their promise, Sun released the complete [[source code]] of the Class library under GPL on May 8, 2007, except some limited parts that were licensed by Sun from 3rd parties who did not want their code to be released under an open-source license&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
| url=http://mail.openjdk.java.net/pipermail/announce/2007-May.txt
| title=Open JDK is here!
| publisher=Sun Microsystems
| date=2007-05-08
| accessdate=2007-05-09}}&lt;/ref&gt; (see also [[Free Java implementations#After the May 2007 code release|Free Java implementations]]). Sun's goal is to replace the parts that remain closed with alternative implementations and make the class library completely open.

In June 2008, [[Red Hat]] announced&lt;ref&gt;[http://truthhappens.redhatmagazine.com/2008/06/19/java-finally-free-and-open/ Java Finally Free and Open]&lt;/ref&gt; that the [[IcedTea]] project has passed the rigorous [[Technology Compatibility Kit|Java TCK]], indicating a fully functional open-source implementation of the Java platform.

====.NET====
Microsoft's .NET '''CLI executable environment''', and some of the corresponding class library, have been standardized and can be freely implemented without a license. A few standards-compliant free software environments have been implemented, such as the [[Mono Project]] and [[DotGNU]]. The Mono Project has also implemented many of Microsoft's non-standard libraries by examining Microsoft materials, similar to GNU Classpath and Java.

Microsoft is currently distributing a [[Shared Source Common Language Infrastructure|shared source]] version of its .NET runtime environment for academic use, however it is only supported on Windows 7 and has not been updated after .NET 4.0.&lt;ref name=&quot;rotor&quot;&gt;[http://msdn.microsoft.com/msdnmag/issues/02/07/SharedSourceCLI/ Rotor: Shared Source CLI Provides Source Code for a FreeBSD Implementation of .NET]&lt;/ref&gt;

The Mono project aims to avoid infringing on any patents or copyrights, and to the extent that they are successful, the project can be safely distributed and used under the [[GNU General Public License|GPL]].  On November 2, 2006, Microsoft and Novell announced a joint agreement whereby Microsoft promised not to sue Novell or its customers for patent infringement.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.novell.com/news/press/item.jsp?id=1196 Microsoft and Novell Announce Broad Collaboration on Windows and Linux Interoperability and Support]&lt;/ref&gt; According to a statement on the blog of Mono project leader [[Miguel de Icaza]], this agreement only extends to Mono for Novell developers and users.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://tirania.org/blog/archive/2006/Nov-04.html|title=Statement on the blog of Mono project leader Miguel de Icaza regarding patent protection for Mono|date=2006-11-04|accessdate = 2006-11-06}}&lt;/ref&gt; Because of the possible threat of Microsoft patents, the [[Free Software Foundation|FSF]] recommends that people avoid creating software that depends on Mono or [[C Sharp (programming language)|C#]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
|title=Why free software shouldn't depend on Mono or C#
|url=http://www.fsf.org/news/dont-depend-on-mono
| last=Stallman|first=Richard
| publisher=[[Free Software Foundation]]
| date=2009-06-26
| quote=''We should systematically arrange to depend on the free C# implementations as little as possible. In other words, we should discourage people from writing programs in C#. Therefore, we should not include C# implementations in the default installation of GNU/Linux distributions, and we should distribute and recommend non-C# applications rather than comparable C# applications whenever possible.''
| accessdate=2009-07-02}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
|title=Microsoft's Empty Promise
|url=http://www.fsf.org/news/2009-07-mscp-mono
| publisher=[[Free Software Foundation]]
| date=2009-07-16
| quote=''Until that happens, free software developers still should not write software that depends on Mono. C# implementations can still be attacked by Microsoft's patents: the Community Promise is designed to give the company several outs if it wants them. We don't want to see developers' hard work lost to the community if we lose the ability to use Mono, and until we eliminate software patents altogether, using another language is the best way to prevent that from happening.''
| accessdate=2009-078-03}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The Microsoft/Novell agreement was criticized by some in the [[open source]] community because it violates the principles of giving equal rights to all users of a particular program (see [[Novell#Agreement with Microsoft|Agreement with Microsoft]] and [[Mono (software)#Mono and Microsoft's patents|Mono and Microsoft's patents]]).

{{POV-section|date=February 2011}}In response to the Microsoft/Novell agreement the [[Free Software Foundation]] revised its [[GNU General Public License]] to close the loophole used by Microsoft and Novell to bypass the GPL's very restrictive provisions on patent deals.&lt;ref name=&quot;gnuvsmicrosoft&quot;&gt;[http://money.cnn.com/magazines/fortune/fortune_archive/2007/05/28/100033867/index.htm Microsoft takes on the free world.]&lt;/ref&gt; The FSF also stated that by selling coupons for Novell's Linux software, the mechanism by which Microsoft circumvented the GNU license, it considers Microsoft to be a Linux vendor, and thereby subject to the full terms and conditions laid out in the GPL.&lt;ref name=&quot;gnuvsmicrosoft&quot;/&gt;

== Community ==

Oracle retains exclusive and unlimited legal rights to its Java [[Intellectual property|intellectual properties]], and the Java community is subject to those rights.

While [[Microsoft]] has developed C# and .NET without a formal community contribution system, the language and some parts of the executable format and runtime have been standardized and freely distributed through Ecma and ISO in an open and vendor-neutral process, rather than a process that retains veto and copy rights for Microsoft.  However, the standards do not include many new libraries that Microsoft has implemented on top of the standard framework (see [[#Standardization|Standardization]]).  Numerous C# and CLI community software projects, help and documentation sites, and discussion forums are under active development and maintenance.

Microsoft is distributing a [[shared source]] release (version 1.0) of the .NET virtual machine that can be compiled and used on Windows, FreeBSD, Mac OS X, and other platforms.&lt;ref name=&quot;sscli1_0&quot;&gt;[http://www.microsoft.com/downloads/details.aspx?FamilyId=3A1C93FA-7462-47D0-8E56-8DD34C6292F0&amp;displaylang=en Shared Source Common Language Infrastructure 1.0 Release]&lt;/ref&gt;  An updated version (2.0) is currently available, but the only officially supported platform is Windows.&lt;ref name=&quot;sscli2_0&quot;&gt;[http://www.microsoft.com/downloads/details.aspx?familyid=8c09fd61-3f26-4555-ae17-3121b4f51d4d&amp;displaylang=en Shared Source Common Language Infrastructure 2.0 Release]&lt;/ref&gt;  A community port to Linux of the 1.0 shared source .NET virtual machine is also available.&lt;ref name=&quot;linuxsscli1_0&quot;&gt;[http://www.ondotnet.com/pub/a/dotnet/2002/07/01/rotorlinux.html Rotor Comes to Linux]&lt;/ref&gt;  In March 2003, O'Reilly Media published a book about Microsoft's shared source .NET runtime.&lt;ref name=&quot;oreilly_sscliess&quot;&gt;[http://www.oreilly.com/catalog/sscliess/ oreilly.com -- Online Catalog: Shared Source CLI Essentials]&lt;/ref&gt;

== Traditional computer applications ==
=== Desktop applications ===

Although Java's [[Abstract Window Toolkit|AWT]] (Abstract Windowing Toolkit) and [[Swing (Java)|Swing]] libraries are not shy of features, Java has struggled to establish a foothold in the desktop market. [[Sun Microsystems]] has also been slow, in the eyes of some,{{Citation needed|date=February 2007}} to promote Java to developers and end users alike in a way which makes it an appealing choice for desktop software.  Even technologies such as [[Java Web Start]], which have few parallels within rival languages and platforms, have barely been promoted.{{Citation needed|date=February 2007}}

The release of Java version 6.0 on December 11, 2006, saw a renewed focus on the desktop market with an extensive set of new tools for closer integration with the desktop.  At the 2007 [[JavaOne]] conference Sun made further desktop related announcements, including a new language aimed at taking on [[Adobe Flash]] ([[JavaFX]]), a new lightweight way of downloading the JRE which sees the initial footprint reduced to under 2Mb, and a renewed focus on [[multimedia]] libraries.

An alternative to AWT and Swing is the [[Standard Widget Toolkit]] ([[Standard Widget Toolkit|SWT]]), which was originally developed by IBM and now maintained by the [[Eclipse Foundation]]. It attempts to achieve improved performance and visualization of Java desktop applications by relying on underlying native libraries where possible.

&lt;!-- Used to be &quot;has taken a significant lead&quot;, except the supporting citation is merely a list of Mono applications, it doesn't offer any comparison with any other language or platform (let alone suggest a 'significant' lead by either.) --&gt;
On Windows, Microsoft's .NET is popular desktop development providing both Windows Forms (a lightweight wrapper around the Win32 API), Windows Presentation Foundation, and Silverlight. With the integration of .NET into the Windows platform, .NET apps are first class citizens in the Windows environment with tighter OS integration and native look and feel compared to Java's Swing.

Outside of Windows, Silverlight is portable to the Mac OSX desktop. Mono is also becoming more common in open source and free software systems due to its inclusion&lt;ref name=&quot;monoapplications&quot;&gt;[http://www.osnews.com/story.php/9780/Mono-Applications-Aplenty! Mono-Applications-Aplenty!, OSNews]&lt;/ref&gt; on many Linux desktop environments.

=== Server applications ===

This is probably the arena in which the two platforms are closest to being considered rivals.  Java, through its [[Java EE]] (a.k.a. Java Platform Enterprise Edition) platform, and .NET through [[ASP.NET]], compete to create web-based dynamic content and applications.

Both platforms are well used and supported in this market, with a bevy of tools and supporting products available for Java EE and .NET. High-end, large-scale, heavy duty solutions tend to opt for Java EE due to higher stability, scalability, and greater availability of senior developers.
For example, for Java: [[Oracle corporation|Oracle]] included direct support for Java into its [[Oracle database|database]], while [[Google]] has used Java to power tools like [[Gmail]].&lt;ref name=&quot;gmail&quot;&gt;[http://code.google.com/webtoolkit/ Google Web Toolkit]&lt;/ref&gt;  One of the most prominent Java EE projects however is [[Apache Tomcat]], which directly competes with Microsoft's own ASP.NET [[Internet Information Services|IIS]] server.  &lt;!-- Can someone please add some examples of noteworthy enterprise space .NET backers?  There aren't any.  Microsoft is it's own backer. --&gt;

&lt;!-- Should the following not be part of Licensing, above ??? --&gt;
&lt;!-- The paragraphs below deal only with licensing and legal issues, and add nothing to the discussion about Server Applications which is the main focus of this topic!! --&gt;
Some of Sun's current Java-related license agreements for Java EE define aspects of the Java platform as a trade secret,&lt;ref name=&quot;sunj2eesdk5update2&quot;&gt;[http://javashoplm.sun.com/ECom/docs/Welcome.jsp?StoreId=22&amp;PartDetailId=java_ee_sdk-5_02-nojdk-oth-JPR&amp;SiteId=JSC&amp;TransactionId=noreg Java EE SDK 5 Update 2 No JDK download page (reference to license agreement)]&lt;/ref&gt; and prohibit the end user from contributing to a third-party Java environment.  Specifically, at least one current license for a Sun Java EE development package contains the following terms: ''&quot;You may make a single archival copy of Software, but otherwise may not copy, modify, or distribute Software.&quot; — &quot;Unless enforcement is prohibited by applicable law, you may not decompile, or reverse engineer Software.&quot; — &quot;You may not publish or provide the results of any  benchmark or comparison tests run on Software to any third party without the prior written consent of Sun.&quot; — &quot;Software is confidential and copyrighted.&quot;''&lt;ref name=&quot;sunj2eesdk5update2&quot;/&gt;  However, while Sun's software is subject to the above license terms, Sun's Java EE [[API]] reference has been implemented under an open source license by the [[JBoss]] and [[JOnAS]] projects.

Microsoft's implementation of [[ASP.NET]] is not part of the standardized CLI, and while Microsoft's runtime environment and development tools are not subject to comparable secrecy agreements to Java EE, the official Microsoft tools are not [[open source]] or [[free software]], and require Windows servers. However, a [[cross-platform]] free software ASP.NET 2.0 implementation is part of the [[Mono (software)|Mono project]] (minus webparts and [[Web Services Enhancements]]).&lt;ref name=&quot;mono_asp_net&quot;&gt;[http://www.mono-project.com/ASP.NET Mono: ASP.NET]&lt;/ref&gt;

== Embedded applications ==
=== Mobile applications ===
Google's popular [[Android_(operating_system)|Android]] platform for mobile application is based on Java. Google created its own customised virtual machine called Dalvik to optimise the execution of Java code for mobile devices.

Oracle provides [[Java ME]]; a reference implementation for mobile OEM venders. Java ME is made up of various profiles that are subsets of the Java desktop environment with additional libraries targeted at mobile and set top box development. Java ME has a very large base within the mobile phone and [[Personal digital assistant|PDA]] markets, with only the cheapest devices now devoid of a [[K virtual machine|KVM]] (a cut down [[JVM|Java Virtual Machine]] for use on devices with limited processing power). Java software, including many games, is commonplace.

While many feature phones include a JVM, they are not always heavily used by users (particularly in North America){{citation needed|date=February 2011}}. Initially Java applications on most phones typically consisted of menuing systems, small games, or systems to download ringtones etc.  However, more powerful phones are increasingly being sold with simple applications pre-loaded, such as translation dictionaries, world clock displays (darkness/light, timezones, etc.) and calculators.  Some of these are written in Java, although how often phone owners actually use them is probably unknown.  &lt;!--Full featured cell phone applications are rare.{{Citation needed|date=November 2010}}--&gt;

Microsoft currently ships the [[.NET Compact Framework]] which runs on Windows CE and mobile devices, set-top boxes, and PDAs as well as the Xbox 360. Microsoft also provides the [[.NET Micro Framework]] for embedded developers with limited resources. Alternatively, Novell licenses embeddable versions of Mono to 3rd parties to use in their devices and commercially distributes the MonoTouch and MonoDroid framework for iPhone and Android development respectively.

=== Home entertainment technologies ===

Java has found a market in digital television, where it can be used to provide software which sits alongside programming, or extends the capabilities of a given [[Set Top Box]].  [[TiVo]], for example, has a facility called &quot;[[Home Media Engine]]&quot;, which allows [[JavaTV]] software to be transmitted to an appropriate TiVo device to complement programming or provide extra functionality (for example, personalized stock tickers on a business news program.)

A variant of Java has been accepted as the official software tool for use on the next generation optical disc technology [[Blu-ray]], via the [[BD-J]] interactive platform.  This will mean that interactive content, such as menus, games, downloadables, etc. on all Blu-ray optical discs will be created under a variant of the Java platform.

Rather than using Java, [[HD DVD]] (the defunct high definition successor to [[DVD]]) used a technology jointly developed by [[Microsoft]] and [[The Walt Disney Company|Disney]] called [[HDi Interactive Format|HDi]] that was based on [[Extensible Markup Language|XML]], [[Cascading Style Sheets|CSS]], [[JavaScript]], and other technologies that are comparable to those used by standard [[web browser]]s.

The BD-J platform [[Application programming interface|API]] is more extensive than its iHD rival, with an alleged 8,000 methods and interfaces, as opposed to iHD's 400.&lt;ref name=&quot;bludvd1&quot;&gt;[http://blogs.zdnet.com/carroll/index.php?p=1583 HD-DVD vs. Blu-Ray, round 2]&lt;/ref&gt;  And while Microsoft is pushing iHD's XML presentation layer by including it with Windows Vista, iHD is still a newcomer in a market sector where Java technologies are already commonplace.&lt;ref name=&quot;bluedvd2&quot;&gt;[http://www.pcauthority.com.au/print.aspx?CIID=60242&amp;SIID=  Format Wars - Blu-ray vs HD DVD]&lt;/ref&gt;

However, the fact that the HD DVD format has been abandoned in favor of Blu-ray means that HDi is no longer supported on any [[Optical disc]] format, making the BD-J format a clear winner.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
| url = http://www.itwire.com/content/view/16780/1154/1/0/
| title = Microsoft's HDi interactivity layer loses from HD DVD's death - but does it matter?
| publisher = itwire.com
| last=Zaharov-Reutt|first=Alex
| quote=''While many claimed that creating interactivity with HDi was much simpler than using BD-J, the fact that HD DVD will see few future releases beyond 2008 means that, whatever the enthusiasts position on the relative merits of HDi vs BD-J, the BD-J interactivity format is now the winner''
| date=2008-02-21
| accessdate = 2008-08-27}} {{Dead link|date=October 2010|bot=H3llBot}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Runtime inclusion in operating systems ==
=== .NET/Mono ===

On Windows, Microsoft is promoting .NET as its flagship development platform,&lt;ref name=&quot;mscsharpflagship&quot;&gt;[http://www.microsoft.com/learning/books/developer/feature/050301.mspx Microsoft article that refers to C# as its &quot;flagship&quot; language.]&lt;/ref&gt; by including the .NET runtime in Windows XP Service Pack 2 and 3, Windows Server 2003, Windows Vista, Windows Server 2008 and Windows 7. Microsoft also distributes the Visual Studio Express development environment at no cost.&lt;ref name=&quot;vsexpress&quot;&gt;[http://www.microsoft.com/express/Windows/ Visual Studio Express]&lt;/ref&gt;

.NET Framework 3.5 runtime is not pre-installed on versions of Windows prior to Vista SP1, and must be downloaded by the user, which has been criticized because of its large size (65 MB download for .NET 3.5).&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
| url=http://channel9.msdn.com/ShowPost.aspx?PageIndex=1&amp;PostID=370737#370737
| title=Dear Microsoft
| date=2008-01-09
| accessdate=2008-02-03 |archiveurl = http://web.archive.org/web/20080205061731/http://channel9.msdn.com/ShowPost.aspx?PageIndex=1&amp;PostID=370737#370737 &lt;!-- Bot retrieved archive --&gt; |archivedate = 2008-02-05}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
| url=http://www.codeprof.com/dev-archive/179/12-1020-1798773.shtm
| title=.Net framework 3.5 size 166MB!
| date=2007-11-10
| accessdate=2008-02-03}}&lt;/ref&gt;

While neither .NET nor Mono are installed with Mac OS X out-of-the-box, the Mono project can be downloaded and installed separately, for free, for any Mac user who wants to build and/or run C# and .NET software. As of 13 May 2008, Mono's System.Windows.Forms 2.0 is API complete (contains 100% of classes, methods etc. in Microsoft's System.Windows.Forms 2.0); also System.Windows.Forms 2.0 works natively on Mac OS X.

C# and the CLI are included and used in a number of Linux and BSD based operating systems by way of including the free software Mono Project.&lt;ref name=&quot;fedoramono&quot;&gt;[http://news.zdnet.co.uk/software/0,1000000121,39246774,00.htm Fedora embraces Mono - ZDNet UK]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;debianmono&quot;&gt;[http://packages.debian.org/mono Debian Mono Packages]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;ubuntumono&quot;&gt;[http://www.osnews.com/story.php?news_id=10714 Wikipedia Uses Mono; Mono Integrated into Ubuntu/Debian - OSNews.com]&lt;/ref&gt;

As a result of inclusion of .NET or Mono runtimes in the distributions of Windows and Linux, non-GUI applications that utilize the programming interfaces that are common to both .NET and Mono can be developed in C# or any other .NET language and then deployed across many operating systems and processor architectures using a runtime environment that is available as a part of the operating system's installation.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.desktoplinux.com/news/NS2809897659.html Fedora Catches Mono]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.mono-project.com/news/archive/2006/May-11-1.html SUSE 10.1 released]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.osnews.com/story.php/10714/Wikipedia-Uses-Mono-Mono-Integrated-into-UbuntuDebian Wikipedia Uses Mono; Mono Integrated into Ubuntu/Debian]&lt;/ref&gt;  Both Microsoft .NET and the Mono project have complete support for the Ecma- and ISO-standardized C# language and .NET runtime, and many of Microsoft's non-standardized .NET programming interfaces have been implemented or are under development in Mono,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url = http://www.mono-project.com/Plans | title = Mono – Plans | accessdate = 2008-12-23}}&lt;/ref&gt; but each environment includes many components that have not been implemented in the other.

=== Java ===
Starting with XP SP1a, Windows does not ship with a Java runtime environment.

Java comes pre-installed on all new Apple computers since Mac OS X 10.0. Because Apple maintains the Java runtime for Mac OS X, updates are usually one or two versions behind the versions available from Sun for the other operating systems, and versions of Java are usually tied to the specific operating system version, so newer Java versions are usually unavailable for older versions of OS X.

Java comes pre-installed with many commercial Unix flavors, including those from [[Sun Microsystems|Sun]], [[IBM]] and [[Hewlett Packard]]. As of June 2009, the [[Fedora (Linux distribution)|Fedora 9]],&lt;ref name=&quot;fedora9redhat&quot;&gt;{{cite web
| url=http://developer.redhatmagazine.com/2008/03/12/openjdk-to-replace-icedtea-in-fedora-9/
| title=OpenJDK in Fedora 9!
| last=Wade|first=Karsten
| publisher=redhatmagazine.com
| quote=''Thomas Fitzsimmons updated the Fedora 9 release notes source pages to reflect that Fedora 9 would ship with [[OpenJDK]] 6 instead of the IcedTea implementation of [[OpenJDK]] 7. Fedora 9 (Sulphur) is due to release in May 2008.''
| date=2008-03-13
| accessdate=2008-04-05}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Ubuntu (operating system)|Ubuntu 8.04]],&lt;ref name=&quot;ubuntu openjdk-6&quot;&gt;{{cite web
| url=https://launchpad.net/ubuntu/+source/openjdk-6
| title=openjdk-6 in Ubuntu
| accessdate=2008-04-19}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Debian]],&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
|url=http://packages.debian.org/stable/openjdk-6-jdk
|title=Package: openjdk-6-jdk
|publisher=debian.org
|date=2009-02-14
|accessdate=2009-02-16}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Slackware]] extra,&lt;ref&gt;[http://packages.slackware.it/package.php?q=current/jdk-6-i586-1 Slackware Java package]&lt;/ref&gt; [[Mandriva]]&lt;ref&gt;[http://qa.mandriva.com/twiki/bin/view/Main/JavaPackaging#Compati Mandriva Java package]&lt;/ref&gt; and [[OpenSUSE]]&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
|url=http://en.opensuse.org/OpenJDK
|title=Package: OpenJDK
|publisher=opensuse.org
|accessdate=2009-06-01}} {{Dead link|date=October 2010|bot=H3llBot}}&lt;/ref&gt; distributions are available with OpenJDK, based completely on [[free software|free]] and [[open source]] code.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
| url=http://blogs.sun.com/mr/entry/in_hardy_heron
| title=There's not a moment to lose!
|last=Reinhold|first=Mark
| date=2008-04-24
| accessdate=2008-04-19}}&lt;/ref&gt; Since June 2008, OpenJDK passed all of the compatibility tests in the Java SE 6 [[Technology Compatibility Kit|JCK]] and can claim to be a fully compatible Java 6 implementation.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
|url=http://blog.softwhere.org/archives/196
|title=Java is finally Free and Open
|date=2008-06-19
|last=Sharples|first=Rich}}
&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;fedora9la&quot;&gt;{{cite web
| url=http://langel.wordpress.com/2008/03/13/openjdk-in-fedora-9/
| title=OpenJDK to replace IcedTea in Fedora 9
| last=Angel|first=Lillian
| date=2008-03-13
| accessdate=2008-04-05}}&lt;/ref&gt; OpenJDK can run complex applications such as [[Netbeans]], [[Eclipse (software)|Eclipse]], [[GlassFish]], or [[JBoss]].

The Operating System Distributor License for Java (DLJ)&lt;ref name=&quot;dlj&quot;&gt;[https://jdk-distros.dev.java.net/ Operating System Distributor License for Java (DLJ)]&lt;/ref&gt; is a Sun initiative to ease distribution issues with operating systems based on OpenSolaris or Linux.

If Java is not installed on a computer by default, it may be downloaded by the user as a web plugin.  The web plugin process has been criticized because of the size of the Java plugin.  Unlike other plugins the Java download is a full runtime environment, capable of running not just applets, but full applications and dynamic WebStart apps.  Because of this the perceived download footprint is larger than some web plugins. However, compared to Java, other popular browser plugins have larger sizes: Java 6 [[Java Runtime Environment|JRE]] is 13 MB, but [[Adobe Acrobat|Acrobat Reader]] is 33 MB, [[QuickTime]] 19 MB, [[Windows Media Player]] 25 MB, the [[.NET Framework|.NET Framework 3.0]] runtime is 54 MB, and the .NET Framework 3.5 runtime is 197 MB (it's a united package for x86, x64 and IA-64, each part has approximately 60 MB).

At the [[JavaOne]] event in May 2007 Sun announced that the deployment issues with Java would be solved in two major updates during the lifespan of Java 6 (the changes will not be held over to Java 7.)  These include:
* the introduction of a new consumer JRE edition, with an initial 2Mb footprint and the ability to download the remaining 9Mb in sections using an on-demand methodology.
* the development of drop-in cross platform [[JavaScript]] code, which can be used from a web page to install the necessary JRE for a given applet or [[Rich Internet Application]] to run, if necessary.
* an improvement in support for automatically downloading updates to the JRE.
* support for pre-loading of the JRE, so applets and applications written in Java start up almost instantaneously.

== See also ==
* [[Comparison of Java and C Sharp|Comparison of Java and C# languages]]
* [[Java (programming language)|Java programming language]]

==References==
{{reflist|2}}

==External links==
* [http://msdn.microsoft.com/en-us/gg715299.aspx Moving to C# and the .NET Framework] at [[MSDN]]
* [http://www.ecma-international.org/publications/standards/ecma-335.htm ECMA-335 Common Language Infrastructure (CLI), 4th edition (June 2006)] Free download of Ecma CLI standard
* [http://www.iso.org/iso/iso_catalogue/catalogue_tc/catalogue_detail.htm?csnumber=42927 ISO/IEC 23271:2006 Common Language Infrastructure (CLI) Partitions I to VI] The official ISO/IEC CLI standard
{{Java (Sun)}}
{{DotNET}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Comparison Of The Java And .Net Platforms}}
[[Category:.NET framework]]
[[Category:Java programming language]]
[[Category:Programming language comparisons|Java and .NET platforms]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
