<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="1081440" ns="0" title="Family (TV channel)"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Dablink|For the American channel, see [[Television networks preceding ABC Family]] or its current form [[ABC Family]].}}
:''For the French version of Disney Junior in Canada, see [[Disney Junior (Canadian French TV channel)]].
{{Infobox TV channel
| name             = Family 
| logofile         = Family Channel 2011.png
| logocaption      = Blue version of the Family logo
| logosize         = 165px
| launch           = September 1, 1988
| closed date      = 
| picture format   = [[1080i]] ([[high-definition television|HDTV]])&lt;br&gt;&lt;small&gt;(2011-present)&lt;/small&gt;&lt;br&gt;[[480i]] ([[standard-definition television|SDTV]])&lt;br&gt;&lt;small&gt;(1988-present)&lt;/small&gt;
| owner            = [[Astral Media]]
| slogan           = 
| country          = [[Canada]]
| broadcast area   = National&lt;br&gt;&lt;small&gt;(also available in [[Jamaica]] and the [[Bahamas]])&lt;/small&gt;
| headquarters     = [[Toronto]], [[Ontario]], [[Canada]]
| former names     = Family Channel (1988-1999)
| replaced names   =
| sister names     = [[Disney XD (Canada)|Disney XD]]&lt;br&gt;[[The Movie Network]]
| timeshift names  =
| web              = [http://www.family.ca Family.ca]
| sat serv 1       = [[Bell TV]]
| sat chan 1       = 556 Family &lt;small&gt;(east) (SD)&lt;/small&gt;&lt;br&gt;557 Family &lt;small&gt;(west) (SD)&lt;/small&gt;&lt;br&gt;1642 Family &lt;small&gt;(east) (HD)&lt;/small&gt;
| sat serv 2       = [[Shaw Direct]]
| sat chan 2       = &lt;small&gt;'''Classic lineup:'''&lt;/small&gt;&lt;br&gt;540 Family &lt;small&gt;(east) (SD)&lt;/small&gt;&lt;br&gt;541 Family &lt;small&gt;(west) (SD)&lt;/small&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;small&gt;'''Advanced lineup:'''&lt;/small&gt;&lt;br&gt;170 Family &lt;small&gt;(east) (SD)&lt;/small&gt;&lt;br&gt;171 Family &lt;small&gt;(west) (SD)&lt;/small&gt;
| cable serv 1     = Available on most Canadian cable systems
| cable chan 1     = Check local listings, channels may vary
| iptv serv 1      = [[Bell Aliant TV]]
| iptv chan 1      = 258 Family &lt;small&gt;(east) (SD)&lt;/small&gt;
| iptv serv 2      = [[Bell Fibe TV]]
| iptv chan 2      = 556 Family &lt;small&gt;(east) (SD)&lt;/small&gt;&lt;br&gt;557 Family &lt;small&gt;(west) (SD)&lt;/small&gt;&lt;br&gt;1556 Family &lt;small&gt;(east) (HD)&lt;/small&gt;
| iptv serv 3      = [[Manitoba Telecom Services|MTS]]
| iptv chan 3      = 153 Family &lt;small&gt;(east) (SD)&lt;/small&gt;&lt;br&gt;154 Family &lt;small&gt;(west) (SD)&lt;/small&gt;
| iptv serv 4      = [[Telus TV|Optik TV]]
| iptv chan 4      = 76 Family &lt;small&gt;(east) (SD)&lt;/small&gt;&lt;br&gt;86 Family &lt;small&gt;(west) (SD)&lt;/small&gt;&lt;br&gt;681 Family &lt;small&gt;(east) (HD)&lt;/small&gt;
| iptv serv 5      = [[SaskTel]]
| iptv chan 5      = 130 Family &lt;small&gt;(east) (SD)&lt;/small&gt;
}}

'''Family''' (often referred to as '''Family Channel''') is a [[Canada|Canadian]] [[English language]] [[Category A services|Category A]] [[premium television]] service marketed to children and teenagers aged 2-15. It is owned by [[Astral Media]]. The channel's headquarters are located at the [[Brookfield Place]] office complex, near the [[Financial District, Toronto|Financial District]] of downtown [[Toronto, Ontario]].

Programming featured on the channel consists primarily of Canadian-produced original series, current and archived original programming imported mainly from [[Disney Channel]] in the United States and some theatrically-released feature films. The channel operates two timeshifted feeds: East ([[North American Eastern Time Zone|Eastern Time]]) and West ([[Pacific Time Zone|Pacific Time]]).

==History==
[[File:Family Channel.svg|thumb|left|100px|The Family logo from [[1988 in television|1988]] until [[1999 in television|1999]]. The &quot;Channel&quot; font was slightly different from 1997 to 1999.]]
Family was licensed as a [[premium television|pay TV]] service by the [[Canadian Radio-television and Telecommunications Commission]] (CRTC) on December 1, 1987 as a joint venture between Allarcom Pay Television Limited (later acquired by [[Western International Communications]]) and [[The Movie Network|First Choice Canadian Communications Corporation]] (by then a division of [[Astral Media|Astral Communications]]), with both companies owning a 50% stake in the service.&lt;ref name=&quot;Decision&quot;&gt;{{cite web| title=Decision CRTC 87-905|publisher=CRTC|url=http://www.crtc.gc.ca/eng/archive/1987/DB87-905.htm}}&lt;/ref&gt; It launched as ''Family Channel'' on September 1, 1988. On October 1, 1999, the channel was rebranded Family. In 2000, [[Corus Entertainment]] acquired Western International Communications' stake in the service and subsequently sold it to Astral in 2001.

Family was originally offered by cable companies as a stand-alone channel; however, beginning in October 1997, most cable and satellite providers started offering the channel as part of a package with that year's wave of new [[specialty channel]]s. While Family initially continued its &quot;pay&quot; format, including broadcasts of older Disney movies which would be repeated several times a month, it soon changed its programming practices such that it now operates as a ''de facto'' specialty channel, much like similarly themed channels such as [[YTV (TV channel)|YTV]]. However, in line with CRTC regulations for premium channels, no [[commercials]] are shown, aside from promotions for other Family programs and Family-sponsored contests aired between shows. Some advertisers work around this rule by co-sponsoring contests which are then promoted on the channel.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.astral-kids.com/family/solutions/opportunities.php |title=Astral Kids Media Sales Site: Family Channel - Client Solutions - Promotional Opportunities |accessdate=2011-08-17}}&lt;/ref&gt; Family also offers promotions of video games and theatrical/DVD movies via [[Interstitial program|interstitial programs]] using the name &quot;Blast&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.astral-kids.com/family/solutions/entinterstitials.php |title=Astral Kids Media Sales Site: Family Channel - Client Solutions - Entertainment Interstitials - Blast |accessdate=2011-08-17}}&lt;/ref&gt;'' [[Dance Fever (2003 TV series)|Dance Fever]]'', which aired on Family in 2003, was the only program to have ever taken breaks during the show.{{Citation needed|date=November 2009}} Family was the last English-language children's network in Canada to switch to a [[24/7]] broadcast schedule, finally eliminating its off-air hours on July 1, 2007.

[[File:Family Channel Logo.svg|150px|thumb|Former logo, used from 1999 to 2011.]]
In February 2007, Family began airing short programs from [[Disney Channel]], such as ''[[Disney's Really Short Report]]'', ''Meet the Family'', and the returning feature ''[[Movie Surfers]]'', alongside their own interstitials, such as music videos (&quot;FamJam&quot;), contest promotions, and movie interviews from corporate sister [[The Movie Network]].

On January 11, 2011, Family debuted a new logo and on-air identity to coincide with the launch of its new [[High-definition television|high-definition]] feed.&lt;ref name=&quot;2011 logo&quot;&gt;{{cite web| title=Family Channel turns on new look|publisher=Playbackonline.ca|url=http://www.marketingmag.ca/news/media-news/family-channel-turns-on-new-look-21104|date=2011-01-11}}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Relationship with The Family Channel (U.S.) / ABC Family ===
The existence of a [[United States]] cable channel, itself long known as The Family Channel, and now known as [[ABC Family]], has occasionally led to the presumption that the two channels are affiliated. The two channels have co-commissioned some programming in the past and both currently have a significant connection to [[The Walt Disney Company]] (Family primarily acquires its foreign programming from Disney Channel and Disney XD, while The Walt Disney Company purchased ABC Family from [[News Corporation]] in 2000). However, the two channels developed separately in each country, and as such, neither channel can be considered an international version of the other, especially given that unlike Family, ABC Family is advertiser-supported. Allarcom and First Choice had first proposed using the &quot;Family Channel&quot; name in 1987.&lt;ref name=&quot;Decision&quot;/&gt; The American channel, initially controlled by televangelist [[Pat Robertson]], was originally known as the [[Christian Broadcasting Network|CBN]] Satellite Service and later CBN Cable Network, before adopting the &quot;CBN Family Channel&quot; name in August 1988, one month before Canada's Family Channel signed on, only dropping the reference to CBN two years later in September 1990.

Despite the current dual relationships with Disney, most of ABC Family's recent original series have aired in Canada on channels other than Family (such as [[MuchMusic]]), as Family's schedule is already filled with Disney Channel programming, Canadian-produced shows and other programs focused on children and preteens. Most recently, Disney has announced a separate partnership with [[Corus Entertainment]] to launch a ABC Family-style channel in Canada in 2012 (to be named [[ABC Spark]] to avoid any confusion with Astral's service).&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.thefutoncritic.com/news/2011/10/26/new-millennial-focused-channel-abc-spark-to-launch-in-canada-789303/20111026abc01/ New Millennial Focused Channel, ABC Spark, to Launch in Canada], ''The Futon Critic''. Accessed 2011-10-26.&lt;/ref&gt; Nevertheless, some American cable providers have used Family's former &quot;Paint and Sun&quot; logo to represent the U.S. channel on program guides, and occasionally the reverse has occurred with ABC Family's Robertson-era logo as The Family Channel (whose &quot;Family&quot; script is similar to the pre-1998 logo of the Canadian channel) appearing in some Canadian listings.

Family's development was in fact more similar to that of Disney Channel; besides common programming and past co-commissioning of original programming, both launched as premium channels prior to pay television providers offering them as basic channels, and both channels do not offer traditional advertising (Disney Channel does not accept traditional advertising outside of  [[PBS]]-style underwriter sponsorships, and breaks within programs consist largely of promotions of its own programming, and Disney Channel-produced featurettes advertising Disney films and consumer products). Due to Disney Channel's longtime programming agreement with Family, Family is often thought of as a ''de facto'' Canadian version of Disney Channel.

==Programming==
{{main|List of programs broadcast by Family (TV channel)}}
Family produces its own original programming, in addition to airing many series and original movies from the U.S. cable network [[Disney Channel]], along with two current original series from [[Disney XD]] (''[[Pair of Kings]]'' and ''[[Kickin' It]]'') and reruns of two now-defunct series from the U.S. flagship of [[Nickelodeon (TV channel)|Nickelodeon]] (''[[Ned's Declassified School Survival Guide]]'' and ''[[Zoey 101]]''). Though the majority of Family's international programming comes from Disney Channel, some Nickelodeon live-action series ran on the channel in the past, this was even as YTV strengthened its programming ties with Nickelodeon during the 2000s; Nickelodeon's programming has now largely migrated to YTV (and its sister channel [[Nickelodeon (Canada)|Nickelodeon Canada]]).

Family broadcasts episodes of its programming in order by the program's production code number, instead of the order of their original broadcast run on American and other foreign channels; many times this places episodes out of order storyline-wise, as many shows film episodes out of order. The network also utilizes an &quot;off-the-clock&quot; schedule for programming airing between 1 a.m. and 10:30 a.m. ET, with series airing during that period running in timeslots of 23-27 minutes, usually concurrent with the program's original runtime without commercials or promos included, as such promo breaks on Family between programs are generally of limited length during the overnight and morning hours.

===Original programming===
The majority of foreign programming is sourced from [[Disney Channel]] however, Family also commissions its own original programming. Some of their most popular shows include ''[[Life With Derek]]'', ''[[The Latest Buzz]]'', ''[[Overruled!]]'', ''[[Wingin' It]]'' and ''[[Naturally, Sadie]]''. Originally though, ''[[Majority Rules (TV series)|Majority Rules]]'' aired on [[Teletoon (Canadian TV channel)|Teletoon]]. Past and present original programs include:
{{multicol}}
* ''[[Mentors (TV series)|Mentors]]'' (1998–2002)
* ''[[Henry's World]]'' (2002–2003)
* ''[[Radio Free Roscoe]]'' (2003–2005)
* ''[[King (2003 TV series)|King]]'' (2003–2005)
* ''[[Franny's Feet]]'' (2004–present)
* ''[[Darcy's Wild Life]]'' (2004–2006)
* ''[[Naturally, Sadie]]'' (2004–2007)
* ''[[Life with Derek]]'' (2005–2009)
{{multicol-break}}
* ''[[The Latest Buzz]]'' (2007–2010)
* ''[[Overruled!]]'' (2009–present)
* ''[[Wingin' It]]'' (2010–present)
* ''[[Baxter (TV Series)|Baxter]]'' (2010–2011)
* ''[[Connor Undercover]]'' (2010–present)
* ''[[What's Up Warthogs!]]'' (2011–present)
* ''[[Really Me!]]'' (2011–present)
* ''[[Debra!]]'' (2011–present)
{{multicol-end}}

===Movies===
The channel also airs films, which are run uninterrupted and typically air on weekends (with two films each on Friday and Sunday evenings, three films on Saturday evenings, and an additional movie on early Saturday and Sunday afternoons). Films aired in these timeslots consist of either made-for-TV films produced by Disney Channel or older theatrically-released feature films (from studios such as [[Walt Disney Motion Pictures Group]] and [[Columbia TriStar Motion Picture Group]]). As it is licensed as a premium service, all films aired on Family are given parental advisories by either the [[Canadian motion picture rating system]] or the [[Television content rating systems#Canada|Canadian TV Classification System]] (the latter also applies to series airing on the channel), prior to the start of the feature. Films aired on Family consist of G, PG and some 14A-rated movies, no films with rated 14+ and above for non-theatrically released films or 18A and above for theatrically-released films are broadcast on the channel.

While Family broadcasts original movies produced by Disney Channel, up until 2010, Family had not produced or distributed their own original [[made-for-TV movie]]s. However, due to the popularity of their original series ''Life with Derek'', Family commissioned its first original movie ''[[Vacation with Derek]]'', a movie based on the series which began production in the summer of 2009; the movie aired in June 2010 on Family. In addition, Family has also been involved in one other made-for-TV film co-production, the 2010 film ''[[16 Wishes]]'', which was co-produced in association with Disney Channel and Marvista Entertainment.

Some of the network's movies also air in a ''[[Pop Up Video]]''-style version (similar to the special versions of select original movies produced by and broadcast on Disney Channel in the United States), with behind-the-scenes trivia overlayed onto the image, such as ''Vacation with Derek: What's Up Edition''.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.myspace.com/ashleyleggat/blog/537955835 |title=Ashley Legatt's blog - 6 Aug 2010 |accessdate=2011-07-02 |quote='Vacation With Derek' will be ... in a pop-up version, that means you will get to see all of the behind the scenes facts and trivia from filming.}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Programming blocks===
====Current====
* '''Disney Junior on Family''' - On May 6, 2011, Playhouse Disney rebranded and became '''Disney Junior on Family'''. It airs shows specially designed for preschoolers every weekday morning from 4:30 to 7 a.m. ET, and 8:45 a.m. to 11 a.m. ET, and weekend mornings from 4:30 to 8 a.m. ET. With the exception of a new show, ''[[Jake and the Never Land Pirates]]'', the block's program schedule remain the same. As of April 2011, shows that currently aired on the block are ''[[Franny's Feet]]'', ''[[Handy Manny]]'', ''[[Harry and His Bucket Full of Dinosaurs]]'', ''[[Henry's World]]'', ''[[Imagination Movers]]'', ''[[Jake and the Never Land Pirates]]'', ''[[Jungle Junction]]'', ''[[Katie and Orbie]]'', ''[[Mickey Mouse Clubhouse]]'', ''[[The Secret World of Benjamin Bear]]'' and ''[[Strawberry Shortcake (2003 TV series)|Strawberry Shortcake]]''.
* '''Surprise Stack Attack!''' - On October 13, 2011, Family began airing 'stacks' of surprise programming. In TV programming guides, it is displayed as &quot;To Be Announced&quot;. Surprise Stack Attack! occurs every Thursday from 5 to 7 p.m. ET/PT.

====Former====
* '''[[Jetix (Canada)|Jetix]]''' - Family began their own Jetix block on September 10, 2006, replaced the &quot;Power Box&quot; block. The original Canadian Jetix block included ''[[Get Ed]]'', ''[[Oban Star Racers]]'', ''[[Yin Yang Yo!]]'', ''[[Pucca]]'', ''[[Power Rangers: Mystic Force]]'', ''[[Power Rangers: Jungle Fury]]'', and ''[[Power Rangers: Operation Overdrive]]''. Jetix aired from 6:03 a.m. EST through 7:45 a.m. EST on weekend mornings. Jetix ended on August 1, 2009. The Canadian version of [[Disney XD (Canada)|Disney XD]] launched on June 1, 2011.
* '''Power Box''' - Until 2006, Family showed an early morning programming block of Japanese-themed fighting shows including ''[[W.I.T.C.H. (TV series)|W.I.T.C.H.]]'', ''[[Power Rangers: Dino Thunder]]'', ''[[Oban Star Racers]]'', and ''[[Super Robot Monkey Team Hyper Force Go!|S.R.M.T.H.F.G.]]'' that started at 6 a.m. EST. In 2006, &quot;Power Box&quot; programming was dropped and replaced with Jetix.
* '''Mad Dash''' - Mad Dash aired mainly Disney animated shows for kids and pre-teens every weekday afternoon from 11:49 a.m. EST until 5:03 p.m. EST. Notable shows that aired are: ''[[Pucca (TV series)|Pucca]]'', ''[[The Suite Life of Zack &amp; Cody]]'', ''[[Wizards of Waverly Place]]'', ''[[Cory in the House]]'', ''[[Fish Hooks]]'', ''[[Ned's Declassified School Survival Guide]]'', ''[[Phineas and Ferb]]'', ''[[Recess (TV series)|Recess]]'', and ''[[The Replacements (TV series)|The Replacements]]''. &quot;Mad Dash&quot; was canceled in early March 2010.
* '''Non Stop''' - It aired mostly live-action sitcoms every weekday evening &amp; all weekend long. Notable shows that aired are: ''[[The Suite Life on Deck]]'', ''[[Hannah Montana]]'', ''[[Sonny With a Chance]]'', ''[[Wizards of Waverly Place]]'', ''[[Zeke and Luther]]'', ''[[Aaron Stone]]'', ''[[Jonas (TV series)|Jonas]]'', and ''[[Overruled!]]'', as well as reruns of ''[[The Suite Life of Zack &amp; Cody]]'', ''[[Cory in the House]]'', ''[[Life with Derek]]'', and ''[[The Latest Buzz]]''. &quot;Non Stop&quot; ended on January 11, 2011 with no replacement.
* '''Non Stop Weekends''' - Every Saturday and Sunday, Family ran a series of '''&quot;Non Stop&quot; programming''' until 9:00 p.m. EST. The block was ended on January 9, 2011, not being replaced.
* '''Family Nights''' - Every Monday to Thursday from 7:30 to 9:30 p.m. EST it featured ''[[The Suite Life on Deck]]'', ''[[Hannah Montana]]'' and other series. Family Nights stopped airing on June 25, 2010.

==Related services==
===Family HD===
On January 11, 2011, Family launched a [[high-definition television|high definition]] feed called '''Family HD''' that simulcasts the East Coast [[standard-definition television|standard definition]] feed.&lt;ref name=&quot;2011 logo&quot;/&gt; The channel broadcasts in the [[1080i]] picture format.

===Family OnDemand===
'''Family OnDemand''' is a [[video on demand]] service featuring programming from Family, available to subscribers of the network. The service features original series produced by Family, as well as original programming supplied by Disney Channel, which provides the vast majority of the American program content on the linear Family channel.

===Disney Junior===
{{main|Disney Junior (Canadian English TV channel)}}
[[File:Disney Junior Logo.png|right|200px|thumb|Disney Junior logo, 2011-present]]
[[File:Playhouse Disney En.png|right|150px|thumb|right|Logo used as Playhouse Disney Channel, 2007-2011]]
A local version of '''[[Disney Junior]]''' was launched as a [[multiplex (TV)|multiplex]] of Family originally known as [[Playhouse Disney|Playhouse Disney Channel]] on November 30, 2007, a 24/7 commercial-free channel carrying programs aimed at [[preschool]]-aged children.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.kidscreen.com/articles/magazine/20071101/playhouse.html?__b=yes; Playhouse Disney splashes out for Canuck launch], KidScreen, [[2007-11-01]]&lt;/ref&gt; Unlike Family, Disney Junior has only one national feed operating from the [[North American Eastern Time Zone|Eastern Time Zone]]. For satellite, it is exclusively carried on [[Bell TV]]. 

The channel was re-launched under the new [[Disney Junior]] brand on May 6, 2011.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.newswire.ca/en/releases/archive/March2011/03/c7649.html DISNEY JUNIOR LAUNCHES MAY 6 WITH NEW PROGRAMS AND A NOD TO CLASSIC DISNEY CHARACTERS AND MAGIC], CNW, [[2011-03-03]]&lt;/ref&gt;

Because Family is licensed as a premium service which allows for the addition of multiplex channels that are consistent with the network's licence, no additional licence was required to launch the service. Existing subscribers of Family are automatically eligible to receive Disney Junior free of charge, subject to carriage by their television service provider; however, it is not available on a standalone basis. The use of Family's existing licence also allows the service to compete with the preschooler-aimed specialty channel, [[Treehouse TV|Treehouse]], despite the format protection guidelines for specialty channels. This is so, because Family's nature of service is to broadcast programming targeted toward &quot;youth to age 17&quot;, in which case, a preschool audience would qualify.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.crtc.gc.ca/eng/archive/2002/db2002-386.htm Broadcasting Decision CRTC 2002-386], CRTC, 2002-11-28&lt;/ref&gt;

A [[Disney Junior (Canadian French TV channel)|French language version]] of Disney Junior (then known as Playhouse Disney Télé) launched on July 5, 2010. It was rebranded as Disney Junior on May 6, 2011 to coincide with the rebranding of the English channel. However, unlike the English version of Disney Junior, the French version is a [[Category 2 specialty channel|category 2]] service using its own licence.

===Disney Junior On Demand===
'''Disney Junior On Demand''' is a [[video on demand]] (VOD) service featuring programming from Disney Junior, available to subscribers of Family and Disney Junior. Disney Junior launched its own VOD channel on May 6, 2011. &lt;ref&gt;[http://www.disneyjunior.ca/en/on-demand.php Disney Junior On Demand]&lt;/ref&gt;

==International distribution==
Outside of Canada, Family is seen on some cable systems in the Caribbean:
* [[Jamaica]] - distributed on '''Flow Cable''' systems.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.flowjamaica.com/index.php?option=com_content&amp;task=view&amp;id=37&amp;Itemid=133 Flow Cable channel lineup]&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[Bahamas]] - distributed on '''Cable Bahamas''' systems.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.cablebahamas.com/television/digital/valuepackages/index.lasso?package=5df943797f5b9841&amp;groupDisplay=0&amp;chanDisplay=214#99 Cable Bahamas channel lineup]&lt;/ref&gt;

==See also==
*[[Disney Junior (Canadian English TV channel)|Disney Junior (English)]]
*[[Disney Junior (Canadian French TV channel)|Disney Junior (French)]]
*[[Disney XD (Canada)]]

==References==
{{reflist}}

== External links ==
* [http://www.family.ca/ Family]
* [http://www.disneyjunior.ca/ Disney Junior Canada]

{{Family Channel original series}}
{{Astral Media}}
{{Canadian family-oriented television channels}}
{{Canadian premium television services}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Family (Tv Channel)}}
[[Category:Children's television networks in Canada]]
[[Category:Astral Media]]
[[Category:Commercial-free television networks]]
[[Category:Television channels and stations established in 1988]]
[[Category:Canadian analog cable television networks]]

[[fr:Family (chaîne de télévision)]]
[[ja:ファミリー (TVチャンネル)]]
[[pt:Family Channel]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
