<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="10854746" ns="0" title="Aircraft Transport and Travel"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">'''Aircraft Transport and Travel Limited''' was a British airline formed during the [[First World War]], a subsidiary of '''[[Airco]]'''. It was the first airline to operate a regular international flight (between London and Paris).
[[File:DH16-AT&amp;T.jpg|thumb|De Havilland DH.16, Aircraft Transport &amp; Travel, probably Croydon 1920]]
==History==
On 5 October 1916, Aircraft Transport and Travel (AT&amp;T) was formed by [[George Holt Thomas]]. Using a fleet of former military [[Airco DH.4]]A biplanes, it operated relief flights between [[Folkestone]] and [[Ghent]]. On 15 July 1919, the company flew a proving flight across the [[English Channel]], despite a lack of support from the [[United Kingdom|British]] government. Flown by Lt. H Shaw in an [[Airco DH.9]] between [[RAF Hendon]] and [[Paris - Le Bourget Airport]], the flight took 2 hours and 30 minutes, and cost £21 per passenger.

On 25 August 1919, the company used [[Airco DH.16|DH.16s]] to start a regular service from [[Hounslow Heath Aerodrome]] to Le Bourget, the first regular (daily) international service in the world. The airline soon gained a reputation for reliability, despite problems with bad weather. In November 1919, it won the first British civil [[airmail]] contract. Six [[Royal Air Force]] [[Airco DH.9A]] aircraft were loaned to the company, to operate the airmail service between [[Hawkinge]] and [[Cologne]]. In 1920, they were returned to the Royal Air Force.

In February 1920, with its parent Aircraft Manufacturing Company Limited (Airco), AT&amp;T, also known as Airco Air Express, became part of the BSA group. It continued operations, under the control of [[Frank Searle (businessman)|Frank Searle]] of [[Daimler Hire|Daimler Hire Limited]]. 

As well as the London (Hounslow) to Paris service, AT&amp;T also operated a [[Croydon Airport]] to [[Amsterdam]] service on behalf of [[KLM]]. On 17 May 1920, a DH.16 (G-EALU) of AT&amp;T operated the first KLM service between London and Amsterdam.

AT&amp;T continued to operate, but Daimler-BSA withdrew support, and overcome with debt in November 1920 it was placed in liquidation, and on 17 December 1920, it ran its last service.&lt;ref&gt;''The Putnam Aeronautical Review'' edited by John Motum, p170 Volume one 1990 Naval Institute Press&lt;/ref&gt; Early in 1921, its assets were purchased by Daimler and rolled with Daimler Air Hire Limited into a new company called [[Daimler Airway|Daimler Airway Limited]] which continued the services.

By 1921, six companies operated a London to Paris service, three [[France|French]] and three [[United Kingdom|British]]. The French airlines were receiving subsidies from the French Government, and in protest the three British airlines stopped services on 28 February 1921.

==Aircraft==
{{Div col|2}}
* [[Airco DH.4]]
* [[Airco DH.4]]A
* [[Airco DH.6]]
* [[Airco DH.9]]
* [[Airco DH.9A]]
* [[Airco DH.9B]]
* [[de Havilland DH.16]]
* [[de Havilland DH.18]]
{{Div col end}}

==References==
{{reflist}}
*{{cite book |last= |first= |authorlink= |coauthors= |title= The Illustrated Encyclopedia of Aircraft (Part Work 1982-1985)|year= |publisher= Orbis Publishing|location= |issn=}}
*{{cite book |last= Jackson|first= A.J.|authorlink= |coauthors= |title= British Civil Aircraft since 1919 Volume 2|year= 1974|publisher= Putnam|location= London|isbn=0-370-10010-7}}

==External links==
*[http://www.britishairways.com/travel/history-1910-1919/public/en_fi British Airways history 1910-1919]

{{Aviation lists}}

[[Category:Airlines established in 1916]]
[[Category:Defunct airlines of the United Kingdom]]

[[de:Aircraft Transport &amp; Travel]]
[[sv:Aircraft Transport and Travel]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
