<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="1086696" ns="0" title="Andy McNab"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Use British English|date=August 2011}}
{{Use dmy dates|date=August 2011}}
{{Infobox military person
|name= Andy McNab
|birth_date= {{birth date and age|1959|12|28|df=yes}}
|birth_place= [[Southwark]], London, England
|image=
|nickname=
|allegiance= United Kingdom
|serviceyears= 1976–1993
|rank= [[Sergeant#United Kingdom|Sergeant]]
|branch= [[Image:Flag of the British Army.svg|22px]] [[British Army]]
|unit= [[Royal Green Jackets]] (1976–84)&lt;br/&gt;[[Special Air Service]] (1984–93)
|commands= [[Bravo Two Zero]]
|battles= [[The Troubles]]&lt;br/&gt;[[Gulf War|First Gulf War]]
|awards= [[Distinguished Conduct Medal]]&lt;br/&gt;[[Military Medal]]
|laterwork= Author
}}
[[Sergeant]] '''‘Andy McNab’''' [[Distinguished Conduct Medal|DCM]] [[Military Medal|MM]] (born 28 December 1959) is the pseudonym&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.independent.co.uk/arts-entertainment/books/features/andy-mcnab-the-hidden-face-of-war-533714.html |title=Hanks, Robert &quot;Andy McNab: The hidden face of war&quot; '&amp;#39;The Independent'&amp;#39;, 19 Nov 2004 |publisher=Independent.co.uk |date=2004-11-19 |accessdate=2011-10-25}}&lt;/ref&gt; of an English novelist and former [[Special Air Service|SAS]] operative and soldier.

McNab came into public prominence in 1993, when he published his account of the failed [[Special Air Service]] (SAS) patrol, [[Bravo Two Zero]] for which he was awarded the [[Distinguished Conduct Medal]] in 1991.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.robmcgibbon.com/resources/pcw_andy_mcnab.pdf |title=McGibbon, Rob, 2005 '&amp;#39;'The Press Conference with Andy McNab'&amp;#39; |publisher=Robmcgibbon.com |date= |accessdate=2011-10-25}}&lt;/ref&gt; He had previously received the [[Military Medal]] in 1980, awarded for an action whilst serving with the [[Royal Green Jackets]] in Northern Ireland during 1979.&lt;ref name=&quot;nuzhound.com&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.nuzhound.com/articles/irish_news/arts2005/aug1_McNab_1979_killing.php |title=Stinson, James 'McNab tells of killing IRA man in 1979 gun battle' '&amp;#39;Irish News'&amp;#39;, 1 August 2005 |publisher=Nuzhound.com |date= |accessdate=2011-10-25}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In addition to ''[[Bravo Two Zero (1993 novel)|Bravo Two Zero]]'' he has written two other autobiographies and a number of fiction books.

==Early life==
McNab was born on 28 December 1959. Found abandoned on the steps of [[Guy's Hospital]] in [[London Borough of Southwark|Southwark]], he was brought up in [[Peckham]], with his adoptive family. He did not do well in school and started just doing odd jobs, usually for friends and relatives, and was partly inspired to join the [[British Army]] because of his brother's time in the army.

He was involved in petty criminality until being arrested for burglary. In 1976, shortly after his arrest, he aspired to a career as an army pilot, but failed the entry test. In the same year, he enlisted with the [[Royal Green Jackets]] at the age of sixteen.&lt;ref name=&quot;andymcnab.co.uk&quot;&gt;[http://www.andymcnab.co.uk/about Biography | Andy McNab Official Website]&lt;/ref&gt;

==Military career==
After McNab enlisted in the Royal Green Jackets he was posted to [[Kent]] for his basic training, and boxed for his regimental team. After his basic training, he was posted to the Rifle Depot, in [[Winchester]]. In 1977, McNab spent time in [[Gibraltar]] as part of his first operational posting, while with 2RGJ.

From December 1977 to June 1978, he was posted to [[South Armagh]], Northern Ireland, as part of the [[British Army]]'s '[[Operation Banner]]'. In 1978 and 1979, he returned to Armagh as a newly promoted [[Lance Corporal#United Kingdom|Lance Corporal]], and claimed to have killed for the first time during a firefight with the [[Provisional Irish Republican Army]]. McNab wrote of the incident: ''&quot;I remember vividly the first time I had to kill someone to stay alive. I was a 19-year-old soldier in Keady, south Armagh, and my patrol stumbled across six IRA terrorists preparing for an ambush. When the shooting started they were just 20 metres away from my patrol. I was scared, very scared.&quot;''&lt;ref name=&quot;nuzhound.com&quot; /&gt; McNab was awarded the [[Military Medal]] for this incident.&lt;ref name=&quot;nuzhound.com&quot; /&gt;  However, security sources later claimed that the person McNab shot was only wounded and died as a result of injuries from a separate shootout later that day.&lt;ref name=&quot;nuzhound.com&quot; /&gt;

In 1982, after spending eight years with the Royal Green Jackets, he decided to attempt SAS [[United Kingdom Special Forces Selection|selection]]. Having failed his first attempt he finally passed in 1984, and transferred to the SAS. While serving with Air Troop, B Squadron, 22 SAS for ten years, McNab worked on both [[Covert operation|covert]] and overt operations worldwide,&lt;ref name=&quot;andymcnab.co.uk&quot; /&gt; which included [[counter terrorism]] and drug operations in the Middle East and Far East, [[South America|South]] and Central America and [[Northern Ireland]]. McNab trained as a specialist in counter terrorism, prime target elimination, demolitions, weapons, tactics, covert surveillance roles and information gathering in hostile environments, and [[Very Important Person|VIP]] protection.&lt;ref name=&quot;andymcnab.co.uk&quot; /&gt; He worked on cooperative operations with police forces, prison services, anti-drug forces and Western backed [[Guerrilla tactics|guerrilla]] movements as well as on conventional special operations. In Northern Ireland, he spent two years working as an undercover operator with [[14 Intelligence Company]], going on to become an instructor.&lt;ref name=&quot;andymcnab.co.uk&quot; /&gt;

During the [[Gulf War|First Gulf War]], McNab commanded Bravo Two Zero, an eight man SAS patrol that was given the task of destroying underground communication links between [[Baghdad]] and north-west [[Iraq]] and with tracking [[Scud]] missile movements in the region. The patrol was dropped into Iraq on 22 January 1991, but was soon compromised, escaping on foot towards [[Syria]], the closest [[Coalition of the Gulf War|coalition]] country.

Three of the eight men were killed; four were captured (including McNab) after three days on the run and one member, '[[Chris Ryan]]', escaped. The four captured men were held for six weeks before being released on 5 March. By the time he was released McNab was suffering from [[nerve damage]] to both hands, a dislocated shoulder, kidney and liver damage and [[hepatitis B]]. After six months of medical treatment he was back on active service. In the words of the SAS's commanding officer, the story of the patrol &quot;will remain in Regimental history forever&quot;.

Awarded both the [[Distinguished Conduct Medal]] (DCM) and [[Military Medal]] (MM) during his military career, McNab claims to have been the British Army's most highly decorated serving soldier when he left the SAS in February 1993.&lt;ref name=&quot;andymcnab.co.uk&quot; /&gt;

==Post military career==
While writing ''Bravo Two Zero'', McNab assumed his pseudonym. When he appears on television to promote his books or to act as a special services expert, his face is shadowed to prevent identification. As [[Larry King]] put it when McNab appeared on the ''[[Larry King Live]]'' show on [[CNN]]: &quot;We have Andy in shadows. He's wanted by terrorist groups.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |url=http://transcripts.cnn.com/TRANSCRIPTS/0111/20/lkl.00.html |title=CNN LARRY KING LIVE: Larry King Interviews Bob Dole, Max Cleland |work=CNN.com – Transcripts |date=20 November 2001 |accessdate=14 November 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt; According to the book ''The Big Breach'', by [[Richard Tomlinson]], a renegade [[MI6]] spy, McNab was part of a special training team after the Iraq war, training MI6 recruits in sabotage and [[guerrilla warfare]] techniques.

Due to the extremely sensitive nature of his work while serving with the SAS, McNab has a legally binding contract obliging him to submit his writings to the [[Ministry of Defence (United Kingdom)|British Ministry of Defence]] for review. He is still believed to be wanted by a number of the world's terrorist organisations; he therefore chooses not to reveal either his face or his current location.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news| url=http://www.independent.co.uk/arts-entertainment/books/features/andy-mcnab-the-hidden-face-of-war-533714.html | work=The Independent | location=London | title=Andy McNab: The hidden face of war | date=19 November 2004 | accessdate=25 April 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;

After leaving the Army, McNab developed and maintained a specialist training course for news crews, journalists and members of non-governmental organisations working in hostile environments. He spent time in Hollywood as technical weapons advisor, and trainer on the [[Michael Mann (film director)|Michael Mann]] film ''[[Heat (1995 film)|Heat]],'' helping to engineer how the master-thief played by [[Robert De Niro]] would go about pulling off robberies on an armoured car and a bank, and how policeman [[Al Pacino]] would go about tracking him down and stopping him. He was also the technical advisor on the 2005 crime film ''[[Dirty (film)|Dirty]]''.&lt;ref name=&quot;imdb&quot;&gt;[http://www.imdb.com/name/nm0573512/ Andy McNab Filmography | Internet Movie Database]&lt;/ref&gt;

In February 2007, McNab returned to Iraq for seven days as ''[[The Sun (newspaper)|The Sun]]'' newspaper's security advisor with his old regiment the Royal Green Jackets. Here he researched the background for his new book, ''Crossfire''.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.thesun.co.uk/article/0,2-2007110295,00.html ''Hero McNab goes back to Iraq''] ''The Sun'', retrieved 27 February 2008&lt;/ref&gt;

McNab has written about his experiences in the SAS in three best-selling books, ''Bravo Two Zero'' (1993), ''[[Immediate Action (book)|Immediate Action]]'' (1995) and ''[[Seven Troop (book)|Seven Troop]]'' (2008). ''Bravo Two Zero'' sold over 1.7&amp;nbsp;million copies, with ''Immediate Action'' selling 1.4&amp;nbsp;million in the UK. To date{{when|date=January 2011}} it has been published in 17 countries and translated into 16 languages.&lt;ref name=&quot;andymcnab.co.uk&quot; /&gt; The CD spoken word version of ''Bravo Two Zero'', narrated by McNab, sold over 60,000 copies and earned a silver disc. A [[BBC]] film of ''[[Bravo Two Zero (film)|Bravo Two Zero]]'', starring [[Sean Bean]], was shown on prime time [[BBC One]] television in 1999 and released on DVD in 2000. ''Immediate Action'', McNab's autobiography, spent 18 weeks at the top of the best-seller lists following the lifting of an ''ex-parte'' injunction granted to the Ministry of Defence in September 1995.&lt;ref name=&quot;andymcnab.co.uk&quot; /&gt;

==Fiction writing==
McNab is the author of a number of action thrillers.

A series of thirteen successful books are based on [[Nick Stone (Andy McNab character)|Nick Stone]] – an ex-SAS soldier working on deniable operations for British intelligence. The series draws extensively on McNab's experiences and knowledge of Special Forces soldiering. He has been officially registered by [[Nielsen BookScan]] as a best-selling British thriller writer.{{Citation needed|date=November 2011}}
The [[Boy Soldier Series]] was written with the cooperation of [[Robert Rigby]] and follows a boy named Danny Watts and his grandfather Fergus, apparently a rogue ex-[[Special Air Service|SAS]] soldier.

Andy McNab has also written two books for [[Quick Reads]], a charity that supports World Book day, ''&quot;The Grey Man&quot;'' and ''&quot;Last Night Another Soldier&quot;''. BBC raw words offers exclusive audio versions of the latest Quick Reads by Andy McNab Last Night Another Soldier read by Rupert Degas.

===Film work===
After working on the Miramax film, ''Heat'', Miramax has acquired the film rights to the first four of McNab's novels, and ''Echelon'' is currently{{when|date=January 2011}} in production, based on the book ''Firewall''  McNab will co-produce and co-write the script and also act as technical adviser. According to McNab on his recent book signing tour, either Jason Statham or Tom Hardy will play the lead role of Nick Stone. He is also a current board-member of a private security company. In conjunction with Spoken Group Ltd, Andy McNab is pioneering spoken drama for download from the Internet and to mobile phones.{{Citation needed|date=January 2009}} These stories include real battle field sound effects. 'McNab' took part in [[E4 (channel)|E4]]'s ''[[Big Brother: Celebrity Hijack]]'' on 13 January 2008.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.thesun.co.uk/sol/homepage/showbiz/tv/celebrity_big_brother_hijack/article683012.ece |title=Behind scenes at SAS hijacking! |publisher=The Sun |date=2008-01-14 |accessdate=2011-10-25}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Current==
He now lives in Norfolk&lt;ref&gt;AccessVideos interview with Rob McGibbon 2008 (part 1)&lt;/ref&gt; and lectures on security and military related topics, in both the US and the UK.&lt;ref name=&quot;andymcnab.co.uk&quot; /&gt;

He is also a director of military service recruitment, mentoring and Foundation organisation, ForceSelect.&lt;ref&gt;www.forceselect.com ForceSelect&lt;/ref&gt;

He worked with DICE on perfecting various situations involving techniques on gun fighting, stance and other war-related issues for Battlefield 3.

==Books==
===Non-fiction===
*''[[Bravo Two Zero (1993 novel)|Bravo Two Zero]]'' (1993)
*''[[Immediate Action (book)|Immediate Action]]'' (1995)
*''[[Seven Troop (book)|Seven Troop]]'' (2008)
*''[[Spoken From The Front]]'' (2009)

===Fiction===
'''[[Nick Stone (Andy McNab character)|Nick Stone]] Missions'''
*''[[Remote Control (novel)|Remote Control]]'' (17 February 1998)
*''[[Crisis Four]]'' (22 August 2000)
*''[[Firewall (Andy McNab novel)|Firewall]]'' (5 October 2000)
*''[[Last Light (novel)|Last Light]] '' (1 October 2001)
*''[[Liberation Day (novel)|Liberation Day]]'' (1 October 2002)
*''[[Dark Winter (novel)|Dark Winter]]'' (3 November 2003)
*''[[Deep Black]]'' (1 November 2004)
*''[[Aggressor (novel)|Aggressor]]'' (1 November 2005)
*''[[Recoil (novel)|Recoil]]'' (6 November 2006)
*''[[Crossfire (2007 novel)|Crossfire]]'' (12 November 2007)
*''Brute Force'' (3 November 2008)
*''Exit Wound''  (5 November 2009)
*''Zero Hour''  (25 November 2010)
*''Dead Centre'' (15 September 2011)

'''[[Boy Soldier Series]]''' (written with [[Robert Rigby]])
*''Boy Soldier'' (US title ''Traitor'', 5 May 2005)
*''Traitor
*''Payback'' (6 October 2005)
*''Avenger'' (4 May 2006)
*''Meltdown'' (3 May 2007)

'''Quick Reads project'''
*''The Grey Man''&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.fantasticfiction.co.uk/series/quick-reads/grey-man.htm |title=The Grey Man (Quick Reads 2006) by Andy McNab |publisher=Fantasticfiction.co.uk |date= |accessdate=2011-10-25}}&lt;/ref&gt; (8 May 2006)
*''Last Night Another Soldier''  (4 May 2010)

'''Audio Stories'''
*''Iraq Ambush'' (May 2007)
*''Royal Kidnap'' (June 2007)
*''Roadside Bomb'' (September 2007)
*''Sniper'' (TBA ?)

'''Dropzone Series'''
*''Dropzone Bk. 1'' (February 2010)
*''Dropzone Bk. 2 – Terminal Velocity (March 2011)

'''Men at War Series''' (written with [Kym Jordan])

*''War Torn'' (13 May 2010)

'''Battlefield 3: The Russian (novel)''' (October 2011)

==Television==
* ''[[Andy McNab's Tour of Duty]]''

==Notes==
{{Reflist}}

==References==

*{{cite book
 | last = Peter
 | first = Ratcliffe
 | title = Eye of the Storm: Twenty-Five Years in Action with the SAS
 | year = 2000
 | publisher=Michael O'Mara Books
 | isbn = 978-1854798091
}}

*{{cite book
 | last = Asher
 | first = Michael
 | title = The Real Bravo Two Zero: The Truth Behind Bravo Two Zero
 | year = 2002
 | publisher=Cassell Military
 | isbn = 978-0304365548
}}

*{{cite book
 | last = Coburn
 | first = Mike
 | title = Soldier Five: The Real Truth About The Bravo Two Zero Mission
 | year = 2004
 | publisher=Mainstream Publishing
 | isbn = 978-1840189070
}}

==External links==
* [http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/programmes/this_week/5132536.stm Essay for BBC's This Week programme]
*{{IMDb name|id=0573512|name=Andy McNab}}
* [http://www.graymansland.com Gray Man's Land] longstanding and respected fan site
* [http://www.bbc.co.uk/raw/words/quickreads/ BBC raw words – Quick Reads]

{{Persondata
| NAME              = Macnab, Andy
| ALTERNATIVE NAMES =
| SHORT DESCRIPTION =
| DATE OF BIRTH     = 28 December 1959
| PLACE OF BIRTH    = [[Southwark]], London, England
| DATE OF DEATH     =
| PLACE OF DEATH    =
}}
{{DEFAULTSORT:Macnab, Andy}}
[[Category:Special Air Service soldiers]]
[[Category:1959 births]]
[[Category:Living people]]
[[Category:British adoptees]]
[[Category:British novelists]]
[[Category:British non-fiction writers]]
[[Category:Recipients of the Distinguished Conduct Medal]]
[[Category:Recipients of the Military Medal]]
[[Category:Royal Green Jackets soldiers]]
[[Category:People from Southwark]]
[[Category:Gulf War prisoners of war]]
[[Category:British prisoners of war]]
[[Category:British Army personnel of the Gulf War]]
[[Category:Pseudonymous writers]]

[[cs:Andy McNab]]
[[da:Andy McNab]]
[[de:Andy McNab]]
[[es:Andy McNab]]
[[fr:Andy McNab]]
[[it:Andy McNab]]
[[he:אנדי מקנב]]
[[hu:Andy McNab]]
[[nl:Andy McNab]]
[[ja:アンディ・マクナブ]]
[[no:Andy McNab]]
[[pl:Andy McNab]]
[[ru:Энди Макнаб]]
[[fi:Andy McNab]]
[[sv:Andy McNab]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
