<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="10894" ns="0" title="The Free Software Definition"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">'''The Free Software Definition''', written by [[Richard Stallman]] and published by [[Free Software Foundation]] (FSF), defines [[free software]], as a matter of liberty, not price. The term &quot;free&quot; is used in the sense of &quot;free speech,&quot; not of &quot;free beer.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;http://www.gnu.org/philosophy/free-sw.html&lt;/ref&gt; The earliest known publication of the definition was in the February 1986 edition&lt;ref name=&quot;bull6&quot;&gt;{{cite web
|url=http://www.gnu.org/bulletins/bull1.txt
|title=GNU's Bulletin, Volume 1 Number 1, page 8
}}&lt;/ref&gt; of the now-discontinued GNU's Bulletin publication of FSF.  The canonical source for the document is in the philosophy section of the [[GNU Project]] website.  As of April 2008, it is published there in 39 languages.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
|url=http://www.gnu.org/philosophy/free-sw.html#translations
|title=The Free Software Definition - Translations of this page
}}&lt;/ref&gt;  FSF publishes a [[list of FSF approved software licenses|list of licenses which meet this definition]].

==The definition==
The definition published by FSF in February 1986 had two points:
&lt;blockquote&gt;
The word &quot;free&quot; in our name does not refer to price; it refers to freedom.  First, the freedom to copy a program and redistribute it to your neighbors, so that they can use it as well as you.  Second, the freedom to change a program, so that you can control it instead of it controlling you; for this, the source code must be made available to
you.&lt;ref name=&quot;bull6&quot; /&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

The modern definition has four points, which it numbers zero to three in compliance with [[zero-based numbering]] common to computer systems.  It defines free software by whether or not the recipient has the following four freedoms:&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
|url=http://www.gnu.org/philosophy/free-sw.html
|title=The Free Software Definition
|accessdate=2007-06-18
}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* Freedom 0: The freedom to run the program for any purpose.
* Freedom 1: The freedom to study how the program works, and change it to make it do what you wish.
* Freedom 2: The freedom to redistribute copies so you can help your neighbor.
* Freedom 3: The freedom to improve the program, and release your improvements (and modified versions in general) to the public, so that the whole community benefits.

Freedoms 1 and 3 require [[source code]] to be available because studying and modifying software without its source code is highly impractical.

==Later definitions==
In July 1997, [[Bruce Perens]] published the [[Debian Free Software Guidelines]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
|author=Bruce Perens
|url=http://lists.debian.org/debian-announce/debian-announce-1997/msg00017.html
|title=Debian's &quot;Social Contract&quot; with the Free Software Community
|work=debian-announce mailing list
}}&lt;/ref&gt;  This was also used by [[Open Source Initiative]] (OSI) under the name &quot;''The Open Source Definition''&quot;, the only change being that use of the term &quot;free software&quot; was replaced by OSI's [[alternative term for free software]], &quot;open-source software&quot;.

==Free Software Definition vs Open Source Definition==
Despite the fundamental philosophical differences between the [[free software movement]] and the [[open source movement]], the official definitions of [[free software]] by the [[Free Software Foundation]] and of [[open source software]] by the [[Open Source Initiative]] basically refer to the same software licenses, with a few minor exceptions. While stressing the philosophical differences, the Free Software Foundation comments:
{{quotation|The term “open source” software is used by some people to mean more or less the same category as free software. It is not exactly the same class of software: they accept some licenses that we consider too restrictive, and there are free software licenses they have not accepted. However, the differences in extension of the category are small: nearly all free software is open source, and nearly all open source software is free.
|Free Software Foundation|http://www.gnu.org/philosophy/categories.html}}

==See also==
{{Portal|Free software}}
*[[Free software movement]]
*[[GNU Manifesto]]
*[[Definition of Free Cultural Works]]
*[[Debian Free Software Guidelines]]
*[[Open Source Definition]]

==External links==
*[http://www.gnu.org/philosophy/free-sw.html The Free Software Definition] - published by FSF
*[http://www.gnu.org/bulletins/bull1.txt GNU's Bulletin, volume 1, number 1] - a February 1986 document defining free software.  Possibly the first published definition.
*[http://fsfeurope.org/documents/freesoftware.en.html The Free Software Definition with notes], by [[Free Software Foundation Europe]]
*[http://www.gnu.org/philosophy/open-source-misses-the-point.html Why “Open Source” misses the point of Free Software], by [[Richard Stallman]]

==References==
{{Reflist|2}}

{{FOSS}}

[[Category:Free software culture and documents]]

[[bn:মুক্ত সফটওয়্যার সংজ্ঞা]]
[[es:Definición de Software Libre]]
[[fa:تعریف نرم‌افزار آزاد]]
[[it:The Free Software Definition]]
[[ja:フリーソフトウェアの定義]]
[[nl:The Free Software Definition]]
[[pl:Definicja Wolnego Oprogramowania]]
[[ru:Определение свободного программного обеспечения]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
