<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="1092619" ns="0" title="Television in Malaysia"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{pp-semi|small=yes}}
{{Use mdy dates|date=September 2010}}
'''Malaysian television broadcasting''' started on 28 December [[Timeline of the introduction of television in countries|1963]] and re-introduced on 2 December 1983. Colour television was introduced on the same day. Full time colour transmissions were launched on 1 January [[Timeline of the introduction of color television in countries|1990]]. Until recently, Malaysia did not had any 100% government-owned stations until Kuala Lumpur became a Malaysian city in 2003. There are currently 6 [[free-to-air]] television stations in [[Malaysia]] and 3 [[Pay-per-view|pay-to-view]] based television networks.

Media Prima Berhad (who owns TV3 and ntv7) were Malaysia's national television provider until 2003 when Kuala Lumpur became a city in Malaysia. TV3 and ntv7 were also broadcasted over-the-fence to [[Kuala Lumpur]]. Kuala Lumpur had many radio stations, but the only station that broadcast to other states are FM 101.5, which are not actually broadcasted from Kuala Lumpur, but are broadcasted from Putrajaya. 


== Television providers ==

Subscription providers are available, with differences in the number of channels, capabilities such as the [[Electronic programme guide|programme guide]] (EPG), [[video on demand]] (VOD), [[high-definition television|high-definition]] (HD), [[interactive television]] via the [[Red Button (Digital Television)|red button]], and coverage across Malaysia. [[Set-top box]]es are generally used to receive these services. Households viewing TV from the internet are not tracked by the Malaysian government.

{| class=&quot;wikitable sortable&quot;
! Provider !! Free or [[pay television|pay]] !! No. broadcast channels !! [[Video on demand|VOD]] !! [[High-definition television|HD]] !! [[Red Button (digital television)|Red button]]
!align=&quot;right&quot;| Country of origin !! Transmission
|-
| [[Analogue terrestrial television in Malaysia|Analogue terrestrial]] || {{free|[[Free-to-air|Free]]}} ||  Up to 7  || {{No}} || {{No}} || {{No}}
|align=&quot;right&quot;| Malaysia || [[Analog television|Analogue]] [[Terrestrial television|terrestrial]]
|-
| [[Astro (satellite TV)|Astro]] || Pay TV || [[List of Astro channels|Around 130]] (TV and radio) || {{yes2}}[[Astro On Demand|Yes]] || {{Yes}} || {{Yes}}
|align=&quot;right&quot;| Malaysia || Digital satellite
|-
| [[Hypp.TV]]  || Free and subscription || 35 || {{No}} || {{No}} || {{No}}
|align=&quot;right&quot;| Malaysia || [[IPTV]]
|-
| [[UniFi]]  ||Subscription || 18 || {{Yes}} || {{Yes}} || {{No}}
|align=&quot;right&quot;| Malaysia|| [[IPTV]]
|-
| [[DETV]]  ||Subscription || 33 || {{No}} || {{No}} || {{No}}
|align=&quot;right&quot;| Malaysia || [[IPTV]]
|-
| [[U Television]] || {{nonfree}}Pay || {{unk}} || {{unk}} || {{unk}} || {{unk}}
|align=&quot;right&quot;| Malaysia|| [[Digital terrestrial television|Digital terrestrial]]
|-
| [[TrueVisions]] (from Thailand) || {{nonfree}}Pay || 200 (Thai+Inter, no MAS) || {{No}} || {{Yes}} || {{No}}
|align=&quot;right&quot;| Thailand|| Digital satellite from Thailand
|}

== Analogue terrestrial television ==
This is currently the traditional way of receiving television in Malaysia, however it has now largely been supplanted by digital providers.  There are 7 channels; three of them are government-owned by Radio Televisyen Malaysia (RTM) the 2 television channels terrestrial free-to-air RTM TV1 (TV1) and RTM TV2; one by Al Hijrah Media Corporation, which operates '''[[TV Alhijrah]]'''; '''[[TV3 (Malaysia)|TV3]]''', '''[[ntv7]]''', '''[[8TV (Malaysia)|8TV]]''' and '''[[TV9 (Malaysia)|TV9]]''' are private-owned, namely by a single operator '''[[Media Prima]]'''. Analogue terrestrial transmissions were scheduled to be switched off in phases as part of the digital switchover, expected to be completed in [[2015]] as a recommendation from ASEAN, however, it does not come to effect. The frequency has been moved to avoid signal jamming with television in [[Thailand]].


{| class=&quot;wikitable sortable&quot;
!Name
!Network
!Owner
!Launch date
!Channel ([[Kuala Lumpur|KL]])
!Broadcasting area
!Transmitted area
!Broadcasting hours
!Formerly known as
|-
|[[TV1 (Malaysia)|TV1]]
|[[Radio Televisyen Malaysia]]
|Government
|28 December 1963
|12 (UHF)
|[[Klang Valley]]
|[[Kuala Lumpur]]
|07:30-01:00
|-
|[[TV2 (Malaysia)|TV2]]
|Radio Televisyen Malaysia
|Government
|17 November 1969
|15 (UHF)
|Klang Valley
|Kuala Lumpur
|24-hours
|-
|[[TV3 (Malaysia)|TV3]]
|Sistem Televisyen Malaysia Berhad
|[[Media Prima Berhad]]
|1 June 1984
|29 (UHF)
|Klang Valley
|Kuala Lumpur
|06:30-00:00
|-
|[[ntv7]]
|Natseven TV Sdn Bhd
|Media Prima Berhad
|7 April 1998
|21 (UHF)
|Klang Valley
|Kuala Lumpur
|07:00-02:00
|-
|[[8TV (Malaysia)|8TV]]
|Metropolitan TV Sdn Bhd
|Media Prima Berhad
|8 January 2004
|25 (UHF)
|Klang Valley
|Kuala Lumpur
|07:00-03:00
|Metrovision
|-
|[[TV9 (Malaysia)|TV9]]
|Channel 9 Sdn Bhd
|Media Prima Berhad
|22 April 2006
|42 (UHF)
|Klang Valley
|Kuala Lumpur
|07:00-01:00
|Channel 9
|-
|[[TV Alhijrah|TV AlHijrah]]
|AlHijrah Media Corporation
|Government 
|7 December 2010
|55 (UHF)
|Klang Valley
|Kuala Lumpur
|12:00-00:00 &lt;br&gt; (07:00-00:00 on Weekends)
|
|}

== Digital terrestrial television ==
In 2005, the Ministry of Information announced their plan to digitalise nationwide [[free-to-air]] TV broadcasts led by Radio Televisyen Malaysia (RTM).&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://english.people.com.cn/200510/06/eng20051006_212641.html|title=Malaysia to launch digital TV trial program|date=2005-10-06|accessdate=2008-06-21}}&lt;/ref&gt; Trial broadcasts were undertaken, involving one thousand households in the [[Klang Valley]] from September 2006 till February 2007. According to the then-Deputy Minister of Information, [[Chia Kwang Chye]], the trial received &quot;very positive&quot; feedback, i.e. &quot;more than 60 percent said the quality of the signal ranged from good to very good. Over 88 percent said the picture quality improved, while 70 percent said the sound quality was better.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;abu&quot;&gt;{{cite news|title=Malaysia adopts DVB-T standard for digital broadcast transmissions|url=http://www.dvb.org/about_dvb/dvb_worldwide/malaysia/index.xml|publisher=[[Asia-Pacific Broadcasting Union|ABU]]|date=2007-03-28|accessdate=2008-06-21}}&lt;/ref&gt;

On 1 January 2008, TV3 announced that they were carrying out their own tests using a completely different system, [[Digital Multimedia Broadcasting|T-DMB]]. However their test transmission is available only to areas surrounding their main headquarters at Sri Pentas, [[Bandar Utama]], [[Petaling Jaya]]. The test signals consists of a single DAB stream, [[Fly FM]], and two T-DMB streams, '''[[TV3 (Malaysia)|TV3]]''' and a Hot Visual, which carries a slide show with audio signal streamed from the radio station [[Hot FM (Malaysia)|Hot FM]].

Despite a success of RTM's pilot trials, the digital terrestrial television transition faced many problems. These problems stemmed from the lesser enthautism of content providers toward the digitisation, with the exception [[Les Copaque]], and the need to improve the nation's [[Internet]] broadband infrastructure. With the resignation of then Prime Minister [[Abdullah Badawi]] and the succession of [[Najib Tun Razak]], the project by RTM was deferred indefinitely.

== Satellite television ==
Malaysia's sole satellite television operator, Measat Broadcast Network Systems (a subsidiary of [[Astro All Asia Networks]]) launched the [[Astro (satellite TV)|Astro]] service in 1996. It currently holds exclusive rights from the Malaysian government to offer satellite television broadcasting services in the country through the year 2017. The rights was extended to 2022 recently.{{Citation needed|date=March 2009}} Now, [[big ugly dish]]es are still found in Malaysia.

There are also laws preventing too many advertisements from being aired on both radio and television, similar to the United Kingdom.{{Citation needed|date=March 2009}}

=== International broadcast ===
Malaysians in the [[United States]] and [[Canada]] can view TV shows instantly from Malaysia by [[SES-1]] satellite, including television from [[Thailand]] and [[Laos]], the channel broadcast are [[Malay Fun TV]], [[Malaysia Sports]] (these stations are Malay-language TV in the USA), [[TVSelangor]], [[Global TV]] (live from Malaysia).

== Cable television ==
[[Mega TV (Malaysia)|Mega TV]] was launched in 1994 by [[TV3 (Malaysia)|TV3]] as the only cable television service. However, it faced stiff competition from the satellite television network [[Astro (satellite TV)|Astro]], and failed to expand its content. Because of this, it closed down in 2001, and was replaced by its competitor since then. {{Citation needed|date=June 2010}}

== IP television (IPTV) ==
In contrast to Internet TV, IPTV refers to services operated and controlled by a single company, who may also control the 'Final Mile' to the consumers' premises.

[[DETV]], a new paid television provider owned by [[REDtone]], provides television and [[video-on-demand]] services on the [[IPTV]] platform, targeting the [[Chinese Malaysian|Chinese]] audiences in Malaysia.

[[Telekom Malaysia|TM]] is expected to launch its IPTV services, currently branded [[Hypp.TV]] in the second quarter of 2009, and now conducts trials with 1,000 selected households in Klang Valley, [[Penang]] and [[Kulim]], [[Kedah]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|author=Goh, T. E.|title=TM sees IPTV commercial roll-out in 12 months|url=http://209.85.175.104/search?q=cache:FKIuG0eYNw4J:www.btimes.com.my/Current_News/BTIMES/Thursday/Nation/gohsg.xml/Article/index_html+%22TM+sees+IPTV+commercial+roll-out+in+12+months%22&amp;hl=en&amp;ct=clnk&amp;cd=1&amp;gl=my|publisher=[[Business Times (Kuala Lumpur)|Business Times]]|date=June 19, 2008|accessdate=June 21, 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt;

TM then successfully released their IPTV based on their [[High Speed Broadband - Unifi|HSBB Unifi]] service which only available to Unifi subscriber.

== Mobile television ==
Maxis, DiGi and U Mobile provide mobile television services for reception on [[3G|third generation]] mobile phones. They consist of a mixture of regular channels as well as made for mobile channels with looped content. Maxis TV now offers more than 20 channels to Maxis 3G subscribers who own compatible mobile phones.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.maxis.com.my/3G/maxistv/maxistv.asp|title=Maxis 3G in Action – Maxis TV|accessdate=June 21, 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt; Yet, Maxis is expected to roll out broadcast mobile TV services based on [[DVB-H]] in the near future.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title=Maxis completes DVB-H trial |url=http://www.mobileworld.com.my/v2/index.php/20070828335/Consumer/News/Maxis_completes_DVB-H_trial.html|publisher=Mobile World|date=August 28, 2007|accessdate=June 21, 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[U Mobile]] also provides broadcast mobile TV to users of selected 3G phones, also based on DVB-H.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|author=Timbuong, J.|title=U Mobile is newest cellular service provider|url=http://star-techcentral.com/tech/story.asp?file=/2007/9/20/technology/18926591&amp;sec=technology|publisher=[[The Star (Malaysia)|The Star]]|date=September 20, 2007|accessdate=June 21, 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In October 2008, Astro launched Astro Mobile TV which currently provides 18 channels, all of which are mobile versions of its existing channels, seven of them are under its own brand. This service is only available to Maxis subscribers with compatible [[2.5G]] or 3G handsets, and does not reprise its role from Maxis TV.

=== Internet television ===
Television received via the Internet may be free, subscription or pay-per-view, [[multicast]], [[unicast]], or [[peer-to-peer]], [[streaming media|streamed]] or [[download]]ed, and use a variety of distribution technologies.  Playback is normally via a computer and broadband Internet connection, although [[digital media receiver]]s or [[Home theater PC|media centre]] computers can be used for playback on televisions, such as a computer equipped with [[Windows Media Center]].

== See also ==
* [[List of television stations in Malaysia]]
*[[List of Malay language television channels]]

== References ==
{{Reflist|2}}

{{Television in Asia}}
{{Malaysia topics}}

[[Category:Television in Malaysia| ]]

[[id:Daftar stasiun televisi Malaysia]]
[[ms:Daftar Stesen Televisyen Malaysia]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
