<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="10971926" ns="0" title="List of EastEnders characters (2000)"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{DISPLAYTITLE:List of ''EastEnders'' characters (2000)}}
The following is a list of characters that first appeared in the [[BBC]] [[soap opera]] ''[[EastEnders]]'' in 2000, by order of first appearance.
{{TOClimit|limit=2}}

==Sandra di Marco==
{{Infobox soap character 2 | series = EastEnders
|image= 
|name=Sandra di Marco
|portrayer=[[Clare Wilkie]]
|years=2000–01
|born=27 August 1973
|first=3 January 2000
|last =19 March 2001
|classification=[[List of past EastEnders characters#Last appeared in 2001|Former; regular]]
|occupation=Personal assistant
|husband=[[Beppe di Marco]]
|sons=[[Joe di Marco]]
}}
'''Sandra di Marco''', played by [[Clare Wilkie]], was the estranged wife of [[Beppe di Marco]], and mother of his son [[Joe di Marco|Joe]]. She had walked out on the family when Joe was just one year old.

Sandra reappeared in Beppe and Joe's lives in 2000 when she tracked them down to [[Walford]]. She had left them because Beppe's family (particularly his grandparents [[Bruno di Marco|Bruno]] and [[Luisa di Marco|Luisa]]) resented her for not being [[Italy|Italian]]. Sandra wanted to go back to work after having Joe, but the family wouldn't allow it, and when Beppe started siding with his family on the issue, Sandra decided to leave him and her son. She later moved in with Beppe's police partner, [[#Jack Robbins|Jack Robbins]].

She left Jack to track down her son, and wormed her way back into Beppe's life. She attempted to get custody of Joe, while working as a personal assistant to [[Ian Beale]], but Beppe used dirty police tactics to prevent this. She eventually came to an agreement to visit Joe, and went back to Jack.
{{-}}

==Ralph Clemens==&lt;!-- This section is linked from [[Ralph Clemens]] --&gt;
{{Infobox soap character 2 | series = EastEnders
|image=
|name=Ralph Clemens
|portrayer=[[Nick Lumley]]
|years=2000
|first=31 January 2000
|last=1 February 2000
}}
'''Ralph Clemens''' was a man who wanted to buy [[Terry Raymond|Terry]] and [[Irene Raymond]]'s recently-purchased [[Triumph Motor Company|Triumph]] car. Terry originally refused to sell it for [[Pounds sterling|£]]1250,&lt;ref name=&quot;31J00&quot;&gt;&quot;[http://www.walford.net/update/20000131.htm MON 31-JAN-00]&quot;, ''walford.net''. URL last accessed 2007-04-26.&lt;/ref&gt; but Ralph then bought the car for £2500.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;[http://www.walford.net/update/20000201.htm TUE 01-FEB-00]&quot;, ''walford.net''. URL last accessed 2007-04-26.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Helen Graham&quot;&gt;&quot;[http://www.walfordweb.co.uk/walfordweb/whoswho-show.php?id=584 Helen Graham]&quot;, ''Walford Web''. URL last accessed 2007-04-26.&lt;/ref&gt;
{{-}}

==Will Harper==&lt;!-- This section is linked from [[Will Harper]] --&gt;
{{Infobox soap character 2 | series = EastEnders
|image=
|name=Will Harper
|portrayer=[[Douglas Fielding]]
|years=2000
|first=31 January 2000
|last=1 February 2000
|occupation=Private investigator
}}
'''Will Harper''' was a private investigator who was hired by [[Steve Owen (EastEnders)|Steve Owen]] to find out who was terrorising him by slashing his tyres, covering his flat in red paint and vandalising his nightclub, [[Scarlet (EastEnders)#e20|e20]]. At first Steve suspected [[Claudia Fielding]], but Harper confirmed that she was residing in America.&lt;ref name=&quot;31J00&quot;/&gt; The culprit turned out to be [[Matthew Rose (EastEnders)|Matthew Rose]], but he got to Steve before Harper could figure this out.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;[http://www.walfordweb.co.uk/walfordweb/whoswho-show.php?id=595 Will Harper]&quot;, ''Walford Web''. URL last accessed 2007-04-26.&lt;/ref&gt;
{{-}}

==Laura Beale==
{{Main|Laura Beale}}

==Sophie Braddock==
{{Infobox soap character 2 | series = EastEnders
|image=
|name=Sophie Braddock
|portrayer=[[Hayley Angel Wardle]]
|years=2000
|first=17 February 2000
|last=18 September 2000
|occupation=Student
}}
'''Sophie Braddock''' attended Walford High School with [[Sonia Fowler|Sonia Jackson]], [[Nicky di Marco]] and [[Jamie Mitchell]]. Sonia was jealous of her and nicknamed her &quot;'''Braddock the Haddock'''&quot;. Jamie asked her out on a date, much to the annoyance of Sonia. The date went well, and Jamie was shocked when Sophie had [[sexual intercourse|sex]] with him in his godfather [[Phil Mitchell|Phil]]'s bed.
{{-}}

==Maureen Carter==
{{Infobox soap character 2 | series = EastEnders
|image=
|name=Maureen Carter
|portrayer=[[Diana Coupland]]
|years=2000
|first=4 May 2000
|last=1 June 2000
|nieces=[[Irene Raymond]]
}}

'''Maureen Carter''' was [[Irene Raymond]]'s aunt. Maureen arrived in [[Walford]] visiting Irene and her husband [[Terry Raymond|Terry]]. She was unpopular with Terry, and outstayed her welcome, eventually leaving Walford and going home. While she was living in [[Albert Square]], she tried to seduce [[Jim Branning]]. With Jim's annoyance of Maureen, one night during a party at the [[Queen Vic]], [[Dot Cotton]] and Jim were at the back of the pub, Maureen wanted to treat Jim for a night of fun, she came round the side, quickly Jim grabbed Dot and kissed her, she saw them and ran off. When she left, Dot slapped Jim, 2 years later Dot and Jim got married. After Maureen found them kissing, she quickly left Walford.
{{-}}

==Rod Morris ==
{{Infobox soap character 2 | series = EastEnders
|image=
|name=Rod Morris
|portrayer=[[Forbes Masson]]
|years=2000
|first=25 May 2000
|last=27 July 2000
|wife=[[#Fiona Morris|Fiona Morris]]
|occupation= Tutor
}}
'''Rodney &quot;Rod&quot; Morris''' was the tutor of [[Nicky di Marco]] who had been contacted by her mother [[Rosa di Marco|Rosa]] in order to help Nicky study for her exams. Nicky became attracted to Rod and went out of her way to make him notice her by doing her hair differently and wearing different outfits. On Rod's next visit, he bought Nicky a copy of [[Five (band)|Five]]'s album [[Invincible (5ive album)|Invincible]] (which she had been saving up for) as a reward for her hard work. 

As time passed, Nicky's feelings for Rod begin to run deeper. On June 15, Rod told Nicky she had caught up enough and they could end the lessons. Nicky desperately tried to convince Rosa to have a word with Rod in order to get him to change his mind. On June 17, Rod and his wife [[#Fiona Morris|Fiona]] came to the diMarcos for dinner and it was obvious to Fiona that Nicky had a crush on her husband.

On June 29, Nicky was found in tears by Rosa and her brother, [[Gianni di Marco|Gianni]] stating that Rod had attacked her. Rod was then arrested, questioned and later bailed. 

On July 6, Rod was attacked by a drunken Gianni who had come to avenge his sister. Gianni was then subsequently arrested and charged with GBH and drink-driving. 

Nicky later admitted she was the one to kiss Rod and he reciprocated. The end result was Rod admitting to not being able to control himself, and escaping a 15-year prison sentence.
{{-}}

==Barbara Owen==
{{Infobox soap character 2 | series = EastEnders
|image=
|name=Barbara Owen
|portrayer=[[Sheila Hancock]]
|years=2000–01
|first=6 July 2000
|last=24 July 2001
|death=26 July 2001
|sons=[[Steve Owen (EastEnders)|Steve Owen]]
|daughters=[[Jackie Owen]]
}}
'''Barbara Jacqueline Owen'''  was first seen in July 2000 as [[Steve Owen (EastEnders)|Steve]] and [[Jackie Owen]]'s poisonous mother. At the time, Steve was going through a [[drugs]] problem and visited his mother after finding out she was dying of [[heart disease]]. Barbara was obsessed with the [[British Royal Family]], though not so caring about her own children.

Barbara attended Steve's wedding to [[Melanie Owen|Melanie]] in March 2001, taking a shine to his nemesis [[Phil Mitchell]], to the point of putting his [[photograph]] on her [[fireplace mantel]].

Steve visited Barbara in July 2001 when she was in a critical condition and confronted her about the abuse she'd showered on him when he was a child. She tried to defend her actions by saying her husband left her to bring up two children with no money. She refused to let Steve call an ambulance and asked him to kiss her. He gave a peck on the forehead but she asked for a kiss on the lips. When he leant forward, she grabbed him and gave him an extremely passionate kiss, telling him he was an attractive man. Steve was disgusted and left. Barbara died soon after.

Melanie was the only person in attendance at Barbara's funeral, while Steve was playing away with another woman.

When Steve died in a car accident in March 2002, his ashes were dumped on Barbara's grave by Phil.
{{-}}

==Fiona Morris ==
&lt;!-- {{Infobox soap character 2 | series = EastEnders
|image=
|name=Fiona Morris
|portrayer=[[Ashley Jensen]]
|years=2000
|first=6 July 2000
|last=11 July 2000
|husband=[[#Rod Morris|Rod Morris]]
}} --&gt;
[[File:Ashley Jensen.jpg|thumb|160px|Scottish actresss Ashley Jenson, who played Fiona Morris.]]
'''Fiona Morris''', played by [[Ashley Jensen]], is [[#Rod Morris|Rod Morris]]'s wife, who appears between 6 and 11 July 2000. Rod had tutored [[Nicky di Marco]] for her maths and Fiona first appeared when Nicky's brother [[Gianni di Marco|Gianni]] came to the Morrises' home and attacked Rod, who Nicky had accused of sexually assaulting her. Fiona tried to fend Gianni off but was shoved to the floor in the process. Several days later, Fiona appeared in Albert Square and cornered Nicky in an attempt to get her to drop her case against Rod but was interrupted when a journalist entered the scene to ask Nicky about the events, prompting her to flee. Later, Nicky, her mother [[Rosa di Marco|Rosa]] and Gianni arrived to confront Fiona after she had labelled Nicky a &quot;tart&quot; and the two began a screaming match in which Fiona stated that Nicky had been flirting with Rod for weeks and that Rod had been a teacher for the past 11 years and had never behaved inappropriately towards a student. This was her last appearance and all the charges against her husband were dropped.

==Jack Robbins==
&lt;!-- {{Infobox soap character 2 | series = EastEnders
|image=
|name=Jack Robbins
|portrayer=[[Chook Sibtain]]
|years=2000-01
|first=21 August 2000
|last=19 March 2001
|occupation = Police Officer
}} --&gt;
'''Jack Robbins''', played by [[Chook Sibtain]], is a former police colleague of [[Beppe di Marco]] and a former lover of Beppe's wife, [[#Sandra di Marco|Sandra]], who first appears on 21 August 2000. Jack tries to win Sandra back but she is insistent that she loves Beppe having reconciled with him several months earlier. Despite this, Jack and Sandra begin an affair. When Beppe finds out he tries to exact rervenge by having Max, another colleague, plant drugs in Jack's house. When Jack turns up at the hospital to see Sandra who is visiting her and Beppe's son [[Joe di Marco|Joe]], Jack reveals the charges did not stick. Jack made his last appearance on 19 March 2001.

==Charlie Slater==
{{Main|Charlie Slater}}

==Mo Harris==
{{Main|Mo Harris}}

==Lynne Hobbs==
{{Main|Lynne Hobbs}}

==Garry Hobbs==
{{Main|Garry Hobbs}}

==Kat Moon==
{{Main|Kat Moon}}

==Little Mo Mitchell==
{{Main|Little Mo Mitchell}}

==Zoe Slater==
{{Main|Zoe Slater}}

==Eddie Skinner==
{{Infobox soap character 2 
|series = EastEnders
|image= 
|name=Eddie Skinner
|portrayer=[[Richard Vanstone]]
|years=2000–01
|first=18 September 2000
|last= 15 February 2001
|occupation=
|family=
|uncles = William Skinner
|daughters = [[Kerry Skinner]]
}}
'''Edward &quot;Eddie&quot; Skinner''' arrived in Walford on 18 September 2000 on the day of his aunt [[Ethel Skinner]]'s funeral and later began lodging with the Fowlers at number 45, along with his daughter, Kerry. Eddie later began working on [[Mark Fowler|Mark]]'s stall and later developed a crush on Mark's mother [[Pauline Fowler|Pauline]], but it was not reciprocated. It was revealed [[Nick Cotton]] had spent some time inside with Eddie and was about to reveal this to Pauline, but Eddie told her first. Eddie later left the Square, his whereabouts are currently unknown.{{-}}

==Adam Cherry==
{{Infobox soap character 2 | series = EastEnders
|image=
|name=Adam Cherry
|portrayer=[[Michael Fenton Stevens]]
|years=2000
|appeared=18 September 2000
|occupation=Vicar
}}
'''The Reverend Adam Cherry''' was the vicar who conducted [[Ethel Skinner]]'s funeral in September 2000.
{{-}}

==Kevin==
&lt;!-- {{Infobox soap character 2
|series=EastEnders
|name=Kevin
|portrayer=
|years=2000
|born=1960s
|first=19 September 2000
|last =10 October 2000
|classification=[[List of past EastEnders characters#Last appeared in 2001|Former; recurring]]
|occupation=Unemployed
}} --&gt;
'''Kevin''' is the ex-boyfriend of [[Kat Slater]]. He appears unexpectedly on 19 September 2000 and calls Kat after [[Melanie Owen]] tells him where Kat and her family live. Kat and Kevin have a row with the neighbours watching, but are interrupted when Kat's grandmother [[Mo Harris]] soaks him with water and Kat's father [[Charlie Slater|Charlie]] takes him home in his cab. He returns on 25 September, when he calls in the middle of the night. Mo soaks him with water again. He returns to number 23 and asks Charlie where Kat is. He goes to [[The Queen Victoria]] pub and finds Kat and her relatives [[Lynne Hobbs|Lynne]], [[Zoe Slater|Zoe]] and [[Little Mo Mitchell|Little Mo]] dancing. He tries to win Kat back but she rejects him. He returns again on 9 October, and Mo tells him Kat is not in the house. Kevin is convinced that Mo is lying and chains himself to the gate outside. Kevin escapes and Kat tells him to back off. He is not seen again.
{{-}}

==James Stocksbridge==
{{Infobox soap character 2 | series = EastEnders
|image=
|name=James Stocksbridge
|portrayer=[[Peter Hamilton-Dyer]]
|years=2000
|appeared=21 September 2000
|occupation=Solicitor
}}
'''James Stocksbridge''' was Ian Beale's solicitor when he was declared bankrupt.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;[http://www.walfordweb.co.uk/walfordweb/whoswho-show.php?id=892 James Stocksbridge]&quot;, ''Walford Web''. URL last accessed 2007-04-26.&lt;/ref&gt; He also mentioned to [[Sandra di Marco]] that he had worked with Ian to win custody of his children, [[Steven Beale|Steven]], [[Peter Beale|Peter]] and [[Lucy Beale|Lucy]], as Sandra wanted to gain custody of her son [[Joe di Marco|Joe]] from her ex-husband [[Beppe di Marco|Beppe]].&lt;ref&gt;&quot;[http://www.walford.net/update/20000921.htm THU 21-SEP-00]&quot;, ''walford.net''. URL last accessed 2007-06-13.&lt;/ref&gt;
{{-}}

==Kerry Skinner==
{{Infobox soap character 2 
|series = EastEnders
|image= 
|name=Kerry Skinner
|portrayer=[[Gemma McKluskie]]
|years=2000–01
|first= 19 October 2000
|last=8 March 2001
|born=
|occupation=
|father=[[Eddie Skinner]]
|great uncles = William Skinner
}}
'''Kerry Skinner'''  arrived in Walford on 19 October 2000, as a friend of [[Zoe Slater]] and the great niece of the late [[Ethel Skinner]]. Kerry briefly dated [[Robbie Jackson]] and got him to propose to her. However, things didn't work out, as it turned out that Kerry had been engaged to another man, Darren, while she was on holiday. Kerry soon left the Square and hasn't been seen or heard of since.
{{-}}

==Rebecca Miller==
{{Infobox soap character 2 | series = EastEnders
|image= 
|name=Rebecca Miller
|portrayer=[[Jade Sharif]] &lt;small&gt;(2005–07)&lt;/small&gt;
|introducer=[[John Yorke (television producer)|John Yorke]] &lt;small&gt;(2000, 2002)&lt;/small&gt;&lt;br&gt;[[Kathleen Hutchison]] &lt;small&gt;(2005)&lt;/small&gt;
|years=2000, 2002, 2005–07
|born=26 October 2000
|first=26 October 2000
|last=2 February 2007
|home=[[London]]
|classification=[[List of past EastEnders characters#Last appeared in 2007|Former; regular]]
|family=[[Beale family|Beale]]/[[Branning family|Branning]]
|mother=[[Sonia Fowler]]
|father=[[Martin Fowler (EastEnders)|Martin Fowler]]
|adoptivefather=[[Neil Miller (EastEnders)|Neil Miller]]
|adoptivemother=[[Sue Miller (EastEnders)|Sue Miller]]
|grandmothers=[[Pauline Fowler]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Carol Jackson]]&lt;br&gt;[[Margaret Wilson (EastEnders)|Margaret Wilson]] &lt;small&gt;(adoptive)&lt;/small&gt;
|grandfathers = [[Arthur Fowler]]
}}
'''Rebecca Chloe Miller''' (née '''Chloe Jackson''') is the daughter of [[Martin Fowler]] and [[Sonia Fowler|Sonia Jackson]]. She was delivered by [[Mo Harris]] on 26 October 2000. Fifteen-year-old Sonia didn't know she was pregnant. Chloe was the result of an underage fling between Sonia and Martin. She was subsequently given up for adoption to [[Neil Miller (EastEnders)|Neil]] and [[Sue Miller (EastEnders)|Sue Miller]]. The Millers changed Chloe's name to Rebecca.

In 2002, Sonia, who had delved into [[clinical depression|depression]] over the guilt of abandoning her daughter, kidnapped Rebecca. While Sonia barricaded herself inside her house, the Millers gave [[Dot Branning]] fifteen minutes to persuade Sonia to hand Rebecca over before they phoned the police. Dot successfully persuaded Sonia to hand Rebecca over.

In 2005, Neil and Sue were killed in a [[car crash]], and Rebecca moved in with Sue's mother, [[Margaret Wilson (EastEnders)|Margaret Wilson]]. The news of the crash was read by Sonia in the newspaper, and she and Martin, who were now married, grew concerned for their daughter and decided to track her down to make sure she was well. Posing as friends of the Millers, Margaret allowed the Fowlers into their home and it was only when they admitted who they really were that she told them to get out.
[[Pauline Fowler]], Martin's mother, demanded to be part of Rebecca's life, causing upset. Sonia was furious when she discovered Pauline and Martin had been seeing her daughter behind her back. Eventually Sonia gave into her urges and grew closer to Rebecca too. Margaret decided to make Sonia and Martin Rebecca's legal guardians in case anything happened to her. Margaret was unaware that Sonia and Martin had separated due to Sonia's lesbian adultery; Sonia persuaded Martin to pretend to Margaret that they were still a couple, but when the truth came out, Margaret was furious and she refused to give Sonia guardianship of Rebecca. When Margaret had a fall and died, Rebecca was given to Martin and Pauline refused Sonia access, causing many rows. 

Sonia and Martin reunited in December 2006. On Christmas Day 2006, Pauline died when she was about to move to America. Rebecca had seen Sonia slapping Pauline before her death and believed that Sonia killed Pauline. Sonia tried to hush Rebecca, but the truth came out and Sonia was arrested following a row with Martin. After absconding with Rebecca, Sonia was cleared of Pauline's murder when [[Joe Macer]], Pauline's husband, admitted to manslaughter.

For Rebecca and Martin's sake, Sonia tearfully left Walford; however, Martin opted to go with her, and he, Sonia and Rebecca left Walford as a family in February 2007.
{{-}}

==Ameena Badawi==
{{Infobox soap character 2 | series = EastEnders
|image=
|name=Ameena Badawi
|portrayer=[[Shobna Gulati]]
|first=30 October 2000
|last=14 December 2000
|years=2000
|occupation=Social worker
}}
'''Ameena Badawi''' was [[Sonia Fowler|Sonia Jackson]]'s [[social worker]] when Sonia gave birth to baby [[Rebecca Miller (EastEnders)|Chloe]] in 2000, aged 15. Ameena tried to persuade Sonia that it would be best to try and bond with her baby. She also thought it would be best for Sonia to tell her mother, [[Carol Jackson|Carol]] that she now had a baby.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;[http://www.walfordweb.co.uk/walfordweb/whoswho-fullprofile.php?fn=Ameena&amp;ln=Badawi Ameena Badawi]&quot;, ''Walford Web''. URL last accessed 3 April 2008&lt;/ref&gt;

Ameena was later promoted, and Sonia's case was taken over by [[#Diane Irving|Diane Irving]].&lt;ref name=&quot;DianeI&quot;&gt;&quot;[http://www.walfordweb.co.uk/walfordweb/whoswho-fullprofile.php?fn=Diane&amp;ln=Irving Diane Irving]&quot;, ''Walford Web''. URL last accessed 3 April 2008&lt;/ref&gt; 
{{-}}

==Audrey Trueman==
{{Infobox soap character 2 | series = EastEnders
|image= 
|name=Audrey Trueman
|portrayer=[[Corinne Skinner-Carter]]
|years=2000–01
|first= 6 November 2000
|last= 7 September 2001
|death= 7 September 2001
|classification=[[List of past EastEnders characters#Last appeared in 2001|Former; regular]]
|occupation=[[Businessperson|Bed and Breakfast owner]]
|husband=[[Patrick Trueman]] (1968–2001)
|sons=[[Paul Trueman]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Anthony Trueman]]
|granddaughters=[[Eleanor Trueman]]
|sisters=Julia
}}
'''Audrey Trueman''' is the mother of [[Anthony Trueman|Anthony]] and [[Paul Trueman]] and later revealed to be the ex-wife of current character [[Patrick Trueman]].

Audrey was introduced by executive producer [[John Yorke (television producer)|John Yorke]] as the matriarch of a new black family moving to Walford in November 2000. Portrayed as a &quot;busy body&quot;, Audrey was axed in September 2001. Actress [[Corinne Skinner-Carter]] has revealed in 2008, that she believes Audrey was axed because of creative differences she had with the writers about Audrey's backstory: &quot;I received a script and it was all about how Audrey’s first job in England had been as a lavatory cleaner, how she had worked her way up from that to become a B&amp;B owner. I didn’t think it was appropriate and I told them so – she may have come from the bottom but not from the bottom of a toilet!”.&lt;ref name=&quot;audrey&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.thecnj.com/review/2008/102308/feature102308_02.html?headline=Corinne_and_the_killing_of_Audrey|title=Corinne and the killing of Audrey|date=23 October 2008|work=Camden New Journal|author=Angela Cobbinah|accessdate=2009-05-20}}&lt;/ref&gt;  Although the toilet cleaner reference was dropped, shortly after Skinner-Carter was informed about &quot;a fantastic development in the script – Audrey was going to be killed off.” Audrey died of a [[brain hemorrhage]] in September 2001.&lt;ref name=&quot;audrey&quot;/&gt;

===Storylines===
Audrey moved to Walford in 2000, taking over the Bed and Breakfast, where she lived with her son [[Dr. Anthony Trueman]]. A religious woman, she became deeply involved with his life, whilst ignoring her other son, tearaway [[Paul Trueman|Paul]]. She didn't approve of Anthony dating [[Kat Slater]] and tried to interfere many times, leading to Anthony rebelling against his mother. 

Audrey's main reason for ignoring Paul was, that in the past, Paul and Anthony had been in a car crash that had crippled a young girl. Anthony was drunk at the time and was driving but Paul took the blame and went to prison. Audrey was unaware of this and continued to ignore Paul despite his attempts at making her notice him. 

In September 2001, Audrey suffered a blow to the head accidentally after being struck by falling debris while walking past some building works. Several days later, after an argument with Paul during which he revealed Anthony was the one who was driving at the time of the accident, Audrey collapsed and suffered a severe headache, caused by a delayed reaction to the blow she received earlier.

Just before she died, Audrey told Paul that she knew about Anthony being the driver and told Paul to tell Anthony that she loved him and Paul said &quot;What about me?&quot;. Just as Audrey was about to say something to him she died. However, everything was left to Paul in Audrey's will. Audrey's ex-husband [[Patrick Trueman|Patrick]] arrived in Walford for her funeral. It was subsequently revealed that he and Audrey married in a [[shotgun wedding]], after Audrey fell pregnant with Paul. Patrick left shortly after Anthony's birth in the early 1970s. The Truemans later discovered that despite Audrey's claims, Paul was not actually Patrick's son; he was the biological child of [[Milton Hibbert]], Patrick's friend with whom Audrey had been having an affair.
{{-}}

==John Charrington==&lt;!-- This section is linked from [[John Charrington]] --&gt;
{{Infobox soap character 2 | series = EastEnders
|image=
|name=John Charrington
|portrayer=[[Jeremy Gittins]]
|years=2000
|first=13 November 2000
|last=14 December 2000
|occupation=[[Accountant]]
}}
'''John Charrington''' was [[Ian Beale]]'s accountant. He advised Ian not to invest in the construction of flats in [[Walford]], a piece of advice Ian ignored, which led to him eventually being declared bankrupt.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;[http://www.walfordweb.co.uk/walfordweb/whoswho-show.php?id=458 John Charrington]&quot;, ''Walford Web''. URL last accessed 2007-04-26.&lt;/ref&gt;
{{-}}

==Helen Graham==&lt;!-- This section is linked from [[Helen Graham]] --&gt;
{{Infobox soap character 2 | series = EastEnders
|image=
|name=Helen Graham
|portrayer=[[Daisy Beaumont]]
|appeared=16 November 2000
|years=2000
}}
'''Helen Graham''' was an employee of the housing association interested in buying the flats Ian Beale was having built, until he was declared bankrupt.&lt;ref name=&quot;Helen Graham&quot;/&gt;
{{-}}

==Danny Harrison==
{{Infobox soap character 2 | series = EastEnders
|image=
|name=Danny Harrison
|portrayer=[[Eddie Osei]]
|years=2000
|first = 12 September 2000
|last= 11 December 2000
|occupation=Building contractor
}}
'''Danny Harrison''' was a building contractor who was working on 'Beale's Homes' in 2000, converting a [[school]] into [[apartment|flats]] for [[Ian Beale]]. He was upset when Ian went behind his back and went to another building contractor.

Ian refused to pay Danny, so he spread rumours of Ian's financial situation, which eventually reached the new builders working on the development, causing a workers' strike. When Ian didn't pay Danny, he was eventually declared [[bankrupt]].
{{-}}

==Anthony Trueman==
{{Main|Anthony Trueman}}

==Trevor Morgan==
{{Main|Trevor Morgan (EastEnders)}}

==References==
{{Reflist}}

==External links==
*{{EEcharlink|audrey_t|Audrey Trueman}}

{{EastEnders}}
{{EastEnders characters|year}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:List Of Eastenders Characters (2000)}}
[[Category:Lists of EastEnders characters|2000]]
[[Category:Fictional characters introduced in 2000|*, EastEnders]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
