<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="1098410" ns="0" title="Osaka University"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Infobox University
| name = Osaka University
| native_name = {{lang|ja|大阪大学}} 
| image = [[File:Osaka University logo.svg|150px|Osaka University logo]]
| motto = {{lang|ja|地域に生き世界に伸びる}}&lt;br /&gt;(Live Locally, Grow Globally)
| established = Founded in 1724 ([[Kaitokudo]]),&lt;br /&gt;Chartered on November 22, 1919 as Osaka Prefectural Medical College. Re-established on May 1, 1931 as Osaka Imperial University.
| type = [[National university|Public (National)]]
| endowment = US$2.3 [[1000000000 (number)|billion]]{{Citation needed|date=February 2008}}&lt;br /&gt;(JP¥264.3 billion){{Citation needed|date=February 2008}}| 
 President = [[Kiyokazu Washida]]
| city = [[Suita, Osaka|Suita]]
| province = [[Osaka]]
| country = [[Japan]]
| students = 25,248&lt;ref name=&quot;Outline&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.osaka-u.ac.jp/en/guide/about/outline.html|title=Osaka University: Outline of the University|accessdate=2010-01-14}}&lt;/ref&gt;
| undergrad = 15,937
| postgrad = 7,856
| other = 1,780 (international students)&lt;ref name=&quot;Outline&quot;/&gt;
| profess = 292
| international = 1,780&lt;ref name=&quot;Outline&quot;/&gt;
| faculty = 2,953 (academic)&lt;ref name=&quot;Outline&quot;/&gt;
| staff = 8,675 (total)&lt;ref name=&quot;Outline&quot;/&gt;
| campus = [[Suburban]] / [[Urban area|Urban]],&lt;br /&gt;1.59 km²|&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.osaka-u.ac.jp/en/guide/about/outline.html Facts &amp; Figures of the University — Osaka University]. Osaka-u.ac.jp (2010-05-01). Retrieved on 2011-06-26.&lt;/ref&gt;
 colors         = [[Sky blue]]
| free_label = Authorized Student Groups
| free = 58 sports-related, 68 culture-related groups &lt;ref&gt;[http://www.osaka-u.ac.jp/en/campus/circle-club/ Introduction to Official Student Groups — Osaka University]. Osaka-u.ac.jp (2010-10-13). Retrieved on 2011-06-26.&lt;/ref&gt;
| affiliations   = [[APRU]], [[AEARU]]
| mascot = ''Macchi'' the Crocodile (unofficial)
| fightsong      = ''Yūyūshiku susumen''
| website = [http://www.osaka-u.ac.jp/en/index.html www.osaka-u.ac.jp]
| footnotes      = 
| address        = 
| telephone      = 
| coor           = 
| logo           = 
}} 
{{nihongo|'''Osaka University'''|大阪大学|Ōsaka daigaku}}, or {{nihongo|Handai|阪大|Handai}}, is a major national university located in [[Osaka]], Japan. It is the sixth oldest university in Japan as the '''Osaka Prefectural Medical College''', and formerly one of the [[Imperial university|Imperial Universities]] of Japan. Numerous prominent scientists worked at the Osaka University such as the Nobel Laureate in Physics [[Hideki Yukawa]].

==History==
{{Portal|Osaka University}}
Academic traditions of the university reach back to {{nihongo|'''''[[Kaitokudō]]'''''|懐徳堂}}, an [[Edo period|Edo-period]] school for local citizens founded in 1724, and {{nihongo|'''''[[Tekijuku]]'''''|適塾|}}, a school of ''[[Rangaku]]'' for [[samurai]] founded by [[Ogata Kōan]] in 1838. The spirit of the university's humanity sciences is believed to be intimately rooted in ''Kaitokudo'', whereas that of the natural and applied sciences, including medicine, is widely believed to be based on ''Tekijuku''.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | title = History of the University | publisher = Osaka University | url = http://www.osaka-u.ac.jp/en/guide/about/history.html | accessdate = 2008-02-08}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Osaka University traces its origin back to 1869 when '''Osaka Prefectural Medical School''' was founded in downtown [[Osaka, Osaka|Osaka]]. The school was later transformed into the '''Osaka Prefectural Medical College''' with university status by the University Ordinance (Imperial Ordinance No. 388 of 1918) in 1919. The college merged with the newly-founded College of Science to form '''Osaka Imperial University'''（大阪帝國大学） in 1931. Osaka Imperial University was inaugurated as the sixth [[imperial universities|imperial university]] in Japan. As part of the University, '''Osaka Technical College''' was later included to form the school of Engineering two years later. The university was eventually renamed '''Osaka University''' in 1947.

Merging with [[Naniwa High School]] and Osaka High School as a result of the government's education system reform in 1949, Osaka University started its postwar era with five faculties: Science, Medicine, Engineering, Letters, and Law. After that, faculties, graduate schools, and research institutes have been successively established. Among these are the School of Engineering Science, the first of its kind among Japanese national universities, which draws upon the excellence of both sciences and engineering disciplines, and the School of Human Sciences, which covers its cross-disciplinary research interest as broadly as psychology, sociology, and education. Built on the then-existing faculties, 10 graduate schools were set up as part of the government's education system reform program in 1953. Two graduate schools, the Graduate School of Language and Culture and the cross-disciplinary and cross-institutional Osaka School of International Public Policy, add to the list, making the number of graduate schools reach 12 in 1994. 

[[Image:Osaka University Hospital.jpg|thumb|right|Osaka University Hospital]]
In 1993, [[Osaka University Hospital]] was relocated from the Nakanoshima campus in downtown Osaka to the Suita campus, completing the implementation of the university's plan to integrate the scattered facilities into the Suita and Toyonaka campuses. In October 2007, a merger between Osaka University and [[Osaka University of Foreign Studies]] was completed. The merger made Osaka University one of two national universities in the country with a School of Foreign Studies (with [[Tokyo University of Foreign Studies]]). In addition, the merger made the university the largest national university in the country. 

In 2009, Osaka University implemented a major revision of its website. The result is a site much more accessible and informative to persons not versed in the Japanese language — a site much more user-friendly to international exchange students, international researchers, and expatriates living in the Osaka area. Currently, thanks to the work of the &quot;Web Design Unit,&quot; virtually all Osaka University's web pages come in pairs — a Japanese page and the same page in English. These pairings include frequent updates on symposiums, seminars, and other events open to staff, students and, often, the general public.

==Campuses==
[[File:Osaka-univ_Toyonaka_frontgate.jpg|thumb|Toyonaka campus main entrance]]
Suita, Toyonaka and Minoh are the university's three campuses. Home to the university's headquarters, the Suita campus extends across [[Suita, Osaka|Suita city]] and [[Ibaraki, Osaka|Ibaraki city]] in Osaka prefecture. The Suita campus houses faculties of Human Sciences, Medicine, Dentistry, Pharmaceutical Sciences, and Engineering. It contains the Graduate School of Frontier Biosciences and a portion of the Graduate School of Information Science and Technology. The campus is also home to the Osaka University Hospital and the Nationwide Joint Institute of Cybermedia Center and Research Center for Nuclear Physics. Because access to the campus by public transportation is relatively inconvenient, automobiles, motorcycles, and bicycles are commonly seen within the campus. While sports activities are primarily concentrated on the Toyonaka campus, tennis activities are concentrated on the Suita campus because of its many tennis facilities.

The Toyonaka campus is home to faculties of Letters, Law, Economics, Science, and Engineering Science. It is also the academic base for Graduate Schools of International Public Policy, Language and Culture, (a portion of) Information Science, and the Center for the Practice of Legal and Political Expertise. All freshmen attend classes on the Toyonaka campus during their first year of enrollment. 

The Minoh campus was incorporated following the merger with [[Osaka University of Foreign Studies]] in October 2007. The Minoh campus is home to School of Foreign Studies, Research Institute for World Languages, and Center for Japanese Language and Culture.

In addition to these three campus, the former Nakanoshima campus, the university's earliest campus located in downtown Osaka, served as the hub for the faculty of medicine until the transfer to the Suita campus was completed in 1993.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.osaka-u.ac.jp/en/guide/about/history.html History of Osaka University — Osaka University]. Osaka-u.ac.jp. Retrieved on 2011-06-26.&lt;/ref&gt; Starting from April 2004, the Nakanoshima campus has been transformed into the &quot;Nakanoshima Center&quot;, serving as a venue for information exchange, adult education classes, and activities involving academic as well as non-academic communities.

==Organization==
Osaka University has 11 faculties (学部) for undergraduate programs and 15 graduate schools (大学院).&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.osaka-u.ac.jp/en/academics/ Undergraduate and Graduate schools &amp; facilities — Osaka University]. Osaka-u.ac.jp. Retrieved on 2011-06-26.&lt;/ref&gt;
{{Osaka University departments}}

==Academic alliances==
Osaka University has completed academic exchange agreements with a large number of universities (in 2010, 78) throughout the world and also exchange agreements between schools at Osaka University and schools and institutes in other countries (in 2010, 323). These agreements facilitate international students studying at Osaka University and Osaka University students studying at overseas universities, schools, and institutes. In many cases, students are able to participate in these exchange agreements without paying any additional tuition.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.osaka-u.ac.jp/en/guide/international/exchange/ University Exchange Agreements — Osaka University]. Osaka-u.ac.jp (2010-11-01). Retrieved on 2011-06-26.&lt;/ref&gt; Below are examples of some of these universities:
{{Osaka University academic alliances}}

==Academic Rankings==
{{Infobox Japanese university ranking
| TSU_N = 4
| Kawai_N = 3
| TR_N = 3
| WE_N = 7
| NikkeiBP_G = 
| NikkeiBP_H = 
| NikkeiBP_K = 2
| NikkeiBP_C = 
| NikkeiBP_KOY = 
| GBUDU_N = SA
| LINE_1 = 0
| QS_A = 8
| ARWU_A = 6
| LINE_2 = 0
| THE_W = 130
| QS_W = 45
| ARWU_W = 75
| TR_W = 
| ENSMP_W = 92
}}
{{Infobox Japanese university ranking (By Subject)
| SOC_1 = 0
| LAW_1 = 0
| ASAHI_L = 
| BE_N = 7
| BE_PR = 8
| ECON_1 = 0
| RE_N = 2
| RE_W = 
| BUS_1 = 
| ED_N = 
| ED_W = 
| CPA_N = 
| LINE_1 = 0
| NSTR_1 = 0
| ENG_1 = 0
| NENG_N = 1
| MAT_1 = 0
| TR_N1 = 2
| TR_W1 = 12
| PHY_1 = 0
| TR_N2 = 3
| TR_W2 = 22
| CHE_1 = 0
| TR_N3 = 3
| TR_W3 = 12
| BIO_1 = 0
| TR_N4 = 3
| TR_W4 = 28
| MATH_1 = 
| ARWU_N1 = 
| ARWU_W1 = 
| COM_1 = 
| ARWU_N2 = 
| ARWU_W2 = 
| ARC_1 = 0
| ARC_N = 21
| LINE_2 = 0
| LIFE_1 = 0
| IMM_1 = 0
| TR_N5 = 1
| TR_W5 = 4
| PHT_1 = 0
| TR_N6 = 9
| TR_W6 = 154
| LINE_3 = 0
| NOTE_1 = T. Reuters World rankings include non-educational institutions
| NOTE_2 = 
}}

Handai is one of the most prestigious universities in Japan. It can be seen in the several rankings such as shown below.

===General Rankings===
The university has been ranked 3rd in 2009 and 4th in 2008 and 2010 in the ranking &quot;[[Truly Strong Universities]]&quot; by [[Toyo Keizai]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Rankings_TSU_N&quot;/&gt; In another ranking, Japanese prep school [[:ja:河合塾|Kawaijuku]] ranked Handai as the 3rd best university in Japan.&lt;ref name=&quot;Rankings_Kawai_N&quot;/&gt;

It is recognized as a leading university, especially in the basic sciences, technology and medical field. The university was ranked the 43rd among the world's best universities and the 3rd best Japanese university in 2009, according to the ''[[THE-QS World University Rankings]]''.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | title = Top 100 Universities | publisher = The Times Higher Education | url= http://www.topuniversities.com/world-university-rankings| accessdate = 2010-01-15}}&lt;/ref&gt; In 2011, it came 45th in the ''[[QS World University Rankings]]''&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.topuniversities.com/university-rankings/world-university-rankings/2011&lt;/ref&gt;, four places higher than the previous year (in 2010 ''[[Times Higher Education World University Rankings]]'' and ''[[QS World University Rankings]]'' parted ways to produce separate rankings).

===Research Performance===
Handai is one of the top research institutions in Japan. According to [[Thomson Reuters]], Handai is the 3rd best research university in Japan.&lt;ref name=&quot;Rankings_TR_N&quot; /&gt; Its research excellence is especially distinctive in Biology &amp; Biochemistry (1st in Japan, 4th in the world), Materials Science (2nd in Japan, 12th in the world), Physics (3rd in Japan, 22nd in the world), Chemistry (3rd in Japan, 12th in the world), Immunology (3rd in Japan, 28th in the world), and Pharmacology &amp; Toxicology (9th in Japan, 154th in the world).&lt;ref name=executive&gt;{{cite web |title=Thomson Reuters 20 Top research institutions in Japan |publisher=Thomson Reuters |url=http://science.thomsonreuters.jp/press/release/2011/esi2011/ranking/|language=Japanese}} (this raking includes non-educational institutions)&lt;/ref&gt;

[[:ja:週刊ダイヤモンド|Weekly Diamond]] also reported that Handai has the 7th highest research standard in Japan in terms of research funding per researchers in [[:ja:グローバルCOEプログラム|COE Program]].&lt;ref&gt;&quot;週刊ダイヤモンド&quot; ダイヤモンド社 2010/2/27 http://web.sapmed.ac.jp/kikaku/infomation/0227daiyamondokiji.pdf&lt;/ref&gt; In the same article, it's also ranked 16th in terms of the quality of education by [[:ja:特色ある大学教育支援プログラム|GP]] funds per student.

Handai also has a high research standard in [[Economics]]. [[Repec]] in Jan 2011 ranked Handai's Economic department as Japan's 2nd best economic research university.&lt;ref&gt;[http://ideas.repec.org/top/old/1101/top.japan.html Within Country and State Rankings at IDEAS: Japan]. Ideas.repec.org. Retrieved on 2011-06-26.&lt;/ref&gt; Handai has provided 5 presidents of [[Japanese Economic Association]] in its 42 year history, and this number is 4th largest.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.jeaweb.org/eng/AboutPresidents.html Japanese Economic Association – JEA Global Site]. Jeaweb.org. Retrieved on 2011-06-26.&lt;/ref&gt;

In addition, [[Nihon Keizai Shimbun|Nikkei Shimbun]]　on 2004/2/16 surveyed about the research standards in [[Engineering|Engineering studies]] based on Thomson Reuters, [[:ja:科学研究費補助金|Grants in Aid for Scientific Research]] and questionnaires to heads of 93 leading Japanese Research Centers, and Handai was placed top (research planning ability 2nd/informative ability of research outcome 5th/ability of business-academia collaboration 9th) in this ranking.&lt;ref&gt;[http://homepage3.nifty.com/katu-kobayashi/doppo/kougaku_kennkyu.htm 大学工学部研究力調査（04.2.22）]. Homepage3.nifty.com. Retrieved on 2011-06-26.&lt;/ref&gt;

Furthermore, Handai got the 4th place at the number of patents accepted (171) during 2009 among Japanese Universities.&lt;ref&gt;{{ja}}[http://www.jpo.go.jp/shiryou/toushin/nenji/nenpou2010/toukei/2-13.pdf 2009年国内大学別特許公開件数], Japanese patent office, accessed May 3rd 2011&lt;/ref&gt;

===Graduate school Rankings===
Handai Law School is considered as one of top Law schools in Japan, as it was ranked 7th in terms of  the number of successful candidates of Japanese [[Bar Examination]] in 2010.&lt;ref&gt;[http://laws.shikakuseek.com/data/2010data-2.html 2010年(平成22年)新司法試験法科大学院別合格率ランキング -法科大学院seek]. Laws.shikakuseek.com. Retrieved on 2011-06-26.&lt;/ref&gt; 

===Alumni Rankings===
According to the [[:ja:エコノミスト (雑誌)|Weekly Economist]]'s 2010 rankings, graduates from Handai have the 7th best employment rate in 400 major companies in Japan.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www2.ttcn.ne.jp/honkawa/3865.html|title=Employment rate in 400 major companies rankings |year=2011 |publisher=Weekly Economist |accessdate=Apr 29, 2011|language=Japanese}}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[École des Mines de Paris]] ranks Handai as 92nd in the world in 2011 in terms of the number of alumni listed among CEOs in the 500 largest worldwide companies.&lt;ref name=&quot;Rankings_ENSMP_W&quot; /&gt;

===Popularity and Selectivity===
Handai is one of the most selective universities in Japan. Its entrance difficulty is usually considered as one of the top in Japan.&lt;ref&gt; e.g. [[:ja:代々木ゼミナール|Yoyogi seminar]] published Hensachi (the indication showing the entrance difficulties by prep schools) rankings http://www.yozemi.ac.jp/rank/gakubu/index.html&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Japanese journalist [[:ja:島野清志|Kiyoshi Shimano]] ranks its entrance difficulty as SA (most selective/out of 11 scales) in Japan. {{cite web |title=危ない大学・消える大学 2012年版 |year=2011 |publisher=YELL books |url=http://www.amazon.co.jp/dp/4753930181|language=Japanese}}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Nikkei Business Publications|Nikkei BP]] has been publishing a ranking system &quot;[[Brand rankings of Japanese universities]]&quot; every year, composed by the various indications related to the power of brand, and Handai was 2nd in 2010 in [[Kansai region|Kansai Area]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://consult.nikkeibp.co.jp/consult/release/ub091210a.html NBPC ニュースリリース「大学ブランド・イメージ調査 2010(首都圏編)」（2009年10月実施）より]. Consult.nikkeibp.co.jp. Retrieved on 2011-06-26.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Rankings_NikkeiBP_K&quot;/&gt;

==List of notable persons==
*[[Osamu Hayaishi]] – [[Wolf Prize in Medicine|The Wolf Prize laureate in Medicine in 1986]]
*[[Osamu Tezuka]] – [[Mangaka|Manga author]] (School of Medicine)
*[[Heizo Takenaka]] – [[Economist]] (Graduate School of Economics)
*[[Akio Morita]] – [[Sony]] founder (School of Science)
*[[Hideki Yukawa]] – [[Physicist|Nobel Prize in Physics]] (Graduate School of Science)
*[[Hantaro Nagaoka]] – [[Physicist]] (First President of Osaka University)
*[[Shiba Ryotaro]] – Japanese author (School of Foreign Studies)
*[[Michio Morishima]] – Japanese economist, co-founder of [[International Economic Review]]
*[[Fathimath Dhiyana Saeed]] – [[SAARC]] Secretary-General
*[[Toru Kumon]] - developer of [[Kumon method]]
*[[Akira Yoshino]] - inventor of [[lithium-ion battery]]
*[[Seishi Yokomizo]] - Japanese novelist, creator of [[private detective]] [[Kosuke Kindaichi]].
*[[Toshio Masuda]]- Japanese film director
*[[Hiroshi Haruki]] - Japanese mathematician, author of [[Haruki's theorem]] and [[Haruki's Lemma]]

== Media ==
*[http://www2.coop.osaka-u.ac.jp/GI/walker/ Handai Walker](in Japanese) - student newspaper.

==See also==
*[[Kansai Science City]]

==References==
&lt;div class=&quot;references&quot; style=&quot;height: 250px; overflow: auto; padding: 3px&quot; &gt;
{{Reflist|30em}}
&lt;/div&gt;

==External links==
{{Commons category}}
*[http://www.osaka-u.ac.jp/eng/index.html Osaka University]
*[http://www.webometrics.info/top100_continent.asp?cont=asia Osaka University in the Ranking Web of Asian Universities]

{{Osaka University}}
{{Template group
|title = Links to related articles
|titlestyle = background:#FFFFFF;color:#2657a4;border:1px solid #FFFFFF;
|list =
{{National Seven Universities}}
{{Global 30}}
{{EU Institute in Japan}}
{{AEARU}}
{{APRU}}
|state =autocollapse
}}

{{coord|34|49|09|N|135|31|36|E|region:JP-27_type:edu_source:dewiki|display=title}}

[[Category:Japanese national universities]]
[[Category:National Seven Universities]]
[[Category:Education in Osaka]]
[[Category:Educational institutions established in 1931]]
[[Category:Android (robot)]]
[[Category:Osaka University|*]]
[[Category:1931 establishments in Japan]]

[[az:Osaka Universiteti]]
[[de:Universität Ōsaka]]
[[es:Universidad de Osaka]]
[[fr:Université d'Osaka]]
[[ko:오사카 대학]]
[[id:Universitas Osaka]]
[[it:Università di Osaka]]
[[kk:Осака университеті]]
[[ky:Осака Университети]]
[[lt:Osakos universitetas]]
[[mn:Осакагийн их сургууль]]
[[nl:Universiteit van Osaka]]
[[ja:大阪大学]]
[[pnb:اوساکا یونیورسٹی]]
[[pl:Uniwersytet Osakijski]]
[[pt:Universidade de Osaka]]
[[ro:Universitatea din Osaka]]
[[ru:Осакский университет]]
[[simple:Osaka University]]
[[ta:ஒசாக்கா பல்கலைக்கழகம்]]
[[tr:Osaka Üniversitesi]]
[[ug:ئوساكا ئۇنىۋېرستېتى]]
[[vi:Đại học Osaka]]
[[zh:大阪大学]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
