<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="1098181" ns="0" title="Ray Guy"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{about|the punter|Humorist|Ray Guy (humorist)}}
{{BLP sources|date=January 2011}}

{{Infobox NFL retired
|image=
|caption=
|width=200
|position=[[Punter (football position)|Punter]]
|number=8
|birth_date={{birth date and age|1949|12|22}}&lt;BR&gt;[[Swainsboro, Georgia]]
|death_date=
|debutyear=1973
|finalyear=1986
|draftyear=1973
|draftround=1
|draftpick=23
|college=[[The University of Southern Mississippi|Southern Mississippi]]
|teams=&lt;nowiki&gt;&lt;/nowiki&gt;&lt;!--This forces MediaWiki to recognize the first bullet. Kind of a workaround to a bug.--&gt;
* [[Oakland Raiders|Oakland / Los Angeles Raiders]] ([[1973 NFL season|1973]]-[[1986 NFL season|1986]])
|stat1label=[[Punt (football)|Punts]]
|stat1value=1,049
|stat2label=Punting Yards
|stat2value=44,493
|stat3label=Punting Avg
|stat3value=42.4
|nfl=GUY474616
|highlights=&lt;nowiki&gt;&lt;/nowiki&gt;&lt;!--This forces MediaWiki to recognize the first bullet. Kind of a workaround to a bug.--&gt;
* 7× [[Pro Bowl]] selection ([[1974 Pro Bowl|1973]], [[1975 Pro Bowl|1974]], [[1976 Pro Bowl|1975]], [[1977 Pro Bowl|1976]], [[1978 Pro Bowl|1977]], [[1979 Pro Bowl|1978]], [[1981 Pro Bowl|1980]])
* 6× First-team [[All-Pro]] selection ([[1973 All-Pro Team|1973]], [[1974 All-Pro Team|1974]], [[1975 All-Pro Team|1975]],  [[1976 All-Pro Team|1976]], [[1977 All-Pro Team|1977]], [[1978 All-Pro Team|1978]])
* 2× Second-team All-Pro Selection ([[1979 All-Pro Team|1979]], [[1980 All-Pro Team|1980]])
* 3× [[Super Bowl]] champion ([[Super Bowl XI|XI]], [[Super Bowl XV|XV]], [[Super Bowl XVIII|XVIII]])
* [[NFL's 75th Anniversary All-Time Team|NFL's 75th Anniversary Team]]
* [[NFL 1970s All-Decade Team]]
* Mississippi Sports Hall of Fame
* [[Georgia Sports Hall of Fame]]
|HOF=
|CollegeHOF=90072
}}
'''William Ray Guy''' (born December 22, 1949 in [[Swainsboro, Georgia|Swainsboro]], [[Georgia (U.S. state)|Georgia]]) is a retired [[American football]] [[Punter (American football)|punter]] for the [[Oakland Raiders|Oakland/Los Angeles Raiders]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.nfl.com/players/profile?id=GUY474616 Ray Guy]. nfl.com&lt;/ref&gt; Coming from the [[University of Southern Mississippi]], he was the only pure punter ever to be drafted in the first round of the [[NFL draft]] when the Oakland Raiders selected him in 1973.

Guy was a key member of three [[Super Bowl]]-winning Raiders teams: Super Bowls [[Super Bowl XI|XI]], [[Super Bowl XV|XV]], and [[Super Bowl XVIII|XVIII]]. Arguably, his best performance was in Super Bowl XVIII against the [[Washington Redskins]]. When the Raiders' offense faltered just outside the field goal range of [[placekicker]] [[Chris Bahr]], Guy, known for his power, showed a great deal of finesse by booting a 27-yard punt that pinned the [[Washington Redskins]] on their own 12-yard line late in the first half. On the very next play, the Raiders' [[Jack Squirek]] intercepted Washington quarterback [[Joe Theismann]] and returned it for a touchdown that gave them a 21-3 halftime lead. 

==Playing success==
Ray Guy was the first and only punter ever to be selected in the first round in the [[NFL Draft]] as of 2010.
Ray Guy retired in 1986. During his career, Guy:
*Played in 207 consecutive games
*Punted 1,049 times for 44,493 yards, averaging 42.4 yards per punt, with a 33.8 net yards average
*Had 210 punts inside the 20 yard line (not counting his first 3 seasons, when the NFL did not keep track of this stat), with just 128 touchbacks
*Led the NFL in punting three times
*Had a streak of 619 consecutive punts before having one blocked
*Has a record of 111 career punts in post season games
*Had five punts of over 60 yards during the 1981 season
*Never had a punt returned for a touchdown

Ray Guy was selected to seven [[American Football Conference|AFC]] Pro Bowl teams, and in 1994, he was named the punter on the [[National Football League 75th Anniversary All-Time Team|National Football League's 75th Anniversary Team]].

He was also an outstanding placekicker at Southern Mississippi, once kicking a then-record 61-yard field goal in a snowstorm during a game in [[Utah]]. After his senior season at Southern Miss, Guy was named Most Valuable Player of the annual College All-Star game, in which an all-star team of college seniors played the current Super Bowl champion.  And in addition to his kicking prowess, Guy was also a starting safety in college.  During his senior season, he intercepted a USM record eight passes, and was named an All-American defensive back.  Guy also played quarterback in his early years and was officially the Oakland Raiders' last-string emergency quarterback, ironically replacing kicker-quarterback [[George Blanda]] in this position.  During the time that Blanda was still with the Raiders, early in Guy's career, Guy would occasionally do kickoffs for the Raiders because the aging Blanda no longer had great range.

Ray Guy has been inducted into both the Mississippi and Georgia Sports Halls of Fame, the National High School Sports Hall of Fame, and the College Football Hall of Fame, and many feel he is worthy of induction into the [[Pro Football Hall of Fame]].&lt;ref&gt;{{Citation |last=Joyner |first=K.C. |title=A Case for Ray Guy Belonging in Pro Football Hall of Fame |url=http://www.nytimes.com/2009/01/25/sports/football/25score.html?ref=football |publisher=''[[The New York Times]]'' |date=2009-01-24 |accessdate=2009-03-02}}&lt;/ref&gt; In 1994, he was the first pure punter to be nominated for enshrinement. On April 21, 2008, Guy was inducted into the [[Bay Area Sports Hall of Fame]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.bashof.org/Hall_of_Fame_2008.html Bay Area Sports Hall of Fame.com]&lt;/ref&gt;

Joe Horrigan, the historian of the [[Pro Football Hall of Fame]] once said: &quot;He's the first punter you could look at and say: 'He won games.'&quot;  Guy's punts often doomed opposing offenses to poor field position.

At the 1976 Pro Bowl, Ray Guy became the first punter to hit the Louisiana Superdome video screen. Officials raised the screen from 90 feet to 200 feet.

Ray Guy was known for punts with a high [[hang time]]; he once punted the ball with so much hangtime that the opponents pulled the ball and had it tested for helium. {{cn|date=November 2011}} The hangtime statistic was also instituted in the NFL during his time, possibly because of him.

==The Ray Guy Award==
In 2000, the Greater Augusta Sports Council instituted the [[Ray Guy Award]], to be awarded to the nation's best collegiate punter. Since many collegiate punters nominated for the Ray Guy Award are either former students or work at his kicking camps, Guy himself does not participate in the voting process to avoid accusations of favoritism.

==Pro kicking camps==
In 2005, Ray Guy helped organize and participated in two-day kicking camps, held throughout the [[United States]], for high-school punters, placekickers, and longsnappers.  In 2007, the camp was once again held on the campus of Colorado College. He has help from son Ryan Guy.

==Personal==

Guy is married to Beverly Guy. On August 14, 2011, Guy filed for bankruptcy and was forced to put up his Super Bowl rings for auction. His son, Ryan  works at Harlem middle school as a coach.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.bloomberg.com/news/2011-08-02/ex-raiders-punter-ray-guy-auctions-three-super-bowl-rings-after-bankruptcy.html]&lt;/ref&gt;  The auction of the rings brought in $96,216, slightly higher than the upper estimate of 90K.&lt;ref&gt;[http://chronicle.augusta.com/latest-news/2011-08-10/guys-super-bowl-rings-bring-almost-100000?v=1312979278]&lt;/ref&gt;

== References ==
{{reflist}}

==External links==
*[http://www.rayguy.net Ray Guy's official website]
*{{pro-football-reference|id=GuyxRa20|name=Ray Guy}}
*[http://www.prokicker.com ''ProKicker.com'']
*[http://www.goldeneaglefans.homestead.com/Guy.html Ray Guy's Southern Miss career]
*[http://chronicle.augusta.com/stories/100800/fea_077-0925.000.shtml ''&quot;The Guy Behind Guy&quot;'' - Article about the Ray Guy Award statue]
{{Walter Camp Alumni of the Year}}
{{Senior Bowl All-Time Team}}
{{1973 NFL Draft}}
{{Super Bowl XI}}
{{Super Bowl XV}}
{{Super Bowl XVIII}}
{{RaidersFirstPick}}
{{NFL1970s}}
{{NFL75}}

{{Persondata &lt;!-- Metadata: see [[Wikipedia:Persondata]]. --&gt;
| NAME              = Guy, Ray
| ALTERNATIVE NAMES =
| SHORT DESCRIPTION =
| DATE OF BIRTH     = December 22, 1949
| PLACE OF BIRTH    =
| DATE OF DEATH     =
| PLACE OF DEATH    =
}}
{{DEFAULTSORT:Guy, Ray}}
[[Category:1949 births]]
[[Category:American Conference Pro Bowl players]]
[[Category:American football punters]]
[[Category:College Football Hall of Fame inductees]]
[[Category:Living people]]
[[Category:Los Angeles Raiders players]] 
[[Category:NFL 75th Anniversary All-Time Team]]
[[Category:Oakland Raiders players]]
[[Category:People from Augusta, Georgia]]
[[Category:Southern Miss Golden Eagles football players]]
[[Category:University of Southern Mississippi alumni]]

[[de:Ray Guy]]
[[fr:Ray Guy]]
[[pt:Ray Guy]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
