<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="11014624" ns="0" title="Holy Innocents&#039; High School"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{coord|1|22|18.99|N|103|53|44.65|E|display=title|region:SG_type:edu}}
{{Infobox school
| name = Holy Innocents' High School &lt;br&gt; '''圣婴中学'''
| image = [[File:abt cp01.jpg]]
| motto = '''谦诚和爱''' Sincerity and Charity 
| established = 1892
| type = Govt-aided
| colours = White and Blue
| address = Singapore
| session = Single
| school code = 7108
| city/town = [[Hougang]]
| enrolment = approx. 1,500
| principal = Ms Soh Lai Leng
| viceprincipal     = Mr Subash Lazar
| homepage = [http://www.holyinnocentshigh.moe.edu.sg Link]
}}

'''Holy Innocents' High School''' ([[Abbreviation]]: HIHS; [[Simplified Chinese]]:'''圣婴中学''', [[Traditional Chinese]]: '''聖嬰中學''', [[pinyin]]: ''Shèngyīng Zhōngxué'') is one of the earliest [[catholic schools]] in [[Singapore]]. Founded in [[1892]] by the [[Church of the Nativity of the Blessed Virgin Mary]], the Chinese mission school is providing secondary school education leading up to a [[Singaporean GCE 'O' Level]] certification, in both express and normal streams. Every year during Thanksgiving Day, the students and teachers attend church for thanksgiving mass and award ceremonies.

The [[co-educational]] high school has received major facelifts in 1994 and 2004 in order to upgrade its old colonial style buildings and facilities. 

Today, Holy Innocents' High School stands on an elevated ground in Hougang Central, surrounded by the [[HDB]] flats and shopping centres.

==Motto==
谦。诚。和。爱
The school motto stresses four areas of student development; intellect, morality, physical wellness and harmony. The four areas branch out and include values like humility, hardwork, honesty, kindness, righteousness, sincerity and charity.

==Culture==
===Students===
[[File:HIHS Celebration 50.JPG|thumb|right|The school celebrated its 50th year in its current location at Hougang in 2008]]
[[File:HIHS Habits of Minds.JPG|thumb|right|Habits of Minds]]
[[File:HIHS Classrooms.JPG|thumb|right|The main classroom block]]
[[File:HIHS Inner Courtyard.JPG|thumb|right|Assembly grounds]]

The [[Chinese language]] is widely spoken in the school. Almost all the students are Chinese, with some Indians and Malays. 

The majority of the students come from [[Holy Innocents' Primary School]], situated about 500 m away. Most students continue their studies in polytechnics or junior colleges such as: 
*[[Anderson Junior College]]
*[[Catholic Junior College]] (affiliated)
*[[Nanyang Junior College]]
*[[National Junior College]]
*[[Serangoon Junior College]]
*[[Temasek Junior College]]
*[[Victoria Junior College]]
*[[Nanyang Polytechnic]]
*[[Temasek Polytechnic]]
Holy Innocents' High School is also attended by international students from [[Indonesia]] and [[Thailand]].

===Uniform===
In 1997 upper secondary boys were allowed the option of wearing long trousers. Lower secondary school boys continued to wear shorts. For both females and males alike, students wear a white top and light blue bottom. The school has introduced a new uniform but the colours of white and blue remain unchanged.

===Class names===
Previously all express streamed classes were named after the alphabet: A, B, C and D. Numbers 1, 2, 3, 4 and 5 were used for Normal Academic and Normal Technical streamed classes.

In 2003, the class naming changed, as below:
{| class=&quot;wikitable&quot; style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;

!colspan=3|Express 
!colspan=3|Normal Academic 
!colspan=3|Normal Technical
|-
! Before 2002
! 2003 to 2006
! 2007–present
! Before 2002
! 2003 to 2006
! 2007–present
! Before 2002
! 2003 to 2006
! 2007–present
|-
| A
| Humility
| Humility
| 1
| Faith
| Faith
| 4
| Hope
| Hope
|-
| B
| Sincerity
| Sincerity
| 2
| Joy
| Joy
| 5
| Unity
|-
| C
| Charity 
| Charity
| 3
| Peace
|-
| D
| Diligence
| Diligence
|-
| E
| Integrity
| Integrity
|-
| -NIL-
| -NIL-
| Respect
|}

===Outward Bound course===
All secondary three students attend the OBS Camp in [[Pulau Ubin]] during school vacations.

==School songs==
===School song===
圣婴中学，黉宇高嵩,

屹立狮岛，美丽如虹,

环境清幽，校址宽宏,

树人树木，俱收事功.

济济多士，共坐春风,

荣主救灵，功德无穷,

砥砺品学，婴德是宗,

谦诚和爱，景仰大同.

宣传文化，中西并攻,

阐扬学术，文质兼丰,

培植翘秀，失勤失忠,

蔚为国器，南邦之雄.

===School Creed===
&lt;poem&gt;
Verse 1:
I am special because God created me,
And he has blessed me with unique talents.
I'll be responsible and strive for excellence,
So that, I can contribute most meaningfully to my
school and society.

Chorus:
I will uphold integrity,
and be sincere and charitable.
In what I do,
I will not hurt others and myself.
So as to create a more loving,
and peaceful community* for all,for all!

Verse 2:
I am special because God created me,
And he has blessed me with great potential.
I'll strive to be an independent lifelong learner,
Humble in spirit, to accept new challenges.[Back to chorus]

Verse 3:
Standing with all, in the HIHS family.
We will be one where the love of God reigns.
&lt;/poem&gt;

==Academic programme==
===Advanced Elective Modules===
Holy Innocents’ High School will be one of the few schools in the pioneering batch to offer [[Advanced Elective Modules]] (AEMs) in 2007. The school will be collaborating with [[Republic Polytechnic]] (RP) to offer elective modules to expand the learning experience of pupils and provide exposure to the practice-oriented learning approaches adopted in the polytechnics. 

AEMs may be used for polytechnic admission under the [[Joint Polytechnic Special Admissions Exercise]] (JPSAE) and the [[Direct Polytechnic Admission]] (DPA) exercise. They may also be used for credit exemption in subjects that are relevant to the pupil’s subsequent course of study in the Polytechnic.

===Subjects offered at GCE O Level===
Beside compulsory subjects, English, Chinese, Elementary Mathematics and Social Studies, the school also offers:
*Additional Mathematics
*Art
*Design and Technology
*Food Science
*Higher Chinese
*Higher Malay
*Pure Biology
*Pure Chemistry
*Pure Physics
*Pure Geography
*Pure Literature
*History
*Principles of Accounts
*Music

==Affiliated Schools==
[[Holy Innocents' Primary School]] and [[Catholic Junior College]]

Holy Innocents' High School is a partner of [[Temasek Polytechnic]] and [[Nanyang Polytechnic]], offering Advanced Elective Modules to the relevant courses of these polytechnics.

==Facilities==
[[File:Greendale Secondary School 2, Jan 06.jpg|thumb|right|275px|Temporary campus in Punggol, now occupied by [[Greendale Secondary School]]]]
In 2004, the school moved to it temporary premises in [[Punggol]] during the rebuilding of Hougang campus. The school moved back in early 2006. 

The upgraded campus at [[Hougang]] Central has an air-conditioned hall, a [[chapel]], an alumni room, two theatres, and a 500 square meters [[roof garden]]. On June 2, 2006, the upgraded campus was opened and blessed by Archbishop [[Nicholas Chia]], head of the Catholic Church, [[Archdiocese of Singapore]].

==Activities==
[[File:HIHS Scouts.JPG|thumb|right|The Hornet Scouts, the school's pride]]
[[File:HIHS Band.JPG|thumb|right|Holy Innocents' Military Band, a popular CCA in the school]]
Holy Innocents' High School has a co-curricular programme, with some groups gaining recognition on national level competition.

===Awards===
====2009====
*Scout: Gold (consecutively for the past 4 years)
*St. John Ambulance: -Silver (consecutively for the past 7 years)
*St. John Ambulance: -6 chief commissioner award receivers
*St. John Ambulance: -zone first aid and home nursing competition (ambulance cadet TOC: 2nd position)
*St. John Ambulance: -zone first aid and home nursing competition (nursing cadet footdrill: 3rd position)
*St. John Ambulance: -zone first aid and home nursing competition (nursing adult footdrill: 2nd position
*Modern Dance: Gold
*Military Band: Silver
*Choir: Silver
*Chinese Orchestra: Bronze
*Drama: Bronze

====2008====
*Scout: Gold
*Scout: 6th National Patrol Camp (Gold Award)
*Scout: Serangoon District Field Day (Scout: Lower Sec Soccer) (Champion)
*Scout: Serangoon District Field Day (Venture: Basketball)(1st Runner-up)
*St. John Ambulance: -Silver (consecutively for the past 6 years)
*St. John Ambulance: -Soccer Girls (Champion)/ Soccer boys golden boots award: Samuel Quah Cheng Kai
*St. John Ambulance: -Zone first aid and home nursing competition (Nursing cadet foot drill: 3rd position)
*St. John Ambulance: - 10 chief commissioner award receivers.
*St. John Ambulance: - Foot drill Competition 2008: Champions

====2007====
*Scout: Gold
*Scout: National Scoutcraft and Pioneering Competition - Gateway (Gold Award)
*Scout: National Scoutcraft and Pioneering Competition - Logging (2nd Runner-up)
*St. John Ambulance: -Silver (consecutively for the past 5 years)
*St. John Ambulance: -Zone first aid and home nursing competition (Ambulance cadet foot drill: Champions)
*Choir: Gold
*English Drama: Gold
*Military Band: Bronze
*Dance: Bronze
*Chinese Orchestra: Bronze

====2006====
*Scout: Gold
*People Developer Standard
*Sustained Achievement Award: Uniformed Group
*Development Award: TAF Award (Silver)
*Achievement Award: Academic Value-added (Normal)
*NPCC: Silver
*St. John's Ambulance: Silver
*Military Band: Merit (Assessment of Marching Bands)

====2005====
*Scout: Silver
*Sustained Achievement Award: Uniformed Group
*Development Award: TAF Award (Silver)
*Choir: Gold
*Military Band: Silver
*NPCC: Silver
*Scout: Silver
*St. John's Ambulance: Silver
*Chinese Orchestra: Bronze
*Dance: Bronze
*Drama: Bronze
*Shooting awards

==History==
[[File:HIHS Stone.JPG|thumb|right|The HIHS stone, first blessed on January 5, 1958]]
*1892 Holy Innocents' High School was one of the first Chinese Mission Schools to be founded and was named Tao Nan School. Bible studies and classical Chinese were taught.
*1920 Rev Fr Becheras was the Supervisor of the school. The name of the school was changed from Tao Nan to Holy Innocents' Boy School. It means pure, wholesome and innocent.
*1942 During the Japanese Occupation, the school name changed to Syonan School
*1957 A two-storey building consisting of 12 classrooms was built at 7 &lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt;/&lt;sub&gt;4&lt;/sub&gt; miles, Upper Serangoon Road (The present site). Rev Fr Berthold, then Supervisor, appointed Rev Fr Shih as Principal.
*1958 Secondary classes were started and the name of the school was modified to Holy Innocents' High School. His Grace, Archbishop, Rt Rev M Olcomendy, blessed the school and declared it open on 5 January.
*1960 to 1964 An additional eight classrooms and two laboratories were built.
*1965 The school started her first Pre-University classes (Science Stream)
*1968 A new three-storey building was added
*1969 Fr Shih was transferred to Taiwan. Rev Fr Peter Lu assumed office as Principal.
*1983 On 9 September, Mr Ho Kah Leong, Parliamentary Secretary, Ministry of Education, officiated the opening of the Auditorium and four classrooms. Rev Fr Peter Lu retired at the end of the year.
*1984 The Vice-Principal, Mr Lee Tho Nee, was appointed Principal
*1985 On 25 March, Holy Innocents' High School's primary school section moved to new premises at Lorong Low Koon and was named Holy Innocents' Primary School. The secondary section functioned as a single-session school
*1987 A School Building Committee was formed headed by then Chairman of the School Management Board, Rev Fr Mathias Tung, to expand the school to a standard-sized secondary school. Approval was given with an 80% capital grant.
*1992 The school's lower secondary classes occupied the ex-Hai Sing High School premises while the upper secondary classes reminded at the present site. Construction and refurbishment work started in May.
*1994 The official commissioning of the upgraded facilities by Gregory Yong, Archbishop of Singapore, took place on 30 July The completed project added three new teaching blocks and an administrative block to the original building. The total built in area was 9000 sq m.
*1996 Mrs Mary Bay, the Vice-Principal, was appointed Principal in July.
*2001 Mrs Pauline Wong was appointed Principal in December
* Moved to holding school at 51 Edgedale Plains in June, while upgrading of the original site was completed.
*2005 moved back to original site in December
*2006 The new school building was officially opened and blessed by His Grace, Archbishop Nicholas Chia on 2 June 2006
*2007 Ms Soh Lai Leng was appointed Principal in December

==Principals==

*1920 : Rev Fr  Becheras
*1957 - 1969: Rev Fr Shih
*1970 - 1984: Rev Fr Peter Lu
*1984 - 1996: Mr Lee Tho Nee
*1996 - 2001: Mrs Mary Bay
*2001 - 2007 : Mrs Pauline Wong
*2008–Present: Ms Soh Lai Leng

==Alumni==
* [[Chew Chor Meng]] - Actor
* [[Li Wei Song]] - Music composer
* [[Edwin Goh]]

==Transport==
The nearest bus stops are opposite and outside Hougang Plaza, which is next to the school. Bus services include [[SBS Transit]] 74, 112, 113, 119, 136 and 147. [[Hougang Central Bus Interchange]], [[Hougang MRT Station]] and [[Hougang Mall]] are within 5 minutes walking distance.

==External links==
* [http://www.holyinnocentshigh.moe.edu.sg/ Holy Innocents' High website]

[[Category:Secondary schools in Singapore]]
[[Category:Educational institutions established in 1892]]
[[Category:Hougang]]
[[Category:Roman Catholic schools in Singapore]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
