<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="1102828" ns="0" title="Seif Adnan Kanaan"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{refimprove|date=December 2010}}

'''Seif Adnan Kanaan''' (died October 22, 2004), was an Iraqi citizen&lt;!--I hope this is correct--&gt; who was abducted in Iraq and beheaded on October 22, 2004.  The reason given by the kidnappers, the [[Army of Ansar Al-Sunna]], was that he was employed by the [[United States Army]].

==Murder==
On October 22, 2004, a video was posted on the website of the [[Jamaat Ansar al-Sunna|Army of Ansar Al-Sunna]], apparently showed the beheading of Kanaan.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.washingtonpost.com/wp-dyn/articles/A56487-2004Oct23.html] Washington Times. October 24, 2004.&lt;/ref&gt; 

Kanaan was shown in a picture surrounded by the three hooded gunmen with a banner of the Army of Ansar Al-Sunna in the background. They accused him of being an American spy recruited in Mosul. In the video the man makes a statement:

&quot;My name is Seif Adnan Kanaan. I work at [[Mosul]] airport... My second job is to supply beverages to the US army,&quot; the victim said, surrounded by three hooded gunmen.

One of the gunmen then reads a statement saying that &quot;the mujahedeen (Islamic fighters) in Mosul were able to capture ... a [[Tenth Crusade|crusader]] [[Espionage|spy]] recruited by US forces to spy and inform on the [[Mujahideen|mujahedeen]] in Mosul.&quot;

The gunman said the purported spy worked at a US base in Mosul airport and &quot;was known for his allegiance to the Americans and his hatred for the mujahedeen.&quot; He had &quot;publicly insulted ([[Islam]]'s) Prophet [[Muhammad|Mohammed]].&quot;

&quot;We tell people like him: the door of repentance is open... Announce your repentance and live in peace among your kin,&quot; the gunman said.  He then warned that &quot;The mujahedeen will catch those who persist in working with US forces, and settle for nothing less than [[Decapitation|beheading]] them.&quot;

The man was beheaded after &quot;confessing to all the actions he carried out.&quot; 
The group also posted the statement on its website, accompanied by pictures of the beheading.

The video showed the man who read the statement later beheading the victim with a [[knife]]. He placed the head on the back of the victim, who lay in a pool of blood.

The man had been killed &quot;to serve as a lesson for others,&quot; the murderer said.

==See also==
{{Portalbox|Iraq|Biography|Terrorism}}
*[[Iraq]]
**[[2003 invasion of Iraq]]
**[[Abu Ghraib torture and prisoner abuse|Abu Ghraib prisoner abuse]]
**[[Human rights in post-invasion Iraq|Human rights situation in post-Saddam Iraq]]
*[[Decapitation]]
**[[Daniel Pearl]]
**[[Nick Berg]]
**[[Paul Marshall Johnson, Jr.]]
**[[Eugene Armstrong]]
**[[Kim Sun-il]]
**[[Kenneth Bigley]]
**[[Piotr Stańczak]]
**[[Jack Hensley]]
**[[Shosei Koda]]

== External links ==
*[http://www.usatoday.com/news/world/2004-10-23-iraqi-worker_x.htm/ USA Today:''Internet tape purportedly shows beheading''] By [[The Associated Press]] Posted: October 23, 2004. Retrieved: December 30, 2010.
*[http://www.washingtonpost.com/wp-dyn/articles/A56487-2004Oct23.html Washington Times:''Car Bombings Kill 17 Iraqis; Attack Injures 6 U.S. Soldiers/Extremists Said to Behead Man Working With Americans''] By Karl Vick. Washington Post Foreign Service. Posted: October 24, 2004. Retrieved: December 30, 2010.

== References ==
{{reflist}}

{{Persondata &lt;!-- Metadata: see [[Wikipedia:Persondata]]. --&gt;
| NAME              = Kanaan, Seif Adnan
| ALTERNATIVE NAMES =
| SHORT DESCRIPTION =
| DATE OF BIRTH     =
| PLACE OF BIRTH    =
| DATE OF DEATH     = October 22, 2004
| PLACE OF DEATH    =
}}
{{DEFAULTSORT:Kanaan, Seif Adnan}}
[[Category:Year of birth missing]]
[[Category:2004 deaths]]
[[Category:Murder in 2004]]
[[Category:Deaths by decapitation]]
[[Category:Filmed executions in Iraq]]
[[Category:Iraqi terrorism victims]]
[[Category:Iraqi people taken hostage]]
[[Category:Terrorism deaths in Iraq]]
[[Category:People murdered in Iraq]]
[[Category:Iraqi murder victims]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
