<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="11034592" ns="0" title="Jaap Goudsmit"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">'''Jaap Goudsmit''' (b. Amsterdam, 22 July 1951) is Dutch scientist, known for his research in the field of [[AIDS]]. 

In 1978 Jaap Goudsmit received his MD degree with [[Latin honors|honor]] at the Faculty of Medicine of the [[University of Amsterdam]]. He was awarded a Fogarty fellowship, and joined the research on [[Kuru (disease)|kuru]] with Nobel Prize winner [[Daniel Carleton Gajdusek]]. He received his PhD  from the University of Amsterdam in 1982. He received a Fogarty Visiting Scientist Award to do postdoctoral research at the [[National Institutes of Health]] in [[Bethesda, Maryland]]. In 1983 Jaap Goudsmit became board certified in the Netherlands as a Medical Microbiologist. In 1989 he became professor in [[virology]] at the University of Amsterdam. In 1990 he was involved in a [[Henk Buck|controversy]] in a research project to use [[antisense]] as a means of inhibiting HIV-replication.

Jaap Goudsmit  has been head of the Department of Human Retrovirology at the [[Academic Medical Center]] (AMC) of the University of Amsterdam from 1996 to 2002 and chairman of the AMC Research Institute for Infectious Diseases and the AMC Institute for Science Education. Since 1984 he is one of the principal researcher of the Amsterdam Cohort Studies on HIV infection and AIDS among homosexual men and HIV drug users. 

He is the founder of PrimaGen, the first biotech company concentrating on [[predictive medicine]]. He chaired the Scientific Advisory Committee of the [[International AIDS Vaccine Initiative]] (IAVI) and has been a member of its board. He was project leader and (co)chair of Eurovacc Foundation. In 2002 Jaap Goudsmit joined [[Crucell]], a  biotechnology company in [[Leiden]], as Chief Medical Officer and Executive Vice President of Vaccine Research and Development. In 2003 he was elected as member of the HIV Vaccine Enterprise Product Development Working Group of the [[Gates Foundation]] and in 2006 he was affiliated with Pevion Biotech as member of the Supervisory Board. In 2006 Jaap Goudsmit entered the board of Vaxin Inc.

Goudsmit is a very productive researcher and author or co-author of more than 450 scientific publications. According to the [[Institute of Scientific Information]], he entered the list of most-cited scientists in 2001.

==Source==
*http://people.forbes.com/profile/jaap-goudsmit/24285

==External links==
*[http://www.eurovacc.org/Advisory.php Scientific Advisory Board]
*[http://www.nrc.nl/krant/article58815.ece?service=Print  Article NRC-handelsblad (Newspaper, dutch)]
* http://www.jaapgoudsmit.nl/

{{Persondata &lt;!-- Metadata: see [[Wikipedia:Persondata]]. --&gt;
| NAME              = Goudsmit, Jaap
| ALTERNATIVE NAMES =
| SHORT DESCRIPTION =
| DATE OF BIRTH     = 22 July 1951
| PLACE OF BIRTH    =
| DATE OF DEATH     =
| PLACE OF DEATH    =
}}
{{DEFAULTSORT:Goudsmit, Jaap}}
[[Category:1951 births]]
[[Category:Living people]]
[[Category:HIV/AIDS researchers]]
[[Category:Dutch physicians]]
[[Category:People from Amsterdam]]

[[nl:Jaap Goudsmit]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
