<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="11055448" ns="0" title="Midland College"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Infobox MidlandCollege
 |name              = Midland College (MC)
 |image_name        =
 |image_size        = 146px
 |caption           =
 |motto             =
 |tagline           =
 |established       = 1972
 |closed            =
 |type              = Community College
 |affiliation       =
 |endowment         =
 |rector            =
 |officer_in_charge =
 |chairman          =
 |chancellor        =
 |president         = Dr. Steve Thomas
 |vice-president    = Dr. Richard Jolly
 |provost           =
 |vice_chancellor   =
 |dean              =
 |director          =
 |head_label        =
 |head              =
 |faculty           =
 |staff             =
 |students          = 7,425
 |undergrad         =
 |postgrad          =
 |doctoral          =
 |other             =
 |city              = {{flagicon|USA}} [[Midland, Texas|Midland]]
 |state             = [[Texas]]
 |province          =
 |country           = USA
 |coor              =
 |campus            = {{convert|224|acre|km2}}
 |former_names      =
 |free_label        =
 |free              =
 |sports            =
 |colors            = Green and Yellow {{color box|#006300}} {{color box|#FFD100}}
 |colours           =
 |nickname          = Chaps
 |mascot            = [[Greater Roadrunner|Chaparral]]
 |athletics         = NJCAA Men's Division I
 |affiliations      =
 |website           = [http://www.midland.edu/ www.midland.edu]
 |logo              =
 |footnotes         = &lt;!--All enrollment figures are as of--&gt;
}}

'''Midland College''' (MC) was established as an independent junior college in 1972 and held its first classes on campus in 1975. Since that time, the campus has expanded to a {{convert|704752|sqft|m2|adj=on}} main campus on {{convert|224|acre|km2}} in [[Midland, Texas]], United States - a county seat of over 100,000 people in the [[Permian Basin (North America)|Permian Basin]] region of west Texas and southeast New Mexico. The school also has numerous 'off-campus' locations in other parts of Midland, and in [[Fort Stockton]], Texas, the [[Pecos County]] seat.

==Mission and accreditation==
Midland College is a comprehensive public college dedicated to educational excellence. The faculty and staff are committed to instruction that sustains a life-long quest for knowledge and provides students with academic, intellectual, occupational, and professional proficiency — including knowledge in and appreciation of the arts and sciences; critical thinking; clear and effective communication; analytical reflection; and technical skills. The College serves the diverse learning communities of its region by providing a range of flexible programs, from community enrichment to the baccalaureate degree.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.midland.edu/about/policies/mission.php Midland College mission statement&lt;/ref&gt;

As defined by the [[Texas Legislature]], the official service area of Midland College is the following:&lt;ref&gt;Texas Education Code, Section 130.188, &quot;Midland Community College District Service Area&quot;.&lt;/ref&gt;
*all of [[Crockett County, Texas|Crockett]], [[Pecos County, Texas|Pecos]], [[Reagan County, Texas|Reagan]], and [[Terrell County, Texas|Terrell]] Counties, and
*all of [[Midland County, Texas|Midland County]] excluding the community of [[Greenwood, Texas|Greenwood]].

Midland College is accredited by the Commission on Colleges of the [[Southern Association of Colleges and Schools]] to award certificates and associate and baccalaureate degrees.

Midland College meets all guidelines and standards as set forth by the Texas Higher Education
Coordinating Board.&lt;ref name=&quot;handbook&quot;&gt;http://www.midland.edu/admissions/images/2008_2009catalog.pdf Midland College Catalog &amp; Student Handbook&lt;/ref&gt;  Midland College is also accredited by the following organizations:
* American Veterinary Medical Association
* Commission on Accreditation of Allied Health Informatics &amp; Information Management Education
* Commission on Accreditation of Allied Health Educational Programs
* Committee on Accreditation for Respiratory Care
* Federal Aviation Administration
* Joint Review Committee on Education in Diagnostic Medical Sonography
* Joint Review Committee on Education in Radiologic Technology
* National Association for the Education of Young Children
* National League for Nursing Accrediting Commission
* Texas Board of Nursing
* Texas Certification Board of Alcoholism and Drug Abuse Counselors
* Texas Commission on Alcohol and Drug Abuse
* Texas Commission on Fire Protection
* Texas Department of Licensing and Regulations
* Texas Department of State Health Services

==History==
Midland College began in September 1969 as the Midland campus of the Permian Junior College system. It was re-created in 1972 with the formation of the Midland College District.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;Midland College: The First 25 Years&quot; by Karen S. Lanier and H.A. Tuck, 1996, Gateway Press, ISBN 978-9997974938&lt;/ref&gt;

==Campus==

===Main campus===
Following the formation of the Midland College District in 1972, bonds in the amount of $5,100,000 were issued for the construction of a {{convert|115|acre|km2|adj=on}} campus. Ground breaking at the new campus was held October 23, 1973.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.midland.edu/about/history.php MC history&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;ref&gt;http://www.midland.edu/directories/maps.php MC Website, Campus Map and Index of buildings&lt;/ref&gt;

Opened in the Spring of 1975:
* Pevehouse Administration Building
* Abell-Hanger Science Faculty Building
Opened in the '''Fall of 1975''':
* Murray Fasken Learning Resource Center
* Dorothy and Clarence Scharbauer, Jr. Student Center
* Technology Center
* Physical Education Building
Opened in 1978:
* Allison Fine Arts Building
* Al G. Langford Chapparral Center
Opened in the following years:
* Davidson Family Health Sciences Building
* Dolly Neal Chapel
* Dorothy and Todd Aaron Medical Science Building
* F. Marie Hall Academic Building
* Helen L. Greathouse Children's Center
* Jack E. Brown Dining Hall
* Leona G. and John E. Fox Science Building

There are also four residence halls on the Midland College Main campus ''(see below)''.

===Off-campus facilities===
* The '''Advanced Technology Center''', located at 3200 W. Cuthbert in Midland, delivers workforce education programs that support the development of a skilled technical workforce for Midland and the Permian Basin. The facility contains more than {{convert|80000|sqft|m2}} of instructional space that features high-tech computer classrooms with Internet access and a tiered lecture hall.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.midland.edu/~atc/ MC Advanced Technology Center&lt;/ref&gt;
* The '''Aviation Maintenance Technology Facility''', located at Midland International Airport, Hangar E, 2405 Windecker, offers students training on actual aircraft as they work towards certification in Airframe Maintenance and Powerplant Maintenance.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.midland.edu/~amt/ MC Aviation Maintenance Technology Center&lt;/ref&gt;
* The '''Bill Pace Cogdell Learning Center''', located at 201 W. Florida, provides ABE, ESL and GED courses, and houses the MC Business and Economic Development Center.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.midland.edu/cogdell/ '''Bill Pace Cogdell Learning Center&lt;/ref&gt;
* The '''Cogdell Technical Building''', located at 111. E. Florida, is an advanced training facility offering hands-on training in trades.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.midland.edu/about/maps/locations.php#CTB MC Cogdell Technical Building&lt;/ref&gt;
* The '''Williams Regional Technical Training Center''' (WRTTC), located at 1309 West I-10 in Fort Stockton provides university parallel, occupational/technical certificate and associate degree programs, and courses offered in collaboration with the Fort Stockton Independent School District (FSISD).&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.midland.edu/wrttc/ '''Williams Regional Technical Training Center]&lt;/ref&gt;

==Academics==
The school offers 100+ degree and certificate programs, as well as a variety of Continuing Education programs. They also offer a Bachelor’s degree in Organizational Management and provide on-campus access to upper-level degrees offered by their seven University Center partners.&lt;ref name=&quot;handbook&quot; /&gt;

===Baccalaureate program===
Midland College offers a bachelor’s degree in Organizational Management, to broaden career opportunities for students and better their chances for promotion to supervisory positions. The program is designed to provide a career-ladder for students who have already completed an associate degree and who wish to continue their education at the bachelor's level.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.midland.edu/bachelor/ Baccalaureate Program Overview&lt;/ref&gt;

===University Center===
The Midland College University Center offers students multiple options for either beginning or completing their education. Programs and courses are now offered by seven area and online universities:  [[Texas Tech University]], [[Lubbock Christian University]], The [[University of Texas of the Permian Basin]], [[Sul Ross State University]], [[Angelo State University]], [[Howard Payne University]] and [[Western Governors University]]. A total of 4 master's degrees and 11 bachelor's degrees, plus Midland College's Bachelor of Applied Technology in Organizational Management and two teacher certification programs, are now offered on the Midland College campus.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.midland.edu/university/ MC University Center&lt;/ref&gt;

===Early College High School===
Early College High School (ECHS) at Midland College is located on the main campus, in the Abell-Hanger Science Faculty Building. The school welcomed its first freshman class on August 24, 2009. The goal for ECHS is that, by the time &quot;the students receive their high school
diploma, they will also have an associate’s degree from Midland College.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.mywesttexas.com/articles/2009/08/20/news/top_stories/early_college_high_school_bts.txt Early College High School a 'once-in-a-lifetime' chance for students]&lt;/ref&gt;

==Student life==
Clubs, intramural sports, cheerleading, student government, and all other student related activities operate through the Student Activities Office.

===Residence halls===
The main campus has four residence halls for students.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.midland.edu/facilities/housing/ MC Housing&lt;/ref&gt;

* O'Shaughnessy Hall is a 96-bed facility for women.
* Nadine and Tom Craddick Hall is a 94-bed co-ed facility.
* Men's Residence Hall is a 96-bed facility for men.
* Family Housing Facility was the college's first residential facility.

===School spirit===
*'''School colors:''' The school's official colors are green and yellow.
*'''Mascot:''' The school [[mascot]] is a [[Greater Roadrunner|Chaparral]].

===Student publications===
*''El Paisano'' - The MC student newspaper is published at five or six times each long semester
*''Chaparral'' - The MC student news/feature magazine is published once each year, during the spring semester
*''Tableau'' - The MC student literary magazine is published once each year during the fall semester
The student publications office at Midland College also maintains its own website ''(see below, in External Links)''

==Athletics==
Midland College has won 20 National Championships in sports since 1975, as well as produced 192 All-Americans. A member of the [[Western Junior College Athletic Conference]], Midland College fields teams in:
* Baseball
* Men's Basketball
* Women's Basketball
* Men's Golf
* Softball
* Volleyball

==Affiliated institutions==

===Midland College Foundation===
Since 1973, the foundation has served as Midland College's nonprofit fundraising organization.

==Alumni==
*[[Jerome Beasley]], basketball player
*David LeMaster, American playwright and author, teacher, actor and speaker&lt;ref&gt;http://www.midland.edu/publicinfo/archives/mcpage/2006/09-17-06.pdf/ Former Student Reflects on his MC Education and Those Instructors Who Made a Difference&lt;/ref&gt;
*[[Chad Campbell]], American professional [[golf]]er&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.midlandcollegefoundation.org/impact/students/students.php?page=campbell.php Chad Campbell at Midland College]&lt;/ref&gt;
*[[Kenneth Ferrie]], English professional golfer with multiple wins on European PGA Tour&lt;ref&gt;http://www.kennethferrie.co.uk/ Kenneth Ferrie, Official Website&lt;/ref&gt;
*[[Spud Webb]], American [[basketball]] player, [[1986]] [[NBA Slam Dunk Contest]] champion
*[[Mookie Blaylock]], American [[basketball]] player, [[NBA]] defensive star
*[[Milt Palacio]], American [[basketball]] player
*[[Nathan Jawai]], Australian [[NBA]] Basketball player, currently with the [[Minnesota Timberwolves]]

==See also==
{{Empty section|date=June 2010}}
==References==
{{reflist}}

==External links==
* [http://www.midland.edu/ Official Midland College website]
* [http://www.midlandcollegefoundation.org/ Midland College Foundation website]
* [http://www.gochaps.com/ Official MC Athletics website]
* [http://www.midlandcollegepress.com/ MC student publications website]

{{coord missing|Texas}}

[[Category:Universities and colleges in Texas]]
[[Category:Education in Midland, Texas]]
[[Category:Universities and colleges accredited by the Southern Association of Colleges and Schools]]
[[Category:Community colleges in Texas]]
[[Category:Education in Midland County, Texas]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
