<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="1107703" ns="0" title="Catastrophic failure"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">A '''catastrophic failure''' is a sudden and total failure of some [[system]] from which recovery is impossible. Catastrophic failures often lead to [[Cascading failure|cascading systems failure]].

The term is most commonly used for structural failures, but has often been extended to many other  disciplines where total and irrecoverable loss occurs. Such failures are investigated using the methods of [[forensic engineering]], which aims to isolate the cause or causes of failure. 

==Structural failure==
[[Image:Original_Tay_Bridge_before_the_1879_collapse.jpg|thumb|left|300px|Original Tay Bridge from the north]]
[[Image:Tay bridge down.JPG|thumb|left|300px|Fallen Tay Bridge from the north]]
Examples of catastrophic failure of engineered structures include:
 
* The [[Tay Rail Bridge disaster]] of 1879, where the center half mile of the bridge was completely destroyed while a train was crossing in a storm. The bridge was badly designed and its replacement was built as a separate structure upstream of the old.
* The failure of the [[South Fork Dam]] in 1889 released 4.8 billion US gallons of water and killed over 2,200 people (popularly known as the [[Johnstown Flood]]).
* The failure of the [[St. Francis Dam]] in 1928 released 12 billion US gallons of water, resulting in an official death toll of 385 people.
* The collapse of the first [[Tacoma Narrows Bridge (1940)|Tacoma Narrows Bridge]] of 1940, where the main deck of the road bridge was totally destroyed by dynamic oscillations in a 40 mph wind.
* The [[De Havilland Comet#Comet disasters of 1954|De Havilland Comet disasters of 1954]], later determined to be structural failures due to unanticipated metal fatigue at the corners of square windows used by the Comet 1.
* The 62 [[Banqiao Dam]]s failure event in China in 1975, due to [[Typhoon Nina]]. Approximately 86,000 people died from flooding and another 145,000 died during subsequent disease, total of 231,000 deaths.
* The [[Hyatt Regency walkway collapse]] of 1981, where a suspended walkway in a hotel lobby collapsed completely, killing many people on the structure and those below. 
* The [[STS-51-L|Space Shuttle Challenger]] of 1986, in which an O-ring of the rocket booster failed, and the entire vehicle was lost.
* The fire at the [[Chernobyl nuclear disaster]], which exploded in 1986 and caused substantial emissions of [[radioactive]] materials.  
* The collapse of the [[Warsaw radio mast]] of 1991, which had up to that point held the title of [[world's tallest structure]].
* The attack and subsequent fire at the [[World Trade Center]] on September 11th, 2001 is believed to have weakened the [[Joist|floor joist]] to the point of catastrophic failure.
* The [[STS-107|Space Shuttle Columbia]] of 2003, where damage to a wing caused at take-off resulted in total loss on re-entry.
* The total collapse of the multi-span [[I-35W Mississippi River Bridge]] on August 1, 2007

==Catastrophic failure in centrifugal pumps==
A catastrophic failure of a [[centrifugal pump]] can occur if the liquid within the pump casing is allowed to vaporize. To prevent flashing due to overheating of the fluid, a flow must be maintained through the pump to keep the liquid below saturation temperature.

If a temperature rise of 15°F is accepted in the casing - minimum flow through a centrifugal pump can be calculated as

q = PBHP / 2.95 • cp • SG         (1)

where 
* q = minimum [[flow rate]] (gpm)
* PBHP = power input (BHP)
* cp = specific heat capacity (Btu/lb °F)
* SG = [[specific gravity]] of the fluid

==Computer failure==
The term catastrophic failure is occasionally used in computer software to indicate an [[Crash (computing)|unexpected error]] from which the system [[Fatal error|cannot meaningfully recover]]. This usually results in a [[screen of death]]. This however, is likely to be recovered by a simple pressing of the reset button, unlike most of the examples above.

==See also==
*[[List of bridge disasters]]
*[[Seismic performance]]
*[[Structural collapse]]
*[[Structural failure]]
*[[Mechanical resonance#Resonance disaster|Resonance disaster]]
*[[Risks to civilization, humans and planet Earth]]

==References==
*  [[Richard Feynman]], [[Ralph Leighton]] (contributor), W. W. Norton, ''[[What Do You Care What Other People Think?]]'', 1988, ISBN 0-553-17334-0
* Peter R. Lewis, ''Beautiful Railway Bridge of the Silvery Tay: Reinvestigating the Tay Bridge Disaster of 1879'', Tempus, 2004, ISBN 0-7524-3160-9


[[Category:Construction terminology]]
[[Category:Civil engineering]]
[[Category:Failure]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
