<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="11103651" ns="0" title="List of EastEnders characters (2007)"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{DISPLAYTITLE:List of ''EastEnders'' characters (2007)}}
The following is a list of characters that first appeared in the [[BBC]] [[soap opera]] ''[[EastEnders]]'' in 2007, by order of first appearance.
{{TOClimit|limit=2}}

== DI Kelly ==
{{Infobox soap character 2 | series = EastEnders
|name=DI Kelly
|portrayer=[[Ian Burfield]]
|creator=
|years=2007–08, 2010
|first= 1 January 2007
|last = 13 July 2010
|occupation=[[Detective Inspector]]
}}
'''Detective Inspector Kelly''' is a [[detective inspector|police detective]] at Walford Police Station. In 2007, he investigates the death of [[Pauline Fowler]] and subsequently arrests [[Sonia Fowler]] for her murder following the funeral. He arrests [[May Wright]] for abducting Summer Swann, and also [[Phil Mitchell]] on suspicion of murdering his fiancée [[Stella Crawford]]. He appears when he is investigating [[Jay Brown]]'s stabbing. In August 2008 he investigates the murder of [[Jase Dyer]] by interrogating [[Billy Mitchell (EastEnders)|Billy Mitchell]] as a key witness. In July 2010 he informs [[Liz Turner]] that a body found in [[Albert Square]] is that of her son [[Owen Turner|Owen]], and takes his ex-wife [[Denise Johnson]] in for questioning. Denise is released without charge. Kelly later informs Denise's family that her car has been discovered abandoned by a canal, and then that the body of a woman was pulled from the canal along with Denise's mobile phone. Lucas identifies the body as Denise's, however, Kelly still believes somebody else was involved in Owen's murder. It soon transpires that the body was not Denise's but a prostitute Lucas had killed and that Lucas was Owen's real killer.
{{-}}

==Adam Childe==
&lt;!-- {{Infobox soap character 2 | series = EastEnders
|name=Adam Childe
|portrayer=[[Matthew Ashforde]]
|creator=[[Christopher Reason]]
|years=2007
|appeared=8 January 2007
|occupation=[[Solicitor]]
}} --&gt;
'''Adam Childe''' played by '''Matthew Ashforde''', is a [[duty solicitor]] who was assigned to represent [[Sonia Fowler]] when she was arrested on suspicion of the murder of her ex-mother-in-law, [[Pauline Fowler|Pauline]], although he first thought she was Sonia Bailey, arrested for shoplifting. He was nervous, and made comments about wanting to murder his mother, ironic to the situation. Sonia was relieved when [[Phil Mitchell]] paid for [[Ritchie Scott]] to represent her instead of Adam.
{{-}}

==Anna Price==
&lt;!-- {{Infobox soap character 2 | series = EastEnders
|name=Anna Price
|portrayer=[[Mandana Jones]]
|creator=[[Dominic Treadwell-Collins]]
|years=2007
|first=15 February 2007
|last=16 February 2007
|occupation= [[Marriage]] [[Family therapy|counsellor]]
}} --&gt;
'''Anna Price''' was the [[marriage]] [[Family therapy|counsellor]] for [[Max Branning|Max]] and [[Tanya Branning]] who appeared on 15 February and 16 February 2007.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;[http://www.digitalspy.co.uk/article/ds41368.html Mandana Jones in EastEnders? UPDATED]&quot;, ''Digital Spy'', URL last accessed 8 January 2006&lt;/ref&gt;
{{-}}

==Derek Evans==
{{Infobox soap character 2 | series = EastEnders
|name=Derek Evans
|portrayer=[[Simon Lowe]]
|years=2007–10
|creator=[[Julia Gilbert]]
|first=1 March 2007
|last=6 August 2010
|occupation=[[Social worker]]
}}
'''Derek Evans''' is a [[social worker]], played by [[Simon Lowe]]. In March 2007, he visits [[Bert Atkinson]] and his grandson [[Jay Brown]], when Bert is trying to get a residency order for Jay to live with him permanently. Jay charms Derek, offering him a cup of tea and talking to him politely, impressing him. In January 2008, Derek visits [[Tanya Branning]] and her sister [[Rainie Cross]]. On October that year, he attempts to sort out Jay's foster care problems when [[Billy Mitchell (EastEnders)|Billy Mitchell]] offers to care for him, as Jay does not want [[Dawn Swann]] to be his foster mother. Derek inspects the flat above [[The Queen Victoria]] [[public house]], and allows Jay to stay with Billy, despite [[Roxy Slater]]'s messiness. In July 2009, he visits [[Denise Wicks]] after [[Jordan Johnson]]'s mother [[Trina Johnson|Trina]] reports her to the police, claiming that Denise has been abusing Jordan. In June 2010, he visits [[Phil Mitchell]] to assess his family including his children [[Louise Mitchell|Louise]] and [[Ben Mitchell (EastEnders)|Ben]], who has assaulted Jordan. The following month he visits Phil and Peggy to say that Louise's mother [[Lisa Fowler]] has made an application to see her daughter. Derek explains that the final decision is not up to Phil and Peggy says that Derek is a typical social worker – an interfering, homewrecking busybody. Derek responds sarcastically and leaves. When Peggy returns Louise to Lisa, they contact Derek again, and when he arrives, Phil steals his bag to get Lisa's address.
{{-}}

==Jed==
{{Infobox soap character 2 | series = EastEnders
|name=Jed
|portrayer=[[Burn Gorman]]
|creator=[[Julia Honour]]
|years=2007
|appeared=9 March 2007
|death=9 March 2007
|daughters=Jade
}}
'''Jed''' was discovered by [[Kevin Wicks]] on [[Dungeness (headland)|Dungeness]] beach. He had been left there the night before while on his stag party. Kevin took Jed to the local pub where Jed told Kevin he was getting married the next week and had a daughter named Jade. He told Kevin he was a bad father, so Kevin told him to sort out his life. Kevin told Jed he had no children and showed him his ferry ticket to [[France]]. Jed then stole Kevin's bag and ticket and got on a bus. Kevin stole a bicycle from outside the pub to follow the bus.

When Kevin caught up to the bus, he discovered it had been involved in an accident. He got on the bus to find several dead bodies, but Jed was missing. Kevin got off the bus and Jed appeared with blood pouring down his face. Jed then fell to the floor and Kevin held him as he died.
{{-}}

==Carl Talbot==
{{Infobox soap character 2 | series = EastEnders
|name=Carl Talbot
|portrayer=[[Alan Cooke]]
|creator=[[David Fox (writer)|David Fox]]
|years=2007
|appeared=20 March 2007
|occupation=[[Bailiff]]
}}
'''Carl Talbot''' was a [[bailiff]] who was sent to claim money from [[Billy Mitchell (EastEnders)|Billy Mitchell]], who was in debt. When Talbot arrived at Walford Video, Billy's shop, Billy lied and said that he was not Billy Mitchell. His cover was blown when [[Keith Miller (EastEnders)|Keith Miller]] came into the shop and called him by his name. Talbot took Billy to the [[Automated teller machine|ATM]] at the [[Walford East tube station|tube station]], but Billy's card was retained by the machine, and after a confrontation with Billy's relative [[Phil Mitchell|Phil]] outside the shop, Billy was forced to give Talbot money from the till.
{{-}}

==Marco Bianco==
{{Infobox soap character 2 | series = EastEnders
|name=Marco Bianco
|portrayer=[[Bart Ruspoli]]
|years=2007
|first=20 March 2007
|last=16 July 2007
|occupation=[[Interior design]]er
}}
'''Marco Bianco''' is the [[interior design]]er who redesigned the flat above [[The Queen Victoria]] pub for [[Peggy Mitchell]]. He worked on the design to renovate the pub itself, after [[Pat Evans]] found a [[flea]] on the bar, though the regulars thought the pub looked the same, and Peggy berated him for it.

Since then, Marco has made a few more appearances, as Peggy got him to do some work for Stella and Phil's wedding reception. He has also helped Patrick Trueman mend a fan of Yolande's that Patrick broke by tripping up.

Marco has also been shown to be homosexual, as he broke down crying to Peggy, when his boyfriend left him.
{{-}}

==Danny Fuller==
{{Infobox soap character 2 | series = EastEnders
|name=Danny Fuller
|portrayer=[[Gyuri Sarossy]]
|years=2007
|creator=[[Richard Zajdlic]]
|first=5 April 2007
|last=30 August 2007
|home=Outside of Walford
|wife=[[#Jess Fuller|Jess Fuller]]
|daughters=Megan Fuller
}}
'''Danny Fuller''' and his wife [[#Jess Fuller|Jess]] appeared in [[Walford]] in April 2007, when they rented 55 Victoria Road from [[Ian Beale]], when he and his family moved to 45 Albert Square. [[Phil Mitchell]] told them of the crime around Walford - the murders of [[Dennis Rickman]] and [[Pauline Fowler]] - and Danny bartered with Ian, demanding that he reduce the rent price by 30%. Ian later accepted this, and asked Danny to tell his daughter [[Lucy Beale|Lucy]] this, so she knew she could not move back to number 55.

Danny left the Square when his daughter secured a place at a private school. Danny and his family relocated to be closer to their daughter's new school.
{{-}}

==Jess Fuller==
{{Infobox soap character 2 | series = EastEnders
|name=Jess Fuller
|years=2007
|creator=[[Richard Zajdlic]]
|appeared=5 April 2007
|home=Outside of Walford
|husband=[[#Danny Fuller|Danny Fuller]]
|daughters=Megan Fuller
}}
'''Jessica &quot;Jess&quot; Fuller''' and her husband [[#Danny Fuller|Danny]] appeared in [[Walford]] in April 2007, when they rented 55 Victoria Road from [[Ian Beale]], when he and his family moved to 45 Albert Square. [[Phil Mitchell]] told them of the crime around Walford - the murders of [[Dennis Rickman]] and [[Pauline Fowler]] - and Ian had to reduce the rent price by 30%.
{{-}}

==Vince Franks==
{{Infobox soap character 2 | series = EastEnders
|name=Vince Franks
|portrayer=[[Jamie Kenna]]
|creator=[[Richard Zajdlic]]
|years=2007
|appeared=6 April 2007
|home=89a George Street
|sons=[[Jez Franks]]
}}
'''Vince &quot;Vinnie&quot; Franks''' was the father of school bully [[Jez Franks]]. He was attacked by [[Phil Mitchell]] after Jez bullied Phil's son [[Ben Mitchell (EastEnders)|Ben]]. When Phil first approached Vince, he seemed sceptical about his son's bullying, so Phil punched him, threatening to attack him again if Jez didn't lay off Ben.
{{-}}

==Mary Lavender==
{{Infobox soap character 2 | series = EastEnders
|name=Mary Lavender
|portrayer=[[Regina Freedman]]
|creator=[[Christopher Reason]]
|years=2007
|appeared=9 April 2007
|home=[[Kent]]
}}
'''The Reverend Mary Lavender''' was the vicar for the church that [[Dot Branning]] used to attend with her friend, Margot Baker. She had been the vicar since 2000. When Dot and her husband [[Jim Branning|Jim]] visited Kent, Dot went to the church and Reverend Lavender informed her that Margot had died two weeks previously. She told Dot that Margot's son [[#Douglas Baker|Douglas]] was at Margot's house, and Dot visited him. 

A young refugee named [[#Anya Covalenco|Anya Covalenco]] left her son [[#Tomas Covalenco|Tomas]] in the church for Reverend Lavender to take in, but Dot took him back to [[Walford]] because Mary was on holiday.
{{-}}

==Douglas Baker==
{{Infobox soap character 2 | series = EastEnders
|name=Douglas Baker
|portrayer=[[Paul Kaye]]
|creator=[[Christopher Reason]]
|years=2007
|born=circa 1964
|appeared=9 April 2007
|mother=Margot Baker
}}
'''Douglas Baker''' is a former vicar who lost his faith in [[God]]. His mother, Margot, was friends with [[Dot Branning]]. He was also a former playmate of Dot's son [[Nick Cotton|Nick]], until Nick put a frog down his trousers. Margot died in March 2007, and Douglas was clearing out her house when Dot visited him. They argued about religion, and Dot reminded Douglas of his mother. He told Dot he was glad his mother was dead, and said that Nick would feel the same when she died.
{{-}}

==Anya Covalenco==
{{Infobox soap character 2 | series = EastEnders
|name=Anya Covalenco
|portrayer=[[Olga Fedori]]
|creator=[[Diederick Santer]]
|years=2007
|first=9 April 2007
|last=13 April 2007
|born=February 1985
|occupation=Pole dancer
|sons=[[#Tomas Covalenco|Tomas Covalenco]]
}}
'''Anya Covalenco''' ([[Ukranian language|Ukrainian]]: Аня Коваленко) was a [[Ukraine|Ukrainian]] illegal immigrant, a pole dancer who abandoned her month-old baby, [[#Tomas Covalenco|Tomas]], in a church in Kent for vicar [[#Mary Lavender|Mary Lavender]] to look after. [[Dot Branning]] later found the baby, and knowing Reverend Lavender was on holiday, took Tomas back to [[Walford]], leaving a note in the church with her address on it. Dot's husband [[Jim Branning|Jim]] went to a pole dancing club, finding a flyer for it with Tomas, to track Anya down, but was told she no longer worked there by a hostess he spoke to. As Jim travelled back to Walford, Anya turned up at Dot and Jim's house. After shouting at Dot for interfering, Dot offered her a place to stay, and she accepted. Jim, however, did not agree with this, and reported her to the immigration authorities. Immigration arrived and Jim told Dot what he had done. Dot took Anya and Tomas out of the house and hid them in the back of her car. Dot returned to the house and told immigration that there was nobody there and it must have been a hoax. Dot and Jim then took Anya and Tomas to a church, believing it to be a sanctuary where they would be safe. The immigration officers followed them to the church, where Dot said Anya and Tomas would be safe in a room at the back of the church and could live there. Dot confronted the officers, [[#Paul Jenkins|Paul Jenkins]] and [[#Warren Rice|Warren Rice]] telling them it was a sanctuary and they couldn't go through. Rice told Dot she was wrong about this. Anya eventually decided to give herself up, but told Jim to take care of Tomas as she now trusted them. She later wrote to Dot in June 2007, telling her to care for her son - not knowing that Tomas is now up for adoption, when Dot realised that she cannot bring up baby Tomas.
{{-}}

==Tomas Covalenco==
{{Infobox soap character 2 | series = EastEnders
|name=Tomas Covalenco
|image=
|portrayer=Dylan Woolf&lt;br /&gt;Tyler Woolf&lt;br /&gt;Joshua Wing
|creator=[[Diederick Santer]]
|years=2007
|first=9 April 2007
|last=8 June 2007
|born= 28 February 2007
|mother=[[#Anya Covalenco|Anya Covalenco]]
}}
'''Tomas Covalenco''' (Ukrainian: Томас Коваленко) was abandoned on 9 April 2007 by his mother, [[#Anya Covalenco|Anya]] in a church in Kent, and found by [[Dot Branning]], who believed that [[Jesus]] had given her a second chance to be a good mother, after she aborted a baby at 21, and her son [[Nick Cotton|Nick]] grew up a criminal. Dot left her address on a notice board in the church, and Anya arrived in [[Walford]] to collect her son on 10 April. She was later arrested by immigration officials [[#Warren Rice|Warren Rice]] and [[#Paul Jenkins|Paul Jenkins]] for being an illegal immigrant, but didn't tell them she had a baby, leaving him with Dot and [[Jim Branning|Jim]]. Jim later told [[Branning family|his family]] that Tomas was the product of an affair between Nick and a prison nurse with no maternal instincts. He was then known as '''George Merton''', until Dot was persuaded by Reverend Stevens and her oldest friend, [[Harold Legg]] to tell Social Services that she had him. He was collected on 8 June by social worker [[#Natasha Powell|Natasha Powell]].
{{-}}

==Hazel Hobbs==
{{Infobox soap character 2 | series = EastEnders
|image= 
|name=Hazel Hobbs
|portrayer=[[Kika Mirylees]]
|creator=[[Diederick Santer]]
|years=2007–08
|first=10 April 2007
|last=24 April 2008
|born=1955
|classification=[[List of past EastEnders characters#Last appeared in 2008|Former; regular]]
|home=Outside [[Walford]]
|occupation=[[Entertainer|Cruise Ship entertainer]]
|sons= [[Garry Hobbs]]
|granddaughters= Vivienne Hobbs
|cousins= Reg 
}}
'''Hazel Hobbs''' was played by [[Kika Mirylees]].&lt;ref name=&quot;mirror&quot;&gt;&quot;[http://www.mirror.co.uk/news/topstories/tm_method=full%26objectid=18393908%26siteid=94762-name_page.html Bad Girl heads to Albert Square]&quot;, ''The Mirror'', URL last accessed 5 January 2007&lt;/ref&gt; She left Walford on 4 February 2008, but returned 21 April, when she was seen reading about Heather and Minty in the magazine they were taking part in. She made her final appearance on 24 April 2008.

Hazel is the mother of [[Garry Hobbs]], and first appeared in April 2007, when Garry attended her wedding. She then decided she didn't want to marry her fiancé, Gerald, because he had too much nasal hair, describing it as &quot;like tusks&quot;. She and Garry rushed back to Gerald's house to collect her belongings, but Gerald arrived at the house before they left, and hit Garry, thinking he was Hazel's toyboy.

Hazel then went to stay with Garry in [[Walford]], falling for his best friend [[Minty Peterson]], before Garry hit Minty and Hazel left Walford.

In August 2007, it was revealed that Hazel and Minty had started a relationship behind Garry's back. They took a romantic weekend in [[Brighton]] but did not know that Garry was also there with [[Dawn Swann]]. Garry found out they were seeing each other and was outraged. Back in Walford, Minty found found the engagement ring that Garry had used to propose to Dawn (she said no) and bent down to pick it up off the floor. He was on one knee, holding the ring, when Hazel came in the room. She assumed that Minty was planning to propose to her and immediately said &quot;Yes, I do&quot;. They have since been planning the wedding, and she got a job as a receptionist at Booty.

On 18 October 2007, Hazel was left devastated when Minty took what was thought to be a heart attack whilst trying to lose weight for their wedding. However, after he was checked out at the hospital it turned out that he had only pulled a muscle in his arm, which left her relieved. She then befriended [[Heather Trott]], who is infatuated with her son Garry, and has been trying to put her off him. On 25 October, Hazel then asked an elated Heather to be her bridesmaid at her upcoming wedding to Minty, to which she accepted.

On 28 January 2008, [[Shirley Carter]] went to the salon to berate Hazel because she replaced Heather as her bridesmaid with [[Dawn Swann]] so that she could increase her chances of winning the contest with a glamorous bridesmaid. During the row, Hazel fainted but Shirley caught her. She later told Minty that she was pregnant. He bought lots of things for the baby but Hazel tearfully revealed on 1 February 2008 that it was the [[menopause]], and she could never have a baby. 

Hazel left the square on 4 February 2008, after experiencing her menopause and realising that she would be restricting Minty's future desires to have a family if she stayed with him. She returned on 22 April 2008 and proposed to Minty on his wedding morning to Heather. Hazel told him that they'd get married and set for a life on the cruise ships but he said no. He then ran after Heather and proposed to her for real. Hazel watched as the wedding went ahead without her and said goodbye to Garry and left.

Hazel was last mentioned a year later on 9 February 2009 when Minty heard that Garry was going to join her to work for the cruise liner however Garry thought he should propose to Dawn again. However when that was unsuccessful for the second time, Garry was presumed dead a week later; when his car was discovered at a popular suicide spot, Dawn and Minty decided to send Garry's personal belongings to Hazel. Minty last heard that her cruise ship was heading for [[Monaco]].
{{-}}

==Paul Jenkins==
{{Infobox soap character 2 | series = EastEnders
|name=Paul Jenkins
|portrayer=[[Simon Quarterman]]
|creator=[[Sarah Phelps]]
|years=2007
|appeared=13 April 2007
|occupation=Immigration official
}}
'''Paul Jenkins''' was an immigration official, acting on a tip-off from [[Jim Branning]], who searched 25 Albert Square for illegal immigrant [[#Anya Covalenco|Anya Covalenco]]. When [[Dot Branning]] returned home, after hiding Anya, she asked him to leave. He later followed Jim, Dot and Anya to a church, where he branded Dot a &quot;religious nut&quot;, and was told to back off by his superior, [[#Warren Rice|Warren Rice]]. He later took Anya away when she gave herself up, not knowing she had left her son [[#Tomas Covalenco|Tomas]] with Jim and Dot.
{{-}}

==Warren Rice==
{{Infobox soap character 2 | series = EastEnders
|name=Warren Rice
|portrayer=[[Ewan Bailey]]
|creator=[[Sarah Phelps]]
|years=2007
|appeared=13 April 2007
|occupation=Immigration official
}}
'''Warren Rice''' was a senior immigration official, acting on a tip-off from [[Jim Branning]], who followed Jim, [[Dot Branning|Dot]] and illegal immigrant [[#Anya Covalenco|Anya]] to a church, where he berated his junior, [[#Paul Jenkins|Paul Jenkins]] when he branded Dot a &quot;religious nut&quot;. He then explained to Dot that under British law, churches are not a sanctuary.
{{-}}

==Olive Woodhouse==
{{Infobox soap character 2 | series = EastEnders
|name=Olive Woodhouse
|portrayer=[[Sylvia Syms]]
|introducer= [[Diederick Santer]]
|years= 2007, 2009–10
|first= 17 April 2007
|last=20 July 2010
|occupation= Bridal shop owner and dress fitter 
}}
'''Olive Woodhouse'''&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.bbc.co.uk/programmes/b00t6npv|title=20/07/2010|publisher=[[BBC Programmes]]|accessdate=12 July 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; is a friend of [[Peggy Mitchell]]'s whom she has known since childhood. She is a dress fitter and first appears fitting [[Stella Crawford]]'s wedding dress in April 2007, and criticises her taste, making her angry.

She returns on 5 March 2009 to fit Peggy's wedding dress and she takes an instant dislike to Peggy's niece and future stepdaughter [[Roxy Mitchell|Roxy]]. The wedding dress she creates for Peggy is slightly provocative and Peggy's fiancé [[Archie Mitchell|Archie]] sees the plans and purposely walks in, seeing Peggy in the dress, making her want to change it in fear of bad luck. She then notices [[Janine Butcher]] following Archie and grows suspicious, thinking they are having an affair. She asks Archie, who then tells her that now they are paying for another dress, he wants to make some changes making the new dress less revealing.

She returns again in 2010,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.digitalspy.co.uk/soaps/scoop/a240722/ronnies-wedding-dress-johns-punched-nikhils-girl.html|title=Ronnie's wedding dress, John's punched, Nikhil's girl|last=Green|first=Kris|date=11 July 2010|publisher=[[Digital Spy]]|accessdate=10 July 2010|location=London}}&lt;/ref&gt; when Peggy, Roxy, Roxy's sister [[Ronnie Mitchell|Ronnie]] and Ronnie and Roxy's mother [[Glenda Mitchell|Glenda]] arrive at her bridal shop to find a dress for Ronnie's wedding to [[Jack Branning]]. Olive feels insulted when Roxy insults the dresses. When Ronnie finds a dress she likes, Olive returns with them to [[The Queen Victoria]] to make adjustments.
{{-}}

==Verity Wright==
{{Infobox soap character 2 | series = EastEnders
|name=Verity Wright
|portrayer=[[Amanda Ryan]]
|years=2007
|creator=[[Diederick Santer]]
|first=1 May 2007
|last=28 May 2007
|sisters=[[May Wright]]
|husband=Richard
|sons=James
|daughters=Esther
}}
'''Verity Wright''' is the sister of [[Walford]]'s former [[general practitioner]], [[May Wright]]. She visited May with her two children on 1 May 2007, when she found the nursery in May's flat meant for [[Dawn Swann]]'s baby, presuming May was pregnant.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;[http://www.bbc.co.uk/eastenders/episodes/past/episode20070501.shtml#2 Dot's secret's in danger]&quot;, ''bbc.co.uk/eastenders'', URL last accessed 7 May 2007&lt;/ref&gt; She later visited May on her birthday, and was shocked to find out that [[Rob Minter|Rob]] had filed for divorce from May.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;[http://www.bbc.co.uk/eastenders/episodes/past/episode20070504.shtml#2 May's torment]&quot;, ''bbc.co.uk/eastenders'', URL last accessed 7 May 2007&lt;/ref&gt; She returned once more on 28 May to visit May and give her a present for the baby she thinks she is having.
{{-}}

==Manju Patel==
{{Infobox soap character 2 | series = EastEnders 
|image= 
|name=Manju Patel
|portrayer=[[Leena Dhingra]]
|creator=[[Alexander Lamb]]
|introducer=[[Diederick Santer]] 
|years=2007
|first=4 May 2007
|last=20 December 2007
|occupation=[[Shopkeeper]]
}}
'''Manju Patel''' was originally a guest character, Mrs Patel's primary purpose was as a plot device in the exit of nurse [[Naomi Julien]], after the actress [[Petra Letang]] left the show.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;[http://www.mirror.co.uk/tvandfilm/tvland/tm_method=full%26objectid=18500094%26siteid=94762-name_page.html Letangoed!]&quot;, ''The Mirror'', URL last accessed 19 January 2007&lt;/ref&gt; However, following her two appearances on 4 May and 21 May 2007, she became popular with fans, to the point where she has been called a &quot;cult icon&quot; by ''[[Digital Spy]]'' soaps editor Kris Green.&lt;ref name=&quot;scoop&quot;&gt;&quot;[http://www.digitalspy.co.uk/soaps/a71738/mrs-manju-patel-an-eastenders-legend.html EXCLUSIVE: Mrs Manju Patel - an 'EastEnders' legend?]&quot;, ''Digital Spy'', URL last accessed 16 August 2007&lt;/ref&gt; It was announced on 16 August 2007 that she would be return to the show later in 2007.&lt;ref name=&quot;scoop&quot;/&gt;
Mrs Patel was a patient of [[Walford]]'s [[general practitioner]], [[May Wright]]. May wrote out a double prescription for her, and took one of the bottles of [[dihydrocodeine]] pills for her own personal use. She later told nurse [[Naomi Julien]] that it was a mistake, after Mrs Patel pointed this out.

Mrs Patel was later mentioned on 9 August 2007 during a telephone conversation between [[Dot Branning]] and [[Charlie Slater]]. On 9 November it was revealed that Mrs Patel was [[Billy Mitchell (EastEnders)|Billy Mitchell]]'s new landlady. She gave him one month's notice to vacate the flat along with his wife [[Honey Mitchell|Honey]] and baby [[Janet Mitchell|Janet]] because she wanted a professional couple with no children to live there. Eventually, Mrs Patel decided to evict the couple from the flat. However, Billy changed the locks so Mrs Patel could not enter the flat. When Billy was out buying nappies, Mrs Patel got help from her nephews to get into the flat and remove Honey, the children and all their belongings. She offered Billy money as a good will gesture but Billy refused to accept it.

Though she does not appear again, Manju was mentioned on 13 May 2008 by [[Shabnam Masood]] who told her mother Zainab that she was going to see if Mrs Patel had any new clothes in her Sari shop. On 24 July Mrs Patel's shop was mentioned by [[Jane Beale]] when she was looking to buy some fabric for an Indian lunch that she and Husband Ian were holding at the cafe. They bought the material from Mrs Patel after seeing it although Mrs Patel wasn't shown. Mrs Patel was then mentioned on 24 March 2009 when [[Syd Chambers]] announced she was renting 13a Turpin Road, the flat above the bookies from her. In April 2010, she rents the flat to [[Syed Masood|Syed]] and [[Amira Shah|Amira Masood]].

{{-}}

==Erek==
{{Infobox soap character 2 | series = EastEnders
|name=Erek
|portrayer=[[Goran Kostic]]
|creator=[[Diederick Santer]]
|years=2007
|first=7 May 2007
|last=15 June 2007
|Occupation=Builder
}}
'''Erek''' was a Polish builder who first appeared on 7 May 2007. [[Ian Beale]] was annoyed by him and the other builders, and when a feud broke out between Ian and [[Phil Mitchell]], Erek helped Phil to humiliate Ian. He later started a relationship with [[Shirley Carter]] but it ended when Shirley's son [[Deano Wicks|Deano]] spoke badly about her, Erek punched him and Shirley then punched Erek.
{{-}}

==Warren Stamp==
{{Infobox soap character 2 | series = EastEnders
|name=Warren Stamp
|portrayer=[[Will Mellor]]
|creator=[[Alison Fisher]]
|years=2007
|first=28 May 2007
|last=31 May 2007
|occupation=Salesman
}}
'''Warren Stamp''' was a salesman who asked [[Preeti Choraria]] out on a date after trying to sell her supplies at Booty. He assaulted Preeti on a date leaving distinct bruises on her arm. A day later he went on a date with [[Carly Wicks]] where he put drugs in her drink in an attempt to rape her. She was rescued by [[Sean Slater]], and Warren ran away.
{{-}}

==Natasha Powell==
{{Infobox soap character 2 | series = EastEnders
|name=Natasha Powell
|portrayer=[[Natasha Gordon]]
|creator=[[Rob Gittins]]
|years=2007
|first=7 June 2007
|last=8 June 2007
|occupation=Social worker
}}
'''Natasha Powell''' was the social worker who arrived in [[Albert Square]] to collect [[#Tomas Covalenco|Tomas Covalenco]] from [[Dot Branning|Dot]] and [[Jim Branning]]'s house, after Dot phoned Social Services and told them that Tomas was the baby of an illegal immigrant, [[#Anya Covalenco|Anya]]. Dot ran away to [[Harold Legg]]'s house, but later returned and handed Tomas over to Natasha.
{{-}}

==Summer Swann==
{{Infobox soap character 2 | series = EastEnders
|image=
| name =Summer Swann
| portrayer = Daisy Fitter &lt;small&gt;(2007)&lt;/small&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Abbie Hackworth &lt;small&gt;(2007)&lt;/small&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Harry Swash &lt;small&gt;(2007)&lt;/small&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Isabella Hegarty &lt;small&gt;(2007–09)&lt;/small&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Rebecca Hegarty &lt;small&gt;(2007–09)&lt;/small&gt;
| creator=[[Diederick Santer]]
| years = 2007–09
| first = 21 June 2007
| last= 27 August 2009
| classification=[[List of past EastEnders characters#Last appeared in 2009|Former; recurring]]
| born = 19 June 2007&lt;!--Though the episode was transmitted on the 21st, it was set on the 19th. Please DO NOT change this--&gt;
| mother= [[Dawn Swann]]
| adoptivefather = [[Jase Dyer]]
| father=[[Rob Minter]]
| halfbrothers= [[Jay Brown]] &lt;small&gt;(adoptive)&lt;/small&gt;
| grandfathers= [[Mike Swann]]
| grandmothers= [[Rosie Miller]]
| uncles=[[Mickey Miller]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Darren Miller]]
| aunts=[[Demi Miller]]
| cousins=[[Aleesha Miller]] &lt;br /&gt; [[George Trott]]
}}
'''Summer Swann''' is the daughter of [[Dawn Swann]] and [[Rob Minter]]. She has previously been played by on-screen uncle [[Joe Swash]]'s son, Harry Swash,&lt;ref&gt;&quot;[http://www.thesun.co.uk/sol/homepage/showbiz/tv/article393690.ece Enders star on being TV mother]&quot;, ''The Sun'', URL last accessed 28 October 2007&lt;/ref&gt; Abbie Hackworth&lt;ref&gt;&quot;[http://www.thesun.co.uk/sol/homepage/news/article1275636.ece Toxic sofa burns TV star baby]&quot;, ''The Sun''. URL last accessed 11 June 2008&lt;/ref&gt; and Daisy Fitter, but is now played by twins Isabella and Rebecca Hegarty.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;[http://www.twinagency.com/index.php?pid=15&amp;showProduct=1&amp;start=156&amp;product_id=929&amp;theme=mooLarge&amp;opid=2 Isabella &amp; Rebecca Hegarty]&quot;&lt;/ref&gt; Along with actors [[Ricky Groves]] and [[Kara Tointon]], the character made her final appearance on 27 August 2009.

Summer was born on 19 June 2007 after her mother, Dawn, went into premature labour on the tube. Dawn made it to the hospital, where she safely delivered Summer with her best friend [[Carly Wicks]] by her side. 

Dawn initially found it hard to bond with Summer as she still wanted to go out partying. However during a trip to [[Brighton]] in August 2007 with Summer and [[Garry Hobbs]], Dawn accepted responsibility for her daughter and vowed to become a proper mother. As January 2008 approached, Summer saw her mother begin a relationship with builder [[Jase Dyer]], and began modelling for catalogues after Dawn took her to an audition. 

Dawn wanted Summer to be a model and entered her for the &quot;Beautiful Baby&quot; competition at [[the Queen Vic]] on her first birthday. Dawn put fake tan on Summer for the competition, which she later had an allergic reaction to, and was named runner-up at the end of the day.   

On Summer's birthday in June 2008 [[May Wright]] returned to Walford, intent on kidnapping Summer from her family. May was married to Summer's father, Rob, when she was conceived during an affair Rob had with Dawn and May, unable to have children, had never quite gotten over it. Upon seeing Summer in fake tan, May branded Dawn a terrible mother before attacking her and her brother [[Mickey Miller|Mickey]] and then trying to make her escape with Summer, who she called Sophie. However, Mickey rescued Summer and locked May out of the bedroom, leaving May trying to break down the door, screaming &quot;Sophie&quot;. Devastated, May went down to the kitchen and committed [[suicide]] by blowing the house up. Mickey then tried to throw Summer out the window but he dropped her when he passed out and Jase caught her. Dawn then pushed Mickey out of the window but passed out, so Keith rushed into the house and rescued her. All three were taken to hospital. Summer was declared healthy once checked on by doctors.

In July 2008, it was revealed that Jase had adopted Summer seen as Dawn had left the father section of her birth certificate blank.

More tragedy struck for Summer's family when her adoptive father, Jase, was murdered by members of a gang he used to run about with, on 26 August 2008. Dawn, Summer, Jase and his son [[Jay Brown|Jay]] had been living at 89b George Street but the flat was cordoned off by police so Dawn and Summer moved in with Garry whilst Jay went into care. However, being in Walford proved too much for Dawn and at the beginning of September she and Summer went to live with their family in the [[Cotswolds]]. Dawn returned to Walford on 6 October for Jase's funeral, leaving Summer with her grandmother [[Rosie Miller|Rosie]], and was adamant that she was returning to the Cotswolds in order to build a new life there with her daughter. However, after much persuasion from Garry, Dawn decided to stay in Walford and two weeks later, mother and daughter moved in with Garry and his flatmates [[Minty Peterson]] and [[Callum Monks]].

Dawn embarked on an affair with her boss [[Phil Mitchell]], but after this was revealed to Garry he decided to give her another chance and they left Walford together sailing on a boat.
{{-}}

==Kenny Morris==
{{Infobox soap character 2 
|series = EastEnders
|name=Kenny Morris
|portrayer=[[Ryan Philpott]]
|years=2007–09, 2011
|first=25 June 2007
|last=6 October 2011
|classification=[[List of past EastEnders characters#Last appeared in 2011|Former; recurring]]
|occupation=Police officer
}}
'''Sergeant Kenny Morris''' is a police officer who was originally introduced as an associate of [[Ian Beale]], who Ian gave free food to in his café, in return for an occasional police presence. He was later called to [[Shirley Carter]]'s flat when a party was getting out of hand. He broke up a fight and was almost hit by Shirley, however, he ended up staying the night and having sex with her.

He later appeared in September 2007, involved in the storyline in which [[Craig Dixon (EastEnders)|Craig Dixon]] attacked [[Patrick Trueman]] and [[Chelsea Fox]] and [[Deano Wicks]] tried to frame [[Sean Slater]] for the crime. In November 2007, [[Kevin Wicks]] sold Morris a stolen car. When [[Darren Miller]] told Kevin that the car was stolen and that Morris was a police officer, they stole the car from Morris and set it on fire. In October 2008, Morris returned to visit [[Stacey Slater]]'s stall after [[Ronnie Mitchell]] called the market inspector about them selling stolen clothes. He later appeared when [[Dawn Swann]] accused [[Jay Brown]] of trying to set fire to her house. He appeared again when [[Max Branning]] called the police following a faked burglary at his home. On 12 January 2009, Morris appeared when him and a colleague found [[Danielle Jones (EastEnders)|Danielle Jones]] sleeping rough on the Square.

He was first seen as a police constable, but later became a sergeant. On 15 January 2009, he appeared when the police had received complaints of a protest outside Gilly's Massage Parlour. &lt;!--what happened on 10 March 2009?--&gt; On 7 January 2011, he visits [[Phil Mitchell]] after his son [[Ben Mitchell (EastEnders)|Ben]] has been accused of pushing [[Glenda Mitchell]] down her stairs. Morris later visits Glenda to take a statement from her.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite episode |title= Episode dated 07/01/2011 |url=http://www.bbc.co.uk/programmes/b00x9zfw |series= EastEnders |serieslink=EastEnders |credits= Director: Mickey Jones; Executive Producer: Bryan Kirkwood; Writer: Paul Mari |network=[[BBC]] |station=[[BBC One]] |city= |airdate=7 January 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; He visits Phil again in October 2011, following complaints of grafitti.
{{-}}

==Heather Trott==
{{Main|Heather Trott}}

==Marion Crawford==
{{Infobox soap character 2 | series = EastEnders
| image = 
| name =Marion Crawford
| portrayer =[[Ann Firbank]]
| years = 2007
| appeared = 29 June 2007 
|classification=[[List of past EastEnders characters#Last appeared in 2007|Former; guest]]
| husband =[[Edward Crawford]]
| daughters =[[Stella Crawford]]&lt;br /&gt;Catherine Crawford
}}
'''Marion Crawford''' was the mother of [[Stella Crawford|Stella]] who appeared when Stella and her fiancé [[Phil Mitchell]] visited Marion and her husband [[#Edward Crawford|Edward]] to announce their engagement. She apologised for her husband's absence, lying that he was out playing golf. Phil, however, saw Edward hiding in another room. While Phil was out of the room, Marion told Stella that she shouldn't be left alone with Phil's son [[Ben Mitchell (EastEnders)|Ben]], and blamed her for the death of her other daughter, Catherine. After Phil and Stella left, Phil pretended to go back to the house to retrieve his lost phone, but instead confronted Edward for hiding from Stella. Marion then revealed that Catherine had died in Stella's care.
{{-}}

==Edward Crawford==
{{Infobox soap character 2 | series = EastEnders
| image =
| name =Edward Crawford
| portrayer = [[David Quilter]]
| years = 2007
| appeared = 29 June 2007
|classification=[[List of past EastEnders characters#Last appeared in 2007|Former; guest]]
| occupation = [[Queen's Counsel]]
| wife = [[Marion Crawford (EastEnders)|Marion Crawford]]
| daughters= [[Stella Crawford]]&lt;br /&gt;Catherine Crawford
}}
'''Edward Crawford''' is the father of [[Stella Crawford|Stella]], who appeared when Stella and her fiancé, [[Phil Mitchell]] visited Stella's parents. He hid in a room away from Stella, and was confronted by Phil when Phil realised he was there, not playing golf as his wife [[#Marion Crawford|Marion]] had told him. Edward revealed that he was estranged from Stella because he and his wife blamed her for the death of their other daughter, Catherine.
{{-}}

==Cheryl Andrews==
{{Infobox soap character 2 | series = EastEnders
| image =
| name =Cheryl Andrews
| portrayer = [[Charlotte Palmer]]
| years = 2007
| appeared = 3 July 2007
| husband = [[Tony Andrews]]
}}
'''Cheryl Andrews''' was the wife of [[Bradley Branning]]'s boss, [[List of EastEnders characters (2006)#Tony Andrews|Tony]], who attended a dinner party with Bradley and his girlfriend [[Stacey Branning|Stacey Slater]]. An East End girl herself, she got on with Stacey, and told her of the merits of being married to a banker, including living in [[Paris]].
{{-}}

==Charity Kase==
{{Infobox soap character 2 | series = EastEnders
| image =
| name =Charity Kase
| portrayer = [[Morgan Crowley]]
| years = 2007, 2009
| first = 9 July 2007
| last = 24 November 2009
| occupation = Drag artist
}}
'''Karl &quot;Charity Kase&quot;''' is an [[Ireland|Irish]] drag act employed by [[Peggy Mitchell]] for a night in [[The Queen Victoria]] public house. He sings &quot;[[Big Spender]]&quot; to [[Billy Mitchell (EastEnders)|Billy Mitchell]] ([[Perry Fenwick]]) and [[Bradley Branning]] ([[Charlie Clements (actor)|Charlie Clements]]), makes Bradley go up on stage and repeat his proposal to [[Stacey Slater]] ([[Lacey Turner]]) in front of the audience, and sings a duet with barmaid [[Shirley Carter]] ([[Linda Henry]]). After being to told by [[Sean Slater]] ([[Robert Kazinsky]]), he dresses up [[Deano Wicks]] ([[Matt Di Angelo]]) and making a fool of him.

He later appears when Shirley is in [[Brighton]] with her best friend [[Heather Trott]] ([[Cheryl Fergison]]) and they runs into him. He offers them a lift back to Walford because their car has been clamped.

In 2009, [[Kim Fox]] ([[Tameka Empson]]) books him for her sister [[Denise Johnson|Denise Wicks]]'s ([[Diane Parish]]) wedding to [[Lucas Johnson]] ([[Don Gilet]]). 
{{-}}

==Zainab Masood==
{{Main|Zainab Masood}}

==Shabnam Masood==
{{Main|Shabnam Masood}}

==Myra Sim==
{{Infobox soap character 2 | series = EastEnders 
|name=Myra Sim
|portrayer=[[Naomi Ryan]]
|years=2007, 2009
|first=17 July 2007
|last=28 December 2009
|occupation=[[Police officer]]
}}
'''Police Constable Myra Sim''' was the police officer who investigated [[Wellard]]'s kidnapping. She spoke to [[Mickey Miller]] and [[Gus Smith]], and found the recently-departed [[Li Chong (EastEnders)|Li Chong]]'s stash of dodgy mobile phones. Mickey asked her not to tell Gus about the phones, which she did not. When [[Bert Atkinson]] later plastered posters of Wellard around [[Walford]], she dealt with a complaint about them, telling Gus to take them down or he would be fined.

She appears again on 26 and 28 December 2009 following the murder of [[Archie Mitchell]],&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.bbc.co.uk/programmes/b00pl715 BBC.co.uk]&lt;/ref&gt; questioning [[Bradley Branning]] and [[Stacey Slater]].
{{-}}

==Jase Dyer==
{{Main|Jase Dyer}}

==Jasmine Field==
&lt;!--{{Infobox soap character 2 | series = EastEnders 
|name=Jasmine Field
|portrayer=[[Karen Ascoe]]
|years=2007, 2010
|first=24 July 2007
|last=12 February 2010
|occupation=[[Police officer]]
}}--&gt;
'''Detective Constable Jasmine Field''', played by [[Karen Ascoe]], is a police officer who, along with her partner [[#Tony Webster|PC Tony Webster]], interviews [[Ben Mitchell (EastEnders)|Ben Mitchell]] on 24 July 2007 following months of abuse from his father [[Phil Mitchell|Phil]]'s fiancée [[Stella Crawford]]. 

She returns on 11 February 2010&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.bbc.co.uk/programmes/b00qp0by|title=EastEnders 11/02/2010|publisher=[[BBC Online]]|accessdate=4 February 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; when she enters [[The Queen Victoria]] with other officers and walks over to the table where the [[Branning family|Brannings]] are sitting. She arrests [[Dot Branning]] for assaulting her granddaughter [[Dotty Cotton]], but releases her without charge as Dot is Dotty's primary carer.
{{-}}

==Tony Webster==
&lt;!--{{Infobox soap character 2 | series = EastEnders 
|name=Tony Webster
|portrayer=
|years=2007
|appeared=24 July 2007
|occupation=[[Police officer]]
}}--&gt;
'''Police Constable Tony Webster''' was the police officer who, along with his partner [[#Jasmine Field|DC Jasmine Field]], interviewed [[Ben Mitchell (EastEnders)|Ben Mitchell]] following months of abuse from his father [[Phil Mitchell|Phil]]'s fiancée [[Stella Crawford]].
{{-}}

==Roxy Mitchell==
{{Main|Roxy Mitchell}}

==Ronnie Mitchell==
{{Main|Ronnie Mitchell}}

==Craig Dixon==
{{Infobox soap character 2 | series = EastEnders
| name =Craig Dixon
| portrayer =[[Rory Jennings]]
| introducer=[[Diederick Santer]]
| years = 2007
| first = 27 July 2007
| last =  7 September 2007
| classification= [[List of past EastEnders characters#Last appeared in 2007|Former, guest]]
| born = 20 July 1989 
}}
'''Craig Dixon''' arrived in [[Albert Square]] for an interview with [[Ian Beale]], to work in Ian's chip shop. Ian employed Craig indifferently while busy cleaning up after his son, [[Bobby Beale (EastEnders)|Bobby]]. Ian's daughter, [[Lucy Beale|Lucy]], liked Craig and they started dating in secret. 

On 3 August 2007, it was revealed that Craig had a [[gun]] in the [[glove compartment]] of his car. On 6 August, [[Lauren Branning]] invited him and Lucy to her house and they played truth or dare. Craig and Lucy left when they were interrupted by Lauren's sister, [[Abi Branning|Abi]]. Craig later dared Lucy to shoplift from the Minute Mart. Craig also had a minor disagreement with [[Patrick Trueman]] when purchasing alcohol from the Minute Mart.

Ian found out about Lucy and Craig from Jane and Lauren at a party. Ian rushed to find Lucy and [[Max Branning]] offered to help. Ian and Max found Lucy and Craig in bed at Craig's flat. Craig was warned by Max whilst Lucy was told to button her top and get out. The next day after taking Lucy home, Ian reported the incident to the [[police]] and Craig was cautioned, much to Ian's annoyance. He visited Craig and gave him £300 to leave his daughter alone. Lucy and Craig later met in secret. Lucy took the cash and warned Craig that she would tell people about him if he didn't do what she wanted.

It was later revealed that it was Craig who attacked [[Patrick Trueman]]. A tape discovered by [[Kevin Wicks]], showed him hitting Patrick over the head. [[Sean Slater]], who had also disagreed with Patrick, was charged with the crime. On the same day, it was revealed that Craig and Lucy had got back together. 

When Lucy [[truancy|played truant]], she went to see Craig and got into his car, almost discovering his gun, but he stopped her by saying there was a wasp in her hair and quickly changing the subject.

On 6 September, Craig and Lucy ran away to a hotel. When Craig came out the shower topless, he made it clear that he wanted to have sex but she threw her drink on him and locked herself in the bathroom. She rung Ian on her mobile but Ian, Jane and Peter had gone looking for her so they never got the call. She left a message but it was cut short when her battery ran out. She persuaded Craig to leave the hotel by saying they would steal money from Ian. Lucy ran to her father, pretending to cry, and told the police that Craig attacked Patrick. Craig was arrested for [[attempted murder]] and was not seen again, resulting in Sean's freedom. However, Craig hid his gun in Lucy's bag. Steven, Lucy's half-brother, later attempted to use the gun to shoot himself but instead wounded Jane.
{{-}}

==Alice Lord==
&lt;!-- {{Infobox soap character 2 | series = EastEnders
| image =
| name =Alice Lord
| portrayer =[[Toni Palmer]]
| years = 2007
| appeared = 2 August 2007
}} --&gt;
'''Alice Lord''' played by '''Toni Palmer''', was a family friend of [[Tanya Branning]] and her sister [[Rainie Cross|Rainie]]. When they were children they would call her '''&quot;Auntie Alice&quot;''', although she was not related to them. She lived on the same housing estate as the sisters, and appeared when Tanya tried to get in contact with Rainie, telling Tanya that Rainie had many men visiting her flat.
&lt;br clear=all&gt;

==Rainie Cross==
{{Main|Rainie Cross}}
'''Rainie Cross''', played by [[Tanya Franks]], is the drug-addicted sister of [[Tanya Branning]] ([[Jo Joyner]]). As of April 2011, she has had four separate stints in the series, in 2007 (two episodes), 2008 (four episodes), 2010, and 2011 onwards. Rainie has been called &quot;troublesome&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;BBC Rainie&quot;&gt;{{cite press release|url=http://www.bbc.co.uk/pressoffice/pressreleases/stories/2011/03_march/21/eastenders.shtml|title=EastEnders: Tanya's mother, Cora Cross, arrives in Walford with Tanya's troublesome sister Rainie in tow|date=21 March 2011|accessdate=22 March 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; and &quot;troubled&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.rte.ie/ten/2011/0321/eastenders.html|title=Tanya's mum to land in Albert Square|date=21 March 2011|work=RTÉ Ten|publisher=[[Raidió Teilifís Éireann]]|accessdate=22 March 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; Franks said that Rainie would be &quot;unlikely to return without stirring up a bit of trouble&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;lastbroadcast&quot;&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.lastbroadcast.co.uk/soaps/interviews/v/14424-tanya-franks-eastenders-rainie-interview.html|title=Tanya Franks (EastEnders' Rainie) interview|work=Last Broadcast|first=Will|last=Martin|date=2 August 2010|accessdate=21 March 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; Her most notable storyline is one of getting [[Phil Mitchell]] ([[Steve McFadden]]) addicted to the drug [[crack cocaine]], which Frank said &quot;gets quite dark and dirty&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;Rainie teases&quot;&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.digitalspy.co.uk/soaps/s2/eastenders/scoop/a258447/enders-rainie-teases-this-weeks-eps.html|title='Enders Rainie teases this week's eps|last=Kilkelly|first=Daniel|date=9 August 2010|publisher=[[Digital Spy]]|accessdate=9 August 2010|location=London}}&lt;/ref&gt; She was given advice from the charity [[DrugScope]] on how to act the part and also undertook some of her own research.&lt;ref name=&quot;Rainie teases&quot; /&gt; The storyline attracted several complaints.&lt;ref name=&quot;drug complaints&quot;&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.digitalspy.co.uk/soaps/s2/eastenders/news/a259613/bbc-defends-eastenders-drug-scenes.html|title=BBC defends 'EastEnders' drug scenes|last=Love|first=Ryan|date=11 August 2010|publisher=[[Digital Spy]]|accessdate=11 August 2010|location=London}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Mail&quot;&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.dailymail.co.uk/tvshowbiz/article-1302462/EastEnders-Viewer-fury-Phil-Mitchells-cocaine-binge-8pm.html|title=Viewer fury over EastEnders cocaine binge at 8pm|date=13 August 2010|work=[[Daily Mail]]|publisher=[[Associated Newspapers]]|accessdate=22 March 2011|location=[[London]]}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Cassidy&quot;&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.dailymail.co.uk/tvshowbiz/article-1304138/Pregnant-Natalie-Cassidy-displays-huge-bump-prepares-baby.html|title=Blooming lovely! Natalie Cassidy displays huge bump as she prepares for arrival of first baby|last=Mail Online reporter|date=19 August 2010|work=[[Daily Mail]]|publisher=[[Associated Newspapers]]|accessdate=21 March 2011|location=[[London]]}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Ellen Dunn==
&lt;!-- {{Infobox soap character 2 | series = EastEnders
| image =
| name =Ellen Dunn
| portrayer =[[Phillipa Peak]]
| years = 2007
| first = 7 August 2007
| last = 7 September 2007
| occupation =Police officer
}} --&gt;
'''Detective Sergeant Ellen Dunn''', played by [[Phillipa Peak]], is the leading officer investigating the attack on [[Patrick Trueman]]. She interrogated [[Sean Slater]], and later interviewed [[Deano Wicks]] when he was attacked after making a statement against Sean. One month later, she led a team of officers to arrest Deano and [[Chelsea Fox]] for attempting to [[pervert the course of justice]]
{{-}}

==Zachary Carson==
&lt;!--{{Infobox soap character 2 | series = EastEnders
| image =
| name =Zachary Carson
| portrayer =[[Jonah Russell]]
| years = 2007
| first = 7 August 2007
| last =13 August 2007
| occupation =Police officer
}}--&gt;
'''Detective Constable Zachary Carson''', played by [[Jonah Russell]], was one of the police officers investigating the attack on [[Patrick Trueman]]. He collected witness statements from [[Deano Wicks]] and [[Chelsea Fox]], who claimed they saw [[Sean Slater]] attack Patrick, and later interviewed Patrick when he regained consciousness, distressing him until [[Denise Wicks]] told Carson to leave the hospital. He left Patrick his card, and Patrick later telephoned him and told him Sean was the culprit. One month later, the police officers arrested Chelsea and Deano after they had been discovered they were [[perverting the course of justice]].
{{-}}

==Alan Simon==
{{Infobox soap character 2 | series = EastEnders
| image =
| name =Alan Simon
| portrayer =[[Simon Meacock]]
| years = 2007
| first = 10 August 2007
| last = 13 August 2007
| occupation = Duty solicitor
}}
'''Alan Simon''' was [[Sean Slater]]'s duty solicitor when he was accused of attacking [[Patrick Trueman]]. He constantly advised Sean that he was allowed to answer &quot;no comment&quot;, as Sean was getting irate with police officers in the interview room. He later visited Sean's girlfriend [[Carly Wicks]].
{{-}}

==Wayne Hughes==
{{Infobox soap character 2 | series = EastEnders
| image =
| name =DC Wayne Hughes
| portrayer =[[Jamie Treacher]]
| years = 2007, 2008, 2009–10
| first = 17 August 2007
| last = 19 February 2010
| occupation = [[Detective Constable]]
}}
'''Detective Constable Wayne Hughes''' is a [[police officer]] who works for the Walford Police. He makes his first appearance on 17 August 2007 when he interviews [[Craig Dixon]] about what happened with [[Lucy Beale]].&lt;!-- what happened with Lucy Beale? --&gt; He returns on 18 March 2008 when Lucy runs away and leaves again on 23 March.

He returns on 28 December 2009 following the murder of [[Archie Mitchell]]. He is the central colleague of [[Jill Marsden (EastEnders)|DCI Jill Marsden]]. When a DNA screening begins, [[Jack Branning]] pays Hughes a bribe to make the samples disappear. Hughes contacts Jack when his nephew [[Bradley Branning]] is about to be arrested. He becomes involved in the chase with Bradley and he watches him fall to his death.
{{-}}

==Jo Davis==
{{Infobox soap character 2 | series = EastEnders
| image =
| name =Jo Davis
| portrayer =[[Jennifer Taylor (actress)|Jennifer Taylor]]
| years = 2007
| appeared = 20 August 2007
| occupation = Receptionist
}}
'''Jo Davis''' was the receptionist who booked [[Garry Hobbs]] and [[Dawn Swann]] a room in a hotel in [[Brighton]]. She was unable to book them a twin room, so booked them a double room instead, and assisted them in getting a cot for Dawn's baby [[Summer Swann|Summer]].
&lt;br clear=all&gt;

==Len Harker==
{{Infobox soap character 2 | series = EastEnders
| image = 
| name =Len Harker
| portrayer =[[Christopher Ellison]]
| years = 2007
| first = 20 August 2007
| last = 24 August 2007
| occupation = Rocking horse maker
}}
'''Len Harker''' was a man who unknowingly helped [[Shirley Carter]] and [[Heather Trott]] to steal a car that [[Pat Evans]] borrowed from [[Kevin Wicks]]. As Shirley and Heather drove away to Brighton, Pat came out from the service station and called out that it was her car, but she slipped and broke her shoe. Len mended her broken shoe, and then offered her a lift to [[Worthing]], where she had been heading for. After Pat accepted, he drove her to a run-down mental facility where Pat's long-lost sister Joan had been sent sixty years previously. After being refused entry, he helped Pat to break in, where they discovered that Joan hadn't died aged 22 as Pat had been told, but had been sent to a different hospital in the 1980s.
However, while running from the police, he dropped the paper which revealed which hospital she had been sent to, but he searched the Internet and found the location. He took Pat there, where they discovered that Joan had only died a few years ago, and that she had married in 1963.
He took Pat back to Walford, where he said goodbye to her, giving her his card, looked around, and then drove away.

He wasn't heard of again until [[Christmas Eve]] 2007, when it was shown through a montage of Yolande carol singing that Pat had received a rocking horse and a card from Len.
{{-}}

==Will Passmore==
{{Infobox soap character 2 | series = EastEnders
| image =
| name =Will Passmore
| portrayer =[[Patrick Brennan (actor)|Patrick Brennan]]
| years = 2007
| appeared = 24 August 2007
| occupation = Care home manager
}}
'''Will Passmore''' was the manager of a care home called Springview, where [[Pat Evans]] sister, Joan, once lived. Pat and her companion [[Len Harker]] found the care home, and Will told them that Joan had died three years ago, but that she had been happily married to a man named Michael and was well liked in the community.
{{-}}

==Damian==
{{Infobox soap character 2 | series = EastEnders
| image =
| name =Damian
| portrayer =[[James Hillier (actor)|James Hillier]]
| years = 2007
| first = 27 August 2007
| last = 29 October 2007
| classification = [[List of past EastEnders characters#Last appeared in 2007|Former; guest]]
|home=[[Ibiza]]
| occupation = Businessman
}}
'''Damian''' was [[Roxy Slater|Roxy Mitchell]]'s fiancé whom she started avoiding calls from during her stay in Walford. Roxy told her sister [[Ronnie Mitchell|Ronnie]] she was going to leave Damian and never go back to Ibiza, but Ronnie warned her to wait until she got the money out of his business. They then both got into an argument over the situation during which Damian turned up totally unexpectedly at [[The Queen Victoria]]. Later left after Roxy and Ronnie tricked him into believing Roxy's new boyfriend was Ian Beale and she was pregnant with Ian's baby and Roxy snogged Ian to prove she loved him with all her heart in front of Damian.  Damian then left to go back to Ibiza.

Two months later, he returned to Walford to be with Roxy, who was then found crying on the bed pretending she had a miscarriage. Ronnie was horrified that Roxy was setting him up. Roxy tried not to let him know that she was using him only for the money to help Peggy pay off her £40,000 debts and the funds for her and Ronnie's future ownership of the [[R&amp;R (EastEnders)|Scarlet]] nightclub. On 29 October, Damian attacked Ian in the cafe when he discovered that he and Roxy were never even in love, and then got himself arrested by [[Jack Branning]] when he 'hit' Ronnie (this was set up by Ronnie, when she made him look like he was sexually assaulting her). Damian also realised what the Mitchell sisters were up to when he then realised that Roxy doesn't really love him, but is using him - only because he had everything.
During the arrest, Ronnie made an excuse and told Damian why he was set up - because he owed her money, so he accepted her offer and then was taken in Jack's car. This was the very last time we ever saw of him.
{{-}}

==Queenie Trott==
{{Infobox soap character 2 | series = EastEnders
| image=
| name =Queenie Trott
| portrayer =[[Judy Cornwell]]
| years = 2007–08
| first = 25 September 2007
| last = 24 April 2008
| classification= [[List of past EastEnders characters#Last appeared in 2008|Former; recurring]]
| father = William Trott
| mother = Holly Trott
| sisters = Val Trott
| daughters =[[Heather Trott]]
| grandsons= [[George Trott]]
| home = [[Eastbourne]]
}}
'''Queenie Trott''' is the mother of [[Heather Trott]]. Queenie is a controlling woman, who prefers Heather to be at her beck and call. She regularly taunts, insults and demeans her daughter, always calling her by the name &quot;Pig&quot;, but she does not react kindly to those who might want to lure her away. When [[Shirley Carter]] asked Heather to move out of her mother's flat and into hers, Queenie manipulated Heather into staying. Queenie claimed she was pleased to see her daughter leave, but then pretended to have an accident and Heather was so concerned for her mother's safety that she decided not to move out. However, Heather later heard Queenie laughing about her deception to a friend on the phone, mocking her daughter's stupidity, calling her a &quot;stupid cow.&quot; Heather was so angry that she decided to move in with Shirley after all, only to find that Shirley had been evicted as she'd failed to pay the rent. Not wanting to remain living with her spiteful mother, Heather decided to pay the rent with money she had in her savings account. She sneaked back to Queenie's to find her savings book, but discovered that her mother had stolen most of her money.

She turned up on Heather's doorstep on 16 March 2008 to meet Heather's new fiancé, [[Minty Peterson]]. She blackmailed Minty and Heather, saying she would not leave unless they gave her their winnings from the wedding competition they were in. Heather revealed to Minty that Queenie had told her that her father walked out on them because he hated living with Heather. Minty then encouraged Heather to stand up to Queenie, which she did, prompting Queenie to leave.

Queenie later tried to stop Minty and Heather's wedding, revealing Heather's true identity to [[List of EastEnders characters (2008)#Marni Merrick|Marni]] from the magazine. Heather married Minty and later berated Queenie for trying to ruin her happiness, and Queenie left.
&lt;br clear=all&gt;

Queenie was mentioned in December 2008 when Heather stated that she wasn't surprised when Queenie hadn't sent her a Christmas card, and again in February 2009 when Heather assumed that she was at [[George Michael]]'s house and reminded herself of her school days, being a fan of George, with Queenie bringing her down of her happiness.

Queenie is mentioned in October 2009, when Heather gave birth to a baby boy whom she named George, after George Michael. Heather phoned Queenie to let her know that she is a grandmother, but was unsurprisingly let down after she took low opinions of the birth. In 2011, Heather tries to visit Queenie but a neighbour tells her that Queenie moved to [[Eastbourne]] a few years ago, and that she wasn't worth Heather's time looking for her.
{{-}}

==Tamwar Masood==
{{Main|Tamwar Masood}}

==Brendan Hughes==
{{Infobox soap character 2 | series = EastEnders
| image =
| name =Brendan Hughes
| portrayer =Tim Hudson
| years = 2007
| first = 1 October 2007
| last =  9 October 2007
| occupation =[[Lawyer]]
}}
'''Brendan Hughes''' was the lawyer of [[Chelsea Fox]] and [[Deano Wicks]]. He represented them in court when they were charged with falsifying evidence in a police enquiry. Despite Mr Hughes' plea for lenience, Deano and Chelsea were sentenced to 6 months in prison.
{{-}}

==Vinnie Monks==
{{Main|Vinnie Monks}}

==Tony Evans==
{{Infobox soap character 2 | series = EastEnders
| image =
| name =Tony Evans
| years = 2007
| appeared = 15 October 2007
| occupation =Psychiatrist
}}
'''Tony Evans''' was a psychiatrist friend of [[Ian Beale]], who agreed to take Ian's ex-stepson, [[Steven Beale|Steven]] into his mental hospital.
{{-}}

==Masood Ahmed==
{{Main|Masood Ahmed}}

==Felix Riley==
{{Infobox soap character 2 | series = EastEnders
| image =
| name =Felix Riley
| portrayer =[[John Webber]]
| years = 2007
| appeared = 22 October 2007
| occupation =Loan shark
| daughters =Melissa Riley
| sons =  James Riley
}}
'''Felix Riley''' was a loan shark, who tried to loan money to [[Peggy Mitchell]] when she was £40,000 in debt. When he explained that he would effectively be buying [[The Queen Vic]] from her and renting it back to her, Peggy threw him out.
{{-}}

==Bird Meadows==
&lt;!--{{Infobox soap character 2 | series = EastEnders
| name =Bird Meadows
| portrayer =[[Brett Fancy]]
| years = 2007, 2009
| occupation = Gangster 
| classification= [[List of past EastEnders characters#Last appeared in 2009|Previous; recurring]] 
| first = 22 October 2007
| last = 29 May 2009
}}--&gt;
'''Liam &quot;Bird&quot; Meadows''', played by [[Brett Fancy]], was a member of [[Terry Bates]]'s gang of football hooligans. He caught up with [[Jase Dyer]], a former member of the gang, in [[Walford]] and attempted to recruit him back into the gang. When Jase refused, Bird helped Terry and the gang to arrange a car crash for a man who had sent Jase to prison. When this failed to win Jase back, the gang raided [[The Queen Vic]] looking for him. In May 2009 he returned during Terry's trial,&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.digitalspy.co.uk/soaps/a156260/the-police-arrive-to-save-billy-and-jay.html Digitalspy.co.uk]&lt;/ref&gt; though he was arrested for assaulting [[Billy Mitchell (EastEnders)|Billy Mitchell]] and holding [[Jay Brown]] hostage.
{{-}}

==Terry Bates==
{{Infobox soap character 2 | series = EastEnders
| image = 
| name = Terry Bates
| portrayer = [[Nicholas Ball (British actor)|Nicholas Ball]]
| introducer = [[Diederick Santer]]
| years = 2007–09
| first = 25 October 2007
| last =29 May 2009
| born = 1945
| home = [[Prison]]
| occupation = Gangster 
| classification= [[List of past EastEnders characters#Last appeared in 2009|Former; recurring]] 
| wife = [[Viv Bates]]
}}
'''Terry Bates''' was the leader of a [[football hooliganism|football firm]], including [[#Bird Meadows|Bird Meadows]], Dee, and formerly [[Jase Dyer]]. Jase had arrived in [[London]] from [[Manchester]] aged 15, and Terry took him under his wing. After Dee told the police about Jase's unruly behaviour, Jase went to [[prison]] and came out a changed man, caring for his son [[Jay Brown|Jay]]. In October 2007, Terry sent Bird to find Jase in [[Walford]], and Jase met the gang at a pub. The gang later turned on Dee when they found out he had told the police about Jase, and arranged for his car to crash, injuring him severely. Jase expressed his wish to have no part in the gang, so Terry visited Jay while Jase was out, taking him to see a firework display. 

Jase later found Terry in a [[snooker]] [[pool hall|hall]], and again said that he wanted no further involvement with the gang. After playing a game of snooker with Jase, Terry let him go home, watching him menacingly as he left.

Later, Terry decided to storm the Vic with a large group of hitmen, believing Jase was there on a date with [[Dawn Swann]]. Not finding him, Terry's gang smashed the place up, and attacked [[Roxy Mitchell]], [[Ronnie Mitchell]], [[Keith Miller (EastEnders)|Keith Miller]], [[Mickey Miller]], [[Darren Miller]], [[Garry Hobbs]] and [[Patrick Trueman]]. He confronted Jase in the cellar and one of his gang members attacked Jase, knocking a pregnant [[Honey Mitchell]] down into some empty beer kegs,  (who was then rushed to hospital by Jase). Terry later left the area with his gang members.

Terry turned up at the hospital, then later visited Jase's flat and turned Jay against Jase. After an encounter with Jase and [[Phil Mitchell]] lying about [[William Mitchell (EastEnders)|William Mitchell]]'s 'death', Terry and Bird were arrested. 

He returned to Walford on 25 July 2008, after Jase, desperate for money, agreed to work for him again. Terry reappeared in August, where he made plans for Jase to get some of his money back for him. It turned out that Jase has been stealing from him, and Terry, in retaliation, set Jase up, then returned to his flat and held Jay hostage. Jase and [[Billy Mitchell (EastEnders)|Billy Mitchell]] rushed to the rescue. A confrontation ensued where Billy managed to get Jay out of the flat to safety in Jase's van. Terry had his men beat Jase to the brink of death. After Jay made a frantic call to Honey, armed [[CO19]] officers stormed 89 George Street and arrested Terry, his men and Billy, who had been hiding in the bathroom after seeing the gang standing over Jase and was too frightened to try to save him. Jase later died in hospital.

Terry returned in May 2009 during his trial. He got his wife [[Viv Bates]] to threaten Billy saying she will hurt Jay if he does go to the trial to testify. When his name is still on the witness list, Viv sent Bird and two other hitmen to hold Jay hostage. However, Terry was found guilty of Jase's murder so Viv left him, throwing her wedding ring at him. He then said he would have revenge on her.
{{-}}

==Dee==
{{Infobox soap character 2 | series = EastEnders
| image =
| name = Dee
| portrayer = [[Steve Chaplin]]
| introducer = [[Diederick Santer]]
| years = 2007
| first = 25 October 2007
| last = 8 November 2007
| classification= [[List of past EastEnders characters#Last appeared in 2007|Previous; recurring]] 
| wife = Vicky
}}
'''Dee''' was a member of [[#Terry Bates|Terry Bates]]' hooligan firm alongside Terry, Liam &quot;Bird&quot; Meadows and [[Jase Dyer]]. It was revealed that Dee was the one who grassed Jase up to the police, resulting in Jase being sent to prison. Terry and his firm arranged a car crash for Dee, which left him severely injured.
{{-}}

==Jack Branning==
{{Main|Jack Branning}}

==Raymond Storry==
{{Infobox soap character 2 | series = EastEnders
| image =
| name =Raymond Storry
| portrayer =[[Julien Ball]]
| creator=[[Sarah Phelps]]
| years = 2007
| appeared = 8 November 2007
| occupation =Psychiatrist
}}
'''Doctor Raymond Storry''' was a psychiatrist who worked at [[#Tony Evans|Tony Evans]]'s mental hospital, who looked after [[Steven Beale]]. He told Steven's grandmother [[Pat Evans]] that Steven was ready to leave the hospital, and prescribed him some pills, which Steven later threw down Pat's sink.
{{-}}

==William Mitchell==
{{Infobox soap character 2 
| series = EastEnders
| name =William Mitchell
| portrayer =Toby Warpole
| image = 
| creator=[[Diederick Santer]]
| years =2007—
| first = 13 November 2007
| last = &lt;!-- 20 June 2011 --&gt;
| family =[[Mitchell family|Mitchell]]
| classification=[[List of characters from EastEnders#Recurring characters|Present; recurring]]
| born = 13 November 2007
| father= [[Billy Mitchell (EastEnders)|Billy Mitchell]]
| mother= [[Honey Mitchell]]
| sisters= [[Janet Mitchell]]
| halfbrothers = Dan Pearce&lt;br&gt;[[Jay Brown]] &lt;small&gt;(foster)&lt;/small&gt; &lt;!-- don't change this please because William's father is Jay's foster father --&gt;
| nieces=[[Lola Pearce]]
| uncles= Charlie Mitchell
| cousins= [[Jamie Mitchell]]
| grandmothers= Janet Edwards&lt;br&gt;Janet Mitchell
| grandfathers=[[Jack Edwards (EastEnders)|Jack Edwards]]&lt;br&gt;Steven Mitchell
}}
'''William Mitchell''', played by Toby Warpole, is the son of [[Billy Mitchell (EastEnders)|Billy]] ([[Perry Fenwick]]) and [[Honey Mitchell]] ([[Emma Barton]]).&lt;ref&gt;&quot;[http://www.walfordweb.co.uk/walfordweb/articles-hqimage.php?id=1118 Honey and William Mitchell]&quot;, ''Walford Web'', URL last accessed 16 July 2008&lt;/ref&gt; On 20 March 2007, Honey finds out she is pregnant again and tells [[Pat Evans]] ([[Pam St. Clement]]), but asks her not to tell Billy. Pat persuades Honey to tell him, but he is distant initially. He soon comes round, following a heart to heart, and admits to being concerned, like Honey, that they would love the new baby more than Janet if it did not have [[Down's Syndrome]], which Janet has. Honey reassures him it will not happen. After this, the two agree they want the baby and gradually tell their family. On the due date, Honey is knocked over during an incident at [[The Queen Victoria]] involving [[Jase Dyer]] ([[Stephen Lord]]), [[Terry Bates]] ([[Nicholas Ball (actor)|Nicholas Ball]]) and Terry's gang, and she goes into labour. When the baby is born, it seems that he is stillborn because he is not breathing but he pulls through. Honey wants to name him after his father and feels guilty about being happy that he does not have Down's syndrome.

William leaves Walford with Honey and Janet on 2 September 2008 when Billy lies about giving Jase's money to charity, which led to his death. It is revealed a few days later that they are living with William's grandfather [[Jack Edwards (EastEnders)|Jack Edwards]] ([[Nicky Henson]]). On 18 September 2008, Janet and William return when [[Peggy Mitchell]] ([[Barbara Windsor]]) wants a family photo taken. On 25 December 2008, he and Janet return again for Christmas but are not seen on-screen. In April 2009, when it is revealed that William is ill, Billy goes to see him, leaving his family, who are torn apart by the true identity of [[Danielle Jones (EastEnders)|Danielle Jones]] ([[Lauren Crace]]) and her subsequent death, to see William. William reappears the following month, along with Janet, for Billy's 50th birthday party. In May 2010, Billy has trouble telling William and Janet that Honey has been involved in a car crash and that Jack has died. He appears in May 2011 when he meets Billy's girlfriend [[Julie Perkins]] ([[Cathy Murphy]]) for the first time as they play in the local park. In June, he visits Billy on Father's Day, and in July, William and Janet meet their niece [[Lola Pearce]] ([[Danielle Harold]]) for the first time.

===Reception===
The scenes in which Honey was attacked were subject to heavy criticism, with [[Ofcom]] receiving 78 complaints from viewers about the level of violence displayed, and concerns for the safety of her baby. The media regulatory body stated that: &quot;In Ofcom's view the violence was not appropriately limited for this time of the evening when many children are available to view television.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;guardian&quot;&gt;{{cite web|author=John Plunkett|url=http://www.guardian.co.uk/media/2008/feb/25/bbc.television2?gusrc=rss&amp;feed=media|title=	
EastEnders violence ruled out of order|publisher=[[The Guardian]]|date=25 February 2008|accessdate=5 March 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt; ''EastEnders'' was found to have breached the broadcasting code on this occasion, though the [[BBC]] defended itself by stating that there had been a gradual build up to the event over several episodes, and that a content warning was aired prior to the episode's broadcast.&lt;ref name=&quot;stage&quot;&gt;{{cite web|author=Matthew Hemley|url=http://www.thestage.co.uk/news/newsstory.php/19929/ofcom-raps-bbc-over-eastenders-violence|title=	
Ofcom raps BBC over EastEnders violence|publisher=[[The Stage]]|date=25 February 2008|accessdate=5 March 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt; 
{{-}}

==Dave Stewart==
{{Infobox soap character 2 | series = EastEnders
| image =
| name =Dave Stewart
| portrayer =[[Vincent Carmichael]]
| years = 2007
| appeared = 20 November 2007
| occupation =Insurance salesman
}}
'''Dave Stewart''' was a colleague of [[Max Branning]] who interviewed Max's son [[Bradley Branning|Bradley]] for a job as an insurance salesman. Stewart was impressed by Bradley in the interview and offered him the job, but Bradley turned him down as he didn't feel that it was the right career path for him.
{{-}}

==Jamie Stewart==
{{Infobox soap character 2 | series = EastEnders
| image =
| name =Jamie Stewart
| portrayer =[[Edward MacLiam]]
| years = 2007–09
| first = 29 November 2007
| last = 21 July 2009
| occupation =Doctor
| wife = [[Laura Stewart]]
| sons = [[Felix Stewart (EastEnders)|Felix Stewart]]
}}
'''Doctor Jamie Stewart''' was an [[Ireland|Irish]] doctor at [[Walford]] General Hospital who helped [[Ronnie Mitchell]] when she sprained her wrist. He flirted with Ronnie's sister, [[Roxy Slater|Roxy]], who invited him to attend the opening of their new nightclub, [[R&amp;R (EastEnders)|R&amp;R]] - which he attended on 30 November.

The character reappeared in May 2008 when Roxy had to go to hospital after fainting. Jamie gave Roxy his number. He later met up with Roxy at the [[Queen Vic]], though was interrupted when his ex-wife [[List of EastEnders characters (2008)#Laura Stewart|Laura]] arrived and asked him to look after their son, [[List of EastEnders characters (2008)#Felix Stewart|Felix]]. Roxy got on well with Felix, but when she fainted and found out she was pregnant, Jamie told her that he couldn't commit to a relationship with her, as he was already preoccupied with Felix.

In 2009 he treated [[Stacey Slater]] after she fell and cut her head.
{{-}}

==Bernadette Logan==
{{Infobox soap character 2 | series = EastEnders
| image =
| name =Bernadette Logan
| portrayer =[[Olivia Grant (1994 British actress)|Olivia Grant]]
| years = 2007–08
| first = 10 December 2007
| last = 24 June 2008
}}
'''Bernadette Logan''' was a child in [[Abi Branning]] and [[Ben Mitchell (EastEnders)|Ben Mitchell]]'s school year. She was first seen when she took part in [[Dot Branning]] and [[Yolande Trueman]]'s 2007 nativity play. Abi was jealous of her as Bernadette was playing [[Mary (mother of Jesus)|Mary]]. After Abi tried to sabotage Bernadette to gain the role of Mary, she was demoted from narrator to the role of the donkey.

Bernadette later appeared at Abi's twelfth birthday party in June 2008, when she teased Abi about having a childish party, but they later became friends. In September 2008, Abi told her father [[Max Branning|Max]] that she'd confided in Bernadette about her mother [[Tanya Branning|Tanya]]'s relationship with Max's brother [[Jack Branning|Jack]], and Bernadette had been calling Tanya a &quot;scrubber&quot;. Max told Abi to stand up to Bernadette, and it was revealed that Abi had hit Bernadette (off-screen) and been suspended from school for four days.
{{-}}

==Oscar Branning==
{{Infobox soap character 2 
| series = EastEnders
| image = 
| name = Oscar Branning
| portrayer =Gabriel Miller-Williams &lt;small&gt;(2007–2008)&lt;/small&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Charlee Hal and Neo Hall &lt;small&gt;{{nowrap|(2008—)}}&lt;/small&gt;
| creator=[[Diederick Santer]]
| years =2007—
| first =14 December 2007
| last = 
| classification=[[List of characters from EastEnders#Present characters|Present; recurring]]
| born = 13 December 2007
| home =5 Albert Square
| occupation = 
| family=[[Branning family|Branning]]
| father =[[Max Branning]]
| mother=[[Tanya Branning]]
| stepfather= [[Greg Jessop]] (2011—)
| halfbrothers=[[Bradley Branning]]
| sisters=[[Lauren Branning]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Abi Branning]]
| grandfathers=[[Jim Branning]]
| grandmothers=[[Cora Cross]]
| aunts=[[Carol Jackson]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Rainie Cross]]
| uncles=[[Jack Branning]]
| cousins=[[Bianca Jackson|Bianca Butcher]]&lt;br/&gt;
}}
'''Oscar Branning''', played by Gabriel Miller-Williams until 2008, and Charlee and Neo Hall since 2008, is the son of [[Tanya Branning]] ([[Jo Joyner]]) and [[Max Branning]] ([[Jake Wood]]) and first appeared on 14 December 2007, being delivered by his father,&lt;ref name=&quot;oscarbravo&quot;&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.mirror.co.uk/showbiz/tv/soapbox/2007/12/08/oscar-bravo-89520-20218047//|title=Oscar.. Bravo!|publisher=''[[Daily Mirror]]''|date=8 December 2007|accessdate=12 December 2007}}&lt;/ref&gt; because it was too late for Tanya to go to [[hospital]]. The midwife is not present so Max has to follow her instructions over the phone. Oscar is named by his sister [[Abi Branning|Abi]] ([[Lorna Fitzgerald]]),&lt;ref name=&quot;oscarbravo&quot;/&gt; although Max is not keen with the name. Tanya later asks [[Jane Beale]] ([[Laurie Brett]]) to be godmother and she accepts. In March 2008, it is revealed that every time Tanya looks at Oscar, it reminds her of when Max had an affair with [[Stacey Branning]] ([[Lacey Turner]]). In 2009, Tanya moves out with Oscar and [[Lauren Branning|Lauren]] ([[Madeline Duggan]], later [[Jacqueline Jossa]]), after discovering that Max has been hiding his financial problems. 

In January 2011, Tanya moves back to the square with Oscar and her new fiancé [[Greg Jessop]] ([[Stefan Booth]]), and rents [[Roxy Mitchell]]'s ([[Rita Simons]]) house. Oscar is seen again at Tanya and Greg's wedding in April 2011, where he walks down the aisle with his mother. Whilst in the care of Tanya's mother, [[Cora Cross]] ([[Ann Mitchell]]), Oscar suffers a fall whilst playing but only suffers minor injuries. 

Oscar is originally played by Gabriel Miller-Williams. In 2008, Miller-Williams was fired as the BBC were cutting costs, and it cost £300 a day to transport him to the set from his home in [[Leigh-on-Sea]]. His mother, Claire, said she was going to sue the BBC as she only found out he was sacked after a taxi failed to pick him up. She said, &quot;It's a disgusting way to treat people. We still haven't had a call explaining why he was sacked. I've sent his contract to solicitors to investigate legal action.&quot; A BBC spokeperson said, &quot;We're looking to hire local babies as we watch costs.&quot; They also said Miller-Williams' agent had been informed.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.mirror.co.uk/celebs/latest/2008/09/09/exclusive-mum-may-sue-after-tv-tot-oscar-is-sacked-from-eastenders-115875-20729743/|title=Mum may sue after TV tot Oscar is sacked from EastEnders|first=Mark|last=Jefferies|date=9 September 2008|accessdate=20 October 2011|work=''[[Daily Mirror]]''}}&lt;/ref&gt; The BBC later issued a statement saying, &quot;It is not unusual for babies to be recast several times in continuing drama series such as ''EastEnders''. In this instance the decision to recast at this time was in part due to Gabriel's travelling costs. As the BBC strives to deliver value for money across all its productions, travel costs are a factor that must be considered.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.dailymail.co.uk/tvshowbiz/article-1053833/EastEnders-bosses-face-legal-action-baby-actor-axed-soap-save-costs.html|title=EastEnders bosses face legal action after baby actor is axed from soap 'to save costs'|first=Tammy|last=Lovell|date=9 September 2008|accessdate=20 October 2011|work=''[[The Mail]]''}}&lt;/ref&gt;
{{-}}

==Gaynor Lucas==
{{Infobox soap character 2 
| series = EastEnders
| name=Gaynor Lucas
| portrayer=[[Kathleen Frazer]]
| creator=[[Diederick Santer]]
| years=2007—
| first= December 2007
| classification= [[List of EastEnders characters#Named extras|Present; extra]]
| occupation=[[Beautician]]
}}
'''Gaynor Lucas'''&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.bbc.co.uk/programmes/b00t9sq3|title=03/08/2010|publisher=[[BBC Programmes]]|accessdate=27 July 2010|airdate=3 August 2010|}}&lt;/ref&gt; played by [[Kathleen Frazer]], is an old friend of [[Tanya Branning]] ([[Jo Joyner]]), who works in Tanya's beauty salon Booty. On 24 February 2009, Gaynor appears as part of an iconic episode of ''EastEnders'' featuring only black members of the cast. Gaynor arranges with Chelsea before they finish work to meet in [[The Queen Victoria]] public house for a drink. [[Theo Kelly (EastEnders)|Theo Kelly]] ([[Rolan Bell]]) uses her to get Chelsea to come to the pub so he can speak to her. This episode marks her first credited appearance and first main speaking part.

Booty closes down in late 2009, so Gaynor loses her job. Gaynor works as a makeup artist for [[Denise Johnson|Denise Wicks]] ([[Diane Parish]]) wedding, to [[Lucas Johnson]] ([[Don Gilet]]). In February 2010 she gives out beauty treatments at [[Bianca Jackson]]'s ([[Patsy Palmer]]) hen party. Gaynor resumes her old job when [[Roxy Mitchell]] ([[Rita Simons]]) reopens the beauty salon as Roxy's. When Roxy faces financial diffuculties, Roxy sells the salon back to Tanya, and Gaynor continues working there. 
{{-}}

==Others==
{| class=&quot;wikitable&quot;
! Date(s) !! Character(s) !! Actor(s) !! Circumstances
|-
|{{Anchor|DS Grimwood}}&lt;small&gt;01/01/07, 11/10/08, 11/09/09&lt;/small&gt;||'''DS Grimwood'''||[[Steve Hansell]]||A police officer investigating [[Pauline Fowler]]'s murder. In October 2008 he investigates [[Max Branning]]'s attempted murder case. In September 2009 he searches for [[Sam Mitchell (EastEnders)|Sam Mitchell]] who become fugitive for the murder of [[Den Watts]].
|-
|{{Anchor|Dermot}}&lt;small&gt;11/01/07, 12/05–15/05/09&lt;/small&gt;||'''Dermot'''||[[Scott Mean]]||A man who came onto [[Stacey Slater]], but ended up being beaten up by her brother [[Sean Slater|Sean]]. In 2009 he and Stacey slept together.
|-
|{{Anchor|Ellie}}&lt;small&gt;11/01–08/05&lt;/small&gt;||'''Ellie'''||[[Hazel Holder]]||A nurse at Walford General Hospital. She appeared when [[May Wright]] pushed [[Dawn Swann]] down some steps.
|-
|{{Anchor|Jonathan}}&lt;small&gt;15/01&lt;/small&gt;||'''Jonathan'''||[[Iain Stirland]]||
|-
|{{Anchor|Jenny}}&lt;small&gt;15/01&lt;/small&gt;||'''Jenny'''||[[Hattie Ladbury]]||
|-
|{{Anchor|Dr Newton}}&lt;small&gt;16/01–18/01&lt;/small&gt;||'''Dr Newton'''||[[Rebecca Sarker]]||
|-
|{{Anchor|Maddy}}&lt;small&gt;16/01–18/01&lt;/small&gt;||'''Maddy'''||[[Annabel Scholey]]||[[Naomi Julien]]'s mortgage advisor.
|-
|{{Anchor|Mr Rogers}}&lt;small&gt;29/01–30/01&lt;/small&gt;||'''Mr Rogers'''||[[Alan Perrin]]||
|-
|{{Anchor|PC Henderson}}{{Anchor|Andy Henderson}}&lt;small&gt;05/02–15/02, 04/12–17/12/09, 9/4/10&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.bbc.co.uk/programmes/b00ryd7d|title=EastEnders 9/4/2010|publisher=[[BBC Online]]|accessdate=1 April 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;/small&gt;||'''PC Andy Henderson'''||[[Jem Wall]]||A police officer involved in the search for missing [[Kevin Wicks]]. In 2009 PC Henderson questions [[Masood Ahmed]] about a car crash,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.bbc.co.uk/programmes/b00p4z22|title=EastEnders 04/12/2009|publisher=[[BBC Online]]|accessdate=3 December 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt; and appears again when [[Roxy Mitchell|Roxy]] and [[Ronnie Mitchell]] hold an event at the community centre, to say they do not have a licence. In 2010 he asks [[Billie Jackson]] about a witness statement he gave regarding a shooting.
|-
|{{Anchor|Guy}}&lt;small&gt;13/02&lt;/small&gt;||'''Guy'''||[[Andrew French]]||
|-
|{{Anchor|Nadezhda}}&lt;small&gt;27/03–29/03&lt;/small&gt;||'''Nadezhda'''||[[Irina Diva]]||A [[Bulgaria]]n woman brought in to work at the Launderette. [[Dot Branning]] berated her for booking too many service washes, so she threw a tantrum, jumping on the laundry.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.digitalspy.co.uk/soaps/a43358/in-video-first-look-eastenders-clip.html|title=EXCLUSIVE: In Video: First-look 'EastEnders' clip|publisher=[[Digital Spy]]|date=1 March 2007|accessdate=19 February 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|-
|{{Anchor|Sian}}&lt;small&gt;13/07&lt;/small&gt;||'''Sian'''||[[Claire Adams (British actress)|Claire Adams]]||A woman who [[Max Branning]] flirted with, who ended up being a supplier for his wife, [[Tanya Branning|Tanya]].
|-
|{{Anchor|Fin}}&lt;small&gt;17/07&lt;/small&gt;||'''Fin'''||[[Danny Alder]]||A vet who told [[Abi Branning]] that her guinea pig, Marge was pregnant.
|-
|{{Anchor|Tamara}}&lt;small&gt;03/09–05/09&lt;/small&gt; ||'''Tamara'''|| [[Helen Coombe]] || [[Gus Smith]]'s date, twin sister of Tonicha.
|-
|{{Anchor|Tonicha}}&lt;small&gt;03/09–05/09&lt;/small&gt; ||'''Tonicha'''|| [[Rachel Coombe]] || [[Mickey Miller]]'s date, twin sister of Tamara.
|-
|{{Anchor|Norman}}&lt;small&gt;24/09/07–12/03/08&lt;/small&gt; ||'''Norman'''|| [[David Schaal (actor)|David Schaal]] || [[Shirley Carter]]'s landlord who she humiliated.
|-
|{{Anchor|Pedro}}&lt;small&gt;05/10&lt;/small&gt; ||'''Pedro'''|| [[Joseph Thompson (actor)|Joseph Thompson]] || Manager of a gay bar which [[Carly Wicks]] worked at. Carly and brother [[Deano Wicks]] lodged at his flat.
|-
|{{Anchor|Gwen}}&lt;small&gt;09/10&lt;/small&gt; ||'''Gwen'''|| [[Rebecca Jo Hanbury]] || [[Chelsea Fox]]'s cellmate.
|-
|{{Anchor|Vicky}}&lt;small&gt;08/11&lt;/small&gt; ||'''Vicky'''|| [[Louise Fullerton]] || Dee's wife, blamed Jase for her husband's injuries.
|-
|{{Anchor|Monique}}&lt;small&gt;20/11–23/11&lt;/small&gt; ||'''Monique'''|| [[Heather Cave]] || [[Peter Beale]]'s French [[exchange student]] who took a liking to [[Steven Beale]]. She left the Square when the Beales forbade her from seeing Steven, setting up Peter with [[Lauren Branning]] in the process.
|}

== References ==
{{reflist}}

{{EastEnders}}
{{EastEnders characters|year}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:List Of Eastenders Characters (2007)}}
[[Category:Lists of EastEnders characters|2007]]
[[Category:Fictional characters introduced in 2007|*, EastEnders]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
