<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="11166703" ns="0" title="Ravisankar"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Other persons|Ravi Shankar}}
{{Orphan|date=February 2009}}
{{Inappropriate tone|date=December 2007}}
{{Infobox musical artist &lt;!-- See Wikipedia:WikiProject_Musicians --&gt;
| name                = Ravisankar&lt;br&gt;രവിശങ്ക൪
| image                 =  
| caption            =  
| image_size            = 300
| background          = solo_singer
| origin              = [[India]]
| instrument          = 
| genre               = [[playback singing]]
| occupation          = 
| years_active        = 1999&amp;ndash;present
| label               = 
| associated_acts     = 
| website                 = [http://www.ravisankar.net ravisankar.net]
| current_members     = 
| past_members        = 
| notable_instruments = 
}}
'''Ravisankar''' ({{lang-ml|രവിശങ്ക൪}}) is an Indian [[playback singer]].  He has about 100 recorded songs to his credit in [[Malayalam]].  With his sweet and romantic voice, he has been creating memorable music for several years.

==Biography==

Ravisankar was born and raised in [[Thiruvananthapuram]], [[Kerala]], [[India]], to S. Ramachandran Nair and S. Hamsini Thankam. He started learning music during school days from his mother, who is a teacher at Bharatiya Vidyabhavan, [[Trivandrum]]. Later, he formally studied music under such renowned musicians as L. Vaikuntapaty, [[Perumbavoor G. Ravindranath]] and [[M. G. Radhakrishnan]]. Right from school days he took part in light music singing competitions such as the [[Kerala]] University and inter-university competitions, and won many prestigious prizes.

After completing schooling in [[Trivandrum]], Ravisankar took a degree in Law from the Kerala Law Academy in [[Trivandrum]], and a Post-Graduate Diploma in Personnel Management from Annamalai University.  Though he started working as a lawyer, he soon realized that his long-term career revolved around his passion &amp;ndash; music.

He debuted in payback singing in 1999, when he recorded his first movie song, ''Ponnolappanthalil Velippennayente Swayamvararajakumari Varumo...''.  It was recorded for the move '''Saaphalyam''' which was directed by G.S. Vijayan, and starred [[Suresh Gopi]] and Praveena.  The song was written by Sri [[Kaithapram]], and was composed by Sri M.G. Radhakrishnan.

Since then, he has come a long way in the playback singing field.  His latest songs for 2007 are 

* Two songs for the movie '''Love Birds''' and
* A song written by Gireesh Puthenchery for the movie Devdaas, which is the remake of the Telugu movie Devdaas

Apart from film music, Ravisankar has recorded several albums, and is active with concerts and other musical programmes.  He has also rendered voice to title songs for several television serials, which have gained much acclaim.  The notable ones are for the serials '''Uma''', '''Vikramadityan''', '''Dial 100''', '''Tenali Raman''', '''Abhirami''' and '''Jeeva Jalakom''', just to mention a few.  His latest hit in this area is for '''Kudumbam''', with the renowned [[Kaithapram]] &amp;ndash; Johnson team.

Currently, Ravisankar is anchoring '''Raindrops''', a musical live entertainer in the [[Malayalam]] channel [[Kairali]].  This program is aired live every Friday from 4PM to 5PM Indian Standard Time, and is much popular among music lovers, especially in the Middle East.

Ravishankar is married to Priyarenjini, a native of [[Kottayam]] and a practicing advocate in [[Trivandrum]].  The couple was blessed with a beautiful daughter, '''Bhadra''', in January 2007.

==Discography==
''&quot;Ponnolappanthalil&quot;'' - Saaphalyam&lt;br&gt;
''&quot;Ormakalil Nee&quot;'' - [[Spandanam(Music Album)]] (2010)&lt;br&gt;
''&quot;Vanakokilaaravam&quot;'' - [[Spandanam(Music Album)]] (2010)&lt;br&gt;
''&quot;Chemparathi Kammalittu&quot;'' - Duet with [[Shreya Ghoshal]] for the movie [[Manikyakkallu]] (2011)

==External links==
* [http://www.ravisankar.net A website on Ravisankar]
* [http://www.youtube.com/results?search_query=ravisankar+raindrops+malayalam&amp;search_type=&amp;aq=f Ravisankar songs on YouTube]

{{Persondata &lt;!-- Metadata: see [[Wikipedia:Persondata]]. --&gt;
| NAME              =
| ALTERNATIVE NAMES =
| SHORT DESCRIPTION =
| DATE OF BIRTH     =
| PLACE OF BIRTH    =
| DATE OF DEATH     =
| PLACE OF DEATH    =
}}
[[Category:Indian film singers]]
[[Category:Living people]]
[[Category:Malayalam playback singers]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
