<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="11173828" ns="0" title="Zoomerang.com"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Multiple issues|advert=January 2010|npov=January 2010|one source=January 2010|refimprove=January 2010}}
{{redirect|Zoomerang}}
{{Infobox Website
| name = Zoomerang
| logo = [[Image:Zoomerang-logo.png]]
| screenshot =  
| caption = Zoomerang homepage
| url = [http://www.zoomerang.com www.zoomerang.com]
| commercial = Yes
| type = online survey software
| language = 
| registration = Over 1,000,000 registered users 
| owner = [[MarketTools]], Inc.
| author = [[MarketTools]], Inc.
| launch date = 1999
| current status = 
| revenue = 
}}
'''Zoomerang.com''' is an online survey tool that allows users to create, send and analyze online survey results on-demand. Additionally, the Zoomerang [[brand]] name encompasses  [[survey sampling|survey samples]], [[Focus group#Online focus groups|online focus groups]], [[Online panel]] and other market research solutions offered by the [[MarketTools]] corporation.

==History==
Created by [[MarketTools]], Inc., a privately held [[market research]] company founded in 1997 and headquartered in [[San Francisco]], California in September 1999, Zoomerang was one of the first online survey software tools on the market.&lt;ref&gt;[http://info.zoomerang.com/press/release030303.htm Zoomerang Press Release Archives]&lt;/ref&gt;  Zoomerang was designed to offer survey [[software as a service]] for businesses conducting consumer, competitor, and customer satisfaction surveys.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.e-myth.com/pub/htdocs/82 E-Myth Newsletter - Bill Schlegel Biography]&lt;/ref&gt; Zoomerang reports more than 1,000,000 registered users.&lt;ref&gt;[http://technology.inc.com/internet/articles/200612/onlinesurveys.html Inc. Technology - Damon Brown]&lt;/ref&gt;

==Products and services==
Zoomerang is an online survey tool that allows individuals to quickly and easily create online surveys to collect and share feedback. Zoomerang offers three subscription levels ranging from a limited-use free version, to more powerful paid versions.  &quot;Zoomerang Basic&quot;, the free version, provides unlimited number of surveys, with up to 30 questions and 100 responses each.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;Tapping Into Your Customers' Brainwaves&quot; by John R. Hall, ''Air Conditioning, Heating &amp; Refrigeration News'', July 9, 2007, page 9.&lt;/ref&gt;   &quot;Zoomerang Pro&quot; and &quot;Zoomerang Premium&quot; are the two paid versions of Zoomerang, offered both as a monthly or annual subscription. These advanced versions provide subscribers with more powerful survey creation and reporting features - such as unlimited number of questions per survey, cross-tabulation, skip logic, filtering, statistics, custom branding, report downloads and customizable charts and graphs.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;Zooming in on Customers&quot; by Alan Horotz. ''Sales and Marketing Management'', November 2004, page 21.&lt;/ref&gt;  Zoomerang also offers an Enterprise version which allows teams to collaborate within their team, or across their organization on survey creation, management, and analysis with other Zoomerang users from one centralized location. In addition to Zoomerang's online survey software, the company offers expert professional services, including survey programming and an online panel of over 2.5 million survey respondents profiled on over 500 attributes. Zoomerang customers also take advantage MarketTools' in-house research services ranging from customer insight management services, online community platforms and online panel management.

==Awards==
* Forbes &quot;Best of the Web&quot; 2000
* 2006 Product of the Year Finalist - Small Business Technology Magazine &lt;ref&gt; [http://www.sbtechnologymagazine.org/magazine/read/archives/articles/article.php?ProposalOnlineID=482 Small Business Technology Magazine]&lt;/ref&gt; (Zoomerang zPro.)

== See also ==
*[[Online questionnaires]]
*[[Online panel]]
*[[Software as a service]]
*[[Application service provider]]

Related services:
* [[Surveytool]], related tool
* [[SurveyShare]], related tool
* [[SurveyProf]], related tool
* [[SurveyMonkey]], similar company


== References ==
&lt;references /&gt;

== External links ==
* [http://www.zoomerang.com Zoomerang homepage]
* [http://money.cnn.com/2005/12/06/technology/opinion_fsb/index.htm Fortune Small Business article on online survey tools.]
* [http://webworkerdaily.com/2007/04/09/serious-surveys-with-zoomerang/ Web Worker Daily review of Zoomerang]

[[Category:Web applications]]
[[Category:Polling_companies]]
[[Category:Companies based in San Francisco, California]]
[[Category:Marketing research companies of the United States]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
