<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="1121871" ns="0" title="Corel Linux"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Infobox_OS |
  name = Corel Linux |
  logo = |
  screenshot = |
  caption = |
  developer = [[Corel]] |
  family = [[Unix-like]], [[Linux]] |
  source_model = |
  working_state = Discontinued |
  latest_release_version = |
  latest_release_date = |
  ui = [[KDE]] |
  kernel_type = |
  license = |
  website = |
}}
'''Corel Linux''', also called '''Corel LinuxOS''', was a [[Debian]]-based [[operating system]] made by [[Corel]] that was released in late 1999. Corel later discontinued the distribution, but did not remove the former Corel Open Source Development website until March 2002.

Corel did not use KFM, the standard [[KDE]] [[file manager]]. It instead used its own file manager, CFM. This, along with other modifications Corel made, meant that Corel Linux suffered at being incompatible with other versions of Linux much more so than other competitors in the industry. At a time when there was relatively little Linux software available, this was a serious hurdle for Corel and its users.

Corel LinuxOS Second Edition was released in download, regular and deluxe editions, the latter of which bundled [[WordPerfect Office|Corel WordPerfect Office]] for Linux.

[[Xandros]] purchased the Corel Linux source code and development team when [[Corel]] scrapped its Linux business in August 2001. However, the Corel Corporation is a stockholder of Xandros.

== Major features ==
Corel Linux featured a file manager that was very close in look and feel to [[Windows Explorer]]. The file manager provided an integrated Windows SMB network browser. 

=== SmartMove === &lt;!--This subheading is redirected to from [[SmartMove]], is the sub-heading is changed or removed, please also edit that redirect. Thank you.--&gt;
Corel '''SmartMove''' was a part of Corel Linux. This application provided the following:
# Migrate Microsoft Windows settings to Corel Linux.
# Automate restoring settings that are changed by SmartMove.
# Provide an easy way to access network folders through Corel Linux.

SmartMove was built around the [[Wine (software)|Wine]] libraries to read the [[Windows registry]] settings for the Windows applications and thus be able to migrate them. SmartMove core libraries created a wrapper for the Windows registry to easily look up the settings.

&lt;blockquote&gt;
SmartMove looks for existing [[Microsoft Windows]] installations on the machine, looks a little further for individual users, and offers to transfer application settings to analogous programs under Linux. It understands how to deal with [[Internet Explorer]] and [[Netscape]] cookies and bookmarks, [[Microsoft Outlook|Outlook]], [[mIRC]], and [[ICQ]] settings, and a variety of desktop preferences, including wallpaper, color scheme, and even mouse &quot;handedness&quot;. We tried it out with a few settings, but since our Windows installation was fairly new, we didn't have much to check against.&lt;ref&gt; {{cite web|url=http://www.linuxplanet.com/linuxplanet/previews/2159/4/ |title=Sneak Preview: Corel Linux OS Second Edition |accessdate=2007-03-19 |last=Hall |first=Michael |date=2000-08-07 |work=LinuxPlanet }}&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

With the death of Corel Linux, this application faded away and is no longer maintained, however similar functionality is now available on at least Ubuntu when installing a dual-boot configuration on a machine that already has Windows on it.&lt;ref&gt;[https://wiki.ubuntu.com/7.04Tour#head-7fb72f38a89c243a38487143fda3a3655d5ded80 Ubuntu feature announcement from Ubuntu 7.04 release]&lt;/ref&gt;

==References==
{{reflist}}

== Further reading ==
* [http://www.washingtonpost.com/ac2/wp-dyn?pagename=article&amp;contentId=A5576-2001Feb14&amp;notFound=true WashingtonPost: Microsoft Faces New Antitrust Probe Over Corel Deal]
* [http://slashdot.org/article.pl?sid=00/10/02/220238 Slashdot: Microsoft Buys into Corel]
* [http://www.forbes.com/2000/10/03/1003corel.html Forbes: Corel Sells Out To Microsoft]
* [http://slashdot.org/article.pl?sid=02/02/17/152203&amp;tid=132 Slashdot: Corel Shuts Down Open Source Development Site]
* [http://archives.cnn.com/2000/TECH/computing/10/16/corel.linux.on.ms.idg/index.html CNN: Interview: Corel's Linux VP on the Microsoft deal]
* [http://slashdot.org/article.pl?sid=99/09/20/1051226&amp;mode=nested Slashdot: Corel Linux Beta License Violates GPL]
* [http://yro.slashdot.org/article.pl?sid=07/06/04/1630233 Slashdot: Microsoft Gives Xandros Users Patent Protection]
* [http://web.archive.org/web/20000308074253/http://corel.com/news/1999/may/may_1999_faqs.htm Archived Corel Linux FAQ]
* [http://web.archive.org/web/20020127150324/http://opensource.corel.com Archived version of OpenSource.Corel.com from Jan 02]

{{Linux-distro}}

[[Category:Discontinued Linux distributions]]
[[Category:Debian-based distributions]]
[[Category:Corel software]]
[[Category:1999 software]]

[[de:Corel Linux]]
[[es:Corel Linux]]
[[zh:Corel Linux]]
[[fa:کورل لینوکس]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
