<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="1126158" ns="0" title="Microsoft Project"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{lead too long|date=February 2011}}
{{refimprove|date=February 2011}}
{{Infobox software
|  name = Microsoft Office Project
|  logo = 
|  screenshot = [[Image:MSProj2010.PNG|250px|Microsoft Project 2010 Screenshot]]
|  caption = Screenshot of Microsoft Project 2010.
|  developer = [[Microsoft]] Corporation
|  latest_release_version = 2010 (14.0)
|  latest_release_date = June 15, 2010
|  operating_system = [[Microsoft Windows]]
|  genre = [[Project management software]]
|  license = [[EULA]]
|  website =[http://office.microsoft.com/en-us/project Microsoft Project Homepage]
}}
'''Microsoft Project''' (MSP, MSOP or WinProj) is a [[project management software]] program, developed and sold by [[Microsoft]], which is designed to assist a [[project manager]] in developing a [[plan]], assigning [[Resource (project management)|resources]] to tasks, tracking progress, managing the [[budget]], and analyzing workloads.

The application creates [[critical path method|critical path]] schedules, and [[critical chain]] and [[event chain methodology]] third-party add-ons also are available. Schedules can be [[resource management|resource leveled]], and chains are visualized in a [[Gantt chart]]. Additionally, MS Project can recognize different classes of users.  These different classes of users can have differing access levels to projects, views, and other data. Custom objects such as calendars, views, tables, filters, and fields are stored in an enterprise global which is shared by all users.

MS Project was the company's third Microsoft Windows-based application, and within a couple of years of its introduction it became the dominant PC-based project management software.

Although branded as a member of the [[Microsoft Office]] family, it never has been included in any of the Office suites (like [[Microsoft Visio|Visio]]).  This also was the case with Office 2010. It is available currently in two editions, Standard and Professional. MS Project's [[Proprietary format|proprietary]] file format is ''.mpp''.

Microsoft Project and [[Microsoft Project Server]] are the cornerstones of the [[Microsoft Office]] [[Enterprise Project Management]] (EPM) product. Microsoft Project 2010 features the [[Ribbon (computing)|Ribbon user interface]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.microsoft.com/Presspass/exec/steve/2007/10-30OPConferenceBallmer.mspx Microsoft Office Project Conference 2007]&lt;/ref&gt;

==History==
[[Image:Screengrab - Microsoft Project 9.0.2000.0224 - (simple Gantt chart) .png|thumb|Microsoft Project 2000]]
Microsoft Project was initially proposed by Microsoft's Manager of Product Development, [[Alan M. Boyd]] as an internal tool to help manage the huge number of software projects that were in development at any time inside the company. Boyd wrote the specification and engaged a local Seattle company to develop the prototype.

The first commercial version of Project was released for [[DOS]] in 1984.  Microsoft bought all rights to the software in 1985 and released version 2. Version 3 for DOS was released in 1986. Version 4 for DOS was the final DOS version, released in 1986. The first [[Microsoft Windows|Windows]] version was released in 1990, and was labelled version 1 for Windows.

In 1991 a [[Macintosh]] version was released.  Development continued until Microsoft Project 4.0 for Mac in 1993. In 1994, Microsoft stopped development of most of its Mac applications and did not offer a new version of Office until 1998, after the creation of the new Microsoft Macintosh Business Unit the year prior. The Mac Business Unit never released an updated version of Project, and the last version does not run natively on [[Mac OS X]].

Microsoft Project 95 was the first to use common Office menus.

Microsoft Project 98 was the first to use Tahoma font in the menu bars and to contain [[Office Assistant]], like all Office 97 applications. Project 98 SR-1 was a major service release addressing several issues in Project 98. &lt;ref&gt; [http://support.microsoft.com/kb/185103/ PRJ98: List of Fixes in Microsoft Project 98 SR-1] &lt;/ref&gt;

Versions were released in 1992 (v3), 1993 (v4), 1995 (4.1a), 1998 (9.0), 2000 (10.0), 2002 (11.0), 2003 (12.0), 2007 (13.0) and 2010 (14.0).&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.microsoft.com/uk/office/previous/project/default.mspx Previous Versions of Microsoft Project], [[Microsoft.com]]{{Dead link|date=March 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; There was no Version 2 on the Windows platform; the original design spec was augmented with the addition of macro capabilities and the extra work required to support a macro language pushed the development schedule out to early 1992 (Version 3).

==Features==
[[Image:proj2007.jpg|thumb|Microsoft Project 2007 showing a simple [[Gantt chart]]]]
Project creates budgets based on assignment work and resource rates. As resources are assigned to tasks and assignment work estimated, the program calculates the cost, equal to the work times the rate, which rolls up to the task level and then to any summary tasks and finally to the project level. Resource definitions (people, equipment and materials) can be shared between projects using a shared resource pool. Each resource can have its own calendar, which defines what days and shifts a resource is available. Resource rates are used to calculate resource assignment costs which are rolled up and summarized at the resource level. Each resource can be assigned to multiple tasks in multiple plans and each task can be assigned multiple resources, and the application schedules task work based on the resource availability as defined in the resource calendars. All resources can be defined in label without limit.  Therefore it cannot determine how many finished products can be produced with a given amount of raw materials.  This makes MS Project unsuitable for solving problems of available materials constrained production.  Additional software is necessary to manage a complex facility that produces physical goods.

===Enhancements===
In later versions of [[Microsoft Office]], Microsoft Project's capabilities were extended with the introduction of [[Microsoft Office Project Server]] and Microsoft Project Web Access.  Project Server stores Project data in a central [[SQL]]-based database, allowing users to display and update this data over the Internet.  Web Access allows authorized users to access a Project Server database across the [[Internet]], and includes timesheets, graphical analysis of resource workloads, and administrative tools.

Microsoft Office suite, the later versions also provide for cross-functionality with products like  [[Microsoft PowerPoint|PowerPoint]] and [[Microsoft Visio|Visio]].

==See also==
*[[Microsoft Office Project Server]]
*[[List of project management software]]

==References==
{{reflist}}

==External links==
*{{Official website|http://www.microsoft.com/project}}
*[http://blogs.msdn.com/project/ Official Microsoft Project team blog]
*[http://blogs.msdn.com/project_programmability/ Official Microsoft Project Programmability blog]
*[http://office.microsoft.com/en-us/project/HA102143771033.aspx The Project Roadmap], introduced in 2001, was developed to lead users from broad PM concepts to MS Project functionality.
*[http://www.microsoft.com/industry/government/products/project2010/default.aspx Microsoft Project for government]


{{Microsoft Office}}

[[Category:Windows software]]
[[Category:Microsoft Office|Project]]
[[Category:Project management software]]
[[Category:Critical Path Scheduling]]
[[Category:1984 software]]

[[ar:مايكروسوفت بروجكت]]
[[bg:Microsoft Project]]
[[ca:Microsoft Project]]
[[cs:Microsoft Project]]
[[da:Microsoft Project]]
[[de:Microsoft Project]]
[[es:Microsoft Project]]
[[fr:Microsoft Project]]
[[ko:마이크로소프트 프로젝트]]
[[it:Microsoft Project]]
[[lv:Microsoft Project]]
[[nl:Microsoft Office Project]]
[[ja:Microsoft Project]]
[[pl:Microsoft Project]]
[[pt:Microsoft Project]]
[[ru:Microsoft Project]]
[[sv:Microsoft Project]]
[[tr:Microsoft Project]]
[[uk:Microsoft Project]]
[[vi:Microsoft Project]]
[[zh:Microsoft Project]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
