<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="11272175" ns="0" title="2004 Israel–Gaza conflict"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{main|Israel-Gaza conflict|Israeli-Palestinian conflict}}
{{mergeto|Operation Rainbow|Operation Days of Penitence|discuss=Talk:2004 Israel–Gaza conflict|date=February 2010}} 
{{Infobox Military Conflict
|conflict=2004 Israel-Gaza conflict
|partof=the [[Second Intifada]]
|image=[[Image:Gaza conflict map.png|300px]]
|caption=Area of the conflict
|date=2004
|place=[[Gaza Strip]]
|casus= Qassam rocket attacks
|result=
|combatant1={{flag|Israel}} ([[Israel Defense Forces|IDF]])
|combatant2=[[File:Flag of Hamas.svg|22px]] [[Hamas]]&lt;br /&gt; {{flagicon image|Flag of Jihad.svg}} [[Palestinian Islamic Jihad|Islamic Jihad]]&lt;br /&gt; [[Popular Resistance Committees|PRC]]&lt;br /&gt;
|commander1=
|commander2=
|strength1=
|strength2=
|casualties1=28 soldiers killed,&lt;br&gt;15 Israeli civilians killed&lt;br&gt;3 Thai civilians killed&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.mfa.gov.il/MFA/Terrorism-+Obstacle+to+Peace/Palestinian+terror+since+2000/Victims+of+Palestinian+Violence+and+Terrorism+sinc.htm Victims of Palestinian Violence and Terrorism since September 2000]&lt;/ref&gt;
|casualties2=101-132 Hamas fighters killed&lt;br&gt;54 civilians killed
}}
{{Campaignbox Al aqsa}}
The '''2004 Israel–Gaza conflict''' refers to the series of battles between [[Palestinian political violence|Palestinian militants]] and the [[Israel Defense Forces]] (IDF). IDF carried out airstrikes and land incursions after several [[qassam rocket]] attacks on [[Israel]] ([[Sderot]] and the [[Negev]]). The fighting included two IDF operations, [[Operation Rainbow]] and [[Operation Days of Penitence]].

== Timeline ==
In response to a repeated shelling of Israeli communities with [[Qassam rocket]]s and mortar shells from Gaza, the [[Israel Defense Forces|IDF]] operated mainly in [[Rafah]] &amp;mdash; to search and destroy [[smuggling tunnel]]s used by militants to obtain [[weapon]]s, [[ammunition]], [[fugitive]]s, [[cigarette]]s, car parts, electrical goods, foreign [[currency]], [[gold]], [[recreational drug use|drugs]], and cloth from  [[Egypt]]. Raids in Rafah left many families homeless. Israel's official stance is that their houses were captured by militants and were destroyed during battles with IDF forces. Many of these houses are abandoned due to Israeli incursions and later destroyed. According to Human Rights Watch, over 1,500 houses were destroyed to create a large buffer zone in the city, many &quot;in the absence of military necessity&quot;, displacing around sixteen thousand people.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.hrw.org/campaigns/gaza/|accessdate=2006-03-29|title=Razing Rafah: Mass Home Demolitions in the Gaza Strip|publisher=[[Human Rights Watch]] |archiveurl = http://web.archive.org/web/20060324012233/http://www.hrw.org/campaigns/gaza/ &lt;!-- Bot retrieved archive --&gt; |archivedate = 2006-03-24}}&lt;/ref&gt;

On 2 February 2004, Israeli Prime Minister [[Ariel Sharon]] announced his plan to transfer all the [[Israeli settlement|Jewish settlers]] from the [[Gaza Strip]]. The Israeli opposition dismissed his announcement as &quot;media spin&quot; but the [[Labor (Israel)|Israeli Labour Party]] said it would support such a move. Sharon's right-wing coalition partners [[National Religious Party]] and [[National Union (Israel)|National Union]] rejected the plan and vowed to quit the government if it were implemented. Surprisingly, [[Yossi Beilin]], peace advocate and architect of the [[Oslo Accords]] and the [[Geneva Accord]], also rejected the proposed withdrawal plan. He claimed that withdrawing from the Gaza Strip without a peace agreement would reward [[terrorism|terror]].

Following the declaration of the '''[[Israel's unilateral disengagement plan|disengagement plan]]''' by Ariel Sharon and as a response to suicide attacks on [[Israeli Gaza Strip barrier|Erez crossing]] and [[Ashdod]] sea[[port]] (10 people were killed), the [[Israel Defense Forces|IDF]] launched a series of armored raids on the Gaza Strip (mainly [[Rafah]] and refugee camps around [[Gaza]]), killing about 70 [[Hamas]] militants. On March 22, 2004, an Israeli helicopter gunship killed Hamas leader Sheikh [[Ahmed Yassin]] and on April 17, after several failed attempts by Hamas to commit suicide bombings, his successor, [[Abdel Aziz al-Rantissi]] was killed by IDF [[Attack helicopter|helicopter gunship]] strike.

The fighting in [[Gaza Strip]] escalated severely in May 2004 after several failed attempts to attack [[Israel Defense Forces checkpoint|Israeli checkpoints]] such as [[Israeli Gaza Strip barrier|Erez crossing]] and [[Karni crossing]]. However, on May 11 and May 12, Palestinian militants destroyed two IDF [[M113 Armored Personnel Carrier|M-113]] [[Armoured personnel carrier|APC]]s, killing 13 soldiers and mutilating their bodies. The IDF launched two raids to recover the bodies in which about 20-40 Palestinians were killed and great damage was caused to structures in the Zaitoun neighbourhood in [[Gaza]] and in south-west [[Rafah]].

Subsequently, on May 18 the IDF launched [[Operation Rainbow]] with a stated aim of striking the terror infrastructure of Rafah, destroying [[smuggling tunnel]]s, and stopping a shipment of [[Strela 2|SA-7]] missiles and improved [[anti-tank]] weapons. The operation ended after the IDF killed 40 Palestinian militants and 12 civilians and demolished about 45-56 structures. The great destruction and killing of 10 protesters led to a worldwide outcry against the operation.

On September 29, after a [[Qassam rocket]] hit the Israeli town of [[Sderot]] and killed two Israeli children, the IDF launched [[Operation Days of Penitence]] in the north of the [[Gaza Strip]]. The operation's stated aim was to remove the threat of Qassam rockets from Sderot and kill the Hamas militants launching them. The operation ended on October 16, leaving widespread destruction and more than 100 Palestinians dead, at least 20 of whom were under the age of 16.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.guardian.co.uk/israel/Story/0,2763,1328916,00.html|title=Army pulls back from Gaza leaving 100 Palestinians dead|publisher=[[The Guardian]]|date=2004-10-16 | location=London | first=Chris | last=McGreal | accessdate=April 22, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; Thirteen-year-old [[Iman Darweesh Al Hams]] was killed by the IDF; some reports claimed a commander had deliberately fired his automatic weapon at her dead body, but the soldier was cleared of all charges.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.thejewishweek.com/news/newscontent.php3?artid=10201|date=2004-12-03|publisher=[[The Jewish Week]]|title=Moral Quagmire}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.csmonitor.com/2004/1126/p07s01-wome.html|date=2004-11-26|publisher=[[Christian Science Monitor]]|title=Israeli army under fire after killing girl}}&lt;/ref&gt; According to Palestinian medics, Israeli forces killed at least 62 militants and 42 other Palestinians believed to be civilians.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.alertnet.org/thenews/newsdesk/L16687192.htm|publisher=Reuters|title=Palestinians sift rubble after Israel's Gaza assault|date=2004-10-16}}&lt;/ref&gt; According to a count performed by [[Haaretz]], 87 combatants and 42 non-combatants were killed. Palestinian refugee camps were heavily damaged by the Israeli assault. The IDF announced that at least 12 Qassam launchings had been thwarted and many terrorists hit during the operation. Three Israelis also were killed, including one civilian.

On October 21, the [[Israeli Air Force]] killed [[Adnan al-Ghoul]], a senior [[Hamas]] bomb maker and the inventor of the [[Qassam rocket]].

Escalation in Gaza began amid the visit of [[Mahmoud Abbas]] to [[Syria]] in order to achieve a [[Hudna]] between Palestinian factions and convince Hamas leadership to halt attacks against Israelis. Hamas vowed to continue the armed struggle, while numerous [[Qassam rocket]]s hit open fields near ''Nahal Oz'' and an anti-tank missile hit a [[kindergarten]] in [[Gush Katif|Kfar Darom]].

On December 9 five weapon smugglers were killed and two were arrested in the border between [[Rafah]] and [[Egypt]]. Later that day, Jamal Abu Samhadana and two of his bodyguards were injured by a missile strike. In the first Israeli airstrike against militants in weeks, an unmanned Israeli drone plane launched one missile at Abu Samahdna's car as it traveled between Rafah and Khan Younis in the southern Gaza Strip. It was the fourth attempt on Samhadana's life by Israel. Samhadana is one of two leaders of the [[Popular Resistance Committees]] and one of the main forces behind the [[smuggling tunnel]]s. Samhadana is believed to be responsible for the [[Improvised explosive device|blast]] against an American diplomatic convoy in [[Gaza]] that killed three Americans.

On December 10, in response to [[Hamas]] firing mortar rounds into the Neveh Dekalim settlement in the [[Gaza Strip]] and wounding four Israelis (including an 8 year old boy), Israeli soldiers fired at the Khan Younis refugee camp (the origin of the mortars) killing a 7-year-old girl. An [[Israel Defense Forces|IDF]] source confirmed troops opened fire at Khan Younis, but said they aimed at Hamas mortar crews. The IDF insisted that it does its utmost to avoid civilian casualties.

The largest attack since the death of [[Yasser Arafat]] claimed the lives of five Israeli soldiers on December 12, wounding ten others. Approximately 1.5 tons of explosives were detonated in a tunnel under an Israeli military-controlled border crossing on the Egyptian border with Gaza near [[Rafah]], collapsing several structures and damaging others. The explosion destroyed part of the outpost and killed three soldiers. Two Palestinian militants then penetrated the outpost and killed two other Israeli soldiers with gunfire. It is believed that Hamas and a new Fatah faction, the &quot;Fatah Hawks,&quot; conducted the highly organized and coordinated attack. A spokesman, &quot;Abu Majad,&quot; claimed responsibility for the attack in the name of the [[Fatah Hawks]] claiming it was in retaliation for &quot;the assassination&quot; of Yasser Arafat, charging he was poisoned by Israel.

==See also==
*[[Timeline up to 2006 Gaza crisis]]
*[[2006 Israel-Gaza conflict]]
*[[2006 Israel-Gaza conflict casualties timeline]]
*[[2007–2008 Israel-Gaza conflict]]
*[[2008 Israel-Gaza conflict]]
*[[List of Qassam rocket attacks]]

==Notes==
{{Reflist|2}}

{{Gaza crisis}}
{{Israeli-Palestinian Conflict}}
{{Arab-Israeli Conflict}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:2004 Israel–Gaza Conflict}}
[[Category:2004 Israel–Gaza conflict| ]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
