<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="1133541" ns="0" title="Nuclear football"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Expert-verify|article|date=December 2008}}
:''This article is about the United States. For similar objects worldwide, see [[Nuclear briefcase]]''

The '''nuclear football''' (also known as the '''atomic football''', the '''president's emergency satchel''', the '''button''', the '''black box''', or just the '''football''') is a [[briefcase]], the contents of which are to be used by the [[President of the United States|President]] of the [[United States|United States of America]] to authorize a [[Nuclear warfare|nuclear attack]] while away from fixed [[command center]]s, such as the [[White House Situation Room]]. It functions as a mobile hub in the strategic defense system of the United States.

== Contents ==
According to a ''[[The Washington Post|Washington Post]]'' article, the President is always accompanied by a military aide carrying a &quot;football&quot; with launch codes for nuclear weapons.&lt;ref&gt;Eggen, Dan. [http://www.washingtonpost.com/wp-dyn/content/article/2008/12/21/AR2008122100869.html &quot;Cheney, Biden Spar In TV Appearances&quot;]. ''[[The Washington Post]]'', December 22, 2008. Accessed 16 December 2009.&lt;/ref&gt;

It is a metallic [[Zero Halliburton]] briefcase&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.baggageforless.com/zero_haliburton_Salt_Lake_Article.asp  &quot;Security: Sleek, sexy and oh, so safe / Utah company's attaché case is a Hollywood staple.&quot;] Glen Warchol, ''[[The Salt Lake Tribune]]''.&lt;/ref&gt; carried in a black leather &quot;jacket&quot;. The package weighs around 45 [[Pound (mass)|pounds]] (20 [[kilograms]]).&lt;ref name=usatoday&gt;[[Associated Press]]. [http://www.usatoday.com/news/washington/2005-05-05-nuclear-football_x.htm &quot;Military aides still carry the president's nuclear 'football'&quot;]. ''[[USA Today]]'', May 5, 2005. Accessed 16 December 2009.&lt;/ref&gt; A small antenna protrudes from the bag near the handle.&lt;ref name=usatoday/&gt;

In his book ''Breaking Cover,'' Bill Gulley, the former director of the [[White House Military Office]] wrote:&lt;ref name=usatoday/&gt;
{{quote|There are four things in the Football. The Black Book containing the retaliatory options, a book listing classified site locations, a manila folder with eight or ten pages stapled together giving a description of procedures for the [[Emergency Broadcast System]], and a three-by-five inch card with authentication codes. The Black Book was about 9 by 12 inches and had 75 loose-leaf pages printed in black and red. The book with classified site locations was about the same size as the Black Book, and was black. It contained information on sites around the country where the president could be taken in an emergency.}}

== Operation ==
If the President (who is [[Commander-in-chief#United States|Commander-in-Chief]]) decided to order the use of nuclear weapons, he would be taken aside by the &quot;carrier&quot; and the briefcase opened. Then a command signal or &quot;watch&quot; alert would be issued to the [[Joint Chiefs of Staff]]. The President would then review the attack options with the aide and decide upon a plan which could range from a single [[cruise missile]] to multiple [[intercontinental ballistic missile|ICBM]] launches. These are preset war plans developed under the [[Single Integrated Operational Plan|SIOP]] (Single Integrated Operational Plan) which at one time represented the entire joint US/[[United Kingdom|UK]] plan for &quot;disassembling&quot; {{Citation needed|date=August 2010}} the [[Soviet Union|USSR]] by means of nuclear weapons.  It is unknown if it uses SATCOM (satellite communications), VLFT ([[very low frequency]] transmission) or VHFT ([[very high frequency]] transmission), although the briefcases have been seen with an antenna protruding from them on more than one occasion.  Next, using whatever communications technology the satchel has, the aide would then presumably make contact with the [[National Military Command Center]] or, in a retaliatory strike situation, multiple airborne command posts (who likely fly [[Boeing E-4|Boeing E-4B]]) and/or nuclear armed submarines.

Before the order can be processed by the military, the President must be positively identified using a special code issued on a plastic card, nicknamed the &quot;[[Gold Codes|biscuit]]&quot;.&lt;ref name=icnnd&gt;[http://www.icnnd.org/research/Jason_Fritz_Hacking_NC2.pdf Hacking Nuclear Command and Control], pg. 10.&lt;/ref&gt; The United States has a [[two-man rule]] in place, and while only the President can order the release of nuclear weapons, the order must be confirmed by the [[United States Secretary of Defense|Secretary of Defense]] (there is a hierarchy of succession in the event that the President has been killed in an attack).&lt;ref name=icnnd/&gt;  Once all the codes have been verified, the military would issue attack orders to the proper units. These orders are given and then re-verified for authenticity. 

The football is carried by one of the rotating presidential military aides, whose work schedule is described by a top-secret rota (one from each of the five service branches). They are occasionally physically attached to the briefcase via a security cable around the wrist. This person is a [[Officer (armed forces)|commissioned officer]] in the [[Military of the United States|U.S. military]], pay-grade [[U.S. military pay grades#Commissioned officers pay grades|O-4]] or above, who has undergone the nation's most rigorous [[background check]] ([[Yankee White]]).&lt;ref name=gs&gt;[http://www.globalsecurity.org/wmd/systems/nuclear-football.htm The Football]—[[GlobalSecurity.org]] article&lt;/ref&gt; These armed officers are required to keep the football readily accessible to the President at all times. Consequently, an aide, football in hand, is always either standing or walking near the President or riding in [[Air Force One]], [[Marine One]], or the [[United States President's limousine|presidential motorcade]] with the President.

There are three such &quot;footballs&quot; in existence. The first travels with the President, a spare is kept at the [[White House]], and the third is with the [[Vice President of the United States|Vice President]].&lt;ref name=usatoday/&gt;

== History ==
The football dates back to [[Dwight D. Eisenhower]], but its current usage came about in the aftermath of the [[Cuba]]n [[Cuban Missile Crisis|missile crisis]], when [[John F. Kennedy]] was concerned that a Soviet commander in Cuba might launch their missiles without authorization from Moscow.&lt;ref name=gs/&gt;

It has been stated in an [[Associated Press]] article that the nickname &quot;football&quot; was derived from an attack plan codenamed &quot;Dropkick&quot;.&lt;ref name=usatoday/&gt;  The nickname has led to some confusion as to the nature—and even the shape—of the device; in the [[graphic novel]] series [[Watchmen]], President Richard Nixon, fictionally depicted as still being President in 1985, was depicted with a literal &quot;nuclear football&quot;—a metal device shaped like a football—handcuffed to his wrist.  While it is never explicitly stated what it is, it is implied that the device is the electronic activation source for the nuclear option.

During their presidencies, both [[Jimmy Carter]] and [[Ronald Reagan]] preferred to keep the launch codes in their jacket pocket.&lt;ref&gt;Reagan, Ronald. ''An American Life.'' Pg. 257.&lt;/ref&gt; On one occasion, Jimmy Carter left nuclear launch codes in his suit when it was sent in for [[dry cleaning]].&lt;ref name=&quot;BBC Article&quot;&gt;[http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/world/americas/328442.stm &quot;Clinton drops nuclear football&quot;]. [[BBC News]], April 26, 1999. Accessed 16 December 2009.&lt;/ref&gt;   Congressman [[John Kline (politician)|John Kline]] served as a colonel in the [[United States Marine Corps]] and carried the football for Presidents Carter and Reagan.  

The football was separated from Ronald Reagan immediately after the 1981 [[Reagan assassination attempt|assassination attempt]] against him.&lt;ref name=&quot;BBC Article&quot;/&gt;  Reagan, like his predecessor Carter, preferred to carry the card in his pocket.  He was separated from it when his clothing was cut off by the emergency room trauma team.  It was later discovered unsecured lying in one of his shoes on the emergency room floor. This led to an urban legend that Reagan carried the code in his sock.  Reagan was separated from the rest of the football as well because the officer who carried it was left behind as the motorcade sped away with the wounded President.
On occasion the President has left his aide carrying the football behind. This happened to Presidents [[Richard Nixon]], [[Gerald Ford]], [[Jimmy Carter]], [[George H. W. Bush]]&lt;ref name=&quot;Pullella&quot;&gt;Pullella, Philip. [http://legacy.signonsandiego.com/news/world/20040604-0731-pope-bush-football.html &quot;Bush's nuclear 'football' in Vatican hallowed halls&quot;]. [[Reuters]] via [[The San Diego Union-Tribune]], June 4, 2004. Accessed 18 August 2010.&lt;/ref&gt; and, most recently, [[Bill Clinton]] on April 24, 1999.&lt;ref name=&quot;BBC Article&quot;/&gt; In none of these cases was the integrity of the football breached.

== See also ==
* [[Cheget]], the Russian counterpart
* [[Permissive Action Link]]
* [[Nuclear briefcase]]

== Notes ==
{{Reflist|2}}

== Further reading ==
* Ford, Daniel F. (1985). ''The Button: The Pentagon's Strategic Command and Control System''. New York: Simon and Schuster. ISBN 0671500686. {{OCLC|11533371}}.
* Gulley, Bill, and Mary Ellen Reese. (1980). ''Breaking Cover''. New York: Simon and Schuster. ISBN 0671245481. {{OCLC|6304331}}.

== External links==
* [http://www.globalsecurity.org/wmd/systems/nuclear-football.htm The Football]—[[GlobalSecurity.org]] article including images of [[Smithsonian Institution]] retired &quot;football&quot;
* [http://store.aetv.com/html/product/index.jhtml?id=73657 ''The Nuclear Football''], a [[History Channel]] Special

{{DEFAULTSORT:Nuclear Football}}
[[Category:Executive Office of the President of the United States]]
[[Category:Military communications]]
[[Category:Nuclear command and control]]

[[de:Atomkoffer]]
[[id:Nuclear Football]]
[[it:Nuclear football]]
[[ja:核のフットボール]]
[[pt:Nuclear Football]]
[[ru:Ядерный чемоданчик (США)]]
[[simple:Nuclear football]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
