<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="11344378" ns="0" title="Republican Party of Texas"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Infobox American political party
| party_name = Republican Party of Texas
| party_articletitle = Republican Party (United States)
| studentwing = [[Texas College Republicans]]
| party_logo =  [[File:RPT_Logo.jpg]]
| website = [http://www.texasgop.org/ www.texasgop.org/]
| headquarters = 1108 Lavaca, Suite 500&lt;br /&gt;[[Austin, Texas]] 78701
| chairman = [[Steve Munisteri]]
| houseleader = [[Joe Straus]]
| senateleader = [[David Dewhurst]]
| foundation = {{start date|1854}}
| fiscalpolicy =
| socialpolicy =
| ideology = [[Conservatism in the United States|Conservatism]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Fiscal conservatism]]
| UHseats =  {{Infobox political party/seats|19|31|hex=red}}
| LHseats =   {{Infobox political party/seats|101|150|hex=red}}
| national = [[Republican Party (United States)|Republican Party]]
}}

{{Refimprove|date=February 2011}}
The '''Republican Party of Texas''' (RPT) is one of the two major political parties in the U.S. State of [[Texas]]. It is affiliated with the United States [[Republican Party (United States)|Republican Party]]. The State Chairman is [[Steve Munisteri]], a retired [[attorney at law (United States)|attorney]] and [[business]]man from [[Houston, Texas|Houston]], and the Vice-Chair is Melinda Fredricks of [[Conroe, Texas|Conroe]]. The RPT is headquartered in [[Downtown Austin|Downtown]] [[Austin, Texas|Austin]]. The RPT's mission is to promote a conservative philosophy of government by promoting conservative principles and by providing the infrastructure through which those who share our conservative principles can get involved in the political process, run for and be elected to public office, and govern according to our principles when elected.  The RPT is legally classified as a [[political action committee]] whose structure is determined by state law &amp; by party rules not in conflict with state law.

==History==

Since the days of [[Reconstruction Era of the United States|Reconstruction]], the Republican Party of Texas went through over 100 years of being a minority party in the state. In 1870, [[Edmund Davis]] was elected Governor, but was soundly defeated in 1874. In the year 1876, Republicans had made gradual gains in Texas, earning nearly one-third of the statewide vote and electing a small number of candidates to the State Legislature (including several African-Americans).  However, by the turn of the century, the Republican Party all but disappeared from Texas with the passage of [[Poll tax|poll taxes]] that many poor Texans could not afford to pay. The first Republican statewide primary was held in 1926, but drew only 15,239 voters.  By contrast, the Democrat primary in the same year drew 821,234 voters. Only two more Republican primaries would be attempted in the next thirty-four years.&lt;ref name=&quot;history&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.texasgop.org/inner.asp?z=3|title=History of the Republican Party of Texas|publisher=texasgop.org|accessdate=April 26, 2011|archiveurl = http://web.archive.org/web/20110422201308/http://www.texasgop.org/inner.asp?z=3 |archivedate = April 22, 2011|deadurl=yes}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The first signs of life in the modern Republican Party of Texas occurred after U.S. Senator [[Lyndon B. Johnson]] was elected Vice-President in 1960, when Texas Republicans claimed their first U.S. Senate victory with the election of [[John Tower]] in a special election held in May 1961.  Tower would serve in this position until his retirement in 1985.  In 1966, two Republicans were elected to the [[US House of Representatives]], including future President [[George H.W. Bush]] for the first time since Reconstruction, three Republicans were elected to the [[Texas House of Representatives]] and one Republican was elected to the [[Texas Senate]].  By 1972, Texas Republicans had made gains to 17 members of the Texas Legislature and 3 members of the Texas Senate.&lt;ref name=history/&gt;

The true turning point for Texas Republicans occurred in the May 1976 primary, when [[Ronald Reagan]] defeated [[Gerald Ford]] by a two to one margin in the state's presidential primary.  According to former Secretary of State [[James A. Baker III]], due to Reagan's victory in the Texas primary, &quot;''the whole shape and nature of the state changed.''&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://blogs.chron.com/txpotomac/2011/02/ronald_reagan_how_he_changed_t_1.html|title=Ronald Reagan: How he changed Texas Politics Forever|publisher=chron.com|accessdate=February 6, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

104 years after the last Republican governor, [[William Clements|Bill Clements]] eked out a narrow victory in November 1978.  Together, Clements and Tower combined their organizational skills to continue building the RPT and started laying the groundwork for future growth. In 1984, Reagan, George H.W. Bush, and [[Phil Gramm]] led a GOP ticket that heavily relied upon the RPT to provide a centralized network of communications. Throughout the rest of the decade, the total Republican vote continued to increase and the party made large gains in both the state legislature and in local races.&lt;ref name=history/&gt;

Since 1994, every statewide elected office has been held by a Republican.  Furthermore, both houses of the [[Texas Legislature]] feature Republican majorities. In the State House, Republicans hold a supermajority of 101 Republican representatives in the 150-member body,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.kwtx.com/centraltexasvotes/localheadlines/And_Longtime_Democrat_Aaron_Pena_Makes_It_101_111881504.html|title=And Longtime Democrat Aaron Pena Makes It 101|publisher=kwtx.com|accessdate=December 14, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; and in the [[Texas Senate]], Republicans hold 19 of 31 seats. Both houses are officially organized on a bipartisan basis, with both Republicans and Democrats holding committee chairs.

At the federal level, the Texas Congressional delegation is currently composed of 23 Republicans and 9 Democrats and both of its US Senators are Republican.  The last time Texas was carried by a Democratic presidential candidate was in [[United States presidential election, 1976|1976]].

==Current elected officials==
The Republican Party of Texas controls all elected statewide offices, holds a 19-12 majority in the [[Texas Senate]], and a 101-49 supermajority in the [[Texas House of Representatives]]. Republicans also hold both of the state's U.S. Senate seats and 23 of the state's 32 U.S. House seats.

===Members of Congress===
====[[U.S. Senate]]====
* [[John Cornyn]]
* [[Kay Bailey Hutchison]]
====[[U.S. House of Representatives]] (listed by district number)====
* [[TX-01]]: [[Louie Gohmert]]
* [[TX-02]]: [[Ted Poe]]
* [[TX-03]]: [[Sam Johnson]]
* [[TX-04]]: [[Ralph Hall]]
* [[TX-05]]: [[Jeb Hensarling]]
* [[TX-06]]: [[Joe Barton]]
* [[TX-07]]: [[John Culberson]]
* [[TX-08]]: [[Kevin Brady]]
* [[TX-10]]: [[Michael McCaul]]
* [[TX-11]]: [[Mike Conaway]]
* [[TX-12]]: [[Kay Granger]]
* [[TX-13]]: [[Mac Thornberry]]
* [[TX-14]]: [[Ron Paul]]
* [[TX-17]]: [[Bill Flores]]
* [[TX-19]]: [[Randy Neugebauer]]
* [[TX-21]]: [[Lamar S. Smith]]
* [[TX-22]]: [[Pete Olson]]
* [[TX-23]]: [[Quico Canseco]]
* [[TX-24]]: [[Kenny Marchant]]
* [[TX-26]]: [[Michael C. Burgess]]
* [[TX-27]]: [[Blake Farenthold]]
* [[TX-31]]: [[John Carter (Texas)|John Carter]]
* [[TX-32]]: [[Pete Sessions]]

===Statewide officials===
* [[List of Governors of Texas|Governor]]: [[Rick Perry]]
* [[Lieutenant Governor of Texas|Lieutenant Governor]]: [[David Dewhurst]]
* [[Texas Attorney General|Attorney General]]: [[Greg Abbott]]
* [[Texas Comptroller of Public Accounts|Comptroller of Public Accounts]]: [[Susan Combs]]
* [[Commissioner of the General Land Office|State Land Commissioner]]: [[Jerry E. Patterson|Jerry Patterson]]
* [[Texas Department of Agriculture|State Agriculture Commissioner]]: [[Todd Staples]]
* [[Texas Railroad Chairmen|Railroad Chairmen]]: [[Elizabeth Ames Jones]]
* [[Texas Railroad Commission|Railroad Commissioner]]: [[David J. Porter|David Porter]]
* [[Texas Railroad Commission|Railroad Commissioner]]: [[Barry Smitherman]]

===[[Texas Legislature|Legislative]]===
* [[Lieutenant Governor of Texas|President of the Senate/Lt. Governor]]: [[David Dewhurst]]
* [[Speaker of the Texas House of Representatives|Speaker of the House]]: [[Joe Straus]]

==List of State Party Chairmen==

;State Party Chairmen since 1976
* [[Ray Hutchison]] - (1976-1977)
* [[Ray Barnhart]] - (1977-1979)
* [[Chet Upham]] - (1979-1983)
* [[George Strake, Jr.]] - (1983-1988)
* [[Fred Meyer (Texas politician)]] - (1988-1994)
* [[Tom Pauken]] - (1994-1997)
* Susan Weddington - (1997-2003)
* [[Tina Benkiser]] - (2003-2009)
* [[Cathie Adams]] - (2009-2010)
* [[Steve Munisteri]] - (2010-present)

==Auxiliary organizations==

The official college Republican Party of Texas' student wing is [[Texas College Republicans]], which has over 35 chapters statewide.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.txcollegerepublicans.com/|title=Texas College Republicans - The Official Home of the Texas College Republicans|publisher=txcollegerepublicans.com|accessdate=April 26, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The Texas Federation of Republican Women (TFRW) is a volunteer women's organization that has &quot;''long-standing goals of education, training, participation in government, electing Republicans and encouraging Republican women to run for office''&quot;. TFRW has 164 local clubs across Texas with over 10,000 members. &lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.tfrw.org/|title=TFRW Home Page|publisher=tfrw.org|accessdate=April 26, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The Texas Republican County Chairmen's Association (TRCCA) is composed of the elected chairman of the county Republican party organizations in Texas and operates to support and provide networking opportunities for elected Republican county chairmen in Texas.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.trcca.org/|title=Texas Republican County Chairmans Association|publisher=trcca.org|accessdate=April 26, 2011|archiveurl = http://web.archive.org/web/20100818030247/http://www.trcca.org/ |archivedate = August 18, 2010|deadurl=yes}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The [http://www.texasyoungrepublicans.com Texas Young Republican Federation] (TYRF) is an organization composed of [[Young Republican]] clubs across Texas which are open to registered voters who are between the ages of 18 and 40 years old. The TYRF goals are grassroots activism, leadership development, community service and club development.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://texasyoungrepublicans.com/|title=Texas Young Republican Federation|publisher=texasyoungrepublicans.com|accessdate=April 26, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The Texas Federation for Republican Outreach is committed to increasing participation and affiliation of African-American voters within the Republican Party, and to increase the number of elected Republican African-American candidates in Texas.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.txfro.org/inner.asp?z=9|title=About Us - Texas Federation for Republican Outreach|publisher=txfro.org|accessdate=April 26, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The Texas Republican Assembly is a grassroots volunteer organization dedicated to promoting and electing conservative Republican candidates in Texas.  There are six charter clubs across Texas.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.texasra.org/chapters|title=Texas Republican Assembly - The Republican Wing of the Republican Party|publisher=texasra.org|accessdate=April 26, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The Republican National Hispanic Assembly has a chapter in Texas, whose mission is to increase participation and affiliation of Hispanic American voters within the Republican Party, and to increase the number of elected Republican Hispanic candidates in Texas.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.rnha.org/|title=About Us - The Republican National Hispanic Assembly|publisher=rnha.org|accessdate=April 26, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The Latino National Republican Coalition of Texas believes &quot;in active civic engagement as a means to bridge the gap between the Hispanic Community and the GOP.&quot;  There are five chapters throughout Texas.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.lnrctexas.org/chapters.html|title=Welcome to the Latino National Republican Coalition of Texas|publisher=lnrctexas.org|accessdate=April 26, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==References==
{{Reflist}}

==External links==
* [http://www.texasgop.org/ The Republican Party of Texas website]
* [http://www.texasgop.org/site/PageServer?pagename=leadership_countyweb/ County Party Web Site Directory]
* [http://www.texashousecaucus.com/ Texas House Republican Caucus]

{{Republican Party (United States)}}
{{TexasPoliticalParties}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Republican Party Of Texas}}
[[Category:Political parties in Texas]]
[[Category:Republican Party (United States) by state|Texas]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
