<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="113700" ns="0" title="Tintin and Alph-Art"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{refimprove|date=September 2011}}
{{Graphicnovelbox|  &lt;!--Wikipedia:WikiProject Comics--&gt;
englishtitle=Tintin and Alph-Art
|foreigntitle=Tintin et l'alph-art
|image=Tintin Cover - Tintin and Alph-Art.jpg
|caption=Cover of the English edition
|publisher=[[Casterman]]
|date=1986
|series=''[[The Adventures of Tintin|The Adventures of Tintin (Les aventures de Tintin)]]''
|origlanguage=French
|origpublication=
|origdate=
|origisbn=|&lt;!-- 2-203-00118-6 --&gt;
|transtitle=Tintin and Alph-Art
|transpublisher=Sundancer
|transdate=1990
|transseriestitle=''[[The Adventures of Tintin]]''
|transisbn=|&lt;!-- 0-316-35848-7 --&gt;
|translator=Leslie Lonsdale-Cooper and Michael Turner
|writers=[[Hergé]]
|artists=[[Hergé]]
|colorists=
|previssue=''[[Tintin and the Picaros]]'', 1976
}}

'''''Tintin and Alph-Art''''' ({{lang-fr|'''Tintin et l'alph-art'''}}) was the intended twenty-fourth and final book in the ''[[The Adventures of Tintin|Tintin]]'' series, created by [[Belgium|Belgian]] comics artist [[Hergé]]. It is a striking departure from the earlier books in tone and subject, as well as in some parts of the style; rather than being set in a usual exotic and action-packed environment this story is largely played out in the world of modern art.

Hergé worked on the book until his death in 1983, and it was published posthumously (despite its unfinished status) in 1986 by [[Casterman]] in association with La Fondation Hergé, and was republished in 2004 with further material. It was released again in late 2010 with the original sketch pad as well as newly found notes and scripts recently discovered in a [[France|French]] Bank archive.

==History==
In 1976, a few months after the publication of ''[[Tintin and the Picaros]]'', Hergé told the journalist and author [[Numa Sadoul]] that he was contemplating the next adventure of Tintin&amp;nbsp;— setting an entire story in an airport departure lounge.&lt;ref name=&quot;HergéSadoul1989&quot;&gt;{{cite book
|last=Sadoul
|first=Numa
|authorlink=Hergé
|title=Entretiens avec Hergé
|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=O4knAQAAIAAJ
|accessdate=10 October 2010
|year=1989
|publisher=Casterman
|language=French
|isbn=9782203017085}}&lt;/ref&gt; This idea was eventually dropped, and in 1978, he decided to set the story in the world of [[modern art]]. During later years Hergé had grown more and more interested in modern art, even attempting it a few times himself as a hobby; so he chose to incorporate his love of [[avant-garde]] artwork into the new story. Hergé was inspired by the [[Ferdinand Legros]] and [[Elmyr de Hory]] affair, and incorporated a second element, a [[new age]] sect and a phoney [[guru]]. He planned to cast [[Rastapopoulos]] as the villain, but according to Harry Thompson, dropped the idea in 1980 when he introduced the alphabet art element. Still, an idea exists that the villain Ramó Nash or his accomplice Enddane Akass may be Rastapopoulous in yet another of his disguises.

==Storyline==
The story opens with [[Captain Haddock]] having a nightmare of being visited by [[Bianca Castafiore]], who demands that he take his medicine (actually a bottle of [[Loch Lomond]] whisky). When he refuses, as he still cannot stand the beverage after the events of [[Tintin and the Picaros|the previous book]], Castafiore turns into a huge bird-like creature and begins to attack Haddock. Fortunately, [[Tintin (character)|Tintin]] manages to wake him up, whereupon Tintin receives a telephone call from the real Castafiore, who tells him that she has arrived in [[Belgium]] for a few days. She continues her conversation with Tintin, telling him about her new spiritual leader, [[Endaddine Akass]], with whom she intends to stay at his villa in [[Ischia]], an island off the coast of [[Naples]].

Later that morning, Captain Haddock comes across Castafiore in a [[Brussels]] street, and in order to avoid her, dashes into the nearby Fourcart Gallery, where he meets [[Jamaican]] [[avant-garde]] artist Ramó Nash (the master of &quot;Alph-Art&quot;) and the owner of the gallery, Henri Fourcart. Fourcart displays considerable interest in meeting Tintin. At the gallery, Haddock is pressed into purchasing a perspex letter &quot;H&quot; (&quot;Personalph-Art&quot;) created by Nash. That evening, when Haddock returns to [[Marlinspike Hall|Marlinspike]], he and Tintin watch a news report featuring their old friend [[Ben Kalish Ezab and Abdullah|Emir Ben Kalish Ezab]], who, flushed with [[petroleum|oil]] profits, plans to buy [[Windsor Castle]] from the [[Her Majesty's Government|Government of the United Kingdom]] and the [[Centre Pompidou]] in [[Paris]]. The same news program then features a report on the suspicious death of art expert Jacques Monastir, who is presumed drowned off the coast of [[Ajaccio]], [[Corsica]].

[[Image:Tintin and Alph-Art - final panel.png|float|right|thumb|The last panel in the book and in the series]]
The next morning, Tintin learns that Fourcart was killed in a car accident, apparently ''en route'' to visit him. He visits the gallery to &quot;make a few enquiries&quot; and meets Martine Vandezande, the gallery assistant, who wears large glasses and a strange pendant resembling two E's lined back to back. She discusses the death of her former employer, while her conversation with Tintin is recorded by a reel-to-reel tape recorder hidden under the counter. Tintin then visits the Garage de l'Avenir at Leignault, where the mechanic tells him the location of Fourcart's car crash. Tintin drives there on his motor scooter and is pursued by a black Mercedes. At the scene, Tintin discovers that Fourcart was murdered. The drivers of the black Mercedes then make a botched attempt on Tintin's life. He returns to Marlinspike and tells the Captain about the events of the day.

The next morning, Tintin returns to the gallery and accuses Miss. Martine of telling his attackers he was going to visit Leignault. However, she bursts into tears, suggesting to a shocked Tintin that she may be innocent. On his way home, Tintin sees a poster in the street advertising a conference&amp;nbsp;— &quot;Health and Magnetism&quot;&amp;nbsp;— to be held by the mystic Endaddine Akass, who is shown on the poster wearing a pendant similar to Miss Martine's. That evening, Tintin and Haddock attend the meeting, where they see not only Miss Martine (a follower of Akass's movement) but also [[Thomson and Thompson|the Thompson twins]] and Mr. Sakharine (from ''[[The Secret of the Unicorn]]'') in attendance. During the ceremony, Tintin recognises the voice of Akass, but cannot place it. He and Haddock encounter Miss Martine as she leaves the conference. Tintin asks her about the pendant that she wears, which was given to her and &quot;magnetized&quot; by Akass. Believing that he is beginning to understand the affair, Tintin informs Miss Martine the next morning of his plan to unmask Fourcart's murderers. Late that evening, he arrives, carrying a red lamp, at the old Fréaux factory, where he had arranged to meet an informer. Tintin lights his lamp, and the &quot;informer&quot; shoots at him. He avoids injury and attempts to arrest the informer, who is saved when an accomplice knocks Tintin unconscious. He awakes in hospital with Haddock at his bedside, to whom he explains his revelation that there is a micro-transmitter concealed in the pendant worn by Miss Vandezande. Tintin infers that Endaddine Akass gave the unwitting Miss Martine the pendant in order to spy upon Fourcart and senses that he is inextricably linked to his death.

The next morning (despite doctor's orders), Tintin visits each of the other occupants in the apartments that house the Fourcart Gallery. He visits the occupants under the pretence of conducting a survey on [[solar power]], and recognises a particularly rude resident as Akass's assistant at the meeting. Knowing that he has been recognized, Akass's assistant sends Tintin away and telephones someone, and then agrees to &quot;take care of&quot; Tintin. The next morning, Tintin leaves [[Marlinspike Hall|the Hall]] for the village on his motor scooter, and is pursued by the same men who had attacked him in the Mercedes. They shoot at Tintin, whose scooter careens off-road and crashes into a tree. Before the would-be assassins can confirm if Tintin was killed, Haddock, having heard the gunfire, arrives in his car, causing them to flee. Once they are gone, Tintin climbs down from his hiding place inside a pollarded willow. Tintin, Haddock and Calculus later assess the situation around the table. Tintin concludes that the entire affair revolves around Endaddine Akass, and that they should find out more about him. Remembering Castafiore's telephone call several days earlier, he decides to go to [[Ischia]], where Akass has a villa.

Upon their arrival, Tintin and Haddock spy out the land, observing Akass's villa from a distance, where they see Ramó Nash (the pioneer of &quot;Alph-Art&quot; from whom Haddock bought his perspex &quot;H&quot;). At their hotel, Tintin receives a threatening telephone call warning him to leave the island, and Haddock receives one from Castafiore, who has discovered their presence on the island, and, informing them that Akass is in [[Rome]] for a few days, invites them to the villa. The next morning, they arrive at the villa, where Castafiore introduces them to a number of her friends&amp;nbsp;— the debutante Angelina Sordi, the corrupt industrialists Mr Gibbons (from ''[[The Blue Lotus]]'') and Mr Trickler (from ''[[The Broken Ear]]''), Emir Ben Kalish Ezab (from ''[[Land of Black Gold]]''), Luigi Randazzo (a singer), and Ramó Nash. Tintin and Haddock stay the night at the villa on Castafiore's insistence.

Tintin is awakened by a noise in the middle of the night, and looking out of the window, sees men loading canvases into a van. Intrigued, he explores the villa. In a huge room he comes across a number of paintings by the great masters&amp;nbsp;— [[Amedeo Modigliani|Modigliani]], [[Fernand Léger|Léger]], [[Pierre-Auguste Renoir|Renoir]], [[Pablo Picasso|Picasso]], [[Gauguin]] and [[Monet]]&amp;nbsp;— and discovers them all to be fakes. He is discovered by Endaddine Akass, of whom it is revealed that he uses Ramó Nash's &quot;Alph-Art&quot; as a front for large-scale art forgeries. He admits to ordering the &quot;disappearance&quot; of Monastir and Fourcart, who were aware of his activities (and in Fourcart's case, wanted to expose them to Tintin), and states that as Tintin knows too much, he will have to die, too. Akass tells Tintin that in order to kill him, he will have liquid [[polyester]] poured over him, so that he may be turned into a statue, be &quot;signed&quot; by [[César Baldaccini|César]], and authenticated by a (presumably corrupt) art expert. The &quot;expansion&quot; piece, entitled &quot;Reporter&quot;, will then be sold to a museum or a rich collector. Tintin is led away by one of Akass's men to a cell, where he is locked up. He manages to make contact with [[Snowy (character)|Snowy]], who is outside the cell. He writes a note to the Captain and throws it to Snowy through the bars on the window. Night passes, and in the morning, Tintin is awakened by Akass's bodyguard. As the guard leads Tintin out of the cell, he says,
{{Cquote|''&quot;Get moving! It's time for you to be turned into a 'César'...&quot;''}}

It is at this point that ''The Adventures of Tintin'' ends, and what is going to happen next, or who Akass really is, is unknown. The text as a whole is essentially a rough draft, and contains enough room for revision.

==Re-discovered pages==
In the 2004 edition of the book, nine additional pages are included, which present alternative ideas for the story. The most significant include the following:

* A change of lifestyle for Captain Haddock&amp;nbsp;— becoming infatuated with a minimalist painter named Ramó Nash, changing his style of dress, transforming the house, and growing [[hashish]] in the cellars at Marlinspike. Haddock and Tintin are accused of drug smuggling, and an investigation takes place in Amsterdam.
* Painting and narcotics; at the Sondenesian embassy (see ''[[Flight 714]]'') a grand soirée is held, which is attended by ambassadors for Saboulistan, [[San Theodoros]], [[Borduria]], and [[Syldavia]]. [[Minor characters in The Adventures of Tintin#Doctor Krollspell|Dr. Krollspell]] (also from ''Flight 714'') makes a reappearance, as director of a brown-sugar factory.
* Captain Haddock suffers from [[neurasthenia]] because he can no longer drink whiskey. He takes up painting, and becomes infatuated with the painter Ramó Nash. Calculus invents a product that will allow Haddock to drink whisky again; during trials, Haddock loses all his hair and blotches appear on his face.
* Endaddine Akass is revealed as Rastapopoulos. This is '''''not''''' confirmed in the actual book, so there is much speculation as to whether Hergé would have used this idea.
* Background information is given of Akass&amp;nbsp;— the readers learn that he is involved with Emir Ben Kalish Ezab, an idea not pursued fully in the story.
* An alternative page featuring Rastapopoulos&amp;nbsp;— this would have taken the place of pages 39–40.
* Haddock is invited to an exhibition by the painter Ramó Nash. A number of old acquaintances attend, such as Dawson (''[[The Blue Lotus]]''), the Bird brothers (''[[The Secret of the Unicorn]]''), and Carreidas (''[[Flight 714]]'').

==Influences==
* Endaddine Akass was based on the real-life character of [[Ferdinand Legros]].
* Ramó Nash was based on the real-life [[Elmyr de Hory]].
* Martine Vandezande's appearance seems to be have been based on the Greek singer [[Nana Mouskouri]]. Her surname may have been taken from the name of a publishing house, l'imprimeur Vandezande, which published a Tintin calendar in 1946.

==Hergé's legacy==
Upon his death, Hergé left around one hundred and fifty pages of pencil sketches for the story. These were edited by a team of experts, including [[Benoît Peeters]], Michel Bareau and Jean-Manuel Duvivier, resulting in forty-two pages of sketches. The album, therefore, only presents the scenarios and sketches of an interrupted tale. However even in its rough state, it is testimony to the extraordinary [[narrative]] and graphic talent of Hergé. The story can appear a little disjointed and convoluted at times, although one must remember that Hergé would have recast and edited the story countless times before it was finished.{{Citation needed|date=August 2011}}{{Who|date=August 2011}}

It is possible that the scenes set at Marlinspike would have been reduced in favour of balance of the story&amp;nbsp;— in the original manuscript, Tintin, Snowy and Haddock do not leave for Ischia until page 31. Furthermore, the scene involving Tintin and Mrs Laijot was marked for possible cutting (20''bis'' on the original manuscript, meaning an additional page 20).

[[Bob de Moor]], Hergé's main assistant, showed an interest in completing the book following Hergé's death. It was not such a surprising request; de Moor had worked with Hergé since 1951, was responsible for running the [[Studios Hergé]] in his absence, adapted the animated film ''[[Tintin and the Lake of Sharks]]'' into comic-strip form, and worked on the previous book ''[[Tintin and the Picaros]]'' with Hergé alone. In de Moor's words, &quot;Personally I would have loved to finish ''Alph-Art''. It would have been a tribute to Hergé. Fanny Remi asked me to finish it, and I began work on it, but after a few months she changed her mind. I didn't insist, but for me it was logical that there was a studio, there were artists in the studio, Casterman asked for it to be finished, there were twenty-three finished books, that one story was not finished; so I had to finish it&quot;.

==Publication history==
[[Image:Alphart01.gif|thumb|right|Cover of the first edition]]
The book was first published in English in 1990 by Sundancer. Unusually&amp;nbsp;— but understandably given the nature of the unfinished artwork with Hergé's original hand-written text&amp;nbsp;— the translations do not replace the original text. They are presented separately in a supplementary booklet included with the book.

The 2004 edition, published by Egmont, uses an entirely new layout, mixing Hergé's pages with the text and enlarged frames to highlight parts of the story. It is in the same format as the standard albums&amp;nbsp;— a hardback book, sixty-two pages in length, and is readily available in the UK.
The same edition was published in 2007 by Little, Brown/Hachette in the USA.

==Pirate editions==
[[File:Th alphart.png|thumb|right|100px|Cover of Yves Rodier's version of the book.]]
A number of [[List of Tintin parodies and pastiches|pirated versions]] of the story exist, finished by other artists. The first was produced by an artist under the name of Ramó Nash. The second, and more renowned, is by Canadian artist [[Yves Rodier]]. Originally drawn and printed (privately) in black-and-white in the early 1990s, a color version was produced in 2004 by Finnish-based group Studio Juhis.  The Rodier edition has been translated into English by various people, the edition by Rackham being the most successful and with a different cover.

==Publication details==
===French===
# Hergé, ''Tintin et l'Alph-Art'' (Casterman, 84pp, 1986) - ISBN 2-203-01701-5
# Hergé, ''Tintin et l'Alph-Art'' (Casterman, 62pp, 2004) - ISBN 2-203-00132-1

===English===
# Hergé, ''Tintin and Alph-Art'' (Sundancer, 94 pp., 1990)—ISBN 0-9512799-2-0
# Hergé, ''Tintin and Alph-Art'' (Egmont, 64 pp., 2004)—ISBN 1-4052-1448-1
# Hergé, ''Tintin and Alph-Art'' (Little, Brown/Hachette, 64 pp., 2007)—ISBN 9780316003759
'''Note:''' the first English-language edition of the book, published by Sundancer, is now out of print.

==Trivia==
* In honor of Hergé's legacy, the awards handed out at the [[Angoulême International Comics Festival|Angoulême Festival]] were given the name Alph-Art between 1989 and 2003.
* The French title actually translates to &quot;Tintin and the Alpha-Art&quot;, but for some reasons that name wasn't used in the English editions of the book.

==References==
===Notes===
{{Reflist}}

===Further reading===
* [[Jean-Marc Lofficier|Lofficier]], Jean-Marc &amp; Randy (2002) ''The Pocket Essential Tintin'' - ISBN 1-904048-17-X
* Thompson, Harry (1991) ''Tintin - Hergé &amp; His Creation'' - ISBN 0-340-52393-X
* Goddin, Philippe (2004) ''Hergé, Chronologie d'une œuvre'' (Tome 5) - ISBN 2-87424-052-4

==External links==
{{Portal box|Belgium|Comics}}
*[http://www.tintinologist.org/guides/books/24alphart.html Tintin and Alph-Art] at Tintinologist.org

{{Tintin and Hergé}}
{{Use dmy dates|date=August 2011}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Tintin And Alph-Art}}
[[Category:1986 books]]
[[Category:Tintin books|Alph-Art]]
[[Category:Unfinished books]]
[[Category:Books published posthumously]]

[[bn:টিনটিন অ্যান্ড অ্যাল্‌ফ-আর্ট]]
[[ca:Tintín i l'Art-Alfa]]
[[da:Tintin og alfa-kunsten]]
[[es:Tintín y el Arte-Alfa]]
[[fa:تن‌تن و هنر الفبا]]
[[fr:Tintin et l'Alph-Art]]
[[gl:Tintín e a Arte-Alfa]]
[[id:Tintin dan Alpha-Art]]
[[nl:Kuifje en de Alfa-kunst]]
[[pt:Tintin et l'Alph-Art]]
[[fi:Tintti ja aakkostaide]]
[[sv:Tintin och alfabetskonsten]]
[[zh:丁丁與字母藝術]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
