<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="11471600" ns="0" title="List of 24 (TV series) media"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">The critical and popular success of the Fox television series ''[[24 (TV series)|24]]'' has led to the series being extended into other arenas, primarily '''media''' specifically created for mobile devices and the internet.  In addition, the series has spawned video and board games, toys, soundtracks from both the series and the video game, and a number of original novels inspired by the series.  A feature film based upon the series is scheduled for sometime in the future.

== Mobile media ==
===''24: Conspiracy''===
{{main|24: Conspiracy}}
''24: Conspiracy'' is a low budget, cellphone-only [[Spin-off (media)|spin-off]] of ''24'' set in Washington, D.C. It spans 24 one-minute episodes and takes place during Day 4, as indicated by a reference to the Heller kidnapping happening that day. It does not take place in real time. All of the episodes were released together as a special for the season 4 DVD boxset.

==Online media ==
=== ''The Rookie'' ===

{{main|The Rookie (Web series)}}

'''The Rookie''', formerly named '''The Rookie CTU''', is a series of online webisodes set at CTU in Los Angeles. It is made by many of the same crew members that make the ''24'' TV show. ''The Rookie'' utilizes the same CTU set as the series, and uses many of the same production elements, such as graphics, editing techniques, and music, giving it an &quot;authentic&quot; look and feel. One exception, however, is that it does not take place in real time. [[Unilever]]'s Degree Men antiperspirant is a sponsor of &quot;The Rookie&quot; series.

The stories revolve around rookie CTU agent, Jason Blaine (played by [[Jeremy Ray Valdez]]), with appearances by Video Surveillance Manager Angie Lawson and CTU Deputy Director Alton Maxwell. In the first season, &quot;Coffee Run&quot;, consisting of three parts, Blaine witnesses a bank robbery in progress during his coffee run. Without a gun, Blaine enters the bank in an attempt to stop the robbery. The second season, &quot;Mistaken Identity&quot;, finds Blaine hand-delivering a Blackberry to his boss in his boss' car. He receives a call from Russian terrorists who believe Blaine is his boss. A third season, &quot;Extraction&quot;, contains six parts and focuses on Blaine having to rescue Alton Maxwell from a drug smuggler named Esteban Salazar.

=== ''24: Day Zero'' ===

''24: Day Zero'' is a series of online animated webisodes set at CTU in Los Angeles. It is a prequel series, focusing on Jack Bauer's first 18 months at CTU. The series debuted on May 21, 2007, following the airing of the Season 6 finale.  As with &quot;The Rookie&quot;, Degree Men is a sponsor of the &quot;Day Zero&quot; series. Since the release of The Rookie: Day 3: Extraction, the Day Zero website has been taken offline; however, the series is available on [http://ca.youtube.com/watch?v=L4sIJTdcQk4 YouTube].

=== ''24: Day 6 Debrief'' ===
''24: Day 6 Debrief'' is a series of two-minute online webisodes starring Kiefer Sutherland and is set 35 hours after the events of Season 6. Available exclusively to [[American Express]] cardholders, the series explains what happened to Jack Bauer in China and set up the events of Season 7. It is in the Season 6 DVD's special features.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.movieweb.com/dvd/news/46/22346.php 24: Season Six on DVD December 4th]&lt;/ref&gt; Like ''24:  Day Zero'', this series also debuted on May 21, 2007 after the airing of the Season 6 finale. American Express is a sponsor of this series and hosted the webisodes on a special page of the Fox website. The series is also available on [http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=_2TYNiFPV_0 YouTube].

== Soundtracks ==
{{main|24: The Soundtrack}}
Various soundtracks have been created for the show, and its properties. The most notable is ''24: The Soundtrack'' which contains nineteen tracks of music composed exclusively for the first three seasons by ''24'''s multi-Emmy award winning composer Sean Callery, including the show's full [[theme song]] which, prior to the soundtrack's release, had never been aired. A second soundtrack was released 13 November in the UK and 14 November in the US with music from seasons 4 and 5.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.play.com/Music/CD/4-/3250904/24_Seasons_4_5/Product.html Play.com (UK) : Sean Callery (Soundtrack) - 24 (Twenty Four) Seasons 4 &amp; 5 : CD - Free Delivery&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt; The soundtrack to ''[[24: Redemption]]'' was released on November 24, 2008 as part of the bridge between seasons 6 and 7.

== Books ==
''24: The House Special Subcommittee's Findings at CTU'' written by [[Marc Cerasini]], was a guide to the first season, as written by an in-universe journalist by the same name. The book contained Jack Bauer's [[grand jury]] testimony as well as character profiles and autopsy reports.

Titan Books published ''24: The Official Companion Seasons 1 &amp; 2'' in 2006 in the US and UK. The second volume, ''24: The Official Companion Seasons 3 &amp; 4'', was released in the UK in February 2007, and released in the US in May 2007. ''24: The Official Companion Season 5'' was released in November 2007. ''24: The Official Companion Guide Season 6'' was released with a bonus DVD in January 2008. All the guides are written by Tara DiLullo Bennett. 

In 2003, an unofficial guide to season 1 of ''24'' was released, written by Jim Sangster.  Later that year, Mark Wright published an unofficial guide to season 2 of ''24'', and Keith Topping published ''A Day in the Life: The Unofficial and Unauthorised Guide to 24''.

Paperback novels have also been published by ''Harper Entertainment'' under the title ''24: Declassified''. They are:
* ''[[Operation Hell Gate]]'', written by Marc Cerasini, released September 27, 2005 (ISBN 978-0-06-084224-6)
* ''Veto Power'', by [[John Whitman]], released on October 25, 2005 (ISBN 978-0-06-084225-3)
* ''Trojan Horse'', by Marc Cerasini, released on January 31, 2006 (ISBN 978-0-06-084226-0)
* ''Cat's Claw'', by John Whitman, released on December 26, 2006 (ISBN 978-0-06-084227-7)
* ''Vanishing Point'', by Marc Cerasini, released on February 27, 2007 (ISBN 978-0-06-084228-8)
* ''Chaos Theory'', by John Whitman, released on May 29, 2007 (ISBN 978-0-06-084229-1)
* ''Storm Force'', by David Jacobs, released on December 26, 2007 (ISBN 978-0-06-137884-3)
* ''Collateral Damage'', by Marc Cerasini, released on February 26, 2008 (ISBN 978-0-06-143118-0)
* ''Trinity'', by John Whitman, released on April 29, 2008 (ISBN 978-0-06-143119-7)
* ''Head Shot'', by David Jacobs, released on April 28, 2009 (ISBN 978-0-06177152-1)
* ''Death Angel'', by David Jacobs, released on April 27, 2010 (ISBN 978-0-06-177153-8)
These titles are also available as [[Amazon Kindle]] editions.

Other titles include:
* ''24: The Ultimate Guide'', written by Michael Goldman featuring information about the first six seasons.
* ''24: Behind the Scenes'', featuring behind the scenes photographs and pictures.
* ''24: The Counter Terrorist Unit Handbook'', featuring a manual of how CTU works and their policies and procedures. It includes pictures from the first six seasons.
* ''24 and Philosophy: The World According to Jack'', published as part of The Blackwell Philosophy and Pop Culture Series.
* ''The Tao of Jack Bauer: What Our Favorite Terrorist Buster Says About Life, Love, Torture, and Saving the World 24 Times in 24 Hours With No Lunch Break'', a study of Jack Bauer's influence in society.
* ''Secrets of 24: The Unauthorized Guide to the Political &amp; Moral Issues Behind TV's Most Riveting Drama'', which collects interviews and essays to pursue real issues of relevance to our times.
* ''Jack Bauer for President: Terrorism and Politics in 24'', another collection of essays.
* ''Reading 24: TV against the Clock'', a scholarly work of critical discussions of the series from many different perspectives.
* ''Jack Bauer's Having a Bad Day: An Unauthorized Investigation of Faith in 24: Season 1'', which uses each episode to help illustrate a spiritual concept.

== Magazine ==
&quot;24: The Official Magazine&quot; was a bi-monthly [[Titan Magazines]] publication that lasted for twelve issues, ceasing publication before the series ended.&lt;ref&gt;[http://24.wikia.com/wiki/24:_The_Official_Magazine 24: The Official Magazine at the 24 Wiki]&lt;/ref&gt;

== Comics ==
Five [[graphic novel]]s have been released by [[IDW Publishing]] taking place at different time periods within the show.  The first, ''[[24: One Shot]]'' (July 2004), attempted to emulate the real-time nature of the show.  It was followed by ''[[24 Stories]]'' (January 2005) and ''[[24: Midnight Sun]]'' (July 2005), which did not emulate the real-time nature of the show.  These three graphic novels have been compiled together in one book simply entitled ''24'', released by [[Titan Books]]. IDW also released a five-issue&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.amazon.com/24-Nightfall-Mark-L-Haynes/dp/1600100899 |title=24: Nightfall (9781600100895): Mark L. Haynes, J. C. Vaughn, Jean Diaz: Books |publisher=Amazon.com |date= |accessdate=2010-09-01}}&lt;/ref&gt; mini-series entitled ''[[24: Nightfall]]'' from November 2006 to March 2007, which was later collected as a trade paperback.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.idwpublishing.com/catalog/book/34|title=24: Nightfall|publisher=IDW Publishing|accessdate=7 March 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; A fifth graphic novel published by IDW entitled ''[[24: Cold Warriors]]'' was released on March 5, 2008.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | title=All-New 24 Comic Book Gives Fans Their Jack Bauer Fix | url=http://forum.newsarama.com/showthread.php?t=146896 | publisher=Newsarama.com | accessdate=2008-03-13}}&lt;/ref&gt;  This 48-page one-shot features Jack Bauer, Chloe O'Brian and others working to stop [[Russia]]n [[terrorists]] in [[Alaska]].

== Games ==
=== ''24: The Game'' ===
{{main|24: The Game}}
''24: The Game'' is a [[video game]] based on the TV series. The game is exclusive to [[Sony]]'s [[PlayStation 2]] console and was developed by [[Sony Computer Entertainment]]'s [[Cambridge]] Studios, and was published by [[2K Games]]. Taking place between seasons two and three, (6 months after Season 2) ''24: The Game'' features most major actors from those two seasons. This first foray into console gaming also serves to bridge the large gap between the second and third seasons.

=== ''24: DVD Board Game'' ===
There is a tabletop [[board game]] published by Pressman Toys, released in August 2006, based on the TV series. Rather than playing characters from the TV series, each player takes on the role of a CTU agent and the accompanying DVD is used to initiate the plot with a terrorist act, then passes threads to the players regarding the full plans of the terrorists, some of which may be useful and others that simply lead nowhere. The winner is the first person to identify and stop a terrorist threat. The DVD also acts as a timer to simulate the &quot;real time&quot; flow of the game. Reviews on websites such as amazon.com &lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.amazon.com/review/product/B000ETZU8E?coliid=&amp;showViewpoints=1&amp;colid=&amp;sortBy=bySubmissionDateDescending |title=Customer Reviews: 24 DVD Board Game |publisher=Amazon.com |date= |accessdate=2010-09-01}}&lt;/ref&gt; indicate that it is almost universally disliked.

=== ''24: Mobile'' ===
There was a ''24'' game for cell phones released in Feb. 2006 from [http://www.iplay.com/24 www.iplay.com]

=== ''24: Agent Down'' ===
There was a 2nd game for cell phones released in Nov. 2006 from [http://www.iplay.com/24 www.iplay.com]

=== ''24: Trading Card Game'' ===
{{Infobox Game |  subject_name= 24 Trading Card Game
|  image_link= 
|  image_caption=
|  designer= Jason Winter and Trevor McGregor
|  publisher= [[Press Pass, Inc.]]
|  players= 2
|  ages= 10+
|  setup_time= 
|  playing_time= approx 20 min.
|  complexity= 
|  strategy= 
|  random_chance= Some 
|  skills= [[Collectible card game|Card playing]]&lt;br&gt;[[Mathematics|Arithmetic]]&lt;br&gt;Basic Reading Ability
|  footnotes=
|  bggid=29821
}}
''24'': TCG is a customizable [[trading card game]] published by [[Press Pass Inc.]] in which 2 players each play a deck of 24 cards made from characters and events from the television show.  Players choose to build their deck as either containing CTU characters or Insurgent characters and play against an opponent, going on missions to attempt to score 24 points.  The game had a preview release in August 2007 and released its First Edition in September 2007.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.presspassinc.com/index.php?/gaming/ Gaming Cards&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Other board games ===
USAOpoly released a [[Cluedo#Variants|variant of the game Clue]] based on ''24''.  Briarpatch has released two ''24'' original board games, Countdown and CTU: Undercover.

==24 Toys==
[[Diamond Select Toys]] released 1/6 scale figures based on Jack Bauer.&lt;br&gt;
2008- Jack Bauer 8:00 AM&lt;br&gt;
2009- Jack Bauer 3:00 PM Season 1&lt;br&gt;
2009- Jack Bauer 9:00 PM Season 1

[[Diamond Select Toys]] released 1/24 scale Minimates based on 24.&lt;br&gt;
2007- Season 1 Box Set (Jack Bauer, Nina Myers, David Palmer, Kim Bauer)&lt;br&gt;
2007- End of Day 1 Two-Pack, PX Exclusive (Jack Bauer, Andre Drazen)&lt;br&gt;
2007- Season 2 Box Set (Season 2 Jack Bauer, Tony Almeda, Michelle Dessler, George Mason)&lt;br&gt;
2007- End of Day 2 Two-Pack, Suncoast/FYE Exclusive (Stretcher Jack Bauer, Prisoner Nina Myers)&lt;br&gt;
CANCELED- Season 3 Box Set (Undercover Jack Bauer, Sherry Palmer, Chloe O'Brien, Chase Edmunds)&lt;br&gt;
CANCELED- End of Day 3 Two-Pack (Jack Bauer, Stephen Saunders)

[[Enterbay]] released 1/6 scale figures based on 24.&lt;br&gt;
2009- Jack Bauer&lt;br&gt;
2009- President David Palmer

[[McFarlane Toys]] released 1/12 scale figures based on Jack Bauer.&lt;br&gt;
2007- Jack Bauer Boxed Set 1&lt;br&gt;
2007- Jack Bauer Boxed Set 2

[[Medicom Toy]] Japan released 1/6 scale figures based on Jack Bauer in their [[Real Action Heroes]] line.&lt;br&gt;
2005- Jack Bauer (Suit) Season 4 7:00 am – 8:00 am&lt;br&gt;
2005- Jack Bauer (Tac) Season 4 11:00 am – 12:00 pm&lt;br&gt;
2007- Jack Bauer Season 5

==Attraction==

On August 4, 2007, a ''24''-themed Interactive game attraction was opened in [[Tokyo, Japan]] in the famous indoor amusement park Tokyo [[Joypolis]].  The attraction is titled &quot;''24'' CTU: The Mission&quot;.  The game attraction features no ''24'' characters but focuses on the CTU aspect of the series.  Guests are agents-in-training at CTU: Tokyo division.  Agents are sent on a simulated mission to find a device which terrorists planted inside the Park, set to go off within 24 hours.  Guests collect clues from around the park, then use the clues to solve a number of problems; problems that need to be solved include determining the location of the device and the identity of the terrorist.  Guests who pass the mission test receive a special CTU agent sticker in return.

==Parodies==
''24''&lt;nowiki&gt;'&lt;/nowiki&gt;s enormous popularity also led the series' format to be parodied in more than one occasion, most prominently in ''[[The Simpsons]]'' season 18 episode &quot;[[24 Minutes]]&quot;, and in ''[[South Park]]'' season 11 episode &quot;[[The Snuke]]&quot;. Also, the series is referred to in the ''[[American Dad!]]'' season 1 episode &quot;[[Threat Levels]]&quot;: when the Smith house is quarantined after it is thought to be infected by a virus, Stan suggests to watch the entire first season of ''24''.  Fellow Fox-aired show ''[[House MD|House]]'' has been known to refer to ''24'' mockingly.

The clock and split-screen style in ''24'' has also been parodied in the anime ''[[Lucky Star (manga)|Lucky Star]]''; in episode 17, Sojiro (Konata's father), Yui, and Yutaka are making a birthday party for Konata, and subsequent scenes mimic this style. The clock/split-screen style was also in the 100th episode of ''[[Keroro Gunsō]]''.

[[CollegeHumor]] created a parody of ''24'' known as ''24: The Unaired 1994 Pilot''. In the short film, Jack Bauer dons a long scruffy hairdo and has to go back and forth to use a telephone booth (due to lack of wireless technology) to call CTU for objectives, as he tries to stop a bomb.

[[Late Night with Conan O'Brien]] had a ''24'' spoof segment called ''60'', where instead of 24's 1 hour episodes, episodes of 60 only lasted one second of a one minute season.  It would take numerous episodes to show a cell phone conversation, including one episode just showing the main character closing his phone.

The 2010 Albuquerque [[48 Hour Film Project]] featured a short parody of ''24'' called ''Jane Backer: Dental Billing Assistant'' -- complete with a female Jack Bauer who tortures an uncooperative dental patient.&lt;ref name=&quot;Jane Backer (film) online&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.bogwood.com/projects/jane-backer/|publisher=Bogwood Films|title=Jane Backer (film) online|month=August|year=2010|accessdate=2010-08-11}}&lt;/ref&gt;  The film won multiple awards.&lt;ref name=&quot;48 Hour Film Project Awards&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.48hourfilm.com/albuquerque/|publisher=48 Hour Film Project|title=48 Hour Film Project Awards|month=August|year=2010|accessdate=2010-08-11}}&lt;/ref&gt; 

In Season 3, Episode 3 of ''[[The Office (US TV series)|The Office]]'', the character of [[Dwight Schrute]] calls [[Jan Levenson]], [[Michael Scott (The Office)|Michael Scott]]'s superior at Corporate, and demands to speak with her in person saying, &quot;I can't talk here. It's too sensitive,&quot; implying that the phone is bugged, which parodies the covertness of ''24''. Dwight then tells her to &quot;pull over at Exit 40. There is a [[Liz Claiborne]] outlet. I know you like that store. Go inside and shop until I can meet you&quot; which makes fun of [[Jack Bauer]]'s surprising knowledge of where certain places are located, his expert ability to predict what certain people are going to do, and his keen skill of persuading people to follow his instructions without question.{{Or|date=July 2010}}

In another episode of ''The Office'', Schrute says when asked to pick his assistant, &quot;My ideal choice?  Jack Bauer.  But he is unavailable, fictional, and overqualified.&quot;

During an episode of [[My Name Is Earl]], Earl and Randy are strapped to a ticking bomb.  Not only do the ticks sound extremely similar to the ticking of the clock in 24, but the scene eventually becomes splitscreen, with each tick adding a subsequent image to the screen, exactly like 24.

The show is also parodied in ''[[Grand Theft Auto IV]]'' as ''72'', where the show's main character targets &quot;every person of color&quot; before they carry out terrorist attacks by staying up for three days straight.

On ''[[MADtv]]'', there are [[MADtv recurring characters|recurring sketches]] called &quot;''24'' with [[Bobby Lee]]&quot; featuring Lee and a guest on the show. Every sketch begins with Bobby sleeping in his underwear in a certain position.  The sketches incorporate the opening with the yellow digital &quot;24&quot; symbol appearing in front of a black background, the yellow text describing when the following scene takes place over the black background accompanied by a voice-over reciting the text, and the usage of the show's background music.

On the 2009 version of ''[[The Electric Company (2009 TV series)|The Electric Company]]'', there are recurring sketches called &quot;:24&quot; featuring a blue dog named &quot;Jack Bowser&quot; who speaks in the same deep voice as Jack Bauer.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|author= |url=http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=1ZyyFJPvFWY |title=THE ELECTRIC COMPANY: 24: Candy Corn |publisher=YouTube |date= |accessdate=2010-09-01}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|author= |url=http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=_aWRTfapvcI |title=THE ELECTRIC COMPANY: 24: Popcorn |publisher=YouTube |date= |accessdate=2010-09-01}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|author= |url=http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=C4rI5Wh4ooM |title=THE ELECTRIC COMPANY: 24: Sprinkles |publisher=YouTube |date= |accessdate=2010-09-02}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The Canadian television show ''[[Corner Gas]]'' season 5 episode &quot;Final Countdown&quot; parodies the clock in one instance. The episode also has a cameo appearance by [[Kiefer Sutherland]].

The split-screen effect from the show was once used in [[Simple Plan]]'s music video for &quot;[[Don't Wanna Think About You]]&quot;, featured on the ''[[Scooby-Doo 2: Monsters Unleashed]]'' soundtrack.

==Soft Drinks==
===''24'': Energy drink===
In late-2007, stores in the UK started selling an energy drink using the ''24'' insignia and branding.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.licensing.biz/news/27/Energy-boost-for-24-fans|title=Energy boost for 24 fans|last=Loveday|first=Samantha|date=24 September 2007|publisher=licensing.biz|accessdate=7 March 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; The drink is produced in regular and diet versions.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.licensemag.com/licensemag/Brands/Fox-Offers-First-Branded-Drink/ArticleStandard/Article/detail/459543|title=Fox Offers First Branded Drink|date=25 September 2007|language=License! Global|accessdate=7 March 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==References==
{{reflist}}

{{24}}

[[Category:24 (TV series)|24]]
[[Category:Books set within one day|24]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
