<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="11496019" ns="0" title="Tuan Nizam Muthaliff"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Infobox military person
|name= Tuan Nizam Muthaliff
|birth_date=1966
|death_date= 2005
|birth_place= Kalubowila
|death_place= Polhengoda, [[Colombo]]
|image= [[Image:T.N.Mutaliff.JPG]]
|caption= Colonel Tuan Nizam Muthaliff
|nickname=
|allegiance= {{flagicon|Sri Lanka}} [[Sri Lanka]]
|serviceyears= 19
|rank=[[Lieutenant Colonel]]
|branch= [[Sri Lanka Army]]
|commands= Commanding Officer, 1st Battalion Military Intelligence Corps
|unit= [[Military Intelligence Corps (Sri Lanka)|Military Intelligence Corps]]
|battles= [[Sri Lankan Civil War]]
|awards= [[Rana Wickrama Padakkama]]
|laterwork=
}}
'''Colonel Tuan Nizam Muthaliff''' [[Rana Wickrama Padakkama|RWP]], [[Military Intelligence Corps (Sri Lanka)|MI]] (July 12, 1966 - May 31, 2005) (O/60727) was the former Commanding Officer of the 1st Battalion [[Military Intelligence Corps (Sri Lanka)|Military Intelligence Corps]].(MIC)

==Background==
Born in to a [[Sri Lankan Malays|Malay]] family in Sri Lanka, Muthaliff had his education at [[D.S. Senanayake College|D.S. Senanayake College, Colombo]]. At school, he excelled in both studies and sports alike.

[[Major]] Muthaliff was married to Major Kumudini Muthaliff Amarasinghe, Commanding Officer of the Sri Lanka Army Women's Corps and has a daughter, Sarah and son, Maalik.

==Career==
On conclusion of his studies, his desire to protect the unity of his motherland made him join the [[Sri Lanka Army]] as a cadet officer in June 1986. He first underwent training in the Military Academy of Diyatalawa and subsequently received a Cadet Officers' Training at the [[Pakistan Military Academy]]. Following this training, he was commissioned as a [[Second Lieutenant]] in the 4th [[Gemunu Watch|Gemunu Regiment]] of the [[Sri Lanka Army]]. His commitment and dedication to the service were rewarded when he was promoted as a Lieutenant on June 2, 1989.
While gaining experience in the Sri Lanka Army, since 1990 he was constantly attached to the Military Intelligence Unit for the Join Operation Command. He was promoted to the rank of [[Captain (land and air)|Captain]] on July 2, 1992 and afterwards as a [[Major]] on July 2, 1995. During that time he had worked as General Staff Officer (GSO) III (Intelligence) at Army Headquarters, Officer Commanding in the MIC training section, Group Commander Intelligence Security Group in [[Jaffna]] for about three and half years, Group Commander at the Directorate of Military Intelligence in Colombo for about three years since 1997 and General Staff Officer (GSO) I (Intelligence), [[Vavuniya]] from 2000 to 2001.
He became the Commanding Officer of Sri Lanka's first [[Military Intelligence]] Unit in November 2004. At the time of death he was also Director of the Colombo Cell.

In addition he has followed several courses overseas with distinction such as the Intelligence Staff Course - Bangladesh, Counter Intelligence Course - Bangladesh, Junior Command Course - India, South Asian Peace Keeping Course - Hawaii, USA and International Intelligence course - USA.

==Death==
Major Muthaliff was shot dead by [[Liberation Tigers of Tamil Eelam|LTTE]] gunmen at Polhengoda, [[Colombo]] when he was on his way to the [[General Sir John Kotelawala Defence University|Kotelawala Defence Academy]] on May 31, 2005. In recognition of his service to the army, he was posthumously promoted to the rank of [[Lieutenant Colonel]] on 1 May 2005 and then he was promoted as a [[Colonel]] on 31 May 2005.

==Awards and decorations==
His gallantry in the battlefield and also through his work in intelligence earned him several awards including the [[Rana Wickrama Padakkama]]. He also received the [[Sri Lanka Armed Services Long Service Medal]], [[North and East Operations Medal]], [[Purna Bhumi Padakkama]], [[Vadamarachchi Operation Medal|Operation Wadamarachchi Medal]], [[Riviresa Campaign Services Medal]], and 50th Independence Anniversary Commemoration Medal for his service during the course of his military career.

==References==
* [http://www.spur.asn.au/LTTE_atrocities%20_Major_Nizam_Muthaliff.htm SPUR]
* [http://www.sundaytimes.lk/050605/news/8.html Sunday Times - Muthaliff shooting: court inquiry continues]
* [http://www.flonnet.com/fl2213/stories/20050701002304200.htm Frontline Magazine -  War by other means]
* [http://www.dailymirror.lk/2005/06/01/front/1.asp Senior Army officer shot dead]
* [http://documents.gov.lk/gazette/2007/pdf/July/06Jul07/6JulI-IE.pdf The Gazette of the Democratic Socialist Republic of Sri Lanka, No. 1,505 – FRIDAY, JULY 06, 2007, PART I : SECTION (I) – GENERAL]

&lt;!--Reference in Sinhala: http://www.rivira.lk/2009/05/31/vishesha8.htm--&gt;

==External links==
*[http://www.army.lk Official Website of Sri Lanka Army]
*[http://www.defence.lk Ministry of Defence, Sri Lanka]
*[http://www.army.lk/mic.php MIC-Military Intelligence Corps]

{{Persondata &lt;!-- Metadata: see [[Wikipedia:Persondata]]. --&gt;
| NAME              = Nizam Muthaliff, Tuan
| ALTERNATIVE NAMES =
| SHORT DESCRIPTION =
| DATE OF BIRTH     = July 12, 1966
| PLACE OF BIRTH    = Kalubowila
| DATE OF DEATH     = May 31, 2005
| PLACE OF DEATH    = Polhengoda, [[Colombo]]
}}
{{DEFAULTSORT:Nizam Muthaliff, Tuan}}
[[Category:1966 births]]
[[Category:2005 deaths]]
[[Category:Deaths by firearm in Sri Lanka]]
[[Category:Sri Lankan Army officers]]
[[Category:Assassinated military personnel]]
[[Category:People assassinated by the Liberation Tigers of Tamil Eelam]]
[[Category:Sri Lankan Muslims]]
[[Category:Sri Lankan Malays]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
