<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="11609726" ns="0" title="University of the Philippines Diliman Extension Program in Pampanga"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Infobox University
|name =  [[Image:UP logotype.svg|300px]]
|native_name = '''Unibersidad ng Pilipinas Diliman - Sudlong na Programa sa Pampanga'''
|image =  [[File:Unibersidad_ng_Pilipinas.png|200px]]&lt;br&gt;&lt;small&gt;[[University of the Philippines Official Seal|Seal]]&lt;/small&gt;
|motto = Honor and Excellence
|established = 1908 (UP System);&lt;br&gt;1979 (UPEPP)
|type = [[Cooperative extension service|Extension Service]]
|president = Alfredo Pascual
|chancellor = Dr. Sergio S. Cao
* |director = Dr. Florencia Charito Imperial-Sebastian
|city = [[Clark Freeport Zone]], [[Angeles City, Pampanga]]
|region = [[Central Luzon]]
|country = [[Philippines]]
|free_label = Hymn
|free = [[U.P. Naming Mahal]]
|nickname = [[UP Fighting Maroons]] |
|free_label = Hymn |
|free = [[U.P. Naming Mahal]] |
|mascot = [[U.P. Oblation]] |
|website = http://upepp.upd.edu.ph/
}}

The '''University of the Philippines Diliman - Extension Program in Pampanga''' ('''U.P.D.E.P.P.'''; informally, '''U.P. Pampanga''') brings the UP standard of education, research, and extension work to the busiest and fastest growing place in Central Luzon, the [[Clark Freeport Zone]] in [[Angeles City, Pampanga]]. It also assists the Clark Development Corporation (CDC) develop its tourism program and the [[Diosdado Macapagal International Airport|Clark International Airport]] Corporation (CIAC) in strengthening its logistics capability. It also has a unit operating in Subic Freeport, called the [[University of the Philippines Diliman Extension Program in Olongapo]] (UPDEPO). UP's presence in Pampanga started when an extension program was established in [[Clark Air Base|Clark Air Force Base]] in 1953. Another unit was established in [[San Fernando City, Pampanga|San Fernando, Pampanga]] in 1979. Then called the UP Extension Program in San Fernando, (UPEPSF), it was formalized in June of that year under a [[Memorandum of Agreement]] between UP and the province of Pampanga under Governor Estelito Mendoza. UPDEPP is also known as ''UP Clark'', ''UP Clarkfield'' or ''UP Pampanga''. It is one of the extension campuses of the [[University of the Philippines Diliman]].

==History==
[[Image:University of the Philippines-Clark.jpg|thumb|200px|left|UP Diliman - EPP Temporary Campus at Clark Freeport in Angeles City]]

UP’s productive presence in Pampanga began when a fledgling unit was established in 1953 at the then Clark Air Force Base in Angeles. The UP Clark faculty immediately distinguished themselves as “Thomasites in reverse” as they promoted Filipino and [[Culture of Asia|Asian culture]] to what would be an entire generation of American expatriates.

To expand UP’s services in the region; an extension program was formally established in San Fernando in June 1979 under a Memorandum of Agreement (MOA) with the province of Pampanga under Governor Estelito Mendoza. The Clark unit closed soon thereafter. In the same spirit, a sister extension program was established in Olongapo in 1984, under an MOA with the city under Mayor [[Richard Gordon (politician)|Richard Gordon]] where it is called [[University of the Philippines Diliman Extension Program in Olongapo]].

The new Pampanga unit was known as the UP Extension Program in San Fernando. It had an initial enrollment of 117 undergraduate and 40 graduate students. From 1980 to 1995, classes were held in an unassuming six-room, two-storey building of the Pampanga High School in San Fernando. In this period, the unit absorbed a good many students from the province, to some extent slackening the load of UP Diliman.

The San Fernando campus abruptly ceased functioning following the eruption of [[Mount Pinatubo|Mt. Pinatubo]] on June 15, 1991 and the ensuing lahar surges. With its building ruined, it defiantly transferred its administrative office to the covered [[basketball court]] of the Pampanga High School.

UPEPP survived the Pinatubo catastrophe and rose to re-start operations in Clark in 1996, moving from one makeshift site to another.

In 1999, it moved to a refurbished warehouse along [[Claro M. Recto]] highway, which it has called home ever since.

On the new, albeit still temporary site containing 15 rooms, UPDEPP has proceeded to significantly improve its faculty profile (10 faculty members with doctorates) and enhance its academic offerings, particularly its graduate program. In June 2010, UPDEPP will launch its new Applied Psychology Program. It will probably be the only academic unit in the Philippines to have such a program. Five months before, in February 2010, the Applied Psychology Program will host an international conference on autism.

Ever faithful to its Kapampangan milieu, UPDEPP has launched researches on Kapampangan history and culture, and notably, has published a book on Kapampangan poetry affectionately entitled “Tuglung.” It has even deftly designed a general education (GE) course in Kapampangan culture called '''Araling Kapampangan''', adding an unmistakable local slant to its curriculum.

Not to ignore the indigenous inhabitants of Pampanga, UPDEPP has also launched the pioneering '''Aeta Studies Center''' in coordination with the Clark Development Corporation (CDC). It is an extension effort that seeks to assist the impoverished Aetas, with UPEPP not losing sight of the program’s immense anthropological and sociological potential.

UPDEPP has also established a research cooperative. It is called '''Central Luzon Assistance and Research Cooperative (CLARC)'''. It holds office in UPDEPP's temporary building in Clark. '''CLARC''' was established in 1995 by UP Pampanga faculty in collaboration with other scholars in the area to promote research and build a network of scholars, researchers, and educators within Clark Freeport, the province of Pampanga, and Central Luzon in general. '''CLARC''' is dedicated to expanding awareness and interest in inter-disciplinary research, publications, and methodologies. It is the most established research network in Pampanga today.

With its research track record, '''CLARC''' now keeps a considerable database about the region. This resource repository has been consulted from time to time by government, non-government, and business sector agencies. In addition, '''CLARC''' hosts a considerable library of various researches and studies conducted by other experts from universities, government agencies, and research outfits in the region. To popularize and propagate its collection, '''CLARC''' is about to launch a '''peer-reviewed academic journal'''.

With all its accomplishments in institution-building, UPDEPP is currently aspiring to become a full-fledged college in the very near future.

==New UP Clarkfield Permanent Site==
On June 22, 2007, in what can be the centerpiece of UP’s fifty four year old existence in the province, the CDC turned over to the university a 3.28-hectare lot for UP Clarkfield’s permanent site. The site was given in a dramatic groundbreaking ceremony capped by an emotional alumni homecoming.

The new site is to be developed jointly by UP and CDC into a &quot;university town&quot;. When completed, it will make the Clark Freeport one of the few progressive [[Special Economic Zone|special economic zones]] in the world to have an institution of higher learning in its premises. The proposed plan of the permanent campus will include a main building, a student and faculty dormitory, a gymnasium, a regional-cultural studies center and an alumni center. Today, it is serving as the intellectual capital of Region 3, is recruiting the brightest in the region and has established an admirable record of intellectual and institutional accomplishments.

At present, its director, Dr. Juliet C. Mallari, is busy raising the US$14 million needed to build the UP Clark University Town. So far, she has already obtained a PhP 50 million appropriation from Congressman Edcel Lagman of Albay. Senator Lito Lapid of Pampanga earlier had pledged another PhP 50 million but backed out for unexplained reasons. Bulacan governor Jon-jon Mendoza has reportedly pledged PhP 1.5 million for the university's fence.

UPDEPP is raising US$ 14 million to construct &quot;UP Clark University Town&quot; inside Clark Freeport. It is racing against time, as its present site will soon give way to an extension of the Diosadado Macapagal International Airport (DMIA) runway.

As of December 22, 2009, the bidding process for the Academic Building and Student Dormitory had been finished. Construction is expected to begin in January, 2010, with a schedule of eight months. The Province of Pampanga has agreed to shoulder the construction of UPDEPP's perimeter concrete wall, and will do so simultaneously with the erection of the two buildings.

==Academic programs==
===Undergraduate Programs===
* BA [[Applied Psychology]]
* BS [[Business Management]]
* BA [[Business economics|Business Economics]]

===Graduate Programs===
* Master of [[Management]]

==Student Organizations and Confraternities==
'''Academic Organizations'''
* Association of Economics Students (AES)
* Business Management Society (BMS)
* Psychology Society (PsychSoc)

'''Socio-Cultural, Political, and Religiously Oriented Organizations'''
* UPDEPP [[Student union|Student Council]]
* Samahang Mag-aaral na Nagkakaisa(SAMANA)
* UP Hijos
* UP Lakan
* Rotaract Club of UPDEPP
* [[Campus Crusade for Christ]] (CCC)
* League of Filipino Students (LFS)
* Graduate Students Association

'''Confraternities'''
* [[Alpha Phi Omega]] Inter Collegiate [[Fraternities and sororities|Fraternity and Sorority]]
* [[Kappa Sigma (Philippines)|Kappa Sigma and Kappa Delta Sigma Confraternity]]
* Pi Sigma and Pi Sigma Delta Confraternity
* Sigma Kappa Pi Fraternity
* Sigma Delta Pi Sorority
* [[Tau Gamma Phi]] and Tau Gamma Sigma Confraternity

==UPEPP Clarkfield Officials==
* '''Dr. Florencia Charito Imperial-Sebastian''' - Director
* '''Prof. Christopher Sanguyu - Deputy Director
* '''Prof. Ramon Ponce''' - Graduate School Coordinator
* '''''' - Undergraduate Coordinator
* '''Prof. Cristabel Tiangco''' - Student Relations Officer
* '''Prof. Florencia Charito Sebastian''' - Coordinator, Committee on Research and Extension
* '''Ms. Anne D. Mabanta-Fabian''' - Coordinator, Committee on Culture and the Arts
* '''Mr. Rhayan G. Melendres''' - Coordinator, Learning Resource Center
* '''Prof. Rosanne Marie G. Echivarre''' - Faculty Counselor
* '''Eddie Judilla''' - Information Staff

==See also==
* [[List of University of the Philippines people]]
* [[UP College Admission Test]]
* [[Pampanga]]

==External links==
* [http://www.up.edu.ph/upnewsletter.php?i=448 Article: UP gets a permanent site at Clark (UP Newsletter Volume xxviii, Number 07, 2007-07-01)]
* [http://www.sunstar.com.ph/static/pam/2007/06/26/news/cdc.grants.permanent.site.for.up.clark..html Article: CDC grants permanent site for UP Clark (Sun Star Pampanga, 2007-06-26)]
* [https://uvle.up.edu.ph/dept.php?collegeCode=12&amp;userId=0&amp;Horde=42288f7920bd6752f9df462978a34ac2 UP Extension Program (UP Clark)]
* [http://www.dtwlab.com/up/ PROPOSED PERMANENT SITE of UP Clarkfield]

{{University of the Philippines Diliman}}
{{UP}}
{{coord missing|Philippines}}

[[Category:University of the Philippines Diliman|Pampanga]]
[[Category:Pampanga]]
[[Category:Angeles, Philippines]]

[[pam:University of the Philippines, Extension Program in Pampanga]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
