<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="1162208" ns="0" title="E/OS"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Unreferenced|date=August 2007}}
{{Infobox OS
| name = E/OS
| logo =
| screenshot = [[Image:EOS LX BWord.png|300px]]&lt;!--please update this picture to version 0.3.0--&gt;
| caption = E/OS Explorer and BWord
| developer = Miguel E. Chanampa
| source_model = [[Free software]]
| latest_release_version = 0.3.0
| latest_release_date = {{release date and age|2008|03|26}}
| kernel_type = [[Hybrid kernel]]
| working_state =
| ui = [[Graphical User Interface]]
| license = [[GNU General Public License|GPL 2.0]]
| website = http://meos.sourceforge.net/
}}

'''E/OS''' ('''E'''mulator '''O'''perating '''S'''ystem) is a virtual machine emulation system.

E/OS is primarily based on the [[Linux]] kernel, [[QEMU]], [[XFree86]], and [[Wine (software)|Wine]], and is intended to be a replacement for operating systems such as [[Microsoft Windows]], [[Mac OS]], [[BeOS]], [[OS/2]], [[DOS]], and [[Linux]]. It aims to make it possible to run any program designed for any operating system without the need to actually install any other operating system. Thus only one operating system, in this case a free alternative to the systems mentioned, would be needed to implement all programs. The project was discontinued in July 2008.

As of version 0.2.8, E/OS also integrates [[MESS]] to emulate many home computer and video game systems, which could eliminate the need to download a different emulator for each console, and add compatibility to older and more obscure home computers.

== History==
The project was started in 1995 with the goal of a free DOS. Until 1998 it was based exclusively on [[FreeDOS]], and since then has been based on [[SEAL GUI]].
In [[2000]] the E/OS project switched to a larger focus, to create a system capable of running programs written for multiple platforms, including [[BeOS]], [[Microsoft Windows]], [[Mac OS]], [[OS/2]], [[MS-DOS]], and [[Linux]], on the same computer simultaneously.

=== Versions ===

On January 24, 2008, the EOS website was updated. At the same time a note was placed on the home page, saying that a new version will be released with a custom kernel.

====0.3.0====

On September 30, 2007, version 0.3.0 (beta) was released in source code only, then on March 26, 2008, version 0.3.0 was released on [[CD-ROM]] as a [[Live CD]], and can be bought on the popular internet store, [[Lulu (company)|Lulu]], for $28 USD.

Version 0.3.0 Live CD has not yet been released for download. &lt;!--I think this will need to be updated soon--&gt;

====0.2.9====
On December 28, 2006, version 0.2.9 was released. It added support for executing applications outside EOS, multimedia support, network support, 3D support for win32 based on libmesa and improved update capabilities via the utility iget.

====0.2.8====
{{Expand section|date=January 2008}} &lt;!--We need more info--&gt;

====0.2.7====
On 16 May 2006 version 0.2.7 was released with a new [[GUI]] and language selection for [[English language|English]] and [[Spanish language|Spanish]]. The 0.2.7 release is capable of being set up under Windows 9x/XP and also has added network support.

====0.2.6====
On 23 March 2006 version 0.2.6 was released as a [[QEMU]] image that makes operating under [[Microsoft Windows|Windows]], [[Linux]], [[FreeBSD]], [[OpenBSD]], [[Darwin (operating system)|Darwin]], [[BeOS]], possible. The 0.2.6 release is fully compatible with [[Linux]] and [[FreeBSD]] programs. The support for [[Unix]] systems and the Ext2 file system is also new.

====0.2.5C ====
On 27 July 2005 version 0.2.5C was released with the first step toward comprehensive network support and better [[Linux]] compatibility. For the first time the system is optionally available on CD.

====0.2.5B ====
On 9 March 2005 version 0.2.5B was released, which improved the new Kernel 205, with added support for Windows and Linux programs, partial [[Mac OS]] support and full [[DOS]] support.

== Status ==
This project is at present in the &quot;[[Development stage#Alpha|alpha]]&quot; phase, and as of yet everyday use is not easily possible. However, it's stability and automatic hardware recognition are now sufficient.
Since the release of version 0.2.5B (beta 2), all later releases have been available as a [[Live CD]]. Since version 0.2.6, [[QEMU]] has been bundled with E/OS [[virtual machine]] support.

== See also ==
{{Portal|Free software}}
*[[FreeDOS]]
*[[Freedows OS|Freedows OS and Alliance OS]] - (defunct)
*[[HydrixOS]]
*[[ReactOS]] - an operating system that is [[object code]]-compatible with Microsoft Windows NT and Windows 2000 applications and drivers.
*[[Wine (software)|Wine]] - a software program that enables a user using a [[POSIX]]-compliant OS to run [[x86]]-compatible software written for Windows

==References==
&lt;!--Please add more references--&gt;
{{Reflist}}

==External links==
*[http://ftp.heanet.ie/mirrors/sourceforge/m/project/me/meos/OldFiles/ E/OS distributions up to eos030.exe]
*[http://sourceforge.net/projects/meos/files/ 2/OS LIVE-CD successor, still by Miguel E. Chanampa, meant to be compatible with DOS and Windows]

{{Commons category|E/OS}}
{{Linux-distro}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:E/Os}}
[[Category:Discontinued Linux distributions]]
[[Category:Free emulation software]]
[[Category:DOS emulators]]
[[Category:Free software operating systems]]
[[Category:Software derived from or incorporating Wine]]

[[de:E/OS]]
[[es:E/OS]]
[[fr:E/OS LX]]
[[ko:E/OS]]
[[it:E/OS]]
[[ja:E/OS]]
[[pl:E/OS]]
[[ru:E/OS]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
