<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="11666813" ns="0" title="Katherine Kennicott Davis"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">[[Image:kkdavis1910.jpg|thumb|Katherine K. Davis]]
{{Other uses|Katherine Davis (disambiguation)}}

'''Katherine Kennicott Davis''' (June 25, 1892 - April 20, 1980) was a composer, pianist, and author of the famous Christmas tune &quot;[[The Little Drummer Boy]]&quot;.

==Biography==
She was born in [[St. Joseph, Missouri]], on June 25, 1892, and composed her first piece of music, &quot;Shadow March,&quot; at the age of 15. She graduated from [[St. Joseph High School]] in 1910, and studied music at [[Wellesley College]] in Massachusetts.&lt;ref name=obit/&gt; In 1914 she won the [[Billings Prize]].&lt;ref name=obit/&gt; After graduation she continued at Wellesley as an assistant in the Music Department, teaching music theory and piano. At the same time she studied at the [[New England Conservatory|New England Conservatory of Music]] in Boston.&lt;ref name=obit/&gt; Davis also studied with [[Nadia Boulanger]] in Paris. She taught music at the [[Concord Academy]] in [[Concord, Massachusetts]], and at the [[Shady Hill School for Girls]] in Philadelphia.

Many of her over 600 compositions were written for the choirs at her school. She wrote &quot;[[The Little Drummer Boy]]&quot; (originally titled &quot;The Carol of the Drum&quot;), in 1941.&lt;ref name=obit/&gt; It became famous when recorded by the [[Harry Simeone Chorale]] in 1958: the recording sailed to the top of the ''Billboard'' charts and Simeone  insisted on a writer's royalty for his arrangement of the song.
Another famous hymn by Katherine Davis is the [[Thanksgiving]] hymn &quot;Let All Things Now Living&quot; which uses the melody of the traditional Welsh folk song [[The Ash Grove]].

She was a member of the [[American Society of Composers, Authors and Publishers]] and was granted an honorary doctorate from [[Stetson University]], in [[DeLand, Florida]]. Katherine K. Davis continued writing music until she became ill in the winter of 1979-1980. She died on April 20, 1980, at the age of 87, in [[Littleton, Massachusetts]].&lt;ref name=obit&gt;{{cite news |author= |coauthors= |title=Katherine Davis, Composer, At 87, Memorial Service At Wheaton |url=http://pqasb.pqarchiver.com/boston/access/685632621.html?dids=685632621:685632621&amp;FMT=ABS&amp;FMTS=ABS:FT&amp;type=current&amp;date=May+17,+1980&amp;author=&amp;pub=Boston+Globe+(pre-1997+Fulltext)&amp;desc=KATHERINE+DAVIS,+COMPOSER,+AT+87,+MEMORIAL+SERVICE+AT+WHEATON&amp;pqatl=google |quote=Miss Davis composed more than 800 selections, sacred and secular, and her work was published by more than 15 companies. Her most well-known song is the carol, &quot;The Little Drummer Boy,&quot; originally published in 1941 as &quot;The Carol of the Drum.&quot; She also composed songs, seven operas, carols, choruses and sacred cantatas for children. Upon graduation from Wellesley College - she won the Billings Prize for composition in the class of 1914 - she taught music at Wellesley College and did graduate study in music at the New England Conservatory of Music. ...|work=[[Boston Globe]] |date=May 17, 1980 |accessdate=2010-07-22 }}&lt;/ref&gt;  She left all of the royalties and proceeds from her compositions, which include operas, choruses, children's operettas, cantatas, piano and organ pieces, and songs, to Wellesley College's Music Department. These funds are used to support musical instrument instruction.

==References==
{{reflist}}

==Further reading==
*{{cite paper
  | author = Boughton, Harrison Charles
  | title = Katherine K. Davis: life and work
  | publisher = Thesis, University of Missouri, reprint by University Microfilms
  | date = 1977
  | place = Ann Arbor, Michigan
 }}
*{{Citation
 | last=Flanagan
 | first=A. L.
 | date=1980-08-14
 | title=Katherine K. Davis, 1892-1980
 | periodical=The American Organist
 | pages=31
}}.
*{{Citation
 | last=Livingston
 | first=C.
 | year=1983
 | title=The Hymns of Katherine K. Davis
 | periodical=The Hymn
 | volume=43
 | issue=1
 | pages=28–33
}}.

{{Persondata &lt;!-- Metadata: see [[Wikipedia:Persondata]]. --&gt;
| NAME              = Davis, Katherine K.
| ALTERNATIVE NAMES =
| SHORT DESCRIPTION =
| DATE OF BIRTH     = June 25, 1892
| PLACE OF BIRTH    =
| DATE OF DEATH     = April 20, 1980
| PLACE OF DEATH    =
}}
{{DEFAULTSORT:Davis, Katherine K.}}
[[Category:1892 births]]
[[Category:1980 deaths]]
[[Category:American composers]]
[[Category:20th-century classical composers]]
[[Category:Women composers]]
[[Category:Wellesley College alumni]]
[[Category:People from St. Joseph, Missouri]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
