<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="1169845" ns="0" title="Upset"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{redirect|Giant-killing}}
{{other uses|Upset (disambiguation)}}

{{Refimprove|date=February 2008}}
{{originalresearch|date=June 2011}}

{{Wiktionary}}

An '''upset''' occurs in a [[competition]], frequently in [[election|electoral]] [[politics]] or [[sports]], when the party popularly expected to win (the favorite), is defeated by an [[underdog (competition)|underdog]] whom the majority expects to lose, defying the [[conventional wisdom]].  The underdog then becomes a '''[[Goliath|giant-killer]]'''.

The meaning of the word has popularly been attributed to the surprising defeat of the horse [[Man o' War]] by the horse Upset (the loss was the only one in Man o' War's career, though Man o' War later defeated Upset), though the term pre-dates that 1919 race.

==Origin==
In 2002, George Thompson, a lexicographic researcher, used the full-text online search capabilities of the ''[[New York Times]]'' databases to trace the usage of the verb ''to upset'' &lt;!-- adjective? --&gt; and the noun ''upset''.  The latter was seen in usage as early as 1877.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.wordorigins.org/index.php/upset&lt;/ref&gt; Thompson's research debunked one popular theory of the term's origin, namely that it was first used after the Thoroughbred racehorse Upset became the only horse to defeat the legendary [[Man o' War]] in 1919.

The meaning of the word &quot;upset&quot; has long included &quot;an overthrowing or overturn of ideas, plans, etc.&quot; (see [[Oxford English Dictionary|OED]] definition 6b), from which the sports definition almost surely derived. &quot;Upset&quot; also once referred to &quot;a curved part of a bridle-bit, fitting over the tongue of the horse,&quot; and though the modern sports meaning of &quot;upset&quot; was first used far more for horse races than for any other competition, there is no evidence of a connection. The name of the horse &quot;Upset&quot; came from the &quot;trouble&quot; or &quot;distress&quot; meaning of word (as shown by the parallelism of the name of Upset's stablemate, [[Regret (horse)|Regret]]).

==Examples of upsets==
&lt;!-- Please provide cites for these examples that actually specifically mention &quot;an upset&quot; --&gt;
*In the [[United States presidential election, 1948]], incumbent President [[Harry Truman]] was widely expected to lose to [[Thomas Dewey]]. The New York Times declared the election was a &quot;foregone conclusion&quot; and a Gallup poll gave Truman's approval rating as just 36%. Truman's campaign was further weakened by a three-way split in the party, with Democrats [[Henry Wallace]] and [[Strom Thurmond]] both running their own presidential campaigns in protest of Truman's policies.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.vahistorical.org/elections/truman.htm Virginia Historical Society]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.kennesaw.edu/pols/3380/pres/1948.html Kennesaw State University]&lt;/ref&gt; In response, Truman launched a frantic and energetic campaign, touring the country where he criticised both Dewey and the Republican-controlled Congress, which he dubbed the &quot;[[Do Nothing Congress]]&quot;. Since pollsters stopped taking polls two months before the election, they failed to notice a dramatic shift of votes towards Truman. In the election, Truman defeated Dewey by a margin of 5% and won a majority in the [[electoral college]].
*In 1998 [[Super Bowl XXXII]] - The [[1997 Denver Broncos season|Denver Broncos]] surprised the heavily-favored [[Super Bowl XXXI|defending Super Bowl champion]] [[1997 Green Bay Packers season|Green Bay Packers]], 31–24, on a 1-yard touchdown run by [[Super Bowl Most Valuable Player Award|game MVP]] [[Terrell Davis]] with 1:45 to play. The win was the first by an [[American Football Conference|AFC]] team [[Super Bowl XVIII|in 14 years]] and the first for Denver in five Super Bowl appearances.{{fact|date=August 2011}}
* In 1913 [[U.S. Open (golf)|U.S. Open]] - [[Francis Ouimet]], a 20-year-old American amateur, defeated golf superstars [[Ted Ray (golfer)|Ted Ray]] and [[Harry Vardon]].{{fact|date=August 2011}}

==References==
{{reflist}}

==See also==
* [[Cinderella (sports)]]
* [[NCAA Men's Division I Basketball Championship Upsets]]

[[Category:Competition]]
[[Category:Terms used in multiple sports]]

[[it:Upset]]
[[ja:番狂わせ]]
[[pt:Zebra (futebol)]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
