<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="1172710" ns="0" title="Psychedelic art"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">&lt;!-- Image with inadequate rationale removed: [[Image:Dukes 25oclock.jpg|thumb|[[The Dukes of Stratosphear]]'s ''[[25 O'Clock]]'' album cover by [[Andy Partridge]]]] --&gt;
[[Image:B23.land of psychedelic illuminations.jpg|thumb|270px|''Land of Psychedelic Illuminations'' (&amp;copy;Brian Exton): example of fractal influence]] &lt;!-- Putting original image back, which was used with permission from artist --&gt;
&lt;!--[[Image:LifePosterCover.jpg|thumb|''[[Life Magazine]]'' issue documenting psychedelic poster art phenomenon. Cover features art by [[Rick Griffin]], [[Wes Wilson]], [[Warren Dayton]] [[Victor Moscoso]], etc. September, 1967 {{deletable image-caption|Saturday, December 18, 2010|date=December 2010}}]]--&gt;
'''Psychedelic art''' is any kind of [[visual artwork]] inspired by [[psychedelic experiences]] induced by drugs such as [[lysergic acid diethylamide|LSD]], [[mescaline]], and [[psilocybin]]. The word &quot;psychedelic&quot; (coined by British psychologist [[Humphry Osmond]])  &quot;mind manifesting&quot;.  By that definition all artistic efforts to depict the inner world of the psyche may be considered &quot;psychedelic&quot;.  In common parlance &quot;Psychedelic Art&quot; refers above all to the art movement of the [[Counterculture of the 1960s|1960s counterculture]].  Psychedelic visual arts were a counterpart to [[psychedelic rock|psychedelic rock music]].  Concert posters, album covers, lightshows, murals, comic books, underground newspapers and more reflected not only the kaleidoscopically swirling patterns of LSD hallucinations,  but also revolutionary political, social and spiritual sentiments inspired by insights derived from these psychedelic states of consciousness.

== Features ==
* Fantastic, metaphysical and surrealistic subject matter
* [[Kaleidoscope|Kaleidoscopic]], [[fractal]] or [[paisley (design)|paisley]] patterns
* Bright and/or highly contrasting colors
* Extreme depth of detail or stylization of detail. Also so called [[Horror vacui]] style.
* Morphing of objects and/or themes and sometimes [[collage]]
* [[Phosphenes]], spirals, concentric circles, [[diffraction]] patterns, and other [[entoptic phenomenon|entoptic]] motifs
* Repetition of motifs
* Innovative typography and hand-lettering, including warping and transposition of positive and negative spaces

==Origins==
&lt;!-- Image with inadequate rationale removed: [[Image:Masson automatic drawing.jpg|thumb|[[André Masson]]. Automatic Drawing. 1924. Ink on paper, 23.5 x 20.6 cm. [[Museum of Modern Art]], New York.]] --&gt;
Psychedelic Art is informed by the notion that altered states of consciousness produced by psychedelic drugs are a source of artistic inspiration.  The psychedelic art movement is similar to the surrealist movement in that it prescribes a mechanism for obtaining inspiration.  Whereas the mechanism for surrealism is the observance of dreams, a psychedelic artist turns to drug induced hallucinations.  Both movements have strong ties to important developments in science.  Whereas the surrealist was fascinated by Freud's theory of the unconscious, the psychedelic artist has been literally &quot;turned on&quot; by [[Albert Hofmann]]'s discovery of LSD.

The early examples of &quot;Psychedelic Art&quot; are literary rather than visual, although there are some examples in the [[Surrealist art]] movement, such as [[Remedios Varo]] and [[André Masson]]. It should also be noted that these came from writers involved in the Surrealist movement.  [[Antonin Artaud]] writes of his Peyote experience in &quot;Journey to the Land of the Tarahumara&quot; (1937).  [[Henri Michaux]] wrote &quot;Miserable Miracle&quot; (1956), to describe his experiments with [[Mescaline]] and also [[hashish]].

[[Aldous Huxley]]'s &quot;The Doors of Perception&quot; (1954), and &quot;Heaven and Hell&quot; (1956), remain definitive statements on the psychedelic experience.

Albert Hofmann and his colleagues at Sandoz Laboratories were convinced immediately after its discovery in 1943 of the power and promise of LSD.  For two decades following its discovery LSD was marketed by Sandoz as an important drug for psychological and neurological research.  Hofmann saw the drug's potential for  poets and artists as well, and took great interest in the German poet, Ernst Junger's psychedelic experiments.

Early artistic experimentation with LSD was conducted in a clinical context by Los Angeles based psychiatrist [[Oscar Janiger]].  Janiger asked a group of 50 different artists to each do a painting from life of a subject of the artist's choosing. They were subsequently asked to do the same painting while under the influence of LSD.  The two paintings were compared by Janiger and also the artist.  The artists almost unanimously reported LSD to be an enhancement to their creativity.  

Ultimately it seems that psychedelics would be most warmly embraced by the American counterculture.  Beatnik poets [[Allen Ginsberg]] and [[William S. Burroughs]] became fascinated by psychedelic drugs as early as the 1950s as evidenced by [[The Yage Letters|The Yage Letters (1963)]]. The Beatniks recognized the role of psychedelics as sacred inebriants in Native American religious ritual, and also had an understanding of the philosophy of the surrealist and symbolist poets who called for a &quot;complete disorientation of the senses&quot; (to paraphrase [[Arthur Rimbaud]]).  They knew that altered states of consciousness played a role in Eastern Mysticism. They were hip to psychedelics as psychiatric medicine.  LSD was the perfect catalyst to electrify the eclectic mix of ideas assembled by the Beats into a cathartic, mass-distributed panacea for the soul of the succeeding generation.

==In 1960s counterculture==
Leading proponents of the 1960s Psychedelic Art movement were San Francisco poster artists such as:  [[Rick Griffin]], [[Victor Moscoso]], [[Bonnie MacLean]], [[Stanley Mouse]] &amp; [[Alton Kelley]], and [[Wes Wilson]].  Their Psychedelic Rock concert posters were inspired by [[Art Nouveau]], Victoriana, [[Dada]], and [[Pop Art]]. The &quot;Fillmore Posters&quot; were among the most notable of the time.  Richly saturated colors in glaring contrast, elaborately ornate lettering, strongly symmetrical composition, collage elements, rubber-like distortions, and bizarre iconography are all hallmarks of the San Francisco psychedelic poster art style.  The style flourished from about 1966 - 1972.  Their work was immediately influential to album cover art, and indeed all of the aforementioned artists also created album covers.

Although San Francisco remained the hub of psychedelic art into the early 1970s, the style also developed internationally: British artist [[Bridget Riley]] became famous for her op-art paintings of psychedlic patterns creating optical illusions. [[Mati Klarwein]] created psychedelic masterpieces for [[Miles Davis|Miles Davis']] Jazz-Rock fusion albums, and also for [[Carlos Santana]] Latin Rock.  [[Pink Floyd]] worked extensively with London based designers, [[Hipgnosis]] to create graphics to support the concepts in their albums. Los Angeles area artists such as [[John Van Hamersveld]], [[Warren Dayton]] and Art Bevacqua and New York artists [[Peter Max]] and [[Milton Glaser]] all produced posters for concerts or social commentary (such as the anti-war movement) that were highly collected during this time. Life Magazine's cover and lead article for the September 1, 1967 issue at the height of the [[Summer of Love]] focused on the explosion of psychedelic art on posters and the artists as leaders in the [[hippie]] counterculture community.  

Psychedelic light-shows were a new art-form developed for rock concerts. Using oil and dye in an emulsion  that was set between large convex lenses upon overhead projectors the lightshow artists created bubbling liquid visuals that pulsed in rhythm to the music.  This was mixed with slideshows and film loops to create an improvisational motion picture art form to give visual representation to the improvisational jams of the rock bands and create a completely &quot;trippy&quot; atmosphere for the audience.  The [[Brotherhood of Light]] were responsible for many of the light-shows in San Francisco psychedelic rock concerts.

Out of the psychedelic counterculture also arose a new genre of comic books: [[underground comix]].  &quot;Zap Comix&quot; was among the original underground comics, and featured the work of [[Robert Crumb]], [[S. Clay Wilson]], Victor Moscoso, [[Rick Griffin]], and [[Robert Williams (artist)|Robert Williams]] among others.  Underground Comix were ribald, intensely satirical, and seemed to pursue weirdness for the sake of weirdness.   [[Gilbert Shelton]] created perhaps the most enduring of underground cartoon characters, &quot;The [[Fabulous Furry Freak Brothers]]&quot;, whose drugged out exploits held a hilarious mirror up to the hippy lifestyle of the 1960s.

Psychedelic art was also applied to the LSD itself.  LSD began to be put on blotter paper in the early 1970s and this gave rise to a specialized art form of decorating the blotter paper.  Often the blotter paper was decorated with tiny insignia on each perforated square tab, but by the 1990s this had progressed to complete four color designs often involving an entire page of 900 or more tabs.  [[Mark McCloud]] is a recognized authority on the history of LSD blotter art.

==In corporate advertising==
By the late 1960s, the commercial potential of psychedelic art had become hard to ignore. General Electric, for instance, promoted clocks with designs by New York artist Peter Max.  A caption explains that each of Max's clocks &quot;transposes time into multi-fantasy colors.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Heimann, Jim. ''60s All American Ads.'' Cologne: Taschen, 2002. pg. 523&lt;/ref&gt; In this and many other corporate advertisements of the late 1960s featuring psychedelic themes, the psychedelic product was often kept at arm's length from the corporate image: while advertisements may have reflected the swirls and colors of an LSD trip, the black-and-white company logo maintained a healthy visual distance. Several companies, however, more explicitly associated themselves with psychedelica: CBS, Neiman Marcus, and NBC all featured thoroughly psychedelic advertisements between 1968 and 1969.&lt;ref&gt;Herdeg, Walter. ''68/69 Graphics Annual.'' Zürich: The Graphics Press, 1968. pgs. 45, 75, 248&lt;/ref&gt;  In 1968, Campbell's soup ran a poster promotion that promised to &quot;Turn your wall souper-delic!&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Heimann, Jim. ''60s All American Ads.'' Cologne: Taschen, 2002. pg. 798&lt;/ref&gt;

The early years of the 1970s saw advertisers using psychedelic art to sell a limitless array of consumer goods. Hair products, cars, cigarettes, and even pantyhose became colorful acts of pseudo-rebellion.&lt;ref&gt;Heimann, Jim. ''70s All American Ads.'' Cologne: Taschen, 2004. pgs. 443, 102, 76, 85, 484.&lt;/ref&gt; The Chelsea National Bank commissioned a psychedelic landscape by Peter Max, and neon green, pink, and blue monkeys inhabited advertisements for a zoo.&lt;ref&gt;Herdeg, Walter. ''71/72 Graphics Annual.'' Zürich: The Graphics Press, 1971. pgs. 39, 49.&lt;/ref&gt; A fantasy land of colorful, swirling, psychedelic bubbles provided the perfect backdrop for a Clearasil ad.&lt;ref&gt;Herdeg, Walter. ''71/72 Graphics Annual.'' Zürich: The Graphics Press, 1971. pg. 78.&lt;/ref&gt;  As Brian Wells explains, &quot;The psychedelic movement has, through the work of artists, designers, and writers, achieved an astonishing degree of cultural diffusion… but, though a great deal of diffusion has taken place, so, too, has a great deal of dilution and distortion.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Wells, Brian. ''Psychedelic Drugs.'' New York: Jason Aronson, 1974. pg. 19&lt;/ref&gt; Even the term &quot;psychedelic&quot; itself underwent a semantic shift, and soon came to mean &quot;anything in youth culture which is colorful, or unusual, or fashionable.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Wells, Brian. ''Psychedelic Drugs.'' New York: Jason Aronson, 1974. pgs. 19-20&lt;/ref&gt; Puns using the concept of &quot;tripping&quot; abounded: as an advertisement for London Britches declared, their product was &quot;great on trips!&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Heimann, Jim. ''70s All-American Ads.'' Cologne: Taschen, 2004. pg. 523&lt;/ref&gt; By the mid-1970s, the psychedelic art movement had been largely co-opted by mainstream commercial forces, incorporated into the very system of capitalism that the hippies had struggled so hard to change.

==The digital age==
[[Image:Juliasetsdkpictfield3.jpg|thumb|250px|Fractal artwork created using the [[Julia set]]]]
[[Computer art]] has allowed for an even greater and more profuse expression of psychedelic vision.  [[Fractal]] generating software gives an accurate depiction of psychedelic hallucinatory patterns, but even more importantly 2D and 3D graphics software allow for unparalleled freedom of image manipulation.  Much of the graphics software seems to permit a direct translation of the psychedelic vision. The &quot;digital revolution&quot; was indeed heralded early on as the &quot;New LSD&quot; by none other than [[Timothy Leary]].  
[[Image:Tie-dye.png|thumb|left|250px|A tie-die design, created with [[GIMP]].]]
The Rave movement of the 1990s was a psychedelic renaissance fueled by the advent of newly available digital technologies.  The rave movement developed a new graphic art style partially influenced by 1960s psychedelic [[poster art]], but also strongly influenced by graffiti art, and by 1970s advertising art, yet clearly defined by what [[digital art]] and [[computer graphics]] software and home computers had to offer at the time of creation.

Concurrent to the rave movement, and in key respects integral to it, are the development of new mind altering drugs, most notably, [[MDMA]] (Ecstasy).  Ecstasy, like LSD, has had a tangible influence on culture and [[aesthetics]], particularly the aesthetics of [[Rave|Rave Culture]].  But MDMA is (arguably) not a real psychedelic, but is described by psychologists as an &quot;empathogen&quot;.  Development of new psychedelics such as &quot;[[2CB]]&quot;  and related compounds (developed primarily by chemist [[Alexander Shulgin]]) are truly psychedelic, and these novel psychedelics are fertile ground for artistic exploration since many of the new psychedelics possess their own unique properties that will affect the artist's vision accordingly.

Even as fashions have changed, and art and culture movements have come and gone, certain artists have steadfastly devoted themselves to psychedelia.  Well-known examples are [[Amanda Sage]], [[Alex Grey]] and [[Robert Venosa]].  These artists have developed unique and distinct styles that while containing elements that are obviously &quot;psychedelic&quot;, are clearly artistic expression that transcend simple categorization.  While it is not necessary to use psychedelics to arrive at such a stage of artistic development, serious psychedelic artists are demonstrating that there is tangible technique to obtaining visions, and that technique is the creative use of psychedelic drugs.

== Psychedelic artists ==
*[[Pablo Amaringo]]
*[[Brummbaer]]
*[[Roger Dean]]
*[[Warren Dayton]]
*[[Scott Draves]]
*[[Ernst Fuchs (artist)|Ernst Fuchs]]
*[[H. R. Giger]]
*[[Alex Grey]]
*[[Rick Griffin]]
*[[John Hurford]]
*[[Alton Kelly|Alton Kelley]]
*[[Mati Klarwein]]
*[[Isaac Abrams]]
*[[Peter Max]]
*[[Stanley Mouse|Stanley &quot;Mouse&quot; Miller]]
*[[Victor Moscoso]]
*[[Gilbert Shelton]]
*[[John Van Hamersveld]]
*[[Robert Williams (artist)|Robert Williams]]
*[[Wes Wilson]]
*[[Oleg A. Korolev]]
*[[Karl Ferris]]
*[[The Fool (design collective)]]

==See also==
*[[Visionary art]]
*[[Entoptic phenomena (archaeology)]]
*[[Psychedelic]]
*[[Psychedelic music]]
*[[Psychedelic literature]]

==Notes and references==
{{Reflist}}

==Further reading==
* Rubin, David S. [http://www.amazon.com/Psychedelic-Optical-Visionary-since-1960s/dp/0262014041 ''Psychedelic: Optical and Visionary Art since the 1960s''] MIT Press (April 2010)
* Masters, Robert E.L. and Houston, Jean ''Psychedelic Art'' New York:1968 A Balance House book—printed by Grove Press, Inc.

==External links==
&lt;!--========================({{No More Links}})============================
    | PLEASE BE CAUTIOUS IN ADDING MORE LINKS TO THIS ARTICLE. WIKIPEDIA  |
    | IS NOT A COLLECTION OF LINKS NOR SHOULD IT BE USED FOR ADVERTISING. |
    |                                                                     |
    |           Excessive or inappropriate links WILL BE DELETED.         |
    | See [[Wikipedia:External links]] &amp; [[Wikipedia:Spam]] for details.  |
    |                                                                     |
    | If there are already plentiful links, please propose additions or   |
    | replacements on this article's discussion page, or submit your link |
    | to the relevant category at the Open Directory Project (dmoz.org)   |
    | and link back to that category using the {{dmoz}} template.         |
    =======================({{No More Links}})=============================--&gt;
*[http://www.erowid.org/culture/art/ Erowid Culture Vault: Visionary Arts Vault]

{{drug use}}

[[Category:Psychedelic art| ]]

[[de:Psychedelische Kunst]]
[[es:Arte psicodélico]]
[[fi:Psykedeelinen taide]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
