<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="117337" ns="0" title="Westlake Village, California"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{for|the district in Los Angeles|Westlake, Los Angeles}}
{{Infobox settlement
|official_name            = City of Westlake Village
|other_name               =
|native_name              = &lt;!-- for cities whose native name is not in English --&gt;
|nickname                 =
|motto                    =
|image_skyline            =
|imagesize                =
|image_caption            =
|image_flag               =
|flag_size                =
|image_seal               =
|seal_size                =
|image_shield             =
|shield_size              =
|image_blank_emblem       =
|blank_emblem_size        = 116
|image_map                = LA County Incorporated Areas Westlake Village highlighted.svg
|mapsize                  = 250x200px
|map_caption              = Location of Westlake Village in [[Los Angeles County, California|Los Angeles]] and [[Ventura County, California|Ventura]] counties, [[California]]
|image_map1               =
|mapsize1                 =
|map_caption1             =
|subdivision_type         = [[List of countries|Country]]
|subdivision_name         = United States
|subdivision_type1        = [[Political divisions of the United States|State]]
|subdivision_name1        = [[California]]
|subdivision_type2        = [[List of counties in California|County]]
|subdivision_name2        = [[Los Angeles County, California|Los Angeles]] and [[Ventura County, California|Ventura]]
|subdivision_type3        =
|subdivision_name3        =
|subdivision_type4        =
|subdivision_name4        =
|government_type          =
|leader_title             = [[Mayor]]
|leader_name              = Robert Slavin&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url = http://www.wlv.org/city_hall/mayor.asp | title = City of Westlake Village – Mayor Robert Slavin | accessdate = December 11, 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|leader_title1            = &lt;!-- for places with, say, both a mayor and a city manager --&gt;
|leader_name1             =
|leader_title2            =
|leader_name2             =
|leader_title3            =
|leader_name3             =
|established_title        = &lt;!-- Settled --&gt;
|established_date         =
|established_title2       = &lt;!-- Incorporated (town) --&gt;
|established_date2        =
|established_title3       = Incorporated (city)
|established_date3        = 1981-12-11&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url = http://www.cacities.org/resource_files/20457.IncorpDateLO.doc |  title = Incorporation Dates of California Cities | accessdate = January 18, 2007}}&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;!-- Area------------------&gt;
|area_magnitude           =
| unit_pref               =US
| area_footnotes          = &lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.census.gov/geo/www/gazetteer/files/Gaz_places_national.txt |title=U.S. Census |date= |accessdate=September 24, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;
| area_total_sq_mi        = 5.505
| area_land_sq_mi         = 5.185
| area_water_sq_mi        = 0.320
| area_total_km2          = 14.257
| area_land_km2           = 13.430
| area_water_km2          = 0.828
| area_water_percent      = 5.80
| area_note               = 
|area_urban_km2           =
|area_urban_sq_mi         =
|area_metro_km2           =
|area_metro_sq_mi         =
|population_as_of         = 2010
|population_note          =
|settlement_type          = [[City]]
|population_total         = 8270
|population_footnotes     = 
|population_density_km2   = auto
|population_density_sq_mi = auto
|population_metro         =
|population_density_metro_km2     =
|population_density_metro_sq_mi   =
|population_urban                 =
|population_density_urban_km2     =
|population_density_urban_sq_mi   =
|timezone                 = [[Pacific Time Zone|PST]]
|utc_offset               = -8
|timezone_DST             = PDT
|utc_offset_DST           = -7
|coordinates_display      = inline,title
|coordinates_type         = region:US_type:city
|latd = 34 |latm = 8 |lats = 31 |latNS = N
|longd = 118 |longm = 49 |longs = 10 |longEW = W
|elevation_m              = 268
|elevation_ft             = 880
|postal_code_type         = [[ZIP Code]]
|postal_code              = 91359, 91361, 91362&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url = http://zip4.usps.com/zip4/zcl_1_results.jsp?visited=1&amp;pagenumber=0&amp;state=ca&amp;city=Westlake%20Village | title = USPS – ZIP Code Lookup – Find a ZIP+ 4 Code By City Results 91362| accessdate = January 18, 2007}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|area_code                = [[Area code 805|805]]/[[Area code 818|818]]
|website                  = http://www.wlv.org/
|blank_name               = [[Federal Information Processing Standard|FIPS code]]
|blank_info               = 06-84438
|blank1_name              =
|blank1_info              =
|footnotes                =
}}
'''Westlake Village''' is a planned community that straddles the Los Angeles and Ventura county line.  The eastern portion is the [[Municipal corporation|incorporated city]] Westlake Village, located on the western edge of [[Los Angeles County, California]]. The city, located in the region known as the [[Conejo Valley]], encompasses half of the area surrounding Westlake Lake, and small neighborhoods primarily south of [[U.S. Route 101 (California)|U.S. Route 101]] and east of La Venta Drive. The population was 8,270 at the 2010 census, down from 8,368 at the 2000 census. It is also the headquarters of the [[Dole Food Company]]. Westlake Village is known for its affluence and secluded character, and is considered one of the wealthiest communities in the Greater Los Angeles Area.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.dexknows.com/geo/c-westlake_village-ca/ |title=Westlake Village, CA Yellow Pages/Online Phone Book, Search Local Business Listings @ |publisher=Dexknows.com |date=September 6, 2011 |accessdate=September 24, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The western portion of Westlake Village is a community, within the city limits of [[Thousand Oaks, California|Thousand Oaks]], in [[Ventura County, California|Ventura County]].  It is important to note, the properties and businesses in this portion of Westlake Village are actually recorded in the Ventura County Recorder's office as &quot;Westlake Village&quot;, as the [[United States Post Office]] maps the 91362 ZIP code to both cities. Most residents recognize the community of Westlake Village as not limited to the incorporated city in Los Angeles County, but encompassing the entire area surrounding the lake on both sides of the county line. 

The original community was known simply as &quot;Westlake&quot;. Roughly two-thirds of it was annexed by the city of Thousand Oaks in two portions, in 1968 and 1972. In 1981, the remaining third eventually incorporated as the City of Westlake Village.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url=http://www.wlv.org/city_hall/city-history.asp | title=City History | publisher=City of Westlake Village | accessdate=June 15, 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==History==
About 3,000 years ago, [[Chumash Indians]] moved into the region and lived by hunting rabbits and other game, and gathering grains and acorns. On-going excavations, archaeological sites, and polychrome rock paintings in the area provide a glimpse into the social and economic complexity of the ancient Chumash world. In 1770, Captain [[Gaspar de Portola]] led a party of Spanish explorers and missionaries, traveling north on the route that became known as [[El Camino Real (California)|El Camino Real]]. The party camped near a Chumash village, believed to be the site of present-day Westlake Village. Father [[Juan Crespi]], chaplain and diarist of the expedition, wrote: “We are on a plain of considerable extent and much beauty, forested on all parts by live oaks and [[oak]] trees, with much pasturage and water.”

When the Spanish finally did settle the area, they were given huge land grants, the largest of which was [[Rancho Simi]], given to the Pico family. When Mexico won independence from Spain in 1821, [[California]] became Mexican territory, and a few more land grants were given.  When California was admitted to the union in 1850, most of the land that later became Ventura County was divided among only 19 families. The picturesque future Westlake Village site among rising knolls, arroyos, barrancas and ancient oaks was recognized as the central part of two Mexican land grants: [[Rancho El Conejo]] and [[Rancho Las Virgenes]]. In 1881, the Russell brothers purchased a large portion of the land for cattle ranching. According to Patricia Allen, historian and family descendant, Andrew Russell beat the competition in buying the land by racing across 6,000 acres (24&amp;nbsp;km²) on a fifteen-minute trip in a buckboard and sealed the deal with a $20 gold piece. The price per acre was $2.50. The area continued to be known as the Russell Ranch although it was sold in 1925 to William Randolph Hearst and again in 1943 to Fred Albertson. The Russell family leased back part of the land to continue its successful cattle ranch operation while the Albertson Company used the vast area as a movie ranch. Many movies and television shows were filmed here, including “[[Robin Hood]],” “King Rat,” “Laredo,” and various episodes of “[[Tarzan]],” “Buck Rogers,” “Gunsmoke,” and “[[Bonanza]].”
[[File:Westlake Village CA Westlake Lake.JPG|thumb|left|Westlake Lake in Westlake Village]]
In 1963, the [[American-Hawaiian Steamship Company]] bought the 12,000 acre (49&amp;nbsp;km²) ranch for $32 million and, in partnership with [[Prudential Financial|Prudential]] Insurance Company, commissioned the preparation of a master plan for a “city in the country.”  Prominent architects, engineers, and land planners participated in designing the new community, a prominent example of planned 1960's-style [[suburbanism]].

The original tract was divided by the Los Angeles/Ventura county line. In 1968 and 1972, the Ventura County side, two portions of Westlake Village consisting of {{convert|8544|acre|km2|0}}, were annexed into the city of [[Thousand Oaks, California|Thousand Oaks]]. In 1981, the Los Angeles County portion ({{convert|3456|acre|km2}} or roughly 1/3) of the Westlake Village master community was incorporated as the City of Westlake Village. California state law prevents a city from existing in two separate counties, so the areas in Ventura County remained part of Thousand Oaks. To this day, many residents of the Ventura County portions of Westlake do not realize that they are actually within the city limits of Thousand Oaks.&lt;ref name=&quot;Acorn20110908&quot;&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.toacorn.com/news/2011-09-08/Front_Page/Which_Westlake.html|title=‘Which Westlake?’|last=Kuperberg|first=Jonathan|date=September 8, 2011|work=Thousand Oaks Acorn|accessdate=September 9, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Geography==
[[Image:Westlake Village CA Office Landscaping.JPG|thumb|Ornate landscaping in front of a Westlake Village office building.]]
Much of Westlake Village is surrounded by open space, including hiking and horse trails, as well as the vast [[Santa Monica Mountains National Recreation Area]]. The town borders the [[Malibu, California|Malibu]] hills, and is nine miles (14&amp;nbsp;km) inland from the Pacific Ocean. Coastal breezes seep through canyons to allow Westlake to stay up to 10 degrees cooler and considerably less smoggy than nearby [[San Fernando Valley]] during the summer months.

In addition to its role as a [[bedroom community]] for Los Angeles via the [[Ventura Freeway]], it is also home to many large commercial offices and the headquarters of the [[Dole Food Company]], [[Pleasant Holidays]], [[K-Swiss]], [[ValueClick]], [[J.D. Power and Associates]], and [[Vorwerk (company)|Jafra Cosmetics]].  The western region office (Region 5) of [[Anheuser-Busch|Anheuser-Busch Inc.]] is also located in the community.  The [[Ventura Freeway]] is one of three of Westlake's lifelines to Los Angeles and Ventura; the [[California State Route 1|Pacific Coast Highway]], and the [[California State Route 118|Ronald Reagan (118) Freeway]] also run nearby. It is a short drive to the nearest mall in Thousand Oaks.

Like many upscale hamlets, Westlake Village is well served by golf courses and country clubs. The [[Westlake Golf Course]], off Route 101, is verdant if noisy. More exclusive venues include [[Sherwood Country Club]] to the west and [[North Ranch Country Club]] to the north.

{{wide image|Westlake Village and Agoura Hills California USA.jpg|700px|Panorama of Westlake Village.}}

Over one half of the original &quot;Westlake&quot; development lies across the county line wholly within the city limits of [[Thousand Oaks, California|Thousand Oaks]]. This boundary which divides the Incorporated City of Westlake Village, and Thousand Oaks portion of Westlake Village, crosses over the Westlake Golf Course, halfway between Lakeview Canyon and Lindero Canyon roads, and half of the Lake itself. Another common misconception is that [[Lake Sherwood, California|Lake Sherwood]] is part of Westlake Village. It lies on the Thousand Oaks/[[Ventura County]] side.

The City of Westlake Village is located at {{Coord|34|8|31|N|118|49|10|W|city}} (34.141973, −118.819514).{{GR|1}} According to the [[United States Census Bureau]], the city has a total area of 5.5 square miles (14.3&amp;nbsp;km²). 5.2 square miles (13.4&amp;nbsp;km²) of it is land and 0.3 square miles (0.8&amp;nbsp;km²) of it (5.80%) is water. It is located approximately {{convert|40|mi|km|0}} West of downtown Los Angeles in the [[Conejo Valley]]. Other communities in the surrounding area include [[Thousand Oaks, California|Thousand Oaks]], [[Oak Park, California|Oak Park]], [[Agoura Hills, California|Agoura Hills]], [[Calabasas, California|Calabasas]], [[Newbury Park, California|Newbury Park]], and [[Malibu, California|Malibu]].

==Demographics==
{{USCensusPop
| 1980=6138
| 1990=7455
| 2000=8469
| 2010=8270
| footnote=source:&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
  |url=http://www.census.gov/prod/www/abs/decennial/index.html
  |title=CENSUS OF POPULATION AND HOUSING (1790–2000)
  |publisher=[[U.S. Census Bureau]]
  |accessdate=July 30, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Census figure for 1980 was enumerated prior to incorporation.&lt;/ref&gt;
}}
===2010===
The [[2010 United States Census]]&lt;ref&gt;{{USCensus-2010CA}}&lt;/ref&gt; reported that Westlake Village had a population of 8,270. The [[population density]] was 1,502.4 people per square mile (580.1/km²). The racial makeup of Westlake Village was 7,326 (88.6%) [[White (U.S. Census)|White]], 98 (1.2%) [[African American (U.S. Census)|African American]], 12 (0.1%) [[Native American (U.S. Census)|Native American]], 490 (5.9%) [[Asian (U.S. Census)|Asian]], 13 (0.2%) [[Pacific Islander (U.S. Census)|Pacific Islander]], 114 (1.4%) from [[Race (United States Census)|other races]], and 217 (2.6%) from two or more races.  [[Hispanic (U.S. Census)|Hispanic]] or [[Latino (U.S. Census)|Latino]] of any race were 533 persons (6.4%). 

The Census reported that 8,142 people (98.5% of the population) lived in households, 121 (1.5%) lived in non-institutionalized group quarters, and 7 (0.1%) were institutionalized.  

There were 3,262 households, out of which 971 (29.8%) had children under the age of 18 living in them, 1,985 (60.9%) were [[marriage|opposite-sex married couples]] living together, 292 (9.0%) had a female householder with no husband present, 119 (3.6%) had a male householder with no wife present.  There were 103 (3.2%) [[POSSLQ|unmarried opposite-sex partnerships]], and 14 (0.4%) [[same-sex partnerships|same-sex married couples or partnerships]]. 712 households (21.8%) were made up of individuals and 376 (11.5%) had someone living alone who was 65 years of age or older. The average household size was 2.50.  There were 2,396 [[family (U.S. Census)|families]] (73.5% of all households); the average family size was 2.92.

The population was spread out with 1,737 people (21.0%) under the age of 18, 479 people (5.8%) aged 18 to 24, 1,380 people (16.7%) aged 25 to 44, 2,917 people (35.3%) aged 45 to 64, and 1,757 people (21.2%) who were 65 years of age or older.  The median age was 48.7 years. For every 100 females there were 94.8 males.  For every 100 females age 18 and over, there were 91.2 males.

There were 3,384 housing units at an average density of 614.7 per square mile (237.4/km²), of which 2,745 (84.2%) were owner-occupied, and 517 (15.8%) were occupied by renters. The homeowner vacancy rate was 1.0%; the rental vacancy rate was 4.4%.  6,906 people (83.5% of the population) lived in owner-occupied housing units and 1,236 people (14.9%) lived in rental housing units.

===2000===
As of the [[census]]{{GR|2}} of 2000, there were 8,469 &lt;ref name=&quot;city-data.com&quot;&gt;{{cite web|title=City-Data Statistics|url=http://www.city-data.com/city/Westlake-Village-California.html|work=[[City-Data]]}}&lt;/ref&gt; people, 3,270 households, and 2,491 families residing in the city. The [[population density]] was 1,605.9 inhabitants per square mile (620.1/km²). There were 3,347 housing units at an average density of 642.3 per square mile (248.0/km²). The racial makeup of the city was 89.70% [[White (U.S. Census)|White]], 6.08% [[Asian (U.S. Census)|Asian]], 0.82% [[African American (U.S. Census)|African American]], 0.13% [[Native American (U.S. Census)|Native American]], 0.07% [[Pacific Islander (U.S. Census)|Pacific Islander]], 1.02% from [[Race (United States Census)|other races]], and 2.17% from two or more races, plus one of California's largest communities for [[Russian American]] and [[American Jewish]] ancestral groups. {{citation needed|date=May 2011}} [[Hispanic (U.S. Census)|Hispanic]] or [[Latino (U.S. Census)|Latino]] of any race were 4.61% of the population. Many locals (the [[Conejo Valley]] and [[Simi Valley]] region in general) are of [[Italian American|Italian]], [[Portuguese American|Portuguese]] and [[Spanish American|Spanish]] ethnic origins. {{citation needed|date=May 2011}}

The median income for a household in the city is $120,089,&lt;ref name=&quot;city-data.com&quot;/&gt; and the median income for a family is $148,885.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Home Relocation Index 2007|url=http://www.relohomesearch.com/NorthAmericaCity/CA/Westlake%20Village.aspx|work=[[Home-Relocation]]}}&lt;/ref&gt; The [[per-capita income]] for the city was $137,355&lt;ref name=&quot;City-Data Statistics&quot;&gt;{{cite web|title=City-Data Statistics|url=http://www.city-data.com/zips/91361.html|work=[[City-Data]]}}&lt;/ref&gt; in 2007, while the median home price was (as of 2007) $1,163,800.&lt;ref name=&quot;City-Data Statistics&quot; /&gt;

There were 3,270 households out of which 32.3% had children under the age of 18 living with them, 65.8% were [[Marriage|married couples]] living together, 8.0% had a female householder with no husband present, and 23.8% were non-families. 19.3% of all households were made up of individuals and 7.9% had someone living alone who was 65 years of age or older. The average household size was 2.56 and the average family size was 2.93.

In the city the population was spread out with 23.8% under the age of 18, 3.9% from 18 to 24, 23.1% from 25 to 44, 31.9% from 45 to 64, and 17.3% who were 65 years of age or older. The median age was 45 years. For every 100 females there were 92.7 males. For every 100 females age 18 and over, there were 89.7 males. About 2.5% of families and 2.5% of the population were below the [[poverty line]], including 1.6% of those under age 18 and 2.8% of those age 65 or over.

==Politics==
In the [[California State Legislature|state legislature]] Westlake Village is located in the 23rd [[California State Senate|Senate]] District, represented by Democrat [[Sheila Kuehl]], and in the 41st [[California State Assembly|Assembly]] District, represented by Democrat [[Julia Brownley]]. Federally, Westlake Village is located in [[California's 30th congressional district]], which has a [[Cook Partisan Voting Index|Cook PVI]] of D +20&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | title = Will Gerrymandered Districts Stem the Wave of Voter Unrest? | publisher = Campaign Legal Center Blog | url=http://www.clcblog.org/blog_item-85.html | accessdate = February 10, 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt; and is represented by Democrat [[Henry Waxman]].

As of May 2009, 1,943 (33%) of the 5,876 registered voters in Westlake Village are registered as Democrats, 2,583 (44%) as Republicans, and 1,101 (19%) declined to state a party affiliation.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.sos.ca.gov/elections/ror/ror-pages/15day-stwdsp-09/politicalsub.pdf|title=Report of Registration as of May 4, 2009; Registration by Political Subdivision by County|publisher=California Secretary of State|page=131|date=May 4, 2009|accessdate=December 16, 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The [[Los Angeles County Sheriff's Department]] (LASD) operates the Malibu/Lost Hills Station in [[Calabasas, California|Calabasas]], serving Westlake Village.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;[http://www.lasd.org/stations/for1/malibu_lhill/index.html Malibu/Lost Hills Station].&quot; [[Los Angeles County Sheriff's Department]]. Retrieved on January 21, 2010.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;&quot;[http://factfinder.census.gov/servlet/MapItDrawServlet?geo_id=16000US0609598&amp;_bucket_id=50&amp;tree_id=420&amp;context=saff&amp;_lang=en&amp;_sse=on Calabasas city, California].&quot; [[U.S. Census Bureau]]. Retrieved on January 21, 2010.&lt;/ref&gt;

==Economy==
[[Dole Food Company]] is headquartered in Westlake Village. In 1994 Dole announced that it would finalize its plans to build its world headquarters on a {{convert|30|acre|m2|adj=on}} site owned by the company, located north of the [[Ventura Freeway]] in Westlake Village. The decision had been delayed by groundwater contamination tests and reviewing of possible site plan revisions. Dole was expected to submit its plans for final approval by the Westlake Village City Council on February 9, 1994.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;[http://www.encyclopedia.com/doc/1G1-15125418.html   	 Dole gets ready to turn first shovel of headquarters dirt: plans are set to go to Westlake Village City Council. (Dole Food Co. Inc.)]&quot; ''[[Los Angeles Business Journal]]''. January 31, 1994. Retrieved on September 27, 2009.&lt;/ref&gt; [[K-Swiss]], [[Guitar Center]],and [[ValueClick]] also have their headquarters in Westlake Village.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;[http://www.kswiss.com/cgi-bin/kswiss/store/help_page.html?article=store_contact Contact Us].&quot; [[K-Swiss]]. Retrieved on January 12, 2010.&lt;/ref&gt;

===Top employers===
According to the City's 2009 Comprehensive Annual Financial Report,&lt;ref name=&quot;cafr2009&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.wlv.org/city_hall/documents/2009_Annual_Financial_RPT.pdf |title=City of Westlake Village CAFR |format=PDF |date= |accessdate=September 24, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; the top employers in the city are:

{| class=&quot;wikitable&quot;
|-
! #
! Employer
! # of Employees
|-
| 1
|[[Bank of America Home Loans]]
|630
|-
| 2
|[[Move (company)|Move]]
|450
|-
| 3
|[[Dole Food Company|Dole]]
|300
|-
| 4
|[[Farmers Insurance Group]]
|300
|-
| 5
|[[Costco]]
|300
|-
| 6
|[[K-Swiss]]
|275
|-
| 7
|[[Securitas AB|Securitas]]
|250
|-
| 8
|[[Guitar Center]]
|230
|-
| 9
|Preferred Hotel Group|Westlake Village Inn
|130
|}

==Notable residents==
&lt;!--Each entry needs a reliable source stating that the person lived in Westlake Village--&gt;
[[File:Mariel Hemingway Farm Gala 2006 2.jpg|thumb|right|200px|[[Mariel Hemingway]]]]
[[File:Mike Lieberthal.jpg|thumb|right|200px|[[Mike Lieberthal]]]]
Notable current and former residents of Westlake Village include, in alphabetical order:
* [[James Caveziel]]&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://virtualglobetrotting.com/map/james-caviezels-house/ |title=James Caviezel's House |publisher=Virtual Globetrotting |accessdate=March 16, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[Jimmy Clausen]]&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://rivals.yahoo.com/ncaa/football/recruiting/player-Jimmy-Clausen-34379 |title=Jimmy Clausen |publisher=Yahoo |accessdate=March 16, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[Lenny Dykstra]], baseball center fielder&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.luxist.com/2009/06/16/lenny-dykstra-house-auction-scheduled/ |title=Lenny Dykstra House Auction Scheduled |author=Deidre Woollard | publisher=Luxist |accessdate=March 16, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*  [[Jamie Foxx]], comedian/singer/actor
*[[Wayne Gretzky]]&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title=From superstars, sons emerge to lead Oaks Christian football|url=http://www.usatoday.com/sports/preps/football/2009-11-05-oaks-christian-trio-of-sons_N.htm|accessdate=November 11, 2010|newspaper=USA Today|date=November 7, 2009|author=David Leon Moore}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[Audley Harrison]], 2000 Olympic heavyweight boxing champion.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.vcstar.com/news/2010/may/15/fighting-for-everything/ |title=Fighting for everything |author=Loren Ledin |date=May 15, 2010 |work=Ventura County Star |accessdate=May 19, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[Mariel Hemingway]], actress&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://virtualglobetrotting.com/map/mariel-hemingways-house/ |title=Mariel Hemingway's House |publisher=Virtual Globetrotting |accessdate=March 16, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[Hulk Hogan]]&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://virtualglobetrotting.com/map/hulk-hogans-house-former-1/ |title=Hulk Hogan's House (former) |publisher=Virtual Globetrotting |accessdate=March 16, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[Cobi Jones]], former Los Angeles Galaxy Player&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://web.mlsnet.com/players/bio.jsp?player=jones_c&amp;playerId=jon165981&amp;team=t106 |title=Cobi Jones|publisher=Major League Soccer |accessdate=March 16, 2010}} {{Dead link|date=September 2010|bot=H3llBot}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[Scarlett Keegan]]&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.imdb.com/name/nm1735139/ |title=Scarlett Keegan  |publisher=IMDb |accessdate=March 16, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[Hayley Kiyoko]]&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.theacorn.com/news/2008-07-24/Community/Westlake_High_student_to_star_in_upcoming_Scooby_D.html |title=Westlake High student to star in upcoming 'Scooby Doo'film  |author=Sophia Fischer |date=July 24, 2008  |work=The Acorn |publisher=J.Bee NP Publishing, Ltd. |accessdate=March 16, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[Martin Lawrence]]&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.findarticles.com/p/articles/mi_m1355/is_15_96/ai_55983443 http://www.findarticles.com/p/articles/mi_m1355/is_15_96/ai_55983443] ''google.com''&lt;/ref&gt;
*[[Mike Lieberthal]], All Star/Gold Glove major league baseball catcher&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://mlb.mlb.com/content/printer_friendly/la/y2006/m12/d06/c1752505.jsp |title=Dodgers sign Lieberthal to one-year deal |author=Los Angeles Dodgers Public Relations |date=December 6, 2006 |accessdate=March 16, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[Jonathan Lipnicki]]&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.imdb.com/name/nm0005151/bio |title=Biography for Jonathan Lipnicki |publisher=IMDb |accessdate=March 16, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[Heather Locklear]], actress&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://articles.latimes.com/2006/jun/25/realestate/re-hotprop25|title=Westlake Village melodrama|last=Ryon|first=Ruth|date=June 25, 2006|work=[[Los Angeles Times]]|accessdate=September 9, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[Maureen McCormick]], actress, played [[Marcia Brady]] in the TV series [[The Brady Bunch]]&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.chicagotribune.com/classified/realestate/chi-maureen-mccormic-snoop-1005oct05,0,3386202.story |title=At home, 'Brady Bunch' sis, Maureen McCormick, meets 'Andy of Mayberry' |author=Nina Metz |date=October 5, 2008 |work=Chicago Tribune |accessdate=March 16, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[Joe Montana]]&lt;ref name=&quot;nytimes.com&quot;&gt;[http://www.nytimes.com/2009/10/14/sports/14oaks.html] ''nytimes.com''&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[Eddie Money]], musician&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.portlandtribune.com/features/story.php?story_id=125615867675667000|title=19 Questions for Eddie Money|last=Eggers|first=Kerry|date=October 22, 2009|work=[[Portland Tribune]]|accessdate=September 9, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[John Ratzenberger]], actor, best known as postal worker Cliff from the 80s sitcom, Cheers.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://virtualglobetrotting.com/map/john-ratzenbergers-house/ |title=John Ratzenberger's House |publisher=Virtual Globetrotting |accessdate=March 16, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[Kim Richards]], child actress and stars on Housewives of Beverly Hills&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.bravotv.com/the-real-housewives-of-beverly-hills |title=Real Housewives of Beverly Hills, Season 1, Episode 8 |publisher=BRAVO TV |accessdate=December 9, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[Mickey Rooney]], actor&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://women.timesonline.co.uk/tol/life_and_style/women/the_way_we_live/article2961457.ece|title=A Life in the Day: Mickey Rooney|last=Scott|first=Danny|date=December 2, 2007|work=[[The Times]]|accessdate=September 9, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[Bas Rutten]]&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.basrutten.co.uk/bas-rutten-bio.php |title=
Bas Rutten Biography |accessdate=March 16, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[Mike Scioscia]]&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |url=http://www.nytimes.com/2009/10/04/sports/baseball/04scioscia.html |title=For Scioscia, Long Drives to Success With Angels  |author=KAREN CROUSE |date=October 3, 2009  |work=New York Times |accessdate=March 16, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[George C. Scott]],  actor&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://articles.latimes.com/1999/sep/24/news/mn-13484 |title=George C. Scott Dies at 71; Refused Oscar for 'Patton' |author=ERIC HARRISON and SUSAN KING |date=September 24, 1999 |work=Los Angeles Times |accessdate=March 16, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[Vin Scully]], voice of the Los Angeles Dodgers&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://sports.espn.go.com/espnmag/story?section=magazine&amp;id=3717497 |title=http://sports.espn.go.com/espnmag/story?section=magazine&amp;id=3717497 ESPN Magazine |publisher=Sports.espn.go.com |date=April 4, 2011 |accessdate=September 24, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*[[Mike Seidman (American football)|Mike Seidman]], NFL football player&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.uclabruins.com/sports/m-footbl/mtt/seidman_mike00.html|title=Player Bio: Mike Seidman|publisher=UCLA Athletics|accessdate=September 9, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*[[Will Smith]], musician and actor&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://articles.latimes.com/2004/sep/19/realestate/re-hotprop19|title=Livin' large on the Westside – Los Angeles Times|last=Ryon|first=Ruth|date=September 19, 2004|work=[[Los Angeles Times]]|accessdate=September 9, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[Guillermo del Toro]]&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.guardian.co.uk/film/2008/jul/27/guillermodeltoro |title=How I made Hellboy in my image |author=Guillermo del Toro |date=July 27, 2008  |work=The Observer |publisher=Guardian News and Media Limited |accessdate=March 16, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*[[Gary Wichard]], college football player and professional sports agent&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://abcnews.go.com/Sports/wireStory?id=13117695|title=Suspended NFL Agent Gary Wichard Dies at 60|agency=Associated Press|accessdate=September 9, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[Eric Wynalda]], soccer player&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://articles.latimes.com/1990-03-04/sports/sp-2732_1_eric-wynalda|title=Westlake High Product Eric Wynalda Making a Strong Bid to Join U.S. Team for the Biggest Soccer Event of All|last=Meyers,|first=Jeff|date=March 4, 1990|work=[[Los Angeles Times]]|accessdate=September 9, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[Robert Young (actor)|Robert Young]], actor&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.tvguide.com/celebrities/robert-young/bio/172454 |title=Robert Young: Biography |publisher=TV Guide |accessdate=March 16, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==References==
{{Reflist|2}}

==External links==
{{Portal|Los Angeles}}
* [http://www.wlv.org www.wlv.org] – Official website of the City of Westlake Village.
* [http://www.wlv.org/city_hall/city-history.asp City-history] Official website of the City of Westlake Village, history page.
* [http://lacdcs.com/station-end-page-22.html LA County Disaster Communications Service ( DCS ) Malibu / Lost Hills Sheriff Station]
* [http://www.westlakerevelations.com/ Westlake Revelations] – Non-political web site and mailing list devoted to communicating information on issues and well researched facts on Westlake Village.
* [http://www.WLVUnited.com WLVUnited] — Opinion and information on New Developments in Westlake Village. Site includes Maps and Environmental Impact analysis.
* [http://conejovalley.com/communities/westlakevillage.html Westlake Village @ The Official Conejo Valley Website], a Web site with local history, events, and community information.
* [http://www.theneighborweb.com Conejo Valley's Community Website]
* [http://www.conejovalleyguide.com Conejo Valley Guide – Activities and Events in the Conejo Valley]

{{Cities of Los Angeles County, California}}
{{Greater Los Angeles Area}}

[[Category:Cities in Los Angeles County, California]]
[[Category:Populated places in Ventura County, California]]
[[Category:Thousand Oaks, California]]
[[Category:Planned cities in the United States]]
[[Category:Populated places established in 1981]]
[[Category:Incorporated cities and towns in California]]

[[ar:ويستلاك فيلاج، لوس أنجليس، كاليفورنيا]]
[[bg:Уестлейк Вилидж (град, Калифорния)]]
[[ca:Westlake Village]]
[[de:Westlake Village]]
[[es:Westlake Village]]
[[fr:Westlake Village]]
[[it:Westlake Village]]
[[sw:Westlake Village, California]]
[[ht:Westlake Village, Kalifòni]]
[[nl:Westlake Village]]
[[pt:Westlake Village]]
[[tl:Westlake Village, California]]
[[vo:Westlake Village]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
