<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="11756601" ns="0" title="List of Gurren Lagann mecha"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{story|date=October 2008}}
{{Refimprove|date=October 2008}}
{{nihongo|'''Gunmen'''|ガンメン|Ganmen}} are the main type of '''[[mecha]]''' used in the [[anime]] series '''''[[Gurren Lagann|Tengen Toppa Gurren Lagann]]'''''. The name itself means &quot;face/facade&quot;(顔面 ガンメン Face Surface); unsurprisingly, the mecha themselves are centered around faces and as such are very varied with few in the series being the same model. Gunmen sport a variety of weaponry: primitive models only use large clubs or bare hands, while advanced ones use swords, or projectile and beam weaponry. Gunmen are powered by their human pilots' Spiral Energy (fighting spirit), or by electricity when piloted by a Beastman.

The original purpose of the Gunmen was to battle the Anti-Spirals, the main antagonistic force of the time. Lord Genome developed them about 1,000 years before the events in the series on a very large scale, with enormous Gunmen (called Dai-Gans) like the Dai-Ganzan and Arc-Gurren being much more commonplace than the smaller models seen through most of the series. Gunmen were also designed for space combat, so no further modifications were necessary when Team Dai-Gurren was launched with their Gunmen into the Earth's satellite orbit to fight the Anti-Spirals.

After the events of the series, there are very few Gunmen left in existence aside from Gurren Lagann and the Super Galaxy Dai-Gurren, with the large bulk of Earth's military being made up of Grapearls.

==Team Dai-Gurren==
With the exception of [[Simon (Gurren Lagann)|Simon]]'s Lagann, all of the Gunmen in [[List of Gurren Lagann characters|Team Dai-Gurren]] have been acquired by capturing them from the Beastmen Empire. However, team members have customized them to be more distinctive and personal to the pilot, rather than the generic looking Gunmen that most lower-ranked Beastmen use. After the time-skip, Team Dai-Gurren's numbers are increased with the addition of the Grapearls support.

Later on, when Team Dai-Gurren leaves Earth to rescue Nia, the battles are fought on a much larger scale. Because of this, Leite, Team Dai-Gurren's engineer, uses the Super Galaxy Dai-Gurren to produce much larger versions of Team Dai-Gurren's personal Gunmen, which are piloted by the personal Gunmen themselves (similar to the way the Gurren-Lagann pilots the Arc-Gurren Lagann). These new Gunmen keep the same name as their smaller forms, but with the prefix &quot;Space&quot; (e.g. Space King Kittan). 
     
Personal and fortress-type units seen thus far in Team Dai-Gurren include the following&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.gurren-lagann.net/mecha/|title=Tengen Toppa Gurren Lagann Mechanic|publisher=Gainax|language=Japanese|date=January 10, 2007|accessdate=2007-05-21}}&lt;/ref&gt;:

===Gurren Lagann===

The {{Nihongo|'''Gurren Lagann'''|グレンラガン|Guren Ragan}}, the titular mech of the series, is piloted jointly by two pilots for most of the story, with the Lagann portion always operated by the series' main protagonist Simon and the Gurren piloted by Kamina initially and then various other characters after his death. The mech was originally formed as a hotblooded response from Kamina to the Enki's initial two-headed configuration. Later in the series, the land-bound Gurren Lagann merges with another unnamed enemy Gunmen and gains a permanent set of wings (without any change in name). After the Battle of Teppelin, the Gurren Lagann is seen as a symbol of humanity's triumph, and later, after the Anti-Spiral's defeat, it is preserved as one of the last true Gunmen and the personal machine of Gimmy and Darry.

Its powers and fighting capabilities are almost entirely based on its ability to generate drills of greatly varying size, shape and usage from multiple points on its body. Over the course of the series, Gurren Lagann produced dozens of different uses for its drills, ranging from projectiles and missiles to shields, [[Archimedes' screw|water screws]], and various melee applications. The most powerful attack seen used by Gurren Lagann is the ''Giga Drill Break'' and its variants, where the pilot forms a huge amount of spiral energy into an enormous drill (or multiple drills) bigger than the mech itself. This special trait, and its status as a fused machine (with two exceptionally spirited pilots), makes it one of the most powerful entities of its size seen in the series. 

Its additional abilities shown in the series include a durable energy shield, which can deflect energy blasts even at short range, the ability to wield the [[sunglasses]] on the Gurren's chest as a melee weapon (a sword or boomerang usually), and a short-term regenerative function which can restore accumulated damage for the duration of the Gurren and the Lagann's union.

====Lagann====

{{Nihongo|'''Lagann'''|ラガン|Ragan}} is Simon's personal Gunmen which he finds in the first episode while digging tunnels in his village. It received its name, Lagann (羅顔)-meaning &quot;enveloping face&quot;-from Kamina and draws power from the ''Core Drill'', a small golden drill Simon uses similar to an ignition key. Unlike any other Gunmen in the series, the Lagann sports a unique cockpit and stands just short of an average human adult, as opposed to the others, which are all mostly the size of small buildings or larger. This physical handicap, in tandem with the usually average level of fighting spirit supplied to it by Simon, puts the Lagann at a considerable disadvantage in single combat against enemy Gunmen. However, when Simon is driven to give his best during combat, the Lagann's power increases exponentially, giving it the unique ability to generate drills from nearly any part of its frame. Lagann's other-and most notable-power is the &quot;Lagann Impact&quot;, its trademark ability to combine with other machines by piercing them with its drills. It is through this ability that the titular ''Gurren Lagann'' is created, along with the other, more large-scale mechas in the series. Physically, Lagann resembles a large statue-like head with arms and legs.

In ''Gurren Lagann Parallel Works'' episode 8, it is revealed that the first Laganns were found by Lord Genome as a child during the Anti-Spirals' initial assault on Earth long before the series' story begins and as such were used as a basis in the creation of the all Gunmen that appear in the show to use against their enemies. While most were cast into the Galactic Spiral Abyss by the Anti-Spiral, a maddened Lord Genome seemingly destroyed all the remaining Laganns except for the one that was placed deep underground until Simon finds it. Currently it is unknown who created the first Laganns, but it is speculated to be the Anti-Spirals (when they were still a spiral race).

In the second film, when Tengen Toppa Gurren Lagann is torn apart by the Anti-Spiral, the head sprouts a set of legs and arms of its own and continues to fight, just as Lagann would on the original mecha. '''Tengen Toppa Lagann''' is soon joined by the other new Tengen Toppa Gunmen and combines with the aid of Lord Genome, forming Super Tengen Toppa Gurren Lagann.

Unlike most Gunmen, Lagann shows signs of sentience. At one point, Lagann comes to Simon without any pilot. The most obvious evidence is in the second film. Lagann, becoming more and more damaged, grabs Simon, and throws him at the Anti-Spiral. Both Simon and Nia is visibly shocked at this, and apparently was not controlling this action, meaning Lagann was doing this action on its own. Moreover, Lagann's eyes are shown to have glowing green spirals.

====Gurren====

{{Nihongo|'''Gurren'''|グレン|Guren}}, originally named &quot;Gunzar&quot; as mentioned by other Beastmen in the manga, is initially an above-average sized Beastmen-piloted mecha, which attacked Litner Village the morning after Team Gurren's arrival early in the series. The mech is subsequently captured, rebuilt, stylized and named by its eventual pilot, Kamina, who had the Gurren's original swords converted into massive sunglasses similar to his own that could be used as a blade or boomerang in combat. Kamina took a liking to the Gurren the first time he saw it because it looked fearsome. Being of typical Gunmen proportions, the Gurren is able to fight without the Lagann's power. While its individual power was initially not on the same level as advanced Gunmen/pilot pairs, such as Viral and his Enki, Kamina eventually became experienced enough to hold his own against multiple enemies. Later on, the Gurren was mainly piloted by Rossiu and one-time pilots until the aftermath of the battle of Teppelin, pilotless until Viral becomes the Gurren's official pilot during the battle against the AntiSpirals. Gurren (紅蓮) means &quot;Crimson Lotus&quot;. As homage to it, a white Gunzar unit is seen during the battle of Tepplin, sporting a pair of pistols rather than blades.

Gurren made a cameo in an issue of [[DC Comics]]' ''[[Countdown to Final Crisis]]'', appearing as a [[Green Lantern]] construct of [[Kyle Rayner]]'s.

====Arc-Gurren====

Named {{nihongo|'''Arc-Gurren'''|アークグレン|Āku-Guren}} by Rossiu, this is one of Lord Genome's Gunmen battleships, a Dai-Gan, which his armies used when he was a Spiral Warrior in events prior to the series. Enormous in size, it is initially used to gather as hundreds of thousands of animals and people onto it as possible to escape world-destroying events later in the series. It uses Spiral Energy to run and only recognizes Lord Genome as its operator. It is capable of going into space for at least a year, and contains an array of large-scale defensive systems and weaponry.

When Simon uses the Gurren Lagann to merge into the Arc-Gurren, he converts the Dai-Gan into a Dai-Gunman called the {{nihongo|'''Arc-Gurren Lagann'''|アークグレンラガン|Āku-Guren Ragan}}, powered up by one of the Gurren Lagann's Giga Drills similar to how the Lagann is powered by Simon's Core Drill. The power of this Gunmen isn't fully displayed in the series, but it has the ability to rip the fabric of space-time itself through its sheer brute force on its debut. The Arc-Gurren Lagann is usually used exclusively by Simon and Viral, in the Gurren-Lagann, but was also operated by Gimmy and Darry, using both of their Grapearls. It can form massive drills or fight with punches.

The Arc Gurren-Lagann resembles the [[Gunbuster]], another giant mecha produced by [[Gainax]].

====Super Galaxy Dai-Gurren====
The {{nihongo|'''Super Galaxy Dai-Gurren'''|超銀河ダイグレン|''Chōginga Daiguren''}}, christened by Simon, is another colossal battleship-type Gunmen akin to the Arc-Gurren and first appeared in the prologue of the first episode before being formally introduced near the end of the third part of the series. Originally, it was called the Cathedral Terra and it was Lord Genome's flagship against the Anti-Spirals. It assumed the form of the Moon until the climatic battle during the Anti Spirals' attack on the Arc-Gurren reveals its true identity, then becomes Team Dai-Gurren's flagship for the final part of the series.

Because of its size, the people on board use teleportation technology to move around the ship. Its combat abilities are unparalleled by any other battleship-type mecha in the series, sporting an enormous array of missiles, beam weapons and shielding capabilities. It also has the capability to transverse to other dimensions and universes and has the manufacturing capabilities to create hundreds of Arc-Gurren Lagann-sized mecha in a short period of time.

During the final battle with the Anti-Spirals, when dealing with the gigantic Ashtanga warships, Simon channeled enough massive Spiral Energy, with aid from the spiral energy of those before Team Dai-Gurren to battle the Anti-Spiral, to transform the battleship into a humanoid shape similar to the method that created the Arc-Gurren Lagann, the Transcendent Super Spiral Dreadnought Gunmen {{nihongo|'''Super Galaxy Gurren Lagann'''|超銀河グレンラガン|''Chōginga Guren-Ragan''}}. Planetary in size, the Super Galaxy Gurren Lagann is piloted by a cascading interface of Simon piloting the Gurren Lagann, which is in turn piloting the Arc-Gurren Lagann which controls the Super Galaxy Gurren Lagann. Because it is so massive to be controlled by a single Gunman, it contains the bridge originally seen on the Super Galaxy Dai-Gurren, in order to alleviate some of the stress in piloting such a powerful mecha (although Lord Genome displayed the ability to singlehandedly control it during his reign, as he either killed or ejected anyone else on board during his takeover). Similar to the Gurren Lagann itself, The Super Galaxy Gurren Lagann sports a colossal pair of sunglasses on its torso materialized during transformation along with a smaller pair for the head.

The sheer power of this mecha shows it to be what is almost certainly the third most powerful machine in the series, capable of both deflecting and destroying objects on a planetary scale with relative ease. Like the Gurren Lagann, it also has the power to create drills from many points on its body at once. Its massive shoulder drills can detach and fit over its forearms, and both drills can fit over each other for a colossal version of its signature Giga Drill Break attack. On top of this, the mecha is equipped with thousands of cannons that appear from the threads of the mecha's drills (and, in some cases, within the threads of those cannons, which resembled drills), each capable of shooting a beam straight through the time-space continuum, used for hitting targets regardless of their locality and [[temporality]] in the [[multiverse]], being able to hit targets in the past, present and future all at once. Leeron also noted that &quot;a [[galaxy]] is being born from within the engines&quot; of the mecha due to its large amount of spiral energy.

In Gurren Lagann Parallel Works episode 8, which focused on Lord Genome's era as a Spiral Warrior, he used the Cathedral Terra in Gunman mode to wipe out the human race. Though it resembled the Super Galaxy Gurren Lagann, it lacked the sunglasses and generally resembled Lazengann. It was piloted by Lazengann inside the Dekabutsu rather than the Gurren Lagann inside the Arc-Gurren Lagann. While in battleship mode, Cathedral Terra's abilities are even more destructive, able to take down several Ashtangas and their escorts in a single blast of its mighty cannon, albeit with help from the surrounding ships. Also, it appears that the Cathedral Terra is a unique ship in the Spiral Warrior's arsenal, as no other ships of this class are ever seen. In 8, Lord Genome also demonstrated his ability to use a Giga Drill Break with Cathedral Terra, hinting that this attack is an innate skill of all spiral beings, rather than a finishing move of any particular individual (as evident how Kittan's one and only attack involving spiral energy was also a Giga Drill Break).

In Lagann Hen, instead of assuming the form of a grinning moon after the defeat of the Mugann army, the Cathedral Terra assumed it's humanoid form and started attacking the earth with a barrage if energy beams and punches. In this form it resembled a demonic, zombified version of Cathedral Lazengann (The Gunman form of the Cathedral Terra as it was originally named by Lord Genome). This was later shown to be a disguise, presumably to demoralize the human race, made by the Anti-Spirals, as it crumbled after Arc Gurren gained control of the massive Gunman. 

This version of the Gurren Lagann has an uncanny likeness to the Buster Machine 07. collective form: [[Diebuster]] from ''[[Diebuster|Top Wo Nerae 2]]'', also called ''Gunbuster 2''.

====Tengen Toppa Gurren Lagann====

By combining his own Spiral Energy with his comrades', Simon created the ultimate entity, the titular '''Tengen Toppa Gurren Lagann''' in the final battle against the Anti-Spirals. Not actually a mecha at all, it is a mass of materialized Spiral Energy on the scale of a large [[galaxy]]. Though being similar to the Gurren Lagann, its design is overall very different from other mecha in the series, its armor being made up of red skulls bound together by Spiral Energy that burns continuously from its core, giving it the appearance of Team Dai-Gurren's emblem.  Each of its many faces has one cockpit containing: Simon and Nia being the head, Viral the torso and the rest of Team Dai-Gurren in the limbs and joints placed in Lagann-style cockpits. Its abdominal mouth is clenched onto the head of the Lazengann, containing a fully resurrected Lord Genome. It has been confirmed in the data books that the Tengen Toppa Gurren Lagann is more than 10 million light years in height. This makes it more than one hundred times the diameter of the [[Milky Way]] Galaxy, and also made it the largest mecha seen in animation to date, until the debut of the Chou Tengen Toppa Gurren Lagann in the second movie.

Tengen Toppa Gurren Lagann draws jointly on abilities from its many pilots, including Simon's drills, Viral's swords, Yoko's rifle and so on. The actual limit of the mecha's abilities is immeasurable, as it gains an infinite amount of power depending on the pilots' will to win. At points, Tengen Toppa Gurren Lagann and the Anti-Spirals' Grand Zamboa fight at forces powerful enough to destroy entire universes; for example, the Infinity [[Big Bang]] Storm used by the Grand Zamboa had, according to Leeron, the &quot;energy capable of creating universes.&quot; The battle was so intense that it was shown to rip holes through various dimensions showing that the power of each was on a God-like scale. This is furthered by the fact that they can alter the fundamental laws of reality, such as altering probability and creating matter out of thin air (which is no small feat even by the series' own standard, as the various drills and weapons materialized are larger than most galaxies). According to the creators of the ''Gurren Lagann'' anime, the Tengen Toppa Gurren Lagann also has the ability to create an entire Super Spiral Space universe within itself, allowing the pilots' recognition to become reality.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=The secrets of Gurren Lagann answered!|author=God Len|date=2007-10-17|publisher=Japanator|url=http://www.japanator.com/the-secrets-of-gurren-lagann-answered--6714.phtml|accessdate=2010-02-08}}&lt;/ref&gt;

====Super Tengen Toppa Gurren Lagann====

Released only in the second movie of the series, titled Lagann-Hen [Ragan-Hen], this form was the peak of the aforementioned Gurren Lagann forms. After Tengen Toppa Gurren Lagann had been destroyed by the Grand Zamboa, the Team Dai-Gurren split its power and pieces to form their own separate Tengen Toppa Gunmen, including Tengen Toppa Gurren Lagann's head becoming Tengen Toppa Lagann. The rest of said team was composed of a Tengen Toppa Gunmen for all surviving members as well as Nia [In the film, all members of Team Dai-Gurren who had died in the final battle other than Kittan had been spared]. Those who normally piloted Dai-Gurren in the first half of the series then worked together to pilot Tengen Toppa Dai-Gurren, which was essentially the body of Dai-Gurren added on top of Super Galaxy Dai-Gurren with demonic features similar to Tengen Toppa Gurren Lagann, holding the nose of Dai-Gurren as a weapon in its left hand and a Team Dai-Gurren flag made of spiral energy in the right. After a lengthy battle, Lordgenome sacrificed himself to create a mass of spiral energy, which Tengen Toppa Lagann split between the team and then used it to combine into Super Tengen Toppa Gurren Lagann. This being appeared as a mass of spiral energy in the form of a faceless entity resembling both Simon (the current main pilot of Gurren Lagann) and Kamina (the former pilot of Gurren, creator of Team Gurren, and Simon's 'bro'), complete with crimson cape and glasses. Its size is approximately 100 times larger than its preceding form, with the Grand Zamboa and all the galaxies looking tiny in comparison.

Just as the Tengen Toppa Gurren Lagann contained all the smaller incarnations one inside the other, the final form does as well, with the original Tengen Toppa Gurren Lagann restored and standing inside the head. During the short battle involving this form, its only notable attack was the powerful Super Tengen Toppa Giga Drill Break, which appears to be many times larger than the Super Tengen Toppa itself, almost approaching the size of a universe. Said attack, when collided with a similar and equal attack from the Super Grand Zamboa (the evolution of the Grand Zamboa), caused the very universe the fight was held in to collapse on itself as a side effect caused by the ripples from their drills. A moment later the Giga Drill shattered, only to be replaced with a Tengen Toppa Giga Drill, then slowly downgrading until once again reaching simply Gurren Lagann, which alone gained enough power to destroy the massive Giga Drill created by the Super Grand Zamboa. In the end, the Super Grand Zamboa and Anti-Spiral are defeated by Simon alone, without his Lagann; in a fist fight with the Anti-Spiral, Simon uses some of his own blood to create a drill powerful enough to defeat the Anti-Spiral.

===Dai-Gurren===

Originally called the {{Nihongo|'''Dai-Gunzan'''|ダイガンザン|Daiganzan}} while under the command of Thymilph, one of Lordgenome's four generals, it is essentially a walking battleship many times larger than conventional Gunmen, with numerous heavy artillery gun turrets and heavy armor. The arms attached to the control tower serves as the hangar bay launchers for its housed Gunmen. After its capture by Team Dai-Gurren, it is renamed the {{nihongo|&quot;'''Dai-Gurren'''&quot;|ダイグレン|Daiguren}} (although still referred to by its original name by the Beastmen) by Yoko and remodeled to accommodate Team Dai-Gurren members, sporting a red color scheme and a different tower on the head as the original was destroyed when Simon took control of it using Lagann.

The Dai-Gurren serves as the flagship and mobile home of Team Dai-Gurren for the first part of the series until the battle of Teppelin where at the end, the Dai-Gurren's hull is self-detonated while the rest is ejected before being deactivated.

Aesthetically, the Dai Gurren resembles the Cathedral Terra, albeit on a smaller scale, with an attached tower, which serves as the Gunman's face, and legs. It also replaced the face on the bow with a knife anchor and two thrusters. There are several Cannons both on the deck and the shoulders of the tower.

Ironically, while it was Kamina's plan to take over the Dai-Gunzan, he would never command it, dying just moments after the victory.

In Parallel Works episode 8, many Dai-Gunzans are seen in Lord Genome's fleet. Aside from all being refitted with an additional bow-mounted drill, they otherwise do not cosmetically differ from the one in the series. However, the Dai-Gunzan seems to be the only one of its kind still in service, with the remaining fleet either destroyed or converted into the newer unnamed battleship Gunman.

In the movie, the crew of the Super Galaxy Gurren instead pilots the Tengen Toppa Dai-Gurren, dwarfing it's fellow Tengen Toppa Gunman in size, and now possessing a more demonic Cathedral Terra as it's bow. It retains Dayakka's &quot;I've got the greatest wife in the universe - Swing!&quot; attack via two bow-mounted Drill Anchors.

===King Kittan===

The {{Nihongo|'''King Kittan'''|キングキタン|Kingu Kitan}} is the Gunman piloted by Kittan. Inspired by Kamina's hijacking of an enemy Gunmen, Kittan and some others seized Gunmen for their own use to fight against the Beastmen. The King Kittan is a gold-colored star-shaped mecha with a menacing face, able to use its body as a weapon. 

After it and the other original Gunmen's abandonment and the adoption of the Grapearls by the human military, the King Kittan, alongside the other Gunmen from Team Dai-Gurren, was reintroduced by Makken and Leite, who equipped it with a cannon on its right arm. The ''Space King Kittan'', a Dai-Gunman piloted by King Kittan, was created by Leite later in the series but was destroyed in a failed attempt to save the Super Galaxy Dai-Gurren from the Anti-Spirals' Galactic Death Spiral by destroying its core. However, before exploding, the normal-sized King Kittan ejected and through Kittan awakening his Spiral Power and the usage of its own variant of Gurren Lagann's ''Giga Drill Break'' attack, it achieved its mission before getting destroyed too along with its pilot.

The {{Nihongo|'''Kiyalunga'''|キヤルンガ|Kiyarunga}}, named for and piloted by Kittan's sister Kiyal, has the ability to transform into a lance and shield for use by the King Kittan, with Kittan referring to the formation as the ''King Kittan Deluxe''. A homage to this Gunman is seen when Kittan piloted the Space King Kittan, where he wielded weapons that resembles the Kiyalunga's lance and shield transformation.

===Dayakkaiser===

The {{Nihongo|'''Dayakkaiser'''|ダヤッカイザー|Dayakkaizā}} is the Gunman initially piloted by Dayakka, but it was transferred over to Kiyoh after he became the captain of the Dai-Gurren. Along with the other human-piloted Gunmen, this was also seized from the Beastmen Empire. It has a cannon mounted on top of its head, which fires explosive solid rounds.

Believed to be destroyed after the adoption of the Grapearls by the human military, the Dayakkaiser, among other Gunmen from Team Dai-Gurren, was in fact retrieved and maintained by Makken and Leite, who also equipped it with Spiral Energy-based weaponry. Since then, it was solely piloted by Yoko. Among the Space Gunmen manufactured by Leite, '''Space Dayakkaiser''' in particular was equipped with many new weapons, such as arm-based rocket launchers and an exceedingly powerful cannon.  Notably it is the only Gunmen (other than the Gurren Lagann) to survive the final battle with the Anti-Spirals.

In the second film, the Dayakkaiser and its successors are absent, their role having been replaced by similar looking Gunmen, the '''Yoko M Tank''', '''Space Yoko W Tank''', and '''Tengen Toppa Yoko W Tank''', which are introduced as Yoko's personal Gunmen in the two movies. While the first two are largely palette swaps of the Dayakkaiser, Tengen Toppa Yoko W Tank has the ability to eject it's heavier armor for a more sleek form, akin to that of Tengen Toppa Solvernia. It also possesses a battery of cannons similar to Yoko's Rifle. In the manga adaptation of the series, Yoko combines the Yoko M Tank with Lagann, and was able to use a new technique called the '''Giga Drill Buster'''.

===Grapearls===

After the seven-year time skip, mass-produced mecha were developed through research of Gurren Lagann. Considered to be more powerful than the Gunmen, the '''Grapearls''' have an arsenal consisting of automatic handguns and blades and were adopted as the new mecha of the human army. The only two named pilots of the Grapearls (although there are many) are Gimmy and Darry, who each pilot a custom-model Grapearl to symbolize their status as commanding figures in the Grapearl squadron. Another grapearl pilot is a man by the name of Nakim, who was one of Yoko's students when he was younger. He is shown to be a grapearl pilot at the series epilogue. Though originally outmatched by the Anti-Spirals, two new weapons developed by Leeron's science team allowed the Grapearls to successfully deal with Mugann units without causing collateral damage.

The name Grapearl&lt;ref&gt;The official name (as of the Bandai R1 DVD Release) is translated as &quot;Grapearl&quot;.&lt;/ref&gt; (グラパール) probably comes from the &quot;Gurren-Lagann (''G''uren-''Ra''gan)&quot;, in reference to the fact they were developed using research on the Gurren-Lagann, and ''pearl'' (written in Japanese as パール), in reference to the silver color of the standard Grapearls (though Gimmy's and Darry's Grapearls are custom models, colored in blue and pink, respectively). However, in the Japanese radio program ''Onsen Toppa Gurren Lagann'', it's stated that the name comes from the phrase &quot;Look at all the Gurren-Laganns!&quot;, said by a child at the end of the epilogue. Leite also gives Grapearl-type space Gunmen to Gimmy and Darry's platoon.

In the second film, Gimmy and Darry pilot a two seater version of the mech named Tengen Toppa Grapearl during the final battle against Grand Zamboa. Physically it resembles a much sleeker Tengen Toppa Gurren Lagann, with one half colored blue and the other pink, split evenly down the middle. In addition, all normal Grapearl Pilots received Mass-produced versions of Lazengann instead of Space Grapearls, due to those being in the hanger of the Super Galaxy Dai-Gurren at the time. The mass produced Space Lazenganns all possessed beam glaives akin to the Alkaid Glaive instead of their standard spiral rifles.

===Other Team Dai-Gurren mecha===

Other Gunmen that join Team Dai-Gurren are manned by Team Dai-Gurren's core group of secondary pilots that join them early in the series. In the final battle with the Anti-Spirals, all of the following individual Gunmen and pilots are destroyed. However, in the second movie they survive and all of them form Tengen Toppa Gunmen.

;Sozoshin

The '''Sozoshin''' is Zoushi's/Zorthe's personal Gunman, which he pilots as part of the main group of Gunmen Team Dai-Gurren deploys. Unlike the other core Gunmen, its design is peculiar and squarish, not resembling any sort of animal or other object. Believed to be destroyed after the adoption of the Grapearls by the human military, the Sozoshin, among other Gunmen from the Team Dai-Gurren, were in fact retrieved and maintained by Makken and Leite, who also equipped them with Spiral Energy-based weaponry. In the final part of the series an Arc-Gurren sized version of this Gunmen named the ''Space Sozoshin'' is created by Leite. However, it is later destroyed by the Anti-Spirals, along with the Sozoshin and its pilot inside.

In the movie, Tengen Toppa Sozoshin possesses a powerful spiral wave attack that is able to help save Kidd and Ailak/Iaraak from the Grand Zamboa.

;Ainzer

{{Nihongo|'''Ainzer'''|アインザー|Ainzā}} is the Gunman that Ailak/Iraak pilots. During the first arc of the story, it served as a mobile rifle platform for Yoko in combat. It resembles a shark with two small legs. Like the other Team Dai-Gurren Gunmen, it was believed to be destroyed after Grapearls were adopted by the military but was later upgraded and reintroduced by Leite in the second part of the series.. The later-created ''Space Ainzer'' differs in appearance from its original in the form of an enormous rocket thruster attached to its rear end.  This Gunman is destroyed by the Anti-Spirals, along with the pilot.

Tengen Toppa Ainsaurus is radically different from the original and space versions, shaped to resemble a mechanical Tyrannosaurus Rex with a golden nose ring. Like the Space Ainzer, it can be operated in tandem with the Tengen Toppa Kidd Knuckle to fire a barrage of beam weapons.

;Kidd Knuckle

{{Nihongo|'''Kidd Knuckle'''|キッドナックル|Kiddo Nakkuru}} is the Gunman piloted by Team Dai-Gurren member Kidd. This Gunman resembles a monkey armed with a pair of guns.  Like the other Team Dai-Gurren Gunmen, it was believed to be destroyed after Grapearls were adopted by the military but was later upgraded and reintroduced by Leite in the second part of the series. Similar to ''Space Ainzer'', the ''Space Kidd Knuckle'' looks similar to its original model but has an additional set of enormous rocket thrusters on its back. The Anti-Spirals destroyed this Gunman, along with the pilot.

Tengen Toppa Kidd Knuckle maintains the short legs and long arms, but it possesses two faces and a bo staff with a spiral pattern. Like the Space Kidd Knuckle, it can operate in tandem with Tengen Toppa Ainzer to fire a barrage of beam weapons.

;Twin Boukun

{{Nihongo|'''Twin Boukun'''|ツインボークン|Tsuin Bōkun}} is a Gunman jointly piloted by the twin brothers, Jorgun and Balinbow. It resembles two faces, each with a fist coming out of its mouth and a leg coming out of its neck. This Gunman vastly differs from most others, as it apparently sports two cockpits, each with a full array of controls similar to that of a typical cockpit. Apparently, this means that each twin would only control half of the twin boukun, making it unpilotable by anyone else (as a strong understanding between the two pilots must exist for them to coherently use the Gunman, much less to use it with skill). Like the other Team Dai-Gurren Gunmen, it was believed to be destroyed after Grapearls were adopted by the military but was later upgraded and reintroduced by Leite in the second part of the series. The design of the colossal ''Space Twin Boukun'' differs from the original in more ways than the other Space Gunmen, having its general design altered so that it has a small head on the center of its body while the two larger faces of the mech act as the shoulders. This is likely due to the original Twin Boukun requiring two pilots, while the larger Space Twin Boukun only needed one. It also has much more detailed armor, a drill and horns protruding of various places and is a good percentage larger than the rest of the Space Gunmen counterparts. In a last-ditch effort to save Gimmy and Darry, Jorgun and Balinbow sacrificed themselves so that the twins may make it to the Super Galaxy Dai Gurren, whilst shielding them from enemy fire, which destroyed the Space Twin Boukun, and by extension the original Twin Boukun and the pilots. Unlike the other Gunman destroyed by the Anti-Spirals, which exploded with minimal damage, the Space Twin Boukun detonated in a massive fireball, engulfing dozens or hundreds of enemies.

Tengen Toppa Twin Vulcan maintains the increased strength compared to other Gunmen (it is capable of catching and crushing two galaxies thrown by the Grand Zamboa to save Yoko in the Tengen Toppa Yoko W Tank) and, unique to itself, possesses a two-man Lagann for use by pilots Jorgun and Balinbow. 

;Moshogun

{{Nihongo|'''Moshogun'''|モーショーグン|Mōshōgun}}, piloted by Makken, is part of Team Dai-Gurren's main Gunmen squad. One of its weapons is a large katana, and its physical appearance is that of an ancient [[samurai|Japanese samurai]]. Believed to be destroyed after the adoption of the Grapearls by the human military, the Moshogun, among other Gunmen from Team Dai-Gurren, were in fact retrieved and maintained by Makken and Leite, who also equipped them with Spiral Energy-based weaponry. Makken is the first to appear to face the Mugann threat in his newly rebuilt Gunman. The ''Space Moshogun'' sports more armor and two katana as opposed to one. It was destroyed when Makken took a suicide dive into an Anti-Spiral missile in an effort to protect the Super Galaxy Dai-Gurren.

Tengen Toppa Moshogun is similar in appearance to the original and space incarnations, however its swords can separate and the pieces will attack separately, as used to great effect to save Kidd and Iraak from the Grand Zamboa.

;Tengen Toppa Slovernia

'''Tengen Toppa Slovernia''' is the Tengen Toppa Gunmen piloted by Nia in the second movie of the series. It forms when Tengen Toppa Lagann is about to be destroyed by the Anti-Spiral after Tengen Toppa Gurren Lagann has been torn to pieces. It is much more feminine in appearance than the other mecha, with an energy cloud resembling Nia's hair cascading from the back of the head. It wields a drill spear in battle and wounds the Anti-Spiral, but loses an arm and is nearly destroyed by the Grand Zamboa's Counterattack, but is protected by Viral and his Tengen Toppa Enki Durga. Notably, it is the only humanoid Gunman in the series to lack an abdominal face.

;Dai-Gurren Army

During the battle of Tepplin, several other villages arrived, along with several battleship-class and personal-class Gunman. Though none are named, they all bear homages to earlier Gunman defeated by Team Dai-Gurren. They are all either salvaged from destroyed Gunman or stolen ones. However none of them are as heavily modified from their original stats, most are simply recolors of enemy mechs. However, the battleship class ones are notably different from both the Dai-Gurren and the standard Dai-Gunman class battleship Gunmen, suggesting that they are all customized.

==Beastmen==

The Beastmen Empire is made up of Lord Genome, his Supreme Generals and countless number of Beastmen. The Generals command a personal Gunman and a fortress-type Gunman, each with an army of Gunmen that are based on the characteristics of the general (e.g. flight-type, aquatic-type, etc.) Gunmen used by the Beastmen run on solar-powered batteries, because Beastmen lack the Spiral Energy normally used to pilot Gunmen.  As a result, they are useless at night.

The personal Gunmen in the Beastmen Empire, piloted by the Generals and high ranked militants like Viral, all have two faces, usually one on the chest and one on the head (Likely a reference to the Gunman of the original Spiral Warriors, who all had two faces in a Gurren-Lagann style setup).

===Enki===

The {{Nihongo|'''Enki'''|エンキ}} is Viral's personal Gunman, modeled after an armored samurai. The Enki is the product of significant innovation in Gunmen technology, and sports a number of advances that eclipse lesser models in performance, and is the first model seen to support solid-based ammunition. Unlike stouter Gunmen, such as the Gurren, that have bulky limbs that can only be used in wide swings, the Enki is more segmented and has multiple joints that allow it to perform complex actions, such as throws, kicks, and various martial arts techniques. The Enki's arm and thigh plates conceal rows of hidden gun turrets that fire large steel projectiles (''[[kunai]]''). There are pop-up compartments in the shoulders that can fire a single volley of rockets, and the entire chest plate can open to reveal a number of launchers that deliver an explosive payload of missiles. The Enki possesses a wrist mounted concave blast-shield, and a helmet with a large black ring atop of it, that is actually the charging focus for a medium-range particle beam cannon. Its helmet is stolen by Simon and Kamina when they first combined to make the Gurren-Lagann, and later becomes part of the latter's body.

Later, the helmet-less Enki has been redeployed as the degraded {{Nihongo|&quot;'''Enkidu'''&quot;|エンキドゥ}} and sports a new sickle-like weapon, which is affixed to its head (a homage to [[Ultraseven|Ultraseven's]] Eye Slugger weapon). When wielded, it provides an alternative to the dual swords the Enki usually resorts to in melee combat. Furthermore, it is also capable of shelling from afar by physically launching munitions from the same point on its head, once the sickle has been removed. When it aided Cytomander's air raid on the Dai-Gurren, it was also equipped with a flight engine, allowing it to fly.

During the Invasion of Teppelin, Viral's Gunmen remodified into the {{Nihongo|&quot;'''Enkidudu'''&quot;|エンキドゥドゥ}}, replacing the sickle crest for an extra pair of arms, meaning the Gunmen can now fight with four blades. When the new form fights the Gurren-Lagann, however, it is swiftly defeated, despite its upgrade. After the timeskip, the Enkidudu is shown fighting the Grapearl units, in order to protect a group of humans who decided to continue living underground. However, the damaged Enkidudu is unable to hold its own against the advanced Grapearls and is ultimately defeated, shutting down as Viral thanked his mecha for lasting this long for his grudge. The fate of the Enkidudu is never known, but is likely scrapped like the other Gunmen.

In the Drama CD, the upgrades were made into running joke in the form of the six-armed and tailed {{Nihongo|&quot;'''Enkidududu'''&quot;|エンキドゥドゥドゥ}}, and the {{Nihongo|&quot;'''Enkidudududu'''&quot;|エンキドゥドゥドゥドゥ}}, which resembled the Enki with eight arms, two tails, a cat-like head on the shoulders, and unique configuration into a giant dragon head.

In the second movie of the series, Viral's Tengen Toppa Gunman is a fourteen-armed mecha with both an abdominal face and a head resembling the helmet on the original Enki. It is called &quot;'''Tengen Toppa Enkidurga'''&quot;. It wields thirteen sabers identical to Viral's original swords as well as one [[kanabō]], a club often used by demons in Japanese mythology. (The wooden club's presence is comically out of place when the rest of the arms draw matching, black sabers.)

All forms are based on figures in [[Sumerian religion|Sumerian]] myth: Enki was a god of wisdom. Enkidu, meanwhile, was the wild man who fought and befriended [[Gilgamesh|King Gilgamesh]] during the Sumerian epic. The latter seems to bear significance to Viral's role in later episodes. It is possible that the mecha's name is a reference to French comic author [[Enki Bilal]] as Viral can also be read &quot;Bilal&quot; in Japanese. This is further evidenced by the title of Viral's theme, &quot;Nikopol&quot;, which is the name of one of Enki Bilal's most famous work, the [[La Foire aux immortels|Nikopol Trilogy]]. The final form, Tengen Toppa Enkidurga, is based on - in name and in form - the ten-armed, many-weaponed Hindu goddess [[Durga]].

===Beastmen General Gunmen===

The four generals of the Beastmen Empire all have their own personal Gunmen, all with the unique ability to transform into a sort of animal or more intimidating form.

;Byakou

The {{Nihongo|'''Byakou'''|ビャコウ|Byakō}} is Thymilph's personal Gunman. It is stored within the Dai-Ganzan's hangar bays and first saw deployment during Team Dai-Gurren's second attack on the mobile Gunman fortress. Equipped with a polearm called the ''Alkaid Glaive'', it is capable of emitting a powerful energy beam attack from the tip of the weapon, dubbed the ''Condemnn Blaze''. The Byakou was especially deadly in single combat and proved to be even more lethal, when paired with the Enki in pummeling the lone Gurren. Unlike personal Gunman units fielded by the other Generals, the Byakou was never shown to have a distinct alternate configuration.

The Byakou was the first victim of the Gurren-Lagann's multi-stage Giga Drill Break attack, which completely obliterated both the Gunmen and its pilot. It was also the last enemy defeated by Kamina, who was heavily wounded and died shortly after.

The Byakou's name is based on Byakko, the White Tiger of the West, one of the [[Four Symbols]] of the [[Chinese constellations]] in Japanese neme.

;Sayrune

The {{Nihongo|'''Sayrune'''|セイルーン|Seirūn}} is currently commissioned as Adiane's personal Gunman and was first seen deployed from her flagship, Dai-Gankai, while pursuing the stolen Dai-Ganzan. It is one of the few Gunman seen thus far in the series to feature two unique configurations: its default winged humanoid appearance, as well as an alternate scorpion-shaped layout. While in its winged state, the Sayrune seems to rely mostly on a range of energy whips and tendrils to mount any sort of attack, whereas its scorpion form is endowed with massive pincer claws and a stinger. The Sayrune can also use its wings to form a double-edged weapon called the ''Bloody Clamper''.

The Sayrune was destroyed, along with its pilot, when it was shot by the Dai-Gurren's cannons at point blank range, after Adiane's failed attempt to take Nia as a hostage.

The Sayrune's name is based on Seiryuu, the Azure Dragon of the East, one of the [[Four Symbols]] of the [[Chinese constellations]] in Japanese neme.

;Gember

The custom Gunmen {{Nihongo|'''Gember'''|ゲンバー|Genbā}} first appeared in action on the deck of the Dai-Gurren as its owner, Guame, had retreated to it, to personally perform his public execution of the captured members of Team Dai-Gurren. It is the second Gunman to feature a transformation. Its standaed form is a rather broad and bulky starfish-like creature, somewhat insect-like with its antennae, which can ensnare enemies. Its second form is a large face-like apparition, with the mouth filled with sharp needles that resemble insectoid legs. The controls of the Gember differ from normal Gunmen to accommodate its user; Guame is placed into a sphere-like crevice with a pair of mechanical hands aiding him. The only known attack of the Gember was its ''Gember Press'', wherein the foe is caught in a bearhug-like hold and crushed by the needles that are released from its arms.

The time of the Gember was short-lived, as it was destroyed by the Gurren-Lagann's Giga Drill Break. However, its pilot ejected himself before his Gunman got obliterated.

The Gember's name is based on Genbu, the Black Tortoise of the North, one of the [[Four Symbols]] of the [[Chinese constellations]] in Japanese neme.

;Shuzack

The {{Nihongo|'''Shuzack'''|シュザック|Shuzakku}} currently serves as the personal Gunman of Cytomander. Whereas the Sayrune was best-suited for underwater combat, the Shuzack is more adapted to aerial superiority, sporting a compact flight engine and a massive winged design. Additionally, its multi-jointed frame allows for both arms to both extend and retract in close-quarter situations. Its torso also holds a deadly buzzsaw. The Shuzack is destroyed, along with its pilot, when it got in the way of the Dai-Gurren ramming into the Dai-Ganten. Like the custom Gunman of the other Generals, the Shuzack can also transform-in its case, into a fierce-looking face with a wing-like crest and arms below its chin. However the full extent of its abilities are unknown, as the Shuzack was immediately destroyed following its transformation.

In the first film, Gurren-hen, the Shuzack attempted to perform an attack involving small needles emerging from every seam on its body. However, Cytomander only managed to say &quot;Destruction Dr-&quot; before his Gunmen was destroyed by Gurren-Lagann.

The Shuzack's name corresponds to Suzaku, the Vermillion Bird of the South, one of the [[Four Symbols]] of the [[Chinese constellations]] in Japanese neme.

===Mobile Fortress Dai-Gans===
Giant Gunmen used to carry smaller Gunmen, similar to the Dai-Gurren.

;Dai-Gankai

The {{Nihongo|'''Dai-Gankai'''|ダイガンカイ|Daigankai}}, rivaling the Dai-Ganzan in terms of sheer bulk and apparently much lengthier, is an aquatic, serpentine Gunmen fortress, which served as Adiane's flagship. Little is known about its abilities, other than its obvious aptitude for sea travel. While it seems to only be able to travel in a body of water, the Dai-Gankai's first appearance was marked by a sudden deluge over the battlefield (suggesting that it may have the ability to either divert or even create large volumes of water). The only appearance of the Dai-Gankai in combat was in episode 12, when it ambushed the Dai-Gurren, while it was crossing the ocean on its march to the Helix Empire's capital. Its main weaponry consisted of torpedoes guided by dolphin Beastmen and two massive pincers, which it used on its attempt to drag the Dai-Gurren to the bottom of the ocean. After bringing the Dai-Gurren back to the surface, the Gurren-Lagann obliterated the Dai-Gankai completely, but Viral, who was commanding the ship at that time, managed to survive.

;Dai-Gando

This domed, fortress-type Gunman is Guame's flagship. Its carapace is extraordinarily resilient, as evidenced by its survival of the aerial carrier Gunman Dai-Ganten's impact. It is propelled by many legs on its underside, and can travel at a decent clip. It later combines its strengths with Teppelin to form a whirling tornado of energy that destroys anything that comes in contact and disrupts communications and navigation. The Gurren-Lagann destroyed the Dai-Gando from beneath the surface of the earth, piercing its armor and reversing its spinning, violating its union with Teppelin and dissipating its energy storm before lancing it clean through, causing it to explode. The Dai-Gando's means of locomotion was later adopted by the humans for the various vehicles they use (cars literally ran on legs, not wheels).

;Dai-Ganten

A fortress-type Gunman, the flying {{Nihongo|'''Dai-Ganten'''|ダイガンテン|Daiganten}} is Cytomander's flagship. The Dai-Ganten made its debut during Cytomander's campaign against the Dai-Gurren, acting primarily as a carrier to launch multiple waves of small aerial Gunmen bombers. As the battle wore on, Simon and Yoko's Gurren-Lagann and Viral's Enkidu found their way deep below its decks and ended up dealing severe internal damage to the ship. Having lost altitude in the process, the Dai-Ganten was eventually damaged by a series of powerful kicks delivered by the Dai-Gurren, which had launched itself into the air using a cliff face. In the process, Team Dai-Gurren managed to snatch one of the enemy airship's two Levia-Spheres for themselves, and used it to safely float back to the ground, while the Dai-Ganten managed to retreat using the remaining one.

A month after the first confrontation, the Dai-Ganten returns in the following episode along Guame's flagship, the Dai-Gando, as Teppelin's last line of defence against Team Dai-Gurren's invasion. Its forces managed to trap the Gurren-Lagann, after the rest of the Dai-Gurren's Gunman forces were forced to retreat and protect it against Guame's offensive, and when the Shuzack was about to finish it, Simon and Rossiu were saved by some unexpected allies who entered the battlefield to aid them. In the end, the Dai-Ganten is sunk after being run through by the flying Dai-Gurren. Pieces of its wreckage fell on the Dai-Gando, provoking a massive explosion, but was unable to damage the heavily armored flagship.

;Dai-Ganzandu

A fortress-type Gunmen, {{Nihongo|'''Dai-Ganzandu'''|ダイガンザンドゥ(|Daiganzandu}} is under the command of Viral and is used during the Gurren chapter of the Gurren Lagann movie. Though being created in the style of Dai-Ganzan/Dai-Gurren, Dai-Ganzandu's design is a mixture of Enkidu and Enkidudu as it two sets of arms and head blade.

;Dai-Gan Doten Kaizen

The combination of all four of the General's flagships, the Doten Kaizen is the ultimate form of the Dai-Gan series of Gunmen and only appeared in the final battle of the Gurren Chapter. As Viral described it, because it's composed of each of the four general's flagships, it was impervious to attacks from land, air and sea. It's one and only attack involved firing a ridiculous amount of missiles at the Dai-Gurren. While the Doten Kaizen was formed with the Dai-Ganzandu, presumably it was designed so that the Dai-Ganzan was originally supposed to fill the main body. Doten Kaizen was created out of desperation at the return of Gurren Lagann, but was subsequently destroyed by its signature move, the Giga Drill Break.

===Lazengann===

Meaning &quot;Spiral Face&quot;, the {{Nihongo|'''Lazengann'''|ラゼンガン|Razengan}} is Lord Genome's personal Gunman, using his consorts as batteries. It is very similar to the Gurren-Lagann and has the same abilities that the Lagann can use (by extension, it also proves immune to being controlled by the Lagann Impact attack). However, it is much stronger and can use more powerful drill techniques, as well as defend against the Gurren-Lagann's techniques with ease. In the end, it took the Lagann on its own to severely damage the Lazengann. The mecha was later recreated as part of the Tengen Toppa Gurren-Lagann, used in the desperation move ''Lazengann Overload'' to convert itself and the energy from the Grand Zamboa's Infinity Big Bang Storm into pure Spiral Energy, taking the form of a gigantic drill with Lord Genome's head on the tip that is ingested by the Tengen Toppa's abdominal mouth.

Its spiral theme is different than the Lagann's, as it is more jagged and square-like, compared to the smooth, more circular theme of the Lagann. Unlike the Gurren-Lagann's focus on using large, bulky Giga Drills, the Lazengann primarily uses long, thin drills that can change angles in mid-extension. Its spiral color is red, unlike the green of the Lagann's, and its spiral gauge within the cockpit rotates counterclockwise when filling, rather than clockwise. The Lazengann is black, with a tail used for attack, a horned helmet, and a mouthplate on the chest armor. It can transform its entire lower body into a gigantic drill (the Gurren-Lagann does the same, when docking with the Arc-Gurren). From an out of series perspective, its silhouette from the side bears a strong likeness to the [[Evangelion (mecha)#Evangelion Unit 01 (Shogōki: 初号機)|EVA-01]] unit from [[Neon Genesis Evangelion franchise|Neon Genesis Evangelion]], another Gainax production. Notably, where Lazengann had one horn, Gurren Lagann had two.

===Dekabutsu===

After the defeat of Guame and Cytomander, the capital city, Teppelin, shed the towers surrounding it to reveal it was in fact a Dai-Gunman, '''Dekabatsu'''. It is extremely bulky, and has a very uncomplicated humanoid shape. Extremely powerful, it was able to stop the Gurren-Lagann's drilling power. On one arm it has a hand, whilst the other has a giant hammer, and it can deploy a vast amount of Gunmen. Like the Arc-Gurren-Lagann, it was designed to be piloted by a normal-sized Gunmen - in this instance, the Lazengann, with Lord Genome's throne directly above it. It was stopped upon the defeat of the Spiral King, automatically shutting down and collapsed. After the seven-year timeskip, it is the capitol building for Kamina City. Half of its head was destroyed when the Anti-Spirals attacked. In Parallel Works 8, it is shown to be able to dock with Super Galaxy Gurren-Lagann in the same way as the Arc Gurren-Lagann did. Also, the tower on top of Dekatbutsu's head was where the Lazengann docks with it. It can be assumed that, after Lazengann docked with Dekabutsu, the tower was constructed around it. The tower also provides a unique interface, allowing Lord Genome to control the entire Space Gunman without needing to be inside Lazengann. The Dekabutsu itself seems to project energy to all allied Gunman, as normally beastmen piloted Gunman are unable to function during the night (the notable exception was during the battle of Teppelin) and the fact that all beastmen Gunman shut down right after Lord Genome's defeat.

==Anti-Spirals==
When the Anti-Spirals begin their attack on the Earth once its human population reached one million, they used mecha that are evidence of the their superior technology ranging from actual mecha to virtual-based ones like the Mugann. Compared to the Gunman and other earth-based mecha, the Anti-Spirals' mecha are each a giant in its right and follow a Hinduist-theme.
{{-}}

===Mugann===
As the human population on Earth reached one million, the Anti-Spiralized Nia began to mentally materialize these virtual weapons out of thin air that start destroying everything with high-tech weaponry, such as a massive laser that obliterates anything it makes contact with. After the first one appeared, these mecha were codenamed '''Mugann''' (from 無顔, meaning &quot;faceless&quot;) by the human forces, because it does not have a face.
They're three types of Mugann that appeared over the series, the soldier class, the black and green '''Jokyu-Mugann''' that acts in deploying and coordinating the attacks of multiple Mugann units, and the two Giant Cage Mugann that attack by separating into smaller pieces and reforming around the target, enveloping it and attacking from all sides or combine into a larger Mugann unit that mostly attacks using its body as projectiles before being destroyed by Arc-Gurren Lagann.

All three types have almost impenetrable energy shield which can deflect bullets and other solid weaponry, however, its defenses and attacks are not enough to stand up to the Gurren-Lagann, which managed to defend against its attacks and drill through the mecha during its initial appearance with the Giga Drill Break. However, unlike normal Gunmen that simply explode or break-down when dealt a fatal blow, these mecha turn into small explosives that devastate anything nearby, causing almost as much damage as the Mugann itself can cause. This is a result of the mecha's unstable molecular structure which also enables it to easily teleport itself through long distances. 

A technique created by Simon to effectively defeat the Mugann without causing damage is by harnessing their lasers' power using the Gurren-Lagann and delivering it back to them all at once, destroying their body, and then shooting down every single explosive they left with the Grapearl force's handguns before they fall into the ground. However, it's also known that this measure could be troublesome against larger numbers of Mugann. Later, Leeron creates a technique where Grapearls can both penetrate the Mugann defenses and create a shield around it, meaning the Mugann can both be destroyed and have its small bombs rendered harmless.

When Nia was recalled, the Mugann stopped attacking Kamina City. The Mugann are the only 3D-animated mechas used in the series.

===Ashtanga===
The {{Nihongo|'''[[Raja Yoga|Ashtanga Class]]'''|アシュタンガ級|Ashutanga Kyū}} are two dreadnaut ships which are encountered by Team Dai-Gurren in space, resembling large, rocky, and roughly spherical, covered with multiple stone faces. They can form a powerful energy barrier that not even the Arc-Gurren Lagann could pierce with its drill. Though there has yet to be any indication of their actual size, they are clearly shown to be many times larger than the planets around them, even throwing the planets as projectiles against the Super Galaxy Gurren-Lagann before it destroyed them both.  In Parallel Works 8, a ship in their class a great distance from the Earth appears visibly larger than the moon.

The Ashtangas' design were created by manga artist, [[Hirohiko Araki]]. {{Citation needed|date=July 2007}}

===Mass-Produced Anti-Spiral Mecha===

These space-faring machines that emerge from the Ashtanga come in three shapes: the foot-like {{Nihongo|'''[[Pada (Hindu mythology)|Pada Class]]'''|パダ級|Pada Kyū}}, the hand-shaped {{Nihongo|'''Hastagurai Class'''|ハスタグライ級|Hasutagurai Kyū}} and a rocket with a foresection that resembles a set of teeth. At first glance, they appear to be weaker than the Mugann, but were faking until their trap is about to spring, revealing to be much stronger than Team Dai-Gurren initially thought. After revealing their true power, they were able to destroy a number of Dai-Gurren Gunmen and their pilots, though the Space Twin Bokken's massive explosion managed to take out the bulk of the armada with the surviving Dai-Gunman destroying the rest when they attempted to force the Super-Galactic Dai-Gurren deeper into the Galactic Spiral Abyss. Several of these are seen fighting against the Lazengann in Parallel Works 8, with some models that resemble the angels from Neon Genesis Evangelion. As the Anti-Spirals having already sealed themselves on their world, it can be assumed that these are autonomous robots controlled by the Anti-Spiral avatar.

===Granzeboma===
{{Nihongo|'''Granzeboma'''|グランゼボーマ|Guranｚebōma}} is the mecha piloted by the Anti-Spiral, created to fight the newly formed Tengen Toppa Gurren-Lagann on even grounds, beat Team Dai-Gurren at its own game and put an end to the fight once and for all. Its styling is similar to the Tengen Toppa Gurren-Lagann, with the Anti-Spiral home world as its core on its forehead and an extra pair of arms, located on its shoulders, which it used to catch the galaxies as well as execute its '''Infinity [[Big-Bang]] Storm''' attack, crushing two galaxies together and producing a blast powerful enough to create and destroy entire universes, in order to instantly vaporize the target; according to Leeron, the attack has the &quot;energy capable of creating universes.&quot; Though the attack was intended to annihilate Team Dai-Gurren, the maneuver backfired when Lordgenome used the Lazengann to take the blast, converting it and himself into Spiral Energy, through quantum division, for the Tengen Toppa Gurren-Lagann. It was ultimately destroyed when Simon and Nia managed to pierce its pilot's body with the Lagann's drill, using the Lagann Impact.

Notably, the Granzeboma's arms were in fact able to transform into drills, normally a symbol of Spiral Beings - however, when they are shown stationary, the drills in fact have entirely straight lines from base to tip, making them spinning lances more than anything else.

===Super Granzeboma===
The Super Granzeboma is the largest and final form of the Grand Zaboma. It appears only in the second movie of the series, titled Lagann-Hen [Ragan-Hen]. The Super Granzeboma is similar to its previous form but with its size and power being equivalent to the Super Tengen Toppa Gurren Lagann. During the short battle involving this form, its powerful Anti-Spiral Giga Drill Break collides with a similar and equal attack from the Super Tengen Toppa Gurren Lagann, causing the entire universe the fight took place in to collapse on itself as a side effect caused by the ripples from their drills. A moment later, the Super Granzeboma shattered the Super Tengen Toppa Giga Drill, proceeding to do the same to the Tengen Toppa Giga Drill, then the latter slowly downgrades until once again reaching simply Gurren Lagann, which alone gains enough power to destroy the massive Giga Drill created by the Super Grand Zaboma.

Unlike the Super Tengen Toppa Gurren Lagann, where each previous form was inside from smallest (Gurren Lagann) to largest (Tengen Toppa Gurren Lagann), the Super Granzeboma wears the Granzeboma like a crown, just as the previous incarnation wears the Anti-Spiral Homeworld on its head. In the end, the Super Granzeboma is defeated by Simon alone, without his Lagann; Simon finds his way onto the Anti-Spiral homeworld within the Super Granzeboma, engages the Anti-Spiral in a fist fight, and uses some of his own blood to create a drill powerful enough to defeat the Anti-Spiral.

==References==
{{reflist}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Gurren Lagann, Tengen Toppa}}
[[Category:Mecha]]
[[Category:Super Robots]]

[[ja:天元突破グレンラガンの登場兵器]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
