<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="11787168" ns="0" title="Ceedo"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Multiple issues|advert=September 2008|refimprove=September 2008}}

{{Infobox Company 
| company_name     = Ceedo Technologies (2005) Ltd.
| company_type     = [[Private company|Private]]
| foundation       = 2005
| location_city    =  [[Rosh Haayin, Israel]]
| key_people       = Dror Wettenstein, Founder;&lt;br /&gt;Joel Fisch, Chairman
| industry         = [[Computer software]]
| products         = Ceedo Personal, Ceedo Enterprise, Ceedo Client Management System
| homepage         = [http://www.ceedo.com www.ceedo.com]
}}

'''Ceedo''' is a software virtualization platform developed by Israeli company Ceedo Technologies. The term &quot;Ceedo&quot; refers both to the company and to the virtual workspace client on which the company's products are based.

Based in Rosh Haayin, Israel, Ceedo Technologies was founded in 2005 by Dror Wettenstein, and its first product, Ceedo Personal, was released shortly after. Ceedo has released additional products based on its virtualization technology, including Ceedo Enterprise and Ceedo Mobile.

Ceedo has several patents pending for its virtualization technology.

== Ceedo Personal ==
{{Advert|section|date=June 2010}}

{{Infobox software
 | name                   = Ceedo Personal
 | logo                   = &lt;!-- [[File: ]] --&gt;
 | screenshot             = 
 | caption                = Ceedo Personal
 | collapsible            = 
 | author                 = 
 | developer              = Ceedo
 | released               = 
 | discontinued           = 
 | latest release version = 
 | latest release date    = 
 | latest preview version = 
 | latest preview date    = 
 | frequently updated     = 
 | programming language   = 
 | operating system       = Windows 2000, XP, Vista, 7
 | platform               = 
 | size                   = 
 | language               = English, French, German, Italian, Spanish, Chinese, Japanese, Korean, Hebrew, Russian, Portuguese, Romanian, Serbian, Norwegian
 | status                 = current
 | genre                  = [[application virtualization]]
 | license                = commercial / closed source
 | website                = http://www.ceedo.com/products/ceedo-personal.html
}}

Ceedo Personal works like a portable operating system by allowing users to carry applications on portable media such as [[USB flash drive]]s and [[pocket hard drive]]s, running them inside a virtual environment. Using a simple interface called the Easy Access Menu, which resembles the Windows Start Menu, users can install standard Windows applications and use them whenever they plug their storage device into a host computer. Since applications running under the Ceedo environment are separate from the host computer, there is no trace left behind once the user disconnects the device.

Ceedo Personal has a variety of popular software applications available to download from its Programs Directory. In addition, Ceedo sells an add-on product called Argo Application Installer that allows the user to install standard Windows application to their Ceedo device that are not available in the Programs Directory.

=== Technology ===

Ceedo Personal uses application virtualization to enable applications to run from a portable device while using resources from the host PC (screen, processing power, drives, internet connection, printers, etc.) The Ceedo client launches the applications’ in an independent environment, allowing them to run regardless of the specific settings of the host computer.

=== Portable Storage Devices ===

Ceedo Personal has been licensed by consumer storage vendors including Lexar&lt;ref&gt;&quot;A Flash Drive That Holds Your Computer&quot;, David Pogue, New York Times: http://www.nytimes.com/2006/06/15/technology/15pogue.html?pagewanted=all&lt;/ref&gt;, Seagate&lt;ref&gt;Seagate FreeAgent Go 160 GB - Review Tom's Hardware: http://www.tomshardware.com/reviews/external-hdd-spring-fever,1582-5.html&lt;/ref&gt;, Verbatim, Maxell, ExcelStor, Venzero and others to add value to their portable storage devices. The product has been pre-bundled on millions of devices and is sold worldwide.

=== Comparison to U3 ===

Ceedo Personal has often been compared to another product, [[U3]], that is similar in both appearance and functionality. However, a key difference between U3 and Ceedo is that Ceedo does not require Windows applications to be modified in order for them to be allowed to be carried on the portable device.

== Ceedo Enterprise ==

{{Infobox software
 | name                   = Ceedo Enterprise
 | logo                   = &lt;!-- [[File: ]] --&gt;
 | screenshot             = 
 | caption                = Ceedo Personal
 | collapsible            = 
 | author                 = 
 | developer              = Ceedo
 | released               = 
 | discontinued           = 
 | latest release version = 
 | latest release date    = 
 | latest preview version = 
 | latest preview date    = 
 | frequently updated     = 
 | programming language   = 
 | operating system       = Windows 2000, XP, Vista, 7
 | platform               = 
 | size                   = 
 | language               = English, French, German, Italian, Spanish, Chinese, Japanese, Korean, Hebrew, Russian, Portuguese, Romanian, Serbian, Norwegian
 | status                 = current
 | genre                  = [[application virtualization]]
 | license                = commercial / closed source
 | website                = http://www.ceedo.com/products/ceedo-enterprise.html
}}

Introduced in 2008&lt;ref&gt;Ceedo Enterprise announcement: http://www.ceedo.com/company/jun-6-2008-ceedo-launches-an-application-virtualization-solution-for-the-enterprise.html&lt;/ref&gt;, Ceedo Enterprise is a version of Ceedo's virtual workspace that is designed for business use and includes remote management capabilities.

Unlike Ceedo Personal, Ceedo Enterprise is designed to be carried primarily on encrypted hardware and it can be customized and pre-configured for corporate customers. It is integrated with a back-end called Ceedo Client Management System (CCMS).

=== CCMS ===

Using CCMS, Ceedo Enterprise Client workspaces can be remotely managed. An IT administrator may want to change policies, update remove or install new software applications, apply patches or perform other operations. These client updates can be performed simultaneously and remotely and apply to the Ceedo Clients in the field.

Some of the capabilities of CCMS include:

* Updating Ceedo software
* Updating installed applications
* Installing new applications
* Removing applications
* Modifying client settings
* Adding or removing files and data

=== Ceedo and Citrix ===

Ceedo and Citrix partnered in 2008 to create a portable version of the [[Citrix]] [[XenApp]] client.&lt;ref&gt;Ceedo and Citrix announcement: http://www.ceedo.com/company/aug-05-2008-ceedo-announces-ceedo-enterprise-for-citrix-xenapp.html&lt;/ref&gt;

==See also==
* [[Application Virtualization]]
* [[Portable Application]]
* [[List of portable software]]
* [[Comparison of application launchers]]
* [[Portable application creators]]
* [[Windows To Go]]
* [[U3]]

==External links==
* [http://www.ceedo.com/ Ceedo.com - Official site]
* [http://www.mobility-office.com/ Mobility-Office.com - Official site of Mobility Office]

==References==

&lt;references/&gt;

[[Category:Windows software]]
[[Category:Portable software]]
[[Category:Portable software suites]]
[[Category:Software companies of Israel]]

[[ru:Ceedo]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
