<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="1178458" ns="0" title="Flickr"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Infobox Website
|name          =Flickr
|favicon       =
|logo          =[[File:Flickr wordmark.svg|200px]]
|screenshot    =&lt;!-- Deleted image removed: [[Image:Flickr.jpg|250px|{{deletable image-caption|1=Saturday, 29 March 2008}}]] --&gt;
|caption       =
|url           =[http://www.flickr.com/ flickr.com]
|alexa         ={{decrease}} 35 ({{as of|2011|11|2|alt=November 2011}})&lt;ref name=&quot;alexa&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url= http://www.alexa.com/siteinfo/Flickr.com |title= Flickr.com Site Info | publisher= [[Alexa Internet]] |accessdate= 2011-11-02 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;!--Updated monthly by OKBot.--&gt;
|commercial    =Yes
|type          =[[Photo sharing|Photo]]/[[Video hosting service]]
|registration  =Yes
|owner         =[[Yahoo! Inc.]]
|language      =[[Standard Cantonese|Chinese]] (traditional)&lt;br&gt;[[English language|English]] (original)&lt;br&gt;[[French language|French]] &lt;br&gt;[[German language|German]]&lt;br&gt;[[Indonesian language|Indonesia]]&lt;br&gt;[[Italian language|Italian]]&lt;br&gt;[[Korean language|Korean]]&lt;br&gt;[[Portuguese language|Portuguese]] (Brazilian)&lt;br&gt;[[Spanish language|Spanish]]&lt;br&gt;[[Vietnamese language|Vietnamese]]
|author        =Ludicorp
|launch date   =February 2004
|current status=Active
}}

'''Flickr''' is an [[image hosting service|image hosting]] and [[video hosting service|video hosting]] website, [[web services]] suite, and [[online community]] that was created by Ludicorp in 2004 and acquired by [[Yahoo!]] in 2005. In addition to being a popular website for users to share and embed personal photographs, the service is widely used by [[blog]]gers to host images that they embed in blogs and [[social media]].&lt;ref name=&quot;flickr-photo-use-by-bloggers&quot;&gt;{{cite news|first=Daniel|last=Terdiman|title=Photo Site a Hit With Bloggers|url=http://www.wired.com/culture/lifestyle/news/2004/12/65958|quote=Flickr enables users to post photos from nearly any camera phone or directly from a PC. It also allows users to post photos from their accounts or from their cameras to most widely used blog services. The result is that an increasing number of bloggers are regularly posting photos from their Flickr accounts.|publisher=[[Wired (magazine)|Wired]]| authorlink=Daniel Terdiman|date=2004-12-09|accessdate=28 August 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt; Yahoo reported in June 2011 that Flickr had a total of 51 million registered members and 80 million unique visitors.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://advertising.yahoo.com/products-solutions/flickr.html|title=Flickr - Advertising Solution|publisher=Yahoo!|date=After June 2011|accessdate=20 September 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; In August 2011 the site reported that it was hosting more than 6 billion images and this number continues to grow steadily according to reporting sources.&lt;ref&gt;[http://news.softpedia.com/newsImage/Flickr-Boasts-6-Billion-Photo-Uploads-2.jpg/] from Flickr Blog&lt;/ref&gt; Photos and videos can be accessed from Flickr without the need to register an account but an account must be made in order to upload content onto the website. Registering an account also allows users to create a profile page containing photos and videos that the user has uploaded and also grants the ability to add another Flickr user as a contact. For mobile users, Flickr has an [[Application software|official app]] for [[iPhone]],&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Official flickr app for iPhone|url=http://itunes.apple.com/us/app/flickr/id328407587?mt=8}}&lt;/ref&gt; for [[Windows Phone 7]], and for [[Android (operating system)|Android]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Official flickr app for Android|url=http://www.flickr.com/android}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==History==
[[File:Photowalk gnangarra 02.jpg|thumb|A [[Photowalking|photowalk]] by the Flickr Group &quot;Photographers in Perth&quot; around [[Guildford, Western Australia]]]]
Flickr was launched in February 2004 by Ludicorp, a [[Vancouver]]-based company founded by [[Stewart Butterfield]] and [[Caterina Fake]]. The service emerged out of tools originally created for Ludicorp's ''Game Neverending'', a web-based [[massively multiplayer online game]]. Flickr proved a more feasible project, and ultimately ''Game Neverending'' was shelved;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|last=Graham|first=Jefferson|title=Flickr of idea on a gaming project led to photo website|work=[[USA Today]]|date=27 February 2006|url=http://www.usatoday.com/tech/products/2006-02-27-flickr_x.htm|accessdate=4 September 2006}}&lt;/ref&gt; however, Butterfield has since launched an online game of similar intent.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.fastcompany.com/1783127/can-a-game-that-wants-you-to-play-nice-become-a-blockbuster|title=A Flickr Founder's Glitch: Can A Game That Wants You To Play Nice Be A Blockbuster?|publisher=Fast Company|date=27 September 2011|accessdate=30 September 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title=Vancouver’s Tiny Speck puts massively multiplayer game Glitch online|publisher=Vancouver Sun|date=28 February 2011|url=http://blogs.vancouversun.com/2011/09/27/vancouvers-tiny-speck-puts-massively-multiplayer-game-glitch-online/|accessdate=30 September 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Early versions of Flickr focused on a multiuser [[chat room]] called FlickrLive with real-time photo exchange capabilities. The successive evolutions focused more on the uploading and filing backend for individual users and the chat room was buried in the site map. It was eventually dropped as Flickr's backend systems evolved away from the Game Neverending's codebase.

Some of the key features of Flickr not initially present were [[tag (metadata)|tags]], marking photos as favorites, group photo pools and interestingness, for which a [[patent pending|patent is pending]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://appft1.uspto.gov/netacgi/nph-Parser?Sect1=PTO1&amp;Sect2=HITOFF&amp;d=PG01&amp;p=1&amp;u=/netahtml/PTO/srchnum.html&amp;r=1&amp;f=G&amp;l=50&amp;s1=%2220060242139%22.PGNR.&amp;OS=DN/20060242139&amp;RS=DN/20060242139| title=US Patent Application 20060242139: Interestingness ranking of media objects|work=Butterfield; Daniel S. ; et al.|date=26 October 2006|accessdate=21 January 2007}}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Yahoo!]] acquired Ludicorp and Flickr in March 2005. The reported acquisition cost was $35 million.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.nytimes.com/2011/01/31/technology/31flickr.html|work=The New York Times|first=Verne G.|last=Kopytoff|title=At Flickr, Fending Off Rumors and Facebook|date=30 January 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; During the week of June 26 – July 2, 2005, all content was migrated from servers in Canada to servers in the United States, resulting in all data becoming subject to [[Law of the United States|United States federal law]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Data moving to U.S. very soon!|work=Flickr|date=10 June 2005|url = http://www.flickr.com/forums/help/8280/|accessdate=4 September 2006}}&lt;/ref&gt;

On May 16, 2006, Flickr updated its services from [[Development stage#Beta|beta]] to &quot;gamma&quot;, along with a design and structural overhaul. According to the site's [[FAQ]], the term &quot;gamma&quot;, rarely used in software development, is intended to be tongue-in-cheek to indicate that the service is always being tested by its users, and is in a state of perpetual improvement.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=What does Flickr Gamma mean?|work=Flickr|url=http://flickr.com/help/general/#167|accessdate=4 September 2006}}&lt;/ref&gt; A further connotation, more specific to photography and the display of images, is that of [[gamma correction]]. The current service is considered a stable release.

In December 2006, upload limits on free accounts were increased to 100&amp;nbsp;MB a month (from 20&amp;nbsp;MB) and were removed from Pro Accounts, permitting unlimited uploads for holders of these accounts (originally a 2&amp;nbsp;GB per month limit).&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=How many photos can I upload for free?|work=Flickr|url=http://www.flickr.com/help/limits/|accessdate=16 May 2007}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In January 2007, Flickr announced that &quot;Old Skool&quot; members—those who had joined before the Yahoo acquisition—would be required to associate their account with a Yahoo ID by March 15 to continue using the service.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Yahoo! IDs, signing in and screen names|work=Flickr|url=http://flickr.com/help/signin/|accessdate=1 February 2007}}&lt;/ref&gt; This move was criticized by some users.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title=Flickr to require Yahoo usernames|work=BBC News|url=http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/technology/6316761.stm|date=1 February 2007|accessdate=15 June 2007}}&lt;/ref&gt;

On April 9, 2008, Flickr began allowing paid subscribers to upload videos, limited to 90 seconds in length and 150&amp;nbsp;MB in size. On March 2, 2009, Flickr added the facility to upload and view [[HD video]]s, and began allowing free users to upload normal-resolution video. At the same time, the set limit for free accounts was lifted.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Video for all + HD!|work=Flickr|url=http://blog.flickr.net/en/2009/03/02/video-for-all-hd/|accessdate=11 April 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In May 2009, [[White House]] official photographer [[Pete Souza]] began using Flickr as a conduit for releasing White House photos. The photos were initially posted with a [[Creative Commons Attribution]] license requiring that the original photographers be credited. Flickr later created a new license which identified them as &quot;United States Government Work&quot;, which does not carry any copyright restrictions.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.wired.com/epicenter/2009/05/flickr-creates-new-license-for-white-house-photos/ Flickr Creates New License for White House Photos - wired.com - 11 May 2009]&lt;/ref&gt; The photos are posted with this disclaimer: &quot;This official White House photograph is being made available only for publication by news organizations and/or for personal use printing by the subject(s) of the photograph. The photograph may not be manipulated in any way and may not be used in commercial or political materials, advertisements, emails, products, promotions that in any way suggests approval or endorsement of the President, the First Family, or the White House.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.flickr.com/photos/whitehouse/ Flickr White House photostream - flickr.com - Retrieved January 4, 2009]&lt;/ref&gt;

===Yahoo! Photos===
Yahoo! Photos had unlimited storage for photos, but it was required that photos have the [[JPEG|jpeg/jpg]] extension. Users were able to create individual photo albums, categorize their photos and place them in the corresponding albums. Users were also able to set access of their albums by publishing them for the viewing pleasure of everyone, disabling access, or marking them as private folders for their own viewing. In an effort to make it simpler and more efficient, Yahoo had an uploader tool to drag and drop the pictures from one's computer to Yahoo! Photos [[web page]]. In March 2005 Yahoo! purchased Flickr, and in May 2007 announced that Yahoo! Photos would be closed down on September 20, 2007 at 9 p.m. PDT, after which all photos would be deleted.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title=Yahoo Photos going dark as Flickr shines on|work=USAToday|url=http://www.usatoday.com/tech/webguide/2007-05-03-yahoo-photos-flickr_N.htm|accessdate=30 May 2007|first=Jefferson|last=Graham|date=4 May 2007}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://yodel.yahoo.com/2007/06/13/give-your-photos-the-fun-of-flickr/ Yodel Anecdotal » Blog Archive » Give your Photos the fun of Flickr]&lt;/ref&gt; During the interim, users had the ability to migrate their photos to Flickr or other services (including [[Shutterfly]], [[Kodak Gallery]], [[Snapfish]], and [[Photobucket]]). All who migrated to Flickr were given three months of a Flickr Pro account.

On 16 June 2007, Yahoo! Photos issued a press release stating that its service would end on 20 September, in order to focus the company's efforts on Flickr.
*March 2000: Yahoo! Photos launched
*Summer 2002:Flickr launched
*29 March 2005: Yahoo bought Flickr (and the company which launched it)
*14 January 2007: Yahoo! Photos updated its site with new features, including free full-resolution downloads from ISPs that have partnerships with Yahoo&lt;ref&gt;[http://help.yahoo.com/l/us/yahoo/photos/photos2/basics/basics-15.html Halp.yahoo.com]&lt;/ref&gt;
*3 May 2007: An informal announcement&lt;ref&gt;[http://blog.wired.com/monkeybites/2007/05/yahoo_shutters_.html Blog.wired.com]&lt;/ref&gt; was made that Yahoo! Photo would be ended&lt;ref&gt;''[[USA Today]]'' reports:
&quot;Yahoo Photos will be shut down by the fall. Users will be directed over a three-month period to transfer their images to Flickr or other photo sites such as Multiply, Shutterfly, Kodak Gallery, Snapfish or Photobucket. Yahoo says it will make the transition easy, with a one-click transfer&quot; process.&quot; [http://www.usatoday.com/tech/webguide/2007-05-03-yahoo-photos-flickr_N.htm USAtoday.com]&lt;/ref&gt;
*June 2007: Yahoo! photos ceased to accept new accounts or allow users to upload photos
*20 September 2007: Yahoo! Photos shuts down. Users in India were terminated on 18 October; users in Australia were terminated on 19 October. Users could follow a link to transfer their photos to one of five providers automatically: Flickr, [[Shutterfly]], [[Photobucket]], [[Snapfish]], or [[Kodak Gallery]].
*18-19 October: Yahoo! Photos shut down for Indian and Australian users and all photos and accounts were deleted.

===Corporate changes===
In June 2008, Flickr co-founder [[Stewart Butterfield]] announced his resignation following his wife and co-founder [[Caterina Fake]], who left the company on June 13, 2008.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.techcrunch.com/2008/06/17/flickr-co-founders-join-mass-exodus-from-yahoo/ Flickr Co-founders Join Mass Exodus From Yahoo]&lt;/ref&gt; Butterfield wrote a humorous resignation letter to [[Brad Garlinghouse]] in which he stated that he was an old tin man in a new age.&lt;ref&gt;[http://valleywag.com/5017424/stewart-butterfields-bizarre-resignation-letter-to-yahoo Stewart Butterfield's bizarre resignation letter to Yahoo] from valleywag.com&lt;/ref&gt;

On December 11, 2008, ''[[The Guardian]]'' reported that three employees had been laid off as Yahoo continued to reduce its workforce.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|last=Johnson|first=Bobbie|url=http://www.guardian.co.uk/technology/blog/2008/dec/11/yahoo-flickr-layoffs|title=Now Flickr is hit by Yahoo layoffs &amp;#124; Technology &amp;#124; guardian.co.uk|publisher=Guardian|date=11 December 2008|accessdate=16 March 2010|location=London}}&lt;/ref&gt;

On November 30, 2010 ''[[CNET]]'' reported Yahoo was on the verge of a major layoff affecting 10%-20% of its workforce. Flickr was specifically named as a target for these layoffs.&lt;ref&gt;[http://news.cnet.com/8301-13577_3-20024161-36.html Yahoo said to be rolling out layoffs|The Social - CNET News]&lt;/ref&gt;

==Features==
===Accounts===
Flickr offers two types of accounts, Free and Pro.
Free account users are allowed to upload 300 MB of images and two videos per month. If a free user has more than 200 photos on the site, they will only be able to see the most recent 200 in their photostream. The other photos that were uploaded are still stored on the site and links to these images in blog posts remain active. Free users can also contribute any one photo to a maximum of 10 photo pools.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.flickr.com/help/groups/|title=Flickr Groups help}}&lt;/ref&gt; If a free account is inactive for 90 consecutive days, Flickr reserves the right to delete it.&lt;ref name=free&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.flickr.com/help/limits/|quote=Note: If your free account is inactive for 90 consecutive days, it may be deleted. ...|title=Help: Free Accounts, Upgrading and Gifts|publisher=Flickr|accessdate=16 March 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; For a free account, no one (including the account owner) can access the original file. If the account is upgraded to a pro account, then the original files are available for download.

Pro accounts allow users to upload an unlimited number of images and videos every month and receive unlimited bandwidth and storage. Photos may be placed in up to 60 group pools, and Pro account users receive ad-free browsing and have access to account statistics. As soon as a Pro account expires, it reverts to the restrictions of a free account, including Flickr's right to delete an account that is &quot;inactive for 90 consecutive days&quot;.&lt;ref name=free/&gt; Flickr may delete a Pro account without giving any reason nor warning to the account's owner.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://thomashawk.com/2011/01/deepa-pravens-protest-after-flickr-deletes-his-paid-pro-account-without-warning-or-explanation.html|title=Deepa Praven’s Protest After Flickr Deletes Her Paid Pro Account Without Warning or Explanation|author=Hawk, Thomas|date=11 January 2011|accessdate=5 March 2011}}{{cite web|url=http://www.socialphototalk.com/flickr-permanently-deletes-yet-another-user-without-warning/|title=Flickr Permanently Deletes Yet Another User Without Warning|date=30 April 2005|accessdate=5 March 2011}}{{cite web|url= http://www.foto-biz.com/Biz/Flickr-screw-your-customers|title=Flickr or How to Screw Your Customers|author=Ritch, Syv|date=3 February 2011|accessdate=5 March 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Organization ===
[[Image:Screenshot-HotTags-Flickr.png|right|thumb|A screenshot of hot tags on Flickr]]
Flickr asks photo submitters to organize images using [[tag (metadata)|tags]] (a form of [[metadata (computing)|metadata]]), which enable searchers to find images related to particular topics, such as place names or subject matter. Flickr was also an early website to implement [[tag cloud]]s, which provide access to images tagged with the most popular keywords. Because of its support for tags, Flickr has been cited as a prime example of effective use of [[folksonomy]], although [[Thomas Vander Wal]] suggested that Flickr is not the best example.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last=Vander Wal|first=Thomas|authorlink=Thomas Vander Wal|title=Folksonomy Research Needs Cleaning Up|date=17 January 2006|url=http://www.vanderwal.net/random/entrysel.php?blog=1781|accessdate=4 September 2006}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Flickr also enables users to organize their photos into &quot;sets&quot;, or groups of photos that fall under the same heading. Sets can be displayed as a slideshow and shared by embedding them in websites. However, sets are more flexible than the traditional folder-based method of organizing files, as one photo can belong to one set, many sets, or none at all. Flickr's &quot;sets&quot; represent a form of categorical [[metadata (computing)|metadata]] rather than a physical hierarchy. [[Geotagging]] can be applied to photos in set.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.gossinteractive.com/flickrsets|title=Creating Flickr sets video|publisher=[[Goss Interactive]]|date=26 February 2010|accessdate=26 February 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; Any sets with geotagging can be related to a map using imapflicker. The resulting map can be embedded in a website.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.gossinteractive.com/flickrmap|title=Mapping Flickr sets video|publisher=Goss Interactive|date=26 February 2010|accessdate=26 February 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; Sets may be grouped into &quot;collections&quot;, and collections further grouped into higher-order collections.

Flickr offers a fairly comprehensive web-service API that enables programmers to create applications that can perform almost any function that a user on the Flickr site can do.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.flickr.com/services/api/ API Documentation] from Flickr&lt;/ref&gt;

===Organizr===
Organizr is a [[web application]] for organizing photos within a Flickr account that can be accessed through the Flickr interface. It allows users to modify tags, descriptions, and set groupings, and to place photos on a world map (a feature provided in conjunction with [[Yahoo! Maps]]). It uses [[Ajax (programming)|Ajax]] to emulate the look, feel, and quick functionality of desktop-based photo-management applications, such as Google's [[Picasa]] and [[F-Spot]]. Users can select and apply changes to multiple photos at a time, making it a better tool for batch editing than the standard Flickr interface.

===Picnik===
Flickr has a partnership with the [[Picnik]] online photo-editing application that includes a reduced-feature version of Picnik built into Flickr as a default photo editor.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://blog.flickr.net/en/2007/12/05/edit-your-photos-on-flickr/|title=Edit your photos! On Flickr!|publisher=Flickr|date=5 December 2007|accessdate=1 October 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Access control===
Flickr provides both private and public image storage. A user uploading an image can set privacy controls that determine who can view the image. A photo can be flagged as either public or private.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.flickr.com/help/privacy/|title=Public/Private|publisher=Flickr|accessdate=1 October 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; Private images are visible by default only to the uploader, but they can also be marked as viewable by friends and/or family. Privacy settings also can be decided by adding photographs from a user's photostream to a &quot;group pool&quot;. If a group is private all the members of that group can see the photo. If a group is public the photo becomes public as well. Flickr also provides a &quot;contact list&quot; which can be used to control image access for a specific set of users in a way similar to that of [[LiveJournal]].

In November 2006 Flickr created a &quot;guest pass&quot; system that allows private photos to be shared with non-Flickr members. A person could e-mail this pass to parents who may not have an account to allow them to see the photos otherwise restricted from public view. This setting allows sets to be shared, or all photos under a certain privacy category (friends or family) to be shared.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.flickr.com/help/guestpass/|title=Guest Pass|publisher=Flickr|accessdate=1 October 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Many members allow their photos to be viewed by anyone, forming a large collaborative [[database]] of categorized photos. By default, other members can leave comments about any image they have permission to view, and in many cases can add to the list of tags associated with an image.

===Interaction and compatibility===
Flickr's functionality includes [[RSS (file format)|RSS]] and [[Atom (standard)|Atom]] feeds and an [[application programming interface|API]] that enables independent programmers to expand its services. This includes a large number of third-party [[Greasemonkey]] scripts which enhance and extend the functionality of the Flickr site. In 2006 Flickr was the second most Greasemonkey-extended site.&lt;ref&gt;[http://blog.flickr.net/en/2006/08/27/flickr-and-greasemonkey/ Flickr and Greasemonkey « Flickr Blog]&lt;/ref&gt;

The core functionality of the site relies on standard [[HTML]] and [[HyperText Transfer Protocol|HTTP]] features, allowing for wide compatibility among [[Operating system|platforms]] and [[Web browser|browsers]]. Organizr uses [[Ajax (programming)|Ajax]], with which most modern browsers are compliant, and most of Flickr's other text-editing and tagging interfaces also possess Ajax functionality.

Images can be posted to the user's photostream via email attachments, enabling direct uploads from many cameraphones and applications with email capabilities.

Flickr has been adopted by many web users as their primary photo storage site, especially members of the [[blog]]ging community. In addition, it is popular with [[Apple Macintosh|Macintosh]] and [[Linux]] users, who are locked out of photo-sharing sites that require Windows and [[Internet Explorer]].

Flickr uses the [[Geo (microformat)|Geo microformat]] on the pages for over 3 million [[geotagging|geotagged]] images.&lt;ref name=&quot;uFwiki&quot;&gt;[http://microformats.org/wiki/geo#Examples_in_the_wild Geo examples, in the wild]&lt;/ref&gt;
{{Infobox software
|name                  =Flickr Uploadr
|logo                  =
|screenshot            =[[Image:FlickrUploadr.png]]
|image_size            =64px
|caption               =
|developer             =[[Yahoo Inc.]]
|latest_release_version=3.2.1
|latest_release_date   =11 June 2009
|operating_system      =[[Mac OS X]], [[Windows 7]], [[Windows Vista|Vista]] &amp; [[Windows XP|XP]]
|license               =[[GPL]]
|website               =http://www.flickr.com/tools/
}}
Flickr has entered into partnerships with third parties to offer printing of various forms of merchandise, including business cards, photo books, stationery, personalized credit cards, and large-size prints, from companies such as [[Moo (company)|Moo]], [[Blurb.com|Blurb]], [[Tiny Prints]], [[Capital One]], [[Imagekind]], and [[QOOP]]. In addition, Flickr has partnered with [[Getty Images]] to sell stock photos from some users.&lt;ref&gt;[http://mashable.com/2009/03/11/getty-images-flickr-collection/ Flickr Photos Become Stock Photography at Getty Images] from mashable.com. Retrieved 18 May 2009&lt;/ref&gt;

Users of [[Windows Live Photo Gallery]], Apple's [[iPhoto]] (version 8), Adobe's Lightroom 3.2 and Apple's [[Aperture (photography software)|Aperture]] (version 3.0) have the ability to upload their photos directly to Flickr.

Flickr provides a desktop client for [[Mac OS X]] and Windows that allows users to upload photos without using the web interface. Uploadr allows drag-and-drop batch uploading of photos, the setting of tags and descriptions for each batch, and the editing of privacy settings.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.flickr.com/tools/|title=Flickr Uploader|publisher=Flickr|accessdate=01 October 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Filtering===
In March 2007 Flickr added new content filtering controls that let members specify by default what types of images they generally upload (photo, art/illustration, or [[screenshot]]) and how &quot;safe&quot; (i.e., unlikely to offend others) their images are, as well as specify that information for specific images individually.&lt;ref&gt;[http://flickr.com/help/filters/ Flickr.com / Help / FAQ / Content filters]&lt;/ref&gt; In addition, users can specify the same criteria when searching for images. There are some restrictions on searches for certain types of users: non-members must always use SafeSearch, which omits images noted as potentially offensive, while members whose Yahoo! accounts indicate that they are underage may use SafeSearch or moderate SafeSearch, but cannot turn SafeSearch off completely.

Flickr has since used this setting to change the level of accessibility to &quot;unsafe&quot; content for entire nations, including South Korea, Hong Kong, and Germany. In summer 2007, German users staged a &quot;revolt&quot; over being assigned to the user rights of a [[minor (law)|minor]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://flickr.com/help/forum/en-us/43626/ Official Topid: German SafeSearch Settings]&lt;/ref&gt; See [[#Censorship|Censorship]] below.

===Licensing===
[[File:Flickr Licenses edit.svg|thumb|250px|Breakdown of [[Creative Commons]] license use on Flickr]]
Flickr offers users the ability to either release their images under certain common usage [[license]]s or label them as &quot;[[all rights reserved]]&quot;. The licensing options primarily include the Creative Commons 2.0 attribution-based and minor content-control licenses - although jurisdiction and version-specific licenses cannot be selected. As with &quot;[[tag (metadata)|tags]]&quot;, the site allows easy searching of only those images that fall under a specific license.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Flickr: Help: Photos: How can I copyright my photos?|work=Flickr|url=http://www.flickr.com/help/photos/#87|accessdate=12 November 2007}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Map sources===
In addition to using commercial mapping data, Flickr now uses [[OpenStreetMap]] mapping for various cities; this began with Beijing during the run-up to the 2008 Olympic games. {{As of|2008|10}}, this is used for Baghdad, Beijing, Kabul, Sydney, and Tokyo.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://blog.flickr.net/en/2008/08/12/around-the-world-and-back-again/|title=Around the world and back again|publisher=blog-flickr.net|accessdate=7 November 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://blog.flickr.net/en/2008/10/30/more-cities/|title=More cities|publisher=blog-flickr.net|accessdate=7 November 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://thinkwhere.wordpress.com/2008/09/16/japan-osm-progress/|title=Japanese progress in osm. Amazing stuff!}}&lt;/ref&gt; OpenStreetMap data is collected by volunteers and is available on a CC-BY-SA 2.0 license from [[Creative Commons]].

===Account-undelete option===
In May 2011 Flickr added an option to easily reverse an account termination. This action was motivated by a very public accidental deletion of a Flickr user's account, and its very protracted restoration.&lt;ref&gt;Stephen Shankland, CNET. &quot;[http://news.cnet.com/8301-30685_3-20066857-264.html?part=rss&amp;subj=news&amp;tag=2547-1_3-0-20 Flickr adds account-undelete option].&quot;  27 May 2011. Retrieved 27 May 2011&lt;/ref&gt;

==Implementation==
According to the company, {{as of|2009|8|lc=on}} Flickr is hosted on 62 [[database]]s across 124 [[server (computing)|servers]], with about 800,000 [[user (computing)|user accounts]] per pair of servers.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.flickr.com/help/forum/en-us/100485/page6/#reply672723|title=Bad case of Hiccups!|author=Kevin Collins|publisher=Flickr|work=The Help Forum|date=16 August 2009|accessdate=18 August 2009|quote=For some of the details, we have 62 DBs across 124 servers- accounts are spread across 2 servers each. There are around 800k accounts per pair, give or take some thousand. On one of the pairs, there is a greater number of &quot;active&quot; members who populate it; stats recalculations have been taking some time longer to execute, and the database has not been happy.}}&lt;/ref&gt; Based on information compiled by highscalability.com, {{as of|2007|11|lc=on}} the [[MySQL]] databases are hosted on servers that are [[Linux]]-based (from [[RedHat]]), with a software platform that includes [[Apache HTTP Server|Apache]], [[PHP]] (with [[PEAR]] and [[Smarty]]), [[shard (database architecture)|shards]], [[Memcached]], [[Squid (software)|Squid]], [[Perl]], [[ImageMagick]], and [[Java (software platform)|Java]]; the system administration tools include [[Ganglia (software)|Ganglia]], [[SystemImager]], Subcon, and [[CVSup]].&lt;ref&gt;Todd Hoff, 14 November 2007 [http://highscalability.com/flickr-architecture Flickr Architecture]&lt;/ref&gt;

==Controversy==
===Censorship===
&lt;!-- Deleted image removed: [[File:FlickrPhotosServerBlocked.JPG|thumb|Users in mainland China could not see any images in Flickr when they log in.]] --&gt;
On 12 June 2007, in the wake of the rollout of localized language versions of the site, Flickr implemented a user-side rating system for filtering out potentially controversial photos. Simultaneously, users with accounts registered with Yahoo subsidiaries in Germany, Singapore, Hong Kong, and Korea were prevented from viewing photos rated &quot;moderate&quot; or &quot;restricted&quot; on the three-part scale used. Many Flickr users, particularly in Germany, protested against the new restrictions, claiming unwanted [[censorship]] from Flickr and Yahoo.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.heise.de/english/newsticker/news/91160 Heise online - Flickr filter raises eyebrows]{{dead link|date=January 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Flickr management, unwilling to go into legal details, implied that the reason for the stringent filtering was some unusually strict age-verification laws in Germany.&lt;!--which does not exist--&gt; The issue received attention in the German national media, especially in online publications. Initial reports indicated that Flickr's action was a sensible, if unattractive, precaution against prosecution,&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.spiegel.de/netzwelt/web/0,1518,488542,00.html Zwangsfilter: Flickr verbietet Deutschen Nacktfotos - Netzwelt - Der Spiegel - Nachrichten]&lt;/ref&gt; although later coverage implied that Flickr's action may have been unnecessarily strict.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.spiegel.de/netzwelt/web/0,1518,489837,00.html Foto-Portal: Jugendschützer: Flickr-Filter nach deutschem Recht nicht nötig - Netzwelt - Der Spiegel - Nachrichten]&lt;/ref&gt;

On June 20, 2007, Flickr reacted by granting German users access to &quot;moderate&quot; (but not &quot;restricted&quot;) images, and hinted at a future solution for Germany, involving advanced age-verification procedures.

On June 1, 2009, Flickr was blocked in China in advance of the 20th anniversary of the [[Tiananmen Square protests of 1989]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.nowpublic.com/culture/china-blocks-twitter-hotmail-flickr-bing-tiananmen-20th China Blocks Twitter, Hotmail, Flickr, Bing Before Tiananmen 20th]&lt;/ref&gt;

===Virgin Mobile ad copyright===
In 2007 [[Virgin Mobile]] launched a bus stop advertising campaign which promoted its cellphone [[text messaging]] service using the work of amateur photographers who uploaded their work to Flickr using a [[Creative Commons Attribution 2.5|Creative Commons by Attribution]] license. Users licensing their images this way freed their work for use by any other entity, as long as the original creator was attributed credit, without any other compensation being required. Virgin upheld this single restriction by printing a URL, leading to the photographer's Flickr page, on each of their ads. However, one picture depicted 15-year-old Alison Chang at a fund-raising carwash for her church,&lt;ref name=&quot;permission&quot;&gt;{{cite news|first=Noam|last=Cohen|title=Use My Photo? Not Without Permission|url=http://www.nytimes.com/2007/10/01/technology/01link.html|quote=One moment, Alison Chang, a 15-year-old student from Dallas, is cheerfully goofing around at a local church-sponsored car wash, posing with a friend for a photo. Weeks later, that photo is posted online and catches the eye of an ad agency in Australia, and the altered image of Alison appears on a billboard in Adelaide as part of a [[Virgin Mobile]] advertising campaign.|publisher=New York Times|accessdate=25 September 2007}}&lt;/ref&gt; for which Chang sued Virgin Mobile and Creative Commons. The photo was taken by Alison's church youth counsellor, Justin Ho-Wee Wong, who uploaded the image to Flickr under the [[Creative Commons]] license.&lt;ref name=&quot;permission&quot;/&gt;

{{quote|The case hinges on privacy, the right of people not to have their likeness used in an ad without permission. So, while Mr. Wong may have given away his rights as a photographer, he did not, and could not, give away Alison's [[Personality rights|rights]]. In the lawsuit, which Mr. Wong is also a party to, there is an argument that Virgin did not honor all the terms of the nonrestrictive license.&lt;ref name=&quot;permission&quot;/&gt;}}

On November 27, 2007, Chang filed for a voluntary dismissal of the lawsuit against Creative Commons,&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.lessig.org/blog/2007/11/from_the_whyagcfromcravathisgr.html From the Why-a-GC-from-Cravath-is-great Department: The lawsuit is over (Lessig Blog)]&lt;/ref&gt;focusing their lawsuit against Virgin Mobile.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|last=Gross|first=Grant|title=Lawsuit Against Creative Commons Dropped|work=[[PC World (magazine)|PC World]]|date=1 December 2007|url=http://www.pcworld.com/businesscenter/article/140189/lawsuit_against_creative_commons_dropped.html|accessdate=25 May 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt; The case was thrown out of court due to lack of jurisdiction and subsequently Virgin Mobile did not incur any damages towards the defendant.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://blog.internetcases.com/2009/01/22/no-personal-jurisdiction-over-australian-defendant-in-flickr-right-of-publicity-case/|title=No personal jurisdiction over Australian defendant in Flickr right of publicity case : Internet law - Evan Brown - Internet Cases|publisher=Blog.internetcases.com|accessdate=16 March 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Flickr being monitored by US Government===
In October 2010 it was reported that Flickr, along with [[Facebook]] and other [[social networking]] sites, is being monitored by the [[US Department of Homeland Security]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.aolnews.com/nation/article/homeland-security-monitoring-social-networking-sites/19675854 Homeland Security Monitoring Social Networking Sites]&lt;/ref&gt;

==The Commons==
Several museums and archives post images released under a &quot;no known restrictions&quot; license, which was first made available on January 16, 2008. The goal of the license is to &quot;firstly show you hidden treasures in the world's public photography archives, and secondly to show how your input and knowledge can help make these collections even richer.&quot; Participants include [[George Eastman House]], [[Library of Congress]], [[Brooklyn Museum]], [[Nationaal Archief]], [[National Archives and Records Administration]], [[State Library of New South Wales]], and [[Smithsonian Institution]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.flickr.com/commons|title=More about The Commons|accessdate=2 February 2009|publisher=Flickr}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|first=Noam|last=Cohen|url=http://www.nytimes.com/2009/01/19/technology/internet/19link.html?_r=1&amp;partner=permalink&amp;exprod=permalink|title=Historical Photos in Web Archives Gain Vivid New Lives|quote=In a similar move to harness the public’s knowledge about old photographs, the Library of Congress a year ago began adding photographs with no known restrictions to a Flickr service called the Commons. The Library of Congress started with 3,500 photos and adds 50 a week.|work=New York Times|date=18 January 2009|accessdate=2 February 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Getty Images==
In 2009 [[Flickr]] announced a partnership with [[Getty Images]] in which selected users could submit photographs for [[stock photography]] usage and receive payment. In 2010 this was changed so that users could label images as suitable for stock use themselves.&lt;ref&gt;[http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/technology/8744817.stm Getty taps into Flickr snappers]&lt;/ref&gt;

==See also==
*[[Blacklist (computing)|Blacklist]]
*[[Image hosting service]]
*[[List of photo sharing websites]]
*[[List of social networking websites]]
*[[Photo sharing]]
*[[User-generated content]]

==References==
{{Reflist|colwidth=30em}}

==External links==
{{Commons category}}
*{{official website|http://www.flickr.com/}}
*[http://blog.flickr.net/ Flickr Blog]
*[http://info.yahoo.com/center/us/yahoo/ Yahoo! corporate website]

{{Yahoo! Inc.}}

[[Category:Image hosting]]
[[Category:Video hosting]]
[[Category:Photography websites]]
[[Category:Social networking services]]
[[Category:Online companies]]
[[Category:Web 2.0]]
[[Category:Yahoo!]]
[[Category:Internet properties established in 2004]]
[[Category:Keyhole Markup Language]]
[[Category:Photo sharing]]
[[Category:Social information processing]]

[[ar:فليكر]]
[[az:Flickr]]
[[bar:Flickr]]
[[ca:Flickr]]
[[cs:Flickr]]
[[cy:Flickr]]
[[da:Flickr]]
[[de:Flickr]]
[[el:Flickr]]
[[es:Flickr]]
[[eu:Flickr]]
[[fa:فلیکر]]
[[fr:Flickr]]
[[gl:Flickr]]
[[ko:플리커]]
[[hi:फ़्लिकर]]
[[hr:Flickr]]
[[id:Flickr]]
[[it:Flickr]]
[[he:פליקר]]
[[jv:Flickr]]
[[kn:ಫ್ಲಿಕರ್]]
[[ka:Flickr]]
[[lt:Flickr]]
[[hu:Flickr]]
[[ml:ഫ്ലിക്കർ]]
[[ms:Flickr]]
[[nl:Flickr]]
[[ja:Flickr]]
[[no:Flickr]]
[[nds:Flickr]]
[[pl:Flickr]]
[[pt:Flickr]]
[[ru:Flickr]]
[[simple:Flickr]]
[[sk:Flickr]]
[[sr:Flickr]]
[[fi:Flickr]]
[[sv:Flickr]]
[[ta:ஃபிளிக்கர்]]
[[th:ฟลิคเกอร์]]
[[tr:Flickr]]
[[uk:Flickr]]
[[vi:Flickr]]
[[wuu:Flickr]]
[[zh-yue:Flickr]]
[[zh:Flickr]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
