<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="1181152" ns="0" title="Liberalism in Egypt"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Refimprove|auto=yes|date=December 2009}}
{{Liberalism sidebar}}

'''[[Liberalism]] in [[Egypt]]''' or '''Egyptian liberalism''' is a political ideology that traces its beginnings to the 19th century.

==The timeline==
{{Main|Egypt's Liberal Experiment}}
{{Expand section|date=June 2008}}

==Introduction==
[[Image:Mustafa Kamil.jpg|thumb|100px|right|[[Mustafa Kamil Pasha|Mustafa Kamil]], a Nationalist Leader Famous for coining the phrase, &quot;If I had not been an Egyptian, I would have wished to become one&quot;, 1874 − 1908.]]
Egyptian self-government, education, and the continued plight of Egypt's peasant majority deteriorated most significantly under British occupation. Slowly, an organized national movement for independence began to form. In its beginnings, it took the form of an Azhar-led religious reform movement that was more concerned with the social conditions of Egyptian society. It gathered momentum between 1882 and 1906, ultimately leading to a resentment against European occupation.&lt;ref&gt;Vatikiotis, p. 189&lt;/ref&gt; Sheikh [[Muhammad Abduh]], the son of a Delta farmer who was briefly exiled for his participation in the Urabi revolt and a future Azhar [[Mufti]], was its most notable advocate. Abduh called for a reform of Egyptian Muslim society and formulated the [[modernism|modernist]] interpretations of [[Islam]] that took hold among younger generations of Egyptians. Among these were [[Mustafa Kamil Pasha|Mustafa Kamil]] and [[Ahmed Lutfi el-Sayed]], the architects of modern Egyptian nationalism. Mustafa Kamil had been a student activist in the 1890s involved in the creation of a secret nationalist society that called for British evacuation from Egypt. He was famous for coining the popular expression, &quot;If I had not been an Egyptian, I would have wished to become one.&quot;

Egyptian nationalist sentiment reached a high point after the 1906 [[Dinshaway Incident]], when following an altercation between a group of British soldiers and Egyptian farmers, four of the farmers were hanged while others were condemned to public flogging. Dinshaway, a watershed in the history of Egyptian anti-[[colonialism|colonial]] resistance, galvanized Egyptian opposition against the British, culminating in the founding of the first two political parties in Egypt: the secular, liberal ''Umma'' (the Nation, 1907) headed by [[Ahmed Lutfi el-Sayed]], and the more radical, pro-Islamic ''Watani'' Party (National Party, 1908) headed by Mustafa Kamil. Lutfi was born to a family of farmers in the Delta province of [[Ad Daqahliyah|Daqahliya]] in 1872. He was educated at al-Azhar where he attended lectures by Mohammed Abduh. Abduh came to have a profound influence on Lutfi's reformist thinking in later years. In 1907, he founded the Umma Party newspaper, el-Garida, whose statement of purpose read: &quot;El-Garida is a purely Egyptian party which aims to defend Egyptian interests of all kinds.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;qtd. in Vatikiotis, p. 227&lt;/ref&gt; 

Both the People and National parties came to dominate Egyptian politics until World War I, but the new leaders of the national movement for independence following four arduous years of war (in which Great Britain declared Egypt a British [[protectorate]]) were closer to the secular, liberal principles of [[Ahmed Lutfi el-Sayed]] and the People's Party. Prominent among these was [[Saad Zaghlul]] who led the new movement through the [[Wafd Party]]. Saad Zaghlul held several ministerial positions before he was elected to the Legislative Assembly and organized a mass movement demanding an end to the British Protectorate. He garnered such massive popularity among the Egyptian people that he came to be known as 'Father of the Egyptians'. When on March 8, 1919 the British arrested Zaghlul and his associates and exiled them to [[Malta]], the Egyptian people staged their [[Egyptian Revolution of 1919|first modern revolution]]. Demonstrations and strikes across Egypt became such a daily occurrence that normal life was brought to a halt.&lt;ref&gt;Jankowski, p. 112&lt;/ref&gt; 

The Wafd Party drafted a [[1923 Constitution of Egypt|new Constitution in 1923]] based on a [[parliamentary system|parliamentary]] representative system. Saad Zaghlul became the first popularly-elected Prime Minister of Egypt in 1924. Egyptian independence at this stage was provisional, as British forces continued to be physically present on Egyptian soil. In 1936, the [[Anglo-Egyptian Treaty of 1936|Anglo-Egyptian Treaty]] was concluded. New forces that came to prominence were the [[Muslim Brotherhood]] and the radical [[Misr El-Fatah (Young Egypt) Party|Young Egypt Party]]. In 1920, [[Banque Misr]] (Bank of Egypt) was founded by [[Talaat Pasha Harb]] as &quot;an Egyptian bank for Egyptians only&quot;,&lt;ref&gt;qtd. in Jankowski p. 123&lt;/ref&gt; which restricted shareholding to native Egyptians and helped finance various new Egyptian-owned businesses.

[[Image:Farouk family official.jpg|thumb|200px|left|[[King Farouk I]], [[Farida of Egypt|Queen Farida]] and their first-born daughter [[Princess Farial of Egypt|Princess Ferial]] ca. 1940]]

Under the parliamentary monarchy, Egypt reached the peak of its modern intellectual Renaissance that was started by Rifa'a el-Tahtawy nearly a century earlier. Among those who set the intellectual tone of a newly independent Egypt, in addition to [[Muhammad Abduh]] and [[Ahmed Lutfi el-Sayed]], were [[Qasim Amin]], [[Muhammad Husayn Haykal]], [[Taha Hussein]], [[Abbas Al-Akkad|Abbas el-'Akkad]], [[Tawfiq al-Hakeem|Tawfiq el-Hakeem]], and [[Salama Moussa]]. They delineated a liberal outlook for their country expressed as a commitment to individual freedom, [[secularism]], an [[evolution]]ary view of the world and faith in science to bring progress to human society.&lt;ref&gt;Jankowski, p. 130&lt;/ref&gt; This period was looked upon with fondness by future generations of Egyptians as a [[Golden Age]] of Egyptian liberalism, openness, and an Egypt-centered attitude that put the country's interests center stage.

When Egyptian novelist and [[Nobel Prize]] laureate [[Naguib Mahfouz]] died in 2006, many Egyptians felt that perhaps the last of the Greats of Egypt's golden age had died. In his dialogues with close associate and journalist Mohamed Salmawy, published as ''Mon Égypte'', Mahfouz had this to say:

{{cquote|Egypt is not just a piece of land. Egypt is the inventor of civilisation... The strange thing is that this country of great history and unsurpassed civilisation is nothing but a thin strip along the banks of the Nile... This thin strip of land created moral values, launched the concept of monotheism, developed arts, invented science and gave the world a stunning administration. These factors enabled the Egyptians to survive while other cultures and nations withered and died... Throughout history Egyptians have felt that their mission is to tend to life. They were proud to turn the land green, to make it blossom with life. The other thing is that Egyptians invented morality long before the major religions appeared on earth. Morality is not just a system for control but a protection against chaos and death... Egypt gave Islam a new voice. It didn't change the basic tenets of Islam, but its cultural weight gave Islam a new voice, one it didn't have back in Arabia. Egypt embraced an Islam that was moderate, tolerant and non-extremist. Egyptians are very pious, but they know how to mix piety with joy, just as their ancestors did centuries ago. Egyptians celebrate religious occasions with flair. For them, religious festivals and the month of Ramadan are occasions to celebrate life.&lt;ref&gt;Salmawy, Mohamed. [http://weekly.ahram.org.eg/2006/807/op6.htm 'Dialogues of Naguib Mahfouz: Mon Egypte']. Al-Ahram Weekly. 10–16 August 2006.&lt;/ref&gt;}}

== Modern Liberal Parties ==

The [[Democratic Front Party]] (''Hizb el-Gabha eldimocratia''), the [[Tomorrow Party]] (''Hisb el-Ghad'') and the [[ New Wafd Party]] (''Hizb el-Wafd el-Gedid'') are some of the contemporary Egyptian liberal parties. The latest liberal party that came to prominence, &quot;Hizb El Ghad&quot;, was founded in November 2004.After the [[Egyptian Revolution of 2011]] many liberal parties came out to light such as [[Egyptian Liberal Party]], the [[Egyptian Social Democratic Party]]

== Liberal parties==
===Historical liberal parties===
* [[Wafd Party|''Wafd'']]
* [[Hizb al-Umma|''Al-Umma'']]
===Active liberal parties===
* [[Egyptian Liberal Party]]- El-Masreen El-Ahrar Party-
* [[Tomorrow Party|''Ghad'']]: [[Ayman Nour]]
* [[Democratic Front Party (Egypt)|''Hizb el-Gabha el-Dimocratia'']]: [[Ossama Al-Ghazaly Harb]]
* [[New Wafd Party]] -Hizb al-Wafd al-Jadid-  (re-established of the wafd party)
* [[Egyptian Social Democratic Party]]

==See also==
*[[Egypt's Liberal Experiment]]
*[[Politics of Egypt]]
*[[List of political parties in Egypt]]
{{Africa topic|Liberalism in}}
{{Asia topic|Liberalism in}}

==References==
{{Reflist}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Liberalism In Egypt}}
[[Category:Liberalism by country|Egypt]]
[[Category:Politics of Egypt]]

[[ar:تجربة مصر الليبرالية]]
[[arz:تجربة الليبراليه فى مصر]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
