<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="1186416" ns="0" title="SpinRite"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{POV|Redisputed|date=September 2009}}
{{Primary sources|date=July 2008}}
{{Infobox software
| name                   = SpinRite
| logo                   = [[Image:Spinrite logo.jpg|100px|SpinRite Logo]]
| screenshot             = [[Image:Spinrite-6.0.png|250px|SpinRite 6.0]]
| caption                = SpinRite 6.0
| developer              = [[Gibson Research Corporation]]
| released               = 1988
|| latest release version     = 6.0
| latest release date        = {{release date|2004|06|7}}
| frequently_updated     = yes&lt;!-- Release version update? Don't edit this page, just click on the version number! --&gt;
| programming language   = [[x86 assembly language]]
| operating system       =included [[FreeDOS]] (doesn't use OS of host PC)
runnable from [[DOS]]
| platform = any PC
| size = 0.169 MB executable, 1.40MB bootable disk image with FreeDOS OS
| language               = English
| genre                  = [[Hard Disk]] Recovery
| license                = [[Proprietary software|proprietary]] and Commercial [[software]]
| website                = [http://www.grc.com/sr/spinrite.htm GRC.com SpinRite Website]
}}
'''SpinRite''' is a [[computer]] [[software program]] for scanning magnetic data storage devices such as [[hard disk]]s, recovering data from them and refreshing their surfaces. It is [[proprietary software|proprietary]] and commercial [[software]] written by [[Steve Gibson (computer programmer)|Steve Gibson]] of [[Gibson Research Corporation#Gibson Research Corporation|Gibson Research Corporation]]. The first version was released in 1988. Version 6.0, still current {{As of|2011|11|lc=on}}, was released in 2004.&lt;ref&gt;{{Citation | title = SpinRite web page| url=http://www.grc.com/sr/spinrite.htm| accessdate = 2009-09-17}}&lt;/ref&gt; SpinRite may be run from a [[bootable]] [[floppy disk]], [[USB flash drive]] or [[CD-ROM]] on a [[IBM PC compatible|PC-compatible]] computer, independent of the [[operating system]] installed on the host computer.

== Features ==
SpinRite tests the data surfaces of writeable magnetic disks, including IDE, [[SATA]], and USB-[[interface]]d hard disks, and floppy disks. It analyzes their contents and is claimed to be able to refresh the magnetic disk surfaces to allow them to operate more reliably.

SpinRite attempts to recover data from hard disks with damaged portions that may not be readable via the operating system. When the program encounters a sector with errors that cannot be corrected by the disk drive's [[error correcting code|error-correcting code]], it tries to read the sector up to 2000 times, in order to determine, by comparing the successive results, the most probable value of each [[bit]]. The data is then saved onto a new block on the same disk; it cannot be saved elsewhere. In this respect SpinRite differs from most [[data recovery]] software, which usually provides (and recommends) an option to save the recovered data onto another disk, or onto a separate partition on the same disk.&lt;ref&gt;{{Citation | title = KickstartNews review | url=http://www.kickstartnews.com/reviews/utilities/spinrite_v6.html | accessdate = 2010-01-30}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Gibson Research Corporation claims their SpinRite software will diagnose the quality of a disk drive, and make it work as reliably as possible with future use. Its developer, [[Steve Gibson]], says his software was specifically designed to fix [[bad sector|sector problems]]. However, if a hard drive's circuit board, drive motors or other mechanical parts are defective, or there is systemic file system corruption, SpinRite may be of little or no help.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.grc.com/sn/sn-155.txt&lt;/ref&gt; In fact, in such circumstances ''no'' purely software-based solution would be sufficient to overcome the problem. When a hard drive has begun to develop mechanical faults, a program like SpinRite may sometimes be able to extend its usable life for long enough to carry out successful file recovery with other specialized software.

SpinRite is declared by its developer to have certain unique features,&lt;ref&gt;{{Citation | title = SpinRite Exclusive Features | url=http://www.grc.com/srdocs.htm | accessdate = 2008-02-16}}&lt;/ref&gt; such as disabling of disk write caching, disabling of auto-relocation, compatibility with disk compression, identification of the &quot;data-to-flux-reversal encoder-decoder&quot; used in a drive, and separate testing of [[Data buffer|buffered]] and unbuffered disk read performance. Another important feature is direct hardware-level access,&lt;ref&gt;http://www.pcworld.com/article/117080/spinrite_6_to_the_rescue.html&lt;/ref&gt; whereby the drive's internal controller interacts directly with the program, rather than through the operating system. This, in turn, allows dynamic head repositioning, whereby, when reading a faulty sector, the reading head is deliberately moved backwards and forwards many times, by varying amounts, in the hope that each time it returns to the sector, it may come to rest in a slightly different position. By performing [[statistical analysis]] on the succession of results thus obtained, SpinRite is, according to its maker, often able to &quot;reconstruct&quot; data from damaged sectors; and even in those cases in which complete reconstruction proves impossible, SpinRite is able to extract all intact bits from a partially damaged sector, and to copy them to a new block, thereby minimizing the amount of data lost.&lt;ref&gt;{{Citation | title = Anticipate Drive Problems Early with SpinRite v6.0 | url=http://www.sysopt.com/tutorials/article.php/12034_3549006_1 | accessdate = 2010-01-30}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Certain claims made by SpinRite's makers have proved controversial. The program's claimed ability to &quot;refresh&quot; aging drives has been met with particular skepticism, while its &quot;recovery&quot; of sectors marked as damaged by the file system controller is considered by some to be undesirable and ultimately counter-productive.&lt;ref&gt;[http://groups.google.com/group/comp.dcom.xdsl/msg/9aeee32323c2978e?dmode=source&amp;hl=en Criticism in 2000 of SpinRite's stated operating principles  – groups comp.dcom.xdsl ]&lt;!-- alternate URL: http://www.radsoft.net/news/roundups/grc/20060123,00.shtml --&gt;&lt;/ref&gt;

SpinRite is written in [[x86]] [[assembly language]], and runs only on [[IBM PC compatible|PC-compatible]] computers with 32-bit Intel or AMD x86 processor, but it can operate on any attached storage device with a compatible interface.&lt;ref&gt;{{Citation | title = PCNet File Catch - SpinRite 6.0 | url=http://www.pcnet-online.com/picks/spinrite.htm | accessdate = 2010-01-30}}&lt;/ref&gt; It can be run only under [[MS-DOS]] or a compatible operating system, but the operating system installed on the machine is irrelevant, as Spinrite is distributed in bootable version with the [[FreeDOS]] operating system. Version 6 is compatible with hard disks containing any [[logical volume management]] or file system such as [[FAT16]] or 32, [[NTFS]], [[Ext3]] as well as other [[File_system#File_systems_under_Linux|Linux File Systems]], [[HFS Plus|HFS+ For Mac OS X]], [[Tivo]] and others, as it operates only on the disk itself. Drives attached to computers with other processors can be recovered by temporarily connecting the drive to a suitable computer.&lt;ref&gt;{{Citation | title = SpinRite 6.0 for Linux Users | url=http://www.linuxjournal.com/article/7684 | accessdate = 2010-01-30 | publisher = [[Linux Journal]]}}&lt;/ref&gt; Version 6 includes a [[Microsoft Windows]] utility to create a [[FreeDOS]] boot [[floppy disk]] or [[CD-ROM]] for the program. [[Image:Spinrite-2.0.png|thumb|250px|SpinRite 2.0, circa 1991.]]

Version 6 is rather different from previous versions. It offers full access to the entire disk surface regardless of [[Disk partitioning|partitioning]], [[S.M.A.R.T.|Self-Monitoring, Analysis, and Reporting Technology (S.M.A.R.T.)]] parameters and control of partial scanning within a specified percentage range. Version 5 was limited to [[AT Attachment]] (PATA, IDE) hard drives; version 6 may, on suitable motherboards, work on newer [[Serial ATA]] (SATA) and [[USB mass storage device class|USB]] hard drives, and with any other type of drive&amp;mdash;[[SCSI]], 1394/[[Firewire]]&amp;mdash;that can be made visible to MS-DOS through the addition of controller [[BIOS]] or add-on DOS [[device driver|driver]]s.&lt;ref&gt;{{Citation | title = SpinRite 6.0 for Linux Users | url=http://www.linuxjournal.com/article/7684 | accessdate = 2010-01-30 | publisher = [[Linux Journal]]}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The price {{As of|2011|1|lc=on}} was [[US$]]89. Documentation may be downloaded free of charge from the SpinRite website.

=== Issue with Serial ATA drives ===

While SATA drives are supported, SATA controllers that include a processor and diagnostic software can limit SpinRite's ability to obtain and display SMART data (&quot;thin controller&quot; SATA controllers do not have this limitation).  This data monitor does not affect SpinRite's recovery and diagnostics ability; SMART data when available helps long-term disk maintenance and failure prediction.&lt;ref&gt;{{Citation | title = SATA Operation with SpinRite | url=http://www.grc.com/sr/kb/sata.htm | accessdate = 2010-01-29}}&lt;/ref&gt; GRC said in 2006 that this issue would be resolved in version 6.1, a free-of-charge upgrade for SpinRite 6.0 users.&lt;ref&gt;{{Citation | title = SATA Operation with SpinRite. Site says &quot;Last Edit: Nov 16, 2006&quot; | url=http://www.grc.com/sr/kb/sata.htm | accessdate = 2010-01-29}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Alternatives==
SpinRite works entirely on the drive under investigation, attempting to recover partially damaged data by rewriting it to an undamaged part of the disk. This approach can cause irreversible data loss and may be unsuitable if there are many errors, as the task may take an unreasonably long time to complete (literally years for a large, badly damaged disc, attempting to read each sector 2000 times). The program may also be unsuitable for disks that are badly damaged and possibly worsening with use, as the data, even if successfully read, cannot be re-written securely on the disk.&lt;ref&gt;{{Citation | title = Why Spinrite is not on my Data Recovery Software List | url=http://www.myharddrivedied.com/blog/why-spinrite-not-my-data-recovery-software-list | accessdate = 2011-01-22}}&lt;/ref&gt; Also, if little free space remains on a faulty disk, there may be insufficient room to transfer all of the recovered data. In these cases, software that can recover as much data as possible and copy it to another drive will generally be a more suitable alternative. However, standard disk imaging and cloning software is not ideally suited for data recovery, even if some such software may be configured to copy only good sectors, ignoring sectors that are not easily readable. 

Though there are many commercial and freeware file recovery programs available, besides SpinRite only the [http://www.dposoft.net/hdd.html HDD Regenerator] offers direct hardware-level access to the disk, while others are more suitable for recovery of deleted and corrupted files and formatted drives. Some are intended to recover only accidentally deleted files (e.g., [http://www.officerecovery.com/freeundelete/ OfficeRecovery's FreeUndelete]). Others will recover files of certain types, using knowledge of the file structure (e.g., [http://www.getdata.com/ GetData's Recover My Files]).

[http://www.roadkil.net/program.php?ProgramID=29 Roadkil's Unstoppable Copier] runs under Windows and copies on a file, not sector, basis. It can be set to copy all undamaged files first, and then to try to copy as much as possible of damaged files (although, during extraction, it is difficult to see which file is being copied, and thus to avoid copying files not worth recovering).

Open Source Unix-based alternatives include [http://www.garloff.de/kurt/linux/ddrescue/ dd_rescue] and [http://www.kalysto.org/utilities/dd_rhelp/index.en.html dd_rhelp], which work together, or [http://www.gnu.org/software/ddrescue/ddrescue.html GNU ddrescue]. dd_rhelp first extracts all the readable data, and saves it to a file, inserting zeros where bytes cannot be read. Then it tries to re-read the invalid data and update this file. [[GNU]] [[ddrescue]] can be used to copy data directly to a new disk if needed, just like Linux [[Dd (Unix)|dd]].

dd_rhelp or GNU ddrescue will yield a complete disk image, faster but possibly with some errors. GNU ddrescue is generally much faster whereas dd_rhelp is a shell script wrapper around dd_rescue. Both dd_rhelp and GNU ddrescue aim to copy data quickly from sectors that are free of errors, then copy in smaller blocks, with retries when necessary, where errors are found. These programs are more complicated to use than SpinRite, although GNU ddrescue is fairly easy to use with default options, and can easily be downloaded and compiled on Linux-based [[Live CD]]s such as [[Knoppix]]. It can also be used with [[SystemRescueCD]].

On some disks, many files may be damaged. In practice, though, in most cases, most damaged files will be unimportant: temporary files, files which may easily be replaced by reinstalling software, and so on. Executable program files are generally not worth rescuing unless they are guaranteed 100% intact. Moreover, fully recovered program folders will often not give rise to working software, as corresponding registry entries will no longer be associated with them correctly. By contrast, some documents may be worth rescuing even if incomplete. For example, a document created by a given word-processing program may become corrupted, thus rendering it unreadable by the program normally associated with it, yet much of the text contained in the document may still be read, and perhaps extracted, by making use of a more generic text editor (although, in such a case, program-specific formatting characters will usually be dispersed throughout the text, making both reading and extraction laborious).

Any sector-based rescue system is bound to spend a lot of its time trying to read unwanted data. File-based systems, by contrast, will often allow the user to ignore files that are a waste of time, and will also often identify and list files that are not intact, so long as the [[file system]] is not so damaged as to be unable to identify files. Such systems can, therefore, sometimes prove more practical for the purposes of useful file recovery. However, a sector-based program, which reads data in raw format, sometimes using specialized techniques to recover partially damaged information, may ultimately recover more useful data.

== See also ==
* [[List of data recovery software]]
* [[S.M.A.R.T.]]

== References ==
{{reflist}}

== External links ==
* [http://www.grc.com/sr/spinrite.htm Official site]

{{DEFAULTSORT:Spinrite}}
[[Category:DOS software]]
[[Category:Data recovery]]
[[Category:Hard disk software]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
