<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="11875" ns="0" title="GNU"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{two other uses|the operating system|the animal|Wildebeest||}}
{{Primary sources|date=July 2010}}
{{Infobox OS
| name                   = GNU
| logo                   = [[Image:Heckert GNU white.svg|128px|Logo]]
| family                 = [[Unix-like]]
| latest_release_version =
| latest_release_date    =
| latest_test_version    =
| latest_test_date       =
| frequently_updated     = yes
| marketing_target       =
| language               = Multilingual
| kernel_type            = [[Microkernel]]
| ui                     = None
| license                = [[GNU General Public License]] and other [[free software license]]s
| working_state          = Under development, no stable releases
| supported_platforms    = [[x86]], [[x86-64]]
| updatemodel            =
| package_manager        =
| website                = [http://www.gnu.org/ gnu.org]
}}
'''GNU''' {{IPAc-en|audio=En-gnu.ogg|ɡ|ə|ˈ|n|uː}}&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.gnu.org/ |title= What is GNU?| work = The GNU Operating System  |date=September 4, 2009 |publisher=[[Free Software Foundation]] |accessdate=October 9, 2009 |quote=The name &quot;GNU&quot; is a [[recursive acronym]] for &quot;GNU's Not Unix!&quot;; it is pronounced ''g-noo'', as one syllable with no vowel sound between the ''g'' and the ''n''.}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;!-- /gnu:/ is not a possible English pronunciation--&gt;
is a [[Unix-like]] computer [[operating system]] developed by the [[GNU project]], ultimately aiming to be a &quot;complete [[Unix]]-compatible software system&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.gnu.org/gnu/manifesto.html |title=GNU Manifesto |publisher=Gnu.org |date= |accessdate=2011-07-27}}&lt;/ref&gt;
composed wholly of [[free software]]. Development of GNU was initiated by [[Richard Stallman]] in 1983 and was the original focus of the [[Free Software Foundation]] (FSF), but no stable release of GNU yet exists as of September 2010.&lt;ref name=computerworld&gt;Vaughan-Nichols, Steven J. &quot;[http://www.computerworld.com/s/article/9131178/Opinion_The_top_10_operating_system_stinkers Opinion: The top 10 operating system stinkers]&quot; in ''[[Computerworld]]'', April 9, 2009: &quot;But after more than 25 years in development, GNU remains incomplete: Its kernel, Hurd, has never really made it out of the starting blocks. ... Almost no one has actually been able to use the OS; it's really more a set of ideas than an operating system.&quot;&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=Hillesley&gt;Hillesley, Richard. &quot;[http://www.h-online.com/open/features/GNU-HURD-Altered-visions-and-lost-promise-1030942.html GNU HURD: Altered visions and lost promise]&quot;, June 30, 2010. See especially [http://www.h-online.com/open/features/GNU-HURD-Altered-visions-and-lost-promise-1030942.html?page=3 page 3]: &quot;Nearly twenty years later the HURD has still to reach maturity, and has never achieved production quality.&quot; ... &quot;Some of us are still wishing and hoping for the real deal, a GNU operating system with a GNU kernel.&quot;&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Lessig, Lawrence. ''The Future of Ideas: The Fate of the Commons in a Connected World'', p. 54. Random House, Inc., 2001. ISBN 9780375505782. Referring to Stallman, Lessig wrote, &quot;He had mixed all of the ingredients needed for an operating system to function, but he was missing the core.&quot;&lt;/ref&gt; The latest [[Alpha test|alpha]] release of the GNU system is GNU 0.401, released on 1 April 2011, featuring [[GNU Hurd]] as the system's [[kernel (computing)|kernel]]. Other (non-GNU) kernels, most famously the [[Linux kernel]], can also be used with GNU. The FSF maintains that [[Linux]], when used with GNU tools and utilities, should be considered a [[GNU variants|variant of GNU]], and promotes the term ''GNU/Linux'' for such systems, (leading to the [[GNU/Linux naming controversy]]).

''GNU'' is a [[recursive acronym]] for ''&quot;GNU's Not Unix!&quot;'', chosen because GNU's design is [[Unix-like]], but differs from Unix by being free software and containing no [[Unix]] code.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url = http://www.gnu.org/ | title = The GNU Operating system | accessdate = 2008-08-18 }}&lt;/ref&gt; Programs released under the auspices of the [[GNU Project]] are called ''GNU packages'' or ''GNU programs''. The system's basic components include the [[GNU Compiler Collection]] (GCC), the [[GNU Binary Utilities]] (binutils), the [[Bash (Unix shell)|bash]] shell, the [[GNU C library]] (glibc), and [[GNU Core Utilities]] (coreutils). GNU developers have contributed Linux [[port (software)|ports]] of GNU applications and utilities, which are now also widely used on other operating systems such as [[Berkeley Software Distribution|BSD]] variants, [[Solaris Operating System|Solaris]] and [[Mac OS X]].

The [[GNU General Public License]] (GPL), the [[GNU Lesser General Public License]] (LGPL), and the [[GNU Free Documentation License]] (GFDL) were written for GNU, but are also used by many unrelated projects. A minority of the software used by GNU, such as the [[X Window System]], is licensed under [[permissive free software license]]s.

Richard Stallman views GNU as a &quot;technical means to a social end&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.gnu.org/philosophy/stallman-kth.html Richard Stallman's speech in Stockholm, Sweden in 1986] www.gnu.org&lt;/ref&gt;

== History ==

The plan for the GNU operating system was publicly announced on September 27, 1983, on the net.unix-wizards and net.usoft [[newsgroup]]s by [[Richard Stallman]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite newsgroup | title = new UNIX implementation | first = Richard | last = Stallman | date = 27 September 1983 | newsgroup = net.unix-wizards | newsgroup = net.usoft | id = 771@mit-eddie.UUCP | url = http://groups.google.com/group/net.unix-wizards/msg/4dadd63a976019d7 | accessdate = 2008-08-18 }}&lt;/ref&gt; Software development began on January 5, 1984, when Stallman quit his job at the [[Massachusetts Institute of Technology]] (MIT) Artificial Intelligence Laboratory so that they could not claim ownership or interfere with distributing GNU as free software. Richard Stallman chose the name by using various plays on words, including the song ''[[The Gnu]]''.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://fsfeurope.org/documents/rms-fs-2006-03-09.en.html#the-name-gnu| title=Stallman explaining why the name &quot;GNU&quot; was chosen|publisher=FSFE|accessdate=2007-02-20}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The goal was to bring a wholly free software operating system into existence. Stallman wanted computer users to be &quot;free&quot;, as most were in the 1960s and 1970s&amp;nbsp;– free to study the source code of the software they use, free to share the software with other people, free to modify the behaviour of the software, and free to publish their modified versions of the software. This philosophy was later published as the [[GNU Manifesto]] in March 1985.

Richard Stallman's experience with the [[Incompatible Timesharing System]] (ITS), an early operating system written in [[assembly language]] that became obsolete due to discontinuation of [[PDP-10]], the computer architecture for which ITS was written, led to a decision that a [[porting|portable]] system was necessary.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://fsfeurope.org/documents/rms-fs-2006-03-09.en.html#choosing-the-unix-design| title=Stallman describing why a Unix-like design was chosen | publisher = FSFE | accessdate = 2007-02-20}}&lt;/ref&gt;  It was thus decided that GNU would be mostly compatible with Unix.  At the time, Unix was already a popular [[proprietary software|proprietary]] operating system. The design of Unix had proven{{Whom?|date=May 2011}} to be solid,{{Citation needed|date=May 2011}} and it was modular, so it could be reimplemented piece by piece.

Much of the needed software had to be written from scratch, but existing compatible third-party free software components were also used such as the [[TeX]] typesetting system, the [[X Window System]], and the [[Mach (kernel)|Mach]] microkernel that forms the basis of the [[GNU Mach]] core of [[GNU Hurd]] (the official kernel of GNU). With the exception of the aforementioned third-party components, most of GNU has been written by volunteers of the [[GNU Project]]; some in their spare time, some paid by companies, educational institutions, and other non-profit organizations. In October 1985, Stallman set up the [[Free Software Foundation]] (FSF). In the late 1980s and 1990s, the FSF hired software developers to write the software needed for GNU.

As GNU gained prominence, interested businesses began contributing to development or selling GNU software and technical support. The most prominent and successful of these was [[Cygnus Solutions]], now part of [[Red Hat]].

{{See also|GNU/Linux naming controversy}}

== Copyright, licenses, and stewardship ==

The GNU Project suggests contributors assign the copyright for GNU packages to the Free Software Foundation,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.gnu.org/prep/maintain/html_node/Copyright-Papers.html |title=Copyright Papers - Information For Maintainers of GNU Software |publisher=Gnu.org |date=2011-06-30 |accessdate=2011-07-27}}&lt;/ref&gt; although this is not required.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.gnu.org/licenses/why-assign.html |title=Why the FSF gets copyright assignments from contributors |publisher=Gnu.org |date=2011-07-15 |accessdate=2011-07-27}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Copyright law grants the copyright-holder significant control over the copying and distributing of a work, but FSF wrote a license for the GNU software which grant recipients permission to copy and redistribute the software under highly permissive terms. For most of the 80s, each GNU package had its own license: the Emacs General Public License, the GCC General Public License, et cetera. In 1989, FSF published a single license they could use for all their software, and which could be used by non-GNU projects: the [[GNU General Public License]] (GPL).

This license is now used by most GNU programs, as well as a large number of free software programs that are not part of the GNU project; it is the most commonly used [[free software license]]. It gives all recipients of a program the right to run, copy, modify and distribute it, while forbidding them from imposing further restrictions on any copies they distribute. This idea is often referred to as [[copyleft]].

In 1991, the [[GNU Lesser General Public License]] (LGPL), then known as the Library General Public License, was written for certain libraries.  1991 also saw the release of version 2 of the GNU GPL. The [[GNU Free Documentation License]] (FDL), for documentation, followed in 2000.  The GPL and LGPL were revised to version 3 in 2007, improving their international applicability, and adding protection for users whose hardware restricts software changes.

Most GNU software is distributed under the GPL.  A minority is distributed under the LGPL, and a handful of packages are distributed under [[permissive free software licences]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://slashdot.org/comments.pl?sid=225606&amp;cid=18272276 |title=What the GPLv3 Means for MS-Novell Agreement |publisher=Slashdot.org |date=2007-03-08 |accessdate=2011-07-27}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== GNU software ==
{{Main|List of GNU packages}}

Prominent components of the GNU system include the [[GNU Compiler Collection]] (GCC), the [[GNU C Library]] (glibc), the [[GNU Emacs]] [[text editor]], and the [[GNOME]] [[desktop environment]].

Many GNU programs have been ported to a multitude of other operating systems, including various [[proprietary software|proprietary]] platforms such as [[Microsoft Windows]] and [[Mac OS X]]. They are often installed on proprietary Unix systems as replacements for the proprietary utilities originally included. However, this practice is controversial:{{Citation needed|date=March 2011}} these GNU component programs were developed with the goal of replacing entire proprietary UNIX systems with free software, not enhancing these systems.{{Citation needed|date=March 2011}}

Many GNU programs have been tested against their proprietary Unix counterparts and shown as being more reliable.&lt;ref&gt;[http://ftp.cs.wisc.edu/pub/paradyn/technical_papers/fuzz-revisited.ps Fuzz Revisited: A Re-examination of the Reliability of UNIX Utilities and Services] - October 1995 - Computer Sciences Department,University of Wisconsin&lt;/ref&gt;

As of 2007, there are a total of 319 GNU packages hosted on the official GNU development site.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://savannah.gnu.org/stats/ |title=Statistics [Savannah&amp;#93; |publisher=Savannah.gnu.org |date=2011-02-13 |accessdate=2011-07-27}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== GNU variants ==
[[File:GNewSense screenshot.png|thumb|200px|[[gNewSense]] is an example of a [[Linux distribution | GNU/Linux Distribution]]]]
{{Main|GNU variants}}

Although the official kernel of GNU is the [[GNU Hurd]] microkernel, variants using other kernels have been developed. Usage with the [[Linux kernel]], a [[monolithic kernel]], is by far the most popular distribution-vector for GNU software, though unlike Hurd, the Linux kernel itself is not part of the GNU Project, though the GNU Project has endorsed variants using the Linux kernel, such as [[gNewSense]].

Other GNU variants which do not use the [[GNU Hurd|Hurd]] as a kernel include [[Nexenta OS]] (GNU plus the kernel of [[OpenSolaris]]) and [[GNU-Darwin]]. Debian GNU/kFreeBSD and Debian GNU/NetBSD from [[Debian]] bring the early plan of GNU on a BSD kernel full circle. (The Debian project distributes GNU itself as [[Debian GNU/Hurd]].)

== GNU logo ==

The logo for GNU is a [[wildebeest|gnu]] head.  The well-known drawing was originally done by Etienne Suvasa. A bolder and simpler version designed by Aurelio Heckert is now preferred.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.gnu.org/graphics/agnuhead.html |title=A GNU Head - Free Software Foundation (FSF) |publisher=Gnu.org |date=2011-07-13 |accessdate=2011-07-27}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.gnu.org/graphics/heckert_gnu.html |title=A Bold GNU Head - Free Software Foundation (FSF) |publisher=Gnu.org |date=2011-07-13 |accessdate=2011-07-27}}&lt;/ref&gt; It appears in GNU software and in printed and electronic documentation for the GNU project, and is also used in Free Software Foundation materials.

==See also==
{{Portal|Free software}}
{{Refbegin|2}}
* [[Creative Commons]]
* [[Free software movement]]
* [[GNU Compiler for Java]]
* [[History of Free Software]]
* [[List of GNU packages]]
* [[List of Linux distributions endorsed by the Free Software Foundation]]
{{Refend}}

== References ==
{{Reflist|2}}

== External links ==
{{Commons}}
* {{Official website|http://www.gnu.org/}}
* [http://unxutils.sourceforge.net/ Ports of GNU utilities for Microsoft Windows]
* [http://www.verbumvanum.org/pesalus/ The daemon, the GNU and the penguin]
* [http://www.gnu.org/gnu/gnu-user-groups.html GNU User Groups]
* [irc://irc.gnu.org/gnu #gnu] IRC channel

{{Unix-like}}
{{GNU|state=expand}}
{{FLOSS}}
{{Operating System}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Gnu}}
[[Category:Computing acronyms]]
[[Category:Free software operating systems]]
[[Category:GNU Project]]
[[Category:GNU Project software]]
[[Category:Microkernel-based operating systems]]
[[Category:Unix variants]]

{{Link GA|pl}}
[[af:GNU]]
[[ar:جنو]]
[[az:GNU]]
[[bn:গনু]]
[[bs:GNU]]
[[bg:ГНУ]]
[[ca:GNU]]
[[cs:GNU]]
[[da:GNU]]
[[de:GNU]]
[[et:GNU]]
[[el:GNU]]
[[es:GNU]]
[[eo:GNU]]
[[eu:GNU]]
[[fa:گنو]]
[[fr:GNU]]
[[gl:GNU (sistema operativo)]]
[[ko:GNU]]
[[hi:जीएनयू]]
[[hr:GNU]]
[[ilo:GNU]]
[[id:GNU]]
[[is:GNU]]
[[it:GNU]]
[[he:גנו (מערכת הפעלה)]]
[[kn:ಗ್ನು]]
[[ku:GNU]]
[[la:GNU]]
[[lv:GNU]]
[[lt:GNU]]
[[jbo:gynus]]
[[lmo:GNU]]
[[hu:GNU]]
[[mk:ГНУ]]
[[ml:ഗ്നു]]
[[ms:GNU]]
[[nah:GNU]]
[[nl:GNU]]
[[ja:GNU]]
[[no:GNU]]
[[mhr:GNU]]
[[uz:GNU]]
[[pl:GNU]]
[[pt:GNU]]
[[ro:GNU]]
[[ru:GNU]]
[[sc:GNU]]
[[sq:GNU]]
[[simple:GNU]]
[[sk:GNU]]
[[sl:GNU]]
[[sr:ГНУ]]
[[sh:GNU]]
[[fi:GNU]]
[[sv:GNU]]
[[tl:GNU]]
[[ta:க்னூ]]
[[th:กนู]]
[[tr:GNU]]
[[uk:GNU]]
[[vec:GNU]]
[[yi:GNU]]
[[zh-yue:GNU]]
[[zh:GNU]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
