<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="1194188" ns="0" title="Stagecoach London"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{refimprove|date=December 2009}}
{{Infobox Company
| company_name     = Stagecoach London
| company_logo     = | 
| vector_logo      = 
| image            = Stagecoach East London bus 17433 (LX51 FKG) 2001 Dennis Trident 2 Alexander ALX400, Ludgate Circus, route 15, 20 May 2011.jpg
| image size       = 200px
| company_type     = [[Limited company|LTD]]
| foundation       = 1st April 1989
| area_served      = ''United Kingdom'' &lt;ref name=&quot;bus&quot;&gt;
{{cite web
|url = http://www.elbg.com/
|title = Sulake: Habbo
|publisher = East London Bus Group}}&lt;/ref&gt;
| industry         = Bus Company
| operating_income = 
| net_income       = 
| num_employees    = 5000
| parent           = [[Stagecoach Group|Stagecoach Group Plc]]
| subsid           = 
| owner            =
| homepage         = [http://www.elbg.com/ www.elbg.com]
}}

'''Stagecoach London''' (known until 2010 as '''East London Bus Group'''), is a bus company which principally operates services in the [[United Kingdom|UK]] [[capital city]] of [[London]], under contract to the [[London Buses]] arm of [[Transport for London]]. It was formed in 1989 as a subsidiary of [[London Buses]]. The company privatised in 1994 and acquired by the [[Stagecoach Group]], but sold to [[Macquarie Group]] in June 2006. It was reacquired by Stagecoach on 15 October 2010.&lt;ref name=&quot;reacq&quot;&gt;{{cite web
|url = http://www.stagecoachgroup.com/scg/ir/newsevents/rns/rnsitem?id=3751051
|title = Stagecoach Group plc acquisition of bus business from East London Bus Group Limited
|publisher = Stagecoach Group}}&lt;/ref&gt; and was renamed as Stagecoach London.&lt;ref name=&quot;homepage&quot;&gt;
{{cite web
|url = http://www.elbg.com/
|title = East London Bus Group
|publisher = East London Bus Group}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==History==
Stagecoach London was created from [[East London (bus company)|East London Bus &amp; Coach Company Ltd]] and [[Selkent|South East London &amp; Kent Bus Company Ltd]]. Both companies were acquired by the [[Stagecoach Group]] from state-owned [[London Buses]] when its subsidiaries were privatised. Legally these companies still exist, and Stagecoach London's buses carried legal lettering for either one or other of these companies.

Both the buses involved in the [[7 July 2005 London Bombings]], Trident 17758 and [[21 July 2005 London Bombings]], Trident 17762 belonged to Stagecoach London, both garaged at Stratford Garage (SD) now closed as part of the Olympic Park redevelopment and replaced by a new Garage in Stephenson Street, West Ham (WH).

[[File:East London Bus Group logo.png|right|thumb|East London Bus Group logo]] 

On 23 June 2006 the Stagecoach Group agreed to sell its London operations to the [[Macquarie Group]]. Stagecoach gave permission to use the Stagecoach London name for a limited time. Quickly the fleets both turned all-over red again, and were given back their old logos, albeit in lower-case lettering rather than capitals. The parent company became known as East London Bus Group.

On 15 October 2010, the Stagecoach Group announced that is was re-acquiring the business from Macquarie for a sum of nearly £59 million,&lt;ref name=&quot;reacq&quot; /&gt; which represents a significant profit for Stagecoach since it sold the company to Macquaire for £263.6 million in June 2006.&lt;ref name=&quot;reacq1&quot;&gt;
{{cite news
|url = http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/business/5108854.stm
|title = Stagecoach sells London bus firm
|publisher = BBC
| date=23 June 2006}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Operation==
Stagecoach London operates London contracted services under the brands '''East London''', '''Selkent''' and '''Thameside''', but these brands tended to be overwhelmed by the much stronger London Buses brand. There also used to be a coaching operation under the brand '''East London Coaches''' which ceased operation in February 2007 and a Travelshop which closed in March 2009 that was based at the Company's Ilford Head Office. The Office is now at the new West Ham Garage in Stephenson Street, Canning Town, London E16.

===East London Bus &amp; Coach Company Ltd===
{{main|East London (bus company)}}

===South East London &amp; Kent Bus Company Ltd===
{{main|Selkent}}

===East London Bus Ltd===
{{main|Thameside (East London Bus Group)}}

==See also==
*[[List of bus operators of the United Kingdom]]

==References==
{{Reflist}}

==External links==
{{commons cat|East London Bus Group}}
*[http://www.elbg.com East London Bus Group website]
*[http://www.tfl.gov.uk/buses London Buses website]

{{StagecoachGroup|state=autocollapse}}
{{london bus operators}}</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
