<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="1196902" ns="0" title="Saif al-Islam Gaddafi"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{For|his younger brother|Saif al-Arab Gaddafi}}
{{Use British English|date=November 2011}}
{{Use dmy dates|date= August 2011}}
{{Contains Arabic text}}
{{Infobox officeholder
|name         = Saif al-Islam Gaddafi&lt;br&gt;&lt;small&gt;سيف الإسلام معمر القذافي&lt;/small&gt;
|image        = 
|birth_date   = {{Birth date and age|df=y|1972|06|25}}
|birth_place  = [[Tripoli]], [[Libya]]
|alma_mater   = [[Al Fateh University]]&lt;br&gt;[[IMADEC University|International Management Development Consulting University]]&lt;br/&gt;[[London School of Economics]]&lt;ref name=&quot;Memo From Tripoli&quot;&gt;{{cite news |last=Thomas |first=Landon |url=http://www.nytimes.com/2010/03/01/world/middleeast/01libya.html |title=Unknotting Father’s Reins in Hope of ‘Reinventing’ Libya |work=[[New York Times]] |date=February 28, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|profession   = [[Engineer]]
|father       = [[Muammar Gaddafi]]
|mother       = [[Safia Farkash]]
|religion     = [[Islam]]
|allegiance   = {{flagicon|Libya|1977}} [[Great Socialist People's Libyan Arab Jamahiriya|Libyan Arab Jamahiriya]]
|branch       = 
|serviceyears = 1{{Citation needed|date=November 2011}}
|rank         = 
|commands     = 
|battles      = '''[[2011 Libyan civil war]]'''&lt;br&gt;* [[Battle of Tripoli (2011)|Battle of Tripoli]]&lt;br&gt;* [[Battle of Bani Walid]]
}}
'''Saif al-Islam Gaddafi''' ({{lang-ar|سيف الإسلام معمر القذافي}}, translated as &quot;Sword of Islam&quot;; born 25 June 1972) is a former [[Libya]]n political figure. He is the second son of [[Muammar Gaddafi]], who ruled Libya from 1969 to 2011, and Gaddafi's second wife [[Safia Farkash]]. He was part of his father's inner circle,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |url=http://english.aljazeera.net/news/africa/2011/02/2011227192852808945.html |title=Inside Gaddafi's inner circle |publisher=Al Jazeera |date=27 February 2011 |accessdate=20 June 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; performing public relations and diplomatic roles on behalf of his father. During his father's reign, he was the second most-widely recognized official in Libya&lt;ref name=&quot;nytimes.com&quot;&gt;{{cite news| url=http://www.nytimes.com/interactive/2010/11/28/world/20101128-cables-viewer.html#report/libya-09TRIPOLI208 | work=New York Times | first1=Alan | last1=McLean | first2=Scott | last2=Shane | first3=Archie | last3=Tse | title=A Selection From the Cache of Diplomatic Dispatches | date=November 28, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; and was mentioned as a possible successor, though he denied this.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |title=The Politics of Blackmail |date=13 September 2008 |work=Newsweek |url=http://www.newsweek.com/id/40280/output/print |accessdate=9 August 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt; He is wanted by the [[International Criminal Court]] for charges of [[crimes against humanity]] against the Libyan people, for allegedly torturing and killing civilians,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=War crimes court issues Gaddafi arrest warrant|work=http://www.guardian.co.uk/world/2011/jun/27/muammar-gaddafi-arrest-warrant-hague}}&lt;/ref&gt; a charge that he has denied.&lt;ref name=&quot;rt_interview&quot;&gt;{{cite news|title=Gaddafi's son: Libya like McDonald's for NATO – fast war as fast food|url=http://rt.com/news/interview-gaddafi-libya-usa/|accessdate=25 October 2011|date=July 1, 2011|agency=[[Russia Today]]}}&lt;/ref&gt; 

He was arrested on 19 November in southern Libya and flown to [[Zintan]] by plane. 

==Education and career==
In 1994, Saif al-Islam Gaddafi graduated with a [[Bachelor of science|BSc]] degree in [[Engineering Science]] from [[Tripoli]]'s [[Al Fateh University]], and earned an [[Master of Business Administration|MBA]] from [[Vienna]]'s [[IMADEC University]] in 2000.

His paintings made up the bulk of the international Libyan art exhibit, &quot;The Desert Is Not Silent&quot; (2002–2005),&lt;ref&gt;[http://web.archive.org/*/http://thedesertisnotsilent.com The Desert Is Not Silent], [http://www.archive.org/web/web.php Internet Archive] record, Historical index.&lt;/ref&gt; a show which was supported by a host of international corporations with direct ties to his father's regime.&lt;ref&gt;[http://replay.web.archive.org/20070629093129/http://www.thedesertisnotsilent.com/home/partners.asp Commercial partners of &quot;The Desert Is Not Silent&quot;], [http://www.archive.org/web/web.php Internet Archive] record, June 29, 2007.&lt;/ref&gt;

In 2008, Gaddafi was awarded a [[Doctor of Philosophy|PhD]] degree from [[London School of Economics]], for a thesis entitled &quot;The role of civil society in the democratisation of global governance institutions: from 'soft power' to collective decision-making?&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Alqadhafi, Saif Al-Islam, ''[https://catalogue.lse.ac.uk/Record/1187568 The role of civil society in the democratisation of global governance institutions: from &quot;soft power&quot; to collective decision-making?]'', [[London School of Economics]] Library, 2008.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;''[http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/8258617.stm Gaddafi son calls for democracy]'', [[BBC News]], September 16, 2009.&lt;/ref&gt; Examined by [[Meghnad Desai, Baron Desai|Meghnad Desai]] (London School of Economics) and Anthony McGrew ([[University of Southampton]]), among the LSE academics acknowledged in the thesis as directly assisting with it were [[Nancy Cartwright (philosopher)|Nancy Cartwright]], [[David Held]] and Alex Voorhoeve (the son of former Dutch minister [[Joris Voorhoeve]]). Professor [[Joseph Nye]] of [[Harvard University]] is also thanked for having read portions of the manuscript and providing advice and direction.&lt;ref&gt;Desai, Meghnad (2011) LSE is paying a heavy price for Saif Gaddafi's PhD: When it comes to Saif Gaddafi and his PhD, hindsight is indeed a wonderful thing, The Guardian, Friday March 4, 2011&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Alqadhafi, Saif Al-Islam (2008) The role of civil society in the democratisation of global governance institutions: from &quot;soft power&quot; to collective decision-making? A thesis submitted to the Department of Philosophy of the London School of Economics for the degree of Doctor of Philosophy, London, September 2007, and published 2008, p.4.&lt;/ref&gt;  In a later investigation by [[Channel 4 News]], they found that 6% of the 93,000-word thesis was copied from other sources.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://blogs.channel4.com/factcheck/5880/5880|title=Fact Check:Saif Gaddafi – Genius or Fraud?|publisher=Channel4 News|date=February 4, 2011|accessdate=February 4, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; Furthermore, allegations abound that Saif's thesis was in many parts ghost-written by consultants from Monitor Group, which pocketed $3 million per year in fees from Muammar Gaddafi.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.independent.co.uk/news/education/education-news/gaddafi-son-plagiarised-his-degree-thesis-at-lse-2229620.html|title=Gaddafi son plagiarised his thesis at LSE.|work=The Independent|date=March 2, 2011|accessdate=October 21, 2011|location=London|first=Adam|last=Sherwin}}&lt;/ref&gt; 

Speaking in [[Sabha, Libya|Sabha]] on 20 August 2008, Gaddafi said that he would no longer involve himself in state affairs. He noted that he had previously &quot;intervene[d] due to the absence of institutions&quot;,&lt;ref name=IHT&gt;[http://www.iht.com/articles/2008/08/22/mideast/libya.php &quot;Qaddafi's son declares he's leaving politics&quot;], Associated Press (''International Herald Tribune''), August 22, 2008.&lt;/ref&gt; but said that he would no longer do so. He dismissed any potential suggestion that this decision was due to disagreement with his father, saying that they were on good terms. He also called for political reforms within the context of the [[Jamahiriya]] system and rejected the notion that he could succeed his father, saying that &quot;this is not a farm to inherit&quot;.&lt;ref name=IHT/&gt;

Gaddafi was the president of the Libyan National Association for Drugs and Narcotics Control (DNAG). In 1997, he founded the official charity, the [[Gaddafi International Foundation for Charity Associations]], which intervened in various hostage situations involving Islamic militants and the crisis of the [[HIV trial in Libya]] and the resulting [[European Union]]-Libyan rapprochement.

==International diplomacy==
Saif was instrumental in negotiations that led to Libya's abandoning a [[weapons of mass destruction]] programme in 2002–2003. He arranged several important business deals on behalf of the Libyan regime in the period of [[rapprochement]] that followed. He was viewed as a reformer, and has openly criticized the regime:&lt;ref name=NYmag&gt;{{cite web |url=http://nymag.com/print/?/news/politics/saif-qaddafi-2011-5/index3.html |title=The Good Bad Son
 |author=James Verini |date=22 May 2011 |accessdate=20 June 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;{{quote|[a] congressional aide asked him what Libya needed most. His one-word answer: democracy.
&quot;You mean Libya needs more democracy?&quot; the aide asked.
&quot;No. 'More democracy’ would imply that we had some,&quot; Saif said.}}

In 2003, he published a report critical of Libya's record on human rights.

On 10 December 2004, shortly before a trip by [[Prime Minister of Canada|Canadian Prime Minister]] [[Paul Martin]] to Tripoli, in an interview with ''[[The Globe and Mail]]'' Saif requested a formal apology from the Canadian government, for joining U.S.-led sanctions against Libya after the [[Lockerbie bombing]], and for denying him a student visa to study in Canada in 1997. His request was met with incredulity in Canada, and the Canadian government announced that no apology would be forthcoming.

===HIV trial===
{{main|HIV trial in Libya}}
Saif admitted in interviews that the Bulgarian nurses charged with conspiring to deliberately infect over 400 children with HIV in 1998 had been tortured and that the government had denied them a fair trial. His admissions were said to have badly damaged his reputation in Libya.&lt;ref name=&quot;nytimes.com&quot;/&gt;

===Isratine proposal===
Saif introduced the [[Isratine proposal]] to permanently resolve the [[Israeli-Palestinian conflict]] through a [[secular state|secular]], [[federalist]], [[republicanism|republican]] [[one-state solution]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=White Book (ISRATIN)|date=May 8, 2003|url=http://www.algathafi.org/html-english/cat_03_03.htm |archiveurl=http://web.archive.org/web/20090530213120/http://www.algathafi.org/html-english/cat_03_03.htm |archivedate=2009-05-30 |accessdate=August 22, 2011 (via web.archive.org)}}&lt;/ref&gt; The first ever opinion poll survey to be undertaken in both Pakistani and Indian-controlled [[Kashmir]], conducted by [[King's College London|King's College]], London, and the polling organisation IPSOS-[[MORI]], was also Saif's brainchild,&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.outlookindia.com/article.aspx?265666 The Survey In Kashmir Was Saif Gaddafi's Idea], ''Outlook'', June 14, 2010.&lt;/ref&gt; having arisen out of discussions he had with British academic Robert Bradnock, the author of the 2010 [[Chatham House]] report on the survey.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.chathamhouse.org.uk/research/asia/papers/view/-/id/881/ Kashmir: Paths to Peace], [[Chatham House]], UK.&lt;/ref&gt;

===2008 agreement with Italy===
Saif was involved in negotiating compensation from Libya's former colonial power, [[Italy]], and on 30 August 2008 a Friendship, Partnership and Cooperation Agreement was signed in [[Benghazi]] by his father and [[Prime Minister of Italy|Italy's prime minister]] [[Silvio Berlusconi]].&lt;ref&gt;
[http://www.voanews.com/english/news/a-13-2008-08-30-voa18-66680987.html VOA: Italy to Pay $5 Billion to Libya in Landmark Accord, 30 August 2008], Ministry of Foreign Affairs, Italy.&lt;/ref&gt; However, the treaty was unilaterally annulled by Italy at the beginning of 2011, after Italy refused to consider Gaddafi government as their interlocutor.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://articles.cnn.com/2011-02-28/world/libya.italy_1_moammar-gadhafi-friendship-treaty-italian-ministry?_s=PM:WORLD |title=CNN World: Italy suspends friendship treaty with Libya |publisher=Articles.cnn.com |date=2011-02-28 |accessdate=2011-11-20}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Compensation for American terror victims===
He was also negotiating with the United States in order to conclude a comprehensive agreement making any further payments for American victims of terror attacks that have been blamed on Libya – such as the [[1986 Berlin discotheque bombing]], the 1988 [[Lockerbie bombing]] and the 1989 [[UTA Flight 772]] bombing – conditional upon U.S. payment of compensation for the 40 Libyans killed and 220 injured in the 1986 [[Operation El Dorado Canyon|United States bombing of Tripoli and Benghazi]]. On 14 August 2008, the U.S.-Libya Comprehensive Claims Settlement Agreement was signed in [[Tripoli]]. Former British Ambassador to Libya [[Oliver Miles]] described the agreement as &quot;a bold step, with political cost for both parties&quot; and wrote an article in the online edition of ''[[The Guardian]]'' querying whether the agreement is likely to work.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news
|title=The long road to normalisation|date=August 16, 2008|url=http://www.guardian.co.uk/commentisfree/2008/aug/16/libya.usa |accessdate=August 17, 2008 | work=The Guardian | location=London | first=Oliver | last=Miles}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In an August 2008 [[BBC]] TV interview, Saif Gaddafi said that Libya had admitted responsibility (but not &quot;guilt&quot;) for the Lockerbie bombing simply to get trade sanctions removed. He further admitted that Libya was being &quot;hypocritical&quot; and was &quot;playing on words&quot;, but Libya had no other choice on the matter. According to Saif, a letter admitting &quot;responsibility&quot; was the only way to end the economic sanctions imposed on Libya. When asked about the compensation that Libya was paying to the victims' families, he again repeated that Libya was doing so because it had no other choice. He went on to describe the families of the Lockerbie victims as &quot;trading with the blood of their sons and daughters&quot; and being very &quot;greedy&quot;: &quot;They were asking for more money and more money and more money&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title=Lockerbie evidence not disclosed|date=August 28, 2008|publisher=BBC |url=http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/scotland/south_of_scotland/7573244.stm |accessdate=August 29, 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Diplomacy for extraditing Libyans===
Interviewed by French newspaper ''[[Le Figaro]]'' on 7 December 2007, Saif said that the seven Libyans convicted for the [[Pan Am Flight 103]] and the [[UTA Flight 772]] bombings &quot;are innocent&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;Le Figaro&quot;&gt;{{fr}} [http://www.lefigaro.fr/international/2007/12/07/01003-20071207ARTFIG00487-seif-el-islam-kadhafi-la-libye-sera-un-pays-heureux.php Saif says &quot;Libyans are innocent&quot; of the Pan Am Flight 103 and UTA Flight 772 bombings], ''[[Le Figaro]]'', December 7, 2007.&lt;/ref&gt; When asked if Libya would therefore seek reimbursement of the compensation paid to the families of the victims (US$2.33 billion), Saif replied: &quot;I don't know.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;Le Figaro&quot;/&gt;
Saif led negotiations with Britain for the [[release of Abdelbaset al-Megrahi]], the convicted Pan Am 103 conspirator.&lt;ref name=NYmag/&gt;

In 2007, Saif al-Islam Gaddafi met with [[President of France|French President]] [[Nicolas Sarkozy]] in Tripoli, with whom it is alleged he helped broker an arms deal, including missiles.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.jpost.com/International/Article.aspx?id=70876 &quot;Sarkozy denies weapons deals to Libya&quot;], ''[[Jerusalem Post]]''. August 4, 2007. Accessed February 27, 2011.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.nytimes.com/2007/08/03/world/europe/03iht-libya.5.6979085.html?_r=1 &quot;EADS confirms it is selling military equipment to Libya&quot;], ''New York Times''. August 3, 2007. Accessed February 27, 2011.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.telegraph.co.uk/news/worldnews/africaandindianocean/libya/6073809/Profile-Colonel-Gaddafis-son-Saif-al-Islam.html &quot;Profile: Colonel Gaddafi's son Saif al-Islam&quot;], ''[[The Daily Telegraph|The Telegraph]]''. August 22, 2009. Accessed February 27, 2011.&lt;/ref&gt;

In November 2008, Saif made a high-profile visit to the United States where he met with US Secretary of State, [[Condoleezza Rice]]. During the meeting, Rice raised the case of Libya's jailed political dissident and democracy activist, [[Fathi El-Jahmi]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
|url=http://www.voanews.com/english/2008-11-20-voa58.cfm
|date=November 20, 2008
|title=Rice Meets Gadhafi Son, Raises Dissident Case
|publisher=[[Voice of America]]
|accessdate=November 21, 2008
}} {{Dead link|date=September 2010|bot=H3llBot}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Stand-off with US officials===
In 2009, Saif claimed that Libya's opinion of him was shaped largely by his role in Libya's engagement with the West, saying &quot;If something goes wrong, people will blame me, whether I am in a certain official position or not.&quot; He expressed frustration with the US, saying Libya's decision to give up its Weapons of Mass Destruction programs was contingent upon &quot;compensation&quot; from the US, including the signing of the [[Trade and Investment Framework Agreement]], economic cooperation, and cooperation in purchasing conventional weapons and military equipment. He stated, &quot;We share rich natural resources – oil and gas – along the borders, yet we have no capacity to defend that wealth.&quot; Because of a US legal embargo, Libya cannot purchase weapons from the United States, Sweden, or Germany, and has been disallowed from buying &quot;Tiger&quot; vehicles with American-manufactured engines from Jordan. He asked for greater military assistance, as Libya had committed itself to destroying chemical stockpiles, but would require at least $25 million to do so. Saif said the United States had &quot;humiliated&quot; his father during his visit to New York in 2009, and said that his father's tent and residence issues were disappointing and his UN speech had been misinterpreted. Saif said that his father was barred from visiting [[Ground Zero]], which also frustrated him. Saif held a standoff with US officials in November 2009, refusing to send a shipment of [[HEU]] back to Russia unless the United States renewed its commitment to cooperation with Libya.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news| url=http://www.nytimes.com/interactive/2010/11/28/world/20101128-cables-viewer.html#report/libya-09TRIPOLI941 | work=New York Times | first1=Alan | last1=McLean | first2=Scott | last2=Shane | first3=Archie | last3=Tse | title=A Selection From the Cache of Diplomatic Dispatches | date=November 28, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==2011 Libyan civil war==
{{See|2011 Libyan civil war}}

On 19 February, several days after the conflict began, Saif al-Islam Gaddafi announced the creation of a commission of inquiry into the violence, chaired by a Libyan judge, as reported on [[state television]]. He stated that the commission was intended to be &quot;for members of Libyan and foreign organizations of human rights&quot; and that it will &quot;investigate the circumstances and events that have caused many victims.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title=Libye: de nouveaux morts lors d'une opération des forces libyennes|url=http://www.ladepeche.fr/article/2011/02/19/1019008-libye-de-nouveaux-morts-lors-d-une-operation-des-forces-libyennes.html|accessdate=30 October 2011|newspaper=[[La Dépêche du Midi]]|date=2011-02-19|agency=[[Agence France-Presse]]}} ([http://translate.google.co.uk/translate?sl=fr&amp;tl=en&amp;js=n&amp;prev=_t&amp;hl=en&amp;ie=UTF-8&amp;layout=2&amp;eotf=1&amp;u=http%3A%2F%2Fwww.ladepeche.fr%2Farticle%2F2011%2F02%2F19%2F1019008-libye-de-nouveaux-morts-lors-d-une-operation-des-forces-libyennes.html&amp;act=url Translation])&lt;/ref&gt; Later in the month, he went on state television to deny allegations that the government had launched airstrikes against Libyan cities and stated that the number of protesters killed had been exaggerated.&lt;ref name=&quot;dailymail_gaddafi&quot;&gt;{{cite news |author=Williams, Davis; Greenhill, Sam|url=http://www.dailymail.co.uk/news/article-1360343/Libya-Gaddafi-blames-Osama-bin-Laden-hallucinogenic-pills-Nescafe-uprising.html |title=Now Gaddafi Blames Hallucinogenic Pills Mixed with Nescafe and bin Laden for Uprisings... Before Ordering Bloody Hit on a Mosque |date=25 February 2011 |work=Daily Mail |location=London |accessdate=18 March 2011 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

On 20 February, he made an extemporaneous speech on Libyan state TV, where he blamed the [[2011 Libyan civil war|civil war]] on tribal factions and [[Islamist]]s acting on their own agendas, drunken and drugged. He promised reforms, and said the alternative would be civil war causing no trade, no oil money, and the country taken over by foreigners.&lt;ref&gt;[http://english.aljazeera.net/news/africa/2011/02/2011220232725966251.html Gaddafi's son talks of conspiracy], [[Aljazeera]], February 20, 2011.&lt;/ref&gt; He closed by saying, &quot;We will not let [[Al Jazeera]], [[Al Arabiya]] and [[BBC]] trick us.&quot; Many analysts disagreed with his assessment, including [[Oliver Miles]], a former British Ambassador to Libya.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.guardian.co.uk/commentisfree/2011/feb/20/libya-protests-oliver-miles How will Libya's protests play out?], [[Oliver Miles]], ''[[The Guardian]]'', February 20, 2011.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.guardian.co.uk/world/2011/feb/20/libya-defiant-protesters-feared-dead Libya on brink as protests hit Tripoli], Ian Black, ''[[The Guardian]]'', February 21, 2011.&lt;/ref&gt; In an interview with [[ABC News]] reporter [[Christiane Amanpour]], Saif al-Islam denied that his father's regime is killing civilians.&lt;ref&gt;[http://abcnews.go.com/ThisWeek/week-transcript-saif-al-islam-saadi-gadhafi/story?id=13012239&amp;page=4 'This Week' Transcript: Saif al-Islam and Saadi Gadhafi], [[ABC News]].&lt;/ref&gt; On 28 February, a video became available online in which Saif Gaddafi appears to spur on a crowd of followers to fight the opposition, and promises weapons to them, while brandishing a [[Heckler &amp; Koch G36|G36]] [[assault rifle]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.cbsnews.com/8301-503543_162-20037200-503543.html Qaddafi's son promises weapons to followers], [[CBS News]], February 28, 2011.&lt;/ref&gt; On 27 June, an arrest warrant was issued by the [[International Criminal Court|ICC]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news| url=http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/world-africa-13927208 | work=BBC News | title=Libya: Muammar Gaddafi subject to ICC arrest warrant | date=June 27, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; In August, Saif gave an interview to the ''[[New York Times]]'' stating that Libya was becoming more closely aligned to Islamists and would likely resemble Iran or Saudi Arabia. Saif said that his father was working closely with Islamists within the rebellion to splinter the resistance.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news| url=http://www.nytimes.com/2011/08/04/world/africa/04seif.html?pagewanted=1&amp;_r=1 | work=New York Times | first=David D. | last=Kirkpatrick | title=Libya Allying With Islamists, Qaddafi Son Says | date=August 3, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In June 2011, Muammar Gaddafi and his son Saif al-Islam Gaddafi announced that they were willing to hold elections and that Gaddafi would step aside if he lost. Saif al-Islam stated that the elections could be held within three months and transparency would be guaranteed through international observers. NATO and the rebels rejected the offer, and NATO soon resumed their bombardment of Tripoli.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|last=Carey|first=Nick|title=Rebels dismiss election offer, NATO pounds Tripoli|url=http://www.reuters.com/article/2011/06/16/us-libya-idUSTRE7270JP20110616|accessdate=27 October 2011|date=June 16, 2011|agency=[[Reuters]]}}&lt;/ref&gt;

On 1 July 2011, Saif had an interview with ''[[RT (TV Network)|Russia Today]]'', where he denied the ICC's allegations that he, or his father, ordered the killing of civilian protesters. He pointed out that he is not a member of the government or the military, and therefore has no authority to give such orders. According to Saif, he made recorded calls to General [[Abdul Fatah Younis]], who later defected to the rebel forces, in order to request not to use force against protesters, to which Younis responded that they are attacking a military site, where surprised guards fired in self-defence. Saif also condemned NATO for bombing Libyan civilians, including his family members and their children, under the false pretence that their homes were military bases. He also stated that NATO offered to drop the ICC charges against him and his father if they accept a secret deal, an offer they rejected. He thus criticised the ICC as &quot;a fake court&quot; that is controlled by the NATO nations.&lt;ref name=&quot;rt_interview&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|last=Smith|first=David|title=Gaddafi's son claims Nato wants deal with Libya|url=http://www.guardian.co.uk/world/2011/jul/01/gaddafi-son-nato-libya-deal|accessdate=29 October 2011|newspaper=[[The Guardian]]|date=1 July 2011|location=London}}&lt;/ref&gt;

On 21 August, the [[National Transitional Council]] claimed that Saif al-Islam was arrested by the [[National Liberation Army (Libya)|National Liberation Army]], pursuant to an arrest warrant issued by the [[International Criminal Court]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |url=http://hosted.ap.org/dynamic/stories/M/ML_LIBYA?SITE=MIBAX&amp;SECTION=HOME&amp;TEMPLATE=DEFAULT |title=Libyan rebels enter Tripoli, arrest Gadhafi's son |agency=AP |date=August 21, 2011 |accessdate=August 21, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; However, on the early morning of 23 August, Saif al-Islam was seen by Western journalists apparently moving around under his own free will outside the [[Rixos Hotel]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news| url=http://www.foxnews.com/world/2011/08/22/reports-saif-al-islam-qaddafi-capture-false-appears-in-tripoli/ | work=Fox News | title=Reports of Saif al-Islam Qaddafi's Capture False, Appears in Tripoli | date=August 22, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://news.sky.com/home/world-news/article/16054331 |title=Tripoli, Libya: Rebels Fight For Capital As The Gaddafi Regime Appears To Near Its End &amp;#124; World News &amp;#124; Sky News |publisher=News.sky.com |date= |accessdate=2011-10-28}}&lt;/ref&gt;

After the fall of Tripoli there are several reports that Saif al-Islam went to [[Bani Walid]],&lt;ref&gt;{{url=http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=KUzLANQvSY0}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{url=http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=O44AIM3hVAA}}&lt;/ref&gt; and stayed there until the town was captured by NTC forces.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |url=http://www.alarabiya.net/articles/2011/10/26/173784.html|title=Insider describes Saif al-Islam Qaddafi escape from Bani Walid|agency=Al Arabia News |date=October 26, 2011 |accessdate=November 23, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; After he left [[Bani Walid]] his convoy was hit by a NATO air attack at Wadi Zamzam where he lost 26 of his supporters.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.telegraph.co.uk/news/worldnews/africaandindianocean/libya/8903424/Libya-relaxed-Saif-al-Islam-Gaddafi-tells-of-injury-by-Nato-infidels.html |publisher=The Telegraph|title=Libya: relaxed Saif al-Islam Gaddafi tells of injury by 'Nato infidels'|date=21 November 2011|location=London}}&lt;/ref&gt; This air strike seems to be strike conducted by NATO 17 October, where &quot;9 military vehicles near to Bani Walid&quot; were hit.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url= http://www.nato.int/nato_static/assets/pdf/pdf_2011_10/20111018_111018-oup-update.pdf| title=NATO and Libya Operational Media Update for 17 October}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.telegraph.co.uk/news/worldnews/africaandindianocean/libya/8903424/Libya-relaxed-Saif-al-Islam-Gaddafi-tells-of-injury-by-Nato-infidels.html |publisher=The Telegraph|title=Libya: relaxed Saif al-Islam Gaddafi tells of injury by 'Nato infidels'|date=21 November 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; His right hand has been wounded and according to his own explanation it happened during the NATO air strike. According to the Libyan Al Mashhad Al Leebi program, the fingers of his right hand were cut off.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.theaustralian.com.au/news/world/gaddafis-son-had-fingers-cut-off/story-e6frg6so-1226204095145|publisher=http://www.theaustralian.com.au/| title=Gaddafi's son had fingers 'cut off'|date=24 November 2011  }}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Aftermath and Capture===
With the death of [[Muammar Gaddafi]] and [[Mutassim Gaddafi]] in [[Sirte]] on 20 October, Saif al-Islam was the only member of the Gaddafi family left in Libya. He appeared on Syrian pro-Gaddafi television 22 October claiming &quot;I am in Libya, I am alive and free and willing to fight to the end and take revenge&quot;,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.digitaljournal.com/article/313227 |title=Libya's NTC claim Saif al-Islam Gaddafi captured alive, uninjured |publisher=Digitaljournal.com |date= |accessdate=2011-11-20}}&lt;/ref&gt; but his whereabouts were unknown and subject for many rumours.
[[File:Saif al-Islam Gaddafi2011.JPG|thumb|Saif al-Islam Gaddafi in a military aircraft in [[Zintan]] after he had been captured by Libyan rebels|250px|right]]
An international team of lawyers representing the interests of Saif al-Islam Gaddafi wrote to US leaders demanding that he be protected from assassination and holding the United States and NATO responsible for the Libyan leader's &quot;brutal assassination&quot; and repeated attacks on Libya's civilian population &lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.indiavision.com/news/article/topnews/241923/international-legal-team-demands-protection-for-saif-gaddafi-from-planned-nato-assassination/ | title= International legal team demands protection for Saif Gaddafi from planned NATO assassination |date=Oct 25, 2011|work=[[Indiavision news]]}}&lt;/ref&gt;

On 19 November 2011 as Saif al-Islam Gaddafi was trying to flee from Libya, he and four aides were captured,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url= http://www.indiavision.com/news/article/international/243165/gaddafis-son-hires-mercenaries-to-flee/| title=Gaddafi's son hires mercenaries to flee|date=31 October 2011|work=[[Indiavision News]]}}&lt;/ref&gt; and detained about 50 kilometers west of the town of [[Ubari]] near [[Sabha]] in southern Libya, 640 km from Tripoli. &lt;ref name=bbccapture/&gt; British Intelligence Agency MI6 had tracked his phone continuously for over a month, using the most advanced technologies. They bugged him when he made two phone calls to unidentified persons and places to say, &quot;I am fine.&quot; The official said, &quot;when someone escapes or is on heels, it is his natural instinct that he can't resist to phone his relatives that he is OK. His natural instincts led to his capture.&quot; Sources say that it was the betrayal of a Libyan nomad, Yussef Saleh al-Hotmani, that finally lead to his capture. Yussef Saleh al-Hotmani told the interviewers that he was hired to guide a man to Niger and that he was offered €1 million for job. Being offered such huge sum of money, he suspected foul play as Saif's agent did not tell him whom he was going to guide. He contacted the rebel fighters and told them where a two vehicle convoy would pass through southern Libya on the night of 18 November and this allowed the rebel fighters to ambush the convoy. Saif was taken to Zintan by plane and held captive there pending trial.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news| url=http://www.telegraph.co.uk/news/worldnews/africaandindianocean/libya/8902994/Libya-conflict-brewing-over-trial-of-Saif-al-Islam-Gaddafi.html | location=London | work=The Daily Telegraph | first=Richard | last=Spencer | title=Libya: conflict brewing over trial of Saif al-Islam Gaddafi | date=20 November 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; His capture has been confirmed by the International Criminal Court (ICC).&lt;ref name=bbccapture&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/world-middle-east-15804299|title=Gaddafi's son Saif al-Islam captured in Libya|work=BBC|date=19 November 2011|accessdate=19 November 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Personal life==
In 2009, a party in [[Montenegro]] for his 37th birthday included well-known guests such as [[Oleg Deripaska]], [[Peter Munk]] and [[Albert II, Prince of Monaco|Prince Albert of Monaco]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.visit-montenegro.com/article-mne-22184.htm Milo with billionaires at Saif Gadaffi’s birthday party], ''Visit Montenegro'', June 28, 2009.&lt;/ref&gt;

===British society===
Gaddafi has been hosted at [[Buckingham Palace]] and [[Windsor Castle]] by the [[British royal family]]. Gaddafi claims that former Prime Minister [[Tony Blair]] is a personal friend who took an interest in advising [[Libya]] on oil revenues and finance. In 2009, he spent a weekend at [[Waddesdon Manor]], home of financier [[Jacob Rothschild, 4th Baron Rothschild]], where he was the guest of [[Lord Mandelson]] and [[Nathaniel Philip Rothschild]]. He later stayed at the Rothschild holiday home in [[Corfu]]. Nathaniel Rothschild was a guest at Saif's 37th birthday celebration in [[Montenegro]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.guardian.co.uk/world/2011/feb/27/gaddafi-son-saif-al-islam-profile &quot;Saif al-Islam Gaddafi: The new face of Libyan defiance&quot;], Jamie Doward. ''[[The Guardian]]''. February 26, 2011. Accessed February 26, 2011.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.thisislondon.co.uk/standard/article-23925939-gaddafi-son-at-heart-of-british-society.do &quot;Gaddafi son at heart of British society&quot;], Joe Murphy. ''[[Evening Standard]]''. February 23, 2011. Accessed February 26, 2011.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.dailymail.co.uk/news/article-1360472/Libya-Gaddafis-son-asks-Tony-Blairs-help-crush-enemies.html?ito=feeds-newsxml &quot;Please help us, my good friend Tony Blair: Gaddafi's son asks for former PM's help to 'crush enemies'], ''[[Daily Mail]]''. February 25, 2011. Accessed February 26, 2011.&lt;/ref&gt;

==Links with the London School of Economics==
{{main|LSE Libya Links}}
Saif received his [[Doctor of Philosophy|PhD]] from the [[London School of Economics]] (LSE) in 2008.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www2.lse.ac.uk/newsAndMedia/news/archives/2011/03/director_steps_down.aspx |title=LSE Director steps down – 03 – 2011 – News archive – News – News and media – Home |publisher=.lse.ac.uk |date= |accessdate=2011-10-28}}&lt;/ref&gt; Through the [[Gaddafi International Foundation for Charity Associations|Gaddafi International Charity and Development Foundation]] (GICDF), Saif subsequently pledged a donation of £1.5&amp;nbsp;million to support the work of the LSE's Centre for the Study of Global Governance on civil society organisations in North Africa. Following the [[LSE Libya Links]] affair, the LSE issued a statement indicating that it will cut all financial ties with the country and will accept no further money from the GICDF, having already received and spent the first £300,000 instalment of the donation.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www2.lse.ac.uk/newsAndMedia/news/archives/2011/02/libya_funding.aspx Statement on Libya], [[London School of Economics]], February 2011.&lt;/ref&gt;

Pressure was put on the LSE to revoke his qualification. LSE set up a review process&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.ft.com/cms/s/0/37c54914-3fa2-11e0-a1ba-00144feabdc0.html#axzz1F5rJwcbG Pressure on LSE to annul Gaddafi son’s PhD], Chris Cook, ''[[Financial Times]]'', February 24, 2011&lt;/ref&gt; to investigate the claims in early 2011.&lt;ref&gt;Eliot Sefton, [http://www.thefirstpost.co.uk/75772,people,news,lse-investigates-saif-al-islam-gaddafi-over-phd-plagiarism-claims LSE investigates Saif Gaddafi plagiarism claims], ''[[The First Post]]'', March 1, 2011.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news | url=http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/education-12608869 | title=LSE investigates Gaddafi's son plagiarism claims | accessdate=March 4, 2011 | author=Sellgren, Katherine | date=March 1, 2011 |publisher=BBC News }}&lt;/ref&gt;

==References==
{{reflist|30em}}

==External links==
{{Portal box|Libya|Biography|Politics}}
*{{cite web|title=Gaddafi International Charity and Development Foundation|url=http://www.gicdf.org|archiveurl=http://web.archive.org/web/20110426074749/http://www.gicdf.org/|archivedate=2011-04-26}}
*[http://www.globalsecurity.org/military/world/libya/saif-qadhafi.htm Profile] at [[GlobalSecurity.org]]
*[http://af.reuters.com/article/libyaNews/idAFLDE71J0QX20110221?sp=true Factbox: Facts about Saif al-Islam Gaddafi], ''[[Reuters]]'', February 21, 2011
*[http://english.aljazeera.net/news/africa/2011/02/20112212175256990.html Profile: Libya's Saif al-Islam], ''[[Aljazeera English]]'', February 21, 2011

{{2011 Libyan civil war|state=uncollapsed}}
{{Muammar Gaddafi}}
{{Arab Spring}}
{{ICC indictees (NavBox)}}

{{Persondata &lt;!-- Metadata: see [[Wikipedia:Persondata]]. --&gt;
|NAME = Gaddafi, Saif al-Islam Muammar
|ALTERNATIVE NAMES =
|SHORT DESCRIPTION = Engineer and politician
|DATE OF BIRTH = 1972-06-25
|PLACE OF BIRTH = Tripoli, Libya
|DATE OF DEATH =
|PLACE OF DEATH =
}}
{{DEFAULTSORT:Gaddafi, Saif Al-Islam}}
[[Category:1972 births]]
[[Category:Alumni of the London School of Economics]]
[[Category:Prisoners and detainees of Libya]]
[[Category:Fugitives wanted by the International Criminal Court]]
[[Category:Fugitives wanted on crimes against humanity charges]]
[[Category:Gaddafi family]]
[[Category:Libyan engineers]]
[[Category:Libyan politicians]]
[[Category:Living people]]
[[Category:People from Tripoli]]
[[Category:People of the 2011 Libyan civil war]]
[[Category:Plagiarism controversies]]
[[Category:Academic scandals]]
[[Category:Libyan people of Hungarian descent]]

[[ar:سيف الإسلام القذافي]]
[[az:Seyf əl-İslam Müəmmər əl-Qəzzafi]]
[[map-bms:Saif al-Islam al-Qaddafi]]
[[bcl:Saif al-Islam Gaddafi]]
[[bg:Саиф ал-Ислам Кадафи]]
[[ca:Saïf al-Islam al-Gaddafi]]
[[cs:Sajf al-Islám Kaddáfí]]
[[de:Saif al-Islam al-Gaddafi]]
[[es:Saif al Islam Gadafi]]
[[eo:Saif al-Islam Kadafi]]
[[fa:سیف‌الاسلام قذافی]]
[[fr:Saïf al-Islam Kadhafi]]
[[ko:사이프 이슬람 카다피]]
[[id:Saif al-Islam al-Qaddafi]]
[[it:Saif al-Islam Gheddafi]]
[[he:סיף אל-אסלאם קדאפי]]
[[hu:Szajf al-Iszlám Kadhafi]]
[[nl:Saif al-Islam al-Qadhafi]]
[[no:Saif al-Islam]]
[[pl:Saif al-Islam al-Kaddafi]]
[[pt:Saif al-Islam Muammar Al-Gaddafi]]
[[ro:Saif al-Islam Gaddafi]]
[[ru:Каддафи, Саиф аль-Ислам]]
[[sa:मु अम्मर् गडाफ़ि]]
[[simple:Saif al-Islam al-Gaddafi]]
[[sr:Сејф ел Ислам Гадафи]]
[[sh:Sejf el Islam Gadafi]]
[[fi:Saif al-Islam Gaddafi]]
[[sv:Saif al-Islam Gaddafi]]
[[ta:சைஃப் அல்-இசுலாம் கதாஃபி]]
[[uk:Саїф аль-Іслам Каддафі]]
[[vi:Saif al-Islam Gaddafi]]
[[zh-yue:賽義夫]]
[[zh:赛义夫·伊斯拉姆·卡扎菲]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
