<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="12051641" ns="0" title="Birtles Shorrock Goble"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Infobox musical artist
| name                = Birtles Shorrock Goble
| image                 = BSGCastle.jpg
| caption            = BSG perform at Castle Towers, Sydney, Australia
| image_size            = 
| background          = group_or_band
| alias               = BSG
| origin              = 
| genre               = [[Pop music]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Rock music]]
| years_active        = 2002–2007
| label               = [[Universal Music Group|Universal]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Capitol Records|Capitol]]
| associated_acts     = [[Little River Band]] &lt;br /&gt; [[Axiom (Australian band)|Axiom]], [[Mississippi (band)|Mississippi]], &lt;br /&gt; [[The Twilights (band)|The Twilights]], [[Zoot (band)|Zoot]]
| website                 = [http://www.birtlesshorrockgoble.com/ birtlesshorrockgoble.com]
| current_members     = [[Beeb Birtles]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Glenn Shorrock]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Graeham Goble]]
| past_members        = 
}}
'''Birtles Shorrock Goble''' are an [[Australia]]n [[pop music|pop]]/[[rock music|rock]] [[Musical ensemble|group]] composed of the three original singers and songwriters of [[Little River Band]], namely [[Beeb Birtles]], [[Glenn Shorrock]], and [[Graeham Goble]]. The members are known for their extensive writing and performance of [[hit song]]s and distinctive vocal harmonies. They are sometimes referred to by the initials '''BSG'''.

==History==
Birtles, Shorrock, and Goble were vital members of popular [[Australia]]n bands prior to forming Little River Band. 

Birtles (born 28 November 1948 in [[The Netherlands]]) was part of [[Zoot (band)|Zoot]] and [[Mississippi (band)|Mississippi]]. Shorrock (born 30 June 1944 in [[England]]) provided lead vocals for [[The Twilights (band)|The Twilights]] and [[Axiom (Australian band)|Axiom]]. Goble (born 15 May 1947 in [[Australia]]) was a member of several bands including Allison Gros, Drummond, and [[Mississippi (band)|Mississippi]]. 

The concept of Little River Band was formulated in [[London]] in late 1974. The band was constituted in [[Melbourne]] and performed for the first time in [[Ballarat]] in March 1975.

Little River Band became one of Australia's first [[Supergroup (music)|supergroup]]s, achieving [[Music recording sales certification|gold and platimum awards]] for multi-million international record sales, Top 10 hits in the [[USA]] for five consecutive years (1978–1982), and headlining concerts worldwide. Songs written and sung by Birtles, Shorrock, and Goble continue to be played around the world more than 25 years after they were recorded:
*Birtles compositions include: &quot;Curiosity Killed the Cat&quot;, &quot;Every Day of My Life&quot;, &quot;Happy Anniversary&quot; (co-written with [[David Briggs (Australian musician)|David Briggs]]), &quot;Home on Monday&quot; (co-written with Glenn Shorrock)
*Shorrock compositions include: &quot;Help Is on Its Way&quot;, &quot;[[Cool Change (song)|Cool Change]]&quot;, &quot;Emma&quot;, &quot;Shut Down Turn Off&quot;, &quot;Home on Monday&quot; (co-written with Beeb Birtles)
*Goble compositions include: &quot;Reminiscing&quot;, &quot;Lady&quot;, &quot;Take It Easy on Me&quot;, &quot;It's a Long Way There&quot;, &quot;The Night Owls&quot;, &quot;The Other Guy&quot;.

==Departure from Little River Band==
Each of these three original members of Little River Band left the band at different times, and for different reasons. 
Shorrock left first in 1982 to pursue a solo career, and as a consequence of increasing tensions between band members. He was replaced as lead vocalist by [[John Farnham]].

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&quot;Basically I was told that my commitment to the group was not 100% and they wanted more commitment from their lead singer. I said I wanted to do some other things and that the songs were running down. I thought we needed to broaden our horizons a bit but that wasn't to be at that time. I was technically sacked. Beeb, Graeham, and Derek [Pellicci] wanted John Farnham in. [I] was thinking about doing solo albums and some other things with my mates.&quot; ''Glenn Shorrock'' (2003)&lt;ref&gt;Cashmere, Paul (2003) [http://www.undercover.com.au/idol/bsg.html Hang On, BSG Is On Its Way]{{dead link|date=January 2011}} [http://www.undercover.com.au/ undercover.com.au]&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

Birtles departed in 1983; his commitment as a [[born-again Christian]] had estranged him from some of the other band members, and he was unhappy with the direction and management of the band.

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&quot;Being a Christian I couldn't lie to them: I had to honestly say, 'My heart isn't here anymore and for that reason I have to leave'. The moment I said that I felt the load lift.&quot; ''Beeb Birtles'' (1989)&lt;ref name=&quot;Forbes&quot;&gt;Forbes, Clark (1989) ''Whispering Jack'', Hutchinson Australia, (ISBN 0-09-169441-8).&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
Goble retired from the band, first as a touring member(in 1989) and subsequently altogether by 1992. 

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&quot;Little River Band no longer had a recording contract and there was no immediate possibility of recording. I always preferred recording to 'live work' and when the future of the band appeared to be just playing the greatest hits for the rest of its life, then I knew it was time for me to leave.&quot; ''Graeham Goble'' (1997)&lt;ref name=&quot;Aue&quot;&gt;Aue, Frankie (1997) [http://www.lrb.net/goble/interview.shtml A web-interview with Mr Goble] 22 July 1997.&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

In 1986, Farnham left the band and LRB effectively split-up. Glenn Shorrock returned to a re-formed Little River Band in 1987. Shorrock left a second time in early 1996 over a dispute about touring.

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&quot;My fellow directors of Little River Band at the time wanted to do a five-month tour. I felt that a three-month commitment was sufficient. They had another agenda and I was informed by fax that they would be employing a substitute vocalist in my place. I attempted to stop them, I sought advice, stepped down, and accepted a financial settlement in lieu of earnings.&quot; ''Glenn Shorrock'' (2005)&lt;ref name=&quot;Miller&quot;&gt;Miller, Chuck (2005) [http://www.chuckthewriter.com/lrb.html Born in the Sign of Water] [[Goldmine (magazine)|Goldmine]], 4 February 2005.&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

Following their departures from the band, Birtles, Shorrock, and Goble continued to maintain careers in the music industry.
 
Birtles settled in the [[United States]] and continued to write songs. Along with Bill Cuomo, he formed a production company, Sonic Sorbet, and released a solo album ''Driven by Dreams'' in 2000.

Shorrock returned to his solo career, including stage shows, corporate gigs, and a career retrospective concert program. He released two solo albums, ''Spin Me 'Round'' and ''Meanwhile ... Acoustically''.

Goble moved back to his passion: recording.  Using some of the best session musicians available, he meticulously crafted four albums: ''Broken Voices'', ''Nautilus'', ''Stop'', and ''The Days Ahead'', albums which reflected his thorough and fastidious recording technique.

==Reformation==
On 28 May 2001, Shorrock and Goble were seated at the same table at the Australian [[Australasian Performing Right Association|APRA]] Awards. Old animosities were forgotten as they realised that their respective careers were inextricably linked.&lt;ref&gt;birtlesshorrockgoble.com [http://www.birtlesshorrockgoble.com/home.html Birtles Shorrock Goble: Welcome!]&lt;/ref&gt; A reunion was first discussed after record producer Paul Rodger approached Graeham Goble and Derek Pellicci with interest from [[Warner Music]] to produce a video concert like the [[Eagles (band)|Eagles]] ''[[Hell Freezes Over]]''. Subsequent telephone calls to Birtles and Shorrock confirmed that they, too, were not averse to a reunion.

The initial plans provided for Birtles, Shorrock, Goble, Pellicci, [[David Briggs (Australian musician)|David Briggs]], and George McArdle to re-form under the band name The Original Little River Band.&lt;ref&gt;Te Koha, Nui (2001) [http://www.auspaytv.com/news/dec01/01121305.htm Legends of rock to return]{{dead link|date=January 2011}} [http://www.auspaytv.com/news/ AUSPAYTV NEWS]{{dead link|date=January 2011}}, 13 December 2001.&lt;/ref&gt; Those plans were quickly frustrated when former Little River Band manager [[Glenn Wheatley]] told Birtles, Shorrock, and Goble that things would be a lot easier if they reformed on their own.{{Citation needed|date=May 2008}} It was determined that the name Little River Band and associated logos had been transferred by Wheatley and Goble to a company owned by LRB lead guitarist Stephen Housden without the permission of the other members of the band.&lt;ref name=&quot;Elder&quot;&gt;Elder, Bruce (2002) [http://www.smh.com.au/articles/2002/11/26/1038274302706.html Help is far away for a famous band] [[The Sydney Morning Herald]], 27 November 2002.&lt;/ref&gt; (See [[#Legal battles|Legal battles]].)

Wheatley decided that the three singer/songwriters would henceforth appear as '''Birtles Shorrock Goble: The Founding Members of Little River Band'''. (&quot;Not BSG,&quot; said Shorrock, &quot;it sounds like something you get at a Chinese restaurant&quot;).&lt;ref name=&quot;Elder&quot; /&gt;

After 7373 days apart, the first public performance of the reformed group would occur on 1 March 2002 at the [[Australian Grand Prix]] Ball. The hour-long set of twelve songs reprised many of their international hits.&lt;ref&gt;Birtles, Beeb (2002) [http://www.birtles.com/bsg2.html BSG 2002 Archives] [http://www.birtles.com/ birtles.com]&lt;/ref&gt;

In March 2003 Birtles Shorrock Goble appointed Paul Rodger as their manager and signed a [[recording contract]] with [[Universal Music Australia]].

==Legal battles==
The seeds of future legal conflict were sown in 1987: with a new lineup and new recording company, the members of Little River Band formed a &quot;clean slate&quot; company known as We Two Pty Ltd. The five band members at that time were made equal shareholders.&lt;ref name=&quot;Miller&quot; /&gt; Band assets, including the name and logo, were transferred into this company. Goble acknowledges that mistakes were made:

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&quot;The LRB name was never 'for sale'.  It was lost to Stephen Housden because of a legal document that transferred the name to We Two Pty. Ltd. The name should have been licensed, not transferred. We were ill-advised and totally unaware of what we were leaving behind.&quot; ''Graeham Goble'' (2005)&lt;ref name=&quot;Miller&quot;/&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

As the other members left over time, by 1997 Stephen Housden was the sole remaining member, and ownership of We Two Pty Ltd (including rights to the name Little River Band) passed to him. He formed a new version of the band and, with various personnel changes, Little River Band continues to tour North America each year.

When Birtles, Shorrock, and Goble initially proposed to re-form as The Original Little River Band, Housden asserted his rights to the name and took the matter to the [[Federal Court of Australia]]. In an out-of-court settlement, it was agreed that Birtles, Shorrock, and Goble would not use the trade mark (name) or logo as the name of their band, or in the name of their band, but &quot;shall be entitled to refer prominently but always only in a descriptive way in promotional and advertising material, to the fact that they were members of the original line up of the Little River Band&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;Federal Court of Australia (2002) [http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/federal_ct/2002/875.rtf We Two Pty Ltd v Shorrock (2002)]&lt;/ref&gt; 


Loss of access to the LRB name for Birtles, Shorrock, and Goble came as a shock to many fans and received considerable attention in the Australian media.&lt;ref name=&quot;Elder&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Gregory, Peter (2002) [http://www.theage.com.au/articles/2002/06/12/1023864297765.html The Little River Band, a name banned] [[The Age]], 13 June 2002&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;McFadyen, Warwick (2002) [http://www.theage.com.au/articles/2002/06/15/1023864363299.html A river too big to cross] [[The Age]], 16 June 2002&lt;/ref&gt; 

The settlement would be tested repeatedly, including the blocking&lt;ref&gt;Cashmere, Paul (2004) [http://www.undercover.com.au/news/2004/oct04/20041014_lrb.html Little River Band DVD Delayed Over Legal Issues]{{dead link|date=January 2011}} [http://www.undercover.com.au/ undercover.com.au], 14 October 2004&lt;/ref&gt; of a Little River Band retrospective DVD put together by Birtles, Shorrock, and Goble.&lt;ref&gt;Raymond, Jean-Luc (2004) [http://noted.blogs.com/westcoastmusic/2004/10/little_river_ba.html Little River Band: It's A Long Way There], 9 October 2004&lt;/ref&gt; Housden also challenged the manner in which BSG described their link to LRB in promotional material and recordings. Further legal action ensued in Australia&lt;ref&gt;Federal Court of Australia (2005) [http://www.austlii.edu.au/au/cases/cth/federal_ct/2005/934.rtf We Two Pty Ltd v Shorrock (No 2) (2005)]&lt;/ref&gt; and in the United States.&lt;ref&gt;Cashmere, Paul (2005) [http://www.undercover.com.au/news/2005/jul05/20050727_bsg.html Birtles, Shorrock and Goble Settle With Steve Housden]{{dead link|date=January 2011}} [http://www.undercover.com.au/ undercover.com.au], 27 July 2005&lt;/ref&gt;

When the ''Full Circle'' DVD was released in the United States, a marquee reference to Little River Band on the cover was digitally altered to &quot;?????? ????? ????&quot; [[:Image:FullCircleDVDUSA.jpg]].

==Touring==
With Birtles residing in the United States and members having solo commitments, opportunities for touring have been limited. Birtles Shorrock Goble have presented more than 70 live performances since 2002 including seven Australian tours, corporate events, and television shows.&lt;ref name=&quot;Live&quot;&gt;graehamgoble.com [http://www.graehamgoble.com/shows-bsg Reminiscing: Live Shows Birtles Shorrock Goble]&lt;/ref&gt;

In August–September 2007 Birtles Shorrock Goble toured Australia with the [[Countdown Spectacular#Countdown Spectacular 2|Countdown Spectacular 2]], which reacquainted Australian fans with many of the outstanding performers who appeared on the iconic television program [[Countdown (Australian TV series)|Countdown]]. Birtles Shorrock Goble were given penultimate billing before [[Rick Springfield]], Birtles' former bandmate in [[Zoot (band)|Zoot]]. BSG performed a medley consisting of eight of their most famous hits.

Birtles Shorrock Goble's most recent performance was on 27 September 2007 as part of the [[2007 AFL Grand Final]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Live&quot;/&gt;

==Birtles Shorrock Goble today==
Since 2007, there have been no further Birtles Shorrock Goble shows.  Whilst there has never been an official announcement of Birtles Shorrock Goble disbanding, when asked in 2010 if they would perform again, Shorrock replied &quot;No... The door is locked, but I have the key... I don’t feel the need to go back and be married to those guys again. We had a stormy marriage [but] a great marriage”.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.stevedow.com.au/default.aspx?id=508|title=Shorrock and awe|last=Dow|first=Steve|date=6 June 2010|work=stevedow.com.au|accessdate=14 July 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== ''Full Circle'' ==
Since reforming, Birtles Shorrock Goble have released a major live DVD and CD. Recorded over two nights at The Forum in Melbourne, Australia, before packed houses, ''Full Circle'' showcased all of the hits made famous by the singers and songwriters of Little River Band, together with album tracks performed during a mid-concert acoustic set. New songs written by each of the members were also introduced.

''Full Circle'' was produced by Birtles Shorrock Goble manager Paul Rodger and [[Audio mixing (recorded music)|mixed]] by longtime supporter and friend Michael Costa at Stream AV Studios in Melbourne.

Credits:

{| class=&quot;wikitable&quot;
|- 
| Beeb Birtles – Guitar, vocals
| Producer and Manager – Paul Rodger
| Tour/Production Manager – Ross Ferguson
|-
| Glenn Shorrock – Lead vocals
| Associate Producer – Michael Costa
| Lighting Designer – Chris McGuffin
|-
| Graeham Goble – Guitar, vocals
| Mix Engineer – Michael Costa
| Lighting Assistant – Jeff Wickenden  
|-
| David Beck – Drums
| Camera Director – Jon Olb
| Stage Monitors – Sid Pittlik
|-
| Simon Hosford – Lead guitar
| On Line Video Editor – Paul &quot;Sinko&quot; Sinkovich
| Stage Technicians – Mark Tinson, Josh Goble, and James Laydon
|-
| Alejandro Vega – Percussion
| Recording and Front of House Engineer – Ern Rose
| Extra Video Footage – Matt Orr
|-
| Jason Vorherr – Bass guitar
| Assistant Recording Engineer and Music Editor – Haydn Buxton
| Still Photographer – Serge Thomann
|-
| Dorian West – Keyboards, trumpet, flugelhorn, steel guitar, piano, accordion
| Digico/Digitrax D5 Operator – David Williams
| Master of Ceremonies – Barry Bissell
|}

== Discography ==

{| class=&quot;wikitable&quot;
|-
! style=&quot;width:150px;&quot;|Release
! style=&quot;width:230px;&quot;|Track listing
! style=&quot;width:300px;&quot;|Reviews and comments
|-
| 
'''''Countdown Spectacular Live 2 (CD)''''' &lt;br /&gt;
Australian release: &lt;br /&gt;
24 November 2007 &lt;br /&gt;
[[Liberation Music]]

'''''Countdown Spectacular Live 2 (DVD)''''' &lt;br /&gt;
Australian release: &lt;br /&gt;
24 November 2007 &lt;br /&gt;
[[Liberation Music]]
|align=&quot;left&quot;|
[[Little River Band]] medley: &lt;br /&gt;
1. It's A Long Way There &lt;br /&gt;
2. Reminiscing &lt;br /&gt;
3. Everyday Of My Life &lt;br /&gt;
4. Curiosity Killed The Cat &lt;br /&gt;
5. The Night Owls &lt;br /&gt;
6. Cool Change &lt;br /&gt;
7. Lonesome Loser &lt;br /&gt;
8. Help Is On Its Way 

An included compilation disc features the original song (CD) and video clip (DVD) of &quot;Lonesome Loser&quot;.
|align=&quot;left&quot;|
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&quot;Legal complications mean Little River Band's original trio of Graeham Goble, Glenn Shorrock, and Beeb Birtles can't use the band name even as they re-create perfectly those harmonies on the songs they wrote.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |first=Bernard |last=Zuel |title=Ageing rockers show how to pack a paunch |url=http://www.smh.com.au/news/music/countdown-spectacular-2/2007/08/20/1187462176526.html |work=[[The Sydney Morning Herald]] |date=2007-08-21 |accessdate=2008-01-27 }}&lt;/ref&gt; &lt;br /&gt; 

&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
&quot;By using a medley format, these guys managed to cram in more hits than anyone else, and demonstrated some fine vocal prowess.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.gusworld.com.au/blog/?p=437 |title=Countdown Spectacular 2, Newcastle: Medleys, momentum and missed opportunities |accessdate=2008-01-27 |last=Gusworld |first= |coauthors= |date=2007-08-18 |work=www.gusworld.com.au |publisher=}}&lt;/ref&gt; &lt;br /&gt; 
|-
| 
'''''Full Circle'' (DVD)''' &lt;br /&gt;
US release: &lt;br /&gt;
7 June 2005 &lt;br /&gt;
[[Capitol Records]] &lt;br /&gt; 

  &lt;br /&gt;
'''''Full Circle'' (DVD)''' &lt;br /&gt;
Australian release: &lt;br /&gt;
6 October 2003 &lt;br /&gt;
[[Universal Music]]
|align=&quot;left&quot;|
1.  Full Circle &lt;br /&gt;
2.  It's A Long Way There &lt;br /&gt;
3.  Man On Your Mind &lt;br /&gt;
4.  Curiosity Killed The Cat &lt;br /&gt;
5.  Days On The Road &lt;br /&gt;
6.  Everyday Of My Life &lt;br /&gt;
7.  Face In The Crowd &lt;br /&gt;
8.  Photogenic &lt;br /&gt;
9.  Happy Anniversary &lt;br /&gt;
10.  Take It Easy On Me &lt;br /&gt;
11.  Soul Searching &lt;br /&gt;
12.  Prelude In A Minor &lt;br /&gt;
13.  Mistress Of Mine &lt;br /&gt;
14.  Lady &lt;br /&gt;
15.  Heart &amp; Soul &lt;br /&gt;
16.  The Night Owls &lt;br /&gt;
17.  The Other Guy &lt;br /&gt;
18.  Seine City &lt;br /&gt;
19.  I'll Always Call Your Name &lt;br /&gt;
20.  Home On Monday &lt;br /&gt;
21.  Deep Water &lt;br /&gt;
22.  The Machine Room &lt;br /&gt;
23.  In The City &lt;br /&gt;
24.  Reminiscing &lt;br /&gt;
25.  Parallel Lines &lt;br /&gt;
26.  It's Cold Out Tonight &lt;br /&gt;
27.  Help Is On Its Way &lt;br /&gt;
28.  Cool Change &lt;br /&gt;
29.  Lonesome Loser &lt;br /&gt;
30.  Just Say That You Love Me &lt;br /&gt;
|align=&quot;left&quot;|
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&quot;''Full Circle'' is an excellent concert experience on DVD, and deserves a place in the collection of every music lover - it will certainly be receiving repeated viewings in my house!&quot; -- [http://www.michaeldvd.com.au/Reviews/Reviews.asp?ID=3793 MichaelDVD review]
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
|-
| 
'''''Full Circle'' (CD)''' &lt;br /&gt;
US release: &lt;br /&gt;
7 June 2005 &lt;br /&gt;
[[Capitol Records]] 

Australian release: &lt;br /&gt;
6 October 2003 &lt;br /&gt;
[[Universal Music]]
|align=&quot;left&quot;|
1. Full Circle  &lt;br /&gt;
2. It's A Long Way There  &lt;br /&gt;
3. Man On Your Mind  &lt;br /&gt;
4. Curiosity Killed The Cat  &lt;br /&gt;
5. Everyday Of My Life  &lt;br /&gt;
6. Happy Anniversary  &lt;br /&gt;
7. Take It Easy On Me  &lt;br /&gt;
8. Prelude In A Minor  &lt;br /&gt;
9. Mistress Of Mine  &lt;br /&gt;
10. Lady  &lt;br /&gt;
11. The Night Owls  &lt;br /&gt;
12. The Other Guy  &lt;br /&gt;
13. Seine City  &lt;br /&gt;
14. Home On Monday  &lt;br /&gt;
15. Reminiscing  &lt;br /&gt;
16. Help Is On Its Way  &lt;br /&gt;
17. Cool Change  &lt;br /&gt;
18. Lonesome Loser  

On the Australian release, &quot;Take It Easy On Me&quot; is placed between &quot;Lady&quot; and &quot;The Night Owls&quot;.
|align=&quot;left&quot;|
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&quot;Despite the billing on the cover, this should be filed in record collections under Little River Band.&quot; -- [{{Allmusic|class=album|id=r782207|pure_url=yes}} Allmusic.com review]&lt;/blockquote&gt; 
|-
| 
'''''[[The Spirit of Christmas 2002|The Spirit of Christmas]]''''' &lt;br /&gt;
Australian release: &lt;br /&gt;
November 2002 &lt;br /&gt;
[[Sony BMG]]
|align=&quot;left&quot;|
3. O Holy Night &lt;br /&gt;
|align=&quot;left&quot;|
&lt;blockquote&gt;
The ''[[The Spirit of Christmas (compilation album)|Spirit of Christmas]]'' is a [[compilation album]] which is released every [[Christmas]] by [[The Salvation Army]] in [[Australia]] with all proceeds going to their Red Shield Appeal, which supports at-risk children and youth. The album features carols from Australia's favourite artists and musicians. It is available through [[Myer]] stores. &lt;br /&gt; 

&lt;br /&gt;
Glenn Shorrock has previously recorded songs for ''[[The Spirit of Christmas 1993]]'', ''[[The Spirit of Christmas 1994]]'', ''[[The Spirit of Christmas 1998]]'' and ''[[The Spirit of Christmas 2000]]''.  &lt;br /&gt; 

&lt;br /&gt;
The recording of &quot;O Holy Night&quot; marked the first time that Birtles, Shorrock, and Goble had recorded together for more than twenty years. Their last combined effort was the ''Time Exposure'' album by Little River Band. &lt;br /&gt; 

&lt;br /&gt;
&quot;O Holy Night&quot; also appears on the compilation album &quot;Holiday Masters: It's Christmas Again&quot; available for download at [http://downloads.walmart.com/swap/LoadAlbumSongList.do?itemId=5347574&amp;highlightItemId=5349452 Wal-Mart]. Also on that album is Graeham Goble's Broken Voices rendition of &quot;Mary's Boy Child&quot;.
|-
| &lt;br /&gt;
'''&lt;br /&gt;
''Beginnings''''' &lt;br /&gt;
Released in 1978 &lt;br /&gt;
[[Capitol Records]] 

  &lt;br /&gt; 

 &lt;br /&gt;
[[Music for Pleasure (record label)|MFP]], [[The Netherlands]]
|align=&quot;left&quot;|
'''Volume 1''' &lt;br /&gt;
1.	Ford's Bridge &lt;br /&gt;
2.	Kings Of The World &lt;br /&gt;
3.	Will I &lt;br /&gt;
4.	Can't Let Go Of This Feeling &lt;br /&gt;
5.	Feel Alone &lt;br /&gt;
6.	Fool's Gold &lt;br /&gt;
7.	Arkansas Grass &lt;br /&gt;
8.	Where In The World &lt;br /&gt;
9.	A Little Ray Of Sunshine &lt;br /&gt;
10.	All Through The Day &lt;br /&gt;
11.	Yesterday, Today And Tomorrow &lt;br /&gt; 

'''Volume 2''' &lt;br /&gt;
12.	Samantha &lt;br /&gt;
13.	Baby Bear &lt;br /&gt;
14.	Take It Or Leave It &lt;br /&gt;
15.	All The Days &lt;br /&gt;
16.	Early Morning &lt;br /&gt;
17.	Mansfield Hotel &lt;br /&gt;
18.	Country Pickin' &lt;br /&gt;
19.	Weaver Of Life &lt;br /&gt;
20.	Who Am I Gonna See  &lt;br /&gt;
21.	Once A Month Country Race Day  &lt;br /&gt;
|align=&quot;left&quot;|

From the liner notes:
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&quot;This album features Shorrock, Birtles, and Goble on some of the finest material to emerge from their pre-Little River Band period. Of value to historian and fan alike, these tracks provide a key to the sounds that have made Little River Band a favorite of audiences throughout the world.&quot; &lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
Released originally as two separate albums on vinyl (Volume 1 and Volume 2), a compilation CD was released in 2000. 

A review: 

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&quot;An album worth getting just for good songs that deserve a listen.&quot; -- [http://www.amazon.com/dp/B00004S3KV Amazon.com review]&lt;/blockquote&gt;
|}

==Awards==
Birtles Shorrock Goble have achieved awards for songwriting, live performance, and recording sales since they reformed:

*'''2003''' – [[Music recording sales certification|Gold Award]] for sales of the ''Full Circle'' live concert DVD&lt;ref name=&quot;Awards&quot;&gt;graehamgoble.com [http://www.graehamgoble.com/reminiscing-awards Reminiscing: Awards]&lt;/ref&gt;

*'''2004''' – Inducted into the [[ARIA Hall of Fame]] with other members of the Classic Lineup of Little River Band&lt;ref&gt;Sams, Christine (2004) [http://www.smh.com.au/articles/2004/09/11/1094789737961.html ARIAs reunite Little River Band] [[The Sydney Morning Herald]], 12 September 2004.&lt;/ref&gt;

*'''2004''' – [[Mo Awards|Australian Entertainment Award]] for Classic Rock Performers of the Year&lt;ref&gt;Cashmere, Paul (2004) [http://www.undercover.com.au/news/2004/june04/20040630_bsg.html Birtles, Shorrock, Goble Score A Mo]{{dead link|date=January 2011}} [http://www.undercover.com.au/ undercover.com.au], 30 June 2004&lt;/ref&gt;

*'''2006''' – Inducted into the Australian Songwriters Association Hall of Fame&lt;ref name=&quot;Awards&quot; /&gt;

==Musicians==
Since forming in 2002, Birtles Shorrock Goble have used a small nucleus of support musicians who have mastered the original LRB sound.&lt;ref&gt;Grafton, Julius (2002) [http://www.juliusmedia.com/cxweb/article.asp?ID=163 Not the Little River Band - Live in Sydney] [http://www.juliusmedia.com/ CX magazine], 29 November 2002.&lt;/ref&gt;

*'''Lead guitar'''
**Simon Hosford 2002–2006
**[[Brett Garsed]] 2007

*'''Bass guitar'''
**Jason Vorherr 2002–2007

*'''Guitar'''
**Joshua Goble 2003, 2007
**Nathan Goble 2007

*'''Drums'''
**John Watson 2002
**Angus Burchall 2002, 2006–2007
**Dave Beck 2002–2005

*'''Keyboard'''
**Stewart Wilkinson 2002
**Dorian West 2002–2005, 2007
**Scott Griffiths 2006

*'''Percussion'''
**James Richardson 2002
**Alejandro Vega 2002–2007

==External links==
* [http://www.birtlesshorrockgoble.com/ Birtles Shorrock Goble website]
* [http://www.birtles.com/bsg.html Beeb Birtles' BSG website]

==Further reading==
Philips, Greg (2003) [http://www.australianmusician.com.au/mag/online/articles/BSG.html BSG - Birtles, Shorrock and Goble]{{dead link|date=January 2011}}, ''[[Australian Musician]]''. 

Cashmere, Paul (2003) [http://www.undercover.com.au/idol/bsg.html Hang On, BSG Is On Its Way]{{dead link|date=January 2011}} [http://www.undercover.com.au/ undercover.com.au], 3 July 2003

Kruger, Debbie (2003) [http://www.debbiekruger.com/writer/freelance/bsg.html Haaang On, BSG is on its way...], Melbourne Weekly Magazine, 6 July 2003

Cashmere, Paul (2003) [http://www.undercover.com.au/idol/bsg2.html Birtles, Shorrock, Goble]{{dead link|date=January 2011}} [http://www.undercover.com.au/ undercover.com.au], October 2003

==References==
&lt;references/&gt;

{{Little River Band}}

[[Category:Australian musical groups]]
[[Category:Australian pop music groups]]
[[Category:Australian rock music groups]]
[[Category:Little River Band members]]
[[Category:Musical groups established in 2002]]

[[sv:Birtles Shorrock Goble]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
