<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="12084106" ns="0" title="Young Frankenstein (musical)"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Infobox musical
|name= Young Frankenstein
|subtitle=
|image= Young_frankenstein_brooksa.JPG
|caption= Original Broadway Cast Album cover
|music= [[Mel Brooks]]
|lyrics= Mel Brooks
|book= Mel Brooks &lt;br&gt; [[Thomas Meehan (writer)|Thomas Meehan]]
|basis= 1974 film ''[[Young Frankenstein]]''
|productions= 2007 [[Seattle]] Tryout&lt;br/&gt;2007 [[Broadway theatre|Broadway]]&lt;br/&gt; 2009 [[United States]] Tour
&lt;!-- Please do not include production-specific (acting, directing, etc.) awards --&gt;
|awards= [[Outer Critics Circle Award|Outer Critics Circle Award for Best Musical]]
}}
'''''Young Frankenstein''''', officially known as '''''The New Mel Brooks Musical Young Frankenstein''''',  is a [[musical theatre|musical]] with a book by [[Mel Brooks]] and [[Thomas Meehan (writer)|Thomas Meehan]] and music and lyrics by Brooks. It is based on [[Young Frankenstein|the 1974 comedy film of the same name]] written by Brooks and [[Gene Wilder]] and directed by Brooks, who has described it as his best film.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | work = New Zealand Herald | title = Mel Brooks Thinks It Time for Frankenstein to Dance | date = April 10, 2006 | url=http://www.nzherald.co.nz/topic/story.cfm?c_id=265&amp;objectid=10376854 | accessdate = 2007-07-04 }}&lt;/ref&gt;  It is a [[parody]] of the [[horror film]] genre, especially the 1931 [[Universal Pictures]] adaptation of [[Mary Shelley]]'s ''[[Frankenstein (1931 film)|Frankenstein]]'' and its 1939 sequel, ''[[Son of Frankenstein]]''. 

After tryouts in [[Seattle, Washington]] and four weeks of previews, the musical opened on [[Broadway theatre|Broadway]] on November 8, 2007 to mixed reviews. The Broadway production closed on January 4, 2009 after 30 previews and 484 performances. A U.S. tour started on September 29, 2009 in [[Providence, Rhode Island]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.playbill.com/news/article/133293-Hensley_and_Bart_Put_on_the_Ritz_on_the_Road_in_Young_Frankenstein &quot;Hensley and Bart Put on the Ritz on the Road in Young Frankenstein&quot;], playbill.com, September 29, 2009&lt;/ref&gt;

==Background==
[[Image:Frankenstein-palace.jpg|thumb|right|220px|Advertisement near the [[Palace Theatre (Broadway)|Palace Theatre]].]]
After the success of his 2001 musical, ''[[The Producers (musical)|The Producers]]'', based on Brooks' earlier film of the same name, it was not surprising that Brooks would musicalize another of his successful films.  Brooks and Meehan (the same team that crafted ''The Producers'') began work on the project in April 2006.  An October 2006 reading of the first draft of the script directed by [[Susan Stroman]] (who had directed the earlier musical)&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | work = Playbill News | title = Chenoweth, Hensley, Kudisch to Star in October Workshop of ''Young Frankenstein'' | date = September 6, 2006 | url=http://www.playbill.com/news/article/101847.html  | accessdate = 2007-07-04 }}&lt;/ref&gt; featured [[Brian d'Arcy James]] as Dr. Frankenstein, [[Kristin Chenoweth]] as Elizabeth, [[Sutton Foster]] as Inga, [[Roger Bart]] as Igor, [[Marc Kudisch]] as Inspector Kemp, and [[Shuler Hensley]] as the Monster.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.playbill.com/news/article/102800.html &quot;It's FRAHN-ken-steen: Brian D'Arcy James Nabs Lead Role in Young Frankenstein Workshop&quot;, playbill.com, Oct. 18, 2006]&lt;/ref&gt; 

[[Cloris Leachman]], reprising her film role as Frau Blücher, also attended the table read, and at the time it was widely reported she would be offered the role of Blücher for the stage show.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | work = Contact Music | title = Leachman to Return for Young Frankenstein Musical | date = August 11, 2006 | url=http://contactmusic.com/news.nsf/article/leachman%20to%20return%20for%20young%20frankenstein%20musical_1013159 | accessdate = 2007-07-04}}&lt;/ref&gt;  However, [[gossip]] [[maven]] [[Liz Smith (journalist)|Liz Smith]] reported in her January 12, 2007 ''[[New York Post]]'' column that Leachman was sent a letter informing her she would not be considered for the Broadway production because the producers wanted to keep the film and stage properties separate (and also because of Brooks's concerns over Leachman's ability to perform the character consistently at her age). However, due to Leachman's success on ''[[Dancing with the Stars (US TV series)|Dancing with the Stars]]'' Brooks reportedly asked her to reprise her role as Frau Blücher after [[Beth Leavel]] left the production. However, the production closed before Leachman could take over the role.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.realitytvworld.com/news/axed-dancing-star-cloris-leachman-may-reprise-frankenstein-role-1015512.php Axed 'Dancing' star Cloris Leachman may reprise 'Frankenstein' role]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.broadwayworld.com/article/Leachman_to_Go_Dancing_with_YOUNG_FRANKENSTEIN_20010101 Leachman to Go 'Dancing' with YOUNG FRANKENSTEIN?]&lt;/ref&gt;

==Productions==
=== Seattle tryout (2007) ===
The pre-Broadway try-out played at the [[Paramount Theatre (Seattle, Washington)|Paramount Theatre]] in [[Seattle, Washington]] from August 7, 2007 through September 1, 2007. 

=== Broadway (2007-2009) ===
''Young Frankenstein'' began previews on [[Broadway theatre|Broadway]] on October 11, 2007 and opened on [[November 8]] at the [[Foxwoods Theatre]] (then the Hilton Theatre) and closed  on January 4, 2009. Directed and choreographed by [[Susan Stroman]], it starred Roger Bart as Frankenstein, [[Megan Mullally]] as Elizabeth, [[Christopher Fitzgerald (actor)|Christopher Fitzgerald]] as Igor, [[Sutton Foster]] as Inga, [[Andrea Martin]] as Frau Blucher, Shuler Hensley as The Monster, and Fred Applegate as Inspector Kemp. [[Kristin Chenoweth]] was originally cast to play Elizabeth. However, due to conflicts with filming ''[[Pushing Daisies]]'', she had to drop out from the role. Sets were designed by Robin Wagner and costumes by [[William Ivey Long]]; orchestrations were by [[Doug Besterman]].  The production had a reported $16 million-plus budget&lt;ref&gt;Brantley, Ben.[http://theater2.nytimes.com/2007/11/09/theater/reviews/09fran.html?scp=1&amp;sq=%22Young+Frankenstein%22&amp;st=nyt &quot;Who Put the Trance in Transylvania?&quot;,]''The New York Times'', November 9, 2007&lt;/ref&gt; and a top ticket price of $450 in its “differential seating.”  It also sold front row tickets for $25 each based on a lottery a few hours before each performance.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.thestage.co.uk/shenton/2007/10/puttin_on_the_ritz_and_the_understu.php Puttin’ on the Ritz (and the understudy) – The Stage – October 23, 2007 Retrieved October 25, 2007]&lt;/ref&gt; The producers indicated that they planned to buck the usual Broadway practice by not reporting Box Office returns.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.variety.com/article/VR1117974373.html?categoryId=2526&amp;cs=1 'Frankenstein' a monster production - Variety - October 19, 2007]&lt;/ref&gt;

The musical's original [[cast album]] was released on December 26, 2007, by Decca Broadway and was third on the Billboard Top Cast Album chart in the beginning of January 2008.&lt;ref&gt; [http://www.playbill.com/news/article/114155.html playbill.com article, &quot;Wicked, Jersey Boys and Young Frankenstein Are Tops on Cast Albums Chart&quot;, January 10, 2008]&lt;/ref&gt;

Replacements for the Broadway company included Kelly Sullivan as Inga; [[Beth Leavel]] as Frau Blucher; Michele Ragusa as Elizabeth Benning; and [[Cory English]] as Igor.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.broadwayworld.com/viewcolumn.cfm?colid=29200 Leavel, Ragusa and Sullivan Join 'Frankenstein' This Summer - broadwayworld.com June 23, 2008]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.broadway.com/Cory-English-Tapped-to-Play-Igor-in-Young-Frankenstein/broadway_news/5015818 Headlines: Cory English Tapped to Play Igor in Young Frankenstein]&lt;/ref&gt;

=== US tour (2009-) ===
A touring production of the show began in September 2009 at the Providence Performing Arts Center, [[Providence, Rhode Island]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.playbill.com/news/article/121705.html Young Frankenstein Will Tour Starting in Fall 2009]&lt;/ref&gt;  The cast for the tour included Roger Bart and Shuler Hensley, reprising their Broadway roles, along with Cory English (Igor), [[Brad Oscar]] (Inspector Kemp/Blind Hermit), Beth Curry (Elizabeth), Joanna Glushak (Frau Blucher) and Anne Horak (Inga).&lt;ref&gt;Jones, Kenneth.[http://www.playbill.com/news/article/131563-Together_Again_Bart_and_Hensley_Will_Tour_in_Young_Frankenstein  &quot;Together Again: Bart and Hensley Will Tour in Young Frankenstein,&quot;] playbill.com, July 30, 2009&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Gray, Channing.[http://www.projo.com/theater/content/lb_frankenstein_review_10-03-09_JRFTM17_v13.217d427.html &quot;Theatre Review:'Young Frankenstein' &quot;]''The Providence Journal'', October 3, 2009&lt;/ref&gt; 

The show went on temporary hiatus on August 8, 2010 and re-opened on September 12, 2010 with a new cast that includes Christopher Ryan as Frederick Frankenstein, Preston Truman Boyd as The Monster, David Benoit as Inspector Kemp, Janine Devita as Elizabeth, and Synthia Link as Inga. English and Glushak continued to play the roles they created on tour.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.youngfrankensteinthemusical.com/html/cast/ Young Frankenstein Cast]&lt;/ref&gt;

The show re-opened for a second National Tour on September 30, 2011 after two previews in [[Utica, New York]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.youngfrankensteinthemusical.com/tickets-and-tour-schedule Official Site] youngfrankensteinthemusical.com&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.wktv.com/community/Thousands-pack-Stanley-for-Young-Frankenstein-performance-130752413.html &quot;Thousands pack Stanley for 'Young Frankenstein' performance&quot;] wktv.com (Utica), September 28, 2011&lt;/ref&gt; The cast included A.J. Holmes (Frederick Frankenstein), Lexie Dorsett (Elizabeth), Elizabeth Pawlowski (Inga), Rory Donovan (The Monster), Pat Sibley (Frau Blucher), Christopher Timson (Igor), Britt Hancock (Inspector Kemp), and an ensemble composed of Edward Charles Carignan II, Gregory Dassonville, Michael Peter Deeb, Jerome Doerger, Brett Figel, Kinsland Howell, Lauren Kadel, Graham Keen, Stephanie Madden, Caitlin Maloney, Kevin Metzger, Ashley Gale Munzek, Sarah O'Connor, Kristen Schoen-Rene, Tug Watson, and Eric Weaver.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.youngfrankensteinthemusical.com/cast &quot;Cast list&quot;] youngfrankensteinthemusical.com&lt;/ref&gt;

==Synopsis==
The plot is largely carried over from the movie, but some scenes are expanded to musical numbers, and many gags have been added or updated.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|work=Asian Week|title=I Enjoy Being a Frankenstein Girl|date=September 8, 2007|url=http://www.asianweek.com/2007/09/08/i-enjoy-being-a-frankenstein-girl/#more-261|accessdate=2007-09-08}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Act I===
In the town of [[Transylvania]] Heights, the year 1934, the villagers celebrate the funeral procession of the [[mad scientist]], Dr. [[Victor Frankenstein|Victor von Frankenstein]]. However, Inspector Kemp, who has a wooden right arm and wooden left leg, ruins the happiness with news about the existence of Victor's grandson: Frederick, the Dean of Anatomy at [[New York]]'s best university, known as the &quot;Johns, Miriam and [[Anthony Hopkins]] School of Medicine.&quot; The village idiot Ziggy convinces the other villagers that there is no way a New York doctor would come to Transylvania, thus continuing the celebration (&quot;The Happiest Town&quot;).

In New York, [[Frederick Frankenstein]] is ashamed to be a Frankenstein, insisting his name be pronounced &quot;Fronkensteen&quot; and that he is not a madman but a scientist. He then lectures his students about the greatest mind of science (&quot;The Brain&quot;). After learning that he has inherited his grandfather's castle in Transylvania, he is forced to resolve the issue of the property. As Elizabeth Benning, Frederick's [[Engagement|fiancée]], sees him off, it is clear that their relationship is far from physical as Elizabeth enumerates all the lustful situations that she is abstaining from (&quot;Please Don't Touch Me&quot;). This number includes the show's famous much lauded attention to her breasts. 

Arriving at Transylvania Heights, Frederick meets the hunchback [[Igor (Young Frankenstein)|Igor]] (pronounced &quot;Eye-gore&quot;), the grandson of Victor's henchman, who is extremely excited to meet him. Igor tries to convince him to continue in his grandfather's footsteps (&quot;Together Again&quot;); he has already hired the services of [[Inga (Young Frankenstein)|Inga]], a yodeling lab assistant with a degree in Laboratory Science from the local community college. During a wagon ride to Castle Frankenstein, a yodeling Inga and the doctor indulge in a &quot;Roll in the Hay&quot; (Roll in the Hay). When they reach the castle, they meet the mysterious Frau Blucher, whose spoken name frightens the horses.

Once inside the castle's main living room, Frederick falls asleep reading ''[[Rebecca of Sunnybrook Farm]]'' and dreams that his grandfather and ancestors encourage him to build a monster complete with line dancing and stage-height monster puppet (&quot;Join the Family Business&quot;). He is awakened by Inga, and, after performing the film's iconic candle/bookcase sequence, they find the secret entrance to his grandfather's laboratory by following eerie violin music. They discover the mysterious violin player to be Frau Blücher, who tells of her past of festival games with the late Victor for whom she was more than just a housekeeper (&quot;He Vas My Boyfriend&quot;). After reviewing his grandfather's notes, Frederick decides to carry on the experiments in the reanimation of the dead. They dig up a huge corpse with &quot;an enormous ''schwanstuker''.&quot; The villagers gather at the local town hall for a meeting and are instructed to be on the lookout for grave robbers (&quot;The Law&quot;).

Frederick sends Igor to find a brain and entrusts him with the vital organ, but the henchman drops it, surreptitiously replacing the brain with another. Frederick creates the creature (&quot;Life, Life&quot;), who goes on a rampage shortly after waking. The doctor is distressed to find that Igor had provided a different brain whose name he recalls as &quot;Abby Normal&quot;.

Inspector Kemp and the townspeople come to investigate, pretending to welcome Frederick (&quot;Welcome to Transylvania&quot;). Frederick and his employees try to stall the villagers (&quot;Transylvania Mania&quot;) while Frau Blücher frees the Monster without letting Frederick know. Panic ensues as the monster breaks free from the stage and tramples through the house just as the Act I curtain falls.

===Act II===
Everyone goes out to search for the Monster. Even Frau Blücher tries bringing back the Monster with the music from the violin, but to no avail (&quot;He's Loose&quot;). Inga talks to the frustrated doctor (&quot;Listen to Your Heart&quot;). Frau Blücher and Igor find the two suspended on the platform, completing what Igor believes to be &quot;an experiment on the female anatomy, and Inga is assisting his brains out.&quot;

Elizabeth arrives unexpectedly in Transylvania with a large entourage (&quot;Surprise&quot;) and finds Frederick and a naked Inga, who tell her that no funny business was taking place. Meanwhile, the Monster finds a blind hermit named Harold after breaking through his house wall (&quot;Please Send Me Someone&quot;). Eventually, after Harold accidentally pours hot soup into the Monster's lap and lights his thumb (mistaking it as a cigar), the Monster is startled into another yelling rampage and leaves. Frederick locks himself into a room with the Monster, and after overcoming his fears he tells the Monster that he is a good looking fellow who is loved and will be hailed by all (&quot;Man About Town&quot;).

The Monster is presented at the [[Loews Hotels|Loews Transylvania Theatre]], now dressed as a gentleman, first walking on command, and then dancing to [[Irving Berlin]]'s &quot;[[Puttin' on the Ritz]]&quot;, complete with backup dancers and strobe lights. While taking his bow, the Monster becomes terrified when some stage lights explode. Elizabeth is kidnapped by the creature and is taken to a cave and raped. However, as her &quot;Ah! Sweet Mystery of Life&quot; demonstrates, she's now seeing a different side of the Monster and discovers what she's been yearning for in her life (&quot;Deep Love&quot;). Luring the Monster back to the castle by the music of a French horn, Frederick attempts an intelligence transfer, but the Monster does not wake, and to make things worse Inspector Kemp and the angry villagers (believing that Elizabeth has been killed by the Monster) break into the castle and bring Frederick to the gallows. The doctor is hanged after finally accepting his family name (&quot;Frederick's Soliloquy&quot;).

The Monster returns, not only able to speak articulately but also using his newly transferred medical skills to discover that Frederick is not dead, but merely unconscious and is able to bring him back to life. Just as the crowd is about to re-hang Frederick and the Monster, Elizabeth arrives. After a hopeful plot twist, the Monster proposes to Elizabeth (&quot;Deep Love&quot; (Reprise)). Then the blind Hermit's voice is heard singing. Frau Blucher announces she has a &quot;blind date&quot; with him. Igor proclaims a miracle, saying that his hump is gone, but quickly realizes that it is in the middle. Inspector Kemp and the villagers all elect the Monster as the Mayor of Transylvania which the Monster happily accepts. Suddenly, [[Count Dracula]] appears, wishing to purchase the castle on the hill, but Frederick tells him the castle is not for sale and he will be living in it and continuing the family business from now on. He then proposes marriage to Inga which she accepts. More comic surprises follow, and all lead to a happy ending that is sure to prove a life of laughter and love for all (&quot;Finale Ultimo&quot;). Just then, Inga realizes when her new husband gave the Monster his brilliant mind, the Monster gave him his  &quot;enormous ''schwanstuker''&quot; in return. &quot;Woof!&quot;

=== Differences from the original film ===
Although the plot remains mostly the same, there are several changes from the original film. &quot;The Happiest Town in Town&quot; is not based on any scene from the film. Elizabeth arrives in Transylvania earlier than in the film, where she arrives after &quot;Puttin' on The Ritz,&quot; a song performed in the film by only Frederick and the Monster; in the musical, it is sung by all the characters, except Elizabeth and the villagers. The scene from the film with the little girl is not in the musical. In the film, the Monster is lured not by a French horn but a violin, and awakens in the laboratory directly after the brain transfer; in the musical, the Villagers hang Frederick before the Monster wakes and saves him, with the ensuing finale much expanded.&lt;ref&gt;Synopsis sources:[http://www.heraldnet.com/article/20070825/ENT/108250011 Herald.net, 8/25/07] and [http://www.variety.com/review/VE1117934491.html?categoryid=33&amp;cs=1 Variety, 8/26/07]&lt;/ref&gt;

==Musical numbers==
{{col-begin}}
{{col-2}}
;Act I
*[[Overture]] - Orchestra 
*The Happiest Town In Town - Kemp and Villagers 
*The Brain - Frederick and Students 
*Please Don't Touch Me - Elizabeth and Voyagers 
*Together Again - Frederick and Igor  
*Roll in The Hay - Inga, Frederick, and Igor 
*Join the Family Business - Victor, Frederick, and Ancestors 
*He Vas My Boyfriend - Frau Blücher 
*The Law - Kemp and Villagers  
*Life, Life - Frederick, Igor, Inga, and Blücher 
*Welcome to Transylvania - Transylvania Quartet  
*Transylvania Mania - Igor, Frederick, Inga, Kemp and Villagers 
{{col-break}}
;Act II
*He's Loose - Kemp and Villagers 
*Listen to Your Heart - Inga 
*Surprise - Elizabeth, Igor, Blücher, and Entourage
*Please Send Me Someone - The Hermit
*Man About Town - Frederick
*[[Puttin' on the Ritz]] (''Music and Lyrics By [[Irving Berlin]]'')– Frederick, The Monster, Inga, Igor, and Ensemble 
*Deep Love - Elizabeth
*Frederick's Soliloquy - Frederick 
*Deep Love (Reprise) - The Monster 
*Finale Ultimo - The Company
{{col-end}}

:''Note: &quot;Alone&quot; - Elizabeth — cut in Seattle but included on the cast recording. &quot;The Law&quot; is not included on the cast recording.''

==Roles and original Broadway cast==
*Dr. [[Frederick Frankenstein]]—[[Roger Bart]]
*The Monster—[[Shuler Hensley]]
*[[Igor (Young Frankenstein)|Igor]]—[[Christopher Fitzgerald (actor)|Christopher Fitzgerald]]
*[[Inga (Young Frankenstein)|Inga]]—[[Sutton Foster]] 
*Elizabeth Benning—[[Megan Mullally]] 
*Frau Blücher—[[Andrea Martin]] 
*Inspector Hans Kemp/Harold the Hermit—[[Fred Applegate (actor)|Fred Applegate]]
*Dr. [[Victor von Frankenstein]]—Kevin Ligon

===Broadway Replacement Cast===
*Kelly Sullivan replaced Sutton Foster as &quot;Inga&quot; on July 8, 2008.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.playbill.com/news/article/119193.html Foster's Roll in the Hay in Young Frankenstein Is Over July 6]&lt;/ref&gt;
*[[Beth Leavel]] replaced Andrea Martin as &quot;Frau Blucher&quot; on July 15, 2008.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.playbill.com/news/article/119249.html Leavel Will Join Young Frankenstein a Week Early]&lt;/ref&gt;
*Michele Ragusa replaced Megan Mullally as &quot;Elizabeth Benning&quot; on August 5, 2008.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.playbill.com/news/article/118920.html Transylvanian Trio: Leavel, Ragusa, Sullivan to Join Young Frankenstein]&lt;/ref&gt;
*[[Cory English]] replaced Christopher Fitzgerald as &quot;Igor&quot; on November 25, 2008.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.playbill.com/news/article/123523.html Hump Day: Cory English Is Young Frankenstein's New Igor, Starting Nov. 25]&lt;/ref&gt;

===2009-2010 National Tour Cast===
*Dr. Frederick Frankenstein—[[Roger Bart]]
*The Monster—[[Shuler Hensley]]
*Igor—[[Cory English]]
*Inspector Kemp/Blind Hermit—[[Brad Oscar]]
*Elizabeth Benning—Beth Curry
*Frau Blucher—Joanna Glushak
*Inga—Anne Horak

===Tour Replacement Cast===
*Rye Mullis temporarily replaced Shuler Hensley as &quot;The Monster&quot; on April 8, 2010.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.shulerhensley.com/yf_tour.htm NATIONAL TOUR 2009/2010]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Hodgins, Paul.[http://articles.ocregister.com/2010-09-15/entertainment/24626742_1_young-frankenstein-frederick-frankenstein-brooks-story 'Young Frankenstein' musical is no classic but delivers the laughs] ocregister.com, September 15, 2010&lt;/ref&gt;
*Shuler Hensley returned to the role of &quot;The Monster&quot; on June 26, 2010.
*Christopher Ryan replaced Roger Bart as &quot;Frederick Frankenstein&quot; on September 12, 2010.
*Preston Truman Boyd replaced Shuler Hensley as &quot;The Monster&quot; on September 12, 2010.
*David Benoit replaced Brad Oscar as &quot;Inspector Kemp&quot; on September 12, 2010.
*Janine DiVita replaced Beth Curry as &quot;Elizabeth Benning&quot; on September 12, 2010.
*Synthia Link replaced Anne Horak as &quot;Inga&quot; on September 12, 2010.

===2011-2012 National Tour Cast===
*Dr. Frederick Frankenstein—A.J. Holmes
*The Monster—Rory Donovan
*Igor—Christopher Timson
*Inspector Kemp/Blind Hermit—Britt Hancock
*Elizabeth Benning—Lexie Dorsett
*Frau Blucher—Pat Sibley
*Inga—Elizabeth Pawlowski
*Ensemble—Edward Charles Carignan II, Gregory Dassonville, Michael Peter Deeb, Jerome Doerger, Brett Figel, Kinsland Howell, Lauren Kadel, Graham Keen, Stephanie Madden, Caitlin Maloney, Kevin Metzger, Ashley Gale Munzek, Sarah O'Connor, Kristen Schoen-Rene, Tug Watson, Eric Weaver

==Reception==
''Young Frankenstein'' generally received mixed critical reviews, and was often compared to ''[[The Producers (musical)|The Producers]]''.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.time.com/time/arts/article/0,8599,1682320,00.html ''Time'' November 9, 2007]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.nydailynews.com/entertainment/culture/2007/11/09/2007-1-09_young_frankenstein_doesnt_measure_up_to_-2.html ''Daily News'', November 9, 2007]&lt;/ref&gt; ''[[The New York Times]]'' called it &quot;an overblown burlesque revue, right down to its giggly smuttiness ... Mr. Brooks’s songs have a throwaway quality, as if they were dashed off on the day of the performance.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;[http://theater2.nytimes.com/2007/11/09/theater/reviews/09fran.html ''New York Times'', November 9, 2007]&lt;/ref&gt;  

''[[The New York Post]]'' gave a more positive review, saying that the show &quot;is nearly very good indeed&quot; and that &quot;Brooks and Stroman pull out every stop. Despite music that's more ho-hum than hummable, Brooks's lyrics are bright and witty. Better yet, the book ... does a great job, with the assistance of co-writer Thomas Meehan, in transferring the original script to the stage.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.nypost.com/seven/11092007/entertainment/theater/not_quite_a_monster_725476.htm ''New York Post'', November 9, 2007]&lt;/ref&gt;

''[[The Daily Telegraph]]'' said that &quot;Susan Stroman directs and choreographs with her usual wit and invention,&quot; but also mentioned that &quot;you cannot escape the impression that everyone is working desperately hard to animate essentially weak material, and the show fatally lacks that touch of the sublime that made ''The Producers'' so special.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.telegraph.co.uk/arts/main.jhtml?xml=/arts/2007/11/09/btfrank109.xml ''The Daily Telegraph'', November 9, 2007]&lt;/ref&gt; 

Despite mixed reviews from [[New York]] critics, ''Young Frankenstein'' was generally popular with audiences, with one attendee saying that although it didn't outdo the film, it's a &quot;fantastic [show] for those new to Broadway&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.broadwaybox.com/reviews/theater/young_frankenstein_the_musical_reviews.aspx Audience Reviews]. BroadwayBox.&lt;/ref&gt; The production won a Broadway.com Audience Award for Favorite New Broadway Musical.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.broadway.com/buzz/97390/2008-audience-award-winners-announced-young-frankenstein-tops-list-of-fan-faves/ 2008 Broadway.com Audience Award Winners; &quot;Young Franenstein&quot; Tops List]&lt;/ref&gt; 

When describing the audience's reaction, Brooks said, &quot;I love what they do. The audience knows 'Young Frankenstein' the movie; they didn't know 'The Producers.' They all neigh when anyone on stage says 'Frau Blucher.' And they can't wait for the Blind Hermit to spill the hot soup on the monster's lap. It's great to see the audience play ping-pong with the actors.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.jsonline.com/entertainment/106254363.html 'Young Frankenstein' comes alive with music | Mel Brooks musical coming to Milwaukee]&lt;/ref&gt;

==Awards and nominations==
;[[2008 Tony Awards]]
*Best Performance By a Featured Actor in a Musical (Christopher Fitzgerald) (nominee)
*Best Performance By a Featured Actress in a Musical (Andrea Martin) (nominee)
*Best Scenic Design of a Musical (Robin Wagner) (nominee)

;[[Outer Critics Circle Award]]&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.playbill.com/news/article/116967.html Playbill News: Young Frankenstein Tops Outer Critics Circle Awards Nominations&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;
*Best Musical ('''won''')
*Best Score (nominee)
*Best Director of a Musical (nominee)
*Best Actor in a Musical (Bart) (nominee)
*Best Featured Actor in a Musical (Fitzgerald &amp; Hensley) (nominees)

;[[Drama Desk Award]]&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.playbill.com/news/article/117195.html playbill article, April 28, 2008, &quot;Drama Desk Nominees Announced; Catered Affair Garners 12 Noms&quot;]&lt;/ref&gt;
*Outstanding Featured Actor in a Musical (Fitzgerald, Hensley) (nominees)
*Outstanding Featured Actress in a Musical (Martin) (nominee)
*Outstanding Lyrics (Brooks) (nominee)
*Outstanding Choreography (nominee)

;[[Drama League Award]]&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.broadwayworld.com/viewcolumn.cfm?colid=27152 Playbill News: 2007-08 Drama Leuage Award Nominations Announced&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;
*Distinguished Production of a Musical (nominee)
*Distinguished Performance (Bart, Foster) (nominee)

;[[Grammy Awards]]&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.playbill.com/news/article/123936.html Gypsy, In the Heights, Mermaid, Pacific and Frankenstein Are Grammy-Nominated&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;
*Best Musical Show Album (nominee)

;2008 Broadway.com Audience Awards&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.broadway.com/buzz/97390/2008-audience-award-winners-announced-young-frankenstein-tops-list-of-fan-faves/ 2008 Broadway.com Audience Award Winners; &quot;Young Franenstein&quot; Tops List]&lt;/ref&gt;
*Favorite New Broadway Musical ('''won''')
*Favorite Leading Actor in a Broadway Musical - Roger Bart ('''won''')
*Favorite Featured Actor in a Broadway Musical - Christopher Fitzgerald ('''won''')
*Favorite Featured Actress in a Broadway Musical - Megan Mullally ('''won''')
*Favorite Onstage Pair - Roger Bart and Sutton Foster ('''won''')

;2011 San Francisco Bay Area Theatre Critics Circle  Awards&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.playbill.com/news/article/148137-Dreamgirls-Shrek-Mandy-Patinkin-Tarell-Alvin-McCarney-Among-Nominees-for-SF-Bay-Area-Critics-Awards] playbill.com&lt;/ref&gt;
*Best Production (nominee)

==References==
{{Reflist|2}}

==External links==
*[http://www.ibdb.com/production.asp?ID=457590 IBDb entry]
*[http://www.youngfrankensteinthemusical.com/ Official Site]
* [http://www.facebook.com/youngfrankensteinmusical Young Frankenstein The Musical on Facebook]

{{Mel Brooks Films}}
{{Young Frankenstein}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Young Frankenstein (Musical)}}
[[Category:2007 musicals]]
[[Category:Broadway musicals]]
[[Category:Musicals based on films]]
[[Category:Frankenstein|Musical]]

[[ca:Young Frankenstein (musical)]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
