<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="12120961" ns="0" title="Kennesaw State University"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Infobox university
|name=         Kennesaw State University
|image=        [[Image:KSU Seal.svg|200px]]
|caption=      Seal of Kennesaw State University  
|established=  1963-10-09 
|type=         [[Public University|Public]]
|calendar          =[[Semester]]
|endowment =   [[United States dollar|U.S. $]]25.7 [[1000000 (number)|million]]&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.usg.edu/usg_stats/annual_fin_rep/2007/ Annual Financial Reports - Board of Regents of the University System of Georgia]&lt;/ref&gt;
|budget (2007)=   [[United States dollar|$]]144.3 million&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://ir.kennesaw.edu/fb/fb2007.aspx?secid=bgt&amp;pageid=bgt_101&amp;subid=budget |title=2006-2007 Fact Book |accessdate=2007-03-18 |publisher=Kennesaw State University }}&lt;/ref&gt;
|students=     23,452 &lt;ref name='Stats07'&gt;{{cite web|url=http://ir/webapp_tools/enroll_comparison_report.aspx?term_code=200708 |title= KSU Enrollment Comparisons |accessdate=2007-10-31 |publisher=Kennesaw State University Enterprise Information Management }}&lt;/ref&gt;
|staff=        1,400+ 
|faculty =     607 &lt;ref name=&quot;Stats&quot;&gt;{{cite web | title = KSU Student Profile | work = Facts and Figures | publisher = Kennesaw State University Office of Institutional Research &amp; Information Management | url = http://ir.kennesaw.edu/webapp_tools/student_profile_select_term.aspx | accessdate = 2007-03-07 }}&lt;/ref&gt; 
|president=    [[Daniel S. Papp]]&lt;ref name=&quot;president&quot; /&gt;
|provost =     Ken Harmon (interim)
|undergrad=    19,171 &lt;ref name=&quot;Stats07&quot;/&gt;
|postgrad=     2,278 &lt;ref name=&quot;Stats07&quot; /&gt;
|doctoral =
|residents=    2,193
|address        =1000 Chastain Rd &lt;br /&gt;Kennesaw, GA 30144
|city           = [[Kennesaw, Georgia|Kennesaw]]
|state          = [[Georgia (U.S. state)|Georgia]]
|country        = [[United States|USA]]    
|campus=       [[urban area|Suburban]] 470 Total (190 hectares)&lt;ref name=&quot;usg&quot;&gt;{{cite news | first= | last= | coauthors= | title=Kennesaw State University | date=2007-02-28 | publisher=Georgia Board of Regents | url =http://www.usg.edu/inst/ksu/ | work = | pages = | accessdate = 2007-03-18 | language = |archiveurl = http://web.archive.org/web/20070216112940/http://www.usg.edu/inst/ksu/ &lt;!-- Bot retrieved archive --&gt; |archivedate = 2007-02-16}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|colors=       KSU Gold, Black, Burgundy {{color box|#FEBC11}} {{color box|#000000}} {{color box|#98002E}} &lt;ref&gt;Kennesaw State University [http://www.kennesaw.edu/webmaster/guidelines/colors.html Kennesaw State University Colors]. 2010.&lt;/ref&gt;
|sports =   [[Kennesaw State Owls|Owls]]
|athletics       = [[National Collegiate Athletic Association|NCAA]] [[Division I (NCAA)|Division I]]
|mascot=        Scrappy the Owl
|nickname=     
|affiliations= [[University System of Georgia|USG]], [[Atlantic Sun Conference|Atlantic Sun]]
|website=      [http://www.kennesaw.edu/ http://www.kennesaw.edu]
|logo= &lt;center&gt;[[Image:ksu.png|200px|Kennesaw State University]]&lt;/center&gt;
}}

'''Kennesaw State University''', also referred to as '''KSU''', '''Kennesaw''', or '''Kennesaw State''', is a [[public]], [[coeducational]], [[Comprehensive school|comprehensive]] [[university]] that is part of the [[University System of Georgia]]. The university's main campus is located in [[Kennesaw, Georgia|Kennesaw]], [[Georgia (U.S. state)|Georgia]], [[United States]], approximately {{convert|20|mi|km}} north of [[Atlanta, Georgia|Atlanta]].  KSU also holds classes at the [[Cobb Galleria Centre]], [[Dalton State College]], [[Appalachian Technical College]] and [[Dallas, Georgia|
Dallas]].&lt;ref&gt;http://www.kennesaw.edu/dallas/&lt;/ref&gt; A current enrollment of 23,452 students makes KSU the third largest university in Georgia, trailing only the [[University of Georgia]] and [[Georgia State University]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.kennesaw.edu/about/ |title=About KSU |accessdate=2007-03-09 |publisher=Office of University Relations }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news | first= | last= | coauthors= | title=Semester Enrollment Reports - Fiscal Year 2007 | date=2006-11-10 | publisher=University System of Georgia | url =http://usg.edu/sra/students/enroll/fy2007/fall06.pdf | work = | pages = | accessdate = 2007-04-01 | language = }}&lt;/ref&gt; The university is well known for academic programs in business, education, nursing and Criminal Justice.

==History==
{{Expand section|date=January 2007}}
[[Image:Kennesaw State University Village Apt.jpg|thumb|right|225px|Image of the University Village at dusk.]]

The university has undergone a number of changes in name (and mission) over its relatively short existence. 

===1963===

The university was officially founded on October 9, 1963, when the [[Georgia Board of Regents]] approved the establishment of a junior college tentatively to be named [[Cobb County, Georgia|Cobb County]] [[Junior college|Junior College]].  In December 1964, [[Horace Sturgis]] was designated to serve as the future college's first president.  When the school opened it was named ''Kennesaw Junior College'' opened in fall of 1966 with an initial enrollment of 1,014 students. &lt;ref&gt;  [http://www.kennesaw.edu/history.shtml &quot;KSU: History&quot;],. Retrieved on 2011-02-24.&lt;/ref&gt; 

===1976: Kennesaw College===


Ten years later, in 1976, the former Kennesaw Junior College became a four-year college and was redesignated ''Kennesaw College''.

===1981-2006: Betty Siegel era===

In 1981 [[Betty Siegel]], known as &quot;The Betty&quot; to many people,  became the second president of KSU and the first female university president in the University System of Georgia.&lt;ref name='bizjournals'&gt;{{cite news | first=Jan | last=Costello | coauthors= | title=Betty Siegel brings out the best in people and places | date=2001-03-30 | publisher=[[American City Business Journals, Inc]] | url =http://atlanta.bizjournals.com/atlanta/stories/2001/04/02/focus1.html | work =Atlanta Business Chronicle | pages = 2 | accessdate = 2007-12-18 | language = }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name='Isakson'&gt;{{cite news | first=Johnny | last=Isakson | coauthors= | title=Floor Statement Congratulating Dr. Betty Siegel | date=2001-05-26 | publisher=[[United States Senate]] | url =http://isakson.senate.gov/floor/2005/052605siegel.htm | work = | pages = | accessdate = 2007-12-18 | language = }}&lt;/ref&gt;

In the late 1980s to mid 1990s, KSU began a period of rapid growth, including a program of expanded offerings, as well as residential housing.

In 1985, KSU initiated its first [[Graduate student#US|graduate degree]] programs, in business and education.

====1988: Kennesaw State College====

In 1988, the former Kennesaw College was renamed ''Kennesaw State College'' and [[Associate degree]]s were discontinued, except for a program in [[nursing]].

In 1990, the [[Coles College of Business]] started the nation's first degree program in professional sales, which is today ranked among the best.

====1996: Kennesaw State University====

In 1996, Kennesaw State's [[College World Series#Division II|baseball]] and [[NCAA Softball Championship|softball]] teams won the [[NCAA Division II]] national championships.  The winning Owls continued excelling in athletics including the Lady Owls 2003 win of the NCAA Women's Division II Soccer Championship and the men's basketball team win of the 2004 [[NCAA Men's Division II Basketball Championship]].  In part due to their winning Division II in 2005, the Owls joined Division I and the [[Atlantic Sun Conference]].

In 1998, the nursing program began offering options for clinical practice abroad. Practicums in Haiti were started by Dr. [[Gerónimo Lluberas]].&lt;ref&gt;«Comprehensive Program Review Self-Study for the M.S.N. Program in the [[WellStar]] Primary Care Nurse Practitioner Program,&quot;School of Nursing, College of Health and Human Services, Kennesaw State University, 2002-2003, p. 10&lt;/ref&gt; 

In 2004, KSU was recognized by the Department of Homeland Security and the National Security Agency as a National Center of Academic Excellence in Information Assurance Education.  At the time, this placed KSU among 67 other institutions recognized as CAE/IAEs with this recognition.  KSU was re-recognized in 2007.  For information on the CAE/IAE program visit the NSA web site (www.nsa.gov). &lt;rf name=’CAEIAE’&gt; {{cite web|url= http://www.nsa.gov/ia/academic_outreach/nat_cae/index.shtml |title=NSA CAE/IAE |accessdate=2010-03-25 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

Also in 2004, the USG Board of Regents approved the Bachelor of Science in Information Security and Assurance, the first degree program of its kind at a public university in the Southeast, and only the second degree program of its kind in the U.S.

In 2006, Dr. Siegel stepped down as one of the longest-serving woman university presidents in American history.  The Siegel era was marked by exponential growth and advancement for the university.

===2006-present: Daniel Papp era===

In the summer of 2006, Dr. [[Daniel S. Papp]], [[Doctor of Philosophy|Ph.D]], became the university's third president.&lt;ref name=&quot;president&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.kennesaw.edu/president/ |title=Office of the President |accessdate=2007-04-04 |last=Papp |first=Daniel |publisher=Kennesaw State University }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news | first=Arlethia | last=Perry-Johnson | coauthors= | title=Papp Named President of Kennesaw State University | date=2006-02-16 | publisher=[[University System of Georgia]] | url =http://www.usg.edu/news/2006/021606.phtml | work = | pages = | accessdate = 2007-04-04 | language = |archiveurl = http://web.archive.org/web/20070211072615/http://www.usg.edu/news/2006/021606.phtml &lt;!-- Bot retrieved archive --&gt; |archivedate = 2007-02-11}}&lt;/ref&gt;  Although the university is mostly non-traditionally aged and commuter students, there has been a renewed effort to become a more traditional campus.&lt;ref name='capital'&gt;{{cite news | first=AIXA | last=PASCUAL | coauthors= | title= KSU launches $75 million capital campaign | date=2007-10-27 | publisher= | url =http://www.ajc.com/metro/content/metro/cobb/stories/2007/10/26/ksu_1027.html | work =Atlanta Journal and Constitution | pages = | accessdate = 2007-10-31 | language = |archiveurl = http://web.archive.org/web/20071029140331/http://www.ajc.com/metro/content/metro/cobb/stories/2007/10/26/ksu_1027.html &lt;!-- Bot retrieved archive --&gt; |archivedate = 2007-10-29}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name='feasibility'&gt;{{cite news | first= | last= | coauthors= | title=KSU Athletics Feasibility Study | date=2007-06-01 | publisher=Kennesaw State University | url =http://www.cstv.com/auto_pdf/p_hotos/s_chools/kenn/genrel/auto_pdf/feasibilitystudy | work = | pages = | accessdate = 2007-10-31 | language = }}&lt;/ref&gt;  Papp's first strategic plan outlined initiatives to lead to an increase in academic standards and retention rates, and more on-campus housing.

In the Spring semester of 2007, KSU started its first doctoral programs in Education in Leadership for Learning and Education.&lt;ref name='ed'&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.kennesaw.edu/education/grad/edd/index.html |title=Graduate Studies |accessdate=2007-10-31 |publisher=Kennesaw State University Enterprise Information Management }}&lt;/ref&gt;

In the Fall semester of 2007, a new {{convert|162595|sqft|m2|abbr=on}} Social Sciences building opened for use by many of the [[Kennesaw State University College of Humanities and Social Sciences|College of Humanities and Social Sciences]] students.  Adjacent to the building, a {{convert|35000|lb|kg|abbr=on}} sculpture entitled &quot;Spaceship Earth&quot;, created by Finnish artist [[Eino]], collapsed in December 2006, three months after installation on campus.  The sculpture was intended to be a permanent reminder to future generations to take care of their delicate planet.  Ironically, the statue was made from quartzite strip-mined within the Brazilian [[Rain forest]].&lt;ref name='Birth'&gt;{{cite news | first=Angela | last=Hill | coauthors= | title=175-ton East Bay-inspired 'Earth Spaceship' needs landing pad | date=2007-03-24 | publisher=MediaNews Group, Inc | url =http://www.lexisnexis.com/ | work =Alameda Times-Star | pages = | accessdate = 2007-11-28 | language = }}&lt;/ref&gt; Reconstruction of the statue was completed on 26 October 2007.

On October 17, 2007, [[Apollo 16]] astronaut [[Charles Duke]] donated several relics from the 1972 lunar mission to Kennesaw State, including a lunar map and a checklist from the flight. It was reported to be the only checklist from an Apollo flight to be in a university library anywhere in the world.&lt;ref name='moon'&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.kennesaw.edu/library/duke/collection.htm |title=From the Moon to the Manuscript: The Charles Duke Donation - About the Collection |accessdate=2008-01-24 |work=Horace W. Sturgis Library |publisher=Kennesaw State University }}&lt;/ref&gt;

On 19 March 2008, the Board of Regents approved the university system's only [[Doctor of Business Administration]], which was also Kennesaw State's second doctoral degree.&lt;ref name='dba'&gt;{{cite news | first=Karen | last=Rosen | coauthors= | title=KSU adds doctoral degree in business, major in dance | date=2008-03-19 | publisher=[[Cox Newspapers]] | url =http://www.ajc.com/metro/content/metro/cobb/stories/2008/03/19/ksu_0319.html | work =The Atlanta Journal-Constitution | pages = | accessdate = 2008-03-19 | language = }}&lt;/ref&gt;  The regents also approved a Bachelors of Arts with a major in Dance, KSU's 46th undergraduate degree, as well as a Master of Arts in Teaching (MAT) Secondary Science degree.&lt;ref name='dba' /&gt;

Damage to the campus from the [[2009 Georgia floods]] forced administration to cancel classes from September 21–23, 2009.

== Campus ==
Kennesaw State University is located on {{convert|240|acre|ha|lk=out}} of land adjacent to [[Interstate 75|I-75]] (similar to three other Georgia universities, [[Georgia Institute of Technology|Georgia Tech]], [[Dalton State College]] and [[Georgia State University]]) where views of the campus can be seen from the highway, including Kennesaw State's &quot;University Village&quot;. KSU, which enrolls over 20,000 students, is the third largest university in the state of Georgia. Convenient to metro Atlanta and northwest Georgia, KSU is a diverse mixture of traditional and non-traditional, residential and commuter students.

=== Social Sciences Building ===
{{main|Kennesaw State University Social Sciences Building}}
[[Image:Kennesaw State Social Science Building.jpg|thumb|right|300px|A view of the Social Science Building and Spaceship Earth.]]
The Social Science building is located on the west section of campus on Campus Loop Road adjacent to the original campus historical district.  The {{convert|163000|sqft|m2|sing=on}} building features a 302 seat auditorium, a 100+ seat Cinema classroom, a newly opened digital media arts lab, and 40 classrooms with advanced technology.  The lobby features a healthy food café and study area.  The Social Science building also meets Silver Rating [[Leadership in Energy and Environmental Design|LEED]] Green Building requirements and is the first building in the [[University System of Georgia]] to meet these specifications.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.usgbc.org/ShowFile.aspx?DocumentID=2314 |title=LEED Registered Project |accessdate=2007-03-09 |format=PDF |publisher=U.S. Green Building Council }}&lt;/ref&gt;

====Spaceship Earth====
{{main|Spaceship Earth (Sculpture)}}
Located adjacent to the Social Sciences Building is a {{convert|350000|lb|kg|adj=on}} sculpture entitled &quot;Spaceship Earth&quot;, created by Finnish American artist [http://www.eino.org Eino].  The sculpture was commissioned by the Maxwell Family Foundation in memory of the late environmentalist [[David Brower]].  The sculpture was intended to be a permanent reminder to future generations to take care of their delicate planet.

In late December 2006, only three months after installation on campus, the structure collapsed.  After the collapse, Eino attributed the disaster to vandalism, but later reports that surfaced associated the collapse to poor construction.

Reconstruction was to have begun in February 2007, but was delayed until July 2007, and was finally completed on October 26, 2010.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.savespaceshipearth.com Save Spaceship Earth Alliance&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Video feed. Retrieved from http://www.youtube.com/savespaceshipearth.&lt;/ref&gt;

The sculpture, completed at an estimated cost of $1.5 million is currently recognized as the world's largest quartz sphere.{{Citation needed|date=January 2008}}

=== A. L. Burruss Building ===
[[Image:Kennesaw State Burruss Building.jpg|thumb|right|300px|A view of the A. L. Burruss Building in Spring.]]
The A. L. Burruss Building is home to the Michael J. Coles College of Business.  It is situated in the east section of campus overlooking the Campus Green.  The ground floor contains a food court with table seating for eating and studying surrounded by numerous lecture halls.  The fourth floor of the Burruss Building is a computer lab open to students and one of the campus data centers.  This building is one of the more dominant features of this sector of the campus, which contains other large structures.  At night, the tower that extends from the center of the Burruss Building facade lights up with the letters &quot;KSU&quot;.  A sidewalk west of the Burruss building leads north to university housing communities University Village and KSU Place.  A 2,500 space parking deck (&quot;Central Deck&quot;) is in construction in the buildings former surface parking lot.  The Central Deck is estimated completion of June 2008 and will accommodate parking for the entire campus.    Easy access to the developing arts district northwest of the Burruss Building (Stillwell Theatre, Performance Hall) is offered from the west exit of the Burruss Building.

=== Campus Green ===
The Campus Green is a grass area in the center of campus.  It offers students an area to relax, study, or throw a football or flying disc between classes. This aesthetic feature has become one of Kennesaw State University's best known features.{{Citation needed|date=February 2008}}  During the Spring and Fall student activity on the green can be seen during the noon and afternoon hours.  During  graduation ceremonies, the Campus Green is no longer utilized as a reception area.  Signs from the East Parking Deck lead students and visitors to the Campus Green surrounded by the towering buildings in the area (Burruss Building, Kennesaw Hall and The Student Recreation &amp; Wellness Center) which offers a unique atmosphere on this suburban campus.  The Campus Green offers direct access to Kennesaw State's James V. Carmichael Student Center.

=== Kennesaw Hall ===
[[Image:Kennesaw State Kennesaw Hall.jpg|thumb|right|300px|a view of Kennesaw Hall in early spring 2007.]]
Kennesaw Hall is home to the Bagwell College of Education and administrative offices of the university.  The Office of the President resides on the top floor of the building that can be seen from Barrett Parkway (a busy Kennesaw road a few miles (kilometers) away) and Kennesaw Mountain.  Kennesaw Hall overlooks the Campus Green and is one of the largest buildings in the East section of campus.

=== Convocation Center ===
{{main|KSU Convocation Center}}
The [[Convocation]] Center is located southeast of the Campus Green and houses the NCAA Division I men's and women's basketball programs at Kennesaw State University.  The Convocation Center is a multipurpose facility that supports academic classes, lectures, concerts, theatrical performances, athletic events, graduations, and convocation ceremonies.  The facility has locker rooms, training rooms, and offices for the athletic department.  The third floor of the center houses hospitality and conference suits that overlook the arena floor.  KSU's Convocation Center is the largest of its kind in northwest Georgia with seating for 4,800.

=== The Bentley Rare Book Gallery ===
[[Bentley_Rare_Book_Gallery|The Bentley Rare Book Gallery &amp; Special Collections]], named in honor of Fred and Sara Bentley, brings together a world-class collection of 15,000 items that spans the history of the written word in the Western World. This collection provides undergraduate students the opportunity to study original works firsthand. Recent additions to this collection includes a fourth folio Shakespeare dated 1685b and a first edition complete works of Chaucer dated 1542. Located on the basement floor of KSU's Sturgis Library, the Rare Book Gallery can be reserved for classroom visits, meetings, presentations, and is open for research by appointment.

=== Other selected buildings ===
[[Image:KSU StudentCenter.jpg|thumb|275px|right|Student Center]]
The 'historic district' of the university (Original Campus) is located in the west section of campus and includes the University College (formerly the Social Sciences Building), Pilcher Public Service and Library, Willingham Hall, Nursing, Advancement, and Technology Annex buildings.  These buildings served primarily as the home to the College of Humanities and Social Science until construction on the Social Science Building was completed at the end of 2006. In 2009, a new two-story, 1,500-seat dining hall known as &quot;The Commons,&quot;opened.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.kennesaw.edu/dining]&lt;/ref&gt; What's more, in 2008 a new $46,000,000, 915 bed freshman residence hall called &quot;University Suites&quot; opened.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.educationdesignshowcase.com/view.esiml?pid=265]&lt;/ref&gt;

=== The Dr. Bobbie Bailey &amp; Family Performance Center ===
The [http://www.kennesaw.edu/music/bpc/about.shtml Bailey Performance Center] opened its doors in October, 2007.  The $9 million facility contains a 630-seat auditorium made to accommodate a variety of performance ensembles, The Gwendolyn Brooker Rehearsal Hall, and the Don Russell Clayton Gallery.
While serving as the heart of Kennesaw State's School of Music, the center hosts rehearsals, masterclasses, recording sessions, and recitals for the music faculty and students.

== Academics ==
{{Expand section|date=March 2007}}

===Profile===
Kennesaw State University is accredited by [[Southern Association of Colleges and Schools]] and is a public institution in [[Georgia (U.S. state)|Georgia]] and is overseen by the [[Georgia Board of Regents]].  As of spring 2007, 19,245 students were enrolled with the largest enrollment being in fall semester 2006 at 19,854.&lt;ref name=&quot;Stats&quot;/&gt;  Over three-quarters of the student body come from [[Cobb County, Georgia|Cobb]],  [[Cherokee County, Georgia|Cherokee]], or [[Fulton County, Georgia|Fulton]] counties,&lt;ref name=&quot;Stats&quot;/&gt; while 9% of the student body come from over 136 countries world wide.&lt;ref name=&quot;Stuinfo&quot;&gt;{{cite web | title = KSU Student Profile | work = Facts and Figures | publisher = Kennesaw State University Office of Institutional Research &amp; Information Management | url = http://ir.kennesaw.edu/fb/fb2007.aspx?secid=stu&amp;pageid=stu_124&amp;subid=demo | accessdate = 2007-03-17 }}&lt;/ref&gt;  About 70% undergraduates are full-time, while the figure for graduate students is 31%.  As of Spring 2007, 56% of undergraduates are under 23 years old; over half (57%) of its graduate students are between 23 and 34 years of age.&lt;ref name=&quot;Stats&quot;/&gt;

For fall 2006, 36% were in its Bagwell College of Education; 35% of graduate enrollments were in the [[Coles College of Business]].  That semester also saw the university continue its trend of having significantly more female (61%) than male (39%) students.  As of 2004, '''KSU''' has the third-largest university enrollment within the [[University System of Georgia]], out of the 34 universities and colleges in the system.&lt;ref name=&quot;Stats&quot;/&gt;

There are 607 faculty members at Kennesaw State with 37% being assistant professors.&lt;ref name=&quot;fac&quot;&gt;{{cite web | title = KSU Student Profile | work = Facts and Figures | publisher = Kennesaw State University Office of Institutional Research &amp; Information Management | url = http://ir.kennesaw.edu/fb/fb2007.aspx?secid=fac&amp;pageid=fac_106&amp;subid=faculty | accessdate = 2007-03-17 }}&lt;/ref&gt;  38% of faculty are tenured and 43% are on a tenured track.  Kennesaw State is currently ranked 10th among other four-year [[University System of Georgia|USG]] institutions with faculty having a [[doctorate]] degree, at 74%.&lt;ref name=&quot;fac&quot; /&gt;

In 2008 for the first time, [http://colleges.usnews.rankingsandreviews.com/college/masters-south-uc-rank U.S. News] polled top college officials to identify schools that have recently made the most promising and innovative changes in academics, faculty, students, campus or facilities. Kennesaw State was among 70 colleges that received the most nominations. KSU was the only public institution in Georgia cited on the list of “Up-and-Coming” schools. [http://news.kennesaw.edu/access/story.asp?sto=419 Additional Details]
Kennesaw State was also the only college in Georgia recognized for its efforts to help freshmen acclimate to the rigors of college life. For the sixth consecutive year, KSU’s First-Year Experience program was cited as a “Program to Look For” by the magazine.

----

===Colleges and degrees===

The university is divided into eight colleges and offers 43 [[bachelor's degree]]s, 16 [[master degree]] programs, and two [[doctoral]] programs.&lt;ref name=&quot;college&quot;&gt;{{cite web | title = KSU Student Profile | work = Facts and Figures | publisher = Kennesaw State University Office of Institutional Research &amp; Information Management | url = http://ir.kennesaw.edu/fb/fb2007.aspx?secid=acd&amp;pageid=acd_136&amp;subid=programs | accessdate = 2007-03-17 }}&lt;/ref&gt;  

{| style='border:1px solid #dddddd; background-color:#fefefe; padding:3px; margin:0px'
|
*'''[[Kennesaw State University College of Arts|College of the Arts]]'''
*'''[[Kennesaw State University College of Science &amp; Mathematics|College of Science &amp; Mathematics]]'''
*'''[[Coles College of Business]]'''
*'''[[Kennesaw State University University College|University College]]'''
|
*'''[[Bagwell College of Education]]'''
*'''[[WellStar College of Health and Human Services]]'''
*'''[[Kennesaw State University College of Humanities and Social Sciences|College of Humanities and Social Sciences]]'''
*'''[[Kennesaw State University Graduate College|Graduate College]]'''
|}

===Continuing Education===
Kennesaw State's Continuing Education, the largest in the nation, is housed in the KSU Center, located a mile away from the main campus.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.kennesaw.edu/coned/fact_sheet.htm |title=Continuing Education Fact Sheet |accessdate=2007-03-09 |publisher=Department of Continuing Education |archiveurl = http://web.archive.org/web/20070517135416/http://www.kennesaw.edu/coned/fact_sheet.htm &lt;!-- Bot retrieved archive --&gt; |archivedate = 2007-05-17}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Kennesaw State is home to the state's largest [http://ksuetc.org Educational Technology Training Center (ETTC)]. The ETTC is one of 13 such centers around the state. Teachers and other school personnel from around the state come to the KSU ETTC for professional development.

KSU's Computer Science and Information Systems department hosts the [http://elections.kennesaw.edu/ Center for Election Systems], which certifies and monitors the [[DRE voting machine|direct recording electronic]] machines used in Georgia elections and trains local elections officials.

== Student life ==
=== Student groups ===
KSU has over 170 registered student groups and organizations for student participation.  Some of the more active organizations in recent years have been Greeks, Religious Life, and [http://www.kennesaw.edu/student_life/intramurals.shtml Club Sports].  There are seven [[line-item]] student organizations, [http://www.ksusg.com/ Student Government], [http://www.ksukab.com/ Kennesaw Activities Board], [http://www.ksuaasa.com/ African American Student Alliance], Global Society, International Student Association, Graduate Students Association and Student Media.  These organizations are awarded a line-item budget yearly ranging from $30,000 to $144,000 that is spent on student programing and activities.  Many of these groups give stipends to their members up to 100 percent of tuition and fees.  All other student organizations have the opportunity to spend up to $350 per year on program from the Student Life budget.  The budgets for student organizations are awarded by the Student Activities and Budget Advisory Committee, which is a majority student, faculty and staff run advisory committee to the Vice President of Students.  This committee meets regularly during the fall and spring semesters approving new organizations, funding requests and [[by-law]] changes.

===Student government===
The purpose of KSU's Student Government is to promote understanding and involvement among all members of the campus community, and to represent and legislate the interest of the university's student body on a campus-wide, local, state, and federal level in accordance with KSU statutes, student codes of conduct, and the policies of the Board of Regents.  All active students at KSU are allowed to vote in the yearly elections during spring semester.  Student Government is made up of the President, Executive Vice President, Parliamentarian, Secretary, Treasurer and five appointed and confirmed Directors and 28 senator positions.  The Student Government has weekly meetings where they discuss and pass legislation, listen to testimony from administrative officials and plan/discuss upcoming campus events.  Senators and a Director (the chair) are separated into five standing committees to facilitate in legislative development. The five standing committees are: Academic Affairs, Student Services, Press and Public Relations, External Affairs, and Operations.

=== Student media ===

*''[[The Sentinel (KSU)]]'' is the official [[newspaper]] for KSU.  It is printed weekly during fall and spring semesters and twice during the summer semester.
*[http://ksutalon.com/ ''The Talon''] is the feature magazine for Kennesaw State University.
*[http://www.ksushare.com/ ''Share''] is KSU's national award winning magazine that features the work of KSU students.
*[http://www.ksuradio.com/ &quot;OWL Radio&quot;] is the student run radio station for KSU.  Currently content is streamed online with live365.
*Talisman is the name of the former Student Yearbook for KSU.

===Greek life===
Kennesaw State University is home to twenty-one fraternities and sororities: five of the [[North-American Interfraternity Conference]] (IFC), four of the [[National Panhellenic Conference]] (NPC), eight of the [[National Pan-Hellenic Council]] (NPHC), and two of the [[National Multicultural Greek Council]] (MGC). 

IFC 

[[Delta Chi]] &lt;br /&gt;
[[Delta Tau Delta]] &lt;br /&gt;
[[Kappa Sigma]] &lt;br /&gt;
[[Pi Kappa Alpha]] &lt;br /&gt;
[[Pi Kappa Phi]] &lt;br /&gt;
[[Theta Chi]] 

NPHC &lt;br /&gt;
	 
[[Alpha Kappa Alpha]] &lt;br /&gt;
[[Delta Sigma Theta]] &lt;br /&gt;
[[Sigma Gamma Rho]] &lt;br /&gt;
[[Zeta Phi Beta]] &lt;br /&gt;
[[Alpha Phi Alpha]] &lt;br /&gt;
[[Kappa Alpha Psi]] &lt;br /&gt;
[[Omega Psi Phi]] &lt;br /&gt;
[[Phi Beta Sigma]] 

Panhellenic Association	

[[Delta Phi Epsilon (social)|Delta Phi Epsilon]] &lt;br /&gt;
[[Gamma Phi Beta]] &lt;br /&gt;
[[Phi Mu]] &lt;br /&gt;
[[Alpha Omicron Pi]] 

MGC           

[[Lambda Theta Alpha]] &lt;br /&gt;
[[Lambda Theta Phi]] 

There are also two service organizations (1 sorority and 1 fraternity) at KSU:

[[Omega Phi Alpha]] &lt;br /&gt;
[[Alpha Phi Omega]]

== Athletics ==
[[Image:Kennesaw State Scrappy.JPG|thumb|right|300px|Scrappy mascot during new student orientation.]]
{{main|Kennesaw State Owls}}
Kennesaw State University's sports teams are called the ''Fighting [[Owl]]s'' and the ''Lady Owls''.  The Athletic Director for the university is Vaughn Williams. Athletic Director Vaughn Williams was hired in April 2011 and previously had served for six and a half years as UConn’s associate athletic director, where he is responsible for strategic planning, facility master planning, and policy and procedure improvement. The Owls participate in [[NCAA]] Division I [[Atlantic Sun Conference]] (and previously Division II [[Peach Belt Conference]]).  The school mascot is Scrappy (the fighting Owl).  The university's biggest sport is its basketball program. Past NCAA Division II National Championships include: Baseball (1996), Men's Basketball (2004), Cheerleading (2004, 2005), Women's Soccer (2003), Softball (1995, 1996).  The Men's Baseball team also won an NAIA National Championship (1994). Kennesaw State is one of two division II schools to win a national championship in four different sports. Grand Valley State University being the other.  KSU also has several other regional and divisional championships.

== Notable people ==
=== Alumni ===
*Susan Sewell, VP Media Relations, ABC Television
*[[Larry Nelson]], Senior PGA Golf Pro
*[[Ty Pennington]], host of ABC's ''[[Extreme Makeover: Home Edition]]'' and TLC's ''[[Trading Spaces]]''
*Robert Henry, pianist, [[Carnegie Hall]] and [[Kennedy Center]] performer
*Cindy Bowden, U.S. Olympian
*Doug Stoner, Georgia State Senator
*[[Andy Azula]], advertising director, creator of a series of [[United Parcel Service|UPS]] commercials
*Ken Burris, First COO of the [[United States Fire Administration]]
*[[Kandice Pelletier]], Miss New York 2005, appeared on CBS's ''[[The Amazing Race]] 10 ''
*[[Cale Yarbrough]], [[mixed martial arts|Mixed Martial Arts (MMA)]] fighter, former cast member of [[SpikeTV]]'s ''[[The Ultimate Fighter 7]]''
*[[Willie Harris]], Washington Nationals [[Major League Baseball]] player, [[World Series]] Champion with [[Chicago White Sox]], 2005
*[[Mac Powell]], Lead Singer of the Contemporary Christian Band &quot;[[Third Day]]&quot;
*Haley Kilpatrick, The founder of [[Girl Talk Inc.]]
*Sean Jerguson, Georgia State Representative
*Nick Ayers, executive director, [[Republican Governors Association]]
*[[James Wade Jr.]], professional basketball player

=== Professors and scholars ===
*[[Newt Gingrich]], former Speaker of the U.S. House of Representatives, visiting History professor
*Dr. [[Gerónimo Lluberas]], College of Nursing, international physician, humanitarian, musician
*Dr. [[Britain J. Williams]], Computer Science professor emeritus, national expert on election systems
*[[Bob Barr]], former U.S. Congressman, adjunct professor teaching a course on privacy rights (Spring 2008), 2008 [[Libertarian Party (United States)|Libertarian Party]] Nominee for [[President of the United States]]
*[[Rhubarb Jones]], former radio diskjockey, professor of Mass Communications
*[[Dr. Kerwin Swint]], Author and Professor of Political Science, internationally known expert on elections, political campaigns, and political history

==References==
&lt;div class='references-small'&gt;
{{reflist|2}}
&lt;/div&gt;

== External links ==
*[http://www.kennesaw.edu/ Kennesaw State Official Website]
*[http://www.ksuowls.com/ KSU Owls Athletic Website]
*[http://ir.kennesaw.edu/ Kennesaw State University Institutional Research]
{{coord|34.037876|-84.58102|region:US_type:edu|display=title}}

{{Kennesaw State Navbox}}
{{Colleges and universities in metropolitan Atlanta}}
{{Atlantic Sun Conference}}

{{UnivSysGa}}

[[Category:Kennesaw State University| ]]
[[Category:University System of Georgia]]
[[Category:Educational institutions established in 1963]]
[[Category:Universities and colleges in Georgia (U.S. state)]]
[[Category:Kennesaw, Georgia]]
[[Category:Marietta, Georgia]]
[[Category:American Association of State Colleges and Universities]]
[[Category:Universities and colleges accredited by the Southern Association of Colleges and Schools]]
[[Category:Education in Cobb County, Georgia]]
[[Category:Buildings and structures in Cobb County, Georgia]]
[[Category:Visitor attractions in Cobb County, Georgia]]

[[de:Kennesaw State University]]
[[no:Kennesaw State University]]
[[simple:Kennesaw State University]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
