<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="12184429" ns="0" title="Yaqui Chub"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Taxobox
| name = Yaqui Chub
| status = EN | status_system = IUCN2.3
| image =  
| regnum = [[Animalia]]
| phylum = [[Chordata]]
| classis = [[Actinopterygii]]
| ordo = [[Cypriniformes]]
| familia = [[Cyprinidae]]
| genus = ''[[Gila]]''
| species = '''''G. purpurea'''''
| binomial = ''Gila purpurea''
| binomial_authority = ([[Charles Frédéric Girard|Girard]], 1856)
| synonyms = }}

The '''Yaqui Chub''' ('''''Gila purpurea''''') is a species of [[ray-finned fish]] in the [[Cyprinidae]] family.
It is found in [[Northern Mexico]] and the [[United States]]. The Yaqui Chub is a medium-sized minnow fish that historically occurred in streams of Rios Matape, Sonora, and the [[Yaqui River|Yaqui]] systems of Sonora, Mexico. It is one of the five species of the ''Gila'' genus in Arizona. The Yaqui Chub is closely related to ''G. ditaenia'' (of Sonora, Mexico), and ''G. orcutti'' (of the Los Angeles Plain in California); and shares several physical characteristics with the'' G. orcutti'' (Arroyo Chub), but proves different by having a black wedge near the base of the caudal fin. 

==Description==										
The Yaqui Chub has a short and rounded snout, which causes the mouth to be small and slightly subterminal. It has large eyes placed on a thick head, placed on a deep body. This is different from the posterior portion of the body, which is much thinner. The Yaqui Chub has enlarged scales that are roughly imbricated. Coloration is usually dark overall, but sometimes has a lighter underside. The Yaqui Chub’s lateral bands are underdeveloped, making them quite difficult to observe. However, a vertically placed, triangle-shaped spot is usually present on the caudal fin. &lt;ref&gt;Minckley, W.L. 1973. Fishes of Arizona. Arizona Game and Fish Department, Phoenix. pp. 107-108.&lt;/ref&gt; 
&lt;br /&gt;Very few Yaqui Chub can grow to about 17.8 cm (7 in) long, while the average length of this fish is less than 13 cm (5.1 in) long. &lt;ref&gt;Rinne, J.N., and W.L. Minckley. 1991. Native fishes of arid lands: a dwindling resource of the desert southwest. U.S. Department of Agriculture, Forest Service, General Technical Report RM-206. Rocky Mountain Forest and Range Experiment Station, Fort Collins, Colorado.&lt;/ref&gt; Juveniles are usually 40-50 mm (1.6-2 in). 

==Range==	
	Although the current distribution of the Yaqui Chub in Mexico is unknown, there are records that show that this species has been introduced and established in Leslie Creek, in the [[Swisshelm Mountains]] of Arizona in 1969. &lt;ref&gt;Minckley, W.L. 1973. Fishes of Arizona. Arizona Game and Fish Department, Phoenix. pp. 107-108.&lt;/ref&gt; This fish can also be found in the [[San Bernardino National Wildlife Refuge|San Bernardino]] (SBNWR) and [[Leslie Canyon National Wildlife Refuge]]s of Cochise County in Arizona. Specifically in the SBNWR, the current distribution of the Yaqui chub ranges from Leslie Creek, to the House, Twin, North, and Mesquite Ponds, and the El Coronado Ranch (Turkey Creek). The Yaqui Chub heavily rely on the [[artesian well]]s and springs of the SBNWR.

==Habitat==
	Yaqui Chubs prefer living in deep pools of smaller streams with dense vegetation in the water; however, some individuals inhabit cleaner, open areas near the gravel bottoms that are covered with large amounts of algae. Habitat: [[Deep]], [[vegetated pools]] of [[Stream|creeks]] and [[spring runs]].

==Diet==
	When available, Yaqui Chub are known to eat aquatic insects and small fish; however, Yaqui Chub consume algae, terrestrial insects, and arachnids more often. &lt;ref&gt;Minckley, W.L. 1973. Fishes of Arizona. Arizona Game and Fish Department, Phoenix. pp. 107-108.&lt;/ref&gt;

==Reproduction==
	Although Yaqui Chub breed sporadically in the summer, young usually spawn around March. &lt;ref&gt;Rinne, J.N., and W.L. Minckley. 1991. Native fishes of arid lands: a dwindling resource of the desert southwest. U.S. Department of Agriculture, Forest Service, General Technical Report RM-206. Rocky Mountain Forest and Range Experiment Station, Fort Collins, Colorado.&lt;/ref&gt; Fish have a distinct coloration during the breeding season: males turn into a “steely-blue” color, while the females become a drearier, yellowish-brown color. 

==Conservation==
	The U.S. population of the Yaqui Chub is low, but stable. However, there are still several threats present, including: increased aquifer pumping, reduction of flows in streams, predation of nonnative fishes, overgrazing, and successive erosion. Protection of the San Bernardino aquifers, and observation of nonnative fishes near the chub stream must be taken into account in order for this species to continue to exist. &lt;br /&gt;
However, some protective measures have been taken in an attempt for Yaqui Chub conservation. In 1980, the Nature Conservancy purchased the San Bernardino Ranch, and eight years later, bought Leslie Canyon, both of which harbor strong Yaqui Chub populations. These places bought by the conservancy were then sold to the U.S. Fish &amp; Wildlife service, to be established as National Wildlife Refuges. Soon after, a “Recovery Plan for the Endangered and Threatened fishes of the [[Yaqui River|Rio Yaqui]]” was organized, and is still under review. The plan’s main goal was to keep the habitats that the Yaqui Chub are currently occupying stable, which includes the habitats in Mexico and Arizona. &lt;ref&gt; USDI, Fish and Wildlife Service. 1984. Endangered and Threatened Wildlife and Plants;
Final Rule to Determine the Yaqui Chub to be an Endangered Species with Critical Habitat, and to determine the Beautiful Shiner and the Yaqui Catfish to be Threatened Species with Critical Habitat. Federal Register 49(171):34490-34497.&lt;/ref&gt; The plan also involved conducting extensive research on the biology and habitat requirements for the Yaqui Chub. 




==References==
{{reflist}}

==Source==
* Contreras-Balderas, S. &amp; Almada-Villela, P. 1996.  [http://www.iucnredlist.org/search/details.php/9190/all Gila purpurea].   [http://www.iucnredlist.org 2006 IUCN Red List of Threatened Species. ]  Downloaded on 19 July 2007.

{{Cyprinidae-stub}}
[[Category:Chub]]

[[ca:Gila purpurea]]
[[es:Gila purpurea]]
[[pt:Gila purpurea]]
[[sr:Gila purpurea]]
[[vi:Gila purpurea]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
