<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="1221360" ns="0" title="Club Necaxa"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{For|the Honduran team|C.D. Necaxa}}
{{Infobox football club
|  clubname  = Necaxa
| current    = 2011–12 Club Necaxa season
|  image     = [[Image:Necaxa logo.svg|150px]]
|  fullname  = Club Necaxa
|  nickname  = {{nowrap begin}}''Rayos'' (Bolts) &lt;br /&gt;''Hidro-Rayos'' (Water Bolts)  &lt;br /&gt;''Los Electricistas'' (The Electricians) &lt;br /&gt; ''Los rojiblancos'' (The red and whites) &lt;br /&gt; ''Orgullo Nacional'' (National Pride) &lt;br /&gt; ''Los once hermanos'' (Eleven brothers){{nowrap end}}
|  founded   = {{Start date and years ago|1923|8|21}}
|  ground    = [[Estadio Victoria]],&lt;br /&gt;[[Aguascalientes]], [[Aguascalientes, Aguascalientes|Aguascalientes]]
|  capacity  = 25,500
| chrtitle   = President
| owner      = {{flagicon|Mexico}} [[Televisa]]
| chairman   = {{flagicon|Mexico}} Luis Ogarrio Kalb
| mgrtitle   = Manager
| manager    = {{flagicon|Mexico}} Luis Francisco García
| league     = [[Liga de Ascenso]]
| Season     = [[Liga de Ascenso de México Clausura 2009|Clausura 2009]]
| Position   = 17th
| Web        = http://www.necaxafutbol.com/
|pattern_la1=_red_stripes|pattern_b1=_necaxa1112h|pattern_ra1=_red_stripes|pattern_sh1=_necaxa201112h||pattern_so1=_necaxa201112h|
  leftarm1=FFFFFF|body1=FFFFFF|rightarm1=FFFFFF|shorts1=FFFFFF|socks1=FFFFFF|
  pattern_la2=|pattern_b2=_necaxa201112a|pattern_ra2=|
  leftarm2=ff0000|body2=CCCCCC|rightarm2=ff0000|shorts2=FF0000|socks2=FF0000|
}}

'''Necaxa''' is a Mexican [[Association football|football]] club and is based in the city of [[Aguascalientes]]. it plays in the [[Estadio Victoria]]. Necaxa is ranked seventh overall and 1st in ranking in Mexican football within the [[IFFHS]] Central and North America's Clubs of the Century in the [[CONCACAF]] behind CD Saprissa San Juan de Tibás of San Costa Rica., After abandoning the First Division league or Professional league, the club plays in the [[Mexico]] Promotion League [[Liga de Ascenso de Mexico]]. The First Division League is currently ranked number 12 in the world and 10th with in the latter part of the decade (2001–2010) by the IFFHS. The Promotion league of Mexico or Liga de Ascenso de Mexico (Second DIvision) is ranked 11th in world of second tier of the pyramids in football. Necaxa is a non membership-based club and with more than 35,000 members outside Mexico.

==History==
===Foundation (Light and Power Company, ''Luz y Fuerza'') (1899–1920)===

Necaxa was founded August 21, 1923. Its early history began when Englishman '''William H. Frasser''', an [[engineer]] and owner of the Light and Power Company (''Compañia de Luz y Fuerza '') in the state of Puebla, and in which he decided to found a [[Association football|football]] team. Frasser, as a student was a devoted football player in the United Kingdom and was a strong advocate for the sport and admired literature.  Frasser consolidates the teams of the Light and Power Company and the Street Car operators ''Compañia de Luz y Fuerza and Tranvías'' in a whole. Frasser economically supported the newly and merged team with company revenue and funds. In addition, the Light and Power Company offered steady employment to players in an era where half of the players were playing at an amateur level.&lt;ref name=&quot;ReferenceA&quot;&gt;La serie Mexico Nuevo Siglo: Rueda de la Fortuna Los Rayos&lt;/ref&gt; However, [[Federación Mexicana de Fútbol Asociación|the Mexican football federation]] did not allow teams to be named after private companies, the team was decided to change its name to Necaxa, after the river of the [[Necaxa River|same name]] that was in close proximity to the electrical plant.
&lt;!-- Deleted image removed: [[File:Luz y fuerza.jpg|right|thumb|300px|Club in 1923 when they were known as '''Luz y Fuerza''']] --&gt;
Historians assert that the colors and Necaxa's crest came from following the arrival of the Cornish community in Mexico,&lt;ref&gt;^ Logan James (reprint 1976). ''The Scottish Gael Or Celtic Manners''. John Donald Publishers Ltd. pp. 249–250. ISBN 100859760219.&lt;/ref&gt; the Cornish community flourished and stayed in Central Mexico until the Mexican Revolution in 1910. Although the Cornish community in Mexico broadly returned to Cornwall, they left a cultural legacy; Cornish pasties, Cornish mining museums,a Cornish Mexican Cultural Society and of course Football, are all part of the local heritage and tradition in and around Mineral del Monte.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.bbc.co.uk/insideout/content/articles/2008/09/30/south_west_cornish_miners_s14_w3_feature.shtml &quot;The Cornish in Mexico&quot;], bbc.co.uk, 30 September 2008, retrieved 2009-09-07&lt;/ref&gt;
In 1923, it was also decided Necaxa team would field all players regardless of origin and race and nationality.

Necaxa organization and foundation was cemented on its history as &quot;Football as a sport which is inclusive and open to all regardless of origin, race ,social status and nationality&quot;.

In that era, the team was called &quot;Los Electricistas&quot; (''The Electricians''). The team adopted the colors red and white as their primary team colors, earning them the nickname &quot;Los roji-blancos&quot;.   Also during this period, the oldest rivalry in Mexican football began to form, between Necaxa and [[Atlante]].

On September 14, 1930, having already been a 2-time champion of the amateur [[Copa Mexico|Copa Eliminatoria]], Necaxa inaugurated its stadium named [[Parque Necaxa]], located on the banks of '''La Piedad River''' on land donated by the Frasser Family. The stadium had a maximum capacity for 15,000 fans, and was known for its memorable clock tower displaying the team's emblem.

Necaxa, in the early days of Mexican Football were members of the Mexican League Amateur Football Association '''[[Primera Fuerza|Liga Mexicana de Fútbol Amateur Association]]''', composed of '''[[Atlante]]''', '''[[Real Club España|Club España]]''', '''[[Germania FV]]''', and seasoned and disciplined team '''[[Asturias F.C.]]'''. Necaxa won championships during the 1932-33, 1934–35, 1936–37, 1937-38. seasons.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.rsssf.com/tablesm/mexhist.html#ama&lt;/ref&gt;

The following season after the stadium's opening, iconic players such as Hilario López and Luis Pérez contributed to the team's success, leading Necaxa all the way to the League final against [[Atlante]], losing 3-2.

But Necaxa would rebound the next season, smashing Atlante by a scandalous 9-0 score. The line-up Necaxa used on that day was the following: 

{|
|valign=&quot;top&quot;|

'''Mexico'''
* {{flagicon|Mexico}} [[José Ruíz]]
*
* {{flagicon|Mexico}} '''Raul Chávez'''
* {{flagicon|Mexico}} '''Garfias'''
* {{flagicon|Mexico}} '''Conception Pérez'''
* {{flagicon|Mexico}} '''Marures'''

* {{flagicon|Mexico}} '''Luis &quot;Pichojos&quot; Pérez'''
* {{flagicon|Mexico}} '''Roberto Jardón'''

 |width=&quot;100&quot;|&amp;nbsp;
|valign=&quot;top&quot;|

'''Foreign'''
* {{flagicon|Peru}} '''Julio Lorez'''
* {{flagicon|England}} '''A.Lonergan'''
* {{flagicon|England}} [[Alfred Crowle]]
|}

During this decade, Necaxa became one of the most popular teams in Mexico. Under the direction of the '''Ernst Pauler''', Necaxa, in one season of play (1935–36), the team dominated and won unforgettable titles.  Titles ranging from Champion of Champions, Champion of the Liga Mayor De La Ciudad, National Champion of League, National Champion and Central American Champions. Their last title, The Central American Championship in [[El Salvador]], where, according to History,  it was the first incident were a club masquerade itself as the national team and won all of their matches and winning and propelling Mexico Futbol into the international spotlight with in the region.

1935 Caribbean games lineup
 
{|
|valign=&quot;top&quot;|

'''Mexico'''
* {{flagicon|Mexico}} [[Raúl Estrada]]
*
* {{flagicon|Mexico}} '''Alfonso Riestra'''
* {{flagicon|Mexico}} '''Antonio Azpiri'''
* {{flagicon|Mexico}} '''Lorenzo Camarena'''
* {{flagicon|Mexico}} '''Miguel Pizano '''

* {{flagicon|Mexico}} '''Guillermo &quot;Perro&quot; Ortega'''
* {{flagicon|Mexico}} '''Ignacio Avila'''
* {{flagicon|Mexico}} '''Felipe &quot;Diente&quot; Rosas'''
 |width=&quot;100&quot;|&amp;nbsp;
|valign=&quot;top&quot;|
* {{flagicon|Mexico}} '''Vicente García '''
* {{flagicon|Mexico}} '''Tomás Lozano'''
* {{flagicon|Mexico}} '''Hilario López'''
* {{flagicon|Peru}} '''Julio Lores  '''
* {{flagicon|Mexico}} '''Luis &quot;Pichojos&quot; Pérez'''
* {{flagicon|Mexico}} '''Luis García Cortina'''
* {{flagicon|England}} [[Alfred Crowle]]&lt;ref&gt;http://www.senorgol.nu/mexico/mexseleccionconvocatorias.htm&lt;/ref&gt;
|}
Paco Martinez de la Vega, an aficionado, would coin the surname for the very first time&quot; Campeonismo&quot; or &quot;Championshipism&quot; in which Necaxa's would later use to justify their achievements and titles.&lt;ref name=&quot;ReferenceA&quot;/&gt;

===Late 1930s: Once Hermanos===

Following the aftermath and effects of the Mexican Revolution, The late 1930s represented Necaxa's most successful all Mexican team. The Once Hermanos or &quot;Eleven Brothers&quot; period was coined by many in that era due to that team's ability of working and playing as a team, great communication on the field and the ability to execute perfectly on the field during competition play. This team was composed of many talented individuals. This Necaxa team,by 1936, wins the [[Copa Mexico]] And in that same year, the emergence of a talented individual gained popularity within Necaxa's benches and competitive play.  Even though he was not one of the original &quot;once hermano&quot; or &quot;eleventh brother&quot; '''Horacio Casarìn''', was a great player in the Mexican league national ranks, Casarin great ability and qualities as a striker, propelled him to succeed and excel on the field, his success even took him to the big screen in [[Mexican Cinema]].&lt;ref name=&quot;ReferenceA&quot;/&gt;

'''Necaxa's &quot;Once Hermanos&quot; lineup'''
{|
|valign=&quot;top&quot;|

'''Mexico'''
* {{flagicon|Mexico}} '''Raúl &quot;Pipiolo&quot; Estrada'''
*
* {{flagicon|Mexico}} '''Pichojos Pérez'''
* {{flagicon|Mexico}} '''Toño Aspiri'''
* {{flagicon|Mexico}} '''Chamaco&quot; García'''
* {{flagicon|Mexico}} '''Hilario López'''
* {{flagicon|Mexico}} '''Poeta Lozano'''
 |width=&quot;100&quot;|&amp;nbsp;
|valign=&quot;top&quot;|
'''Mexico'''
* {{flagicon|Mexico}} '''Abuelo Camarena'''
* {{flagicon|Mexico}} '''Calavera Ávila'''
* {{flagicon|Mexico}} '''Marcial &quot;Ranchero&quot; Ortiz'''
* {{flagicon|Mexico}} '''Chino López'''
* {{flagicon|Mexico}} '''Ivan vazquez moralesa'''
* {{flagicon|Mexico}} '''Gerado &quot;Day&quot; Madriz'''
|}

&lt;div style=&quot;position: relative;&quot;&gt;

===1940s brief hiatus===

Necaxa disappears from competitive play with in the Mexican League in 1943&lt;ref&gt;http://www.mediotiempo.com/futbol/editoriales/carlos-calderon/2009/06/el-necaxa-iii-los-gloriosos-anos-30&lt;/ref&gt; altogether due to the [[Professionalism|professionalization]] of Mexican Football. As new ownership and new heirs of the team attempt to take the team in a new direction, stating its famous phrase '''&quot;the competitive spirit of Club Necaxa is not reasonable with the Commercialization of Football&quot;'''. it would be half a decade were the Necaxa emblem and uniform would be represented on the field again.&lt;ref name=&quot;ReferenceA&quot;/&gt;

===1950-60s resurgence===
Seven years later, Club Necaxa returns to competitive play under the conditions of the commercialization of the Mexican league. Under the new ownership of the '''Union of Electricians''' and '''Juan Jose Rivas Rojas''', Club Necaxa plays their first game on September 25, 1950 in the old district of '''Oblatos''', in a stadium called '''Parque Oblatos''' or &quot;Oblatos Stadium&quot; otherwise called the Municipal Stadium of '''Felipe Martinez Sandoval''' in [[Guadalajara]], [[Mexico]]. This park inaugurated Necaxa's comeback to the Football which would lodge them in the heart of [[Guadalajara]], counting on great facilities for the time which became the great grand stage of [[Jalisco]], [[Mexico]].''' Necaxa''' won many supporters in [[Jalisco]] at this time. In the fifties, Necaxa were tenants and played in the Federal District of Mexico City in present day [[Estadio Azul]] (1950–1955).

In the late sixties, Necaxa, becomes a handful of new tenants, plays football in Estadio Azteca in Mexico City. A modern illumination system in Estadio Azetca was inaugurated on June 5, 1966 with the first night game between Valencia C.F. and Necaxa. The first goal of the game was scored by Honduran José Cardona. In this game Roberto Martínez o Caña Brava scored the first goal made by a Mexican. Estadio Azteca was the largest stadium in Latin America, and the fifth largest stadium in the world. The stadium is the first stadium to host two FIFA World Cup finals, in 1970 and 1986. It is also the home of the &quot;Game of the Century&quot; semi-final match between Italy and Germany at the 1970 FIFA World Cup. The Azteca stadium has also hosted the Summer Olympics, the Panamerican Games. It is also renownedly known throughout North America and South America as the home [[Home]] stadium for the Mexico national football team. 

Throughout the 1950s Necaxa struggled financially to keep afloat
In 1955, large debts obligate Necaxa to sell the majority of its star players. '''Miguel Ramierz Vazquez''' a new owner, contracts the services of the [[Uruguay]]an coach '''Donald Ross''', who eventually took [[Guadalajara]] to a championship 1957, begins a road to stability, yet, not winning championships.

The electricians won the Title cup in 1960 and the following year, in the University Olympic stadium in Brazil, &quot;the electricians&quot; defeated Rey Pele and the talented club and team of the Santos of Brazil in a official match.  This was an impressive feat in that era, &quot;Morocho&quot; Dante Juarez assisted in two victorious goals in Necaxa's win over the Santos de Brazil.

Through the early '60s, Necaxa struggles financially until it is sold and  new ownership,'''Julio Orvañanos''' purchases the team and brings a championship in 1965&amp;ndash;1966.&lt;ref name=&quot;ReferenceA&quot;/&gt;

===Mexico 68 and Carlos Albert vs Necaxa===
In this decade,the organization was in deep financial trouble, the team poor attendance in Mexico City,due the population unrest and other factors to a precursor to [[Mexico 68]]. The late Sixties Club Necaxa experiences issues internally which placed the players, management and ownership in disagreement. In this  decade in the late '60s and early '70s, The organization had many internal issues.

The case of Carlos Albert begins with a small group of Veteran soccer players in the spring of 1969. Club Necaxa Veteran players petitioned the organization for better wages and argued that as a team and group, they have always responded to the team's performance. Carlos Albert was the face of the disagreement between the players and management.

Under contract, Albert was placed by Necaxa Management as transferable and was retained with half of his salary, although he asked management to be void his contract in order, to avoid loss of income and to be able to continue playing in the League with another team. Necaxa Management did not accept his request.

The courts failed in favor of Necaxa on Thursday 8 October 1971, and  Necaxa was forced to pay 77 thousand pesos to Carlos Albert by the concept of indemnification by his services from 1961. This case motivated several players to request a better treatment and rights of Mexican Soccer players. The Case of Carlos Albert and Necaxa was the first incident an organization and several players organized. Carlos Albert,who had left, set an organized a movement by a labor(Union)collective contract in Mexican Soccer.

===Atlético Español 1971 to 1982===

On September 19, 1971, Club Necaxa experiences financial trouble and becomes in debt with players and Management. Ownership, in the Federal District of Mexico City, decides to sell the club to a group of Capitalist wealthy businessmen from Spain. The ownership handles the player contracts, disputes and the franchises debt. The new Spaniard ownership successfully restructure contracts and make Club Necaxa financially solvent. The new ownership takes the organization with its already rich history to a new directive in order to attract more fans. This Necaxa plays under the name of the Spanish Athletic Bulls or &quot; Toros del [[Atlético Español]] &quot;.  The reason for the name change was due to their nationality and ideology in the world of business.
In this decade of the seventies,Club Necaxa loses many fans within Mexico city due to the Spaniard ownership decision to change its name and unsuccessful attempts in capturing a championship title. In 1975 the organization would win their first and only international title in the [[CONCACAF Champions' Cup]], they played the final against Transvaal of Suriname defeating them 5-1 in aggregate. In 1973-74 they would reach the final against a strong Cruz Azul. They would play a two legged tie in which the Atlético Español would win the first leg 2-1 but lose the second 3-0, becoming sub champion of the league.
Notable players who distinguished themselves in [[Atlético Español]] were,the Brazilian striker Carlos Eloir Perucci, Ricardo Brandón, Salvador Plascencia,'Sabanita' Rivera
Juan Santillán,and of course Tomás Boy, under the direction of Miguel Marín, 'the Witch' Gutiérrez,
Enrique Díaz and 'Chucho' Prado and the Chiliean Prieto.&lt;ref&gt;http://necaxa.blogspot.com/search/label/La%20Vieja%20Guardia&lt;/ref&gt;
In 1982, the Spanish ownership within the Federal District of Mexico city decides to sell the Franchise due to several internal issues.  A new group of Capitalist Mexican businessmen purchase Necaxa by 1982, then Monopoly telecommunications Giant Grupo Televisa, establish the organization's original name from 1971 and opens its training Facilities in Cuautitlán Izcalli in the state of Mexico.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.elsiglodedurango.com.mx/noticia/6015.necaxa-deja-cuautitlan.html&lt;/ref&gt; This ownership in Mexico City rename the Franchise Necaxa by 1982 after the Cultural and historical importance of the Franchise in Mexican Soccer. While the whole country of Mexico experiences a financial crisis called &quot; the Lost Decade &quot;  or &quot;[[La Decada Perdida]]&quot;&lt;ref&gt;http://www.econlink.com.ar/subdesarrollo/decada-perdida&lt;/ref&gt;  in the 80s' and early '70s, Necaxa in the '80s struggles against two relegation matches. One at the end of the 1982&amp;ndash;1983 season against [[Zacatepec]] and another by the end of the 1984&amp;ndash;1985 season against [[Club Universidad de Guadalajara|Leones U de G]]. 

Atlético Español Footballers: Goalkeepers: Julito Aguilar, Jan Gomola, Goyo Cortez,Enrique Vazquez del Mercado, Defense: El Pimienta Rico, Juan Manuel Alvarez, Mario Trejo, Midfielder: Juan Carlos Rodriguez Vega, Manuel Manzo,Benito Buen Hombre Pardo, Tomas Boy. Forwards: Juan Manuel Borbolla, J.J. Muñante, Romano, Carlos Eloir Perucci, El Cachito Ramirez, Ricardo Brandon, Pio Tabaré Gonzalez, Juan Carlos Rossete

===Necaxa (1990–2000)===
In 1988, Futbol Club Necaxa is purchased by Capitalist and monopoly Mexican telecommunications giant '''Grupo Televisa S.A C.V'''.  The now late owner, [[Emilio Azcárraga Milmo]] (father of [[Emilio Azcárraga Jean]]), and several associates take a new directive in the acquisition of the team. The effort of Management and coaches of football operations showed key and important personnel and financial decisions with respect to the livelihood of the Club in the First Division league or  &quot; La Primera A&quot;.

In the season of 1989 and 1990, then director of football operations [[Anibal Ruiz]] takes on the campaign and renovation of the management decisions in acquiring the services of the then now great Ecuadorian midfielder, [[Alex Aguinaga]], one of the iconic figures of the Necaxa in the 1990s and one of the most talented foreign players, who has ever set foot on Mexican soil.

Necaxa has a great season, previously in the 1980s they battled twice against the First Division's regulations rules of the Mexican League. In that Year Necaxa classified to the finals losing to the well built team of Pumas of the University of Mexico. The following season [[Aníbal Ruiz]] was replaced with new coach, the Argentine ex-defender, [[Eduardo Luján Manera]] who contracted the services of the Chilean [[Ivo Basay]], who was an instrumental part of the team in the following season. Under Manera, Necaxa didn’t qualify to the finals of the championship, yet, his team did show show a talented offensive line. However, unsatisfied, managements decisions of the team's play, the acquisition of new coach [[Roberto Marcos Saporitti]], marked the beginning of the seriousness of a commitment toward competition excellence a period known to Necaxa fans as &quot;La Epoca Necaxista abajo Capitalismo &quot; or &quot;the new era of Necaxa under Capitalism&quot;.

In 1992, the talented footballer, deeply rooted in the Institution of producing great footballers Pumas of [[Club Universidad Nacional|U.N.A.M.]], Ex-Puma player [[Enrique Borja]] is under contract and heads the clubs football operations to continue the commitment of excellence with in the organization and leaving Saporitti as head coach of Necaxa. The following season the team loses a decisive match and key to Saporitti future.  Eventually,Saporitti is replaced. The team Saporitti, Manera, Ruiz leave is an offensive minded team, that was disciplined, yet lack great defensive talent.  The following season, management asks the services of Manuel Lapuente, who balanced the mind set of the teams needs. Both in offense, which was already there and defense. [[Sergio &quot;El Ratón&quot; Zarate]], [[Octavio &quot;Picas&quot; Becerril]], the Chilean [[Eduardo &quot;Lalo&quot; Vilches]], y [[José María &quot;El Chema&quot; Higareda]] were key figures in the defense and offense of the football Club. [[Manuel Lapuente]] manages Club Necaxa to three successful Championship titles in Mexico's National Football League.

After 56 years, once again Necaxa found itself with the title of &quot;Campeonismo&quot; and contributing great talent in the '90s and late in the millennium and with in all of the First Division of the Mexican League and within the Mexican national team.

Winning the Mexican League Championship in 1994 (beating [[Club Deportivo Cruz Azul|Cruz Azul]]), in 1995 (beating Celaya) and 1998 (beating Guadalajara), becoming Champion of CONCACAF and champion of champions  the legacy of the &quot;Once Hermanos&quot; attempted to be reestablished within the Franchises values and mind set. The Necaxa team of the '90s and represented the cohesion and ability of working and playing as a team under lucrative financial incentives,forced great communication on the field and execution on the field during advanced Capitalism competition play. Necaxa's Championships were similar, yet different reminder of the spirit of &quot;Los Once Hermanos&quot; or &quot;the Eleven Brothers&quot; in the late 1930s.

===Necaxa Championship squads===

*10 consecutive games without a loss
{|
|valign=&quot;top&quot;|

'''1994-95 Champions'''
* {{flagicon|Mexico}} '''Nicolás Navarro'''
* {{flagicon|Mexico}} José Maria Higareda
* {{flagicon|Mexico}} Octavio Becerril
* {{flagicon|Mexico}} Gerardo Esquível
* {{flagicon|Mexico}} [[Ignacio Ambriz]]
* {{flagicon|Mexico}} Luis Hernandez
* {{flagicon|Mexico}} Efraín Herrera
*{{flagicon|Mexico}} [[Ricardo Pelaez]]
*{{flagicon|Mexico}} [[Alberto García Aspe]]
* {{flagicon|Chile}} Eduardo Vilches
* {{flagicon|Ecuador}} [[Alex Aguinaga]]
* {{flagicon|Argentina}} Sergio Zarate
* {{flagicon|Chile}} [[Ivo Basay]].
*{{flagicon|Mexico}} [[Manuel Lapuente]] [[Coach (sport)|Coach]]
*Team bench roster and substitutes
|width=&quot;100&quot;|&amp;nbsp;
|valign=&quot;top&quot;|
'''1995-96 Champions'''
* {{flagicon|Mexico}} '''Nicolás Navarro'''
* {{flagicon|Mexico}} José Maria Higareda
* {{flagicon|Mexico}} Octavio Becerril
* {{flagicon|Mexico}} Gerardo Esquível
* {{flagicon|Mexico}} [[Ignacio Ambriz]]
* {{flagicon|Mexico}} Luis Hernandez
* {{flagicon|Mexico}} Efraín Herrera
*{{flagicon|Mexico}} [[Ricardo Pelaez]]
*{{flagicon|Mexico}} [[Alberto García Aspe]]
*{{flagicon|Chile}} Eduardo Vilches
*{{flagicon|Germany}} Uwe Wolf
*{{flagicon|Ecuador}} Alex Aguinaga
*{{flagicon|Argentina}} Sergio Zarate
*{{flagicon|Mexico}} [[Manuel Lapuente]] [[Coach (sport)|Coach]]
*Team bench roster and substitutes
|width=&quot;100&quot;|&amp;nbsp;
|valign=&quot;top&quot;|
'''Winter 98'''
* {{flagicon|Mexico}} '''Adolfo Rios'''
* {{flagicon|Mexico}} José Maria Higareda
* {{flagicon|Mexico}} [[Carlos Hermosillo]]
* {{flagicon|Mexico}} Sergio Vázquez
* {{flagicon|Mexico}} Markus López
* {{flagicon|Mexico}} Jose Manuel de la Torre
* {{flagicon|Mexico}} Marco Antonio Sanchez
*{{flagicon|Mexico}} Raul Gordillo
*{{flagicon|Mexico}} Salvador Cabrera
*{{flagicon|Mexico}} Sergio Almaguer
*{{flagicon|Mexico}} Jose Luis Montes de Oca
*{{flagicon|Ecuador}} Alex Aguinaga
*{{flagicon|Argentina}} Sergio Zarate
*{{flagicon|Mexico}} [[Raúl Arias]] [[Coach (sport)|Coach]]
*Team bench roster and substitutes
|}

To start the millennium, Club Necaxa participated in the 2000 FIFA Club World Championship in Brazil. Necaxa's third place finish in the [[2000 FIFA Club World Championship]] is the highest by any Mexican club team (Club America played in the Consolation Round but lost in 2006). No other club in Mexican league history, in FIFA World Club Championship play has managed to surpass or challenge Necaxa's 3rd place finish, beating [[Real Madrid C.F.|Real Madrid]].

=== Necaxa (2000&amp;ndash;2009) ===
After having a successful decade, many children and adults who witnessed and watched Necaxa financial and team successes. With its very small fan base in Mexico city and many fans outside the state of Mexico, In the opening Fall 2003 tournament, Estadio Victoria,in the city of Aguascalientes, becomes the new home for the organization Club Necaxa. The organization brings the rich history of the game of Football. A history of Necaxa's history of tradition of unity, teamwork and dissent thus gaining aficionados in the region.

Club Necaxa move from the state of Mexico to the state of Aguascalientes occurred in 2003 with its new stadium, and much supported fan base. 

In one and many occasions, Club Necaxa teams in the latter half of 1990s and with in the new millennium have been dismembered to fortify the ambitions of the C.F America of Mexico squad (2004&amp;ndash;2005&amp;ndash;2006&amp;ndash;2007&amp;ndash;2008&amp;ndash;2009).&lt;ref name=&quot;ReferenceA&quot;/&gt; The debate is still ongoing within FIFA, which is a monopoly in itself, Emilio Azcárraga Jean's Televisa, the owner of several teams, this seen by many as a reason to question the integrity of the sport.

2008-09 Necaxa, and ''some'' of its players wear and wore the emblem with pride, and some players devoted serious time, effort and energy to keep the team alive from the regulation rules within the &quot;professional&quot; '''commercialized''' first division A League of Mexico.

'''On May 9, 2009, with the starting line up of''''
# Ivan Vazquez, Carlos Infante, Pablo Quattrocchi, Luis Omar Hernandez, Ricardo Francisco Rojas (loan from C.F America), Mario Pérez, Jose Gonzalez, Eduardo Coudet, Federico Insua (loan from C.F America), Carlos Pavon, Alfredo Moreno (loan from C.F America)
# DT: Raul Arias

# 63´ Diego Cervantes for Carlos Pavon # 81´ Germán Villa (loan from C.F America) for Eduardo Coudet # 81´ Marco Antonio Gomez for Jose Gonzalez

6 out 11  having a Monetary policy and an affinity with the C.F America or San Luis F.C.  This Necaxa was represented on the field and played their final 2009 match within the Mexican First Division League in the 2009 season after losing 1-0 vs [[Club America]]. Under the rules of regulation of the Mexican league, Necaxa would not be able to participate in the 1st division competition play in the fall 2009 and spring 2010 year.

Necaxa faced [[Irapuato]] on December 12, 2009 in the FIFA recognized Promotion league (Liga de Ascenso). Necaxa won 4-3 in global goals. Necaxa became the single season Champion of the Fall 2009 campaign and obtaining their first title in the Liga de Ascenso. Necaxa will therefore face the 2010 season winner of la Liga de Ascenso in a future match to be disputed in the summer.
Though the opening fall competition, Club Necaxa starting line up was

Necaxa's Closing Spring 2010 league performance was noted with some accomplishments.  Necaxa held an undefeated record at home throughout the fall 2009. But, in the spring 2010 campaign, Necaxa only loss in the season came against F.C Leon,&lt;ref&gt;http://www.televisadeportes.com/futbol/futbolmexico/equipos/necaxa/&lt;/ref&gt; furthermore,  Necaxa faced F.C Leon on May 8, 2010 for the second leg of the Bicentennial Closing Spring Tournament of 2010. Necaxa wins 4-2 on aggregate. With this result, Necaxa will abandon the Liga de Ascenso and will return to First Division Fall 2010 season. As a result of this match Necaxa's wins the Bi-championship in the Liga de Ascenso and First Promotion title in their Franchise history.  With the starting lineup of:

{|
|valign=&quot;top&quot;|

'''Winter 2009 Champions'''
*31. - {{flagicon|Mexico}} Ivan Vazquez,
*44. - {{flagicon|Mexico}} J.Mendoza,
*33. - {{flagicon|Argentina}} Pablo Quatrocchi,
*40. - {{flagicon|Mexico}} Arturo Ledesma,
*30. - {{flagicon|Brazil}} Everaldo Barbosa,
*51. - {{flagicon|Mexico}} Carlos Alberto Hurtado,
*58. - {{flagicon|Mexico}} Pedro Hernandez,
*50. - {{flagicon|Mexico}} Paulo César Chávez,
*54. - {{flagicon|Mexico}} Alejandro Castillo,
*59. - {{flagicon|Mexico}} M.Romero,
*56. - {{flagicon|Uruguay}} Nelson Maz
* - {{flagicon|Mexico}} O.Arellano [[Athletic trainer|Trainer]]
 |width=&quot;100&quot;|&amp;nbsp;
|valign=&quot;top&quot;|
'''Spring 2010 Champions '''
*45. - {{flagicon|Mexico}} Pedro Hernandez,
*48. - {{flagicon|Mexico}} Arturo Ledesma,
*33. - {{flagicon|Argentina}} Pablo Quatrocchi,
*31. - {{flagicon|Mexico}} Luis Alberto Padilla,
*30. - {{flagicon|Brazil}} Everaldo Barbosa,
*47. - {{flagicon|Mexico}} Javier Saavedra (loan from [[Tigres de la U.A.N.L.|Tigres U.A.N.L.]]),
*46. - {{flagicon|Mexico}} Juan Carlos Mosqueda,
*50. - {{flagicon|Mexico}} Paulo César Chávez,
*51. - {{flagicon|Mexico}} Carlos AlbertoHurtado,
*40. - {{flagicon|Mexico}} Juan de Dios Hernandez,
*59. - {{flagicon|Mexico}} M.Romero,
*53. - {{flagicon|Uruguay}} Nelson Maz
* - {{flagicon|Mexico}} O.Arellano [[Athletic trainer|Trainer]]
|}

===Necaxa in the Liga de Ascenso and FMF First Division A (2011 - present)===

In its début season 2011, the team won the Liga de Ascenso, before joining the FMF First Division A (see jersey logo) at the start of the 2011 season. Club Necaxa had won back-to-back league championships in la Liga de Ascenso de Mexico with Trainer Omar Arelleno and the team.  Displeased with the early performance of footballer/trainerOmar Arellano performance in First Division A and the team, the Necaxa Management decides to seek a coaching change. This Necaxa management decision favored its decision and services of ESPN television Commentator/Personality/ex-football player Daniel Brailovsky.  Club Necaxa begins its roller coaster season with four losses straight with [[Daniel Brailovsky]]. Necaxa Management [[Professionalism|professional sport]] executive decisions and Necaxa's cumulation of points and performance were the highlights for its loyal fans and supporters.  

On 16 April 2011,  After a draw 1–1 of Atlante F.C., the club's first key game in 2011, Necaxa could not cumulate enough points in order evade regulation. For a second time, Club Necaxa was relegated to the Liga de Ascenso, the second tier, for the 2011&amp;ndash;2012 season.

==Ownership history==
{{Main|List of Necaxa Club Ownership and Presidents }}

==Player records==
{{Main|Club records }}

==Sponsorship==
Since its founding, Club Necaxa has never worn corporate advertisements on their Jersey until 1987. Began sponsorship ( Athletico Espanol era )

===Shirt sponsors and manufacturers===
{| class=&quot;wikitable&quot; style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;
|-
!Period
![[Kit (association football)|Kit]] manufacturer
!Shirt partner
|-
|1922-23
| No sponsors*
| ''Light&amp;Power Co.''
|-
|1922-23
| No sponsors*
| ''StreetCar Operators''
|-
|1923-26
| No sponsors*
| ''none''
|-
|1926-36
| No sponsors*
| ''None''
|-
|1936-40
| No sponsors*
|''None''
|-
|1950–1970
| to be determined*
|''None''
|---
|-
|1971-82
| To be determined
|''None''
|---
|1987-88
| Adidas
|Chocó Milk
|-
|1989-92
| Adidas
|
|-
|1993-94
| Adidas
| Cola Cola / Elf
|-
|1994-95
| [[Adidas]]*
| Cola Cola / Elf
|-
|1995-96
| [[Umbro]]*
| Cola Cola / Elf
|-
|1996-97
| Umbro
| Cola Cola / AFORE Garante
|-
|1998 (Winter'98)
| Umbro*
| Cola Cola
|-
|1999-00
| EEscord
| Cola Cola
|-
|2000-01
| EEscord
| Cola Cola/Sol
|-
|2001
|EEscord
| Masfresco / Victoria / Coca Cola
|-
|2002
|Atletica
| Cola Cola / Sol
|-
|2003
|[[Atletica]]
| Bimbo / Victoria / Coca Cola
|-
|2004
|Atletica
| Bimbo / Office Depot / Victoria
|-
|2005
|Atletica
| Visa / Leche San Marcos / Banamex
|-
|2006
|Atletica
| Visa / Seguros Argos SA de CV / Leche San Marcos / Corona / Banamex
|-
|2007-08
| Atletica
|Visa / Seguros Argos SA de CV / Leche San Marcos / Corona / Aeroméxico  / Banamex/ Cemex Monterey / Caja Libertad
|-
|2008
|[[Voit]]
|Sabritas / Corona / Leche San Marcos
|-
|2009
|Voit
|Diversity Capital / Corona / Leche San Marcos
|-
|2009-10
|Voit*
|Casa Popular Mexicana / Corona / Seguros Argos
|-
|2010-11
|Voit* / Atletica
|Casa Popular Mexicana / Corona / Bimbo / ETN / Cola Cola / Voit-Casa Popular Mexicana / Rolcar / ETN / Bimbo / Corona-Atletica&lt;ref name=&quot;necaxafutbol.com&quot;&gt;http://www.necaxafutbol.com/&lt;/ref&gt;
|-
|2011–present
|Atletica
|Futura/Leche San Marcos/Corona,Casa Popular Mexicana/SKY/CocaCola/Trucka/Rolcar/Agro depot&lt;ref name=&quot;necaxafutbol.com&quot;/&gt;
|}
* Championship jerseys

===First kit evolution===
{|
|
{{Football kit |
  pattern_la = |
  pattern_b  = _collar|
  pattern_ra =  |
  pattern_sh1 = |
  leftarm1  = FFF|
  body     = FFF|
  rightarm1    = FFF|
  shorts     = 000000|
  socks      = 000000|
| t=s|
  title      = 1922&amp;ndash;1923 &lt;ref&gt;http://www.lacatedralrojiblanca.com/?p=5298&lt;/ref&gt;
}}
|
{{Football kit |
  pattern_la = |
  pattern_b  = |
  pattern_ra =  |
  leftarm  = 082567|
  body     = 082567|
  rightarm    = 082567|
  shorts     = fff |
  socks      = fff|
  title      = Second 1922&amp;ndash;1923
}}
|
{{Football kit |
  pattern_la = |
  pattern_b  = _collar |
  pattern_ra =  |
  leftarm  = FFF|
  body     = FFF|
  rightarm    = FFF|
  shorts     = fff |
  socks      = fff|
  title      = 1922-1923
}}
|
|
{{Football kit |
  pattern_la =_red_stripes |
  pattern_b  = _red_stripes|
  pattern_ra =_red_stripes |
  leftarm  = FFFFFF|
  body     = FFFFFF|
  rightarm    = FFFFFF|
  shorts     = ffffff |
  socks      = FFFFFF|
  title      = 1923&amp;ndash;1971
}}
|
{{
Football kit |
  pattern_la =_white_stripes |
  pattern_b  = _whitestripes|
  pattern_ra =_white_stripes |
  leftarm  = 000000|
  body     = 000000|
  rightarm    = 000000|
  shorts     = 000000 |
  socks      = FFFFFF|
  title      = 1971&amp;ndash;1981
}}
|
{{Football kit |
 pattern_la = |
 pattern_b = _GeorgeaBoots9|
 pattern_ra = |
 leftarm =FFFFFF |
 body = FFFFFF |
 rightarm = FFFFFF |
 shorts = 000000 |
 socks = FFFFFF |
 title = 1973&amp;ndash;1975
}}
|
{{Football kit |
 pattern_la = |
 pattern_b = _GeorgeaBoots9|
 pattern_ra = |
 leftarm =FFFFFF |
 body = FFFFFF |
 rightarm = FFFFFF |
 shorts = ffffff |
 socks = FFFFFF |
 title = 1972
}}
|}

===1990-present kit evolution===
{|
|
{{Football kit |
 pattern_la = |
 pattern_b = _necaxa6|
 pattern_ra = |
 leftarm = FFFFFF |
 body = FFFFFF |
 rightarm = FFFFFF |
 shorts = ffffff |
 socks = FFFFFF |
 title = 1992
}}
|
{{Football kit |
 pattern_la = |
 pattern_b = _necaxa4|
 pattern_ra = |
 leftarm = FFFFFF |
 body = FFFFFF |
 rightarm = FFFFFF |
 shorts = ffffff |
 socks = FFFFFF |
 title = 1994
}}
|
{{Football kit |
 pattern_la = _red_stripes|
 pattern_b = _necaxa5|
 pattern_ra =_red_stripes |
 leftarm = FFFFFF |
 body = FFFFFF |
 rightarm = FFFFFF |
 shorts = ffffff |
 socks = FFFFFF |
 title = 1995
}}
|
{{Football kit |
 pattern_la = |
 pattern_b = _necaxa7|
 pattern_ra = |
 leftarm = FFFFFF |
 body = FFFFFF |
 rightarm = FFFFFF |
 shorts = ffffff |
 socks = FFFFFF |
 title = 1996
}}
|
{{Football kit |
 pattern_la = |
 pattern_b = _necaxa3|
 pattern_ra = |
 leftarm =FF0000 |
 body = FFFFFF |
 rightarm = FFFFFF |
 shorts = ffffff |
 socks = FFFFFF |
 title = 1999
}}
|
{{Football kit |
pattern_la = |
 pattern_b = _necaxa8|
 pattern_ra = |
 leftarm =FFFFFF |
 body = FFFFFF |
 rightarm = FFFFFF |
 shorts = ffffff |
 socks = FFFFFF |
 title = 2005
}}
|
{{Football kit |
 pattern_la=_red_stripes |
 pattern_b=_necaxa1112h |
 pattern_ra=_red_stripes |
 pattern_sh=_necaxa201112h |
 pattern_so=_necaxa201112h |
 leftarm=FFFFFF |
 body=FFFFFF |
 rightarm=FFFFFF |
 shorts=FFFFFF
 socks=FFFFFF |
title = 2011
}}
|}

==Current roster==
''As of June 11, 2011''
{{Fs start}}
{{Fs player | no= 1 | nat=MEX | pos=GK | name= [[Iván Vázquez]]}}
{{Fs player | no= 2 | nat=MEX | pos=DF | name= [[Luis Omar Hernández]]}}
{{Fs player | no= 3 | nat=ARG | pos=DF | name= [[Pablo Quatrocchi]]}} (''[[Captain (association football)|Captain]]'')
{{Fs player | no= 4 | nat=MEX | pos=MF | name= [[Jorge Zataraín]]}}
{{Fs player | no= 5 | nat=MEX | pos=MF | name= [[Luis Ernesto Pérez Martínez|Luis Ernesto Pérez]]}}
{{Fs player | no= 6 | nat=MEX | pos=DF | name= [[Daniel Cervantes]]}}
{{Fs player | no= 7 | nat=MEX | pos=FW | name= [[Alejandro Castillo]]}}
{{Fs player | no= 8 | nat=BRA | pos=MF | name= [[Everaldo Barbosa]]}}
{{Fs player | no= 9 | nat=MEX | pos=FW | name= [[Victor Lojero]]}}
{{Fs player | no=10 | nat=URU | pos=FW | name= [[Sergio Blanco]]}}
{{Fs player | no=11 | nat=MEX | pos=MF | name= [[Carlos Alberto Hurtado]]}}
{{Fs player | no=12 | nat=MEX | pos=GK | name= [[Carlos Alberto Trejo]]}}
{{Fs player | no=13 | nat=MEX | pos=FW | name= [[Juan Carlos Mosqueda]]}}
{{Fs mid}}
{{Fs player | no=14 | nat=MEX | pos=DF | name= [[Luis Alberto Padilla]]}}
{{Fs player | no=15 | nat=MEX | pos=DF | name= [[Marvin de la Cruz]]}}
{{Fs player | no=17 | nat=MEX | pos=MF | name= [[Jesús Palacios]]}}
{{Fs player | no=18 | nat=MEX | pos=MF | name= [[Juan José de la Cruz]]}}
{{Fs player | no=19 | nat=MEX | pos=DF | name= [[Fernando López (footballer)|Fernando López]]}}
{{Fs player | no=20 | nat=MEX | pos=MF | name= [[Jesús Antonio Isijara]]}}
{{Fs player | no=21 | nat=MEX | pos=MF | name= [[Luis Alberto Valdés]]}}
{{Fs player | no=22 | nat=MEX | pos=MF | name= [[Luis Francisco García]]}}
{{Fs player | no=23 | nat=MEX | pos=DF | name= [[Pierre Ibarra]]}}
{{Fs player | no=27 | nat=MEX | pos=FW | name= [[Ezequiel Orozco]]}}
{{Fs player | no=29 | nat=MEX | pos=FW | name= [[Héctor Gimenez (footballer)|Héctor Gimenez]]}}
{{Fs player | no=33 | nat=MEX | pos=DF | name= [[José Antonio Castro]]}}
{{fs end}}

===Reserve team===
Due to the FMF rules 2010 to elevate the injustices of professional and commercialization capitalist marketing strategies, from the discriminatory ideology of All Mexican brand&lt;ref&gt;http://www.chivascampeon.com/&lt;/ref&gt; to Estadio Azteca/America/Team Mexico &quot;America es Grande muy Grande&quot; Gimmick.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.foxsportsla.com/futbol/Barcelona-es-grande-muy-Grande-vencio-al-America-20110806-0053.html&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;http://www.clubamerica.com.mx/&lt;/ref&gt;

All football clubs now have their independent body of U-15-20 for the advancement of Mexican Football
 
*Necaxa U-20: Reserve team that plays in the U-20 tournament coinciding with the regular season tournament
*Necaxa U-17: Reserve team that plays in the U-17 tournament coinciding with the regular season tournament
*Necaxa U-15: Reserve team that plays in the U-15 tournament coinciding with the regular season tournament

===Current technical staff===

&lt;!-- Instructions how to use these templates are in the bottom --&gt;
{{Fb cs header}}
{{Fb cs staff |bg=  |p=Manager |s={{flagicon|MEX}} Luis Francisco Garcia}}
{{Fb cs staff |bg=  |p=Assistant Manager |s={{flagicon|MEX}} [[Luis Armando González]]}}
{{Fb cs staff |bg=  |p=Assistant Manager |s={{flagicon|MEX}} [[Jorge Rivera (coach)|Jorge Rivera]]}}
{{Fb cs staff |bg=  |p=Physical fitness coach |s={{flagicon|MEX}} [[Hugo Adrián Parra]]}}
{{Fb cs staff |bg=  |p=Team Doctor |s={{flagicon|MEX}} [[Jesus Negrete]]}}
{{Fb cs staff |bg=  |p=Massage Therapist |s={{flagicon|MEX}} [[Julio Montes de Oca]]}}
{{Fb cs staff |bg=  |p=Utilityman |s={{flagicon|MEX}} [[Ismael Murguía]]}}
{{Fb cs staff |bg=  |p=Chief Scout |s={{flagicon|MEX}} [[----]]}}
{{Fb cs staff |bg=  |p=Youth Academy Director |s={{flagicon|MEX}} [[----]]}}
{{Fb cs footer |u=08 August 2009 |s=[http://www.clubnecaxa.com/site/index.php?option=com_content&amp;view=article&amp;id=91&amp;Itemid=57  Club Necaxa Official Website]|date=July 2011}}
&lt;!--

Template:Fb cs staff (Football - coach staff - staff)

Parameters
bg : background color. y = yes; blank = no
p  : staff position
s  : staff

Template:Fb cs footer (Football - coach staff - footer)

Parameters
u  : date of last update
s  : source

--&gt;

==Honours==
===Domestic===
'''Amateur'''

*'''[[Primera Fuerza]]: 4'''
::1932-33, 1934-35, 1936-37, 1937-38

*'''[[Copa México]]: 3'''
::1932-33, 1934-35, 1935-36
*'''Runner up 2'''
::1939-40, 1940-41

*'''[[Campeón de Campeones]]: 2'''
::1932-33, 1935-36

*'''[[Campeonísimo]]: 2'''
::1932-33, 1934-35

'''FMF 1st Division A'''
*'''[[Primera División A]]: 3'''
::1994-95, 1995-96, Invierno 1998

*'''[[Copa México]]: 3'''
::1959-60, 1965-66, 1994-95

*'''[[Campeón de Campeones]]: 2'''
::1966, 1995

*'''[[Second Division]]: 2'''
::Clausura 2009, Bicentenario 2010

===International Tournaments===
*'''[[Central American and Caribbean Games]]: 1'''
::1935

*'''[[CONCACAF Champions' Cup]]: 2'''
::1975 (as [[Atlético Español]]), 1999

*'''[[InterLiga]]: 1'''
::2007
 
*'''[[FIFA Club World Cup]]: 0'''
::3 place - [[2000 FIFA Club World Championship|2000]]

*'''[[CONCACAF Cup Winners Cup]]: 1'''
::[[CONCACAF Champions' Cup 1994|1994]]

==References==
* La serie Mexico Nuevo Siglo: ''Rueda de la Fortuna'' ''Los Rayos
* Juan Cid y Mulet: Libro de Oro del Fútbol Mexicano - Tomo 2
* http://www.mediotiempo.com/futbol/editoriales/carlos-calderon/2011/08/el-partido-que-duro-4-horas
* IFFHS All-Time Club World Ranking

{{Reflist}}

==Fan clubs==
*Sobredosis Albirroja &quot;The Red and the White Overdose&quot;

==External links==
*[http://www.clubnecaxa.com/   Necaxa FanZine!! Website (Español/Spanish)]
*[http://www.necaxafutbol.com/ Official Website (Español/English/日本語 )]

{{Liga de Ascenso teamlist}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Necaxa}}
[[Category:Mexican football clubs]]
[[Category:Association football clubs established in 1923]]
[[Category:Club Necaxa|  ]]
[[Category:Primera División de México teams]]

[[ar:نادي نيكاكسا]]
[[ca:Club Necaxa]]
[[de:Necaxa]]
[[es:Club Necaxa]]
[[fr:Club Necaxa]]
[[it:Club Necaxa]]
[[nl:Necaxa]]
[[ja:ネカサ]]
[[pl:Club Necaxa]]
[[pt:Club Necaxa]]
[[ru:Некакса]]
[[fi:Club Necaxa]]
[[sv:Club Necaxa]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
