<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><redirects><r from="Khôr" to="Syldavia" tofragment="Currency" /></redirects><pages><page pageid="54552" ns="0" title="Syldavia"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Refimprove|date=April 2008}}
{{Infobox fictional country
|native_name =
|common_name = Syldavia
|conventional_long_name = Kingdom of Syldavia
|series = Tintin
|event_start = battle of Zileheroum
|year_start = 1127
|year_end=
|p1     = [[Ottoman Empire]]
|flag_p1   =
|image_flag = Flag of Syldavia.svg
|image_coat = Coat of Arms of Syldavia.png
|national_motto = ''Eih bennek, eih blavek.''&lt;br&gt;
(English: ''If you gather thistles, expect prickles.'')
|national_anthem = ''Syldavians unite! Praise our King's might: The Sceptre his right!''
|image_map  = Balkanpeninsula.png
|map_caption = General location of Syldavia
|image_map2  =
|map_caption2 =
| source     = ''[[The Adventures of Tintin]]''
| creator    = [[Hergé]]
| genre      = [[Comic strip]]
|continent = [[Europe]]
|country  =
|capital     = Klow
|official_languages = [[Syldavian]]
|ethnic_groups = Syldavian
|government_type = [[Monarchy]]
|leader_title1 = [[King]]
|leader_name1 = [[Muskar XII]]
|leader_title2 =
|leader_name2 =
|population = 642,000 (1939)
|currency = Khôr
}}
'''Syldavia''' (Cyrillic: Зилдaвиa) is a [[Fictional country|fictional]] [[Balkan peninsula|Balkan]] kingdom featured in ''[[The Adventures of Tintin]]'' by [[Hergé]]. The name was derived from [[Transylvania|Tran'''SYL'''vania]] and [[Moldavia|Mol'''DAVIA''']].

==Overview==
Syldavia is a [[monarchy]], ruled at the time of the ''[[King Ottokar's Sceptre]]'' story by [[Minor characters in The Adventures of Tintin#King Muskar XII|King Muskar XII]]. The capital is Klow, formerly Zileheroum, located at the confluence of the fictional Moltus and Wladir Rivers (after [[Prague]], which is on the [[Moldau]]/Vltava River). Other cities named in the books are Niedzdrow, Istow, Dbrnouk, Douma and Zlip. The population of Syldavia is 642,000 with 122,000 living in Klow. The national airline is [[Syldair]] and the official currency is the '''khôr''' (Зилдaв хор).

Syldavia is also called &quot;The Kingdom of the Black Pelican&quot; and its flag is yellow with a black pelican in the center.  It somewhat resembles the flag of the [[Holy Roman Empire]], the Basque [[Arrano beltza]], as well as the [[flag of Albania]]. However, the royal seal on the wall in [[King Ottokar's Sceptre]] bears a striking resemblance with the [[Coat of arms of Montenegro]].

The people speak [[Syldavian]], a Slavic-sounding [[West Germanic language]] written in the [[Cyrillic alphabet]]. Curiously, the [[Latin alphabet]] is used in medieval documents, and the Cyrillic letters used are a straight transcription from the Latin letters (e.g., &quot;sh&quot; is written &quot;сз&quot; rather than &quot;ш&quot;).

The kingdom's motto is &quot;Eih bennek, eih blavek!&quot; which Hergé translates as &quot;''Qui s'y frotte s'y pique''&quot; &quot;Who rubs himself there gets stung&quot; (in fact, the motto of [[Nancy, France|Nancy]], from the Latin ''non inultus premor'', referring to its emblem, the [[thistle]]; in the British edition, the translators rendered the motto &quot;If you gather Thistles, expect Prickles&quot;). The motto can also be interpreted as a [[Brussels]] [[dialect]] rendering of the Dutch phrase &quot;''Hier ben ik, hier blijf ik''&quot; (&quot;Here I am, here I stay&quot;).

Syldavians seem to be fond of [[mineral water]], which does not go down well with the [[whisky]]-drinking [[Captain Haddock]], one of Tintin's travelling companions.

==Location and Inspiration==
{{Unreferenced section|date=March 2010}}
The exact location of Syldavia is not given in the comics, and nothing more is known than that it is located in [[Balkan peninsula]], bordering another fictional country [[Borduria]], and that it has an access to the sea. In ''[[Destination Moon (Tintin)|Destination Moon]]'', the trail of the Syldavian-launched rocket points to a location north of the [[Danube]]. There are various inspirations for Syldavia. As Hergé noted himself the primary inspiration was inter-war [[Albania]], but the country's history is modeled after many Balkan countries. According to a brochure read by Tintin on his plane, Syldavia gained independence from [[Ottoman empire]] early, resembling [[Montenegro]] and [[Serbia]]. Medieval kings of Syldavia have similarities with many Balkan rulers of [[Montenegro]], [[Serbia]], [[Bosnia]] etc. The battle of Zileheroum resembles the [[Battle of Kosovo]] and the [[Battle of Maritsa]] and rebelled nobility are similar of those who divided the [[Serbian empire]]. However Muskar I a.k.a. Hveghi may be inspired by [[George Kastrioti Skanderbeg]], Albanian rebel and later ruler. The king's court is inspired by Montenegrin nobility. As for geography, in [[King Ottokar's Sceptre]] it is a typical Balkan country with high mountains with small towns located in plains below. Niedzdrow twin towns can be found all around [[Albania]], northern Montenegro and southern Serbia ([[Sandzak]] region), [[Bosnia and Herzegovina]], [[Republic of Macedonia|Macedonia]], south [[Bulgaria]] and so on. Syldavia has a small coastline and two known towns on it: Douma, the seaplane service harbour, and Dbrnouk, whose name might be inspired by [[Croatia]]n city of [[Dubrovnik]], although the fisherman on the brochure's photo, described as its inhabitant, is certainly Muslim typical for south Montenegrin ([[Ulcinj]]) and Albanian coast. Only the landscape around Kropow castle is more Central-European, bearing its likeness to upper-[[Danube]] regions. In post-war stories the basic inspiration seems to be [[Carpathian Mountains]] and in ''[[Tintin and the Lake of Sharks]]'' - Macedonia. The capital Klow resembles [[Tirana]], [[Sarajevo]], [[Skopje]] and [[Podgorica]]. The national saint is St Vladimir and many sources claim it's [[Vladimir I of Kiev]], but due to the Balkan likeness, the more appropriate would be [[Saint Jovan Vladimir]], a ruler later proclaimed saint, prince of [[Duklja]], the medieval state of Montenegro also occupying the [[Shkoder]] region in north Albania.

==History==
The region of Syldavia was inhabited by nomadic tribes of unknown origin until 6th century, when it was overrun by [[Slavs]]. It was conquered in 10th century by the [[Turkish people|Turks]], who occupied the plains forcing the Slavs into the mountains (a historical inaccuracy, since the [[Balkans]] were conquered in 14th century). The modern Syldavia was formed in 1127 when a tribal chief called Hveghi drove away Turkish conquerors defeated at the battle of Zileheroum and took the name Muskar ruling until 1168. He reigned well, but his son Muskar II was not as good as him. [[Borduria]] conquered the country during the reign of Muskar II in 1195 until Ottokar I (his real name and title being baron Almaszout) drove them away in 1275.

King Ottokar IV became King in 1360. He took away the power of many upstart nobles. When an enemy, Baron Staszrvitch, claimed the Throne and attacked him with his sword, Ottokar struck him to the ground with his [[sceptre]]. The King then said the motto and decreed that the ruler of Syldavia must have hold on the sceptre, otherwise he would lose his authority, as it had saved his life. This custom had a power of law as late as 1939.

In 1939 Syldavia was nearly invaded by its neighbor [[Borduria]], part of it was a plot to oust King Muskar XII. The the sceptre was stolen, in the hope Muskar would abdicate. Tintin had a hand in defusing the situation by returning the sceptre just before St Vladmir's day. The Bordurians then announced they were withdrawing troops 15 miles from the borders. (The situation was very similar to that of [[Anschluss]] in [[Austria]] in 1938 though the conclusion was not the same).

King Muskar XII was a keen motorist who even had his own gun for protection. He was an actual ruler rather than a [[constitutional monarch]] (see [[enlightened absolutism]]). He himself ordered his ministers and generals to make the moves necessary to prevent the coup and the invasion. However, the king is noticeably absent from the other stories set in Syldavia such as the launch of the moon rocket. King Muskar XII was married, but his queen's name is not known.

==Coat of arms==
The Syldavian [[achievement of arms]] is shown on the [[title page]] and page 62 of the ''[[King Ottokar's Sceptre]]'' album. It would be [[blazon]]ed heraldically as follows:

''[[Quartering (heraldry)|Quarterly]], first and fourth [[Or (heraldry)|Or]] a pelican displayed [[sable (heraldry)|sable]], second and third [[gules]] two [[increscent]]s in [[fess]] [[argent]]; for a [[crest (heraldry)|crest]], on a barred helmet affronty or, [[lambrequin|mantled]] [[azure]] doubled [[Or (heraldry)|Or]], the Royal Crown of Syldavia&lt;ref&gt;This crown appears in the scenes in the Treasure Chamber on page 41 and others of ''King Ottokar's Sceptre''.&lt;/ref&gt; [[tincture (heraldry)#Proper|proper]]; behind the [[shield (heraldry)|shield]] the Royal Sceptre of Syldavia&lt;ref&gt;This appears in ''King Ottokar's Sceptre'' from page 67 onwards.&lt;/ref&gt; and a sceptre of justice&lt;ref&gt;A [[sceptre]] topped with a hand of benediction, known as the ''main de justice'', was part of the regalia of the [[King of France|Kings of France]].&lt;/ref&gt; in [[saltire]]; the motto &quot;Eih bennek, eih blavek&quot; on a scroll below the shield, pendent therefrom the badge of the Order of the Golden Pelican.&lt;ref&gt;Tintin is shown being invested with this insignia on page 60 of ''King Ottokar's Sceptre''.&lt;/ref&gt;''

==Language==
{{Main|Syldavian}}

In their book ''Tintin Ketje de Bruxelles'' (Casterman, 2004 ISBN 2-203-01716-3), Daniel Justens and Alain Préaux have documented how the [[Syldavian]] language is based on ''[[Marols]]'' or ''Marollien'', the dialect of the [[Marollen]], a formerly working-class (though now trendy) quarter of [[Brussels]]. Marols, which Hergé learnt from his grandmother, is a form of [[Dutch language|Dutch]] incorporating many words of French origin as well as a sprinkling of Spanish.

Educated Syldavians are shown speaking Tintin's language (French in the original).

==Cuisine==
Syldavian cuisine appears to be typical of Eastern Europe; [[blini]], herbs, [[sausage]] and garnish are seen in the kitchen of a Syldavian restaurant in  ''[[King Ottokar's Sceptre]]''. Mineral water is an important export, and alcohol is scarce, much to [[Captain Haddock]]'s disgust. When Haddock tries to bring in alcohol with him when visiting Calculus at the research facility, he is hit with high alcohol duty.

It is mentioned that a prime dish in the country is slaczek, described by a waiter as the hind leg of a young dog in heavy Syldavian sauce. However, this may not be true as the waiter was deliberately attempting to disturb Tintin. Slaczek is served to Tintin with mushrooms and a salad.

== Atomic research ==
In the 1950s Syldavia had a secret but successful space program in the area of Sbrodj (named Sprodj in the English edition).

The Sprodj Atomic Research Centre, seen in ''[[Destination Moon (Tintin)|Destination Moon]]'' and ''[[Explorers on the Moon]]'' is located in Syldavia. The sprawling complex is located in the Zymylpathian Mountains of Syldavia (a play on the [[Carpathian Mountains]]), located close to rich deposits of [[uranium]]. The Centre is secretive and has very tightly-guarded security, including a large number of security checkpoints, [[helicopter]] surveillance, [[anti-aircraft]] artillery, and a squadron of [[fighter aircraft]] based at the facility. Work at the centre, carried out by a large team of international [[physicist]]s recruited by the Syldavian government, involves research into protection from the effects of [[nuclear weapon]]s, and is the base for the Syldavian [[space program]]. The facility, which seems to be entirely self-sufficient, is administered by the Director, Mr. Baxter. The Sprodj Centre has its own [[atomic pile]] for processing [[uranium]] into [[plutonium]], and has vast facilities for the research and construction of the rocket-ship which carries Tintin and his colleagues to [[the moon]]. The gargantuan complex is last seen at the end of ''[[Explorers on the Moon]]'', and is never again seen in the Tintin series.

In ''Destination Moon'', the Sprodj Atomic Research Centre invites [[Professor Cuthbert Calculus]] to head its space division, and later Tintin and [[Captain Haddock]] to be part of the moon mission. In ''[[The Calculus Affair]]'', Syldavia's secret agents compete with archrival Bordurian agents to kidnap Professor Calculus and obtain the secrets to develop sound-based weapons.

== National Dance ==
The Blushtika, meaning &quot;Goat Dance Twisting,&quot; as seen in ''[[Tintin and the Lake of Sharks]]''.

== National Lake ==
The national lake is &quot;Pollishoff&quot;, meaning &quot;Lake of Sharks&quot;. The inspiration for this lake seems to be various lakes in [[Republic of Macedonia|Macedonia]], particularly the [[Ohrid lake]].

== National Defense ==
Syldavia has an extensive military, ranging from anti-aircraft guns to radar stations.
The army appears to have a considerable Eastern European appearance, possibly modeled on that of Poland or Russia. It appears to have well prepared defensive systems, including radar stations, anti-aircraft installations, checkpoints and bunkers.

== Capital ==
The capital of Syldavia is Klow. The city was founded in the 10th century by the invading Turks, and was then named Zilehorum. The Magyar nomads that lived there were forced to live in Zmyhlpathernian mountains, while the Turks themselves settled in the newly founded city located in the lush hills. In the year [[1127]], the nomads, led by their chief Hveghi, defeated and drove away the Turkish conquerors. Hveghi took the name Muskar, meaning &quot;the brave&quot; and Zileheroum was renamed to Klow, meaning &quot;freetown&quot; from ''kloho'' (&quot;freedom&quot;) and ''ow'' (''town''). In [[1168]], Muskar died, and was followed by his son Muskar II. Muskar II, however, was weak, and the neighboring [[Borduria]]ns took over the country.

Klow has a big variety of cultural styles. Mostly typical [[Yugoslavia]]n, there is also many buildings of [[Austrians|Austrian]] and [[Turkic peoples|Turkish]] descent, for example the old mosques. However, the Kropow castle's architecture and decoration is of Bohemian descent, but this could be because of the fame of [[Bohemian|Czech]] architecture.

As a large and relateively well-off capital city, Klow has a large museum of natural science with mounted dinosaur skeletons. Klow is told to be the Capital of Mineral Water, and they are famous for their Klowaswa (Cyrillic: Кловасва), their national mineral water, literally meaning &quot;Klow Water&quot; or &quot;Water from Klow&quot;. In contrast to ordinary Syldavians, who use the [[Cyrillic alphabet]], the Royal Court in Klow uses the [[Latin alphabet]].

==In popular culture==
The song ''Sildavia'' from the Spanish group ''La Unión'' (''Mil Siluetas'', 1984) mentions this country as a land of dreams. The Dutch group [[Flairck]] also has a song called ''Syldavian walz'', featured in his album ''The Emigrant'' (''Syldavishe walls'', ''De Emigrant'', 1989).

==Sources==
Tintin stories with Syldavia:
* ''[[:fr:Le Sceptre d'Ottokar|Le Sceptre d'Ottokar]]'' (''[[King Ottokar's Sceptre]]'', 1939)
* ''[[:fr:Objectif Lune|Objectif Lune]]'' (''[[Destination Moon (Tintin)|Destination Moon]]'', 1953)
* ''[[:fr:On a marché sur la Lune|On a marché sur la Lune]]'' (''[[Explorers on the Moon]]'', 1954, for earth scenes only)
* ''[[:fr:L'Affaire Tournesol|L'Affaire Tournesol]]'' (''[[The Calculus Affair]]'', 1956)
* ''[[Tintin and the Lake of Sharks]]''

== See also ==
* [[Borduria]]
* [[Fictional European countries]]

==Notes==
&lt;references/&gt;

==External links==
* [http://www.zompist.com/syldavian.html On the Syldavian language] by [[Zompist.com|Mark Rosenfelder]]

{{Tintin and Hergé}}

[[Category:Tintin countries]]
[[Category:Fictional European countries]]

[[bn:সিলদাভিয়া]]
[[br:Sildavia]]
[[da:Syldavien]]
[[es:Syldavia]]
[[eo:Sildavio]]
[[fr:Syldavie]]
[[id:Syldavia]]
[[it:Syldavia]]
[[lb:Syldawien]]
[[nl:Syldavië]]
[[pt:Sildávia]]
[[ru:Сильдавия]]
[[fi:Syldavia]]
[[sv:Syldavien]]
[[tr:Sildavya]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
