<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="12346158" ns="0" title="Smosh"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{pp-semi-blp|small=yes|expiry=February 28, 2012}}
{{Infobox person
| name                      = Smosh
| image                     = Smosh YouTube Live.jpg
| caption                   = Anthony (right) and Ian (left) at [[YouTube Live]]
| birth_date                = '''Anthony Padilla''': {{birth date and age|mf=yes|1987|9|16}}&lt;ref name=smosh-about-us&gt;{{cite web|title=About Us|url=http://www.smosh.com/about-us|publisher=Smosh|accessdate=23 October 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;br&gt; '''Ian Hecox''': {{birth date and age|mf=yes|1987|11|30}}&lt;ref name=smosh-about-us /&gt;
| nationality               = [[United States|American]]
| home_town                 = [[Sacramento]], California
| occupation                = [[YouTube]] comedy duo, YouTube Partner
| years_active              = 2005–present&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url= http://www.smosh.com/  |title= smosh.com |archiveurl = http://web.archive.org/web/20021124191813/http://www.smosh.com/ |archivedate = 2002-11-24}} - Official Website.&lt;/ref&gt;
| website                   = [http://www.smosh.com/ smosh.com]
}}
'''Smosh''' is a web-based comedy duo consisting of '''Ian Hecox''' and '''Anthony Padilla'''.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url= http://www.batchbuzz.com/detailedStoryDefault.php?id=751|title= BB Suggests: The Best of Web TV|accessdate=2009-11-16 |date= November 13, 2009 |publisher= Batch Buzz}}&lt;/ref&gt; Padilla first began posting [[flash animation|flash movies]] on [[Newgrounds]] in early 2003, under the name Smosh. He was later joined by his friend Ian Hecox. Soon afterward they began to post videos on [[YouTube]] in the autumn of 2005 and became one of the most popular channels on that site, with more than 3.7 million subscribers as of November 2011.&lt;ref name=&quot;smosh channel&quot;&gt;{{cite web|title=smosh's Channel|url=http://www.youtube.com/smosh|publisher=YouTube|accessdate=November 6, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Four Smosh-related channels exist on YouTube. The base &quot;Smosh&quot; channel, where both Ian and Anthony post their skits and other videos, has new videos every Friday. From &quot;IanH&quot; (used at first for vlogs and other non-scripted videos), the pair upload their side series &quot;Ian is Bored&quot; on Mondays and &quot;Lunchtime with Smosh&quot; on Thursdays, while their associate performer Mari does &quot;Smosh Pit Weekly&quot; videos on Saturday. A third channel, called &quot;AskCharlie&quot;, is based on the popular Smosh character Charlie the Drunk Guinea Pig. It uploads videos every Wednesday. Their final channel, &quot;AnthonyPadilla&quot;, has been inactive since February 2011; it was formerly where Anthony made vlog-like videos on his own.

==History==
===Formation and ''Pokémon Theme Music Video'': 2005–2009===
Smosh began when Ian Hecox and Anthony Padilla made several videos together, lip syncing to theme songs such as [[Mortal Kombat]], [[Power Rangers]], and [[Teenage Mutant Ninja Turtles]]. At first, these videos were not intended to be posted online, but after they sent them to their friends, they started a [[YouTube]] channel.

One of Smosh's earliest videos, &quot;Pokémon Theme Music Video,&quot; was released in November 2005. It followed the same style as their other earlier videos, featuring the duo lip-synching the original English theme song for the [[Pokémon anime]]. However, the video instantly became much more popular than any of their other videos; over the course of its lifetime, it gained 24.7 million views, becoming the most-viewed video on all of YouTube at that time.&lt;ref name=&quot;nyt-1&quot;&gt;{{cite news | url=http://www.nytimes.com/2006/04/04/arts/04iht-videos.html | title= Comic shorts, home on the Web | publisher=The New York Times | author= [[Virginia Heffernan]] | date= April 4, 2006 | accessdate=November 23, 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt; It held that title for about six months, but was removed by YouTube after the website received a notice from [[Shogakukan Productions Co., Ltd.]], claiming copyright infringement.{{Citation needed|date=August 2011}}

The success of their ''Pokémon'' video and other videos led Smosh to be featured in the &quot;Person of the Year: You&quot; issue of ''[[Time Magazine]]'', published December 13, 2006. It also inspired them to expand their style beyond basic lip-synching videos, and eventually to start creating videos of various genres, such as mini-skits and sketch comedies.{{Citation needed|date=August 2011}}. In March 2007, a user named Andii2000 re-uploaded the original Pokémon video. It has over 12.9 million views as of November 2011.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=mOX3OmUhQoo |title=SMOSH - POKEMON THEME SONG |author=Andii2000 |date=March 17, 2007 |publisher=YouTube |accessdate=November 6, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===2010 era===
In January 2010, Smosh launched the &quot;Smosh Pit&quot; feature, a blog that consists of various pieces of pop-culture trivia. In addition, 2010 saw the channel launch 3 different Smosh-based web series: &quot;Ian is Bored,&quot; which started as a collection of comedic videos by Hecox, but then turned primarily into Smosh opening [[fan mail]] segments called &quot;Mail time with Smosh&quot;; &quot;Ask Charlie&quot; (which is an interactive series where people ask Charlie, from their January 2010 &quot;Charlie the Drunk Guinea Pig&quot; video, random questions); and &quot;Lunchtime with Smosh,&quot; a Comedy series featuring Smosh getting and eating food from various places.

Also in early 2010, Smosh created the &quot;iShut Up App&quot; for [[Android (operating system)|Android]] phones as part of a [[Google]] sponsorship; it eventually made its way to the [[iTunes]] app store. As of November 19 2011, Smosh is the third most-subscribed channel on YouTube.&lt;ref name=&quot;smosh channel&quot;/&gt;

== References ==
{{reflist}}

== External links ==
* {{official website|http://smosh.com}}
* {{YouTube|channel=smosh|smosh}}
* {{YouTube|channel=IanH|IanH}}
* {{YouTube|channel=askcharlie|askcharlie}}
* {{YouTube|channel=AnthonyPadilla|AnthonyPadilla}}

{{s-start}}
{{s-ach|ach}}
{{s-bef|before=[[nigahiga]]}}
{{s-ttl|title=Top Subscribed Channel on YouTube|years=smosh&lt;br&gt;Ranked third as of November 2011}}
{{s-aft|after=[[machinima]]}}
{{s-bef|before=[[Riot Games|RiotGamesInc]]}}
{{s-ttl|title=Top Subscribed Channel on YouTube|years=IanH&lt;br&gt;Ranked 50 as of November 2011}}
{{s-aft|after=communitychannel}}
{{s-end}}

[[Category:Living people]]
[[Category:American comedians]]
[[Category:Comedy duos]]
[[Category:American Internet personalities]]

[[es:Smosh (dúo)]]
[[it:Smosh]]
[[nl:Smosh]]
[[ja:スモッシュ]]
[[no:Smosh]]
[[fi:Smosh]]
[[sv:Smosh]]
[[tr:Smosh]]
[[zh:Smosh]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
