<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="12350958" ns="0" title="Terry Wiles"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">[[Image:len-terry-wiles.jpg|thumb|right|Len and Terry Wiles c.1970]]
{{for|the Christian minister|Crossroads Community Cathedral}}
'''Terrence 'Terry' Wiles''' (born January 12, 1962) was one of the most disabled [[thalidomide]] babies born in the UK. He has since become known internationally through the television drama ''On Giant's Shoulders'' and the best-selling book of the same name.

==Early life==
Originally named Andrew, Wiles was born in [[Peterborough]], [[England]], to a [[prostitute]] mother and a visiting [[African American]] father.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.gordonmoyes.com/2007/08/08/breaking-barriers/] Gordon Moyes 'Breaking Barriers'&lt;/ref&gt; During her pregnancy Andrew's mother took [[thalidomide]] to combat her morning sickness, resulting in his severe disabilities at birth. 

Unable to cope, Andrew's mother put him into care. He met Leonard and Hazel Wiles at Chailey Hospital in [[Sussex]] in October 1967, and after initial opposition from his birth mother and [[Social Services]], Leonard and Hazel were able to [[Adoption|adopt]] the young Andrew. As part of his fresh start with his new parents, Andrew decided to change his name to Terrence Wiles.&lt;ref name=giants&gt;On Giant's Shoulders : the story of Terry Wiles  by Marjorie Wallace and Michael Robson  Times Books, London  1976  ISBN 0723001464&lt;/ref&gt;

Over the years Len Wiles, who was technically-minded and helped to design military equipment during [[World War II]], built a series of 'Supercars' for Terry, based on the [[forklift truck]], which enabled Terry to both augment his height and move around freely for the first time.&lt;ref name=giants/&gt;

Wiles suffered a nervous breakdown due to abuse at his [[secondary school]] [[St Neots Community College|Ernulf Community College]] in [[St. Neots]], where on one occasion some students put him in a bag and dragged him around a room. He left the school to study at a [[polytechnic (United Kingdom)|polytechnic]].&lt;ref name=fight&gt;'Fight For Love' Channel 4 documentary 1997&lt;/ref&gt;

==''On Giant's Shoulders''==
Then aged 19, Wiles played himself in a [[1979]] [[BBC]] television ''Play of the Week'' entitled ''On Giant's Shoulders'', starring [[Judi Dench]] as Hazel Wiles and [[Bryan Pringle]] as Leonard Wiles.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.imdb.com/title/tt0079663/] 'On Giant's Shoulders' on the Internet Movie Database&lt;/ref&gt; The film was based on [[Marjorie Wallace (SANE)|Marjorie Wallace]] and Michael Robson's book about Wiles' life of the same name published in 1976.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.timesonline.co.uk/tol/life_and_style/article1086514.ece] 'The Times' online November 5, 2006&lt;/ref&gt;

==Recent years==
After Wiles received financial compensation for his birth defects he and his adoptive parents [[emigrated]] to [[New Zealand]].

Later, Wiles met Robyn, a married nurse who left her husband to be with him. The couple faced a great deal of opposition from both families; Wiles' parents believed that Robyn was only interested in his money, the financial payout that he had received from the thalidomide manufacturers ([[Distillers Company]]). However, they married in 1991 and began to live together in [[Hamilton, New Zealand]]. Len and Hazel Wiles severed all contact with the couple.&lt;ref&gt;Pilger, John (ed.). ''Tell Me No Lies: Investigative Journalism and its Triumphs''&lt;/ref&gt; Leonard Wiles died in 1996.

Terry and his wife continue to live in Hamilton, where Terry counsels others with disabilities. In 1997 [[Channel 4]] filmed Terry and Robyn in New Zealand for a [[Documentary film|documentary]] entitled ''Fight For Love''.&lt;ref name=fight/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.imdb.com/title/tt1015982/] 'Fight For Love' on the Internet Movie Database&lt;/ref&gt;

==References==
{{reflist}}

==External links==
*[http://ftvdb.bfi.org.uk/sift/individual/55056 The British Film Institute entry for Terry Wiles]

*{{imdb title|0079663|On Giant's Shoulders}}
*{{imdb title|1015982|Fight For Love}}
*[http://www.djdchronology.com/ongiantsshoulders79.htm Website about 'On Giants's Shoulders' the 1979 film of the life of Terry Wiles]
*[http://www.terrywiles.20m.com A website about the life of Terry Wiles]
*[http://www.imdb.com/title/tt0958967/episodes BBC 'Play of the Week' entry for 'On Giant's Shoulders' (1979)]
*[http://www.time.com/time/magazine/article/0,9171,950412,00.html?promoid=googlep 'Time Magazine' review of 'On Giant's Shoulders']
*[http://www.people.com/people/archive/article/0,,20076047,00.html 'Leonard Wiles Is a Saint in the Workshop for Adopted Son Terry and Other Victims of Thalidomide' - article on people.com 17 March 1980]

{{Persondata &lt;!-- Metadata: see [[Wikipedia:Persondata]]. --&gt;
| NAME              = Wiles, Terry
| ALTERNATIVE NAMES =
| SHORT DESCRIPTION =
| DATE OF BIRTH     = January 12, 1962
| PLACE OF BIRTH    =
| DATE OF DEATH     =
| PLACE OF DEATH    =
}}
{{DEFAULTSORT:Wiles, Terry}}
[[Category:1962 births]]
[[Category:Living people]]
[[Category:New Zealand people of English descent]]
[[Category:English people with disabilities]]
[[Category:New Zealand people with disabilities]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
