<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="123654" ns="0" title="Billings, Montana"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Redirect|Billings}}

{{Infobox settlement
|official_name            = Billings, Montana
|settlement_type          = [[City]]
|motto                    = Star of the Big Sky Country
|image_skyline            = Billings Pano.JPG
|imagesize                = 300px
|image_caption            = Billings skyline with the [[Beartooth Mountains]] in the background.
|image_flag               = Billings.png
|image_seal               = Seal of Billings, Montana.png
|nickname = Magic City
|image_map = Yellowstone_County_Montana_Incorporated_and_Unincorporated_areas_Billings_Highlighted.svg
|mapsize                  = 250px
|map_caption              = Location in Yellowstone County and Montana
|image_map1               = Map of USA MT.svg
|mapsize1                 =
|map_caption1             = Location of the state of Montana in the United States
|pushpin_map =USA
|pushpin_map_caption = Location in the United States
|coordinates_region       = US-MT
|subdivision_type         = [[List of countries|Country]]
|subdivision_name         = [[United States]]
|subdivision_type1        = [[Political divisions of the United States|State]]
|subdivision_name1        = [[Montana]]
|subdivision_type2        = [[List of counties in Montana|County]]
|subdivision_name2        = [[Yellowstone County, Montana|Yellowstone]]
|government_type          = [[Mayor-council government|Mayor-Council]]
|leader_title             = [[Mayor]]
|leader_name              = Tom Hanel
|leader_title1            = [[City Administrator|City Admin.]]
|leader_name1             = Christina &quot;Tina&quot; Volek
|leader_title2            = Governing body
|leader_name2             = [[Billings City Council|City Council]]
|established_title        = Founded
|established_title2       = [[Municipal incorporation|Incorporated]]
|established_date         = 1877
|established_date2        = 1882
|area_magnitude           =
|unit_pref                = Imperial
|area_total_sq_mi         = 33.8
|area_total_km2           = 87.6
|area_land_sq_mi          = 33.7
|area_land_km2            = 87.3
|area_water_sq_mi         = 0.1
|area_water_km2           = 0.3
|area_urban_sq_mi         =
|area_urban_km2           =
|area_metro_sq_mi         =
|area_metro_km2           =
|population_as_of         = 2010 census
|population_footnotes     =&lt;ref name=&quot;US Census Fact Finder&quot;&gt;[http://factfinder2.census.gov/faces/tableservices/jsf/pages/productview.xhtml?pid=DEC_10_PL_GCTPL2.ST13&amp;prodType=table US Census Fact Finder]&lt;/ref&gt;
|population_total         = 104170 
|population_metro         = 158050
|population_urban         =
|population_density_km2   = 1047.0
|population_density_sq_mi = 3081.9
|timezone                 = [[Mountain Time Zone|Mountain]]
|utc_offset               = -7
|timezone_DST             = Mountain
|utc_offset_DST           = -6
|coordinates_display      = inline,title
|coordinates_type         = region:US_type:city
|latd = 45 |latm = 47 |lats = 12 |latNS = N
|longd = 108 |longm = 32 |longs = 14 |longEW = W
|elevation_m              = 952
|elevation_ft             = 3123
|website                  = [http://www.cityofbillings.net www.cityofbillings.net]
|postal_code_type         = [[ZIP code]]s
|postal_code              = 59101, 59102, 59103, 59104, 59105, 59106, 59107, 59108, 59109, 59110, 59111, 59112, 59113, 59114, 59115, 59116, 59117&lt;ref name=ZIPcode&gt;{{cite web|date=November 10, 2007 |url=http://zip4.usps.com/zip4/citytown.jsp |title=ZIP Code Lookup |format=[[JavaScript]]/[[HTML]] |publisher=[[United States Postal Service]] |accessdate=November 10, 2007| archiveurl = http://www.webcitation.org/5uRWp2Zfd | archivedate = 2010-11-22| deadurl=no}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|area_code                = [[Area code 406|406]]
|blank_name               = [[Federal Information Processing Standard|FIPS code]]
|blank_info               = 30-06550
|blank1_name              = [[Geographic Names Information System|GNIS]] feature ID
|blank1_info              = 0802034
|blank2_name              = [[List of Montana numbered highways|Highways]]
|blank2_info              = [[File:I-90.svg|20px|link=Interstate 90]] [[File:I-94.svg|20px|link=Interstate 94]] [[File:US 87.svg|20px|link=U.S. Route 87]]
|footnotes                =
}}

'''Billings''' is the largest city in the [[U.S. state]] of [[Montana]], and is the principal city of the [[Billings Metropolitan Area]], the largest [[metropolitan area]] in over {{convert|500|mi|km}}. With a trade area of over half a million people&lt;ref name=&quot;autogenerated1&quot;&gt;[http://money.cnn.com/smallbusiness/best_places_launch/2009/snapshot/34.html Best Places to Launch a Small Business 2009 - Billings, MT - FORTUNE Small Business]&lt;/ref&gt; it is the largest metropolitan area between [[Denver, Colorado|Denver]] and [[Calgary, Alberta|Calgary]] and between [[Sioux Falls, South Dakota]], and [[Spokane, Washington]].&lt;ref&gt;http://www.census.gov/popest/metro/tables/2009/CBSA-EST2009-01.csv&lt;/ref&gt;

Billings is located in the south-central portion of the state and is the [[county seat]] of [[Yellowstone County, Montana|Yellowstone County]], 2010 population of 147,972.{{Geographic reference|6}} The 2010 Census put the Billings population at 104,170,&lt;ref&gt;http://2010.census.gov/news/releases/operations/cb11-cn85.html&lt;/ref&gt; the only city in Montana to surpass 100,000 people.&lt;ref name=&quot;census.gov&quot;/&gt; The city is experiencing rapid growth and a strong economy; it has had and is continuing to have the largest growth of any city in Montana.&lt;ref name=&quot;census.gov&quot;&gt;http://www.census.gov/popest/cities/tables/SUB-EST2009-04-30.csv&lt;/ref&gt; Parts of the metro area are seeing hyper growth. From 2000 to 2010 [[Lockwood, Montana|Lockwood]], a southeastern suburb of the city saw growth of 57.8% the largest percentage growth of any Montana community.&lt;ref&gt;http://quickfacts.census.gov/qfd/states/30/3044200.html&lt;/ref&gt; Billings has avoided the economic downturn that hit most of the nation as well as avoiding the housing bust.&lt;ref&gt;http://missoulian.com/special-section/montana-economy/article_46ed8913-601a-58b8-ad39-036786d870bd.html&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;http://billingsgazette.com/business/article_b322d771-a414-54b0-b344-009ca2993bb9.html&lt;/ref&gt;  With the Bakken oil play in eastern Montana and western North Dakota, the largest oil discovery in U.S. history,&lt;ref name=&quot;marketwire.com&quot;&gt;http://www.marketwire.com/press-release/bakken-the-biggest-oil-discovery-in-us-history-843988.htm&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;wallstreet-online.de&quot;&gt;http://www.wallstreet-online.de/diskussion/1140450-1-10/bakken-the-biggest-oil-discovery-in-u-s-history&lt;/ref&gt; as well as the Heath shale oil play just north of Billings,&lt;ref&gt;http://billingsgazette.com/business/article_e8dba1c2-de7e-5488-aa12-34dff4f2f31c.html&lt;/ref&gt; the city's already rapid growth rate is expected to escalate.&lt;ref&gt;http://billingsgazette.com/news/local/article_3cef647d-8107-5b41-802a-5bc038d1b177.html&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;2012poleshift.wetpaint.com&quot;&gt;http://2012poleshift.wetpaint.com/page/N.+Dakota+Bakken+Oil+Deposit+Would+Free+USA+of+Foreign+Oil+Dependence&lt;/ref&gt;    

Billings was nicknamed the [[Magic City]] because of its growth from its founding as a railroad town in 1882. The city is named for [[Frederick H. Billings]], a former president of the [[Northern Pacific Railroad]]. With one of the largest trade areas in the United States,&lt;ref name=&quot;http://www.bigskyeda-edc.org&quot;&gt;[http://www.bigskyeda-edc.org/ Big Sky Economic Development]&lt;/ref&gt; Billings is the trade and distribution center for most of [[Montana]], Northern [[Wyoming]] and western portions of [[North Dakota]] and [[South Dakota]]. Billings is also the retail destination for much of the same area. With more hotel accommodations than any area within a five state region, the city hosts a variety of conventions, concerts, sporting events and other rallies.&lt;ref name=&quot;http://www.bigskyeda-edc.org&quot;/&gt;

Area attractions include [[Yellowstone National Park]], [[Pompey's Pillar National Monument|Pompey's Pillar]], [[Little Bighorn Battlefield National Monument]], [[Bighorn Canyon National Recreation Area]], [[Pictograph Cave (Billings, Montana)|Pictograph Cave]], [[Chief Plenty Coups State Park]], [[Zoo Montana]], [[Red Lodge Mountain Resort]] and the [[Beartooth Highway]].

==History==
===Before the city===
[[File:Popi sig550.jpg|thumb|William Clark’s inscription on Pompeys Pillar]]

Much of Billings is located in the Yellowstone Valley, carved out by the [[Yellowstone River]]. Over 10 million years ago, this valley was underwater with the tops of the Rimrocks, {{convert|500|to|800|ft|m|adj=on}} cliffs to the north and east of downtown, being a prehistoric beach.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.comevisitbillings.com/&lt;/ref&gt; Some pictographs in the [[Pictograph Cave (Billings, Montana)]] {{convert|6|mi|km}} south of Billings are 2,100 years old. The Pictograph, Middle, and Ghost cave complex were home to generations of prehistoric hunters. Approximately 30,000 artifacts, ranging from stone tools, weapons, paintings and the instruments used, have been identified from the site.&lt;ref name=&quot;visitmt1&quot;&gt;[http://custer.visitmt.com/categories/moreinfo.asp?siteid=129&amp;IDRRecordID=3107 Pictograph Cave State Park]&lt;/ref&gt; They were carved from the Eagle sandstone cliff by the forces of water and wind.&lt;ref name=&quot;visitmt1&quot;/&gt; The [[Crow Indians]] frequented this area from about the year 1700. In 1806, [[William Clark (explorer)|William Clark]] traveled through the region on the Lewis and Clark Expedition. He inscribed his name on [[Pompey's Pillar National Monument|Pompey's Pillar]], a rock formation {{convert|25|mi|km}} northeast of Billings, on July 25, 1806 William Clark wrote that he climbed the sandstone pillar and &quot;had a most extensive view in every direction on the Northerly Side of the river&quot;. Clark named the place &quot;Pompys Tower&quot; in honor of a young [[Shoshone]] boy he had nicknamed &quot;Pompy.&quot; The boy's mother was [[Sacajawea]], who had helped guide the Lewis and Clark expedition and had acted as an interpreter. The name of the formation was changed by 1814 to the current title. Clark's inscription is the only remaining physical evidence found along the route that was followed by the expedition.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.visitmt.com/categories/moreinfo.asp?IDRRecordID=7009&amp;siteid=1 Pompeys Pillar National Monument]&lt;/ref&gt;

===Coulson / Billings===

Billings was established in 1882 in [[Montana Territory]] near the already existing town of Coulson. The city of Billings was a rail hub founded by the Northern Pacific Railroad on a site originally known as Clark's Fork Bottom. The location was steered by a plan to develop freight hauling up Alkali Creek to Ft Benton and beyond into the productive Judith and Musselshell Basins. This inauspicious location was three miles (5&amp;nbsp;km) from fresh water on the alkali flats above the Yellowstone River, and was far from an ideal location to start a town.&lt;ref name=&quot;autogenerated2&quot;&gt;[http://www.yhpb.org/VirtualTours/BillingsTour/billings.html Historic Downtown Billings - Historical Overview]&lt;/ref&gt;

The nearby town of Coulson, five years old and perched on the river's edge just to the northeast, appeared a far more likely site. Coulson was a rough and tumble town where arguments were often followed by gunplay. Coulson's first sheriff was none other than [[Liver-Eating Johnston]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://johnlivereatingjohnston.com/ John Liver Eating Johnston - Home]&lt;/ref&gt; Perhaps the most famous person to be buried in Coulsons Boothill cemetery is Muggins Taylor,&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.billings.k12.mt.us/talesw/teamtale/castle/taylor.htm Taylor]&lt;/ref&gt; the scout who carried the news of Custer's Last Stand to the world. Most buried here were said to have died with their boots on. Settlers moving east from the Gallatin Valley had farmed the flats around Coulson since 1877, and rejoiced at the news that the railroad was coming their way. In the end, though, Billings edged out Coulson, to the great disappointment of those living in the settlement. The town of  Coulson had been situated on the [[Yellowstone River]], which made it ideal for the commerce that [[Steamboats]] brought up the river. However, when the Montana &amp; Minnesota Land Company oversaw the development of potential railroad land, they ignored Coulson, and platted the new town of Billings just a couple of miles to the Northwest. Coulson quickly faded away; most of her residents were absorbed into Billings. Yet for a short time the two towns co-existed: a trolley even ran between the two. But ultimately there was no future for Coulson as Billings grew. Though it stood on the banks of the Yellowstone River only a couple of miles from the heart of present day Downtown Billings, the city of Billings never built on the land where Coulson once stood. Today Coulson Park sits along the banks of the Yellowstone where the valley's first town once stood.&lt;ref name=&quot;autogenerated2&quot;/&gt;

===Early railroad town===

Billings railroad ancestry is seen in its townsite configuration. Unlike mining towns of the region whose contours traced the haphazard routes of streambeds and ore bodies, railroad towns were orderly geometric affairs. Laid out on rectilinear grids, the rail lines formed the spine of the townsite, with streets for businesses and homes projecting away at right angles. Taking advantage of the unique way that Billings straddled two sections, Clark platted the town to include two main commercial streets, paralleling and fronting onto the rail line. These twin streets, named Montana and Minnesota for the mother company that gave them life, formed the commercial center of the new town.&lt;ref name=&quot;autogenerated2&quot;/&gt;

On April 1, 1882, Heman Clark arrived at Billings. Detailing the creation of the Billings townsite, what he described was basically an instant city planned to hold 20,000 inhabitants. Eight or nine sawmills, a {{convert|16|mi|km|adj=on}} irrigation system, rail spurs to nearby mines and money for the first bank in town came with the package. The railroad's promise to pump massive capital into the town &quot;lit the fuse of a crazed land boom&quot;, and when M&amp;MLI agent G. B. Hulme joined Clark the following week, the land rush was on.&lt;ref name=&quot;autogenerated2&quot;/&gt;

Meanwhile, work on the approaching NP line continued at breakneck pace. Henry Villard, then president of the NP, was pushing hard for the transcontinental connection. While rail crews built east from Portland, others continued west up the Yellowstone valley. In August 1882, the line was completed to Billings, and on September 8, 1883, spike-driving celebrations at Gold Creek, Montana forged the final link in the NP's chain across the continent.&lt;ref name=&quot;autogenerated2&quot;/&gt;

By May 1882, there were three buildings on the spot destined to become Billings. They were headquarters to lodge railroad survey crews, H. Clark's townsite office and mercantile, and a lone residence. Immediately, the building of town began. Many of the first structures were tents that sheltered hustling new businesses and town residents. Alongside them, cabins of rough-hewn log sprouted in about equal numbers and rapidly replaced the tents. By mid-June the first year, 79 tent shelters were in use, 81 houses were complete and another 75 homes were underway. Buildings to house new arrivals were hastily constructed south of the tracks, while commercial buildings and hotels were planted close to the hub of railroad activities. To keep order in the midst of the flurry, it was decreed that all dwellings be kept off the middle of streets&lt;ref name=&quot;autogenerated2&quot;/&gt;

The building boom continued, and by the end of 1883, the newspaper reported some 400 buildings, occupied by over 1,500 citizens. Maps of the day reveal that downtown encompassed about a nine-block area, split about evenly north and south of the railroad tracks. However, on the south the buildings were all of wood frame construction, while to the north, brick buildings were already beginning to edge out first generation frame buildings. Beyond downtown, the area south of the tracks became the first large residential neighborhood.&lt;ref name=&quot;autogenerated2&quot;/&gt;

On November 19, 1888, a visiting reporter described Billings' progress through her first half decade.

''In January 1882, Billings was a bright prairie. Today it is a sprightly, live, energetic and aggressive town of 1,500 inhabitants. It has certain metropolitan characteristics such as a splendid system of water works, electric lights, graded streets, efficient fire department, excellent schools and churches, good society, an intelligent class of people, wide awake and quick to respond to any demands upon their purses in the interest of the community.''&lt;ref name=&quot;autogenerated2&quot;/&gt;
[[File:MT Billings 1904.jpg|thumb|Billings 1904]]
[[File:MT-Billings 1914 Ref.jpg|thumb|Downtown Billings Post Office 1914]]

===20th century===

The railroad and the new townsite drew settlers from far and wide. Many of the new arrivals came from other countries (the 1900 census recorded a quarter of the population foreign-born), creating a cosmopolitan mix of people and cultures in early Billings. The Northern Pacific employed many Chinese on their rail crews, and many took up resident status in the new city of Billings. A police officer of the day remembered there were some 90 people, mainly &quot;laundry and restaurant employees, born in China and with families still in China. The Chinese lived close together, primarily at the east end of the townsite near Minnesota Ave. Sam Lee, one of the most prominent Chinese businessmen, owned much of block 189 including the L &amp; L Building which still stands at 2624 Minnesota Ave.&lt;ref name=&quot;autogenerated2&quot;/&gt;

In 1909, the Great Northern Railway built through Montana to Billings and beyond. That same year, Congress passed the Enlarged Homestead Act, allowing people to lay claim to {{convert|320|acre|km2}} farms (double the previous size). What had been a steady flow of settlement suddenly became a raging torrent. In the heartland of dry farming, Billings was both a farm and rail hub. Outside of town, some {{convert|100,000|acre|km2}} were put into cultivation, while greater Yellowstone County reported {{convert|2500000|acre|km2}} dry were tilled for homestead farms.&lt;ref name=&quot;autogenerated2&quot;/&gt;

Banks abounded in Billings, each a monument to local prosperity. By 1905, there were six banks in town, with a combined capital of over half a million dollars. Downtown was transformed during this &quot;modern&quot; era, and buildings of the late 19th century gave way to new, larger buildings that reflected the prosperity of Billings in the early 20th century. The presence of the Burlington and Milwaukee Railroad along the 5th Avenue North right-of-way drew downtown development that direction, and northern portions of downtown became increasingly urban. On March 24, 1909, a new downtown &quot;Union Depot&quot; serving the NP, Great Northern and Burlington lines opened to the public. Hotels large and small sprouted at the heart of downtown to serve travelers to Billings. Most prominent were the Northern and the Grand Hotels. Both buildings remain today, and are commanding on the Billings skyline. Smaller hotels also grew up in the shadow of the depot. Along Montana in the depot district, several small hotels were erected during the second decade of the 20th century. The Eagle, McCormick, Rex, Lincoln and Carlin are among those buildings that still remain.&lt;ref name=&quot;autogenerated2&quot;/&gt;

By the 1910 census, Billings' population had risen to 10,031 ranking it the sixth fastest growing community in the nation.&lt;ref name=&quot;autogenerated2&quot;/&gt; In 1911, a new Federal Building at First Ave. North and North 26th St. was begun. Completed in January 1914, it housed the post office, courthouse, and a booming U.S. Land Office. In 1912, the Montana Power Company constructed the Electric Building, aglow at night with recessed panel lighting. In May 1918, the Hart-Albin Building was completed and opened for business at Broadway and Second Ave. North.&lt;ref name=&quot;autogenerated2&quot;/&gt;

{{Panorama
|image      = File:MT Panoramic view of Billings 1915.jpg|MT
|fullwidth  = 2000
|fullheight = 396
|caption    = Panoramic view of downtown Billings 1915.
|height     = 200
}}

Homes and older commercial buildings in the way of the boom were quick to go. At the same time, desirable neighborhoods rose up on the edge of the expanding downtown. A stone mansion and carriage house (&quot;The Castle&quot;) built by Austin North in the 600 block of North 29th St. helped to set the pace in this fashionable northern part of town. On the western side of town, P.B. Moss built a red stone house on Division,&lt;ref name=&quot;mossmansion.com&quot;&gt;[http://www.mossmansion.com/ Welcome to the Historic Moss Mansion - About the Museum]&lt;/ref&gt; and I.D. O'Donnell built a large new home at First St. West and Clark St. in 1904.&lt;ref name=&quot;autogenerated2&quot;/&gt;

Toward the end of the homestead boom, oil production began on the outskirts of town. The Elk Basin oil field on the Montana-Wyoming border was located in mid-1915, and by the following year, the first well near Billings was drilled. Soon the Montana-Wyoming Oil Journal was in print to report on the latest developments from the oil fields. Just 6 years later, natural gas was also discovered in the basin, and plans for a pipeline to the city were discussed. In the 1940s and 1950s, this industry helped pull Billings into a new era and became a lynchpin of the local economy.&lt;ref name=&quot;autogenerated2&quot;/&gt;

After [[World War II]], Billings boomed into the major financial, medical and cultural center of the region. Billings always experienced rapid growth from its founding, in its first 50 years growth was at times in the 300 and 400 percentile.&lt;ref&gt;http://books.google.com/books?id=T9HrAAAAMAAJ&amp;pg=PA311&amp;lpg=PA311&amp;dq=census+billings+montana+1900&amp;source=bl&amp;ots=Nbo9SdNvbB&amp;sig=yXIoRpGw-r6X29YPdRLOruUuFMM&amp;hl=en&amp;ei=xd53TaKbK4r1rAGp9f3WDQ&amp;sa=X&amp;oi=book_result&amp;ct=result&amp;resnum=5&amp;ved=0CD4Q6AEwBDgK#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false&lt;/ref&gt; Billings's growth has remained robust throughout the years and at times almost unmanageable as in the 1950s when it had a growth rate of 66.0%. The [[1973 oil embargo]] by [[OPEC]] spurred an oil boom in eastern Montana, northern Wyoming and Western North Dakota. With this increase in oil production, Billings became the headquarters for energy sector companies. In 1975 and 1976, the [[Colstrip]] coal fire generation plants 1 and 2 were completed; plants 3 and 4 were operational in 1984 and 1986.

In the 1970s and 1980s, Billings saw major growth in its downtown core; the first high-rise buildings to be built in Montana were erected. In 1980, the 22-floor Sheraton Hotel was completed. At the time, it was the tallest building from Minneapolis, Minnesota to Seattle, Washington and from Denver, Colorado to Calgary, Alberta (Canada). Upon its completion it was also declared &quot;the tallest load-bearing brick masonry building in the world&quot; by the Brick Institute of America.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.emporis.com/application/?nav=building&amp;lng=3&amp;id=sheratonbillingshotel-billings-mt-usa Crowne Plaza, Billings, U.S.A. &amp;#124; Emporis.com]&lt;/ref&gt; During the 1970s and 1980s, Billings also saw the completion of other important buildings in its downtown core;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.emporis.com/wm/ci/bu/?id=102598 Buildings of Billings &amp;#124; Emporis.com]&lt;/ref&gt; the Norwest Building (now Wells Fargo), Granite Tower, Sage Tower the MetraPark arena, the TransWestern Center, many new city owned parking garages and the First Interstate Tower, now the tallest building in a five state area.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.emporis.com/application/?nav=building&amp;lng=3&amp;id=1interstatecenter-billings-mt-usa First Interstate Center, Billings, U.S.A. &amp;#124; Emporis.com]&lt;/ref&gt;

With the completion of large sections of the interstate system in Montana in the 1970s, Billings became an even bigger shopping destination for an ever increasingly larger area. The 1970s and 1980s saw new shopping districts and shopping centers developed in the Billings area. In addition to the other shopping centers developed, two new malls were developed and a third mall redeveloped and enlarged, Rimrock Mall on what was then the city's west end, Cross Roads Mall, ''no longer in existence,'' in Billings Heights, and West Park Plaza mall in midtown. In addition, several new business parks were developed on the city's west end during this period. Billings was affected by the [[1980 eruption of Mount St. Helens]] in May; the city received about an inch of ash on the ground.&lt;ref&gt;[http://pubs.usgs.gov/fs/2000/fs036-00/ Mount St. Helens - From the 1980 Eruption to 2000, Fact Sheet 036-00]&lt;/ref&gt; The [[Yellowstone fires of 1988]] blanketed Billings in smoke for weeks.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.yellowstone-bearman.com/yfire.html Yellowstone's Year Of Fire-1988]&lt;/ref&gt;

{{Panorama
|image      = Image:Billings Pano.JPG
|fullwidth  = 2000
|fullheight = 396
|caption    = Downtown Billings.
|height     = 200
}}

In the 1990s, Billings saw further enlargement of its service sector with the arrival of new shopping centers built around stores such as Target, Wal Mart and Office Depot, all of which built multiple outlets in the Billings area. With the addition of more interchange exits along [[I-90]], even more hotel chains and service industry outlets are being built in Billings. Development of more business parks and large residential developments on the city's west end, South Hills area Lockwood and the Billings Heights were all part of the 1990s. Billings received the [[All-America City Award]] in 1992.
[[File:First Interstate Center, Billings, MT cropped.jpg|thumb|First Interstate Tower downtown Is the tallest building from Denver to Calgary, Alberta, Canada and from Minneapolis to Spokane.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.emporis.com/building/1interstatecenter-billings-mt-usa&lt;/ref&gt;]]

===21st century===

In the 21st century, Billings saw the development of operations centers in the city's business parks and downtown core by such national companies as GE, Wells Fargo and First Interstate Bank. It also saw renewed growth in the downtown core with the addition of numerous new buildings, new parking garages and a new MET Transit Center and in 2002 [[Skypoint]] was completed. Downtown also saw a renaissance of the historic areas within the downtown core as building after building was restored to its previous glory. In 2007, Billings was designated a [[Preserve America Community]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.preserveamerica.gov/12-26-07PAcommunity-billingsMT.html Preserve America Community.]&lt;/ref&gt; With the completion of the Shiloh interchange exit off [[Interstate 90]], The TransTech  Center was developed&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.transtechcenter.com/ Transtech Center]&lt;/ref&gt; and yet more hotel development as well. In 2010 the Shiloh corridor was open for business with the completion of the Shiloh parkway, a {{convert|4.8|mi|km|adj=on}} multi-lane street with eight [[roundabouts]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://billingsgazette.com/news/local/government-and-politics/article_146041ab-beff-52c0-97a1-791734c50f36.html Shiloh Road open end to end]&lt;/ref&gt; Even more shopping centers were developed in the 21st century. Some of the new centers are Shiloh Crossing which brought the first [[Kohl's]]&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.kohlscorporation.com/maps/SiteAdvantage/advantage.asp Kohl's Department Stores: Store Locator]&lt;/ref&gt; department store to Montana, Billings Town Square with Montana's first [[Cabela's]],&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.cabelas.com/retail-stores-billings.shtml Cabela's Billings, MT Store - 4550 King Avenue East - Billings, MT 59101 - Store Locations : Cabela]&lt;/ref&gt; and West Park Promenade, Montana's first open-air shopping mall. In 2009, ''Fortune Small Business'' magazine named Billings the best small city in which to start a business.&lt;ref name=&quot;autogenerated1&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;billingsgazette.com&quot;&gt;[http://billingsgazette.com/news/local/article_1b8ca078-b7f7-11de-b482-001cc4c03286.html Magazine names Billings best small city for launching business]&lt;/ref&gt; Billings saw continued growth with the largest actual growth of any city in Montana. On June 20, 2010 (Father's Day), a tornado, dubbed by the media the [[Fathers Day Tornado]],&lt;ref name=&quot;cbsnews1&quot;&gt;[http://www.cbsnews.com/stories/2010/06/21/national/main6602309.shtml Montana Tornado Rips Roof off Sports Arena - CBS News]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;kulr1&quot;&gt;[http://www.kulr8.com/younews/96832384.html Last pics of Father's Day Tornado &amp;#124; KULR-8 News, Sports, Weather - Billings, Montana YouNews™]&lt;/ref&gt; touched down in the downtown core and Heights sections of Billings. The [[Rimrock Auto Arena at MetraPark]] and area businesses suffered major damage. While the nation has been feeling the effects of a recession, Billings's economy has been strong. Construction and housing starts have been up has well as large investments in the community by national companies and major new road construction projects. The state's economy is healthier than most states but as western Montana is suffering from a crash in real estate and the near demise of its timber industry, eastern Montana and North Dakota are experiencing an energy boom due to coal and the [[Bakken formation]]  the largest oil discovery in U.S. history.&lt;ref name=&quot;marketwire.com&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;wallstreet-online.de&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;2012poleshift.wetpaint.com&quot;/&gt; Billings is Montana's oasis of economic growth.&lt;ref name=&quot;autogenerated1&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://billingsgazette.com/business/article_b322d771-a414-54b0-b344-009ca2993bb9.html Eastern part of state faring better economically]&lt;/ref&gt;

==Geography==
[[File:Billings MT and Yellowstone River .jpg|thumb|The Rims border the north and east edges of the downtown core]]
Billings is located at {{Coord|45|47|12|N|108|32|14|W|type:city}} (45.786553, -108.537139){{Geographic reference|1}}, with two-thirds of the city being in the Yellowstone Valley and the South Hills area and one-third being in the Heights-Lockwood area. The city is divided by the Rims, long cliffs, also called the [[Rimrocks]]. The Rims run to the north and east of the downtown core, separating it from the Heights to the north and Lockwood to the east, with the cliffs to the north being {{convert|500|ft|m}} tall and to the east of downtown, the face rises {{convert|800|ft|m}}. The [[Yellowstone River]] runs through the southeast portion of the city. According to the [[United States Census Bureau]], the city has a total area of 33.8&amp;nbsp;square miles (87.6&amp;nbsp;km²), of which 33.7&amp;nbsp;square miles (87.3&amp;nbsp;km²) is land and 0.1&amp;nbsp;square mile (0.3&amp;nbsp;km²) (0.33%) is water. Around Billings, six mountain ranges can be viewed, the [[Bighorn Mountains]], [[Pryor Mountains]], [[Beartooth Mountains]], [[Crazy Mountains]], [[Big Snowy Mountains]] and the [[Bull Mountains]].

==Climate==
Billings has a semi-arid climate ([[Koppen climate classification|Koppen]] ''BSk''),&lt;ref&gt;Peel, M. C., Finlayson, B. L., and McMahon, T. A.: [[Media:Americas Koppen Map.png|Updated world map of the Köppen-Geiger climate classification]], Hydrol. Earth Syst. Sci., 11, 1633-1644, 2007.&lt;/ref&gt; with hot summers, and cold, dry winters. In the summer, the temperature can rise to over {{convert|100|°F|0}} (1 to 3 times per year)&lt;ref name = &quot;NCDC Billings Airport&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref name = &quot;NCDC Downtown Billings &quot; /&gt; while the winter can bring temperatures below zero (-17°C), with 17 to 18 such nights per year.&lt;ref name = &quot;NCDC Billings Airport&quot; /&gt; The snowfall averages about 57&amp;nbsp;inches a year, but because of warm [[Chinook winds]] that pass through the region between December and March, the snow does not usually accumulate heavily or remain on the ground for long. First frosts generally come early (late September to early October) and last frosts (late April to early May) late.&lt;ref name = &quot;NCDC Billings Airport&quot; /&gt; Spring and autumn in Billings are usually mild, but brief. Winds, while strong at times, are considered light compared with the rest of Montana and the Rocky Mountain front.

{{Weather box
|location = Billings, Montana ([[Billings Logan International Airport|Billings Airport]])
|single line = Y
|collapsed = Y
|Jan high F = 32.8
|Feb high F = 39.5
|Mar high F = 47.6
|Apr high F = 57.5
|May high F = 67.4
|Jun high F = 78.0
|Jul high F = 85.8
|Aug high F = 84.5
|Sep high F = 71.8
|Oct high F = 58.9
|Nov high F = 42.7
|Dec high F = 34.5
|year high F = 58.4
|Jan low F = 15.1
|Feb low F = 20.1
|Mar low F = 26.4
|Apr low F = 34.7
|May low F = 44.0
|Jun low F = 52.5
|Jul low F = 58.3
|Aug low F = 57.3
|Sep low F = 47.1
|Oct low F = 37.2
|Nov low F = 25.6
|Dec low F = 17.7
|year low F = 36.3
|Jan precipitation inch =  .81
|Feb precipitation inch =  .58
|Mar precipitation inch = 1.12
|Apr precipitation inch = 1.74
|May precipitation inch = 2.48
|Jun precipitation inch = 1.89
|Jul precipitation inch = 1.28
|Aug precipitation inch =  .85
|Sep precipitation inch = 1.34
|Oct precipitation inch = 1.26
|Nov precipitation inch =  .75
|Dec precipitation inch =  .67
|year precipitation inch = 14.77
|Jan snow inch = 10.3
|Feb snow inch = 6.5
|Mar snow inch = 10.3
|Apr snow inch = 7.7
|May snow inch = 1.8
|Jun snow inch = 0
|Jul snow inch = 0
|Aug snow inch = 0
|Sep snow inch = 1.3
|Oct snow inch = 4.2
|Nov snow inch = 7.5
|Dec snow inch = 8.2
|year snow inch = 57.8
|unit precipitation days = 0.01 in
|unit snow days = 0.1 in
|Jan precipitation days = 8.0
|Feb precipitation days = 6.9
|Mar precipitation days = 9.3
|Apr precipitation days = 10.7
|May precipitation days = 12.0
|Jun precipitation days = 11.0
|Jul precipitation days = 8.1
|Aug precipitation days = 6.6
|Sep precipitation days = 7.2
|Oct precipitation days = 6.8
|Nov precipitation days = 6.3
|Dec precipitation days = 7.2
|Jan snow days = 7.2
|Feb snow days = 6.2
|Mar snow days = 7.2
|Apr snow days = 4.3
|May snow days =  .8
|Jun snow days =   0
|Jul snow days =   0
|Aug snow days =   0
|Sep snow days =  .5
|Oct snow days = 2.2
|Nov snow days = 4.8
|Dec snow days = 7.2
|Jan sun = 130.2
|Feb sun = 158.2
|Mar sun = 235.6
|Apr sun = 255.0
|May sun = 282.1
|Jun sun = 306.0
|Jul sun = 356.5
|Aug sun = 328.6
|Sep sun = 255.0
|Oct sun = 204.6
|Nov sun = 129.0
|Dec sun = 117.8
|source 1 = NOAA (1971-2000)&lt;ref name = &quot;NCDC Billings Airport&quot; &gt;
{{cite web
| title = Climatography of the United States No. 20: BILLINGS INTL AP, MT 1971-2000
| url = http://cdo.ncdc.noaa.gov/climatenormals/clim20/mt/240807.pdf
| format = PDF
| publisher = National Oceanic and Atmospheric Administration
| accessdate = 2010-09-25
}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|source 2 = HKO (sun only, 1961-1990)&lt;ref name = HKO &gt;
{{cite web
| title = Climatological Normals of Billings
| url = http://www.weather.gov.hk/wxinfo/climat/world/eng/n_america/us/billings_e.htm
| publisher = [[Hong Kong Observatory]]
| accessdate = 2010-09-25
}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|date = August 2010
}}

{{Weather box
|location = Billings, Montana (downtown)
|collapsed = Y
|single line = Y
|Jan high F = 37.3
|Feb high F = 44.2
|Mar high F = 53.2
|Apr high F = 62.7
|May high F = 71.7
|Jun high F = 81.1
|Jul high F = 88.4
|Aug high F = 87.8
|Sep high F = 77.1
|Oct high F = 65.3
|Nov high F = 47.9
|Dec high F = 39.1
|year high F = 63.0
|Jan low F = 13.3
|Feb low F = 18.3
|Mar low F = 25.4
|Apr low F = 33.8
|May low F = 43.1
|Jun low F = 51.2
|Jul low F = 56.2
|Aug low F = 54.8
|Sep low F = 44.9
|Oct low F = 35.3
|Nov low F = 24.0
|Dec low F = 15.8
|year low F = 34.7
|Jan record high F = 75
|Feb record high F = 76
|Mar record high F = 82
|Apr record high F = 92
|May record high F = 99
|Jun record high F = 108
|Jul record high F = 112
|Aug record high F = 107
|Sep record high F = 100
|Oct record high F = 95
|Nov record high F = 80
|Dec record high F = 75
|year record high F = 112
|Jan record low F = −39
|Feb record low F = −49
|Mar record low F = −34
|Apr record low F = −5
|May record low F = 14
|Jun record low F = 26
|Jul record low F = 37
|Aug record low F = 28
|Sep record low F = 18
|Oct record low F = −11
|Nov record low F = −28
|Dec record low F = −41
|year record low F = −49
|Jan precipitation inch =  .62
|Feb precipitation inch =  .49
|Mar precipitation inch =  .87
|Apr precipitation inch = 1.55
|May precipitation inch = 2.39
|Jun precipitation inch = 1.98
|Jul precipitation inch = 1.19
|Aug precipitation inch =  .92
|Sep precipitation inch = 1.42
|Oct precipitation inch = 1.32
|Nov precipitation inch =  .64
|Dec precipitation inch =  .57
|year precipitation inch = 13.96
|unit precipitation days = 0.01 in
|Jan precipitation days = 6.3
|Feb precipitation days = 4.5
|Mar precipitation days = 5.9
|Apr precipitation days = 7.5
|May precipitation days = 9.4
|Jun precipitation days = 9.7
|Jul precipitation days = 6.0
|Aug precipitation days = 5.3
|Sep precipitation days = 6.0
|Oct precipitation days = 5.9
|Nov precipitation days = 4.9
|Dec precipitation days = 5.1
|source 1 = NOAA (normals 1971-2000, extremes 1894-2001)&lt;ref name = &quot;NCDC Downtown Billings&quot; &gt;
{{cite web
| title = Climatography of the United States No. 20: BILLINGS WATER PLANT, MT 1971-2000
| url = http://cdo.ncdc.noaa.gov/climatenormals/clim20/mt/240802.pdf
| format = PDF
| publisher = National Oceanic and Atmospheric Administration
| accessdate = 2010-09-25
}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|date=December 2010}}

===Severe weather===
Although far from [[Tornado Alley]], Billings is not immune from severe weather, but tornadoes are very rare in Billings. In most cases, severe storms travel fast at 25 to 30 miles per hour and either veer to the north or south of the city. The first recorded tornado to touch down in Billings was on June 2, 1958. On June 20, 2010, a tornado dubbed the [[Fathers Day Tornado]]&lt;ref name=&quot;cbsnews1&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;kulr1&quot;/&gt; touched down in the Billings Heights and Downtown sections of the city. The tornado was accompanied by hail up to golf ball size, dangerous cloud to ground lightning, and heavy winds. The tornado destroyed a number of businesses and severely damaged the 12,000-seat [[Rimrock Auto Arena at MetraPark]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.mtstandard.com/news/state-and-regional/article_b8d6f6ec-7cc5-11df-886c-001cc4c002e0.html UPDATED: Tornado heavily damages MetraPark, Billings stores]&lt;/ref&gt;

==Demographics==
===Population===
{{USCensusPop
| 1870=145
| 1880=587
| 1890=836
| 1900=3211
| 1910=10031
| 1920=15100
| 1930=16386
| 1940=23216
| 1950=31834
| 1960=52851
| 1970=61581
| 1980=66798
| 1990=81151
| 2000=89847
| 2010=104170
| estyear=2010
| footnote=Source:&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web| url=http://www.census.gov/population/www/documentation/twps0076.html | title=Historical Census Statistics On Population Totals By Race, 1790 to 1990, and By Hispanic Origin, 1970 to 1990, For the top 100 Cities And Other Urban Places In The United States (Montana) |author=Campbell Gibson and Kay Jung | publisher=U.S. Census Bureau | month=February | year=2005 | accessdate=2009-08-21}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web| url=http://www.census.gov/population/www/documentation/twps0027.html | title=Population of top 100 US cities and other urban places in the United States: 1790 to 1990 | author= Campbell Gibson | publisher=U.S. Census Bureau | month=June | year=1998 | accessdate=2007-11-16 | archiveurl = http://www.webcitation.org/5QDWouvv1 | archivedate = 2007-07-09| deadurl=no}}&lt;/ref&gt;
}}

The 2010 Census recorded Billings' population at 104,934 with a population density of 3,080.9 per square mile (1,047.0/km2).&lt;ref name=&quot;US Census Fact Finder&quot;/&gt; 

According to the 2010 Census, the city's population was 89.6% White (86.9% Non-Hispanic White alone), 0.8% Black or African American, 4.4% American Indian and Alaska Native, 0.7% Asian, 0.1% Native Hawaiian and Other Pacific Islander, 1.4% from Some Other Race and 2.9% from Two or More Races. Hispanics and Latinos of any race made up 5.2% of the population. &lt;ref&gt;http://factfinder2.census.gov/faces/tableservices/jsf/pages/productview.xhtml?pid=DEC_10_DP_DPDP1&amp;prodType=table&lt;/ref&gt;

There were 37,525 households out of which 29.2% had children under the age of 18 living with them, 47.2% were [[Marriage|married couples]] living together, 10.8% had a female householder with no husband present, and 38.3% were non-families. 31.3% of all households were made up of individuals and 11.4% had someone living alone who was 65 years of age or older. The average household size was 2.32 and the average family size was 2.93.

In the city, the population was spread out with 24.0% under the age of 18, 10.1% from 18 to 24, 28.7% from 25 to 44, 22.3% from 45 to 64, and 14.8% who were 65 years of age or older. The median age was 37 years. For every 100 females there were 92.7 males. For every 100 females age 18 and over, there were 88.8 males.

The median income for a household in the city was $35,147, and the median income for a family was $45,032. Males had a median income of $32,525 versus $21,824 for females. The [[per capita income]] for the city was $19,207. About 9.2% of families and 12.0% of the population were below the [[poverty line]], including 16.5% of those under age 18 and 7.0% of those age 65 or over. 29.4% of the population had a Bachelor's degree or higher.&lt;ref&gt;[http://factfinder.census.gov/servlet/ADPTable?_bm=y&amp;-qr_name=ACS_2009_3YR_G00_DP3YR5&amp;-geo_id=31200US137403006550&amp;-context=adp&amp;-ds_name=&amp;-tree_id=3309&amp;-_lang=en&amp;-redoLog=false&amp;-format=7]&lt;/ref&gt;

===Sections===
[[File:Billings MT Downtown.jpg|thumb|Tree lined streets on a late summer day Downtown]]

Billings has many sections that comprise the whole of the city. Because of the unique geography of Billings many of these sections are defined by actual physical characteristics of the terrain. For example; the Heights is separated from Downtown by a {{convert|500|ft|m|adj=on}} cliff known as the (Rims).

{{Main|Sections of Billings, Montana}}
There are currently 10 official first level of districts called &quot;sections&quot; within the city limits of Billings, Montana.

===Neighborhoods and zones===

The city's neighborhoods make up the soul of Billings. The south side of Billings is probably the oldest residential area in the city, and it is the city’s most culturally diverse Neighborhood. South Park is an old growth City park, host to countless food fairs and festivals in the summer months. The Bottom Westend Historic District is home to many of Billings first mansions.  Mid-town, the most densely populated portion of the city is in the midst of [[gentrification]] on a level that few if any areas in Montana have ever seen.  Or even Josephine Crossing, one of Billings' many new contemporary neighborhoods.

{{Main|Neighborhoods and Zones of Billings, Montana}}

===Suburbs and communities of the Billings Metro Area===

Billings is surrounded by many incorporated and unincorporated communities, which make up the [[Billings Metropolitan Area]]. They include Laurel, Lockwood, Shepherd, Huntley, Worden, Pompey's Pillar and Ballantine all in Yellowstone County. In Carbon County are Red Lodge, Bridger, Joliet, Bearcreek, Belfry, Fromberg, Boyd, Edgar, Fox, Luther, Roberts, Rockvale, Roscoe, Silesia and Washoe.

{{Main|Suburbs of Billings, Montana}}

==Government==
{| class=&quot;toccolours&quot; border=&quot;1&quot; cellpadding=&quot;2&quot; cellspacing=&quot;0&quot; style=&quot;border-collapse: collapse; float:right; margin: .5em;&quot;
|+ '''City Council:'''&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://ci.billings.mt.us/index.aspx?NID=159 |title=City Council Members |author= |date= |work= |publisher=The City of Billings, Montana |accessdate=12 September 2010}}
&lt;/ref&gt;
|-
| '''Mayor''' || [[Tom Hanel]]
|-
| '''Ward 1''' || Peggie Denney Gaghen / Jim Ronquillo
|-
| '''Ward 2''' || Angela Cimmino / Denis Pitman
|-
| '''Ward 3''' || Richard McFadden / Vince Ruegamer
|-
| '''Ward 4''' || Jani McCall / Ed Ulledalen
|-
| '''Ward 5''' || Richard (Dick) Clark / Mark Astle
|}
{{Main|Billings, Montana Government and Politics}}

Billings is governed via the mayor council system.  There are ten members of the city council who are elected from one of five wards with each ward electing two members. The mayor is elected in a citywide vote. The current city charter, also called the Billings, Montana City Code (BMCC) was established 1977.

{{Main|Mayors of Billings, Montana}}

==Public safety==
The [[Billings Police Department]] is the main [[law enforcement agency]] in Billings. It is the largest city police force in [[Montana]], with about 136 sworn officers and 80 civilian employees. There are nine police beats.

The [[Billings Fire Department]] provides emergency services including fire suppression, emergency medical response, hazardous materials response, high angle rescue, confined space rescue, vehicle accident extrication, fire investigations, fire inspections, and fire education. The department has 97 employees, including four battalion chiefs, 27 captains, 27 engineers, and 39 firefighters.

[[American Medical Response]] (AMR) provides emergency medical services at the [[paramedic]] care level in Billings, and supports other agencies throughout Yellowstone County.

==The tallest buildings in Montana==
[[List of tallest buildings in Billings]].
The tallest buildings in Montana and a five state region are in Billings. This is a list of the ten tallest buildings in the city.&lt;ref&gt; http://www.emporis.com/application/?nav=building&amp;lng=3&amp;id=1interstatecenter-billings-mt-usa &lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;http://www.emporis.com/application/?nav=building&amp;lng=3&amp;id=1interstatecenter-billings-mt-usa&lt;/ref&gt; 
[[File:Skyline 2.JPG|thumb|left|The Crowne Plaza Downtown]]&lt;ref&gt;http://skyscraperpage.com/cities/?buildingID=6284&lt;/ref&gt;

==Economy==
The geographic location of Billings was essential to its economic success. It is the center of a large area, bordered by Minneapolis, Minnesota to the east and  Seattle, Washington to the west, Calgary, Alberta (Canada) to the north and Denver, Colorado to the south.&lt;ref name=&quot;ci.billings.mt.us&quot;&gt;[http://ci.billings.mt.us/ City of Billings, MT - Official Website]&lt;/ref&gt; Billings' future as a major trade and distribution center was basically assured from its founding as a railroad hub due to its geographic location. As Billings quickly became the region's economic hub it outgrew the other cities in the region. Billings trade area is geographically one of the largest trade areas in the United States.&lt;ref name=&quot;ci.billings.mt.us&quot;/&gt; The Billings trade area serves over a half million people.&lt;ref name=&quot;autogenerated1&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;ci.billings.mt.us&quot;/&gt; A major trade and distribution center, the city is home to many regional headquarters and corporate headquarters.&lt;ref name=&quot;ci.billings.mt.us&quot;/&gt; With Montana having no sales tax, Billings is a retail destination for much of Wyoming, North and South Dakota as well as most of Montana.&lt;ref name=&quot;ci.billings.mt.us&quot;/&gt; Billings is an energy center; Billings sits amidst the largest coal reserves in the United States as well as large oil and natural gas fields.&lt;ref name=&quot;ci.billings.mt.us&quot;/&gt;

[[File:Billings MT Downtown from above.jpg|thumb|Foreground: The Historic Grand Building Downtown]]

In 2009, ''Fortune Small Business'' magazine named Billings the best small city in which to start a business.&lt;ref name=&quot;billingsgazette.com&quot;/&gt; Billings has a diverse economy including a large and rapidly growing medical corridor that includes inpatient and outpatient health care. Billiings has a large service sector including retail, hospitality and entertainment. The metro area is also home to 3 oil refineries, a sugar beet refining plant, a coal fire generation plant, commercial and residential construction, building materials mfg and distribution, professional services, financial services, banking, trucking, higher education (4 campuses, 19 others have a physical presence/classes here), auto parts wholesaling and repair services, passenger and cargo air, cattle, media, printing, wheat and barley farming, sugar beet refining, milk processing, heavy equipment sales and service, business services, consumer services, food distribution, ag chemical mfg and distribution, energy exploration and production, surface and underground mining, metal fabrication, and many others providing a diverse and robust economy.

Corporate headquarters include [[Stillwater Mining Company]], [[Kampgrounds of America]], [[First Interstate BancSystem|First Interstate Bank]], Computers Unlimited, Tire-Rama, Western Plains Machinery, Tractor &amp; Equipment Co., Bresnan Communications, Corporate Air, Employee Benefits Management Services, Edwards Jet Service, Waggoners Trucking, Meadowlark Agency, Ryan Restaurant Corp., CTA Architects &amp; Engineers, JGA Architects, HKM Engineering, Electrical Consultants Inc. engineering, Unifield Engineering, Energy Labs, and others.&lt;ref name=&quot;bigskyeda-edc.org&quot;&gt;[http://www.bigskyeda-edc.org/ Big Sky Economic Development]&lt;/ref&gt; Fortune 500 firms with branch operations in Billings include Exxon/Mobil, Wal-mart, GM, Conoco-Phillips, Ford, Wells Fargo, General Electric, [[USBank]], Travelers, BNSF, Pennsylvania Power &amp; Light, MDU Resources, Sears/K-Mart, [[Target Corporation]], New York Life, Morgan Stanley.&lt;ref name=&quot;bigskyeda-edc.org&quot;/&gt;

==Transportation==
[[File:UnitedShuttle737-corrected.jpg|thumb|United Shuttles at the Airport]]
'''&lt;big&gt;Airports&lt;/big&gt;'''

Because of Billings' unique geography,  [[Billings Logan International Airport]] is located just moments from the heart of downtown; it sits on top of (the Rims), a {{convert|500|ft|m|adj=on}} cliff overlooking the downtown core. Billings Logan International Airport is the largest and busiest airport within a four state region (Montana, Wyoming, North and South Dakota) both in passenger boardings and air cargo.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.faa.gov/airports Airport Programs &amp; Guidance]&lt;/ref&gt;

The [[Laurel Municipal Airport]] is a publicly owned public-use airport in [[Laurel, Montana]], which is located eleven miles (17&amp;nbsp;km) southwest of the central business district (CBD) of Billings, Montana. The airport has three runways exclusively serving privately operated general aviation aircraft and helicopters.&lt;ref&gt;http://maps.google.com/maps/place?hl=en&amp;client=safari&amp;rls=en&amp;psj=1&amp;um=1&amp;ie=UTF-8&amp;q=airports+yellowstone+county+montana&amp;fb=1&amp;gl=us&amp;hq=airports&amp;hnear=Yellowstone,+Montana&amp;cid=7817700564093957969&lt;/ref&gt;

'''&lt;big&gt;Public Transportation&lt;/big&gt;'''

The [[Billings METropolitan Transit]] is the public transit system in Billings. MET Transit provides fixed-route and paratransit bus service to the City of Billings. All MET buses are accessible by citizens who use wheelchairs and other mobility devices. They are wheelchair lift-equipped and accessible to all citizens that are unable to use the stairs. MET buses are equipped with bike racks for their bike riding passengers.&lt;ref&gt;[http://ci.billings.mt.us/index.aspx?nid=259 City of Billings, MT - Official Website - MET Transit]&lt;/ref&gt; There are also numerous Taxicab and Limousine services within the city.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.magicyellow.com/category/Taxicabs/Billings_MT.html Billings Taxicabs &amp;#124; Cabs in Billings, MT]&lt;/ref&gt; The Billings Bus Terminal is served by [[Greyhound Lines|Greyhound]] has well as Rimrock [[Trailways]] which also provides regional and interstate bus service.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.greyhound.com/ Greyhound.com &amp;#124; Home]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.rimrocktrailways.com/ Welcome to Rimrock Trailways - Rimrock Trailways]&lt;/ref&gt;

'''&lt;big&gt;Biking / Walking&lt;/big&gt;'''

Billings has an extensive system of Bike trails. The Heritage Trail System includes a network of non-motorized multi-use trails and biking facilities within the greater Billings area. The City has a variety of multi-use trails and open spaces available for Walking, jogging, biking, or inline skating. The rapidly expanding system is being developed and maintained by the Billings Parks and Recreation Department.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.prpl.info/parks/trails.html Billings Parks &amp; Rec - Trails]&lt;/ref&gt;

''[[Bicycling (magazine)|Bicycling]]'' magazine ranked Billings among the nation's 50 most bike friendly communities ranking above cities like Salt Lake City, St. Louis, Miami, and Baltimore.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.bicycling.com/news/featured-stories/bicyclings-top-50 Bicycling's Top 50 &amp;#124; Bicycling Magazine]&lt;/ref&gt;

'''&lt;big&gt;Roads&lt;/big&gt;'''

[[Interstate 90]] runs east/west through the southern portion of Billings, serving as a corridor between the Heights, Lockwood and Downtown, South Hills, Westend, Shiloh, and Laurel. East of Downtown, between the Heights and Lockwood, Interstate 90 connects with [[Interstate 94]] which serves as an east/west corridor between Shepherd, Huntley and Heights, Lockwood, Downtown, South Hills, Westend, Shiloh, Laurel via its connection with I-90.

[[U.S. Highway 87]] is a north/south highway that runs along the edge of the North Rims Connecting Downtown and the Westend with the Rehberg Ranch, Indian Cliffs and the Heights. It turns into Main Street in the Heights before connecting to [[U.S. Highway 87 East]] which runs through Lockwood as Old Hardin Road.&lt;ref name=&quot;google1&quot;&gt;http://maps.google.com/maps?client=safari&amp;rls=en&amp;q=billings+montana&amp;oe=UTF-8&amp;um=1&amp;ie=UTF-8&amp;hq=&amp;hnear=Billings,+Mt&amp;gl=us&amp;ei=fuEkTY62CcL7lweu3YTpAQ&amp;sa=X&amp;oi=geocode_result&amp;ct=title&amp;resnum=1&amp;ved=0CCUQ8gEwAA&lt;/ref&gt;

'''''Some major streets in the Billings valley include''''' Zoo Drive, Gabel Road, Overland Av, Neibauer Road, Hesper Road, King Avenue West, King Avenue East, Monad Road, Central Avenue, Broadwater Avenue, Grand Avenue, Poly Drive, Rimrock Road, 64th Street West, 62nd Street West, 58th Street West, 54th Street West, 48th Street West, Shiloh Road, Zimmerman Trail/32nd Street West, 24th Street West, 19th Street West/20th Street West, 16th Street West, 15th Street West, 8th Street West, 6th Street West, 5th Street West, Moore Lane, State Av, Laurel Road, Billings Blvd, Calhoun Lane, Southgate Drive, Midland Road, Mullowney Lane, South Frontage Road, Hollowell Lane, Jackson Street, Sugar Av and Garden Av.&lt;ref name=&quot;google1&quot;/&gt;

'''''Some major Streets in the South Hills include''''' Blue Creek Road, Hillcrest Road, and Briarwood Blvd.&lt;ref name=&quot;google1&quot;/&gt;

'''''Some of the major streets Downtown include''''' Division, 30th, 29th, Broadway, 27th, 26th, 25th, 24th, 13th, Exposition, 1st Av South, Minnesota Av, Montana Av, 1st Av North, 2nd Av North, 3rd Av North, 4th Av North, 6th Av North, 9th Av North, 12th Av North, Poly, and Rimrock.&lt;ref name=&quot;google1&quot;/&gt;

'''''Some of the major Streets in the Heights include''''' Airport Road, Alkali Creek Road, Aronson Av, Hilltop Road, Lake Elmo Road, Governors Blvd, Senators Blvd, Wicks Lane, Main Street, Bench Blvd, and Yellowstone River Road.&lt;ref name=&quot;google1&quot;/&gt;

==Medical facilities==
The [[Billings Metro Area]] has two Level II trauma hospitals, [[St. Vincent Healthcare]] and the [[Billings Clinic]] which is the largest cluster of medical facilities between Salt Lake, Denver, Boise, Lethbridge, Rapid City, and Fargo.  Employs over 5,000 directly.  Neurosurgery, highly rated cardiac surgery, neonatology and obstetrics, extensive cancer treatment, inpatient psychiatric care, orthopedics and rehab, dedicated air ambulances both fixed-wing planes and helicopters.

Other medical facilities include the [[Northern Rockies Radiation Oncology Center]], [[Rimrock Foundation]] (addiction treatment both inpatient and outpatient), Advanced Care Hospital of Montana (a 40-bed long term acute care hospital), South Central Montana Mental Health Center, Billings VA Community Based Outpatient Clinic, Billings Clinic Research Center (pharmaceutical field trials, osteoporosis are two long-time focuses), Billings MRI, City/County Public Health's Riverstone Health, HealthSouth Surgery Center and Physical Therapy offices, Baxter/Travenol BioLife plasma collection center, and many independent practices.

An increasing number of assisted living facilities and senior independent living options, a static number of nursing homes, and sizable home health care services target the rapidly growing aging population, already 1 in 8 Montanans are over 65 making it the 4th &quot;oldest&quot; state in the U.S. after Florida, Arizona, and Wyoming.

Billings campuses train physician assistants, biochemists, paramedics, registered nurses, speech pathologists, licensed practical nurses, surgical technicians, x-ray technicians, medical records clerks, athletic trainers, and health care business students at the undergraduate and graduate level as of 2007.

==Education==
===Public===
The city of Billings operates 22 elementary schools in district 2. The elementary schools are Alkali Creek, Arrowhead, Beartooth, Bench, Big Sky, Bitterroot, Boulder, Broadwater, Burlington, Central Heights, Eagle Cliffs, Highland, McKinley, Meadowlark, Miles Avenue, Newman, Orchard, Poly Drive, Ponderosa, Rose Park, Sandstone, and Washington. There is also a district 3 in Billings, which only contains the elementary school Blue Creek and a district 8, which contains Elder Grove School,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.eldergrove.k12.mt.us/ |title=Elder Grove School |author= |date= |work= |publisher= |accessdate=13 September 2010}}
&lt;/ref&gt; teaching grades K - 8. The four middle schools in Billings are Riverside Middle School, Lewis and Clark, Will James, and Castle Rock. There are three high schools as well, including Billings Senior High, West High, and Skyview.

===Private===
* The Billings Catholic Schools operates [[Billings Central Catholic High School]] (grades 9-12), St. Francis Upper (grades 6-8), St Francis Intermediate (grades 3-5), St Francis Primary, (K-2) and St Francis Daycare
* Trinity Lutheran Church operates Trinity Lutheran School, serving grades K-8
* Billings Christian Schools serving grades K-12
* Adelphi Christian Academy serving grades K-12 (Closed at the end of the 2009 School Year)&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://adelphichristian.org/ |title=? |author= |date= |work= |publisher= |accessdate=}}{{Dead link|date=September 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* Billings Educational Academy serving grades K-12
* Grace Montessori Academy serves Pre-6&lt;ref&gt;h{{cite web|url=gmamt.org |title=? |author= |date= |work= |publisher= |accessdate=}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Colleges and universities===
There are several institutions of higher learning in Billings. These include state schools (Montana State University Billings and the MSU Billings College of Technology) and private schools (Rocky Mountain College and Yellowstone Baptist College).

[[File:McMullen.JPG|thumb|McMullen Hall, [[Montana State University Billings]]]]

[[Montana State University Billings]] was originally named Eastern Montana Normal School when it was founded and then named Eastern Montana College before being renamed to its present name when the Montana State University System reorganized in 1994. The university was established in 1927  and offers Associate/Bachelor/Master degrees and certificates in various education fields. Currently around 5,000 students attend MSU Billings.

[[MSU Billings College of Technology]] (West campus) was originally a vocational-technical school associated with the Billings School District.  Now as a college of Montana State University Billings, the COT offers associate-level degrees, entry into the four year programs as well as community college programming. In the past few years, enrollment has risen to over 1,200 full time students (accounting for nearly 1/5 of the student body). Projections with grant improvements and workforce needs foresee a 2,000 student increase in the near future and the evolution into a comprehensive community college.  

Billings also offers two private schools. [[Rocky Mountain College]] is Montana's oldest and first institution of higher learning, founded in 1878. It is a private comprehensive college offering over 40 liberal arts and professionally oriented majors. Rocky Mountain College is often simply called &quot;Rocky&quot; or &quot;RMC&quot; for short. Rocky is proud of its standing record of being ranked by U.S. News &amp; World Report as one of the top 10 in quality and a “best value” among comprehensive colleges in the West. Along with its quality Rocky also continues to maintain a 99% graduate placement rate. [[Yellowstone Baptist College]] also offers a limited curriculum.

==Culture==
===Arts===
[[File:HK TST K11 mall 122 Deborah Butterfield - Captain.JPG|thumb|[[Deborah Butterfield]] Sculpture - Captain]]
* [[Alberta Bair Theater]]
* [[Babcock Theatre]]
* [[Billings Studio Theater]]
* [[Billings Symphony Orchestra]]
* [[Rimrock Opera Company]]
* [[Venture Theatre]]
* [[Yellowstone Art Museum]]
* [[Yellowstone Chamber Players]]
* [[Yellowstone County Museum]]
* [[Western Heritage Center]]

===Recreation/events===

[[File:US 212 looking west from Vista Point, Montana .jpg|thumb|The [[Beartooth Highway]] heading into the [[Beartooth Mountains]] ]][[File:Red Lodge Palisades.jpg|thumb|The Palisades area on the north end of the ski area at [[Red Lodge Mountain Resort]]]][[File:Pictograms-nps-land-skateboarding.svg|The Downtown Billings skateboard park is open all year round]][[File:Discs in basket.jpg|thumb|[[disc golf]] Basket. Billings has some of the best disc golf courses around]]&lt;ref&gt;http://www.airfairways.com/&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;http://www.billingsbulletin.com/diamondX.asp&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;http://www.nrdga.com/index.php?module=pagemaster&amp;PAGE_user_op=view_page&amp;PAGE_id=2&amp;MMN_position=2:2&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;http://www.motodom.com/BrentBell.htm&lt;/ref&gt;

Activities in and around Billings include [[hiking]], [[rock climbing]], [[mountain climbing]], [[fishing]], [[skiing]], [[boating]], [[disc golf]], [[skateboarding]], the Downtown Skateboard Park, [[motorcycle trials]], [[golf]], [[mountain biking]], [[rappelling]], extensive walking and bike trails, art walks, concerts, food fairs and [[rodeos]]. Some annual events include:
* [[Wine]] &amp; [[Food]] Festival at MSU Billings: May
* [[Strawberry]] Festival under [[Skypoint]]: June
* SummerFair at North Park: July
* 4 July Parade in [[Laurel, Montana]]: July
* Gay Pride Weekend
* Alive After 5 concerts: Thursdays June - September
* Battle of the Little Big Horn Re-enactment near [[Crow Agency, Montana]]: June
* Farmers Market under Skypoint: Every Saturday June to October
* Big Sky State Games - July
* Great American Championship Motorcycle Hill Climb
* Skyfest ([[Hot air balloons]]): July/August
* MontanaFair at the MetraPark fairgrounds: August 13–21&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.montanafair.com |title=MontanaFair in Billings |author= |date= |work= |publisher= |accessdate=13 September 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* Magic City Blues Festival: August in [[Downtown Billings]]
* [[Crow Fair]] &amp; Rodeo in [[Crow Agency, Montana]]: August
* Burn the Point (classic car show): September in Downtown Billings
* Harvest Fest: October
* Christmas Parade in Downtown Billings: November 24
* Festival of Trees: December
* The Christmas Stroll in Downtown Billings: December
* Billings Artwalk

===Media===
{{Main|Billings, Montana Media}}

Bilings is the largest media Market in Montana and Wyoming. Billings is serviced by a variety of print media. Newspaper service includes [[The Billings Gazette]]&lt;ref&gt;ttp://billingsgazette.com/&lt;/ref&gt; which is a daily morning broadsheet newspaper printed in Billings, Montana and owned by [[Lee Enterprises]]. It is the largest daily newspaper in Montana, with a Sunday circulation of 52,434 and a weekday circulation of 47,105. The paper publishes in three editions: the state edition, which circulates in most of Eastern Montana and all of South Central Montana; the Wyoming edition, which circulates in Northern Wyoming; and the city edition, which circulates in Yellowstone County. Other publications include the Billings Outpost,&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.billingsnews.com/ The Billings Outpost Frontpage]&lt;/ref&gt; a weekly publication, and the alternative publication The Grindstone,&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.facebook.com/Grindstonemagazine Grindstone Magazine &amp;#124; Facebook]&lt;/ref&gt; which is published monthly. As well as other more specialized weekly and monthly publications, Billings also has several community magazines amongst them are Magic City Magazine&lt;ref&gt;[http://magiccitymagazine.com/ Magic - Billings' City Magazine Since 2003]&lt;/ref&gt; and Yellowstone Valley Woman.&lt;ref&gt;[http://yellowstonevalleywoman.com/ Yellowstone Valley Woman]&lt;/ref&gt;

The Billings area is served by four major non-news television stations, two major news television stations, one community television station, four [[Public Broadcasting Service|PBS]] chanels&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.superpages.com/yellowpages/C-Television+Broadcasting+Companies+%26+Stations/S-MT/T-Billings/ Billings Television Broadcasting Companies &amp; Stations in Billings MT Yellow Pages by SuperPages]&lt;/ref&gt; and several Low Power Television ([[LPTV]]) channels. The Billings area is also served by twenty-two commercial radio stations and Yellowstone Public Radio ([[NPR]]).&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.ontheradio.net/metro/billings_mt.aspx Radio Stations in Billings MT]&lt;/ref&gt;

===Attractions===
[[File:Old Faithful Rainbow.jpg|thumb|Old Faithful, Yellowstone National Park]]

Attractions located within Billings include the [[Yellowstone Art Museum]], [[Moss Mansion]] Historic House Museum, the [[Western Heritage Center]], the [[Billings Depot]], and [[Skypoint]].
* The Moss Mansion Historic House Museum is located in Billings on 914 Division St. It is a turn of the century, red-stoned mansion built in 1903 by P.B. Moss, who moved to Billings from [[Paris, Missouri]]. It was inhabited solely by Mr. and Mrs. Moss, their six children, and three servants.&lt;ref name=&quot;mossmansion.com&quot; /&gt; The house was built for a cost of $105,000, when most homes averaged about $3,000. It has 28 rooms, and is {{convert|60|ft|m}} square. It rises {{convert|45|ft|m}} into the air. The Mansion is listed on the [[National Register of Historic Places]]. Visitors can still see the original furniture, draperies, carpets and fixtures during a one-hour guided tour. Seasonal exhibits are also featured. The Moss Mansion was designed by the famous [[New York]] [[Architect]] [[Henry Hardenbergh]], who also designed the original [[Waldorf-Astoria]], [[Plaza Hotel]], [[Willard Hotel]], and [[Copley Hotel]]. The Moss Mansion is operated by the Billings Preservation Society, Inc., a non-profit organization.&lt;ref name=&quot;mossmansion.com&quot;/&gt;
[[File:Yellowstone - Lower Falls.JPG|thumb|Yellowstone Park - Lower Falls]]

* '''Western Heritage Center:''' Downtown attractions include the Western Heritage Center Museum which is located in the historic Parmly Billings Library building on Montana Avenue in the downtown Historic District.  The Parmly Billings library, a [[Richardsonian Romanesque]] sandstone building built in 1901, is listed on the National Register of Historic Places.  This regional museum interprets a unique collection of artifacts and oral histories that document the history of the [[Yellowstone River]] Valley and the Northern High Plains.  The Western Heritage Center is an affiliate museum of the [[Smithsonian Institution]].  The Western Heritage Center is one of six museums in the state of Montana accredited by the American Association of Museums.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.ywhc.org/ Western Heritage Center - Home]&lt;/ref&gt;

* '''Downtown Historic District:''' In 1977, the Billings City Council created the Billings Historical District: Montana Avenue from North 26th Street to North 22nd and north to First Avenue North. In 1978, the Historic District has was entered into the National Register of Historic Places. The Northern Pacific Billings Depot or simply the [[Billings Depot]] is a cornerstone of the Historic District. The arrival of the railroad in 1882 signaled the real beginning of Billings. Designed in the [[Beaux-Arts architecture|Beaux Arts]] Eclectic style, the four original buildings included the Depot building, railroad lunchroom, mail building and an office building. The Depot featured a spacious waiting area for 200 passengers, a gentlemen's smoking room, a ladies' waiting room, a baggage area and service offices. Today, the Depot is used as an events center hosting a wide variety of events.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.billingsdepot.org/history-of-the-depot/ History of the Depot &amp;#124; Billings Depot]&lt;/ref&gt;
[[File:Little Bighorn August 2007.JPG|thumb|Little Bighorn Battlefield]]

* '''Boothill Cemetery:''' is a burial ground for Coulson Montana, a rough cow town that presided Billings. Coulson stood on the banks of the Yellowstone river about two miles (3&amp;nbsp;km) from present day downtown Billings. Most of the people buried here were said to have died with their boots on. The cemetery was started when one gent in a Coulson saloon called another a liar. Nearly all of those interred at Boothill met with violent deaths. The most famous person to be buried here is Muggins Taylor, the scout who carried the news of Custer's Last Stand to the world. The last burial at Boothill was in 1882. Today, Boothill is at the base of Swords Park and just off of Main Street in Billings Heights, the busiest street in Montana.&lt;ref name=&quot;billingsguide.com&quot;&gt;[http://www.billingsguide.com/Visguide13.html Billings Historic Site Tour]&lt;/ref&gt;
[[File:Popi ownpillar.jpg|200px|thumb|right|Pompeys Pillar National Monument]][[File:Pictograph Cave, Billings, Montana.jpg|thumb|Pictograph Cave, Billings, Montana]]

* '''Black Otter Trail''' is a scenic drive just off of Airport Road, U.S. 318. The road passes Boothill Cemetery, climbs Kelly Hill and winds through Swords Park a large city park in the center of the City. The park is on the edge of the [[Rimrocks]], {{convert|500|ft|m|adj=on}} cliffs that divide the downtown area from Billings Heights. Black Otter Trail is named after a Crow chief who was killed here by a Sioux war party. He was given a treetop burial on a site overlooking the Yellowstone River.&lt;ref name=&quot;billingsguide.com&quot;/&gt;

* '''Yellowstone Kelly’s Grave''' is a monument to Yellowstone Kelly, who lived from 1849 to 1928. Kelly was the epitome of a frontiersman, army scout, dispatch rider, and hunter. At his own request, he was buried on Kelly Hill which is near the edge of the [[Rimrocks]] in Swords Park overlooking the Yellowstone River and now downtown Billings.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.moon.com/destinations/montana/billings/billings/the-rimrocks/yellowstone-kelly-s-grave Yellowstone Kelly’s Grave &amp;#124; MOON TRAVEL GUIDES]&lt;/ref&gt; Six mountain ranges can be viewed from here the [[Bighorn Mountains]], the [[Pryor Mountains]], the [[Beartooth Mountains]], the [[Crazy Mountains]], the [[Big Snowy Mountains]] and the [[Bull Mountains]].

* '''Skypoint''' is a tent-like structure over the intersection 2nd Avenue and Broadway, located in downtown Billings. Its highest point is {{convert|73|ft|m}} tall. There are three &quot;sails&quot; that make up the structure. The largest sail can move to let the sun through or to cover the intersection if it rains. This is part of the plan to revitalize downtown Billings and attract more people to downtown. Skypoint was completed in 2002 and was originally named the &quot;Defining Element&quot; until it got its current name in a naming contest. It was built as a new icon for the city of Billings and to hold events such as the [[Strawberry]] Festival, the Christmas Stroll, and other events.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.dcmemorials.com/index_indiv0006656.htm Skypoint in Billings, Montana]&lt;/ref&gt;

* '''ZooMontana:''' [[ZooMontana]] is a {{convert|70|acre|m2|adj=on}} wildlife park and botanical park located in Billings and is [[Montana]]'s only zoo. The zoo was first planned in the early 1980s. It is home to both native and non-native animals from around the world. The zoo is one of the regions most popular tourist attractions. The zoo hosts animals not only native to the Rockies but also species from Asia and Europe. Among the animals featured is a Siberian Tiger, Eastern Gray Wolves, North American River Otters, Bighorn Sheep, Red Pandas, Great Horned Owls, Bald Eagles, Sika Deer, Wyoming Toads, Wolverines, Waterfowls, Pygmy Marmosets, Green Iguanas, Grizzly Bears, Farm Animals, Tree Boas, Black Footed Ferrets, Minks and Lesser Spot-Nosed Guenon. The animals live in state-of-the-art enclosures designed to imitate their natural habitats.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.zoomontana.org/ ZooMontana]&lt;/ref&gt;
[[File:Granite Peak Montana.jpg|thumb|Granite Peak in the Beartooth Mountains, the highest point in Montana]]

* '''The Pictograph Cave National Historic Landmark''' is a {{convert|93|acre|m2|adj=on}} area of three [[caves]] (Pictograph, Middle, and Ghost caves) located {{convert|6|mi|km}} south of Billings. There are over 30,000 artifacts which have been identified. Paintings known as [[pictograph]]s are still visible in Pictograph Cave, which is the largest of the three caves. Some of the pictographs are 2,000 years old. They are paintings of animals, warriors, and even rifles that document the story of the Native Americans of the area for thousands of years.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.visitmt.com/history/Montana_the_Magazine_of_Western_History/caves.htm Pictograph Cave State Park]&lt;/ref&gt;

* '''Attractions near Billings''' include
** [[Yellowstone National Park]] is a national park located southwest of Billings, in Montana, Wyoming and Idaho. Yellowstone was the first national park in the world, and is known for its wildlife and its many geothermal features, such as [[Old Faithful Geyser]], one of the most popular features in the park.
** [[Bighorn Canyon National Recreation Area]] is just southeast of Billings. Bighorn Lake extends 71&amp;nbsp;miles (114&amp;nbsp;km) through Wyoming and Montana, 55&amp;nbsp;miles (89&amp;nbsp;km) of which are held within spectacular Bighorn Canyon.
** [[Pompey's Pillar National Monument]] is a rock formation located just west of the city that is a [[National Monument]]. The pillar features an abundance of Native American [[pictographs]], as well as the signature of [[William Clark]], co-leader of the [[Lewis and Clark Expedition]]. Clark's inscription is the only remaining physical evidence of the expedition. The inscription consists of his signature and the date, July 25, 1806.
** [[Chief Plenty Coups (Alek-Chea-Ahoosh) State Park and Home|Chief Plenty Coups State Park]] Chief Plenty Coups, the last traditional tribal Chief of the Apsáalooke people and his wife, Strikes the Iron, left their home and property to &quot;all people&quot; in 1928. The only museum of Apsáalooke culture in the United States is located there as well as a memorial to Plenty Coups and his achievements.
** [[Beartooth Mountains]] are part of the 900,000&amp;nbsp;acre (3,600&amp;nbsp;km²) [[Absaroka-Beartooth Wilderness]], within Custer, Gallatin National Forest and Shoshone National Forests. The Beartooths are the location of [[Granite Peak]], which at 12,799&amp;nbsp;feet (3,901&amp;nbsp;m) is the highest point in the state of Montana.
** [[Beartooth Highway]] is the highway that takes you into the Beartooth Mountains and to Yellowstone National Park. It has been called &quot;the most beautiful drive in America,&quot; by late [[CBS]] correspondent [[Charles Kuralt]], and are just southwest of Billings.
** [[Little Bighorn Battlefield National Monument]] The site of the [[Battle of the Little Bighorn]] is located southeast of Billings. Little Bighorn Battlefield National Monument preserves the site of the June 26, 1876 [[Battle of the Little Bighorn]]. It also serves as a memorial to those who fought in the battle: [[George Armstrong Custer]]'s [[U.S. 7th Cavalry Regiment|7th Cavalry]] and a combined [[Lakota people|Lakota]]-[[Northern Cheyenne]] force. Custer National Cemetery, on the battlefield, is part of the [[U.S. National Monument|national monument]]. The site of a related military action led by [[Marcus Reno]] and [[Frederick Benteen]] is also part of the national monument, but is about 3&amp;nbsp;miles (5&amp;nbsp;km) southeast of the Little Bighorn battlefield.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.nps.gov/libi/index.htm Little Bighorn Battlefield National Monument (U.S. National Park Service)]&lt;/ref&gt;
** [[Red Lodge Mountain Resort]] is an alpine ski area located just southwest of Billings near the town of [[Red Lodge, Montana]] in the [[Billings Metropolitan Area]] and sets along the eastern front of the Beartooth Mountains.

===Sports===
* [[Billings Bulls]] an [[American West Hockey League]] Jr. A Tier III hockey team.
* [[Billings Mustangs]], a [[Pioneer Baseball League|Pioneer League]] Baseball Team affiliated with the [[Cincinnati Reds]]
* The NILE (Northern International Livestock Exposition) Rodeo at [[MetraPark Arena]].
* Great American Championship Motorcycle Hill Climb - ''billed as The Oldest, Richest and Biggest Motorcycle Hill Climb in the United States''

===Venues===
====Rimrock Auto Arena at MetraPark====
[[Rimrock Auto Arena at MetraPark|Rimrock Auto Arena]] is a 12,000-seat multi-purpose [[arena]] in Billings. MetraPark Arena was completed in 1975. The original name of the area was the METRA, an Acronym standing for Montana Trade and Recreation Arena. The naming rights were sold to Billings-based Rimrock Auto Group in 2007 and the arena now goes by the name Rimrock Auto Arena at MetraPark.&lt;ref&gt;http://billingsgazette.com/news/local/article_8e0c7b98-7dc5-5d29-88cb-53b65b3b3625.html&lt;/ref&gt;  It is owned by the City of Billings and Yellowstone County. In 2005, MetraPark arena marked its 30th anniversary. The Arena is host to Montana's largest concerts, family shows, rodeos, ice shows, motor sports events, and more.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.metrapark.com/site/facilities/ MetraPark Facilities &amp;#124; Arena, Expo Center, Montana Pavilion, The Grandstands]&lt;/ref&gt; The Metrapark has hosted Pre-Season [[National Basketball Association|NBA]] games on a semi-regular basis. On June 20, 2010, the Rimrock Auto Arena was heavily damaged by a tornado, dubbed by the local media as the [[Fathers Day Tornado]].&lt;ref name=&quot;cbsnews1&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;kulr1&quot;/&gt; According to Metra officials, &quot;the tornado also lifted most of the roof off the arena and collapsed walls.&quot; The arena is currently being redesigned and rebuilt. When completed in 2011 it will have many new amenities such as improved acoustics, improved seating, more restrooms and concession areas, and easier access from the parking areas. The new arena will be an energy efficient building with contemporary aesthetics. On April 10, 2011, with the outer arena still under construction [[Elton John]] played the first concert in the new Rimrock Auto Arena since the Tornado.&lt;ref&gt;[http://billingsgazette.com/news/local/article_7cb6947f-bd6f-52f2-a0bd-d25bd166b79b.html MetraPark construction still aims for April finish]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://billingsgazette.com/news/local/government-and-politics/article_9ccc214c-cd11-11df-9b7b-001cc4c03286.html Architects update proposal for arena]&lt;/ref&gt;

====Alberta Bair Theater====
It was originally called The Fox Theater when it opened its doors on November 13, 1931. Today, the Alberta Bair Theater is the largest fully equipped performing arts center in the region. The 1,400-seat venue showcases professional touring companies, featuring musician, dance, and theater performances, as well as local performing groups. The Alberta Bair Theater provides outstanding educational programming for 25,000 school children annually and serves a population of 400,000. A 20-ton capacity hydraulic lift raises and lowers the stage apron for performances, allows equipment and furniture to be moved on and off stage easily and provides direct access to the dressing rooms.

====Shrine Auditorium====
The Auditorium was built in 1950, a year after the city and county opted not to erect a civic center, the Shrine thrived as a concert venue in the 1950s, 1960s and 1970s with an impressive list of performers filing through. These days, the Shrine host national shows that might not be able to play Billings if it were not for this smaller cost affective venue. The Shrine seats 2340 for concerts with off street parking for 550 cars.

====Dehler Park====
 
[[File:Cobbfield.jpg|thumb|Cobb Field]]

[[Dehler Park]] is the new multi-use stadium that replaced Cobb Field in the summer of 2008. [[Cobb Field]] was a [[baseball]] [[stadium]], it was the home of the [[Billings Mustangs]], the [[Pioneer Baseball League|Pioneer League]] Rookie Affiliate of the [[Cincinnati Reds]], since 1948. Cobb Field was named after Bob Cobb, who was responsible for bringing professional baseball with the [[Billings Mustangs|Mustangs]] to Billings. Cobb Field also hosted home games for local [[American Legion|American Legion baseball]] teams. In 2006, Billings voters approved $12 million to be spent on constructing a new multi-use sports facility. Cobb Field was demolished in 2007 and construction of Dehler Park began at the end of the 2007 baseball season. The new park debuted on June 29, 2008, when the Billings Scarlets faced the Bozeman Bucks in American Legion regular season play. The new Dehler Park has a crowd capacity of 3,500 to over 6,000.

====Wendy's Field====
[[Wendy's Field at Daylis Stadium]] is a local area stadium used for high school games. It is located adjacent to Billings Senior High.

====Centennial Ice Arena====
[[Centennial Ice Arena]] is home to the Billings Amateur Hockey League, Figure Skating Clubs, Adult Hockey &amp; the Junior A [[Billings Bulls]].

====Babcock Theater====
[[Babcock Theater]] is a 750-seat performing arts theater in Billings, Montana. It was built in 1907 and at the time was considered the largest theater between Minneapolis and Seattle. Today, after extensive renovations, it hosts a variety of national acts.

====Alterowitz Arena and Physical Education Building MSU-Billings====
The arena is a 4,000-seat venue primarily hosting Yellowjacket sports, local events and occasionally national touring events. This facility contains gyms and racket ball courts as well as an Olympic size pool with bleachers for aquatic events.

====The Grandstand at MetraPark====
The Grandstand is a canopied outdoor venue that seats 6,500 for concerts, rodeos, horse racing, auto events, and field and track.

====The Expo Center====
The Expo Center is a {{convert|77400|sqft|m2|adj=on}} multi-purpose arena on the MetraPark grounds.

====The Montana Pavilion====
The Montana Pavilion is a {{convert|28800|sqft|m2|adj=on}} multi-purpose arena on the MetraPark grounds.

====Northern Pacific Billings Depot====
The [[Billings Depot]] is the historic former train depot. It is now an events center that hosts a wide variety of events.

====Fortin Center====
Fortin Center is a 3,000-seat arena on the campus of [[Rocky Mountain College]] it is primarily  used for the Rocky Mountain sports events.

==Notable natives and residents==
More widely famous people who have lived in Billings include:

===Historical===
[[File:LindberghStLouis.jpg|thumb|Charles Lindbergh]]
* [[Calamity Jane]], frontierswoman
* [[Charles Lindbergh]], aviator
* [[Terry C. Johnston]], western novelist

===Sports===
* [[Gary Albright]], wrestler
* [[Jeff Ballard (baseball pitcher)|Jeff Ballard]], [[Major League Baseball]] pitcher
* [[Ed Breding]], former NFL player
* [[Kurt Burris]], former NFL player
* [[Mike Burton (swimming)|Mike Burton]], Olympic gold medalist in swimming
* [[Ruben Castillo (boxer)|Ruben Castillo]], boxer
* [[Jim Creighton (basketball)|Jim Creighton]], former NBA player
* [[Mitch Donahue]], former NFL player
* [[Dwan Edwards]], [[Buffalo Bills]] player
* [[Brad Holland]], former [[National Basketball Association|NBA]] player
* [[Dave McNally]], Major League Baseball pitcher
* [[Roy McPipe]], former [[American Basketball Association (1967-1976)|ABA]] player
* [[Andy Moog]], NHL player
* [[Brent Musburger]], sportscaster
* [[Steve Oliver]], former NFL player
* [[Kirk Scrafford]], former NFL player
* [[Greg Smith (ice hockey)|Greg Smith]], [[National Hockey League|NHL]] player
* [[Leslie Spalding]], [[LPGA]] golfer
* [[Keith Wortman]], former [[National Football League|NFL]] player

===Arts and entertainment===
[[File:Arlo Guthrie 2007.jpg|thumb|Arlo Guthrie 2007]]
* [[Arlo Guthrie]], folk singer
* [[Phil Amato]], television host
* [[Stanley Anderson]], actor
* [[Katie Blair]], Miss Teen USA 2006
* [[John Dahl]], movie director
* [[Annie Duke]], professional [[poker]] player and author
* [[Bob Enevoldsen]], [[jazz]] [[multi-instrumentalist]]
* [[Joshua Frank]], author, journalist
* [[Brad Fregger]], author, publisher, and video game producer
* [[Ethel Hays]], [[cartoonist]] and [[illustrator]]
* [[Will James (artist)|Will James]], western artist
* [[Wesley Kimler]], [[artist]]
* [[Amanda Kimmel]], former [[Miss Montana USA]] and ''[[Survivor: China]]'' and ''[[Survivor: Micronesia]]'' runner up and ''[[Survivor: Heroes vs. Villains]]'' contestant
* [[Jeff Kober]], actor
* [[Wally Kurth]], actor
* [[Bud Luckey]], famed [[PIXAR]] [[animator]] and [[Academy Award|Oscar]] nominee
* [[T. J. Lynch]], screenwriter
* [[Helen Lynch]], actress
* [[Stan Lynde]], creator of the [[comic strip]] ''[[Rick O'Shay]]'', painter, and novelist
* [[Marlene Morrow]], former ''[[Playboy]]'' [[Playboy Playmate|Playmate]] of the Month
* [[J. K. Ralston]], longtime resident, western painter
* [[Chan Romero]], pioneer of [[rock and roll]] was born in Billings
* [[Rick Rydell]], [[talk radio]] host
* [[Auggie Smith]], comedian
* [[David Yost]], actor and producer, most notably the Blue Power Ranger on the ''Mighty Morphin Power Rangers''.

===Political===
* [[James Franklin Battin]], former Congressman from Montana
* [[Jim Battin]], a [[California State Senator]]
* [[John Bohlinger]], current [[Lieutenant Governor of Montana]]
* [[Roy Brown (Montana politician)|Roy Brown]], former Montana State Senator for District 25 and former gubernatorial candidate.
* [[Conrad Burns]], who served in the United States Senate from 1988 to 2007.
* [[Ray Metcalfe]], member of the [[Alaska House of Representatives]]
* [[Henry L. Myers]], [[United States Senator]] and justice of the [[Supreme Court of Montana]]
* [[Denny Rehberg]], Congressman from Montana and former Lieutenant Governor of Montana
* [[Tom Stout]], former Congressman from Montana and editorial writer for the ''Billings Gazette''
* [[Burt L. Talcott]], former Congressman from California

==Sister cities==
* {{Flagicon|Germany}} [[Billings, Hessen|Billings]], [[Germany]]
* {{Flagicon|Russia}} [[Kemerovo]], [[Russia]]
* {{Flagicon|Japan}} [[Kumamoto]], [[Japan]]
* {{Flagicon|Turkey}} [[Diyarbakir]], [[Turkey]]
* {{Flagicon|China}} [[Panjin]], [[China]]

==Miscellaneous==
* Billings was named ''[[Magic City|The Magic City]]'' because of the city's seemingly overnight appearance.
* Billings is also known as ''The City by the [[Rimrocks|Rims]]'' because of the sandstone cliff that rises in the North Elevation section of Billings; ''[[Montana's Trailhead]]'' is Billings' [[brand]]ing and ''Star of the Big Sky Country'' is Billings' [[Motto]]
* Billings is often referred to on social networking sites as B-Town or Billville.
* Billings was the first stop on the 11th leg of ''[[The Amazing Race 8]]''
* Although the city was named after him, [[Frederick Billings]], the railroad baron, never actually stayed there overnight.

==References==
{{Reflist|2}}

s

==External links==
{{Commons category|Billings, Montana}}
* [http://www.cityofbillings.net/ City of Billings Official Website]
* [http://www.billingschamber.com Billings Chamber of Commerce]
* [http://www.billingscvb.visitmt.com Billings, Montana Convention and Visitors Bureau]
* [http://www.billingsschools.org/ Billings Public Schools website]
* [http://www.usacitiesonline.com/mtcountybillings.htm#statistics Billings Statistics]
* [http://www.bigskyeda-edc.org/  Big Sky EDA-EDC]

{{Geographic location
|Center    = Billings (central city)
|North     = [[Roundup, Montana]]
|Northeast = [[Shepherd, Montana]]
|East      = [[Lockwood, Montana]]
|Southeast = [[Crow Agency, Montana]]
|South     = [[Pryor, Montana]]
|Southwest = [[Laurel, Montana]]
|West      = [[Bozeman, Montana]]
|Northwest = [[Helena, Montana]]
|image     =
}}

{{Billings, Montana}}
{{Yellowstone County, Montana}}
{{Montana}}
{{Montana Regions and Towns with Breweries}}

[[Category:Cities in Montana]]
[[Category:Populated places in Yellowstone County, Montana]]
[[Category:Billings Metropolitan Area]]
[[Category:County seats in Montana]]
[[Category:Populated places established in 1877]]
[[Category:Billings, Montana| ]]

[[ar:بيلينغز، مونتانا]]
[[an:Billings (Montana)]]
[[ast:Billings]]
[[zh-min-nan:Billings, Montana]]
[[bg:Билингс (Монтана)]]
[[ca:Billings]]
[[cs:Billings]]
[[da:Billings (Montana)]]
[[de:Billings (Montana)]]
[[es:Billings (Montana)]]
[[eo:Billings (Montano)]]
[[eu:Billings (Montana)]]
[[fa:بیلینگز]]
[[fr:Billings (Montana)]]
[[gl:Billings, Montana]]
[[ko:빌링스 (몬태나 주)]]
[[id:Billings, Montana]]
[[ia:Billings, Montana]]
[[is:Billings]]
[[it:Billings (Montana)]]
[[he:בילינגס]]
[[ht:Billings, Montana]]
[[mrj:Биллингс (Монтана)]]
[[la:Billings]]
[[lmo:Billings, Montana]]
[[mr:बिलिंग्स, मोंटाना]]
[[nl:Billings (Montana)]]
[[ja:ビリングス (モンタナ州)]]
[[no:Billings]]
[[pl:Billings (Montana)]]
[[pt:Billings (Montana)]]
[[ro:Billings, Montana]]
[[ru:Биллингс (Монтана)]]
[[sah:Биллингс]]
[[simple:Billings, Montana]]
[[sk:Billings (Montana)]]
[[sr:Билингс]]
[[fi:Billings]]
[[sv:Billings]]
[[tl:Billings, Montana]]
[[vi:Billings, Montana]]
[[vo:Billings (Montana)]]
[[war:Billings, Montana]]
[[zh:比靈斯]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
