<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="1240607" ns="0" title="Egg Bowl"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{| class=&quot;infobox&quot; style=&quot;width: 28em; font-size: 95%;&quot;
|-
| colspan=&quot;2&quot; style=&quot;text-align: center; font-size: 150%;&quot; | '''Battle for the Golden Egg''' 
|-
|-
| style=&quot;width:50%; vertical-align:middle; text-align:center;&quot; | [[File:Mississippi State Football 2.png|125px|]]
| style=&quot;width:50%; vertical-align:middle; text-align:center;&quot; | [[File:Mississippi Football.png|125px]]
|-
{{#if: {{{image location&lt;includeonly&gt;|&lt;/includeonly&gt;}}} |
{{!}} style=&quot;text-align: center;&quot; colspan=&quot;2&quot; {{!}}  }}
|-
| '''Teams'''
| [[Mississippi State Bulldogs football|Mississippi State Bulldogs]]&lt;/br&gt;[[Ole Miss Rebels football|Ole Miss Rebels]]
|-
| '''Originated'''
| 1901
|-
| style=&quot;vertical-align: top;&quot; | '''{{nowrap|Total meetings}}''' || 108
|-
| '''Series'''
| Ole Miss leads 60–42–6 	
|-	
| '''Largest Victory'''	
| Mississippi State 65&lt;/br&gt; Ole Miss 0 &lt;br /&gt;November 6, 1915	
|-	
| '''Longest Win Streak'''	
| Mississippi State, 13, 1911–1925 
|-
| '''Highest Scoring Game'''
| Ole Miss 45&lt;/br&gt; Mississippi State 30&lt;br /&gt;November 23, 2000
|-
| '''Most Recent Game'''
| Mississippi State 31&lt;/br&gt; Ole Miss 3&lt;br /&gt;November 26, 2011
|-
|'''Current Streak'''
| Miss. State 3 (2009-2011)
| colspan=&quot;2&quot; align=&quot;center&quot;| &lt;hr&gt;
|-
|}

The '''Battle for the Golden Egg''', also known as the '''Egg Bowl''', is an American [[college football]] [[college rivalry|rivalry]] game between played annually by the [[Mississippi State Bulldogs football]] team of [[Mississippi State University|Mississippi State University]] and the [[Ole Miss Rebels football]] team of the [[University of Mississippi]] (Ole Miss).  The rivalry is the tenth longest uninterrupted series in the United States. The two teams have played each other since 1901, now having played each other a total of 108 times. 1927 was the first year the trophy was awarded to the winner.  The &quot;Battle for the Golden Egg&quot; has never been an official name for the game.  Additionally, the &quot;Egg&quot; part refers to more modern footballers referring to the 1927 football shaped in the old way, which resembles an egg compared to the modern design.  Thus, &quot;Egg&quot; was obviously never considered at the time of the trophy's conception as it was the norm of the day. While the game is called a &quot;bowl,&quot; it is not in fact a postseason bowl game, but rather a regular season game between two SEC West teams.

==Series history==
Up until 1926, Ole Miss had won only five times out of twenty-three. When Ole Miss beat what was then known as Mississippi A&amp;M College 7-6, the Ole Miss fans rushed the field, some trying to tear the goalposts down. A&amp;M fans did not take well to the Ole Miss fans destroying their property and fights broke out. Some A&amp;M fans defended the goal posts with wooden chairs, and several injuries were reported. To prevent such events in the future, students of the two schools created the &quot;Golden Egg&quot;, a large trophy which has been awarded to the winning team each year since 1927. The trophy is a large football-shaped brass piece mounted to a wooden base and traditionally symbolizes supremacy in college football in the state of [[Mississippi]] for the year. The footballs used in [[American football]] in the 1920s were considerably more ovoid and blunter than those in use today and similar to the balls still used in [[Rugby football|rugby]]; the trophy thus, to modern eyes, more resembles an [[egg (food)|egg]] than a football. The awarding of the &quot;Golden Egg&quot; was instituted in 1927 by joint agreement between the two schools' student bodies. In the event of a tie, the school that won the game the previous year keeps the trophy for the first half of the new year and then the trophy is sent to the other school for the second half of the new year.&lt;ref name=&quot;Ole Miss ootball 2007 Media guide&quot;&gt;[http://www.olemisssports.com/ViewArticle.dbml?DB_OEM_ID=2600&amp;ATCLID=1208400&amp;SPID=737&amp;SPSID=82783 Ole Miss football 2007 Media guide]&lt;/ref&gt;

The game is a typical example of the intrastate rivalries between several public universities in the [[United States|U.S.]] These games are usually between one bearing the state's name alone, and the [[land-grant university]], often styled as &quot;State University.&quot; Like most such rivalries, it is contested at the end of the regular season, in this case on [[Thanksgiving (United States)|Thanksgiving]] weekend, sometimes on Thanksgiving Day (or, in recent years, Thanksgiving Night) itself. At one point the level of rivalry was such that a victory by one of the schools in this game could salvage what had otherwise been a poor season. This was however proven ''not'' to always be the case when in 2004 Ole Miss won the game but fired its [[coach (sports)|coach]], [[David Cutcliffe]], the next week, following a disappointing season.

For many years this game was played at [[Mississippi Veterans Memorial Stadium]] in [[Jackson, Mississippi|Jackson]], which seats approximately 62,000. Besides being centrally located in the state, at the time it was the only venue in the state capable of seating the anticipated crowd; for many years [[Vaught-Hemingway Stadium]] in [[Oxford, Mississippi|Oxford]], seated only about 32,000 and [[Davis Wade Stadium|Scott Field]] in [[Starkville, Mississippi|Starkville]], seated only about 31,000. Both have been considerably expanded and are now capable of accommodating the crowds which can realistically be expected, and both on-campus venues have been continually upgraded to the point where they are actually superior in amenities to Mississippi Veterans Memorial Stadium. Since the Egg Bowl was moved back to the campuses, Mississippi State has won 12 games to Ole Miss' 9.

==Notable games==
[[Image:1929 Ole Miss vs MSU egg bowl program.JPG|right|thumb|200px|1929 Mississippi vs. Mississippi A&amp;M football program. The game ended tied 7-7. Note on the cover the game was referred to as &quot;Mississippi's Football Classic&quot; and not the &quot;Egg Bowl&quot;.]]
*'''1907:''' Ole Miss and Mississippi A&amp;M played a scoreless first half in extremely muddy conditions.&lt;ref name=&quot;Egg Bowl&quot; /&gt; Before the second half began, Ole Miss head coach [[Frank A. Mason]] brought out an urn filled with whisky-laced coffee in an attempt to warm his players.&lt;ref name=&quot;Egg Bowl&quot;&gt;{{cite book|title=The Egg Bowl: Mississippi State Vs. Ole Miss|year=2010|publisher=Univ. Press of Mississippi|location=Oxford, MS|isbn=1604738324, 9781604738322|pages=26–27|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=54L0Bv-uNVgC&amp;pg=PA26&amp;dq|coauthors=William G. Barner &amp; Danny McKenzie|accessdate=16 October 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Hall of Shame&quot;&gt;{{cite book|title=Football Hall of Shame|year=1991|publisher=Simon and Schuster|location=New York City|isbn=0671745514, 9780671745516|pages=42|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=jaD_is-geogC&amp;pg=PT51&amp;dq|coauthors=Bruce Nash and Allan Zullo|accessdate=16 October 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Conner|first=Floyd|title=Football's Most Wanted|year=2000|publisher=Potomac Books, Inc.|isbn=1574883097, 9781574883091|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=2j_Fr_2FiwYC&amp;pg=PT106&amp;lpg=PT106&amp;dq}}&lt;/ref&gt; Sloppy second-half play resulted in a 15 to 0 A&amp;M victory. After the game, many of the Ole Miss players blamed Mason for the loss. When asked if his team was returning home that night, Mason replied &quot;Yes, the team is going north at 11 o'clock. I'm going in another direction, and hope I never see them again!&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;Egg Bowl&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Hall of Shame&quot; /&gt; It would be his final game as head coach.&lt;ref name=&quot;Egg Bowl&quot; /&gt;

*'''1941:''' Mississippi State won the Southeastern Conference title, behind quarterback Jennings Moates, after winning 6-0.

*'''1976 and 1977:''' Mississippi State won the Egg Bowl these two years but had to forfeit the wins due to NCAA violations.

*'''1983 - The Immaculate Deflection, or the Wind Bowl:''' In what has become known to Mississippi and MSU fans as &quot;The Immaculate Deflection,&quot; the 1983 Egg Bowl played in Jackson is notable because the wind helped preserve Ole Miss' 24-23 victory. Down by a point with 24 seconds left in the game, MSU kicked what would have been a 27-yard game winning field goal. MSU freshman kicker Artie Cosby kicked it straight and long and what appeared to be over the crossbar, but as the ball reached the goal posts, a 40&amp;nbsp;mph gusting wind suspended the ball inches from the uprights, after which it fell short of the goal post, securing the victory for the Rebels.&lt;ref&gt;[http://orig.clarionledger.com/news/sports/football2003tab/zcover.html ''The ClarionLedger'': Cosby tried, God blew, and 2 teams celebrated]&lt;/ref&gt;

*'''1992 - The Stand:''' In a defensive struggle that saw a combined 12 turnovers between the two, a goal line stand of epic proportions by the &quot;Red Death&quot; defense ultimately gave Ole Miss the win.  Mississippi St. had 11 plays in 2 different possessions inside the Rebel 10 with in the last 4 minutes of the contest but failed to score.  The first possession ended on a third down pass that was intercepted in the end zone by Michael Lowery who would bring the ball out to the 2 yardline.  A couple of plays later saw rebel running back Cory Philpot fumble the ball back to the Dogs making for the Rebels 7th turnover.  On the ensuing possession, State had fourth and goal and the pass was incomplete.  However, pass interference on Orlanda Truitt kept the drive alive, moving the ball to the 2.  However, the next four plays resulted in negative yardage, with the final pass falling incomplete with only 20 seconds remaining.  The Rebels won 17-10.   

*'''1997:''' A melee broke out between the teams before the game.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=OEdpLFgaQEs YouTube: Video of the 1997 Egg Bowl melee]&lt;/ref&gt; The game was won 15-14 by Ole Miss on a game-winning 4th quarter drive. A first and 10 pass was completed to Andre Rone for the touchdown to bring the score to 14-13, advantage MSU.  [[Tommy Tuberville]], in his third season as the Rebels' head coach, opted to attempt a two-point conversion, determined to secure the victory in regulation. The conversion was successful as QB Stewart Patridge connected with Corey Peterson for the score.  A late pass by MSU was intercepted by Tim Strickland to secure the win for the Rebels.  Both teams finished 7-4, however, with limited bowl spots available, Ole Miss would secure its first bowl berth since 1992 while Mississippi St. would fail to reach a bowl for the 3rd consecutive season.

*'''1998:''' Mississippi State clinched their first [[Southeastern Conference#Football|SEC West division]] title after winning 28-6. This win sent MSU to the SEC Championship game where they were defeated 24-14 by eventual national champion [[Tennessee Volunteers football|Tennessee]].  Also noteworthy is the fact that the following day it was announced that Ole Miss's Tommy Tubbervile was to be the new coach at Auburn.

*'''1999 - The Pick and the Kick:''' Known as &quot;The Pick and the Kick,&quot; this game is best known for its dramatic ending. Down 20-6, MSU rallied late in the 4th quarter to tie the game. With 20 seconds left, instead of kneeling the ball to go to overtime, Mississippi decided to run a play, deep in their own territory. Rebel quarterback Romero Miller dropped back and lobbed a deep pass which was deflected by the hands and then the foot of MSU cornerback Robert Bean before being intercepted by Eugene Clinton and returned deep into Rebel territory. On the next play, with 8 seconds left, Bulldog kicker Scott Westerfield kicked a 44-yard game-winning field goal.

*'''2003:''' This year saw the 100th meeting between the two teams. Ole Miss earned a share of its first SEC West division title  with current [[New York Giants]] [[quarterback]] and [[Super Bowl XLII]] [[Most Valuable Player|MVP]] [[Eli Manning]] leading the team. A torrential downpour prevailed much of the game, with both teams fighting tooth and nail for the first 20 or so minutes of the contest.  The heavily favored Rebs ultimately proved to be too much as the Rebels had 3 2nd quarter scores to take a 24-0 lead into the locker room.  The final would be 31-0 marking the first shutout by the Rebels in this rivalry since 1971 (48-0). This Egg Bowl marked Jackie Sherrill's final game as a football coach as in the middle of the 2003 season he had announced his retirement.  Sherrill had an overall record of 7-6 against the Rebels.

*'''2007-The Comeback:''' Mississippi State, after trailing 14-0 late in the fourth quarter, reeled off seventeen points in the final 7 minutes, 51 seconds to win the game and leave Mississippi winless in the SEC for the first time in 25 years. Mississippi head coach [[Ed Orgeron]] was fired after the game and former [[Arkansas Razorbacks football|Arkansas Razorbacks]] head coach [[Houston Nutt]] was hired.

*'''2008:''' A year had passed since the epic meltdown in Starkville that resulted in the firing of Ed Orgeron.  The Rebels, determined to right the wrong, won big with a 45-0 shutout, the third biggest margin ever in the series, to Mississippi State's 65-0 victory in 1915 and Ole Miss's 48-0 victory in 1971.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.clarionledger.com/article/20081129/SPORTS030106/811290338 The Clarion-Ledger: Ole Miss stifles State, allowing 37 total yards]&lt;/ref&gt; Only once did the Mississippi State offense cross the 50-yard line into Ole Miss territory.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.clarionledger.com/apps/pbcs.dll/section?category=PluckPersona&amp;U=5b4ec637f7b54961a37c5c1ac670829d&amp;plckController=PersonaBlog&amp;plckScript=personaScript&amp;plckElementId=personaDest&amp;plckPersonaPage=BlogViewPost&amp;plckPostId=Blog%3a5b4ec637f7b54961a37c5c1ac670829dPost%3a66c7dddf-938f-4549-a846-e1f492e3b509&amp;sid=sitelife.clarionledger.com The Clarion-Ledger: Late night ramblings: Egg Bowl edition]&lt;/ref&gt; Mississippi held MSU to just 37 total yards, which nets minus 51 rushing yards against 88 yards passing. The next day Sylvester Croom resigned as Mississippi State's head coach.

*'''2009:''' Mississippi State won 41-27. The 41 points scored by the Bulldogs was their most in the series since 1917, the most scored on Ole Miss all season, and their 412 yards of offense was the most that the vaunted &quot;Land Shark&quot; defense had given up all year.&lt;ref&gt;[http://sports.espn.go.com/ncf/recap?gameId=293320344 ESPN: Relf guides Mississippi State to Egg Bowl upset]&lt;/ref&gt; The game ended by MSU taking a knee two times on the Ole Miss 4 yard line to run out the last 1:17 on the clock. This was the first Egg Bowl for new Bulldog Head Coach Dan Mullen.

*'''2010:''' Mississippi State won 31-23. MSU led 31-9 in the fourth quarter before Ole Miss scored two late touchdowns. Head Coach Dan Mullen becomes the first Mississippi State head coach since 1940 to win his first two Egg Bowls. 

*'''2011:''' Mississippi State came into this game with five wins and six losses, needing a win to secure a bowl. At the end of the first half, Mississippi State had a 21 to 0 lead. Mississippi State scored 10 more points in the second half, and held Mississippi from a last second touchdown, to win 31-3. This gave Mississippi State a bowl birth, and their head coach, Dan Mullen, his third Egg Bowl in his three appearances. It is the first time since 1941 Mississippi State has won 3 consecutive Egg Bowls. 

==Game results==
[[File:Ole Miss and Mississippi State Egg Bowl 1970s.jpg|thumb|300px|Ole Miss and MSU meet during a 1970s Egg Bowl]]
&lt;!-- Deleted image removed: [[File:Fdwl.jpg|300px|thumb|MSU's new high definition scoreboard shows the final score of the 2009 Egg Bowl and parodies Ole Miss' troubles with their song ''From Dixie with Love''.  Mississippi State 41, Mississippi 27.]] --&gt;
''Mississippi State victories shaded in &lt;font color=&quot;#800000&quot;&gt;██&lt;/font&gt; maroon.  Mississippi victories are shaded &lt;font color=&quot;#002868&quot;&gt;██&lt;/font&gt; blue.  Ties shaded white. Forfeits shaded &lt;font color=&quot;#808080&quot;&gt;██&lt;/font&gt; gray.''

{| class=&quot;wikitable&quot;
!style=&quot;background: #e3e3e3;&quot;|Date
!style=&quot;background: #e3e3e3;&quot;|Site
!style=&quot;background: #e3e3e3;&quot; colspan=2|Winning team
!style=&quot;background: #e3e3e3;&quot; colspan=2|Losing team
!style=&quot;background: #e3e3e3;&quot;|Series
|-align=center style=&quot;background: #660000; color: white&quot;
|October 28, 1901 || Starkville
|align=left|'''Mississippi State'''&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;||&amp;nbsp;'''17'''&amp;nbsp; || align=left|Mississippi||0
|MSU 1-0
|-align=center style=&quot;background: #002868; color: #CE1126&quot;
|October 25, 1902 || Starkville
|align=left|'''Mississippi'''||'''21''' || align=left|Mississippi State&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;||0
|Tied 1-1
|-align=center
|November 14, 1903 || Oxford
|align=left|Mississippi||6 || align=left|Mississippi State||6
|Tied 1-1-1
|-align=center style=&quot;background: #002868; color: #CE1126&quot;
|October 22, 1904 || Columbus
|align=left|'''Mississippi'''||'''17''' || align=left|Mississippi State&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;||5
|MISS 2-1-1
|-align=center style=&quot;background: #800000; color: white&quot;
|&amp;nbsp;November 30, 1905&amp;nbsp; || Jackson
|align=left|'''Mississippi State'''||'''11''' || align=left|Mississippi||0
|Tied 2-2-1
|-align=center style=&quot;background: #002868; color: #CE1126&quot;
|November 29, 1906 || Jackson
|align=left|'''Mississippi'''||'''29''' || align=left|Mississippi State||5
|MISS 3-2-1
|-align=center style=&quot;background: #800000; color: white&quot;
|November 28, 1907 || Jackson
|align=left|'''Mississippi State'''||'''15''' || align=left|Mississippi||0
|Tied 3-3-1
|-align=center style=&quot;background: #800000; color: white&quot;
|November 26, 1908 || Jackson
|align=left|'''Mississippi State'''||'''44''' || align=left|Mississippi||6
|MSU 4-3-1
|-align=center style=&quot;background: #002868; color: #CE1126&quot;
|November 25, 1909 || Jackson
|align=left|'''Mississippi'''||'''9''' || align=left|Mississippi State||5
|Tied 4-4-1
|-align=center style=&quot;background: #002868; color: #CE1126&quot;
|November 24, 1910 || Jackson
|align=left|'''Mississippi'''||'''30''' || align=left|Mississippi State||0
|MISS 5-4-1
|-align=center style=&quot;background: #800000; color: white&quot;
|November 30, 1911 || Jackson
|align=left|'''Mississippi State'''||'''6''' || align=left|Mississippi||0
|Tied 5-5-1
|-align=center style=&quot;background: #800000; color: white&quot;
|November 6, 1915 || Tupelo
|align=left|'''Mississippi State'''||'''65''' || align=left|Mississippi||0
|MSU 6-5-1
|-align=center style=&quot;background: #800000; color: white&quot;
|November 3, 1916 || Tupelo
|align=left|'''Mississippi State'''||'''36''' || align=left|Mississippi||0
|MSU 7-5-1
|-align=center style=&quot;background: #800000; color: white&quot;
|November 3, 1917 || Tupelo
|align=left|'''Mississippi State'''||'''41''' || align=left|Mississippi||&amp;nbsp;14&amp;nbsp;
|MSU 8-5-1
|-align=center style=&quot;background: #800000; color: white&quot;
|November 28, 1918 || Starkville
|align=left|'''Mississippi State'''||'''34''' || align=left|Mississippi||0
|MSU 9-5-1
|-align=center style=&quot;background: #800000; color: white&quot;
|December 7, 1918 || Oxford
|align=left|'''Mississippi State'''||'''13''' || align=left|Mississippi||0
|MSU 10-5-1
|-align=center style=&quot;background: #800000; color: white&quot;
|November 8, 1919 || Clarksdale
|align=left|'''Mississippi State'''||'''33''' || align=left|Mississippi||0
|MSU 11-5-1
|-align=center style=&quot;background: #800000; color: white&quot;
|November 6, 1920 || Greenwood
|align=left|'''Mississippi State'''||'''20''' || align=left|Mississippi||0
|MSU 12-5-1
|-align=center style=&quot;background: #800000; color: white&quot;
|October 29, 1921 || Greenwood
|align=left|'''Mississippi State'''||'''21''' || align=left|Mississippi||0
|MSU 13-5-1
|-align=center style=&quot;background: #800000; color: white&quot;
|October 21, 1922 || Jackson
|align=left|'''Mississippi State'''||'''19''' || align=left|Mississippi||13
|MSU 14-5-1
|-align=center style=&quot;background: #800000; color: white&quot;
|October 20, 1923 || Jackson
|align=left|'''Mississippi State'''||'''13''' || align=left|Mississippi||6
|MSU 15-5-1
|-align=center style=&quot;background: #800000; color: white&quot;
|October 18, 1924 || Jackson
|align=left|'''Mississippi State'''||'''20''' || align=left|Mississippi||0
|MSU 16-5-1
|-align=center style=&quot;background: #800000; color: white&quot;
|October 24, 1925 || Jackson
|align=left|'''Mississippi State'''||'''6''' || align=left|Mississippi||0
|MSU 17-5-1
|-align=center style=&quot;background: #002868; color: #CE1126&quot;
|November 25, 1926 || Starkville
|align=left|'''Mississippi'''||'''7''' || align=left|Mississippi State||6
|MSU 17-6-1
|-align=center style=&quot;background: #002868; color: #CE1126&quot;
|November 24, 1927 || Oxford
|align=left|'''Mississippi'''||'''20''' || align=left|Mississippi State||12
|MSU 17-7-1
|-align=center style=&quot;background: #002868; color: #CE1126&quot;
|November 29, 1928 || Starkville
|align=left|'''Mississippi'''||'''20''' || align=left|Mississippi State||19
|MSU 17-8-1
|-align=center
|November 28, 1929 || Oxford
|align=left|Mississippi||7 || align=left|Mississippi State||7
|MSU 17-8-2
|-align=center style=&quot;background: #002868; color: #CE1126&quot;
|November 27, 1930 || Starkville
|align=left|'''Mississippi'''||'''20''' || align=left|Mississippi State||0
|MSU 17-9-2
|-align=center style=&quot;background: #002868; color: #CE1126&quot;
|November 26, 1931 || Oxford
|align=left|'''Mississippi'''||'''25''' || align=left|Mississippi State||14
|&amp;nbsp;MSU 17-10-2&amp;nbsp;
|-align=center style=&quot;background: #002868; color: #CE1126&quot;
|November 24, 1932 || Starkville
|align=left|'''Mississippi'''||'''13''' || align=left|Mississippi State||0
|MSU 17-11-2
|-align=center style=&quot;background: #002868; color: #CE1126&quot;
|December 2, 1933 || Oxford
|align=left|'''Mississippi'''||'''31''' || align=left|Mississippi State||0
|MSU 17-12-2
|-align=center style=&quot;background: #002868; color: #CE1126&quot;
|December 1, 1934 || Starkville
|align=left|'''Mississippi'''||'''7''' || align=left|Mississippi State||3
|MSU 17-13-2
|-align=center style=&quot;background: #002868; color: #CE1126&quot;
|November 30, 1935 || Oxford
|align=left|'''Mississippi'''||'''14''' || align=left|Mississippi State||6
|MSU 17-14-2
|-align=center style=&quot;background: #800000; color: white&quot;
|November 21, 1936 || Starkville
|align=left|'''Mississippi State'''||'''26''' || align=left|Mississippi||6
|MSU 18-14-2
|-align=center style=&quot;background: #800000; color: white&quot;
|November 25, 1937 || Oxford
|align=left|'''Mississippi State'''||'''9''' || align=left|Mississippi||7
|MSU 19-14-2
|-align=center style=&quot;background: #002868; color: #CE1126&quot;
|November 26, 1938 || Starkville
|align=left|'''Mississippi'''||'''19''' || align=left|Mississippi State||6
|MSU 19-15-2
|-align=center style=&quot;background: #800000; color: white&quot;
|November 25, 1939 || Oxford
|align=left|'''Mississippi State'''||'''18''' || align=left|Mississippi||6
|MSU 20-15-2
|-align=center style=&quot;background: #800000; color: white&quot;
|November 23, 1940 || Starkville
|align=left|'''Mississippi State'''||'''19''' || align=left|Mississippi||0
|MSU 21-15-2
|-align=center style=&quot;background: #800000; color: white&quot;
|November 29, 1941 || Oxford
|align=left|'''Mississippi State'''||'''6''' || align=left|Mississippi||0
|MSU 22-15-2
|-align=center style=&quot;background: #800000; color: white&quot;
|November 28, 1942 || Starkville
|align=left|'''Mississippi State'''||'''34''' || align=left|Mississippi||12
|MSU 23-15-2
|-align=center style=&quot;background: #002868; color: #CE1126&quot;
|November 25, 1944 || Oxford
|align=left|'''Mississippi'''||'''13''' || align=left|Mississippi State||8
|MSU 23-16-2
|-align=center style=&quot;background: #002868; color: #CE1126&quot;
|November 24, 1945 || Starkville
|align=left|'''Mississippi'''||'''7''' || align=left|Mississippi State||6
|MSU 23-17-2
|-align=center style=&quot;background: #800000; color: white&quot;
|November 23, 1946 || Oxford
|align=left|'''Mississippi State'''||'''20''' || align=left|Mississippi||0
|MSU 24-17-2
|-align=center style=&quot;background: #002868; color: #CE1126&quot;
|November 29, 1947 || Starkville
|align=left|'''Mississippi'''||'''33''' || align=left|Mississippi State||14
|MSU 24-18-2
|-align=center style=&quot;background: #002868; color: #CE1126&quot;
|November 27, 1948 || Oxford
|align=left|'''Mississippi'''||'''34''' || align=left|Mississippi State||7
|MSU 24-19-2
|-align=center style=&quot;background: #002868; color: #CE1126&quot;
|November 26, 1949 || Starkville
|align=left|'''Mississippi'''||'''26''' || align=left|Mississippi State||0
|MSU 24-20-2
|-align=center style=&quot;background: #002868; color: #CE1126&quot;
|December 2, 1950 || Oxford
|align=left|'''Mississippi'''||'''27''' || align=left|Mississippi State||20
|MSU 24-21-2
|-align=center style=&quot;background: #002868; color: #CE1126&quot;
|December 1, 1951 || Starkville
|align=left|'''Mississippi'''||'''49''' || align=left|Mississippi State||7
|MSU 24-22-2
|-align=center style=&quot;background: #002868; color: #CE1126&quot;
|November 29, 1952 || Oxford
|align=left|'''Mississippi'''||'''20''' || align=left|Mississippi State||14
|MSU 24-23-2
|-align=center
|November 28, 1953 || Starkville
|align=left|Mississippi||7 || align=left|Mississippi State||7
|MSU 24-23-3
|-align=center style=&quot;background: #002868; color: #CE1126&quot;
|November 27, 1954 || Oxford
|align=left|'''Mississippi'''||'''14''' || align=left|Mississippi State||0
|Tied 24-24-3
|-align=center style=&quot;background: #002868; color: #CE1126&quot;
|November 26, 1955 || Starkville
|align=left|'''Mississippi'''||'''26''' || align=left|Mississippi State||0
|MISS 25-24-3
|-align=center style=&quot;background: #002868; color: #CE1126&quot;
|December 1, 1956 || Oxford
|align=left|'''Mississippi'''||'''13''' || align=left|Mississippi State||7
|MISS 26-24-3
|-align=center
|November 30, 1957 || Starkville
|align=left|Mississippi State||7 || align=left|Mississippi||7
|MISS 26-24-4
|-align=center style=&quot;background: #002868; color: #CE1126&quot;
|November 29, 1958 || Oxford
|align=left|'''Mississippi'''||'''21''' || align=left|Mississippi State||0
|MISS 27-24-4
|-align=center style=&quot;background: #002868; color: #CE1126&quot;
|November 28, 1959 || Starkville
|align=left|'''Mississippi'''||'''42''' || align=left|Mississippi State||0
|MISS 28-24-4
|-align=center style=&quot;background: #002868; color: #CE1126&quot;
|November 26, 1960 || Oxford
|align=left|'''Mississippi'''||'''35''' || align=left|Mississippi State||9
|MISS 29-24-4
|-align=center style=&quot;background: #002868; color: #CE1126&quot;
|December 2, 1961 || Starkville
|align=left|'''Mississippi'''||'''37''' || align=left|Mississippi State||7
|MISS 30-24-4
|-align=center style=&quot;background: #002868; color: #CE1126&quot;
|December 1, 1962 || Oxford
|align=left|'''Mississippi'''||'''13''' || align=left|Mississippi State||6
|MISS 31-24-4
|-align=center
|November 30, 1963 || Starkville
|align=left|Mississippi State||10 || align=left|Mississippi||10
|MISS 31-24-5
|-align=center style=&quot;background: #800000; color: white&quot;
|December 5, 1964 || Oxford
|align=left|'''Mississippi State'''||'''20''' || align=left|Mississippi||17
|MISS 31-25-5
|-align=center style=&quot;background: #002868; color: #CE1126&quot;
|November 27, 1965 || Starkville
|align=left|'''Mississippi'''||'''21''' || align=left|Mississippi State||0
|MISS 32-25-5
|-align=center style=&quot;background: #002868; color: #CE1126&quot;
|November 26, 1966 || Oxford
|align=left|'''Mississippi'''||'''24''' || align=left|Mississippi State||0
|MISS 33-25-5
|-align=center style=&quot;background: #002868; color: #CE1126&quot;
|December 2, 1967 || Starkville
|align=left|'''Mississippi'''||'''10''' || align=left|Mississippi State||3
|MISS 34-25-5
|-align=center
|November 30, 1968 || Oxford
|align=left|Mississippi||17 || align=left|Mississippi State||17
|MISS 34-25-6
|-align=center style=&quot;background: #002868; color: #CE1126&quot;
|November 27, 1969 || Starkville
|align=left|'''Mississippi'''||'''48''' || align=left|Mississippi State||22
|MISS 35-25-6
|-align=center style=&quot;background: #660000; color: white&quot;
|November 26, 1970 || Oxford
|align=left|'''Mississippi State'''||'''19''' || align=left|Mississippi||14
|MISS 35-26-6
|-align=center style=&quot;background: #002868; color: #CE1126&quot;
|November 25, 1971 || Starkville
|align=left|'''Mississippi'''||'''48''' || align=left|Mississippi State||0
|MISS 36-26-6
|-align=center style=&quot;background: #002868; color: #CE1126&quot;
|November 25, 1972 || Oxford
|align=left|'''Mississippi'''||'''51''' || align=left|Mississippi State||14
|MISS 37-26-6
|-align=center style=&quot;background: #002868; color: #CE1126&quot;
|November 24, 1973 || Jackson
|align=left|'''Mississippi'''||'''38''' || align=left|Mississippi State||10
|MISS 38-26-6
|-align=center style=&quot;background: #800000; color: white&quot;
|November 23, 1974 || Jackson
|align=left|'''Mississippi State'''||'''31''' || align=left|Mississippi||13
|MISS 38-27-6
|-align=center style=&quot;background: #002868; color: #CE1126&quot;
|November 22, 1975 || Jackson
|align=left|'''Mississippi'''||'''13''' || align=left|Mississippi State||7
|MISS 39-27-6
|-align=center style=&quot;background:#808080; color: white&quot;
|November 20, 1976 || Jackson
|align=left|Mississippi||11 || align=left|'''Mississippi State'''||'''28*'''
|MISS 40-27-6
|-align=center style=&quot;background:#808080; color: white&quot;
|November 19, 1977 || Jackson
|align=left|Mississippi||14 || align=left|'''Mississippi State'''||'''18*'''
|MISS 41-27-6
|-align=center style=&quot;background: #002868; color: #CE1126&quot;
|November 25, 1978 || Jackson
|align=left|'''Mississippi'''||'''27''' || align=left|Mississippi State||7
|MISS 42-27-6
|-align=center style=&quot;background: #002868; color: #CE1126&quot;
|November 24, 1979 || Jackson
|align=left|'''Mississippi'''||'''14''' || align=left|Mississippi State||9
|MISS 43-27-6
|-align=center style=&quot;background: #800000; color: white&quot;
|November 22, 1980 || Jackson
|align=left|'''Mississippi State'''||'''19''' || align=left|Mississippi||14
|MISS 43-28-6
|-align=center style=&quot;background: #002868; color: #CE1126&quot;
|November 21, 1981 || Jackson
|align=left|'''Mississippi'''||'''21''' || align=left|Mississippi State||17
|MISS 44-28-6
|-align=center style=&quot;background: #800000; color: white&quot;
|November 20, 1982 || Jackson
|align=left|'''Mississippi State'''||'''27''' || align=left|Mississippi||10
|MISS 44-29-6
|-align=center style=&quot;background: #002868; color: #CE1126&quot;
|November 19, 1983 || Jackson
|align=left|'''Mississippi'''||'''24''' || align=left|Mississippi State||23
|MISS 45-29-6
|-align=center style=&quot;background: #002868; color: #CE1126&quot;
|November 24, 1984 || Jackson
|align=left|'''Mississippi'''||'''24''' || align=left|Mississippi State||3
|MISS 46-29-6
|-align=center style=&quot;background: #002868; color: #CE1126&quot;
|November 23, 1985 || Jackson
|align=left|'''Mississippi'''||'''45''' || align=left|Mississippi State||27
|MISS 47-29-6
|-align=center style=&quot;background: #002868; color: #CE1126&quot;
|November 22, 1986 || Jackson
|align=left|'''Mississippi'''||'''24''' || align=left|Mississippi State||3
|MISS 48-29-6
|-align=center style=&quot;background: #800000; color: white&quot;
|November 21, 1987 || Jackson
|align=left|'''Mississippi State'''||'''30''' || align=left|Mississippi||20
|MISS 48-30-6
|-align=center style=&quot;background: #002868; color: #CE1126&quot;
|November 26, 1988 || Jackson
|align=left|'''Mississippi'''||'''33''' || align=left|Mississippi State||6
|MISS 49-30-6
|-align=center style=&quot;background: #002868; color: #CE1126&quot;
|November 25, 1989 || Jackson
|align=left|'''Mississippi'''||'''21''' || align=left|Mississippi State||11
|MISS 50-30-6
|-align=center style=&quot;background: #002868; color: #CE1126&quot;
|November 24, 1990 || Jackson
|align=left|'''Mississippi'''||'''21''' || align=left|Mississippi State||9
|MISS 51-30-6
|-align=center style=&quot;background: #800000; color: white&quot;
|November 23, 1991 || Starkville
|align=left|'''Mississippi State'''||'''24''' || align=left|Mississippi||9
|MISS 51-31-6
|-align=center style=&quot;background: #002868; color: #CE1126&quot;
|November 28, 1992 || Oxford
|align=left|'''Mississippi'''||'''17''' || align=left|Mississippi State||10
|MISS 52-31-6
|-align=center style=&quot;background: #800000; color: white&quot;
|November 27, 1993 || Starkville
|align=left|'''Mississippi State'''||'''20''' || align=left|Mississippi||13
|MISS 52-32-6
|-align=center style=&quot;background: #800000; color: white&quot;
|November 26, 1994 || Oxford
|align=left|'''Mississippi State'''||'''21''' || align=left|Mississippi||17
|MISS 52-33-6
|-align=center style=&quot;background: #002868; color: #CE1126&quot;
|November 25, 1995 || Starkville
|align=left|'''Mississippi'''||'''13''' || align=left|Mississippi State||10
|MISS 53-33-6
|-align=center style=&quot;background: #800000; color: white&quot;
|November 30, 1996 || Oxford
|align=left|'''Mississippi State'''||'''17''' || align=left|Mississippi||0
|MISS 53-34-6
|-align=center style=&quot;background: #002868; color: #CE1126&quot;
|November 29, 1997 || Starkville
|align=left|'''Mississippi'''||'''15''' || align=left|Mississippi State||14
|MISS 54-34-6
|-align=center style=&quot;background: #800000; color: white&quot;
|November 26, 1998 || Oxford
|align=left|'''Mississippi State'''||'''28''' || align=left|Mississippi||6
|MISS 54-35-6
|-align=center style=&quot;background: #800000; color: white&quot;
|November 25, 1999 || Starkville
|align=left|'''Mississippi State'''||'''23''' || align=left|Mississippi||20
|MISS 54-36-6
|-align=center style=&quot;background: #002868; color: #CE1126&quot;
|November 23, 2000 || Oxford
|align=left|'''Mississippi'''||'''45''' || align=left|Mississippi State||30
|MISS 55-36-6
|-align=center style=&quot;background: #800000; color: white&quot;
|November 22, 2001 || Starkville
|align=left|'''Mississippi State'''||'''36''' || align=left|Mississippi||28
|MISS 55-37-6
|-align=center style=&quot;background: #002868; color: #CE1126&quot;
|November 28, 2002 || Oxford
|align=left|'''Mississippi'''||'''24''' || align=left|Mississippi State||12
|MISS 56-37-6
|-align=center style=&quot;background: #002868; color: #CE1126&quot;
|November 27, 2003 || Starkville
|align=left|'''Mississippi'''||'''31''' || align=left|Mississippi State||0
|MISS 57-37-6
|-align=center style=&quot;background: #002868; color: #CE1126&quot;
|November 27, 2004 || Oxford
|align=left|'''Mississippi'''||'''20''' || align=left|Mississippi State||3
|MISS 58-37-6
|-align=center style=&quot;background: #800000; color: white&quot;
|November 26, 2005 || Starkville
|align=left|'''Mississippi State'''||'''35''' || align=left|Mississippi||14
|MISS 58-38-6
|-align=center style=&quot;background: #002868; color: #CE1126&quot;
|November 25, 2006 || Oxford
|align=left|'''Mississippi'''||'''20'''|| align=left|Mississippi State||17||MISS 59-38-6
|-align=center style=&quot;background: #800000; color: white&quot;
|November 23, 2007 || Starkville
|align=left|'''Mississippi State'''||'''17'''|| align=left|Mississippi||14||MISS 59-39-6
|-align=center style=&quot;background: #002868; color: #CE1126&quot;
|November 28, 2008 ||Oxford
|align=left|'''Mississippi'''||'''45''' || align=left|Mississippi State||0
|MISS 60-39-6
|-align=center style=&quot;background: #800000; color: white&quot;
|November 28, 2009 || Starkville
|align=left|'''Mississippi State'''||'''41'''|| align=left| Mississippi ||27||MISS 60-40-6
|-align=center style=&quot;background: #800000; color: white&quot;
|November 27, 2010 || Oxford
|align=left| '''Mississippi State'''||'''31'''|| align=left| Mississippi ||23||MISS 60-41-6
|-align=center style=&quot;background: #800000; color: white&quot;
|November 26, 2011 || Starkville
|align=left| '''Mississippi State'''||'''31'''|| align=left| Mississippi ||3||MISS 60-42-6

|}

&lt;nowiki&gt;*&lt;/nowiki&gt;Mississippi State won the Egg Bowl on the field in 1976 and 1977, but were later forced to forfeit the games by the NCAA.

==References==
{{Reflist}}

==External links==
*[http://orig.clarionledger.com/news/sports/football2003tab/index.html 2003 The ClarionLedger Egg Bowl Series]

{{Mississippi State Bulldogs football navbox}}
{{Ole Miss Rebels football navbox}}
{{Southeastern Conference football rivalry navbox}}

[[Category:College football rivalries in the United States]]
[[Category:Mississippi State Bulldogs football]]
[[Category:Ole Miss Rebels football]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
