<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="12431" ns="0" title="Google Search"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{infobox website
| logo           = [[file:Googlelogo.png|220px]]
| screenshot     = [[file:Google web search.png|250px]]
| caption        = Google Search homepage
| url            = {{URL|http://www.google.com/|Google.com}}
| commercial     = Yes
| type           = [[Web search engine]]
| language       = Multilingual (124)
| ipv6           = Yes, by arrangement&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.google.com/intl/en/ipv6/|title=Google over IPv6|accessdate=2010-12-08}}&lt;/ref&gt; or [http://ipv6.google.com/ ipv6.google.com]
| registration   = Optional
| owner          = [[Google]]
| author         = [[Sergey Brin]] and [[Larry Page]]
| launch date    = {{start date|1997|9|15}}&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web| url=http://reports.internic.net/cgi/whois?whois_nic=google.com&amp;type=domain | title=WHOIS - google.com | accessdate=2009-01-27}}&lt;/ref&gt;
| current status = Active
| revenue        = From [[AdWords]]
| slogan         =
| alexa          = {{steady}} 1 ({{as of|2011|11|2|alt=November 2011}})&lt;ref name=&quot;alexa&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url= http://www.alexa.com/siteinfo/google.com |title= Google.com Site Info | publisher= [[Alexa Internet]] |accessdate= 2011-11-02 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;!--Updated monthly by OKBot.--&gt;
}}

'''Google''' or '''Google Web Search''' is a [[web search engine]] owned by [[Google Inc.]] Google Search is the most-used search engine on the [[World Wide Web]],&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.alexa.com/siteinfo/google.com+yahoo.com+altavista.com |title=Alexa Search Engine ranking |accessdate=2009-11-15}}&lt;/ref&gt; receiving several hundred million queries each day through its various services.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://searchenginewatch.com/showPage.html?page=3630718 |title=Almost 12 Billion U.S. Searches Conducted in July |publisher=SearchEngineWatch |date=2008-09-02 |accessdate=}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The order of search results on Google's search-results pages is based, in part, on a priority rank called a &quot;[[PageRank]]&quot;. Google Search provides many options for customized search, using [[Boolean logic|Boolean]] operators such as: exclusion (&quot;-xx&quot;), alternatives (&quot;xx OR yy&quot;), and wildcard (&quot;x * x&quot;).&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.google.co.nz/support/websearch/bin/answer.py?answer=136861 ''...The *, or wildcard, is a little-known feature that can be very powerful...'']&lt;/ref&gt;

The main purpose of Google Search is to hunt for text in Web pages, as opposed to other data, such as with [[Google Image Search]]. Google Search was originally developed by [[Larry Page]] and [[Sergey Brin]] in 1997.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url= http://reports.internic.net/cgi/whois?whois_nic=google.com&amp;type=domain|title=WHOIS - google.com|accessdate=2009-01-27}}&lt;/ref&gt; Google Search provides at least 22 special features beyond the original word-search capability.&lt;ref name=fea/&gt; These include synonyms, weather forecasts, time zones, stock quotes, maps, earthquake data, movie showtimes, airports, home listings, and sports scores. There are special features for numbers, including ranges (70..73),&lt;ref name=csheet/&gt; prices, temperatures, money/unit conversions (&quot;10.5 cm in inches&quot;), calculations ({{nowrap|&quot;3*4+sqrt(6)-pi/2&quot;}}), package tracking, patents, area codes,&lt;ref name=fea/&gt; and [[language translation]] of displayed pages. In June 2011, Google introduced &quot;[[Google Voice Search]]&quot; and &quot;Search by Image&quot; features for allowing the users to search words by speaking and by giving images.&lt;ref&gt;[http://qualitypoint.blogspot.com/2011/06/voice-search-for-googlecom.html ''Voice Search for Google.com - Just click the mic and say your search. And, Search Google by giving Image'']&lt;/ref&gt;

The frequency of use of many search terms have reached a volume that they may indicate broader economic, social and health trends.&lt;ref name=&quot;Pulse&quot;&gt;{{cite book|first=Douglas|last=Hubbard|title=Pulse: The New Science of Harnessing Internet Buzz to Track Threats and Opportunities|publisher=John Wiley &amp; Sons|year=2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; Data about the frequency of use of search terms on Google (available through Google Adwords, Google Trends, and Google Insights for Search) have been shown to correlate with flu outbreaks and unemployment levels and provide the information faster than traditional reporting methods and government surveys.

==Search engine== 
===PageRank===
 {{Main|PageRank}} Google's rise to success was in large part due to a [[patent]]ed [[algorithm]] called [[PageRank]] that helps rank web pages that match a given search string.{{cite doi|10.1016/S0169-7552(98)00110-X}} When Google was a Stanford research project, it was nicknamed BackRub because the technology checks backlinks to determine a site's importance. Previous keyword-based methods of ranking search results, used by many search engines that were once more popular than Google, would rank pages by how often the search terms occurred in the page, or how strongly associated the search terms were within each resulting page. The PageRank algorithm instead analyzes human-generated [[hyperlink|links]] assuming that web pages linked from many important pages are themselves likely to be important. The algorithm computes a [[recursion|recursive]] score for pages, based on the weighted sum of the PageRanks of the pages linking to them. PageRank is thought to [[correlation|correlate]] well with human concepts of importance. In addition to PageRank, Google, over the years, has added many other secret criteria for determining the ranking of pages on result lists, reported to be over 200 different indicators.{{cite web|url=http://www.google.com/corporate/tech.html |title=Corporate Information: Technology Overview |publisher=[[Google]] |accessdate=2009-11-15}}[http://www.wired.com/magazine/2010/02/ff_google_algorithm/ Wired.com] The specifics of which are kept secret to keep spammers at bay and help Google maintain an edge over its competitors globally. ===Search results=== The exact percentage of the total of web pages that Google [[Index (search engine)|indexes]] is not known, as it is very difficult to accurately calculate. Google not only indexes and caches web pages, but also takes &quot;snapshots&quot; of other file types, which include [[Portable Document Format|PDF]], [[Word document]]s, [[Excel spreadsheet]]s, Flash SWF, plain text files, and so on.{{cite web|url=http://www.google.com/help/faq_filetypes.html#what | title=Google Frequently Asked Questions - File Types | publisher=[[Google]] |accessdate=2011-09-12}}Except in the case of text and [[SWF]] files, the cached version is a conversion to (X)HTML, allowing those without the corresponding viewer application to read the file. Users can customize the search engine, by setting a default language, using the &quot;SafeSearch&quot; filtering technology and set the number of results shown on each page. Google has been criticized for placing long-term [[HTTP cookie|cookies]] on users' machines to store these preferences, a tactic which also enables them to track a user's search terms and retain the data for more than a year.{{citation needed|date=November 2011}} For any query, up to the first 1000 results can be shown with a maximum of 100 displayed per page. The ability to specify the number of results is available only if &quot;Instant Search&quot; is not enabled. If &quot;Instant Search&quot; is enabled, only 10 results are displayed, regardless of this setting.{{Or|date=September 2011}} ===Non-indexable data=== Despite its immense index, there is also a considerable amount of data available in online databases which are accessible by means of queries but not by links. This so-called invisible or [[deep Web]] is minimally covered by Google and other search engines.{{cite web|author=Sherman, Chris and Price, Gary |title=The Invisible Web: Uncovering Sources Search Engines Can't See, In: ''Library Trends'' 52 (2) 2003: Organizing the Internet: |pages=282–298 |url= http://hdl.handle.net/2142/8528}} The deep Web contains [[library catalog]]s, official [[legislative]] documents of governments, [[phone book]]s, and other content which is dynamically prepared to respond to a query. ===Google optimization=== {{Main|Search engine optimization}} Since Google is the most popular search engine, many [[webmaster]]s have become eager to influence their website's Google rankings. An industry of consultants has arisen to help websites increase their rankings on Google and on other search engines. This field, called [[search engine optimization]], attempts to discern patterns in search engine listings, and then develop a methodology for improving rankings to draw more searchers to their client's sites. Search engine optimization encompasses both &quot;on page&quot; factors (like body copy, title elements, H1 heading elements and image [[alt attribute]] values) and Off Page Optimization factors (like [[anchor text]] and PageRank). The general idea is to affect Google's relevance algorithm by incorporating the keywords being targeted in various places &quot;on page&quot;, in particular the title element and the body copy (note: the higher up in the page, presumably the better its keyword prominence and thus the ranking). Too many occurrences of the keyword, however, cause the page to look suspect to Google's spam checking algorithms. Google has published guidelines for website owners who would like to raise their rankings when using legitimate optimization consultants.{{cite web|url=http://www.google.com/webmasters/guidelines.html |title=Google Webmaster Guidelines |publisher=Google |accessdate=2009-11-15}} It has been hypothesized, and, allegedly, is the opinion of the owner of one business about which there has been numerous complaints, that negative publicity, for example, numerous consumer complaints, may serve as well to elevate page rank on Google Search as favorable comments.{{cite news |title=A Bully Finds a Pulpit on the Web|first=David|last=Segal|newspaper=The New York Times|date=November 26, 2010|url=https://www.nytimes.com/2010/11/28/business/28borker.html|accessdate=November 27, 2010}} The particular problem addressed in ''[[The New York Times]]'' article, which involved [[DecorMyEyes]], was addressed shortly thereafter by an undisclosed fix in the Google algorithm. According to Google, it was not the frequently published consumer complaints about DecorMyEyes which resulted in the high ranking but mentions on news websites of events which affected the firm such as legal actions against it.[http://googleblog.blogspot.com/2010/12/being-bad-to-your-customers-is-bad-for.html Blogspot.com]

==Functionality==
&lt;!--This section might need to be separated into a new and separate article about the Google Search Engine--&gt;
&lt;!--A link to the new article should be added to see also if or when this section is removed--&gt;
&lt;!--Do not add to [[google platform]] as it is hardware related--&gt;
[[File:Feature.png|right|thumb|Image of definition link provided for many search terms.]]
Google search consists of a series of localized websites. The largest of those, the google.com site, is the top most-visited website in the world.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.alexa.com/site/ds/top_sites?ts_mode=global&amp;lang=none |title=Top 500 |accessdate=2008-04-15 |publisher=[[Alexa Internet|Alexa]]}}&lt;/ref&gt; Some of its features include a definition link for most searches including dictionary words, the number of results you got on your search, links to other searches (e.g. for words that Google believes to be misspelled, it provides a link to the search results using its proposed spelling), and many more.

===Search syntax===
Google's search engine normally accepts queries as a simple text, and breaks up the user's text into a sequence of search terms, which will usually be words that are to occur in the results, but one can also use [[Boolean logic|Boolean]] operators, such as: quotations marks (&quot;) for a phrase, a prefix such as &quot;+&quot; , &quot;-&quot; for qualified terms (no longer valid, the '+' was removed from google on 10/19/11&lt;ref name=&quot;Google changes the operators&quot;&gt;[http://www.frag.co.uk/blog/2011/10/googles-changes-the-operators/], Google changes the operators.&lt;/ref&gt;), or one of several advanced operators, such as &quot;site:&quot;. The webpages of &quot;Google Search Basics&quot;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.google.com/support/websearch/bin/answer.py?answer=136861 Google.com]&lt;/ref&gt; describe each of these additional queries and options (''see below:'' [[#Search options|Search options]]).
Google's Advanced Search web form gives several additional fields which may be used to qualify searches by such criteria as date of first retrieval. All advanced queries transform to regular queries, usually with additional qualified term.

===Query expansion===
Google applies [[query expansion]] to the submitted search query, transforming it into the query that will actually be used to retrieve results. As with page ranking, the exact details of the algorithm Google uses are deliberately obscure, but certainly the following transformations are among those that occur:
* Term reordering: in [[information retrieval]] this is a standard technique to reduce the work involved in retrieving results. This transformation is invisible to the user, since the results ordering uses the original query order to determine relevance.
* [[Stemming]] is used to increase search quality by keeping small syntactic variants of search terms.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.google.com/support/bin/answer.py?answer=35889#stemming |title=Google:Stemming |publisher=Google}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* There is a limited facility to fix possible misspellings in queries.

===&quot;I'm Feeling Lucky&quot;===
Google's homepage includes a button labelled &quot;I'm Feeling Lucky&quot;. When a user types in a search and clicks on the button the user will be taken directly to the first search result, bypassing the [[search engine results page]]. The thought is that if a user is &quot;feeling lucky&quot;, the search engine will return the perfect match the first time without having to page through the search results. However, with the introduction of [[Google Instant]], it is not possible to use the button properly unless the Google Instant function is switched off. According to a study by Tom Chavez of &quot;Rapt&quot;, this feature costs Google $110 million a year as 1% of all searches use this feature and bypass all advertising.&lt;ref name=&quot;I'm feeling lucky&quot;&gt;{{cite web| title=I'm feeling lucky( button costs Google $110 million per year | year=2007 | publisher=Valleywag | url=http://valleywag.com/tech/google/im-feeling-lucky-button-costs-google-110-million-per-year-324927.php | accessdate=2008-01-19}}&lt;/ref&gt;

On October 30, 2009, for some users, the &quot;I'm Feeling Lucky&quot; button was removed from Google's main page, along with the regular search button. Both buttons were replaced with a field that reads,                                                                                                          &quot;This space intentionally left blank.&quot; This text faded out when the mouse was moved on the page, and normal search functionality is achieved by filling in the search field with the desired terms and pressing enter. A Google spokesperson explains, &quot;This is just a test, and a way for us to gauge whether our users will like an even simpler search interface.&quot;&lt;ref name=Google’s New Homepage Motto: 'This Space Intentionally Left Blank'&gt;{{cite web| title=Google’s New Homepage Motto: 'This Space Intentionally Left Blank' | year=2009 | publisher=WallStreetJournal | url=http://digitaldaily.allthingsd.com/20091030/goog-page/ | accessdate=2009-11-17}}&lt;/ref&gt; Personalized Google homepages retained both buttons and their normal functions.

On May 21, 2010, the 30th anniversary of [[Pac-Man]], the &quot;I'm Feeling Lucky&quot; button was replaced with a button reading the words &quot;Insert Coin&quot;. After pressing the button, the user would begin a Google-themed game of Pac-Man in the area where the Google logo would normally be. Pressing the button a second time would begin a two-player version of the same game that includes Ms. Pacman for player 2. This version can be accessed at &lt;code&gt;www.google.com/pacman/&lt;/code&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.google.com/pacman Google.com]&lt;/ref&gt; as a permanent link to the page.

===Rich Snippets===
On 12 May 2009, Google announced that they would be parsing the [[hCard]], [[hReview]], and [[hProduct]] [[microformat]]s and using them to populate search result pages with what they called &quot;Rich Snippets&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;Rich-Snippets&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://googlewebmastercentral.blogspot.com/2009/05/introducing-rich-snippets.html|title=Introducing Rich Snippets|last=Goel|first=Kavi|coauthors=Ramanathan V. Guha, Othar Hansson|date=2009-05-12|work=Google Webmaster Central Blog|publisher=Google|accessdate=2009-05-25}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Special features{{Anchor|Search engine features}}===
Besides the main search-engine feature of searching for text, Google Search has more than 22 &quot;special features&quot; (activated by entering any of dozens of ''trigger words'') when searching:&lt;ref name=&quot;fea&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.google.com/intl/en/help/features.html |title=Search Features |publisher=Google.com |date=May 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;csheet&quot;&gt;{{cite web
 | title=Google Help : Cheat Sheet
 | url=http://www.google.com/help/cheatsheet.html
 | publisher=Google | year=2010}}
&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;EmU&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.law.emory.edu/law-library/research/advanced-legal-research-class/finding-aids-and-searching/google.html |title=Google and Search Engines |publisher=[[Emory University Law School]] |year=2006}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* weather – The weather conditions, temperature, wind, humidity, and forecast,&lt;ref name=fea/&gt; for many cities, can be viewed by typing &quot;weather&quot; along with a city for larger cities or city and state, U.S. zip code, or city and country for smaller cities (such as: weather [[Lawrence, Kansas]]; weather [[Paris, France|Paris]]; weather [[Bremen, Germany]]).
* stock quotes – The market data&lt;ref name=fea/&gt; for a specific company or fund can be viewed, by typing the [[ticker symbol]] (or include &quot;stock&quot;), such as: [[Cisco Systems|CSCO]]; [[Microsoft|MSFT]]; IBM stock; F stock (lists [[Ford Motor Company|Ford Motor Co.]]); or AIVSX (fund). Results show inter-day changes, or 5-year graph, etc. This does not work for stock names which are one letter long, such as Citigroup (C) or Macy's (M) (Ford being an exception), or are common words, such as Diamond Offshore (DO) or Majesco (COOL).
* time – The current time in many cities (worldwide),&lt;ref name=fea/&gt; can be viewed by typing &quot;time&quot; and the name of the city (such as: time Cairo; time [[Pratt, KS]]).
* sports scores – The scores and schedules, for sports teams,&lt;ref name=fea/&gt; can be displayed by typing the team name or league name into the search box.
* unit conversion – Measurements can be converted,&lt;ref name=fea/&gt; by entering each phrase, such as: 10.5&amp;nbsp;cm in inches; or 90&amp;nbsp;km in miles
* currency conversion – A money or currency converter can be selected,&lt;ref name=fea/&gt; by typing the names or [[currency codes]] (listed by [[ISO 4217]]): 6789 [[Euro]] in [[USD]]; 150 [[GBP]] in USD; 5000 [[Yen]] in USD; 5000 [[Chinese yuan|Yuan]] in [[lira]] (the U.S. dollar can be ''USD'' or &quot;US$&quot; or &quot;$&quot;, while Canadian is ''CAD'', etc.).
* {{anchor|calculator}}calculator – [[Calculation]] results can be determined,&lt;ref name=fea/&gt; as calculated live, by entering a formula in numbers or words, such as: 6*77 +pi +sqrt(e^3)/888 plus 0.45. The user is given the option to search for the formula, after calculation. The calculator also uses the unit and currency conversion functions to allow unit-aware calculations. For example, &quot;(3 EUR/liter) / (40 miles/gallon) in USD / mile&quot; calculates the dollar cost per mile for a 40 mpg car with gas costing 3 euros a liter. The caret &quot;^&quot; raises a number to an exponent power, and percentages are allowed (&quot;40% of 300&quot;).&lt;ref name=csheet/&gt; There is also some debate as to Google's calculation of 0^0. Many mathematicians believe that 0^0 is undefined but Google's calculator shows the result as 1.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.google.com/search?output=&amp;sitesearch=&amp;hl=en&amp;q=2%2B2&amp;submit=Search+the+Web#hl=en&amp;expIds=17259,22104,25907,26637,26659,26741,26817,26992,27095&amp;sugexp=ldymls&amp;xhr=t&amp;q=0%5E0&amp;cp=3&amp;pf=p&amp;sclient=psy&amp;aq=f&amp;aqi=g4g-o1&amp;aql=&amp;oq=0%5E0&amp;gs_rfai=&amp;pbx=1&amp;fp=433548e9226de17c Google.com]&lt;/ref&gt;
* numeric ranges – A set of numbers can be matched by using a double-dot between range numbers (70..73 or 90..100) to match any positive number in the range, inclusive.&lt;ref name=csheet/&gt; Negative numbers are treated as using exclusion-dash to not match the number.
* dictionary lookup – A definition for a word or phrase can be found,&lt;ref name=fea/&gt; by entering &quot;define&quot; followed by a colon and the word(s) to lookup (such as, &quot;define:philosophy&quot;)
* maps – Some related maps can be displayed,&lt;ref name=fea/&gt; by typing in the name or U.S. [[ZIP code]] of a location and the word &quot;map&quot; (such as: New York map; Kansas map; or Paris map).
* movie showtimes – Reviews or [[film]] showtimes can be listed for any movies playing nearby,&lt;ref name=fea/&gt; by typing &quot;movies&quot; or the name of any current film into the search box. If a specific location was saved on a previous search, the top search result will display showtimes for nearby theaters for that movie.
* public data – Trends for population (or unemployment rates)&lt;ref name=fea/&gt; can be found for U.S. states &amp; counties, by typing &quot;population&quot; or &quot;unemployment rate&quot; followed by a state or county name.
* real estate and housing – Home listings in a given area can be displayed,&lt;ref name=fea/&gt; using the trigger words &quot;housing&quot;, &quot;home&quot;, or &quot;real estate&quot; followed by the name of a city or U.S. zip code.
* travel data/airports – The flight status for arriving or departing U.S. flights can be displayed,&lt;ref name=fea/&gt; by typing in the name of the [[airline]] and the flight number into the search box (such as: [[American Airlines|American airlines]] 18). Delays at a specific airport can also be viewed (by typing the name of the city or three-letter airport code plus word &quot;airport&quot;).
* package tracking – Package mail can be tracked&lt;ref name=fea/&gt; by typing the tracking number of a [[Royal Mail]], [[United Parcel Service|UPS]], [[FedEx]] or [[United States Postal Service|USPS]] package directly into the search box. Results will include quick links to track the status of each shipment.
* patent numbers – U.S. [[patents]] can be searched&lt;ref name=fea/&gt;&lt;ref name=EmU/&gt; by entering the word &quot;patent&quot; followed by the patent number into the search box (such as: Patent 5123123).
* area code – The geographical location (for any U.S. telephone [[area code]])&lt;ref name=fea/&gt; can be displayed by typing a 3-digit area code (such as: 650).
* synonym search – A search can match words similar to those specified,&lt;ref name=fea/&gt; by placing the tilde sign (~) immediately in front of a search term, such as:&amp;nbsp; ~fast food.

===Search options===
The webpages maintained by the Google Help Center have text describing more than 15 various search options.&lt;ref name=&quot;GH&quot;&gt;
 &quot;Google Help Center – Alternate query types&quot;, 2009,
 webpage: [http://www.google.com/help/operators.html G-help].
&lt;/ref&gt;
The Google operators:
* OR – Search for either one, such as &quot;price high OR low&quot; searches for ''&quot;price&quot;'' with ''&quot;high&quot;'' or ''&quot;low&quot;''.
* &quot;-&quot; – Search while excluding a word, such as &quot;apple -tree&quot; searches where word ''&quot;tree&quot;'' is not used.
* &quot;+&quot; – (Removed on 10/19/11&lt;ref name=&quot;Google changes the operators&quot;&gt;[http://www.frag.co.uk/blog/2011/10/googles-changes-the-operators/], Google changes the operators.&lt;/ref&gt;) Force inclusion of a word, such as &quot;Name +of +the Game&quot; to require the words ''&quot;of&quot;'' &amp; ''&quot;the&quot;'' to appear on a matching page.
* &quot;*&quot; – Wildcard operator to match any words between other specific words.

Some of the query options are as follows:
* define: – The query prefix &quot;define:&quot; will provide a definition&lt;ref name=GH/&gt; of the words listed after it.
* stocks: – After &quot;stocks:&quot; the query terms are treated as stock ticker symbols&lt;ref name=GH/&gt; for lookup.
* site: – Restrict the results to those websites in the given domain,&lt;ref name=GH/&gt; such as, site:www.acmeacme.com. The option &quot;site:com&quot; will search all domain URLs named with &quot;.com&quot; (no space after &quot;site:&quot;).
* allintitle: – Only the page titles are searched&lt;ref name=GH/&gt; (not the remaining text on each webpage).
* intitle: – Prefix to search in a webpage title,&lt;ref name=GH/&gt; such as &quot;intitle:google search&quot; will list pages with word &quot;google&quot; in title, and word &quot;search&quot; anywhere (no space after &quot;intitle:&quot;).
* allinurl: – Only the page URL address lines are searched&lt;ref name=GH/&gt; (not the text inside each webpage).
* inurl: – Prefix for each word to be found in the URL;&lt;ref name=GH/&gt; others words are matched anywhere, such as &quot;inurl:acme search&quot; matches &quot;acme&quot; in a URL, but matches &quot;search&quot; anywhere (no space after &quot;inurl:&quot;).

The page-display options (or query types) are:
* cache: – Highlights the search-words within the cached document, such as &quot;cache:www.google.com xxx&quot; shows cached content with word &quot;xxx&quot; highlighted.
* link: – The prefix &quot;link:&quot; will list webpages that have links to the specified webpage, such as &quot;link:www.google.com&quot; lists webpages linking to the Google homepage.
* related: – The prefix &quot;related:&quot; will list webpages that are &quot;similar&quot; to a specified web page.
* info: – The prefix &quot;info:&quot; will display some background information about one specified webpage, such as, info:www.google.com. Typically, the info is the first text (160 bytes, about 23 words) contained in the page, displayed in the style of a results entry (for just the 1 page as matching the search).
* filetype: – results will only show files of the desired type (ex filetype:pdf will return pdf files)

===Error messages===
Some searches will give a 403 Forbidden error with the text
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&quot;We're sorry...

 ... but your query looks similar to automated requests from a computer virus or spyware application. To protect our users, we can't process your request right now.

 We'll restore your access as quickly as possible, so try again soon. In the meantime, if you suspect that your computer or network has been infected, you might want to run a virus checker or spyware remover to make sure that your systems are free of viruses and other spurious software.

 We apologize for the inconvenience, and hope we'll see you again on Google.&quot;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
sometimes followed by a [[CAPTCHA]] prompt.&lt;ref name=&quot;Google error page&quot;&gt;{{cite web| url=http://www.google.com/support/bin/answer.py?answer=15661 | title=Google error page | accessdate=2008-12-31}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Image:Google Server Error.PNG|thumb|right|Google's Server Error page]]

The screen was first reported in 2005, and was a response to the heavy use of Google by [[search engine optimization]] companies to check on ranks of sites they were optimizing. The message is triggered by high volumes of requests from a single IP address. Google apparently uses the [[Google and privacy|Google cookie]] as part of its determination of refusing service.&lt;ref name=&quot;Google error page&quot;/&gt;

In June 2009, after the death of pop superstar [[Michael Jackson]], this message appeared to many internet users who were searching Google for news stories related to the singer, and was assumed by Google to be a [[Denial-of-service attack|DDoS attack]], although many queries were submitted by legitimate searchers.

====January 2009 malware bug====
[[File:Malware.png|thumb|right|A screen-shot of the error of January 31, 2009.]]

Google flags search results with the message &quot;This site may harm your computer&quot; if the site is known to install malicious software in the background or otherwise surreptitiously. Google does this to protect users against visiting sites that could harm their computers. For approximately 40 minutes on January 31, 2009, ''all'' search results were mistakenly classified as [[malware]] and could therefore not be clicked; instead a warning message was displayed and the user was required to enter the requested URL manually. The bug was caused by human error.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|url=http://voices.washingtonpost.com/securityfix/2009/01/google_this_internet_will_harm.html?hpid=news-col-blog|title=Google: This Internet May Harm Your Computer|last=Krebs|first=Brian|date=2009-01-31|publisher=The Washington Post|accessdate=2009-01-31}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;googleblog&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://googleblog.blogspot.com/2009/01/this-site-may-harm-your-computer-on.html|title=This site may harm your computer on every search result?!?!|last=Mayer|first=Marissa|date=2009-01-31|work=The Official Google Blog|publisher=[[Google]]|accessdate=2009-01-31}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;stopbadware&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://blog.stopbadware.org/2009/01/31/google-glitch-causes-confusion|title=Google glitch causes confusion|last=Weinstein|first=Maxim|date=2009-1-31|publisher=StopBadware.org|accessdate=2010-5-10}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://securityblog.verizonbusiness.com/2009/01/31/serious-problems-with-google-search/|title=Serious problems with Google search|last=Cooper|first=Russ|date=January 31, 2009|publisher=Verizon Business Security Blog|accessdate=2010-5-10}}&lt;/ref&gt;&amp;nbsp;The [[URL]] of &quot;/&quot; (which expands to all URLs) was mistakenly added to the malware patterns file.&lt;ref name=&quot;googleblog&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;stopbadware&quot; /&gt;

===Google Doodles===
{{Main|Google logo}}
On certain occasions, the [[Google logo|logo]] on Google's webpage will change to a special version, known as a &quot;Google Doodle&quot;. Clicking on the Doodle links to a string of Google search results about the topic. The first was a reference to the [[Burning Man Festival]] in 1998,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|author=Hwang, Dennis |url=http://googleblog.blogspot.com/2004/06/oodles-of-doodles.html |title=Oodles of Doodles |publisher=[[Google]] (corporate blog) |date=June 8, 2004 |accessdate=July 19, 2006}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Doodle History|url=http://www.google.com/doodle4google/history.html|accessdate=5-10-2010|publisher=Google, Inc.}}&lt;/ref&gt; and others have been produced for the birthdays of notable people like [[Albert Einstein]], historical events like the interlocking [[Lego]] block's 50th anniversary and holidays like [[Valentine's Day]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Google logos:''Valentine's Day logo'' |url=http://www.google.com/logos/valentine07.gif |date=February 14, 2007 |accessdate=April 6, 2007}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Google Caffeine===
In August 2009, Google announced the rollout of a new search architecture, codenamed &quot;Caffeine&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;Harvey&quot;&gt;{{Cite news
 |url=http://technology.timesonline.co.uk/tol/news/tech_and_web/personal_tech/article6792403.ece
 |title=Google unveils new &quot;Caffeine&quot; search engine
 |date=11 August 2009
 |first=Mike
 |last=Harvey
 |publisher=The Times
 |accessdate=14 August 2009
 |location=London
}}&lt;/ref&gt;
The new architecture was designed to return results faster and to better deal with rapidly updated information&lt;ref name=&quot;Lovestowrite&quot;&gt;{{Cite news
 |url=http://www.siivo.com/blog/2010/07/what-does-google-caffeine-mean-for-my-website
 |title=What Does Google &quot;Caffeine&quot; Mean for My Website?
 |date=21 July 2010
 |publisher=Siivo Corp
 |accessdate=21 July 2010
 |location=New York
}}&lt;/ref&gt; from services including [[Facebook]] and [[Twitter]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Harvey&quot;/&gt;
Google developers noted that most users would notice little immediate change, but invited developers to test the new search in its [[Sandbox (computer security)|sandbox]].&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news
 |title=Google introduces new &quot;Caffeine&quot; search system
 |first=Katie
 |last=Culp
 |publisher=Fox News
 |date=12 August 2009
 |accessdate=14 August 2009
 |url=http://www.foxbusiness.com/story/markets/industries/technology/google-introduces-new-caffeine-search/
}} {{Dead link|date=October 2010|bot=H3llBot}}&lt;/ref&gt;
Differences noted for their impact upon [[search engine optimization]] included heavier keyword weighting and the importance of the domain's age.&lt;ref name=&quot;Martin&quot;&gt;{{Cite news
 |url=http://blog.cube3marketing.com/2009/07/31/bing-the-new-search-engine-from-microsoft-and-yahoo/
 |title=Bing - The new Search Engine from Microsoft and Yahoo
 |date=31 July 2009
 |first=Paul
 |last=Martin
 |publisher=Cube3 Marketing
 |accessdate=12 January 2010
}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Paul&quot;&gt;{{Cite news
 |url=http://blog.cube3marketing.com/2009/08/27/caffeine-the-new-google-update/
 |title=Caffeine - The New Google Update
 |date=27 August 2009
 |first=Paul
 |last=Martin
 |publisher=Cube3 Marketing
 |accessdate=12 January 2010
}}&lt;/ref&gt;
The move was interpreted in some quarters as a response to Microsoft's recent release of an upgraded version of its own search service, renamed [[Bing]].&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news
 |first=Emma
 |last=Barnett
 |url=http://www.telegraph.co.uk/technology/google/6009176/Google-reveals-caffeine-a-new-faster-search-engine.html
 |publisher=The Telegraph
 |title=Google reveals caffeine: a new faster search engine
 |date=11 August 2009
 |accessdate=14 August 2009
}}&lt;/ref&gt;
Google announced completion of Caffeine on 8 June 2010, claiming 50% fresher results due to continuous updating of its index.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
 |url=http://googleblog.blogspot.com/2010/06/our-new-search-index-caffeine.html
 |title=Our new search index: Caffeine
 |author=Grimes, Carrie
 |date=8 June 2010
 |work=The Official Google Blog
 |accessdate=18 June 2010
}}&lt;/ref&gt;
With Caffeine, Google moved its back-end indexing system away from [[MapReduce]] and onto [[BigTable]], the company's distributed database platform.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.theregister.co.uk/2010/09/09/google_caffeine_explained/ Google search index splits with MapReduce] – The Register&lt;/ref&gt; Caffeine is also based on Colossus, or GFS2,&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.theregister.co.uk/2009/08/14/google_caffeine_truth/ Google Caffeine: What it really is] – The Register&lt;/ref&gt; an overhaul of the [[Google File System|GFS]] distributed file system.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.theregister.co.uk/2009/08/12/google_file_system_part_deux/ Google File System II: Dawn of the Multiplying Master Nodes] – The Register&lt;/ref&gt;

===Encrypted Search===
In May 2010 Google rolled out SSL-encrypted web search.&lt;ref name=&quot;sslsearch01&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.google.com/support/websearch/bin/answer.py?answer=173733&amp;hl=en |title=SSL Search: Features - Web Search Help |accessdate=2010-07-07 |publisher=Google |work=Web Search Help |year=2010 |month=May}}&lt;/ref&gt; The encrypted search can be accessed at &lt;code&gt;encrypted.google.com&lt;/code&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://encrypted.google.com Encrypted.google.com]&lt;/ref&gt;

== Instant Search ==

Google Instant, a feature that [[Incremental search|displays suggested results while the user types]], was introduced on September 8, 2010.  Google expects Google Instant to save users 2 to 5 seconds in every search, which they say will be collectively 11 million seconds per hour.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite video| people = Peter Nowak| title = Tech Bytes: Google Instant| medium = Television production | publisher = ABC News | location = United States | date = 2010 }}&lt;/ref&gt; Search engine marketing pundits speculate that Google Instant will have a great impact on local and [[paid search]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web| Van Wagner = Spiegel| first = Rachel| title = How Google Saved $100 Million By Launching Google Instant| url=http://searchengineland.com/how-google-saved-100-million-by-launching-google-instant-51270| accessdate = 20 September 2010 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

In concert with the Google Instant launch, Google disabled the ability of users to choose to see more than 10 search results per page. Instant Search can be disabled via Google's &quot;preferences&quot; menu, but [[autocomplete]]-style search suggestions now cannot be disabled. A Google representative stated, &quot;It's in keeping with our vision of a unified Google search experience to make popular, useful features part of the default experience, rather than maintain different versions of Google. As Autocomplete quality has improved, we felt it was appropriate to have it always on for all of our users.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.google.com/support/forum/p/Web+Search/thread?tid=5a69f1094357f31b&amp;hl=en Google Web Search Help Forum] ([http://www.webcitation.org/5sy2ImYdO WebCite archive])&lt;/ref&gt;

The publication [[2600: The Hacker Quarterly]] has compiled a list of words that are restricted by [[Google Instant]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.2600.com/googleblacklist/ 2600.com: Google Blacklist - Words That Google Instant Doesn't Like]&lt;/ref&gt; These are terms the web giant's new instant search feature will not search.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.cnn.com/2010/TECH/web/09/29/google.instant.blacklist.mashable/index.html?eref=mrss_igoogle_cnn CNN: Which words does Google Instant blacklist?]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;huffingtonpost.com&quot;&gt;[http://www.huffingtonpost.com/2010/09/29/google-instant-censorship_n_743203.html The Huffington Post: Google Instant Censorship: The Strangest Terms Blacklisted By Google]&lt;/ref&gt; Most terms are often vulgar and derogatory in nature, but some apparently irrelevant searches including &quot;Myleak&quot; are removed.&lt;ref name=&quot;huffingtonpost.com&quot;/&gt;

== Redesign ==

In late June 2011, Google introduced a new look to the Google home page in order to boost the use of the Google+ social tools.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last=Boulton|first=Clint|title=Google Redesign Backs Social Effort|url=http://www.eweekeurope.co.uk/comment/google-redesign-backs-social-effort-32954|work=eWeek Europe|publisher=eWeek Europe|accessdate=1 July 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

One of the major changes was replacing the classic navigation bar with a black one. Google's digital creative director Chris Wiggins explains: &quot;We're working on a project to bring you a new and improved Google experience, and over the next few months, you'll continue to see more updates to our look and feel.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;[http://latimesblogs.latimes.com/technology/2011/06/google-redesigns-its-homepage-with-new-black-bar-up-top-google-social-network.html Google redesigns its homepage [[Los Angeles Times]]]&lt;/ref&gt; The new navigation bar has been negatively received by a vocal minority.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.google.com/support/forum/p/Web+Search/thread?tid=7ddbf7a4c8fa04a9&amp;hl=en Google support forum, one of many threads on being unable to switch off the black navigation bar]&lt;/ref&gt;

==International==
{{main|List of Google domains}}

Google is available in many languages and has been localized completely or partly for many countries.&lt;ref name=&quot;international&quot;&gt;[http://www.google.com/language_tools?hl=en Language Tools&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;

The interface has also been made available in some languages for humorous purpose:
* [[Swedish Chef|Bork, bork, bork!]]
* [[Elmer Fudd]]
* [[Leetspeak]]
* [[Klingon language|Klingon]]
* [[Pig Latin]]
* [[Talk like a pirate|Pirate]]

In addition to the main URL Google.com, Google Inc. owns 160 domain names for each of the countries/regions in which it has been localized.&lt;ref name=&quot;international&quot; /&gt;

==Search products==
{{Main|List of Google products}}

In addition to its tool for searching [[webpage]]s, Google also provides services for searching [[raster graphics|images]], [[Usenet]] [[newsgroup]]s, news [[websites]], [[Google Video|videos]], searching by locality, maps, and items for sale online. In 2006, Google has indexed over 25 billion web pages,&lt;ref name=gwcds&gt;[http://www.seas.upenn.edu/~zives/cis555/slides/I-Crawlers-Sync.ppt Google, Web Crawling and Distributed Synchronization] p. 11.&lt;/ref&gt; 400 million queries per day,&lt;ref name=&quot;gwcds&quot;/&gt; 1.3 billion images, and over one billion Usenet messages. It also [[cache]]s much of the content that it [[web indexing|indexes]]. Google operates other tools and services including [[Google News]], Google Suggest, [[Google Product Search]], [[Google Maps]], [[Google Co-op]], [[Google Earth]], [[Google Docs]], [[Picasa]], [[Panoramio]], [[YouTube]], [[Google Translate]], [[Google Blog]] Search and [[Google Desktop]] Search.

There are also products available from Google that are not directly search-related. [[Gmail]], for example, is a [[webmail]] application, but still includes search features; [[Google Browser Sync]] does not offer any search facilities, although it aims to organize your browsing time.

Also Google starts many new beta products, like Google Social Search or [[Google Image Swirl]].
&lt;!-- Deleted image removed: [[Image:Google beta.PNG|thumb|left|alt=Google's new Homepage, for random Beta Users]] --&gt;

==Energy consumption==
Google claims that a search query requires altogether about 1 [[Joule|kJ]] or 0.0003 [[Kilowatt hours|kW·h]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://googleblog.blogspot.com/2009/01/powering-google-search.html Blogspot.com], Powering a Google search&lt;/ref&gt;

==See also==
{{Portal|Google}}
* [[Google search features]]
* [[Google Searchology]]
* [[History of Google]]
* [[List of Google domains]]
* [[List of search engines]]
* [[List of Google products]]
* [[Criticism of Google]]
* [[Googlewhack]]
* [[Social graph]]

==References==
&lt;!-- This article uses [[Wikipedia:Footnotes]]. Please use this format when adding references within the article. Any external links directly added to this section will be deleted. --&gt;
{{Reflist|colwidth=30em}}

==Further reading==
* ''[[Google Hacks]]'' from [[O'Reilly Media|O'Reilly]] is a book containing tips about using Google effectively. Now in its third edition. ISBN 0-596-52706-3.
* ''Google: The Missing Manual'' by Sarah Milstein and Rael Dornfest (O'Reilly, 2004). ISBN 0-596-00613-6
* ''How to Do Everything with Google'' by Fritz Schneider, Nancy Blachman, and Eric Fredricksen (McGraw-Hill Osborne Media, 2003). ISBN 0-07-223174-2
* ''Google Power'' by Chris Sherman (McGraw-Hill Osborne Media, 2005). ISBN 0-07-225787-3
* {{Cite journal|last=Barroso |first=Luiz Andre |authorlink= |coauthors=Dean, Jeffrey; Hölzle, Urs |year=2003 |month= |title=Web Search for a Planet: The Google Cluster Architecture |journal=[[IEEE Micro]] |volume=23 |issue=2 |pages=22–28 |doi=10.1109/MM.2003.1196112 |url= |accessdate= |quote= }}

==External links==
* [http://www.google.com Google.com]
* [http://web.archive.org/web/19981111183552/google.stanford.edu/ The Original Google!]

{{Google Inc.}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Google Search}}
&lt;!--categories--&gt;
[[Category:Internet search engines]]
[[Category:American websites]]
[[Category:Multilingual websites]]
[[Category:Google services|Search]]
[[Category:1997 introductions]]

[[am:ጉግል ፍለጋ]]
[[ar:بحث جوجل]]
[[be-x-old:Google search]]
[[bg:Google търсачка]]
[[br:Google (lusker enklask)]]
[[cs:Google (vyhledávač)]]
[[de:Google]]
[[es:Buscador de Google]]
[[fa:جستجوگر گوگل]]
[[fr:Google (moteur de recherche)]]
[[hi:गूगल खोज]]
[[hr:Google (tražilica)]]
[[os:Google]]
[[it:Google]]
[[he:גוגל (מנוע חיפוש)]]
[[sw:Google]]
[[lb:Google]]
[[hu:Google kereső]]
[[mr:गूगल शोध]]
[[ms:Carian Google]]
[[nl:Google]]
[[nds-nl:Google]]
[[ja:Google検索]]
[[no:Google Søk]]
[[oc:Google (motor de recèrca)]]
[[pap:Google]]
[[pl:Wyszukiwarka Google]]
[[pt:Google Search]]
[[ro:Google (motor de căutare)]]
[[ru:Google]]
[[simple:Google Search]]
[[sv:Google (sökmotor)]]
[[te:గూగుల్ శోధన]]
[[th:กูเกิล เสิร์ช]]
[[tr:Google (arama motoru)]]
[[vi:Google Search]]
[[yi:גוגל (זוכמאשין)]]
[[zh:Google搜索]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
