<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="12512655" ns="0" title="GetDeb"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Refimprove|date=August 2010}}
{{Infobox Website
|name           = GetDeb
|logo           = 
|screenshot     =&lt;!-- Deleted image removed:  [[Image:Getdeb-homepage-20070909.png|250px]] --&gt;
|caption        = GetDeb homepage on 2007-08-29.
|url            = [http://www.getdeb.net www.getdeb.net] [http://www.playdeb.net www.playdeb.net]
|alexa          = 
|commercial     = no
|type           = Ubuntu Software Portal
|language       = English
|registration   = No
|owner          = Jo&amp;atilde;o Pinto
|author         = Jo&amp;atilde;o Pinto
|launch date    = 
|current status = 
|revenue        = 
|slogan         =
}}

'''GetDeb''' is an [[Ubuntu (operating system)|Ubuntu]] [[software portal]] with ready-to-install applications in Ubuntu's default [[deb (file format)|package format]]. It was created to simplify the installation of new software for [[Ubuntu (operating system)|Ubuntu]] users. GetDeb focuses both on providing newer versions of software included in Ubuntu and software that is omitted from the official repositories.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://lifehacker.com/5400209/getdebnet-repository-makes-newer-ubuntu-apps-easily-available |title=GetDeb.net Repository Makes Newer Ubuntu Apps Easily Available |publisher=Lifehacker |first=Kevin |last=Purdy |date=November 9, 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt;

'''PlayDeb''' is a sister project to GetDeb, likewise serving the Ubuntu community, but with an explicit focus on games.

The GetDeb and PlayDeb services are also supported in [[Linux Mint]], a prominent Ubuntu derivative with its own utilities.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.linuxmint.com/blog/?p=140 |title=mintInstall to support GetDeb and APT (and CNR?) |publisher=The Linux Mint Blog |author=Clem |date=January 30, 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Purpose ==

As [[Ubuntu (operating system)|Ubuntu]] and [[Debian]] upon which it is based use the [[deb (file format)|deb]] [[Software package (installation)|package]] format, it is easiest to install software packaged in that format. While utilities such as the [[GNU build system]] typically allow users to install or uninstall software after building it from [[source code]], they do not integrate with any one [[Linux distribution]], nor do they solve [[Coupling (computer science)|dependencies]]. Thus, ideally software is installed in a distribution-specific format.

GetDeb and its sister project PlayDeb package software such that it can easily be installed in a user-friendly [[point-and-click]] manner on Ubuntu, removing hurdles for less-technical users.

== Pros and cons ==

GetDeb and PlayDeb serve two primary purposes. They allow Ubuntu users to install software that is not yet included in the main repositories, and offer current versions of many packages that are included in the Ubuntu repositories. The latter is of utility because, due to the release cycle adopted by Ubuntu, most packages will be several months out of date at the time of release, and will not receive feature updates until the next discrete release for stability reasons.

It is generally advisable to run from Ubuntu's own packages where possible, as software offered by GetDeb and PlayDeb has not been extensively tested with the current Ubuntu release. However, in many cases newer versions of software are only omitted from a specific Ubuntu release due to releases typically being static except for security updates. In some cases, software packaged by GetDeb and PlayDeb may be [[Development stage#Beta|beta]] or [[Development stage#Alpha|alpha]] releases.

Additionally, software offered may not conform to the Debian or Ubuntu packaging guidelines. GetDeb and PlayDeb overlap somewhat in purpose with the [[rolling release]] Debian Sid and the Ubuntu Backports repository.

== Downtime ==
In 2010, the server was off-line from February 28 to March 9. GetDeb was also down from May 28 until June 13.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://blog.getdeb.net/2010/05/web-site-and-archive-down-again.html |title=Web site and archive down *again*  |publisher=All about getdeb |first=João |last=Pinto|date=May 28, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; The official blog for GetDeb is updated to reflect maintenance and downtime.

As an [[Ubuntu (operating system)|Ubuntu]] [[software portal]] and repository, the downtime of GetDeb, as with any other repository, can cause problems for users as they cannot install or update software that is provided through GetDeb if the service is unavailable.

== See also ==
* [[deb (file format)]]
* [[Medibuntu]]

== References ==
{{reflist}}

== External links ==
*[http://www.getdeb.net GetDeb]
*[http://wiki.getdeb.net/ GetDeb Wiki]
*[http://blog.getdeb.net GetDeb Blog]
*[http://www.playdeb.net PlayDeb]

{{website-stub}}
{{linux-stub}}

{{Ubuntu}}

[[Category:News websites]]
[[Category:Ubuntu (operating system)]]

[[ca:Getdeb]]
[[it:Getdeb]]
[[simple:Getdeb]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
