<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="1252914" ns="0" title="Indiana Jones and the Kingdom of the Crystal Skull"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Redirect|Indy 4|the arcade game|Indy 4 (arcade game)|the video game which is labeled as Indy 4|Indiana Jones and the Fate of Atlantis}}
{{pp-move-indef}}
{{Infobox film
| name           = Indiana Jones and the&lt;br /&gt;Kingdom of the Crystal Skull
| image          = Kingdomofthecrystalskull.jpg
| caption        = Theatrical release poster
| director       = [[Steven Spielberg]]
| producer       = [[Frank Marshall (film producer)|Frank Marshall]]&lt;br /&gt;[[George Lucas]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Kathleen Kennedy (film producer)|Kathleen Kennedy]]
| screenplay     = [[David Koepp]]
| story          = George Lucas&lt;br /&gt;[[Jeff Nathanson]]
| starring       = [[Harrison Ford]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Shia LaBeouf]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Cate Blanchett]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Karen Allen]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Ray Winstone]]&lt;br /&gt;[[John Hurt]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Jim Broadbent]]
| music          = [[John Williams]]
| cinematography = [[Janusz Kamiński]]
| editing        = [[Michael Kahn (film editor)|Michael Kahn]]
| studio         = [[Lucasfilm|Lucasfilm Ltd.]]
| distributor    = [[Paramount Pictures]]
| released       = {{Film date|2008|5|18|[[Cannes Film Festival|Cannes]]|2008|5|22}}
| runtime        = 122 minutes
| country        = {{Film US}}
| language       = English
| budget         = $185 million
| gross          = $786,636,033&lt;ref name=&quot;BOM&quot;/&gt;
}}
{{DISPLAYTITLE:''Indiana Jones and the Kingdom of the Crystal Skull''}}
'''''Indiana Jones and the Kingdom of the Crystal Skull''''' is a 2008 American [[adventure science fiction]] film. It is the fourth film in the [[Indiana Jones (franchise)|''Indiana Jones'' franchise]], created by [[George Lucas]] and directed by [[Steven Spielberg]]. Released nineteen years after [[Indiana Jones and the Last Crusade|the previous film]], the film acknowledges its star [[Harrison Ford]]'s age by being set in 1957. It pays tribute to the [[B movies (Transition in the 1950s)|science fiction B-movies of the era]], pitting [[Indiana Jones]] against [[Soviet Union|Soviet]] agents—led by Irina Spalko ([[Cate Blanchett]])&amp;mdash;for a psychic alien [[crystal skull]]. Indiana is aided by his former lover [[Marion Ravenwood]] ([[Karen Allen]]) and their son [[Mutt Williams]] ([[Shia LaBeouf]]). [[Ray Winstone]], [[John Hurt]] and [[Jim Broadbent]] are also part of the supporting cast.

Screenwriters [[Jeb Stuart (writer)|Jeb Stuart]], [[Jeffrey Boam]], [[Frank Darabont]] and [[Jeff Nathanson]] wrote drafts before [[David Koepp]]'s script satisfied the producers. Shooting began on June 18, 2007 and took place in various locations: New Mexico, New Haven, Connecticut, Hawaii, Fresno, California and on soundstages in Los Angeles. To keep aesthetic continuity with the previous films the crew relied on traditional stunt work instead of computer-generated stunt doubles and [[cinematographer]] [[Janusz Kamiński]] studied [[Douglas Slocombe]]'s style from the previous films.

Marketing relied heavily on the public's nostalgia for the series, with products taking inspiration from all four films. Anticipation for the film was heightened by secrecy, which resulted in a legal dispute over an extra violating his [[non-disclosure agreement]] and the arrest of another man for stealing a computer containing various documents related to the production. ''Indiana Jones and the Kingdom of the Crystal Skull'' was released worldwide on May 22, 2008, and was a financial success, grossing over $786 million worldwide, becoming the highest-grossing film of the franchise, the second highest-grossing film of 2008 and the third highest-grossing film ever produced by [[Lucasfilm]] when not adjusted for inflation, after ''[[Star Wars Episode I: The Phantom Menace]]'' and ''[[Star Wars Episode III: Revenge of the Sith]]''.

== Plot ==
&lt;!-- Wikipedia:WikiProject Films/Style guidelines states this section's length should be kept around 700 words.--&gt;
In 1957, [[World War II]] hero Indiana Jones and his long-time partner [[List of characters in the Indiana Jones series#Mac|George &quot;Mac&quot; McHale]] are kidnapped by a group of [[Soviet Union|Soviet]] agents led by the mysterious [[List of characters in the Indiana Jones series#Irina Spalko|Colonel Dr. Irina Spalko]]. The Soviets infiltrate a warehouse labeled &quot;[[Area 51|51]]&quot; in [[Nevada]] and force &quot;Dr. Jones&quot; to find a crate containing the remains of an [[Extraterrestrial life|extraterrestrial]] being that [[Roswell UFO incident|crashed ten years prior]] near [[Roswell, New Mexico]]. After finding the crate—its contents possessing [[magnetism|magnetic]] properties—Mac double-crosses Indiana, having been bought off by the Soviets. After a fight with the Soviets, Indiana manages to escape into the desert (though not before the crate containing the [[Ark of the Covenant]] from ''[[Raiders of the Lost Ark]]'' is revealed in the same warehouse); he then stumbles upon a [[Nevada Test Site|nuclear test town]] and survives a nuclear explosion by hiding in a [[lead]]-lined refrigerator. He is later debriefed by the [[Federal Bureau of Investigation|FBI]] because of Mac's Soviet ties. Shortly after returning to [[Marshall College]], Indiana is offered an indefinite leave of absence to avoid being fired because of the incident.

At a train station, Indiana is stopped by [[greaser (subculture)|greaser]] Henry &quot;Mutt&quot; Williams, who tells him that his old colleague [[List of characters in the Indiana Jones series#Harold Oxley|Harold Oxley]] was kidnapped after discovering a [[crystal skull]] in [[Peru]]. Indiana proceeds to tell Mutt the legend of a [[crystal skull]] found in the mystical city of [[El Dorado|Akator]], in which whoever returns the skull to the city would be given control over its supernatural powers. Mutt gives Indiana a letter from his mother, who was also kidnapped, containing a riddle written by Oxley in an ancient [[Indigenous peoples of the Americas|Native American]] language, which leads them to the [[Nazca Lines]] in Peru. There they discover that Oxley was incarcerated in a psychiatric hospital, having suffered a mental breakdown from the powers of the skull, until he was kidnapped by the Soviets. In Oxley's cell, they find clues that lead them to the grave of [[Francisco de Orellana]], a [[Conquistador]] who went missing in the 16th century while searching for Akator. They discover the skull at the grave, with Indiana reasoning that Oxley had hidden it there after finding it.

Shortly afterward, Indiana and Mutt are captured by the Soviets and taken to their camp, where they find Oxley and Mutt's mother, who turns out to be Indiana's old love, Marion Ravenwood, and reveals that Mutt is Indiana's son, Henry Jones III. Spalko believes that the crystal skull belongs to an [[Extraterrestrial life|interdimensional being]] and holds great [[psychic]] power, and reveals that the specimen stolen from the warehouse is also a crystal skull. She also believes that returning the skull to Akator will grant the Soviets the advantage of psychic warfare. Indiana, Marion, Mutt and Oxley manage to escape from the Soviets into the [[Amazon Rainforest|Amazon]]; however, they are recaptured after Indiana falls into a swamp and Oxley fetches the Soviets for help, and with their hands tied taken to the city [[temple]] through the Rainforest. Marion and Indiana argue so much that the Soviet guard finally gags Marion with a cloth. However, Indiana and Mutt manage to overpower him while he does this. Indiana frees himself with a hidden knife of Mutt's. He ungags Marion, then Mutt frees her while Indiana throws out the driver. A fight ensues (displaying Spalko's [[fencing]] prowess), but only after evading the Soviets again during a brush with [[Siafu|siafu ants]], negotiating three waterfalls in a [[Amphibious vehicle|duck]], and nearly being killed by an elusive tribe living in the long-abandoned city, are they able to enter the temple. Mac, who claims to be a [[double agent]] (to Indiana's bewilderment, questioning his loyalty), secretly leaves a trail for the Soviets to follow.

Inside the temple, they find artifacts from several [[Civilization|ancient civilizations]]. Indiana deduces that the creatures were kindred spirits; they too were &quot;[[Ancient astronauts|archaeologists]]&quot; studying the different cultures of [[Earth]]. The five enter a chamber containing the crystal skeletons of thirteen interdimensional beings seated on thrones in a circle, one missing a skull. After the Soviets arrive, Spalko places the skull onto the headless skeleton. They begin communicating to the group through Oxley in an ancient dialect, promising to reward them with a &quot;big gift&quot;; Spalko approaches them and demands to &quot;know everything&quot;. The skeletons grant her request and psychically transfer their collective knowledge into her mind, activating a [[Portals in fiction|portal]] to another dimension. Indiana, Marion, Mutt and the now-sane Oxley escape the temple, but Mac and the other Soviets are sucked into the portal. The skeletons, meanwhile, combine to form a single living interdimensional being which overwhelms Spalko, causing her to disintegrate; her scattered essence is then drawn into the portal. The temple crumbles and reveals a massive fast-spinning [[flying saucer]] slowly rising from the debris (thought to be buried for millennia, the aliens &quot;instructing&quot; the [[human]] ancestors to build a city on top of it to hide it from plain sight); the survivors watch as it hovers in the atmosphere, defying the [[laws of physics]] and disappears into the cosmos in a split second, the &quot;space between spaces&quot;. Indiana, amazed by the spectacle but also overwhelmed by the sudden turn of events, is now happily reconciled with his new family.

Not long afterward, Indiana, now reinstated and made an associate dean at Marshall College, marries Marion. At the wedding's conclusion, a sudden wind bursts through the church doors and blows Indiana's hat onto the floor at Mutt's feet. Mutt picks it up and is about to place it on his head, only to have his father grab and put it on as he and his wife walk down the aisle.

== Cast ==
{{See also|Indiana Jones characters#Introduced in Kingdom of the Crystal Skull|l1=Indiana Jones characters introduced in Kingdom of the Crystal Skull}}
[[File:Indianajones4.jpg|thumb|right|300px|[[Harrison Ford]] during the filming of the movie.]]
* [[Harrison Ford]] reprises the role of [[Indiana Jones|Dr. Henry &quot;Indiana&quot; Jones, Jr.]] To prepare for the role, the 64&lt;!-- don't change, he turned 65 during filming which is after the training--&gt;-year-old Ford spent three hours a day at a gym, practiced with the [[bullwhip]] for two weeks,&lt;ref name=pre/&gt; and relied on a high-protein diet of fish and vegetables.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|title=Indiana Jones 4: A fit Ford|work=Monsters and Critics|date=2007-02-27|url=http://movies.monstersandcritics.com/news/article_1270011.php|accessdate=2008-03-29}}&lt;/ref&gt; Ford had kept fit during the series' hiatus anyway, as he hoped for another film.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news | author = Scott Bowles | title = Here come Harrison (in fine form) and 'Indiana Jones' | publisher = USA Today | date = 2008-02-12 | url = http://www.usatoday.com/life/movies/news/2008-02-12-indiana-jones_N.htm | accessdate=2008-02-14}}&lt;/ref&gt; He performed many of his own stunts because stunt technology had become safer since 1989, and he also felt it improved his performance.&lt;ref name=ford/&gt; He argued, &quot;The appeal of Indiana Jones isn't his youth but his imagination, his resourcefulness. His physicality is a big part of it, especially the way he gets out of tight situations. But it's not all hitting people and falling from high places. My ambition in action is to have the audience look straight in the face of character and not at the back of a capable stuntman's head. I hope to continue that no matter how old I get.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news | title = Space Cowboys and Indianas | publisher = TheRaider.net | date = 2008-04-28 | url = http://www.theraider.net/news/fullstory_miscellaneous.php?id=736 | accessdate=2008-04-30}}&lt;/ref&gt; Ford felt his return would also help American culture be less paranoid about aging (he refused to dye his hair for the role), because of the film's family appeal: &quot;This is a movie which is geared not to [the young] segment of the demographic, an age-defined segment [...] We've got a great shot at breaking the movie demographic constraints.&quot;&lt;ref name=ford&gt;{{cite news|author=Steve Daly|title=Harrison Ford Q&amp;A: Indy speaks!|publisher=Entertainment Weekly|date=2008-04-19|url=http://www.ew.com/ew/article/0,,20192918,00.html|accessdate=2008-04-18}}&lt;/ref&gt; He told Koepp to add more references to his age in the script.&lt;ref name=&quot;Koeppmag&quot;&gt;{{Cite journal |author=Peter N. Chumo II |title=Matinee Magic: David Koepp and Indiana Jones Enter the Kingdom of the Crystal Skull |journal=Creative Screenwriting |volume=15 |issue=3 |year=2008 |month=May/June}}&lt;/ref&gt; Spielberg said Ford was not too old to play Indiana: &quot;When a guy gets to be that age and he still packs the same punch, and he still runs just as fast and climbs just as high, he's gonna be breathing a little heavier at the end of the set piece. And I felt, 'Let's have some fun with that. Let's not hide that.{{'&quot;}}&lt;ref name=titans/&gt; Spielberg recalled the line in ''Raiders'', &quot;It's not the years, it's the mileage,&quot;&lt;ref name=titans/&gt; and felt he could not tell the difference between Ford during the shoots for ''Last Crusade'' and ''Kingdom of the Crystal Skull''.&lt;ref name=&quot;sitdown&quot;/&gt;
[[Image:Marlon Brando - The Wild One (Madame Tussaud).JPG|right|upright|thumb|[[Madame Tussauds]] waxwork exhibit of Brando in ''The Wild One'' albeit with a later 1957/8 model [[Triumph Thunderbird]].]]
* [[Shia LaBeouf]] plays [[List of Indiana Jones characters#Mutt Williams|Henry &quot;Mutt Williams&quot; Jones III]], a motorcycle-riding greaser and Indiana's sidekick and son. The concept of Indiana Jones having offspring was introduced in ''[[The Young Indiana Jones Chronicles]]'', in which Old Indy is shown to have a daughter.&lt;ref&gt;''The Young Indiana Jones Chronicles'', &quot;Ireland, April 1916&quot;&lt;/ref&gt; During development of ''Kingdom of the Crystal Skull'', this idea was incorporated into [[Frank Darabont]]'s script, with Indiana and Marion having a 13-year-old daughter. However, Spielberg found this too similar to ''[[The Lost World: Jurassic Park]]'',&lt;ref name=atomicants&gt;Rinzler, Bouzereau, Chapter 11: &quot;Atomic Ants from Space: May 1989 to June 2007&quot; p. 231–247&lt;/ref&gt; so a son was created instead.&lt;ref name=legend&gt;''Indiana Jones and the Kingdom of the Crystal Skull'' DVD special features: ''The Return of a Legend''&lt;/ref&gt; Koepp credited the character's creation to [[Jeff Nathanson]] and Lucas.&lt;ref name=&quot;Koeppmag&quot;/&gt; Koepp wanted to make Mutt into a nerd, but Lucas refused, explaining he had to resemble [[Marlon Brando]] in ''[[The Wild One]]''; &quot;he needs to be what Indiana Jones' father thought of [him]&amp;nbsp;– the curse returns in the form of his own son&amp;nbsp;– he's everything a father can't stand&quot;.&lt;ref name=atomicants /&gt; LaBeouf was Spielberg's first choice for the role, having been impressed by his performance in ''[[Holes (film)|Holes]]''.&lt;ref name=pre/&gt; Excited at the prospect of being in an Indiana Jones film, LaBeouf signed on without reading the script and did not know what character he would play.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news | author = Anthony Breznican | title = Shia LaBeouf tapped for 'Indy 4' role | publisher = USA Today | date = 2007-04-13 | url = http://www.usatoday.com/life/movies/news/2007-04-12-shia-indiana-jones_N.htm?csp=34 | accessdate = 2007-04-13}}&lt;/ref&gt; He worked out and gained fifteen pounds of muscle for the role,&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news | author = Aaron Parsley | title = Shia LaBeouf: How I'm Getting Buff for Indiana Jones | publisher = People | date = 2007-04-23 | url = http://www.people.com/people/article/0,,20036458,00.html | accessdate=2007-04-24}}&lt;/ref&gt; and also repeatedly watched the other films to get into character.&lt;ref name=shootingstart&gt;{{Cite web | url=http://www.indianajones.com/site/index.html?deeplink=videos/1/v18 | title=New Indy Adventure Begins Shooting | accessdate=2008-04-08 | date=2007-06-18 | publisher=IndianaJones.com}}&lt;/ref&gt; LaBeouf also watched ''[[Blackboard Jungle]]'', ''[[Rebel Without a Cause]]'' and ''[[The Wild One]]'' to get into his character's mindset,&lt;ref name=pre/&gt; copying mannerisms and words from characters in those films, such as the use of a [[switchblade]] as a weapon.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news | author = Nick de Semlyen | title = Shia LaBeouf is Indiana Jones Jr. | publisher = Empire | date = April 2008 | pages = 76}}&lt;/ref&gt; Lucas also consulted on the greaser look, joking that LaBeouf was &quot;sent to the ''[[American Graffiti]]'' school of greaserland.&quot;&lt;ref name=titans/&gt; LaBeouf pulled his [[rotator cuff]] when filming his duel with Spalko, which was his first injury in his career, an injury which worsened throughout filming. He later pulled his groin.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news | author = Shawn Adler | title = Shia Gets Injured On ‘Indy 4,’ Gears Up For ‘Transformers 2’ | publisher = MTV | date = 2008-04-07 | url = http://moviesblog.mtv.com/2008/04/07/shia-gets-injured-on-indy-4-gears-up-for-transformers-2/ | accessdate=2008-04-07}}&lt;/ref&gt;

* [[Cate Blanchett]] plays the villainous Soviet agent [[Irina Spalko]]. Screenwriter David Koepp created the character.&lt;ref name=&quot;Koeppmag&quot;/&gt; Frank Marshall said Spalko continued the tradition of Indiana having a love-hate relationship &quot;with every woman he ever comes in contact with&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;whipcracks&quot;&gt;{{Cite news | author = Anthony Breznican | title = First look: Whip cracks over new 'Indiana Jones' movie | publisher = USA Today | date = 2007-12-09 | url = http://www.usatoday.com/life/movies/news/2007-12-09-indiana-jones_N.htm | accessdate=2007-12-10}}&lt;/ref&gt; Blanchett had wanted to play a villain for a &quot;couple of years&quot;, and enjoyed being part of the Indiana Jones legacy as she loved the previous films.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news | author = Scott Huver | title = Cate Blanchett: The Oscar Nominee On Dylan, Ledger and Indiana Jones | publisher = Hollywood.com | year = 2007 | url = http://www.hollywood.com/feature/Cate_Blanchett_Oscar_Dylan_Ledger_Indiana_Jones/5055256 | accessdate=2008-02-29}}&lt;/ref&gt; Spielberg praised Blanchett as a &quot;master of disguise&quot;, and considers her his favorite Indiana Jones villain for coming up with much of Spalko's characteristics.&lt;ref name=titans&gt;{{cite news | author = Steve Daly | title = Steven Spielberg and George Lucas: The Titans Talk! | publisher = Entertainment Weekly | date = 2008-04-16 | url = http://www.ew.com/ew/article/0,,20192040,00.html | accessdate=2008-04-17}}&lt;/ref&gt; Spalko's [[bob cut]] was her idea, with the character's stern looks and behaviour recalling [[Rosa Klebb]] in ''[[From Russia with Love (film)|From Russia with Love]]''.&lt;ref name=empire/&gt; Blanchett learned to fence for the character, but during filming, Spielberg decided to give Spalko &quot;karate chop&quot; skills.&lt;ref name=notes/&gt; LaBeouf recalled Blanchett was elusive on set, and Ford was surprised when he met her on set outside of costume. He noted, &quot;There's no aspect of her behavior that was not consistent with this bizarre person she's playing.&quot;&lt;ref name=ford/&gt;

* [[Karen Allen]] reprises the role of [[Marion Ravenwood]], under the married name of Marion Williams, who appeared in ''[[Raiders of the Lost Ark]]''. Frank Darabont's script introduced the idea of Marion Ravenwood returning as Indiana's love interest.&lt;ref name=atomicants/&gt; Allen was not aware her character was in the script until Spielberg called her in January 2007, saying, &quot;It's been announced! We're gonna make ''Indiana Jones 4''! And guess what? You're in it!&quot;&lt;ref name=untold&gt;{{cite news | author = Steve Daly | title = Indiana Jones: The Untold Story | publisher = Entertainment Weekly | date = 2008-04-16 | url = http://www.ew.com/ew/article/0,,20192043,00.html | accessdate=2008-04-17}}&lt;/ref&gt; Ford found Allen &quot;one of the easiest people to work with [he's] ever known. She's a completely self-sufficient woman, and that's part of the character she plays. A lot of her charm and the charm of the character is there. And again, it's not an age-dependent thing. It has to do with her spirit and her nature.&quot;&lt;ref name=ford/&gt; Allen found Ford easier to work with on this film, in contrast to the first film, where she slowly befriended the private actor.&lt;ref name=glory&gt;{{cite news | author = Matthew Leyland | title = Fortune and Glory | publisher = Total Film | date = June 2008 | pages = 68–71}}&lt;/ref&gt;

* [[Ray Winstone]] plays George &quot;Mac&quot; McHale, a British agent whom Jones worked alongside in World War II, but has now allied with the Russians due to his financial problems. The character acts as a spin on [[Sallah]] and [[List of characters in the Indiana Jones series#René Belloq|René Belloq]] - Jones's friend and nemesis, respectively, in ''Raiders of the Lost Ark''.&lt;ref name=&quot;villainess&quot;&gt;{{Cite news | author = Shawn Adler | title = 'Indiana Jones' Roles For Cate Blanchett, Ray Winstone Revealed Exclusively To MTV News | publisher = MTV | date = 2007-12-07 | url = http://www.mtv.com/movies/news/articles/1576038/20071207/story.jhtml | accessdate=2007-12-07}}&lt;/ref&gt; Spielberg cast Winstone as he found him &quot;one of the most brilliant actors around&quot;, having seen ''[[Sexy Beast]]''.&lt;ref name=notes&gt;{{cite web | title = About the Production | publisher = Official site | url = http://www.indianajones.com/site/index.html | format = Flash | accessdate=2008-05-14}} To access, click &quot;The Film&quot;&lt;/ref&gt; Winstone tore his [[hamstring]] during filming. &quot;I keep getting these action parts as I’m getting older,&quot; he remarked.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news | author = Kim Gregory | title = Ray Winstone thinks Cate Blanchett is the best actress in the world | publisher = Showbiz Spy | date = 2008-02-15 | url = http://www.showbizspy.com/2008/02/15/ray-winstone-thinks-cate-blanchett-is-the-best-actress-in-the-world/ | accessdate=2008-02-15}}&lt;/ref&gt; Like John Hurt, Winstone wished to see the script prior to committing to the film. In interviews on British TV&lt;ref&gt;&quot;Soccer AM&quot; (Sky Sports 1) and &quot;Friday Night with Jonathan Ross&quot; (BBC1)&lt;/ref&gt; Winstone explained that he was only able to read the script if it was delivered by courier, who waited while he read the script, and returned to the US with the script once Winstone had read it. His reasoning for wanting to read the script was, &quot;If I'm gonna be in it, I want to ''be'' in it.&quot; He gave suggestions to Spielberg, including the idea of Mac pretending to be a [[double agent]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.myparkmag.co.uk/articles/celebrity/ray-winstones-spielberg-suggestions.html|title=Ray Winstone's Spielberg suggestions|work=My Park magazine|date=2008-12-27|accessdate=2008-12-27}}&lt;/ref&gt; He also stated that once filming was completed he had to return the script, such was the secrecy about the film. He was later presented with a copy of the script to keep.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news | title = Friday Night with Jonathan Ross, BBC1, May 23, 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt;

* [[John Hurt]] plays Harold &quot;Ox&quot; Oxley, Mutt's surrogate father and an old friend of Indiana, whom he lost contact with in 1937. Six months prior to the events of the film, he went insane after discovering the crystal skull, which commanded him to return it to Akator. Frank Darabont had suggested Hurt when he was writing the screenplay.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|author=Shawn Adler|title=Frank Darabont Expects Fight Over ‘Indy IV’ Writing Credits|publisher=MTV|date=2007-11-12|url=http://moviesblog.mtv.com/2007/11/12/frank-darabont-expects-fight-over-indy-iv-writing-credits/|accessdate=2007-11-14}}&lt;/ref&gt; The character is inspired by Ben Gunn from ''[[Treasure Island]]''.&lt;ref name=notes/&gt; Hurt wanted to read the script before signing on, unlike other cast members who came on &quot;because Steven&amp;nbsp;— you know, 'God'&amp;nbsp;— was doing it. And I said, 'Well, I need to have a little bit of previous knowledge even if God is doing it.' So they sent a [[courier]] over with the script from Los Angeles, gave it to me at three o'clock in the afternoon in London, collected it again at eight o'clock in the evening, and he returned the next day to Los Angeles.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;peru&quot;&gt;{{Cite news | author = Matt Mueller | title = Q&amp;A Exclusive: John Hurt on 'Indiana Jones and the Kingdom of the Crystal Skull' | publisher = Premiere | date = 2007-12-20 | url = http://www.premiere.com/features/4335/q-a-exclusive-john-hurt-on-indiana-jones-and-the-kingdom-of-the-crystal-skull.html  | accessdate=2008-12-18 |archiveurl = http://web.archive.org/web/20080208231813/http://www.premiere.com/features/4335/q-a-exclusive-john-hurt-on-indiana-jones-and-the-kingdom-of-the-crystal-skull.html |archivedate = 2008-02-08}}&lt;/ref&gt;

* [[Jim Broadbent]] plays Dean Charles Stanforth, an academic colleague and friend of Jones. Broadbent's character stands in for [[Marcus Brody]], whose portrayer, [[Denholm Elliott]], died in 1992.&lt;ref name=notes/&gt; As a tribute to Elliott, the filmmakers put a portrait and a statue on the Marshall College location, and a picture on Jones' desk, saying he died shortly after Indiana's father.

* [[Igor Jijikine]] plays the Russian Colonel Dovchenko. His character stands in for the heavily built henchman [[Pat Roach]] played in the previous films (Roach died in 2004).&lt;ref name=notes/&gt;

[[Joel Stoffer]] and [[Neil Flynn]] have minor roles as FBI agents interrogating Indiana in a scene following the opening sequence. [[Alan Dale]] plays General Ross, who protests his innocence. [[Andrew Divoff]] and [[Pavel Lychnikoff]] play Russian soldiers. Spielberg cast Russian-speaking actors as Russian soldiers so their accents would be authentic.&lt;ref name=&quot;sitdown&quot;&gt;{{Cite news | author = Heather Newgen | title = Spielberg Talks Indy 4, Transformers &amp; Tintin! | publisher = Comingsoon.net | date = 2007-10-10 | url = http://www.comingsoon.net/news/movienews.php?id=38211 | accessdate=2007-10-10}}&lt;/ref&gt; Dimitri Diatchenko plays Spalko's right hand man who battles Indiana at Marshall College. Diatchenko bulked up to 250 pounds to look menacing, and his role was originally minor with ten days of filming. When shooting the fight, Ford accidentally hit his chin, and Spielberg liked Diatchenko's humorous looking reaction, so he expanded his role to three months of filming.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news | author = Army Archerd | title = There's No Biz Like&amp;nbsp;– | publisher = Variety | date = 2008-04-14 | url = http://www.armyarcherd.com/2008/04/theres-no-biz-l.html | accessdate=2008-04-22}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Ernie Reyes, Jr.]] plays a cemetery guard.

[[Sean Connery]] turned down an offer to reprise his role as [[Henry Jones, Sr.]], as he found retirement too enjoyable.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news | author = Lucasfilm | title = The Indiana Jones Cast Expands | publisher = IndianaJones.com | date = 2007-06-07 | url = http://www.indianajones.com/site/index.html?deeplink=news/n13 | accessdate=2008-04-08}}&lt;/ref&gt; Lucas stated that in hindsight it was good that Connery did not briefly appear, as it would disappoint the audience when his character would not come along for the film's adventure.&lt;ref name=&quot;cameo&quot;&gt;{{Cite news | author = Steve Sonsky | title = George Lucas Hails Maverick Filmmakers, Teases Indy 4 | publisher = [[TV Guide]] | date = 2007-09-18 | url = http://www.tvguide.com/news/george-lucas-maverick/070918-01 | accessdate=2007-09-18}}&lt;/ref&gt; Ford joked, &quot;I'm old enough to play my own father in this one.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;ford&quot; /&gt; The film addresses Connery's absence by Indiana mentioning that both Henry, Sr. and Marcus Brody died before the events of this movie. Connery later stated that he liked the film, describing it as &quot;rather good and rather long.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://moviesblog.mtv.com/2009/03/31/sean-connery-reviews-indiana-jones-and-the-kingdom-of-the-crystal-skull/|title=Sean Connery Reviews 'Indiana Jones And The Kingdom Of The Crystal Skull'|date=2009-03-31|first=Jocelyn|last=Vena|publisher=MTV|accessdate=2009-01}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Production ==
=== Development ===
{{Quote_box|width=40%|align=right|quote=&lt;div style=&quot;text-align:left;&quot;&gt;''Indiana Jones and the Saucer Men from Mars'' script by [[Jeb Stuart (writer)|Jeb Stuart]], dated February 20, 1995:
The second draft's prologue is set in [[Borneo]] in 1949, with Indiana proposing to Dr. Elaine McGregor after defeating pirates. She abandons him at the altar, because the government requests her aid in decoding an alien cylinder (covered in Egyptian, Mayan and Sanskrit symbols) in New Mexico. Indiana pursues her, and battles Russians agents and aliens for the cylinder.

The script featured [[army ant]]s, a [[rocket sled]] fight, Indiana surviving an atomic explosion by sealing himself in a fridge, and a climactic battle between the US military and flying saucers. Henry Jones, Sr., [[Short Round]], Sallah, Marion Ravenwood and [[Willie Scott (Indiana Jones character)|Willie]] cameo at Indiana and Elaine's wedding(s). Indiana is also a former colonel and was assigned to the [[Office of Strategic Services|OSS]] during World War II.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news | author = Bellosh | title = Raiders of the Lost Drafts | publisher = TheRaider.net | date = 2001-01-16 | url = http://www.theraider.net/features/articles/lost_drafts_05.php | accessdate=2008-04-18}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;/div&gt;}}

During the late 1970s, [[George Lucas]] and [[Steven Spielberg]] made a deal with [[Paramount Pictures]] for five Indiana Jones films.&lt;ref&gt;Rinzler, Bouzereau, p. 36&lt;/ref&gt; Following the 1989 release of ''[[Indiana Jones and the Last Crusade]]'', Lucas let the series end as he felt he could not think of a good [[plot device]] to drive the next installment, and chose instead to produce ''The Young Indiana Jones Chronicles'' for TV, which explored the character in his early years.&lt;ref name=atomicants /&gt; Harrison Ford played Indiana in one episode, narrating his adventures in 1920 Chicago. When Lucas shot Ford's role in December 1992, he realized the scene opened up the possibility of a film with an older Indiana set in the 1950s. The film could reflect a science fiction 1950s B-movie, with aliens as the plot device.&lt;ref name=atomicants /&gt; Meanwhile, Spielberg believed he was going to &quot;mature&quot; as a filmmaker after making the trilogy, and felt he would just produce any future installments.&lt;ref name=legend/&gt;

Ford disliked the new angle, telling Lucas, &quot;No way am I being in a Steven Spielberg movie like that.&quot;&lt;ref name=untold /&gt; Spielberg himself, who depicted aliens in ''[[Close Encounters of the Third Kind]]'' and ''[[E.T. the Extra-Terrestrial]]'', resisted it. Lucas came up with a story, which Jeb Stuart turned into a script from October 1993 to May 1994.&lt;ref name=atomicants/&gt; (Stuart had previously written ''The Fugitive,'' which starred Ford.) Lucas wanted Indiana to get married, which would allow Henry Jones, Sr. to return, expressing concern over whether his son is happy with what he has accomplished. After he learned that [[Joseph Stalin]] was interested in psychic warfare, he decided to have Russians as the villains and the aliens to have psychic powers.&lt;ref name=commentary&gt;Rinzler, Bouzereau, &quot;Script draft by David Koepp summary and commentary: April 23, 2007&quot;, p. 248–255&lt;/ref&gt; Following Stuart's next draft, Lucas hired ''Last Crusade'' writer [[Jeffrey Boam]] to write the next three versions, the last of which was completed in March 1996. Three months later, ''[[Independence Day (film)|Independence Day]]'' was released, and Spielberg told Lucas he would not make another alien invasion film. Lucas decided to focus on the ''Star Wars'' prequels''.&lt;ref name=atomicants /&gt;

In 2000, Spielberg's son asked when the next Indiana Jones film would be released, which made him interested in reviving the project.&lt;ref name=&quot;curse&quot;&gt;{{Cite news | author = Ann Donahue | title = Indiana Jones and the Curse of Development Hell | publisher = [[Premiere (magazine)|Premiere]] |date=January 2007}}&lt;/ref&gt; The same year, Ford, Lucas, Spielberg, [[Frank Marshall (film producer)|Frank Marshall]] and [[Kathleen Kennedy (film producer)|Kathleen Kennedy]] met during the [[American Film Institute]]'s tribute to Ford, and decided they wanted to enjoy the experience of making an Indiana Jones film again. Spielberg also found returning to the series a respite from his many dark films during this period, such as ''A.I.: Artificial Intelligence,'' ''Minority Report,'' and ''Munich''.&lt;ref name=glory/&gt; Lucas convinced Spielberg to use aliens in the plot by saying they were not &quot;extraterrestrials,&quot; but &quot;[[Multiverse|interdimensional]],&quot; with this concept taking inspiration in the [[superstring theory]].&lt;ref name=legend/&gt; Spielberg and Lucas discussed the central idea of a B-movie involving aliens, and Lucas suggested using the [[crystal skull]]s to ground the idea. Lucas found those artifacts as fascinating as the [[Ark of the Covenant]],&lt;ref name=keys&gt;{{Cite news | author = Jim Windolf | title = Keys to the Kingdom | publisher = [[Vanity Fair (magazine)|Vanity Fair]] | date = February 2008 | url = http://www.vanityfair.com/culture/features/2008/02/indianajones200802 | accessdate=2008-01-02}}&lt;/ref&gt; and had intended to feature them for a ''Young Indiana Jones'' episode before the show's cancellation.&lt;ref name=atomicants/&gt; [[M. Night Shyamalan]] was hired to write for an intended 2002 shoot,&lt;ref name=&quot;curse&quot; /&gt; but he was overwhelmed writing a sequel to a film he loved like ''[[Raiders of the Lost Ark]]'', and claimed it was difficult to get Ford, Spielberg and Lucas to focus.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news | author = Patrick Lee | title = M. Night Shyamalan had a sense that all ''Signs'' pointed to Mel Gibson | publisher = ''Science Fiction Weekly'' | date = 2002-08-05 | url = http://www.scifi.com/sfw/interviews/sfw8748.html | accessdate = 2007-07-17 |archiveurl = http://web.archive.org/web/20071011135930/http://scifi.com/sfw/interviews/sfw8748.html |archivedate = October 11, 2007}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Stephen Gaghan]] and [[Tom Stoppard]] were also approached.&lt;ref name=&quot;curse&quot;/&gt;

[[Frank Darabont]], who wrote various ''Young Indiana Jones'' episodes, was hired to write in May 2002.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news | author = Ken Plume | title = IGN FilmForce Exclusive: Has Indy IV Found Its Writer? | publisher = [[IGN]] | date = 2002-05-17 | url = http://uk.movies.ign.com/articles/359/359715p1.html | accessdate = 2007-01-02}}&lt;/ref&gt; His script, entitled ''Indiana Jones and the City of Gods'',&lt;ref name=atomicants/&gt; was set in the 1950s, with [[Ex-Nazi Party members|ex-Nazis]] pursuing Jones.&lt;ref name=&quot;notfatherson&quot;&gt;{{Cite news | author = Jim Windolf | title = Q&amp;A: Steven Spielberg | publisher = [[Vanity Fair (magazine)|Vanity Fair]] | date = 2007-12-02 | url = http://www.vanityfair.com/culture/features/2008/02/spielberg_qanda200802 | accessdate=2007-12-02}}&lt;/ref&gt; Spielberg conceived the idea because of real life figures such as [[Juan Perón]] in [[Argentina]], who protected Nazi war criminals.&lt;ref name=atomicants/&gt; Darabont claimed Spielberg loved the script, but Lucas had issues with it, and decided to take over writing himself.&lt;ref name=atomicants/&gt; Lucas and Spielberg acknowledged the 1950s setting could not ignore the [[Cold War]], and the Russians were more plausible villains. Spielberg decided he could not satirize the Nazis after directing ''[[Schindler's List]]'',&lt;ref name=titans/&gt; while Ford noted, &quot;We plum[b] wore the Nazis out.&quot;&lt;ref name=untold/&gt;

[[Jeff Nathanson]] met with Spielberg and Lucas in August 2004, and turned in the next drafts in October and November 2005, titled ''The Atomic Ants''. [[David Koepp]] continued on from there, giving his script the subtitle ''Destroyer of Worlds'',&lt;ref name=atomicants/&gt; based on the [[J. Robert Oppenheimer]] quote. It was changed to ''Kingdom of the Crystal Skull'', as Spielberg found it more inviting a title and actually named the plot device of the crystal skulls. Lucas insisted on the ''Kingdom'' part.&lt;ref name=wild&gt;Rinzler, Bouzereau, Chapter 12: &quot;Mr. Jones's Wild Ride: June to December 2007&quot;, p. 254–295&lt;/ref&gt; Koepp's &quot;bright [title] idea&quot; was ''Indiana Jones and the Son of Indiana Jones'', and Spielberg had also considered having the title name the aliens as ''[[The Mysterians]]'', but dropped that when he remembered that was the name of a film.&lt;ref name=legend/&gt; Koepp collaborated with ''Raiders of the Lost Ark'' screenwriter [[Lawrence Kasdan]] on the film's &quot;love dialogue.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;Koeppmag&quot; /&gt;

=== Filming ===
[[Image:Indiana Jones and the Kingdom of the Crystal Skull.jpg|thumb|The production crew converts a storefront in downtown New Haven, Connecticut to be used in a scene set in the 1950s.]]
Unlike the previous Indiana Jones films, Spielberg shot the entire film in the United States, stating he did not want to be away from his family.&lt;ref name=lucasqaa/&gt; Shooting began on June 18, 2007&lt;ref name=&quot;shootingstart&quot; /&gt; at [[Deming, New Mexico]].&lt;ref name=&quot;isle&quot;&gt;{{Cite news | author=John Burnett | title=Ford lands on Big Isle | publisher=Hawaii Tribune-Herald | date=2007-07-11 | url=http://www.hawaiitribune-herald.com/articles/2007/07/11/local_news/local07.txt | accessdate=2007-07-17}}&lt;/ref&gt; An extensive chase scene set at Indiana Jones's fictional Marshall College was filmed between June 28 and July 7 at [[Yale University]] in New Haven, Connecticut (where Spielberg's son Theo was studying).&lt;ref name=&quot;isle&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;path&quot;&gt;{{Cite news | author=Ed Stannard | title=Casting call creates excitement far and wide | publisher=New Haven Register | date=2007-06-04}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=fandango/&gt; To keep in line with the fact the story takes place in the 1950s, several facades were changed, although signs were put up in between shots to tell the public what the store or restaurant actually was.

[[Image:HarrisonShiaSkullNewHaven.jpg|thumb|left|Harrison Ford and Shia LaBeouf's stunt doubles during filming in 2007 in New Haven, Connecticut.]]
Afterwards, they filmed scenes set in the Peruvian jungles in Hilo, Hawaii until August.&lt;ref name=fandango&gt;{{cite web | title = Indy’s Worldwide Trek | publisher = Fandango | url = http://summermovies.fandango.com/roadtrips/index.php?show=0&amp;artid=27 | accessdate=2008-05-09}}&lt;/ref&gt; ''Indiana Jones and the Kingdom of the Crystal Skull'' is the biggest film shot in Hawaii since ''[[Waterworld]]'', and was estimated to generate [[United States dollar|$]]22 million to $45 million in the local economy.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news | author = Kevin Dayton | title = 'Indiana Jones' having big impact on the Big Island | publisher = The Honolulu Advertiser | date = 2007-07-14 | url = http://the.honoluluadvertiser.com/article/2007/Jul/14/ln/FP707140318.html | accessdate=2007-07-17}}&lt;/ref&gt; Because of an [[Hurricane Flossie (2007)|approaching hurricane]], Spielberg was unable to shoot a fight at a waterfall, so he sent the [[second unit]] to film shots of [[Brazil]]'s and [[Argentina]]'s [[Iguazu Falls]]. These were digitally combined into the fight, which was shot at the [[Universal Studios Hollywood|Universal]] backlot.&lt;ref name=fandango/&gt;

Half the film was scheduled to shoot on five sound stages at Los Angeles:&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news | author = Jamyes Song | title = Ford can still fit into Indy's trousers | publisher =[USA Today | date = 2007-07-14 | url = http://www.usatoday.com/life/movies/2007-07-14-4032861888_x.htm | accessdate=2007-09-30}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Downey, California|Downey]], [[Sony Pictures Studios|Sony]], [[Warner Bros.]], [[Paramount Pictures|Paramount]] and [[Universal Studios Hollywood|Universal]].&lt;ref name=peru/&gt; Filming moved to [[Fresno Chandler Executive Airport|Chandler Field]] in [[Fresno, California]], substituting for [[Mexico City International Airport]], on October 11, 2007.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news | author = Maureen Naylor | title = Indiana Jones Will Be Filmed in Fresno | publisher = ABC30 | date = 2007-10-09 | url = http://abclocal.go.com/kfsn/story?section=local&amp;id=5699055 | accessdate=2007-10-10}}&lt;/ref&gt; After shooting aerial shots of Chandler Airport and a [[Douglas DC-3|DC-3]] on the morning of October 12, 2007, filming wrapped.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news | title = A Hollywood Movie Crew Is Leaving Fresno | publisher = ABC30 | date = 2007-10-12 | url = http://abclocal.go.com/kfsn/story?section=local&amp;id=5704653 | accessdate=2007-10-12}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=windingdown&gt;{{Cite news | author = Todd Gilchrist, Eric Moro | title = Indy IV Winding Down | publisher = IGN | date = 2007-10-09 | url = http://movies.ign.com/articles/826/826026p1.html | accessdate=2007-10-10}}&lt;/ref&gt; Although he originally found no need for re-shoots after viewing his first cut of the film,&lt;ref name=&quot;notfatherson&quot; /&gt; Spielberg decided to add an [[establishing shot]], which was filmed on February 29, 2008 at [[Pasadena, California]].&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news | title = Indiana Jones 4 Reshoots? | publisher = SlashFilm | date = 2008-02-27 | url = http://www.slashfilm.com/2008/02/27/indiana-jones-4-reshoots/ | accessdate=2008-02-29}}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Design ===
Spielberg and [[Janusz Kamiński]], who has shot all of the director's films since 1993's ''Schindler's List'', reviewed the previous films to study [[Douglas Slocombe]]'s style. &quot;I didn’t want Janusz to modernize and bring us into the 21st century,&quot; Spielberg explained. &quot;I still wanted the film to have a lighting style not dissimilar to the work Doug Slocombe had achieved, which meant that both Janusz and I had to swallow our pride. Janusz had to approximate another cinematographer's look, and I had to approximate this younger director's look that I thought I had moved away from after almost two decades.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;keys&quot; /&gt; Spielberg also hired production designer [[Guy Hendrix Dyas]] after admiring his design work for ''[[Superman Returns]]''. Spielberg did not want to [[fast cutting|fast cut]] action scenes, relying on his script instead for a fast pace,&lt;ref name=&quot;keys&quot; /&gt; and had confirmed in 2002 that he would not shoot the film digitally, a format Lucas had adopted.&lt;ref name=&quot;lie&quot;&gt;{{Cite news | title = Come Lie With Me | pages= 80–1 | publisher = [[Empire (magazine)|Empire]] | date=2003-01-03}}&lt;/ref&gt; Lucas felt &quot;it looks like it was shot three years after ''Last Crusade''. The people, the look of it, everything. You’d never know there was 20 years between shooting.&quot;&lt;ref name=lucasqaa&gt;{{cite news | author = Jim Windolf | title = Q&amp;A: George Lucas | publisher = [[Vanity Fair (magazine)|Vanity Fair]] | date = 2008-01-02 | url = http://www.vanityfair.com/culture/features/2008/02/lucas_qanda200802?currentPage=4 | accessdate=2007-01-02}}&lt;/ref&gt; Kamiński commented upon watching the three films back-to-back, he was amazed how each of them advanced technologically, but were all nevertheless consistent, neither too brightly or darkly lit.&lt;ref name=pre&gt;''Pre-production'' DVD featurette, 2008&lt;/ref&gt;

While shooting ''[[War of the Worlds (2005 film)|War of the Worlds]]'' in late 2004, Spielberg met with stunt coordinator [[Vic Armstrong]], who doubled for Ford in the previous films, to discuss three action sequences he had envisioned.&lt;ref name=&quot;race against time&quot;&gt;{{Cite news | author=Nick de Semlyen, Ian Freer, Chris Hewitt, Ian Nathan, Sam Toy | title = A Race Against Time: Indiana Jones IV | pages = 100 | publisher = [[Empire (magazine)|Empire]] | date=2006-09-29}}&lt;/ref&gt; However, Armstrong was filming ''[[The Mummy: Tomb of the Dragon Emperor]]'' during shooting of ''Kingdom of the Crystal Skull'', so [[Dan Bradley]] was hired instead.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news | title = Is Dan Bradley stunt coordinator for Indy 4? | publisher = TheRaider.net | date = 2007-09-04 | url = http://www.theraider.net/news/fullstory_indy4.php?id=308 | accessdate=2007-09-11}}&lt;/ref&gt; Bradley and Spielberg used [[previsualization]] for all the action scenes, except the motorcycle chase at Marshall College, because that idea was conceived after the animators had left. Bradley drew traditional [[storyboard]]s instead, and was given free rein to create dramatic moments, just as ''Raiders of the Lost Ark'' [[second unit]] director [[Michael D. Moore]] did when filming the truck chase.&lt;ref name=empire&gt;{{cite news | author = [[Ian Freer]] | title = The Kingdom of the Crystal Skull | publisher = [[Empire (magazine)|Empire]] | date = May 2008 | pages = 80&amp;nbsp;– 82}}&lt;/ref&gt; Spielberg improvised on set, changing the location of Mutt and Spalko's duel from the ground to on top of vehicles.&lt;ref name=pre/&gt;

The [[Ark of the Covenant]] is seen in a broken crate during the Hangar 51 opening sequence. Lucasfilm used the same prop from ''[[Raiders of the Lost Ark]]''. Guards were hired to protect the highly-sought after piece of film memorabilia during the day of its use. A replica of the staff carried by [[Charlton Heston]] in ''[[The Ten Commandments (1956 film)|The Ten Commandments]]'' was also used to populate the set to illustrate the Hangar's history.&lt;ref name=wild/&gt;

=== Effects ===
[[Image:IJandthefakeleaves.jpg|thumb|250px|Stunts involving vehicles were shot on location in Hawaii, while CGI was used to add plants to the forest]]
Producer Frank Marshall stated in 2003 that the film would use traditional stunt work so as to be consistent with the previous films.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news | title = Exclusive: B-Movie Feel For Indy IV | publisher = [[Empire (magazine)|Empire]] | date=2003-09-09 | url=http://www.empireonline.com/news/story.asp?nid=11918|accessdate=2007-02-28}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Computer-generated imagery|CGI]] was used to remove the visible safety wires on the actors when they did their stunts (such as when Indy swings on a lamp with his whip).&lt;ref name=empire/&gt; Timed explosives were used for a scene where Indiana drives a truck through crates. During the take, an explosive failed to detonate and landed in the seat beside Ford. However, it did not go off and he was not injured.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news | author = Chrissy Iley | title = Keeping up with Indiana Jones | publisher = [[The Observer]] | date = 2008-04-27 | url = http://film.guardian.co.uk/interview/interviewpages/0,,2275988,00.html | accessdate=2008-04-30 | location=London}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Steven Spielberg stated before production began that very few CGI effects would be used to maintain consistency with the other films. During filming however, significantly more CGI work was done than initially anticipated as in many cases it proved to be more practical. There ended up being a total of about 450 CGI shots in the film, with an estimated 30 percent of the film's shots containing CG [[matte painting]]s.&lt;ref name=windingdown/&gt; Spielberg initially wanted brushstrokes to be visible on the paintings for added consistency with the previous films, but decided against it.&lt;ref name=untold/&gt; The script also required a non-deforested jungle for a chase scene, but this would have been unsafe and much CGI work was done to create the jungle action sequence. [[Visual effects supervisor]] Pablo Helman (who worked on Lucas' ''[[Star Wars Episode I: The Phantom Menace]]'' and ''[[Star Wars Episode II: Attack of the Clones]]'' as well as Spielberg's ''[[War of the Worlds (2005 film)|War of the Worlds]]'' and ''[[Munich (film)|Munich]]'') traveled to Brazil and Argentina to photograph elements that were composited into the final images. Industrial Light and Magic then effectively created a virtual jungle with a geography like the real Amazon.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news | author = Derrik J. Lang/[[Associated Press]] | title = 'Indiana Jones' and the computer-generated jungle | work = [[Seattle Times]] | date = 2008-05-22 | url = http://seattletimes.nwsource.com/html/movies/2004430694_apfilmindyeffects.html | accessdate=2008-10-11}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The appearance of a live alien and flying saucer was in flux. Spielberg wanted the alien to resemble a [[Gray alien]], and also rejected early versions of the saucer that looked &quot;too ''[[Close Encounters of the Third Kind|Close Encounters]]''&quot;. Art director Christian Alzmann said the aesthetic was &quot;looking at a lot of older B-movie designs&amp;nbsp;– but trying to make that look more real and gritty to fit in with the Indy universe.&quot; Other reference for the visual effects work included government tapes of nuclear tests, and video reference of real [[prairie dog]]s shot in 1080p by Nathan Edward Denning.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|author=Patrick Kolan|title=The Indiana Jones 4 Post-Mortem|work=[[IGN]]|date=2008-10-29|url=http://uk.dvd.ign.com/articles/925/925408p1.html|accessdate=2008-10-30}}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Music ===
{{Main|Indiana Jones and the Kingdom of the Crystal Skull (soundtrack)}}
[[John Williams]] began composing the score in October 2007;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news | title = News, Etc. | publisher = [[Empire (magazine)|Empire]] | date = March 2008 | pages = 16–17}}&lt;/ref&gt; ten days of recording sessions wrapped on March 6, 2008 at [[Sony Pictures Studios]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news | title = 'Indy 4' Recording Sessions are Over | publisher = jwfan.com | date = 2008-03-06 | url = http://www.jwfan.com/index.php?option=com_content&amp;task=view&amp;id=939&amp;Itemid=1 | accessdate=2008-03-09}}&lt;/ref&gt; Williams described composing for the Indiana Jones universe again as &quot;like sitting down and finishing a letter that you started 25 years ago&quot;. He reused Indiana's theme as well as Marion's from the first film, and also composed five new motifs for Mutt, Spalko and the skull. Williams gave Mutt's a swashbuckling feel, and homaged [[film noir]] and 1950s B-movies for Spalko and the crystal skull respectively. As an in-joke, Williams incorporated a [[bar (music)|measure]] and a half of [[Johannes Brahms]]' &quot;[[Academic Festival Overture]]&quot; when Indiana and Mutt crash into the library.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.variety.com/article/VR1117997973.html|title=John Williams|author=Jon Burlingame|work=[[Variety (magazine)|Variety]]|date=2009-01-05|accessdate=2009-01-20}}&lt;/ref&gt; The soundtrack features a [[Continuum (instrument)|Continuum]], an instrument often used for sound effects instead of music.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news | author = Peter Kim | title = 'Indiana Jones' movie to use professor's musical invention | publisher = [[Daily Illini]] | date = 2008-03-05 | url = http://media.www.dailyillini.com/media/storage/paper736/news/2008/03/05/News/indiana.Jones.Movie.To.Use.Professors.Musical.Invention-3251800.shtml | accessdate=2008-05-06}}&lt;/ref&gt; The [[Concord Music Group]] released [[Indiana Jones and the Kingdom of the Crystal Skull (soundtrack)|the soundtrack]] on May 20, 2008.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | title = Kingdom of the Crystal Skull soundtrack | publisher = MovieMusic | url = http://www.moviemusic.com/soundtrack/indianajones4 | accessdate=2008-04-01}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Release ==
''Indiana Jones and the Kingdom of the Crystal Skull'' premiered at the [[Cannes Film Festival]] on May 18, 2008, ahead of its worldwide May 22 release date. It was the first Spielberg film since 1982's ''[[E.T. the Extra-Terrestrial]]'' to premiere at Cannes.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news | author = Tatiana Siegel, Anne Thompson | title = Cannes premiere for 'Indiana Jones' | publisher = [[Variety (magazine)|Variety]] | date = 2007-02-28 | url = http://www.variety.com/article/VR1117981645.html?categoryid=13&amp;cs=1 | accessdate=2008-02-29}}&lt;/ref&gt; The film was released in approximately 4000 theaters in the United States, and dubbed into 25 languages for its worldwide release.&lt;ref name=&quot;keys&quot; /&gt; More than 12,000 [[release print]]s were distributed, which is the largest in [[Paramount Pictures]]' history.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news | author = Stephanie Sanchez | title = Indiana Jones Second Trailer Coming! | publisher = IESB | date = 2008-03-10 | url = http://www.iesb.net/index.php?option=com_content&amp;task=view&amp;id=4496&amp;Itemid=99 | accessdate=2008-03-11}}&lt;/ref&gt; Although Spielberg insisted his films only be watched traditionally at theaters, Paramount chose to release the film in [[digital cinema]]s as part of a scheme to convert 10,000 U.S. cinemas to the format.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news | author = David M. Halbfinger | title = Studios Announce a Deal to Help Cinemas Go 3-D | publisher = [[New York Times]] | date = 2008-03-12 | url = http://www.nytimes.com/2008/03/12/movies/12scre.html?_r=1&amp;ref=movies&amp;oref=slogin | accessdate=2008-03-12}}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Secrecy ===
Frank Marshall remarked, &quot;In today's information age, secrecy has been a real challenge. [...] People actually said, 'No, we're going to respect Steven's vision.&quot; Fans on the internet have scrutinized numerous photos and the film's promotional [[LEGO]] sets in hope of understanding plot details; Spielberg biographer [[Ian Freer]] wrote, &quot;What ''Indy IV'' is actually about has been the great cultural guessing game of 2007/08. Yet, it has to be said, there is something refreshing about being ten weeks away from a giant blockbuster and knowing next to nothing about it.&quot;&lt;ref name=empire/&gt; To distract investigative fans from the film's title during filming,&lt;ref name=&quot;decision&quot;&gt;{{Cite news | author = Robert Sanchez | title = IESB Chats with The Master&amp;nbsp;— Steven Spielberg! | publisher = IESB | date = 2008-10-09 | url = http://www.iesb.net/index.php?option=com_content&amp;task=view&amp;id=3450&amp;Itemid=99 | accessdate=2008-02-09}}&lt;/ref&gt; five fake titles were registered with the [[Motion Picture Association of America]]; ''The City of Gods'', ''The Destroyer of Worlds'', ''The Fourth Corner of the Earth'', ''The Lost City of Gold'' and ''The Quest for the Covenant''.&lt;ref name=&quot;titles&quot;&gt;{{Cite news | title = The 25 Most Exciting Movies of 2008 | publisher = [[Empire (magazine)|Empire]] | url = http://www.empireonline.com/features/25_most_exciting_movies_of_2008/default.asp | accessdate=2008-02-09}}&lt;/ref&gt; Lucas and Spielberg had also wanted to keep Karen Allen's return a secret until the film's release, but decided to confirm it at the 2007 [[Comic-Con International|Comic-Con]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | author = | title = Indiana casting a surprise for Allen | publisher = [[Television New Zealand]] | url = http://tvnz.co.nz/view/page/411749/1764589 | accessdate=2008-05-06}}&lt;/ref&gt;

An extra in the film, Tyler Nelson, violated his [[nondisclosure agreement]] in an interview with ''[[The Edmond Sun]]'' on September 17, 2007, which was then picked up by the mainstream media. It is unknown if he remained in the final cut.&lt;ref name=&quot;Tyler Nelson&quot;&gt;{{Cite news|url=http://news.sky.com/skynews/article/0,,30200-1286762,00.html|title=Court Adventure for Indiana Jones|publisher=[[Sky News]]|date=2007-10-03|accessdate=2007-10-03}}&lt;/ref&gt; At Nelson's request, ''The Edmond Sun'' subsequently pulled the story from its website.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news | title = Extra! Extra! Dancing Russian spills beans on Indy secrets | publisher = [[The Guardian]] | date = 2007-09-30 | url = http://film.guardian.co.uk/news/story/0,,2173056,00.html | accessdate=2007-09-29 | location=London}}&lt;/ref&gt; On October 2, 2007, a [[Superior Court]] order was filed finding that Nelson knowingly violated the agreement. The terms of the settlement were not disclosed.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news | title = 'Indiana Jones' lawsuit settled | url = http://www.usatoday.com/life/movies/news/2007-10-03-indiana-jones-settlement_N.htm?csp=34 | publisher = [[USA Today]] | date = 2007-10-03 | accessdate=2007-10-03}}&lt;/ref&gt; A number of production photos and sensitive documents pertaining to the film's production budget were also stolen from [[Steven Spielberg]]’s production office. The [[Los Angeles County Sheriff's Department]] set up a [[sting operation]] after being alerted by a webmaster that the thief might try to sell the photos. On October 4, 2007, the seller, 37-year old Roderick Eric Davis, was arrested. He pleaded guilty to two felony counts and was sentenced to two years and four months in prison.&lt;ref name=empire/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|url=http://uk.reuters.com/article/filmNews/idUKN0245764420071003|title=Police probe &quot;Indiana Jones&quot; theft mystery: report |publisher=[[Reuters]]|date=2007-10-03|accessdate=2007-10-03}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|url=http://www.iht.com/articles/ap/2007/11/02/arts/NA-A-E-MOV-US-Indiana-Jones-Theft.php|title=Man pleads guilty in theft of 'Indiana Jones' movie materials|publisher=[[International Herald Tribune]]|date=2007-11-02|accessdate=2007-11-02}}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Marketing ===
{{For|a broader view of the franchise's revival in 2008|Indiana Jones franchise}}
Howard Roffman, President of Lucas Licensing, attributed the film's large marketing campaign to it having been &quot;nineteen years since the last film, and we are sensing a huge pent-up demand for everything Indy&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;merch&quot;&gt;{{Cite news | title = Indy Backed By Major Companies in Global Licensing and Promotional Program | publisher = IndianaJones.com | date = 2007-06-18 | url = http://www.indianajones.com/site/index.html?deeplink=news/n12 | accessdate=2007-06-18}}&lt;/ref&gt; Paramount spent at least $150 million to promote the film,&lt;ref name=treasure/&gt; whereas most film promotions range from $70 to 100 million. As well as fans, the film also needed to appeal to younger viewers.&lt;ref name=inescapable&gt;{{cite news | author = Mary Ellen Podmolik | title = Indiana Jones and the inescapable ads | publisher = [[Chicago Tribune]] | date = 2008-05-09 | url = http://www.chicagotribune.com/business/chi-sat_indiana_jones_marketingmay10,0,7087607.story | accessdate=2008-05-11}}&lt;/ref&gt; Licensing deals include [[Expedia]], [[Dr Pepper]], [[Burger King]], [[M&amp;M's]] and [[Lunchables]].&lt;ref name=inescapable/&gt; Paramount sponsored an Indiana Jones [[open wheel car]] for [[Marco Andretti]] in the [[2008 Indianapolis 500]], and his racing suit was designed to resemble Indiana Jones's outfit.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news |publisher = PaddockTalk.com|title = IndyCar Driver Marco Andretti To Run 'Indiana Jones' Livery For Indy 500 |url = http://www.paddocktalk.com/news/html/modules.php?op=modload&amp;name=News&amp;file=article&amp;sid=83076 | date = 2008-05-02 | accessdate = 2008-05-06}}&lt;/ref&gt; The distributor also paired with [[M&amp;M's]] to sponsor the #18 [[Joe Gibbs Racing]] [[Toyota]], with [[NASCAR]] driver [[Kyle Busch]] behind the wheel, in the [[2008 Dodge Challenger 500]] at Darlington Raceway.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Limited-Edition Indiana Jones M&amp;M’S Brand Candies and Snickers Bars Whip Into Stores for the Highly Anticipated Release of Indiana Jones and the Kingdom of the Crystal Skull|work=M&amp;M|url=http://www.pwrnewmedia.com/2008/mms_040208/index.html|accessdate=2009-04-15}}&lt;/ref&gt; Kyle Busch and the #18 team won the race and visited victory lane with Indiana Jones on the car.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=THE RACE: Dodge Challenger 500|publisher=Jayski|url=http://www.jayski.com/next/2008/11darl2008.htm|accessdate=2009-04-15}}&lt;/ref&gt; With the film's release, producer [[Frank Marshall (film producer)|Frank Marshall]] and [[UNESCO]] worked together to promote conservation of [[World Heritage Site]]s around the world.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.friendsofworldheritage.org/get-involved/about-the-campaign.html Friends of the World Heritage Adventure Quiz]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.prweb.com/releases/World_Heritage/Indiana_Jones/prweb1074374.htm Friends of World Heritage Teams Up with Indiana Jones to Offer Travelers the Chance to Follow in Indy's Footsteps]&lt;/ref&gt;

The [[Boston]]-based design studio [[Creative Pilot]] created the packaging style for the film's merchandise, which merged [[Drew Struzan]]'s original illustrations &quot;with a fresh new look, which showcases the whip, a map and exotic [[hieroglyph]]ic patterns&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news | title = New Packaging whipped up for Indy | publisher = Star Wars.com | date = 2007-10-10 | url = http://www.starwars.com/community/news/films/news20071010.html | accessdate = 2008-02-02}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Hasbro]], [[Lego]], [[Sideshow Collectibles]], [[Topps]], [[Diamond Comic Distributors|Diamond Select]], [[Hallmark Cards]],&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | title = Indiana Jones Merchandising | publisher = TheRaider.net | url = http://www.theraider.net/information/collectibles/index.php | accessdate=2008-04-07}}&lt;/ref&gt; and [[Cartamundi]] all sold products.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web | title = Indiana Jones Playing Cards | publisher = [[Cartamundi]] | url = http://www.cartamundiusa.com/Content/cmusa/products/licensed/indianajones/1/index.html | accessdate=2007-12-12 |archiveurl = http://web.archive.org/web/20080207021803/http://www.cartamundiusa.com/Content/cmusa/products/licensed/indianajones/1/index.html |archivedate = February 7, 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt; A [[THQ]] [[mobile game]] based on the film was released,&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news | author = Stuart Dredge | title = Hands on with THQ Wireless' Indiana Jones mobile game | publisher = PocketGamer.co.uk | date = 2008-02-13 | url = http://www.pocketgamer.co.uk/r/MobileIndiana%2BJones%2Band%2Bthe%2BKingdom%2Bof%2Bthe%2BCrystal%2BSkull/news.asp?c=5721 | accessdate = 2008-02-19}}&lt;/ref&gt; as was a [[Lego Indiana Jones: The Videogame|Lego video game]] based on the past films.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web | author = [[LucasArts]] | title = Indiana Jones | publisher = [http://www.lucasarts.com/ LucasArts.com] | date = | url = http://www.lucasarts.com/games/indianajones/ | accessdate=2007-07-22}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web | author = [[LucasArts]] | title = If Family Adventure Has a Name, It Must Be ''LEGO'' ''Indiana Jones: The Videogame'' | publisher = [http://www.lucasarts.com/ LucasArts.com] | date = 2007-07-27 | url = http://www.lucasarts.com/company/release/news20070727.html | accessdate=2008-02-15}}&lt;/ref&gt; Lego also released a series of computer-animated spoofs, ''[[Lego Indiana Jones and the Raiders of the Lost Brick]]'', directed by [[Peder Pedersen (director)|Peder Pedersen]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://indianajones.lego.com|title=''Raiders of the Lost Brick''|publisher=[[Lego]]|accessdate=2008-05-25}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Stern (game company)|Stern Pinball]] released a new Indiana Jones [[Pinball|pinball machine]], designed by John Borg, based on all four films.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news | publisher = Pinball News | title = Indiana Jones | url = http://pinballnews.com/games/indianajones/index.html | date = 2008-03-20 | accessdate = 2008-03-20}}&lt;/ref&gt; From October 2007 to April 2008, the reedited episodes of ''The Young Indiana Jones Chronicles'' were released in three DVD box sets.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web | title = YoungIndy.com | publisher = Paramount Pictures/Lucasfilm Ltd. | url = http://www.youngindy.com/ | accessdate = 2008-02-04}}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Random House]], [[Dark Horse Comics]], [[Diamond Comic Distributors]], [[Scholastic Corporation|Scholastic]] and [[Dorling Kindersley|DK]] published books,&lt;ref name=&quot;merch&quot; /&gt; including [[James Rollins]]' [[novelization]] of ''Kingdom of the Crystal Skull'',&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book | author = [[James Rollins]] | title = Indiana Jones and the Kingdom of the Crystal Skull | publisher = [[Del Ray Books]] | year = 2008 | url = http://www.randomhouse.com/delrey/catalog/display.pperl?isbn=9780345501288 | isbn = 978-0-345-50128-8}}&lt;/ref&gt; a two-issue [[comic book]] adaptation written by [[John Jackson Miller]] and drawn by Luke Ross (''[[Samurai: Heaven and Earth]]''), children's novelizations of all four films,&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news | title = Indiana Jones Junior Novelizations On the Way | url = http://www.starwars.com/community/news/films/news20080219b.html | author = | publisher = StarWars.com | date = 2008-02-19 | accessdate = 2008-02-19 |archiveurl = http://web.archive.org/web/20080225133825/http://www.starwars.com/community/news/films/news20080219b.html |archivedate = February 25, 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt; the ''Indiana Jones Adventures'' comic book series aimed at children,&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news | title =Dark Horse Comics for May | publisher = Comics Continuum | date = 2008-02-13 | url = http://www.comicscontinuum.com/stories/0802/13/darkhorsemay.htm | accessdate=2008-02-15}}&lt;/ref&gt; and the official ''Indiana Jones Magazine''.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web | author = | title = Indiana Jones and the Magazine | publisher = [http://scoop.diamondgalleries.com/public/ Scoop.diamondgalleries.com] | date = | url = http://scoop.diamondgalleries.com/public/default.asp?t=1&amp;m=1&amp;c=34&amp;s=259&amp;ai=66533 | accessdate=2008-02-09}}&lt;/ref&gt; Scholastic featured Indiana and Mutt on the covers of ''Scholastic News'' and ''Scholastic Maths'', to the concern of parents, though Jack Silbert, editor of the latter, felt the film would interest children in archaeology.&lt;ref name=inescapable/&gt;

=== Home media ===
The film was released on [[Blu-ray Disc]] and [[DVD]] in North America on October 14, 2008. This includes a two-disc edition Blu-ray; a two-disc Special Edition DVD; and a one-disc edition DVD.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|title=Indy's Latest Comes to Blu-Ray and DVD October 14th|work=StarWars.com|date=2008-08-12|url=http://www.starwars.com/movies/other/indy/20080808news.html|accessdate=2008-08-20}}&lt;/ref&gt; These editions were released in the UK on November 10.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|author=Dave Foster|title=Indiana Jones and the Kingdom of the Crystal Skull (UK BD) in November|work=DVD Times|date=2008-09-17|url=http://www.dvdtimes.co.uk/content.php?contentid=68935|accessdate=2008-09-18}}&lt;/ref&gt; Among the collectible editions include; [[Kmart]], which contains four LEGO posters parodying those of the films; [[Target Corporation]], whose DVD has an eighty-page book of photographs; and [[Best Buy]], whose edition contains a replica of a crystal skull created by [[Sideshow Collectibles]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title=Indiana Jones 4 DVD and Blu-ray Exclusives|work=TheRaider.net|date=2008-10-10|url=http://www.theraider.net/news/fullstory_merchandise.php?id=943|accessdate=2008-10-11}}&lt;/ref&gt; As of March 1, 2009, it has made $109,296,975 in revenue.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.the-numbers.com/movies/2008/INDI4.php|title=Indiana Jones and the Kingdom of the Crystal Skull|work=The Numbers|accessdate=2008-10-31}}&lt;/ref&gt; It made its worldwide television premiere on USA on December 9, 2010.

== Performance ==
=== Box office ===
{| class=&quot;wikitable&quot; width=99% border=&quot;1&quot;
| colspan=&quot;3&quot; align=&quot;center&quot; | '''Box office revenue'''
| colspan=&quot;2&quot; align=&quot;center&quot; text=&quot;wrap&quot; | '''Box office ranking'''
| rowspan=&quot;2&quot; align=&quot;center&quot; | '''Reference'''
|-
| align=&quot;center&quot; | '''United States'''
| align=&quot;center&quot; | '''Foreign'''
| align=&quot;center&quot; | '''Worldwide'''
| align=&quot;center&quot; | '''All time domestic'''
| align=&quot;center&quot; | '''All time worldwide'''
|-
| $317,101,119
| $469,534,914
| $786,636,033
| align=&quot;center&quot; | #28
| align=&quot;center&quot; | #35
| align=&quot;center&quot; |&lt;ref name=&quot;BOM&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.boxofficemojo.com/movies/?id=indianajones4.htm |title=Indiana Jones and the Kingdom of the Crystal Skull (2008) |publisher=[[Box Office Mojo]] |accessdate=2011-07-29}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|}

''Indiana Jones'' is distributed by one entity, Paramount, but owned by another, [[Lucasfilm]]. The pre-production arrangement between the two organizations granted Paramount 12.5% of the film's revenue. As the $185 million budget was larger than the original $125 million estimate,&lt;ref name=&quot;titles&quot; /&gt; Lucas, Spielberg and Ford turned down large upfront salaries so Paramount could cover the film's costs. In order for Paramount to see a profit beyond its distribution fee, the film had to make over $400 million. At that point, Lucas, Spielberg, Ford and those with smaller profit-sharing deals would also begin to collect their cut.&lt;ref name=treasure&gt;{{cite news | author = Claudia Eller | title = Ford, Lucas, Spielberg on risky quest for treasure | publisher = [[Los Angeles Times]] | date = 2008-04-21 | url = http://www.latimes.com/business/la-fi-indianajones21apr21,1,4784324.story | accessdate=2008-04-21 |archiveurl = http://web.archive.org/web/20080422143034/http://www.latimes.com/business/la-fi-indianajones21apr21,1,4784324.story |archivedate = April 22, 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt;

''Indiana Jones and the Kingdom of the Crystal Skull'' was released Thursday May 22 in North America and grossed $25 million its opening day.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news | author = Pamela McClintock | title= 'Jones' grosses $25 mil on Thursday | publisher = [[Variety (magazine)|Variety]] | date = 2008-05-23 | url = http://www.variety.com/article/VR1117986369.html?categoryid=13&amp;cs=1 | accessdate=2008-05-24}}&lt;/ref&gt; In its opening weekend, the film grossed an estimated $101 million in 4,260 theaters in the United States and Canada, ranking #1 at the box office,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.boxofficemojo.com/movies/?page=weekend&amp;id=indianajones4.htm |title=Indiana Jones and the Kingdom of the Crystal Skull (2008) - Weekend Box Office Results |accessdate=2008-05-26 |publisher=[[Box Office Mojo]]}}&lt;/ref&gt; and making it the third widest opening of all time.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.boxofficemojo.com/alltime/widest.htm?page=WIDESTOPEN&amp;p=.htm |title=Movies With the Widest Openings at the Box Office |accessdate=2008-05-26 |publisher=[[Box Office Mojo]]}}&lt;/ref&gt; Within its first five days of release, it grossed $311 million worldwide. The film's total $151 million gross in the United States ranked it as the second biggest [[Memorial Day]] weekend release, behind ''[[Pirates of the Caribbean: At World's End]]''.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news | author = Dean Goodman | title = &quot;Indiana Jones&quot; hits $311 million worldwide | publisher = [[Reuters]] | date = 2008-05-26 | url = http://www.reuters.com/article/newsOne/idUSN2235236020080526 | accessdate=2008-05-26}}&lt;/ref&gt; It was the third most successful film of 2008 domestically, behind ''[[The Dark Knight (film)|The Dark Knight]]'' and ''[[Iron Man (film)|Iron Man]]'' respectively,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url=http://www.boxofficemojo.com/yearly/chart/?yr=2008&amp;p=.htm | title=2008 DOMESTIC GROSSES | publisher=[[Box Office Mojo]] | accessdate=2009-01-04}}&lt;/ref&gt; and the second highest-grossing film of 2008 internationally, behind ''The Dark Knight''.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url=http://www.boxofficemojo.com/yearly/chart/?view2=worldwide&amp;yr=2008&amp;p=.htm | title=2008 WORLDWIDE GROSSES | publisher=[[Box Office Mojo]] | accessdate=2008-09-16}}&lt;/ref&gt; In February 2010 it was the [[List of highest-grossing films|25th highest-grossing film of all time]] domestically, and 35th highest-grossing worldwide, as well as the most financially successful ''Indiana Jones'' film when not adjusted for inflation of ticket prices.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url=http://www.boxofficemojo.com/alltime/domestic.htm | title=DOMESTIC GROSSES | publisher=[[Box Office Mojo]] | accessdate=2010-02-19}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url=http://www.boxofficemojo.com/alltime/world/ | title=WORLDWIDE GROSSES | publisher=[[Box Office Mojo]] | accessdate=2010-02-19}}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Reception ===
The film received mostly positive reviews. [[Rotten Tomatoes]] reported that 77% of critics gave the film positive reviews, based on 246 reviews. The consensus was: &quot;Though the plot elements are certainly familiar, ''Indiana Jones and the Kingdom of the Crystal Skull'' still delivers the thrills and Harrison Ford's return in the title role is more than welcome.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url= http://www.rottentomatoes.com/m/indiana_jones_and_the_kingdom_of_the_crystal_skull/ | title=Indiana Jones and the Kingdom of the Crystal Skull (2008) | publisher=[[Rotten Tomatoes]] | accessdate=2008-05-26}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Metacritic]] reported the film had a score of 65 out of 100, indicating &quot;generally favorable reviews,&quot; based on 40 critics' reviews.&lt;ref name=&quot;Metacritic&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.metacritic.com/film/titles/indianajones4 |title=Indiana Jones and the Kingdom of the Crystal Skull (2008): Reviews |accessdate=2008-05-23 |publisher=[[Metacritic]]}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Yahoo!]] estimated an average rating of B from 15 reviews.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url= http://movies.yahoo.com/movie/1808404510/critic | title=Indiana Jones and the Kingdom of the Crystal Skull (2008): Reviews | publisher=[[Yahoo]] | accessdate=2008-05-24}}&lt;/ref&gt; A [[CinemaScore]] survey conducted during its opening weekend indicated a general &quot;B&quot; rating.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|author=Joshua Rich|title='Indiana Jones 4' Digs Big Box Office|work=[[Entertainment Weekly]]|date=2008-05-22|url=http://www.ew.com/ew/article/0,,20202447,00.html|accessdate=2008-10-11}}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Roger Ebert]] gave the film 3.5 stars out of 4, a rating he also gave to ''The Last Crusade''. Ebert argued that the only critical criterion for judging the latest film was comparing it to the previous three. He found it &quot;same old, same old,&quot; but that was what &quot;I want it to be.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news | author = [[Roger Ebert]] | title = Indiana Jones and the Kingdom of the Crystal Skull | date = 2008-05-18 | url = http://rogerebert.suntimes.com/apps/pbcs.dll/article?AID=/20080518/REVIEWS/969461084 | accessdate=2008-05-19 | work=Chicago Sun-Times}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Leonard Maltin]] also gave the film 3 1/2 stars out of 4, though he had only given 2 stars to ''Temple of Doom'' and 2 1/2 to ''Last Crusade.'' &quot;After a 19-year hiatus,&quot; Maltin wrote, &quot;Indy returns with the same brand of high adventure that marked the original ''Raiders of the Lost Ark.''&quot;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.amazon.com/dp/0452289785 Leonard Maltin's Movie Guide 2009, p. 669]&lt;/ref&gt; 

The film was nominated for Best Action Movie at the 2009 [[Critics' Choice Award]]s.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.variety.com/article/VR1117997072.html?categoryId=13&amp;cs=1|author=Dade Hayes|title=Critics Choice favors 'Milk,' 'Button'|work=[[Variety (magazine)|Variety]]|date=2008-12-09|accessdate=2008-12-09}}&lt;/ref&gt; The [[Visual Effects Society]] nominated it for Best Single Visual Effect of the Year (the valley destruction), Best Outstanding Matte Paintings, Best Models and Miniatures, and Best Created Environment in a Feature Motion Picture (the inside of the temple).&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title=Visual Effects Society|work=IESB.net|date=2009-01-19|url=http://www.iesb.net/index.php?option=com_content&amp;task=view&amp;id=6128&amp;Itemid=99|accessdate=2009-01-19}}&lt;/ref&gt; The film ranks 453rd on ''[[Empire (magazine)|Empire]]'''s 2008 list of the 500 greatest movies of all time.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.empireonline.com/500/8.asp&lt;/ref&gt; At the [[51st Grammy Awards]], John Williams won an award for the Mutt Williams theme.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.grammy.com/grammy_awards/51st_show/list.aspx|title=51st Grammy Awards|publisher=Grammy.com|accessdate=2009-02-10}}&lt;/ref&gt; It was nominated at the [[Saturn Award]]s for Best Science Fiction Film, Best Director, Best Actor, Best Supporting Actor, Best Costumes and Best Special Effects. It won Best Costumes.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url=http://www.saturnawards.org/nominations.html | title=Nominations for the 35th Annual Saturn Awards | publisher=[[Saturn Award|Academy of Science Fiction, Fantasy &amp; Horror Films]] | accessdate=2009-03-17}}&lt;/ref&gt;

However, the ''[[Associated Press]]'' reported the film received a &quot;respectful&amp;nbsp;– though far from glowing&amp;nbsp;– reception,&quot; saying that &quot;some viewers at its first press screening loved it, some called it slick and enjoyable though formulaic, some said it was not worth the 19-year wait,&quot; adding that J. Sperling Reich, who writes for FilmStew.com, said: &quot;It really looked like they were going through the motions. It really looked like no one had their heart in it.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news | title = 'Indiana Jones' debut survives Cannes critics | author = David Germain | publisher = [[Associated Press]] |date = 2008-05-18 | url = http://ap.google.com/article/ALeqM5gq0O5YBFJqvdAnoL89UdFD0q1d9wD90O72G00 | accessdate = 2008-05-29}}&lt;/ref&gt;  

''[[USA Today]]'' stated reviews were &quot;mixed&quot; and reviewers felt the &quot;movie suffers from predictable plot points and cheesy special effects.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news | author = Scott Bowles | title = 'Indiana Jones' gets mixed reviews on the Web | publisher = [[USA Today]] | date = 2008-05-11 | url = http://www.usatoday.com/life/movies/news/2008-05-11-indy-web-reviews_N.htm | accessdate=2008-05-30}}&lt;/ref&gt; 

Critic [[James Berardinelli]] gave the film 2 stars out of 4, calling it &quot;the most lifeless of the series&quot; and &quot;simply [not] a very good motion picture.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | author = [[James Berardinelli]] | title = Indiana Jones and the Kingdom of the Crystal Skull | publisher = Reel Views | url = http://www.reelviews.net/movies/i/indiana_jones4.html | accessdate=2008-05-19}}&lt;/ref&gt; Margaret Pomeranz of ''[[At the Movies (Australian TV series)|At the Movies]]'' gave the film 2 1/2 stars out of 5, saying that the filmmakers &quot;had 19 years since the last Indiana Jones movie to come up with something truly exciting and fresh, but I feel there’s a certain laziness and cynicism in this latest adventure.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.abc.net.au/atthemovies/txt/s2258196.htm]&lt;/ref&gt; Metacritic user ratings for the film (as opposed to critics' ratings) rank at only 5.1 out of 10.&lt;ref name=&quot;Metacritic&quot;/&gt; 

In 2009, the film won the [[Golden Raspberry Award|Razzie Award]] for [[Golden Raspberry Award for Worst Prequel, Remake, Rip-off or Sequel|Worst Prequel, Remake, Rip-off or Sequel]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.razzies.com/history/08winners.asp |title= 29th Annual Golden Raspberry Award Winners |publisher=[[Golden Raspberry Award|Razzies]] |accessdate= July 4, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.imdb.com/title/tt0367882/awards |title= ''Indiana Jones and the Kingdom of the Crystal Skull'': Award Wins and Nominations |publisher= [[IMDb|IMDb.com]] |date= |accessdate= July 4, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; The film was voted by [[Comcast]] as 11th worst movie sequel of all time.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.comcast.net/slideshow/entertainment-worstsequels/40/ |title= Worst Sequels of All Time |publisher=[[Comcast]].com |accessdate= July 4, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; ''[[Paste (magazine)|Paste]]'' magazine ranked the movie 10th on its list &quot;The 20 Worst Sequels to Good Movies.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.pastemagazine.com/blogs/lists/2009/10/-worst-sequels-to-good-movies.html?p=3 |title=The 20 Worst Sequels to Good Movies |publisher= ''[[Paste (magazine)|Paste]]'' magazine |date= |accessdate= July 4, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; Listverse.com ranked the movie 8th on its list of the &quot;Top 10 Worst Movie Sequels.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://listverse.com/2010/05/20/top-10-worst-movie-sequels/ |title= Top 10 Worst Movie Sequels |publisher= listverse.com |date= |accessdate= July 4, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Some fans of the franchise who were disappointed with the film adopted the term &quot;[[nuking the fridge|nuked the fridge]],&quot; based on a scene in the film where Indiana Jones survives a nuclear blast by hiding in a refrigerator, which then blows Jones miraculously all the way to safety. To users of the phrase, the phrase denotes the point in a movie series when it has passed its peak and crossed into the level of the absurd, similar to &quot;[[jumping the shark]]&quot; on television. This phrase has since appeared across the Internet,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news | url= http://www.newsweek.com/id/143782 | title=‘Jump the Shark,’ Meet ‘Nuke the Fridge’ | date = 2008-07-14 | work=[[Newsweek]] | accessdate=2008-07-07}}&lt;/ref&gt; and was chosen as #5 on [[Time Magazine]]'s list of &quot;top ten buzzwords&quot; of 2008.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news| url=http://www.time.com/time/specials/2008/top10/article/0,30583,1855948_1864100_1864105,00.html | work=Time | title=The Top 10 Everything Of 2008 | date=2008-11-03 | accessdate=2010-05-05}}&lt;/ref&gt; ''[[South Park]]'' parodied the film in the episode &quot;[[The China Probrem]],&quot; broadcast five months after the film's release. The episode was highly critical of the movie, with the characters filing a police report against Lucas and Spielberg for [[raping]] Indiana Jones.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|author=Carl Cortez|title=South Park&amp;nbsp;— Season Twelve&amp;nbsp;— The China Probrem|work=iF Magazine|date=2008-10-09|url=http://www.ifmagazine.com/review.asp?article=2809|accessdate=2008-10-09}} {{Dead link|date=October 2010|bot=H3llBot}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The [[Communist Party of the Russian Federation]] called for the film to be banned, accusing the production team of demonizing the Soviet Union. Party official Andrei Andreyev said: &quot;It is very disturbing if talented directors want to provoke a new Cold War.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |url=http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/entertainment/7418727.stm |title=Indiana angers Russian communists |accessdate=2008-05-25 |publisher=[[BBC News Online]] |date=2008-05-24 }}&lt;/ref&gt; Another party official commented, &quot;(I)n 1957 the USSR was not sending terrorists to America but sending the [[Sputnik 1|Sputnik satellite]] into space!&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |url=http://www.russiatoday.ru/entertainment/news/25168 |title=Indiana Jones and the Propaganda Machine |accessdate=2008-05-26 |publisher=[[Russia Today]] |date=2008-05-23}}&lt;/ref&gt; Spielberg responded that he is not unfamiliar with Russia. He explained: &quot;When we decided the fourth installment would take place in 1957, we had no choice but to make the Russians the enemies. [[World War II]] had just ended and the [[Cold War]] had begun. The U.S. didn't have any other enemies at the time.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |url=http://orenburg.kp.ru/daily/24103/329446/ |title= Steven Spielberg: &quot;I'm Russian. But that doesn't explain a thing.&quot; |accessdate=2008-05-26 |publisher= [[Komsomolskaya Pravda]] |date=2008-05-24}}&lt;/ref&gt; The film's depiction of Peru also received criticism from the Peruvian and Spanish-speaking public.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |url=http://www.eluniversal.com.mx/notas/510903.html |title=Califican en Perú de ''ofensivos'' errores en ''Indiana Jones'' |accessdate=2008-05-26 |publisher=[[El Universal (Mexico City)|El Universal]] |date=2008-05-30}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;http://www.filmaffinity.com/es/reviews2/1/301570.html&lt;/ref&gt;

Historical and Geographical inaccuracies are present throughout the movie - like Nazca being apparently located in Cuzco. 

The mixed fanbase reaction did not surprise Lucas, who was familiar with mixed response to the ''Star Wars'' prequels. &quot;We're all going to get people throwing tomatoes at us,&quot; the series' creator had predicted. &quot;But it's a fun movie to make.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news | title = Indiana Jones rides into Cannes | work = [[Reuters]] | date = 2008-05-17 | url = http://uk.reuters.com/article/filmNews/idUKELK76198620080517?pageNumber=2&amp;virtualBrandChannel=0 | accessdate=2008-05-29}}&lt;/ref&gt; David Koepp reflects, &quot;I knew I was going to get hammered from a number of quarters [but] what I liked about the way the movie ended up playing was it was popular with families. I like that families really embraced it.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|author=Shawn Adler|title=Shia LaBeouf Defends 'Nuking The Fridge' And Other Fantastical 'Indy 4' Moments|work=[[MTV]]|date=2008-09-16|url=http://www.mtv.com/movies/news/articles/1594844/story.jhtml|accessdate=2008-09-16}}&lt;/ref&gt;

When asked about the infamous &quot;[[nuke the fridge]]&quot; sequence, Spielberg replied, Blame me. Don't blame George. That was my silly idea. People stopped saying 'jump the shark'. They now say, &quot;nuked the fridge&quot;. I'm proud of that. I'm glad I was able to bring that into popular culture.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;http://www.empireonline.com/news/story.asp?NID=32315&lt;/ref&gt;

==Notes==
{{Reflist|colwidth=30em}}

==References==
* {{Cite book | last = Rinzler | first = J.W. | authorlink = | coauthors = Laurent Bouzereau | title = The Complete Making of Indiana Jones | publisher = [[Random House]] | year = 2008 | isbn = 9780091926618}}

==External links==
{{Commons category}}
{{Wikiquote}}
* {{Official website|http://www.indianajones.com}}
* {{IMDb title|0367882|Indiana Jones and the Kingdom of the Crystal Skull}}
* {{Amg movie|384336|Indiana Jones and the Kingdom of the Crystal Skull}}
* {{Rotten-tomatoes|indiana_jones_and_the_kingdom_of_the_crystal_skull|Indiana Jones and the Kingdom of the Crystal Skull}}
* {{Metacritic film|indianajones4|Indiana Jones and the Kingdom of the Crystal Skull}}
* {{Mojo title|indianajones4|Indiana Jones and the Kingdom of the Crystal Skull}}

{{Indiana Jones}}
{{Steven Spielberg}}
{{George Lucas productions}}
{{Good article}}

[[Category:2000s action films]]
[[Category:2000s adventure films]]
[[Category:2008 films]]
[[Category:Alien visitation films]]
[[Category:American action films]]
[[Category:American adventure films]]
[[Category:Ancient astronauts in fiction]]
[[Category:Cold War films]]
[[Category:Films set in 1957]]
[[Category:Films set in Connecticut]]
[[Category:Films set in Nevada]]
[[Category:Films set in Peru]]
[[Category:Films shot anamorphically]]
[[Category:Films shot in Brazil]]
[[Category:Films shot in California]]
[[Category:Films shot in Connecticut]]
[[Category:Films shot in Hawaii]]
[[Category:Films shot in New Mexico]]
[[Category:Lucasfilm films]]
[[Category:Paramount Pictures films]]
[[Category:Roswell UFO incident]]
[[Category:Sequel films]]
[[Category:Treasure hunt films]]
[[Category:Works about McCarthyism]]

{{Link GA|tr}}

[[ar:إنديانا جونز ومملكة الجمجمة الكريستالية]]
[[bg:Индиана Джоунс и кралството на кристалния череп]]
[[ca:Indiana Jones i el regne de la calavera de cristall]]
[[cs:Indiana Jones a království křišťálové lebky]]
[[cy:Indiana Jones and the Kingdom of the Crystal Skull]]
[[da:Indiana Jones og Krystalkraniets Kongerige]]
[[de:Indiana Jones und das Königreich des Kristallschädels]]
[[et:Indiana Jones ja Kristallpealuu kuningriik]]
[[el:Ο Ιντιάνα Τζόουνς και Το Βασίλειο του Κρυστάλλινου Κρανίου]]
[[es:Indiana Jones y el reino de la calavera de cristal]]
[[eo:Indiana Jones kaj la Reĝlando de la Kristala Kranio]]
[[eu:Indiana Jones and the Kingdom of the Crystal Skull]]
[[fa:ایندیانا جونز و قلمرو جمجمه بلورین]]
[[fr:Indiana Jones et le Royaume du crâne de cristal]]
[[ko:인디아나 존스: 크리스탈 해골의 왕국]]
[[hr:Indiana Jones i Kraljevstvo kristalne lubanje]]
[[id:Indiana Jones and the Kingdom of the Crystal Skull]]
[[it:Indiana Jones e il regno del teschio di cristallo]]
[[he:אינדיאנה ג'ונס וממלכת גולגולת הבדולח]]
[[jv:Indiana Jones and the Kingdom of the Crystal Skull]]
[[lv:Indiana Džonss un kristāla galvaskausa karaļvalsts]]
[[hu:Indiana Jones és a kristálykoponya királysága]]
[[mk:Индијана Џонс и Кралството на кристалниот череп]]
[[nl:Indiana Jones and the Kingdom of the Crystal Skull]]
[[ja:インディ・ジョーンズ/クリスタル・スカルの王国]]
[[no:Indiana Jones og krystallhodeskallens rike]]
[[pl:Indiana Jones i Królestwo Kryształowej Czaszki]]
[[pt:Indiana Jones e o Reino da Caveira de Cristal]]
[[ru:Индиана Джонс и Королевство хрустального черепа]]
[[simple:Indiana Jones and the Kingdom of the Crystal Skull]]
[[sr:Indijana Džouns i kraljevstvo kristalne lobanje]]
[[fi:Indiana Jones ja kristallikallon valtakunta]]
[[sv:Indiana Jones och Kristalldödskallens rike]]
[[th:ขุมทรัพย์สุดขอบฟ้า 4: อาณาจักรกะโหลกแก้ว]]
[[tr:Indiana Jones ve Kristal Kafatası Krallığı]]
[[wuu:印第安纳琼斯 —— 水晶骷髅王国]]
[[zh:印地安納瓊斯：水晶骷髏王國]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
