<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="125665" ns="0" title="Paterson, New Jersey"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Infobox settlement
|official_name            = '''City of Paterson'''
|other_name               =
|native_name              = &lt;!-- for cities whose native name is not in English --&gt;
|nickname                 = The Silk City
|motto                    =
|image_skyline            = Downtown-paterson-nj2.jpg
|imagesize                =
|image_caption            =
|image_flag               =
|flag_size                =
|image_seal               =
|image_map                = paterson_nj.png
|mapsize                  = 250x200px
|map_caption              = Map of Paterson in Passaic County. Inset: Passaic County's location in New Jersey.
|image_map1               = Census Bureau map of Paterson, New Jersey.gif
|mapsize1                 = 250x200px
|map_caption1             = Census Bureau map of Paterson, New Jersey
|coordinates_region       = US-NJ
|subdivision_type         = [[List of countries|Country]]
|subdivision_name         = United States
|subdivision_type1        = [[U.S. state|State]]
|subdivision_name1        = [[New Jersey]]
|subdivision_type2        = [[List of counties in New Jersey|County]]
|subdivision_name2        = [[Passaic County, New Jersey|Passaic]]
|government_type          = [[Faulkner Act (New Jersey)|Faulkner Act]] [[Faulkner Act (Mayor-Council)|Mayor-Council]]
|settlement_type          = [[City (New Jersey)|City]]
|leader_title             = [[Mayor]]
|leader_name              = Jeff Jones (term ends 2014)&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.state.nj.us/dca/home/20110502mayors.pdf 2011 New Jersey Mayors Directory], [[New Jersey Department of Community Affairs]]. Accessed July 19, 2011.&lt;/ref&gt;
|established_title        = Established
|established_date         = 1792
|established_title2       = [[Municipal corporation|Incorporated]]
|established_date2        = April 11, 1831
|area_magnitude           =
|area_footnotes           = &lt;ref name=CensusArea&gt;[http://factfinder.census.gov/servlet/GCTTable?_bm=y&amp;-context=gct&amp;-ds_name=DEC_2000_SF1_U&amp;-CONTEXT=gct&amp;-mt_name=DEC_2000_SF1_U_GCTPH1_CO2&amp;-tree_id=4001&amp;-redoLog=true&amp;-_caller=geoselect&amp;-geo_id=05000US34031&amp;-format=CO-2&amp;-_lang=en GCT-PH1. Population, Housing Units, Area, and Density: 2000 for Passaic County, New Jersey -- County Subdivision and Place], [[United States Census Bureau]]. Accessed September 4, 2011.&lt;/ref&gt;
|area_total_km2           = 22.6
|area_land_km2            = 21.9
|area_water_km2           =  0.8
|area_total_sq_mi         =  8.73
|area_land_sq_mi          =  8.44
|area_water_sq_mi         =  0.29
|area_water_percent       =  3.32
|area_urban_km2           =
|area_urban_sq_mi         =
|area_metro_km2           =
|area_metro_sq_mi         =
|population_as_of         = [[2010 United States Census|2010]]
|population_footnotes     = &lt;ref name=Census2010/&gt;
|population_note          =
|population_total         = 146,199
|population_density_km2   = auto
|population_density_sq_mi = auto
|population_metro         = 
|population_urban         = 
|timezone                 = Eastern
|utc_offset               = -5
|timezone_DST             = Eastern
|utc_offset_DST           = -4
|coordinates_display      = display=inline,title
|latd = 40 |latm = 54 |lats = 56 |latNS = N
|longd = 74 |longm = 09 |longs = 47 |longEW = W
|elevation_m              = 32
|elevation_ft             = 105
|elevation_footnotes      = &lt;ref&gt;{{Gnis|885343|City of Paterson}}, [[Geographic Names Information System]], accessed May 26, 2007.&lt;/ref&gt;
|postal_code_type         = [[ZIP code]]s
|postal_code              = 07501-07505, 07508-07514, 07522, 07524, 07533, 07538, 07543, 07544&lt;ref&gt;[https://tools.usps.com/go/ZipLookupResultsAction!input.action?resultMode=0&amp;city=paterson&amp;state=NJ Look Up a ZIP Code], [[United States Postal Service]]. Accessed September 4, 2011.&lt;/ref&gt;
|area_code                = [[Area codes 862 and 973|862/973]]
|blank_name               = [[Federal Information Processing Standard|FIPS code]]
|blank_info               = 34-57000{{GR|2}}&lt;ref&gt;[http://mcdc2.missouri.edu/webrepts/commoncodes/ccc_nj.html A Cure for the Common Codes: New Jersey], Missouri Census Data Center. Accessed July 14, 2008.&lt;/ref&gt;
|blank1_name              = [[Geographic Names Information System|GNIS]] feature ID
|blank1_info              = 0879164{{GR|3}}
|website                  = http://www.patersonnj.gov
|footnotes                =
}}
[[Image:Paterson NJ 1880.jpg|300px|right|thumb|View of Paterson circa 1880.]]
[[Image:Passaic falls.jpg|300px|right|thumb|The [[Great Falls of the Passaic River]] in Paterson, which are the second-highest large-volume falls on the East Coast of the United States.]]
[[Image:Paterson new jersey.jpg|300px|right|thumb|The skyline of Paterson, New Jersey, showing the canyon of the [[Passaic River]] in the foreground. The area along the river was formerly the site of most of the mills that flourished throughout the city's history.]]
'''Paterson''' is a [[City (New Jersey)|city]] serving as the county seat of [[Passaic County, New Jersey|Passaic County]], [[New Jersey]],{{GR|6}} United States. As of the [[2010 United States Census]], its population was 146,199,&lt;ref name=Census2010/&gt; rendering it New Jersey's third [[List of municipalities in New Jersey|largest city]] and one of the largest cities in the [[New York City Metropolitan Area]], despite a decrease of 3,023 residents (2.0%) from its [[2000 United States Census|2000 Census]] population of 149,222.&lt;ref name=Census2010XLS&gt;[http://2010.census.gov/news/xls/st34-final_newjersey.xls The Counties and Most Populous Cities and Townships in 2010 in New Jersey: 2000 and 2010], [[United States Census Bureau]]. Accessed September 3, 2011.&lt;/ref&gt; Paterson is known as the &quot;Silk City&quot; for its dominant role in silk production during the latter half of the 19th century.&lt;ref name=Reuters&gt;Thomasch, Paul. [http://www.reuters.com/article/2011/09/01/storm-irene-paterson-idUSN1E7801T720110901 &quot;Irene another blow to struggling New Jersey city&quot;], [[Reuters]], September 1, 2011. Accessed September 4, 2011.&lt;/ref&gt;

==History==
[[Image:Paterson New Jersey from airplane.jpg|250px|thumb|left|Paterson as seen from an airplane, looking south]]
In 1791, [[Alexander Hamilton]] helped found the [[Society for the Establishment of Useful Manufactures]] (SUM), which helped encourage the harnessing of energy from the [[Great Falls of the Passaic River]], to secure economic independence from British manufacturers. Paterson, which was founded by the society, became the cradle of the industrial revolution in America.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.patersongreatfalls.org/significance.html District Significance], Paterson Friends of the Great Falls. Accessed September 4, 2011.&lt;/ref&gt; Paterson was named for [[William Paterson (judge)|William Paterson]], statesman, signer of the [[United States Constitution|Constitution]] and [[Governor of New Jersey]] who signed the 1792 charter that established the Town of Paterson.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.wpunj.edu/university/history/WilliamPaterson_Bio.dot Who Was William Paterson?], [[William Paterson University]]. Accessed September 4, 2011. &quot;He also supported a proposal by Secretary of the Treasury Alexander Hamilton and a group of investors to incorporate them as the [[Society for Establishing Useful Manufactures]] (SUM). In 1792 he signed the charter incorporating SUM as well as a municipal charter covering 36 square miles for the Corporation of the Town of Paterson at the site of the Great Falls of the Passaic River.&quot;&lt;/ref&gt;

Architect, engineer, and city planner [[Pierre L'Enfant|Pierre (Peter) Charles L'Enfant]], who had earlier developed the initial plans for [[Washington, D.C.]], was the first planner for the SUM project.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Jusserand|first=Jean Jules|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=u2MUAAAAYAAJ&amp;printsec=frontcover&amp;dq=Jusserand,+Jules#v=onepage&amp;q=Paterson&amp;f=false|title=With Americans of Past and Present Days|chapter=Major L'Enfant and the Federal City|location=New York|publisher=Charles Scribner's Sons|page=184|year=1916|accessdate=2011-08-15}}&lt;/ref&gt; His plan proposed to harness the power of the Great Falls through a channel in the rock and an aqueduct. However, the society's directors felt he was taking too long and was over budget. He was replaced by Peter Colt, who used a less-complicated reservoir system to get the water flowing to factories in 1794. Eventually, Colt's system developed some problems and a scheme resembling L'Enfant's original plan was used after 1846.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.patersongreatfalls.org/sum.html Society for Establishing Useful Manufactures], Paterson Friends of the Great Falls. Accessed August 15, 2011.&lt;/ref&gt;

Paterson was originally formed as a [[township (New Jersey)|township]] from portions of [[Acquackanonk Township, New Jersey|Acquackanonk Township]] on April 11, 1831, while the area was still part of [[Essex County, New Jersey|Essex County]]. Paterson became part of the newly created Passaic County on February 7, 1837. Paterson was incorporated as a city on April 14, 1851, based on the results of a referendum held that day. The city was reincorporated on March 14, 1861.&lt;ref name=Story&gt;&quot;The Story of New Jersey's Civil Boundaries: 1606-1968&quot;, John P. Snyder, Bureau of Geology and Topography; Trenton, New Jersey; 1969. p. 210.&lt;/ref&gt;

The industries developed in Paterson were powered by the 77-foot high Great Falls, and a system of water raceways that harnessed the power of the falls. The city began growing around the falls and until 1914 the mills were powered by the waterfalls. The district originally included dozens of mill buildings and other manufacturing structures associated with the textile industry and later, the firearms, silk, and railroad locomotive manufacturing industries. In the latter half of the 19th century, [[silk]] production became the dominant industry and formed the basis of Paterson's most prosperous period, earning it the nickname &quot;Silk City.&quot; In 1835, Samuel Colt began producing firearms in Paterson, although within a few years he moved his business to [[Hartford, Connecticut]]. Later in the 19th century, Paterson was the site of early experiments with submarines by Irish-American inventor [[John Phillip Holland]]. Two of Holland's early models &amp;mdash; one found at the bottom of the Passaic River &amp;mdash; are on display in the [[Paterson Museum]], housed in the former [[Rogers Locomotive and Machine Works]] near the Passaic Falls.

The city was a mecca for [[immigrant]] [[laborers]] who worked in its factories. Paterson was the site of historic labor unrest that focused on anti-child labor legislation, and the six-month long [[Paterson silk strike of 1913]] that demanded the [[eight-hour day]] and better working conditions, but was defeated by the employers with workers forced to return under pre-strike conditions. Factory workers labored long hours for low wages under dangerous conditions, and lived in crowded tenement buildings around the mills. The factories then moved south where there were no labor unions, and later moved overseas. 

In 1919, Paterson was one of eight locations bombed by self-identified anarchists.&lt;ref&gt;Salerno, Salvatore. [http://libcom.org/history/patersons-italian-anarchist-silk-workers-politics-race-salvatore-salerno &quot;Paterson's Italian Anarchist Silk Workers and the Politics of Race by Salvatore Salerno&quot;], libcom.org, February 5, 2011. Accessed November 28, 2011.&lt;/ref&gt;

In 1932, Paterson opened [[Hinchliffe Stadium]], a 10,000-seat stadium named in honor of [[John V. Hinchliffe]], the [[Mayor of Paterson, New Jersey]] at the time. Hinchliffe originally served as the site for high school and professional athletic events. From 1933–1937, 1939–1945, Hinchliffe was the home of the [[New York Black Yankees]] and from 1935 to 1936 the home of the [[New York Cubans]] of the [[Negro National League (1933-1948)|Negro National League]].  The historic ballpark was also a venue for many professional football games, track and field events, boxing matches and auto and motorcycle racing. [[Abbott and Costello]] performed at Hinchliffe prior to boxing matches. Hinchliffe is one of only three [[Negro League]] stadiums left standing in the United States, and is on the [[National Register of Historic Places]]. In 1963, the Paterson Public Schools acquired the stadium and used it for public school events until 1997, but it is currently in a state of disrepair, while the schools have been taken over by the state.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.preservationnation.org/travel-and-sites/sites/northeast-region/hinchliffe-stadium.html Hinchliffe Stadium], [[National Trust for Historic Preservation]]. Accessed September 4, 2011.&lt;/ref&gt;

During [[World War II]] Paterson played an important part in the aircraft engine industry. By the end of WWII, however, there was a decline in urban areas and Paterson was no exception, and since the 1970s the city has suffered high unemployment rates ([[white flight]]).

Once a premier shopping and leisure destination of northern New Jersey, competition from the malls in upscale neighboring towns like [[Wayne, New Jersey|Wayne]] and [[Paramus, New Jersey|Paramus]] have forced the big-chain stores out of Paterson’s downtown. The biggest industries are now small businesses because the factories have moved overseas. However, the city still, as always, attracts many [[immigrants]], who have revived the city's economy, especially through small businesses.

The downtown area was struck by massive fires several times, most recently January 17, 1991. In this fire, a near full city block (bordered on the north and south by Main and Washington Street and on the east and west by Ellison Street and College Boulevard, a stretch of Van Houten Street that is dominated by [[Passaic County Community College]]) was engulfed in flames due to an electrical fire in the basement of a bar at 161 Main Street and spread to other buildings.&lt;ref&gt;[http://patersonfirejournal.blogspot.com/2008/06/last-alarm.html Paterson Fire Journal: Last Alarm]&lt;/ref&gt; Firefighter John A. Nicosia, 28, of Engine 4, went missing in the fire, having gotten lost in the basement. His body was located two days later.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news| url=http://www.nytimes.com/1991/01/21/nyregion/firefighter-s-body-is-found.html | work=[[The New York Times]] | title=Firefighter's Body Is Found | date=January 21, 1991}}&lt;/ref&gt; A plaque honoring his memory was later placed on a wall near the area. The area was so badly damaged that most of the burned buildings were demolished, with an outdoor mall standing in their place. The most notable of the destroyed buildings was the Meyer Brothers department store, which closed in 1987 and since had been parceled out.

Paterson boasts numerous locations on the [[National Register of Historic Places listings in Passaic County, New Jersey|National Register of Historic Places]], including museums, civic buildings such as [[Paterson City Hall|City Hall]], Hinchliffe Stadium, [[Public School Number Two]] and the [[Danforth Memorial Library]], churches ([[Cathedral of St. John the Baptist (Paterson, New Jersey)|Cathedral of St. John the Baptist]] and [[St. Michael's Roman Catholic Church]],) individual residences and districts of the city, such as the [[Paterson Downtown Commercial Historic District]], the [[Great Falls (Passaic River)|Great Falls/Society for the Establishment of Useful Manufactures Historic District]] and the Eastside Park Historic District.

In 2011, Paterson was severely affected in the aftermath of [[Hurricane Irene (2011)|Hurricane Irene]], particularly by flooding of the Passaic which led to the displacement of thousands and the closure of bridges over the river.&lt;ref&gt;{{Citation | last = dolnick  | first = Sam   | title = River, at 100-Year High, Ravages a City That Once Thrived on It  | newspaper = [[The New York Times]] | date = September 1, 2011    | url = http://www.nytimes.com/2011/09/01/nyregion/paterson-nj-is-devastated-by-floods-after-hurricane-irene.html | accessdate = 2011-09-11   }}&lt;/ref&gt; Touring the area on August 31 with [[Federal Emergency Management Agency]] Administrator [[Craig Fugate]], U.S. Homeland Security Secretary [[Janet Napolitano]] declared, &quot;This is as bad as I’ve seen, and I’ve been in eight states that have been impacted by Irene.&quot; The president the same day declared New Jersey a [[disaster area]],&lt;ref&gt;{{Citation | title = President Obama declares N.J. a disaster area as residents continue to deal with Hurricane Irene's impact  | newspaper = [[The Star-Ledger]] | date = September 1, 2011  | url = http://www.nj.com/news/index.ssf/2011/09/president_obama_declares_nj_a.html | accessdate = 2011-09-01 }}&lt;/ref&gt; and announced that he would visit the city.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news | last = Friedman | first = Matt | title = President Obama to visit Paterson to survey Hurricane Irene damage | newspaper = The Star-Ledger | date = August 31, 2011 | url = http://www.nj.com/news/index.ssf/2011/08/president_obama_to_visit_pater.html | accessdate = 2011-08-31 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Citation | last = Cityblog | title = Obama to visit Paterson on Sunday and the Overflowing Passaic River | newspaper = [[The New York Times]] | date = September 1, 2011 | url = http://cityroom.blogs.nytimes.com/2011/08/31/obama-to-visit-paterson-on-sunday-and-the-overflowing-passaic-river/ | accessdate = 2011-09-01   }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Jackson, Herb. [http://www.northjersey.com/news/national/obama_preview.html &quot;Paterson prepares for President Obama's visit today&quot;], ''[[The Record (Bergen County)]]'', September 4, 2011. Accessed September 4, 2011. &quot;Details are being tightly guarded about where President Obama will go Sunday when he visits Paterson to see the damage wrought by Hurricane Irene. Only Obama’s arrival at Newark Liberty International Airport is open to the press. The rest of his travels Sunday afternoon will be watched by a small group of pool reporters.&quot;&lt;/ref&gt;

==Geography==
Paterson is located at {{Coord|40.915498|-74.162927|type:city_region:US|format=dms|display=inline}} (40.915498, -74.162927){{GR|1}} in the [[Piedmont (United States)|Piedmont]] region between the [[Appalachian]] foothills and the [[Coastal Plain]].

the city has a total area of {{convert|8.73|sqmi}}, of which, {{convert|8.44|sqmi}} of it is land and {{convert|0.29|sqmi}} of it (2.74%) is water.&lt;ref name=CensusArea/&gt;

==Neighborhoods==
[[Image:Patercityhall.JPG|thumb|left|City Hall]]
{{Paterson, New Jersey neighborhoods}}
'''The Great Falls Historic District''' is the most famous neighborhood in Paterson, because of the landmark Great Falls of the Passaic River. The city has attempted to revitalize the area in recent years, including the installation of period lamp posts and the conversion of old industrial buildings into apartments and retail. Many artists live in this section of Paterson. A major redevelopment project is planned for this district in the coming years. The [[Paterson Museum]] of industrial history at [[Rogers Locomotive and Machine Works]] is situated in the Historic District.

'''[[Downtown Paterson]]''' is the main commercial district of the city and was once a shopping destination for northern New Jersey. After a devastating fire in 1902, the city rebuilt the downtown with massive [[Beaux-Arts architecture|Beaux-Arts-style]] buildings, many of which remain to this day. These buildings are usually four to seven stories tall. Downtown Paterson is home to [[Paterson City Hall]] and the Passaic County Courthouse Annex, two of the city's architectural landmarks. City Hall was designed by the New York firm [[Carrere and Hastings]] in 1894, and was modeled after the Hôtel de Ville (city hall) in [[Lyon, France]], capital of the silk industry in [[Europe]].

The former Orpheum Theatre located on Van Houten street, has been converted to a [[Mosque]] by The Islamic Foundation of New Jersey. The massive structure now known as Masjid Jalalabad, can accommodate 1,500 worshippers.

As with many other old downtown districts in the United States, Downtown Paterson suffered as shoppers and retailers moved to the [[suburban]] shopping malls of the region. Many historic buildings are in disrepair or are abandoned after years of neglect. In addition, Downtown Paterson is an [[Urban Enterprise Zone]]. The city has, in recent years, begun initiatives in hopes of reviving the downtown area. A project called the Center City project will convert a downtown parking lot into a commercial and entertainment center with office space. Downtown Paterson is located in the city's 1st Ward.

'''Eastside Park Historic District''' consists of about 1,000 homes in a variety of architectural styles, including [[Tudor Revival architecture|Tudors]], [[Colonial Revival architecture|Georgian colonials]], [[Victorian house|Victorians]], [[Italianate architecture|Italianate villas]] and [[Dutch Colonial Revival architecture|Dutch colonials]]. It is located east of downtown. Once the home of the city's industrial and political leaders, the neighborhood experienced a significant downturn as industry fled Paterson. In recent years, [[gentrification]] has begun to occur in the neighborhood and some of the area's historic houses have been restored. The Eastside Park Historic District is a state and nationally registered historic place. The jewel of the neighborhood is Eastside Park and the mansions that surround it. This section of Paterson once had a large [[American Jews|Jewish]] population that reached 40,000 at its peak, and there is still a [[synagogue]] left.&lt;ref&gt;Hyman, Vicki. [http://www.nj.com/homegarden/homeimprovement/index.ssf/2009/07/colonial_mansion_restored_in_p.html &quot;Colonial mansion restored in Paterson's once- (and again) grand Eastside Park&quot;], ''[[The Star-Ledger]]'', July 1, 2009. Accessed September 22, 2011. &quot;Smaller but no less spectacular examples of Tudor, Craftsman, Dutch Colonial, Federal, Greek Revival, Spanish and even mid-century modern homes sprang up over the next half-century. Eastside Park at one point was home to as many as 40,000 Jews, but they decamped rapidly to burgeoning suburbs starting in the late 1950s (though Temple Emanuel, the octogonal art deco neighborhood landmark, didn't pull up roots until 2005).&quot;&lt;/ref&gt; Eastside Park and what is commonly known as the Upper Eastside are located in Paterson's 3rd Ward. 

'''Manor Section''' is a residential neighborhood in Paterson. It is located east of East 33rd Street, north of Broadway and south-west of Route 20 and the [[Passaic River]]. The Manor section of Paterson is located in the city's 3rd Ward.

'''South Paterson''' is a diverse neighborhood in the city's 6th Ward with a significant [[Arab]] as well as [[Turkish people|Turkish]], and [[Hispanic]] community located east of Main Street and west of West Railway Avenue. A majority of the city's Arabs live in this section of Paterson. Many of the retail shops and restaurants cater to this community. The neighborhood is also characterized by [[Halal]] meat markets which offer goat and lamb, and shop signs in Arabic. South Paterson's Arab community is mostly made up of [[Jordanians]], [[Palestinians]], [[Demographics of Syria|Syrians]] and [[Lebanon|Lebanese]] people.&lt;ref&gt;La Valle-Finn, Lisa. [http://njmonthly.com/articles/lifestyle/people/living-the-dream.html &quot;Living The Dream: Palestinian traditions and American freedoms blend perfectly in Paterson.&quot;], ''[[New Jersey Monthly]]'', November 10, 2009. Accessed November 14, 2011.&lt;/ref&gt;

'''Lakeview''' is situated in the southern part of the city, the Lakeview Section is a [[middle class]] neighborhood. Interstate 80 runs north of this district. Lakeview is home to the Paterson Farmers Market, where people from all across North Jersey come to buy fresh produce. The neighborhood consists primarily of [[Hispanics]] and [[African American]]s, although this neighborhood also has a sizable [[Europe]]an descent, [[Middle-Eastern]] and [[Asian people|Asian]] population, including a significant [[Filipino American|Filipino]] presence. Lakeview also shares some of the same characteristics as neighboring [[Clifton, New Jersey|Clifton]] as they both share the neighborhood bearing the same name. The Lakeview section of Paterson is located in the city's 6th Ward.

'''Hillcrest''' is a large mostly residential, [[middle class]] [[enclave]], to the west of the downtown area. Its borders' limits are Preakness Avenue to the east, Cumberland Avenue to the west and Totowa Avenue along with West Side Park and the Passaic River to the south. Hillcrest is one of Paterson's most desirable neighborhoods. The Hillcrest section of Paterson is located in the city's 2nd Ward.

'''People's Park''' is a vibrant neighborhood located north of 23rd Avenue and South of Market Street.
Twenty-First Avenue or &quot;La Ventiuno&quot; as it's known by most of Paterson's Spanish-speaking community, is located in the People's Park section of Paterson. It is an active and vibrant retail strip featuring a variety of shops and services catering to a diverse clientele. Twenty First Avenue, home to SLD, used to have a large [[Italian people|Italian]] population. Although there is still a significant Italian presence left in the neighborhood, it also has a large first-generation [[Hispanic]] population, particularly [[Colombian people|Colombian]].

'''Wrigley Park''' is a neighborhood that has suffered from years of poverty, crime, and neglect. It is mostly [[African-American]]. Poverty, crime, open-air drug markets, prostitution, vacant lots, and boarded-up windows are common in this area. However, there are new houses being built and crime has dropped in recent years. This neighborhood is located north of Broadway.

'''Sandy Hill''' is a neighborhood in Paterson located roughly west of Madison Avenue, north of 21st Avenue, south of Park Avenue and east of Straight Street. Due to Paterson's significant population turn-over, this neighborhood is now home to a large Hispanic community, mostly first-generation [[Dominican Republic|Dominicans]]. The Sandy Hill section of Paterson is located in the city's 5th Ward. [[Roberto Clemente]] Park, which was originally known as Sandy Hill Park is located in this neighborhood.

'''Northside''', located north of Downtown, suffers from some of the social problems currently facing the Wrigley Park neighborhood but to a lesser extent. This neighborhood borders the boroughs of [[Haledon, New Jersey|Haledon]] and [[Prospect Park, New Jersey|Prospect Park]] and it is known for its hills and having sweeping views of [[New York City]]. The Northside section of Paterson is located in the city's 1st Ward.

'''Totowa Section''' is a large neighborhood located west of the [[Passaic River]], south-west of West Broadway and north-east of Preakness Avenue. It is mostly [[Hispanic]] but with an increasing [[South Asian]] community, mainly [[Bangladesh]]i. Many Bengali grocery stores and clothing stores are locating on Union Avenue and the surrounding streets. Masjid Al-Ferdous is located on Union Ave, which accommodates the daily Bangladeshi pedestrian population.

A large [[Italian people|Italian]] presence remains in this neighborhood. Many [[Peru]]vian and other [[Latin American cuisine|Latin American]] restaurants and businesses are located on Union Avenue. Colonial Village and Brooks Sloate Terraces are located in this neighborhood. The Totowa Section is located in parts of the 1st and 2nd Wards of Paterson.

'''Stoney Road''' is Paterson's most south-west neighborhood, bordering [[Woodland Park, New Jersey|Woodland Park]] to the south and Totowa across the Passaic River to the west. This neighborhood is home to Pennington Park, Hayden Heights, [[Lou Costello]] Pool, the Levine reservoir, Murray Avenue, Mc Bride Avenue and Garret Heights. A strong [[Italian people|Italian]] presence remains in this neighborhood. The Stoney Road section of Paterson is located in the city's 2nd Ward.

'''Riverside''' is a larger neighborhood in Paterson and, as its name states, this neighborhood is bound by the [[Passaic River]] to the north and east, separating the city from [[Hawthorne, New Jersey|Hawthorne]] and [[Fair Lawn, New Jersey|Fair Lawn]]. Riverside is a [[working-class]] neighborhood. The neighborhood is mostly residential with some industrial uses. Madison Avenue cuts through the heart of this district. Route 20 runs through the eastern border of Riverside providing an easy commute to Route 80 East and [[New York City]]. This section is ethnically diverse with a growing Hispanic community concentrating mostly north and along River Street. Many [[Albanians]] make their home in the East 18th Street and River Street areas. River View Terrace is located in this neighborhood. Riverside is located in parts of the 3rd and 4th Wards of Paterson.

'''Bunker Hill''' is a mostly [[industry|industrial]] area west of River Street and east of the Passaic River.

'''Westside Park''' located off Totowa Avenue and probably best known to young boys of days past for storing the Holland Submarine. Built in 1897 for the U.S. Navy, it became the target of graffiti artists because the fence surrounding it was too low and too close to the submarine itself. The sub is now located in the Great Falls State Park [http://www.patersongreatfalls.org/ Paterson Great Falls National Park], Paterson, NJ.

==Diversity==
Since its early beginnings, Paterson has been a melting pot.  [[Irish people|Irish]], [[Germans]], [[Dutch (ethnic group)|Dutch]] and [[Jews]] settled in the City in the 19th century. [[Italians|Italian]] and [[Eastern Europe]]an immigrants soon followed. As early as 1890, many [[Syria]]n and [[Lebanon|Lebanese]] immigrants also arrived in Paterson.

Many 2nd and 3rd generation [[Puerto Ricans in the United States|Puerto Ricans]] have been calling Paterson home since the 1950s but most recently first generation [[Dominican Republic|Dominican]], [[Peru]]vian, [[Colombia]]n, [[Mexican people|Mexican]], [[Central America]]n, and various [[South American]] immigrants have arrived.
Western Market Street, sometimes called [[Little Lima]] by tourists, is home to many [[Peru]]vian and other Latin-American businesses. In contrast if one travels east on Market Street, a heavy concentration of [[Dominican Republic|Dominican]]-owned restaurants, beauty salons, barber shops and other businesses can be seen. The Great Falls Historic District, Cianci Street, Union Avenue and 21st Avenue have several Italian businesses. To the north of the Great Falls is a fast-growing [[Bangladesh]]i population. Park Avenue and Market Street between Straight Street and Madison Avenue is heavily [[Dominican Republic|Dominican]] and [[Puerto Rican American|Puerto Rican]]. Main Street, just south of downtown, is heavily Mexican with a declining [[Puerto-Rican]] community.  [[Costa Ricans]] and other [[Central American]] immigrant communities are growing in the Riverside and Peoples Park neighborhoods. Broadway or Martin Luther King Jr. Way is predominantly black, as is the Fourth Ward and parts of Eastside and Northside. Paterson's black community is made up of a declining population of [[African Americans]] of Southern heritage and more recent [[Caribbean]] and [[African]] immigrants. Main Street between the [[Clifton, New Jersey|Clifton]] border and Madison Avenue is heavily [[Turkish people|Turkish]] and [[Arab]]. 21st Avenue in the People's Park section is characterized by [[Colombia]]n and other [[Latin America]]n restaurants and shops.

Every summer, Patersonians have enjoyed an African-American Day Parade, a Dominican Day Parade, a Puerto Rican Day Parade, a Peruvian Day Parade, and a Turkish-American Day Parade, though budget cuts in 2011 have meant that parade organizers have been asked to contribute to cover the costs of police and other municipal services.&lt;ref&gt;Schectman, Joel; and Patberg, Zach. [http://www.northjersey.com/news/123730599_Budget_cuts_doom_ethnic_parades.html &quot;Ethnic parades in Paterson likely to be victims of city budget stress&quot;], ''[[The Record (Bergen County)]]'', June 13, 2011. Accessed September 4, 2011. &quot;The Puerto Rican, Dominican and African-American parades, which attracted tens of thousands of people, face shutdown after Mayor Jeffery Jones demanded that organizers pay as much as $100,000 for police and cleanup after the event.... Peruvians were set to celebrate their 25th annual parade in Paterson next month. The event has brought in more than 35,000 people from as far away as Florida.&quot;&lt;/ref&gt;

Paterson is considered by many the capital of the [[Peru]]vian [[Diaspora]] in the U.S. Paterson's Peruvian community celebrates what is known as [[Señor de los Milagros]] or &quot;Our Lord of Miracles&quot; in English on October 18 through 28th of every year. In the 2000 Census, 4.72% of residents listed themselves as being of [[Peruvian American]] ancestry, the third-highest percentage of the population of any municipality in New Jersey and the United States, behind [[East Newark, New Jersey|East Newark]] with 10.1% and [[Harrison, New Jersey|Harrison]] with 7.01%.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.epodunk.com/ancestry/Peruvian.html Peruvian Communities], [[EPodunk]]. Accessed July 19, 2011.&lt;/ref&gt;

Paterson is home to the third-largest Dominican-American Community in the United States, after [[New York City]] and [[Lawrence, Massachusetts]]. In the 2000 Census, 10.27% of residents listed themselves as being of [[Dominican American]] ancestry, the eighth highest percentage of the population of any municipality in the United States and the third highest percentage in New Jersey, behind [[Perth Amboy, New Jersey|Perth Amboy]]'s 18.81% and [[Union City, New Jersey|Union City's]] 11.46%.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.epodunk.com/ancestry/Dominican-Republic.html Dominican Republic Ancestry], [[EPodunk]]. Accessed July 19, 2011.&lt;/ref&gt;

Paterson is home to the largest [[Turks in the United States|Turkish-American]] immigrant community in the United States ([[Little Istanbul]]) and the second largest [[Arab American|Arab-American]] community after [[Dearborn, Michigan]].&lt;ref name=ST2004/&gt; The Greater Paterson area which includes the cities of [[Clifton, New Jersey|Clifton]] and [[Wayne, New Jersey|Wayne]] and the boroughs of [[Haledon, New Jersey|Haledon]], [[Prospect Park, New Jersey|Prospect Park]], [[North Haledon, New Jersey|North Haledon]], [[Totowa, New Jersey|Totowa]], [[Woodland Park, New Jersey|Woodland Park]], and [[Little Falls, New Jersey|Little Falls]], is home to the nation's largest [[North Caucasian peoples|North Caucasian]] population, mostly [[Adyghe people|Circassians]], [[Karachays]], and a small [[Chechens|Chechen]] community. Reflective of these communities, Paterson and Prospect Park public schools observe [[Muslim holidays]].

Paterson has incorporated a rapidly growing [[Bangladeshi American]] community, the largest in the United States outside [[New York City]]. A branch of the Sonali Exchange Company Inc. has opened on Union Avenue in the Totowa Section; the Sonali Exchange Company is a subsidiary of [[Sonali Bank]], the largest state-owned commercial bank in [[Bangladesh]].

==The greater Paterson area==
The following municipalities border Paterson and are considered to be its [[suburb]]s: The boroughs of [[Prospect Park, New Jersey|Prospect Park]], [[Haledon, New Jersey|Haledon]], [[Totowa, New Jersey|Totowa]], [[Woodland Park, New Jersey|Woodland Park]] (formerly West Paterson), and [[Hawthorne, New Jersey|Hawthorne]], the township of [[Wayne, New Jersey|Wayne]], and the City of [[Clifton, New Jersey|Clifton]], all in Passaic County; and the boroughs of [[Elmwood Park, New Jersey|Elmwood Park]] (formerly East Paterson) and [[Fair Lawn, New Jersey|Fair Lawn]] in [[Bergen County, New Jersey|Bergen County]].

==Demographics==
{{USCensusPop
| 1840=7596
| 1850=11334
| 1860=19586
| 1870=33579
| 1880=51031
| 1890=78347
| 1900=105171
| 1910=125600
| 1920=135875
| 1930=138513
| 1940=139656
| 1950=139336
| 1960=143663
| 1970=144824
| 1980=137970
| 1990=140891
| 2000=149222
| 2010=146199
| footnote=Population sources:&lt;br&gt;&lt;small&gt;1860-1930&lt;ref&gt;[http://books.google.com/books?id=kifRAAAAMAAJ&amp;pg=PA712 &quot;Fifteenth Census of the United States: 1930 - Population Volume I&quot;], [[United States Census Bureau]]. Accessed November 28, 2011.&lt;/ref&gt; 1930-1990&lt;ref&gt;[http://web.archive.org/web/20090502173646/http://www.wnjpin.net/OneStopCareerCenter/LaborMarketInformation/lmi01/poptrd6.htm New Jersey Resident Population by Municipality: 1930 - 1990], Workforce New Jersey Public Information Network, backed up by the [[Internet Archive]] as of May 2, 2009. Accessed July 6, 2011.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
  |url=http://www.census.gov/population/www/documentation/twps0027.html
  |title=Population of the 100 Largest Cities and Other Urban Places in The United States: 1790 to 1990
  |author=Campbell Gibson
  |publisher=[[United States Census Bureau]]
  |month=June | year=1998
  |accessdate=2007-03-06}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;br&gt;2000&lt;ref name=Census2000/&gt; 2010&lt;ref name=Districts2011/&gt;&lt;ref name=Census2010/&gt;&lt;ref name=Census2010XLS/&gt;&lt;ref name=Census2010Press&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.census.gov/newsroom/releases/archives/2010_census/cb11-cn15.html|title=U.S. Census Bureau Delivers New Jersey's 2010 Census Population Totals|date=2011-02-03|publisher=[[United States Census Bureau]]|accessdate=2011-02-05}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;/small&gt;
}}
The [[2010 United States Census]] reported that there were 146,199 people, 44,329 households and 32,731 families residing in the city. The racial makeup of Paterson was 50,706 (34.7%) [[White (U.S. Census)|White]], 46,314 (31.7%) [[African American (U.S. Census)|African American]], 1,547 (1.1%) [[Native American (U.S. Census)|Native American]], 4,878 (3.3%) [[Asian (U.S. Census)|Asian]], 60 (0.0%) [[Pacific Islander (U.S. Census)|Pacific Islander]], 34,999 (23.9%) from [[Race (United States Census)|other races]], and 7,695 (5.3%) from two or more races.  [[Hispanic (U.S. Census)|Hispanic]] or [[Latino (U.S. Census)|Latino]] of any race were 84,254 persons (57.6%).&lt;ref name=Census2010&gt;[http://factfinder2.census.gov/bkmk/table/1.0/en/DEC/10_DP/DPDP1/0600000US3403157000 DP-1 - Profile of General Population and Housing Characteristics: 2010 for Paterson city, Passaic County, New Jersey], [[United States Census Bureau]]. Accessed November 28, 2011.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=LWD2010&gt;[http://lwd.dol.state.nj.us/labor/lpa/census/2010/dp/dp1_pas/paterson1.pdf Table DP-1. Profile of General Demographic Characteristics: 2010 for Paterson city], [[New Jersey Department of Labor and Workforce Development]]. Accessed November 27, 2011.&lt;/ref&gt;

As of the [[census]]{{GR|2}} of 2000, there were 149,222 people, 44,710 households, and 33,353 families residing in the city, for a [[population density]] of 17,675.4 per square mile (6,826.4/km&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt;).&lt;ref name=Census2000&gt;[http://factfinder.census.gov/servlet/SAFFFacts?_event=ChangeGeoContext&amp;geo_id=16000US3457000&amp;_geoContext=01000US|04000US34|16000US3401090&amp;_street=&amp;_county=paterson&amp;_cityTown=paterson&amp;_state=04000US34&amp;_zip=&amp;_lang=en&amp;_sse=on&amp;ActiveGeoDiv=geoSelect&amp;_useEV=&amp;pctxt=fph&amp;pgsl=010&amp;_submenuId=factsheet_1&amp;ds_name=DEC_2000_SAFF&amp;_ci_nbr=null&amp;qr_name=null&amp;reg=null%3Anull&amp;_keyword=&amp;_industry= Census 2000 Demographic Profile Highlights: Paterson city, New Jersey], [[United States Census Bureau]]. Accessed September 4, 2011.&lt;/ref&gt; Among cities with a population higher than 100,000, Paterson is the second most densely populated large city in the United States, only after [[New York City]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.census.gov/statab/ccdb/cit1040r.txt Cities with 100,000 or More Population in 2000 ranked by Population per Square Mile, 2000 in Rank Order], [[United States Census Bureau]]. Accessed September 5, 2011.&lt;/ref&gt;

There were 47,169 housing units at an average density of 5,587.2 per square mile (2,157.8/km&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt;). The racial makeup of the city was 32.90% [[African American (U.S. Census)|African American]], 13.20% [[White (U.S. Census)|White]], 0.60% [[Native American (U.S. Census)|Native American]], 1.90% [[Asian (U.S. Census)|Asian]], 0.06% [[Pacific Islander (U.S. Census)|Pacific Islander]], 27.60% from [[Race (United States Census)|other races]] which many Latinos identify with, and 6.17% from two or more races. [[Latino (U.S. Census)|Latino]] of any race were 50.1% of the population.&lt;ref name=Census2000/&gt; The majority of Latinos are [[Puerto Ricans in the United States|Puerto Rican]] 14%, [[Dominican Americans|Dominican]] 10%, [[Peruvian American|Peruvian]] 5% and [[Colombian American|Colombian]] 3%. Paterson's rapidly growing [[Bangladeshi American]], [[Turkish American]], [[Arab American]],&lt;ref name=ST2004&gt;via [[Associated Press]]. [http://seattletimes.nwsource.com/html/nationworld/2002057985_webmuslims08.html &quot;Muslims could prove key in choosing next U.S. president&quot;], ''[[The Seattle Times]]'', October 8, 2004. Accessed July 17, 2011. &quot;... Paterson, which is the nation's second-largest Arab-American community after the Dearborn, Mich.-area.&quot;&lt;/ref&gt; and [[Peruvian American]] communities are among the largest and most prominent in the United States, the latter owing partially to the presence of the [[Consulate]] of [[Peru]]. Paterson's [[Muslim]] population has been estimated at 25,000 to 30,000.&lt;ref name=Reuters/&gt;

There were 44,710 households out of which 40.9% had children under the age of 18 living with them, 39.4% were [[Marriage|married couples]] living together, 26.8% had a female householder with no husband present, and 25.4% were non-families. 20.4% of all households were made up of individuals and 7.9% had someone living alone who was 65 years of age or older. The average household size was 3.25 and the average family size was 3.71.&lt;ref name=Census2000/&gt;

In the city the population was spread out with 29.8% under the age of 18, 11.2% from 18 to 24, 32.0% from 25 to 44, 18.7% from 45 to 64, and 8.3% who were 65 years of age or older. The median age was 30 years. For every 100 females there were 94.4 males. For every 100 females age 18 and over, there were 91.1 males.&lt;ref name=Census2000/&gt;

The median income for a household in the city was $30,127, and the median income for a family was $32,983. Males had a median income of $27,911 versus $21,733 for females. The [[per capita income]] for the city was $13,257. About 19.2% of families and 22.2% of the population were below the [[poverty line]], including 29.0% of those under age 18 and 19.4% of those age 65 or over.&lt;ref name=Census2000/&gt;

==Government==
===Local government===
The City of Paterson Municipal Council was created as a result of a 1974 decision to change its form of government from a 1907 statute-based form, to a [[Faulkner Act (New Jersey)|Faulkner Act]] Plan-D [[Faulkner Act (Mayor-Council)|Mayor-Council]] form.&lt;ref&gt;''2005 New Jersey Legislative District Data Book'', [[Rutgers University]] [[Edward J. Bloustein School of Planning and Public Policy]], April 2005, p. 151.&lt;/ref&gt;

The 1907 statute-based form consisted of various boards. A Board of Aldermen, Board of Finance, Board of Health, Board of Public Works, Board of Fire and Police Commissioners.

The Mayor-Council plan consisted of the [[Mayor of Paterson, New Jersey]] and nine Council members. Six of the Council members represent the city's six wards while the other three are elected as [[at-large]] members by the entire city. The Municipal Council has the responsibility of reviewing and approving Municipal legislation.

Under the Mayor-Council plan, the Mayor is the chief executive and is responsible for administering the City's activities. The Mayor is elected for a four-year term by the citizens and is responsible for them. His/Her function includes enforcing the charter and the ordinances and laws passed by the City Council. The Mayor appoints all department heads including the business administrator, with the advise and consent of the Council s/he may also remove and or all department heads after giving them notice and an opportunity to be heard.

With the assistance of the business administrator, the Mayor is responsible for preparation of the municipal budget. The Mayor submits the budget to the Council along with a detailed analysis of expenditures and revenues. The Council may reduce any item or items in the budget by a majority vote, but can only increase an item by a two-thirds vote.

{{asof|2011}}, the [[Mayor of Paterson, New Jersey]] is Jeffrey Jones, who defeated two-term incumbent Jose &quot;Joey&quot; Torres in the May 2010 Paterson elections and was sworn into office on July 1, 2010.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.northjersey.com/news/070110_Patersons_new_mayor_sworn_in.html Jeffery Jones sworn in, vows more open Paterson&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt; City Council Members are Council President Aslon Goow, Sr. (Second Ward), Vice President Anthony Davis (First Ward), Vera Ames (Fourth Ward), William C. McKoy (Third Ward), Ken Morris, Jr. (At-Large), Rigo Rodriguez (At-Large), Andre Sayegh (Sixth Ward), Julio Tavarez (Fifth Ward) and Benjie E. Wimberly (At-Large).&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.patersonnj.gov/council/ City Council], City of Paterson. Accessed February 27, 2011.&lt;/ref&gt;

In the May 2010 Paterson city elections, City Council President Jeff Jones defeated the incumbent mayor Joey Torres in a three-way election with sixth ward councilman Andre Sayegh.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.northjersey.com/news/051110_Jones_wins_mayors_seat_in_Paterson.html Jeffery Jones wins mayor's seat in Paterson upset&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt; Incumbent Councilman At-Large Kenneth Morris was returned to office and Paterson recreation director and former Paterson Catholic football coach Benjie Wimberly was elected to one of the other At-Large seats.&lt;ref name=&quot;northjersey.com&quot;&gt;[http://www.northjersey.com/news/051110_Wimberlie_Patersons_recreation_director_wins_city_council_seat.html Wimberly, Paterson’s recreation director, wins city council seat&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;

The third Council At-Large position has been in dispute since the results of the May 2010 election, where newcomer Kenneth McDaniel and incumbent councilman Rigo Rodriguez have engaged in various court battles over the results of the election.&lt;ref name=&quot;northjersey.com&quot;/&gt; When the initial count was completed McDaniel was ahead of Rodriguez by 25 votes. An automatic recount was conducted and Rodriguez gained nineteen votes, with 49 mail-in ballots in dispute. A New Jersey court ruled that 47 of the ballots had to be counted, and Rodriguez's name was on all 47. This gave the councilman a 41-vote victory and he was sworn in with the rest of the council in July 2010.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.northjersey.com/news/060210_Mail-in_ballots_put_Rodriguez_on_top_in_Paterson_council_race.html Mail-in ballots put Rodriguez on top in Paterson council race&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt; McDaniel has continued to insist the ballots were tampered with and filed a motion in state court to overturn the results of the election, but the same judge that ordered the recount dismissed his motion.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.northjersey.com/news/104622224_Judge_finds_no_evidence_of_voter_fraud.html Judge finds no evidence of voter fraud in Paterson&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt; However, McDaniel appealed to New Jersey Attorney General [[Paula Dow]] to investigate, and the resulting findings caused several Rodriguez aides to be arrested on November 30 and December 1, 2010 and eventually the councilman himself on December 2, 2010 on charges of witness tampering in the court case where McDaniel's claim was dismissed.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.politicsdaily.com/2010/12/02/winning-candidate-arrested-in-new-jersey-voter-fraud-case/?icid=maing|main5|1|link4|28983 Winning Candidate Arrested in New Jersey Voter Fraud Case&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;

The status of the Fourth Ward seat currently held by Vera Ames-Garnes is in question as well. Councilwoman Ames-Garnes is standing trial in a [[Hawthorne, New Jersey]] court on a disorderly persons charge. The councilwoman was arrested by a [[Prospect Park, New Jersey]] police officer after she allegedly interfered with a traffic stop the officer made in Paterson after the suspect in the incident crossed over from Prospect Park into Paterson. Ames-Garnes contends that the officer had no right to issue a summons to the suspect, a Paterson resident, while the officer maintains the infraction occurred in Prospect Park and Ames-Garnes' interference was unwarranted. In December 2010 the trial concluded with the councilwoman being convicted, but she was only required to pay a fine and was not forced to forfeit her office. As of January 3, 2011, the Passaic County Prosecutor's Office has not decided whether it will appeal the decision to allow Ames-Garnes to keep her office.

===Federal, state and county representation===
Paterson is in the 8th Congressional district and is part of New Jersey's 35th state legislative district.&lt;ref name=LWV&gt;[http://www.lwvnj.org/pubs/CG-2011.pdf#page=62 2011 New Jersey Citizen's Guide to Government], New Jersey [[League of Women Voters]], p. 62. Accessed September 4, 2011.&lt;/ref&gt; The legislative district was kept unchanged by the [[New Jersey Apportionment Commission]] based on the results of the 2010 Census.&lt;ref name=Districts2011&gt;[http://www.njelections.org/2011-legislative-districts/towns-alpha.pdf#page=8 2011 Apportionment Redistricting: Municipalities sorted alphabetically], [[Secretary of State of New Jersey|New Jersey Department of State]], p. 8. Accessed September 4, 2011.&lt;/ref&gt;

{{NJ Congress 08}} {{NJ Senate}}

{{NJ Legislative 35}} {{NJ Governor}}

{{NJ Passaic County Freeholders}}

==Emergency services==

The City of Paterson is served by a professional police department&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.patersonnj.gov/department/index.php?fDD=5-0 Paterson Police Department], City of Paterson. Accessed November 14, 2011.&lt;/ref&gt; and [[Paterson Fire Department|fire department]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.patersonfd.com/ Paterson Fire Department]&lt;/ref&gt; The Paterson Fire Department is also responsible for the city's [[Emergency Medical Services]] division and ambulance units.

In addition to local services, Paterson is home to the Passaic County [[Sheriffs in the United States|Sheriff's]] Office Courts Division in the Passaic County Courthouse and Correctional Division in the Passaic County Jail.

In April 2011, Paterson was forced to layoff 125 police officers, nearly 25% of the total force in the city, due to severe budget constraints caused by a $70 million deficit.&lt;ref&gt;Patberg, Zach. [http://www.northjersey.com/news/041811_Paterson_layoff_of_125_police_officers_draws_protests.html &quot;Paterson layoff of 125 police officers draws protests&quot;], ''[[The Record (Bergen County)]]'', April 18, 2011. Accessed September 4, 2011.&lt;/ref&gt; At the same time, the [[Guardian Angels]], a New York City-based volunteer citizen safety patrol organization, began operating in Paterson at the invitation of the Mayor.&lt;ref&gt;Lynn, Kathleen. [http://www.northjersey.com/news/041711_Guardian_Angels_begin_Paterson_patrols.html &quot;Guardian Angels begin Paterson patrols&quot;], ''[[The Record (Bergen County)]]'', April 17, 2011. Accessed September 4, 2011. &quot;Responding to the layoffs of 125 Paterson police officers, the New York City-based Guardian Angels began patrols in the city Sunday. The Guardian Angels arrived in Paterson on Sunday to begin patrolling the city.The 18 Angels, in signature red jackets and berets, were greeted in front of City Hall by Mayor Jeffery Jones, who had invited the volunteer safety patrol organization in February as the city’s budget problems deepened.&quot;&lt;/ref&gt;

St. Joseph's Regional Medical Center is a large institution providing comprehensive emergency services as well as non-emergent medical care to Paterson and the surrounding community.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.stjosephshealth.org/index.php/sjrmc-home-page Home page], St. Joseph's Regional Medical Center. Accessed September 4, 2011.&lt;/ref&gt;

==Commerce==
Portions of Paterson are part of an [[Urban Enterprise Zone]]. In addition to other benefits to encourage employment within the Zone, shoppers can take advantage of a reduced 3½% [[sales tax]] rate (versus the 7% rate charged statewide).&lt;ref&gt;[http://replay.waybackmachine.org/20090525053101/http://www.state.nj.us/njbusiness/financing/tax/geographic.shtml#2 Geographic &amp; Urban Redevelopment Tax Credit Programs: Urban Enterprise Zone Employee Tax Credit], State of [[New Jersey]], backed up by the [[Internet Archive]] as of May 25, 2009. Accessed July 19, 2011.&lt;/ref&gt;

==Transportation==
The city is served by the [[New Jersey Transit]] [[Main Line (NJ Transit)|Main Line]] [[commuter rail]] service, with the [[Paterson (NJT station)|station]] located in [[Downtown Paterson]]. Plans are being developed for Paterson to receive new commuter rail service on the existing [[New York, Susquehanna and Western Railway|NYS&amp;W]] line, which is currently single-tracked. This rail line would be called the [[Passaic-Bergen Rail Line]] and would have five stops in Paterson.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.njtransit.com/tm/tm_servlet.srv?hdnPageAction=PressReleaseTo&amp;PRESS_RELEASE_ID=2313 &quot;PASSAIC-BERGEN RAIL PLAN ADVANCES: NJT Board amends contract to cover final design expenses&quot;], [[New Jersey Transit]] press release dated April 18, 2007. Accessed July 19, 2011.&lt;/ref&gt;

Bus service to locations in Passaic, [[Bergen County, New Jersey|Bergen]], [[Essex County, New Jersey|Essex]] and [[Hudson County, New Jersey|Hudson]] counties is provided by [[New Jersey Transit]], making the city a regional transit hub. The [[Broadway Bus Terminal (Paterson)|Broadway Bus Terminal]], also downtown, is the terminus for many NJ Transit bus lines 

Service to the [[Port Authority Bus Terminal]] in [[Midtown Manhattan]] is offered on the [[161 (New Jersey bus)|161]] and the [[190 (New Jersey bus)|190]], by the [[171 (New Jersey bus)|171]] to the [[George Washington Bridge Bus Terminal]] in [[Washington Heights, Manhattan]], on the [[72 (New Jersey bus)|72]] to [[Newark, New Jersey|Newark]], with local service provided on the [[74 (New Jersey bus)|74]], [[702 (New Jersey bus)|702]], [[703 (New Jersey bus)|703]], [[704 (New Jersey bus)|704]], [[707 (New Jersey bus)|707]], [[712 (New Jersey bus)|712]], [[722 (New Jersey bus)|722]], [[742 (New Jersey bus)|742]] (Saturday only), [[744 (New Jersey bus)|744]], [[746 (New Jersey bus)|746]], [[748 (New Jersey bus)|748]], [[770 (New Jersey bus)|770]], [[970 (New Jersey bus)|970]] and [[971 (New Jersey bus)|971]] routes.&lt;ref&gt;[http://web.archive.org/web/20090522212307/http://www.njtransit.com/sf/sf_servlet.srv?hdnPageAction=BusRoutesPassaicCountyTo Passaic County Bus/Rail Connections], [[New Jersey Transit]], backed up by the [[Internet Archive]] as of May 22, 2009. Accessed July 19, 2011.&lt;/ref&gt; City Hall has many buses that stop at or near it, going to various points in the area, including New York and the neighboring communities. Service to Manhattan and shopping centers in Bergen County is also provided by independent bus carriers.

By road, Paterson is served directly by [[Route 80 (New Jersey)|Interstate Route 80]], as well as State Routes [[Route 4 (New Jersey)|4]], [[Route 19 (New Jersey)|19]] and [[Route 20 (New Jersey)|20]]. United States Route [[Route 46 (New Jersey)|46]], the [[Garden State Parkway]], and State Routes [[Route 3 (New Jersey)|3]], [[Route 17 (New Jersey)|17]], [[Route 21 (New Jersey)|21]] and [[Route 208 (New Jersey)|208]] are also nearby and serve as feeder roads to the community.

Paterson also served as the terminus for numerous major secondary roads in northern New Jersey.  The [[Paterson Plank Road]] linked the city to Jersey City and eventually the Hudson River waterfront in Hoboken, while the Paterson-Hamburg Turnpike connected the city with Sussex County along what is now parts of [[State Route 23 (New Jersey)|State Route 23]].

==Education==
The [[Paterson Public Schools]] serve students in kindergarten through twelfth grade and also includes the Paterson Charter School for Science and Technology. The district is one of 31 [[Abbott District]]s statewide.&lt;ref&gt;[http://replay.waybackmachine.org/20090515214519/http://www.nj.gov/cgi-bin/education/abbotts/abbotturls.pl?string=code&amp;maxhits=100 Abbott Districts], [[New Jersey Department of Education]], backed up by the [[Internet Archive]] as of May 15, 2009. Accessed July 19, 2011.&lt;/ref&gt; The school system has over 30,000 students who speak 25 different languages. The school system currently has 52 schools with over 6,000 employees, with a per pupil expenditure of nearly $16,000, of which $8,148 goes towards classroom instruction.

In 2011, all of Paterson's high schools were changed to theme schools, as part of a goal to give students a better choice in areas they wanted to pursue.&lt;ref&gt;Brody, Leslie. [http://www.northjersey.com/news/030711_Paterson_to_split_JFK_high_school_into_four_academies.html &quot;Paterson to split JFK high school into four academies&quot;], ''[[The Record (Bergen County)]]'', March 7, 2011. Accessed November 14, 2011. &quot;Paterson school officials will split the troubled John F. Kennedy High School into four smaller academies so that starting next fall, all public high school students in the city will be enrolled in a “choice’’ magnet school.&quot;&lt;/ref&gt;

However the school system in the city has a very poor record in terms of education. A recent statement made by the school broad had declared that out of the city's 30,000 students K-12 only 15,000 ever graduate from the districts high schools. Despite many attempts to improve the over all education outlook, many of the programs have yet to make any real changes. With the city's test scores lacking in many areas, control by the State of NJ was almost certain. In 1988, New Jersey became the first state in the nation to authorize its State Department of Education to take over local school districts that were failing according to an established monitoring process. In 1991, the city of Paterson became the second of the three troubled districts forced to cede control of its public schools to the state.&lt;ref&gt;Staff. [http://www.nytimes.com/1991/08/08/nyregion/state-seizes-paterson-schools.html &quot;State Seizes Paterson Schools&quot;], ''[[The New York Times]]'', August 8, 1991. Accessed November 14, 2011. &quot;The New Jersey Board of Education today seized administrative control of the Paterson schools, thus placing two of the three largest districts in the state under its control.&quot;&lt;/ref&gt; The presumption was that improvement would follow. To date, Paterson Public schools are still controlled by the [[State of New Jersey Department of Education]]. As such, Paterson public schools are managed by a state-appointed Superintendent and a School Advisory Board that serves in an advisory capacity only.

The city is host to the state's annual robotics competition that is held at [[Passaic County Community College]]. The competition called the North Jersey Robotics Competition or NJRC began with the idea to place high educational merit on the students of Paterson.  The competition brings schools from around NJ, to take part in the event. Three events make up the meet which takes place on two different days. As of 2011 the competition has gone on for 10 years. With the 2011 winner being Panther high school of Paterson, New Jersey. 

[[Paterson Catholic High School]], formerly the city's only remaining Catholic high school, was closed by the [[Roman Catholic Diocese of Paterson]] at the end of the 2009-10 academic year, which cited declining enrollment and financial difficulties as reasons for the closure.&lt;ref&gt;Naanes, Marlene. [http://www.northjersey.com/news/education/042110_Paterson_Catholic_to_close_by_end_of_school_year.html &quot;Paterson Catholic to close by end of school year&quot;], ''[[The Record (Bergen County)]]'', April 21, 2010. Accessed June 21, 2011. &quot;Paterson Catholic Regional High School, which has prided itself for four decades on serving some of the area’s poorest and immigrant families, will close its doors the diocese said Wednesday, citing enormous debt, plummeting donations and a bad economy.&quot;&lt;/ref&gt;

==Arts and recreation==

Paterson boasts a significant parks and recreation system, including larger areas such as Eastside, Westside and Pennington Parks, as well as neighborhood parks such as Wrigley, Robert Clemente, and People's. The [[Great Falls (Passaic River)|Great Falls of the Passaic]] are part of the state, and unofficially the national, park system.

{{Main|Paterson Museum}}
The [[Paterson Museum]], located in the [[Great Falls Historic District]], was founded in 1925 and is owned and operated by the city of Paterson. Its mission is to preserve and display the industrial history of the city. Since 1982 the museum has been housed in the Thomas Rogers Building on Market Street, the former erecting shop of [[Rogers Locomotive and Machine Works]], a major 19th-century manufacturer of railroad steam locomotives.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.patersonnj.gov/department/index.php?fDD=24-0 Paterson Museum], City of Paterson. Accessed November 14, 2011.&lt;/ref&gt;

{{Main|Lambert Castle}}
Belle Vista, locally known as [[Belle Vista (Paterson, New Jersey)|Lambert Castle]], was built in 1892 as the home of [[Catholina Lambert]], the self-made owner of a prominent silk mill in Paterson. After Lambert's death in 1923, his family sold the building to the city, which in turn sold it to the County of Passaic a few years later. The county used the building for administrative offices, and in 1936, provided one room to the fledgling Passaic County Historical Society to serve as its historical museum. As time went by the museum grew, room by room, until the entire first floor became the historical museum. 

In the late 1990s, the Castle underwent a multi-million dollar restoration and all four floors of the building were developed into a museum and library. Today, Passaic County remains the owner of the building and generously supports the facilities' operation; however, the Passaic County Historical Society is solely responsible for the operation and management of Lambert Castle Museum with its historical period rooms, long-term and changing exhibition galleries, educational programs for elementary and middle-school students, and research library/archive.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.lambertcastle.org/ Lambert Castle], Passaic County Historical Society. Accessed November 14, 2011.&lt;/ref&gt;

Above Lambert Castle stands an 75-foot observation tower, located at the peak of [[Watchung Mountains|Garret Mountain]], which while technically standing in [[Woodland Park, New Jersey|Woodland Park]], was constructed when the property was considered part of Paterson. The tower is part of the [[Garret Mountain Reservation]] and was recently renovated to its original condition as built by Lambert in 1896, who used the tower to impress guests with its view of the [[New York City skyline]].

Attempts are being made to fund the restoration of the [[Paterson Armory]] as a recreation and cultural center.

==Sister cities==
[[Sister cities]] of Paterson include:
*{{flagicon|Turkey}} [[Eskişehir]], [[Turkey]], May 22, 2002 &lt;ref&gt;[http://www.eskisehir-bld.gov.tr/spot_kardes_sehir.php Eskisehir Municipality's Sister Cities List ]&lt;/ref&gt;
*[[Lyon]], [[France]]{{citation needed|date=November 2011}}
*[[Lowell, Massachusetts]]{{citation needed|date=November 2011}}

==In popular culture==
Paterson is the subject of [[William Carlos Williams]]' five-book epic poem ''[[Paterson (poem)|Paterson]]'', a cornerstone work of modern American poetry.&lt;ref name=Reuters/&gt; Paterson is also mentioned in the twelfth line of Part 1 of [[Allen Ginsberg]]'s poem ''[[Howl]]''. 

Paterson is the setting of many of [[Junot Diaz]]'s short stories and novels, including the Pulitzer Prize-winning [[The Brief Wondrous Life of Oscar Wao]], and [[John Updike]]'s 1997 novel ''[[In the Beauty of the Lilies]].''

The controversial arrest and conviction of boxer [[Rubin &quot;Hurricane&quot; Carter]], whose conviction was overturned in 1985, as dramatized in the [[1999 in film|1999]] [[Denzel Washington]] film, ''[[The Hurricane (1999 film)|The Hurricane]]'', partially shot in the city.&lt;ref name=Reuters/&gt; The lyrics of the [[Bob Dylan]] song [[Hurricane (song)|&quot;Hurricane&quot;]] include ''&quot;In Paterson that's just the way things go / If you're Black you might as well not show / Up on the street / Unless you want to draw the heat&quot;''. ''[[Lean on Me (film)|Lean On Me]]'' is based on events that occurred in Paterson's Eastside High School.&lt;ref name=LeanOnMe/&gt; ''[[Alice, Sweet Alice]]'' (1976) with [[Brooke Shields]] was filmed entirely in Paterson, the director's hometown.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.terrortrap.com/honorablementions/alicesweetalice/ The Terror Trap: Alice Sweet Alice]&lt;/ref&gt; as was ''[[State Property (film)|State Property]]''.{{Citation needed|date=May 2010}}. Its sequel, ''[[State Property 2]]'', and  ''[[Far from Heaven]]'', ''[[The Preacher's Wife]]'', and ''[[Purple Rose of Cairo]]'' are the among the other films also partially shot Paterson.

[[Paterson Falls]] was featured in the first season of ''[[The Sopranos]]'' in the episode ''[[Pax Soprana (The Sopranos episode)|Pax Soprana]]'' as the place where [[Junior Soprano]]'s friend, Capri's grandson committed suicide after taking poor designer drugs. As a favor, Junior Soprano had [[List of characters from The Sopranos#Mikey Palmice|Mikey Palmice]] and another individual toss the dealer, [[List of characters from The Sopranos in the DiMeo Crime Family#Rusty Irish|Rusty Irish]], over the falls. Some interior shots for the show were filmed in the unused [[Barnert Hospital]]. The Sopranos also shot a scene at Ralph Piccolo Pizza and renamed it &quot;UF-FA'S Pizzeria&quot;  

The Band [[Blanks 77]], an American punk rock band Founding member lived in Paterson. Founded in 1991.{{Citation needed|date=May 2010}} The NJ-based band [[Suit of Lights]] pays tribute to Paterson in their song, ''[[Goodbye Silk City]]''. The 1983 music video &quot;[[Two Tribes]]&quot; by [[Frankie Goes to Hollywood]] makes reference to Paterson in its opening sequence.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=RTOQUnvI3CA YouTube - ‪FRANKIE GOES TO HOLLYWOOD - Two Tribes(1983)‬‏]&lt;/ref&gt;

The first marketable revolver was produced in Paterson by [[Samuel Colt]] starting in 1836, and was known as the [[Colt Paterson]].&lt;ref&gt;Richard C. Rattenbury, [http://www.tshaonline.org/handbook/online/articles/lnc01 &quot;COLT REVOLVERS&quot;], ''[[Handbook of Texas Online]]'', published by the [[Texas State Historical Association]]. Accessed November 14, 2011.&lt;/ref&gt;

==Notable residents==
&lt;span style=&quot;color:blue;&quot;&gt;''' (B)'''&lt;/span&gt; denotes that the person was born there.
* [[Mike Adams (safety)|Mike Adams]] (born 1981), pro football player, currently playing for the [[Cleveland Browns]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.clevelandbrowns.com/team/player.php?id=3123 Mike Adams], [[Cleveland Browns]]. Accessed May 19, 2008.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Idec, Keith. [http://www.northjersey.com/sports/107870149_Browns_enjoy_playing_for_that_other_Ryan.html &quot;Browns enjoy playing for that other Ryan&quot;], ''[[The Record (Bergen County)]]'', November 14, 2010. Accessed September 4, 2011. &quot;Paterson native Mike Adams couldn’t help but laugh when he heard and read about the controversy Jets head coach Rex Ryan caused with his R-rated vocabulary during episodes of HBO’s ''Hard Knocks'' this summer.&quot;&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[Bruce Arians]] (born 1952), [[offensive coordinator]] for the [[Pittsburgh Steelers]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://news.steelers.com/team/coach/49259/ Bruce Arians], [[Pittsburgh Steelers]]. Accessed November 25, 2007.&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[Charles D. Beckwith]] (1838–1921), represented [[New Jersey's 5th congressional district]] from 1889 to 1891, and was mayor of Paterson from 1885 to 1889.&lt;ref&gt;[http://bioguide.congress.gov/scripts/biodisplay.pl?index=B000295 Charles Dyer Beckwith profile], ''[[Biographical Directory of the United States Congress]]''. Accessed August 13, 2007.&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[Alexander Berzin (scholar)|Alexander Berzin]] (born 1944), Buddhist Scholar, translator and teacher focusing on the Tibetan tradition.&lt;ref&gt;Fineman, Mark. [http://pqasb.pqarchiver.com/latimes/access/60852577.html?dids=60852577:60852577&amp;FMT=ABS&amp;FMTS=ABS:FT&amp;date=Jan+01%2C+1991&amp;author=MARK+FINEMAN&amp;pub=Los+Angeles+Times+(pre-1997+Fulltext)&amp;desc=Dalai+Lama's+Disciples+Gather+for+Peace+Prayer+Religion%3A+About+150%2C000+participate+in+ceremony+with+the+Peace+Prize+winner.&amp;pqatl=google &quot;Dalai Lama's Disciples Gather for Peace Prayer Religion: About 150,000 participate in ceremony with the Peace Prize winner.&quot;], ''[[Los Angeles Times]]'', January 1, 1991. Accessed December 5, 2008.&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[Gaetano Bresci]] (1869–1901), weaver and anarchist, assassinated Italian king [[Umberto I]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://query.nytimes.com/gst/abstract.html?res=9E0CE7D6113BEE33A25752C3A9619C946197D6CF&amp;scp=1&amp;sq=%22Gaetano+Bresci%22+Paterson&amp;st=p &quot;Assassin's lot fell upon anarchist here; Gaetano Bresci, the King's Murderer, Lived in Paterson. Was in America six years his identity established, and his membership in an Italian Anarchistic Group in the New Jersey Town.&quot;], ''[[The New York Times]]'', July 31, 1900. Accessed May 19, 2008.&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[Mark Brown (American football)|Mark Brown]] (born 1980), NFL linebacker who played for the [[New York Jets]].&lt;ref&gt;Picker, David. [http://www.nytimes.com/2004/12/18/sports/18jets.html?fta=y &quot;Long Climb Pays Off for Jets' Linebacker&quot;], ''[[The New York Times]]'', December 18, 2004. Accessed November 28, 2007. &quot;Brown, a native of Paterson, N.J., stayed in the area and close to the phone.&quot;&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[Rubin Carter|Rubin &quot;Hurricane&quot; Carter]] (born 1937), boxer whose triple murder conviction was later overturned, subject of the [[Bob Dylan]] song &quot;[[Hurricane (song)|Hurricane]]&quot; and the movie ''[[The Hurricane (1999 movie)|The Hurricane]]''.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.biography.com/search/article.do?id=9542248 Rubin &quot;Hurricane&quot; Carter Biography (1937-)], [[The Biography Channel]]. Accessed September 4, 2011.&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[Federico Castelluccio]] (born 1964), [[Italy|Italian]]-born actor, most known for portraying [[Furio Giunta]] on the [[Home Box Office|HBO]] series ''[[The Sopranos]]''.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.corriere.com/viewstory.php?storyid=39495 &quot;«I Sopranos? No agli stereotipi ma non facciamone un dramma» - Federico Castelluccio, il Furio Giunta della celebre serie tv, a Toronto per incontrare gli zii&quot;], ''Corriere Canadese'', May 11, 2005.&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[Joe Louis Clark|Joe Clark]] (born 1938), educator and former principal of [[Eastside High School (Paterson, New Jersey)|Eastside High School]], depicted by [[Morgan Freeman]] in the movie ''[[Lean on Me (film)|Lean on Me]]''.&lt;ref name=LeanOnMe&gt;[[Janet Maslin|Maslin, Janet]]. [http://movies.nytimes.com/movie/review?_r=1&amp;res=950DE7D6123EF930A35750C0A96F948260 &quot;Movie Review: ''Lean on Me''&quot;], ''[[The New York Times]]'', March 3, 1989. Accessed May 19, 2008. &quot;And Morgan Freeman manages it in ''Lean on Me,'' in which he plays Joe Clark, the controversial high-school principal from Paterson, N.J.&quot;&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[Lou Costello]] (1906–59), of the comedy duo [[Abbott and Costello]]. &lt;span style=&quot;color:blue;&quot;&gt;''' (B)'''&lt;/span&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.imdb.com/name/nm0182579/bio Biography for Lou Costello], accessed November 28, 2006.&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[Christos M. Cotsakos]], (born 1948), former CEO of [[E*TRADE]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://ww2.wpunj.edu/adminsrv/pub-info/Cotsakos.htm &quot;Trading on a great education wp's richard reiss has a conversation with E*TRADE ceo christos cotsakos&quot;], ''WP: The Magazine of William Paterson University'', Fall/Winter 1999. Accessed December 6, 2007. &quot;Born and raised in Paterson, New Jersey, Cotsakos was a 1965 graduate of Eastside High School. He will tell you -- 'barely.'&quot;&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[Sunda Croonquist]], comic and actress.&lt;ref&gt;DeMasters, Karen. [http://www.nytimes.com/1999/08/01/nyregion/comedy-hearing-the-laughter-in-women-s-lives.html &quot;Hearing the Laughter in Women's Lives&quot;], ''New York Times'', August 1, 1999. Accessed May 1, 2010. &quot;Like Ms. Langan, Ms. Croonquist now lives in Manhattan, but she grew up in Paterson, where she attended Roman Catholic schools from first grade through college.&quot;&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[Larry Doby]] (1923–2003), [[Baseball Hall of Fame|Hall of Fame]] [[Major League Baseball]] player who broke the [[Baseball color line|color barrier]] in the [[American League]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C04E0DA1231F934A15755C0A961958260&amp;n=Top%2fReference%2fTimes%20Topics%2fPeople%2fD%2fDoby%2c%20Larry Paterson Is Making Move to Honor Doby], ''[[The New York Times]]'', June 27, 1997.&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[Lou Duva]] (born 1922), [[boxing]] trainer, manager, and promoter. He is a member of the [[International Boxing Hall Of Fame]].&lt;ref&gt;James, George. [http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CE0D6163DF93AA35755C0A9649C8B63 &quot;In person; Slugging It Out All These Years&quot;], ''[[The New York Times]]'', June 9, 2002. Accessed November 4, 2007. &quot;Lou Duva grew up the second youngest of seven children in a working-class family in Paterson.&quot;&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[Eddie Einhorn]] (born 1936), part owner of the [[Chicago White Sox]].&lt;ref&gt;Cahillane, Kevin. [http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C01E6D61430F936A1575AC0A9639C8B63 &quot;Worth nothing; White Sox Fans? Say It Ain't So&quot;], ''[[The New York Times]]'', September 25, 2005. Accessed December 9, 2007. &quot;Mr. Einhorn -- who was born and raised in Paterson and lives in Alpine -- is the flamboyant yin to the steely yang of the principal owner, Jerry Reinsdorf.&quot;&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[Allen Ginsberg]] (1926–97), writer and [[Beat Generation]] poet.&lt;ref&gt;Hampton, Wilborn. [http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A0CE6D7143CF935A35757C0A961958260 &quot;Allen Ginsberg, Master Poet Of Beat Generation, Dies at 70&quot;], ''[[The New York Times]]'', April 6, 1997. Accessed December 4, 2007. &quot;Allen Ginsberg was born on June 3, 1926, in Newark and grew up in Paterson, N.J., the second son of Louis Ginsberg, a schoolteacher and sometime poet, and the former Naomi Levy, a Russian emigree and fervent Marxist.&quot;&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[Bill Haast]] (1910–2011), snake and venom specialist, director of Miami Serpentarium Laboratories. &lt;span style=&quot;color:blue;&quot;&gt;''' (B)'''&lt;/span&gt; &lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |last=Kursh |first=Harry |year=1965 |title=Cobras in his Garden |publisher=Irvington-on-Hudson |location=New York: Harvey House, Inc.}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[Hijackers in the September 11 attacks]] [[Hani Hanjour]], [[Nawaf Alhazmi]], [[Salem Alhazmi]], [[Majed Moqed]], [[Abdulaziz Alomari]], [[Khalid Almihdhar]], and probably Ahmed Alghamdi rented and lived in an apartment from March to September 2001.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.historycommons.org/context.jsp?item=a0801nsaentrance History Commons]&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[Gerald Hayes]] (born 1980), linebacker for the [[Arizona Cardinals]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.nflplayers.com/players/player.aspx?id=34632 Gerald Hayes player profile], [[National Football League Players Association]]. Accessed July 23, 2007. &quot;resides in Paterson, New Jersey.&quot;&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[Ureli Corelli Hill]] (1802–75), music conductor and founder of the [[New York Symphony Orchestra]].&lt;ref&gt;Blumenthal, Ralph.[http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C06E6DB1338F93AA15754C0A9649C8B63 &quot;Philharmonic Gets Diary Of a Savvy Music Man&quot;], ''[[The New York Times]]'', July 29, 2002. Accessed November 15, 2007. &quot;Hill played violin with the orchestra until he was over 70, then fell into poverty and depression. In 1875, living in Paterson, N.J., he wrote a farewell note to his second wife: ''Why should or how can a man exist and be powerless to earn means for his family?''&quot;&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[Garret A. Hobart]] (1844–99), Speaker of the New Jersey General Assembly, President of the New Jersey State Senate and the 24th Vice President of the United States, serving under President William McKinley.&lt;ref&gt;Staff. [http://pqasb.pqarchiver.com/courant/access/789817792.html?dids=789817792:789817792&amp;FMT=ABS&amp;FMTS=ABS:AI&amp;type=historic&amp;date=Nov+22%2C+1899&amp;author=&amp;pub=Hartford+Courant&amp;desc=GARRET+A.+HOBART&amp;pqatl=google &quot;GARRET A. HOBART: The Vice-President Dies of Angina Pectoris FUNERAL TO BE HELD AT PATERSON SATURDAY The End Come Yesterday Morning--President Mckinley Issues a Proclamation -- Arrangements for the Funeral Mr. Hobart's Career&quot;], ''[[Hartford Courant]]'', November 22, 1899. Accessed September 4, 2011. &quot;Paterson, N. J., Nov. 21.-- Garret A. Hobart, vice-president of the United States, died of angina pectoris at 8:30 o'clock this morning at his home in this city.&quot;&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[Charlie Jamieson]] (1893–1969), Major League Baseball player.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.baseball-reference.com/j/jamiech01.shtml Charlie Jamieson], [[Baseball-Reference.com]]. Accessed December 14, 2008.&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[Jemal Johnson]] (born 1985), soccer player who currently plays for English [[Coca Cola League One]] side [[Milton Keynes Dons]].&lt;ref&gt;Ubha, Ravi. [http://soccernet.espn.go.com/columns/story?id=526591&amp;root=americansabroad&amp;&amp;cc=5901 &quot;Johnson finds a home with the M.K. Dons&quot;], ''[[ESPNsoccernet]]'', April 17, 2008. Accessed December 14, 2008. &quot;Johnson was born in Paterson, N.J., moved to England when he was 5, and can also compete for Jamaica, given his mother's background.&quot;&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[Alan Rowe Kelly]] (born 1959), actor, director and producer in genre movies, known for ''[[The Blood Shed]]'', ''[[Gallery of Fear]]'' and ''[[I'll Bury You Tomorrow]]''.&lt;ref&gt;Driscoll, Eugene. [http://pqasb.pqarchiver.com/courant/access/1298861961.html?dids=1298861961:1298861961&amp;FMT=ABS&amp;FMTS=ABS:FT&amp;type=current&amp;date=Jul+03%2C+2007&amp;author=EUGENE+DRISCOLL%3B+COURANT+STAFF+WRITER&amp;pub=Hartford+Courant&amp;desc=WHERE+HORROR+IS+A+REAL+PLEASURE+%3B+`GORE+HOUNDS'+MINGLE+AT+FANGO&amp;pqatl=google &quot;WHERE HORROR IS A REAL PLEASURE ; `GORE HOUNDS' MINGLE AT FANGO&quot;], ''[[Hartford Courant]]'', July 3, 2007. Accessed September 22, 2011. &quot;Blood Shed director Alan Rowe Kelly waved his freak-flag high. Kelly 49 from Paterson N.J. stood out from the macho heavily tattooed speed-metal crowd thanks to his jet-black dye job silver earrings and hot-pink heels...&quot;&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[Bernard Kerik]] (born 1955), former New York City Police Commissioner&lt;ref&gt;James, Randy. [http://www.time.com/time/nation/article/0,8599,1935825,00.html &quot;2-MIN. BIO: Bernard Kerik&quot;], ''[[Time (magazine)]]'' November 6, 2009. Accessed May 1, 2010. &quot;Born Sept. 4, 1955, in Newark, N.J., 'Bernie' grew up in a tough neighborhood of Paterson, N.J., a suburb of New York City.&quot;&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[Dan Long (broadcaster)|Dan Long]] (born 1984), sports broadcaster, founder of [http://www.DLSportsMedia.com DL Sports Media]&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.dlsportsmedia.com &quot;DL Sports Media&quot;], Accessed August 10, 2010.&lt;/ref&gt; and &quot;The Voice of the [[Bergen Catholic]] Radio Network.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.bergencatholic.org/athlet/ &quot;Bergen Catholic Athletics&quot;], Accessed August 10, 2010.&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[Edward L. Masry]] (1932–2005), attorney whose firm was behind the case featured in ''[[Erin Brockovich (film)|Erin Brockovich]]''.&lt;ref&gt;Martin, Douglas. [http://www.nytimes.com/2005/12/08/national/08masry.html?_r=1&amp;oref=slogin &quot;Edward L. Masry, 73, Pugnacious Lawyer, Dies&quot;], ''[[The New York Times]]'', December 8, 2005. Accessed [[December 8]], 2007. &quot;Edward L. Masry was born in Paterson, N.J., on July 29, 1932. His parents started a silk apparel business, but when silk import tariffs were lifted, the business faltered. The family then headed for California.&quot;&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[Don Martin (cartoonist)|Don Martin]] (1931–2000), cartoonist from ''[[Mad (magazine)|Mad]]'' magazine.&lt;ref&gt;Woo, Elaine. [http://pqasb.pqarchiver.com/latimes/access/47755346.html?dids=47755346:47755346&amp;FMT=ABS&amp;FMTS=ABS:FT&amp;type=current&amp;date=Jan+08%2C+2000&amp;author=ELAINE+WOO&amp;pub=Los+Angeles+Times&amp;desc=Obituaries%3B+Don+Martin%3B+Cartoonist+Exemplified+Mad+Magazine+in+Sight+and+Sound&amp;pqatl=google &quot;Obituaries; Don Martin; Cartoonist Exemplified Mad Magazine in Sight and Sound&quot;], ''[[Los Angeles Times]]'', January 8, 2000. Accessed January 2, 2011. &quot;Born in Patterson{{sic}} N.J. Martin showed an early talent for drawing.&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[Thomas McEwan, Jr.]] (1854–1926), represented [[New Jersey's 7th congressional district]] from 1895 to 1899.&lt;ref&gt;[http://bioguide.congress.gov/scripts/biodisplay.pl?index=M000431 Thomas McEwan, Jr.], ''[[Biographical Directory of the United States Congress]]''. Accessed August 11, 2007.&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[David Prater]] (1937–88), of the soul duo [[Sam &amp; Dave]].&lt;ref&gt;via [[Associated Press]]. [http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=940DE4DF1538F930A25757C0A96E948260 &quot;Dave Prater, 50, Dies; Soul Singer of the 60's&quot;], ''[[The New York Times]]'', April 13, 1988. Accessed November 4, 2007. &quot;Dave Prater Sr., of the soul-singing duo Sam and Dave, was killed Saturday when the car he was driving went off Interstate 75 near Sycamore, Ga., and hit a tree. He was 50 years old. Mr. Prater had lived in Paterson since 1974 and his body will be returned to New Jersey for burial next week, his widow, Rosemary, said Monday.&quot;&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[Amos H. Radcliffe]] (1870–1950), Mayor of Paterson, New Jersey from 1916 to 1919, and represented [[New Jersey's 7th congressional district]] from 1919 to 1923.&lt;ref&gt;[http://bioguide.congress.gov/scripts/biodisplay.pl?index=R000005 Amos Henry Radcliffe], ''[[Biographical Directory of the United States Congress]]''. Accessed July 23, 2007.&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[Frederick Reines]] (1918–98), [[Nobel Prize]]-winning [[physicist]] who co-discovered the [[neutrino]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://nobelprize.org/nobel_prizes/physics/laureates/1995/reines-autobio.html Frederick Reines: The Nobel Prize in Physics 1995 - Autobiography], Nobel Prize Organization. Accessed April 5, 2007.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:blue;&quot;&gt;''' (B)'''&lt;/span&gt;
* [[Frankie Ruiz]] (born 1958), [[salsa music]] singer.&lt;ref&gt;Dominguez, Robert; with Hinckley, David. [http://articles.nydailynews.com/1998-08-11/news/18088511_1_salsa-singer-latin-music-frankie-ruiz &quot;Frankie Ruiz, Salsa Singer, Dead At 40&quot;], ''[[Daily News (New York)]]'', August 11, 1998. Accessed November 14, 2011. &quot;Born in Paterson, N.J., Ruiz spent his childhood in Puerto Rico and was singing professionally with Orquesta La Solucion by the time he was a teenager.&quot;&lt;/ref&gt; ''' (B)''' 
* [[Marcel Shipp]] (born 1978), running back for the [[Arizona Cardinals]]&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.nflplayers.com/players/player.aspx?id=30772 Marcel Shipp player profile], [[National Football League Players Association]]. Accessed July 24, 2007. &quot;Hometown: Paterson, N.J. Played one year of prep football at Milford (Conn.) Academy and was all-New Jersey choice as a senior at Passaic County Technical High School&quot;&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[Tim Thomas (basketball)|Tim Thomas]] (born 1977), NBA basketball player.&lt;ref&gt;Popper, Steve. [http://www.nytimes.com/2004/03/04/sports/basketball/04KNIC.html &quot;PRO BASKETBALL; Marbury and Tim Thomas Connect in Victory&quot;], ''[[The New York Times]]'', March 4, 2004. Accessed September 4, 2011. &quot;One would like to believe that the play had been rehearsed on playgrounds and in gyms when they were younger. Stephon Marbury and Tim Thomas, one from Brooklyn, the other from Paterson, N.J., grew up playing together on all-star teams and in tournaments.&quot;&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.nba.com/playerfile/tim_thomas/bio.html NBA.com: Tim Thomas Bio Page]. Accessed June 30, 2010. &quot;Hails from Paterson, New Jersey.&quot;&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[Floyd Vivino|“Uncle” Floyd Vivino]] (born 1951), comic, and star of ''Uncle Floyd Show'', the longest-running ever [[Public-access television]] [[cable TV]] show in New Jersey. Also co-starred in the film ''[[Good Morning, Vietnam]]''.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.sirius.com/servlet/ContentServer?pagename=Sirius/Page&amp;c=StreamJockey&amp;cid=1118961468762 Floyd Vivino profile] from [[Sirius Satellite Radio]], accessed December 20, 2006.&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[Patrick Warburton]] (born 1964), actor, performs in movies and on television, famous for his roles in ''[[Seinfeld]]'' and ''[[Family Guy]]''. &lt;span style=&quot;color:blue;&quot;&gt;''' (B)'''&lt;/span&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Yannis, Alex. [http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9407E4D61239F93BA35753C1A963958260 &quot;Hockey; The Devils, And Fans, Ignite First Match&quot;], ''[[The New York Times]]'', October 8, 1995. Accessed November 25, 2007. &quot;Moments after the banner was raised, Patrick Warburton, the actor who portrayed a fanatic Devils' fan in a segment of the &quot;Seinfeld&quot; television show, was called upon to drop the puck. With his face painted in Devils red and black, the native of nearby Paterson dropped the puck, then stripped the Brodeur jersey he was wearing to display the letter D on his chest.&quot;&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[Carl Weinrich]] (1904–91), classical organist known for his recitals and recordings of [[Baroque music|Baroque]] organ music (born in Paterson).&lt;ref&gt;Randel, Don Michael, [http://books.google.co.uk/books?id=9fjl7NhMmWwC&amp;pg=PA975&amp;dq=%22Weinrich,+Carl%22+1991&amp;hl=en&amp;ei=A9-GTMrQI8fJswbs-7XwCg&amp;sa=X&amp;oi=book_result&amp;ct=result&amp;resnum=2&amp;ved=0CDIQ6AEwAQ#v=onepage&amp;q=%22Weinrich%2C%20Carl%22%201991&amp;f=false &quot;Weinrich, Carl&quot;], ''[[Harvard Dictionary of Music |The Harvard Biographical Dictionary of Music]]'', [[Harvard University Press]], 1996, p. 975. ISBN 0674372999.&lt;/ref&gt;

== References ==
{{Reflist|30em}}

== External links ==
{{Commons category}}
* [http://www.patersonnj.gov/ City of Paterson, New Jersey (official site)]
* [http://www.paterson.k12.nj.us/ Paterson Public Schools]
* {{NJReportCard|31|4010|0|Paterson Public Schools}}
* [http://nces.ed.gov/ccd/schoolsearch/school_list.asp?Search=1&amp;DistrictID=3412690 Data for the Paterson Public Schools], [[National Center for Education Statistics]]
* [http://www.centercitypaterson.com/ centercitypaterson.com]
* [http://www.patersononline.net/ patersononline.net]
* [http://www.patersonpulseonline.com/ patersonpulseonline.net]
* [http://www.patersonPulse.net/ patersonpulse.net]
* [http://cameo.njit.edu/urbanparks/paterson_competition/index.htm Paterson: Great Falls State Park. Master plan design competition]
* [http://www.nps.gov/history/NR/twhp/wwwlps/lessons/102paterson/102paterson.htm ''Paterson, New Jersey: America's Silk City,'' a National Park Service Teaching with Historic Places (TwHP) lesson plan]
* [http://www.stoneyroad.org/ Stoney Road, Paterson, New Jersey]
* [http://www.hamiltonpartnership.org/ Hamilton Partnership for Paterson]
* [http://www.hinchliffestadium.org/ Friends of Hinchliffe Stadium]
* [http://memory.loc.gov/ammem/collections/paterson/ ''Working in Paterson: Occupational Heritage in an Urban Setting''] An ethnographic study from the [[Library of Congress]]. Oral history interviews and photographs from a study of working life in Paterson conducted in 1994. Retrieved August 28, 2009.
{{Passaic County, New Jersey}}
{{New Jersey}}
{{New York metropolitan area}}
{{New Jersey cities and mayors of 100,000 population}}

&lt;!-- Please respect alphabetical order --&gt;

[[Category:Cities in New Jersey]]
[[Category:County seats in New Jersey]]
[[Category:Early American industrial centers]]
[[Category:Faulkner Act Mayor-Council]]
[[Category:Former townships in New Jersey]]
[[Category:New Jersey Urban Enterprise Zones]]
[[Category:Paterson, New Jersey| ]]
[[Category:Turkish communities in the United States]]
[[Category:Populated places established in 1831]]
[[Category:Populated places in the United States with Hispanic majority populations]]
[[Category:Populated places in Passaic County, New Jersey]]

[[zh-min-nan:Paterson]]
[[bg:Патерсън]]
[[ca:Paterson]]
[[de:Paterson (New Jersey)]]
[[es:Paterson]]
[[fr:Paterson (New Jersey)]]
[[ga:Paterson, New Jersey]]
[[id:Paterson, New Jersey]]
[[ia:Paterson, New Jersey]]
[[it:Paterson (New Jersey)]]
[[sw:Paterson, New Jersey]]
[[ht:Paterson, New Jersey]]
[[nl:Paterson]]
[[ja:パターソン (ニュージャージー州)]]
[[no:Paterson]]
[[pl:Paterson]]
[[pt:Paterson (Nova Jérsei)]]
[[ro:Paterson, New Jersey]]
[[ru:Патерсон (Нью-Джерси)]]
[[sk:Paterson (New Jersey)]]
[[fi:Paterson]]
[[sv:Paterson]]
[[tl:Paterson, New Jersey]]
[[tr:Paterson, New Jersey]]
[[vi:Paterson, New Jersey]]
[[vo:Paterson]]
[[war:Paterson, New Jersey]]
[[zh:帕特森 (新泽西州)]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
