<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="12566" ns="0" title="George Mason University"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Infobox university
|name= George Mason University
|image_name= Gmuseal.svg
|motto= Freedom and Learning
|mottoeng=
|established= 1957
|type= [[Public university]]
|endowment= $44.9 million (2010)&lt;ref&gt;http://colleges.usnews.rankingsandreviews.com/best-colleges/george-mason-university-3749&lt;/ref&gt;
|president= [[Alan G. Merten]]
|provost= [[Peter Stearns]]
|faculty= 2,893
|staff=
|students= 32,562
|undergrad= 20,157 (Fall 2010)&lt;ref name=&quot;quickfacts&quot;&gt;[http://mediarelations.gmu.edu/docs/pkQuickFacts.pdf Quick Facts about Mason 2010–2011], Office of Media and Public Relations, George Mason University&lt;/ref&gt;
|postgrad= 12,405 (Fall 2010)&lt;ref name=&quot;quickfacts&quot;/&gt;
|campus= [[Suburb]]an, {{convert|806|acre|km2}} total across all campuses
|city= [[Fairfax, Virginia]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Arlington, Virginia]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Manassas, Virginia]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Sterling, Virginia]]&lt;ref&gt;[http://loudoun.gmu.edu/ Mason in Loudoun – George Mason University]. Loudoun.gmu.edu (2011-02-02). Retrieved on 2011-03-11.&lt;/ref&gt;
|state=
|country=
|coor= {{Coord|38.8308|-77.3075|display=title}}
|athletics= [[National Collegiate Athletic Association|NCAA]] [[Division I (NCAA)|Division I]], [[Colonial Athletic Association|CAA]], 22 varsity teams
|colors= [[Green (colour)|Mason Green]] and [[Gold (colour)|Mason Gold]] {{color box|#006633}} {{color box|#FFCC33}}&lt;ref&gt;[http://logo.gmu.edu/webguide/ George Mason University's Visual Identity Guide] George Mason University&lt;/ref&gt;
|nickname= [[George Mason Patriots|Patriots]]
|mascot= The Patriot (formerly &quot;Gunston&quot;)
|website= [http://www.gmu.edu/ www.gmu.edu]
|logo = [[File:GMU logo.svg|170px]]
}}
'''George Mason University''' (often referred to as '''GMU''' or '''Mason''') is a [[public university]] based in [[unincorporated area|unincorporated]] [[Fairfax County, Virginia|Fairfax County]], [[Virginia]], [[United States]], south of and adjacent to the city of [[Fairfax, Virginia|Fairfax]].&lt;ref&gt;&quot;[http://www.fairfaxva.gov/Maps/CITY_MAP.pdf City Map].&quot; ''[[Fairfax, Virginia|City of Fairfax]]''. Accessed October 20, 2008.&lt;/ref&gt; Additional campuses are located nearby in [[Arlington County, Virginia|Arlington County]], [[Prince William County, Virginia|Prince William County]], and [[Loudoun County, Virginia|Loudoun County]]. The university's [[motto]] is ''Freedom and Learning'' while its [[slogan]] or tagline is ''Where Innovation Is Tradition''.&lt;ref&gt;[http://logo.gmu.edu/ George Mason University's Visual Identity Guide]. Logo.gmu.edu. Retrieved on 2011-03-11.&lt;/ref&gt;

Named after [[United States|American]] [[American Revolution|revolutionary]], [[Patriot (American Revolution)|patriot]], and [[Founding Fathers of the United States|founding father]] [[George Mason]], the university was founded as a branch of the [[University of Virginia]] in 1957 and became an independent institution in 1972.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://grad-schools.usnews.rankingsandreviews.com/usnews/edu/grad/rankings/law/brief/lawrank_brief.php|title=America's Best Graduate Schools 2008: Top Law Schools|publisher=[[U.S. News &amp; World Report]]|accessdate=2008-11-05}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.econphd.net/rank/rpublc.htm|title=Rankings: Political Economy|publisher=EconPhD.net|accessdate=2008-11-05}}&lt;/ref&gt; Today, Mason is recognized for its strong programs in [[economics]], [[law]], [[creative writing]], and [[computer science]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Teles|first=Steven Michael|year=2008|title=The rise of the conservative legal movement|page=182}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Vault Editors|first=|year=2006|title=The Law School Buzz Book|page=458}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.pw.org/content/2010_mfa_rankings_top_fifty_0 2010 MFA Rankings: The Top Fifty | Poets &amp; Writers]. Pw.org. Retrieved on 2011-03-11.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://grad-schools.usnews.rankingsandreviews.com/best-graduate-schools/top-science-schools/computer-science-rankings/page+3 ]{{dead link|date=March 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; In recent years, George Mason faculty have twice won the [[Nobel Prize in Economics]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://econfaculty.gmu.edu/wew/articles/02/nobel.html Another Nobel Laureate] Walter E. Williams, GMU, Department of Economics, October 14, 2002&lt;/ref&gt; The university enrolls over 32,500 students, making it the largest university by head count in the Commonwealth of Virginia.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www2.timesdispatch.com/rtd/news/local/education/article/GMUU15_20091014-221605/299431/ In head count, George Mason edges VCU | Richmond Times-Dispatch]. .timesdispatch.com. Retrieved on 2011-03-11.&lt;/ref&gt;

==History==
The [[Virginia General Assembly]] passed a resolution in January 1956, establishing a branch college of the [[University of Virginia]] in [[Northern Virginia]]. In September 1957 the new college opened its doors to seventeen students, all of whom enrolled as freshmen in a renovated elementary school building at [[Bailey's Crossroads]]. John Norville Gibson Finley served as Director of the new branch, which was known as University College.&lt;ref&gt;[http://hdl.handle.net/1920/2712 MARS: Photograph: J.N.G. Finley]. Hdl.handle.net (1963-12-31). Retrieved on 2011-03-11.&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Image:George Mason.jpg|left|thumb|200px|[[George Mason]], (1725–1792) after whom the University is named.]]
The city of Fairfax purchased and donated {{convert|150|acre|km2}} of land to the University of Virginia for the college's new site,&lt;ref&gt;[http://www2.gmu.edu/resources/visitors/history.html A Brief History of George Mason University] George Mason University&lt;/ref&gt; which was referred to as the [[George Mason University Fairfax Campus|Fairfax Campus]]. In 1959, the [[Board of Visitors]] of UVA selected a permanent name for the college: George Mason College of the University of Virginia. The Fairfax campus construction planning that began in early 1960 showed visible results when the development of the first {{convert|40|acre|m2}} of Fairfax Campus began in 1962. In the Fall of 1964 the new campus welcomed 356 students.

Local jurisdictions of [[Fairfax County, Virginia|Fairfax County]], [[Arlington County, Virginia|Arlington County]], and the cities of [[Alexandria, Virginia|Alexandria]] and [[Falls Church, Virginia|Falls Church]] agreed to appropriate $3 million to purchase land adjacent to Mason to provide for a {{convert|600|acre|km2|sing=on}} Fairfax Campus in 1966 with the intention that the institution would expand into a regional university of major proportions, including the granting of graduate degrees.

On April 7, 1972 the [[Virginia General Assembly]] enacted legislation which separated George Mason College from its parent institution, the [[University of Virginia]]. Renamed that day by the legislation, George Mason College became George Mason University.

In 1978, the George Mason University Foundation purchased the former Kann's department store in Arlington. In March 1979 the Virginia General Assembly authorized the establishment of the George Mason University School of Law (GMUSL) – contingent on the transfer of the Kann's building to George Mason University. GMUSL began operations in that building on July 1, 1979 and received provisional accreditation from the American Bar Association in 1980. The ABA granted full approval to GMUSL in 1986.

Also, in 1979, the university moved all of its athletic programs to [[National Collegiate Athletic Association|NCAA]] Division I. Enrollment that year passed 11,000. The university opened its Arlington campus in 1982, two blocks from the [[Virginia Square-GMU (Washington Metro)|Virginia Square-GMU station]] in Arlington. In 1986 the university's governing body, the Board of Visitors, approved a new master plan for the year based on an enrollment of 20,000 full-time students with housing for 5,000 students by 1995. That same year university housing opened to bring the total number of residential students to 700.

Through a bequest of Russian immigrant Shelley Krasnow the University established the [[Krasnow Institute for Advanced Study]] in 1991. The Institute was created to further the understanding of the mind and intelligence by combining the fields of [[cognitive psychology]], [[neurobiology]], and [[artificial intelligence]]. In 1992, Mason's new Prince William Institute began classes in a temporary site in [[Manassas, Virginia]]. The Institute moved to a permanent {{convert|124|acre|km2|sing=on}} site located on the [[Virginia State Route 234|Rt. 234]] bypass, ten miles (16&amp;nbsp;km) south of Manassas, by the year 1997, and is now known as the Prince William Campus. The university graduated more than 5,000 students that following spring.

While George Mason University is young compared to established research universities in Virginia, it has grown rapidly, reaching an enrollment of 30,714 students in 2008.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | title = 2008–2009 Facts and Figures | work = www.gmu.edu | publisher = George Mason University | url = http://www2.gmu.edu/resources/visitors/masonfacts/}}&lt;/ref&gt; According to a 2005 report issued by the university, enrollment is expected to reach 35,000 students by 2011 with more than 7,000 resident students.&lt;ref&gt;[http://research.schev.edu/enrollment/E2_Report.asp Fall Headcount Enrollment] State Council of Higher Education for Virginia&lt;/ref&gt;

In 2002, Mason celebrated its 30th anniversary as a university by launching its first capital campaign, trying to raise $110 million. The school raised $142 million, $32 million more than its goal. The George Mason University logo, originally designed in 1982, was updated in 2004.{{Citation needed|date=November 2010}}

In 2008, the School of Management celebrated its 30th anniversary. Also, in 2008 Mason changed its mascot from the &quot;Gunston&quot; animal to the &quot;Patriot&quot;.{{Citation needed|date=November 2010}}

==Campuses==
{{Refimprove section|date=November 2009}}

===Fairfax Campus===
[[Image:GeorgeMasonAcademicVI.JPG|thumb|right|280px|The Volgenau School of Engineering building.]]

The main campus of George Mason University is situated on {{convert|677|acre|km2}} just south of the [[City of Fairfax, Virginia]] in central [[Fairfax County, Virginia|Fairfax County]], approximately {{convert|15|mi|km}} west of [[Washington, D.C.]] The Fairfax campus is served on the [[Washington Metro]] by the [[Vienna (WMATA station)|Vienna]] station on the [[Orange Line (Washington Metro)|Orange line]]. A 15 minute shuttle in addition to the [[City-University-Energysaver|CUE]] bus, free for students with a Mason ID card, serves the students through routes from the Metro station to the University.&lt;ref&gt;[http://shuttle.gmu.edu/ &quot;Mason Shuttle Services&quot;], George Mason University&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.fairfaxva.gov/CUEBus/CUEBus.asp &quot;Cue Bus System&quot;], City of Fairfax Virginia&lt;/ref&gt;

====Design and construction====
In the early 1960s four buildings were constructed around a lawn in Fairfax, appropriately named East, West, North (later, Krug Hall), and South (later, Finley Hall). The first four structures, today dubbed &quot;The Original Four,&quot; &quot;around a lawn&quot; were understood as a clear reference to the buildings around [[The Lawn]] of the University of Virginia in [[Charlottesville, Virginia|Charlottesville]]. In addition, in the words of the architects, the architecture of the buildings was meant to reflect [[Thomas Jefferson|Jeffersonian]] influence through the use of red brick with buff colored mortar, white vertical columns, and sloped shingled roofs.

Master plans were developed to incorporate further development, which saw new additions such as Fenwick Library and Lecture Hall. By 1979 master plan development was handled by the firm of [[Hideo Sasaki|Sasaki &amp; Associates]], which continued to work alongside the university in the years that followed. Student housing first became available in 1977. The 1980s saw the university expand with a new building being added on each year, including the [[Patriot Center]]. As well as the construction of the Fairfax campuses network of hot and cold water piping that provides power efficient, centralized heating and cooling for the university's buildings.

Recent years have once again brought a new construction boom to the Fairfax campus, which is currently undergoing a massive, $900 million construction campaign (between 2002–2012) based on the 2002 University Master Plan.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url= http://facilities.gmu.edu/masterplans/universitymasterplan.pdf|title=Master Plan|publisher=GMU}}&lt;/ref&gt; This has brought about a huge influx of new buildings to campus, and renovations of existing buildings, most recently:

Building Name / Type / Description - Completion Date
* Southside - New - All you can eat style dining hall - Fall 2008
* Recreation and Athletic Complex [RAC] - Renovated/Expanded - Fall 2009
* Hampton Roads - New - Student housing for ~400 - Fall 2010
* Pilot House - New - Late night dinner open from 5pm to 4am - Fall 2010
* Performing Arts Building - Expansion - Expanded teaching and performing space for College of Visual and Performing Arts - Fall 2010&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Performing Arts Building|url=http://facilities.gmu.edu/projects/perArts/index.htm}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* Student Union I [SUB I] - Renovation/Expansion - Fall 2011&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Student Union I Renovation/Expansion|url=http://facilities.gmu.edu/projects/subI/index.htm}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* Student Union II [SUB II] - Renovated - Spring 2011&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Student Union II Renovation/Expansion|url=http://facilities.gmu.edu/projects/SubII/index.htm}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* Rogers and Whitetop Halls- Suite and Apartment style Residence Halls - Under Construction - Spring 2012&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Student Housing VIII (Phase A)|url=http://facilities.gmu.edu/projects/HousingVIII/index.htm}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* Thompson Hall - Under Renovation - Fall 2011&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Thompson Hall Renovation|url=http://facilities.gmu.edu/projects/thompson/index.htm}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* Science &amp; Technology II Renovation/Expansion - Under Renovation/Construction - 2013&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Science &amp; Technology II Renovation/Expansion|url=http://facilities.gmu.edu/projects/ScTech2RenAdd/index.htm}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* Fenwick Library Renovation/Expansion - Design Phase - 2014&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Fenwick Library Renovation/Expansion|url=http://facilities.gmu.edu/projects/FenLibPh1/index.htm}}&lt;/ref&gt;

====Housing and residence life====
Fairfax is the only campus of George Mason University with on-campus student housing. The campus is divided up into three neighborhoods, which combine house approximately 5,400 students. A seventh housing area is currently under construction to house an additional 600 students and more dining facilities.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://facilities.gmu.edu/projects/HousingVIII/index.htm|title=Housing VIII}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Shenandoah (formerly Southeast):
[[Image:LibertySquare2008.JPG|right|280px|thumb|Liberty Square, an upperclassmen residence area which opened in 2003]]
* Liberty Square - Upperclassmen - Completed 2003, and housing approximately 500 students in two and four person apartments. Each apartment is fully furnished, and contains a kitchen and living/dining area.
* Potomac Heights - Upperclassmen - Completed 2004, and housing approximately 500 students in apartments which can accommodate two, four or six students in single and double bedrooms. Each apartment is fully furnished, and contains a kitchen and living/dining area.
* Presidents Park - Freshmen - Completed in 1989, and housing approximately 1,100 students in twelve halls (Adams, Kennedy, Roosevelt, Harrison, Lincoln, Truman, Jackson, Madison, Wilson, Jefferson, Monroe, Washington). All rooms are fully furnished and residents reside in double, triple, or quad rooms and use shared common bathrooms cleaned daily by janitorial staff. By Fall 2011 all halls will have been renovated within the last 4 years. The twelve resident halls surround Eisenhower hall in the center, a non-residential building which contains a late night diner called Ike's (open until 4am), a large study lounge, a handful of small group study rooms, HDTV lounge with a pool table and vending machines.

Rappahannock (formerly Central):
[[Image:MasonNortheastSectorMay2009.JPG|thumb|right|285px|A view of George Mason's Chesapeake housing area.]]
* Chesapeake - Upperclassmen - Completed 2004, and housing approximately 800 students among its 4 halls (Blue Ridge, Sandbridge (formerly named Shenandoah), Piedmont, Tidewater) in suite-style apartments for four people which vary in combining single and double bedrooms, all which share a common bathroom. Each apartment is fully furnished, and each floor of every building contains at least two large study rooms (in some cases three). Blue Ridge currently houses the One Stop Patriot Shop convenience store on its lower level. Additionally, Tidewater is the location of GMU's very own Red Mango and Auntie Anne’s, open in Fall 2011.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://broadsideonline.com/2011/02/28/auntie%E2%80%88anne%E2%80%99s-einstein%E2%80%88bros-among-new-restaurants-coming-soon-2886/|title=Auntie Anne’s, Einstein Bros., among new restaurants coming soon}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* Dominion - Upperclassmen - Completed in 1981, and housing approximately 500 students in suite-style double occupancy rooms, which share bathrooms with the adjacent suite. All rooms are fully furnished and each floor contains a single study lounge. Renovations are currently being planned.
* Eastern Shore - Freshmen Honors College Students - Completed in 2009, and housing approximately 200 students in suite-style rooms holding up to four residents sharing a single bathroom. Each cluster of 16 students has access to a common living room, kitchen and study space.
* University Commons - Freshmen - Completed in 1986, and housing approximately 500 students in seven halls (Amherst, Brunswick, Carroll, Dickenson, Essex, Franklin, and Grayson). All rooms are fully furnished and residents reside in single, double, or triple rooms and use shared common bathrooms cleaned daily by janitorial staff. Renovations are currently scheduled to take place in phases, and will be completed by 2013.

Aquia(formerly Northwest):
* Commonwealth - Upperclassman - Completed in 1981, and housing approximately 500 students in suite-style double occupancy rooms, which share bathrooms with the adjacent suite. All rooms are fully furnished and each floor contains a single study lounge. Renovations are currently being planned.
* Hampton Roads - All Students - Completed in 2010 and housing approximately 400 students. Hampton Roads is also home to the Pilot House (open until 4am), Mason's second on-campus late night diner.
* Northern Neck - Upperclassman - Completed in 2008 and housing approximately 400 students. Northern Neck is also home to Mason's only Starbucks, located in its first floor.
* Student Apartments - Upperclassman - Completed in 1977 and housing approximately 500 students, in bedroom apartments, each bedroom accommodating two students and each suite sharing one bathroom. Suites has between one, to three bedrooms and are fully furnished, and contains a small kitchen and combined living/dining area.
* Townhouses - Upperclassman - 35 two-bedroom townhouses located 1/8 of a mile north of the campus on [[State Route 123 (Virginia)|State Route 123]]
* Rogers and Whitetop (Housing VIII) - TBD - Opening in spring 2012, Rogers and Whitetop contain suite-style and suite-with-kitchen style accommodations. These buildings will temporarily house the residents of University Commons during dorm renovations.&lt;ref name=&quot;Rogers and Whitetop&quot;&gt;{{cite web|last=Housing|first=George Mason|title=The Commons Renovation Project|url= http://housing.gmu.edu/freshman/index.asp?fresh=11|work=The Commons Renovation Proj|publisher=George Mason University Housing|accessdate=2011-08-22}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Former Buildings:
* Patriot Village
In summer 2008 the Patriot Village area was demolished to make room for the RAC (an on campus gym complex). Patriots Village consisted of dozens of permanent [[mobile home|modulars]] located just outside of Patriot Circle, east of Ox Road, offering modular and suite-style units.

====Notable campus buildings====
=====Johnson Center=====
The George W. Johnson Learning Center, more commonly known as the Johnson Center or JC, is the central hub on campus, completed in 1995 and named after University President of 18-years, George W. Johnson. Located in the center of campus, the $30 million, {{convert|320000|sqft|m2|sing=on}} building was built as the first of its kind building on any American campus, acting both as a [[library]] and a [[Student activity center|student union]]. The ground floor includes a buffet style restaurant named the Bistro, the campus radio station [[WGMU Radio]], a coffee shop named Jazzman's, 300-seat movie theater, and Dewberry Hall. The main floor includes the campus bookstore, a large food court with several fast food restaurants, a patisserie and the ground floor of the library. The second and third floors of the Johnson Center are primarily used by the library, with multiple group meeting rooms, computer labs, and a full service restaurant named George's located on the third floor.

The Johnson Center serves as the center for student life with many activities and productions sponsored by Program Board and Student Government. In 2004 during the [[Democratic Party (United States) presidential primaries, 2004|Democratic Primaries]], Senator [[John Kerry]], the eventual Democratic Nominee for President, visited George Mason University and gave a speech on the floor of the Johnson Center. In 2007, shortly after announcing on his website that he would establish a [[Exploratory committee|presidential exploratory committee]], Senator [[Barack Obama]] gave a speech at the &quot;Yes We Can&quot; rally at the Johnson Center atrium. The next week he formally announced his intentions of running for president.

=====Center for the Arts=====
[[Image:George Mason Performing Arts.JPG|thumb|280px|right|George Mason University's Center for the Arts.]]
The Center for the Arts includes a 2,000-seat Concert Hall built in 1990. The concert hall can be converted into a more intimate 800-seat theater. Most ''Center for the Arts'' events take place here, including [[operas]], [[orchestras]], [[ballets]], and musical and theatrical performances such as [[Kid Cudi]] in 2010.

=====Patriot Center=====
The [[Patriot Center]] is a 10,000 seat arena, home court for the Men's and Women's [[George Mason Patriots|basketball]] team. The Patriot Center is also host to over 100 concerts and events throughout the year, annually attracting major performers like the [[Ringling Bros. and Barnum &amp; Bailey Circus]].

=====Aquatic and Fitness Center=====
The {{convert|68000|sqft|m2|sing=on}} Aquatic and Fitness Center opened in 1998 at a cost of $11 million. The center includes an [[Olympic size swimming pool]] containing eight 50-meter lanes, twenty-two {{convert|25|yd|m|sing=on}} lanes, two movable bulkheads, and a diving area equipped with two 1-meter and two 3-meter spring boards, a Warm-water [[swimming pool|recreational pool]], Locker rooms, a [[hot tub|whirlpool]], a coed [[sauna]], and a family changing room.
{{Citation needed|date=August 2011}}

[[Image:Fenwick 2007.jpg|thumb|280px|left|Fenwick Library]]

=====Fenwick Library=====
Fenwick Library was originally built in 1967, with additions in 1974, a tower in 1983, and renovations in 2005–2006. It was named for Charles Rogers Fenwick, one of George Mason's founders. Fenwick Library is the main [[research library]] at George Mason. Its resources include: most of the university's books, microfilms, print and bound journals, government documents, and maps. Electronic resources include networked and stand-alone [[CD-ROM]]s, the libraries' [[OPAC|online catalog]], a number of databases available through the libraries' membership in various consortia, and [[Internet access]]. Another important collection of research materials housed in Fenwick is the Government Documents collection. This collection includes both federal and Virginia state documents. Both sets of documents contain items from the [[executive branch|administrative]], [[United States Congress|legislative]], and [[judicial branch|judicial]] branches of government, and constitute an invaluable source of primary source materials for students and faculty in [[political science]], [[Policy|public policy]], [[sociology]], [[business]] and other fields. There is also a special GIS center in Fenwick Library which conducts [[GIS]] drop-in sessions every week.

George Mason is a member of the [[Consortium of Universities of the Washington Metropolitan Area]], granting it access to resources of thirteen other libraries in the District of Columbia.

===Arlington Campus===
[[Image:Gmu law school.jpg|thumb|right|280px|The [[George Mason University School of Law]] on the Arlington campus]]
The {{convert|5.2|acre|m2|sing=on}} Arlington campus was established in 1979 by the [[Virginia General Assembly]] for the newly founded [[George Mason University School of Law|law school]]. In 1980, graduate and professional programs were also offered in the building, a converted [[Kann's]] department store. Since then the school has grown to offer a multitude of graduate degrees. In 1996, Arlington's campus began its first phase in a three phase campus redevelopment project. In 1998, Hazel Hall was completed to house the law school, the [[Mercatus Center]], and the [[Institute for Humane Studies]]. The second phase, to be completed in 2010, is underway for a {{convert|250000|sqft|m2|sing=on}} building named Founders Hall is to house the Schools of Public Policy, Education and Human Development, [[Information Technology]], [[Engineering]], [[Management]], the [[Institute for Conflict Analysis and Resolution]], [[Computational Science]], and the College of Visual &amp; Performing Arts and academic and student supports services.&lt;ref&gt;[http://arlington.gmu.edu//newconstruction.html Arlington Campus – George Mason University]. Arlington.gmu.edu. Retrieved on 2011-03-11.&lt;/ref&gt; Arlington's campus is projected to reach an enrollment of 10,000 students by the completion of its redevelopment.

The Arlington campus is served on the [[Washington Metro]] by the [[Virginia Square–GMU (Washington Metro)|Virginia Square-GMU]] station on the [[Orange Line (Washington Metro)|Orange line]]. The station is located approximately two blocks west of the campus.

===Prince William Campus===&lt;!-- This section is linked from [[Manassas, Virginia]] --&gt;
George Mason's Prince William campus opened on August 25, 1997 in [[Manassas, Virginia|Manassas]]. It is located on {{convert|124|acre|km2}} of land. The campus offers a high-tech/bio-tech and emphasizes [[bioinformatics]], [[biotechnology]], forensic biosciences educational and research programs in addition to computer and [[information technology]]. The campus also offers creative programs of instruction, research, and public/private partnerships in the [[Prince William County]] area.{{Citation needed|date=November 2010}}

Prince William offers an M.A. in New Professional Studies in Teaching, an M.A.I.S. with a concentration in Recreation Resources Management, a B.S. in Administration of Justice, undergraduate programs in health, fitness, and 'Recreation Resources', graduate programs in exercise, fitness and 'Health Promotion', and nontraditional programs through continuing and professional education in geographic information systems and facility management.{{Citation needed|date=November 2010}}

Prince William also boasts the 300-seat Verizon Auditorium, the {{convert|110000|sqft|m2|sing=on}} Freedom Aquatic and Fitness Center, and a {{convert|85000|sqft|m2|sing=on}}, $46 million [[Hylton Performing Arts Center]] which opened in 2010.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title=George Mason University gets ready to raise a new curtain|first=Jacqueline|last=Trescott|date=April 29, 2010|page=C2|work=Washington Post}}&lt;/ref&gt; Other buildings on the Prince William campus include the Occoquan Building, which houses various academic, research, and administrative resources including a Student Health clinic, Bull Run Hall, a {{convert|100000|sqft|m2|sing=on}} building which opened in the fall of 2004, and Discovery Hall, which was completed in 1998 at a cost of $20.4 million.{{Citation needed|date=November 2010}}

===Loudoun Campus===
In the fall of 2005, the university opened a site in [[Loudoun County, Virginia]]. Several months later, it announced the gift of {{convert|123|acre|km2}} of land by Greenvest, LLC, to build a fourth suburban campus. The campus was scheduled to open in 2009. However, the proposal was voted down by the Loudoun County Board of Supervisors, as part of the larger Dulles South project. Greenvest rescinded the gift.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.washingtonpost.com/wp-dyn/content/article/2006/11/08/AR2006110802433.html Loudoun Supervisors Quash Dulles South Project] The Washington Post&lt;/ref&gt; Committed to expanding its presence in Loudoun, the university has now proposed a possible joint campus with [[Northern Virginia Community College]]. The campus would be located in [[Broadlands, Virginia]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.loudountimes.com/news/2008/aug/15/joint-gmu-nvcc-campus-considered-loudoun/ Joint GMU-NVCC campus proposed for Loudoun] Loudon Times-Mirror&lt;/ref&gt;

Mason's current Loudoun site offers several graduate programs; an MA in [[Master of Business Administration|Business Administration]], Masters and doctoral programs in the College of Education and Human Development (CEHD), a graduate degree in [[nursing]], and a Master of Science in [[telecommunications]]. The Loudon campus also offers five undergraduate programs; a minor in business and management, certificates in the College of Education and Human Development, a BS in [[health science]], a minor in [[information technology]], and an introductory course in [[social work]]. Other graduate level courses, such as those offered by the Department of Information and Software Engineering, are periodically taught at the site.{{Citation needed|date=November 2010}}

==Ras Al Khaimah==
George Mason opened a 'campus' in the [[Ras Al Khaimah]] emirate of the [[United Arab Emirates]] in 2005.&lt;ref&gt;[http://rak.gmu.edu/ The Ras Al Khaimah Campus] George Mason University&lt;/ref&gt; No one ever graduated from the Ras al Khaimah 'campus' and it never grew beyond one building.&lt;ref&gt;[http://chronicle.com/daily/2009/02/12575n.htm, George Mason U. Will Close Its Campus in the Persian Gulf] Mills, Andrew. The Chronicle&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.nytimes.com/2009/03/01/education/01campus.html?em George Mason University, Among First With an Emirates Branch, Is Pulling Out] The New York Times&lt;/ref&gt; The Ras Al Khaimah 'campus' nominally offered three undergraduate Bachelors of Science degrees in [[biology]], business administration, and [[electronics and communications engineering]]. They subsequently added a course in &quot;educational leadership and management.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;[http://gse.gmu.edu/programs/edleadership/ Education Leadership] George Mason University Graduate School of Education&lt;/ref&gt;

On February 27, 2009, Mason announced they would close the Ras Al Khamimah campus at the end of the Spring 2009 semester. University Provost, [[Peter Stearns]], cited that the relationship between George Mason University and the partner foundation in RAK worked smoothly until early 2009. He explained that the foundation would be reducing the financial support as well as attempting to change the academic reporting structure. In an e-mail to students Stearns wrote, &quot;We have not been able to reach agreement with our RAK partner on a budget and administrative structure that, in our judgment, assures our ability to provide an education that meets Mason standards.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.thenational.ae/article/20090226/NATIONAL/302411756/0/NEWS UAE news – The National]. Thenational.ae. Retrieved on 2011-03-11.&lt;/ref&gt;

==Academics==
[[Image:Photo the institute.jpg|thumb|280px|right|The [[Krasnow Institute for Advanced Study]] is located on the Fairfax campus.]]
The university has strength in the basic and applied sciences with critical mass in [[proteomics]], [[neuroscience]] and [[computer science|computational sciences]]. Research support comes to Mason faculty from such agencies as the [[National Institutes of Health]], [[NASA]], the [[National Science Foundation]] and the [[Defense Advanced Research Projects Agency]]. Likewise, the Center for Secure Information Systems is designated as a Center of Academic Excellence (CAE) as well as a Center of Academic Excellence in Research (CAE-R) in Information Assurance Education by the National Security Agency.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.nsa.gov/ia/academic_outreach/nat_cae/institutions.shtml#va, National Centers of Academic Excellence Institutions]&lt;/ref&gt;

Mason's [[Center for History and New Media]] attracts more{{When|date=November 2010}} than one million visitors to its websites every month.{{Citation needed|date=November 2010}}

Mason's Center for Global Education's [[study abroad]] program has been rated highly{{By whom|date=November 2010}} offering dozens of programs ranging from one-week spring break programs to full year programs.{{Citation needed|date=November 2010}}.

Mason's flagship Study Abroad experience is the prestigious Oxford Honors Program in which highly qualified students endure a rigorous application and interview process and, if selected, travel to the [[United Kingdom]] where they study for 6–12 months as matriculated students of [[Oxford University]].

Mason was awarded $25 million in 2005 from the [[National Institute of Allergy and Infectious Diseases]] (NIAID), part of the [[National Institutes of Health]], for construction of a Regional Biocontainment Laboratory at the Prince William Campus in [[Manassas]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://eagle.gmu.edu/newsroom/509/ George Mason University Receives $25 Million Federal Award For Construction of a Regional Biocontainment Laboratory] George Mason Media and Public Relations&lt;/ref&gt;

===Rankings and distinctions===
&lt;!-- Please put department-specific rankings in the article for that particular college--&gt;
{{Infobox US university ranking
| ARWU_W = 151-200
| USNWR_NU = 138
| Wamo_NU = 199
}}

===Rankings===
[[US News &amp; World Report]] Undergraduate rankings include:
* 138 (Tier 1) – National Universities Rankings 2011&lt;ref&gt;[http://colleges.usnews.rankingsandreviews.com/best-colleges/fairfax-va/george-mason-university-3749 George Mason University | Best College | US News]. http://colleges.usnews.rankingsandreviews.com/best-colleges/rankings/national-universities (2011-01-31). Retrieved on 2011-09-15.&lt;/ref&gt;
* 2nd – new category of &quot;Up-and-coming National Universities&quot; 2011&lt;ref&gt;[http://colleges.usnews.rankingsandreviews.com/best-colleges/george-mason-university-232186/overall-rankings]. Colleges.usnews.rankingsandreviews.com (2011-01-31). Retrieved on 2011-03-11.&lt;/ref&gt;{{full}}
* 69th – Top Public National Universities 2011&lt;ref&gt;[http://colleges.usnews.rankingsandreviews.com/best-colleges/national-top-public Top Public Schools | Rankings | Top National Universities | US News]. Colleges.usnews.rankingsandreviews.com (2011-01-31). Retrieved on 2011-03-11.&lt;/ref&gt;
* 88th – Best Undergraduate Business Programs 2011&lt;ref name=&quot;som.gmu.edu&quot;&gt;[http://som.gmu.edu/our-school/accreditation-a-rankings Accreditation &amp; Rankings]. Som.gmu.edu. Retrieved on 2011-03-11.&lt;/ref&gt;{{full}}
* 31st – The Systems Engineering and Operations Research Department for Best Engineering Schools in Industrial and Manufacturing, 2009&lt;ref&gt;[http://seor.gmu.edu/ George Mason University]&lt;/ref&gt;{{Better source|date=November 2009}}

[[US News &amp; World Report]] Graduate program rankings include:
* 40th – Law 2011 &lt;ref&gt;[http://grad-schools.usnews.rankingsandreviews.com/grad/law Best Graduate Schools | Top Graduate Programs | US News Education]. Grad-schools.usnews.rankingsandreviews.com. Retrieved on 2011-03-11.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://grad-schools.usnews.rankingsandreviews.com/best-graduate-schools/top-law-schools/rankings/page+2 Best Law School Rankings | Law Program Rankings | US News]. Grad-schools.usnews.rankingsandreviews.com. Retrieved on 2011-03-11.&lt;/ref&gt;{{full}}
* 51st – Political Science 2011&lt;ref&gt;[http://grad-schools.usnews.rankingsandreviews.com/best-graduate-schools/top-political-science-schools/rankings/page+3 ''US News &amp; World Report'']&lt;/ref&gt;
* 64th – History 2011&lt;ref&gt;[http://grad-schools.usnews.rankingsandreviews.com/best-graduate-schools/top-history-schools/rankings/page+3 ]{{dead link|date=March 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* 45th – Public Affairs 2011&lt;ref&gt;[http://grad-schools.usnews.rankingsandreviews.com/grad/pad/search/page+2 Best Graduate Schools | Top Graduate Programs | US News Education]. Grad-schools.usnews.rankingsandreviews.com. Retrieved on 2011-03-11.&lt;/ref&gt;
* 79th – Nursing 2011&lt;ref&gt;[http://grad-schools.usnews.rankingsandreviews.com/best-graduate-schools/top-nursing-schools/rankings/page+3 ]{{dead link|date=March 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.uscollegeranking.org/health/top-100-nursing-graduate-school-ranking-in-2009.html Nursing School Ranking]&lt;/ref&gt;
* 66th – Education 2011&lt;ref&gt;[http://grad-schools.usnews.rankingsandreviews.com/grad/edu/search/page+3 Best Graduate Schools | Top Graduate Programs | US News Education]. Grad-schools.usnews.rankingsandreviews.com. Retrieved on 2011-03-11.&lt;/ref&gt;{{full}}
* 70th – Part time MBA 2011&lt;ref name=&quot;som.gmu.edu&quot;/&gt;
* 8th – Industrial Organization Psychology PhD program 2001 &lt;ref&gt;[http://www.siop.org/tip/backissues/tipapr02/02gibby.aspx The Top I-O Psych Doctoral Programs of North America Apr 02]. Siop.org. Retrieved on 2011-03-11.&lt;/ref&gt;
* 63rd – Computer Science 2011&lt;ref&gt;[http://grad-schools.usnews.rankingsandreviews.com/best-graduate-schools/top-science-schools/computer-science-rankings/page+3 Best Computer Science Programs | Top Computer Science Schools | US News Best Graduate Schools]. Grad-schools.usnews.rankingsandreviews.com. Retrieved on 2011-03-11.&lt;/ref&gt;{{full}}

Other rankings:
* The School of Public Policy is ranked 1st in the nation{{When|date=November 2009}} for federally-funded public policy, public affairs, public administration and political science research.&lt;ref&gt;[http://eagle.gmu.edu/newsroom/753/ National Science Foundation Rankings Show Research Is Flourishing at Mason – Media and Public Relations – George Mason University]. Eagle.gmu.edu (2009-04-08). Retrieved on 2011-03-11.&lt;/ref&gt;{{Better source|date=November 2009}}
* The university is ranked 58th in North America and 75th worldwide by the web-based Webometrics Ranking of World Universities&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.webometrics.info/top100_continent.asp?cont=usa_canada World Universities' ranking on the Web: Top USA &amp; Canada]&lt;/ref&gt;
* 4th most diverse university in the nation, by the [[Princeton Review]] in 2008.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.princetonreview.com/college/research/rankings/rankingDetails.asp?categoryID=2&amp;topicID=20 |title=Demographics&amp;nbsp;— Diverse Student Population |publisher=The Princeton Review |accessdate=2008-11-15 |archiveurl = http://web.archive.org/web/20080617230607/http%3A//www.princetonreview.com/college/research/rankings/rankingDetails.asp%3FcategoryID%3D2%26topicID%3D20 |archivedate = June 17, 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* 8th in the world [[political economy]], 30th in [[public economics]] by econphd.net.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.econphd.net/rank/rpublc.htm econphd.net]&lt;/ref&gt;{{Dead link|date=November 2009}}
* {{As of|2008}}, the ''Southern Economic Journal'' ranks Mason economics as 3rd in Methodology and History of Economic Thought, 9th in General Economics and Teaching, 11th in Law and Economics, 25th in Public Economics and 25th in Microeconomics.&lt;ref&gt;Therese C. Grijalva and Cliffor Nowell, &quot;A Guide to Graduate Study in Economics: Ranking Economics Departments by Fields of Expertise,&quot; Southern Econ. Journal, April 2008, Vol. 74, No. 4, pp. 971–996&lt;/ref&gt;

===Schools and colleges===
Research at Mason is organized into centers, laboratories, and collaborative programs.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.gmu.edu/research/centers/ Research and Scholarship] George Mason University&lt;/ref&gt; These include the College of Humanities and Social Sciences, the College of Education and Human Development, New Century College, the College of Health and Human Services, the College of Visual and Performing Arts, the Institute for Conflict Analysis and Resolution, the [[Krasnow Institute for Advanced Study]], the School of Computational Sciences, the [[Volgenau School of Information Technology and Engineering]], the [[George Mason University School of Law|School of Law]], the [[George Mason University School of Public Policy|School of Public Policy]], the College of Science, and the School of Management. In addition, Mason's Office of the [[Provost (education)|Provost]] includes research centers that deal with economics, global education, and teaching excellence.{{Citation needed|date=December 2010}}

In addition to a business undergraduate major and minor, Mason's School of Management has graduate programs for the Master of Business Administration degree (MBA) with a wide variety of concentrations/specializations, an Executive Master of Business Administration degree (EMBA), a Master of Science in Accounting (MSA), a joint MBA/MSA degree and a Master of Science in Technology Management degree.{{Citation needed|date=December 2010}}

==Athletics==
{{Main|George Mason Patriots}}
{{See also|George Mason Patriots men's basketball|2005–06 George Mason Patriots men's basketball team}}
The school's sports teams are called the Patriots. The university's men's and women's sports teams participate in the [[National Collegiate Athletic Association|NCAA]]'s [[Division I (NCAA)|Division I]], and are members of the [[Colonial Athletic Association]], or CAA. The school's colors are green and gold. George Mason has two NCAA Division I National Championship to its credit; [[1985 in sports|1985]] [[NCAA Women's Soccer Championship|Women's Soccer]] and [[1996 in sports|1996]] [[NCAA Men's Indoor Track and Field Championship|Men's Indoor Track &amp; Field]].

George Mason University was catapulted into the national spotlight in March 2006, when its men's basketball team advanced to the [[NCAA Men's Division I Basketball Championship|Final Four]] of the [[2006 NCAA Men's Division I Basketball Tournament|NCAA Men's Basketball Tournament]] by defeating the [[Michigan State Spartans men's basketball|Michigan State Spartans]], the defending champion [[2005–06 North Carolina Tar Heels men's basketball team|North Carolina Tar Heels]], the [[Wichita State Shockers men's basketball|Wichita State Shockers]], and the top-seeded [[Connecticut Huskies men's basketball|Connecticut Huskies]]. Their &quot;[[Cinderella (sports)|Cinderella]]&quot; journey ended in the Final Four with a loss to the eventual tournament champion [[2005–06 Florida Gators men's basketball team|Florida Gators]] by a score of 73–58.&lt;ref&gt;[http://sports.yahoo.com/ncaab/recap;_ylt=AiztqaWfF1ZYwdwwkU.FwJfevbYF?gid=200604010210 Florida 73, George Mason 58 – College Basketball – Rivals.com]. Sports.yahoo.com. Retrieved on 2011-03-11.&lt;/ref&gt; As a result of the team's success in the tournament, the Patriots were ranked 8th in the final [[ESPN]]/[[USA Today]] Poll for the [[2005–06 NCAA Division I men's basketball season|2005–06 season.]] ''[[The New York Times]]'', ''[[The Washington Post]]'', ''[[Baltimore Sun]]'', and ''[[USA Today]]'' featured the story on their front pages, and was ranked by several publications as the sports story of the year.

The Patriots, who had never won an NCAA tournament game before 2006, became the first team from the CAA to crash the Final Four and were the first true [[mid-major]] conference team since 1979 to do so (that year, the [[Larry Bird]]-led [[1978–79 Indiana State Sycamores men's basketball team|Indiana State Sycamores]] as a #1 seed, and the [[Penn Quakers men's basketball|Penn Quakers]] as a #9 seed both reached the Final Four). As #11-seeds, the 2006 Patriots also tied the 1986 [[LSU Tigers]] as the lowest-seeded team ever to reach the Final Four.{{Citation needed|date=November 2010}}

In [[2007–08 NCAA Division I men's basketball season|2008]], the Patriots returned to the [[2008 NCAA Men's Division I Basketball Tournament|NCAA Tournament]] after winning the CAA Tournament. They were given a 12 seed and matched up against 5th-seeded [[2007-08 Notre Dame Fighting Irish men's basketball team|Notre Dame]]. The Patriots were unable to make another miracle run, losing to the Irish by a score of 68–50.{{Citation needed|date=November 2010}}

==Organizations==
George Mason offers more than 200 clubs and organizations, including 16 [[fraternities]], 15 [[sororities]], 24 International-student organizations, 25 religious organizations, a student programming board, [[student government]], club sports, debate team, and student media. The Office of Student Involvement at Mason administrates Student Government, Program Board, Fraternity and Sorority Life, Recognized Student Organization (RSO), Graduate and Professional Student Association (GAPSA), and Weekends at Mason (WAM).&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last=Wolf|first=Karen|title=Student Involvement|url=http://si.gmu.edu/|publisher=George Mason University|accessdate=5 May 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; Mason also offers an [[United States Army|Army]] [[ROTC]] program, called The &quot;Patriot Battalion.&quot; Mason's club sports include [[Ultimate (sport)|ultimate frisbee]], [[Rowing (sport)|crew]], [[equestrianism|equestrian]], [[field hockey]], football, lacrosse, [[underwater hockey]], fencing, and [[college rugby|rugby]].{{Citation needed|date=April 2010}}

The George Mason University Forensics program is one of the top ranked competitive speech teams in the United States and has achieved international recognition in the field of communication studies.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.americanforensics.org/organization/awards/champions-national-i/champions-national-individual-events-tou Champions of the National Individual Events Tournament | American Forensic Association]. Americanforensics.org. Retrieved on 2011-03-11.&lt;/ref&gt; The team was founded in 1970 and has won nearly 10,000 individual speech awards. In 2010 the team placed 4th at the [[American Forensics Association National Tournament]] and won the International Forensics Association Championship. The Forensics Program has been extremely active on the George Mason campus with an active Community Service Committee. GMU hosts the annual Virginia is for Lovers collegiate speech tournament, the Patriot Games scholastic speech competition (which in 2009 had over 1,000 entries), and also will host the 2011 [[Catholic Forensics League Grand National Tournament]]. Currently Dr. Peter Pober is the Program Director with Jeremy Hodgson as Assistant Director.&lt;ref&gt;[http://gmuforensics.org/ GMU Forensics]. GMU Forensics. Retrieved on 2011-03-11.&lt;/ref&gt;

===Media===
Mason offers two regular print publications, ''[[Broadside (newspaper)|Broadside]]'', the [[student newspaper]], and the ''Mason Gazette'', the University-published newspaper. Mason also operates a [[Campus radio]] station, [[WGMU Radio]]. The online radio station offers music, entertainment, news, and public affairs relating to the University community, regional area and the country. GMU-TV is the university's professional [[Distance learning|Educational-access television]] station. GMU-TV is an award-winning leader in educational, informational and public interest programming. The unit offers a broad spectrum of content, ranging from public affairs and humanities to science, medicine and the arts. The Mason Cable Network, or MCN, is the student organized and operated station, and offers student produced entertainment and information on campus channel 89, available on the Fairfax campus of GMU. Mason also sponsors several student-run publications through its Office of Student Media,&lt;ref&gt;[http://studentmedia.gmu.edu/ Student Media – An office of University Life]. Studentmedia.gmu.edu. Retrieved on 2011-03-11.&lt;/ref&gt; including the ''VoxPop'', a feature magazine, Connect2Mason, an online media and news convergence Web site,&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.connect2mason.com/ Connect2Mason]. Connect2Mason. Retrieved on 2011-03-11.&lt;/ref&gt; ''Volition'', an undergraduate student literary and art magazine, ''Phoebe'', a graduate literary journal, ''So to Speak'', a feminist literary journal, ''GMView and Senior Speak'', an annual yearbook publication and video, ''New Voices in Public Policy'', School of Public Policy student journal, and ''Hispanic Culture Review'', a student bilingual (Spanish/English) journal on Hispanic literature and culture. Mason also sponsors several academic journals including, ''[[TABLET the International Affairs Journal of George Mason University|''TABLET, the International Affairs Journal of George Mason University'']]''. Between approximately 1993 and 1998, the University was also the home of ''The Fractal: Journal of Science Fiction and Fantasy''.

Between 1999 and 2005, the [[underground newspaper]] ''Expulsion'' was distributed on the Mason campus. It also experienced a brief online resurgence in 2007.&lt;ref&gt;[http://web.archive.org/web/*/expulsion.org Internet Archive Wayback Machine]. Web.archive.org. Retrieved on 2011-03-11.&lt;/ref&gt;

The staff of the [[Center for History and New Media]] produces a podcast called ''Digital Campus''.

In fall 2008, the satirical online newspaper, ''The Mason Squire'', premiered.&lt;ref&gt;[http://themasonsquire.com/about/ ]{{dead link|date=March 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; The site featured fake news stories criticizing the university. The newspaper's mottos were &quot;Because fake news doesn't report itself&quot; and &quot;Fake news just got a whole lot sexier&quot;. However, the site has been inactive since late 2009.

===Fraternity and sorority life===
{{See also|List of Fraternities and Sororities at George Mason University}}
George Mason University does not have traditional Fraternity &amp; Sorority housing or a &quot;Greek row.&quot; For several years, three Panhellenic Council organizations had established &quot;Living/Learning Floors&quot; in the University Commons. [[Alpha Omicron Pi]] had a floor 2004–2010, [[Gamma Phi Beta]] had a floor 2006–2010, and [[Alpha Phi]] had a floor 2007–2010.{{Citation needed|date=November 2010}}

Officially, Mason refers to &quot;Greek Life&quot; as &quot;Fraternity &amp; Sorority Life&quot; to avoid confusion with the Hellenic Society club, a student organization focusing on the people and culture of Greece.{{Citation needed|date=November 2010}}

Most organizations in the Interfraternity Council (IFC) and Panhellenic Council (PHC) hold one or two large charitable events each year. Most organizations in the National Pan-Hellenic Conference (NPHC) and Multicultural Greek Council (MGC) hold a series of smaller charitable events throughout the year. The NPHC is also known for its annual Step Show.{{Citation needed|date=November 2010}}

The most well-known{{By whom|date=November 2010}} event associated with Fraternity &amp; Sorority Life on campus is held each spring and is called Greek Week. This annual event includes competitive sporting and trivia events, charitable fund raising, and is usually ended with Greek Sing. Organizations participating in Greek Sing put together 10–15 minute themed shows which have included extravagant costumes, set designs, lighting displays, multimedia presentations, dances, singing, acrobatics, and more.{{Citation needed|date=November 2010}}

PHC holds a formal recruitment each fall. Informal recruitment is held in spring. Many PHC organizations also offer continuous open recruitment (or continuous open bidding) after the designated recruitment period. IFC has a designated one-week rush period in the fall and spring. This week is regulated and monitored, but participants are not registered or tracked.{{Citation needed|date=November 2010}}

==Presidents past and present==
* Lorin A. Thompson, (1966–73)
* Vergil H. Dykstra, (1973–1977){{Citation needed|date=November 2010}}
* Robert C. Krug, (1977–1978){{Citation needed|date=November 2010}}
* George W. Johnson, (1978–1996)
* [[Alan G. Merten]], (1996–2012)&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.washingtonpost.com/local/education/alan-g-merten-to-retire-as-george-mason-university-president/2011/03/23/ABConfJB_story.html |title=Alan G. Merten to retire as George Mason University president |author=Daniel de Vise and Lisa Rein |date=March 23, 2011 |publisher=The Washington Post}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Notable alumni==
===Corporate/non-profit===
* [[Muna Abu-Sulayman]], Secretary General and Executive Director, Alwaleed Bin Talal Foundation
* [[Yusuf Azizullah]], consultant
* [[Zainab Salbi]], President, [[Women for Women International]]
* [[Will Seippel]], business executive
* [[Roy Speckhardt]], executive director of the [[American Humanist Association]]
* [[Martin Andrew Taylor]], senior executive Corporate VP of [[Windows Live]] and [[MSN]], Chief of Staff to Microsoft CEO [[Steve Ballmer]]

===Government and politics===
[[File:Anna Escobedo Cabral, official Treasury photo.jpg|thumb|100px|Anna Cabral [[Treasurer of the United States]]]]
&lt;!-- Deleted image removed: [[File:Attorney General Ken Cuccinelli.jpg|thumb|100px|[[Attorney General of Virginia]]]] --&gt;
[[File:Karl Rove.jpg|thumb|100px|Karl Rove [[White House Deputy Chief of Staff|Deputy Chief of Staff]] to President [[George W. Bush]]]]
[[File:Kathleen L. Casey official portrait.jpg|thumb|100px|Kathleen Casey Commissioner of the [[U.S. Securities and Exchange Commission]]]]
{{div col|2}}
* [[Abdiweli Mohamed Ali]], Prime Minister of Somalia
* [[David Bobzien]], member of the [[Nevada Assembly]]
* [[Denise Bode]], energy expert, member of President [[George W. Bush]] Energy Transition Advisory Team
* [[Anna E. Cabral]], Treasurer of the United States under President [[George W. Bush]]
* [[Kathleen L. Casey]], Commissioner of the [[U.S. Securities and Exchange Commission]]
* [[Sean Connaughton]], Virginia Secretary of Transportation, former U.S. Maritime Administrator
* [[Garrison Courtney]], Chief Public Affairs of the [[Drug Enforcement Agency]]
* [[Ken Cuccinelli]], [[Attorney General of Virginia]]
* [[Bob Deuell]], Texas State Senator
* [[Igor Doubenko]], Executive Director, [[United Nations Human Rights Educational Project|UN Human Rights Educational Project]]
* [[Michael Frey]], member of the [[Fairfax County Board of Supervisors]]
* [[Nancy Garland]], member of the [[Ohio house of representatives]]
* [[Juleanna Glover Weiss|Juleanna Glover]], press secretary to Vice President [[Dick Cheney]]
* [[William D. Hansen]], [[US Deputy Secretary of Education]] under President [[George W. Bush]]
* [[Cathy Hudgins]], member of the [[Fairfax County Board of Supervisors]]
* [[Mohammad Khazaee]], Representative of the Islamic Republic of Iran to the [[United Nations|UN]]
* [[Kaye Kory]], Virginia House Delegate
* [[Sherri Kraham]], deputy VP at the [[Millennium Challenge Corporation]]
* [[Mark B. Madsen]], Utah State Senator
* [[Mike Mazzei]], Oklahoma State Senator
* [[William W. Mercer]], [[United States Attorney]] for the District of Montana
* [[John Morlu]], Liberian Presidential Candidate
* [[Liam O'Grady]], [[United States federal judge]]
* [[Paul F. Nichols]], Virginia House Delegate
* [[Nancy Pfotenhauer]], adviser to the [[John McCain]] presidential campaign 2008
* [[Steve Ricchetti]], former Deputy Chief of Staff to President [[Bill Clinton]]
* [[Karl Rove]], former Deputy Chief of Staff to President [[George W. Bush]]&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news | last = McKinnon| first = John D.| title = Karl Rove to Resign At the End of August | newspaper = [[The Wall Street Journal]]| date = August 13, 2007 | url = http://online.wsj.com/article/SB118698747711695773.html| accessdate =April 12, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[James M. Scott (politician)|James M. Scott]], Virginia House Delegate
* [[William P. Winfree]], NASA
* [[Richard L. Young]], [[United States federal judge]]
{{div col end}}

===Literary and media===
{{div col|3}}
* [[Richard Bausch]], novelist
* [[Robert Bausch]], novelist
* [[Stuart Cosgrove]], Scottish journalist, broadcaster and television executive
* [[Chad Ford]], sports journalist and founder of [[ESPN]] Insider
* [[Angie Goff]], traffic presenter, WUSA-9 TV
* [[Hala Gorani]], news anchor, [[CNN]]
* [[Brian Krebs]], journalist
* [[Carolyn Kreiter-Foronda]], [[Poet Laureate of Virginia]]&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.loc.gov/rr/main/poets/virginia.html Virginia Law and Library of Congress List of Poets Laureate of Virginia]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.carolynforonda.com/ Official Site of Carolyn Kreiter-Foronda – Poet, Artist, Educator, Poet Laureate of Virginia]. Carolynforonda.com. Retrieved on 2011-03-11.&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[J. Michael Martinez]], poet
* [[Nadine Meyer]], poet
* [[Stephen Moore (economist)|Stephen Moore]], journalist and policy analyst
* [[Evan Oakley]], poet
* [[Nancy K. Pearson]], poet
* [[Susan Rook]], news anchor, [[CNN]]
* [[Rebecca Wee]], poet
* [[Mark Winegardner]], author
{{div col end}}

===Sports and entertainment===
{{div col|3}}
* [[Julius Achon]], [[Ugandan]] distance runner, 800m American Collegiate record holder
* [[Joe Addo]], soccer player
* [[Mark Adickes]], football player
* [[Negar Assari]], artist
* [[Abdi Bile]], Olympic runner
* [[Lamar Butler]], basketball player
* [[Shawn Camp]], baseball player, [[Toronto Blue Jays]]
* [[Folarin Campbell]], basketball player
* [[Terri Dendy]], Olympic track and field athlete
* [[Ben Dogra]], sports agent
* [[Brent Brockman]], soccer player
* [[Charlie Raphael]], soccer player
* [[Rebecca Cardon]], actress
* [[John Driscoll (actor)|John Driscoll]], actor
* [[Chad Dukes (radio personality)|Chad Dukes]], radio host, [[WJFK-FM]]
* [[Jennifer Derevjanik]], basketball player
* [[Jerry Dunn]], basketball coach
* [[George Evans (basketball)|George Evans]], basketball player
* [[Mike Garrett (soccer)|Mike Garrett]], soccer player
* [[Kristi Lauren Glakas]], Miss Virginia Teen, Miss Virginia USA
* [[King Kamali]], Iranian bodybuilder
* [[Archie Kao]], actor
* [[Jai Lewis]], basketball player
* [[Bob Lilley]], soccer player and head coach
* [[Tamir Linhart]], soccer player
* [[Jason Miskiri]], basketball player
* [[Dayton Moore]], general manager, senior VP, [[Kansas City Royals]]
* [[Rob Muzzio]], Decathlon champion, Olympic athlete
* [[Anthony Noreiga]], soccer player
* [[Gabe Norwood]], [[Philippine Basketball Association]] player
* [[Maegan Phillips]], Miss Virginia USA
* [[Jennifer Pitts]], Miss Virginia, Miss Virginia USA
* [[Mark Pulisic]], soccer player
* [[Kenny Sanders]], basketball player
* [[Tony Skinn]], basketball player
* [[Tommy Steenberg]], iceskater
* [[Will Thomas (basketball)|Will Thomas]], basketball player
* [[Chris Widger]], baseball player
* [[Aimee Willard]], lacrosse player
* [[Ricky Wilson (basketball)|Ricky Wilson]], basketball player
* [[Carlos Yates]], basketball player
* [[Kate Ziegler]], World Record distance swimmer
{{div col end}}

===Other===
{{div col|2}}
* [[Anousheh Ansari]], space tourist
* [[Amir Ansari]], venture capitalist
* [[Sandy Antunes]], astronomer
* [[Randall C. Berg, Jr.]], lawyer
* [[M. Brian Blake]], professor
* [[Mark A. Calabria]], Director of Financial Regulation Studies at the [[Cato Institute]]
* [[Alan M. Davis]], engineer and businessman
* [[Chris DiBona]], Google Public Sector Director
* [[Taylor Edgar]], stand-up comic and musician
* [[Sibel Edmonds]], former [[Federal Bureau of Investigation]] translator
* [[Fred E. Foldvary]], economist
* [[Graham Foust]], professor and poet
* [[Jon Gettman]], marijuana reform activist
* [[Steven Horwitz]], professor
* [[Raynard Jackson]], Republican [[political consultant]]
* [[Matt Kibbe]], President and CEO of [[FreedomWorks]]
* [[Jonathan Klick]], professor
* [[Robert A. Levy]], Chairman of the [[Cato Institute]]
* [[Jeb Livingood]], professor and writer
* [[Daniel Mann (lawyer)|Daniel Mann]], lawyer
* [[George Michael (professor)|George Michael]], professor
* [[Kendrick Moxon]], lawyer and Scientologist
* [[Michael L. Murray]], American folklorist
* [[Angela Orebaugh]], cyber security technologist and professor
* [[Mark Perry (economist)]], professor
* [[Brad Pfaff]], [[USDA]] Wisconsin Farm Service Agency executive director
* [[David Prychitko]], economist
* [[Jose Rodriguez (activist)|Jose Rodriguez]], political activist
* [[Eric Schansberg]], economics professor
* [[Stephen Slivinski]], economist for the [[Goldwater Institute]]
* [[Victoria Stiles]], [[makeup artist]]
* [[Edward Stringham]], professor
* [[Joshua N. Weiss]], mediator
* [[Deborah Willis (artist)|Deborah Willis]], photographer and professor
{{div col end}}

==Notable faculty==
===College of Humanities and Social Sciences===
{{div col|3}}
* [[William Sims Bainbridge]]
* [[Shaul Bakhash]], scholar of Persian studies. Husband of [[Haleh Esfandiari]].
* [[Mary Catherine Bateson]], daughter of American [[cultural anthropologist]] [[Margaret Mead]], former Clarence J. Robinson Professor in Anthropology and English, now Professor Emerita.
* [[Robert Bausch]], novelist
* [[Rei Berroa]], poet
* [[Andrés Boiarsky]]
* [[Courtney Angela Brkic]], poet
* [[Michael Bunn]]
* [[Arthur W. Chickering]]
* [[Alan Cheuse]], novelist
* [[Wilfrid Desan]]
* [[Bùi Diễm]], [[South Vietnam]]'s Ambassador to the United States
* [[Robert J. Elder, Jr]], Air Force Commander
* [[Marita Golden]], novelist
* [[Gerald L. Gordon]]
* [[Joshua Greenberg]]
* [[Hugh Gusterson]]
* [[Helon Habila]]
* [[Deanna Hammond]]
* [[Frances V. Harbour]]
* [[Hugh Heclo]], professor of American politics and winner of John Gaus award.
* [[Carma Hinton]], documentary flimmaker. Credits include [[The Gate of Heavenly Peace]]
* [[Mark N. Katz]]
* [[Peter Klappert]], poet
* [[Gary L Kreps]]
* [[Lawrence W. Levine]], historian
* [[Suzannah Lessard]], writer
* [[Samuel Robert Lichter]], former professor at [[Princeton University]], [[Georgetown University]], [[George Washington University]], [[Yale]], and [[Columbia University]].
* [[Peter Mandaville]], professor of international affairs and scholar of political Islam.
* [[Nadine Meyer]], poet
* [[Robert Nadeau (science historian)|Robert Nadeau]], English professor
* [[Eric Pankey]], poet
* [[Roy Rosenzweig]]
* [[Richard E. Rubenstein]]
* [[Martin Sherwin]], [[Pulitzer Prize]] winner for his biography of [[Robert Oppenheimer]]
* [[Clare Shore]]
* [[Susan Shreve]]
* [[Richard Norton Smith]] Presidential historian &amp; former director of five presidential libraries.&lt;ref&gt;[http://georgewbush-whitehouse.archives.gov/government/smith-bio.html Biography of Richard Norton Smith]. Georgewbush-whitehouse.archives.gov (2005-09-06). Retrieved on 2011-03-11.&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[Rod Smith (poet)|Rod Smith]], poet
* [[Peter Stearns]], American historian and current provost
* [[Rex A. Wade]], professor of Russian history.
* [[Roger Wilkins]], [[Pulitzer Prize]] winner for coverage of the [[Watergate scandal]] (along with [[Bob Woodward]] and [[Carl Bernstein]] while he was working at ''[[The Washington Post]].'') Now retired.
* [[Margaret R. Yocom]]
* [[Mary Kay Zuravleff]], novelist
{{div col end}}

===Department of Economics===
{{div col|3}}
[[File:James Buchanan by Atlas network.jpg|thumb|100px|[[James M. Buchanan]], [[Nobel Prize]]-winning [[economist]]]]
[[File:VernonSmith2.jpg|thumb|100px|[[Vernon L. Smith]], [[Nobel Prize]]-winning [[economist]]]]
&lt;!-- Deleted image removed: [[File:Wew2010.jpg|thumb|100px|[[Walter E. Williams]], [[Print syndication|Syndicated]] Columnist]] --&gt;
[[File:Gordon tullock.jpg|thumb|100px|[[Gordon Tullock]], Developed the [[Public Choice theory]]]]
* [[Peter Boettke]]
* [[Kenneth E. Boulding]], cofounder of the [[General Systems Theory]]
* [[Donald J. Boudreaux]]
* [[James M. Buchanan]], [[Nobel Prize]]-winning [[economist]] (1986)
* [[Henry N. Butler]]
* [[Bryan Caplan]]
* [[Tyler Cowen]]
* [[Christopher Coyne (professor)|Christopher Coyne]]
* [[Richard H. Fink]], Executive Vice President of the [[Koch Industries]]
* [[Joseph L. Fisher]], U.S. Congressman from Virginia
* [[Jack A. Goldstone]]
* [[Wendy Lee Gramm]]
* [[Robin Hanson]]
* [[Laurence Iannaccone]]
* [[Manuel H. Johnson]], Former Vice Governor of the Federal Reserve
* [[Arnold Kling]]
* [[Daniel B. Klein]]
* [[Don Lavoie]]
* [[Peter T. Leeson]]
* [[Kevin McCabe (economist)|Kevin McCabe]]
* [[Maurice McTigue]], former Minister for Labor in New Zealand
* [[James C. Miller III]], Director of the Office of Management and Budget under President [[Ronald Reagan]]
* [[Russell Roberts (economist)|Russell Roberts]]
* [[George Selgin]]
* [[Vernon L. Smith]], [[Nobel Prize]]-winning [[economist]] (2002)
* [[Alex Tabarrok]]
* [[Robert Tollison]]
* [[Gordon Tullock]], Developed the [[Public Choice Theory]]
* [[Bruce Yandle]], Executive Director of the [[Federal Trade Commission]]
* [[Richard E. Wagner]]
* [[Lawrence H. White]]
* [[Walter E. Williams]], John M. Olin Distinguished Professor of Economics
* [[Bart Wilson]]
{{div col end}}

===School of Public Policy===
[[File:Michael Hayden, CIA official portrait.jpg|thumb|100px|[[Michael Hayden (general)|Michael Hayden]], former director of the [[CIA]]]]
[[File:Thomas J Miller - State 2002.gif|thumb|100px|[[United States Ambassador to Greece]] and [[United States Ambassador to Bosnia and Herzegovina|Bosnia and Herzegovina]]]]
* [[Zoltan Acs]]
* [[David S. Alberts]], Director of Research for the Office of the [[Assistant Secretary of Defense]]
* [[Kenneth Button]]
* [[Thomas M. Davis]], former U.S. Congressman from Virginia
* [[Desmond Dinan]]
* [[Richard Florida]]
* [[William Conrad Gibbons]]
* [[Marc Gopin]]
* [[Stephen Haseler]]
* [[Michael Hayden (general)|Michael Hayden]], former CIA Director
* [[Seymour Martin Lipset]]
* [[Patrick Mendis]], US Diplomat
* [[Patrick Michaels]]
* [[Thomas J. Miller (diplomat)|Thomas J. Miller]], US Ambassador to Greece, and Bosnia and Herzegovina
* [[Bill Schneider (journalist)]], CNN's senior political analyst
* [[Louise Shelley]]
* [[Jeremy Shearmur]]
* [[Richard Norton Smith]]
* [[John N. Warfield]]

===College of Science===
* [[David Albright]]
* [[Ken Alibek]], Colonel in the [[Soviet Union]] in charge of biodefense
* [[Robert Axtell]]
* [[Caroline Crocker]], [[pharmacologist|immunopharmacologist]] who teaches [[Objections to evolution|creationist claims]] about [[evolution]]
* [[Peter J. Denning]]
* [[Klaus Fischer (mathematician)|Klaus Fischer]], mathematician
* [[Peter A. Freeman]]
* [[Robert Hazen]], Clarence Robinson Professor of Earth Science, and author
* [[Abul Hussam]], inventor of the Sono arsenic filter, for which he received the 2007 sustainability prize awarded by the National Academy of Engineering
* [[Angela Orebaugh]]
* [[Suresh V. Shenoy]]
* [[Fred Singer]]
* [[Jagdish Shukla]], founding member of the [[International Centre for Theoretical Physics]]
* [[John P. Snyder]], cartographer
* [[James Trefil]], physicist, and author
* [[Ernst Volgenau]], chairman and founder of [[SRA International]]
* [[Edward Wegman]], statistician
* [[Boris Willis]]

===School of Management===
* [[Teresa J. Domzal]], dean of the school of management
* [[Jim Larranaga]], Mason's head men's basketball coach since 1997
* [[Anthony Sanders]], Distinguished Professor of Real Estate Finance
* [[Raymond W. Smith]]

===School of Law===
* [[Peter Berkowitz]]
* [[David Bernstein (law professor)|David Bernstein]]
* [[Lawrence J. Block]], [[Federal Judge]]
* [[Frank H. Buckley]]
* [[Henry N. Butler]], Republican Candidate for member of the [[U.S. House of Representatives]] from [[Virginia's 11th congressional district]]
* [[Susan Dudley]], Administrator of the [[Office of Information and Regulatory Affairs]] under President [[George W. Bush]]
* [[Victoria Espinel]], United States Intellectual Property Enforcement Coordinator
* [[Adrian S. Fisher]], lawyer, diplomat, and politician during the 60s and 70s
* [[Sandra Froman]], President of the [[National Rifle Association of America]]
* [[Sigrid Fry-Revere]], founder and president of [[Center for Ethical Solutions]]
* [[Ernest Gellhorn]]
* [[Douglas H. Ginsburg]], judge on the [[United States Court of Appeals for the District of Columbia Circuit]], and Ronald Reagan's nominee to the [[United States Supreme Court]]
* [[Irving Kayton]], founder of the [[Patent Resources Group]], Inc. (PRG)
* [[William Kovacic]], former member of the [[Federal Trade Commission]]
* [[Michael I. Krauss]], former Commissioner for Québec's Human Rights Commission
* [[William H. Lash]], former United States Assistant Secretary of Commerce
* [[James LeMunyon]], former United States Assistant Secretary of Commerce
* [[Leonard Liggio]], Vice President of [[Atlas Economic Research Foundation]]
* [[Deborah Platt Majoras]], former chairman of the [[Federal Trade Commission]]
* [[Henry Manne]]
* [[James C. Miller III]], Chairman of the [[Federal Trade Commission]] and [[Office of Management and Budget|Budget Director]] for President Ronald Reagan
* [[Timothy Muris]], former chairman of the [[Federal Trade Commission]]
* [[Raymond O'Brien]]
* [[Jeremy A. Rabkin]]
* [[Chuck Robb]], former Governor of Virginia and former U.S. Senator
* [[William J. Roberts]], [[Copyright Royalty Board|copyright royalty judge]]
* [[Kyndra Miller Rotunda]], Army JAG officer
* [[Hans-Bernd Schäfer]]
* [[Loren A. Smith]], [[Federal Judge]]
* [[Michael Uhlmann]]
* [[Clay T. Whitehead]], former director of the White House Office of Telecommunications Policy
* [[Todd Zywicki]], former Director of the Office of Policy Planning at the [[Federal Trade Commission]]

===School of Recreation, Health, and Tourism===
* [[Steve Baumann]], Chief Executive of the [[National Soccer Hall of Fame]]
* [[Charley Casserly]], General Manager of the [[Washington Redskins]] and [[Houston Texans]]
* [[Craig Esherick]], former head coach of the Georgetown basketball team

==Accreditation==
* [[Southern Association of Colleges and Schools]]

==References==
{{Reflist|colwidth=30em}}

==External links==
{{Spoken Wikipedia|George_Mason_University.ogg|2006-01-16}}
* [http://www.gmu.edu/ Official website]
* [http://gomason.cstv.com/ Official Athletics website]
* [http://www.connect2mason.com/ Connect2Mason Student Run Blog]

{{George Mason University}}
{{Colleges and universities in Virginia}}
{{Colonial Athletic Association}}
{{Fairfax County navbox}}

[[Category:Educational institutions established in 1957]]
[[Category:George Mason]]
[[Category:George Mason University| ]]
[[Category:Universities and colleges in Virginia]]
[[Category:Association of Public and Land-Grant Universities]]
[[Category:American Association of State Colleges and Universities]]
[[Category:Education in Fairfax County, Virginia]]
[[Category:Engineering universities and colleges in Virginia]]
[[Category:Oak Ridge Associated Universities]]
[[Category:Universities and colleges in Ras al-Khaimah]]
[[Category:Universities and colleges accredited by the Southern Association of Colleges and Schools]]
[[Category:Public universities in the United States]]
[[Category:Education in Arlington County, Virginia]]
[[Category:Education in Prince William County, Virginia]]
[[Category:Education in Loudoun County, Virginia]]

[[ar:جامعة جورج ميسن]]
[[bg:Университет Джордж Мейсън]]
[[de:George Mason University]]
[[es:Universidad George Mason]]
[[fa:دانشگاه جرج میسون]]
[[fr:George Mason University]]
[[ga:Ollscoil George Mason]]
[[ja:ジョージ・メイソン大学]]
[[pt:Universidade George Mason]]
[[ru:Университет Джорджа Мейсона]]
[[simple:George Mason University]]
[[fi:George Masonin yliopisto]]
[[sv:George Mason University]]
[[vi:Đại học George Mason]]
[[zh:喬治梅森大學]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
