<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="1258430" ns="0" title="Malayali"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Use dmy dates|date=October 2011}}
{{Infobox Ethnic group
|group= '''മലയാളി'''&lt;br&gt;'''Malayali'''&lt;br&gt;'''''Plural: Malayalikal'''''
|image = [[File:AdiShankara1.jpg|85px]] [[File:Shashi Tharoor WEF.png|75px]]&lt;br /&gt;[[File:Arundhati Roy.jpg|78px]] [[File:DirectorAdoor.jpg|77px]] [[File:Narayana Guru.jpg|77px]][[File:Ravivarma1 140x190.jpg|85px]] [[File:Kocheril Raman Narayanan.jpg|85px]]
|caption  = '''[[List of people from Kerala|Notable List of Malayalees]]:'''	
[[Adi Shankara]]{{•}}[[Shashi Tharoor]]{{•}}[[Arundhati Roy]]{{•}}[[Adoor Gopalakrishnan]]{{•}}[[Sreesanth]]{{•}}{{•}}[[Narayana Guru]]{{•}}[[Raja Ravi Varma]]{{•}}[[K. R. Narayanan]]
|poptime  = '''35,757,100''' (1997)&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.ethnologue.com/show_language.asp?code=mal Ethnologue report for Malayalam]&lt;/ref&gt;
|region1 = {{Flagu|India}}
|pop1    =  33,066,392
|region2 = {{Flagu|United Arab Emirates}}
|pop2    = 773,624
|ref2    =&lt;ref name=&quot;NoRKA&quot;&gt;Zachariah, K. C. &amp; Rajan, S. Irudaya (2008), ''[http://www.cds.edu/admin/homeFiles/Kerala%20Migration%20Survey%202007.pdf Kerala Migration Survey 2007]'' (PDF), Department of Non-resident Keralite Affairs, Government of Kerala, p. 48. This is the number of emigrants from Kerala, which is closely related to but different from the actual number of Malayalis.&lt;/ref&gt;
|region3 = {{Flagu|Saudi Arabia}}
|pop3    = 447,440
|ref3    =&lt;ref name=&quot;NoRKA&quot;/&gt;
|region4 = {{Flagu|Kuwait}}
|pop4    = 134,728
|ref4    =&lt;ref name=&quot;NoRKA&quot;/&gt;
|region5 = {{Flagu|Oman}}
|pop5    = 134,019
|ref5    =&lt;ref name=&quot;NoRKA&quot;/&gt;
|region6 = {{Flagu|United States}}
|pop6    = 105,655
|ref6    =&lt;ref name=&quot;NoRKA&quot;/&gt;
|region7 = {{Flagu|United Kingdom}}
|pop7    = 100,737
|ref7    =&lt;ref name=&quot;NoRKA&quot;/&gt;
|region8 = {{Flagu|Qatar}}
|pop8    = 94,310
|ref8    =&lt;ref name=&quot;NoRKA&quot;/&gt;
|region9 = {{Flagu|Bahrain}}
|pop9    = 58,146
|ref9    =&lt;ref name=&quot;NoRKA&quot;/&gt;
|region10 = {{Flagu|Canada}}
|pop10    = 12,346
|ref10    =&lt;ref name=&quot;NoRKA&quot;/&gt;
|region11 = {{Flagu|Malaysia}}
|pop11    = 11,936
|ref11    =&lt;ref name=&quot;NoRKA&quot;/&gt;
|region12 = {{Flagu|Australia}}
|pop12    = 10,793
|ref12    =&lt;ref name=&quot;IMMI&quot;/&gt;
|region13 = {{Flagu|Singapore}}
|pop13    = 7,800
|ref13    =&lt;ref name=&quot;NoRKA&quot;/&gt;
|region14 = {{Flagu|Pakistan}}
|pop14    = 6,000
|ref14    =&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.dnaindia.com/world/report_where-malayalees-once-held-sway_4610 Where Malayalees once held sway: DNA India]&lt;/ref&gt;
|region15 = {{Flagu|Israel}}
|region16 = {{Flagu|Germany}}
|region17 = {{Flagu|Thailand}}
|region18 = {{Flagu|South Africa}}
|region19 = {{Flagu|Botswana}}
|region20 = {{Flagu|Maldives}}
|langs    = [[Malayalam language|Malayalam]] (മലയാളം)
|religions =[[Hinduism]], Islam, Christianity, [[Jainism]], [[Buddhism]], Judaism
|related = [[Dravidian people]], [[Brahui people]], [[Kannadiga]], [[Tamil people]], [[Telugu people]], [[Tuluva]]}}

'''Malayali''' (also spelled '''Malayalee'''; {{indic|lang=ml|indic=മലയാളി|trans=Malayāḷi}}; plural: '''Malayalikal''') is the term used to refer to the native speakers of [[Malayalam]], originating from the Indian state of [[Kerala]]. The Malayali identity is primarily linguistic, although in recent times the definition has been broadened to include emigrants of Malayali descent who partly maintain Malayali [[cultural identity|cultural traditions]], even if they do not regularly speak the language. While the origins of the Malayali people are in the state of Kerala, significant populations also exist in other parts of India, the Middle East, Europe and North America. According to the Indian census of 2001, there were 30,803,747 speakers of Malayalam in Kerala,&lt;ref name = &quot;Censusedia&quot;/&gt; making up 96.7% of the total population of that state. Hence the word '''Keralite''' is often used in the same context, though a proper definition is ambiguous.

==Etymology==
Malayalam, the Malayalis' native language, has its origin from the words ''mala'' meaning ''mountain'' and ''alam'' meaning land ([[Tamil language|Tamil]]/[[Malayalam]]) or locality (which lies along side the mountain).&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.kerala.gov.in/|title=kerala.gov.in}}-go to the website and click the link –  language &amp; literature to retrieve the information&lt;/ref&gt; Hence 'Malayali' means ''people from the mountains'' who lived beyond the [[Western Ghats]], and Malayalam the language that was spoken there.

==Geographic distribution and population==
{{See also|Kerala Gulf diaspora}}
According to the Indian census of 2001, there were 30,803,747 speakers of Malayalam in Kerala, making up 93.2% of the total number of Malayalam speakers in India, and 96.7% of the total population of the state. There were a further 701,673 (2.1% of the total number) in [[Karnataka]], 557,705 (1.7%) in [[Tamil Nadu]], and 406,358 (1.2%) in [[Maharashtra]]. The number of Malayalam speakers in [[Lakshadweep]] is 51,100, which is only 0.15% of the total number, but is as much as about 84% of the population of Lakshadweep. In all, Malayalis made up 3.22% of the total Indian population in 2001. Of the total 33,066,392 Malayalam speakers in India in 2001,  33,015,420 spoke the standard dialects, 19,643 spoke the ''Yerava'' dialect and 31,329 spoke non-standard regional variations like ''Eranadan''.&lt;ref name = &quot;Censusedia&quot;&gt;[http://www.censusindia.gov.in/Census_Data_2001/Census_Data_Online/Language/data_on_language.html], ''censusindia.net''&lt;/ref&gt; As per the 1991 census data, 28.85% of all Malayalam speakers in India spoke another second language and 19.64% of the total knew 3 or more languages. 

Large numbers of Malayalis have settled in [[Delhi]], [[Bangalore]], [[Hyderabad, Andhra Pradesh|Hyderabad]], [[Mumbai]] (Bombay), [[Pune]] and [[Chennai]] (Madras). A large number of Malayalis have also emigrated to the [[Middle East]], the [[United States]], and [[Europe]]. There were 179,860 speakers of Malayalam in the [[United States]], according to the 2000 census, with the highest concentrations in [[Bergen County, New Jersey]] and [[Rockland County, New York]]. There were 7,093 Malayalam speakers in [[Australia]] in 2006.&lt;ref name = &quot;IMMI&quot;&gt;[http://www.immi.gov.au/media/publications/research/_pdf/poa-2008.pdf]&lt;/ref&gt; The 2001 [[Canadian census]] reported 7,070 people who listed Malayalam as their mother tongue.  The 2006 [[New Zealand]] census reported 2,139 speakers.&lt;ref name = &quot;NZ&quot;&gt;[http://www.stats.govt.nz/~/media/Statistics/Publications/Census/2006%20Census%20reports/QuickStats%20About%20A%20Subject/QuickStats%20About%20Culture%20and%20Identity/quickstats-about-culture-and-identity-tables.ashx Statistics New Zealand:Language spoken (total responses) for the 1996–2006 censuses (Table 16)], ''stats.govt.nz''&lt;/ref&gt; 134 Malayalam speaking households were reported in 1956 in [[Fiji]]. There is also a considerable Malayali population in the [[Persian Gulf]] regions, especially in [[Dubai]].

==Communities==
Historically, religion and caste played a major role in community, with individuals associating and marrying within their religion or caste.  Hence, Malayali communities can be differentiated along historical religious lines.

===Hindu===
====Ezhava====
{{Main|Ezhava}}

The Ezhavas are the largest [[Hindu]] community in [[Kerala]]. [[Ezhava]]s are also found amongst the Malayali diaspora around the world. Ezhavas are today a social group sharing a common history from the pre-social reform era. With a population of 7.3&amp;nbsp;million Ezhavas are the largest Hindu community in Kerala.

====Samanta Kshatriya====
{{Main|Samanta Kshatriya}}

The Samanta Kshatriyas (also known as Malayala Kshatriya) who use the surname Varma or Raja, are a group of people who belonged to the [[Chandravanshi]] [[Kshatriya]] division of the [[Hindu]] [[caste]] system among Malayalees and their residences were traditionally called ''Kovilakams'' or ''Kottaram'' or ''Swaroopams''. They themselves belong to a subgroup of [[Nairs]] and they form the highest ranking division among [[Nairs]]. In traditional texts such as the [[Keralolpathi]] they are referred to as &quot;Samantha Kshatriyas&quot;.

====Nambudiri====
{{Main|Nambudiri}}

The Nambudiri Brahmins are the indigenous [[Brahmins]] of [[Kerala]], who are considered the most [[orthodoxy|orthodox]] Brahmins in India.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.encyclopedia.com/doc/1B1-372990.html], ''encyclopedia.com''&lt;/ref&gt; They perform rituals in temples of Kerala based on Tantra Vidhi, a complex and ancient branch of [[Tantra|Tantric]] traditions found only in Kerala, and some ''Mahakshetras'' (&quot;Great Temples&quot;) around India (which have a Nambudiri acting as the Head Priest). Namboothiris follow the conservative and ritualistic [[Śrauta]] traditions and the ancient [[Mimamsa|Purva Mimamsa]], unlike the majority of other Brahmins in India who follow the [[Vedanta]].

====Nair====
{{Main|Nair}}
[[Image:Raja Ravi Varma, There Comes Papa (1893).jpg|thumbnail|right|A  lady wearing the [[Mundum Neryathum]] in the traditional regal style]]
Nairs (sometimes spelled '''Nayar''') are a [[Hindu]] upper caste belonging to [[Nagavanshi]]  division of the [[Hindu]] [[caste]] system. The Nairs were a martial nobility&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.canisius.edu/topos/archives/rajeev6.pdf Neither Newton nor Leibniz], ''canisius.edu''&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.veda.harekrsna.cz/encyclopedia/aikido.htm From Vedic Martial Arts to Aikido], ''veda.harekrsna.cz''&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.rediff.com/travel/1998/apr/30kala1.htm A travel feature on the ancient Kerala art of Kalaripayattu], ''rediff.com''&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.enskalari.org.in/kalari.htm Kalaripayattu, the traditional martial art], ''enskalari.org.in''&lt;/ref&gt; and figure prominently in the history of Kerala. The Nairs form the second largest Hindu community in Kerala.

====Ambalavasi====
{{Main|Ambalavasi}}

Ambalavasi is the name of a [[Kerala]] community (not to be confused with caste) composed of a number of [[Hindu]] [[castes]] such as [[Pushpaka Brahmin|Pushpakas]] ([[Unni]], [[Nambeesan]], etc.), [[Chakyar]]s, [[Moothath]]s, [[Ilayath]]s, [[Kurukkal]]s, [[Warrier]]s, [[Marar]]s, [[Nambiar (Ambalavasi)|Nambiar]]s, [[Pisharody]], etc. Traditionally, they perform temple related jobs and art forms.

====Pulaya====
{{Main|Pulayar}}

[[File:Ayyankali Statue.jpg|150px|thumb|Ayyankali statue at [[Thiruvananthapuram]]]]
The Pulayas, also known as Pulayar are one of the main [[social groups]] found in the [[Kerala]] society, who were traditionally engaged in various agriculture-related occupations. [[Ayyankali]] (1863–1914), one among the great social reformers of India, who was praised by Mahatma Gandhi when he visited [[Venganoor]], was born to a Malayali [[Pulaya]] family.

===Muslim===
{{Main|Mappila}}

Malayali Muslims are members of a Malayalam-speaking Islamic community spread across [[Kerala]], [[Lakshadweep]], [[Kodagu]] and across Malayali Diaspora around the world. In [[North Kerala]] they are known as [[Mappila]]s or Moplahs. The word ''mappila'' is derived from the old (pure) Malayalam words ''Amma'' and ''pilla'' meaning ''Child Mother''. The Mappilas are believed to be the earliest known Indian Muslim community, having existed since the 8th century CE, when [[Arab]] merchants who had long been trading with the [[Chera dynasty|Chera]] kingdom  settled in Kerala. The Muslims in Kerala cannot be easily distinguished in the community as they still retain their Malayali features.{{Citation needed|date=January 2009}} They follow the preachings of [[monotheism]] by [[Muhammad]] in [[Arabia]], especially the [[UAE]] and other Gulf countries . They propagated their Islamic faith along the [[Malabarian Coast|Malabar Coast]]. Most Mappila Muslims follow the [[Shafi'i]] school of Muslim Jurisprudence (in contrast to the [[Hanafi]] school followed by most South Asian Muslims). A good amount of mappila's find their income from gulf region. In north [[Malabar (Northern Kerala)|malabar]], from [[malappuram]] to [[kasargod]], at least one of 3 Muslim house have foreign income.

===Christian===
{{Main|Saint Thomas Christians}}

Christians form the third largest group in Kerala. Over the centuries, they have blended well with the changing socio-cultural environment of the region, becoming uniquely Indian and Christian.

According to beliefs, Christianity in India dates to [[Thomas the Apostle]]’s conversion of local population in Kerala during the 1st century CE.&lt;ref name=&quot;AFM&quot;&gt;A.E. Medlycott, ''India and The Apostle Thomas'', pp.1–71, 213–97; M.R. James, ''Apocryphal New Testament'', pp.364–436; Eusebius, ''History'', chapter 4:30; J.N. Farquhar, ''The Apostle Thomas in North India'', chapter 4:30; V.A. Smith, ''Early History of India'', p.235; L.W. Brown, ''The Indian Christians of St. Thomas'', p.49-59&lt;/ref&gt; The 3rd and 4th centuries saw an influx of Christians from the Middle East. [[Knanaya]] communities arrived during this time. Distance kept the community of [[St Thomas Christians]] separate from other Christian communities until about the 8th century, when they started receiving [[bishops]] and support from the [[Chaldean Church]]. The arrival of [[Europeans]] in the 15th century and discontent with Portuguese interference in religious matters fomented [[schism ]]into [[Catholic]] and [[Orthodox]] communities. Further schism, rearrangements, and missionary activity led to the formation of the other Indian Churches. [[Latin Rite]] Christians were converted by the [[Portugal|Portuguese]] in the 16th and 19th centuries mainly from communities where fishing was the traditional occupation. [[Anglo-Indian]] Christian communities formed around this time as Europeans and local Malayalis intermarried.  [[Protestantism]] arrived a few centuries later with missionary activity during [[British rule]]. The community today can broadly divided into [[Catholic]], [[Oriental Orthodoxy|Orthodox]], [[Pentecost]] and [[Protestant]] groups.  It is important to note that despite being a heterogeneous group, Malayali Christians find unity in a common history and faith.

===Jewish===
[[Image:Cochin Jews.jpg|thumb|An Indian Jewish family in [[Cochin]], circa 1900.]]

{{See also|Cochin Jews|Paradesi Jews|Sephardic Jews in India}}

Cochin Jews, also called Malabar Jews (Malabar Yehudan) are the ancient Jews and their descendants of the erstwhile state of [[Kingdom of Cochin]] which includes the present day port city of [[Kochi, India|Kochi]].&lt;ref&gt;Katz 2000; Koder 1973; Menachery 1998; Thomas Puthiakunnel 1973; Weil 1982; Menachery 1998.&lt;/ref&gt; They traditionally spoke [[Judeo-Malayalam]], a form of the [[Malayalam]] tongue, native to the state of Kerala. The Jews of Cochin did not adhere to the [[Talmud]]ic prohibition, followed by other [[Orthodox Jew]]s, against public singing by women, and therefore have a rich tradition of Jewish prayers and narrative songs performed by women in Judeo-Malayalam.

Their population has been greatly reduced from historical numbers, as many have emigrated to [[Israel]] to settle in the [[Negev]]. Part of the decline in Kerala's Jewish population can also be attributed to conversion.&lt;ref name=Weil-Menachery-Menachery&gt;Weil S. 1982; Jessay P.M. 1986; Menachery 1973; Menachery 1998.&lt;/ref&gt; Many of the Jews that converted during the time of [[Thomas the Apostle|Saint Thomas]] became [[Kerala|Kerala's]] [[Syrian Malabar Nasrani|Nasrani]] or [[Saint Thomas Christians]].&lt;ref name=Weil-Menachery-Menachery/&gt;

===Unclassified===
{{Main|Atheism in Kerala}}

With the growth in intermarriage between Malayali communities and also with other groups, especially outside Kerala, many people who identify themselves with Kerala or with Malayali culture can not readily be labeled as members of one of the historic castes or communities listed above. Also, although a number of these groups were historically affiliated to one or other religion or sect, many of their modern members may be agnostic or [[atheist]], or identify more strongly with some other religious or [[non-religious]] ideology. Nevertheless, Malayalis have been a open-minded people who are accepting of various groups irrespective of caste and class in their community.

==Culture==
Malayali cultural genesis can be traced to their membership (around the 3rd century CE) in a well defined historical region known as ''[[ancient Tamil country|Tamilakam]]'', encompassing the [[Chera Dynasty|Chera]], [[Chola]], and [[Pandya]] kingdoms and southern coastal [[Karnataka]]. Later upon the arrival of other ethnic groups such as [[Namboothiris]], [[Nairs]], etc. the distinct culture took shape. This was later elaborated upon by centuries of contact with foreign cultures such as [[Syrian]], [[Judeo]], [[Arabian]], Portuguese, English communities which have left their mark.&lt;ref name=&quot;Bhagyalekshmy_2004_7&quot;&gt;{{harvnb|Bhagyalekshmy|2004|pp=6–7}}.&lt;/ref&gt; These foreign communities often settled in Kerala and assimilated with  the local population resulting in different ethnic groups such as the [[Cochin Jews]], [[Mappila]]s, [[Syrian Malabar Nasranis]], and [[Anglo Indian]].

===Language and Literature===
[[File:Aasaan.jpg|150px|thumb|Mahakavi [[Kumaran Asan]] was one of the Triumvirate poets of modern Malayalam. Shown here is a portrait of Asan.]]
Malayalam is the language spoken by the Malayalis. Malayalam is derived from Middle Tamil in the 6th century, of which [[Tamil language|Modern Tamil]] was also derived.&lt;ref name=&quot;ReferenceA&quot;&gt;Malayalam, R. E. Asher, T. C. Kumari, Routledge, ISBN 0-415-02242-8, 1997&lt;/ref&gt; An alternative theory proposes a split in more ancient times.&lt;ref name=&quot;ReferenceA&quot;/&gt; For cultural purposes Malayalam and Sanskrit formed a language known as [[Manipravalam]], where both languages were used in an alternating style. Malayalam is the only among the major [[Dravidian languages]] without [[diglossia]]. This means, that the Malayalam which is spoken does not differ from the written variant. Malayalam is written using the [[Malayalam script]].

[[Malayalam literature]] is ancient in origin. The oldest literature works in [[Malayalam]], distinct from the Tamil tradition, is dated between 9th century and 11th century.&lt;ref name=&quot;ReferenceA&quot;/&gt; Malayalam literature includes the 14th century [[Niranam poets]] (Madhava Panikkar, Sankara Panikkar and Rama Panikkar), whose works mark the dawn of both modern Malayalam language and indigenous Keralite poetry. The [[Triumvirate poets of modern malayalam|Triumvirate of poets]] (''Kavithrayam'':  Kumaran Asan, [[Vallathol Narayana Menon]] and Ulloor S. Parameswara Iyer)&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://books.google.co.in/books?id=vfSPI2irzUgC&amp;pg=PA185&amp;dq=Vallathol#v=onepage&amp;q=Vallathol&amp;f=false|title=Trios of modern Malayalam literature}}&lt;/ref&gt; are recognized for moving Keralite poetry away from archaic [[sophistry]] and [[metaphysics]] and towards a more [[lyrics|lyrical]] mode.In the second half of the 20th century, [[Jnanpith]] awardees like [[G. Sankara Kurup]], [[S. K. Pottekkatt]], [[Thakazhi Sivasankara Pillai]] and [[M. T. Vasudevan Nair]] have made valuable contributions to the Malayalam literature. Later, such Keralite writers as [[O. V. Vijayan]], [[Kamaladas]], [[M. Mukundan]], and [[Booker Prize]] winner [[Arundhati Roy]], whose 1996 semi-autobiographical bestseller&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |author=Cooper KJ &lt;!--|last=Cooper |first=Kenneth--&gt; |title=For India, No Small Thing; Native Daughter Arundhati Roy Wins Coveted Booker Prize |work=Washington Post |date=20 October 1997 |accessdate=28 December 2008 |url=http://pqasb.pqarchiver.com/washingtonpost/access/19563051.html?dids=19563051:19563051&amp;FMT=ABS&amp;FMTS=ABS:FT&amp;date=OCT+20%2C+1997&amp;author=Kenneth+J.+Cooper&amp;pub=The+Washington+Post&amp;desc=For+India%2C+No+Small+Thing%3B+Native+Daughter+Arundhati+Roy+Wins+Coveted+Booker+Prize&amp;pqatl=google }}&lt;/ref&gt; ''[[The God of Small Things]]'' is set in the [[Kottayam]] town of Ayemenem, have gained international recognition.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |title=Indian's First Novel Wins Booker Prize in Britain |work=New York Times |date=15 October 1997 |accessdate=11 November 2007 |url=http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A01E6DD173FF936A25753C1A961958260 | first=Sarah | last=Lyall}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |title=Winds, Rivers &amp; Rain |publisher=[[Salon.com|Salon]] |month=September | year=1997 |accessdate=11 November 2007 |url=http://www.salon.com/sept97/00roy.html }}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Tharavadu===
{{Main|Tharavadu}}

Tharavadu is a system of joint family practised by Malayalis, especially castes like [[Nambudiri]]s, [[Nairs]], and [[Ezhavas]]. Each Tharavadu has a unique name.  The Tharavadu was administered by the ''Karanavan'', the oldest male member of the family.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://books.google.co.in/books?id=rMRw0gTZSJwC&amp;pg=PA84&amp;dq=Malayali+tharavadu+system#v=onepage&amp;q=&amp;f=false|title=Tharavadu system}}&lt;/ref&gt; He would be the eldest maternal uncle of the family as well. The members of the Tharavadu consisted of mother, daughters, sons, sisters and brothers. The fathers and husbands had very minimal role to play in the affairs of the Tharavadu. It was a true matrilineal affair. The Karanavar took all major decisions. He was usually autocratic. However, the consent of the eldest female member of the family was taken before implementing the decisions. This eldest female member would be his maternal grandmother, own mother, mother's sister, his own sister or a sister through his maternal lineage. Since the lineage was through the female members, the birth of a daughter was always welcomed. Each Tharavadu also has a ''Para Devatha'' (clan deity) revered by those in the particular Tharavadu. Temples were built to honor these deities.

Kerala's society is less patriarchical than the rest of the [[Majority World]].&lt;ref name=&quot;McKibben_2006&quot;&gt;{{Harvnb|McKibben|2006}}.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Lindberg_2004_18-19&quot;&gt;{{Harvnb|Lindberg|2004|pp=18–19}}.&lt;/ref&gt; Certain Hindu communities such as the Nairs, some [[Ezhava]] families in [[Travancore]] and [[Cochin]], [[Ezhava]]s in north [[Kerala]] and Muslims around [[Kannur]] used to follow a traditional matrilineal system known as ''[[marumakkathayam]]'' which has in the recent years (post Indian independence) ceased to exist. Christians, Muslims, and some Hindu castes such as the Namboothiris and some Ezhavas follow ''makkathayam'', a patrilineal system.&lt;ref name=&quot;GOK_2002b&quot;&gt;{{Harvnb|Government of Kerala|2002b}}.&lt;/ref&gt; Kerala's gender relations are among the most equitable in India and the Majority World.&lt;ref name=&quot;GOK_2004r_366&quot;&gt;{{Harvnb|Government of Kerala|2004r|p=366}}.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Lindberg_2004_1&quot;&gt;{{Harvnb|Lindberg|2004|p=1}}.&lt;/ref&gt;

===Architecture===
{{main|Architecture of Kerala}}

Kerala, the native land of Malayalis has a tropical climate with excessive rains and intensive solar radiation.&lt;ref name=&quot;Kerala architecture&quot;&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.keralahistory.ac.in/keralaarchitecture.htm|title=Kerala architecture}}&lt;/ref&gt; The architecture of this region has evolved  to meet these climatic conditions by having the form of buildings with low walls, sloping roof and projecting caves.&lt;ref name=&quot;Kerala architecture&quot;/&gt; The setting of the building in the open garden plot was again necessitated by the requirement of wind for giving comfort in the humid climate.&lt;ref name=&quot;Kerala architecture&quot;/&gt; Timber is the prime structural material abundantly available in many varieties in Kerala. Perhaps the skillful choice of timber, accurate joinery, artful assembly and delicate carving of wood work for columns, walls and roofs frames are the unique characteristics of Malayali architecture.&lt;ref name=&quot;Kerala architecture&quot;/&gt; From the limitations of the materials, a mixed mode of construction was evolved in Malayali architecture. The stone work was restricted to the plinth even in important buildings such as temples. Laterite was used for walls. The roof structure in timber was covered with palm leaf thatching for most buildings and rarely with tiles for palaces or temples.&lt;ref name=&quot;Kerala architecture&quot;/&gt; The ''Kerala murals'' are paintings with vegetable dyes on wet walls in subdued shades of brown. The indigenous adoption of the available raw materials and their transformation as enduring media for architectural expression thus became the dominant feature of the Malayali style of architecture.&lt;ref name=&quot;Kerala architecture&quot;/&gt;

====Nalukettu====
[[Image:Paliam naalukettu.jpg|thumb| A typical [[Nalukettu]] structure]]

[[Nalukettu]] is a quadrangular building constructed after following the Tachu Sastra(Science of Carpentry).  In past, Nalukettu was the house in which Malayalis lived.&lt;ref name=&quot;Nalukettu&quot;&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.malayalamresourcecentre.org/Mrc/culture/cultureofkerala/kerala.html|title=Nalukettu}}-Malayalam Resource Centre&lt;/ref&gt;  It was a typical house which was flanked by out-houses and utility structures.The large house-Nalukettu is constructed within a large compound.It was called Nalukettu because it consisted of four wings around a central [[courtyard]] called ''Nadumuttom''.&lt;ref name=&quot;Nalukettu&quot;/&gt;
The house has a [[Quadrangle (architecture)|quadrangle]] in the center.  The quadrangle is in every way the center of life in the house and very useful for the performance of rituals.The layout of these homes was simple, and catered to the dwelling of a large number of people, usually part of a [[tharavadu]]. Ettukettu (eight halled with two central courtyards) or Pathinarukettu (sixteen halled with four central courtyards) are the more elaborate forms of the same architecture.
An example of a Nalukettu structure is ''[[Mattancherry Palace]]''.&lt;ref name=&quot;Nalukettu&quot;/&gt;

===Performing Arts and Music===
&lt;!-- Deleted image removed: [[Image:Kerala-Art-Forms.png|thumb|250px|[[Mohiniaattam]], [[Kathakali]], [[Kutiyattam]] and [[Ottamthullal]] performers. {{pufc|Kerala-Art-Forms.png}}]] --&gt;Malayalis use two words to denote dance, which is ''attom'' and ''thullal''.&lt;ref name=&quot;Kerala dance forms&quot;&gt;{{cite news|url=http://books.google.co.in/books?id=waWQ8mAUrC8C&amp;pg=PA139&amp;dq=Kerala+dance#v=onepage&amp;q=Kerala%20dance&amp;f=false|title=Kerala dance forms}}&lt;/ref&gt; The art forms of Malayalis are classified into three types.They are (i)''Religious'' like [[Theyyam]], Bhagavatipattu etc., (ii)''Semi religious'' like Sanghakali, Krishnanattom etc., and (iii)''Secular'' like [[Kathakali]], [[Mohiniaattam]], Thullal etc.&lt;ref name=&quot;Kerala dance forms&quot;/&gt;''Kathakali'' and ''Mohiniaattam'' are the two [[Indian classical dance|classical dance]] forms from Kerala.&lt;ref name=&quot;Classical dance forms of India&quot;&gt;{{cite news|url=http://dances.indobase.com/classical-dances/index.html|title=Classical dance forms of India}}&lt;/ref&gt; Kathakali is actually a ''dance-drama''.Mohiniaattam is a very sensual and graceful dance form that is performed both solo and in a group by women.&lt;ref name=&quot;Classical dance forms of India&quot;/&gt;[[Kutiyattam]] is a traditional performing art form from Kerala, which is recognised by [[UNESCO]] and given the status ''Masterpieces of Oral and Intangible Heritage of Humanity''.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://books.google.co.in/books?id=lDhuAAAAMAAJ&amp;q=Koodiyattam+UNESCO&amp;dq=Koodiyattam+UNESCO|title=Koodiyattam}}&lt;/ref&gt;[[Ottamthullal]] is another performing art, which is also known as the ''poor man's Kathakali'', which was created by the poet [[Kunchan Nambiar]] as an alternative to ''[[Chakiarkooth]]'' (another performing art),which was open only for higher castes to see.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://books.google.co.in/books?id=L8bExoV6GL8C&amp;pg=PA70&amp;dq=Ottamthullal#v=onepage&amp;q=Ottamthullal&amp;f=false|title=Ottamthullal}}&lt;/ref&gt;[[Theyyam]] is a ritualistic art form of Malayalis, which is thought to predate [[hinduism]] and to have developed from folk dances performed in conjunction with harvest celebrations.[[Theyyam]] is performed as an offering to gods so as to get rid of poverty and illness.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://books.google.co.in/books?id=Fk8FQa2ZSFQC&amp;pg=PA928&amp;dq=Theyyam#v=onepage&amp;q=Theyyam&amp;f=false|title=Theyyam}}&lt;/ref&gt; Velakali is another ritualistic art form, mainly performed at temples in the festival time.[[Kolkali]] is a folk art in which dance performers move in a circle, striking small sticks and keeping rhythm with special steps. Many ancient Malayali family houses in Kerala have special snake shrines called ''Kavu''. [[Sarpam Thullal]] is usually performed in the courtyard of houses having snake shrines. This is a votive offering for family wealth and happiness.

[[File:Kannangat_bagavati.jpg|left|thumb|A [[Theyyam]] performance]]
Performing arts in Kerala is not limited to a single religion of the Malayali society. The Malayalam speaking Muslim community of Kerala, known as ''Mappila'' and the Christian community has their own unique performing art forms.[[Duff Muttu]], also known as ''Dubh Muttu/Aravanamuttu''&lt;ref name=&quot;Duffmuttu&quot;&gt;{{cite news|url=http://books.google.co.in/books?id=ZYfRBcLdTNYC&amp;pg=PA8&amp;dq=duffmuttu#v=onepage&amp;q=duffmuttu&amp;f=false|title=Duffmuttu}}&lt;/ref&gt; is a performing art form prevalent among the Muslim community.It is a group performance,staged as a social event during festivals and nuptial ceremonies.&lt;ref name=&quot;Duffmuttu&quot;/&gt;
[[Oppana]] is a popular form of social entertainment among the Muslim community.It is a form accompanied by clapping of hands, in which both men and women participate.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://books.google.co.in/books?id=zh6z0nuIjAgC&amp;pg=PA149&amp;dq=Oppana#v=onepage&amp;q=Oppana&amp;f=false|title=Oppana}}&lt;/ref&gt;
[[Margamkali]] is a performing art which is popular among the ''Syro-Malabar'' and ''Syro-Malankara'' Christians.It combines both devotion and entertainment, and was performed by women in groups.&lt;ref name=&quot;Christian art foms&quot;&gt;{{cite news|url=http://books.google.co.in/books?id=ZOlNv8MAXIEC&amp;pg=RA2-PA945&amp;dq=Margamkali#v=onepage&amp;q=Margamkali&amp;f=false|title=Christian art foms}}&lt;/ref&gt; Since 1980's women also have found groups.The dancers themselves sing the ''margamkali songs'' in unison call and response form.&lt;ref name=&quot;Christian art foms&quot;/&gt;''Parichamuttikali'' is another performing art which is popular among all sections of Christian community.This is an artistic adaptation of the martial art of Kerala, [[Kalaripayattu]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Christian art foms&quot;/&gt; ''[[Chavittu nadakom]]'' is a theatrical art form observed mainly by Kerala Latin Christians, dating back to second half of 16th century.&lt;ref name=&quot;Christian art foms&quot;/&gt;

However, many of these native art forms largely play to tourists or at youth festivals, and are not as popular among ordinary Keralites. Thus, more contemporary forms – including those heavily based on the use of often risqué and [[political correctness|politically incorrect]] [[mimicry]] and [[parody]] – have gained considerable mass appeal in recent years. Indeed, contemporary artists often use such modes to mock socioeconomic elites. In recent decades, [[Malayalam Cinema|Malayalam cinema]], yet another mode of widely popular artistic expression, have provided a distinct and indigenous Keralite alternative to both [[Bollywood]] and Hollywood.

Music formed a major part of early [[Malayalam literature]], which is believed to have started developing by 9th century [[Common Era|CE]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |title=Kerala Charithram |last=Sreedhara Menon|first=A.  |authorlink=A. Sreedhara Menon |publisher=D.C. Books |location=Kottayam, Kerala |isbn= |page=494 |url= }}&lt;/ref&gt; The significance of music in the [[culture of Kerala]] can be established just by the fact that in Malayalam language, musical poetry was developed long before [[prose]].[[Kerala]] is musically known for [[Sopanam]].  Sopanam is religious in nature, and developed through singing invocatory songs at the [[Kalam]] of [[Kali]], and later inside temples. Sopanam came to prominence in the wake of the increasing popularity of [[Works of Jayadeva|Jayadeva]]'s [[Gita Govinda]] or [[Ashtapadis]]. Sopana ''sangeetham'' (music), as the very name suggests, is sung by the side of the ''holy steps'' (sopanam) leading to the [[sanctum sanctorum]] of a [[shrine]]. It is sung, typically employing plain notes, to the accompaniment of the small, hourglass-shaped ethnic drum called ''[[idakka]]'', besides the chengila or the handy metallic gong to sound the beats. Sopanam is traditionally sung by men of the [[Marar]] and [[Pothuval]] community, who are [[Ambalavasi]] (semi-Brahmin) castes engaged to do it as their hereditary profession. Kerala is also home of [[Carnatic music]]. Legends like [[Swati Tirunal]], Shadkala Govinda Maarar,Sangitha Vidwan Gopala Pillai Bhagavathar, Chertala Gopalan Nair, [[M. D. Ramanathan]], [[T. V. Gopalakrishnan]], [[M.S.Gopalakrishnan]],K.J.Yesudas,L.Subramaniam  and [[T. N. Krishnan]] are Malayali musicians.Also among the younger generations with wide acclaim and promise is Child Prodigy Violinist [[L.Athira Krishna]] etc., who are looked upon as Maestros of tomorrow.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |title=Ritual Music and Hindu Rituals of Kerala |last=Rolf |first=Killius |year=2006 |publisher=BR Rhythms |location=New Delhi |isbn=81-88827-07-X |url= }}&lt;/ref&gt;
Kerala also has a significant presence of [[Hindustani music]] as well.&lt;ref name=&quot;Music&quot;&gt;{{Cite web |url=http://www.keral.com/movies/music.htm |title=Music |accessdate=2 January 2009 |publisher=Keral.com |archiveurl = http://web.archive.org/web/20080802081714/http://www.keral.com/movies/music.htm &lt;!-- Bot retrieved archive --&gt; |archivedate = 2 August 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt; The king of Travancore, Swathi Thirunal patronaged and contributed much to the Hindustani Music.
The [[pulluvar]] of Kerala are closely connected to the serpent worship. One group among these people consider the snake gods as their presiding deity and perform certain sacrifices and sing songs. This is called ''Pulluvan Pattu''.The song conducted by the pulluvar in serpent temples and snake groves is called Sarppapaattu, Naagam Paattu, Sarpam Thullal, Sarppolsavam, Paambum Thullal or Paambum Kalam.
[[Mappila Songs|Mappila Paattukal]] or ''Mappila Songs'' are folklore Muslim devotional songs in the Malayalam language. Mappila songs are composed in colloquial Malayalam and are sung in a distinctive tune. They are composed in a mixture of Malayalam and [[Arabic language|Arabic]].

[[Film music]], which refers to [[playback singing]] in the context of [[Music of India|Indian music]], forms the most important canon of popular music in India. Film music of Kerala in particular is the most popular form of music in the state.&lt;ref name=&quot;Music&quot;/&gt; Before [[Malayalam cinema]] and Malayalam film music developed, the [[Keralite]]s eagerly followed [[Tamil language|Tamil]] and [[Hindi]] film songs and that habit has stayed with them till now.

===Vallam Kali===

[[Vallam Kali]], is the race of country made boats. It is mainly conducted during the season of the harvest festival Onam in Autumn. Vallam Kali include races of many kinds of traditional boats of Kerala. The race of [[Chundan Vallam]] (snake boat) is the major item. Hence Vallam Kali is also known in English as Snake Boat Race and a major tourist attraction. Other types of boats which do participate in various events in the race are ''Churulan Vallam'', ''Iruttukuthy Vallam'', ''Odi Vallam'', ''Veppu Vallam (Vaipu Vallam)'', ''Vadakkanody Vallam'', and ''Kochu Vallam''. [[Nehru Trophy Boat Race]] is one the famous Vallam Kali held in [[Punnamada Lake]] in [[Alappuzha district]] of Kerala. [[Champakulam Moolam Boat Race]] is the oldest and most popular Vallam Kali in Kerala. The race is held on [[Pamba River|river Pamba]] on the moolam day (according to the [[Malayalam calendar|Malayalam Era]]) of the Malayalam month Midhunam, the day of the installation of the deity at the [[Ambalappuzha]] Sree Krishna Temple. The [[Aranmula Boat Race]] takes place at [[Aranmula]], near a temple dedicated to [[Krishna|Lord Krishna]] and [[Arjuna]]. Thousands of people gather on the banks of the river Pamba to watch the snake boat races. Nearly 30 snake boats or chundan vallams participate in the festival. [[Payippadu Vallam Kali|Payippad Jalotsavam]] is a three day water festival. Its conducted in Payippad Lake which is 35&amp;nbsp;km from Alappuzha district of Kerala state. There is a close relation between this Payippad boat race and Subramanya Swamy Temple in [[Haripad]]. [[Indira Gandhi Boat Race]] is a boat race festival celebrated in the last week of December in the backwaters of [[Kochi, India|Kochi]], a city in Kerala. This boat race is one of the most popular Vallam Kali in Kerala. This festival is conducted to promote [[Tourism in Kerala|Kerala tourism]].

===Festivals===
Malayalis celebrate a variety of festivals. Other than the two given below Malayalis also celebrate Christmas and [[Eid al-Adha|Bakrid]].

====Onam====
{{Main|Onam}}
[[Image:Thiruvathira Kali During Onam.jpg|thumb|''Thiruvathira kali'']]
Onam is an annual harvest festival, celebrated mainly in Kerala, although celebrations also occur among the diaspora. It is the foremost festival among the cultural repertoire of Malayalis, and falls during the month of Chingam (August–September as per the [[Gregorian calendar]]), the first month of the Malayalam calendar and lasts for ten days from the Star Atham in Chingam. Though it is essentially a harvest festival of Malayalis, mythologically it is linked to Malayali-Hindu folktales. Like many other religious festivals in India, Onam is celebrated by people across all castes and faiths. Onam has been part of Malayali psyche for centuries. There are records of Onam being celebrated during the Sangam Age. The earliest record of Onam is found during time of Kulasekhara Perumals around AD 800, soon after the Kalabhra Interregnum of Kerala History. Until the eighth century the political history is mostly unknown and is usually known as the Kalabhra Interregnum. Kalabhras were supposed to have been ruling Kerala until at least the sixth century. Kalabhras probably refers to Keralaputras. They are believed to be people of Mayavi.

Onam has two specific significance.  First it is the communal memory and celebration of past history as ennunciated in the Mahabali Legend. A story of how paradise was lost. Second it is the celebration of the harvest tied with the memory of the golden age of prosperity. It is believed that during those days the whole of Chingam was celebrated as Onam season. After the rain drenched month of Karkidakam with its privations, Chingam is a welcome month for people in the state of Kerala. The festival is the harbinger of spring – signalling the start of the harvest season. Onam epitomizes the newfound vigour and enthusiasm of the season, and is celebrated with traditional fervour with visit to temples, family get-togethers, gifting each other clothes called Onakkodi and lots of merry making.
Thiruvathira is in the malayalam month Dhanu (Dec–Jan). it is considering as the bithday of Lord Shiva.

====Vishu====
{{Main|Vishu}}
[[Image:Vishu kani.jpg|thumb|[[Vishu#Vishukani or Kanikanal|Vishukkani]]]]
Vishu is a festival celebrated by Malayalis around the first day in the Malayalam month of Medam (April – May). This occasion signifies the Sun's transit to the zodiac Mesha (Mesha Raasi) as per Indian astrological calculations. Vishu is also considered as the Malayalam New Year day and thus the importance of this day to all Malayalis regardless of their religion or sect. Similarly the day is celebrated in almost all places in India by the Hindus albeit by different names. In [[Assam]] this day is called Bihu, in [[Punjab (India)|Punjab]] Baisakhi and in [[Tamil Nadu]] Puthandu. The word &quot;Vishu&quot; in Sanskrit means &quot;equal&quot;. Therefore Vishu is more probably denoting one of the equinox days.

The festival is marked with offerings to the divine called Vishukkani. The offerings consist of a ritual arrangement in the puja room of auspicious articles like raw rice, fresh linen, golden cucumber, betel leaves, arecanut, metal mirror, the yellow flowers konna (Cassia fistula), and a holy text and coins, in a bell metal vessel called uruli. A lighted bell metal lamp called nilavilakku is also placed alongside. This arrangement is completed the previous night. On the day of Vishu, the custom is to wake up at dawn and go to the puja room with the eyes closed so that the Vishukkani is the first thing one sees. Since the occasion marks the beginning of Malayalam New Year, it is also considered auspicious to read verses from Hindu Holy book Ramayanam after seeing the Vishukkani. It is also believed by some that the page of the Ramayanam to which you open up will have a bearing on your life in the coming year. Devotees also throng the well-known temples like Sabarimala Ayyappan Teample, Guruvayur Sree Krishna temple to have a &quot;Vishukkani Kazhcha&quot; on the early hours of &quot;Vishu&quot; day.

===Cuisine===
{{Main|Cuisine of Kerala}}

The cuisine of Malayalis are linked in all its richness to the history, geography and culture of the land. Spices form an important ingredient in almost all curries. Malayali cuisine is not homogeneous and regional variations are visible throughout. Kerala is known for its traditional sadhyas, a vegetarian meal served with boiled rice and a host of side-dishes. The sadhya is complemented by payasam, a sweet milk dessert native to Kerala. The sadhya is, as per custom, served on a banana leaf. Traditional dishes include sambar, aviyal, kaalan, theeyal, thoran, injipully, pulisherry, appam, kappa (tapioca), puttu (steamed rice powder), and puzhukku. [[Coconut]] is an essential ingredient in most of the food items and is liberally used.

Puttu is a culinary specialty in Kerala. It is a steamed rice cake which is a favourite breakfast of most Malayalis. It is served with either brown chickpeas cooked in a spicy gravy, papadams and boiled small green lentils, or tiny ripe yellow Kerala plantains. In the highlands there is also a variety of puttu served with paani (the boiled-down syrup from [[Palm wine|sweet palm toddy]]) and sweet boiled bananas. to steam the puttu, there is a special utensil called &quot;Puttu Kutti&quot;. It consists of two sections. The lower bulkier portion is where the water for steaming is stored. The upper detachable leaner portion which is separated from lower portion with peforated lids so as to allow the steam to pass through and bake the rice powder which has been filled. The upper portion of the leaner section is covered with a peforated cup shaped lid once it is filled with rice powder.

Appam is a pancake made of fermented batter. The batter is made of rice flour and fermented using either yeast or toddy, the local spirit. It is fried using a special frying pan called appa-chatti and is served with egg curry, chicken curry, mutton stew, vegetable curry and chick pea curry.

===Martial arts===
{{See also|Kalaripayattu}}
[[Image:Kadhara.jpg|right|thumb|[[Kalaripayattu]] in which both opponents are armed with [[Chuttuval]] and [[Shield|Paricha]]]]
Malayalis have their own lethal form of martial arts called [[Kalaripayattu]]. This type of martial arts was used as defensive mechanism against intruders . In ancient times, disputes between ''(naaduvazhis or Vazhunors)nobles'' were also settled by the outcome of a Kalaripayattu tournament. This ancient martial art is claimed as ''the mother of all martial arts'' – even the Chinese [[Shaolin Kung Fu|Shaolin]] chuan from the famous Shaolin temple traces its ancestry to [[Bodhidharma]], an Indian [[Buddhist]] monk who was a Kalaripayattu expert.&lt;ref name=&quot;discoverychannelasia.com&quot;&gt;[http://www.yourdiscovery.com/martialarts/southasia/kalaripayatta/index.shtml]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Bodhidharma bought Kalari to China ''[http://books.google.co.in/books?id=YSytrrJ8hnsC&amp;pg=PR18&amp;dq=kalaripayattu+bodhidharma&amp;hl=en&amp;ei=vdOSTprGLsTOrQeB7qCEAQ&amp;sa=X&amp;oi=book_result&amp;ct=result&amp;resnum=9&amp;ved=0CFYQ6AEwCA#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false]''&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Bodhidharma and Kalari ''[http://books.google.co.in/books?id=3FF2h2hs_ZoC&amp;pg=PA256&amp;dq=bodhidharma+Kalari&amp;hl=en&amp;ei=mtaSTuKxIoTYrQfGv8TaAw&amp;sa=X&amp;oi=book_result&amp;ct=result&amp;resnum=1&amp;ved=0CC0Q6AEwAA#v=onepage&amp;q=bodhidharma%20Kalari&amp;f=false]''&lt;/ref&gt; The word &quot;[[kalari]]&quot; can be traced to ancient [[Sangam literature]].&lt;ref&gt;Suresh, P. R. (2005). ''[http://www.palmlandtours.net/kerala/tours/kalari/kalaripayatte/kalari.htm Kalari Payatte – The martial art of Kerala.]''&lt;/ref&gt; The martial tradition of Kalaripayattu is also dated to ancient [[Dravidian people|Dravidian]] traditions.&lt;ref&gt;[http://books.google.com/books?vid=ISBN1843311682&amp;id=3gwJrF7yvDMC&amp;pg=RA1-PA22&amp;lpg=RA1-PA22&amp;vq=dhanur+veda&amp;dq=kalari++Sangam+literature&amp;sig=kmoIM25C34HbOWUhlZemrVUAtVs Subaltern Sports: Politics and Sports in South Asia By James H. Mills. Published 2005, Anthem Press. Subject: Archaeology /Anthropology. ISBN 1-84331-167-4]&lt;/ref&gt; [[Phillip Zarrilli]], a professor at the University of Exeter and one of the few Western authorities on kalaripayattu, estimates that kalarippayattu dates back to at least the 12th century CE.&lt;ref name=Zarrilli1&gt;Zarrilli, Phillip B. [http://www.spa.ex.ac.uk/drama/staff/kalari/power.html A South Indian Martial Art and the Yoga and Ayurvedic Paradigms.] [[University of Wisconsin–Madison]].&lt;/ref&gt; The historian Elamkulam Kunjan Pillai attributes the birth of Kalaripayattu to an extended period of warfare between the [[Chera dynasty|Cheras]] and the [[Cholas]] in the 11th century CE.&lt;ref name=&quot;Zarrilli1&quot;/&gt; What eventually crystallized into this style is thought to have been a product of existing South Indian styles of combat, combined with techniques brought by migration from the north along the western coast.&lt;ref name=&quot;Zarrilli1&quot;/&gt; What eventually crystallized as kalarippayattu combined indigenous [[Dravidian people|Dravidian]] techniques with the martial practices and ethos brought by brahman migrations from Saurastra and Konkan down the west Indian coast into Karnataka and eventually Kerala. [[Discovery channel]] notes that Kalaripayattu may be one of the oldest martial arts in existence.&lt;ref name=&quot;discoverychannelasia.com&quot;/&gt; The oldest western reference to Kalaripayattu is a 16th century travelogue of [[Duarte Barbosa]], a Portuguese explorer. The Southern style, which places more emphasis on open hand combat was mostly practiced in the southern regions of Kerala.&lt;ref&gt;Phillip B. Zarrilli, When the Body Becomes All Eyes&lt;/ref&gt;

==Keralites==
[[List of famous Keralites]]

==See also==
* [[Non Resident Keralites Affairs]]
* [[World Malayalee Council]]
{{Portal|Kerala}}
{{Topics related to Kerala}}

==References==
{{Reflist|2}}

{{Kerala topics}}

{| align=&quot;center&quot; style=&quot;text-align:left&quot;
| [[Image:Wikinews-logo.png|35px|&lt;nowiki&gt;&lt;/nowiki&gt;]]
| '''[[n:Kerala|Kerala on Wikinews]]'''&lt;br /&gt; News
| [[Image:Wikiquote-logo.svg|35px|&lt;nowiki&gt;&lt;/nowiki&gt;]]
| '''[[q:Kerala|Kerala on Wikiquote]]'''&lt;br /&gt; Quotes
| [[Image:Commons-logo.svg|35px|&lt;nowiki&gt;&lt;/nowiki&gt;]]
| '''[[commons:Category:Kerala|Kerala on Commons]]'''&lt;br /&gt; Images
| [[Image:Wikisource-logo.png|35px|&lt;nowiki&gt;&lt;/nowiki&gt;]]
| '''[[s:Category:Kerala|Kerala on Wikisource]]'''&lt;br /&gt; Texts
|}

==External links==
{{commons category|Malayali people}}
{{Wiktionary|Malayali}}
*[http://www.kerala.gov.in  Official site of Kerala Government]
*[http://www.malayalamresourcecentre.org  Malayalam Resource Centre]

{| align=&quot;center&quot; style=&quot;text-align:left&quot;
|{{commons|Kerala}}
|{{Wikiquote}}
|}

{| align=&quot;center&quot; style=&quot;text-align:left&quot;
|{{InterWiki|code=ml}}
||}

[[Category:Kerala society]]
[[Category:Malayali people|*]]
[[Category:Dravidian peoples]]

&lt;!--Other languages--&gt;

[[ca:Malayalikal]]
[[hr:Malayali]]
[[kk:Малаялилер]]
[[ml:മലയാളി]]
[[ms:Malayalee]]
[[pl:Keralczycy]]
[[ru:Малаяли]]
[[sh:Malajali]]
[[sv:Malayalamfolket]]
[[ta:மலையாளிகள்]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
