<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="1261419" ns="0" title="John Bradley (Navy)"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Other persons|John Bradley}}
{{Refimprove|date=April 2008}}
{{Infobox military person
|name= John Bradley
|birth_date= {{birth date|mf=yes|1923|07|10}}
|death_date= {{death date and age|mf=yes|1994|01|11|1923|07|10}}
|birth_place= [[Antigo, Wisconsin]]
|death_place= [[Antigo, Wisconsin]]
|placeofburial= [[Queen of Peace Catholic Cemetery]]
|placeofburial_label= Place of burial
|image= [[File:John Bradley.jpg|200px]]
|caption= John Bradley stands next to a War Bond drive poster depicting the flag raising.
|nickname= &quot;Jack,&quot; &quot;Doc&quot;
|allegiance= {{flagicon|United States}} [[United States|United States of America]]
|branch= [[United States Navy]]
|serviceyears= 1942–1945
|rank= [[Image:PHM2cl small.jpg‎|25px]] [[Pharmacist's Mate Second Class]]
|commands= 
|unit= [[2nd Battalion, 28th Marines]]
|battles= [[World War II]]
*[[Battle of Iwo Jima]]
|awards= [[Navy Cross]]&lt;br/&gt;[[Purple Heart]]
|laterwork=
}}
'''John Henry &quot;Jack&quot; &quot;Doc&quot; Bradley''' (July 10, 1923 – January 11, 1994) was a [[United States Navy]] [[corpsman]] during [[World War II]], and one of the six men who took part in [[raising the Flag on Iwo Jima]].  Bradley was already on the summit of [[Mount Suribachi]] with his platoon, when Sergeant [[Michael Strank]], Corporal [[Harlon Block]], PFC [[Ira Hayes]], PFC [[Rene Gagnon]] and PFC [[Franklin Sousley]], who had a larger flag on orders to place it so that it could be seen from great distance, asked him to lend them a hand in raising the flag attached to a heavy length of pipe. He was the last surviving of the six men.

==Early years==
Born John Henry Bradley in [[Antigo, Wisconsin]] to James (&quot;Cabbage&quot;) and Kathryn Bradley, he was the second of five children. He grew up in [[Appleton, Wisconsin]], and reportedly had an interest in entering the [[funeral]] business from an early age.

==World War II==
When he was 19, his father suggested he enlist in the Navy so he could avoid ground combat; however, the Navy chose him to become a Pharmacist's Mate and he was eventually assigned to the [[United States Marine Corps]]. As a Hospital Corpsman assigned to the Marines, he took part in the assault on [[Battle of Iwo Jima|Iwo Jima]], one of the most bitterly fought battles of the [[Pacific War]]'s [[Leapfrogging (strategy)|island-hopping]] campaign.

In March 1943, Bradley began his Hospital Corpsman training and was initially stationed at the U.S. Naval Hospital in [[Oakland, California|Oakland]]. He was then assigned to the [[2nd Battalion, 28th Marines]], of the [[5th Marine Division]], which was being formed at [[Marine Corps Base Camp Pendleton|Camp Pendleton]], [[California]].

Before participating in the famous flag-raising at [[Mt. Suribachi]] on Iwo Jima, John Bradley earned the [[Navy Cross]] for rushing to a wounded man's aid under heavy Japanese fire. A few days later, he received several [[Shrapnel shell|shrapnel]] wounds in his legs, and was evacuated from the combat zone to a hospital in [[Hawaii]].

==Awards==
Pharmacist's Mate Second Class Bradley was awarded the following decorations and awards:
[[File:FofBradley.JPG|left|thumb| PM2 Bradley's awards and decorations at the time of his discharge from the Navy.]]

*[[Navy Cross]]
*[[Purple Heart]]
*[[Presidential Unit Citation (United States)|Presidential Unit Citation]] with one star (for Iwo Jima)
*[[American Campaign Medal]]
*[[Asiatic-Pacific Campaign Medal]] with one battle star (for Iwo Jima), and;
*[[World War II Victory Medal]]

[[File:Raising the Flag outline.png|thumb|A photo to show all six men]]

===Navy Cross citation===
''&quot;For extraordinary heroism in action against the enemy at Iwo Jima on Feb. 21, 1945 as a hospital corpsman attached to a Marine Rifle platoon. During a furious assault by his company upon a strongly defended enemy zone at the base of Mt. Suribachi, Bradley observed a Marine infantryman fall wounded in an open area under a pounding barrage by mortars, interlaced with a merciless crossfire from Machine guns. 

''With complete disregard for his own safety, he ran through the intense fire to the side of the fallen Marine, examined his wounds and ascertained that an immediate administration of plasma was necessary to save the man's life. Unwilling to subject any of his comrades to the danger to which he had so valiantly exposed himself, he signaled would-be assistants to remain where they were. Placing himself in a position to shield the wounded man, he tied a plasma unit to a rifle planted upright in the sand and continued his life saving mission. 

''The Marine's wounds bandaged and the condition of shock relieved by plasma, Bradley pulled the man thirty yards through intense enemy fire to a position of safety. His indomitable spirit, dauntless initiative, and heroic devotion to duty were an inspiration to those with who he served and were in keeping with the highest tradition of the United States Naval Service.&quot;''''''

Bradley was modest about his achievement. His family did not learn about the award until after his death.

==Post-war life==
Sergeant [[Mike Strank]], Corporal [[Harlon Block]], and PFC [[Franklin Sousley]] were all [[killed in action]] later in the battle. Only John Bradley, Ira Hayes and Rene Gagnon survived the battle, and they were brought back to the United States to tour the country for the seventh [[war bond]] drive. The bond drive helped lift morale at home.

===Marriage and family life===
Following his appearances at the last bond tour, John Bradley married his childhood sweetheart, Betty Van Gorp, settled down in Antigo, had eight children, and was active in numerous civic clubs. He rarely took part in ceremonies celebrating the flag raising, and by the 1960s avoided them altogether. He fulfilled his life-long dream by buying and managing his own funeral parlor, but was tormented by memories of the war. Betty says he wept in his sleep for the first four years of their marriage and kept a large knife in a dresser drawer for &quot;protection&quot;. He also had many flashbacks of his best friend Iggy, [[Ralph Ignatowski]], who was captured and tortured by Japanese soldiers. Bradley never could forgive himself for not being there to try and save his friend's life.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book | author = James Bradley (John Bradley's son) &amp; Ron Powers | title = Flags of Our Fathers | publisher = Bantam | year = 2000 | isbn = 0-553-11133-7}}&lt;/ref&gt;
[[File:John Bradley Memorial on Mt Suribachi.jpg|thumb|right|Memorial plaque placed by his family on the spot of the flag raising]]

===Post-raising views===
He rarely spoke of the raising of the flag, stating once that he &quot;just happened to be there&quot;. His son [[James Bradley (author)|James Bradley]] (who wrote a book about the flag-raisers in 2000 titled ''[[Flags of Our Fathers]]'') speculated that his father's determined silence and discomfort on the subject of his role in the [[Battle of Iwo Jima]] was largely due to memories of John's best friend, [[Ralph Ignatowski|Ralph &quot;Iggy&quot; Ignatowski]]. In his own words, and only once, he briefly told his son what happened with &quot;Iggy&quot;.  From the book ''Flags of Our Fathers'':

{{quote|I have tried so hard to block this out. To forget it. We could choose a buddy to go in with. My buddy was a guy from Milwaukee. We were pinned down in one area. Someone elsewhere fell injured and I ran to help out, and when I came back my buddy was gone. I couldn’t figure out where he was. I could see all around, but he wasn’t there. And nobody knew where he was.

A few days later someone yelled that they’d found him. They called me over because I was a corpsman. The Japanese had pulled him underground and tortured him. His fingernails... his tongue... It was terrible. I’ve tried hard to forget all this.&quot;|John Bradley}}

According to James Bradley, as recounted in ''Flags of our Fathers'', official reports revealed Ignatowski was captured, dragged into a tunnel by Japanese soldiers during the battle, and was later found with his eyes, ears, fingernails, and tongue removed, his teeth smashed, the back of his head caved in, multiple bayonet wounds to the abdomen, his arms broken, and his severed genitalia stuffed into his mouth.  John Bradley's recollections of discovering and taking care of Ignatowski's remains haunted him until his death, and he suffered for many years from [[Post-traumatic stress disorder]].

The Battalion Aid Station for the United States Marine Corps Officer Candidates School at Marine Corps Base (MCB) Quantico is named in honor of John Bradley.

===Death===
John Bradley had a [[heart attack]], but died of a [[stroke]] at 2:12 am in an Antigo hospital on January 11, 1994, at the age of 70, the last of the six men who raised the second flag to die. He said more than once to his children that the only real heroes on Iwo Jima were those that did not survive. John Bradley's family had no idea he had received the [[Navy Cross]] until after his death. He is buried in Queen of Peace Cemetery, [[Antigo, Wisconsin]].&lt;ref&gt;''Flags of Our Fathers'', by [[James Bradley]], page 197.&lt;/ref&gt;

==Portrayal in film==
*Bradley portrayed himself in the 1949 [[war film]], ''[[Sands of Iwo Jima]]''. It starred [[John Wayne]]. The other two surviving flag-raisers also participated, Ira Hayes and Rene Gagnon.
*Bradley was played by [[Forrest Compton]] in the 1961 film ''[[The Outsider (1961 film)|The Outsider]]''.
*[[Ryan Phillippe]] portrayed him in the 2006 film ''[[Flags of Our Fathers (film)|Flags of Our Fathers]]''.

==See also==
{{Portal box|United States Navy|World War II}}

*[[Marine Corps War Memorial]] (known as the Iwo Jima Memorial)
*[[United States Navy Hospital Corpsman]]
*[[Meliton Kantaria]] - Soviet flag raiser over the [[Reichstag (building)|Reichstag]] in [[Berlin]], 1945
*[[M.A. Yegorov|Mikhail Yegorov]] - Soviet flag raiser over the [[Reichstag (building)|Reichstag]] in [[Berlin]], 1945
*[http://www.imdb.com/title/tt0418689/    Flags of Our Fathers] - Movie

==References==
{{Reflist}}

==External links==
{{commons category|John Bradley (Navy)|John Bradley}}
*[http://www.history.navy.mil/faqs/faq87-3l.htm John Bradley's account of the Battle of Iwo Jima from the US Navy's oral history program]
*{{cite book | author = James Bradley (John Bradley's son) &amp; Ron Powers | title = Flags of Our Fathers | publisher = Bantam | year = 2006 | isbn = 0-553-11133-7}} A history of the flagraisers
*[http://www.imdb.com/title/tt0418689/    Flags of Our Fathers] - Movie

{{Persondata &lt;!-- Metadata: see [[Wikipedia:Persondata]]. --&gt;
| NAME              =Bradley, John
| ALTERNATIVE NAMES =
| SHORT DESCRIPTION =Navy corpsman in World War Two, flagraiser at Iwo Jima
| DATE OF BIRTH     =July 10, 1923
| PLACE OF BIRTH    =[[Antigo, Wisconsin]]
| DATE OF DEATH     =January 11, 1994
| PLACE OF DEATH    =[[Antigo, Wisconsin]]
}}
{{DEFAULTSORT:Bradley, John}}
[[Category:Battle of Iwo Jima]]
[[Category:1923 births]]
[[Category:1994 deaths]]
[[Category:American military personnel of World War II]]
[[Category:Recipients of the Navy Cross]]
[[Category:People from Langlade County, Wisconsin]]
[[Category:Recipients of the Purple Heart medal]]
[[Category:United States Navy sailors]]
[[Category:American military personnel from Wisconsin]]

[[es:John Bradley (Iwo Jima)]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
