<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="12630306" ns="0" title="Vadamarachchi Operation"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Infobox Military Conflict
| conflict    = Vadamarachchi Operation
| partof      = the [[Sri Lankan civil war]], [[Eelam War I]]
| image       =
| caption     =
| date        = May 26, 1987  - June 1987
| place       = [[Jaffna]], [[Sri Lanka]]
| coordinates =
| map_type    =
| latitude    =
| longitude   =
| map_size    =
| map_caption =
| territory   =
| result      = Partial Sri Lankan Army victory
| status      =
| combatant1  = [[Image:Coat of arms of Sri Lanka.svg|18px]] [[Military of Sri Lanka]]
| combatant2  = [[Liberation Tigers of Tamil Eelam]]
| combatant3  =
| commander1  = [[Lieutenant General|Lt Gen]] (later [[General|Gen]]) [[Nalin Seneviratne]],&lt;br&gt; [[Brigadier|Brig]] (later [[Lieutenant General|Lt Gen]]) [[Denzil Kobbekaduwa]],&lt;br&gt; [[Colonel|Col]] (later [[Major General|Maj Gen]]) [[Vijaya Wimalaratne]],&lt;br&gt;[[Major|Maj]] (later [[Colonel, Secy Def|Col, Secy Def]]) [[Gotabaya Rajapakse]],&lt;br&gt;[[Major|Maj]] (later [[Colonel|Col]]) [[Lucky Rajasinghe]]
| commander2  = Velupillai Pirabakaran
| commander3  =
| strength1   = 8,000
| strength2   = Unknown
| strength3   =
| casualties1 = 689 killed&lt;ref name=&quot;Welcome to UTHR, Sri Lanka&quot;&gt;[http://www.uthr.org/BP/volume1/Chapter7.htm Welcome to UTHR, Sri Lanka&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;
| casualties2 = 631 killed&lt;ref name=&quot;Welcome to UTHR, Sri Lanka&quot;/&gt;
| casualties3 =
| notes       =
}}
{{Campaignbox Eelam War I}}

&lt;!--  Commented out: [[Image:Vadamarachchi Operation Medal.gif|thumb|right|250px|Vadamarachchi Operation Medal]] --&gt;
The '''Operation Liberation''' or '''Vadamarachchi Operation''', the military offensive carried out by the [[Military of Sri Lanka|Sri Lankan military]] during May to June 1987, to re-gain the territory of [[Vadamarachi|Vadamarachchi]] in [[Jaffna peninsula]] from the [[LTTE]] control. This military offensive marked in [[Sri Lanka]]n military history as first ever engaged in [[conventional warfare]] in Sri Lankan soil after the British colonial rule.

==The battle==
[[Brigadier]] [[Denzil Kobbekaduwa]] and [[Colonel]] [[Vijaya Wimalaratne]] are the two key military personnel who committed themselves to gain the victory for the government troops. Former [[President of Sri Lanka|Sri Lankan President]] [[Junius Richard Jayewardene]] and minister of National Security [[Lalith Athulathmudali]] given the political leadership for the operation until the government of [[India]] violated the Sri Lankan air space using air force to [[Air Drop|drop]] food over Jaffna ([[Operation Poomalai]]) on June 4, 1987, which forced to accept [[Indo-Sri Lankan Accord]].

The offensive started on May 26, 1987, under the leadership of the two commanders with 8,000 troops from several battalions from [[Gemunu Watch]] (Under the Command of Lt. Colonel Vipul Botheju and Lt. Colonel Wasantha Perera), [[Gajaba Regiment]] (under the Command of Lt. Colonel Sathis Jayasundara and Major Gotabaya Rajapakse) and [[Sri Lanka Light Infantry]] (Under Lt. Colonel Naradha Wickramarathne), supported by the [[Sri Lanka Air Force]]. The difficulty for the troops to out from Thondamanaru area because LTTE forces blew up the Thondamanaru bridge to delay the troops reaching [[Valvettithurai]], the native place of LTTE leader [[V. Prabhakaran]]. Eastern side of Thondamanaru was heavliy mined by the LTTE and clearing of the mines and booby traps were left to a field engineer Squadron of the [[Sri Lanka Engineers]] commanded by Major Lucky Rajasinghe. First day of the battle belong to the heroics of field engineer squadron which suffered 42 deaths in a span of 4 hours and its squadren commander Lucky Rajasinghe, yet broke through the mine field under the intensive fire from the LTTE bunkers, with the support of the troops from the 1 Gajaba Regiment Commanded by Major Gotabaya Rajapakse. On May 28 troops managed to capture Udupiddy and Valvettithurai and also another military column (Commandos, under the command of Major Sarath Handapangoda) captured Nelliady and advanced towards [[Point Pedro]] without giving any possibility to re-grouping of the LTTE units. On first week of June troops managed gain control over entire zone and captured large amount of arms left by LTTE. The military intelligence disclosed the LTTE leader Prabakaran along with [[Sea Tiger]] leader [[Colonel Soosai]] narrowly escaped from advancing troops.

Though the second stage of this operation was launched on June 3, 1987, to capture the city of [[Jaffna]], the military abandoned it. Indian Aircraft escorted by fighter aircraft infiltrated Sri Lankan air space and dropped humanitarian relief supplies in the Jaffna area on June 4 as people of Jaffna mostly ethnic Tamils were without food and other provisions. No weapons were dropped and there is no record of dropping food or other provisions to Tamil Tigers as opposed to people. Operation Poomalai &lt;ref&gt;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Operation_Poomalai&lt;/ref&gt; as it was known was only a relief operation. It had no bearing in stopping the war. After six weeks later Indian Forces landed in Sri Lanka on July 29 with the signing of Indo-Lanka Accord&lt;ref&gt;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Indo-Sri-Lankan_accord&lt;/ref&gt;.

==Trivia==
* Both [[Brigadier]] (later [[Lieutenant General]]) [[Denzil Kobbekaduwa]] and [[Colonel]] (later [[Major General]]) [[Vijaya Wimalaratne]] were killed on August 8, 1992, when they were making preparations for an operation to capture the [[Jaffna Peninsula]].
* The current [[Permanent Secretary]] to the Ministry of Defence, Lt. Col. (Ret) [[Gotabaya Rajapaksa]], brother of the President [[Mahinda Rajapaksa]], participated the military offensive, then as a [[Major]].

==See also==
* [[List of Sri Lankan Civil War battles]]

==References==
{{Reflist}}

==References==
&lt;references/&gt;
* Dissanayaka, T.D.S.A.: ''War or Peace in Sri Lanka, Volume II''. Swastika (Pvt.) Ltd., Colombo 1998.
* Dixit, J.N.: ''Assignment Colombo'', ISBN 81-220-0499-7. (Dixit was the Indian High Commissioner during the 1980s negotiations that led to the IPKF presence.)
* Hoole, R., Somasundaram, D., Sritharan K., and Thiranagama, R. ''The Broken Palmyra - The Tamil Crisis in Sri Lanka: An Inside Account''. The Sri Lanka Studies Institute, Claremont 1990. (Also available online [http://www.uthr.org/BP/Content.htm].)
* Narayan Swamy, M. R.: ''Tigers of Lanka: from Boys to Guerrillas''. Konark Publishers; 3rd ed. 2002, ISBN 81-220-0631-0.
* ''War and Peace in Sri Lanka: With a Post-Accord Report From Jaffna''. ISBN 9552600014/ISBN 978-9552600012, Institute of Fundamental Studies, Sri Lanka; 1 edition (October 1, 1987), By [[Rohan Gunaratna]].
* ''Indian intervention in Sri Lanka: The role of India's intelligence agencies''. ISBN 9559519905/ISBN 978-9559519904, South Asian Network on Conflict Research (1993), By [[Rohan Gunaratna]].

{{Sri Lankan Civil War}}

==External links==
;Official websites
*[http://www.airforce.lk/hist/hist1/h3c2p2.htm The role of the air force during Operation Liberation]
*[http://www.defence.lk/ Ministry of Defence, Sri Lanka]
*[http://www.peaceinsrilanka.org/ Government of Sri Lanka Peace Secretariat]
*[http://www.ltteps.org/ LTTE Peace Secretariat]
*[http://www.slmm.lk/ Sri Lanka Monitoring Mission]
;Independent reports and texts
* [http://www.c-r.org/our-work/accord/sri-lanka/key-texts.php Texts of key agreements in the peace process and an analysis of the process by Conciliation Resources]
* [http://www.asiafoundation.org/Locations/srilanka_publications.html Report on the Sri Lankan peace process by Asiafoundation]
* [http://www.hweb.org.uk/content/view/27/4/ hWeb - Sri Lanka’s recent history of ethnic conflict and political crisis originates from its colonial legacy]

{{coord missing|Sri Lanka}}

[[Category:Eelam War I]]
[[Category:Battles of the Sri Lankan Civil War]]
[[Category:Battles involving Sri Lanka]]
[[Category:Military history of Sri Lanka]]
[[Category:Tamil Eelam]]
[[Category:1987 in Sri Lanka]]
[[Category:1987 in Asia]]
[[Category:20th-century conflicts]]

[[de:Bürgerkrieg in Sri Lanka]]
[[es:Guerra Civil de Sri Lanka]]
[[nl:Conflict in Sri Lanka]]
[[no:Etnisk konflikt i Sri Lanka]]
[[fi:Sri Lankan sisällissota]]
[[sv:Inbördeskriget i Sri Lanka]]
[[ta:வடமராட்சி ஒப்பரேசன் லிபரேசன்]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
