<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="12683099" ns="0" title="Katherine Mayfair"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Infobox soap character
| bgcolor         = #C41E3A
| name             = Katherine Mayfair
| series           = [[Desperate Housewives]]
| image            = [[File:KatherineMayfair2.jpg|200px]]
| portrayer        = [[Dana Delany]]
| caption          = [[Dana Delany]] as Katherine Mayfair
| creator          = [[Marc Cherry]]
| gender           = 
| first            = &quot;[[Now You Know (Desperate Housewives)|Now You Know]]&quot;&lt;br&gt;4x01, September 30, 2007
| last             = 
| cause            = 
| occupation       = '''Former''' &lt;br /&gt;  President of the Homeowners Association (2007-2015)&lt;br /&gt;  Housewife&lt;br /&gt;  [[Caterer]]
| residence        = [[Wisteria Lane#No. 4356|4356 Wisteria Lane]] in [[Fairview (Desperate Housewives)|Fairview, Eagle State]] - year 1994 to 1995 and season 4th to late 6th&lt;br /&gt;[[Chicago]] - year 1995 to 2007&lt;br&gt; [[Paris]] - since late season 6	
| alias            = '''Katherine Davis''' (first married name)&lt;br /&gt;  '''Katherine Mayfair''' (second married name)&lt;br /&gt;  '''&quot;Kathy&quot;''' (nickname by Wayne)
| spouse           = '''[[List of Desperate Housewives characters#Wayne Davis|Wayne Davis]]''' (ex-husband; deceased) &lt;br /&gt;  '''[[List of Desperate Housewives characters#Adam Mayfair|Adam Mayfair]]''' (ex-husband)
| romances         = '''[[Acquaintances of Susan Mayer#Tim Bremmer|Tim Bremmer]]''' (ex-lover) &lt;br /&gt; '''Peter Hickey''' (one-night stand) &lt;br /&gt; '''[[Mike Delfino]]''' (ex-fiancé)&lt;br /&gt;  '''[[List of Desperate Housewives characters#Robin Gallagher|Robin Gallagher]]''' (girlfriend)
| children         =  '''Dylan Davis''' (daughter; deceased) &lt;br /&gt;  '''[[List of Desperate Housewives characters#Dylan Mayfair|Dylan Mayfair]]''' (adoptive daughter)
| relatives        =  '''Bradley''' (son-in-law) &lt;br /&gt;  '''Unnamed Grandchild'''&lt;br /&gt;  '''[[List of Desperate Housewives characters#Lillian Simms|Lillian Simms]]''' (aunt; deceased) &lt;br /&gt;  '''Mr. Simms''' (cousin) &lt;br /&gt;   '''Mr. Simms''' (uncle; deceased)
}}

'''Katherine Mayfair''' (formerly '''Davis''') is a [[fictional character]] created by [[television producer]] and [[screenwriter]] [[Marc Cherry]] for the [[American Broadcasting Company|ABC]] [[television series]] ''[[Desperate Housewives]]''. The character is played by [[Dana Delany]] and first appeared in the series' [[Now You Know (Desperate Housewives)|fourth season premiere]] on September 30, 2007 as the focus of the yearly mystery.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.tvguide.com/tvshows/desperate-housewives-2007/episode-1-season-4/know/100118 ''Desperate Housewives'' Episode: &quot;Now You Know&quot;]. ''[[TV Guide]]''. Retrieved June 16, 2010.&lt;/ref&gt;

Katherine is generally characterized by her cold demeanour and impressive domestic skills. Though initially a [[homemaker]], Katherine started a catering business with neighbour, [[Bree Van de Kamp|Bree Hodge]] ([[Marcia Cross]]), with whom she shares &quot;a heated rivalry.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;[http://abc.go.com/shows/desperate-housewives/bio/katherine-mayfair/96261 &quot;Katherine Mayfair (Dana Delany): Official Character Biography&quot;]. [[American Broadcasting Company]]. Retrieved June 16, 2010.&lt;/ref&gt; She has been married twice, to [[List of Desperate Housewives characters#Wayne Davis|Wayne Davis]] ([[Gary Cole]]) and [[List of Desperate Housewives characters#Adam Mayfair|Adam Mayfair]] ([[Nathan Fillion]]), but both relationships ended in divorce. Katherine has had two children: Dylan Davis (Hailee Denham), her daughter who died as a young child, and [[List of Desperate Housewives characters#Dylan Mayfair|Dylan Mayfair]] ([[Lyndsy Fonseca]]), her adoptive daughter. Delany left the series during the [[Desperate Housewives (season 6)|sixth season]], and the character has relocated to [[Paris]] indefinitely.&lt;ref name=&quot;men&quot;&gt;&quot;[[My Two Young Men]]&quot;. [[David Grossman (director)|David Grossman]] (director), [[Bob Daily]] (writer). ''[[Desperate Housewives]]''. [[American Broadcasting Company|ABC]]. March 21, 2010. Season 6, no. 18.&lt;/ref&gt;

Delany's portrayal of the character has received critical praise. Many critics attributed the improved quality of [[Desperate Housewives (season 4)|season four]] to Delany's performance. Delany was a critics' favourite for an [[Emmy Award]] nomination for [[Primetime Emmy Award for Outstanding Supporting Actress – Comedy Series|Outstanding Supporting Actress in a Comedy Series]] in 2008. The character received media attention when she was involved in the series' first lesbian relationship.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.dailymail.co.uk/tvshowbiz/article-1254603/Desperate-Housewives-Robin-seduces-Katherine-shows-lesbian-relationship.html &quot;Desperate Housewives: Robin seduces Katherine in show's first lesbian relationship&quot;]. ''[[Daily Mail]]''. March 1, 2010. Retrieved June 19, 2010.&lt;/ref&gt; She is set to return during the final series in 2011/2012.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.hollywoodreporter.com/live-feed/desperate-housewives-dana-delany-kyle-maclachlan-andrea-bowen-265405&lt;/ref&gt;

==Development and casting==
Delany auditioned for the series' [[Pilot (Desperate Housewives)|pilot episode]] in 2004 for the role of Bree Van de Kamp. Creator Marc Cherry thought she delivered &quot;a fantastic audition.&quot; Delany was offered the role but rejected it three times.&lt;ref name=&quot;ask dh audition&quot;&gt;[http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=pH4yOwp7dlM &quot;Ask Desperate Housewives Part 3&quot;]. [[YouTube]]. February 21, 2009. Retrieved June 16, 2010.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;tuned in&quot;&gt;Owen, Rob (August 17, 2007). [http://www.post-gazette.com/pg/07229/810119-237.stm?cmpid=entertainment.xml &quot;Tuned In: 'Desperate' measures include adding Dana Delany to cast&quot;]. ''[[Pittsburgh Post-Gazette]]''. Retrieved June 17, 2010.&lt;/ref&gt; Delany has since insisted that she was not ready to do another television series at the time and that the character of Bree was too similar to her character on ''[[Pasadena (TV series)|Pasadena]]''.&lt;ref name=&quot;ask dh audition&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;tuned in&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Brady, James (April 27, 2008). [http://www.parade.com/articles/editions/2008/edition_04-27-2008/In_Step_With...Dana_Delany &quot;In Step With... Dana Delany&quot;]. ''[[Parade (magazine)|Parade]]''. Retrieved June 16, 2010.&lt;/ref&gt; The role eventually went to [[Marcia Cross]], Cherry's second choice.&lt;ref name=&quot;tuned in&quot; /&gt; Delany reportedly regretted not accepting the part.&lt;ref name=&quot;season 4 secrets&quot;&gt;[http://television.aol.com/tv-celebrity-interviews/marc-cherry 'Desperate Housewives' Creator Dishes Season Four Secrets]. [[AOL Television]]. September 26, 2007. Retrieved June 16, 2010.&lt;/ref&gt;

{{Quote box |quoted=true |bgcolor=#FFFFF0 |salign=center |width=205px |align=left
 | quote  = I've never ever been in this for the money. I just like to do what challenges me. Thankfully, Marc [Cherry] circled back. That's unusual in Hollywood. Usually when you say &quot;no,&quot; they hold it against you for the rest of your career. I've experienced that. [Cherry] said I was sly, and that I got the slyness of the show.
 | source = '''Dana Delany'''&lt;ref name=&quot;sfgate&quot; /&gt;
}}
When Cherry was developing Katherine, a character with &quot;a lot of Alpha female qualities and some slyness and darkness,&quot; he offered Delany the role.&lt;ref name=&quot;season 4 secrets&quot; /&gt; She accepted the role and remained on the series until the end of the [[Desperate Housewives (Season 6)|sixth season]]. Following her multi-episode guest role on another ABC series, ''[[Castle (TV series)|Castle]]'', network executives offered Delany the lead in a new pilot for the [[2010–2011 United States network television schedule|2010-2011 television season]].&lt;ref name=&quot;zap2it&quot;&gt;Roffman, Marisa (March 22, 2010). [http://blog.zap2it.com/korbitv/2010/03/dana-delany-on-nathan-fillion-castle-and-her-desperate-housewives-exit.html &quot;Dana Delany on Nathan Fillion, 'Castle' and her 'Desperate Housewives' exit&quot;]. [[Zap2it]]. Retrieved June 17, 2010.&lt;/ref&gt; Delany filmed the pilot for ''[[Body of Proof]]'' in April 2010; her absence in ''Desperate Housewives'' was explained by having Katherine and her girlfriend, [[List of Desperate Housewives characters#Robin Gallagher|Robin Gallagher]] ([[Julie Benz]]), leave town indefinitely.&lt;ref name=&quot;zap2it&quot; /&gt; In May, ABC picked up ''Body of Proof'' for thirteen episodes; thus, Delany will not return for the [[Desperate Housewives (season 7)|seventh season]] of ''Desperate Housewives'' as a series regular.&lt;ref&gt;[[Michael Ausiello|Ausiello, Michael]] (May 14, 2010). [http://ausiellofiles.ew.com/2010/05/14/abc-picks-up-off-the-map/ &quot;Breaking: ABC Picks Up 'Off the Map' and Dana Delany Drama&quot;]. ''[[Entertainment Weekly]]''. Retrieved June 17, 2010.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Abrams, Natalie (May 14, 2010). [http://www.tvguide.com/News/ABC-Proof-Map-1018477.aspx &quot;ABC Orders ''Body of Proof'', ''Off the Map''&quot;]. ''[[TV Guide]]''. Retrieved June 17, 2010.&lt;/ref&gt; Delany admits that her exit from the series was quick, but insists that she may return to the series at some point, regardless of whether or not her new series is successful.&lt;ref&gt;Wightman, Catriona (May 17, 2010). [http://www.digitalspy.com/ustv/s21/desperate-housewives/news/a220244/delany-unsure-about-leaving-housewives.html &quot;Delany 'unsure about leaving Housewives'&quot;]. ''[[Digital Spy]]''. Retrieved June 17, 2010.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Wightman, Catriona (June 16, 2010). [http://www.digitalspy.com/ustv/s21/desperate-housewives/news/a228233/delany-housewives-exit-was-so-quick.html &quot;Delany: 'Housewives' Exit was so quick'&quot;]. ''[[Digital Spy]]''. Retrieved June 17, 2010.&lt;/ref&gt; She will return during the final series in 2012.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.hollywoodreporter.com/live-feed/desperate-housewives-dana-delany-kyle-maclachlan-andrea-bowen-265405&lt;/ref&gt;

==Personality==
When Katherine was introduced to the series, many critics noted that she was very similar to [[Bree Van de Kamp|Bree Hodge]] ([[Marcia Cross]]), in that both prided themselves on their domestic skills.&lt;ref name=&quot;menopause&quot;&gt;[[Tim Stack|Stack, Tim]]] (October 2, 2007). [http://www.ew.com/ew/article/0,,20068930,00.html &quot;The Menopause Button&quot;]. ''[[Entertainment Weekly]]''. Retrieved June 16, 2010.&lt;/ref&gt; Cherry noted that Katherine &quot;was clearly different&quot; before her arrival in the fourth season,&lt;ref name=&quot;season 4 secrets&quot; /&gt; which Susan confirms when she claims Katherine is &quot;not as fun as she used to be.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;free&quot;&gt;&quot;[[Free (Desperate Housewives)|Free]]&quot;. [[David Grossman (director)|David Grossman]] (director), [[Jeff Greenstein]] (writer). ''[[Desperate Housewives]]''. [[American Broadcasting Company|ABC]]. May 18, 2008. Season 4, no. 17.&lt;/ref&gt; Her cold exterior is noted by many characters, including [[Gabrielle Solis]] ([[Eva Longoria|Eva Longoria Parker]]), who remarks that Katherine is &quot;smug and 'holier than thou'&quot; and is &quot;getting a reputation around [the neighbourhood] for having a stick up [her] ass!&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;game&quot;&gt;&quot;[[The Game (Desperate Housewives)|The Game]]&quot;. [[Bethany Rooney]] (director), [[Joey Murphy]] (writer), [[John Pardee]] (writer). ''[[Desperate Housewives]]''. [[American Broadcasting Company|ABC]]. October 14, 2007. Season 4, no. 3.&lt;/ref&gt; Though Katherine immediately conflicts with the other women on the street,&lt;ref name=&quot;season 4 secrets&quot; /&gt; most notably Bree,&lt;ref name=&quot;menopause&quot; /&gt; she eventually develops close friendships with her neighbours.&lt;ref name=&quot;free&quot; /&gt; Nevertheless, her rivalry with Bree continues but as a natural part of their sisterly relationship.&lt;ref name=&quot;woman&quot;&gt;&quot;[[There's Always a Woman (Desperate Housewives)|There's Always a Woman]]&quot;. [[Matthew Diamond]] (director), [[John Paul Bullock III]] (writer). ''[[Desperate Housewives]]''. [[American Broadcasting Company|ABC]]. November 2, 2008. Season 5, no. 6.&lt;/ref&gt; In the sixth season, however, Katherine &quot;[morphs] into the person the housewives have to hate&quot; in the absence of [[Edie Britt]].&lt;ref name=&quot;sfgate&quot;&gt;Martin, Denise (November 11, 2009). [http://articles.sfgate.com/2009-11-11/entertainment/17179074_1_nurse-colleen-mcmurphy-desperate-housewives-katherine-mayfair &quot;Dana Delany turned down 'Sex,' got ''Desperate'&quot;]. ''[[San Francisco Chronicle]]''. Retrieved June 25, 2010.&lt;/ref&gt;

Katherine appears to be dependent on a romantic partner. Her first husband, Wayne, was abusive but she eventually left him and married [[Adam Mayfair]]. When he leaves, she tries convincing him to come home, saying that she is &quot;lonely,&quot; despite having discovered that he had an affair.&lt;ref name=&quot;kanagawa&quot;&gt;&quot;[[Welcome to Kanagawa]]&quot;. [[Larry Shaw (director)|Larry Shaw]] (director), [[Jamie Gorenberg]] (writer), [[Jordon Nardino]] (writer). ''[[Desperate Housewives]]''. January 6, 2008. Season 4, no. 10.&lt;/ref&gt; Later, in the fifth season, Katherine contemplates leaving Fairview because she is single, later revisiting the option in an attempt to force Mike to realize he loves her.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;[[Connect! Connect!]]&quot;. [[Ken Whittingham]] (director), [[Jordon Nardino]] (writer). ''[[Desperate Housewives]]''. [[American Broadcasting Company|ABC]]. January 11, 2009. Season 5, no. 12.&lt;/ref&gt; She also resorts to trickery in order to ensure that Mike does not end their engagement.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;[[Bargaining (Desperate Housewives)|Bargaining]]&quot;. [[David Grossman (director)|David Grossman]] (director), [[David Schladweiler]] (writer). ''[[Desperate Housewives]]''. [[American Broadcasting Company|ABC]]. May 3, 2009. Season 5, no. 21.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;marry&quot;&gt;&quot;[[Marry Me a Little (Desperate Housewives)|Marry Me a Little]]&quot;. [[Larry Shaw (director)|Larry Shaw]] (director), [[Jason Ganzel]] (writer). ''[[Desperate Housewives]]''. [[American Broadcasting Company|ABC]]. May 10, 2009. Season 5, no. 22.&lt;/ref&gt; When Mike leaves Katherine for Susan, she suffers a complete nervous breakdown.&lt;ref name=&quot;sfgate&quot; /&gt; When she becomes romantically involved with a woman, she puts her life in Fairview on hold indefinitely while trying to evaluate everything during an extended vacation in Paris.&lt;ref name=&quot;men&quot; /&gt;

==Overview ==
Before the series, Katherine was married to abusive police officer [[List of Desperate Housewives characters#Wayne Davis|Wayne Davis]] ([[Gary Cole]]). Together, they had a daughter named Dylan (Hailee Denham). Wayne became increasingly violent, forcing Katherine to flee with Dylan (Hailee Denham), and seek refuge with her aunt, [[List of Desperate Housewives characters#Lillian Simms|Lillian Simms]] ([[Ellen Geer]]). While living on Wisteria Lane, Katherine befriends her neighbours, [[Mary Alice Young]] and [[Susan Mayer]].&lt;ref name=&quot;know&quot;&gt;&quot;[[Now You Know (Desperate Housewives)|Now You Know]]&quot;. [[Larry Shaw (director)|Larry Shaw]] (director), [[Marc Cherry]] (writer). ''[[Desperate Housewives]]''. [[American Broadcasting Company|ABC]]. September 30, 2007. Season 4, no. 1.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;smiles&quot;&gt;&quot;[[Smiles of a Summer Night (Desperate Housewives)|Smiles of a Summer Night]]&quot;. [[David Grossman (director)|David Grossman]] (director), [[Bob Daily]] (writer), [[Matt Berry]] (director). ''[[Desperate Housewives]]''. [[American Broadcasting Company|ABC]]. October 7, 2007. Season 4, no. 2.&lt;/ref&gt; One night, Katherine returned to find Wayne had visited Dylan and gave her a new doll. Katherine put the doll on top of a [[chest of drawers|dresser]].&lt;ref name=&quot;free&quot; /&gt; and got into a fight with Wayne, hitting him with a candlestick. After Wayne left, Katherine and Lillian discover Dylan had tried to retrieve her doll and died when the dresser fell on top of her. Fearing Wayne’s wrath, Katherine and Lillian buried Dylan in nearby woods and left Wisteria Lane, telling Susan and Mary Alice that she had taken a job offer in Chicago.&lt;ref name=&quot;smiles&quot; /&gt; 

Katherine adopted a girl very similar to Dylan from a Romanian orphanage. &lt;ref name=&quot;free&quot; /&gt; Katherine began raising her adopted daughter, [[List of Desperate Housewives characters#Dylan Mayfair|Dylan]] ([[Lyndsy Fonseca]]), and they moved to Chicago. Eventually, Katherine married [[gynecologist]] [[List of Desperate Housewives characters#Adam Mayfair|Adam Mayfair]] ([[Nathan Fillion]]). Katherine tells Adam that Wayne killed her biological daughter and he agrees to keep her secret and protect them from her ex-husband. Years later, the Mayfairs move to Wisteria Lane to care for Lillian, now terminally ill, and escape the humiliation of Adam's alleged sexual harassment of one of his patients.

===Season Four===
Twelve years after leaving Wisteria Lane, Katherine, Adam and Dylan move in to Lillian's house. Susan introduces Katherine to Bree, Lynette and Gabrielle, her friends and neighbours; Katherine immediately clashes with each of them, particularly Bree. Meanwhile, Dylan doesn't remember living on Wisteria Lane. Katherine begins integrating herself into Susan's circle of friends but continues to conflict with Bree, Gabrielle and Lynette. Katherine's mysterious and cold exterior and Dylan’s lack of memories about life on Wisteria Lane raise the suspicions of their neighbours. Dylan questions Katherine about her birth father but Katherine only says that he is too dangerous to let back into their lives. 

Lillian moves into the Mayfairs' guest bedroom and writes a detailed account of the original Dylan’s death in a note addressed to Dylan Mayfair, but dies before she can give it to her. [[List of Desperate Housewives characters#Sylvia Greene|Sylvia Greene]] ([[Melora Walters]]), the woman who accused Adam of sexual harassment in Chicago, visits him - hoping to rekindle their romance. Katherine thinks Sylvia's accusations are false but Adam admits having had an affair with her, which is why he settled out of court and they &quot;lost everything&quot; in Chicago. Katherine kicks Adam out of the house. While packing, he finds Lillian's note and leaves after confronting Katherine about her lies and she throws the note in the fire. However, Dylan salvages a few pieces and deducts that Katherine killed Wayne. She calls Adam for more answers but he calls Katherine. He promises to give her one last alibi and lie to Dylan but their marriage is still over. 

Katherine and Bree put aside their rivalry to start a catering business. Meanwhile, Wayne tracks down Dylan and the two start meeting in private; eventually, she reintroduces the two. Hoping to drive Wayne away, Katherine tells him that Dylan is not his daughter and a DNA test confirms that. Adam learns that Wayne has located Katherine and Dylan and offers to help them escape, deciding to take Dylan on a graduation trip and never return but Wayne kidnaps Adam. Fearing Wayne has killed Adam, Katherine begs Dylan to leave immediately but Dylan demands the entire truth. Katherine tells her, prompting Dylan to walk out. Later, Wayne corners Katherine and takes her hostage. Before he can shoot her, Adam arrives. Knowing Wayne will always track her, Katherine shoots him. Bree, Susan, Lynette, and Gabrielle tell the police that her actions were in self-defence and Katherine is finally integrated into their social group. Dylan returns and reunites with her mother.

===Season Five===
During the five years between seasons four and five, Katherine remains on Wisteria Lane.  Katherine briefly moves in with Bree, a recovering alcoholic who relapses when her husband, [[Orson Hodge]] ([[Kyle MacLachlan]]), leaves for jail.&lt;ref name=&quot;mirror&quot;&gt;&quot;[[Mirror Mirror (Desperate Housewives)|Mirror, Mirror]]&quot;. [[David Grossman (director)|David Grossman]] (director), [[Jeff Greenstein]] (writer). ''[[Desperate Housewives]]''. [[American Broadcasting Company|ABC]]. October 26, 2008. Season 5, no. 5.&lt;/ref&gt;Katherine's rivalry with Bree continues despite their shared business. Katherine is unhappy when she realises that Bree has used her recipes in her cookbook and leaves her to run the business while she publicises it. Her resentment deepens when Bree hires Orson as an employee. Yearning for romance, Katherine secretly begins dating [[Mike Delfino]] ([[James Denton]]), Susan's ex-husband. Eventually, Susan finds out about the relationship and feels betrayed. She eventually gives them her blessing but is uncomfortable with their relationship.

Katherine begins spending more time with Susan and Mike's son, [[Acquaintances of Susan Mayer#M.J. Delfino|M.J.]] ([[Mason Vale Cotton (actor)|Mason Vale Cotton]]) and move in together. Susan tells Mike and Katherine that she's marrying Jackson but is horrified to learn that Mike will no longer have to pay her alimony. Katherine deceives Susan by letting her think Mike will pay alimony regardless. When Susan wants to thank Mike herself, Katherine admits not telling him that Susan's engagement to Jackson isn't real, afraid that he would leave her for Susan. The couple elope to [[Las Vegas metropolitan area|Las Vegas]], but Mike leaves Katherine at the airport when he learns that their neighbour, [[List of Desperate Housewives characters#Dave Williams|Dave Williams]] ([[Neal McDonough]]), plans to kill M.J. in revenge. M.J. escapes unharmed and Mike and Susan share a passionate kiss following the ordeal.

===Season Six===
In the [[Nice is Different Than Good|sixth season premiere]], it is revealed that Mike married Susan, not Katherine. When Susan is out, her wedding dress is delivered to Katherine's house. Katherine wears it while cooking to annoy Susan. She also demands that Susan publicly apologize to her for taking Mike away. Susan initially refuses and locks her in a closet, Katherine then breaks free and crashes the wedding. Susan then apologizes, but Katherine's feelings remain bitter. When Susan is away, Katherine visits Mike, gives him a kiss and tells him she'll be there for him. Katherine then tells Orson that Mike made a pass at her, hoping this will get back to Susan. Bree becomes concerned when she sees Katherine spying through Susan and Mike's windows one night. After an incident at a wedding they were catering, Bree fires Katherine and advises her to seek professional help. Furious, Katherine scratches Bree's car. 

Katherine's rivalry with Susan intensifies as she continues pursuing Mike. Things come to a head at a neighborhood watch meeting after Susan ignores Katherine when she tries to volunteer, escalating into Susan publicly threatening Katherine if she doesn't leave her and Mike alone. Realizing the danger Katherine poses, Susan begins suspecting Katherine attacked her daughter, [[Acquaintances of Susan Mayer#Julie Mayer|Julie Mayer]], out of revenge. Though Katherine has an alibi, Susan and Mike's fears about Katherine are soon realized. When Mike hears Katherine told M.J. that Susan is a bad mother, he coldly tells her that he never loved her. When he leaves, Katherine stabs herself in the stomach with a knife that has Mike's fingerprints on it. Katherine frames Mike and he is sent to jail while she is in hospital. Susan worries that Katherine has suffered a [[nervous breakdown]] and asks Dylan to visit and have her mother committed for psychiatric observation. She then learns that Katherine has been telling Dylan that she, not Susan, was married to Mike. When Katherine realizes she's been caught, she has a complete breakdown. Katherine is institutionalized for a couple of months. 
 
When Katherine returns to Wisteria Lane, she develops a friendship with [[List of Desperate Housewives characters#Robin Gallagher|Robin Gallagher]] ([[Julie Benz]]), a former stripper who moves in with Susan and Mike. In order to preserve her friendship with Susan, Robin moves in with Katherine. Katherine is surprised to learn that Robin is a lesbian and begins to develop a physical attraction to her, as well as an emotional connection. Katherine is very confused by these new feelings. Soon, the two become sexually involved. When their relationship is made public, Katherine decides that she cares too much about what others think and suggests that she and Robin take a vacation in Paris while they work on defining their relationship. Robin agrees and the two leave town that night.

==Reception==

===Critical===
Katherine's arrival to the series in the fourth season received positive reviews. [[Robert Bianco]] of ''[[USA Today]]'' praised Delany's portrayal of the character, noting that the season was &quot;shaping up to be the best since the first&quot; due to performance.&lt;ref&gt;[[Robert Bianco|Biano, Robert]] (October 25, 2007). [http://www.usatoday.com/life/television/news/2007-10-25-three-shows_N.htm “Three hit TV shows remind us why we liked them”]. ''USA Today''. Retrieved June 16, 2010.&lt;/ref&gt; Other critics agreed that Delany's performance helped the series return to the quality of its first season.&lt;ref name=&quot;emmys&quot;&gt;Alston, Joshua (July 15, 2009). [http://www.newsweek.com/2008/07/15/emmys-special-victims-unit.html “Emmys: Special Victims Unit”]. ''[[Newsweek]]''. Retrieved June 17, 2010.&lt;/ref&gt; [[Tim Stack]] of ''[[Entertainment Weekly]]'' confessed that while he is not a fan of Delany's acting, she is &quot;perfect for this role and looks to be a choice adversary for Bree.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;menopause&quot; /&gt;

===Awards===
Following the 2007-2008 television season, Delany was a promising contender for an [[Emmy Award]] in the [[Primetime Emmy Award for Outstanding Supporting Actress – Comedy Series|Outstanding Supporting Actress in a Comedy Series]] category,&lt;ref name=&quot;emmys&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref&gt;O’Neil, Tom (June 4, 2008). [http://www.chicagotribune.com/topic/env-en-contention4-2008jun04,0,6721505.htmlstory “Prospects for Emmy Acting Awards”]. ''[[Chicago Tribune]]''. Retrieved June 16, 2010.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;O’Neil, Tom (May 19, 2008). [http://goldderby.latimes.com/awards_goldderby/2008/05/tv-guides-mike.html “TV Guide's Mike Ausiello reveals his dream Emmy ballot: Dana Delany, Jim Parsons...”]. ''[[Los Angeles Times]]''. Retrieved June 17, 2010.&lt;/ref&gt; though she did not receive a nomination. In 2009, Delany received a [[Entertainment Industries Council#PRISM Awards|Prism Award]] for Best Performance in a Comedy Series.&lt;ref&gt;[http://archive.constantcontact.com/fs057/1101507314005/archive/1102557928323.html 2009 Prism Award Winners]. Entertainment Industries Council, Inc. Retrieved June 17, 2010.&lt;/ref&gt;

== References ==
{{Reflist|3}}

== External links ==
* {{imdb character|0028925|Katherine Mayfair}}

{{Desperate Housewives}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Mayfair, Katherine}}
[[Category:Desperate Housewives characters]]
[[Category:Fictional bisexuals]]
[[Category:Fictional characters introduced in 2007]]
[[Category:Fictional murderers]]

[[es:Katherine (Desperate Housewives)]]
[[fr:Katherine Mayfair]]
[[it:Katherine Mayfair]]
[[hu:Katherine Mayfair]]
[[mk:Кетрин Мејфер]]
[[nl:Katherine Mayfair]]
[[ja:キャサリン・メイフェア]]
[[pl:Katherine Mayfair]]
[[pt:Katherine Mayfair]]
[[ru:Кэтрин Мейфеир]]
[[fi:Katherine Mayfair]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
