<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="12712929" ns="0" title="Nero Vision"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Infobox software
| name                   = Nero Vision
| title                  = Nero Vision Xtra
| logo                   = [[File:Nero Vision Xtra.png]]
| screenshot             = [[File:Nero Vision Xtra Screenshot.jpg|250px]]
| caption                = Video editing area of Nero Vision Xtra
| collapsible            = 
| author                 = [[Nero AG]]
| developer              = [[Nero AG]]
| released               = {{Start date|2010|04|12}}&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.pascal90.de/2010/04/nero-10-erschienen/ Pascal90.de: Nero 10 publicated] (shown at 11th June 2011)&lt;/ref&gt;
| discontinued           = 
| latest release version = 
| latest release date    = 
| latest preview version = 
| latest preview date    = 
| frequently updated     = 
| programming language   = 
| operating system       = [[Windows XP]], [[Windows Vista|Vista]], [[Windows 7|7]]
| platform               = 
| size                   = 
| language               = 
| status                 = 
| genre                  = 
| license                = [[Proprietary software|proprietary]]
| website                = {{URL|http://www.nero.com/eng/vision-xtra-overview.html}}
}}

'''Nero Vision''' is a [[video editing software]] publicated by [[Nero AG]] which is suitable for multichannel video editing - even with images. After editing the software burns a DVD, whose menu and chapters you can create individually in single steps before finishing. 

== Development ==
This software shows a strong technical development between the single versions: 
=== Nero Vision 4 ===
In the first version “Nero Vision 4” you already could edit videos in a small template: Per film unchangeable the are one video channel, one effect channel, one text channel and to audio channels. Images can't be added into a film. The menu editing is only maneuverable in an automatic template. 
=== Nero Vision 5 ===
Now also [[high-definition video|High Definition]] videos become possible. In the menu areas now more templates are choosable, but at large no strong innovations. 
=== Nero 9 ===
In the third version of this software menu editing is maualyzed. Now also additional submenus can be created. Furthermore images can be added into videos. 
=== Nero Vision Xtra ===
In the hitherto newest version of the program more channel editing became possible; also visually it was optimised. Here many effects came to those of the earlier versions as well as optional point markings on the timeline for example to variate the image size. In menu editing areas no essential things were changed. But now even burning [[Blu-ray Disc|Blu-ray Discs]] became possible.

== Single functions ==
The main functions of the current version Nero Vision Xtra are following: 
*Transfer of video from external equipment (also [[Digital Video]])
*More channel editing (practically unlimited)
*[[Chromakey|Cromakey (=BlueScreen)]]
*Effects for single videos ''or'' all
*Upload of videos to [[iTunes]] or [[Microsoft Office PowerPoint|PowerPoint presentations]]
*Burning of [[Blu-ray Disc|Blu-ray Discs]]
*Manualyzed menu editing (optional extra menus, several main menus etc.
*Optional burning onto [[hard drive]]
*Use of many file types, e.g. [[Adobe Flash|*.flv]], [[Windows Media|*.wma]]

== References ==
&lt;references /&gt;

[[Category:Video editing software]]
[[Category:Mac OS software]]
[[Category:Windows software]]
[[Category:Proprietary software]]

[[de:Nero Video]]
[[la:Nero Vision]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
