<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="12734316" ns="0" title="Graf Zeppelin class aircraft carrier"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{|{{Infobox ship begin}}
{{Infobox ship image
|Ship image=[[Image:Graf-Zeppelin-2.jpg|300px|Graf Zeppelin]]
|Ship caption=Aircraft carrier ''Graf Zeppelin''
}}
{{Infobox ship class overview
|Name=
|Builders=
|Operators=
|Class before=
|Class after=
|Subclasses=
|Cost=
|Built range=
|In service range=
|In commission range=
|Total ships building=
|Total ships planned=2
|Total ships completed=
|Total ships cancelled=2
|Total ships active=
|Total ships laid up=
|Total ships lost=
|Total ships retired=
|Total ships preserved=
}}
{{Infobox ship characteristics
|Hide header=
|Header caption=
|Ship class=
|Ship displacement=33,550 tonnes
|Ship length={{convert|262.5|m|ftin|abbr=on}}
|Ship beam={{convert|31.5|m|ftin|abbr=on}}
|Ship draft={{convert|7.6|m|ftin|abbr=on}}
|Ship propulsion=Geared turbines, 200,000 hp (150,000 kW), four screws
|Ship speed= {{convert|35|knots|km/h}}
|Ship range= {{convert|14816|km|nmi|abbr=off|abbr=on}} at {{convert|19|knots|km/h}}
|Ship complement=1,720 crew&lt;br&gt;306 flight personnel
|Ship sensors=
|Ship EW=
|Ship armament=	16 × [[15 cm SK C/28]] guns&lt;br/ &gt;12 × [[Flak]] (10.5 cm)&lt;br/ &gt;22 × [[3.7 cm SK C/30]] (AA)&lt;br/ &gt;28 × Flak (2.0 cm)
|Ship armor=
|Ship aircraft=Complement of 43&lt;br /&gt;10 × [[Messerschmitt Bf 109]] [[Fighter aircraft|fighters]]&lt;br /&gt;13 × [[Junkers Ju 87]] [[dive bombers]]&lt;br /&gt;20 × [[Fieseler Fi 167]] [[torpedo bombers]] 
|Ship notes=
}}
|}

The '''''Graf Zeppelin''-class aircraft carriers''' were two [[Germany|German]] [[Kriegsmarine]] [[aircraft carrier]]s laid down in the mid-1930s as part of the [[Plan Z]] rearmament program. Four ships were initially envisioned but reduced to two by [[Grand Admiral]] [[Erich Raeder]] in 1939. ''Flugzeugträger A'' (christened [[German aircraft carrier Graf Zeppelin|''Graf Zeppelin'']]) was launched in 1938 but never completed; she was sunk as a target ship by the Soviets in 1947. Construction on the second ship, ''[[Flugzeugträger B]]'', was halted in 1939 when only complete up to the armor deck; it was scrapped the following year.

==Planning and construction==
[[File:Bundesarchiv RM 25 Bild-13, Flugzeugträger &quot;Graf Zeppelin&quot;, Bau.jpg|thumb|left|Construction work in Kiel, 1938]]
Wilhelm Hadeler had been Assistant to the Professor of Naval Construction at the [[Technical University of Berlin]] for nine years when he was appointed to draft preliminary designs for an aircraft carrier in April 1934.&lt;ref name=Reynolds42&gt;Reynolds, p.42&lt;/ref&gt;  The [[Anglo-German Naval Agreement]] signed 18 June 1935 allowed Germany to construct aircraft carriers with displacement up to 38,500 tons.&lt;ref name=Reynolds43&gt;Reynolds, p.43&lt;/ref&gt;  In 1935, [[Adolf Hitler]] announced that Germany would construct aircraft carriers to strengthen the ''[[Kriegsmarine]]''.  A Luftwaffe officer, a naval officer and a constructor visited Japan in the autumn of 1935 to obtain flight deck equipment blueprints and inspect the [[Japanese aircraft carrier Akagi|Japanese aircraft carrier ''Akagi'']].&lt;ref name=Reynolds44&gt;Reynolds, p.44&lt;/ref&gt;  The keel of ''Graf Zeppelin'' was laid down the next year.  
Two years later, [[Großadmiral]] (Grand Admiral) [[Erich Raeder]] presented an ambitious shipbuilding program called [[Plan Z]] which would build up the German Navy to a point where it could challenge the British Royal Navy in the North Sea. Under Plan Z, by 1945 as part of the balanced force the navy would have four carriers. In 1939, Raeder revised the plan, reducing the number to two.

The ''Kriegsmarine'' has always maintained a policy of not assigning a name to a ship until it is launched. The first German carrier, laid down as &quot;''Flugzeugträger'' A&quot; (&quot;Aircraft carrier A&quot;), was named ''Graf Zeppelin'' when launched in 1938. The second carrier &amp;mdash; never launched &amp;mdash; bore only the title &quot;[[Flugzeugträger B|''Flugzeugträger'' B]]&quot;, but might, if completed, have been called [[Peter Strasser]].&lt;ref
name=Greene/Swanborough&gt;Greene/Swanborough&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:Bundesarchiv RM 25 Bild-27, Flugzeugträger &quot;Graf Zeppelin&quot;, Stapellauf.jpg|thumb|right|''Graf Zeppelin'' is launched, 8 December 1938]]

A review of Hitler's conferences on the German Navy, the minutes of which were captured after the fall of the Third Reich, reveals his decreasing interest in the carriers. [[Reichsmarschall]] [[Hermann Göring]], Commander of the [[Luftwaffe]], was resentful of any incursion on his authority as head of the country's air power, and he frustrated Raeder at every opportunity. Within his own service, Raeder found opposition in Admiral [[Karl Dönitz]], a submariner.

Having no experience building such ships, the Kriegsmarine had difficulty implementing advanced technologies such as aircraft catapults into the ''Graf Zeppelin'' class, even with the [[Heinkel]] firm's previous creation of compressed air catapults for use with ships like the ''[[SS Westfalen]]'', used as a mid-Atlantic seaplane tender for [[Dornier Do J|Dornier Wal]] flying boats for [[Dornier Do J#South Atlantic air mail|trans-Atlantic mail service to South America]] during the early 1930s. German designers were able to study Japanese designs, but were constrained by the realities of creating a North Sea carrier vs. a &quot;Blue Water&quot; design.  Several cruiser-type guns were envisioned to allow commerce raiding and defense against British cruisers, for example.  This is in contrast to American and Japanese designs, which were more oriented toward a task-force defense, using supporting cruisers for surface firepower.

==Design==
===Hull===
The ''Graf Zeppelin'' class's hull was divided into 19 watertight compartments, the standard division for all capital ships in the Kriegsmarine.&lt;ref name=Breyer33&gt;Breyer, p.33&lt;/ref&gt; Their belt armor was to vary from {{convert|100|mm|abbr=on}} over the machinery spaces and aft magazines, to {{convert|60|mm|abbr=on}} over the forward magazines and tapered down to {{convert|30|mm|abbr=on}} at the bows. Stern armor was kept at {{convert|80|mm|abbr=on}} to protect the steering gear. Inboard of the main armor belt was a {{convert|20|mm|abbr=on}} anti-torpedo bulkhead.&lt;ref name=Whitley157&gt;Whitley, p.157&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:Bundesarchiv RM 25 Bild-62, Flugzeugträger &quot;Graf Zeppelin&quot;, Bau.jpg|thumb|right|''Graf Zeppelin'' at Kiel, June 1940, displaying her newly rebuilt bow. The photo is marked ''Geheim'' (&quot;secret&quot;)]]

Horizontal armor protection against aerial bombs and plunging shellfire started with the flight deck, which acted as the main strength deck. The armor was generally {{convert|20|mm|abbr=on}} thick except for those areas around the elevator shafts and funnel uptakes where thickness increased to {{convert|40|mm|abbr=on}} in order to give the elevators necessary structural strength and the critical uptakes greater splinter protection.&lt;ref name=Whitley157/&gt; Beneath the lower hangar was the main armored deck (or tween deck) where armor thickness varied from {{convert|60|mm|abbr=on}} over the magazines to {{convert|40|mm|abbr=on}} over the machinery spaces. Along the peripheries, it formed a 45 degree slope where it joined the lower portion of the waterline belt armor.&lt;ref name=Whitley157/&gt;

The ''Graf Zeppelins''' original length-to-beam ratio was 9.26:1, resulting in a slender silhouette. However, in May 1942, the accumulating top-weight of recent design changes required the addition of deep bulges to either side of ''Graf Zeppelin's'' hull, decreasing that ratio to 8.33:1 and giving her the widest beam of any carrier designed prior to 1942.&lt;ref name=Brown9&gt;Brown, p. 9&lt;/ref&gt; The bulges served mainly to improve ''Graf Zeppelin's'' stability but they also gave her an added degree of anti-torpedo protection and increased her operating range because selected compartments were designed to store approximately 1500&amp;nbsp;tons more fuel oil.&lt;ref name=Whitley31&gt;Whitley, p.31&lt;/ref&gt;

''Graf Zeppelin's'' straight-stemmed prow was rebuilt in early 1940 with the addition of a more sharply angled &quot;Atlantic prow&quot;, intended to improve overall seakeeping. This added {{convert|5.2|m|abbr=on}} to her overall length.&lt;ref name=Breyer33&gt;Breyer, p.33&lt;/ref&gt;

===Machinery===
The ''Graf Zeppelin'' class's power plant was to consist of 16 La Mont high-pressure boilers, similar to those used in the ''[[Admiral Hipper class cruiser|Admiral Hipper]]''-class heavy cruisers. Their four sets of geared turbines, connected to four shafts, were expected to produce {{convert|200000|shp|lk=in|abbr=on}} and propel the carrier at a top speed of {{convert|35|kn|mph km/h}}. With a maximum bunkerage capacity of 5000&amp;nbsp;tons of fuel oil (prior to the addition of bulges in 1942), the ''Graf Zeppelins''' calculated radius of action was {{convert|9600|mi}} at {{convert|19|kn}}, though wartime experience on ships with similar powerplants showed such estimates were highly inaccurate. Actual operational ranges tended to be much lower.&lt;ref name=Whitley159&gt;Whitley, p.159&lt;/ref&gt;

Two [[Voith Schneider Propeller|Voith-Schneider cycloidal propeller-rudders]] were to be installed in the forward bow of the ship along the center-line. These were intended to assist in berthing the ship in harbor and also in negotiating narrow waterways such as the [[Kiel Canal]] where, due to the carrier’s high freeboard and difficulty in maneuvering at speeds below {{convert|8|kn}}, gusting winds might push the ship into the canal sides. In an emergency, the units could have been used to steer the ships at speeds under {{convert|12|kn}} and, if the ships' main engines were rendered inoperable, could propel the vessel at a speed of {{convert|4|kn}} in calm seas. When not in use, they were to be retracted into their vertical shafts and protected by water-tight covers.&lt;ref name=Whitley159/&gt;

===Flight deck &amp; hangars===
The ''Graf Zeppelins''' steel flight deck, overlaid with wooden planking, was {{convert|242|m|abbr=on}} long by {{convert|30|m|abbr=on}} wide at its maximum. It had a slight round down right aft and overhung the main superstructure but not the stern; being supported by steel girders. At the bow, the carriers were to have an open forecastle and the leading edge of her flight deck was uneven (mainly due to the blunt ends of her catapult tracks), but it did not appear likely that would have caused any undue air turbulence. Careful wind-tunnel studies using models confirmed this, but they also revealed that their long low island structure would generate a vortex over the flight deck in these tests when the ship yawed to port. This was considered to be an acceptable hazard when conducting air operations.&lt;ref name=Brown10&gt;Brown, p.10&lt;/ref&gt;

The ''Graf Zeppelin'' class's upper and lower hangars were long and narrow with unarmored sides and ends. Workshops, stores and crew quarters were located outboard of the hangars, a design feature similar to that of British carriers.&lt;ref name=Brown10/&gt; The upper hangar measured {{convert|185|m|abbr=on}} x {{convert|16|m|abbr=on}}; the lower hangar {{convert|172|m|abbr=on}} x {{convert|16|m|abbr=on}}. The upper hangar had {{convert|6|m|abbr=on}} vertical clearance while the lower hangar had {{convert|0.3|m|abbr=on}} less headroom due to the ceiling braces. Total usable hangar space was {{convert|5450|m2|abbr=on}} with stowage for 41 aircraft: 18 [[Fieseler Fi 167]] torpedo-planes in the lower hangar; 13 [[Junkers Ju 87|Junkers Ju 87C]] dive-bombers and 10 [[Messerschmitt Me 109|Messerschmitt Bf 109T]] fighters in the upper hangar.&lt;ref name=Breyer52&gt;Breyer, p.52&lt;/ref&gt;

The ''Graf Zeppelin'' class had three electrically operated elevators positioned along the flight-deck's center-line: one near the bow, abreast the forward end of the island; one amidships; and one aft. They were octagonal in shape, measuring {{convert|13|m|abbr=on}} x {{convert|14|m|abbr=on}}, and were designed to transfer aircraft weighing up to 5.5 tons between decks.&lt;ref name=Whitley155&gt;Whitley, p.155&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=Breyer54&gt;Breyer, p.54&lt;/ref&gt;

Two Deutsche Werke compressed air-driven telescoping [[Aircraft catapult|catapults]] were installed at the forward end of the flight deck for power-assisted launches. They were {{convert|23|m|abbr=on}} long and designed to accelerate a {{convert|2500|kg|abbr=on}} fighter to a speed of approximately {{convert|140|km/h|abbr=on}} and a {{convert|5000|kg|abbr=on}} bomber to {{convert|130|km/h|abbr=on}}.&lt;ref name=Breyer54/&gt;

A dual set of rails led back from the catapults to the forward and midship elevators. In the hangars, aircraft were to be hoisted by crane onto collapsible launch trollies. The aircraft/trolley combination would then be lifted to flight deck level on the elevator and trundled forward to the catapult start points. As each plane lifted off, its launch trolley would be caught in a metal &quot;basket&quot; at the end of the catapult track, lowered to the forecastle on &quot;B&quot; deck and rolled back into the upper hangar for re-use via a secondary set of rails. When not in use, the catapult tracks were to be covered with sheet metal farings to protect them from harsh weather.&lt;ref name=Breyer54/&gt;

Eighteen aircraft could have theoretically been launched at a rate of one every 30 seconds before exhausting the catapult air reservoirs. It would then have taken 50 minutes to recharge the reservoirs. The two large cylinders holding the compressed air were housed in insulated compartments located between the two catapult tracks, below flight deck level but above the main armored deck. This positioning afforded them only light protection from potential battle damage. The insulated compartments were to be electrically heated to a temperature of {{convert|20|C}} in order to prevent ice from forming on the cylinder piping and control equipment as the compressed air was vented during launches.&lt;ref name=Burke87&gt;Burke, p.87&lt;/ref&gt;

It was intended from the outset that all of the ''Graf Zeppelins''' aircraft would normally launch via catapult. Rolling take-offs would be performed only in an emergency or if the catapults were inoperable due to battle damage or mechanical failure. Whether this practice would have been strictly adhered to or later modified, based on actual air trials and combat experience, is open to question, especially given the limited capacity of the air reservoirs and the long recharging times necessary between launches.&lt;ref name=Breyer54/&gt; One advantage of of such a system, however, was that the ''Graf Zeppelins'' could have launched their aircraft without need for turning the ship into the wind or under conditions where the prevailing winds were too light to provide enough lift for her heavier aircraft. They could also have launched and landed aircraft simultaneously.&lt;ref name=Marshall23&gt;Marshall, p.23&lt;/ref&gt;

To facilitate rapid catapult launches and eliminate the necessity of time-consuming engine warm-ups, up to eight aircraft were to be kept in readiness in the hangars by the use of steam pre-heaters. These would keep the aircraft engines at an operational temperature of {{convert|70|C}}. In addition, engine oil was to be kept warmed in separate holding tanks, then added via hand-pumps to the aircraft engines shortly before launch. Once the aircraft were raised to flight deck level via the elevators, aircraft oil temperature could be maintained, if need be, through the use of electric pre-heaters plugged into power points on the flight deck. Otherwise the aircraft could have been immediately catapult-launched as their engines would already have been at or near normal operating temperature.&lt;ref name=Burke86&gt;Burke, p.86&lt;/ref&gt;

Four arrester wires were positioned at the after end of the flight deck with two more emergency wires located afore and abaft of the amidships elevator. Original drawings show four additional wires fore and aft of the forward lift, possibly intended to allow recovery of aircraft over the bows, but these may have been deleted from the ship's final configuration.&lt;ref name=Whitley155/&gt; To assist with night landings, the arrester wires were to be illuminated with neon lights.&lt;ref name=Marshall23/&gt;

Two {{convert|4|m|abbr=on}} high, slitted steel wind barriers were installed afore the midships and forward elevators. These were designed to reduce wind velocity over the flight deck to a distance of approximately {{convert|40|m|abbr=on}} behind them. When not in use they would have been lowered flush with the deck to allow aircraft to pass over them.&lt;ref name=Whitley155/&gt;

The ''Graf Zeppelins''' starboard-side island housed the command and navigating bridges and charthouse. It also served as a platform for three searchlights, four domed stabilized fire-control directors and a large vertical funnel. To compensate for the weight of the island, the carrier's flight deck and hangars were offset {{convert|0.5|m|abbr=on}} to port from her longitudinal axis.&lt;ref name=Breyer33/&gt; Design additions proposed in 1942 included a tall fighter-director tower, air search radar antennas and a curved cap for her funnel, the latter intended to keep smoke and exhaust gases away from the armored fighter-director cabin.&lt;ref name=Breyer18&gt;Breyer, p.18&lt;/ref&gt;

===Armament===
The ''Graf Zeppelins'' were to be armed with separate high and low angle guns for AA and anti-ship defense at a time when most other major navies were switching to dual-purpose AA weapons and relying on escort ships to protect their carriers from surface threats.&lt;ref name=Whitley159/&gt; Her primary anti-shipping armament consisted of sixteen {{convert|15|cm|abbr=on}} guns paired in eight armored casemates. These were mounted, two each, at the four corners of the carriers' upper hangar deck, positions that raised the possibility the guns would be washed out in heavy seas, especially those in the forward casemates.&lt;ref name=Whitley159/&gt;

Chief Engineer Hadeler had originally planned for only eight such weapons on the carriers, four on each side in single mountings. However, the Naval Armaments Office misinterpreted his proposal to save space by pairing them and instead doubled the number of guns to sixteen, resulting in a need for increased ammunition stowage and more electrically operated hoists to service them.&lt;ref name=Breyer43&gt;Breyer, p.43&lt;/ref&gt; Later in ''Graf Zeppelin's'' construction, some consideration was given to deleting these guns and replacing them with {{convert|10.5|cm|abbr=on}} guns mounted on sponsons just below flight deck level. But the structural modifications needed to accommodate such a change were judged too difficult and time-consuming, requiring major changes to the ship’s design, and the matter was shelved.&lt;ref name=Breyer44&gt;Breyer, p.44&lt;/ref&gt;

Primary AA protection came from 12 {{convert|10.5|cm|abbr=on}} guns, paired in six turrets positioned three afore and three aft of the carrier’s island. Potential blast damage to planes sited on the flight deck when these guns fired to port was an unavoidable risk and would have limited any flight activity during an engagement.&lt;ref name=Brown10/&gt;

The ''Graf Zeppelin'' class's secondary AA defenses consisted of 11 twin {{convert|37|mm|abbr=on}} [[3.7 cm SK C/30|SK C/30]] guns mounted on sponsons located along the flight deck edges: four on the starboard side, six to port and one mounted on the ship's forecastle. In addition, seven {{convert|20|mm|abbr=on}} MG C/30 guns were installed on single-mount platforms on either side of the carrier: four to port and three to starboard. These guns were later changed to quadruple mountings.&lt;ref name=Breyer48&gt;Breyer, p.48&lt;/ref&gt;

==Flight testing at Travemünde==
In 1937, with ''Graf Zeppelin’s'' launch scheduled for the end of the following year, the Luftwaffe’s experimental test facility at Travemünde (''Erprobungsstelle'' See or ''E-Stelle'' See) on the Baltic coast began a lengthy program of testing prototype carrier aircraft. This included performing simulated carrier landings and take-offs and training future carrier pilots.&lt;ref name=Reynolds46&gt;Reynolds, p.46&lt;/ref&gt;

The runway was painted with a contoured outline of ''Graf Zeppelin’s'' flight deck and simulated deck landings were then conducted over an arresting cable strung width-wise across the airstrip. The cable was attached to an electromechanical braking device manufactured by DEMAG (Deutsche Maschinenfabrik A.G. Duisburg). Testing began in March 1938 using the [[Heinkel He 50]], [[Arado Ar 195]] and [[Ar 197]]. Later, a stronger braking winch was supplied by Atlas-Werke of Bremen and this allowed heavier aircraft, such as the Fieseler Fi 167 and Junkers Ju 87, to be tested.&lt;ref name=Israel66&gt;Israel, p.66&lt;/ref&gt; After some initial problems, Luftwaffe pilots performed 1,500 successful braked landings out of 1,800 attempted.&lt;ref name=Breyer66&gt;Breyer, p.66&lt;/ref&gt;

Launches were practiced using a {{convert|20|m|abbr=on}} long barge-mounted pneumatic catapult, moored in the Trave River estuary. The Heinkel-designed catapult, built by Deutsche Werke Kiel (DWK), could accelerate aircraft to speeds of {{convert|145|km/h|abbr=on}} depending on wind conditions. Test planes were first hoisted by crane onto collapsible launch carriages in the same manner as intended on ''Graf Zeppelin''.&lt;ref name=Breyer67&gt;Breyer, p.67&lt;/ref&gt;

The catapult test program began in April 1940 and, by early May, 36 launches had been conducted, all carefully documented and filmed for later study: 17 by Arado Ar 197s, 15 by modified Junkers Ju 87Bs and four using a modified Messerschmitt Bf 109D. Further testing followed and by June Luftwaffe officials were fully satisfied with the catapult system’s performance.&lt;ref name=Israel65&gt;Israel, p.65&lt;/ref&gt;

==Aircraft==
The expected role of the ''Graf Zeppelin'' class was that of a sea-going scouting platform and her initial planned air group reflected that emphasis: 20 [[Fieseler Fi 167]] biplanes for scouting and torpedo attack, 10 [[Messerschmitt Bf 109 variants#Bf 109T &quot;Trägerflugzeug&quot; (carrier aircraft)|Messerschmitt Bf 109]] fighters, and 13 [[Junkers Ju 87]] dive-bombers.&lt;ref name=Reynolds44/&gt; This was later changed to 30 Bf 109 fighters and 12 Ju 87 dive-bombers as carrier doctrine in Japan, Great Britain and the United States shifted away from purely reconnaissance duties towards offensive combat missions.&lt;ref name=Reynolds44/&gt;

===Messerschmitt Bf 109 T===
In late 1938, the Technische Amt RLM (Technical Office of the ''Reichsluftfahrtministerium'' or State Ministry of Aviation) requested that Messerschmitt’s Augsburg design bureau draw up plans for a carrier-borne version of the Bf 109 E fighter, to be designated Bf 109 T (the &quot;T&quot; standing for Träger or Carrier). The resulting aircraft, nicknamed 'Toni' by its pilots,&lt;ref name=Marshall16&gt;Marshall, p.16&lt;/ref&gt; was powered by a Daimler-Benz DB 601N 1,175 PS engine, giving it a maximum speed of {{convert|568|km/h|abbr=on}} at {{convert|20,000|ft|m}}. Armament comprised two fuselage-mounted {{convert|7.92|mm|abbr=on}} MG 17 machine guns with two additional MG 17s or 20mm MG FF/M cannons in the wings.&lt;ref name=Whitley162&gt;Whitley, p.162&lt;/ref&gt;

Wing area was increased through the addition of two {{convert|0.6|m|abbr=on}} outer panels, extending overall span to {{convert|11|m|abbr=on}}, and retractable spoilers were fitted to the upper wing surfaces. This significantly shortened the aircraft’s normal take-off and landing runs, improved low-speed stability and allowed for steeper glide angles.

[[Image:Bf109T 3Seiten neu.jpg|thumb|Bf 109T-1]]

Four catapult attachment points were added to the fuselage and an arrester hook to the tail.&lt;ref name=Green550&gt;Green, p.550&lt;/ref&gt; The arrester hooks were later widened to minimize bending of the arresting cables when landing. The hooks also tended to bounce against the fuselage, causing dents. This problem was remedied by incorporating a metal spring into the design and adding a rubber buffer pad to the rear fuselage.&lt;ref name=Marshall16&gt;Marshall, p.16&lt;/ref&gt;

An under-fuselage ETC rack was fitted for carrying a {{convert|300|L}} center-line drop-tank.&lt;ref name=Marshall17&gt;Marshall, p.17&lt;/ref&gt; The undercarriage oleo legs were also strengthened to better absorb the higher descent rates and greater stresses associated with carrier landings.&lt;ref name=Green550/&gt; Thicker head and armrest padding in the cockpit improved pilot comfort when making catapult launches. No provision was made for wing-folding on the Bf 109 T as it was considered unnecessary since the aircraft easily fit within the {{convert|14|m|abbr=on}} width of ''Graf Zeppelin's'' elevators.&lt;ref name=Marshall16/&gt;

After acceptance by the RLM in early 1939, the project was turned over to Fieseler-Werke for final details and the conversion of 60 Bf 109E airframes into T-1s. This order was progressively increased to 155 machines by September but, with work on ''Graf Zeppelin's'' sister carrier, ''Flugzeugträger B'', suspended that same month, planned production reverted to an initial batch of 70 aircraft. By December 1940, the RLM decided to complete only seven carrier-equipped Bf 109 T-1s and to finish the remainder as land-based T-2s since work on ''Graf Zeppelin'' had ceased back in April and there appeared to be little likelihood she would then be commissioned any time soon.&lt;ref name=Marshall24&gt;Marshall, p.24&lt;/ref&gt;

Due to delays in production of the Bf 109 E series in mid-1940, design alterations to the plane's wing spar and Daimler Benz's slow delivery of the promised DB 601N engines, the first Bf 109 T-1 was not delivered until January 1941. By June, however, all 70 machines were completed. One T-1 was sent to ''E-Stelle'' See in Travemünde for evaluation and six more were reserved for further testing. The remaining 63 T-2s were then ferried to Norway via Denmark and served in I/JG 77 and JGr Trondheim where their short take-off and landing characteristics made them ideally suited to that country’s small windswept airstrips.&lt;ref name=Breyer69&gt;Breyer, p.69&lt;/ref&gt;

At the end of 1941, when interest in completing ''Graf Zeppelin'' revived, the surviving Bf 109 T-2s were withdrawn from front-line service in order to again prepare them for possible carrier duty. Seven T-2s were rebuilt to T-1 standards and handed over to the Kriegsmarine on 19 May 1942. By December, a total of 48 Bf 109 T-2s had been converted back into T-1s. 46 of these were stationed at Pillau in East Prussia and reserved for use aboard the carrier. By February 1943, however, all work on ''Graf Zeppelin'' had ceased and the aircraft were returned to Luftwaffe service in April.&lt;ref name=Breyer69/&gt;

===Fieseler Fi 167===
In competition with Arado, Fieseler Werke submitted a design in 1937 at the request of the Technische Amt for a two-seater multi-purpose carrier plane capable of performing bombing, torpedo bombing and reconnaissance duties. Fieseler’s submission, the Fieseler Fi 167 (nicknamed “Dragonfly”) was a lean-looking biplane powered by an inline 1,100 PS Daimler-Benz DB601B engine. This gave it a maximum speed of {{convert|320|km/h|abbr=on}} and a much sleeker appearance than Arado’s radial-engined entry, the Ar 195. Fieseler's plane featured folding wings for carrier stowage, an arrester hook, an enclosed cockpit for a crew of two, a fixed undercarriage (which could be jettisoned in the event of an emergency water landing by electrically triggering two sets of spring-loaded bolts)&lt;ref name=Green169&gt;Green, p.169&lt;/ref&gt; and full-span automatic leading edge slats along the upper and lower wings, with the lower wings also sporting large trailing edge flaps. These latter features gave the plane unparalleled stability at low speeds.&lt;ref name=Breyer64&gt;Breyer, p.64&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:Bundesarchiv Bild 146-1977-110-06, Flugzeug Fieseler Fi 167.jpg|thumb|right|A Fieseler Fi 167, the fifth of 12 pre-production machines, banks through the clouds on a test flight.]]

Armament consisted of a maximum bomb load of one {{convert|1000|kg|abbr=on}} bomb or a standard {{convert|764|kg|abbr=on}} LT F 5b torpedo plus one forward-firing {{convert|7.92|mm|abbr=on}} MG 17 machine mounted over the engine cowling and one 7.92&amp;nbsp;mm MG 15 machine gun on a flexible mount in the rear cockpit to be operated by the observer/navigator. Normal operating range (with bomb load) was{{convert|1300|km|abbr=on}} but this could be extended to {{convert|1500|km|abbr=on}} for reconnaissance missions with the addition of a {{convert|300|L|abbr=on}} external drop-tank.&lt;ref name=Green170&gt;Green, p.170&lt;/ref&gt;

Comparative testing at the Luftwaffe's ''Erprobungsstelle'' [[Rechlin]] test facility quickly demonstrated the Fi 167's superiority to the Ar 195 in all respects, so much so that Fieseler opted to forego constructing a third prototype in order to begin assembly of twelve pre-production machines. Since ''Graf Zeppelin'' would not be ready for sea trials until summer 1940, however, work on the pre-production order proceeded at a desultory pace and it was not until spring 1940 that the first example, Fi 167 A-01, began flight testing.&lt;ref name=Green169/&gt;

When work on ''Graf Zeppelin'' was suspended in May 1940, the 12 completed Fi 167s were organized into ''Erprobungsstaffel'' 167 for the purpose of conducting further operational trials. By the time work on the carrier resumed two years later in May 1942, the Fi 167 was no longer considered adequate for its intended role and the Technische Amt decided to replace it with a modified torpedo-carrying version of the Junkers Ju 87D.&lt;ref name=Green169/&gt;

===Junkers Ju 87 C===
In 1938 the Technische Amt decided to include a squadron (''Staffel'') of dive-bombers in the ''Graf Zeppelins''' air groups, the obvious choice being the combat-proven Junkers Ju 87 Stuka. Work on converting the Ju 87 B into the carrier version Ju 87 C began later that year. Pre-production Ju 87Cs had manually folded wings, reducing carrier stowage width to just {{convert|5|m|abbr=on}}; production series aircraft featured an electrically actuated wing folding mechanism. Overall wingspan was {{convert|0.6|m|abbr=on}} shorter than the Ju 87 B. Catapult attachment points were added to the lower fuselage and an arrester hook was installed just forward of the tail wheel. The fuselage and landing gear were also strengthened to better withstand the stresses of carrier landings. The two propeller-driven sirens normally mounted on the Stuka’s fixed undercarriage legs were deleted, which helped reduce drag.&lt;ref name=Breyer72&gt;Breyer, p.72&lt;/ref&gt;

The Ju 87 C’s fixed landing gear could be jettisoned via explosive charges in the event it had to ditch over water. This would help minimize the likelihood of the plane flipping over as it touched down. Flotation bags in the body and wings of the plane were installed and sealants applied to seams and openings to delay the aircraft’s sinking should it be forced to make a water landing, thereby giving the crew sufficient time to exit the cockpit and deploy the inflatable rubber dinghy stowed on board for just such emergencies.&lt;ref name=Breyer72/&gt;

Internal fuel stowage was increased with the addition of two auxiliary wing tanks and could be further augmented by attaching two {{convert|300|l}} external drop-tanks to the wing undersides. This extended the aircraft’s maximum range to over {{convert|1100|km}}. In an emergency, all fuel could be dumped in approximately one minute.&lt;ref name=Breyer72/&gt;

Powered by a Junkers Jumo 211D 1,200 PS engine, the Ju 87 C had a top speed of {{convert|332|km/h|abbr=on}}. Armament comprised a maximum bomb load of {{convert|700|kg|abbr=on}}, two fixed forward-firing {{convert|7.92|mm|abbr=on}} MG 17 machine guns in the wings and one flexible 7.92&amp;nbsp;mm MG 15 machine gun mounted in the rear cockpit, manned by the navigator/radio operator.&lt;ref name=Israel79&gt;Israel, p.79&lt;/ref&gt;

Ten Ju 87 C-0 pre-production aircraft were built and sent to the testing facilities at Rechlin and Travemünde where they underwent extensive service trials, including catapult launches and simulated deck landings. But of the 170 Ju 87 C-1 ordered, only a few saw completion, suspension of work on ''Graf Zeppelin'' in May 1940 resulting in cancellation of the entire order. Existing aircraft and those airframes in process were eventually converted back into Ju 87 B-2s.&lt;ref name=Breyer72/&gt;

===Junkers Ju 87 E===
Work on developing a torpedo-carrying version of the Ju 87 D for anti-shipping sorties in the Mediterranean had already commenced in early 1942 when the possibility again arose that ''Graf Zeppelin'' might be completed. As the Fieseler Fi 167 was now considered obsolete, the Technische Amt requested that Junkers modify the Ju 87 D-4 into a carrier-borne torpedo-bomber/recon plane to be designated Ju 87 E-1. Production aircraft would have electrically actuated folding wings and receive the same carrier fittings as applied to the Ju 87 C as well as attachment points for a {{convert|764|kg|abbr=on}} LT F 5b torpedo. Consideration was also given to fitting the aircraft with rocket-assisted take-off gear (RATOG) in order to shorten its take-off run on the carrier.&lt;ref name=Breyer73&gt;Breyer, p.73&lt;/ref&gt;

Testing was conducted in the spring and summer of 1942 at ''Erprobungsstelle'' See in Travemünde and the results were sufficiently satisfactory that the RLM issued an order for 115 machines. But when all further work on ''Graf Zeppelin'' was halted for good in February 1943, the entire order was canceled. None of the Ju 87 Ds converted to carry a torpedo were used operationally.&lt;ref name=Breyer73/&gt;

===Messerschmitt Me 155===
By May 1942, when work was ordered resumed on ''Graf Zeppelin'', the older Bf 109T carrier-borne fighter was considered obsolete. Consequently, the Technische Amt invited Messerschmitt A.G. to submit new design proposals for a shipboard fighter designated [[Blohm &amp; Voss BV 155|Me 155]]. Emphasis was placed on using current Bf 109 components for ease of manufacturing and to limit the workload on Messerschmitt's busy design staff. By September 1942 detailed plans were completed.&lt;ref name=Green88&gt;Green, p.88&lt;/ref&gt;

The Me 155 utilized a standard Bf 109 G airframe wedded to a newly designed wing, capable of  folding for carrier stowage. The wing retained the same span as that of the Bf 109 G, {{convert|11|m|abbr=on}}, however the designers replaced the Bf 109 G's narrow outward-retracting main landing gear with a wide-track inward-retracting undercarriage, giving the plane more stable landing characteristics. This was especially desirable in an aircraft expected to negotiate the restricted width of a pitching carrier deck. Catapult attachment points, an arrester hook and flotation gear were also added. Proposed armament consisted of an engine-mounted {{convert|20|mm|abbr=on}} MG 151 cannon plus two 20&amp;nbsp;mm MG 151s and two {{convert|13|mm|abbr=on}} MG 131 machine guns in the wings. Powered by a DB 605A-1 engine rated at 1,475 PS, the aircraft was expected to attain a top speed of {{convert|649|km/h|abbr=on}} with a calculated endurance of 1.16 hours (minus external drop-tank).&lt;ref name=Green88/&gt;

When it became apparent ''Graf Zeppelin'' would not be commissioned for at least another two years, Messerschmitt was unofficially told to shelve the projected fighter design. No prototype of the carrier-borne version of the plane was ever constructed.&lt;ref name=Green88/&gt;

==Air units==
On 1 August, 1938, four months prior to ''Graf Zeppelin's'' launch date, the ''Luftwaffe'' formed its first carrier-based air unit, designated ''Trägergruppe I/186'', on Rugia Island near Burg. It was composed of three squadrons (''Staffeln'') and was intended to serve aboard both carriers when completed. By October, however, shipyard construction delays resulted in disbandment of the air group as it was considered too large and costly to maintain given the uncertainty over when the two vessels would be ready for sea trials. Instead, on 1 November that same year a single fighter squadron (''Trägerjagdstaffel'') was created, 6./186, and placed under the command of Cpt. Heinrich Seeliger. Later, a dive-bomber squadron was added, 4./186, equipped with Ju 87Bs under Cpt. Blattner. Six months after, in July 1939, a second fighter squadron was formed, 5./186, under ''Oberleutnant'' Gerhard Kadow and partly staffed with pilots culled from 6./186. By August the three squadrons were reorganised into ''Trägergruppe II/186'' under the command of Major Walter Hagen in anticipation that ''Graf Zeppelin'' would be ready for service trials by the summer of 1940.&lt;ref name=Breyer55&gt;Breyer, p.55&lt;/ref&gt;

==Ships in class==
[[File:Bundesarchiv Bild 134-B0676, Flugzeugträger &quot;Graf Zeppelin&quot;.jpg|thumb|''Graf Zeppelin'' moored at [[Szczecin|Stettin]], mid-1941. The improved &quot;Atlantic prow&quot;, the two empty openings for the 15cm (5.9-inch) gun casemates (just below and forward of the funnel), the telescoping masts and the ends of the twin catapult tracks on the flight deck are all visible.]]

Construction on the Kriegsmarine's two aircraft carriers had been fitful from the start due to a shortage of welders and delays in obtaining materials. 

===''Flugzeugträger A'' ([[German aircraft carrier Graf Zeppelin|''Graf Zeppelin'']])===
Work started on ''Flugzeugträger A'' in 1936. She was laid down on 28 December that year, and launched on 8 December 1938. However she was incomplete by April 1940, when a changed strategic situation led to work on her being suspended.&lt;ref name=Whitley30&gt;Whitley, p.30&lt;/ref&gt; However by the spring of 1942 the usefulness of aircraft carriers in modern naval warfare had been amply demonstrated, and on 13 May 1942, with Hitler's authorization, the German Naval Supreme Command ordered work resumed on the carrier.&lt;ref name=Reynolds47&gt;Reynolds, p.47&lt;/ref&gt;

With technical problems, such as the demand for newer planes specifically designed for carrier use, and  the need for modernization, progress was delayed. The German naval staff hoped all these changes could be accomplished by April 1943, with the carrier's first sea trials taking place in August that same year. However, by late January 1943 Hitler had become so disenchanted with the [[Kriegsmarine]], especially with what he perceived as the poor performance of its surface fleet, that he ordered all of its larger ships taken out of service and scrapped. As of 2 February 1943, construction on the carrier ended for good.

''Graf Zeppelin'' languished for the next two years in various Baltic ports. On 25 April 1945 she was scuttled at Stettin, ahead of the advancing [[Red Army]].&lt;ref name=Breyer32&gt;Breyer, p.32&lt;/ref&gt;

=== ''Flugzeugträger B'' ===
Work on ''Flugzeugträger B'' began in 1938 but was halted on 19 September 1939 because, now that Germany was at war with Great Britain and France, priority had shifted to [[U-boat]] construction. The hull, completed only up to the armored deck, sat rusting on its slipway until 28 February 1940, when Admiral Raeder ordered her broken up and scrapped.&lt;ref name=Breyer14&gt;Breyer, p.14&lt;/ref&gt; Scrapping was completed four months later.

==See also==
* [[List of aircraft carriers]]
* [[List of World War II ships]]
* [[List of naval ships of Germany]]
* [[List of naval ship classes of Germany]]
* [[List of Kriegsmarine ships]]
* [[List of ship launches in 1938]]
* [[Flugzeugträger B]] - ''Graf Zeppelin'''s sister ship

== References ==
{{reflist|colwidth=30em}}

== Bibliography ==
{{refbegin}}
* {{cite journal|author=Barker, Lt. Cmdr Edward L. |title=War Without Aircraft Carriers |publisher=United States Naval Institute Proceedings |month=March | year=1954}}
* {{cite book|last=Breyer |first=Siegfried |title=The German Aircraft Carrier Graf Zeppelin |location=Atglen, Pennsylvania |publisher=Schiffer Publishing Ltd |year=1989}}
* {{cite book|last=Breyer |first=Siegfried |title=Encyclopedia of Warships 42: Graf Zeppelin |location=Gdansk |publisher=A.J. Press |year=2004}}
* {{cite book|last=Brown |first=David |title=WWII Fact Files: Aircraft Carriers |location=New York |publisher=Arco Publishing |year=1977}}
* {{cite book|last=Burke |first=Stephen |title=Without Wings: The Story of Hitler's Aircraft Carrier |publisher=Trafford Publishing |year=Sept 2007 |isbn= 1425122167}}
* {{cite book|last=Green |first=William |title=The Warplanes of the Third Reich |location=New York |publisher=Doubleday and Company, Inc|year=1979}}
* {{cite book|last=Green|first=William|authorlink= |coauthors= Gordon Swanborough|title=The Complete Book of Fighters |publisher=Salamander Books |year=1994|isbn=0-8317-3939-8}}
* {{cite book|last=Israel |first=Ulrich H.-J. |title=Graf Zeppelin: Einziger Deutscher Flugzeugträger |location=Hamburg |publisher=Verlag Koehler/Mittler |year=1994}}
* {{cite journal|author=Israel, Ulrich H.-J. |title=&quot;Flugdeck klar!&quot; Deutsche Trägerflugzeuge bis 1945 |publisher=Flieger Revue Extra |year=2003}}
* {{cite book|last=Lake| first=Jon|title=Lancaster Squadrons 1942-43|publisher=Osprey|year=2002|isbn=1841763136}}
* {{cite book|last=Marshall |first=Francis L. |title=Sea Eagles - The Operational History of the Messerschmitt Bf 109T |location=Walton on Thames, Surrey, UK |publisher=Air Research Publications |year=1994}}
* {{cite journal|author=Reynolds, Clark G. |title=Hitler's Flattop: The End of the Beginning |publisher=United States Naval Institute Proceedings |month=January | year=1967}}
* {{cite book|last=Smith |first=Peter C. |title=Junkers Ju 87 Stuka |location=Ramsbury |publisher=The Crowood Press |year=1998}}
* {{cite journal|author=Whitley, M.J. |title=Warship 31: Graf Zeppelin, Part 1 |location=London |publisher=Conway Maritime Press Ltd |month=July | year=1984}}
* {{cite book|author=Whitley, M.J. |title=Warship 33, Vol IX: Graf Zeppelin, Part 2 |location=London |publisher=Conway Maritime Press Ltd | year=1985}}
{{refend}}

==External links==
{{Commons|German aircraft carrier Graf Zeppelin}}
* [http://www.bundesarchiv.de/aktuelles/aus_dem_archiv/galerie/00159/index.html ''Graf Zeppelin'' images from Bundesarchiv Freiburg] (text in German but lots of images)
*[http://www.maritimequest.com/warship_directory/germany/pages/aircraft_carriers/graf_zeppelin.htm Maritimequest ''Graf Zeppelin'' photo gallery]
* [http://www.spiegel.de/international/0,1518,428857,00.html &quot;''Graf Zeppelin'' Rediscovered&amp;mdash;Hitler's Showpiece Aircraft Carrier Found.&quot;] Spiegel Online International article dated 27-7-2006. Retrieved 20-9-2010.

{{Coord|55|31|03|N|18|17|09|E|type:landmark|display=title}}

{{Graf Zeppelin class aircraft carrier}}
{{WWIIGermanShips}}

[[Category:Aircraft carrier classes]]
[[Category:Graf Zeppelin class aircraft carriers| ]]
[[Category:Proposed aircraft carriers]]
[[Category:Plan Z]]

[[de:Graf-Zeppelin-Klasse]]
[[hr:Nosači zrakoplova klase Graf Zeppelin]]
[[ru:Авианосцы типа «Граф Цеппелин»]]
[[sv:Graf Zeppelin-klass]]
[[vi:Graf Zeppelin (lớp tàu sân bay)]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
