<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="12761868" ns="0" title="Kuruvi"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Refimprove|date=May 2010}}
{{Infobox film
| name =Kuruvi
| image = Kuruvi poster.jpg
| caption = Tagline: Where Eagles Dare
| director = [[Dharani (director)|Dharani]]
| producer = [[Udhayanidhi Stalin]]
| writer = [[Dharani (director)|Dharani]]
| starring = [[Joseph Vijay]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Trisha Krishnan]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Suman (actor)|Suman]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Vivek (actor)|Vivek]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Ashish Vidyarthi]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Malavika]]&lt;br&gt;[[Saranya Ponvannan]]
| music = [[Vidyasagar (music director)|Vidyasagar]]
| cinematography = [[Gopinath]]
| editing =
| distributor = [[Udhayanidhi Stalin|Red Giant Movies]]
| released = 3 May 2008
| country = {{Film India}}
| language = [[Tamil language|Tami]]
}}
'''''Kuruvi''''' ({{lang-ta| குருவி}}; {{lang-en|Sparrow}}) is a [[2008 in film|2008]] [[Tamil language|Tamil]] [[Action film]]. Directed and co-written by [[Dharani (director)|Dharani]] and produced by Udhayanidhi Stalin, it stars [[Joseph Vijay]], [[Trisha Krishnan]] and [[Suman (actor)|Suman]] in the lead roles. [[Vivek (actor)|Vivek]], [[Ashish Vidyarthi]], [[Manivannan]] and [[Malavika]] played other roles in the movie.

The film revolves around a son who declares revenge on the villain, who betrayed and caused the mysterious disappearance of his father by stealing a diamond. The son in his attempt to recover his dues ends up stealing the villain’s precious diamond and also wins the heart of his sister, who runs away with him to Chennai to avoid a marriage with her brother’s henchman.

The film opened to Indian audiences after several delays, on 3 May 2008 to negative reviews.

==Plot==
Varadharajan ([[Joseph Vijay]]) is a brave young man who lives with his large family in Chennai. His father is out of station on business and he comes to know that a gentleman named Koccha ([[Suman]]) owes his father a huge sum of money. Finding that Koccha is based in Malaysia, Vetrivel and vivek fly to [[Malaysia]], as 'Kuruvi' (courier), the trade jargon for low-level contraband carriers. He steps into the group at a time when internal rivalry and problems are surfacing in Koccha's family. Koccha's darling sister Devi ([[Trisha Krishnan]]) has refused to marry her cousin, the boy approved by her family members. Irritated and preoccupied, nobody wants to devote any time or attention to resolve Vetrivel's problem. Vetrivel is abused, harassed, suffers more ill-treatment and is thrown out of Koccha's place without any help rendered. These callous actions enrage the young man. Totally enraged, with a do-or-die attitude, deciding to get his work done no matter who gets hurt, Vetri becomes a veritable suicide machine and launches into a terrific scuffle with the dangerous gang. Determined to return only after the issue is solved to his satisfaction, motivated by an urge to reveal the truth, Vetrivel conceals himself in Koccha's palace-like residence. He returns to India after stealing a large diamond that was in Koccha's possession.

Devi follows Varadharajan and comes to India too. Knowing that Varadharajan has taken his diamond Koccha and his gang visit Varadharajan's house and threaten his family. After confronting Koccha, Varadharajan comes to know that his father [[Manivannan]] is held as bonded labor along with many innocent people in Kadapa.

The rest of the film is how Kuruvi goes to [[Kadapa]], [[Andhra Pradesh]] and discovers a slave camp run by Kocha and his associate Konda Reddy ([[Ashish Vidyarthi]]), at the collieries and also finds his long lost father. Kuruvi single handedly takes on the mining mafia and finally annihilates them.

==Cast==

* [[Joseph Vijay]] as Vetrivel
* [[Trisha Krishnan]] as Devi
* [[Vivek (actor)|Vivek]] as Ops, Vetrivel's sidekick
* [[Suman (actor)|Suman]] as Koccha
* [[Manivannan]] as Singamuthu.
* [[Ashish Vidyarthi]] as Konda Reddy
* [[Nassar]] as Raj, the general of the police encounter squad targeting businesses (cameo appearance)
* [[Malavika]] in a [[cameo appearance]] in the song &quot;Dandaana Darna&quot;
* [[Saranya Ponvannan]] as Koccha's wife and Devi's sister-in-law.
* [[Niveda]] as Vijay's Sister

==Release and Reception==
This film got mixed reviews from the major review generators. But the opening of the film was really big because of the [[Ghilli]] team.This film's budjet was {{INR}}18 crore and its boxoffice collection was around {{INR}}30 crore.The film ran for 150 days in the box office.After the big opening this film was declared a hit in BoxOffice.

==Snippets==

'''''Kuruvi''''' has uncredited cameos by ''[[Vimal]]'' and ''Vidharth'', who later became full fledged heroes with hit movies ''[[Pasanga]]'' and ''[[Mynaa]]'' respectively.

==Soundtrack==
{{Infobox album | &lt;!-- See Wikipedia:WikiProject_Albums --&gt;
| Name       = Kuruvi
| Type       = [[Soundtrack]]
| Artist     = [[Vidyasagar (music director)|Vidyasagar]]
| Cover      =
| Released   = 2008
| Recorded   =
| Genres     = [[World Music]]
| Length     =
| Label      =
| Producer   = [[Vidyasagar (music director)|Vidyasagar]]
| Last album = ''[[Mulla (film)|Mulla]]''&lt;br /&gt;(2008)
| This album = '''''Kuruvi'''''&lt;br /&gt;(2008)
| Next album = ''[[Neelathaamara (2009)| Neelathaamara]]''&lt;br /&gt;(2009)
}}
=== Track listing ===
{| border=&quot;2&quot; cellpadding=&quot;4&quot; cellspacing=&quot;0&quot; style=&quot;margin: 1em 1em 1em 0; background: #f9f9f9; border: 1px #aaa solid; border-collapse: collapse; font-size: 95%;&quot;
|- bgcolor=&quot;#CCCCCF&quot; align=&quot;center&quot;
| '''No.''' || '''Song''' || '''Singers''' || '''Length (min:sec)'''
|-1
| 1|| &quot;Happy New Year&quot; || Yogi B, Dr. Burn, Mc.jazz, [[Sunidhi Chauhan]] || 04:05
|-
| 2|| &quot;Dandaana Darna&quot; || Sangeeth Althipur || 03:40
|-
| 3|| &quot;Thaen Thaen Thaen&quot; || [[Udit Narayan]], [[Shreya Ghoshal]] || 03:38
|-
| 4|| &quot;Palaanadhu Palaanadhu&quot; || [[Vidyasagar (music director)|Vidyasagar]] and [[Rajalakshmi]] || 04:05
|-
| 5|| &quot;Theme Music&quot; || Praveen Mani, Dr. Burn, Ranina, Suvi || 02:00
|-
| 6|| &quot;Mozha Mozhannu&quot; || [[KK]], [[Anuradha Sriram]] || 03:55
|}

==References==
{{Reflist}}
{{Use dmy dates|date=August 2011}}


[[Category:Tamil-language films]]
[[Category:Indian films]]
[[Category:2008 films]]

[[fr:Kuruvi]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
