<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="1278092" ns="0" title="McMurry University"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{About|the university in Abilene, Texas|MacMurray College in Jacksonville, Illinois|MacMurray College}}

{{Infobox university
|name = McMurry University
|image = [[File:McMurryUniversity.png]]
|motto =
|established = 1923
|type = [[Private school|Private]] [[University]]
|affiliations = [[United Methodist]]
|president = Dr. John H. Russell
|city = [[Abilene, Texas|Abilene]]
|state = [[Texas]]
|country = [[United States]]
|undergrad = 1,430
|endowment = USD $52.0 million&lt;ref&gt;As of June 30, 2009.  {{Cite web| title = U.S. and Canadian Institutions Listed by Fiscal Year 2009 Endowment Market Value and Percentage Change in Endowment Market Value from FY 2008 to FY 2009| work = 2009 NACUBO-Commonfund Study of Endowments | publisher = National Association of College and University Business Officers | url = http://www.nacubo.org/Documents/research/2009_NCSE_Public_Tables_Endowment_Market_Values.pdf| format = PDF | accessdate = February 24, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|nickname = [[War Hawks]] &lt;small&gt;&lt;/small&gt;
|campus = [[Urban area|Urban]], 40 acres (.16 km²)
|website = [http://www.mcm.edu/ www.mcm.edu]
}}

'''McMurry University''', founded in 1923, is a private [[co-educational]] [[university]] in [[Abilene, Texas]]. It is a [[liberal arts]] school offering forty-one majors in the fields of [[fine arts]], [[humanities]], [[social sciences|social]] and [[natural sciences]], [[education]], [[business]], and [[religion]], and nine pre-professional programs, including pre-engineering, [[nursing]], [[dentistry]], [[medicine]], [[pharmacy]], [[veterinary]], and [[law]]. McMurry is affiliated with the [[United Methodist]] church.

McMurry has roughly 1,430 students.  Methodist students comprise 27 percent of the student population. Ninety five percent of students are [[Texas|Texan]].  [[minority group|Minority]] groups make up approximately one-fourth of the student body. In the [[freshman]] class, 98 percent of students receive some [[Student financial aid|financial aid]]. Fifty-three percent of students live on campus, and 75 percent of students are involved in at least one [[extracurricular]] activity.

More than 80 percent of the [[Faculty (teaching staff)|faculty]] have earned a [[doctorate]] or other terminal degree in their field.  McMurry is accredited by the Commission on Colleges of the Southern Association of Colleges and Schools, the [[Texas Education Agency]], the University Senate of the United Methodist Church, the National League for Nursing, and the Texas State Board of Nurse Examiners.

McMurry has been recognized annually since 1996 by [[U.S. News &amp; World Report]] for quality and value in the Southwest division of third tier schools.  Recent graduates have gained admission to graduate and professional schools at nationally prominent institutions, including Harvard, Yale, Princeton, Duke, Vanderbilt, SMU, Baylor, and the University of Texas.  McMurry's honors program offers academic scholarships ranging up to full-tuition for four years to outstanding students.  

==Indians mascot controversy==
In late August 2005, the [[National Collegiate Athletic Association]] (NCAA) handed down a decision calling for the eighteen universities with [[Native Americans in the United States|Native American]] [[mascot]]s to change their names or obtain a waiver from their representative tribe for the use of the mascot name. The McMurry Indians were part of this list.  The Indians nickname was chosen as a tribute to the University's first president, [[J.W. Hunt]], who grew up on an Indian Reservation in the [[Indian Territory]].

On May 18, 2006, the NCAA rejected McMurry's appeal to keep their nickname. The school has chosen to appeal the ruling, and indicated their intention to do so by the June 18, 2006 deadline. According to a press release, &quot;the University’s appeal will be based on the arbitrariness of the NCAA’s decision-making process and the inconsistent results and messages that have come from the process.&quot;  Other schools, such as [[Florida State University]], have made successful appeals by garnering the endorsement of Indian tribes.  Although McMurry has not actively sought an endorsement, representatives from the [[Kaw (tribe)|Kaw]], [[Kiowa]], and [[Comanche]] tribes have voiced their approval of McMurry's mascot.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.mcm.edu/newsite/web/univ_relations/NCAAletter.htm|title=Alumni Update|work=mcm.edu|author=Russell, John H. Ph.D.|accessdate=2006-09-07}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In October 2006, McMurry's Board of Trustees decided that the university would no longer use any names for its athletic teams.  Citing the school's 83-year history of honoring Native Americans, the school announced that in spite of no longer using names to designate athletic teams, the school traditions created to honor Native Americans will continue.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.mcm.edu/newsite/web/univ_relations/NCAA.htm|title=McMurry Board Announces Decision|work=mcm.edu|author=Russell, John H. Ph.D.|accessdate=2006-10-18}}&lt;/ref&gt; The school's stadium has now been changed from Indian Stadium to [[Wilford Moore Stadium]], as of Sunday May 13, 2007. [[Wilford Moore]] was the highest winning coach in McMurry football history.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.mcm.edu/athletics/051307.html|title=McMurry renames football and track stadium to Wilford Moore Stadium|work=mcm.edu|accessdate=2007-05-13}} {{Dead link|date=September 2010|bot=H3llBot}}&lt;/ref&gt;
on March 11, 2011 it was announced that McMurry University's athletic teams would be known as the War Hawks. The new mascot was chosen after a nearly year-long search to find a new mascot to replace the former Indian mascot, which had been taken away by the NCAA in 2006.  The war hawk is meant to represent pride, courage and fierce competition for McMurry's athletic teams.

==Athletics==
McMurry's school colors are [[Maroon (color)|maroon]] and [[White (color)|white]].  All teams play in the NCAA [[Division III]] [[American Southwest Conference]]. McMurry fields teams in 19 different intercollegiate sports. For the men, McMurry competes in [[baseball]], [[basketball]], [[cross country running|cross country]], [[American football|football]], [[golf]], [[soccer]], [[swimming (sport)|swimming]], [[tennis]] and indoor and outdoor [[Athletics (track and field)|track and field]].  For the women, McMurry competes in basketball, cross country, golf, soccer, swimming, tennis, indoor and outdoor track and field and [[volleyball]].

McMurry University is transitioning to play in the [[Division II (NCAA)|Division II]]. In July 2011,  the school announced that it had been accepted as candidate for D-II membership and would join the Heartland Conference in the fall of 2012.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.mcmurrysports.com/news/2011/7/12/GEN_0712111147.aspx NCAA accepts McMurry's application to transition to Division II  - www.mcmurrysports.com - July 12, 2011]&lt;/ref&gt; This move will strengthen McMurry's cross-town rivalry with [[Abilene Christian University]],  a member of the D-II [[Lone Star Conference]].

==Notable alumni==
*[[Grant Teaff]]
: former head football coach for [[Baylor University]], and executive director for the [[American Football Coaches Association]]&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://baylorbears.cstv.com/sports/m-footbl/spec-rel/092105aaa.html|title=Grant Teaff To Receive Stagg Award|work=Baylor Football|date=2005-09-21|accessdate=2006-09-07}}&lt;/ref&gt;.   Member of College Football Hall of Fame
*[[Sarah Weddington]]
:[[Attorney at law (United States)|attorney]] for [[John Doe|Jane Roe]] ([[Norma McCorvey]]) in ''[[Roe v. Wade]]''&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.weddingtoncenter.com/earlyyears.html|title=Early Years|work=The Weddington Center|accessdate=2006-09-07 |archiveurl = http://web.archive.org/web/20060319084436/http://www.weddingtoncenter.com/earlyyears.html &lt;!-- Bot retrieved archive --&gt; |archivedate = 2006-03-19}}&lt;/ref&gt; and the first woman elected to the [[Texas House of Representatives]]
*Chuck Fallon
: president of [[Burger King]]'s North America division, Bloomberg Business Week&lt;ref&gt;http://investing.businessweek.com/research/stocks/people/person.asp?personId=11778674&amp;ticker=BKC:US&lt;/ref&gt;
* Larry Conlee
: COO, Engineering and Manufacturing at [[Research In Motion]]&lt;ref&gt;http://investing.businessweek.com/research/stocks/people/person.asp?personId=1504276&amp;ticker=RIMM:US&lt;/ref&gt;
*Jerry Campbell
: President, [[Claremont School of Theology]] &lt;ref&gt;
http://www.cst.edu/academics/faculty/profile/jerry-campbell &lt;/ref&gt;

==Notable faculty==
* Virgil Bottom
: Faculty from 1958 to 1973.  Pioneer in quartz crystal research and science advisor to President Eisenhower.  Several of his students would later become leaders in Hewlett-Packard, Motorola, and Quartzdyne.
*[[William Curry Holden]]
: historian and [[archeologist]], founder of the McMurry History Department and the [[West Texas Historical Association]]; later, first director of the [[Museum of Texas Tech University]] in [[Lubbock, Texas|Lubbock]]
*[[Lou Halsell Rodenberger]]
: Author of women's history and literature.
* Donald S. Frazier
: Author and historian of the Civil War in the Trans-Mississippi and Texas history.  A highly acclaimed educational entrepreneur, he started the [http://www.mcwhiney.org/index.html McWhiney Foundation] and became active in historic preservation and publishing including work with [[Frontier Texas!|Frontier Texas]], [[Buffalo Gap Historic Village|The Buffalo Gap Historic Village]], The Texas Frontier Heritage and Cultural Center, and State House Press.
* Stephen L. Hardin
: Historian and author of Texas history, member of the [[Texas Institute of Letters]], Fellow of the [[Texas State Historical Association]].
*C. Jeffery Kinlaw
: Philosopher and noted scholar of German Idealism.
*John-Eric Swenson
: Psychologist and former Chair of the Board of the Christian Association for Psychological Studies.

==References==
{{Reflist}}

==External links==
*[http://www.mcm.edu/ McMurry University]

{{Private colleges and universities in Texas}}
{{MethodistColleges}}
{{American Southwest Conference}}
{{Heartland Conference}}

{{Coord missing|Texas}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Mcmurry University}}
[[Category:McMurry University| ]]
[[Category:Educational institutions established in 1923]]
[[Category:Universities and colleges in Texas]]
[[Category:Council of Independent Colleges]]
[[Category:National Association of Independent Colleges and Universities members]]
[[Category:Education in Taylor County, Texas]]
[[Category:Education in Abilene, Texas]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
