<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="12797932" ns="0" title="List of EastEnders characters (1990)"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{DISPLAYTITLE:List of ''EastEnders'' characters (1990)}}
The following is a list of characters that first appeared in the [[BBC]] [[soap opera]] ''[[EastEnders]]'' in 1990, by order of first appearance.
{{TOC limit|limit=2}}

==Harry Osborne==
{{redirect|Harry Osborne|the [[Marvel Comics]] character|Harry Osborn}}
{{Infobox soap character 2 | series = EastEnders
|image=
|name=Harry Osborne
|portrayer=[[John Boswall]]
|years=1990
|first=23 January 1990
|last=22 February 1990
|death=22 February 1990
|occupation=[[Retirement|Retired]]
}}
In January 1990 a mysterious old man was seen lingering around [[Albert Square]]. He was initially reluctant to divulge his identity, but it was apparent that he knew some of the residents, in particular the [[Beale family]]. Café worker [[Rod Norman]] and his girlfriend Hazel took an interest in the man, whose name was later revealed to be '''Harry Osborne'''. They discovered that he had travelled the world before his recent return to Walford. Hazel — spurred on by Harry's tales — left Rod to do some travelling of her own.

Harry was seen regularly over the following weeks, mysteriously enquiring about old faces on the Square and cryptically turning up at the [[infant baptism|christening]] of [[Steven Beale]], much to the bemusement of everyone else. Rod found out that he had once been the boyfriend of [[Lou Beale]]'s sister, Doris. Lou had died in 1988, but Harry was persuaded to pay her daughter [[Pauline Fowler|Pauline]] a visit to find out about Doris. He knocked on her door, but fearfully fled before she answered. It soon became clear that Harry's past wasn't the only thing troubling him, he was also suffering from ill health and was seen clutching his chest in obvious pain. One cold, rainy afternoon, Harry sat in pain on a bench in Albert Square gardens, where he died. His body was found by [[Willy (EastEnders)|Willy]], [[Ethel Skinner]]'s dog. Ethel recognised Harry and seemed to know a lot about his history.

She revealed that Harry had grown up at number 29 Albert Square and when he was 15 years old he had fallen in love with Doris and vowed to marry her. However when the [[Second World War]] broke, he was [[conscription|conscripted]] into the [[army]] and sent to war. Doris promised to wait until Harry returned, but he was later reported [[missing in action]] and presumed dead. Doris subsequently married another man named Morris Miller. When Harry returned he managed to find employment working on the [[Dock (maritime)|dock]]s, where he occasionally got his hands on scarce food items, which he smuggled out and shared with his neighbours. On one occasion he gave some [[meat]] to a nine year old girl. However the meat turned out to be unsanitary and it accidentally poisoned her. She died and Harry fled the country in shame amidst accusations of murder. He had spent over 40 years in self-imposed exile and it seemed that Harry had only come back to his childhood home to die.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;[http://walford.net/cgi-bin/profile.pl?record=0425 Harry Osborne]&quot;, ''Walford.net''. URL last accessed on 2007-03-25.&lt;/ref&gt; Harry's death upset Rod and he left Walford soon after to travel the world.
{{-}}

==Phil Mitchell==
{{Main|Phil Mitchell}}
'''Phil Mitchell''' is played by [[Steve McFadden]]. Phil first arrived in [[Albert Square]] on 20 February 1990, and was soon joined by his brother, [[Grant Mitchell (EastEnders)|Grant]], sister [[Sam Mitchell (EastEnders)|Sam]] and  mother [[Peggy Mitchell|Peggy]]. He has become one of the soap's most popular characters and is the second longest-running male protagonist to appear in the serial. He was first introduced as the lesser of two thugs, but became a darker character after Grant left. More recent storylines, such as the return of his son [[Ben Mitchell (EastEnders)|Ben]], have shown a softer side to the character. In 2010, McFadden was given six weeks off EastEnders, so he could appear in pantomime.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.digitalspy.co.uk/soaps/s2/eastenders/news/a212545/mcfadden-given-special-leave-from-enders.html|title=McFadden 'given special leave' from 'Enders|last=Millar|first=Paul|date=5 April 2010|publisher=[[Digital Spy]]|accessdate=5 April 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; He has, at various times, owned many businesses in the Square. He has been married three times and featured in numerous high profile storylines, including the much-hyped [[whodunnit]], dubbed &quot;[[Who Shot Phil?]]&quot;—when the character was gunned down outside his home – and an affair with his brother's wife, dubbed &quot;[[Sharongate]]&quot;.

==Bev Williams==
{{Infobox soap character 2 
|series = EastEnders
|name=Bev Williams
|portrayer=Uncredited (1990) &lt;br/&gt; [[Diane Langton]] (1998–99)
|years=1990, 1998–99
|first=20 February 1990
|last=10 August 1999
|husband=Tom Williams
|daughters=[[Cindy Beale]] &lt;br/&gt; [[Gina Williams]]
|grandsons=[[Steven Beale]] &lt;br/&gt; [[Peter Beale]]
|granddaughters=[[Lucy Beale]] &lt;br/&gt; [[Cindy Williams (EastEnders)|Cindy Williams]]
}}
'''Bev Williams''' is the mother of [[Cindy Beale]] ([[Michelle Collins]]). Bev was originally called Lucy and Cindy names her daughter after her in 1994,&lt;ref&gt;&quot;[http://www.walford.net/update/19940113.htm 13-JAN-94]&quot;, ''walford.net''. URL last accessed 2007-02-07.&lt;/ref&gt; however from 1998 she was referred to as Bev. During the 1980s, Bev owned a hat stall on Turpin road market, which Cindy ran for her in 1988. Bev and her husband then moves to [[Devon]] and her pitch on the market was taken over by [[Laurie Bates]] in 1989. Bev remained unseen until February 1990, when she and her husband attends their grandson [[Steven Beale]]'s (Edward Farrell) christening. At the end of 1990, Cindy, [[Simon Wicks]] ([[Nick Berry]]) and Steven moves away from London to stay with Bev in Devon.

Bev is not seen again until November 1998, when Cindy's former husband, [[Ian Beale]] ([[Adam Woodyatt]]), meets her at the coroner's office following Cindy's death. She has been estranged from her daughter until a few months before she died, when Cindy contacted her asking for money. She could not give Cindy any money however, as her husband, Tom, had left her that year. Ian gives her a lift to the hospital to see Cindy's newborn baby, [[Cindy Williams (EastEnders)|Cindy]] (Ella Wortley), and she tries to get him to take the child in as his own, threatening to put the baby into care. However, custody of the baby is eventually given to Bev's other daughter [[#Gina Williams|Gina Williams]] ([[Nicola Cowper]]), who lives with her mother in Devon. Bev appears at Cindy's funeral, and later in August 1999 when Ian visits her and Gina to watch the eclipse. She persuades [[Melanie Owen]] ([[Tamzin Outhwaite]]) to propose to Ian, as Gina was trying to split them up. Even though in 2007, Gina and Cindy Jr only appeared without Bev. In August 2010, her granddaughter [[Lucy Beale]] ([[Melissa Suffield]]) moves to Devon to live with Bev. Four months later, her grandson [[Peter Beale]] ([[Thomas Law]]) goes to live with her.
{{-}}

==Grant Mitchell==
{{Main|Grant Mitchell (EastEnders)}}
'''Grant Mitchell''' was played by [[Ross Kemp]]. Grant first appeared in 1990, introduced by producer [[Michael Ferguson (director)|Michael Ferguson]] to revamp the show. Kemp remained until 1999 when he opted to leave. In 2005 and 2006, Kemp was persuaded to return to the role for brief stints during a period of heavy media criticism aimed at ''EastEnders''. The return proved to be a ratings success, though Kemp has since been skeptical about the possibility of another return. A popular character, prominent in the series, Grant is portrayed as a tough persona, known for his fiery temper and his tendency to resort to violence. Family is important to him, particularly his relationship with his brother, [[Phil Mitchell|Phil]]. Grant and Phil known as the &quot;Mitchell brothers&quot; have become household names in the United Kingdom. They have been parodied even in adverts where their gruff, tough talking, cockney accents have been impersonated. One of ''EastEnders'' most popular and highly-rated storylines was ''[[Sharongate]]'', where Grant discovers that his wife [[Sharon Rickman|Sharon]] has been having an affair with his brother. In the latter part of 1989 ''EastEnders'' acquired a new executive producer named [[Michael Ferguson (director)|Michael Ferguson]], who took over from [[Mike Gibbon]]. Ferguson had previously been a producer on [[ITV]]'s ''[[The Bill]]'' — a hard-hitting, gritty and successful police drama, which seemed to be challenging ''EastEnders'' in providing a realistic vision of modern life in [[London]]. Due to his success on ''The Bill'', [[Peter Cregeen]], the Head of Series at the BBC, poached Ferguson to become executive producer of ''EastEnders''.&lt;ref name=&quot;first10years&quot;&gt;{{cite book |last=Brake|first= Colin|authorlink= Colin Brake|title= [[EastEnders books#Non-fiction books|EastEnders: The First 10 Years: A Celebration]] |year=1995|publisher=BBC Books|isbn=0-563-37057-2}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Jackie Stone==
{{Infobox soap character 2 | series = EastEnders
|name=Jackie Stone
|portrayer=[[Richard Beale]]
|years=1990-91
|first=20 March 1990
|last=
|occupation= Market Trader
}}
'''Jack &quot;Jackie&quot; Stone''' was a market trader who was elected as the Chairman of the Bridge Street Market Traders Association. He was asked to liaise with [[Phil Mitchell|Phil]] and [[Grant Mitchell (EastEnders)|Grant]], who had purchased land that had been used by traders previously. However, Jackie found himself in an awkward position when he realised that he had been a friend of the Mitchell brothers' late father, Eric; they had boxed together and some traders believed that Jackie was showing favouritism to the Mitchell brothers.

When the council attempted to close part of the market for a possible development, Jackie along with the other traders petitioned and protested against it, although fruit and veg trader [[Pete Beale]] was not impressed with his efforts and usurped his post as chairman. The councilman in charge of the development, Stuart Kendle, attempted to bribe Pete and Jackie to drop their opposition. Impressed by Pete's determination, Phil and Grant broke into Kendle's office and found evidence that proved he was corrupt. The market was saved.

In March 1991, [[Ian Beale]] decided that he wanted to take over the lease of the Dagmar winebar, where Jackie was squatting. He planted a computer that Phil and Grant had stolen from the council in the winebar so that Jackie would be evicted.

==Disa O'Brien==
{{Infobox soap character 2 | series = EastEnders
|image=
|name=Disa O'Brien
|portrayer=[[Jan Graveson]]
|years=1990–91
|first=27 March 1990
|last=28 February 1991
|born=
|home=[[Sunderland, Tyne and Wear|Sunderland]]
|occupation=Unemployed
|mother=Sandra Raynor
|halfsisters=Ginny O'Brien
|daughters=[[#Jasmine O'Brien|Jasmine O'Brien]]
|stepfather=[[#Ken Raynor|Ken Raynor]]
}}

'''Disa O'Brien''' is a [[fictional character]] from the [[BBC]] [[soap opera]] ''[[EastEnders]]'', played by [[Jan Graveson]].

Disa was a tough seeming [[Wearside]] runaway, who helped [[Diane Butcher]] to survive when she lived rough on the streets.

Disa was first seen in March 1990. Diane Butcher had run away from home and was fending for herself living on the streets of [[London]], where she befriended Disa, a fellow teenage runaway. Disa was working as a [[prostitute]] and tried to convince Diane to follow the same path with the hope that they could raise the funds to share a flat together. Diane couldn't bring herself to do this however, but took up nude modelling for an artist instead. Eventually Diane's father [[Frank Butcher|Frank]] tracked her down and brought her back to [[Walford]], whilst a bedraggled Disa remained living on the streets, begging and selling sex.

Disa had fallen pregnant in 1990, and she was still living rough in London just before the birth of her child. Knowing this, Diane spent days searching the streets of London for Disa, hoping to provide her and her soon to be born baby with accommodation. After a series of leads resulted in nothing, Diane was about to give up hope when her friend [[Mark Fowler]] spotted Disa arguing with an unknown man about her baby. However when Mark made his presence known she and the man scarpered, and Disa disappeared. The following day, on Christmas Eve, Diane was approached by a homeless man who agreed to bring Disa to her in exchange for money. Diane finally got a chance to speak to her friend, but Disa refused to take her help and told her that she hoped she and her baby froze to death. She ordered Diane to stay out of her life and left. On Christmas Day Disa went into labour, alone in a derelict building near Walford, and gave birth to a little girl. Disa knew that a life living rough on the streets was no place for a new born baby, so that same day she decided to leave her baby in a cardboard box on the Butcher's doorstep, with the hope that Diane would take her in.

Diane and her boyfriend Mark once again searched the streets of London and eventually found Disa. They managed to bring her back to [[Albert Square]] (under protest) to live in [[Mo Butcher]]'s empty flat, in the hope that she would become attached to the child, who was originally called Billie, but was later renamed [[#kJasmine O'Brien|Jasmine]].

It was a rough ride for Disa, as she was severely lacking parenting skills. She also found it difficult to bond with her baby initially, but with the help of Diane and Mark she began to settle into life in the Square, and she soon grew to love her baby. [[Dot Cotton]], who often attracted waifs and strays, looked after the child when Disa wouldn't or couldn't. On one occasion, she unwittingly let a stranger called [[#Ken Raynor|Ken Raynor]] into the flat, who claimed to be Disa's uncle. However, Ken was actually Disa's stepfather, and he was also the father of baby Jasmine. Whilst Disa was living with him and her mother, she had been the victim of his sexual abuse and rape, which had left her pregnant and driven her onto the streets. In an attempt to get Disa back within his power, Ken kidnapped Jasmine, leaving Disa frantic with worry. With the help of the police, Dot managed to trap him. Ken was arrested and imprisoned, and the baby was returned to Disa unharmed.

Despite suspicion from the [[Department of Social Security|DSS]], Disa refused to admit to the sexual abuse she had been subjected to, even when she was told that Ken would be imprisoned for a long time if she did. However, she did confide in [[Kathy Beale]] through the Samaritans. Kathy helped Disa to find the courage to tell her mother, Sandra, that Ken had forced both her and her younger half sister to have sex with him, and that he was the father of her child. Sandra refused to believe her daughter's horrific tale at first. She hit Disa and accused her of lying, before breaking down and accepting the truth. Sandra made Disa visit Ken in prison so she could see his response to her accusations. While there, a repulsed Disa confronted Ken about the sexual abuse she had endured since the age of 12. Disgusted, Sandra informed Ken that she and her children would be testifying to this in court, to ensure that he was locked away for a very long time. Sandra then took Disa and Jasmine back up north to live with her. Disa's last appearance was in February 1991.
{{-}}

==Carol Hanley==
{{Infobox soap character 2
|series = EastEnders
|name=Carol Hanley
|portrayer=[[Sheila White (actress)|Sheila White]]
|years=1990
|first=28 June 1990
|last=1 November 1990
|husband=Ron Hanley
|daughters=[[Sharon Rickman]]
|sons=Chris Hanley
|grandsons=Dennis Rickman, Jr.
}}
'''Carol Ann Hanley''' (née '''Stretton'''), played by [[Sheila White (actress)|Sheila White]], was the biological mother of [[Sharon Watts]] ([[Letitia Dean]]), who appears in 1990 having been tracked down by Sharon. Sharon's best friend [[Michelle Fowler]] ([[Susan Tully]]) visits Carol, who is heavily pregnant and her husband Ron. Michelle speaks to them about contacting Sharon after years of absence. Sharon later visits Carol after her baby is born. Carol and Sharon gets on well, but after Carol's confession that she only thought of her as a good friend, Sharon realises there would never be a parental bond between them and stops seeing her.
{{-}}

==Eddie Royle==
{{Main|Eddie Royle}}
'''Edward &quot;Eddie&quot; Royle''' was played by [[Michael Melia]] from 1990 until 1991. Eddie arrived in [[Walford]] in July 1990, as the new landlord of the [[Queen Vic]] pub, which he bought from [[Frank Butcher]]. He was a serious minded landlord, far different to his predecessors. Not everyone took to him, particularly when they discovered his prior profession -a [[policeman]]. Born in [[Ireland]], Eddie came to [[UK|Britain]] with his parents as a boy. Bright and energetic, he couldn't wait to join the [[police]] force and when he did, he loved his job, priding himself on being an honest copper.

==Celestine Tavernier==
{{Main|Celestine and Etta Tavernier}}
'''Celestine Tavernier''' was played by [[Leroy Golding]]. He appeared primarily in the serial between 1990 and 1992. Celestine made a further guest appearance in 1993. Celestine was portrayed as a strict disciplinarian and a devout Christian who expected everyone in his family to show similar dedication to the church and abide by his rules. His unwavering demand for respect often alienated his children and almost caused the breakdown of his marriage.&lt;ref name=&quot;EEHandbook&quot;&gt;{{cite book |last= Kingsley|first= Hilary|title= [[EastEnders books#Non-fiction books|The EastEnders Handbook]] |year=1990|publisher=BBC books|isbn=0-563-206010-563-36292-8-2}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Clyde Tavernier==
{{Main|Clyde Tavernier}}
'''Clyde Tavernier''' was played by [[Steven Woodcock]]. Introduced in the summer of 1990, Clyde was featured in various promient storylines including an inter-racial relationship with [[Michelle Fowler]], and being framed for the murder of publican [[Eddie Royle]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url= http://www.thefreelibrary.com/EastEnders+at+15%3a+tragic+moments%3b+1991-1993.-a061515690|title=EastEnders at 15: tragic moments; 1991-1993.|publisher=''Sunday Mail'' |accessdate=2009-09-16 | date=16 April 2000}}&lt;/ref&gt; The character was wriiten out in 1993 and was given a happy ending. In the latter part of 1989 ''EastEnders'' acquired a new executive producer named [[Michael Ferguson (director)|Michael Ferguson]], who took over from [[Mike Gibbon]]. Ferguson had previously been a producer on [[ITV]]'s ''[[The Bill]]'' – a hard-hitting, gritty and successful police drama, which seemed to be challenging ''EastEnders'' in providing a realistic vision of modern life in [[London]]. Due to his success on ''The Bill'', [[Peter Cregeen]], the Head of Series at the BBC, poached Ferguson to become executive producer of ''EastEnders''.&lt;ref name=&quot;first10years&quot;&gt;{{cite book |last=Brake|first= Colin|authorlink= Colin Brake|title= [[EastEnders books#Non-fiction books|EastEnders: The First 10 Years: A Celebration]] |year=1995|publisher=BBC Books|isbn=0-563-37057-2}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Etta Tavernier==
{{Main|Celestine and Etta Tavernier}}
'''Etta Tavernier''' was played by [[Jacqui Gordon-Lawrence]]. She appeared between 1990 and 1992. Etta made a guest appearance in 1994, visiting remaining members of the Tavernier family who remained in the serial. Also religious like her husband, Etta was portrayed as a career woman; her most prominent storylines concerned marital problems and crises of faith.&lt;ref name=&quot;EEHandbook&quot;/&gt; Etta was Gordon-Lawrence's first television role. Golding was awarded the part and claims that his inexperience helped rather than hindered the Tavernier family to gel together as it created a sense of &quot;camaraderie&quot; among them; he suggests that he and his screen wife Gordon-Lawrence &quot;played very well off each other&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;Larry Jaffee&quot;&gt;{{cite web|work=Walford Gazette|url= http://www.wgazette.com/int-ler.html|title=THE GOLDING VARIATION|accessdate= 2 April 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Hattie Tavernier==
{{Main|Hattie Tavernier}}

==Jules Tavernier==
{{Main|Jules Tavernier (EastEnders)}}

==Lloyd Tavernier==
{{Infobox soap character 2 | series = EastEnders
|image= 
|name=Lloyd Tavernier
|portrayer=[[Garey Bridges]]
|years=1990–92
|first=5 July 1990
|last=9 June 1992
|classification=[[List of past EastEnders characters#Last appeared in 1992|Former; regular]]
|born=12 April 1975
|home = [[Norwich]]
|father=[[Celestine Tavernier]]
|mother=[[Etta Tavernier]]
|brothers=[[Clyde Tavernier]]
|sisters=[[Hattie Tavernier]]
|grandfathers=[[Jules Tavernier (EastEnders)|Jules Tavernier]]
|nephews=[[Kofi Tavernier]]
|cousins=[[Gidea Thompson]]
}}
'''Lloyd Tavernier''', played by [[Garey Bridges]], arrived in [[Albert Square]] in July 1990 with the rest of the Tavernier clan: father [[Celestine Tavernier|Celestine]], mother [[Etta Tavernier|Etta]], grandfather [[Jules Tavernier (EastEnders)|Jules]], older brother [[Clyde Tavernier|Clyde]] and twin sister [[Hattie Tavernier|Hattie]].

Lloyd suffered with the degenerative disease [[sickle-cell anaemia]] and because of this his entire family tended to 'wrap him up in cotton-wool', which often left him feeling smothered. His father's strict rules only sought to alienate him further so he spent most of his time on the square attempting to rebel against them. His condition meant that he became easily tired so he was forbidden from getting a job as his parents feared that he would over-exert himself. Lloyd ignored his family's wishes and secretly got a job as a paper boy. He regretted his defiance however, as during a delivery run he collapsed and was rushed to hospital frightening his family with a near death experience. The incident underlined the seriousness of his condition and only sought to increase his parents overbearing concern.

Lloyd soon grew sick of his 'limited existence' and he eventually began to turn his back on education and the 'sanctimonious preachings' of the [[Christian Church|church]] that his parents held with such high regard. In an attempt to rebel he neglected his studies and turned to petty crime. He and his friends hi-jacked a car in April 1992 and took it for a joy-ride, which culminated in him getting caught and arrested by the [[police]]. His expedition earned him a suspended sentence, much to his father's shame. His older brother Clyde took him under his wing, however, and helped him straighten his life out.

Lloyd eventually moved to [[Norwich]] with his mother and father. His last appearance was in June 1992.
{{-}}

==April McIntosh==
{{Infobox soap character 2 | series = EastEnders
|image=
|name=April McIntosh
|portrayer=[[Helen Pearson]]
|years=1990
|first=5 July 1990
|last=10 July 1990
|occupation=Market Trader
|husband=Greg McIntosh
}}
'''April McIntosh''' was a market trader whose livelihood was under threat in 1990 when Walford Borough Council threatened to demolish the Market.
{{-}}

==Sam Mitchell==
{{Main|Sam Mitchell (EastEnders)}}

==John Royle==
{{Infobox soap character 2 | series = EastEnders
|image=
|name=John Royle
|portrayer=[[Paddy Joyce (actor)|Paddy Joyce]]
|years=1990–91, 1993
|first=16 August 1990
|last=21 January 1993
|occupation=Retired metal worker
|sons=[[Eddie Royle]]
|home = [[Ireland]]
}}
'''John Royle''' was the widowed father of [[Eddie Royle]] — the publican of [[The Queen Vic]]. He first appeared in [[Walford]] in August 1990 when he came to visit his son. John was a wily [[Irish people|Irishman]] and a retired metal worker. In his youth, he was a talented [[Football (soccer)|footballer]] and could have played professionally if he'd wanted to leave [[Dublin]], which he didn't.

He was often the life and soul of the party in Walford, and was known to like a pint of [[Guinness]] or two. He was a perfect pal for the other seniors on the Square — [[Jules Tavernier (EastEnders)|Jules Tavernier]] and [[Ethel Skinner]]. He could often be seen engaging in a game of [[poker]] with Jules. On one occasion Jules managed to thrash John, but was mortified when John paid the winnings in [[chicken]]s instead of money. [[Mo Butcher]] ended up taking them back to her family's Bed and Breakfast.

John was very proud of his son and wouldn't get mixed up in anything that would have earned his disapproval. John would show up periodically to visit Eddie, and on one occasion he brought Eddie's ex-girlfriend, [[Eibhlin O'Donnell]], with him. Unfortunately, John's timing couldn't have been worse, as her arrival spelt the end of his son's relationship with [[Kathy Hills|Kathy Beale]]. However, within a few months, Eddie had changed his mind and asked Eibhlin to marry him.

Eddie was murdered by [[Nick Cotton]] in September 1991, and John was devastated to lose his pride and joy, especially in such horrific circumstances.

After this time, John was not seen in Walford until January 1993, when he attended the [[trial (law)|trial]] of Nick Cotton. He had found the death of his son hard to get over and he hoped that seeing justice served to his son's killer would bring closure. He was horrified and inconsolable, however, when the verdict came back as not guilty.
{{-}}

==Joan Garwood==
{{Infobox soap character 2 | series = EastEnders
|image=
|name=Joan Garwood
|portrayer=[[Mary Millar]]
|years=1990
|first=20 November 1990
|last=29 November 1990
|home= [[Colchester]]
|occupation=Banker
|father=Chike Butcher
|mother=[[Mo Butcher]]
|brothers=[[Frank Butcher]]
|uncles= Sidney
|nephews=[[Ricky Butcher]]&lt;br /&gt;Danny Butcher
|nieces=[[Clare Butcher]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Diane Butcher]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Janine Butcher]]
}}
'''Joan Garwood''' (née '''Butcher'''), played by [[Mary Millar]], was the older sister of [[Frank Butcher]], and the first child of [[Mo Butcher|Mo]] and Chike Butcher. Joan was far brighter than Frank and after graduating from school with 7 O levels, she got a job in a bank and married a chief accountant.

When Mo was diagnosed with [[Alzheimer's Disease]] in 1990, she came to Walford to assess the situation. She and her brother Frank had not spoken for many years, but they were forced to call a truce for their mother's sake. Soon after, Frank took a confused Mo on an excursion to visit Joan in [[Colchester]]. She began demanding to move to her daughter's because she feared Frank wanted to kill her, but in moments of lucidity, she pleaded with her son to do just that.

Frank could not cope with his mother's illness, and when he began talking about ending her misery for her, Joan decided that Mo should not remain living with him. She and her husband took Mo to live with them in Colchester, where she died on 31 December 1992.
{{-}}

==Marcus Christie==
{{Infobox soap character 2 | series = EastEnders
|image= 
|name=Marcus Christie
|portrayer=[[Stephen Churchett]]
|years={{nowrap|1990–91,}} 1993, 1996, 1998, {{nowrap|2000–04}}
|first=27 November 1990
|last=23 December 2004
|occupation= Retired solicitor
}}
'''Marcus Christie''' is a [[fictional character]] from the [[BBC]] [[soap opera]] ''[[EastEnders]]'', played by [[Stephen Churchett]].
Marcus was solicitor to [[Phil Mitchell|Phil]] and [[Grant Mitchell (EastEnders)|Grant Mitchell]], and represented them in numerous criminal cases from 1990 onwards. Marcus often got Phil and Grant out of trouble and was never afraid to bend the rules; he once conned [[Dan Sullivan (EastEnders)|Dan Sullivan]] into selling his share of the Queen Victoria Pub to Phil.

His last appearance was in December 2004, when he conned [[Sam Mitchell (EastEnders)|Sam]] by telling her that Phil (who was on the run) needed all the money he could get. Sam sold all of the Mitchell empire (including The Queen Vic to [[Den Watts]]), and gave Marcus the money. Marcus then fled Walford to start a new life abroad with all the money leaving Sam penniless and homeless after her husband [[Andy Hunter (EastEnders)|Andy Hunter]] threw her out. It was also revealed that Marcus was in on the con with Den Watts, because Den wanted to regain his position as the landlord of the Queen Vic 16 years after he had first sold it. This ultimately ended in Den's demise, as one of the three 'Walford Witches', Sam, wanted revenge for the con, and Den ended up dead after a confrontation in February 2005.
{{-}}

==Kofi Tavernier==
{{Infobox soap character 2 | series = EastEnders
|image= 
|name=Kofi Tavernier
|portrayer=[[Marcel Smith]]
|years=1990–93
|first=27 November 1990
|last=22 July 1993
|classification=[[List of past EastEnders characters#Last appeared in 1993|Former; regular]]
|born=
|home=[[Trinidad]]
|occupation=
|family=
|father=[[Clyde Tavernier]]
|mother=Abigail Chadwick
|aunts=[[Hattie Tavernier]]
|uncles=[[Lloyd Tavernier]]
|grandfathers=[[Celestine Tavernier]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Henry Chadwick (EastEnders)|Henry Chadwick]]
|grandmothers=[[Etta Tavernier]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Pearl Chadwick]]
|relatives=[[Jules Tavernier (EastEnders)|Jules Tavernier]]
}}
'''Kofi Tavernier''' is  a [[fictional character]] from the BBC soap opera ''EastEnders'',&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url= http://www.bbc.co.uk/cult/ilove/years/1991/gallery/eastenders-kofitavernier.shtml |title= 1991 photo gallery|publisher=''I Love 1991'' |accessdate=2007-10-21}}&lt;/ref&gt; played by Marcel Smith from 1990 to 1993.&lt;ref name=&quot;EEHandbook&quot;/&gt;

The Tavernier family were introduced in 1990 by the newly appointed executive producer [[Michael Ferguson (director)|Michael Ferguson]].&lt;ref name=&quot;first10years&quot;&gt;{{cite book |last=Brake|first= Colin|authorlink= Colin Brake|title= [[EastEnders books#Non-fiction books|EastEnders: The First 10 Years: A Celebration]] |year=1995|publisher=BBC Books|isbn=0-563-37057-2}}&lt;/ref&gt; The introduction of the Tavernier family heralded the first time that an entire family had joined ''EastEnders'' all at the same time—all except Kofi, who first appeared several months after the core family's introduction. The Taverniers were also a well-intentioned attempt to portray a wider range of black characters than had previously been achieved on the show.&lt;ref name=&quot;first10years&quot;/&gt;

It took a long time to cast the complete Tavernier family. Once ''EastEnders'' became a success, the producers had no difficulties in finding &quot;good actors&quot; who wanted to join the cast; however, what became hard was finding families—combinations of performers who &quot;look and sound as though they could be related.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;EEHandbook&quot;&gt;{{cite book |last= Kingsley|first= Hilary|title= [[EastEnders books#Non-fiction books|The EastEnders Handbook]] |year=1990|publisher=BBC books|isbn=0-563-206010-563-36292-8-2}}&lt;/ref&gt; According to producers [[Corinne Hollingworth]] and [[Pat Sandys]], the Taveriner family were especially difficult, as upon Kofi's arrival, four male generations of the family were being featured, great grandfather [[Jules Tavernier (EastEnders)|Jules]], grandfather [[Celestine Tavernier|Celestine]], father [[Clyde Tavernier|Clyde]] and son Kofi. Hollingworth has commented &quot;The most difficult job we've had was finding…black actors who fitted the bill for the Tavernier family.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;EEHandbook&quot;/&gt;

Kofi's backstory was told through Clyde before he made an appearance—he was a result of a relationship between Clyde and a girl named Abigail (unseen in the serial). Until December 1990, Kofi lived outside of the area that the soap is set—remaining with his maternal grandparents in Bristol following the death of his mother. Clyde accepted this as he was unable to provide financially for his child, a fact that he was seen to agonise over, and a source of friction between him and his father Celestine.&lt;ref name=&quot;EEHandbook&quot;/&gt; Clyde eventually brought Kofi to live with him in Walford when Abigail's parents threatened to take Kofi to live in the West Indies.&lt;ref name=&quot;20years&quot;&gt;{{cite book |last= Smith|first= Rupert|title= [[EastEnders books#Non-fiction books|''EastEnders: 20 years in Albert Square]] |year=2005|publisher=BBC books|isbn=0-563-52165-1}}&lt;/ref&gt; Kofi was often in scenes with another child actress, Samantha Leigh-Martin, who played [[Vicki Fowler]]. Their friendship was part of the reason that Clyde and Vicki's mother, [[Michelle Fowler|Michelle]], formed a relationship. He was also featured in a special set of offset episodes, written by [[Tony Jordan]] and airing in November 1991. The episodes were the climax of a &quot;mini-storyline&quot; that saw Clyde and Michelle go &quot;on the run&quot; from the police with Kofi and Vicki, after Clyde was falsely accused of murder. Directed by Mike Dormer, the episode has been described as one &quot;of the most exciting thriller episodes of ''EastEnders''.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;first10years&quot;/&gt;

Kofi remained in the programme until July 1993, when he and his father Clyde were written out of the serial. On-screen Clyde left Walford with Kofi to explore his roots in Trinidad.&lt;ref name=&quot;first10years&quot;/&gt;

===Storylines===
Kofi was the son of [[Clyde Tavernier]] and he initially lived with his maternal grandparents in [[Bristol]] following the death of his mother, Abigail.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url= http://www.bbc.co.uk/eastenders/characters_cast/characters/character_clyde_t.shtml |title= Clyde Tavernier|publisher=''BBC'' |accessdate=2007-10-21}}&lt;/ref&gt; After Clyde discovered that Kofi's grandparents were planning on emigrating to [[Jamaica]] with his son, he tailed them to the airport and brought Kofi back to [[Walford]] on [[Christmas day]] 1990.

Kofi became friendly with [[Vicki Fowler]] at a toddler group, and as a result of their friendship Clyde grew close to Vicki's mother, [[Michelle Fowler]].

In 1991, Kofi's father was wrongly accused of the murder of [[Eddie Royle]] and so Clyde and Michelle went on the run and took Vicki and Kofi with them in an ill-fated attempt to start a new life together in [[France]]. However, Clyde was arrested before he could escape and was subsequently imprisoned. During this time Kofi was looked after by the rest of the Taverniers until Clyde was cleared of all charges and released three months later.

In July 1993, Clyde and Kofi emigrated to [[Trinidad]] to live with Clyde's girlfriend [[Gidea Thompson]], who was also his cousin.

== Pearl Chadwick ==&lt;!-- This section is linked from [[Pearl Chadwick]] --&gt;
{{Infobox soap character 2 | series = EastEnders
|image=
|name=Pearl Chadwick
|portrayer=[[Ellen Thomas (actress)|Ellen Thomas]]
|years=1990
|first=27 November 1990
|last=20 December 1990
|home= [[Jamaica]]
|occupation=[[Retirement|Retired]]
|husband=[[Henry Chadwick (EastEnders)|Henry Chadwick]]
|daughters=Abigail Chadwick
|grandsons=[[Kofi Tavernier]]
}}
'''Pearl Chadwick'''&lt;nowiki&gt;'&lt;/nowiki&gt;s daughter, Abigail, had been killed in a motor accident and Abigail's son, [[Kofi Tavernier|Kofi]], was left in Pearl's care. He resided with her and her husband Henry in [[Bristol]]. Kofi's father, [[Clyde Tavernier]], visited occasionally, but he desperately missed his son and he was furious to discover that Pearl and Henry were planning to emigrate with Kofi to [[Jamaica]] in December 1990. Clyde was unable to talk Pearl out of taking Kofi, but Clyde's mother stepped in and they allowed Clyde to spend some time with Kofi in [[Walford]] before departing for the airport. Clyde could not bear lose his son, and he followed the Chadwicks to the airport and persuaded them that he could give Kofi the stability he needed. Clyde brought Kofi home to Walford in time for Christmas.
{{-}}

== Henry Chadwick ==&lt;!-- This section is linked from [[Henry Chadwick (EastEnders)]] --&gt;
{{Infobox soap character 2 | series = EastEnders
|image=
|name=Henry Chadwick
|portrayer=[[Thomas Baptiste]]
|years=1990
|first=13 December 1990
|last=20 December 1990
|home= [[Jamaica]]
|occupation=[[Retirement|Retired]]
|wife=[[Pearl Chadwick]]
|daughters=Abigail Chadwick
|grandsons=[[Kofi Tavernier]]
}}
'''Henry Chadwick'''&lt;nowiki&gt;'&lt;/nowiki&gt;s daughter, Abigail, had been killed in a motor accident and Abigail's son, [[Kofi Tavernier|Kofi]], was left in his care. Kofi resided with Henry and his wife Pearl in [[Bristol]]. Kofi's father, [[Clyde Tavernier]], visited occasionally, but he desperately missed his son and he was furious to discover that Pearl and Henry were planning to emigrate with Kofi to [[Jamaica]] in December 1990. Clyde was unable to talk them out of taking Kofi, but Clyde's mother stepped in and they allowed Clyde to spend some time with Kofi in [[Walford]] before departing for the airport. Clyde could not bear lose his son, and he followed the Chadwicks to the airport and persuaded them that he could give Kofi the stability he needed. Clyde brought Kofi home to Walford in time for Christmas.
{{-}}

== Ken Raynor ==&lt;!-- This section is linked from [[Ken Raynor]] --&gt;
{{Infobox soap character 2 | series = EastEnders
|image=
|name=Ken Raynor
|portrayer=[[Ian Redford (actor)|Ian Redford]]
|years=1990–91
|first=18 December 1990
|last=28 February 1991
|introducer=[[Michael Ferguson (director)|Michael Ferguson]]
|wife=[[Sandra Raynor]] &lt;small&gt;(divorced)&lt;/small&gt;
|daughters=[[#Jasmine O'Brien|Jasmine O'Brien]]
|stepdaughters=Ginny O'Brien&lt;br&gt;[[#Disa O'Brien|Disa O'Brien]]
}}
'''Ken Raynor''' married Sandra O'Brien in [[Sunderland, Tyne and Wear|Sunderland]] and became stepfather to her two children [[#Disa O'Brien|Disa]] and Ginny. Unbeknown to Sandra, Ken sexually abused both her girls. Disa ran away from home to live rough on the streets of London, turning to prostitution to survive. However, Disa had fallen pregnant with Ken's child, and he followed her there.

Ken was first seen on-screen in December 1990, when [[Mark Fowler]] witnessed him harassing Disa and scared him away. Disa gave birth to Ken's daughter on Christmas Day 1990 in a derelict building. She abandoned the baby — initially named Billie, later renamed Jasmine — on [[Diane Butcher]]'s doorstep, until Diane convinced her to stay in an empty flat in Walford, and helped her to bond with the child.

Ken traced Disa there in January 1991. He tricked Disa's childminder, [[Dot Branning|Dot Cotton]], into letting him see the baby by pretending to be Disa's concerned uncle. He then kidnapped Jasmine. Ken wanted Disa back under his control, but Dot, with police assistance, tricked him into meeting her, and led him straight into the hands of the police. The baby was returned to Disa, and Ken was imprisoned.

With the possibility that Ken could be released, Disa was forced to admit to the sexual abuse he had subjected her to. Disa and her mother Sandra visited Ken in prison to confront him. Disgusted, Sandra informed Ken that she and her children would be testifying in court to ensure that he was imprisoned for a very long time.
{{-}}

== Jasmine O'Brien ==&lt;!-- This section is linked from [[Jasmine O'Brien]] --&gt;
{{Infobox soap character 2 | series = EastEnders
|image=
|name=Jasmine O'Brien
|portrayer=
|years=1990–91
|first=25 December 1990
|born=25 December 1990
|last=28 February 1991
|introducer=[[Michael Ferguson (director)|Michael Ferguson]]
|grandmothers=[[Sandra Raynor]]
|aunts= Ginny O'Brien
|home=[[Sunderland, Tyne and Wear|Sunderland]]
|mother=[[#Disa O'Brien|Disa O'Brien]]
|father=[[#Ken Raynor|Ken Raynor]]
}}
'''Jasmine O'Brien''' is the daughter of [[#Disa O'Brien|Disa O'Brien]], who gave birth to her daughter alone, in a derelict building, on Christmas Day 1990. She abandoned the child in a cardboard box on [[Diane Butcher]]'s doorstep. Diane cared for the baby in secret, with the help of her friend [[Mark Fowler]], until they tracked Disa down and threatened to hand the baby over to the Social Services unless she returned to Walford with them. Disa did so, under protest, and lived in [[Mo Butcher]]'s vacant flat on Albert Square. With the help of Diane and [[Dot Branning|Dot Cotton]], Disa began to bond with her daughter, who was originally named Billie, but later renamed Jasmine.

Unbeknown to everyone else, Disa's baby was the product of sexual abuse by her stepfather [[#Ken Raynor|Ken Raynor]]. Ken arrived in Walford and tricked Dot into allowing him to see the baby by pretending he was Disa's concerned uncle. He then kidnapped the child. Ken wanted Disa back under his control, but Dot, with police assistance, tricked him into meeting her, and led him straight into the hands of the police. The baby was returned to Disa, and Ken was imprisoned.

With the possibility that Ken could be released, Disa was forced to admit to the sexual abuse he had subjected her to. Disa and her mother [[Sandra Raynor|Sandra]] visited Ken in prison to confront him. Disgusted, Sandra informed Ken that she and her children would be testifying in court to ensure that he was imprisoned for a very long time. Reunited with her mother, Disa took Jasmine back to their home in [[Sunderland, Tyne and Wear|Sunderland]].
{{-}}

==References==
{{Reflist}}

==External links==
*{{EEcharlink|marcus_c|Marcus Christie}}
{{EastEnders}}
{{EastEnders characters|year}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:List Of Eastenders Characters (1990)}}
[[Category:Lists of EastEnders characters|1990]]
[[Category:Fictional characters introduced in 1990|*, EastEnders]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
