<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="12811306" ns="0" title="List of EastEnders characters (2003)"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{DISPLAYTITLE:List of ''EastEnders'' characters (2003)}}
The following is a list of characters that first appeared in the [[BBC]] [[soap opera]] ''[[EastEnders]]'' in 2003, by order of first appearance.
{{TOClimit|limit=2}}

== Eleanor Trueman ==
{{Infobox soap character 2 | series = EastEnders
|image=
|name=Eleanor Trueman
|portrayer=[[Charnae Leckie]]
|years=2003
|first=7 March 2003
|last=25 April 2003
|mother=Amy
|father=[[Paul Trueman]]
|grandfathers=[[Milton Hibbert]]
|grandmothers=[[Audrey Trueman]]
|uncles=[[Anthony Trueman]]
|aunts=[[Rebecca Hibbert]]
}}
'''Eleanor &quot;Ellie&quot; Trueman''' (real name '''Amber''') was the result of a [[one-night-stand]] between [[Paul Trueman]] and a woman called Amy. Amy dumped her on Paul's doorstep, and he struggled to cope as a single parent. He named the baby Eleanor, after his stepfather, [[Patrick Trueman|Patrick]]'s mother. As Paul started to cope with looking after Eleanor, Amy decided she wanted her back, and Social Services collected her, leaving Paul heartbroken.
{{-}}

==Dominic Price==
{{Infobox soap character 2 | series = EastEnders
|image=
|name=Dominic Price
|portrayer=[[Paul Brennen]]
|years=2003–05
|first=10 March 2003
|last=6 January 2005
|occupation=Detective
}}
'''Detective Inspector Dominic Price''' was first seen in March 2003, while his colleague, PC [[Kate Mitchell|Kate Morton]] was undercover as a honeytrap on [[Phil Mitchell]], investigating the disappearance of [[Lisa Fowler]], mother of Phil's daughter [[Louise Fowler|Louise]].

He mainly helped Kate with initial searches of the Mitchell house, constantly reminding her that &quot;the boss&quot; wanted to nail Phil. He later started to suspect that Kate was developing feelings for Phil, and reminded her that Phil could have been a murderer. Kate gave Phil an ultimatum: to tell the truth about Lisa's whereabouts or she would finish with him. After Phil called her bluff and finished with her, Price took Kate off the case, however, after Phil phoned her and said he would tell her everything, she was congratulated by &quot;the boss&quot; - DCI [[Jill Marsden (EastEnders)|Jill Marsden]] - who had wanted to convict Phil since 2001.

Kate went to the Mitchell's house wearing a wire, and heard Phil's confession that he had mentally abused Lisa into handing over Louise, leaving her in [[Portugal]]. After this, Kate took off her wire, telling Price and Marsden that she had fallen in love with Phil. They stuck around outside, hoping that Kate had changed tactic and was still on their side, but they could not hear what was happening as the wire had broken, so Marsden called Kate's mobile phone, which led to Phil discovering the wire. After a heated argument, Price and Marsden stormed into the house to find Phil with his hand around Kate's throat. She refused to press charges so they could not arrest him, and they had to leave, deflated.

Price appeared again in May 2003 when Kate returned to work and was asked to choose between her job and Phil. She chose to resign, and asked Price for one last favour as a leaving present: to get [[George Peters (EastEnders)|George Peters]] (a heavy employed by [[Jack Dalton (EastEnders)|Jack Dalton]] who was sent to rape her) arrested for dealing cocaine.

Price and Marsden later appeared in November 2003, when [[Den Watts]] and [[Dennis Rickman]] set Phil up for armed robbery; this time they were successful in convicting him, keeping him in custody until his case collapsed in 2005.

In late 2004, an off-duty Price visited Kate, now running a salon, and she told him she was bored of her career. He found her another job in the police, based in [[Brighton]], which caused her to leave [[Walford]], the next day, for good.
{{-}}

==Dennis Rickman==
{{Main|Dennis Rickman}}
'''Dennis Rickman''', played by [[Nigel Harman]], is introduced as the hardman successor to the character of [[Steve Owen (EastEnders)|Steve Owen]] ([[Martin Kemp (entertainer)|Martin Kemp]]), who left the series in 2002.&lt;ref name=&quot;ananova&quot;&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.ananova.com/entertainment/story/sm_906509.html?menu=entertainment.comedy|title=Ant &amp; Dec the new Morcombe and Wise|work=[[Ananova]]|accessdate=2009-12-20}}&lt;/ref&gt; Dennis made his first appearance on 14 April 2003. His storylines involved his difficult past and childhood, relationship with his infamous father, [[Den Watts]] ([[Leslie Grantham]]), clashes with the rival [[Mitchell family]], and a forbidden romance with his adopted sister, [[Sharon Watts]] ([[Letitia Dean]]). He is described as the show's &quot;bad boy pin-up character.&lt;ref name=&quot;2004 Observer&quot;&gt;{{cite news |title=I blame forgettable characters, outlandish story lines and absent stars |author=Flett, Kathryn |url=http://www.guardian.co.uk/media/2004/sep/26/edinburghtvfestival2004.broadcasting |newspaper=The Observer |date=26 September 2004 |accessdate=2010-01-01 |language= |quote= |archiveurl= |archivedate= |ref= | location=London}}&lt;/ref&gt; In 2005, Harman quit the show alongside co-star Dean,&lt;ref name=&quot;Updated: Two 'EastEnders' stars to quit&quot;&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.digitalspy.co.uk/soaps/news/a23437/two-eastenders-stars-to-quit.html|title=Updated: &quot;Two 'EastEnders' stars to quit&quot;|publisher=[[Digital Spy]]|first=Kris|last=Green|date=13 August 2005|accessdate=23 February 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; and made his last appearance on 30 December 2005.

==Mickey Miller==
{{Main|Mickey Miller}}

==Shirley Benson==
{{Infobox soap character 2 | series = EastEnders
|image= 
|name=Shirley Benson
|portrayer=[[Robyn Moore (British actor)|Robyn Moore]]
|years=2003–04
|classification=[[List of past EastEnders characters#Last appeared in 2004|Former; regular]]
|first=5 May 2003
|last=17 February 2004
|born=
|occupation=Betting shop clerk
|creator = [[Louise Berridge]]
|home = [[New Zealand]]
|family=
}}
'''Shirley Benson''' is a [[fictional character]] from the [[BBC]] [[soap opera]] ''[[EastEnders]]'', played by [[Robyn Moore (British actor)|Robyn Moore]]. The character was axed in 2004.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.digitalspy.co.uk/soaps/a13120/another-eastenders-actor-axed.html Another 'EastEnders' actor axed]&lt;/ref&gt;

Shirley was initially seen in [[Albert Square]] in May 2003. A divorcée, she had three sons, now grown up; two were in the [[army]] and the other lived in [[New Zealand]]. She worked at the [[Walford]] Bookies and lived with her [[cat]], Boots, at 89a George Street.

[[Dan Ferreira]] needed a date for an upcoming wedding, so he asked Shirley and she agreed. Dan told Shirley that his wife, [[Pushpa Ferreira|Pushpa]], was dead, when they had only separated, following Pushpa's [[infidelity]]. At the wedding, everyone was enjoying the day until Pushpa introduced herself to Shirley. She was mortified to discover Dan's lies, telling him that her ex-husband was a liar and she was not prepared to put up with lying again. She also told Dan that she wanted nothing more to do with him.

In August that year, Shirley had problems with her new neighbour, [[Gavin Sharp]]. He lived in the flat above hers and played extremely loud music at all hours, meaning Shirley could not sleep. She tried reasoning with him several times but he laughed at her, only playing his music louder, so she complained to the council. Maddened, Gavin threatened to make her life a misery as payback. Days later, Shirley's cat, disappeared and Shirley feared that Gavin was responsible. Whilst Dan confronted Gavin about Boots, [[Little Mo Mitchell|Little Mo]] walked in to [[The Queen Vic]], cuddling Boots. Shirley rewarded her with money but later that day, Shirley found Boots on her doorstep — dead in a plastic bin bag. Shirley turned to the Ferreiras for help, and Dan confronted Gavin again. Gavin denied killing Boots and said that he found her lying dead in the road and left her on Shirley's doorstep so she could bury her. Shirley, however, was not convinced. Gavin's taunting continued when he put her telephone number on a card, advertising  her as a [[prostitute]], and distributed it across Walford. Later, while she was at work, Gavin broke into her flat and tipped rotten rubbish all over the floor. Shirley was at her wits' end, and seeing her angst, [[Ash Ferreira]], decided to lend a helping hand. He played Gavin at his own game, borrowing his brother's [[amplifier]] and speakers and played dance music extremely loudly. He then broke into Gavin's flat and let a [[rat]] loose. Gavin was petrified of rats and when he discovered it, he agreed to call a truce if they removed it. 

The saga brought Ash and Shirley closer together and it was not long before they started a relationship. Ash wanted to keep it a secret because he knew his father would be furious if he found out. Shirley began to get irritated with Ash's inability to tell Dan, particularly when Dan started to try to woo Shirley for a second time. Ash explained that he had been a compulsive [[gambling|gambler]], and Dan had bailed him out of serious financial difficulties after he lost his house and his wife. He owed his father everything and was unwilling to hurt him. Things came to a head when Dan tried kissing Shirley and she told him that she was seeing his son. This revelation caused huge rows at the Ferreiras' and although Ash loved Shirley, he felt he had no choice but to finish with her to keep the peace.

In February 2004, [[Andy Hunter (EastEnders)|Andy Hunter]] took over the bookies where Shirley worked. Shirley did not like the way Andy ran things and after she complained repeatedly about his conduct, Andy fired her. Shirley demonstrated about her unfair dismissal with a placard outside the bookies. Eventually Andy offered her a large sum of money to leave. Shirley was thrilled with the pay-off and decided to go to New Zealand to visit her son.
{{-}}

== Carl Bromley ==
{{Infobox soap character 2 | series = EastEnders
|image=
|name=Carl Bromley
|portrayer=[[Joe Rice]]
|years=2003
|first=8 May 2003
|last=19 May 2003
|occupation=Lawyer
}}
'''Carl Bromley''' was the owner of a chain of car lots, and approached [[Barry Evans (EastEnders)|Barry Evans]] with a proposition to buy into Evans and Son. Barry refused, but [[Janine Evans|Janine]] later met up with Bromley, and forged a deal. When she discovered that Bromley was double-crossing her and Barry, she terminated the deal. 
{{-}}

==Jack Dalton==
{{Infobox soap character 2 | series = EastEnders
|image= 
|name=Jack Dalton
|portrayer=[[Hywel Bennett]]
|introducer=[[Louise Berridge]]
|years=2003
|first=12 May 2003
|last=18 July 2003
|classification=[[List of past EastEnders characters#Last appeared in 2003|Former; guest]]
|born=1945
|death=18 July 2003
|occupation=Gangster&lt;br /&gt;Nightclub manager
}}
'''Jack Dalton''' was a gangster and head of the criminal organisation known as The Firm.

He first appeared in the show in May 2003, although the events surrounding the apparent death of the character [[Den Watts]] (who was supposedly murdered in February 1989) were then [[retcon]]ned to include him.

Dalton was a fearsome gangland boss, and as head of [[The Firm (EastEnders)|The Firm]], he was responsible for ordering Den's death 14 years earlier.

In the late 1980s, Den had become involved with &quot;Walford Investments&quot;, aka &quot;The Firm&quot;, and was forced to become the titular manager of Strokes wine bar (formerly Henry's), which was owned by The Firm and was really a front for illegal gambling.

Strokes had a rival bar in the form of The Dagmar, fronted by [[James Wilmott-Brown]], who went on to rape [[Kathy Beale]], the wife of Den's best friend. Den used his connections with &quot;The Firm&quot; to arrange for The Dagmar to be torched. 

The fire drew attention to the illegal goings-on at Strokes, and thus greatly angered The Firm. Den refused to take the blame and The Firm believed that he had grassed them up to the police.

Consequently Dalton decided to have Den murdered, and two of their members followed him to [[Manchester]] in September 1988 when he went there to seek refuge with a friend. However, he managed to outrun them in his friend's car and handed himself into the police, who remanded him in custody on an arson charge until he appeared in court the following February.

In one of the series' most famous exits, Den (who just hours earlier had escaped after members of The Firm had intercepted the taxi taking him to court) was shot as he walked by the canal by a member of The Firm, who was walking with a woman and had a gun hidden in a bunch of daffodils. 

Three weeks later, spots of blood were found on the canal towpath and the police identified this as Den's blood, and believed that he had been murdered. However, an initial search of the canal failed to uncover his body. In May 1990, a local boy was fishing in the canal when he discovered Den's distinctive signet ring, prompting another search of the canal which this time uncovered a body which was identified as Den's. 

As Den was not seen falling into the water (the viewers only heard a shot and a splash) the series was able to resurrect him 14 years later. 

In 2003, it was revealed that Den had indeed been shot, but the shot had only wounded him and was able to escape to Spain (aided by his mistress [[Jan Hammond]]) where he forged a new life. He finally returned to [[Walford]] on [[29 September]] that year.

The body which had been found, wrongly-identified and buried had actually been the body of the unseen Mr. Vinnicombe, who was said to have been Dalton's predecessor as head of the Firm during the 1980s. 

Dalton had been displeased with Vinnicombe's failure to murder Den, and so ordered a member of The Firm to kill him and dump his body in the canal at the location where Den had been shot (his teeth were then bricked out to prevent dental identification) - implying a power struggle for control of &quot;The Firm&quot; at this time. He also dumped Den's distinctive ring in the canal to further increase the likelihood of the body being identified as that of Den.

Upon Vinnicombe's demise, Dalton was able to gain firm control of the organisation.

By the 1990s, many of Jack's loyal gangland allies had turned against him. Jack had just got too big for his own good. He responded drastically to attempts on his life - none of his former associates were ever seen again. (''Source'': BBC Character Profile)

By 2003, Jack was now operating from his nightclub; The Imperial Room. During his brief spell on screen, he showed a Machiavellian and ruthless streak: he had [[Spencer Moon]] beaten up (although it was [[Alfie Moon|Alfie]] who took the beating, pretending to be his brother) for using forged currency in his club and then ordered the murder of [[Kate Mitchell|Kate Morton]] after he discovered that she was a police officer working undercover at his nightclub, but [[Phil Mitchell]] was able to persuade him to call off the hit but Dalton told Phil that he now owed him a favour.

Dalton later ordered Phil to kill [[Dennis Rickman]], one of his most loyal employees, when he began blackmailing him for money. Unbeknownst to Dalton at the time, Dennis was Den Watts' illegitimate son. 

Unfortunately for Dalton, Dennis managed to convince Phil that he would murder Dalton himself so the two of them would be free of him. 

Armed with a gun, Dennis forced Dalton to drive into the woods and to the edge of a railway track where he duly murdered him as a train roared past and drowned out the gunshot sound. Before dying, Jack revealed the truth about Den Watts; that he was in fact alive. He begged Dennis that this &quot;had to make a difference&quot; in the hope that he would not shoot him, but Dennis went ahead and pulled the trigger.

Dalton would appear to be somewhat [[nihilism|nihilistic]]. When Dennis told Dalton that he wanted a new life away from a life of crime, Dalton responded &quot;There isn't any new life! Just the old humdrum life bobbing along, making a living, getting old, waiting to die.&quot; nonchalantly, echoing [[Dot Branning]]'s words when she was depressed.

== Vanessa Bird ==
{{Infobox soap character 2 | series = EastEnders
|image=
|name=Vanessa Bird
|portrayer=[[Sara Houghton]]
|years=2003
|appeared=22 May 2003
|occupation=Lawyer
}}
'''Vanessa Bird''' was [[Gus Smith]]'s [[lawyer]] when he was wrongly arrested for a robbery at The Minute Mart. He had been trying to stop [[Martin Fowler (EastEnders)|Martin]] and [[Vicki Fowler]] from robbing the shop, and got arrested after they ran away. Gus was found not guilty.
{{-}}

==George Peters==
{{Infobox soap character 2 | series = EastEnders
|image=
|name=George Peters
|portrayer= [[Andy Beckwith]]
|years=2003
|first=22 May 2003
|last=30 May 2003
|occupation=Drug dealer
}}
'''George Peters''' was a heavy employed by [[Jack Dalton (EastEnders)|Jack Dalton]] in his [[nightclub]]. Peters was sent by Dalton to [[rape]] and murder [[Kate Mitchell|Kate Morton]], a police officer. However, [[Phil Mitchell]] managed to scupper his plans, causing a [[Feud|vendetta]] between Phil and George.

Kate later got him arrested for dealing [[crack cocaine]] to schoolchildren.
{{-}}

==Dan Ferreira==
{{Main|Ferreira family}}

==Ash Ferreira==
{{Main|Ferreira family}}

==Adi Ferreira==
{{Main|Ferreira family}}

==Kareena Ferreira==
{{Main|Ferreira family}}

==Tariq Larousi==
{{Main|Ferreira family}}

==Pushpa Ferreira==
{{Main|Ferreira family}}

==Tony Jamison==
{{Infobox soap character 2 | series = EastEnders
|image=
|name=Tony Jamison
|portrayer= [[Ben Cartwright (actor)|Ben Cartwright]]
|years= 2003
|first=1 July 2003
|last=14 October 2003
|occupation= Criminal
}}
'''Tony Jamison''' was the ex-partner-in-crime of [[Dennis Rickman]], and used to work with Dennis for [[Jack Dalton (EastEnders)|Jack Dalton]], before Dennis's arrest and imprisonment.

A broke Tony visited Dennis in 2003 asking for money. He persuaded Dennis to ask Dalton for a loan on his behalf. This provoked Dalton to order [[Phil Mitchell]] to shoot and kill Dennis. However, Dennis persuaded Phil to let him kill Dalton, which he did in a nearby forest. Tony was not seen or heard from after this.
{{-}}

==Andy Hunter==
{{Main|Andy Hunter (EastEnders)}}

==Sasha Perkins==
{{Infobox soap character 2 | series = EastEnders
|image= 
|name=Sasha Perkins
|introducer=[[Louise Berridge]]
|portrayer=[[Jemma Walker]]
|years=2003–05
|classification=[[List of past EastEnders characters#Last appeared in 2005|Former; regular]]
|first=8 July 2003
|last=22 March 2005
|occupation=Cab firm manager
}}
'''Sasha Perkins''' is a [[fictional character]] from the [[BBC]] [[soap opera]] ''[[EastEnders]]'', played by [[Jemma Walker]].

She was initially shown as [[Adi Ferreira]]'s escort friend in 2003, whom he hired to pretend was his girlfriend at a wedding to impress his father. Originally a guest character, executive producer Louise Berridge opted to bring her back the following year, offering actress Jemma Walker a 6 month contract. Walker commented in 2004, &quot;I think she's a bit of light relief around the place [...] Sasha called herself an 'escort', but I think she was actually on the game. But she doesn't have any issues with it. You do what you have to do to survive.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;sash&quot;&gt;{{cite news|url=http://findarticles.com/p/articles/mi_qn4161/is_20040815/ai_n12902597/|title='I've blown away the EastEnders boys'|publisher=Sunday Mirror|first=Jenny|last=Cockle|date=15 August 2004|accessdate=25 June 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt; Sasha was reportedly brought in to spice up the Asian Ferreira family, who were heavily criticised in the British media.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.digitalspy.co.uk/soaps/a14882/ees-ferreira-family-set-to-be-spiced-up.html|title=EE's Ferreira family set to be spiced up|publisher=Digital Spy|date=1 July 2004|accessdate=25 June 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt; 

Sasha began a relationship with Adi and moved in with him, bringing her pet snake called Lionel. Walker has commented, &quot;Adi's shy and hasn't had much experience with the ladies. Sasha's had enough [bastards]  mess her around and now she wants someone to settle down with.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;sash&quot;/&gt;

Sasha joined the Ferreira family mini-cab firm - they named the company Toucan Cars after her toucan slippers. She eventually realised that Adi was not right for her; she cheated on him with [[Danny Moon]] and then ended the relationship. Following this she slept with [[Billy Mitchell (EastEnders)|Billy Mitchell]] on the rebound, and left [[Walford]]. In reality, the character was one of many to be axed by executive producer [[Kathleen Hutchison]] following a media backlash and falling ratings surrounding the soap.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.guardian.co.uk/media/2004/oct/14/broadcasting.bbc1|title=Ferreiras kicked out of EastEnders|publisher=The Guardian|date=14 October 2004|accessdate=25 June 2009 | location=London | first=Jason | last=Deans}}&lt;/ref&gt;
{{-}}

== Nobby Stuart ==
{{Infobox soap character 2 | series = EastEnders
|image=
|name=Nobby Stuart
|portrayer=[[Antony Booth]]
|years=2003 
|appeared=26 June 2003
|wife=Mary Stuart (1977–2003)
|}}
'''Nobby Stuart''' was a tramp who gave [[Alfie Moon]] ([[Shane Richie]]) a condom, needed for seducing [[Kat Moon|Kat Slater]] ([[Jessie Wallace]]). He first appeared when Alfie walked into the Midnight Mission at the local church hall for a cup of tea. He sat with Nobby and explained his situation. Nobby told Alfie that his wife of 26 years, Mary, had died recently, and gave him a condom, which Alfie later dropped in the river.
{{-}}

==Bobby Beale==
{{Infobox soap character 2 | series = EastEnders
|image= &lt;!-- [[File:New bobby beale.JPG|200px]] --&gt;
|caption=Bobby Beale as portrayed by Alex Francis
|name=Bobby Beale
|introducer=[[Louise Berridge]]
|portrayer=Kevin Curran &lt;small&gt;(2003–07)&lt;/small&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Alex Francis &lt;small&gt;(2007—)&lt;/small&gt;
|years=2003—
|first=24 July 2003
|classification=[[List of characters from EastEnders#Present characters|Present; recurring]]
|born=22 July 2003
|home=45 Albert Square
|occupation=[[Student]]
|image2= &lt;!-- [[File:Bobby Beale.jpg|150px]] --&gt;
|caption2=Kevin Curran as Bobby in December 2006.
|family = [[Beale family|Beale]]
|father= [[Ian Beale]]
|mother= [[Laura Beale]]
|adoptivemother= [[Jane Beale]]
|halfsisters= [[Lucy Beale]]
|halfbrothers=[[Peter Beale]]
}}
'''Bobby Beale''' is the son of [[Ian Beale|Ian]] and [[Laura Beale]] ([[Adam Woodyatt]] and [[Hannah Waterman]]). Kevin Curran played Bobby from 2003 to 2007, who was replaced by Alex Francis on 7 May 2007. Francis was not credited in the role until 10 March 2008.

Laura becomes pregnant after a drunken fling whilst married to Ian Beale with [[Garry Hobbs]] ([[Ricky Groves]]). Ian had earlier had a secret [[vasectomy]] and assumes the child is not his, so he throws Laura out on [[Christmas Day]], when she is in the early stages of pregnancy. Laura continues to let Garry believe he is the father after Bobby's birth, despite the fact that Laura knows that Ian ''is'' the father after all (he had sex with Laura within six weeks of having the vasectomy, thus the procedure had not taken full effect), but she keeps this to herself. In 2004, Laura falls down the stairs and dies. [[Pat Evans]] ([[Pam St. Clement]]) finds Bobby's birth certificate, stating that Ian is Bobby's father. Ian takes Bobby to live with him, leaving Garry heart-broken.

Bobby now lives with Ian and his fourth wife [[Jane Beale|Jane]] ([[Laurie Brett]]), and his older half siblings [[Peter Beale|Peter]] and [[Lucy Beale|Lucy]]. In July 2009, Ian enters Bobby into a children's talent contest, but realises he cannot sing very well. He decides to cheat and gets Bobby's friend [[List of EastEnders characters (2009)#Colin|Colin]] (William Keeler) to sing while Bobby mimes. [[Dotty Cotton]] (Molly Conlin) discovers this during the contest and unplugs Colin's microphone, leaving Bobby upset. 

Since Bobby's mother dies when he is nine months old, Jane is the only maternal influence in his life. Bobby thinks of Jane as his real mother (as was shown when he gives her a card on her birthday addressing her as &quot;Mum&quot;). Jane addresses her mum as [[Linda Clarke|Granny Linda]] ([[Lynda Baron]]) when she is talking to Bobby. In November 2009 Jane walks out on the family and Bobby takes her leaving very badly. He starts bullying [[Tiffany Dean]] ([[Maisie Smith]]), and when Tiffany confronts Bobby, he yells at her. When Ian tries to restrain Bobby, he shouts that he wants his mum. In December, Bobby goes missing from school. Jane returns to help search for him, and Bobby runs to her saying he was out looking for her. 

In August 2010, Ian tells Jane that he wants her to adopt Bobby. He receives the papers in November. Bobby's half sister [[Lucy Beale]] leaves Albert Square in August 2010 to live with her grandmother in Devon. Peter also leaves for Devon in December 2010.

In May 2011, Bobby and Ian plan to surprise a 40th birthday party for Jane. However as she walks through the door she is caught kissing a man named [[Martin (EastEnders)|Martin]]. Bobby is confused and the next day, Ian sarcastically asks her how he should tell Bobby that Jane is possibly embarking on an affair. After Jane divorces Ian, she leaves Walford. Bobby hears in August 2011 that Jane has died from [[Shenice Quinn]] (Lily Harvey), after Ian started lying that he was widowed to get women. Bobby is upset so Ian explains that he was only joking, and calls Jane to prove to Bobby that she is alive. When [[Mandy Salter]] ([[Nicola Stapleton]]), moves in with Ian and Bobby, Bobby takes a liking to her, and the pair bond. He later sneaks away and visits Jane, prompting her return to Walford.
{{-}}

==Johnathon Leroy==
{{Infobox soap character 2 | series = EastEnders
|image=
|name=Johnathon Leroy
|portrayer=[[Ivan Kaye]]
|years=2003–05
|first=21 August 2003
|last=23 May 2005
|occupation=[[Physician|Doctor]]
}}
Viewers were introduced to '''Doctor Johnathon Leroy''' and his wife as [[Phil Mitchell]]'s unwelcome tenants that had been fraudulently rented Phil's house by his nanny [[List of EastEnders characters (2002)#Joanne Ryan|Joanne Ryan]], as an act of revenge for him spurning her advances. Dr. Leroy continued as a recurrent character in the role of new doctor for [[Albert Square]] until he was replaced by [[Oliver Cousins]]. His wife was not seen after her first appearance in 2003. Leroy was also a member of the Queen Vic's ill-fated pub football team Real Walford.
{{-}}

==Gavin Sharp==
{{Infobox soap character 2 | series = EastEnders
|image= 
|name=Gavin Sharp
|portrayer=[[Steve Nicolson]]
|years=2003
|classification=[[List of past EastEnders characters#Last appeared in 2003|Former; recurring]]
|born=
|first = 22 August 2003
|last  = 31 October 2003
|occupation=Video shop worker
|family=
}}
'''Gavin Sharp''' was [[Shirley Benson]]'s neighbour from hell. He was first seen in [[Walford]] in August 2003 when he moved into 89b George street, which was the flat above [[Shirley Benson]]'s. He worked in the Walford video shop.

As soon as he moved in, Gavin started causing problems for Shirley, by playing his music extremely loudly at all hours of the day and night. After a while, Shirley pleaded with him to stop being so inconsiderate, but this only made him play his music louder. Eventually, Shirley reported him to the landlord, and then to [[environmental health]]. After Gavin was visited from a council representative, he vowed to make Shirley's life a misery. Days later, Shirley's [[cat]], Boots, went missing, and she feared that Gavin may have been responsible. After several weeks, the cat was found dead in a plastic bin bag on Shirley's doorstep. A distraught Shirley turned to her friends, the Ferreiras, for help, but Gavin claimed that he found the cat dead in the road and returned it to Shirley as an act of kindness. Shirley was not convinced.

Gavin continued to make Shirley's life hell by putting her telephone number on a call-girl card and posting them around Walford. He later broke into her flat and tipped rubbish all over her floor. [[Ash Ferreira]] decided to step in and play him at his own game. He borrowed his brother's speakers and played [[dance music]] extremely loudly, which maddened Gavin and he reported them to the landlord. Shirley and Ash were ready for this, and upon the landlord's visit, they played [[european classical music|classical music]] and pretended they were involved in a book club. This satisfied the landlord and left Gavin looking like a fool. Obviously, this did not please Gavin and he threatened both Shirley and Ash, and made regular [[racist]] comments whenever any of the Ferreiras were around. A few days later, Ash overheard an altercation between Gavin and the road sweeper [[Gus Smith]]. Gavin was unhappy about the uncleanliness of the Square, particularly as it could attract [[rat]]s. Sensing Gavin's fear of rats, Ash and family convinced Gus to trap a rat in the Square, and with the help of [[Tariq Larousi]], he broke into Gavin's flat and set the rat free. The plan worked and Gavin was petrified. He promised to call a truce with Shirley if they removed the rat. 

However, Gavin decided to perform one last malicious act as payback. He sabotaged the Ferreiras clothing stock with [[paint]]. When the Ferreiras attempted to reclaim for the damages on their [[insurance]], they were furious to learn that [[Adi Ferreira|Adi]] had forgotten to renew it.

Gavin's last appearance was in October 2003.

{{-}}

== Geoff Morton ==
{{Infobox soap character 2 | series = EastEnders
|image=
|name=Geoff Morton
|portrayer=[[Maurice Roëves]]
|years=2003
|first=4 September 2003
|last=5 September 2003
|death = 4 March 2004
|daughters=[[Kate Mitchell]]
|}}
'''Detective Chief Inspector Geoff Morton''' was the alcoholic father of [[Kate Mitchell|Kate Morton]], who arrived for her wedding to [[Phil Mitchell]]. He was not impressed on Phil's stag night, when [[Minty Peterson]] told him about Phil's immigrant ex-wife [[Nadia Mitchell|Nadia]]. He was also disappointed that Phil did not drink, and accepted the dare of drinking a yard of ale, before being thrown out of [[The Queen Victoria|The Queen Vic]] for insulting [[Nana Moon]]. He then went to [[R&amp;R (EastEnders)#Angie's Den|Angie's Den]] where he insulted [[Little Mo Mitchell]] and was hit by her husband, [[Billy Mitchell (EastEnders)|Billy]]. He later refused to attend Kate and Phil's wedding, but had a conversation with Phil about alcoholism and returned to [[Newcastle upon Tyne|Newcastle]] to seek help, however, in March 2004, Kate heard the news that Geoff had committed suicide.
{{-}}

==Yolande Trueman==
{{Main|Yolande Trueman}}

==Graham Foster==
{{Infobox soap character 2 | series = EastEnders
|image=
|name=Graham Foster
|portrayer=[[Alex McSweeney]]
|years=2003–05
|first=17 September 2003
|last=24 January 2005
|classification=[[List of past EastEnders characters#Last appeared in 2005|Former; regular]]
|mother=[[Barbara Foster]]
|sons=[[Freddie Mitchell (EastEnders)|Freddie Mitchell]]
}}
'''Graham Foster''' first appeared in 2003 as a customer in [[The Queen Victoria]] pub and befriended barmaid [[Little Mo Mitchell]]. They became friends after discovering they both loved crosswords and Graham gave Mo a pen to use when she did them. He also bought her a rose when a flower salesman was in the pub. 

One night in The Queen Vic when he and Little Mo were alone, Graham refused to leave until the song that was playing on the [[jukebox]] ended (Mo did not know he had put the song on repeat). Graham eventually made his intentions towards Mo clear by trying to kiss her. She fled in fear, but Graham chased her and raped her on the pub floor. This resulted in her conceiving their son [[Freddie Mitchell (EastEnders)|Freddie]].

Little Mo's father, [[Charlie Slater]] subsequently assaulted Graham, resulting in three months imprisonment and a suspension of his taxi license. Graham then sued Charlie for compensation, which was paid by Little Mo's sister [[Kat Moon]] and her husband, [[Alfie Moon|Alfie]]. They offered and Graham accepted £10,000, which they had borrowed from [[Andy Hunter (EastEnders)|Andy Hunter]].
 
On 5 November 2004, Graham was sentenced to eight years in prison. Mo felt sorry for Graham's mother as the way he spoke to her, reminded Mo of the way Trevor used to speak to her. Mrs Foster was upset at having another grandchild she could not see so Mo gave her her address and asked her to keep in touch. 

Graham last appeared in January 2005 when Billy Mitchell went to visit him in prison after receiving a visiting order, which he requested. Graham goaded Billy about not being Freddie's real father and pointed out Freddie had siblings, two sisters. He told Billy that Freddie would probably look like him, and he was looking forward to seeing him when he was released in four years time.
{{-}}

==Mark Stone==
{{Infobox soap character 2 | series = EastEnders
|image=
|name=Mark Stone
|portrayer=[[William Ilkeley]]
|years=2003
|first=17 November 2003
|last=18 November 2003
|}}
'''Mark Stone''' was an old accomplice of [[Phil Mitchell]], who met him to discuss a robbery Phil planned on going on with [[Den Watts]].
{{-}}

==Victor Duke==
{{Infobox soap character 2 | series = EastEnders
|image=
|name=Victor Duke
|portrayer=[[Ben Thomas (actor)|Ben Thomas]]
|years=2003
|home=[[Trinidad]]
|first=17 November 2003
|last=24 November 2003
|wife=[[Yolande Trueman|Yolande Duke]] (?–2003)
}}
'''Victor Duke''' was the husband of [[Yolande Trueman|Yolande Duke]], who arrived in [[Walford]] when his wife had run away to live with [[Patrick Trueman]]. He offered Patrick £10,000 to dump Yolande, then told Yolande that Patrick asked for money to dump her, and when she saw Patrick with the money Victor tried to tempt him with, she took the money and left, saying she did not want to be with either of them. After Victor returned to Trinidad, Yolande returned to Walford with the money, to share it with Patrick. Yolande later divorced him.
{{-}}

==Mary Harkinson==
{{Infobox soap character 2 | series = EastEnders
|image=
|name=Mary Harkinson
|portrayer=[[Mary Woodvine]]
|years=2003
|first=2 December 2003
|last=26 December 2003
|father=[[Derek Harkinson]]
|mother=Cynthia Harkinson
|brothers=[[#Alex Harkinson|Alex Harkinson]]
|nephews=[[#Danny Harkinson|Danny Harkinson]]
}}
'''Mary Harkinson''' was the estranged daughter of [[Derek Harkinson]]. She had not seen her father since he walked out on her mother, Cynthia, to live with another man, Robert. When Derek's friend [[Pauline Fowler]] found out that Derek had children, she contacted Mary without telling Derek. Mary initially agreed to meet with Derek, but shut the door in his face when he arrived at her house. Derek eventually persuaded Mary to see him, and they met, along with Mary's brother [[#Alex Harkinson|Alex]] and his son [[#Danny Harkinson|Danny]]. Derek later left [[Walford]] to live with Mary after a string of arguments with Pauline.
{{-}}

==Edwin Caldecott==
{{Infobox soap character 2 | series = EastEnders
|name=Edwin Caldecott
|portrayer=[[Ron Moody]]
|years=2003
|first=8 December 2003
|last=18 December 2003
|occupation=[[Retired]]
}}
'''Edwin Caldecott''' was a nemesis of [[Jim Branning]], from his days as a [[boxing|boxer]]. Edwin goaded Jim into one final match, which his wife [[Dot Branning|Dot]] and granddaughter [[Sonia Fowler|Sonia Jackson]] had advised him against. On the day of the fight, Jim was geared up to fight Edwin, but when Dot appeared at the community centre, Jim was distracted and Edwin took the advantage to get first the punch in, knocking Jim flat. Dot decided to let Jim think he'd won afterward.

{{-}}

==Alex Harkinson==
{{Infobox soap character 2 | series = EastEnders
|image=
|name=Alex Harkinson
|portrayer=[[Ben Nealon]]
|years=2003
|first=12 December 2003
|last=26 December 2003
|father=[[Derek Harkinson]]
|mother=Cynthia Harkinson
|sisters=[[#Mary Harkinson|Mary Harkinson]]
|sons=[[#Danny Harkinson|Danny Harkinson]]
}}
'''Alex Harkinson''' was the estranged son of [[Derek Harkinson]]. He had not seen his father since he walked out on his mother, Cynthia, to live with another man, Robert, when Alex was eight years old. When Derek's friend [[Pauline Fowler]] found out that Derek had children, she contacted Mary without telling Derek. Mary initially agreed to meet with Derek, but shut the door in his face when he arrived at her house, so Pauline went to Alex's house to speak to him. Alex, not knowing that his father was [[homosexual|gay]], assumed that Pauline was the woman Derek had left Cynthia for, and told her to leave. Mary later visited Derek on Boxing Day 2003, and was followed by Alex, who berated her and argued with Derek, but later relented and introduced him to his son, [[#Danny Harkinson|Danny]].
{{-}}

==Danny Harkinson==
{{Infobox soap character 2 | series = EastEnders
|image=
|name=Danny Harkinson
|portrayer=[[Josh Alexander]]
|years=2003
|first=22 December 2003
|last=26 December 2003
|father=[[#Alex Harkinson|Alex Harkinson]]
|grandfathers=[[Derek Harkinson]]
|grandmothers=Cynthia Harkinson
|aunts=[[#Mary Harkinson|Mary Harkinson]]
}}
'''Danny Harkinson''' was the son of [[Derek Harkinson]]'s estranged son [[#Alex Harkinson|Alex]]. He had never met his grandfather until Alex and Derek reconciled on Boxing Day 2003, and Alex introduced him to Derek.
{{-}}

==Maxwell Moon==
{{Infobox soap character 2 | series = EastEnders
|image=
|name=Maxwell Moon
|portrayer= [[Andrew Paul]]
|years= 2003
|first=5 December 2003
|last=25 December 2003
|home = [[Australia]]
|occupation= Film crew
|father=Joseph Moon
|mother=Melissa Moon
|relatives=[[Alfie Moon]]&lt;br&gt;[[Spencer Moon]]&lt;br&gt;[[Jake Moon]]&lt;br&gt;[[Danny Moon]]
}}
'''Maxwell Moon''' the second cousin of [[Alfie Moon]], who he visited on 5 December 2003. He enjoyed a day of drinking and reminiscing about old times, but was offended when he realised Alfie had only invited him round to ask him a favour. Alfie wanted a snow machine for his wedding to [[Kat Moon|Kat Slater]], and he knew Maxwell could get him one, as he worked in the film business.
Maxwell ripped up his wedding invite, but Kat charmed him into coming to the wedding, while Alfie mended the invitation. Maxwell later attended the wedding and provided a snow machine.
When [[Spencer Moon|Spencer]] got into trouble with the police, he was sent to live with Maxwell in [[Australia]].
{{-}}

==Liza Moon==
{{Infobox soap character 2 | series = EastEnders
|image=
|name=Liza Moon
|portrayer=[[Joanne Adams]]
|years=2003
|first=5 December 2003
|last=8 December 2003
|mother=Marlene
|husband=[[Alfie Moon]] (1998–2003)
}}
'''Liza Moon''' was the estranged wife of [[Alfie Moon]]. She had not seen Alfie since he was sent to prison for [[credit card]] [[fraud]], but Alfie paid a visit to her when he needed a divorce so he could marry his new fiancée [[Kat Moon|Kat Slater]]. She did not want a divorce, but gave up on a reconciliation with Alfie when she realised he loved Kat and not her. She then agreed to a divorce, and Kat and Alfie married on [[Christmas Day]] 2003.
{{-}}

== Paula Campbell ==
{{Infobox soap character 2 | series = EastEnders
|image=
|name=Paula Campbell
|portrayer=[[Mia Soteriou]]
|years=2003
|first=16 December 2003
|last=19 December 2003
|occupation=Police officer
}}
'''Police Constable Paula Campbell''' was a police officer at [[Walford]] Constabulary. She was [[Little Mo Mitchell]]'s police liaison officer during her rape case against [[#Graham Foster|Graham Foster]]. Graham raped her and she pressed charges, so Paula was assigned the job of liaising with Mo and [[Slater family|her family]].
{{-}}

== Tony Macrae ==
{{Infobox soap character 2 | series = EastEnders
|image=
|name=Tony Macrae
|portrayer=[[Tam White]]
|years=2003–04
|first=31 December 2003
|last=2 January 2004
|home=Scotland
}}
'''Tony Macrae''' was a local who lived near the [[Scotland|Scottish]] hotel where [[Barry Evans (EastEnders)|Barry]] and [[Janine Evans]] were married. He acted as one of the witnesses, alongside [[Paul Trueman]], to Barry and Janine's quiet wedding in the hotel.

When Janine pushed Barry into a [[ravine]], Tony joined the search party to look for Barry, and eventually found his body in the ravine.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;[http://www.walfordweb.co.uk/walfordweb/whoswho-show.php?id=1625 Tony Macrae]&quot;, ''Walford Web''. URL last accessed 2007-06-05.&lt;/ref&gt;
{{-}}

==Others==
{| class=&quot;wikitable&quot;
! Date(s) !! Character !! Actor !! Circumstances
|-
|{{Anchor|Joel}}&lt;small&gt;01/01–28/02&lt;/small&gt;||'''Joel'''||[[Scott Adkins]]||Barman at [[Angie's Den]], employed by [[Sam Mitchell (EastEnders)|Sam Mitchell]], when he took his top off and she saw his torso. He was attracted to [[Vicki Fowler]].
|-
|{{Anchor|Malcolm}}&lt;small&gt;07/01–16/01&lt;/small&gt;||'''Malcolm'''&lt;br /&gt;'''Teresa'''||[[Peter McMichael]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Monica Gibb]]||[[Anthony Trueman]]'s practice partner and manager, whose company [[Kat Moon|Kat]] found boring.
|-
|{{Anchor|Ben}}&lt;small&gt;03/03&lt;/small&gt;||'''Ben'''||[[Neil McDermott]]||Replacement market cleaner for [[Robbie Jackson]] while he was on holiday. He annoys the locals and they put glue on his broom.
|-
|{{Anchor|D.S. Marsh}}&lt;small&gt;22/05–28/11&lt;br /&gt;20/01/2011&lt;/small&gt;||'''D.S. Marsh'''||[[Steve Money]]&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite episode |title= Episode dated 20/01/2011 |url=http://www.bbc.co.uk/programmes/b00xwwjt |series= EastEnders |serieslink=EastEnders |network=[[BBC]] |station=[[BBC One]] |city= |airdate=20 January 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;||&lt;!-- need 2003 details, 7 episodes: http://www.imdb.com/name/nm0597948/filmoseries#tt0088512 --&gt; In 2011, he investigates an attack on [[Connor Stanley]], interviewing [[Ricky Butcher]], [[Whitney Dean]], [[Max Branning]] and Connor.
|-
|{{Anchor|Aaron}}&lt;small&gt;14/10&lt;/small&gt;||'''Aaron'''||[[Thomas Aldridge]]||A member of a stag party at Angie's Den, who grabbed [[Sharon Rickman|Sharon]], and was thrown out by [[Den Watts|Den]] and [[Dennis Rickman|Dennis]].
|-
|{{Anchor|Leonard Jay}}&lt;small&gt;08/12–25/12&lt;/small&gt;||'''Leonard Jay'''||[[Geoff Leesley]]||Registrar who performed [[Alfie Moon|Alfie]] and [[Kat Moon]]'s wedding.
|}

== References ==
{{Reflist}}

==External links==
*{{EEcharlink|shirley_b|Shirley Benson}}
*{{EEcharlink|sasha_p|Sasha Perkins}}
*{{EEcharlink|jack_d|Jack Dalton}}
*{{EEcharlink|bobby-beale|Bobby Beale}}

{{EastEnders}}
{{EastEnders characters|year}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:List Of Eastenders Characters (2003)}}
[[Category:Lists of EastEnders characters|2003]]
[[Category:Fictional characters introduced in 2003|*, EastEnders]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
