<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="12810942" ns="0" title="List of EastEnders characters (1997)"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{DISPLAYTITLE:List of ''EastEnders'' characters (1997)}}
The following is a list of characters that first appeared in the [[BBC]] [[soap opera]] ''[[EastEnders]]'' in 1997, by order of first appearance.
{{TOClimit|limit=2}}

==Neelam Kapoor==
{{Infobox soap character 2 | series = EastEnders
|image= 
|name=Neelam Kapoor
|portrayer=[[Jamila Massey]]
|years=1997–98
|first=3 March 1997
|last=28 July 1998
|born=
|home=[[Bristol]]
|occupation=Shop proprietor
|sons=[[Sanjay Kapoor (EastEnders)|Sanjay Kapoor]]
|granddaughters=[[Sharmilla Kapoor]]
}}
'''Neelam Kapoor''' is a [[fictional character]] from the [[BBC]] [[soap opera]] ''[[EastEnders]]'', played by [[Jamila Massey]].

Neelam and her husband built themselves a profitable clothing business, but left it in the hands of their son, Sanjay, in the late 1980s and emigrated to their native [[India]]. However Sanjay proved to be a poor businessman and after some bad monetary investments, his business went [[bankrupt]]. Sanjay kept this from his parents and moved to Walford to open a clothing stall in 1993.

In February 1997 Sanjay heard news that his father had died. He travelled to India for the [[funeral]] and returned early in March with his mother in tow. Gita was horrified. She had always had a tempestuous relationship with Sanjay's interfering mother and she was furious that he'd brought her to live with them without her consent. Neelam, sensing Gita's disapproval, went out of her way to be as obliging as possible and she was even understanding upon hearing the clothing business had floundered. Gita begrudgingly began to accept Neelam's presence but found her domineering mannerisms a little irksome.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;[http://archives.walford.net/1420.htm ''EastEnders'' TUE 04-MAR-97  episode description]&quot;, ''Walford.net''. URL last accessed on 2007-03-30.&lt;/ref&gt; 

Neelam pitched in with the running of the Kapoor's market stall before buying the First Til Last grocery store in August 1997. Neelam was adamant that the shop should be run as a family business, so she fired the resident shop assistant, [[Carol Jackson]], which didn't go down well. Neelam continued to irritate Gita as the year wore on by instructing her on the upbringing of her daughter, Sharmilla, and accusing her of being a bad wife to Sanjay. Sanjay allowed Neelam to pamper him and cater to his every whim, which infuriated Gita further. By October Gita could take no more so she decided to leave Walford for a holiday with her sister, but not before telling Neelam a few home truths about Sanjay's adultery before departing. Neelam was appalled, but she was only to happy to believe her precious son when he claimed Gita was merely lying.

Gita was due to return in January 1998, but she went missing in suspicious circumstances and the police suspected foul play. It transpired that Gita had merely run away after falling [[pregnant]] with another man's baby. Sanjay tracked her down and Gita was persuaded to return to Walford with her new baby. Neelam was furious about Gita's immoral behaviour and would not condone Sanjay taking on another man's child as his own. She tried to convince him to divorce Gita and fight for custody of Sharmilla. Sanjay defiantly refused to do this, so Neelam sold her shop to [[Terry Raymond]] and left Walford to live with her extended family in [[Bristol]], disowning her son on the way out. Her last appearance was in July 1998.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;[http://archives.walford.net/1651.htm ''EastEnders'' TUE 28-JUL-98 episode description]&quot;, ''Walford.net''. URL last accessed on 2007-03-30.&lt;/ref&gt;
{{-}}

==Courtney Mitchell==
{{Infobox soap character 2 | series = EastEnders
|image= 
|caption=Megan Jossa as Courtney Mitchell in 2006.
|name= Courtney Mitchell
|introducer=[[Jane Harris (producer)|Jane Harris]] &lt;small&gt;(1997)&lt;/small&gt;&lt;br /&gt;[[Kate Harwood]] &lt;small&gt;(2006)&lt;/small&gt;
|portrayer=Carissa O'Meara &lt;small&gt;(1997–99)&lt;/small&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Josephine O'Meara &lt;small&gt;(1997–99)&lt;/small&gt;&lt;br /&gt;[[Megan Jossa]] &lt;small&gt;(2006)&lt;/small&gt;
|years=1997–99, 2006
|born=11 March 1997
|first=11 March 1997
|last=9 June 2006
|home=[[Portugal]]
|classification=[[List of past EastEnders characters#Last appeared in 2006|Former; regular]]
|family=[[Mitchell family|Mitchell]]
|father= [[Grant Mitchell (EastEnders)|Grant Mitchell]]
|mother= [[Tiffany Mitchell]]
|halfbrothers= Mark Fowler Jr
|grandfathers= Eric Mitchell&lt;br /&gt;[[Terry Raymond]]
|grandmothers=[[Peggy Mitchell]] &lt;br&gt; [[Louise Raymond]]
|uncles= [[Phil Mitchell]] &lt;br&gt; [[Simon Raymond]]
|aunts=[[Sam Mitchell (EastEnders)|Sam Mitchell]]
|cousins=[[Ben Mitchell (EastEnders)|Ben Mitchell]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Louise Mitchell]]&lt;br /&gt;[[List of EastEnders characters (2010)#Richard Mitchell|Richard Mitchell]]
}}

'''Courtney Mitchell''' is a [[fictional character]] from the [[BBC]] [[soap opera]] ''[[EastEnders]]''. She is the daughter of characters [[Grant Mitchell (EastEnders)|Grant]] ([[Ross Kemp]]) and [[Tiffany Mitchell]] ([[Martine McCutcheon]]). From her birth in 1997 until 1999, Courtney was played by identical [[twin]]s Carissa and Josephine O'Meara. She was written out of the soap when Ross Kemp decided to quit. When Grant and Courtney returned in 2006, Courtney was played by [[Megan Jossa]] until they departed once again in June that year. Jossa said: &quot;I couldn't believe it when I heard I had got the part... it's going to be amazing and I can't wait.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://news.bbc.co.uk/cbbcnews/hi/newsid_4620000/newsid_4627500/4627592.stm|title=Grant's daughter back in 'Enders|publisher=[[BBC Online]]|date=19 January 2006|accessdate=4 September 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt; Described as &quot;charming, intelligent yet spoilt&quot;, Courtney &quot;loves being the centre of attention and hates sharing the spotlight with anyone&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.digitalspy.co.uk/soaps/a28246/mitchell-kids-to-return-to-walford.html|title=Mitchell kids to return to Walford|publisher=[[Digital Spy]]|date=19 January 2006|accessdate=4 September 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt;   

Courtney was born prematurely by [[caesarean section]] in March 1997. At first it was unknown whether her father was Grant Mitchell or [[Tony Hills]], but a DNA test revealed that Grant was her father. Grant and Tiffany separated and Tiffany was about to leave with Courtney on New Year's Eve 1998, but while chasing Grant who had snatched Courtney, she was struck and killed by [[Frank Butcher]]'s car.

Grant and Courtney move to [[Rio de Janeiro]] in October 1999, and Courtney lives with her dad and stepmother [[Carla Mitchell|Carla]], before returning to [[London]] on 27 March 2006 with Grant. Beyond mischievous, Courtney often refuses to do as she's told, backtalks, and argues with her cousin Ben. Ben actually tells Courtney that her father killed her mother. Initially she refuses to believe Grant's claim that Tiffany's death was an accidentoften refusing to do as she is told, answers back and continually bullies and argues with her cousin, Ben. Ben tells Courtney that Grant killed her mother, Tiffany, causing various problems in Courtney's behaviour and she initially refuses to believe Grant when he said Tiffany's death was an accident. 

When Grant's wife [[Carla Mitchell|Carla]] arrives, Courtney shows her blatant dislike. Grant decides that they should move to [[Portugal]] for a fresh start. But he dumps Carla on 9 June 2006 after discovering that she plans to fleece him and run off with another man, so just Grant and Courtney move to Portugal. Courtney was last heard on the phone to Peggy in 2010.
{{-}}

==Polly Becker==
{{Main|Polly Becker}}

==Alex Healy==
{{Main|Alex Healy (EastEnders)}}

==Annie Palmer==
{{Main|Annie Palmer}}

==Lorna Cartwright==
{{Main|Lorna Cartwright}}

==Irene Raymond==
{{Main|Irene Raymond}}

==Susan Rose==
{{Infobox soap character 2 | series = EastEnders
|image= 
|name=Susan Rose
|portrayer=[[Tilly Vosburgh]]
|years=1997–99
|first=25 August 1997
|last=14 February 1999
|home = Leeds
|occupation= 
|husband=[[Michael Rose (EastEnders)|Michael Rose]]
|sons=[[Matthew Rose (EastEnders)|Matthew Rose]]
}}
'''Susan Rose''', played by [[Tilly Vosburgh]],  is the ex-wife of market inspector [[Michael Rose (EastEnders)|Michael Rose]] and mother of [[Matthew Rose (EastEnders)|Matthew Rose]].

She arrived in [[Walford]] in 1997 along with her son Matthew. She started suffering from [[multiple sclerosis]] and Michael and Matthew ended up caring for her. Michael and Susan's relationship took an upward turn as a result of this and they soon rekindled their relationship. When a new market inspector [[Lisa Fowler|Lisa Shaw]] arrived in Walford in late 1998, Michael became attracted to her, and soon after, he and Lisa started an affair. Michael ended the affair with Lisa within weeks after Susan wanted Michael to move away with her to [[Leeds]]. Susan and Michael left Walford together in 1999 and Susan was unaware of Michael and Lisa's fling. Although Michael occasionally returned to Walford to support Matthew who was on trial for the murder of [[Saskia Duncan]], although the real culprit was [[Steve Owen (EastEnders)|Steve Owen]]. Susan did not return and has not been seen since.
{{-}}

==Matthew Rose==
{{Main|Matthew Rose (EastEnders)}}

==Julie Haye==
{{Main|Julie Haye}}

==Conor Flaherty==
{{Main|Conor Flaherty}}

==Mary Flaherty==
{{Main|Mary Flaherty (EastEnders)}}

==Maggie Flaherty==
{{Main|EastEnders episodes in Ireland#Maggie Flaherty}}

==Sean Flaherty==
{{Main|EastEnders episodes in Ireland#Sean Flaherty}}

==Eamonn Flaherty==
{{Main|EastEnders episodes in Ireland#Eamonn Flaherty}}

==Brenda Flaherty==
{{Main|EastEnders episodes in Ireland#Brenda Flaherty}}

==Collette Flaherty==
{{Main|EastEnders episodes in Ireland#Collette Flaherty}}

==Gerry McCrae==
{{Main|EastEnders episodes in Ireland#Gerry McCrae}}

==Eamonn Flaherty Jr.==
{{Main|EastEnders episodes in Ireland#Eamonn Flaherty Jr.}}

==John Flaherty==
{{Main|EastEnders episodes in Ireland#Other family members}}

==Declan Flaherty==
{{Main|EastEnders episodes in Ireland#Other family members}}

==Carl Flaherty==
{{Main|EastEnders episodes in Ireland#Other family members}}

==Kylie Flaherty==
{{Main|EastEnders episodes in Ireland#Other family members}}

==Jessie Moore==
{{Infobox soap character 2 | series = EastEnders
|image=
|name=Jessie Moore
|portrayer=[[Chelsey Paden]]
|born=3 February 1991
|years=1997–98
|first=7 October 1997
|last=5 May 1998
|mother=[[Nicole Moore]]
}}
'''Jessie Moore''' had been put into [[foster care]] when her drug addict mother was imprisoned on remand for various offences. In October 1997 Jessie was housed with [[Mark Fowler|Mark]] and [[Ruth Fowler]] in Walford. Six year old Jessie was a deeply troubled child, who was extremely shy and refused to speak initially. She was also a bedwetter and Mark and Ruth seemed unable to get her to open up to them, but they eventually managed to make progress and they became extremely attached to her.

In 1998, Jessie's mother, Nicole, telephoned the Fowlers and asked Jessie to visit her in prison. Mark refused to allow this, but the [[social worker]] assured him that Nicole had completed her [[Drug detoxification|de-tox]] programme and that contact between her and Jessie was particularly important. Jessie visited and became excited to learn that Nicole would soon be released from prison. 

Nicole paid Jessie an impromptu visit on the day of her 7th birthday in February 1998. Nicole had found herself a bedsit and wanted to take Jessie back. Mark and Ruth tried to contest Nicole's decision, but they were told that reuniting children with their parents was what fostering was all about. 

Nicole spent several weeks visiting Jessie to rebuild their relationship and eventually Ruth and Mark realised how close they were. They retracted their opposition and Nicole was given custody of Jessie in March 1998. Ruth was particularly saddened by Jessie's departure and she bought her a necklace to remind her of the time they had spent together. 
{{-}}

==Hazel Foster==
{{Infobox soap character 2 | series = EastEnders
|image=
|name=Hazel Foster
|portrayer=[[Jean Rimmer]]
|years=1997
|appeared=21 October 1997
|daughters=[[Lorraine Wicks]]
|grandsons=[[Joe Wicks]]
|granddaughters=Karen Wicks
|home=Bolton
|}}
'''Hazel Foster''' was the mother of [[Lorraine Wicks]], who [[Mary Flaherty (EastEnders)|Mary Flaherty]] visited in Bolton to try and track down [[Joe Wicks|Joe]].
{{-}}

==Ros Thorne==
{{Infobox soap character 2 | series = EastEnders
|image=
|name=Ros Thorne
|portrayer=[[Clare Grogan]]
|years=1997–98
|first=3 November 1997
|last=10 April 1998
|occupation=[[Private Investigator]]
|}}
'''Ros Thorne''' was a Scottish private detective who [[Ian Beale]] hired to trace his two sons, [[Steven Beale|Steven]] and [[Peter Beale|Peter]]. Steven and Peter had been taken by their mother, [[Cindy Beale|Cindy]], following her failed attempt to have Ian killed by a professional hitman in 1996.

Ian and Ros discovered that Cindy was residing in [[Italy]] and followed her there in November 1997. While hunting for Cindy, Ian and Ros became attracted to each other. They had a brief sexual encounter, though their relationship never progressed into anything serious as Ian was preoccupied with his children. After days of searching, Ros eventually found Cindy working in an Italian bar and she and Ian concocted a plan to abscond with Ian's children. They lured Cindy into a trap, while [[Phil Mitchell|Phil]] and [[Grant Mitchell (EastEnders)|Grant Mitchell]] kidnapped Steven and Peter and brought them to the airport to reunite with their father. Despite a few hitches, Ian managed to bring the children safely back to Walford, with Cindy in pursuit. 

Cindy threatened to take Ian to court for custody of the children. Ian continued to use Ros to investigate Cindy and her new partner, [[#Nick Holland|Nick Holland]]—a rich businessman who was funding the custody case. Ros also began investigating Ian's hitman, [[John Valecue]], who was now being held in prison for an unrelated murder. Valecue was unwilling to admit that Cindy hired him to kill Ian, as his sentence would likely increase if he admitted to his involvement. However, after [[Annie Palmer]] threatened him with severe repercussions from her associates within the prison, Valecue eventually confessed. Cindy was arrested and imprisoned, and Ian was given custody of his children. Ros was not seen again following the completion of the case.
{{-}}

==Melanie Thomas==
{{Infobox soap character 2 | series = EastEnders
|image=
|name=Melanie Thomas
|portrayer=[[Ava Healy]]
|years=1997
|first=13 November 1997
|last=14 November 1997
|occupation=Councillor
}}
'''Melanie Thomas''' was [[Ian Beale]]'s opponent in the election for a seat on [[Walford]] Council. She won the seat and later annoyed Ian by approving [[Alex Healy (EastEnders)|Alex Healy]]'s application for a shelter for homeless people in Bridge Street, called Bridge House, which Ian was strongly opposed to.
{{-}}

==Nick Holland==
{{Infobox soap character 2 | series = EastEnders
|image=
|name=Nick Holland
|portrayer=[[Dominic Taylor]]
|years=1997–98
|first=12 November 1997
|last=10 April 1998 
|home= [[Italy]]
|occupation= Businessman
|daughters=[[Cindy Williams (EastEnders)|Cindy Williams]]
|}}
'''Nick Holland''' first appeared in 1997 when [[Cindy Beale]] met him in [[Italy]] while on the run after escaping from [[Walford]] with her children. They became lovers, and Cindy became pregnant with his child.

When Cindy's ex-husband [[Ian Beale]] tracked her down and stole the children back from Cindy and returned to Walford, Nick at first tried to help Cindy and came with her back to Walford to get custody of the children. But during the trial Cindy was arrested for attempted murder of Ian and Nick realised what Cindy was really like.

Nick returned to Italy after the trial ended. After Cindy died while giving birth in prison, Nick never came back for his daughter also named [[Cindy Williams (EastEnders)|Cindy Williams]], who was sent to live with her grandparents in [[Cornwall]].
{{-}}

==Josh Saunders==
{{Infobox soap character 2 | series = EastEnders
|image= 
|name=Josh Saunders
|portrayer=[[Jon Lee (singer and actor)|Jon Lee]]
|years=1997–98
|first=18 November 1997
|last=30 April 1998
|home=[[Scotland]]
|occupation= Student
|mother=[[Julie Haye]]
|father=[[Eliot Saunders]]
|}}
'''Josh Saunders''' is a [[fictional character]] from the BBC soap opera ''[[EastEnders]]'', played by [[Jon Lee (singer and actor)|Jon Lee]] between 1997 and 1998.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url= http://findarticles.com/p/articles/mi_qn4161/is_20030413/ai_n12863948 |title= Fashion: Join the club |publisher=''Sunday Mirror'' |accessdate=2007-10-21 | first=Dierdre | last=O'Brien | date=13 April 2003}}&lt;/ref&gt; Josh was a love interest for the  character [[Clare Bates]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url= http://www.bbc.co.uk/eastenders/characters_cast/characters/character_clare_b.shtml |title= Clare Bates |publisher=''BBC'' |accessdate=2007-10-21}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Josh was introduced as part of a storyline to aid the departure of the long-running characters, [[Nigel Bates|Nigel]] and [[Clare Bates]] (played by [[Paul Bradley (actor)|Paul Bradley]] and [[Gemma Bissix]]). Actor Paul Bradley had decided to leave the serial, reportedly for fear of being typecast.&lt;ref name=&quot;nerd&quot;&gt;{{cite news|url= http://findarticles.com/p/articles/mi_qn4161/is_19971116/ai_n14470623 |title= LOVE AT LAST FOR NIGEL THE NERD|publisher=''[[Daily Mirror|The Mirror]]'' | date = 1997-11-16| accessdate=2007-10-21}}&lt;/ref&gt; The writers of ''EastEnders'' wanted to give Nigel a happy ending, so a character named [[Julie Haye]] ([[Karen Henthorn]]) was invented to be a love interest for Nigel, whilst her son, Josh, was invented to be a love interest for Nigel's daughter, Clare.&lt;ref name=&quot;gazette&quot;&gt;{{cite news|url= http://www.wgazette.com/wint04-henthorn.html |title= Interview with Karen Henthorn|publisher=''Walford Gazette'' |accessdate=2007-10-21}}&lt;/ref&gt; 

Josh, was played by [[Jon Lee (singer and actor)|Jon Lee]], who went on to find greater fame as a singer in the successful pop band, [[S Club 7]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url= http://www.jonleeofficial.com/bio.php|title= Jone Lee|publisher=''www.jonleeofficial.com'' | accessdate=2007-10-21 |archiveurl = http://web.archive.org/web/20071016172221/http://jonleeofficial.com/bio.php &lt;!-- Bot retrieved archive --&gt; |archivedate = 2007-10-16}}&lt;/ref&gt; Lee has said that he won a part in ''EastEnders'' “by complete accident really.”&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url= http://www.wgazette.com/wint04-henthorn.html |title= The Big Interview: Jon Lee|publisher=officiallondontheatre.co.uk|accessdate=2007-10-21}}&lt;/ref&gt; He played the role of Josh for six months. When the storyline reached its end, the Bates family joined Josh and his mother for a new life in [[Scotland]]. Josh last appeared in April 1998.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url= http://gaydarnation.com/UserPortal/Article/Detail.aspx?ID=6024&amp;sid=43 |title= Totty Watch |publisher=gaydarnation.com|accessdate=2007-10-21}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Storylines===
Josh Saunders was first seen as a pupil rescuing [[Clare Bates]] from a gang of bullies—her former friends who became her enemies after she refused to socialise with them. Clare developed an instant crush on Josh, and she spent the following few weeks trying to impress him. They started dating, despite initial objections from Clare's father. It transpired that Josh was actually the son of Clare's teacher, [[Julie Haye]]. Clare was mortified by this initially, and she refused to speak to Josh for a brief period. She soon came to accept the situation, and was even pleased when her father, [[Nigel Bates|Nigel]], began dating Josh's mother.

Josh found himself caught in the middle of his warring parents—his father, [[List of EastEnders characters (1998)#Eliot Saunders|Eliot]], had been furious when Julie announced that she was planning to move to Scotland with Josh in 1998. Josh's father was Jewish, and Josh was obliged to have a [[Bar Mitzvah]] to appease his father before he left for Scotland. Josh was initially opposed to this, as he was not remotely interested in religion. He started missing his Bar Mitzvah tutorials, which did not please his father; he was told that performing the ceremony was ultimately his choice, but if he did not do it before he left, his family would not be present to support him. Josh decided to go ahead with the Bar Mitzvah. It took place in March 1998 and Clare was present as his guest.

Nigel and Julie's relationship ended when Nigel began to have second thoughts—he felt that he was betraying his deceased wife. Julie and Josh left Walford for Scotland in April 1998. Clare was upset to see Josh go, they said their goodbyes, but just at the last minute, Nigel changed his mind again, and asked Julie if he and Clare could move to Scotland with her and Josh. Clare was overjoyed and Josh and Julie returned to collect the Bateses a few weeks later.

Following Clare's return to Walford a decade later, in 2008, she revealed that as she had aged, Josh had taken her place in Nigel's affections.
{{-}}

==Jeff Healy==
{{Infobox soap character 2 | series = EastEnders
|image= 
|name=Jeff Healy
|portrayer=[[Leslie Schofield]]
|years=1997–2000
|first=9 December 1997
|last=3 August 2000
|born= 26 March 1945
|occupation=Handyman
|wife=[[Jane Healy]]
|sons=[[Alex Healy (EastEnders)|Alex Healy]]
|daughters=[[Melanie Owen]]&lt;br /&gt;Katie Healy
}}

'''Jeff Healy''' is played by [[Leslie Schofield]], introduced in 1997. The character was axed in 2000 by executive producer [[John Yorke (producer)|John Yorke]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|work=BBC News|date= 2 March 2000|url= http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/entertainment/664219.stm|title=Axe falls on five EastEnders|accessdate= 2 April 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; 

He is an [[atheist]] who disapproves of his son being a vicar. He first arrived in [[Albert Square]] in December 1997 to try and rebuild bridges with his son [[Alex Healy (EastEnders)|Alex]]. One of Jeff's daughters, [[Melanie Owen|Melanie]], made a reappearance in his life and the three of them gradually began living as a family again. Jeff had a brief courtship with [[Pauline Fowler]] but was rejected when he proposed to her. Jeff left [[Walford]] in August 2000.
{{-}}

==References==
{{reflist}}

==External links==
*{{EEcharlink|courtney_m|Courtney Mitchell}}

{{EastEnders}}
{{EastEnders characters|year}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:List Of Eastenders Characters (1997)}}
[[Category:Lists of EastEnders characters|1997]]
[[Category:Fictional characters introduced in 1997|*, EastEnders]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
