<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="12811303" ns="0" title="List of EastEnders characters (2001)"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{DISPLAYTITLE:List of ''EastEnders'' characters (2001)}}
{{Use dmy dates|date=December 2010}}
The following is a list of characters that first appeared in the [[BBC]] [[soap opera]] ''[[EastEnders]]'' in 2001, by order of appearance.
{{TOClimit|limit=2}}

==Jill Marsden==
{{Infobox soap character 2 | series = EastEnders
|image=
|name=Jill Marsden
|portrayer=[[Sophie Stanton]]
|years=2001–03, 2009–10, 2011-
|classification=[[List of past EastEnders characters#Last appeared in 2010|Former; recurring]]
|first = 5 March 2001
|born=27 November
|occupation=[[Detective Chief Inspector]]
}}
'''Detective Chief Inspector Jill Marsden''' first appears as the investigating police officer when [[Phil Mitchell]] ([[Steve McFadden]]) is shot in March 2001. Marsden reappears whenever Phil is suspected of being involved in a crime, including the suspected murder of [[Lisa Fowler]] ([[Lucy Benjamin]]). She originally appears between 5 March 2001 when Phil is shot and 22 December 2003 when Phil is arrested for armed robbery. She returns on 28 December 2009 to investigate the murder of [[Archie Mitchell]] ([[Larry Lamb (actor)|Larry Lamb]]).&lt;ref name=&quot;marsden return&quot;&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.digitalspy.co.uk/soaps/s2/eastenders/news/a186176/dci-jill-marsden-returns-to-eastenders.html|title=DCI Jill Marsden returns to 'EastEnders'|publisher=[[Digital Spy]]|first=Kris|last=Green|date=10 November 2009|accessdate=10 November 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt; A source is quoted as saying: &quot;Marsden has a score to settle with Phil. She was never far behind Phil when he put a foot out of place all those years ago and she's back with a vengeance. With so many people in the frame for Archie's murder, Marsden has a difficult job on her hands if she wants to pin it on Phil.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;marsden return&quot;/&gt; 

===Storylines===
In 2001, Jill helps set up the honey-trap on Phil with PC [[Kate Mitchell|Kate Morton]] ([[Jill Halfpenny]]) and DI [[Dominic Price]] (Paul Brennen) and fires Kate when she falls for Phil. 

She reappears on Albert Square in 2010. She arrives on the scene and wants to question the Mitchells first, saying &quot;it was only a matter of time&quot;. Several people say they suspect [[Janine Butcher]] ([[Charlie Brooks]]), but Marsden waits before questioning her. When she sees Phil, she says it is good to see him again and looks forward to catching up with him soon. She makes a television appeal for witnesses and later interviews Phil, but he is given an alibi by his girlfriend [[Shirley Carter]] ([[Linda Henry]]). A few days later, a red fingernail is found at the scene of the murder, so Marsden visits the  female locals, checking their hands. Seeing an upset [[Heather Trott]] ([[Cheryl Fergison]]), knowing that she is vulnerable and lives with Shirley, talks about Christmas Day and Heather lets slip that Phil wasn't there. She talks to Phil and later visits his home, asking to see the clothes he was wearing on Christmas Day. Shirley shows her a clean shirt, and Marsden closes down the laundrette, hoping anyone with blood-stained clothes will not be able to wash them. After a tip-off, Marsden arrests [[Sam Mitchell (EastEnders)|Sam Mitchell]] ([[Daniella Westbrook]]), but she accuses her mother, [[Peggy Mitchell]] ([[Barbara Windsor]]), of the murder. Marsden confirms she was there to talk to Peggy, questioning Peggy and Sam at the police station. Peggy is released without charge but Sam is detained for jumping bail. Marsden visits Janine, who insists people will say anything to get her in trouble. She asks Janine why she was out in the cold on Christmas Day and asks if Janine knows where Archie's laptop is as it has gone missing.

On 15 January, Marsden arrests [[Ian Beale]] ([[Adam Woodyatt]]) after Janine tells Marsden that Ian took advantage of her, stole Archie's laptop containing a recording of them having sex, and dumped it in the canal. Ian refuses to talk but when Marsden shows him CCTV footage of him dumping the laptop and then shows him the recovered laptop, he admits visiting Archie on Christmas Day as Archie was threatening him. He wanted to delete the recording but denies murdering Archie but Marsden charges him, regardless. On 26 January, Janine tells Marsden she saw Ian leave The Queen Victoria on Christmas Day but the bust of Queen Victoria was on the bar after he left. Marsden places Janine at the scene but she also denies murdering Archie. Marsden tells Ian that although the murder charge will be dropped, he will still be charged with burglary and theft of Acrhie's laptop. On 28 January, she and [[Wayne Hughes (EastEnders)|DC Wayne Hughes]] ([[Jamie Treacher]]) attend Archie's funeral, watching people's reactions, hoping for a new lead, and see Peggy return to his grave and apologise. Marsden asks what for and Peggy explains that she didn't believe him when he said his cancer had returned.

The following week, [[Ronnie Mitchell]] ([[Samantha Womack]]) spots her ex-boyfriend [[Jack Branning]] ([[Scott Maslen]]) talking to Marsden. Jack tells Ronnie that he was fishing for information. With no new leads, Marsden's boss threatens to take her off the case so she reviews the suspects and decides to question Jack as he is asking more questions than he has answered. In the café, Marsden and Hughes discuss new information she has, making sure that she is overheard. [[Chinese whisper]]-style rumours then begin circulating, ending with people saying Marsden is going to arrest Ronnie. Ronnie sees Marsden in the Square and a struggle ensues. Ronnie hits Marsden, knocking her to the ground, and is arrested and charged with assaulting a police officer but released on bail. Marsden suspects Ronnie more, saying she has now shown her true colours. Later, [[Jasmine Field|DC Jasmine Field]] ([[Karen Ascoe]]) enters the pub with other officers to arrest someone and Ronnie leaves Walford. Jack confronts Marsden for unnecessarily sending a uniformed officer to arrest [[Dot Branning]] ([[June Brown]]) to unsettle the locals, and realises that there was no new information. Janine tells Marsden that Ronnie has fled but finds her at The Queen Victoria when she asks for her. She reveals that a new forensic profile has been found and DNA screening of white males will begin shortly. After Hughes takes a bribe from Jack to make the DNA samples disappear, Marsden receives an anonymous tip-off. The police search Janine's flat and find the engagement ring that went missing on the night of Archie's murder, and Janine is arrested, but is shortly released due to lack of evidence. [[Becca Swanson (EastEnders)|Becca Swanson]] ([[Simone James]]) calls the police, saying that [[Bradley Branning]] ([[Charlie Clements]]) attacked Archie on Christmas Day, and the police arrive to arrest him. Marsden spots him when his phone rings, and two police officers chase him to the rooftops where he stumbles and falls to his death. The investigation ends as the police believe Bradley killed Archie, but his killer was actually [[Stacey Slater]] ([[Lacey Turner]]).

==Ritchie Stringer==
{{Infobox soap character 2 | series = EastEnders
|image=
|name=Ritchie Stringer
|portrayer=[[Gareth Hunt]]
|years=2001
|first=10 April 2001
|last=12 April 2001
|classification=[[List of past EastEnders characters#Last appeared in 2001|Former; guest]]
|occupation=Gangster
}}
'''Ritchie Stringer''' was a gang boss who knew [[Phil Mitchell]]. Phil contacted him in April 2001 to call in a few favours. Ritchie and Phil had a mutual acquaintance, [[Dan Sullivan (EastEnders)|Dan Sullivan]]. Phil asked Ritchie to help him frame Dan. Dan had worked for Ritchie in the past, and so he did not suspect anything untoward when Ritchie provided him with a gun to do a raid on Phil. However it was all part of Phil's plan, and Dan was caught by the police in the middle of the armed robbery. It transpired that the gun Ritchie had given Dan, was the same gun that [[Lisa Fowler|Lisa Shaw]] had used to shoot Phil earlier that year. Dan was blamed for the shooting.

Ritchie Stringer was 10/3 at [[Ladbrokes]] bookmakers as the culprit in the &quot;[[Who Shot Phil?]]&quot; storyline, despite not being one of the [[Who Shot Phil?#Suspects|named suspects]].&lt;ref&gt;&quot;[http://www.bbc.co.uk/threecounties/content/articles/2004/10/11/gentle_hook_gareth_hunt_feature.shtml Gareth will have you hooked?]&quot;, ''BBC''. Retrieved 14 March 2007.&lt;/ref&gt; When the BBC announced that actor [[Gareth Hunt]] was appearing in ''EastEnders'', there was a massive betting flurry on Ritchie being the culprit. Bookmakers William Hill even &quot;closed the book&quot;. William Hill spokesman Graham Sharpe commented that there were &quot;dozens of calls&quot; within half an hour of a 16/1 price being quoted and the bookmakers had nearly been &quot;knocked over in the rush of punters wanting to place bets of hundreds of pounds on the actor&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;[http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/entertainment/1204282.stm Betting flurry on EastEnders killing]&quot;, ''BBC''. Retrieved 14 March 2007.&lt;/ref&gt; William Hill decided to reopen the book later in the week after &quot;information from unofficial BBC sources had convinced them that [Gareth Hunt's] character [was] not the killer.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;&quot;[http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/entertainment/1207435.stm Hunt 'ruled out' of EastEnders shooting]&quot;, ''BBC''. Retrieved 14 March 2007.&lt;/ref&gt;
{{-}}

==Paul Trueman==
{{Main|Paul Trueman}}
'''Paul Trueman''' was played by [[Gary Beadle]] between 2001 and 2004. Gary was introduced as part of the already established Trueman family. He was portrayed as a bad boy. Beadle left the role in 2004, following a suspension, reportedly for failing to learn his lines. In his exit storyline, Paul became a [[drug dealer]], and Beadle has been critical of the storyline, suggesting it played into black, racial stereotyping. It was implied that Paul was killed upon his exit, though his death was not screened.

==Donna Andrews==
{{Infobox soap character 2 
|series = EastEnders
|image=
|name=Donna Andrews
|portrayer=Alison Senior (2001) &lt;br/&gt; Paula Jennings (2001–02)
|years=2001–02
|first=24 April 2001
|last=8 November 2002
|classification=[[List of past EastEnders characters#Last appeared in 2002|Former; recurring]]
|sons = [[#Sean Andrews|Sean Andrews]]
|occupation=[[Mistress]]
}}
'''Donna Andrews''', played by Allison Senior (2001) and Paula Jennings (2001–02), is the mistress of [[Trevor Morgan (EastEnders)|Trevor Morgan]] ([[Alex Ferns]]), who first appears on 24 April when [[Billy Mitchell (EastEnders)|Billy Mitchell]] ([[Perry Fenwick]]) spots them entering Donna's house. A few days later, after much agonising over whether to tell [[Little Mo Mitchell|Little Mo Morgan]] ([[Kacey Ainsworth]]), Trevor's wife, Billy takes Little Mo to see for herself. On 28 August, Little Mo's sisters, [[Kat Moon|Kat Slater]] ([[Jessie Wallace]]) and [[Lynne Hobbs]] ([[Elaine Lordan]]), reveal that Donna is pregnant with Trevor's baby. Little Mo went to visit Donna several days later, and was urged by her not to let Trevor hurt her any more.

The following summer, Donna appears at Little Mo's trial for assaulting Trevor with an iron and gives evidence against Trevor. This proves fruitless as Little Mo is found guilty and given a prison sentence, although her conviction for attempted murder is quashed on appeal and she is released from prison within weeks of the verdict.

Donna next appears in November, when Trevor forces her way into her home in [[Swindon]] and attacked her and kidnaps their son, Sean. On his return to Walford, Trevor also captures Little Mo and attempts to kill them all in a house fire, only for Little Mo and Sean to be rescued, but Trevor and local fireman [[Tom Banks (EastEnders)|Tom Banks]] ([[Colm Ó Maonlaí]]) die in the resulting explosion, leaving Donna feeling Little Mo should be grieving for Tom, rather than Trevor. Donna makes her last appearance was on 8 November, a week after Trevor's death.
{{-}}

==Harry Slater==
{{Infobox soap character 2 | series = EastEnders
|image=
|name=Harry Slater
|portrayer=[[Michael Elphick]]
|years=2001
|first=3 May 2001
|last=4 October 2001
|born= 5 January 1946
|death= 4 February 2002&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.bbc.co.uk/pressoffice/proginfo/tv/2010/wk7/feature_eastenders.shtml |title=Press Office - Network TV Programme Information BBC Week 7 EastEnders feature |publisher=BBC |date= |accessdate=20 December 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|occupation=[[Businessperson|Bar owner]]
|classification=[[List of past EastEnders characters#Last appeared in 2001|Former; regular]]
|father = Frederick Slater
|mother = Mary Slater
|brothers =[[Charlie Slater]]
|sisters=Violet Slater
|daughters=[[Zoe Slater]]
|nieces= [[Lynne Hobbs]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Kat Moon]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Little Mo Mitchell]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Belinda Peacock]]
}}
'''Harold &quot;Harry&quot; Slater''', played by [[Michael Elphick]], is the younger brother of [[Charlie Slater]] ([[Derek Martin]]) and uncle of [[Kat Moon|Kat Slater]] ([[Jessie Wallace]]) whom he raped when she was a child.

Harry was the uncle of Kat. Harry used to groom her as a child and it was later revealed that Harry had [[raped]] his niece Kat when she was 13 years old and therefore Kat became pregnant with [[Zoe Slater]] ([[Michelle Ryan]]). Zoe was initially thought to have been Kat's sister but she was in fact is Kat's and Harry's daughter. Charlie didn't know the father was Harry so he decided to raise Zoe as his own daughter and Kat had to become her sister. Harry fled to Spain soon after the incident and didn't reappear until the death of his sister, Violet, in 1988. After Violet's funeral, Harry quickly left again.

===Storylines===
Harry arrives in [[Walford]] on 3 May to visit his older brother, Charlie. He develops a romance with [[Peggy Mitchell]] ([[Barbara Windsor]]) and they quickly make plans to get married and emigrate to [[Spain]], where Harry lives. Zoe announces she is leaving Walford to live with Harry in Spain and a furious Kat refuses to let her go. Zoe storms out saying she's leaving and Kat follows. The two argue and Kat shouts that she is her mother. When Zoe demands that Kat tell her who her real father is, Kat shocks her by revealing that it's Harry. Charlie discovers this and goes to find Harry and attacks him in [[The Queen Victoria]] but is restrained by the punters. Charlie threatens Harry to leave Walford, telling him to never return again otherwise he will kill him. He also warned that he is to end his engagement with Peggy and he does so by writing her a letter. He arrives at the Slaters' saying he is ashamed of his actions and that it's ruined his life. He admits that Viv told him to leave, revealing the reason he went to Spain suddenly a couple of weeks after it happened. He goes to shake Charlie's hand to say goodbye but Charlie, disgusted by him, spits in his face calling him a monster. Kat confronts Harry and he says she must hate him. She denies that she hates him but just thinks he's a [[pervert]]. Kat reveals that Harry got her pregnant and told him that Zoe is the child. She says that Zoe hates him for what he did to Kat. Harry calls Kat a bitch and leaves in a taxi. Kat attempts suicide but is found in the park by Zoe and is rushed to hospital. The following year, Charlie receives news that Harry has died from a heart attack. Harry leaves Zoe £18000 in his will, but when Zoe sees how much the idea of taking anything from Harry was upsetting Kat, she burns the cheque saying she doesn't need his money.
{{-}}

==Gary Bolton==
{{Infobox soap character 2 | series = EastEnders
|image=
|name=Gary Bolton
|portrayer=[[Bruce Byron]]
|years=2001
|first=14 May 2001
|last=10 July 2001
|occupation=Builder
|home=Portsmouth
|sons=[[#Kevin Bolton|Kevin Bolton]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Robbie Jackson]]

}}
'''Gary Bolton''' was the biological father of [[Robbie Jackson]], who lived with his mother [[Carol Jackson|Carol Branning]] as her boyfriend, and her daughter [[Bianca Jackson|Bianca]] until a year after Robbie's birth. When David Wicks was revealed as Bianca's father in 1994, Carol told Robbie she had left his father because he was having relationships with under-age girls; however, this was retconned when the character appeared on-screen for the first time in 2001.

He tried to get in touch with Robbie on his eighteenth birthday by phoning Carol's father [[Jim Branning|Jim]], but Jim refused to give Gary Carol's number.

In May 2001, Robbie and his half sister [[Sonia Fowler|Sonia]] went to [[Portsmouth]] to find Gary. They found his number when they saw an advert for a builder called G. Bolton. When they went to his house, Gary gave Robbie a present he had saved from his first birthday and a cheque to make up for &quot;backdated pocket money&quot;. Robbie then met his half brother, Gary's son [[#Kevin Bolton|Kevin]], and when he realised that Gary had left Carol to be with Kevin's mother, he threw the cheque back at Gary and left.

In June, Gary arrived in [[Walford]] to talk to Robbie. He told Robbie he would pay for him to go to college, but Jim told him to leave. Later, in July, Gary returned to Walford and was happy to see old friend [[Mo Harris]]. Gary and Mo spent the day reminiscing in [[The Queen Victoria|The Queen Vic]], and when Robbie came in, Gary gave him a cheque for [[Pounds sterling|£]]10,000. This was the last time Gary was seen. Robbie used £1,000 of his money to travel to [[India]], and gave Sonia £9,000 to pay her college fees.
{{-}}

== Margaret Walker ==
{{Infobox soap character 2 | series = EastEnders
|image=
|name=Margaret Walker
|portrayer=[[Susan George (actress)|Susan George]]
|years=2001
|first=11 June 2001
|last=24 August 2001
|brothers=David Walker
}}
'''Margaret Walker''' began renting a flat from [[Janine Evans|Janine Butcher]] and [[Terry Raymond]]'s letting agency in June 2001. Terry and Margaret were attracted to each other and a relationship soon developed.

Janine and Margaret did not get along, which made things awkward for Terry as he and Janine lived together. Janine grew extremely jealous of Margaret and Terry's relationship and she began playing various tricks to split them up. Margaret was not perturbed and vowed to beat Janine at her own game, leading to numerous squabbles. When Janine discovered a photo of Margaret and another man, she immediately assumed the worst and informed Terry that Margaret was cheating on him. Margaret explained that the man in the photo was her brother, who was dying of cancer and she was paying for his placement in a drug trial in America.

After continued hostility, Margaret tried to persuade Terry to throw Janine out, and he eventually gave in and arranged for Janine to move into one of his bedsits. Janine was aware of Terry's paternal feelings towards her, and she began using [[emotional blackmail]] to [[Psychological manipulation|manipulate]] him. Margaret eventually grew tired of all the game playing and so she and Terry booked a trip to Paris in order to spend some time alone together. Janine was furious and Margaret goaded her further by telling her that she planned to propose to Terry while they were away.

In order to prevent this, Janine went to Margaret's property to steal Terry's passport, and whilst there she witnessed Margaret kissing her supposed brother goodbye. Janine became suspicious and when Terry told her that he was planning to give Margaret £10,000 to help her brother, she told him that Margaret was conning him and informed him about the kiss she'd witnessed. Furious, Terry went to Margaret's to discover the truth, but she refused to let him see her brother and after he insulted her, she slammed the door in his face.

Later that day Margaret confronted Terry demanding an apology. However Terry was adamant that she had been conning him for his money all along. She denied this, but he refused to believe her. He branded her a prostitute and ordered her to leave. After having one last fight with a smug Janine, Margaret went home, where it was revealed that the man at her flat really was her brother after all. She put him into a taxi and told him that he was all that mattered to her.

Although sources prior to the filming of this storyline had suggested that Margaret would be a sophisticated conwoman,&lt;ref&gt;&quot;[http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/entertainment/1287212.stm EastEnders welcomes George]&quot;, ''BBC''. Retrieved 11 July 2007.&lt;/ref&gt; this was never actually confirmed on-screen. The ending was left ambiguous and although the man at Margaret's flat turned out to be her brother, Margaret's final line - &quot;We'll find the money somehow&quot; - did not confirm he was dying.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;[http://www.bbc.co.uk/eastenders/episodes/past/episode20010824.shtml#4 Fri 24 Aug 2001]&quot;, ''BBC''. Retrieved 11 July 2007.&lt;/ref&gt;
{{-}}

==Angel Hudson==
{{Infobox soap character 2 
|series = EastEnders
|name=Angel Hudson
|portrayer=[[Goldie]]
|years=2001–02
|first=19 June 2001
|last=19 July 2002
|classification=[[List of past EastEnders characters#Last appeared in 2002|Former; regular]]
|born=
|occupation=[[Gangster]]
|wife=[[Precious Hudson]]
}}
'''Angel Hudson''', played by [[Goldie]] the gold-toothed [[gangster]] who was first seen in June 2001 when he attended a poker game that [[Steve Owen (EastEnders)|Steve Owen]] ([[Martin Kemp]]) was holding. His appearance was a huge shock to one of the other gamblers, [[Paul Trueman]] ([[Gary Beadle]]), and it was soon clear that they had unresolved issues. Later, during a break from the game, Angel told Paul that he wanted what he was owed: [[pound sterling|£]]30,000. He told Paul that he had a week to pay up or he would make sure he disappeared for good!

[[File:Goldie 2003.jpg|130px|thumb|left|[[Goldie]] (''pictured'') portrayed Angel Hudson from 2001 until 2002.]]Paul tried to get the money by stealing property from his mother, [[Audrey Trueman]] ([[Corinne Skinner-Carter]]), pawning the goods and gambling the money he received. This failed and he ended up with less money than he began with. At the end of the week, Angel came to collect his money, and when Paul failed to pay, Angel gave him a severe beating and trashed his mother's bed and breakfast. After more threats from Angel, Paul blackmailed his brother, [[Anthony Trueman]] ([[Nicholas R. Bailey]]), into giving him the money. Anthony was the local [[General Practitioner|GP]], a respectable man with a worthy profession, but he had a dark secret. When he was 15 years old, after a heavy drinking session, Anthony had driven a car, hit a pedestrian and then left the scene. Not wanting to ruin his brother's chance of a successful career, Paul took the blame and subsequently served 18 months in [[prison]]. Paul threatened to tell their mother the truth unless Anthony gave him the money he needed. Anthony felt he had no choice but to oblige, so he took out a [[loan]] and Paul paid Angel. Satisfied, Angel left, but told Paul they would meet again.

Angel returned in June 2002 with more orders for Paul. Angel was soon to stand trial for murder and was using his wife, [[Precious Hudson]] ([[Judi Shekoni]]), as a fake [[wiktionary:alibi|alibi]]. He wanted Paul to guard her until she could testify. Paul obliged and Precious moved to [[Albert Square]]. Paul was initially unaware that Precious was Angel's wife, so when she set about seducing him, he had no qualms about sleeping with her. When he discovered the truth, he was terrified of what Angel would do if he found out. However, Precious did a runner, leaving Paul to face a furious Angel. Paul went to get Precious back, while Angel held his father, [[Patrick Trueman]] ([[Rudolph Walker]]), and his brother's girlfriend, [[Zoe Slater]] ([[Michelle Ryan]]), hostage. Luckily, Paul persuaded Precious to return before Angel did any real harm. Their affair continued and it soon blossomed into love.

Later in the month, the family of the man that Angel had killed, tried to silence Precious by placing a bomb under her car. [[Garry Hobbs]] ([[Ricky Groves]]) received minor injuries but, furious, Precious told Angel she would only provide his alibi if he promised to divorce her. Angel agreed but, days later, Precious was kidnapped by the victim's family. They convinced her that Angel would never let her go and that the only way to be rid of him was to get him locked up. Precious agreed and at the trial, denied being with Angel at the time of the murder. Precious assumed that this would be enough to put Angel away, but was shocked when he was found not guilty.

Paul and Precious decided to leave the country. However, Angel caught up with Precious before she could get away. He told her that her betrayal didn't bother him enough to kill her and that she could have her divorce on one condition – she was to stay away from Paul. If he ever found out she and Paul were together, he promised to kill them both. Precious had no choice but to finish with Paul and leave Walford alone. Angel's last appearance was in July 2002.
{{-}}

==Sean Andrews==
{{Infobox soap character 2 
|series = EastEnders
|name = Sean Andrews
|portrayer = Victor Hunter (2001) &lt;br/&gt; Harry Hunter (2001) &lt;br/&gt; Oliver Bradley (2002)
|years = 2001, 2002
|first = 30 August 2001
|last = 8 November 2002
|born = 31 August 2001
|father = [[Trevor Morgan (EastEnders)|Trevor Morgan]]
|mother = [[Donna Andrews (EastEnders)|Donna Andrews]]
}}
'''Sean Andrews''', played by Victor and Harry Hunter (2001) and Oliver Bradley (2002), is the son of [[Trevor Morgan (EastEnders)|Trevor Morgan]] ([[Alex Ferns]]) and  [[Donna Andrews (EastEnders)|Donna Andrews]] (Paula Jennings), born on 31 August 2001. Sean is the product of his parents' extra-marital affair. Donna was originally Trevor's mistress.

Sean is first metioned by [[Little Mo Mitchell|Little Mo Morgan]] ([[Kacey Ainsworth]]), Sean's stepmother, who urges Trevor to be a part of Sean's life despite him abusing both her and Donna in the past. Donna then flees to the Slaters' house to hide from Trevor who is on a violent rampage but is eventually found and leaves Sean with [[Mo Harris]] ([[Laila Morse]]). Trevor bursts in to the house and the police are called. A violent Trevor demands to see his son but [[Kat Moon|Kat Slater]] ([[Jessie Wallace]]) fights off trevor, letting him beat her in order to prevent him going out the back where Sean is being kept and to stall for the police's arrival. The police arrive and arrests Trevor and Donna takes Sean home. In November 2002, Sean is kidnapped from Donna's house by Trevor. Trevor strarts abusing Little Mo but she stands up to him saying she's not frightened of him. He threatens to start a fire but Little Mo shows little interest and goes to get Sean and leave but Trevor grabs Mo, causing her to drop the lit match and starts a house fire at Little Mo's home. Local fireman [[Tom Banks (EastEnders)|Tom Banks]] ([[Colm Ó Maonlaí]]) saves Sean and Little Mo, but dies when going back to save Trevor, who also dies. Donna and Sean leave shortly afterwards.
{{-}}

==Patrick Trueman==
{{Main|Patrick Trueman}}
'''Patrick Neville Loftus Alfonso Trueman''' is played by [[Rudolph Walker]]. He made his first appearance on 13 September 2001. The character Patrick, played by Rudolph Walker, was introduced by [[John Yorke (television producer)|John Yorke]] as a replacement parental figure to the Trueman brothers, Anthony ([[Nick Bailey]]) and Paul ([[Gary Beadle]]), following the departure of [[Audrey Trueman]] ([[Corinne Skinner-Carter]]), a character killed-off in the serial in September 2001.&lt;ref name=&quot;audrey&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.thecnj.com/review/2008/102308/feature102308_02.html?headline=Corinne_and_the_killing_of_Audrey|title=Corinne and the killing of Audrey|date=23 October 2008|work=Camden New Journal|author=Angela Cobbinah|accessdate=2009-05-20}}&lt;/ref&gt; Patrick first appeared at Audrey's &quot;rum-fuelled wake&quot; as her estranged husband.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.guardian.co.uk/media/2001/sep/14/tvandradio.television1|title=Here comes the son|date=14 September 2001|work=[[The Guardian]]|author=[[Nancy Banks-Smith]]|accessdate=2009-05-20}}&lt;/ref&gt; Walker was keen to play a comic element to the character, telling Larry Jaffee of ''Walford Gazette'', &quot;Before joining, I told the producer [comedy] is an area I would like to explore [with the character] because there was not enough of it [in the show]. [Patrick] treats a lot of things with a certain amount of humour. His way of escaping a problem is to find something funny to do or say or sometimes to get himself out of a tight corner. That’s really the sort of foundation. I try to put as much humour as possible into the character.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.wgazette.com/wint09-rudolph.html|title=Exclusive Interview With Rudolph Waker (Patrick Trueman)|year= 2009|work=Walford Gazette|author=Larry Jaffee|accessdate=2010-04-04}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Belinda Peacock==
{{Infobox soap character 2 | series = EastEnders
|image=
|name=Belinda Peacock
|portrayer=[[Leanne Lakey]]
|years=2001–03
|first=1 October 2001
|last=25 December 2003
|spinoffs=''[[Slaters in Detention]]'' (2003)
|born=11 November 1975
|home=[[Kent]]
|occupation=
|husband=Neville Peacock (1997—)
|father=[[Charlie Slater]]
|mother=[[Viv Slater]]
|classification=[[List of past EastEnders characters#Last appeared in 2003|Former; recurring]]
|sisters=[[Lynne Hobbs]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Kat Moon]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Little Mo Mitchell]]
|nieces=[[Zoe Slater]]
|grandmothers=[[Mo Harris]]
}}
'''Belinda Peacock''' (née '''Slater''') played by [[Leanne Lakey]], is the sister of [[Kat Moon|Kat Slater]] ([[Jessie Wallace]]), [[Lynne Hobbs]] ([[Elaine Lordan]]), [[Little Mo Mitchell|Little Mo Slater]] ([[Kacey Ainsworth]]) and daughter of [[Viv Slater|Viv]] (Spril Martin and Natasya Rush) and [[Charlie Slater]] ([[Derek Martin]]). Belinda rejected her working class roots and likes to think she is superior to her sisters, but is not as classy as she makes out. 

===Storylines===
Belinda is married to Neville Peacock who is wealthy and Belinda frequntly brags about this to her sisters. She wears a blonde wig and speaks in an exaggerated accent, but revealed her true self at Lynne's hen night under the influence of [[alcohol]]. Belinda usually turns up in [[Albert Square]] when she is having marriage problems. She has had flings with [[Jamie Mitchell]] ([[Jack Ryder]]) and her brother-in-law [[Garry Hobbs]] ([[Ricky Groves]]).

Although Belinda resides in Kent, within driving distance of [[Walford]], she makes great use of her villa in [[Lanzarote]]. She often holidays there and her grandmother [[Mo Harris]] ([[Laila Morse]]) frequently visits, although Belinda often lets down her father Charlie. The most recent mention of Belinda was in 2008 when she promised Charlie that she was returning to spend some time with him, only then to cancel, leaving Charlie very upset. Belinda also makes a small cameo appearance in ''Slaters in Detention'' where she has been arrested after Charlie says she was the only normal daughter her has, but sees Belinda at the station and withdraws the remark.
{{-}}

==Louise Mitchell==
{{Infobox soap character 2 | series = EastEnders
|image=
|caption=Brittany Papple as Louise (2010)
|name=Louise Mitchell
|introducer=[[John Yorke (television producer)|John Yorke]] &lt;small&gt;(2001)&lt;/small&gt;&lt;br /&gt;[[Diederick Santer]] &lt;small&gt;(2008, 2010)&lt;/small&gt;
|portrayer=Rachel Cox &lt;small&gt;(2001–03)&lt;/small&gt;&lt;br /&gt;[[Danni Bennatar]] &lt;small&gt;(2008)&lt;/small&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Brittany&lt;!-- please no not link as it redirects back here, thanks. --&gt; Papple &lt;small&gt;(2010)&lt;/small&gt;
|years=2001–03, 2008, 2010
|first=5 November 2001
|last=5 August 2010
|classification=[[List of past EastEnders characters#Last appeared in 2010|Former; regular]]
|born= 5 November 2001
|occupation=Student
|home= Outside [[Walford]]
|family=[[Mitchell family|Mitchell]]
|father=[[Phil Mitchell]]
|mother=[[Lisa Fowler]]
|stepfather=[[Mark Fowler]]
|halfbrothers=[[Ben Mitchell (EastEnders)|Ben Mitchell]]
|grandmothers=[[Peggy Mitchell]]
|uncles=[[Grant Mitchell (EastEnders)|Grant Mitchell]]
|aunts=[[Sam Mitchell (EastEnders)|Sam Mitchell]]
|cousins=[[List of EastEnders characters (1997)#Courtney Mitchell|Courtney Mitchell]]&lt;br&gt;Mark Fowler Jr &lt;br&gt;[[Richard Mitchell (EastEnders)|Richard Mitchell]]
}}
'''Louise Mitchell''' (née '''Fowler''') is the daughter of [[Phil Mitchell]] and [[Lisa Fowler]].  Due to a difficult relationship, Lisa is determined to make sure Phil does not realise he is the father of her baby. For this reason, she marries [[Mark Fowler]] and names him as the father on Louise's birth certificate and names her daughter after Mark's late grandmother, [[Lou Beale]]. Everything is fine until [[Sharon Watts]] discovers Louise's true paternity and tells Phil.

Wanting his daughter, he goes after Lisa, soon persuading her to have an affair with him and moving into the flat above [[The Queen Victoria]] public house with him and his mother, [[Peggy Mitchell]], when Mark discovers Lisa's infidelity. It is soon clear that Phil and Peggy want Louise, not Lisa. They take over caring for Louise, excluding Lisa completely and hiring a nanny, [[Joanne Ryan]], telling her and the other Mitchells that Lisa is mentally unstable. This comes to a head on the day of Peggy's party to celebrate changing Louise's name to Mitchell legally. Desperate to get away, Lisa snatches Louise and runs away to Portugal, joining her best friend, [[Melanie Owen]]. Lisa leaves behind a postcard with Mel's address and Phil goes after her, returning with Louise, telling his family that Lisa will not be back.

The police, however, are suspicious, and send an undercover officer, [[Kate Mitchell|Kate Morton]] (using the name Kate Tyler), to get Phil to confess to Lisa's murder. Kate gets a confession but it is not what she and her boss expect - he bullied Lisa to give him custody of Louise and told her to stay away so Louise would not be confused. Phil goes on to marry Kate, and is shocked when Lisa returns on their wedding day, wanting Louise back. Lisa plans to shoot Phil but [[Den Watts]] talks her out of it and looks after her. He and his son, [[Dennis Rickman]] frame Phil for armed robbery and when he is arrested, Lisa takes Louise and leaves Walford.

In 2007, Phil suggests to his son, [[Ben Mitchell (EastEnders)|Ben]], that they find Louise. Ben is not keen so Phil drops it but in later in the year, [[Jack Branning]] tells Phil he knows where Louise is and helps him find her. Jack gives Phil a picture of Louise and her address so Phil goes to find her on 4 January 2008 and tells her that he is her daddy only to be disappointed when she points to an unfamiliar man and calls him her daddy.

Louise returns&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.bbc.co.uk/programmes/b00rmprl|title=EastEnders 22&amp;nbsp;March 2010|publisher=BBC Online|accessdate=15 March 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; on 16 March 2010, though she is initially credited as &quot;Little Girl&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.bbc.co.uk/programmes/b00rhg6k|title=EastEnders 16&amp;nbsp;March 2010|publisher=[[BBC Online]]|accessdate=9 March 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; A show insider said &quot;Her arrival is going to be massive. It will send shockwaves around the square.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.dailystar.co.uk/playlist/view/125471/Eastenders-Secret-Mitchell-hits-square/|title=EASTENDERS: SECRET MITCHELL HITS SQUARE|last=Dyke|first=Peter|coauthors=Begley, Katie|date=9 March 2010|work=[[Daily Star (United Kingdom)|Daily Star]]|accessdate=9 March 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; Louise is dropped outside the tube station in a car where Phil's cousin [[Ronnie Mitchell]] approaches her. Louise tells Ronnie she is looking for her father and shows Ronnie a photo. Ronnie tells her that she knows him and will take her to see him. Louise tells Ronnie that her mother went on holiday but did not return. When Ronnie finds Phil, she sees him arguing with people in the pub and tells Louise that she could not find him. Wanting the best for Louise, she calls Social Services, who take her into care. However, Phil finds out that Louise returned to the Square and angrily confronts Ronnie, just as Louise enters the Queen Vic. Louise spends the weekend with her father, and he tries to keep her visit a secret. When the police arrive, he tells them he has not seen her. Phil allows her to stay off school, which annoys Ben. After Phil speaks to [[Shirley Carter]], he decides to contact Social Services, who take Louise away, but Phil vows to fight to get custody. However, he soon discovers he will need a DNA test to prove he is Louise's father as Mark is listed as Louise's father on her birth certificate. The results show that Phil is the father, and a social worker, [[List of EastEnders characters (2010)#Terry|Terry]], visits Phil's home. After [[Billie Jackson]] and his gang hold up the bar, Terry decides it is not a safe environment for Louise, but [[Shirley Carter]] tells him that Phil is moving in with her soon. The social worker eventually allows Louise to move in with Phil and Shirley, but her arrival upsets Ben, especially when she tells him she dislikes Shirley. She causes further problems for Ben by stealing his diary and writing entries in it, then reading them to her friends. Phil forces Louise to apologise to Ben, but she does not, and when Phil is out, Ben burns Louise's hand with a hot spoon.

Louise sees Ben with a bottle of alcohol that he took from the pub, and tries to get Ben in trouble by asking Phil what alcohol tastes like. Later, Ben tells Louise that Phil will not believe her if she says anything but if she does he will make her pay for it. Ben is left with the responsibility of taking Louise to school but instead locks her in a shed all day, leaving Phil worried that she has run away because he saw a note she wrote saying she wishes she was not there. Ben &quot;finds&quot; Louise and takes her home, and she blames [[Jordan Johnson]] for locking her up. Ben tells her she is a good girl and will not lock her in the shed again. The next day, Phil sees burns on her arm and she reveals that Ben was to blame. A suspicious Phil questions Ben but he denies burning Louise and locking her in the shed. Worried that Ben is copying Stella, Phil asks Heather to keep an eye on them but Ben sends Heather out to buy some crisps and rent a DVD. A worried Phil rushes home and sees Louise's doll in pieces and Ben about to burn his sister. Ben claims he is playing a game but Phil angrily punches him. Ben is later imprisoned for an attack on Jordan. Phil learns that Lisa has applied for contact with Louise, but Phil keeps this from his daughter, asking his solicitor [[Ritchie Scott]] to find a legal way of stopping Lisa seeing Louise.

Louise asks Peggy when Lisa is returning from her holiday. Peggy reveals that she already has done and that she wants to see Louise. Louise demands to see her mother but Peggy insults her, so Louise storms off and then runs away from home. Phil eventually finds her and she tells him she wants to see her mother and needs to know if she still loves her. Back at home, Phil shouts at Louise, telling her not to mention her mother again, and she sees Phil slap Peggy after she says he is not fit to be a parent. Phil shuts Louise in the house, telling nobody to answer the phone or door. However, Peggy sneaks Louise out to apologise for insulting Lisa. Louise asks if she can see her mother, so Peggy takes her there. Peggy is unable to assure Lisa that Phil will never harm Louise, so allows her to stay with Lisa as long as Phil can visit regularly. When Peggy returns home, she tells Phil what she has done. He drives to Lisa's house and kicks down the door to find the house is empty and Lisa has disappeared with Louise.

==Nathan Williams==
{{Infobox soap character 2 | series = EastEnders
|image=
|name=Nathan Williams
|portrayer=[[Doug Allen (actor)|Doug Allen]]
|years=2001–02
|first = 13 November 2001
|last = 24 May 2002
|occupation=Car dealer
|father= [[Roy Evans (EastEnders)|Roy Evans]]
|mother = [[Jane Williams (EastEnders)|Jane Williams]]
|halfbrothers= [[Barry Evans (EastEnders)|Barry Evans]]
|nephews = [[Jack Evans (EastEnders)|Jack Evans]]
}}
'''Nathan Williams''' was played by [[Doug Allen (actor)|Doug Allen]]. The character was axed after 6 months, reportedly because of Allen's failure to learn his lines adequately.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.highbeam.com/doc/1G1-87685824.html soap gossip]&lt;/ref&gt;

Nathan was the [[illegitimate]] son of [[Roy Evans (EastEnders)|Roy Evans]], born, unbeknownst to Roy, out of an extramarital affair with his former employee [[Jane Williams (EastEnders)|Jane Williams]]. Nathan made his first appearance in [[Albert Square]] in 2001, after his mother, who was terminally ill with [[cancer]], confessed to Roy that Nathan was actually his son.

Nathan initially refused Roy's attempts to get to know him. However, after Jane died (on the same day that Roy's grandson [[Jack Evans (EastEnders)|Jack]] was born), Nathan was left penniless with a bankrupt business, so he begrudgingly turned to Roy for help. Soon after, he moved in with the Evanses, much to the annoyance of Roy's other son [[Barry Evans (EastEnders)|Barry]], who resented Nathan and was furious with his father for betraying his dead mother. It also became clear that Nathan equally disliked Barry and resented the fact that he had known and been brought up by his father, whilst he had only just met him. The pair spent much time winding each other up, with Barry usually ending up looking the fool.

Nathan quickly integrated into life in Albert Square, growing closer to his father and having a brief fling with [[Walford]] resident [[Melanie Owen]]. He started working in the car lot with Roy, whilst Barry stayed at home playing at house-husband and looking after his son Jack. Barry resented him even more for this and felt that Nathan was taking over his role as dutiful son. It seemed as if Nathan could do no wrong, but it was the petty jealousy and sibling rivalry between him and Barry that would eventually turn out to be his undoing.

In an attempt to exclude Barry and take his place in his father's heart, Nathan made a plan to set Barry up and steal the affections of Barry's wife [[Natalie Evans|Natalie]]. His first advancement towards Natalie resulted in the pair kissing, but Natalie was adamant that it would go no further and despite further flirtations from Nathan, their kiss was a one-off occurrence. Undeterred, Nathan continued with his plan. Aware of Barry's past monetary blunders, and knowing that any subsequent mistakes would not be tolerated by Roy, Nathan stole money from the car-lot and set Barry up for the blame. The plan seemed to be working, until Natalie pieced it together and uncovered his ploy. With Nathan's true character unveiled, Roy decided that he wanted nothing more to do with him and Nathan was banished from Albert Square in mid 2002
{{-}}

==Nita Mistry==
{{Infobox soap character 2 | series = EastEnders
|name=Nita Mistry
|portrayer=[[Bindya Solanki]]
|image=
|years=2001–03
|first=26 November 2001
|last=28 February 2003
|classification=[[List of past EastEnders characters#Last appeared in 2003|Former; regular]]
|home=[[India]]
|occupation=Shop assistant
|husband=[[Robbie Jackson]] (2004—)
|sons=[[Anish Mistry]]
|cousins=Samir Mistry
}}
'''Nita Mistry''', played by [[Bindya Solanki]], is a love interest for [[Robbie Jackson]] ([[Dean Gaffney]]). When she arrives, she is a single mother to [[Anish Mistry|Anish]] and a [[widow]]. She gets a job at the local shop, the Minute Mart, and becomes involved in the community [[theatre]], where she meets Robbie. In 2003, Nita gets an offer from her family in [[India]], asking her to return and they will support her and Anish. In February 2003, Nita takes up her parents' offer to return to Mumbai. Nita, Robbie and Anish leave for India. This is Anish and Nita's last appearance. In reality, the character was axed along with Robbie. In a press report, executive-producer [[Louise Berridge]] commented &quot;Dean and Bindya have contributed an enormous amount to the programme. However, we feel that the characters have reached the end of their natural course in the show, and they will both be leaving in Spring 2003. [...] It is always sad to be saying goodbye to a good double act, so we will be leaving the door open for both characters&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;[http://www.digitalspy.co.uk/article/ds9652.html Dean Gaffney to leave 'EastEnders']&quot;, ''[[Digital Spy]]''. Retrieved 25 September 2006.&lt;/ref&gt;

In February 2010, Robbie returns for his sister [[Bianca Jackson]]'s ([[Patsy Palmer]]) wedding and reveals that Nita is six months pregnant.
{{-}}

==Jane Williams ==
{{Infobox soap character 2 | series = EastEnders
|image
|name=Jane Williams
|portrayer=[[Ann Mitchell]]
|years=2001–02
|first = 26 November 2001
|last = 11 January 2002
|classification=[[List of past EastEnders characters#Last appeared in 2002|Former; guest]]
|death = 11 January 2002
|sons =[[#Nathan Williams|Nathan Williams]]
}}
'''Jane Williams''', played by [[Ann Mitchell]], was a former employee and the former mistress of [[Roy Evans (EastEnders)|Roy Evans]] ([[Tony Caunter]]). She was first seen when Roy appeared at her house to confront her about him being named as the father of her son [[#Nathan Williams|Nathan Williams]] ([[Doug Allen (actor)|Doug Allen]]), who had arrived in [[Walford]] several days earlier and told Roy this. Jane assured Roy that he was and gave him a gold pen.

As it emerged that Jane was dying of [[Cancer]], Roy began spending more and more time with her arousing the suspicions of Roy's other son [[Barry Evans (EastEnders)|Barry Evans]] ([[Shaun Williamson]]). and Roy's wife [[Pat Evans]] ([[Pam St. Clement]]). Eventually Roy was forced to confess to his family that Nathan was his son, much to the upset of Barry, as Roy had slept with Jane the night Barry's mother and Roy's first wife Doreen had died. On 11 January, Jane peacefully died of her progressing cancer on the same day Roy's grandson, [[Jack Evans (EastEnders)|Jack Evans]] (Samuel and Joseph Timson) was born.

Ann Mitchell appeared from 11 April 2011 as another character, [[Cora Cross]], the mother of [[Tanya Branning|Tanya Jessop]] ([[Jo Joyner]]) and [[Rainie Cross]] ([[Tanya Franks]]).&lt;ref name=&quot;Cora Cross&quot;&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.digitalspy.co.uk/soaps/s2/eastenders/news/a310006/eastenders-confirms-tanyas-mum-casting.html|title='EastEnders' confirms Tanya's mum casting|last=Kilkelly|first=Daniel|date=21 March 2011|work=[[Digital Spy]]|publisher=[[Hachette Filipacchi UK]]|accessdate=21 March 2011|location=[[London]]}}&lt;/ref&gt; She initially appeared from 11 April to 15 April and re-appeared as a full-time regular character on 28 July.&lt;ref name=&quot;28July&quot;&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.digitalspy.co.uk/soaps/s2/eastenders/spoilers/a330392/michael-vows-to-get-revenge-against-eddie.html|title=Michael vows to get revenge against Eddie|last=Kilkelly|first=Daniel|date=28 July 2011|work=[[Digital Spy]]|publisher=[[Hachette Filipacchi UK]]|accessdate=19 July 2011|location=[[London]]}}&lt;/ref&gt;

{{-}}

==Roxy Drake==
{{Infobox soap character 2 | series = EastEnders
|image=
|name=Roxy Drake
|portrayer=[[Tracy Brabin]]
|years=2001
|first=10 December 2001
|last=25 December 2001
|classification=[[List of past EastEnders characters#Last appeared in 2001|Former; guest]]
|occupation=[[Pimp]]
}}
'''Roxy Drake''', played by [[Tracy Brabin]], was a [[pimp]] who first appeared on 10 December 2001. She groomed [[Zoe Slater]] ([[Michelle Ryan]]), who had run away from home and was living on the streets. Roxy found Zoe a flat to live in. However, Roxy forced her to [[prostitute]] herself. Roxy and fellow prostitute [[Kelly Taylor (EastEnders)|Kelly Taylor]] ([[Brooke Kinsella]]) dressed and made-up Zoe, but Zoe got drunk on whiskey and vomited on her first client much to the anger of Roxy. Some days later, Zoe's mother, [[Kat Moon]] ([[Jessie Wallace]]) came looking for Zoe along with [[Anthony Trueman]] ([[Nicholas Bailey]]). The found her and came to take Zoe home, but Roxy tried to prevent Kat taking Zoe. Kat ended up headbutting Roxy in the face. A humiliated Roxy then got in her car and drove away, and had not been seen since.
{{-}}

==Kelly Taylor==
{{Main|Kelly Taylor (EastEnders)}}
'''Kelly Taylor''' was played by actress [[Brooke Kinsella]]. The character was introduced by executive producer [[John Yorke (television producer)|John Yorke]], in 2001. She was only due to appear in eight episodes as part of a [[prostitution]]/[[homelessness]] storyline featuring [[Michelle Ryan]]'s established character, [[Zoe Slater]], who had run away from home in late 2001 and was living at the same brothel as Kelly. However, the viewer response to Kelly was positive, so she was reintroduced as a regular at the end of 2002. The character remained in the serial until 2004, when executive producer [[Louise Berridge]] decided that her storylines had come to a natural end. 

In the past, Kinsella had auditioned for the parts of [[Janine Butcher]], Zoe Slater and [[Sonia Fowler]], but had been unsuccessful. Kinsella has commented, &quot;I went up for the part of every girl in the Square. I was closest to getting the part of Zoe. I did workshops with all the Slater girls but you have to say they are all dark and look very alike while I'm blonde. Obviously that wasn't the right one for me. It was hard at the time but I'm very glad because I love playing Kelly. She's totally different from any other character and she's good fun to play.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;knock&quot;&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.highbeam.com/doc/1G1-105900590.html |title= I was knocked back 3 times for a star role in EastEnders; Brooke Kinsella: My battle to land a part in Albert Square|publisher=''[[Sunday Mail (Scotland)|Sunday Mail]]'' | author = STEVE HENDRY  | date = 2003-07-27| accessdate=2007-12-03}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Derek Harkinson==
{{Infobox soap character 2 | series = EastEnders
|name=Derek Harkinson
|image=
|portrayer=[[Ian Lavender]]
|years=2001–05
|first=29 November 2001
|last=19 May 2005
|classification=[[List of past EastEnders characters#Last appeared in 2005|Former; regular]]
|born=
|occupation= Community Centre Manager
|wife=Cynthia Harkinson
|sons=[[Alex Harkinson]]
|daughters=[[Mary Harkinson]]
|grandsons=[[Danny Harkinson]]
}}
'''Derek Harkinson''', played by [[Ian Lavender]], was a childhood friend of [[Pauline Fowler]]. He reappears in her life through her involvement in the Community Theatre. Pauline makes a play for him but he reveals he is gay. They decide to stay friends and Derek moves in with Pauline, becoming a new father-figure for her son [[Martin Fowler (EastEnders)|Martin]]. He helps out with the fruit and veg stall, teaches Martin to drive, and takes the blame when Martin is caught growing [[cannabis]]. Derek gets in touch with his estranged son and daughter, [[Alex Harkinson|Alex]] and [[Mary Harkinson|Mary]], and Alex's son [[Danny Harkinson|Danny]]. He has a long string of arguments with Pauline in 2005 and goes to live with Alex.
{{-}}

==Tom Stuart==
{{Infobox soap character 2 
|series = EastEnders
|name = Tom Stuart
|portrayer = [[Shaun Dooley]]
|first = 17 December 2001
|last = 6 July 2004
|years = 2001–04
|occupation = [[Vicar]]
|classification = [[List of past EastEnders characters#Last appeared in 2004|Former; recurring]]
}}

'''The Reverend Tom Stuart''' is a [[recurring character|recurring]] [[fictional character]] from the [[BBC]] [[soap opera]] ''[[EastEnders]]'', played by [[Shaun Dooley]].

Tom was the [[vicar]] for the [[parish]] of [[Walford]], and one of his earliest appearances was conducting the wedding ceremony of [[Dot Branning|Dot]] ([[June Brown]]) and [[Jim Branning]] ([[John Bardon]]) on Valentine's Day 2002. However, he was earlier seen in December 2001 talking to Dot and Jim right after Dot returned from a visit to Nigel.  He has performed his vicarly duties since then, which have included the conduction of [[Jamie Mitchell]]'s [[funeral]], and performing [[Kat Moon|Kat Slater]] ([[Jessie Wallace]])  and [[Andy Hunter (EastEnders)|Andy Hunter]]'s ([[Michael Higgs]]) wedding ceremony that was crashed by [[Alfie Moon]] [[Shane Richie]]). He also occasionally appeared when Dot attended church meetings and suchlike. He was replaced off-screen by [[Reverend Stevens]] ([[Michael Keating]]).
{{-}}

==Others==

{| class=&quot;wikitable plainrowheaders&quot; style=&quot;font-size:90%&quot;
|-
! scope=&quot;col&quot; | Character
! scope=&quot;col&quot; | Date(s)
! scope=&quot;col&quot; | Actor
! scope=&quot;col&quot; | Circumstances
|-
! scope=&quot;row&quot; | {{nowrap|Diane Irving}}
| {{nowrap|9 January, 14 April}}
| {{nowrap|[[Sheila Whitfield]]&lt;ref name=&quot;DianeI&quot;&gt;[http://www.walfordweb.co.uk/walfordweb/whoswho-fullprofile.php?fn=Diane&amp;ln=Irving Diane Irving], ''Walford Web''. Retrieved 3 April 2008.&lt;/ref&gt;}}
| {{Anchor|Dina Irving}} A social worker took over from [[Ameena Badawi]] on the case of [[Rebecca Miller (EastEnders)|Chloe Jackson]], when Ameena was promoted. She eventually found Chloe a home with [[Neil Miller (EastEnders)|Neil]] and [[Sue Miller (EastEnders)|Sue Miller]], who renamed her Rebecca.
|-
! scope=&quot;row&quot; | {{nowrap|George Hawkins}}
| {{nowrap|23–24 April}}
| {{nowrap|[[Gary Lucas]]&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.walfordweb.co.uk/walfordweb/whoswho-show.php?id=602 George Hawkins], ''Walford Web''. Retrieved 8 May 2007.&lt;/ref&gt;}}
| {{Anchor|George Hawkins}} A salesman who tried to sell his wares to [[Ian Beale]] at his fish and chip shop. He was nicknamed &quot;Cuban Man&quot; by [[Beppe di Marco]], a minicab driver as he insisted on smoking [[cigar]]s in his taxi.
|-
! scope=&quot;row&quot; | {{nowrap|Norman Dunn}}
| {{nowrap|7 May}}
| {{nowrap|[[Roland Oliver (actor)|Roland Oliver]]}}
| {{Anchor|Norman Dunn}} The father of [[Laura Beale]], and appeared in [[Walford]] for Laura's wedding to [[Ian Beale]] in 2001, along with his wife [[#Edwina Dunn|Edwina]]. He was very conservative and disapproved of Laura and Ian's marriage, as Ian had been declared bankrupt just a few months earlier. He threatened to disinherit Laura and when she refused to postpone the wedding, he refused to attend. When Edwina returned to Walford in 2005 for [[Janine Evans]]'s trial for Laura's murder, she spoke to [[Pat Evans]] and said that Norman was very upset about his daughter's death.
|-
! scope=&quot;row&quot; | {{nowrap|Edwina Dunn}}
| {{nowrap|7 May 2001 &lt;br/&gt; 9 December 2005}}
| {{nowrap|[[Patricia Maynard]] &lt;small&gt;(2001)&lt;/small&gt; &lt;br/&gt; [[Gay Hamilton]] &lt;small&gt;(2005)&lt;/small&gt;}}
| {{Anchor|Edwina Dunn}} The mother of [[Laura Beale]], and appeared for Laura's wedding to [[Ian Beale]] in 2001, along with her husband, [[#Norman Dunn|Norman]], but did not attend the ceremony as Norman disapproved of Ian being declared bankrupt in the past. She reappeared in December 2005 to attend [[Janine Butcher]]'s trial for the murder of Laura, and unknowingly persuaded [[Pat Evans]] to change her testimony, allowing the innocent Janine to walk free.
|-
! scope=&quot;row&quot; | {{nowrap|Kevin Bolton}}
| {{nowrap|17 May}}
| {{nowrap|[[Rupert Hill]]&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.walfordweb.co.uk/walfordweb/whoswho-show.php?id=397 Kevin Bolton], ''Walford Web''. Retrieved 30 April 2007.&lt;/ref&gt;}}
| {{Anchor|Kevin Bolton}} The son of [[#Gary Bolton|Gary Bolton]], and half brother of [[Robbie Jackson]]. He appeared when Robbie and his half sister [[Sonia Fowler|Sonia]] tracked Gary down to [[Portsmouth]]. He was jealous of Robbie's presence in his father's life.
|-
! scope=&quot;row&quot; | {{nowrap|Kay Bradshaw}}
| {{nowrap|14–19 June}}
| {{nowrap|[[Vanessa Earl]]&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.walfordweb.co.uk/walfordweb/whoswho-show.php?id=398 Kay Bradshaw], ''Walford Web''. Retrieved 29 April 2007.&lt;/ref&gt;}}
| {{Anchor|Kay Bradshaw}} A woman who [[Beppe di Marco]] had a one-night-stand with. It was later revealed that she was Beppe's son [[Joe di Marco|Joe]]'s teacher, when Joe walked in on Beppe and Kay lying together on the sofa, and refused to go to school the next day.
|-
! scope=&quot;row&quot; | {{nowrap|Sidney Gibbs}}
| {{nowrap|2–3 July}}
| {{nowrap|[[James Marcus (actor)|James Marcus]]&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.walfordweb.co.uk/walfordweb/whoswho-show.php?id=581 Sidney Gibbs], ''Walford Web''. Retrieved 29 April 2007.&lt;/ref&gt;}}
| {{Anchor|Sidney Gibbs}} the owner of a cleaning firm, Sid's Scrubbers, who were hired by [[Sharon Watts]] in order to get [[Billy Mitchell (EastEnders)|Billy Mitchell]] to lower the prices of his cleaning firm.
|-
! scope=&quot;row&quot; | {{nowrap|Jan Sherwood}}
| {{nowrap|17–21 September}}
| {{nowrap|[[Cherie Lunghi]]&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.walfordweb.co.uk/walfordweb/whoswho-fullprofile.php?fn=Jan&amp;ln=Sherwood Walford Web | Jan Sherwood]&lt;/ref&gt;}}
| {{Anchor|Jan Sherwood}} A woman who [[Steve Owen (EastEnders)|Steve Owen]] met when he and his gang attempted a robbery targeting Jan's lover and wealthy businessman Alan Mills. When Steve seduced her, she tricked him and took off with all the money leaving him and his gang with nothing. It was however revealed in a plot twist that she and Steve were both in on the plan for her to take off with all the money and later share it with Steve. Steve fooled his gang into thinking Jan had gone with all the money and their plan had failed. He met up secretly with Jan and took his half of the money and never saw her again.
|-
! scope=&quot;row&quot; | {{nowrap|John Davies}}
| {{nowrap|11 October–2 December}}
| {{nowrap|[[Huw Higginson]]&lt;ref&gt;&quot;[http://www.walfordweb.co.uk/walfordweb/whoswho-show.php?id=522 John Davis]&quot;, ''Walford Web''. Retrieved 26 April 2007.&lt;/ref&gt;}}
| {{Anchor|John Davies}} The landlord of 15a Turpin Road. He doubled the rent on the flat, then offered to help [[Laura Beale]] with the money, but only if she would have [[sexual intercourse|sex]] with him.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;[http://www.walford.net/update/20011102.htm FRI 02-NOV-01]&quot;, ''walford.net''. Retrieved 27 April 2007.&lt;/ref&gt;
|-
! scope=&quot;row&quot; | {{nowrap|Chris Wallace}}
| {{nowrap|16–19 October}}
| {{nowrap|[[Georgia Reece]]&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.walfordweb.co.uk/walfordweb/whoswho-show.php?id=1188 Chris Wallace], ''Walford Web''. Retrieved 27 April 2007.&lt;/ref&gt;}}
| {{Anchor|Chris Wallace}} The interior designer who redesigned e20 after a fire there, and had an affair with the manager [[Beppe di Marco]], and caught a [[sexually transmitted infection]] from him, leading to her husband [[#Tony Wallace|Tony]] discovering the affair and attacking Beppe.
|-
! scope=&quot;row&quot; | {{nowrap|Tony Wallace}}
| {{nowrap|1 November}}
| {{nowrap|[[Andy Capie]]&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.walford.net/update/20011101.htm THU 01-NOV-01], ''walford.net''. Retrieved 27 April 2007.&lt;/ref&gt;}}
| {{Anchor|Tony Wallace}} The husband of [[#Chris Wallace|Chris Wallace]], who attacked Beppe di Marco at the e20 [[Hallowe'en]] party after Beppe and Chris had an affair and Beppe gave Chris a sexually transmitted infection.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;[http://www.walfordweb.co.uk/walfordweb/whoswho-show.php?id=1197 Tony Wallace]&quot;, ''Walford Web''. Retrieved 27 April 2007.&lt;/ref&gt;
|}

== References ==
{{Reflist}}

==External links==
*[http://www.bbc.co.uk/eastenders/features/marsden.shtml Marsden's video diaries]
*{{EEcharlink|jill-marsden|Jill Marsden}}
*{{EEcharlink|belinda_p|Belinda Peacock}}
*{{EEcharlink|angel|Angel Hudson}}
*{{EEcharlink|nita_m|Nita Mistry}}
*{{EEcharlink|harry_s|Harry Slater}}

{{EastEnders}}
{{EastEnders characters|year}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:List Of Eastenders Characters (2001)}}
[[Category:Lists of EastEnders characters|2001]]
[[Category:Fictional characters introduced in 2001|*, EastEnders]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
