<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="12810941" ns="0" title="List of EastEnders characters (1996)"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{DISPLAYTITLE:List of ''EastEnders'' characters (1996)}}
The following is a list of fictional characters that first appeared in the [[BBC]] [[soap opera]] ''[[EastEnders]]'' in 1996, by order of first appearance.
{{TOClimit|limit=2}}

==Michael Rose==
{{Infobox soap character 2 
|series=EastEnders
|image= 
|name=Michael Rose
|portrayer=[[Russell Floyd]]
|years=1996–99
|first=15 February 1996
|last=19 October 1999
|classification=[[List of past EastEnders characters#Last appeared in 1999|Former; regular]]
|home = Leeds
|occupation= Market Inspector
|sons= [[Matthew Rose (EastEnders)|Matthew Rose]]
|wife=[[Susan Rose]]
|brothers=Colin Rose
}}
'''Michael Rose''', played by [[Russell Floyd]], first appeared when he was chosen, randomly, to be the [[best man]] at [[Terry Raymond]]'s ([[Gavin Richards]]) wedding (which was later called off).  He settled in [[Walford]] as a Market Inspector in 1996. He initially had very few storylines in his early years. He had a crush on [[April Branning]] but no relationship ever developed between him and April. Then there was the arrival of his teenage son [[Matthew Rose (EastEnders)|Matthew]] ([[Joe Absolom]]) and former wife [[Susan Rose]] ([[Tilly Vosburgh]]) in 1997.

His ex-wife Susan was suffering from [[multiple sclerosis]] and Michael ended up caring for her. Eventually he and Susan got back together and seemed happy until the arrival of [[Lisa Fowler|Lisa Shaw]] ([[Lucy Benjamin]]) who was also a Market Inspector. He and Lisa became attracted to each other and had an affair behind Susan's back. Michael ended the affair and decided to leave Walford with Susan and start a new life in [[Leeds]], with Susan unaware of the affair.

He returned occasionally in 1999 when his son Matthew was wrongly imprisoned for the [[murder]] of [[Saskia Duncan]] (Deborah Sheridan-Taylor). The real culprit was [[Steve Owen (EastEnders)|Steve Owen]] ([[Martin Kemp]]) and Michael became one of his enemies for framing his son. Michael's last appearance was in October 1999.
{{-}}

==Sal Martin==
{{Main|Sal Martin}}
'''Sal Martin''', often referred to as '''Aunt Sal''',&lt;ref name=&quot;sally&quot;&gt;{{cite news |title=Bosom pals for 30 years|url= http://www.highbeam.com/doc/1G1-61324146.html|publisher= ''[[Daily Mirror|The Mirror]]''|date=16 March 2002 |accessdate=2008-10-02}}&lt;/ref&gt;  is a recurring character, played by [[Anna Karen]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |title=Me and My Trolley ...with Anna Karen|url= http://www.highbeam.com/doc/1G1-61114166.html|publisher= ''[[The People]]''|date=19 January 1997 |accessdate=2008-10-02}}&lt;/ref&gt; She has appeared sporadically over the years, usually for only one or two episodes at a time. As of April 2011, Sal has collectively featured in 41 episodes of the show since she first appeared in 1996. In February 1996, it was announced that comedy actress Anna Karen would be joining the cast of ''EastEnders'' as [[Peggy Mitchell]]'s sister Sal. Anna Karen and the actress who plays Peggy, [[Barbara Windsor]], are &quot;best friends&quot; in reality and Windsor has expressed how happy she was to have Karen on the cast of ''EastEnders''.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |title=Asthma Campaign - Actors and authors put weight behind the|url= http://findarticles.com/p/articles/mi_qn4158/is_20020331/ai_n12602409?tag=content;col1|publisher= ''[[The Independent]]''|date=31 March 2002 |accessdate=2008-10-02}} {{Dead link|date=September 2010|bot=RjwilmsiBot}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |title=TAKE A BUTCHER'S AT BABS|url= http://www.highbeam.com/doc/1G1-61157527.html|publisher= ''[[The People]]''|date=3 February 1996 |accessdate=2008-10-02}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Ben Mitchell==
{{Main|Ben Mitchell (EastEnders)}}
'''Ben Mitchell''' has been played by four different actors. Matthew Silver appeared as an infant Ben from 1996–98, and Morgan Whittle played him as a toddler from 1999–2000. After a six-year absence from the series, [[Charlie Jones (actor)|Charlie Jones]] assumed the role of Ben in 2006. Executive producer [[Bryan Kirkwood (producer)|Bryan Kirkwood]] axed Jones as part of a series revamp in 2010; the role was recast to Joshua Pascoe later that year. Having previously appeared as a baby and a toddler, Ben returned to ''EastEnders'' in 2006 played by child actor Charlie Jones. Jones was cast alongside [[Megan Jossa]], who would play his cousin [[Courtney Mitchell]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.digitalspy.co.uk/soaps/news/a28246/mitchell-kids-to-return-to-walford.html|title=Mitchell kids to return to Walford |last=Wilkes|first=Neil|date=19 January 2006|work=[[Digital Spy]]|publisher=Digital Spy Ltd|accessdate=21 July 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt; While Ben is partially deaf, Jones is a hearing actor. ''[[The Guardian]]''{{'s}} Rebecca Atkinson suggested that, as only the second disabled character in ''EastEnders''{{'s}} history, Ben was introduced to fulfil a BBC quota. She criticised Jones' casting, and opined, &quot;The use of able-bodied actors to play disabled characters is endemic. Maybe in theory there's nothing wrong with that, but while real disabled people are invisible it is downright offensive to persistently cast able-bodied people in disabled roles.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.guardian.co.uk/commentisfree/2006/jul/11/television.comment|title=Big Brother's 'freak show' has produced the first warts-and-all disabled person on TV - when will the soaps follow?|last=Atkinson|first=Rebecca|date=11 July 2006|work=[[The Guardian]]|publisher=[[Guardian News and Media]]|accessdate=18 November 2011|location=London}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Joe Wicks==
{{Main|Joe Wicks}}
'''Joe Wicks''' was played by [[Paul Nicholls (actor)|Paul Nicholls]]. He appeared on screen between 25 March 1996 and 14 November 1997. ''EastEnders'' was praised for the character's portrayal of [[schizophrenia]]. ''EastEnders'' story editor, Ian Aldwinkle, decided to introduce a character with schizophrenia after working on the drama series ''[[Casualty (TV series)|Casualty]]'', which featured violent and dramatic incidents involving people with the illness, but only focussed on the medical side. Aldwinkle researched the illness and says he was shocked to discover that it affects one in 100 people, but it was rarely spoken about. He said: &quot;Because it has a continuing storyline, ''EastEnders'' was able to look at the effect that schizophrenia has on a family and on individual relationships. I wanted to humanise it and look at the emotional impact it has on people.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;schizophrenia&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.schizophrenia.com/newsletter/697/697eastend.htm|title=EastEnders TV Program covers Schizophrenia |publisher=schizophrenia.com|date=10 May 1997|accessdate=12 May 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt; He said he hoped that the storyline would be helpful, saying &quot;It seems to me that mental illness is one of the last subjects that you can still make jokes about without being labelled politically incorrect, and that seems wrong. If I get just one letter from one person saying that the character of Joe Wicks has helped to change their life for the better, then I will be pleased.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;schizophrenia&quot;/&gt;

==Lorraine Wicks==
{{Main|Lorraine Wicks}}
'''Lorraine Wicks''' was played by [[Jacqueline Leonard]] between 1996 and 1997. Introduced in April 1996, Lorraine was the former wife of the already established character [[David Wicks]] ([[Michael French]]). She was brought into the serial along with her son [[Joe Wicks]] ([[Paul Nicholls]]).&lt;ref name=&quot;20years&quot;&gt;{{cite book |last= Smith|first= Rupert|title= [[EastEnders books#Non-fiction books|''EastEnders: 20 years in Albert Square]] |year=2005|publisher=BBC books|isbn=0-563-52165-1}}&lt;/ref&gt; Author Kate Lock has described Lorraine as &quot;relentlessly sensible, fair and nice&quot; but with a &quot;rogue gene&quot; that prompted her to select the wrong kind of men.&lt;ref name=&quot;who&quot;&gt;{{cite book |last=Lock |first= Kate|title=[[EastEnders books|EastEnders Who's Who]] |year=2000|publisher=BBC Books|isbn=0-563-55178-X}}&lt;/ref&gt; As well as a high-profile storyline concentrating on Joe's diagnosis of [[schizophrenia]], Lorraine's most prominent storyline was a love triangle between herself, [[Grant Mitchell (EastEnders)|Grant Mitchell]] ([[Ross Kemp]]) and Grant's wife [[Tiffany Mitchell|Tiffany]] ([[Martine McCutcheon]]). In the storyline, Lorraine discovered that Tiffany was keeping a secret from Grant - that he was potentially not the father of her unborn child. When Tiffany refused to tell Grant the truth, Lorraine did, making way for them to become a legitimate couple, albeit briefly. Leonard commented in December 1996, &quot;Lorraine has had a year on her own and she feels that she probably needs a bit of contact - and Grant's quite macho. It was very interesting from my point of view because Lorraine could be perceived as being bitchy and she's not. She genuinely cares about Tiffany and their marriage and the baby and she wants the whole situation sorted out. But she and Grant do like each other and care about each other and it loses control a bit.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;xmas&quot;&gt;{{cite news|title=Lorraine's seasons cheatings; EastEnder Jacqueline Leonard tells all about her festive frolics|publisher=[[Daily Record (Scotland)|Daily Record]]|first=John|last=Millar|date=24 December 1996|accessdate=26 July 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Alistair Matthews==
{{Infobox soap character 2 
|series=EastEnders
|name=Alistair Matthews
|portrayer=[[Neil Clark (actor)|Neil Clark]]
|years=1996–97
|first=23 April 1996
|last=31 March 1997
|classification=[[List of past EastEnders characters#Last appeared in 1997|Former; recurring]]
|occupation=Store manager
}}
'''Alistair Matthews''', played by [[Neil Clark (actor)|Neil Clark]], was a store manager who caught [[Sarah Hills]] ([[Daniela Denby-Ashe]]) shoplifting in April 1996, but promised not to call the police if she attended his Christian fellowship and turned her back on her sinful ways. Sarah was captivated by Alistair's Christian preachings and joined his fellowship. [[Frankie Pierre]] was drawn to Alistair too, and when he turned her advances down, she spread rumours that they were sexually involved; although Alistair publicly denied this, causing Frankie's downfall in Walford.

Alistair condemned Sarah for having pre-marital sex with [[Robbie Jackson]] ([[Dean Gaffney]]) during a crisis of faith. However, Sarah was hurt to discover that Alistair did not practice the piety that he preached, and when she realised that he was having pre-marital sex with his girlfriend Sue Taylor, she denounced him publicly in front of his congregation.
{{-}}

==Jim Branning==
{{Main|Jim Branning}}
'''Jim Branning''' was played by [[John Bardon]], first appearing on 29 April 1996 and becoming a regular character in 1999 and has remained in the series right up to 2011. Jim was written out of the show in August 2007 due to Bardon suffering a [[stroke]]. A storyline was created that Jim also suffered a stroke. It was reported on 10 March 2008 that Bardon would be returning to the role of Jim in summer 2008.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.thesun.co.uk/sol/homepage/showbiz/tv/article895063.ece|title=Jim Branning back in Walford|work=[[The Sun (United Kingdom)|The Sun]]|date=2008-03-10|accessdate=2008-03-10|location=London|first=Sara|last=Nathan}}&lt;/ref&gt; Bardon returned to film four episodes in the latter half of 2008. He returned permanently from the episode broadcast on 20 August 2009. On 1 April 2011 it was reported by the [[Daily Mirror]] that Bardon had filmed his final scenes and had left. He departed on 26 May 2011. On the behest of producer [[John Yorke (television producer)|John Yorke]] in 2000, Jim was paired romantically with pensioner [[Dot Cotton]], played by [[June Brown]]; a slow courtship was featured, with Dot often shown to be outraged by Jim's advances, resulting in numerous rejections. Dot finally succumbed and accepted his marriage proposal in an episode that aired in November 2001; the scenes were filmed inside one of the carriages of the [[London Eye]] on the [[South Bank]] of the [[River Thames]]. Their wedding aired on 14 February 2002, [[Valentine's Day]]. ''The Guardian'' critic, [[Nancy Banks-Smith]], described the wedding as &quot;uniquely uneventful [...] For Dot and Jim 'In sickness and health... till death do us part' seemed to carry more resonance than for most.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.guardian.co.uk/media/2002/feb/15/tvandradio.television2|title= Cotton shocks|work=The Guardian|date=15 February 2002|accessdate=2 August 2009 | location=London | first=Nancy | last=Banks-Smith}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Suzy Branning==
{{Main|Suzy Branning}}
'''Suzy Branning''' (originally known as '''Sue''') was played by [[Maggie O'Neill]] in 2008,&lt;ref name=&quot;sun&quot;&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.thesun.co.uk/sol/homepage/showbiz/tv/soaps/article1076832.ece|title=Maggie wants her Mitchell|work=[[The Sun (United Kingdom)|The Sun]]|date=2008-04-23|accessdate=2008-04-23}}&lt;/ref&gt; and was played by Julie Christian-Young for a brief appearance in 1996. O'Neill began filming in May 2008, and she made her first on-screen appearance on 8 July 2008.&lt;ref name=&quot;DS&quot;&gt;&quot;[http://www.digitalspy.co.uk/soaps/a94437/shameless-actress-joins-eastenders.html 'Shameless' actress joins 'EastEnders']&quot;, ''Digital Spy''. URL last accessed 2008-04-23.&lt;/ref&gt;. She made her last appearance on Boxing Day 2008. Suzy, who is referred to as Sue in her younger days, was born to [[Jim Branning|Jim]] and [[Reenie Branning]], in 1966. She is their fourth child, with [[April Branning|April]], [[Derek Branning|Derek]] and [[Carol Jackson|Carol]] being her older siblings. Until brothers [[Max Branning|Max]] and [[Jack Branning|Jack]] came along, she was the centre of attention. She is first seen in 1996 for April's wedding to her fiancé Nikos, along with her children, Rebecca and Kevin.

==Derek Branning==
{{Main|Derek Branning}}
'''Derek Branning''', played by [[Terence Beesley]] in 1996 and [[Jamie Foreman]] from 2011 onwards, is the eldest child of [[Jim Branning]] ([[John Bardon]]) and [[Reenie Branning]] (Joy Graham). Derek made his first appearance on 29 April 1996 and departed not long after. The character returned as a regular character on 24 November 2011, played by Foreman.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Enders fiver for Jamie Foreman|url=http://www.thesun.co.uk/sol/homepage/showbiz/tv/soaps/3896536/Enders-fiver-for-Jamie-Foreman.html|work=[[The Sun (United Kingdom)|The Sun]]|accessdate=29 November 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; Derek is originally portrayed as a [[racist]] and is against his sister [[Carol Jackson|Carol]] ([[Lindsey Coulson]]) marrying [[Alan Jackson (EastEnders)|Alan]] ([[Howard Antony]]). Derek is described as a &quot;charmer&quot;{{Fact|date=November 2011}} and &quot;proper East-End&quot;.{{Fact|date=November 2011}} In an interview with ''[[Daybreak]]'', Foreman said he wants viewers to &quot;like Derek&quot;.{{Fact|date=November 2011}} Discussing Derek's personality, Foreman told ''[[TV Choice]]'': &quot;There's always this little undercurrent of, 'This guy isn't who we want around for long', if you see what I mean. Derek's just come back from a 10-year prison sentence for armed robbery. He's a very complicated character, who could either be perceived as a bully or as someone who cares for his family very much.&quot;{{Fact|date=November 2011}}
{{-}}

==Reenie Branning==
{{Infobox soap character 2 | series = EastEnders
|image=
|name=Reenie Branning
|portrayer=[[Joy Graham]]
|years=1996
|first=29 April 1996
|last=30 April 1996
|classification=[[List of past EastEnders characters#Last appeared in 1996|Former; guest]]
|born=
|death =8 October 1999
|occupation=Retired
|family=[[Branning family|Branning]]
|husband=[[Jim Branning]] (1960–99)
|sons=[[Derek Branning]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Max Branning]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Jack Branning]]
|daughters=[[April Branning]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Suzy Branning]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Carol Jackson]]
|grandsons=[[Bradley Branning]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Oscar Branning]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Robbie Jackson]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Billie Jackson]]&lt;br /&gt;[[#Kevin|Kevin]]&lt;br&gt;[[Richard Mitchell (EastEnders)|Richard Mitchell]] &lt;br /&gt; [[James Branning]]
|granddaughters=[[Lauren Branning]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Abi Branning]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Penny Branning]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Bianca Butcher]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Sonia Fowler]]&lt;br /&gt;[[#Rebecca|Rebecca]] &lt;br&gt; [[Amy Mitchell]]
}}
'''Doreen &quot;Reenie&quot; Branning''' played by Joy Graham, is the first wife of [[Jim Branning]] ([[John Bardon]]), and mother of [[Derek Branning]] ([[Jamie Foreman]]) [[April Branning]] ([[Debbie Arnold]]), [[Carol Jackson]] ([[Lindsey Coulson]]), [[Suzy Branning]] ([[Maggie O'Neill]]), [[Max Branning]] ([[Jake Wood]]) and [[Jack Branning]] ([[Scott Maslen]]).

Reenie had dated Jim in the early 1960s and gave birth to his oldest child Derek out of wedlock. When she got pregnant again with daughter April, Jim then stepped up and proposed, and they married in a [[shotgun wedding]]. However they never got on well together and fought like cat and dog, but Reenie depended heavily on her husband and whenever they got close to separating and ending their marriage, she got pregnant. This resulted in her giving birth, in chronological order, to Derek (1960), April (1961),&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |last=Lock |first= Kate|title=[[EastEnders books|EastEnders Who's Who]] |year=2000|publisher=BBC Books|id=ISBN 0-563-55178-X}}&lt;/ref&gt; Carol (1962),  Suzy (1966),&lt;ref&gt;&quot;[http://www.digitalspy.co.uk/soaps/a135765/max-visits-tanya-in-prison.html Max visits Tanya in prison]&quot;, [[Digital Spy]]. URL last accessed 2008-11-20.&lt;/ref&gt; Max(1969)&lt;ref&gt;{{cite episode |title=&quot;Tony loses his cool&quot;|url=http://www.bbc.co.uk/eastenders/episodes/past/episode20080925.shtml|series=EastEnders|serieslink=EastEnders|credits=Written by [[Annie Wood]]. Series created by [[Julia Smith]] and [[Tony Holland]]. Directed by [[Jo Johnson]]. Executive producer: [[Diederick Santer]].|network=[[BBC One]]|airdate=2008-09-25}}&lt;/ref&gt; and Jack (1972).&lt;ref&gt;{{cite episode |title=&quot;Max stops the move&quot;|url=http://www.bbc.co.uk/eastenders/episodes/past/episode20081024.shtml|series=EastEnders|serieslink=EastEnders|credits=Written by [[Carey Andrews]]. Series created by [[Julia Smith]] and [[Tony Holland]]. Directed by [[Michael Owen Morris]]. Script editor: [[Peter Mattessi]], executive producer: [[Diederick Santer]].|network=[[BBC One]]|airdate=2008-10-24|minutes=10:32}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Reenie was said to be very maternal and doted on all of her children, despite their faults. She was particularly close to her oldest daughter April, whilst her relationship with daughters Carol and Suzy was notably strained due to their choice of lifestyle. She was also said to be very distraught when her son Max walked out on the family in 1989, and despite keeping in regular contact with her grandson [[Bradley Branning|Bradley]] and Max's ex-wife [[Rachel Branning|Rachel]], she never saw Max again. Reenie appeared on-screen in April 1996, in the lead-up to April's wedding to her fiancé Nikos.

Off-screen, in October 1999 it was revealed that Reenie was critically ill, and her daughter Carol left Walford to care for her. A few weeks later Reenie died, and it was mentioned by her grandson [[Robbie Jackson|Robbie]] that her funeral was attended by Carol, Carol's ex-husband [[Alan Jackson|Alan]] and her grandchildren Robbie, [[Sonia Fowler|Sonia]] and [[Billie Jackson|Billie]]. Her oldest granddaughter [[Bianca Jackson|Bianca]] was notably not present at the funeral due to her feud with her mother. A month after her demise Reenie's husband Jim arrived in Walford to care for their grandchildren Robbie and Sonia after Carol reconciled with Alan.
{{-}}

==Huw Edwards==
{{main|Huw Edwards (EastEnders)}}
'''Huw Edwards''' was played by [[Wales|welsh]] actor [[Richard Elis]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.thefreelibrary.com/EASTENDER+HUW+WEDS+HIS+PATIENT.-a060640297|title=EASTENDER HUW WEDS HIS PATIENT.|publisher=[[The People]]|date=19 April 1999|accessdate=1 July 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt; Huw was introduced in 1996 and remained on-screen till 1999.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/wales/2910939.stm|title=Sixties icon joins EastEnders|publisher=[[BBC News]]|date=3 April 2003|accessdate=1 July 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt; Actor Richard Elis was cast in the minor role of Huw for a period of three episodes in 1996; however, producers enjoyed the character and his contract was extended.&lt;ref name=&quot;interview&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.thefreelibrary.com/East+End+Welsh+boy%3b+He+was+responsible+for+the+only+Welsh+accent+to...-a0218855472|title=East End Welsh boy|publisher=[[Western Mail (Wales)|Western Mail]]|date=13 February 2010|accessdate=1 July 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt; It was reported in December 1998 that executive producer [[Matthew Robinson (producer)|Matthew Robinson]] had axed Huw because the character was &quot;going nowhere&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.thefreelibrary.com/Matthew+Wright's+Column%3a+Operation+Deserted+Square%3b+Tiff's+mum+the...-a060624929|title=Operation Deserted Square|publisher=[[Daily Mirror|The Mirror]]|date=23 December 1998|accessdate=1 July 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt; However, Elis claimed in 2010 that he decided to leave the role in 1999 after three years playing Huw as he feared being typecast. Elis has commented, &quot;My agent at the time told me that if you are in a soap for three years, it takes three years for the viewers to forget you, whereas if you are in one for five years, it takes another 10 years before they forget you. I just felt it was time to go. It was great to be on it but it was just a job to me.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;interview&quot;/&gt;

==Lenny Wallace==
{{Main|Lenny Wallace}}
'''Lenny Wallace''' was played by [[Desune Coleman]]. Lenny is a fun loving individual, who doesn't take life too seriously. He has a penchant for loud music and an eye for the ladies. Lenny was first seen in [[Walford]] in May 1996. Lenny, along with his Welsh friend, [[Huw Edwards (EastEnders)|Huw Edwards]] ([[Richard Elis]]), were employed by [[George Palmer (EastEnders)|George Palmer]] (Paul Moriarty) as barmen for the [[Scarlet (EastEnders)|Cobra Club]]. Lenny had a keen interest in [[motorcycle speedway|speedway]] [[motorcycle sport|motorbike racing]], and took Ricky Butcher along with him on one occasion. Ricky turned out to be quite a skilled racer and Lenny was soon persuading him to take up speedway racing professionally so he could be his manager. He was sacked shortly after when Ricky's wife Bianca decided to take over the job in his place. Lenny returned to work as a barman in 1998, firstly for [[Annie Palmer]] ([[Nadia Sawalha]]) at the Market Cellar until she fired him, and then for [[Steve Owen (EastEnders)|Steve Owen]] ([[Martin Kemp]]) at the e20.

==Simon Raymond==
{{Main|Simon Raymond}}
'''Simon Raymond''' was played by [[Andrew Lynford]]. Simon was introduced in 1996 as the homosexual brother of [[Tiffany Mitchell]] ([[Martine McCutcheon]]). His relationship with the bisexual character [[Tony Hills]] ([[Mark Homer]]) featured a gay kiss that caused controversy in the UK; numerous complaints were made because of its broadcasting. Simon remained in the serial until 1999, at which time it was mutually agreed between Lynford and executive producer [[Matthew Robinson (producer)|Matthew Robinson]], that the character had run its course. The character was given a happy ending, reuniting with his former boyfriend Tony to travel Europe. Lynford has suggested that he and the writers of ''EastEnders'' intended to portray Simon as a &quot;perfectly normal&quot; young gay man who would entertain and educate and for whom sexuality was &quot;no big deal&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;gazette&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.wgazette.com/aut04-response.html|title=EastEnders Actor Responds to Gazette Article |publisher=Walford Gazette|accessdate=1 July 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Frankie Pierre==
{{Main|Frankie Pierre}}
'''Maxine Francesca &quot;Frankie&quot; Pierre'''&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url= http://web.archive.org/web/20010806115910/www.bbc.co.uk/eastenders/characters/frankie_p_biog.shtml|title= Frankie Pierre|publisher=''[[BBC]]'' |accessdate=28 November 2007}}&lt;/ref&gt; She appeared between 1996 and 1997, played by [[Syan Blake]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url= http://www.bbc.co.uk/eastenders/characters_cast/characters/character_frankie_p.shtml|title= Frankie Pierre|publisher=''[[BBC]]'' |accessdate=28 November 2007}}&lt;/ref&gt; Frankie was introduced as a &quot;super-bitch&quot; and home wrecker. She attempted to ruin the established relationships of several characters during her year in the soap, purposefully seducing attached men. Frankie’s arrival in June 1996 was part of a storyline that broke up the marriage of the characters [[Alan Jackson (EastEnders)|Alan]] and [[Carol Jackson]] ([[Howard Antony]] and [[Lindsey Coulson]]).&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url= http://findarticles.com/p/articles/mi_qn4161/is_19970608/ai_n14465052|title= EastEnder Carol's love life is more complicated than TV soap plot|publisher=''[[Sunday Mirror]]'' | author = Alison Bowyer| date = 8 June 1997| accessdate=28 November 2007}}&lt;/ref&gt; Frankie eventually departed the serial in March 1997 amidst a failed attempt at seducing a religious evangelist, [[Alistair Matthews]], who had been trying to make her change her promiscuous lifestyle. Off-screen it was reported that Syan Blake and the producers of ''EastEnders'' had decided to write the character out of the serial, as the actress was receiving death threats from angry fans that could not separate fact from fiction, and blamed Blake for her character’s home-wrecking. The official ''EastEnders'' book ''Who’s Who'' states that Frankie “had a carnivorous approach to relationships, hunting down her quarry, devouring her victim in two gulps and then moving onto the next kill.”&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |last=Lock |first= Kate|title=[[EastEnders books|EastEnders Who's Who]] |year=2000|publisher=BBC Books|id=ISBN 0-563-55178-X}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title= Once burnt, Syan's shy: Hunted by the media and confused fans |publisher=''[[The Voice (newspaper)|The Voice]]'' | date = 2 June 1997| accessdate=28 November 2007}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Mick McFarlane==
{{Main|Mick McFarlane}}
'''Mick McFarlane''' was played by [[Sylvester Williams (actor)|Sylvester Williams]]. Mick was an easy-going guy, who hoped to make it big as a [[musician]]. However his music career failed and he ended up selling CDs on a market stall in [[Albert Square]]. After several ill-fated attempts at a career change, he finally got his life's wish and left [[Walford]] in 2002 to tour with a [[band (music)|band]]. When Kim discovered what Mick had been through, she bought his saxophone back with the money for her school trip, contacted Mick's musician contact and accepted the gig on his behalf. Kim was adamant that Mick should follow his dream, and so Mick left Kim with a relative away from the Square and left Walford in January 2002.

==George Palmer==
{{Main|George Palmer (EastEnders)}}
'''George Palmer''' was played by [[Paul Moriarty (actor)|Paul Moriarty]]. He appeared between 1996 and 1998, but was one of many characters axed by then Executive Producer [[Matthew Robinson (producer)|Matthew Robinson]]. Actor Paul Moriarty was asked to read for the role of George along with 10 other actors.&lt;ref name=&quot;gazette&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.wgazette.com/int-moriarty.html|title=George Palmer, Who Art Thou?|publisher=Walford Gazette|first=Tim|last=Wilson|accessdate=15 August 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt; Moriarty was called back instantly and asked to begin working on the role the following day. He has commented to an American fan-based publication, &quot;[It was] quite overwhelming. I had watched the show but not religiously [...] So I show up at [the studios in] Borehamwood the very next day, straight to make-up and then onto [the soap's setting of] Albert Square to do my first bit [...] I might just as well have landed on Mars.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;gazette&quot;/&gt; George had been described as &quot;shady&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.mirror.co.uk/news/top-stories/2009/08/27/soap-bride-and-gloom-115875-21627191/|title=Soap bride and gloom|work=[[Daily Mirror]]|accessdate=2009-08-25}}&lt;/ref&gt; The character was one of many to be axed in 1998 by Executive Producer [[Matthew Robinson (producer)|Matthew Robinson]], following a dip in ratings.&lt;ref name=&quot;axed&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.highbeam.com/doc/1G1-60565546.html|title=ALBERT SQUARE MASSACRE|work=[[Daily Record (Scotland)|Daily Record]]|accessdate=2009-08-25}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Charlie Mason==
{{Infobox soap character 2 | series = EastEnders
|image=
|name=Charlie Mason
|portrayer=[[Campbell Morrison]]
|years=1996, 1998–99
|first=8 October 1996
|last=5 October 1999
|occupation=[[Detective]]
}}
'''Detective Chief Inspector Charlie Mason''' was a detective who first appeared when [[Ian Beale]] was shot by hitman [[John Valecue]], working for his wife, [[Cindy Beale|Cindy]]. He later appeared when [[Tiffany Mitchell]] fell down the stairs at [[The Queen Vic]], and arrested [[Grant Mitchell (EastEnders)|Grant Mitchell]] for her attempted murder on [[Christmas Day]] 1998. He later appeared at the inquest into Tiffany's death in January 1999. He also investigated [[Saskia Duncan]]'s disappearance in March 1999 and appeared at [[Steve Owen (EastEnders)|Steve Owen]] and [[Matthew Rose (EastEnders)|Matthew Rose]]'s trial for her murder in October 1999. This was his last appearance.
{{-}}

==Terry Raymond==
{{Main|Terry Raymond}}
'''Terry Raymond''' was played by [[Gavin Richards]]. Terry was initially introduced briefly in 1996 as the drunken father of [[Tiffany Mitchell|Tiffany]] ([[Martine McCutcheon]]) and [[Simon Raymond]] ([[Andrew Lynford]]). He was reintroduced as a full-time character in 1997 and remained in the serial until 2002, when actor Gavin Richards decided to leave. It was announced that Gavin Richards quit the role in November 2001. He commented, &quot;I had a wonderful time but feel I have to devote my energies to other projects.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.dailymail.co.uk/tvshowbiz/article-85353/EastEnders-Terry-quit-soap.html|title=EastEnders' Terry to quit soap|publisher=Daily Mail|date=2001-11-21|accessdate=2011-02-09 | location=London}}&lt;/ref&gt; A source reportedly told the press that Richards had been unhappy in the role since the exit of his on-screen wife Irene ([[Roberta Taylor]]), as he felt that he had &quot;not been given enough juicy storylines.&quot; Terry was not killed off in the soap; he departed in 2002 in search of his estranged wife.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.thefreelibrary.com/ENDER+THE+LINE+FOR+TV+TERRY%3b+Soap+star+quits.-a080220213|title=ENDER THE LINE FOR TV TERRY; Soap star quits|publisher=Daily Record|date=2001-11-21|accessdate=2011-02-09 | location=London}}&lt;/ref&gt; Tim Randall from the ''Daily Record'' suggested in 2001 that Terry and Irene's double-act was &quot;''EastEnders'' at its best&quot;, but that the relationship between Terry and Janine was &quot;enough to turn your stomach&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.thefreelibrary.com/Soap+gossip...-a080501651|title=Soap gossip|publisher=Daily Record|date=2001-12-01|accessdate=2011-02-09 | location=London | first=Charles | last=Oulton}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;br clear=all&gt;

==Others==
{| class=&quot;wikitable plainrowheaders&quot; style=&quot;font-size:90%&quot;
|-
! scope=&quot;col&quot; | Character
! scope=&quot;col&quot; | Date(s)
! scope=&quot;col&quot; | Actor
! scope=&quot;col&quot; | Circumstances
|-
! scope=&quot;row&quot; | {{nowrap|Kevin}}
| {{nowrap|29–30 April}}
| {{nowrap|[[Jamie Dispirito]]}}
| {{Anchor|Kevin}} The young son of [[Suzy Branning]] attending his aunt, [[April Branning]]'s wedding. He acted as the pageboy. He was then mentioned in December 2008 when Suzy told her fiancé Phil that she had a son and a daughter but never spoke to them.
|-
! scope=&quot;row&quot; | {{nowrap|Rebecca}}
| {{nowrap|29–30 April}}
| {{nowrap|[[Alice Dawnay]]}}
| {{Anchor|Rebecca}} The teenage daughter of [[Suzy Branning]] attending her aunt, [[April Branning]]'s wedding. She acted as a bridesmaid and her cousin [[Robbie Jackson]] was attracted to her. She was then mentioned in December 2008 when Suzy told her fiancee Phil that she had a son and a daughter but never spoke to them.
|-
! scope=&quot;row&quot; | {{nowrap|John Valecue}}
| {{nowrap|28 October 1996– &lt;br/&gt; 10 April 1998}}
| {{nowrap|[[Steve Weston (English actor)|Steve Weston]]}}
| {{Anchor|John Valecue}} A [[contract killing|professional hitman]], hired by [[Cindy Beale]] to kill her husband [[Ian Beale|Ian]]. He shot Ian on 7 October 1996, but failed to kill him, leaving him wounded in hospital. Ian failed to identify his assailant, but Valecue was later arrested for another failed shooting. [[Annie Palmer]] and [[Ros Thorne]] visited him in prison in 1998 when they were trying to help Ian get custody of his stepson [[Steven Beale|Steven]] and son [[Peter Beale|Peter]]. Annie threatened to use her contacts inside the prison to get at Valecue, unless he implicated Cindy in the attempted murder of Ian. He did so and Cindy was arrested and charged for attempted murder.
|}

==References==
{{reflist}}

{{EastEnders}}
{{EastEnders characters|year}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:List Of Eastenders Characters (1996)}}
[[Category:Lists of EastEnders characters|1996]]
[[Category:Fictional characters introduced in 1996|*, EastEnders]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
