<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="12811304" ns="0" title="List of EastEnders characters (2002)"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{DISPLAYTITLE:List of ''EastEnders'' characters (2002)}}
The following is a list of characters that first appeared in the [[BBC]] [[soap opera]] ''[[EastEnders]]'' in 2002, by order of first appearance.
{{TOClimit|limit=2}}

==Jack Evans==
{{Infobox soap character 2 | series = EastEnders
|image=
|name=Jack Evans
|portrayer=Samuel Timson &lt;br /&gt;Joseph Timson
|years=2002–04
|first=11 January 2002
|last=10 May 2004
|born= 11 January 2002
|mother=[[Natalie Evans]]
|father=[[Barry Evans (EastEnders)|Barry Evans]]
|grandfathers=[[Roy Evans (EastEnders)|Roy Evans]]&lt;br /&gt;Dave Price
|grandmothers=Doreen Evans&lt;br /&gt;[[Andrea Price]]
|uncles=[[Nathan Williams (EastEnders)|Nathan Williams]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Jack Price (EastEnders)|Jack Price]]&lt;br /&gt;Kevin Price
|aunts=[[Susie Price]]
|cousins=Chris
}}
'''Jack Evans''' was played by the [[identical twins]] Samuel Timson and Joseph Timson. He was the son of [[Barry Evans (EastEnders)|Barry]] and [[Natalie Evans]] and he had a traumatic [[breech birth]] early in 2002. He was named after Natalie's younger brother.

Jack initially lived with his parents, his grandfather [[Roy Evans (EastEnders)|Roy]] and Roy's wife [[Pat Evans|Pat]], but moved out of [[Albert Square]] in March 2003 following his parents' [[divorce]]. Barry was devoted to Jack and agonised over the fact that he couldn't be a full-time father to him.

Jack's father met an untimely demise early in 2004 and, as no [[Will (law)|will]] was in place, Barry's new wife [[Janine Evans]] inherited all Barry's money and assets, leaving Jack with nothing.  When Jack's mother discovered that Janine was responsible for Barry's death, she left [[Walford]] for a new start with Jack. Before they departed, Natalie and Jack planted a [[tree]] on the Square in Barry's name. Jack's last appearance was in May 2004.
{{-}}

==Anish Mistry==
{{Infobox soap character 2 | series = EastEnders
|image=
|name=Anish Mistry
|portrayer=[[Ali Zahoor]]
|years=2002–03
|first=25 January 2002
|last=28 February 2003
|home=[[India]]
|mother=[[Nita Mistry]]
|stepfather=[[Robbie Jackson]]
}}
'''Anish Mistry''' was about eight years old and arrived in 2002 with his mother [[Nita Mistry]]. Anish liked playing [[Football (soccer)|football]]. He left [[Walford]] in 2003 to live in [[India]] with Nita and her boyfriend [[Robbie Jackson]].
{{-}}

==Minty Peterson==
{{Main|Minty Peterson}}

==Tom Banks==
{{Main|Tom Banks (EastEnders)}}

==Neil Miller==
{{Infobox soap character 2 | series = EastEnders
|image=
|name=Neil Miller
|portrayer= Robin Sneller
|years=2002
|first=7 May 2002
|last=9 May 2002
|born=1969
|death=March 2005
|wife= [[Sue Miller (EastEnders)|Sue Wilson]] (?–2005)
|adoptivedaughters=[[Rebecca Miller (EastEnders)|Rebecca Miller]]
}}
'''Neil Miller''' first appeared on in May 2002. He was the adoptive father of [[Sonia Fowler|Sonia Jackson]] and [[Martin Fowler (EastEnders)|Martin Fowler]]'s daughter. Sonia gave birth to baby [[Rebecca Miller (EastEnders)|Chloe]] in 2000, but decided to give her daughter up for adoption. Chloe's social worker, [[Diane Irving]] found Chloe a home with Neil and his wife [[Sue Miller (EastEnders)|Sue]], a childless couple, though this was not seen on screen. Neil and Sue changed Chloe's name to Rebecca.

In 2002, Sonia [[kidnap]]ped Rebecca while Neil and Sue were out. Sonia told their babysitter that she was a family friend, and snatched Rebecca, taking her to [[Walford]]. Neil and Sue worked this out and were hot on her trail.

While Sonia barricaded herself inside her house, the Millers gave [[Dot Branning]] fifteen minutes to persuade Sonia to hand Rebecca over before they phoned the police. Dot successfully persuaded Sonia to hand Rebecca over, and just as the Millers were about to call the police, Sonia returned Rebecca.

Sonia read in a newspaper in 2005 that Neil and Sue had died in a car crash. This led to her gaining contact with Rebecca again.
{{-}}

==Sue Miller==
{{Infobox soap character 2 | series = EastEnders
|image=
|name=Sue Miller
|portrayer=Victoria Willing
|years=2002
|first=7 May 2002
|last=9 May 2002
|born=1967
|death=March 2005
|husband= [[#Neil Miller|Neil Miller]] (?–2005)
|mother=[[Margaret Wilson (EastEnders)|Margaret Wilson]]
|adoptivedaughters=[[Rebecca Miller (EastEnders)|Rebecca Miller]]
}}
'''Sue Miller''' (née '''Wilson''') first appeared on in May 2002. She was the adoptive mother of [[Sonia Fowler|Sonia Jackson]] and [[Martin Fowler (EastEnders)|Martin Fowler]]'s daughter. Sonia gave birth to baby [[Rebecca Miller (EastEnders)|Chloe]] in 2000, but decided to give her daughter up for adoption. Chloe's social worker, [[List of EastEnders characters (2001)#Diane Irving|Diane Irving]] found Chloe a home with Sue and her husband [[Neil Miller (EastEnders)|Neil]], a childless couple, though this was not seen on screen. Neil and Sue changed Chloe's name to Rebecca.

In 2002, Sonia [[kidnap]]ped Rebecca while Neil and Sue were out. Sonia told their babysitter that she was a family friend, and snatched Rebecca, taking her to [[Walford]]. Neil and Sue worked this out and were hot on her trail.

While Sonia barricaded herself inside her house, the Millers gave [[Dot Branning]] fifteen minutes to persuade Sonia to hand Rebecca over before they phoned the police. Dot successfully persuaded Sonia to hand Rebecca over, and just as the Millers were about to call the police, Sonia returned Rebecca.

Sonia read in a newspaper in 2005 that Neil and Sue had died in a car crash. This led to her gaining contact with Rebecca again.
{{-}}

==Gus Smith==
{{Main|Gus Smith}}

==Precious Hudson==
{{Infobox soap character 2 | series = EastEnders
|image=
|name=Precious Hudson
|portrayer=[[Judi Shekoni]]
|years=2002
|first=11 June 2002
|last=19 July 2002
|husband= [[Angel Hudson]]
|mother=[[Estella Hulton]]
}}
'''Marjorie &quot;Precious&quot; Hudson''' (née '''Hulton''') was the glamorous wife of [[gangster]] [[Angel Hudson]] and she was first seen in [[Walford]] in June 2002 when Angel forced his old associate, [[Paul Trueman]], to keep a watchful eye over her. It turned out that Precious was Angel's fake [[alibi]] in a [[murder]] [[trial]] and fearing that she might skip town or be harmed before she could testify, he arranged for Precious to move in with the Trueman's and instructed Paul not to let her out of his sight.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;[http://www.thesun.co.uk/article/0,,7-2002301165,00.html A punchy chat with Judi]&quot;, ''[[The Sun (United Kingdom)|The Sun]]''. URL last accessed 2007-09-05.&lt;/ref&gt;

Initially Paul was unaware of the fact that Precious was Angel's wife, and so when she made her amorous intentions towards him clear, he had no qualms whatsoever about sharing a bed with her. When she finally told him the truth, he was horrified, and petrified of what Angel would do should he discover what had occurred between them. Precious reassured him that their marriage was a sham and promised not to divulge the affair. However later that night, whilst Paul went to get a take-away for a cosy night in together, Precious packed her bags and left. Paul was frantic, particularly when Angel showed up looking for her. Paul fed Angel a story and he along with his brother, [[Anthony Trueman|Anthony]], went in search of Precious, leaving Angel home alone with their father, [[Patrick Trueman|Patrick]]. Paul eventually tracked Precious to her mother's hair salon, and desperately tried to persuade her to return, but she refused and sped off in a [[Taxicab|taxi]]. Paul returned home to discover his father bound and gagged by Angel, who was also holding Anthony's girlfriend, [[Zoe Slater|Zoe]], hostage. Angel attacked Paul, just as Precious walked in the door. She had changed her mind about returning because she loved Paul.

A few days later some shady characters were seen placing a bomb underneath Precious' car - timed to go off half an hour before she was due to be at the [[solicitor]] with Angel. However Precious had put her car into the local mechanics for a service and when it exploded only [[Garry Hobbs]] was hurt but the injuries where fortunately not serious. Precious was furious that her life was under threat and she told Angel she would lie for him in the trial but only if he gave her a divorce. Soon after Precious was [[kidnap]]ped by the father of the man Angel murdered. He convinced Precious that the only way to get rid of Angel was to get him locked up. Precious realised that Angel would never divorce her and would rather see her dead, so she decided to tell the truth in the trial the following day, but to her horror Angel was found not guilty anyway. 

Paul and Precious then decided to flee Walford for [[Spain]]. However an altercation in [[The Queen Vic]] between the Truemans and the Slaters stalled their departure and after Paul got into a fight with [[Garry Hobbs]] he was carted away by the police. Meanwhile, Precious, who was waiting for Paul was caught by Angel.

Precious told Angel she was in love with Paul and wanted a divorce. Surprisingly Angel wasn't bothered and he told Precious that he didn't care enough about her betrayal to kill her and that she could have her divorce. Paul was a different matter however. He promised that if he ever found out that she and Paul were together, he would kill him. In order to protect Paul, Precious was forced to lie. She told him she wasn't in love with him and said she was just using him as an escape from Angel. After which she left Walford, leaving Paul with a broken heart. Her last appearance was July 2002.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;[http://www.thesun.co.uk/article/0,,2001330006-2002311236,00.html Guide to soaps]&quot;, ''[[The Sun (United Kingdom)|The Sun]]''. URL last accessed 2007-09-05.&lt;/ref&gt;
{{-}}

==Juley Smith==
{{Infobox soap character 2 | series = EastEnders
|image= 
|name=Juley Smith
|portrayer=[[Joseph Kpobie]]
|years=2002–06
|classification=[[List of past EastEnders characters#Last appeared in 2006|Former; regular]] 
|first= 29 July 2002
|last = 27 July 2006
|occupation=[[Waiter]]
|creator = [[Louise Berridge]]
|mother = Pearl Smith
|brothers=[[Gus Smith]]
|aunts=[[Opal Smith]]
}}
'''Julius &quot;Juley&quot; Smith''', played by [[Joseph Kpobie]], first appeared in July 2002 as [[Gus Smith]]'s brother. He proved to be a problem for Gus, as he got involved in crime, including firearm possession and the theft of charity money, which led to his departure in April 2005. In September 2005 he returned and went to France with Gus, [[Rick 'Minty' Peterson|Minty]], [[Garry Hobbs]] and [[Mickey Miller]]. Mickey and [[Dawn Swann|Dawn]]'s dad, [[Mike Swann]], saw straight through him and exposed him as a con-man. He returned to Walford and promised to change, then had a romance with [[Ruby Allen]].

Their crush started on 21 November 2005; however, they really pushed the limits on 12 December 2005 when they slept together, despite Johnny's watchful eye. Ruby and Juley did not seem to care about Johnny.

Juley had a near-fatal encounter with Johnny on 15 December 2005 when Johnny ambushed him with a pair of kitchen scissors, with the intent to harm him. Juley was only saved when [[Dennis Rickman]] intervened.

It was subsequently revealed that Juley was working for [[Phil Mitchell]], who was paying him to be with Ruby to antagonise Johnny. Ruby later moved in with Juley.

Juley started to fall in love with Ruby and decided to call it off with Phil, who ordered Juley to give back all the money he had been paid. Juley had put some of the money into his brother Gus's fund to see his dog, [[Wellard]], who had been arrested for biting [[Ian Beale]]. Gus caught Juley with the money, and forced Juley into confessing about his working for Phil. In January 2006, Phil wanted Juley to end his relationship with Ruby, saying if Juley didn't end it, Phil would tell Johnny the truth and Johnny would most likely kill Juley. Juley broke up with Ruby in the harshest way he could, despite his true feelings. Johnny was released from hospital and found out about Phil paying Juley. Johnny threatened to kill Juley if he ever went near Ruby again.

When Ruby returned to Walford after her father's arrest, Juley talked to her in the market to see if she was okay, but was badly beaten by [[Jake Moon]], still guilty for killing his brother [[Danny Moon|Danny]], who was over-protective towards Ruby.

Juley left Walford on July 27, 2006 due to his criminal activity. Juley mugged Ruby and hit her, leaving her with a minor injury. He then stole £2000 from her which she was going to use for her holiday with her best friend, [[Stacey Slater]]. Ruby entered Scarlet to put the £2000 in a safe but when she was leaving the office, Juley crept into the nightclub. Ruby was about to leave the club when she heard a noise coming from the office. This was where Juley was, retrieving the £2000. When she walked into the office, she found him and he ran away, pushing her onto the floor. The next day, Juley's brother Gus discovered the £2000 in Juley's bedroom. He alerted Juley that he knew what was going on and then tried to deliver the money through the postbox of Scarlet, but [[Jake Moon]] was watching. He called Gus inside the club to discuss what was going on. Gus lied, but then confessed to Jake that it was Juley who stole the money. Jake then ordered Gus to find Juley and bring him to the club, otherwise he would report Juley to the police. Gus returned to the flat and told Juley what Jake was planning to do to him. Jake closely followed Gus and demanded Juley to open the door. Juley and Gus then hugged and squeezed hands, which was followed by Juley leaving Walford through the back door of their flat.
{{-}}

==Milton Hibbert==
{{Infobox soap character 2 | series = EastEnders
|image=
|name=Milton Hibbert
|portrayer=[[Jeffrey Kissoon]]
|years=2002
|first=9 August 2002
|last=13 August 2002
|sons = [[Paul Trueman]]
|daughters = [[Rebecca Hibbert]]
|granddaughters = [[Eleanor Trueman]]
}}
'''Milton Hibbert''' was an old friend of [[Patrick Trueman]], who had grown up in [[Trinidad]] with him and his late wife [[Audrey Trueman|Audrey]]. Milton had arrived in the square for Patrick's son [[Anthony Trueman|Anthony]]'s wedding to [[Zoe Slater]]. Paul, Anthony's brother had suspicions of Patrick not being their father and Anthony had secretly taken blood from Patrick, who had cut himself and Paul. After the tests had proven, Patrick and Paul not to be father and son, Anthony saw a close resemblance between Milton and Paul. Milton's daughter Rebecca later met with Paul in the [[Queen Vic]] and they began to hit off, before they had the opportunity to sleep together, Anthony stopped them and revealed the truth: Milton was Paul's father. After a heated Argument with Patrick, Milton was promptly thrown out and not seen again.

 
{{-}}

==Rebecca Hibbert==
{{Infobox soap character 2 | series = EastEnders
|image=
|name=Rebecca Hibbert
|portrayer=Paulette Williams
|years=2002
|first=12 August 2002
|last=13 August 2002
|father= [[Milton Hibbert]]
|halfbrothers = [[Paul Trueman]]
|nieces = [[Eleanor Trueman]]
}}
'''Rebecca Hibbert''' is the daughter of Milton Hibbert. She and [[Paul Trueman]] began to hit it off, much to the worry of Paul's brother [[Anthony Trueman|Anthony]], who had discovered that Milton was in fact, Paul's father and revealed it to Paul before he could sleep with Rebecca. Rebecca and Milton quickly left Walford and weren't seen or heard from again.

{{-}}

==Joanne Ryan==
{{Infobox soap character 2 | series = EastEnders
|image=
|name=Joanne Ryan
|portrayer=[[Tara Lynne O'Neill]]
|years=2002–03
|first=20 September 2002
|last=21 August 2003
|occupation=[[Nanny]]
}}
'''Joanne Ryan''' was hired by [[Peggy Mitchell]] as a [[nanny]] to care for baby [[Louise Mitchell]], much to Louise's mother [[Lisa Fowler]]'s dismay. Joanne had a [[limerence|crush]] on Louise's father [[Phil Mitchell]] and was sacked when she tried to seduce him. Joanne had also had a fling with the newly-arrived [[Dennis Rickman]]. After being rejected, Joanne got her revenge on Phil by renting his house to [[Albert Square]]'s new doctor, [[List of EastEnders characters (2003)#Johnathon Leroy|Johnathon Leroy]] and his wife. After this she left [[Walford]] and has not been seen since.
{{-}}

== Clive Mitchell ==
{{Infobox soap character 2 | series = EastEnders
|image=
|name=Clive Mitchell
|portrayer=[[Tony Selby]]
|years=2002
|family=[[Mitchell family|Mitchell]]
|appeared=3 October 2002
|classification=[[List of past EastEnders characters#Last appeared in 2002|Former; guest]]
|born=
|home=[[London]] (outside Walford) 
|father=Philip Mitchell
|mother=Sandra Mitchell
|wife=Elaine Mitchell
|sons=
|brothers=Eric Mitchell&lt;br /&gt;[[Archie Mitchell]]
|nephews=[[Phil Mitchell]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Grant Mitchell (EastEnders)|Grant Mitchell]]
|nieces=[[Sam Mitchell (EastEnders)|Sam Mitchell]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Ronnie Mitchell]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Roxy Mitchell]]
}}
'''Clive Mitchell''' is the uncle of [[Phil Mitchell|Phil]], [[Grant Mitchell (EastEnders)|Grant]], [[Sam Mitchell (EastEnders)|Sam]], [[Ronnie Mitchell|Ronnie]], [[Roxy Mitchell|Roxy]] and brother of Eric and [[Archie Mitchell]]. He appears in October 2002 along with his wife, Elaine, at his great niece's [[Louise Mitchell|Louise]]'s &quot;naming party&quot;, where her name is changed from [[Beale family|Fowler]] to Mitchell. 
{{-}}

== Dave Roberts ==
{{Infobox soap character 2 | series = EastEnders
|image=
|name=Dave Roberts
|portrayer=[[David Kennedy (actor)|David Kennedy]]
|years=2002
|first=25 October 2002
|last=7 November 2002
|occupation=Barman
}}
When [[Peggy Mitchell]] needed a bar manager for her pub, [[The Queen Victoria|The Queen Vic]], she only had one candidate left to interview; a man named '''Dave Roberts'''. He won Peggy over by claiming to know her son, [[Grant Mitchell (EastEnders)|Grant]],&lt;ref&gt;&quot;[http://walford.net/update/20021025.htm FRI 25-OCT-02]&quot;, ''walford.net''. URL last accessed 2007-06-05.&lt;/ref&gt; and started the job on 28 October,&lt;ref&gt;&quot;[http://walford.net/update/20021028.htm MON 28-OCT-02]&quot;, ''walford.net''. URL last accessed 2007-06-05.&lt;/ref&gt; inviting his dodgy friends to the pub, worrying Peggy about the type of customers he may attract.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;[http://walford.net/update/20021029.htm TUE 29-OCT-02]&quot;, ''walford.net''. URL last accessed 2007-06-05.&lt;/ref&gt;

He made it up to her by offering to check the [[fire alarm]]s in The Vic, but annoyed her further by going through a drawer full of her personal documents and asking her about her daughter [[Sam Mitchell (EastEnders)|Sam]]'s love life.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;[http://www.bbc.co.uk/eastenders/episodes/past/episode20021104.shtml#2 Little Mo tries to accept Trevor is really dead, page 2]&quot;, ''bbc.co.uk''. URL last accessed 2007-06-06.&lt;/ref&gt; He went on to question Sam about her relationships with [[Trevor Morgan (EastEnders)|Trevor Morgan]] and [[Ricky Butcher]].&lt;ref name=&quot;nov5&quot;&gt;&quot;[http://walford.net/update/20021105.htm TUE 05-NOV-02]&quot;, ''walford.net''. URL last accessed 2007-06-05.&lt;/ref&gt;

He later berated Sam for cancelling the pub's [[bonfire]] party in the aftermath of the deaths of [[Tom Banks (EastEnders)|Tom Banks]] and Trevor Morgan, but praised Peggy for the cancellation.&lt;ref name=&quot;nov5&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;&quot;[http://www.bbc.co.uk/eastenders/episodes/past/episode20021105.shtml Little Mo blames herself for Tom's death]&quot;, ''bbc.co.uk''. URL last accessed 2007-06-06.&lt;/ref&gt; Sam became suspicious of Dave when he allowed one of his friends to smoke [[cannabis]] in the pub.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;[http://www.bbc.co.uk/eastenders/episodes/past/episode20021105.shtml#2 Little Mo blames herself for Tom's death, page 2]&quot;, ''bbc.co.uk''. URL last accessed 2007-06-06.&lt;/ref&gt;

After one of Dave's friends barged into [[Patrick Trueman]] in the pub, Peggy threatened to bar anyone who upset her regular customers.Later that night, Sam caught Dave scheming with his friends to have a lock-in after hours.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;[http://www.bbc.co.uk/eastenders/episodes/past/episode20021105.shtml#3 Little Mo blames herself for Tom's death, page 3]&quot;, ''bbc.co.uk''. URL last accessed 2007-06-06.&lt;/ref&gt; She threatened to call the [[police]] when they didn't leave, but Dave grabbed her and started to pull her shirt off. Sam kneed him in the [[groin]] and ran away.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;[http://www.bbc.co.uk/eastenders/episodes/past/episode20021105.shtml#4 Little Mo blames herself for Tom's death, page 4]&quot;, ''bbc.co.uk''. URL last accessed 2007-06-06.&lt;/ref&gt; The next morning, the pub and the living quarters above were trashed. Peggy was angry, but couldn't get rid of Dave until his contract ended. Sam urged her to sack him sooner. Later in the bar, Dave started getting close to Sam, at which point she told Peggy what had happened the night before. Peggy told her daughter that Dave wouldn't get away with it.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;[http://www.bbc.co.uk/eastenders/episodes/past/episode20021107.shtml Little Mo organises Trevor's funeral]&quot;, ''bbc.co.uk''. URL last accessed 2007-06-06.&lt;/ref&gt;

After Dave's friends caused more havoc in the pub, this time upsetting [[Roy Evans (EastEnders)|Roy Evans]], Dave claimed that [[Walford]] was &quot;soft&quot; without [[Phil Mitchell|Phil]] and Grant Mitchell around, which enraged Peggy further.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;[http://www.bbc.co.uk/eastenders/episodes/past/episode20021107.shtml#3 Little Mo organises Trevor's funeral, page 3]&quot;, ''bbc.co.uk''. URL last accessed 2007-06-06.&lt;/ref&gt; Peggy confronted Dave and told him that she would be terminating his contract with immediate effect. When Dave refused to leave, Peggy tried to round up some of Phil and Grant's associates, but to no avail.&lt;ref name=&quot;davegone&quot;&gt;&quot;[http://www.bbc.co.uk/eastenders/episodes/past/episode20021107.shtml#4 Little Mo organises Trevor's funeral, page 4]&quot;, ''bbc.co.uk''. URL last accessed 2007-06-06.&lt;/ref&gt;

When Dave's friends trashed the floral tributes to Tom, Roy stepped in and tried to stop them, after [[Sharon Rickman|Sharon]] became distraught at the sight. The rest of Walford's male residents united to drive the thugs out of town, and they were closely followed by Dave, who had tried to steal some money from The Vic's till, but was stopped by Sam wielding a [[baseball bat]].&lt;ref name=&quot;davegone&quot;/&gt;
{{-}}

==Alfie Moon==
{{Main|Alfie Moon}}

==Doris Moisey==
{{Infobox soap character 2 | series = EastEnders
|image=
|name=Doris Moisey
|portrayer= [[Marcia Ashton]]
|years=2002–03
|first=28 November 2002
|last=28 February 2003
|occupation= Retired
}}
'''Doris Moisey''' was a [[pensioner]] [[spinster]] who met [[Jim Branning]] at the [[gym]] in [[Walford]] and set her sights on him.

Doris pestered Jim and even started going to his house to see him while his wife [[Dot Branning|Dot]] was away. She sent Jim a [[Valentine's day]] card, and intercepted Dot's card in the mail, making Jim think that Dot had forgotten their anniversary.

When Jim hurt his back, Doris gave him a [[massage]] on his bed, only to be interrupted by Dot returning home. After Dot refused to sleep in the same room as Jim, he went for a drink with Doris and was torn between the two women.

[[Patrick Trueman]] persuaded Jim to make a list of pros and cons about both women. Dot found the list and left Jim, leaving Doris to think she'd won. Dot later moved back in with Jim and Doris left [[Albert Square]]. She has not been seen since.
{{-}}

==Spencer Moon==
{{Main|Spencer Moon}}

==Nana Moon==
{{Main|Nana Moon}}

==Chris Wright==
{{Infobox soap character 2 | series = EastEnders
|image=
|name=Chris Wright
|portrayer=[[Tom Roberts (actor)|Tom Roberts]]
|years=2002
|appeared=13 December 2002
}}
'''Chris Wright''', played by [[Tom Roberts (actor)|Tom Roberts]], is the original applicant for job of bar manager of [[The Queen Victoria]] public house who is usurped by [[Alfie Moon]], who used his name and identity three weeks earlier, and tells Chris by telephone that the position has been filled. Chris arrives on 13 December 2002 to talk to the landlady, [[Peggy Mitchell]]. Alfie, fearing his facade will be unravelled, thinks of a scheme to get rid of Chris and tells them his grandmother, [[Victoria Moon]] is Peggy. When Chris confronts Victoria about Alfie having his job and insults Alfie, she tells him to leave and threatens to set the dog on him.
{{-}}

==Kate Mitchell==
{{Main|Kate Mitchell}}

==Dougie Slade==
{{Infobox soap character 2 | series = EastEnders
|image=
|name=Dougie Slade
|portrayer=[[John Bowler (actor)|John Bowler]]
|years=2002–03
|first=31 December 2002
|last=24 January 2003
|occupation= Retired [[Police officer|Detective Sergeant]]
}}
'''Detective Sergeant Dougie Slade''' was a bent ex-police officer who was involved in the case which led to [[Alfie Moon]] being imprisoned for [[credit card fraud]].

When [[The Queen Vic]] won the &quot;East End Pub of the Year Award&quot;, Alfie was photographed and appeared in the paper. Alfie was still using the false identity of [[Chris Wright (EastEnders)|Chris Wright]], which he had used to get his job there. When Dougie saw the picture in the paper, he visited Alfie and threatened to expose his true identity unless he stole £4,000 from the till at The Vic.

Dougie's plan was eventually scuppered when Alfie ran away and [[Peggy Mitchell]], the owner of the pub, caught Dougie helping himself to money from the till. Alfie was exposed afterwards, but still kept his job at the pub, due to his [[superficial charm|charm]] and [[charisma]].
{{-}}

== References ==
{{Reflist}}

==External links==
*{{EEcharlink|precious|Precious Hudson}}
*{{EEcharlink|joanne_r|Joanne Ryan}}

{{EastEnders}}
{{EastEnders characters|year}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:List Of Eastenders Characters (2002)}}
[[Category:Lists of EastEnders characters|2002]]
[[Category:Fictional characters introduced in 2002|*, EastEnders]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
