<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="12810946" ns="0" title="List of EastEnders characters (1999)"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{DISPLAYTITLE:List of ''EastEnders'' characters (1999)}}
The following is a list of characters that first appeared in the [[BBC]] [[soap opera]] ''[[EastEnders]]'' in 1999, by order of first appearance.

{{TOClimit|limit=2}}

==Nina Harris==
{{Main|Nina Harris}}
'''Nina Harris''', played by [[Troy Titus-Adams]], appeared between 1999 and 2000. The character was axed by [[John Yorke (television producer)|John Yorke]], making her final appearance in June 2000. Titus-Adams was critical about the lack of material given to her, accusing the BBC of [[tokenism]]. Nina arrives in [[Walford]] looking for a fresh start away from her past as a prostitute. Nina helped imprison her violent pimp Vinny, a former boyfriend who had got her addicted to drugs and then persuaded her to turn to prostitution so she could feed their habit.&lt;ref name=&quot;who&quot;&gt;{{cite book |last=Lock |first= Kate|title=[[EastEnders books|EastEnders Who's Who]] |year=2000|publisher=BBC Books|isbn=0-563-55178-X}}&lt;/ref&gt; She stays with her aunt [[Irene Raymond]] ([[Roberta Taylor]]) and settles in by becoming a barmaid in [[The Queen Victoria]] public house.

==Claudia Fielding==
{{Infobox soap character 2 | series = EastEnders
|image=
|name=Claudia Fielding
|portrayer=[[Romla Walker]]
|years=1999
|first=23 February 1999
|last=5 October 1999
|home=[[USA]]
|sisters=[[Saskia Duncan]]
}}
'''Claudia Fielding''' (née '''Duncan''') was the sister of [[Saskia Duncan]], who arrived in [[Walford]] after her sister's death on 14 February 1999. She went to Walford as it was the last place Saskia was seen, and her disappearance was being investigated by the police. She was suspicious of [[Steve Owen (EastEnders)|Steve Owen]], her sister's former fiancé and killer, but then became dependent on him, alternating between the two and irritating Steve. [[Matthew Rose (EastEnders)|Matthew Rose]], who witnessed Saskia's death, worried that Claudia would discover that her sister was dead. She eventually returned home after Saskia's body was found buried in [[Epping Forest]].

Claudia testified at Steve's trial and was devastated when he was cleared of Saskia's murder.
{{-}}

==Dan Sullivan==
{{Main|Dan Sullivan (EastEnders)}}
'''Dan Sullivan''', played by [[Craig Fairbrass]], arrives in [[Albert Square]] as [[Carol Jackson]]'s ([[Lindsey Coulson]]) latest boyfriend in 1999 and they plan to marry on discovering she is expecting his child. Carol's daughter [[Bianca Butcher]] ([[Patsy Palmer]]) is stunned to see him, as they had a fling when she was a teenager on holiday, many years before. Dan and Bianca begin an affair, which is discovered, leading Carol to have an abortion and leave Walford. Bianca also leaves Walford.

==Susie Price==
{{Infobox soap character 2 | series = EastEnders
|image=
|name=Susie Price
|portrayer=[[Viva Duce]]
|years=1999
|first=17 August 1999
|last=31 December 1999
|occupation= [[Hairdresser]]
|father=Dave Price
|mother=[[Andrea Price]]
|sisters=[[Natalie Evans]]
|brothers=[[Jack Price (EastEnders)|Jack Price]]&lt;br /&gt;Kevin Price
|husband=Darren
|sons=Chris
|nephews=[[Jack Evans (EastEnders)|Jack Evans]]
}}
'''Susie Price''' was the older sister of [[Natalie Evans|Natalie Price]] and she was first seen in ''EastEnders'' in August 1999, when Natalie, who had been estranged from her family for some time, returned to her family home to introduce her new fiancé, [[Barry Evans (EastEnders)|Barry Evans]]. 

Natalie and Susie did not get along. Their mother, [[Andrea Price|Andrea]], had always favoured Susie, and the two of them liked nothing better than to pick holes in Natalie. Susie was angry with Natalie because she had been absent for several years and she constantly jibed Natalie about her appearance and how unattractive Barry was. Susie's last appearance was in December 1999, when she attended Natalie and Barry's wedding. 
{{-}}

==Jackie Owen==
{{Infobox soap character 2 | series = EastEnders
|image= 
|name=Jackie Owen
|portrayer=[[Race Davies]]
|introducer=[[Matthew Robinson (producer)|Matthew Robinson]]
|years=1999–2000
|first=10 September 1999
|last=1 June 2000
|born=15 August 1963
|occupation= Waitress
|husband=Doug Bayliss
|mother=[[Barbara Owen]]
|brothers=[[Steve Owen (EastEnders)|Steve Owen]]
}}
'''Jacqueline &quot;Jackie&quot; Owen''' (previously '''Bayliss''') is the sister of [[Steve Owen (EastEnders)|Steve Owen]], played by [[Race Davies]] from 1999 to 2000. Davies quit the role in 2000 after only four months on the soap. She commented, &quot;I've really enjoyed myself working on ''EastEnders'' but I feel that I've done as much as I can on the show and I'm looking forward to new challenges.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|work=The Mirror |date= 4 February 2000|url= http://www.thefreelibrary.com/Matthew+Wright's+column%3a+NOW+RACE+RUNS.-a060278259/|title=NOW RACE RUNS|accessdate= 2 April 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;
 
When Jackie arrived in Walford she was a woman with a mission, and that was to keep her brother out of jail. She had a fiery temper caused by severe [[PMS]] and her violent outbursts were too much for her boyfriend to handle.

Jackie arrived in [[Walford]] in September 1999, looking for her brother, [[Steve Owen (EastEnders)|Steve]], after hearing that he was to stand trial for murdering [[Saskia Duncan]]. Jackie's husband, Doug (a hotelier and club owner), was sent to prison for manslaughter after accidentally killing a violent punter. Whilst there, he committed suicide, so she was determined her brother would not share the same fate. 

Jackie believed her brother was innocent, but aware of the hostility towards him in the Square, and initially refrained from revealing her connection to him. She took a job as a waitress at Giuseppe's Italian restaurant, owned by the di Marco family. In between shifts, Jackie started questioning the residents of Walford about Steve, hoping to find something that would exonerate him. When [[Gianni di Marco]] discovered a prison visiting order in Jackie's belongings, he revealed her true identity, infuriating the locals. During Steve's trial, Jackie realised that Steve was lying about murdering Saskia. She was furious but still gave tearful and moving testimony that undoubtedly swayed the jury in Steve's favour and probably bought his freedom. Steve was found not guilty, whilst [[Matthew Rose (EastEnders)|Matthew Rose]], who Steve had framed, was found guilty of manslaughter and was sent to prison for a crime he didn't commit.

Jackie and Steve were the targets of regular animosity on the Square, regarding Steve's actions. [[Martin Fowler (EastEnders)|Martin Fowler]] in particular, had it in for Jackie, and after goading her in the restaurant one day, Jackie finally lost it and fiercely ordered him to leave. Martin proceeded to steal a customer's money from a nearby table and then did a runner. Jackie and Gianni followed him into a half-demolished building and as Martin looked back from outside, he heard Jackie shriek as a huge piece of piping fell towards her. Jackie was trapped but awake and Gianni lay half-conscious beside her.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|work=Daily Record|date= 23 October 1999|url= http://www.thefreelibrary.com/Soap+watch%3b+More+disasters+on+EastEnders'+horizon.-a060362961/|title=More disasters on EastEnders' horizon.|accessdate= 2 April 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; Whilst they waited to be rescued, they began sharing life stories and began to bond. The firemen had difficulty moving the debris as any wrong move would have brought the whole roof down. Amidst all the chaos, Jackie and Gianni managed to kill time by flirting and just as the two leant in to kiss, the roof collapsed! Steve rushed into the building to save them and neither was badly injured. 

Over the following months, Jackie got involved with the free Matthew Rose campaign, possibly to relieve her guilt for her part in his imprisonment. She and Gianni began a relationship and it seemed as if the womanising Italian was really falling for Jackie. However, Jackie wasn't the easiest woman to please. She had a quick temper and a jealous streak and as time went by, these tendencies became more and more apparent. 

Jackie began taking everything Gianni said the wrong way, resulting in screaming matches for seemingly no reason. After Jackie managed to scald Gianni by tipping hot [[coffee]] over him in a fit of rage, she finally explained she suffered with severe [[Premenstrual stress syndrome|Premenstrual Tension]] (PMS) for a week every month which made her enraged and violent. Gianni was uncharacteristically sympathetic and he tried making allowances for Jackie's behaviour. Later, after injuring Gianni by punching him in the face and smashing up the restaurant, Jackie sought medical help. She was given medication and hoped that this would solve her problem but it didn't. After hitting Gianni with a saucepan one night, Jackie decided to end the relationship as she couldn't stand the thought of harming him. Gianni was stunned, as by then he had fallen deeply in love with her. Gianni made one last attempt to save their relationship, but when his mother, [[Rosa di Marco|Rosa]], discovered the abuse Jackie had put him through, she forbade Jackie from having anything more to do with him.

Jackie left Walford after learning of her brother's drug habit in June 2000. Steve returned from rehab alone. When their mother, [[Barbara Owen|Barbara]], fell ill a year later, she relayed that Jackie refused to help her and it was subsequently revealed that they hated each other. Jackie refused to attend her funeral in 2001 and didn't attend Steve's funeral in 2002 either. 

In April 2002, Steve's widow, [[Melanie Owen|Melanie]], discovered she and Jackie were being investigated by the police for money laundering and drug trafficking. Steve was actually guilty of these crimes but had set them up as company directors of his illegitimate businesses, and following his death, they were held accountable.
{{-}}

== Troy Harvey==
{{Infobox soap character 2 | series = EastEnders
|image=
|name=Troy Harvey
|portrayer=[[Jamie Jarvis]]
|years=1999
|first=20 September 1999
|last=25 December 1999
|brothers = Wilf Harvey
}}
'''Troy Harvey''' was a friend of [[Tony Hills]], who had attended school with his older brother. Troy arrived in Albert Square looking for Tony, but had missed him as he had gone to Amsterdam with his boyfriend and stepbrother, [[Simon Raymond]].

Troy began staying with Tony's mother [[Irene Raymond]] and her husband [[Terry Raymond|Terry]] at 87 George Street and began helping out in their shop. 

It became apparent that Troy was attracted to Irene and began flirting with her. Soon the two of them began an illicit affair, behind Terry's back. 

The affair ended on [[Christmas Day]] 1999 when Terry discovered an engraved watch given to Troy by Irene and began to realise his wife was cheating on him.

After punching Troy, Terry offered Irene to him, stating that he loved her enough to give her up if that was what she wanted. Seeing that Troy was unwilling to accept Irene, Terry threw him out of the house and threatened to kill him if he ever attempted to contact Irene or showed his face again.
{{-}}

==Asif Malik==
{{Infobox soap character 2 | series = EastEnders
|image=&lt;!--[[Image:Asif Malik EE.jpg|200px]]--&gt;
|name=Asif Malik
|portrayer=Ashvin Luximon
|years=1999–2003
|first=21 September 1999
|last=10 October 2003
|born=19 September 1984
|home=[[Edinburgh]]
|occupation=Student
|family=
}}
'''Asif Malik''' is a [[fictional character]] from the [[BBC]] [[soap opera]] ''[[EastEnders]]'', played by Ashvin Luximon from 1999 to 2003. 

Asif was a school friend of [[Martin Fowler (EastEnders)|Martin Fowler]] and together they would get into lots of trouble such as [[shoplifting]] and [[vandalism]], but almost always when Martin would be caught, Asif would leave him behind to explain himself to his mother [[Pauline Fowler|Pauline]]. His own family was never seen on-screen but were mentioned occasionally.

He rarely had storylines which centered only on him and all his storylines were linked with Martin or with his fellow schoolmates [[Nicky di Marco]] and [[Janine Butcher]]. He went on a few dates with Nicky but it didn't turn into anything serious. He also had a crush on Janine which was not reciprocated.

He was last seen in October 2003 when he passed his [[Advanced Level (UK)|A-levels]] and went to [[University]]. He has not appeared since. It was revealed in 2004 that Asif was living in Edinburgh and had got married; he invited Martin to his stag party off-screen.
{{-}}

== Enrico di Clemente ==
{{Infobox soap character 2 | series = EastEnders
|name=Enrico di Clemente
|portrayer=[[Francois Pandolfo]]
|years=1999
|first=30 September 1999
|last=28 October 1999
|occupation=Student
|home=[[Italy]]
}}
'''Enrico di Clemente''' was an Italian [[foreign exchange student]], who stayed with the Fowler family in 1999. He made a big impression on [[Sonia Jackson]], particularly when she discovered that he was a fellow trumpet player with a penchant for jazz music. However, he also received a lot of unwanted attention from Sonia's friend, [[Nicky di Marco]], which caused several arguments. 

Sonia was sure that Enrico preferred Nicky and so she shunned him when he asked her on a date. Nicky eventually grew tired of Enrico constantly talking about Sonia, so she told him to tell her how he felt. He did, and Sonia was overjoyed. However their romance was short-lived, as Enrico went home to Italy the following day, but not before he'd taken her for a romantic meal and a dance at Giuseppe's Italian restaurant. They shared a kiss, and Sonia confessed that it had been her first.
{{-}}

==Others==   
{| class=&quot;wikitable plainrowheaders&quot; style=&quot;font-size:90%&quot;
! scope=&quot;col&quot; | Character 
! scope=&quot;col&quot; | Date(s) 
! scope=&quot;col&quot; | Actor 
! scope=&quot;col&quot; | Circumstances
|-
! scope=&quot;row&quot; | {{nowrap|Jack Price}}
| {{nowrap|17-19 August}}
| {{nowrap|[[Dax O'Callaghan]]&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite episode |title= Episode dated 03/01/2011 |url=http://www.bbc.co.uk/programmes/b00x9yf0 |series= EastEnders |serieslink=EastEnders |credits= Director: Mickey Jones; Executive Producer: Bryan Kirkwood; Writer: Pete Lawson |network=[[BBC]] |station=[[BBC One]] |city= |airdate=3 January 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;}} 
| {{Anchor|Jack Price}} the young brother of [[Natalie Evans|Natalie Price]]. Jack appears when Natalie took her new fiancé, [[Barry Evans (EastEnders)|Barry]], to visit their mother, [[Andrea Price]]. Jack is a talented [[Football (soccer)|footballer]] and has just been offered a [[scholarship]] with [[Liverpool F.C.]], a fact that Barry is unaware of. Jack manages to use this to his advantage when he cons Barry into betting him a pound for every minute he manages to [[Keepie uppie|keep a football in the air]]. Over half an hour later, Jack has still not dropped the ball and Barry is forced to pay a sizeable sum. 
|-
! scope=&quot;row&quot; | {{nowrap|Jane Healy}}
| {{nowrap|31 December}}
| {{nowrap|[[Shirley Stelfox]]&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite episode |title= Episode dated 03/01/2011 |url=http://www.bbc.co.uk/programmes/b00x9yf0 |series= EastEnders |serieslink=EastEnders |credits= Director: Mickey Jones; Executive Producer: Bryan Kirkwood; Writer: Pete Lawson |network=[[BBC]] |station=[[BBC One]] |city= |airdate=3 January 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;}} 
| {{Anchor|Jane Healy}} [[Melanie Owen]]'s mother who attends her wedding to [[Ian Beale]] on New Year's Eve. Jane spends much of the day bickering with her ex-husband [[Jeff Healy (EastEnders)|Jeff Healy]].
|}

==References==
{{Reflist}}

{{EastEnders}}
{{EastEnders characters|year}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:List Of Eastenders Characters (1999)}}
[[Category:Lists of EastEnders characters|1999]]
[[Category:Fictional characters introduced in 1999|*, EastEnders]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
