<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="1291396" ns="0" title="License-free software"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Primary sources|date=June 2008}}

'''License-free software''' is [[computer software]] that is not explicitly in the [[public domain]], but the copyright owner has not made explicit the terms of the [[software license|license]].

== Examples ==

Well known examples of license-free software formerly included programs written by [[Daniel J. Bernstein]], specifically [[qmail]], [[djbdns]], [[daemontools]], and [[ucspi-tcp]].  Bernstein previously held the copyright and distributed these works, but he placed them in the [[public domain]] on December 28, 2007.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
 |year=[[2007]]
 |url=http://cr.yp.to/distributors.html
 |title=Frequently asked questions from distributors
 |accessdate=2008-01-18
}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
 |year=[[2007]]
 |url=http://cr.yp.to/qmail/dist.html
 |title=Information for distributors
 |accessdate=2008-01-18
}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Additionally, small [[Scripting language|script]]s are frequently released without specifying a license.  For example, the website [http://userscripts.org/ Userscripts.org] hosts more than 52,000 [[Greasemonkey]] user scripts,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
 |url=http://userscripts.org/scripts
 |title=Scripts &amp;mdash; Userscripts.org
 |accessdate=2010-06-29
}}&lt;/ref&gt; the majority of which have no specified license.{{Citation needed|date=July 2010}}

== Rights for users ==

On his [http://cr.yp.to/softwarelaw.html Software users' rights] web page, Bernstein explains his belief that under the terms of copyright law itself software users are always allowed to modify software for their own personal use, regardless of [[Software license agreement|license agreements]].  He says &quot;If you think you need a license from the copyright holder, you've been bamboozled by Microsoft. As long as you're not distributing the software, you have nothing to worry about.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;[http://cr.yp.to/softwarelaw.html Software users' rights]&lt;/ref&gt;

He also says that software users are allowed to back up, to compile, and to run the software that they possess.

He further says that &quot;since it's not [[copyright infringement]] for you to apply a [[patch (computing)|patch]], it's also not copyright infringement for someone to give you a patch,&quot; noting the case of ''[[Galoob v. Nintendo]]'' as precedent.  Thus modified versions of license-free software can legally be distributed in [[source code]] form in whatever way that the original can, by distributing a [[patch (computing)|patch]] alongside it.

Although they come without a license document, it can be argued{{Weasel-inline|date=February 2009}} that such programs are legally bound by a license. For example, on his various web pages giving [http://cr.yp.to/distributors.html information for distributors], Bernstein granted permission for users to redistribute the packages, in [[source code]] form, verbatim.  This permission granted by the copyright holder can be construed as a [[license|copyright license]]{{Citation needed|date=March 2008}}.  However, there is significant and long standing dispute in the community as to its validity and weight{{Citation needed|date=March 2008}}, given the transient and wholly electronic nature of the license [[document]].

These concerns have been expressed{{Citation needed|date=March 2008}} for the same reasons about the non-paper licenses of [[Shrink wrap contract|shrink wrapped software]].  Given Bernstein's own opposition to [[software license]]s, arguments for the validity of Bernstein's web pages as licenses may also strengthen the case for the validity of &quot;click wrap&quot; [[software license agreement|end-user license agreements]], although this seems unlikely because the latter are contracts, whereas pure copyright licenses need never be seen by a user to be in force.{{Citation needed|date=July 2008}}  This contract variance makes sense: a difference remains in that Bernstein's license is purely permissive whereas most &quot;click wrap&quot; licenses forbid certain actions of the user.{{Citation needed|date=January 2008}}

== Difficulties ==

Advocates of license-free software, such as Bernstein, argue that [[software license]]s are harmful because they restrict the freedom to use software, and copyright law provides enough freedom without the need for licenses.  However, [[Free software licence|free]] and [[Open-source license|open source]] licenses do not restrict the freedoms that license-free advocates want to protect.{{Dubious|date=March 2008}} Though having some restrictions, these licenses allow certain actions that are disallowed by copyright laws in some jurisdictions. If a license tries to restrict an action allowed by a copyright system, by Bernstein's argument those restrictions can be ignored.  In fact, Bernstein's &quot;non-license&quot; of verbatim retransmission of source code is very similar in nature.

The disagreement hampers the spread of license-free software, largely because the free software and open source philosophies are far stronger influences.{{Citation needed|date=March 2008}} For example, some [[Linux distribution]]s used to classify qmail as &quot;non-free&quot; because when distributors modified it, the modified version could not be distributed.

==References==
{{Reflist}}

== External links ==
* [http://www4.law.cornell.edu/uscode/17/117.html 17 USC 117]
* [http://web.archive.org/web/20080206094355/http://www.fsf.org/licensing/licenses/index_html (archive.org's snapshot copy of) The FSF's (erstwhile) categorisation of the qmail licence as &quot;non-free&quot;]
* [http://qmail.org/not-open-source.html &quot;qmail is not open source&quot;] - an article published by Russell Nelson, OSI board member (Note: now changed to &quot;qmail is now open source&quot; - an important difference!)

=== UK Legislation ===
*{{UK-LEG ext|path=ukpga/1988/48|title=Copyright Designs and Patents Act 1988|type=ukpga}}
*{{UK-LEG ext|path=2003/2498|title=Copyright and Related Rights Regulations 2003|type=uksi}}
[[Category:Software licenses]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
