<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="13104" ns="0" title="Grinnell College"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Infobox University
| name = Grinnell College
| image = [[Image:Grinnell College Logo New.jpg|125px]]
| motto = ''Veritas et Humanitas'' ([[Latin]])
| mottoeng =Truth and Humanity
| established = 1846
| type = [[Private university|Private]]
| affiliations = [[Midwest Conference]]
| president = [[Raynard S. Kington]]
| city = [[Grinnell, Iowa|Grinnell]]
|state = [[Iowa]]
|country = [[United States|USA]]
|students = 1688&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.princetonreview.com/college/research/profiles/studentbody.asp?listing=1023453&amp;ltid=1&amp;intbucketid= &quot;Grinnell College: Student Body], ''The Princeton Review''. Retrieved April 30, 2008.&lt;/ref&gt;
| faculty = 156 full-time,
43 part-time
| endowment = $1.26 billion (January 27, 2011)&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news
 | last = Brainard
 | first = Jeffrey
 | date= 27 January 2011
 | title =  Endowments Regain Ground With 12% Returns
 | periodical=Chronicle of Higher Education
 | postscript = &lt;!--None--&gt;
 | url = http://chronicle.com/article/Colleges-Endowments-Earned-12/126071/
}}&lt;/ref&gt;
| campus = [[Rural]], 120 acres (48.6 ha)
| nickname = Pioneers
| colors = [[Scarlet (color)|Scarlet]] and Black {{colorbox|#FF2400}} {{colorbox|black}}|
 website = [http://www.grinnell.edu/ grinnell.edu]
}}
&lt;!-- Please do not add &quot;highly-selective&quot; to the lead without reaching consensus on the talk page first. --&gt;
'''Grinnell College''' is a private [[Liberal arts colleges in the United States|liberal arts college]] in [[Grinnell, Iowa|Grinnell]], [[Iowa]], [[U.S.]] known for its strong tradition of [[social activism]].&lt;ref name=&quot;pc&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref name = &quot;tljzhk&quot;&gt;[http://www.princetonreview.com/college/research/profiles/academics.asp?listing=1023453&amp;ltid=1&amp;intbucketid= &quot;Grinnell College: Academics&quot;], ''The Princeton Review'.' Retrieved April 30, 2008.&lt;/ref&gt; It was founded in 1846, when a group of pioneer New England [[Congregational church|Congregationalists]] established the Trustees of Iowa College.

In its 2011 edition of America's Best Colleges, Grinnell was ranked 18th among all liberal arts colleges in the United States by ''[[U.S. News &amp; World Report]]'', tied with [[Hamilton College (New York)|Hamilton College]] and [[Harvey Mudd College]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://colleges.usnews.rankingsandreviews.com/best-colleges/liberal-arts-rankings|title=Liberal Arts Rankings |publisher=Colleges.usnews.rankingsandreviews.com |date=2009-08-19 |accessdate=2011-01-31}}&lt;/ref&gt; In 2004, it received the &quot;Best All-Around&quot; college rating from ''Newsweek''.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news
|first= Mary
|last= Carmichael
|coauthors=Karen Springen
|title= The Hot Schools Of 2004
|url= http://www.newsweek.com/id/59925
|work= Newsweek Magazine
|publisher= Newsweek, Inc.
|date= 1 September 2003
|accessdate=23 November 2008 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

==History==
{{See also|List of presidents of Grinnell College}}
[[Image:Josiah Bushnell Grinnell - Brady-Handy.jpg|thumb|right|upright|[[Josiah Bushnell Grinnell]]: founder of Grinnell Iowa and benefactor of Grinnell College.]]
[[File:Blair-hall-grinnell-college.jpg|thumb|right|[[Blair Hall]]: Constructed between 1882-1886 and razed in 1961.]]
In 1843, eleven Congregational ministers, all of whom trained at [[Andover Theological Seminary]] in [[Massachusetts]], set out to proselytize on the frontier. Each man pledged to gather a church and together the group or band would seek to establish a college. When the group arrived in Iowa later that year, each selected a different town in which to establish a congregation. In 1846, they collectively established Iowa College in [[Davenport, Iowa|Davenport]]. A few months later, Iowa joined the Union.

The first 25 years of Grinnell's history saw a change in name and location. Iowa College moved farther west from Davenport, Iowa, to the town of Grinnell and unofficially adopted the name of its benefactor: an [[abolitionism|abolitionist]] minister, [[Josiah Bushnell Grinnell]], to whom journalist [[Horace Greeley]] famously wrote &quot;[[Go West, young man]], go West, and grow up with the country!&quot; The name of the corporation &quot;The Trustees of Iowa College&quot; remained, but in 1909 the name &quot;Grinnell College&quot; was adopted by the trustees for the institution.

In its early years, the College experienced setbacks. Although two students received bachelor of arts degrees in 1854 (the first to be granted by a college west of the [[Mississippi River]]), within 10 years the [[American Civil War|Civil War]] had claimed most of Grinnell's students and professors. In the decade following the war, growth resumed: women were officially admitted as candidates for degrees, and the curriculum was enlarged to include then-new areas of academic studies, such as [[natural sciences]] with laboratory work.

In 1882, Grinnell College was struck by a tornado — then called a cyclone, after which the college yearbook was named. The storm devastated the campus and destroyed both College buildings. Rebuilding began immediately, and the determination to expand wasn't limited to architecture: the curriculum was again extended to include departments in [[political science]] (the first in the United States) and modern languages.

Grinnell became known as the center of the [[Social Gospel]] reform movement,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal
 | last = Morgan
 | first = J.
 | year= 1969
 | title = The Development of Sociology and the Social Gospel in America
 | periodical=Sociological Analysis
 | volume=30
 | issue=1
 | pages=42–53| doi = 10.2307/3709933
 | jstor = 3709933
 | publisher = Oxford University Press
 | postscript = &lt;!--None--&gt;
}}. see footnote 4.&lt;/ref&gt; as Robert Handy writes, &quot;The movement centered on the campus of Iowa (now Grinnell) College. Its leading figures were [[George D. Herron|Professor George D. Herron]] and President George A. Gates&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal
 | last = Handy
 | first = Robert
 | year= 1950
 | title = George D. Herron and the Kingdom Movement
 | periodical=Church History
 | volume=19
 | issue=2
 | pages=97–115| doi = 10.2307/3162192
 | jstor = 3162192
 | publisher = American Society of Church History
 | postscript = &lt;!--None--&gt;
}}&lt;/ref&gt; Other firsts pointed to the lighter side of college life: the first intercollegiate [[American football|football]] and [[baseball]] games west of the Mississippi were played in Grinnell, and the home teams won.

As the 20th century began, Grinnell established a [[Phi Beta Kappa]] chapter, introduced the departmental &quot;major&quot; system of study, began Grinnell-in-China (an educational mission that lasted until the [[Second Sino-Japanese War|Japanese invasion]] and resumed in 1987), and built a women's residence hall system that became a national model.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news
 | last = McHale
 | first = Cathryn
 | year= 1935
 | title =  Education for Women: The significance of Present-Day College Education for Women and Curriculum Changes
 | periodical=Journal of Higher Education| postscript = &lt;!--None--&gt;
}}&lt;/ref&gt; The social consciousness fostered at Grinnell during these years became evident during [[Franklin D. Roosevelt|Franklin D. Roosevelt's]] presidency, when Grinnell graduates [[Harry Hopkins]] '12, [[Chester Davis]] '11, [[Paul H. Appleby|Paul Appleby]] '13, [[Hallie Flanagan]] '11, and [[Florence Kerr]] '12 became influential [[New Deal]] administrators.

Concern with social issues, educational innovation, and individual expression continue to shape Grinnell. As an example, the school’s &quot;5th year travel-service program,&quot; preceded the establishment of the [[Peace Corps]] by many years. Other recent innovations include first-year tutorials, cooperative pre-professional programs, and programs in quantitative studies and the societal impacts of technology.

==Academics==
=== Reputation===
[[Image:Grinnell 002.JPG|thumb|right|John H. T. Main Residence Hall]] Grinnell College is nationally recognized as a leading undergraduate institution. In July 2006, ''[[The New York Times]]'' included Grinnell in its profile of the 20 colleges and universities of &quot;established or rising scholarship&quot; which are fast becoming viable alternatives to [[Ivy League]] institutions,&lt;ref&gt;Archibold, R.C. [http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9500E3D7163FF933A05754C0A9609C8B63&amp;sec=&amp;spon=&amp;pagewanted=2 &quot;Off the Beaten Path&quot;], ''The New York Times'', July 30, 2006.&lt;/ref&gt; and is considered one of the 30 [[Hidden Ivies]].&lt;ref&gt;Greene, Howard and Greene, Mathew [http://www.harpercollins.com/browseinside/index.aspx?isbn13=9780061726729Grinnell], ''The Hidden Ivies'', 2009.&lt;/ref&gt;  Grinnell was ranked 14th in the ''[[Washington Monthly]]'' rankings, now 20th,&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.washingtonmonthly.com/features/2006/0609.libarts.html &quot;The Washington Monthly College Ratings: Liberal Arts Colleges&quot;], ''The Washington Monthly'', September 2006.&lt;/ref&gt; which focus on key outputs such as research, dollar value of scientific grants won and certain types of public service. Grinnell is a member of the [[Eight of the Best]] colleges (along with [[Claremont McKenna College]], [[Colorado College]], [[Connecticut College]], [[Haverford College]], [[Kenyon College]], [[Macalester College]], and [[Sarah Lawrence College]]), which is &quot;a group of eight highly selective, nationally recognized liberal arts colleges.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.grinnell.edu/admission/meetus/eightofthebest]&lt;/ref&gt; According to ''[[U.S. News and World Report]]'' rankings, Grinnell is the #18 liberal arts college in the United States. The College has been consistently ranked in the top 18 liberal arts colleges in the nation since the publication began in 1983.&lt;ref&gt;[http://chronicle.com/stats/usnews/index.php?category=Liberal+Arts+Colleges &quot;U.S. News Rankings Through the Years&quot;], ''Chronicle of Higher Education''&lt;/ref&gt;
In 2009, Grinnell College was ranked by [[The Princeton Review]] as one of the Top 10 best values in private colleges.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.princetonreview.com/SchoolList.aspx?id=758 |title=Test Prep: GMAT, GRE, LSAT, MCAT, SAT, ACT, and More |publisher=Princetonreview.com |date= |accessdate=2010-02-28}}&lt;/ref&gt; The 2009 Review also gave Grinnell its highest academic rating of 99, on a scale of 60-99, reflecting how hard students work and how much they get back for their efforts. This rating is calculated from student survey results and statistical information reported by administrators. Factors weighed include how many hours students study and the quality of students the school attracts.&lt;ref name=&quot;tljzhk&quot;/&gt;

Recent data place Grinnell at number eight among all U.S. undergraduate institutions in the proportion of graduates who go on to earn Ph.D. degrees and 15th for graduating female Ph.D. earners.&lt;ref&gt;Higher Education Data Sharing Consortium. &quot;Weighted Baccalaureate Origins Study.&quot; 2006.&lt;/ref&gt; Grinnell College graduates enjoy a high acceptance rate to law school; over 46% of all applications submitted by students have been accepted by law schools.&lt;ref&gt;Grinnell College Career Development Office [http://web.grinnell.edu/careerdevelopment/gradschool/LawSchoolAdmissionReport/GeneralStatistics.html#anchor619447 Law School Admission Report]&lt;/ref&gt; Indeed, Grinnell ranked 44th in a 2004 ''[[Wall Street Journal]]'' survey of the top &quot;feeder schools&quot; to the fifteen most prestigious business, law, and medical schools in the country.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.wsjclassroom.com/pdfs/wsj_college_092503.pdf &quot;Ranking the Colleges...&quot;], ''The Wall Street Journal''&lt;/ref&gt; Unigo.com's 2010 college rankings place Grinnell College in the &quot;Top 10 Colleges Where the Pursuit of Knowledge Goes Outside the Classroom&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.unigo.com/articles/nietzschean_supermen_(and_superwomen)/?taxonomyId=1137716&lt;/ref&gt;

However, [[Forbes magazine|''Forbes'' magazine's]] first ever rankings for academic institutions, ''America's Best Colleges'' (which uses a non-traditional ranking system based on RateMyProfessor.com evaluations, notable alumni, student debt, percentage of students graduating in four years, and the number of students or faculty receiving prestigious awards), Grinnell College has a comparatively lower rank of 107th best school overall, one behind [[Wells College]] and one in front of [[Virginia Military Institute]]. In the same study, [[Dartmouth College]] received a rank of 127.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.forbes.com/lists/2008/94/opinions_college08_Grinnell-College_94168.html |title=America's Best Colleges: #107 Grinnell College |publisher=Forbes.com |date= |accessdate=2010-02-28}}&lt;/ref&gt; In the current [[Forbes]] rankings, Grinnell is #78;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news| url=http://www.forbes.com/lists/2010/94/best-colleges-10_Grinnell-College_94168.html | work=Forbes | title=#78 Grinnell College | date=August 11, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; Dartmouth is #30.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news| url=http://www.forbes.com/lists/2010/94/best-colleges-10_Dartmouth-College_94114.html | work=Forbes | title=#30 Dartmouth College | date=August 11, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Faculty===
Grinnell has 150 voting faculty, 95% of whom possess a doctorate or the [[terminal degree]] in their field.&lt;ref&gt;[http://collegeprowler.com/grinnell-college/academics/ College Prowler website]&lt;/ref&gt; At the end of each semester, students fill out course surveys which play a large role in determining faculty tenure decisions and merit raises.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.cs.grinnell.edu/~rebelsky/about-eoc.html#merit SamR's Site: About End-Of-Course Evaluations&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;

===Academic program===
[[Image:Grinnell College Alumni Recitation Hall.jpg|thumb|right|Alumni Recitation Hall]]

The academic program at Grinnell College emphasizes active learning and one-on-one interactions between faculty members and students.  There are few large lecture classes.  In sharp contrast to all [[public universities]] and many private universities in the United States, no classes, labs or other courses are taught by [[graduate student]]s.

Grinnell's open curriculum encourages students to take initiative and to assume responsibility for their own courses of study.  The sole [[Curriculum#Core curriculum|core, or general education, requirement]] is the completion of the First-Year Tutorial, a one-semester, [[Course credit|four-credit]] special topics [[seminar]] that stresses methods of inquiry, critical analysis, and writing skills.  All other classes are chosen, with the direct guidance of a faculty member in the student's major department, by the student.

Grinnell College expects all students to possess significant academic achievements.  The curriculum is rigorous and advanced, and no remedial classes are offered.  For example, the math department does not offer any basic-level classes such as college algebra, trigonometry, or pre-calculus.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.grinnell.edu/academic/catalog/courses/mathstats/ Mathematics and Statistics courses offered]&lt;/ref&gt;  However, several independent, non-credit programs assist students who need help in a specific subject.  They are the Library Lab, Math Lab, Reading Lab, Science Learning Center, and the Writing Lab.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.grinnell.edu/academic/ Links to labs]&lt;/ref&gt;  While private tutors can be hired, participation in these programs is free for any enrolled student.

Grinnell has twenty-six major departments and ten interdisciplinary concentrations. Popular majors include [[Psychology]], [[Economics]], [[Biology]], [[History]], [[English language|English]], and [[Political Science]]. In every division, students have opportunities to conduct original research and undertake advanced study through independent and interdisciplinary projects that foster intellectual discovery.  The minimum requirements in a major area of study are typically limited to 32 credits in a single department, with some departments additionally requiring a small number of classes in related fields that are deemed critical for all students in that field.  For example, the biology program requires 32 credits in the biology department plus two classes in chemistry and one in math.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.grinnell.edu/academic/catalog/courses/biology/ Biology major requirements]&lt;/ref&gt; Many students exceed the minimum requirements.

To graduate, students are normally expected to complete at least 32 credits in a major field and a total of 124 credits of academic work.  To encourage students to explore courses outside of their primary interest area, no more than 48 credits in one department and no more than 92 credits in one division are counted towards this requirement.

[[File:Grinnell College Bucksbaum Rotunda.jpg|thumb|right|Bucksbaum Rotunda]]
Grinnell’s commitment to the importance of off-campus study reflects the school’s emphasis on social and political awareness and the international nature of its campus. Approximately 60 percent of all Grinnell students participate in at least one of more than seventy off-campus programs, including the Grinnell-in-[[London]] program and study tours of [[China]], [[France]], [[Greece]], and [[Russia]]. These study programs in [[Europe]] (including Russia), [[Africa]], the [[Near East]], and [[Asia]], as well as nine programs in [[Central America|Central]] and [[South America]], provide the opportunity for research in many disciplines, from archaeology to education to mathematics. In addition to off-campus programs, Grinnell offers internship programs in such areas as urban studies, art, and marine biology for students interested in field-based learning and experience in professional settings. Second- and third-year students may apply for summer internship grants and receive credit for the experience. Semester programs in the United States include those at [[Oak Ridge National Laboratory]], [[Newberry Library]], [[National Theatre Institute]], and Grinnell-in-[[Washington, D.C.]]

Grinnell also has invested in several interdisciplinary programs:  the Center for Prairie Studies, Center for the Humanities, Center for International Studies, Noun Program in Women's Studies, Peace Studies Program, Rosenfield Public Affairs Program, and the Donald L. Wilson Program in Enterprise and Leadership.

Despite the growing trend of U.S. students taking five or more years to finish an undergraduate degree{{Citation needed|date=April 2008}}, Grinnell College is strongly oriented towards students being enrolled full time in exactly eight consecutive semesters at the college, although exceptions are available for medical issues and other emergencies.&lt;ref&gt;Grinnell College. [http://www.grinnell.edu/academic/catalog/acadreg/courseloads/ &quot;Academic Catalog: Academic Regulations&quot;]&lt;/ref&gt; To avoid being suspended from the college, students must make &quot;normal progress towards graduation.&quot;  This generally means that the student must pass at least 12 credits of classes in each individual semester, with grades of a C or better, and have accumulated enough credits to make graduation possible at the end of four years, which requires an average of 15.5 credits each semester.  A student who is not making normal progress towards graduation is placed on academic probation and may be dismissed from the college.&lt;ref&gt;Grinnell College. [http://www.grinnell.edu/academic/catalog/acadreg/probation/ &quot;Academic Catalog: Academic Regulations&quot;]&lt;/ref&gt;

==Admission==

[[File:Grinnell College MacEachron Field.JPG|thumb|right|Grinnell College MacEachron Field]]Grinnell College is a highly selective liberal arts college. Historically, it has offered admission to less than half of applicants, and approximately one-third of accepted students typically enroll in the fall. In the spring of 2009, 29.1% of applicants were accepted for a class size of 380.&lt;ref name=Factbook2009&gt;[https://itwebforms.grinnell.edu/factbook/pdfs/factbook2009.pdf Grinnell College Factbook Fall 2009]. Retrieved 2011-08-25.&lt;/ref&gt;

Two-thirds of admitted students were in the top 10% of their high school class.&lt;ref name=Factbook2009/&gt;  One in five students is a National Merit Finalist, National Merit Scholar, or National Merit Commended Student.&lt;ref name=Factbook2009/&gt;  15% are Advanced Placement Scholars.&lt;ref name=Factbook2009/&gt;

Due to the high [[SAT]] and [[ACT (examination)|ACT]] scores achieved by its students and their class rankings, [[U.S. News and World Reports]] considers Grinnell College to be one of the &quot;most selective&quot; schools.&lt;ref&gt;[http://colleges.usnews.rankingsandreviews.com/usnews/edu/college/directory/brief/drglance_1868_brief.php US News and World Reports]. Retrieved 2008-04-20.&lt;/ref&gt; For the class of 2013, the mid-50% SAT combined score range is 1300-1480, and the mid-50% ACT composite score is 29-33.&lt;ref name=Factbook2009/&gt;

Grinnell College's admissions selectivity rank according to [[The Princeton Review]] is a 95 out of 99.&lt;ref&gt;[[The Princeton Review]]. [http://www.princetonreview.com/schools/college/CollegeAdmissions.aspx?iid=1023453 Grinnell College]. Retrieved November 23, 2008.&lt;/ref&gt; This ranking is determined by several institutionally-reported factors, including: the class rank, average standardized test scores, and average high school GPA of entering freshmen; the percentage of students who hail from out-of-state; and the percentage of applicants accepted.&lt;ref&gt;[[The Princeton Review]]. [http://www.princetonreview.com/college/research/articles/find/ratings.asp#selectivity About College]&lt;/ref&gt;

The primary factor in evaluating applicants is the quality of the education they have received, as shown by their [[transcript (education)|transcript]].  Additional factors include [[standardized test]] scores, student writing skills, recommendations, and extracurricular activities.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.grinnell.edu/admission/apply/faqs/#lookingfor Grinnell College Admission FAQ]. Retrieved 2008-05-15.&lt;/ref&gt;

Early decision opportunities are offered to students in the fall; most students apply in January of their final year in high school.  Admissions letters are usually received by April 1 of each year.  All students begin classes in August.

For American students, the students' expectation of needing financial assistance does not affect the admission process.&lt;ref name=SandB&gt;Montgomery, David. [http://web.grinnell.edu/sandb/archives/volume_121/number_17/news/article06.html &quot;International student financial aid goes need-sensitive&quot;], ''The Scarlet &amp; Black'', March 4, 2005&lt;/ref&gt;  International students whose needs can be met with the limited financial aid available to them are given an edge in the admissions process.

A few students are admitted before they graduate from high school; these students have typically taken all of the academic classes offered at their school.

==Tuition and financial aid==
[[Image:Grinnell College- Robert Noyce Science Center.jpg|thumb|right|Robert Noyce Science Center]]
Grinnell's combined tuition, room, board, and fees for the 2009-2010 academic year is $45,012. Tuition and fees are $36,476 and room and board are $8,536.&lt;ref&gt;Grinnell College, Office of Admissions. [http://www.grinnell.edu/admission/apply/tuition/ Tuition and Financial Aid]. Retrieved November 12, 2009.&lt;/ref&gt; Grinnell offers a significant amount of need-based and merit-based aid in comparison with peer institutions.  About 90% of students receive some form of financial aid.&lt;ref&gt;Grinnell College, Office of Admission. [http://www.grinnell.edu/admission/tuifees/ Tuition &amp; Fees]. Retrieved February 26, 2007.&lt;/ref&gt; The average financial aid package is over $26,000.&lt;ref&gt;College Board. [http://collegesearch.collegeboard.com/search/CollegeDetail.jsp?collegeId=442&amp;profileId=2 &quot;College Board Profile of Grinnell College&quot;]. Retrieved October 2, 2007.&lt;/ref&gt;

Grinnell College is one of a few dozen US colleges that maintain [[need-blind admission]]s and meets the full demonstrated financial need of all U.S. residents who are admitted to the college.&lt;ref name=SandB/&gt;

With the first-year students enrolled in the 2006-2007 school year, Grinnell has ended its [[need-blind admission]]s policy for international applicants. Under the old policy, students from countries outside the U.S. were admitted without any consideration of their ability to afford four years of study at the college. However, financial aid offers to these students were limited to half the cost of tuition.&lt;ref name=SandB/&gt;  International students frequently carried very high workloads in an effort to pay the bills, and their academic performance often suffered.&lt;ref&gt;Leavens, Kennedy. [http://web.grinnell.edu/sandb/archives/volume_119/number_19/news/3.html &quot;Need-sensitivity? Admissions may start looking at international students’ bank accounts&quot;], ''The Scarlet &amp; Black'', February 28, 2003.&lt;/ref&gt;  Under the new &quot;need-sensitive&quot; or &quot;need-aware&quot; policy, international students whose demonstrated financial needs can be met are given a slight admissions edge over applicants who can't. The twin hopes are that the enrolled international students will be able to dedicate more energy to their schoolwork, and also that this will ultimately allow the college to provide higher tuition grants to international students.

Additionally, several extremely competitive &quot;special scholarships&quot; were set up to meet the full demonstrated financial needs for students from the following countries or regions:  Africa, Eastern and Central Europe, Latin America, Middle East and Asia, Nepal, the People's Republic of China, as well as for native speakers of Russian regardless of citizenship, available every other year.&lt;ref&gt;Grinnell College. [http://www.grinnell.edu/admission/apply/international/finaid/ &quot;International Student Financial Aid Policy&quot;].&lt;/ref&gt;

==Athletics==
[[Image:Honor 'G'.png|thumb|right|Grinnell Athletics &quot;Honor G&quot;]]

The school's varsity sports teams are named the '''Pioneers'''. They participate in eighteen intercollegiate sports at the [[National Collegiate Athletic Association|NCAA]] Division III level and in the [[Midwest Conference]]. In addition, Grinnell has several club sports teams that compete in non-varsity sports such as [[water polo]], [[Ultimate (sport)|ultimate]] and [[rugby union]]. 

Nearly one-third of recent Grinnell graduates participated in at least one of 20 varsity sports while attending the college and the college has led the Midwest Conference in the total number of Academic All-Conference honorees in last six years.

The Water Polo club team, the Wild Turkeys, were runners-up in the 2007 Division III Collegiate National Club Championships organized by the [[CWPA]] in Lindenwood University, St. Louis. The Men's Ultimate team, nicknamed the Grinnellephants, qualified in 2008 for its first Division III National Championship in Versailles, Ohio. The Women's Ultimate team, nicknamed The Sticky Tongue Frogs, tied for third place in the 2010 Division III National Championship in [[Appleton, Wisconsin]].&lt;ref&gt;[[USA Ultimate]]. [http://scores.usaultimate.org/scores/#college-womens/tournament/6639 2010 UPA College Division III Womens Championships]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://web.grinnell.edu/groups/frisbee/women/women.html The Sticky Tongue Frogs Grinnell Womens Ultimate]&lt;/ref&gt; The success was repeated in 2011 when the men's team placed third in 2011 Division III National Championship in Buffalo.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.usaultimate.org/news/2011-d-iii-college-championships--sunday-open-recap/&lt;/ref&gt;

In February 2005, Grinnell became the first Division III school featured in a regular season basketball game by the ESPN network family in 30 years when it faced off against the [[Beloit College|Beloit]] Buccaneers on [[ESPN2]].&lt;ref&gt;Amy Farnum. NCAA Sports. [http://www.ncaasports.com/basketball/mens/story/8141645 Grinnell Goes Big-Time]. January 28, 2005.&lt;/ref&gt; Grinnell lost 86-85.&lt;ref&gt;D3Hoops.com [http://www.d3hoops.com/story.php?story=38975 Beloit 86, Grinnell 85]. February 3, 2005.&lt;/ref&gt; Grinnell College's basketball team attracted ESPN due to the team's [[run and gun (basketball)|run and gun]] style of playing basketball, known in Grinnell simply as &quot;The System.&quot;  Coach David Arseneault's &quot;system&quot; incorporates a continual full-court press, a fast-paced offense, an emphasis on offensive rebounding, a barrage of three-point shots and substitutions of five players at a time every 35 to 40 seconds.  This allows a higher average playing time for more players than the &quot;starters&quot; and suits the Division III goals of scholar-athletes.  &quot;The System&quot; has been criticized for not teaching the principles of defense. However, under &quot;The System,&quot; Grinnell has won three conference championships over the past ten years and have regularly placed in the top half of the conference. Coach Arseneault's teams have set numerous NCAA scoring records and several individuals on the Grinnell team have led the nation in scoring or assists.&lt;ref&gt;Official 2007 NCAA Men's Basketball Records Book, [http://www.ncaa.org/library/records/basketball/m_basketball_records_book/2007/2007_m_basketball_records.pdf NCAA.org] Retrieved March 7, 2007.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;br&gt; On November 19, 2011 Grinnell player Griffin Lentsch set a new Division III individual scoring record in a game against [[Principia College]]. The 6-foot 4-inch guard scored 89 points, besting the old record of 77, also set by a Pioneers player - Jeff Clement - in 1998. Lentsch made 27 of his 55 shots, including 15 three-pointers as Grinnell won the high-scoring game 145 to 97.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://rivals.yahoo.com/ncaa/basketball/blog/the_dagger/post/Grinnell-College-star-shatters-Division-III-reco?urn=ncaab-wp6348|title=Grinnell College star shatters Division III scoring record|published= Rivals.com via Yahoo Sports website|date=2011-11-22|acceesdate|2011-11-22}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Campus==
[[File:GrinnellCollege EastRHalls.JPG|thumb|right|East Campus dormitories connected by Grinnell's distinctive [[loggia]].]]
Grinnell College is located in the town of [[Grinnell, Iowa]], about halfway between [[Des Moines, IA|Des Moines]] and [[Iowa City, IA|Iowa City]]. The {{convert|120|acre|km2|sing=on}} campus contains sixty-three buildings ranging in style from [[Collegiate Gothic]] to [[Bauhaus]]. The residential part of campus is divided into three sections: North Campus, East Campus, and South Campus. Each campus's dormitories, modeled explicitly after the residential colleges of Oxford and Cambridge, are connected by a [[loggia]], an architectural signature of the college.

The college maintains a {{convert|365|acre|km2|sing=on}} environmental research area called the [[Conard Environmental Research Area]] (CERA). The U.S. Green Building Council awarded CERA's Environmental Education Center a gold certification.&lt;ref&gt;[[United States Green Building Council]]. [http://www.usgbc.org/ShowFile.aspx?DocumentID=1548 &quot;Cera Environmental Education Center LEED Scorecard&quot;]. Accessed May 14, 2007.&lt;/ref&gt; The building is the first in Iowa to receive the designation.&lt;ref&gt;American Association for the Advancement of Sustainability in Higher Education. ''AAASHE Bulletin'' [http://www.aashe.org/archives/2006/06_06_08.php &quot;Grinnell College Education Center Receives LEED Gold Certification&quot;], June 8, 2006. Retrieved April 29, 2008.&lt;/ref&gt;

Many building projects have been undertaken in recent years at the College including a new athletics center, the [[Bucksbaum Center for the Arts]], the renovation of the Robert Noyce '49 Science Center and the Joe Rosenfield '25 Student Center. Noted architect [[César Pelli]] designed the athletics center, the Joe Rosenfield '25 Student Center, and the [[Bucksbaum Center for the Arts]].&lt;ref&gt;Hebel, Sara. [http://chronicle.com/weekly/v52/i31/31a01501.htm &quot;In Iowa, 2 Colleges Separated by 150 Miles and $1.37-Billion&quot;], ''[[The Chronicle of Higher Education]]'', April 7, 2006. Retrieved April 30, 2008.&lt;/ref&gt;

==Social activities and organizations==
[[File:GrinnellCollegeGatesTower.jpg|thumb|right|Gates Tower and Rawson Hall]]
The organizational structure of the Student Government Association, wielding a yearly budget of over $360,000 and unusually strong administrative influence, covers almost all aspects of student activity and campus life. There are no sororities or fraternities.

Founded in 2004, the student-run Student Endowment Investing Group (SEIG), actively invests over $100,000 of Grinnell College's endowment in the stock market. The group's mission is to provide interested students with valuable experience for future careers in finance.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.grinnell.edu/student/groups/seig/approach/ Student Endowment Investment Group&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;

Service organizations are popular. The Alternative Break (&quot;AltBreak&quot;) program takes students to pursue service initiatives during school holidays, and as of 2005, Grinnell had more alumni per capita serving in the [[Peace Corps]] than any other college in the nation.&lt;ref name=&quot;pc&quot;&gt;[[Peace Corps]]. [http://www.peacecorps.gov/index.cfm?shell=resources.media.press.view&amp;news_id=1011 Peace Corps Announces the Colleges and Universities that Have Produced the Most Peace Corps Volunteers]. January 24, 2005.&lt;/ref&gt; The college also runs its own post-graduation service program known as Grinnell Corps in [[Grinnell, Iowa|Grinnell]], [[People's Republic of China|China]], [[Namibia]], [[Lesotho]], [[New Orleans]], and [[Thailand]], and has previously operated programs in [[Greece]], [[Macau]], and [[Nepal]].&lt;ref&gt;Grinnell College, Office of Social Commitment. [http://www.grinnell.edu/offices/socialcommitment/grinnellcorps/ Grinnell Corps]. Retrieved February 26, 2007.&lt;/ref&gt;

The ''[[Scarlet and Black]]'' is the campus newspaper and [[KDIC]] (88.5 FM) is the student-run radio station. The school has a monthly satirical newspaper, &quot;[http://www.thebands.biz The B&amp;S].&quot;

In April 2007, Grinnell college students founded the [[Social Entrepreneurs of Grinnell]], a student operated microfinance lending institution. The group collects donations for the purpose of making small loans at zero interest to business owners and artisans in developing nations. It is affiliated with [[kiva.org]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://web.grinnell.edu/groups/socentre/index.shtml Social Entrepreneurs of Grinnell&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;

Grinnell also has an entirely student-run textbook lending library on campus. Aimed at the economically disadvantaged yet open to all, it allows students to check out books for the semester for free, defraying the high cost of college textbooks.&lt;ref&gt;Grinnell College, Student Government Association, [http://www.grinnellsga.com/?p=161 Grinnellsga.com], Retrieved July 13, 2008.&lt;/ref&gt; The library has no funding, relying solely on books donated. Since its founding in 2005, the collection has grown to thousands of books due to the generosity of the campus community. The library has expanded to include caps and gowns, which are lent out to graduating seniors every spring.&lt;ref&gt;Grinnell College, Commencement Information. [http://www.grinnell.edu/offices/ce/commencement/info/ Grinnell.edu], Retrieved July 13, 2008.&lt;/ref&gt;

Grinnell hosts the [[Titular Head (film festival)|Titular Head]] film festival.

==Self-governance==
Students at Grinnell adhere to an honor system known as &quot;[[self-governance]]&quot; wherein they are expected to govern their own choices and behavior with minimal direct intervention by the college administration. By cultivating a community based on freedom of choice, self-governance aims to encourage students to become responsible, respectful, and accountable members of the campus, town, and global community.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.grinnell.edu/offices/studentaffairs/selfgovernance/ |title=Self Governance - Student Affairs &amp;#124; Grinnell College |publisher=Grinnell.edu |date= |accessdate=2010-02-28}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Endowment==
[[File:Grinnell College Joe Rosenfield '25 Center.JPG|thumb|right|Joe Rosenfield '25 Center]]Grinnell College is the 49th wealthiest educational institution, of any size, in North America with a larger endowment than many research universities such as [[Georgetown University]], [[Tufts University]] and [[UCLA]].&lt;ref&gt;NACUBO Endowment Market Values 2010 http://www.nacubo.org/Documents/research/2010NCSE_Public_Tables_Endowment_Market_Values_Final.pdf&lt;/ref&gt; The $1.26 billion endowment as of the end of FY 2010 – the fifth-largest among United States liberal arts colleges – is evident in the college's facilities, art collections, and generous financial aid programs.&lt;ref name=&quot;NACUBO&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.nacubo.org/Images/All%20Institutions%20Listed%20by%20FY%202007%20Market%20Value%20of%20Endowment%20Assets_2007%20NES.pdf|title= Annual NACUBO Endowment Study 2007. |accessdate=2008-01-26 |work=}}&lt;/ref&gt;  Under the stewardship of [[Warren Buffett]] and [[Joseph Rosenfield]], the college has adopted an opportunistic and innovative strategy in managing its assets. In 1976, Grinnell's capital fund acquired a TV station, [[WDTN]] in Dayton, Ohio,&lt;ref&gt;''[[Time (magazine)|Time]]''. [http://www.time.com/time/magazine/article/0,9171,920003,00.html Time.com], January 15, 1979.&lt;/ref&gt; one of many investments that were unprecedented in their time for a college endowment. (Grinnell would sell the station in 1981.) Another innovative move that significantly increased the endowment occurred when Rosenfield and the college contributed to the founding of [[Intel]]—an investment exceeding 10% of the venture capital raised to start the semiconductor company ([[Intel]] co-founder [[Robert Noyce]] is a Grinnell alumnus).&lt;ref&gt;[[CNNMoney.com]],  [http://money.cnn.com/2000/06/01/zweig_on_funds/zweig_on_funds/a.htm Zweig on funds], June 1, 2000.&lt;/ref&gt;

Since joining the board in 1968, Warren Buffett has played a visible role in growing the endowment at Grinnell, where he serves as a life trustee.&lt;ref&gt;Grinnell College, Office of the President. [http://www.grinnell.edu/Offices/president/trustee/memberintro/buffett/ &quot;Board of Trustees: Warren E. Buffett 1968; Life Trustee 1987&quot;.] Accessed May 12, 2008.&lt;/ref&gt;

A campaign is currently under way to create more transparency and social responsibility in the endowment's investments.

==Notable alumni==
&lt;!-- PLEASE go to the TALK PAGE before editing this list. No more than SIX NAMES should be included on THIS page.--&gt;

{{main|List of Grinnell College alumni}}

Many former students at Grinnell College have gone into politics, made important contributions to science, or become prominent entertainers.

* [[Harry Hopkins]], 1912, senior advisor to [[Franklin Delano Roosevelt]], principal architect of the [[New Deal]], [[Works Progress Administration|WPA]] administrator.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url = http://www.u-s-history.com/pages/h1610.html | title = Harry Hopkins | publisher = U-S-History.com  | accessdate = 2007-02-25}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[Joseph Welch]], 1914, Head attorney for the [[United States Army]] during the [[Army-McCarthy Hearings]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url = http://www.biography.com/search/article.do?id=9527075 | title = Joseph Nye Welch Biography | publisher = The Biography Channel  | accessdate = 2007-02-25}} {{Dead link|date=September 2010|bot=H3llBot}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[Robert Noyce]], 1949, nicknamed &quot;Mayor of Silicon Valley&quot;, co-founder of [[Intel]], co-inventor of the [[integrated circuit]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url = http://www.ieeeghn.org/wiki/index.php/Robert_Noyce | title = IEEEGHN: Robert Noyce | publisher = IEEE  | accessdate = 2007-02-26}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[Herbie Hancock]], 1960, Jazz musician and composer who has won an [[Academy Award]] and multiple [[Grammy Awards]], member of [[Miles Davis|Miles Davis's]] &quot;second great quintet&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url = http://www.grinnell.edu/publicrelations/bucksbaum/herbie.html | title = Herbie Hancock | publisher = Grinnell College  | accessdate = 2007-02-02 |archiveurl = http://web.archive.org/web/20070128073232/http://www.grinnell.edu/publicrelations/bucksbaum/herbie.html &lt;!-- Bot retrieved archive --&gt; |archivedate = 2007-01-28}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[John Garang]], 1969, leader of the rebel [[Sudan People's Liberation Army]], later vice president of [[Sudan]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url = http://www.gurtong.org/GarangTribute/Biographyof_LateDr.JohnGarangde-Mabior.asp | title = Biography of the Late Dr. John Garang de-Mabior | publisher = Gurtong Peace Project  | accessdate = 2007-02-25}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[Thomas Cech]], 1970, Co-winner of 1989 [[Nobel Prize in Chemistry]] &quot;for [...] discovery of catalytic properties of RNA&quot;, past president of the [[Howard Hughes Medical Institute]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web| url = http://nobelprize.org/nobel_prizes/chemistry/laureates/1989/index.html | title = Chemistry 1989 | publisher = [[Nobel Foundation]]  | accessdate = 2007-03-11}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.hhmi.org/research/investigators/cech_bio.html HHMI.org], Thomas Cech&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[Ian Roberts]], 1987, Actor [[Bring it On]]

==References==
{{reflist|colwidth=30em}}

==External links==
{{commons|Grinnell College, Iowa}}
*[http://www.grinnell.edu/ Official website]

{{Colleges and universities in Iowa}}
{{Midwest Conference}}
{{Annapolis Group}}
{{Associated Colleges of the Midwest}}
{{CLAC}}
{{Oberlin Group}}
{{568 Group}}

[[Category:Grinnell College| ]]
[[Category:Associated Colleges of the Midwest]]
[[Category:Buildings and structures in Poweshiek County, Iowa]]
[[Category:Council of Independent Colleges]]
[[Category:Education in Poweshiek County, Iowa]]
[[Category:Educational institutions established in 1846]]
[[Category:Liberal arts colleges]]
[[Category:Members of the Annapolis Group]]
[[Category:Midwest Conference]]
[[Category:National Association of Independent Colleges and Universities members]]
[[Category:North Central Association of Colleges and Schools]]
[[Category:Posse schools]]
[[Category:Universities and colleges in Iowa]]
[[Category:Visitor attractions in Poweshiek County, Iowa]]

[[bg:Гринелски колеж]]
[[no:Grinnell College]]
[[zh:格林内尔学院]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
