<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="13110188" ns="0" title="Mets–Yankees rivalry"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Infobox MLB rivalry
|team1=New York Mets
|team2=New York Yankees
|team1abr=NYM
|team2abr=NYY
|team1logo=[[Image:New York Mets Insignia.svg|120px|Mets Logo]]
|team2logo=[[Image:NewYorkYankees caplogo.svg|120px|Yankees Logo]]
|first_meeting=June 16, 1997
|last_meeting=July 3, 2011
|next_meeting=June 8, 2012
|meetings=89
|regularseason=NYY, 49–35
|largest_victory=
|current_streak=
|longeststreak_team1=3
|longeststreak_team2=7
|postseason1=[[2000 World Series]]
|postseason1result=NYY, 4–1
}}
The '''New York Mets – New York Yankees rivalry''' is the latest incarnation of the [[Subway Series]], the competition between [[New York City]]'s [[Major League Baseball]] teams, the [[American League]] [[New York Yankees]] and the [[National League]] [[New York Mets]]. Until [[Interleague play]] started, the two teams had only met in exhibition games. Since the inception of interleague play the two teams have met every regular season since 1997, and since 1999 they have met six times each season, playing two three-game series, one in each team's ballpark.  They have made the postseason in the same year three times: {{by|1999}}, {{by|2000}}, and {{by|2006}}, and faced off in the [[2000 World Series]].

==1962–1996: Formation of the Mets, Mayor's Trophy and pre-interleague era==
===Background and formation of Mets===
The Mets–Yankees rivalry has its origins in the history of the [[History of the Brooklyn Dodgers|Brooklyn Dodgers]] and [[History of the New York Giants (NL)|New York Giants]], as well as the [[History of the New York Yankees|history of the Yankees]], the three [[Major League Baseball]] teams of [[New York City]] from 1903 to 1957.&lt;ref name=&quot;RivalryRoots&quot;&gt;{{cite news|title=Back to the future: a New York baseball turf fight|date=October 5, 1999|first=Hal|last=Bock|agency=Associated Press}}&lt;/ref&gt; For most of that time, the Giants played in [[Manhattan]], the Dodgers in [[Brooklyn]], and the Yankees in the [[Bronx]].  

Throughout their time in New York, the three teams chronicled a fierce intra-city rivalry.  The [[Dodgers–Giants rivalry]] was formed by both teams' competition for dominance in the [[National League]], exemplified by [[Bobby Thomson]]'s [[Shot Heard 'Round the World (baseball)|Shot Heard 'Round the World]] in the [[1951 National League tie-breaker series]].&lt;ref name=&quot;RivalryRoots&quot;/&gt; The Yankees, as the city's only [[American League]] team, would form the [[Yankees–Giants rivalry]] and [[Yankees–Dodgers rivalry]] around their multiple [[Subway Series]] competitions with the two teams, where the Yankees would compile a 10-3 record in the thirteen all-New York [[World Series]].&lt;ref name=&quot;RivalryRoots&quot;/&gt;

However, in {{By|1958}}, both of New York's National League teams moved to [[California]], the Giants to [[San Francisco, California|San Francisco]] to become the [[San Francisco Giants]], and the Dodgers to [[Los Angeles, California|Los Angeles]] to become the [[Los Angeles Dodgers]]. The Yankees were New York City's only Major League Baseball team until {{By|1962}}, when the expansion Mets joined the National League. The Mets sought to create a fan base from fans of the departed National League teams, and adopted the Giants' NY insignia in the Giant color of orange set against a cap of Dodger blue. They played their first two seasons in the Giants' old stadium, the [[Polo Grounds]], before moving into [[Shea Stadium]] in the borough of [[Queens]].

===World Series championships===
{{MLBBioRet
|Image  = YankeesRetired37.svg
|Name   = Casey Stengel
|Number = 37
|Team   = New York Yankees
|Year   = 1970
|}}{{MLBBioRet
|Image  = Metret37.PNG
|Name   = Casey Stengel
|Number = 37
|Team   = New York Mets
|Year   = 1965
|}}
[[1962 Major League Baseball season|1962]] was the inaugural season of the New York Mets and they would post one of the worst regular season records in MLB history, 40-120.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title=The Mets' Long Season Ends With Their 120th Defeat, 5 to 1|date=October 1, 1962|first=Louis|last=Effrat|newspaper=New York Times|page=43|authorlink=Louis Effrat}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title=Mark? Mets can keep it ; Tigers win 5 of 6 to finish 1 shy of record 120 losses|date=September 29, 2003|first=Larry|last=Lage|agency=Associated Press|newspaper=Chicago Tribune|page=3}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title=The Tigers Are Happy To Avoid Making History|date=September 29, 2003|url=http://www.nytimes.com/2003/09/29/sports/baseball-the-tigers-are-happy-to-avoid-making-history.html?pagewanted=print&amp;src=pm&amp;gwh=D5EED5C6D8BDBFF62DFF597F69EE8740|first=Joe|last=Lapointe|newspaper=New York Times|page=D3}}&lt;/ref&gt;  Meanwhile, the Yankees won the [[1962 World Series|World Series]] that year, the last such World Series won by the aging lineup of the 1950s dynasty. The Yankees would go to the World Series in {{wsy|1963}} and {{wsy|1964}}, but lose both times.  The 1962 and 1963 World Series were played against the Yankees' former [[Subway Series]] rivals, the Giants in '62 and Dodgers in '63.

The Mets hired former Yankee legend [[Casey Stengel]] as their first manager and former Yankee legend and Hall of Famer [[Red Ruffing]] as their first pitching coach. Stengel's number 37 serves as the only number retired by both the Yankees and Mets. The Mets emerged as one of the worst teams in baseball for their first seven seasons.  In 1966, the Mets bypassed Hall of Famer and future Yankee [[Reggie Jackson]] in the amateur draft, instead selecting [[Steve Chilcott]], who never played in the majors.  However, behind pitching ace [[Tom Seaver]], the [[1969 New York Mets season|1969 &quot;Miracle Mets&quot;]] staged a remarkable turnaround for the franchise and defeated the heavily-favored [[1969 Baltimore Orioles season|Baltimore Orioles]] in the [[1969 World Series|World Series]]. 

The Mets staged a surprising late season run to capture the [[1973 National League Championship Series|1973 National League Pennant]], but lost the [[1973 World Series|World Series]] in seven games to the [[Oakland Athletics]], particularly due to the efforts in Game 7 of Reggie Jackson. The Mets winning this National League pennant was notable because it was the only time between 1970 and 1980 that the [[National League East|NL East]] title was not won by either the [[Phillies–Pirates rivalry|Philadelphia Phillies or the Pittsburgh Pirates]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://philadelphia.phillies.mlb.com/news/article.jsp?ymd=20050707&amp;content_id=1119893&amp;vkey=news_phi&amp;fext=.jsp&amp;c_id=phi|title=Notes: Phils&amp;ndash;Pirates rivalry fading|date=July 7, 2005|accessdate=January 3, 2011|first=George|last=Von Benko|work=Phillies.MLB.com|publisher=Major League Baseball}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title=Pirates perform rare three-peat feat 4&amp;ndash;2|date=September 28, 1992|newspaper=USA Today|page=5C}}&lt;/ref&gt; Former Yankee catcher [[Yogi Berra]] was a Met coach in 1969 and manager of the team in 1973. Both teams shared [[Shea Stadium]] as their home field when [[Yankee Stadium (1923)|Yankee Stadium]] was being refit during the {{By|1974}} and {{By|1975}} seasons.

The Yankees returned to the World Series in {{wsy|1976}}, but were swept by the [[Big Red Machine]] of the [[Cincinnati Reds]]. In {{wsy|1977}}, behind Reggie Jackson, the Yankees won their first World Series in 15 years against former [[Subway Series]] [[Yankees–Dodgers rivalry|rival]] [[Los Angeles Dodgers]], where Jackson earned the moniker &quot;Mr. October&quot; by hitting three home runs off of three different Dodger pitchers, all on the first pitch, in Game 6. That year, future Yankees manager [[Joe Torre]] made his managerial debut with the Mets. The following year, the Yankees again defeated the Dodgers in six games in the [[1978 World Series|World Series]].

The Yankees again faced the Dodgers in the [[1981 World Series]], but lost in six games in the same way the Dodgers lost the 1978 series (winning the first two games at home, but dropping the next four). After the series, Yankees' owner [[George Steinbrenner]] issued a public apology to the City of New York for his team's performance and at the same time assuring the fans that plans to put the team together for 1982 would begin immediately.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title=Steinbrenner Makes an Apology to the Fans for How Yankees Played|date=October 29, 1981|author=Associated Press|newspaper=Los Angeles Times|page=G1}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title=Steinbrenner Issues an Apology to Fans|date=October 29, 1981|first=Jane|last=Gross|newspaper=New York Times|page=B13}}&lt;/ref&gt; Steinbrenner was criticized heartily by players and press alike for doing so, as most people felt losing the World Series was not something that needed an apology.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.nytimes.com/2003/10/26/sports/sports-of-the-times-yanks-are-now-0-4-on-the-brink-at-the-stadium.html?pagewanted=1&amp;pagewanted=print|title=Yanks Are Now 0-4 on the Brink at the Stadium|date=October 26, 2003|first=Dave|last=Anderson|newspaper=New York Times|page=8.4|authorlink=Dave Anderson (sportswriter)}}&lt;/ref&gt; This would begin another long championship drought for the Yankees, 18 years, the longest since they first won in {{wsy|1923}}. The 1980s would also be the only decade since their first championship in which they did not win a World Series.

In contrast, the Mets enjoyed success during much of the decade and won the World Series in {{wsy|1986}} against the Yankees' [[Yankees – Red Sox rivalry|biggest nemesis]], the [[Boston Red Sox]], in seven games. ''[[The New York Times]]'' called the series a &quot;painful series.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title=It's More than Baseball; For Yankee Fans, A Painful Series|date=October 19, 1986|first=Dennis|last=Hevesi|newspaper=The New York Times|page=A51}}&lt;/ref&gt; ''[[Newsday]]'' called it &quot;woeful days for Yankee fans.&quot;&lt;ref name=Steinbrenner&gt;{{cite news|title=And What If You're a Yankees Fan?|date=October 18, 1986|first=Richard C.|last=Firstman|newspaper=Newsday|page=83}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Mike Lupica]] of the ''[[Daily News (New York)|New York Daily News]]'' called the series &quot;the World Series that is the Yankee nightmare.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title=Yankees' Fans Get Worst of Both Worlds|date=October 18, 1986|first=Mike|last=Lupica|authorlink=Mike Lupica|newspaper=New York Daily News}}&lt;/ref&gt; Both ''[[Newsday]]'' and ''The Boston Globe'' said that there were Mets T-shirts saying &quot;[[George Steinbrenner|Steinbrenner]]'s nightmare,&quot;&lt;ref name=Steinbrenner/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|quote=At McGonnell's bar, the sporting center of New York City...on display for sale behind the bar were Mets/Sox T-shirts with &quot;Steinbrenner's nightmare&quot; stenciled on the backs, the creation of one of the bar's regulars.|title=Lopsided Score Means Early Exit for NY Fans|date=October 20, 1986|first=Diane|last=Alters|newspaper=The Boston Globe|page=42}}&lt;/ref&gt; referring to Yankees owner [[George Steinbrenner]]. John Powers of the ''Globe'' quoted Claire Smith, who covered the Yankees for ''The Hartford Courant'', as having said that &quot;this really is the World Series of the nightmares.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title=Connecticut State of Confusion|date=October 20, 1986|first=John|last=Powers|newspaper=The Boston Globe|page=38}}&lt;/ref&gt; Yankee fans attended the Mets' celebration parade, saying that &quot;anyone who beats Boston is worth coming down for.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title=Ticker tape blizzard grips Gotham|date=October 29, 1986|first=Dan|last=Andrews|agency=United Press International}}&lt;/ref&gt; The Mets would also win the National League East in 1988, but fall in seven games to the [[1988 World Series|eventual champion]] Los Angeles Dodgers in the [[1988 National League Championship Series|NLCS]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.baseball-reference.com/leagues/NL/1988.shtml|title=1988 National League Team Statistics and Standings|work=Baseball-Reference.com|publisher=Sports Reference LLC|accessdate=November 25, 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The Yankees finished with the best record in the American League in [[1994 New York Yankees season|1994]], but the [[1994–95 Major League Baseball strike|players' strike]] canceled that year's postseason.&lt;ref name=&quot;94Yankees&quot;&gt;{{cite news|last=Costello|first=Brian|title='94 Yanks Cut Short|newspaper=[[New York Post]]|date=August 8, 2004|page=58}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Yankees-94Strike&quot;&gt;{{cite news|title=Finishing What They Started|date=April 25, 1995|first=Jack|last=O'Connell|newspaper=The Hartford Courant|page=G2|quote=In the lengthy and uncertain off-season, an unfair anointing was bestowed on the Yankees. To emphasize the sense of loss with no World Series, many columnists kept referring to the dates in October when the Yankees might have played a Series game. This kind of reference occurred so often, fans may have gotten the idea the Yankees were a lock for the Series. An unforeseen stumble on the way to the playoffs or in one of the newly expanded rounds of postseason play was out of the question.}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;BuckShowalter&quot;&gt;{{cite news|last=Amore|first=Dom|title=Imagine: [[Buck Showalter|Buck]]'s Yankees, But Not [[Derek Jeter|Jeter]]'s|newspaper=[[The Hartford Courant]]|date=May 15, 2005|page=E8}}&lt;/ref&gt; The Yankees won the American League Wild Card in 1995, but lost the [[1995 American League Division Series|ALDS]] to the [[Seattle Mariners]] in five games. They returned to the World Series in {{wsy|1996}} and defeated the returning champion [[Atlanta Braves]] in six games. This was the first World Series victory in a new Yankees dynasty managed by former Met manager [[Joe Torre]] and included career-long Yankees [[Mariano Rivera]], [[Jorge Posada]], and then rookie [[Derek Jeter]].  It also included future Yankee skipper [[Joe Girardi]]. Besides Torre, the 1996 Yankees included several former Met stars, including pitchers [[Dwight Gooden]] and [[David Cone]], who played for the Mets in the 1988 NLCS, and slugger [[Darryl Strawberry]], who had been on the 1986 Mets team that won the World Series.

===Mayor's Trophy===
Before the creation of [[Interleague]] play, teams from the National League never played teams from the American League in official games except during the World Series. The Yankees and Mets occasionally met in spring training exhibition games and from 1963 to 1983 played annually in the Mayor's Trophy Game, an in-season exhibition game, where the Yankees posted a record of 10–8–1 over the Mets.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title=Yankees-Mets Spring Series|newspaper=The New York Times|date=December 6, 1989|page=D30}}&lt;/ref&gt;

;Mayor's Trophy Game Results

{| class=&quot;wikitable sortable&quot;
! Date !! Result !! Location
|-
|{{dts|June 20, 1963}}
|Mets 6, Yankees 2 || [[Yankee Stadium]]
|-
|{{dts|August 24, 1964}}
|Yankees 6, Mets 4 || [[Shea Stadium]]
|-
|{{dts|May 3, 1965}}
|Mets 2, Yankees 1 || [[Yankee Stadium]]
|-
|{{dts|June 27, 1966}}
|Yankees 5, Mets 2 || [[Shea Stadium]]
|-
|{{dts|July 12, 1967}}
|Mets 4, Yankees 0 || [[Yankee Stadium]]
|-
|{{dts|May 27, 1968}}
|Mets 4, Yankees 3 || [[Shea Stadium]]
|-
|{{dts|September 29, 1969}}
|Mets 7, Yankees 6 || [[Shea Stadium]]
|-
|{{dts|August 17, 1970}}
|Yankees 9, Mets 4 || [[Yankee Stadium]]
|-
|{{dts|September 9, 1971}}
|Yankees 2, Mets 1 || [[Shea Stadium]]
|-
|{{dts|August 24, 1972}}
|Yankees 2, Mets 1 || [[Yankee Stadium]]
|-
|{{dts|May 10, 1973}}
|Mets 8, Yankees 4  || [[Shea Stadium]]
|-
|{{dts|May 30, 1974}}
|Yankees 9, Mets 4 || [[Shea Stadium]]
|-
|{{dts|May 15, 1975}}
|Yankees 9, Mets 4 || [[Shea Stadium]]
|-
|{{dts|June 14, 1976}}
|Yankees 8, Mets 4 || [[Yankee Stadium]]
|-
|{{dts|June 23, 1977}}
|Mets 6, Yankees 4 || [[Shea Stadium]]
|-
|{{dts|April 27, 1978}}
|Yankees 4, Mets 3 || [[Yankee Stadium]]
|-
|{{dts|April 16, 1979}}
|Mets 1, Yankees 1 || [[Shea Stadium]]
|-
|{{dts|May 27, 1982}}
|Mets 4, Yankees 1 || [[Yankee Stadium]]
|-
|{{dts|April 21, 1983}}
|Yankees 4, Mets 1 || [[Shea Stadium]]
|}

==1997–1999: Interleague regular season play begins==
===1997–1998: First official games===
In {{By|1997}}, Major League Baseball scheduled official regular season games between the American and National Leagues for the first time. On June 16, the Mets and Yankees played their first official game at Yankee Stadium, which the Mets won 6–0 behind [[Dave Mlicki]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title=The First Brag Belongs to Mlicki and the Mets|date=June 17, 1997|first=Murray|last=Chass|newspaper=New York Times|page=B9|authorlink=Murray Chass}}&lt;/ref&gt; The Yankees won the next two games for a series win.  The Mets  acquired [[Mike Piazza]] for the 1998 season and made a run for the playoffs, but were eliminated in the last regular game series of the season by the Atlanta Braves.  The Yankees won that year's interleague series at Shea Stadium two games to one, and would also win the [[1998 World Series]], the first of three straight titles for them. David Cone won 20 games in 1998 for the Yankees, just 10 years after he accomplished the same feat for the Mets, becoming the first and only player to win 20 games for both teams.

These interleague games between the Mets and Yankees would come to be referred to as a [[Subway Series]], extending the use of that phrase outside the historical context of an all-New York World Series.

===1999: Both teams reach the playoffs===
In 1999, Major League Baseball expanded Interleague play, allowing the Mets and Yankees to host a series at their home stadiums. At Shea, the Mets won their first series against the Yankees, 2 games to 1, though the regular season series was tied by virtue of a Yankees series win (2 to 1) at Yankee Stadium earlier that year. That year marked the first time both teams reached the playoffs in the same season, though the Mets needed an [[1999 National League Wild Card tie-breaker game|extra game]] for their first playoff appearance since losing the [[1988 National League Championship Series]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title=The Mets Eliminate Cincinnati, The Doubts and the Frustration|date=October 5, 1999|first=Judy|last=Battista|newspaper=New York Times|page=A1}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Both the Mets and Yankees reached their respective League Championship Series and played their respective rivals. The Mets were defeated by their [[Braves–Mets rivalry|division rival]] [[Atlanta Braves]] in [[1999 National League Championship Series|their LCS]],&lt;ref name=2000WorldSeries/&gt; while the Yankees defeated [[Yankees – Red Sox rivalry|long time rival]] [[Boston Red Sox]] in  [[1999 ALCS|that year's ALCS]].  The Yankees then swept the Braves in the [[1999 World Series]] for their 25th franchise title.

==2000: World Series meeting==
{{main|2000 World Series}}
During the regular season on July 8, 2000, the Yankees defeated the Mets by identical 4-2 scores in both ends of an unusual day-night doubleheader. With the first game played at [[Shea Stadium]] and the nightcap at [[Yankee Stadium (1923)|Yankee Stadium]], it was the first time since [[1903 in baseball|1903]] that two teams played two games in different stadiums on the same day. [[Dwight Gooden]] won the first game with a six inning effort in his first start since returning to the Yankees. [[Roger Clemens]] won the nightcap.&lt;ref name=&quot;july8a&quot;&gt;[http://sportsillustrated.cnn.com/baseball/mlb/2000/world_series/news/2000/10/19/season_series_ap/ Mets-Yankees season series recap] at sportsillustrated.cnn.com, URL accessed January 1, 2011. [http://www.webcitation.org/5vQUUrmEV Archived] 01-01-11&lt;/ref&gt; However, in the second game of that double header, an event occurred that made the rivalry between the two teams more contentious. Clemens hit Mets' star [[Mike Piazza]] in the helmet with an inside fastball, causing Piazza to suffer a [[concussion]] and placing him on the disabled list.&lt;ref name=&quot;july8b&quot;&gt;[http://sportsillustrated.cnn.com/vault/gallery/featured/GAL1155798/3/8/index.htm Interleague Play Memorable Moments (Photo 3 of 8)] at sportsillustrated.cnn.com, URL accessed January 1, 2011. [http://www.webcitation.org/5vQUf9ZZx Archived] 01-01-2011&lt;/ref&gt;

The Mets and Yankees returned to the playoffs that year and won their respective pennants, meeting in the [[2000 World Series]] for their first championship contest. It was the Yankees' fourth appearance in five years and the Mets' first appearance since winning the title in {{wsy|1986}}. It was the first [[Subway Series]] World Series since {{wsy|1956}}. Game 1 went to extra innings in what was then the longest World Series game of all time, with the Yankees winning on a walk-off hit by former Met [[José Vizcaíno]].

Controversy ensued in Game 2 when Yankees pitcher [[Roger Clemens]] faced Mets catcher [[Mike Piazza]] for the first time since the hit-by-pitch earlier that season. In the match-up, Piazza shattered his bat after fouling off one of Clemens' pitches, and the splintered bathead hurtled towards the mound. Clemens threw the bathead towards the baseline and nearly hit Piazza who had been running down the foul line. The incident caused both benches to clear.  The Yankees won the game 6-5.

The Mets won Game 3, snapping the Yankees' fourteen game winning streak in World Series play dating back to 1996 and Yankee hurler Orlando &quot;El Duque&quot; Hernandez's previously undefeated postseason record (6–0). However, this would prove to be the only high point for the Mets. [[Derek Jeter]] hit a home run on the very first pitch of Game 4, immediately shifting momentum back to the Yankees who would win the game. Footage of this home run currently serves as the background for the title screen of YES Network's &quot;[[Yankeeography]]&quot; series.  Despite no game in the series being decided by more than two runs, the Yankees would only require five games to beat the Mets. [[Al Leiter]], a former Yankee prospect, would take the mound for the Mets in Game 5 and lose.  The Yankees clinched their third straight World Series championship when Mariano Rivera got Mike Piazza to pop up for the final out of Game 5. 

[[World Series MVP]] Derek Jeter said of the Mets: &quot;In my opinion, the Mets were the toughest team we have played in my five years here.  Every one of these games could have gone either way. They could have given up after [losing] the first two games, but they never quit. You can't say enough about the New York Mets.&quot;  &lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
  | last = Schmuck
  | first = Peter
  | title = Threepeat
  | work = 
  | publisher = Baltimore Sun
  | date = October 27, 2000
  | url = http://articles.baltimoresun.com/2000-10-27/sports/0010300264_1_luis-sojo-derek-jeter-subway-series
  | accessdate = October 15, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The 12.4 television rating and 21 share of the 2000 World Series was the worst in history when it was played.&lt;ref name=Ratings&gt;{{cite news|title=Subway Series the Lowest-Rated|date=October 27, 2000|first=Howard|last=Fendrich|agency=Associated Press}}&lt;/ref&gt; For the Mets, the 12.4 rating was less than half of what they were when during their previous appearance, when Game 7 drew a 38.9 rating and 55 share.

Both teams thanked the [[St. Louis Cardinals]] for this series.&lt;ref name=2000WorldSeries&gt;{{cite book|title=The subway series: the Yankees, the Mets and a season to remember|year=2000|publisher=The Sporting News|location=St. Louis, Mo.|isbn=0-89204-659-7}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title=From Wild Card to World Series|date=October 17, 2000|first=Murray|last=Chass|newspaper=New York Times|authorlink=Murray Chass}}&lt;/ref&gt; Their sweep of the [[Atlanta Braves]] in the [[2000 National League Division Series|NLDS]] made the Mets' run to the World Series much easier.&lt;ref name=2000WorldSeries/&gt; The Braves had eliminated the Mets from the playoffs on the final day of the {{mlby|1998}} season and in the [[1999 National League Championship Series|1999 NLCS]].&lt;ref name=2000WorldSeries/&gt;

==2001–2008: The rivalry continues in the 21st century==
{{Prose|section|date=June 2011}}
[[Image:Subway Series 2008.jpg|thumb|upright|Subway Series 2008, [[Johnny Damon]] with the Yankees (left) and [[Brian Schneider]] with the Mets]]
[[Image:YankeeSheaDay 033.jpg|thumb|upright|A Subway Series game at [[Shea Stadium]] on 6/27/2008, with [[Citi Field]] under construction beyond the outfield.]]
[[Image:436 Yankee Stadium.jpg|thumb|upright|A full house at [[Yankee Stadium (1923)|Yankee Stadium]] for a Subway Series game against the Mets on 6/16/2007.]]
[[Image:Alex Rodriguez 2008-08-22.jpg|thumb|upright|Alex Rodriguez plays for the Yankees, but grew up as a fan of the New York Mets.]]
The 2000 championship was the Yankees' last title until their [[2009 World Series]] win. Since their appearance in 2000, the Mets would have several losing seasons until the emergence of [[David Wright (baseball)|David Wright]] and [[José Reyes (shortstop)|José Reyes]].

*In {{mlby|2001}}, there was a moment of peace in the rivalry in the aftermath of [[September 11 attacks|the attacks in New York City]]. During the weekend of September 21–23, [[Shea Stadium]] hosted the first professional sporting event in New York City since the attacks when the Mets hosted the [[Atlanta Braves]] while [[Yankee Stadium (1923)|Yankee Stadium]] hosted a special memorial service titled &quot;Prayer for America.&quot;

* On June 15, {{mlby|2002}}, Roger Clemens faced the Mets for the first time at Shea Stadium since the Piazza controversy. Anticipation mounted about retalliation against Clemens. Mets manager [[Bobby Valentine]] chided Clemens by saying he wore a &quot;skirt&quot; when compared to past pitchers who threw hard at people like [[Bob Gibson]] and [[Don Drysdale]] because Clemens did not have to bat in the American League. When the game arrived, Clemens was forced to bat and Mets pitcher [[Shawn Estes]] attempted to hit Clemens in retaliation but instead threw a pitch behind Clemens, prompting the home plate umpire to warn both benches. Estes later homered off of Clemens as the Mets won the game 8-0. &lt;ref&gt;http://articles.nydailynews.com/2000-10-19/sports/18145129_1_beaning-of-mike-piazza-ancient-history-feelings&lt;/ref&gt;

* {{mlby|2003}} – the Yankees become the first and, as of [[2011 Major League Baseball season|2011]], only team to sweep the season series, winning all six games, including a two-park day-night doubleheader.

* {{mlby|2004}} – the Mets win the season series for the first time, going 4–2 and sweep the three games at [[Shea Stadium]].

* In 2005, the Mets signed Manager [[Willie Randolph]], who coached with the Yankees for over a decade. Randolph played much of his career with the Yankees and also played for the Mets before retiring as a player. Because of his history with the Yankees championship teams of the 70s (as a player) and the 90s (as a coach), he holds a very cordial relationship with Yankee fans despite his tenure with the Mets organization, as noted by a [[Subway (restaurant)|Subway]] (a pun on the restaurant's name and the Subway Series) commercial featuring him and former Yankees manager [[Joe Torre]], who had managed the Yankees during their most recent dynastic run. Torre had also been associated with the Mets as they were the last team he ever played for and the first team he ever managed. On August 2, 2008, less than two months after his abrupt and controversial dismissal as Mets manager, Randolph was greeted with a [[standing ovation]] by the Yankee Stadium crowd when he appeared in a Yankees uniform for the [[Old-Timers' Day|Old-Timers' Game]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://newyork.yankees.mlb.com/news/article.jsp?ymd=20080802&amp;content_id=3240619&amp;vkey=news_nyy&amp;fext=.jsp&amp;c_id=nyy|title=Randolph returns for Yanks 'reunion'|date=August 2, 2008|first=Bryan|last=Hoch|work=Yankees.MLB.com|publisher=Major League Baseball}}&lt;/ref&gt;

* On June 26, 2005,  the Mets won their first series at Yankee Stadium and were three outs from a sweep when [[Jason Giambi]]'s bases loaded single off of [[Braden Looper]] in the ninth drove home the tying and winning runs for the Yankees, who forced a season series split with the Mets.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.baseball-reference.com/boxes/NYA/NYA200506260.shtml|title=Sunday, June 26, 2005 8:09PM, Yankee Stadium II|work=Baseball-Reference.com|publisher=Sports Publishing LLC}}&lt;/ref&gt;

* On May 19, 2006, in the first Subway Series of that year at Shea, the Yankees took the lead three times in the first four innings, but the Mets rallied each time against [[Randy Johnson]] and the game was tied 6-6 going into the bottom of the ninth. With two outs and runners on first and second, David Wright drives home the winning run for the Mets with a single off of Yankee ace [[Mariano Rivera]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.baseball-reference.com/boxes/NYN/NYN200605190.shtml|title=Friday, May 19, 2006 7:10PM, Shea Stadium|publisher=Sports Publishing LLC|work=Baseball-Reference.com}}&lt;/ref&gt;

* On May 20, 2006, less than 24 hours after the Mets' comeback win, [[Pedro Martinez]] and [[Duaner Sanchez]] kept the Yankees scoreless for eight winnings while the Mets score four runs off of [[Mike Mussina]]. In the top of the ninth, however, closer [[Billy Wagner]], who pitched a perfect ninth the night before to get the win, gave up four runs to tie the game and force extra innings. In the top of the 11th, [[Andy Phillips]] singled in the go-ahead run for the Yankees while Mariano Rivera pitched two shutout innings for the win.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.baseball-reference.com/boxes/NYN/NYN200605200.shtml|title=Saturday, May 20, 2006 1:25PM, Shea Stadium|publisher=Sports Publishing LLC|work=Baseball-Reference.com}}&lt;/ref&gt;

* History is made at the [[2006 Major League Baseball All-Star Game]] when two positions on both teams are manned by players from teams of the same city. [[David Wright (baseball)|David Wright]] and [[José Reyes (shortstop)|José Reyes]] started at third base and shortstop respectively for the National League while [[Alex Rodriguez]] and [[Derek Jeter]] started at the same respective positions for the American League.

* Both teams in {{By|2006}} finished at the top of their division in the same season for the first time in history. For the Yankees, this was their ninth straight division title, while the Mets won their first division title since [[1988 New York Mets season|1988]]. Despite sharing baseball's best regular season record (97-65), they would have disappointing postseasons as both lost enroute to the two teams that eventually met in that year's [[2006 World Series|World Series]], the [[Detroit Tigers]] and [[St. Louis Cardinals]].

* The teams' inverse success relationship was highlighted in {{By|2007}}. On May 29, the Yankees were tied for last place and 14.5 games back of the [[Boston Red Sox]] while the Mets were in first place ahead of the [[Atlanta Braves]] by four games, with the lead being as high as seven in mid-September. A late season meltdown led to the Mets being eliminated from playoff contention, losing the NL East title to the [[Philadelphia Phillies]] on the last day of the season. On the other hand, the Yankees, though unable to finish first in the AL East for the first time since 1997, rebounded from their losing ways and clinched their 13th consecutive playoff berth.

* March 24, 2008: In an article written in the ''[[New York Daily News]]'', Alex Rodriguez said how he regretted signing with the [[Texas Rangers (baseball)|Texas Rangers]] (the team the Yankees acquired him from) in the first place and wished he had signed with the Mets rather than Texas. Rodriguez grew up a Met fan and former Met first baseman turned announcer [[Keith Hernandez]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://jockbio.com/Bios/ARod/ARod_bio.html |title=Alex Rodriguez |publisher=Jockbio |date=1975-07-27 |accessdate=2010-08-04}}&lt;/ref&gt; Rodriguez stated how he listened to his agent [[Scott Boras]] about taking more money instead and did not want to make the same mistake of not being on a team he liked playing for by leaving the Yankees.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.nydailynews.com/sports/baseball/yankees/2008/03/24/2008-03-24_arod_regrets_saying_no_to_mets_parts_wit.html| title = A-Rod regrets saying no to Mets, parts with Scott Boras to avoid same mistake | first = John|last=Harper | work = New York Daily News}} {{Dead link|date=August 2010|bot=RjwilmsiBot}}&lt;/ref&gt;

* June 27, 2008: In the first game of a two-stadium, day-night doubleheader against the Yankees, [[Carlos Delgado]] scores 9 RBIs (including a grand slam) in a 15–6 victory for the Mets, setting a team record for most RBIs in a single game and tying the record for most RBIs in a single game by a visiting player at [[Yankee Stadium (1923)|Yankee Stadium]].

* {{mlby|2008}} – For just the second time, the Mets win the season series against the Yankees, 4–2, including the Mets' first and only sweep at [[Yankee Stadium (1923)|the old Yankee Stadium]].

* The 2008 season marked the first time since 1993 that both the Yankees and Mets failed to qualify for postseason, the first time for the Yankees since that year and the second straight year where the Mets were eliminated on the last day of the season. It was also the last year both teams played at their old respective ballparks, [[Yankee Stadium (1923)|Yankee Stadium]] and [[Shea Stadium]]. [[Yogi Berra]] was present at the closing ceremonies of both stadiums. Both teams finished with the same record (89-73) that year.

==2009 to present: New stadiums ==
{{Prose|section|date=June 2011}}
The {{mlby|2009}} season was the first year that both teams played in their new stadiums, Mets at [[Citi Field]] and the Yankees at the new [[Yankee Stadium]]. The Yankees took it one step further opened their new stadium with their 27th World Series championship against the [[Philadelphia Phillies]], the [[2008 World Series|defending champions]], becoming the first team to inaugurate two stadiums with World Series wins.

* June 12, 2009: Both teams played each other for the first time at the new Yankee Stadium. The game had several lead changes, including [[Mariano Rivera]] giving up the go ahead run to the Mets in the 8th. In the bottom of the 9th, after Derek Jeter stole 2nd base and [[Mark Texiera]] was intentionally walked, the Mets new closer [[Francisco Rodríguez (baseball, born 1982)|Francisco Rodriguez]] (K-Rod) paired off against Alex Rodriguez (A-Rod). In what seemed a routine pop with two outs, Mets 2nd baseman and three time [[Rawlings Gold Glove Award|gold glove]] award winner [[Luis Castillo (baseball)|Luis Castillo]] dropped the ball. Texiera wound up scoring the winning run all the way from first on the error. It would prove to be the Yankees' 7th walk off game that season and the first statistical blown save for K-Rod as a Met. After the game, injured Yankees pitcher [[Brian Bruney]] criticized K-Rod and his animated behavior on the mound to reporters. &quot;[It] couldn't have happened to a better guy on the mound, either,&quot; said Bruney. &quot;He's got a tired act. ... He gets what he deserves, man. I just don't like watching the guy pitch. I think it's embarrassing.&quot; Rodriguez responded, &quot;Instead of sending a message in the paper, next time when he sees me at [[Citi Field]], come up to me and say it. Don't be sending a message to the media. I don't even know who that guy is, somewhere in Double-A and not even pitching one full season.&quot; &lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url=http://mlb.mlb.com/news/article.jsp?ymd=20090613&amp;content_id=5308050&amp;vkey=news_mlb&amp;fext=.jsp&amp;c_id=mlb|title=K-Rod, Bruney trade barbs over antics |publisher=MLB.com|date=June 13, 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt;

* June 14, 2009 – Francisco Rodriguez confronts Bruney during batting practice and are separated by teammates. The Yankees shutout the Mets 15–0 in the biggest blowout in the history of the series, tagging Met ace Johan Santana for nine runs in {{frac|3|1|3}} innings, the most Santana has ever allowed in his career.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.nydailynews.com/blogs/mets/2009/06/k-rod-bruney-hostility-continu.html|title=K-Rod, Bruney hostility continues|date=June 14, 2009|first=Adam|last=Rubin|work=New York Daily News|publisher=nydailynews.com}}&lt;/ref&gt;

* June 26, 2009 – The two teams played each other for the first time at Citi Field. Alex Rodriguez hit his 564th home run, moving past [[Reggie Jackson]] into 11th place on the career home run list. The Yankees defeat the Mets 9–1 after the Mets had committed three errors that led to four runs in the second inning, the most ever against the Yankees.

* June 28, 2009 – Yankees closer Mariano Rivera, who entered the game to face a batter in the 8th inning, bats against Mets closer Francisco Rodriguez at the top of the 9th inning. Rivera drew a walk with the bases loaded, forcing home [[Brett Gardner]] to earn his first career [[RBI]].  Rivera would go on to finish the game and earn his 500th career save as the Yankees swept the series at Citi Field.

* May 22, 2010 - The Mets win their first Subway Series game at Citi Field with a 5-3 victory over the Yankees.

* June 20, 2010 - The Yankees earn their 9,500th franchise victory with a 4-0 win over the Mets. [[Mark Texiera]] provided the only runs of the game with a third inning grand slam off of [[Johan Santana]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.pinstripealley.com/2010/6/20/1527339/new-york-yankees-4-new-york-mets-0|title=New York Yankees 4, New York Mets 0: What A Grand Win|date=June 20, 2010|author=Brandon C.|work=PinstripeAlley.com}}&lt;/ref&gt;

* July 3, 2011 -  The Mets, down to their final strike and on the verge of getting swept at Citi Field by the Yankees for the second time in three years, tie the final game of that year's Subway Series against [[Mariano Rivera]] in the bottom of the ninth on an RBI single from [[Ronny Paulino]]. In 23 previous save opportunities against the Mets, spanning the regular season and the [[2000 World Series]], Rivera had converted 22 &lt;ref name=&quot;TimesRivera&quot;/&gt; (his only previous blown save against the team was on July 10, 1999 &lt;ref&gt;http://www.baseball-reference.com/boxes/NYN/NYN199907100.shtml&lt;/ref&gt;). The Mets would win in the 10th inning on an RBI single from [[Jason Bay]], who had been struggling all season, off of former Met pitcher [[Luis Ayala]].&lt;ref name=&quot;DailyNewsBay&quot;/&gt; Manager [[Terry Collins]] called the game &quot;enormous.&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;TimesRivera&quot;&gt;{{cite news| url=http://www.nytimes.com/2011/07/04/sports/baseball/mets-salvage-finale-of-subway-series.html?_r=1&amp;pagewanted=print|title=When All Seems Lost, Mets Rally to Win|first=Ben|last=Shpigel|newspaper=The New York Times|date=July 4, 2011|page=D1}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;DailyNewsBay&quot;&gt;{{cite web | url=http://www.nydailynews.com/sports/baseball/mets/2011/07/03/2011-07-03_jason_bay_delivers_rbi_single_in_10th_as_mets_come_back_against_mariano_rivera__.html?r=topnews |title=Jason Bay delivers RBI single in 10th as Mets come back against Mariano Rivera &amp; Yankees, 3-2|author=Roger Rubin|publisher=NY Daily News|date=July 3, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; The Yankees still won the season series 4 games to 2.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://scores.espn.go.com/mlb/recap?gameId=310703121|title=Jason Bay lifts Mets by Yankees in 10 to avoid sweep|date=July 3, 2011|author=Associated Press|work=ESPN.com}}&lt;/ref&gt;

* July 12, 2011 - Days after gaining entry into the [[3,000 hit club]], Yankee shortstop [[Derek Jeter]] elected to sit out of the [[2011 Major League Baseball All-Star Game]] citing &quot;physical and emotional exhaustion&quot; and recovery from a recent visit to the disabled list. Jeter, who throughout his career had been praised by people in and out of baseball for good behavior, was criticized by some players and officials including Mets outfielder [[Carlos Beltran]]. Beltran stated that &quot;I do believe, as a ballplayer, if you have no injuries, you should be here...the fans are the ones that vote for you and want to see you here.&quot; Mets shortstop [[José Reyes (shortstop)|José Reyes]], who also was injured, also opined on the incident saying &quot;I want to come no matter what happens.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://espn.go.com/new-york/mlb/story/_/id/6761243/new-york-yankees-derek-jeter-skips-all-star-festivities-creates-stir|title=Derek Jeter All-Star decision causes stir|date=July 12, 2011|work=ESPNNewYork.com}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Fan demographics==
In 1998, the Independent Budget Office of the city of New York published a study on the economic effect of the city's two Major League Baseball teams. The study included an analysis of where fans of both the Mets and the Yankees resided. The study found that 39% of Mets fans lived in one of the five boroughs of New York, 49% in the tri-state area outside the city and 12% elsewhere. Mets fans were more likely to be found in [[Queens]], [[Brooklyn]], [[Staten Island]], and the [[Long Island]] counties of [[Nassau County, New York|Nassau]] and [[Suffolk County, New York|Suffolk]], whereas [[Manhattan]], [[the Bronx]], [[New Jersey]], [[Connecticut]], and the counties of [[Westchester County, New York|Westchester]] and [[Rockland County, New York|Rockland]], as well as the upper Hudson Valley and the upstate New York region, leaned more towards the Yankees.&lt;ref name=&quot;IBO&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.ibo.nyc.ny.us/iboreports/stadiumsurvey.html|title=Home Base for Mets and Yankees Fans|publisher=The City of New York Independent Budget Office|date=1998-09-28}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Fans of other New York City teams===
{{see also|Sports in New York City}}
Historically, Yankees fans tend to root for the [[New York Giants]] (who once played in Yankee Stadium) and the [[New York Rangers]] (all three being the older, more established teams), while Mets fans tend to root for the [[New York Jets]] (who once played in Shea Stadium) and [[New York Islanders]].&lt;ref name=NYCTeams&gt;{{cite web|url=http://sports.espn.go.com/espn/print?id=2449846&amp;type=story|title=Yankees, Mets coexist despite their differences|first=John|last=Helyar|publisher =ESPN|date=May 19, 2006}}&lt;/ref&gt; However, rivalries have made Yankees fans root for the Jets (both teams have intense rivalries with [[Sports in Boston|Boston]], as the fierce [[Yankees – Red Sox rivalry]] has led to the rivalry between the [[Jets–Patriots rivalry|New York Jets and the New England Patriots]] and the [[National Basketball Association rivalries|New York Knicks and the Boston Celtics]]),&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title=Baseball's Fault Lines Show Stress In Arizona|date=February 2, 2008|first=Dan|last=Steinberg|newspaper=The Washington Post|page=E11|url=http://www.washingtonpost.com/wp-dyn/content/article/2008/02/01/AR2008020103259_pf.html}}&lt;/ref&gt; while the Mets fans [[Mets–Phillies rivalry|rivalry]] with the [[Philadelphia Phillies]] translates into a greater sports rivalry with [[Sports in Philadelphia|Philadelphia]] between the [[Eagles–Giants rivalry|New York Giants and the Philadelphia Eagles]] and the [[Flyers–Rangers rivalry|New York Rangers and the Philadelphia Flyers]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title=A City's Hopes Fly High on the Wings of Eagles|date=January 5, 2001|first=Peter|last=Mucha|newspaper=Philadelphia Inquirer|page=A1|quote=New York teams&amp;mdash;the Mets, Rangers, Giants and Knicks&amp;mdash;rank among Philadelphia's most loathed rivals.}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Rivalry outside of baseball==
Outside of Major League Baseball, the teams rivalry has shown passions from fans of both sides.

*In the movie ''[[Two Weeks Notice]]'', [[Sandra Bullock]] and [[Hugh Grant]]'s characters Lucy Kelson and George Wade attended a Mets game. When an opposing player hit a pop-fly and Mets catcher Mike Piazza went towards the stands to get it, Lucy reached over and stole the pop fly from Piazza, preventing him from getting the player out. Piazza quipped saying she should be a Yankee fan.
*During the 2000 World Series, the [[Mayor of New York City]], [[Rudy Giuliani]], showed no remorse in his partisan support of the Yankees despite being the sitting mayor in office, though he had attended Mets games before and after. Examples of this include the Mets opened the 1996 season, he threw out the ceremonial first pitch along with the [[Governor of New York]] [[George Pataki]],&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title=For the '96 Mets, an upbeat start|date=April 2, 1996|first=Tom|last=Withers|agency=Associated Press|quote=New York Governor George Pataki and New York City Mayor Rudolph Giuliani threw out ceremonial first pitches, and actress [[Glenn Close]] sang the national anthem.}}&lt;/ref&gt; during the Mets' season opener in {{mlby|1998}},&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title=Mets win Opener in Extra Innings&amp;mdash;&amp; Heat|date=April 1, 1998|first=Virgina|last=Breen|first2=Martin|last2=Mbugua|coauthors=Siemaszko, Corky|newspaper=New York Daily News|page=Sports.7|quote=Mayor Giuliani, the city's No. 1 Yankee fan, was greeted by mixed cheers and boos as he made his way to his box seat at Shea. But his smile never wavered...'I'm a Yankee fan overall, but I root for the Mets in the National League, certainly against the [[Philadelphia Phillies|Phillies]],' Giuliani said.}}&lt;/ref&gt; and when the Mets hosted the first professional sporting event in New York since September 11, 2001.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title=Changing His Pinstripes|date=September 22, 2001|first=Jennifer|last=Steinhauer|newspaper=New York Times|page=B10}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*In 2010, pop star singer and Yankee fan [[Lady Gaga]], attended a Mets game at Citi Field with the San Diego Padres where she gave Met fans [[the middle finger]]. Actor and comedian [[Jerry Seinfeld]], a Met fan, criticized Gaga for the incident due to children being at the game and became upset knowing that she had done the action from his personal luxury box.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Jerry Seinfeld: Lady Gaga 'Is A Jerk.'|work=The Huffington Post|date=June 22, 2010|accessdate=Feb. 15, 2011|url=http://www.huffingtonpost.com/2010/06/22/jerry-seinfeld-lady-gaga_n_621224.html}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==See also==
*[[Subway Series]]
*[[Major League Baseball rivalries]]

==References==
{{Reflist|colwidth=30em}}

{{Navboxes|list1=
{{New York Mets}}
{{New York Yankees}}
{{2000 New York Yankees}}
{{MLB rivalries}}
{{Subway Series}}
}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Mets–Yankees Rivalry}}
[[Category:Baseball in New York City]]
[[Category:New York Mets]]
[[Category:New York Yankees]]
[[Category:Interleague play]]
[[Category:Major League Baseball rivalries]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
