<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="13151101" ns="0" title="Glaiza de Castro"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Infobox person
| name = '''Glaiza de Castro'''
| image = Glaiza de Castro.jpg
| caption = 
| birth_date = {{Birth date and age|1988|1|21}}
| birth_place = [[Valenzuela City]], [[Philippines]]
| birth_name = Glaiza Galura De Castro
| occupation = Actress, singer
| Instrument = Vocals
| Genre = [[Pop music|pop]], [[Rhythm and blues|R&amp;B]]
| yearsactive = 2001-present
}}

'''Glaiza Galura de Castro''' (born January 21, 1988 in [[Valenzuela City]], [[Philippines]]), better known as '''Glaiza de Castro''', is a [[Filipino people|Filipina]] actress and singer. She is currently working for [[GMA-7]], where she has been performing since 2006.

After beginning her career in GMA in 2001, she transferred to its rival network, [[ABS-CBN]], where she played mostly minor and supporting roles before returning to GMA in 2006. During the first two years of her second stint with GMA, she continued to play supporting roles in series such as ''[[Boys Nxt Door]]'' and ''[[Asian Treasures]]'' before landing a lead role in the television remake of the film ''[[Kaputol ng Isang Awit]]''. She appeared in villain roles in the remakes of ''[[Kung Aagawin Mo Ang Lahat Sa Akin]]'' and ''[[Stairway to Heaven (TV series)|Stairway to Heaven]]'', and on the musical series ''[[Diva (Philippine TV series)|Diva]]'' before finally achieving leading lady status in the fantasy series ''[[Grazilda]]'' in 2010. In addition to her television appearances, she has also acted in a number of mainstream and independent films, including ''[[Sukob]]'', ''Batanes'', and ''Still Life''.

As a singer, de Castro has so far released two albums: ''Magbalik Ka'', released in 2001, and the self-titled ''Glaiza'', released in 2006.

==Early life and work==
Glaiza de Castro was born on January 21, 1988, in [[Valenzuela City]], a city in the northern part of the Philippines' [[National Capital Region]], to a family of [[born-again]] [[Baptists]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Inquirer.net&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url=http://showbizandstyle.inquirer.net/entertainment/entertainment/view/20090310-193234/Glaiza-warned-against-Patrick |title=
Glaiza warned against Patrick |author=Marinel Cruz|publisher=[[Philippine Daily Inquirer]]|date=March 10, 2009|accessdate=November 21, 2009 }}&lt;/ref&gt; Her parents are both musicians who have performed in countries all across Asia. Her uncle, Dan Alvaro, and her brother, Alchris Galura, are also actors. As a child, de Castro sang at her local ministry as a member of a children's choir; later on, in [[high school]], she formed a band with her friends, where she acted as both songwriter and vocalist.&lt;ref name=&quot;Telebisyon.net&quot;&gt;{{tl icon}} {{cite web |url=http://telebisyon.net/balita/Big-time-na-si-Glaiza-de-Castro/artikulo/24189/|title=
iGMA: Big time na si Glaiza de Castro |author=George Vail Kabristante|publisher=Taliba|date=June 23, 2008|accessdate=November 20, 2009 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

de Castro began her career in show business between the ages of 12 to 13 by appearing as an [[film extra|extra]]. She had several appearances on the late-night [[talk show]], ''[[Walang Tulugan with the Master Showman]]'', which was followed by a role in the 2001 movie ''Cool Dudes 24/7''&lt;ref name=&quot;Telebisyon.net&quot;&gt;{{tl icon}}{{cite web |url=http://telebisyon.net/balita/Big-time-na-si-Glaiza-de-Castro/artikulo/24189/|title=
iGMA: Big tim na si Glaiza de Castro |author=George Vail Kabristante|publisher=Taliba|date=June 23, 2008|accessdate=November 20, 2009 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;&quot;Bata pa ako noon, may shooting sa tabi ng church namin. I think Eddie Garcia film yun... Sabi ko sa ate ko, kailangan daw nila ng extra. Ayaw niya, ako na lang daw. So balik na naman ako. Sabi ko ayaw ng ate ko, sabi niya, ikaw gusto mo bang mag-artista? Sabi ko, ok. Mga 12 or 13 years old ako noon.&quot; ... &quot;Pero hindi nagtuloy-tuloy yun kasi we met a lot of talent scouts who turned out to be namemera lang... Until nakapasok ako sa GMA, sa Master Showman, then nag-Cool Dudes ako and then I had several guestings sa GMA.&quot; {{cite web |url=http://www.philstar.com/article.aspx?articleid=524455&amp;publicationsubcategoryid=51 |title=
Why viewers love to hate Glaiza de Castro |author=Vanessa A. Valbuena|publisher=The Freeman|date=November 18, 2009|accessdate=November 29, 2009 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Acting career==
===Early career: minor roles on television and in movies (2002-2006)===
de Castro began her career with [[GMA-7]] playing a minor role in the soap opera ''[[Ikaw Lang Ang Mamahalin]]''. However, after only a few months with the company, she transferred to rival network [[ABS-CBN]] and became a contracted artist of [[Star Magic]], the company's training ground for young talent. During her time in ABS-CBN, she continued to play both supporting and minor roles, two of the most prominent being the role of Halley in the teen-oriented show, ''[[Berks (TV series)|Berks]]'' and the role of Pinky in the teen-horror series, ''[[Spirits (TV series)|Spirits]]''.

Between 2002 and 2005, she would only appear in films sporadically, playing [[bit part]]s in movies such as ''Singsing ni Lola'' (2002) and ''Miss Pinoy'' (2005). By 2006, she began to appear in films more frequently, with minor parts in the horror films ''[[Sukob]]'' and ''[[White Lady (film)|White Lady]]'', as well as the [[Manny Pacquiao]] [[biopic]], ''[[Pacquiao: The Movie]]''. Her most prominent film role during this point in her career was as a minor antagonist in the film adaptation of [[Carlo Vergara]]'s [[graphic novel]], ''[[Zsazsa Zaturnnah]]''; the film was an entry to the 2006 [[Metro Manila Film Festival]].&lt;ref name=&quot;PEP.ph&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.pep.ph/news/11763/Glaiza-de-Castro-sees-Asian-Treasures-as-her-chance-to-be-known-not-as-Angel-Locsin|title=
Glaiza de Castro sees 'Asian Treasures' as her chance to be known not as Angel Locsin|author=Wells Avante|publisher=Philippine Entertainment Portal|date=January 4, 2007|accessdate=November 16, 2009 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Return to GMA and breakout roles (2006-2008)===
After four years with ABS-CBN, de Castro returned to its rival [[GMA Network]] in 2006. One of her first roles back was as Honey on the [[Fantaserye and telefantasya|fantasy-adventure]] series, ''[[Fantastikids]]'', where she starred alongside Marky Cielo, [[Jackie Rice]] and [[Ryza Cenon]], as well as former child star [[Paolo Contis]] and former [[beauty queen]] [[Melanie Marquez]]. The reception to the show was mostly warm; journalist Paul Daza of ''[[The Philippine Daily Inquirer]]'' compared it favorably to its counterpart on ABS-CBN (fantasy-drama [[anthology series|anthology]] ''[[Komiks (TV series)|Komiks]]''), and commented that, based on ratings, &quot;it would seem like the new [GMA-7] stars are outshining the more established [ABS-CBN] performers.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://services.inquirer.net/print/print.php?article_id=2370|title=
'Komiks' vs. 'Fantastikids!' |author=Paul Daza|date=May 21, 2006|accessdate=November 28, 2009 }}&lt;/ref&gt; At this time, she also performed regularly on GMA's regular Sunday [[variety show]], ''[[SOP Rules]]''.

In 2007, de Castro appeared in the afternoon [[teen drama]] ''[[Boys Nxt Door]]''.&lt;ref name=&quot;iGMA.tv&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.igma.tv/story/1331/Meet-the-Boys-Nxt-Door|title=
Meet the Boys Nxt Door|date=June 23, 2007|accessdate=November 28, 2009 }}&lt;/ref&gt; The series has been dubbed in [[Malay language|Malay]] on the [[Malaysia]]n channel [[8TV]] and became the first Filipino drama to air in [[South Korea]], via [[KBS2]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title= Defunct GMA-7 teen show &quot;Boys Nxt Door&quot; to air in Malaysia and South Korea. |url=http://www.pep.ph/news/16886/Defunct-GMA-7-teen-show-Boys-Nxt-Door-to-be-aired-in-Malaysia-and-South-Korea |author=Dinno Erece|publisher=Philippine Entertainment Portal |date=March 28, 2008|accessdate=December 11, 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt; The second role was in the 2007 action-adventure series, ''[[Asian Treasures]]'', GMA-7's most expensive show to date.&lt;ref name=&quot;Cerfin.net&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url=http://cerphin.net/balita/Robin-Padilla-and-Angel-Locsin-team-up-to-find-Asian-Treasures/artikulo/15440/|title=
Robin Padilla and Angel Locsin team up to find 'Asian Treasures' |author=Wells Avante|accessdate=November 16, 2009 }}&lt;/ref&gt; de Castro played Clara, an expert on history and geography who would use this knowledge to help the main characters find the titular treasures.&lt;ref name=&quot;PEP.ph&quot;/&gt;

2007 also saw her featured prominently in the [[independent film]] ''Still Life'', a film written and directed by Katski Flores, about an artist stricken with a [[terminal illness]] who has traveled to an isolated island to paint his last work. In the film, de Castro plays Emma, a woman who relates her past to the main character. Her portrayal of Emma was noted by film critic Tito Valiente of ''Business Mirror'' as &quot;one reason the short life on that island becomes very real.&quot; Valiente went on to note that de Castro's character was &quot;vulnerable but not whiny. Even in tears she conjures an image of a woman whose only way out of life is finding life in anything.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;Business Mirror.&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.businessmirror.com.ph/10162007/life03.html |title=
Moving: &quot;Still Life&quot; |author=Tito Valiente|accessdate=November 21, 2009 }} {{Dead link|date=October 2010|bot=H3llBot}}&lt;/ref&gt; The film was a [[finalist]] at that year's [[Cinemalaya Philippine Independent Film Festival]], where de Castro received a Golden Screen Awards nomination in the Best Actress category.&lt;ref name=&quot;Telebisyon.net&quot;&gt;{{tl icon}} {{cite web |url=http://telebisyon.net/balita/Big-time-na-si-Glaiza-de-Castro/artikulo/24189/|title=
iGMA: Big time na si Glaiza de Castro |author=George Vail Kabristante|accessdate=November 20, 2009 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{tl icon}} {{cite web |url=http://cerphin.net/balita/Glaiza-de-Castro-feels-fulfilled-in-doing-indie-films/source/14530/|title=
Glaiza de Castro feels fulfilled in doing indie films|author=Archie de Calma|date=May 12, 2008|accessdate=November 21, 2009 }}&lt;/ref&gt; She also played a supporting role that year in the romantic film ''Batanes'', alongside top GMA actress [[Iza Calzado]], [[Taiwanese people|Taiwanese]] singer-actor [[Ken Chu]], and Marky Cielo. The following year, 2008, she started shooting another independent film, ''Rakenrol''. The film is based on director Quark Henares' views on growing up in the local rock scene, as well as his own personal experiences in starting a band. de Castro described the film, which was still in production as of March 2009,&lt;ref name=&quot;Inquirer.net&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url=http://showbizandstyle.inquirer.net/entertainment/entertainment/view/20090310-193234/Glaiza-warned-against-Patrick |title=
Glaiza warned against Patrick |author=Marinel Cruz|work=[[Philippine Daily Inquirer]]|date=March 10, 2009|accessdate=November 21, 2009 }}&lt;/ref&gt; as &quot;a lighter version of ''[[Almost Famous]]'' and &quot;a fun, feel-good movie&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;Philstar.com&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.philstar.com/Article.aspx?articleId=30748 |title=
Glaiza off to a good start |author=Jerry Donato|publisher=[[The Philippine Star]]|date=December 1, 2007|accessdate=November 15, 2009 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

In 2008, she played the lead role in the television adaptation of the 1991 film, ''[[Kaputol ng Isang Awit]]''.&lt;ref name=&quot;PEP.ph&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.pep.ph/news/16348/Jolina-Magdangal-picks-Pinoy-Idol-over-Kaputol-Ng-Isang-Awit |title=
Jolina Magdangal pics 'Pinoy Idol over 'Kaputol ng Isang Awit' |author=Nora Calderon|accessdate=November 15, 2009 }}&lt;/ref&gt; In the series, de Castro played Sarah Monteza a poor girl with a good voice but low self-esteem. de Castro herself would later go on to say that the role was her &quot;biggest break&quot; thus far.&lt;ref&gt;{{tl icon}} {{cite web |url=http://www.pep.ph/news/16346/Glaiza-de-Castro-considers-Kaputol-Ng-Isang-Awit-a-make-or-break-project |title=Glaiza de Castro considers Kaputol ng Isang Awit a make-or-break project|author=Rose Garcia|publisher=Philippine Entertainment Portal|date=February 9, 2008|accessdate=November 29, 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.pep.ph/news/16636/TV-Ratings-(March-3-6):-Kaputol-ng-Isang-Awit-debuts-impressively|title=&quot;Kaputol ng Isang Awit&quot; debuts impressively|author=Bong Godinez|publisher=Philippine Entertainment Portal|date=March 7, 2008|accessdate=November 30, 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===2009-present===
After another supporting role in the television adaptation of comic-book writer [[Carlo J. Caparas]]' graphic novel ''[[Gagambino]]'', de Castro once again landed a lead role on another television adaptation of a Filipino film, ''[[Kung Aagawin Mo Ang Lahat Sa Akin]]'' opposite [[Patrick Garcia]], [[Maxene Magalona]], [[Jackie Rice]] and [[JC Tiuseco]]. In the series she played the primary antagonist, Gladys Andrada (a role originated by co-star [[Jackie Lou Blanco]]), the jealous, only biological child of Gilbert (played by [[Nonie Buencamino]]) and Clara Andrada (played by Blanco). Her portrayal was well-received; columnist Jason John Lim commented that while she knew she was breaking out of her comfort zone, &quot;What she didn't know that she would also begin breaking the expectations of everybody.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;GMA News.tv&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www8.gmanews.tv/story/170657/igma-glaiza-de-castro-gets-reborn-on-stairway-to-heaven |title=
iGMA: Glaiza de Castro gets reborn on ''Stairway to Heaven'' |author=Jason John S. Lim|publisher=GMANews.tv|date=August 25, 2009|accessdate=November 15, 2009 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

Right after ''[[Kung Aagawin Mo Ang Lahat Sa Akin]]'', she played another supporting role on an episode of the drama anthology [[SRO Cinemaserye]], which chronicled the life story of singer [[Eva Castillo]] (portrayed in this episode by [[Manilyn Reynes]]).&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.mb.com.ph/articles/213362/the-eva-castillo-story-continues-tonight|title='The Eva Castillo Story' continues tonight|author=Crispina Martinez Belen|publisher=[[Manila Bulletin]]|date=July 29, 2009|accessdate=December 13, 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt; Shortly thereafter, she landed another role as the primary antagonist in the Philippine remake of the widely-popular [[Korean wave|Korean]] television drama, ''[[Stairway to Heaven (TV series)|Stairway to Heaven]]'', alongside [[Dingdong Dantes]], [[Rhian Ramos]] and [[TJ Trinidad]]. She portrayed Eunice Manansala (serving as the counterpart for Han Yoori, played by actress [[Kim Tae-hee]]), the envious stepsister of Jodi Reyes (played by Rhian Ramos). To prepare for the role, de Castro watched the original series in order to attempt to get an idea of who her character was as a person.&lt;ref name=&quot;GMA News.tv&quot;/&gt; de Castro also commented on the relative complexity of her character in this series compared to her character in ''Kung Aagawin Mo Ang Lahat Sa Akin'': &quot;Unlike my previous role, you don’t know what is going on inside the mind of Eunice. What's going inside her head is really devious. She is subtle in her approach and very scheming... Despite being evil, she still has a heart and there's a reason she became a bad person. If she is stepping down on people, she is also being stepped on by other people. She also has to fulfill her needs and wants and she will do everything for the person she loves.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;MB.com&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.mb.com.ph/node/221714/glaiza-de-ca|title=
Glaiza de Castro: &quot;I'm not in love, yet&quot; |author=Walden Sadiri|publisher=[[Manila Bulletin]]|date=September 22, 2009|accessdate=November 15, 2009 }}&lt;/ref&gt; As with her two previous major roles, her portrayal was also well-received by critics; Jerry Donato of ''[[The Philippine Star]]'', in particular, has gone so far to say that &quot;So far, Glaiza has given her Korean counterpart a run for her money.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;Philstar.com&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.philstar.com/Article.aspx?articleId=519604&amp;publicationSubCategoryId=70|title=
Glaiza gives the contravida a new face |author=Jerry Donato|publisher=[[The Philippine Star]]|date=December 1, 2007|accessdate=November 15, 2009 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

In 2009, de Castro appeared in five films. In the first, the independent political thriller ''Bente''she replaced former ''[[StarStruck (Philippine TV series)|StarStruck]]'' contestant and fellow GMA star [[Jewel Mische]] when the latter refused to film a sex scene she considered &quot;beyond [her] moral standards&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;PEP.ph&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.pep.ph/articles/19070/(UPDATED)-Glaiza-de-Castro-steps-into-Jewel-Mische%27s-bed |title=
Glaiza de Castro steps into Jewel Mische's bed|author=Rose Garcia|publisher=Philippine Entertainment Portal|date=May 18, 2009|accessdate=November 21, 2009 }}&lt;/ref&gt; as directed by Mel Chionglo.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.pep.ph/guide/4155/Richard-Gomez-and-Jinggoy-Estrada-cast-in-political-thriller-Bente|title=
Richard Gomez and Jinggoy Estrada cast in political thriller Bente|author=Monica Palad|publisher=Philippine Entertainment Portal|date=June 24, 2009|accessdate=November 21, 2009 }}&lt;/ref&gt; The film was released in June 2009&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://showbizandstyle.inquirer.net/entertainment/entertainment/view/20090623-212064/Bente-challenges-Transformers |title=
'Bente' challenges 'Transformers|author=Bayani San Diego Jr.|publisher=[[Philippine Daily Inquirer]]|date=June 23, 2009|accessdate=November 30, 2009 }}&lt;/ref&gt; and received mixed reviews, with Rito Asilo of the ''Philippine Daily Inquirer'' citing its thematic substance and Gomez's and Calzado's &quot;insightful performances&quot;, while also going on to blast the film's &quot;disparate stories&quot;, &quot;incohesive feel and style&quot;, and sudden ending &quot;in a convenient anticlimax&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://services.inquirer.net/mobile/09/07/10/html_output/xmlhtml/20090710-214861-xml.html |title=Indies raise daunting questions|author=Rito Asilo|publisher=[[Philippine Daily Inquirer]]|date=July 10, 2009|accessdate=November 30, 2009 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

The second film was the horror movie ''Tarot'', released on August 26. The film, about a girl who is able to predict the future through the use of [[tarot]] cards, was directed by Jun Lana and was top-billed by [[Marian Rivera]] and [[Dennis Trillo]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.philstar.com/article.aspx?articleid=496633|title=The scary secrets of the tarot|publisher=[[The Philippine Star]]|date=August 17, 2009|accessdate=November 30, 2009 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

A third film, ''Ang Manghuhula'', was released commercially in September (it had been shown at the [[Cinemanila International Film Festival]] the previous year).&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.mb.com.ph/articles/218447/manghuhula-star-a-movie|title='Manghuhula' as the star of a movie|author=Crispina Martinez-Belen|publisher=[[Manila Bulletin]]|date=August 31, 2009|accessdate=November 30, 2009 }}&lt;/ref&gt; The film was directed by Paolo Herras and saw de Castro playing the daughter of Messina (played by [[Eula Valdez]]), a seer. The production was received warmly, with Noelani Torre of the ''Philippine Daily Inquirer'' noting its &quot;fascinating subject matter&quot;, &quot;colorful cast&quot; and &quot;visual richness and clarity&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://showbizandstyle.inquirer.net/entertainment/entertainment/view/20090904-223572/Community_of_fortune-tellers_comes_to_life |title=Community of fortune-tellers comes to life|author=Noelani Torre|publisher=[[Philippine Daily Inquirer]]|date=September 4, 2009|accessdate=November 30, 2009 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

The fourth film de Castro starred in that year was the independent film ''Astig'' (international title: ''Squalor'') alongside [[Sid Lucero]], [[Edgar Allan Guzman]], [[Arnold Reyes]] and [[Dennis Trillo]] (who also directed the film. In ''Astig'', de Castro playing Elgine, a teenager afflicted with a [[sexually transmitted disease]] who eventually becomes the love interest of Trillo's character.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.hollywoodreporter.com/hr/film-reviews/squalor-film-review-1004022772.story |title=
Squalor&amp;mdash;Film Review |author=Maggie Lee|date=October 15, 2009|accessdate=December 26, 2009 }} {{Dead link|date=October 2010|bot=H3llBot}}&lt;/ref&gt; The film, released in July of that year, was a critical and financial success, topping the box office in that year's Cinemalaya Film Festival, with a profit of P137,890.00.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://globalnation.inquirer.net/cebudailynews/news/view/20090726-217322/Astig-tops-Cinemalaya-box-office |title=
'Astig' tops Cinemalaya box office |author=Marinel Cruz|publisher=Inquirer.net|date=July 26, 2009|accessdate=November 29, 2009 }}&lt;/ref&gt; Darwin Chiong of GMANews.tv called the film's [[cinematography]] &quot;remarkable&quot; and praised the cast as a whole, saying, &quot;The movie gathers an ensemble of actors that deliver in the acting department, even those in supporting roles like Glaiza de Castro and Malou Crisologo.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.gmanews.tv/story/168469/film-review-astig |title=
Film review: 'Astig' |author=Darwin Chiong|publisher=GMANews.tv|date=July 28, 2009|accessdate=November 29, 2009 }}&lt;/ref&gt; Her performance in this film earned her a nomination in the Best Supporting Actress Category at the 33rd [[Gawad Urian]] Awards.&lt;ref name=Diva&gt;{{cite web |url=http://showbizandstyle.inquirer.net/entertainment/entertainment/view/20100214-253180/A-Glee-moment-for-Glaiza|title=A 'Glee' moment for Glaiza|author=Bayani San Diego Jr.|publisher=Inquirer.net|date=February 14, 2010|accessdate=February 27, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{citation | first = Butch| last = Francisco| title = Who are on the 33rd Gawad Urian list? | newspaper = The Philippine Star | date = 27 February 2010}}.&lt;/ref&gt;

The fifth film was the sixth film under the ''[[Mano Po 6: A Mother's Love|Mano Po]]'' banner, subtitled ''A Mother's Love''. The film, directed by [[Joel Lamangan]] and top-billed by Sharon Cuneta, [[Zsa Zsa Padilla]], [[Heart Evangelista]] and Dennis Trillo, saw de Castro playing a younger version of Cuneta's character, Melinda Uy.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.mb.com.ph/articles/235414/an-absorbing-story|title=An absorbing story|author=Mario E. Bautista|publisher=[[Manila Bulletin]]|date=December 23, 2009|accessdate=December 26, 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt; The film was released on 25 December and was an entry to that year's annual Metro Manila Film Festival.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.malaya.com.ph/11302009/ent1.html|title='Mano Po 6' budget reaches P70M because of Beijing shoot|publisher=Malaya.com|date=November 30, 2009|accessdate=December 8, 2009 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

Her first project on GMA for 2010 was in another villain role in what was billed as the Philippines' first [[Musical theatre|musical]], [[comedy-drama]] series, ''[[Diva (Philippines TV series)|Diva]]'', which debuted on GMA Network on March 1, 2010 and ended on July 30 of that year. The show, which also starred [[Regine Velasquez]], [[Mark Anthony Fernandez]], [[TJ Trinidad]] and singer [[Jaya (singer)|Jaya]] and is partly based on the American movie trilogy ''[[High School Musical]]'' and the American television series ''[[Glee (TV series)|Glee]]'', saw de Castro playing the ambitious Tiffany, who is Lady's ([[Ruffa Mae Quinto]]) assistant and soon-to-be a villainess to singer-actress [[Regine Velasquez]]'s heroine Melody.&lt;ref name=&quot;Diva&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{tl icon}} {{cite web|url=http://www.pep.ph/news/24221/Regine-Velasquez-had-no-second-thoughts-playing-villain-to-Marian-Rivera-in-Darna|title=Regine Velasquez had no second thoughts playing villain to Marian Rivera|author=Nora Calderon|publisher=Philippine Entertainment Portal|date=December 22, 2009|accessdate=December 24, 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt;

After Diva, de Castro auditioned for and won the title role on the primetime fantasy series ''[[Grazilda]]''. The show, a sequel to the [[Cinderella]] story, centers on Grazilda, who is in turn based on one of Cinderella's wicked stepsisters, [[List of Disney's Cinderella characters#Drizella Tremaine|Drizella]]. The plot revolves around Grazilda's banishment from her home world of Fantasia to the human world, where she suffers a fate similar to Cinderella's. The series, which premiered on September 13, 2010, also stars [[Geoff Eigenmann]], [[Yasmien Kurdi]], [[Jolina Magdangal]] and [[Cherie Gil]], and marks de Castro's first lead role in a primetime series. Prior to the show's debut, the actress was constantly quoted as being unable to believe her success; she had by then been accustomed to playing only villainous roles and expected to do so for the remainder of her career.&lt;ref name=&quot;Grazilda&quot;&gt;{{tl icon}} {{cite web|url=http://www.pep.ph/news/26550/Glaiza-de-Castro-gets-her-star-turn-in-primetime-Grazilda|title=Glaiza de Castro gets her star turn in primetime Grazilda|author=Ruel J. Mendoza|publisher=Philippine Entertainment Portal|date=August 22, 2010|accessdate=September 17, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; The show was both a critical and commercial success, beating its rival show ''[[1DOL]]'' by a margin of 5 points in the AGB Mega Manila ratings. In light of the show's success, de Castro's manager, Manny Valera, has decided to turn down any further villain roles on behalf of his talent in order to build her up as a lead star.&lt;ref name=&quot;Manny&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.journal.com.ph/index.php/showbiz-tsismis/19537-richard-denies-leaks-in-survivor.html|title=Richard denies leaks in &quot;Survivor&quot;|author=Mario E. Bautista|publisher=Journal Online|date=October 3, 2010|accessdate=October 25, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;

On October 30, it was announced that de Castro would no longer be cast in the remake of the film ''Temptation Island'' and would instead be launched as a lead star in the 2011 remake of the 1992 film ''Aswang'', produced by [[Regal Films]] with film director [[Topel Lee]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.philstar.com/Article.aspx?articleId=625543&amp;publicationSubCategoryId=96|title=Aktor kailangang dalas-dalasan ang labas ng bahay!|author=Nitz Miralles|publisher=Pilipino Star Ngayon|date=October 30, 2010|accessdate=October 30, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Music==
De Castro has so far released two albums. The first one, titled ''Magbalik Ka'', was released under XAX Music Entertainment, in 2001, when she was thirteen. Five years later, she released a second album, the self-entitled ''Glaiza'', this time released under Dyna Records. The latter album, described by de Castro herself as &quot;more defined&quot; compared to her first album, comprises [[Pop music|pop]] and [[R&amp;B]] songs, and contains mostly original content except for two songs: a [[Tagalog language|Tagalog]] version of [[Joey Albert]]'s song &quot;How Can I Make You See&quot; (titled &quot;Paano&quot; in the album), and an [[English language|English]] version of [[Dingdong Avanzado]]'s &quot;Basta't Kasama Kita&quot;. When asked why it took her half a decade to release a second album, de Castro explained that after the first album was completed, she did not renew her contract with the record company and instead focused on her television career.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;Mas defined ngayon.&quot; ... &quot;After the first, hindi na kami nag-renew [ng contract]. Hindi na rin ako nagwo-work. Nagka-manager na din ako. Nagconcentrate sa TV shows. Puro TV ginagawa ko.&quot; {{cite web |url=http://www.pep.ph/guide/214/Glaiza-de-Castro-releases-self-titled-album |title=
Glaiza de Castro releases self-titled album |author=Wells Avante|publisher=Philippine Entertainment Portal|date=January 22, 2007|accessdate=November 29, 2009 }}&lt;/ref&gt; In June 2008, ''Glaiza'' was officially launched, two years after the album was released.&lt;ref&gt;{{tl icon}} {{cite web |url=http://www.pep.ph/news/17829/Glaiza-de-Castro%27s-debut-album-to-be-launched-two-years-after-its-release/2/1 |title=
Glaiza de Castro's debut album to be launched two years after its release|author=Rose Garcia|publisher=Philippine Entertainment Portal|date=June 10, 2008|accessdate=November 29, 2009 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Personal life==

She also maintained a close friendship with consistent on-screen partner Marky Cielo for a significant part of the latter's career until his death in 2008. In the wake of her friend's death, de Castro recounted an exchange she had the day before Cielo died: she told Cielo about a dream she had about him and Rich Asuncion; according to her, Cielo had had other people tell him they had dreams about him, which he took to be an omen of death.&lt;ref name=&quot;Philippine Entertainment Portal&quot;&gt;&quot;Ang panaginip ko, silang dalawa ni Rich [Asuncion, StarStruck 4 First Princess] parang tinutukso-tukso ko, magkasama sila sa kotse.&quot; ... &quot;Tapos, ang text back sa akin ni Marky, marami raw siyang naririnig na napapaginipan din siya. Ang sabi niya, 'Bakit kaya maraming nagsasabing napaginipan nila ako, mamamatay na kaya ako?' Na talagang ngayon ko lang naalala yung sinabi niyang yun, kaya kinilabutan ako!&quot; {{tl icon}} {{cite web |url=http://www.pep.ph/news/20162/Glaiza-de-Castro-had-a-dream-about-Marky-Cielo-before-he-passed-away |title=
Glaiza de Castro had a dream about Marky Cielo before he passed away |author=Mell Navarro|date=December 8, 2008|accessdate=November 28, 2009 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

Despite gaining wider recognition for her roles as a villain in ''Kung Aagawin Mo Ang Lahat Sa Akin'' and ''Stairway to Heaven'', de Castro has reportedly had qualms about portraying a villain again in future projects. Of this, she commented, &quot;I don't want to be [[Typecasting (acting)|typecast]] as an antagonist forever because it's difficult to get rid of that sort of image.&quot; However, she has expressed preference for antagonist roles over &quot;sexy&quot; roles.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;Ayokong ma-typecast na kontrabida forever kasi mahirap makakawala sa ganoong image.&quot;{{cite web |url=http://www.mb.com.ph/articles/220026/i-ll-say-no-next-villainess-role-glaiza-de-castro|title=
'I'll say no to next villainess role' - Glaiza de Castro |author=Alex Valentin Brosas | publisher=[[Manila Bulletin]]|date=September 10, 2009|accessdate=November 29, 2009 }}&lt;/ref&gt; She later retracted this statement, saying that she &quot;didn't think [she'd] get typecast because [she] plays different kinds of women each time&quot; and explained this by saying, &quot;The stories are different, so [her] characters' [motivations] are also different.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;Diva&quot;/&gt;

Although she had, in the past, considered posing for magazines such as [[FHM]] &quot;for instant fame and fortune&quot;, she eventually decided against it and opted to hone her craft as a serious actress, saying, &quot;I just want to start on the right foot by focusing more on acting than diverting my attention to other interests. I want to become an actress and to show what I can do.&quot; She has also expressed interest in playing &quot;out-of-the-box and extreme roles&quot;, in the vein of [[Natalie Portman]] in ''[[V for Vendetta]]'' and [[Charlize Theron]] in ''[[Monster (2003 film)|Monster]]''.&lt;ref name=&quot;Philstar.com&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.philstar.com/Article.aspx?articleId=30748 |title=
Glaiza off to a good start |author=Jerry Donato|accessdate=November 15, 2009 }}&lt;/ref&gt; In 2008, she spoke of her preference for independent film, commenting in Taglish, &quot;As for me, I feel fulfilled in indie films. I'm given roles in indie projects that are heavier compared to the [[mainstream]]. And I'm rarely offered roles in mainstream [films] anyway.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;&quot;Ang sa akin lang, fulfilled ako sa indie films. Nabibigyan ako ng roles sa indie projects na mabigat kung ikukumpara sa mainstream. At saka madalang naman akong mabigyan ng offer sa mainstream.&quot;{{cite web |url=http://cerphin.net/balita/Glaiza-de-Castro-feels-fulfilled-in-doing-indie-films/source/14530/|title=
Glaiza de Castro feels fulfilled in doing indie films|author=Archie de Calma|date=May 12, 2008|accessdate=November 21, 2009 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Filmography and television==
===Filmography===
{| border=&quot;1&quot; cellpadding=&quot;0&quot; cellspacing=&quot;0&quot; style=&quot;margin: 1em 1em 1em 0; background: #f9f9f9; border: 1px #aaa solid; border-collapse: collapse;”
|- bgcolor=&quot;#CCCCCC&quot; align=&quot;center&quot;
! colspan=&quot;5&quot; style=&quot;background: LightSteelBlue;&quot; | Films
|- bgcolor=&quot;#CCCCCC&quot; align=&quot;center&quot;
| '''Year''' || '''Title''' || '''Role''' || '''Notes''' || '''Awards'''  
|-
|rowspan=&quot;1&quot;| 2001
| ''Cool Dudes 24/7''
|
| 
|-
|rowspan=&quot;1&quot;| 2002
| ''[[Singsing ni Lola]]''
| Tacion
|
|-
|rowspan=&quot;1&quot;| 2005
|''Miss Pinoy''
|
|
|-
|rowspan=&quot;7&quot;| 2006
|''Sukob''
| Grace
|
|-
|''Manay Po!''
| Pauleen
|
|-
|''[[Pacquiao: The Movie]]''
| Cecille
|
|-
|''[[White Lady (film)|White Lady]]''
| Jowee
|
|-
|''Twilight Dancers''
|
|
|-
|''Close to You''
| Lance's Cousin
|
|-
|''Zsa Zsa Zaturnnah: Ze Moveeh''
| Dina B.
|
|-
|rowspan=&quot;2&quot;| 2007
|''Still Life''
| Emma
| Nominated &amp;ndash; Golden Screen Award for Best Supporting Actress
|-
|''Batanes''
|
|
|-
|rowspan=&quot;5&quot;| 2009
|''[[Tarot (2009 film)|Tarot]]''
| Teen Nena
|
|-
|''Bente''
| Rise
|
|-
|''Astig''
| Elgine
| Nominated &amp;ndash; Gawad Urian Award for Best Supporting Actress
|-
|''Ang Manghuhula''
| Claire
|
|-
|''[[Mano Po 6: A Mother's Love]]''
| young Melinda
|
|-
|rowspan=&quot;5&quot;| 2011
|''Aswang''
|
|
|-
|}

===Television ===
{| border=&quot;1&quot; cellpadding=&quot;0&quot; cellspacing=&quot;0&quot; style=&quot;margin: 1em 1em 1em 0; background: #f9f9f9; border: 1px #aaa solid; border-collapse: collapse;”
|- bgcolor=&quot;#CCCCCC&quot; align=&quot;center&quot;
! colspan=&quot;4&quot; style=&quot;background: LightSteelBlue;&quot; | Television
|- bgcolor=&quot;#CCCCCC&quot; align=&quot;center&quot;
| '''Year''' || '''Title''' || '''Role''' || '''Network''' 
|-
|rowspan=&quot;2&quot;| 2001
|''[[Ikaw Lang Ang Mamahalin]]''
| Marga's friend
|''[[GMA Network]]''
|-
| ''[[Berks (TV series)|Berks]]''
| Halley
| rowspan=&quot;3&quot;| [[ABS-CBN]]
|-
| 2004
| ''[[Spirits]]''
| Pinky
|-
| 2005
|''[[Ikaw Ang Lahat Sa Akin]]''
| Magnolia Cortez
|-
| 2006
|''[[Fantastikids]]''
| Honey
| rowspan=&quot;19&quot;| [[GMA Network]]
|-
| 2007–2010
| ''[[SOP Fully Charged]]''
| Herself
|-
|rowspan=&quot;3&quot;| 2007
|''[[Asian Treasures]]''
| Clara
|-
|''[[Boys Nxt Door]]''
| Sari
|-
|''[[Kamandag]]''
| young Alicia
|-
|rowspan=&quot;3&quot;| 2008
|''[[Kaputol ng Isang Awit|Sine Novela: Kaputol ng Isang Awit]]''
| Sarah Monteza
|-
|''[[Dear Friend|Dear Friend: Igorota]]''
| Guest role
|-
|''[[Maynila (TV series)|Maynila]]''
| Guest role
|-
| 2008–2009
| ''[[Gagambino]]''
| Leah Abuento/Super Bee
|-
|rowspan=&quot;3&quot;| 2009
|''[[Kung Aagawin Mo Ang Lahat Sa Akin|Sine Novela: Kung Aagawin Mo Ang Lahat Sa Akin]]''
| Gladys Andrada
|-
|''[[SRO Cinemaserye|SRO Cinemaserye: Eva Castillo Story]]''
| teenage Eva Castillo
|-
| ''[[Stairway to Heaven (Philippines TV series)|Stairway to Heaven]]''
| Eunice
|-
|rowspan=&quot;7&quot;| 2010
| ''[[Diva (Philippines TV series)|Diva]]''
| Tiffany Mendoza
|-
| ''[[Diz Iz It]]''
| Guest Celebrity Judge
|-
| ''[[Party Pilipinas]]''
| Herself/Performer
|-
| ''[[Laff En Roll]]''
| Herself/Co-Host
|-
| ''[[Claudine (TV series)|Claudine Presents: A Love Story]]''
| Various roles
|-
| ''[[Show Me Da Manny]]''
| Guest
|-
| ''[[Grazilda]]''
| Grazilda
|-
| rowspan=&quot;2&quot;|2011 
| ''[[Amaya (TV series)|Amaya]]''
| Binayaan or yangterisayan
|}

==Discography==
* ''Magbalik Ka'' (2001)
* ''Glaiza'' (2006)

==See also==
*[[List of programs broadcast by GMA Network]]

==References==
{{Reflist|2}}

==External links==
*[http://www.igma.tv/profile/glaiza-de-castro Glaiza de Castro] at [http://www.igma.tv/ iGMA.tv]
*{{imdb name|1270699}}

{{Persondata &lt;!-- Metadata: see [[Wikipedia:Persondata]]. --&gt;
| NAME              =De Castro, Glaiza
| ALTERNATIVE NAMES =
| SHORT DESCRIPTION =
| DATE OF BIRTH     =January 21, 1988
| PLACE OF BIRTH    =[[Valenzuela City]], [[Philippines]]
| DATE OF DEATH     =
| PLACE OF DEATH    =
}}
{{DEFAULTSORT:De Castro, Glaiza}}
[[Category:1988 births]]
[[Category:Filipino actors]]
[[Category:Filipino child actors]]
[[Category:Filipino film actors]]
[[Category:Filipino television actors]]
[[Category:Filipino female singers]]
[[Category:Filipino television personalities]]
[[Category:Members of Iglesia ni Cristo]]
[[Category:Filipino Christians]]
[[Category:Filipino evangelicals]]
[[Category:Filipino Pentecostals]]
[[Category:Filipino Protestants]]
[[Category:GMA Network]]
[[Category:Living people]]
[[Category:People from Valenzuela City]]
[[Category:Star Magic Batch 11]]

[[es:Glaiza de Castro]]
[[ms:Glaiza de Castro]]
[[tl:Glaiza de Castro]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
