<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="13317820" ns="0" title="University of Florida Taser incident"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">On September 17, 2007, [[United States Senate|U.S. Senator]] [[John Kerry]] addressed a [[Constitution Day (United States)|Constitution Day]] forum at the [[University of Florida]] in [[Gainesville, Florida|Gainesville]], which was organized by the [[ACCENT Speakers Bureau]], an agency of the university's [[student government]]. Initially allowed to ask questions after the close of the question period, [[Andrew Meyer]], a 21-year-old fourth-year undergraduate [[mass communication]] student, was subsequently removed from the forum by [[campus police|university police]] for unruly behavior. During the struggle to arrest Meyer, one of the officers [[Taser#Drive Stun|drive stunned]] him with a [[Taser]] following Meyer's pleading shout to the police, &quot;'''Don't tase me, bro!'''&quot;.

Several videos of the episode were then posted on the Internet. The most viewed version of the video, shot by Kyle Mitchell of ''[[The Gainesville Sun]]'', has more than 6,086,748 views on YouTube as of November 26th, 2011.&lt;ref name=&quot;thevideoitself&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=6bVa6jn4rpE|title=Video &quot;University of Florida student Tasered at Kerry forum&quot;|date=September 17, 2007}}&lt;/ref&gt; The ''[[New Oxford American Dictionary]]'' listed &quot;tase/taze&quot; as one of the words of the year for 2007, popularized by the widespread use of the phrase &quot;Don't tase me, bro!&quot;  ''[[The Yale Book of Quotations]]'' designated Meyer's exclamation as the most memorable quote of 2007.&lt;ref name=&quot;Reuters1&quot;&gt;{{cite news |title=&quot;Don't Tase Me, Bro!&quot; tops '07 memorable quote list|url=http://www.reuters.com/article/oddlyEnoughNews/idUSN1959512020071219?loc=interstitialskip|agency=[[Reuters]]|first=Arthur|last=Spiegelman|date=2007-12-19|accessdate=2008-07-25}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Mick Jones (The Clash)|Mick Jones]], former guitarist for [[The Clash]], wrote and published a song inspired from the event, &quot;Don't Tase Me, Bro&quot;, and new wave band [[Devo]] use the quote in their song &quot;[[Don't Shoot (I'm a Man)]].&quot; The quote was also used by laptop rapper, [[MC Lars]] in his song &quot;True Player For Real&quot;.

== Details ==
=== Student ===
'''Andrew William Meyer''' (born September 15, 1986 in [[Fort Lauderdale, Florida]]&lt;ref name=&quot;offensereport&quot; /&gt;), was, at the time of the incident, an undergraduate student [[academic major|majoring]] in television [[journalism]] at the [[University of Florida]]. He attended [[Cypress Bay High School]] in [[Weston, Florida]], where he worked at the [[school newspaper]], ''The Circuit'', and was a member of the [[National Honor Society]]. At the University of Florida, Meyer worked as a [[columnist]] for the college paper ''[[Independent Florida Alligator]]''. Meyer has stated that he writes &quot;mostly whimsical nonsense columns about nothing in particular, yet occasionally finds [himself] angry enough to rain down [[fire and brimstone]] on an unsuspecting politician or celebrity&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.freewebs.com/newforum/bioandpersonalstories.htm|title=Andrew Meyer|publisher=The New Forum|accessdate=2007-09-22}}&lt;/ref&gt;

He received international publicity when videos were posted of police [[Electroshock weapon|tasering]] him at the town hall forum featuring Senator Kerry.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |last=Moses |first=Asher|url=http://www.smh.com.au/news/web/dont-tase-me-bro/2007/09/20/1189881651002.htm |title='Don't Tase me, bro!' a global sensation |work=[[The Sydney Morning Herald]] |date=2007-09-20 |accessdate=2008-07-25}} {{Dead link|date=September 2010|bot=H3llBot}}&lt;/ref&gt;
''[[The Miami Herald]]'' has stated that &quot;Meyer's grandmother, Lucy Meyer of [[Pembroke Pines, Florida]], told ''The Miami Herald'' that he is a hardworking student with no prior run-ins with the law.&quot; She also said &quot;He gets very, very overcome with passion for whatever he is feeling. Maybe the passion took over&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |title=Student Tasered at Kerry forum has a penchant for practical jokes |url=http://www.iht.com/articles/ap/2007/09/18/america/NA-GEN-US-Student-Tasered.php |work=[[International Herald Tribune]] |publisher= |date=2007-09-17 |accessdate=2008-07-25 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Incident prior to start of video ===
[[Image:Meyersarrest.jpg|thumb|University of Florida police attempt to force Andrew Meyer out of the auditorium.]]
According to eyewitness and police reports, the widely circulated video of the confrontation captured on Meyer's camera was not the  first interaction between police and Meyer at the event that day. According to reports,  Meyer was in line for access to the microphone, when it was announced by former Ambassador [[Dennis Jett]], a University of Florida political science instructor and the forum's moderator,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|last=Stripling|first=Jack |url=http://www.heraldtribune.com/article/20070920/NEWS/709200767 |title=Stun gun case fuels claims of repression at UF |work=The Gainesville Sun |date=2007-09-20 |accessdate=2008-07-25}}&lt;/ref&gt; that one more question would be taken from the microphone on the right as seen from the stage. Meyer then grabbed the second microphone, on the left, which had been shut off, and loudly demanded he be allowed to ask a question. Meyer reportedly yelled, &quot;Why don't you answer my questions, I have been waiting and listening to you speak in circles for the last two hours.&quot; &quot;These officers are going to arrest me&quot;,&lt;!--This is very poorly written; why is the punctuation and quotations done so haphazardly? Please take some time to do it right!--&gt;  &quot;You will take my question because I have been listening to your crap for two hours&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |title=Cops on leave after Taser incident, student's behavior under scrutiny |url=http://www.cnn.com/2007/US/09/18/student.tasered/index.html |publisher=[[CNN]] |date=2007-09-18 |accessdate=2008-07-25 }}&lt;/ref&gt;  When an officer intervened, attempted to cut Meyer off, and attempted to escort Meyer out of the hall, Meyer then broke away and continued to shout. Kerry then intervened and requested that Meyer be allowed to ask a question. Meyer was then brought back to the microphone with police officers on either side of him.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |first=Dennis |last=Jett |title=What YouTube doesn't show |url=http://www.csmonitor.com/2007/1031/p09s01-coop.html |work=[[The Christian Science Monitor]] |publisher= |date=2007-10-31 |accessdate=2008-07-25 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

Meyer then handed his camera to the woman who was standing in front of him in line and requested that she record him. Kerry then finished answering a previous question, and Meyer was then recognized by Kerry to ask a question.

=== Video begins ===

At this point, Meyer's video began. Meyer spoke for approximately 1 minute and 20 seconds, beginning by citing the book ''[[Armed Madhouse]]'' and its author [[Greg Palast]]'s description of the [[United States presidential election, 2004|2004 U.S. presidential election]] and reports of [[2004 United States election voting controversies|election irregularities]].&lt;ref name=&quot;wapo&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Fox excessive&quot;&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.foxnews.com/story/0,2933,297197,00.html|title=Florida College Student Who Was Tasered, Arrested at John Kerry Campus Forum Is Released From Jail|work=FoxNews.com|date=September 18, 2007|accessdate=2007-09-18}}&lt;/ref&gt; According to ''[[The Washington Post]]'', Meyer's question turned into &quot;an increasingly agitated three-parter.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;wapo&quot;&gt;{{cite news|last=Hesse|first=Monica|url=http://www.washingtonpost.com/wp-dyn/content/article/2007/09/18/AR2007091802115.html| title=Aiming to Agitate, Florida Student Got a Shock|work=The Washington Post|date=2007-09-19|accessdate=2007-09-19}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Meyer questioned Kerry's concession of the 2004 U.S. presidential election, Kerry's support or lack of support of the [[efforts to impeach George W. Bush]],&lt;ref name=&quot;wapo&quot; /&gt; and Kerry's involvement in the [[Yale University]] [[secret society]] known as [[Skull and Bones]].&lt;ref name=&quot;wapo&quot; /&gt;
After Meyer used the term &quot;[[Fellatio|blowjob]]&quot;, (in reference to the impeachment of [[Bill Clinton]]) and while he was asking about Kerry's involvement in Skull and Bones, Meyer's microphone was cut off. Later, Steven Blank, ACCENT chairman, said, &quot;We make it clear that any profanity and vulgarity by anyone asking questions will result in a cutting off of the mic.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;fla gator&quot;&gt;[http://www.alligator.org/articles/2007/09/18/news/student_government/accent.txt &quot;Meyer incident won't affect Accent security policy, chairman says&quot;] By DEVIN CULCLASURE, ''Alligator'' Writer. ''The Independent Florida Alligator''{{Dead link|date=September 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Removal and arrest ===

After his microphone was turned off, two University of Florida police officers attempted to take him away.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|last=Leusner|first=Jim|coauthors=Katie Fretland|url=http://www.orlandosentinel.com/news/local/state/orl-taseredgator19sep19,0,4218845.story?coll=orl-jobs-utility|title='Don't Tase Me Bro' becomes rallying cry at UF following arrest of student|publisher=''Orlando Sentinel''|date=September 19, 2007}}&lt;/ref&gt; Steven Blank, ACCENT chairman, later said &quot;They [the police] acted independently of Accent&lt;!-- SIC: properly capitalized &quot;ACCENT&quot; --&gt;.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;fla gator&quot; /&gt; Some members of the crowd began to cheer and applaud. Physical contact by the police occurred right after Meyer remarked, &quot;Thank you for cutting my mic!&quot; Kerry responded to the police action, &quot;That's all right, let me answer his question&quot;,&lt;ref name=&quot;wapo&quot; /&gt; but two police officers continued to hold Meyer and attempted to escort him towards the exit. Meyer repeatedly asked why he was being arrested. He struggled for several seconds shouting, &quot;Get off me! What are you doing? What is going on?&quot; while a third police officer kept a Taser aimed at him.&lt;ref name=&quot;Fox excessive&quot;/&gt; Meyer managed to get back towards the stage and stated, &quot;I want to stand and listen to the answers to my questions!&quot; A fourth officer joined in, and single-handedly managed to remove Meyer to the back of the auditorium while being escorted by the three other officers. Meyer was carried part of the way by officer King, holding Greg Palast's book up in the air with his one free arm and shouting, &quot;Why are you arresting me? Help! Help!&quot; Close to the exit, Meyer broke free for a short moment and then was wrestled to the ground. Two more officers joined in and Meyer was now held down by four officers on the body and two on the legs. The officers managed to [[handcuffs|handcuff]] only one hand.

As Meyer requested to be allowed to leave of his own accord, they informed him that he no longer had a say in the matter and threatened several times to [[taser]] him if he did not comply. Meyer asked again to leave, and yelled &quot;Don't tase me, bro! Don't tase me!&quot; but was [[Taser#Drive_Stun|drive stunned]] (referred to in the police report as a &quot;contact tase&quot;) in the shoulder by officer  her department-issued [[Taser#Taser|X-26 Taser]] when he failed to comply.&lt;ref name=&quot;offensereport&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;wapo&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Fox excessive&quot;/&gt;

{{quote|I managed to take control of Meyer's right hand and restrain it into one side of my handcuffs. Due to Meyer's erratic flailing, the inability to attain Meyer's left arm from his resistance, and increased potential for injury with one cuff on, Sgt. King attempted to deploy a contact tase to no avail. He then instructed The officer to apply a contact tase to gain compliance in order to place Meyer's left hand into the other cuff. The officer gave verbal commands and informed Meyer that he would be tased if he did not comply. Once The officerapplied the tase, Wise assisted Meyer's left arm to where I was able to apply the other cuff. Once he was restrained, he was escorted out of the Auditorium where I checked the fitting and applied the double-locked function on the cuffs.|Police Report, Statement of Officer Pablo De Jesus, Jr.|&lt;ref name=&quot;offensereport&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://i.a.cnn.net/cnn/2007/images/09/18/offense.report.072274.pdf|title=University of Florida Police Department offense report|date=2007-10-18|publisher=[[CNN]]|accessdate=2008-07-25|format=PDF}}&lt;/ref&gt;}}

Meyer continued screaming for help as the officers removed him from the room. During the altercation, Kerry urged everyone to calm down, joked that &quot;Unfortunately, he [Andrew Meyer] is not available to come up here and swear me in as President&quot; and continued his response to Meyer's question, which he referred to as &quot;very important&quot;. Senator Kerry later released a statement saying that he was unaware that any Tasing had occurred until afterwards.&lt;ref name=&quot;Fox excessive&quot;/&gt;

{{quote|'''Police ''[in background]'':''' &quot;Get down!&quot;

'''Senator Kerry:''' &quot;Hey officers ... could we ... Hey folks ... I think that if everybody just...&quot;

'''Police:''' &quot;Do it now!&quot;

'''Senator Kerry:''' &quot;... calms down this situation would calm down. [unintelligible] ...I'll answer his question. Unfortunately, he is not available to come up here and swear me in as President.&quot;

'''Andrew Meyer:''' &quot;Why are they arresting me? Did someone do something here? Are they arresting?&quot;

'''Senator Kerry:''' &quot;Let me just say, because it is a very important question.&quot;|YouTube Video Tape starting at 2:34 &lt;ref name=&quot;tapeusedfortranscript&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=SaiWCS10C5s|title=Video &quot;UF Police Taser Student During Kerry Forum&quot;|date=September 19, 2007}}&lt;/ref&gt;}}

Meyer was then escorted off the premises, remaining uncooperative with police during questioning.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.liveleak.com/view?i=3ec_1190097717|title=Kerry Taser Incident....raw footage of after he was tasered and led away|publisher=www.liveleak.com|accessdate=2007-09-21}}&lt;/ref&gt; He was detained overnight in the Alachua County Jail.&lt;ref name=&quot;aparrestarticle&quot; /&gt; A large gathering of students protested outside the jail that evening.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.timesonline.co.uk/tol/news/world/us_and_americas/article2489183.ece|title=Andrew Meyer, the student who begged: 'Don't Tase me bro!', becomes internet star|publisher=''The Times''|date=September 19, 2007 | location=London | first=Nico | last=Hines | accessdate=May 27, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Legal action ===
After the incident, Meyer was arrested for inciting a riot and charged with [[Resisting arrest|resisting an officer]] and [[disturbing the peace]] and taken to [[Alachua County, Florida|Alachua County]] Jail.&lt;ref name=&quot;aparrestarticle&quot;&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.miamiherald.com/775/story/241199.html|title=Florida student Tasered at Kerry forum after election question|date=September 18, 2007}}&lt;/ref&gt; Police recommended charges of resisting arrest with violence, a felony, and disturbing the peace and interfering with school administrative functions, a misdemeanor. Meyer spent one night in the Alachua County Jail and was released the following morning.&lt;ref name=&quot;aparrestarticle&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;alligatorjailarticle&quot;&gt;{{cite news|last=Wilmath|first=Kim|url=http://www.alligator.org/articles/2007/09/18/news/campus/arraignment.txt|title=Meyer released from jail|work=The Independent Florida Alligator|date=September 18, 2007}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Meyer's attorney, Robert S. Griscti, stated he would seek to have the charges dismissed.&lt;ref name=&quot;alligatorjailarticle&quot; /&gt; Meyer later issued a public apology for his &quot;failure to act calmly&quot;, stating that he &quot;stepped out of line&quot;. He also insisted there was no reason for his arrest and demanded an apology from the Alachua County Police Department.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.alligator.org/articles/2007/10/30/news/campus/meyer.txt &quot;News – Meyer apologizes in letter to students&quot;] ''The Independent Florida Alligator''&lt;/ref&gt; The state attorney stated he would drop prosecution of Meyer's case if he completed a voluntary 18-month probation.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.sptimes.com/2007/10/31/State/Tasered_student_is_so.shtml State: Tasered student is sorry&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt; He returned as a student in the spring semester of 2008 with the charges dropped despite serving no probation.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.msnbc.msn.com/id/21541335/ ‘Don't Tase me, bro’ student won't be charged – Crime &amp; courts – MSNBC.com&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;

== Issues raised ==
=== Allegations of excessive force ===
[[CNN]].com has stated that student opinions on the [[University of Florida]] campus are evenly divided as to whether the officers acted properly.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|last=Ortiz|first=Eunic|title= Students stunned – and tired – about Taser incident|publisher=CNN.com|date=2007-09-19|url=http://www.cnn.com/2007/US/09/19/cnnu.tase/index.html|accessdate=2007-09-24}}&lt;/ref&gt; About 300 students marched to the steps of campus police headquarters the following day with another 100 marching to Emerson Alumni Hall. They chanted that police used [[excessive force]] and waved signs that read &quot;Stop police brutality&quot;, &quot;Taze Pigs&quot;, &quot;Freedom of Speech not a Felony&quot;, &quot;Tasers Kill&quot;, and Meyer's words, &quot;Don't Tase me, bro&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|last=Tiegen|first=Alex|coauthors=Ileana Morales|url=http://www.alligator.org/articles/2007/09/20/news/campus/protest.txt|title=Students continue protesting Taser incident Wednesday|publisher=''The Independent Florida Alligator''|date=September 20, 2007}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|last=Gawade|first=Tejas|url=http://media.www.sbstatesman.com/media/storage/paper955/news/2007/09/24/News/Another.College.Student.Falls.Victim.To.Tasers-2985004.shtml|title=Another College Student Falls Victim to Tasers|publisher=''The Statesman''|date=September 24, 2007}}&lt;/ref&gt;  They demanded that Tasers be banned from campus, and that charges be filed against the police officers that restrained and tased Meyer.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.local6.com/news/14144444/detail.html|title=Students Erupt In Protest, Demand Charges Filed Against Officers At Kerry Event|publisher=[[WKMG-TV]]'s website ''www.local6.com''|date=September 18, 2007}}&lt;/ref&gt; Four weeks after the incident the university sponsored a panel to discuss appropriate police practices. Fifteen people attended and one signed up to make comments.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.alligator.org/articles/2007/10/16/news/campus/panel.txt &quot;Policy panel draws 15 attendees&quot;].&lt;/ref&gt;

James W. Preston, president of the Florida State Lodge of the Fraternal Order of Police, referred to student Andrew Meyer's actions during the Kerry town hall forum as a &quot;theatrical production&quot; that &quot;set the stage for Andrew Meyer's own gratification to bring attention to himself.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.gainesvillesun.com/article/20070926/NEWS/709260331/-1/news07 Police union official blasts UF – News – GainesvilleSun.com&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Free speech issues ===
Some critics of the actions of the police have suggested that it was not Meyer's actions which led to his removal, but the content of his remarks. For example, writer Palast said, &quot;When you bring up uncomfortable stuff, it's going to create discomfort.  Obviously, if he was speaking about baseball scores—if he maybe had a different political viewpoint that wasn't seen as combative or outside of what's permissible—then the cops' backs wouldn't have been up.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.gainesvillesun.com/article/20070920/NEWS/709200326/1007/NEWS Taser sparks debate] Gainesville sun&lt;/ref&gt;

The [[American Civil Liberties Union]]'s Florida chapter released a statement on September 18, 2007 expressing dismay over the incident.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.aclufl.org/news_events/?action=viewRelease&amp;emailAlertID=2980 University of Florida Taser Incident Should Have Been Avoided, Says ACLU&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;

{{quote|Apart from the taser use issues, one must consider the free speech implications of the police officers’ actions&quot;, said Howard Simon, ACLU of Florida Executive Director. &quot;People have a reasonable expectation to ask questions in a public setting&amp;nbsp;– even if they are aggressive and some disagree with their position&amp;nbsp;– that is free speech plain and simple. Similarly&amp;nbsp;– Kerry had a reasonable expectation to be able to answer those questions. Neither of them was able to exercise their free speech rights due to the police action.}}

=== Criticism of Andrew Meyer ===
News articles about the incident have reported that Meyer had posted on his web site numerous comedy videos.&lt;ref name=&quot;suntimes1911&quot;&gt;[http://www.suntimes.com/news/nation/563864,CST-NWS-taser19.article Chicago Sun-Times article Sept 19]&lt;/ref&gt; It has also been pointed out that Meyer made arrangements to have himself filmed and have speculated that the incident may have been a stunt by Meyer. The reported behavior of Meyer when no cameras were present is also cited as evidence that the incident was a prank.  According to the police report: &quot;as [Meyer] was escorted down stairs with no cameras in sight, he remained quiet, but once the cameras made their way down stairs he started screaming and yelling again.&quot; Additionally, the report states that Meyer was &quot;laughing and being lighthearted in the car, his demeanor completely changed once the cameras were not in sight.&quot; The police officers have said that during the ride, Meyer said: &quot;I am not mad at you guys, you didn't do anything wrong, you were just trying to do your job.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;offensereport&quot; /&gt;

John Levy, a graduate student at the university and a friend of Meyer's since the second grade, has said that he spoke with Meyer shortly before Meyer entered the Kerry forum. He said that Meyer felt excited, had come up with several questions, and wanted to hear the senator's responses. Levy also said that Meyer was &quot;really upset that people are more concerned with the police attack and not with the dialogue he was trying to start with Kerry&quot; and that &quot;What kind of message does that send? He wants to show students it's okay to ask hard questions, and then he gets tased for doing it.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;wapo&quot;/&gt; In the 2008 film ''Free For All'', filmmaker [[John Wellington Ennis|John Ennis]] and [[Greg Palast]] (the author of the book Meyer was holding during the event) strongly echo this sentiment.  When &quot;asked about speculation that Meyer [[publicity stunt|staged]] the confrontation&quot;, University spokesman Steve Orlando has stated that a member of the Office of Student Affairs told Orlando that Meyer brought a [[video camera]] to the forum and gave it to Clarissa Jessup, the young woman who was next in line to ask a question,&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.washingtonpost.com/wp-dyn/content/article/2007/09/23/AR2007092301286.html?nav=rss_politics 'Washington Post''article Sept 24 &quot;Got a Camera by Howard Kurtz]&lt;/ref&gt; with whom he was unacquainted, before he spoke.  Henry Perlstein, a university senior who has known Meyer since [[high school]], said, &quot;My first impression was that [the video] was a [[home movie]] he made for his friends because it was so [[surrealism|surreal]]. Then I heard the screams and he sounded genuinely afraid.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.theapple.com/news/articles/1188-student-tasered-while-questioning-sen-kerry|title=Student Tasered While Questioning Sen. Kerry|accessdate=2007-09-23|last=Hesse|first=Monica}}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== University investigation ===
On September 18, in Emerson Alumni Hall, University of Florida President, [[J. Bernard Machen]]  held a press conference about the incident. He also issued a letter&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.president.ufl.edu/incident.htm|title=President Machen presents update on issues related to student arrest}}&lt;/ref&gt; in which he stated that the University Police Chief Linda Stump had requested that the [[Florida Department of Law Enforcement (FDLE)]] investigate the arrest. President Machen stated that &quot;We plan to assemble a panel of faculty and students to review our police protocols, our management practices and the FDLE report to come up with a series of recommendations for the university.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://gainesvillesun.com/article/20070918/NEWS/70918014/1007/NEWS|title=Two officers suspended in Tasering}}&lt;/ref&gt; The [[State Attorney's Office]] will review the charges as well.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.gainesvillesun.com/article/20070918/NEWS/70918020/1007/NEWS|title=State Attorney's Office to expedite review}}&lt;/ref&gt;

''[[The Miami Herald]]'' has stated that, at the press conference, President Machen called the situation &quot;regretful for us&quot; and announced that two officers involved in the incident had been placed on paid administrative leave pending the outcome of the probe. University spokesman Steve Orlando said Meyer was asked to leave the microphone after his allotted time was up. However, a transcript of the event shows that this is untrue; he was not told to leave at any point. The university president &quot;would not say whether he thought the latest episode was a [[prank]].&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|last=Reed|first=Travis|url=http://www.miamiherald.com/775/story/241199.html|title=Student Tasered at Kerry forum has a penchant for practical jokes|publisher=''Miami Herald'' (AP)|date=September 18, 2007}}&lt;/ref&gt;

On October 24, 2007 the Florida Department of Law Enforcement released a report&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.president.ufl.edu/incident/FDLE-Executive-Summary.pdf FDLE Case GA-27-0008]&lt;/ref&gt; on their investigation of the incident. They found that the officer's actions were justified.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.iht.com/articles/ap/2007/10/24/america/NA-GEN-US-Student-Tasered.php|title=University of Florida police cleared in use of stun gun on student|work=[[International Herald Tribune]]|date=October 24, 2007}}&lt;/ref&gt; University President Bernie Machen stated that &quot;I have full confidence in the police department&quot; and that the two officers previously placed on paid administrative leave have been fully reinstated.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://insideuf.ufl.edu/2007/10/24/machen-fdle/|title=President addresses summary of FDLE report|publisher=''[http://insideuf.ufl.edu/ Inside UF]''|date=October 24, 2007}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The [[Florida Department of Law Enforcement]] investigated the incident and, in a report released on October 25, 2007, concluded that Meyer may have planned a 'disruption' of the forum.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.gainesville.com/article/20071025/NEWS/710250322/0/news UF police cleared in Tasering Gainsvile Sun]&lt;/ref&gt; The same report cleared the police officers involved of any wrongdoing in subduing Meyer.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.miamiherald.com/top_stories/story/283492.html UF police cleared in 'Don't Tase me, Bro' case Miami Herald 25 Oct 2007]&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Response from Senator Kerry ===
On the day following the incident, Kerry's office issued a statement:

{{quote|In 37 years of public appearances, through wars, protests and highly emotional events, I have never had a dialogue end this way. I believe I could have handled the situation without interruption, but I do not know what warnings or other exchanges transpired between the young man and the police prior to his barging to the front of the line and their intervention. I asked the police to allow me to answer the question and was in the process of responding when he was taken into custody. I was not aware that a taser was used until after I left the building. I hope that neither the student nor any of the police were injured. I regret enormously that a good healthy discussion was interrupted.|[[John Kerry]]&lt;ref name=&quot;kerry_statement&quot;&gt;{{cite web|publisher=Office of Senator John Kerry|url=http://kerry.senate.gov/cfm/record.cfm?id=283508|title=Kerry Statement on Florida Campus Incident|date=September 18, 2007}}&lt;/ref&gt;}}

==See also==
*[[Taser controversy]]
*[[Taser safety issues]]
*[[Taser International]] – Taser Manufacturer
*[[Braidwood Inquiry]] – Official Canadian enquiry into Tasers and similar devices
*[[UCLA Taser incident]]
*[[Robert Dziekański Taser incident]]
*[[Iman Morales Taser incident]]
*[[Student protest]]

== References ==
{{Reflist|2}}

== External links ==
*{{youtube|SaiWCS10C5s|UF Police Taser Student During Kerry Forum}}
* {{youtube|r7Qef8oPmag|Extended Video}}
* [http://www.theandrewmeyer.com/ Andrew Meyer's website]
* [http://sg.ufl.edu/accent/press/johnkerrypressrelease.pdf Press Release for Town Hall Forum]

{{DEFAULTSORT:University Of Florida Taser Incident}}
[[Category:2007 controversies in the United States]]
[[Category:John Kerry]]
[[Category:University of Florida]]
[[Category:Internet memes]]
[[Category:Electroshock weapon controversies]]
[[Category:Viral videos]]
[[Category:Taser]]

[[fr:Incident au taser à l'Université de Floride]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
