<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="1331235" ns="0" title="Parental controls"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{About|computer options|the TV series|Parental Control|the software included with Windows Vista and Windows 7|Windows Parental Controls}}
{{Multiple issues |original research=July 2011 |pov-check=July 2011 |refimprove=May 2009}}

&lt;!-- Deleted image removed: [[Image:Screenshot parental controls panel.jpg|right|200px||thumb|Parental Control panel in Microsoft [[Windows Vista]] operating system.|{{deletable image-caption|1=Wednesday, 16 January 2008}}]] --&gt;

'''Parental controls''' are features which may be included in [[digital television]] services, [[Video game|computer and video games]], [[mobile phone]]s and [[computer software]]. Parental controls fall into roughly four categories, ''[[Content-control software|content filters]]'', which limit access to [[age appropriate]] content, ''usage controls'', which constrain the usage of these devices such as placing time-limits on usage or forbidding certain types of usage, ''[[Computer Usage Company|computer usage management tools]]'', which allow parents to enforce learning time into child computing time, and ''[[monitoring]]'', which can track location and activity when using the devices.

Content filters were the first popular type of parental controls to limit access to Internet content. Also television stations began introducing [[V-Chip]] technology to limit access to television content. Controls are now being applied to content ranging from explicit songs to objectionable movies available for purchase online. Usage controls are increasing in sophistication; examples include turning devices off during specific times of day, limiting the volume of the music playing in the car, and with GPS technology becoming affordable, it is now possible to know where a child is at curfew.

== Overview ==
Several techniques exist aimed at creating parental controls for blocking websites. Add-on parental control software may monitor [[API]] in order to observe applications such as a web browser or Internet chat application and  to intervene according to certain criteria, such as a match in a database of banned words. Virtually all parental control software includes a password or other form of authentication to prevent unauthorised users from disabling it.

Techniques involving a [[proxy server]] are also used. A web browser is set to send requests for web content to the proxy server rather than directly to the web server intended. The proxy server then fetches the web page from the web server on the web browser's behalf and passes on the content to the browser. Proxy servers can inspect the data being sent and received and intervene depending on various criteria relating to content of the page or the URL being requested, for example, using a database of banned words or banned URLs. The proxy method's major disadvantage is that it requires that the client application to be configured to utilize the proxy, and if it is possible for the user to reconfigure applications to access the Internet directly rather than going through the proxy then this control is easily bypassed. Proxy servers themselves may be used to circumvent parental controls. There are other techniques used to bypass parental controls.

Computer usage management method, unlike content filters, is focused on empowering the parents to balance the computing environment for children by regulating gaming. The main idea of these applications is to allow parents to enforce learning component into the computing time of children, where children must earn gaming time while working through educational contents.

==Parental controls on mobile phones==

The increased use of mobile phones that include full featured internet browsers and downloadable applications has created a demand for parental controls on these mobile, smart handhelds.  In November 2007, Verizon was the first carrier to offer age-appropriate content filters as well as the first to offer content-generic content filters recognizing that mobile phones were used to access all manner of content from movies and music to short-code programs and websites. In June 2009, on the iPhone OS version 3.0, Apple Computer was the first mobile device company to provide a built in mechanism on iPhone and iPod Touch devices to create age brackets for users that would block unwanted applications from being downloaded to the device.  The introduction of a safe mobile web browser, called [http://www.surfbalance.com Surfbalance] Kids browser for iPhone in June 2009, filled a need for parental web controls in the mobile phone arena.

Mobile phone software from [http://www.mymobilewatchdog.com My Mobile Watchdog] enables parents to restrict which applications their child can access while also allowing parents to monitor text messages, phone logs, MMS pictures, and other transactions occurring on their child's mobile phone.

[http://mylockster.blogspot.com Lockster app] enables parents to set time limit on the usage of mobile phones.

[http://www.myfone.mobi/learn_more.html Myfone.mobi] provide free information on the dangers of mobile phone use by children.  Topics include Phone Bullying, Sexting, Grooming and other inappropriate behaviour. Software from  [http://www.myfone.mobi Myfone.mobi] allows parents to track the exact location of their children every 15 minutes as well as monitor calls in and out and the content of texts in and out.

==Parental controls on the iPod Touch==
There are also parental controls on the [[iPod Touch]]. Parents can block the icons for some apps, block access to the Internet or [[YouTube]], and restrict the apps and movies that may be downloaded.

==Commonly used methods to bypass parental controls==

Several methods of bypassing parental controls are commonly used. If the filtering software is located locally within the computer, all Internet software can be easily bypassed by booting up the computer in question from alternative media or with an alternative operating system. However, if the computer's [[BIOS]] is configured to disallow booting from removable media, and if changes to the BIOS are prohibited without proper authentication, then this approach is not available.

Another technique involves using external proxy servers or other servers. The user sends requests to the external server which retrieves content on the user's behalf. Filtering software may then never be able to know which URLs the user is accessing, as all communications are with the one external server and filtering software never sees any communications with the web servers from which content really originated. To counter this, filtering  software may also block access to popular proxies. Additionally, filtering systems which only permit access to a set of allowed URLs will not permit access anything outside this list, including proxy servers.

==Criticisms of parental controls==
{{Criticism section|date=July 2011}}
An argument that is present is that: children will get access to questionable content, either through friends or by cracking the software.  Parenting organizations{{Who|date=July 2011}} feel, especially with older children and adolescents, that the best way to keep kids from viewing questionable content is by teaching kids about the hazards of viewing such content.{{Citation needed|date=July 2011}}

==Video game systems that have used parental controls==
''Listed in chronological order''
*[[PlayStation 3]]
*[[PlayStation 2]] (only for DVDs)
*[[PlayStation Portable]]
*[[Xbox]]
*[[Xbox 360]]
*[[Wii]]
*[[Nintendo DSi]]
*[[Nintendo 3DS]]

==Operating systems with parental controls==
{{Expand section|date=May 2007}}
Below is a list of [[operating systems]] which currently have parental control features:

*[[Mac OS X]] (10.3-10.7)
*[[Windows Vista]]&lt;ref&gt;http://windows.microsoft.com/en-US/windows-vista/Set-up-Parental-Controls&lt;/ref&gt;
*[[Windows 7]]
*[[Mandriva Linux]] (via drakguard)
*[[Linux]] using [[DansGuardian]] either on the machine or, with Windows or Mac machines, as a server/proxy.

==Tools for parents for social networking sites==
There are tools available for parents to monitor their children's activities within social networking sites.&lt;ref&gt;CNN, [http://www.cnn.com/2010/TECH/web/10/04/cyber.bullying.tips/] How to protect your child from online bullies, by Doug Gross, 10/06&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Baltimore Sun, [http://weblogs.baltimoresun.com/news/education/blog/2010/06/new_tools_to_monitor_bullying.html] New tools to monitor bullying, predators on Facebook&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;USA Today, [http://content.usatoday.com/communities/technologylive/post/2010/06/new-monitoring-tool-helps-parents-stop-facebook-bullies-and-predators/1] Monitoring tool helps parents stop Facebook bullies and predators&lt;/ref&gt;

* [http://www.gogostat.com/home/parental GoGoStat Parental Guidance]
* [http://www.socialshield.com/ SocialShield]

==TV channel blocker==
The TV channel blocker (TVCB) is a parental control add-on unit can be mounted at the tap output or at the consumer's residence of their television, it can allow parents to block unwanted cable channels from your cable lineup or antenna reception.  Block as many analog cable channels as you would like from channel 2 through channel, a  padlock can be added to block from changing the settings. It also includes the TV Timer bob and will allow to block out certain channels during certain times of the day.  The device can only be ordered online&lt;ref&gt; [http://www.familysafemedia.com/channel_blocker.html TV Channel Blocker] &lt;/ref&gt;

==See also==
* [[Content-control software]]
* [[David Burt (filtering advocate)|David Burt]]
* [[Internet censorship]]
* [[Motion picture rating system]]
* [[Television rating system]]
* [[V-Chip]]
* [[Videogame Rating Council]]

==External links==
* [http://www.1800cabletv.com/articles/cable-providers-parental-controls.aspx Cable Providers and Parental Controls]
* [http://www.smartmoney.com/dealoftheday/index.cfm?story=20070316 Deal of the Day:  New Technology to Keep Track of Your Kids], by Kelli B. Grant, ''SmartMoney'', 16 Mar 2007
* [http://windows.microsoft.com/en-us/windows7/Set-up-Parental-Controls Windows 7 Parental Controls Setup]
*[http://www.fbi.gov/kids/k5th/safety2.htm An FBI report about child Internet safety]
* [http://www.isoftwise.com/index.php?option=com_content&amp;view=article&amp;id=18:learn-the-lingo-that-kids-and-adults-are-using-to-text-message&amp;catid=10:family-safety&amp;Itemid=11 Text message lingo]
* A number of Corporate Sites on Parental Controls: [http://www.parentalcontrolcenter.com Parental Control Tools Education site],  [http://www.surfbalance.com Use of parental controls on iPhone mobile device][http://www.dolphinsecure.com Parental Controlled Browser and Social Network]
* An Open Source project: [https://sourceforge.net/projects/mtime/ mTime at SourceForge]
* Information &amp; Advice for Parents and Teachers: [http://www.parentalcontrol.ie Threat overviews &amp; Control software download links]

==Notes==
{{Reflist}}

{{Use dmy dates|date=January 2011}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Parental Controls}}
[[Category:Internet safety]]

[[ca:Control patern]]
[[es:Control paterno]]
[[fr:Contrôle parental]]
[[ko:자녀 보호]]
[[it:Filtro famiglia]]
[[he:בקרת הורים]]
[[nl:Parental control]]
[[ja:ペアレンタルコントロール]]
[[pl:Kontrola rodzicielska]]
[[ru:Родительский контроль]]
[[fi:Lapsilukko]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
