<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="1332168" ns="0" title="1966 World Series"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Infobox World Series Expanded
  | image = 
  | year = 1966
  | champion = [[1966 Baltimore Orioles season|Baltimore Orioles]] (4)
  | champion_manager = [[Hank Bauer]]
  | champion_games = 97–63, .606, GA: 9
  | runnerup = [[1966 Los Angeles Dodgers season|Los Angeles Dodgers]] (0)
  | runnerup_manager = [[Walt Alston]]
  | runnerup_games = 95–67, .586, GA: 1½
  | date = October 5 – October 9
  | MVP = [[Frank Robinson]] (Baltimore)
  | television = [[Major League Baseball on NBC|NBC]] 
  | announcers = [[Curt Gowdy]], [[Vin Scully]] (Games 1–2) and [[Chuck Thompson]] (Games 3–4)
  | radio_network = [[Major League Baseball on NBC Radio|NBC]]
  | radio_announcers = [[Bob Prince]], [[Chuck Thompson]] (Games 1–2) and [[Vin Scully]] (Games 3–4)
  | umpires = [[Bill Jackowski]] (NL), [[Nestor Chylak]] (AL), [[Chris Pelekoudas]] (NL), [[Johnny Rice]] (AL), [[Mel Steiner]] (NL), [[Cal Drummond]] (AL)
  | HOFers = '''Orioles:''' [[Luis Aparicio]], [[Jim Palmer]], [[Brooks Robinson]], [[Frank Robinson]].&lt;br&gt;'''Dodgers:''' [[Walt Alston]] (mgr.), [[Don Drysdale]], [[Sandy Koufax]]
  | ALCS = &lt;!-- none ---&gt;
  | NLCS = &lt;!-- none ---&gt;
  | image2 = 
}}

The '''1966 World Series''' matched the [[1966 Baltimore Orioles season|Baltimore Orioles]] against the defending champion [[1966 Los Angeles Dodgers season|Los Angeles Dodgers]], with the Orioles sweeping the Series in four games to capture their first championship in franchise history. It was also the last World Series played before [[Major League Baseball|MLB]] introduced the [[Commissioner's Trophy (MLB)|Commissioner's Trophy]] [[1967 World Series|the following year]].

==Background==
Despite the general consensus that the Orioles were short of pitching when compared to the likes of [[Don Drysdale]] and [[Sandy Koufax]], Orioles pitching allowed only two runs in the entire series and ended up with a 0.50 team ERA, the second lowest in World Series history.  The Orioles scored more runs in the first inning of the first game than the Dodgers would score in the whole series.

The Dodgers' young [[Jim Barbieri]] became the first player to play in both a [[Little League World Series]] and also the Major League [[World Series]] when he pinch-hit for a Dodger relief pitcher in Game 1 of the series. A strikeout, it was the final appearance of his brief career.

==Summary==
{{MLB Playoff Summary
| summary = AL [[Baltimore Orioles]] (4) vs. NL [[Los Angeles Dodgers]] (0)
| winner =
| score =
| score1 = '''Baltimore Orioles''' – 5, Los Angeles Dodgers – 2
| date1 = October 5
| loc1 = [[Dodger Stadium]]
| time1 = 2:56
| att1 = 55,941
| ref1 = &lt;ref name=&quot;Game1&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.retrosheet.org/boxesetc/1966/B10050LAN1966.htm|title=1966 World Series Game 1 - Baltimore Orioles vs. Los Angeles Dodgers|accessdate=2009-09-13|publisher=Retrosheet}}&lt;/ref&gt;
| score2 = '''Baltimore Orioles''' – 6, Los Angeles Dodgers – 0
| date2 = October 6
| loc2 = Dodger Stadium
| time2 = 2:26
| att2 = 55,947
| ref2 = &lt;ref name=&quot;Game2&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.retrosheet.org/boxesetc/1966/B10060LAN1966.htm|title=1966 World Series Game 2 - Baltimore Orioles vs. Los Angeles Dodgers|accessdate=2009-09-13|publisher=Retrosheet}}&lt;/ref&gt;
| score3 = Los Angeles Dodgers – 0, '''Baltimore Orioles''' – 1
| date3 = October 8
| loc3 = [[Memorial Stadium (Baltimore)|Memorial Stadium]]
| time3 = 1:55
| att3 = 54,445
| ref3 = &lt;ref name=&quot;Game3&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.retrosheet.org/boxesetc/1966/B10080BAL1966.htm|title=1966 World Series Game 3 - Los Angeles Dodgers vs. Baltimore Orioles|accessdate=2009-09-13|publisher=Retrosheet}}&lt;/ref&gt;
| score4 = Los Angeles Dodgers – 0, '''Baltimore Orioles''' – 1
| date4 = October 9
| loc4 = Memorial Stadium
| time4 = 1:45
| att4 = 54,458
| ref4 = &lt;ref name=&quot;Game4&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.retrosheet.org/boxesetc/1966/B10090BAL1966.htm|title=1966 World Series Game 4 - Los Angeles Dodgers vs. Baltimore Orioles|accessdate=2009-09-13|publisher=Retrosheet}}&lt;/ref&gt;
}}

==Matchups==
===Game 1===
Wednesday, October 5, 1966 at [[Dodger Stadium]] in [[Los Angeles, California]]
{{Linescore|
|Road='''Baltimore'''|RoadAbr=BAL
|R1=3|R2=1|R3=0|R4=1|R5=0|R6=0|R7=0|R8=0|R9=0|RR=5|RH=9|RE=0
|Home=Los Angeles|HomeAbr=LAD
|H1=0|H2=1|H3=1|H4=0|H5=0|H6=0|H7=0|H8=0|H9=0|HR=2|HH=3|HE=0
|RSP=|HSP=
|WP=[[Moe Drabowsky]] (1–0)|LP=[[Don Drysdale]] (0–1)|SV=
|RoadHR=[[Frank Robinson]] (1), [[Brooks Robinson]] (1)|HomeHR=[[Jim Lefebvre]] (1)
|}}

&lt;!-- '''Starting pitchers:''' [[Don Drysdale]] (13–16, [[earned run average|3.42]]), [[Dave McNally]] (13–6, 3.17) --&gt;

In the top of the first inning, after [[Luis Aparicio]] flied to right, Drysdale walked [[Russ Snyder]], and then [[Frank Robinson]] and [[Brooks Robinson]] hit back-to-back home runs to give the Orioles an early 3–0 lead. In the bottom half of the frame, McNally walked Dodger leadoff man [[Maury Wills]], who subsequently stole second. However, the Dodgers failed to score. In the second inning, with [[Andy Etchebarren]] on second base, Snyder slapped a base hit past L.A. shortstop Wills and Etchebarren scored to widen the lead to 4–0. 

However, McNally soon began to struggle with his command. In the bottom of the second inning, second baseman [[Jim Lefebvre]] tagged him for a 400-foot home run. First baseman [[Wes Parker]] hit a fair ball down the right-field foul line, but a fan reached over the wall and picked the ball out of the dirt, turning a possible triple into a ground rule double. After McNally walked [[Jim Gilliam]], [[John Roseboro]] hit a fly ball to right center, but Snyder saved at least a run with a lunging catch, and neither baserunner scored. Drysdale was pulled from the game in the third and replaced with [[Joe Moeller]], who allowed another run in the fourth when [[Davey Johnson]] scored from second on a fielder's choice by Aparicio.

With one out in the bottom of the third inning, McNally was replaced by [[Moe Drabowsky]] after loading the bases on walks. Drabowsky struck out Parker and walked Gilliam, forcing in a run, before Roseboro fouled out. Drabowsky struck out six consecutive batters (tying [[Hod Eller]]'s six in the scandal-tainted [[1919 World Series]]) in the next two innings, tying a World Series record. Drabowsky's total of 11 strikeouts in {{frac|6|2|3}} innings of relief are a record for a relief pitcher in a World Series game. The Orioles won, 5–2, and the Dodgers would not get another runner across the plate in the series.

===Game 2===
Thursday, October 6, 1966 at [[Dodger Stadium]] in [[Los Angeles, California]]
{{Linescore|
|Road='''Baltimore'''|RoadAbr=BAL
|R1=0|R2=0|R3=0|R4=0|R5=3|R6=1|R7=0|R8=2|R9=0|RR=6|RH=8|RE=0
|Home=Los Angeles|HomeAbr=LAD
|H1=0|H2=0|H3=0|H4=0|H5=0|H6=0|H7=0|H8=0|H9=0|HR=0|HH=4|HE=6
|RSP=|HSP=
|WP=[[Jim Palmer]] (1–0)|LP=[[Sandy Koufax]] (0–1)|SV=
|RoadHR=|HomeHR=
|}}

&lt;!-- '''Starting Pitchers:''' [[Sandy Koufax]] (27–9, 1.73), [[Jim Palmer]] (15–10, 3.46) --&gt;

Game 2 pitted 20-year-old Jim Palmer against the Dodgers' ace Sandy Koufax (both future members of the Hall of Fame), whose 1966 season was among his best with 27 wins, 317 strikeouts, 5 shutouts, and his career best 1.73 ERA. Palmer got into trouble in the second with two on and two out, but walked Roseboro and induced Koufax to pop up to second base. Despite the obvious mismatch, Palmer and Koufax traded zeroes on the scoreboard until the top of the fifth inning, when Koufax's defense let him down. 

[[Boog Powell]] singled, and then [[Paul Blair (baseball)|Paul Blair]] hit a routine fly ball to center, but normally reliable [[Willie Davis (baseball)|Willie Davis]] lost the ball in the sun and both runners were safe on the error. Then, Etchebarren hit another fly to center, but Davis bobbled the ball and then dropped it. Powell scored on the error, and Davis rushed the throw to third base. The throw was high, and Blair scored on the throwing error, Davis' third of the inning. Aparicio then cracked a stand-up double, scoring Etchebarren from third. Davis was charged with three errors in this inning alone, a World Series record, and all three runs were unearned.

The O's then earned one from Koufax in the sixth as [[Frank Robinson]] tripled and Powell drove him in with a single to right-center. Johnson followed with a single to right, and the runners advanced on an error by [[Ron Fairly]]. Koufax escaped the inning after walking Blair intentionally and getting Etchebarren to ground into a double play. Etchebarren would be the final batter that Koufax ever faced in his career. 

Koufax was replaced in the seventh by [[Ron Perranoski]], who set the Orioles down 1-2-3. They would get two from him in the eighth, however, on a walk to Frank Robinson, a single by Brooks Robinson, a [[sacrifice bunt]] from Powell and a Johnson single off of Perranoski's shins. Perranoski threw the ball away in a desperate play for an out at first, and Brooks scored on the error. Palmer completed the shutout when Roseboro popped to Aparicio, the Orioles' shortstop. Jim Palmer, just nine days shy of his 21st birthday, became the youngest pitcher to throw a [[shutout|complete game shutout]] in the World Series. Baltimore won by a decisive 6–0 score, and took a 2–0 lead in the Series.  The Dodgers tied the 1906 [[Chicago White Sox]] for most errors by a team in a game in the Series when the Sox made 6 errors against the [[Chicago Cubs]] in Game 5 of the [[1906 World Series]].

===Game 3===
Saturday, October 8, 1966 at [[Memorial Stadium (Baltimore)|Memorial Stadium]] in [[Baltimore, Maryland]]
{{Linescore|
|Road=Los Angeles|RoadAbr=LAD
|R1=0|R2=0|R3=0|R4=0|R5=0|R6=0|R7=0|R8=0|R9=0|RR=0|RH=6|RE=0
|Home='''Baltimore'''|HomeAbr=BAL
|H1=0|H2=0|H3=0|H4=0|H5=1|H6=0|H7=0|H8=0|H9=X|HR=1|HH=3|HE=0
|RSP=|HSP=
|WP=[[Wally Bunker]] (1–0)|LP=[[Claude Osteen]] (0–1)|SV=
|RoadHR=|HomeHR=[[Paul Blair (baseball)|Paul Blair]] (1)
|}}

&lt;!-- '''Starting pitchers:''' [[Wally Bunker]] (10–6, 4.29), [[Claude Osteen]] (17–14, 2.85) --&gt;

The series moved to Baltimore with the Orioles enjoying a 2–0 series lead.

Wally Bunker, plagued with injuries in the regular season, retired the first three batters he faced, and pitched a six-hit, complete game gem, while Osteen allowed only three hits in seven innings. Unfortunately, one of those hits was a solo home run from [[Paul Blair (baseball)|Paul Blair]] in the fifth, which turned to be the game's only run. The Dodgers' defense woke up after Game 2's embarrassment with six-errors, and they turned several excellent plays, most notably first baseman Wes Parker's robbing [[Curt Blefary]] of a base hit with a spectacular jump to snare his sixth inning line drive. Bunker, without a complete game shutout in the regular season, completed the Orioles' second consecutive shutout in this World Series, and they won 1–0.

===Game 4===
Sunday, October 9, 1966 at [[Memorial Stadium (Baltimore)|Memorial Stadium]] in [[Baltimore, Maryland]]
{{Linescore|
|Road=Los Angeles|RoadAbr=LAD
|R1=0|R2=0|R3=0|R4=0|R5=0|R6=0|R7=0|R8=0|R9=0|RR=0|RH=4|RE=0
|Home='''Baltimore'''|HomeAbr=BAL
|H1=0|H2=0|H3=0|H4=1|H5=0|H6=0|H7=0|H8=0|H9=X|HR=1|HH=4|HE=0
|RSP=|HSP=
|WP=[[Dave McNally]] (1–0)|LP=[[Don Drysdale]] (0–2)|SV=
|RoadHR=|HomeHR=[[Frank Robinson]] (2)
|}}

&lt;!-- '''Starting Pitchers:''' [[Dave McNally]] (0–0), [[Don Drysdale]] (0–1) --&gt;

On the brink of a sweep, Game 4 was a rematch of the first game, pitting the young pitcher [[Dave McNally]] against the veteran [[Don Drysdale]], both of whom had struggled in their previous match-up. However, in this outing, both pitchers excelled as Drysdale and McNally each allowed only four hits. Again, the only run scored was on a solo home run, this one by [[Frank Robinson]]. [[Willie Davis (baseball)|Willie Davis]] redeemed himself from his miserable Game 2 defensive blunders by robbing [[Boog Powell]] of a home run in the fourth, but to no avail as [[Paul Blair (baseball)|Paul Blair]] did the same to [[Jim Lefebvre]] in the eighth, and the Dodgers were shut out for the third consecutive time and for 33 consecutive innings, a World Series record. The Orioles won Game 4, 1–0, and swept the World Series. 

The Orioles became the first non-Yankee [[American League]] team to win the [[World Series]] since the [[1948 Cleveland Indians season|1948 Cleveland Indians]]. The Orioles also became the last of the original eight [[American League]] teams to win a World Series at all. The Orioles had played in the Fall Classic as the St. Louis Browns in the [[1944 World Series]], in which they were also the last of the original eight AL teams to ''participate'' in a World Series.

[[Frank Robinson]] became the first non-pitcher from a winning World Series team to win the World Series MVP trophy. ([[Bobby Richardson]] had won it for the Series-losing [[New York Yankees]] in the [[1960 World Series]].)

==Composite box==
1966 World Series '''(4–0): [[Baltimore Orioles]] (A.L.)''' over [[Los Angeles Dodgers]] (N.L.)
{{Linescore|
|Road='''[[Baltimore Orioles]]'''
|R1=3|R2=1|R3=0|R4=2|R5=4|R6=1|R7=0|R8=2|R9=0|RR=13|RH=24|RE=0
|Home='''[[Los Angeles Dodgers]]'''
|H1=0|H2=1|H3=1|H4=0|H5=0|H6=0|H7=0|H8=0|H9=0|HR=2|HH=17|HE=6
{{!-}}
{{!}} style=&quot;text-align:left;&quot; colspan=&quot;13&quot; {{!}} &lt;small&gt;'''Total attendance''': 220,791 &amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;'''Average attendance''': 55,198&lt;/small&gt;
{{!-}}
{{!}} style=&quot;text-align:left;&quot; colspan=&quot;13&quot; {{!}} &lt;small&gt;'''Winning player’s share''': $11,683 &amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;'''Losing player’s share''': $8,189&lt;/small&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;wsshares&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.baseball-almanac.com/ws/wsshares.shtml|title=World Series Gate Receipts and Player Shares|accessdate=2009-06-14|publisher=Baseball Almanac}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|}}

==Broadcasting==
[[Major League Baseball on NBC|NBC]] broadcast the Series on both television and radio. In prior years, the local announcers for both the home and away team had split calling the play-by-play for the telecast of each Series game; however, beginning this year and continuing through {{wsy|1976}}, only the home-team announcer would do TV for each game, splitting play-by-play and color commentary with a neutral NBC announcer, while the visiting-team announcer would help call the radio broadcast. Thus, in 1966 NBC's [[Curt Gowdy]] (completing his first season as the network's lead baseball voice) worked the telecasts the Dodgers' [[Vin Scully]] for the games in Los Angeles and with the Orioles' [[Chuck Thompson]] for the games in Baltimore. [[Bob Prince]], in turn, worked the radio broadcasts with Thompson (in Los Angeles) and Scully (in Baltimore).

==Aftermath==
This was the last hurrah for the Dodgers of this era. In an eight-year span from 1959 to 1966, they played in four World Series, winning three of them. In addition, they finished second twice (once losing in a playoff). [[Sandy Koufax]], though arguably at the peak of his career, was to announce his retirement following the World Series due to chronic arthritis and bursitis in his pitching elbow. In addition, the Dodgers' team captain and sparkplug [[Maury Wills]] would be traded to the [[Pittsburgh Pirates]] in December, while the N.L. batting champion for 1962 and '63, Tommy Davis, would be traded to the [[New York Mets]]. The Dodgers finished in eighth place in 1967, and in seventh in 1968, before a new crop of youngsters led them back to contention for about ⅔ of the {{By|1969}} season. From 1969 to 1983, the Dodgers finished first in the [[National League West|National League Western Division]] five times, and finished second seven times, with the [[Cincinnati Reds]] dominating that division. In this period, the Dodgers won one [[World Series]] and won four [[National League Championship Series]].

Meanwhile, the Baltimore Orioles became a dominant team in the late 60s and early 70s. Injuries slowed them down in 1967 and 1968, but they won three straight A.L. pennants from 1969 through '71, including the [[1970 World Series]]. The Orioles won the [[American League East|American League Eastern Division]] again in 1973 and 1974, but they fell to the [[Oakland Athletics]] dynasty, which went to the World Series three years in a row. The Orioles returned to the [[1979 World Series|World Series in 1979]], but they lost to the Pirates in seven games. The Orioles won at least 90 games in all but three seasons from 1968 through 1983, culminating in their [[1983 World Series]] victory over the Phillies.

==Low scoring==
*The [[Baltimore Orioles]] shut the [[Los Angeles Dodgers]] out for a [[World Series]] record 33 consecutive innings - from the fourth inning of Game 1 to the end of Game 4.
*The [[Baltimore Orioles]] pitching staff only allowed two (2) earned runs and finished with a team [[earned run average|ERA]] of 0.50. 

'''Top American League ''World Series'' pitching staffs through 1966:'''
{|
|-
! Rank !! A.L. Teams !! ERA !! Year
|-
| 1 || [[Baltimore Orioles]] || 0.50 || 1966
|-
| 2 || [[Cleveland Indians]] || 0.89 || [[1920 World Series|1920]]
|-
| 3 || [[New York Yankees]] || 1.22 || [[1939 World Series|1939]]
|-
| 4 || [[Oakland Athletics|Philadelphia Athletics]] || 1.29 || [[1911 World Series|1911]]
|-
| 5 || [[Oakland Athletics|Philadelphia Athletics]] || 1.47 || [[1905 World Series|1905]]
|-
|&amp;nbsp;|| [[Boston Red Sox]] || 1.47 || [[1916 World Series|1916]]
|-
| 7 || [[Chicago White Sox]] || 1.50 || [[1906 World Series|1906]]
|-
| 8 || [[Boston Red Sox]] || 1.70 || [[1918 World Series|1918]]
|-
| 9 || [[Oakland Athletics|Philadelphia Athletics]] || 1.73 || [[1930 World Series|1930]]
|-
| 10 || [[New York Yankees]] || 1.80 || [[1941 World Series|1941]]
|}

==Notes==
{{Reflist|2}}

==References==
*Neft, David S., and Richard M. Cohen. ''The World Series.'' 1st ed. New York: St Martins, 1990.
*Reichler, Joseph, ed. (1982). ''The Baseball Encyclopedia'' (5th ed.), p.&amp;nbsp;2174. MacMillian Publishing. ISBN 0-02-579010-2.
*{{cite web |author=Forman, Sean L. |title=1966 World Series |date= |work=Baseball-Reference.com - Major League Statistics and Information. |url=http://www.baseball-reference.com/postseason/1966_WS.shtml |accessdate=2007-12-09}}

==External links==
{{WSExtLinks|year=1966}}

{{WorldSeries}}
{{Baltimore Orioles}}
{{Los Angeles Dodgers}}
{{1966 Baltimore Orioles}}
{{1966 MLB season by team}}
{{Major League Baseball on NBC}}
{{Major League Baseball on NBC Radio}}

[[Category:1966 Major League Baseball season|World Series]]
[[Category:Baltimore Orioles postseason]]
[[Category:Los Angeles Dodgers postseason]]
[[Category:World Series]]

[[ja:1966年のワールドシリーズ]]
[[ru:Мировая серия 1966]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
