<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="1341129" ns="0" title="A Night in Sickbay"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Infobox television episode
|Title = A Night In Sickbay
|Image=[[Image:Kreetassan Apology Closeup.jpg|270px]]
|Caption = Captain Archer delivers an intricate ritual apology
|Series = [[Star Trek:Enterprise]]
|Episode = 30
|Production = 205
|Airdate = October 16, 2002
|Writer =[[Rick Berman]]&lt;BR/&gt;[[Brannon Braga]]
|Director = [[David Straiton]]
|Guests = [[Vaughn Armstrong]]
|Prev = [[Dead Stop]]
|Next = [[Marauders (Star Trek: Enterprise)|Marauders]]
| Episode list = [[List of Star Trek: Enterprise episodes|List of ''Star Trek: Enterprise'' episodes]]
}}
__NOTOC__
'''&quot;A Night In Sickbay&quot;''' is the title of the 30th episode (production #205) of the [[Television program|television series]] ''[[Star Trek: Enterprise]]'' which originally aired on October 16, 2002 in the [[United States]].

This episode was nominated for a [[Hugo Award]] and received the highest number of viewers in season 2: 6.2 million according to TrekToday.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.trektoday.com/news/231002_02.shtml TrekToday - 'Sickbay' Cures Ratings Woes&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;

==Plot summary==
A light-weight, [[Comedy-drama|dramedy]] episode, &quot;A Night in Sickbay&quot; sees Captain [[Jonathan Archer]] dealing with the [[List of Star Trek races#Kreetassan|Kreetassans]]—a race of grouchy, officious aliens whom Archer and his crew originally met in the episode &quot;[[Vox Sola]]&quot;. This time, the Kreetassans are insulted and negotiations for a badly needed plasma injector break down when Archer's [[dog]], [[Jonathan Archer#Porthos|Porthos]], [[Territory (animal)|urinates]] on one of the aliens' sacred trees. A secondary subplot sees Archer and Dr. [[Phlox (Star Trek)|Phlox]] tending to Porthos after the dog contracts a potentially deadly virus on the planet, and Archer is so consumed with worry that he ends up spending the night in Sick Bay to look after his ailing pet. A tertiary subplot has Archer dealing with unbidden sexual dreams about his first officer, [[T'Pol]]. Through it all, Archer struggles to reach an emotional understanding with Phlox and T'Pol, as the two alien crew members have little grasp of just how important pets are to humans and Phlox keeps offering Archer unwanted advice about dealing with his new feelings for T'Pol. T'Pol also keeps urging Archer to apologize to the Kreetassans for Porthos' behavior, but Archer resists doing this because he blames them for Porthos' life-threatening illness.

In the end, Porthos recovers from his illness. Swallowing his pride, the captain goes down to the Kreetassan capital city and delivers an intricate ritual apology which involves cutting off slices of a tree trunk with a [[chainsaw]], arranging the pieces of wood in a complex pattern on the ground, and intoning ceremonial phrases in the Kreetassan language. Having mollified the Kretassans, the ''Enterprise'' crew finally manage to procure not one, but three plasma injectors from the high-strung aliens.

==References==
{{Reflist}}

==External links==
*{{imdb title|id=0572172}}
*{{TV.com episode|183018}}
*{{memoryalpha}}
*{{StarTrek.com link|ENT|125906}}
* [http://www.agonybooth.com/recaps/Star_Trek/Enterprise/A_Night_in_Sickbay.aspx A Night in Sickbay] reviewed in [http://www.agonybooth.com The Agony Booth]

{{Star Trek ENT S2}}
{{Star Trek ENT}}
{{Star Trek}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Night In Sickbay, A}}
[[Category:Star Trek: Enterprise episodes]]
[[Category:2002 television episodes]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
