<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="1346366" ns="0" title="Yick Wo v. Hopkins"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Refimprove|date=November 2009}}
{{SCOTUSCase
  |Litigants=Yick Wo v. Hopkins
  |Litigants2=Wo Lee v. Hopkins
  |SubmitDate=April 14
  |SubmitYear=1886
  |DecideDate=May 10
  |DecideYear=1886
  |FullName=Yick Wo v. Hopkins, Sheriff
  |USVol=118
  |USPage=356
  |Citation=6 S. Ct. 1064; 30 L. Ed. 220; 1886 U.S. LEXIS 1938
  |Prior=''In re Yick Wo'', writ of habeas corpus denied, 9 P. 139 (Cal. 1885); ''In re Wo Lee'', writ of habeas corpus denied, 26 F. 471 (D. Cal. 1886)
  |Subsequent=
  |Holding=Racially discriminatory application of a facially neutral statute violates the Equal Protection Clause of the Fourteenth Amendment.  Supreme Court of California and Circuit Court for the District of California reversed.
  |SCOTUS=1882-1887
  |Majority=Matthews
  |JoinMajority=''all''
  |LawsApplied=[[Fourteenth Amendment to the United States Constitution|U.S. Const. amend. XIV]]
}}
'''''Yick Wo v. Hopkins''''', [[Case citation|118 U.S. 356]] (1886),&lt;ref name=&quot;citation&quot;&gt;{{caselaw source
 |case=''Yick Wo v. Hopkins'', 118 U.S. 356 (1886)
 |findlaw=http://caselaw.lp.findlaw.com/scripts/getcase.pl?navby=CASE&amp;court=US&amp;vol=118&amp;page=356
 |justia=http://supreme.justia.com/us/118/356/case.html
}}&lt;/ref&gt; was the first case where the [[United States Supreme Court]]  ruled that a law that is race-neutral on its face, but is administered in a prejudicial manner, is an infringement of the [[Equal Protection Clause]] in the [[Fourteenth Amendment to the United States Constitution|Fourteenth Amendment]] to the [[U.S. Constitution]].

==Background==
In the 1880s, [[Chinese immigration to the United States|Chinese immigrants to California]] faced many legal and economic hurdles, including discriminatory provisions in the [[California Constitution]].  As a result, they were excluded, either by law or by bias, from many professions.  Many turned to the [[laundry]] business and in [[San Francisco]] about 89% of the laundry workers were of Chinese descent. 

In 1880, the city of San Francisco passed an ordinance that persons could not operate a laundry in a wooden building without a permit from the [[Board of Supervisors]]. The ordinance conferred upon the Board of Supervisors the discretion to grant or withhold the permits.  At the time, about 95% of the city's 320 laundries were operated in wooden buildings.  Approximately two-thirds of those laundries were owned by Chinese persons.  Although most of the city's wooden building laundry owners applied for a permit, none were granted to any Chinese owner, while only one out of approximately eighty non-Chinese applicants was denied a permit.

Yick Wo (益和, Pinyin: ''Yì Hé'', [[Americanization]]: Lee Yick), who had lived in [[California]] and had operated a laundry in the same wooden building for many years and held a valid license to operate his laundry issued by the Board of Fire-Wardens, continued to operate his laundry and was convicted and fined $10.00 for violating the [[local ordinance|ordinance]].  He sued for a writ of ''[[habeas corpus]]'' after he was imprisoned in default for having refused to pay the fine.

==The California Statute at Issue==
Order No. 156, passed May 26, 1880

:SEC. 1. It shall be unlawful, from and after the passage of this order, for any person or persons to establish, maintain, or carry on a laundry within the corporate limits of the city and county of San Francisco without having first obtained the consent of the board of supervisors, except the same be located in a building constructed either of brick or stone.

:SEC. 2. It shall be unlawful for any person to erect, build, or maintain, or cause to be erected, built, or maintained, over or upon the roof of any building now erected or which may hereafter be erected within the limits of said city and county, any scaffolding without first obtaining the written permission of the board of supervisors, which permit shall state fully for what purpose said scaffolding is to be erected and used, and such scaffolding shall not be used for any other purpose than that designated in such permit.

:SEC. 3. Any person who shall violate any of the provisions of this order shall be deemed guilty of a misdemeanor, and upon conviction thereof shall be punished by a fine of not more than one thousand dollars, or by imprisonment in the county jail not more than six months, or by both such fine and imprisonment.

==Issue before the Court==
The state argued that the ordinance was strictly one out of concern for safety, as laundries of the day often needed very hot stoves to boil water for laundry, and indeed laundry fires were not unknown and often resulted in the destruction of adjoining buildings as well.  

However, the petitioner pointed out that prior to the new ordinance, the inspection and approval of laundries in wooden buildings had been left up to fire wardens.  Yick Wo's laundry had never failed an inspection for fire safety.  Moreover, the application of the prior law focused only on laundries in crowded areas of the city, while the new law was being enforced on isolated wooden buildings as well.  The law also ignored other wooden buildings where fires were common—even cooking stoves posed the same risk as those used for laundries.

==Opinion of the Court==
{{Unreferenced section|date=November 2009}}
The Court, in a unanimous opinion written by [[Stanley Matthews (lawyer)|Justice Matthews]], found that the ''administration'' of the statute in question was discriminatory and that there was therefore no need to even consider whether the ordinance itself was lawful. Even though the Chinese laundry owners were usually not American [[citizens]], the court ruled they were still entitled to equal protection under the Fourteenth Amendment. Justice Matthews also noted that the court had previously ruled that it was acceptable to hold administrators of the law liable when they abused their authority. He denounced the law as a blatant attempt to exclude Chinese from the laundry trade in San Francisco, and the court struck down the law, ordering dismissal of all charges against other laundry owners who had been jailed.

==Legacy==
''Yick Wo'' had little application shortly after the decision. In fact, it was not long after that the Court developed the &quot;separate but equal&quot; doctrine in ''[[Plessy v. Ferguson]]'', [[Case citation|163 U.S. 537]] (1896), in practice allowing discriminatory treatment of [[African Americans]]. ''Yick Wo'' was never applied at the time to [[Jim Crow laws]] which, although also racially neutral, were in practice discriminatory against blacks. However, by the 1950s, the [[Warren Court]] used the principle established in ''Yick Wo'' to strike down several attempts by states and municipalities in the [[Deep South]] to limit the political rights of blacks. ''Yick Wo'' has been cited in well over 150 Supreme Court cases since it was decided.

''Yick Wo'' is cited in ''[[Hirabayashi v. United States]]'' (320 US 81, 1943) to recognize that: &quot;Distinctions between citizens solely based because of their ancestry are by their very nature odious to a free people whose institutions are founded upon the doctrine of equality. For that reason, legislative classification or discrimination based on race alone has often been held to be a denial of equal protection.&quot; However, the US Supreme Court upheld the conviction of [[Gordon Hirabayashi]], the [[Japanese American]] who tested the curfew law and refused to register for the forced internment of people of Japanese descent during [[World War II]].

In [[San Francisco]] there is a public school named [[Yick Wo Alternative Elementary School]] in honor of Yick Wo.

==See also==
{{Portalbox|San Francisco Bay Area|Biography|Discrimination|Asian Americans}}
*[[Chinese American]]
*[[Chinese Hand Laundry Alliance]]
*[[List of United States Supreme Court cases, volume 118]]
{{-}}

==References==
{{reflist}}

==External links==
{{wikisource}}
*Background [http://usinfo.state.gov/usa/infousa/facts/democrac/64.htm]
* Chin, Gabriel J. (2007), [http://papers.ssrn.com/sol3/papers.cfm?abstract_id=1075563''Unexplainable on Grounds of Race: Doubts About ''Yick Wo], Arizona Legal Studies Working Paper No. 30-07.
* [http://www.lawnix.com/cases/yick-wo-hopkins.html Case Brief for Yick Wo v. Hopkins at Lawnix.com]
*[http://sunnylandsclassroom.org/Asset.aspx?id=1475 A documentary on Yick Wo v. Hopkins]
{{Chinese American|state=collapsed}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Yick Wo V. Hopkins}}
[[Category:Chinese American history]]
[[Category:History of civil rights in the United States]]
[[Category:United States civil rights case law]]
[[Category:United States Fourteenth Amendment case law]]
[[Category:United States Supreme Court cases]]
[[Category:1886 in United States case law]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
