<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="13491002" ns="0" title="Huawei E220"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Inappropriate tone|date=January 2008}}
[[Image:Huawei E220 HSDPA USB modem.jpg|right|thumb|Huawei E220 [[HSDPA]] [[USB]] [[modem]]]]

The '''Huawei E220''' is a [[Huawei]] [[HSDPA]] access device ('''[[modem]]''') manufactured by [[Huawei]] and notable for using the [[USB]] interface (USB modem).

Technically it is a modem, USB and (due to the [[CDfs]] format) virtual [[CD-ROM]] device.

Launched on 21 June 2006&lt;ref name=&quot;pr&quot;&gt;[http://www-cnc.huawei.com/mobileweb/en/news/view.do?id=281&amp;cid=61&amp;type=0 Huawei Terminal&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;, the device is used for wireless [[Internet]] access using [[3.5G]], [[3G]], or [[2G]] mobile telephony networks.  It supports [[UMTS]] (including [[HSDPA]]), [[Enhanced Data Rates for GSM Evolution|EDGE]], [[GPRS]] and [[GSM]].

E220 works well with [[Linux]], as support for it was added in [[Linux kernel]] 2.6.20 (2007-02-04&lt;ref&gt;[http://kerneltrap.org/node/7670 kerneltrap.org - Linux: 2.6.20 Kernel Released]&lt;/ref&gt;), but there are workarounds for distributions with older kernels.&lt;ref name=&quot;e220kern&quot;&gt; [http://pyhumod.ooz.ie/2011/04/huawei-e220-3g-hsdpa-usb-modem-support.html Huawei E220 HSDPA USB 3G Modem in Linux&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;javaddict&quot;&gt;[http://web.archive.org/web/20080203130840/http://javaaddict.blogspirit.com/archive/2006/12/31/huawei-e220-working-on-linux.html Huawei E220 working on Linux!!! : Java Addict&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;kernel&quot;&gt;[http://www.kernel.org/pub/linux/kernel/people/gregkh/usb/2.6/2.6.20-rc1/ Kernel.org&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;cblog&quot;&gt;[http://cnapagoda.blogspot.com/2008/10/huawei-e220-modem-on-ubuntu.html Huawei E220 working on Ubuntu!!! &lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;  The card is also supported by Vodafone Mobile Connect Card driver for Linux, and it is possible to monitor the signal strength through other Linux applications.&lt;ref name=&quot;linuxsignal&quot;&gt;[http://mybroadband.co.za/vb/archive/index.php/t-70602.html Huawei E620 - pppd dies after disconnecting monitor on /dev/ttyUSB2 [Archive&amp;#93; - ADSL &amp; Broadband Forums - Internet, Gaming, Hardware, Software&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;

Most 3G network operators bundle the device with a contract, with some operators [[simlock]]ing&lt;ref name=&quot;simlock&quot;&gt;[http://mybroadband.co.za/vb/showthread.php?t=63014&amp;page=4 Vodafone Huawei E220 USB Modem - first impressions - Page 4 - ADSL &amp; Broadband Forums - Internet, Gaming, Hardware, Software&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt; the device . Unlocked and unbranded modems can also be bought from independent suppliers.

== Features ==

The device contains not only the cellular antenna but also about 22&amp;nbsp;MB (10 MB on older versions) of storage memory accessible to the operating system as a USB mass storage device&lt;ref name=&quot;ske&quot;&gt;[http://ske.sourceforge.net/html/projects/huawei/huawei_tre.html Using Huawei E220 with Debian/Linux]&lt;/ref&gt; formatted with [[CDfs]], thus emulating a CD-ROM drive. In this memory, E220 devices supplied by mobile operators may contain 3G dialer software written by the operator, while Huawei-branded devices contain Huawei's original dialing software, which they call 'Dashboard'. Huawei's Dashboard and updates for it are also available from Huawei's website&lt;ref name=&quot;flashdownload&quot;&gt;[http://www.huawei.com/mobileweb/en/doc/list.do?type=-1&amp;id=736 Huawei Terminal&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;, or the 11.313.02.00.01 firmware for 7.2 Mbit/s from NetCom (in reality '' 'flashing' '' this device means writing a firmware image to its internal flash memory, which is different from &quot;updating the dashboard&quot;, which is simply writing a new CDFS disc image to the USB mass storage device that appears in the operating system).  Flashing the firmware of this device doesn't change the USB Mass Storage memory used for the operator's software, therefore connection settings (such as APN) will be retained. When the device is first attached, Windows will automatically run the software stored on it, unless that feature has been turned off in Windows. This feature can be bypassed by pressing the Shift key while attaching the device, or by turning off the autostart feature entirely. It is possible to remove the operator branding by flashing the device with Huawei's Mobile Partner software.
Huawei does not publicly release firmware updates for its devices, only Dashboard updates. The standard way of obtaining firmware updates is through the service provider, however some firmware updates are publicly available over the Internet and some users have cross-flashed (i.e. using a firmware provided by service provider &quot;X&quot; with modem supplied by service provider &quot;Y&quot;) their modems without trouble.
Updating the modem's Dashboard does not remove or affect the network-lock (that may be in effect with modems purchased subsidized from a service provider) that prevents you from using the modem with any service provider. However updating the modem's firmware may remove this network-lock or even the opposite, turn a network-lock free modem into a locked one.

== Hardware ==

The E220 connects to the computer with a standard [[Mini USB]] cable.  The device comes with two cables, one short and one long.  The long one has two USB A interfaces, one used for data and power and the other optionally only for assistance power in case the computer is not able to provide the full 500 mA ([[ampere|milliamperes]]) required for the device to work from one USB interface only.
If your connection gets disrupted often or isn't really stable (or you can surf at slow speed only), consider using the two plug USB cable.

The E220 antenna is internal; the USB cable does not act as an antenna. The external antenna connector is not accessible without opening the device (voiding any warranty). It is still possible to connect an external antenna &lt;ref&gt;[http://www.poyntingdirect.co.za/ProductInfo.aspx?productid=ADPT-024 Poyntingdirect.co.za]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.poynting-europe.com/ Poynting-europe.com]&lt;/ref&gt; without opening the device and using the (internal) external antenna connector. Together with a high gain antenna like an [[Log-periodic antenna|LPDA]] or an [[Omnidirectional antenna|OMNI]] booster antenna and an adapter, signal strength can be considerably improved.
There is also a way to do this, open the modem, remove the small internal antenna, and solder a UMTS-antenna cable onto the board. You will invalidate the [[warranty]], but it can be a cheap and functional way to connect an external antenna.
&lt;ref&gt;[http://gniza.org/e220/DSCF0931.JPG GNIZA.org]&lt;/ref&gt;

== Software ==
[[Image:HuaweiE220.JPG|right|thumb|Vodafone [[3G]] [[USB]] [[modem]]|185px]]

The Huawei E220 includes its own [[Microsoft Windows|Windows]] software in its internal memory, which self-installs through the Windows's auto-start feature and can be [[Flash memory|flashed]] (overwritten) by the end user.  The standard software by Huawei is called ''Mobile Partner'' and is indicated by the code UTPS.

Some [[network operator]]s selling the E220, however, replace Huawei's software with their own, which often is software-locked ([[wikt:albeit|albeit]] not [[SIM-lock]]ed) to work only with the operator's own network.  End-users can use either third-party software such as [http://www.mwconn.com/ MWconn] (freeware) or alternative operating systems (e.g. [[Linux]]) to [[wikt:circumvent|circumvent]] this and use their E220 with any SIM, or flash their device with Huawei's original software.{{Dubious|date=November 2008}}

Since the release of [[Windows 7]] users have reported a number of issues that require a firmware upgrade to the modem. [[Huawei]] have released new firmware to the operators, who have generally made it available on their websites. The firmware upgrade must be carried out from a machine running [[Windows XP]] or [[Windows Vista]] and which can see the modem. Once this is complete [[Windows 7]] can see and use the modem. 

The following operator(s) are known to replace Huawei's software with their own:

* Metfone ([[Cambodia]])
* BT Business ([[UK]])
* BASE eplus ([[Germany]])
* [[Claro (mobile phone network)|Claro]] ([[Americas]])
* [[Dialog Axiata ]] ([[Sri Lanka]])
* [[Hutchison 3G|Drei]] ([[Austria]])
* [[Zain]] ([[Nigeria]])
* [[Visafone]] ([[Nigeria]])
* [[Mobilkom Austria]] ([[Austria]]) - uses software from Austrian software vendor mquadr.at&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.mquadr.at/en Mquadr.at]&lt;/ref&gt; for both its brands A1 and Bob.
* [[Movistar]] ([[Spain]], [[Argentina]])
* [[Mobily]] ([[Saudi Arabia]])
* [[VIVA - Kuwait Telecom Company|VIVA]] ([[Kuwait]])
* [[MTN Group|MTN]] ([[Uganda]])
* [[MTN Group|MTN SA]] ([[South Africa]])
* [[Mobilna Telefonija Srbije|mt:s]] ([[Serbia]])
* [[MTC Namibia|MTC]] ([[Namibia]])
* [[Mobile TeleSystems|MTS]] ([[Russia]])
* [[Multilinks TeleKoms]] ([[Nigeria]])
* [[Nawras]] ([[Oman]]) 
* [[Optimus Telecomunicações]] ([[Portugal]])
* [[Orange (telecommunications)|Orange]] ([[Austria]])
* [[Play Mobile]] ([[Poland]])
* [[Sun Cellular]] ([[Philippines]])
* [[T-Mobile]] ([[Austria]])
* [[Turkcell]] ([[Turkey]])
* [[Telkomsel]] &amp; Axis ([[Indonesia]]) (but not sim-locked)
* [[Hutchison 3G|Three]] ([[Australia]], [[Austria]], [[Italy]], [[UK]], [[Sweden]])
* [http://www.wind.com.gr/ WIND Greece]
* [[Vodacom|Vodacom SA]] ([[South Africa]])
* [[Safaricom]] ([[Kenya]])
* [[Vodafone]] - Vodafone puts on its E220 ([[Vodafone Mobile Connect USB Modem]]) its Windows [[Vodafone Mobile Connect Lite]] software, which is a lighter version of [[Vodafone Mobile Connect]]. In Windows it uses the excutable VodafoneUSBPP.[[EXE|exe]]. This device is also supported in [[Linux]], using [[Vodafone Mobile Connect Card driver for Linux]], which can be downloaded from [[Betavine|Vodafone Betavine]]. - Vodafone in New Zealand markets the Huawei D220 as the '''Vodem'''. 
- Vodafone in Fiji markets the Huawei Modem as the Flashnet.&lt;ref&gt;
{{cite journal
| last        = Saarinen
| first       = Juha
| date        = 2007-01-29
| title       = Vodafone Vodem
| journal     = New Zealand PC World
| url         = http://pcworld.co.nz/pcworld/pcw.nsf/reviews/vodafone-vodem
| accessdate  = 2010-07-22
| quote       = [...] the Vodem is actually a rebranded Huawei E220 put together in China
}}
&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[Zain]] ([[Sudan]])

=== Operating systems ===

* Microsoft Windows XP, Vista and 7
* Mac OS X v10.2.6 Jaguar or higher
* Linux 2.6.20 or higher. One can use [[wvdial]] or [[NetworkManager]] with this modem in Linux.
** [[Debian]], [[Ubuntu (operating system)|Ubuntu]] &lt;ref&gt;[https://help.ubuntu.com/community/DialupModemHowto/Huawei/E220 help.ubuntu.com Huawei E220]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://wwwu.uni-klu.ac.at/agebhard/HuaweiE220/ Huawei E220]&lt;/ref&gt; and [[gnuLinEx]]
** [[openSUSE]]
** [[Fedora (Linux distribution)|Fedora]]
** [[Debian Linux]]
** [[Arch Linux]]
** [[Ark Linux]]
** [[Gentoo Linux]]
** [[Xandros Linux]]
** [[Sabayon Linux]]
** [[Mandriva]]
** [[PcLinuxOS]]
** [[Slax]]
** [[Suse]]
** [[Guadalinex]]
** [[Caixa Mágica|Linux Caixa Mágica]]
* [[FreeBSD]]
* [[OpenSolaris]]
* [[AROS]] Poseidon stack

== Compatibility issues  ==

A number of software compatibility issues are known to exist with the E220 USB modem. This is mainly related to CD Writing software, software that creates virtual CD-ROM drives &lt;ref&gt;[http://mybroadband.co.za/vb/showthread.php?t=86757 Compatibility Issues with Huawei E220 USB Modem - ADSL &amp; Broadband Forums - Internet, Gaming, Hardware, Software&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt; and with Microsoft ActiveSync.  Also early versions of the firmware and Vodafone Connect software are incompatible with Windows Vista.  This has been remedied in later updates.

== Similar modems ==
* HSDPA:
** [[ZTE MF620]]
** VigSys VM10
** Huawei E160 (E160E, E160G, E160X, K3565)
** Huawei E169
* HSUPA: 
** [[Novatel Ovation MC950D]]
** [[Huawei E270]]

== See also ==
* [[Cellular broadband]]
* [[Cellular coverage]]
* [[Ethernet over USB]]
* [[Gammu (software)|Gammu]]
* [[Mobile Broadband Configuration Assistant]] (MBCA) for NetworkManager.
* [[Mobile Internet]]
* [[NetworkManager]]
* [[Nexus Hawk]]
* [[SIM cloning]]
* [[SMA connector]]
* [[wvdial]]
* [[WiFi]]
* [[WiMAX]]

== References ==
{{reflist}}

== External links ==
* [http://www.huaweidevice.com/worldwide/productFeatures.do?pinfoId=282&amp;treeId=282&amp;directoryId=2462 Product home page]
* [http://www.twayf.com/huawei-e220 Huawei E220 Price]
* [https://fjallfoss.fcc.gov/prod/oet/forms/blobs/retrieve.cgi?attachment_id=672546&amp;native_or_pdf=pdf E220 User Manual]
* [http://www.mcdigital.ru/stat/huawei_e220--nastrojka_i_ispolzovanie_v_srede_10_6.html E220 Mac OS X Settings (Russian)]
* [http://blog.lmartin.fr/dc2/index.php/post/2008/05/15/Cle-3G-SFR-HUAWEI-E172-sous-Mac-OS-X-105 E172 Mac OS X Settings: should work for E220 too (French)]

[[Category:Consumer electronics]]
[[Category:High-Speed Packet Access]]
[[ar:هواوي E220]]
[[es:Huawei E220]]
[[ru:Huawei E220]]
[[ja:D02HW]]
[[pl:Huawei E220]]
[[wuu:华为E220]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
