<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="1351481" ns="0" title="Indiana University South Bend"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Infobox University
|name=Indiana University South Bend&lt;br/&gt;'''IUSB'''
|image= [[File:Indiana University seal.svg|180px]]
|established=1916
|type=[[public university|public]] [[coeducational]]
|endowment=$25.6 million
|faculty=281
|chancellor=Una Mae Reck
|city=[[South Bend, Indiana|South Bend]]
|state=[[Indiana|IN]]
|country=[[USA]]
|students=8,394
|undergrad=7,496 
|postgrad=898
|campus=urban: 80 acres (0.32 km²)
|free_label=[[Sports|Athletics]]
|free=2 Division I [[National Association of Intercollegiate Athletics|NAIA]]
|mascot=Titans
|colors=[[Crimson]] and [[Cream (colour)|Cream]]
|affiliations=[[Indiana University|Indiana University System]]
|website=[http://www.iusb.edu www.iusb.edu]
}}
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;!--end of floated right section; article starts here--&gt;

'''Indiana University South Bend''' is the third largest campus of the [[Indiana University]] system. It is popularly known as IUSB or IU South Bend. It is located in [[South Bend, Indiana]], in [[St. Joseph County, Indiana]].

{{TOCleft}}

==History==

Indiana University began offering classes in South Bend in 1916 as an extension of the main campus of [[Indiana University Bloomington]]. In the Depression, the superintendent of South Bend schools asked that more classes be added for those who could not afford to attend the Bloomington campus. 

The classes were offered at Central High School in downtown South Bend and within a few years enrollment reached 500. Classes were taught by local high school teachers with master's degrees and occasionally by Bloomington faculty who traveled once a week for class.

The university appointed a resident director in 1940. Lynton Keith Caldwell, then a graduate student at the University of Chicago, took on the job. 

In 1941, Ernest Gerkin was named the first permanent full-time faculty member. 

Donald Carmony became the director from 1944 to 1950, followed by Jack Detzler, who remained in the job until 1964. 

In 1961 the first IUSB building was constructed on newly acquired land on the north shore of the [[St. Joseph River (Lake Michigan)|St. Joseph River]]. It was first named the IU Center. In 1962 it was renamed South Bend-Mishawaka Campus.

In 1965, Lester Wolfson was appointed director and assistant dean of the campus. Wolfson was named chancellor in 1969 and his leadership continued until his retirement in 1987. 

Four year degree programs were authorized in 1965 and the campus awarded its first degrees in 1967. Thirty-one students graduated the first year.

The name officially becomes Indiana University at South Bend or IUSB in 1968. The first master's degrees were conferred in 1970.

Enrollment exceeds 5,000 in 1971 and the addition to Northside Hall is opened in 1972. The purchased of the Associate Building (now known as the Administration Building) was completed in 1975. 

Groundbreaking for the Schurz Library was in 1986 and it is opened in 1989. Chancellor Wolfson retired in 1987 and H. Daniel Cohen was named chancellor. Cohen concentrated on improving facilities, grounds and programming. 

In 1994, the university purchased the former Playland Park, a 26.5 acre parcel on the south side of the St. Joseph River. Playland had been an amusement park, a golf course and a ballpark. 

Cohn resigned in 1995 and long time history professor Lester C. Lamon assumed the position of acting chancellor for two years until Kenneth L. Perrin was named chancellor.

During Perrin's tenure, two major projects were completed. First, Wiekamp Hall was opened in 1998. The building provided much needed classroom, computer lab and office space. And secondly, the $15.7 million Student Activities Center was constructed and completed in early 2002.

Perrin retired in 2002 and Una Mae Reck was named chancellor. Reck was formerly the vice president for academic affairs at the State University of New York at Fredonia.  

During Reck's administration a number of major projects were completed - student housing, a bridge connecting the campus to student housing across the St. Joseph River, the Elkhart Center and remodeling of the administration building.

==Campus==

IU South Bend is centered on a large green pedestrian mall located along the St. Joseph River. When the campus officially opened in the early 1960s, it featured two buildings: Northside Hall and Greenlawn Hall, a former [[tool and die]] factory. Growing steadily over the last 40 years, the campus now consists of 12 buildings, including the Franklin D. Schurz Library. A recent addition is the 100,000 square foot (9,000 m²) Student Activities Center (SAC) featuring [[basketball]], [[volleyball]], and [[racquetball]] courts, a walking track, a [[physical fitness|fitness]] and [[Wellness (alternative medicine)|wellness]] center, a café, a student lounge, and student life offices. The university also owns {{convert|26|acre|m2}} on the south bank of the St. Joseph River.

The SAC is the site for athletics, new student orientation, intramurals, fitness classes, exercising, meetings and recognition ceremonies. 

A pedestrian bridge that bears the words &quot;Indiana University South Bend&quot; connects the main campus with the athletic fields across the river. Construction on the bridge began in December 2005 and was completed in September 2006. On September 22, 2006, the Indiana University Board of Trustees voted to approve housing for IU South Bend, to be located across the river. The housing facilities, opened in the fall of 2008, consist of 400 beds in 8 apartment-style units across the river, along with a community building.

In August 2007 construction was completed on the {{convert|25000|sqft|m2|adj=on}} Indiana University South Bend Elkhart Center in downtown [[Elkhart, Indiana]]. The university also maintains a center at [[Plymouth, Indiana]] at Plymouth High School.

As of January 1, 2008 the IUSB campus and all properties owned by the school are non-smoking areas.

==Academics==
===Academic areas===

*'''College of Liberal Arts and Sciences'''[http://www.iusb.edu/~lasi]
**containing the Departments of Biological Sciences, Chemistry, Criminal Justice, Computer and Information Sciences, English, General Studies, History, Informatics, Mathematical Sciences, Philosophy, Physics and Astronomy, Political Science, Psychology, Sociology and Anthropology, Women's Studies, World Language Studies
*'''College of Health Sciences'''[http://www.iusb.edu/~sbhealth] containing nursing, dental education and radiography
*'''Ernestine M. Raclin School of the Arts'''[http://www.iusb.edu/~sbarts] containing Communication Arts, Music, New Media, Theater and Dance and Visual Arts
*'''School of Business and Economics'''[http://www.iusb.edu/~buse] containing accounting, advertising, banking, finance, economics, health care management, human resources management, international business, marketing, small business entrepreneurship.
*'''School of Education'''[http://www.iusb.edu/~edud]
**containing the Departments of Elementary Education and Early Childhood Education, Secondary Education and Foundations of Education, and Professional Educational Services
*'''School of Social Work'''[http://www.iusb.edu/~socw]
*'''Labor Studies Program'''[http://www.iusb.edu/~sblabor]
*'''Division of Extended Learning Services'''[http://www.iusb.edu/~extendsb/]
**containing the Office of Continuing Education [http://www.iusb.edu/~cted]

Indiana University South Bend also has a branch of the [[Purdue University]] College of Technology.

[[Image:South-bend-iusb.jpg|thumb|400px|IUSB's campus on Mishawaka Avenue in South Bend.]]

===Franklin D. Schurz Library===

The IU South Bend Libraries are the Franklin D. Schurz Library, which contains the central collections and services, and the Learning Resource Center, a specialized education library and media production center, located in Greenlawn Hall. Users at IU campus libraries across the state have access to the 7 million bound volumes and 26 million other materials in the systemwide Indiana University Libraries.

The Indiana University South Bend Archives, located in the Franklin D. Schurz Library, is the repository for materials that document the history of Indiana University South Bend as well as the histories of the larger Michiana area. In addition, the Archives operates the campus records management program on campus and holds the campus Special Collections. The main objectives of the IU South Bend Archives are to preserve, organize, and make available its materials to IU South Bend campus as well as the community at large.

==Student body==

IU South Bend's enrollment in the fall semester of 2010 was 8,590 students, of whom 69.1 percent were full time. Females account for 60.3 percent of the student population while males account for 39.7 percent. Minorities make up 14.8 percent of the student population. International students make up 2.8 percent. About $57 million in financial aid was distributed to 62 percent of students or 6,533 students in 2009-10.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.iusb.edu/fastfacts&lt;/ref&gt;

==Student life==
The Office of Student Life oversees all student-administered interests. There are a variety of on-campus and off-campus activities that are sponsored by the university. More than 80 clubs and student organizations exist, including the Student Government Association, Titan Productions, political and spiritual groups and other clubs related to student interests. 

The Student Government Association (SGA) consists of 12 senators, a president, a vice president, a secretary and a treasurer. SGA allocates student activity funds and serves as a student voice for the administration. The Student Government Judicial Council interprets and provides guidance on the SGA Constitution and Policies, consisting of a chief justice and four associate justices.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.iusb.edu/~sblife/sga.shtml&lt;/ref&gt;

Titan Productions is a student organization funded through the Student Activity Fee (SAF) whose purpose is to plan and present non-academic entertainment and programs primarily for the student body of IU South Bend. The organization hosts movie nights and special entertainment on campus.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.iusb.edu/~sblife/titan.shtml&lt;/ref&gt;

IU South Bend has a weekly student publication called The Preface. The university also publishes the annual ''Undergraduate Research Journal,'' ''New Views on Gender,'' and an award-winning literary magazine, ''Analecta.''

The Office of Student Services provides on-campus career placement center, child development center, and learning and writing centers, which offer free, on-site tutoring.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.iusb.edu/~sbinfo/alsfaq.shtml&lt;/ref&gt;

===Housing===

Fall 2008 marked the first semester of which the university offered student housing. The River Crossing Residences are beautifully designed&lt;ref&gt;http://newsinfo.iu.edu/news/page/normal/8667.html&lt;/ref&gt; and located along the St. Joseph River. They are a short walk across the pedestrian bridge from classes, the Franklin D. Schurz Library and the Student Activities Center. The housing complex includes walking trails, bicycle paths, and recreational fields.

The housing community center features wireless Internet, computer kiosks, a big screen TV, study areas, fitness equipment, and laundry facilities. The property is protected by IU South Bend Police Department and Resident Assistants live on-site. A supermarket, pharmacy, and several restaurants are within walking distance. Shopping, museums, and theatres are available by a public transportation.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.housing.iusb.edu IU South Bend Student Housing]&lt;/ref&gt;

==Athletics==
[[Image:IUSBBasketball.JPG|thumb|right|150 px|]]
The [[National Association of Intercollegiate Athletics|NAIA]] Division I Women's [[Basketball]] team qualified for the national tournament in 2005, winning the [[Chicagoland Collegiate Athletic Conference]] (CCAC). Former Head Coach [[Mary Wisniewski]] (214-135, .630) was voted CCAC Coach of the Year for the sixth time in 10 years by her peers. Wisniewski won the award in 94-95, 96-97, 97-98, 98-99, 00-01, and 04-05. Seniors Jamie Bonner and Emily Ladd earned 1st Team All-CCAC honors for the second straight year and freshmen Jessica Hass and Jennifer VanderZanden earned Honorable Mention All-CCAC honors.

The men's basketball coach is Chad Tapp and he is in his first year in 2010-11.
Women's coach is Steve Bruce. He is in his fifth year in 2010-11.
Women's volleyball coach is Jamie Ashmore and she is in the first year in 2010-11.

====Champions of Character====
IU South Bend was recognized as a [[National Association of Intercollegiate Athletics|NAIA]]Champions of Character institution in 2008-09 and 09-10.&lt;ref&gt;'NAIA Announces 2008-09 Champions of Character Institutions' http://www.championsofcharacter.org/article/10.php (Oct 23, 2009) Retrieved: Oct 29, 2011&lt;/ref&gt;

====NAIA Academic All-Americans====
For 2009-10 - Tim Davis, Dylan Morris, Betsy Grogan and Katie Hacker

====Women's Basketball====
NAIA Scholar Team Award Recipient - in 2008-09 and 09-10
Forward Katie Hacker was named an NAIA Honorable All-American 2008-09 and 09-10 season.

====Men's Basketball====
Chad Tapp named new basketball coach of men's team on May 4, 2010. He served as assistant coach at Taylor University for six seasons. At Taylor, the team won three Mid-Central Conference basketball championships.

Forward Ben Warner was anmed an NAIA Honorable Mention All-American in 2009-10.

====Women's Volleyball====

Inaugural season of varsity women's volleyball will begin in the fall of 2011. 

Jamie Ashmore named coach on May 14, 2010.

====Dodgeball====

The IU South Bend [[Dodgeball]] Club were the 2005 National Indoor [[Dodgeball]] Champions, Men’s C Division and grasped the second place B Division title the following year in 2006.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.dodgeballusa.com/results/05winternationals.html&lt;/ref&gt;

====Bowling====

The IU South Bend [[Bowling]] Club beat the [[University of Notre Dame]] by 60 pins at the 2005 Blue and Gold Classic.{{Citation needed|date=April 2009}}

==Faculty==

IU South Bend reported in fall 2010 that it employed 305 full-time faculty, lecturers, and academic administrators. The campus also had 309 part-time faculty. Of the full-time faculty, 43.75 were tenured.

Like the student body, IU South Bend's faculty is predominantly caucasian. Of full-time administrators, faculty, and lecturers, 44 were [[Asian people|Asian]], 12 were [[African-American]], five were [[Hispanic]], and 230 were &quot;other.&quot; More women than men (51%) held academic appointments at the university.

For Fall 2010, professors at IU South Bend were near the mid range in pay when compared to their counterparts in the Indiana University system. A full-time professor earned an average of $81,538, an associate professor $55,722, and an assistant professor $52.959, including salary, retirement, health insurance and other fringe benefits.

===Notable faculty===
Notable faculty of IU South Bend include [[Alexander Toradze]],&lt;ref name=&quot;toradzepianostudio.org&quot;&gt;http://www.toradzepianostudio.org/eng/presentazione.htm&lt;/ref&gt; the celebrated [[concert pianist]], master teacher&lt;ref&gt;http://www.toradzepianostudio.org/eng/toradze/presentazione.asp&lt;/ref&gt; and founder of the multi-national Toradze Piano Studio at IUSB. The Toradze studio has received high praise for their contributions to the piano world, and has developed into a worldwide touring ensemble that has gathered critical acclaim on an international level.&lt;ref name=&quot;toradzepianostudio.org&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;http://www.indiana.edu/~alldrp/members/toradze.html&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;http://www.cincinnatisymphony.org/Musicians/GuestArtists/Toradze.asp&lt;/ref&gt; Lester Lamon is a nationally known civil rights historian and author.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.iusb.edu/~sbocm/mar04/lamon.shtml&lt;/ref&gt; [[Tuck Langland]], who recently retired, is one of the premier [[sculptors]] in this country.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.gobronze.org/artists/langland/langland.html&lt;/ref&gt; Several of his pieces grace the campus.

In addition, recent examples of IU South Bend faculty scholarship receiving international recognition include Fred Naffziger’s extensive commentary on the [[BBC]], [[NBC]], [[NPR]], [[Wall Street Journal]], [[NY Times]], and [[USA Today]] regarding the [[Catholic Church]]'s [[bankruptcy]] crises&lt;ref&gt;http://www.iusb.edu/~sbocm/nov04/naffziger.shtml&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Citation
  | last = Tu
  | first = Janet
  | author-link =
  | last2 =
  | first2 =
  | author2-link =
  | title = Spokane diocese files for bankruptcy
  | newspaper = The Seattle Times
  | date = 2004-12-07
  | url = http://seattletimes.nwsource.com/html/localnews/2002111403_diocese07m.html
  | accessdate = 2010-02-20
}}&lt;/ref&gt; and Ilan Levine’s cutting-edge research on [[astroparticle physics]].&lt;ref&gt;{{Citation
  | last = Chaplin
  | first = Steve
  | author-link =
  | last2 =
  | first2 =
  | author2-link =
  | title = Ilan Levine
  | newspaper = IU Home Pages
  | date = February 2009
  | url = http://homepages.indiana.edu/web/page/normal/10104.html
  | accessdate = 2010-02-20
}}&lt;/ref&gt; Rolf Schimmrigk and Monika Lynker are associated with the discovery of [[mirror symmetry]] in [[string theory]].&lt;ref&gt;{{Citation
  | last =
  | first =
  | author-link =
  | last2 =
  | first2 =
  | author2-link =
  | title = Rolf Schimmrigk Joins Department
  | newspaper = The Printed PAGe
  | date = October 2005
  | url = http://www.iusb.edu/~iusbphys/ppage_v6n1.pdf
  | accessdate = 2010-02-20
}}&lt;/ref&gt; Biologist Andrew Schnabel’s work with [[pollen]] in an East [[African]] community is supported by a [[National Science Foundation]] grant.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.nsf.gov/awardsearch/showAward.do?AwardNumber=0722930&lt;/ref&gt; Geologist [[Henry Scott]] &lt;ref&gt;http://www.indiana.edu/~rcapub/v27n2/abstracts.shtml&lt;/ref&gt; leads a team of distinguished scientists responsible for groundbreaking discoveries about [[methane]] [[gas]].

==Notable alumni==
*[[Michael Kube-McDowell]] - science fiction author
*Ron Monsma - artist
*Peter J. Welling - illustrator/author.

==External links==
*[http://www.iusb.edu Official website]
*[http://www.iusbtitans.com/ Official athletics website]

{{coord|41.664128|-86.220833|region:US_type:edu|display=title}}

==References==
{{reflist}}

{{Public colleges and universities in Indiana}}
{{IU System}}

[[Category:Indiana University]]
[[Category:Education in South Bend, Indiana]]
[[Category:Universities and colleges in Indiana]]
[[Category:Association of American Universities]]
[[Category:American Association of State Colleges and Universities]]
[[Category:Educational institutions established in 1916]]
[[Category:Education in St. Joseph County, Indiana]]
[[Category:North Central Association of Colleges and Schools]]
[[Category:Visitor attractions in St. Joseph County, Indiana]]

[[ja:インディアナ大学サウスベンド校]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
