<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="1357586" ns="0" title="WOOD-TV"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Infobox_Broadcast |
  call_letters             = WOOD-TV|
  city                     = Grand Rapids|
  station_logo             = [[Image:WOOD.png|200px]] |
  station_slogan           = ''Watching Out For You''|
  station_branding         = WOOD-TV 8 &lt;small&gt;(general)&lt;/small&gt;&lt;br&gt;24 Hour News 8&lt;br&gt;WXSP The X &lt;small&gt;(on DT2)&lt;/small&gt;|
  analog                   = |
  digital                  = 7 ([[VHF]])|
  other_chs                = &lt;small&gt;46 ([[UHF]]) [[Muskegon, Michigan|Muskegon]]&lt;br&gt;WOGC-CA 25 [[Holland, Michigan|Holland]]&lt;/small&gt;|
  subchannels              = 8.1 [[NBC]]&lt;br&gt;[[WXSP-CD|8.2]] [[MyNetworkTV]]&lt;br&gt;8.3 [[weather radar]]|
  network                  = |
  founded                  = |
  airdate                  = [[1949 in television|August 15, 1949]]|
  location                 = [[Grand Rapids, Michigan]]|
  callsign_meaning         = '''WOOD''' refers to furniture industry|
  former_callsigns         = WLAV-TV (1949-1951)&lt;br&gt;WOOD-TV (1951-1972)&lt;br&gt;WOTV (1972-1992)|
  former_channel_numbers   = Analog:&lt;br&gt;7 (VHF, 1949-1953)&lt;br&gt;8 (VHF, 1953-2009)|
  owner                    = [[LIN TV Corporation]]|
  licensee                 = WOOD License Company, LLC|
  sister_stations          = [[WOTV]], WXSP-CD|
  former_affiliations      = [[CBS]] (1949-1960)&lt;br&gt;[[American Broadcasting Company|ABC]] (1949-1962)&lt;br&gt;[[DuMont Television Network|DuMont]] (1949-1955)&lt;br&gt;all secondary|
  effective_radiated_power = 30 [[kilowatt|kW]] |
  HAAT                     = 288 m |
  class                    = |
  facility_id              = 36838|
  coordinates              = {{coord|42|41|14|N|85|30|34|W|type:landmark_scale:2000}}|
  homepage                 = [http://www.woodtv.com/ woodtv.com/]|
}}

'''WOOD-TV''' is the [[NBC]]-affiliated [[television station]] for [[West Michigan|Southwestern Michigan]] licensed to [[Grand Rapids, Michigan|Grand Rapids]]. It broadcasts a [[High-definition television|high definition]] digital signal on [[VHF]] channel 7 from a transmitter in [[Middleville, Michigan|Middleville]] near the [[Barry County, Michigan|Barry]] and [[Allegan County, Michigan|Allegan]] County line. The station can also be seen on [[Comcast]] and [[Charter Communications|Charter]] channel 8 with high definition on Comcast digital channel 232 and Charter digital channel 788. Owned by the [[LIN TV Corporation]], WOOD-TV is sister to [[American Broadcasting Company|ABC]] affiliate [[WOTV]] and [[Class A television service|Class A]] [[MyNetworkTV]] affiliate [[WXSP-CD]]. All three share studios on College Avenue Southeast in the [[Heritage Hill Historic District (Grand Rapids, Michigan)|Heritage Hill]] section of Grand Rapids. 

[[television syndication|Syndicated]] programming on this channel includes: ''[[Inside Edition]]'', ''[[Access Hollywood]]'', ''[[The Ellen DeGeneres Show|Ellen]]'', and ''[[The Doctors (2008 TV series)|The Doctors]]''. In addition to its main signal, WOOD-TV operates Class A analog translator WOGC-CA on [[UHF]] channel 25 licensed to [[Holland, Michigan|Holland]] with a transmitter in [[Zeeland, Michigan|Zeeland]] along [[Interstate 196|I-196]] on the tower of [[WJQK]]-FM. There is also a digital repeater on channel 46 licensed to [[Muskegon, Michigan|Muskegon]] with a transmitter in the [[Wolf Lake, Michigan|Wolf Lake]] section of [[Egelston Township, Michigan|Egelston Township]].

===Digital programming===
On WOOD-DT2 is a [[SDTV|standard definition]] simulcast of sister station WXSP. On WOOD-DT3 is a 24-hour live feed of its regional [[weather radar]], plus a local feed of NOAA [[weather radio]]. This is simulcasted early Saturday and Sunday mornings on WOTV as well as overnight on WXSP.

{| class=&quot;wikitable&quot;
|-
! Virtual&lt;br&gt;channel
! [[Video resolution|Video]]
! [[Aspect ratio|Aspect]]
! Programming
|-
| 8.1 || [[1080i]] || [[16:9]] || main WOOD-TV programming/NBC HD
|-
| 8.2 || [[480i]] || [[4:3]] || WXSP-CD (MyNetworkTV)
|-
| 8.3 || [[480p]] || 4:3 || WOOD-DT3 &quot;Storm Team 8 Live Doppler Network&quot;
|}

==History==
The station signed-on August 15, 1949. It had the call sign '''WLAV-TV''' and aired an analog signal on VHF channel 7. It was the fourth television station in [[Michigan]] and the first outside of [[Detroit]]. The original owner was Grand Rapids businessman Leonard Adrian Verslius, who had signed-on Grand Rapids' second radio station, WLAV (AM 1340, now [[WJRW]]) in 1940. 

In 1951, Verslius sold the television station to Grandwood Broadcasting (a subsidiary of the Bitner Group) for [[US dollar|$]]1.37 million.  That company was owner of Grand Rapids' first radio station, [[WOOD (AM)|WOOD]]. Grandwood had applied for a television license back in 1948 but it came just after the [[Federal Communications Commission]] (FCC) imposed a freeze on new television [[construction permit]]s. In fact, WLAV-TV had been one of the last construction permits issued before the freeze. Grandwood eventually grew tired of waiting and cut a deal with Verslius to buy the station.  On October 19, WLAV changed its calls to '''WOOD-TV''' to match its radio sister and began airing from a new transmitter in Northeastern Grand Rapids. On [[1953 in television|December 8, 1953]], the station moved from channel 7 to VHF channel 8 and increased its power from 28,000 to 100,000 [[watt]]s. The channel change was promoted as &quot;Mark the date: We move to Channel Eight on December Eight&quot;. The move was to alleviate interference with WBKB-TV (now [[WLS-TV]]) in [[Chicago]]. In 1955, it moved to the current facilities in the Heritage Hill area of Grand Rapids. Its studios replaced the [[Anna Sutherland Bissell|Bissell]] mansion (of [[Bissell Inc.|Bissell vacuum]] fame) and are across the street from the Voigt House Victorian Museum. [[Time Warner|Time-Life, Inc.]] bought WOOD-AM-TV in 1957. 

WOOD-TV has been an NBC affiliate from the very beginning, although it had a secondary [[CBS]] affiliation until WKZO-TV (now [[WWMT]]) in [[Kalamazoo, Michigan|Kalamazoo]] expanded its signal to cover Grand Rapids. It also had secondary affiliations with [[American Broadcasting Company|ABC]] and [[DuMont Television Network|DuMont]]. The ABC affiliation lasted until 1962 when [[WZZM-TV]] signed-on. The DuMont affiliation ended in 1956 when that network ceased operations. Its call letters became '''WOTV''' in 1972 when WOOD-AM was sold. Time-Life also sold most of its television stations to [[McGraw-Hill]] that year, but held on to WOTV until 1983 when it was sold to LIN Broadcasting. In 1992, the station reclaimed its old call letters with WOOD-AM's permission. The station then donated the WOTV calls to WUHQ, the ABC affiliate for the southern portion of the Southwestern Michigan [[media market|market]] with whom it had a [[local marketing agreement]] (LMA) with. 

In 1994, LIN Broadcasting spun-off its television division into a separate company known as LIN TV but WOOD-TV was not included. Instead, the station became wholly owned by [[American Telephone &amp; Telegraph|AT&amp;T]] (which also owned 45 percent of LIN TV at the time) when that company absorbed the remainder of LIN Broadcasting in 1995. However, LIN TV continued to manage both WOOD-TV and WOTV. LIN TV reacquired WOOD-TV and its LMA with WOTV in 1999 when AT&amp;T sold-off its stake in the company to Hicks, Muse, Furst, and Tate (now [[HM Capital]]). On August 14, WOOD-TV became the first station in the area to air a high definition digital signal on VHF channel 7. LIN TV eventually purchased WOTV outright in 2001. On June 12, 2009 at 10 in the morning, its digital signal remained on channel 7 when the [[Digital television transition|analog to digital conversion]] was completed.

==News operation==
[[Image:West michigan open.png|thumb|right|News open.]]

Originally, WWMT (then WKZO) was Southwestern Michigan's top rated television station. In the late-1970s, WZZM took over the lead but was dethroned by WOOD-TV in the mid-1980s. For the most part, this station has maintained the number one spot since then. For a time in the mid-1990s even though most of its fellow CBS affiliates were in third place or worse, WWMT was very competitive with WZZM and WOOD-TV often resulting in close [[Nielsen ratings]] during sweeps periods. 

Since its city of license is Kalamazoo, WWMT has traditionally focused in the southern areas of the market much like WOTV did while it operated a news department. WZZM focused on the northern parts of the market, due to it's transmitter location near Grant, Michigan. Besides being a stronghold in the ratings, WOOD-TV has also been the leader in operating a news department. The station was the first to use electronic news gathering equipment in 1975. Five years later, it aired live news from outside its studios. In 1983, it introduced the area's first television [[helicopter]] to assist in coverage. 

WOOD-TV's weekday morning show premiered in 1984 and aired for a half-hour at 6:30. This was expanded to a two-hour format in 1995 along with the weekday noon and weekend 6 p.m. show adding a half-hour. As a result, ''[[NBC Nightly News]]'' is preempted on weekends. As a result of being unable to compete in the southern areas of the market, WOTV's original news department was shut down in 1990. WOOD-TV then began simulcasting some of its newscasts on that channel as well as airing specially produced newscasts covering Battle Creek and Kalamazoo. Essentially, WOTV was functioning as a news bureau for WOOD-TV. 

In 1992, WOTV brought back a full news department for a second time. However, like the previous attempt, the channel could not gain enough viewers or make a dent in the ratings. LIN TV finally decided to shut down WOTV's news operation for good in August 2003. Since then, the station has [[simulcast]] some of WOOD-TV's newscasts, but this time without any separate opens or segments. There are weeknight prime time weather updates featuring Chief Meteorologist Bill Steffen. 

Currently, only the second hour of WOOD-TV's weekday morning show and nightly newscast at 6 (first half-hour only) is simulcast on WOTV. On October 21, 2007, WOOD-TV began offering a nightly prime time broadcast at 10 on WXSP joining productions on [[Fox Network|Fox]] affiliate [[WXMI]] and [[The CW|CW]] affiliate [[WWMT-DT2]]. The entertainment and lifestyle magazine show ''eightWest'' premiered on October 5, 2009 and airs weekday mornings at 11 for an hour as well as being streamed live on the channel's website. Also on that date, WOOD-TV became the second station in southwestern Michigan to begin offering local newscasts in [[16:9]] [[enhanced definition]] [[widescreen]]. Although not truly high definition, the broadcast match the ratio of HD television screens. The simulcasts on WOTV were included in the upgrade. On October 22, 2011, WOOD-TV became the third television station in southwestern Michigan (behind Fox affiliate WXMI and CBS affiliate WWMT) to broadcast local newscasts in high definition.

''Sports Overtime'' is a weekly half-hour sports highlight show that airs Sunday nights after the 11 o'clock news. ''Football Frenzy'' is WOOD-TV's weekly highlight program covering the Friday night high school football games as well as other sports news of the day. The 11 p.m. newscast is shortened to allow ''Football Frenzy'' to air during the regular time slot. ''To The Point'' is a weekly political talk show hosted by Rick Albin that airs Sunday mornings at 10. 

WOOD-TV has the distinction of being one of the last remaining broadcast television stations in the [[United States]] currently utilizing the [[24 Hour News Source]] format which it began using in 1990. The other stations still using the format {{as of|February 2010}} are sister station CBS affiliate [[WISH-TV]] in [[Indianapolis]], ABC affiliate [[KCRG-TV]] in [[Cedar Rapids, Iowa]], and NBC affiliate [[KFDX-TV]] in [[Wichita Falls, Texas]]. In addition to featuring live regional [[National Weather Service]] radar data, this station operates its own weather radar on top of the Oakwood Manor Apartments next to its studios.
===Newscast Titles===
*''News and Events'' (1949-1959)
*''The Marlboro News'' (1959-1962)
*''The Big News'' (1962-1972)
*''6pm Report/11 Report'' (1970s)
*''News in Action'' (1972-1976)
*''[[NewsCenter]] 8'' (1976-1984)
*''News 8'' (1984-1995)
*''24-Hour News 8'' (1995-present)
===Station Slogans===
*''We're The Best on TV-8'' (1977-1981)
*''The Team To Watch'' (1981-1984)
*''Come on Home to TV-8'' (1987-1988, localized version of NBC ad campaign)
*''Come Home to the Best, Only on TV-8'' (1988-1989, localized version of NBC ad campaign)
*''The First Team for News in West Michigan'' (early-mid 1990s)
*''First. Best. Live.'' (mid 1990s-1999)
*''West Michigan's News Leader'' (1999-2011)
*''On Air. Online. On The Go.'' (2009-present; used in news opens)
*''Watching Out For You'' (2011-present)

==News Team==
'''Anchors'''
*Brett Thomas - weekday mornings, noon and Executive Producer
*Emily Linnert - weekday mornings and noon
*Brian Sterling - weeknights at 5, 5:30, 6, 10, and 11
*Susan Shaw - weeknights at 5, 5:30, 6 and 11
*Marlee Ginter - weeknights at 10; also weeknight reporter 
*Marc Thompson - weekend mornings/reporter
*Larry Figurski - weekend evenings
*Rachael Ruiz - ''eightWest'' host

'''''Storm Team 8'' meteorologists'''
*Bill Steffen, Chief Meteorologist ([[AMS]] Seal of Approval) - weeknights 5, 5:30, 6, 10 and 11
*Terri DeBoer (AMS Seal of Approval) - weekday mornings and ''eightWest'' host
*Matt Kirkwood (AMS Seal of Approval) - weekdays at noon
*Laura Velasquez (AMS [[Certified Broadcast Meteorologist]]) - weekend mornings
*Kyle Underwood (AMS/[[NWA]] Seals of Approval) - weekend evenings at 6, 10 and 11

'''Sports'''
*Jack Doles - Director seen weeknights at 6, 10 and 11
**''Football Frenzy'' host 
*Jason Terzis - weekends at 6, 10 and 11
**''Sports Overtime'' host and producer
**reporter
*Larry Figurski - Reporter/News
*Hondo Carpenter - ''[[Michigan State Spartans|Spartan]] Nation'' host

'''Reporters'''
*Rick Albin - political reporter / ''To The Point'' host
*Dani Carlson
*Henry Erb - Senior investigative reporter
*Leon Hendrix
*Tom Hillen
*Crystal Hilliard
*Steve Kelso
*Joe LaFurgey
*Ken Kolker
*Lindsay Ropp - reporter/producer
*Anne Schieber - &quot;Your Money&quot; reporter
*Tony Tagliavia - education reporter
*Ryan Takeo

'''Other On Air Personalities'''
*Eva Aguirre Cooper - Communications Director
*Lori Cook &quot;Maranda&quot; - Children and Family Services Manager as well as ''Where You Live'' host
**heard on [[WSRW-FM]] 105.7

'''Notable former staff'''
*[[Steve Kmetko]] - former [[E!]] host
*[[Janet Shamlian]] - now at [[NBC News]]
*[[John Stehr]] - now at [[WTHR]]

==External links==
*[http://www.woodtv.com/ WOOD-TV]
*[http://www.live8.com WOOD-TV mobile]
*[http://www.wotv.com/ WOTV]
*[http://www.wxsp.com/ WXSP-CD]
*{{TVQ|WOOD-TV}}
*{{TVQ|WOGC-CA}}

{{Grand Rapids TV}}
{{NBC Michigan}}
{{LIN TV}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Wood-Tv}}
[[Category:NBC network affiliates]]
[[Category:Television channels and stations established in 1949]]
[[Category:Channel 7 digital TV stations in the United States]]
[[Category:Television stations in Michigan]]
[[Category:Television stations in Grand Rapids, Michigan]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
