<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="1359774" ns="0" title="Hampton University"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Infobox university
 |name              = Hampton University 
 |native_name       = 
 |image_name        = Hampton University logo.png
 |image_size        = 
 |caption           = 
 |latin_name        = 
 |motto             = &quot;The Standard of Excellence, An Education for Life&quot;
 |mottoeng          = 
 |established       = {{Start date|1868|04|01}}
 |closed            = 
 |type              = [[Private school|Private]], [[Historically black colleges and universities|HBCU]]
 |affiliation       = 
 |endowment         = $193 million&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.nacubo.org/Documents/research/2009_NCSE_Public_Tables_Endowment_Market_Values.pdf|title=NCSE Public Tables}}&lt;/ref&gt;
 |officer_in_charge = 
 |chairman          = 
 |chancellor        = 
 |president         = William R. Harvey
 |vice-president    = 
 |superintendent    = 
 |provost           = 
 |vice_chancellor   = 
 |rector            = 
 |principal         = 
 |dean              = 
 |director          = 
 |head_label        = 
 |head              = 
 |faculty           = 
 |staff             = 
 |students          = 5,000
 |undergrad         = 
 |postgrad          = 
 |doctoral          = 
 |other             = 
 |city              = [[Hampton, Virginia|Hampton]]
 |state             = [[Virginia]] 
 |province          = 
 |country           = [[United States of America|United States]] 
 |coor              = 
 |campus            = [[Suburban]] 
 |former_names      = Hampton Normal and Agricultural Institute&lt;br /&gt;Hampton Institute
 |free_label        = 
 |free              = 
 |sports            = 
 |colors = blue &amp; white &lt;span style=&quot;background:#00216E; width:50px; border:1px solid #000;&quot;&gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/span&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;span style=&quot;background:white; width:50px; border:1px solid #000;&quot;&gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/span&gt;
 |nickname          = Pirates
 |mascot            = 
 |athletics         = [[National Collegiate Athletic Association|NCAA]] [[Division I (NCAA)#Football Championship Subdivision|Division I FCS]]
 |affiliations      = [[Mid-Eastern Athletic Conference|MEAC]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Middle Atlantic Intercollegiate Sailing Association|MAISA]]
 |website           = [http://www.hamptonu.edu/ www.hamptonu.edu]
 |logo              = [[File:HamptonU.jpg]]
 |footnotes         = 
}}'''Hampton University''' is a [[Historically black colleges and universities|historically black university]] located in [[Hampton, Virginia]], [[United States]]. It was founded by black and white leaders of the [[American Missionary Association]] after the [[American Civil War]] to provide education to [[freedmen]].

==History==
The campus looking south across the harbor of [[Hampton Roads]] was founded on the grounds of &quot;Little Scotland&quot;, a former plantation in [[Elizabeth City County, Virginia|Elizabeth City County]] not far from [[Fortress Monroe]] and the [[Grand Contraband Camp]] that gathered nearby.  These facilities represented freedom to former [[History of slavery in the United States|slaves]], who sought refuge with Union forces in the first year of the war.   

The [[American Missionary Association]] (AMA) responded in 1861 to the former slaves' need for education by hiring its first black teacher, [[Mary S. Peake|Mary Smith Peake]], who had secretly been teaching slaves and free blacks in the area despite the state's prohibition in law. She first taught for the AMA on September 17, 1861 and was said to gather her pupils under a large oak.  After it was the site in 1863 of the first reading in the South of the [[Emancipation Proclamation]], it was called the [[Emancipation Oak]]. The tree, a symbol of the university and the city, is part of the [[National Historic Landmark District]] at Hampton University.

The Hampton Agricultural and Industrial School, later called the [[Hampton Institute]], was founded in 1868 after the war by the biracial leadership of the AMA, who were chiefly Congregation and Presbyterian ministers.  It was first led by former [[Union Army|Union]] General [[Samuel Chapman Armstrong]].  Among the school's famous alumni is [[Booker T. Washington|Dr. Booker T. Washington]], who became an educator and later founded [[Tuskeegee Institute]], another college supported by the AMA. The President [[Abraham Lincoln]]'s Emancipation Proclamation was read to local freedmen under the same historic tree, which is still located on the campus today.  It serves as a symbol for the modern city of Hampton.

===Civil War===
During the [[American Civil War]] (1861&amp;ndash;1865), Union-held [[Fortress Monroe]] in southeastern [[Virginia]] at the mouth of [[Hampton Roads]] became a gathering point and safe haven of sorts for [[fugitive slave]]s. The commander, General [[Benjamin Franklin Butler (politician)|Benjamin F. Butler]], determined they were [[contraband (American Civil War)|&quot;contraband of War]], to protect them from being returned to slaveholders, who clamored to reclaim them. As numerous individuals sought freedom behind Union lines, the Army arranged the construction of the [[Grand Contraband Camp]] nearby from materials reclaimed from the ruins of Hampton, which had been burned by retreating [[Confederate States of America|Confederates]]. This area was later called &quot;Slabtown.&quot;  

Hampton University can trace its roots to the work of [[Mary S. Peake]], which began in 1861 with outdoor classes which she taught under the landmark [[Emancipation Oak]] in the nearby area of [[Elizabeth City County, Virginia|Elizabeth City County]]. The newly issued [[Emancipation Proclamation]] was first read to a gathering under the historic tree there in 1863.

===After the War: teaching teachers===
[[Image:Hampton Institute - geography.jpg|thumb|An 1899 class in mathematical geography]] After the War, a [[normal school]] (&quot;normal&quot; meaning to establish standards or ''norms'' while educating teachers) was formalized in 1868, with former [[Union (American Civil War)|Union]] brevet Brigadier General [[Samuel Chapman Armstrong]] (1839&amp;ndash;1893) as its first principal. The new school was established on the grounds of a former [[plantation]] named &quot;Little Scotland&quot;, which had a view of Hampton Roads.  The original school buildings fronted the Hampton River. Legally [[charter]]ed in 1870 as a [[land grant university|land grant school]],it was first known as &quot;Hampton Normal and Agricultural Institute.&quot;

Typical of [[historically black colleges]], Hampton received much of its financial support in the years following the Civil War from the [[American Missionary Association]] (whose black and white leaders represented the [[Congregational]] and [[Presbyterian]] churches), other church groups and former officers and soldiers of the Union Army. One of the many Civil War veterans who gave substantial sums to the school was General [[William Jackson Palmer]], a Union cavalry commander from [[Philadelphia, Pennsylvania|Philadelphia]].  He later built the [[Denver and Rio Grande Western Railroad]], and founded [[Colorado Springs, Colorado]]. As the Civil War began in 1861, although his [[Quaker]] upbringing made Palmer abhor violence, his passion to see the [[slavery|slave]]s freed compelled him to enter the war. He was awarded the [[Medal of Honor]] for bravery in 1894. (The current Palmer Hall on the campus is named in his honor.)   

[[Image:Hampton Institute - bricklaying.jpg|thumb|Students in an 1899 bricklaying class]] Unlike the wealthy Palmer, Sam Armstrong was the son of a [[missionary]] to the [[Hawaiian Islands|Sandwich Islands]] (which later became the U.S. state of [[Hawaii]]). He also had dreams  for the betterment of the freedmen. He patterned his new school after the model of his father, who had overseen the teaching of reading, writing and arithmetic to the Polynesians. He wanted to teach the skills necessary for blacks to be self-supporting in the impoverished South. Under his guidance, a Hampton-style education became well-known as an education that combined cultural uplift with moral and manual training.  Armstrong said it was an education that encompassed &quot;the head, the heart, and the hands.&quot; 

At the close of its first decade, the school reported a total admission in the ten years of 927 students, with 277 graduates, all but 17 of whom had become teachers. Many of them had bought land and established themselves in homes; many were farming as well as teaching; some had gone into business. Only a very small proportion failed to do well. By another 10 years, there had been over 600 graduates. In 1888, of the 537 still alive, three-fourths were teaching, and about half as many undergraduates were also teaching. It was estimated that 15,000 children in community schools were being taught by Hampton's students and alumni that year.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.rootsweb.com/%7Eusgenweb/va/history/lamb/lamb5.html ''Our Twin Cities of the Nineteenth Century: Norfolk and Portsmouth, Their Past, Present, and Future''], Robert W. Lamb, Editor. Norfolk, VA: Barcroft, Publisher. 1887&amp;ndash;8. Norfolk Landmark Steam Presses.&lt;/ref&gt;

===Booker T. Washington: spreading the educational work===
{{details|Booker T. Washington}}Among Hampton's earliest students was [[Booker T. Washington]], who arrived from [[West Virginia]] in 1872 at the age of 16. He worked his way through Hampton, and then went on to attend [[Wayland Seminary]] in Washington D.C. After graduation, he returned to Hampton and became a teacher. Upon recommendation of Sam Armstrong to founder [[Lewis Adams]] and others, in 1881, Washington was sent to [[Alabama]] at age 25 to head another new normal school. This new Institution eventually became [[Tuskegee University]]. Embracing much of Armstrong's philosophy, Washington built Tuskegee into a substantial school and became nationally famous as an educator, orator, and fund-raiser as well. He collaborated with the [[philanthropist]] [[Julius Rosenwald]] in the early 20th century to create a model for rural black schools - Rosenwald established a fund that matched monies raised by communities to build more than 5,000 schools for rural black children, mostly in the South.

===Native Americans===
In 1878, Hampton established a formal education program for [[Native Americans in the United States|Native Americans]].  In 1875 at the end of the Indian Wars, the United States Army sent seventy-two warriors from the Cheyenne, Kiowa, Comanche and Caddo Nations, to imprisonment and exile in St. Augustine, Florida. Essentially they were considered hostages to persuade their peoples in the West to keep peace.  [[Richard Henry Pratt]] supervised them at [[Fort Marion]] and began to arrange for their education in the English language and American culture. Numerous visitors to St. Augustine from the North became interested in their cases and volunteered as teachers. They also provided them with art supplies, and some of the works by the men are held by the [[Smithsonian Institution]]. At the end of the warriors' incarceration, Pratt convinced seventeen of the younger men to enroll at Hampton Institute for a fuller education.&lt;ref&gt;Landis, B. (n.d.). Carlisle Indian Industrial School History. Frontier Homepage Powered by Yahoo!. Retrieved November 6, 2010, from http://home.epix.net/~landis/histry.html&lt;/ref&gt; (Later Pratt founded the [[Carlisle Indian Industrial School]] based on the success of some of the men with education and assimilation).

===Name changes, expansion, community===

[[Image:HamptonUniversityHarveyLibrary.JPG|thumb|Library entrance]]

Hampton Normal and Agricultural Institute became simply Hampton Institute in 1930.  With the addition of departments and graduate programs, it was accredited as Hampton University in 1984.&lt;ref&gt;school site&lt;/ref&gt; Originally located in [[Elizabeth City County, Virginia|Elizabeth City County]], it was long-located in the Town of [[Phoebus, Virginia|Phoebus]], incorporated in 1900.  Phoebus and Elizabeth City County were consolidated with the neighboring [[Hampton, Virginia|City of Hampton]] to form a much larger [[independent city]] in 1952. The City of Hampton uses the Emancipation Oak on its official seal. From 1960 to 1970, noted [[diplomat]] and educator [[Jerome H. Holland]] was president of the Hampton Institute.

The school is informally called simply &quot;Hampton&quot; or &quot;HU&quot; by many students, faculty and supporters. Hampton University and Howard University constantly claim the title, &quot;The Real HU&quot;. Both schools enjoy the friendly rivalry.

== Campus ==

[[Image:Hampton University aerial view.jpg|thumb|Aerial view of Hampton University]]

The campus contains several buildings that contribute to its [[National Historic Landmark]] district: Virginia-Cleveland Hall (freshman female dormitory, as well as home to the school's two cafeterias), Wigwam building (home to administrative offices), Academy Building (administrative offices), Memorial Chapel (religious services) and the President's Mansion House.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.hamptonu.edu/studentservices/admissions/tour/index.htm|title=Hampton University - Admissions|accessdate=2007-05-03 |archiveurl = http://web.archive.org/web/20070430004509/http://www.hamptonu.edu/studentservices/admissions/tour/index.htm &lt;!-- Bot retrieved archive --&gt; |archivedate = 2007-04-30}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.cr.nps.gov/nhl/designations/Lists/VA01.pdf|format=PDF|title=National Historic Landmarks Survey: Listing of National Historic Landmarks by State:Virginia|accessdate=2007-05-03}}&lt;/ref&gt; 

The original High School on the campus became Phenix Hall when [[Hampton City Public Schools]] opened a new Phenix High School in 1959. Phenix Hall was damaged in a minor fire on June 12, 2008.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.dailypress.com/news/local/dp-now-hufire.jn12,0,3772406.story|title=Fire damages historic building on HU campus &amp;mdash; dailypress.com&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The Emancipation Oak was cited by the [[National Geographic Society]] as one of the 10 great trees in the world.

===National Historic Landmark District===
{{Infobox NRHP
 | name =Hampton Institute
 | nrhp_type = nhld
 | image = 
 | caption = 
 | location= NW of jct. of U.S. 60 and the Hampton Roads Bridge Tunnel, [[Hampton, Virginia]]
 | locmapin = Virginia
 | area =
 | built =1866
 | architect= [[Richard Morris Hunt]]; Et al.
 | architecture=
 | designated_nrhp_type = May 30, 1974&lt;ref name=&quot;nhlsum&quot;/&gt;
 | added = November 12, 1969&lt;ref name=&quot;nris&quot;&gt;{{NRISref|2007a}}&lt;/ref&gt;
 | governing_body = Private
 | refnum=69000323
}}A {{convert|15|acre|m2|sing=on}} portion of the campus along the Hampton River, including many of the older buildings, is a U.S. [[National Historic Landmark District]].  Buildings included are:
*''Mansion House'', original plantation residence of Little Scotland
*''Virginia Hall'' built in 1873
*''Academic Hall''
*''Wigwam''
*''Marquand Memorial Chapel'', a [[Romanesque Revival]] red brick chapel with a {{convert|150|ft|m|sing=on}} tower
In addition, Cleveland Hall, Ogden, and the Administration building are also included in the district.&lt;ref name=&quot;nrhpinv2&quot;/&gt;

The district was listed on the [[National Register of Historic Places]] in 1969,&lt;ref name=&quot;nris&quot;/&gt; and declared a [[National Historic Landmark]] in 1974.&lt;ref name=&quot;nhlsum&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://tps.cr.nps.gov/nhl/detail.cfm?ResourceId=868&amp;ResourceType=District
|title=Hampton Institute |accessdate=2008-05-30|work=National Historic Landmark summary listing|publisher=National Park Service}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;nrhpinv2&quot;&gt;{{Cite document|url=http://pdfhost.focus.nps.gov/docs/NHLS/Text/69000323.pdf|title=National Register of Historic Places Inventory-Nomination: Hampton Institute / Hampton Normal and Industrial Institute|date=January 9, 1974 |author=Carol Ann Poh |publisher=National Park Service|postscript=&lt;!--None--&gt;}} and {{PDFlink|[http://pdfhost.focus.nps.gov/docs/NHLS/Photos/69000323.pdf ''Accompanying 17 photos, from 1973'']|5.84&amp;nbsp;MB}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Student activities==
===Athletics===
In 1995, Hampton joined the [[Mid-Eastern Athletic Conference]], commonly referred to as the MEAC. Since joining, Hampton has won dozens of MEAC titles in football, men's and women's basketball, men's and women's track, and men's and women's tennis. In March 2001, the men's basketball team made NCAA Tournament history, becoming only the fourth 15th-seeded team to defeat a 2nd-seeded team. Hampton defeated [[Iowa State]], 58&amp;ndash;57 on March 15, but lost to [[Georgetown University|Georgetown]] two days later. The win still makes [[SportsCenter]]'s Top 10 NCAA tournament upsets.

Rivals include [[Norfolk State University]], located across [[Hampton Roads]] in downtown Norfolk, and [[Howard University]] in [[Washington, D.C.]]

Hampton's colors are [[blue]] and [[white]], and their nickname is &quot;The  Pirates&quot;. Hampton sports teams participate in NCAA Division I (I-AA for [[College football|football]]) in the [[Mid-Eastern Athletic Conference]] (MEAC) in which they joined in 1995 after leaving the Central Intercollegiate Athletic Association. Since joining, Hampton has won MEAC titles in many sports, including football, men's and women's basketball, men's and women's track, and men's and women's tennis. In 2001, the Hampton [[basketball]] team won its first [[NCAA Men's Basketball Division I Championship|NCAA Tournament]] game, when they beat [[Iowa State University|Iowa State]] 58&amp;ndash;57, in one of the largest [[upset]]s of all time. The &quot;Lady Pirates&quot; basketball team has seen great success as well, and made trips to the [[NCAA Women's Division I Basketball Championship|NCAA tournament]] in 2000, 2003, 2004, and 2010. In 1988, as a [[Division II (NCAA)|Division II]] school, the Lady Pirates won the [[NCAA Women's Division II Basketball Championship]], defeating [[West Texas State]].

They won their conference in football in 1997, shared one in 1998 and 2004, and won the conference out right in 2005, 2006. From 2004 to 2007, the university's football team saw much success. The team won 3 MEAC Championships, 3 SBN-Black College National Championships, and was ranked in the Division I FCS top 25 poll each year.  The Pirates also sent five players to the NFL Combine in 2007, the most out of any FCS subdivision school for that year. They have also been dominant in tennis winning the MEAC from 1996–1999, 2001-2003 &amp; 2007 for the men and 1998, 2002-2004 for the women.  They've also won the men's conference basketball tournament in 2001, 2002, 2006, and 2010.

Pirate athletics are supported by a plethora of groups, including &quot;The Force&quot; Marching Band. The marching band has appeared at several notable performances, including the Barack Obama Presidential Inauguration parade (Washington, DC). &quot;The Force&quot; was chosen out of a large pool of applicants to participate in the parade as the representative for the state of Virginia.

==Notable Alumni==
===Business===
{{AlumniStart}}
{{Alum|name=George R. Lewis|year=|nota=former President &amp; CEO, [[Altria Group|Phillip Morris]] Capital Corporation; Listed among the ''Top 50 Black Executives'' by [[Ebony Magazine]]|ref=&lt;ref&gt;money.cnn.com/magazines/.../index.htm&lt;/ref&gt;}}
{{Alum|name=[[Charles Phillips (businessman)|Charles Phillips]]|year=|nota=CEO, Infor; Former President, [[Oracle Corporation]]|ref=}}
{{Alum|name=Tami Simmons|year=|nota=Senior Vice President, [[Wells Fargo]]|ref=}}
{{AlumniEnd}}

===Education===
{{AlumniStart}}
{{Alum|name=[[Martha Louise Morrow Foxx]]|year=|nota=noted blind educator|ref=}}
{{Alum|name=[[St. Clair Drake]]|year=1931|nota=Notable sociologist and anthropologist, who created one of the first African American Studies programs at a college or university in the United States.|ref=}}
{{Alum|name=[[Freeman A. Hrabowski III]]|year=|nota=President of the [[University of Maryland, Baltimore County]]|ref=}}
{{Alum|name=Kimberly Oliver|year=|nota=2006 National Teacher of the Year|ref=&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.ccsso.org/projects/national_teacher_of_the_year/national_teachers/8144.cfm Kimberly Oliver&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;}}
{{Alum|name=William C. Hunter|year=|nota=Dean of the [[Tippie College of Business]] at [[University of Iowa]]|ref=&lt;ref&gt;http://www.tippie.uiowa.edu/about/message.cfm&lt;/ref&gt;}}
{{Alum|name=Dr. Wilmer Leon|year=|nota=Political Scientist and Associate Professor in the Political Science Department at [[Howard University]]. Talk show host on [[The Power (XM)]] Channel 169 on [[Sirius XM Radio]]|ref=&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.wilmerleon.com/showbio.htm|title=Inside the Issues With Wilmer Leon|publisher=wilmerleon.com|accessdate=January 22, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;}}

{{Alum|name=Dianne Boardley Suber|year=|nota=President of [[St. Augustine's College (North Carolina)|Saint Augustine's College]]|ref=}}
{{Alum|name=Edward McIntosh|year=|nota=Scholar and Educator|ref=}}
{{AlumniEnd}}

===Entertainment===
{{AlumniStart}}
{{Alum|name=[[John T. Biggers]]|year=|nota=[[Harlem Renaissance]] Muralist and founder of the Art Department at [[Texas Southern University]]|ref=}}
{{Alum|name=[[Spencer Christian]]|year=|nota=former weatherman for ''[[Good Morning America]]'' from 1986 to 1998|ref=}}
{{Alum|name=[[Wanda Sykes]]|year=1986|nota=comedian|ref=}}
{{Alum|name=[[DJ Envy]]|year=1999|nota=disc jockey|ref=}}
{{Alum|name=Dr. Kenneth L. Riddle|year=2004|nota=Recording artist &amp;mdash; Member of Tye Tribbett and Greater Anointing|ref=}}
{{Alum|name=Robi Reed|year=|nota=casting director, ''School Daze'', ''Love Jones'', ''Soul Food''|ref=}}
{{Alum|name=[[Dorothy Maynor]]|year=|nota=concert singer|ref=}}
{{Alum|name=[[Brandon Fobbs]]|year=2002|nota=actor; movies such as ''Pride with Terrence Howard''|ref= }}
{{Alum|name=[[Beverly Gooden]]|year=2005|nota=Best Selling Author, ''Confessions of a Church Girl''|ref=}}
{{Alum|name=Emil Wilbekin|year=1989|nota=entertainment journalist, former editor-in-chief for ''[[Vibe Magazine]]''|ref=}}
{{Alum|name=Angela Burt Murray|year=N/A|nota=Editor in Chief of ''Essence Magazine''|ref=}}
{{Alum|name=[[Biff Henderson]]|year=|nota=Stage Manager and Personality on [[The Late Show with David Letterman]]''|ref=}}
{{Alum|name=[[A. S. &quot;Doc&quot; Young|A. S. (Doc) Young]]|year=1941|nota=Sports journalist|ref=&lt;ref name='Jet-30Sep1996'&gt;{{cite journal |last= |first= |author= |authorlink= |coauthors= |editor1-first=Sylvia P. |editor1-last=Flanagan |editor1-link= |date=September 30, 1996 |year= |month= |title=A.S. 'Doc' Young, Noted Journalist-Author, Dies |trans_title= |journal=Jet |volume=90 |series= |issue=20 |page=60 |pages= |at= |publisher=Johnson Publishing Company, Inc. |location=Chicago, Illinois |issn= |pmid= |pmc= |doi= |bibcode= |oclc= |id= |url= |language= |format= |archiveurl= |archivedate= |accessdate= |laysummary= |laysource= |laydate= |quote= |ref= |separator= |postscript= }}&lt;/ref&gt;}}
{{AlumniEnd}}

===Politics and government===
{{AlumniStart}}
{{Alum|name=[[Allyson Kay Duncan]]|year=|nota=4th Cir US Circuit Court Judge|ref=}}
{{Alum|name=Michael K. Fauntroy|year=|nota=Professor of public policy at [[George Mason University]]  and political commentator. He is the nephew of minister and civil rights leader [[Walter Fauntroy]]|ref=}}
{{Alum|name=[[Vanessa D. Gilmore]]|year=|nota=Federal Judge of the [[United States District Court for the Southern District of Texas]]|ref=}}
{{Alum|name=Theodore Theopolis Jones II|year=|nota=Associate Judge of the [[Court of Appeals]], [[New York]]|ref=}}
{{Alum|name=Gloria Gary Lawlah|year=1960|nota=Secretary of Aging for the State of [[Maryland]]|ref=&lt;ref&gt;http://www.msa.md.gov/msa/mdmanual/10da/html/msa12153.html&lt;/ref&gt;}}
{{Alum|name=Bryan T. Norwood|year=|nota=Police Chief of Richmond Police Department, [[Richmond, Virginia]]|ref=}}
{{Alum|name=[[Douglas Palmer]]|year=|nota=Mayor of [[Trenton, New Jersey]]|ref=}}
{{Alum|name=[[Henry E. Parker]]|year=|nota=Former State Treasurer of Connecticut|ref=}}
{{Alum|name=[[Joan Pratt]]|year=1974|nota=Comptroller [[City of Baltimore]] |ref=}}
{{Alum|name=[[Gregory M. Sleet]]|year=|nota=U.S. District Court Judge for the [[United States District Court for the District of Delaware]]|ref=}}
{{Alum|name=[[Robert Ferrell]]|year=1983|nota=Brigadier General [[U.S. Army]]|ref=}}
{{AlumniEnd}}

===Science===
{{AlumniStart}}
{{Alum|name=[[Booker T. Washington]]|year=1875|nota=Founded [[Tuskegee Institute]] in Alabama.|ref=}}
{{AlumniEnd}}

===Sociology===
{{AlumniStart}}
{{Alum|name=[[Alberta Williams King]]|year=1924|nota=mother of Martin Luther King Jr.|ref=}}
{{Alum|name=[[Elizabeth Omilami]]|year=|nota=Chief Executive Officer, Hosea Feed the Hungry and Homeless|ref=}}
{{AlumniEnd}}

===Sports===
{{AlumniStart}}
{{Alum|name=[[Darian Barnes]]|year=|nota=Running Back, [[National Football League|NFL]], [[Tampa Bay Buccaneers]] (2002 &amp;ndash; 2007)|ref=&lt;ref name=&quot;Hampton Pros&quot;&gt;{{cite web|title=NFL Players who attended Hampton University |publisher=databaseSports.com|url=http://www.databasefootball.com/players/bycollege.htm?sch=Hampton+University|accessdate=2008-04-05}}&lt;/ref&gt;}}
{{Alum|name=[[Johnnie Barnes]]|year=|nota=[[National Football League|NFL]],(1992 &amp;ndash; 1995)|ref=&lt;ref name=&quot;Hampton Pros&quot;/&gt;}}
{{Alum|name=[[James Carter (athlete)|James Carter]]|year=|nota=award-winning [[Track and field|Track]] athlete|ref=}}
{{Alum|name=[[Alonzo Coleman]]|year=|nota=[[National Football League|NFL]], [[Dallas Cowboys]]|ref=}}
{{Alum|name=[[Justin Durant]]|year=|nota=[[National Football League|NFL]] Football Player, [[Detroit Lions]]|ref=}}
{{Alum|name=[[Devin Green]]|year=2005|nota=former [[National Basketball League|NBA]] Player|ref=}}
{{Alum|name=[[Rick Mahorn]]|year=1980|nota=former [[National Basketball Association|NBA]] Player [[Washington Bullets, Detroit Pistons, New Jersey Nets]], WNBA Detroit Shock Head Coach|ref=}}
{{Alum|name=[[Nevin McCaskill]]|year=|nota= [[National Football League|NFL]] Football Player, [[Buffalo Bills]]|ref=}}
{{Alum|name=[[Francena McCorory]]|year=2010|nota= [[Track and Field]], [[NCAA]] 400m 3X-Champion|ref=&lt;ref&gt;http://www.iaaf.org/athletes/biographies/country=USA/athcode=205239/index.html&lt;/ref&gt;}}
{{Alum|name=[[Marquay McDaniel]]|year=2007|nota= [[Canadian Football League|CFL]] Football Player, [[Hamilton Tiger-Cats]]|ref=}}
{{Alum|name=Dick Price|year=1957|nota=former head football coach at [[Norfolk State University]] from 1974 to 1983, and held positions as heach coach of track team and athletic director at Norfolk State|ref=&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://hamptonroads.com/2009/02/exnorfolk-state-football-coach-dick-price-dies-75|title=Ex-Norfolk State football coach Dick Price dies at 75|publisher=hamptonroads.com|accessdate=January 23, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;}}
{{Alum|name=Donovan Rose|year=1980|nota=former NFL defensive back and current head coach of the Hampton Pirate football team |ref=&lt;ref name=&quot;Hampton Pros&quot;/&gt;}}
{{Alum|name=[[Terrence Warren]]|year=|nota=[[Seattle Seahawks]] (1993 &amp;ndash; 1995)|ref=&lt;ref name=&quot;Hampton Pros&quot;/&gt;}}
{{Alum|name=[[Cordell Taylor]]|year=|nota=Jacksonville Jaguars 1998|ref=}}
{{Alum|name=[[Jerome Mathis]]|year=|nota=Houston Texans 2005 / Pro Bowl Selection|ref=}}
{{Alum|name=[[Isaac Hilton]]|year=|nota=New York Giants 2004}}
{{AlumniEnd}}

== External links ==
{{Commons category}}
* [http://www.hamptonu.edu/ www.hamptonu.edu] -- Official web site
* [http://www.aaheritageva.org/search/sites.asp?MailingListID=19 Information on Hampton University from Virginia African Heritage Program]

== References ==
{{reflist|2}}

{{Colleges and universities in Virginia}}
{{Registered Historic Places}}
{{HBCU}}
{{Associated New American Colleges}}
{{Mid-Eastern Athletic Conference}}

{{Coord|37.02128|N|76.33713|W|source:placeopedia|display=title}}

[[Category:Hampton University| ]]
[[Category:Universities and colleges in Virginia]]
[[Category:Historically black universities and colleges in the United States|Hampton University]]
[[Category:Educational institutions established in 1868]]
[[Category:National Association of Independent Colleges and Universities members]]
[[Category:Education in Hampton, Virginia]]
[[Category:National Historic Landmarks in Virginia]]
[[Category:Universities and colleges accredited by the Southern Association of Colleges and Schools]]
[[Category:Buildings and structures in Hampton, Virginia]]
[[Category:African American history in Virginia]]

[[fr:Université de Hampton]]
[[no:Hampton University]]
[[simple:Hampton University]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
