<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="13590" ns="0" title="House"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Other uses}}
{{Pp-move-indef}}
[[File:Novosibirsk picturesque-traditional-house.JPG|thumb|A traditional house in [[Novosibirsk]], [[Siberia]], [[Russia]]]]
[[File:Ranch style home in Salinas, California.JPG|thumb|A [[Ranch-style house|ranch style house]] in [[Salinas, California]], [[United States]]]]
A '''house''' is a [[building]] or [[structure]] that has the ability to be occupied for dwelling by [[human beings]] or other creatures. The term house includes many kinds of different dwellings ranging from rudimentary huts of [[nomadic tribes]] to free standing individual structures.&lt;ref name=schoenauer&gt;Schoenauer, Norbert (2000). ''6,000 Years of Housing'' (rev. ed.) (New York: W.W. Norton &amp; Company).&lt;/ref&gt; In some contexts, &quot;house&quot; may mean the same as dwelling, [[residence]], [[home]], [[abode]], [[lodging]], accommodation, or housing, among other meanings.

[[File:Teremok in Talashkino.JPG|thumb|&quot;Terem&quot; – Traditional house in [[European Russia]].]]
The social unit that lives in a house is known as a [[household]]. Most commonly, a household is a [[family]] unit of some kind, though households can be other [[Group (sociology)|social groups]], such as single persons, or groups of unrelated individuals. Settled agrarian and [[Industrial society|industrial societies]] are composed of household units living permanently in housing of various types, according to a variety of forms of [[land tenure]]. [[English language|English-speaking]] people generally call any [[building]] they routinely occupy &quot;home&quot;. Many people leave their houses during the day for [[employment|work]] and [[recreation]], and return to them to [[sleep]] and for other activities.{{Citation needed|date=May 2011}}

[[File:Gurvger.jpg|thumb|A [[mongolian]] [[yurt]] near the [[Gurvan Saikhan Uul|Gurvan Saikhan Mountains]] (in the background); part of [[Gobi Gurvansaikhan National Park]].]]
A growing point of interest is the energy consumption of a house; while many houses in Japan have no [[Kotatsu#Use|insulation]] at all, in Europe from 2018 all houses built should have no energy consumption [[Zero-energy building|at all]].

==Etymology==
House derives directly from Old English '''Hus''' meaning 'Dwelling, shelter, home, house,&quot; which in turn derives from [[Proto-Germanic]] Khusan (reconstructed by etymological analysis) which is of unknown origin.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.etymonline.com/index.php?term=house&lt;/ref&gt;

== Inside the house ==
=== Layout ===
[[File:Gingerbread House Essex CT.jpg|thumb|Example of an early [[Victorian architecture|Victorian]] &quot;Gingerbread House&quot; in [[Connecticut]], United States, built in 1855]]
{{main|House plan}}
Ideally, [[architect]]s of houses design rooms to meet the needs of the people who will live in the house. Such designing, known as &quot;[[interior design]]&quot;, has become a popular subject in universities. [[Feng shui]], originally a Chinese method of moving houses according to such factors as rain and micro-climates, has recently expanded its scope to address the design of interior spaces with a view to promoting harmonious effects on the people living inside the house. Feng shui can also mean the &quot;aura&quot; in or around a dwelling. Compare the [[real estate|real-estate]] sales concept of &quot;indoor-outdoor flow&quot;.

The [[square footage]] of a house in the United States reports the area of &quot;living space&quot;, excluding the garage and other non-living spaces. The &quot;square meters&quot; figure of a house in Europe &lt;!-- including Malta ? --&gt; reports the area of the walls enclosing the home, and thus includes any attached garage and non-living spaces.{{Citation needed|date=February 2007}} How many floors, or levels, the home is will play a big role in determining the square footage of a home.{{Citation needed|date=May 2011}}

=== Parts ===
[[File:HouseFlrPlan.JPG|thumb|left|[[Floor plan]] of a &quot;[[American Foursquare|foursquare]]&quot; house]]
Many houses have several large rooms with specialized functions and several very small rooms for other various reasons. These may include a living/eating area, a sleeping area, and (if suitable facilities and services exist) washing and [[lavatory]] areas. Additionally, spa room, indoor pool, indoor basketball goal, and so forth. In traditional agriculture-oriented societies, [[List of domesticated animals|domestic animals]] such as chickens or larger livestock (like cattle) often share part of the house with human beings. Most conventional modern houses will at least contain a [[bedroom]], [[bathroom]], [[kitchen]] (or kitchen area), and a [[living room]]. A typical &quot;[[American Foursquare|foursquare]] house&quot; (as pictured) occurred commonly in the early history of the [[United States of America]] where they were mainly built, with a [[staircase]] in the center of the house, surrounded by [[Four Rooms|four rooms]], and connected to other sections of the house (including in more recent eras a [[Garage (house)|garage]]).
&lt;br clear=&quot;left&quot; /&gt;

The names of parts of a house often echo the names of parts of other buildings, but could typically include:
{{col-begin}}
{{col-break}}
* [[Atrium (architecture)|Atrium]]
* [[Attic]]
* [[Alcove]]
* [[Basement]]/[[Basement|cellar]]
* [[Bathroom]] (in various senses of the word)
:* [[Bathtub|Bath]]/[[shower]]
:* [[Toilet]]
* [[Bedroom]] (or [[Nursery (room)|nursery]], for infants or small children)
* [[Room#Box-room|Box-room]] / storage room
* [[Conservatory (greenhouse)|Conservatory]]
* [[Dining room]]
* [[Family room]] or [[den (room)|den]]
:*[[Fireplace]] (for warmth during winter; generally not found in warmer climates)
* [[Foyer]]
* [[Front room]] (in various senses of the phrase)
* [[Garage (house)|Garage]]
* [[Hallway]] / [[Hall|passage]] / [[Vestibule (architecture)|Vestibule]]
{{col-break}}
* [[Hearth]] – often an important symbolic focus of family togetherness
* [[Kitchen]]
* [[Larder]]
* [[Laundry room]]
* [[Library]]
* [[Living room]]
* [[Loft]]
* [[wikt:nook|Nook]]
* [[Window]]
* [[Office]] or [[study (room)|study]]
* [[Pantry]]
* [[Parlour]]
* [[Pew]]/porch
* [[Recreation room]] / [[rumpus room]] / [[television]] room
* [[Shrine]]s to serve the religious functions associated with a family
* [[Stairwell]]
* [[Sunroom]]
* [[Workshop]]
Some houses have a pool in the backyard, or a trampoline, or a playground.
{{col-end}}

===History of the Interior===
{{see also|Room (architecture)}}
It is unknown of the complete origin of the house and its interior, but it can be traced back to the most simplest form of [[shelter]]s. [[Ancient Rome|Roman]] architect [[Vitruvius|Vitruvius']] theories have claimed the first form of [[architecture]] as a frame of timber branches finished in mud, also known as the [[primitive hut]].&lt;ref name=&quot;ReferenceA&quot; &gt;Hill, Jonathan “Immaterial Architecture” New York: Routledge 2006&lt;/ref&gt;
Philip Tabor later states the contribution of 17th century Dutch houses as the foundation of houses today.
:'''‘As far as the idea of the home is concerned, the home of the home is the [[Netherlands]]. This idea’s crystallization might be dated to the first three-quarters of the seventeeth century, when the [[Netherlands|Dutch]] Netherlands amassed the unprecedented and unrivalled accumulation of capital, and emptied their purses into [[domestic]] [[space]].’'&lt;ref&gt;Tabor, Philip &quot;Striking Home: The Telematic Assault on Identity' . Published in Jonathan Hill, editor. Occupying Architecture: Between the Architect and the User&lt;/ref&gt;''&lt;sub&gt;&lt;/sub&gt;

====Communal Rooms====

In the [[Middle Ages]], the [[Manor house|Manor Houses]] facilitated different activities and events. Furthermore, the houses accommodated numerous people, including the likes of the family, relatives, employees, servants and their guests.&lt;ref name=&quot;ReferenceA&quot;/&gt; Their lifestyles were largely communal, as areas such as the [[Great Hall]] enforced  the custom of dining and meetings and the [[Solar (room)|Solar]] intended for shared sleeping beds.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.middle-ages.org.uk/manor-house.htm&lt;/ref&gt;

====Interconnecting Rooms====

During the 15th and 16th centuries, the [[Italian Renaissance architecture|Italian Renaissance Palazzo]] consisted of plentiful rooms of connectivity. Unlike the qualities and uses of the Manor Houses, most rooms of the [[palazzo]] contained no purpose, yet were given several [[doors]]. These doors adjoined rooms in which [[Robin Evans]] describes as a ‘matrix of discrete but thoroughly interconnected chambers.’&lt;ref name=&quot;ReferenceB&quot;&gt;Evans, Robin “Translations from Drawing to Building: Figures, Doors and Passages” London: Architectural Associations Publications 2005&lt;/ref&gt; The layout allowed occupants to freely walk room to room from one door to another, thus breaking the boundaries of [[privacy]]. 
:''‘Once inside it is necessary to pass from on room to the next, then to the next to traverse the building. Where [[passages]] and [[staircases]] are used, as inevitably they are, they nearly always connect just one space to another and never serve as general distributors of movement. Thus, despite the precise architectural containment offered by the addition of room upon room, the [[villa]] was, in terms of occupation, an open plan, relatively permeable to the numerous members of the [[household]].’&lt;ref name=&quot;ReferenceB&quot;/&gt;''
Although very public, the open [[House plan|plan]] however encouraged sociality and connectivity for all inhabitants.&lt;ref name=&quot;ReferenceA&quot;/&gt;

====The Corridor====
It is believed that the segregation of rooms and the initiation of privacy may have been first founded in 1597, [[England]] at the Beaufort House, [[Chelsea, London|Chelsea]]. Designed by [[Architect|English Architect]] [[John Thorpe]], he writes on his plans, ‘A Long Entry through all’.&lt;ref&gt;Summerson, John “The Book Of Architecture of John Thorpe in Sit John Soan’s museum: 40th Volume of the Walpole Society” England: The Society 1964&lt;/ref&gt; The separation of the passageway from the room developed the function of the [[corridor]]. This new extension was revolutionary at the time, allowing the integration of one door per room, in which all universally connected to the same corridor. [[English people|English]]-[[Germans|German]] Architect, [[Sir Roger Pratt]] states ‘the common way in the middle through the whole length of the house, [avoids] the offices (i.e. utility rooms) from one molesting the other by continual passing through them.’&lt;ref name=&quot;ReferenceC&quot;&gt;Pratt, Sir Roger “Sir R. Pratt on Architecture” 1928&lt;/ref&gt; [[Social hierarchies]] within the 17th century was highly regarded, as architecture was able epitomize the servants and the upper class. More privacy is offered to the [[occupant]] as Pratt further claims, ‘the ordinary servants may never publicly appear in passing to and fro for their occasions there.’&lt;ref name=&quot;ReferenceC&quot;/&gt; These prejudices between rich and poor soon influenced the integration of the corridor in housing by the 19th century. 

[[Witold Rybczynski]] later states, ‘the subdivision of the house into day and night uses, and into formal and informal areas, had begun.’&lt;ref&gt;Rybczynski, Witold “Home: A Short History of An Idea” London: Pengui 1986&lt;/ref&gt; Rooms were changed from public to private as single entryways forced notions of entering a room with a specific purpose.&lt;ref name=&quot;ReferenceA&quot;/&gt;

====Work-Free House====
Compared to the large scaled houses in England and the Renaissance, the [[Dutch Golden Age|17th Century Dutch]] house was smaller, and was only inhabited by up to four to five members.&lt;ref name=&quot;ReferenceA&quot;/&gt; This was due to their embracement of ‘self-reliance’,&lt;ref name=&quot;ReferenceA&quot;/&gt; distinguishing the dependence on servants and encompassing lifestyles surrounded by [[family]]. It was important for the Dutch to separate work from domesticity, as the [[home]] became an escape and a place of [[comfort]]. This way of living and the home is noted to be highly similar to the [[contemporary]] family and their inhabitations. House layouts also possessed the idea of the corridor as well as the importance of function and privacy. 

By the end of the 17th Century, the house layout was soon transformed to become work-free, enforcing these ideas within the long future. This came in favour for the [[industrial revolution]], gaining large-scale factory production and workers.&lt;ref name=&quot;ReferenceA&quot;/&gt; The house layout of the Dutch and its functions are still relevant today.

====Technology and Privacy====
The introduction of [[technology]] and [[electronic systems]] within the house has questioned the impressions of privacy as well as the segregation of work from [[home]]. Technological advances of [[surveillance]] and [[Internet|communications]] allow insight of personal habits and private lives.&lt;ref name=&quot;ReferenceA&quot;/&gt; As a result, the ‘private becomes ever more public, [and] the desire for a [[protective]] home life increases, fuelled by the very media that undermine it’ writes Hill.&lt;ref name=&quot;ReferenceA&quot;/&gt; Work also, has been altered due to the increase of communications. The ‘deluge of [[information]]’,&lt;ref name=&quot;ReferenceA&quot;/&gt; has expressed the efforts of work, conveniently gaining access inside the house. Although commuting is reduced, ‘the desire to separate working and living remains apparent.’&lt;ref name=&quot;ReferenceA&quot;/&gt; In Jonathon Hill's book ''[http://www.bartlett.ucl.ac.uk/research/architecture/profiles/Hill.htm '''Immature Architecture'']'', he identifies this new invasion of privacy as ''[[Electromagnetic]] Weather''. Natural or man-made [[weather]] remain concurrent inside or outside the house, yet the electromagnetic weather is able to generate within both positions.&lt;ref name=&quot;ReferenceA&quot;/&gt;

== Construction ==
[[File:HouseStructure.JPG|left|thumb|The structure of the house (under [[demolition]]). This house is constructed from bricks and wood and was later covered by insulating panels. The roof construction is also seen.]]
In the [[United States]], modern house-construction techniques include [[Framing (construction)|light-frame construction]] (in areas with access to supplies of wood) and [[adobe]] or sometimes [[Rammed earth|rammed-earth construction]] (in arid regions with scarce wood-resources). Some areas use [[brick]] almost exclusively, and quarried [[Rock (geology)|stone]] has long provided walling. To some extent, aluminum and steel have displaced some traditional [[building material]]s. Increasingly popular alternative construction materials include [[insulating concrete form]]s (foam forms filled with [[concrete]]), structural insulated panels (foam panels faced with [[oriented strand board]] or fiber cement), and light-gauge steel framing and heavy-gauge steel framing.{{Citation needed|date=May 2011}}

[[File:Saitta House Dyker Heights.JPG|thumb|upright|The [[Saitta House]], [[Dyker Heights]], [[Brooklyn]], [[New York]], [[United States]] built in [[1899 in architecture|1899]] is made of and decorated in [[wood]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.dykerheightscivicassociation.com/saittareport.pdf Saitta House – Report Part 1]&lt;/ref&gt;]]
More generally, people often build houses out of the nearest available material, and often tradition and/or culture govern construction-materials, so whole towns, areas, counties or even states/countries may be built out of one main type of material. For example, a large fraction of American houses use wood, while most British and many European houses utilize stone or brick.

In the 1900s, some house designers started using [[prefabrication]]. [[Sears, Roebuck &amp; Co.]] first marketed their [[Sears Catalog Home]]s to the general public in 1908. Prefab techniques became popular after [[World War II]]. First small inside rooms framing, then later, whole walls were prefabricated and carried to the [[Construction|construction site]]. The original impetus was to use the [[labor force]] inside a shelter during inclement weather. More recently builders have begun to collaborate with structural engineers who use computers and [[finite element analysis]] to design prefabricated [[Steel frame|steel-framed]] homes with known resistance to high wind-loads and [[earthquake|seismic]] forces. These newer products provide labor savings, more consistent quality, and possibly accelerated construction processes.

Lesser-used construction methods have gained (or regained) popularity in recent years. Though not in wide use, these methods frequently appeal to homeowners who may become actively involved in the construction process. They include:
* [[Hempcrete|Cannabrick construction]]
* [[Cordwood construction]]
* [[Geodesic dome]]s
* [[Straw-bale construction]]
* [[Wattle and daub]]
[[File:Passivhaus thermogram gedaemmt ungedaemmt.png|thumb|Thermographic comparison of traditional (left) and &quot;[[passivhaus]]&quot; (right) buildings]]

=== Energy-efficiency ===
In the developed world, [[energy conservation|energy-conservation]] has grown in importance in house-design. Housing produces a major proportion of [[carbon emissions]] ([[Energy efficiency in British housing|30% of the total in the UK]], for example).&lt;ref &gt;http://www.direct.gov.uk/en/HomeAndCommunity/BuyingAndSellingYourHome/Energyperformancecertificates/DG_177026&lt;/ref&gt;

Development of a number of [[:category:low-energy building|low-energy building]] types and techniques continues. They include the [[zero-energy house]], the [[passive solar house]], the [[autonomous buildings]], the [[Superinsulation|superinsulated]] and houses built to the ''[[Passive house|Passivhaus]]'' standard.

=== Earthquake protection ===
One tool of [[earthquake engineering]] is [[base isolation]] which is increasingly used for [[earthquake]] protection. [[Base isolation]] is a collection of structural elements of a [[building]] that should substantially [[decouple]] it from the shaking ground thus protecting the building's integrity&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=HuSiRRoz72Y&amp;feature=related YouTube – Testing of a New Line of Seismic Base Isolators&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt; and enhancing its [[seismic performance]]. This technology, which is a kind of seismic [[vibration control]], can be applied both to a newly designed building and to seismic upgrading of existing structures.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |author=James M. Kelly, Professor Emeritus Civil and Environmental Engineering |title=Base Isolation: Origins and Development  |url=http://nisee.berkeley.edu/lessons/kelly.html |publisher=National Information Service for Earthquake Engineering, [[University of California]], Berkeley}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Normally, excavations are made around the building and the building is separated from the foundations. Steel or [[reinforced concrete]] beams replace the connections to the foundations, while under these, the isolating pads, or ''base isolators'', replace the material removed. While the ''[[base isolation]]'' tends to restrict transmission of the ground motion to the building, it also keeps the building positioned properly over the foundation. Careful attention to detail is required where the building interfaces with the ground, especially at entrances, stairways and ramps, to ensure sufficient [[Kinematics|relative motion]] of those structural elements.

== Legal issues ==
Buildings with historical importance have restrictions.

=== United Kingdom ===
New houses in the UK are not covered by the [[Sale of Goods Act]]. When purchasing a new house the buyer has less legal protection than when buying a new car. New houses in the UK may be covered by a [[NHBC]] guarantee but some people feel that it would be more useful to put new houses on the same legal footing as other products.{{Citation needed|date=December 2010}}

=== United States and Canada ===
In the US and Canada, many new houses are built in [[housing tracts]], which provide homeowners a sense of &quot;belonging&quot; and the feeling they have &quot;made the best use&quot; of their money. However, these houses are sometimes built as cheaply and quickly as possible by large builders seeking to maximize profits. Many [[environmental health]] issues may be ignored or minimized in the construction of these structures. In one case in [[Benicia]], [[California]], a [[Tract housing|housing tract]] was built over an old landfill. Home buyers were never told, and only found out when some began having reactions to high levels of [[lead]] and [[chromium]].{{Citation needed|date=May 2011}}

== Identifying houses ==
With the growth of dense settlement, humans designed ways of identifying houses and/or [[Land lot|parcels]] of land. Individual houses sometimes acquire [[proper name]]s; and those names may acquire in their turn considerable emotional connotations: see for example the house of ''[[Howards End]]'' or the castle of ''[[Brideshead Revisited]]''. A more systematic and general approach to identifying houses may use various methods of [[house numbering]].

== Animal houses ==
Humans often build &quot;houses&quot; for domestic or [[Wildlife|wild animals]], often resembling smaller versions of human domiciles. [[Familiar animal]] houses built by humans include [[bird house|bird-houses]], [[hen house|hen-house]]s/chicken-coops and [[doghouse]]s ([[kennel]]s); while housed agricultural animals more often live in [[Barn (building)|barns]] and [[stables]]. However, human interest in building houses for animals does not stop at the domestic [[pet]]. People build bat-houses, nesting-sites for wild ducks and other birds, bee houses, giraffe houses, kangaroo houses, worm houses, [[hermit crab]] houses, as well as shelters for many other animals.

== Shelter ==
[[File:Canberra house.jpg|thumb|A modern-style house in [[Canberra]], [[Australia]]]]
[[File:Quaresma005.JPG|thumb|A mountain house in [[Barzio]], [[Italy]]]]

Forms of (relatively) simple shelter may include:
&lt;div style=&quot;-moz-column-count:4; column-count:4;&quot;&gt;
* [[Bus stop]]
* [[Trailer (vehicle)|Camper]]
* [[Chalet]]
* [[Cottage]]
* [[Izba]]
* [[Dugout (shelter)]]
* [[Gazebo]]
* [[Hangar]]
* [[Houseboat]]
* [[Hut (dwelling)|Hut]]
* [[Lean-to]]
* [[Log cabin]]
* [[Nuclear bunker]]
* [[Shack]]
* [[Tent]] (see also [[Campsite]])
* [[Travel trailer]]
* [[Umbrella]]
* [[Yaodong]]
&lt;/div&gt;

== Houses and symbolism ==
Houses may express the circumstances or opinions of their builders or their inhabitants. Thus a vast and elaborate house may serve as a sign of conspicuous wealth, whereas a low-profile house built of recycled materials may indicate support of energy conservation.

Houses of particular historical significance (former residences of the famous, for example, or even just very old houses) may gain a protected status in [[town planning]] as examples of built [[Cultural heritage|heritage]] and/or of streetscape values. [[Commemorative plaques]] may mark such structures.

[[Home ownership]] provides a common measure of [[prosperity]] in [[economics]]. Contrast the importance of house-destruction, tent dwelling and house rebuilding in the wake of many [[natural disaster]]s.

Peter Olshavsky's [http://www.mcgill.ca/files/architecture-theory/olshavsky.pdf House for the Dance of Death] provides a [['pataphysics|'pataphysical]] variation on the house.

=== Heraldry ===
The house occurs as a rare [[Charge (heraldry)|charge]] in [[heraldry]].

=== Historical statistics on housing ===
According to statistics from the [[World Bank]] and the [[Economic Commission for Europe]] ([[UN]]), the average usable floorspace of dwellings in existence in 1976 in various countries were as follows:&lt;ref &gt;Housing in Europe edited by Martin Wynn&lt;/ref&gt;
{| class=&quot;wikitable sortable&quot;
! country || m&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt;
|-
| Austria || 86
|-
| Belgium || 97
|-
| Denmark || 122
|-
| Finland || 71
|-
| France || 82
|-
| Ireland || 88
|-
| Luxembourg || 107
|-
| Norway || 89
|-
| Netherlands || 71
|-
| United Kingdom || 70
|-
| Sweden || 109
|-
| Switzerland || 98
|-
| Greece || 80
|-
| Spain || 82
|-
| Portugal || 104
|-
| West Germany || 95
|-
| Soviet Union || 49
|-
| East Germany || 60
|-
| Bulgaria || 63
|-
| Hungary || 65
|-
| Poland || 58
|-
| Romania || 54
|-
| Czechoslovakia || 69
|-
| Yugoslavia || 65
|-
| Canada || 89
|-
| United States of America || 120
|}

== See also ==
{{Commons category|Houses}}
&lt;div style=&quot;-moz-column-count:2; column-count:2;&quot;&gt;

;Institutions
* [[U.S. Department of Housing and Urban Development]]
** [[Regulatory Barriers Clearinghouse]]
** [[HUD USER]]

;Economics
* [[Affordable housing]]
* [[Housing bubble]]
** [[United States housing bubble]]
* [[Housing tenure]]

;Functions
* [[Building science]]
* [[Mixed-use development]]
* [[Visitability]]

;Types
* [[Boarding house]]
* [[Earth sheltering]]
* [[Home automation]]
* [[Housing estate]]
* [[Housing in Japan]]
* [[Hurricane-proof house]]
* [[Lodging]]
* [[Lustron house]]
* [[Mobile home]]
* [[Modular home]]

;Miscellaneous
* [[Domestic robot]]
* [[Housewarming party]]
* [[Squatting]]

;Lists
* [[List of famous American houses]]
* [[List of house styles]]
* [[List of house types]]
* [[List of human habitation forms]]
* [[List of real estate topics]]
&lt;/div&gt;

== References ==
{{reflist|colwidth=30em}}

== External links ==
{{wiktionary}}
* [http://ucblibraries.colorado.edu/govpubs/us/housing.htm Housing] from ''UCB Libraries GovPubs''

{{Buildings and structures}}
{{Room}}

[[Category:Houses| ]]
[[Category:Structural system]]

[[als:Haus]]
[[ar:منزل]]
[[an:Casa]]
[[arc:ܒܝܬܐ]]
[[gn:Óga]]
[[ay:Uta]]
[[bn:ঘর]]
[[zh-min-nan:Chū-the̍h]]
[[ba:Торлаҡ]]
[[be:Жыллё]]
[[be-x-old:Жытло]]
[[bo:ནང་།]]
[[bs:Kuća]]
[[br:Ti]]
[[bg:Къща]]
[[ca:Casa]]
[[cs:Dům]]
[[sn:Imba]]
[[co:Casa]]
[[cy:Tŷ]]
[[da:Hus]]
[[de:Haus]]
[[et:Elamu]]
[[el:Κατοικία]]
[[es:Casa]]
[[eo:Domo]]
[[eu:Etxe]]
[[fa:خانه]]
[[hif:Ghar]]
[[fr:Maison]]
[[fur:Cjase]]
[[gl:Casa]]
[[gan:屋]]
[[xal:Гер]]
[[ko:집]]
[[hi:घर]]
[[hr:Kuća]]
[[id:Rumah]]
[[is:Hús]]
[[it:Casa]]
[[he:בית מגורים]]
[[jv:Omah]]
[[kn:ಮನೆ]]
[[ka:სახლი]]
[[kw:Chy]]
[[sw:Nyumba]]
[[ht:Kay]]
[[la:Domus]]
[[lv:Māja]]
[[lt:Namas]]
[[ln:Ndáko]]
[[lmo:Cà (custrüziun)]]
[[hu:Ház]]
[[mg:Trano]]
[[ml:വീട്]]
[[arz:بيت]]
[[ms:Rumah]]
[[nah:Chāntli]]
[[nl:Huis (woning)]]
[[nds-nl:Huus]]
[[cr:ᐙᔅᑲᐦᐄᑲᓐ]]
[[ja:家屋]]
[[or:ଘର]]
[[pih:Haus]]
[[no:Hus]]
[[nn:Hus]]
[[nrm:Maisoun]]
[[oc:Ostal]]
[[mhr:Пӧрт]]
[[pfl:Haus]]
[[pnb:کعر]]
[[pl:Dom]]
[[pt:Casa]]
[[ro:Casă]]
[[rmy:Kher]]
[[qu:Wasi]]
[[rue:Хыжа]]
[[ru:Жилище]]
[[sc:Domo]]
[[sco:Hoose]]
[[sq:Shtëpia]]
[[scn:Casa]]
[[simple:House]]
[[sk:Dom (objekt)]]
[[sl:Hiša]]
[[sr:Кућа]]
[[sh:Kuća]]
[[su:Imah]]
[[fi:Talo]]
[[sv:Hus]]
[[tl:Tahanan]]
[[ta:வீடு]]
[[kab:Axxam]]
[[te:ఇల్లు]]
[[th:บ้าน]]
[[tg:Хона]]
[[tr:Ev]]
[[bug:Bola]]
[[uk:Житло]]
[[ur:مکان]]
[[vec:Caxa]]
[[vi:Nhà]]
[[wa:Måjhon]]
[[vls:Uus]]
[[war:Baláy]]
[[wo:Kër]]
[[wuu:房子]]
[[yi:הויז]]
[[zh-yue:住宅]]
[[diq:Keye]]
[[bat-smg:Noms]]
[[zh:住宅]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
