<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="13644722" ns="0" title="Wong Shun Leung"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Chinese name|[[Wong (surname)|Wong]]}}
{{Infobox martial artist
| name = Wong Shun Leung
| other_names = 
| image = 
| image_size = 
| caption = 
| birth_name = 
| birth_date = {{birth date|df=y|1935|5|8}}
| birth_place = Hong Kong
| residence = 
| death_date = {{death date and age|df=y|1997|1|28|1935|5|8}}
| death_place = Hong Kong
| death_cause = Stroke
| martial_art = [[Wing Chun]]
| teacher = [[Yip Man]]
| rank = [[Grandmaster (martial arts)|Grandmaster]]
| students = Bruce Lee, Wan Kam Leung, Gary Lam, Philipp Bayer, David Peterson
| website = 
| footnotes = 
}}
{{wikiquote}}
{{contains Chinese text}}

'''Wong Shun Leung''' ({{zh|c=黃淳樑|p=Huang Shun Liáng}}; 8 May 1935&amp;nbsp;– 28 January 1997){{ref_label|A|a|none}} was a Chinese martial artist from Hong Kong who studied [[wing chun]] [[kung fu]] under [[Yip Man]] (葉問)&lt;ref name=&quot;VTAA1990a&quot;&gt;Ving Tsun Athletic Association (1990): [http://www.vingtsun.org.hk/Development_1954-60.HTM The development of Ving Tsun Kungfu in Hong Kong: 1954-1960] Retrieved on 24 June 2009.&lt;/ref&gt; and is credited with training [[Bruce Lee]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Castrounis1997&quot;&gt;Castrounis, L. (1997): [http://www.teamwingchun.co.uk/wong.php Wong Shun Leung (1936–1997)] (''sic''). Retrieved on 4 July 2009.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;PetersonPeterboro&quot;&gt;Peterson, D.: [http://homepage.ntlworld.com/pborowingchun1/different.htm Wong Shun Leung: The Legend behind the Legend; Recalling the life of Bruce Lee's teacher] Retrieved on 25 June 2009.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Montaigue&quot;&gt;Montaigue, E.: [http://www.vingtsunupdate.com/index.php?option=com_content&amp;task=view&amp;id=44&amp;Itemid=77 Interview with Wong Shun Leung] Retrieved on 6 July 2009.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;VTU&quot;&gt;[http://www.vingtsunupdate.com/index.php?option=com_content&amp;task=view&amp;id=52&amp;Itemid=76 Ving Tsun Update: Interview with Wong Shun Leung] Retrieved on 6 July 2009.&lt;/ref&gt; Wong reportedly won at least 60, and perhaps over 100, street fights against martial artists of various styles.&lt;ref name=&quot;PetersonPeterboro&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Poon&quot;&gt;Poon, D.: [http://www.vingtsunupdate.com/index.php?option=com_content&amp;task=view&amp;id=82&amp;Itemid=76  Interview with Wong Shun Leung] (originally published in ''Qi Magazine''). Retrieved on 6 July 2009.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Peterson2001a&quot;&gt;Peterson, D. (2001): [http://wslwingchun.resolvedesign.com/wong_shun_leung_ving_tsun_gung_fu.htm Wong Shun Leung Ving Tsun Gung Fu: A scientific approach to combat] (originally published in ''Fight Times'', October 2001, New Zealand). Retrieved on 15 March 2009.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;WSLVTAUK&quot;&gt;[http://www.wongvingtsun.co.uk/ Wong Shun Leung Ving Tsun Kung Fu Association UK] Retrieved on 4 July 2009.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Smith2006&quot;&gt;Smith, J. (16 November 2006): [http://www.vingtsunforum.com/forum/index.php?topic=303.msg837#msg837 Yesteryear Ving Tsun by Yuen Yim Keung] (interview). Retrieved on 5 July 2009.&lt;/ref&gt; Due to his reputation, he came to be known as 'Gong Sau Wong' (講手王 or 'King of Talking Hands').&lt;ref name=&quot;PetersonPeterboro&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Peterson2001a&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;NgFamily&quot;&gt;[http://www.ngfamilymartialarts.com/vingtsun_lineage/wongshunleung.htm Ng Family Martial Arts: Wong Shun Leung 1935–1997] Retrieved on 6 July 2009.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;PetersonVerratti1998&quot;&gt;Peterson, D., &amp; Verratti, E. (1998): [http://wslwingchun.resolvedesign.com/ving_tsun_by_definition.htm Ving Tsun by definition: Getting it right ... the “Wong Way”!!!] (originally published in ''Martial arts legends: Wing Chun'', November 1998, USA). Retrieved on 7 July 2009.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Peterson2001b&quot;&gt;Peterson, D. (2001): [http://wslwingchun.resolvedesign.com/get_out_of_the_way_and_make_them_pay_by_david_peterson.htm Get out of the way, ... and make them pay: The street-effective footwork of Wing Chun] (originally published in ''Fight Times'', December 2001 and January 2002, New Zealand). Retrieved on 6 July 2009.&lt;/ref&gt; Wong recorded one instructional film entitled ''Wing Chun: The science of in-fighting''.&lt;ref name=&quot;Cebridge2003&quot;&gt;Anonymous (2003): [http://www.cebridge.com.au/Ipman/Sifus/Wong%20Shun%20Leung.htm Wong Shun Leung] Retrieved on 4 July 2008.&lt;/ref&gt;

== Early martial arts training ==
Wong reportedly trained in several martial art styles in his youth, primarily in [[t'ai chi ch'uan]] and either [[boxing]] or [[kickboxing]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Castrounis1997&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Poon&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;NgFamily&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Peterson1990&quot;&gt;Peterson, D. (1990): [http://home.vtmuseum.org/articles/peterson/wongpers.php Wong Shun Leung: Wing Chun personified] (originally published in ''Inside Kung-Fu'', vol. 18, no. 2). Retrieved on 25 June 2009.&lt;/ref&gt; He abandoned boxing because of two incidents: one with his boxing coach and one with Yip Man.&lt;ref name=&quot;Peterson1990&quot;/&gt; The first incident apparently occurred because Wong accidentally struck his boxing coach during sparring. The angry coach attacked in earnest, only to be eventually knocked out by Wong; the incident caused Wong to leave boxing.&lt;ref name=&quot;Peterson1990&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Bayer&quot;&gt;Bayer, P.: [http://www.vingtsunupdate.com/index.php?option=com_content&amp;task=view&amp;id=12&amp;Itemid=48 Ving Tsun Update: Wong Shun Leung] Retrieved on 25 June 2009.&lt;/ref&gt; In another account, however, Wong said he had defeated his boxing coach with wing chun techniques: &quot;I was sparring with my instructor and I hit him very hard, he got real mad and came at me very hard. I fought back with wing chun and he ended up bleeding. Boxing was over for me!&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;VTU&quot;/&gt;

The second incident came about from Wong's fascination with the stories of legendary wing chun figures, such as  [[Chan Wah-shun]] (陳華順) and [[Leung Jan]] (梁贊). This interest led Wong to look for a wing chun teacher. Friends of his older brother took him to meet Yip Man. According to one version of events, after defeating at least two of Yip's students, Wong had a match with Yip himself and was defeated easily.&lt;ref name=&quot;NgFamily&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Peterson1990&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Bayer&quot;/&gt; Another version is that after Wong faced Lo Man Kam, Yip Po Ching defeated Wong.&lt;ref name=&quot;VTAA1990a&quot;/&gt; In any case, Wong joined the wing chun group and eventually came to assist Yip with teaching,&lt;ref name=&quot;NgFamily&quot;/&gt; with students including Bruce Lee. Lee once wrote in a letter to Wong, &quot;Even though I am (technically) a student of Yip Man, in reality I learned my Kung-fu from you.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;PetersonPeterboro&quot;/&gt; Wong was believed to have carried the letter in his wallet.&lt;ref name=&quot;Castrounis1997&quot;/&gt; Perhaps the best-known letter from Lee to Wong is that of 11 January 1970,&lt;ref name=&quot;Lee1970&quot;&gt;Lee, B. (1970): [http://www.jkd.com.hk/Chi/Photo_Gallery/images/wong_letter_big.jpg Bruce Lee's letter to Wong Shun Leung on 11 January 1970] (scan). Retrieved on 4 July 2009.&lt;/ref&gt; which has been translated into English as an appendix to an article by Wong.&lt;ref name=&quot;Wong1&quot;&gt;Wong, S. L.: [http://homepage.ntlworld.com/pborowingchun1/bruce_lee.htm Wong Shun Leung and His Friendship with Bruce Lee] Retrieved on 4 July 2009.&lt;/ref&gt;

== Fighting career ==
=== ''Beimo'' competition ===
[[File:Hong Kong view from The Peak 01.jpg|right|250px|thumb|Wong taught wing chun in Hong Kong throughout his life]]

Wong became active in ''beimo'' (比武): semi-organised bare-knuckle challenge fights in Hong Kong (sometimes known as 'kung fu elimination contests').&lt;ref name=&quot;wcheung&quot;&gt;[http://www.cheungswingchun.com/g/906/grandmaster-william-cheung.html Grandmaster William Cheung] Retrieved on 5 July 2009.&lt;/ref&gt; There were no rules, protective equipment, or time limits.&lt;ref name=&quot;PetersonPeterboro&quot;/&gt; As Wong recalled in an interview, &quot;When I competed, it was in secret. We went into a room, and the door was shut and there were no rules. The government did not allow them. They were illegal, but we didn't care. We fought until the other guy was knocked out.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;Poon&quot;/&gt; ''Beimo'' competitions were held anywhere that was found to be convenient. Some ''beimo'' competitions were held on the streets in Hong Kong.&lt;ref name=&quot;Cheung&quot;&gt;Cheung, H.: [http://www.hawkinscheung.com/html/profile.htm Hawkins Cheung Profile] Retrieved on 6 July 2009.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Peterson2005&quot;&gt;Peterson, D. (2005): [http://wslwingchun.resolvedesign.com/wong_shun_leung.htm The Wong Shun Leung Method of Wing Chun Fung Fu] (''sic''). Retrieved on 6 July 2009.&lt;/ref&gt;

In the early 1950s, compared to other kung fu styles, wing chun was hardly known.&lt;ref name=&quot;Leung&quot;&gt;Leung, D.: [http://members.tripod.com/~Wing_Chun/ The rise and fall of the Wing Chun (Ving Tsun) Family] Retrieved on 5 July 2009.&lt;/ref&gt; It was a style of kung fu practiced by a minority—mostly members of the Association of Restaurant Workers of Hong Kong.&lt;ref name=&quot;VTAA1990b&quot;&gt;Ving Tsun Athletic Association (1990): [http://www.vingtsun.org.hk/Development_1950-53.HTM The Development of Ving Tsun Kungfu in Hong Kong: 1950-1953] Retrieved on 5 July 2009.&lt;/ref&gt; Different kung fu schools met secretly with each other for challenge matches. Wong was said to have faced opponents from many disciplines—&quot;virtually every style of martial art in the colony.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;Peterson1990&quot;/&gt; He defeated many opponents in ''beimo'' matches in Hong Kong between the ages of 17 and 32, and his reputation grew as he continued winning these matches.&lt;ref name=&quot;Castrounis1997&quot;/&gt; Some have attributed wing chun's fame in Hong Kong to Wong's ''beimo'' reputation.&lt;ref name=&quot;Smith2006&quot;/&gt;

Students from different schools sometimes visited each other's schools and issued challenge to their top students and instructors. If a student was able to beat the main teacher or master of a particular school, the school would close down.&lt;ref name=&quot;Montaigue&quot;/&gt; According to some of Yip's first-generation students, Wong &quot;reputedly 'closed down' quite a number of schools in that way.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;Montaigue&quot;/&gt; Reportedly, Wong won most of these contests within a few punches.&lt;ref name=&quot;PetersonPeterboro&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Cebridge2003&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Martin2004&quot;&gt;Martin, M. (2004): [http://wslwingchun.resolvedesign.com/david_peterson_always_asume_there_is_somthing_to_learn.htm David Peterson: If you always assume that there’s always something to learn, you will always be successful!] (originally published in ''Combat Magazine'', September and October 2004). Retrieved on 6 July 2009.&lt;/ref&gt; Wong's prowess in ''beimo'' helped him convince his secondary school classmate, Wu Chan Nam, to become his first student—Wu witnessed his win in a ''beimo'' match.&lt;ref name=&quot;Wu&quot;&gt;Wu, C. N.: [http://web.archive.org/web/20090727201045/http://hk.geocities.com/hkvingtsun/introduction.htm  Ving Tsun Wu Chan Nam: Introduction] Retrieved on 6 July 2009.&lt;/ref&gt; In addition, he encouraged his junior fellow students and his own students to compete in ''beimo'' competitions and arranged matches for them.&lt;ref name=&quot;Smith2006&quot;/&gt; According to Yuen Yim Keung (袁炎強), Wong's student, Wong stopped arranging these matches because &quot;his students were defeating not only other Kung Fu styles but also other students of Ving Tsun outside of the Wong Shun Leung family.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;Smith2006&quot;/&gt; Wong also reportedly had a ''beimo'' match with a much bigger Russian boxer called Giko.&lt;ref name=&quot;PetersonPeterboro&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Peterson1990&quot;/&gt; John Smith (a student of one of Wong's students),&lt;ref name=&quot;Smith2004&quot;&gt;Smith, J. (2004): [http://members.ozemail.com.au/~jr.smith/index.html Illawarra Ving Tsun School: John Smith] Retrieved on 7 July 2009.&lt;/ref&gt; reports that Wong defeated Giko,&lt;ref name=&quot;Smith2005&quot;&gt;Smith, J. (2005): [http://www.takeforum.com/forum/viewtopic.php?p=779&amp;mforum=wongshunleung&amp;sid=d2ca617ab3d205509f00188c98ce2d26 Wong Shun Leung: The man and his method] (www.takeforum.com). This discussion is no longer available from the original host server, but [http://google.com/search?q=cache:_QGkzG5ZO5UJ:www.takeforum.com/forum/viewtopic.php%3Ft%3D107%26sid%3De47ba4ad6b9178f1466320d7a1c6e64a%26mforum%3Dwongshunleung+Giko+site:takeforum.com&amp;cd=1&amp;hl=en&amp;ct=clnk&amp;gl=au a copy from Google's cache] was retrieved on 7 July 2009.&lt;/ref&gt; and that Wong himself told Smith how he was able to achieve this victory.&lt;ref name=&quot;Smith2005&quot;/&gt;

Wong was believed to have had over 60, and perhaps over 100, ''beimo'' matches and never lost.&lt;ref name=&quot;Poon&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;WSLVTAUK&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Smith2006&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;NgFamily&quot;/&gt; This reputation earned him the name 'Gong Sau Wong' (i.e., 'King of Talking Hands').&lt;ref name=&quot;NgFamily&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;PetersonVerratti1998&quot;&gt;Peterson, D., &amp; Verratti, E. (1998): [http://wslwingchun.resolvedesign.com/ving_tsun_by_definition.htm Ving Tsun by definition: Getting it right ... the “Wong Way”!!!] (originally published in ''Martial arts legends: Wing Chun'', November 1998, USA). Retrieved on 7 July 2009.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Peterson2001b&quot;&gt;Peterson, D. (2001): [http://wslwingchun.resolvedesign.com/get_out_of_the_way_and_make_them_pay_by_david_peterson.htm Get out of the way, ... and make them pay: The street-effective footwork of Wing Chun] (originally published in ''Fight Times'', December 2001 and January 2002, New Zealand). Retrieved on 6 July 2009.&lt;/ref&gt; Once asked if he was the best fighter in the world, he replied, &quot;No, only the second best&quot;; when then asked who was the best, he said, &quot;I have not met him yet.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;Castrounis1997&quot;/&gt;

=== Retirement from ''beimo'' competition ===
In what was to be Wong's last ''beimo'' match, he unintentionally blinded his opponent's eye; he then decided to quit ''beimo'' fighting.&lt;ref name=&quot;LeBlanc&quot;&gt;LeBlanc, G. E.: [http://www.garylamwingchun.com/index.php?view=article&amp;catid=34%3Aarticles&amp;id=71%3Awing-chun-qi-sao-training-by-gregory-e-leblanc&amp;option=com_content&amp;Itemid=113 Wing Chun Qi Sao training] Retrieved on 7 July 2009.&lt;/ref&gt; Lee Hang Cheong (李恆昌), one of Wong's students, recalled that Wong had insulted his intended opponent (apparently a well-known kung fu instructor) to coerce him to fight, but regretted both instigating the fight and accidentally blinding the other man in one eye.&lt;ref name=&quot;LeeHC&quot;&gt;Lee, H. C.: [http://www.cnvt.com/mysifu5.htm 一代宗師黃淳樑: 黃淳樑之壯年, 作者: 李恆昌] (''The legendary Master Wong Shun Leung: His young and strong age'') {{zh icon}}. Retrieved on 7 July 2009.&lt;/ref&gt; There is a discrepancy between Lee's account and others about Wong's age when he retired from ''beimo'' competition. A few sources claim that Wong competed in ''beimo'' until the age of 32.&lt;ref name=&quot;Castrounis1997&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;PetersonPeterboro&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Cebridge2003&quot;/&gt; Lee, however, said that Wong was around the age of 24.&lt;ref name=&quot;LeeHC&quot;/&gt;
 
. When Wu Chan Nam fought in a ''beimo'' match, there was a referee present—Wong Kiu.&lt;ref name=&quot;WuWong&quot;&gt;Wu, C. N.: [http://web.archive.org/web/20090727201045/http://hk.geocities.com/hkvingtsun/picture_gallery.htm  Ving Tsun Wu Chan Nam Si Fu: Picture Gallery] Retrieved on 7 July 2009.&lt;/ref&gt; According to ''Life and Legend of Bruce Lee'', there was always supposed to be a referee present at a ''beimo'' match, as Wong re-enacted the scene of a 1950s ''beimo'' match on a rooftop and played the role of the referee.&lt;ref name=&quot;IMDbLifeLegend&quot;&gt;[http://www.imdb.com/title/tt0198652/ IMDb: Life and Legend of Bruce Lee] Retrieved on 7 July 2009.&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Other competitions ===
On 22 November 1957, the inaugural Taiwan–Hong Kong–Macau Open Chinese Kung Fu Competition (台港澳國術比賽) was held in Taiwan. Thirty-two competitors from Hong Kong and Macau formed a team and participated in this competition,&lt;ref name=&quot;Li1998&quot;&gt;Li, P. (July 1998). 李小龍: 神話再現 (''From limited to limitless: The ways of Bruce Lee'') {{zh icon}}. Hong Kong: Oriental Resources Company (東方匯澤公司).&lt;/ref&gt; but only two Hong Kong competitors scored a victory.&lt;ref name=&quot;Longley&quot;&gt;Longley, K.: [http://members-central.optushome.com.au/meanstreets/clf/clfsifu.htm Dave Lacey 'Lai Dai Wai': Buck Sing Choy Lay Fut's unrepentant 'Black Panther'] (originally published in ''Impact International Martial Arts Magazine''). Retrieved on 7 July 2009.&lt;/ref&gt; Wong competed in his weight class and had a preliminary match with Wu Ming Jeet (吳明哲), a Taiwanese fighter known for his powerful kicks, but was knocked out and eliminated.&lt;ref name=&quot;Li1998&quot;/&gt; A documentary film covering the competition was played in Hong Kong, with a first-day showing on 12 February 1958.&lt;ref name=&quot;Li1998&quot;/&gt;  In 1974, Unicorn Chan (小麒麟) recalled that it was in 1958 when Bruce Lee took him to watch a documentary film on kung fu competitions, and that Lee had watched it seven times before within the last four days.&lt;ref name=&quot;Li1998&quot;/&gt;

Wong once defeated a [[fencing]] champion on television with his wing chun [[balisong (knife)|butterfly knives]].&lt;ref name=&quot;LamLeBlanc&quot;&gt;Lam, G., &amp; LeBlanc, G. E.: [http://www.garylamwingchun.com/index.php?view=article&amp;catid=34%3Aarticles&amp;id=73%3Athe-wing-chun-double-knife-training-baat-jaam-do-by-sifu-gary-lam-with-gregory-e-leblanc&amp;option=com_content&amp;Itemid=113 The Wing Chun double knife training: Baat Jaam Do] Retrieved on 7 July 2009.&lt;/ref&gt; Gary Lam recounted that &quot;several years ago my Sifu, the late Wong Shun Leung, sparred with a champion western fencer on television. Wong easy beat the fencer, and when the fencer complained Wong had an unfair advantage with two swords, Wong offered him a second blade and beat him again.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;LamLeBlanc&quot;/&gt;

Wan Kam Leung (溫鑑良) witnessed the fight Wong fought with Bruce Lee when Lee returned to Hong Kong from the United States.&lt;ref name=&quot;WanYouTube2009&quot;&gt;[http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=LjuYLc4kt7w YouTube: Wan Kam Leung recalls Bruce lee fighting with Wong Shun Leung] (25 July 2009). Retrieved on 8 May 2010.&lt;/ref&gt; It took place at Lee's home in Kowloon Tong. Wong claimed that his hands were faster acting than Lee's, however Bruce retaliated by saying his kicks were much faster, thus provoking the friendly scuffle. Wan commented that Lee's kicks were fast and powerful whilst Wong's wing chun hand techniques were modified and practical. Wong and Lee only fought for a short period of time.&lt;ref name=&quot;WanYouTube2009&quot;/&gt;

== Filmography ==
=== Enter the Dragon ===
Some sources claim that Wong choreographed some fight scenes in ''[[Enter the Dragon]]'' (龍爭虎鬥), saying that &quot;... when shooting ''Enter the Dragon'' in Hong Kong, he [Bruce Lee] invited Wong to come on location to discuss the fight scenes&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;PetersonPeterboro&quot;/&gt; and that &quot;Wong in fact had been invited to choreograph some of the fight scenes in ''Enter the Dragon''.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;WSLVTAUK&quot;/&gt; The documentary ''Dragon since 1973'' consists of  interviews with various Hong Kong personalities, mostly those who worked with Lee in his [[Golden Harvest]] days. None of the interviewees, including Bee Chan (陳會毅; one of Lee's most trusted assistants),  [[Shek Kin]] (石堅), and Chaplin Chang (張欽鵬), mentioned that Wong had been invited to work as a fight scene choreographer for ''Enter the Dragon''.&lt;ref name=&quot;DragonSince1973&quot;&gt;[http://www.artoftoy.com/drsi19.html 龍一九七三以後] (''Dragon since 1973''). Retrieved on 8 July 2009.&lt;/ref&gt; 
 
A photograph of Wong, Lee, and [[Raymond Chow]] (鄒文懐) on one of the sets of ''Enter the Dragon'' (the weapon room) implies that Wong was present during filming.&lt;ref name=&quot;WSLVTAUK&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Bayer&quot;/&gt; Wong appears in the same clothing in that photograph as he wears in the footage of himself sparring with an extra on that particular set,&lt;ref name=&quot;IMDbBruceLeeLegend&quot;&gt;[http://www.imdb.com/title/tt0075788/ IMDb: Bruce Lee, the Legend] Retrieved on 7 July 2009.&lt;/ref&gt; and thus could have been from the time when Wong attended a screen test for ''Game of Death'', as described below.

=== Game of Death ===
Wong received an invitation to appear in ''[[Game of Death]]'' (死亡遊戲), but declined. He was scheduled to attend a screen test on the set of ''Enter the Dragon'' after Bruce Lee had finished shooting the film and was working on dubbing. Lee returned to Hong Kong from his last trip to the United States of America in late May 1973.&lt;ref name=&quot;Li1998&quot;/&gt; Thus, Wong would have attended the screen test sometime in June 1973.&lt;ref name=&quot;IMDbBruceLeeLegend&quot;/&gt; Wong recalled, &quot;About two months before he (Bruce Lee) died he gave me a phone call ... After this he left Hong Kong to settle his film business. When he came back, he called me up and wanted me to participate in the making of ''Game of Death''. He had also invited me to the studio to attend a screen test. I did not promise to act in the film, yet I still went to attend the screen test to please him.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;Wong2&quot;&gt;Wong, S. L.: [http://web.ukonline.co.uk/ray.d8/article13.html Wong Shun Leung on Bruce Lee] Retrieved on 7 July 2009.&lt;/ref&gt; In a 1986 interview, Wong said, &quot;I told him (Bruce Lee) that I didn't want to go and die in my first movie! ... I wasn't in dire financial straits at the time, so I didn't have to do the film (just) to make money.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;PetersonPeterboro&quot;/&gt; The role of Lee's final opponent was thus played by basketball star Kareem Abdul-Jabbar.&lt;ref name=&quot;PetersonPeterboro&quot;/&gt; In another interview, Wong said, &quot;It was for ''Game of Death'', but I declined because I thought that the moves of Wing Chun style wouldn’t look good on film. I think the Wing Chun method is ugly for movies but very good and very logical for real fighting.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;VTU&quot;/&gt;

=== Later film work ===
In 1973, shortly after Bruce Lee's death, Wong acted in ''Life and Legend of Bruce Lee''. In this Chinese film, Wong played the role of himself, an instructor at Yip Man's wing chun school who first met a teenager named Lee in the 1950s.&lt;ref name=&quot;IMDbLifeLegend&quot;/&gt; In the 1993 documentary film ''Death by Misadventure'', Wong talked about his experiences with Lee.&lt;ref name=&quot;IMDbDeathByMisadventure&quot;&gt;[http://www.imdb.com/title/tt0121193/ IMDb: Death by Misadventure] Retrieved on 8 July 2009.&lt;/ref&gt; He also starred in a training video, entitled ''Wing Chun: the Science of In-fighting'', which was produced in the early 1980s.&lt;ref name=&quot;Cebridge2003&quot;/&gt;

== Legacy ==

Wong's participation in, and views on, tournaments reflected his philosophy on martial arts. When asked, &quot;Did you compete in any organised tournaments with rules?&quot; Wong replied, &quot;Not in boxing. When I competed, it was in secret. We went into a room, and the door was shut and there were no rules. The government did not allow them. They were illegal, but we didn't care. We fought until the other guy was knocked out.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;Poon&quot;/&gt; When asked, &quot;Did you ever consider competing in combat sports?&quot; Wong replied, &quot;I have always liked boxing, I like anything about fighting, but my kind of fighting is not the sport version, it is real fighting where there are no rules.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;VTU&quot;/&gt;

== Notes ==
&lt;div class=&quot;references-small&quot;&gt;
'''a.''' {{note_label|A|a|none}} Wong's date of birth is given as 8 May 1935 by Philipp Bayer (one of his students) and Roy Horan (in an article for ''Black Belt'' magazine in 1983),&lt;ref name=&quot;Bayer&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Horan1983&quot;&gt;Horan, R. (1983): &quot;Wong Shun Leung: A Wing Chun phenomenon.&quot; ''Black Belt'', 21(9):28–35&lt;/ref&gt; but some other sources give his date of birth as 8 June 1935.&lt;ref name=&quot;AuyeungLuk2005&quot;&gt;Auyeung, C., &amp; Luk, L. (''c.'' 2005): [http://wslwingchun.resolvedesign.com/wong_shun_leung_the_legend.htm Wong Shun Leung, the Legend] Retrieved on 8 May 2010.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;WCA2006&quot;&gt;[http://www.wcarchive.com/bios/wsl-method.htm The Wing Chun Archive: The Wong Shun Leung Method] (20 February 2006). Retrieved on 8 May 2010.&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

==References==
{{reflist|2}}

{{Persondata &lt;!-- Metadata: see [[Wikipedia:Persondata]] --&gt;
|NAME = Wong, Shun Leung
|ALTERNATIVE NAMES = 
|SHORT DESCRIPTION = Martial artist
|DATE OF BIRTH = 8 May 1935
|PLACE OF BIRTH = [[Hong Kong]]
|DATE OF DEATH = 28 January 1997
|PLACE OF DEATH = [[Hong Kong]]
}} &lt;!-- Goes above DEFAULTSORT/Categories --&gt;
{{DEFAULTSORT:Wong, Shun Leung}}
[[Category:1935 births]]
[[Category:1997 deaths]]
[[Category:Chinese martial artists]]
[[Category:Chinese Wing Chun practitioners]]
[[Category:Deaths from stroke]]
[[Category:Wing Chun]]
[[Category:Wing Chun practitioners from Hong Kong]]

[[fr:Wong Shun Leung]]
[[it:Wong Shun Leung]]
[[pl:Wong Shun Leung]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
