<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="136530" ns="0" title="RTFM"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{about|the help-request response|the knowledge-base application|Request Tracker|the Poster Children album|RTFM (album)}}
{{essay-like|date=May 2011}}
:''In [[ray tracing]] or within the context of [[BRL-CAD]], &quot;RTFM&quot; may stand for &quot;ray tracing figure of merit&quot;.

'''RTFM''' is an [[acronym and initialism|initialism]] for the direction &quot;'''R'''ead '''T'''he '''F'''ucking '''M'''anual&quot;. This instruction is sometimes given in response to a question when the person being asked believes that the question could be easily answered by reading the relevant [[user guide|user's manual]] or instructions. In [[expurgation|expurgated]] texts, substitutions such as &quot;read the flaming manual&quot; or &quot;read the friendly manual&quot; are used&lt;ref&gt;Howard, Michael, David LeBlanc, and [[John Viega]]. ''19 Deadly Sins of Software Security: Programming Flaws and How to Fix Them''. New York: McGraw-Hill/Osborne, 2005. ISBN 0072260858.&lt;/ref&gt; (or [[#List of expurgated expansions|similar variants]]). Initialisms similar to the one above include ''' GIYF''' (&quot;[[Google search|Google]] is your friend&quot;) and '''LMGTFY''' (&quot;let me google that for you&quot;). These indicate that the item under question can easily be researched on the [[World_wide_web|Internet]].

Many alternative expansions for &quot;RTFM&quot; exist (particularly [[#List of expurgated expansions|expurgated ones]]), as do many [[#List of similar initialisms|similarly themed alternative initialisms]].

==Possible origins==
The phrase RTFM may have first appeared in print in 1979 on the Table of Contents page of the ''[[LINPACK]] Users' Guide''&lt;ref&gt;Dongarra, J. J., C. B. Moler, J. R. Bunch, and G. W. Stewart. ''LINPACK User's Guide''. Philadelphia: SIAM, 1979.  ISBN 089871172X.&lt;/ref&gt;  in the form: [http://books.google.com/books?id=AmSm1n3Vw0cC&amp;printsec=toc &quot;R.T.F.M.&quot; -- Anonymous]. Apocryphally, some of the authors heard it from a [[Tektronix]] salesman.

The phrase RTFM was in common use in the early 1950s by radio and radar technicians in the US Air Force.  Operators frequently did not check simple faults, for example checking whether a fuse had blown or a power plug had become disconnected.{{Citation needed|date=August 2009}}

== Context-sensitive factors in determining (in)appropriateness ==
The appropriateness or inappropriateness of an RTFM or GIYF response depends on the context and the people involved.

=== When asking represents shirking (ant-versus-grasshopper contexts) ===
In contexts where the people involved are peers in a harsh (or at least competitive) environment—one where everyone is equal, there is work to be done, and each ought to pull his own weight—it can be inappropriate to ask beginner-level questions of one's peers without having &quot;done one's homework first&quot;. The asker shows a degree of either incompetence or rudeness, which harder-working colleagues do not wish to reward. The implicit subtext in the responder's mind is, &quot;We all have to work hard, and to learn the hard way, in this environment. If I had to work my way up to where I am, why should I reward ''your'' laziness or ineptitude with free [[concierge]] service?&quot; This kind of situation is analogous to that of ''[[The Ant and the Grasshopper]]'', in which the ant's refusal to suffer the foolishness of the grasshopper is understandable. This principle can be found among peers in workplaces, schools, and some online communities. For example: 
* '''&quot;On the job&quot; or &quot;in the field&quot;.''' It takes a certain minimum level of competence and self-guided effort to be a [[programmer]], and most especially a [[Hacker (programmer subculture)|hacker-grade programmer]]. One cannot attain the role just by asking others to hand it to him. (This is also true of many other skills in life.) Hackers have often suggested that in some situations, &quot;RTFM&quot; is actually the best advice that an aspiring hacker can receive.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.catb.org/~esr/faqs/smart-questions.html &quot;How To Ask Questions The Smart Way&quot;]—Eric Steven Raymond and Rick Moen&lt;/ref&gt; They posit that hacking is a dynamic art that requires independence and drive on the part of the hacker, and see &quot;RTFM&quot; as more of a long-term advisement than it is a response to any single query.
* '''At school.''' There is a difference between someone who's trying hard, studying conscientiously, and just needs some tutoring (on one hand) and someone who idly shirked his homework and now expects his peers to give him the answers (on the other). The former deserves respect and help; the latter chooses to forfeit both.

=== When asking is excusable or even natural ===
The ant-versus-grasshopper argument only applies to the types of cases discussed earlier. It does not apply in cases where the asker's [[naïve|naïveté]] is excusable (and often may be entirely appropriate). For example, [[technical support]] staff for consumer software or devices would be fired for giving RTFM or GIYF responses, because it is their ''job'' to help [[wikt:novice#Noun|novices]]. To expect minimum background knowledge on the part of the user is not always well-founded; there is a spectrum of appropriateness for different products or services. For example, with radiographic equipment such as a [[X-ray computed tomography|CT scanner]], one would reasonably require the operator to have competence in [[Radiobiology|radiological safety]]; but for consumer electronics, the goal (distant as it often may be) is to shield the user from having to possess any arbitrary threshold of skill. In fact, when it comes to software for general-population users, the evolving standard in [[usability]] is that software be engineered (often at great pains) to be usable without a manual at all, since users don't often actually read them, and in many contexts, perhaps should not even be expected to.&lt;ref&gt;[http://joelonsoftware.com/uibook/chapters/fog0000000062.html User Interface Design for Programmers - Chapter 6: Designing for People Who Have Better Things To Do With Their Lives]&lt;/ref&gt; For example, some of the &quot;great pains&quot; that engineers now go to in order to shield users from complexity &quot;under the hood&quot; are the &quot;contextual help&quot; paradigm; [[automation]] (as with [[engine control unit]]s, [[anti-lock braking system]]s, and [[traction control system]]s that make car operation closer to foolproof than it used to be); weak [[artificial intelligence]] (AI) (such as today's [[expert system]]s); and the ongoing quest for strong AI (to build tomorrow's expert systems). 

Whenever the target market is the consumer among the general public, to assume ''any'' degree of competence is to ask for trouble, even for products that incompetents have no legitimate excuse to be operating (e.g., [[motor vehicle]]s, [[firearm]]s, [[heavy equipment (construction)|construction equipment]]). Even for the latter products, every effort is made in their engineering to make them as negligence-resistant and fail-safe as possible within the bounds of physics and of [[break-even (economics)|breaking even]].

=== Gray areas (gradients between ant-vs-grasshopper and legitimate needs) ===
There are contexts and participants for which a gradient of RTFM (in)appropriateness exists. These are the [[wikt:grey area|gray areas]] between black and white. Some examples are given in the following sections.

==== Internet forums ====
An [[internet forum]] where users should read the [[FAQ]] before posting their questions is more likely to have a better [[signal-to-noise ratio#Informal use|signal-to-noise ratio]] than one that is filled with repetitive postings, and hence is more useful and more likely to attract continued participation. When evaluating whether it is acceptable to express sentiments like RTFM, one must consider the trade-off between maintaining the [[usability]] of a forum for its existing users, and making a forum welcoming to newcomers. The balance point for a particular forum depends on how general the audience is intended to be; but, as with the motor vehicle and firearm examples earlier, one must allow for the inevitability that people will find their way into the user population who do not meet the expectations. And unlike with motor vehicles and firearms (where unqualified users are committing an infraction by the very act of participating), there is nothing inappropriate about novices learning, for example, to play games or to use [[office suite|office software suite]]s. In these cases, as in the technical support example, there is no reasonable expectation of minimum skill requirements. In such environments, frequent users of RTFM or GIYF responses are simply expressing [[elitism]], stroking a personality flaw such as a need to tear others down to seek self-esteem. Their time could better be spent adding the question and answer to an FAQ, pointing the user to a helpful website, or simply not responding.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.linuxquestions.org/questions/showthread.php?t=195983  Telling people to use &quot;Google,&quot; to &quot;RTFM,&quot; or &quot;Use the search feature&quot;]—[[LinuxQuestions.org]]&lt;/ref&gt; This is especially true when, for example, it is not even clear which &quot;manual&quot; the receiver of the RTFM response should be reading.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.linuxquestions.org/questions/showthread.php?t=305648  Please point to the right &quot;M&quot; so I can &quot;RTFM&quot;]—LinuxQuestions.org&lt;/ref&gt;  One of the most frequent criticisms of the [[open source]] community is lack of friendly support for newcomers. The [[Ubuntu (operating system)|Ubuntu]] Forums and LinuxQuestions.org, for instance, have instituted &quot;no RTFM&quot; policies to promote a welcoming atmosphere.&lt;ref&gt;[http://ubuntuforums.org/index.php?page=policy Forum Policies and Expectations]—Ubuntu Forums&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.linuxquestions.org/questions/showthread.php?p=2164604#post2164604 &quot;Newbie subspecies&quot;]—thread on LinuxQuestions.org&lt;/ref&gt;

{{Quote|RTFM [and] &quot;Go look on google&quot; are two inappropriate responses to a question. If you don't know the answer or don't wish to help, please say nothing instead of brushing off someone's question. Politely showing someone how you searched or obtained the answer to a question is acceptable, even encouraged.

...

If you wish to remind a user to use search tools or other resources when they have asked a question you feel is basic or common, please be very polite. Any replies for help that contain language disrespectful towards the user asking the question, i.e. &quot;[[Shut up|STFU]]&quot; or &quot;RTFM&quot; are unacceptable and will not be tolerated.|[http://ubuntuforums.org/index.php?page=policy Forum Policies and Expectations]|Ubuntu Forums}}

==== Superior-to-subordinate feedback in workplaces or schools ====
Unlike with feedback between peers in workplaces or schools (where the ant-and-grasshopper model may often clearly apply), feedback from superiors to subordinates involves a degree of [[wikt:forbearance#Noun|forbearance]] regarding incompetence. Not all incompetence is permanent, and not all infractions are grave. Managers and teachers have to walk a line and find the right balance. Laziness and incompetence are themselves teachable faults to some degree, which means that a superior has a responsibility &quot;to help the asker to ''learn'' to help himself&quot;, even if it takes time and various attempts; but at some point, a line may be crossed, where fairness to others (and duty to other obligations) precludes any further &quot;hand holding&quot; or &quot;training wheels&quot;. In the workplace, the worker might have to be fired; in the school, the student may have to be disciplined (if able but unwilling) or (more likely) referred for special help or shifted into a different group of students. The school environment is more complex than the workplace, with greater responsibility on the part of the superior, because a schoolteacher always has a responsibility to recognize possible attention deficit or learning disability, and to refer the student for help in those areas (without which help, the student's inability to help himself is, to an important degree, not his own fault). In the business world, however, where the very employment itself is conditional on competence, the manager does not shoulder that responsibility beyond a basic degree of &quot;giving a fair shake&quot;. Although there exists such a thing as improper termination, an RTFM/GIYF response from a manager tends to be more justified than one from a teacher. Even a teacher, though, is usually justified in saying, &quot;If you didn't want to fail the quiz, then you should have done your homework instead of skateboarding/watching TV/etc.&quot;

==== Technological evolution catching workers off guard ====
The rapid advance of technology has caught many workers off guard, and they find that &quot;the bar was raised and I didn't see it coming.&quot; Competencies that formerly were optional have become minimum requirements; certain knowledge, which they were formerly not responsible for having, has become a [[wikt:sine qua non#Noun|sine qua non]], either in general culture or at least in the culture of a particular occupation. Common examples are [[digital literacy]] and [[acronym and initialism|initialism]] literacy in the workplace. Many workers today might agree that someone who doesn't know what the initialisms &quot;FYI&quot; or &quot;OS&quot; stand for is probably not competent to continue holding a white-collar job, because such jobs require a minimum degree of general knowledge, and initialisms such as those are no longer just [[slang]] for [[computer science|comp-sci]] geeks but rather have become common vocabulary in the general knowledge of all but IT illiterates. In other words, at some point in history, terms that used to be slang shift into basic vocabulary, and this principle applies to decades-old [[internet slang]] just as it has always applied to many other kinds of slang. If, on top of that, the asker also doesn't know that they should search its expansion before asking someone, then once again, there may be legitimate resentment in his subordinates that they must &quot;[[managing upward|manage upward]]&quot; to such a [[wikt:mollycoddling|mollycoddling]] degree, because the very GIYF principle itself has been shifting into the area of &quot;general knowledge that is lacked only by incompetents.&quot; The degree of mollycoddling needed also indicates that the executives further up the line are themselves failing to do their jobs, because they have not provided adequate training or retraining (beyond mere on-the-job scrambling). Other example pieces of knowledge that used to be optional but have become a minimum requirement in the business world include basic [[file manager|file management]]. The grayer areas are ones where incompetence is currently stretching past annoyance toward negligence. The shade of gray for any particular skill (or lack thereof) depends on the occupation.

==List of expurgated expansions==
* Read the [[field manual]] (military contexts)
* Read the fine manual
* Read the freaking manual
* Read the friendly manual
* Read the full manual
* Read the full-on manual

==List of similar initialisms==
===Encouraging the reading of the manual or other background information===
* {{Visible anchor|RTBM}}  (&quot;read the bloody manual&quot;) (In some countries, e.g., the UK and Australia, this is a fractionally more polite alternative with identical meaning&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://foldoc.org/RTBM |title=RTBM definition |publisher=foldoc.com |accessdate=2009-12-08}}&lt;/ref&gt;)
* {{Visible anchor|RTFA}} (&quot;read the fucking article&quot;—common on news forums such as [[Fark.com]]&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://forums.fark.com/cgi/fark/comments.pl?IDLink=4047872 |title=Routine traffic stop has man up in arms. Er, caught red-handed. Er, never mind, just RTFA |publisher=Fark.com |date=2008-11-28 |accessdate=2009-01-27}}&lt;/ref&gt; and [[Slashdot]], where using &quot;TFA&quot; instead of &quot;the article&quot; has become a [[Internet meme|meme]])
* {{Visible anchor|RTFE}} (&quot;read the fucking e-mail&quot;)
* {{Visible anchor|RTFC}} (&quot;read the fucking code&quot; [also &quot;reboot the fucking computer&quot; or &quot;read the fucking card&quot;])
* {{Visible anchor|RTFSC}} (&quot;read the fucking [[source code]]&quot;)
* {{Visible anchor|RTFSM}} (&quot;read the fucking [[SWIFT]] message&quot;)
* {{Visible anchor|RTFQ}} (&quot;read the fucking question&quot;)
* {{Visible anchor|RTFFAQ}} (&quot;read the fucking [[frequently asked questions]]&quot;)
* {{Visible anchor|UTFH}} (&quot;use the fucking help&quot;)
* {{Visible anchor|UTSL}} (&quot;use the source, Luke&quot;, a play on the famous ''Star Wars'' quote, &quot;Use the [[Force (Star Wars)|Force]], [[Luke Skywalker|Luke]]&quot;, referring to freely available [[source code]])

===Encouraging the use of at least a basic search===
* {{Visible anchor|UTFG}} (&quot;Use the fucking Google&quot;)
* {{Visible anchor|GIYF}} (&quot;Google is your friend&quot;)
* {{Visible anchor|JFGI}} (&quot;just fucking Google it&quot;)
* {{Visible anchor|JFWI}} (&quot;just fucking [[Wikipedia|Wiki]] it&quot;)
* {{Visible anchor|JGIYN}} (&quot;just Google it, you [[noob]]&quot;)
* {{Visible anchor|STFG}} (&quot;search the fucking [[Google search|Google]]&quot; (the initials are [[literary consonance|consonant]] with [[Shut up|STFU]])
* {{Visible anchor|STFW}} (&quot;[[Web search engine|search]] the fucking [[World Wide Web|Web]]&quot;) (the initials are [[literary consonance|consonant]] with [[Shut up|STFU]])
* {{Visible anchor|WIDGI}} (&quot;when in doubt, Google it&quot;—also occasionally &quot;WIDGIT&quot;)
* {{Visible anchor|WABM}} (&quot;write a better manual&quot; – an answer to complaining that the manual is not written well)

==See also==
{{wiktionary|RTFM|RTFA}}
* [[Internet slang]]
* [[Unix manual]] (&quot;man&quot; pages)
* [[Usability engineering]]
* [[User interface design]]

==References==
{{reflist}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Rtfm}}
[[Category:Internet slang]]
[[Category:Technical communication]]

[[bg:RTFM]]
[[cs:RTFM]]
[[de:Liste von Abkürzungen (Netzjargon)#R]]
[[es:RTFM]]
[[ko:RTFM]]
[[it:RTFM]]
[[he:RTFM]]
[[nl:Read the fucking manual]]
[[no:RTFM]]
[[pl:RTFM]]
[[pt:RTFM]]
[[ru:RTFM (компьютерный сленг)]]
[[sk:RTFM]]
[[uk:RTFM]]
[[zh:RTFM]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
