<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="13730210" ns="0" title="Battle for the A-9 highway"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Refimprove|date=August 2008}}
{{Infobox Military Conflict
|conflict=Battle for the A-9 highway
|partof=the [[Sri Lankan civil war]]&lt;br&gt;[[Operation Unceasing Waves III]]
|image=
|caption=
|date=March 27, 2000 – April 20, 2000
|place=[[Sri Lanka]]
|casus=
|territory=
|result=Tamil Tiger victory
|combatant1=[[Image:Coat of arms of Sri Lanka.svg|18px]] [[Military of Sri Lanka]]
|combatant2=[[Liberation Tigers of Tamil Eelam]]
|commander1=Unknown
|commander2=[[Velupillai Prabhakaran]]
|strength1=
|strength2=
|casualties1=203 killed&lt;br&gt;1,067 wounded&lt;ref name='strategypage'&gt;[http://www.strategypage.com/search.asp?target=d:\inetpub\strategypageroot\fyeo\qndguide\docs\archives\sril2ka.htm&amp;search=sri+lanka+2000+january-june StrategyPage.com - Search the StrategyPage&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;
|casualties2=317 killed&lt;ref name='strategypage'/&gt;
|casualties3=50 civilians killed&lt;ref name='strategypage'/&gt;
|notes=
}}
{{Campaignbox Eelam War III}}
{{Campaignbox Sri Lankan Civil War}}

The '''Battle for the A-9 highway''' was a battle fought in March and April 2000 for the control of the Sri Lankan A-9 highway.

==Background==
The A-9 highway connected the Sri Lankan capital with the northern Jaffna peninsula.  More impotently the [[Elephant Pass]] military base, which was the only land route for Jaffna. If the rebels were going to surround Elephant Pass they would have to take the north-south highway.

==Battle==
On March 27, the LTTE attacked the north-south highway. LTTE rebels attacked a coastal army base with a combined land and amphibious assault. The navy shot up the LTTE flotilla of small boats, but the ground attack continued. Heavy fighting continued into the night.

On March 28, the LTTE offensive is closing in on a four-base government complex. By next morning those bases fall. Several SLA tanks are also captured.

By March 30, the Tigers took another government base and managed to cut the A-9 highway. By this point thousands of civilian refugees had fled the area. The air force had been hitting rebel columns caught in the open while the navy had prevented the rebels from landing reinforcements along the coast. 

By April 3, the LTTE continued to hold a four kilometer stretch of the A-9 highway. However more army reinforcements were coming in by air and sea, and also air strikes and navy ships were hitting the rebels hard stalling the LTTE offensive.

On April 11, the army managed, after two weeks of heavy fighting, to retake the A-9 highway and clear all rebel positions from it.

On April 18, however, the LTTE renewed its offensive on the A-9. And the next day they cut the A-9 highway again. By the next day all remaining SLA troops were in retreat toward the Elephant Pass military base, which was coming under heavy rebel artillery fire. Thus the operation to take the highway was a success for the Tigers and this led to a more greater success in the battle for Elephant Pass, which fell three days later.&lt;ref name='strategypage'/&gt;

==See also==
*[[List of Sri Lankan Civil War battles]]

==References==
{{Reflist}}

{{coord missing|Sri Lanka}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Battle For The A-9 Highway}}
[[Category:Conflicts in 2000]]
[[Category:2000 in Sri Lanka]]
[[Category:Eelam War III]]
[[Category:Battles of the Sri Lankan Civil War]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
