<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="13746825" ns="0" title="First Battle of Elephant Pass"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Infobox Military Conflict
|conflict=First Battle of Elephant Pass
|partof=the [[Sri Lankan civil war]]
|image=
|caption=
|date=July 10, 1991 - August 9, 1991
|place=[[Elephant Pass]], [[Sri Lanka]]
|casus=
|territory=
|result=Sri Lankan Army victory
|combatant1=[[Image:Coat of arms of Sri Lanka.svg|18px]] [[Military of Sri Lanka]]
|combatant2=[[Liberation Tigers of Tamil Eelam]]
|commander1=
|commander2=
|strength1=10,800
|strength2=5,000
|casualties1=202-400+ killed&lt;ref name='atimes'&gt;[http://atimes.com/atimes/South_Asia/DG27Df02.html Asia Times&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;
|casualties2=573-1,000+ killed&lt;ref name='atimes'/&gt;
|notes=
}}
{{Campaignbox Eelam War II}}
{{Campaignbox Sri Lankan Civil War}}

The '''First Battle of Elephant Pass''' was a battle fought in July 1991 for the control of the Sri Lankan military base of [[Elephant Pass]], which was of strategic importance as it linked the northern mainland known as Wanni with the Jaffna Peninsula.

==The battle==
On July 10, 1991, the LTTE launched a massive attack at Elephant Pass. The battle for Elephant Pass was up till then the most violent and bloody confrontation that ever took place between the LTTE and the Sri Lankan Army. The LTTE had previously surrounded the base and blocked off routes north and south so no reinforcements could come in. Also at the beginning of July the LTTE moved anti-aircraft guns close to the base so no helicopters can bring in supplies. Thus the 800 troops of the 6th battalion of the [[Sri Lanka Sinha Regiment]] stationed in the base were trapped, yet led by Major (later Major General) Sanath Karunaratne fought on. The assault came from the south. On the first day the LTTE captured a few bunkers held by Sri Lankan troops. The LTTE used in the attack steel plated earth moving vehicles and tractors. They fired hundreds of mortar rounds on the positions of the armed forces. By the next day the second-in-command of the base was killed in a mortar attack.

Helicopters were not able to land at the base because of heavy enemy fire. Eventually, the Rest House camp in the southern sector of the base, fell into the hands of the LTTE. Sustaining heavy losses, the Sri Lankan troops fell back to the rear positions.

As dusk fell the LTTE cadres launched several attacks. Flanked by hundreds of their armed cadres, they surrounded the Army's fortifications. But the sight of a hitherto unknown bulldozer covered with armored plates looking like a huge tank sent shock waves among soldiers at all sentry points as the huge bulldozer tank was a mystery to all on guard.Equipped with a machine gun atop it and containing a haul of arms and ammunition inside it rumbled towards the southern entrance of the camp and Lance Corporal [[Gamini Kularatne]] in his pensive mood thought this new rolling weapon would definitely be able to swarm the garrison within seconds taking a heavy toll of his fellowmen.Suddenly Lance Corporal Kularatne, holding two grenades in his hands, dashed out towards the incoming bulldozer tank, clambered up the tank's ladder and tossed the two grenades inside it. The tank exploded and [[Gamini Kularatne]] was killed instantly. He was awarded the 
[[Parama Weera Vibhushanaya]] (Equivalent to medal of honor in USA) highest medal awarded to on service men in srilanka.

==Operation Balavegaya==
{{main|Operation Balavegaya}}
Fierce fighting continued for four days before a rescue force was sent. A huge force of 10,000 soldiers was sent to reinforce the Sri Lankan Army. An amphibious landing was conducted at Vettilaikerni, which was just 12 kilometers east of the base. However, much resistance was encountered from the Tigers, due to which it took them 18 days to reach the Elephant Pass base.

With the heavy losses in men and material, the troops finally reached the Elephant Pass base, on the evening of August 3. The fighting continued until August 9, when finally the LTTE made a tactical withdrawal. The LTTE suffered 573 Tigers killed according to Tamil sources, but according to SLA sources over 1,000 of them were killed. The Army had 202 dead according to government sources, but according to LTTE sources over 400 were killed. Estimates in later years put the number of dead on both sides to be 2,000 killed. The president called the battle the 'Mother of all Battles'. However, eight and a half years later the base was attacked again and that time the Tigers overran and took the base.&lt;ref name='atimes'/&gt; And after another eight and half years the [[Sri Lankan Army]] took control of the base ([[Third Battle of Elephant Pass]])in there northern offensive which ended on May 2009 completely destroying the LTTE.

==See also==
*[[Second Battle of Elephant Pass]]
*[[Third Battle of Elephant Pass]]
*[[List of Sri Lankan Civil War battles]]
*[[Gamini Kularatne]]
*[[Second Battle of Elephant Pass]]
*[[Third Battle of Elephant Pass]]

==References==
{{Reflist}}

{{coord|9.54726|80.408936|type:landmark_region:LK|display=title}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:First Battle Of Elephant Pass}}
[[Category:Eelam War II]]
[[Category:Battles of the Sri Lankan Civil War]]
[[Category:Military history of Sri Lanka]]
[[Category:Conflicts in 1991]]
[[Category:1991 in Sri Lanka]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
