<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="13787" ns="0" title="Hermetic Order of the Golden Dawn"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{About|the historical organization of the late 19th century|similar later organizations|Golden Dawn (disambiguation)}}
{{Hermetism}}
The '''Hermetic Order of the Golden Dawn''' (or, more commonly, the '''Golden Dawn''') was a [[Magical organization|magical order]] active in [[Great Britain]] during the late 19th and early 20th centuries, which practiced [[theurgy]] and spiritual development.  It has been one of the largest single influences on 20th-century Western [[occultism]].&lt;ref&gt;Jenkins, Phillip (2000) ''Mystics and Messiahs: Cults and New Religions in American History'', pg. 74. &quot;Also in the 1880s, the tradition of ritual magic was revived in London by a group of Masonic adepts, who formed the Order of the Golden Dawn, which would prove an incalculable influence on the whole subsequent history of occultism.&quot; USA: Oxford University Press.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Smoley, Richard (1999) ''Hidden Wisdom: A Guide to the Western Inner Traditions'', ppg 102-103. &quot;Founded in 1888, the Golden Dawn lasted a mere twelve years before it was shattered by personal conflicts. At it's{{sic?}} height it probably had no more than a hundred members. Yet its influence on magic and esoteric thought in the English-speaking world would be hard to overestimate.&quot; USA: Quest Books.&lt;/ref&gt;

Concepts of [[Magic (paranormal)|magic]] and ritual at the center of contemporary traditions, such as [[Wicca]]&lt;ref name=Colquhoun&gt;[[Ithell Colquhoun|Colquhoun, Ithell]] (1975) ''The Sword of Wisdom: MacGregor Mathers &amp; the Golden Dawn''. New York: G.P. Putnam's Sons.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Phillips, Julia (1991) [http://www.geraldgardner.com/History_of_Wicca_Revised.pdf ''History of Wicca in England: 1939 - present day''].  Lecture at the Wiccan Conference in Canberra, 1991.&lt;/ref&gt; and [[Thelema]], were inspired by the Golden Dawn.

The three founders, [[William Robert Woodman]], [[William Wynn Westcott]], and [[Samuel Liddell MacGregor Mathers]] were [[Freemasons]] and members of [[Societas Rosicruciana in Anglia]] (S.R.I.A.).&lt;ref&gt;Regardie, 1993, page 10&lt;/ref&gt;   Westcott appears to have been the initial driving force behind the establishment of the Golden Dawn.

The Golden Dawn system was based on hierarchy and initiation like the [[Masonic Lodge]]s; however women were admitted on an equal basis with men.  The &quot;Golden Dawn&quot; was the first of three Orders, although all three are often collectively referred to as the &quot;Golden Dawn&quot;.  The First Order taught esoteric philosophy based on the [[Hermetic Qabalah]] and personal development through study and awareness of the [[Classical Elements|four Classical Elements]] as well as the basics of [[astrology]], [[tarot divination]], and [[geomancy]].  The Second or &quot;Inner&quot; Order, the ''Rosae Rubeae et Aureae Crucis'' (the Ruby Rose and Cross of Gold), taught proper magic, including [[scrying]], [[Astral projection|astral travel]], and [[alchemy]].  The Third Order was that of the &quot;[[Secret Chiefs]]&quot;, who were said to be highly skilled; they supposedly directed the activities of the lower two orders by spirit communication with the Chiefs of the Second Order.

==History==
===Cipher Manuscripts===
{{Main|Cipher Manuscripts}}
[[File:Folio 13.png|thumb|right|Folio 13 of the [[Cipher Manuscripts]]]]
The foundational documents of the original Order of the Golden Dawn are known as the [[Cipher Manuscripts]]; they were written in English using [[Trithemius cipher]].  The Manuscripts give the specific outlines of the Grade Rituals of the Order and prescribe a curriculum of graduated teachings that encompass the [[Hermetic Qabalah]], [[astrology]], [[Divinatory, esoteric and occult tarot|occult tarot]], [[geomancy]], and [[alchemy]].

According to the records of the Order, the manuscripts were passed from [[Kenneth Mackenzie]], a Masonic scholar, to Rev. A.F.A. Woodford, whom British occult writer [[Francis X. King|Francis King]] describes as the fourth founder&lt;ref name=&quot;ref&quot;&gt;King, 1989, page 42-43&lt;/ref&gt; (although Woodford died shortly after the Order was founded).&lt;ref name=&quot;yoga&quot;&gt;King, 1989, page 47&lt;/ref&gt;  The documents did not excite Woodford and in February 1886 he passed them on to Freemason [[William Wynn Westcott]], who managed to decode them in 1887.&lt;ref name=&quot;ref&quot;/&gt; Westcott was pleased with his discovery and called on fellow Freemason [[Samuel Liddell MacGregor Mathers]]  for a second opinion. Westcott asked for Mathers' help to turn the manuscripts into a coherent system for lodge work. Mathers in turn asked fellow Freemason [[William Robert Woodman]] to assist the two and he accepted.&lt;ref name=&quot;ref&quot;/&gt; Mathers and Westcott have been credited for developing the ritual outlines in the Cipher Manuscripts into a workable format.&lt;ref&gt;Golden Dawn researcher R. A. Gilbert has found evidence which suggests that Westcott was instrumental in developing the Order's rituals from the Cipher Manuscripts. See Gilbert's article, ''From Cipher to Enigma: The Role of William Wynn Westcott in the Creation of the Hermetic Order of the Golden Dawn'', from Carroll Runyon's book ''Secrets of the Golden Dawn Cypher Manuscripts.''&lt;/ref&gt; Mathers, however, is generally credited with the design of the curriculum and rituals of the Second Order, which he called the ''Rosae Rubae et Aureae Crucis'' (&quot;Ruby Rose and Golden Cross&quot; or the ''RR et AC'').&lt;ref&gt;Regardie, 1993, page 92&lt;/ref&gt;

==Influences==
Influences on Golden Dawn concepts and work include:  [[Christian mysticism]], [[Hermetic Qabalah|Qabalah]], [[Hermeticism]], the [[religion of Ancient Egypt]], [[Theurgy]], [[Freemasonry]], [[Alchemy]], [[Theosophy]], [[Eliphas Levi]], [[Papus]], [[Enochian magic]], and [[Renaissance]] [[grimoire]]s.

===Founding of first temple===
In October 1887, Westcott wrote to [[Anna Sprengel]], whose name and address he received through the decoding of the Cipher Manuscripts.  Westcott claimed to receive a wise reply which conferred honorary grades of [[Adept|Adeptus Exemptus]] on Westcott, Mathers, and Woodman and chartered a Golden Dawn temple consisting of the five grades outlined in the manuscripts.&lt;ref name=&quot;king&quot;&gt;King, 1989, page 43&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;regard&quot;&gt;Regardie, 1993, page 11.&lt;/ref&gt;

In 1888, the [[Isis-Urania Temple]] was founded in [[London]],&lt;ref name=&quot;king&quot;/&gt; where the rituals decoded from the cipher manuscripts were developed and practiced.&lt;ref&gt;King, 1997, page 35&lt;/ref&gt; In addition, there was an insistence on women being allowed to participate in the Order in &quot;perfect equality&quot; with men, in contrast to the S.R.I.A. and Masonry.&lt;ref name=&quot;regard&quot;/&gt; This first lodge did not teach any magical practices ''per se'' (except for basic &quot;banishing&quot; rituals and meditation), but was rather a philosophical and metaphysical teaching order. It was called &quot;the Outer Order&quot; or &quot;First Order&quot; and for four years the Golden Dawn existed only in this order. The &quot;Inner Order&quot;, which became active in 1892, was the circle of adepts who had completed the entire course of study for the Outer Order. This group eventually became known as the Second Order.{{Citation needed|date=April 2009}}

In a short time, the Osiris temple in [[Weston-super-Mare]], the Horus temple in [[Bradford]], and the Amen-Ra temple in [[Edinburgh]] were founded. A few years after this, Mathers founded the Ahathoor temple in [[Paris]].&lt;ref name=&quot;king&quot;/&gt;

===Secret Chiefs===
{{Main|Secret Chiefs}}
In 1891, Westcott's correspondence with Anna Sprengel suddenly ceased, and he received word from Germany either that she was dead or  that her companions did not approve of the founding of the Order and no further contact was to be made. If the founders were to contact the [[Secret Chiefs]], therefore, it had to be done on their own.&lt;ref name=&quot;king&quot;&gt;King, 1989, page 43&lt;/ref&gt; In 1892, Mathers claimed a link to the Secret Chiefs had been formed and supplied rituals for the Second Order, called the Red Rose and Cross of Gold.&lt;ref name=&quot;king&quot;/&gt; These rituals were based on the tradition of the tomb of [[Christian Rosenkreuz]], and a ''Vault of Adepts'' became the controlling force behind the Outer Order.&lt;ref&gt;King, 1989, page 44&lt;/ref&gt; Later in 1916, Westcott claimed that Mathers also constructed these rituals from materials he received from Frater Lux ex Tenebris, a purported ''Continental Adept''.&lt;ref&gt;King, 1989, page 46&lt;/ref&gt;

Some followers{{Who|date=August 2009}} of the Golden Dawn tradition believe that the Secret Chiefs are not necessarily living humans or supernatural beings, but are rather symbolic of actual and legendary sources of spiritual esotericism, a great leader, or teacher of a spiritual path or practice that found its way into the teachings of the Order.&lt;ref&gt;Penczak, Christopher. ''Spirit Allies'', p. 27.  Red Wheel/Weiser Books. ISBN 1-57863-214-5&lt;/ref&gt;

===Golden Age===
By the mid 1890s, the Golden Dawn was well established in Great Britain, with membership rising to over a hundred and including every class of [[Victorian era|Victorian]] society.&lt;ref name=&quot;yoga&quot;/&gt; In its heyday, many celebrities belonged to the Golden Dawn, such as actress [[Florence Farr]], Irish revolutionary [[Maud Gonne]], Irish writer [[William Butler Yeats]], Welsh author [[Arthur Machen]], English author [[Evelyn Underhill]], and English writer [[Aleister Crowley]].

Around 1897, Westcott broke all ties to the Golden Dawn, leaving Mathers in control. It is speculated that this was due to some occult papers having been found in a [[hansom cab]], in which Westcott's connection to the Golden Dawn came to the attention of his superiors. He may have been told to either resign from the Order or to give up his occupation as [[coroner]].&lt;ref&gt;King, 1989, page 48&lt;/ref&gt; After Westcott's departure, Mathers appointed Florence Farr to be Chief Adept in Anglia. 

Mathers was the only active founding member after Westcott's &quot;departure&quot;. However, due to personality clashes with other members and absences from the center of Lodge activity in Great Britain, challenges to Mathers' authority as leader developed among the members of the Second Order.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book| last = [[Kathleen Raine|Raine, Kathleen]] | editor = Liam Miller| title = Yeats, the Tarot and the Golden Dawn| edition = second| series = New Yeats Papers| volume = II| origyear = 1972| year = 1976| publisher = Dolmen Press| location = Dublin| page = 6}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Revolt===
Towards the end of 1899, the Adepts of the Isis-Urania and Amen-Ra temples had become dissatisfied with Mathers' leadership as well as his growing friendship with Crowley. They were also anxious to make contact with the Secret Chiefs themselves, instead of relying on Mathers.&lt;ref name=&quot;meatloaf&quot;&gt;King, 1989, page 66&lt;/ref&gt; Among the personal disagreements within the Isis-Urania temple, disputes were arising from Florence Farr's ''The Sphere'', a secret society within the Isis-Urania, and the rest of the Adepts Minor.&lt;ref name=&quot;meatloaf&quot;/&gt;

Crowley was refused initiation into the Adeptus Minor grade by the London officials. Mathers overrode their decision and quickly initiated him at the Ahathoor temple in Paris on January 16, 1900.&lt;ref name=&quot;farr&quot;&gt;King, 1989, page 67&lt;/ref&gt; Upon his return to the London temple, Crowley requested the grade papers to which he was now entitled from Miss Cracknell, the acting secretary. To the London Adepts, this was the last straw. Farr, already of the opinion that the London temple should be closed, wrote to Mathers expressing her wish to resign as his representative, though she was willing to carry on until a successor was found.&lt;ref name=&quot;farr&quot;/&gt; Mathers replied on February 16, believing  Westcott was behind this turn of events. Once the other Adepts in London were notified, they elected a committee of seven on March 3 and requested a full investigation of the matter. Mathers sent an immediate reply, declining to provide proof, refusing to acknowledge the London temple, and dismissing Farr as his representative on March 23.&lt;ref&gt;King, 1989, page 68-69&lt;/ref&gt; In response, a general meeting was called on March 29 in London to remove Mathers as chief and expel him from the Order.&lt;ref&gt;King, 1989, page 69&lt;/ref&gt;

====Splinters====
In 1901, W. B. Yeats privately published a pamphlet titled ''Is the Order of R. R. &amp; A. C. to Remain a Magical Order?''&lt;ref&gt;Melton, J. Gordon, editor, ''Encyclopedia of Occultism and Parapsychology'', v. 2 p. 1327, Gale Group, 2001 ISBN 0-8103-9489-8&lt;/ref&gt;
After the Isis-Urania temple claimed its independence, there were even more disputes, leading to Yeats resigning.&lt;ref&gt;King, 1989, page 78&lt;/ref&gt; A committee of three was to temporarily govern, which included P.W. Bullock, M.W. Blackden and [[J. W. Brodie-Innes]]. After a short time, Bullock resigned, and Dr. [[Robert Felkin]] took his place.&lt;ref&gt;King, 1989, page 94&lt;/ref&gt;

In 1903, [[Arthur Edward Waite|A.E. Waite]] and Blackden joined forces to retain the name Isis-Urania, while Felkin and other London members formed the [[Stella Matutina]], Yeats remaining in it until 1921, and Brodie-Innes continued his Amen-Ra temple in Edinburgh.&lt;ref&gt;King, 1989, pages 95-96&lt;/ref&gt;

===Reconstruction===
Once Mathers realised that reconciliation was impossible, he made efforts to reestablish himself in London. The Bradford and Weston-super-Mare temples remained loyal to him, but their numbers were few.&lt;ref&gt;King, 1989, page 109&lt;/ref&gt; He then appointed [[Edmund William Berridge|Edward Berridge]] as his representative.&lt;ref name=&quot;coffee&quot;&gt;King, 1989, page 110&lt;/ref&gt; According to Francis King, historical evidence shows that there were &quot;twenty three members of a flourishing Second Order under Berridge-Mathers in 1913.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;coffee&quot;/&gt;

J.W. Brodie-Innes continued leading the Amen-Ra temple, deciding that the revolt was unjustified. By 1908, Mathers and Brodie-Innes were in complete accord.&lt;ref name=&quot;serpent&quot;&gt;Regardie, 1993, page 33&lt;/ref&gt; According to sources that differ regarding the actual date, sometime between 1901 and 1913 Mathers renamed the branch of the Golden Dawn remaining loyal to his leadership to [[Alpha et Omega]].&lt;ref&gt;King, 1971, p. 110-111&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;donouts&quot;&gt;King, 1989, page 111&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;freemason-bio&quot;&gt;&quot;The Golden Dawn ceased to exist by that name after October, 1901, replaced by Mathers' Alpha et Omega and the London group’s Order of the Morgan Rothe. No longer associated with the SRIA after 1902, Mathers continued to oversee a few temples until his death, when his wife, Moina, assumed supervision.&quot; Samuel Liddel MacGregor Mathers biography, [http://freemasonry.bcy.ca/biography/esoterica/mathers_m/mathers_m.html Grand Lodge of British Columbia and Yukon], February 26, 2001&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;llew-timeline&quot;&gt;''Golden Dawn Time Line'', Chic Cicero and Sandra Tabatha Cicero, [http://www.llewellynencyclopedia.com/article/35 Llewellyn Encyclopedia]&lt;/ref&gt; Brodie-Innes assumed command of the English and Scottish temples, while Mathers concentrated on building up his Ahathoor temple and extending his American connections.&lt;ref name=&quot;donouts&quot;/&gt; According to occultist [[Israel Regardie]], the Golden Dawn had spread to the [[United States of America]] before 1900 and a Thoth-Hermes temple had been founded in [[Chicago]].&lt;ref name=&quot;serpent&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;donouts&quot;/&gt; By the beginning of the [[First World War]] in 1914, Mathers had established two to three American temples.

Most temples of the Alpha et Omega and Stella Matutina closed or went into abeyance by the end of the 1930s, with the exceptions of two Stella Matutina temples: Hermes Temple in [[Bristol]], which operated sporadically until 1970, and the [[Whare Ra]] in [[Havelock North]], [[New Zealand]], which operated regularly until its closure in 1978.&lt;ref name=Companion&gt;Gilbert, R. A. ''Golden Dawn Companion''. Aquarian Press, 1986. ISBN 0850304369&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=LlewellynEncyclopedia&gt;Llewellyn Encyclopedia: [http://www.llewellynencyclopedia.com/article/35 &quot;Golden Dawn Time Line&quot;]&lt;/ref&gt;

==Structure and grades==
[[File:Rose Cross Lamen.svg|thumb|right|[[Rosy Cross]] of the Golden Dawn]]
Much of the hierarchical structure for the Golden dawn came from the [[Societas Rosicruciana in Anglia]], which was itself derived from the [[Order of the Golden and Rosy Cross]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://freemasonry.bcy.ca/aqc/waite/waite.html The masonic career of A.E. Waite] by Bro. R. A. Gilbert&lt;/ref&gt;

;First Order:
*Introduction—Neophyte 0=0
*Zelator 1=10
*Theoricus 2=9
*Practicus 3=8
*Philosophus 4=7
*Intermediate—Portal Grade

;Second Order:
*Adeptus Minor 5=6
*Adeptus Major 6=5
*Adeptus Exemptus 7=4

;Third Order:
*Magister Templi 8=3
*Magus 9=2
*Ipsissimus 10=1

The paired numbers attached to the Grades relate to positions on the Tree of Life. The Neophyte Grade of &quot;0=0&quot; indicates no position on the Tree. In the other pairs, the first numeral is the number of steps up from the bottom (Malkuth), and the second numeral is the number of steps down from the top (Kether).

The First Order Grades were related to the [[Classical elements|four elements]] of Earth, Air, Water, and Fire, respectively.  The Aspirant to a Grade received instruction on the metaphysical meaning of each of these Elements and had to pass a written examination and demonstrate certain skills to receive admission to that Grade.

The Portal Grade was an &quot;Invisible&quot; or in-between grade separating the First Order from the Second Order.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.golden-dawn.org/wgd.html Golden Dawn Research Center - What is the Golden Dawn?]&lt;/ref&gt; The Circle of existing Adepts from the Second Order had to consent to allow an Aspirant to be initiated as an Adept and join the Second Order.

The Second Order was not, properly, part of the &quot;Golden Dawn&quot;, but a separate Order in its own right, known as the R.R. et A.C. The Second Order directed the teachings of the First Order and was the governing force behind the First Order.

After passing the Portal, the Aspirant was instructed in the techniques of practical magic. When another examination was passed, and the other Adepts consented, the Aspirant attained the Grade of Adeptus Minor (5=6). There were also four sub-Grades of instruction for the Adeptus Minor, again relating to the four Outer Order grades.

A member of the Second Order had the power and authority to initiate aspirants to the First Order, though usually not without the permission of the Chiefs of his or her Lodge.

==''Golden Dawn'' book==
The ''Golden Dawn'' as system and book has been the most intensively used source for modern western occult and magical writing. As a book it is both a text and an encyclopedia.&lt;ref&gt;Weschcke, Carl L., Publisher, ''Publishers Preface'' (1982) The Golden Dawn&lt;/ref&gt;

==Known or alleged members==
*[[Sara Allgood]] (1879–1950), Irish stage actress and later film actress in America
*[[Allan Bennett]] (1872–1923), best known for introducing [[Buddhism]] to the West
*[[Arnold Bennett]] (1867–1931), British novelist&lt;ref&gt;Regardie, 1982, page 16&lt;/ref&gt;
*[[Edmund William Berridge|Edward W. Berridge]] (ca. 1843–1923), British homeopathic physician&lt;ref name=Colquhoun/&gt;{{rp|148–149}}
*[[Algernon Blackwood]] (1869–1951), English writer and radio broadcaster of supernatural stories&lt;ref name=&quot;members&quot;&gt;Regardie, 1982, foreword - page ix&lt;/ref&gt;
*[[Aleister Crowley]] (1875–1947), occult writer and mountaineer&lt;ref name=&quot;members&quot;/&gt;
&lt;!-- Paul Foster Case was not a member of the Golden Dawn, but rather the Alpha et Omega. Please do not add him --&gt;
*[[Florence Farr]] (1860–1917), London stage actress and musician&lt;ref name=&quot;members&quot;/&gt;
*[[Robert Felkin]] (1853–1925), medical missionary, explorer and anthropologist in Central Africa, author
&lt;!-- Dion Fortune was not a member of the Golden Dawn, but rather the Stella Matutina. Please do not add her --&gt;
*[[Frederick Leigh Gardner]] (1857–1930), British stock broker and occultist; published three-volume bibliography ''Catalogue Raisonné of Works on the Occult Sciences'' (1912)&lt;ref&gt;[http://freemasonry.bcy.ca/biography/esoterica/gardner_f/gardner_f.html &quot;Frederick Leigh Gardner&quot;], Biographies: Fringe freemasons, Grand Lodge of British Columbia and Yukon (Freemasons) web site. Retrieved November 2008.&lt;/ref&gt;
*[[Maud Gonne]] (1866–1953), Irish revolutionary, author, feminist
*[[Annie Horniman]] (1860–1937), British repertory theatre producer and pioneer; member of the wealthy Horniman family of tea-traders&lt;ref name=&quot;members&quot;/&gt;
*[[Arthur Machen]] (1863–1947), leading London writer of the 1890s, author of acclaimed works of imaginative and occult fiction, such as &quot;The Great God Pan&quot;, &quot;The White People&quot; and &quot;The Hill of Dreams&quot;. Welsh by birth and upbringing.
*[[Gustav Meyrink]] (1868–1932), Austrian author, storyteller, dramatist, translator, banker, and Buddhist
*[[E. Nesbit]] (1858–1924), real name Edith Bland; English author and political activist
&lt;!-- Israel Regardie was not a member of the Golden Dawn, but rather the Stella Matutina. Please do not add him --&gt;
*[[Charles Rosher]] (1885–1974), British cinematographer
*[[Pamela Colman Smith]] (1878–1951), British-American artist and co-creator of the [[Rider-Waite Tarot deck]]
*[[William Sharp]] (1855–1905), poet and author; alias Fiona MacLeod
*[[Bram Stoker]]&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|title=The occult power behind the spear which pierced the side of Christ |first=Trevor |last=Ravenscroft |year=1982 |publisher=Red Wheel |page=165 |isbn=0877285470}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|title=The Templar Revelation: Secret Guardians of the True Identity of Christ |first=Lynn |last=Picknett |year=2004 |publisher=Simon and Schuster |page=201 |isbn=0743273257}}&lt;/ref&gt; (1847–1912), Irish writer best-known today for his 1897 horror novel ''Dracula''
*[[John Todhunter]] (1839–1916), ''Aktis Heliou'' Irish poet and playwright who wrote seven volumes of poetry, and several plays
*[[Violet Tweedale]] (1862–1936), author.
*[[Evelyn Underhill]] (1875–1941), British Christian mystic, author of ''Mysticism: A Study in Nature and Development of Spiritual Consciousness''
*[[Charles Williams (UK writer)|Charles Williams]] (1886–1945), British poet, novelist, theologian, and literary critic
*[[Arthur Edward Waite]] (1857–1942), British-American author, [[Freemasonry|Freemason]] and co-creator of the [[Rider-Waite Tarot deck]]&lt;ref name=&quot;members&quot;/&gt;
*[[William Butler Yeats]] (1865–1939), Irish poet, dramatist, and writer.

==Contemporary Golden Dawn Orders==
&lt;!--======================== {{No more links}} ============================
    | PLEASE BE CAUTIOUS IN ADDING MORE LINKS TO THIS ARTICLE. Wikipedia  |
    | is not a collection of links nor should it be used for advertising. |
    |                                                                     |
    |           Excessive or inappropriate links WILL BE DELETED.         |
    | See [[Wikipedia:External links]] &amp; [[Wikipedia:Spam]] for details.  |
    |                                                                     |
    | If there are already plentiful links, please propose additions or   |
    | replacements on this article's discussion page, or submit your link |
    | to the relevant category at the Open Directory Project (dmoz.org)   |
    | and link back to that category using the {{dmoz}} template.         |
    ======================= {{No more links}} =============================--&gt;

While no temples in the original chartered lineage of the Golden Dawn survived past the 1970s,&lt;ref name=Companion/&gt;&lt;ref name=LlewellynEncyclopedia/&gt; several organizations have since revived its teachings and rituals. Among these, the following are notable:

*[[The Hermetic Order of the Golden Dawn, Inc.]]
*[[The Open Source Order of the Golden Dawn]]

==See also==
*[[A∴A∴]]
*[[Tattva vision]]

==Notes==
{{reflist|2}}

==References==
* Fra. A.o.C. (2002). [http://www.osogd.org/library/biscuits/history.html A Short Treatise on the History, Culture and Practices of The Hermetic Order of the Golden Dawn]. Retrieved August 3, 2007.
* Armstrong, Allan &amp; R. A. Gilbert, eds. (1997). ''Golden Dawn: The Proceedings of the Golden Dawn Conference, London - 1997''. Hermetic Research Trust.
* [[Chic Cicero|Cicero, Chic]] and [[Tabatha Cicero]] (1991). ''The New Golden Dawn Ritual Tarot.'' St. Paul, MN: Llewellyn Publications. ISBN 0-87542-139-3
* [[Ithell Colquhoun|Colquhoun, Ithell]] (1975). ''Sword of Wisdom: Macgregor Mathers and the Golden Dawn''. Neville Spearman. ISBN 0-85435-092-6.
* Greer, Mary K. (1994). ''Women of the Golden Dawn''. Park Street. ISBN 0-89281-516-7.
*Greer, Mary K. &amp; Darcy Kuntz (1999) ''The Chronology of the Golden Dawn.'' Holmes Publishing Group. ISBN 1-55818-354-X
* Gilbert, Robert A. (1983). ''The Golden Dawn: Twilight of the Magicians''. The Aquarian Press. ISBN 0-85030-278-1
* Gilbert, Robert A. (1986). ''The Golden Dawn Companion''. [[Weiser Books]]. ISBN 0-85030-436-9
* Gilbert, Robert A. ''Golden Dawn Scrapbook - The Rise and Fall of a Magical Order''. [[Weiser Books]] (1998) ISBN 1-57863-037-1
* Howe, Ellic (1978). ''The Magicians of the Golden Dawn: A Documentary History of a Magical Order 1887-1923''. [[Samuel Weiser]]. ISBN 0-87728-369-9.
* Jenkins, Phillip (2000) ''Mystics and Messiahs: Cults and New Religions in American History''. [[Oxford University Press]]. ISBN 978-0195127447
* [[Francis X. King|King, Francis]] (1971). ''The Rites of Modern Occult Magic''. New York: Macmillan Company. Library of Congress Catalog Card Number 76-158-933
* King, Francis (1989). ''Modern Ritual Magic: The Rise of Western Occultism''. ISBN 1-85327-032-6
* King, Francis, ed. (1997). ''Ritual Magic of the Golden Dawn: Works by S. L. MacGregor Mathers and Others''. Destiny Books. ISBN 0-89281-617-1
* {{cite book
|isbn=0-87542-664-6
|publisher= Llewellyn Publications
|author=[[Israel Regardie|Regardie, Israel]]
|title=The Golden Dawn
|year=1982
}}
* Regardie, Israel, et al., eds. (1989). ''The Golden Dawn: A Complete Course in Practical Ceremonial Magic''. Llewellyn. ISBN 0-87542-663-8
* Regardie, Israel (1993). ''What You Should Know About the Golden Dawn'' (6th ed.). ISBN 1-56184-064-5
* Runyon, Carroll (1997). ''Secrets of the Golden Dawn Cipher Manuscripts''. C.H.S. ISBN 0-9654881-2-8
* Smoley, Richard (1999). ''Hidden Wisdom: A Guide to the Western Inner Traditions''. Quest Books ISBN 978-0835608442
* Suster, Gerald (1990). ''Crowley's Apprentice: The Life and Ideas of Israel Regardie.'' Weiser Books. ISBN 0-87728-700-7
* Wasserman, James (2005). ''The Mystery Traditions: Secret Symbols and Sacred Art''. Rochester, VT: Destiny Books. ISBN 1-59477-088-3

==External links==
*[http://www.hermetic.com/gdlibrary/gd-faq.html The Golden Dawn FAQ] (original from 1990s Usenet groups)
*[http://www.hermetic.com/gdlibrary/ The Golden Dawn Library Project]
*[http://www.llewellynencyclopedia.com/term/Golden+Dawn Golden Dawn entries in Llewellyn Encyclopedia]
*[http://altreligion.about.com/library/texts/bl_historygoldendawn.htm Golden Dawn Tradition, by co-founder Dr. W. Wynn Westcott]
*[http://www.hermetic.com/gdlibrary/cipher/ Photocopies and the translation of the original Cipher Manuscripts]
*[http://www.nli.ie/yeats/ Lots of GD material on display in Yeats exhibition including Ritual Notebooks.]
*[http://www.angelfire.com/ab6/imuhtuk/rollcall.htm The Golden Dawn Roll Call]	
*{{dmoz|Society/Religion_and_Spirituality/Esoteric_and_Occult/Golden_Dawn|Golden Dawn}}

----
{{Magic and Witchcraft in the British Isles}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Hermetic Order Of The Golden Dawn}}[[Category:Apocalypticists]]
[[Category:Hermetic Order of the Golden Dawn|*]]
[[Category:Organizations established in 1888]]
[[Category:Esoteric schools of thought]]

[[bg:Златната Зора]]
[[ca:Orde Hermètic de l'Alba Daurada]]
[[cs:Hermetický řád Zlatého úsvitu]]
[[da:Hermetic Order of the Golden Dawn]]
[[de:Hermetic Order of the Golden Dawn]]
[[es:Orden Hermética del Alba Dorada]]
[[fr:Ordre hermétique de l'Aube dorée]]
[[gl:Orde Hermética da Alba Dourada]]
[[hr:Hermetički red Zlatne zore]]
[[it:Golden Dawn]]
[[he:השחר המוזהב]]
[[mk:Златна зора]]
[[nl:Golden Dawn]]
[[ja:黄金の夜明け団]]
[[no:Golden Dawn]]
[[pl:Hermetyczny Zakon Złotego Brzasku]]
[[pt:Ordem Hermética da Aurora Dourada]]
[[ro:Zorii Aurii]]
[[ru:Герметический Орден Золотая Заря]]
[[sq:Urdhëri Hermetik i Agimit të Artë]]
[[simple:Hermetic Order of the Golden Dawn]]
[[sk:Hermetický rád Zlatého úsvitu]]
[[sr:Златна зора]]
[[fi:Hermetic Order of the Golden Dawn]]
[[sv:Golden Dawn]]
[[tr:Altın Şafak Hermetik Cemiyeti]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
