<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="13821075" ns="0" title="Battle of Jaffna (1995)"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Infobox Military Conflict
|conflict=Battle of Jaffna (1995)
|partof=the [[Sri Lankan civil war]]
|image=
|caption=
|date=October 17, 1995 - December 5, 1995
|place=[[Jaffna]], [[Sri Lanka]]
|casus=
|territory=
|result=Sri Lankan Army victory
|combatant1=[[Image:Coat of arms of Sri Lanka.svg|18px]] [[Military of Sri Lanka]]
|combatant2=[[Liberation Tigers of Tamil Eelam]]
|commander1=[[Major General]] (later General) [[Rohan Daluwatte]],&lt;br/&gt; [[Brigadier]]  (later Major General) [[Janaka Perera]]
|commander2=
|strength1=10,000
|strength2=Unknown
|casualties1=500 killed (According to Sri Lankan Government claims)&lt;ref name='CBA'&gt;[http://www.comebackalive.com/df/dplaces/srilanka/index.htm Sri Lanka - DangerFinder&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;
|casualties2=2,000 killed (According to Sri Lankan Government claims)&lt;ref name='CBA'/&gt;
|notes=
}}
{{Campaignbox Eelam War II}}
{{Campaignbox Sri Lankan Civil War}}

The '''Battle of Jaffna''' was a battle fought from October to December 1995 for the city of [[Jaffna]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://news.bbc.co.uk/onthisday/hi/dates/stories/december/5/newsid_4618000/4618661.stm|title=1995: Jaffna falls to Sri Lankan army|publisher=BBC News|date=December 05, 1995}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==The battle==
The city of Jaffna had been for years a major stronghold of the LTTE. The Tigers wieved the city as the capital of their new independent state. The city was briefly recaptured by the Indian army in 1987 but was later captured again by the Tigers. The new president of Sri Lanka, Kumaratunga, initially wanted to resolve all difference with the Tamils by peaceful means but the army pressured her to order an offensive against the LTTE. On October 17, 1995, 10,000 SLA soldiers attacked the city and in a 50-day siege that lasted until December 5, 1995, up to 500 soldiers and 2,000 rebels were killed. In the end the army managed to take the city and the peninsula from the Tigers, thus cripling the LTTE, however most of the LTTE forces managed to retreat into the jungle.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://edition.cnn.com/WORLD/9512/sri_lanka/index.html|title=Sri Lankan army hails capture of Jaffna|publisher=CNN|date=December 5, 1995}} {{Dead link|date=September 2010|bot=RjwilmsiBot}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Aftermath==

Initially the Army stated that the battle for Jaffna ended the war and the LTTE will never again be able to fight major battles against the government. It was believed that the insurgency was at its end. However this was not the case, which was apparent when the LTTE attacked an army detachment in Batticaloa district December 23, killing 33 troops. Military sources reported that more than 60 rebels were killed. Over the next seven months the LTTE reorganised and regrouped and in July 1996, the rebels launched [[Operation Unceasing Waves I|Operation Unceasing Waves]], which was the codename for the attack on the military base at [[Mullaitivu]]. More than 1,200 soldiers were killed and the base was destroyed.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.cnn.com/WORLD/9604/21/sri.lanka/|title=Sri Lankan troops continue push into rebel territory|publisher=CNN News|date=April 21, 1996}} {{Dead link|date=September 2010|bot=RjwilmsiBot}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==See also==
*[[Battle of Jaffna (2006)]]
*[[List of Sri Lankan Civil War battles]]

==References==
{{reflist}}

{{coord missing|Sri Lanka}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Battle Of Jaffna (1995)}}
[[Category:Eelam War III]]
[[Category:Conflicts in 1995]]
[[Category:1995 in Sri Lanka]]
[[Category:Battles of the Sri Lankan Civil War]]
[[Category:Jaffna District]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
