<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="13878916" ns="0" title="SV Dynamo"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Infobox Sports team
| color1        = #000000
| color2        = white
| logo          = SV Dynamo logo wreath.svg
| pixels        = 293px
| founded       = {{Start date and age |1953|03|27}}; dissolved: {{Start date and age |1989|11|23}}
| league        = [[Olympics]], [[FIFA World Cup|World cup]], [[European Championship]] Nat. League
| history       =
| arena         = [[Palast der Republik]], [[Dynamo-Sportforum]], [[Altenberg bobsleigh, luge, and skeleton track]], [[Dynamo Sports Hotel]]
| ballpark      =
| stadium       = [[Dynamo Stadium (Dresden)]], [[Friedrich Ludwig Jahn Sportpark]], [[Heinz Steyer Stadion]] and others
| city          = [[East Berlin]], {{GDR}}
| colors        = wine-red white/
wine-red silver
| owner         = Ministry of Interior of the GDR: [[Volkspolizei]], [[Border control|Zollverwaltung]], [[Stasi|Ministry for State Security]], [[Firefighter|Feuerwehr]]
| president     = [[Erich Mielke]]
| coach         =
| manager       =
| championships = 2.187 nat.; approx. 182 European cup medals approx. 324  World cup medals; approx. 215 Olympic medals&lt;ref&gt;[http://dispatch.opac.ddb.de/DB=1.1/LNG=DU/SID=690ceed1-30/LNG=EN/ Data bank for the Magazine Dynamo sport/ Please insert Dynamosport for searching (atttention:German language) It is for proving the medals; extra beside the linked athletes here.]&lt;/ref&gt;
}}
The '''Sports Club Dynamo''' ({{lang-de|Sportvereinigung Dynamo/ SV Dynamo}}, {{IPA-de|ˈspɔʁtˌfɛɐ̯ˈʔaɪ̯nɪɡʊŋ dyːnamoː}}) was the sport organization of the security agencies ([[Volkspolizei]], [[Border control|Zollverwaltung]], [[Stasi|Ministry for State Security]] and [[Firefighter|Feuerwehr]]) of former [[East Germany]]. The sports club was founded on 27 March 1953 and was headquartered in [[Hohenschönhausen]] in [[East Berlin]]. From the date of its inception until 23 November 1989 the president of SV Dynamo was [[Erich Mielke]], who was also the Minister of State Security. Dynamo was created in accordance with the multi-[[sports]] club model developed in the [[Soviet Union]] and adopted throughout Eastern Europe. From the beginning it had an overtly political as well as sporting agenda and its many successes were always portrayed as a triumph of the GDR state. After the [[German reunification]] in 1990 the SV Dynamo was liquidated. At its height the association had a membership of over 280,000 active members.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite conference | first = Barsuhn | last = Michael | coauthors = Jutta Braun and Hans Joachim Teichler | title = Chronik der Sporteinheit vom Mauerfall bis zur Aufnahme der fünf neuen Landessportbünde am 15. Dezember 1990 in den Deutschen Sportbund | publisher = Deutscher Sportbund | url = http://www.dosb.de/fileadmin/fm-dsb/arbeitsfelder/wiss-ges/Dateien/Siegel-Endversion-Sporteinheit-19072006.pdf | accessdate = 2008-05-13}}&lt;/ref&gt; Athletes of the association enjoyed considerable success both in national and international competitions, winning for example more than 200 [[Olympic Games|olympic medals]]. After the German reunification the systematic [[Doping (sport)|doping]] of Dynamo athletes from 1971 until 1990 was revealed in German media reports. The systematic doping of athletes was done under the supervision of the Staatssicherheit and with full backing of the government.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.dw-world.de/dw/article/0,2144,786574,00.html |title=Sports Doping Statistics Reach Plateau in Germany |publisher=''[[Deutsche Welle]]'' |date=2003-02-26 |accessdate=2007-08-04}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Organization==
[[File:Bundesarchiv Bild 183-1982-1016-021, Antje Mahlich, Monika Müller, Simone Nikolaizig.jpg|left|250px|thumb|Acrobatics- show in 1982]]The SV Dynamo was divided into fifteen regional units, corresponding to the fifteen [[Administrative division of the German Democratic Republic|districts]] of the German Democratic Republic. Within each regional unit individual sports clubs existed, with each sport club specializing in different disciplines. 290 sections were included [[Dynamo Dresden|SG Dynamo Dresden]] ([[Association football|football]]), SC Dynamo [[Hoppegarten]] ([[judo]], [[shooting sports]], [[parachuting]]), the SC Dynamo [[Klingenthal]] ([[Nordic skiing]]), SG Dynamo [[Luckenwalde]] ([[wrestling]]), SG Dynamo [[Potsdam]] ([[Rowing (sport)|rowing]] and [[Canoe racing|canoe sprint]]), SG Dynamo [[Weißwasser]] ([[ice hockey]]) and the [[SG Dynamo Zinnwald]] in [[Altenberg, Germany|Altenberg]] ([[biathlon]], [[bobsleigh]], [[luge]], [[Skeleton (sport)|skeleton]]). The most famous sports club of the SV Dynamo was probably the [[SC Dynamo Berlin]] offering most Olympic disciplines. The sports system was not designed for transfers, but on schedule. The athletes had to be viewed in their own country.
Administrators and coaches from Dynamo Berlin were often sent to support their development. The district organizations always worn the initials SV Dynamo ... . The districts been the same districts of the state.
As a sports brand only [[Adidas]] could be worn by the athletes, in international competitions or the home made brand Champion. If this were not respected, the athletes would have been blocked in intl. competitions for a time, then Dynamo had only hidden contracts with Adidas. Never was an athlete punished.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.gymn-forum.net/bios/women/gnauck.html Gymn Forum: Maxi Gnauck Biography&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;
For small children, there was even a Dynamo-[[Kindergarten]]. Henceforth the larger children trained every day before and after classes. All children were happy with doing that.
For the training, there exists a basic plan. If the children themselves are not good at school, they were being excluded from the training. The emphasis has been respected that the athletes had to pursued themselves the sporting ideology, because otherwise no success would have been guaranteed. The Dynamo athletes should always did stow in their offices sports equipment. This should be at least 10 minutes during working break. These included: [[dumbbells]], expander, impander and poles for [[Pull-up (exercise)|pull-ups]]. In each year, the best Dynamo-athlete were voted. Few could win ''50,- M'' when they themselves were those who chose the sportswoman/ sportsman of the year.&lt;ref&gt;[[Dynamosport]]: 1974&lt;/ref&gt; Athletes may not overwhelmed, and to do this.
Particularly, it should be respected so that there were more athletes than fans there. The officials had always successful attempts by the people to the stadiums to attract these onto the sports fields.&lt;ref&gt;[[Dynamosport]]:page: 6; first edition; 1974&lt;/ref&gt; Dynamo employed a planning cycle that set out the club's objectives for the upcoming four year period. 
This sports club was anti-fascistic with the human goals against [[imperialism]]. The grounders of thus here were former prisoners in concentration camps and leaders in the battle against [[National socialists]] and [[Social Democrats]] at the [[Weimar Republic]]. The Dynamo-Youth commemorated about it at the [[Soviet War Memorial (Treptower Park)]], [[Sachsenhausen concentration camp]]. The names of murdered/death communists was given as honourary titles for Dynamo-Clubs, which must fought for it... . For example: SG Dynamo &quot;[[Feliks E. Dzierzynski]]&quot; Dresden or SG Dynamo &quot;Dr. [[Richard Sorge]]&quot; Erfurt.
There were also many [[hymns]] and [[odes]] of Dynamo, which would written.
Gerhard Kube, Helmut Baierl and Kurt Barthel formed many poems, which playing the sports club a role.

=== SV Dynamo districts ===
[[File:SV Dynamo Flag Bezirksorganisation Dresden.svg|thumb|200px|right|Flag example]]The districts been the same districts of the state with: Sportvereinigung Dynamo District - Organisation  [[Rostock (Bezirk)|Rostock]], Sportvereinigung Dynamo District - Organisation [[Neubrandenburg (Bezirk)|Neubrandenburg]], Sportvereinigung Dynamo District - Organisation [[Schwerin (Bezirk)|Schwerin]], Sportvereinigung Dynamo District - Organisation [[Magdeburg (Bezirk)|Magdeburg]], Sportvereinigung Dynamo District - Organisation [[Potsdam (Bezirk)|Potsdam]], Sportvereinigung Dynamo District - Organisation [[Frankfurt Oder (Bezirk)|Frankfurt Oder]], Sportvereinigung Dynamo District - Organisation [[East Berlin (Bezirk)|East Berlin]], Sportvereinigung Dynamo District - Organisation [[Cottbus (Bezirk)|Cottbus]], Sportvereinigung Dynamo District - Organisation [[Halle (Bezirk)|Halle]], Sportvereinigung Dynamo District - Organisation [[Leipzig (Bezirk)|Leipzig]], Sportvereinigung Dynamo District - Organisation [[Erfurt (Bezirk)|Erfurt]], Sportvereinigung Dynamo District - Organisation [[Gera (Bezirk)|Gera]], Sportvereinigung Dynamo District - Organisation [[Suhl (Bezirk)|Suhl]], Sportvereinigung Dynamo District - Organisation [[Dresden (Bezirk)|Dresden]] and Sportvereinigung Dynamo District - Organisation [[Karl-Marx-Stadt (Bezirk)|Karl-Marx-Stadt]]. Every district has owned a wine-red silk banner with these writing. The measure is 2.8 × 1.5 m, with, of course, a logo of the SV.

== Members ==
Key to East German sporting success was a pyramid system with schoolchildren being assessed for athletic potential and the best (typically the top 2.5%) in each school-year being offered specialised coaching. A small fraction of those would go on to become the top adult athletes of the next generation. This model was initially derided in the West as a &quot;sausage machine&quot; but it has since been adopted in modified form by [[Australia]], [[France]], [[Spain]] and others with thousands of children being educated at specialised (often residential) sports schools rather than going through the normal [[high school]] system. Overall, 3,7 million{{Clarify|date=August 2010}} athletes were in the GDR at the German Sports federation ([[DTSB]]) registered in many other successful clubs in 1989.
&lt;div style=&quot;clear: both&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
{| class=&quot;wikitable&quot; style=&quot;text-align: center;&quot;
|+ Members by year&lt;ref&gt;SV Dynamo Almanach 1977&lt;/ref&gt;
|-
!Year
!Adults
!Children
!Total
|-
||1953||23162 ||none||23162
|-
||1955||55991 ||10874||66856
|-
||1958||90160 ||18846||109006
|-
||1961|| 105530||42822||148352
|-
||1966||118651 ||54691||173306
|-
||1970||131752 ||74266||206018
|-
||1972||139013 ||85295||224308
|-
||1974||144356 ||93071||237427
|-
|1975||146127 ||96666||242793
|-
|1976|| 148054||99337||247391
|-
|1983||170.000||110.000||280.000
|}

== Trainers ==
Most coaches were also even teachers or other specific occupations. They were all in principle to took members fears before starting competitions. Also said that never was like everything bad could happen if .... Problems are always packed at its source in order to eradicate this. At the same time, they were also the guardian of morality.
&lt;div style=&quot;clear: both&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
{| class=&quot;wikitable&quot; style=&quot;text-align: center;&quot;
|+Trainers by year&lt;ref&gt;SV Dynamo Almanach&lt;/ref&gt;
|-
!Year
!Level 1
!Level 2
!Level 3/4
!Total
|-
||1964||none||none||none||9989
|-
||1965||none||none||none||9673
|-
||1966||6785||2466||1362||10613
|-
||1967||6717||2476||1489||10682
|-
||1968||7078||2731||1712||11521
|-
||1969||7536||3009||1915||12460
|-
||1970||7321||3211||2058||12590
|-
||1971||7215||3412||2119||12746
|-
|1972||7334||3598||2580||13512
|-
|1973||7394||3791||3016||14201
|-
|1974||11358||3906||3098||18362
|-
|1975||11812||3949||3407||19168
|-
|1976|| 12369||4219||3524||20112
|}

==Controversies surrounding the Sport Club Dynamo Berlin==
===The case of doping===
[[File:Bundesarchiv Bild 183-Z0701-033, Birgit Meinecke.jpg|right|230px|thumb|[[Birgit Meineke]] with coach [[Rolf Gläser]]]] [[File:Bundesarchiv Bild 183-R0605-0008, Rosemarie Gabriel.jpg|right|230px|thumb|[[Rosemarie Gabriel]] with coach [[Rolf Gläser]]]]The ''Sportvereinigung Dynamo''&lt;ref&gt;Pain And Injury in Sport: Social And Ethical Analysis, Section III, Chapter 7, Page 111, by Sigmund Loland, Berit Skirstad, Ivan Waddington, Published by Routledge in 2006, ASIN: B000OI0HZG&lt;/ref&gt; was especially singled out as a center for doping in the former East Germany.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://members.lycos.co.uk/dopingopfer/kommentar_ordner/09_2002/dynamo_liste_web.htm|title=Dynamo Liste|language=German|publisher=doping_opfer@yahoo.com|date=September 2002|accessdate=2008-03-10}}&lt;/ref&gt; Many former club officials and some athletes found themselves charged after the dissolution of the country. A special page on the internet was created by doping victims trying to gain justice and compensation, listing people involved in doping at the club, the so called ''Dynamo Liste''.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://members.lycos.co.uk/dopingopfer/taeter/taeter_alle.htm|title=Dynamo Liste: Die Täter|language=German|publisher=doping_opfer@yahoo.com|date=September 2002|accessdate=2008-03-11}}&lt;/ref&gt;

State-endorsed doping began with the Cold War when every eastern bloc gold was an ideological victory. From 1974, Manfred Ewald, the head of the GDR's sports federation, imposed blanket doping. At the 1968 Mexico City Olympics, the country of 17 million collected nine gold medals. Four years later the total was 20 and in 1976 it doubled again to 40.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://sports.espn.go.com/oly/news/story?id=2048448|title=Jenapharm says drugs were legal|publisher=ESPN|date=28 April 2005|accessdate=2008-03-11}}&lt;/ref&gt; Ewald was quoted as having told coaches, &quot;They're still so young and don't have to know everything.&quot; He was given a 22-month suspended sentence, to the outrage of his victims.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://findarticles.com/p/articles/mi_qn4158/is_20021025/ai_n12658822|title=Obituary: Manfred Ewald|publisher=The Independent|date=25 October 2002|accessdate=2008-03-11}} {{Dead link|date=October 2010|bot=RjwilmsiBot}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Often, doping was carried out without the knowledge of the athletes, some of them as young as ten years of age. It is estimated that around 10,000 former athletes bear the physical and mental scars of years of drug abuse,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/europe/4341045.stm|title=GDR athletes sue over steroid damage |publisher=BBC News Europe|date=13 March 2005|accessdate=2008-03-11}}&lt;/ref&gt; one of them is [[Rica Reinisch]], a triple Olympic champion and world record-setter at the Moscow Games in 1980, has since suffered numerous miscarriages and recurring ovarian cysts. Athletes like Renate Vogel, silver medalist at the [[1972 Summer Olympics|1972 Olympics]] in the swimming competitions, were told the injections were vitamins but failed to believe the explanation and quit her sport.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.3sat.de/3sat.php?http://www.3sat.de/nano/bstuecke/63280/index.html|title=Doping im DDR-Sport: &quot;Wir waren Versuchskaninchen&quot;|language=German|publisher=3sat.online|date=3 February 2005|accessdate=2008-03-13}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Two former [[Dynamo Berlin]] club doctors, Dieter Binus, chief of the national women's team from 1976 to 80, and Bernd Pansold, in charge of the sports medicine center in East-Berlin, were committed for trial for allegedly supplying 19 teenagers with illegal substances.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/sport/34496.stm|title=New doping charges against East German doctors|publisher=BBC News|date=25 November 1997|accessdate=2008-03-07}}&lt;/ref&gt; Binus was sentenced in August,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/sport/161913.stm|title=East German coaches fined over doping|publisher=BBC News|date=31 August 1998|accessdate=2008-03-11}}&lt;/ref&gt; Pansold in December 1998 after both being found guilty of administering hormones to underage female athletes from 1975 to 1984.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.svl.ch/doping/ddr_doping_minderjaehrige.html|title=Doping of underage athletes in the former GDR|language=German|publisher=Schwimmverein Limmat Zürich |date=23 March 2000|accessdate=2008-03-10}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Virtually no East German athlete ever failed an official drug test, though Stasi files show that many did, indeed, produced positive tests at [[Kreischa]], the Saxon laboratory (German:''Zentrale Dopingkontroll-Labor des Sportmedizinischen Dienstes'') that was at the time approved by the International Olympic Committee,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.ergogenics.org/ddrroids2.html|title=Drug claim could be a bitter pill|publisher=Times Online|date=2 March 2005|accessdate=2008-03-13}}&lt;/ref&gt; now called the ''Institute of Doping Analysis and Sports Biochemistry'' (IDAS).&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.wada-ama.org/en/dynamic.ch2?pageCategory.id=333|title=Accredited Laboratories|publisher=World Anti-Doping Agency|date=January 2004|accessdate=2008-03-13}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In 2005, fifteen years after the end or the ''GDR'', the manufacturer of the drugs in former East Germany, [[Jenapharm]], still finds itself involved in numerous lawsuits from doping victims, being sued by almost 200 former athletes.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://sport.guardian.co.uk/athletics/story/0,10082,1605761,00.html|title=Forgotten victims of East German doping take their battle to court|publisher=The Guardian|date=1 November 2005|accessdate=2008-03-11 | location=London | first=Luke | last=Harding}}&lt;/ref&gt; Many of the substances handed out were, even under East German law, illegal.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.ergogenics.org/ddrroids2.html|title=Eine gewisse Geheimniskrämerei|language=German|publisher=Times Online, Grit Hartmann|date=28 July 2005|accessdate=2008-03-14}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Former Sport Club Dynamo athletes who publicly admitted to doping, accusing their coaches&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://findarticles.com/p/articles/mi_qa3883/is_199807/ai_n8790764|title=Drugs update|publisher=Sports Publications|date=July 1998|accessdate=2008-03-11}} {{Dead link|date=October 2010|bot=RjwilmsiBot}}&lt;/ref&gt;:
*[[Daniela Hunger]]
*[[Andrea Pollack]]
*[[Katharina Bullin]]
*[[Andreas Krieger]]
Former Sport Club Dynamo athletes disqualified for doping:
*[[Ilona Slupianek]]&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.milano2007.org/html_eng/storia_coppa.asp|title=1977: Here comes Mr. Doping|publisher=European Cup - Milan 2007|year=2007|accessdate=2008-03-11}}&lt;/ref&gt; (''Ilona Slupianek tested positive along with three Finnish athletes at the 1977 European Cup, becoming the only East German athlete ever to be convicted of doping''&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=940DE6DD1031F937A35754C0A96E948260&amp;sec=&amp;spon=&amp;pagewanted=all|title=Article on Sports in East Germany |publisher=The New York Times|author=Michael Janofsky|date=4 July 1988|accessdate=2008-03-13}}&lt;/ref&gt;). Based on the self-admission by Pollack, the [[United States Olympic Committee]] asked for the redistribution of gold medals won in the [[1976 Summer Olympics|1976 Olympics]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A05E0DE173CF936A15753C1A96E958260&amp;sec=&amp;spon=&amp;pagewanted=3|title=OLYMPICS; U.S. Seeks Redress for 1976 Doping In Olympics |publisher=The New York Times|date=25 October 1998|accessdate=2008-03-12 | first=Jere | last=Longman}}&lt;/ref&gt; Despite court rulings in Germany that substantiate claims of systematic doping by some East German swimmers, the IOC executive board announced that it has no intention of revising the Olympic record books. This is an understandable decision as it could otherwise trigger a flood of such claims involving former eastern block athletes. In rejecting the American petition on behalf of its women's medley relay team in Montreal and a similar petition from the [[British Olympic Association]] on behalf of [[Sharron Davies]], the [[IOC]] made it clear that it wanted to discourage any such appeals in the future.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.iht.com/articles/1998/12/16/medals.t.php|title=Despite Doping, Olympic Medals Stand|publisher=International Herald Tribune|date=16 December 1998|accessdate=2008-03-12}} {{Dead link|date=October 2010|bot=H3llBot}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===The ''Stasi'' and ''Erich Mielke''===
[[Erich Mielke]], chief of Dynamo, was also the all-powerful leader of the [[Stasi]],&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/europe/764397.stm|title=Ex-Stasi chief dies|publisher=BBC News|date=25 May 2000|accessdate=2008-03-11}}&lt;/ref&gt; the Secret Police of East Germany, mother organisation of Dynamo. The ''Stasi'' was widely regarded as one of the most effective intelligence agencies in the world. The intensity of state surveillance was probably without parallel anywhere in the world. In 1989, the Stasi had 91,000 staff members and 174,000 unofficial collaborators - a ratio of one spy for every 62 citizens.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.amnesty.nl/bibliotheek_vervolg/thema_berechting_case_1|title=GERMANY AND THE GERMAN DEMOCRATIC REPUBLIC - Truth and justice|publisher=Amnesty International, Daan Bronkhorst|date=June 2006|accessdate=2008-03-11}}&lt;/ref&gt; Some of them were well known athletes, like [[Harald Czudaj]], who admitted working as an informer for the Stasi, writing at least 10 reports about teammates and officials of the [[Altenberg bobsleigh, luge, and skeleton track|Dynamo bobsled club]] in [[Altenberg, Germany|Altenberg]], East Germany, from 1988 to 1990. He apologized to his teammates. After his admission, Czudaj's teammates appealed to German officials to let him compete in the [[1992 Winter Olympics]] because they had not been harmed by his work for the Stasi.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0CE3DB1131F932A25751C0A964958260|title=Germany Won't Ban Sledder Who Informed|publisher=The New York Times|date=11 February 1992|accessdate=2008-03-12}}&lt;/ref&gt; ''Mielke'' himself was sentenced in Berlin to six years in prison in 1993 for the murder of two policemen in 1931. However he was freed after two years when he was diagnosed as senile.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.wsws.org/articles/2000/aug2000/miel-a24.shtml|title=Erich Mielke—the career of a German Stalinist|publisher=World Socialist Web Site, Ludwig Niethammer|date=24 August 2000|accessdate=2008-03-11}}&lt;/ref&gt;

After reunification, the members of the [[Felix Dzerzhinsky Watch Regiment]], all soldiers were automatically members of Dynamo, got no pension, although they could win sporting successes. It is proven that only an elite army members and no spies were known from the '' MFS'', which has been belonged to. That these members of agencies weren't been agents. Also only if they are served for terrorism defense.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.isor-sozialverein.de/Hilfen/NeuePet_170105/PetNorbert.htm Aus der Petition einer Angestellten der Sportvereinigung „Dynamo“&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;
Some also get little pension, although they worked as a teacher, and their acts would have been checked.
&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.isor-sozialverein.de/Hilfen/NeuePet_170105/PetInge1.htm Aus der Petition einer Angestellten der Sportvereinigung „Dynamo“&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;
Employees of the State Security were camouflaged as civilians in events. Sometimes they did recognize themselfes with the same souvenirs. For example: Bananas and Sandwiches. These was a sort of a &quot;sport-police&quot;. On [[Hooligans]] are even used [[Espionage|agent]]'s. That happened for years and nobody could it remember. This were often happened with the [[BFC Dynamo]] and the [[SG Dynamo Dresden]]. Members of the organs of the [[Ministry of Interior of the GDR]] had to support the ''SV'', otherwise, there was not a good omen for them.&lt;ref&gt;Willmann, Frank; Stadionpartisanen Fans und Hooligans in der DDR; Neues Leben Publishers, August 2007; 223 Pages - Language: German - 213x149x27 mm; ISBN 9783355017442&lt;/ref&gt;[[File:Bundesarchiv Bild 183-1983-0325-037, Festveranstaltung SV Dynamo, Erich Mielke.jpg|right|thumb|250px|Army Gen. and Minister [[Erich Mielke]], [[1983]]]]

====Targets and Soviet brotherhood phrases for affluence fakes====
Dynamo was created in accordance with the multi-sports club model developed in the [[Soviet Union]] and adopted throughout Eastern Europe. From the beginning it had an overtly political as well as sporting agenda and its many successes were always portrayed as a triumph of the GDR state. It was frequently lauded by East German leaders in their speeches. For example -
&quot;If we speak of the good results the [[East Germany|GDR]] sport, then the Sports Club Dynamo has of it an important portion. But we say dear friends and comrades of the Sports Club all ranges of the physical culture and the sport to you affect. We appreciate however not the large achievements in the area the physical culture and the sport, but say also all comrades of our protection and safety organs thanks for the fact that them us altogether in our work, with which education, with which development of physical culture and sport supported and also with the security of our results and successes in the whole past years in so outstanding way. If we speak of new tasks and new far-stretched goals, then we count on the fact that the sport. Dynamo may be as in the past also in the future an equally strong asset in ours, German gymnastic and sport organisation. The Sport Club Dynamo always took an outstanding place. In the competition of the Sports Club and district organizations it often distinguished, also in districts represent our comrades the Sports Club Dynamo a strong position of our sport organization. We all however know that our tasks become in the future not only larger, but also still various possibilities to open are to carry a still better work out in order to justify hopes of the people and the party.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Manfred Ewald, chairman of the DTSB of the GDR, in the welcoming address on the 6. Conference of the centers line of the Sportvereinigung Dynamo March 23, 1973&lt;/ref&gt;
„We have the certainty that you use all your power; because SV Dynamo, means more than only driving power; (…)
[[File:Bundesarchiv Bild 183-1985-0206-032, Berlin, 35. Jahrestag des MfS, Probe des Rahmenprogramms.jpg|right|180px|thumb|Athletes of Dynamo in their pride.]]
The name Sport Club Dynamo, that is progress that is [[socialism]], [[communism]], means, after the progressive theory of mankind to work after [[Marxism]] and [[Leninism]]. (…)Sport Club Dynamo that is undestructable friendship to the Soviet Union, to the [[Communist Party of the Soviet Union]] and for Soviet brother organization [[Dynamo (sports society)|Dynamo]]. (…)Sports Club Dynamo , is bounded with the party, with the [[working class]] and the workers of the [[German Democratic Republic]]. (…) Sports Club Dynamo is called to give to the [[DTSB]] of the GDR large support with the fulfilment of the tasks is called to work as progressive powers in the selection crews of the GDR, in the district organizations, everywhere, where Dynamo sportsmen work. (…)
Sports Club Dynamo, that means, to carry out the resolutions with humans in the interest of humans for the further stabilization of the GDR.”&lt;ref&gt;Rudi Hellmann, chairman of the department of sport in the ZK of the SED, on the VII. central delegate conference of the Sports Club Dynamo 1974&lt;/ref&gt;

====Professional soccer- cheating with GDR &quot;Oberliga&quot; championships====
[[File:Bundesarchiv Bild 183-1988-1210-025, Schiedsrichter Adolf Prokop.jpg|thumb|left|180px|&quot;Officer in special mission&quot; (MfS: &quot;[[OibE]], OSKAR&quot;) [[Adolf Prokop]]]] The controversies surrounding this club are therefore part of this clubs article. The other Dynamo football departments however remained under the authority of the ''Sportvereinigung''. The accusations of match fixing associated with the ''BFC Dynamo'' do not extend to the other ''Dynamo'' clubs and a club like [[Dynamo Dresden]] remains immensely popular in former East Germany and beyond. According to a denunciation by IM in October 1980 it was recommended initially, remove the three players of Dynamo Dresden to face down for the GDR national team, Dynamo soccer player such as [[Peter Kotte]] ([[invalid]] by malpractice), [[Gerd Weber]], [[Klaus Müller]] (all three at [[Dynamo Dresden]]) when the Stasi had a lack of time and the players were picked on day of departure &quot;and arrested two other men and two women...&quot;. The harsh sentences against Weber (which will be discussed by IM entanglement Pleil), end of career and other consequences for released players are observed impressively. It is also exciting that students and the public developed forms of protest against the victimization of those affected with the slogan &quot;Kotte; Müller; Weber, Gerd: Alle sind sie eingesperrt! ([[English language|English]]: Kotte; Müller; Weber, Gerd: They are all locked up!). The MfS controlled the press and responded with misinformation and pressure. They had hard existential problems with the Stasi or became a labor ban.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.dynamo-dresden.de/verein/tradition/geschichte/1980-1989/fall-mueller-kotte-weber/&lt;/ref&gt; Successful escaped athletes were not always secure like [[Lutz Eigendorf]] ([[BFC Dynamo]]). He died under mysterious circumstances. His wife were been watched around the clock in [[East Berlin]] by agents.

One of the best known East German Referee is [[Adolf Prokop]]. He is mostly known for supervising two matches in the FIFA World Cup, one in 1978 and one in 1982. He was also active at [[UEFA]] Championships 1984. As an officer for special missions of the [[Stasi|Ministry for State Security]], he was during his time a referee of the [[DDR-Oberliga]] and accused for dominating [[BFC Dynamo]] match results. The referees of the set for [[BFC Dynamo]] and [[Dynamo Dresden]] games were recorded as IM, as research has confirmed.
However, it is often misunderstood, that the BFC Dynamo was punctuated by MfS only and never been Dynamo Dresden. This is a [[fairy tale]], at least 18 Dyn. players has been exposed (without officials, [[Coach (sport)|coaches]], [[physician|doctor]]s, [[gardener]]s etc. ...) in Dresden as &quot;IM&quot;. But much love tales of these stories. In addition, the SV Dynamo won over 15 [[DFV]] championships in a row.
The [[Dresden]] [[Socialist Unity Party of Germany]] was interested in a successful representation of the district. It happened with [[Dynamo Dresden]] an arbitrary doping with knowledge of the SED and the Stasi - the officials access to doping, to strengthen the position of the ''&quot;[[Black]]- [[Yellow]]s&quot;'' for honour, ''friends'', [[Intershop]] consumption (The Ministry of State Security monitored the Intershop's very strong, often members of Stasi employees or officials were working as shop assistants.). It has completed and researched the [[Faculty (university)|faculty]] of Social and Cultural Studies at [[Humboldt University of Berlin]] and [[University of Potsdam]] in 2002.&lt;ref&gt;http://hsozkult.geschichte.hu-berlin.de/REZENSIO/buecher/2001/SpGi1201.htm&lt;/ref&gt; Moreover, the style of football was very much geared to endurance than for duel tactics or techniques. A book with the title &quot;Mielke, power and championships&quot; (German: &quot;[[Mielke, Macht und Meisterschaft]]&quot;)&lt;ref&gt;http://www.amazon.de/Mieke-Macht-Meisterschaft-Ingolf-Pleil/dp/3861532352&lt;/ref&gt; deals extensively with the issue to call the victims with their names and not the trigger, but it is not exactly received by the author for doping as it should then he was strong biased for Dynamo Dresden. Interviews with former athletes confirmed that they didn't live ''under a rock'' and were able to get some funds administered in [[tablets]] and [[Injection (medicine)|injections]].

====Historical circumstances====
In addition, the [[Dresdner Sportclub|Dresden Sportclub]] (the successor of [[Dresden English Football Club]]) has been dissolved by strange action before the founding of the SG Dynamo Dresden. Erich Mielke himself ordered the ban in lifeless behaviour. The DSC was previously the most popular club in Dresden and at the last German championship celebration were hundreds of thousands of fans.
Moreover, the switch in the professional field athletes were assessed on personality and attitude so true talents often ''missed the train''. In the 70's and 80's of the 20th century, there was no international morality in the sense of doping. Seldom gave anybody the technical resources, laws and controls and it is nothing to the latest [[World Anti-Doping Agency|WADA]] control standards of today. In addition other clubs, associations suspects against each other for doping at a hight international level, especially in the era of atomized [[Cold War]].

== Dynamo-Hall of fame ==
[[File:Bundesarchiv Bild 183-L0827-0221, XX. Olympiade, DDR-Turnerinnen, Karin Janz.jpg|right|250px|thumb|A winner procession for a Dynamo member at the Olympics.]]
They lived across in normal rented houses besides workers or even came from peasant families. They got no million contracts for their actions. Some also studied along their athletic careers, with extra curriculas has been prepared for them. This is proved as progressive.
*[[Gerhard Kaminski]] awarded the German [[Federal Cross of Merit]] for his super trainer career at the Dynamo-Sports-Hall in Gymnastics. He trained world class gymnasts in a 50 years record era, for the Olympic Games. In 1999, he awarded the [[Manfred von Richthofen]] - price.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.gymmedia.com//news/kaminski01.htm&lt;/ref&gt;
*Dynamo athletes won medals in many Olympic and World Championship events. The annual contribution defrauded per year only converted 0,60 - € / 0,90- $/ 12,- M. The citizen of the GDR deserved in average approximately 500,- ''[[East German mark]] (''Mark'')'' per month.
*The [[genius]] Dr. med. orth. hab. [[Karin Büttner-Janz]] (Olympic winner, medical scientist on the [[Humboldt University]]), is the gymnast 20th century. She also invented the artificial [[intervertebral disc]].
*Dipl. Ing. [[Sigmund Jähn]] was the first [[cosmonaut]] in [[space]] from the [[East Germany|GDR]]. He was also an honorary member of the SV. The honorary title does he won for the SV Dynamo district Karl-Marx-Stadt; at the SC Dynamo Klingenthal, in 1978. When he got the certificate, he said: &quot;As a skijumper were Harry Glaß my personal model for the start to the [[Universe|Cosmos]].&quot; This skijumper had nearly broken neck, and was in pension of ability.&lt;ref&gt;Dynamosport Magazine; 1978; 20th edition on page 2&lt;/ref&gt;
*Dynamo athletes were also the one, which may could learn [[karate]] or even [[jujutsu]] as well as the general citizens could only learn [[judo]].
*Spies in the [[United States]] has earned the complete knowledge about the martial arts training of the [[CIA]] and Dynamo became this informations.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.kampfkunst-board.info/forum/f15/mfs-35510/index2.html MfS&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;
* One of the best of the bests, were [[Maxi Gnauck]] (very famous), [[Bernd Wiesner]], [[Jutta Hampe]], [[Katrin Boron]], [[Caren Metschuck]] mostly in rowing, gymnastics and parashuting.
Among the Dynamo top scorers were:&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.olympic.org/uk/athletes/index_uk.asp International Olympic Committee - Athletes&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.sport-komplett.de/sport-komplett/sportarten/index_sportarten.htm Sport Complete]&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.allcompetitions.com/ Competition Results / Resultados de Competiciones&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;
{{Main|List of international winning SV Dynamo sports club athletes}}

== Achievements==
===Olympics===
The sports club won approx. 215 Olympic [[medals]] in a 37 years period.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.sportmuseum-leipzig.de&lt;/ref&gt;

===World-Championships===
The sports club won approx. 324 World Cup medals in a 37 years period.
Completely won the SV Dynamo more as World champion titles as hundreds of other nations (2008).The most titles have won the rowers.&lt;ref&gt;[http://dispatch.opac.ddb.de/DB=1.1/LNG=DU/SID=690ceed1-30/LNG=EN/ Data bank for the Magazine Dynamo sport/ Please insert Dynamosport for searching (atttention:German language) It is for proofing the medals; extra beside the linked athletes here.]&lt;/ref&gt;

===European-Championships===
The athletes won approx. 182 European titles.&lt;ref&gt;[http://dispatch.opac.ddb.de/DB=1.1/LNG=DU/SID=690ceed1-30/LNG=EN/ Data bank for the Magazine Dynamo sport/ Please insert Dynamosport for searching (atttention:German language) It is for proving the medals; extra beside the linked athletes here.]&lt;/ref&gt;
{{see also|List of international winning SV Dynamo sports club athletes}}

=== Championships===
The Dynamo-Athletes won altogether 2.187 titles in 35 sport-sections in a 37 year period.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.sport-komplett.de www.sport-komplett.de - Sportnachrichten, Sportergebnisse, Sportstatistiken, Sporthistorie, Autogramme, Sportveranstaltungen, Sportbücher&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;
The Dynamo-Athletes won altogether 2.187 titles in 35 sport-sections over a 37 year period.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.sport-komplett.de www.sport-komplett.de - Sportnachrichten, Sportergebnisse, Sportstatistiken, Sporthistorie, Autogramme, Sportveranstaltungen, Sportbücher&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;
{{Main|List of the national championships of the SV Dynamo}}
With 280,000 members, it is not surprising that the SV Dynamo [[multi-sport club]] has a lot of championships won in the GDR, so that a separate category should be needed.
&lt;ref&gt;http://www.sportmuseum-leipzig.de (all about the facts and figures at the archives)&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.olympic.org/uk/athletes/index_uk.asp International Olympic Committee - Athletes&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.sport-komplett.de/sport-komplett/sportarten/index_sportarten.htm Sport Complete]&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.allcompetitions.com/ Competition Results / Resultados de Competiciones&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;

==Gallery==
===Photos===
&lt;gallery perrow=&quot;6&quot;&gt;
File:Bundesarchiv Bild 183-B0903-0025-005, Schwerin, Kindergarten Lamprechtsgrund, Spielplatz, Sport- und Kongresshalle.jpg|[[Schwerin]]'s multi use hall
File:Fotothek df ps 0003655 Kinder ^ Kinderbeschäftigungen ^ badend.jpg|Arnhold-Bath, Dresden
File:Bundesarchiv Bild 183-74500-0082, Warnemünde, Hafen, Leuchtturm.jpg|Sailing in Warnemünde
File:Bundesarchiv Bild 183-J0711-0024-001, Bernd Rudel, Lutz Unger, K.-Rüdiger Mann, Peter Rund.jpg|Swimmer
File:Bundesarchiv Bild 183-1987-0708-047, Berlin, Friedrich-Ludwig-Jahn-Sportpark.jpg|Jahn-Stadium (East Berlin)
File:Bundesarchiv Bild 183-R0811-0302, Berlin, Schwimmhalle.jpg|Berlin indoor swimming pool
File:Bundesarchiv Bild 183-1984-0511-025, Maxi Gnauck, Hannelore Sauer.jpg|Gymnastics
File:Bundesarchiv Bild 183-M1031-0300, DDR-Sportler des Jahres 1973, Mannschaftsfoto Dynamo Dresden.jpg|1973, Munich
File:Bundesarchiv Bild 183-B1201-0008-003, Hollstein, Reimer.jpg|Cross country running
File:Bundesarchiv Bild 183-1985-0721-008, B. Peter, R. Balthasar, M. Schöter, S. Schwabe.jpg|Rowing
File:Bundesarchiv Bild 183-46639-0002, Rostock, Schwimmhalle &quot;Neptun&quot;.jpg|Indoor swimming pool [[Rostock]]
File:Bundesarchiv Bild 183-1986-0811-040, Dresden, Heinz-Steyer-Stadion.jpg|Dresden, Steyer-Stadium
&lt;/gallery&gt;

==See also==
*[[Use of performance-enhancing drugs in sport]]
For other famous multi-sport clubs:
*[[:Category:Red Bull sports teams|Red Bull Sports]]
*[[Panathinaikos]]
*[[Real Madrid]]
*[[Sporting Clube de Portugal]]
*[[The New York Athletic Club]]
{{Commons category|SV Dynamo}}

==Further reading==
*[http://www.clinchem.org/cgi/content/full/43/7/1262 Hormonal doping and androgenization of athletes: a secret program of the German Democratic Republic government], by: Werner W. Franke (Hölderlin High School, Heidelberg, Germany) and Brigitte Berendonk, publisher:American Association for Clinical Chemistry

== Literature ==
&lt;div class=&quot;references-small&quot;&gt;
*[[Dynamosport]]
* {{cite book |last = Gläser| first =Andreas | title= [[SV Dynamo Ein Almanach]]| year=1976 |id=ASIN B0027432ZC}} {{de icon}}
* {{cite book |last = | first =| title= SV Dynamo [[Mut und Kraft]]| year=1984| publisher =Offizin Andersen Nexö Leipzig |id=ASIN none}} {{de icon}}
&lt;/div&gt;

==References==
&lt;div class=&quot;references-small&quot;&gt;{{Reflist|2}}&lt;/div&gt;

== External links ==
{{Wiktionary|Dynamo}}
&lt;div class=&quot;references-small&quot;&gt;
*[http://www.mfs-insider.de/SachbuchPDF/HAXX6.pdf Declaration by the Stasi itself to their Dynamo Sports Society's past] {{de icon}}
*[http://www.dynamo-rostock.de/ SV Dynamo of Rostock] {{de icon}}
*[http://www.runde-ecke-leipzig.de/sammlung/index.php?seite=1 Citizens Committee of Leipzig, the custodian of the “Runde Ecke” Memorial Museum and the Stasi Museum] {{en icon}}
*[http://www.bild.bundesarchiv.de Federal Commissioner for the Stasi Archives - Pictures] {{de icon}}
*[http://www.bstu.bund.de/nn_715182/DE/Regionales/Aussenstelle-Chemnitz/Veranstaltungen/Leihausstellungen/leihausstellung__doppeltes__spiel.html__nnn=true Federal Commissioner for the Stasi Archives: The Dynamo-State-System of the communist East Germany] {{de icon}}
*[http://www.bstu.bund.de/cln_028/nn_712118/sid_DF7FD27805E1A8084FB3F18E3D39A3BA/DE/MfS-DDR-Geschichte/Hintergruende-zur-Staatssicherheit/Struktur-und-Aufgaben/aufgaben__sv__dynamo.html__nnn=true Federal Commissioner for the Stasi Archives: Structures and Missions at the SVD] {{de icon}}
*[http://www.bstu.bund.de/nn_1091102/DE/Archiv/Findhilfsmittel/Aktenverzeichnisse/aktenverzeichnis__mfs__filme__videos,templateId=raw,property=publicationFile.pdf/aktenverzeichnis_mfs_filme_videos.pdf Movies from the Federal Commissioner for the Stasi Archives] {{de icon}}
*[http://books.google.de/books?id=qdjaKkWthDkC&amp;printsec=frontcover&amp;dq=mielke+macht+und+meisterschaft&amp;hl=de&amp;ei=UtPKTKiZCMmdOqPc_b0B&amp;sa=X&amp;oi=book_result&amp;ct=result&amp;resnum=1&amp;ved=0CCkQ6AEwAA#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false ''Mielke Macht und Meisterschaft'': Supervision of Dynamo-Club sections in the light of the representative part Dynamo Dresden] {{de icon}}
&lt;/div&gt;

{{SV Dynamo}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Dynamo, Sv}}
[[Category:Multi-sport clubs]]
[[Category:Sports history of East Germany]]
[[Category:Sport in East Germany]]
[[Category:SV Dynamo| ]]
[[Category:Sports clubs disestablished in 1990]]
[[Category:Sports clubs established in 1953]]
[[Category:Stasi]]
[[Category:Dynamo sports society]]

[[de:Sportvereinigung Dynamo]]
[[es:Sportvereinigung Dynamo]]
[[ru:Динамо (ГДР)]]
[[fi:SV Dynamo]]
[[sv:Dynamo (sport)]]
[[zh:迪纳摩体育协会]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
