<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="1394165" ns="0" title="Wormmon"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Unreferenced|date=May 2009}}{{In-universe|date=October 2009}}
&lt;!-- When listing information, such as attacks and Digivolutions (evolutions), please indicate where the information comes from. Information that cannot be [[WP:V|verified]] will be removed without warning. --&gt;
{{Digimon Infobox
|partner=[[Ken Ichijouji]]
|actors=[[Naozumi Takahashi]] (Japanese)&lt;br&gt; [[Paul St. Peter]] (English)
|name=Wormmon
|katakana=ワームモン
|japname=
|image=[[Image:Wormmon.gif|center|270px|]]
|fresh=Leafmon
|in-training=Minomon
|rookie='''Wormmon'''
|champion=Stingmon
|ultimate=Dinobeemon&lt;ref&gt;''[[Digimon Tamers: Brave Tamer]]''&lt;/ref&gt; Jewelbeemon
|mega=GranKuwagamon&lt;ref&gt;''[[Digimon Tamers: Brave Tamer]]''&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;!--THOSE ARE HIS ULTIMATE AND MEGA FORMS ACCORDING TO THE DIGIMON TAMERS: BRAVE TAMER VIDEOGAME, WHICH IS CANONICAL TO THE TV SERIES--&gt;
|armor1=Bucchiemon
|egg1=Kindness
|DNApartner=[[ExVeemon]]
|DNAultimate=Paildramon
|DNAmega=Imperialdramon
|DNAmega2=Imperialdramon Fighter Mode
|DNAmega3=Imperialdramon Paladin Mode
}}

'''[[wikia:digimon:List of Rookie Digimon (Part 2)#Wormmon|Wormmon]]''' is a [[Digimon (creature)|Digimon creature]] from the [[Japan]]ese [[Digimon|Digimon media franchise]] that comprises [[anime]], [[manga]], toys, [[video games]], [[Collectible card game|trading card games]] and other media. 

&quot;Wormmon&quot; is the name that all members of this particular Digimon species share. There are several different Wormmon that appear in various Digimon anime and manga series.

Wormmon's name is derived from the word &quot;worm&quot;, which is often also used as a term to describe the larval form of insects.

==Appearance==
Wormmon is a small green worm-like creature. Like a real insect, Wormmon possesses the ability to adhere to surfaces and is also able to generate silk from its mouth.

==Description==

Wormmon is a main character in [[Digimon Adventure 02]], and also appears in the movie [[Digimon Adventure 02#Diaboromon Strikes Back|Diablomon Strikes Back]]. 

Wormmon's story begun when a young [[Ken Ichijouji]] was sucked into the Digital World for the first time via his brother's computer. Ken, along with [[Ryo Akiyama]], traveled together with their Digimon through the Digital World desert, where they battled and defeated [[Millenniummon]]. With its death, Millenniummon released the Dark Spores, one of which burrowed inside Ken's neck. 

The next time Wormmon met Ken, the boy had assumed the guise of the Digimon Emperor. Although Ken, as the Digimon Emperor, treated Wormmon cruelly; Wormmon still chose to stand by him out of friendship and loyalty. However, when [[Kimeramon]] was finally created and went on a swathe of destruction across the Digital World, Wormmon finally decided to make a final attempt to save Ken by disobeying him. Wormmon led [[Daisuke Motomiya|Davis]] and [[Veemon]] to the [[Digi-Egg#Miracles|Digi-Egg of Miracles]], which turned Veemon into [[Magnamon]]. Ken still refusing to give up and with Magnamon losing, Wormmon took drastic measures and surrendered all its life force to Magnamon. This gave Magnamon enough power to kill Kimeramon, but it cost Wormmon its life.  This last noble act, however, was enough to finally make Ken realize his evil doings and resign from them.

Wormmon was reborn as a Digi-Egg in ''Primary Village'' and reunited with his partner Ken. Ken then vowed to fix the damage he had caused, but discovered that he was only being used by [[Arukenimon]] to establish the Control Spires. To fight the monsters created from the towers, Wormmon achieved the power to Digivolve to his champion form - Stingmon. The two became official members of the team when [[Stingmon]] merged with [[Veemon#ExVeemon|ExVeemon]] to form Paildramon. With [[Azulongmon]]'s power, Paildramon was later able to Digivolve further into [[Imperialdramon]]. 

Of all the protagonist Digimon of [[Digimon Adventure 02]], Wormmon is the only one to have the Virus attribute; in fact, Wormmon was the first known Virus type partner Digimon in the Digimon anime series. He is also the only one to be able to digivolve to the champion level when a control spire is present.

&lt;u&gt;'''Attacks&lt;/u&gt;'''
*'''Silk Thread''': Shoots a thick strand of thread.
*'''Sticky Net''' (ネバネバネット): Makes a net to immobilize enemies.

==Other Forms==
The name &quot;Wormmon&quot; refers to only the [[Digivolution#Digivolutionary Levels|rookie form]] of this Digimon. Throughout the series, Wormmon gains the ability to [[Digivolution|Digivolve]] into a number of more powerful forms (each with a different name). The rookie form, however, is its most common and preferred form.

{|wikitable
|-
| style=&quot;background:WhiteSmoke&quot; |
=== Leafmon ===
[[Image:Leafmon.jpg|thumb|Leafmon (リーフモン)]]
[[List of Fresh Digimon#Leafmon|Leafmon]] is the fresh form of Wormmon. Leafmon first appears in [[Digimon Adventure 02]] episode 23, when Ken found him in Primary Village. He also appeared when [[Wormmon#Paildramon|Paildramon]] loses so much power that Wormmon and [[Veemon]] are no longer able to maintain their Rookie forms, though this is rectified once digivolving into Imperialdramon via [[Azulongmon]]'s cores allowing him to assume his rookie form regardless of how high the evolution and energy loss. 

Leafmon is small and green, and has a long tail resembling a leaf. This is where the name &quot;Leafmon&quot; comes from. It has two small ears on its round head and a pink pacifier. Like most baby level Digimon, Leafmon has small black eyes and two round pink cheeks under its eyes. Once Ken was freed from the evil that overtook him as the Digimon Emperor, Wormmon returned to Ken in this form and subsequently digivolved back into Minomon.

&lt;u&gt;'''Attacks&lt;/u&gt;'''
* '''Bubble Blow''' (''Acid Bubbles''): Fires bubbles from its mouth.
|-
|

=== Minomon ===
[[Image:Minomon.jpg|thumb|Minomon (ミノモン)]]
[[List of In-Training Digimon#Minomon|Minomon]] is Wormmon's In-Training form. The name &quot;Minomon&quot; comes from the Japanese word &quot;minomushi&quot;, which refers to the larval form of an insect called &quot;minoga&quot;.

Minomon sometimes appears when Wormmon is forced to de-digivolve after a particularly difficult battle, or if he regresses to Leafmon and digivolves back again in the real world.

&lt;u&gt;'''Attacks&lt;/u&gt;'''
* '''Pincone Attack''' (''Pinecone''): An attack that involves shooting pine cone projectiles at its enemies.
|-
| style=&quot;background:WhiteSmoke&quot; |

=== Pucchiemon ===
Pucchiemon is the Armor Digivolved form of Wormmon through the [[Digieggs#Kindness|Digi-Egg of Kindness]]. Wormmon gained the ability Armor Digivolve to Pucchiemon in the CD drama '''Digimon Adventure 02: Michi e no Armor Shinka'''( The Road to Armor Evolution ) to stop Davis from harming [[Veemon]]. What is Wormmon?

&lt;u&gt;'''Attacks&lt;/u&gt;'''
* '''Heartner Beam'''
* '''Love and Fire'''
* '''Love Lazer'''
|-
|

=== Stingmon ===
[[Image:Stingmon.jpg|thumb|Stingmon (スティングモン)]]
[[List of Champion Digimon (Part 4)#Stingmon|Stingmon]] is Wormmon's natural champion form. Stingmon first appeared when [[Arukenimon]] began her reign of terror by creating fake Digimon out of Control Spires. At first, Stingmon and [[Ken Ichijouji|Ken]] worked alone to destroy these Digimon and the Control Spires, but eventually they teamed up with the other [[DigiDestined]]. Stingmon made his first appearance when one of the Control Spire Digimon, [[Thundermon]], attacked ''Primary Village''.

Unlike his earlier form Wormmon, Stingmon is a formidable fighter with a cool and collected personality.

&lt;u&gt;'''Attacks&lt;/u&gt;'''
* '''Spiking Strike''' (''Spiking Finish''): The spikes on Stingmon's shoulders stand up and a pink energy spike on his forearm activates. Stingmon uses this spike to vaporize his enemies.
*'''Insect Lord'''  (''Bug Ki''): Stingmon releases a swarm of insects that have stinger on their abdomens, and attacks the enemy.  
|-
|

=== Paildramon ===
[[List of Ultimate Digimon (Part 3)#Paildramon|Paildramon]] is an Ultimate level digimon who is the Ultimate form of Veemon and DNA of Stingmon and [[Exveemon]] in season 2, combining the features and attributes of an Insectoid type Digimon with that of a Dragon type. Some of his recognizable parts are ExVeemon's wings, lower legs, and tail; and Stingmon's hands and body, or he looks like ExVeemon wearing Stingmon as body armor.

Wormmon and Veemon are the first of the [[Digimon Adventure 02|second generation]] DigiDestined Digimon to achieve [[Digivolution#DNA Digivolution|DNA Digivolution]]. When Ken's former base threatened to explode, [[Arukenimon]] attempted to stop the [[DigiDestined]] with an [[Okuwamon]] she had created. [[Ken Ichijouji|Ken]] had been willing to throw away his life to undo the damage he caused, but [[Daisuke Motomiya|Davis]] managed to convince him to get over what he did in the past and keep living. At that instant, when the hearts of Davis and Ken were beating as one, ExVeemon and Stingmon were able to merge and form Paildramon.

Paildramon was strong enough to destroy Okuwamon and stop the detonation of Ken's base. For a while, Paildramon was the only ultimate digimon on the DigiDestined's team, and was a valuable ally in their fight against [[Arukenimon]], [[Mummymon]], and later [[BlackWarGreymon]].

&lt;u&gt;'''Attacks&lt;/u&gt;'''
* '''Desperado Blaster''': Fires energy bullets from the weapons on his hips.
* '''Cable Catcher''' (''Esgreamer''): Fires off his claws and binds his enemy like wires.
* '''Sting Strike''' : Attacks with the spikes on his arms, hitting the enemy hard

=== Imperialdramon ===
[[Image:Imperialdramon.gif|thumb|Imperialdramon (インペリアルドラモン)]]
Imperialdramon is a mega level Digimon who is the alternate mega form of Veemon. Around Christmas time, [[Veemon]] and Wormmon were given power from one of the DigiCores of [[Azulongmon]]. This allowed them, as Paildramon, to Digivolve further into Imperialdramon. Imperialdramon's enormous power allowed him to help send digimon who had been appearing in the Real World back to the [[Digimon World]].

Imperialdramon was also responsible for transporting the [[DigiDestined]] around the world so they could help the DigiDestined of other countries. It was through Imperialdramon that [[MaloMyotismon]] was finally destroyed at the very end of [[Digimon Adventure 02]].

&lt;u&gt;'''Attacks&lt;/u&gt;'''
* '''Positron Laser''': Fires a huge laser blast from the cannon on his back.
|-
| 

==== Imperialdramon Fighter Mode ====
[[Image:ImperialdramonFighter.gif|thumb|Imperialdramon Fighter Mode (インペリアルドラモン・ファイターモード)]]
[[List of Mega Digimon (Part 3)#Imperialdramon Fighter Mode|Imperialdramon Fighter Mode]] is the mega form, besides [[UlforceVeedramon]], of Veemon. The Fighter Mode gives Imperialdramon a more human shape and more precise control over his immense power, said to triple it.

This form was first achieved in Episode 43 of [[Digimon Adventure 02]]. When the evil Digimon [[Daemon (Digimon)|Daemon]] and its Daemon Corps appeared, Imperialdramon was frozen by [[SkullSatamon]]. To free Imperialdramon, the Digimon of the older DigiDestined De-Digivolved from their Ultimate forms and gave their remaining power to Imperialdramon, triggering the Mode Change.

Imperialdramon Fighter Mode was powerful enough to kill SkullSatamon in an instant before he slew numerous children inside a school bus, fight Daemon and seal him in the dark ocean, and finally destroy MaloMyotison with his Giga Crusher.

&lt;u&gt;'''Attacks&lt;/u&gt;'''
* '''Positron Laser''': Fires a huge purple laser from the cannon on his arm.
* '''Splendor Blade''': Imperialdramon slashes at his enemies with blades of energy made within the &quot;spikes&quot; on his arm armor.
* '''Giga Crusher''' (''Giga Death''): Transforms the Positron Laser cannon on his arm into a bigger cannon held by both arms which fires a powerful purple blast on his enemy,Caused when the international digidestined group together and use their digivices to give him power to open up the giga crusher laser, used to destroy MaloMyotismon. By Movie 4 (Revenge of Diaboromon) he can fire the same attack when the dragon mouth on his chest opens up to fire a white spherical version, inflicting immense damage.
|-
| style=&quot;background:WhiteSmoke&quot; |

==== Imperialdramon Paladin Mode ====
[[Image:ImperialdramonPaladin.gif|thumb|Imperialdramon Paladin Mode (インペリアルドラモン・パラディンモード)]]
[[List of Mega Digimon (Part 3)#Imperialdramon Paladin Mode|Imperialdramon Paladin Mode]] is an even more powerful alternate form of Imperialdramon, achieved after [[Omnimon]] gave Imperialdramon Fighter Mode his power.

Imperialdramon Paladin Mode appears in the Digimon movie [[Digimon Adventure 02#Diablomon Strikes Back|Diablomon Strikes Back]], or Revenge of Diaboromon (English version). Imperialdramon Fighter Mode had been fighting [[Armageddemon]] using his Giga Crusher attack. However, it was not strong enough, and ended up injured in Armageddemon's counterattack. [[Omnimon]], who had already been badly injured by [[Armageddemon]], gave his remaining energy to Imperialdramon. Omnimon's arms separated from his main body to become [[Agumon]] and [[Gabumon]] again, while his main body became the ''Omni Sword''. Imperialdramon Fighter Mode, wielding this sword, turned into Imperialdramon Paladin Mode and defeated Armageddemon.
Imperialdramon Paladin Mode loses all aspects of one of its original Digimon, Stingmon; fans have noted Paladin mode looks more like a Veemon and Omnimon DNA digivolution.

&lt;u&gt;'''Attacks&lt;/u&gt;'''
* '''Omni Sword''' (''Omega Blade''): Strikes his opponents with his Holy Blade. The Sword contains Omnimon's power.
|}

== References ==
{{reflist}}


{{Digimon}}

[[Category:Chosen Digimon]]
[[Category:Fictional bees]]
[[Category:Fictional beetles]]

[[it:Wormmon]]
[[ms:Wormmon]]
[[ja:ワームモン]]
[[pt:Wormmon]]
[[fi:Wormmon]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
