<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="1396115" ns="0" title="Star Fox: Assault"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Infobox video game
|image=[[Image:assaultbox.jpg|250px]]
|caption=North American box art
|developer=[[Namco]]
|publisher=[[Nintendo]]
|director=Toshiyuki Nakanishi&lt;br&gt;Hideki Okazaki&lt;br&gt;Yutaka Yoshida
|producer=Tsuyoshi Kobayashi&lt;br&gt;[[Shigeru Miyamoto]]
|composer=Yoshie Arakawa&lt;br&gt;Yoshinori Kawamoto
|series=''[[Star Fox (series)|Star Fox]]''
|platforms=[[Nintendo GameCube]]
|released={{vgrelease|NA=February 14, 2005}}{{vgrelease|JP=February 24, 2005|EU=April 29, 2005|AUS=June 16, 2005}}
|genre=[[Action game|Action]], [[third-person shooter]], [[rail shooter]]
|modes=[[Single-player]], [[multiplayer]]
|ratings={{vgratings|ACB=G8+|CERO=All ages|ESRB=T|PEGI=7+}}
}}
Star Fox: Assault (スターフォックス アサルト Sutā Fokkusu Asaruto) is a [[third-person shooter]] [[video game]] for the [[Nintendo GameCube]] developed by [[Namco]] and published by [[Nintendo]]. It is the fourth released title in the ''[[Star Fox (series)|Star Fox]]'' series. It was released on February 14, 2005 in North America, on February 24, 2005 in Japan, on April 29, 2005 in Europe, and on June 16, 2005 in Australia. The game was available at [[Blockbuster (movie rental store)|Blockbuster]] and [[Movie Gallery|Hollywood Video]] stores starting February 1, 2005 as a promotion.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |title=Rent Star Fox Assault Early |publisher=IGN |url=http://cube.ign.com/articles/583/583126p1.html |accessdate=2006-07-28}}&lt;/ref&gt;

''Assault'' returns the ''Star Fox'' series to its space-combat roots after the previous game in the series, ''[[Star Fox Adventures]]'', took a more action-RPG approach.  ''Assault'' takes place one year after the events of ''Adventures'' and introduces a new enemy named the ''Aparoids'', a race bent on the assimilation of the Lylat system into their [[Collectivism|collective]] mind.&lt;ref name=&quot;booklet&quot;&gt;{{cite book |year=2005 |editor=Namco |title=Star Fox Assault Instruction Booklet |pages=7, 29, 34–35 |publisher=Nintendo of America }}&lt;/ref&gt;

When ''Assault'' was initially announced by Nintendo and Namco, it was also rumored that an [[arcade game]] was under development.&lt;ref name=&quot;arcade&quot;&gt;{{cite web |title=Namco Brings GCN Support |publisher=IGN |url=http://cube.ign.com/articles/358/358767p1.html |accessdate=2006-09-12}}&lt;/ref&gt; However, the arcade game was never heard about again in the public.

==Gameplay==
[[Image:sauriaSFA.jpg|left|thumb|Fox helps destroy the aparoids that have appeared on Sauria with his Arwing in a similar manner to previous titles]]
The gameplay of ''Star Fox: Assault'' is divided into three distinctive types. The player can either fly an [[Arwing]] (a spacecraft), or drive a [[Landmaster (Star Fox)|Landmaster]] (a tank), or perform certain tasks on foot. All three play types are available for [[multiplayer game|multiplayer mode]] although some levels on multi-player mode are specific. For example, Level 1, &quot;Fortuna: A New Enemy&quot; is specifically Arwing. The game follows a completely linear track, unlike its predecessors ''[[Star Fox (video game)|Star Fox]]'' and ''[[Star Fox 64]]''.

Arwing missions in ''Assault'' are similar to those of the first two games in the series. The player flies in space or close to the ground and shoots down enemies. Some levels are [[Shooter on Яails|on rails]], while others allow full freedom of movement in a relatively small area. As in previous games, the [[Wingman|wing mates]] of Fox, the main character, occasionally call for help when chased by enemies. Additionally, in some levels, the player has the ability to hop in and out of the Arwing at will.

While in the Landmaster, the player has complete freedom to move about the level. They are free to shoot or run over enemies as well as assist their wingmates when necessary. Playing on foot essentially turns the game into a [[third-person shooter]]—the player starts armed with the blaster, a type of gun, and can acquire a variety of other weapons, including but not limited to a [[machine gun]] and a [[Shoulder-launched missile weapon|homing launcher]]. In two [[Shooter game#Shooting gallery|shooting gallery]] levels, the player rides on the wing of an Arwing or a Wolfen fighter, shooting enemies on the ground and in the air with a plasma cannon.

As an added bonus, by collecting all silver medals throughout the game, the player can unlock the [[NES]] port of the [[scrolling shooter]] [[arcade game]], ''[[Xevious]]''.&lt;ref name=&quot;booklet&quot; /&gt;

===Multiplayer===
The game features [[multiplayer video game|multiplayer]] with support for up to four players [[simultaneously]]. This mode starts off very limited, with only a few playable characters, weapons, items, and maps; but many more can be unlocked by either playing a certain number of multiplayer games or achieving certain accomplishments in-game. Players are able to fight on foot or in a vehicle (a Landmaster, Arwing, or [[Star Fox (series)#Wolfen|Wolfen]]), though some stages prohibit certain modes of travel. Playable characters include the entire [[Star Fox team]] (including Peppy) as well as [[Wolf O'Donnell]].

Multiplayer mode offers several stages for playing, including stages from the single-player mode, &quot;Simple Maps&quot; (which look like they're made of building blocks), and other new maps. There are also several modes for play available, which can force a certain weapon (sniper, rocket launcher, etc.) or change the style of play (capture the crown, etc.). Also, there are a few customizable options, such as turning radar on/off, turning special weapons on/off, and turning Demon Launches on/off.

Multiplayer has a number of items and weapons, most of which are taken directly from the single-player mode. There are also special unlockable weapons such as the Demon Sniper and Demon Launcher (dubbed &quot;The Loser Gun&quot; by the gaming community, because one gets it when one is losing) which have the ability to kill in one hit. In addition, there are a couple special items such as jet packs (which give a player on foot a hovering ability similar to Landmaster's hover), and the &quot;Stealth Suit&quot;, which can make the player [[Invisibility|invisible]] for a long period of time.&lt;ref name=&quot;booklet&quot; /&gt;

===Weapons and items===
''Assault'' features a number of projectile weapons, such as the [[Raygun|blaster]], [[machine gun]], [[Shoulder-launched missile weapon|Homing Launcher]], [[sniper rifle]] and the [[hand grenade]]&lt;ref name=&quot;booklet&quot; /&gt; Also used is the [[Plasma rifle|Plasma Cannon]], a rapid-fire gun with unlimited ammunition. This, however, is only used at two specific points in ''Assault''. The game also has a number of special items, including personal [[Force field (science fiction)|barriers]] which deflect enemy attacks. The usual rings seen in other ''Star Fox'' games that restore a vehicle's shield are also present.&lt;ref name=&quot;booklet&quot; /&gt;

==Plot==
===Setting and characters===
{{main|List of Star Fox characters}}
''Star Fox: Assault'' takes place in the Lylat system, a location featured in the previous games. All of the planets visited in the game, save for the Aparoid Homeworld, have been seen in previous titles. Venom, prominently featured in past installments, is not seen.

''Assault'' features the core Star Fox team, with [[Falco Lombardi]] having returned, and [[Krystal McCloud|Krystal]] taking over [[Peppy Hare]]'s former spot. Peppy has retired from flying, and now resides in the ''Great Fox'' with ROB overseeing the missions. [[Star Wolf team|Star Wolf]], absent from ''Adventures'', returns as well.  [[Pigma Dengar]] was kicked out, and [[Andrew Oikonny]] left. In their place is newcomer [[Panther Caroso]].

The game marks the introduction of the Aparoids - insect-like creatures that are part-machine, part-life form. The Aparoids are capable of [[infection|infecting]] other life forms and machines and transforming them into Aparoids. The game calls this infection ''Aparoidedation''. Large Aparoids contain a core memory that contains instructions as well as information on contacting the Aparoid Homeworld.

The Aparoids are led by the Aparoid Queen (Aparoid Mother in the Japanese version) on their home planet. The Queen believes that all things in the universe exist for the Aparoids to infect, and that becoming an Aparoid is not infection, but rather a form of [[evolution]]. [[Beltino Toad]] created a program that took advantage of the fact that Aparoids cells are created using [[apoptosis]] which is a chemical used in self-destruct programs. Fox used this program to destroy the Aparoid Queen. As all Aparoids are networked together in a hive mind, once Fox executed the self-destruct program in the Aparoid Queen all of the Aparoids and their home planet were forever annihilated.

The Aparoids seem to draw heavy inspiration from ''[[Star Trek]]''&lt;nowiki&gt;'&lt;/nowiki&gt;s [[Borg (Star Trek)|Borg]], which assimilate other life forms. The appearance of the Aparoid Queen who serves as the leader also reinforces this.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |title=Electric Playground |publisher=Electric Playground |url=http://www.elecplay.com/reviews_article.php?article=11219 |accessdate=2006-08-09}} &lt;/ref&gt;

===Story===
''Star Fox: Assault'' takes place one year after the events of ''[[Star Fox Adventures]]''. [[Andrew Oikonny]], [[Andross]]'s nephew, assumes leadership over his dead uncle's army and starts a rebellion against the Cornerian Army.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite video game|quote='''Corneria Army:''' Remnants of Andross's butchers! You've kept us busy! Now, your end is at hand! |title=Star Fox Assault |developer=Namco|date=February 14, 2005|level=Introduction}}&lt;/ref&gt; The [[Star Fox team]], consisting of [[Fox McCloud]], [[Falco Lombardi]], [[Krystal McCloud|Krystal]], [[Slippy Toad]], and [[Peppy Hare]] (who has retired from piloting, and instead stays in the Great Fox with ROB to Guide the Star Fox team through missions), quickly fly in to assist them. Once they fight their way through his forces, they follow Andrew to Fortuna, where he attacks them by transforming his ship into an imitation of Andross's final form, but much weaker. Before his battle with the team is through, however, his ship is destroyed by a strange, insect-like creature, which then attacks the team. Fox destroys it, and takes a partial &quot;core memory&quot; from it for research just before a large number of insects identical to the one just destroyed arrive.

Once back at the ''Great Fox'', Fox and the team learn from [[Beltino Toad]] that the attacking creature was an Aparoid, one of a powerful species capable of destroying entire Cornerian fleets with little effort.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite video game|quote='''Beltino:''' I believe it was about 17 years ago, a whole fleet was destroyed by a sole aparoid. |title=Star Fox Assault |developer=Namco|date=February 14, 2005}}&lt;/ref&gt; The team also learns that a distress signal is being sent from Katina and they suspect Aparoid involvement. Fox investigates the planet on foot, only to be trapped inside the base with the Aparoids. With the help of a Landmaster, he is able to fight them off. After defeating a large Aparoid [[boss (video games)|boss]], resembling a giant [[unidentified flying object|UFO]] with four legs, he recovers another Core Memory.  This is quickly stolen by [[Pigma Dengar]], who sent out the distress signal himself and believed he can become rich from the Core Memory's sale.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite video game|quote='''Pigma:''' Is it that important? Heh heh! Then I'm gonna be rich! |title=Star Fox Assault |developer=Namco}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The Star Fox team tracks Pigma to the Sargasso Space Zone, a popular hideout for bandits, which is overseen by the Star Wolf leader, [[Wolf O'Donnell]]. After infiltrating the base, they discover Pigma is not there and the Star Wolf team shows up with [[Panther Caroso]] as their newest member, soon after their discovery.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite video game|quote='''Panther:''' Allow me to introduce myself. I am Panther...and all who see my rose meet death! |title=Star Fox Assault |developer=Namco}}&lt;/ref&gt; Wolf, [[Leon Powalski|Leon]], and Panther engage the Star Fox team in a dogfight, which they subsequently lose. Wolf then told Fox that Pigma was no longer part of Star Wolf.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite video game|quote='''Wolf:''' Pigma's no longer part of Star Wolf. And if he'd shown his filthy hide here, my men would have driven him out. |title=Star Fox Assault |developer=Namco}}&lt;/ref&gt; Panther however, attempting to flirt with Krystal, tells her that Pigma is on the planet Fichina. When Fox and crew quickly rush over to the planet, they discover that Pigma had deactivated its climate control center, turning it into a snowy wasteland. After defeating an Aparoid that threatened to destroy the control center reactor, the team then follows Pigma through an asteroid belt. Once they catch up to him, they find that Pigma had been taken over by the Aparoids and had no control over his actions.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite video game|quote='''Fox:'' Looks like Pigma's already gone...who or what are you? / '''Pigma:''' We will answer. We are the ultimate existence. You cannot resist us. You will join us. |title=Star Fox Assault |developer=Namco|date=February 14, 2005}}&lt;/ref&gt; He lets himself be assimilated (to avoid capture) into a large spacecraft with large tentacle-like metal arms as weapons. Fox fights and destroys Pigma, and retrieves the core memory, which has the information that will lead the team to the Aparoid Homeworld.

Krystal receives a sudden distress call from Sauria - formerly known as Dinosaur Planet - which is under attack by the Aparoids.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite video game|quote='''Krystal:''' I'm sensing a distress call from planet Sauria. |title=Star Fox Assault |developer=Namco}}&lt;/ref&gt; Fox quickly lands on the planet and destroys the Aparoid hatchers before the [[dinosaur]]s there are wiped out. After the battle, Fox and Krystal reunite with [[Prince Tricky]], now a teenaged EarthWalker. Back on the ''Great Fox'', General Pepper informs that while the Star Fox team was on Sauria, Corneria City was hit with a full-scale attack by the Aparoids, leaving it and its fleet devastated.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite video game|quote='''Pepper:''' Everyone, heed closely what I am about to say. While you were on Sauria, a colossal aparoid armada appeared. The majority of the Cornerian defense fleet...was decimated. |title=Star Fox Assault |developer=Namco|date=February 14, 2005|Mission 7 Prelude}}&lt;/ref&gt; Fox, with the help of Star Wolf, who arrived to assist in defeating a common enemy, is able to take out most of the attacking Aparoids. They soon find out, though, that [[General Pepper]]'s ship(with the General inside being taken over as well) had been taken over by the Aparoids, and has started to attack Fox. However, General Pepper insists that Fox destroys the ship and himself.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite video game|quote='''Pepper:''' This is my final request. Destroy this ship, destroy me! |title=Star Fox Assault |developer=Namco}}&lt;/ref&gt; Fox is able to take down the ship with his plasma cannon and Peppy saves Pepper by using his Arwing. After the battle, the Star Fox team heads for a large [[space station]] above Corneria, the Orbital Gate, which is used for warping to other planets. Before they are able to travel to the Aparoid homeworld, they are forced to defend it, with the help of Star Wolf again, from a series of various Aparoid missiles. They eventually destroy the missiles, just in time for Beltino Toad to finish creating a program that will destroy the Aparoids.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite video game|quote='''Beltino:''' We just finished the self-destruct program too. |title=Star Fox Assault |developer=Namco}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Once the Star Fox team reaches the Aparoid Homeworld, they realize that the entry to the core of the planet is blocked by a base and a large shield. Though the Star Fox Team is able to infiltrate the base and destroy a large amount of Aparoids, and the first shield, a second shield is formed and laser power is useless against it.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite video game|quote='''Slippy''': The energy is forming a shield! Laser power's gonna be useless! |title=Star Fox Assault |developer=Namco}}&lt;/ref&gt; However, the ''Great Fox'' - damaged by the Aparoids - appears and destroys the base.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite video game|quote='''ROB''': Extreme Impairment. Main hull will not survive more damage. / '''Peppy''': Who cares? Divert all energy to the main guns! Fire!! |title=Star Fox Assault |developer=Namco}}&lt;/ref&gt; Peppy and ROB ram the ''Great Fox'' into the shield and open it long enough for the team to get through before it explodes.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite video game|quote='''Fox:''' Enough! Peppy's opened a road for us. We've got to move on...without him. So, come on, come on, let's move! |title=Star Fox Assault |developer=Namco}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The team enters the core of the planet, with Star Wolf showing up again to help them. Right before they reach the Queen, they are attacked by an extremely durable swarm of Aparoids. Wolf, Leon, and Panther decide to distract them to allow Fox to proceed onwards to the Queen's lair.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite video game|quote='''Wolf:''' We'll distract 'em...you guys take out the queen! Leon, Panther, let's go! |title=Star Fox Assault |developer=Namco}}&lt;/ref&gt; The team confronts the [[Aparoid Queen]], who uses the voices of Peppy, General Pepper, Pigma, and [[James McCloud|Fox's father]] in an attempt to deceive them into joining her.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite video game|quote='''Peppy:''' Give in. This is not sacrifice...it is evolution. / '''???:''' Fox... / '''Fox:''' Dad!? |title=Star Fox Assault |developer=Namco}}&lt;/ref&gt; The team ignores her pleas, and fight her until Fox is able to shoot the program inside of her. However, the queen is able to repress it, and attempts to escape.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite video game|quote='''Krystal:''' Is the self-destruct program working? / '''Slippy:''' It should be working, but the queen's suppressing it! |title=Star Fox Assault |developer=Namco}}&lt;/ref&gt; Slippy informs Fox that if he does not destroy her and launch the program, the queen will create an [[antibody]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite video game|quote='''Slippy:''' This is bad. If she escapes, she'll create an anti-body! |title=Star Fox: Assault |developer=Namco}}&lt;/ref&gt; Fox drives a missile into the queen's heart which then explodes, killing her. The program launches, and the Aparoids go into self activated meltdown and are killed. The team escapes from the core of the homeworld, and soon discover that ROB and Peppy are still alive in an escape pod.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite video game|quote='''Falco:''' Hey, could that be...No! It couldn't! / '''Peppy:''' Hey, you're all OK! Whew! That was hairy. I promise I'm really going to retire after this. |title=Star Fox Assault |developer=Namco|date=February 14, 2005|level=Ending sequence}}&lt;/ref&gt; Fox mentions the possibility of Star Wolf's escape.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite video game|quote='''Krystal:''' Pepper is all right as well? / '''Fox:''' Yeah...it's possible. And Wolf's team |title=Star Fox Assault |developer=Namco|date=February 14, 2005|level=Ending sequence}}&lt;/ref&gt; The game ends with Fox thanking the team for their efforts.

==Development==
''Star Fox: Assault'' was first announced on May 8, 2002. It had a tentative release date of April 2003 for Japan, and would be developed by the same employees who worked on ''[[Ace Combat 2]]'' at Namco.&lt;ref name=&quot;arcade&quot;/&gt; New information about the game didn't show up until a short video [[montage (film)|montage]] at 2003's [[E3 (Electronic Entertainment Expo)|E3]] in [[Los Angeles, California|Los Angeles]], which showcased the game's [[first-person shooter|first-person]] perspective.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |title=Arwing Landing Gallery - Star Fox Assault/06 |publisher=Arwinglanding.net |url=http://arwinglanding.net/gallery/displayimage.php?album=14&amp;pos=5 |accessdate=2006-09-04}}&lt;/ref&gt; According to ''Electronic Gaming Monthly'', the video was booed by viewers, and ''EGM'' itself said the video was &quot;remarkably unimpressive&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |year=2003 |title=Electronic Gaming Monthly |date=August 2003 |issue=169 |publisher=Ziff Davis Media Inc. |page=30}}&lt;/ref&gt;

During development, the game had the working title: ''Star Fox Armada'',&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |title=GC Soft / Star Fox: Armada |url=http://www.nintendo.co.jp/n10/e3/gcsoft/starfox/index.html |publisher=Nintendo |accessdate=3 August 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt; but eventually came to be known as ''Star Fox: Assault''.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |title=Star Fox Title Change |publisher=IGN |url=http://cube.ign.com/articles/561/561504p1.html| accessdate=2006-07-28}}&lt;/ref&gt;
In 2003, the game was intended to be multi player oriented, and the ground missions of the game had a control scheme similar to the on-foot multi player mode in ''[[Star Fox 64]]''.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |title=Star Fox Assault Preview |publisher=IGN |url=http://cube.ign.com/articles/402/402539p1.html| accessdate=2007-01-31}}&lt;/ref&gt;

At 2004's [[Electronic Entertainment Expo|E3]], ''EGM'', the same magazine that wrote poorly about it a year before, wrote a follow-up that said the game looked &quot;much better than...a year ago&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|year=2004 |title=Electronic Gaming Monthly |date=August 2004 |issue=181 |publisher=Ziff Davis Media Inc. |page=84}}&lt;/ref&gt; ''Assault'' was scheduled for a November 2004 release, but was delayed to the beginning of 2005.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |title=Star Fox Flies into Next Year |publisher=IGN |url=http://cube.ign.com/articles/538/538831p1.html |accessdate=2006-09-14}}&lt;/ref&gt;

''Assault'' uses [[Game Middleware|middleware]] provided by the Japanese company [[CRI Middleware]] as a [[game engine]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |title=Middleware: CRI |publisher=MobyGames |url=http://www.mobygames.com/game-group/middleware-cri/ |accessdate=2006-08-28}}&lt;/ref&gt; Yoshie Arakawa and Yoshinori Kanemoto provided ''Assault'' with a musical score and sound effects with the music performed by the Tokyo New City Orchestra.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |title=Game Credits for Star Fox Assault |publisher=MobyGames |url=http://www.mobygames.com/game/gamecube/star-fox-assault/credits |accessdate=2006-09-14}}&lt;/ref&gt; Most of the score pieces use themes from ''[[Star Fox 64]]'', composed by [[Koji Kondo]] and Hajime Wakai.

==Reception==
''Star Fox: Assault'' was met with mixed reviews and currently has an average score of 71% on [[Game Rankings]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |title=Star Fox: Assault Reviews |publisher=GameRankings |url=http://www.gamerankings.com/htmlpages2/561297.asp |accessdate=2006-08-28}}&lt;/ref&gt; Some complaints were aimed at the control scheme during on-foot portions; [[IGN]] worded the complaint as &quot;ground missions suffering from sloppy control&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;IGN&quot;&gt;{{cite web |title=Star Fox Assault Review |publisher=IGN |url=http://cube.ign.com/articles/584/584886p1.html |accessdate=2006-07-27}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[GameSpot]] noted that the multiplayer portion of the game has little lasting value, an annoyance that IGN felt as well. IGN went on to say the [[level design|design]] was too simplistic.&lt;ref name=&quot;IGN&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |title=Star Fox: Assault for GameCube Review |publisher=GameSpot |url=http://www.gamespot.com/gamecube/action/starfoxworkingtitle/review.html |accessdate=2006-07-27}}&lt;/ref&gt; However, IGN noted that being able to switch between the Arwing and Landmaster at will was a &quot;welcome addition&quot;. In ''Electronic Gaming Monthly'', two of the reviewers gave it an 8.0 out of 10. [[Play (UK magazine)|Play Magazine]] gave the game 8 out of 10. [[Thunderbolt (website)|Thunderbolt]] gave it 9 out of 10. Kevin Gifford said that &quot;the game is aimed less at the ''Mario'' club and more toward the hardcore crowd&quot;. ''EGM'' also noted that ''Assault'' had an epic feel, helped by a great soundtrack.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |title=Star Fox: Assault GC Review |publisher=1UP |url=http://www.1up.com/do/reviewPage?cId=2007390&amp;did=2 |accessdate=2006-07-27}} {{Dead link|date=September 2010|bot=H3llBot}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The game became enough of a commercial success for it to be included in Nintendo's [[Player's Choice]] line, which also includes ''[[Star Fox 64]]'' and ''[[Star Fox Adventures]]''.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |title=Star Fox Assault |publisher=Nintendo.com |url=http://www.nintendo.com/gamemini?gameid=0b746eac-10e2-4bf6-8a49-9d3441139961&amp; |accessdate=2006-08-11| archiveurl = http://web.archive.org/web/20060706212133/http://www.nintendo.com/gamemini?gameid=0b746eac-10e2-4bf6-8a49-9d3441139961&amp;| archivedate = July 6, 2006}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==References==
{{reflist|colwidth=30em}}

==External links==
{{wikiquote}}
* {{Official website|http://www.starfox.com/assault}}
* [http://www.nintendo.co.jp/ngc/gf7j/ Official Japanese website]
* {{imdb title|0446037}}
* {{StrategyWiki}}

{{Star Fox series}}

[[Category:2005 video games]]
[[Category:Nintendo GameCube games]]
[[Category:Nintendo GameCube-only games]]
[[Category:Namco games]]
[[Category:Star Fox video games|Assault]]
[[Category:Video games featuring anthropomorphic characters]]

[[es:Star Fox: Assault]]
[[fr:Star Fox: Assault]]
[[ja:スターフォックス アサルト]]
[[pt:Star Fox: Assault]]
[[ru:Star Fox: Assault]]
[[fi:Star Fox: Assault]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
