<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="1398206" ns="0" title="DSniff"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{lowercase|title=dsniff}}
{{Infobox software
|name = dsniff
|developer = [[Dug Song]]
|latest_release_date ={{release date and age|2000|12|17}}
|latest release version = 2.3
|operating_system = [[Unix-like]]
|genre = [[Packet sniffer]]
|license = 
|website = [http://www.monkey.org/~dugsong/dsniff/ www.monkey.org/~dugsong/dsniff/]
}}
'''Dsniff''' is a password [[sniffer]] written by Dug Song and a package of utilities that parse many different application protocols and extract interesting information.
dsniff, filesnarf, mailsnarf, msgsnarf, urlsnarf, and webspy passively monitor a network for interesting data (passwords, e-mail, files, etc.). arpspoof, dnsspoof, and macof facilitate the interception of network traffic normally unavailable to an attacker (e.g, due to layer-2 switching). sshmitm and webmitm implement active monkey-in-the-middle attacks against redirected SSH and HTTPS sessions by exploiting weak bindings in ad-hoc PKI.[http://www.monkey.org/~dugsong/dsniff/]
&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|author=Christopher R. Russel|title=Penetration Testing with dsniff|url=http://www.ouah.org/dsniffintr.htm}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Overview==
'''dsniff''' is a [[packet sniffer]] and set of traffic analysis tools written by Dug Song. The application sniffs usernames and passwords, web pages being visited, contents of email, etc. Dsniff, as the name implies, is a network [[sniffer]], but designed for different testings. Furthermore, it can be used to crush the normal behavior of switched networks and cause network traffic from other hosts on the same network segment to be visible, not just traffic involving the host dsniff is running on.

It handles [[FTP]], [[Telnet]], [[SMTP]], [[HTTP]], [[Post Office Protocol|POP]], poppass, [[NNTP]], [[IMAP]], [[Simple Network Management Protocol|SNMP]], [[LDAP]], [[Rlogin]], [[Routing information protocol|RIP]], [[OSPF]], [[PPTP]] [[Challenge-handshake authentication protocol|MS-CHAP]], [[Network File System (protocol)|NFS]], [[VRRP]], [[Network Information Service|YP/NIS]], [[SOCKS]], [[X11]], [[Concurrent Versions System|CVS]], [[IRC]], [[AOL Instant Messenger|AIM]], [[ICQ]], [[Napster]], [[PostgreSQL]], [[Meeting Maker]], [[Citrix ICA]], [[PcAnywhere|Symantec pc Anywhere]], NAI [[Sniffer]], [[Microsoft]] [[Server Message Block|SMB]], [[Oracle Corporation|Oracle]] [[Oracle Database|SQL*Net]], [[Sybase]] and [[Microsoft SQL]] protocols.

The name &quot;dsniff&quot; refers both to the package as well as an included tool. &quot;dsniff&quot; the tool decodes passwords sent in [[cleartext]] across a [[Network switch|switched]] or unswitched [[Ethernet]] network. Its [[man page]] explains that he wrote dsniff with &quot;honest intentions - to audit my own network, and to demonstrate the insecurity of cleartext network protocols.&quot; He then requests, &quot;Please do not abuse this software.&quot;

These are the files that are configured in dsniff folder '''/etc/dsniff/'''

'''/etc/dsniff/dnsspoof.hosts     --&gt;''' Sample hosts file. [http://linux.die.net/man/8/dnsspoof]
If no hostfile is specified, replies will forged for all address queries on the LAN with an answer of the local machine’s IP address.  

/'''etc/dsniff/dsniff.magic        --&gt;''' Network protocol magic

'''/etc/dsniff/dsniff.services	--&gt;''' Default trigger table

The man page for dsniff explains all the flags. To learn more about using dsniff you can explore the Linux man page. [http://linux.die.net/man/8/dsniff]

This is a list of descriptions for the various dsniff programs. This text belong to the
dsniff “README” written by the author Dug Song.

{| class=&quot;wikitable&quot; border=&quot;1&quot;
|-
! Name
! Description
|-
| arpspoofing [[ARP spoofing]]
| Redirect packets from a target host (or all hosts) on the LAN intended for another local host by forging ARP replies. This is an extremely effective way of sniffing traffic on a switch. kernel IP forwarding (or a userland program which accomplishes the same, e.g. fragrouter :-) must be turned on ahead of time.
|-
| dnsspoof
| Forge replies to arbitrary DNS address / pointer queries on the LAN. this is useful in bypassing hostname-based access controls, or in implementing a variety of man-in-the middle attacks (HTTP, HTTPS, SSH, Kerberos, etc).
|-
| [[tcpkill]]	
| Kills specified in-progress [[Transmission Control Protocol|TCP]] connections (useful for libnids-based applications which require a full [[Transmission Control Protocol|TCP]] 3-whs for TCB creation). Can be effective for [[bandwidth control]]. 
|}
'''See also:''' filesnarf [http://www.ouah.org/dsniffintr.htm], macof [http://www.ouah.org/dsniffintr.htm], mailsnarf [http://www.ouah.org/dsniffintr.htm], msgsnarf [http://www.ouah.org/dsniffintr.htm], sshmitm [http://www.ouah.org/dsniffintr.htm], tcpnice [http://www.ouah.org/dsniffintr.htm], urlsnarf [http://www.ouah.org/dsniffintr.htm] webmitm [http://www.ouah.org/dsniffintr.htm], webspy [http://www.ouah.org/dsniffintr.htm].
 	

Other tools included with the package include:
*&quot;webspy&quot;, a program which intercepts URLs sent by a specific IP address and directs your web browser to connect to the same URL.  This results in your browser opening up the same web pages as the target being sniffed.
*&quot;sshmitm&quot; and &quot;webmitm&quot;, programs designed to intercept [[Secure shell|SSH]] version 1 communications and web traffic respectively with a [[Man in the middle attack|man-in-the-middle attack]]
*&quot;msgsnarf&quot;, a program designed to intercept [[Instant Messenger]] and [[IRC]] conversations
*&quot;macof&quot;, a program designed to break poorly-designed [[Network switch|Ethernet switch]]es by flooding them with packets with bogus [[MAC address]]es ([[MAC flooding]]).

----

'''Bandwidth Control'''

Tomasz Chmielewski's Bandwidth−Limiting−HOWTO [http://tldp.org/HOWTO/Bandwidth-Limiting-HOWTO/index.html] is a clear reference document for [[Class based queueing|CBQ]] (Class Based Queueing). [[Class based queueing|CBQ]] will let you to allocate bandwidth to particular network services. To learn more about [[Class based queueing|CBQ]] read more information in the link mentioned above.

==References==
&lt;references /&gt;
*[1] Song, Dug. &quot;dsniff.&quot; http://www.monkey.org/~dugsong/dsniff/

*[3] Dsniff - Linux man page, http://linux.die.net/man/8/dsniff

*[4] Dsniff most recent version 2.3, http://dsniff.darwinports.com/

*[6] Dunston, Duane, Linuxsecurity.com, “And away we spoof!!!” http://www.linuxsecurity.com/docs/PDF/dsniff-n-mirror.pdf

==External links==
*[http://www.monkey.org/~dugsong/dsniff/ Official website]
*[http://www.monkey.org/~dugsong/dsniff/faq.html dsniff FAQ]

==See also==
*[[Comparison of packet analyzers]]
*[[Network tap]]

{{DEFAULTSORT:Dsniff}}
[[Category:Network analyzers]]
[[Category:Password cracking software]]
[[Category:Open source network management software]]

[[fr:DSniff]]
[[ka:DSniff]]
[[pl:DSniff]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
