<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="1399555" ns="0" title="Florida Gulf Coast University"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Other uses|Gulf University (disambiguation){{!}}Gulf University}}
{{Infobox university
|name              =Florida Gulf Coast University
|native_name       =
|image_name        =FGCU logo.png
|image_size        =
|caption           =
|latin_name        =
|motto             =
|tagline           =
|established       =1991
|vision            =&quot;Florida Gulf Coast University will achieve national prominence in undergraduate education with expanding recognition for selected graduate programs.&quot;
|type              =[[public university|Public]]
|affiliation       =
|calendar          =[[Semester]]
|endowment         =US$57.1 million&lt;ref&gt;http://www.news-press.com/article/20110531/NEWS0104/110531040/1002/NEWS01/FGCU-portfolio-surpasses-57-million?odyssey=nav|head&lt;/ref&gt;
|debt              =
|rector            =
|officer_in_charge =
|chairman          =
|chancellor        =
|president         =[[Wilson G. Bradshaw]]
|vice-president    =
|superintendent    =
|provost           =Ronald Toll
|vice_chancellor   =
|principal         =
|dean              =
|director          =
|head_label        =
|head              =
|faculty           =500 total: 336 instructional and administrative faculty, 164 adjunct faculty (2006)
|staff             =681
|students          =12,024&lt;ref name=&quot;fgcu.edu&quot;&gt;http://www.fgcu.edu/Foundation/Files/09-10_Annual_Report.pdf&lt;/ref&gt;
|undergrad         =10,333&lt;ref name=&quot;fgcu.edu&quot;/&gt;
|postgrad          =1,150&lt;ref name=&quot;fgcu.edu&quot;/&gt;
|doctoral          =
|divinity          =
|residents         =
|other             =541&lt;ref name=&quot;fgcu.edu&quot;/&gt;
|profess           =
|alumni            =
|city              =[[Fort Myers]]
|state             =Florida
|province          =
|country           =USA
|address           =10501 FGCU Blvd South &lt;br&gt; Fort Myers, FL  33965-6565
|telephone         =(239)590-1000
|coordinates       =
|campus            =[[Suburb|Suburban Area]] &lt;br&gt; 760 acres (3.08 km²), of which  400 acres (1.6 km2) is dedicated as a nature preserve
|free_label        =
|free              =
|sports            =
|colors            =[[Cobalt blue|Cobalt Blue]] and [[Emerald (color)|Emerald Green]], and as an accent, [[Old Gold]] {{color box|#0047AB}}{{color box|#50C878}}{{color box|#CFB53B}}
|colours           =
|nickname          = [[Eagle]]s
|mascot            = Azul the Eagle
|fightsong         =
|athletics         =[[National Collegiate Athletic Association|NCAA]] [[Division I (NCAA)|Division I]], [[Atlantic Sun Conference|ASC]]; 6 men's varsity teams / 9 women's
|affiliations      =[[AACSB]], [[Southern Association of Colleges and Schools|SACS]], [[SUSF]]
|nobel_laureates   =
|website           = [http://www.fgcu.edu/ fgcu.edu] 
|logo              =
|publictransit     =
|footnotes         =
}}

'''Florida Gulf Coast University''', also known as '''FGCU''', is a [[coeducational]] public university located just south of the [[Southwest Florida International Airport]] in the [[South Fort Myers, Florida|South Fort Myers]] region of [[unincorporated area|unincorporated]] [[Lee County, Florida|Lee County]], [[Florida]], [[United States]].  The university belongs to the 11-campus [[State University System of Florida]].  FGCU competes in the [[Atlantic Sun Conference]] in [[Division I (NCAA)|Division I]] sports and is accredited by the Commission on Colleges of the [[Southern Association of Colleges and Schools]] to award [[Associate's Degree|associate's]], [[Bachelor's Degree|bachelor's]], master's and [[Doctorate|doctoral]] degrees.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.sacscoc.org/details.asp?instid=30580 Commission on Colleges]&lt;/ref&gt;

==History==
===Establishment===
The school was established by then-governor [[Lawton Chiles]] in 1991, although the site of the university was not chosen until 1992, and construction pushed back even further still (until 1995). The school first held classes in August 1997.  Roy McTarnaghan was named as the university's founding president.  In August 1998, the university completed its first phase of student housing, which featured traditional dorms in which two students shared a single room and cohabited together.  On May 1, 1999, McTarnaghan announced his decision to step down from his position as [[University president|President]] of FGCU.

===Expansion and Growth===
[[File:Cohencenter.png|thumb|The Cohen Center, FGCU's student union.]]
In July 1999, William C. Merwin was named as FGCU's President.  Merwin brought with him a different vision for FGCU.  Instead of being a commuter school, which dealt mostly with non-traditional students who took classes online,  he envisioned a traditional four-year university that leveraged modern-day technology to enhance both the learning and day to day experience of the FGCU student body.  New [[apartment]]-style [[Dormitory|dorms]] were constructed, which allowed for FGCU students to have a greater degree of privacy.  Every student would have his or her own room and there would be a kitchen that would be shared by the four other students in the apartment.  The internet was not seen as the exclusive means by which students took classes, but as an additional supplement to the traditional classroom environment.

Under the new university structure, students would attend small, in-person classes that used an online system to increase communication between the professor and the students.   Merwin engaged in an aggressive fund raising effort in order to make the construction of the highest quality facilities a reality for FGCU.  In an eight year period, he raised more than $250&amp;nbsp;million for the university and engaged in a rapid expansion of the student and faculty populations.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last=Dillon |first=Liam |url=http://www.naplesnews.com/news/2009/mar/14/donations-endowments-take-hit-local-colleges-econo/ |title=Donations, endowments take a hit at local colleges as economy sours » Naples Daily News |publisher=Naplesnews.com |date=2010-07-08 |accessdate=2010-07-15}}&lt;/ref&gt;  Multiple state-of-the-art buildings were constructed, including: Lutgert College of Business, Holmes Hall (U.A. Whitaker School of Engineering), Whitaker Hall, Academic Building 5, the [[student activity center|student union]] building, [[Alico Arena]] and a massive expansion of on-campus housing.  As a result of the fund raising and aggressive construction, student enrollment at FGCU has annually increased in double digits, from approximately 2,000 students in its first year to over 12,000 today.{{when?|date=August 2011}} Over the next three years,{{when?|date=August 2011}} undergraduate enrollment is expected to increase to more than 15,000 students.  Later in 2007, [[Wilson G. Bradshaw]] was named as the university's third president.

===Recent History===
Under Bradshaw, the years from 2007 to 2010 also saw an aggressive expansion of the campus facilities.  Two new dorm buildings that could house over 800 additional student were built, and two more large dorm buildings are currently under construction.  There was also a {{convert|24,700|sqft|m2|adj=on}} expansion of the fine arts building, the construction of the {{convert|60,000|sqft|m2|adj=on}} academic building 7, the addition of a solar panel field, a {{convert|20,000|sqft|m2|adj=on}} expansion of the student union building, the purchase/donation of more than {{convert|530|acre|km2}} of land and the acquisition of the college club apartments.

Bradshaw also began a serious exploration as to the possibility of football at FGCU.  He commissioned an independent consulting firm to explore what the costs of football would be at the university.  The consulting firm revealed it would cost as much as $144 million, and would not be feasible for the university in the near future.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.nbc-2.com/Global/story.asp?S=13865090&lt;/ref&gt;

==Campus==
&lt;!-- Deleted image removed: [[File:FGCU.jpg|right|thumb| The Library Annex and Reed Hall from left to right.]] --&gt;
FGCU's campus is located south of Fort Myers, Florida and {{convert|21|mi|km}} from [[Naples, Florida]]. FGCU is located on {{convert|760|acre|km2}} in [[Southwest Florida]].  The campus site was originally donated by the Alico corporation after the Board of Regents reviewed 22 prospective sites.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url = http://www.naplesnews.com/news/2007/aug/20/fgcu_past_board_regents_selects_alico_university_s/ | title = FGCU past: Board of Regents selects Alico as university site | accessdate = 2009-10-07}}&lt;/ref&gt; The campus has two entrances: the main entrance which features the &quot;Florida Gulf Coast University&quot; sign, and the north entrance.  Both roads connect to FGCU Boulevard which is a circular road encompassing all of the academic buildings.  The center of the campus is considered the &quot;academic core&quot;: it is located over {{convert|150|acre|km2}} and contains all of the academic research and parking buildings throughout the university.  There are two separate housing villages located on periphery of the campus: North Lake and South Lake Village.  North Lake Village overlooks a massive lakes which allows for students to engage in recreational activities such as boating, and water skiing.  North Lake is unique because of its apartment style housing.  South Lake Village is located on the opposite end of the campus and currently has two five story buildings which features individual rooms for all of the students.

===Growth and New Construction===
[[File:FGCULibrary.png|left|thumb|FGCU's Library Complex]]
The {{convert|63000|sqft|m2|sing=on}} Lutgert College of Business building and the {{convert|70000|sqft|m2|sing=on}} Holmes Hall – U.A. Whitaker School of Engineering Building have recently{{when|date=July 2011}} been built. In addition, the {{convert|40000|sqft|m2|sing=on}} Herbert J. Sugden Hall – Resort &amp; Hospitality Management Building has been completed.  The university recently{{when|date=July 2011}} completed {{convert|60000|sqft|m2|sing=on}} Academic Building 7 for the College of Arts and Sciences and has also completed construction of Academic building 8:  a $24&amp;nbsp;million, {{convert|60000|sqft|m2|sing=on}} building for use by the College of Health Professions.&lt;ref name=&quot;Academic Building 8 Fact Sheet&quot;&gt;{{cite web | url = http://www.fgcu.edu/facilities/AB8_Fact_Sheet_CM.pdf | title = Facilities Program Fact Sheet | accessdate = 2009-11-02 | publisher=Florida Gulf Coast University}} {{Dead link|date=September 2010|bot=H3llBot}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Academic Building 8 Details&quot;&gt;{{cite web | url = http://www.fgcu.edu/facilities/AB8_Facilities_Program.pdf | title = Facilities Program – Academic Building 8| accessdate = 2009-11-02 | publisher=Florida Gulf Coast University}} {{Dead link|date=September 2010|bot=H3llBot}}&lt;/ref&gt;  Other recently completed construction projects on the campus include the {{convert|20000|sqft|m2|sing=on}} expansion of the student union building, the {{convert|24700|sqft|m2|sing=on}} addition to the fine arts building (which will be a {{convert|58000|sqft|m2|sing=on}} addition at build-out)&lt;ref name=&quot;Fine Arts Building Project&quot;&gt;{{cite web | url = http://www.fgcu.edu/facilities/FineArts2FactSheet.pdf | title = Project Fact Sheet – Fine Arts 2 | accessdate = 2009-11-02 | publisher=Florida Gulf Coast University}} {{Dead link|date=September 2010|bot=H3llBot}}&lt;/ref&gt; and the construction of one of the largest solar panel fields at any university.  The university recently{{when|date=July 2011}} broke ground on the construction of new dormitories which will house an additional 800 students on campus.&lt;ref name=&quot;FGCU Solar Project&quot;&gt;{{cite web | url = http://www.fgcusolar.com/home | title = FGCU Solar – Home | accessdate = 2009-11-02 | publisher=Florida Gulf Coast University}}&lt;/ref&gt; The university has also announced that they will build a shared-use facility at the Naples Botanical Gardens.&lt;ref name=&quot;Facilities Planning&quot;&gt;{{cite web | title = FGCU-Facilities Planning | publisher=Florida Gulf Coast University | url = http://www.fgcu.edu/facilities/progress.html | accessdate = 2008-08-12}} {{Dead link|date=September 2010|bot=H3llBot}}&lt;/ref&gt;  In 2008, FGCU became one of the first academic institutions in the country to include the [[metric system]] on its roadsigns.&lt;ref name=&quot;Metric System Road Signs at FGCU&quot;&gt;{{cite web | url = http://www.fgcu.edu/crm/pressrelease.asp?id=20098 | title = FGCU Professor Contributes to Metric Conversion of Speed Limit Signs on Campus | accessdate = 2009-10-07 | publisher=Florida Gulf Coast University}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Acquisition of Additional Land and Creation of Satellite Campuses===
[[File:AcademiccoreFGCU.jpg|thumb|FGCU's Academic Core]]
There are three other satellite campus locations:  Naples, the [[Cape Coral]] Center and the Charlotte Center in [[Punta Gorda, Florida|Punta Gorda]], which are yet to be expanded.  FGCU recently{{when|date=July 2011}} purchased 12 acres adjacent to the main campus from Miramar Development for $3.8 million.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.naplesnews.com/news/2011/jan/18/fgcu-campus-purchase-buy-12-acre-land-Miromar/&lt;/ref&gt;  The FGCU board of trustees voted in January 2010 to assume ownership of {{convert|500|acre|km2}} in Buckingham.  Located between East Fort Myers and Lehigh Acres, the land already contains over 60 buildings and housing for 300 people. Originally, the piece of land was controlled by the Florida Environmental Protection Agency, but was abandoned and given to FGCU.

In 2007, the university purchased the former Bonita Beach Plantation Resort in [[Bonita Springs, Florida|Bonita Springs]] for use as a marine research laboratory.  The Norm and Nancy Vester Marine and Environmental Science Research Field Station site has 10 boat slips and is located on [[Estero Bay, Florida|Estero Bay]].  The site includes laboratories, offices, apartments for visiting researchers and a classroom.&lt;ref name=&quot;Vester Station&quot;&gt;{{cite web | url = http://www.fgcu.edu/CWI/files/Vester_Field_Station_-_Pinnacle_Summer_2008.pdf | title = Water water everywhere | accessdate = 2009-11-02 | publisher=Pinnacle Magazine, alumni publication of Florida Gulf Coast University}}&lt;/ref&gt;  In addition, the university has been preparing plans for a research center at the [[Rookery Bay National Estuarine Research Reserve]] which is mid-way between [[Naples, Florida|Naples]] and [[Marco Island]].&lt;ref name=&quot;FGCU Bonita Waterfront&quot;&gt;{{cite web | last = Bonner | first = Jessie |title = FGCU purchases Bonita Springs waterfront property for marine lab | publisher=Naples News | url = http://www.naplesnews.com/news/2007/Jul/09/fgcu_purchases_bonita_springs_waterfront_property_/ | accessdate = 2008-08-12}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In October 2006, a 12-person panel of leading [[Charlotte County, Florida|Charlotte County]] citizens was tasked with selecting the future location of an FGCU-Charlotte Satellite Center.  There were five respondents to the Invitation to Negotiate (ITN).  Each respondent met the minimum criteria of the ITN (although one was later removed from the process for falling short on (2) of the requirements) of {{convert|150|acre|km2}} of land, $5M in cash to the university.  In a unanimous vote by the panel (notably including Charlotte County Board of Commissioners Chairman, Tom Moore), only one was chosen, Hudson Sun-River. In their proposal to the FGCU, Hudson Sun-River offered $5M in cash, 150ac of land (located within their 2,458ac 'University Village' master-planned development), $750,000 in annual operating funds and up to $70M of built-out infrastructure.

===Environmental Sustainability===
Since its founding, {{convert|400|acre|km2}} on the main campus has been set aside for environmental preservation.  FGCU also has constructed a number of lakes on the campus which are home to large numbers of wild life; the lakes also help promote the ecology of the area.  Environmental sustainability is the principal goal expressed in the university charter.  Academic Building 7, the new facility housing science laboratories and classrooms for the College of arts and sciences, achieved platinum certification, the highest level awarded by the U.S. Green Building Council’s Leadership in Energy and Environmental Design.  The University’s {{convert|15|acre|m2|adj=on}} solar field supplies about 85 percent of the energy needed to operate Holmes and Lutgert halls as well as Academic Building 7, reducing FGCu’s reliance on Florida power &amp; light Co. by 18 percent. An ice thermal storage plant sends chilled water through an underground loop that cools campus buildings, saving more than $1.64 million over 
five years. The newest 400-bed residence halls, Biscayne and Everglades, get hot water from rooftop solar tanks.

==Academics==
The Fall 2010 acceptance rate for FGCU is 60.4 percent, more selective than previous terms.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.news-press.com/article/20110117/NEWS0104/110116034/FGCU-becoming-regional-favorite&lt;/ref&gt; [[US News]] ranks FGCU as first-tier among Regional Universities in the [[Southern United States|South]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://colleges.usnews.rankingsandreviews.com/best-colleges/fort-myers-fl/fgcu-32553 |title=Florida Gulf Coast University - Best College - Education - US News |publisher=Colleges.usnews.rankingsandreviews.com |date=2010-08-16 |accessdate=2010-08-24}}&lt;/ref&gt; The Lutgert College of business is an [[Association to Advance Collegiate Schools of Business|AACSB]] accredited institution, offering undergraduate degrees in [[Accountancy|Accounting]], [[Computer Information Systems]], Economics, [[Finance]], [[Management]] and [[Marketing]].  In addition, the college offers the following graduate degrees:  Accounting and Taxation, Computer Information Systems and [[Master of Business Administration|Business Administration]] (both traditional and executive).&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.fgcu.edu/cob/ |title=FGCU Lutgert College of Business |publisher=Fgcu.edu |date=2010-06-24 |accessdate=2010-07-15}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Princeton Review]] also cites it as one of the top 301 business schools in the country.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url = http://www.naplesnews.com/news/2009/oct/29/higher-education-briefs-lutgert-college-business-n/ | title = Higher education briefs: Lutgert College of Business named among 301 best in nation | publisher=Naples Daily News| accessdate = 2009-11-02}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Hospitality Management]] is a popular major on campus, with students getting the opportunity to gain supervised field work experience at one of many resorts in the area. [[Professional Golf Association|Professional Golf Management]] is a unique program with limited access, much like the [[Bachelor of Science in Nursing|Nursing]], [[Music education|Music]] and [[Athletic Training]] programs. FGCU has a unique requirement prior to graduation, University Colloquium, as it was built in an ecologically sensitive area. The aim of this Colloquium is to educate graduates on the importance of ecology and [[Environmental preservation|preservation]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.fgcu.edu/Colloquium/index.html |title=Colloquium |publisher=Fgcu.edu |date=1997-01-15 |accessdate=2010-07-15}}&lt;/ref&gt;  FGCU recently{{when|date=July 2011}} announced the addition of a real estate undergraduate degree to begin in fall of 2012&lt;ref&gt;http://www.review.net/section/detail/wednesdays-cup-biz-school-launches-real-estate-major/&lt;/ref&gt;  As of 2011, the student body carries an average GPA of 2.97.&lt;ref name=&quot;naplesnews.com&quot;&gt;http://www.naplesnews.com/news/2010/nov/27/fgcu-student-athletes-gpa-ncaa-division-chris-sale/&lt;/ref&gt;

The academic demands and qualifications of FGCU students have continued to increase over the years.  
{| class=&quot;wikitable&quot; style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;
|| '''Test Score or GPA 2011'''&lt;ref name=&quot;naplesnews.com&quot;/&gt; ||'''Score'''||
|-
| Average ACT (out of a possible 36)
| 21.9
|-
| Average SAT (out of a possible 1600)
| 1032
|-
| Average High School GPA (out of 4.0)
| 3.35
|-
| Average College GPA
| 2.97
|-
|}

===Engineering Program===
FGCU also offers [[Civil engineering|Civil]], [[Environmental engineering|Environmental]], and [[Bioengineering]]. The first graduating classes of all three of these disciplines received their diplomas in May 2009. As of Fall 2010 FGCU's engineering program is ABET accredited. Holmes Hall was built primarily to facilitate the new Engineering program; however, [[Computer Science]] majors also use the building for their majors, and some nursing classes take place there as well. As of 2011 the engineering program has become a separate entity known as the UA Whitaker School of Engineering, and FGCU ranks with a 80 % passing rate on the Fundamentals of Engineering exam.

===Environmental Forensics===
The university is currently expanding its graduate offerings and is adding to its research capabilities, with an Environmental [[Forensic science|Forensics]] Facility or &quot;body farm&quot; in the works, under the direction of Dr. Heather Walsh-Haney. The Division of Justice Studies in the College of Professional Studies is in its 3rd year of offering a Master of Science in Criminal Forensic Studies. Students can choose to become qualified as a Forensic [[Professional practice of behavior analysis|Behavior Analyst]], under Dr. Duane Dobbert, or in Human Identity under Dr. Walsh-Haney.

===Death Investigator Concentration===
The Death Investigator concentration prepares students to work in the field as [[Forensic entomology#Medico-legal forensic entomology|medico-legal death investigators]] for [[Medical examiner|Medical examiner's]] offices, as well as crime scene investigators or law enforcement [[detective]]s. Those in Death Investigations specialize in Human Identity and Trauma Analysis. The Human and Trauma ID concentration, under the direction of [[forensic anthropology|forensic anthropologist]] Dr. Walsh-Haney, trains students to identify human remains through skeletal attributes, and analyze decomposed and skeletal remains for signs of [[Physical trauma|trauma]]. The forensic [[Behaviorism|behaviorist]] track offers students an opportunity to learn how to analyze the [[psychological]] aspect of crime scenes, specifically pertaining to [[pedophilia]].

===Colleges and Academic Divisions===
[[File:Metric System-Speed Limit Sign.JPG|thumb|Metric System-Speed Limit Sign posted on roads at FGCU]]
Florida Gulf Coast University academics are divided into six colleges.  These colleges include:
{| class=&quot;toccolours&quot;  style=&quot;float:center; margin-left:1em; font-size:95%; line-height:1.5em; width:500px;&quot;
! colspan=&quot;2&quot; style=&quot;text-align: center;&quot; | '''College/school founding'''&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.fgcu.edu/about.asp |title=About FGCU |publisher=Fgcu.edu |date= |accessdate=2010-07-15}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|-
| '''College/school''' || '''Year founded'''
|-
| colspan=&quot;4&quot; |&lt;hr&gt;
|-
| College of Arts and Sciences || 1995
|-
| College of Health Professions || 1997
|-
| College of Professional Studies || 1997
|-
| College of Education || 2001
|-
| U.A. Whitaker School of Engineering || 2005
|-
| Lutgert College of Business || 2008
|}

===Research===
In FGCU's inaugural year, under $3&amp;nbsp;million of research was funded.  By 2010, $14.4&amp;nbsp;million in funds were granted for research annually.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.fgcu.edu/orsp/&lt;/ref&gt;  Research institutes include: the Biotechnology Research Group, the Lucas Center for [[Real Estate]], Coastal Watershed Institute, Center for Environmental &amp; Sustainability Education, FGCU Center for Leadership and Innovation, Florida Institute of Government, Center for Positive Aging, Whitaker Center for Science, Mathematics, &amp; Technology Education, Institute for Youth and Justice Studies.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.fgcu.edu/orsp/ |title=Office of Research and Sponsored Programs |publisher=Fgcu.edu |date= |accessdate=2010-07-15}}&lt;/ref&gt;  Since FGCU first opened, the total funds awarded for research has amounted to $119&amp;nbsp;million.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.fgcu.edu/CRM/fastfacts.html/ |title=Community Relations and Marketing |publisher=Fgcu.edu |date= |accessdate=2010-07-15}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Tuition===
As a result of the economic recession, FGCU has had double digit tuition rate increases the past several years. {{Citation needed|date=February 2011}}

{|  style=&quot;text-align:center; float:right; margin-left:1em; margin:auto;&quot;  class=&quot;wikitable&quot;
|+ ''Tuition Fee Schedule Spring 2011''&lt;ref&gt;http://www.fgcu.edu/cashiers/tuition-and-fees.html&lt;/ref&gt;
|-
! &amp;nbsp; !! Undergraduate FL Resident Differential!!Undergraduate FL Resident No Differential !!Undergraduate Non FL Resident Differential!!Undergraduate Non FL Resident No Differential!!Graduate FL Resident  !! Graduate Non FL Resident !!
|-
! Tuition (per credit hour)
| $166.04||$153.24||$710.27||$697.47||$322.08||$1,117.08
|-
! ID Card Fee
| $10.00||$10.00||$10.00||$10.00||$10.00||$10.00
|-
! Repeat Surcharge (per credit hour)
| $163.38||$163.38||$163.38||$163.38||N/A||N/A
|}

FGCU remains less expensive than almost any other public university in the state of Florida.  The chart above illustrates the current tuition per credit hour for residents and non residents of the state of Florida.

==Student Enrollment and Demographics==

FGCU has a multitude of students from different backgrounds, ethnicities, and nationalities.

{| class=&quot;wikitable&quot; style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;
|| '''Ethnic enrollment, 2010'''&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.fgcu.edu/trustees/AgendaFile/2009/1-2009/BOTIS_1-2009.pdf] Retrieved on 2009-10-08.&lt;/ref&gt; ||'''Total Population'''||'''Percent'''||'''US Census'''
|-
|[[Native Americans in the United States|American Indian]]
| 93
| 0.8%
| 0.8%
|-
|[[Asian American]]
| 263
| 2.2%
| 4.3%
|-
|[[Black American|Black (non-Hispanic)]]
| 719 
| 6.0%
| 12.4%
|-
|[[Hispanic]]
| 1789
| 14.9%
| 14.7%
|-
|[[White American|White (non-Hispanic)]]
| 8873
| 73.7%
| 73.9%
|-
|International, Other
| 186
| 1.5%
|
|-
|Race/Ethnicity Unknown
| 124
| 1.0%
|
|-
|Total
| 12047
| 100%
| 100%
|}

==Athletics==
[[File:FGCU Eagle.PNG|thumb|right|Athletics logo]]

FGCU's athletics teams are known as the [[Florida Gulf Coast Eagles|Eagles]]. FGCU is currently undergoing a transition to [[NCAA Division I]] for all athletics programs; final notification is expected in late spring of 2011.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |title= FGCU closer than ever to Division 1 status |author= |url= http://www.nbc-2.com/Global/story.asp?S=13247263 |newspaper= Rishi Barrannbc-2.com |date= September 30, 2010 |accessdate=December 15, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; The Eagles currently compete in the Division I [[Atlantic Sun Conference]] (A-Sun), which they joined in 2007.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |title= After a rapid rise, how will FGCU sports grow in the next decade? |author= Seth Soffian|url=http://pqasb.pqarchiver.com/news_press/access/2117193881.html?FMT=ABS&amp;date=Aug+22%2C+2010 |newspaper= [[The News-Press]] |date= August 22, 2010 |accessdate=December 15, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;

FGCU intercollegiate athletics offers:
*men's and women's golf,
*men's and women's tennis,
*men's and women's basketball,
*women's softball,
*men's baseball,
*men's and women's cross country,
*women's volleyball,
*men's and women's soccer
*women's swimming and diving.
 
FGCU is a member of the National Collegiate Athletics Association (NCAA) Division I and a member of the Atlantic Sun Conference, as well as the Coastal Collegiate Swimming Association. FGCU plays its men's and women's basketball games at [[Alico Arena]] and its baseball games at [[Swanson Stadium]].

The average GPA of a student athlete at FGCU was 3.13 in the spring semester of 2010.&lt;ref name=&quot;naplesnews.com&quot;/&gt;

===Basketball===
FGCU women's basketball has experienced significant success in recent years.  On March 24, 2007, FGCU women's basketball team ended their 35–1 season with a loss in the [[Division II (NCAA)|Division II]] National Championship to [[Southern Connecticut State University]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.naplesnews.com/news/2007/mar/24/despite_loss_national_championship_recruits_optimi/ Disappointment, heartbreak]&lt;/ref&gt;  One year later, in 2008, the Women's Basketball team qualified for the [[WNIT]], becoming the first team to qualify for the WNIT in its first season of [[Division I (NCAA)|Division I]] sports.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.fgcuathletics.com/wbasketball/news/66/744/ Women's Basketball to Host USF in First Round of WNIT]&lt;/ref&gt; During the 2008 WNIT Tourney, the team became the first [[Atlantic Sun]] conference team to win a post-season game since 1998, when [[Florida International University]] won in the Women's NCAA tourney.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.fgcuathletics.com/wbasketball/news/66/754/ FGCU Athletics – Official Site]&lt;/ref&gt; The Women's team won the [[Atlantic Sun Conference]] regular season championship with a conference record of 17–3&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.atlanticsun.org/wbasketball/ |title=Women's Basketball - Home - Atlantic Sun Conference Official Site |publisher=Atlanticsun.org |date= |accessdate=2010-07-15}}&lt;/ref&gt; but is ineligible to compete in the conference tourney, as the team is still in transition from [[Division II (NCAA)|Division II]] to [[Division I (NCAA)|Division I]] athletics.  In the 2010-2011 season, the FGCU woman's basketball team won the Atlantic Sun Conference again.

===Baseball===
The FGCU baseball team has won the Atlantic Sun Conference championship three years in a row and will be allowed to compete in the NCAA post season for this first time in the 2010 season as a result of the two year NCAA reclassifying period.  FGCU currently has several former baseball players playing in the minor leagues, and currently has two pitchers ([[Chris Sale]], [[Casey Coleman]]) pitching in the majors.

===Legal Controversy===
FGCU was the defendant in a federal lawsuit that charges the school with retaliation against two female coaches after they challenged the school's compliance with Title IX.  Its former General Counsel, Wendy Morris, also filed a lawsuit in federal court in April 2008, alleging that the university retaliated against her when she expressed concerns about gender discrimination in athletics, and that her employment was terminated as a direct result of her refusal to go along with the school's actions.&lt;ref name=&quot;FGCU Lawsuit&quot;&gt;{{cite web | title = Second Former Coach Sues Florida School for Retaliation | publisher=Florida Gulf Coast University | url = http://www.publicjustice.net/PR/Flood_SecondCoach_041208.htm | accessdate = 2008-08-12}}&lt;/ref&gt; However, an independent review cleared the school of any wrongdoing.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url = http://www.naplesnews.com/news/2009/jul/29/fgcu-external-review-finds-athletic-department-com/?partner=RSS | title = FGCU: External review finds athletic department in compliance with gender-equity requirements | accessdate = 2009-10-07 | work=Naples Daily News}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Student life==
===Residence life===
[[File:south village.jpg|right|thumb|Everglades Hall in South Village. This complex is designed for First-Year Residents.]]
About 25 percent of the student population lives on campus which is consistent with most universities within the state of Florida.{{citation needed|date=October 2010}} On-campus housing is made up of three sections: North Lake Village, South Village, and West Lake Village. North Lake Village is located on an {{convert|80|acre|m2}} lake and features apartment-style residence halls, with [[Surface water sports|waterfront recreation]]. West Lake Village was previous owned by [[American Campus Communities]] and formally called College Club Apartments. The college purchased the apartment complex for $17 million and the apartments officially became part of FGCU Housing and Residence Life in October 2010.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last=Hale |first=Leslie Williams |url=http://www.naplesnews.com/news/2010/jun/10/fgcu-seeks-buy-college-club-apartments-17m/ |title=FGCU seeks to buy College Club Apartments for $17M |publisher=Naples News |date=2010-06-10 |accessdate=2010-10-11}}&lt;/ref&gt;   Themed housing is available, such as Honors and Wellness communities. South Village (SoVi) is a [[suite|suite-style]] residence hall with three buildings: Everglades Hall, Palmetto Hall, and Biscayne Hall, housing a total of over 1200 first-year students. In August of 2012, South Village will open its fourth residence hall, Osprey Hall, which will house approximately 500 first-year students. In total, there are currently over 2,700 students living in both North Lake Village and SoVi. Freshmen are not required to live on campus; however, given the unique apartment nature of the residence halls, on campus housing is still filled to capacity every year. Individual halls sponsor their own activities and socials, and leadership positions are available in the Resident Hall Association. A commonly used form of transportation on campus is called the Eagle Express.  This shuttle operates daily, taking students from their residence halls to classes and activities around campus.  There is also a shuttle which takes students from the dorms to Gulf Coast Town Center that runs from Thursday through Saturday.

===Greek life===
Florida Gulf Coast University has 18 [[Fraternities and sororities|fraternity and sorority chapters]] currently on campus.  Greek life is governed by the Panhellenic Council, National PanHellenic Council, and the Interfraternity Council.  The Interfraternity Council comprises six fraternities, and the Panhellenic Council comprises four sororities.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://studentservices.fgcu.edu/Panhellenic/661.asp |title=Panhellenic |publisher=Studentservices.fgcu.edu |date=1990-09-29 |accessdate=2010-07-15|archiveurl = http://web.archive.org/web/20080612022107/http%3A//studentservices.fgcu.edu/Panhellenic/661.asp |archivedate = June 12, 2008|deadurl=yes}}&lt;/ref&gt;  As of 2011, there is no Greek Housing on campus.

{| class=&quot;wikitable&quot;
|-
!|Fraternities
!|Sororities
|-
|  style=&quot;vertical-align:top; font-size:smaller;&quot;|
* [[Kappa Alpha Order]]
* [[Kappa Alpha Psi]]
* [[Kappa Sigma]]
* [[Lambda Chi Alpha]]
* [[Pi Kappa Alpha]]
* [[Sigma Chi]]
* [[Sigma Lambda Beta]]
* [[Sigma Phi Epsilon]]
* [[Phi Beta Sigma]]
* [[Omega Psi Phi]]
|  style=&quot;vertical-align:top; font-size:smaller;&quot;|
* [[Alpha Kappa Alpha]]
* [[Chi Omega]]
* [[Delta Delta Delta]]
* [[Delta Sigma Theta]]
* [[Kappa Delta]]
* [[Sigma Iota Alpha]]
* [[Sigma Lambda Gamma]]
* [[Zeta Phi Beta]]
* [[Zeta Tau Alpha]]
|}

===Campus Recreation===

The school has over 100 student clubs and organizations, representing nearly every interest. Sport Clubs and Intramural Sports are also offered along with other recreational venues. Campus Recreation is that largest student employer on campus with over 100 student-staff. Offering positions as Fitness Center Staff, Personal Trainers, Group Fitness Instructors, Lifeguards(Lake Front and Pool), Intramural Sports Referees and even Marketing/Advertising opportunities.[[Student governments in the United States|Student Government Association]] (SGA) and other leadership organizations are available. Dining options on campus include a [[food court]] with several fast-food outlets, and C3, a [[Starbucks]] coffee shop located in the library, and a bagel bar in the large Student Union.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url = http://www.fgcu.edu/auxiliary/studentunion/ | title = The Student Union at Florida Gulf Coast University | publisher=Florida Gulf Coast University | accessdate = 2009-10-02}}&lt;/ref&gt; A sandwich shop called The Perch is also in the Union. South Village residence complex contains Fresh Food Company cafe.

The North Village residence halls are on a large lake with a beach, providing students a beach to relax on and to engage in water sports. Eagle's Landing is a small study and game lounge in the middle of North Village, adjacent to the common area. In addition, plenty of [[wetlands]], green space, and ponds are present on campus, and the campus is surrounded by a huge nature preserve. The school's athletic venues, including [[Alico Arena]] are right next to the complex.

Eaglepalooza is a party thrown by Student Government every fall. It is a campus-wide event that is free for the student body and features games, headlining performances and other spirit activities.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.fgcu.edu/campusrec/Eaglepalooza.html |title=Campus Recreation |publisher=Fgcu.edu |date=2008-11-05 |accessdate=2010-07-15}}&lt;/ref&gt; The event in 2008 attracted 7,000 people, featuring big-name headliners [[Flo Rida]] (who was forced to cancel due to schedule conflict) and [[Busta Rhymes]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url = http://www.naplesnews.com/news/2008/nov/21/busta-rhymes-draws-thousands-fgcus-eaglepalooza/ | title = Busta Rhymes draws thousands to FGCU’s Eaglepalooza | publisher=Naples Daily News | accessdate = 2009-10-02}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Yung Joc]] performed for the 2007 event.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url = http://media.www.eaglenews.org/media/storage/paper1344/news/2008/10/22/News/FloRida.Scheduled.For.Eaglepalooza.08-3500161.shtml | title = Flo-Rida scheduled for EaglePalooza '08 | publisher=Eagle News | accessdate = 2009-10-07}}&lt;/ref&gt;  [[Sean Paul]] and [[Mims]] performed at the 2009 Eaglepalooza event. At 2010's Eaglepalooza, hip-hop group [[LMFAO (group)|LMFAO]] performed.

===Off-Campus Recreation===
Nearby off-campus diversions include Gulf Coast Town Center and Miromar Outlets, both located two miles (3&amp;nbsp;km) from campus, which are open-air malls featuring nightlife. Coconut Point is another open-air mall only a bit further away, on [[Tamiami Trail]]. Entertainment that is around the [[Southwest Florida]] area include [[Fort Myers Downtown Commercial District|Downtown Fort Myers]],&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|author=Raymond L. Daugherty Jr. |url=http://www.downtownfortmyers.com/Night_Clubs/default.cfm |title=Night Clubs |publisher=Downtown Fort Myers |date= |accessdate=2010-07-15}}&lt;/ref&gt; Naples Beach which has been called Best All-Around Beach by [[Travel Channel]] in 2005,&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.paradisecoast.com/cms/d/naples_americas_best_all_around_beach_for_2005.php ]{{Dead link|date=July 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; entertainment district 5th Avenue South in [[Naples, Florida|Naples]],&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.fifthavenuesouth.com/index.php |title=Fifth Avenue South Naples, Naples Florida Shopping, Restaurants and Accommodations, Naples Florida Entertainment - Naples Florida |publisher=Fifthavenuesouth.com |date= |accessdate=2010-07-15}}&lt;/ref&gt; downtown [[Cape Coral]]&lt;ref&gt;http://www.downtowncapecoral.net/&lt;/ref&gt; and [[The Everglades]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.nps.gov/ever/index.htm |title=Everglades National Park (U.S. National Park Service) |publisher=Nps.gov |date=2010-05-29 |accessdate=2010-07-15}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Career Development and Internships===
The office of Career Development Services acts as a referral services for the students seeking internships and full time employment in the area.&lt;ref&gt;http://studentservices.fgcu.edu/careers/&lt;/ref&gt;  The department offers major selection, interview coaching, and guidance for undergraduate, graduate, doctoral students, and alumni of the university

==Media==
The university has operated [[public broadcasting]] stations [[WGCU (TV)|WGCU]] television and [[WGCU-FM]] since 1996, when the license was transferred from the [[University of South Florida]] in [[Tampa, Florida|Tampa]]. WGCU is a [[PBS]] member while WGCU-FM is an [[NPR]] member and broadcasts news, talk and  [[jazz]].  The  ''Eagle News'' is the school's official newspaper; it is printed weekly and also publishes news and blogs on their [http://www.eaglenews.org/ website].

===Student Activism===
The school has gained media attention for its involvement in activism, namely in banning fast-food chain [[KFC]] from campus for its alleged torture of chickens.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | last = Jeremiah | first = Jacobsen | url = http://www.winknews.com/news/local/15044996.html | publisher=Fort Myers Broadcasting | accessdate = 2009-10-07 | title = FGCU students: KFC not allowed on campus}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url = http://www.peta.org/MC/NewsItem.asp?id=10879 | publisher=PETA | accessdate=2009-10-07 | title = FGCU Students Ban KFC}}&lt;/ref&gt;  In addition, FGCU students are receiving nationwide attention for their call to prohibit Chick fil-A from being on campus because of the company's ties to anti-gay groups.  At least half a dozen universities have been emboldened by FGCU's example and have also called for Chick fil-A to be banned from their campus as well.&lt;ref&gt;https://news.change.org/stories/why-fgcu-student-rashad-davis-is-standing-up-to-chick-fil-a&lt;/ref&gt;

==Performing Arts and Music==
FGCU is home to the black box theater where multiple plays and performances are held every year.  The university just completed a {{convert|24,700|sqft|m2|adj=on}} expansion of the fine arts building where the Bower School of Music is to be located.

==Distinguished Speaker Series==
FGCU has a distinguished speaker series where one major, high-profile speaker comes and speaks to the students every year.   Former [[United States Secretary of State|Secretary of State]] and retired General [[Colin Powell]] spoke to a crowd of 4,000 at FGCU's [[Alico Arena]] on March 23, 2007, as a part of the University Lecture Series.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.naplesnews.com/news/2007/mar/24/powell_it_or_not_iraq_civil_war/?local_news Powell: Like it or not, Iraq is a civil war]&lt;/ref&gt;  [[Maya Angelou]] also spoke to a crowd of about 4,000 FGCU students.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.naplesnews.com/news/2005/mar/01/ndn_maya_angelou_thrills_southwest_florida_audienc/ |title=Maya Angelou thrills Southwest Florida audience » Naples Daily News |publisher=Naplesnews.com |date=2010-07-08 |accessdate=2010-07-15}}&lt;/ref&gt;  [[Mikhail Gorbachev]] spoke to a sold-out crowd of FGCU students as well. Current U.S. Vice President [[Joe Biden]] has held an event here, as well as former VP [[Dick Cheney]].  Between 2008 and 2010, the lecture series was put on hold, but returned in April 2011, with former [[first lady]] [[Laura Bush]] as the guest speaker.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.fgcu.edu/lectureseries/  &quot;The President’s Lecture 2011&quot;]&lt;/ref&gt;

==Notable Alumni==

{| class=&quot;wikitable&quot;
|-
! Alumni
! Notability
|-
|'''[[Don Carman]]'''
|Retired [[Major League Baseball]] pitcher for the ''[[Philadelphia Phillies]]''
|-
|'''[[Courtney Jolly]]'''
|Currently a professional [[monster truck]] driver
|-
|'''[[Andy Stickel]]'''
|Bass player for modern rock band [[7 Blue Skies]]&lt;ref&gt;http://www.eklectrikmusic.com/7-blue-skies/index.php&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;http://www.myspace.com/7blueskies&lt;/ref&gt;
|-
|'''[[Derek Lamely]]'''
|Professional Golfer on the PGA Tour.
|-
|'''[[Casey Coleman (baseball)|Casey Coleman]]'''
|Pitcher for the [[Chicago Cubs]].
|-
|'''[[Chris Sale]]'''
|Pitcher for the [[Chicago White Sox]].
|-
|'''Brooke Sweat'''
|Professional Volleyball Player.
|-
|'''Matt Caldwell'''
|Currently serving in the [[Florida House of Representatives]]. 
|-
|}

==See also==
*[[Germain Arena]], stadium two miles (3&amp;nbsp;km) south which is home to FGCU's [[Ice hockey|hockey]] team
*[[List of Florida Gulf Coast University people]]
*[[Paradise Coast]]

==References==
{{Reflist|2}}

== External links ==
*[http://www.fgcu.edu/ Official website]
*[http://www.fgcuathletics.com Official Athletics website]

{{Coord|26.462499|-81.772898|region:US_type:edu|display=title}}

{{State University System of Florida}}
{{Atlantic Sun Conference}}
{{Division1floridacolleges}}
{{Use mdy dates|date=August 2010}}

[[Category:Educational institutions established in 1991]]
[[Category:Florida Gulf Coast University]]
[[Category:American Association of State Colleges and Universities]]
[[Category:Universities and colleges in Florida]]
[[Category:Buildings and structures in Lee County, Florida]]
[[Category:Universities and colleges accredited by the Southern Association of Colleges and Schools]]
[[Category:Education in Lee County, Florida]]
[[Category:Visitor attractions in Lee County, Florida]]

[[de:Florida Gulf Coast University]]
[[no:Florida Gulf Coast University]]
[[simple:Florida Gulf Coast University]]
[[tr:Florida Gulf Coast Üniversitesi]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
