<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="14006825" ns="0" title="Bucknell Bison"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Infobox college athletics
|logo = BucknellBison.png
|logo_width = 125
|name = Bucknell Bison
|university = Bucknell University
|conference = [[Patriot League]]
|association = [[National Collegiate Athletic Association|NCAA]]
|division = [[Division I (NCAA)|Division I]]
|director = John Hardt
|city = Lewisburg
|state = Pennsylvania
|stateabb = PA
|teams = 25
|stadium = [[Christy Mathewson-Memorial Stadium]]
|arena = [[Sojka Pavilion]]
|baseballfield = [[Eugene B. Depew Field]]
|mascot =
|nickname = ''The Bison''
|fightsong = ''Ray Bucknell''
|color1 = [[Orange (color)|Orange]]
|color2 = [[Blue (color)|Blue]]
|hex1 = FF9900
|hex2 = 003399
|pageurl = http://www.bucknellbison.com/
|pagename = http://www.bucknellbison.com/
}}

The '''Bucknell Bison''' are the athletic teams of [[Bucknell University]].  The program is a member of the [[Patriot League]] for [[Division I (NCAA)|Division I]] [[sports]], Division I-AA in football.

Bucknell won the first [[Orange Bowl (game)|Orange Bowl]] (26–0 over the [[University of Miami]] on January 1, 1935). It is also the alma mater of [[baseball]] pitcher [[Christy Mathewson]] who requested burial in a cemetery adjoining Bucknell's campus.

In 2005, the [[Bucknell Bison men's basketball|men's basketball team]] went to the [[National Collegiate Athletic Association|NCAA]] men's basketball tournament and became the first [[Patriot League]] team to win an NCAA tournament game, in an upset of [[University of Kansas|Kansas]] (64–63). The victory followed a year that included wins over #9 Pittsburgh and Saint Joseph's. They lost to [[University of Wisconsin–Madison|Wisconsin]] in the following round, but received the honor of &quot;Best Upset&quot; at the 2005 [[ESPY Awards]].
In 2006, the Bison continued their success with high-profile victories at Syracuse, then ranked 19th, DePaul, and Saint Joseph's, a sequence that saw the Bison nearly enter the Associated Press's top-25 rankings. However, those wins were followed by high-profile losses against Villanova, then ranked fourth in the nation, and at Duke, then ranked first. Patriot League play began after the Duke loss, and the Bison did not lose a league game in 2006. The team was ranked 24th in the nation in both the [[Associated Press]] and [[ESPN]]/[[USA Today]] college basketball polls for the week of February 13. This was the Bucknell program's first national ranking, and the first time since the league's creation in 1990 that any Patriot League men's basketball team has been ranked.  The team was seeded ninth in the [[Oakland, California|Oakland]] bracket for the 2006 NCAA tournament, and defeated the [[Arkansas Razorbacks]] in the first round (59–55).  The Bison were defeated by [[University of Memphis|Memphis]] in the second round, losing by a score of 72–56.  They finished the regular season ranked 25th in the ESPN poll.  Entering the 2006–2007 season, the Bison had scheduled a number of high-profile games, including a season opener against [[Wake Forest University|Wake Forest]].  The schedule also included a match-up against [[George Mason University|George Mason]], a team that had made the 2006 Final Four. In a tight game, the Bison were defeated by Wake Forest 86–83 in overtime. They did, however, go on to defeat George Mason.  Bucknell made it to the 2007 Patriot League Championship Game where they faced [[College of the Holy Cross|Holy Cross]].  The Bison lost by a score of 66–74.

In 2006 the Bucknell Men's soccer team went on a surprise run to capture the Patriot League championship. In the semifinal they beat top seeded Lehigh in a game that went to a shootout. Then in the final they defeated Lehigh in a game that also ended in a shootout. This qualified them for the NCAA Soccer tournament. They faced George Mason in the first round and won on an overtime goal. In the second round they fell to fourth ranked Virginia.

In 2006 the Bucknell Women's rowing team won the Patriot League Championship and its Lightweight Women scored a 6th place finish at the National Championship IRA Regatta. The following year the team repeated as Patriot League team champions, and the lightweight eight was crowned national champions at the IRA for the first time.

In 2003, Bucknell made history by becoming the only school in Patriot League history to capture both the [[Men's and Women's Patriot League Swimming Championship]]&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.bucknellbison.com/sports/m-swim/recaps/022203aaa.html Bucknell Official Athletic Site]&lt;/ref&gt;  in the same season (2003).  These teams were led by seniors Gonzalo Diaz, Christopher Feinthel, Michael Guskey, Geoffrey Konopka, Kurt &quot;Russell&quot; McCoy, Stelios Saffos and Stephen Schwanhausser on the Men's team and seniors Rebecca Dolan and Darby Golino on the Women's team. This historic win was accomplished at the newly opened Kinney Natatorium at Bucknell. The men's swimming and diving team also captured the Division II national championship in 1964.

[[File:Navy-Bucknell lacrosse.jpg|thumb|Bucknell plays [[Navy Midshipmen men's lacrosse|Navy]] in 2006]]

Bucknell also has a reputable men's lacrosse program that is often nationally-ranked. The team reached the [[NCAA Men's Lacrosse Championship]] in 2001. Former head coach [[Sid Jamieson]] is currently ranked 14th in all-time Division I wins.  In 2005, the team upset No. 2 ranked Navy during the regular season, and again in 2006 the team upset No. 1 Maryland.  In 2008, the team broke into the top 10 National Rankings for only the second time in school history.

Beginning in the 2006–2007 season, Bucknell has re-instituted its men's wrestling program in response to a private donation of $5.6 million from wrestling alumnus William Graham, after it was originally dropped by the university in efforts to be in compliance with [[Title IX]] in 2001.  In 2009, the team has a program record of 6 NCAA qualifiers.

In 2008, the Bucknell baseball team entered the Tallahassee regional of the NCAA tournament and upset the Florida State Seminoles, 7–0.

== Fight song ==


'Ray Bucknell, 'Ray Bucknell,&lt;br/&gt;
'Ray for the Orange and the Blue!&lt;br/&gt;
'Ray, 'Ray, 'Ray, 'Ray,&lt;br/&gt;
'Ray for the Orange and the Blue!

==See also==
* [[Lacrosse in Pennsylvania]]

== References ==
{{reflist}}

==External links==
* [http://www.bucknellbison.com/ Official site]

{{Patriot League}}
{{Colleges and Universities in Pennsylvania}}
{{Annapolis Group}}
{{Oberlin Group}}
{{CLAC}}


[[Category:Bucknell Bison| ]]
[[Category:College sports teams in the United States by team]]
[[Category:College sports teams in Pennsylvania]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
