<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="14001987" ns="0" title="Lincoln Hospital (Bronx, New York)"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Infobox Hospital
| Name        = Lincoln Hospital
| Org/Group   = New York City Health and Hospitals Corporation
| Image       = Lincoln Hospital Morris Av jeh.jpg
| Caption     = &lt;!-- optional --&gt;
| map_type    = &lt;!-- optional: uses the &quot;Template:Location map&quot; format; must have latitude and longitude if using this. --&gt;
| latitude    = &lt;!-- used only for adding a map, with map_type --&gt;
| longitude   = &lt;!-- used only for adding a map, with map_type --&gt;
| Logo        = &lt;!-- optional --&gt;
| Location    = 234 East 149th Street
| Region      = Bronx
| State       = New York
| Country     = US
| Coordinates = {{coord|40.817046|-73.924127|display=inline,title}}
| HealthCare  = Public
| Type        = Full Service Medical Center &amp; Teaching Hospital
| Speciality  = &lt;!-- if devoted to a speciality, i.e. not if has broad spectrum of specialities --&gt;
| Standards   = &lt;!-- optional if no national standards --&gt;
| Emergency   = Level I Trauma Center
| Affiliation = Downtown Bronx Medical Association, [[Weill Cornell Medical College]]
| Beds        = 342&lt;ref name=lincoln-site /&gt;
| Founded     = 1839
| Closed      = &lt;!-- optional --&gt;
| Website     = http://www.nyc.gov/html/hhc/html/facilities/lincoln.shtml
| Wiki-Links  = &lt;!-- optional --&gt;
|}}

'''Lincoln Medical and Mental Health Center''', founded in 1839, is in the [[South Bronx]] region of [[New York City]], aggressively tackling issues such as asthma, obesity, cancer, diabetes and tuberculosis.&lt;ref name=lincoln-site&gt;{{cite web
|url= http://www.nyc.gov/html/hhc/html/facilities/lincoln.shtml
|title= HHC - Lincoln Medical And Mental Health Center
|accessdate= 2008-01-14
|publisher= The City of New York
}}&lt;/ref&gt; It is known for innovative programs addressing the specific needs of the community it serves.&lt;ref name=lincoln-site /&gt; With over 144,000 ER visits,&lt;ref name=lincoln-site /&gt; Lincoln has the busiest single site Emergency Room in the region. 

Adult and pediatric asthma patients receive immediate attention in the emergency room from Lincoln's expert medical staff.&lt;ref name=lincoln-site /&gt; Adult patients are enrolled in Lincoln’s Comprehensive Care for Patients with Asthma Clinic.&lt;ref name=lincoln-site /&gt; The Lincoln Asthma and Allergy Clinic provides an individualized, multidisciplinary approach to asthma and allergy management.&lt;ref name=lincoln-site /&gt; This is an important service to the residents of the South Bronx, who have the highest occurrence of asthma in New York City.&lt;ref name=lincoln-site /&gt;

Lincoln’s specialty diabetes clinics include adult, pediatric, pregnancy and diabetes education programs.&lt;ref name=lincoln-site /&gt; Certified diabetes educators can be consulted around-the-clock and diabetes case management is available for pediatric patients.&lt;ref name=lincoln-site /&gt; Recently, Lincoln received a grant from the United Hospital Fund to implement a new health literacy program for its diabetes clinic, POWER/PODER.&lt;ref name=lincoln-site /&gt;

Lincoln Medical and Mental Health Center received high quality ratings from the New York State Department of Health from hospital profiles comparing key quality measures and treatments for specific conditions in hospitals statewide.&lt;ref name=lincoln-site /&gt; Lincoln ranked number two for appropriate care in New York State in the areas of heart attack and heart failure care as well as surgical infection prevention, an HHC corporate initiative.&lt;ref name=lincoln-site /&gt;

Lincoln was also singled out for its outstanding work in the prevention of surgical site infection and is the demonstration site for a national training video on this topic.&lt;ref name=lincoln-site /&gt; The video is part of a series produced by the Hospital Association of New York State (HANYS), which is partnering with the Institute for Healthcare Improvement (IHI).&lt;ref name=lincoln-site /&gt;

The New York State Department of Health selected Lincoln as the first hospital in the South Bronx to receive designation as an official Stroke Center.&lt;ref name=lincoln-site /&gt; Stroke Center designation ensures that stroke victims will be seen quickly and receive the specific treatment that is critical to preventing permanent disability or death.&lt;ref name=lincoln-site /&gt;

Some of Lincoln Medical and Mental Health Center's specialty services include: AIDS Center; Asthma Treatment; Diabetes Treatment; Level III Perinatal Center; Regional Trauma Center; Stroke Center; Women's Health Center; Child and Teen Health Services; SAFE (SART) Center.&lt;ref name=lincoln-site /&gt;

==History==

Lincoln Hospital was originally founded in 1839 as the &quot;Home for the Relief of Aged Indigent Black Persons&quot; by a group of prominent philanthropists.&lt;ref name=lincoln-history&gt;{{cite web
|url= http://www.lincolnemresidency.com/lincolnhospitalhistory
|title= History of Lincoln Medical Center
|accessdate= 2008-01-17
}}&lt;/ref&gt; The hospital's function gradually became the most important aspect of the operation, and in 1882, the name was changed to &quot;The Colored Home and Hospital.&quot;&lt;ref name=lincoln-history /&gt;

In 1895, after more than half a century of occupying various sites in [[Manhattan]], the Board of Trustees purchased a large lot in the South Bronx—then a semi-rural area of the city—at the corner of 141st Street and Southern Boulevard. A new hospital was built; its facilities included the latest developments in medical care.&lt;ref name=lincoln-history /&gt; The dedication took place on April 29, 1899. The hospital became a general hospital open to all people without regard to color or creed, although it maintained its founding connection as an institution dedicated to the relief and advancement of the Black people. During the hospital's reorganization and eventual occupation of the new site, its name was changed to Lincoln Hospital, to honor the Great Emancipator.&lt;ref name=lincoln-history /&gt;

Because of the increasing demand for services required by a more densely populated South Bronx—and a decreasing supply of philanthropic funds—in 1925 the Board of Trustees decided to sell Lincoln Hospital to the Department of Public Welfare of the City of New York.  The great outflow of physicians to the Armed Forces during World War II and the drastic socioeconomic decline in the area that followed—erosion of the middle class and great immigration from the southern regions of the United States, the Caribbean, and countries of Latin America—took their toll on Lincoln Hospital. However, the hospital enjoyed a resurgence in the 1970s as one of the finest institutions for the care of the sick and the training of professionals in the newly formed New York City Health and Hospitals Corporation.&lt;ref name=lincoln-history /&gt;

In the 1990s, Lincoln became part of the North-Manhattan/South Bronx &quot;Generations Plus Network&quot; together with Metropolitan Hospital, Morrisania Diagnostic and Treatment Center, and Segundo Ruiz Belvis Diagnostic and Treatment Center. In spite of dire predictions, this network continues to strive to provide quality care to a diverse, multiethnic urban population in this era of managed care.&lt;ref name=lincoln-history /&gt;

==Lincoln Medical Center today==

In 1976, a new facility was dedicated about two miles from the &quot;Old Lincoln,&quot; at a construction cost of 220 million dollars.&lt;ref name=lincoln-history /&gt; The present hospital building incorporates some of the most advanced concepts in hospital design and sophisticated equipment.&lt;ref name=lincoln-history /&gt; It occupies five full city blocks, providing health care to the entire South Bronx community, as well as parts of Upper Manhattan.&lt;ref name=lincoln-history /&gt; Lincoln also administers the Substance Abuse Division, located at 349 East 140th Street.&lt;ref name=lincoln-history /&gt;

As of 2007, Lincoln has a capacity of 342 beds.&lt;ref name=lincoln-site /&gt; Although it constitutes 9% of the beds in the region, Lincoln caters to 31% of the health care visits of this community, where there is fewer than one primary care physician for every 4,000 people.&lt;ref name=lincoln-history /&gt;

Over the last decade, Lincoln Medical and Mental Health Center has successfully transformed itself to a highly respected medical facility.  Past criticisms about its quality of service&lt;ref name=kozol&gt;{{cite book  
 | last = Kozol 
 | first = Jonathan 
 | authorlink = Jonathan Kozol 
 | title = Amazing Grace: The Lives of Children and the Conscience of a Nation 
 | origyear = 1995 
 | edition = HarperPerennial edition 
 | year = 1996 
 | publisher = Crown Publishers, Inc. 
 | location = New York 
 | isbn = 0-06-097697-7 
}}&lt;/ref&gt; have been replaced by accolades—It now receives high quality ratings from the New York State Department of Health and is prominently featured in a national training video produced by the Hospital Association of New York State (HANYS) in partnership with the Institute for Health Care Improvement (ICI).&lt;ref name=lincoln-site /&gt;

==References==
{{reflist}}

[[Category:Hospitals in New York City]]
[[Category:1839 establishments in the United States]]
[[Category:Hospitals established in 1839]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
