<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="14014116" ns="0" title="GOS (operating system)"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{lowercase}}
{{Infobox OS
| name                   = gOS 3.1 Gadgets
| logo                   = [[File:GOS (operating system) logo.png|120px]]
| screenshot             = [[Image:Gos gadgets widgets.jpg|300px]]
| caption                = Current Distribution, gOS 3.1, is based on Ubuntu 8.04.1 LTS
| developer              = Good OS LLC
| source_model           = [[Free and open source software]]
| kernel_type            = [[Monolithic kernel|Monolithic]] ([[Linux kernel|Linux]])
| supported_platforms    = [[x86 architecture|x86]], [[Netbook]]s
| ui                     = [[GNOME]]
| family                 = [[Unix-like]]
| released               = {{start date|2007|11|01}}
| latest_release_version = 3.1 &quot;Gadgets&quot;
| latest_release_date    = {{Release date|2009|01|03}}
| latest_test_version    = 
| latest_test_date       = 
| marketing_target       = 
| programmed_in          = 
| prog_language          = 
| language               = [[English language|English]]
| updatemodel            = 
| package_manager        = 
| working_state          = Discontinued
| license                = [[Creative Commons licenses|Creative Commons Attribution Noncommercial]] [[Share Alike]] 3.1 Unported
| website                = http://www.thinkgos.com/
}}

'''gOS''' or &quot;good OS&quot; was an Ubuntu-based [[GNU/Linux distribution]] created by '''Good OS LLC''', a [[Los Angeles]]-based corporation.  Its [[Chief information officer|CIO]] Dave Liu described that after meeting [[Enlightenment (window manager)|Enlightenment]] and [[open source]] people, he realized that his dream to bring [[Web 2.0]] applications into mainstream use could be achieved by creating a GNU/Linux distribution that made it easy for users to access [[Google]] and Web 2.0 applications.&lt;ref&gt;''Linuxjournal'', March 2008, p. 58.&lt;/ref&gt;

==History==
The company initially advertised gOS 1.0 as &quot;An alternative OS with [[Google Apps]] and other Web 2.0 apps for the modern user.&quot; This first version gOS (1.0.1_386) was based on [[Ubuntu (operating system)|Ubuntu]] 7.10 and the Enlightenment window manager E17.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
    | title = gOS 1 at linuxquestions.org
    | url =http://iso.linuxquestions.org/gos/gos-1.0.1/
    }}&lt;/ref&gt;

On January 7, 2008, a test version (2.0.0-beta1) of gOS, intended to demonstrate the [[Everex]] [[CloudBook]] at the 2008 [[Consumer Electronics Show]], and named '''gOS Rocket''', was released. This version was also E17 based.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
    | last = Babcock
    | first = Charles
    | title = Rocket Linux To Launch At CES
    | work = InformationWeek
    | date = 2008-01-03
    | url = http://www.informationweek.com/news/showArticle.jhtml?articleID=205208008
    | accessdate = 2008-01-10
    }}&lt;/ref&gt; The definitive second version of gOS debuted at the end February 2008, together with the launch of Everex's new CloudBook, the [[gBook]] laptop, and a new, second version of the gPC, the &quot;encore&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.everex.com/products/gpc2/gpc2.htm the gPC2 at Everex]&lt;/ref&gt; This version was called gOS V2 Rocket, and was completely rewritten and now based on the [[GNOME]] window manager, a built in [[Compositing window manager]], and the [[Avant Window Navigator]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.insidesocal.com/click/2008/02/heard_at_scale_6x_the_everex_c.html announcement that gOS rocket will be based on Gnome, not E17]&lt;/ref&gt;

On April 6, 2008, Good OS launched a publicly available version of gOS, called gOS 2.9 &quot;Space&quot;, intended for the [[gPC mini]],&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.everex.com/products/gpc_mini/gpc_mini.htm gPC mini at Everex]&lt;/ref&gt; This version is based on Compiz fusion, Gnome, and the Avant Window Navigator [[Dock (computing)|dock]] manager, but also uses E17 code. It has a dock with a &quot;[[Stacks (software)|stack]]&quot; very much like the &quot;fan view&quot; of [[Mac OS X v10.5]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://blogs.techrepublic.com.com/opensource/?p=237 gOS space] at techrepublic.com&lt;/ref&gt;

On September 23, 2008, Good OS launched gOS 3 Gadgets, which is described by Good OS, as &quot;The third and best version of gOS to date, Perfect for Netbooks&quot;. It is still based on GNOME but has replaced [[Avant Window Navigator|AWN]] with yet another launcher called [http://freshmeat.net/projects/wbar/ Wbar]. It introduces the full support for [[Wine (software)|Wine]] 1.0, [[Picasa]] (using the Wine libraries) and [[Google Gadgets]].

On December 1, 2008, Good OS announced its next operating system, '''[[Cloud (operating system)|Cloud]]'''. Cloud can be described as an &quot;[[instant on]] browser based application environment&quot;. With Cloud, users can browse the Internet seconds after turning on their computer, and can also use it to run applications, like Skype, or a media player. Cloud shows a Dock similar to gOS 3 in the browser window, and will keep loading the main operating system (Windows, GNU/linux, OSX) in the background. An icon in the Dock will tell the user when the main OS has finished booting in the background, and can be used to switch instantly to the main OS, when tasks not (yet) supported under Cloud are needed. A beta test program for Cloud version 1.0 was announced January 30, 2009.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.thinkgos.com/cloud/ Official Cloud page]&lt;/ref&gt; 

On January 3, 2009, Good OS released gOS 3.1 Gadgets (SP1), or Service pack 1, a bug-fixed version of gOS 3.0.&lt;ref name=&quot;dgadgets&quot;&gt;[http://thinkgos.com/dgadgets.php Download site for gOS 3.1]&lt;/ref&gt; Simultaneously, the Good OS team also launched a new official forum, as a replacement for the Google discussion group used previously and '''faqly''', which is now defunct. 

Faqly was a cross between an [[Internet forum]] and a [[FAQ]] where gOS users could ask questions and browse for answers. Other gOS users, or [[GNU/Linux]] experts, could then provide answers to the questions. But Faqly had some large usability problems, notably the fact that users had problems deciding when the system was searching for an answer, or entering a new question. Additionally, questions and answers could not be edited or deleted.

Around May 2008, all members of the Good OS team ceased to post in any blog, twitter, or any other web medium, including their own forum and website. While the website is still on-line, and gOS 3.1 can be downloaded, no sign of the developers has been heard of since then. Additionally, there are no sources of gOS available. Development of gOS seems to have been stalled, and the official forum (http://forum.thinkgos.com/) was not moderated anymore and was quickly overrun by spam and was closed halfway through 2009 (one of the few life-signs of the Good OS team after mid 2008); its function has been taken over by the unofficial forum. No sign of promised developments like the netbook launcher version or cloud have been realized.

According to [[DistroWatch.com]], gOS is discontinued.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://distrowatch.com/table.php?distribution=gos |title=DistroWatch.com: gOS |publisher=DistroWatch.com |date=2011-02-15 |accessdate=2011-02-15}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Design==
gOS-1 was based on the [[Ubuntu (operating system)|Ubuntu]] 7.10 distribution (later versions after 2.9 use version 8.04) and themed desktop environment somewhat similar in appearance to [[Mac OS X Leopard]]. The earlier versions (1 and 2-beta) used the [[Enlightenment (window manager)|Enlightenment]] 17 window manager instead of the usual [[GNOME]] or [[KDE]] desktops, to create a desktop that had a similar appearance to [[Mac OS X]]. Enlightenment acted both as an [[X window manager]] and a [[desktop environment]]. Therefore early versions of gOS worked on systems as low end as a 350&amp;nbsp;MHz Pentium II with 196 MB of RAM,&lt;ref&gt;196 MB was needed to install gOS through the Live CD, but it ran on as little RAM as 128MB when installed, or when running from the Live CD&lt;/ref&gt; but a typical gOS system would have used as a minimum a 1&amp;nbsp;GHz [[Pentium III]] with 256 MB RAM. After gOS2-beta the later versions of gOS abandoned the use of Enlightenment as desktop manager (although some E17 code still seemed to be used), in favor of using GNOME, with Compiz Fusion and the [[Avant Window Navigator]]. This increased the need for memory to values similar to normal Ubuntu.

Based on the idea of [[cloud computing]], all versions of gOS lean heavily on on-line applications built on Web 2.0 and [[Ajax (programming)|AJAX]] technology so they also do not use much hard disk space for applications. The whole gOS-1 system fitted comfortably in less than 2 GB. Also many of the documents created with gOS, such as [[Google Docs]] documents, can be saved on Google servers instead of on the local hard disk, so gOS can work with very small hard disks. In gOS V2 Rocket, Good OS introduced the use of Google's &quot;[[Google Gears]]&quot; technology which promises to make Google's [[web application]]s usable without an Internet connection.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.linuxelectrons.com/news/linux/15642/linux-based-gos-2-0-will-debut-monday Linux Based gOS 2.0 Will Debut on Monday | LinuxElectrons&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt; Currently, [[Google Reader]] and [[Google Docs]] are the only supported Google applications, though other web applications such as [[Remember the Milk]] have added Google Gears functionality.

gOS 2.0 Rocket's primary features include a Mac OS X-like [[Dock (computing)|Dock]] called &quot;the Launcher&quot; (using [[Avant Window Navigator]] in gOS Rocket G and gOS Space, and iTask-NG in gOS Rocket E), containing icons to launch programs like the [[Mozilla Firefox|Firefox]] web browser, [[Rhythmbox]] audio player, [[Xine]] video player, and [[Skype]] for Internet telephony. There are also options to open many Google-based web application like [[Gmail|Google Mail]], [[Google Docs]], [[Google Calendar]], and [[Google Maps]]. Other programs could be added to the Launcher as well. The first E17 based version of gOS used another Dock-style interface called the iBar.

Other installed programs could be started through menus, among the most important was the photo and picture editing program [[the GIMP]], the document viewer [[Evince]], and the [[OpenOffice.org]] office suite. More programs could be installed using the built-in [[Synaptic Package Manager]].&lt;ref name = &quot;add/remove&quot;&gt;gOS 1.0.1 had Ubuntu's easy to use &quot;add/remove&quot; application installer, but was missing in gOS 2-beta. However the synaptic package manager is available in all versions of gOS. and in gOS 3.0 add/remove has returned.&lt;/ref&gt;

==Versions==
===gOS 1.0.1===
[[Image:800px-Gos1.0.1desktop.gif|thumb|200px|left|gOS 1.0.1 desktop]]
'''gOS 1.0.1''' was introduced on November 1, 2007, preinstalled on the Everex Green gPC TC2502 sold at [[Wal-Mart]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
| last=Needleman
| first=Rafe
| date=2007-10-31
| title=Almost the Google PC: Everex gPC available at Wal-Mart
| url=http://www.webware.com/8301-1_109-9807133-2.html?tag=cnetfd.mt
| accessdate=2008-01-10
}}&lt;/ref&gt; gOS 1.0.1 fully supported the advanced [[Power management]] capabilities of the gPC TC2502, so the system could be put in suspend mode and after turning on again was ready in a few seconds.

In December 2007, [[PC Club]] followed suit and reintroduced their [[Enpower]] Fuzion desktop&lt;ref&gt;
{{cite web
    | title = ENFZ07 ENPOWER FUZION07
    | publisher = PC Club
    | url = http://www.enpower.com/showSystemSpec.cfm?id=ENFZ07
    | accessdate = 2008-01-10
    }}&lt;/ref&gt; for sale with gOS installed for $189, which is their second system to include a GNU/Linux distribution since their controversial temporary inclusion of [[Linspire]] (then LindowsOS) in late 2003/early 2004&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web 
| date=2003-09-03
| location=San Diego
| publisher=Lindows.com Inc
| url=http://www.linspire.com/lindows_news_pressreleases_archives.php?id=64 
| title=PC Club Announces Largest Linux Launch With More Than 50 Retail Stores Now Carrying LindowsOS Computers
| accessdate=2008-01-10
}} {{Dead link|date=October 2010|bot=H3llBot}}&lt;/ref&gt; and the sale of the Empower Essence system with Ubuntu during the month of June 2007.

Everex followed on by creating the [[CloudBook]], a laptop based on the VIA [[NanoBook]] reference. The CloudBook was bundled with gOS Rocket with a hint that later versions would include a touchscreen. At an RRP of $400, it was to compete with the ASUS [[Eee PC]] in the cheap miniature Laptop space.&lt;ref&gt;[http://clumpc.com/?p=9 Walmart takes on the EeePC with Cloudbook » CLUMPC&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web 
|last= Shah
|first= Agam
|url=http://www.pcworld.com/businesscenter/article/139196/everex_readies_sub300_linux_notebooks.html
|title=Everex Readies Sub-$300 Linux Notebooks 
|accessdate=2007-11-08 |date=2007-11-02
|publisher=pcworld}}&lt;/ref&gt; Less well known is the fact that Everex simultaneously also worked on a more classic notebook, called the gBook, and on the [[Mac mini]] like gPC mini all designed to run gOS v2.&lt;ref&gt;[http://cafelinux.org/gosforum/index.php/topic,341.0.html gBook details on the official gOS forum]&lt;/ref&gt;

Online vendor [[ClubIT.com]] offered a [[RoHS]]-compliant [[VIA C7]] developer board bundled with gOS.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
| title=VIA Motherboard Bundle
| url=http://clubit.com/product_detail.cfm?itemno=A4842001 
| accessdate=2008-01-10
}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===gOS 2-beta (gOS Rocket E)===
[[Image:GOS Rocket desktop.jpg|thumb|200px|gOS Rocket E desktop]]
On 2008-01-07, Good OS LLC released a beta of the second version of gOS, called '''gOS-live-2.0.0-beta1''' and nicknamed &quot;Rocket&quot;. However this version did not seem to be a valid replacement for rev 1.0.1 as it was missing some essential functions, such as hardware and system administration tools, and the easy to use application installer &quot;Add/Remove&quot;.&lt;ref name =&quot;add/remove&quot;/&gt; It also missed the capability to access CDs and hard-disk partitions other than its own. The demo version status of this version became extra apparent when the new Everex [[CloudBook]] which was due to debut January 25, 2008 was delayed for a month to allow Good OS time to rewrite this second version of gOS for the CloudBook, gBook. and second version of the gPC.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.computerworld.com/action/article.do?command=viewArticleBasic&amp;taxonomyName=networking_and_internet&amp;articleId=9059060&amp;taxonomyId=16 Software 'tweaks,' Chinese new year delay Everex CloudBook], ''Computerworld''.&lt;/ref&gt; On April 11, 2008, Good OS released an updated version of gOS Rocket E.&lt;ref&gt;[http://dev.thinkgos.com/blog/gos-rocket-e-and-g-are-online gOS Rocket E and G are Online]&lt;/ref&gt; In addition, a fan of gOS has also released an unauthorized remaster of gOS Rocket E which includes the aforementioned system administration tools and drive mounting as well as the [[Thunar]] file manager.&lt;ref&gt;[http://darthchaosofrspw.wordpress.com/2008/06/15/gos-ultimate-e-now-available-for-download/ gOS Ultimate E now available for download]&lt;/ref&gt;

===gOS V2 Rocket (gOS Rocket G)===
[[Image:Awn screenshot.png|thumb|300px|[[Avant Window Navigator]]]]
Later it became apparent that the month was needed because Everex had decided that future versions of gOS for the Cloudbook, gBook and gPC2, would use the GNOME desktop environment, instead of E17. It was announced that this version would also be called &quot;Rocket&quot;, to be precise '''gOS V2 &quot;Rocket&quot;''', (this version would also be offered to new gPC2 users)&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.tuxmachines.org/node/24070 gOS for the Cloudbook to use GNOME]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://cafelinux.org/gosforum/index.php/topic,308.msg1351/topicseen.html#msg1351 Confirmation by development team that the CloudBook will use a GNOME based gOS]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://blog.laptopmag.com/category/cloudbook Unwrapping of an early CloudBook]&lt;/ref&gt; and would use the [[Avant Window Navigator]] system to create a [[Dock (computing)|dock]] to resemble the older gOS versions in looks and functionality. Until the launch of gOS 2.9 this version was '''not''' available as a [[Live CD]], but only to CloudBook owners. But after the launch of 2.9 it has now also become available as a Live_CD download from one of the mirrors as found on the Good OS web-site. This version is now referenced to as &quot;gOS rocket G&quot; (&quot;G&quot; for Gnome) to distinguish it from the older beta version now called &quot;gOS rocket E&quot;, which is also still available for download.&lt;ref&gt;[http://dev.thinkgos.com/downloads/gos-rocketG gOS Download page]&lt;/ref&gt;

===gOS 2.9 Space===
[[Image:GOS space.png|thumb|200px|gOS Space]]
gOS 2.9 Space became available as a generic [[GNU/Linux distribution]] on April 7, 2008, and is a debugged and extended version of the older gOS V2 Rocket G. It can be downloaded as an .ISO&lt;ref&gt;[http://dev.thinkgos.com/downloads gOS Downloads]&lt;/ref&gt; that can be burned on a DVD (it's slightly too large for a CD), or can be put on another external bootable medium such as a [[memory stick]] or [[Secure Digital card]] reader acting as an external USB drive, with enough capacity. A gOS 2.9 DVD was also announced to be sold from The Good OS store on their website, but until now has not become available.&lt;ref&gt;[http://dev.thinkgos.com/store gOS Store]&lt;/ref&gt; gOS Space is loaded with new MySpace features, but all the existing Google applications can still be used. As a GNU/Linux distribution, 2.9 is much more complete than 2.0-beta and is also less buggy. gOS Space is less &quot;light&quot; (using a small amount of memory) than older, publicly-available versions, as it's based on a combination of [[Ubuntu (operating system)|Ubuntu]] 7.10, the GNOME windows manager enhanced with [[Compiz fusion]], and the [[Avant Window Navigator]], a [[Dock (computing)|Dock]]-like launcher that has been enhanced with [[Stacks (software)|Stacks]]. According to Good OS, there is also [[Enlightenment (window manager)|Enlightenment]] code used, but its exact purpose is still unknown. In any case gOS Space needs about 384MB of RAM to work reasonably, the same amount as straight Ubuntu 7.10. When [[Ubuntu (operating system)#Ubuntu 8.04 (Hardy Heron)|Ubuntu 8.04 (Hardy Heron)]] became available on April 24, 2008 it became obvious that trying to upgrade gOS 2.9 to the new Ubuntu renders it without any working [[Linux kernel|kernels]], leaving a non-working system, so upgrading gOS has been disabled by Good OS. It is not expected that this will be fixed, but that instead a new gOS (rev 3.0) will be released, based on Ubuntu 8.04.

===gOS 2.9M Escape Pod===
As of July 2, 2008 ''Good OS'', in consortium with [[Osram Sylvania|Digital Gadgets]], launched the '''Sylvania g netbook'''. The Sylvania name is used under license by Digital Gadgets. Its similar to the original Everex CloudBook with more memory, and the trackpad and buttons have moved to the front of the device. the new system runs gOS 2.9M, a specially modified version of gOS 2.9 &quot;space&quot; based on Ubuntu 8.04 &lt;ref&gt;[http://www.thinkgos.com/ gOS official website]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://sylvaniacomputers.com/ SYLVANIA G Netbook Computer&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;

===gOS 3.0 Gadgets===
About a month after a first beta version, the final version of gOS 3.0 was released on the gOS website on September 23, 2008. It features integrated [[Google Gadgets]] integrated into the desktop (not in a browser window) and includes [[Wine (software)|Wine 1.0]] and [[Mozilla Prism]]. gOS 3.0 is based on the newer Ubuntu 8.04.1. This version goes &quot;back to its roots&quot;, as it is intended for [[netbook]]s. The [[Avant Window Navigator]]'s (abbreviated '''AWN''' or '''Awn''') [[Dock (computing)|dock]]-like bar has been removed in favor of a more &quot;lightweight&quot; launch bar called [http://code.google.com/p/wbar/ Wbar]. It is similar to the one used in the first [[Enlightenment (window manager)|Enlightenment]]-based gOS version. The gOS 3.0 Gadgets Live CD can be downloaded from the thinkgos site.&lt;ref name=&quot;dgadgets&quot; /&gt; In an official press release issued on August 6, 2008,&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.thinkgos.com/pr/gOS3-Gadgets/ gOS Announces gOS 3 Gadgets]&lt;/ref&gt; gOS 3.0 Gadgets was announced to use [[LXDE]] technology&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.desktoplinux.com/news/NS7428727466.html?kc=rss Lightweight GNOME alternative emerges]&lt;/ref&gt; but this plan was later put aside.&lt;ref&gt;[http://groups.google.com/group/goslinux/web/technical-faq gOS Technical FAQ]&lt;/ref&gt; Launching Synaptic will reveal that none of the applications listed at LXDE's [http://lxde.org/lxde About page] are installed.

===gOS 3.1 Gadgets===
'''gOS 3.1 Gadgets''' was launched on January 3, 2009 as an upgraded bug fixed version of gOS 3.0 gadgets. This version fixes some bugs in gOS 3.0, but it isn't an obligatory update for users of 3.0 because bugfixes in gOS 3.0 are distributed using the built-in updater automatically. This version has had over 45,000 downloads.

===Netbook Launcher===
On October 22, 2008, a beta version of the gOS '''Netbook Launcher''' was released. This is an independently developed extension of gOS that gives gOS 3.0 Gadgets the possibility to switch to a new &quot;netbook user interface&quot;, similar to [[Ubuntu Netbook Remix]]. You can switch between a netbook user interface and the classic gOS desktop at will. This Launcher is provided by the gOS Community and is not officially supported by Good OS for system manufacturers. It is still in beta, and therefore contains some bugs. One remaining problem is that it does not work well with [[Compiz]].&lt;ref name=&quot;wordpress netbook ed&quot;&gt;[http://gosportal.wordpress.com/netbook-edition/ Netbook edition]&lt;/ref&gt;

==Upgrade problem for versions before gOS 2.9M==
When Ubuntu released version 8.04 (Hardy Heron) on April 24, 2008, it became apparent that gOS (versions before gOS 2.9M Escape pod) could no longer use the update/upgrade facilities that Ubuntu offered. Any attempt to upgrade any version of gOS before version 2.9M will either fail with an &quot;incompatible windows manager&quot; error or will remove all [[Linux kernel|kernels]] from the system. Version 3.0 of gOS solves the problem, as it is actually based on Ubuntu 8.04. Good OS claims that new versions of gOS won't use Ubuntu's upgrading repositories, to prevent the problem from happening again.&lt;ref&gt;[http://groups.google.com/group/goslinux/browse_frm/thread/67296373f8b0ff3d/e33f1431121b610e?lnk=gst&amp;q=upgrade#e33f1431121b610e gOS upgrading problem]&lt;/ref&gt;

==Version history table==
{| class=&quot;wikitable&quot;
|-
! Colour
! Meaning
|-
| style=&quot;background-color:#fa8072;&quot; | Red
| Release no longer officially available
|-
| style=&quot;background-color:#A0E75A;&quot; | Green
| Release still officially available
|-
| style=&quot;background-color:#87ceeb;&quot; | Blue
| Future release
|-
| style=&quot;background-color:#f8ffff;&quot; | White
| Not publicly available
|}

{| class=&quot;wikitable&quot; style=&quot;width:100%;&quot;
! Version (screenshots) !! Code name !! development name !! Release date  !! released for !! Based on !! Freely available? || Desktop Manager !! Dock manager !! Features and Changes
|----
| style=&quot;background-color:#fa8072;&quot;|[http://www.thecodingstudio.com/opensource/linux/screenshots/index.php?linux_distribution_sm=gOS%201.0 1.0.1_386]
|gOS
| Painfull&lt;!-- from memory, It could be wrong --&gt;
|2007-11-01
|[[Everex green computers|Everex]] gPC
|[[Ubuntu (operating system)#Ubuntu 7.10 (Gutsy Gibbon)|Gutsy Gibbon]]
|Yes Live_CD
|[[Enlightenment (window manager)|E17]]
| iBar &lt;ref&gt;[http://wiki.enlightenment.org/index.php/E17_User_Guide/iBar iBar] at the E17 User Guide&lt;/ref&gt;
|Initial release; Based on Ubuntu 7.10 and the Enlightenment 17 Desktop environment, plus lots of Google applications
|----
| style=&quot;background-color:#fa8072;&quot;|[http://www.thecodingstudio.com/opensource/linux/screenshots/index.php?linux_distribution_sm=gOS%202.0 2.0.1-beta1 Screenshot]
| gOS Rocket (E) 
| Reloaded
|2008-01-07
| Everex [[CloudBook]] Demo at CES 2008
|Gutsy Gibbon
|Yes Live_CD
|E17
| iBar
| Beta demo version especially developed to demonstrate with the Everex CloudBook at the 2008 [[Consumer Electronics Show]]. still based on Enlightenment 17 desktop
|----
|style=&quot;background-color:#fa8072;&quot;|[http://www.everexstore.com/support/add_skype/add_skype.htm V2]
| gOS Rocket (G)
| Unknown
|2008-02-22
|Everex CloudBook, gBook, gPC and gPC2
|Gutsy Gibbon
|V2 NO, gOS 2G Yes
|[[GNOME]]
|[[Avant Window Navigator|AWN]]
| Final version as delivered installed on the CloudBook, and later the gBook and the gPC2. Not available as a live CD until the launch of Space. Now based on AWN and [[Compiz fusion]].
|----
| style=&quot;background-color:#fa8072;&quot; |[http://www.thecodingstudio.com/opensource/linux/screenshots/index.php?linux_distribution_sm=gOS%20Space%202.9 2.9]
| gOS Space
| Unknown
|2008-04-06
| Everex gPC mini
|Gutsy Gibbon
|Yes as Live_CD
|GNOME 
|AWN
| Specially promoted as a version for [[MySpace]] users, adds &quot;stacks&quot; to the AWN launcher, and uses MySpace applications, does not need 3D hardware to support AWN. Fits on a live [[DVD]].
|----
| style=&quot;background-color:#f8ffff;&quot; |[http://sylvaniacomputers.com/products.php?p=g 2.9M]
| gOS Escape pod 2.9M
| Unknown
|2008-02-07
| [[Osram Sylvania|Sylvania]] g&amp;nbsp;netbook
|Hardy Heron (8.04)
|No, only on g-netbook
| GNOME
|AWN
| Specific &quot;light&quot; version, especially developed for netbook systems
|----
| style=&quot;background-color:#fa8072;&quot; | [http://www.thecodingstudio.com/opensource/linux/screenshots/index.php?linux_distribution_sm=gOS%203.0%20Beta%20Gadgets 3.0 beta]
| gOS 3.0 Gadgets beta
| Aphrodite
| 2008-08-06
| Netbooks
|Hardy Heron (8.04.1)
|Yes, as live CD
| GNOME
| Wbar &lt;ref&gt;[http://code.google.com/p/wbar/ Wbar code] at google.com&lt;/ref&gt;
| Light netbook version that supports the Google desktop, including [[Google Gadgets]],&lt;ref name=&quot;eeepc.itrunsonlinux.com&quot;&gt;http://eeepc.itrunsonlinux.com/the-news/1-latest-news/126-gos3-linux-for-netbooks&lt;/ref&gt; and adds [[Wine (software)|Wine 1.0]], and [[Picasa]]. Fits on a [[Live CD]], but it was a beta and had a few bugs.&lt;ref&gt;http://groups.google.com/group/goslinux/browse_frm/thread/1154ad8ee6e3edb5&lt;/ref&gt;
|---- 
| style=&quot;background-color:#fa8072;&quot; | [http://www.thecodingstudio.com/opensource/linux/screenshots/index.php?linux_distribution_sm=gOS%203.0%20Gadgets 3.0 final]
| gOS 3.0 Gadgets final (Gnome)
| Aphrodite
| 2008-09-24
| [[Netbook]]s and [[Nettop]]s
|Hardy Heron (8.04.1)
| Yes, as live CD
| GNOME
| Wbar
| Light netbook version that supports the Google desktop, including Google Gadgets,&lt;ref name=&quot;eeepc.itrunsonlinux.com&quot;/&gt; and adds Wine 1.0, and Picasa. Fits on a Live CD. Other flavors are still announced.
|----
| style=&quot;background-color:#fa8072;&quot; | [http://www.thecodingstudio.com/opensource/linux/screenshots/index.php?linux_distribution_sm=gOS%203.0%20Gadgets 3.1 (SP1)]
| gOS 3.1 Gadgets (SP1) (Gnome)
| Aphrodite
| 2009-01-03
| Netbooks and Nettops
|Hardy Heron (8.04.1)
| Yes, as live CD
| GNOME
| Wbar
| Upgrade (bug fixed) version (service pack 1) of gOS 3.0
|----
| style=&quot;background-color:#fa8072;&quot; | 3.0 (Netbook edition beta)
| gOS 3.0 Gadgets final with netbook launcher beta
| Unknown
| 2008-10-22 (beta)
| Netbooks and Nettops
| Hardy Heron (8.04.1)
| The free netbook launcher can be installed on top of regular gOS 3.0.
| GNOME
| Wbar
| for gOS 3 a special netbook application launcher is released, although it is still in beta, and is developed independently from Good OS. With it you can switch between a [[Ubuntu Netbook Remix|Netbook launcher]] or the classic gOS desktop.&lt;ref name=&quot;wordpress netbook ed&quot; /&gt;
|}

==Live USB==
A [[Live USB]] of gOS can be created manually or with [[UNetbootin]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://unetbootin.wiki.sourceforge.net/supported-distributions Unetbootin supported distributions]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.linux-tip.net/cms/content/view/352/1/ Information] at linux-tip.net&lt;/ref&gt;

==See also==
* [[EasyPeasy]]
* [[Elive]] - visually similar to gOS
* [[Everex green computers]]
* [[Goobuntu]]
* [[Google Chrome OS]]
* [[Joli OS]]
* [[LXDE]]
* [[Zonbu]]

==References==
{{Reflist|colwidth=30em}}

==External links==
* [http://www.thinkgos.com/ Official website, (down as of early march 2011) ]
* [http://groups.google.com/group/goslinux/ gOS official forum (defunct)]
* [http://gosforums.org/ the (only) active gOS forum]
* [http://gosportal.wordpress.com/ gOS community portal]
* [http://www.fsckin.com/2007/11/03/interview-with-gos-founder-linux-for-human-beings-who-shop-at-walmart/ Interview with David Liu]

{{Ubuntu}}
{{Linux-distro}}
{{Cloud computing}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Gos (Operating System)}}
[[Category:Discontinued Linux distributions]]
[[Category:Ubuntu (operating system) derivatives]]
[[Category:Linux distributions used in appliances]]
[[Category:Cloud clients]]
[[Category:Everex]]

[[ar:جي أو إس]]
[[bn:জিওএস (অপারেটিং সিস্টেম)]]
[[ca:GOS (sistema operatiu)]]
[[de:GOS (Betriebssystem)]]
[[es:GOS]]
[[fr:GOS]]
[[it:GOS Linux]]
[[lt:GOS (operacinė sistema)]]
[[nl:GOS (Linuxdistributie)]]
[[ja:GOS]]
[[pt:GOS]]
[[ro:GOS Rocket]]
[[ru:GOS]]
[[fi:GOS]]
[[sv:GOS]]
[[pl:gOS]]
[[tr:GOS]]
[[zh:GOS]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
