<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="1401599" ns="0" title="Sopor Æternus &amp; the Ensemble of Shadows"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{multiple issues|BLP sources=February 2009|original research=November 2011|peacock=November 2011|primary sources=November 2011|self-published=November 2011|unreliable sources=November 2011|notability=November 2011}}
{{Infobox musical artist
|name                = Sopor Aeternus &amp; the Ensemble of Shadows
|Logo                = Soporaeternusandtheensembleofshadowslogo1995.gif
| alias              = Sopor Aeternus,&lt;ref name=&quot;MySpace&quot;/&gt; Sopor&lt;ref&gt;http://www.myspace.com/soporaeternusofficial&lt;/ref&gt;
| image                 =
| caption            =
|background          = group_or_band
|origin              = [[Frankfurt|Frankfurt, Hesse, Germany]]&lt;ref name=&quot;Official Italian Fan Club&quot;/&gt;
| genre              = [[Neoclassical (Dark Wave)|Neoclassical darkwave]]&lt;br/&gt;[[Dark folk]]&lt;br/&gt;[[Neo-Medieval music|Neo-Medieval]]&lt;br&gt;[[Gothic rock]]
|years_active        = 1989&amp;ndash;present&lt;ref name=&quot;MySpace&quot;/&gt;
|label               = [[Trisol Music Group|Apocalyptic Vision]]&lt;ref name=&quot;Official German Fansite&quot;&gt;[http://www.soporaeternus.de/ Sopor Aeternus  Official German Fansite]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.discogs.com/label/Apocalyptic+Vision Apocalyptic Vision on Discogs]&lt;/ref&gt;
|associated_acts     =[[White Onyx Elephants]]&lt;ref name=&quot;Official German Fansite Discography&quot;&gt;[http://www.soporaeternus.de/code/disco.html Sopor Aeternus  Official German Fansite: Discography]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;br&gt;[[Nenia C'alladhan]]&lt;ref name=&quot;Official German Fansite Discography&quot;/&gt;
|website                 = [http://www.soporaeternus.de soporaeternus.de]
|current_members     = Anna-Varney Cantodea&lt;ref&gt;http://www.soporaeternus.de/SOPOR_AETERNUS___The_Ensemble_Of_Shadows.html&lt;/ref&gt;
| past_members       = Holger&lt;ref name=&quot;Official German Fansite&quot;/&gt;
}}
'''Sopor Aeternus &amp; the Ensemble of Shadows''' ([[Latin]]: &quot;Eternal Sleep&quot;;&lt;ref name=&quot;premonition.org&quot;&gt;[http://www.premonition.org/premor.php3?lien=actu/actu.php3X1Xactuid=213007&amp;ta=3 Anna-Varney: interview on premonition.org]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://home.tiscalinet.de/daffodils/Neu/ubersopor.htm Sopor Aeternus German Fansite on tiscalinet.de]&lt;/ref&gt; often referred to as '''Sopor Aeternus''' or '''Sopor'''&lt;ref name=&quot;MySpace&quot;&gt;[http://profile.myspace.com/index.cfm?fuseaction=user.viewprofile&amp;friendID=277399870 MySpace.com - SOPOR AETERNUS (official)]&lt;/ref&gt;) is a [[darkwave]] musical project based in [[Frankfurt]]&lt;ref name=&quot;Official Italian Fan Club&quot;&gt;[http://www.soporaeternus.it/eng/home.htm Sopor Aeternus Official Italian Fan Club]&lt;/ref&gt;, founded in 1989 by '''Anna-Varney Cantodea'''.&lt;ref name=&quot;MySpace&quot;/&gt; Since the project's beginnings, Anna-Varney's music has gained notoriety for being extremely personalized, melancholic and pessimistic, drawing on a number of different musical and visual styles.&lt;ref name=&quot;soporaeternus.de&quot;&gt;http://www.soporaeternus.de/Info.html&lt;/ref&gt;

== Anna-Varney Cantodea ==
[[File:Symbol of Jusa.png|thumb|The symbol of Jusa, as seen on all Sopor Aeternus albums]]
Her name comes from the common name [[Anna (given name)|Anna]], as well as the [[Latin]] word ''cantodea'', a composed neologism meaning &quot;I sing the goddess&quot;. Cantodea had been using the pseudonym 'Varney' prior to 1997, with that name coming from the [[Victorian literature|Victorian]] [[Gothic horror]] story ''[[Varney the Vampire|Varney, the Vampire or the Feast of Blood]]''.&lt;ref name=&quot;premonition.org&quot;/&gt; 

Reportedly, Cantodea suffered beatings at the hands of her parents, and peers in school.&lt;ref&gt;http://vampirefreaks.com/content/comment.php?entry=279&amp;t=Interview+with+SOPOR+AETERNUS+%26+The+Ensemble+of+Shadows&lt;/ref&gt; At the age of six, she was subject to an out-of-body experience whilst under sedation due during a tonsillectomy.&lt;ref name=&quot;VampireFreaks&quot;&gt;[http://vampirefreaks.com/content/comment.php?entry=279&amp;t=Interview+with+SOPOR+AETERNUS+%26+The+Ensemble+of+Shadows Sopor Aeternus &amp; the Ensemble of Shadows: VampireFreaks Interview by DeathWish]&lt;/ref&gt; 

Cantodea seems to be voluntarily isolated, as she has spoken of [[fear]], disgust, or sadness when in the presence of most individuals. She has stated that she does not [[Concert|perform live]] &quot;in front of [[humans]].&quot; Despite this, she currently seems to be acquainted with the [[pagan]] and [[occult]] author [http://www.ravendigitalis.com Raven Digitalis], who is one of the &quot;managers&quot; of the [http://www.myspace.com/soporaeternusofficial official Sopor Aeternus MySpace] profile.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.myspace.com/soporaeternusofficial/blog/335165238&lt;/ref&gt; She has an affinity for [[author]] [[Edgar Allan Poe]], recreating his poems through songs on several occasions; and is also an avid supporter of several activist philosophies, including [[euthanasia]], [[LGBT rights]], [[veganism]] and [[vegetarianism]].&lt;ref name=&quot;VampireFreaks&quot;/&gt; Cantodea is a very spiritual person, with devotion placed on the [[Rome|Roman]] [[deity]] [[Saturn (mythology)|Saturn]]. Saturn's astrological symbol is combined with that of [[Jupiter (mythology)|Jupiter]]'s to create the ''Symbol of Jusa'', an icon created by Cantodea that reflects her spirituality and has become an insignia for herself and her music. Much of the artwork presented in Varney's albums include astrological imagery.

== History ==
=== 1989 &amp;ndash; 1995 ===
Sopor Aeternus &amp; the Ensemble of Shadows was founded by Anna-Varney Cantodea (then known as Varney) and Holger in 1989, and started out as a [[neue deutsche todeskunst]] musical project. The two had met in [[Frankfurt]], [[Germany]], in a [[Goth subculture|Goth]] club called Negativ. The two had met on one of Cantodea's rare outings into the public world.&lt;ref name=&quot;forum.sopor-aeternus.de&quot;&gt;[http://forum.sopor-aeternus.de/viewtopic.php?t=1427 forum.sopor-aeternus.de - Dark Entries interview]&lt;/ref&gt; Cantodea and Holger worked together with what little money they had to purchase musical equipment and recorded three demo tapes: ''[[Es reiten die Toten so schnell...]]'', ''Rufus'' and ''[[Till Time and Times Are Done]]''. The three demos were recorded between 1989 and 1992, with ''Es reiten...'' being the only publicly released cassette. They are collectively referred to as &quot;Blut der Schwarzen Rose&quot; ([[German language|German]]: &quot;Blood of the Black Rose&quot;)&lt;ref name=&quot;soporaeternus.ru&quot;&gt;[http://www.soporaeternus.ru/music.htm Sopor Aeternus &amp; the Ensemble of Shadows Russian Webpage]&lt;/ref&gt; or &quot;The Undead-Trilogy&quot;. Shortly after the cassettes were created, Holger left Sopor Aeternus.&lt;ref name=&quot;forum.sopor-aeternus.de&quot;/&gt;

In 1994, Varney was able to sign with [[Apocalyptic Vision]] to release her first album, ''[[…Ich töte mich…]]''. The album, like the demo tapes before it, showcased [[darkwave]] music with a [[Neoclassical (Dark Wave)|neo-classical bent]], punctuated by Varney's tortured voice and the recurring imagery of death, despair and [[vampires]]. It is unknown if Varney received financial assistance to produce the record.

===1995 &amp;ndash; 2003===
Sopor Aeternus' second album, ''[[Todeswunsch]]'', was an abrupt change in direction. While the album retained qualities of [[Dark Wave|darkwave]] music, the album was stripped of its heavy use of synthesizers and drum machines. A companion EP, ''[[Ehjeh Ascher Ehjeh]]'', was released later that year. Varney would also record four songs for an Apocalyptic Vision compilation, ''Jekura &amp;ndash; Deep the Eternal Forest''; two of the songs appeared under the pseudonym White Onyx Elephants.

Sopor's third album, ''[[The Inexperienced Spiral Traveller]]'', was released in 1997 alongside a remix album, ''[[Voyager: The Jugglers of Jusa]]''. It was around this time that Varney changed her name to Anna-Varney Cantodea; Anna being a common female name, and ''cantodea'', the Latin word for &quot;I sing the goddess&quot; (whereas female singer would be &quot;cantor deæ&quot;).

1999 saw the double concept album, ''[[Dead Lovers' Sarabande (Face One)]]''; a project dedicated to the memory of [[Christian Death]] frontman, [[Rozz Williams]]. ''Dead Lovers' Sarabande'' chronicled a nameless protagonist's seemingly futile quest to re-unite with her deceased lover. The album was released in two parts throughout the year, and was the first to be released on vinyl as well as on CD. The following year saw Sopor's sixth album, ''[[Songs from the Inverted Womb]]''.&lt;ref&gt;http://blogs.myspace.com/index.cfm?fuseaction=blog.view&amp;friendId=277399870&amp;blogId=536183564&lt;/ref&gt;

=== 2003 &amp;ndash; Present ===
In 2003, producer John A. Rivers was brought aboard to produce the seventh album, ''[[Es reiten die Toten so schnell|Es Reiten die Toten so Schnell]]''. Rivers would go on to produce all new Sopor Aeternus' albums. During the following year, the first six Sopor albums were remastered by Rivers and repackaged with new artwork as a lead up to their eighth album, ''[[La Chambre D'Echo|La Chabre d'Echo]]''. Where ''Es Reiten...'' started to re-introduce synthesizers into the group's sound, ''La Chambre d'Echo'' became the first album in a decade to prominently feature synthesizers and drum machines, in a nod to Sopor's first recordings. The companion EP, ''[[Flowers in Formaldehyde]]'', as well as the career-spanning rarities box set, ''[[Like a Corpse Standing in Desperation]]'', followed.

Around this time, Cantodea became more engaging with her fans; first, by [[crossdresser|crossdressing]] heavily (starting with a photoshoot for 2003's ''Es Reiten...'',) appearing more and more feminine each time. Her ninth album, ''[[Les Fleurs du Mal (album)|Les Fleurs du Mal]]'', fully embraced the feminine persona. At the beginning of 2010, the band's official ReverbNation page was updated with the status: &quot;... is currently in seclusion ... - writing beautiful new music(k).&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.reverbnation.com/soporaeternustheensembleofshadows&lt;/ref&gt; Later on in the year, Anna-Varney began posting blogs on the band's official Vampire Freaks page, mentioning the upcoming trilogy ''A Triptychon of Ghosts''. On September, 26 it was announced that ''[[A Strange Thing to Say]]'' was released in 2010 as the opening chapter to ''A Triptychon of Ghosts''. Sopor Aeternus' 10th studio album, ''[[Have You Seen This Ghost?]]'' was released in April, 2011 and in the same year, its latest album ''[[Children of the Corn]]'' will be released on November, 25.

==Musical Characteristics==
[[File:Sopor entrevista 5.jpg|right||thumb|Cantodea, [[photographed]] in 2000 for ''[[Songs from the Inverted Womb]]'']]The sound of Sopor Aeternus is rooted in [[renaissance music|renaissance]] and [[baroque music]], with main use of [[brass instruments]], [[woodwinds]], [[string instrument|string]]s, [[pipe organ]]s, [[Bell (instrument)|bell]]s, and [[guitar]]s. While earlier works used [[drum machine]]s, later albums feature live percussion. Cantodea's work has shown a progression towards livelier arrangements and more [[wall of sound]] production, compared to earlier works; more recent albums have also employed a slightly more mainstream sound, incorporating [[Electronic music|electronic]] and slight [[gothic rock]] sentiments.&lt;ref name=&quot;soporaeternus.de&quot;/&gt; Though considered by genre a [[darkwave]] band, Cantodea has stated that she ignores this notion and simply creates ''&quot;...-music for dead children [and otherwise wounded souls], that is all.&quot;'' On several occasions, Cantodea has re-recorded and recycled elements from previous songs; other times, motifs are used; the most notable example is &quot;Birth - Fiendish Figuration&quot;, which has been re-recorded at least four times.

Cantodea has clearly stated that she creates her music about herself, solely for herself. Major themes include death, unrequited love, karmatic pain, loneliness, sadness, spirituality and failure; more recently, Cantodea has featured occultism, sexuality and romance into her lyrics. A strong recurring theme is [[transexuality]],&lt;ref name=&quot;soporaeternus.de&quot;/&gt; especially the removal of male genitalia. Several albums feature Cantodea nude with a [[vagina]] (which was edited in in post-production.) Many allusions to spirituality and Roman deities appear in her lyrics; aside from Jupiter and Saturn, [[Morpheus (mythology)|Morpheus]], [[Hades (mythology)|Hades]], [[Uranus (mythology)|Uranus]] and [[Charon (mythology)|Charon]] have been addressed by name. Other supernatural figures mentioned include the Sister of Self-Destruction, the Goat, the Old Man and the Lord of the Darkest Side.

==Discography==
===[[Demo]] Tapes===
The three [[demo tape]]s are often referred to as &quot;Blut der schwarzen Rose&quot; or &quot;The Undead-Trilogy&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;soporaeternus.ru&quot;/&gt; Only the first has been released.

* ''[[Es reiten die Toten so schnell…]]'' (1989)
*''[[Rufus (demo)|Rufus]]'' (1992)
*''[[Till Time and Times Are Done]]'' (1992)

===Studio Albums===
* ''[[…Ich töte mich…|&quot;…Ich Töte Mich Jedesmal aufs Neue, doch Ich Bin Unsterblich, und Ich Erstehe Wieder auf; in Einer Vision des Untergangs…&quot;]]'' (1994)
* ''[[Todeswunsch - Sous le soleil de Saturne|Todeswunsch - Sous le Soleil de Saturne]]'' (1995)
* ''[[The Inexperienced Spiral Traveller|The Inexperienced Spiral Traveller (Aus dem Schoß der Hölle Ward Geboren die Totensonne)]]'' (1997)
* ''[[Dead Lovers' Sarabande (Face One)]]'' (1999)
* ''[[Dead Lovers' Sarabande (Face Two)]]'' (1999)
* ''[[Songs from the Inverted Womb]]'' (2000)
* ''[[Es reiten die Toten so schnell|Es Reiten die Toten so Schnell (or: the Vampyre Sucking at His Own Vein)]]'' (2003)
* ''[[La Chambre D'Echo - Where the dead Birds sing|La Chambre d'Echo - Where the Dead Birds Sing]]'' (2004)
* ''[[Les Fleurs du Mal (album)|Les Fleurs du Mal - Die Blumen des Bösen]]'' (2007)
* ''[[Have You Seen This Ghost?| A Triptychon of Ghosts (Part Two) - Have You Seen This Ghost?]]'' (2011)

===[[Extended play|EP]]s and Remix Albums (&quot;Sister Albums&quot;)===
* ''[[Ehjeh Ascher Ehjeh]]'' (1995)
* ''[[Voyager - The Jugglers of Jusa]]'' (1997)
* ''[[Flowers in Formaldehyde]]'' (2004)
* ''[[Sanatorium Altrosa|Sanatorium Altrosa (Musical Therapy for ''Spiritual'' Dysfunction)]]'' (2008)
* ''[[A Strange Thing to Say|A Triptychon of Ghosts (Part One) - A Strange Thing to Say]]'' (2010)
* ''[[Children of the Corn (album)| A Triptychon of Ghosts (Part Three) - Children of the Corn]]'' (2011)

===Singles===
* ''[[The Goat / The Bells Have Stopped Ringing|The Goat/The Bells Have Stopped Ringing]]'' (2005)
* ''[[In der Palästra]]'' (2007)
* ''[[Imhotep (CD Single)|Imhotep]]'' (2011)

===Other Releases===
*''[[Jekura - Deep the Eternal Forest]]'' (1995) – a compilation featuring four songs by Sopor Aeternus&lt;ref name=&quot;discogs.com&quot;&gt;[http://www.discogs.com/release/339766 Various - Jekura - Deep the Eternal Forest&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;
* ''[[Nenia C'alladhan]]'' (2002) – a self-titled side project with [[Constance Fröhling]]
* ''[[Like a Corpse Standing in Desperation]]'' (2005) – a boxed set of rarities and hard-to-find albums
* ''The Goat and Other Re-Animated Bodies'' (2009) - DVD of previously released videos

==Videography==
Sopor Aeternus has released promotional videos to accompany their music.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.soporaeternus.de/Video.html&lt;/ref&gt; Most videos are noticeably abstract, with several layers of footage composited to create a distinctly blurred effect.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.soporaeternus.de/VIDEOS.html&lt;/ref&gt; ''Deep the Eternal Forest'' received two versions: one with Varney in white robes, and the second with Varney in black robes.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=MmXKlxDKo30&lt;/ref&gt; The first six listed here were included as part of the box set ''[[Like a Corpse Standing in Desperation]]'', while ''In der Palästra'' was included on its own DVD single. All of Sopor Aeternus' videos have been directed by Anna-Varney Cantodea herself.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.imdb.com/name/nm2056971/&lt;/ref&gt;

==Notes==
{{Reflist}}

==References==
{{Reflist|2}}

==External Links==
* [http://www.soporaeternus.de/ Sopor Aeternus' Official Website] -
* [http://www.soporaeternus.de/bloxx.html Blog of Anna-Varney Cantodea]
* [http://www.vampirefreaks.com/soporaeternus Sopor Aeternus at VampireFreaks.com]
* {{youtube|u=soporvideoarchive}}
* [http://www.reverbnation.com/soporaeternustheensembleofshadows Sopor Aeternus on Reverbnation.com]
* [http://www.infrarot.de/sopor-aeternus/c3185 Official Sopor Aeternus retailer]

{{DEFAULTSORT:Sopor Aeternus And The Ensemble Of Shadows}}
[[Category:Sopor Aeternus]]

[[bg:Sopor Aeternus and the Ensemble of Shadows]]
[[ca:Sopor Aeternus &amp; the Ensemble of Shadows]]
[[de:Sopor Aeternus]]
[[es:Sopor Aeternus and the Ensemble of Shadows]]
[[fr:Sopor Aeternus &amp; The Ensemble of Shadows]]
[[it:Sopor Aeternus &amp; The Ensemble of Shadows]]
[[la:Sopor Aeternus]]
[[hu:Sopor Aeternus &amp; The Ensemble Of Shadows]]
[[pl:Sopor Aeternus]]
[[pt:Sopor Aeternus &amp; The Ensemble of Shadows]]
[[ro:Sopor Aeternus]]
[[ru:Sopor Aeternus &amp; The Ensemble of Shadows]]
[[sv:Sopor Aeternus]]
[[tr:Sopor Aeternus &amp; The Ensemble Of Shadows]]
[[zh:永恒沉睡]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
