<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="14071771" ns="0" title="Hyatt Regency Atlanta"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Infobox hotel
| hotel_name         = Hyatt Regency Atlanta
| logo               =  
| logo_width         =  
| image              = Hyatt-regency-atlanta-side.jpg
| image_width        = 250px
| caption            = Viewed from the [[Atlanta Marriott Marquis]]
| location           = [[United States]]
| address            = 265 Peachtree Street NE&lt;br&gt;[[Atlanta]], [[Georgia (U.S. state)|Georgia]]
| chain              = [[Global Hyatt Corporation]]
| coordinates        = {{coord|33.76138|-84.38666|region:US-GA_type:landmark|display=title,inline}}
| opening_date       = 1967
| closing_date       = 
| developer          = 
| architect          = [[John C. Portman, Jr.|John Portman &amp; Associates]] 
| operator           = 
| cost               = 
| owner              = 
| number_of_rooms    = 1,260
| number_of_suites   = 
| number_of_restaurants= ''Parasol Bar'' &lt;br&gt;''Perks'' &lt;br&gt;''Kafe Köbenhavn'' &lt;br&gt;''Avanzare''
| floor_area         = &lt;!-- {{convert||sqft|abbr=on}} --&gt;
| floors             = 24
| height             = {{convert|103.63|m|abbr=on}}
| parking            = 
| website            = [http://www.hyattregencyatlanta.com/ www.HyattRegencyAtlanta.com]
| footnotes          = &lt;ref&gt;{{emporis|121255}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{skyscraperpage|1432}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{structurae|s0025177}}&lt;/ref&gt;
}}

The '''Hyatt Regency Atlanta''', located on [[Peachtree Street]] in [[downtown Atlanta]], [[Georgia (U.S. state)|Georgia]], is an award winning hotel which opened in 1967. The [[John C. Portman, Jr.]] designed building was the first hotel constructed around an atrium, and has influenced [[hotel design]] since.{{Citation needed|date=November 2007}} When it was first built in 1967, the Regency Hyatt House, as the hotel was originally called, instantly became one of the most recognized buildings in Atlanta, and its open-air 22-story atrium and revolving rooftop restaurant became a &quot;must-see&quot; attraction by Atlantans and tourists alike.

The building consists of the main &quot;Atrium Tower&quot; and two extensions, completed in 1971 and 1982, containing a total of 1,260 rooms.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.emporis.com/en/wm/bu/?id=hyattregencyatlanta-atlanta-ga-usa Hyatt Regency Atlanta, Atlanta&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt; On top of the Hyatt Regency is a revolving restaurant called Polaris, located just beneath the blue dome-shaped structure which gives the hotel its distinctive profile. This was John Portman's first designed revolving restaurant of many. When the hotel first opened, the restaurant gave diners an ever-changing panoramic view of the entire city; however, as taller buildings were erected on all sides of the hotel, the restaurant's view became increasingly constricted. Hotel managers cited renovation needs when the Polaris closed in August 2004, but no plans to re-open the restaurant have been announced.

In 1971 the Ivy Tower (now called Radius Tower) was constructed, which was also designed by John Portman. It closely resembles his [[Westin Peachtree Plaza]], which opened five years later. So similar are the two buildings that in 1981, the Tower doubled for the Peachtree Plaza in the film [[Sharky's Machine (film)|Sharky's Machine]] starring [[Burt Reynolds]].  Stuntman [[Dar Robinson]] dropped ({{convert|67|m|abbr=on}} from the Tower, setting a record for the highest freefall (unrestrained) jump from a building in a film.  In 1970, [[Jim Morrison]], lead singer of The Doors, stayed at The Hyatt Regency Atlanta while attending the [[Atlanta Film Festival]].  At the awards ceremony, he gave his room key to the woman presenting him the plaque.

In 1982, the International Tower was added, which is the same as the original design but has expanded rooms and suites.

&lt;gallery&gt;
File:Hyatt regency atlanta atrium.JPG|View of the Atrium and glass elevators looking up from the lobby floor
File:Hyatt-regency-atlanta-atrium.jpg|View of the Atrium from the 8th floor
File:Hyatt-regency-atlanta-aerial.jpg|View of the Hyatt from the [[Westin Peachtree Plaza]]
&lt;/gallery&gt;

==References==
{{Reflist}}

==External links==
{{commons|Atlanta Hyatt Regency}}
*[http://www.hyattregencyatlanta.com/The Hyatt Regency Atlanta official website]
*[http://atlantaregency.hyatt.com/hyatt/hotels/index.jsp?src=tig_wiki_atlra_lk_0909 The Hyatt Regency Atlanta corporate website]
*[http://www.invisiblethemepark.com/2011/04/hyatt-regency-atlanta-and-jim-morrison When Jim Morrison of The Doors Stayed at The Hyatt Regency Atlanta]

{{Atlanta landmarks}}

[[Category:Buildings and structures with revolving restaurants]]
[[Category:Hotels in Atlanta, Georgia]]
[[Category:Hyatt]]
[[Category:Skyscraper hotels in the United States]]
[[Category:Buildings and structures completed in 1967]]
[[Category:John C. Portman, Jr. buildings]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
