<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="14100573" ns="0" title="Reel Corporation"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Infobox_Company
| company_name = Reel Corporation
| company_logo = [[Image:Reel corporation logo.jpg|150px]]
| company_type = Subsidiary
| parent = [[Village Roadshow Entertainment Group]]
| owner = [[Village Roadshow]]
| foundation = 1980
| location_city =  Melbourne, Australia
| location_country = Australia
| key_people = 
| num_employees =
| industry = [[Motion picture|Motion pictures]]
| products =
| revenue = 
| operating_income =
| homepage = 
}}

'''Reel Corporation''' is an independent Australian film distributor. Reel Corporation Australia established a joint venture sales company with [[Village Roadshow|Roadshow Entertainment]] called Reel DVD.  

==History==
Reel Corporation distributes many films, children programmes and television series.  It also deals with independent studio film content titles which would receive limited release in cinemas. While instead [[Village Roadshow]] would release big blockbusters from studios such as [[Warner Bros.]] and [[New Line Cinema]].

Reel Corporation would look after genre titles which didn't necessarily have big studio output deals, which aided in International Distribution for films which include '[[Teaching Mrs. Tingle]]' and '[[Bride of Chucky]]'.

==Revival==
Starting in February 2007, Village Roadshow allocated many of its 'smaller' titles to Reel DVD to be repackaged and re-distributed, and sold at discount prices.  These also included big budget films like '[[Jason X]]' and '[[The Art of War (film)]]' which hadn't achieved high sales on DVD.  They were submitted for Revision at the [[Office of Film and Literature Classification]] (Australia's censorship board) and officially given new Classification logos and simpler Classification Advice.

Reel continues to distribute small scale and direct to DVD films, the most recent being '[[A Love Song for Bobby Long]]' 2007.

[[Category:Film production companies of Australia]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
