<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="1413600" ns="0" title="New York University School of Law"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Coord|40.7305|N|73.9995|W|type:edu|display=title}}
{{Infobox Law School
|name           = New York University School of Law
|image          = [[Image:NyuTorch.png|75px|New York University]]
|established    = 1835
|head  = [[Richard Revesz]]
|type           = [[Private university|Private]]
|city           = [[New York City]]
|state          = [[New York]]
|ranking = 6&lt;ref&gt;[http://grad-schools.usnews.rankingsandreviews.com/grad/law Law - Best Graduate Schools - Education - US News and World Report]&lt;/ref&gt;
|country        = [[United States|USA]]
|students      = 1700
| faculty        = 125&lt;ref name=ABAData&gt;[http://officialguide.lsac.org/SearchResults/SchoolPage_PDFs/ABA_LawSchoolData/ABA2599.pdf Official ABA Data]&lt;/ref&gt;
| bar pass rate  = 97.18%&lt;ref name=ABAData/&gt;
|annual tuition = $46,196&lt;ref name=ABAData/&gt;
|homepage=[http://www.law.nyu.edu www.law.nyu.edu]
|aba profile    = [http://officialguide.lsac.org/SearchResults/SchoolPage_PDFs/ABA_LawSchoolData/ABA2599.pdf NYU Law Profile]
}}

The '''New York University School of Law''' ('''NYU Law''') is the law school of [[New York University]]. Established in 1835, the school offers the [[Juris Doctor|J.D.]], [[LL.M.]], and [[J.S.D.]] degrees in law, and is located in [[Greenwich Village]], in the [[New York City]] [[borough (New York City)|borough]] of [[Manhattan]].

NYU Law was the first [[Law school in the United States#Oldest law schools|law school]] established in New York City.  It is considered to be among the '''Top Ten''' most selective and prestigious [[law schools in the United States]] and is currently ranked #6 by the [[U.S. News &amp; World Report]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://grad-schools.usnews.rankingsandreviews.com/best-graduate-schools/top-law-schools/rankings America's Best Graduate Schools 2009: Top Law Schools],. ''[[U.S. News &amp; World Report]]''. Accessed July 12, 2009.&lt;/ref&gt; In terms of specialization, NYU Law is ranked # 1 in both International Law&lt;ref&gt;http://grad-schools.usnews.rankingsandreviews.com/best-graduate-schools/top-law-schools/international-law&lt;/ref&gt; and Tax Law&lt;ref&gt;http://grad-schools.usnews.rankingsandreviews.com/best-graduate-schools/top-law-schools/tax-law&lt;/ref&gt; by the said report. The school is especially known for its dedication to the public sector, emphasis on diversity, and large firm placement. The median starting salary of NYU Law graduates working in the private sector was $160,000 for the class of 2008 (a figure which does not include bonuses).&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.top-law-schools.com/nyu-law-school.html],. &quot;[[Top Law Schools]]&quot;. Accessed August 8, 2010.&lt;/ref&gt;

==Academics==
[[Image:Nyu law vanderbilt.jpg|right|500px|New York University School of Law, Vanderbilt Hall]]

NYU Law publishes eight student-edited [[law review|law journals]], which are, in order of their founding:

{|
|-
| valign=&quot;top&quot; |
*[[NYU Law Review|New York University Law Review]]
*[[NYU Annual Survey of American Law]]
*[[NYU Journal of International Law and Politics]]
*[http://www.law.nyu.edu/pubs/socialchange/ Review of Law &amp; Social Change]
| valign=&quot;top&quot; |
*[http://www.environmentallawjournal.com Environmental Law Journal]
*[http://www.law.nyu.edu/journals/legislation/ Journal of Legislation &amp; Public Policy]
*[http://www.law.nyu.edu/journals/lawliberty/ Journal of Law &amp; Liberty]
*[http://www.law.nyu.edu/journals/lawbusiness/ Journal of Law &amp; Business]
|}

The law school's longstanding commitment to public service is exemplified by its many notable alumni and the [[Root-Tilden Scholarship|Root-Tilden-Kern Scholarship Program]], a full-tuition scholarship awarded each year to twenty students committed to public service.

NYU Law offers several fellowships to students admitted to the LLM Program. The most selective is the Hauser Global Scholarship: eight to ten top LLM students are admitted from all over the world. The scholarship includes full tuition waiver and reasonable accommodation costs. In addition, it offers the Hugo Grotius as well as Vanderbilt scholarships for International law studies and other branches of law respectively.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.nyulawglobal.org/fellowsscholars/HauserGlobalScholars-LL.M.Candidates.htm]&lt;/ref&gt;

The Law school has a law and business program in which eight of the nation's preeminent student-leaders in law and business are awarded fellowships in the Mitchell Jacobson Leadership Program&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.law.nyu.edu/leadershipprogram].&lt;/ref&gt;

NYU Law also hosts the original chapter of the [[Unemployment Action Center]].

===LL.M. in Taxation Program===

NYU Law School's LL.M. in Taxation program is widely considered to be the strongest LL.M. in Taxation program in the United States, and has been consistently ranked #1 by the U.S. News &amp; World Report magazine since they started ranking specialty law school programs in 1992.&lt;ref&gt;http://grad-schools.usnews.rankingsandreviews.com/best-graduate-schools/top-law-schools/tax-law-rankings&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;http://taxprof.typepad.com/taxprof_blog/2010/04/us-news-.html&lt;/ref&gt; Joshua D. Blank is currently the faculty director of the program.&lt;ref&gt;https://its.law.nyu.edu/facultyprofiles/profile.cfm?personID=23511&lt;/ref&gt;

Tax LL.M. students are permitted to enroll in a general course of study or specialize in specific areas such as business taxation or estate planning.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.law.nyu.edu/llmjsd/tax/academicprograms/graduatetaxprogram/suggestedcurricula/index.htm&lt;/ref&gt; Due to its location in the heart of corporate America, many of the program's professors are the leading practitioners in their respective fields.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.law.nyu.edu/llmjsd/tax/index.htm&lt;/ref&gt;

LL.M is an abbreviation for Master of Laws, an advanced academic degree, pursued by those holding a professional law degree. In general, there are two types of LL.M. programs in the United States. The majority are programs designed to expose foreign legal graduates to the American Common Law. The other programs involve post doctoral study of a specialized area of the law such as Admiralty, Tax Law, Banking and Financial Law, Elder Law, Aeronautical Law or International Law.&lt;ref&gt;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Master_of_Laws&lt;/ref&gt;

===Partnerships===

In 2005, NYU Law entered into an agreement with the [[Osgoode Hall Law School]] of [[York University]], in [[Toronto]], [[Canada]], that will allow select students to obtain a joint-[[Bachelor of Laws]] (LL.B.) and JD, studying at both schools, in four years. The competitive program began in the fall of 2006 and accommodates up to 3 students per year. Since then, they have also implemented a jointly granted NYU/Osgoode LLB/LLM program in which graduates are granted the LLB as well as an LLM from NYU in only 3 and a half years instead of the normally required four.
More recently, the NYU School of Law has entered into similar dual degree agreements with the [[National University of Singapore Faculty of Law]] and the [[Melbourne Law School|University of Melbourne Law School]].

[[Oxford University]] has a program of academic exchanges with New York University School of Law, mainly involving Faculty members and research students working in areas of shared interest.&lt;ref&gt;[http://denning.law.ox.ac.uk/members/partner.shtml]&lt;/ref&gt;

NYU Law offers a dual-degree program with [[Harvard]]'s [[John F. Kennedy School of Government]]. Students may earn a JD/MPA or a JD/MPP.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.law.nyu.edu/admissions/jdadmissions/dualdegreeprograms/harvarduniversity/index.htm&lt;/ref&gt;

NYU Law offers a dual-degree program with [[Princeton University|Princeton]]'s [[Woodrow Wilson School of Public and International Affairs]]. Students may earn a JD/MPA.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.law.nyu.edu/admissions/jdadmissions/dualdegreeprograms/princetonuniversity/index.htm&lt;/ref&gt;

There is also a limited amount of cross-registration permitted with [[Columbia Law School]]. Each year, a limited number of students are permitted to take classes at each other's schools.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.law.nyu.edu/recordsandregistration/crossregistration/columbialawschoolnyuschooloflawexchange/index.htm&lt;/ref&gt; Columbia Law and NYU Law also play a basketball game every spring, the [[Deans' Cup]], to raise money for their public interest and community service organizations.

==Faculty==

Some of NYU's notable professors include:

{|
|-
| valign=&quot;top&quot; |
*[[Philip Alston]] (Human Rights)
*[[Anthony Amsterdam]] (Criminal Law, Capital Punishment)
*[[Rachel Barkow]] (Administrative Law, Criminal Law and Procedure)
*[[Derrick Bell]] (Constitutional Law)
*[[Paul G.H. Chevigny]] (Evidence, Human rights)
*[[Jerome Cohen]] (Chinese Law)
*[[Norman Dorsen]] (Constitutional Law)
*[[Ronald Dworkin]] (Legal Philosophy)
*[[Richard Allen Epstein|Richard Epstein]] (Law and Economics)
*[[Cynthia Estlund]] (Labor Law, Employment Law, Property)
*[[Samuel Estreicher]] (Labor Law, Employment Law)
*[[Barry E Friedman]] (Constitutional Law)
*[[Stephen Gillers]] ([[Legal Ethics]])
*[[Douglas H. Ginsburg]] ([[Administrative Law]])
*[[Karen Joy Greenberg]] executive director of the Center on Law and Security&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Leadership &amp; Staff {{!}} The Center on Law and Security | Policy, Programs, Publications | at NYU School of Law|url=http://www.lawandsecurity.org/About/leadership|publisher=[[New York University School of Law]]|accessdate=27 July 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;  
*[[Helen Hershkoff]] (Procedure, Civil Liberties)
*[[Samuel Issacharoff]] (Procedure, Democracy)
| valign=&quot;top&quot; |
*[[Mattias Kumm]] (Legal Philosophy)
*[[Theodor Meron]] (International Law)
*[[Arthur R. Miller]] (Civil Procedure, Copyright, and Privacy)
*[[Thomas Nagel]] (Legal Philosophy)
*[[Burt Neuborne]] (Evidence, Holocaust Litigation Expert)
*[[Richard Pildes]] (Constitutional Law, Election Law)
*[[Samuel Rascoff]] (National Security, Regulatory Law)
*[[Richard Revesz]] (Dean, Environmental Law)
*[[Samuel Scheffler]] (Legal Philosophy)
*[[Catherine Sharkey]] (Tort Law, Empirical Legal Studies)
*[[Bryan Stevenson]] (Criminal Law, Capital Punishment)
*[http://its.law.nyu.edu/facultyprofiles/profile.cfm?personID=20316 Richard Stewart] (Administrative Law)
*[[Jeremy Waldron]] (Legal Philosophy)
*[[Joseph H. H. Weiler]] (International Law)
*[[Kenji Yoshino]] (Constitutional Law)
|}

==Notable alumni==
:''See main article [[List of NYU Law School people]]; see also [[List of New York University people]]

Famous alumni include Governor and Democratic presidential candidate [[Samuel J. Tilden]]; former New York City mayors [[Fiorello La Guardia]], [[Ed Koch]] and [[Rudy Giuliani]]; New York City Police Commissioner [[Raymond Kelly]]; the four founders of the prominent law firm [[Wachtell, Lipton, Rosen &amp; Katz]]; Evan Chesler, the current Presiding Partner at [[Cravath, Swaine &amp; Moore]]; comedian [[Demetri Martin]]; [[President of the Republic of China|Republic of China president]] [[Ma Ying-Jeou]]; former [[President of Panama]] [[Guillermo Endara]]; former Director of the FBI [[Louis Freeh]]; U.S. Senators [[Lamar Alexander]], [[Rudy Boschwitz]] and [[Jacob Javits]]; sportscaster [[Howard Cosell]]; Former NFL Commissioner [[Paul Tagliabue]];NHL Commissioner [[Gary Bettman]];[[John F. Kennedy, Jr.]]; Special Inspector General of the Troubled Asset Relief Program [[Neil Barofsky]]; many U.S. Representatives, including [[Mitchell Jenkins]], [[Jefferson Monroe Levy]] and [[Isaac Siegel]]; former Chairman of [[Paramount Pictures]] Jonathan Dolgen; Hollywood and Broadway producer [[Marc E. Platt]]; Hollywood producer and former Chairman and CEO of Sony Pictures Entertainment [[Peter Guber]]; several corporate leaders including [[Interpublic Group of Companies]] Chairman and CEO Michael I. Roth; [[ConocoPhillips]] President and COO John A. Carrig; [[Robert Half International]] Chairman and CEO Harold Max Messner; and [[Southwest Airlines]] founder [[Herb Kelleher]]; as well as [[Nobel Peace Prize]] laureates [[Elihu Root]] and [[Mohamed ElBaradei]]. 

Among judges, [[Judith Kaye]], former Chief Judge of the [[New York Court of Appeals]], is an alumna; [[Dennis G. Jacobs]], Chief Judge of the [[United States Court of Appeals for the Second Circuit]] is an alumnus. Judge [[Pauline Newman]] of the [[United States Court of Appeals for the Federal Circuit]] also graduated from NYU Law.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www3.law.nyu.edu/alumni/notable.html Notable NYU School of Law Alumni], NYU School of Law. Accessed July 7, 2007.&lt;/ref&gt; NYU Law alumni have served as judges of the [[International Court of Justice]], which is popularly known as the [[World Court]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.nyu.edu/nyutoday/archives/16/04/Stories/Law.html &quot;NYU Law’s Owada named to International Court of Justice: Joins three law school alumni already on ICJ], ''NYU Today'', Vol. 16 No. 4, December 10, 2002. Accessed July 7, 2007.&lt;/ref&gt;

==Admissions==
Admission to the New York University School of Law is highly competitive. For the class entering Fall 2010, 476 full-time students out of close to 8,000 applicants enrolled.  The 25th and 75th [[LSAT]] percentiles were 169 (97th percentile) and 175 (99th percentile), respectively, with a median of 172 (98th to 99th percentile). The 25th and 75th undergraduate [[GPA]] percentiles were 3.6 and 3.9, respectively.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.law.nyu.edu/admissions/jdadmissions/applicants/classprofile/index.htm]. ''[[NYU Law School Admission]]''. Accessed August 31, 2010.&lt;/ref&gt;

==Facilities==

{{Boxboxtop|NYU School of Law Halls|right}}
&lt;!-- Image with unknown copyright status removed: [[Image:furman1.jpg|thumb|150px|Furman {{speedy-image-c|2007-06-02}} ]] --&gt;

&lt;!-- Image with unknown copyright status removed: [[Image:vanderbiltnyu.jpg|right|thumb|150px|Vanderbilt Hall {{deletable image-caption}}]] --&gt;
[[File:Vanderbilt arches NYU jeh.JPG|thumb|Vanderbilt Hall]]
[[Image:NYU-Mercer Street Residence.jpg|thumb|Mercer Street Residence]]
{{Boxboxbottom}}
NYU Law School facilities at the school's Washington Square Campus include:

===Furman Hall===
Located on West Third Street between Sullivan and Thompson, Furman Hall opened on January 22, 2004 and is named for alumnus and donor [[Jay Furman]]. It connects to Vanderbilt Hall through the law library, part of which is underneath Sullivan street. The underground level also hosts the Lawyering faculty. Floors one-three have classrooms, lounges, and study space. The fourth floor hosts the career counseling program, and the fifth and sixth floors house the legal practice clinics. The highest floors, generally inaccessible to non-residents, are luxury apartments for faculty and their families. The ninth floor is accessible to students and hosts the Lester Pollack Colloquium room.

===Vanderbilt Hall===
The Law School's Main Building, named after [[Arthur T. Vanderbilt]], occupies the entire block between West Third and Washington Square South (West Fourth) and between Macdougal and Sullivan Streets. Part of the first floor as well as the underground floors host the library, which it shares with Furman Hall. The first floor also holds the auditorium, student center, and main banquet hall. The second floor is mostly classrooms, while the third and fourth floors are mostly faculty and dean offices.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.law.nyu.edu/specialevents/locationguide/vanderbilthall/index.htm&lt;/ref&gt;

===Mercer Street Residence===
Located at 240 Mercer Street, on the southern side of West Third street, adjacent to Broadway, and a couple blocks east of D'Agostino Hall, Wilf Hall, Furman Hall and Vanderbilt Hall, the [http://www.law.nyu.edu/housing/oncampushousing/accommodations/mercerstreetresidence/index.htm Mercer Residence] houses approximately 500 hundred Law students and faculty. Its rooms are quite a bit more spacious than those in D'Agostino Hall. The seventh floor enjoys a terrace and two computer rooms and the 8th floor provides four small study rooms. The lobby level houses a game room (pool table, foos ball, dart board, ping pong table)and the basement is home to &quot;Mercer Pub&quot; (a room with couches, tables, and a small kitchen that can also be reserved by student groups for social events) and several student run organizations.  Mercer Residence is available for summer housing for non-NYU Law students through its [http://www.law.nyu.edu/housing/summerhousing/summerlivinginnyslny/index.htm Summer Living in New York program].

===D'Agostino Residence Hall===
Located at the intersection of West Third Street and MacDougal Street in Greenwich Village, [http://www.law.nyu.edu/housing/oncampushousing/accommodations/dagostinohall/index.htm D'Agostino Residence Hall] houses approximately 300 law students and faculty.{{Citation needed|date=May 2010}}It is across the street from the backside of the main building of the law school, Vanderbilt Hall, and less than 1 block from Wilf Hall and Furman Hall. The building has two terraces - one on the 12th floor and one on the 14th floor- that offer beautiful views of Washington Square Park and the Empire State Building.&lt;ref&gt;http://128.122.51.11/nyu_law_website/housing/ratesandoptions/summerlivinginnewyorkslny/longtermratesandoptions/dagostinohall/index.htm&lt;/ref&gt;

The lobby is a double-split-level. Elevators to the apartments are on the highest level, the Front Desk is on the street level, and The Commons (residents' lounge with computers and printers) is on the lower level.  One floor beneath The Commons is the sub-basement, home to most of NYU's legal journals. The second (above-ground) floor, houses numerous administrative offices (Development, Alumni Relations, Special Events, Communications, Human Resources and Financial Services).  Two large function rooms - Lipton Hall and the Faculty Club - are also located in the building.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.law.nyu.edu/housing/oncampushousing/accommodations/dagostinohall/index.htm&lt;/ref&gt; 

The law building is named after Filomen D'Agostino, one of the first woman lawyers, who graduated in 1920.  Later in life, Ms. D'Agostino donated $4 million to support residential scholarship and faculty research; the school responded by naming their new apartment building after her.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9403E6DC1E38F933A05751C1A962948260|work=[[The New York Times]]|title=Law School at N.Y.U. Given a $4 Million Gift|date=December 30, 1984}}&lt;/ref&gt;

D'Agostino Hall is also available for summer housing for non-NYU Law students through its [http://www.law.nyu.edu/housing/summerhousing/summerlivinginnyslny/index.htm Summer Living in New York program].

===22 Washington Square North===
22 Washington Square North, located in a historic 1830's townhouse on the north side of [[Washington Square Park]] in &quot;[[Washington Square North|The Row]]&quot;, houses the [http://www.nyustraus.org/index.html Straus Institute for the Advanced Study of Law &amp; Justice], the [http://centers.law.nyu.edu/jeanmonnet/ Jean Monnet Center for International and Regional Economic Law &amp; Justice], and the [http://www.nyutikvah.org/ Tikvah Center for Law &amp; Jewish Civilization].  This building was renovated in 2009 by [[Morris Adjmi Architects]], has a green wall, and should meet silver Leadership in Energy and Environmental Design standards.

===Wilf Hall===
Wilf Hall, at 139 Macdougal Street, houses approximately a dozen of the schools centers, programs and institutes as well as the admissions offices (Graduate and JD).  Per the [http://blogs.law.nyu.edu/magazine/2010/an-illustrated-guide-to-wilf-hall/ NYU Law Magazine], it is a &quot;campus destination for faculty, students, and research scholars from an array of disciplines to exchange ideas and, through their work, shape the public discourse around the leading social and politicial issues of the day&quot;.  Wilf Hall is hoped to be one of a small number of buildings in New York City to achieve a platinum rating in the Leadership in Energy and Environmental Design Green Building Rating System.  Among numerous environmental features, Wilf Hall has a green roof and terraces and a bicycle storage room and showers for commuting riders.

Wilf Hall also contains the [[Provincetown Playhouse]].  The playhouse opened in the 1920s and premiered many Eugene O'Neil plays.  The theatre is run by NYU's Steinhardt School of Education.

Wilf Hall was designed by [[Morris Adjmi Architects]].

==Centers and Institutes==

NYU Law is home to many centers and institutes, specializing in various areas of law.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.law.nyu.edu/centers/bytopic/index.htm&lt;/ref&gt;

The [[Brennan Center for Justice]] is a progressive, non-partisan public policy and law institute that focuses on issues involving democracy and justice.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.brennancenter.org/&lt;/ref&gt;

The Center for Law, Economics and Organization promotes interdisciplinary research and teaching in law and economics. It is directed by Jennifer Arlen, Oren Bar-Gill, John Ferejohn, Mark Geistfeld, Lewis Kornhauser, and Geoffrey Miller.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.law.nyu.edu/centers/laweconomics/index.htm&lt;/ref&gt;

The Center on Law and Security is an independent, non-partisan, global center of expertise designed to promote an informed understanding of the major legal and security issues that define the post-9/11 environment.  Towards that end, the Center brings together policymakers, practitioners, scholars, journalists and other experts who might not otherwise meet to address major issues and gaps in policy discourse and to provide concrete policy recommendations. Its fellows include: [[Peter Bergen]], [[Sidney Blumenthal]], [[Peter Clarke (police officer)|Peter Clarke]], [[Roger Cressey]], [[Joshua Dratel]], Carol Dysinger, [[Barton Gellman]], Bernard Haykel, Thomas Hegghammer, Brian Palmer, [[Michael A. Sheehan|Michael Sheehan]], Alexandra Starr, Robert Windrem, and [[Lawrence Wright]].&lt;ref name=&quot;CLS fellows&quot;&gt;{{cite web |author=. |year=2011 |title=Fellows |publisher=[[New York University School of Law#Centers and Institutes|Center on Law and Security]], New York University School of Law |url=http://www.lawandsecurity.org/about_fellows.cfm}}&lt;/ref&gt; Its former fellows included: Paul Cruickshank, [[Amos Elon]], [[Baltasar Garzón]], [[Tara McKelvey]], [[Dana Priest]], and [[Nir Rosen]].&lt;ref name=&quot;CLS fellows&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |author=Greenberg, Karen J. |date=February 16, 2011 |title=Official CLS statement on Nir Rosen |publisher=[[New York University School of Law#Centers and Institutes|Center on Law and Security]], New York University School of Law |url=http://www.lawandsecurity.org/get_article/?id=154}}&lt;/ref&gt;  Through its many activities, the Center generates local, national, and international awareness of the legal dimension of security issues, including the Terrorist Trial Report Card, a comprehensive study on every terrorism prosecution in the United States since the [[September 11, 2001 terrorist attacks]].&lt;ref&gt;http://www.lawandsecurity.org/&lt;/ref&gt;

The [[Center on the Administration of Criminal Law]] is a think-tank dedicated to the promotion of good government and prosecution practices in criminal matters.  The Center analyzes important issues in criminal law or having implications for the administration criminal law. In particular, the Center focuses on the exercise of power and discretion by prosecutors.  The Center accomplishes its mission in three areas: academia, litigation, and participating in public policy and media debates.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.law.nyu.edu/centers/adminofcriminallaw/index.htm&lt;/ref&gt;  The Center's academic component gathers empirical research, publishes scholarship, and organizes and hosts conferences and symposia.  The Center's litigation component uses the Center's research, experience, and expertise to litigate criminal cases or cases having implications for the administration of criminal law, particularly in cases in which the exercise of power and discretion by prosecutors raises substantive legal issues.  The Center's public policy and media component seeks to improve public dialogue on criminal justice matters in various ways, including testifying before public officials and the publishing of op-ed pieces.&lt;ref&gt;http://judiciary.senate.gov/hearings/testimony.cfm?id=1260&amp;wit_id=3684&lt;/ref&gt;

The [[Furman Center for Real Estate and Urban Policy]] is a joint venture between the law school and NYU's [[Robert F. Wagner Graduate School of Public Service]]. It is an academic research center devoted to the public policy aspects of land use, real estate development and housing.&lt;ref&gt;http://furmancenter.org/&lt;/ref&gt;

The Hauser Global Law School Program, launched in 1994, has moved NYU School of Law beyond the traditional study of comparative and international law to systematic examination of transnational issues and the development of new ways to train 21st-century lawyers.  The Program incorporates non-U.S. and transnational legal perspectives into the Law School’s curriculum, promotes scholarship on comparative and global law, and brings together faculty, scholars, and students from around the world.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.law.nyu.edu/global/index.htm&lt;/ref&gt;

The Institute for International Law and Justice integrates the law school’s scholarly excellence in international law into the policy activities of the [[United Nations]], [[non-governmental organizations]], [[law firms]], and [[industry]].&lt;ref&gt;http://www.iilj.org/&lt;/ref&gt;

The Institute for Law &amp; Society is a joint venture between the law school and the [[NYU Graduate School of Arts and Science]]. It serves as an intellectual center for faculty, graduate students, and law students interested in studying law and legal institutions from an interdisciplinary social science perspective. It offers an opportunity to earn a J.D.-Ph.D or J.D.-M.A. dual degree in law and society.&lt;ref&gt;http://www1.law.nyu.edu/ils/&lt;/ref&gt;

The Institute for Policy Integrity is headed by [[Richard Revesz]] and Michael Livermore. It advocates for sound cost-benefit analysis at the state, national, and global levels.&lt;ref&gt;http://policyintegrity.org/&lt;/ref&gt;

The Pollack Center for Law and Business is a joint venture between the law school and the [[New York University Stern School of Business]]. The Center is designed to enrich the professional education of students of law and business and to facilitate joint teaching to involve leaders in banking, business, and law in the intellectual life of the University through sponsorship of meetings, conferences and dinners. The Pollack Center also offers a program for students to earn the Advanced Professional Certificate in Law and Business.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.law.nyu.edu/llmjsd/advancedprofessionalcertificateprograms/advancedcertificateinlawandbusiness/index.htm&lt;/ref&gt; The director is William T. Allen, a professor at the law school and former Chancellor of the [[Delaware Court of Chancery]].&lt;ref&gt;http://www.law.nyu.edu/centers/lawbusiness/index.htm&lt;/ref&gt;

The Straus Institute for the Advanced Study of Law &amp; Justice brings in as Fellows each year approximately 14 leading scholars from different disciplines and cultures. Each year the Straus Institute defines an annual theme that serves as the overarching subject around which the annual fora, colloquia and conference are set. The faculty director is [[Joseph H. H. Weiler]].&lt;ref&gt;http://www.nyustraus.org/index.html&lt;/ref&gt;

The Tikvah Center for Law &amp; Jewish Civilization is headed by [[Moshe Halbertal]] and [[Joseph H. H. Weiler]]. The foundational premise of the Center is 1) that the study of Jewish law can profit immensely from insights gained from general jurisprudence; and 2) that Jewish law and Jewish civilization can provide illuminating perspectives both on the general study of law as a per se academic discipline, and on the reflection of law as a central social institution refracting the most important issues in our society.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.nyutikvah.org/&lt;/ref&gt;

The U.S.-Asia Law Institute serves as a resource and partner to various Asian countries as they reform and further develop their legal systems and institutions. It also works to improve the understanding of Asian legal systems by lawyers, academics, policy makers and the public. The faculty director is [[Jerome Cohen]].&lt;ref&gt;http://www.usasialaw.org/&lt;/ref&gt;

==References==
{{Reflist}}

==External links==
*[http://www.law.nyu.edu/ New York University School of Law]
*[http://www.nyu.edu/ New York University]
*[http://www.brennancenter.org Brennan Center for Justice]
*[http://furmancenter.org/ Furman Center for Real Estate and Urban Policy]
*[http://www.lawandsecurity.org/ The Center on Law and Security]
*[http://www.prosecutioncenter.org/  The Center on the Administration of Criminal Law]
*[http://www.iilj.org/ Institute for International Law and Justice]
*[http://www.chrgj.org/ Center for Human Rights and Global Justice]

{{New York University}}
{{Law schools in New York City}}
{{Law Schools of the Mid-Atlantic States}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:New York University School Of Law}}
[[Category:Educational institutions established in 1835]]
[[Category:Law schools in New York]]
[[Category:New York University schools|Law, School of]]
[[Category:Education in Manhattan]]
[[Category:Law schools in New York City]]

[[fr:New York University School of Law]]
[[ko:뉴욕 대학교 법학대학원]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
