<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="14160104" ns="0" title="2007–08 Vanderbilt Commodores men&#039;s basketball team"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{NCAATeamSeason
|Mode=Basketball
|Year=2007–08
|Prev year=2006–07
|Next year=2008–09
|Team=Vanderbilt Commodores
|Image=
|ImageSize=130px
|Conference=Southeastern Conference
|ShortConference=SEC East
|CoachRank=25
|APRank=25
|Record=26–8
|ConfRecord=10–6, 3rd
|HeadCoach=[[Kevin Stallings]]
|AsstCoach1=Dan Muller
|AsstCoach2=Tom Richardson
|AsstCoach3=King Rice
|StadiumArena=[[Memorial Gymnasium (Vanderbilt University)|Memorial Gymnasium]]
|BowlTourney=[[2008 NCAA Men's Division I Basketball Tournament|NCAA Tournament First Round]]
|BowlTourneyResult=Lost to Siena 83–62
}}
The '''2007–08 [[Vanderbilt Commodores men's basketball]] team''' represented [[Vanderbilt University]] in the 2007–08 [[college basketball]] season. The team was led by head coach [[Kevin Stallings]] and played home games at [[Memorial Gymnasium (Vanderbilt University)|Memorial Gymnasium]].

The 2007–08 team finished the season 26–8, and ranked 25th in both the [[AP Poll]] and the [[Coaches Poll|ESPN/USA Today (Coaches) poll]]. Their 16–0 start was the best in school history. The team finished in 3rd place in the SEC Eastern Division with a 10–6 conference record.

During [[NCAA basketball tournament selection process#Selection Sunday|Selection Sunday]], Vanderbilt received a #4 seed in the Midwest Region of the [[2008 NCAA Men's Division I Basketball Tournament]]. They faced #13 seed [[Siena Saints men's basketball|Siena]] in the first round on March 21, 2008. The Commodores were upset at a final score of 83–62,&lt;ref name=&quot;saints&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://scores.espn.go.com/ncb/recap?gameId=284000005|title=Siena 83, No. 19 Vanderbilt 62|date=2008-03-21|accessdate=2008-03-21}}&lt;/ref&gt; becoming the second #4 seed upset after [[2007-08 Connecticut Huskies men's basketball team|UConn]]'s overtime loss to [[San Diego Toreros men's basketball|San Diego]].

==Preseason outlook==
Entering the season, Vanderbilt was picked by the media attending the SEC's media days in October to finish 4th in the SEC East, behind [[Tennessee Vols|Tennessee]], [[Kentucky Wildcats|Kentucky]] and two-time defending national champion [[Florida Gators|Florida]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.secsports.com/index.php?s=&amp;url_channel_id=3&amp;url_subchannel_id=&amp;url_article_id=9770&amp;change_well_id=2|title=Media Tabs UT as 2008 SEC Men's Basketball Champs|publisher=SECsports.com|accessdate=2007-11-09}} {{Dead link|date=October 2010|bot=H3llBot}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Vanderbilt lost two starters from last year's team—2007 SEC-player of the year [[Derrick Byars]] (19.1 ppg) and shooting guard, Dan Cage (11.2 ppg) – and return three starters—swingman [[Shan Foster]], point guard Alex Gordon and power forward Ross Neltner.

Shan Foster was the Commodores' second leading scorer last season (15.6 ppg) and is the third leading returning scorer in the SEC. Foster was selected by the SEC media to the pre-season all-SEC second team. Alex Gordon had only 51 turnovers last season, tops among starting SEC point guards, and his 2.22-to-1 assist-to-turnover ratio was fourth best in the SEC. Neltner provided a versatile presence inside, averaging 5.7 rebounds per game, dishing out 74 assists and hitting 11-of-28 attempts from three-point range.

Sophomores Jermaine Beal and George Drake and freshman Keegan Bell are expected to compete for the shooting guard spot vacated by Cage. The Commodores appear set at center, where senior Alan Metcalfe and freshman [[Andrew Ogilvy|Andrew (A.J.) Ogilvy]] will share time. Metcalfe missed part of last season with a foot injury, while Ogilvy comes highly touted after spending four years at the [[Australian Institute of Sport]]. Other newcomers expected to vie for playing time are guard Keegan Bell and forwards Andre Walker and Darshawn McClellan.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://vucommodores.cstv.com/sports/m-baskbl/spec-rel/102307aad.html|title=Recent Taste of Success Has Commodores Wanting More|publisher=vucommodores.cstv.com|accessdate=2007-11-09}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Game Recaps==
===Regular Season===
'''Games 1–4'''. Vanderbilt (4–0) began its season with an 81–67 home win over Austin Peay (0–1), then won at [[Toledo Rockets|Toledo]] (1–1) 77–70. The Commodores beat [[Valparaiso Crusaders men's basketball|Valparaiso]] 87–78 and [[Utah State Aggies|Utah State]] 77–56 in the South Padre Island Shootout.

'''Game 5'''. Vanderbilt (5–0) defeated [[Bradley University|Bradley]] (4–2) 95–86 in the championship game of the South Padre Island Shootout on November 24, 2007. A.J. Oglivy scored 23 points, and Shan Foster 22, to lead the Commodores. After the Commodores raced to an 18-point halftime lead (53–35), Bradley senior point guard Daniel Ruffin led the Braves back to within 85–84 late in the game. But Alex Gordon hit a 10-foot jump shot and sank four free throws in the final 30&amp;nbsp;seconds as the Commodores pulled away.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://scores.espn.go.com/ncb/recap?gameId=273280071|title=Vandy downs Bradley to win South Padre Island Shootout|publisher=ESPN.com|accessdate=2007-11-25}}&lt;/ref&gt; Ruffin—the half-brother of former [[Indiana Hoosiers men's basketball|Indiana]] All-American [[A.J. Guyton]] – finished with 23 points and 6 assists. Bradley (22–13 last season, [[Missouri Valley Conference|MVC]]: 10–8, 4th) was picked to finish second in the [[Missouri Valley Conference]] this season by the league's coaches, media and sports information directors, behind unanimous first-place selection [[Southern Illinois Salukis|Southern Illinois]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.bubraves.com/ViewArticle.dbml?SPSID=25965&amp;SPID=1498&amp;DB_OEM_ID=3400&amp;ATCLID=1292325|title=Braves Picked Second In MVC Men's Basketball Poll|publisher=BUBraves.com|accessdate=2007-11-24}}&lt;/ref&gt;

'''Game 6'''. Vanderbilt (6–0) defeated [[South Alabama Jaguars men's basketball|South Alabama]] (4–3) 91–88 in double overtime on November 29, 2007. Shan Foster scored 26 points, as the Commodores rallied from a 59–51 deficit with 12:02 left. Andrew Oglivy had 19 points and 8 rebounds, while Ross Neltner added 15. Senior guard Demetric Bennett—a preseason All-Sun Belt first team selection—led the Jaguars with 25 points and reserve junior guard Domonic Tilford had 20. South Alabama was picked to finish second in the East Division of the [[Sun Belt Conference]] preseason media poll behind [[Western Kentucky University|Western Kentucky]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.usajaguars.com/ViewArticle.dbml?DB_OEM_ID=8300&amp;ATCLID=1329168|title=Jaguars Wrap Up Four-Game Trip at Vanderbilt|publisher=USAJaguars.com|accessdate=2007-11-29}}&lt;/ref&gt;

'''Game 7'''. Vanderbilt (7–0) beat [[2007-08 Georgia Tech Yellow Jackets men's basketball team|Georgia Tech]] (3–4) 92–79 on December 1, 2007. The Yellow Jackets led briefly 2–0, but Shan Foster hit a 3 to give the Commodores a lead they would not relinquish. Vanderbilt led by as many as 28 points in the second half before emptying its bench. Foster finished with 17 points, while Andrew Oglivy had 16 and Alan Metcalfe 15. Anthony Morrow, Tech's leading scorer, had only 2 points with 5&amp;nbsp;minutes to go, when Vandy led 86–58. He came into the game averaging 19.0 ppg.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://sports-ak.espn.go.com/ncb/recap?gameId=273350238|title=Vanderbilt 92, Georgia Tech 79|publisher=ESPN.com|accessdate=2007-12-03}}&lt;/ref&gt; Georgia Tech was picked to finish seventh in the [[Atlantic Coast Conference|ACC]] by the league's media.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://ramblinwreck.cstv.com/sports/m-baskbl/spec-rel/102107aaa.html|title=Tech Picked Seventh at ACC Operation Basketball|publisher=RamblinWreck.cstv.com|accessdate=2007-12-03}}&lt;/ref&gt;

'''Game 8'''. No. 23 Vanderbilt (8–0) (AP, No. 25 Coaches poll) remained perfect with a tight 83–80 win over [[2007-08 Wake Forest Demon Deacons men's basketball team|Wake Forest]] (5–2) on December 5, 2007. Shan Foster scored 26 points to go with 7 rebounds, and A.J. Oglivy scored 23, for the Commodores, who are 8–0 for only the fifth time ever. The game was close throughout, and neither team led by more than six points in the second half. Harvey Hale and James Johnson led Wake with 18 points apiece.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://scores.espn.go.com/ncb/recap?gameId=273390238|title=Ogilvy keys last-minute push past Wake Forest|publisher=ESPN.com|accessdate=2007-12-06}}&lt;/ref&gt; The Demon Deacons (2006: 15–16, 5–11 (10th)) were picked to finish 11th by the [[Atlantic Coast Conference|ACC's]] media.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://wakeforestsports.cstv.com/sports/m-baskbl/spec-rel/102207aab.html|title=Wake Forest Picked to Finish 11th in ACC Preseason Poll|publisher=WakeForestSports.cstv.com|accessdate=2007-12-06}}&lt;/ref&gt;

'''Game 9'''. No. 23 Vanderbilt (9–0) (AP, No. 25 Coaches poll) used a fast start to defeat [[Lipscomb University|Lipscomb]] (4–6) 90–67 on December 8, 2007. A.J. Oglivy scored a career-high 26 points, and Shan Foster had 21 for the Commodores, who raced out to an 18–4 lead and never led by less than 8 points after that.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://scores.espn.go.com/ncb/recap?gameId=273420238|title=Ogilvy dumps in career-best 26 as Vandy coasts on early run|publisher=ESPN.com|accessdate=2007-12-09}}&lt;/ref&gt;

'''Game 10'''. No. 20 Vanderbilt (10–0) (AP, No. 21 Coaches poll) rallied from an 18-point deficit early in the second half to beat [[DePaul Blue Demons|DePaul]] (2–4) 91–85 in overtime in [[Chicago]] on December 12, 2007. With Shan Foster and A.J. Oglivy both struggling, the Commodores trailed 58–40 after Dar Tucker scored on an alley-opp dunk with 15:15 to go. Vanderbilt seemed to revive, finally tying the score at 79–79 with 22&amp;nbsp;seconds left. Foster and Oglivy, the SEC's top two leading scorers, each finished with 19 points.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://sports.espn.go.com/ncb/recap?gameId=273460305|title=Vanderbilt rallies past DePaul to OT to stay undefeated|publisher=ESPN.com|accessdate=2007-12-13}}&lt;/ref&gt;

'''Game 11'''. No. 17 Vanderbilt (11–0) (AP and Coaches polls) had to overcome a large second half deficit for the second game in a row, downing [[Tennessee State University|Tennessee State]] (3–7) 83–74 on December 22, 2007. Playing after a 10-day break for exams, the Commodores trailed 56–47 with 11:53 to go. However, they stormed back with an 18–4 run to lead 65–60 with 7:33 left. Shan Foster had 22 points and Alex Gordon 16 for Vanderbilt, while Gerald Robinson led all scorers with 24 for the Tigers.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://sports.espn.go.com/ncb/recap?gameId=273560238|title=No. 17 Commodores rally from nine down, improve to 11–0|publisher=ESPN.com|accessdate=2007-12-26}}&lt;/ref&gt;

'''Game 12'''. No. 15 Vanderbilt (12–0) (AP and Coaches polls) beat [[University of Tennessee at Martin|UT Martin]] (5–8) 92–85 on December 29, 2007. The Commodores jumped out to a 13-point lead in the first half. However, Vandy's starters let UTM go on a 10–0 to start the 2nd half, even losing the lead at one point. Shan Foster hit a 3-pointer with the score tied at 83, and the Dores never trailed after that. A.J. Ogilvy led Vanderbilt with 21 points and just missed a [[Double (basketball)#Double-double|double-double]] with 9 rebounds. UT-Martin's Lester Hudson (3rd in NCAA in ppg) led all scorers with 36 points.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://sports.espn.go.com/ncb/recap?gameId=273630238|title=Vanderbilt equals best start in school history with win|publisher=ESPN.com|accessdate=2007-12-30}}&lt;/ref&gt;

'''Game 13'''. No. 15 Vanderbilt (13–0) (AP and Coaches polls) set a season high for points scored during a 97–73 rout of [[Iona College (New York)|Iona]] (5–9) on December 29, 2007. The Commodores achieved their best ever start, bettering a 12–0 start in 2003–04. After trading baskets for much of the first half, the Commodores built a 5-point lead at halftime. Unlike their previous game, the Commodores went on a 26–5 run to start the second half, putting the game out of reach and allowing the walk-on players to get some playing time. Vanderbilt continued to display a lax defense, but more than made up for it by shooting 56% from the floor and 55% from beyond the arc. Vanderbilt had four players in double figures, led by A.J. Ogilvy (who again just missed a double-double with 20 points and 9 rebounds) and Shan Foster (20 points).&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://sports.espn.go.com/ncb/recap?gameId=273650238|title=No. 15 Vanderbilt overwhelms Iona for 13th victory|publisher=ESPN.com|accessdate=2007-12-31}}&lt;/ref&gt;

'''Game 14'''. No. 15 Vanderbilt (14–0) (AP and Coaches polls) put together a solid effort in beating [[Rice Owls|Rice]] (3–9) 76–58 on January 3, 2008. The Commodores used a stifling defense to take control of the game from the onset, forcing a season-high 24 turnovers. Shan Foster netted 24 points, while A.J. Ogilvy added 14 points and 9 rebounds and Alex Gordon had 11 points.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://sports.espn.go.com/ncb/recap?gameId=280030238|title=Vanderbilt topples Rice, remains undefeated behind Foster's 24|publisher=ESPN.com|accessdate=2008-01-04}}&lt;/ref&gt;

'''Game 15'''. No. 15 Vanderbilt (15–0) (AP and Coaches polls) overcame deficits of 9 and 14 points to beat [[UMass Minutemen|Massachusetts]] (11–3) 97–88 on January 5, 2008, tying a season high for points scored. Vandy was led by senior guard Shan Foster, who scored 32 points and hit 8 3-pointers, and freshman center A.J. Ogilvy, who notched a double-double with 25 points and 11 rebounds. Sophomore point guard Jermaine Beal added a career-high 15 points for the Commodores. Ricky Harris led the Minutemen with 25 points.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://sports.espn.go.com/ncb/recap?gameId=280050238|title=Rally lifts Vandy to school-best 15–0 start|publisher=ESPN.com|accessdate=2008-01-05}}&lt;/ref&gt;

'''Game 16'''. No. 13 Vanderbilt (16–0, 1–0) (AP, No. 12 Coaches polls) won its SEC opener by beating [[South Carolina Gamecocks|South Carolina]] (8–7, 0–1) by a score of 80–73 on January 9, 2008. Vanderbilt was led by freshman sensation A.J. Ogilvy with 25 points, while seniors Alex Gordon and Shan Foster had 13 points apiece. The Gamecocks were led by Devan Downey, who had 22 points. After hitting a 3-pointer in the game, Shan Foster became the Commodores' all-time leading 3-point shooter.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://sports.espn.go.com/ncb/recap?gameId=280090238|title=Vanderbilt gets fourth straight win vs. South Carolina|publisher=ESPN.com|accessdate=2008-01-09}}&lt;/ref&gt;

'''Game 17'''. No. 13 Vanderbilt (16–1, 1–1) (AP, No. 12 Coaches poll) lost its first game of the season, 79–73 in double-overtime to [[Kentucky Wildcats men's basketball|Kentucky]] (7–7, 1–0) at [[Rupp Arena]]. The loss snapped the Commodores' 4-game winning streak against the Wildcats. Vanderbilt entered the game as one of five remaining unbeaten teams in men's Division I basketball. Kentucky controlled most of the game, taking a 16-point lead five minutes into the second half. The Commodores, who never led in regulation, tied the game on a three-pointer by Shan Foster with 14&amp;nbsp;seconds left to force overtime. The teams traded leads in the first overtime, but Vandy needed an A.J. Ogilvy-putback with 1.8&amp;nbsp;seconds left to force a second overtime. The Wildcats outscored Vanderbilt 7–1 in the second overtime to win the game. [[Patrick Patterson (basketball)|Patrick Patterson]] led the Wildcats with 23 points and 12 rebounds, while [[Ramel Bradley]] added 20 points and [[Joe Crawford (basketball)|Joe Crawford]] 17. The Commodores were led by Foster's 20 points and Ogilvy's 16 points and 5 rebounds.&lt;ref name=&quot;Vandy-UK&quot;&gt;{{cite news|url=http://scores.espn.go.com/ncb/recap?gameId=280120096 |title=Vanderbilt rallies from 16-point deficit, but falls in 2OT to Kentucky |agency=Associated Press |publisher=ESPN.com|date=2008-01-12|accessdate=2008-01-12}}&lt;/ref&gt;

'''Game 18'''. No. 16 Vanderbilt (16–2, 1–2) (AP, No. 14 Coaches poll) lost 80–60 to No. 6 [[Tennessee Volunteers men's basketball|Tennessee]] (15–1, 3–0) (AP, No. 7 Coaches poll) in [[Knoxville, Tennessee|Knoxville, TN]], its second loss in a row. The Vols held the Commodores well below their season scoring average (86.0 ppg) and limited them to 3 three-pointers. Vanderbilt stayed close for about 11&amp;nbsp;minutes, but a 16–3 run gave Tennessee a 33–18 lead with 3:59 left in the first half. After halftime, the Vols used a 17–6 run to take a 59–38 lead, but the Commodores responded with a 15–2 run to make it 61–53 with 7:48 to go. They would get no closer. Wayne Chism led the Vols with 18 points and 18 rebounds, while Shan Foster led the Commodores with 14 points and 6 rebounds.&lt;ref name=&quot;Vandy-UT&quot;&gt;{{cite news|url=http://sports.espn.go.com/ncb/recap?gameId=280172633|title=Tennessee's shooters hot from 3-point range in win over No. 14 Vandy|publisher=ESPN.com|date=2008-01-17|accessdate=2008-02-07}}&lt;/ref&gt;

'''Game 19'''. No. 16 Vanderbilt (17–2, 2–2) (AP, No. 14 Coaches poll) defeated [[LSU Tigers basketball|LSU]] (7–11, 0–4) 92–76, ending a two-game losing skid.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://sports.espn.go.com/ncb/recap?gameId=280190238|title=No. 14 Vandy stops two-game slide on Foster's 3-point shooting|publisher=ESPN.com|accessdate=2008-03-01}}&lt;/ref&gt;

'''Game 20'''. After an eight-day layoff, No. 14 Vanderbilt (17–3, 2–3) (AP, No. 13 Coaches poll) lost 86–64 to [[2007-08 Florida Gators men's basketball team|Florida]] (18–3, 5–1) in [[Gainesville, Florida|Gainesville]]. The Gators went on a 23–0 run early in the first half to put the game out of reach early.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://sports.espn.go.com/ncb/recap?gameId=280270057|title=Florida rides 23–0 run in first half past No. 13 Vandy|publisher=ESPN.com|accessdate=2008-03-01}}&lt;/ref&gt;

'''Game 21'''. No. 19 Vanderbilt (17–4, 2–4) (AP, No. 18 Coaches poll) lost 74–58 to No. 24 [[Ole Miss Rebels|Ole Miss]] (16–3, 3–4) (AP, No. 22 Coaches poll) in [[Oxford, Mississippi]], its fourth consecutive road loss in SEC play.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://sports.espn.go.com/ncb/recap?gameId=280300145|title=Ole Miss rebounds to hand Vandy fourth loss in five games|publisher=ESPN.com|accessdate=2008-03-01}}&lt;/ref&gt;

'''Game 22'''. After losing four of their last five games, No. 19 Vanderbilt (18–4, 3–4) (AP, No. 18 Coaches poll) defeated [[Auburn Tigers men's basketball|Auburn]] (12–8, 2–5) 78–71.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://sports.espn.go.com/ncb/recap?gameId=280330238|title=Ogilvy scores 19 to lead No. 18 Vanderbilt over Auburn|publisher=ESPN.com|accessdate=2008-03-01}}&lt;/ref&gt;

'''Game 23'''. No. 23 Vanderbilt (19–4, 4–4) (AP, No. 20 Coaches poll) picked up an important road win in SEC play, defeating [[Georgia Bulldogs|Georgia]] (11–9, 2–5) in [[Athens, Georgia|Athens]] by a score of 67–59.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://sports.espn.go.com/ncb/recap?gameId=280370061|title=Neltner hits key baskets as Vandy holds off Georgia|publisher=ESPN.com|accessdate=2008-03-01}}&lt;/ref&gt;

'''Game 24'''. No. 23 Vanderbilt (20–4, 5–4) (AP, No. 20 Coaches poll) traveled to [[Columbia, South Carolina]] to take on [[South Carolina Gamecocks|South Carolina]] (11–10, 3–4) on Saturday, February 9, 2008. The Commodores defeated the Gamecocks for the second time this season with a score of 66–65 as sophomore Jermaine Beal hit a short fadeaway jumper with 0.6&amp;nbsp;seconds left.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://sports.espn.go.com/ncb/recap?gameId=280402579|title=Beal's late heroics carry No. 20 Commodores past Gamecocks|publisher=ESPN.com|accessdate=2008-03-01}}&lt;/ref&gt;

'''Game 25'''. No. 24 Vanderbilt (21–4, 6–4) (AP, No. 19 Coaches poll) were at home in Memorial Gymnasium to face the [[Kentucky Wildcats]] (12–10, 6–3). Kentucky suffered their worst defeat in 21 years, and their worst SEC defeat ever, as they fell to the Commodores at a final score of 93–52. [[Shan Foster]] scored 20 points and A. J. Ogilvy added another 19 for Vanderbilt.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://sports.espn.go.com/ncb/recap?gameId=280430238|title=Kentucky suffers worst SEC loss in school history|publisher=ESPN.com|accessdate=2008-03-01}}&lt;/ref&gt;

'''Game 26'''. No. 24 Vanderbilt (22–4, 7–4) (AP, No. 19 Coaches poll) hosted the [[Florida Gators men's basketball|Florida Gators]] (19–7, 6–5), who defeated the Commodores in Gainesville earlier in the season. The Commodores won 61–58 as Alex Gordon made four free throws in the final 24&amp;nbsp;seconds; Florida freshman Nick Calethas also committed a costly backcourt violation in the closing seconds. Alex Gordon and A.J. Ogilvy each scored 12 points and Shan Foster added 19 points and 6 rebounds.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://sports.espn.go.com/ncb/recap?gameId=280470238|title=Vanderbilt holds off Florida at home to move into third in SEC East|publisher=ESPN.com|accessdate=2008-03-01}}&lt;/ref&gt;

'''Game 27'''. No. 20 Vanderbilt (23–4, 8–4) (AP, No. 16 Coaches poll), for the third straight game, were at home at Memorial Gymnasium as they faced the [[Georgia Bulldogs]] (12–13, 3–9), who they had defeated just a few weeks earlier in [[Athens, Georgia|Athens]]. The Bulldogs led 38–37 at halftime, but Vanderbilt stormed out of the gates in the second half as they opened on a 29–11 run. The Commodores won the game at a final score of 86–74 with 29 points from Shan Foster and 23 points from Alex Gordon.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://sports.espn.go.com/ncb/recap?gameId=280540238|title=Vanderbilt extends winning streak to five games|publisher=ESPN.com|accessdate=2008-03-01}}&lt;/ref&gt;

'''Game 28'''. No. 18 Vanderbilt (24–4, 9–4) (AP, No. 14 Coaches poll) faced their toughest test of the season as they hosted in-state rivals No. 1 [[Tennessee Volunteers men's basketball|Tennessee Volunteers]] (25–3, 11–2) (AP and coaches polls). Shan Foster contributed 32 points and Jermaine Beal scored 17. With 1.8&amp;nbsp;seconds left, Tennessee threw a shot downcourt to force overtime but it was not close, and the Commodores defeated their rivals at a final score of 72–69.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://sports.espn.go.com/ncb/recap?gameId=280570238|title=Vols lose first game after gaining No. 1 ranking|publisher=ESPN.com|accessdate=2008-03-01}}&lt;/ref&gt;

'''Game 29'''. No. 18 Vanderbilt (24–5, 9–5) (AP, No. 14 Coaches poll) traveled to [[Fayetteville, AR]] to take on the [[Arkansas Razorbacks men's basketball|Arkansas Razorbacks]] (19–9, 8–6). Although Shan Foster scored 22 points, becoming Vanderbilt's all-time leading scorer in the process, the Commodores fell to the Razorbacks 78–73. Down by 1 point with under 10&amp;nbsp;seconds to play and no timeouts left, Vanderbilt senior Ross Neltner called for a timeout, receiving a technical foul that sealed the win for the Razorbacks.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://sports.espn.go.com/ncb/recap?gameId=280610008|title=Arkansas hangs on after Vandy calls a timeout they don't have|publisher=ESPN.com|accessdate=2008-03-01}}&lt;/ref&gt;

'''Game 30'''. No. 16 Vanderbilt (25–5, 10–5) (AP and coaches' polls) hosted [[Mississippi State Bulldogs|Mississippi State]] (No. 25 coaches' poll) for their final home game of the season. On senior night, Shan Foster hit his final nine three-pointers and amassed a career high of 42 points, as Vanderbilt defeated the Bulldogs 86–85 in overtime. With the victory, Vanderbilt finished the season undefeated at home in Memorial Gym.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=
http://sports.espn.go.com/ncb/recap?gameId=280650238|title=Foster's late 3 lifts Vanderbilt past Mississippi State in OT|publisher=ESPN.com|accessdate=2008-03-06}}&lt;/ref&gt;

'''Game 31'''. No. 16 Vanderbilt (25–6, 10–6) (AP and coaches' polls) were at [[Coleman Coliseum]] to face [[Alabama Crimson Tide|Alabama]] in the final game of the season for both sides. Vanderbilt shot .280 percent from behind the arc. Though Shan Foster scored 21 points and A.J. Ogily added another 17, the Commodores fell to the Tide 78–73 in overtime. Alabama guard Mykal Riley scored 26 points, including the first 13 points for the Tide in overtime.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=
http://sports.espn.go.com/ncb/recap?gameId=280680333|title=Senior scores first 13 points in overtime to lift Tide to upset|publisher=ESPN.com|accessdate=2008-03-10}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===SEC Tournament===
'''Game 32'''. No. 18 Vanderbilt (26–6) (AP, No. 17 coaches' poll) traveled to [[Atlanta, GA]] for the [[2008 SEC Men's Basketball Tournament|SEC Tournament]] to face [[Auburn Tigers|Auburn]] (14–16) in a first-round matchup. Behind a career-high 27 points from A.J. Ogilvy and 26 points from Shan Foster, Vanderbilt beat the Tigers 93–82 to advance to the quarterfinals of the tournament.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://sports.espn.go.com/ncb/recap?gameId=280730238|title=Vandy shoots 67 percent in win, falls just shy of tourney record|publisher=ESPN.com|accessdate=2008-03-13}}&lt;/ref&gt;

'''Game 33'''. No. 18 Vanderbilt (26–7) (AP, No. 17 coaches' poll) faced off against [[Arkansas Razorbacks|Arkansas]] in an SEC Tournament quarterfinal matchup. The Razorbacks extended their win streak to five games&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://vucommodores.cstv.com/sports/m-baskbl/spec-rel/011406aaa.html|title=Men's Hoops Drop One to Hogs|publisher=[[Vanderbilt University]]|accessdate=2008-03-19}}&lt;/ref&gt; over the Commodores by dominating the rebounds and points in the paint. Vanderbilt senior Alex Gordon led all scorers with 22 points in the loss.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://sports.espn.go.com/ncb/recap?gameId=280740008|title=Townes and Ervin's 36 combined points pace Razorbacks' win over Vandy|publisher=ESPN.com|accessdate=2008-03-15}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===NCAA Tournament===
'''Game 34'''. No. 18 Vanderbilt (26–8) (AP, No. 17 coaches' poll) were selected as a #4 seed in the Midwest Region of the 2008 NCAA Tournament to face #13 seed [[Siena College|Siena]] Saints. In his final collegiate game, [[Shan Foster]] scored just 13 points and was 1-for-5 from three-point range. The Commodores struggled to find consistent offense, going 4-for-20 from beyond the arc. Siena guard Kenny Hasbrouck scored 30 points to lead the Saints to an 83–62 upset of the #4 seeded Commodores.&lt;ref name=&quot;saints&quot;/&gt;

==Roster and individual statistics==
{| class=&quot;wikitable&quot;
|-
|'''#'''
|'''Name'''
|'''Pos.'''
|'''Height'''
|'''Weight'''
|'''Year'''
|'''Hometown'''
|'''High School'''
|'''GP'''
|'''Min'''
|'''Ppg'''
|'''Rpg'''
|'''Apg'''
|-
| 0
| Jermaine Beal
| G
| 6–3
| 210
| Sophomore
| [[DeSoto, Texas|DeSoto, TX]]
| [[DeSoto High School (DeSoto, Texas)|DeSoto]]
| 34
| 27.5
| 7.6
| 2.1
| 4.6
|-
| 1
| [[Festus Ezeli]]&lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt;
| C
| 6–11
| 245
| Freshman
| [[Benin City|Benin City, Nigeria]]
| Igbinedion Education Center
| –
| –
| –
| –
| –
|-
| 2
| Charles Hinkle&lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt;
| G/F
| 6–6
| 200
| Freshman
| [[Los Alamitos, California|Los Alamitos, CA]]
| [[Hebron Academy|Hebron Academy (Maine)]]/[[Los Alamitos High School|Los Alamitos]]
| –
| –
| –
| –
| –
|-
| 3
| Alex Gordon
| G
| 6–0
| 170
| Senior
| [[Pensacola, Florida|Pensacola, FL]]
| [[Pensacola High School|Pensacola]]
| 34
| 29.8
| 10.8
| 2.4
| 3.1
|-
| 4
| [[Andrew Ogilvy|Andrew (A.J.) Ogilvy]]
| C
| 6–10
| 250
| Freshman
| [[Sydney]], [[Australia]]
| [[Australian Institute of Sport]], [[Canberra]]
| 34
| 26.4
| 17.0
| 6.7
| 1.2
|-
| 11
| Alan Metcalfe
| F
| 6–9
| 265
| Senior
| [[St Helens, Merseyside|St. Helens, England]]
| [[Notre Dame Academy (Middleburg, Virginia)|Notre Dame Academy (Va.)]]
| 34
| 11.6
| 5.3
| 2.3
| 0.2
|-
| 13
| Keegan Bell
| G
| 6–1
| 180
| Freshman
| [[Hazel Green, Alabama|Hazel Green, AL]]
| [[Hazel Green High School|Hazel Green]]
| 34
| 13.5
| 2.7
| 1.2
| 2.8
|-
| 15
| Elliott Cole&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt;
| G
| 5–11
| 175
| Freshman
| [[Memphis, Tennessee|Memphis, TN]]
| [[Memphis University School]]
| 5
| 0.8
| 0.0
| 0.6
| 0.0
|-
| 21
| Darshawn McClellan
| F
| 6–7
| 220
| Freshman
| [[Fresno, California|Fresno, CA]]
| [[Edison High School (Fresno, California)|Edison (Fresno)]]
| 34
| 14.1
| 2.7
| 3.0
| 0.7
|-
| 22
| Jamie Graham&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt;
| G
| 5–11
| 180
| Freshman
| [[Nashville, Tennessee|Nashville, TN]]
| Whites Creek
| 15
| 4.3
| 1.5
| 0.7
| 0.3
|-
| 24
| Andre Walker
| F
| 6–7
| 214
| Freshman
| [[Flossmoor, Illinois|Flossmoor, IL]]
| [[Brewster Academy|Brewster Academy (N.H.)]]/[[Homewood-Flossmoor High School|Homewood-Flossmoor]]
| 34
| 11.2
| 2.4
| 2.0
| 1.1
|-
| 32
| [[Shan Foster]]
| G-F
| 6–5
| 205
| Senior
| [[Kenner, Louisiana|Kenner, LA]]
| Alfred Bonnabel
| 34
| 33.7
| 20.3
| 4.9
| 1.6
|-
| 34
| George Drake
| G-F
| 6–4
| 210
| Sophomore
| [[Calera, Alabama|Calera, AL]]
| Calera
| 33
| 8.0
| 2.1
| 1.2
| 0.4
|-
| 41
| Ross Neltner
| F
| 6–9
| 240
| Senior
| [[Fort Thomas, Kentucky|Fort Thomas, KY]]
| [[Highlands High School (Fort Thomas, Kentucky)|Highlands]]
| 34
| 27.0
| 8.3
| 5.6
| 2.0
|-
| 50
| Joe Duffy&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt;
| F
| 6–8
| 225
| Freshman
| [[Charlotte, N.C.]]
| [[Phillips Exeter Academy|Phillips Exeter Academy (N.H.)]]/[[Charlotte Catholic High School|Charlotte Catholic]]
| 11
| 1.7
| 0.9
| 0.2
| 0.0
|}

&lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt; Reshirted this season.
&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt; Walk-on.

Stats through 33 games. Source: ESPN.com&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://sports.espn.go.com/ncb/clubhouse?teamId=238|title=Vanderbilt Commodores' Clubhouse|publisher=ESPN.com|accessdate=2008-03-15}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==2007–08 schedule and results==
{| class=&quot;wikitable&quot;
|-
! Date !! Opponent !! Location !! Time !! Result !! Overall !! Conf.
|-
| colspan=&quot;7&quot; | &lt;center&gt;'''Exhibition Game'''&lt;/center&gt;
|- style=&quot;background:#dfd;&quot;
| November 5, 2007 || Tusculum || Nashville, TN || || '''W''' 80–79 || – || –
|-
| colspan=&quot;7&quot; | &lt;center&gt;'''Regular Season'''&lt;/center&gt;
|- style=&quot;background:#dfd;&quot;
| November 10, 2007 || Austin Peay || Nashville, TN || 8:00&amp;nbsp;pm || '''W''' 81–67 || 1–0 || 0–0
|- style=&quot;background:#dfd;&quot;
| November 13, 2007 || Toledo || Toledo, OH || 7:00&amp;nbsp;pm || '''W''' 77–70 || 2–0 || 0–0
|- style=&quot;background:#dfd;&quot;
| November 20, 2007 || Valparaiso&lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt; || Nashville, TN || 8:00&amp;nbsp;pm || '''W''' 87–78 || 3–0 || 0–0
|- style=&quot;background:#dfd;&quot;
| November 23, 2007 || Utah State&lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt; || South Padre Island, TX || 10:00&amp;nbsp;pm || '''W''' 77–56 || 4–0 || 0–0
|- style=&quot;background:#dfd;&quot;
| November 24, 2007 || Bradley&lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt; || South Padre Island, TX || 8:30&amp;nbsp;pm || '''W''' 95–86 || 5–0 || 0–0
|- style=&quot;background:#dfd;&quot;
| November 29, 2007 || South Alabama || Nashville, TN || 8:00&amp;nbsp;pm || '''W''' 91–88 &lt;sup&gt;(2 OT)&lt;/sup&gt; || 6–0 || 0–0
|- style=&quot;background:#dfd;&quot;
| December 1, 2007 || Georgia Tech || Nashville, TN || 1:00&amp;nbsp;pm || '''W''' 92–79 || 7–0 || 0–0
|- style=&quot;background:#dfd;&quot;
| December 5, 2007 || Wake Forest || Nashville, TN || 7:00&amp;nbsp;pm || '''W''' 83–80 || 8–0 || 0–0
|- style=&quot;background:#dfd;&quot;
| December 8, 2007 || Lipscomb || Nashville, TN || 8:00&amp;nbsp;pm || '''W''' 90–67 || 9–0 || 0–0
|- style=&quot;background:#dfd;&quot;
| December 12, 2007 || DePaul || Chicago, IL || 8:30&amp;nbsp;pm || '''W''' 91–85 &lt;sup&gt;(OT)&lt;/sup&gt; || 10–0 || 0–0
|- style=&quot;background:#dfd;&quot;
| December 22, 2007 || Tennessee State || Nashville, TN || 9:00&amp;nbsp;pm || '''W''' 83–74 || 11–0 || 0–0
|- style=&quot;background:#dfd;&quot;
| December 29, 2007 || Tennessee-Martin || Nashville, TN || 1:00&amp;nbsp;pm || '''W''' 92–85 || 12–0 || 0–0
|- style=&quot;background:#dfd;&quot;
| December 31, 2007 || Iona || Nashville, TN || 1:00&amp;nbsp;pm || '''W''' 97–73 || 13–0 || 0–0
|- style=&quot;background:#dfd;&quot;
| January 3, 2008 || Rice || Nashville, TN || 8:00&amp;nbsp;pm || '''W''' 76–58 || 14–0 || 0–0
|- style=&quot;background:#dfd;&quot;
| January 5, 2008 || Massachusetts || Nashville, TN || 4:00&amp;nbsp;pm || '''W''' 97–88 || 15–0 || 0–0
|- style=&quot;background:#dfd;&quot;
| January 9, 2008 || South Carolina* || Nashville, TN ||  8:00&amp;nbsp;pm || '''W''' 80–73 || 16–0 || 1–0
|- style=&quot;background:#fcc;&quot;
| January 12, 2008 || Kentucky* || Lexington, KY || 1:30&amp;nbsp;pm || '''L''' 79–73 &lt;sup&gt;(2 OT)&lt;/sup&gt; || 16–1 || 1–1
|- style=&quot;background:#fcc;&quot;
| January 17, 2008 || &lt;sup&gt;#6&lt;/sup&gt; Tennessee* || Knoxville, TN || 7:00&amp;nbsp;pm || '''L''' 80–60 || 16–2 || 1–2
|- style=&quot;background:#dfd;&quot;
| January 19, 2008 || LSU* || Nashville, TN || 1:00&amp;nbsp;pm || '''W''' 92–76 || 17–2 || 2–2
|- style=&quot;background:#fcc;&quot;
| January 27, 2008 || Florida* || Gainesville, FL || 1:00&amp;nbsp;pm || '''L''' 86–64 || 17–3 || 2–3
|- style=&quot;background:#fcc;&quot;
| January 30, 2008 || &lt;sup&gt;#24&lt;/sup&gt; Ole Miss* || Oxford, MS || 8:00&amp;nbsp;pm || '''L''' 74–58 || 17–4 || 2–4
|- style=&quot;background:#dfd;&quot;
| February 2, 2008 || Auburn* || Nashville, TN || 5:00&amp;nbsp;pm || '''W''' 78–71 || 18–4 || 3–4
|- style=&quot;background:#dfd;&quot;
| February 6, 2008 || Georgia* || Athens, GA || 7:30&amp;nbsp;pm || '''W''' 67–59 || 19–4 || 4–4
|- style=&quot;background:#dfd;&quot;
| February 9, 2008 || South Carolina* || Columbia, S.C. || 5:00&amp;nbsp;pm || '''W''' 66–65 || 20–4 || 5–4
|- style=&quot;background:#dfd;&quot;
| February 12, 2008 || Kentucky* || Nashville, TN || 9:00&amp;nbsp;pm || '''W''' 93–52 || 21–4 || 6–4
|- style=&quot;background:#dfd;&quot;
| February 16, 2008 || Florida* || Nashville, TN || 3:00&amp;nbsp;pm || '''W''' 61–58 || 22–4 || 7–4
|- style=&quot;background:#dfd;&quot;
| February 23, 2008 || Georgia* || Nashville, TN || 4:00&amp;nbsp;pm || '''W''' 86–74 || 23–4 || 8–4
|- style=&quot;background:#dfd;&quot;
| February 26, 2008 || &lt;sup&gt;#1&lt;/sup&gt; Tennessee* || Nashville, TN || 9:00&amp;nbsp;pm || '''W''' 72–69 || 24–4 || 9–4
|- style=&quot;background:#fcc;&quot;
| March 1, 2008 || Arkansas* || Fayetteville, AR || 4:05&amp;nbsp;pm || '''L''' 78–73 || 24–5 || 9–5
|- style=&quot;background:#dfd;&quot;
| March 5, 2008 || Mississippi State* || Nashville, TN || 8:00&amp;nbsp;pm || '''W''' 86–85 &lt;sup&gt;(OT)&lt;/sup&gt; || 25–5 || 10–5
|- style=&quot;background:#fcc;&quot;
| March 8, 2008 || Alabama* || Tuscaloosa, AL || 7:00&amp;nbsp;pm || '''L''' 78–73 &lt;sup&gt;(OT)&lt;/sup&gt; || 25–6 || 10–6
|-
| colspan=&quot;7&quot; | &lt;center&gt;'''[[2008 SEC Men's Basketball Tournament|SEC Tournament]]'''&lt;/center&gt;
|- style=&quot;background:#dfd;&quot;
| March 13, 2008 || Auburn || Atlanta, GA || 3:15&amp;nbsp;pm || '''W''' 93–82 || 26–6 || 10–6
|- style=&quot;background:#fcc;&quot;
| March 14, 2008 || Arkansas || Atlanta, GA || 3:15&amp;nbsp;pm || '''L''' 81–75 || 26–7 || 10–6
|-
| colspan=&quot;7&quot; | &lt;center&gt;'''[[2008 NCAA Men's Division I Basketball Tournament|NCAA Tournament]]'''&lt;/center&gt;
|- style=&quot;background:#fcc;&quot;
| March 21, 2008 || Siena || Tampa, FL || 6:20&amp;nbsp;PM || '''L''' 83–62 || 26–8 || 10–6
|-
| colspan=&quot;7&quot; | &lt;small&gt;*Conference game. &lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt; South Padre Island Shoot-out&lt;/font&gt;&lt;/small&gt;
|}
&lt;small&gt;* Opponent rankings are those of the Associated Press Poll at the time the game was played.&lt;/small&gt;

==References==
{{reflist|colwidth=30em}}

{{2007–08 Southeastern Conference men's basketball}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:2007-08 Vanderbilt Commodores Men's Basketball Team}}
[[Category:Vanderbilt Commodores men's basketball seasons]]
[[Category:2007–08 Southeastern Conference men's basketball season|Vanderbilt]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
