<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><redirects><r from="Tuxedo kitty" to="Bicolor cat" /></redirects><pages><page pageid="63896" ns="0" title="Bicolor cat"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">[[Image:socks-clinton.jpg|frame|right|[[Chelsea Clinton]]'s cat, [[Socks (cat)|Socks]] (1989-2009), lived in the [[White House]] from 1993 to 2001. Socks was a bicolor cat with low grade spotting, or ''tuxedo cat''.]]

A '''bicolor''' '''[[cat]]''' has [[white]] [[fur]] combined with fur of some other [[color]], for example black or [[tabby]].  There are various patterns of bicolor cat.  These range from [[Turkish Van|Van pattern]] (color on the crown of the head and the tail only) through to solid color with a throat locket.  The '''tuxedo''' pattern is one of many possible bicolor patterns.

Where there is low-to-medium grade white spotting limited to the face, paws, throat and chest of an otherwise black cat, they are known in the United States as a '''tuxedo cat''' or '''Billicat'''{{fact|date=September 2011}}.  High grade bicolor results in Van-pattern cats. There are many patterns between, such as &quot;cap-and-saddle&quot;, &quot;mask-and-mantle&quot; and &quot;magpie&quot; (more randomly splashed).   Bicolors are found in many breeds, as well as being common in [[domestic longhair cat]]s and [[domestic shorthair cat]]s.

Solid color bicolor cats occur because there is a [[white spotting gene]] present along with a recessive allele of the [[agouti gene]], which evens out the usual striped pattern of the colors of the coat. In contrast, ''tabby'' cats have an agouti gene that produces striping of the coat. The [[Abyssinian (cat)|Abyssinian]] has agouti (ticked tabby) fur, giving the appearance of even color with color-banded hairs.

White spotting can also occur with any of the tabby patterns, resulting in tabby-and-white bicolors.  Colorpoint ([[Himalayan pattern]]) cats can have bicolor points, although this variation is not recognized for showing.  The body markings of bicolor colorpoints become clearer with age, as the body fur of colorpoint cats darkens as the cats grow older and the white patches become more visible.

==Grades 1 - 10 of bicolor in cats==
{{cleanup|section|date=June 2011}}
{{Ref improve section|date=June 2011}}
[[Image:Bicolours.png|500px|thumb|right|The Various Bicolor Patterns]]
[[File:Bicolor he-cat.JPG|thumb|right|Mask-and-mantle cat]]
[[Image:BW Cat.jpg|thumb|right|A &quot;cow&quot; pattern]]

There are 10 identifiable grades of bicolor in cats, plus several patterns with their own names.  The cat labelled &quot;bicolor&quot; is the preferred pattern in show-quality bicolor purebred cats.

A low-grade spotting black-and-white bicolor cat is often known as a &quot;tuxedo cat&quot; or a &quot;Billicat&quot;. To be considered a tuxedo cat, its black coloring should be solid throughout, with white limited to the paws, belly, chest, throat, face, and possibly the chin: it should appear as if the cat were wearing a [[black tie|tuxedo]].

Another type of black-and-white bicolor cat is nicknamed &quot;cow cat&quot; or &quot;moo cat&quot; (for a perceived resemblance to [[Holstein (cattle)|Holstein cattle]]) {{Citation needed|date=June 2011}} and includes the magpie, cap-and-saddle and mask-and-mantle patterns.  A cow cat does not have the solid black &quot;jacket&quot; of the tuxedo cat.  Instead, it has big black patches over a mostly white body, often with a black mask over the head.  &quot;Black Mask Cats&quot; are so called because they look like they are wearing a black mask over their head.  The [[Turkish Van]] (white and red) is one good example of a bicolor [[cat breeds|breed]].  Van pattern is known to animal geneticists as the [[Seychelles]] (Seychellois) Pattern and is classified into 3 variants:&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.breedlist.com/seychellois-breeders.html |title=Seychellois |accessdate=2007-08-05 |publisher=Fanciers Breeder Referral List}}&lt;/ref&gt;

*Seychellois Neuvieme - white with colored tail and head splashes (classic Van Pattern)
*Seychellois Huitieme - white with colored tail and head splashes plus additional splashes of color on the legs
*Seychellois Septieme - white with splashes of color on the legs and body in addition to those on the head and the colored tail.

This is high grade white spotting of types 9, 8 and 7 on the bicolor chart above.

==Frequency in different breeds==
This coloration is not restricted to a specific breed of cat, as it can be found in many different types of pure-breed as well as mixed-breed domestic cats.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.travelswithtigger.com/fanciers/breed-desc.html |title=Cat Breed Descriptions |accessdate=2007-08-05 |publisher=Laura Gilbreath}}&lt;/ref&gt; However, some breeds of cats are especially noted for having bicolor coats in their breed standards. These include the [[Turkish Van]], [[American Shorthair]], [[Manx (cat)|Manx]], [[British Shorthair]], [[Turkish Angora]], and [[Bombay (cat)|Bombay]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.cfa.org/breeds.html |title=CFA Breeds |accessdate=2007-08-05 |publisher=The Cat Fanciers' Association}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In contrast, other common breeds of cat have specific coat patterns specified in their breed standards. These cats are therefore never seen in the bicolor pattern. Cats with such specific coat patterns such as the [[Russian Blue]] which has a coat of one solid color.

==Genetics of coat patterns==
[[File:NYY 084.jpg|thumb|A black and white variation]]

{{Main|Cat coat genetics}}
The basic colors and patterns of cat fur are defined by fewer than ten genes.&lt;ref name=genome/&gt; Cats with white color in their coats are thought to have a mutant ''white-spotting'' gene that prevents the formation of coat color in patches over the cat's body. This gene has been investigated in several species, particularly mice, and is [[Dominance relationship|co-dominant]] to normal coat color as it prevents the migration of [[melanocyte]]s into the developing hair follicles.&lt;ref name=&quot;pmid11764276&quot;&gt;{{Cite journal|author=Yoshida H, Kunisada T, Grimm T, Nishimura EK, Nishioka E, Nishikawa SI |title=Review: melanocyte migration and survival controlled by SCF/c-kit expression |journal=J. Investig. Dermatol. Symp. Proc. |volume=6 |issue=1 |pages=1–5 |year=2001 |pmid=11764276 |doi=10.1046/j.0022-202x.2001.00006.x}}&lt;/ref&gt; The genetics of this pattern are not as well understood in cats but at least some of the genes involved in melanocyte migration and survival may play a role similar as in other animals.&lt;ref name=&quot;pmid16573531&quot;&gt;{{Cite journal|author=Cooper MP, Fretwell N, Bailey SJ, Lyons LA |title=White spotting in the domestic cat (Felis catus) maps near KIT on feline chromosome B1 |journal=Anim. Genet. |volume=37 |issue=2 |pages=163–5 |year=2006 |pmid=16573531 |pmc=1464422 |doi=10.1111/j.1365-2052.2005.01389.x}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Three genotypes possible with the ''S'' (white spotting) gene, with capital ''S'' standing for a wild-type copy and lower-case ''s'' standing for the mutant.&lt;ref name=genome&gt;{{cite web|url=http://faculty.vetmed.ucdavis.edu/faculty/lalyons/Sites/color.htm |title=Coat Colors &amp; Fur Types |accessdate=2007-08-05 |publisher=Feline Genome project}} {{Dead link|date=September 2010|bot=H3llBot}}&lt;/ref&gt;

*SS (two dominant alleles) results in high grades of white spotting (sometimes resulting in a solid-looking white cat or a white cat with just a few color hairs)
*Ss (one dominant, one recessive allele) results in medium grades of white spotting
*ss (two recessive alleles) results in solid color or low grades of white spotting (sometimes as little as a few white hairs)

The lack of tabby striping in bicolor cats is controlled by the [[agouti signalling peptide|agouti protein]], which inhibits the production of [[melanin]] and thus prevents the formation of dark hair colors.&lt;ref name=&quot;pmid9300652&quot;&gt;{{Cite journal|author=Jackson IJ |title=Homologous pigmentation mutations in human, mouse and other model organisms |journal=Hum. Mol. Genet. |volume=6 |issue=10 |pages=1613–24 |year=1997 |pmid=9300652 |url=http://hmg.oxfordjournals.org/cgi/content/full/6/10/1613 | doi = 10.1093/hmg/6.10.1613}}&lt;/ref&gt; In agouti cats the gene is turned on and off as the hair grows, producing hairs with alternating stripes yellow and black.&lt;ref name=genome/&gt; In domestic cats, inactivation of the agouti gene by a [[deletion (genetics)|deletion mutation]] causes all-black coat color.&lt;ref name=&quot;pmid12620197&quot;&gt;{{Cite journal|author=Eizirik E, Yuhki N, Johnson WE, Menotti-Raymond M, Hannah SS, O'Brien SJ |title=Molecular genetics and evolution of melanism in the cat family |journal=Curr. Biol. |volume=13 |issue=5 |pages=448–53 |year=2003 |pmid=12620197 | doi = 10.1016/S0960-9822(03)00128-3}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Tuxedo cats==
[[File:Georgetuxedocat.jpg|thumb|left|A typical tuxedo cat.]]
A '''tuxedo cat''' is a bicolor cat with a [[white]] and [[black]] [[Coat (animal)|coat]]. They are called, &quot;tuxedo&quot; cats, because the animal appears to be wearing the type of [[black tie]] [[formal wear]] commonly known in the [[United States]] and [[Canada]] as a [[black tie|tuxedo]]. Most tuxedo cats are also black mask cats, a common name for felines who, due to their facial coloration, look as if they are wearing a [[black]] [[mask]] over their eyes, and often over their entire head. To be considered a true tuxedo cat, the feline's coloring should consist of a solid [[black]] [[Coat (animal)|coat]], with [[white]] [[fur]] limited to the paws, belly, chest, throat, and often the chin, although many tuxedo cats appear to sport [[goatee]]s, due to the [[black]] coloration of their [[mandible]] -- that is, the lower [[jaw]] and [[chin]]. Bicolor may also appear in the skin color. [[Paw]] pads may be black or pink, often matching the coat in that area; if the color boundary crosses the underside of the paw, the pads on either side may be different colors or even bicolored. Bicoloring of the nose and mouth are also common.

==In popular culture==
In the [[United Kingdom]], the tuxedo cat is sometimes known as the &quot;[[Jellicle|Jellicle cat]]&quot;, after the fictional tribe of black and white cats described by [[T. S. Eliot]] in ''[[Old Possum's Book of Practical Cats]]'', which was first published in 1939.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|title=Old Possum's Book of Practical Cats | author=T. S. Eliot | publisher=Harcourt | year=1982 |isbn=0-15-168656-4}}&lt;/ref&gt; In its derivative musical, ''[[Cats (musical)|Cats]]'', the tuxedo cat is exemplified by the character of the magical [[Mr. Mistoffelees]], who is portrayed as a [[stage magician]] wearing a lacy [[ruff (clothing)|ruff]] and [[bow tie]]. The musical differed from the book in that the characters included cats with many different coat colors, rather than just bicolor cats, but it retains the repeated assertion that &quot;Jellicle cats are black and white.&quot; Cats with these markings also played a starring role in the drawings illustrating ''[[The Unadulterated Cat]]'', a book written by [[Terry Pratchett]], with cartoons by Joliffe Gray.&lt;ref&gt;[[Terry Pratchett]] and Joliffe Gray ''The Unadulterated Cat'' Orion; New Ed edition (26 September 2002) ISBN 0-752-85369-4&lt;/ref&gt;

Other well known cartoon bicolor cats include [[Felix the Cat]], [[Tom Cat]] from ''[[Tom and Jerry]]'', Jess from ''[[Postman Pat]]'', [[Kitty Softpaws]] from the [[Shrek]] spin-off [[Puss in Boots (2011 film)|Puss in Boots]], [[Figaro (Disney)|Figaro]] and [[Sylvester (Looney Tunes)|Sylvester]]. A bicolor cat named Mittens is the main deuteragonist in the 2008 Disney animated film &quot;[[Bolt (2008 film)|Bolt]]&quot;.

==Examples of various bicolor patterns==
===Tuxedos===
&lt;gallery&gt;
Image:Scooter Tuxedo.jpg|A long-hair female with classic tuxedo markings.
Image:TuxedoCat Mustache.jpg|Male Tuxedo Cat with a white mustache.
Image:Tuxedo-Cat-Kitty-Ryan.JPG|Adult female tuxedo cat.
Image:Tuxedo_Cat.jpg|Adult Female Tuxedo Cat.
Image:A Closeup of Bizzel - July 2009.JPG|A closeup of a male tuxedo cat with asymmetrical face markings.
Image:Cat Tuxedo.jpg| Tuxedo Markings with &quot;goatee&quot; marking.  
&lt;/gallery&gt;

===Non-tuxedo bicolor variations===
&lt;gallery&gt;

Image:Dntvosot.JPG|Two bicolors with distinct coats.
Image:Tanukicat crop.png|An adult shorthair displaying the &quot;mask and mantle&quot; pattern
Image:Gato dormindo.jpg|Another non-tuxedo.
Image:Kit_Trinna_II.jpg|An adolescent with a Cap-and-Saddle pattern.
&lt;/gallery&gt;

===Other Bicolor Variations===
&lt;gallery&gt;
Image:Koscat1.jpg|Orange bicolor with mostly white (van pattern)
Image:TuxedoKitten.jpg|A six days old bicolor kitten, demonstrating how early the pattern can be seen
Image:trey_mississippi.jpg|Ebony White Bicolor Oriental Shorthair Male
Image:Royal_talbot.jpg|A bicolor cat with a symmetrical pattern on his face.
&lt;/gallery&gt;

===Various Colors of Bicolor Cat===
&lt;gallery&gt;
Image:Cats-MaineCoon-Caroline.png|Red bicolor
Image:Cat-heiki_bed1.jpg|Chocolate bicolor cat
Image:Harlequin_CornishRex_2003.JPG|Black Smoke Tuxedo on male [[Cornish Rex]]
Image:Bicolor cat.JPG|Bicolor cat with a grade 6 on the bicolor chart.
&lt;/gallery&gt;

==See also==
* [[Cat]]
* [[Domestic longhair cat]]
* [[Domestic shorthaired cat]]&lt;!-- Image with unknown copyright status removed: [[Image:Rhubarb.JPG|thumb|Rhubarb, the Ellis Family tuxedo cat.]] --&gt;
* [[Felidae]]
* [[Fictional cats]]
* [[Felix the Cat]]
* [[Sylvester the Cat]]
* [[Socks (cat)|Socks]]
* [[Tom Cat]]
* [[Kat Kong]]

==References==
{{Reflist}}

==External links==
*[http://www.catfacts.org/bicolor-cat-facts.htm Catfacts about Bicolor cats]

&lt;!-- Please see the talk page ([[Talk:Bicolor cat#Image overload!]]) before adding an image to this gallery; also, please try to limit to four images per section, for aesthetic reasons --&gt;

{{Cat nav}}

{{Commons category|Bicolor cats}}
{{Use dmy dates|date=September 2010}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Bicolor Cat}}
[[Category:Cat types]]

{{Link FA|fr}}
[[fr:Bicolore (robe de chat)]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
