<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="14192437" ns="0" title="SpongeBob SquarePants (season 3)"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{multiple issues|in-universe=April 2011|original research=April 2011|unreferenced=April 2011}}
{{wikify|reason=Episodes are not in proper format|date=September 2011}}
{{infobox television season
| season_name = SpongeBob SquarePants''&lt;br /&gt;Season 3
| bgcolour = #73B1B7
| show_name = ''[[SpongeBob SquarePants]]''
| image = [[Image:SBSPseason3.jpg|200px]]
| caption = ''SpongeBob SquarePants'', Season 3 
| dvd_release_date = Region 1: September 27, 2005&lt;br /&gt;Region 2: December 3, 2007&lt;br /&gt;Region 4: November 8, 2007
| dvd_format =
| country = [[United States|USA]]
| network = [[Nickelodeon (TV channel)|Nickelodeon]]
| first_aired = October 5, 2001
| last_aired = October 11, 2004
| prev_season = [[SpongeBob SquarePants (season 2)|Season 2]]
| next_season = [[SpongeBob SquarePants (season 4)|Season 4]]
|}}
'''Season Three''' of the animated television series ''[[SpongeBob SquarePants]]'' on Nickelodeon aired 37 episodes from October 5, 2001 with &quot;[[Just One Bite|The Bully]]&quot; and &quot;[[Just One Bite]]&quot; to October 11, 2004 with &quot;[[SpongeBob Meets the Strangler]]&quot; and &quot;[[Pranks a Lot]]&quot;. The show was put on hiatus during 2003. Episodes aired every few months after that date until October 11, 2004 which it ended. The show was put on hiatus again, however, and [[SpongeBob SquarePants (season 4)|Season 4]] would not begin until 6 May 2005. Like previous seasons, season three consists of 20 episodes. Season 3 was released on DVD in Regions 1, 4 and 2 on  September 27, 2005, November 8, 2007 and December 3, 2007. Season 3 was the last season with [[Stephen Hillenburg]] as the series producer - he left after the [[The SpongeBob SquarePants Movie|movie]]. After his departure, [[Derek Drymon]] became the new series producer.

===Season 3 (2001 - 2004)===


==Episodes==
===The Algae's Always Greener / SpongeGuard on Duty===
'''The Algae's Always Greener'''
{{Infobox SpongeBob episode
| Title = The Algae's Always Greener
| Image =  
| Episode = 41a
| Season = 3
| Airdate = March 22, 2002
| Guests =
| Writer = [[Aaron Springer]]&lt;br /&gt;[[C. H. Greenblatt|C.H. Greenblatt]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Merriwether Williams]]
| Director = Aaron Springer&lt;br&gt;C.H. Greenblatt&lt;br&gt;[[Frank Weiss]]&lt;br&gt;[[Derek Drymon]]
|}}

Plankton wants Mr. Krabs' secret formula, so he uses a machine to help him switch lives with the delusional crab, to see what it is like. Plankton gets so close to getting the Krabby Patty, but he is challenged by all the things Mr. Krabs has to face, such as SpongeBob’s weekly performance review, Squidward's hatred against working with SpongeBob, Pearl wanting a bigger allowance, Squidward's awful performance, and invasions from his rival (who is now a naked Mr. Krabs), and the horrid &quot;Victory Screech&quot; that the staff and customers of the Krusty Krab emit after a failed invasion by the rival. Eventually, all of these disturbances cause a deeply bothered Plankton to switch back to his life. In the end, he's happy again.{{-}}

'''SpongeGuard on Duty'''
{{Infobox SpongeBob episode
| Title = SpongeGuard on Duty
| Image =  
| Episode = 41b
| Season = 3
| Airdate = March 22, 2002
| Guests =
| Writer = [[Jay Lender]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Sam Henderson]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Mark O'Hare]]
| Director = Jay Lender&lt;br&gt;Sam Henderson&lt;br&gt;Caleb Meurer&lt;br&gt;[[Sean Dempsey]]&lt;br&gt;Derek Drymon 
|}}

SpongeBob volunteers for life guard duty at Goo Lagoon when Larry the Lobster mistakes ice cream on SpongeBob's nose for sun block (man sauce), the official sign of a Goo Lagoon lifeguard. When Larry swims to save a stranded and drowning swimmer, SpongeBob begins to struggle with the fact that he cannot swim, and thus, cannot save lives (not even his own). When Larry leaves SpongeBob in charge, the sponge tries to prevent disaster by closing off the beachfront, offering everyone free ice cream, and invoking the one-hour waiting period after eating. Then [[Patrick Star|Patrick]] shows up misunderstanding things and running into the water, and SpongeBob must save his pal. But he fails (because of Patrick), and Larry rescues them both. He then gives them swimming lessons.
{{-}}

===Club SpongeBob / My Pretty Seahorse===
'''Club SpongeBob'''
{{Infobox SpongeBob episode
| Title = Club SpongeBob
| Image = [[File:Club SpongeBob.jpg]]  
| Episode = 42a
| Season = 3
| Airdate = July 12, 2002
| Guests =
| Writer = [[Walt Dohrn]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Mark O'Hare]] 
|}}

SpongeBob and Patrick form a club, and become trapped in a [[clubhouse]] that hardly has any room. When SpongeBob states that the cephalopod wouldn't fit in, Squidward becomes offended and decides to try to join anyway. Despite SpongeBob and Patrick's pleas to stay out, Squidward squeezes himself into their tiny clubhouse. As it turns out, Patrick was speaking literally when he said Squidward wouldn't fit in, to which SpongeBob adds that they have been stuck in the clubhouse for 3 days. While trying to climb out, Squidward causes the clubhouse to land in a tropical forest in the middle of nowhere. While he seeks for a way out, SpongeBob and Patrick take the advice of their &quot;Magic Conch Shell&quot; (a parody of the magic conch from ''[[Lord of the Flies]]'' and the popular [[Magic 8-Ball]]), which tells them to do &quot;nothing&quot; and wait, a method that surprisingly works to their advantage. Meanwhile, Squidward does not share his companions' belief in the supposed powers of the shell. When supplies fall from the sky,(from a plane) Squidward keeps asking the magic conch if he can have something to eat though the magic conch keeps replying with &quot;No&quot;. The last time that he asks, he gets really angry (though it's not known if at this point, he would have to smash it on the ground). Eventually, a potential rescuer arrives, but he is also a Magic Conch Shell's club member (much to Squidward's dismay). The conch tells them to do &quot;nothing&quot; again and sit down. Squidward then decides to surrender and sit down with the three.
{{-}}

'''My Pretty Seahorse'''
{{Infobox SpongeBob episode
| Title = My Pretty Seahorse
| Image =  
| Episode = 42b
| Season = 3
| Airdate = July 12, 2002
| Guests =
| Writer = Kent Osborne&lt;br /&gt;[[Paul Tibbitt]]
| Director = Kent Osborne&lt;br&gt;Paul Tibbitt&lt;br&gt;Carson Kugler&lt;br&gt;Caleb Meurer&lt;br&gt;William Reiss&lt;br&gt;[[Tom Yasumi]]&lt;br&gt;Derek Drymon
|}}

SpongeBob finds a lost [[Seahorse]] near his house one day and decides to adopt it. He names her &quot;Mystery&quot;. When SpongeBob brings Mystery to work one day, Mr. Krabs orders him to get rid of her. The sponge decides to hide Mystery inside the restaurant, only to see that it's quite difficult to cook food and keep a wild animal from being seen at the same time, since Mystery keeps escaping and eating everything in sight, including one of the customers and all the money in the restaurant's [[safe]].
* One Time appearance: Mystery the [[Seahorse]]
* This may be Mystery's only appearance in the TV series but you can ride her in the Game Boy version of Battle for Bikini Bottom.
* The DiC logo was accidentally used in the closing logo flaw, but was fixed in 2008 after DiC was merged with Cookie Jar Entertainment.

===The Bully / Just One Bite===
'''The Bully'''
{{Infobox SpongeBob episode
| Title = The Bully
| Image =  
| Episode = 43a
| Season = 3
| Airdate = October 5, 2001
| Guests =
| Writer = [[Aaron Springer]]&lt;br /&gt;[[C. H. Greenblatt|C.H. Greenblatt]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Merriwether Williams]]
| Director = Aaron Springer&lt;br&gt;C.H. Greenblatt&lt;br&gt;Frank Weiss&lt;br&gt;Derek Drymon
|}}

SpongeBob is terrified when a new student named Flats comes to his boating school and says he wants to kick SpongeBob's beautiful butt. After being stalked by Flats all day, Flats catches up with him and gets ready to kick his butt, although, every time he strikes SpongeBob the blows are absorbed by SpongeBob's sponge-material body. Flats continues to punch SpongeBob all day and night. The next day, at school, Flats runs out of energy and passes out. Mrs. Puff enters the classroom and gasps at the sight of Flats lying on the floor and SpongeBob standing beside him with his fist raised. Thinking SpongeBob has beat up Flats for no reason, she says she's going to kick SpongeBob's butt.  

*Third appearance of Boating Students.
*Third appearance of Flatts
*Note: Though it may seem so, this is not Flats's first appearance. His debut was in fact in the [[SpongeBob SquarePants (season 1)|season 1]] episode &quot;[[Sandy's Rocket]]&quot;. When SpongeBob and Patrick believe they are on the [[Moon]] (when in reality they are still in Bikini Bottom, [[Earth]]), and wrongly assume that the Bikini Bottomites are untrustworthy aliens that are disguised as the citizens of Bikini Bottom, SpongeBob hides behind the door in Flats's bathroom [[mirror]] and traps him using a net gun. Flats made a second appearance in the episode &quot;[[SpongeBob SquarePants (season 1)#Texas|Texas]]&quot;, when Sandy realizes that her real home is in Bikini Bottom, not [[Texas]] SpongeBob and Patrick throw a party for Sandy at the Krusty Krab and SpongeBob shows her [[square dancing]] (Flats dancing with a purple box).
*Twice during the episode, SpongeBob runs in fear from Flats, and inadvertently points to a old fish when he says Flats is gonna kick his butt. The citizens of Bikini Bottom, led by Harold, are angry at this, and beat up the old fish.
*There is a deleted scene in this episode. One of the things SpongeBob does while being beaten up by Flats is playing [[leapfrog]] with Patrick.
{{-}}

'''Just One Bite'''
{{Infobox SpongeBob episode
| Title = Just One Bite
| Image = 
| Episode = 43b
| Season = 3
| Airdate = October 5, 2001
| Guests =
| Writer = [[Jay Lender]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Sam Henderson]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Merriwether Williams]]
| Director = Jay Lender&lt;br&gt;Sam Henderson&lt;br&gt;Caleb Meurer&lt;br&gt;Sean Dempsey&lt;br&gt;Derek Drymon
|}}

When SpongeBob learns that Squidward has never had a Krabby Patty, it becomes his obsession to get his co-worker to take just one bite, believing that it is the reason why he is &quot;always so miserable&quot;. When Squidward finally does, he hates it; at least that's what he tells SpongeBob. In front of SpongeBob, Squidward throws the Krabby Patty to the ground, stamps on it twice, hits it with a block of [[wood]] and then slams a [[headstone]] down on it. After SpongeBob goes away, Squidward digs the Krabby Patty out and swallows what remains of it, including some excess [[sand]]. He then tries to get a Krabby Patty from SpongeBob, telling him a customer ordered it. When no one claims the patty, Squidward tells SpongeBob to leave it at the counter, but SpongeBob eats it instead. Squidward attempts to eat one out of the garbage but SpongeBob intervenes and &quot;[[Cremation|cremates]] it&quot;. That night, Squidward [[dream]]s of meeting a Krabby Patty, falling in love with it, marrying it, having children with it, growing old with it and dying with it. Afterwards, he goes to the Krusty Krab and sneaks into the patty vault inside the Krusty Krab. Squidward unexpectedly sees SpongeBob come in and SpongeBob realises that Squidward does likes Krabby Patties. Squidward admits this and eats dozens of the Krabby Patties in the vault. SpongeBob tries to warn Squidward that eating too many patties at once will cause him to explode, but it's already too late. He is taken away to the [[hospital]] with his head separated from the remains of his body and the [[paramedic]] who is there in the ambulance with Squidward tells him &quot;Yeah, I remember my first Krabby Patty.&quot;

*Note: This episode is a parody of the book ''[[Green Eggs and Ham]]'' with SpongeBob as &quot;Sam I am&quot; and Squidward as the grumpy unnamed character who claims to dislike green eggs and ham before admitting liking them after trying them.
*There is a deleted scene in this episode. In the original episode, when Squidward enters the Krusty Krab at night after his dream, he runs up against the door, looks into the restaurant and says &quot;There it is! Unguarded! All I have to do is...&quot;, However, he then realizes breaking in is too easy and then notices a bucket of an unseen substance on top of the door. He thinks it is just [[water]], so he kicks the door open and the bucket falls on the ground, causing the substance in the bucket to spill. Squidward walks inside the Krusty Krab and notices that the bucket did not contain water, but [[gasoline]]. A robotic arm then appears behind Squidward and drops a lit match into the gasoline puddle and Squidward screams as the Krusty Krab goes up in flames, burning him badly as well. Squidward runs into the kitchen, thinking that his pain is over, but is thwarted by another bucket of gasoline, which causes the same scenario as before. He then sees the Patty Vault and walks over to it, no longer blackened from the fire. This entire scene was later cut out, resulting in Squidward walking up to the Patty Vault without even entering the Krusty Krab. No explanation has ever been given for this, but it may be either because the scene was thought to be too violent or to ensure young children were not encouraged to play with fire, also the fact that the episode aired so close to the [[September 11 attacks]] it was believed to be considered inappropriate to air explosions and fire during the aftermath of the attack. The deleted scene can be watched via [[YouTube]].
*When the uncut version of this episode used to air The Bully used to air first but airing of the edited version has this in reverse.
*There is a [[Continuity error|continuity error]] as well. Though Squidward claims to have never eaten a Krabby Patty, this is actually false. In &quot;[[Your Shoe's Untied]]&quot;, which aired the previous season, SpongeBob constantly trips over his untied shoelaces and accidentally launches hundreds of Krabby Patties directly into Squidward's mouth and down his throat, causing Squidward to grow to enormous size. However, Squidward never had any intention to eat them, which probably explains his denial.
{{-}}

===Nasty Patty / Idiot Box===
'''Nasty Patty'''
{{Infobox SpongeBob episode
| Title = Nasty Patty
| Image = 
| Episode = 44a
| Season = 3
| Airdate = March 1, 2002
| Guests =
| Writer = [[Paul Tibbitt]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Kazimieras G. Prapuolenis|Kaz]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Mark O'Hare]] 
|}}

A health inspector comes to the Krusty Krab. Mr. Krabs and Spongebob has given the inspector a big meal. After the health inspector finish all the food, he asked for a Krabby Patty so he can pass the inspection. After Mr. Krabs and Spongebob saw the news about a man who disguised as the health inspector so he can have &quot;free food&quot;. Spongebob and Mr. Krabs thought that the heath inspector is the &quot;imposter&quot;, so they make a nasty patty and give it to the health inspector because they think he's a fake inspector.  After he faints from eating the patty, SpongeBob and Krabs think they killed him (when what actually happened was that a fly got stuck in the inspector's throat). They are panicking, but still they cannot give up, so they went to bury the health inspector's body. However, when Spongebob threw a big rock out of the way, the health inspector woke up and says &quot;Where am I?&quot; and got hit by a big rock that Spongebob threw. When the cops came to fake an arrest with them, Mr. Krabs and Spongebob thought they were gonna get arrested for killing the health inspector, but Mr. Krabs said &quot;What will be the charges?&quot; and the cops said &quot;For not being in the Krusty Krab to whip us up for some delicious Krabby Patty.&quot; After the health inspector slided down the mountain to Spongebob's foot, they shrieked and Spongebob put him in the trunk and knocked out the inspector again, without seeing him, while Mr. Krabs kept the cops busy. When they got to the Krusty Krab, Spongebob tries to put the inspector's body in the freezer, but the back door to the freezer is locked, he put the body in his hat. When the cops are about to leave, the officer says &quot;I want a soda,&quot; then Mr. Krabs gave her a soda, but when she wanted ice, Mr. Krabs tried to tell her that there is no ice. The officer said &quot;It seems like you two committed a murder,&quot; Mr. Krabs, finally confesses and when they open the freezer door, it's nothing but melted ice. After the officer said &quot;Is this some kind of a joke?&quot; and Mr. Krabs say yes. The officer must have thought that he turned into a zombie and walked out and laughed. Meanwhile, after the health inspector walked in, yawning the kitchen, Spongebob screamed &quot;Ahhh!!! It's a zombie!!!&quot; The officers hit the inspector on the head, and then when he got up he said that the Krusty Krab has passed the inspection. After the inspector crawled out of the kitchen, the door shut on the inspector's head.
{{-}}

'''Idiot Box'''
{{Infobox SpongeBob episode
| Title = Idiot Box
| Image = 
| Episode = 44b
| Season = 3
| Airdate = March 1, 2002
| Guests =
| Writer = [[Paul Tibbitt]]&lt;br /&gt;Kent Osborne&lt;br /&gt;[[Merriwether Williams]]
|}}

SpongeBob and Patrick order a giant Television set just so that they can play in the box. They let Squidward have the TV, but when Squidward tells them their idea to play in the box is stupid, SpongeBob and Patrick deny this saying that imagination is better than Television. Squidward when he begins to leave begins to hear sound effects from the box as SpongeBob and Patrick play their &quot;Imagination&quot; games. Squidward asks them how is noise being made, but they deny being aware of this. They add that it is caused by &quot;Imagination.&quot; Squidward begins to suspect later that they are using a tape recorder instead of their imaginations and so he comes into the box to find out what the sounds are caused by, but when he, Patrick, and SponeBob imagine &quot;Robot-Pirate Island&quot; the sounds are not heard. Squidward still believes that there is a tape recorder or anything that makes sound and so he sneaks into the box at night and imagines himself as a race car driver and he hears the sounds, but a garbage truck confuses the box to be garbage and it takes it to the dump with Squidward inside.
In an epilogue, SpongeBob and Patrick go outside the next day to find their box gone, and so they decide to go to visit Squidward instead. 

*During the liftoff sounds, [[NASA]] commentator [[Steve Nesbit]] can be heard during the &quot;ascent&quot;.
*The commentary of the launch was of the fatal [[STS-51-L]] Challenger mission.
{{-}}

===Mermaid Man and Barnacle Boy IV / Doing Time===
'''Mermaid Man and Barnacle Boy IV'''
{{Infobox SpongeBob episode
| Title = Mermaid Man and Barnacle Boy IV
| Image =  
| Episode = 45a
| Season = 3
| Airdate = January 21, 2002
| Guests =
| Writer = [[Jay Lender]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Sam Henderson]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Merriwether Williams]]
| Director = Jay Lender&lt;br&gt;Sam Henderson&lt;br&gt;Caleb Meurer&lt;br&gt;Sean Dempsey&lt;br&gt;Derek Drymon
|}}

When Mermaid Man accidentally leaves his belt behind as he and Barnacle Boy leave the Krusty Krab, SpongeBob picks it up and proceeds to test it out with a barrel of pickles. Amazed at what it does, he shrinks the kitchen props. As he serves Krabby Patties to [[cockroach]]es, Squidward discovers the belt. Surprised that Mermaid Man lent it to SpongeBob, he picks up the phone and threatens to tell on him. SpongeBob is concerned that Mermaid Man will be mad, so he shrinks Squidward in order to stop him. Squidward grows angry and demands him to unshrink him this instant or he is gonna be in very big trouble. SpongeBob agrees and tries to, but unfortunately, he doesn't know how to, so he runs over to Patrick's house, where Pat thinks Squidward is an action figure. After being told by SpongeBob to stop playing with it, Pat advises him to turn the M on the belt upside-down to make a W for &quot;Wumbo&quot; and SpongeBob proceeds to fire away, but he accidentally shrinks Patrick. SpongeBob quickly panics and shrinks everybody in Bikini Bottom, including Mermaid Man and Barnacle Boy. It is quickly discovered that the shrink ray's effects are irreversible, so the Bikini Bottomites climb into SpongeBob's body through his pores and begin to attack him on the inside; before they can do any real damage, SpongeBob atones for his mistakes by shrinking the city of Bikini Bottom and himself, allowing everyone to live out their lives peacefully. However, Plankton soon arrives back from his vacation to find a city his size which however accomplishes his dream to be taller to crush his enemies.
{{-}}

'''Doing Time'''
{{Infobox SpongeBob episode
| Title = Doing Time
| Image =  
| Episode = 45b
| Season = 3
| Airdate = January 21, 2002
| Guests =
| Writer = [[Aaron Springer]]&lt;br /&gt;[[C. H. Greenblatt|C.H. Greenblatt]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Merriwether Williams]]
| Director = Aaron Springer&lt;br&gt;C.H. Greenblatt&lt;br&gt;Frank Weiss&lt;br&gt;Derek Drymon
|}}

Spongebob has begun yet another reckless driving rampage during his driver's test, which ends plunging off a cliff. When the car nose-dives into a tanker truck full of fruit juice, which floods out an entire nursing home, Mrs. Puff is arrested on the spot and thrown in prison. Spongebob tries every will to help Mrs. Puff escape from prison, yet every time he appears, Mrs. Puff refuses to deal because she enjoys prison, especially because Spongebob isn't around. Continuous attempts by SpongeBob and Patrick to get Mrs. Puff out of jail get her in trouble with the prison wardens, and eventually, she is locked up in a straight jacket, and placed in [[padded cell]]ed-solitary confinement. To Mrs. Puff's dismay, the walls are made of &quot;sponge,&quot; and Spongebob's maniacally-laughing face ends up appearing on the walls, floor, and ceiling. Mrs. Puff begins screaming, only to wake up from a dream. It turns out she and Spongebob are still plunging off a cliff, this time ending in the same outcome as before, only this time Spongebob gets arrested. Mrs. Puff then begins to relax, only to appear in shackles and a prison outfit. She wakes up screaming again, and is still sitting in the boatmobile going off a cliff. Now an uninviting inmate from the first dream is driving, and she wakes up screaming again. Spongebob still happens to be driving off a cliff. Mrs. Puff groans, &quot;Oh, forget it.&quot;

*Almost all episode is dream
{{-}}

===Snowball Effect / One Krab's Trash===
'''Snowball Effect'''
{{Infobox SpongeBob episode
| Title = Snowball Effect
| Image =  
| Episode = 46a
| Season = 3
| Airdate = February 22, 2002
| Guests =
| Writer = [[Paul Tibbitt]]&lt;br /&gt;Kent Osborne&lt;br /&gt;[[Merriwether Williams]]
| Director = Paul Tibbitt&lt;br&gt;Kent Osborne&lt;br&gt;Carson Kugler&lt;br&gt;Caleb Meurer&lt;br&gt;William Reiss&lt;br&gt;Andrew Overtoom&lt;br&gt;Derek Drymon
|}}

A snowstorm hits Bikini Bottom, thanks to a [[glacier]] that settled above the city. For SpongeBob and Patrick, this means snowball fights. An attempt to recruit Squidward is unsuccessful, as he finds such an activity to be immature, until the prospect of his neighbors injuring each other entices him. But pretty soon, Squidward [[paranoia|goes overboard with the whole thing]]. Eventually, SpongeBob and Patrick decide to go inside, but Squidward thinks they're still outside and playing (partly because of a tree that is dropping snow on him, which he thinks is SpongeBob and Patrick still throwing snowballs at him).
{{-}}

'''One Krab's Trash'''
{{Infobox SpongeBob episode
| Title = One Krab's Trash
| Image = 
| Episode = 46b
| Season = 3
| Airdate = February 22, 2002
| Guests = Gary Carter III
| Writer = [[Paul Tibbitt]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Kazimieras G. Prapuolenis|Kaz]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Mark O'Hare]]
|}}

Mr. Krabs sells some junk. He sold a toilet plunger to Patrick, but when he said that it looks like the toilet plunger he threw out last Tuesday, Mr. Krabs flips the bottom part over and says that it's a 17th century soup ladle. Mr. Krabs sells it for $5, but when Patrick says &quot;I only got seven,&quot; and Mr. Krabs takes the offer, he calls himself a smart shopper. Among the other junk there was a novelty soda-drink hat, which SpongeBob purchases. When Mr. Krabs finds that the hat is rare, and worth a million dollars, he tries everything he can to get it back. Eventually, he pretends to be the &quot;Ghost of Soda-drink Hats&quot; by hooking a badly drawn ghost to a fishing rod and sticking it through spongebob's houses window, and tells SpongeBob that the hat once belonged to a now-deceased person named &quot;''Smitty Werbenjaegermanjenson''&quot;. He tells SpongeBob that if he doesn't place the hat in Smithy's grave, he'll be cursed. So, a frightened SpongeBob decides to fulfill the command, though he apparently placed it in the grave of &quot;Smitty ''Werbenjaegermanjanson''&quot;. Mr. Krabs defiles his grave and takes the hat, only for Smitty Werbenmanjanson to rise from the dead in the form of an animated skeleton, and asks Mr. Krabs to give him the hat back. Mr. Krabs refuses, so Smitty summons the &quot;army of the living dead&quot; to kill Mr. Krabs and take the hat back. But Mr. Krabs defeats them all, and leaves the graveyard. He then tries to sell the hat, only to learn it is it is now considered worthless, since a warehouse full of them was recently discovered. Then, SpongeBob passes by with his new hat, which claps with hands on it, and it is worth even more money &amp;nbsp;&amp;mdash; a billion dollars. Mr. Krabs then cries. Squidward is passing by and mocks Mr. Krabs by saying &quot;What a baby!&quot; a verse which Mr. Krabs said by watching Squidward dig up a grave of his &quot;Own Wishes, Hopes and Dreams&quot;.
{{-}}

===As Seen on TV / Can You Spare a Dime?===
'''As Seen on TV '''
{{Infobox SpongeBob episode
| Title = As Seen on TV
| Image = 
| Episode = 47a
| Season = 3
| Airdate = March 8, 2002
| Guests =
| Writer = [[Aaron Springer]]&lt;br /&gt;[[C. H. Greenblatt|C.H. Greenblatt]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Merriwether Williams]]
| Director = C.H. Greenblatt&lt;br&gt;Aaron Springer&lt;br&gt;Frank Weiss&lt;br&gt;Derek Drymon
|}}

The Krusty Krab makes a low-budget TV commercial, starring Mr. Krabs, Squidward, and Pearl. SpongeBob is in it, too, but only the very top of his head can be seen from the dining area, and only his chest is seen on a close-up of a Krabby Patty. When he heads to work the next morning, SpongeBob is completely convinced that his few seconds on TV would make him a star to many, even though his face was never seen, and the inflation of his ego gets in the way of his kitchen duties.
{{-}}

'''Can You Spare a Dime?'''
{{Infobox SpongeBob episode
| Title = Can You Spare a Dime?
| Image = 
| Episode = 47b
| Season = 3
| Airdate = March 8, 2002
| Guests =
| Writer = [[Jay Lender]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Sam Henderson]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Merriwether Williams]]
| Director = Jay Lender&lt;br&gt;Sam Henderson&lt;br&gt;Caleb Meurer&lt;br&gt;Sean Dempsey&lt;br&gt;Derek Drymon
|}}

Mr. Krabs loses his lucky first dime. Because he kept in in the register for luck, he accuses Squidward of stealing it, being the cashier. An argument ensues, and Squidward quits, setting out to fulfill his fantasies. However, SpongeBob finds Squidward on the street, living in a box and begging for change. Although Spongebob is oblivious as to what happened to him, Squidward convinces Spongebob that he lost everything in the wake of quitting his job, going as far as eating his own artwork since nobody would buy it. SpongeBob lets him move in to his house, but Squidward quickly takes over. After &quot;months&quot; of being Squidward's slave, SpongeBob tries to convince Mr. Krabs to hire Squidward back. Mr. Krabs refuses because he still believes that Squidward stole his dime. SpongeBob explodes in rage and strangles Mr. Krabs, finding out the dime (a giant ring-shaped boulder) was in his pocket. Mr. Krabs then agrees to re-hire Squidward, but then accuses him of placing the dime in his pocket.&lt;br /&gt; 

*Note: There is a [[Continuity error|continuity error]] in this episode. When SpongeBob shows Squidward some possible jobs in a newspaper, Squidward says he is allergic to newsprint. However, in several future episodes, Squidward is shown reading a newspaper and is not getting affected by it. It is possible that Squidward faked the allergies so he didn't have to see the jobs.
{{-}}

===No Weenies Allowed / Squilliam Returns===
'''No Weenies Allowed'''
{{Infobox SpongeBob episode
| Title = No Weenies Allowed
| Image = 
| Episode = 48a
| Season = 3
| Airdate = March 15, 2002
| Guests =
| Writer = [[Paul Tibbitt]]&lt;br /&gt;Kent Osborne&lt;br /&gt;[[Merriwether Williams]]
| Director = Paul Tibbitt&lt;br&gt;Kent Osborne&lt;br&gt;Carson Kugler&lt;br&gt;Caleb Meurer&lt;br&gt;William Reiss&lt;br&gt;Andrew Overtoom&lt;br&gt;Derek Drymon
|}}

SpongeBob wants to get into the Salty Spittoon, the toughest club in Bikini Bottom. Sandy proves her worth and gains admission. Spongebob attempts to join as well, but the bouncer says he is a &quot;weenie&quot; (weakling) and suggests going to a restaurant called &quot;Weenie Hut Jr.'s.&quot; SpongeBob is in denial, saying he is tough enough to get in but ends up at Weenie Hut Jr.'s and meets two real &quot;weenies&quot; once he's in there. He then tries to get into the Salty Spittoon numerous times, only to end up at Weenie Hut Jr.'s once again. He then finds Patrick at Weenie Hut Jr.'s, and convinces Patrick to fake a fight with him so he can get into the Salty Spittoon. At first, their act proves unconvincing, but when SpongeBob calls Patrick &quot;Tubby&quot;, an angered Patrick punches SpongeBob. However, SpongeBob reminds Patrick that he was supposed to let him win, so Patrick agrees. He then puts on an act by beating himself senseless without his own appendages. SpongeBob seems to be the victor, so he is granted permission to enter. The next thing SpongeBob knows, he is in an ambulance on the way to a hospital with Sandy, finding out he injured himself by slipping on an ice cube. At the hospital, the doctor says he has gone to the wrong hospital (because SpongeBob described his injuries as &quot;boo boos&quot;) and tells him to go to a hospital called &quot;Weenie Hut General&quot;. SpongeBob then goes into denial once again.
{{-}}

'''Squilliam Returns'''
{{Infobox SpongeBob episode
| Title = Squilliam Returns
| Image =  
| Episode = 48b
| Season = 3
| Airdate = March 15, 2002
| Guests = [[Dee Bradley Baker]] as Squilliam Fancyson
| Writer = [[Sam Henderson]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Jay Lender]]&lt;br /&gt;Kent Osborne
| Director = Jay Lender&lt;br&gt;Sam Henderson&lt;br&gt;Heather Martinez&lt;br&gt;[[Mike Roth]]&lt;br&gt;Sean Dempsey&lt;br&gt;Derek Drymon 
|}}

Squidward is on his lunch break and he spots his arch-rival from high school, Squilliam Fancyson, who is very wealthy and succeeded in everything Squidward failed at since high school. Squidward says he owns a five star restaurant and it has great food. After successfully asking Mr. Krabs if he can run the restaurant for one night, Squidward makes Mr. Krabs the cook, SpongeBob the waiter, and Patrick the coat-check. But once everybody proves to be completely inept, Squidward prepares to confess the truth to Squilliam. However, when Squilliam arrives, SpongeBob is the best waiter ever because he (literally) emptied his mind of everything except fine dining and breathing. Squilliam loves the restaurant and asks for SpongeBob's name. But SpongeBob does not remember his name, and in a mental breakdown, he ruins the Krusty Krab, revealing it is normally a fast-food restaurant. Squidward then admits he is really a cashier, and owns no restaurant. Squilliam tells him he's also a cashier who's not in the upper-class, but soon reveals it was actually a lie. Squilliam and his friends leave, leaving Squidward humiliated.

*This episode is a [[Flashback (narrative)|flashback]] as though Squidward and Squilliam have not met before in the series, even though Squilliam appeared in the [[SpongeBob SquarePants (season 2)|Season 2]] episode [[Band Geeks]].
{{-}}

===Krab Borg / Rock-a-Bye Bivalve===
'''Krab Borg'''
{{Infobox SpongeBob episode
| Title = Krab Borg
| Image = 
| Episode = 49a
| Season = 3
| Airdate = March 29, 2002
| Guests = [[Rodney Bingenheimer]] as The DJ
| Writer = [[Paul Tibbitt]]&lt;br /&gt;Kent Osborne&lt;br /&gt;[[Mark O'Hare]]
| Director = Paul Tibbitt&lt;br&gt;Kent Osborne&lt;br&gt;Carson Kugler&lt;br&gt;Caleb Meurer&lt;br&gt;William Reiss&lt;br&gt;Tom Yasumi&lt;br&gt;Derek Drymon
|}}

SpongeBob watches a scary robot movie and thinks everything is a robot, even Gary. The next day, SpongeBob thinks Mr. Krabs is a robot and tells Squidward that robots have glowing red eyes, pinchers for hands and ran on batteries. seconds after, Mr.Krabs comes out after accidentally spilling salt on his eyes causing them to glow red and has a pincher in his hand to fish an egg out of a pot and batteries in his pocket from his radio. Spongebob and Squidward soon believe that robots have conquered the world, and they team up to overpower and question the &quot;robot&quot; and find out what he did with the &quot;real&quot; Mr. Krabs, oblivious to the fact that the Mr. Krabs they see is not a robot, and is no fake. The interrogation involves torturing him (like slapping him and destroying many of his valuables) in an attempt to &quot;find out&quot; about the location of the &quot;real&quot; Mr. Krabs. When they find out Mr. Krabs isn't a robot (and is the genuine Mr. Krabs), SpongeBob recalls that the ending of the movie revealed the events of the movie was just their imagination. He then runs away, leaving Squidward out to dry.{{-}}

'''Rock-a-Bye Bivalve'''
{{Infobox SpongeBob episode
| Title = Rock-a-Bye Bivalve
| Image =  
| Episode = 49b
| Season = 3
| Airdate = March 29, 2002
| Guests =
| Writer = [[Jay Lender]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Sam Henderson]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Mark O'Hare]]
|}}

Patrick and SpongeBob are outside one day and find an abandoned baby [[scallop]], the undersea equivalent of birds. Since its parents are nowhere to be found, they decide to raise it, and additionally act as the parents of the scallop; SpongeBob is the &quot;mother&quot; while Patrick is the &quot;father&quot;. However, things quickly grow out of hand as SpongeBob ends up as the sole caretaker of the scallop, while Patrick goes to &quot;work.&quot; Spongebob grows suspicious of Patrick's rare appearances during the daytime, revealing the amount of diapers he has had to change (e.g., an [[excavator]] organizing a pile outside his house). Even though Patrick apologizes, he continues on with his routine the next morning. After returning from &quot;work,&quot; Spongebob confronts Patrick about his late evening schedules, which causes Patrick to be overwhelmed and go back to &quot;work,&quot; which is revealed to be just lounging at his residence. This fuels a heated argument between the two, instantly broken up when the scallop is perched on Spongebob's window. The two apologize and prepare to catch  the scallop, but never happens now that it is revealed that it can fly. Spongebob and Patrick wave to the scallop as it flies away.

Note:This is the most controversial episode of SpongeBob, mostly because its so-called &quot;references to homosexuality.&quot; One scene during the episode has Spongebob and Patrick appear to get in bed together, only to reveal that Patrick is actually sleeping under the mattress similar to how he sleeps under his rock. Also, at the end Patrick says to Spongebob &quot;let's have another.&quot;.
*One Time appearance: Junior
{{-}}

===Wet Painters / Krusty Krab Training Video===
'''Wet Painters'''
{{Infobox SpongeBob episode
 | Title = Wet Painters
 | Series = [[SpongeBob SquarePants]]
 | Image = &lt;!-- Title card --&gt;
 | Season = 3
 | Episode = 50a
 | Production = &lt;!-- Production number --&gt;
 | Airdate = May 10, 2002
 | BDE Rank = 92
 | Guests = &lt;!-- List guest stars and which character they played --&gt;
 | Writer = [[C. H. Greenblatt|C.H. Greenblatt]], [[Kazimieras G. Prapuolenis|Kaz]] and [[Mark O'Hare]]
 | Director = 
 | Storyboard Artist = 
 | Supervising Producer = 
 | Director = 
 | Director (Storyboard) = 
 | Director (Animation) = 
 | Director (Creative) = 
 | Director (Technical) = 
 |}}

Patrick and SpongeBob are hired to paint Mr. Krabs' house, but are told that it is permanent paint, threatening to amputate their butts and mount them over his fireplace if they get even one drop on anything but his walls. After they finish painting, chaos ensues when they get a tiny drop of paint on Mr. Krabs' first dollar. SpongeBob desperately tries to remove the paint from the dollar, but only ends up spreading it all over. When Mr. Krabs comes back, he licks the paint off and reveals the paint is [[saliva]]-soluble. When Mr. Krabs informs them that his previous warning was just to mess with them, SpongeBob and Patrick get angry and storm off. Mr. Krabs laughs at his charade so hard that spittle gets scattered all over the walls and ruins the paint job. 
{{-}}

'''Krusty Krab Training Video'''
{{Infobox SpongeBob episode
| Title = Krusty Krab Training Video
| Image = 
| Episode = 50b
| Season = 3
| Airdate = May 10, 2002
| Guests = Steve Keleha
| Writer = [[Aaron Springer]]&lt;br /&gt;[[C. H. Greenblatt|C.H. Greenblatt]]&lt;br /&gt;Kent Osborne
| Director = Aaron Springer&lt;br&gt;C.H. Greenblatt&lt;br&gt;Frank Weiss&lt;br&gt;Derek Drymon
|}}

A training narration of the Krusty Krab, demonstrating what work is like and how it takes place at the Krusty Krab. The entire episode is formatted like a sort of an employee training video, and features an anxious SpongeBob waiting to make a Krabby Patty. However, when he finally learns the recipe, the video abruptly ends before it's revealed to keep it secret.

*Note: After the end credits there shown the [[Klasky Csupo Inc.|Klasky Csupo]] Robot logo, instead of the [[United Plankton Pictures Inc.]]
{{-}}

===[[Party Pooper Pants]]===
'''Party Pooper Pants'''
{{Infobox SpongeBob episode
| Title = Party Pooper Pants
| Image = 
| Episode = 51
| Season = 3
| Airdate = May 17, 2002
| Guests =
| Writer = [[Paul Tibbitt]]&lt;br /&gt;Kent Osborne&lt;br /&gt;[[Mark O'Hare]]
| Director = Paul Tibbitt&lt;br&gt;Kent Osborne&lt;br&gt;Carson Kugler&lt;br&gt;Caleb Meurer&lt;br&gt;William Reiss&lt;br&gt;Mike Roth&lt;br&gt;Andrew Overtoom&lt;br&gt;Derek Drymon
|}}

SpongeBob gets a plan-your-own-party kit and decides to plan a party and invite everyone he knows even though a lot of people don't know him. He panics when the first guest is 30 seconds late but eventually everyone arrives. When he leaves to the coat room thinking the party is out of control while everyone is just having fun and he breaks it up and tries to read comics in an organized and boring fashion. After he is locked out accidentally the police throw him in jail for busting into his own house but when he returns Patrick tells him that it was a best party ever.

*Note: Nickeldeon promoted this episode as &quot;SpongeBob's House Party&quot;.
{{-}}

===Chocolate with Nuts / Mermaid Man and Barnacle Boy V===
'''Chocolate with Nuts'''
{{Infobox SpongeBob episode
| Title = Chocolate with Nuts
| Image = 
| Episode = 52a
| Season = 3
| Airdate = June 1, 2002
| Guests = 
| Writer = [[Paul Tibbitt]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Kazimieras G. Prapuolenis|Kaz]]&lt;br /&gt;Kent Osborne&lt;br /&gt;[[Merriwether Williams]]
|}}

After accidentally getting Squidward's &quot;Fancy Living Digest&quot; in the mail, SpongeBob and Patrick want to live fancy too. They decide they will get rich by selling candy bars. People keep turning them down so they lie about the candy. People start to buy the candy, but at the last house they go to, a con man tricks them out of everything they earned up to that point. When they feel all hope is lost, a chocolate maniac catches them and wants to purchase all their chocolate. With all the money they have they decide to rent out the local fancy restaurant, aptly named 'Fancy!'.

This episode is very well known for the chocolate maniac's exclamation, &quot;CHOCOLATE!&quot;
{{-}}

'''Mermaid Man and Barnacle Boy V'''
{{Infobox SpongeBob episode
| Title = Mermaid Man and Barnacle Boy V
| Image =  
| Episode = 52b
| Season = 3
| Airdate = June 1, 2002
| Guests = [[Ernest Borgnine]] as Mermaid Man&lt;br /&gt;[[Tim Conway]] as Barnacle Boy
| Writer = [[C. H. Greenblatt|C.H. Greenblatt]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Kazimieras G. Prapuolenis|Kaz]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Merriwether Williams]]
|}}

Barnacle Boy is sick of being treated like an actual boy by Mermaid Man (and everyone else), so he decides to become evil and teams up with the Dirty Bubble and Manray. Barnacle Man (as he is now called) and his gang, known as '''E.V.I.L.''' ('''E'''very '''V'''illain '''I'''s '''L'''emons), go around town doing evil. SpongeBob, Squidward, Patrick, Sandy, and Mermaid Man team up to get Barnacle Boy back. Everybody but Mermaidman fails to do so. Barnacle Boy tells Mermaid Man that there are just 3 things that he wants. He wants to be treated like a real superhero (and not just Mermaid Man's [[sidekick]]), to be called &quot;Barnacle Man&quot; (although, he is still called Barnacle Boy in later episodes), and to get an adult-sized Krabby Patty, which Mermaid Man agrees to. Barnacle Man goes back to the good side, and his friendship with Mermaid Man is restored. 

*Note: Another name for this episode is &quot;Superfriends&quot;.
{{-}}

===New Student Starfish / Clams===
'''New Student Starfish'''
{{Infobox SpongeBob episode
| Title = New Student Starfish
| Image =  
| Episode = 53a
| Season = 3
| Airdate = September 20, 2002
| Guests = 
| Writer = [[Paul Tibbitt]]&lt;br /&gt;Kent Osborne&lt;br /&gt;[[Mark O'Hare]]
|}}

Patrick tells SpongeBob that he is bored whenever he spends the day at boating school, so SpongeBob lets the starfish tag along. Unfortunately, this only leads to trouble, as Patrick's antics during class get SpongeBob sent to the back of the classroom, and costs him one of his &quot;good noodle stars.&quot; SpongeBob's anger leads to a lame excuse for a fight in the hallway between he and Patrick, getting them sent to detention after school.









'''Clams'''
{{Infobox SpongeBob episode
| Title = Clams
| Image =  
| Episode = 53b
| Season = 3
| Airdate = September 20, 2002
| Guests =
| Writer = [[Jay Lender]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Sam Henderson]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Mark O'Hare]]
| Director = Jay Lender&lt;br&gt;Sam Henderson&lt;br&gt;Caleb Meurer&lt;br&gt;Sean Dempsey&lt;br&gt;Derek Drymon
|}}

Mr. Krabs earns his millionth dollar, and rewards SpongeBob and Squidward by taking them clam fishing for the weekend (though Squidward doesn't like this reward). A major problem soon arises, as Mr. Krabs loses his millionth dollar when a giant clam snatches it away (due to SpongeBob accidentally hooking it while fishing). The mishap sends him over the edge, as he forces SpongeBob and Squidward to find the dollar, telling them they can't leave until it's found. To show he's serious, he tosses all of their food overboard, leaving only one sandwich (a parody of [[Herman Melville]]'s classic, ''[[Moby-Dick]]''). When they try to sneak away, Mr. Krabs goes completely insane and uses the two as live bait. But, as the clam is about to eat them, he seizes the opportunity to get his dollar, causing him to get eaten. When the two think he's gone for good, he reappears with the dollar but he traded his entire body except for his head and left arm for it.

*This episode spoofs [[Steven Spielberg]]'s film ''[[Jaws (film)|Jaws]]''.
{{-}}

===[[wikt:ugh|Ugh]]===
'''Ugh '''
{{Infobox SpongeBob episode
| Title = Spongebobs B.C.
| Image =  
| Episode = 54
| Season = 1
| Airdate = July 17, 1999
| Guests =
| Writer = [[Paul Tibbitt]]&lt;br /&gt;Kent Osborne
| Director = Derek Drymon&lt;br&gt;Carson Kugler&lt;br&gt;Caleb Meurer&lt;br&gt;Kent Osborne&lt;br&gt;[[Mark Osborne (filmmaker)|Mark Osborne]]&lt;br&gt;Andrew Overtoom&lt;br&gt;William Reiss&lt;br&gt;Paul Tibbitt
}}

Prehistoric ancestors of SpongeBob, Patrick and Squidward &amp;nbsp;&amp;mdash; SpongeGar, Patar, and Squog (respectively), discover fire after a lightning bolt strikes a piece of wood and sets it ablaze. After realizing that food can be cooked over the fire, the three have a feast with their surroundings as the food. After their feast, the three cannot decide on who would keep the fire at their house for the night, and fight over it. But rain puts the fire out. After SpongeGar and Patar apologize to Squog for their arguments, just as he prepares to hit SpongeGar and Patar over the head, Squog gets struck by lightning, and gets set ablaze.

Meanwhile, in a prehistoric home, Potty the Parrot and Patchy the Pirate argue over which era is better, the future or the past; Potty prefers the future, and Patchy prefers the past. Eventually, though, Potty unites a futuristic robot and a prehistoric caveman together, and they sing a song. And despite Patchy soon becoming interested in the future too, Potty gives him a T-Rex, which bites him.

*Nickeldeon promoted this episode as &quot;SpongeBob B.C.&quot;
{{-}}

===The Great Snail Race / Mid-Life Crustacean===
'''The Great Snail Race'''
{{Infobox SpongeBob episode
| Title = The Great Snail Race
| Image =  
| Episode = 55a
| Season = 3
| Airdate = January 29, 2003
| Guests =
| Writer = [[Paul Tibbitt]]&lt;br /&gt;Kent Osborne&lt;br /&gt;Joe Liss
|}}

SpongeBob and Patrick discover that Squidward has ordered a female purebred racing snail named Snellie (voiced by [[Tom Kenny]]), whom he plans to enter in Bikini Bottom's most famous snail race. SpongeBob decides to enter Gary in the race, when Squidward brags that Snellie is better than Gary, despite being scoffed at by Squidward because Gary is a mutt. Patrick also decides to enter a rock that he confuses with a snail named &quot;Rocky&quot; (despite being told continuously by other characters that Rocky is a rock). SpongeBob and Patrick enter the snail and rock in the race anyway, but SpongeBob trains Gary roughly and nonstop, resulting in Gary falling apart in an ironic fashion (his insides basically are pieces of machinery). However, just as Snellie is about to cross the finish line, she turns back to comfort Gary, and the two snails fall in love. However, at the end of the episode, one question remains: who won the race? It was revealed that Rocky somehow won the race.  

And also, the music in the background of the title of the episode is the same music that is in The Spongebob SquarePants Movie. The song is called, &quot;Now That We're Men&quot;.

*The running gag is that Squidward's family name is mispronounced as &quot;Tennisballs&quot;, &quot;Tentpoles&quot;, and &quot;Tortellini&quot; despite that Squidward repeatedly tells them his name is &quot;Squidward Tentacles&quot;
* There was a deleted scene in which Sandy gets arrested for kicking Spongebob's butt.
{{-}}

'''Mid-Life Crustacean'''
{{Infobox SpongeBob episode
| Title = Mid-Life Crustacean
| Image =  
| Episode = 55b
| Season = 3
| Airdate = January 29, 2003
| Guests =
| Writer = [[C. H. Greenblatt|C.H. Greenblatt]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Kazimieras G. Prapuolenis|Kaz]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Mark O'Hare]]
|}}

Mr. Krabs has hit his [[midlife crisis]], so he decides to tag along with SpongeBob and Patrick when they have a night in the town, hoping that he will feel young and wild again. However, Mr. Krabs quickly finds that SpongeBob and Patrick's idea of a wild night is anything but wild, or even cool They go on a [[panty raid]] to go look for girls underwear only to find out that is Mrs. Krabs house and Mr. Krabs gets grounded for the rest of the night SpongeBob comes back to apologize for what happened and Mr. Krabs forgives him on his race car bed.
{{-}}

===Born Again Krabs / I Had an Accident===
'''Born Again Krabs'''
{{Infobox SpongeBob episode
| Title = Born Again Krabs
| Image =  
| Episode = 56a
| Season = 3
| Airdate = October 4, 2003
| Guests =
| Writer = [[Paul Tibbitt]]&lt;br /&gt;Kent Osborne&lt;br /&gt;[[Merriwether Williams]]
|}}

One night during closing, SpongeBob finds an old, moldy Krabby Patty under the grill. Mr. Krabs forbids him to make another one until the moldy Krabby Patty is sold, causing the restaurant to go for weeks without customers. When the penny-pinching crab takes a bite from the patty, he ends up in the hospital with a potentially fatal case of food poisoning. Mr. Krabs makes a deal with the Flying Dutchman that he can keep his soul if he promises to never be cheap again, a deal he's good at upholding for a while. But when Mr. Krabs loses all of his money, and finds out that the he is awake, he finds the deal too hard to uphold, and becomes cheap again. When the Flying Dutchman arrives, SpongeBob puts himself before Mr. Krabs, hoping that Mr. Krabs will prove himself to be not cheap. But instead, Mr. Krabs carelessly gives him to the Flying Dutchman in exchange for 62 cents. Squidward scolds Mr. Krabs for selling out the only person who stood up for him, and Mr. Krabs begins to regret having sold SpongeBob. The Flying Dutchman returns SpongeBob, but not because of Mr. Krabs' regret for selling SpongeBob, but because SpongeBob being deemed by the Dutchman as &quot;a fate worse than death&quot; because he talked up a storm after just 30 seconds.

When the Flying Dutchman returns to his residence, he answers a call. But it turns out to be from SpongeBob, who again chatters and annoys him.
{{-}}

'''I Had an Accident'''
{{Infobox SpongeBob episode
| Title = I Had an Accident
| Image =  
| Episode = 56b
| Season = 3
| Airdate = October 4, 2003
| Guests =
| Writer = [[C. H. Greenblatt|C.H. Greenblatt]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Kazimieras G. Prapuolenis|Kaz]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Merriwether Williams]]
|}}

SpongeBob shatters his rear end in a sand-boarding injury. In order to avoid the &quot;Iron Butt,&quot; he commits himself to stay indoors for the rest of his life, leaving Sandy and Patrick to try to convince him that the outdoors aren't always so dangerous.

After several attempts to lure Spongebob outside, Sandy and Patrick try to traumatize him by having Patrick dress up in a gorilla suit and threaten Sandy. Spongebob still isn't convinced, knowing Patrick wore the suit the previous Halloween. However, Patrick, not in a gorilla suit, walks onto the scene, greeting Sandy, yet confuses her why there are two Patricks on the scene. Patrick says he is in the gorilla suit, which reveals that the other Patrick is revealed to be an actual gorilla (in actuality, a human in a gorilla suit). Spongebob is finally convinced to leave his house (after the &quot;gorilla&quot; throws Patrick and Sandy into a sack and beats them up), allowing him to come outside to attempt to save Sandy and Patrick. However, SpongeBob is ripped in half by the gorilla, but is still able to express his newfound fear of gorillas, with Sandy and Patrick expressing the same fears. SpongeBob then says out loud, &quot;What's a gorilla doing underwater in the first place?&quot;. The gorilla then says, &quot;Well, you see, it's funny because... GEORGE! THEY'RE ONTO US!&quot; He then hitches a ride on a man in a zebra suit, and they gallop into the sunset.

*Note: Another name for this episode is &quot;Safety Freak SpongeBob&quot;.
*Note: This is the only SpongeBob episode that is revealed, at the end, to have been watched on a TV by a family. They then turn the TV off.
{{-}}

===Krabby Land / The Camping Episode===
'''Krabby Land'''
{{Infobox SpongeBob episode
| Title = Krabby Land
| Image =  
| Episode = 57a
| Season = 3
| Airdate = April 3, 2004
| Guests =
| Writer = [[Paul Tibbitt]]&lt;br /&gt;Kent Osborne&lt;br /&gt;[[Mark O'Hare]]
|}}

It's summer in Bikini Bottom, and that means the kids are out of school. For Mr. Krabs, their temporary freedom means more profit for him (even he raises the price of cheapest Krabby Patty meal, &quot;Kiddie Meal&quot;, into most expensive in menu). To attract them, he sets up a playground consisting of rusty, poorly-constructed, and dangerous equipment, with a promise to the kids that they would get to meet Krabby the Clown before the day's end. However, he soon finds out that the kids probably shouldn't be underestimated. At the end, the kids were having fun and a kid was tossing [[money]], but after Mr. Krabs [[Betrayal|betrayed]] the kids (he promised that Krabby The Clown would be at the Krusty Krab, but after he told them that he was here, he put on a frozen [[tomato]] on his nose and dressed as a clown, children were upset), they tortured him with [[Phaseolus lunatus|lima beans]].
{{-}}

'''The Camping Episode'''
{{Infobox SpongeBob episode
| Title = The Camping Episode
| Image =  
| Episode = 57b
| Season = 3
| Airdate = April 3, 2004
| Guests =
| Writer = [[Jay Lender]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Sam Henderson]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Merriwether Williams]] 
|}}

SpongeBob and Patrick go camping one night, which excites their neighbor Squidward, who hopes that the two will get lost in the woods and never come back. However, Squidward soon learns that SpongeBob and Patrick's chosen campsite was ten feet outside SpongeBob's pineapple. The two get Squidward to join them in camping after Squidward is convinced that SpongeBob and Patrick think that he is weak for not going camping in the first place. But Squidward is forced to endure the camping rituals of SpongeBob and Patrick, such as roasting marshmallows and singing campfire songs, resulting in SpongeBob's musical number &quot;The Campfire Song Song&quot;. In return, Squidward decides to play his clarinet. Spongebob suddenly averts Squidward from playing (after shooting a marshmallow in his throat via his clarinet, nearly choking him in the process) since it is said to attract a &quot;sea-bear.&quot; Squidward doubts them at first, believing sea-bears are hoaxes, but SpongeBob and Patrick present him with a tabloid newspaper front page entitled &quot;Sea Bears and Fairy Tales are Real&quot;. After learning the doings that can attract sea bears, Squidward attempts to prove they are untrue by performing those actions. However, Squidward eventually does attract a sea bear, and gets mauled in the process. While this happens, Spongebob and Patrick are huddled inside a circle drawn on the ground said to deter sea-bears. After being brutally assaulted by the sea-bear multiple times, Squidward squeezes inside the two's safe circle, causing the sea-bear to retreat. However, the episode ends just as Squidward learns about sea rhinoceroses and that the only protection is wearing Anti-Sea-Rhionosares under garments...

*Note: At first the title of this episode was &quot;Squidward Goes Camping&quot;.
*Note: The date in the episode is the 25th of May.

===Missing Identity / Plankton's Army===
'''Missing Identity'''
{{Infobox SpongeBob episode
| Title = Missing Identity
| Image =  
| Episode = 58a
| Season = 3
| Airdate = January 19, 2004
| Guests =
| Writer = [[Paul Tibbitt]]&lt;br /&gt;Kent Osborne&lt;br /&gt;[[Merriwether Williams]]
| Director = Paul Tibbitt&lt;br&gt;Kent Osborne&lt;br&gt;Zeus Cervas&lt;br&gt;Caleb Meurer&lt;br&gt;Carson Kugler&lt;br&gt;William Reiss&lt;br&gt;Tom Yasumi&lt;br&gt;Derek Drymon
|}}
On a rainy day in a diner, SpongeBob recounts a recent tale in which he loses his nametag:

Mr. Krabs is to do a surprise uniform inspection, with the consequence of the least prepared employee getting &quot;the boot&quot; (which is literally, a large stinky boot that must be worn for the rest of the workday). SpongeBob recruits Patrick to help him retrace his steps to find his nametag, but quickly learns that this method isn't perhaps the best one, and that Patrick isn't much help at all. After searching in a dumpster, he finds out he was wearing his shirt backwards, and when he puts his shirt on the right way, he discovers that his nametag was on all along. However, because he was in a dumpster, SpongeBob smells awful, so Mr. Krabs boots him out of the Krusty Krab.

*Note: You may slightly notice the missing nametag in shortcut by witnessing Spongebob's lack of backtracking which he changes his clothes.
{{-}}

'''Plankton's Army'''
{{Infobox SpongeBob episode
| Title = Plankton's Army
| Image =  
| Episode = 58b
| Season = 3
| Airdate = January 19, 2004
| Guests =
| Writer = [[Jay Lender]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Sam Henderson]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Merriwether Williams]]
| Director = Jay Lender&lt;br&gt;Sam Henderson&lt;br&gt;Caleb Meurer&lt;br&gt;Sean Dempsey&lt;br&gt;Derek Drymon
|}}

Mr. Krabs tells his employees that today is the 25th anniversary of Plankton's first attempt at stealing the Krabby Patty's secret formula. Plankton, meanwhile, tries to hire henchmen to help him steal it, but he's too small. He has another idea: he'll hire as many of his relatives as possible to help him steal it. They invade the Krusty Krab, and trap Squidward and Mr. Krabs in a toilet. (SpongeBob was cleaning out the men's room, and that's why he is only seen in the beginning and end of this episode) Plankton does a [[Snare drum|Snare Drum roll]] and reads what seems to be the secret formula, and it says that plankton are part of the recipe. This scares off Plankton and his relatives (except for one of them, who is illiterate and whom Mr. Krabs commands to &quot;Get out of here!&quot;). After the Plankton family flees from the Krusty Krab, Mr. Krabs points out that the recipe that the Planktons read is a fake, says that he's sure Plankton will eventually realize that it's a fake and attempt to go after the real formula, but says he hid the real formula in a place that nobody will ever find. But when Squidward correctly guesses the hiding place (at Mr. Krabs' home, under his [[mattress]]), Mr. Krabs hurriedly attempts to find a new hiding place for the real formula.

*Note: Nickelodeon branded this episode as &quot;Plankton's Revenge&quot;.
{{-}}

===The Sponge Who Could Fly===
'''The Sponge Who Could Fly'''
{{main|The Sponge Who Could Fly}} 
{{Infobox SpongeBob episode
| Title = The Sponge Who Could Fly
| Image =
| Episode = 59
| Season = 3
| Airdate = March 21, 2003
| Guests =
| Writer = [[Paul Tibbitt]]&lt;br /&gt;Kent Osborne&lt;br /&gt;[[Merriwether Williams]]
| Director = Derek Drymon&lt;br&gt;Carson Kugler&lt;br&gt;Caleb Meurer&lt;br&gt;Mark O'Hare&lt;br&gt;Kent Osborne&lt;br&gt;[[Mark Osborne (filmmaker)|Mark Osborne]]&lt;br&gt;Andrew Overtoom&lt;br&gt;William Reiss&lt;br&gt;Paul Tibbitt&lt;br&gt;Tom Yasumi
|}}
In the live action section, Patchy intends on presenting a lost episode of SpongeBob SquarePants; however, he has lost it. He then uses a treasure map to find it which leads him to a playground where a video tape is buried. When Patchy starts the video it initially only shows SpongeBob walk cycles which upsets Patchy that he starts getting rid of all his SpongeBob merchandise and runs away. However, Potty informs the tape is still on because the real episode is playing next. Happy again, Patchy returns home and replaces all his stuff.

The animated section begins and SpongeBob wishes he could fly with the jellyfish. He constructs several flying machines, all of which fail to fly for very long. In his attempts, he uses a biplane, bat wings, a garden chair with balloons, and a giant kite pulled by a bicycle driven by Patrick. After attempting to fly but failing, he is called &quot;The Birdman of Bikini Bottom&quot; and is ridiculed. Depressed, he finally finds out a way to fly: inflatable pants. Now that he can fly, though, the other citizens of Bikini Bottom take advantage of him, and when he finally refuses he is left alone in jellyfish fields with his pants taken away. SpongeBob decides that flying is not for him. But the jellyfish take him flying across the sky to cheer him up. When they drop him off at his home, Patrick asks him if he wants to &quot;fly&quot; over to a pizza joint, to which he declines to. Patrick just replies, &quot;suit yourself&quot; and literally flies off, leaving SpongeBob in absolute shock.

After the episode, in another live action section, Patchy decides to play it again. Not knowing a thing about technology, he accidentally wrecks the tape so it   can't be seen again. outside, the narrator talks about Patchy's day and then you can see a Spongebob constellation.

*Note: Nickelodeon promoted this episode as &quot;SpongeBob: The Lost Episode&quot;
{{-}}

===SpongeBob Meets the Strangler / Pranks a Lot===
'''SpongeBob Meets the Strangler'''
{{Infobox SpongeBob episode
| Title = SpongeBob Meets the Strangler
| Image = 
| Episode = 60a
| Season = 3
| Airdate = October 11, 2004
| Guests =
| Writer = [[Paul Tibbitt]]&lt;br /&gt;Kent Osborne&lt;br /&gt;[[C. H. Greenblatt|C.H. Greenblatt]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Merriwether Williams]]
| Director = Paul Tibbitt&lt;br&gt;Kent Osborne&lt;br&gt;Zeus Cervas&lt;br&gt;Chuck Klein&lt;br&gt;Mike Roth&lt;br&gt;C.H. Greenblatt&lt;br&gt;Tom Yasumi&lt;br&gt;Derek Drymon
|}}

SpongeBob tattles on the &quot;Tattle-tale Strangler&quot;, a criminal who promises to strangle anyone who reports on him and his crimes. He escapes the police's clutches and wants to go after SpongeBob for tattling on him. SpongeBob wants a bodyguard to help protect him from the Tattle-tale Strangler. He asks a lot of people, but they are all too scared of the Tattle-tale Strangler. Then just when he was going to leave town, someone claims to be offering help. The man is the Tattle-tale Strangler wearing a fake mustache. SpongeBob doesn't know this though, and allows him to become his bodyguard. The strangler is trying to get him alone so he can strangle him without getting caught. But every time he tries to strangle him, SpongeBob is either talking to him, doing something, or he is with another person(s). 

After a while, the strangler gives up and tries to run away from SpongeBob. He ends up confessing and staying in jail. He is glad that he is away from the &quot;yellow idiot&quot; (SpongeBob), but is then surprised to see Patrick (who turned himself in because of a lie that the Tattle-tale Strangler told to the extremely gullible starfish, making him think he is the Tattle-tale Strangler) as a cell-mate. Patrick says to the Tattle-tale Strangler, &quot;Hey Mac. What are you in for?&quot;.
*One Time appearance: The Strangler
{{-}}

'''Pranks a Lot'''
{{Infobox SpongeBob episode
| Title = Pranks a Lot
| Image =  
| Episode = 60b
| Season = 3
| Airdate = October 11, 2004
| Guests =
| Writer = [[Paul Tibbitt]]&lt;br /&gt;Kent Osborne&lt;br /&gt;[[Merriwether Williams]]
|}}

In the original series finale, SpongeBob goes to the &quot;Palace of Pranks&quot; with Patrick and says he got his Gag Seanut Brittle Can (a spoof of [[Brittle (food)|peanut brittle]]) from there saying it's a gag. Patrick assumes that there is really Brittle inside and opens it only to discover it was a prank.

They go inside and purchase &quot;Invisible Paint&quot;, a can of spray-paint that can turn things invisible. SpongeBob and Patrick intend to use it to spray a park bench, and then sit on it, making it look like they are floating (and so the people around them will be amazed by this as a result). Remembering a warning that the paint stains clothes, the two completely strip down to their birthday suits, then fight over who should spray the bench, leading them to spray each other until they're completely invisible, and also end up accidentally spraying it onto their clothes. So, SpongeBob and Patrick decide to go around tricking people into thinking they're ghosts. At first, it works, as they scare everyone in town, including Mr. Krabs, who initially claimed that he couldn't be scared. But Mr. Krabs eventually finds out (by throwing water at them, as he was trying to put out a lit match that they were going to use to burn a dollar bill as part of their plan of torturing him), and gets back at SpongeBob and Patrick when he makes a show called &quot;Live Nude Pranksters&quot;, which show SpongeBob and Patrick's nudity to the customers of the Krusty Krab. SpongeBob, ashamed, concludes the episode be saying to Patrick that they should have bought a whoopie cushion.
{{-}}

==''The SpongeBob SquarePants Movie''==
'''The SpongeBob SquarePants Movie'''
{{main|The SpongeBob SquarePants Movie}} 
{{Infobox SpongeBob episode
| Title = The SpongeBob SquarePants Movie
| Image = 
| Episode = 
| Season = 3
| Airdate = November 19, 2004
| UK Airdate = May 25, 2008
| Latin Airdate = July 3, 2009
| Guests = [[Alec Baldwin]] (Dennis) &lt;br /&gt;[[Jeffrey Tambor]] (King Neptune) &lt;br /&gt;[[Scarlett Johansson]] (Princess Mindy) &lt;br /&gt;[[Carlos Alazraqui]] (King Neptune's squire) &lt;br /&gt;[[Neil Ross]] (Cyclops) &lt;br /&gt;[[David Hasselhoff]] (David Hasselhoff) 
| Writer = [[Stephen Hillenburg]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Derek Drymon]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Tim Hill]]&lt;br /&gt;Kent Osborne&lt;br /&gt;[[Aaron Springer]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Paul Tibbitt]] 
| Director = Stephen Hillenburg&lt;br /&gt;[[Mark Osborne (filmmaker)|Mark Osborne]]
|}}
 
Squidward becomes manager of the Krusty Krab 2, leaving SpongeBob depressed as he feels that he should have been chosen instead. Plankton steals King Neptune's crown, sells it to a person in Shell City, and frames Mr. Krabs. King Neptune freezes Mr. Krabs until SpongeBob and Patrick come back with his crown in 6 days (thanks to Patrick). Meanwhile, Plankton controls Bikini Bottom, now Planktopolis. SpongeBob and Patrick face many obstacles including two motormouths, thugs, monsters, an abyss, Dennis (a person sent by Plankton to destroy SpongeBob and Patrick), a diver, a heat lamp, and Plankton's minions. In the end, SpongeBob becomes the manager of the Krusty Krab 2.
{{-}}

== References ==
{{reflist}}

{{SpongeBob SquarePants}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Spongebob Squarepants (Season 3)}}
[[Category:2001 television seasons]]
[[Category:2002 television seasons]]
[[Category:2003 television seasons]]
[[Category:2004 television seasons]]
[[Category:SpongeBob SquarePants]]

[[id:SpongeBob SquarePants (musim ke-3)]]
[[it:Spongebob stagione 3]]
[[nl:Lijst van afleveringen van SpongeBob SquarePants (seizoen 3)]]
[[ru:Третий сезон мультсериала «Губка Боб Квадратные Штаны»]]
[[tr:SpongeBob SquarePants (season 3)]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
