<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="14192171" ns="0" title="SpongeBob SquarePants (season 2)"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{wikify|reason=Episodes are not in proper format|date=September 2011}}
{{infobox tvseason |
  | season_name = SpongeBob SquarePants''&lt;br /&gt;Season 2
  | bgcolour = #E3701A
  | fgcolour = #FFF
  | show_name = ''[[SpongeBob SquarePants]]''
  | image = [[Image:SBSPseason2.jpg|200px]]
  | caption = ''SpongeBob SquarePants'', Season 2 
  | dvd_release_date = Region 1: October 19, 2004&lt;br /&gt;Region 2: October 23, 2006&lt;br /&gt;Region 4: November 30, 2006
  | dvd_format = Boxset
  | country = [[United States|USA]]
  | network = [[Nickelodeon (TV channel)|Nickelodeon]]
  | first_aired = October 26, 2000
  | last_aired = July 26, 2003
  | prev_season = [[SpongeBob SquarePants (season 1)|Season 1]]
  | next_season = [[SpongeBob SquarePants (season 3)|Season 3]]
|}}

'''Season Two''' of the animated television comedy, ''[[SpongeBob SquarePants]]'' on Nickelodeon aired twenty episodes from October 26, 2000, with the episodes &quot;[[SpongeBob SquarePants (season 2)#Something Smells / Bossy Boots|Something Smells]]&quot; and &quot;[[SpongeBob SquarePants (season 2)#Something Smells / Bossy Boots|Bossy Boots]]&quot;, to July 26, 2003 with &quot;[[Gary Takes a Bath]]&quot; officially ending season 2. The DVD for the season was released in Regions 1, 2, and 4 on October 19, 2004, October 23, 2006, and November 30, 2006, respectively.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.tv.com/SpongeBob-SquarePants/show/3428/episode_listings.html?season=2&amp;tag=nav_bar;2 |title=SpongeBob SquarePants episode list, season two |accessdate=2008-01-19 |work=TV.com }}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Season 2 (2000 - 2003)===
==Episodes==
===Your Shoe's Untied / Squid's Day Off===
'''Your Shoe's Untied'''
{{Infobox SpongeBob episode
| Title = Your Shoe's Untied
| [[shoeuntied.JPG]]

Similar ‑ More sizes ‑ 
| Episode = 21a
| Season = 2
| Airdate = November 2, 2000
| Guests = [[Ween]] (musical performance)
| Writer = [[Walt Dohrn]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Paul Tibbitt]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Merriwether Williams]]
|}}

[[Patrick Star|Patrick]] purchases shoes and asks [[SpongeBob SquarePants (character)|SpongeBob]] to help him tie them. SpongeBob realizes that he forgot how to tie his shoes, because his shoes have been tied as long as he can remember. Patrick is less than impressed. SpongeBob goes to sleep, hoping that he’ll remember how to tie his shoes. The next morning, he tries to go to work, but his shoes are still untied. Because of that, SpongeBob falls down repeatedly on his way to work. Much to his dismay, Patrick is at the [[Krusty Krab]]. In order to avoid Patrick from knowing that he really did forget how to tie his shoes, SpongeBob slams his feet through the wood floor. He hopes that he can feel safe in the kitchen if he stands in the same spot all day, but [[Squidward Tentacles|Squidward]] immediately needs SpongeBob to bring him a customer's order. SpongeBob trips over his laces and accidentally flings the Krabby Patties into Squidward’s mouth, in which he eats them all. SpongeBob then breaks down and cries in the kitchen, and the customers complain and leave. [[Mr. Krabs]] tries to convince them not to leave, but his pants fall down due to the fact that he was in the restroom. SpongeBob then has to admit that he forgot how to tie his shoes.

SpongeBob tries to find someone to help him tie his shoes. However, nobody he asks actually wears shoes. The ghostly [[Pearl Krabs (character)|Flying Dutchman]] then appears to help SpongeBob tie a knot. The Dutchman knows how to tie many different kinds of knots, but he proclaims he cannot tie shoes since he hasn’t worn them in 5,000 years. He then disappears, and SpongeBob crawls back to his house. He is met by his pet [[Gary (SpongeBob SquarePants)|Gary]], who surprisingly knows how to tie shoes since he wears shoes beneath his shell. Gary then turns on a record that plays a song about tying shoes. SpongeBob then learns how to tie his own shoes.

*Trivia: This is the first SpongeBob episode to use digital ink and paint.
{{-}}

'''Squid's Day Off'''
{{Infobox SpongeBob episode
| Title = Squid's Day Off
| Image =  
| Episode = 21b
| Season = 2
| Airdate = November 2, 2000
| Guests = 
| Writer = [[Walt Dohrn]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Paul Tibbitt]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Merriwether Williams]]
|}}

Squidward is angered by having to work on a Sunday at the Krusty Krab, when there are no customers. He drops money on the ground, which alerts Mr. Krabs, who rushes to the money's &quot;rescue&quot;. He takes it to the sink to be washed, but he accidentally drops a dime down the drain. He tries to reach in and grab it, but his  claw becomes stuck in the drain. Rather than letting go of the dime, he tries to pull his arm out with SpongeBob’s help. However, both of his arms fall off in the struggle, and accidentally has various objects fall on his head, and he is taken to the hospital — leaving Squidward in charge. Immediately after Mr. Krabs leaves, Squidward &quot;promotes&quot; SpongeBob to cashier, meaning SpongeBob has to take orders at the cash register ''and'' cook the food. Squidward says he has to run some &quot;managerial errands&quot;, but this is just a ploy to allow him to leave.

Squidward then goes home to enjoy the day. However, Squidward is immediately concerned, because he thinks SpongeBob is going to single-handedly destroy the Krusty Krab by either accidentally giving away all the money or by setting the place on fire. Squidward tries to relax, but he keeps having visions of SpongeBob destroying the Krusty Krab. Because of this, Squidward repeatedly runs back and forth from his house to the Krusty Krab to check on SpongeBob, who has been standing at the register the whole time doing nothing. Squidward is unable to relax and keeps running back and forth over and over again — assuring himself that SpongeBob will mess up something. To prevent himself from going to the Krusty Krab again, he bolts his front door shut and takes a bath. All the while, he is slowly going insane over the safety of the Krusty Krab.

He imagines that SpongeBob is spying on him to see if he really is doing errands, even imaging that SpongeBob is in the bathtub with him. He thinks that SpongeBob caught him, and he rushes back to the Krusty Krab without any clothes on before SpongeBob can tell Mr. Krabs. He bursts through the doors of the Krusty Krab to find SpongeBob standing there. After scolding SpongeBob for apparently appearing outside of his house and in his bathtub, he realizes that he’s gone crazy and turns back to normal. He tells SpongeBob that he’s done with his &quot;errands&quot; and wants to go back to his cashier duties. Then, SpongeBob realizes that they forgot to change the &quot;Closed&quot; sign to &quot;Open&quot;, and says they could have had the whole day off.
{{-}}

===Something Smells / Bossy Boots===
'''Something Smells'''
{{Infobox SpongeBob episode
| Title = Something Smells
| Image =  
| Episode = 22a
| Season = 2
| Airdate = October 26, 2000
| Guests = 
| Writer = [[Aaron Springer]]&lt;br /&gt;[[C. H. Greenblatt|C.H. Greenblatt]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Merriwether Williams]]
|}}

SpongeBob wants to make an ice cream [[sundae]], but he doesn’t have any of the needed ingredients. So, he creates a &quot;sundae&quot; with leftover ingredients such as [[ketchup]] and [[onion]]s. This produces a very foul-smelling &quot;sundae&quot;, but SpongeBob eats it anyway. This gives SpongeBob [[halitosis|terrible-smelling breath]]. Gary the Snail is the first to notice SpongeBob’s foul breath. Being SpongeBob’s day off on Sunday, his agenda is to go say &quot;Hi&quot; to everyone in Bikini Bottom, but he is unaware that he has bad breath. Every person he comes across on the street is immediately repulsed by SpongeBob’s breath, and SpongeBob doesn’t realize why everyone is running away from him.

He comes across Patrick on a park bench and tells him that everyone in [[Bikini Bottom Jail|Bikini Bottom]] is acting weird. However, Patrick is unaware of SpongeBob’s bad breath because he doesn't have a nose. Patrick says that everyone is running away from SpongeBob because he’s ugly. SpongeBob is devastated by his &quot;ugliness&quot;, but Patrick convinces him to be confident with his appearance. After boosting SpongeBob’s confidence, they decide to go to the local [[movie theater]] and watch a movie. When they go to sit down in their seats, SpongeBob asks those sitting next to him not to be distracted by his ugliness, but the people run away because of his foul breath. SpongeBob then becomes very sad. Angered that no one has the nerve to face SpongeBob's &quot;ugliness&quot;, Patrick flies into a rage and forces everyone to look at SpongeBob, and everyone in the room (except for Patrick and SpongeBob), leave the room and the theater as a whole, though this was really because they couldn't tolerate his breath. They then decide to go to the snack bar, but the clerk has run away. SpongeBob remembers that he still had some of his &quot;sundae&quot; in his pocket, and Patrick eats it. He immediately has to run to the restroom with an upset stomach, where the people in the restroom are repulsed by Patrick’s newly acquired bad breath, so they leave the restroom and the theater. Unaware of the real reason, Patrick thinks he got &quot;the ugly&quot; from SpongeBob. SpongeBob finds Patrick crying in the restroom, and he is quick to notice Patrick’s bad breath. After the two realize that everyone they encountered ran way not because of their &quot;ugliness&quot;, but because of their terrible breath, SpongeBob and Patrick express to each other how they are fine with having bad breath. They destroy the theater and run around Bikini Bottom with glee.
{{-}}
* Note: In this episode Patrick says he doesn't have a sister but in season seven there is an episode where his sister Sam visits him.

'''Bossy Boots'''
{{Infobox SpongeBob episode
| Title = Bossy Boots
| Image =  
| Episode = 22b
| Season = 2
| Airdate = October 26, 2000
| Guests = 
| Writer = [[Walt Dohrn]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Paul Tibbitt]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Doug Lawrence|Mr. Lawrence]]
|}}

Mr. Krabs’ daughter, [[Pearl Krabs|Pearl]], comes to work at the Krusty Krab during her summer vacation, and she has many ideas for improving the restaurant — all to the delight of Mr. Krabs. The first change she has is to change the name of the Krusty Krab to the Kuddly Krab, but not before several name suggestions by SpongeBob and Pearl, and transform it into a teen-oriented restaurant. SpongeBob and Mr. Krabs are excited by these changes, but Squidward is not, especially after Pearl introduces their new pink uniforms. Squidward then quits after being mistaken for a [[female]] and tore off his uniform. Unfortunately, he got a [[ticket]] for being [[naked]] in public.  At first, SpongeBob is all for the changes until he realizes that the Krabby Patty was removed from the menu in favor of only salads and tea. Pearl even gets rid of the grill, and forces him to dress up in an embarrassing crab costume.

Upset, SpongeBob confronts Mr. Krabs and tells him that Pearl is ruining the Krusty Krab. Mr. Krabs tells SpongeBob that she’s really saving the restaurant until he realizes that these new changes have cost him too much. He then agrees with SpongeBob and decides Pearl needs to be [[Dismissal (employment)|fired]], but Mr. Krabs doesn’t want to have to fire his own daughter. He tells SpongeBob that he should fire Pearl instead, and he reluctantly agrees. When SpongeBob pulls Pearl off to the side, Pearl admits that she was intentionally trying to be fired since her job is cutting into her life. It works out for both of them, as SpongeBob fires Pearl with Mr. Krabs listening in the other room. Mr. Krabs is upset by seeing Pearl fired, but he quickly cheers up when SpongeBob brings a dollar to him and says that Pearl's life is fine. Pearl leaves the restaurant and jumps into a car with a bunch of her friends to go to the mall. After that, Mr. Krabs gets his money back by selling all the decorations and things Pearl has bought to SpongeBob for a year's salary.

*Note: This episode is a flashback as Mr. Krabs introduces Pearl.
{{-}}

===Big Pink Loser / Bubble Buddy===
'''Big Pink Loser'''
{{Infobox SpongeBob episode
| Title = Big Pink Loser
| Image =  
| Episode = 23a
| Season = 2
| Airdate = November 16, 2000
| Guests = 
| Writer = [[Jay Lender]]&lt;br /&gt;William Reiss&lt;br /&gt;[[Merriwether Williams]]
|}}

A [[trophy]] arrives in the mail at Patrick’s house, and he is overjoyed to receive a trophy. He rushes over to SpongeBob’s house to show him his new trophy, but SpongeBob alerts him to the fact that the trophy has his name on it and that it was accidentally delivered to Patrick. Patrick is distraught that he has no trophies, especially after he opens SpongeBob’s closet and a mountain of trophies comes out. SpongeBob tells him that he must earn a trophy, and the easiest way to do that would be to get a job at the Krusty Krab. Patrick gets a job there, but he is unable to perform even the basic essentials of the job, such as serving food, answering the phone, and sweeping the floor. All the while, Patrick keeps asking if he’s earned a trophy. He gets angrier when a delivery man brings a stack of trophies for SpongeBob. SpongeBob takes Patrick back into the kitchen and gives him a simple job of opening jars, but even this is hard for Patrick. Patrick finally opens the jar and thinks he broke it, but SpongeBob is excited that Patrick opened the jar, and tells him that he has succeeded. Patrick becomes very happy.

After SpongeBob tells Patrick, &quot;If you do exactly what I do then you'll have an award in no time&quot;, Patrick then takes this to mean that if he wants to get as many trophies as SpongeBob, he must copy his every move, including dressing and acting just like him. This angers SpongeBob, and in retaliation, he decides to act like Patrick. While they are arguing with each other outside their houses, a truck drops off a trophy for Patrick — a trophy for doing absolutely nothing longer than anybody else. Patrick is jubilant and goes back inside his house to defend his title by doing nothing.
{{-}}

'''Bubble Buddy'''
{{Infobox SpongeBob episode
| Title = Bubble Buddy
| Image =  
| Episode = 23b
| Season = 2
| Airdate = November 16, 2000
| Guests = 
| Writer = [[Jay Lender]]&lt;br /&gt;William Reiss&lt;br /&gt;[[Mr. Lawrence]]
|}}

On [[Leif Erikson Day]] SpongeBob wants to celebrate it with somebody, but Patrick and Sandy are gone, Patrick writes &quot;Went to go buy more giant paper...Happy Leif Erikson Day&quot; which is posted on his home, and Squidward (as usual) just doesn't want to do anything with SpongeBob (yet this time, SpongeBob accepts Squidward's orders to stay away). Feeling lonely, SpongeBob creates his own friend, Bubble Buddy, which he creates by blowing a bubble in the shape of a person. The duo ventures to the Krusty Krab, where SpongeBob introduces Bubble Buddy to the unenthusiastic Squidward. Mr. Krabs gets excited when SpongeBob orders one of everything on the menu for Bubble Buddy, but Squidward is annoyed by having to serve him, especially when SpongeBob says that Bubble Buddy needs a tremendous amount of accommodations. They leave, and Squidward informs Mr. Krabs that Bubble Buddy paid for all the food with &quot;bubble money&quot;, which pops in Squidward’s hand, much to their anger.

The duo then goes to Goo Lagoon, where Bubble Buddy stales the other swimmers by taking two hours in the only bathroom. They then begin unknowingly angering all the other beachgoers, including Pearl and Larry the Lobster. Squidward and Mr. Krabs catch up with Bubble Buddy on the beach, where they organize a mob consisting of other angered citizens, with the intent of popping Bubble Buddy. SpongeBob protests that they shouldn’t pop his friend, but the crowd throws SpongeBob off the screen. Squidward proceeds to stab the bubble with a sewing pin. However, Bubble Buddy comes to life at the last second and stops Squidward from doing so. Bubble Buddy says that things are getting too weird for him, and he catches a &quot;bubble [[taxicab|taxi]]&quot;. Though surprised, the beachgoers quickly accept this and leave.
{{-}}

* This is the first appearance of Bubble Buddy, but he made a much larger roll in &quot;Battle for Bikini Bottom&quot; where he gave Spongebob tasks and introduced new bubble techniques for Spongebob.

* A sequel Bubble Buddy Returns will air November 25, 2011, 11 years after this episode.

===Dying for Pie / Imitation Krabs===
''' Dying for Pie'''
{{Infobox SpongeBob episode
| Title = Dying for Pie
| Image =  
| Episode = 24a
| Season = 2
| Airdate = December 28, 2000| Guests = [[Dee Bradley Baker]] as the Pirate Captain
| Writer = [[Aaron Springer]]&lt;br /&gt;[[C. H. Greenblatt|C.H. Greenblatt]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Merriwether Williams]]
|}}

Mr. Krabs decides to hold an &quot;Employee Brotherhood Day&quot;, in which employees must exchange homemade gifts. SpongeBob’s gift to Squidward is an extremely itchy, homemade sweater made of his own [[eyelash]]es. Squidward, who isn't interested in exchanging gifts with SpongeBob, throws the sweater back at the heartbroken SpongeBob, making him sad. SpongeBob then presents Squidward with a sweater that he just made out of his own [[tears]], and under pressure from Mr. Krabs, Squidward agrees to make a gift for SpongeBob. He goes back into the kitchen, but he has no idea what to make. He then looks out the window and sees a group of [[piracy|pirates]] trying to load their [[treasure|booty]] — a giant bag filled with explosive pies — onto their ship. He goes up to the pirates and asks if he can purchase a homemade pie, though one of the pirates tells him that the pies are actually pie-shaped bombs made in a factory. When Squidward waves money and says he wants to actually buy ''pies'', the ship's captain (voiced by [[Dee Bradley Baker]]) says that they really are pies and are not explosives and charges him $25.

Squidward takes the seemingly ordinary pie into Mr. Krabs' office to show him that he really did make SpongeBob something. Mr. Krabs wants to taste a small portion of the pie, and he carries it over to a table to get some milk. However, he trips in the process, and the small piece of pie explodes, blowing a hole in the wall and sending Squidward and Mr. Krabs flying out of the Krusty Krab. The two are shocked when they realize that the pie really is explosive, and that the rest of it is still sitting inside the Krusty Krab. They scramble back into the building to find the pie gone and SpongeBob licking his fingers. They presume that SpongeBob ate the bomb/pie, and Mr. Krabs scolds Squidward for giving SpongeBob a disguised bomb. Mr. Krabs informs Squidward that there is nothing they can do, and that SpongeBob will probably explode by sundown. Squidward then feels remorseful and wants to make SpongeBob’s last day eventful by spending time with him to do fun things. Unfortunately for Squidward, SpongeBob already has a large list of things that Squidward feels obligated to do, which includes wearing SpongeBob as a face, babbling like an idiot, dressing in a salmon costume, and even [[Cardiac surgery|open-heart surgery]]. The last thing on the list is for the two of them to watch the [[sunset]] together, and Squidward is extremely nervous since he thinks SpongeBob will explode at any moment. When the sun sets, SpongeBob does not blow up, and he reveals that he did not eat the pie and was saving it for the two of them to eat. Squidward becomes angry that he wasted the whole day with SpongeBob doing strange things due to his wrongful assumptions that his death was imminent. SpongeBob then trips, accidentally throwing the pie at Squidward’s face, and it explodes, destroying the city
except Spongebob. Squidward moans in pain.

*The video that plays that shows the explosion that destroys Bikini Bottom is, in the real world, actual video footage of the [[:Image:Crossroads baker explosion.jpg|''Baker'' explosion]] from the [[Operation Crossroads]] nuclear test. It is seen again in a later episode, &quot;The Krusty Plate&quot;.

*This episode was pulled by [[Nickelodeon (TV channel)|Nickelodeon]] from broadcast after [[September 11 attacks|9/11]] due to its depiction of bombs, and the end where Bikini Bottom blows up (although it did air a few times later). The same goes with syndication, as it has never been aired on Nicktoons Network. It is also absent from the Second Season DVD &amp; VHS Release, and is available online at Nick.com, and it is therefore not available anywhere.

*This is the first Spongebob episode to depict [[blood]] when [[Spongebob (character)|Spongebob SquarePants]] pokes at Squidward's heart; the second is Spongebob vs: The Big One when [[Mr. Krabs (character)|Mr. Krabs]] splashes into The Devil's Galley.

{{-}} 

'''Imitation Krabs'''
{{Infobox SpongeBob episode
| Title = Imitation Krabs
| Image =  
| Episode = 24b
| Season = 2
| Airdate = December 28, 2000
| Guests = 
| Writer = [[Walt Dohrn]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Paul Tibbitt]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Doug Lawrence|Mr. Lawrence]]
|}}

After another failed attempt to steal the Krabby Patty secret formula, Plankton builds and pilots a robotic Mr. Krabs to fool SpongeBob and steal the Krabby Patty secret formula. But first he has to get rid of the ''real'' Mr. Krabs because Mr. Krabs is always coming in-and-out to see what's going on with SpongeBob, so he throws out a penny and Mr. Krabs begins to chase it far away. His plan almost succeeds, but in order to convince SpongeBob to give him the secret formula, he has to accomplish the secret salute (which is extremely difficult and lengthy). When Plankton is about to get the formula, the ''real'' Mr. Krabs comes back and they both argue about who is the real Mr. Krabs. So, SpongeBob gives them a couple of questions in order to find out who is the real one, but the real Mr. Krabs has forgotten, and the robot succeeds, and the real Mr. Krabs is thrown out. SpongeBob gives the fake Mr. Krabs the formula, but SpongeBob picks up a penny and puts it into the self-destruction coin slot on the stomach of the robot. Plankton runs back to the Chum Bucket, and then it explodes. SpongeBob realizes his mistake, so he takes the real Mr. Krabs back to the Krusty Krab and apologizes. 
{{-}}

===Wormy / Patty Hype===
'''Wormy'''
{{Infobox SpongeBob episode
| Title = Wormy
| Image =  
| Episode = 25a
| Season = 2
| Airdate = February 17, 2001
| Guests = 
| Writer = [[Walt Dohrn]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Paul Tibbitt]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Merriwether Williams]]
|}}

Sandy is going on vacation for a few days and has Patrick and SpongeBob take care of her many pets. However, SpongeBob and Patrick find Sandy's caterpillar, Wormy, adorable and decide to play with it. Overnight, Wormy turns into a butterfly. The next day, SpongeBob and Patrick come to Sandy's treedome and try to find Wormy. Later, they find the butterfly, and think the butterfly is a monster that has eaten Wormy. Spongebob and Patrick are terrified that the &quot;monster&quot; is going to eat them, so they trap it in a bubble. The butterfly then flies to the Krusty Krab, and Spongebob &quot;saves&quot; Mr.Krabs and Squidward. They try to convince Spongebob and Patrick that it is not harmful, but when Mr.Krabs and Squidward become scared of it, they run out the door. Spongebob thinks the butterfly has eaten them as well. Spongebob and Patrick alert the town, which turns Bikini Bottom into a path of destruction. Sandy returns, and puts her pet in a jar, and the town citizens praise her.

*Note: There is a continuity error in this episode; SpongeBob actually has seen a butterfly before. In [[Your Shoe's Untied]], which aired three months prior to this episode, [[Pearl Krabs (character)|the Flying Dutchman]] shows SpongeBob a butterfly and he finds it adorable. In his fear that the butterfly ate Wormy, he might have forgotten how he much liked them.

*One Time appearance: Wormy the [[Monarch (butterfly)|Monarch Butterfly]]
*Note: Wormy is mentioned in BFBB in Sandy's Treedome where he calls ''Here Wormy''.
{{-}} 

'''Patty Hype'''
{{Infobox SpongeBob episode
| Title = Patty Hype
| Image =  
| Episode = 25b
| Season = 2
| Airdate = February 17, 2001
| Guests = 
| Writer = [[Jay Lender]]&lt;br /&gt;William Reiss&lt;br /&gt;[[Doug Lawrence|Mr. Lawrence]]
|}}

The Krusty Krab mysteriously hasn't had a customer for thirty-six days. Though served by the same staff, the abandoned condition of the restaurant even turns away a starving fish. Mr. Krabs steps outside to find out that most of his usual customers now eat at the Shell Shack, which even has a singing dog. Thought Mr. Krabs successfully pulls people into his restaurant, all his customers are called back to the Shell Shack. Mr. Krabs is now desperate for an idea. SpongeBob’s idea is that they should sell “Pretty Patties” — colorfully painted versions of the Krabby Patty. Mr. Krabs and Squidward find the idea of Pretty Patties hysterical, and begin mocking SpongeBob and creating stupid ideas of their own such as Sequin Milkshakes and Bowtie French Fries. Angered, SpongeBob storms out of the Krusty Krab and declares opening his own restaurant. 

Assisted by Patrick, Spongebob sets up a roadside stand in front of his house to sell Pretty Patties. After hours without a single customer, Spongebob is ready to give up, but a pedestrian expresses interest in his stand. At first, the man is highly amused by Spongebob's product pitch, a green-colored Pretty Patty, until Spongebob desperately presents the whole spectrum of burgers. The man is overjoyed when he finds his favorite color, purple, on Spongebob's tray and immediately declares the idea a success. In a matter of just a few minutes, SpongeBob and Patrick have thousands of customers, as people are mesmerized by the colorful patties, which now seem to come in all colors and color patterns (including [[Tartan|plaid]]). Their roadside stand draws in many customers, and Mr. Krabs — whose restaurant lies in a worse condition than before — sees them on the news giving away their money, not knowing what to do with it. Shocked, he rushes to see SpongeBob. He gives SpongeBob the key to the Krusty Krab in exchange for the Pretty Patties stand. The ultimate dream of SpongeBob, he takes the keys as the new owner of the Krusty Krab. Mr. Krabs then starts selling Pretty Patties.

The next day, however, the customers storm at Mr. Krabs and demand a refund. The Pretty Patties apparently caused those who ate them to change to the color of the patties they ate — including one guy whose tongue glowed in the dark. Mr. Krabs is then chased by the mob of angry costumers. When he runs back to the Krusty Krab, he finds himself locked out. SpongeBob is rubbing two pickles together resulting in a squeaky noise, preventing him from hearing Mr. Krabs' pleas for help.

*Note: In following episodes, Mr. Krabs tries to save patties no matter what condition they are in.
{{-}}

===Grandma's Kisses / Squidville===
'''Grandma's Kisses'''
{{Infobox SpongeBob episode
| Title = Grandma's Kisses
| Image =  
| Episode = 26a
| Season = 2
| Airdate = March 6, 2001
| Guests = [[Marion Ross]] as Grandma SquarePants
| Writer = [[Walt Dohrn]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Paul Tibbitt]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Merriwether Williams]]
|}}

SpongeBob loves going to his Grandma's house but feels embarrassed after he gets a kiss mark on his forehead and Squidward and everyone else makes fun of him. The next time SpongeBob goes to Grandma's house, he and Patrick try to show her that they are grown, mature men. However, after Patrick refuses to be mature after getting cookies and kisses from SpongeBob's Grandma, SpongeBob grows jealous. While walking toward the door, SpongeBob cries back to Grandma's house into a river of tears and tells her that he doesn't want to grow up and wants to be a baby again and do all the stuff that he had done with Grandma as a baby. But Grandma tells SpongeBob that he doesn't have to be a baby to get her love, and she gives him a cookie and then a hug. However Squidward, and the people at the Krusty Krab earlier manage to follow SpongeBob to Grandma's house and are watching Grandma hug SpongeBob and start laughing again.

* First appearance: [[Flatts|Grandma SquarePants]]
{{-}}

'''Squidville'''
{{Infobox SpongeBob episode
| Title = Squidville
| Image =  
| Episode = 26b
| Airdate = March 6, 2001
| Guests = [[Dee Bradley Baker]] (as one of the Tentacle Acres guards)
| Writer = [[Aaron Springer]]&lt;br /&gt;[[C. H. Greenblatt|C.H. Greenblatt]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Merriwether Williams]]
|}}

SpongeBob and Patrick are excited to get their new &quot;[[leaf blower|reef blowers]]&quot; in the mail, and they immediately go on a spree of destruction, which culminates in Squidward’s house getting reduced to rubble. Squidward is finally fed up with their antics and plans to move far away. While watching a television set from the debris of his own house, he sees a commercial for Tentacle Acres — a [[gated community]] exclusively for his own kind. Squidward moves into the community and is overjoyed at being far away from SpongeBob and Patrick, who begin to try to apologize and find Squidward to bring him back home.

In his new life, Squidward begins a daily routine of riding his bike, buying canned bread, dancing at an [[interpretive dance]] academy, and playing in a [[clarinet]] trio. He proclaims the town to be perfect. Of course, every other person in the community looks and acts like Squidward and follows the same daily routine. A few days later, Squidward becomes bored with his daily routine and searches for a little fun. Another person, who was cleaning a public park with a reef blower, leaves his blower behind to go on a break. Squidward is reminded of SpongeBob and Patrick’s antics and begins to play with the reef blower. He starts causing trouble in the park, and the other people look down on his childish behavior. In spite of the others, he goes on a rampage by sucking up and blowing everything.

Meanwhile, SpongeBob and Patrick find the gated community, but their entry is denied by the security guards, because their &quot;kind isn't allowed [there]&quot;. However, Patrick had just eaten some fried oyster skins, and the repugnant odor travels through the intercom and causes the guards to pass out and accidentally hit the button to open the gate. SpongeBob and Patrick try to find Squidward, but are confused since everyone in the city looks similar to him. The other townspeople retaliate in protest and corner Squidward with a list of well-organized grievances. Squidward erupts on the others for their lack of fun, but he is informed that he doesn’t really have to live in Tentacle Acres. Squidward then blows himself over the community wall with his reef blower, but SpongeBob assumes that he certainly cannot be the real Squidward (not knowing that Squidward's behavior has changed).
{{-}}

===Prehibernation Week / Life of Crime===
'''Prehibernation Week'''
{{Infobox SpongeBob episode
| Title = Prehibernation Week
| Image =  
| Episode = 27a
| Season = 2
| Airdate = May 5, 2001
| Guests = [[Pantera]] (musical performance)
| Writer = [[Aaron Springer]]&lt;br /&gt;[[C. H. Greenblatt|C.H. Greenblatt]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Merriwether Williams]]
|}}

As Sandy prepares for hibernation, SpongeBob happily agrees to play with Sandy. Sandy presses a button on her remote to wake up SpongeBob. But when SpongeBob finds out that Sandy's &quot;fun&quot; activities are extremely dangerous, he runs away and hides under Patrick's house. Sandy, not knowing where he is, makes a search party for SpongeBob. But because they all have looked in poor places, being forced by Sandy, they all run away and hide under Patrick's rock too. Still frantic, Sandy starts overturning the town, looking for SpongeBob. The people soon discover SpongeBob under the rock, throw him out, and Squidward shouts out where SpongeBob is. Sandy hears him and runs to give SpongeBob a bone-crushing hug. She goes crazy again and tries to take him for another dangerous game before she hibernates, but SpongeBob is exhausted from all the antics and stands up for himself. Just then Sandy falls asleep. SpongeBob is relieved and falls asleep too.

The song in the episode is &quot;Death Rattle&quot; by former [[heavy metal music|heavy metal]] band [[Pantera]], who come from the same state as Sandy: [[Texas]].
{{-}}

'''Life of Crime'''
{{Infobox SpongeBob episode
| Title = Life of Crime
| Image =  
| Episode = 27b
| Season = 2
| Airdate = May 5, 2001
| Guests = 
| Writer = [[Jay Lender]]&lt;br /&gt;William Reiss&lt;br /&gt;[[Doug Lawrence|Mr. Lawrence]]
|}}

Mr. Krabs tells SpongeBob and Patrick that it's okay to borrow things if you plan to return them. He sorts through his belongings, and SpongeBob and Patrick, noting what they are, check to make sure Mr. Krabs hasn't stolen any of the items. Mr. Krabs assures them that he was didn't steal those items, and the two leave. However, Mr. Krabs says to himself, &quot;That was a close one&quot;, suggesting that he may really be a thief.

SpongeBob and Patrick, bored out of their minds, borrow a balloon from the balloon man, since they have no money. While playing with it, Patrick accidentally pops it. Realizing they can't return it, SpongeBob and Patrick run from the law. Just a little while after running away, SpongeBob realizes they won't have food because they are criminals. He takes two candy bars out of his pocket and gives Patrick his. Patrick then eats it, but, not realizing he ate it, bites his hand. They start to argue about Patrick's candy bar because Patrick thinks that SpongeBob has stolen it, ending in them both running towards the police station trying to denounce each other, but instead confessing their crime. They are sent to prison — for only a few seconds, since they stole a balloon on &quot;''Free'' Balloon Day&quot;. Then they both head home, with the policemen watching. They offer SpongeBob and Patrick lollipops for the long trip home. After one bite, Patrick's candy is gone and blames SpongeBob and the police.
{{-}}

===Christmas Who?===
'''Christmas Who?''' 
{{main|Christmas Who?}} 
{{Infobox SpongeBob episode
| Title = Christmas Who?
| Image = 
| Episode = 28
| Season = 2
| Airdate = December 6, 2000
| Guests = 
| Writer = [[Walt Dohrn]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Paul Tibbitt]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Doug Lawrence|Mr. Lawrence]]
|}}

This [[Christmas]] special is narrated by [[Pearl Krabs (character)|Patchy the Pirate]], the president of the SpongeBob SquarePants fan club. In the episode, Sandy tells SpongeBob about Christmas traditions, and he then relays the event to everybody in Bikini Bottom. The town becomes convinced that [[Santa Claus]] will come and grant their wishes. SpongeBob and Patrick then go to decorate their end of Bikini Bottom with festive decorations. On [[Christmas Eve]], Bikini Bottom gathers around Squidward's fallen &quot;Coral Tree&quot; and sings Christmas Carols in anticipation of Santa. When Santa fails to come, SpongeBob becomes riddled with sorrow, and Squidward revels in remorse. He makes up for mocking SpongeBob's belief in Santa by giving away everything he owns, posing as Santa. The real Santa later appears to thank Squidward. As Santa leaves, Squidward questions his sanity.

*First appearance: [[Pearl Krabs (character)|Patchy the Pirate]], [[Pearl Krabs (character)|Potty the Parrot]], Santa Claus.
*Note: There are two Patrick gags in this episode: one being Patrick's reference to Santa as &quot;Like a genie!&quot;, the other being Patrick ripping his paper.
*Another gag is that Mr. Krabs thinks to Christmas as a chance to get money. The first gag is Mr. Krabs as he refers to Christmas and his letter to Santa as &quot;as good as a blank check to the First National Bank of Santa Claus.&quot; and the other is Mr Krabs wishing for a pony, carrying bags full of money to Santa. Also, when the Bikini Bottomites sings their Christmas song &quot;The Very First Christmas to Me&quot; Mr. Krabs sings, as part of the lyrics &quot;This Christmas feels like the very first Christmas to me!&quot; with a girly accent, twice.
*When Sandy acts out the things about Christmas for SpongeBob, you'll notice that one of her acts is a reference of the [[Coyote and Road Runner|Road Runner]] from ''[[Looney Tunes]]''.
*In the episode ''The Secret Box'' from the same season, Patrick claims that his secret for his box is an embarrassing photo of SpongeBob at a Christmas Party. The embarrassing photo is seen 2 years later, in a stop-motion Nickelodeon Christmas short when it is shown of Spongebob with ripped pants.
*Nickelodeon promoted this episode as The SpongeBob Christmas Special.
*There is a [[continuity error]] in this episode. Though no one in Bikini Bottom claims to have heard of Christmas, Christmas has been mentioned twice before in the series. In the [[SpongeBob SquarePants (season 1)|season one]] episode &quot;[[Jellyfishing]]&quot;, Squidward ends up in the hospital after falling off a cliff and SpongeBob and Patrick decide to throw a welcome back party for him. When Squidward returns home, Patrick exclaims &quot;Merry Christmas!&quot; Christmas is again mentioned in the season 2 premiere &quot;[[Your Shoe's Untied|Your Shoe's United]]&quot;, in which SpongeBob learns to tie his shoes from the song &quot;Loop de Loop&quot; by [[Ween]] and one line from the song is &quot;...like bunny ears or a Christmas bow.&quot;
{{-}}

===Survival of the Idiots / Dumped===
'''Survival of the Idiots'''
{{Infobox SpongeBob episode
| Title = Survival of the Idiots
| Image =  
| Episode = 29a
| Season = 2
| Airdate = March 5, 2001
| Guests = 
| Writer = [[Aaron Springer]]&lt;br /&gt;[[C. H. Greenblatt|C.H. Greenblatt]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Merriwether Williams]]
|}}

Patrick and SpongeBob rush to Sandy’s treedome only to find that she just started [[hibernation|hibernating]]. As soon as they enter, a television turns on with a video warning them that they should stay away while she’s hibernating. They ignore the video and enter the treedome anyway, only to find that it is snowing inside the treedome. The water from the snow allows them to stay alive in Sandy's treedome without a water helmet. They go inside Sandy’s tree to find Sandy sleeping. Sandy is very overweight, as she stored up food for her long hibernation. While Sandy is sleeping, she’s having dreams of [[American Old West|Old Western]] [[outlaw]]s named Dirty Dan and Pinhead Larry, and she is the sheriff. SpongeBob and Patrick accidentally &quot;wake&quot; up the monstrous Sandy, who, while [[sleepwalking]], believes that they are really the outlaws. They decide to put earmuffs on Sandy so she won't &quot;wake&quot; up again. They leave her tree and start playing outside in the snow. They pretend that they are Dirty Dan and Pinhead Larry, and their noises outside &quot;wake&quot; up Sandy again. She comes out of her tree and chases SpongeBob and Patrick, who she still believes are the outlaws.

After suffering a beating at the hands of Sandy, Patrick and SpongeBob try to leave the treedome, but the latch on her door is frozen — trapping them inside. They soon succumb to the cold and must find a way to stay warm through the winter. They go back inside Sandy’s tree, but rather than staying warm in there, they decide they can stay warm outside if they use Sandy’s fur. They strip Sandy of all her fur and go back outside, preparing to stay warm throughout the winter. At that moment, winter suddenly ends, all the snow melts, and Sandy wakes up from her hibernation. However, the door is still frozen, and Sandy — fully alert and back into her normal form — comes outside to greet them. Curious as to why Patrick and SpongeBob are wearing fur, she looks down to realize that she is completely naked. Later, Sandy is drinking lemonade wearing Patrick and SpongeBob as &quot;punishment&quot; for taking her fur.
{{-}}

'''Dumped'''
{{Infobox SpongeBob episode
| Title = Dumped
| Image =  
| Episode = 29b
| Season = 2
| Airdate = March 5, 2001
| Guests = 
| Writer = [[Paul Tibbitt]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Walt Dohrn]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Merriwether Williams]]
|}}

SpongeBob and his pet snail Gary are playing [[tag (game)|tag]]. Patrick shows up and wants to join in the game, and SpongeBob tags him &quot;it&quot;. Patrick tags Gary and proclaims his victory. Gary then starts crawling all over Patrick to the amusement of Patrick and SpongeBob. This goes on for many hours, and it gets dark outside. SpongeBob takes Gary into his house to go to bed, but Gary sneaks over to Patrick at his house. Patrick recommends that he and Gary have a sleepover, and SpongeBob is happy to see his two best friends getting along. The next morning, SpongeBob cheerfully asks Patrick about their sleepover. SpongeBob sees how much fun the two of them are having, and he wants to join in on the fun. However, Gary is completely ignoring SpongeBob and continues to follow Patrick. SpongeBob begins to wonder why Gary is ignoring him and only playing with Patrick. SpongeBob goes to great length to get Gary’s attention, including pretending to close a window on his head, but nothing works. SpongeBob confronts Gary and questions why he’s being ignored and physically carries Gary back to his house. Patrick intervenes and tells SpongeBob that Gary has the right to choose who he wants to be with. Despite SpongeBob’s cries, Gary goes straight to Patrick, and the two of them go back to Patrick’s house.  

Later that night, SpongeBob is crying over losing Gary, and he resolves to simply get another pet. The next day, SpongeBob shows up with a pet [[worm]] named Rex. With Patrick and Gary looking on, SpongeBob proclaims that worms are better and more reliable than snails, but Rex sits there panting and ignores SpongeBob's request for tricks. When SpongeBob turns his back, Rex quickly boards a bus and leaves. SpongeBob then gets a new snail named Lary (so that he only has to change one letter on Gary's food dish), but this snail is very irritable and mean, refusing to play with SpongeBob and even overtaking his bed at night. SpongeBob realizes that Lary is nothing like Gary, and he begins to break down and cry. At that moment, Patrick and Gary show up at SpongeBob’s house to do laundry. Reminiscing that he and Gary used to do laundry together, SpongeBob begins crying excessively and begs Gary to come home and gives Gary a &quot;no rules rule&quot; that he could do anything he wants. Nothing seems to work. Then, Patrick takes off his shorts and tosses them into the washing machine, and Gary follows Patrick’s shorts into the washing machine. It turns out that Gary only liked Patrick because he wanted the cookie that was in his back pocket. Gary then goes back to SpongeBob. SpongeBob is delighted, but Patrick starts mourning.
{{-}}

===No Free Rides / I'm Your Biggest Fanatic===
'''No Free Rides'''
{{Infobox SpongeBob episode
| Title = No Free Rides
| Image =  
| Episode = 30a
| Season = 2
| Airdate = March 7, 2001
| Guests = 
| Writer = [[Aaron Springer]]&lt;br /&gt;[[C. H. Greenblatt|C.H. Greenblatt]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Doug Lawrence|Mr. Lawrence]]
|}}

Tired of SpongeBob failing his driver's test, Mrs. Puff gives him a very short essay, which he almost fails, then his license, so that she doesn't have to deal with him anymore. Later that night, SpongeBob's parents show up to thank her for really trying to teach him and not taking &quot;the easy way out&quot; and show her a new boatmobile for SpongeBob, who faints in excitement. Learning this, and realizing that she has given the not-so-ready SpongeBob free rein to drive on the streets of Bikini Bottom and wreak havoc there, Mrs. Puff attempts to steal it. When Mrs. Puff does, SpongeBob thinks she's a boat-jacker and tries to stop her. Right before riding off a cliff and into a police boat, he discovers that the boat-jacker is really Mrs. Puff trying to take the car back. Afterward, Mrs. Puff lands in jail and admits to SpongeBob he's not ready. It should be noted that Spongebob's license reveals his birthday, July 14, 1986, for the second time in the series, first was [[Sleepy Time (SpongeBob SquarePants episode)|Sleepy Time]].

Note: When SpongeBob thinks Mrs. Puff is a boat-jacker and tries to stop her, stop-motion-animation is used instead of the normal digital ink and paint when SpongeBob passes the signs.
{{-}}

'''I'm Your Biggest Fanatic'''
{{Infobox SpongeBob episode
| Title = I'm Your Biggest Fanatic
| Image =  
| Episode = 30b
| Season = 2
| Airdate = March 7, 2001
| Guests = 
| Writer = [[Jay Lender]]&lt;br /&gt;William Reiss&lt;br /&gt;[[Doug Lawrence|Mr. Lawrence]]
|}}

At a Jellyfishers' convention, SpongeBob meets the Jellyspotters, a highly-regarded group of jellyfishing experts. The group's arrogant leader, Kevin, invites him to become part of the group, but the challenges they give him are more designed to embrass than test. SpongeBob passes the tests with ease, but Kevin, having become increasingly annoyed at SpongeBob's success (and at his numerous stings from the jellyfish) tricks him into immobilizing himself in order to catch a &quot;Queen Jellyfish&quot;. SpongeBob agrees to this, only to be stung and chased by the Queen Jelly. As SpongeBob begs for mercy, the Jellyspotters appear from inside the Queen Jelly (revealing it to be a robot) and start mocking him. Soon after, though, the &quot;[[Cnidaria]] Rex/King Jellyfish&quot; appears and, mesmerized at the Queen Jelly, attempts to seduce it. SopngeBob and the Jellyspotters flee, only to crash into a billboard. Realizing that it's a trick, an angry King Jelly chases the gang into a cave, where Kevin and the others cry for their moms. SpongeBob exits the cave and blows a pie-shaped bubble for the King Jellyfish, enticing him to go away. Kevin then returns to his snotty state and claims that SpongeBob is still not in the club because he didn't catch a Queen Jelly, but the Jellyspotters rip Kevin's &quot;crown&quot; off his head and place it on SpongeBob's, making him the new leader of the Jellyspotters.

*One Time appearances: Kevin the Sea Cucumber, The Jellyspotters
*The real King Jellyfish appeared in &quot;Jellyfishing&quot;.
{{-}}

===Mermaid Man and Barnacle Boy III / Squirrel Jokes===
'''Mermaid Man and Barnacle Boy III'''
{{Infobox SpongeBob episode
| Title = Mermaid Man and Barnacle Boy III
| Image = 
| Episode = 31a
| Season = 2
| Airdate = November 27, 2000
| Guests = [[John Rhys-Davies]] as Man Ray
| Writer = [[Paul Tibbitt]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Walt Dohrn]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Merriwether Williams]]
|}}

Mermaid Man and Barnacle Boy are “bravely” packing for vacation. While they are gone on vacation, they have SpongeBob and Patrick watch their Merma-Lair, but they immediately want to touch everything. Mermaid Man and Barnacle Boy forbid them from touching anything, and they leave for the week.  While going through the halls of the cave, they stumble upon Man Ray, Mermaid Man and Barnacle Boy’s fiercest enemy. However, Man Ray is suspended in frozen [[tartar sauce]]. Patrick decides to unfreeze Man Ray, but SpongeBob stops him with only Man Ray’s head unfrozen. Man Ray commands them to release him, but they are hesitant to do so since Man Ray is evil. SpongeBob says that he will only let Man Ray go if he were good and not evil, so Man Ray convinces them that he is good. However, once he is released, he affirms that he's evil and lunges at the two. Just in time, SpongeBob activates Man Ray’s tickle belt to cause him to laugh uncontrollably. Man Ray tries to trick them into unlocking the belt, and he pretends that he’s tired of being evil and wants to be good. SpongeBob and Patrick take up the challenge of turning Man Ray good, while Man Ray just wants to get rid of the belt.

SpongeBob first tries to make Man Ray good by making him return Patrick’s [[wallet]] that he just dropped on the ground.  However, when he goes to give Patrick his wallet back, Patrick doesn’t realize that the wallet is his — even after Man-Ray shows him his ID in the wallet. Man Ray gets mad, and SpongeBob tickles him with the belt. For the next lesson, Man Ray is to help Patrick carry a heavy box, but Patrick repeatedly drops it on Man Ray’s foot. He beats Patrick senseless, even after being tickled. Angered, Patrick takes the controller for the tickle belt and starts tickling Man Ray repeatedly.  SpongeBob and Patrick argue over the controller until they break it, which causes the tickle belt to malfunction and increase its speed. Man Ray asks them to take off the belt, and they do so since he said &quot;please&quot;. Once he is released from the belt, Man-Ray helps himself to Mermaid Man and Barnacle Boy’s arsenal of weapons before leaving the cave — intent on ruling Bikini Bottom. Patrick and SpongeBob pursue him.

Man Ray easily pushes his way through SpongeBob and Patrick and has his eyes set on robbing a bank. He bursts in the doors and tries to tell the people to hand over all their money, but the effects of the tickle belt can still be felt, even though he is not wearing it. He starts laughing hysterically, and all the people in the bank start laughing at him. Man Ray loses his urge to be evil, and he just opens up a checking account instead. He comes across Patrick and SpongeBob and tells them that he is not evil anymore. He says he has no use for his mask, and he takes it off and gives it to SpongeBob before bidding farewell.

*First appearance: [[Pearl Krabs (character)|Man Ray]]
{{-}}

'''Squirrel Jokes'''
{{Infobox SpongeBob episode
| Title = Squirrel Jokes
| Image =  
| Episode = 31b
| Season = 2
| Airdate = November 27, 2000
| Guests = 
| Writer = [[Paul Tibbitt]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Walt Dohrn]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Merriwether Williams]]
|}}

The Krusty Krab begins hosting [[stand-up comedy]] nights, with SpongeBob being one of the comedians involved. His routine bombs with very bad jokes. He saves himself by telling harmful jokes about squirrels, which has the whole town cheering for him, except for Sandy, because she is a squirrel and especially because the jokes also make her the target of mistreatment by all the Bikini Bottomites. Sandy talks to SpongeBob to stop this, however, he does not know any other kind of funny jokes, so he keeps up with the squirrel jokes. Sandy tricks him into believing that she has begun to think they're funny, and invites him to her treedome. But when he gets there. Sandy makes him understand her suffering by pretending that the derogatory squirrel stereotypes that he created are real (and thus physically harms him), and at the next comedy night he does not make fun of squirrels, but instead, makes fun of every other species in the sea, including his own. Everybody is amused. Then, SpongeBob is telling not to get started on starfish.
{{-}}

===Pressure / The Smoking Peanut===
'''Pressure'''
{{Infobox SpongeBob episode
| Title = Pressure
| Image =  
| Episode = 32a
| Season = 2
| Airdate = March 8, 2001
| Guests = 
| Writer = [[Jay Lender]]&lt;br /&gt;William Reiss&lt;br /&gt;David B. Fain
|}}

Sandy, SpongeBob, Patrick, Mr. Krabs, and Squidward start fighting because the sea creatures think that they are better than land creatures, and Sandy thinks the opposite. Sandy tries to get rid of her protective suit to prove she can breathe underwater, but eventually has to breathe again. In return, Sandy makes SpongeBob and the other sea creatures go on land for 1 minute. To her surprise, they survive the air, but she has to save them from the seagulls that are attacking her friends. They finally conclude that sea creatures are good at some things, and land creatures good at others, and that neither can do everything,causing them to make up with each other 
{{-}}

'''The Smoking Peanut'''
{{Infobox SpongeBob episode
| Title = The Smoking Peanut
| Image =  
| Episode = 32b
| Season = 2
| Airdate = March 8, 2001
| Guests =
| Writer = [[Paul Tibbitt]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Walt Dohrn]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Doug Lawrence|Mr. Lawrence]]
|}}

SpongeBob and Patrick go to the zoo one day to see Clamu, the &quot;largest oyster held in captivity&quot;. But they see that the clam is asleep, so SpongeBob throws a peanut at it to wake it up, but it starts crying and bothering the town. SpongeBob is privately worried that his peanut bothered the clam, and all of his friends are angry at whoever made the clam cry. He goes to ask them for advice without revealing he did it. He goes to Sandy, but becomes immediately frightened by her because she says that whoever made the clam cry, she is going to beat them up. SpongeBob immediately runs off, while leaving Sandy questioning his &quot;hair&quot;. He goes to Squidward, who is stressed from the clam's noise, and SpongeBob begins saying that he knows the guy who did it (which is SpongeBob himself). Squidward becomes overjoyed and says that they can go turn him in. But SpongeBob says that he was only speaking hypothetically, and gets the door slammed in his face. He then gets questioned by the police, and Patrick gets arrested. Feeling bad, SpongeBob heads to the stadium where Patrick is being held. The angry citizens throw peanuts at Patrick to &quot;see how he likes it&quot;, but SpongeBob shows up, reveals that ''he'' threw the peanut, and publicly apologizes to everybody. However, the citizens simply decide to throw peanuts at both SpongeBob ''and'' Patrick, but are stopped from doing so when the zookeeper reveals that the reason behind the clam's sorrow is not because SpongeBob threw a peanut at it, but because Mr. Krabs stole its pearl, which is revealed to be an egg that hatches; Mr. Krabs excuses himself by stating that it was &quot;Free Day&quot; at the zoo. The clam is happy again, and the citizens punish Mr. Krabs for his crime by completely burying him in peanuts.

*Note: There is a book for this episode called Zoo Day Disaster.
{{-}}

===Shanghaied / Gary Takes a Bath===
'''Shanghaied'''
{{Infobox SpongeBob episode
| Title = Shanghaied
| Image =  
| Episode = 33a
| Season = 2
| Airdate = March 9, 2001
| Guests = 
| Writer = [[Aaron Springer]]&lt;br /&gt;[[C. H. Greenblatt|C.H. Greenblatt]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Merriwether Williams]]
|}}

A &quot;Patchy's Pick&quot; episode, SpongeBob, Squidward and Patrick climb to the Flying Dutchman's ship after its anchor damaged both SpongeBob’s and Squidward's houses, as they were trying to investigate. Squidward insults the ship, which bothers the Flying Dutchman. Eventually, the Flying Dutchman is so annoyed by Squidward that he puts him through a zipper-like portal leading to a scary place, called the &quot;Fly of Despair&quot; (which is, actually, drawn as [[spaghetti]] and [[meatball]]s). The Dutchman forces SpongeBob and Patrick to become his crew-mates, but they are horrible at it. Eventually, the Dutchman tells them that he will eat them, but while he prepares for making a meal out of SpongeBob and Patrick, he puts them in a cell. They try to escape, but the main door is locked, so they attempt to escape through the perfume department, which they hate because they are always sprayed by bursts of perfume. Then they escape, steal the Dutchman's &quot;lucky dining sock&quot; (so that he won't be able to eat them), so the Flying Dutchman gives them three wishes in exchange. Patrick says he wants five wishes, and then the Flying Dutchman proposes four. Then Patrick says, &quot;Three! Take it or leave it!&quot;,(much like in the Spongebob Sqaurepants movie) the Flying Dutchman agrees (much to SpongeBob's despair). Patrick wastes the first one, saying he wished to know about it earlier. SpongeBob wishes Squidward was with them, thus freeing him from the Fly of Despair (causing him to fall through a portal that lead into his house, and was then teleported to the Dutchman's ship). The three argue over who gets the last wish, so the Flying Dutchman randomly picks SpongeBob (By playing enie menie minie mo) to get that last wish. SpongeBob wishes the Dutchman was a vegetarian (in an attempt to make sure they wouldn't get eaten). When a pineapple appears above the trio's heads, they think it is SpongeBob's house. However, it turns out that the trio are still on-board the Dutchman's ship, and for some reason, the Flying Dutchman transforms them into fruits, put them in a blender (along with the pineapple), and it seems that he is still trying to eat them. Frightened, the trio attempt to escape the clutches of the Flying Dutchman. During this chase scene, the Dutchman's ship is shown to have been transported to a strange place, and the episode ends with a cliffhanger...

*Note: There are three different endings for this episode, all involving who gets the last wish and the consequences: the first is the original (with SpongeBob getting it), the second being Squidward getting it and wishing that he never met SpongeBob and Patrick (which only results in the two's memories of him being erased), and the third is Patrick getting the last wish and wishing for gum to prepare for being on-board the Dutchman's ship for all eternity with &quot;fresh breath&quot;; both the second and third endings conclude with the Dutchman chasing the trio around his ship, preparing to eat them. Note that the second and third endings are only available in the &quot;Sea Stories&quot; DVD, and the original ending is featured on television, Sea Stories and the Complete Second Season DVD.

*Note: This episode along with ''Gary Takes a Bath'' play as the episode ''[[Ugh (SpongeBob SquarePants)|Ugh]]'' on [[Netflix]] instant streaming known as a glitch Netflix hasn't fixed.
{{-}}

'''Gary Takes a Bath'''
{{Infobox SpongeBob episode
| Title = Gary Takes a Bath
| Image = 
| Episode = 33b
| Season = 2
| Airdate = July 26, 2003&lt;ref&gt;&quot;Shanghaied&quot; originally premiered by itself in 2003, and didn't air again until July 26, 2003, with this episode.[http://www.tvguide.com/detail/tv-show.aspx?tvobjectid=191781&amp;more=ucepisodelist]&lt;/ref&gt;
| Guests = 
| Writer = [[Aaron Springer]]&lt;br /&gt;[[C. H. Greenblatt|C.H. Greenblatt]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Merriwether Williams]]
|}}

When Gary has to take a bath, he refuses to enter the bathtub. SpongeBob keeps trying and trying to get Gary in the bathtub. While Gary is watching TV SpongeBob makes a fake pirate map and dresses up like one and convinces Gary to follow the map. SpongeBob was so upset that Gary would not take a bath and nothing will work. Eventually, SpongeBob absorbs the bathwater and chases Gary around, trying to wash him, but eventually gets stuck on a tree. But SpongeBob sees a record player and gets fooled. SpongeBob accidentally falls off and gets himself dirty.

*Note: Since Shanghaied is longer than a regular episode (15 minutes), &quot;Gary Takes a Bath&quot; is shorter (like about 7 minutes).
{{-}}

===Welcome to the Chum Bucket / Frankendoodle===
'''Welcome to the Chum Bucket'''
{{Infobox SpongeBob episode
| Title = Welcome to the Chum Bucket
| Image =  
| Episode = 34a
| Season = 
| Airdate = January 21, 2002
| Guests = 
| Writer = [[Walt Dohrn]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Paul Tibbitt]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Doug Lawrence|Mr. Lawrence]]
|}}

One night, Mr. Krabs and Plankton play cards. Mr. Krabs is confident (&quot;I've been taking him to the cleaners every Thursday night for fifteen years! I never lose!&quot;), so he bets SpongeBob's contract and loses (because Plankton cheated). Mr. Krabs now has to give SpongeBob to Plankton. SpongeBob doesn't feel good at The Chum Bucket, so Plankton tries to appeal to him so that he'll make a Krabby Patty, but this results in SpongeBob increasingly becoming a spoiled and bratty person instead. Eventually, due to the disobedience of SpongeBob, Plankton takes SpongeBob's brain out and puts it into a robot, but even that doesn't work. In frustration, Plankton gives SpongeBob back to Mr. Krabs, and he is once again employed at the Krusty Krab.
{{-}}

'''Frankendoodle'''
{{Infobox SpongeBob episode
| Title = Frankendoodle
| Image =  
| Episode = 34b
| Season = 2
| Airdate = January 21, 2002
| Guests = [[Doug Lawrence]], a.k.a. &quot;Mr. Lawrence&quot;&lt;br&gt;(as the sea-faring artist)
| Writer = [[Walt Dohrn]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Paul Tibbitt]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Merriwether Williams]]
|}}

SpongeBob and Patrick discover a pencil that fell down from the surface from a human artist at sea, and that it's no ordinary pencil — whatever artwork they make using it comes to life. SpongeBob draws a crudely made self-portrait that he later names &quot;DoodleBob&quot;, but he turns evil, so SpongeBob and Patrick pursue him. They catch DoodleBob, and use the magic pencil's eraser to erase him all — except for his arm, but SpongeBob and Patrick are unaware that DoodleBob hasn't been completely erased. 

DoodleBob comes to SpongeBob's house at night, and uses the pencil to restore himself. SpongeBob and DoodleBob battle, but once the evil drawing steps on a piece of paper, he gets stuck to it. This gives SpongeBob an idea: he decides to trap DoodleBob in a book, so DoodleBob becomes an ordinary drawing on a piece of paper, which SpongeBob later posts on his wall. SpongeBob tells Patrick that DoodleBob wasn't evil, just an uncomfortable 2-dimensional being in a 3-dimensional world.

SpongeBob and Patrick then decide to return the magic pencil to the surface, as they believe that its powers are too much for them to handle. The human artist at sea that was seen earlier retrieves his pencil. However, he breaks the tip of it, and while the artist cries and yells, the French Narrator remarks that an artist at sea should always bring a pencil sharpener.

*One Time appearance: The DoodleBob
*Note: The episode title uses the first half of the last name of [[Victor Frankenstein|Dr. Frankenstein]], the mad scientist from the horror novel ''[[Frankenstein]]''.
*Note: The video game ''[[Drawn to Life: SpongeBob SquarePants Edition]]'' has a story that is the sequel to this episode, as there are magic pencils (''two'' of them this time), and DoodleBob is featured as the main antagonist once again.
{{-}}

===The Secret Box / Band Geeks===
'''The Secret Box'''
{{Infobox SpongeBob episode
| Title = The Secret Box
| Image =  
| Episode = 35a
| Season = 2
| Airdate = September 7, 2001
| Guests = 
| Writer = [[Walt Dohrn]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Paul Tibbitt]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Merriwether Williams]]
|}}

SpongeBob wants Patrick to go jellyfishing with him, but Patrick is distracted by his “secret box” — which Patrick claims has life-altering contents within.  This immediately sparks SpongeBob’s curiosity, but Patrick won’t show him what’s inside his box. Despite Patrick's stupidity, SpongeBob is unable to trick him into letting him look inside. Patrick then goes ecstatic while looking at the contents of his own box, and this angers SpongeBob. Patrick becomes extremely defensive when SpongeBob tries to look inside his box. Patrick calls their friendship into question but claims that the secret contents of his box are so irresistible — further tempting SpongeBob...

Later that night, SpongeBob continues to dwell over and question what could possibly be in the secret box. He then plots to break into Patrick’s house that night to take a peek at the contents. However, in the process, every little move SpongeBob makes causes a lot of noise; however, Patrick sleeps through it all until SpongeBob quietly remarks that Patrick is a heavy sleeper. Patrick scolds SpongeBob for trying to see inside his secret box, but he eventually allows him to have a look anyway. As it turns out, the secret box contains a piece of “secret string”. SpongeBob laughs off the situation and leaves Patrick’s house. Patrick then looks at the string inside his box and pulls it, revealing a secret compartment that contains an embarrassing picture of SpongeBob at the Christmas party (seen in &quot;Christmas Who?&quot;). Patrick laughs hysterically.
{{-}}

'''Band Geeks'''
{{Infobox SpongeBob episode
| Title = Band Geeks
| Image =  
| Episode = 35b
| Season = 2
| Airdate = September 7, 2001
| Guests = [[David Glen Eisley]] (SpongeBob's singing voice)&lt;br /&gt;[[Dee Bradley Baker]] (Squilliam Fancyson)
| Writer = [[C. H. Greenblatt|C.H. Greenblatt]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Aaron Springer]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Merriwether Williams]]
|}}

Squidward receives a phone call from his old high school band rival [[Squilliam Fancyson]], who is living out Squidward’s dreams of success. Squilliam says he was supposed to play at the big &quot;[[Liberty Bowl Memorial Stadium|Bubble Bowl]]&quot; (a sports stadium) next week but cannot attend. Knowing Squidward has no band, he asks him if his &quot;band&quot; could perform in his absence. Squilliam then makes fun of Squidward’s lack of success. Squidward, not wanting to admit that he works at a fast food restaurant, says that he does have a band and that they would be glad to play at the Bubble Bowl. Of course, Squidward has no band.

So, he posts [[Flyer (pamphlet)|fliers]] around Bikini Bottom for people to join his [[marching band]] in preparation for the Bubble Bowl. He attracts a large group of people, which consists of SpongeBob, Patrick, Plankton, Pearl, Mr. Krabs, Larry the Lobster, Mrs. Puff, Sandy, and many others. Things start off badly when Squidward finds out that nobody in the group knows how to play any instruments properly. Their rehearsals are very unproductive and out of control, and the Bubble Bowl is only days away. The band is very terrible and shows no signs of progress. The day before the Bubble Bowl, Squidward yells at the band for being terrible. This causes the band to turn on itself with their instruments, and a brawl ensues until practice is over. Then, they all calmly start to leave. Squidward sadly tells them not to show up tomorrow for the Bubble Bowl because of their lack of progress, telling them that he'll just tell Squilliam they all died, and he leaves. SpongeBob convinces the group that they should continue practicing, because they shouldn't disappoint Squidward.

The next day, Squidward enters the stadium for the Bubble Bowl, and told Squilliam that all of his band members died. To his surprise, however, all of the band members show up and are standing right behind him ready to play. He is also shocked because he didn't expect to see them due to their poor performance the last time he checked on them. They enter a glass dome and are lifted up into a realistic-looking [[American football|football]] field to perform for a [[halftime show]] in front of live humans (though Squidward's band believes that they're mutant fish), making Squidward feel even more worried that he might embarrass himself in front of Squilliam and the humans. Fearing that he may never show his face in public again, Squidward worryingly gives the cue to start playing. Conversely, the band’s introduction is magnificent, and Squidward is surprised and feels proud of himself. He takes credit for their success when Squilliam appears next to the stage. Squilliam, who watches the band in horror, suffers from a [[Cardiac arrest|heart attack]] and is transported out of the stadium on a [[stretcher]]. The highly-choreographed band plays “Sweet Victory” with SpongeBob (singing voiced by [[David Glen Eisley]]) singing the lead.{{-}}

*First appearance: Squilliam Fancyson
{{-}}

===Graveyard Shift / Krusty Love===
'''Graveyard Shift'''
{{main|Graveyard Shift (SpongeBob SquarePants)}} 
{{Infobox SpongeBob episode
| Title = Graveyard Shift
| Image =  
| Episode = 36a
| Season = 2
| Airdate = September 6, 2002
| Guests = [[Max Schreck]] as [[Count Orlok]] ([[Stock footage|archive footage]])
| Writer = [[Doug Lawrence|Mr. Lawrence]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Jay Lender]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Dan Povenmire]]
|}}

Late at night, Squidward is anxiously waiting to leave the Krusty Krab at closing time, but a customer comes up the door and proceeds to order food — despite Squidward pointing out the closing sign. The customer then complains that they must not want his money, while Squidward says that he can't stay all night cause he's got a life. Mr. Krabs, who seems to not care at all, drops from the ceiling and proclaims the Krusty Krab to now be open 24 hours a day, and he says the same thing Squidward said, although Mr. Krabs promptly leaves, with SpongeBob and Squidward left to work at the Krusty Krab 24/7. SpongeBob is excited to never get to leave work, while Squidward is less than enthused. However, SpongeBob is soon scared by having to take out the trash at night, and Squidward tries to scare SpongeBob into not liking the nightshift anymore. He then proceeds to tell a bogus [[horror fiction|scary story]] about the “Hash-Slinging Slasher” — a former Krusty Krab fry cook who accidentally chopped off his own hand while cutting hamburger patties, replaced his hand with a rusty spatula, got hit by a bus, and was fired at his funeral. Squidward says that this person comes back to the Krusty Krab every Tuesday night (the night they were working) to seek revenge. He tells of the three signs signaling the Hash-Slinging Slasher’s arrival: the lights will flicker on and off, the phone will ring but nobody answers, and his arrival in the ghost of the bus that ran him over. The story scares SpongeBob incredibly, but he begins laughing when Squidward tells him it was only a joke, either way, annoying Squidward.

Soon, all the late-night customers leave, and Squidward is bored out of his mind, while SpongeBob mops the ceiling with his extra time. Squidward is still mad that the Krusty Krab is open with no business, saying, &quot;Open 24 hours a day - what a stupid idea! Who wants a Krabby Patty at 3 in the morning?!&quot; (At that instant there is a scene of Patrick getting waken up by an alarm clock and, saying, &quot;Oh, boy, 3 AM!&quot;, and begins to eat a Krabby Patty that was hidden under his [[quilt]]). Then the lights start flickering on and off, and Squidward blames SpongeBob, though he is not responsible. Squidward shrugs it off, as not being built to run 24 hours a day, when SpongeBob begins to think Squidward is doing it. Then the phone rings, but nobody answers. SpongeBob compliments at Squidward's humor thinking he was pretending the mysterious call really happened, but Squidward then tells SpongeBob that he is not doing this. At that point, Squidward gets scared and starts to believe his own story about the Hash-Slinging Slasher. A mysterious bus then stops in front of the Krusty Krab and drops off a shadowy figure — someone they believe is the Hash-Slinging Slasher. SpongeBob thinks it's just Squidward disguised as a ghostly fry cook to entertain him and is touched that Squidward must really like him. But Squidward tells SpongeBob that he hates him, and that it's unlikely that he is dressed like the ghost because he is standing right next to him. These facts lead Spongebob to realize that Squidward is not responsible, and the REAL Hash-Slinging Slasher is right outside. They are both very scared, yelling at the person to go away. However, when the person steps into the light, it is just a nerdy-looking person coming in to get a job application. He happened to be carrying his own spatula. He said he called earlier but hung up since he was too nervous. Squidward then wonders who it was that was turning the lights on and off. They all look over to see that the lights were being turned on and off by [[Nosferatu]] ([[Count Orlok]], played by [[Max Schreck]] in the 1922 silent film).

*One Time appearance: The Hash-Slinging-Slasher
*Note: When Squidward tells the story from the second sign to the end of the story, the episode plays music from ''[[Night of the Living Dead]]''.
*Note: There was a deleted scene from this episode when Spongebob delivers the mail to &quot;Floorboard Harry&quot;.
{{-}}

'''Krusty Love'''
{{Infobox SpongeBob episode
| Title = Krusty Love
| Image =  
| Episode = 36b
| Season = 2
| Airdate = September 6, 2002
| Guests = 
| Writer = [[Doug Lawrence|Mr. Lawrence]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Jay Lender]]&lt;br /&gt;William Reiss
|}}

Mr. Krabs is sitting in his office at the Krusty Krab when he senses that something is wrong with Squidward’s cash register. The amount in the register is $49.08 and says that it's a [[penny]] short, and he proceeds to cry. When SpongeBob tells Mr. Krabs that a penny is not that important, Mr. Krabs goes on a rant and explains how money makes the world go around. He then notices Mrs. Puff, SpongeBob’s driving instructor, and he is immediately smitten but too self-conscious to go and talk to her. SpongeBob convinces him to do so, but Mr. Krabs is so nervous that his speech is nothing but incomprehensible gibberish. SpongeBob &quot;translates&quot; for Mr. Krabs, and he asks Mrs. Puff if she’d like to go on a date with Mr. Krabs. She agrees.

That night, Mr. Krabs and Mrs. Puff go on a date to the fanciest restaurant in town — an undersea [[impossible bottle|ship in a bottle]], complete with [[massage|masseurs]] and imported music (a real life human in a scuba suit playing the piano). Mr. Krabs spares no expense on the date, even paying people to carry Mrs. Puff so that she doesn’t have to walk. However, he must pay a bill of $100,000. He is emotionally distraught that he couldn't help but spend every cent he had on Mrs. Puff, and he tells SpongeBob that he couldn’t control himself.  He's got another date first thing in the morning, so Mr. Krabs puts SpongeBob in charge of his money so that he won’t spend any. The next day, the two of them go to Mrs. Puff’s house, and SpongeBob has vowed not to give Mr. Krabs any money. However, even before Mrs. Puff answers the door, Mr. Krabs yells at SpongeBob to go buy her flowers. When SpongeBob returns with the flowers, Mr. Krabs yells at him for spending his money.  Mr. Krabs cannot control his spending, and he tells SpongeBob that he needs to buy Mrs. Puff many expensive things, such as chocolates, a fur coat, a bedroom furniture set, fine jewelry, and even a washing machine — even before they leave Mrs. Puff’s front yard. The whole time, SpongeBob is trying to save Mr. Krabs money, but Mr. Krabs begs him to buy Mrs. Puff many things that she doesn't need. Then, he yells at SpongeBob every time he returns with the items that Mr. Krabs originally requested.

Finally, SpongeBob explodes on Mr. Krabs for his contradicting nature. Mr. Krabs then blames SpongeBob for being loose with his money, and SpongeBob gives him a verbal scalding before storming off. Mr. Krabs is shocked, and Mrs. Puff says that she cannot accept all of Mr. Krabs' gifts. She then requests that she would really like to “[[Going Dutch|go Dutch]]” on their date.
{{-}}

===Procrastination / I'm With Stupid===
'''Procrastination'''
{{Infobox SpongeBob episode
| Title = Procrastination
| Image =  
| Episode = 37a
| Season = 2
| Airdate = November 30, 2001
| Guests = 
| Writer = [[Walt Dohrn]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Paul Tibbitt]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Doug Lawrence|Mr. Lawrence]]
|}}

SpongeBob is sitting in Mrs. Puff’s class, and he is excited to hear that they are getting an essay assignment as homework. The assignment is an 800-word essay on what not to do at a [[traffic light|stoplight]]. SpongeBob rushes home to immediately start writing his essay, even though it is a beautiful day outside. He pulls up a chair at his desk and prepares to write what he says will be the greatest essay ever written.  All he writes is his name and title, but three hours pass and SpongeBob is still staring at the piece of paper — encountering a major case of [[writer's block]].

He then looks out the window and sees everybody is having fun, and Patrick encourages him to come outside and enjoy the day (this scene wasn't seen in the final concept). Unfortunately, he must stay inside and write his essay. He says he has plenty of time since it’s only 6:00, but he has no idea what to write. In order to boost his energy, he starts exercising but soon gets easily distracted, even by the rhythmic squeaking of his chair. (The exercising scene was also removed.) Gary then comes in the room, and SpongeBob is very persistent in feeding Gary to take up time, even though he says he’s not hungry. After Gary eats, SpongeBob says that he can’t write his essay with a dirty kitchen, and he proceeds to clean the entire kitchen — even his dirty trash can. After that’s done, he is shocked to see that it is now 10:00, and his essay hasn't even been started. He then writes on his essay, but in actuality, all he writes is the word “The” and then says he needs a break with only 799 words to go on his essay. He takes a break to call Patrick who is sleeping, but Patrick says that he knows that he was just called as a distraction so SpongeBob wouldn’t have to write his essay. Everything distracts SpongeBob from writing his essay, like eraser shavings on his paper and his sudden hunger. Although it’s late at night, a package is delivered, and SpongeBob proceeds to talk to the [[mail carrier|mailman]], who then asks if SpongeBob should be writing his paper. SpongeBob walks back to his house and watches TV, but the story of his procrastination had made it into the news. Confused and shocked, SpongeBob smashes his TV.  

SpongeBob then starts hallucinating as midnight approaches. He thinks his couch talking to him, and that his pants have run away. Trying to catch his pants, he leaves his house and gets locked out of it. Then, his house suddenly goes on fire. His house then starts yelling at SpongeBob for wasting time and not writing his paper. SpongeBob then sees an anthropomorphic flame in his house burn his essay as a means of torturing SpongeBob. It says with a grim smile &quot;Only 799 words to go!!&quot;, and then it cackles as the house is burned down.

SpongeBob suddenly wakes up from these hallucinations. But he sees that it’s 8:55 in the morning, and class starts in five minutes. He then gets a surge of ideas for his essay on what not to do at a stoplight, such as feeding your snail, making a sandwich, and all the other things he dreamt of that night instead of writing his essay. He rushes to class to excitingly give his essay to Mrs. Puff, but the classroom is empty. Mrs. Puff arrives to say that class was canceled for the day and so was the assignment — stating that they were just going to take a field trip to a stoplight instead. SpongeBob rips his paper and himself in half.

*Note: This is one of the few episodes after season 1 to be produced with traditional cel animation.

*Second appearance of Boating Students. 3/4 of this episode is part of a dream SpongeBob had while writing his essay.
{{-}}

'''I'm With Stupid'''
{{Infobox SpongeBob episode
| Title = I'm With Stupid
| Image =  
| Episode = 37b
| Season = 2
| Airdate = November 30, 2001
| Guests = 
| Writer = [[Aaron Springer]]&lt;br /&gt;[[C. H. Greenblatt|C.H. Greenblatt]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Mark O'Hare]]
|}}

Patrick is frantically cleaning his house when SpongeBob arrives. He questions Patrick’s sudden home improvements, and Patrick yells at him for not having any responsibilities. He then proceeds to cry, but SpongeBob doesn’t know why — thinking he just forgot how to eat again. Patrick then shows SpongeBob a letter he got from his parents saying that they are coming for a visit.  Patrick says that his parents think he is very dumb, and he said that he is going to let his parents down again. SpongeBob agrees to help out Patrick by pretending to be dumber than Patrick is when his parents arrive, so that Patrick will seem smarter by comparison. 

The next day, a couple (whom Patrick recognizes as his parents) arrive at his house, and they are happy to see that Patrick at least recognized them. They start to treat Patrick like a child, even helping him back inside his house in case he forgot where the inside of his house was. His dad is even happy to see that Patrick actually put the drinks in a glass this time.  

Then, the doorbell rings, and it is SpongeBob — only this time he is acting as though he's incredibly dumb and wearing a protective helmet (in actuality, his karate helmet). SpongeBob tries to shake hands with Patrick’s dad, but SpongeBob stares blankly and acts as though he doesn’t know how to shake his dad’s hand. All the while, Patrick is encouraging SpongeBob to act dumb and invites him to stay for dinner. SpongeBob constantly makes nonsense noises and bounces around Patrick’s house to the amusement of his parents. Patrick then starts to make fun of SpongeBob’s &quot;normal&quot; appearance, including his attire, physique, and apparent use of [[mascara]]. SpongeBob then calls out Patrick’s name in disgust and tells Patrick he wants to talk to him in the kitchen. All the while, Patrick is over-exploiting SpongeBob’s fake stupidity to his parents in order to make it seem like he is smarter. In the other room, SpongeBob tries to reassure Patrick that it is just a rouse and part of the plan, but Patrick is taking it too seriously. SpongeBob takes off his helmet and approaches Patrick’s parents as his normal self. He tells them that he is not stupid and that it was just an act. However, Patrick’s parents believe that Patrick was behind SpongeBob’s sudden increase in intellect. SpongeBob gets annoyed and starts to demonstrate his intelligence, but Patrick’s parents give full credit to Patrick for teaching SpongeBob. They all begin laughing excessively at SpongeBob to the point where he can’t take it anymore, and he busts out of Patrick’s house.

Patrick’s dad then says that he has newfound appreciation of Patrick after seeing how dumb SpongeBob was. Patrick’s parents then call each other by name — and Patrick suddenly realizes that these two are not his real parents, and angrily begins to intimidate them. At that moment, Squidward rings the doorbell and presents Patrick with two more starfish who are Patrick’s real parents, stating that they have been standing outside of his house asking where Patrick is all day. The fake parents then realize that they never had a son, and they nonchalantly walk away. Patrick decides to just act like his normal (dumb) self to his real parents, and they all start laughing.
{{-}}

===Sailor Mouth / Artist Unknown===
'''Sailor Mouth'''
{{main|Sailor Mouth}}
{{Infobox SpongeBob episode
| Title = Sailor Mouth
| Image =
| Episode = 38a
| Season = 2
| Airdate = September 21, 2001
| Guests = 
| Writer = [[Walt Dohrn]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Paul Tibbitt]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Merriwether Williams]]
|}}

SpongeBob and Patrick discover a [[Curse Word|swear word]] graffitied onto the Krusty Krab dumpster. Although SpongeBob is unsure of its meaning, Patrick assures him that it is a &quot;sentence enhancer&quot; that will make them sound &quot;fancy&quot;. The two repeat the word incessantly throughout the Krusty Krab, including over the loudspeaker, offending many of the Krusty Krab patrons (with the swear word being censored by the vocalization of a dolphin rather than a beeping sound). However, the two regret their utterings after Mr. Krabs informs them that the word is highly inappropriate, being number eleven in a list of thirteen bad words total. 

Later, SpongeBob tries to win a game of &quot;Eels and Escalators&quot; (based on [[Snakes and ladders]]) to Patrick, but Patrick wins much to SpongeBob's dismay and he says the word again. Patrick races to the Krusty Krab to tell Mr. Krabs, but SpongeBob tries to stop him. Patrick reminds SpongeBob of the word he used, actually saying it himself, so SpongeBob runs to tell on him. Mr. Krabs is outraged, and punishes both of them by having to paint the Krusty Krab. Before they start painting, Mr. Krabs trips on a rock, which stubs his foot, and causes him to shout all 13 bad words, including one that was censored by an old-fashioned car horn sound. SpongeBob, Patrick, and Mr. Krabs rush to the house of Mama Krabs (Mr. Krabs' mother) to tell on each other. 

When they get there, all three begin tattling on one another to Mama Krabs, saying the word and some new ones creating a lot of profanity. Mama Krabs, overwhelmed by the barrage of expletives, faints and falls to the ground. Mr. Krabs weeps while pulling money out of his mother's pocket. After regaining consciousness, Mama Krabs tells the group that if they are going to talk like sailors, then they are going to work like sailors. and puts all three to work painting her house. While watching them paint, Mama Krabs hurts herself exactly the same way Mr. Krabs did, and as she begins yelling out in pain, an old-fashioned car horn sound is heard over part of her shouting. The three look at Mama Krabs in shock, thinking that she is using one of the swear words. However they all begin to laugh when they discover that Old Man Jenkins was honking the horn of his old [[jalopy]], which happened to correspond exactly with her outburst.

*Note: Every curse word in this episode is censored by various pirate and sea noises.And on the title card, there were Pirates singing.
{{-}}

'''Artist Unknown'''
{{Infobox SpongeBob episode
| Title = Artist Unknown
| Image =  
| Episode = 38b
| Season = 2
| Airdate = September 21, 2001
| Guests = 
| Writer = [[Walt Dohrn]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Paul Tibbitt]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Mark O'Hare]]
|}}

Squidward one day gets a job to be an [[art]] teacher at the Rec Center. He is very excited thinking that one day he'll get to become famous for his art. Although the problem is that he has no [[Aptitude|talent]]. A trash urgent of the class tells him to &quot;calm down&quot;. But everybody asks if the class is a [[cooking]] class. They leave, making SpongeBob the only student. SpongeBob somehow learned that Squidward is teaching art. Squidward tries to yell to everybody that the class was a cooking class so he won't have SpongeBob as a student, but fails. Squidward says to SpongeBob that he doesn't have any talent but Mr. Tentacles (Squidward) has all the talent. Squidward makes a poorly drawn [[circle]] to show SpongeBob what to do. But SpongeBob however makes a perfect circle. Squidward says the circle wasn't right. SpongeBob draws a [[head]], and erases it making another perfect circle. Squidward forbids it again and crumples the paper. SpongeBob then crumples it again on his own, making an [[origami]] of him and Squidward playing [[Leapfrog]] with Squidward on the bottom. Squidward rips it after he forbids it. SpongeBob thinking that Squidward forbade it because he wasn't on top of the origami, then makes a [[puzzle]] out of the ripped paper shreds, of him and Squidward playing Leapfrog together with Squidward on top this time. Jealous that SpongeBob has all the good ideas, Squidward forbids it again. Squidward then tries to teach SpongeBob the art of [[Sculpture|sculpting]] statues. Squidward uses a hammer and a nail and hits his block of marble, but instead of making a statue, it just broke into dust. SpongeBob does the same thing, but he made a statue (which happens to be a replica of Michelangelo's ''David'' statue with a clam shell covering the genitals for the censors). Squidward forbids it again saying that it's not art unless it takes more time. He also says he got the nose wrong. Squidward then places a nose like his own on the statue and calls it &quot;art&quot;.

SpongeBob breaks down and apologizes for arrogantly shunning Squidward’s lessons. Crying, he proceeds to leave the room but the door suddenly flies open, knocking SpongeBob out of the window and into a garbage truck on its way to the dump. The person entering the door is Monty P. Moneybanks — a world famous art collector. Ecstatic, Squidward insists that Moneybanks makes a role for his (Squidward's) art (''Squidward in Ripose'' and ''Bold and Brash''), which are terrible. Moneybanks then sees the statue that SpongeBob had just created, and he proclaims it to be the greatest piece of art in the world (except for the nose that Squidward had added). He said that he will bestow fame and fortune upon the artist responsible, and Squidward takes credit. Moneybanks says he will make Squidward immortal, and Squidward attempts to carry the statue out to Moneybanks’ car. However, the statue is too tall to fit through the door, and Squidward accidentally knocks the statue’s head off, where it shatters to dust. Moneybanks says it shouldn’t be a problem for Squidward to make another statue. Moneybanks agrees to come back tomorrow, and Squidward must desperately find SpongeBob at the dump (where some of Squidward’s art was thrown to).  

Squidward convinces SpongeBob to give art another chance, but SpongeBob believes he is a disgrace, but he later agrees to Squidward's request. However, the sponge then decides to follow art “by the book”, and he loses all of his innate talents; he can’t even draw a perfect circle anymore. Squidward tells him to forget about the book, but SpongeBob’s talents are still lost. When SpongeBob tries to sculpt a new statue, his block of marble is reduced to a pile of dust with one strike of the chisel, and he adds a Squidward-like nose to the dust and proclaims it art — much to the dismay of Squidward. Squidward then becomes very angry and starts to mess up the room. SpongeBob then retreats back to the dump. In the process of messing around with things, Moneybanks arrives again. He shockingly asks, “Who is responsible for ''this''?”. Squidward says that the janitor is responsible and then storms out of the room. Unknown to Squidward, while he was destroying several blocks of marble, he inadvertently recreated SpongeBob’s version of ''David'' without even knowing it. After passing down credit to the janitor, Moneybanks tells the janitor he is the greatest artist who has ever lived.
{{-}}

===Jellyfish Hunter / The Fry Cook Games===
'''Jellyfish Hunter'''
{{Infobox SpongeBob episode
| Title = Jellyfish Hunter
| Image =  
| Episode = 39a| Season = 2
| Airdate = September 28, 2002
| Guests = 
| Writer = [[Walt Dohrn]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Paul Tibbitt]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Mark O'Hare]]
|}}

SpongeBob is hunting in Jellyfish Fields, trying to catch and name every [[jellyfish]]. In addition to that, he likes collecting jellyfish jelly (similar to [[honey bee|honeybee’s]] [[honey]]). He comes across a blue jellyfish — the only known such colored jellyfish — which he has never been able to catch. Therefore, he refers to the elusive jellyfish as &quot;No Name&quot;. He tries hard to catch the jellyfish, but it escapes every time. The next day at the Krusty Krab, SpongeBob is taking his lunch break, and he brought with him a jar of jellyfish jelly to put on a Krabby Patty. Another customer overhears SpongeBob enjoying his sandwich and asks to try some of the jelly on his hamburger. The customer is so ecstatic about how great it tastes that he breaks out into a song and dance and gives all the other customers jelly on their hamburgers.  All of the customers love the jelly. Mr. Krabs at first dislikes the idea, but later sees it as a way to make lots of money by selling the &quot;Jelly Patty&quot;. He convinces SpongeBob to catch jellyfish to harvest their jelly. He wants so much jelly for the new sandwich that SpongeBob eventually captures every jellyfish in Jellyfish Fields — except for No Name.

Later that night, No Name follows SpongeBob to his home. In [[horror film|scary movie]] fashion, No Name makes an eerie prank phone call (he calls SpongeBob, but SpongeBob can only hear ominous breathing sounds), and cuts out the electricity in SpongeBob’s house, and SpongeBob gets scared. To calm his nerves, he goes to the kitchen to see a Jelly Patty — with BLUE jelly. Realizing that the blue jelly must have came from No Name, he reveals himself and catches SpongeBob by putting him in a glass jar (as SpongeBob did with the other jellyfishes), and then he carries SpongeBob to a factory operated by Mr. Krabs. In this factory, Mr. Krabs is torturing the jellyfish into making jelly for his own profit. Outraged, SpongeBob and No Name break in and demand that Mr. Krabs cease operation of the factory and let the jellyfish go. Mr. Krabs refuses. So, SpongeBob tries to break open the door to the area where the captured jellyfish are being held. While explaining to SpongeBob about the door, Mr. Krabs says that it is voice-activated, and will only open when he says &quot;OPEN&quot;. After Krabs realizes his mistake, the door unlocks, and the jellyfish are freed. As revenge, the jellyfish throw a nasty zap on Mr. Krabs, who foolishly tries to escape on a [[stationary bicycle|stationary exercise bike]]. The jellyfish sting him with great intensity and then leave the factory, and Mr. Krabs, who is suffering intense burns, says he will take the Jelly Patty off the menu. At that point, No Name allows SpongeBob to capture him, and he renames the blue jellyfish as &quot;Friend&quot;.
{{-}}

'''The Fry Cook Games'''
{{Infobox SpongeBob episode
| Title = The Fry Cook Games
| Image =  
| Episode = 39b
| Season = 2
| Airdate = September 28, 2001
| Guests = 
| Writer = [[Jay Lender]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Dan Povenmire]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Merriwether Williams]]
|}}

At the Fast Food Coliseum, the Fry Cook Games (a fast food-themed sports competition) commence. The main event is a bitter rivalry between Mr. Krabs and Plankton — fast food competitors and former Fry Cook Games athletes. However, at this year’s event, SpongeBob is now representing the Krusty Krab at the games. While getting warmed up, Patrick approaches and is excited when SpongeBob says he’s training for the games. Patrick wants to play, but he can’t since he doesn’t work at a restaurant. SpongeBob tells Patrick to go home after he makes fun of SpongeBob’s profession as a fry cook. They start arguing, and the argument culminates in making fun of each other’s color — SpongeBob being yellow and Patrick pink. Patrick vows to get a job as a fry cook and beat SpongeBob in the games. Not so long later, Plankton arrives at the stadium and introduces a new representative for the Chum Bucket. As it turns out, Plankton introduces Patrick as the new fry cook for the Chum Bucket, and Patrick is now able to compete in the games. Plankton and Mr. Krabs try to convince their respective employees that they are really not friends with each other in order to motivate them for the games and turn them against each other.

The first event is the deep-fry [[pole vault]] over a vat of grease. The next event is the Chocolate [[diving|High-Dive]], in which they dive into [[Chocolate syrup]], making the diver look like ice cream. The two are equally skilled in both of these events. Many more events are followed, but the score is tied going into the final event: Bun [[Wrestling]]. The two are wrestling in a ring on top of a giant [[Hamburger|hamburger bun]], and they both reveal incredibly muscular bodies beneath their wrestling robes. The fight culminates with the two [[grappling]] with each other, repeatedly yelling how much they hate each other. When they begin struggling too much, they both rip their pants. Patrick turns out to be wearing yellow underwear, and SpongeBob is wearing pink underwear. Realizing that the color of their underwear matches the other’s color, they realize that they really do care about each other. They both walk out of the ring, ending the match much to the dismay of Plankton and Mr. Krabs, who wanted to see them kill each other. As they are walking out to scores of booing from the audience, Patrick says that his yellow underwear was white when he bought them.
{{-}}

===Squid on Strike / Sandy, SpongeBob, and the Worm===
'''Squid on Strike'''
{{Infobox SpongeBob episode
| Title = Squid on Strike
| Image =  
| Episode = 40a
| Season = 2
| Airdate = October 12, 2001
| Guests = 
| Writer = [[Walt Dohrn]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Paul Tibbitt]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Mark O'Hare]]
|}}

Mr. Krabs is in his office at the Krusty Krab counting the day’s profits. He realizes that profits are down $3.00 from the previous month and that he needs to start running a tighter shift. He scolds Squidward for giving a customer change and even yells at him for wasting time breathing. Mr. Krabs then gives Squidward and SpongeBob their paychecks. However, Squidward is immediately  and extremely furious to discover that they have actually received bills; Mr. Krabs as part of his plan to make a ''tighter shift'' is charging them for ''all'' non-work activity, including standing, breathing, talking, and even ''existing''. Mr. Krabs says that anytime if he catches them goofing off or doing non-work activities, he will charge them for it. SpongeBob goes along with Mr. Krabs' scheme, and he attempts to give his money back to Mr. Krabs. Squidward convinces SpongeBob that the two of them should go on [[Strike action|strike]] in order to get better benefits and treatment. SpongeBob is happy to go on strike, but he doesn’t even know what that means. He approaches Mr. Krabs and happily tells him that they are going on strike. However, they end up getting fired instead, and SpongeBob is crying excessively while they stand outside of the Krusty Krab.

Squidward angrily tells SpongeBob that they need to go on strike to get their jobs back. Squidward tries to teach SpongeBob how to strike. First, he tells him to throw his hat on the ground and stomp on it, but SpongeBob can’t since he likes the hat. Squidward says he threw his hat on the ground, but he ends up getting a ticket for littering. Squidward then tries to show SpongeBob how to make a [[Picketing (protest)|picket sign]], but SpongeBob keeps getting it wrong. His first attempt at making a picket sign turns out to resemble a [[picket fence]], and his second one shows a person [[Nose-picking|picking his nose]]. He then accidentally makes a sign that says &quot;Krusty Krab is [[funfair|''fun''fair]]&quot; instead of ''un''fair, and a slew of customers run inside for the Krusty Krab &quot;funfair&quot;. Squidward tells SpongeBob that he’s a terrible striker, and he tells SpongeBob to go stand behind a telephone pole. He gets on a [[megaphone]] and [[harangues]] an approaching crowd on the misdeeds of the Krusty Krab, but the audience doesn’t really know what he’s talking about. The crowd decides that their support is making them hungry, and they go eat at the Krusty Krab. Mr. Krabs taunts them over how &quot;successful&quot; their striking is, and this turns SpongeBob against him.

SpongeBob has been finally absorbed by Squidward into the striking cause, but he takes things too far. SpongeBob tells an unconcerned Mr. Krabs that they will stay on strike to get what they deserve even if it takes forever, but the thought of being united with SpongeBob forever frightens Squidward. He realizes he has to end the strike in order to get rid of his alliance with SpongeBob. He goes to rush to the Krusty Krab, but Mr. Krabs is already at Squidward’s door begging him to take his job back since the teenagers he hired to replace him and SpongeBob are driving him crazy. To make matters worse, they won't leave him alone. Realizing he has the upper-hand, Squidward begins negotiating with Mr. Krabs late into the night. However, SpongeBob, not knowing this and thinking that he and Squidward are still on strike, feels the need to impress Squidward by destroying the Krusty Krab — reducing it to a pile of rubble. The next morning, Squidward and Mr. Krabs approach the now-demolished Krusty Krab with SpongeBob still there. But Squidward is shocked instead of impressed (unknown to SpongeBob), and Mr. Krabs doesn’t even realize that the building is destroyed until he makes his way to where his office used to be. Then in anger he falls to pieces. In order to pay off the damages to the Krusty Krab, Mr. Krabs forces them into working for him forever. Squidward is frightened about the fact that he must work at the Krusty Krab (and with SpongeBob) forever, obviously. On the other hand, SpongeBob is excited about this. 

An &quot;eternity&quot; later, SpongeBob and Squidward are still working at the Krusty Krab. They are now animated skeletons.

*Note: A running gag in the episode is that whenever Squidward hears the word &quot;forever&quot;, he is &quot;hypnotized&quot;.
{{-}}

'''Sandy, SpongeBob, and the Worm'''
{{Infobox SpongeBob episode
| Title = Sandy, SpongeBob, and the Worm'''
| Image =  
| Episode = 40b
| Season = 2
| Airdate = October 12, 2001
| Guests = 
| Writer = [[Jay Lender]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Dan Povenmire]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Merriwether Williams]]
|}}

SpongeBob is sound asleep at night when a giant creature rumbles toward him and devours half of his house. When he wakes up, he is frightened to see that he was approached by a fictional Alaskan bull worm, and he alerts the town the next morning. The bull worm is a giant pink worm that has an insatiable appetite towards eating everything. When the citizens are making suggestions on how to get rid of the worm, Patrick says they should push the whole town to another location, but Squidward says that’s a terrible idea. Sandy Cheeks appears and tells the townspeople that she will capture the bull worm, because it ate her tail when she had her back turned. Calling the bull worm a coward, she says she will seek revenge. However, SpongeBob is concerned about Sandy’s safety, and he tries to talk her out of it while the rest of the town cheers for her. In the meantime, they take up Patrick’s idea and move the whole town by pushing it.

Sandy tells SpongeBob that she’s too tough since she’s from [[Texas]] and that SpongeBob is just scared. She insists that she’s going to catch the bull worm, and she pushes her way through a protesting SpongeBob. SpongeBob repeatedly attempts to talk Sandy out of it, but Sandy flat-out refuses to listen to him, positive that she can handle the worm. She goes into what she thinks is a cave where the bull worm is, and a fight ensues off-screen.  Sandy is cheerful that she’s winning, but SpongeBob is trying to tell her that the creature she’s wrangling is really just the worm’s tongue. She ties up the tongue in a knot, but looks up to see the rest of the massive bull worm over her. The Alaskan bull worm starts to chase Sandy and SpongeBob, but SpongeBob is arguing for Sandy to admit that he was right all along, even though they’re inches away from being devoured. She admits that she was wrong, and the two of them manage to jump on top of the bull worm. They continue riding the bull worm in triumph until they realize that it’s headed right off of a cliff.  They jump off of the bull worm just in time before it plunges over the cliff. However, at the bottom of the cliff, the townspeople finally rest the town in its new location after pushing. Just as they do that, the worm falls and crushes the relocated town.

*Note: The entire scene where the townspeople of Bikini Bottom gather in the Krusty Krab to discuss what to do about the Alaskan Bull Worm is a parody of the famous scene in the film Jaws where the townspeople gather to discuss what to do about the shark.
{{-}}

==References==
{{reflist}}

{{SpongeBob SquarePants}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Spongebob Squarepants (Season 2)}}
[[Category:2000 television seasons]]
[[Category:2001 television seasons]]
[[Category:2002 television seasons]]
[[Category:2003 television seasons]]
[[Category:SpongeBob SquarePants]]

[[id:SpongeBob SquarePants (musim ke-2)]]
[[it:Spongebob stagione 2]]
[[nl:Lijst van afleveringen van SpongeBob SquarePants (seizoen 2)]]
[[ru:Второй сезон мультсериала «Губка Боб Квадратные Штаны»]]
[[tl:Talaan ng mga kabanata ng SpongeBob SquarePants (ika-2 kapanahunan)]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
