<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="14200152" ns="0" title="DCC Alliance"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{distinguish|Linux Core Consortium}}  
The '''DCC Alliance''' ('''DCCA''') was an industry association designed to promote a common subset of the [[Debian]] GNU/Linux operating system that multiple companies within the consortium could distribute.

==History==

The main force behind the DCC Alliance was [[Ian Murdock]], the original founder of the Debian project.  The DCC Alliance was formed whilst Murdock was CEO of Progeny Linux Systems, and he remained the key spokesperson for the consortium during their visible existence.  The founding of the DCC Alliance was announced at [[LinuxWorld]] [[San Francisco]] on the 9 August 2005, following a number of pre-announcements.

The stated intention was to assemble a standards-based core of Debian, provide a predictable release cycle and [[Linux Standards Base]] compliance.&lt;ref&gt;ZDNet News,  [http://news.zdnet.co.uk/software/0,1000000121,39210798,00.htm Consortium to push Debian to the fore], 2005-07-26.&lt;/ref&gt;

DCC Alliance shipped their first code 6 months after the original pre-announcements, providing a Linux Standards Base (LSB) 3.0 compliant set of program packages based on those available from Debian.&lt;ref&gt;Eweek, [http://www.eweek.com/article2/0,1759,1898116,00.asp DCC Alliance Leads Way to Linux Standard Base 3.0 Compliance], 2005-12-08.&lt;/ref&gt;

The Alliance's primary goals were to:{{Fact|date=November 2007}}
*Assemble a 100 percent Debian common core that addresses the needs of enterprise business users
*Maintain certification of the common core with the [[Free Standards Group]] open specification, the [[Linux Standard Base]]
*Use the Alliance's combined strength to accelerate the commercial adoption of Debian
*Work with the Debian project to ensure predictable release cycles and features important to commercial adoption

==Membership==

There were two classes of membership in the DCC Alliance:
*'''Members''', those organisation creating products based on the DCC-provided core subset of packages.
:* [[Knoppix]], [[LinEx]], [[Linspire]], [[MEPIS]], [[Progeny Linux Systems|Progeny]], [[Sunwah - PearL Linux|Sun Wah Linux]], [[Xandros]]
*'''Associate Members''', [[Independent software vendor]]s, [[Independent hardware vendor|hardware vendors]], [[Original equipment manufacturer|OEM]]s and community partners providing related support or business.
:* credativ, [[Skolelinux]], [[UserLinux]]

Membership remained open to additional organizations with an interest in Debian-based solutions.  The most visible absent from any involvement was the [[Ubuntu (operating system)|Ubuntu]] distribution who declined to join the Alliance.{{Fact|date=October 2008}} The Ubuntu founder, Mark Shuttleworth, stated in 2006 that he did not believe that the DCC Alliance had any future.&lt;ref&gt;Ubuntu &quot;Sounder&quot; mailing list [https://lists.ubuntu.com/archives/sounder/2006-January/003630.html Mark Shuttleworth: Debian Common Core Alliance] [sic], 2006-01-03.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Linux-Watch, [http://www.linux-watch.com/news/NS8432548714.html Debian, Ubuntu, and the DCC, oh my!], 2006-01-05.&lt;/ref&gt;

One of the founding members, [[MEPIS]], later left the DCCA, citing &quot;creative differences&quot;.  MEPIS transitioned their SimplyMEPIS Linux distribution from a Debian Unstable/DCCA-provided core to an [[Ubuntu Linux|Ubuntu]]-based one.&lt;ref&gt;Desktop Linux, [http://www.desktoplinux.com/news/NS6045116609.html MEPIS founder plots transition to Ubuntu], 2006-03-21.&lt;/ref&gt;{{Fact|reason=When did SimplyMEPIS use a DCCA-provided core?|date=October 2008}}

In 2006 [[Ian Murdock]] left the DCC Alliance to chair the [[Linux Standard Base]] workgroup&lt;ref&gt;Linux-Watch, [http://www.linux-watch.com/news/NS4876054750.html Debian founder takes over LSB leadership], 2006-02-02.&lt;/ref&gt; and later moved his employment to [[Sun Microsystems]].&lt;ref&gt;CNET News.com, [http://www.news.com/2100-7344_3-6168567.html Sun hires Debian Linux founder], 2007-03-19.&lt;/ref&gt; In 2007, [[Progeny Linux Systems|Progeny]], the original driver behind the consortium was wound up.&lt;ref&gt;Linux.com, [http://www.linux.com/feature/114289 Progeny Linux ceases operation], 2007-05-02.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Linux Journal, [http://www.linuxjournal.com/node/1000223 Remembering Progeny], 2007-05-17.&lt;/ref&gt;  In 2006, Xandros was still claiming that Xandros &quot;leads the engineering team at the DCCA&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.xandros.com/partners/pik.pdf Xandros Partner Information Kit], published 2006.&lt;/ref&gt;

==Naming controversy==
When originally formed, the names given to the media were that of the &quot;''Debian Core Consortium''&quot;, and then &quot;''Debian Common Core''&quot;.  Following [[trademark]] notification from the Debian project, the name was withdrawn and replaced—without a formal announcement—by &quot;''DCC Alliance''&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;Linux.com, [http://www.linux.com/feature/49084 Ian Murdock responds to Debian-DCC Alliance trademark dispute], 2005-10-09.&lt;/ref&gt; Ian Murdock explained that the ''D'' should no longer be treated as an [[abbreviation]] of ''Debian'', but of ''DCC''—becoming a [[recursive acronym]] for &quot;''&lt;u&gt;D&lt;/u&gt;CC &lt;u&gt;C&lt;/u&gt;ommon &lt;u&gt;C&lt;/u&gt;ore''&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;[[Ian Murdock]], blog: [http://ianmurdock.com/?p=274 What’s in a name?], 2005-10-05.&lt;/ref&gt;  The trademark decision is notable:

* The &quot;Debian&quot; trademark that was being denied to Mr. Murdock and the DCC Alliance originates from a combination of the ''-ian'' part of Mr. Murdock's own [[given name]], [[concatenation|concatenated]] to that of his wife's name; Debra Murdock.  
* The decision over the infringement of the trademark fell to the then [[Debian Project Leader]] (DPL).
* The DPL at the time was [[Branden Robinson]], an employee of [[Progeny Linux Systems]] (and of Mr. Murdock) during the time at which the decision was made.  Mr. Robinson stated that this would not represent a [[conflict of interest]].&lt;ref&gt;[[Software in the Public Interest|SPI]] (Legal owner of Debian trademark) [http://www.spi-inc.org/corporate/meeting-minutes/2005/board-meeting-august-16th-2005.html Board Meeting, August 16th, 2005], &quot;Debian Core Consortium issues&quot;.&lt;/ref&gt;

==References==
{{reflist}}

{{Debian}}

[[Category:Debian]]
[[Category:Linux organizations]]

[[de:DCC Alliance]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
