<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="1422095" ns="0" title="The Junkies"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Infobox Radio Show
| show_name          = The Sports Junkies
| image              =
| imagesize          = 
| caption            = The Sports Junkies
| format             = Talk, Sports
| runtime            = Monday through Friday 5 am to 10 am
| creator            = 
| writer             = 
| producer          = Bret Oliverio&lt;br&gt;Matt Myers
| starring           = John Martin “Cakes” Auville&lt;br&gt;Eric Carlton “E.B.” Bickel&lt;br&gt;Jason William “Lurch” Bishop&lt;br&gt;John-Paul “J.P.” Flaim
| opentheme          = 
| endtheme           = 
| country            = {{USA}}
| first_aired        = 1996
| last_aired         = present
| num_episodes       = 
| website            = [http://www.junks.tv Junks.TV]
| home_station       = [[WJFK-FM]]
| podcast	     = [http://itunes.apple.com/podcast/the-sports-junkies/id367825854 Podcasts]
}}

'''The Sports Junkies''', also known as '''The Junkies''', are the hosts of an eponymous [[morning drive]] time radio show aired in the [[Baltimore-Washington Metropolitan Area]]. The hosts are John Auville, Eric Bickel, Jason Bishop and John-Paul Flaim. Their show is heard on [[WJFK-FM]], at 106.7 on the FM radio dial. Their show focuses on a mix of discussions about sports, women, [[popular culture]], and the day-to-day lives of the Junkies.

The show debuted at #100 in the 2008 edition of [[Talkers Magazine Heavy 100]], moved up to #84 in the 2009 edition&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news | first= | last= | coauthors= | title=Talkers 2008 Heavy 100 | date= | publisher= | url =http://66.227.50.219/main/index.php?option=com_content&amp;task=view&amp;id=19&amp;Itemid=44 | work = | pages = | accessdate = 2008-02-13 | language = }}&lt;/ref&gt; and most recently #75 in the 2010 edition.&lt;ref&gt;http://talkers.com/online/?p=3774&lt;/ref&gt;

==On-air hosts==
===John Martin “Cakes” Auville===
Known as “Cakes,” Auville was born in 1970 and adopted by his parents  at five weeks old.&lt;ref name=&quot;wp01&quot;&gt;[http://www.washingtonpost.com/wp-dyn/content/article/2006/02/21/AR2006022101409_pf.html ''The Washington Post Magazine'' cover article (02/26/2006)]&lt;/ref&gt; He was raised in  [[Bowie, Maryland|Bowie]], [[Maryland]] alongside fellow Junkies Eric Bickel and John-Paul Flaim, and attended [[Eleanor Roosevelt High School (Maryland)|Eleanor Roosevelt High School]] in [[Greenbelt, Maryland|Greenbelt]], Maryland.  After high school, Auville studied communications at [[Towson University]] in [[Baltimore, Maryland|Baltimore]], Maryland, about which he is occasionally ridiculed for achieving a 1.5 GPA one semester;&lt;ref name=&quot;wp01&quot;/&gt; he then managed a local [[Toys R Us|Toys Я Us]] store until making radio his full-time occupation in 1996.&lt;ref name=&quot;jw01&quot;&gt;[http://www.junkiesradio.com The Junkies Official Web Site]&lt;/ref&gt; Auville's family currently lives in [[Olney, Maryland|Olney]], Maryland. He married his wife, Amy, in 1995.  They have three children, Kurt Joseph (1997), Juliet (2002), and Brendan Craig (2004). After the birth of their third child, Auville had a [[vasectomy]] and has since been mocked with the name “Johnny Blanks.”&lt;ref name=&quot;jw01&quot;/&gt;

===Eric Carlton “E.B.” Bickel===
Bickel was born in 1970 and grew up in Bowie, Maryland where he grew up across the street from fellow Junkie John-Paul Flaim and in the same neighborhood as John Auville.  Bickel attended [[DeMatha Catholic High School]] in [[Hyattsville, Maryland|Hyattsville]], Maryland, where he befriended soon-to-be-Junkie Jason Bishop.  He lettered in tennis. After high school, Bickel attended the [[University of Maryland, College Park|University of Maryland]], where he majored in [[psychology]], worked as a study hall monitor, and received his master’s degree in school counseling before becoming a &quot;Junkie&quot; in 1997. Bickel married his wife, Dina, in 1996.  They have three children, Stephen (2000), Megan (2002) and Katherine (2009).&lt;ref name=&quot;wp01&quot;/&gt; Bickel's [[schtick]] includes a combustible personality, a hair-trigger temper a a penchant for botching  clichés.{{Fact|date=November 2011}}

===Jason William “Lurch Poppa” Bishop===
Nicknamed &quot;[[Lurch]]&quot; because of his 6'6&quot; height (an allusion to the [[Frankenstein]]-like butler on the television show “[[The Addams Family (TV series)|The Addams Family]]”), Bishop grew up in [[Lanham, Maryland]] and befriended fellow Junkie Eric Bickel while attending DeMatha Catholic High School in Hyattsville, Maryland, where he played [[basketball]]. Bishop went on to play basketball at the [[University of Richmond]], where he received a scholarship but struggled to make his morning classes and after failing out, transferred to [[Salisbury State University]] the following year to pursue a degree in communications.&lt;ref name=&quot;jw01&quot;/&gt;  He currently lives in [[Ashburn, Virginia|Ashburn]], Virginia with his wife Teresa and their two daughters, and has a second home in [[Ocean City, MD]] where he enjoys body surfing, volleyball, watching Red Sox highlights, and angling.

===John-Paul “J.P.” Flaim===
Simply known as “J.P.,” Flaim was born in 1970 and grew up across the street from fellow Junkie Eric Bickel in Bowie, Maryland.  Flaim attended Eleanor Roosevelt High School in Greenbelt, Maryland, and then went on to major in [[international business]] at the University of Maryland, College Park before studying law at the [[Temple University Beasley School of Law]] in [[Philadelphia, Pennsylvania|Philadelphia]], [[Pennsylvania]].&lt;ref name=&quot;wp01&quot;/&gt;   In 1997, Flaim failed the Maryland [[bar exam]], reading his results publicly while on the air; however, he passed the exam the following year and can now legally practice law in Maryland.&lt;ref name=&quot;jw01&quot;/&gt;

Flaim has also fought as a professional middleweight boxer. His record is 0-1, having lost his December 9, 2006 debut fight to Jay Watts by [[Technical Knockout|TKO]] in the first round, just days after the death of Flaim's father-in-law.&lt;ref name=&quot;wpjpfight&quot;&gt;[http://www.washingtonpost.com/wp-dyn/content/article/2006/12/10/AR2006121000902.html  &quot;Glass Jaw Is Half Empty&quot; ''The Washington Post'' article (12/11/2006)]&lt;/ref&gt; In 2007, he was ranked 991st out of the top 999 boxers in the light middleweight division.&lt;ref name=&quot;boxrec&quot;&gt;[http://www.boxrec.com/boxer_display.php?boxer_id=377751 BoxRec.com  Retrieved on 06/30/2007]&lt;/ref&gt;  J.P.'s performance in his professional debut earned him the nickname [[Glass Joe]].{{Citation needed|date=October 2007}}. 

Flaim and his ex-wife (Carol) have two children together, a daughter Kelsie (2000),&lt;ref name=&quot;wp01&quot;/&gt; and a son, Dylan Carlos (2007).{{Citation needed|date=November 2009}}. As of June 6, 2011, J.P. is engaged to his fiancee Jessica, a professional fitness model and former [[Washington Redskins]]' [[Cheerleader]].

==Other show staffers==

*'''Executive Producer Bret Oliverio''': joined the show as an intern when he was 18. He attended [[Lake Braddock Secondary School]] and graduated from [[James Madison University]] and loves water sports. He is an expert in horseback riding, scuba diving, and above torso photography.  He won $50,000 while participating in the [[Bodog]]'s [[Calvin Ayre]] Wild Card Poker tournament in 2006.&lt;ref name=&quot;bretpoker01&quot;&gt;[http://web.archive.org/web/20070408055235/http://www.bodognation.com/celebrity-gossip/from-underdog-to-shark.html Bret Oliverio Takes Home the Win in Episode 2 of Calvin Ayre Wild Card Poker (04/18/2006). Archived from the original on 04/08/2007. Retrieved on 06/30/2007]&lt;/ref&gt; 

*'''Associate Producer Matt Myers (aka Matt Valdez)''': named show producer in July 2009. Grew up in [[Pasadena, Maryland]] and graduated summa cum laude from the [[University of Maryland]] with a degree in journalism. He is the show historian.

*'''Kevin &quot;BDK&quot; McCarthy''' Reviews movies weekly on the show as well as on his personal site and local Fox affiliate [[WTTG]]. He suffers from [[obsessive compulsive disorder]].

*'''Former Executive Producer Chris Kinard (a.k.a. CK):''' Has been with the show since 1998 as an intern, named producer in 1999. He moved with the show to WHFS in 2002, and back to WJFK in 2005. Kinard grew up in [[Fairfax Station, VA]] and attended [[Lake Braddock Secondary School]] and [[American University]].&lt;ref name=&quot;jw01&quot;/&gt;  He is WJFK's Program Director and relinquished his producing duties after the station's format change in July 2009.&lt;ref name=&quot;jw01&quot;&gt;[http://www.wjfk.com/pages/287693.php WJFK Official Web Site, &quot;TalkBack to 106.7 WJFK&quot;]&lt;/ref&gt;

*'''Current Fall 2011 Show Intern - Irina Divinsky:''' Started with the show in October 2011, majors in kinesiology, born in Kiev, Ukraine, fluent in Russian, competitive snowboarder and previously hosted a snowboarding segment in Colorado for Louisiana Action Sports Channel. She is an aspiring NFL agent and will be taking her NFLPA exam this July 2012, following a failed attempt to take it last year, July 2011, due to the NFL lockout.

==History==
Auville, Bickel, and Flaim grew up as friends in Bowie, Maryland. Auville and Flaim attended Eleanor Roosevelt High School; at the same time, Bickel met Bishop at DeMatha Catholic High School. Bickel and Flaim also attended the University of Maryland together.  After graduating from college, the foursome and other friends hung out and often shared living quarters. In 1995, the four began their broadcasting career as a hobby with a 30-minute [[Public-access television]] [[cable TV]] show in Bowie featuring sports chat and irreverent humor.

The show focused on the interplay of the foursome, featuring guests such as [[Playboy]] models, rock notables, and local sports celebrities such as University of Maryland basketball coach [[Gary Williams]].  Their high local ratings lead to their national debut on May 18, 1999, airing on about 50 affiliates of [[Westwood One]]'s radio network.&lt;ref name=&quot;ss61999&quot;&gt;[http://www.junksweb.com/news/EEVkupZZVEUrBMqOug.shtml &quot;Called up to 'The Show'&quot; ''Street &amp; Smith's Sports Business Journal'' article (06/07/21999)]&lt;/ref&gt;  That syndication was short-lived, however. {{Citation needed|date=March 2008}}

Through the show's history it occupied a night slot from 7-11 p.m. and 8-midnight from mid-2001 until early 2002.  In October 2002, the show moved from WJFK to [[WHFS]] during the morning drive time slot.&lt;ref name=&quot;jw01&quot;/&gt; When WHFS changed formats from alternative rock to Spanish-language, the show returned to WJFK-FM in a lunchtime spot.  In 2006, the Junkies' show returned to the morning drive, replacing ''[[The Howard Stern Show]]'' when it ended its run on terrestrial radio.

==Events==
* '''Junkies Poker Open'''
The Junkies have sponsored a semi-annual &quot;Junkie Poker Open&quot; event at the [[Borgata]] casino in [[Atlantic City, New Jersey]].  The [[Texas hold'em]] poker tournament has gained some notoriety as former [[World Series of Poker]] contestants (Lee Childs, among others) have participated in the events.

{| class=&quot;wikitable&quot;
|-

! Event

! Location

! Date

! # of Players

! Purse

! Winner
|-
| JPO 1
| Borgata Hotel Casino
| November 30, 2006
| 300
| ≈$28,000
| Derrick Childress
|-
| JPO 2
| Borgata Hotel Casino
| May ??, 2007
| ≈420
| ≈$32,000
| Gary Heffner
|-
| JPO 3
| Borgata Hotel Casino
| November 29, 2007
| 365 
| ≈$28,000
| Andrew Phillips
|-
| JPO 4
| Borgata Hotel Casino
| May 29, 2008
| 310
| $29,934
| Al from Brooklyn + 10 Player [[Chopping the blinds|Chop]]
|-
| JPO 5
| Borgata Hotel Casino
| November 13, 2008
| 535
| $39,000
| Scotty Baggs + [[Chopping the blinds|Chop]]
|-
| JPO 6
| Borgata Hotel Casino
| May 21, 2009
| 
| 
| 
|-
| JPO 7
| Borgata Hotel Casino
| November 12, 2009
| 597
| ≈$23,000
|Matt Stohlman + 7 player [[Chopping the blinds|Chop]]
|-
| JPO 8
| Borgata Hotel Casino
| May 20, 2010
| 
| ≈$25,000
|&quot;O&quot;
|-
| JPO 9
| Borgata Hotel Casino
| November 11, 2010
| 714
| $142,000
|
|}

* '''Unauthorized Redskins Pre-Game Show'''
Since the 2004 season, the Junkies have hosted a two-hour pregame show prior to the kick-off of each Washington Redskins game. The show is broadcast live from a Washington area restaurant or bar and airs on [[WJFK-FM]].  The show is considered &quot;unauthorized&quot; because they have continued doing the program even though WJFK no longer holds the rights to broadcast the team's games.

* '''Upersay Owlbay Party'''
The Junkies host a party for the [[NFL]] championship game at a Washington area restaurant or bar.  The name is based on a [[Pig Latin]] version of the phrase &quot;super bowl&quot; due to the NFL's [[Super_Bowl#NFL_trademark_issues|active pursuit of trademark issues with the Super Bowl name]].

* '''Junkies' Spring Break Party'''
An annual spring break themed party held at the State Theater in [[Falls Church, Virginia]].

* '''Sundress Sillies Party'''
First held in 2008, the Junkies host an annual end-of-summer party at the Backyard Bar &amp; Grille in [[Chantilly, Virginia]]. Women are encouraged to attend wearing a [[sundress]].  They also promote a &quot;V.I.P. section&quot; for women who do not wear underwear, but do not actively check to verify &quot;V.I.P.&quot; eligibility.

As of 2011 the Junkies were forced to change the name of the part to &quot;Summer Dress Party&quot; due to trademark issues with an undisclosed company.

==Controversy==
An interview with tennis player [[Justin Gimelstob]] made international headlines because of comments Gimelstob made about [[Anna Kournikova]] and other female tennis players. Gimelstob was reprimanded by his employer, [[Tennis Channel]], and made a donation to the Women's Sports Foundation as a result of the incident.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.timesonline.co.uk/tol/sport/tennis/article4228384.ece Fault! Tennis star's sexist attack on Anna Kournikova was way over the line], ''The Times'', June 27, 2008&lt;/ref&gt;

==References==
{{reflist}}

==External links==
*[http://junks.tv/ Official Site]
*[http://1067thefandc.cbslocal.com/shows/the-sports-junkies/ Show Page on 1067 the Fan]
*{{MySpace|junkiesradio4}}
*[http://www.washingtonpost.com/wp-dyn/content/article/2006/02/21/AR2006022101409_pf.html ''The Washington Post Magazine'' cover article (02/26/2006)]
*[http://www.junkscast.com/ Junkscast.com - The Sports Junkies Podcast Segment Archive]

{{DEFAULTSORT:Junkies, The}}
[[Category:American radio personalities]]
[[Category:American comedy radio programs]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
