<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="14253599" ns="0" title="Louisville–West Virginia rivalry"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{| class=&quot;infobox&quot; style=&quot;width: 26em; font-size: 95%;&quot;
|-
| colspan=&quot;2&quot; style=&quot;text-align: center; font-size: 110%;&quot; | '''Louisville–West Virginia rivalry'''
|-
| align=&quot;center&quot; colspan=&quot;2&quot; |
|-
| '''Teams''' &lt;!-- In alphabetical order --&gt;
| [[Louisville Cardinals]]&lt;br&gt;[[West Virginia Mountaineers]]
|-
| '''Basketball Series'''
| Louisville leads (8–4)
|-
| '''Last Winner'''
| West Virginia &lt;small&gt;(2011)&lt;/small&gt;
|-
| '''Football Series'''
| West Virginia leads (10–3)
|-
| '''Last Winner'''
| Louisville &lt;small&gt;(2011)&lt;/small&gt;
|-
| colspan=&quot;2&quot; align=&quot;center&quot;| &lt;hr&gt;
|-
| align=&quot;center&quot; style=&quot;width:13em&quot; | [[File:Louisville scipt L logo.png|85px]]
| align=&quot;center&quot; style=&quot;width:13em&quot; | [[Image:West Virginia Flying WV logo.svg|85px]]
|- 
| align=&quot;center&quot; | '''Louisville'''
| align=&quot;center&quot; | '''West Virginia'''
|}
The '''Louisville–West Virginia rivalry''' is a new rivalry [[American football|football]] game between the [[University of Louisville]] and [[West Virginia University]]. The rivalry was introduced in 2005, as Louisville left [[Conference USA]] and moved into the [[Big East]] conference. Since then, it has become a marquee matchup in Big East football and basketball.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.wvustats.com/mbasketball/opp.php?team_id=308&amp;opp_id=144 WVU Series Record vs. Louisville&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;

West Virginia leads the current football series 5–2, and the all-time football series 10–3&lt;ref name=&quot;one&quot;&gt;[http://www.wvustats.com/football/opp.php?team_id=308&amp;opp_id=144 WVU Series Record vs. Louisville&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt; while Louisville leads the current basketball series 5–2, and the all-time basketball series 8–3.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.wvustats.com/mbasketball/opp.php?team_id=308&amp;opp_id=144&lt;/ref&gt;

==Football==
===History===
====Pre-rivalry====
The Mountaineers and Cardinals first met on a football field in 1984.&lt;ref name=&quot;one&quot; /&gt; In that game, the Cardinals were defeated at [[Mountaineer Field]] in [[Morgantown, West Virginia|Morgantown]] by a score of 30–6. The next year, 1985, the Mountaineers again defeated Louisville, this time by a score of 52–13, in front of 62,000 fans in Morgantown. In 1986, the first game was played in [[Louisville, Kentucky|Louisville]], but the Mountaineers won for the third-straight time, 42-19.

In 1989, the #9 Mountaineers came into Louisville to fans who were calling the game the &quot;Game of the Century.&quot;  Louisville legend [[Johnny Unitas]] and West Virginia legend [[Sam Huff]] were brought in on helicopter to watch the ceremonial coin toss in front of a [[CBS]]-televised audience. The Cardinals were winning the game going into the fourth quarter, before the Mountaineers rolled off 17 unanswered fourth-quarter points to win the game, 30-21.&lt;ref name=&quot;msn&quot;&gt;[http://www.msnsportsnet.com/page.cfm?story=10002&amp;cat=exclusives MSNsportsNET.Com - West Virginia University Mountaineers&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;

In 1990, the Mountaineers suffered their first loss to the Cardinals. In Morgantown, the Mountaineers fell to Louisville, 9–7.&lt;ref name=&quot;one&quot; /&gt; The game was hailed as &quot;The Rematch&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;Mountaineer Illustrated&lt;/ref&gt;{{Verify source|date=January 2008}} In 1993, the Mountaineers were down 21–10 going into the fourth quarter. The Mountaineers used Louisville turnovers to then come back and win by a score of 36–34.

====Early rivalry====
In 2005, the [[Big East Conference]] opened its season with the arrival of three teams from the [[Conference USA]]: [[University of Louisville|Louisville]], [[University of Cincinnati|Cincinnati]], and [[USF|South Florida]]. Louisville entered the season behind [[Heisman]] candidates [[Brian Brohm]] and [[Michael Bush]]. West Virginia entered the season with a young team. The Mountaineers lost early to [[Virginia Tech]], but rallied behind freshman [[Patrick White (American football)|Pat White]] and [[Steve Slaton]] to have a 5–1 record for the matchup, while Louisville entered with a 4–1 record after being upset by South Florida. In the game, Louisville held a 24–7 record going into the fourth quarter. The Mountaineers rallied behind Slaton and scored three consecutive times to tie the game 24–24. The game went into three overtimes, and the Mountaineers held a 46–44 lead after Louisville scored a touchdown. Brohm tried to run on the ensuing 2-point conversion, but was tackled short of the endzone by [[Eric Wicks]] to win the game, 46-44, for the Mountaineers. Slaton scored a Big East record six times in this game, cementing his place in West Virginia lore. Controversy surrounded this game due to an onside kick in the fourth quarter by West Virginia, which fans determined was illegal. The Big East apologized for missing the call after the game.&lt;ref&gt;[http://sports.espn.go.com/ncf/news/story?id=2195722 ESPN - Big East: Officials missed call in WVU-Louisville game - College Football&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt; The Mountaineers won the Big East championship and upset the [[Georgia Bulldogs]] in the [[Sugar Bowl]], 38–35. Louisville lost to Virginia Tech in the [[Gator Bowl]], 35–24.

In 2006, the Mountaineers and Cardinals entered the game undefeated. The Mountaineers were ranked #3, while the Cardinals were ranked #5. The game ended with a 44–34 score in the Cardinals' biggest win in school history.&lt;ref name=&quot;two&quot;&gt;[http://sports.espn.go.com/ncf/recap?gameId=263060097 ESPN - Louisville slugs West Virginia to jump ahead in BCS race - NCAA College Football Recap&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt; The Cardinals entered the game without Michael Bush, but relied on the arm of Brian Brohm and their defense to win the shootout. The Mountaineers committed three turnovers and the Cardinals took a punt and fumble back for touchdowns. Slaton ran for 156 yards and a score, but fumbled twice, and White threw for 222 yards and ran for 125 yards and 4 touchdowns. But Brohm was the star, as he threw for 354 yards and a touchdown against the poor Mountaineers' secondary.&lt;ref name=&quot;two&quot; /&gt; The game set a new [[Big East]] record with 1,008 total yards in the game.&lt;ref name=&quot;two&quot; /&gt; The Cardinals won the Big East crown and won in the [[Orange Bowl (game)|Orange Bowl]] against the [[Atlantic Coast Conference|ACC]] champs, [[Wake Forest University|Wake Forest]]. The Mountaineers earned runner-up status in conference play and won in the [[Gator Bowl]] against [[2006 Georgia Tech Yellow Jackets football team|Georgia Tech]], 38–35.

In 2007, the #7 Mountaineers entered the match-up with a 7–1 record after losing to South Florida, who after the win was ranked #2 in the nation before losing three games in a row. The Cardinals entered the season with a new head coach, [[Steve Kragthorpe]], and entered the game with a disappointing 5-4 record after an early season loss to [[University of Syracuse|Syracuse]]. The Cardinals, however, still had [[Brian Brohm]], while Slaton and White were still juniors for the Mountaineers. The game looked good for the Mountaineers, who jumped out to an early 21–7 lead. However, Brohm had a one-yard touchdown run to make the score 21–14 at halftime. The Mountaineers added a field goal, and then forced Brohm to fumble on a sack that safety [[Eric Wicks]] took 44 yards for a score to make the game 31–14. The Cardinals answered with three straight scores - two touchdowns and a field goal - to make it 31–31 with 3:05 left in the game. However, freshman running back [[Noel Devine]] returned a kickoff for 41 yards, which led to Patrick White's 50-yard game-winning touchdown run.&lt;ref&gt;[http://sports.espn.go.com/ncf/boxscore?gameId=273120277 ESPN - Louisville Cardinals vs. West Virginia Mountaineers Box Score, November 8, 2007 - NCAA College Football&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt; West Virginia kicker [[Pat McAfee]] booted the ensuing kickoff down to the one-yard line as it rolled between the Cardinals' returners' legs, which sealed the 38–31 win. White racked up 328 total yards and 3 touchdowns, even though fumbling twice, while Slaton was held to 60 yards and a touchdown on 17 carries. Brohm had 345 yards and 3 touchdowns through the air, and a rushing touchdown, as he tried to lead the Cardinals to a comeback win.

In the 2006 matchup, the Louisville Cardinals announced that the game would be &quot;Black Out Thursday&quot;. The Louisville fans showed up at the game in all-black, and the Cardinals' uniforms were black alternates. Additionally, in that game, the stadium lights on the east side of the stadium went out, causing a &quot;black out&quot;. In 2007, the Mountaineers announced that the game would be a &quot;Gold Rush&quot;, returning the favor. The Mountaineers sported all-gold uniforms.&lt;ref name=&quot;msn&quot; /&gt;

==Game results==
''Louisville victories shaded in &lt;font color=&quot;#FF2533&quot;&gt;■&lt;/font&gt; red. West Virginia victories are shaded &lt;font color=&quot;#003366&quot;&gt;■&lt;/font&gt; blue. ''
''Games before the game was officially considered a rivalry are annoted with * by the date.''

{| class=&quot;wikitable&quot;
!bgcolor=&quot;#e5e5e5&quot;| Year !! colspan=&quot;2&quot; bgcolor=&quot;#e5e5e5&quot;| Winning Team !! colspan=&quot;2&quot; bgcolor=&quot;#e5e5e5&quot;| Losing Team !! bgcolor=&quot;#e5e5e5&quot; | Site !! bgcolor=&quot;#e5e5e5&quot; | Series
|-align=center style=&quot;background: #003366; color: #FFCC00&quot;
| 1984* || '''West Virginia''' || '''30''' || Louisville || 6 || Morgantown, WV || WVU 1–0
|-align=center style=&quot;background: #003366; color: #FFCC00&quot;
| 1985* || '''West Virginia''' || '''52''' || Louisville || 13 || Morgantown, WV || WVU 2–0
|-align=center style=&quot;background: #003366; color: #FFCC00&quot;
| 1986* || '''West Virginia''' || '''42''' || Louisville || 19 || Louisville, KY || WVU 3–0
|-align=center style=&quot;background: #003366; color: #FFCC00&quot;
| 1989* || '''West Virginia''' || '''30''' || Louisville || 21 || Louisville, KY || WVU 4–0
|-align=center style=&quot;background: #FF2533; color: #FFFFFF&quot;
| 1990* || '''Louisville''' || '''9''' || West Virginia || 7 || Morgantown, WV || WVU 4–1
|-align=center style=&quot;background: #003366; color: #FFCC00&quot;
| 1993* || '''West Virginia''' || '''36''' || Louisville || 34 || Morgantown, WV || WVU 5–1
|-align=center style=&quot;background: #003366; color: #FFCC00&quot;
| 2005 || '''West Virginia''' || '''46''' || Louisville || 44 || Morgantown, WV || WVU 6–1
|-align=center style=&quot;background: #FF2533; color: #FFFFFF&quot;
| 2006 || '''Louisville''' || '''44''' || West Virginia || 34 || Louisville, KY || WVU 6–2
|-align=center style=&quot;background: #003366; color: #FFCC00&quot;
| 2007 || '''West Virginia''' || '''38''' || Louisville || 31 || Morgantown, WV || WVU 7–2
|-align=center style=&quot;background: #003366; color: #FFCC00&quot;
| 2008 || '''West Virginia''' || '''35''' || Louisville || 21 || Louisville, KY || WVU 8–2
|-align=center style=&quot;background: #003366; color: #FFCC00&quot;
| 2009 || '''West Virginia''' || '''17''' || Louisville || 9 || Morgantown, WV || WVU 9–2
|-align=center style=&quot;background: #003366; color: #FFCC00&quot;
| 2010 || '''West Virginia''' || '''17''' || Louisville || 10 || Louisville, KY || WVU 10–2
|-align=center style=&quot;background: #FF2533; color: #FFFFFF&quot;
| 2011 || '''Louisville''' || '''38''' || West Virginia || 35 || Morgantown, WV || WVU 10–3
|}

==Basketball==
===History===
West Virginia and Louisville first met on a basketball court in 1959, in which the Mountaineers picked up a 94–79 victory with [[Jerry West]] and [[Willie Akers]]. The two teams next met in 1978, 19 years later, in which Louisville picked up a 106–60 victory in [[Louisville, Kentucky]]. Two years later, 1980, the Mountaineers were defeated to the score of 90–78 in [[West Virginia]]. In the 2005 [[2005 NCAA Men's Division I Basketball Tournament|NCAA Tournament]], the two teams met in the Elite 8 matchup, West Virginia was up by 18 at half time, but  in the second half Louisville came back and the game went to over time.Louisville pulled away in overtime with a 93–85 victory on their way to a Final Four run.

The teams regularly met after the 2005 tournament game due to  the [[Big East Conference]] and [[Conference USA]] re-alignments, in which Louisville became part of the Big East with West Virginia. The teams' first conference matchup was the 2006 game in West Virginia, in which West Virginia won 86–84. The two teams then met in the Big East Tournament in 2007, with Louisville taking the game 82–71. Louisville also won the 2008 matchup in [[Kentucky]], 63–54. In January of the 2009, the two teams met up in Kentucky, in which Louisville won 69–63. Two months later, Louisville defeated the Mountaineers 62–59 in [[Morgantown, West Virginia]] in front of a record-crowd for [[College GameDay (basketball)|College GameDay]]. On January 30, 2010, the 9th ranked Mountaineers and Cardinals met in Morgantown with a 77–74 West Virginia win.

==References==
{{Reflist}}

{{Louisville Cardinals football navbox}}
{{West Virginia Mountaineers football navbox}}

{{Use mdy dates|date=August 2010}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Louisville–West Virginia Rivalry}}
[[Category:College football rivalries in the United States]]
[[Category:Louisville Cardinals football]]
[[Category:West Virginia Mountaineers football]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
