<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><redirects><r from="List of characters in 2003 Strawberry Shortcake" to="List of Strawberry Shortcake characters" tofragment="2003" /></redirects><pages><page pageid="18203902" ns="0" title="List of Strawberry Shortcake characters"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">This is a '''list of ''[[Strawberry Shortcake]]'' characters'''. The original ''Strawberry Shortcake'' characters were created in the 1980s. In 2003, they were reimagined only to be reimagined once again in 2009.
{{TOCright}}
==1980s==
===Strawberry Shortcake===
Strawberry Shortcake is the [[protagonist]] and the title character of the ''Strawberry Shortcake'' franchise. She is a bright and energetic little girl with red hair and freckles, said to be about six years old. She usually wears a red dress with a white pinafore, and a large pink bonnet decorated with strawberries. In her earliest adventures, Strawberry's home was a [[shortcake]] surrounded by well-tended strawberry vines, but in 1983 she moved into her &quot;Berry Happy Home&quot;, a large and ornate mansion. Strawberry is kind, resourceful, and always ready to help a friend in need. Huckleberry Pie, Blueberry Muffin, Raspberry Tart, Orange Blossom, Plum Puddin' and Lemon Meringue are her best friends. Other than her friends, Strawberry Shortcake also loves her cat, Custard.

===Huckleberry Pie===
Huckleberry Pie is one of Strawberry Shortcake's friends, who lives, not surprisingly, in a large Huckleberry Pie-shaped cabin, just down the road from Strawberry Shortcake's house. The obvious inspiration for his character was [[Mark Twain]]'s literary creation [[Huckleberry Finn (character)|Huckleberry Finn]]. Huck bore more than a passing resemblance to the more famous Huck Finn, from his straw hat and overalls to his tendencies towards fishing and general [[laziness]]. Huckleberry Pie was, for the most part, the sole boy character in a female-dominated franchise, a condition that prevails even into the 2003 reintroduction of the show. In the 1980s series, Huckleberry Pie was voiced by a female actress, Julie McWhirter. His pet is a dog called Pupcake.

===Blueberry Muffin===
Blueberry Muffin has been Strawberry Shortcake's friend since the very beginning. In the 1980s, the character was depicted with blue hair in pigtails. Speaking with a Southern drawl, she was also as being more than a little forgetful. Both of these traits were downplayed as the series progressed. Her pet mouse was named Cheescake.

===Apple Dumplin'===
Apple Dumplin' was the first of many &quot;baby&quot; characters introduced in the vast world of Strawberry Shortcake. Smaller and less independent than the older Strawberryland kids, Apple has also proven to be more than capable of taking care of herself when the situation warrants. Apple's hair is bright orange, and her pet is Tea Time Turtle. Being just a little baby, she doesn't speak as yet, but has surprisingly good penmanship skills.

===Raspberry Tart===
Another of Strawberry Shortcake's earliest friends, Raspberry Tart lived up to her name in the 1980s, she is mean at first but learns to be nice as the series progressed. Her pet monkey was named Rhubarb.

===Plum Puddin'===
The last of Strawberry Shortcake's original 1980s friends, Plum Puddin' was the bespectacled genius of the group. A surprisingly non-token second male character in Strawberry's early adventures, Plum Puddin' vanished from Strawberryland in 1982, only to return to the series in 1984 as a brainy female. Strawberry Shortcake seemed not to notice. Plum remained Strawberry Shortcake's scientific advisor through the franchise's disbanding in 1985. Her pet is an owl called Elderberry.

===Orange Blossom===
Strawberry Shortcake met urban artist Orange Blossom during her trip to [[New York City|Big Apple City]] in the 1981 TV special. Orange Blossom followed Strawberry home at the conclusion of her trip, and has been at her side ever since. Orange Blossom's pet butterfly, Marmalade, actually pre-dates the introduction of Orange Blossom's character, and the two were merchandised as a team a year before &quot;Pets On Parade&quot; supplied every resident of Strawberryland with an animal companion.

===Lemon Meringue===
Another of Strawberry Shortcake's new friends from her trip to Big Apple City, Lemon Meringue is a primping beauty known around the city as a famous model. When pressed for details, however, she admits that her &quot;pictures&quot; are mostly owned by members of her immediate family. It seems unlikely that a glamorous girl such as Lemon Meringue would choose a frog for a pet. But it is actually because of the fact that Frappé in no way competes with Lemon's beauty that they get along so well.

===T.N. Honey===
T.N. Honey, a brilliant British scientist, is a rather obscure character in the Strawberry Shortcake pantheon. &quot;Big Apple City&quot; marked her singular appearance in a Strawberry Shortcake adventure, although she was also featured in occasional American Greetings card illustrations. T.N. used her scientific expertise to repair Strawberry's oven when it befell sabotage at the hands of The Purple Pie Man at the Big TV Bake-Off. At the end of the &quot;Big Apple City&quot; adventure, T.N. is seen journeying to Strawberryland along with other newcomers such as Orange Blossom and Lemon Meringue. But T.N. Honey was never seen again. Plum Puddin', Strawberry's other glasses-wearing friend, disappeared around this same time until 1984. She was voiced by Julie McWhirter.

===Apricot===
Apricot is a little white-haired baby with an unusual vocabulary of oversized words. Apricot and her pet bunny Hopsalot lived in Big Apple City, down the hall from Lemon Meringue and T.N. Honey, and like them, she re-located to Strawberryland at the conclusion of Strawberry Shortcake's visit.

===Butter Cookie===
Butter Cookie is probably Strawberry Shortcake's youngest friend ever, a baby just learning to crawl. As such, she hasn't yet developed any interesting personality traits, but is plenty adorable nonetheless. Her pet is a yellow teddy called Jelly Bear.

===Lime Chiffon===
Lime Chiffon was a bubbly and flighty ballerina in the 1980s series, always dancing and spinning to and fro, with her parrot Parfait, who often seemed to be the intellectual one of the pair.

===Cherry Cuddler===
Cherry Cuddler was another baby character, known for her propensity for hugging and being hugged by her friends. Her pet is a goose called Gooseberry.

===Angel Cake===
Overly polite Angel Cake seemed to take the &quot;Angel&quot; portion of her name a little too seriously. Never missing an opportunity to say &quot;please&quot; and &quot;thank you&quot;, she even went so far as to play the harp and wear a halo-shaped headband in her hair. Angel Cake's hair was often depicted as a lavender color in the greeting card illustrations and the cartoon, but the dolls and toys made by Kenner had white hair. Angel Cake imagined herself as having a weight problem, seeing as angel cakes are supposed to be &quot;light&quot;, but was also seen constantly eating candy and ice cream. Her direct quote: &quot;...If you don't think about it, the calories don't count.&quot; She adopted her pet skunk Soufflé as part of the action of Strawberry Shortcake's &quot;Pets on Parade&quot; adventure, and quickly put him on a &quot;diet&quot; as well.

===Almond Tea===
Almond Tea was one of the many new friends met by Strawberry Shortcake during her trip around the world immediately prior to the 1983 TV special. A native of the Asian country of [[China]] Cup, Almond Tea returned the favor and visited Strawberryland to help Strawberry Shortcake celebrate her move into her Berry Happy Home with a huge housewarming party. A provocative and unexplored facet of Almond Tea's personality is that she is said to possess psychic powers, and was able to, on occasion, see glimpses of the future. Her pet Marza Panda had a similar gift, only it worked in reverse, and only allowed him to see flashbacks.

===Café Olé===
Strawberry Shortcake's friend from the [[Mexico]]coa leg of her round-the-world trip, Café Olé's name is a play on the coffee beverage [[Café au lait]]. She is said to be adept at handicrafts such as weaving. Her pet is a donkey called Burrito.

===Crepe Suzette===
Crepe Suzette met Strawberry Shortcake during the latter's visit to the city of [[Paris|Pear-ee]] in the 1983 TV special. She later travelled to Strawberryland to surprise her new friend at her &quot;Berry Happy Home&quot; housewarming party. She is quintessentially French, and speaks English with a thick French accent. Billed as the best cook of all of Strawberry Shortcake's friends (and that's saying something!), Crepe Suzette has also been described as a bit of a perfectionist. She pushed the thematic green-and-white stripes of the Strawberry Shortcake character's stockings to the limit, wearing them as a full-length leotard as part of her street dancer's costume. Crepe Suzette was the only one of Strawberry's foreign friends of 1983 to not be carried over into the 1984 &quot;Party Pleasers&quot; line of Kenner dolls. Her pet is a French poodle called Eclair.

===Mint Tulip===
Sweet Mint Tulip was a pretty little Dutch girl, from the land of [[Holland]]aise. Her name is an interesting play on the alcoholic beverage [[mint julep]]. In the 1980s, her flower gardens were said to be the finest in all Strawberryland, and her pet is a duck called Marsh Mallard. Mint Tulip was featured in the 1985 &quot;Berrykins&quot; line of Kenner Dolls, despite the fact that she did NOT appear in the TV Special &quot;Strawberry Shortcake Meets The Berrykins&quot;, a testament to the character's popularity, or at least the popularity of her character's mint scent.

===Lem and Ada===
Lem and Ada (a somewhat clumsy pun on [[lemonade]]) are twin brother and sister, from [[England]]'s &quot;Pickle-Dilly Circus&quot;, a [[parody]] of [[Piccadilly Circus]]. Although the same size as other babies in the series, the twins seemed to be especially precocious. Not only did they speak quite well, they even finished each others sentences! Although it is fairly obvious by looking at them which twin is Lem and which is Ada, apparently telling them apart was problematic for those who lived in Strawberryland. Only their pet sheepdog Sugar Woofer seemed to know for sure.

===Peach Blush===
Peach Blush debuted near the end of Strawberry Shortcake's initial run in the 1980s. A delicate and dramatic Southern belle, from &quot;The Land of The Magnolias&quot;, Peach Blush turned up in Strawberryland along with the returning Plum Puddin', and the title character of the special, Baby Needs-A-Name. Peach Blush's pet lamb Melonie Belle appeared in limited media (a Kenner coloring book) under her original name, &quot;Honey Lamb&quot;.

===Baby Needs-A-Name===
This sweet little baby was the last of the younger characters to be introduced in the classic 1980s version of Strawberry Shortcake. Her gentle nature endeared her to everyone who met her, and she had but two wishes in her young heart: to have a pet, and to have a name, for no one had been able to think of one for her. One of these wishes came true during Strawberry Shortcake's annual camping trip in the 1984 special, when the baby encountered the unusual but adorable &quot;monster&quot; Fig Boot. The two bonded instantly, and, following the foiling of a plot by the Purple Pie Man and Sour Grapes to exploit the creature, remain inseparable. The Baby's quest for a proper name remains unresolved.

===Banana Twirl===
The final friend of Strawberry Shortcake to be introduced in the 1980s, Banana Twirl was an energetic exercise enthusiast. Because she came along so late in the line, she was never featured in American Greetings artwork, and remains noteworthy due to the scarcity of what merchandise of her was actually made.

===Mr. Sun===
Mr. Sun is just that—the sun in the sky, anthropomorphed into a friendly character with a face, who keeps a watchful eye on most all the goings-on in Strawberryland. As such, he also officiated as the narrator of the six 1980s-era Strawberry Shortcake TV Specials, and on more than one occasion acted as the [[deus ex machina]] means of resolving Strawberry Shortcake's storyline conflict therein. Mr. Sun was voiced by Romeo Muller in the first three specials, and was voiced by Chris Wiggins in the final three shows. In the more recent Strawberry Shortcake revival, the sun has been depicted with a smiling face, but has yet to interact with the characters of Strawberryland.

===Lucky Bug===
Lucky Bug is a tiny ladybug. Normally merely a benign observer of the goings-on in Strawberryland (he can be seen in much American Greetings artwork, perched inobtrusively on a leaf), Lucky Bug was enlisted by Huckleberry Pie to spy on Strawberry Shortcake in the initial TV special, in order to learn what she wanted for her birthday. Lucky Bug communicates with a series of musical buzzes, which are well understood by the inhabitants of Strawberryland, even including the Purple Pie Man.

===Escargot===
Years and years before the internet and e-mail made the term &quot;Snail Mail&quot; popular, Escargot is believed to have originated the term, to describe his own extremely slow method of postal delivery around Strawberryland. An enormous snail with a French accent, Escargot was voiced by Bob Holt, and appeared in the first two Strawberry Shortcake Specials of the 1980s. He was merchandised by Kenner as a plastic toy, which pulled a berry cart behind him as his head moved from side to side.

===Flitter-Bit===
While Strawberry Shortcake's friend Orange Blossom has a small, delicate butterfly for a pet, Strawberryland also sports butterflies of the enormous variety, such as Flitter-Bit. This obvious disparity of size doesn't faze the inhabitants of Strawberryland in the slightest. A gigantic yellow-and- green butterfly, large enough for the residents of Strawberryland to ride on his back, Flitter-Bit comprises Strawberryland Airlines, and flew Strawberry Shortcake from Strawberryland to the bright lights of Big Apple City. A bright plastic Flitter-Bit toy was produced by Kenner in 1981, the year that he made his sole animated appearance in the &quot;Strawberry Shortcake in Big Apple City&quot; special. Another, smaller solid plastic version was included with the Strawberry Shortcake Play-Doh playset. Recently, however, large yellow butterflies that greatly resemble Flitter-Bit were featured in Strawberry Shortcake's 2006 &quot;Sweet Dreams Movie&quot;.

===Tamale===
Tamale is a large, furry Mexican mole, with an apparent poor sense of direction. While tunnelling underground (as moles do) to Acapulco, Tamale somehow surfaced in Big Apple City, just in time to assist Strawberry Shortcake and her new friend Orange Blossom avoid a sabotaged traffic light, by digging a tunnel to Orange Blossom's home in [[Greenwich Village|Spinach Village]]. Like many other supporting characters featured in the &quot;Big Apple City&quot; adventure (T.N. Honey, Horseradish), Tamale decided to relocate to Strawberryland following Strawberry Shortcake's heart-warming description of her small-town life. However, for reasons that remain unknown, following this mass migration, none of these characters were ever seen again. For reasons that remain unclear, Tamale has also been billed under the unlikely name &quot;Guaca-Mole&quot; in some media. His appearance on one of a set of 1981-circa Strawberry Shortcake trading cards is as close to being merchandised as Tamale/Guaca-Mole ever got.

===Horseradish===
Prior to Honey Pie Pony, even before Maple Stirrup, Strawberry Shortcake's first horse acquaintance was a buck-toothed blue horse called Horseradish. Horseradish pulled a [[Hansom Cab]] in Big Apple City, and delivered Strawberry and her growing retinue of friends to her engagement at The Little Theatre Off [[Times Square|Times Pear]], to compete in the Big TV Bake-Off. Horseradish never appeared again following this adventure, and he was not merchadised as a toy.

===Coco Nutwork===
Coco Nutwork is a balding middle-aged executive, &quot;Vice President in Charge of Everything&quot; of CCN-TV, the TV studio that sponsored the Big TV Bake-Off. Billed as &quot;The One-Man Network&quot;, Coco operated the cameras, ran the production booth, was the entire orchestra, did voice-over announcements, emceed, and even dressed in drag as a lovely spokesmodel! Good-natured but weak-minded, Coco befell hypnotism and mind-control at the fiendish hands of The Purple Pie Man, but came to upon tasting the actual entries in the Bake-Off. Despite expressing an interest in giving up the &quot;Brat Race&quot; and relocating to Strawberryland, and even giving up his job(s) at the TV Station, Coco Nutwork was NOT seen accompanying Strawberry Shortcake and her new friends back home in the closing scene of the Special.

===Berry Busy Bug===
Berry Busy Bug is some sort of strange purple insect, with six legs (one pair functions as hands) and a long squiggly tail. He pushes a wheelbarrow as he pulls a series of flower-shaped trailers behind him, merrily transporting Strawberry Shortcake and her friends to and fro. If the scale of the toy made of Berry Busy Bug in 1982 is to be believed, he is arguably the largest known creature in all Strawberryland, for he towers over the Miniature figurines for which he was marketed as a vehicle/accessory. As a character, however, Berry Busy Bug is absolutely minor. A walk-on cameo appearance in the &quot;Pets On Parade&quot; adventure is all the storyline treatment he ever received.

===Philbert Wormly III===
Philbert Wormly III is a dapper British inchworm, of the larger-than-average variety. Clad in a top hat, bow tie and tweed suit, Philbert also wears an ornate saddle with twin sidebaskets, so that Strawberry Shortcake can ride on his back, as he bounces along at a surprisingly quick pace. He answers to the sound of a whistle, as though he were performing a taxi service, and has been known to &quot;spook&quot; when someone brings up the subject of fishing. His toy was billed as the &quot;Berry Merry Worm&quot;.

===Maple Stirrup===
Maple Stirrup was the first Strawberry Shortcake horse character to be merchandised as a toy. A warm brown pony with a bright green-and-white striped mane and tail, Maple Stirrup pulled a light two-wheeled carriage called The Oatsmobile.

A mention of Maple Stirrup was made in the 2003-series Strawberry Shortcake GBA Game, &quot;Ice Cream Island Riding Camp&quot;, along with many other obscure fillies. However, it is unclear if American Greetings was planning to revive this filly for the 2003 franchise revival.

===The Berry Princess and The Berrykins===
The Berry Princess is a beautiful fairy who possesses amazing mystical powers. With a wave of her magic wand, she can appear and disappear in a shower of sparkles, cleanse the skies of pollution, and even make hair grow to fantastic lengths instantly! Supposedly the Guardian of The Berrykins, a group of elf-like beings who are charged with giving fruits and berries their sweet fragrances, the Berry Princess nonetheless entrusted her charges into the care of Strawberry Shortcake and her friends in 1985, which was the last year that Strawberry was produced in the 1980s. The Peculiar Purple Pieman of Porcupine Peak seems to have a crush on her. The known Berrykins are:

*Strawberrykin
*Blueberrykin
*Raspberrykin
*Orange Berrykin
*Lemon Berrykin
*Lime Berrykin
*Plum Berrykin
*Peach Berrykin
*Banana Berrykin
*Mint Berrykin

===The Peculiar Purple Pieman===
The Purple Pieman of Porcupine Peak was introduced in Strawberry Shortcake's first adventure, ''[[The World of Strawberry Shortcake]]'', where  he succeeded in flooding Strawberryland and stealing all the berries in the valley.  This was the closest the Pieman ever came to a decisive victory over Strawberry Shortcake.  Later episodes show the Purple Pieman harassing the residents of Strawberryland.  In ''[[Strawberry Shortcake in Big Apple City]]'' it is said that he has an 'evil conscience,'  but he rarely does anything that is more than &quot;mildly mischievous.&quot;  He is known for doing a tap dance while saying, &quot;Yah-tah-tah-tah-tah-tah-tah-tah, tah-tah-tah-tah! Cha!&quot;

In the 1980s series, the Purple Pieman is shown living in a ramshackle tower of cookware dubbed The Pie Tin Palace, situated high atop Strawberryland on Porcupine Peak.  In his tower, he had a wealth of baking supplies, such as ovens, pans, and dough.  The Pieman also possessed a magic pie tin, which he sometimes used to spy on the residents of Strawberryland.  While he was a clever liar and cheat, and a convincing master of disguise, he was an admittedly poor baker in the '80s specials.  The Purple Pieman frequently referred to himself in the third person, and always performed a quick jig after doing so. In the [[2006]] film ''[[Strawberry Shortcake: The Sweet Dreams Movie]]'' he even signs his name with fanfare written in.  He dislikes snakes and Sour Grapes' singing, but hates Strawberry Shortcake's 'Berry Talk' (that is, to substitute &quot;berry&quot; for any word that rhymes) above all else.  [[List of Strawberry Shortcake characters#Mr. Sun|Mr. Sun]] describes him as a &quot;misanthropic fathead with a skinny physique&quot; in ''[[Strawberry Shortcake in Big Apple City]]''.

The Purple Pieman has a flock of Berry Birds, which he uses to steal berries and eavesdrop on the denizens of Strawberryland.  The largest Berry Bird was originally called Captain Cackle.

===Sour Grapes===
Sour Grapes was introduced in the third Strawberry Shortcake special, ''[[Strawberry Shortcake: Pets on Parade]]'',  In 1982. In the special, she introduced herself as the Purple Pieman's old partner in crime.  She sang when excited, much to the Pieman's chagrin, as her singing was loud and off-key (Her 'song' was introduced as a &quot;yogurt-curdling yodel&quot; upon her first appearance, but was later modified into a shrill operatic pronouncement).  She was very fond of her pet snake, Dregs, whom she frequently wore as a stole.

===Raisin Cane===
Raisin Cane was introduced in the [[1985]] [[Star Comics]] Strawberry Shortcake title.  She is Sour Grapes' adolescent niece.  In her first appearance, she was selected to infiltrate Strawberryland's annual pie baking contest.  By the end of this adventure, Raisin realized that she wanted to be friends with Strawberry Shortcake and her companions, but her loyalties were still with her aunt and the Purple Pieman.  Her pet is a worm named Durt. Due to her comic only appearance, she remains a fairly obscure character. She was not rereleased for the 2003 series. The two distinctly different sides to her character were filled through the new characters Peppermint Fizz and Rainbow Sherbet.

==2003==
{{Multiple image|direction=vertical|align=right|image1=Strawberry_Shortcake_Chars_Year1_Year2.png|image2=Strawberry_Shortcake_Chars_Year3_Year4.png|width=300|caption1=The characters of 2003 Strawberry Shortcake during year 1 and year 2|caption2=New characters of 2003 Strawberry Shortcake introduced during year 3 and year 4}}
Throughout the 2003 reintroduction of the ''[[Strawberry Shortcake]]'' series, a number of recurring characters appear.

===Year 1===
====Strawberry Shortcake====
Strawberry Shortcake is the [[protagonist]] and the title character of the ''Strawberry Shortcake'' franchise. She is said to be the &quot;unofficial princess&quot; of Strawberryland,&lt;ref&gt;http://www.huckleberrybriar.com/characters.php Huckleberry Briar: ...and as the unofficial berry princess of Strawberryland, she puts her heart and soul into seeing that things improve for everyone she meets...&lt;/ref&gt; and is often seen wearing a pink hat with strawberries printed on it. In this version, she lives in a large [[strawberry]].

She shares her berry bungalow with her little sister Apple Dumplin', her cat Custard (voiced by [[Sarah Koslosky]], and later [[Anna Jordan]]), and her dog Pupcake (voiced by [[Nils Haaland]]). Many of Strawberry Shortcake’s days are spent in the simple pleasures of tending [[strawberry|berry]] vines. Strawberry also likes to spend time with her friends, so she frequently visits nearby lands. Strawberry is always cheerful and is ready for helping her friends at any time.

This version of Strawberry Shortcake appears slightly older than her 1980s counterpart, and was voiced by [[Sarah Heinke]] from 2004 to until the franchise's reboot in 2009.

====Apple Dumplin'====
Apple Dumplin' was the first of many &quot;baby&quot; characters in the vast world of Strawberry Shortcake. Smaller and less independent than the older Strawberryland kids, Apple has also proven to be more than capable of taking care of herself when the situation warrants. In the modern rendition of the franchise, it has been learned that Apple Dumplin' is Strawberry Shortcake's baby sisterberry-shaped cottage. Also, in this version, her hair is black and white,she wears a purple shirt,and a ponytail 

====Ginger Snap====
Ginger Snap is an all-new character for the 2000s reboot of the franchise. With updated characters Orange Blossom and Angel Cake, Ginger Snap completes the nucleus of Strawberry Shortcake's ever-expanding circle of friends. Ginger Snap is an expert inventor, and purveyor of every known kind of cookie. Her massive gingerbread factory in Cookie Corners combines these two interests neatly. She is shown to have a pet chipmunk named Chocolate Chipmunk.  Played by the voice of Samantha Triba.

====Orange Blossom====
In the 2003 incarnation, Orange Blossom manages Orange Blossom Acres, and lives in an orange-shaped tree house high in one of her trees. She retains her status as front and center in Strawberry Shortcake's close circle of friends. She has a orange butterfly named Marmalade.

====Angel Cake====
This incarnation of the character of Angel Cake very different from her original incarnation in the 80s. She even teamed with a different pet, a lamb called Vanilla Icing. The new Angel Cake is blonde and possesses a tremendous talent for cake decoration. However she is also known to be a perfectionist and can become rather ill-tempered if things don't go her way.&lt;ref name=&quot;Outfield&quot;&gt;DiC Entertainment/20th Century Fox, Angel Cake In The Outfield, Play Day Surprise, DVD, 2005&lt;/ref&gt; Her neighborhood in Strawberryland is called Cakewalk, and is a frosting-coated layer cake testament to her abilities. She is super moody and gets mad at the littlest things but overall she is very sweet.

====Huckleberry Pie====
One of Shortcake's friends, Huckleberry Pie is, so far, the only male protagonist of the series. The obvious inspiration for his character was [[Mark Twain]]'s literary creation [[Huckleberry Finn (character)|Huckleberry Finn]]. In this incarnation, Huckleberry Pie remains the token male of the line, although his character has been updated, and distanced from literary allusion. These days, a very modern Huck lives in a fort in a place called Huckleberry Briar. His wild abode features a [[skate park]] full of ramps and secret entrances, a testament to him being a skateboarder. He has a pet frog named Shoofly.

He was first voiced by [[Daniel Canfield]] and later voiced by [[James Street (actor)|James Street]].

===Year 2===
====Peppermint Fizz====
Like the 1980s character [[List of Strawberry Shortcake villains#Raisin Cane|Raisin Cane]] before her, Peppermint Fizz is an argumentative trouble-making [[brat]]. Conniving, manipulative and greedy, she epitomizes every bad quality that a child might possess. But still Strawberry Shortcake sees whatever good might lurk beneath the sour surface, and does her best to cultivate goodness in her. Deep inside her though, there is still some good in her. Her pet is ''Cola Chameleon''. For series 4, Peppermint Fizz's negative traits were toned down.she owns a cafe

====Rainbow Sherbet====
Rainbow Sherbet is a seafaring girl. She is captain of the Rainbow Float, an ornate paddle boat on the Punch Bowl Pond. Her pet toucan has been called by several different names from various sources including ''Triple Treat'' and ''Triple Dip'', but ''Triple Ripple'' has been confirmed as the official name by American Greetings.

====Coco Calypso====
Coco Calypso is good friends with Strawberry Shortcake and her pals, but she lives on Seaberry Shore, a beautiful tropical beach far removed from her Strawberryland friends. Upon the girls' discovery of another, secret resident of the area, Coco found a new friend, and was not so lonely for companionship between Strawberry Shortcake's visits. Coco Calypso's pet is ''Papaya Parrot''. Coco has dark brown hair and dark brown eyes. She is a very adventurous little girl.

====Seaberry Delight====
Seaberry Delight lives in a shell-shaped cottage in a secret grotto off of Seaberry Shore. A fantastic swimmer, Seaberry loves the water so much, she was mistaken for a mermaid when first encountered by Strawberry Shortcake and her friends. Once unaware of each others' co-existence on the beach, Seaberry and Coco Calypso have since become fast friends.

====Blueberry Muffin====
Blueberry Muffin has been Strawberry Shortcake's friend since the very beginning. While Blueberry Muffin was absent from the earliest 2000s Strawberry Shortcake Adventures, she first re-appeared in 2005's ''Seaberry Beach Party'' DVD. She received an official re-introduction in the ''Moonlight Mysteries'' DVD later that year. In the modern version, Blueberry Muffin has been re-imagined as a book-loving dramatist, who lives in a muffin-shaped cottage in Blueberry Valley. Her hair was also altered to an uncharacteristic brown color, but she re-instated her trademark blue hair in 2007, with mixed reactions from fans. Blueberry has curly brown hair and is in love with theater. She can be drama queen at times and tends to over exaggerate things but she is sweet. She is very smart and always has her nose in a book. She loves making up stories and she wishes to be a writer when she grows up. She has a blue mouse named Cheesecake as her pet.

===Year 3===
====Tea Blossom====
Originally Almond Tea, the character was [[retcon]]ned somewhat for Strawberry's 2006 &quot;A World of Friends&quot; campaign. Now called Tea Blossom, her home is in the Plum Blossom Province, near [[Great Wall of China|The Great Wall of Chocolate]], but her pet Marza Panda remains the same.

====Crepes' Suzette====
Although her name and even her pet remain the same since her 1980s introduction, Strawberry Shortcake's French friend Crepes' Suzette's image has undergone an extreme makeover for her 2000s.
She sports long, wavy pink locks. She operates a chic boutique in the heart of [[Paris|Pearis]], when she is not visiting Strawberry Shortcake at her home in Strawberryland.
Crepes Suzette Voice By [http://Victoria%20Cook Victoria Cook]

====Frosty Puff====
In 2006, the Strawberry Shortcake DVD &quot;World of Friends&quot; introduced a re-telling of the events of the 1983 &quot;Housewarming Surprise&quot; TV special, with a few changes to the story as well as the cast. While some of her &quot;new&quot; friends from around the world stayed nearly the same (Crepes Suzette), and others underwent minor changes (Almond Tea/Tea Blossom), still others (Mint Tulip, Café Olé) were replaced altogether by new, original characters. Frosty Puff, a warm-hearted girl from icy-cold [[Iceland|Niceland]], was one of these new foreign friends. Although it is not obvious by her cold-weather appearance and attire, Frosty Puff's scent is that of Blackberries, a first in the Strawberry Shortcake toy line. Her pet is a penguin called Freezer Pop.

====Tangerina Torta====
Tangerina Torta, another new &quot;Around The World&quot; Strawberry Shortcake friend for 2006, is a real nature girl. She lives in a tree-house in the Tangerine Bosque, a lush tropical rain forest, presumably in the Strawberry Shortcake version of South America, though no country name has been given. Tangerina has a pet monkey called Banana Bongo. Oddly, a similar monkey (with the same name) was a companion of Coco Calypso on the Seaberry Shore nearly a year prior to the introduction of Tangerina Torta and HER Banana Bongo.

====Raspberry Torte====
Another of Strawberry Shortcake's earliest friends, Raspberry has undergone more changes than most for her re-introduction in the 2000s. For one thing, her last name was altered to &quot;[[Torte]]&quot;, apparently since American Greetings didn't like an unseemly connotation that the word &quot;Tart&quot; has acquired (though a [[tart]] and a torte are markedly different types of [[dessert]]s). Also, while Raspberry's new pet in the 2000s retains the name &quot;Rhubarb&quot;, it is now a raccoon, instead of a monkey, as in the 1980s. She is seen by some to share certain negative characteristics with Peppermint Fizz, although thankfully she does not share the worst of Peppermint's characteristics. Furthermore, although the &quot;new&quot; Raspberry can be brash and thoughtless, she is generally seen as the [[Sport|athletic]] and [[physical fitness|fitness]] fanatic of Strawberryland. Her home was originally announced in the 2003 series to be Raspberry Fields, but was changed to Raspberry Meadows some time before her debut in the Sweet Dreams Movie.

====Lemon Meringue====
In this incarnation of the franchise, her leanings towards style and glamor remain, in that she runs a beauty salon out of her home on Lemon Lane in Strawberryland. Her pet, however, has changed to a yellow skunk named Sourball. In the new updated version, Lemon Meringue seems to have an especially close friendship with Raspberry Torte.

====The Berry Fairies====
Apparently meant to replace the Berrykins of the 1980s series, the Berry Fairies serve a similar purpose to the Berrykins in the new 2003 series in the sense that they are entrusted with giving the fruits in Strawberryland their unusually large size, their scent and abundant quantities in the new series. The Berry Fairies are ruled by the Berry Fairy Queen, who is in turn advised by an adviser.

====Licorice Whip====
Licorice Whip is introduced in the [[2005]] [[DVD]] ''Adventures on Ice Cream Island''.  He is a traveling horse-napper who [[kidnapping|kidnaps]] Strawberry Shortcake's filly friend, Honey Pie Pony, to be the star of his Traveling Horsey [[Hoedown]] show.  He is a tall, slim man dressed in tall black boots, a long black overcoat, and a licorice-ribbed vest.  He has reddish-brown hair and wears a tall, black, licorice-ribbed stove-pipe hat.  His pet helper is an under-appreciated bird known as Raven.  Due to this under-appreciation, Raven actually turned against Licorice Whip by the end of the show, helping Strawberry, her friends, and their fillies rescue Honey Pie Pony from an escaping raft.  In the end, after his captured horses escape, Licorice Whip yells &quot;I'll be back!&quot; . His return was chronicled in the game ''Strawberry Shortcake: Ice Cream Island Riding Camp'' for the [[GameBoy Advance]], in which he was drilling Ice Cream Island for its cookie crust foundation to be sold as frozen snacks. His constant and reckless drilling destabilized the island's foundations, and he ultimately gets himself into trouble. He redeems himself after Strawberry Shortcake rescues him at the end of the game.

===Year 4===
[[Image:Year 4.png|thumb|300px|Characters who change their looks in year 4, along with the rest of new characters introduced in the said period of [[Strawberry Shortcake]] series.]]
Starting from year 4, a number of characters change their looks to be more aged than in previous periods. The stories of the episodes also start to revolve around more mature things such as getting jobs, making a band, driving a car, and even becoming a movie star.

====Apricot====
In this incarnation of the franchise, Apricot is depicted as being close to the same age as Strawberry Shortcake and her friends. Now apricot-haired Apricot is the new girl in Strawberryland, and feeling insecure, resorted to telling tall tales of wealth and accomplishment in an attempt to win friends. She soon learned her lesson, and was welcomed warmly into Strawberry Shortcake's wide circle of friends.

====Cherry Cuddler====
Cherry Cuddler was another baby character, known for her propensity for hugging and being hugged by her friends. A new updated character design has been seen for a still-younger 2000s Cherry Cuddler, but she has yet to appear in a storyline. She has already been introduced direct-to-toy-line by Playmates, however.

====Plum Puddin'====
Originally introduced as a male when the franchise was first introduced in the 1980s, Plum Puddin' was changed to a girl in 1984. Still a girl when she was reintroduced, she was added to the ever-growing line-up of Strawberry's revival in 2008.  While still a  brainy character, she's also a bit of a walking disaster.

====Banana Candy====
Formerly Banana Twirl, on joining the ever-expanding cast of the Strawberry Shortcake revival in 2008, she is now known as Banana Candy, her former vigor and energy seem to have translated into workaholism, for she runs the small town of Banana Boro all by herself. As in the 1980s, she seems destined to remain petless&lt;ref name=&quot;pet&quot;&gt;Prototype toys of a line of &quot;Baby Pets&quot;, from a projected (but unproduced) line of Strawberry Shortcake &quot;Babies&quot; dolls, apparently planned for release in 1986, are known to exist. Included in this line-up are infant versions of Custard, Marmalade, Marsh Mallard, Elderberry, Melonie Belle, Cheesecake, Frappe', and an otherwise unheard-of yellow baby elephant. Since five of these eight pets correspond to the girls featured in 1985 &quot;Berrykins&quot; Assortment of dolls (Strawberry, Orange Blossom, Mint Tulip, Plum Puddin' and Peach Blush), it appears that the unknown pet may be associated with the sixth Berrykins Doll, Banana Twirl.&lt;/ref&gt; Banana Candy has long, brown hair and is a mechanic.

====Watermelon Kiss====
Strawberry Shortcake's new friend Watermelon Kiss is a sunny, summer-loving girl who loves horses.

====Annie Oatmeal====
Annie Oatmeal owns and operates the Berry Prairie Dude Ranch. Her name is apparently a play on famous western sharpshooting celebrity [[Annie Oakley]], while also evidently referencing oatmeal cookies. Seemingly around the same age as the recently (as of 2008) more grown up Strawberry Shortcake, Annie Oatmeal hired Strawberry and her friend Angel Cake to work as hands on her ranch. In her role as Strawberry's employer, however, Annie Oatmeal is depicted as less of a peer, and more of an authority figure, something new and very different in Strawberry Shortcake's previously carefree world.

====Carmel Corn====
A surprise new character introduction in the &quot;Big Country Fun&quot; DVD, Carmel Corn is a hard-working farm girl, whose motif appears to be that of triangle-shaped CANDY corn. Carmel's land was being coveted by The Purple Pie Man and Sour Grapes, who wanted to build a parking lot for their adjacent &quot;Pie Man Land&quot; Amusement Park. With the help of Strawberry Shortcake and her friends, a large Country Fair was thrown, all of the animals that had &quot;disappeared&quot; were returned, and Carmel Corn's farm was saved.

====Brambleberry Fairy====
Originally thought to be an anti-hero character first introduced as a fairy in the said episode, DiC/Cookie Jar has since admitted on the back of the Happily Ever After DVD that she is actually Angel Cake with her negative traits greatly exaggerated, hair recolored into purple, and skin tone darkened.&lt;ref name=&quot;alterego&quot;&gt;''In &quot;Sleeping Beauty&quot;, Brambleberry Fairy  (Angel Cake) feels neglected and casts a spell that puts princess Strawberry Rose to sleep...'' - Happily Ever After DVD back cover, 20th Century Fox/Cookie Jar, 2009&lt;/ref&gt; She cursed Baby Strawberry Rose to vanish forever if she gets her finger pricked by a brambleberry bush, although later Appleberry weakened the curse, replacing vanish with sleep. Later in the story, she regrets ever making the curse and starts setting things right, such as bringing Strawberry Rose out of her sleep and apologizing for her early mistakes. In progress, she learns and understands forgiveness and friendship.

====Appleberry Fairy====
A fairy version of Apple Dumplin' for use in the &quot;Sleeping Beauty&quot; episode in Happily Ever After. She at first was clueless on what gift to give to Strawberry Rose, but after Brambleberry had casted her curse, Appleberry used her gift to partially weaken the curse.
Appleberry fairy is friends with gingerberry fairy(Ginger Snap),tangerinaberry fairy(Tangerina Torta),rainbowberry fairy(Rainbow Sherbert).

====Princess Strawberry Rose====
A version of Strawberry Shortcake greatly exaggerated for use in the &quot;Sleeping Beauty&quot; episode in Happily Ever After. She fell into a deep sleep by a prick from brambleberry bush as an effect from Brambleberry's curse, and later brought out of the spell by Brambleberry herself along with other fairies.

====Lime Light====
Apparently the reintroduction of Lime Chiffon, Lime Light is a character that was introduced in the episodes on the DVD ''Berrywood Here We Come''. Lime Light is initially a selfish, self-centered spoiled child star (not unlike how [[Shirley Temple|Sugar Dimples]] initially was in the [[Madeline]] universe), but was eventually reformed by Strawberry Shortcake by the end of the episode, and, as of then, she starts thinking of others.

====The Peculiar Purple Pieman====
In the 2003 series, Porcupine Peak is never seen. The Purple Pieman usually traversed throughout Strawberryland and the surrounding areas in a cart drawn by [[Dobbin]], his horse. He was much the same as he was in his original form, though given further depth and humanness of character. An 'evil conscience' is not mentioned this time around, and the Purple Pieman at last reforms in time for the series finale.

The Purple Pieman has a flock of Berry Birds, which he uses to steal berries and eavesdrop on the denizens of Strawberryland. The Berry Birds are nameless in the rerelease.

====Sour Grapes====
In the 2006 &quot;Sweet Dreams Movie,&quot; Sour Grapes was reintroduced as the Purple Pieman's sister. In a number of ways, her personality stayed as it had been before. As in the '80s, she chided the Pieman for his ridiculousness. Unlike her '80s form, however, Sour Grapes had a greater sense of morality this time around. Also changed was her position in the crimes; whereas before she had suggested schemes herself and often talked the Purple Pieman into them, this time she was the follower and it can be argued that she followed out of affectionate familial devotion. Despite her shortcomings witnessed in the episode &quot;Queen For a Day&quot; and despite her initial reactions to the children in the aforementioned feature movie, she was repeatedly shown to be quite maternal and intelligent. When excited, her personality often changed from that of bitter adult to playful young girl. Though irritable, to emotionally reach her for the better was not at all a hard task. An allergy to strawberries, a suspectibility to headaches and hints to poor physical health in general further added to her depth of character.

The 'first' reformation of this character occurred in the episode &quot;Dancin' in Disguise&quot; and while she remained partners with her brother throughout the series, she did wish for things to be different. In the finale, the Purple Pieman is at last reformed, thus inevitably sealing Sour Grapes' own reformation. Dregs, the pet snake, did make a reappearance in the &quot;Queen For a Day&quot; episode. Strangely, he did not return after this.

===Animals===
====Pets====
At the beginning of the series, Strawberry Shortcake is introduced and is paired with Custard the cat and Pupcake the Dog. Indeed, no other pets were introduced up until the episode ''Best Pets Yet''

=====Custard=====
A pink cat with darker pink stripes, and is one of the two pets introduced at the start of the franchise itself, Custard is one of the few animals in the show's universe that could talk to humans. Indeed, Custard's ability to talk to the other pets and the humans proves invaluable as a translator for Pupcake to Strawberry. Custard is generally snobbish and sarcastic in temperament, but under all the sarcasm and snobbishness is a heart of gold. Custard is voiced By Sarah Koslosky in the first four episodes of the show, but the voice cast was changed to Anna Jordan for the rest of the series.

=====Pupcake=====
A white dog with blue spots, a blue tail, blue ears and a blue strawberry shaped patch over one eye, Pupcake is a very energetic and easily excitable puppy, although unlike Custard he is unable to talk to humans. Pupcake's design and existence has been the source of controversy among many fans of the series. The episode that tells the story of Pupcake entering Strawberry Shortcake's life, ''Here Comes Pupcake'', contained various inconsistencies that contradict with the first episode, ''Meet Strawberry Shortcake''. Likewise, while many official merchandise features the Strawberry-shaped patch on Pupcake's left eye, there exist other official merchandise that features the patch on Pupcake's right eye instead. Lastly, Pupcake's eye color has been opened to some debate, with most merchandise depicting it as brown while some depict it as blue. Pupcake also appears to be very apt at lip-syncing, as he's been seen doing so in quite a few episodes. He is also assumed to be the narrator of the Berry Brick Road episode ''Toto's Tale''. Pupcake is voiced by Nils Haaland.

=====Chocolate Chipmunk=====
A brown [[chipmunk]] that wears a white baker's hat with a gingerbread man cookie on it, and a purple collar with a cookie-shaped tag, Chocolate Chipmunk is bright and as technically apt as his owner, '''Ginger Snap'''. While he does not speak human language, apparently the inhabitants of Strawberryland, and especially Ginger Snap, are capable of understanding his chipmunk chatters.

=====Vanilla Icing=====
A light-purple lamb with a snow-white fleece who is '''Angel Cake''''s pet.

=====Marmalade Butterfly=====
An orange colored butterfly, Marmalade is the quietest of pets in Strawberryland, apparently only able to make soft tongue rolling noises.
Marmalade is '''Orange Blossom''''s pet.

=====Triple Ripple Toucan=====
Known under various aliases, including ''Triple Dip'' and ''Triple Treat'', although ''Triple Ripple'' has been confirmed to be the official name by American Greetings. '''Rainbow Sherbet''''s pet has been released direct to toy line and makes an appearance in the Windows/Mac edutainment title ''Strawberry Shortcake: Berry Best Friends''. However, the character made a very late appearance in the show's run, only finally appearing in the episode &quot;A Princess Named Rap&quot;, a few years after it was released to the toy line.

=====Papaya Parrot=====
Another one of the few animals in the Strawberry Shortcake universe that could talk, Papaya Parrot only appeared in the episodes &quot;The Mystery of Seaberry Shore&quot; and &quot;The Legend Of The Lost Treasure&quot;. Sadly, like her owner, '''Coco Calypso''', she was never seen again after.

=====Kiwi Sea Turtle=====
Kiwi was never seen on the series. However, he has been produced as toy by Bandai. He is '''Seaberry Delight''''s pet.

=====Cola Chameleon=====
Able to change color, and also talented at lip-syncing. He is '''Peppermint Fizz''''s pet.

=====Raven=====
Pet of the villain Licorice Whip. Raven is another one of the few animals in Strawberry Shortcake's universe to be able to talk to humans. He is also one of the first villains to redeem himself.

=====Other pets=====
* '''Shoofly''' - '''Huckleberry Pie''''s frog
* '''Apple Ducklin''' - '''Apple Dumplin''''s duckling
* '''Cheesecake''' - a mouse who is very smart and sweet. He is '''Blueberry Muffin''''s pet.
* '''Éclair''' - '''Crêpe Suzette''''s poodle
* '''Marza Panda''' - '''Tea Blossom''''s panda
* '''Freezer Pop''' - '''Frosty Puff''''s penguin
* '''Sourball''' - '''Lemon Meringue''''s skunk
* '''Rhubarb''' - '''Raspberry Torte''''s raccoon
* '''Dreggs''' - '''Sour Grapes'''' snake
* '''Pallmama''' - '''Holiday fruits''' Parrot

====Fillies====
Back in the 1980s incarnation of the World of Strawberry Shortcake, the character encountered a couple of [[List of 1980s Strawberry Shortcake characters#Supporting_Cast|horses]] in her travels, with varying degrees of success. With the advent of the 2003 series, American Greetings introduced a whole range of fillies to the revived franchise.

Honey Pie was introduced in the first episode, ''Meet Strawberry Shortcake'',&lt;ref name=&quot;meetssc&quot;&gt;20th Century Fox/DiC Entertainment, Meet Strawberry Shortcake, DVD, 2004&lt;/ref&gt; while Cookie Dough, Milkshake and Orange Twist were introduced in ''Horse of A Different Color''.&lt;ref name=&quot;ICI&quot;&gt;20th Century Fox/DiC Entertainment, Horse of A Different Color, Adventures on Ice Cream Island DVD, 2004&lt;/ref&gt; The remaining fillies were direct-to-toy-line, and most never appeared in the TV series beyond an on-screen cameo, although Huckleberry Hash, Blueberry Sundae and Ambrosia subsequently appeared in books.&lt;ref name=&quot;ffriends&quot;&gt;Megan E. Bryant, SI Artists; Strawberry Shortcake's Filly Friends, Grosset &amp; Dunlap, ISBN 0-448-43574-8&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;berryPrincess&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;ftrip&quot;&gt;Megan E. Bryant, SI Artists; The Friendship Trip, Grosset &amp; Dunlap, ISBN 978-0-448-44557-1&lt;/ref&gt; A few of the remaining fillies also made an appearance in the edutainment title ''Strawberry Shortcake and Her Berry Best Friends'' for Windows and Mac.

As of the TV series' Year 4, and with the transition of the Strawberry Shortcake franchise from Bandai to PlayMates, a number of very different new directions were embarked upon, including a new approach concerning the merchandising of horses for the line. The ensuing toy &quot;ponies&quot; were a noted departure in that they had no names of their own, and were designated by the name of the character to whom they were linked (&quot;Strawberry Shortcake's Pony&quot;, for instance, who was obviously not Honey Pie Pony). A number of these direct-to-toy-line ponies were given names in the ''Big Country Fun'' DVD, and are the first ponies introduced for Year 4 characters.&lt;ref name=&quot;bcfDVD&quot;&gt;20th Century Fox/DiC Entertainment, Best Ranch Hand, Big Country Fun, DVD, 2008&lt;/ref&gt; Honey Pie Pony and her filly contemporaries have been sidelined by this development, and as a result have received reduced screen time in Year 4.

=====Honey Pie Pony=====
A talking palomino [[horse]] (and the only horse on the series that could talk) who was introduced with the franchise's revival, Honey Pie Pony likes to chat about anything, often leading to meandering monologues on her extensive travels of the world. Honey Pie is prone to exaggerating the truth, however, which makes her surprise at learning of the existence of a whole island of fillies (Ice Cream Island) nearby to Strawberryland a bit more understandable. Honey Pie is also picky about who can ride on her back; Strawberry Shortcake is her rider of choice. Never one to do things the way others do, Honey Pie has a friend/pet bee called Honey Doodle.&lt;ref name=&quot;rememberingbook&quot;&gt;Mentioned in the remembering book provided with the remembering book interactive Strawberry Shortcake toy manufactured by Ban-dai&lt;/ref&gt; She is voiced by Hannah Koslosky.

=====Cookie Dough=====
Cookie Dough is known as the slowest of the fillies, owing to her inability to refrain from stopping to nibble every sweet thing that crosses her path. She and Ginger Snap get along famously especially because of this, for Ginger Snap is seldom without a cookie to share. A cream-colored filly decorated with tan and brown speckles, Cookie Dough's dark brown mane and tail were augmented later in the toy line with streaks of bright purple.

=====Milkshake=====
Milkshake is a very timid white filly with pink, light blue and purple mane, who frightens easily, which made it difficult for Angel Cake to get to know her initially. Angel Cake's understanding and encouragement enable Milkshake to face her numerous fears. Milkshake's life of running from her fears has made her the fastest filly around.

=====Orange Twist=====
Orange Twist's pale orange sherbet-colored coat is marked with bright orange swirl designs. Her bright blonde mane and tail are streaked with orange as well. She is generally a wild filly, jumping and bucking when most people attempt to ride her. Orange Blossom, though, is NOT most people. Orange Blossom's shy nature has a disarming effect on Orange Twist, making her calm and agreeable.

=====Huckleberry Hash=====
Huckleberry Hash was introduced seemingly as an afterthought, towards the end of Bandai's run of producing Strawberry Shortcake Toys. A medium blue filly dotted with lighter and darker blue spots, Huckleberry Hash was merchandised as part of the &quot;Fantasy Sparkles&quot; filly line, and came wearing a pair of large blue fabric fairy wings.

=====Cherry Vanilla=====
Cherry Vanilla is paired with Peppermint Fizz, and was marketed in the line of Bandai's Strawberryland Fillies despite the fact that Bandai never produced a doll of Peppermint Fizz to ride her. A deep pink filly with red speckles and a vivid red mane and tail, Cherry Vanilla is said to be the sweetest natured of the Ice Cream Island fillies, as she attempts to compensate for the often &quot;bratty&quot; nature of her human counterpart.

=====Spumoni=====
A curiously coated filly, colored in large swirled swatches of pink, green and brown, like the multi-colored ice cream for which she is named, Spumoni has a lush dark brown mane and tail, which perfectly matches Coco Calypso's hair. Like most of the Ice Cream Island fillies, who received nothing in the way of storyline or development from the animated shows, the only information on Spumoni's character comes from the packaging of her toy, which states that she likes to have her mane braided.

=====Blueberry Sundae=====
Blueberry Sundae was planned to be introduced as part of Bandai's &quot;Filly Parade&quot; line of toy horses, but was not actually released as a toy until the final wave of &quot;Fantasy Sparkle&quot; fillies. A filly dappled in bright shades of blue with white legs and mane and tail, Blueberry Sundae is said to be very vain about her striking appearance, and will stop in her tracks to admire her reflection whenever she encounters it. Blueberry Sundae made a short appearance on the episode &quot;Horse of a Different Color&quot;, over 4 episodes before her owner, Blueberry Muffin, was introduced.

=====Pistachio=====
Pistachio is teamed with Seaberry Delight, and loves to splash in the ocean waves just as much as her human friend. Her coat, mane and tail are all creamy shades of green, though for some reason, the head of Bandai's toy Pistachio is a much darker green than the rest of her.

=====Butter Pecan=====
Butter Pecan is an adventurous filly who likes being groomed and who loves to travel. Her coat is a warm tan, dotted with brown specks and streaked with unusual brown zebra-like stripes. Her mane and tail are bright yellow.

=====Lemon Ice=====
Lemon Ice and Raspberry Ripple (below) share something in common with Cherry Vanilla, in that they were marketed without benefit of having a kid character counterpart to ride them. Dolls of said counterparts Lemon Meringue and Raspberry Torte were said to be in the works as the final wave of Bandai's &quot;Fantasy Sparkle&quot; fillies were released (in a limited market), but the Strawberry Shortcake license passed from Bandai to PlayMates before this could come to pass. PlayMate's initial Strawberry Shortcake &quot;Flavor Swirl&quot; Wave included dolls of both Lemon Meringue and Raspberry Torte, but their filly friends from Bandai were long gone by then. Lemon Meringue has since been aligned with a new PlayMates pony named Daffodil.

=====Raspberry Ripple=====
Raspberry Ripple is a dazzling fuchsia pink color, swirled through with &quot;ripples&quot; of bright white on her face, legs and hindquarters. Like Lemon Ice (above), her toy was released in very limited quantities, in Bandai's final &quot;Fantasy Sparkles&quot; wave of fillies.

=====Ambrosia=====
Ambrosia is perhaps the most obscure horse in a list of many fairly obscure horses. Never featured on Strawberry Shortcake's animated TV show, nor ever produced as a toy, Ambrosia is a magical unicorn depicted in the book &quot;Berry Princess&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;berryPrincess&quot;&gt;Megan E. Bryant, MJ Illustrations; Berry Princess, Grosset &amp; Dunlap, ISBN 0-448-43954-9&lt;/ref&gt; In the book, Strawberry and friends are told by a magic mirror that Ambrosia is lost in a maze in the forest and can only be rescued by the Berry Princess. Strawberry Shortcake successfully rescues Ambrosia, implying that she is indeed the Berry Princess.&lt;ref name=&quot;berryPrincess&quot;/&gt;

=====Buttercup=====
The Berry Prairie Dude Ranch was stocked to overflowing, with enough ponies to accommodate two teams of four &quot;dude&quot; visitors, as well as hired hands Strawberry Shortcake and Angel Cake and ranch owner Annie Oatmeal. Of nearly a dozen ponies on hand, a mere few had their names mentioned. Surprisingly, the bright pink pony rode by Strawberry Shortcake was not named, but &quot;Ol' Buttercup&quot;, who was paired with Blueberry Muffin on Strawberry Shortcake's team, was.

=====Sunflower=====
Apricot was assigned to Sunflower, a pretty peach-colored pony during her stay at The Berry Prairie Dude Ranch. Sunflower was billed simply as &quot;Apricot's Pony&quot; when she was released as part of the &quot;Sugar Sweet Ponies&quot; line of PlayMates toys, the same wave that included horses for Strawberry Shortcake, Angel Cake, and Crepes' Suzette, the last of whom was not included in the &quot;Big Country Fun&quot; animated DVD adventures.

=====Daffodil=====
One of merely two PlayMates-era ponies to have both a toy AND a name, Daffodil is a sunny yellow. Dubbed &quot;Lemon Meringue's Pony&quot; by PlayMates, Daffodil was released as part of the &quot;Big Country Fun&quot;-aligned &quot;Picnic Pie Ponies&quot; wave.

=====Thunder=====
While the other ponies introduced in the &quot;Big Country Fun&quot; DVD were named after various flowers, the pony that Annie Oatmeal matched with perennial newcomer Plum Puddin' was called Thunder. A deep purple pony with a cropped lavendar mane and tail, Thunder was referred to both as a he AND a she during the course of the adventure, not unlike '''Plum Puddin''' during the course of the character's history.

=====Holiday Juice=====
The owner of Holiday Juice is by Holiday Fruits she has a [[White]] mane with berries and with a hint of purple juice her body mane is yellow spots and she is magic shows she makes she is talented.

==2009==
In late 2008, American Greetings relaunched the series with redesigned characters and changed personalities.

===Strawberry Shortcake===
Strawberry Shortcake (voiced by [[Anna Cummer]] with singing voice by [[Tracey Moore]]) is the [[protagonist]] and the title character of the ''Strawberry Shortcake'' franchise. In this version, Strawberry Shortcake runs Berry Bitty Cafe, a restaurant where she makes many treats, like her famous rainbow shake seen in one of the episodes. She also wears a strawberry-shaped hat.

===Orange Blossom===
One of Strawberry's earliest friends met in the Big Apple City in the 80s. In the present incarnation, Orange Blossom (voiced by [[Janyse Jaud]]) manages Orange Mart, a general store that sells all sorts of odds and ends, including cameras. She also wears a flower clip in her hair.

===Lemon Meringue===
Like previous versions of her franchise, her leanings towards style and glamour remain, in that she once again runs a beauty salon, Lemon Salon, in Strawberryland (although due to a reset in the series, Lemon Lane no longer exists in the new series. It's now just another shop in Berry Bitty City). Lemon's pet is yet to be reintroduced in the 2009 series. In this incarnation, she's voiced by [[Andrea Libman]]. She is also the one who saves the girls' 'bad hair days' with her creative sense of style and her skill with scissors. She wears a lemon clip in her hair. 

===Raspberry Torte===
Another of Strawberry Shortcake's earliest friends, Raspberry is yet again carried over to the 2009 relaunch. In the 2009 relaunch of the franchise, Raspberry runs the Fresh Fashions Boutique, a garment fashion shop in which she designs, makes, and sells the merchandise, such as dresses. Raspberry sometimes can get competitive when it comes to fashion with Lemon Meringue. She also wears a raspberry headband and is voiced by [[Ingrid Neilson]].

===Plum Pudding===
Still a girl in the 2009 relaunch, she is no longer a brainy character, but to be fair she is no longer a walking disaster either. She now apparently runs a dance studio in Berry Bitty City called the Sweet Steps Studio, where she teaches any type of dances, such as ballet. She also sports a ponytail with a plum clip and wears leg-warmers and voiced by [[Ashleigh Ball]]

===Blueberry Muffin===
Blueberry Muffin has been Strawberry Shortcake's friend since the very beginning, and is one of the first 6 to be reintroduced in the 2009 canon. In this version, Blueberry Muffin now runs a bookstore in Berry Bitty City called Blueberry Books, where she sells many books to read, including cookbooks for Strawberry. She also wears a blueberry headband and voiced by [[Kelly Sheridan]].

===The Berrykins===
In the rebooted series, the Berrykins are an innumerable work force of berry-headed dwarf-like creatures, nearly identical to one another with the exception of their various color schemes. The Berrykins happily tend all the Fruit and Berry Crops in the patch where Berry Bitty City is located. Instead of a Berry Princess governing them, they are now governed by a Princess Berrykin. They work in Berry Bitty Grove, where they harvest glimmerberries that can be converted into juice, which serves as the source of power in Berry Bitty City.

===Mr. Longface===

On the 2009 version of the show, Mr. Longface is a paranoid caterpillar who owns a mini golf course. He can get worried sometimes, but in the end things usually turn out fine. He wears a blue vest, walks with a wooden cane, and wears a navy blue top hat. Who voices him is currently unknown.

===The Ladybug Twins===

The ladybug twins, Sadiebug and Katiebug, are two naughty ladybug relatives of Jadybug, the mail bug. They do not live in Berry Bitty City, but often visit and cause mayhem. They both wear headbands, bracelets and glossy boots. They first appeared in the 2010 episode of &quot;Strawberry Shortcake&quot;: Strawberry's House Pests.&quot; They also appeared in the episode, &quot;Good Citizens Club.&quot;

=== Cherry Jam ===
{{Expand section|date=November 2011}}
pop star singer, has purple hair with star streaks, and wears a pink dress with pink and purple leggings,and is the latest member of berry bitty city. At first the berry girls (minus Strawberry) try too hard to get her to like them, as they act as her entourage. Not friends, the way she wishes for them to do. She is somewhat sensitive and only wishes to be treated normally.

==References==
{{reflist}}

{{Strawberry Shortcake}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:List Of Strawberry Shortcake Characters}}
[[Category:Lists of fictional children]]
[[Category:Strawberry Shortcake]]
[[Category:Lists of toy characters]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
