<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="14351449" ns="0" title="Snagit"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Ad|date=November 2011}}
{{Infobox Software
| name                   = Snagit
| logo                   = [[Image:SnagIt Icon.png|64px]]
| screenshot             = [[Image:SnagIt screenshot.png|300px|Snagit Screenshot under Windows]]
| caption                = 
| author                 = 
| developer              = [[TechSmith]]
| released               = 1990
| latest release version = 10.0.1
| latest release date    = {{release date and age|2011|04|21}}
| latest preview version = 
| latest preview date    = 
| programming language   = 
| operating system       = 
| platform               = [[Microsoft Windows|Windows]]
| language               = 
| status                 = Active
| genre                  = [[Screenshot]]
| license                = Commercial
| website                = http://www.techsmith.com/snagit
}}
'''Snagit''' is a [[screenshot]] program for [[Microsoft Windows|Windows]]. It is created and distributed by [[TechSmith]], which also makes [[Camtasia Studio]], and was first launched in 1990.&lt;ref name=&quot;About.com&quot;/&gt;  Snagit is available in English, French, German, Korean, and Japanese versions.

''Snagit'' replaces the native [[print screen]] function with additional features. It contains most features needed by [[technical writer]]s (scrolling page screenshots and automatic &quot;trim edges&quot; function, for example).{{Citation needed|date=September 2008}}

Newer versions allow batch capture of embedded items such as links, pictures, and multimedia. The user can set parameters and keyboard shortcuts to capture particular types of data, which are stored in a folder called &quot;Catalog&quot; by default. ''Snagit'' can also follow links in web pages, capturing the specified data from the linked pages.

''Snagit'' Accessories extend its features. For example, Flickr Output enables the user to upload screen captures to a [[Flickr]] account.

==Features==
A quick [[toolbar]] of Snagit can increase capture speed by either using the last capture method applied or by allowing the method to be quickly changed through an option menu.

It has a preview [[window]] which shows a zoomed thumbnail of whatever the [[Cursor (computers)|cursor]] is hovering over and a [[webpage]] catalog maker. The preview window can gather all screen captures quickly and create a webpage in five simple steps.

Snagit supports different selection formats, which are All-in-One, Full Screen, Copy to clipboard, Web page as a [[PDF]] with links, Copy text to clipboard, Free hand, and Menu with time delay. The capture tool has a batch [[converter]] which allows alteration of a large numbers of files at once. 

Snagit can automatically move screenshots to the Edit section once captured, where they can be resized, annotated, or special effects can be added.

==Critical reception==
TopTen Reviews rated the software 4/4 in all categories—the highest score of 10 comparative packages reviewed. The review highlighted the capture quality, ease of use, and support.&lt;ref&gt;[http://screen-capture-software-review.toptenreviews.com/ &quot;Screen Capture Software Review&quot;], TopTen Reviews&lt;/ref&gt; [[CNET]] rated the software 8/10, mentioning the ability to take screenshots of entire web pages, but pointed out weaknesses including a poor wizard and fewer output file formats than competitors—though this review is from July 2002.&lt;ref name=&quot;CNET&quot;&gt;[http://reviews.cnet.com/file-conversion/techsmith-snagit/4505-3685_7-8333679.html &quot;TechSmith SnagIt&quot;], [[CNET]]&lt;/ref&gt; [[About.com]] is also very positive, awarding 5/5 and pointing out the ease of use, comprehensive features, and multiple views, but they stated that text entry in the Snagit Editor is slow, lagging behind as text is typed in the [[edit box]]. This review was based on version 8.&lt;ref name=&quot;About.com&quot;&gt;[http://graphicssoft.about.com/od/screencapture/gr/snagit.htm &quot;TechSmith SnagIt 8 Screen Capture Utility for Windows&quot;], Sue Chastain, [[About.com]]&lt;/ref&gt;

==Snagit Editor==
The Snagit Editor is a basic image editing program which comes with Snagit. It can be used to make simple changes to screenshots, including adding arrows, blurring sections, or [[cropping (image)|cropping]]. Other features include adding new images called &quot;stamps&quot; onto screenshots, changing the viewing perspective of screen captures, adding annotations, using the eyedropper tool to determine the [[RGB]] values of any color, and other tools for improving the overall look of screen captures. The Snagit Editor uses [[Microsoft]]'s [[Fluent (user interface)|Fluent]] Ribbon UI.
&lt;gallery&gt;
&lt;!-- Deleted image removed: Image:SnagIt_Editor.png|The Snagit Editor --&gt;
&lt;/gallery&gt;
==See also==
* [[Camtasia Studio]]

==References==
{{reflist}}

==External links==
* [http://www.techsmith.com/snagit/ Snagit website]

[[Category:Screenshot software]]
[[Category:Screencasting software]]
[[Category:Windows software]]
[[Category:Mac_OS_software]]

[[de:SnagIt]]
[[ru:SnagIt]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
