<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="143803" ns="0" title="Tears"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Other uses|Tear (disambiguation)}}
[[Image:Tear system.svg|250px|thumb|The tear system.{{Break}}
A) Tear gland/Lacrimal gland{{Break}}
B) Superior lacrimal punctum{{Break}}
C) Superior lacrimal canal lacrimation leads to tears{{Break}}
D) Tear sac/Lacrimal sac{{Break}}
E) Inferior lacrimal punctum{{Break}}
F) Inferior lacrimal canal{{Break}}
G) Nasolacrimal canal]]

'''Tears''' are secretions that clean and lubricate the [[Human eye|eye]]s. '''Lacrimation''' or '''lachrymation''' (from [[Latin]] ''lacrima'' &quot;tear&quot;) is the production or shedding of tears.

Strong emotions such as [[Sorrow (emotion)|sorrow]] or [[Happiness|elation]], irritation of the eyes, and [[yawning]] may lead to an increased production of tears, or [[crying]].

==Physiology==
In humans, the tear film coating the eye, known as the precorneal film, has three distinct layers, from the most outer surface:

{| class=&quot;wikitable&quot; border=&quot;1&quot;
|-
!Name 
!Container(s)
!Secretors
!Functions
|-
|Lipid  layer
|[[lipid|oils]]
|[[meibomian glands]] (or tarsal glands)
|coats the aqueous layer; provides a [[hydrophobic]] barrier that evaporates and prevents tears from spilling onto the cheek.  These glands are found among the [[Tarsus (eyelids)|tarsal plates]].  Thus, the tear fluid deposits between the eye proper and oil barriers of the lids.&lt;ref name=&quot;ReferenceA&quot;&gt;&quot;eye, human.&quot;Encyclopædia Britannica from [[Encyclopædia Britannica 2006 Ultimate Reference Suite DVD]] 2009&lt;/ref&gt;
|-
|Aqueous layer
|[[water]] and other substances such as proteins (e.g., tear lipocalin, [[lactoferrin]], [[lysozyme]]&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.medrounds.org/ocular-pathology-study-guide/2005/10/tear-proteins.html Ocular Pathology Study Guide: Tear Proteins&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt; and [[lacritin]])
|[[lacrimal gland]]
|promotes spreading of the tear film; promotes the control of infectious agents; promotes osmotic regulation
|-
|Mucous layer
|[[mucin]]
|conjunctival [[goblet cells]]
|coats the [[cornea]];provides a [[hydrophilic]] layer;allows for even distribution of the tear film; covers the cornea
|}

Having a '''thin''' tear film may prevent one's ability to wear [[contact lenses]], as the amount of [[oxygen]] needed is higher than normal, and contact lenses stop oxygen from entering the eye. Eyes with thin tear film will dry out while wearing contact lenses. Special [[eye drops]] are available for contact lens wearers. Certain types of contact lenses are designed to let more oxygen through to the eye.

==Drainage of tear film==
{{Ref improve section|date=August 2007}}
The lacrimal glands secrete lacrimal fluid, which flows through the main excretory ducts into the space between the eyeball and lids.  When the eyes blink, the lacrimal fluid is spread across the surface of the eye.  Lacrimal fluid gathers in the [[lacrimal lake]], and is drawn into the [[puncta lacrimalia|puncta]] by capillary action, then flows through the [[lacrimal canaliculi]] at the inner corner of the eyelids entering the [[lacrimal sac]],&lt;ref name=&quot;ReferenceA&quot;/&gt; then on to the [[nasolacrimal duct]], and finally into the [[nasal cavity]].  An excess of tears, as with strong [[emotion]], can thus cause the nose to run.
[http://www.academy.org.uk/tutorials/dilate3.jpg]

==Types==

There are three very basic types of tears:
{| class=&quot;wikitable&quot; border=&quot;1&quot;
|-
!Category
!Description
|-
| Basal tears
|In healthy [[mammal]]ian eyes, the [[cornea]] is continually kept wet and nourished by ''basal tears''. They lubricate the eye, and help to keep it clear of [[dust]]. Tear fluid contains water, [[mucin]], [[lipids]], [[lysozyme]], [[lactoferrin]], [[lipocalin]], [[lacritin]], [[immunoglobulin]]s, [[glucose]], [[urea]], [[sodium]], and [[potassium]]. Some of the substances in lacrimal fluid (such as lysozyme) fight against [[bacteria]]l [[infection]] as a part of the [[immune system]].  Lysozyme does this by dissolving a layer in the outer coating, called peptidoglycan, of certain bacteria.  It is a typical body fluid with a salt content similar to blood plasma.  Usually, in a 24-hour period, 0.75 to 1.1&amp;nbsp;grams (0.03–0.04 ounce avoirdupois) of tears is secreted; this rate slows with age.&lt;ref name=&quot;ReferenceA&quot;/&gt;
|-
| Reflex tears
|The second type of tears results from irritation of the eye by foreign particles, or from the presence of irritant substances such as [[onion]] vapors, [[tear gas]], or [[pepper spray]] in the eye's environment, including the cornea, conjunctiva, or nasal mucosa.  It can also occur with bright light and hot or peppery stimuli to the tongue and mouth.  It is also linked with vomiting, coughing, and yawning.&lt;ref name=&quot;ReferenceA&quot;/&gt;  These ''reflex tears'' attempt to wash out irritants that may have come into contact with the eye.
|-
|[[crying|Crying or weeping]] (psychic tears)
|The third category, in general, referred to as ''crying'' or ''weeping'', is increased lacrimation due to strong [[emotional stress]], [[anger]], [[suffering]], [[mourning]], or [[Pain|physical pain]]. It DOES NOT OCCUR during the brain's [[Fight-or-flight response]] because the sympathetic nervous system inhibits lacrimation. This practice is not restricted to negative emotions; many people cry when extremely happy. In humans, ''emotional tears'' can be accompanied by reddening of the face and sobbing — cough-like, convulsive breathing, sometimes involving spasms of the whole upper body. Tears brought about by emotions have a different chemical make-up than those for lubrication; emotional tears contain more of the protein-based hormones [[prolactin]], [[adrenocorticotropic hormone]], and [[leucine]] [[enkephalin]] (a natural painkiller) than basal or reflex tears.  The [[limbic system]] is involved in production of basic emotional drives, such as anger, fear, etc.  The limbic system, to be specific, the hypothalamus, also has a degree of control over the autonomic system.  The [[parasympathetic]] branch of the [[autonomic nervous system]] controls the lacrimal glands via the neurotransmitter [[acetylcholine]] through both the [[nicotinic]] and [[muscarinic]] receptors.  When these receptors are activated, the lacrimal gland is stimulated to produce tears.&lt;ref&gt;Skorucak A. [http://www.scienceiq.com/Facts/ScienceOfTears.cfm &quot;The Science of Tears.&quot;] ScienceIQ.com. Accessed September 29, 2006.&lt;/ref&gt;
|}
[[Image:Crying-girl.jpg|thumb|A toddler producing tears due to emotional stress or pain|150px]]

===Neural Aspects===
The [[trigeminal]] V&lt;sub&gt;1&lt;/sub&gt; (fifth cranial) nerve bears the sensory pathway of the tear reflexes.  When the trigeminal nerve is cut, tears from reflexes will stop, but not emotional tears.  Likewise, application of [[cocaine]] to the surface of the eye, due to its paralyzing effect on the sensory nerve endings, inhibits the reflex even under exposure to strong tear gases.  The motor pathway is autonomic (involuntary), and, in general, uses the pathway of the [[Facial nerve|facial]] (seventh) nerve in the parasympathetic division.  In parasympathetic imitators (such as acetylcholine), more tears are produced, and an [[anticholinergic]] drug like atropine inhibits tear production.  A newborn infant has insufficient development of nervous control, so s/he &quot;cries without weeping.&quot;  If lacrimal gland malfunctions but does not cause any severe drying of the cornea, and the main lacrimal gland may be damaged in surgery or other failure of lacrimal function occur, it is not a serious matter, for the accessory glands are enough for general secretion.  In reflex situations, copious tears are produced mainly in emergencies.&lt;ref name=&quot;ReferenceA&quot;/&gt;

==Diseases and disorders==&lt;!-- This section is linked from [[Bell's palsy]] --&gt;
{{Main|List of eye diseases and disorders}}

Quality of vision is affected by the stability of the tear film.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |author=Szczesna DH, Jaro&amp;#x144;ski J, Kasprzak HT, Stenevi U |title=Interferometric measurements of dynamic changes of tear film |journal=J Biomed Opt |volume=11 |issue=3 |pages=34028 |year=2006 |pmid=16822077 |doi=10.1117/1.2209881 |url=http://link.aip.org/link/?jbo/11/34028&amp;agg=MEDLINE_JBO}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&quot;[[Crocodile tear]]s syndrome&quot; is an uncommon consequence of nerve regeneration subsequent to [[Bell's palsy]] or other damage to the [[facial nerve]] in which efferent fibers from the [[superior salivary nucleus]] become improperly connected to nerve axons projecting to the [[lacrimal glands]] (tear ducts), causing one to shed tears ([[lacrimate]]) during salivation while smelling foods or eating. It is presumed that one would also salivate while crying due to the inverse improper connection of the lacrimal nucleus to the salivary glands, but this would be less noticeable.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |author=Morais Pérez D, Dalmau Galofre J, Bernat Gili A, Ayerbe Torrero V |title=[Crocodile tears syndrome] |language=Spanish; Castilian |journal=Acta Otorrinolaringol Esp |volume=41 |issue=3 |pages=175–7 |year=1990 |pmid=2261223 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Keratoconjunctivitis sicca]], known as dry eye, is a very common disorder of the tear film.  However, sufferers can experience watering of the eyes, which is in fact a response to irritation caused by the original tear film deficiency.

[[Familial dysautonomia]] is a genetic condition that can be associated with a lack of overflow tears (alacrima) during emotional crying.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | author=Felicia B Axelrod and Gabrielle Gold-von Simson | title=Hereditary sensory and autonomic neuropathies: types II, III, and IV | journal=Orphanet Journal of Rare Diseases | date=October 3, 2007 | volume=2 | issue=39 | pmid=17915006 | pmc=2098750 | doi=10.1186/1750-1172-2-39 | url=http://www.ojrd.com/content/2/1/39  | pages=39 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Societal aspects ==
[[File:Crying boy.jpg|thumb|Crying boy]]
In nearly all cultures, crying is seen as a specific act associated with tears trickling down the cheeks and accompanied by characteristic sobbing sounds. Emotional triggers are most often sadness and grief, but crying can also be triggered by anger, happiness, fear,  laughter or [[humor]], frustration, remorse, or other strong, intense emotions.
In many cultures, crying is associated with babies and children. Some cultures consider crying to be undignified and infantile, casting aspersions on those who cry publicly, except if it is due to the death of a close friend or relative.  In most cultures, it is more socially acceptable for women and children to cry than men. In some Latin regions, crying among men is acceptable.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web| url = http://www.rd.com/living-healthy/big-boys-dont-cry----and-other-myths-about-men-and-their-emotions/article18053-1.html| title = Big Boys Don't Cry — and Other Myths About Men and Their Emotions (page 2 of 3)| accessdate = 2008-07-20| author = Dianne Hales| date = October 2005| publisher = ''[[Reader's Digest]]''}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web| url = http://www.news.com.au/couriermail/story/0,23739,23660131-23272,00.html| title = These days it's OK for men to cry, say famous guys| accessdate = 2008-07-20| author = Fran Metcalf| date = May 8, 2008| publisher = ''[[The Courier Mail]]''}} {{Dead link|date=September 2010|bot=H3llBot}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news| url = http://www.theage.com.au/articles/2003/08/27/1061663846142.html| title = Why we cry| accessdate = 2008-07-20| author = John-Paul Flintoff| date = August 30, 2003| publisher = ''[[The Age]]''}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Some modern [[psychotherapy|therapy]] movements such as [[Re-evaluation Counseling]] teach that crying is beneficial to health and mental well-being, encouraging it positively.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.rc.org/theory/recovery.html Re-evaluation Counseling site: &quot;The Recovery Process&quot;]&lt;/ref&gt;
An insincere display of grief or dishonest remorse is sometimes called [[crocodile tears]] in reference to an Ancient Greek anecdote that crocodiles would ''pretend'' to weep while luring or devouring their prey.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.worldwidewords.org/qa/qa-cro1.htm World Wide Words: Crocodile tears&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt; In addition, in medical terms, someone is said to have Crocodile tears syndrome as an uncommon consequence of recovery from [[Bell's palsy]], in which faulty regeneration of the facial nerve causes sufferers to shed tears while eating.

== Chemicals in Tears ==

In a research conducted by the [[Weizmann Institute of Science]] in Rehovot, Israel, emotional tears from women have been found to reduce sexual arousal in men. Emotional tears are made up of a different chemical component than those evoked by eye irritants and can relay chemical messages to others.&lt;ref&gt;Weaver,Janelle. ''Crying Women Turn Men Off”. Scientific American Mind, May/June 2011, p. 22, 6.&lt;/ref&gt; The change in sex drive could be attributed to the drop in testosterone provoked by the chemicals in the tears meant to reduce aggression. In the animal world, it has been found that some blind mole rats would rub tears all over their bodies as a strategy to keep aggressive mole rats away.&lt;ref&gt;Dell'Amore, Christine. [http://news.nationalgeographic.com/news/2011/01/110106-womens-tears-sex-drive-turn-off-sexual-health-arousal-men-science/ &quot; Women's Tears Reduce Sex Drive in Men, Study Hints&quot;], “National Geographic'', January 6, 2011, accessed June 6, 2011.&lt;/ref&gt;

==See also==
{{commons}}
*[[Epiphora (medical)|Epiphora]]
*[[Eyelid]]
*[[Dacryocystocele]]
*[[Professional mourning]]

==References==
{{Reflist}}

==External links==
{{wikiquote}}
{{Wiktionary}}
*{{EMedicine|ent|5|Nasolacrimal System Anatomy}}
*[http://www.nytimes.com/1984/02/22/garden/personal-health-002144.html?&amp;pagewanted=all PERSONAL HEALTH : &lt;small&gt;&quot;University of Minnesota researchers who are studying the chemical composition of tears have recently isolated two important chemicals, leucine-enkephalin and prolactin, from emotional tears. The first of these may be an endorphin, one of the body's natural pain-relieving substances. — Both chemicals are found only in tears that are shed in response to emotion. Tears shed because of exposure to a cut onion would contain no such substance.&quot;&lt;small&gt;] By JANE E. BRODY, published February 22, 1984

[[Category:Human physiology]]
[[Category:Eye]]
[[Category:Body fluids]]

[[ar:دموع]]
[[arc:ܕܡܥܬܐ]]
[[gn:Tesay]]
[[av:МагӀу]]
[[az:Göz yaşları]]
[[be:Сляза]]
[[be-x-old:Сьляза]]
[[ca:Llàgrima]]
[[cs:Slzy]]
[[sn:Misodzi]]
[[da:Tårevæske]]
[[de:Träne]]
[[dv:ކަރުނަ]]
[[es:Lágrima]]
[[eo:Larmo]]
[[fa:اشک]]
[[fr:Larme]]
[[gl:Lágrima]]
[[ko:눈물]]
[[hr:Suza]]
[[io:Lakrimo]]
[[id:Air mata]]
[[it:Lacrima]]
[[he:דמעות]]
[[jv:Luh]]
[[lbe:Макь]]
[[la:Lacrimae]]
[[lt:Ašara]]
[[ml:കണ്ണുനീർ]]
[[nl:Traan (oog)]]
[[ja:涙]]
[[no:Tårer]]
[[nn:Tåre]]
[[oc:Pleurs]]
[[pl:Łza]]
[[pt:Lágrima]]
[[ro:Lacrimă]]
[[qu:Wiqi]]
[[ru:Слеза]]
[[scn:Làcrima]]
[[sl:Solze]]
[[sh:Suze]]
[[fi:Kyynelneste]]
[[sv:Tårar]]
[[tl:Luha]]
[[te:కన్నీరు]]
[[th:น้ำตา]]
[[tr:Gözyaşı]]
[[uk:Сльози]]
[[ur:آنسو]]
[[yi:טרערן]]
[[zh-yue:眼水]]
[[zh:淚]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
