<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="144638" ns="0" title="Bhopal disaster"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">[[File:Bhopal-Union Carbide 1 crop memorial.jpg|right|upright=1.3|thumb|Bhopal memorial for those killed and disabled by the 1984 toxic gas release.]]

The '''Bhopal disaster''' (commonly referred to as '''Bhopal gas tragedy''') was a [[gas leak]] incident in [[India]], considered one of the world's worst [[List of industrial disasters|industrial catastrophe]]s.&lt;ref name=&quot;convictions&quot;&gt;{{cite news|url=http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/world/south_asia/8725140.stm|title=Bhopal trial: Eight convicted over India gas disaster |date=2010-06-07|work=[[BBC News]]|accessdate=2010-06-07}}&lt;/ref&gt; It occurred on the night of December 2–3, 1984 at the [[Union Carbide India Limited]] (UCIL) [[pesticide]] plant in [[Bhopal]], [[Madhya Pradesh]], India. A leak of [[methyl isocyanate]]  gas and other chemicals from the plant resulted in the exposure of hundreds of thousands of people. Estimates vary on the death toll. The official immediate death toll was 2,259 and the government of Madhya Pradesh has confirmed a total of 3,787 deaths related to the gas release.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.mp.gov.in/bgtrrdmp/relief.htm&lt;/ref&gt; Others estimate 3,000 died within weeks and another 8,000 have since died from gas-related diseases.&lt;ref name=&quot;Eckerman2001&quot;&gt;Eckerman (2001) (see &quot;References&quot; below).&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Eckerman2004&quot;&gt;Eckerman (2004) (see &quot;References&quot; below).&lt;/ref&gt; A government affidavit in 2006 stated the leak caused 558,125 injuries including 38,478 temporary partial and approximately 3,900 severely and permanently disabling injuries.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.first14.com/bhopal-gas-tragedy-92-injuries-termed-minor-822.html|accessdate=26 June 2010|newspaper=First14 News|date=21 June 2010|author=AK Dubey|archiveurl=http://www.webcitation.org/5qmWBEWcb|archivedate=26 June 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; As many as 25,000 deaths have been attributed to the disaster in recent estimates.&lt;ref name=&quot;Tehelka2010&quot;&gt; {{cite news | first = Shoma | last = Chadhury | coauthors = Shantanu Guha Ray | title = For A Few Pieces Of Silver | date = 2010-06-26 | url = http://www.tehelka.com/story_main45.asp?filename=Ne260610coverstory.asp | work = Tehelka | accessdate = 2011-12-04}}&lt;/ref&gt;

UCIL was the Indian subsidiary of [[Union Carbide]] Corporation (UCC), with Indian Government controlled banks and the Indian public holding a 49.1 percent stake. In 1994, the Supreme Court of India allowed UCC to sell its 50.9 percent share. Union Carbide sold UCIL, the Bhopal plant operator, to [[Eveready Industries|Eveready Industries India Limited]] in 1994. The Bhopal plant was later sold to McLeod Russel (India) Ltd.  [[Dow Chemical Company]] purchased UCC in 2001.

Civil and criminal cases are pending in the United States District Court, Manhattan and the District Court of Bhopal, India, involving UCC, UCIL employees, and [[Warren Anderson (chairman)|Warren Anderson]], UCC CEO at the time of the disaster.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |publisher=[[New York Times]] |title=Company Defends Chief in Bhopal Disaster |url=http://dealbook.blogs.nytimes.com/2009/08/03/company-defends-chief-in-bhopal-disaster/ | date=2009-08-03 | accessdate=2010-04-26}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |publisher=[[CBS News]] |title=U.S. Exec Arrest Sought in Bhopal Disaster |url=http://www.cbsnews.com/stories/2009/07/31/world/main5201155.shtml | date=2009-07-31}}&lt;/ref&gt; In June 2010, seven ex-employees, including the former UCIL chairman, were convicted in Bhopal of causing death by negligence and sentenced to two years imprisonment and a fine of about $2,000 each, the maximum punishment allowed by law. An eighth former employee was also convicted, but died before judgment was passed.&lt;ref name=&quot;convictions&quot; /&gt;

==Summary of background ==
The UCIL factory was built in 1969 to produce the pesticide Sevin (UCC's brand name for [[carbaryl]]) using methyl isocyanate (MIC) as an intermediate. An MIC production plant was added in 1979.&lt;ref name=&quot;UCCmanual1976&quot;&gt;UCC manual (1976).&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;UCCmanual1978&quot;&gt;UCC manual (1978).&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;UCCmanual1979&quot;&gt;UCC manual (1979).&lt;/ref&gt;

During the night of December 2–3, 1984, water entered a tank containing 42 tons of MIC. The resulting [[exothermic reaction]] increased the temperature inside the tank to over {{convert|200|°C|°F}} and raised the pressure. The tank vented releasing toxic gases into the atmosphere. The gases were blown by northwesterly winds over Bhopal.

Theories differ as to how the water entered the tank. At the time, workers were cleaning out a clogged pipe with water about 400 feet from the tank.  The operators assumed that owing to bad maintenance and leaking valves, it was possible for the water to leak into the tank.&lt;ref name=&quot;Chouhan&quot;&gt;Chouhan ''et al.'' (2004).&lt;/ref&gt; However, this water entry route could not be reproduced.&lt;ref name=&quot;Weisman NYT Dec 1985 p.5&quot;&gt;{{cite news|author=Steven R. Weisman|title=Bhopal a Year Later: An Eerie Silence|publisher=''The New York Times''|pate=Dec. 5, 1985|page=5}}&lt;/ref&gt; UCC also maintains that this route was not possible, but instead alleges water was introduced directly into the tank as an act of sabotage by a disgruntled worker via a connection to a missing pressure gauge on the top of the tank. Early the next morning, a UCIL manager asked the instrument engineer to replace the gauge. UCIL's investigation team found no evidence of the necessary connection; however, the investigation was totally controlled by the government denying UCC investigators access to the tank or interviews with the operators.&lt;ref name=&quot;Kalelkar&quot;&gt;Kalelkar (1988).&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;tradeunion&quot;&gt;Trade Union Report (1985).&lt;/ref&gt;
The 1985 reports give a picture of what led to the disaster and how it developed, although they differ in details.&lt;ref name=&quot;tradeunion&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;UCC1985&quot;&gt;UCC Investigation Report (1985).&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Varadarajan&quot;&gt;Varadarajan (1985).&lt;/ref&gt;

Factors leading to the magnitude of the gas leak include:

* Storing MIC in large tanks and filling beyond recommended levels
* Poor maintenance after the plant ceased MIC production at the end of 1984
* Failure of several safety systems (due to poor maintenance)
* Safety systems being switched off to save money—including the MIC tank refrigeration system which could have mitigated the disaster severity

The problem was made worse by the mushrooming of slums in the vicinity of the plant, non-existent catastrophe plans, and shortcomings in health care and socio-economic rehabilitation.&lt;ref name=&quot;Eckerman2001&quot;&gt;Eckerman (2001).&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Eckerman2004&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Eckerman2005&quot;&gt;Eckerman (2005) (see &quot;References&quot; below).&lt;/ref&gt;

===Public information===
Much speculation arose in the aftermath. The closing of the plant to outsiders (including UCC) by the Indian government and the failure to make data public contributed to the confusion. The initial investigation was conducted entirely by Council of Scientific and Industrial Research (CSIR) and the Central Bureau of Investigation.  CSIR was forbidden to publish health effect data until after 1994. &lt;ref name=&quot;Eckerman2004&quot;&gt;Eckerman (2004).&lt;/ref&gt;

===Plant production process===
[[File:Preparation of carbaryl as in Bhopal.png|thumb|upright=1.4|right|[[Methylamine]] ('''1''') reacts with [[phosgene]] ('''2''') producing [[methyl isocyanate]] ('''3''') which reacts with [[1-naphthol]] ('''4''') to yield [[carbaryl]] ('''5''')]]
UCC produced carbaryl using MIC as an intermediate.&lt;ref name=&quot;Eckerman2004&quot; /&gt; After the Bhopal plant was built, other manufacturers including [[Bayer]] produced carbaryl without MIC, though at a greater [[manufacturing cost]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Kovel&quot;&gt;Kovel (2002).&lt;/ref&gt; However, Bayer also uses the UCC process at the chemical plant once owned by UCC at Institute, West Virginia, USA and many other states

==Contributing factors==
Other factors identified by the inquiry included: use of a more dangerous pesticide manufacturing method, large-scale MIC storage, plant location close to a densely populated area, undersized safety devices, and the dependence on manual operations.&lt;ref name=&quot;Eckerman2004&quot; /&gt;

Plant management deficiencies were also identified&amp;nbsp;– lack of skilled operators, reduction of safety management, insufficient maintenance, and inadequate emergency action plans.&lt;ref name=&quot;Eckerman2004&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Eckerman2006&quot;&gt;Eckerman (2006) (see &quot;References&quot; below).&lt;/ref&gt;

The chemical process, or &quot;route&quot;, used in the Bhopal plant reacted [[methylamine]] with [[phosgene]] to form MIC (methyl isocyanate), which was then reacted with [[1-naphthol]] to form the final product, carbaryl. This route differs from MIC-free routes used elsewhere, in which the same raw materials are combined in a different manufacturing order, with phosgene first reacted with naphthol to form a chloroformate ester, which is then reacted with methyl amine. In the early 1980s, the demand for pesticides had fallen, but production continued, leading to buildup of stores of unused MIC.&lt;ref name=&quot;Eckerman2004&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Kovel&quot; /&gt;

{{See also|Carbaryl#Production}}

===Work conditions===
Attempts to reduce expenses affected the factory's employees and their conditions. Kurzman argues that &quot;cuts...meant less stringent quality control and thus looser safety rules. A pipe leaked? Don't replace it, employees said they were told&amp;nbsp;... MIC workers needed more training? They could do with less. Promotions were halted, seriously affecting employee morale and driving some of the most skilled&amp;nbsp;... elsewhere&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;Kurzman1987&quot;&gt;Kurzman (1987).&lt;/ref&gt; Workers were forced to use English manuals, even though only a few had a grasp of the language.&lt;ref name=&quot;Chouhan&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Cassels&quot;&gt;Cassels (1983).&lt;/ref&gt;

By 1984, only six of the original twelve operators were still working with MIC and the number of supervisory personnel was also cut in half. No maintenance supervisor was placed on the night shift and instrument readings were taken every two hours, rather than the previous and required one-hour readings.&lt;ref name=&quot;Chouhan&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Kurzman1987&quot; /&gt; Workers made complaints about the cuts through their union but were ignored. One employee was fired after going on a 15-day hunger strike. 70% of the plant's employees were fined before the disaster for refusing to deviate from the proper safety regulations under pressure from management.&lt;ref name=&quot;Chouhan&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Kurzman1987&quot; /&gt;

In addition, some observers, such as those writing in the Trade Environmental Database (TED) Case Studies as part of the Mandala Project from [[American University]], have pointed to &quot;serious communication problems and management gaps between Union Carbide and its Indian operation&quot;, characterized by &quot;the parent companies [''sic''] hands-off approach to its overseas operation&quot; and &quot;cross-cultural barriers&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;TED&quot;&gt;TED case 233 (1997).&lt;/ref&gt;

===Equipment and safety regulations===
[[File:Bhopal-Union Carbide 2.jpg|right|thumb|250px|Union Carbide MIC plant]]
In 1998, during civil action suits in India, it emerged that the plant was not prepared for problems. No action plans had been established to cope with incidents of this magnitude. This included not informing local authorities of the quantities or dangers of chemicals used and manufactured at Bhopal.&lt;ref name=Eckerman2001/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Eckerman2004&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Chouhan&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Kovel&quot;/&gt;
* The MIC tank alarms had not worked for four years.&lt;ref name=Eckerman2001/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Eckerman2004&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Chouhan&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=Lepowski&gt;Lepowski (1994).&lt;/ref&gt;
* There was only one manual back-up system, compared to a four-stage system used in the US.&lt;ref name=Eckerman2001/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Eckerman2004&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Chouhan&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=Lepowski/&gt;
* The flare tower and several vent gas scrubbers had been out of service for five months before the disaster. Only one gas scrubber was operating, and it could not treat such a great amuont of MIC with [[sodium hydroxide]] (caustic soda), bringing the concentration down to a safe level.&lt;ref name=Lepowski/&gt;. In fact, The maximum amount of MIC the scrubber could handle was only a quarter of the pressure during the leak. The flare tower could only hold a quarter of the gas that leaked in 1984, and moreover it was out of order at the time of the incident.&lt;ref name=Eckerman2001/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Eckerman2004&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Chouhan&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=Weir&gt;Weir (1987).&lt;/ref&gt;
* To reduce energy costs, the refrigeration system was idle. The MIC was kept at 20 degrees Celsius, not the 4.5 degrees advised by the manual.&lt;ref name=Eckerman2001/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Eckerman2004&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Chouhan&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=Lepowski/&gt;
* The steam boiler, intended to clean the pipes, was out of action for unknown reasons.&lt;ref name=Eckerman2001/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Eckerman2004&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Chouhan&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=Lepowski/&gt;
* Slip-blind plates that would have prevented water from pipes being cleaned from leaking into the MIC tanks through faulty valves were not installed. Their installation had been omitted from the cleaning checklist.&lt;ref name=Eckerman2001/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Eckerman2004&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Chouhan&quot;/&gt;
* The water pressure was too weak to spray the escaping gases from the stack. They could not spray high enough to reduce the concentration of escaping gas.&lt;ref name=Eckerman2001/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Eckerman2004&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Chouhan&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=Lepowski/&gt;
* According to the operators the MIC tank pressure gauge had been malfunctioning for roughly a week. Other tanks were used rather than repairing the gauge. The build-up in temperature and pressure is believed to have affected the magnitude of the gas release.&lt;ref name=Eckerman2001/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Eckerman2004&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Chouhan&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=Lepowski/&gt; UCC investigation studies have disputed this hypothesis.
* Carbon steel valves were used at the factory, even though they corrode when exposed to acid.&lt;ref name=&quot;Kovel&quot;/&gt;
* UCC admitted in their own investigation report that most of the safety systems were not functioning on the night of December 3, 1984.&lt;ref name=&quot;UCC1985&quot;/&gt;
* The design of the MIC plant, following government guidelines, was &quot;Indianized&quot; by UCIL engineers to maximize the use of indigenous materials and products. Mumbai based Humphreys and Glasgow Consultants PVT. Ltd. were the main consultants, Larsen and Toubro fabricated the MIC storage tanks, and Taylor of India Ltd. provided the instrumentation.&lt;ref name=D&gt;D'Silva, The Black Box of Bhopal (2006).&lt;/ref&gt;

==Previous warnings and incidents==
A series of prior warnings and MIC-related incidents had occurred:
* In 1976, the two trade unions reacted because of pollution within the plant.&lt;ref name=&quot;Eckerman2004&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Eckerman2006&quot;&gt;Eckerman (2006).&lt;/ref&gt;
* In 1981, a worker was splashed with [[phosgene]]. In panic he ripped off his mask, thus inhaling a large amount of phosgene gas; he died 72 hours later.&lt;ref name=&quot;Eckerman2004&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Eckerman2006&quot; /&gt;
* In January 1982, there was a phosgene leak, when 24 workers were exposed and had to be admitted to hospital. None of the workers had been ordered to wear protective masks.
* In February 1982, an MIC leak affected 18 workers.&lt;ref name=&quot;Eckerman2004&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Eckerman2006&quot; /&gt;
* In August 1982, a chemical engineer came into contact with liquid MIC, resulting in burns over 30 percent of his body.&lt;ref name=&quot;Eckerman2004&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Eckerman2006&quot; /&gt;
* In October 1982, there was a leak of MIC, methylcarbaryl chloride, chloroform and hydrochloric acid. In attempting to stop the leak, the MIC supervisor suffered intensive chemical burns and two other workers were severely exposed to the gases.&lt;ref name=&quot;Eckerman2004&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Eckerman2006&quot; /&gt;
* During 1983 and 1984, leaks of the following substances regularly took place in the MIC plant: MIC, chlorine, monomethylamine, phosgene, and [[carbon tetrachloride]], sometimes in combination.&lt;ref name=&quot;Eckerman2004&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Eckerman2006&quot; /&gt;
* Reports issued months before the incident by UCC engineers warned of the possibility of an incident almost identical to that which occurred in Bhopal. The reports never reached UCC's senior management.&lt;ref name=&quot;Eckerman2004&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Kovel&quot; /&gt;
* UCC was warned by American experts who visited the plant after 1981 of the potential of a &quot;[[Thermal runaway|runaway reaction]]&quot; in the MIC storage tank. Local Indian authorities warned the company of problems on several occasions from 1979 onwards.&lt;ref name=&quot;Eckerman2004&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Kovel&quot; /&gt;

==The leakage==
In November 1984, most of the safety systems were not functioning. Many valves and lines were in poor condition. Tank 610 contained 42 tons of MIC (disputed), much more than safety rules allowed.&lt;ref name=&quot;Eckerman2004&quot; /&gt; During the nights of 2–3 December, a large amount of water is claimed to have entered tank 610. A [[Thermal runaway|runaway reaction]] started, which was accelerated by contaminants, high temperatures and other factors. The reaction generated a major increase in the temperature inside the tank to over 200&amp;nbsp;°C (400&amp;nbsp;°F). This forced the emergency venting of pressure from the MIC holding tank, releasing a large volume of toxic gases. The reaction was sped up by the presence of iron from corroding non-stainless steel pipelines.&lt;ref name=&quot;Eckerman2004&quot; /&gt; Workers cleaned pipelines with water and claim they were not told to isolate the tank with a pipe slip-blind plate. Because of this, and the bad maintenance, the workers consider it possible for water to have accidentally entered the tank.&lt;ref name=&quot;Eckerman2004&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Chouhan&quot; /&gt; UCC maintains that a &quot;disgruntled worker&quot; deliberately connected a hose to a pressure gauge connection.&lt;ref name=&quot;Eckerman2004&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Kalelkar&quot; /&gt;

==Health effects==
===Short term health effects===
[[File:Glutathione + Methylisocyanate Reaction.png|thumb|Reversible reaction of [[glutathione]] (top) with [[methyl isocyanate]] (MIC, middle) allows the MIC to be transported into the body]]
The leakage caused many short term health effects in the surrounding areas. Apart from MIC, the gas cloud may have contained [[phosgene]], [[hydrogen cyanide]], [[carbon monoxide]], [[hydrogen chloride]], [[Nitrogen oxide|oxides of nitrogen]], [[Methylamine|monomethyl amine]] (MMA) and [[carbon dioxide]], either produced in the storage tank or in the atmosphere.&lt;ref name=&quot;Eckerman2004&quot; /&gt;

The gas cloud was composed mainly of materials denser than the surrounding air, stayed close to the ground and spread outwards through the surrounding community. The initial effects of exposure were coughing, vomiting, severe eye irritation and a feeling of suffocation. People awakened by these symptoms fled away from the plant. Those who ran inhaled more than those who had a vehicle to ride. Owing to their height, children and other people of shorter stature inhaled higher concentrations. Many people were trampled trying to escape.&lt;ref name=&quot;Eckerman2004&quot; /&gt;

Thousands of people had succumbed by the morning hours. There were mass funerals and mass cremations as well as disposal of bodies in the Narmada river. 170,000 people were treated at hospitals and temporary dispensaries. 2,000 buffalo, goats, and other animals were collected and buried. Within a few days, leaves on trees yellowed and fell off. Supplies, including food, became scarce owing to suppliers' safety fears. Fishing was prohibited causing further supply shortages.&lt;ref name=&quot;Eckerman2004&quot; /&gt;

A total of 36 wards were marked by the authorities as being &quot;gas affected&quot;, affecting a population of 520,000. Of these, 200,000 were below 15 years of age, and 3,000 were pregnant women. In 1991, 3,928 deaths had been certified. Independent organizations recorded 8,000 dead in the first days. Other estimations vary between 10,000 and 30,000. Another 100,000 to 200,000 people are estimated to have permanent injuries of different degrees.&lt;ref name=&quot;Eckerman2004&quot; /&gt;

The acute symptoms were burning in the respiratory tract and eyes, [[blepharospasm]], breathlessness, stomach pains and vomiting. The causes of deaths were [[choking]], reflexogenic [[circulatory collapse]] and [[pulmonary oedema]]. Findings during [[autopsy|autopsies]] revealed changes not only in the lungs but also [[cerebral oedema]], [[tubular necrosis]] of the kidneys, [[Fatty liver|fatty degeneration of the liver]] and necrotising [[enteritis]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Sriramachari&quot;&gt;Sriramachari (2004).&lt;/ref&gt; The [[stillbirth]] rate increased by up to 300% and [[Perinatal mortality#Neonatal mortality|neonatal mortality]] rate by 200%.&lt;ref name=&quot;Eckerman2004&quot; /&gt;

===Hydrogen cyanide debate===
Whether [[hydrogen cyanide]] was present in the gas mixture is still a controversy.&lt;ref name=&quot;Sriramachari&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;GassertDhara&quot;&gt;Gassert TH, Dhara VR, (2005).&lt;/ref&gt;
Exposed to high temperatures, MIC breaks down to hydrogen cyanide (HCN). According to Kulling and Lorin, at +200&amp;nbsp;°C, 3% of the gas is HCN.&lt;ref name=&quot;Kulling&quot;&gt;Kulling and Lorin (1987).&lt;/ref&gt; However, according to another scientific publication,&lt;ref&gt;P.G. Blake and S. Ijadi-Maghsoodi, Kinetics and Mechanism of Thermal Decomposition of Methyl Isocyanate, ''International Journal of Chemical Kinetics'', vol.14, (1982), pp. 945–952.&lt;/ref&gt; MIC when heated in the gas-phase starts to break down to hydrogen cyanide (HCN) and other products above 400&amp;nbsp;°C. Concentrations of 300 ppm can lead to immediate collapse.

Laboratory replication studies by CSIR and UCC scientists failed to detect any HCN or HCN-derived side products. Chemically, HCN is known to be very reactive with MIC.&lt;ref&gt;K.H. Slotta, R. Tschesche, ''Berichte'', vol.60, 1927, p.1031.&lt;/ref&gt; HCN is also known to react with hydrochloric acid, ammonia, and methylamine (also produced in tank 610 during the vigorous reaction with water and chloroform) and also with itself under acidic conditions to form trimers of HCN called triazenes. None of the HCN-derived side products were detected in the tank residue.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | last1 = Grundmann | first1 = Christoph | last2 = Kreutzberger | first2 = Alfred | title = Triazines. IX. 1,3,5-Triazine and its Formation from Hydrocyanic Acid | journal = J. Am. Chem. Soc. |volume=76 |year= 1954 |pages= 5646–5650 | doi = 10.1021/ja01651a013 | issue = 22 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

The non-toxic antidote [[sodium thiosulfate]] (Na&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;S&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;O&lt;sub&gt;3&lt;/sub&gt;) in intravenous injections increases the rate of conversion from cyanide to non-toxic thiocyanate. Treatment was suggested early and tentatively used on some people, but it did not provide any significative relief.&lt;ref&gt;jean de maleissye, Histoire du poison, 1991.&lt;/ref&gt;
In this way, bronchodilators were proven more effective as could in part reverse the acute respiratory failure caused by pulmonary edema due to MIC.&lt;ref&gt;jean de maleissye, Histoire du poison, 1991.&lt;/ref&gt; Initial reports based on the autopsies of victims' bodies suggested cyanide poisoning based on which Dr.Bipan Avashia of Union Carbide advised Amyl Nitrate and Sodium Thiosulphate.&lt;ref name='ThePittsburghPress1985'&gt; {{cite news | first = Shyam | last = Bhatia | title = Cyanide gas reported present in fatal chemical leak at Bhopal | date = 1985-11-13 | url = http://news.google.com/newspapers?id=WBwhAAAAIBAJ&amp;sjid=JmMEAAAAIBAJ&amp;pg=6985,8167738&amp;dq=bhopal+cyanide&amp;hl=en | work = The Pittsburgh Press | accessdate = 2011-12-04}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name='ThePalmBeachPost1987'&gt; {{cite news | title = Killing fog covered 25 miles; Assurances false: MIC worse than tear gas | date = 1987-11-30 | url = http://news.google.com/newspapers?id=LyYuAAAAIBAJ&amp;sjid=D88FAAAAIBAJ&amp;pg=3139,8927887&amp;dq=bhopal+cyanide&amp;hl=en | work = The Palm Beach Post | accessdate = 2011-12-04}}&lt;/ref&gt; However, critics argue that both the Government and Union Carbide tried to avoid mentioning the emotionally provocative word &quot;cyanide.&quot;&lt;ref name='ThePalmBeachPost1987'/&gt;

===Long term health effects===
[[File:BHOPAL (231583728).jpg|thumb|Victims of Bhopal disaster asking for Warren Anderson's extradition from the USA]]
It is estimated 100,000 to 200,000 people have permanent injuries. Reported symptoms are eye problems, [[respiratory]] difficulties, immune and neurological disorders, cardiac failure secondary to lung injury, female reproductive difficulties and birth defects among children born to affected women.&lt;ref name=&quot;Eckerman2004&quot; /&gt; The Indian Government and UCC deny permanent injuries were caused by MIC or the other gases.

==Aftermath of the leakage==

* Medical staff were unprepared for the thousands of casualties.&lt;ref name=&quot;Eckerman2004&quot; /&gt;
* Doctors and hospitals were not informed of proper treatment methods for MIC gas inhalation. They were told to simply give cough medicine and eye drops to their patients.&lt;ref name=&quot;Eckerman2004&quot; /&gt;
* The gases immediately caused visible damage to the trees. Within a few days, all the leaves fell off.&lt;ref name=&quot;Eckerman2004&quot; /&gt;
* 2,000 bloated animal carcasses had to be disposed of.&lt;ref name=&quot;Eckerman2004&quot; /&gt;
* &quot;Operation Faith&quot;: On December 16, the tanks 611 and 619 were emptied of the remaining MIC. This led to a second mass evacuation from Bhopal.&lt;ref name=&quot;Eckerman2004&quot; /&gt;
* Complaints of a lack of information or misinformation were widespread. The Bhopal plant medical doctor did not have proper information about the properties of the gases. An Indian Government spokesman said that &quot;Carbide is more interested in getting information from us than in helping our relief work.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;Eckerman2004&quot; /&gt;
* As of 2008, UCC had not released information about the possible composition of the cloud.&lt;ref name=&quot;Eckerman2004&quot; /&gt;
* Formal statements were issued that air, water, vegetation and foodstuffs were safe within the city. At the same time, people were informed that poultry was unaffected, but were warned not to consume fish.&lt;ref name=&quot;Eckerman2004&quot; /&gt;

===Compensation from Union Carbide===
* The Government of India passed the Bhopal Gas Leak Disaster Act that gave the government rights to represent all victims in or outside India.&lt;ref name= &quot;Eckerman2004&quot; /&gt;
* UCC offered US $350 million, the insurance sum.&lt;ref name=&quot;Eckerman2004&quot; /&gt; The Government of India claimed US$ {{Nowrap|3.3 billion}} from UCC.&lt;ref name=&quot;Eckerman2004&quot; /&gt; In 1989, a settlement was reached under which UCC agreed to pay {{Nowrap|US$470 million}} (the insurance sum, plus interest) in a full and final settlement of its civil and criminal liability.&lt;ref name=&quot;Eckerman2004&quot; /&gt;
* When UCC wanted to sell its shares in UCIL, it was directed by the Supreme Court to finance a 500-bed hospital for the medical care of the survivors. Bhopal Memorial Hospital and Research Centre (BMHRC) was inaugurated in 1998. It was obliged to give free care for survivors for eight years.&lt;ref name=&quot;Eckerman2004&quot; /&gt;

===Economic rehabilitation===
* After the incident, no one under the age of 18 was registered. The number of children exposed to the gases was at least 200,000.&lt;ref name=&quot;Eckerman2004&quot; /&gt;
* Immediate relief was decided two days after the [[Tragedy (event)|tragedy]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Eckerman2004&quot; /&gt;
* Relief measures commenced in 1985 when food was distributed for a short period and ration cards were distributed.&lt;ref name=&quot;Eckerman2004&quot; /&gt;
* Widow pension of the rate of Rs 200/per month (later Rs 750) was provided.&lt;ref name=&quot;Eckerman2004&quot; /&gt;
* One-time ex-gratia payment of Rs 1,500 to families with monthly income Rs 500 or less was decided.&lt;ref name=&quot;Eckerman2004&quot; /&gt;
* Each claimant was to be categorised by a doctor. In court, the claimants were expected to prove &quot;beyond reasonable doubt&quot; that death or injury in each case was attributable to exposure. In 1992, 44 percent of the claimants still had to be medically examined.&lt;ref name=&quot;Eckerman2004&quot; /&gt;
* From 1990 interim relief of Rs 200 was paid to everyone in the family who was born before the disaster.&lt;ref name=&quot;Eckerman2004&quot; /&gt;
* The final compensation (including interim relief) for personal injury was for the majority Rs 25,000 (US$ 830). For death claim, the average sum paid out was Rs 62,000 (US$ 2,058).&lt;ref name=&quot;Eckerman2004&quot; /&gt;
* Effects of interim relief were more children sent to school, more money spent on treatment, more money spent on food, improvement of housing conditions.&lt;ref name=&quot;Eckerman2004&quot; /&gt;
* The management of registration and distribution of relief showed many shortcomings.&lt;ref name=&quot;singh&quot;&gt;Singh (2008).&lt;/ref&gt;
* In 2007, 1,029,517 cases were registered and decided. Number of awarded cases were 574,304 and number of rejected cases 455,213. Total compensation awarded was Rs.1,546.47 crores.&lt;ref name=&quot;GovMP&quot;&gt;{{cite web |title=Bhopal Gas Tragedy Relief and Rehabilitation Department |date=2008-12-05 |url=http://www.mp.gov.in/bgtrrdmp/}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*On June 24, the [[Union Cabinet]] of the [[Government of India]] approved a [[Indian Rupee|Rs]]1265[[Crore|cr]] aid package. It will be funded by Indian taxpayers through the government.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.dnaindia.com/india/report_bhopal-gas-tragedy-extra-aid-to-help-just-42000-victims_1400833&lt;/ref&gt;

===Occupational rehabilitation===
* 33 of the 50 planned work-sheds for gas victims started. All except one was closed down by 1992.&lt;ref name=&quot;Eckerman2004&quot; /&gt;
* 1986, the MP government invested in the Special Industrial Area Bhopal. 152 of the planned 200 work-sheds were built. In 2000, 16 were partially functioning.&lt;ref name=&quot;Eckerman2004&quot; /&gt;
* It is estimated that 50,000 persons need alternative jobs, and that less than 100 gas victims have found regular employment under the government's scheme.&lt;ref name=&quot;Eckerman2004&quot; /&gt;

===Habitation rehabilitation===
* 2,486 flats in two- and four-story buildings were constructed in the &quot;Widows colony&quot; outside Bhopal. The water did not reach the upper floors. It was not possible to keep cattle. Infrastructure like buses, schools, etc. were missing for at least a decade.&lt;ref name=&quot;Eckerman2004&quot; /&gt;

===Health care===
* In the immediate aftermath of the disaster, the health care system became tremendously overloaded. Within weeks, the State Government established a number of hospitals, clinics and mobile units in the gas-affected area.&lt;ref name=&quot;Eckerman2004&quot; /&gt;
* Radical health groups set up JSK (the People's Health Centre) that was working a few years from 1985.&lt;ref name=&quot;Eckerman2004&quot; /&gt;
* Since the leak, a very large number of private practitioners have opened in Bhopal. In the severely affected areas, nearly 70 percent do not appear to be professionally qualified.&lt;ref name=&quot;Eckerman2004&quot; /&gt;
* The Government of India has focused primarily on increasing the hospital-based services for gas victims. Several hospitals have been built after the disaster. In 1994, there were approximately 1.25 beds per 1,000, compared to the recommendation from the World bank of 1.0 beds per 1,000 in developing countries.&lt;ref name=&quot;Eckerman2004&quot; /&gt;
* [http://bmhrc.org The Bhopal Memorial Hospital and Research Centre] (BMHRC) is a 350-bedded super speciality hospital. Heart surgery and hemodialysis are done. Major specialities missing are gynecology, obstetrics and pediatrics. Eight mini-units (outreach health centers) were started. Free health care for gas victims should be offered until 2006.&lt;ref name=&quot;Eckerman2004&quot; /&gt; The management has faced problems with strikes, and the quality of the health care is disputed.&lt;ref name=&quot;BMHT2005&quot;&gt;[http://www.hindu.com/2005/07/04/stories/2005070401510500.htm Bhopal Memorial Hospital closed indefinitely] The Hindu 4.7.2005.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;BMHT2006&quot;&gt;[http://www.bhopal.net/delhi-marchers/factsheets/BMHT%20sheet.pdf Bhopal Memorial Hospital Trust](2001).&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[Sambhavna Trust]] is a charitable trust that registered in 1995. The clinic gives [[modern medicine|modern]] and [[Ayurvedic]] treatments to gas victims, free of charge.&lt;ref name=&quot;Eckerman2004&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;sambhavna&quot;&gt;{{cite web |publisher=Sambhavna Trust |title=The Bhopal Medical appeal |url=http://www.bhopal.org}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Environmental rehabilitation===

* When the factory was closed in 1985–1986, pipes, drums and tanks were sold. The MIC and the Sevin plants are still there, as are storages of different residues. Isolation material is falling down and spreading.&lt;ref name=&quot;Eckerman2004&quot; /&gt;

* The area around the plant was used as a dumping area for hazardous chemicals. In 1982 [[tubewell]]s in the vicinity of the UCC factory had to be abandoned.&lt;ref name=&quot;Eckerman2004&quot; /&gt; UCC's laboratory tests in 1989 revealed that soil and water samples collected from near the factory and inside the plant were toxic to fish.&lt;ref name=&quot;UCC1989&quot;&gt;UCC (1989).&lt;/ref&gt; Several other studies have shown polluted soil and groundwater in the area.&lt;ref name=&quot;Eckerman2004&quot; /&gt;

* Reported polluting compounds include [[naphthol]]{{dn|date=September 2011}}, [[naphthalene]], [[Carbaryl|Sevin]], [[tar|tarry residue]], [[mercury (element)|mercury]], toxic [[organochlorine]]s, volatile organochlorine compounds, [[chromium]], [[copper]], [[nickel]], [[lead]], [[hexachloroethane]], [[hexachlorobutadiene]], and the pesticide [[Hexachlorocyclohexane|HCH]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Eckerman2004&quot; /&gt;

* In order to provide safe drinking water to the population around the UCC factory, there is a scheme for improvement of water supply.&lt;ref name=&quot;GovMP&quot; /&gt;
* In December 2008, the Madhya Pradesh High Court decided that the toxic waste should be incinerated at [[Ankleshwar]] in [[Gujarat]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Times of India 16 Dec 2008&quot;&gt;{{cite news |first= |last= |coauthors= |authorlink= |title=Carbide waste to go: HC |date=16 December 2008 |publisher= |url=http://timesofindia.indiatimes.com/India/Carbide_waste_to_go_HC/articleshow/3847412.cms |work= The Times Of India|pages= |accessdate=2009-01-07 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Union Carbide's defense==
Now owned by [[Dow Chemical Company]], Union Carbide denies allegations against it on its website dedicated to the tragedy. The corporation claims that the incident was the result of sabotage, stating that safety systems were in place and operative. It also stresses that it did all it could to alleviate human suffering following the disaster.&lt;ref name=&quot;ucs&quot;&gt;{{cite web |title=Statement of Union Carbide Corporation Regarding the Bhopal Tragedy |url=http://www.bhopal.com/ucs.htm |publisher=Bhopal Information Center, UCC}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Investigation into possible sabotage===
Theories differ as to how the water entered the tank. At the time, workers were cleaning out pipes with water. The workers maintain that entry of water through the plant's piping system during the washing of lines was possible because a slip-blind was not used, the downstream bleeder lines were partially clogged, many valves were leaking, and the tank was not pressurized. The water, which was not draining properly through the bleeder valves, may have built up in the pipe, rising high enough to pour back down through another series of lines in the MIC storage tank. Once water had accumulated to a height of 6 meters (20&amp;nbsp;feet), it could drain by gravity flow back into the system. Alternatively, the water may have been routed through another standby &quot;jumper line&quot; that had only recently been connected to the system. Indian scientists suggested that additional water might have been introduced as a &quot;back-flow&quot; from the defectively designed vent-gas scrubber.&lt;ref name=&quot;Eckerman2004&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Chouhan&quot; /&gt; However, none of these postulated routes of entry could be duplicated when tested by the Central Bureau of Investigators (CBI) and UCIL engineers.
The company cites an investigation conducted by the engineering consulting firm [[Arthur D. Little]], which concluded that a single employee secretly and deliberately introduced a large amount of water into the MIC tank by removing a meter and connecting a water hose directly to the tank through the metering port.&lt;ref name=&quot;Kalelkar&quot; /&gt; Carbide claims such a large amount of water could not have found its way into the tank by accident, and safety systems were not designed to deal with intentional sabotage. Documents cited in the Arthur D. Little Report state that the Central Bureau of Investigation (CBI) along with UCIL engineers tried to simulate the water-washing hypothesis as a route of the entry of water into the tank. This all-important test failed to support this as a route of water entry. UCC claims the plant staff falsified numerous records to distance themselves from the incident, and that the Indian Government impeded its investigation and declined to prosecute the employee responsible, presumably because that would weaken its allegations of negligence by Union Carbide.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.bhopal.com/faq.htm |title=Frequently Asked Questions |month=November |year=2009 |work=Bhopal Information Center |publisher=Union Carbide Corporation |accessdate=4 April 2010 |quote=The Indian authorities are well aware of the identity of the employee [who sabotaged the plant] and the nature of the evidence against him. Indian authorities refused to pursue this individual because they, as litigants, were not interested in proving that anyone other than Union Carbide was to blame for the tragedy.}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Safety and equipment issues===
The corporation denies the claim that the valves on the tank were malfunctioning, claiming that &quot;documented evidence gathered after the incident showed that the valve close to the plant's water-washing operation was closed and leak-tight. Furthermore, process safety systems—in place and operational—would have prevented water from entering the tank by accident&quot;. Carbide states that the safety concerns identified in 1982 were all allayed before 1984 and &quot;none of them had anything to do with the incident&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;faq&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.bhopal.com/faq.htm |publisher=Bhopal Information Center, UCC |title=Frequently Asked Questions}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The company admits that &quot;the safety systems in place could not have prevented a chemical reaction of this magnitude from causing a leak&quot;. According to Carbide, &quot;in designing the plant's safety systems, a chemical reaction of this magnitude was not factored in&quot; because &quot;the tank's gas storage system was designed to automatically prevent such a large amount of water from being inadvertently introduced into the system&quot; and &quot;process safety systems—in place and operational—would have prevented water from entering the tank by accident&quot;. Instead, they claim that &quot;employee sabotage—not faulty design or operation—was the cause of the tragedy&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;faq&quot; /&gt;

===Response===
The company stresses the &quot;immediate action&quot; taken after the disaster and their continued commitment to helping the victims. On December 4, the day following the leak, Union Carbide sent material aid and several international medical experts to assist the medical facilities in Bhopal.&lt;ref name=&quot;faq&quot; /&gt;

Union Carbide states on its website that it put $2 million into the Indian Prime Minister's immediate disaster relief fund on 11 December 1984.&lt;ref name=&quot;faq&quot; /&gt; The corporation established the Employees' Bhopal Relief Fund in February 1985, which raised more than {{Nowrap|$5 million}} for immediate relief.&lt;ref name=&quot;chrono&quot;&gt;{{cite web |publisher=Bhopal Information Center, UCC |title=Chronology |month=November |year=2006 |url=http://www.bhopal.com/chrono.htm}}&lt;/ref&gt;

According to Union Carbide, in August 1987, they made an additional {{Nowrap|$4.6 million}} in humanitarian interim relief available.&lt;ref name=&quot;chrono&quot; /&gt;

Union Carbide states that it also undertook several steps to provide continuing aid to the victims of the Bhopal disaster after the court ruling, including:
* The sale of its 50.9 percent interest in UCIL in April 1992 and establishment of a charitable trust to contribute to the building of a local hospital. The sale was finalized in November 1994. The hospital was begun in October 1995 and was opened in 2001. The company provided a fund with around {{Nowrap|$90 million}} from sale of its UCIL stock. In 1991, the trust had amounted approximately {{Nowrap|$100 million}}. The hospital caters for the treatment of heart, lung and eye problems.&lt;ref name=&quot;ucs&quot; /&gt;
* Providing &quot;a $2.2 million grant to Arizona State University to establish a vocational-technical center in Bhopal, which was constructed and opened, but was later closed and leveled by the government&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;irs&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.bhopal.com/irs.htm |publisher=Bhopal Information Center, UCC |title=Incident Response and Settlement}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* Donating $5 million to the [[Indian Red Cross]].&lt;ref name=&quot;irs&quot; /&gt;
* Developing the [[Responsible Care]] system with other members of the chemical industry as a response to the Bhopal crisis, which is designed &quot;to help prevent such an event in the future by improving community awareness, emergency preparedness and process safety standards&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;chrono&quot; /&gt;

==Long-term fallout==
Legal action against Union Carbide has dominated the aftermath of the disaster. However, other issues have also continued to develop. These include the problems of ongoing contamination, criticisms of the clean-up operation undertaken by Union Carbide, and a 2004 hoax.

===Legal action against Union Carbide===
Legal proceedings involving UCC, the United States and Indian governments, local Bhopal authorities, and the disaster victims started immediately after the catastrophe.

====Legal proceedings leading to the settlement====
On 14 December 1984, the Chairman and CEO of Union Carbide, [[Warren Anderson (chairman)|Warren Anderson]], addressed the US Congress, stressing the company's &quot;commitment to safety&quot; and promising to ensure that a similar incident &quot;cannot happen again&quot;. However, the Indian Government passed the Bhopal Gas Leak Act in March 1985, allowing the Government of India to act as the legal representative for victims of the disaster,&lt;ref name=&quot;chrono&quot; /&gt; leading to the beginning of legal wrangling.

In 1985, [[Henry Waxman]], a [[California]] Democrat, called for a US government inquiry into the Bhopal disaster, which resulted in US legislation regarding the accidental release of toxic chemicals in the United States.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title=BP, Bhopal and the humble Indian brinjal|url=http://www.hindustantimes.com/BP-Bhopal-and-the-humble-Indian-brinjal/Article1-561254.aspx|accessdate=26 June 2010|newspaper=[[Hindustan Times]]|date=22 June 2010|author=Dipankar De Sarkar}}&lt;/ref&gt;

March 1986 saw Union Carbide propose a settlement figure, endorsed by plaintiffs' US attorneys, of {{Nowrap|$350 million}} that would, according to the company, &quot;generate a fund for Bhopal victims of between {{Nowrap|$500–600 million}} over 20 years&quot;. In May, litigation was transferred from the US to Indian courts by US District Court Judge. Following an appeal of this decision, the US Court of Appeals affirmed the transfer, judging, in January 1987, that UCIL was a &quot;separate entity, owned, managed and operated exclusively by Indian citizens in India&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;chrono&quot; /&gt; The judge in the US granted UCC's forum request, thus moving the case to India. This meant that, under US federal law, the company had to submit to Indian jurisdiction.

Litigation continued in India during 1988. The Government of India claimed US$ {{Nowrap|350 million}} from UCC.&lt;ref name=&quot;Eckerman2004&quot; /&gt; The [[Supreme Court of India|Indian Supreme Court]] told both sides to come to an agreement and &quot;start with a clean slate&quot; in November 1988.&lt;ref name=&quot;chrono&quot; /&gt; Eventually, in an out-of-court settlement reached in 1989, Union Carbide agreed to pay [[USD|US$]] {{Nowrap|470 million}} for damages caused in the Bhopal disaster, 15% of the original {{Nowrap|$3 billion}} claimed in the lawsuit.&lt;ref name=&quot;Eckerman2004&quot; /&gt; By the end of October 2003, according to the Bhopal Gas Tragedy Relief and Rehabilitation Department, compensation had been awarded to 554,895 people for injuries received and 15,310 survivors of those killed. The average amount to families of the dead was $2,200.&lt;ref name=&quot;broughton&quot;&gt;Broughton (2005).&lt;/ref&gt;

Throughout 1990, the Indian Supreme Court heard appeals against the settlement from &quot;activist petitions&quot;. In October 1991, the Supreme Court upheld the original {{Nowrap|$470 million}}, dismissing any other outstanding petitions that challenged the original decision. The Court ordered the Indian government &quot;to purchase, out of settlement fund, a group medical insurance policy to cover 100,000 persons who may later develop symptoms&quot; and cover any shortfall in the settlement fund. It also requested UCC and its subsidiary &quot;voluntarily&quot; fund a hospital in Bhopal, at an estimated {{Nowrap|$17 million}}, to specifically treat victims of the Bhopal disaster. The company agreed to this.&lt;ref name=&quot;chrono&quot; /&gt;

====Charges against Warren Anderson and others====
UCC Chairman and CEO Warren Anderson was arrested and released on bail by the Madhya Pradesh Police in Bhopal on December 7, 1984. The arrest, which took place at the airport, ensured Anderson would meet no harm by the Bhopal community. Anderson was taken to UCC's house after which he was released six hours later on $2,100 bail and flown out on a government plane.  In 1987, the [[Indian government]] summoned Anderson, eight other executives and two company affiliates with [[homicide]] charges to appear in Indian court.&lt;ref name=&quot;nytimes88&quot;&gt;{{cite news|url=http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=940DE0D71F3CF934A25756C0A96E948260|title=India Acts in Carbide Case|publisher=The New York Times|date=May 17, 1988|page=D15}}&lt;/ref&gt; Union Carbide balked, saying the company is not under Indian jurisdiction.&lt;ref name=&quot;nytimes88&quot; /&gt;

In 1991, local Bhopal authorities charged Anderson, who had retired in 1986, with manslaughter, a crime that carries a maximum penalty of 10 years in prison. He was declared a fugitive from justice by the Chief Judicial Magistrate of Bhopal on February 1, 1992, for failing to appear at the court hearings in a culpable [[homicide]] case in which he was named the chief defendant. Orders were passed to the Government of India to press for an [[extradition]] from the United States.

The [[Supreme Court of the United States|U.S. Supreme Court]] refused to hear an appeal of the decision of the lower federal courts in October 1993, meaning that victims of the Bhopal disaster could not seek damages in a US court.&lt;ref name=&quot;chrono&quot; /&gt;

In 2004, the Indian Supreme Court ordered the Indian government to release any remaining settlement funds to victims. In September 2006, the Welfare Commission for Bhopal Gas Victims announced that all original compensation claims and revised petitions had been &quot;cleared&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;chrono&quot; /&gt;

In 2006, the [[United States Court of Appeals for the Second Circuit|Second Circuit Court of Appeals]] in [[New York City]] upheld the dismissal of remaining claims in the case of ''Bano v. Union Carbide Corporation''. This move blocked plaintiffs' motions for class certification and claims for property damages and remediation. In the view of UCC, &quot;the ruling reaffirms UCC's long-held positions and finally puts to rest—both procedurally and substantively—the issues raised in the class action complaint first filed against Union Carbide in 1999 by Haseena Bi and several organizations representing the residents of Bhopal&quot;.

In June 2010, seven former employees of the Union Carbide subsidiary, all Indian nationals and many in their 70s, were convicted of causing death by [[negligence]] and each sentenced to two years imprisonment and fined [[Indian rupee|Rs.]]1 [[lakh]] ([[US$]]2,124).&lt;ref&gt;8 [http://www.cbi.gov.in/whats_new/bhopalgas_judgement.pdf Cr. Case No. 8460/1996]&lt;/ref&gt; All were released on bail shortly after the verdict. The names of those convicted are: Keshub Mahindra, former non-executive chairman of Union Carbide India Limited; V.P. Gokhale, managing director; Kishore Kamdar, vice-president; J. Mukund, works manager; S.P. Chowdhury, production manager; K.V. Shetty, plant superintendent; and S.I. Qureshi, production assistant.
Federal class action litigation, Sahu v. Union Carbide et al. is presently pending on appeal before the Second Circuit Court of Appeals in New York.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.bhopal.net/pdfs/Sahu%20Opinion%2011.3.08.pdf&lt;/ref&gt; The litigation seeks damages for personal injury, medical monitoring&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.thetruthaboutdow.org/article.php?id=945 The Truth About Dow: Govt handling of Bhopal: Blot on Indian Democracy, 224 Indian groups tell PM&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;].&lt;/ref&gt; and injunctive relief in the form of cleanup&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.thetruthaboutdow.org/article.php?id=920 The Truth About Dow: 25 years on, Govt wakes up to Bhopal waste but can't find any one to clean it up&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;].&lt;/ref&gt; of the drinking water supplies&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.thetruthaboutdow.org/article.php?id=1038 The Truth About Dow: Decades Later, Toxic Sludge Torments Bhopal&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;].&lt;/ref&gt; for residential areas near the Bhopal plant. A related complaint seeking similar relief for property damage claimants is stayed pending the outcome of the Sahu appeal before the federal district court in the Southern District of New York.

==Ongoing contamination==
Chemicals abandoned at the plant continue to leak and pollute the [[groundwater]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |publisher=[[BBC]] |title=No takers for Bhopal toxic waste |url=http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/south_asia/7569891.stm | date=2008-09-30 | accessdate=2010-01-01 |first=KS |last=Shaini}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |last1=Broughton |first1=Edward |year=2005 |title=The Bhopal disaster and its aftermath: a review |journal=Environmental Health |volume=4 |issue=6 |url=http://www.ehjournal.net/content/4/1/6 |doi=10.1186/1476-069X-4-6 |page=6 |pmid=15882472 |pmc=1142333 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |last1=Chander |first1=J. |year=2001 |title=Water contamination: a legacy of the union carbide disaster in Bhopal, India |journal=Int J Occup Environ Health |volume=7 |issue=1 |pages=72–3 |pmid=11210017}}&lt;/ref&gt; Whether the chemicals pose a health hazard is disputed.&lt;ref name=&quot;msnbc&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.msnbc.msn.com/id/34247132/ns/world_news-south_and_central_asia/page/2/|title=Industrial Disaster Still Haunts India&amp;nbsp;– South and Central Asia&amp;nbsp;– msnbc.com|date=December 2, 2009|accessdate=December 3, 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Contamination at the site and surrounding area was not caused by the gas leakage. The area around the plant was used as a dumping ground for hazardous chemicals. By 1982 water wells in the vicinity of the UCC factory had to be abandoned. In 1991 the municipal authorities declared water from over 100 wells unfit for drinking.&lt;ref name=&quot;Eckerman2004&quot; /&gt;

UCC's laboratory tests in 1989 revealed that soil and water samples collected from near the factory were toxic to fish. Twenty one areas inside the plant were reported to be highly polluted. In 1994 it was reported that 21% of the factory premises were seriously contaminated with chemicals.&lt;ref name=&quot;UCC1989&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Labunska&quot;&gt;Labunska et al. (2003).&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;down&quot;&gt;Down to Earth (2003).&lt;/ref&gt;

Studies made by [[Greenpeace]] and others from soil, groundwater, wellwater and vegetables from the residential areas around UCIL and from the UCIL factory area show contamination with a range of toxic heavy metals and chemical compounds.&lt;ref name=&quot;Labunska&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;down&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;stringer&quot;&gt;Stringer et al. (2002).&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;srishti&quot;&gt;Srishti (2002).&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Peoples&quot;&gt;Peoples' Science Institute (2001).&lt;/ref&gt;

Substances found, according to the reports, are [[naphthol]]{{dn|date=September 2011}}, [[naphthalene]], Sevin, tarry residues, [[1-naphthol|alpha naphthol]], mercury, [[organochlorines]], [[chromium]], [[copper]], [[nickel]], lead, hexachlorethane, [[Hexachlorobutadiene]], pesticide HCH ([[Hexachlorocyclohexane|BHC]]), [[volatile organic compound]]s and halo-organics. Many of these contaminants were also found in breast milk.

In 2002, an inquiry found a number of toxins, including [[mercury (element)|mercury]], [[lead]], 1,3,5 [[trichlorobenzene]], [[dichloromethane]] and [[chloroform]], in nursing women's breast milk. Well water and groundwater tests conducted in the surrounding areas in 1999 showed mercury levels to be at &quot;20,000 and {{Nowrap|6 million}} times&quot; higher than expected levels; heavy metals and organochlorines were present in the soil. Chemicals that have been linked to various forms of cancer were also discovered, as well as [[trichloroethylene]], known to impair fetal development, at 50 times above safety limits specified by the [[United States Environmental Protection Agency]] (EPA).&lt;ref name=&quot;BMA&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.bhopal.org/whathappened.html |publisher=The Bhopal Medical Appeal |title=What Happened in Bhopal?}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In a 2004 broadcast on [[BBC Radio 5 Live|BBC Radio 5]],&lt;ref name=&quot;BBC&quot;&gt;{{cite web |publisher=BBC Radio 5 |title=Bhopal faces risk of 'poisoning' |date=2004-11-14 |url=http://search.bbc.co.uk/cgi-bin/search/results.pl?scope=all&amp;tab=av&amp;recipe=all&amp;q=bhopal+faces+risk+of+%27poisoning%27&amp;x=0&amp;y=0}}&lt;/ref&gt; it was reported that the site is still contaminated with 'thousands' of metric tons of toxic chemicals, including [[Hexachlorocyclohexane|benzene hexachloride]] and [[Mercury (element)|mercury]], held in open containers or loose on the ground. A drinking water sample from a well near the site had levels of contamination 500 times higher than the maximum limits recommended by the World Health Organization.&lt;ref name=&quot;BBC Radio 5 website&quot;&gt;{{cite news |publisher=BBC Radio 5 website |title=Bhopal 'faces risk of poisoning' |date=2004-11-14 |url=http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/south_asia/4010511.stm | accessdate=2010-01-01 |first=Paul |last=Vickers}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In 2009, the Centre for Science and Environment (CSE), a Delhi based pollution monitoring lab, released test results showing pesticide groundwater contamination up to three kilometers from the factory.
&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | title=Bhopal gas leak survivors still being poisoned: Study | url=http://www.cseindia.org/AboutUs/press_releases/press-20091201.htm | location=Bhopal | date=1 December 2009 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

The BBC took a water sample from a frequently used hand pump, located just north of the plant. The sample, tested in UK, was found to contain 1000 times the World Health Organization's recommended maximum amount of carbon tetrachloride, a carcinogenic toxin.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news
|url=http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/south_asia/8392206.stm|title=Bhopal marks 25 years since gas leak devastation|date= December 3, 2009
 | work=BBC News | accessdate=2010-01-01}}&lt;/ref&gt;

UCC states that &quot;after the incident, UCIL began clean-up work at the site under the direction of Indian central and state government authorities&quot;, which was continued after 1994 by the successor to UCIL, Eveready Industries, until 1998, when it was placed under the authority of the Madhya Pradesh Government.&lt;ref name=&quot;chrono&quot; /&gt;  The successor, Eveready Industries India, Limited (EIIL), ended its 99-year lease in 1998 and turned over control of the site to the state government of Madhya Pradesh.&lt;ref name=&quot;ucs&quot; /&gt;

==Settlement fund hoax==
[[Image:Dow apologizes.jpg|right|thumb|Bichlbaum as Finisterra on BBC World News]]

On December 3, 2004, the twentieth anniversary of the disaster, a man claiming to be a Dow representative named Jude Finisterra was interviewed on [[BBC World News]]. He claimed that the company had agreed to clean up the site and compensate those harmed in the incident, by liquidating Union Carbide for {{Nowrap|$12 billion}} USD.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.theyesmen.org/hijinks/dow/video.html video].&lt;/ref&gt;

Immediately afterward, Dow's share price fell 4.2% in 23 minutes, for a loss of {{Nowrap|$2 billion}} in market value. Dow quickly issued a statement saying that they had no employee by that name—that he was an impostor, not affiliated with Dow, and that his claims were a hoax. The BBC broadcast a correction and an apology.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.zmag.org/content/showarticle.cfm?SectionID=66&amp;ItemID=6795 Corporate Responsibility. 5 December 2004. Published by [[ZNet]]]&lt;/ref&gt;

&quot;Jude Finisterra&quot; was actually [[Jacque Servin|Andy Bichlbaum]], a member of the activist prankster group [[The Yes Men]]. In 2002, The Yes Men issued a fake press release explaining why Dow refused to take responsibility for the disaster and started up a website, at &quot;[http://dowethics.com/ DowEthics.com]&quot;, designed to look like the real Dow website, but with what they felt was a more accurate cast on the events.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.theyesmen.org/hijinks/dow/ The Yes Men]&lt;/ref&gt;

==References and additional resources==
=== Footnotes ===
{{Reflist|colwidth=30em}}

===Books and reports===
* {{cite book |last=Browning |first=Jackson |title=Union Carbide: Disaster at Bhopal |editor=Jack A. Gottschalk |series=Crisis Response: Inside Stories on Managing Image Under Siege |location=Detroit |year=1993 |url=http://www.bhopal.com/pdfs/browning.pdf |format=PDF |quote=Union Carbide's former vice-president of health, safety and environmental programs tells how he dealt with the catastrophe from a PR point of view.}}
* Cassels, J. (1993). ''The Uncertain Promise Of Law: Lessons From Bhopal.'' University Of Toronto Press.
*{{cite book |last=ChouhanTR and others |title=Bhopal: the Inside Story—Carbide Workers Speak Out on the World's Worst Industrial Disaster |year=1994, 2004 |publisher=The Apex Press |location=US |isbn=1-891843-30-3}} India: Other India Press ISBN 81-85569-65-7 Main author Chouhan was an operator at the plant. Contains many technical details.
* {{cite book |url=http://www.grazian-archive.com/governing/bhopal/index.htm |author=De Grazia A |title=A Cloud over Bhopal, |publisher=Popular Prakashan |location=Bombay |year=1985}}
*{{cite book |last=Dhara VR|url=http://webdrive.service.emory.edu/users/vdhara/www.BhopalPublications/Health%20Effects%20&amp;%20Epidemiology/Dhara%20Disseration%20Bhopal%20Disaster.pdf |title=The Bhopal Gas Leak: Lessons from studying the impact of a disaster in a developing nation. |location=US |publisher=Univ. of Massachusetts Lowell |year=2000}} Doctoral thesis.
* {{cite book |last=Doyle |first=Jack |url=http://www.trespassagainstus.com/index.php |title=Trespass Against Us. Dow Chemical &amp; The Toxic Century |year=2004 |publisher=Common Courage Press |location=US |isbn=1-56751-268-2}} A story of how one company's chemical prducts and byproducts have damaged public health and the environment. 466 pages.
* {{cite book |last=D'Silva |first=Themistocles |year=2006 |title=The Black Box of Bhopal: A Closer Look at the World's Deadliest Industrial Disaster |url=http://books.google.com/?id=lpcwvvK9xlsC&amp;printsec=frontcover#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false |isbn=1-4120-8412-1 |publisher=Trafford |location=Victoria, B.C.}} [http://pubs.acs.org/cen/books/85/8528books.html Review] Written by a retired former employee of UCC who was a member of the investigation committee that reproduced the tank residue and determined the true cause of the incident. Includes several original documents including correspondence between UCIL and the Ministries of the Government of India.
* {{cite book |url=http://www.lakareformiljon.org/images/stories/dokument/2009/bhopal_gas_disaster.pdf |title=Chemical Industry and Public Health—Bhopal as an example |last=Eckerman |first=Ingrid |year=2001 |format=PDF}} Essay for MPH. A short overview, 57 pages, 82 references.
* {{cite book |last=Eckerman |first=Ingrid |title=The Bhopal Saga—Causes and Consequences of the World's Largest Industrial Disaster |url=http://www.eckerman.nu/default.cfm?page=The%20Bhopal%20Saga |year=2005 |publisher=Universities Press |location=India |isbn=81-7371-515-7 }} [http://books.google.com/books?id=rvn7ybZUo4kC&amp;hl=en Preview Google books] All known facts 1960s&amp;nbsp;– 2003, systematized and analyzed. 283 pages, over 200 references.
* Eckerman I (2011) Bhopal Gas Catastrophe 1984: Causes and Consequences. In: Nriagu JO (ed.) Encyclopedia of Environmental Health, volume 1, pp.&amp;nbsp;302–316 Burlington: Elsevier.
* {{cite book |title=Advocacy after Bhopal. Environmentalism, Disaster, New Global Orders |year=2001 |author=Fortun, Kim |isbn=0-226-25720-7 |publisher=University of Chicago Press |url=http://books.google.com/books?id=B4V2BepBCKAC&amp;pg=PA134&amp;dq=chouhan#v=onepage&amp;q=chouhan&amp;f=false }}
* {{cite book |title=A Cloud over Bhopal—Causes, Consequences and Constructive Solutions |year=1985 |author=de Grazia, Alfred |isbn=0-940268-09-9 |url=http://www.grazian-archive.com/governing/bhopal/Publishers%20Note.html |quote=The first book on the Bhopal disaster, written on-site a few weeks after the accident. |unused_data=Metron Publications}}
*{{cite book |last=Hanna B, Morehouse W, Sarangi S |title=The Bhopal Reader. Remembering Twenty Years of the World's Worst Industrial Disaster |year=2005 |publisher=The Apex Press |location=US |url=http://books.google.com/?id=8Zzl85Yt_-YC&amp;printsec=frontcover#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false |isbn=1-891843-32-X USA, 81-85569-70-3 India}} Reprinting and annotating landmark writing from across the years.
* {{cite book |author=Jasanoff, Sheila ed. |title=Learning from Disaster. Risk Management After Bhopal |year=1994 |publisher=University of Pennsylvania Press |url=http://books.google.com/?id=XaN-VkDFSWgC&amp;printsec=frontcover#v=onepage&amp;q=&amp;f=false |isbn=081221532X, 9780812215328}} 291 pages.
* {{cite book |author=Johnson S, Sahu R, Jadon N, Duca C |title=Contamination of soil and water inside and outside the Union Carbide India Limited, Bhopal |year=2009 |publisher=New Delhi: Centre for Science and Environment}} In [[Down To Earth (magazine)|Down to Earth]]
* {{cite book |url=http://bhopal.bard.edu/resources/documents/1988ArthurD.Littlereport.pdf |format=PDF |author=Kalelkar AS, Little AD. |year=1998 |title=Investigation of Large-magnitude incidents: Bhopal as a Case Study.}} London: The Institution of Chemical Engineers Conference on Preventing Major Chemical Accidents
*{{cite book |last=Kovel |first=J |year=2002 |isbn=978-1-55266-255-7 |title=The Enemy of Nature: The End of Capitalism or the End of the World? |publisher=London: Zed Books |url=http://books.google.com/?id=W-eavh4NQcwC&amp;printsec=frontcover#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false}}
* {{cite book |last=Kulling P, Lorin H |year=1987 |isbn= |title=The Toxic Gas Disaster in Bhopal December 2–3, 1984 |publisher=Stockholm: National Defence Research Institute}} [In Swedish]
* Kurzman, D. (1987). ''A Killing Wind: Inside Union Carbide and the Bhopal Catastrophe''. New York: McGraw-Hill.
*{{cite book |url=http://webdrive.service.emory.edu/users/vdhara/www.BhopalPublications/Environmental%20Health/Greenpeace%20Bhopal%20Report.pdf |format=PDF |last=Labunska I, Stephenson A, Brigden K, Stringer R, Santillo D, Johnston P.A. |year=1999 |title=The Bhopal Legacy. Toxic contaminants at the former Union Carbide factory site, Bhopal, India: 15 years after the Bhopal accident}}Greenpeace Research Laboratories, Department of Biological Sciences, University of Exeter, Exeter UK
* {{cite book |last=Lapierre |first=Dominique |coauthors=Moro, Javier |year=2001 |isbn=0-446-53088-3 |title=Five Past Midnight in Bhopal |publisher=Warner Books |location=New York, NY}} A novel, based on facts, that describes the development from the 1960s to the disaster itself. Very thrilling.
*{{cite book |url=http://www.unu.edu/unupress/unupbooks/uu21le/uu21le00.htm#Contents |last=Mitchel |first=James |title=The long road to recovery: Community responses to industrial disaster |year=1996 |publisher=Tokyo and New York: United Nations University Press |isbn=92-808-0926-1}}
*{{cite book |last=Singh |first=Moti |title=Unfolding the Betrayal of Bhopal Gas Tragedy |year=2008 |publisher=B.R. Publishing Corporation |location=Delhi, India |isbn=8176466220}} The chief coordinator of rescue operations at the district level writes rather critically on how the administration and bureaucracy functioned after the disaster.
*{{cite book |last=Shrishti |title=Toxic present—toxic future. A report on Human and Environmental Chemical Contamination around the Bhopal disaster site |year=2002 |publisher=The Other Media |location=Delhi}}
* {{cite book |url=http://www.greenpeace.org/raw/content/international/press/reports/chemical-stockpiles-at-union-c.pdf |format=PDF |author=Stringer R, Labunska I, Brigden K, Santillo D. |year=2002 |title=Chemical Stockpiles at Union Carbide India Limited in Bhopal: An investigation |publisher=Greenpeace Research Laboratories |unused_data=Technical Note 12/2002}}
*{{cite book |last=Varadarajan S et al. |title=Report on Scientific Studies on the Factors Related to Bhopal Toxic Gas Leakage |year=1985 |publisher=Indian Council for Scientific and Industrial Research |location=New Delhi}}
* {{cite book |last=Weir D |year=1987 |title=The Bhopal Syndrome: Pesticides, Environment and Health |location=San Francisco |publisher=[[Sierra Club Books]] |isbn=0871567180}}
*{{cite book |url=http://www.aiche.org/uploadedFiles/CCPS/About/Bhopal20YearsLater.pdf |author=Willey RJ, Hendershot DC, Berger S |title=The Accident in Bhopal: Observations 20 Years Later |year=2006 |publisher=AIChE |location=Orlando, Florida, USA}}
* {{cite book |url=http://www.bhopal.net/oldsite/documentlibrary/unionreport1985.html |title=The Trade Union Report on Bhopal |publisher=ICFTU-ICEF |location=Geneva, Switzerland |year=1985}}

===Journal articles and academic papers===
* {{cite web |url=http://webdrive.service.emory.edu/users/vdhara/www.BhopalPublications |title=Health and Epidemiology Papers About the Bhopal Disaster}}
* {{cite journal |doi=10.1016/j.jlp.2005.07.006 |url=http://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/B6TGH-4H21R3C-1/2/922a6ed2ebad15a178dea4a26daa0683 |author=Bisarya RK, Puri S |title=The Bhopal Gas Tragedy&amp;nbsp;– a Perspective |year=2005 |journal=Journal of Loss Prevention in the process industry |volume=18 |pages=209–212 |issue=4–6 }}
* {{cite journal |url=http://unified.icheme.org/~/media/Documents/icheme/Resources/LPB/LPB%20samples/063bhopal.ashx|title=Bhopal&amp;nbsp;– the company's report, based on the Union Carbide Corporation's report, March 1985 |work=Loss Prevention Bulletin |year= 1985 |issue= LPB issue 063, |publisher=IChemE,|location= Rugby, UK.}}
* {{cite journal |author=Broughton E |title=The Bhopal disaster and its aftermath: a review |journal=Environmental Health |volume=4 |issue=1 |pages=6 pages |doi=10.1186/1476-069X-4-6 |pmid=15882472 |url=http://www.ehjournal.net/content/4/1/6 |pmc=1142333 |date=10 May 2005 }}
* {{cite journal |doi=10.1016/j.jlp.2005.07.025 |url=http://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/B6TGH-4H2G8YH-1/2/2f70debf0a05a3303428303074800554|author=Chouhan TR |title=The Unfolding of Bhopal Disaster |year=2005 |journal=Journal of Loss Prevention in the process industry| volume= 18| pages= 205–208 |issue=4–6}}
* {{cite web |url=http://webdrive.service.emory.edu/users/vdhara/www.BhopalPublications/Health%20Effects%20&amp;%20Epidemiology/Health%20Effects%20Review%20articles/Health%20Effects%20Review%20AEH.pdf |format=reprint |title=The Union Carbide disaster in Bhopal: A review of health effects |last=Dhara |first=V. Ramana |coauthors=Dhara, Rosaline |work=Archives of Environmental Health |year=2002 |month=Sept/October |pages=391–404}}
* {{cite journal |author=Dhara VR, Gassert TH |month=September |year=2005 |title=The Bhopal gas tragedy: Evidence for cyanide poisoning not convincing |journal=Current Science |volume=89 |issue=6 |pages=923–5 |url=http://webdrive.service.emory.edu/users/vdhara/www.BhopalPublications/Toxicology/Current%20Science%20article%20&amp;%20critique/Current%20Science%20critique%20Gassert%20Dhara%20&amp;%20Sriramachari%20response.pdf}}
* {{cite journal |url=http://www.docstoc.com/docs/42335332/The-Bhopal-gas-tragedy-1984-to-The-evasion-of|author=Dinham B, Sarangi S |title=The Bhopal gas tragedy 1984&amp;nbsp;– ? The evasion of corporate responsibility |work=Environment&amp;Urbanization  | year= 2002| volume=14 | pages=89–99 }}
* {{cite journal |author=D'Silva TDJ, Lopes A, Jones RL, Singhawangcha S, Chan JK |title=Studies of methyl isocyanate chemistry in the Bhopal incident |year=1986 |journal=[[J. Org. Chem.]] |volume=51 |issue=20 |pages=3781–3788 |doi=10.1021/jo00370a007 }}
* {{cite journal |doi=10.1016/j.jlp.2005.07.007 |url=http://www.sciencedirect.com/science?_ob=ArticleURL&amp;_udi=B6TGH-4GWC0T0-7&amp;_user=10&amp;_coverDate=11%2F30%2F2005&amp;_rdoc=1&amp;_fmt=high&amp;_orig=search&amp;_origin=search&amp;_sort=d&amp;_docanchor=&amp;view=c&amp;_acct=C000050221&amp;_version=1&amp;_urlVersion=0&amp;_userid=10&amp;md5=0eba928fff2cbeb78b3fe9c61f4d8bdd&amp;searchtype=a
 |title=The Bhopal gas leak: Analyses of causes and consequences by three different models |year=2005 |journal=Journal of Loss Prevention in the process industry |last=Eckerman |first=Ingrid | volume= 18| pages= 213–217 |issue=4–6}}
* {{cite journal |url=http://www.ttl.fi/en/publications/electronic_journals/asian_pacific_newsletter/archives/Documents/asian_pacific_newsletter2_2006.pdf |title=The Bhopal Disaster 1984&amp;nbsp;– working conditions and the role of the trade unions |format=PDF |last=Eckerman |first=Ingrid |work=Asian Pacific Newsletter on occupational health and safety |year=2006 | volume=  13|issue=2 | pages= 48–49}}
* {{cite journal |url=http://webdrive.service.emory.edu/users/vdhara/www.BhopalPublications/Toxicology/Current%20Science%20article%20&amp;%20critique/Current%20Science%20critique%20Gassert%20Dhara%20&amp;%20Sriramachari%20response.pdf |title=Debate on cyanide poisoning in Bhopal victims |work=Current Science |year=Sep 2005. |format=PDF |last=Gassert TH, Dhara VR,  | volume = 89 | issue=6}}
* {{cite web|url=http://www.corpwatch.org/article.php?id=15485 |title=Bhopal: Generations of Poison |author=Jayaraman N }} CorpWatch, December 2, 2009
* {{cite journal |journal=Isis |year=2007 |volume=98 |pages=344–350 |title=Bhopal's Trials of Knowledge and Ignorance |first=Sheila |last=Jasanoff |url=http://www.journals.uchicago.edu/doi/full/10.1086/518194 |doi=10.1086/518194 |issue=2}}
* {{cite journal |title=Provision of health care for Bhopal survivors |author=Katrak H |journal=Pesticides News |year=2010 |volume=87 |issue=March 2010 |pages=20–23}}
* {{cite journal |journal=Indian Journal of Ophthalmology |year=1987 |volume=35 |issue=3 |pages=136–137 |title=Long term follow up of ocular lesion of methyl-isocyanate gas disaster in Bhopal |author=Khurrum MA, S Hafeez Ahmad S |url=http://www.ijo.in/article.asp?issn=0301-4738;year=1987;volume=35;issue=3;spage=136;epage=137;aulast=Khurrum |pmid=3507407}}
* {{cite journal |title=Bhopal: The victims are still being born |author=Lakhani N |url=http://www.independent.co.uk/news/world/asia/bhopal-the-victims-are-still-being-born-1830516.html | work=The Independent | location=London | date=2009-11-29 | accessdate=2010-04-26}}
* Lepowski, W. &quot;Ten Years Later: Bhopal&quot;. Chemical and Engineering News, 19 December 1994.
* {{cite web |url=http://www.solidarity-us.org/node/555 |title=Dioxin, Bhopal and Dow Chemical |author= McTaggart U}} Solidarity ATC 106, September–October 2003
* {{cite journal |author=Mishra PK, Dabadghao S, Modi1 GK, Desikan P, Jain A, Mittra I, Gupta D, Chauhan C, Jain SK, Maudar KK |journal=Occupational and Environmental Medicine |year=2009 |volume=66 |page=279 |title=In utero exposure to methyl isocyanate in the Bhopal gas disaster: evidence of persisting hyperactivation of immune system two decades later |url=http://oem.bmj.com/content/66/4/279.extract |doi=10.1136/oem.2008.041517 |pmid=19295137 |issue=4}}
* {{cite journal |journal=Journal of Post-Graduate Medicine |year=1986 |volume=32 |issue=4 |pages=175–84 |title=Medical survey of methyl isocyanate gas affected population of Bhopal. Part&amp;nbsp;I. General medical observations 15 weeks following exposure |author=Naik SR, Acharya VN, Bhalerao RA, Kowli SS, Nazareth HH, Mahashur AA, Shah SS, Potnis AV, Mehta AC
|url=http://www.jpgmonline.com/article.asp?issn=0022-3859;year=1986;volume=32;issue=4;spage=175;epage=84;aulast=Naik |pmid=3585790}}
* {{cite journal |journal=Journal of Post-Graduate Medicine |year=1986 |volume=32 |issue=4 |pages=185–91 |title=Medical survey of methyl isocyanate gas affected population of Bhopal. Part&amp;nbsp;II. Pulmonary effects in Bhopal victims as seen 15 weeks after M.I.C. exposure |author=Naik SR, Acharya VN, Bhalerao RA, Kowli SS, Nazareth HH, Mahashur AA, Shah SS, Potnis AV, Mehta AC
|url=http://www.jpgmonline.com/article.asp?issn=0022-3859;year=1986;volume=32;issue=4;spage=185;epage=91;aulast=Naik |pmid=3585791}}
* {{cite web |url=http://www.umass.edu/sts/ethics/bhopal.html |title=Case study: Bhopal Plant Disaster |author=Peterson M.J | work= Science, Technology &amp; Society Initiative, University of Massachusetts Amherst}}
* {{cite journal |doi=10.1001/jama.290.14.1856 |journal=JAMA |volume=290 |year=2003 |pages=1856–7 |issue=14 |title=Methyl Isocyanate Exposure and Growth Patterns of Adolescents in Bhopal Methyl Isocyanate Exposure and Growth Patterns of Adolescents in Bhopal |author=Ranjan N, Sarangi S, Padmanabhan VT, Holleran S, Ramakrishnan R, Varma DR |url=http://jama.ama-assn.org/cgi/content/full/290/14/1856 |pmid=14532313}}
* {{cite journal |url=http://www.ttl.fi/NR/rdonlyres/AF130282-A0AB-4439-8E3C-AFF55CDEF59F/0/AsianPacific_Nwesletter22006.pdf |title=Bhopal Revisited—the tragedy of lessons ignored |format=PDF |last=Rice |first=Annie |coauthors=ILO |work=Asian Pacific Newsletter on occupational health and safety |year=2006 | volume=13 | pages= 46–47 | issue = 2 }}
*{{cite journal |url=http://webdrive.service.emory.edu/users/vdhara/www.BhopalPublications/Toxicology/Current%20Science%20article%20&amp;%20critique/Curr%20Science%20Bhopal%20article%20Sriramachari.pdf |format=PDF |last=Sriramachari S |title=The Bhopal gas tragedy: An environmental disaster |journal=Current Science |year=2004 |volume=86 |pages=905–920}}
* {{cite journal |doi=10.1016/j.jlp.2005.06.007 |url=http://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/B6TGH-4GTW8RJ-1/2/367c60ca972ec8fde9ad2d3c1234e01c |author=Sriramachari S |title=Bhopal gas tragedy: scientific challenges and lessons for future |year=2005 |journal=Journal of Loss Prevention in the process industry| volume= 18| pages=264–267 |issue=4–6 }}
*{{cite journal |url=http://www.environmentalistonline.com/article/2011-10-13/bhopal-s-never-ending-disaster |author= Tinsley A, Ansell R |title=Bhopal's never ending disaster |journal=the environmentalist |year=2011 |volume= October 2011|pages=pp 16-20}}
* {{cite journal |journal=Pesticide News |year=2010 |volume=87 |issue=March 2010 |title=Toxic groundwater&amp;nbsp;– Bhopal's second disaster |author=Toogood C}}

===Governmental institutions===
* {{cite book |title=Health Effects of the Toxic Gas Leak from the Union Carbide Methyl Isocyanate Plant in Bhopal. Technical report on Population Based Long Term, Epidemiological Studies (1985–1994)}} Bhopal Gas Disaster Research Centre, Gandhi Medical College, Bhopal (2003?) Contains the studies performed by the Indian Council of Medical Research (ICMR)
* {{cite book |title=An Epidemiological Study of Symptomatic Morbidities in Communities Living Around Solar Evaporation Ponds And Behind Union Carbide Factory, Bhopal}} Department of Community Medicine, Gandhi Medical College, Bhopal (2009)
* {{cite book |title=At A Glance. Bhopal Gas Tragedy Relief &amp; Rehabilitation 1985–2009}} Bhopal Gas Tragedy Relief &amp; Rehabilitation Department, Bhopal (2009)

===Union Carbide Corporation===
* {{cite book |title=Methyl Isocyanate. Union Carbide F-41443A&amp;nbsp;– 7/76}} Union Carbide Corporation, New York (1976)
* {{cite book |title=Carbon monoxide, Phosgene and Methyl isocyanate. Unit Safety Procedures Manual}} Union Carbide India Limited, Agricultural Products Division: Bhopal (1978)
* {{cite book |title=Operating Manual Part&amp;nbsp;II. Methyl Isocyanate Unit |publisher=Union Carbide India Limited, Agricultural Products Division (1979)}}
* {{cite book |title=Bhopal Methyl Isocyanate Incident. Investigation Team Report |publisher=Union Carbide Corporation, Danbury, CT (1985)}}
* {{cite book |title=Presence of Toxic Ingredients in Soil/Water Samples Inside Plant Premises}} Union Carbide Corporation, US (1989).

===Dow Chemical===
* {{cite book |url=http://www.dow.com/financial/2007prox/161-00662.pdf |title=Stockholder Proposal on Bhopal 2007}} In Notice of the Annual Meeting of Stockholders to be held on Thursday, May 10, 2007 (Agenda item 4, pp 39–41)
* {{cite book |url=http://www.dow.com/corpgov/pdf/20070510_voting.pdf |title=Annual Meeting Final Voting Results}} May 10, 2007

===Mixed===
* {{cite web |url=http://www.american.edu/ted/bhopal.htm |title=Bhopal Disaster |publisher=Trade Environmental Database. TED case studies no. 233, American University, Washington (1 Nov 1997)}}
* {{cite web |url=http://webdrive.service.emory.edu/users/vdhara/papers.htm |title=Bhopal Papers. Conference Announcement and Call for Papers}} A collection of different articles and papers concerning the Bhopal disaster.
* [http://www.anindianmuslim.com/2009/12/horrors-of-bhopal-gas-tragedy-1984.html Three part series on Horrors of Bhopal Gas Tragedy]
* {{cite web |url=http://www.alyssaalappen.org/2002/12/04/bibliography-on-bhopal-disaster/|title=Bibliography on Bhopal disaster}} A condensed list of books, reports, and articles on the Bhopal disaster and related issues.
* {{cite web |url=http://bioterrorism.slu.edu/pulmonary/quick/methyliso.pdf |format=PDF |title=Chemical Terrorism Fact Sheet: Methyl Isocyanate}} CSB&amp;EI, Saint Louis University School of Public Health, US
* {{cite web |url=http://www.bhopal.net/oldsite/unproventechnology.html |title=Unproven technology |publisher=Bhopal.net |date=14 Nov 2002}}
* {{cite web |url=http://www.amnesty.org/en/library/info/ASA20/015/2004/en |title=Clouds of injustice. Bhopal disaster 20 years}} Amnesty International, London (2004) Report (pdf).
* {{cite web |url=http://old.studentsforbhopal.org/Resources.htm |title=No more Bhopals}} Contains original documents and categorizes resources by subject.
* [http://bhopal.bard.edu The Bhopal Memory Project] Material from UCC, the trade union and other original material has been scanned and can be found here.
* {{cite book |title=Fighting for Our Right to Live |publisher=Chingari trust |location=Bhopal |year=2008}} Chingari Trust works with disabled children.
*{{cite web |url=http://www.pan-uk.org/Internat/indhaz/Charter.pdf  |format=PDF |title=Charter on Industrial Hazards and Human Rights |archiveurl = http://web.archive.org/web/20071015132925/http://www.pan-uk.org/Internat/indhaz/Charter.pdf |archivedate = 2007-10-15}} Permanent Peoples' Tribunal on Industrial Hazards and Human Rights, 1996, adopted after the session in Bhopal, 1992.
* {{cite book |title=Industrial Hygien Programs at Foreign Locations |year=1988 |location=Canada |publisher=John Wiley &amp; Sons |editor  =Garett JT, Cralley LJ, Craley LV}} One page, where the role of the Government of India is emphasized. [http://books.google.com.sg/books?id=f0a_zfxmSbEC&amp;lpg=PA113&amp;ots=zm5HW8Qz--&amp;dq=The%20Indian%20government%20had%20its%20heavy%20hand%20on%20every%20aspect%20of%20the%20Bhopal%20plant%2C%20from%20its%20design%20and%20construction%20to%20its%20eventual%20operation.%20Initially%2C%20the%20facility%20merely%20imported%20raw%20pesticides%2C%20such%20as%20one%20called%20Sevin%2C%20and%20then%20diluted%2C%20packaged%20and%20shipped%20them.%20This%20was%20a%20relatively%20safe%20and%20simple%20operation.&amp;pg=PA113#v=onepage&amp;q=The%20Indian%20government%20had%20its%20heavy%20hand%20on%20every%20aspect%20of%20the%20Bhopal%20plant%2C%20from%20its%20design%20and%20construction%20to%20its%20eventual%20operation.%20Initially%2C%20the%20facility%20merely%20imported%20raw%20pesticides%2C%20such%20as%20one%20called%20Sevin%2C%20and%20then%20diluted%2C%20packaged%20and%20shipped%20them.%20This%20was%20a%20relatively%20safe%20and%20simple%20operation.&amp;f=false Preview Google books]
* {{cite web |url=http://www.greenpeace.org/raw/content/international/press/reports/chemical-stockpiles-at-union-c.pdf |title=Chemical Stockpiles at Union Carbide India Limited in Bhopal: an investigation}} Greenpeace Research Laboratories, Technical note, 12/2002

===Presentations===
* Eckerman, Ingrid. {{cite web |url=http://www.lakareformiljon.org/images/stories/LfM_blandat/Bhopal_Bangalore_2010.pdf |title=The Bhopal Gas Disaster 1984&amp;nbsp;– Children's Acute and Chronic Exposure to Toxic Substances |format=PDF}} Power point presentation (2010)
* Eckerman, Ingrid. {{cite web |url=http://www.lakareformiljon.org/images/stories/dokument/2009/bhopal_gas_tragedy_march_2008.pdf |title=The Bhopal Saga—Causes and Consequences of the World's Largest Industrial Disaster |format=PDF}} Power point presentation in easy English (2008)
* Eckerman, Ingrid. {{cite web |url=http://www.lakareformiljon.org/images/stories/dokument/2009/epidemiology_lkarstmman_2007_engelska.pdf |title=The Bhopal Gas Leak—too late for good epidemiology |format=PDF}} Poster presentation (2007)

==External and Wikipedia links==
{{Commons category}}
* [http://indiaenvironmentportal.org.in/category/thesaurus/hazardous-waste/industrial-disasters/bhopal-gas-disaster Resources on Bhopal Gas Disaster, India Environment Portal]
*[http://www.thebhopalpost.com/index.php The Bhopal Post] A website edited by Raajkumar Keswani, the journalist who warned what was going to happen
*[http://www.bhopalbus.com/ The Bhopal Europe Bus Tour], October–November 2009
*[http://www.amnesty.org/en/news-and-updates/bhopal-end-25-years-injustice-20091030 End 25 years of injustice], [[Amnesty International]], 16 October 2009
* [http://www.cipa-apex.org/books/bhopal/ The Bhopal Library], The Apex Press, New York
* [http://www.bhopal.net/ International Campaign For Justice in Bhopal]
* [http://www.bhopal.org/ Bhopal Medical Appeal and Sambhavna Trust Clinic]
* [http://www.studentsforbhopal.org/ Students for Bhopal]
* [[Students for Bhopal]]
* [http://www.scribd.com/doc/1867809/The-Lesson-of-Bhopal Lesson of Bhopal]
* [http://www.bhopal.com/ Bhopal Information Center], Union Carbide
* [http://www.mp.gov.in/bgtrrdmp/ Bhopal Gas Tragedy Relief &amp; Rehabilitation Department], The official website of the Government of Madhya Pradesh
* [http://www.dowethics.com/ Dow Ethics], parody website by [[The Yes Men]]
* [http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/in_depth/business/2009/bhopal/default.stm Bhopal: 25 years on] BBC News' website on the Bhopal disaster
* [http://www.chingaritrustbhopal.com/ Chingari Trust] Provides medical care for children being born in Bhopal with malformations and brain damages.
* [[International Medical Commission on Bhopal]]

===News===
* [http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/science/nature/7961062.stm Bhopal's health effects probed], BBC News 26 March 2009
* [http://news.bbc.co.uk/player/nol/newsid_4010000/newsid_4010500/4010545.stm &quot;Bhopal faces risk of 'poisoning'&quot;], BBC News, 14 Nov 2004
* [http://www.dnaindia.com/india/report_bhopal-gas-tragedy-completes-25-years-victims-woes-still-on_1319210/ 25 years on, Bhopal gas victims still suffering], DNA India newspaper
* [http://www.indianexpress.com/news/25-years-after-bhopal-gas-tragedy-plant-to-be-open-to-public/538733/ 25 years after Bhopal gas tragedy, plant to be open to public], Indian-Express newspaper
* [http://beta.thehindu.com/news/national/article447628.ece Bhopal court to pronounce historic judgment in gas leak case on Monday] The Hindu June 6, 2010
* [http://news.rediff.com/report/2010/jun/07/union-carbide-rejects-bhopal-courts-verdict.htm Union Carbide rejects Bhopal court's verdict] Rediff News June 7, 2010
* [http://www.guardian.co.uk/environment/2010/aug/31/india-reopens-bhopal-case India reopens Bhopal toxic gas leak case], ''Guardian'', August 31, 2010
* [http://web.archive.org/web/20080113184610/http://www.irastimes.org/bhopal_gas_tragedy.htm Bhopal Gas Tragedy] A railway officer describes how he received victims coming by train, 2002
* [http://www.environmentalistonline.com/article/2011-10-13/bhopal-s-never-ending-disaster Bhopal's never ending disaster] Update and summary by two British environmental scientists ''the environmentalist'' October 2011

===Important Court Orders===
* [http://indiaenvironmentportal.org.in/content/supreme-court-order-cbis-curative-petition-against-1996-apex-court-judgement-bhopal-gas-trag/ Supreme Court order on CBI's curative petition against 1996 apex court judgement on Bhopal gas tragedy.]

===Films===
* [http://www.imdb.com/title/tt0281656/ Bhopal Express], 1999 film based on the disaster.
* [http://www.bhopalithemovie.com/ Bhopali, a documentary feature] Directed by Van Maximilian Carlson
* [http://bhopal.strategicvideo.net/ Twenty Years Without Justice: The Bhopal Chemical Disaster] International Campaign for Justice for Bhopal video
* {{cite news |publisher=[[BBC News]] |url=http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/programmes/bhopal/default.stm |title=One Night in Bhopal | date=2009-12-02 | accessdate=2010-01-01}}
* [http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=Xz-BfXLjQ9c&amp;feature=related It Happened in Bhopal], 27 Aug 2007
* [http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=SGdvwspjBPA Shrouds of Silence], August 2008
* [http://kleck-rochs.ucoz.org/load/audio_i_video_dlja_vsekh/video/avarija_v_bkhopale_indija_dokumentalnyj_film/59-1-0-330 The Bhopal Chemical Disaster. documentary film]
*[http://www.democracynow.org/2010/11/8/hundreds_of_survivors_of_bhopal_disaster Hundreds of Survivors of Bhopal Disaster Protest President Obama's 2010 India Visit] - video report by ''[[Democracy Now!]]''
*'' [[Bhopal: Prayer for Rain]]'', 2010 film based on the disaster.
* ''[[The Yes Men Fix the World]]'', documentary which includes discussion of the disaster.

===Musical tributes===
* &quot;No Thunder, No Fire, No Rain&quot; by [[Tim Finn]], from the 1986 album ''[[Big Canoe]]'', presents a lyrical narrative of the disaster.
* &quot;Bhopal (Driftnet Plan)&quot; by [[Bob Wiseman]], from his 1989 album ''In Her Dream: Bob Wiseman Sings Wrench Tuttle'', explores who is to blame for the disaster.
* &quot;Close My Eyes&quot; from the 1987 album ''Exorcise This Wasteland'' by [[Single Gun Theory]]

===Photos===
* [http://www.magnumphotos.com/Archive/c.aspx?VP=XSpecific_MAG.StoryDetail_VPage&amp;pid=2TYRYDDG70XJ Raghu Rai], 1984
* [http://www.netphotograph.com/pablo/bhopal_photos.html Pablo Bartholomew], 1984
* [http://www.commonlanguageproject.net/photos/BhopalSlideshowFinal.htm The Ghosts of Bhopal], Common Language Project
* [http://www.boston.com/bigpicture/2009/11/25th_anniversary_of_the_bhopal.html 25th anniversary of the Bhopal disaster], The Boston Globe

{{Dow Chemical}}
{{Toxicology}}
{{Coord|23|16|51|N|77|24|38|E|region:IN-MP_type:landmark|display=title}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Bhopal Disaster}}
[[Category:Bhopal disaster| ]]
[[Category:Man-made disasters]]
[[Category:Trials in India]]
[[Category:1984 in the environment]]

[[af:Bhopal-ramp]]
[[ar:كارثة بوبال]]
[[bn:ভোপালের বিপর্যয়]]
[[zh-min-nan:Bhopal Sū-kiāⁿ]]
[[ca:Desastre de Bhopal]]
[[cs:Bhópálská katastrofa]]
[[cy:Trychineb Bhopal]]
[[da:Bhopalulykken]]
[[de:Katastrophe von Bhopal]]
[[et:Bhopali avarii]]
[[es:Desastre de Bhopal]]
[[eo:Bhopala tragedio]]
[[eu:Bhopaleko istripua]]
[[fr:Catastrophe de Bhopal]]
[[ko:보팔 가스 사고]]
[[hi:भोपाल गैस काण्ड]]
[[id:Tragedi Bhopal]]
[[it:Disastro di Bhopal]]
[[he:אסון בופאל]]
[[jv:Tragedi Bhopal]]
[[kn:ಭೋಪಾಲ್ ದುರಂತ]]
[[hu:Bhopáli katasztrófa]]
[[ml:ഭോപ്പാൽ ദുരന്തം]]
[[mr:भोपाळ वायुदुर्घटना]]
[[ms:Tragedi Bhopal 1984]]
[[nl:Giframp Bhopal]]
[[ne:भोपाल ग्यास काण्ड]]
[[ja:ボパール化学工場事故]]
[[no:Bhopal-katastrofen]]
[[pl:Katastrofa w Bhopalu]]
[[pt:Desastre de Bhopal]]
[[ru:Бхопальская катастрофа]]
[[simple:Bhopal disaster]]
[[sl:Bhopalska nesreča]]
[[sr:Бопалска катастрофа]]
[[fi:Bhopalin onnettomuus]]
[[ta:போப்பால் பேரழிவு]]
[[th:โศกนาฏกรรมที่โบปาล]]
[[tr:Bhopal felaketi]]
[[uk:Трагедія Бхопала]]
[[vi:Thảm họa Bhopal]]
[[zh:博帕爾事件]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
