<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="145161" ns="0" title="Blickling Hall"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Geobox|stately home
| name =Blickling Hall  
| category =stately home 
| image = BlicklingHall.JPG
| image_caption = View from the garden of Blickling Hall in [[Norfolk]], England.
| flag =
| symbol = 
| country = England
| County =     [[Norfolk]]
| region =   [[East of England]]
| district =   [[North Norfolk]]
| municipality = [[Blickling]] 
| location = 
| elevation =
| prominence =
| lat_d = 
| lat_m =
| lat_s =
| lat_NS =
| long_d =
| long_m =
| long_s =
| long_EW =
| length = 
| length_orientation = 
| width = 
| width_orientation = 
| height =
| depth = 
| volume =
| area = 
| author =
| style = 
| material =
| established =Built in 1616
| date =
| owner = in the care of the National Trust
| public =
| visitation =accessible to the public with a fee 
| visitation_date = All year round
| access =
&lt;!-- *** Free fields *** --&gt;
| free = | free_type = 
&lt;!-- *** Maps *** --&gt;
| map =
| map_caption = 
| map_background = 
| map_locator =
| map_locator_x =
| map_locator_y = 
&lt;!-- *** Website *** --&gt; 
| website =http://www.nationaltrust.org.uk/
&lt;!-- *** Footnotes *** --&gt;
| footnotes =
}}

'''Blickling Hall''' is a [[stately home]] in the village of [[Blickling]] north of [[Aylsham]] in [[Norfolk, England|Norfolk]], England, that has been in the care of the [[National Trust for Places of Historic Interest or Natural Beauty|National Trust]] since 1940.

==History==
In the fifteenth century, Blickling Hall was in the possession of [[John Fastolf|Sir John Fastolf of Caister]] in Norfolk (1380–1459), who made a fortune in the [[Hundred Years' War]], and whose coat of arms is still on display there.  Later, the Hall was in the possession of the Boleyn family, and home to Sir [[Thomas Boleyn]], created Earl of Wiltshire, and his wife, [[Elizabeth Boleyn|Elizabeth]], between 1499 and 1505. It is presumed that their first two children [[Mary Boleyn|Mary]] and [[George Boleyn|George]] were born at Blickling Hall, along with several other Boleyn infants who did not live long. If the couple's most famous child, [[Anne Boleyn]], was born before 1505 (as one school of historical thought contends) then she too was born at Blickling. Other historians maintain that Anne was born after 1505, probably in 1507, and by that time Sir Thomas had moved to [[Hever Castle]] in [[Kent]]. Nonetheless, a statue and portrait of [[Anne Boleyn]] reside in Blickling Hall claiming &quot;Anna Bolena hic nata 1507&quot; (''Anne Boleyn born here 1507'').

The current Blickling Hall was built on the ruins of the old Boleyn property in the reign of [[James I of England|James I]], by [[Sir Henry Hobart]], [[Lord Chief Justice of the Common Pleas]] and 1st Baronet, who bought Blickling from Robert Clere in 1616. The architect of [[Hatfield House]], [[Robert Lyminge]], is credited with the design of the current structure. The Lord Chief Justice married Dorothy, the daughter of [[Sir Robert Bell]] of [[Beaupre Hall]], [[Outwell]]/[[Upwell|Upwell, Norfolk]], [[Speaker of the British House of Commons|Speaker of the House of Commons]] 1572&amp;ndash;1576. A grand display of heraldic material is present throughout the estate.

== In the 20th century ==
During [[World War II]] the house was requisitioned and served as the Officers Mess of nearby [[RAF Oulton]]. It was at this time that the house and its estate passed to The National Trust, under the terms of the Country Houses Scheme.

At the end of the war, the house was de-requisitioned. The National Trust again let it to tenants until 1960, when the Trust began the work to restore the house to a style reflecting its history. The house and grounds were opened to the public in 1962 and remain open under the name &quot;Blickling Hall, Garden &amp; Park&quot;.

== Library ==
The library at Blickling Hall contained and still contains one of the most historically significant collections of manuscripts and books in England. The most important manuscript associated with the house is the [[Blickling homilies]], which is one of the earliest extant examples of English vernacular homiletic writings.&lt;ref&gt;This volume is now housed in the Firestone Library at [[Princeton University]] (MS. 71, s.x/xi) and privately owned by the Scheide family who reside in [[New Jersey]].&lt;/ref&gt; The Blickling homilies were first edited and translated in the 19th century by Richard Morris, whose work is still considered definitive. A more recent translation and edition by Richard J. Kelly was widely panned by scholars and critics upon publication.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.jstor.org/stable/4146761 Book Review of Kelly's Blickling Homilies in Church History, Vol. 73]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://findarticles.com/p/articles/mi_hb6408/is_1_75/ai_n29286155/ Review of Kelly's Blickling Homilies in Medium Aevum, Spring 2006]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://journals.cambridge.org/action/displayFulltext?type=1&amp;pdftype=1&amp;fid=6583512&amp;jid=SPC&amp;volumeId=80&amp;issueId=02&amp;aid=6583508 Review of Kelly's Blicking Homilies in Speculum, Vol 80, Issue 2]&lt;/ref&gt; Another important manuscript formerly at Blickling Hall is the Blickling or Lothian Psalter, an eight-century illuminated [[psalter]] with Old English glosses, now owned by the [[Pierpont Morgan Library]], where it is MS M.776.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.questia.com/PM.qst?a=o&amp;d=91101089 Blickling Psalter] Retrieved 12 October 2009&lt;/ref&gt;
[[Image:Blickling Hall Ben W Bell 21 10 2005.jpg|thumb|right|300px|Blickling Hall main entrance]]

== In popular culture ==
It is said that every year, on the anniversary of her execution, Anne Boleyn's headless ghost arrives at Blickling Hall in a carriage driven by an equally headless coachman. But she hasn't lost her head completely in the afterlife—she carries it along with her during her hauntings.

Blickling Hall is used as &quot;[[Bono]]'s house&quot; in the series 2 episode of ''[[I'm Alan Partridge]]'' ''&quot;I Know What Alan Did Last Summer&quot;''. 

It was voted the most haunted house in Britain in a National Trust survey in October 2007.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.telegraph.co.uk/news/main.jhtml?xml=/news/2007/10/28/nhal128.xml Daily Telegraph article] Retrieved 19 October 2009&lt;/ref&gt; 
[[Image:Blickling Hall 02.jpg|thumb|Norah Lindsay's replanting of the parterre garden]]

== The Blickling estate ==
The estate covers {{convert|4777|acres}} and includes: {{convert|500|acres}} of woodland, {{convert|450|acres}} of parkland and {{convert|3500| acres}} of farmland. Much of it is classified as Grade 2 and 3 agricultural land which is actively managed by the National Trust to provide income to support the house, gardens, park and woods.&lt;ref name=Bli/&gt;

===Garden history===
A house and garden existed at Blickling before the estate was purchased by the [[Thomas Boleyn, 1st Earl of Wiltshire|Boleyn]] family in the 1450s, but no records survive to give an indication of their appearance. After [[Sir Henry Hobart]] acquired the estate in 1616, he remodelled the gardens to include ponds, wilderness and a [[parterre]]. A garden mount&amp;ndash; an artificial hill in Blickling's flat landscape, was made to provide views of the new garden. With the accession of [[Sir John Hobart, 2nd Baronet|Sir John Hobart]] (later the 1st Earl of Buckingham) in 1698 the garden was expanded to add a new wilderness and the temple was constructed. 

In the latter half of the 18th century John Hobart, 2nd Earl of Buckingham, embarked on works that would radically change the appearance of the gardens. All traces of formality were removed, and naturally arranged clumps of trees were planted to create a [[landscape garden]]. By the 1780s an [[orangery]] had been built to overwinter tender [[citrus]] trees. Following the 2nd Earl's death in 1793, his youngest daughter Caroline, Lady Suffield, employed landscape gardener [[Humphry Repton]] and his son John Adie to advise on garden matters. John Adie Repton would go on to provide designs for many garden features. The estate was inherited by nine-year-old William Schomberg Robert Kerr, 8th Marquess of Lothian in 1840. He later re-introduced the formality and colour schemes of the parterre. After his death at the age of 38, responsibility for the gardens rested with Lady Lothian and her head gardener Mr Lyon. [[Philip Henry Kerr]], 11th Marquis of Lothian, inherited the estate in 1930. After disparaging comments in a publication of [[Country Life (magazine)|''Country Life'']], Lothian engaged [[socialite]] gardener [[Norah Lindsay]] to remodel the gardens. In the parterre she replaced the jumble of minuscule flower beds with four large square beds planted with a mixture of  herbaceous plants in graduated and harmonious colours. Other improvements included removal of a line of [[conifers]] in the Temple walk, which were replaced with plantings of [[azaleas]].&lt;ref name=Bli&gt;Newman, J.''The National Trust, Blickling Hall'' pp56-65, p69 ISBN 0-7078-0086-2&lt;/ref&gt;

== The garden today ==
The garden at Blickling contains formal and informal gardens, [[Grade II listed]] buildings and structures, woodland, specimen trees, [[Victorian era|Victorian]] garden ornaments, [[topiary]], the kitchen garden (open to the public (2010), and 18th century [[Taxus baccata|yew]] hedges.

The lawns which frame the main approach to the hall are bounded by yew hedges which were first recorded by William Freeman of Hamels in 1745.&lt;ref name=Bli/&gt; Surrounding the hall on three sides is the dry '''Moat'''. The plantings in the moist, sheltered conditions of the moat were considerably revised by Lindsay who introduced [[hosta]], species of [[hydrangea]], [[budlea]] and [[rosemary]]. 
To the rear of the hall is the noted '''Parterre''' garden which is located on the east lawn. Originally created as a Victorian sunken garden it was remodelled by Lindsay in the early 1930s. Set around an 18th century listed stone fountain, she divided the garden into four large, colourful [[herbaceous plant|herbaceous]] beds surrounded by L shaped borders stocked with roses and [[catmint]] with an [[acorn]] shaped yew marking each corner. In the terraces above the parterre there are plantings of [[peony]], seasonal beds and the '''Double Borders''' created in 2006, contain a wide variety of [[perennials]], shrubs and [[grasses]] with colours ranging from hot to cool. Close by, are the '''White''' and '''Black Borders''' which were established in 2009, together with a collection of [[elaeagnus]]. The western side of the garden features the lawned '''Acre''' which is fringed by a spreading [[oriental plane]] tree. Outdoor sports such as [[croquet]] are played here in the summer months. Further highlights are a collection of [[magnolia]] underplanted with autumn [[cyclamen]] , the shell fountain and the kitchen garden. To the north of the parterre is the '''Wilderness''' garden which is bisected by radial grassed avenues flanked with [[turkey oak]], [[Tilia|lime]] and [[beech]] trees and naturalised bulbs. The wilderness hides a '''Secret Garden''' with a [[Summerhouse (building)|summerhouse]], scented plants and a central [[sundial]]. Nearby is the listed 18th century [[orangery]] which houses a collection of [[citrus]] trees. Adjacent, to the building is the steep sided '''Dell''' which is home to many woodland plants including a selection of [[hellebore]] and [[foxglove]]. In 2009, an area of woodland was cleared close to the orangery to create a new garden. Stocked with a wide range of woodland plants including [[camellia]] and varieties of [[mahonia]]. Opened in 2010, it will be known as the '''Orangery Garden'''. The Grade II listed Temple is approached by the Temple walk which is lined with [[azalea]] planted by Lindsay in her original 1930s design. Scattered throughout the garden are many garden ornaments including thirty pieces supplied to Lady Lothian in 1877 by Austin &amp; Seeley of [[Euston Road]], London.&lt;ref name=Bli/&gt;

==References==
{{Reflist}}
* [[Thomas Woodcock (officer of arms)|Woodcock, T.]], [[John Martin Robinson|Robinson, J.]], ''Heraldry in Historic Houses of Great Britain'', p.&amp;nbsp;46-51,pb. 2000, ISBN 0-8109-6691-3
* Stephen Cooper, ''The Real Falstaff, Sir John Fastolf and the Hundred Years War'',  (Pen &amp; Sword, 2010)

==External links ==
{{commons category|Blickling Hall}}
*[http://www.nationaltrust.org.uk/main/w-vh/w-visits/w-findaplace/w-blickling-estate.htm Blickling Hall, Garden &amp; Park information at the National Trust]
*[http://www.mythsandlegends.com/mythsandlegends/story17-the-headless-ghosts-of-blickling-hall.html The Headless ghosts of Blickling Hall - an animated myth]
{{coord|52.8118|N|1.2318|E|display=title}}

[[Category:Broadland]]
[[Category:Gardens in Norfolk]]
[[Category:Country houses in Norfolk]]
[[Category:Historic house museums in Norfolk]]
[[Category:National Trust properties in Norfolk]]
[[Category:Grade I listed buildings in Norfolk]]
[[Category:Grade I listed houses]]
[[Category:Houses completed in 1616]]

[[de:Blickling Hall]]
[[es:Blickling Hall]]
[[no:Blickling Hall]]
[[pt:Blickling Hall]]
[[ru:Бликлинг-холл]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
