<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="14609626" ns="0" title="Battle of Sampur"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Infobox military conflict
|conflict=Battle of Sampur
|partof=the [[Sri Lankan civil war]]
|image=
|caption=
|date=28 August 2006 - 4 September 2006
|place=[[Sampur (Sri Lanka)|Sampur]], [[Sri Lanka]]
|casus=
|territory=
|result=Sri Lankan Army victory
|combatant1=[[Image:Coat of arms of Sri Lanka.svg|18px]] [[Military of Sri Lanka]]
|combatant2=[[Liberation Tigers of Tamil Eelam]]
|commander1=
|commander2=
|strength1=
|strength2=
|casualties1=33 killed (SLA claim) {{Citation needed|date=July 2008}}
|casualties2=200+ killed (SLA claim) {{Citation needed|date=July 2008}}
|notes=
}}
{{Campaignbox Sri Lankan Civil War}}
{{Main|Eastern Theater of Eelam War IV}}

The '''Battle of Sampur''' was a battle fought in 2006 for the town of [[Sampur (Sri Lanka)|Sampur]].

==Background==

Since the resumption of violence, concerns were mounting among the military establishment that the strategically crucial&lt;ref name=&quot;reuters1&quot;&gt;{{cite news |url = http://today.reuters.co.uk/news/CrisesArticle.aspx?storyId=COL24804|title = Sri Lanka army battles rebels in northeast|work = Peter Apps|publisher = Reuters |date = 12 September 2006}}&lt;/ref&gt; Sri Lanka Navy base in Trinconmalee was under grave threat from LTTE gun positions located in and around [[Sampur (Sri Lanka)|Sampur]], which lies across the Koddiyar Bay from Trincomalee.&lt;ref name=&quot;saag1&quot;&gt;{{cite news |url = http://www.saag.org/%5Cnotes4%5Cnote331.html|title = Sri Lanka: LTTE's moment of truth at Sampur - Update 101|work = Col R Hariharan (retd.|publisher = South Asai Analysis Group |date = 8 September 2006}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;hindu4&quot;&gt;{{cite news |url = http://www.hindu.com/2006/09/05/stories/2006090505251300.htm|title =  Sri Lankan army captures Sampur|work = B. Muralidhar Reddy |publisher = The Hindu |date = 5 September 2006}}&lt;/ref&gt; Artillery fired from LTTE bases in the area could potentially cripple the naval base, bringing it to a complete standstill and therefore cutting the only military supply chain to Jaffna. All movements of naval vessels were also under the constant surveillance of the LTTE.&lt;ref name=&quot;saag1&quot;/&gt; These fears were backed up by a United States military advisory team which visited the island in 2005.

==The battle==

Following the clashes in Mavil Aru (Mavil Oya) and Muttur (Mooduthara), the LTTE had intensified attacks targeting the naval base in Trincomalee ,&lt;ref name=&quot;hindu4&quot;/&gt; and in a speech on 21 August, Sri Lankan president Mahinda Rajapakse made clear the government intentions were to neutralise the LTTE threat from [[Sampur (Sri Lanka)|Sampur]] .&lt;ref name=&quot;hindu4&quot;/&gt; On 28 August, the Sri Lankan military launched an assault to retake the LTTE camps in [[Sampur (Sri Lanka)|Sampur]], and the adjoining Kaddaiparichchan and Thoppur  areas. This led the LTTE to declare that if the offensive continued, the ceasefire would be officially over.{{Citation needed|date=January 2009}}

After steady progress, Sri Lankan security forces led by Brigade Commander Sarath Wijesinghe&lt;ref name=&quot;hindu5&quot;/&gt; re-captured [[Sampur (Sri Lanka)|Sampur]] (Somapura) from the LTTE on 4 September, and began to establish military bases there,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |url = http://www.bloomberg.com/apps/news?pid=20601080&amp;sid=ax6hzULkWuCE|title = Sri Lanka Army captures Sampur|work = |publisher = [[Bloomberg.com]] |date = 4 September 2006}}&lt;/ref&gt; as the LTTE admitted that the army had control of the area and stated their cadres withdrew from the strategically important town.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |url = http://www.bbc.co.uk/sinhala/news/story/2006/09/060904_sampoor_defeat.shtml| title = LTTE admits defeat in Sampoor|work = |publisher = BBC |date = 4 September 2006}}&lt;/ref&gt; It marked the first significant territorial change of hands since the signing of the ceasefire agreement in 2002.&lt;ref name=&quot;iht1&quot;&gt;{{cite news |url = http://www.iht.com/articles/ap/2006/09/04/asia/AS_GEN_Sri_Lanka.php|title =  Sri Lankan military captures key rebel territory, Tigers vow to keep fighting|work = |publisher = [[International Herald Tribune]] |date = 3 September 2006}}&lt;/ref&gt; The Sri Lankan Military claimed that it lost 33 soldiers in the offensive. The Sri Lankan Military further claimed that and over 200 LTTE cadres were killed.&lt;ref name=&quot;hindu5&quot;&gt;{{cite news |url = http://www.hindu.com/2006/09/12/stories/2006091204601400.htm|title =  Fierce battles continue in Jaffna|work = B. Muralidhar Reddy|publisher = The Hindu |date = 12 September 2006}}&lt;/ref&gt; LTTE claimed that 97 civilians were killed and over 215 civilians were further injured as a result of the military offensive. LTTE also pointed out that this offensive was a violation of the Cease Fire Agreement by the Sri Lankan Military.&lt;ref name=&quot;hindu4&quot;/&gt;

==See also==
*[[List of Sri Lankan Civil War battles]]

==References==
{{Reflist}}

{{coord missing|Sri Lanka}}
{{Use dmy dates|date=August 2010}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Battle Of Sampur}}
[[Category:Battles of the Sri Lankan Civil War]]
[[Category:Conflicts in 2006]]
[[Category:2006 in Sri Lanka]]
[[Category:Eelam War IV]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
