<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="14609962" ns="0" title="Ahmed Fouad Negm"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Infobox musical artist
|name = Ahmed Fouad Negm
|image = احمد فؤاد نجم.jpg
|caption = Ahmed Fouad Negm
|image_size = 
|background =  solo_singer
|birth_name = 
|alias = Ahmed Negm
|birth_date = {{Birth date|1929|5|22|df=y}}
|origin = [[Sharqia Governorate|Sharqia]], [[Egypt]]
| Nationality = Egyptian
| death_date  =
| death_place = [[Egypt]]
|instrument = [[Vocals]], [[Oud]]
|genre = Egyptian music          
|occupation = [[Vernacular]] [[poetry|poet]]
|years_active = 
|label = 
|associated_acts = 
|website = 
|current_members = 
|past_members = 
}}

'''Ahmed Fouad Negm''' ({{lang-ar|احمد فؤاد نجم}}, {{IPA-arz|ˈæħmæd foˈʔæːd ˈneɡm|pron}}; popularly known as '''el-Fagommi''' الفاجومي ({{IPA-arz|elfæˈɡuːmi|}}) is an [[Egyptians|Egyptian]] [[vernacular]] [[poetry|poet]]. Born in [[Sharqia Governorate|Sharqia]], [[Egypt]] on May 22, 1929, Negm is well-known for his work with Egyptian composer [[Sheikh Imam]], as well as his patriotic and revolutionary [[Egyptian Arabic]] poetry. Negm has been regarded as a folk hero and voice for the Egyptian underclass.&lt;ref&gt;Slackman, NYT 2006&lt;/ref&gt;

==Background==

Ahmed Fouad Negm was born to a family of [[fellah]]in the Egyptian countryside. His mother, Hanem Morsi Negm, was a housewife, and his father Mohammed Ezat Negm, a police officer. Negm was one of seventeen brothers, only six of whom are still living. Like many poets and writers of his generation, he received his education at the religious Kutaab schools managed by [[El-Azhar]].

When his father died, he went to live with his uncle Hussein in [[Zagazig]], but was placed in an orphanage in 1936 where he first met famous singer [[Abdel Halim Hafez]]. In 1945, at the age of 17, he left the orphanage and returned to his village to work as a shepherd. Later, he moved to [[Cairo]] to live with his brother who eventually kicked him out only to return to his village again to work in one of the English camps while helping with guerilla operations. 

After the agreement between [[Egypt]] and [[United Kingdom|Britain]], the Egyptian National Workers’ Movement asked everyone in the English camps to quit their job. Negm was then appointed by the Egyptian government as a laborer in mechanical workshops. He was imprisoned for 3 years for counterfeiting form, during which he participated and won first place in a writing competition organized by the Supreme Council for the Arts. He then published his first collection “Pictures from Life and Prison” in vernacular Egyptian Arabic and became famous after Suhair El-Alamawi introduced his book while he was still in prison. After he was released, he was appointed as a clerk in the organization for Asian and African peoples. He also became a regular poet on Egyptian radio. 

Negm lived in a small room on the rooftop of a house in [[Boulaq]] el-Dakror neighborhood. When he met singer and composer [[Sheikh Imam]] in Khosh Adam neighborhood, they became roommates and formed a famous signing duet. Negm was also imprisoned several times due to his political views, particularly his harsh criticism of [[President of Egypt|Egyptian presidents]] [[Gamal Abdel Nasser]], [[Anwar Sadat]] and [[Hosni Mubarak]].
 
In 2007, Negm was chosen by the [[United Nations]] Poverty Action as Ambassador of the poor.

== Work ==
{{Expand section|date=June 2008}}
This link is for some of his work...
[http://www.egyptsons.com/misr/showthread.php?t=865]
Kalb elset
Arees Eldawla
Elbetaa

==Notes==
{{reflist}}

==External links==
*[http://www.bel3arabi.com/sha3er.php?id=1 Ahmed Foad Negm on Bel3arabi.com Network ].
*[http://www.alarabiya.net/programs/2011/02/08/136774.html Rawafed: documentary interview Ahmed Fouad Negm &quot;part one&quot; Alarabiya.net]
*[http://www.alarabiya.net/programs/2011/02/09/136934.html Rawafed: documentary interview Ahmed Fouad Negm &quot;part two&quot; Alarabiya.net]

==References==
* Slackman, Michael. [http://www.nytimes.com/2006/05/13/world/africa/13negm.html?_r=1&amp;hp&amp;ex=1147579200&amp;en=64349ca24dfa0403&amp;ei=5094&amp;partner=homepage&amp;oref=slogin A Poet Whose Political Incorrectness Is a Crime]. New York Times. May 13, 2006.

{{Persondata &lt;!-- Metadata: see [[Wikipedia:Persondata]]. --&gt;
| NAME              = Negm, Ahmad Fouad
| ALTERNATIVE NAMES =
| SHORT DESCRIPTION =
| DATE OF BIRTH     = May 22, 1929
| PLACE OF BIRTH    =
| DATE OF DEATH     =
| PLACE OF DEATH    = [[Egypt]]
}}
{{DEFAULTSORT:Negm, Ahmad Fouad}}
[[Category:1929 births]]
[[Category:Living people]]
[[Category:Egyptian poets]]
[[Category:People from Sharqia Governorate]]
[[Category:Members of the Free Egyptians Party]]

[[ar:أحمد فؤاد نجم]]
[[fr:Ahmed Fouad Najm]]
[[arz:احمد فؤاد نجم]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
