<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="146249" ns="0" title="Outer core"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">[[Image:Earth-crust-cutaway-english.svg|thumb|350px|right|Earth cutaway from core to [[exosphere]]. '''Partially to scale''']]

The '''outer core''' of the [[Earth]] is a liquid layer about 2,266 kilometers thick composed of [[iron]] and [[nickel]] which lies above the Earth's solid [[inner core]] and below its [[mantle (geology)|mantle]]. Its outer boundary lies {{convert|2890|km|mi|abbr=on}} beneath the Earth's surface. The transition between the inner core and outer core is located approximately 5,150&amp;nbsp;km beneath the Earth's surface.

The temperature of the outer core ranges from 4400 °C in the outer regions to 6100 °C near the inner core. Because of its high temperature, modeling work has shown that the outer core is a low [[viscosity]] fluid (about ten times the viscosity of liquid metals at the surface) that convects [[turbulence|turbulently]].&lt;ref&gt;Gilles A. de Wijs et. al., ''The viscosity of liquid iron at the physical conditions of the Earth's core,'' Nature 392, 805-807 (23 April 1998) {{cite journal|doi=10.1038/33905 | volume=392 | issue=6678}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Eddy current]]s in the nickel iron [[fluid]] of the outer core are believed to influence the [[Earth's magnetic field]]. The average magnetic field strength in the Earth's outer core was measured to be 25 Gauss, 50 times stronger than the magnetic field at the surface.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.science20.com/news_articles/first_measurement_magnetic_field_inside_earths_core&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;http://www.nature.com/nature/journal/v468/n7326/full/nature09643.html&lt;/ref&gt; The outer core is not under enough pressure to be solid, so it is liquid even though it has a composition similar to that of the inner core. [[Sulfur]] and [[oxygen]] could also be present in the outer core.

As heat is transferred outward toward the mantle, the net trend is for the inner boundary of the liquid region to freeze, causing the solid core to grow.&lt;ref name=nature473_361&gt;{{citation | first1=David | last1=Gubbins | first2=Binod | last2=Sreenivasan | first3=Jon | last3=Mound | first4=Sebastian | last4=Rost | title=Melting of the Earth’s inner core | journal=Nature | volume=473 | pages=361–363 | date=May 19, 2011 | doi=doi:10.1038/nature10068 }}&lt;/ref&gt; This growth rate is estimated to be 1&amp;nbsp;mm per year.&lt;ref name=ng4_264&gt;{{citation | title=Reconciling the hemispherical structure of Earth’s inner core with its super-rotation | first1=Lauren | last1=Waszek | first2=Jessica | last2=Irving | first3=Arwen | last3=Deuss | journal=Nature Geoscience | volume=4 | pages=264–267 | doi=doi:10.1038/ngeo1083 | date=February 20, 2011 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

Without the outer core, life on Earth would be very different. Convection of liquid metals in the outer core creates the Earth's magnetic field.&lt;ref&gt;[http://woodrowshew.com/pepi05.pdf Woodrow L. Shew, Daniel P. Lathrop, ''Liquid sodium model of geophysical core convection,'' Physics of the Earth and Planetary Interiors 153 (2005) 136–149]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Kent C. Condie, ''Plate Tectonics,'' Butterworth-Heinemann; 4th ed., 1997, p. 140 ISBN 978-0750633864&lt;/ref&gt; This magnetic field extends outward from the Earth for several thousand kilometers, and creates a protective bubble around the Earth that deflects the Sun's [[solar wind]]. Without this field, the solar wind would directly strike the [[Earth's atmosphere]]. This could potentially have slowly removed the Earth's atmosphere, rendering it nearly lifeless, as is hypothesized for [[Mars]].&lt;ref&gt;http://scign.jpl.nasa.gov/learn/plate1.htm&lt;/ref&gt;

The low viscosity of the outer core is important in [[seismology]] because low-viscosity fluids can not sustain [[shear stress]]es: their rapid deformation in response to shear stresses causes the stresses to go to zero. Therefore, [[s-wave]]s attenuate completely in the outer core, and the only s-waves that appear after a wave exits the outer core do so due to splitting of [[p-wave]]s into an s-wave component.
==See also==
* [[Structure of the Earth]]

==References==
&lt;references/&gt;

==External links==
* [http://www.universetoday.com/guide-to-space/earth/earths-outer-core/ Outer core from universetoday.com]

{{earth}}
{{earthsinterior}}

[[Category:Structure of the Earth]]
[[Category:Geomagnetism]]

{{Geophysics-stub}}

[[ca:Nucli extern]]
[[de:Äußerer Erdkern]]
[[et:Välistuum]]
[[es:Núcleo externo]]
[[hu:Külső mag]]
[[ko:외핵]]
[[it:Nucleo esterno]]
[[nl:Buitenkern]]
[[nn:Den ytre kjernen]]
[[pl:Jądro Ziemi]]
[[pt:Núcleo externo]]
[[tr:Dış çekirdek]]
[[vi:Lõi ngoài (Trái Đất)]]
[[zh:外核]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
