<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="146405" ns="0" title="Icelandic króna"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Redirect|ISK|the currency of the Eve Online video game|Gameplay of Eve Online#Economy}}
{{Infobox Currency
|currency_name_in_local = íslensk króna &lt;small&gt;{{is icon}}&lt;/small&gt;
|image_1 = Iceland Krona Coins.jpg
|image_title_1 = 1, 10, 50 and 100 krónur
|image_2 = Isl 500 Kroner.JPG
|image_title_2 = 500 krónur
|iso_code = ISK
|using_countries = {{flag|Iceland}}
|inflation_rate = 3.4%
|inflation_source_date = [http://www.sedlabanki.is/?pageid=201 Central Bank of Iceland] (Statistics Iceland, June 2011)
|subunit_ratio_1 = 1/100
|subunit_name_1 = eyrir (obsolete)
|symbol = kr, Íkr
|plural = krónur
|plural_subunit_1 = aurar
|nickname = kall (100 kr=100kall/hundraðkall)
|used_coins = 1, 5, 10, 50, 100 krónur
|used_banknotes = 500, 1000, 2000, 5000 krónur
|issuing_authority = [[Central Bank of Iceland]]
|issuing_authority_website = www.sedlabanki.is
}}

The '''króna''' (plural '''krónur''') ([[currency sign|sign]]: '''kr'''; [[ISO 4217|code]]: '''ISK''') is the [[currency]] of [[Iceland]]. The króna is technically subdivided into 100 ''aurar'' (singular ''eyrir''),&lt;ref&gt;[http://bin.arnastofnun.is/leit.php?id=4736 &quot;Beygingarlýsing íslensks nútímamáls&quot;]&lt;/ref&gt; but in practice this subdivision is no longer used.

The word ''króna'', meaning &quot;crown&quot;, is related to that of other [[Nordic countries|Nordic]] currencies (such as the [[Danish krone]], [[Swedish krona]] and [[Norwegian krone]]) and to the [[Latin language|Latin]] word ''corona'' (&quot;crown&quot;).&lt;ref&gt;See [[wikt:corona|Wiktionary: ''corona'']].&lt;/ref&gt; The name &quot;Icelandic crown&quot; is sometimes used, for example in the financial markets.

==First króna, 1874–1981==
The [[Danish krone]] was introduced to Iceland in 1874, replacing the earlier Danish currency, the [[Danish rigsdaler|rigsdaler]]. In 1885, Iceland began issuing its own banknotes.

The Icelandic króna separated from the [[Danish krone]] after the dissolution of the [[Scandinavian Monetary Union]] at the start of [[World War I]] and Icelandic autonomy from [[Denmark]] in 1918. The first coins were issued in 1922.

===Coins===
Iceland's first coins were 10 and 25 eyrir pieces introduced in 1922. These were followed in 1925 by denominations 1 and 2 króna pieces and in 1926 by 1, 2 and 5 eyrir pieces. In 1946, the coins' designs were altered to remove the royal monogram (CXR), following Icelandic independence from Denmark in 1944, when Denmark (but not Iceland) was occupied by [[Nazi Germany]].

Starting in 1967, new coins were introduced due to a considerable fall in the value of the króna. 10 króna coins were introduced in that year, followed by 50 eyrir and 5 króna pieces in 1969 and 50 króna pieces in 1970.

===Banknotes===
The first notes issued in 1885 by the ''Landssjóð Íslands'' were in denominations of 5, 10 and 50 krónur. In 1904, the Bank of Iceland (''Íslands Banki'') took over note production and introduced 100 króna notes. In 1921, the ''Ríkissjóður Íslands'' began issuing paper money, with notes for 1, 5, 10 and 50 krónur.

In 1929, another bank, the ''[[Landsbanki Íslands]]'' took over issuance of denominations of 5 krónur and above, with the Ríkissjóð Íslands continuing to issue 1 króna notes until 1947. The Landsbanki Íslands introduced 500 króna notes in 1935, followed by 25 and 1000 króna notes in 1957.

In 1961, the ''[[Central Bank of Iceland|Seðlabanki Íslands]]'' became the central bank of Iceland and started issuing paper money, in denominations of 10, 25, 100, 500, 1000 and 5000 krónur.

==Second króna, 1981–present==
In 1981, the Icelandic króna was revalued, with 100 old krónur (ISJ) being worth 1 new króna (ISK).

Technically, the króna is still composed of 100 aurar, although, in practice, coins less than one króna have not circulated for many years. In September 2002, [[Davíð Oddsson]], the Icelandic [[Prime Minister of Iceland|Prime Minister]] at the time, signed two regulations decreeing that all monetary amounts on invoices and financial claims should be stated and paid in whole krónur only and that coins with a value of less than one króna should be withdrawn from circulation. Aurar are still used for pricing certain shares on the [[Iceland Stock Exchange]].

===Coins===
In 1981, coins were introduced in denominations of 5, 10 and 50 aurar, 1 and 5 krónur. These were followed by 10 króna pieces in 1984, 50 krónur in 1987 and 100 krónur in 1995. As of 1 October 2003, Icelandic banks no longer accept the 5, 10 and 50 aurar coins.

===Banknotes===
Icelandic banknotes are printed with the dates from which the legal basis of the currency derives. In 1981, notes were issued in denominations of 10, 50, 100 and 500 krónur on the law of 29 March 1961. 1000 krónur notes were introduced in 1984, followed by 5000 krónur notes in 1986 with the same law.

100, 500, and 1000 krónur were reissued in 1994 on the law of 5 May 1986. In the following year, a new denomination 2000 krónur was issued for the very first time. The 2000 króna note is subtly different from the other notes. For example, the underprint pattern extends all the way upward and downward, while the other denominations had white margins on every side. The [[Arabic numerals|Arabic numeral]] ''2000'' is printed in multi color on 3 of the 4 instances. And the numeral ''2000'' on the lower left corner of reverse is vertical. The &quot;shadow&quot; of the numeral is printed with SÍ in [[microprint]].

The 22 May 2001 series saw more changes than mere date update. The underprint and microprint change of the 2000 króna note were incorporated. The 1000 and 5000 krónur notes also received metallic foils next to the portrait.

Notes of 100 krónur or less no longer circulate, as they have been withdrawn by the central bank. As of 2006, the vast majority of banknotes in circulation are of the 500, 1000, 2000 and 5000 denominations (these generally being the only notes dispensed in ATMs, for example).

{| class=&quot;wikitable&quot; style=&quot;font-size: 90%&quot;
|-
!colspan=&quot;9&quot;| Law of 29 March 1961 Series&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.sedlabanki.is/?PageID=272 &quot;Valid notes in Iceland&quot;]. ''Central Bank of Iceland''.&lt;/ref&gt;
|-
!colspan=&quot;2&quot;| Image !!rowspan=&quot;2&quot;| Value !!rowspan=&quot;2&quot;| Dimensions !!rowspan=&quot;2&quot;| Main Colour !!colspan=&quot;3&quot;| Description !!rowspan=&quot;2&quot;| Date of issue
|-
! Obverse !! Reverse !! Obverse !! Reverse !! Watermark
|-
|  style=&quot;text-align:center; background:#888;&quot;| [[Image:ISK 10 note.jpg|91px|10 krónur]]
|  style=&quot;text-align:center; background:#888;&quot;| &lt;!-- Deleted image removed: [[Image:ISK 10 note back.jpg|91px|10 krónur]] --&gt;
| 10 krónur
| 130 × 70&amp;nbsp;mm
| Blue
| [[Arngrímur Jónsson|Arngrímur Jónsson the Learned]]
| Old Icelandic household scene based on [[Auguste Mayer]]'s drawing
|rowspan=&quot;6&quot;| [[Jón Sigurðsson]]
|rowspan=&quot;4&quot;| 1981
|-
|  style=&quot;text-align:center; background:#888;&quot;| &lt;!-- Deleted image removed: [[Image:ISK 50 note.jpg|95px|50 krónur]] --&gt;
|  style=&quot;text-align:center; background:#888;&quot;| &lt;!-- Deleted image removed: [[Image:ISK 50 note back.jpg|95px|50 krónur]] --&gt;
| 50 krónur
| 135 × 70&amp;nbsp;mm
| Brown
| [[Guðbrandur Þorláksson]]
| Printers at work in the 16th century
|-
|  style=&quot;text-align:center; background:#888;&quot;|[[Image:Isl Krone.JPG|91px]]
|  style=&quot;text-align:center; background:#888;&quot;|&lt;!-- Deleted image removed: [[Image:100 kronur reverse.jpg|91px]] --&gt;
| 100 krónur
| 140 × 70&amp;nbsp;mm
| Green
| [[Árni Magnússon]]
| Monastic scribe
|-
|  style=&quot;text-align:center; background:#888;&quot;|
|  style=&quot;text-align:center; background:#888;&quot;|
| 500 krónur
| 145 × 70&amp;nbsp;mm
| Red
| [[Jón Sigurðsson]]
| Jón at his writing desk
|-
|  style=&quot;text-align:center; background:#888;&quot;|
|  style=&quot;text-align:center; background:#888;&quot;|
| 1000 krónur
| 150 × 70&amp;nbsp;mm
| Purple
| [[Brynjólfur Sveinsson]]
| Brynjólfskirkja church (1650–1802) at [[Skálholt]]
| 1984
|-
|  style=&quot;text-align:center; background:#888;&quot;| &lt;!-- Deleted image removed: [[Image:ISK 5000 note.jpg|109px|5000 krónur]] --&gt;
|  style=&quot;text-align:center; background:#888;&quot;|
| 5000 krónur
| 155 × 70&amp;nbsp;mm
| Blue-green multicolour
| [[Ragnheiður Jónsdóttir]]
| Ragnheiður instructing two girls in embroidery
| 1986
|-
!colspan=&quot;9&quot;| Law of 5 May 1986 Series
|-
|  style=&quot;text-align:center; background:#888;&quot;| &lt;!-- Deleted image removed: [[Image:ISK 100 note.jpg|98px|100 krónur]] --&gt;
|  style=&quot;text-align:center; background:#888;&quot;| &lt;!-- Deleted image removed: [[Image:ISK 100 note back.jpg|98px|100 krónur]] --&gt;
| 100 krónur
|colspan=&quot;5&quot; rowspan=&quot;3&quot;| As previous
|rowspan=&quot;3&quot;| 1994
|-
|  style=&quot;text-align:center; background:#888;&quot;| [[Image:Isl 500 Kroner.JPG|102px|500 krónur]]
|  style=&quot;text-align:center; background:#888;&quot;| &lt;!-- Deleted image removed: [[Image:ISK 500 note back.JPG|102px|500 krónur]] --&gt;
| 500 krónur
|-
|  style=&quot;text-align:center; background:#888;&quot;| &lt;!-- Deleted image removed: [[Image:ISK 1000 note.jpg|105px|1000 krónur]] --&gt;
|  style=&quot;text-align:center; background:#888;&quot;|
| 1000 krónur
|-
|  style=&quot;text-align:center; background:#888;&quot;| &lt;!-- Deleted image removed: [[Image:ISK 2000 note.jpg|105px|2000 krónur]] --&gt;
|  style=&quot;text-align:center; background:#888;&quot;| &lt;!-- Deleted image removed: [[Image:ISK 2000 note back.jpg|105px|2000 krónur]] --&gt;
| 2000 krónur
| 150 × 70&amp;nbsp;mm
| Multicolour
| [[Jóhannes Kjarval]]
| Kjarval's painting ''Yearning for Flight'' and his drawing ''Woman and Flowers''
| [[Jón Sigurðsson]]
| 1995
|-
!colspan=&quot;9&quot;| Law of 22 May 2001 Series
|-
|  style=&quot;text-align:center; background:#888;&quot;|
|  style=&quot;text-align:center; background:#888;&quot;|
| 500 krónur
|colspan=&quot;5&quot; rowspan=&quot;3&quot;| As previous, but the underprint design extends upward and downward to fill the margin
| October 2005
|-
|  style=&quot;text-align:center; background:#888;&quot;|
|  style=&quot;text-align:center; background:#888;&quot;| &lt;!-- Deleted image removed: [[Image:ISK 1000 note back.jpg|105px|1000 krónur]] --&gt;
| 1000 krónur
| November 2004
|-
|  style=&quot;text-align:center; background:#888;&quot;|
|  style=&quot;text-align:center; background:#888;&quot;| &lt;!-- Deleted image removed: [[Image:ISK 5000 note back.jpg|109px|5000 krónur]] --&gt;
| 5000 krónur
| November 2003
|-
|colspan=&quot;9&quot;|{{Standard banknote table notice|standard_scale=Y|BrE=Y}}
|}

==Currency issues==
Iceland is not currently a member of the [[European Union]] and does not use the [[euro]].
The Icelandic currency is a low-volume world currency, strongly managed by its central bank, with a high degree of volatility against the US and [[Canadian dollar]]s, and against the currencies of the other Nordic countries ([[Swedish krona]], [[Norwegian krone]], [[Danish krone]], and euro). For example, during the first half of 2006, the Icelandic króna ranged between 50 and 80 per US$. Prior to the currency's collapse in October 2008, the króna was considered overvalued; in July 2008, a [[Big Mac Index|Big Mac]] cost the equivalent of nearly six US dollars, versus $3.57 in the US.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.economist.com/finance/displaystory.cfm?story_id=11793125 Big Macs reveal Europe's strong currencies]&lt;/ref&gt;

At most shops electronic payment is accepted. Other currencies are very rarely accepted in Iceland. A notable exception is [[Keflavík International Airport]] (which has many transfer passengers), where the US dollar, euro and some other currencies are accepted by all merchants. Certain stores in downtown Reykjavík accept some foreign currencies.

The overall level of technological sophistication is noteworthy in Iceland. Iceland has, for example, among the highest per capita computer usage in the world ([[List of Internet users by country|far higher than the UK or US]]).&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.itu.int/ITU-D/ict/statistics/material/excel/2010/InternetUsersPercentage00-10.xls |title=Internet users |publisher=[[International Telecommunication Union]] |accessdate=2011-11-14 |format=XLS}}&lt;/ref&gt; The saturation of technology in Iceland has had ramifications in the monetary system; a very large percentage of all transactions in Iceland take place through electronic forms of payment, such as debit and credit cards and online bank transfers. It is also worth noting that the value of banknotes is relatively small, e.g., the largest denomination banknote is the 5000 króna note, while a mid-range dinner for two in Iceland, without drinks or dessert, can easily exceed 5000 krónur (ca. EUR 28 in June 2009). This effect may accelerate the Icelandic move towards a semi-cashless economy.

===2008 financial crisis===
[[File:EUR against ISK 2000-2009.png|thumb|Exchange rate ISK per euro]]
{{Main|2008–2011 Icelandic financial crisis}}

In October 2008, the effects of the [[Financial crisis of 2007–2008|2007/08 global financial crisis]] brought about a collapse of the Icelandic banking sector. The value of the Icelandic króna plummeted, and on 7 October 2008 the Icelandic Central Bank attempted to peg it at 131 against the euro.&lt;ref&gt;Mason, Rowena. [http://www.telegraph.co.uk/finance/newsbysector/banksandfinance/3154116/Financial-crisis-Iceland-nationalises-bank-and-seeks-Russian-loan.html &quot;Financial crisis: Iceland nationalises bank and seeks Russian loan&quot;]. ''[[The Daily Telegraph]]''. 8 October 2008.&lt;/ref&gt; This peg was abandoned the next day.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.bloomberg.com/apps/news?pid=20601087&amp;sid=ahAQVJ69AmOc&amp;refer=home&lt;/ref&gt; The króna later fell to 340 against the euro before trade in the currency was suspended&lt;ref&gt;Brogger, Tasneem; Einarsdottir, Helga Kristin. [http://www.bloomberg.com/apps/news?pid=20601087&amp;sid=aVFtDRGwcc50&amp;refer=home&amp;refer=europe &quot;Icelandic Shoppers Splurge as Currency Woes Reduce Food Imports&quot;]. [[Bloomberg, L.P.]] 13 October 2008.&lt;/ref&gt; (by comparison, the rate at the start of 2008 was about 90 krónur to the euro&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.ecb.int/stats/exchange/eurofxref/html/eurofxref-graph-isk.en.html Historical EUR/ISK exchange rate graphs], European Central Bank&lt;/ref&gt;). After a period of tentative, very low-volume international trading in the króna, activity had been expected to pick up again throughout November 2008, albeit still with low liquidity, as Iceland secured an [[International Monetary Fund]] loan.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.guardian.co.uk/business/feedarticle/7993351 Iceland crown international trade seen restarting soon], ''Guardian''/Reuters, November 6, 2008&lt;/ref&gt; However as of January 2009 the krona was still not being traded regularly, with the ECB reference rate being set only intermittently, the last time on December 3, 2008 at 290 ISK per euro.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.ecb.int/stats/exchange/eurofxref/html/index.en.html&lt;/ref&gt;

The Icelandic krona similarly fell in value against the US dollar, from c. 50 to 80 per dollar to about 110-115 per dollar; by mid-November 2008 it had continued its slide to c. 135 to the dollar. As of April 2, 2009, the value hovered around 119 per US dollar, roughly maintaining that value over the next two years with March 23, 2011, prices around 114 per US dollar.&lt;ref&gt;[http://finance.yahoo.com/q?s=USDISK=X Yahoo finance data]&lt;/ref&gt; Previously high costs for foreign tourists thereby dropped, which Iceland's tourism industry hopes to exploit.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.icelandtouristboard.com/dateline/jan09/email.html&lt;/ref&gt;

===Iceland and the euro===
Theoretically the adoption of the euro could have several advantages. Adopting a stronger currency may help Iceland to &quot;avoid the turbulence surrounding speculations in international financial markets&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;Iceland's currency dilemma&quot;&gt;http://www.ifo.de/pls/guestci/download/CESifo%20Forum%202006/CESifo%20Forum%202/2006/forum2-06-special.pdf&lt;/ref&gt; In addition, Icelandic economists listed several arguments in favour of the euro before the crisis. &quot;In terms of growth potentials and welfare, the euro could be expected to bring lower long-term interest rates [...]. This would of course increase capital investment and labour productivity. The euro might lower consumer prices by facilitating a comparison with other euro countries.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;Iceland's currency dilemma&quot;/&gt;
Because of the volatility between the [[euro]] and the króna, former [[Minister for Foreign Affairs of Iceland|Foreign Minister]] [[Valgerður Sverrisdóttir]] considered the idea that Iceland might [[dollarize]] itself into the [[eurozone]] without joining the European Union.{{Citation needed|reason=claimed to be from Norwegian news NRK|date=June 2009}}

The opinion regarding the euro is mixed among Icelanders. An opinion poll on the matter of Iceland joining the European Union released on September 11, 2007, by Capacent Gallup showed that 53% of respondents were in favour of adopting the [[euro]], 37% opposed and 10% undecided.&lt;ref&gt;Olafsdottir, Audbjorg. [http://www.reuters.com/article/bondsNews/idUSL1111656420070911 &quot;Euro support in Iceland hits five-year high&quot;]. [[Reuters]]. 11 September 2007.&lt;/ref&gt; Another poll produced for the Icelandic newspaper Fréttablaðið and released on 30 September 2007 showed 56% opposed to euro adoption and 44% in favour.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.mbl.is/mm/frettir/innlent/frett.html?nid=1294123 &quot;Meirihluti andvígur upptöku evru&quot;] (Icelandic). ''[[Morgunblaðið]]''. 30 September 2007.&lt;/ref&gt; In January 2008, a poll by the Icelandic Chamber of Commence put support for Iceland to abandon the króna for another currency at 63%. Additionally, a number of companies in Iceland such as [[Ossur]], have started to pay their employees in euros or US dollars, mainly due the high inflation and high volatility.&lt;ref&gt;Furlong, Ray.                                             [http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/business/7651313.stm &quot;Iceland's financial freeze&quot;]. [[BBC]]. 3 October 2008.&lt;/ref&gt;

The 2008/2009 financial crisis prompted further calls for Iceland to join the eurozone. In January 2009, one senior Icelandic official stated that due to the crisis &quot;the krona is dead. We need a new currency. The only serious option is the euro.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.guardian.co.uk/world/2009/jan/30/iceland-join-eu Iceland to be fast-tracked into the EU], the Guardian&lt;/ref&gt; In March 2009, a report by Iceland's Minister for Foreign Affairs, Össur Skarphédinsson, considered three options: retaining the krona, adopting the euro without joining the EU and adopting the euro through EU membership. The report recommended the third option.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.icelandreview.com/icelandreview/daily_news/?cat_id=29314&amp;ew_0_a_id=321992 &quot;Could EU Application Save Billions for Iceland?&quot;], Iceland Review Online, 27 March 2009&lt;/ref&gt;

An economic study of the impact of the adoption of the euro by Iceland found that &quot;the Icelandic krona acts as a barrier to international trade, and that by joining the EU and adopting the euro, Icelandic trade could increase by 60%&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;http://cje.oxfordjournals.org/cgi/content/abstract/30/5/723&lt;/ref&gt;

In July 2009, the Alþingi narrowly voted to apply for EU membership (see [[Accession of Iceland to the European Union]]).
{{Exchange Rate|ISK|DKK|NOK|SEK}}

==See also==
* [[Scandinavian Monetary Union]]
* [[Economy of Iceland]]

==References==
{{Reflist}}
{{Refbegin}}
* {{numis cite SCWC | date=1991}}
* {{numis cite SCWPM | date=1994}}
{{Refend}}

==External links==
* [http://www.coinsv.narod.ru/c_pages/island.htm Vitaly Getmansky coins]

{{Iceland topics|state=autocollapse}}
{{Krone}}
{{Currencies of Europe}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Icelandic Krona}}
[[Category:Economy of Iceland|Krona, Icelandic]]

[[ar:كرونة آيسلندية]]
[[be:Ісландская крона]]
[[be-x-old:Ісьляндзкая крона]]
[[bs:Islandska kruna]]
[[bg:Исландска крона]]
[[ca:Corona islandesa]]
[[cs:Islandská koruna]]
[[da:Islandsk króna]]
[[de:Isländische Krone]]
[[et:Islandi kroon]]
[[el:Κορόνα Ισλανδίας]]
[[es:Corona islandesa]]
[[eo:Islanda krono]]
[[eu:Islandiar koroa]]
[[fr:Couronne islandaise]]
[[ga:Króna]]
[[gl:Coroa islandesa]]
[[ko:아이슬란드 크로나]]
[[hi:आइसलैंडिक क्रोना]]
[[hr:Islandska kruna]]
[[bpy:আইসল্যান্ডিক ক্রোনা]]
[[id:Króna Islandia]]
[[os:Исландийы кронæ]]
[[is:Íslensk króna]]
[[it:Corona islandese]]
[[he:כתר איסלנדי]]
[[ka:ისლანდიური კრონი]]
[[kv:Исландияса крона]]
[[lt:Islandijos krona]]
[[hu:Izlandi korona]]
[[mk:Исландска круна]]
[[nl:IJslandse kroon]]
[[ja:アイスランド・クローナ]]
[[no:Islandsk krone]]
[[nn:Islandsk króna]]
[[pl:Korona islandzka]]
[[pt:Coroa islandesa]]
[[ro:Coroană islandeză]]
[[ru:Исландская крона]]
[[sah:Исландия кроната]]
[[sk:Islandská koruna]]
[[sr:Исландска круна]]
[[sh:Islandska kruna]]
[[fi:Islannin kruunu]]
[[sv:Isländsk krona]]
[[ta:ஐஸ்லாந்திய குரோனா]]
[[tg:Кронаи Исдандия]]
[[tr:İzlanda kronası]]
[[uk:Ісландська крона]]
[[yo:Icelandic króna]]
[[zh-yue:冰島克朗]]
[[bat-smg:Islandėjės kruona]]
[[zh:冰岛克朗]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
