<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="1468357" ns="0" title="Stephanie Mills"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{BLP sources|date=October 2008}}
: ''For the TV series character, see [[Stephanie Mills (All in the Family)]]''.
{{Infobox musical artist
| Image               = Stephanie_Mills_in_2005.jpg
| name                = Stephanie Mills
| background          = solo_singer
| birth_name          = Stephanie Dorthea Mills
| alias               = Cookie
| birth_date                = {{birth date and age|1957|03|22}}
| death_date                =
| origin              = [[Brooklyn]], [[New York City|New York]], [[United States|U.S.]]
| instrument          =
| genre               = [[Contemporary R&amp;B|R&amp;B]], [[Soul music|soul]], [[Gospel Music|gospel]]
| occupation          = [[Singer]]
| years_active        = 1968–present
| label               = [[Motown Records|Motown]], [[20th Century Records|20th Century]], [[Casablanca Records|Casablanca]]
[[MCA Records|MCA]], [[GospoCentric Records|GospoCentric]], LightYear, [[Expansion Records]]
| associated_acts     =
| website                 = [http://www.stephaniemillsmusic.com/ Official website]
| current_members     =
| past_members        =
| notable_instruments =
}}
'''Stephanie Dorthea Mills''' (born March 22, 1957) is an [[United States|American]] [[rhythm and blues|R&amp;B]] and [[soul music|soul]] singer, and a former [[Broadway theatre|Broadway]] star.

==Career==
Mills began her career appearing in her first play at the age of nine. Two years later, Mills won Amateur Night at the [[Apollo Theater]] a record six times. The victory led to her being cast in her first [[Broadway theatre|Broadway]] role, the orphaned child of a runaway slave in the [[musical theatre|musical]] ''[[Maggie Flynn]]''.

In 1973, Mills' musical recording career was launched when she was signed to Paramount records by [[Michael Barbiero]], and her first single &quot;I Knew It Was Love&quot; was released.  She was later signed to Motown.  Her first two albums there failed to generate a buzz as the label could not find Mills' sound and she left the label in 1976.

Mills' career took a rise when she portrayed Dorothy in an [[African American]] adaptation of ''[[The Wonderful Wizard of Oz]]'' entitled ''[[The Wiz]]'', where she began dating [[Michael Jackson]]. Filled with a more urban style of music and scenery, ''The Wiz'' made Mills a star particularly because of her stellar performance of the song &quot;Home.&quot; It would become her signature tune for years, and would be covered later by [[Diana Ross]] for the big-screen adaptation three years later and by [[Whitney Houston]] for her dramatic musical performance debut on TV in the early 1980s.

Musical success was elusive until 1979, when signed under the [[20th Century Fox Records]] record label, Mills found her breakthrough in disco music, recording songs such as &quot;[[Put Your Body In It]],&quot; &quot;You Can Get Over,&quot; and &quot;[[What Cha' Gonna Do With My Lovin (song)|What Cha' Gonna Do With My Lovin']].&quot; The resulting album, ''[[What Cha' Gonna Do with My Lovin']]'', was Mills' first gold record.

She quickly followed the success with 1980's ''Sweet Sensation'', which featured Mills' biggest hit to date, the [[Reggie Lucas]]-produced &quot;[[Never Knew Love Like This Before]]&quot;. The single became a #12 R&amp;B and #6 Pop hit in 1980, as well as reaching #4 in the [[UK Singles Chart]].&lt;ref name=&quot;British Hit Singles &amp; Albums&quot;&gt;{{cite book
| first= David
| last= Roberts
| year= 2006
| title= British Hit Singles &amp; Albums
| edition= 19th
| publisher= Guinness World Records Limited
| location= London
| isbn= 1-904994-10-5
| page= 367}}&lt;/ref&gt; 1981's ''[[Stephanie (Stephanie Mills album)|Stephanie]]'' featured a top hit for her and [[Teddy Pendergrass]] entitled &quot;Two Hearts,&quot; while her 1983 album, ''Merciless'', featured her hit [[cover version|cover]] of Prince's &quot;How Come You Don't Call Me Anymore?&quot;, as well as the #3 dance chart hit &quot;Pilot Error&quot;, which was her first dance hit in the U.S. In 1984, Mills had her third UK hit with &quot;[[The Medicine Song]]&quot; (#29),&lt;ref name=&quot;British Hit Singles &amp; Albums&quot;/&gt; which also reached #1 on the U.S. dance chart.

Success for Mills had peaked until 1985, when her version of the [[Angela Winbush]]-penned &quot;[[I Have Learned to Respect the Power of Love]],&quot; hit #1 on the R&amp;B singles chart. Mills truly returned, however, with her next release, ''If I Were Your Woman'' in 1987 under [[Music Corporation of America|MCA Records]], which she was now signed. The hits from the album include the title track, originally a hit for [[Gladys Knight &amp; the Pips]] in 1971; a three-week #1 R&amp;B hit, &quot;I Feel Good All Over&quot; (a song her label mate [[Patti LaBelle]] did not wish to cover); and &quot;You're Puttin' a Rush on Me,&quot; to name a few of the songs released. The album reached [[RIAA certification|platinum]] status. That same year, she appeared in the NBC TV special, ''Motown: Merry Christmas'' along with other musical artists and actors, performing the song, &quot;Christmas Everyday&quot;, which was written by actor/comedian [[Redd Foxx]].

Mills' success continued with 1989's ''Home'' album. The hits from that album include &quot;The Comfort of a Man,&quot; the title track, a cover of her old standard from ''The Wiz'' and another song penned by Winbush titled &quot;Something in the Way You Make Me Feel.&quot; It became another platinum record for Mills.

Mills would record one more album (1992's ''Something Real'') and a Christmas album before being released from her contract with MCA in 1992. Mills released a live gospel recording in 1995 on [[GospoCentric Records]] entitled ''Personal Inspirations''. The set was produced by [[Donald Lawrence]] and featured a spiritualized retooling of her hit &quot;I Have Learned To Respect The Power Of Love.&quot; Thereafter, Stephanie took a break from recording to care for her son.

Mills returned to musical theater in 1997, playing the lead in a major production of [[Stephen Schwartz (composer)|Stephen Schwartz]]'s ''[[Children of Eden]]'' in New Jersey, which Schwartz has called &quot;the definitive production&quot; of the show.  Mills was heavily featured in the soundtrack CD that resulted from this production.

In 2000, Mills began a comeback with singles recorded with [[BeBe Winans]] and rapper [[DMX (rapper)|DMX]] to name a few. She made a comeback in independently-releasing ''Born For This'' (released on [[Expansion Records]] in the UK) on 3 August 2004. Her first single in over a decade, &quot;Can't Let Him Go,&quot; garnered buzz at urban contemporary radio. Mills is currently touring. A 2-disc, career-spanning greatest hits compilation entitled ''Gold'' was released by Hip-O/Universal Music earlier last year. Mills just finished production of a live DVD recorded at BB Kings in New York which will be sold online and at her shows.

Mills made an appearance in the 2007 gospel TV series ''Sunday Best'' and was recently featured in a live interview on ''The Yolanda Adams Morning Show'', where she mentioned that she now has her own record label (JM Records).

Mills performed prior to [[Pope Benedict XVI]] celebrating Mass at [[Yankee Stadium]] in New York on April 20, 2008.

In a recent interview Mills stated that she would be releasing her Live CD during the end of this year and that Live CD will include two new tracks.

Her new album entitled &quot;Breathless&quot; is set to be released soon. Her New Single &quot;Yesterday&quot; is available for download on iTunes.

==Personal life==
Stephanie is the fifth of six children. She was born and raised predominantly in Brooklyn, New York. Mills claims that she was romantically involved with [[Michael Jackson]] for a short period of time while she was doing ''The Wiz''.{{Citation needed|date=August 2011}}

In 1992, ''[[Ebony (magazine)|Ebony]]'' magazine reported that Mills had been married in the 1970s for a brief period, to [[Jeffrey Daniel]] from the soul group [[Shalamar]] and again in the mid 1980s to Dino Meminger&lt;ref&gt;[http://v1019.radio.com/2010/03/22/happy-birthday-stephanie-mills/ V109.9 &quot;Happy Birthday Stephnie Mills&quot; March 22, 2010]&lt;/ref&gt; but that both marriages had ended in less than two years.&lt;ref&gt;[http://findarticles.com/p/articles/mi_m1077/is_n2_v48/ai_12970639/ Ebony Magazine. &quot;The new Stephanie Mills - singer&quot; Interview by Lynn Norment. Dec, 1992]&lt;/ref&gt;  &quot;I also wanted to know why my relationships never made it to two years. I knew it was me,&quot; says Mills. &quot;You can't blame it on another person. That's where a lot of women go wrong... carrying over from a bad relationship to a new relationship.&quot;

Mills married a third time to Charlotte, North Carolina radio program manager Michael Saunders in 1993 in a wedding ceremony performed by Minister [[Louis Farrakhan]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://findarticles.com/p/articles/mi_m1355/is_n15_v83/ai_13402053/ Jet Magazine. &quot;Stephanie Mills weds&quot; Feb 8, 1993]&lt;/ref&gt;  The couple divorced sometime later.

In an interview with ''Soul Music'' in 2002, Mills said that she had a son, Farad. Mills would not comment on the identity of Farad’s father, other than to say that she is not married, and that her ex-husband Michael Saunders is not Farad's father.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.soulmusic.com/stmi20in.html Soul Music.  &quot;An Interview with Stephanie Mills&quot; By David Nathan. 2002]&lt;/ref&gt;  Mills added that giving birth “was the best thing I’ve ever done. It was amazingly wonderful and I wish I had started earlier. I might have had two or three before but I had some problems before in being able to have children. But things work out when they’re supposed to... now I’m a single working parent and loving it!&quot;

In an interview with Windy City Times in 2010, Mills said that she presently makes her home in [[Charlotte, North Carolina]] and that her son, Farad has [[Down syndrome|Down's Syndrome]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://chicago.gopride.com/news/interview.cfm/articleid/185481 Windy City Times. &quot;Interview :: Stephanie Mills&quot; August 11, 2010]&lt;/ref&gt; &quot;The Shriners are celebrating their 88th anniversary, and they have 22 hospitals nationwide,&quot; says Mills. &quot;And what I love is even my son — I have a child with Down's syndrome — can get access to the best spinal-cord doctors in the country.&quot;

==Discography==
{{Main|Stephanie Mills discography}}

*''[[Movin' in the Right Direction]]'' – 1974
*''[[For the First Time (Stephanie Mills album)|For the First Time]]'' – 1975
*''[[What Cha' Gonna Do with My Lovin']]'' – 1979
*''[[Sweet Sensation (album)|Sweet Sensation]]'' – 1980
*''[[Stephanie (album)|Stephanie]]'' – 1981
*''Tantalizingly Hot'' – 1982
*''Merciless'' – 1983
*''I've Got the Cure'' – 1984
*''Stephanie Mills'' – 1985
*''[[If I Were Your Woman (Stephanie Mills album)|If I Were Your Woman]]'' – 1987
*''Home'' – 1989
*''Christmas'' – 1991
*''Something Real'' – 1992
*''Personal Inspirations'' – 1995
*''Born for This!'' – 2004
*''Breathless'' – 2010

==Awards==
* 1974 &amp;ndash; nominated for [[Drama Desk Award]] for Outstanding Actress - Musical (&quot;The Wiz&quot;).
* 1979 &amp;ndash; nominated for [[American Music Award]]: Favorite Female Artist - Soul / Rhythm &amp; Blues.
* 1980 &amp;ndash; won [[Grammy Award]]: Best Rhythm &amp; Blues Vocal Performance - Female (&quot;Never Knew Love Like This Before&quot;).
* 1980 &amp;ndash; nominated for an [[American Music Award]]: Favorite Female Artist - Soul / Rhythm &amp; Blues
* 1980 &amp;ndash; nominated for [[Young Artist Awards]]: Best Young Musical Recording Artist - Female (&quot;Two Hearts&quot;).
* 1981 &amp;ndash; nominated for a [[Grammy]] Award: Best Rhythm &amp; Blues Vocal Performance - Female (Stephanie).
* 1981 &amp;ndash; won [[American Music Award]] for Favorite Female Artist - Soul / Rhythm &amp; Blues
* 1983 &amp;ndash; nominated for a [[Grammy]] Award: Best Rhythm &amp; Blues Vocal Performance - Female (&quot;Merciless&quot;).
* 1989 &amp;ndash; nominated for [[American Music Award]]: Favorite Female Artist - Soul / Rhythm &amp; Blues

==See also==
* [[List of number-one dance hits (United States)]]
* [[List of artists who reached number one on the US Dance chart]]

==References==
{{Reflist}}

==External links==
*[http://www.stephaniemillsmusic.com/ Stephanie Mills] official website
*[http://www.wlatalent.com/roster/stephanie_mills/artistprofile.htm Stephanie Mills] at Wenig-LaMonica Associates
*{{Allmusic|class=artist|id=p4918}}
*{{IMDb name|0590196}}
*{{IBDB name|53170}}

{{Persondata &lt;!-- Metadata: see [[Wikipedia:Persondata]]. --&gt;
| NAME              =Mills, Stephanie
| ALTERNATIVE NAMES =Mills, Stephanie Dorthea
| SHORT DESCRIPTION =
| DATE OF BIRTH     =March 22, 1957
| PLACE OF BIRTH    =
| DATE OF DEATH     =
| PLACE OF DEATH    =
}}
{{DEFAULTSORT:Mills, Stephanie}}
[[Category:1957 births]]
[[Category:African American singers]]
[[Category:African American female singers]]
[[Category:American child singers]]
[[Category:American dance musicians]]
[[Category:American female singers]]
[[Category:American rhythm and blues singers]]
[[Category:American soul singers]]
[[Category:Grammy Award winners]]
[[Category:Living people]]
[[Category:Motown artists]]
[[Category:People from Brooklyn]]
[[Category:Erasmus Hall High School alumni]]
[[Category:MCA Records artists]]
[[Category:GospoCentric artists]]

[[de:Stephanie Mills]]
[[fr:Stephanie Mills]]
[[nl:Stephanie Mills]]
[[pt:Stephanie Mills]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
