<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="1470770" ns="0" title="Southwick, West Sussex"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Infobox UK place 
 | official_name=Southwick
 | country=England 
 | region=South East England 
 | static_image=
 | static_image_caption=
 | area_footnotes=&lt;ref name=&quot;WSCC2001&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.westsussex.gov.uk/communityandliving/census2001/pop_parish_summary.pdf|title=2001 Census: West Sussex – Population by Parish|publisher=West Sussex County Council|accessdate=22 March 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt;  
 | area_total_sq_mi= 3.33
| population = 13,195
| population_ref = [[United Kingdom Census 2001|2001 Census]]&lt;ref name=&quot;WSCC2001&quot; /&gt;
  | population_density={{convert|3962|/sqmi|/km2|abbr=on}}
 | os_grid_reference=TQ241055
 | latitude=50.836            
 | longitude=-0.239          
 | post_town=SOUTHWICK
 | postcode_area=BN   
 | postcode_district=BN42  
 | dial_code=01273        
 | constituency_westminster=[[East Worthing and Shoreham (UK Parliament constituency)|East Worthing and Shoreham]]
 | london_distance={{convert|46|mi}} [[Boxing the compass|N]]
 | shire_district=[[Adur (district)|Adur]]
 | shire_county=[[West Sussex]]        
 | website=    
 }}
'''Southwick''' is a small town and [[civil parishes in England|civil parish]] in the [[Adur (district)|Adur]] District of [[West Sussex]], [[England]] located  three miles (5&amp;nbsp;km) west of [[Brighton]] and a suburb of the [[East Sussex]] resort City of [[Brighton &amp; Hove]]. The civil parish covers an area of 863.7&amp;nbsp;hectares and has a population of 13,195 persons (2001 census).

The town is loosely divided into three sections: south of Brighton Road is the harbour with its associated industries and businesses; north of Brighton Road up to Old Shoreham Road is mainly residential properties dating from the middle of the nineteenth century to the 1950s; and the area between Old Shoreham Road and [[South Downs]] being the most recent to be developed, although still largely residential.

The main road which passes through the town is the [[A259 road|A259 coast road]]. The [[A27 road]] bypasses the town to its north.

==History==
Southwick was recorded in the [[Domesday book]] (1085): ''Nigel holds Esmerwick of William. Azor held it of King Edward. Then, and now, it vouched for one hide and a half. There is land for 4 ploughs. In demesne are 2 ploughs, and 4 villeins and 6 bordars with 2 ploughs. In the time of King Edward it was worth 40 shillings, and afterwards 30 shillings. Now 4 pounds''. In that excerpt, the village is referred to by its Saxon name, Esmerewick, meaning ''East pool [[hamlet (place)|hamlet]]''.  The village was first recorded as Suthewicke in 1309. 
The town grew as the coast became a popular holiday destination, many of the properties being tourist accommodation. The [[Southwick railway station|railway]] arrived in the town on 12 May 1840, being the original terminus of the line at that time.

The town also has Roman history. The Methodist church on Manor Hall Road is built on top of a Roman villa. There are also corresponding road names in the area, such as Roman Road, and Roman Crescent.

The Manor Cottage and what used to be the doctor's surgery are also of historic interest. One of the town's schools, Eastbrook; was formerly known as Manor Hall Middle School; suggesting that there may have been a larger manor linked with the cottage.

===Historical residents===
*[[Dame (title)|Dame]] [[Clara Butt]], celebrated [[contralto]], was born at 27 Adur Terrace.
*[[Attila the Stockbroker]], punk poet, was born in Southwick. 
*[[David Baboulene]], humorous travel writer, lives on Church Lane.
*[[George Albert Smith (inventor)]], pioneer film-maker, lived in Roman Crescent.
*[[Benjamin Jumeaux]], surgeon and early colour film experimenter, lived at 4 Colebrook Road.
*Wing Commander [[Ken Wallis]],leading exponents of autogyros, lived in Church Lane.
*[[Roger Ferris]], British pop composer. Sound engineer on recordings by The Beatles lives on Manor Hall Road.
*[[Douglas Herbert Lott]] Opera singer. Lived at [[Bendemere]] village green. Died 1914.
*[[Ralf Rangnick]], German football player and manager

==Community==
[[File:St Michael and All Angels Church, Southwick, Adur (IoE Code 297346).jpg|thumb|right|[[St Michael and All Angels Church, Southwick|St Michael and All Angels Church]]]]
There are several [[Church (building)|church]]es in Southwick: [[St Michael and All Angels Church, Southwick|St Michael and All Angels]] in Church Lane, [[Thérèse of Lisieux|St Theresa of Lisieux]] ([[Roman Catholicism|RC]]) in Downland Avenue, Southwick [[Methodism|Methodist]] Church in Manor Hall Road, All Souls Centre in Downsway and, Southwick [[Christian]] [[House church|Community Church]] in Roman Crescent.  The town's open-air shopping centre, Southwick Square, is home to many traditional and local businesses as well as some larger chains, and was central to the old village prior to its expansion north of the Old Shoreham Road in the middle of the twentieth century.  Adjacent to 'the Square', as it is known locally, is the Southwick Community Centre, and Southwick [[Library]], which was rebuilt for 2007.
Famous tourist attractions include Orchard Close during the Christmas season in which every house in the street is decorated in lavish Christmas lights, with all money raised from the collection box going to various charities.

===Education===
Primary/Middle schools are Manor Hall First School and Manor Hall Middle School on Manor Hall Road, Holmbush First School and Herons Dale School, a community [[special school]], both in Hawkins Crescent (just on the Shoreham side of the Shoreham/Southwick border), and Glebe Middle School in Church Lane. The Manor Hall schools will combine with the nearby Fishersgate First School to form Eastbrook School, from September 2008.

The main secondary schools for this catchment area are in Shoreham-By-Sea: King's Manor Community College (comprehensive), now rebranded the Shoreham Academy and Shoreham College (public). Some children may go further afield and attend Portslade Community College, St Andrew's CE High School for Boys or Davisons School for Girls in [[Worthing]], Cardinal Newman Catholic School in Hove, or [[Steyning Grammar School]].

===Recreation===
There is a leisure centre and recreation ground in Old Barn Way, which is also home to [[Southwick F.C.|Southwick Football Club]], who will play the 2009-10 season in the [[Sussex County Football League|Sussex County League]] Division Two.  Southwick Rangers Youth Football Club, Adur Athletic Football Club and Southwick Hockey Club are also based in the town.

The Green, once common land central to the old village, consists of two separate fields divided by a short road of the same name.  The smaller southern field, also home to the town's war memorial located in the south-eastern corner, is often used for local cricket matches.  The larger northern field contains a small children's playground and is most often used for general recreation and is also the location where travelling fairgrounds and local fairs will set-up during the summer and autumn months.  There is also some parkland off Cross Road, just south of the Old Shoreham Road.  North of the Old Shoreham Road, there is Quayside, once home to the Quayside Youth Centre which burned down in May 2005, and more open land off Downsway.

Unusually for a town of its size, Southwick has a vibrant theatrical scene thanks to the Barn Theatre, an 18th century barn building converted into a theatre in 1951 and thoroughly revamped in 1998.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.wicktheatre.co.uk/barntheatre.htm Wick Theatre Company]&lt;/ref&gt;

There are also several pubs in Southwick:
*The Romans, on Manor Hall Road.
*The Cricketers, on The Green.
*The Ship Inn, on Southwick Street.(It is to be noted that there are always boxer shorts in the window.)
*The Pilot, on Station Road. (This closed in January 2010)
*The Schooner Inn, on Albion Street.
(The large Windmill Inn, on Old Shoreham Road closed in May 2010 and was demolished in September of the same year)

==Religious Life==
===Churches===
*St Michael and All Angels Church
*Southwick Methodist Church
*Southwick Christian Community Church

==References==
{{reflist}}

==External links==
*[http://www.southwickcommunitycentre.org.uk/ Southwick Community Centre]
*[http://www.southwickrangers.com Southwick Rangers Football Club]
*[http://www.crsbi.ac.uk/ed/sx/swick/ St Michael &amp; All Angels parish church]
*[http://www.southwickchurch.org.uk/ Southwick Christian Community Church Website]
*[http://www.dabnet.org/southwck.htm Catholic church]

{{Adur}}
{{West Sussex}}

[[Category:Towns in West Sussex]]
[[Category:Adur]]
[[Category:Populated coastal places in West Sussex]]

[[it:Southwick (West Sussex)]]
[[pl:Southwick (West Sussex)]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
