<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="147367" ns="0" title="Aretha Franklin"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Use mdy dates|date=July 2011}}
{{Infobox musical artist
|name=Aretha Franklin
|image=Aretha Franklin on January 20, 2009.jpg &lt;!-- only free-content images are allowed for depicting living people - ALBUM COVERS ARE NOT ALLOWED! - see [[WP:NONFREE]] --&gt;
|caption = Franklin performing at President [[Barack Obama]]'s inauguration in 2009
|background = solo_singer
|birth_name = Aretha Louise Franklin
|Born = {{birth date and age|mf=yes|1942|3|25}}&lt;br /&gt;[[Memphis, Tennessee]], U.S.
|origin = [[Detroit, Michigan]], U.S.
|occupation = Singer, songwriter, pianist
|years_active = 1956–present
|genre = [[Soul music|Soul]], [[jazz]], [[blues]], [[Rhythm and blues|R&amp;B]], [[Gospel music|gospel]], [[rock music|rock]]
|instrument = Vocals, piano
|label = [[Columbia Records|Columbia]]&lt;br&gt;[[Atlantic Records|Atlantic]]&lt;br&gt;[[Arista Records|Arista]]
|associated_acts = [[Sweet Inspirations]], [[Carolyn Franklin]], [[Erma Franklin]], [[Cissy Houston]], [[George Benson]], [[George Michael]], [[Michael McDonald (singer)|Michael McDonald]], [[Eurythmics]]
}}

'''Aretha Louise Franklin''' (born March 25, 1942) is an American singer, songwriter, and pianist. Although known for her [[Soul music|soul]] recordings and referred to as '''The Queen of Soul''', Franklin is also adept at [[jazz]], [[blues]], [[Rhythm and blues|R&amp;B]], [[gospel music]], and [[rock music|rock]]. ''[[Rolling Stone]]'' magazine ranked her atop its list of The Greatest Singers of All Time&lt;ref&gt;[http://detnews.com/article/20100408/ENT09/4080377/Grapevine--Gospel-singer-in-negotiations-to-play-Aretha-in-film Detroit News Grapevine: Gospel singer in negotiations to play Aretha Franklin in upcoming film]. ''The Detroit News''. Retrieved on July 8, 2011.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.mlive.com/entertainment/detroit/index.ssf/2010/02/queen_of_soul_aretha_franklin.html &quot;Queen of Soul Aretha Franklin says she's in control on new album&quot;], Associated Press&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.time.com/time/photoessays/10questions/0,30255,1966496,00.html Profile: Aretha Franklin]. ''Time''. Retrieved on July 8, 2011.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|title=The 100 Greatest Singers of All Time|journal=[[Rolling Stone]]|issue=1066|page=73|date=November 27, 2008|url=http://www.rollingstone.com/music/lists/6027/32782/32784|accessdate=October 6, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; as well as the
[http://www.rollingstone.com/music/lists/100-greatest-artists-of-all-time-19691231/aretha-franklin-19691231 ninth greatest artist of all time]. She has won 18 competitive Grammys and two honorary Grammys. She has 20 No.1 singles on the [[Hot R&amp;B/Hip-Hop Songs|Billboard R&amp;B Singles Chart]] and two No.1 hits on the [[Billboard Hot 100]]: &quot;[[Respect (song)|Respect]]&quot; (1967) and &quot;[[I Knew You Were Waiting (For Me)]]&quot; (1987), a duet with [[George Michael]]. Since 1961, she has scored a total of 45 Top 40 hits on the [[Billboard Hot 100]]. She also has the most million-selling singles (14) of any female artist{{Citation needed|date=April 2011}}. Between 1967 and 1982 she had 10 No.1 R&amp;B albums—more than any other female artist. In 1987, Franklin became the first female artist to be inducted into the [[Rock and Roll Hall of Fame]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.futurerocklegends.com/preyear.php?induction_year=1987 Franklin first female artist to be inducted into the Rock and Roll Hall of Fame]. Futurerocklegends.com (2007-01-03). Retrieved on July 8, 2011.&lt;/ref&gt; She was the only featured singer at the 2009 [[Inauguration of Barack Obama|presidential inauguration]] of [[Barack Obama]].

==Biography==
===Early life and career: 1942–1959===
[[File:Aretha Franklin birthplace 406 Lucy Ave Memphis TN 06.jpg|thumb|left|Aretha Franklin's birthplace at 406 Lucy Ave. in Memphis, Tennessee]] 

Aretha Louise Franklin (named for two aunts) was born in a two-room house in [[Memphis, Tennessee|Memphis]] located at 406 Lucy St.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.morethings.com/music/aretha_franklin/photo_gallery13.htm|title=Sister Ree's Scrapbook, An Aretha Franklin Photo Gallery 13|accessdate=November 6, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; She was the third of four children born to [[Barbara Siggers Franklin|Barbara (née Siggers)]] and [[C. L. Franklin|C.L. Franklin]] and the fifth of six overall in between past relationships by her parents. Franklin's family moved to [[Buffalo, New York|Buffalo]], when Franklin was two, and then by four, they had settled in [[Detroit]]. Following the move to Detroit, Franklin's parents, who had a troubled marriage, split. Due to her father's work as a [[Baptist]] minister, Franklin was primarily raised by her grandmother, Rachel. Franklin suffered a tragedy when her mother died in Buffalo when Aretha was ten. Franklin sang in church at an early age and learned how to play piano by ear.

By her late preteens, Franklin was regularly singing solo numbers in her father's [http://www.nbbcdetroit.org New Bethel Baptist Church]. C.L. (né Clarence LaVaughn) Franklin, Aretha's father, was a respected local preacher. She grew up with local and national celebrities hanging out at her father's home including gospel greats [[Albertina Walker]] and her group [[The Caravans]], [[Mahalia Jackson]] and [[Clara Ward]], three women who played a pivotal role in her vocal development as a child.

===Early success: 1960–1966===
She released her first single for Columbia in September 1960, aged 18. It reached No. 10 on ''Billboard'''s R&amp;B chart. Her first album was released in January 1961. The label had her record mainly [[jazz]]-influenced pop music, hoping for success with this format as the label had with [[Billie Holiday]]. Columbia founder [[John H. Hammond]] acknowledged in an interview years later that he felt Columbia did not really understand Franklin's background in gospel and failed to bring that aspect out in her secular recordings.&lt;ref name=pc52&gt;{{Gilliland|http://digital.library.unt.edu/ark:/67531/metadc19834/m1|Show 52 - The Soul Reformation: Phase three, soul music at the summit. [Part 8&amp;#93; : UNT Digital Library}}&lt;/ref&gt;
After scoring two more Top 10 R&amp;B hits with &quot;Operation Heartbreak&quot; and &quot;Won't Be Long&quot; in 1961, Franklin scored her first Top 40 pop hit with her rendition of &quot;[[Rock-A-Bye Your Baby With a Dixie Melody]]&quot;. Later releases failed to find similar success, although Franklin had a near-Top 50 hit with &quot;Runnin' Out of Fools&quot; (1963).

After the release of a tribute album to [[Dinah Washington]], Columbia drifted away from their early jazz dreams for Franklin and had the singer record renditions of [[girl group]]-oriented hits including &quot;[[The Shoop Shoop Song (It's In His Kiss)]]&quot;, &quot;[[Every Little Bit Hurts]]&quot; and &quot;[[Mockingbird (Inez &amp; Charlie Foxx song)|Mockingbird]]&quot; but every attempt to bring her success with the material failed. This did not, however, prevent her building a reputation as a multi-talented vocalist and musician. During a show in 1965, the master of ceremonies gave Franklin a [[tiara]] and declared her &quot;the queen of soul&quot;. The title would prove to be prophetic. By 1966, struggling with recording for Columbia, Franklin decided not to sign a new contract with the label and settled on a deal with [[Atlantic Records|Atlantic]]. After she gained success at Atlantic, Columbia began releasing Franklin material from its vaults, and continued doing so until 1969.

===Superstardom: 1967–1972===
Franklin began recording her first songs for Atlantic in early 1967. Initially sent to Muscle Shoals's legendary FAME studios where the [[Muscle Shoals Rhythm Section]] was the in-house band, Franklin cut her first song – the [[blues]] ballad &quot;[[I Never Loved a Man (The Way I Love You)]]&quot;,&lt;ref name=pc52/&gt; which finally allowed Franklin to show her gospel side. Tensions between Franklin's then-husband and then-manager Ted White and a musician led to Franklin and White hiding from public view in New York. Franklin eventually returned to the studio in New York to record the b-side, the gospel-oriented &quot;[[Do Right Woman, Do Right Man]]&quot;. &quot;I Never Loved a Man&quot; soared up both the pop and R&amp;B charts upon its release peaking at number-nine and number-one respectively. 

Her second single with Atlantic would also be her biggest, most acclaimed work. &quot;[[Respect (song)|Respect]]&quot;,&lt;ref name=pc52/&gt; originally recorded and written by R&amp;B singer [[Otis Redding]], would become a bigger hit after Franklin's gospel-fueled rendition of the song. The song also started a pattern of Franklin in later songs during this period producing a [[call and response]] vocal with Franklin usually backed up by her sisters [[Erma Franklin|Erma]] and [[Carolyn Franklin]] or [[The Sweet Inspirations]]. Franklin is credited with arranging the background vocals and ad-libbing the line, &quot;r-e-s-p-e-c-t, find out what it means to me/take care of TCB&quot;, while her sisters shouted afterwards, &quot;sock it to me&quot;. Franklin's version peaked at number one on [[Billboard Hot 100|the ''Billboard'' Hot 100]], becoming a sixties anthem. Franklin had three more top ten hits in 1967 – &quot;[[Baby I Love You (Aretha Franklin song)|Baby I Love You]]&quot;, &quot;[[(You Make Me Feel Like) A Natural Woman]]&quot; and &quot;[[Chain of Fools (song)|Chain of Fools]]&quot;.&lt;ref name=pc52/&gt; &quot;Respect&quot; later won Franklin her first two [[Grammy Award|Grammys]]. She eventually won eight consecutive Grammys under the [[Grammy Award for Best Female R&amp;B Vocal Performance|Best Female R&amp;B Vocal Performance]] category.&lt;ref name=8grammies&gt;[[Natalie Cole]] broke Franklin's &quot;Best Female R&amp;B Vocal Performance&quot; winning streak with her 1975 single &quot;This Will Be (An Everlasting Love)&quot; (which, ironically, was originally offered to Franklin).&lt;/ref&gt;

By the end of the year, Franklin not only became a superstar but she stood as one of the symbols of the [[civil rights movement]] partially due to her rendition of &quot;Respect&quot;, which had a feminist-powered theme after Franklin recorded it. Franklin's other hits during the late sixties included &quot;[[Think (Aretha Franklin song)|Think]]&quot;,&lt;ref name=pc52/&gt; her rendition of [[Dionne Warwick]]'s &quot;[[I Say a Little Prayer]]&quot;, &quot;[[Ain't No Way]]&quot; and &quot;The House That Jack Built&quot; among others. By the end of the sixties, Franklin's title as &quot;the queen of soul&quot; became permanent in the eyes of the media. After a few struggles in 1969, she returned with the ballad, &quot;[[Call Me (Aretha Franklin song)|Call Me]]&quot; in January 1970. That same year she had another hit with her gospel version of [[Ben E. King]]'s &quot;[[Don't Play That Song]]&quot;, while in 1971, Franklin was one of the first black performers to headline [[Fillmore West]]&lt;ref name=&quot;Bill Graham&quot;&gt;{{cite web|title= Aretha Franklin songs|url=http://www.wolfgangsvault.com/aretha-franklin/songs}} – from the Bill Graham archives; requires free login. &lt;!-- Editors: These are fully legal and licensed. See http://www.wolfgangsvault.com/concerts/support/about-concert-vault.html  --&gt;&lt;/ref&gt; where she later released a live album. That same year she released the acclaimed ''Young, Gifted &amp; Black'' album, which featured two top ten hits, the ballad &quot;[[Daydreamin']]&quot; and the [[funk]]-oriented &quot;[[Rock Steady (Aretha Franklin song)|Rocksteady]]&quot;. In 1972, she released her first gospel album in nearly two decades with ''[[Amazing Grace (Aretha Franklin album)|Amazing Grace]]''. The album eventually became her biggest-selling release ever, selling over two million copies and becoming the best-selling gospel album of all time.

===Decline and fallout with Atlantic: 1973–1979===
Aretha had another number-one R&amp;B hit in 1973 with the [[Carolyn Franklin]] and William &quot;Sonny&quot; Sanders-composed &quot;[[Angel (Aretha Franklin song)|Angel]]&quot;, however its parent album, ''[[Hey Now Hey (The Other Side of the Sky)]]'', failed to repeat the success of Franklin's other albums. By 1974, after four years performing in [[Afrocentric]]-styled clothing, the singer glammed up her look and styled red hair releasing ''[[Let Me In Your Life]]''. The album yielded the smash single, &quot;[[Until You Come Back to Me (That's What I'm Gonna Do)]]&quot;. {{Citation needed|date=May 2011}} While several singles would later find success on the R&amp;B charts, Franklin was losing favor with pop audiences as soul music was starting to be overtaken by the emerging [[disco]] genre. Atlantic Records had also by this point given priority attention to [[Roberta Flack]], leading to relations between Franklin and the company becoming estranged as a result. Franklin turned down a number of tracks giving to her by Marvin Yancy and Chuck Jackson (though eventually they would contribute to her 1975 album, ''[[You (Aretha Franklin album)|You]]''). Several of the songs including &quot;[[This Will Be (An Everlasting Love)]]&quot; was later recorded by [[Natalie Cole]]. After the arrivals of Cole and [[Chaka Khan]], Franklin's star ebbed. {{Citation needed|date=May 2011}}

She briefly returned to the top 40 in 1976 with the [[Curtis Mayfield]] production, ''[[Sparkle (Aretha Franklin album)|Sparkle]]'', which spawned the number-one R&amp;B hit, &quot;[[Giving Him Something He Can Feel]]&quot;. Despite this, Franklin struggled to find success with subsequent releases. After the release of 1979's ''[[La Diva (Aretha Franklin album)|La Diva]]'', an attempt for Franklin to find a disco audience that flopped, selling less than 50,000 copies, Franklin's contract with Atlantic expired. Neither Atlantic nor Aretha had any interest in renewing it. While she was performing in Las Vegas on June 10, 1979, Franklin's father, C.L., was shot during an attempted robbery at his LaSalle Street home in Detroit. The incident left C.L. in a coma for the next five years. Aretha moved back to the Detroit area in late 1982 from Los Angeles (where she had lived since 1976) to help care for her father.

===Comeback: 1980–1989===
In 1980, Franklin, among other prominent [[rhythm and blues]] and [[soul music|soul]] artists including [[Ray Charles]] and [[James Brown]], appeared in the film ''[[The Blues Brothers (film)|The Blues Brothers]].'' Franklin appeared as the wife of musician Matt &quot;Guitar&quot; Murphy, who engages in a brief war of words with [[Dan Aykroyd]] and [[John Belushi]] before going into &quot;Think&quot;. Following that performance, [[Clive Davis]] signed Franklin to his [[Arista Records]] imprint. The singles &quot;United Together&quot; and the [[George Benson]]-featured &quot;Love All the Hurt Away&quot; returned Franklin to the R&amp;B top ten while 1982's ''[[Jump to It]]'', featuring a [[contemporary R&amp;B]] production style by [[Luther Vandross]], became a comeback of sorts for Franklin on the pop music chart. The album stayed at No. 1 on the R&amp;B Albums chart for seven weeks and crossed to No. 23 on the [[Billboard 200|''Billboard'' 200 album chart]], selling over 600,000 units and becoming Aretha's first [[RIAA|gold-certified]] album since the ''[[Sparkle (Aretha Franklin album)|Sparkle soundtrack]]''. The title track became Franklin's first number-one R&amp;B hit in five years while also hitting No. 24 on the Hot 100. After the relative failure of her 1983 follow-up, ''Get It Right'', also produced by Vandross, Franklin took some personal time off. Following the July 1984 death of her father, she entered the United Sound Studios in Detroit to record a new album for Arista in October of that year. Inspired by the recent success of fellow artist [[Tina Turner]] and Arista's emerging star [[Whitney Houston]], Arista paired Franklin with [[Narada Michael Walden]]. {{Citation needed|date=May 2011}}

The album released in July 1985, ''[[Who's Zoomin' Who?]]'', featured R&amp;B, pop, [[dance-pop|dance]], [[synthpop]] and [[rock and roll|rock]] elements and became Franklin's first [[RIAA|platinum]]-certified success. The album launched several major hits including the title track and the [[Motown]]-inspired &quot;[[Freeway of Love]]&quot;. The rock-influenced [[Annie Lennox]] duet, &quot;[[Sisters Are Doin' It for Themselves]]&quot; also became a hit for Franklin on the pop charts though it failed to climb higher than No.66 on the R&amp;B chart due to its more [[pop rock]]-leaning sound. Music Videos for each of the singles became prominent fixtures on MTV, [[BET]] and [[VH-1]] among other video channels. In 1986, Franklin released her [[Aretha (1986 album)|self-titled follow-up]] to ''Who's Zoomin' Who''. The album sold almost a million copies, and featured the number-one hit, &quot;[[I Knew You Were Waiting for Me]]&quot;, a duet with [[George Michael]]. In April 1987, the song became Franklin's first single since &quot;Respect&quot; to hit No. 1 on the Hot 100. {{Citation needed|date=May 2011}} 

Other hits from the album included a cover of &quot;[[Jumpin' Jack Flash]]&quot; and another Motown-inspired hit, &quot;[[Jimmy Lee (song)|Jimmy Lee]]&quot;. In 1987 she returned to her gospel roots with the album, ''[[One Lord, One Faith, One Baptism]]'', which failed to repeat the success of ''Amazing Grace'' despite a powerful rendition of &quot;[[Oh Happy Day]]&quot;, featuring [[Mavis Staples]], but did reach the Top 10 of Billboard's gospel chart. In 1986, she sang the theme song (&quot;Together&quot;) for the [[American Broadcasting Company|ABC]] television network. {{Citation needed|date=May 2011}}

===Later work: 1989–2003===
In 1989, Franklin returned with her first pop album in three years with ''[[Through the Storm (Aretha Franklin album)|Through the Storm]]'' but despite scoring a Top 20 hit with the title track featuring [[Elton John]] and the presence of Whitney Houston in their duet single, &quot;It Isn't, It Wasn't, It Ain't Ever Gonna Be&quot;, the album tanked, as did a follow-up, 1991's [[new jack swing]] effort, ''What You See Is What You Sweat''. After singing [[Donny Hathaway]]'s &quot;[[Someday We'll All Be Free]]&quot; on the ''[[Malcolm X (film)|Malcolm X soundtrack]]'' in 1992 and singing at then-President [[Bill Clinton]]'s inauguration ceremony in 1993, Franklin returned to favor with pop audiences later in 1993 with the release of the dance single, &quot;Deeper Love&quot;, which was featured on the soundtrack of ''[[Sister Act 2: Back in the Habit]]''. The following year, Franklin issued her Arista hits album and with [[Babyface (musician)|Babyface]] released two hit singles, &quot;Honey&quot; and the top 40 pop ballad &quot;Willing to Forgive&quot;. In 1995, her song &quot;It Hurts Like Hell&quot; appeared on the soundtrack for the movie ''[[Waiting to Exhale]]''. Four years passed until Franklin released another album. 1998's ''[[A Rose Is Still a Rose]]'' reintroduced Franklin to a new R&amp;B audience and featured elements of [[neo soul]] and [[hip hop soul]] with production from [[Lauryn Hill]], [[Jermaine Dupri]] and [[Sean Combs|Sean &quot;Puffy&quot; Combs]]. The title track, written and produced by Hill, became Franklin's biggest hit in years reaching number 26 on the Hot 100 and reaching the R&amp;B top five. 

She later reprised her role as Matt &quot;Guitar&quot; Murphy's wife in the Blues Brothers remake, ''[[Blues Brothers 2000]]'' singing &quot;Respect&quot;. She struggled to record a successful follow-up, however, and it would be five more years before a new album emerged. Franklin issued her next album, ''[[So Damn Happy (Aretha Franklin album)|So Damn Happy]]'', in 2003. {{Citation needed|date=May 2011}}

===Current work: 2004–present===
[[File:arethafranklin.jpg|thumb|240px|left|Franklin performing on April 21, 2007 at the Nokia Theater in Dallas, Texas]]
In 2003, after 23 years with Arista, Franklin parted with the company and decided to go on the independent route, forming Aretha's Records two years later. Franklin released a duets compilation album, ''[[Jewels in the Crown: All-Star Duets with the Queen]]'', in 2007. The album featured the [[Fantasia Barrino|Fantasia]] duet, &quot;[[Put You Up on Game]]&quot;, which despite becoming a modest hit on Urban AC radio, stalled at No. 41 on the R&amp;B charts. A year later, Franklin issued her first holiday album, ''[[This Christmas, Aretha]]''. After initially being released as a [[Borders Group|Borders]] exclusive, it was later released by the DMI label.

In 2008, Franklin was honored as [[MusiCares]] &quot;Person of the Year&quot;, two days prior to the [[50th Annual Grammy Awards]], where she was awarded her 18th career Grammy. Franklin was personally asked by then newly-elected President [[Barack Obama]] to perform at his inauguration singing &quot;My Country 'tis of Thee&quot;. The memorable hat she wore at the ceremony was donated to the [[Smithsonian Institution]].&lt;ref name=&quot;usnews.com&quot;&gt;[http://www.usnews.com/money/blogs/luxe-life/2009/02/02/aretha-franklins-hat-requested-by-smithsonian.html] {{dead link|date=July 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;{{dead link|date=December 2010}} In 2010, Franklin received an honorary music degree from Yale University.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|url=http://www.yaledailynews.com/news/2010/may/24/univ-confers-3243-degrees-at-309th-commencement|first=Lauren|last=Rosenthal|publisher=Yale Daily News|date=May 24, 2010|title=Univ. confers 3,243 degrees at 309th Commencement|accessdate=November 30, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In 2010 and through early 2011, Franklin had told the media she had selected actress [[Halle Berry]] to play her in the featured role of the legendary singer in a biopic loosely based on Franklin's memoirs, ''Aretha: From These Roots''. In January 2011, Berry turned down the role. Franklin said she's now setting her sights on singers [[Fantasia Barrino|Fantasia]] and [[Jennifer Hudson]] on getting the lucrative role.

Marking her 50th anniversary in [[show business]], Franklin released her thirty-eighth studio album, ''[[A Woman Falling Out Of Love]]'', on May 3, 2011, through [[WalMart]]. It is the first release off Franklin's own record label, Aretha's Records, a label she formed back in the 1990s. However, Aretha's new disc peaked at a disappointing #54 on ''Billboard'''s main album chart, dropping off after only two weeks. She co-produced some of the new tracks. The first single from the album is the ballad &quot;How Long I've Been Waiting&quot; which failed to chart. [[Ronald Isley]] will be featured in the album doing the [[Barbra Streisand]] standard, &quot;The Way We Were&quot;, as he and Franklin covered the [[Carole King]] classic, &quot;[[You've Got a Friend]]&quot;, first issued on Isley's ''Mr. I'' album. 

Following her exit from the stage in November, 2010 and her surgery the following month, Franklin has recently returned to the stage, rescheduling dates she was forced to cancel due to recent health problems.

In September 2011, [[Tony Bennett]] released a duet with Aretha entitled &quot;[[How Do You Keep The Music Playing]]&quot; off of his new album, [[Duets II (Tony Bennett album)]].

==Personal life==
In 1956, shortly after her 14th birthday, Franklin gave birth to her eldest child, a son she named Clarence (for her father).  In January of 1957 she gave birth to another son, Edward.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|author=Nick Salvatore|title=Singing in a Strange Land: C.L. Franklin, the Black Church, and the Transformation of America|publisher=Little Brown|year=2005|isbn=0-316-16037-7|oclc=56104283|pages=203–204, 224|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=bRDAQSK9DlkC&amp;pg=PA203}}&lt;/ref&gt; She never identified by name the father of either child. {{Citation needed|date=July 2011}} Her grandmother, Rachel, raised the boys while Aretha pursued her singing career. Rachel lived in a guest house behind C.L. Franklin's LaSalle Street home. The Franklin family moved from their home on Boston Street in Detroit's North End section to LaSalle Street during the late 1950s.

Against her father's wishes Aretha began dating a family acquaintance named Ted White. In 1961 they were quickly married in Ohio by a judge. White became her personal manager as well as co-writer. Shortly afterward, she purchased a house on Sorrento Avenue in northwest Detroit, where she resided for the next decade. Their son Teddy (Ted White Jr.) was born in 1964. She and Ted divorced in 1969. Teddy is the musical director and guitarist of her touring band. From 1969 until 1976, she had a seven-year relationship with her road manager Ken Cunningham. (Although she and Ted White did not divorce until late 1969, Aretha conceived her fourth child in June of that year.) In the early 1970s the couple moved from Detroit to New York City, at which time Aretha's grandmother moved into her Sorrento Avenue home. Their son Kecalf (from the initials of his parents' names: '''K'''enneth '''E''' '''C'''unningham '''A'''retha '''L'''ouise '''F'''ranklin and pronounced &quot;kelf&quot;)&lt;ref&gt;''Aretha Franklin The Queen Of Soul'' by Mark Bego&lt;/ref&gt; was born on March 28, 1970 at Detroit's [[Henry Ford Hospital]].

On April 11, 1978, Aretha Franklin married actor [[Glynn Turman]] at her father's New Bethel Baptist Church in Detroit. Franklin's father performed the marriage ceremony. The couple returned to their home in [[Encino, California]]. In late 1982, Franklin moved back to Detroit, and in 1985 she purchased a home in West Bloomfield, where she still resides. Turman and Franklin divorced in early 1984. The couple did not have children. They remained friends, and she sang the theme song for his show, ''[[A Different World (TV series)|A Different World]]'', in the late 1980s.

Franklin's sisters [[Erma Franklin|Erma]] and [[Carolyn Franklin|Carolyn]], are both deceased, as is her brother Cecil. As of 2011, her half-brother Vaughn (born 1934) is alive as is her half-sister, Carl Ellan Kelley (née Jennings; born 1940). Kelley is  C.L. Franklin's daughter by Mildred Jennings, a then 13-year-old congregant of New Salem Baptist Church of [[Memphis, Tennessee]], where C.L. was pastor in the late 1930s and early 1940s.&lt;ref&gt; Salvatore, Nick, ''Singing in a Strange Land: C. L. Franklin, the Black Church, and the Transformation of America'', Little Brown, 2005, Hardcover ISBN 0-316-16037-7, pp. 61–62&lt;/ref&gt; Aretha's sons, Ted White Jr. (&quot;Teddy&quot;) and Kecalf Cunningham, are active in the music business. Teddy has been a guitarist in Aretha's back up band since the late 1980s, while Kecalf works as a [[Christian hip-hop]] rapper and producer. {{Citation needed|date=May 2011}}

Aretha Franklin is a registered [[Democratic Party (United States)|Democrat]].&lt;ref&gt;On an ABC promo aired on July 27, 2010 announcing Franklin and Rice's apperaring together in concert there was a segment in which Franklin was being interviewed and she said herself, &quot;I am a Democrat&quot;.&lt;/ref&gt;

In September 2010, her son Edward was attacked and severely beaten by three people while at a gas station on Joy Road in northwest Detroit.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://news.yahoo.com/s/ap/20100921/ap_en_mu/us_aretha_franklin_son_beaten|title=Spokeswoman: Aretha Franklin's Son Severely Beaten}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Franklin's long friendship with [[Cissy Houston]] during Houston's time with [[The Sweet Inspirations]] led to Franklin becoming [[Whitney Houston]]'s godmother. Cissy Houston sang the operatic soprano whoop in the background of Franklin's &quot;[[Ain't No Way]]&quot;. {{Citation needed|date=May 2011}}

===2010 surgery and rumors of cancer===
In 2010, Franklin suffered a pain in her side which she said, &quot;was so hard it almost brought me to my knees.&quot; After continuing a concert tour, the pain recurred, and she subsequently underwent surgery for an undisclosed ailment. At this time, rumors surfaced that she was suffering terminal [[pancreatic cancer]]. In discussing the events in 2011, she has said that this was not the case and that her doctor told her, &quot;the surgery that you just had is going to add 15 to 20 more years to your life.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;cancerrumor&quot;&gt;{{cite web | publisher=Access Hollywood | date=January 13, 2011 | url=http://www.accesshollywood.com/aretha-franklin-sets-the-record-straight-on-her-health-i-dont-know-where-pancreatic-cancer-came-from_article_42228 | title=Aretha Franklin Sets The Record Straight On Her Health}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Awards and achievements==
[[Image:Aretha Franklin honored with the Presidential Medal of Freedom.jpg|thumb|290px|Aretha Franklin wipes a tear after being honored with the [[Presidential Medal of Freedom]] on November 9, 2005, at the [[White House]]. Seated with her are fellow recipients [[Robert Conquest]], left, and [[Alan Greenspan]]]]
*On June 28, 1968 she became the second African-American woman to appear on the cover of ''[[Time (Magazine)|TIME]]'' magazine.&lt;ref name=&quot;TIME magazine - 28Jun1968 - cover - Aretha Franklin&quot;&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.time.com/time/covers/0,16641,19680628,00.html|title=TIME Magazine Cover:  Aretha Franklin|date=June 28, 1968 	|publisher=[[Time Magazine|TIME]]|accessdate=30 September 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*In 1985, then-Gov. [[James Blanchard (politician)|James Blanchard]] of Michigan declared her voice “a natural resource” during a ceremony that marked her 25 years in show business.
*Aretha Franklin is one of three musicians, along with [[Madonna (entertainer)|Madonna]] &amp; [[Marvin Gaye]], to have singles peak at each of the top 10 positions on the US [[Billboard Hot 100]].
*On January 20, 1987, she became the first woman to be inducted into the [[Rock and Roll Hall of Fame]].
*On March 29, 1987, Franklin sang &quot;America the Beautiful&quot; at ''[[WrestleMania III]]''.
*In 1987, she was awarded an honorary Doctor of [[Musicology]] degree from the [[University of Detroit]].{{Citation needed|date=February 2008}}
*In September 1999, she was awarded The [[National Medal of Arts]] by President Clinton.
*In 2004, ''[[Rolling Stone]]'' ranked her No. 9 on their list of the [http://www.rollingstone.com/music/lists/100-greatest-artists-of-all-time-19691231 100 Greatest Artists of All Time].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=The Immortals: The First Fifty|work=Rolling Stone Issue 946|url=http://www.rollingstone.com/news/story/5939214/the_immortals_the_first_fifty}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*In 2005, she was awarded The [[Presidential Medal of Freedom]] by President George W. Bush.
*In 2005, she became the second woman (Madonna being the first, a founding member) to be inducted into the [[UK Music Hall of Fame]].
* In 2005, Franklin was inducted into the Michigan Rock and Roll Legends Hall of Fame.
*On February 6, 2006, she performed, along with [[Aaron Neville]], &quot;[[The Star-Spangled Banner]]&quot; at [[Super Bowl XL]].
*On May 13, 2006, she was presented with an [[Honorary degree|honorary]] [[Doctor of Music]] [[Academic degree|degree]] by the [[Berklee College of Music]].
*On April 1, 2007 Aretha sang &quot;America the Beautiful&quot; at ''[[WrestleMania 23]].''
*On May 14, 2007, she was presented with an honorary Doctor of Music degree from the University of Pennsylvania.
*In 2007, Aretha Franklin's recording of &quot;Respect&quot; was voted a Legendary Michigan Song.
*Is an honorary member of [[Delta Sigma Theta]] sorority
*On February 8, 2008, Franklin was honored as [[MusiCares]] &quot;Person of the Year&quot;.
*On February 14, 2008, Franklin was given the Vanguard award at the NAACP Image awards.
*On May 4, 2008, Franklin was given the Key to the City of Memphis at the 2008 &quot;Memphis in May International Music Festival&quot; by Mayor Dr. Willie Herenton during her performance onstage.
*On September 13, 2008, Franklin was ranked No .19 on the ''Billboard Hot 100 All-Time Top Artists'' list by ''Billboard''.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.billboard.com/bbcom/specials/hot100/charts/top100-artists-20.shtml The Billboard Hot 100 All-Time Top Artists]. Billboard.com. Retrieved on July 8, 2011.&lt;/ref&gt;
*November 2008, Franklin was named by ''Rolling Stone'' as the No. 1 all-time best singer of the rock era, according to the magazine's survey of 179 musicians, producers, Rolling Stone editors, and other music industry insiders.&lt;ref name=&quot;rollingstones&quot;&gt;[http://music.yahoo.com/read/news/61852568 Aretha Franklin greatest singer in rock era: poll]. Music.yahoo.com (2008-11-11). Retrieved on July 8, 2011.&lt;/ref&gt;
*On January 20, 2009, Franklin performed &quot;[[My Country, 'Tis of Thee]]&quot; during the [[Barack Obama 2009 presidential inauguration|inauguration ceremony]] of [[Barack Obama]]. The distinctive hat she wore during that performance is displayed at the Smithsonian.&lt;ref name=&quot;usnews.com&quot;/&gt;
*On May 23, 2010, Franklin received an Honorary Doctorate in Music from [[Yale University]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://newsone.com/nation/news-one-staff/aretha-franklin-receives-honorary-doctorate-from-yale Franklin receives honorary doctorate from Yale]. Newsone.com (2010-05-24). Retrieved on July 8, 2011.&lt;/ref&gt;
On June 1, 2010, Aretha Franklin's recording of &quot;Chain Of Fools&quot; was voted a Legendary Michigan Song.&lt;ref&gt;www.michiganrockandrolllegends.com&lt;/ref&gt;
*On February 13, 2011, the Grammy Awards paid tribute to Franklin with a medley of her classics by fellow singers [[Christina Aguilera]], [[Florence Welch]], [[Jennifer Hudson]], [[Martina McBride]] and [[Yolanda Adams]]&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.grammy.com/news/stars-to-join-for-aretha-franklin-tribute Grammay Awards tribute to Aretha Franklin]&lt;/ref&gt;
*On October 16, 2011, Franklin sang &quot;Precious Lord (Take My Hand)&quot; for Dr. Martin Luther King Jr.'s memorial dedication ceremony in Washington, D.C. Again, she met with President Obama. 
 
===Grammy Awards===
Franklin has won eighteen Grammy Awards in total during her career (she first charted in 1961) and holds the record for most Best Female R&amp;B Vocal Performance awards with eleven to her name (including eight consecutive awards from 1968 to 1975 – the first eight awarded in that category).

{|class=&quot;wikitable&quot;
|-
!colspan=&quot;5&quot;|Aretha Franklin's 18 Grammy Award Wins
|-
!#
!Year
!Category
!Genre
!Title
|-
| 1 || style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;| 1968 || [[Grammy Award for Best Rhythm &amp; Blues Recording|Best Rhythm &amp; Blues Recording]] || R&amp;B ||Respect
|-
| 2 || style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;| 1968 || |[[Grammy Award for Best Female R&amp;B Vocal Performance|Best Female R&amp;B Vocal Performance]] || R&amp;B || Respect
|-
| 3 || style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;| 1969 || Best Female R&amp;B Vocal Performance || R&amp;B || Chain Of Fools
|-
| 4 || style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;| 1970 || Best Female R&amp;B Vocal Performance || R&amp;B || Share Your Love With Me
|-
| 5 || style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;| 1971 || Best Female R&amp;B Vocal Performance || R&amp;B || Don't Play That Song For Me
|-
| 6 || style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;| 1972 || Best Female R&amp;B Vocal Performance || R&amp;B || Bridge Over Troubled Water
|-
| 7 || style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;| 1973 || Best Female R&amp;B Vocal Performance || R&amp;B || Young, Gifted and Black (album)
|-
| 8 || style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;| 1973 || [[Grammy Award for Best Soul Gospel Performance|Best Soul Gospel Performance]] || Gospel || Amazing Grace (album)
|-
| 9 || style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;| 1974 || Best Female R&amp;B Vocal Performance || R&amp;B || Master Of Eyes
|-
|10 || style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;| 1975 || Best Female R&amp;B Vocal Performance || R&amp;B || Ain't Nothing Like The Real Thing
|-
|11 || style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;| 1982 || Best Female R&amp;B Vocal Performance || R&amp;B || Hold On...I'm Comin' (album track)
|-
|12 || style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;| 1986 || Best Female R&amp;B Vocal Performance || R&amp;B || Freeway Of Love
|-
|13 || style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;| 1988 || Best Female R&amp;B Vocal Performance || R&amp;B || Aretha (album)
|-
|14 || style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;| 1988 || [[Grammy Award for Best R&amp;B Performance by a Duo or Group with Vocals|Best R&amp;B Performance – Duo Or Group with Vocals]] || R&amp;B || I Knew You Were Waiting (For Me) (with [[George Michael]])
|-
|15 || style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;| 1989 || [[Grammy Award for Best Soul Gospel Performance, Female|Best Soul Gospel Performance – Female]] || Gospel || One Lord, One Faith, One Baptism (album)
|-
|*|| style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;| 1991 || [[Grammy Legend Award|Living Legend Award]] || Special
|
|-
|*|| style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;| 1994 || [[Grammy Lifetime Achievement Award|Lifetime Achievement Award]] || Special
|
|-
|16 || style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;| 2004 || [[Grammy Award for Best Traditional R&amp;B Vocal Performance|Best Traditional R&amp;B Vocal Performance]] || R&amp;B || Wonderful
|-
|17|| style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;| 2006 || Best Traditional R&amp;B Vocal Performance || R&amp;B || A House Is Not A Home
|-
|18|| style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;| 2008 || Best Gospel-Soul Vocal Performance by a Duo or Group || Gospel
|Never Gonna Break My Faith (with [[Mary J. Blige]])
|}
&lt;nowiki&gt;*&lt;/nowiki&gt;According to NARAS Rules: 'Special' Grammy Awards (such as Lifetime Achievement) are not counted in a performer's tally.

==Discography==
{{See|Aretha Franklin discography}}

===Top 10 US Hot 100 singles===
{| class=&quot;wikitable&quot;
|-
!  style=&quot;vertical-align:top; text-align:center; width:30px;&quot;| Year
!  style=&quot;vertical-align:top; text-align:center; width:300px;&quot;| Title
!  style=&quot;vertical-align:top; text-align:center; width:50px;&quot;| Peak
|-
| 1967
| &quot;[[I Never Loved a Man (The Way I Love You)]]&quot;
| style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;| 9
|-
| 1967
| &quot;[[Respect (song)|Respect]]&quot;
| style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;| 1
|-
| 1967
| &quot;[[Baby I Love You (Aretha Franklin song)|Baby I Love You]]&quot;
| style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;| 4
|-
| 1967
| &quot;[[(You Make Me Feel Like) A Natural Woman]]&quot;
| style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;| 8
|-
| 1967
| &quot;[[Chain of Fools (song)|Chain of Fools]]&quot;
| style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;| 2
|-
| 1968
| &quot;[[(Sweet Sweet Baby) Since You've Been Gone]]&quot;
| style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;| 5
|-
| 1968
| &quot;[[Think (Aretha Franklin song)|Think]]&quot;
| style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;| 7
|-
| 1968
| &quot;The House That Jack Built&quot;
| style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;| 6
|-
| 1968
| &quot;[[I Say a Little Prayer]]&quot;
| style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;| 10
|-
| 1971
| &quot;[[Bridge over Troubled Water (song)|Bridge Over Troubled Water]]&quot; / &quot;Brand New Me&quot;
| style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;| 6
|-
| 1971
| &quot;[[Spanish Harlem (song)|Spanish Harlem]]&quot;
| style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;| 2
|-
| 1971
| &quot;[[Rock Steady (Aretha Franklin song)|Rock Steady]]&quot;
| style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;| 9
|-
| 1972
| &quot;[[Day Dreaming (Aretha Franklin song)|Day Dreaming]]&quot;
| style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;| 5
|-
| 1973
| &quot;[[Until You Come Back to Me (That's What I'm Gonna Do)]]&quot;
| style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;| 3
|-
| 1985
| &quot;[[Freeway of Love]]&quot;
| style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;| 3
|-
| 1985
| &quot;[[Who's Zoomin' Who]]&quot;
| style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;| 7
|-
| 1987
| &quot;[[I Knew You Were Waiting (For Me)]]&quot; (with George Michael)
| style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;| 1
|}Source:&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Aretha Franklin-Biography|work=Rolling Stone|accessdate=March 21, 2010|url=http://www.rollingstone.com/artists/arethafranklin/biography}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===All no. 1 hits in US  R&amp;B  100 singles===
{| class=&quot;wikitable&quot;
|-
!  style=&quot;vertical-align:top; text-align:center; width:30px;&quot;| Year
!  style=&quot;vertical-align:top; text-align:center; width:300px;&quot;| Title
!  style=&quot;vertical-align:top; text-align:center; width:50px;&quot;| Peak
|- 
| 1967
| &quot;[[I Never Loved a Man (The Way I Love You)]]&quot;
| style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;| 1
|-
| 1967
| &quot;[[Respect (song)|Respect]]&quot;
| style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;| 1
|-
| 1967
| &quot;[[Baby I Love You (Aretha Franklin song)|Baby I Love You]]&quot;
| style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;| 1
|-
| 1967
| &quot;[[Chain of Fools (song)|Chain of Fools]]&quot;
| style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;| 1
|-
| 1968
| &quot;[[(Sweet Sweet Baby) Since You've Been Gone]]&quot;
| style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;| 1
|-
| 1968
| &quot;[[Think (Aretha Franklin song)|Think]]&quot;
| style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;| 1
|-
| 1969
| &quot;[[Share Your Love with Me]]&quot;
| style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;| 1
|-
| 1970
| &quot;[[Call Me (Aretha Franklin song)|Call Me]]&quot;
| style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;| 1
|-
| 1970
| &quot;[[Don't Play That Song (You Lied)]]&quot;
| style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;| 1
|-
| 1971
| &quot;[[Bridge over Troubled Water (song)|Bridge Over Troubled Water]]&quot; / &quot;Brand New Me&quot;
| style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;| 1
|-
| 1971
| &quot;[[Spanish Harlem (song)|Spanish Harlem]]&quot;
| style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;| 1
|-
| 1972
| &quot;[[Day Dreaming (Aretha Franklin song)|Day Dreaming]]&quot;
| style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;| 1
|-
| 1973
| &quot;[[Angel (Aretha Franklin song)|Angel]]&quot;
| style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;| 1
|-
| 1973
| &quot;[[Until You Come Back to Me (That's What I'm Gonna Do)]]&quot;
| style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;| 1
|-
| 1974
| &quot;[[I'm in Love (Bobby Womack song)|I'm in Love]]&quot;
| style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;| 1
|-
| 1976
| &quot;[[Something He Can Feel]]&quot;
| style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;| 1
|-
| 1977
| &quot;[[Break It to Me Gently (Aretha Franklin song)|Break It to Me Gently]]&quot;
| style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;| 1
|-
| 1982
| &quot;[[Jump to It (song)|Jump to It]]&quot;
| style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;| 1
|-
| 1983
| &quot;[[Get It Right (song)|Get It Right]]&quot;
| style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;| 1
|-
| 1985
| &quot;[[Freeway of Love]]&quot;
| style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;| 1
|}Source:&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Aretha Franklin-Biography|work=Rolling Stone|accessdate=March 21, 2010|url=http://www.rollingstone.com/artists/arethafranklin/biography}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Filmography==
===Movies===
*''[[Cooley High]]'' (1975)
*''[[The Blues Brothers (film)|The Blues Brothers]]'' (1980)
*''Motown 40: The Music Is Forever'' (1998) (ABC-TV documentary)
*''[[Blues Brothers 2000]]'' (1998)
*''DIVAS LIVE'' (1998)
*''Immaculate Funk'' (2000) (documentary)
*''Rhythm, Love and Soul'' (2002)
*''Tom Dowd &amp; the Language of Music'' (2003) (documentary)
*''Singing in the Shadow: The Children of Rock Royalty'' (2003) (documentary)
*''From The Heart / The Four Tops 50th Anniversary and Celebration'' (2004)
*''Atlantic Records: The House that Ahmet Built'' (2007) (documentary)

===Television===
*''[[The Mike Douglas Show]]
*  In 1972, she had a role in the TV show [[Room 222]]
*''[[Solid Gold (TV series)|Solid Gold]]''  (numerous appearances with the last in 1982 performing &quot;Jump To It&quot;)
*''Kelly &amp; Company'' (Marilyn Turner and John Kelly, Detroit)
*''Dayna'' (Dayna Eubanks, fomer Detroit newscaster)
*''Rolonda Show'' ([[Rolonda Watts]])
*''[[The Oprah Winfrey Show]]'' (numerous appearances including Oprah's 40th birthday, with [[Patti LaBelle]] and [[Gladys Knight]])
*''[[Live with Regis and Kelly]]'' (numerous appearances)
*''[[The View (U.S. TV series)|The View]]''

==References==
{{Reflist|3}}

==External links==
{{commons category}}
{{Wikipedia-Books|Aretha Franklin}}
{{Portal box|Biography|African American}}
* [http://www.legacyrecordings.com/artists/aretha-franklin Aretha Franklin] at [[Legacy Recordings]]
*{{C-SPAN|arethafranklin}}
*{{IMDb name|0291349|Aretha Franklin}}
*[http://www.npr.org/artists/15662553/aretha-franklin Aretha Franklin] at [[NPR Music]]
*{{NYTtopic|people/f/aretha_franklin}}
*{{Guardiantopic|music/aretha-frankl}}
*{{Worldcat id|lccn-n84-28907}}
*{{answers.com|aretha-franklin}}
*{{Discogs artist}}

{{Aretha Franklin}}
{{Kennedy Center Honorees 1990s}}

&lt;!-- Metadata: see [[Wikipedia:Persondata]] --&gt;
{{Persondata
|NAME              = Franklin, Aretha Louise
|ALTERNATIVE NAMES =
|SHORT DESCRIPTION = American singer
|DATE OF BIRTH     = March 25, 1942
|PLACE OF BIRTH    = [[Memphis, Tennessee]], U.S.
|DATE OF DEATH     =
|PLACE OF DEATH    =
}}
{{DEFAULTSORT:Franklin, Aretha}}
[[Category:1942 births]]
[[Category:African American pianists]]
[[Category:African American female singer-songwriters]]
[[Category:American child singers]]
[[Category:American gospel singers]]
[[Category:American rhythm and blues singer-songwriters]]
[[Category:American soul singers]]
[[Category:Arista Records artists]]
[[Category:Atlantic Records artists]]
[[Category:Baptists from the United States]]
[[Category:Columbia Records artists]]
[[Category:Feminist musicians]]
[[Category:Grammy Award winners]]
[[Category:Grammy Lifetime Achievement Award winners]]
[[Category:Kennedy Center honorees]]
[[Category:Living people]]
[[Category:Musicians from Tennessee]]
[[Category:Musicians from Detroit, Michigan]]
[[Category:Presidential Medal of Freedom recipients]]
[[Category:Rhythm and blues pianists]]
[[Category:Rock and Roll Hall of Fame inductees]]
[[Category:Songwriters from Michigan]]
[[Category:United States National Medal of Arts recipients]]
[[Category:MusiCares Person of the Year]]
[[Category:Grammy Legend Award]]

[[ar:أريثا فرانكلين]]
[[an:Aretha Franklin]]
[[ast:Aretha Franklin]]
[[be:Арэта Франклін]]
[[bg:Арета Франклин]]
[[ca:Aretha Franklin]]
[[cs:Aretha Franklinová]]
[[da:Aretha Franklin]]
[[de:Aretha Franklin]]
[[el:Αρίθα Φράνκλιν]]
[[es:Aretha Franklin]]
[[eo:Aretha Franklin]]
[[eu:Aretha Franklin]]
[[fa:آرتا فرانکلین]]
[[fr:Aretha Franklin]]
[[ga:Aretha Franklin]]
[[ko:어리사 프랭클린]]
[[hr:Aretha Franklin]]
[[io:Aretha Franklin]]
[[id:Aretha Franklin]]
[[is:Aretha Franklin]]
[[it:Aretha Franklin]]
[[he:אריתה פרנקלין]]
[[ka:არეთა ფრანკლინი]]
[[sw:Aretha Franklin]]
[[la:Aretha Franklin]]
[[lv:Areta Franklina]]
[[lt:Aretha Franklin]]
[[hu:Aretha Franklin]]
[[ms:Aretha Franklin]]
[[nl:Aretha Franklin]]
[[new:आरेथा फ्र्यान्क्लिन]]
[[ja:アレサ・フランクリン]]
[[no:Aretha Franklin]]
[[nn:Aretha Franklin]]
[[pl:Aretha Franklin]]
[[pt:Aretha Franklin]]
[[ru:Франклин, Арета]]
[[se:Aretha Franklin]]
[[sc:Aretha Franklin]]
[[sq:Aretha Franklin]]
[[simple:Aretha Franklin]]
[[sk:Aretha Franklinová]]
[[sr:Арета Френклин]]
[[sh:Aretha Franklin]]
[[fi:Aretha Franklin]]
[[sv:Aretha Franklin]]
[[th:อารีธา แฟรงคลิน]]
[[tr:Aretha Franklin]]
[[uk:Арета Франклін]]
[[vi:Aretha Franklin]]
[[war:Aretha Franklin]]
[[yo:Aretha Franklin]]
[[zh:艾瑞莎·弗蘭克林]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
