<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="147944" ns="0" title="Rodney Mullen"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Infobox sportsperson
| image       = Rodney Mullen-2.jpg
| birth_name  = Rodney Mullen
| birth_date  = {{Birth date and age|1966|8|17}}
| Death_date  =
| birth_place = [[Gainesville, Florida]], [[United States|U.S.]]
| website     = rodneymullen.net
| sport       = [[Skateboarding]]
| country     = {{USA}}
}}
'''John Rodney &quot;''[[Duke|Duc]]''&quot; Mullen''' (August 17, 1966) is a professional [[Freestyle skateboarding|freestyle]] and [[Street skateboarding|street]] [[skateboarder]].&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;

'''He is widely acknowledged as one of the most innovative and influential street skaters in the history of skateboarding'''.&lt;ref&gt;Weyland, J (2002) ''The Answer is Never: A Skateboarder's History of the World'' Arrow, London. p276. ISBN 0-09-943186-6&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;br /&gt;''[[Duke|Le Duc]]'' Mullen is credited with inventing the flatground ollie (originally named the &quot;ollie pop prop&quot;), the [[kickflip]] (originally called the &quot;magic flip&quot;) in 1983, the heelflip, the [[Impossible (skateboarding trick)|impossible]] and a long list of other original tricks.&lt;ref name=&quot;rodneymullen.net&quot;&gt;http://www.rodneymullen.net/bio.html&lt;/ref&gt; &lt;br /&gt; He is credited in numerous skateboarding videos, and has authored an autobiography entitled ''The Mutt: How to Skateboard and not Kill Yourself''.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
| title = Rodney Mullen Bio
| publisher = Rodney Mullen Fan Page
| url = http://www.rodneymullen.net/bio.html
| accessdate = 2009-08-16}} {{Dead link|date=November 2010|bot=H3llBot}}
&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;http://www.kidzworld.com/article/4077-rodney-mullen-biography&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
In a 2009 video Mullen sums up his passion for skateboarding as follows:

&lt;blockquote&gt;I fell in love with skateboarding because it was individual. There were no teams, there were no captains... it was completely opposite of what I saw in so many sports: It was creative.&lt;ref name=&quot;youtube.com&quot;&gt;{{cite web|title =Rodney Mullen Interview, Slamtrick 2003| url = http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=ekzjzFFE_pY&amp;feature=related|accessdate = 2009-08-16}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

==Early career: 1977 - 1990==
Rodney Mullen began skateboarding at the age of ten after he promised his worried father he would stop the first time he became seriously injured. Rodney began practicing in full pads, and hung out with his sister's surfer friends who skateboarded on the week days.&lt;ref name=&quot;ReferenceA&quot;&gt;Rodney Mullen - From the Ground Up. ON Video Magazine. Winter, 2002&lt;/ref&gt; In 1978, having owned a skateboard for less than a year, Rodney took fifth place in Boy's Freestyle at the U.S. Open Championships at Kona Skatepark in Jacksonville. Bruce Walker saw his performance and sponsored Mullen through Walker Skateboards in 1978, 1979, and 1980.  Rodney's biggest influence in skateboarding at that time was Walker pro skater Jim McCall.  Rodney was coached in his early years by Bruce Walker (who also coached a young Kelly Slater, now considered to be the greatest surfer of all time).  In later years, Mullen was coached by Barry Zaritzky, aka SIO Barry.
	 
When his family moved to a farm in a remote part of Florida, Rodney began perfecting his flatground techniques in the family garage. Mullen cites the isolation and lack of terrain naturally influenced him toward [[freestyle skateboarding]]. Rodney cites 1979 - 1980 as his &quot;most creative time&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;ReferenceA&quot;/&gt; Mullen put together a string of 30 straight competitive amateur victories in the late 70s, mostly in his home state, [[Florida]], culminating in a win at the [[Oceanside, California|Oceanside]] Nationals in June, 1979.
			
[[Image:Rodney mullen air.jpg|thumb|right|alt=Rodney Mullen in air|Rodney Mullen, 1988]]

In 1980, 14-year-old Rodney Mullen entered the Oasis Pro competition, defeating world champion [[Steve Rocco]]. Mullen soon turned professional as a member of the [[Bones Brigade]] sponsored by [[Powell Peralta]]. Rodney competed voraciously throughout the 80s—often frustrating both competitors and judges with his consistency and progressive ability&lt;ref name=&quot;Mullen 2004&quot;&gt;[[#Mullen04|Mullen 2004]]&lt;/ref&gt;. By 1990 Rodney had won 34 out of 35 freestyle competitions that he entered, having been beaten only once by fellow Bones Brigade member [[Per Welinder]]. Rodney thus established the most successful competitive run in the history of the sport.

Despite Alan Gelfand's justifiable fame for inventing the ollie air (Gelfand's maneuver being primarily a transition-oriented trick) Mullen is responsible for the invention and development of the street ollie. The ability to pop the board off of the ground and land back on the board while moving has quite likely been the most significant development in modern skateboarding. This invention alone would rank Mullen the most important skateboarder of all time.

Throughout the 1980s, he invented the majority of skating's ollie and flip tricks, including the flatground ollie, the Kickflip, the Heelflip.{{Citation needed|date=September 2011}} These tricks are now considered an essential part of modern vertical and street skateboarding.
			
In early 1989, Mullen left the Bones Brigade to form [[World Industries]] as a principal investor with longtime friend and former rival Steve Rocco&lt;ref name=&quot;Mullen 2004&quot;/&gt;.

As the popularity of freestyle skateboarding declined, Mullen was often urged to move his style toward [[Street skateboarding|street skating]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Mullen 2004&quot;&gt;[[#Mullen04|Mullen 2004]]&lt;/ref&gt; This is hinted at in the World Industries video ''Rubbish Heap'', where Mullen's sequence ends with team member [[Jeremy Klein]] breaking Rodney's freestyle skateboard, and handing him a note from Steve Rocco, symbolizing the end of freestyle.&lt;ref&gt;''Rubbish Heap''. World Industries. 1989.&lt;/ref&gt;

==1990s - Present==
In 1991 Mullen joined the high-profile skateboarding team [[Plan B Skateboards|Plan B]]. Mike Ternasky, the owner of Plan B, influenced Rodney to transition from freestyle to street skating, and showcased the results in the 1992 Plan B video ''Questionable''. Mullen's segment begins with traditional freestyle tricks done on flat ground, but quickly accelerates across public terrain to shift into standard street skating. In relation to obstacles, he sequences tricks, mixes flip tricks with [[Grind (sport)|grinds]] and board slides. In the video, Mullen introduced two newly invented tricks, the Kickflip Underflip and the Casper slide.

Mullen's ''Questionable'' performance may have marked the beginning of a new era in street skateboarding. His reluctant departure from freestyle to become a street skater was a symbol that legitimized the technical direction street skating had taken over the previous few years. Mullen specialized at this progression in subsequent Plan B videos; noteworthy is 1993's ''Virtual Reality'' where Mullen showcases the newly-mastered [[Darkslide]].

Mullen's participation in Plan B dissolved after Mike Ternasky died unexpectedly in 1994. In 1997, Mullen started another company, A-Team, with the intent of forming a super team with the defection of [[Plan B Skateboards|Plan B]] from the [[World Industries]] empire.&lt;ref name=&quot;ReferenceA&quot;/&gt; Rodney talked to friend and fellow pro [[Daewon Song]] to plan the video ''Rodney vs. Daewon'', which featured each skater competing in segments from trick to trick.

Since 1999, Rodney Mullen has appeared in most of the console games of the [[Tony Hawk's|Tony Hawk's Pro Skater]] series, Tony Hawk Underground, Tony Hawk Underground 2 ,Tony Hawk American Wasteland, Tony Hawks Proving Ground, and the last game he was in was [[Tony Hawk: Ride]] &lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
| title = Tony Hawk's Proving Ground Featured Skaters
| publisher = [[Activision]]
| url = http://www.thpgonline.com/gamefeatures-skaters.php
| accessdate = 2007-10-15
}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The A-Team folded in 2000 and Mullen went from company founder to company rider under former Maple rider [[Marc Johnson (skateboarder)|Marc Johnson]], who started [[Enjoi|Enjoi Skateboards]]. Mullen left Enjoi to head [[Almost Skateboards]] with [[Daewon Song]], the company which he still helms and skates for.  Mullen's role at Almost includes research and development on new designs and technologies, including [[Tensor Trucks|Tensor truck]] in 2000&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
| title = Turning On a Dick
| publisher = Transworld Business
| date = 2000-07-11
| accessdate = 2007-09-29}}&lt;/ref&gt;
and experimental and composite deck constructions for [[Dwindle Distribution|Dwindle]] brands.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.dwindle-experimental.com/]&lt;/ref&gt;

In 2002 the [[World Industries]] companies, under the holding name Kubic Marketing, were bought out by [[Globe International]] for $46 million. Kubic's management remained intact and Mullen began working for Globe International under the [[Dwindle Distribution]] brand.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
| title = Globe Buys Kubic
| publisher = Transworld Business
| date = 2002-07-05
| url = http://skateboarding.transworld.net/2002/07/05/globe-buys-kubic/
| accessdate = 2007-10-08}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In 2003, Mullen wrote and released his autobiography, entitled ''The Mutt: How to skateboard and not kill yourself''. In late 2003 he was voted as the all-time greatest action sports athlete on the [[Extreme Sports Channel|Extreme Sports Channel's]] ''Legends of the Extreme'' countdown.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
| date =2009-02-05
| title =Hometown: Rodney Mullen
| publisher = Transworld Skateboarding
| author = Sean Mortimer
| url = http://skateboarding.transworld.net/2009/02/05/hometown-rodney-mullen/
| accessdate = 2009-09-28
}}
&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
| title =Rodney Mullen - &quot;United By Fate&quot; segment
| url = http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=ArtLC4USpsw
| accessdate = 2009-09-21
}}&lt;/ref&gt;

From 2007 to 2009, Mullen worked to erase his riding stance, allowing him to move from regular stance to goofy. In an interview with Tony Hawk, Mullen explained that he had developed problems in his right hip joint and that his transition between stances came out of an effort to favor his leg. He goes on to describe that scar tissue had built up in his joint as a result of habitually hyper-extending his leg while skating. Mullen stated that through extensive and consistent stretching he was able to tear away the scar tissue. &lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
| publisher = SkateOrDie
| title = SkateOrDie Interview
| url = http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=bZQKEi_9TdE
| accessdate = 2011-01-08}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In December 2010 Mullen stated in an interview that he is preparing to film a part for the upcoming Almost video.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
| title = Globe Warehouse Interview
| url = http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=CzvqpS5kGGk&amp;feature=related}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Filmography==
{{Quote box |quoted=true |bgcolor=#FFFFF0 |salign=center |width=30em
|quote=I can't wait to wake up in the morning... A lot of times I can't sleep because I can't wait to try something new. How many people ever really experience that feeling?
''Rodney Mullen, 2003''&lt;ref name=&quot;youtube.com&quot;&gt;{{cite web
| title =Rodney Mullen Interview, Slamtrick 2003
| url = http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=ekzjzFFE_pY&amp;feature=related
| accessdate = 2009-08-16
}}&lt;/ref&gt;
}}
* Powell Peralta: ''Skateboarding in the '80's'' (1982)
* Powell Peralta: ''The Bones Brigade Video Show'' (1984)
* Powell Peralta: ''Future Primitive'' (1985)
* Powell Peralta: ''Public Domain'' (1988)
* [[Gleaming the Cube]] (&quot;Skate double&quot;, 1989)
* World Industries: ''Rubbish Heap'' (1989)
* Plan B: ''Questionable'' (1992)
* Plan B: ''Virtual Reality'' (1993)
* Plan B: ''Second Hand Smoke'' (1995)
* ''Rodney Mullen vs. Daewon Song'' (1997)
* ''Rodney Mullen Vs. Daewon Song Round 2'' (1999)
* Globe: ''Opinion''
* ''[[Almost: Round Three]]'' (2004)
* Transworld: ''Show Me the Way'' (Darkslide)
* ''Tony Hawk's Secret Skatepark Tour'' (2005)
*''[[John from Cincinnati]]'' (Skate double, Episode 10, 2007)
* Globe: ''United by Fate'' (2008)

==References==
{{reflist}}

==Further reading==
*Brooke, M (1999). ''Concrete Wave: The History Of Skateboarding''. ISBN 1-894020-54-5.
*{{cite book |last=Mullen |first=Rodney |year=2004 |title=The Mutt: How to Skateboard and not Kill Yourself |publisher=Regan Books |ref=Mullen04}}

{{Persondata &lt;!-- Metadata: see [[Wikipedia:Persondata]]. --&gt;
| NAME              = Mullen, Rodney
| ALTERNATIVE NAMES =
| SHORT DESCRIPTION =
| DATE OF BIRTH     = 1966-08-17
| PLACE OF BIRTH    = [[Gainesville, Florida]], [[United States|U.S.]]
| DATE OF DEATH     =
| PLACE OF DEATH    =
}}
{{DEFAULTSORT:Mullen, Rodney}}
[[Category:American skateboarders]]
[[Category:Freestyle skateboarders]]
[[Category:1966 births]]
[[Category:Living people]]
[[Category:University of Florida alumni]]
[[Category:People from Gainesville, Florida]]
[[bg:Родни Мълън]]
[[ca:Rodney Mullen]]
[[da:Rodney Mullen]]
[[de:Rodney Mullen]]
[[et:Rodney Mullen]]
[[es:Rodney Mullen]]
[[fr:Rodney Mullen]]
[[it:Rodney Mullen]]
[[nl:Rodney Mullen]]
[[ja:ロドニー・ミューレン]]
[[no:Rodney Mullen]]
[[pl:Rodney Mullen]]
[[pt:Rodney Mullen]]
[[ro:Rodney Mullen]]
[[ru:Маллен, Родни]]
[[simple:Rodney Mullen]]
[[sk:Rodney Mullen]]
[[sl:Rodney Mullen]]
[[fi:Rodney Mullen]]
[[sv:Rodney Mullen]]
[[tr:Rodney Mullen]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
