<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="148131" ns="0" title="Economic development"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Economics sidebar}}

'''Economic development''' generally refers to the sustained, concerted actions of [[policymakers]] and [[community|communities]] that promote the [[standard of living]] and [[Economic expansion|economic health]] of a specific area. Such actions can involve multiple areas including development of [[human capital]], [[critical infrastructure]], regional [[competitiveness]], [[environmental sustainability]], [[social inclusion]], [[health]], [[safety]], [[literacy]], and other initiatives. Economic development differs from [[economic growth]]. Whereas economic development is a [[public policy|policy intervention]] endeavor with aims of economic and social well-being of people, economic growth is a phenomenon of [[market]] [[productivity]] and rise in [[GDP]]. Consequently, as economist [[Amartya Sen]] points out: “economic growth is one aspect of the process of economic development.” &lt;ref name= &quot;Development: Which Way Now?&quot;&gt;Sen, A. (1983). Development: Which Way Now? Economic Journal, Vol. 93 Issue 372. Pp.745-762.&lt;/ref&gt;

==Term==

The scope of economic development includes the process and policies by which a nation improves the economic, political, and social well-being of its people.&lt;ref&gt;O'Sullivan, A. and Sheffrin, S. M. (2003). Economics: Principles in action. Pearson Prentice Hall, Upper Saddle River, New Jersey. 471pgs.&lt;/ref&gt;

The ''University of Iowa's Center for International Finance and Development'' states that:

&lt;blockquote&gt;
'Economic development' is a term that economists, politicians, and others have used frequently in the 20th century. The concept, however, has been in existence in the West for centuries. [[Modernization]], Westernization, and especially Industrialization are other terms people have used when discussing economic development. Although no one is sure when the concept originated, most people agree that development is closely bound up with the evolution of capitalism and the demise of feudalism.&lt;ref&gt;R. Conteras, &quot;How the Concept of Development Got Started&quot; University of Iowa Center for International Finance and Development E-Book [http://www.uiowa.edu/ifdebook/ebook2/contents/part1-I.shtml]&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

Mansell and Wehn also state that economic development has been understood since the [[World War II]] to involve economic growth, namely the increases in [[per capita income]], and (if currently absent) the attainment of a standard of living equivalent to that of [[industrialized countries]].&lt;ref&gt;http://cbdd.wsu.edu/kewlcontent/cdoutput/TR501/page59.htm&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Mansell, R &amp; and Wehn, U. 1998. Knowledge Societies: Information Technology for Sustainable Development. New York: Oxford University Press.&lt;/ref&gt; Economic development can also be considered as a static theory that documents the state of an economy at a certain time. According to Schumpeter (2003), the changes in this equilibrium state to document in economic theory can only be caused by intervening factors coming from the outside.&lt;ref&gt;Schumpeter, J. &amp; Backhaus, U., 2003. The Theory of Economic Development. In Joseph Alois Schumpeter. pp. 61-116. Available at: http://dx.doi.org/10.1007/0-306-48082-4_3 [Accessed October 19, 2009].&lt;/ref&gt;

==Social Science Research==

The study of economic development by [[social scientists]] encompasses theories of industrial/economic [[modernization]] causes, the historical phases or waves of economic development, and the organizational aspects of enterprise development in [[Modernity|modern societies]]. Economic development embraces [[sociology|sociological research]] on a variety of topics including: [[Industrial organization|business organization]], [[enterprise development]], evolution of [[market]]s and [[management]], and cross-national comparisons of [[industrial organization]] patterns. One example inquiry would be: &quot;Why are levels of direct foreign investment and labour productivity significantly higher in some countries than in others?&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Lewis F. Abbott, ''Theories Of Industrial Modernization &amp; Enterprise Development: A Review'', ISR/Google Books, revised 2nd edition 2003, pages 1&amp;ndash;2. ISBN 978-0-906321-26-3.[http://books.google.com/books?q=theories+of+industrial+modernization+and+enterprise+development&amp;btnG=Search+Books]&lt;/ref&gt;

In economics, the study of economic development was borne out of an extension to traditional economics that focused entirely on [[Gross national product|national product]], or the aggregate output of goods and services. Economic development was concerned in the expansion of people’s [[entitlement]]s and their corresponding capabilities, [[morbidity]], [[nourishment]], [[literacy]], [[education]], and other [[Socioeconomics|socio-economic]] indicators. Borne out of the backdrop of [[Keynesian]], advocating government intervention, and [[neoclassical economics]], stressing reduced intervention, with rise of high-growth countries ([[Singapore]], [[South Korea]], [[Hong Kong]]) and planned governments ([[Argentina]], [[Chile]], [[Sudan]], [[Uganda]]), economic development, more generally development economics, emerged amidst these mid-20th century theoretical interpretations of how economies prosper.&lt;ref name= &quot;Development: Which Way Now?&quot;/&gt; Also, economist [[Albert O. Hirschman]], a major contributor to [[development economics]], asserted that economic development grew to concentrate on the [[Developing country|poor regions of the world]], primarily in [[Africa]], [[Asia]] and [[Latin America]] yet on the outpouring of fundamental ideas and models.&lt;ref&gt;Hirschman, A. O. (1981). The Rise and Decline of Development Economics. Essays in Trespassing: Economics to Politics to Beyond. Pp. 1-24&lt;/ref&gt;

===Growth and Development===
Dependency theorists argue that poor countries have sometimes experienced [[economic growth]] with little or no economic development initiatives; for instance, in cases where they have functioned mainly as resource-providers to wealthy industrialized countries. There is an opposing argument, however, that growth causes development because some of the increase in income gets spent on human development such as education and health. 
 
According to Ranis et al. (2000), economic growth and [[Human development (humanity)|human development]] is a two-way relationship. Moreover, the first chain consists of economic growth benefiting human development with [[GNP]]. Specifically, GNP increases human development by expenditure from families, government and organizations such as [[NGO]]s. With the rise in economic growth, families and individuals will likely increase expenditures with heightened incomes, which in turn leads to growth in human development. Further, with the increased consumption, health and education grow, also contributing to economic growth.&lt;ref&gt;Ranis, G., Stewart, F. &amp; Ramirez, A., 2000. Economic Growth and Human Development. World Development, 28(2), 197-219.&lt;/ref&gt;

In addition to increasing private incomes, economic growth also generate additional [[resource]]s that can be used to improve [[social service]]s (such as [[healthcare]], safe [[drinking water]], etc.). By generating additional resources for social services, unequal [[income distribution]] will be mitigated as such social services are distributed equally across each [[community]], thereby benefiting each individual. Thus, increasing living standards for the public.&lt;ref&gt;Anand, S. &amp; Sen, A., 2000. Human Development and Economic Sustainability. World Development, 28(12), 2029-2049.&lt;/ref&gt;
Concisely, the relationship between human development and economic development can be explained in three ways. First, increase in average income leads to improvement in [[health]] and [[nutrition]] (known as Capability Expansion through Economic Growth). Second, it is believed that social outcomes can only be improved by reducing income [[poverty]] (known as Capability Expansion through Poverty Reduction). Lastly, social outcomes can also be improved with essential services such as [[education]], [[healthcare]], and clean [[drinking water]] (known as Capability Expansion through Social Services).&lt;ref&gt;Anand, S. &amp; Ravallion, M., 1993. Human Development in Poor Countries: On the Role of Private Incomes and Public Services. The Journal of Economic Perspectives, 7(1), 133-150.&lt;/ref&gt;

John Joseph Puthenkalam's research aims at the process of economic growth theories that lead to economic development. After analyzing the existing capitalistic growth-development theoretical apparatus, he introduces the new model which integrates the variables of freedom, democracy and human rights into the existing models and argue that any future economic growth-development of any nation depends on this emerging model as we witness the third wave of unfolding demand for democracy in the Middle East. He develops the knowledge sector in growth theories with two new concepts of 'mirco knowledge' and 'macro knowledge'. Micro knowledge is what an individual learns from school or from various existing knowledge and macro knowledge is the core philosophical thinking of a nation that all individuals inherently receive. How to combine both these knowledge would determine further growth that leads to economic development of developing nations. For further reading, please refer to &quot;Integrating Freedom, Democracy and Human Rights into Theories of Economic Growth&quot; &amp; other publications(1998,2000&amp;2010).

'''''''''''''==Goals==
In the United States, [[Project Socrates]]  outlined [[competitiveness]] as the driving factor for successful economic development in [[government]] and [[industry]]. By addressing technology directly, to meet customer needs,  competitiveness was fostered in the surrounding environment and resulted in greater economic performance and sustained growth.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | title = DoD Unveils Competitive Tool: Project Socrates Offers Valuable Analysis | journal = Washington Technology | date = 1988-05-05 | first = Esther | last = Smith| id = }}&lt;/ref&gt;

Economic development typically involves improvements in a variety of indicators such as [[literacy rate]]s, [[life expectancy]], and [[poverty rate]]s. [[GDP]] does not take into account other aspects such as [[leisure]] time, [[natural environment|environment]]al quality, [[Political freedom|freedom]], or [[social justice]]; alternative measures of economic well-being have been proposed ([[Gross domestic product#Limitations of GDP to judge the health of an economy|more]]). Essentially, a country's economic development is related to its human development, which encompasses, among other things, health and education. These factors are, however, closely related to economic growth so that development and growth often go together.&lt;ref&gt;Hanushek, Eric A., and Ludger Woessmann. 2008. &quot;The role of cognitive skills in economic development.&quot; ''Journal of Economic Literature'', 46, no. 3 (September): 607-668.&lt;/ref&gt;'''''''''''''

==Regional policy==

[[File:Anatomy of a Cluster.jpg|thumb|Diagram of key components of a strong regional cluster, U.S. Economic Development Administration [http://www.eda.gov/PDF/EDA_FY_2010_Annual_Report.pdf]]]
In its broadest sense, policies of economic development encompass three major areas:
* Governments undertaking to meet broad economic objectives such as [[price]] stability, high [[employment]], and [[Sustainable development|sustainable growth]]. Such efforts include [[monetary policy|monetary]] and [[fiscal policies]], regulation of [[financial institutions]], [[trade]], and [[tax]] policies.
* Programs that provide infrastructure and services such as [[highway]]s, [[park]]s, [[affordable housing]], [[crime prevention]], and [[Primary education|K&amp;ndash;12 education]].
* [[Job creation]] and retention through specific efforts in business [[finance]], [[marketing]], [[Community development|neighborhood development]], [[workforce development]], [[small business]] development, [[business]] retention and expansion, [[technology transfer]], and [[real estate]] development. This third category is a primary focus of economic development professionals.

One growing understanding in economic development is the promotion of [[business cluster|regional clusters]] and a thriving [[metropolitan economy]]. In today’s global landscape, location is vitally important and becomes a key in [[competitive advantage]]. The cluster of similar industries, specialties, skilled laborforce, and technologies help lower transaction costs and foster a growing environment of [[commerce]], [[entrepreneurship]], [[exports]], and other market productive activities. Additionally, local services such as restaurants, stores, and trades experience growth as well, helping to develop a vibrant region for the wider community.&lt;ref&gt;Porter, M. E. (1998). Clusters and the New Economics of Competition. Harvard Business Review. Pp. 77-90.&lt;/ref&gt; Even the U.S.’s [[Economic Development Administration]] recognizes the importance of clusters with their continued Regional Innovation Clusters initiative which aims to “create jobs and grow the economy” through the geographic concentrations of industries and firms in their need for talent, technology, and infrastructure.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.eda.gov/AboutEDA/RIC/&lt;/ref&gt;

International trade and exchange rates are a key issue in economic development. Currencies are often either under-valued or [[Kemal Kurdas|over-valued]], resulting in trade surpluses or deficits.

===Organization===
Economic development has evolved into a professional industry of highly specialized practitioners. The practitioners have two key roles: one is to provide leadership in [[Public policy|policy-making]], and the other is to administer policy, programs, and projects. Economic development practitioners generally work in public offices on the state, regional, or municipal level, or in public-private partnerships organizations that may be partially funded by local, regional, state, or federal tax money. These economic development organizations (EDO's) function as individual entities and in some cases as departments of local governments. Their role is to seek out new economic opportunities and retain their existing business wealth.

There are numerous other organizations whose primary function is not economic development work in partnership with economic developers. They include the news media, foundations, utilities, schools, health care providers, faith-based organizations, and colleges, universities, and other education or research institutions.

===International Economic Development Council===

With more than 20,000 professional economic developers employed world wide in this highly specialized industry, the [[International Economic Development Council]] (IEDC) headquartered in Washington, D.C. is a non-profit organization dedicated to helping economic developers do their job more effectively and raising the profile of the profession. With over 4,500 members across the US and internationally, serving exclusively the economic development community, IEDC membership represents the entire range of the profession ranging from regional, state, local, rural, urban, and international economic development organizations, as well as chambers of commerce, technology development agencies, utility companies, educational institutions, consultants and redevelopment authorities. Many individual states also have associations comprising economic development professionals, who work closely with IEDC.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.iedconline.org&lt;/ref&gt;

==Community Competition==

One unintended consequence of economic development is the intense competition between communities, states, and nations for new economic development projects in today's [[globalization|globalized world]]. With the struggle to attract and retain business, competition is further intensified by the use of many variations of economic incentives to the potential business such as: tax incentives, investment capital, donated land, utility rate discounts, and many others. IEDC places significant attention on the various activities undertaken by economic development organizations to help them compete and sustain vibrant communities. 

Additionally, the use of community profiling tools and [[database]] templates to measure community assets versus other communities is also an important aspect of economic development. Job creation, economic output, and increase in taxable basis are the most common measurement tools. When considering measurement, too much emphasis has been placed on economic developers for &quot;not creating jobs.&quot; However, the reality is that economic developers do not typically create jobs, but facilitate the process for existing businesses and [[Startup company|start-ups]] to do so. Therefore, the economic developer must make sure that there are sufficient economic development programs in place to assist the businesses achieve their goals. Those types of programs are usually policy-created and can be local, regional, statewide and national in nature.

==See also==
{{Wikibooks|Economic Development}}
{{commons category|Economic development}}

* [[Business cluster]]
* [[Constitutional economics]]
* [[Development economics]]
* [[Economic growth]]
* [[FORGE Program]]
* [[Infrastructure]]
* [[Metropolitan economy]]
* [[Private Sector Development]]
* [[Public capital]]

==References==
{{Reflist|2}}

{{GDP country lists}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Economic Development}}
[[Category:Economics]]
[[Category:Development]]

[[bg:Икономическо развитие]]
[[es:Desarrollo económico]]
[[fa:توسعه اقتصادی]]
[[hi:आर्थिक विकास]]
[[it:Sviluppo economico]]
[[mk:Економски развој]]
[[ja:経済発展]]
[[pt:Desenvolvimento econômico]]
[[ru:Экономическое развитие]]
[[vi:Phát triển kinh tế]]
[[zh:經濟發展]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
