<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="14814259" ns="0" title="Discovery One"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Infobox Fictional Spacecraft
| name           = ''Discovery One''
| image          = Discovery1b.JPG
| caption        = ''Discovery'' launching an [[Extra-vehicular activity|EVA]] pod
| first          = [[2001: A Space Odyssey (film)|2001: A Space Odyssey]]
| last           = [[2010 (film)|2010]]
| status         = Destroyed
| affiliation    = {{USA}}
| launched       =
| decommissioned =
| class          =
| registry       = XD-1
| maxspeed       =
| fighters       =
| auxcraft       = [[EVA Pod]]s
| armaments      =
| defense        =
| propulsion     = Cavradyne Plasma Propulsion Engines
| power          = Nuclear Reactor
| mass           = 5,440 tonnes
| length         = 140.1 m
| width          = 16.7 m
| height         = 17 m
| primeref       =
}}

'''United States Spacecraft ''Discovery One''''' is a [[fiction]]al [[spacecraft]] appearing in [[The Space Odyssey series]], including the movie ''[[2001: A Space Odyssey (film)|2001: A Space Odyssey]]''. ''Discovery One'' is a large, nuclear-powered interplanetary spaceship.

==History==
[[File:Discovery One.jpg|right|thumb|Early pre-production illustration of ''Discovery'']]

The [[spacecraft]] is founded on solid, if as-yet unrealized, science. One concession was made for the purpose of reducing confusion, and that was to eliminate the huge cooling &quot;wings&quot; which would be needed to radiate the heat produced by the [[Spacecraft propulsion|propulsion system]]. [[Stanley Kubrick]] felt that the audience might interpret the wings as meaning that the spacecraft was intended to fly through an [[Celestial body atmosphere|atmosphere]].

''Discovery'' was named after [[Robert Falcon Scott|Captain Robert Scott]]'s [[RRS Discovery|RRS ''Discovery'']], launched 1901; Arthur C. Clarke used to visit the ship when she was moored in London. It shares its name with a real spacecraft, the [[Space Shuttle]] [[Space Shuttle Discovery|''Discovery'' (OV-103)]].

== Background ==

In ''2001: A Space Odyssey'', the ''Discovery'' is described as 460 feet (140 m) long (the 2010 movie mentions 250 ft.) and powered by &quot;Cavradyne&quot; [[Gas core reactor rocket|gaseous core nuclear reactor engines]]. 275 feet (84 m) of tankage and structure separate the spherical part of the ship where the crew quarters, the computer, flight controls, small auxiliary craft, and instrumentation were located. In the [[Artificial gravity#Rotational Gravity|centrifuge]], a crew would have enjoyed Moon-like [[gravity]] conditions created by spinning; it was there that they spent most of their time and where the hibernating astronauts slept in their [[Hibernation#Human Hibernation|hibernacula]]. Actual [[piloting]], navigational checks, and the like took place in the zero-gravity environment [[command module]]. Other sections of the sphere include the pod bay, where three one-man repair and inspection craft were housed, and the [[HAL 9000]] [[computer]] with its level-upon-level of memory storage and related elements. Because of its lack of [[aerodynamic]] design and its large size, the ship was assembled and launched from Earth's orbit. As described in the novel, ''Discovery One'' was originally intended to survey Jupiter only but the mission was switched to Saturn to investigate the transmission of the Tycho monolith. As a result the mission becomes 'one way', following the survey of Saturn the crew are to remain in hibernation for an unknown period until a sister ship ''Discovery Two'' is built that will be able to travel to Saturn and return the crew.

=== Cavradyne Engines ===

According to the book, the ship's propulsion controls would be designed with the assistance of [[General Electric]]'s Valley Forge Space Technology Center and the UK Atomic Energy Authority.  These controls were located in the command module. A [[Honeywell]] nuclear reactor [[control panel (engineering)|control panel]] displayed information on such parameters as [[turbine]], [[Gas compressor|compressor]], heat exchanger, secondary circulatory, and radiator [[liquid helium]] storage, generator and recuperator performance, and pressures and temperatures at various stations. Precise readings could be obtained instantaneously on the control screen, if desired, as well as past performance and predicted future performance.

The fictional Cavradyne engines were based on research into gaseous core [[nuclear reactors]] and high-temperature [[ionized gases]]. The theory was presumed to have shown that gaseous [[uranium]]-235 could be made critical in a [[Dense plasma focus|cavity reactor]] only several feet or meters in diameter if the uranium [[atom]]ic density were kept high, and if temperatures were maintained at a minimum of 20,000 °F (11,400 K). At first, progress was slow because of such early unsolved problems as how to reduce [[vortex]] turbulence in order to achieve high [[Separation ratio]]s, and how to achieve adequate wall cooling in the face of the thermal [[radiation]] from the high-temperature plasma. In the Cavradyne system, the temperature of the reactor was not directly limited by the capabilities of solid materials, since the central cavity was surrounded by a thick [[graphite]] wall that moderates the [[neutrons]], reflecting most of them back into the cavity. Wall cooling would be ensured by circulating the [[hydrogen]] [[propellant]] prior to its being heated. Fissionable fuel energy was said to be transferred to the [[propellant]] by [[radiation]] through a specially designed rigid—and coolable—container.

===Centrifuge===
The ship's [[centrifuge]] was a spinning band of deck, mounted inside the crew compartment. The [[centrifugal force]] created by its spin simulated the effects of gravity. It was the primary living and work area, featuring consoles, panels, screens, and devices. There was an automated [[kitchen]] developed with the assistance of [[General Mills]]; a ship-to-Earth communications center; a complete medical section where the [[astronauts]] undergo regular automated checkups (results were displayed and recorded, and [[diagnosis]] of deficiencies given directly on a readout screen, and medicament or other treatment prescribed) an [[observatory]], created with the help of astronomers at the [[Royal Greenwich Observatory]]; and a geophysical exploration module worked out with [[France|French]] engineers from the Paris-based [[Schlumberger Limited]]. The latter permitted a wide variety of surface and subsurface experimentation to take place on an alien body, such as an [[asteroid]] or a [[natural satellite|moon]]. Since subsurface structure could be extremely important in the spaceship's investigatory program in the [[Jovian system]], a [[drill]] was incorporated into a remotely-controlled surface [[Lander (spacecraft)|lander]]. Controls on the console included a depth selector, drilling rate selector, equipment calibration, recording and error analysis controls, and various screen and gauge indications of subsurface characteristics.

=== Communications ===

The ''Discovery'' is described as a very large ship that could be handled by only two [[astronauts]] ([[David Bowman (Space Odyssey)|David Bowman]]  and [[Frank Poole]]), along with the HAL 9000. In the book [[IBM]] predicted that [[computer development]] would have advanced to such an extent that the mission could be undertaken with all the [[astronauts]] placed in [[hibernation]]. It was said to be desired, however, that regular communications be maintained throughout the voyage between the [[pilot (spaceflight)|pilot]] and copilot and [[mission control]] back on Earth. During communication, account was taken of the elapsed time for [[Electromagnetic radiation|electromagnetic]] waves crossing space between the spaceship and the [[Earth]]. Naturally, this time would depend on the relative positions of the bodies in the [[Solar System]] at any given moment.

==The Fate of the ''Discovery''==

Following the malfunction of [[HAL 9000]], Bowman deactivates the malfunctioning computer and thus effectively isolates himself onboard ''Discovery''. When the spacecraft arrives at  [[Jupiter]], it encounters TMA-1's considerably larger cousin, 'Big Brother' or 'TMA-2' at the [[Lagrange point#L1|L1]] point between Jupiter and [[Io (moon)|Io]]. Bowman decides to leave ''Discovery'' and examine the Monolith only to be taken inside it. ''Discovery'' is left abandoned and drifts into a decaying orbit about Io.

In the novel [[2010: Odyssey Two]], set nine years after the events of [[2001: A Space Odyssey]], a joint Soviet-US mission (including [[Heywood Floyd]]) travels to [[Jupiter]] aboard the spacecraft ''[[Leonov (fictional spacecraft)|Alexei Leonov]]''  to investigate the mysteries surrounding the 2001 mission, believing ''Discovery'' harbors many of the answers. ''Leonov'' docks with ''Discovery'', reactivates the onboard systems and brings it out of orbit around Io. Hal's creator, Dr. Chandra is sent aboard to reactivate the [[HAL 9000]] computer and ascertain any information he can regarding the previous mission.

Later on, an apparition of Dave Bowman appears before Floyd, warning him that ''Leonov'' must leave Jupiter within fifteen days. Floyd asks what will happen at that time and Bowman replies, 'Something wonderful.' Floyd has difficulty convincing the rest of the crew, at first, but a dark spot on Jupiter begins to form and starts growing. HAL's telescope observations reveal that the “Great Black Spot” is in fact a vast population of monoliths, increasing at a geometric rate. (The film accelerates the pace, both shortening Bowman's deadline to two days and making the spot grow faster.)

Initially it was planned to inject ''Discovery'' on an Earth-bound trajectory (though it would not arrive back for some years), however when faced with Bowman's warning, ''Leonov'' crew devises a plan to use ''Discovery'' as a '[[booster rocket]]', enabling them to return to [[Earth]] ahead of schedule, but leaving ''Discovery'' in a wide orbit of Jupiter. The crew worries that Hal will have the same neuroses on discovering that he will be abandoned yet again, and Chandra must convince HAL that the human crew must leave.

Detaching itself from ''Discovery'', ''Leonov'' makes a hasty exit from the Jupiter system, just in time to witness the swarm of Monoliths engulf Jupiter. Through a mechanism the novel only partially explains, these monoliths increase Jupiter's density until the planet achieves [[nuclear fusion]], becoming a small star.

As ''Leonov'' leaves Jupiter, Bowman instructs HAL to begin repeatedly broadcasting the message:
{{blockquote|ALL THESE WORLDS ARE YOURS EXCEPT EUROPA. ATTEMPT NO LANDINGS THERE.}}
The movie version, as part of its heightened [[Cold War]] emphasis at [[Earth]], adds the words: 
{{blockquote|USE THEM TOGETHER. USE THEM IN PEACE}}

The new star, which Earth eventually dubs &quot;[[Lucifer]]&quot;, destroys ''Discovery'' entirely. HAL is transformed into the same kind of life form as David Bowman, and becomes Bowman's companion.

==Specifications==
'''Official Name:''' USSC ''Discovery One'' &lt;br&gt;
'''USSA &quot;Registration Number&quot;:''' XD-1 &lt;br&gt;
'''Overall Length:''' 140.1 m &lt;br&gt;
'''Overall Beam:''' 16.7 m &lt;br&gt;
'''Overall Draft:''' 17 m &lt;br&gt;
'''Command Module Diameter:''' 16.5 m &lt;br&gt;
'''Reactor Module Length:''' 32.2 m &lt;br&gt;
'''Reactor Module Draft:''' 8.8 m &lt;br&gt;
'''Mass:''' 5,440 tonnes &lt;br&gt;
'''Life Support:''' (two men, out of [[hibernation]]): 90 months

'''Engine Type:''' Cavradyne [[Plasma (physics)|Plasma]] [[Spacecraft propulsion|Propulsion]] System (Six Engines) - [[Ammonia|Liquid Ammonia]] Fuel- Thrust Deflector Plates- Maximum [[Thrust]] 280,000 [[kilogram-force|kgf]] (2.75 [[meganewton|MN]]).

&lt;!-- Image with inadequate rationale removed: [[File:Hal brain room605.JPG|thumb|Bowman enters [[HAL 9000]]'s Central Core in the ''Discovery''.]] --&gt;

'''Computer:''' [[HAL 9000]] Logic Memory System (Completed Jan. 12, 1992 at the HAL Plant in [[Urbana, Illinois|Urbana]], IL.)

[[File:2001humanhibernation.jpg|thumb|[[2001: A Space Odyssey]] — Three of the ''Discovery One'' crew are in a state of hibernation, ostensibly to conserve resources for the voyage.]]

'''[[Cryonics|Suspended Animation]] System:''' Meditech 712-R Hibernacula (3 Centrifuge, 5 Medical Level)

'''[[Extra-vehicular activity|EVA]] Craft:''' [[2001 EVA Pod|Grumman DC-3 EVA Pods]] (3)

'''Pod Bay features:''' Three each Pod turntable Base, Extension motor, Extension Platform, Outer hull door, [[Space suit]] rack. Test bench with two [[LCD]] screens and HAL 9000 terminal. Two large emergency [[oxygen]] bottles. Nine small emergency oxygen bottles. [[Circuit breaker|Circuit Breaker]] Box. Manual control station with HAL 9000 terminal, Six [[LCD]] screens, and full control set.

'''Pod Bay Deck:''' Along with the Pod Bay, the Pod Bay Deck also features an emergency [[airlock]], circuitry storage bay, two fresh [[water]] tanks, a maintenance equipment room, an emergency shelter and [[space suit]] rack, emergency [[battery (electricity)|batteries]] for the [[centrifuge]] and pod bay, and a zero-''g'' [[toilet]].

'''Living Module:''' Centrifuge, Magnetic-Drive type. 11.6 m. diameter. Rotation Rate 3 RPM. 
Living Module Control Stations: 12-screen HAL 9000 [[User interface|interface]]/ communications module, [[Nuclear reactor]] monitoring station, Remote [[Unmanned space mission|probe]] control, [[Radar]] mapping station, climate control, and Revival Monitoring Station.

'''Living Module Habitation Features:''' Sanitary module, (Shower, Sink, Waste water recycling Control) Three Meditech 712-R Hibernacula, Sun-ray tanning station, [[Water closet]] (Head), Three [[Circuit breaker]] panels. One emergency space suit locker, Two spare part lockers, Three clothing lockers.

'''[[Cockpit (aviation)|Cockpit]]:''' Two seats for [[Commander#NASA_rank|Mission Commander]] and Deputy Commander. Full range of instruments and control panels. Two sets of four LCD screens and HAL Visual Sensor.

'''Command Deck:''' The Command Deck includes the [[Cockpit (aviation)|cockpit]], zero-''g'' [[astronomy]] lab, zero-g sciences lab, two [[fresh water]] tanks, six-spacesuit recharge unit, a pre-launch personnel clearance area, the [[circuit breaker]] room, and a zero-''g'' toilet. The [[Command Deck]] also includes all [[HAL 9000]] related systems (see below).

'''[[HAL 9000]] systems:''' Logic memory center, auxiliary power unit, computer climate regulation system, autonomic systems control center, and reactor control system.

'''[[Attitude control|Thrusters]]:''' Eight Mk 114 on command module. 720 kgf (7.1&amp;nbsp;kN) thrust each. Two forward and two aft of reactor module. Nine Mk 29 vernier thrusters; three clustered around each [[Cavradyne]] engine exhaust. 1,600 kgf (15.7&amp;nbsp;kN) thrust each. Eight mid-course correction [[Rocket engine|thrusters]] (four on each TJI propulsion mount) Four emergency escape rockets at [[Command Module]] rear.

'''Central Communications Complex:''' ''Discovery One's'' central communications complex is mounted atop the seventh fuel module aft of the command section. The main audio-visual communications [[antenna (radio)|antenna]] measures 4.13 meters in diameter. Both [[telemetry]] antennas measure 1.26 meters across. The entire assembly can be swiveled 360 [[degree (angle)|degree]]s and aimed upwards or downwards at any angle between 0 and 285 degrees.

'''Misc. Equipment:''' An emergency communications antenna, about half the size of the main antenna, is stored beneath the blow-away cover at the command module's top. Four probes (two atmospheric, two remote-controlled landers) and a [[telescope]] array are stored beneath the bottom blow-away cover.

'''Structural Support:''' ''Discovery One's'' reactor module is secured to the aftermost fuel module by four heavy-duty [[docking latches]]. Twelve reinforced coupling units along the spine provide additional support. The spine and reactor module are held in place by six docking latches at the intermodule adapter plate. The entire spine/reactor assembly can be jettisoned in an emergency by eight [[explosive bolt|explosive separation bolts]] installed in the adapter plate. Finally, the entire Emergency [[Spacecraft propulsion|Propulsion]] System (EPS) can be jettisoned using a ring of 16 [[explosive bolts]] installed in a ring around the forward section of the EPS. There is no re-docking capability for any assembly.

'''Crew:'''
* [[David Bowman (Space Odyssey)|David Bowman]] (Mission Commander)
* [[Frank Poole]] (Deputy Commander)
* Victor Kaminsky (Survey Team Leader) [Geophysicist in the novel]
* Jack Kimball (Geophysicist) [Peter Whitehead/Survey Team Leader in the novel]
* Charles Hunter (Astrophysicist)

==References==
*[[Arthur C Clarke]] &quot;The Lost Worlds of 2001&quot;, Signet, 1972

{{Spaceodyssey}}

[[Category:Fictional spacecraft]]
[[Category:Space Odyssey series]]

[[es:Discovery]]
[[fr:Discovery One]]
[[nl:Discovery One]]
[[pl:Discovery One]]
[[sv:Discovery One]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
