<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="14881751" ns="0" title="Inspecção Geral das Actividades Culturais"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">'''IGAC''', Inspecção Geral das Actividades Culturais (English: General Inspection of Cultural Activities), is an organization, part of the [[Ministry of Culture (Portugal)|Portuguese Ministry of Culture]]. [[Image:IGAC.jpg|right|70px]]
It is the organization responsible for the rating of videogames, movies and related media released in [[Portugal]]. 

Movies are rated using the following classifications:

* '''M/4''' Suitable for all ages. Content with this rating should be of short duration and easy to understand. It should not provoke fear and/or collide with the sense of fantasy.
* '''M/6''' Not recommended to children below the age of 6. Content with this rating may be of longer duration and contain some fear factor.
* '''M/12''' Not recommended to children below the age of 12. Content with this rating may, due to its length and complexity, provoke in younger viewers fatigue and psychiatric trauma. Children below the age of 12 must be accompanied by an adult.
* '''M/16''' Not recommended to children below the age of 16. Content with this rating may explore aspects of sexuality, physical and psychic violence. Children below the age of 16 must be accompanied by an adult.
* '''M/18''' Adults only. Content with this rating may be of explicit sexual nature. Children must be accompanied by an adult, and ticket sellers reserve the right to block very young children from these screenings.
==External links==
*[http://www.igac.pt/ ''IGAC'', Official website] {{pt icon}}
*[http://www.portaldacultura.gov.pt/ ''Portuguese Ministry of Culture'', Official website] {{pt icon}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Inspeccao Geral Das Actividades Culturais}}
[[Category:Organisations based in Portugal]]
[[Category:Motion picture rating systems]]


{{portugal-stub}}

[[ja:文化活動監察機構]]
[[pt:Inspecção-Geral das Actividades Culturais]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
