<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="14912487" ns="0" title="Aquagenic urticaria"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Refimprove|date=March 2010}}
{{Infobox Disease
 | Name           = Aquagenic urticaria (gremmlin disease)
 | Image          = 
 | Caption        = 
 | DiseasesDB     = 
 | ICD10          = L50.8 ([[ILDS]] L50.830)
 | ICD9           = 
 | ICDO           = 
 | OMIM           = 
 | MedlinePlus    = 
 | eMedicineSubj  = 
 | eMedicineTopic = 
 | MeshID         = 
}}
'''Aquagenic urticaria''', also known as '''water urticaria''' and '''aquagenous urticaria''', is a rarely diagnosed form of [[physical urticaria]]. It is sometimes described as an [[allergy]], although it is not a true [[histamine]] releasing allergic reaction like other forms of urticaria. The defining symptom is a painful skin reaction resulting from contact with [[water]].This may also be a cause of different temperatures of water, such as cold or hot and can flare with chemicals such as chlorine

==Symptoms==
Aquagenic urticaria usually causes the skin to itch and burn after being exposed to water of any kind. The skin may develop [[hives]]. Showers may result in severely dry eyes and soreness. Higher water temperatures tend to expedite the formation of hives. Shortness of breath or swelling in the throat can occur when drinking water. The pain usually persists for between 10–120 minutes.&lt;ref&gt;Healthy Skin Guide&lt;/ref&gt;

==Causes==
Contact with any form of water can cause symptoms to appear. One's own or someone else’s [[sweat]] can cause a reaction, so most affected people try to stay cool in summer to avoid sweating as much as possible. [[Tears]] on one's face from crying can also cause pain. Most people with aquagenic urticaria try to stay out of the rain and carry umbrellas as a precautionary measure. Cleansing the body often induces such an intense reaction that affected people may take very short showers to lessen the severity of the pain.&lt;ref&gt;MailOnline&lt;/ref&gt;

==Treatment==
There is no known treatment for aquagenic urticaria. [[Dermatologists]] recommend avoiding contact with water as much as possible by taking short showers, staying cool, and avoiding rain to ease symptoms. [[Antihistamines]], [[Zostrix]], and other types of medications may be prescribed to help reduce the intensity of the reaction.&lt;ref&gt;MailOnline&lt;/ref&gt;

== See also ==
* [[Aquagenic pruritus]]
* [[Aquadynia]]
* [[Cholinergic urticaria]]
* [[List of cutaneous conditions]]

== References ==
{{reflist}}

== External links ==
* [http://dermatology.about.com/cs/hives/a/waterurt.htm About.com Dermatology Article]
* [http://www.dailymail.co.uk/pages/live/articles/news/worldnews.html?in_article_id=520329&amp;in_page_id=1811 Dailymail] Teenage girl who is allergic to water - The Daily Mail News
* [http://www.dailymail.co.uk/health/article-1172102/Mothers-allergy-water-means-drink-bathe-wipe-away-sons-tears.html Dailymail]

{{Urticaria and erythema}}

[[Category:Urticaria and angioedema]]
[[Category:Rare diseases]]
[[Category:Allergology]]

[[de:Wassernesselsucht]]
[[fr:Urticaire aquagénique]]
[[ja:水アレルギー]]
[[no:Aquagenic Urticaria]]
[[pt:Urticária aquagênica]]
[[fi:Vesiallergia]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
