<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="149281" ns="0" title="Performance art"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{about|performance art|other topics|performance (disambiguation)}}

In [[art]], '''performance art''' is a [[performance]] presented to an [[audience]], traditionally [[interdisciplinary]]. Performance may be either scripted or unscripted, random or carefully orchestrated; spontaneous or otherwise carefully planned with or without audience participation. The performance can be live or via media; the performer can be present or absent. It can be any situation that involves four basic elements: time, space, the performer's body, or presence in a medium, and a relationship between performer and audience. Performance art can happen anywhere, in any venue or setting and for any length of time. The actions of an individual or a group at a particular place and in a particular time constitute the work.

== Visual arts, performing arts and art performance ==
[[Image:ZoneImmaterielKlein2.jpg|thumb|upright|left|[[Yves Klein]] and [[Dino Buzzati]] engaged in the ritual transfer of immateriality, January 26, 1962]]
Performance art is an essentially contested concept: any single definition of it implies the recognition of rival uses. As concepts like &quot;democracy&quot; or &quot;art&quot;, it implies productive disagreement with itself.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book | last1 = Carlson | first1 = Marvin | title = Performance: A Critical Introduction | publisher = Routledge | year = 1998 (first 1996) | location = London and New York | pages = 1, 2 | isbn = 0-415-13703-9}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The meaning of the term in the narrower sense is related to postmodernist traditions in Western culture. From about the mid-1960s into the 1970s, often derived from concepts of visual art, with respect to [[Antonin Artaud]], [[Dada]], the [[Situationist]]s, [[Fluxus]], [[Installation art]], and [[Conceptual Art]], performance art tended to be defined as an [[antithesis]] to [[theatre]], challenging orthodox artforms and cultural norms. The ideal had been an ephemeral and authentic experience for performer and audience in an [[event]] that could not be repeated, captured or purchased.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book | last1 = Parr | first1 = Adrian | title = Becoming + Performance Art | editors = Adrian Parr | work = The Deleuze Dictionary | publisher = Edinburgh University Press | year = 2005 | pages = 25, 2 | url = http://books.google.de/books?id=OsVOy4s1QLMC&amp;printsec=frontcover#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false | accessdate = 2010-10-26 | isbn = 0748618988 / 0748618996}}&lt;/ref&gt; The in this time widely discussed difference, how concepts of visual arts and concepts of performing arts are utilized, can determine the meanings of a performance art presentation (compare ''Performance: A Critical Introduction'' by Marvin Carlson, P. 103,2-105,1).

Performance art is a term usually reserved to refer to a [[conceptual art]] which conveys a content-based meaning in a more drama-related sense, rather than being simple performance for its own sake for entertainment purposes. It largely refers to a performance which is presented to an audience, but which does not seek to present a conventional theatrical play or a formal linear narrative, or which alternately does not seek to depict a set of fictitious characters in formal scripted interactions. It therefore can include action or spoken word as a communication between the artist and audience, or even ignore expectations of an audience, rather than following a script written beforehand.

Some kinds of performance art nevertheless can be close to performing arts. Such performance may utilize a script or create a fictitious dramatic setting, but still constitute performance art in that it does not seek to follow the usual dramatic norm of creating a fictitious setting with a linear script which follows conventional real-world dynamics; rather, it would intentionally seek to satirize or to transcend the usual real-world dynamics which are used in conventional theatrical plays.

Performance artists often challenge the audience to think in new and unconventional ways, break conventions of traditional arts, and break down conventional ideas about &quot;what art is&quot;. As long as the performer does not become a player who repeats a role, performance art can include satirical elements (compare [[Blue Man Group]]); utilize [[robot]]s and machines as performers, as in pieces of the [[Survival Research Laboratories]]; or borrow elements of any [[performing arts]] such as [[dance]], [[music]], and [[circus (performing art)|circus]].

Some artists, e.g. the [[Viennese Actionism|Viennese Actionists]] and [[neo-Dada]]ists, prefer to use the terms [[Live Art (art form)|&quot;live art&quot;]], &quot;action art&quot;, &quot;actions&quot;, &quot;intervention&quot; (see [[art intervention]]) or &quot;manoeuvre&quot; to describe their performing activities. As genres of performance art appear [[body art]], fluxus-performance, [[happening]], [[action poetry]], and [[intermedia]].

==Origins==
Performance art activity is not confined to European or American art traditions; notable practitioners can be found in [[Asia]] and [[Latin America]]. Performance artists and theorists point to different traditions and histories, ranging from tribal to sporting and ritual or religious events. In an episode of [[In our time]] broadcast on Thu, 20 Oct 2005, 21:30 on BBC Radio 4, [[Angie Hobbs]], Lecturer in Philosophy, University of Warwick; [[Miriam Griffin]], Fellow of Somerville College, Oxford; and [[John Moles]], Professor of Latin, University of Newcastle discussed with [[Melvin Bragg]] the idea that [[Antisthenes]] and [[Diogenes]] in ancient Greece practiced a form of performance art and that they acquired the epithet of [[cynic]] which means &quot;dog&quot; due to Diogenes behaving repeatedly like a dog in his performances.

There are also accounts of [[Renaissance]] artists such as  [[itinerant poets]] putting on public performances that could be said to be ancestors of performance art.{{Citation needed|date=April 2011}}

[[Image:Le Saut Dans le Vide.jpg|thumb|upright|Conceptual work by [[Yves Klein]] at Rue Gentil-Bernard, Fontenay-aux-Roses, October 1960, photo by Harry Shunk. ''Le Saut dans le Vide'' (Leap into the Void)]]
Western cultural theorists often trace performance art activity back to the beginning of the 20th century, to the [[Constructivism (art)|Russian constructivists]], [[Futurism|Futurists]] and [[Dada]]. Dada provided a significant progenitor with the unconventional performances of poetry, often at the [[Cabaret Voltaire (Zurich)|Cabaret Voltaire]], by the likes of [[Richard Huelsenbeck]] and [[Tristan Tzara]]. [[Russian Futurist]] artists could be identified as precursors of performance, such as [[David Burliuk]], who painted his face for his actions (1910–20) and [[Alexander Rodchenko]] and his wife [[Varvara Stepanova]].

According to the art critic [[Harold Rosenberg]] in the 1940s and 1950s [[Action Painting]] gave artists the freedom to perform - the canvas as &quot;an arena in which to act&quot;, thereby rendering the paintings as traces of the artist's performance in his/her studio. [[Abstract expressionism]] and [[Action painting]] preceded the [[Fluxus movement]], [[Happenings]] and the emergence of Performance Art. 

Performance art was anticipated, if not explicitly formulated, by [[Japan]]'s [[Gutai group]] of the 1950s, especially in such works as [[Atsuko Tanaka (artist)|Atsuko Tanaka]]'s &quot;Electric Dress&quot; (1956) [http://nymag.com/nymetro/arts/art/reviews/9937/].

[[Yves Klein]] had been a precursor of performance art with the conceptual pieces of ''[[Zone de Sensibilité Picturale Immatérielle]]'' (''Zones of Immaterial Pictorial Sensibility'') 1959–62, and works like the photomontage, Saut dans le vide (Leap into the Void). In the late 1960s [[Land art|Earth artists]] as diverse as [[Robert Smithson]], [[Dennis Oppenheim]], [[Michael Heizer]] and [[Carl Andre]] created environmental pieces that predict the performance art of the 1970s. Works of conceptual artists in the early 1980s, like [[Sol LeWitt]], who converted mural-style drawing into an act of performance by others, were influenced by Yves Klein and the Earth artists as well.

==1960s==
In the 1960s a variety of new works, concepts and the increasing number of artists led to new kinds of performance art. 

Prototypic for the artform later explicitly labeled &quot;performance art&quot;, were works of artists like [[Yoko Ono]] with her ''Wall piece for orchestra'' (1962); [[Carolee Schneemann]] with pieces like ''Meat Joy'' (1964); [[Joseph Beuys]] with ''How to Explain Pictures to a Dead Hare'' (1965); [[Yayoi Kusama]], with actions such as a naked flag-burning on the Brooklyn Bridge (1968) and [[Allan Kaprow]] in his many ''Happenings''. 

Kaprow had coined the term [[Happening]] describing a new artform, at the beginning of the 1960s. A ''Happening'' allows the artist to experiment with body motion, recorded sounds, written and spoken texts, and even smells. One of Kaprow's earliest was &quot;Happenings in the New York Scene,&quot; written in 1961 as the form was developing.&lt;ref&gt;Montfort, Nick, and Noah Wardrip-Fruin. The New Media Reader. Cambridge, Mass. [u.a.: MIT, 2003. Print.&lt;/ref&gt;  Notably in the Happenings of Allan Kaprow, the audience members become performers. While the audiences in Happenings had been welcomed as the performers, it is only sometimes and often unwittingly that they become an active part in a Performance. Other artists who created Happenings besides Kaprow include [[Jim Dine]], [[Claes Oldenburg]], [[Robert Whitman]], and [[Wolf Vostell]]: ''Theater is in the Street'' (Paris in 1958). 

[[Hermann Nitsch]] in 1962 presented his &quot;Theatre of Orgies and Mysteries&quot; (Orgien- und Mysterien Theater), a precursor to performance art, close to the performing arts. 

[[Andy Warhol]] during the early 1960s beginning to create films and video, in the mid-60s sponsored the [[Velvet Underground]] and staged events and performances in New York, like the [[Exploding Plastic Inevitable]] (1966) that featured live Rock music, exploding lights, and film.  

Indirectly influential for art-world performance, particularly in the United States, were new forms of theatre, embodied by the [[San Francisco Mime Troupe]] and the [[Living Theatre]] and showcased in Off-Off Broadway theaters in SoHO and at [[La MaMa Experimental Theatre Club|La MaMa]] in New York City. The Living Theatre chiefly toured in Europe between 1963 and 1968, and in the U.S. in 1968. A work of this period, [[Paradise Now]] was notorious for its audience participation and a scene in which actors recited a list of social taboos that included nudity, while disrobing.

The work of performance artists after 1968 often showed influences of the cultural and political events of that year. [[Barbara T. Smith]] with ''Ritual Meal'' (1969) was at the forefront of the feminist body-, and performance art of the 1970s; among others including: [[Carolee Schneemann]], and [[Joan Jonas]]. Schneemann and Jonas along with [[Yoko Ono]], [[Joseph Beuys]], [[Vito Acconci]], and [[Chris Burden]] pioneered the relationship between ''[[Body art]]'' and performance art.

== 1970s ==
[[Image:Burden-Transfixed.jpg|thumb|[[Chris Burden]] during the performance of his 1974 piece ''Trans-fixed'' where he was nailed to the back of a [[Volkswagen]]]]
Artists whose work already before tended to be a performance art, as well as new artists, at the beginning of the 1970s began to present performance art in a stricter form. 

New artists with radical performances were [[Chris Burden]], with the 1971 performance piece ''Shoot'', in which he was shot in his left arm by an assistant from a distance of about five meters, and [[Vito Acconci]] in the same year with ''[[Seedbed]]''.

The book [[Expanded Cinema]], by [[Gene Youngblood]], marked a shift in the use of media by performance artists. The first book considering video art as an art form, mentions [[Jud Yalkut]] as a pioneering video artist. Since 1965 he had collaborated in dozens of intermedia performances throughout the United States, also with [[Nam June Paik]], who beginning of the 1960s already had been a fluxus performer on the way to become a media artist. As to the art of Paik, Youngblood refers to works of Carolee Schneemann and [[Robert Whitman]] from the 1960s, which had been pioneering for performance art, becoming an independent artform at the beginning of the 1970s.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book | last1 = Youngblood | first1 = Gene | title = Expanded Cinema | publisher = A. Dutton | year = 1970 | location = New York, New York}}&lt;/ref&gt; 

The British-based pair [[Gilbert and George]], already in 1970, had documented actions of themselves on video, and created their &quot;living sculpture&quot; performance, being painted in gold and singing &quot;Underneath The Arches&quot; for extended periods. [[Joan Jonas]] began to include video in her experimental performances in 1972.

In 1973 [[Laurie Anderson]] performed ''Duets on Ice'', on the streets of New York City. [[Marina Abramović]], in the performance &quot;Rhythm 10&quot;, conceptually included the violation of her body.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url = http://www.medienkunstnetz.de/works/rhythm-10-2/ | title = Marina Abramović Rhythm 10 | accessdate = 2011-03-24 | publisher = Media Art Net}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Since 1973 the Feminist Studio Workshop at the [[Woman's Building]] in Los Angeles had a formative impact on the wave of performances with feminist background. 

[[Carolee Schneemann]] work in 1963, ''Eye Body'', already had been a prototype of performance art. Schneemann in 1975 drew on with innovative solo performances, like ''Interior Scroll'', showing the female body as an artistic medium. 

Performance art, because of its relative transience, by the 1970s, had a fairly robust presence in the avant-garde of East Bloc countries, especially Yugoslavia and Poland.

== 1980s ==

Until the 1980s, performance art had been demystifying virtuosity. Now it began to embrace technical brilliance.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book | last1 = Banes | first1 = Sally | title = Subversive expectations: performance art and paratheater in New York, 1976-85 | publisher = The University of Michigan Press | year = 1998 | location = New York, New York | pages = 120, 1 | url = http://books.google.de/books?id=DdrVYfkAm6IC&amp;pg=PA10&amp;dq=1980s+performance+art&amp;ct=result#v=onepage&amp;q=1980s%20performance%20art&amp;f=false | accessdate = 2011-03-23 | isbn = 0-472-09678-8}}&lt;/ref&gt; In reference to ''Presence and Resistance''&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book | last1 = Auslander | first1 = Philip | title = Presence and Resistance: Postmodernism and Cultural politics in Contemporary American Performance | publisher = University of Michigan Press | year = 1992 | location = Ann Arbour | pages = P. 64–65, 78–79}}&lt;/ref&gt; by [[Philip Auslander]], a performance art critic, [[Sally Banes]] writes “… by the end of the 1980s, performance art had become so widely known that it no longer needed to be defined; mass culture, especially television, had come to supply both structure and subject matter for much performance art; and several performance artists, including [[Laurie Anderson]], [[Spalding Gray]], [[Eric Bogosian]], [[Willem Dafoe]], and [[Ann Magnuson]], had indeed become crossover artists in mainstream entertainment.”&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book | last1 = Banes | first1 = Sally | title = Subversive expectations: performance art and paratheater in New York, 1976-85 | publisher = The University of Michigan Press | year = 1998 | location = New York, New York | pages = 10, 1 | url = http://books.google.de/books?id=DdrVYfkAm6IC&amp;pg=PA10&amp;dq=1980s+performance+art&amp;ct=result#v=onepage&amp;q=1980s%20performance%20art&amp;f=false | accessdate = 2011-03-23 | isbn = 0-472-09678-8}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Despite the fact that many performances are held within the circle of a small art-world group, [[RoseLee Goldberg]] notes, in ''Performance Art: From Futurism to the Present'' that &quot;performance has been a way of appealing directly to a large public, as well as shocking audiences into reassessing their own notions of art and its relation to culture. Conversely, public interest in the medium, especially in the 1980s, stems from an apparent desire of that public to gain access to the art world, to be a spectator of its ritual and its distinct community, and to be surprised by the unexpected, always unorthodox presentations that the artists devise.”&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.amazon.com/gp/product/0500203393 Performance Art from Futurism to the Present by [[RoseLee Goldberg]] accessed online August 31, 2007]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

Among the performance art most discussed in the art-world of this decade were a performance by Linda Montano and Tehching Hsieh between July 1983 and July 1984, ''Art/Life: One Year Performance'' (Rope Piece), and Karen Finlay’s ''I'm an Ass Man'' 1987.

Until the decline of the European eastern block during the late 1980s, performance art by most communist governments had actively been rejected. With the exception of Poland and Yugoslavia, performance art was more or less banned in countries where any independent public event was feared. In the GDR, Czechoslovakia, Hungary and Latvia it happened in apartments, at seemingly spontaneous gatherings in artist studios, in church-controlled settings, or covered as another activity, like a photo-shooting. Isolated of the western conceptual context, in different settings it could be like a playful protest or like a bitter comment, using subversive metaphors to express dissent with the political situation.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url = http://perfomap.de/current/kart/reclaiming-the-invisible | title = Reclaiming the Invisible Past of Eastern Europe | accessdate = 2011-03-23 | last = Zajanckauska | first = Zane | coauthors = Interview with Ieva Astahovska | publisher = map - media archive performance}}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Hedwig Gorski]] before 1982 came up up with the term [[performance poetry]], to distinguish her text-based vocal performances from performance art, especially the work of performance artists, such as Laurie Anderson, who worked with music at that time. Performance poets relied more on the rhetorical and philosophical expression in their poetics than performance artists, who arose from the visual art genres of painting and sculpture.

== 1990s ==

While the Soviet bloc disintegrated, formerly repressed activities of performance artists like [[György Galántai]] in Hungary, or the Collective Action Group in Russia, became better known. Young artists from all over the former Eastern bloc, including Russia, turned to performance. Performance art at about the same time appeared in Cuba, the Caribbean and China. Chinese performance artists like [[Zhang Huan]] had been performing underground since the late 1980s. Beginning of the 1990s [[chinese performance art]] already was acclaimed in the international artscene.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book | last1 = Montano | first1 = Linda M. | title = Performance artists talking in the eighties | publisher = University of California Press Berkeley | year = 2000 | location = Los Angeles, London | pages = 479, 1 | url = http://books.google.com/books?id=5Bl6wm-cV_oC&amp;pg=PA479&amp;dq=performance+art+1990s&amp;ct=result#v=onepage&amp;q=performance%20art&amp;f=false | accessdate = 2011-03-31 | isbn = 0-520-21022-0}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&quot;In these contexts performance art became a critical new voice with a social force similar to that found in Western Europe, the United States and South America in the 1960s and early 1970s. It should be emphasized that the eruption of performance art in the 1990s in Eastern Europe, China, South Africa, Cuba, and elsewhere should never be considered either secondary to or imitative of the West.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book | last1 = Montano | first1 = Linda M. | title = Performance artists talking in the eighties | publisher = University of California Press University of California Press Berkeley | year = 2000 | location = Los Angeles, London | pages = 479, 2 | url = http://books.google.com/books?id=5Bl6wm-cV_oC&amp;pg=PA479&amp;dq=performance+art+1990s&amp;ct=result#v=onepage&amp;q=performance%20art&amp;f=false | accessdate = 2011-03-31 | isbn = 0-520-21022-0}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In the western world in the 1990s, even sophisticated performance art became part of the cultural mainstream: performance art as a complete artform gained admittance into art museums and became a museal topic.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book | last1 = Targ Brill | first1 = Marlene | title = America in the 1990s | publisher = Lerner Publishing Group | year = 2009 | pages = 93, 1 | location = Minneapolis | url = http://books.google.com/books?id=BNXeIFQScocC&amp;dq=performance+art+1990s&amp;q=performance#v=snippet&amp;q=performance&amp;f=false | accessdate = 2011-03-31 | isbn = 978-0-8225-7603-7}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==2000s==
In the second half of the decade, computer-aided forms of performance art began to take place.&lt;ref&gt;Anderson, Nate (2009), [http://arstechnica.com/web/news/2009/09/horrifically-bad-software-demos-become-performance-art.ars ''Horrifically bad software demo becomes performance art'']&quot;&lt;/ref&gt;

From March 14 to May 31, 2010, the [[Museum of Modern Art]] held a major retrospective and performance recreation of [[Marina Abramović]]'s work, the biggest exhibition of performance art in MoMA's history.&lt;ref&gt;Kino, Carol (March 10, 2010). &quot;[http://www.nytimes.com/2010/03/14/arts/design/14performance.html?pagewanted=all A Rebel Form Gains Favor. Fights Ensue.]&quot;, ''[[The New York Times]]''. Retrieved 2010-04-16.&lt;/ref&gt; During the run of the exhibition, Abramović performed &quot;The Artist is Present,&quot; a 736-hour and 30-minute static, silent piece, in which she sat immobile in the museum's atrium, while spectators were invited to take turns sitting opposite her.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.huffingtonpost.com/yazmany-arboleda/bringing-marina-flowers_b_592597.html|title=SBringing Marina Flowers|last=Arboleda|first=Yazmany|authorlink=Yazmany Arboleda|date=May 28, 2010|newspaper=The Huffington Post|accessdate=2010-06-16|archiveurl = http://www.webcitation.org/5vy37wSbU |archivedate = 2011-01-23|deadurl=no}}&lt;/ref&gt; A support group for the &quot;sitters,&quot; &quot;Sitting with Marina,&quot; was established on [[Facebook]].&lt;ref&gt;http://www.facebook.com/group.php?gid=122578407758954&quot;&lt;/ref&gt; The performance attracted celebrities such as [[Björk]] and [[James Franco]] and received coverage on the internet including an essay by NYC-author [[Tao Lin]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://thoughtcatalog.com/2010/marina-abramovic-the-staring-woman-at-moma/ thoughtcatalog.com/2010/marina-abramovic]&lt;/ref&gt;

==Gallery==
&lt;gallery widths=&quot;150px&quot; heights=&quot;150px&quot; perrow=&quot;4&quot;&gt;
Image:BeuysAchberg78.jpg|Performance artist [[Joseph Beuys]] in 1978: ''Jeder Mensch ein Künstler — Auf dem Weg zur Freiheitsgestalt des sozialen Organismus'' - Every person an artist — On the way to the libertarian form of the social organism
Image:Stelarc ArsElectronica97.jpg|[[Stelarc]] &quot;Parasite: Event for Invaded and Involuntary Body&quot; (1997) [[Ars Electronica]] Festival
File:Marina_1_1.jpg|[[Marina Abramović]]: ''[[Seven Easy Pieces]]'', 9. November 2005
File:artistIsPresent.jpg|[[Marina Abramović]] performing in &quot;The Artist is Present&quot; at the [[Museum of Modern Art]], May 2010
&lt;/gallery&gt;

==See also==

*[[Classificatory disputes about art]]
*[[Danger music]]
*[[Flash mob]]
*[[Noise music]]
*[[New media art]]
*[[Living statue]]
*[[List of performance artists]]
*[[Survival Research Laboratories]]

==References==
&lt;references/&gt;

==Bibliography==
* Carlson, Marvin (1996) Performance: A Critical Introduction. London and New York: Routledge. ISBN 0-415-13702-0, 0-415-13703-9
* Carr, C. (1993) On Edge: Performance at the End of the Twentieth Century. Wesleyan University Press. ISBN 0819552674, 0819562696
* Thomas Dreher: ''Performance Art nach 1945. Aktionstheater und Intermedia.'' München: Wilhelm Fink 2001. ISBN 3-7705-3452-2 (in German)
* Erika Fischer-Lichte: ''Ästhetik des Performativen''. Frankfurt: edition suhrkamp 2004. ISBN 3-518-12373-4 (in German)
* [[Roselee Goldberg|Goldberg, Roselee]] (1998) Performance: Live Art Since 1960. Harry N. Abrams, NY NY. ISBN 9780810943605
* Goldberg, Roselee (2001) Performance Art: From Futurism to the Present (World of Art). Thames &amp; Hudson
* Gómez-Peña, Guillermo (2005) Ethno-techno: Writings on performance, activism and pedagogy. Routledge, London. ISBN 0415362482
* Jones, Amelia and Adrian Heathfield (eds.) (2012), Perform, Repeat, Record. Live Art in History. Intellect, Bristol. ISBN 9781841504896
* Rockwell, John (2004) Preserve Performance Art? New York Times, April 30.
* Schimmel, Paul (ed.) (1998) Out of Actions: Between Performance and the Object, 1949-1979. Thames and Hudson, Los Angeles. Library of the Congress NX456.5.P38 S35 1998
* Smith, Roberta (2005) Performance Art Gets Its Biennial. New York Times, November 2.

==External links==
{{commons category|Performance art}}
{{wikiversity|Performance art}}
{{wikiquote}}
* [http://www.bris.ac.uk/theatrecollection/liveart/liveart_archivesmain.html Live Art Archives at the University of Bristol Theatre Collection]
* [http://dreher.netzliteratur.net/2_Performance_Kunst_Titel.html Thomas Dreher]: Intermedia Art: Performance Art (most articles in German)

{{Westernart}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Performance Art}}
[[Category:Performance art| 01]]
[[Category:Contemporary art]]
[[Category:Postmodern art]]
[[Category:Performing arts]]
[[Category:Theatre]]
[[Category:Culture jamming techniques]]
[[Category:Art movements]]

[[ar:فن الأداء]]
[[be-x-old:Пэрформанс]]
[[bo:སྤྱོད་ལམ་སྒྱུ་རྩལ་ཐོག]]
[[ca:Actuació artística]]
[[da:Performancekunst]]
[[de:Performance (Kunst)]]
[[es:Performance]]
[[fa:هنر اجرا]]
[[fr:Art performance]]
[[id:Seni pertunjukan]]
[[it:Performance art]]
[[he:מיצג]]
[[kk:Перфоманс]]
[[lt:Performansas]]
[[hu:Performansz]]
[[nl:Performance]]
[[ja:パフォーマンスアート]]
[[no:Performance]]
[[nds:Performance (Kunst)]]
[[pl:Performance]]
[[pt:Performance]]
[[ru:Перформанс]]
[[sk:Performance Art]]
[[sr:Перформанс]]
[[su:Seni Pintonan]]
[[fi:Performanssi]]
[[sv:Performance]]
[[tr:Performans sanatı]]
[[uk:Перформанс]]
[[zh:行为艺术]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
