<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="14931652" ns="0" title="Amazon MP3"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Infobox online music service
|opened=September 25, 2007
|service_name=Amazon MP3
|service_screenshot=[[Image:Amazon mp3.png|250px]]
|pricing=variable pricing per album
|platforms=[[Microsoft Windows|Windows]], [[Mac OS X]], [[Linux]]
|format=[[MP3]] (.mp3) @ 256 [[kbit/s]] [[variable bitrate|VBR]]
|restrictions=None
|catalogue=16,024,267 songs
|preview=30 Seconds
|availability=United States, United Kingdom, Germany, France, Austria, Switzerland, Japan
|homepage={{URL|www.amazonmp3.com}}
|footnotes=
}}
'''Amazon MP3''' is an [[online music store]] owned and operated by [[Amazon.com]].  Launched in [[public beta]] on September 25, 2007,&lt;ref name=&quot;launch-pr&quot; /&gt; in January 2008 it became the first music store to sell music without [[digital rights management]] (DRM) from the four major music labels ([[EMI]], [[Universal Music Group|Universal]], [[Warner Music]], and [[Sony BMG]]), as well as many independents.&lt;ref name=&quot;launch-pr&quot;&gt;[http://home.businesswire.com/portal/site/google/index.jsp?ndmViewId=news_view&amp;newsId=20070925005710&amp;newsLang=en Amazon.com Launches Public Beta of Amazon MP3]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;warner&quot;&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.nytimes.com/2007/12/28/technology/28music.html|title=Amazon to Sell Warner Music Minus Copy Protection|publisher=[[The New York Times]]|date=December 28, 2007|accessdate=2007-12-28|last=Leeds|first=Jeff}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;sony1&quot;&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.informationweek.com/news/showArticle.jhtml?articleID=205602334&amp;subSection=All+Stories|title=Amazon Adds Fourth Major Record Label To DRM-Free Music Store|publisher=[[InformationWeek]]|accessdate=2008-01-12|date=January 10, 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;sony2&quot;&gt;{{cite news|url=http://bits.blogs.nytimes.com/2008/01/10/sony-drives-another-nail-in-the-drm-coffin/?ref=technology|title=Sony Drives Another Nail in the D.R.M. Coffin|publisher=New York Times|date=January 10, 2008|accessdate=2008-01-12 | first=Saul | last=Hansell}}&lt;/ref&gt; All tracks were originally sold in 256 kilobits-per-second [[variable bitrate]] [[MP3]] format without per-customer [[watermark (data file)|watermarking]] or DRM; however some tracks are now watermarked.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.amazon.com/dp/B004BUKIK2#productDetails|title=Example of Product with Watermarking}}&lt;/ref&gt; Licensing agreements with recording companies restrict the countries in which music can be sold: Amazon.com only sells music to US customers while Amazon.co.uk only sells music to UK customers.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.amazon.com/gp/help/customer/display.html?nodeId=200154280 Amazon.com: Help &gt; Digital Products Help &gt; Amazon MP3 Music Downloads &gt; Amazon MP3 Music Terms of Use&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;

After the [[United States]], Amazon MP3 was launched in the [[United Kingdom]] on December 3, 2008, in [[Germany]] on April 1, 2009, and in [[France]] on June 10, 2009.&lt;ref name=&quot;afpfr&quot;&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.google.com/hostednews/afp/article/ALeqM5i-NTxsgt1Zq8xWeqGG83z0XpUfaw|title=Amazon lance sa boutique de musique en ligne en France|language=French|publisher=AFP|date=June 10, 2009|accessdate=2009-06-10}}&lt;/ref&gt; The German edition has been available in Austria and Switzerland since December 3, 2009.&lt;ref name=&quot;atch-avail&quot;&gt;{{cite news|url=http://crenk.com/amazon-mp3-music-store-launched-in-switzerland-and-austria/|title=Amazon MP3 Music Store Launched in Switzerland and Austria}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Amazon launched Amazon Cloud Player as an extension to Amazon MP3 store in the [[United States]] on March 29, 2011.

==Catalog availability==
At launch, Amazon offered &quot;over 2 million songs from more than 180,000 artists and over 20,000 labels, including [[EMI Music]] and [[Universal Music Group]]&quot;, to customers located in the United States only.&lt;ref name=&quot;launch-pr&quot; /&gt;  In December 2007 [[Warner Music]] announced that it would offer its catalog on Amazon MP3&lt;ref name=&quot;warner&quot;/&gt; and in January 2008, [[Sony Music Entertainment|Sony BMG]] followed suit.&lt;ref name=&quot;sony1&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;sony2&quot; /&gt;  The current catalog is 14.8 million songs.&lt;ref name=&quot;mp3clips&quot;&gt;[http://www.amazon.com/s?url=search-alias%3Ddigital-music&amp;field-keywords=&amp;x=14&amp;y=8 An empty search query on the Amazon MP3 website shows a catalog of 14.8 million songs]&lt;/ref&gt;

In January 2008, Amazon announced plans to roll Amazon MP3 out &quot;internationally&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;intl&quot;&gt;[http://phx.corporate-ir.net/phoenix.zhtml?c=176060&amp;p=irol-newsArticle&amp;ID=1100347 Amazon to Begin International Rollout of Amazon MP3 in 2008]&lt;/ref&gt; Amazon limits international access by checking users' credit card issued country. The first international version was launched December 3, 2008 in the [[United Kingdom]]. A German and then a French version of the store followed.

==Supported platforms==
Amazon MP3's catalog is accessible from the Amazon.com web site by searching for an artist or title name.  To download purchased music, Amazon.com offers the [http://www.amazon.com/gp/help/customer/display.html?nodeId=200154260 Amazon MP3 Downloader] which is optional for individual tracks and required for album purchases.  The Downloader is available for Windows (XP, Vista, or 7), Mac OS X 10.4 or higher, and Linux (packages are provided for [[Ubuntu (operating system)|Ubuntu]], [[Debian]], [[Fedora (operating system)|Fedora]] and [[openSUSE]]), although the Linux versions are not consistently updated to be compliant with the most recent releases and are not available for 64-bit architectures. Since March 2008 respectively December 2009 there exist the [[free software|free]] alternative downloaders ''clamz'' and ''pymazon'' for Linux.&lt;ref&gt;Dominik Wagenführ: ''[http://www.freiesmagazin.de/mobil/freiesMagazin-2010-09-bilder.html#10_09_amazon-mp3s MP3s von Amazon herunterladen].'' In: freiesMagazin, 2010-09, ISSN 1867-7991. Republished in a [http://www.linux-community.de/Internal/Artikel/Online-Artikel/MP3s-von-Amazon-im-AMZ-Format-herunterladen linux-community article]. Retrieved 2010-10-11.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[https://code.google.com/p/clamz/downloads/list clamz downloads] and [http://code.google.com/p/pymazon/source/list pymazon source]. Retrieved 2010-10-18.&lt;/ref&gt;

It saves purchased music into a particular folder and can, at the user's discretion, add purchased tracks to the library in [[Windows Media Player]] (Windows only) or [[iTunes]] (Windows and Mac OS X only) automatically after download.

An Amazon MP3 application for the [[Android (operating system)|Android]] operating system is preloaded on [[T-Mobile G1]] and [[Motorola Droid|Droid]] smartphones.  The application allows mobile phone users to download individual tracks and albums when on a Wi-Fi network.&lt;ref name=Hachman&gt;{{cite news|author=Hachman, Mark|title=Amazon Confirms Music Store for 'Google Phone'|url=http://www.pcmag.com/article2/0,2817,2330974,00.asp|date=September 23, 2008|work=PC Magazine|publisher=Ziff Davis|accessdate=2008-09-23}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=Yager&gt;{{cite news|author=Yager, Tom|title=Android to debut in T-Mobile's G1 smartphone|url=http://www.infoworld.com/article/08/09/23/Android_to_debut_in_T-Mobiles_G1_smartphone_1.html|date=September 23, 2008|work=InfoWorld|publisher=IDG|accessdate=2008-09-23}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Palm, Inc.|Palm]] phones based on [[webOS]] have a preloaded Amazon MP3 application as well&lt;ref name=&quot;palmpre&quot;&gt;[http://news.cnet.com/8301-13526_3-10141045-27.html Palm Pre: Where's the music?]&lt;/ref&gt; and users may download tracks over Wi-Fi or cellular networks. The Amazon MP3 app cannot be removed without rooting the phone and voiding its warranty.

The media management application [[doubleTwist]] for Mac OS X and Windows also has an integrated Amazon MP3 store which enables users to search, buy and sync MP3s directly to non-Apple devices.&lt;ref name=&quot;doubleTwist&quot;&gt;[http://www.suntimes.com/technology/ihnatko/1813418,ihnatko-doubletwist-android-music-100709.article The media management application doubleTwist for Mac OS X and WIndows has an integrated Amazon MP3 Store]&lt;/ref&gt;

==Partnerships==
On February 1, 2008, [[Pepsi]] introduced a [[Pepsi Stuff]] promotion in partnership with Amazon MP3.&lt;ref name=&quot;internetnews&quot;&gt;[http://www.internetnews.com/bus-news/article.php/3721576 Amazon, Pepsi Team For Super Bowl MP3 Giveaway]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Billboard&quot;&gt;[http://www.billboard.biz/bbbiz/content_display/industry/e3ib7d80868802f32c71a03013e01994297 Amazon, Pepsi Prep Massive MP3 Promotion]&lt;/ref&gt;  Customers can exchange points offered on 4 billion Pepsi bottles for, among other prizes, MP3 downloads from Warner, EMI, and Sony BMG (though not Universal).

[[Rockstar Games]]' 2008 title ''[[Grand Theft Auto IV]]'' connects to Amazon MP3.  Players can register on the [[Rockstar Games Social Club]] web site to receive e-mail outside the game containing a link to buy marked songs from Amazon MP3.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|date=2008-04-10|url=http://videogames.yahoo.com/events/grand-theft-auto-iv/gta-iv-unveils-new-music-download-model/1199430|title=GTA IV Unveils New Music Download Model|publisher=[[Yahoo!]]|accessdate=2008-04-10}}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[MySpace]] has sold music from Amazon MP3 as part of its MySpace Music feature since September 2008.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|author=Van Buskirk, Eliot|title=MySpace Takes On iTunes With DRM-Free, Amazon-Backed Site|url=http://blog.wired.com/music/2008/09/myspace-launche.html|date=September 24, 2008|work=Wired News|publisher=CondéNet|accessdate=2008-09-25}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Reaction==
Initial reaction to Amazon MP3 was generally positive. The unofficial Apple Weblog praised the lack of DRM especially given that track prices were cheaper than [[iTunes Plus]] songs at launch, but the reviewer considered the user experience better in iTunes than on the Amazon web site.&lt;ref name=&quot;tuaw&quot;&gt;[http://www.tuaw.com/2007/09/25/amazon-mp3-a-quick-review/ Amazon MP3: a quick review]&lt;/ref&gt;  [[Om Malik]] of [[GigaOM]] also praised the lack of DRM and the high bitrate but disliked the need to install another application to download albums.  Overall, the reviewer said &quot;…I think it makes sense for everyone to browse the Amazon store before hitting the 'buy' button on iTunes.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;gigaom&quot;&gt;[http://gigaom.com/2007/09/25/amazon-mp3-vs-apple-itunes-whos-better-now/ Amazon MP3 vs. Apple iTunes: Where Should You Shop?]&lt;/ref&gt;

A [[2007]] study by Eliot Van Buskirk of ''[[Wired News]]'''s &quot;Listening Post&quot; blog investigated whether Amazon MP3 was [[watermark (data file)|watermarking]] tracks with [[personally identifiable information]].  Van Buskirk quoted an Amazon spokesperson as saying, &quot;Amazon does not apply watermarks. Files are generally provided to us from the labels and some labels use watermarks to identify the retailer who sold the tracks (there is no information on the tracks that identifies the customer).&quot;  The study concluded that although tracks may be watermarked to indicate that they were purchased on Amazon MP3, there is no data to indicate which specific customer purchased a given MP3 file.&lt;ref name=&quot;wired&quot;&gt;[http://blog.wired.com/music/2007/09/some-of-amazons.html Some of Amazon's MP3 Tracks Contain Watermarks]&lt;/ref&gt; This observation reflected Amazon's policy at the time:&lt;ref name=&quot;wired&quot;&gt;[http://www.wired.com/listening_post/2007/09/some-of-amazons/ Some Of Amazon’s MP3 Tracks Contain Watermarks]&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;Amazon does not apply watermarks.
Files are generally provided to us from the labels and some labels use watermarks to identify the retailer who sold the tracks (there is no information on the tracks that identifies the customer).&lt;/blockquote&gt;

By [[2011]] however the policy had changed and certain explicitly labeled tracks embed &quot;Record Company Required Metadata&quot; including, among other information, unique identifiers:&lt;ref&gt;[http://webmink.com/2011/05/23/gagagate-drm-and-how-to-cripple-the-cloud/ GagaGate, DRM and How To Cripple The Cloud]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.amazon.com/gp/help/customer/display.html/ref=dm_adp_uits?ie=UTF8&amp;nodeId=200422000 Record Company Required Metadata]&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;Embedded in the metadata of each purchased MP3 from this record company are a random number Amazon assigns to your order, the Amazon store name, the purchase date and time, codes that identify the album and song (the UPC and ISRC), Amazon’s digital signature, and an identifier that can be used to determine whether the audio has been modified.  In addition, Amazon inserts the first part of the email address associated with your Amazon.com account&lt;/blockquote&gt;

==Amazon Cloud Drive/Player==

{{main|Amazon Cloud Drive}}
The Amazon Cloud Drive and Cloud Player are integrated with the MP3 store and allow users to store their music on [[Amazon Cloud Drive]], and play that music from any supported web browsers. Currently, Amazon Cloud Player is available on the website and within the Amazon MP3 Android application.

Amazon Cloud Player comes with Amazon MP3 Uploader which is an Adobe AIR application that allows a user to upload their [[iTunes]] library or [[Windows Media Player]] library to Amazon Cloud Drive.

==References==
{{reflist}}

==External links==
*[http://www.amazon.com/b?node=163856011 Official website], US
*[http://www.amazon.co.uk/b?node=77197031 Official website], UK
*[http://www.amazon.de/b?node=77195031 Official website], Germany
*[http://amazon.fr/b/?node=77196031 Official website], France
*{{twitter|amazonmp3}}

{{Amazon}}
{{Digital distribution platforms}}

[[Category:Amazon.com|MP3]]
[[Category:Online music stores]]
[[Category:Android software]]
[[Category:BlackBerry software]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
