<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="14967787" ns="0" title="Kaltura"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{advert|date=December 2010}}
{{Infobox Company
| name             = 
| logo             = [[File:Kaltura.png|200px]] 
| type             = Privately held
| genre            = 
| foundation       = 2006
| founder          = Ron Yekutiel, Shay David, Michal Tsur, and Eran Etam 
| location_city    = [[New York]]
| location_country = US
| location         = 
| locations        = 
| area_served      = 
| key_people       = 
| industry         = [[Social media]]
| products         = 
| services         =  Open Source Video Platform
| market cap       = 
| revenue          = 
| operating_income = 
| net_income       = 
| assets           = 
| equity           = 
| owner            = 
| num_employees    = 85 (as of summer 2010)&lt;ref name=&quot;urlConversation with Kaltura Founder Ron Yekutiel | CenterNetworks&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.centernetworks.com/conversation-with-kaltura-founder |title=Conversation with Kaltura Founder Ron Yekutiel | work=CenterNetworks |format= |accessdate=}}&lt;/ref&gt; 
| parent           = 
| divisions        = 
| subsid           = 
| homepage         = 
| footnotes        = 
| intl             = 
}}

'''Kaltura''' is a [[software company]] based in [[New York]] which was founded in  2006.&lt;ref name=&quot;urlConversation with Kaltura Founder Ron Yekutiel | CenterNetworks&quot;/&gt;

Kaltura's technology allows publishers and content owners to publish, manage, monetize and analyze their video and other rich-media content.  The main components of Kaltura's online video platform are based on [[open-source]] software, enabling any site to add advanced video and rich-media capabilities.

==Concept==
The original concept was built on the collaborative [[Wiki]] model but uses media rather than text.  Over time, the company changed its focus to providing an open source video platform with a focus on universities, enterprises, media companies and service providers looking to deploy video in their organizations. 

Publishers can add video capabilities using Kaltura’s hosted services, download the open source community edition, deploy the platform on-premise behind their own firewall, or on the cloud (such as Amazon Web Services). Kaltura also provides self-serve video packages for web-platforms such as [[MediaWiki]], [[WordPress]], [[Drupal]], [[Joomla]], etc.

==History==
Kaltura was founded in the fall of 2006 by Ron Yekutiel (CEO as of 2008), Dr. Shay David (VP of Community and Business Development as of 2008), Dr. Michal Tsur (a co-founder of [[Cyota]], President and COO as of 2008) and Eran Etam (a co-founder of [[ICQ]], Kaltura's CTO as of 2008).&lt;ref&gt;http://corp.kaltura.com/about/leadership (accessed August 6, 2008)&lt;/ref&gt;

Kaltura was launched at the [[TechCrunch40]] industry event in San Francisco on September 18, 2007, and won the People’s Choice award based on a vote of the conference's attendees.&lt;ref name=&quot;tc07&quot;&gt;Mark Hendrickson: [http://www.techcrunch.com/2007/09/18/kaltura-wins-spot-as-40th-company-at-techcrunch40/ Kaltura Wins Spot as 40th Company at TechCrunch40] [[TechCrunch]], September 18, 2007&lt;/ref&gt; At that time, the company had 20 employees, and had received 2.1 million dollars in funding from [[business angel]]s and Californian [[Venture capital|VC fund]] ''Avalon Ventures''.&lt;ref name=&quot;tc07&quot;/&gt;

On December 21, 2007, Kaltura won the People’s Choice award (over 250,000 users participated in voting) in the Video Sharing category for the [[Mashable]] Open Web Awards.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://mashable.com/2007/12/21/open-web-awards-winners/|date=2007-12-21|title=Open Web Awards: Final Winners Announced!|publisher=[[Mashable]]}}&lt;/ref&gt;  Also in 2007, Kaltura began a partnership with the [[New York Public Library]], whose team was headed by [[Joshua Greenberg]]. In 2008, Kaltura was selected as one of the &quot;Global 250 Winners&quot; by [[AlwaysOn]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://alwayson.goingon.com/permalink/post/27959 ''AO Global 250 Winners''] July 17, 2008&lt;/ref&gt; Kaltura CEO and cofounder Ron Yekutiel was photographed for the article &quot;The Suit, Vers. 3.0&quot; in [[Esquire Magazine]]'s July 2008 edition.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.esquire.com/style/fashion-story/suits-0708 The Suit, Version 3.0] ''Esquire Magazine'' online, July 7, 2008&lt;/ref&gt;

In January 2008, the [[Wikimedia Foundation]] and Kaltura announced that they had begun a collaboration aimed at bringing rich-media collaboration to [[Wikipedia]] and other wiki websites.&lt;ref&gt;[http://wikimediafoundation.org/wiki/Wikipedia_Invites_Users_to_Take_Part_in_Open%2C_Collaborative_Video_Experiment Wikipedia Invites Users to Take Part in Open, Collaborative Video Experiment]. Wikimedia press release, January 17, 2008&lt;/ref&gt;  The technology behind this project is a form of [[video-wiki]] software (open source and still in beta) that is integrated into the [[Mediawiki]] platform as an extension, allowing users to add collaborative video players that enable all users to add and edit images, sounds, diagrams, animations and movies in the same manner as they do today with text.

Kaltura was a sponsor of the [[Wikimania 2008]] event, where it announced that it is sponsoring Michael Dale, an open source video developer, to support the further development of a 100% open source video editing solution integrated into MediaWiki.&lt;ref&gt;http://blog.wikimedia.org/2008/07/23/kaltura-sponsors-michael-dale-open-source-video-developer/&lt;/ref&gt;

In addition to support of MediaWiki, Kaltura enables interactive videos integrated within popular CMS and blogging platforms such as [[WordPress]].

Kaltura is also a founder of the Open Video Alliance, a group of organizations, academics, artists and entrepreneurs, geared towards promoting open standards for video on the web.

== Products ==
{{Expand section|date=August 2008}}
Kaltura products include video players, video editors (including a collaborative video editor), a [[content management system]], a [[WordPress]] [[Plug-in (computing)|plugin]], a [[Drupal]] module, a [[Mediawiki]] extension,  and [[Ruby (programming language)|Ruby]] and [[PHP]] frameworks.
In essence, according to the company's website, Kaltura’s open-source video management platform enables organizations to deploy applications that involve video creation, ingestion, publishing, management, syndication, engagement, monetization and analysis.  Kaltura’s free community-supported self-hosted software and source-code is available at www.kaltura.org.  A commercial version of the software can be obtained at www.kaltura.com along with Kaltura services such as rich media streaming, hosting, transcoding, analytics, ad serving, support and maintenance packages, and professional development.   Kaltura’s Application Exchange enables software and service providers to market solutions that are integrated with Kaltura’s API.

==References==
{{reflist}}

==External links==
*[http://www.kaltura.com Kaltura - Open Source Video Platform]
*[[Yochai Benkler]]: [http://www.kaltura.com/blog/2007/10/17/love-or-money/ Love or money?], Kaltura's blog, October 17, 2007. Commentary by Professor Benkler (a Kaltura adviser) on Kaltura's view of the human motivation for creative online collaboration (see also [[Carr-Benkler wager]])
*''[http://wikimediafoundation.org/wiki/Wikipedia_Invites_Users_to_Take_Part_in_Open%2C_Collaborative_Video_Experiment Wikipedia Invites Users to Take Part in Open, Collaborative Video Experiment. Kaltura, Wikimedia Foundation and WikiEducator announce a beta program to allow users to create collaborative video and other forms of rich media]'' Press release, January 17, 2008
**[http://wikieducator.org/Help:Collaborative_video Wikieducator's Collaborative Video page]
**[http://wikimediafoundation.org/wiki/Collaborative_Video Wikimedia Foundation's Collaborative Video page]
*[http://sourceforge.net/projects/kaltura Kaltura's GPL licenced code at Sourceforge]
**[http://lists.wikimedia.org/pipermail/foundation-l/2008-January/037829.html Kaltura's software code hopes for 2008 according to its Chief Technical Officer]
*[http://sourceforge.net/project/showfiles.php?group_id=213701 Kaltura’s Video-wiki extension for the MediaWiki software]
*[http://wordpress.org/extend/plugins/all-in-one-video-pack/ Kaltura’s All-In-One Video Plugin for WordPress]
*[http://drupal.org/project/kaltura/ Kaltura’s All-In-One Video Plugin for Drupal]

;Articles
*[http://corp.kaltura.com/news Full news coverage on Kaltura’s corporate site]
*[http://www.techcrunch.com/2007/11/26/techcrunch40-presenters-traffic-two-months-in/ TechCrunch] November 26, 2007
*[http://www.cbronline.com/article_news.asp?guid=05DD3784-44A3-4DC1-9FC7-55A0AC5BBBB7 Computer Business Review] November 22, 2007
*[http://venturebeat.com/2007/09/18/mint-wins-techcrunch-latest-start-ups-mego-wixi-xtr3d-flowplay/ Venture Beat] September 28, 2007
*[http://blogs.zdnet.com/BTL/?p=6315 ZDNet] September 19, 2007
*[http://www.buzzmachine.com/2007/10/01/in-the-company-of-innovators/ BuzzMachine] October 1, 2007
*[http://blog.gartner.com/blog/media.php?itemid=2709 Gartner] 28 September 2007
*[http://mashable.com/2008/08/04/kaltura-wordpress/ Mashable] August 4, 2008
*[http://ostatic.com/165472-blog/kaltura-gets-funding-expands-its-open-source-video-efforts Ostatic] June 18, 2008
*[http://www.washingtonpost.com/wp-dyn/content/article/2008/06/18/AR2008061800732.html Washington Post] June 18, 2008
*[http://news.cnet.com/8301-13505_3-9918865-16.html CNET]  April 14, 2008

[[Category:Software companies of the United States]]
[[Category:Photography websites]]
[[Category:Social networking services]]
[[Category:Image hosting]]
[[Category:Video on demand services]]
[[Category:Video hosting]]
[[Category:Companies based in New York]]

[[es:Kaltura]]
[[eu:Kaltura]]
[[fr:Kaltura]]
[[it:Kaltura]]
[[he:קלטורה]]
[[ru:Kaltura]]
[[yi:קאלטורא]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
