<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><redirects><r from="Astros–Cardinals rivalry" to="Major League Baseball rivalries" /></redirects><pages><page pageid="30260811" ns="0" title="Major League Baseball rivalries"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">'''[[List of sports rivalries|Rivalries]]''' in '''[[Major League Baseball]]''' (MLB), like in other sports, have occurred between many teams and cities.  Rivalries have arisen for many different reasons, the primary ones include geographic proximity, familiarity with opponents, violence, and cultural, linguistic, or national pride.

[[Interleague play|Interleague]] rivalries can be inconsistently scheduled during the regular season and generally tend to be based on geographic proximity and previous [[World Series]] match-ups. An exception to this inconsistent scheduling is the eleven pairs of teams which meet six times a year during interleague play.

==Background==
{{see|Major League Baseball schedule}}
During the &quot;Original Sixteen&quot; era (1901 to 1960), there were eight teams in each league and teams in each league would play each other 22 times a season.&lt;ref name=&quot;OriginalSchedule&quot;&gt;{{cite news|title=Vote Unanimous on Ten-Club Plan|first=John|last=Drebinger|newspaper=New York Times|date=December 8, 1960|page=48}}&lt;/ref&gt; With the [[Texas Rangers (baseball)|Washington Senators]] (now the Texas Rangers) and [[Los Angeles Angels of Anaheim|Los Angeles Angels]] (now the Los Angeles Angels of Anaheim) entering play as expansion teams in {{mlby|1961}}, MLB increased the total number of games American League teams played to 162, which meant teams would play each other 18 times a season.&lt;ref name=&quot;OriginalSchedule&quot;/&gt; The [[National League]] didn't implement this until the following year when the [[New York Mets]] and the [[Houston Astros|Houston Colt 45's]] (now the Houston Astros) entered play.&lt;ref name=&quot;OriginalSchedule&quot;/&gt;

In {{mlby|1969}}, with the [[San Diego Padres]], [[Seattle Pilots]], [[Kansas City Royals]], and [[Montreal Expos]] entering play as expansion teams, MLB split both leagues into two divisions with six teams each.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title=Major Leagues Adopt 2-Division, 162-Game Format for 1969 Only|first=Leonard|last=Koppet|newspaper=New York Times|date=July 11, 1968|page=45}}&lt;/ref&gt; Teams would play a total of 90 intra-divisional games, playing teams within the division 18 times each and 72 inter-divisional games, playing each team in the other division 12 times.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title=New National League Format Has Cincinnati in West and St. Louis in East|newspaper=New York Times|date=February 9, 1969|page=S2}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Schedule&quot;&gt;{{cite news|title=NL Changes Format|date=September 3, 1992|agency=Associated Press}}&lt;/ref&gt; However, in {{mlby|1977}}, the addition of the [[Seattle Mariners]] and the [[Toronto Blue Jays]] reduced the total number of intra-divisional games American League teams played to 78, as each team would play each team within the division 13 times.&lt;ref name=&quot;Schedule&quot;/&gt; However, they would still play each team in the other division 12 times, but the total number of inter-divisional games increased to 84.&lt;ref name=&quot;Schedule&quot;/&gt; The National League didn't institute this until {{mlby|1993}}, when the [[Florida Marlins]] and [[Colorado Rockies]] entered play.&lt;ref name=&quot;Schedule&quot;/&gt;

In {{mlby|1994}}, MLB split each league into three divisions,&lt;ref name=PhilliesRealignment/&gt; but kept the 1993 format in scheduling.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title=Central and West teams are realignment winners|date=January 25, 1994|first=Hal|last=Bodley|newspaper=USA Today|page=5C}}&lt;/ref&gt; In {{mlby|1997}}, with the MLB adopting [[interleague play]],&lt;ref name=&quot;InterleaguePlay&quot;/&gt; the schedules were changed.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title=In '97, Let the Games (Between the Leagues) Begin|first=Murray|last=Chass|newspaper=New York Times|date=January 19, 1996|page=B9|url=http://www.nytimes.com/1996/01/19/sports/baseball-in-97-let-the-games-between-the-leagues-begin.html?pagewanted=print&amp;src=pm|accessdate=March 15, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; The schedule for interleague play comprises 84 three-game series, namely six series (18 games) for each of fourteen AL teams and as many as six for each of sixteen NL teams.

MLB changed its scheduling format in {{mlby|2001}}, further intensifying division matchups throughout the league.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.nytimes.com/2000/12/06/sports/baseball-division-race-just-got-harder-for-mets.html?pagewanted=print&amp;src=pm|title=Division Race Just Got Harder For Mets|date=December 6, 2000|accessdate=June 2, 2011|first=Murray|last=Chass|newspaper=New York Times}}&lt;/ref&gt; The new &quot;unbalanced schedule&quot; allowed for additional games in each season between divisional rivals, replacing additional series with teams outside the division.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://sportsillustrated.cnn.com/baseball/mlb/news/2001/03/20/unbalanced/|title=New schedule will make for some hot division races|last=Donovan|first=John|date=March 21, 2001|work=CNNSI.com|publisher=CNN/Sports Illustrated}}&lt;/ref&gt; Due to the change, division rivals now played each other 17 or more times each season.&lt;ref name=&quot;Enemies&quot;/&gt; The scheduling drew criticism both when it was enacted and after the fact, with some analysts even positing that the unbalanced schedule ''hurt'' intra-divisional play.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.baseballprospectus.com/article.php?articleid=2330|title=Checks and Balances: Looking at the Unbalanced Schedule|last=Click|first=James|date=September 19, 2003|publisher=Baseball Prospectus}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==American League==
===New York Yankees vs. Boston Red Sox===
{{main|Yankees–Red Sox rivalry}}
The Yankees – Red Sox rivalry is one of the oldest, most famous and fiercest [[List of sports rivalries|rivalries in professional sport]]s.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Shaughnessy|2005|page=21}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Frommer|Frommer|2004|page=78}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=UltimateRivalry&gt;{{cite news|title=Sport's ultimate rivalry; Yanks-Red Sox epic battles go way back|url=http://www.usatoday.com/sports/baseball/playoffs/2004-10-20-yanks-sox-rivalry_x.htm|date=October 21, 2004|accessdate=January 26, 2011|first=Hal|last=Bodley|newspaper=USA Today|page=October 21, 2004|page=3C}}&lt;/ref&gt; For over 100 years, the [[Boston Red Sox]] and [[New York Yankees]] have been intense rivals.&lt;ref name=&quot;Enemies&quot;&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.usatoday.com/sports/baseball/playoffs/2004-10-11-cover-rivalry_x.htm|title=Here they go again...; Red Sox vs. Yankees: Bitter enemies clash with Series on line|date=October 12, 2004|accessdate=January 27, 2011|first=Mike|last=Dodd|newspaper=USA Today|page=1C}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The rivalry is sometimes so polarizing that it is often a heated subject, like [[religion]] or [[politics]], in the [[Northeastern United States]].&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Shaughnessy|2005|page=19}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title=Sox-Yankees rivalry led to attack, police say|first=Michele|last=Richinick|newspaper=The Boston Globe|date=October 4, 2010|page=B2|url=http://www.boston.com/news/local/massachusetts/articles/2010/10/04/sox_yankees_rivalry_led_to_attack_police_say/}}&lt;/ref&gt; Since the inception of the [[Major League Baseball Wild Card|wild card]] team and an added Division Series, the [[American League East]] rivals have squared off in the [[American League Championship Series]] three times, with the Yankees winning twice in [[1999 American League Championship Series|1999]] and [[2003 American League Championship Series|2003]] and the Sox winning in [[2004 American League Championship Series|2004]].&lt;ref name=&quot;ALCS&quot;&gt;{{cite news|title=They Love to Hate Each Other; Red Sox and Yankees carry bitter rivalry into championship series that starts tonight|date=October 12, 2004|first=Mike|last=DiGiovanna|newspaper=Los Angeles Times|page=D1}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title=A World Series ticket; Sox complete comeback, oust Yankees for AL title|date=October 21, 2004|first=Dan|last=Shaughnessy|newspaper=The Boston Globe|page=A1|url=http://www.boston.com/sports/baseball/redsox/articles/2004/10/21/a_world_series_party/?page=full}}&lt;/ref&gt; In addition, the teams have twice met in the last regular-season series of a season to decide the league title, in {{mlby|1904}} (when the Red Sox won) and {{mlby|1949}} (when the Yankees won).&lt;ref name=&quot;ALCS&quot;/&gt;

The teams also finished tied for first in {{mlby|1978}}, when the Yankees won a high-profile [[1978 American League East tie-breaker game|one-game playoff]] for the division title.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Frommer|Frommer|2004|pages=177&amp;ndash;179}}&lt;/ref&gt; The 1978 division race is memorable for the Red Sox having held a 14-game lead over the Yankees more than halfway through the season.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Frommer|Frommer|2004|page=175}}&lt;/ref&gt; Similarly, the 2004 AL Championship Series is notable for the Yankees leading 3 games to 0 and ultimately losing a best of seven series.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title=Back From Dead, Red Sox Bury Yanks and Go to Series|first=Tyler|last=Kepner|newspaper=New York Times|date=October 21, 2004|page=A1}}&lt;/ref&gt; The Red Sox comeback was the only time in baseball history that a team has come back from a 0&amp;ndash;3 deficit to win a series.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title=Bruins' fall brings back memories of 2004|last=Rieber|first=Anthony|newspaper=Newsday|date=May 16, 2010|page=68|quote=The 2004 Yankees...are the only baseball team in history to lead a postseason series 3&amp;ndash;0 and not win it.}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The rivalry is often termed &quot;the best&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;CardinalsCubs&quot;/&gt; and &quot;greatest rivalry in all of sports.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|title=The rivals: the Boston Red Sox vs. the New York Yankees: an inside history|last=The New York Times|last2=The Boston Globe|location=New York|publisher=St. Martin's Press|year=2004|isbn=0-312-33616-0|edition=1st|authorlink=The New York Times|authorlink=The New York Times|authorlink2=The Boston Globe|page=1}}&lt;/ref&gt; Games between the two teams are often broadcast on national television, schedule permitting.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title=Yankees vs. Red Sox: Long-running drama|url=http://www.usatoday.com/SPORTS/usaedition/2010-05-07-yanksox07_cv_U.htm?csp=34|first=Jorge L.|last=Ortiz|newspaper=USA Today|date=May 7, 2010|page=1C}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==National League==
===National League Central===
====Chicago Cubs vs. St. Louis Cardinals====
{{main|Cardinals–Cubs rivalry}}
The Cardinals–Cubs rivalry refers to games between the [[St. Louis Cardinals]] and the [[Chicago Cubs]]. The rivalry is also known as the I-55 series (or in earlier years the Route 66 series), deriving its name from the roadway connecting the two cities, [[Interstate 55]] (which itself succeeded the famous [[U.S. Route 66]]). The Cubs lead the series 1,091&amp;ndash;1,044 through {{mlby|2010}},&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Head-to-Head results for Chicago Orphans and Chicago Cubs vs. St. Louis Cardinals from 1901 to 2010|url=http://www.baseball-reference.com/games/head2head-games.cgi?team1=CHC&amp;team2=STL&amp;from=1901&amp;to=2010|accessdate=January 11, 2011|publisher=Sports Reference LLC|work=baseball-reference.com}}&lt;/ref&gt; while the Cardinals lead in [[National League]] pennants with 18 against the Cubs' 16. However, the Cardinals have a clear edge when it comes to [[World Series]] successes, having won 11 championships to the Cubs' 2. Cardinals-Cubs games see numerous visiting fans in either St. Louis' [[Busch Stadium]] or Chicago's [[Wrigley Field]].&lt;ref name=CardinalsCubs&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.nesn.com/2011/01/cubs-cardinals-must-emulate-yankees-red-sox-to-rekindle-rivalry.html|title=Cubs, Cardinals Must Emulate Yankees, Red Sox to Rekindle Rivalry|date=January 12, 2011|accessdate=February 6, 2011|first=Tony|last=Lee|work=NESN}}&lt;/ref&gt; When the National League split into two, and then three divisions, the Cardinals and Cubs remained together. This has added excitement to several pennant races over the years, most recently in {{mlby|1989}}, {{mlby|2001}}, and {{mlby|2003}}; twice by the Cubs, and once a 1st place tie with [[Houston Astros|Houston]] by the Cardinals.

===National League West===
====Los Angeles Dodgers vs. San Francisco Giants====
{{main|Dodgers–Giants rivalry}}
The Dodgers–Giants rivalry is the longest-standing and one of the most storied rivalries in the [[history of baseball]].

The feud between the [[Los Angeles Dodgers]] and the [[San Francisco Giants]] began in the late 19th century when both clubs were based in [[New York City]], with the Dodgers playing in [[Brooklyn]] and the Giants playing at the [[Polo Grounds]] in [[Manhattan]]. After the {{mlby|1957}} season, Dodgers owner [[Walter O'Malley]] decided to move the team to [[Los Angeles]] for financial reasons, among others.&lt;ref name=MoveToCalifornia&gt;{{cite book|title=After many a summer: the passing of the Giants and Dodgers and a golden age in New York baseball|first=Robert|last=Murphy|year=2009|location=New York|publisher=Sterling|isbn=9781402760686}}&lt;/ref&gt; Along the way, he managed to convince Giants owner [[Horace Stoneham]] (who was considering moving his team to [[Minnesota]]) to preserve the rivalry by bringing his team to [[California]] as well.&lt;ref name=MoveToCalifornia/&gt; [[Sports in New York City|New York]] baseball fans were stunned and heartbroken by the move.&lt;ref name=MoveToCalifornia/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|title=The Dodgers move west: the transfer of the Brooklyn baseball franchise to Los Angeles|first=Neil J.|last=Sullivan|location=New York|publisher=Oxford University Press|year=1987|isbn=0195043669}}&lt;/ref&gt; Given that the cities of [[Los Angeles]] and [[San Francisco]] have long been competitors in economic, cultural, and political arenas, the new venue in California became fertile ground for its transplantation.

Each team's ability to have endured for over a century while leaping across an entire continent, as well as the rivalry's growth from a cross-city to a cross-state engagement, have led to the rivalry being considered one of the greatest in sports history.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title=The 10 greatest rivalries |url=http://espn.go.com/endofcentury/s/other/bestrivalries.html|date=January 3, 2000|work=ESPN.com}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|last=Caple|first=Jim |title=Giants-Dodgers best rivalry in baseball |url=http://static.espn.go.com/mlb/columns/caple_jim/1432476.html|date=September 16, 2002|work=ESPN.com}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|last=Beard |first=Donald |title=Giants-Dodgers Covers a Lot of Ground |url=http://www.washingtonpost.com/ac2/wp-dyn/A8285-2005Mar28?language=printer|date=March 30, 2005|newspaper=The Washington Post|page=H5}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Unlike many other historic baseball match-ups in which one team remains dominant for most of their history, the Dodgers–Giants rivalry has exhibited a persistent balance in the respective successes of the two teams. While the Giants have more wins in franchise history, both [[National League West]] teams are tied for the most National League pennants with 21,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://mlb.mlb.com/mlb/gameday/index.jsp?gid=2011_10_16_slnmlb_milmlb_1&amp;mode=recap_away&amp;c_id=stl|title=Take flight: Homers send Cards to Fall Classic|date=October 17, 2011|accessdate=October 17, 2011|first=Matthew|last=Leach|work=MLB.com|publisher=Major League Baseball}}&lt;/ref&gt; and both teams have each won six [[World Series]] titles. The [[2010 World Series]] was the Giants' first championship since moving to California, while the Dodgers' last title came in the [[1988 World Series]].

==Interleague==
===Background===
{{see|Interleague play}}
====Early discussions about interleague play====

Interleague or interconference matchups have long been the norm in other professional sports leagues such as the [[National Football League|NFL]].&lt;ref name=&quot;InterleaguePlay&quot;/&gt; Regular season interleague play was discussed for baseball's major leagues as early as the 1930s. In December 1956, Major League owners considered a proposal by [[Cleveland Indians|Cleveland]] general manager and minority-owner [[Hank Greenberg]] to implement limited interleague play beginning in 1958.&lt;ref name=&quot;InterlagueProposal&quot;&gt;{{cite news|title=Player Limit, Interleague Games Toy Issues on Majors' Agenda|first=John|last=Drebinger|newspaper=New York Times|date=December 9, 1956|page=235}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Under Greenberg's proposal, each team would continue to play 154-games in the season, 126 of which would be within the league, and 28 against the eight clubs. The interleague games would all be played during a period immediately following the All-Star Game. Notably, under Greenberg's proposal, all results would count in regular season game standings and league statistics.&lt;ref name=&quot;InterlagueProposal&quot;/&gt; While this proposal was not adopted, the current system shares many elements. [[Bill Veeck]] predicted in 1963 that Major League Baseball would someday have Interleague play.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|first=Hy|last=Hurwitz|title=Veeck Predicts Big Time Will Adopt Interloop Play|date=May 4, 1963|publisher=[[The Sporting News]]|pages=4}}&lt;/ref&gt; The concept did not take hold until the 1990s (at least in part as an effort to renew the public's interest in MLB following the [[1994–95 Major League Baseball strike|1994 players' strike]]).&lt;ref name=&quot;InterleaguePlay&quot;&gt;{{cite news|title=Owners Approve Interleague Play; Don't See DH as Problem|date=January 18, 1996|first=Ronald|last=Blum|agency=Associated Press}}&lt;/ref&gt;

====First Interleague games====

MLB's first regular season interleague game took place on June 12, 1997, when the [[Texas Rangers (baseball)|Texas Rangers]] hosted the [[San Francisco Giants]] at [[Rangers Ballpark in Arlington]].&lt;ref name=FirstGames&gt;{{cite news|title=Baseball Crosses Great Divide: AL 3, NL 1|first=Murray|last=Chass|newspaper=New York Times|date=June 13, 1997|page=B9}}&lt;/ref&gt; There were four interleague games on the schedule that night, but the other three were played on the West Coast, so the Giants–Rangers matchup started a few hours earlier than the others.&lt;ref name=FirstGames/&gt; Texas' [[Darren Oliver]] threw the game's first pitch and San Francisco outfielder [[Glenallen Hill]] was the first [[designated hitter]] used in a regular-season game by a [[National League]] team.&lt;ref name=FirstGames/&gt; San Francisco's [[Stan Javier]] hit the first home run in interleague play, and the Giants won the game, 4&amp;ndash;3.&lt;ref name=FirstGames/&gt;

For the first five seasons of Interleague Play, each division played against the same division from the other league (NL East vs. AL East, NL Central vs. AL Central and NL West vs. AL West), typically scheduled to alternate between home and away in consecutive years.&lt;ref name=&quot;Matchups&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://mlb.mlb.com/mlb/history/interleague/index.jsp|title=Interleague History|work=MLB.com|accessdate=May 20, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; However, in 2002, a new format to Interleague Play was instituted where teams play Interleague games against various divisions.&lt;ref name=&quot;Matchups&quot;/&gt; Matchups which had been of particular interest prior to this format—mainly geographic rivals—were preserved. This is expected to be the continuing format of the interleague schedule. Corresponding divisions however, were skipped once when this rotation began, but were put back in the rotation in 2006.

Since 2002, all interleague games have been played prior to the [[Major League Baseball All-Star Game|All-Star Game]]. Most games are played in June, though May games have been scheduled since 2005. Among the 224 interleague pairs of teams, 11 play six games every year, which are scheduled in two three-game series &quot;home and home,&quot; or one at each home ballpark. Five of these matches feature two teams in the same city or in neighboring cities, where they wholly or partly share territorial rights. Six are regional matches at greater distance, four of which are in the same state.

===New York Yankees vs. Brooklyn/Los Angeles Dodgers===
{{main|Yankees–Dodgers rivalry}}
The [[New York Yankees|Yankees]]–[[Los Angeles Dodgers|Dodgers]] rivalry is one of the most well-known rivalries in Major League Baseball.&lt;ref name=YankeesDodgers&gt;{{cite news|title=Oscars of interleague: Stars coming out for Yankees-Dodgers|date=June 25, 2010|first=Bob|last=Nightengale|newspaper=USA Today|page=C4|url=http://www.usatoday.com/sports/baseball/2010-06-24-yankees-dodgers-preview_N.htm}}&lt;/ref&gt; The two teams have met 11 times in the [[World Series]], more times than any other pair of teams from the [[American League|American]] and [[National League]]s.&lt;ref name=YankeesDodgers/&gt; The initial significance was embodied in the two teams' proximity in [[New York City]], when the Dodgers initially played in [[Brooklyn]]. After the Dodgers moved to [[Los Angeles]] in {{by|1958}}, the rivalry retained its significance as the two teams represented the dominant cities on each coast of the [[United States]], and [[Largest cities in the United States by population by decade|since the 1980s]], the two largest cities in the United States.

Although the rivalry's significance arose from the two teams' numerous World Series meetings,&lt;ref name=YankeesDodgers/&gt; the Yankees and Dodgers have not met in the World Series since {{wsy|1981}}.&lt;ref name=YankeesDodgers/&gt; They would not play each other in a non-exhibition game until 2004, when they played a 3-game [[Interleague play|interleague]] series.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title=Dodgers play host to Yankees in classic old-rivalry series|first=Mel|last=Antonen|newspaper=USA Today|date=June 18, 2004|page=C1}}&lt;/ref&gt; Their last meeting was in June 2010.&lt;ref name=YankeesDodgers/&gt;

===Bay Bridge Series: Oakland Athletics vs. San Francisco Giants===
{{main|Bay Bridge Series}}
The Bay Bridge Series is the name of a series games played between&amp;mdash;and the rivalry of&amp;mdash;the [[Oakland Athletics]] of the [[American League]] and [[San Francisco Giants]] of the [[National League]]. The series takes its name from the [[San Francisco – Oakland Bay Bridge]] which links the cities of [[Oakland, California|Oakland]] and [[San Francisco]]. Although competitive, the regional rivalry between the A's and Giants is considered a friendly one with mostly mutual companionship between the fans, as opposed to [[White Sox – Cubs rivalry|White Sox–Cubs]], or [[Mets–Yankees rivalry|Yankees–Mets]] games where animosity runs high. While many fans have a very strong dislike for the other team, some others actually like both. Bay Area baseball fans tend to disagree with each other on this topic. 

The series is also occasionally referred to as the &quot;BART Series&quot; for the [[Bay Area Rapid Transit]] system that links Oakland to San Francisco. However, the name &quot;BART Series&quot; has never been popular beyond a small selection of history books and national broadcasters and has fallen out of favor. Bay Area locals almost exclusively refer to the rivalry as the &quot;Bay Bridge Series&quot;.

Originally, the term described a series of exhibition games played between the two clubs after the conclusion of [[spring training]], immediately prior to the start of the regular season. It was first used to refer to the [[1989 World Series]] in which the Athletics won their most recent championship and the first time both teams had met since they moved to the [[San Francisco Bay Area]]. Today, it also refers to games played between the teams during the regular season since the commencement of [[interleague play]] in 1997. Through May 22, 2011, the A's have won 42 games, and the Giants have won 41.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.baseball-reference.com/games/head2head.cgi?teams=OAK&amp;from=1997&amp;to=2009&amp;submit=Submit|work=baseball-reference.com|title=Head-to-Head record for Oakland Athletics against the listed opponents from 1997 to 2009|publisher=Sports Reference LLC.}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Crosstown Classic: Chicago Cubs vs. Chicago White Sox===
{{main|White Sox–Cubs rivalry}}
The White Sox-Cubs Rivalry (also known as the BP Crosstown Cup, Crosstown Classic, The Windy City Showdown,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Buehrle Opens Windy City Showdown|first=Scott|last=Merkin|work=MLB.com|publisher=WhiteSox.com|date=June 21, 2007|url=http://chicago.whitesox.mlb.com/news/print.jspymd=20070620&amp;content_id=2038439&amp;vkey=news_cws&amp;fext=.jsp&amp;c_id=cws&amp;affiliateId=CommentWidget}}&lt;/ref&gt; Red Line Series, City Series, Crosstown Series,&lt;ref name=&quot;USAToday&quot;&gt;{{cite news| last=Dodd|first=Mike|first2=Judy|last2=Keen|title=There Are Two Sides To the Story for Cubs and White Sox Fans|newspaper=USA Today|date=October 3, 2008|url=http://www.usatoday.com/sports/baseball/playoffs/2008-10-03-chicago-fans_N.htm|}}&lt;/ref&gt; Crosstown Cup or Crosstown Showdown&lt;ref name=&quot;USAToday&quot;/&gt;) refers to the rivalry between two [[Major League Baseball]] teams that play their home games in [[Chicago]], [[Illinois]]. The [[Chicago Cubs]] of the [[National League]] play their home games at [[Wrigley Field]] located on the city's [[North Side, Chicago|North side]], while the [[Chicago White Sox]] of the [[American League]] play their home games at [[U.S. Cellular Field]] on the city's [[South side (Chicago)|South side]].

The terms &quot;North Siders&quot; and &quot;South Siders&quot; are synonymous with the respective teams and their fans, setting up an enduring rivalry. The White Sox currently lead the regular season series 41–37. There have been six series sweeps since interleague play began: four by the Cubs in 1998, 2004, 2007, and 2008, and two by the White Sox in 1999 and 2008. The [[Chicago Transit Authority]]'s [[Red Line (Chicago Transit Authority)|Red Line]] runs north-south through Chicago's [[Neighborhoods of Chicago|neighborhoods]], stopping at [[Wrigley Field]] and [[U.S. Cellular Field]].

===Subway Series: New York Mets vs. New York Yankees===
{{main|Mets–Yankees rivalry}}
The New York Mets – New York Yankees rivalry is the latest incarnation of the [[Subway Series]], the competition between [[New York City]]'s Major League Baseball teams, the [[American League]] Yankees and the [[National League]] Mets. Until [[Interleague play]] started, the two teams had only met in exhibition games. Since the inception of interleague play the teams have met in every season since 1997 and faced off in the [[2000 World Series]].

==Historical==
===New York Yankees vs. New York/San Francisco Giants===
{{main|Yankees–Giants rivalry}}
The rivalry between the [[History of the New York Giants (NL)|New York Giants]] and the [[New York Yankees]] was intense as both teams not only inhabited [[New York City]] but also, for a time, the same ball park.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|title=1921: The Yankees, the Giants, and the Battle for Baseball Supremacy in New York|first=Lyle|last=Spatz|first2=Steve|last2=Steinberg|year=2010|publisher=University of Nebraska Press|location=Lincoln, Ne.}}&lt;/ref&gt; During that era the opportunities for them to meet could only have been in a [[World Series]]. Both teams kicked off the first [[Subway Series]] between the [[National League]] and the [[American League]] in 1921.

===Cincinnati Reds vs. Los Angeles Dodgers===
The rivalry between the [[Cincinnati Reds]] and the [[Los Angeles Dodgers]] was one of the most intense match-ups in Baseball during the 1970's and 1980's. They often competed for the NL West division title. From 1970 through 1990 they had eleven 1-2 finishes in the standings, with seven of them being within {{frac|5|1|2}} games or fewer. Both teams also played in numerous championships during this span, combining to win 10 NL Pennants and 5 World Series titles from {{wsy|1970}} to {{wsy|1990}}. Reds Manager [[Sparky Anderson]] once said, &quot;I don't think there's a rivalry like ours in either league. The Giants are supposed to be the Dodgers' natural rivals, but I don't think the feeling is there anymore. It's not there the way it is with us and the Dodgers.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|url=http://cnnsi.printthis.clickability.com/pt/cpt?expire=&amp;title=Los+Angeles+and+Cincinnati+have+the+most+inflammatory+-+04.28.75+-+SI+Vault&amp;urlID=455502997&amp;action=cpt&amp;partnerID=289881&amp;fb=Y&amp;url=http%3A%2F%2Fsportsillustrated.cnn.com%2Fvault%2Farticle%2Fmagazine%2FMAG1089769%2Findex.htm%257Ctitle%3DWhere|title=Where There's Smoke There's Ire|date=April 28, 1975|first=Ron|last=Fimrite|journal=Sports Illustrated}}&lt;/ref&gt; The rivalry ended when division realignment moved the Reds to the NL Central. However, they did face one another in the [[1995 National League Division Series|1995 NLDS]].

===Philadelphia Phillies vs. Pittsburgh Pirates===
{{main|Phillies–Pirates rivalry}}
The rivalry between the [[Philadelphia Phillies]] and the [[Pittsburgh Pirates]] was considered by some to be one of the best rivalries in the [[National League]].&lt;ref name=Forbes&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.forbes.com/2009/04/28/baseball-best-rivalries-lifestyle-sports-baseball.html|title=In Depth: Baseball's Most Intense Rivalries|publisher=Forbes|first=Matt|last=Woolsey|date=April 28, 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=LostRivalry&gt;{{cite news|title=Pirates&amp;mdash;Phillies: A Rivalry Lost and Missed|date=July 4, 2005|first=Gene|last=Collier|newspaper=Pittsburgh Post-Gazette|page=D1}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=PhilliesPirates&gt;{{cite web|url=http://philadelphia.phillies.mlb.com/news/article.jsp?ymd=20050707&amp;content_id=1119893&amp;vkey=news_phi&amp;fext=.jsp&amp;c_id=phi|title=Notes: Phils–Pirates rivalry fading|date=July 7, 2005|accessdate=January 3, 2011|first=George|last=Von Benko|work=Phillies.MLB.com|publisher=Major League Baseball}}&lt;/ref&gt; The rivalry started when the Pittsburgh Pirates entered play in 1887, four years after the Phillies.&lt;ref name=PhilliesRealignment&gt;{{cite news|title=Baseball Owners Vote to Break Each League Into Three Divisions|date=September 10, 1993|first=Jayson|last=Stark|newspaper=Philadelphia Inquirer|page=A1|authorlink=Jayson Stark}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The Phillies and the Pirates had remained together after the National League split into two divisions in {{mlby|1969}}. During the period of two-division play (1969 to {{mlby|1993}}), the two [[National League East]] division rivals won the two highest numbers of division championships, the Pirates 9, the Phillies 6; together, the two teams' 15 championships accounted for more than half of the 25 NL East championships during that span.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title=Pirates, Phillies Have Owned the Outgoing NL East Division|date=September 27, 1993|first=Gene|last=Collier|newspaper=Pittsburgh Post-Gazette|page=D1}}&lt;/ref&gt;

However, after the Pirates moved to the [[National League Central]] in {{mlby|1994}}, the rivalry came to an end. The teams have since faced each other only in two series per year and the rivalry has effectively died in the intervening years since division realignment moved the Pirates out of the NL East.&lt;ref name=LostRivalry/&gt;&lt;ref name=PhilliesPirates/&gt;

== See also ==
*[[List of sports rivalries]]
*[[Major League Baseball]]

==External links==
*[http://www.retrosheet.org/Regional%20Series/ Regional Postseason Series], Retrosheet

==References==
;Inline citations
{{reflist}}

;Bibliography
*{{cite book|title=Red Sox vs. Yankees: The Great Rivalry|first=Harvey|last=Frommer|first2=Frederic J.|last2=Frommer|publisher=Sports Publishing, LLC|year=2004|isbn=1-58261-767-8}}
*{{cite book|last=Shaughnessy|first=Dan|title=Reversing the [[Curse of the Bambino|Curse]]|year=2005|publisher=Houghton Mifflin Company|location=Boston|isbn=0-618-51748-0|authorlink=Dan Shaughnessy}}

{{MLB}}
{{MLB rivalries}}
{{Subway Series}}
[[Category:Major League Baseball lists|Rivalries]]
[[Category:Major League Baseball rivalries| ]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
