<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="15003674" ns="0" title="Dudu Nobre"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Infobox musical artist &lt;!-- See Wikipedia:WikiProject_Musicians --&gt;
| name                = Dudu Nobre
| image               = 
| caption             = 
| image_size          = 
| background          = solo_singer
| birth_name          = João Eduardo de Salles Nobre
| alias               = 
| birth_date                = {{Birth date and age|1974|11|6|mf=y}}
| death_date          = 
| origin              = [[Image:Flag of Brazil.svg|25px|Brazilian flag]] [[Brazil]]
| instrument          = 
| genre               = [[Samba]], [[pagode]]
| occupation          = 
| years_active        = 
| label               = 
| associated_acts     = 
| website             = 
| notable_instruments = 
}}

'''João Eduardo de Salles Nobre''', known as '''Dudu Nobre''' ([[Rio de Janeiro (city)|Rio de Janeiro, RJ]], November 6 of 1974), is a [[Brazil]]ian [[composer]] and [[singer]].

== Biography ==
He is the son of the [[Engineering|engineer]] João Nobre and of Anita Nobre. His mother, Anita Nobre, controlled three [[pagode]] bands, where Dudu, already in his infancy, used to play with tam-tam and [[pandeiro]] with the same ease that his neighbors were applied in marbles. And he did not reject this apprenticeship in his backyard.&lt;ref name=pla020885&gt;{{pt icon}} [http://www.dudunobre.com.br/?sec_atual=11 Official Site]&lt;/ref&gt;
As a result, when he was six years old, he started to study classic [[piano]], and when he was nine he received the instrument that would never separate from him—the [[cavaquinho]].&lt;ref name=pla020885/&gt;

When Dudu was ten years old, he iniciated his career in the samba schools for beginners. There he met the mythical Beto &quot;''Sem Braço''&quot; (Without arm) and the two starred in the [[samba-enredo]] of Alegria da Passarela, a school that later became Aprendizes do Salgueiro, the school for beginners owned by [[GRES Acadêmicos do Salgueiro]]. &quot;Beto was one of the most experienced (''sambistas'') that I ever knew,&quot; Dudu cites in his official site.&lt;ref name=pla020885/&gt; 

After this he attributed credit to three sambas in Aprendizes do Salgueiro, another in Herdeiros da Vila, and one more in Estrelinha da Mocidade and also in Império do Futuro. This as an adolescent composer. 

As a musician, when he was thirteen he made a cycle of shows with [[Mocidade Independente de Padre Miguel]] and when he was 15 he rotated in [[Switzerland]], [[Finland]], [[England]], and [[Germany]], with Cia. Brasiliana.&lt;ref name=pla020885/&gt;

Back in Brazil, he joined the band of [[Almir Guineto]] and later played with Dicró and Pedrinho da Flor. When Dudu was 19 years old, he joined the band of [[Zeca Pagodinho]], same epoch when Dudu entered into the Law Faculty. The advocacy was repealed in the fifth year.&lt;ref name=pla020885/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.getmein.com/world-music/dudu-nobre-1/info.html Getmein]&lt;/ref&gt; 

Dudu writes that &quot;Zeca is a godfather. And he tells me that the samba is a passion and that I was chosen by the samba&quot;.&lt;ref name=pla020885/&gt;
 
Dudu was married with the model and dancer [[Adriana Bombom]] and has two daughters: Olivia and Thalita.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.imdb.com/name/nm1658494/bio IMBD]&lt;/ref&gt; They got divorced in 2009.&lt;ref&gt;[http://ego.globo.com/Gente/Noticias/0,,MUL1282035-9798,00-DUDU+NOBRE+CONFIRMA+AFASTAMENTO+DE+ADRIANA+BOMBOM+AGORA+E+NOTORIO.html Dudu Nobre confirma afastamento de Adriana Bombom: ‘Agora é notório’]&lt;/ref&gt; He is the brother of the standard bearer Lucinha Nobre.

== Compositions ==
Among the musics that really succeeded, are detached:

# ''Vou botar teu nome na macumba'' (I am going to put your name in the [[macumba]]);
# ''Posso até me apaixonar'' (I can even fall in love);
# ''...São Jorge, Anastácia e as crianças'' (...[[Saint George]], Anastsia, and the children);
# ''Água da Minha Sede'' (Water of my thirst);
# ''Pro Amor Render'' (Fot the love to surrender);
# ''Chegue Mais'' (Arrive more).

== References ==
{{reflist}}

{{Persondata &lt;!-- Metadata: see [[Wikipedia:Persondata]]. --&gt;
| NAME              =Nobre, Dudu
| ALTERNATIVE NAMES =
| SHORT DESCRIPTION =
| DATE OF BIRTH     =November 6, 1974
| PLACE OF BIRTH    =
| DATE OF DEATH     =
| PLACE OF DEATH    =
}}
{{DEFAULTSORT:Nobre, Dudu}}
[[Category:1974 births]]
[[Category:Living people]]
[[Category:Brazilian composers]]
[[Category:Brazilian singers]]

[[pt:Dudu Nobre]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
