<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="15051916" ns="0" title="Marols"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{dablink|For the town in France, see [[Marols, Loire]].}}
[[Image:1939 les Marolles derrière le Palais de Justice dessin par Léon van Dievoet 13 juillet 1939.JPG|thumb|350px|right|Sketch of the district of Marollen in 1939 by Léon van Dievoet.]]

'''Marols''' or '''Marollien''' (also known as ''Brusselse Sproek'', ''brusseler, brusseleir, brusselair'' or ''brusseleer'' &lt;ref name=evans&gt; Mary Anne Evans, ''Frommer's Brussels and Bruges Day by Day. First Edition'' (Hoboken: John Wiley &amp; Sons, 2008), 71.&lt;/ref&gt;) was a [[dialect]] spoken in [[Brussels]].  Essentially it is a [[Dutch language|Dutch]] [[dialect]] incorporating many words of [[French language|French]] origin as well as a sprinkling of [[Spanish language|Spanish]] dating back to the rule of the [[Spanish Netherlands|Low Countries]] by the [[Habsburgs]] (1519-1713).  Its name refers to a district of Brussels called [[Marollen]] (Marolles), a neighborhood in the central municipality of Brussels, not far from the [[Law Courts of Brussels|Palace of Justice]].  The district takes its name from the former [[abbey]] of the [[nuns]] Maria Colentes (''Marikollen'').  It was a working-class neighborhood, though now it has become a fashionable part of the city. Marols is described as &quot;totally indecipherable to the foreigner (which covers everyone not born in the Marolles) which is probably a good thing as it is richly abusive.&quot;&lt;ref name=evans/&gt; 

The Théâtre Royal de Toone in Brussels puts on [[puppet]] plays in Marols.&lt;ref name=evans/&gt;

==What is Marols?==
There is much confusion about the meaning of Marols, which is considered by many people to be distinctive from Brussels Dutch.&lt;ref&gt;Jeanine Treffers-Daller, ''Mixing Two Languages: French-Dutch Contact in a Comparative Perspective'' (Walter de Gruyter, 1994), 25.&lt;/ref&gt;  According to Jeanine Treffers-Daller, “the dialect has a tremendous prestige and a lot of myths are doing the rounds.”&lt;ref&gt;Jeanine Treffers-Daller, ''Mixing Two Languages: French-Dutch Contact in a Comparative Perspective'' (Walter de Gruyter, 1994), 25.&lt;/ref&gt;

{{Quotation|If you ask ten Brusselers what “Marollien” is, you get ten different answers.  For some people it is French contaminated by Flemish and spoken in the neighborhood of the rue Haute and the rue Blaes, whereas for others it is Frenchified Flemish.  Still others say that it is a vernacular variety of French, spoken in the whole cit, etc., etc.  Marollien, however, is exceptional if not unique, because it is a double language.  In fact it is not between the germanic and romance languages, it is both.|Jacques Pohl, 1953| &lt;ref&gt;Quoted Jeanine Treffers-Daller, Mixing Two Languages: French-Dutch Contact in a Comparative Perspective (Walter de Gruyter, 1994), 25.&lt;/ref&gt;}}

==Examples==
An example of Marols is:
   
{{Quotation|Na mooie ni paaze da'k ee da poèzeke em zitte deklameire /
Allien mo vè aile 't amuzeire / Neineie... ik em aile wille demonsteire / Dat as er zain dee uile me konviksen e stuk in uilen uur drinke. / Dat da ni seulement en allien es vè te drinke.|&lt;ref&gt;[http://listserv.linguistlist.org/cgi-bin/wa?A2=ind9908D&amp;L=lowlands-l&amp;P=1132 LOWLANDS-L archives - August 1999, week 4 (#9)&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;|}}

==Marols and ''[[The Adventures of Tintin|Tintin]]''==
[[Image:Coat of Arms of Syldavia.png|thumb|200px|right|The coat-of-arms of [[Syldavia]] features a motto in [[Syldavian]], which is based on Marols. It reads ''Eih bennek, eih blavek'', in [[English language|English]]: (&quot;Here I am, here I stay&quot;).]]
For the popular Belgian [[comic]] series [[The Adventures of Tintin|Tintin]], the author [[Hergé]] modeled his fictional languages [[Syldavian]]&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.zompist.com/syldavian.html Hergé's Syldavian&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt; and [[Bordurian]] on Marols, and modeled many other personal and place-names in his works on the dialect (e.g. the city of Khemkhâh in the fictional [[Middle Eastern]] country of Khemed comes from the Marols phrase for &quot;I'm cold&quot;).  Bordurian, for example, has as one of its words the Marols-based &quot;mänhir&quot;, meaning &quot;mister&quot; (cf. [[Dutch language|Dutch]] &quot;mijnheer&quot;).  In the original French, the fictional Arumbaya language of [[San Theodoros]] is another incarnation of Marols.

== References ==
{{Reflist}}


{{ie-lang-stub}}

[[Category:Dialects]]
[[Category:History of Belgium]]
[[Category:Culture in Brussels]]
[[Category:Dutch language]]
[[Category:Languages of Belgium]]
[[Category:Languages of the Netherlands]]
[[Category:Tintin]]

[[ru:Марольский социолект]]
[[eo:Brusela lingvo]]
[[nl:Brussels (dialect)]]
[[ro:Limba brusselară]]
[[fr:Brusseleer]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
