<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="15065624" ns="0" title="William &amp; Mary Tribe"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Infobox college athletics
|name             = William &amp; Mary Tribe
|logo             = 
|logo_width       = 130
|university       = The College of William &amp; Mary
|conference       = [[Colonial Athletic Association]]&lt;br&gt;[[Eastern Intercollegiate Gymnastics League]]
|association      = [[National Collegiate Athletic Association|NCAA]]
|division         = [[Division I (NCAA)|Division I]]
|director         = [[Terry Driscoll]]
|city             = Williamsburg
|state            = Virginia
|stateabb         = VA
|teams            = 23
|stadium          = [[Zable Stadium]]
|baseballfield    = [[Plumeri Park]]
|soccerlacrossestadium = [[Albert-Daly Field]]
|arena            = [[Kaplan Arena]]
|arena2           = [[McCormack-Nagelsen Tennis Center]]
|mascot           = Griffin
|nickname         = Tribe
|fightsong        = ''[[Tribe Fight Song]]''
|color1           = [[Green]]
|color2           = [[Gold]]
|hex1             = 006400
|hex2             = FFD700
|pageurl          = http://www.tribeathletics.com/
|pagename         = Tribe Athletics
|}}

The '''William &amp; Mary Tribe''' are the athletic teams for the [[College of William &amp; Mary]]. The name Tribe now refers to the unity and comradery that William &amp; Mary student-athletes share when competing in the classroom and on the field. William &amp; Mary has transitioned through several official nicknames since its athletic program began in 1893. From 1893 to 1909, William &amp; Mary football players were known as the '''Orange and White''' because those were the old official school colors. From 1910 to 1916, the team colors changed to orange and black, leading to a change in nickname to &quot;The Orange and Black.&quot; From 1916 to the mid-1980's, William &amp; Mary athletic teams were referred to as the '''Indians'''.   And, most recently, from 1978 to the present day they have been known as the '''Tribe'''.

During the 2006-07 school year, then-College President [[Gene Nichol]] chose to remove the two tribal feathers from William &amp; Mary’s logo due to [[NCAA]] regulations. On April 6, 2010, it was revealed that a [[griffin]] would become the new mascot.

William &amp; Mary has won two team national championships (both in men’s [[tennis]]), the AIAW championships in women's golf, the NAIA championships in women's gymnastics, thirteen USA Gymnastics Collegiate Championships, and many individual national championships. The College has more conference championships than any other school in the Colonial Athletic Association. As of the end of the 2004-05 academic year, the Tribe had won 84 conference championships. Dating back to the athletic program’s beginning, there have been over 142 conference titles in all.

==Baseball==
In the 1960s [[Joe Plumeri]], future Chairman &amp; CEO of [[Willis Group Holdings]] and owner of the [[Trenton Thunder]], who later donated $2 million to build the team's [[Plumeri Park]], played on the baseball team as a second baseman and outfielder.&lt;ref name=&quot;autogenerated2&quot;&gt;{{cite news|url=http://web.wm.edu/news/archive/index.php?id=6860|author=Ben Kennedy |title=Plumeri tapped to lead homecoming parade  |publisher=W&amp;M Alumni Magazine|date=October 9, 2006|accessdate=July 15, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;nytimes1&quot;&gt;{{cite news|last=Treaster |first=Joseph B. |url=http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9803E6D61E31F934A15751C1A9609C8B63&amp;sec=&amp;spon=&amp;pagewanted=2 |title=Corporate Insurance Underdog Ramps Up for Challenge |publisher=The New York Times |date=December 27, 2006 |accessdate=July 15, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=autogenerated4&gt;[http://www.tribeathletics.com/story.php/1344/ &quot;Plumeri Park&quot;], TribeAthletics.com, accessed July 16, 2010&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=autogenerated4&gt;[http://www.tribeathletics.com/story.php/1344/ &quot;Plumeri Park&quot;], TribeAthletics.com, accessed July 16, 2010&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;&lt;/ref&gt;   Plumeri also funded the Joseph J. Plumeri Endowment Fund for baseball scholarships for the school.&lt;ref name=autogenerated4 /&gt;  The baseball team qualified for the [[NCAA Division I Baseball Championship]] in 1983 and 2001.

==Football==
{{main|William &amp; Mary Tribe football}}
The football team has won eight conference championships. While a member of the [[Southern Conference]], W&amp;M were champions or co-champions in 1942, 1947, 1966, and 1970. In the 1960s, future [[Willis Group Holdings]] Chairman &amp; CEO [[Joe Plumeri]] played on the football team on scholarship as a [[Halfback (American football)|halfback]] for [[Lou Holtz]].&lt;ref name=&quot;autogenerated2&quot;&gt;{{cite news|url=http://web.wm.edu/news/archive/index.php?id=6860|author=Ben Kennedy |title=Plumeri tapped to lead homecoming parade  |publisher=W&amp;M Alumni Magazine|date=October 9, 2006|accessdate=July 15, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;nytimes1&quot;&gt;{{cite news|last=Treaster |first=Joseph B. |url=http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9803E6D61E31F934A15751C1A9609C8B63&amp;sec=&amp;spon=&amp;pagewanted=2 |title=Corporate Insurance Underdog Ramps Up for Challenge |publisher=The New York Times |date=December 27, 2006 |accessdate=July 15, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=autogenerated4&gt;[http://www.tribeathletics.com/story.php/1344/ &quot;Plumeri Park&quot;], TribeAthletics.com, accessed July 16, 2010&lt;/ref&gt;  After joining the [[Yankee Conference]], the Tribe won the Mid-Atlantic Division in 1993 and won the conference championship in 1996. After the Yankee Conference's 1997 merger with the [[Atlantic 10 Conference|A-10 Conference]], the Tribe were co-champions in 2001 and 2004. After the [[Colonial Athletic Association]] began sponsoring football with the 2007 season, the Tribe were co-champions in 2010.

The 2004 season saw William &amp; Mary reach the Division I-AA national semi-finals before finally falling to rival [[James Madison University]].

In 2008, the Tribe played [[Richmond Spiders football|Richmond]], at home, on the very last game of the season. Both teams entered the game needing a win to secure a playoff spot, while the loser would not reach the postseason. William &amp; Mary trailed by 14 points going into the 4th quarter but made a huge comeback (largely due to [[Derek Cox]]) to send the game into overtime. After failing to convert a field goal themselves, the Tribe would go on to lose the game by a field goal. William &amp; Mary missed the playoffs because of it. Richmond, however, would go on an improbable run to win the [[NCAA Division I Football Championship]] by defeating the University of Montana 24–7.

In 2009, the Tribe played their academic rivals, the [[Virginia Cavaliers football|Virginia Cavaliers]] (UVA), in a season opening match-up for both schools in [[Charlottesville, Virginia|Charlottesville]] for the first time since 1986. The Tribe upset Virginia 16–14. It was the second Tribe win over UVA in as many tries and mirrored several other recent wins by CAA (FCS) programs over those in the ACC (FBS).  The Tribe finished the year 11-3, after a run to the national semifinals that ended with a 14-13 loss to CAA rival and eventual champion Villanova.

==Men's basketball==
{{main|William &amp; Mary Tribe men's basketball}}
Traditionally, the Tribe has not been a storied basketball program. Their only postseason berths ever were the [[1983 National Invitation Tournament]] after winning the regular season conference title and the [[2010 National Invitation Tournament]] after beating both [[Wake Forest University]] and the [[University of Maryland]] on the road during the regular season. They have appeared in seven conference tournament finals; while in the [[Southern Conference]] they lost the tournament final in 1958, 1961, 1965, and 1975, and while in the [[Eastern College Athletic Conference|ECAC South]] (precursor to the [[Colonial Athletic Association]]) they lost the 1983 final to [[James Madison University]], 41-38. Their most recent conference tournament final appearances came in the 2008 [[Colonial Athletic Association|CAA]] final when W&amp;M dropped a 68-59 decision to [[George Mason University]] and in the 2010 CAA final when W&amp;M lost to [[Old Dominion University]] 60-53.

==Cross Country / Track &amp; Field==
The College of William &amp; Mary’s most dominant sports are its men’s and women’s cross country and track &amp; field teams. The totals below are current as of the end of the 2010-11 season.
===Men===
The men's cross country team has qualified for fourteen straight NCAA Division I championships, and 24 total NCAA championship appearances. Alumnus Brian Hyde represented the United States in the [[1996 Olympics]].

Total conference championships:
*Cross Country - 33
*Track &amp; Field - 27

===Women===
The women's cross country squad has made six NCAA championship appearances, most recently in 2005.

Total conference championships:
*Cross Country - 17
*Track &amp; Field - 10

==Soccer==
===Men===
The Tribe men’s soccer team has produced two First Team All-Americans and fourteen NCAA Tournament appearances, most recently in 2010. They have won eight conference tournaments since the program's inception in 1965. The most famous alumnus from this program is TV [[Pundit (expert)|pundit]] [[Jon Stewart]]. He played from 1981–1983 and scored the lone goal in a 1-0 victory over [[UConn]] in the 1983 ECAC Tournament Championship to give William &amp; Mary their second ever conference tournament championship crown. Stewart ended his career with 10 goals and 12 assists while playing as a defender.

The majority of the Tribe's success in men's soccer was overseen by [[Al Albert (soccer coach) | Al Albert]] during an illustrious 33 year career as head coach.  In 2004, Albert passed the coaching reins to his capable protege, Chris Norris.  Norris was a player and assistant coach at W&amp;M for 13 years before becoming Albert's successor in Williamsburg.

===Women===
{{main|William &amp; Mary Tribe women's soccer}}
When counting all-time women’s soccer NCAA Tournament appearances, just behind national powerhouses [[North Carolina Tar Heels women's soccer|North Carolina]] (with 29) and [[University of Connecticut|UConn]] (with 28)  are the William &amp; Mary Tribe (23). As of the end of 2010, they are on an NCAA-record 29-year consecutive winning seasons streak (tied with North Carolina), dating back to 1982, capturing ten conference tournament crowns in that span. Twice have players been selected at the [[NSCAA]] National Player of the Year (1987, 1995), and three times the team has made it all the way to the Tournament’s Elite 8 (1987, 1994, 1997).

==Other sports==
In addition to the sports listed above, the College of William &amp; Mary also fields [[Division I (NCAA)|Division I]] teams for men and women in gymnastics, swimming and diving, golf and tennis. Exclusive to women are field hockey, lacrosse and volleyball.

==National championships==
William &amp; Mary has won two national championships, both of which are men’s tennis in the [[NCAA]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.ncaa.org/champadmin/champs_listing1.html|title=How many NCAA Division I championships has your school won?|publisher=NCAA|accessdate=2008-07-23 |archiveurl = http://web.archive.org/web/20080419050813/http://www.ncaa.org/champadmin/champs_listing1.html |archivedate = 2008-04-19}}&lt;/ref&gt; The Tribe won back-to-back national championships in 1947 and 1948.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.tribeathletics.com/story.php/1121/|title=About William &amp; Mary athletics|publisher=The College of William &amp; Mary|accessdate=2008-07-23}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Rivalries==
William &amp; Mary’s most heated rivalries are with [[James Madison University|James Madison (JMU)]], [[University of Delaware|Delaware (UD)]], and [[Old Dominion University|Old Dominion (ODU)]]. In recent years, the William &amp; Mary-[[George Mason University|George Mason]] basketball series has attracted much attention after Mason’s improbable run in the [[2006 NCAA Men's Division I Basketball Tournament|2006 NCAA Championship]], coupled with W&amp;M’s [[2008 CAA Men's Basketball Tournament|conference tournament championship appearance]] in 2008. Additionally, every year William &amp; Mary squares off against the [[Richmond Spiders]] in what is termed the &quot;Oldest Football Rivalry in the South.&quot; The Tribe first visited Richmond in 1898, losing 15-0. However, William &amp; Mary holds the all-time series edge 59-54-5. The winner of this annual contest wins the [[Capital Cup#Trophy|Capital Cup]].

In addition, William &amp; Mary football maintains a lighthearted contest with their academic rival [[UVA]] unofficially coined &quot;The Jefferson Cup.&quot;  The Tribe stunned [[UVA]] on September 5, 2009 with a 26-14 victory on the season opener at [[Charlottesville]].  The Tribe last took home the Jefferson Cup in 1986 with a less dramatic 41-37 victory over The Cavaliers.

==Notable alumni==
:''[[List of College of William and Mary people#Athletics|Main article: List of William &amp; Mary alumni#Sports]]''

Notable graduates from the athletic programs include [[Jon Stewart]], [[Adin Brown]], [[Mike Leach (long snapper)|Mike Leach]], [[Buster Ramsey]], [[Darren Sharper]], [[Mike Tomlin]], [[Bill Chambers (basketball)|Bill Chambers]], [[J. D. Gibbs]], [[Steve Christie]], [[Wade Barrett (soccer)|Wade Barrett]] and [[Derek Cox]].

==Fight songs==
{{main|Tribe Fight Song}}

In addition to the most common Fight Song, the &quot;William and Mary Victory March&quot; (composed in the 1930s by Rolf Kennard) is occasionally heard before games. There is a long-running superstition that playing the Victory March during a game will lead to a bad result.

==See also==
*[[List of NCAA college football rivalry games#NCAA Division I Football Championship Subdivision|List of NCAA college football rivalry games]]

==References==
{{reflist}}

==External links==
* [http://www.tribeathletics.com/index.php Official Athletic Site]
* [http://www.wm.edu/ The College of William &amp; Mary]

{{W&amp;M}}
{{Colonial Athletic Association}}

[[Category:William &amp; Mary Tribe|*]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
