<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="15096830" ns="0" title="University of Sydney Business School"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Infobox University
|image_name     = University of Sydney new logo stacked.png
|image_size     = 
|name           = The University of Sydney Business School
|established    = 2011
|type           = [[Public]]
|dean           = Tyrone Carlin (Acting)
|city           = [[Camperdown, New South Wales|Camperdown]] / [[Darlington, New South Wales|Darlington]]
|state          = [[New South Wales]]
|country        = [[Australia]]
|affiliations   = [[University of Sydney]]
|students       =
|staff          =
|campus         =
|website        = [http://sydney.edu.au/business/ sydney.edu.au/business]
}}

'''The University of Sydney Business School''' is the business faculty and a constituent body of the [[University of Sydney]]. It was established in January 2011 and formed from the School of Business within the previous '''Faculty of Economics and Business'''. The former combined faculty itself descended from the original Faculty of Economics founded in 1920, which was the first faculty of its kind in Australia.

The Business School has an impressive academic reputation and is currently placed 28th in the world for Accounting and Finance by the [[QS World University Rankings]]. It was the first business school in Australia to receive accreditation by the [[Association to Advance Collegiate Schools of Business]] (AACSB)&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.aacsb.edu/General/InstLists.asp?lid=3 Association to Advance Collegiate Schools of Business - Schools Accredited in Business], retrieved on 2008-01-15.&lt;/ref&gt; and the [[European Quality Improvement System]] (EQUIS) from the [[European Foundation for Management Development]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.efmd.org/html/Accreditations/link_overview.asp?id=040929sqku&amp;tid=4&amp;ref=ind European Quality Improvement System Accredited Members], retrieved on 2008-01-15.&lt;/ref&gt; It is also the only Australian business school to become an Associate member of the [[ Global Alliance in Management Education]] (CEMS).&lt;ref&gt;[[CEMS|-  Global Alliance in Management Education]], retrieved on 2011-08-10.&lt;/ref&gt; The Business School's CEMS Master of International Management (CEMS MIM) was ranked as the No. 1 pre-experience management program in the world by The Financial Times 2009 Business School Rankings.

In 2010, the Faculty of Economics and Business had a total student enrolment of 8,389 (18% of the University's students), consisting of 4,161 undergraduate and 4,228 postgraduate students. In terms of total enrolment numbers it is the University's second-largest faculty. By large margins, the Faculty of Economics and Business had the greatest number and proportion of international students of any of the University of Sydney's 16 faculties. In 2008, 49% of the faculty's enrolment consisted of international students, more than double the University-wide rate of 22%.

[[File:Econ bus building.jpg|right|thumb|300px|The Economics and Business Building]]

==History==

Established in 1920, the Faculty of Economics initially offered the ''Bachelor of Economics'' degree, which commenced in 1930. The postgraduate ''Master of Economics'' degree commenced in 1970.

In 1985 the faculty introduced its second undergraduate and postgraduate degree programs, the ''Bachelor of Economic and Social Sciences'' and the ''Master of Economic and Social Sciences'', respectively.

In 1993 its third undergraduate degree program, the ''Bachelor of Commerce'', was introduced. The ''Master of International Studies'' followed in 1991, the ''Master of Commerce'' in 1995 and the ''Master of International Business'' in 1999.

In 2005 the Business School ended its association with the jointly run [[Australian Graduate School of Management]] with [[The University of New South Wales]].

From 2006 to 2007, the University conducted a review of its social sciences faculties. As a result of that review, it was determined that parts of the School of Economics within the Faculty of Economics and Business were to be transferred to the Faculty of Arts (as it then was). In January 2008, the Disciplines of Government &amp; International Relations and Political Economy were transferred to the Faculty of Arts. In January 2011, the Discipline of Economics, the Centre for International Security Studies and the Graduate School of Government were also transferred to the Faculty of Arts, which was renamed the [[University of Sydney Faculty of Arts and Social Sciences|Faculty of Arts and Social Sciences]]. Concurrently, the remaining disciplines of the Faculty of Economics and Business formed the University of Sydney Business School.

==Organisation==
The University of Sydney Business School consists of the following nine disciplines.
* [http://sydney.edu.au/business/accounting/ Discipline of Accounting]
* [http://sydney.edu.au/business/information_systems/ Discipline of Business Information Systems]
* [http://sydney.edu.au/business/business_law/ Discipline of Business Law]
* [http://sydney.edu.au/business/finance/ Discipline of Finance]
* [http://sydney.edu.au/business/international_business/ Discipline of International Business]
* [http://sydney.edu.au/business/marketing/ Discipline of Marketing]
* [http://sydney.edu.au/business/ome/ Discipline of Operations Management and Econometrics]
* [http://sydney.edu.au/business/wos/ Discipline of Work and Organisational Studies]

In addition to these, the faculty also offers postgraduate programs and research through its Centre for International Security Studies, Institute of Transport and Logistics Studies, Workplace Research Centre and Graduate School of Government.&lt;ref&gt;[http://sydney.edu.au/business/org/ University of Sydney Business School - Organisation], retrieved on 2008-01-15.&lt;/ref&gt;

==Professional accreditation==
Studies in accounting are recognised by [[CPA Australia]] and the [[Institute of Chartered Accountants of Australia]] (ICAA).

Majors in Industrial Relations and Human Resource Management can be accredited by the Australian Human Resource Institute (AHRI).

An extended major in Business Information Systems can be accredited by the [[Australian Computer Society]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.econ.usyd.edu.au/2387.html Quality Assurance and Professional Accreditation - Faculty of Economics and Business], retrieved on 2008-01-15.&lt;/ref&gt;

==Faculty journals==
* Abacus
* [[Accounting, Auditing &amp; Accountability Journal]]
* Australian Accounting Review
* Australian Review of Public Affairs
* Australian Tax Forum
* International Journal of Development Issues
* International Journal of Forecasting
* International Journal of Information Management
* [[International Journal of Management Reviews]]
* Journal of Australian Political Economy
* [[Journal of Industrial Relations]]
* Journal of International Financial Management &amp; Accounting
* Labour History

==Alumni==
The Faculty of Economics and Business has produced many graduates of prominence, including:
* [[Anthony Albanese]], &lt;small&gt;BEc 1984&lt;/small&gt;, Australian Labor politician and Minister of Infrastructure and Transport
* [[John Carrick (Australian politician)|John L Carrick]], &lt;small&gt;BEc 1941&lt;/small&gt;, former Australian Liberal politician
* [[David S. Clarke|David S Clarke]], &lt;small&gt;BEc (Hons)&lt;/small&gt;, former Executive Chairman, [[Macquarie Bank Limited]] &lt;small&gt;(1985—2007)&lt;/small&gt;
* [[Greg Combet]], &lt;small&gt;BEc 1987, Grad Dip Labour Relations and the Law 1991&lt;/small&gt;, Australian Labor politician and Minister for Climate Change and Energy Efficiency&lt;small&gt;&lt;/small&gt;
* Professor [[Margaret Gardner]] AO, &lt;small&gt;BEc (Hons) 1976, PhD (Econ) 1984&lt;/small&gt;, Vice-Chancellor and President of [[RMIT University]]
* [[Nick Greiner]], &lt;small&gt;BEc (Hons)&lt;/small&gt;, Australian Liberal politician and former premier of New South Wales &lt;small&gt;(1988–1992)&lt;/small&gt;
* [[Morris Iemma]], &lt;small&gt;BEc&lt;/small&gt;, Australian Labor politician, and former premier of New South Wales &lt;small&gt;(2005–2008)&lt;/small&gt;
* Justice [[Michael Kirby (judge)|Michael Kirby]], &lt;small&gt;BEc&lt;/small&gt;, Justice of the [[High Court of Australia]] (1996–2009)
* [[Mark Latham]], &lt;small&gt;BEc&lt;/small&gt;, former Australian Labor politician, leader of the Australian Labor Party and opposition leader of Australia &lt;small&gt;(2003–2005)&lt;/small&gt;
* [[Malcolm Mackerras]], &lt;small&gt;BEc 1962&lt;/small&gt;, psephologist and political commentator
* [[Glenn Stevens]], &lt;small&gt;BEc (Hons) 1979&lt;/small&gt;, economist and Governor of the Reserve Bank of Australia &lt;small&gt;(2006—)&lt;/small&gt;

==References==
{{Reflist}}

==External links==
* [http://sydney.edu.au/business/ University of Sydney Business School]

{{University of Sydney}}
{{coord missing|New South Wales}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:University Of Sydney Business School}}
[[Category:Business schools in Australia]]
[[Category:Economics schools]]
[[Category:Educational institutions established in 1920]]
[[Category:Faculties of the University of Sydney|Business School]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
