<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="151967" ns="0" title="Windowing system"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">[[File:KDE 4.png|300px|thumb|right|[[KDE]] desktop]]
A '''windowing system''' (or '''window system''') is a component of a [[graphical user interface]] (GUI), and more specifically of a [[desktop environment]], which supports the implementation of [[window manager]]s, and provides basic support for graphics hardware, pointing devices such as mice, and keyboards. The mouse cursor is also generally drawn by the windowing system.  

The term '''windowing system''' is sometimes used to refer to other elements of a graphical interface such as those belonging to window managers or even applications. While on some operating systems the distinction between applications, window managers, and their supporting technologies are blurred, strictly speaking, a windowing system does not include windows themselves. 

From a [[programmer]]'s point of view, a windowing system implements graphical primitives such as rendering [[typeface|fonts]] or drawing a line on the screen, effectively providing an abstraction of the graphics hardware from higher level elements of the graphical interface like window managers.

A windowing system enables the computer user to work with several programs at the same time. Each program runs in its own window, which is generally a rectangular area of the screen. Most windowing systems have basic support of re-parenting which allows windows to overlap, however the ways in which windows interact is usually controlled by the window manager.

Some windowing systems, like the [[X Window System]], have advanced capabilities such as [[network transparency]], allowing the user to display graphical applications running on a [[remote computer|remote machine]]. The X Window System takes a strictly layered approach, and does not implement any specific policy regarding the look and feel of the graphical user interfaces, and their behaviour, leaving that to the [[X window manager]]s, [[widget toolkit]]s and [[desktop environment]]s.

==List of windowing systems==
===For [[Unix-like]] operating systems===
* [[8½ (Plan 9)|8½]] and [[rio (windowing system)|rio]] for [[Plan 9 from Bell Labs|Plan 9]]
* [[Fresco (windowing system)|Fresco/Berlin]]
* FramebufferUI (fbui) in-kernel windowing system
* HP Windows
* [[ManaGeR]] (MGR)
* [[Metisse]]
* [[MicroXwin]]
* [[NeWS]] / [[OpenWindows]]
* [[NeXTSTEP|NeXT DPS]]
* [[Qt Extended]]
* [[Quartz Compositor]] ([[Mac OS X]])
* [[SunView]]
* [[Twin (windowing system)|Twin]] (Text WINdows)
* [[W Window System]]
* [[Wayland (display server)|Wayland]]
* [[X Window System]]
* [[Xynth]]
* [[XFast]]
* [[Y Window System]]

===[[World Wide Web|Web]] windowing systems===
* [[Dojo Toolkit|Dojo]]
* [[Ext (JavaScript_library)|ExtJS]]
* [[Tibco Software|TIBCO]] General Interface
* [[WebWM|Web Window Manager]]

===Other===
* [[DM (windowing system)|DM]] 
* [[Graphical Environment Manager|GEM]]
* [[OPIE user interface|OPIE]]
* [[Intuition (Amiga)|Intuition]]
* [[Microwindows]]
* [[MiniGUI]]
* OOHG

Operating systems such as [[Microsoft Windows]], [[History of Mac OS|Mac OS]] (version [[Mac OS 9|9]] and earlier), and [[Palm OS]], contain a windowing system which is integrated with the OS.

==See also==
* [[History of the graphical user interface]]
* [[Widget toolkit]]
* [[Desktop environment]]

{{Window Managers}} 

[[Category:Windowing systems| ]]

[[ca:Sistema de finestres]]
[[de:Fenstersystem]]
[[fr:Système de fenêtrage]]
[[ko:윈도 시스템]]
[[is:Gluggakerfi]]
[[nl:Venstersysteem]]
[[ja:ウィンドウシステム]]
[[ta:சாளர ஒருங்கியம்]]
[[zh:視窗系統]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
