<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="1524734" ns="0" title="Red Hat Enterprise Linux derivatives"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">'''Red Hat Enterprise Linux derivatives''' are [[Linux distributions]] that are based on the source code of [[Red Hat Enterprise Linux]].

==History==

[[Red Hat Linux]] was one of the first and most popular [[Linux distribution]]s. This was largely because, while a paid-for supported version was available, a freely downloadable version was also available. Since the only difference between the paid-for option and the free option was support, a great number of people chose to use the free version.

[[Red Hat]] made the decision to split its Red Hat Linux product into two: [[Red Hat Enterprise Linux]] for customers who were willing to pay for it, and [[Fedora (operating system)|Fedora]] that was made available free of charge but gets updates for every release for approximately 13 months.

Fedora has its own beta cycle and has some issues fixed by contributors who include Red Hat staff. However, its quick and nonconservative release cycle means it might not be suitable for some users. Since the release of Fedora, Red Hat has no longer made binary versions of its commercial product available free-of-charge.

==Motivations==

Red Hat does not make a [[compiler|compiled]] version of its Enterprise Linux product available for free download. However, as the license terms on which it is mostly based explicitly stipulate, Red Hat has made the entire [[source code]] available in [[RPM Package Manager|RPM]] format via their network of servers. The availability of the complete source code of the distribution in RPM format makes it relatively easy to recompile the entire distribution. Several [[Linux distributions|distributions]] were created that took Red Hat's source code, recompiled it, and released it.

==Features==

The Red Hat Enterprise Linux derivatives generally include the union set{{Clarify|date=July 2010}}, which is included in the different versions of RHEL. The version numbers are typically identical to the ones featured in RHEL; as such, the free versions maintain binary compatibility with the paid-for version, which means software intended for RHEL typically runs just as well on a free version. Relatively few changes need to be made to the distributions. However, RHEL used to use [[Red Hat|Red Hat's]] own [[Up2date]] technology for providing updates. For convenience, several of the free alternatives ship with [[Yellow dog Updater Modified|yum]] replacing up2date, something that makes providing mirrors for upgrades significantly easier. Red Hat Enterprise Linux 5 and above releases use yum as their native system for providing updates, with up2date being just its front end.

==Legal aspects==

Free redistributions are expressly permitted by the [[GNU General Public License]] upon which Red Hat's distributions are based.{{Citation needed|date=August 2010}} However, to avoid misrepresentation of Red Hat's trademark, material in the original distribution covered by the trademark must be stripped off or removed from the redistribution.

Where distributions (e.g., [[CentOS]]) have not been deemed sufficiently thorough in removing references to Red Hat, they have received warnings from [[Red Hat]]'s legal counsel. CentOS received such a notice seeking to have it remove all mention of Red Hat's asserted trademarks from their website and their distribution. CentOS now refers to Red Hat as the &quot;Upstream Vendor&quot;.

==List of Red Hat Enterprise Linux derivatives==

The following are listed by [[DistroWatch]] as being among the top 100 most popular distros for the past 12 months (as of December 2010):

*[[CentOS]]
*[[ClearOS]]
*[[Oracle Linux]] - Requests registration, with personal information (name, email, company) and agreements, but does not require payment to download or deploy. Payment is required for support.&lt;ref&gt;http://blogs.oracle.com/wim/2008/09/reminder_oracle_enterprise_lin.html&lt;/ref&gt;
*[[Scientific Linux]]
*[[Yellow Dog Linux]]

Other less well-known distros:

*[[CAOS Linux]] (multiple lineage)
*[[Fermi Linux]], a.k.a. Fermi Scientific Linux, derived from Scientific Linux
*GENtOS Linux
*StartCom Enterprise Linux
*[[PUIAS Linux]]
*[[Rocks Cluster Distribution]] - derived from RHEL (earlier versions) and CentOS (recent releases)
*[[Groupe Bull|Bull]]'s XBAS (for high-performance computing) &lt;ref&gt;[https://computing.llnl.gov/linux/slurm/slurm_ug_2010/01-mh-cea.pdf SLURM at CEA]&lt;/ref&gt;
*[[Ascendos]]

The following derivatives have ceased production:

*Pie Box Enterprise Linux, no longer operating as of 2009-08-01
*Lineox
*TaoLinux - 4.0 i386 Final Release available on 2005-04-20; 3.0 Update 4 available on 2005-01-10, Ceased production on 2006-06-14. The web site includes instructions for updating to ''[[CentOS]]'' for continued updates
*X/OS Linux - Ceased production in 2008. The web site includes instructions for updating to ''[[CentOS]]'' for continued updates.
*[[White Box Enterprise Linux]] - No formal announcement but no longer actively developed

The following appliance-oriented derivatives are also based on Red Hat Enterprise Linux

*[[Cisco Unified Communications Manager]]&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Cisco Unified Communications Manager - Hardware, Software and Clustering|url=http://searchnetworkingchannel.techtarget.com/generic/0,295582,sid100_gci1316822,00.html|accessdate=2009-02-05}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*[[VMWare]] ESX's Service Console software

==References==
&lt;!--This article uses the Cite.php citation mechanism. If you would like more information on how to add references to this article, please see http://meta.wikimedia.org/wiki/Cite/Cite.php --&gt;
{{Reflist}}

==External links==
{{Portal|Free software}}
* [http://lwn.net/Articles/128952/ Revisiting RHEL Clones]
* [http://linuxmafia.com/faq/RedHat/rhel-forks.html rhel-forks]

{{RedHatFedora-distro}}
{{Red Hat}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Red Hat Enterprise Linux Derivatives}}
&lt;!-- Categories --&gt;
[[Category:Red Hat]]

[[es:Clones de RedHat Enterprise Linux]]
[[ru:Категория:Дистрибутивы семейства RedHat]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
