<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="15298702" ns="0" title="Green Bay Phoenix"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Infobox college athletics 
|logo                = PhoenixLogo.jpg
|logo_width          = 200
|name                = Green Bay Phoenix 
|university          = University of Wisconsin–Green Bay 
|conference          = [[Horizon League]] 
|division            = [[Division I (NCAA)|Division I]] 
||teams              = 16
|director            = Ken Bothof
|city                = Green Bay
|state               = Wisconsin 
|stateabb            = WI
|soccerstadium       = [[Aldo Santaga Stadium]] 
|arena               = [[Resch Center]] (men)&lt;br&gt;[[Kress Events Center]] (women)
|arena2              = 
|mascot              = Phlash the Phoenix 
|nickname            = Phoenix
|fightsong           = UWGB Fight Song 
|color1              = Green
|color2              = White 
|hex1                = 006633 
|hex2                = FFFFFF 
|pageurl             = http://www.greenbayphoenix.com/ 
|pagename = GreenBayPhoenix.com
|}}
[[File:UWGBMascot2010.jpg|thumb|right|Mascot in 2010]]
The '''Green Bay Phoenix''', previously known as the '''UW–Green Bay Phoenix''' and '''UWGB Phoenix''', are the athletic teams of the [[University of Wisconsin–Green Bay]]. A total of 16 Phoenix athletic teams compete in  the [[Horizon League]] of [[NCAA Division I]]. They do not sponsor a football team.

==Team highlights==
===Women's basketball===

The Green Bay women's basketball team has won or tied for the Horizon League regular-season championship nine times, including the last eight years.[http://horizonleague.cstv.com/sports/w-baskbl/spec-rel/110504aac.html] They have been to the NCAA tournament eight times, as well, including four of the last five years.  In 2007, they were seeded #9 and defeated the [[New Mexico Lobos|New Mexico]] in the first round before falling to the top seeded [[Connecticut Huskies women's basketball|Connecticut]] in the second round despite leading 40-38 at the half.  That loss ended their school-record and nation-leading 26-game winning streak. In 2009, they made it to the first round. In 2010, they made it to the second round, and in 2011, made it to the Sweet 16. They also received their first national ranking in 2003, when they were ranked as high as #16 in both the Associated Press poll and the Coaches' Poll.  In 2005, they also received a national ranking and a bid to the NCAA Tournament, but were knocked out in the first round by [[Maryland Terrapins women's basketball|Maryland]].  They have also made three appearances in the Women's NIT (National Invitational Tournament), most recently in 2008, where they lost to [[Drake Bulldogs|Drake]] in a first round game.

===Men's basketball===
{{main|Green Bay Phoenix men's basketball}}

===Softball===

The Green Bay softball team has also entered the national spotlight recently.  In the 2005 season, they claimed their first Horizon League tournament championship after being picked to finish last in the conference.  They went on to the national tournament, where they defeated #6 seed [[Oregon State Beavers|Oregon State]] in the first round of the tournament.

==See also==
*[[History records of the Green Bay Phoenix]]

==Notable sports figures==
===Athletes===
*[[Tony Bennett (basketball)|Tony Bennett]], former [[National Basketball Association|NBA]] basketball player and current men's head basketball coach at the [[Virginia Cavaliers men's basketball|University of Virginia]].
*[[Logan Vander Velden]], former NBA basketball player.
*[[Jeff Nordgaard]], former NBA basketball player, current European basketball player.
*[[Tosaint Ricketts]], professional soccer player, member of the Canadian national team for the [[U-20 World Cup]]

===Coaches===
*[[Dick Bennett]], former head basketball coach (and father of the aforementioned Tony Bennett)
*[[Kevin Borseth]], former women's head basketball coach

==External links==
*[http://www.greenbayphoenix.com Green Bay Phoenix website]
*[http://www.uwgb.edu UWGB website]

==References==
{{reflist}}

{{Horizon League}}
{{Wisconsin Sports}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Green Bay Phoenix}}
[[Category:Green Bay Phoenix| ]]
[[Category:College sports teams in the United States by team]]

[[es:Green Bay Phoenix]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
