<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="152924" ns="0" title="Early tablet computers"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{For|other forms of tablet and slate computers and devices|Tablet device (disambiguation)}}

[[File:Tablet.jpg|thumb|300px|HP Compaq tablet PC with rotating/removable keyboard]]

'''Early [[tablet computer]]s''' included many of the features of [[personal computer]]s. These devices ran adapted versions of [[Microsoft Windows]] or [[desktop Linux]] and were capable of running many of the same applications. Most featured [[pen computing|pen-based input]].

In 2001 [[Microsoft]] announced a set of specifications for the ''[[Microsoft Tablet PC|Tablet PC]]'', which popularized that term.&lt;ref&gt;Page, M [http://www.transmetazone.com/articleview.cfm?articleID=499 Microsoft Tablet PC Overview], TransmetaZone, 2000-12-21&lt;/ref&gt;

==System software==
===Microsoft Windows===
{{see|Microsoft Tablet PC#History}}
In 2002, [[original equipment manufacturer]]s' released the first tablet PCs designed to the Microsoft Tablet PC specification. This generation of Microsoft Tablet PCs were designed to run Windows XP Tablet PC Edition, the Tablet PC version of [[Windows XP]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Microsoft 2005&quot;&gt;{{Citation
 | last=Microsoft
 | title= Windows XP Tablet PC Edition 2005 Hardware Requirements
 | year=2005
 | publisher=www.microsoft.com
 | url=http://users.erols.com/rwservices/pens/biblio10.html#Microsoft06i
 | accessdate = 2009-03-14}}&lt;/ref&gt; This version of [[Microsoft Windows]] superseded Microsoft's earlier [[pen computing]] operating environment, [[Windows for Pen Computing|Windows for Pen Computing 2.0]]. After releasing Windows XP Tablet PC Edition, Microsoft designed the successive [[desktop computer]] versions of Windows, [[Windows Vista]] and [[Windows 7]], to support pen computing intrinsically.

===Linux===
[[File:N800 frontside2.jpg|thumb|The [[Nokia N800]]]]
One early implementation of a [[Linux]] tablet was the [[ProGear]] by FrontPath. The ProGear used a Transmeta chip and a resistive digitizer.
The ProGear initially came with a version of [[Slackware Linux]], but could later be bought with [[Windows 98]]. Because these computers are general purpose [[IBM PC compatible]] machines, they can run many different operating systems.  However, the device is no longer for sale and FrontPath has ceased operations. It is important to note that many touch screen sub-notebook computers can run any of several Linux distributions with little customization.

[[X.Org Foundation|X.org]] now supports screen rotation and tablet input through Wacom drivers, and handwriting recognition software from both the [[Qt (framework)|Qt]]-based [[Qtopia]] and [[GTK+]]-based [[Internet Tablet OS]] provide promising free and [[open source]] systems for future development.

Open source note taking software in Linux includes applications such as [[Xournal]] (which supports PDF file annotation), Gournal (a Gnome based note taking application), and the Java-based [[Jarnal]] (which supports handwriting recognition as a built-in function). Before the advent of the aforementioned software, many users had to rely on on-screen keyboards and alternative text input methods like [[Dasher]]. There is a stand alone handwriting recognition program available, CellWriter, in which users must write letters separately in a grid.

A number of Linux based OS projects are dedicated to tablet PCs. Since all these are open source, they are freely available and can be run or ported to devices that conform to the tablet PC design. [[Maemo]] (rebranded MeeGo in 2010), a [[Debian]] Linux based graphical user environment, was developed for the [[Nokia Internet Tablet]] devices (770, N800, N810 &amp; N900). It is currently in generation 5, and has a vast array of applications available in both official and user supported repositories. The [[Ubuntu Netbook Edition|Ubuntu Netbook Remix edition]], as well as the Intel sponsored Moblin project, both have touchscreen support integrated into their user interfaces. [[Canonical Ltd]] has hinted at better supporting tablets with the [[Unity (desktop environment)|Unity UI]] for [[Ubuntu (operating system)|Ubuntu 10.10]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Ubuntu gets multitouch support, Unity netbook UI|url=http://www.linuxfordevices.com/c/a/News/Canonical-uTouch-and-Ubuntu-Maverick-Meerkat/|publisher=eWeek}}&lt;/ref&gt;

TabletKiosk currently offers a hybrid digitizer / touch device running [[openSUSE]] Linux. It is the first device with this feature to support Linux.

====webOS ====
{{Main|webOS}}
Initially developed by [[Palm, Inc.]] in January 2009 as the [[Palm OS]], [[webOS]] was purchased by [[HP]] to be their proprietary operating system running on the Linux kernel. Versions 1.0 to 2.1 of webOS uses the patched Linux 2.6.24 kernel. HP has continued to develop the webOS platform for use in multiple products, including smartphones, tablet PCs, and printers. HP announced plans on March 2011 for a version of webOS by the end of 2011 to run within the Microsoft Windows operating system to be used in HP desktop and notebook computers in 2012.

HP TouchPad, the first addition to HP's tablet family, has been shipped out with versions 3.0.2.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=
HP Touchpad 9.7 Inch Tablet PC|url=http://tabletpcfan.com/2011/hp-touchpad-9-7-inch-tablet/|publisher=TabletPCfan|accessdate=9 August 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; Version 3.0.2 gives the tablet support for multitasking, applications, and HP Synergy. HP have also claimed in its webcatalog to support over 200 apps with its release.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=
HP Touchpad Catalog|url=http://h41112.www4.hp.com/promo/webos/us/en/tablet/touchpad.html/|publisher=HP|accessdate=13 August 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;

On August 18, 2011, HP announced that it would discontinue production of all webOS devices.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.businesswire.com/news/home/20110818006301/en/HP-Confirms-Discussions-Autonomy-Corporation-plc-Business|title=HP Confirms Discussions with Autonomy Corporation plc Regarding Possible Business Combination; Makes Other Announcements|accessdate=18 Aug 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.appleinsider.com/articles/11/08/18/hp_to_spin_off_pc_business_to_focus_on_enterprise_software.html|title=HP kills webOS, spins off PC business to focus on software|accessdate=18 Aug 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

====MeeGo====
{{Main|Maemo|MeeGo}}
Nokia entered the tablet space with the [[Nokia 770 Internet Tablet|Nokia 770]] running [[Maemo]], a Debian-based Linux distribution custom-made for their [[Nokia Internet Tablet]] line. The product line continued with the [[N900]] which is the first to add phone capabilities. Intel, following the launch of the UMPC, started the [[Mobile Internet Device]] initiative, which took the same hardware and combined it with a Linux operating system custom-built for portable tablets. Intel co-developed the lightweight [[Moblin]] operating system following the successful launch of the Atom CPU series on netbooks.

[[MeeGo]] is a new operating system developed by [[Intel]] and [[Nokia]] supports Netbooks, Smartphones and tablet PCs. In 2010, Nokia and Intel combined the Maemo and Moblin projects to form MeeGo. The first{{clarify|date=November 2010}} MeeGo powered tablet PC is the [[Neofonie]] [[WeTab]]. The WeTab uses an extended version of the MeeGo operating system called WeTab OS. WeTab OS adds runtimes for [[Android (operating system)|Android]] and [[Adobe AIR]] and provides a proprietary user interface optimized for the WeTab device. {{Citation needed|date=November 2010}}

===Apple===
====Mac OS X Modbook====
Apple has never sold a tablet PC computer running [[Mac OS X]], although OS X does have support for handwriting recognition via [[Inkwell (Macintosh)|Inkwell]]. However, Apple sells the [[iOS (Apple)|iOS]]-based [[iPad]] [[Tablet computer]], introduced in 2010 and iPad 2, released in 2011.

Before the introduction of the iPad, Axiotron introduced the [[Axiotron Modbook|Modbook]], a heavily modified Apple [[MacBook]], Mac OS X-based tablet computer at Macworld in 2007.&lt;ref name='modbookRelease'&gt;[http://www.tabletpcreview.com/default.asp?newsID=695]&lt;/ref&gt; The Modbook used Apple's Inkwell handwriting and gesture recognition, and used digitization hardware from [[Wacom]]. To support the [[digitizer]] on the integrated tablet, the Modbook was supplied with a third-party driver called [http://www.thinkyhead.com/tabletmagic TabletMagic]. Wacom does not provide drivers for this device.

==Display size trends==
Although tablet PCs are usually larger than [[tablet computer]]s, they tend to be based on relatively small laptop designs, with screen sizes from {{convert|7|to|14|in}}.{{Citation needed|date=June 2011}}

==Timeline of tablet PC history==
{{main|History of tablet computers}}

==See also==
{{Commons}}
{{Portal|Electronics}}
* [[Tablet computer]]
* [[Personal digital assistant]]
* [[Comparison of tablet computers]]
* [[Graphics tablet]]
* [[Nettop]]
* [[Pen computing]]
* [[Smartbook]]
* [[Ultra-Mobile PC]]

==References==
&lt;!--&lt;nowiki&gt;
See http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Wikipedia:Footnotes for an explanation of how to generate footnotes using the&lt;ref&gt; and &lt;/ref&gt; tags, and the template below.
&lt;/nowiki&gt;--&gt;
{{Reflist|colwidth=30em}}

==External links==
{{wiktionary|tablet computer|tablet PC}}
{{commons category|Tablet PC}}
*{{HSW|1787-jeff-han-talks-about-touch-driven-computer-screens-video|Jeff Han Talks About Touch-Driven Computer Screens}}
* [http://pen.cs.brown.edu/ Microsoft Center for Research on Pen-Centric Computing]
{{Use dmy dates|date=October 2010}}

[[Category:Tablet computers]]
[[Category:Personal computers]]
[[Category:Personal computing]]

[[ar:قرص الكمبيوتر الشخصي]]
[[ca:Tablet PC]]
[[cs:Tablet PC]]
[[de:Tablet-PC]]
[[eml:Tavlátta (zarvlán)]]
[[fa:لوح رایانه]]
[[fr:Tablet PC]]
[[gl:Tablet PC]]
[[ko:태블릿 PC]]
[[hi:टैबलेट कम्प्यूटर]]
[[id:Tablet PC]]
[[is:Spjaldtölva]]
[[it:Tablet PC]]
[[he:מחשב לוח]]
[[kn:ಟ್ಯಾಬ್ಲೆಟ್ PC]]
[[ka:Tablet PC]]
[[kk:Планшетті компьютер]]
[[lv:Planšetdators]]
[[hu:Tablet PC]]
[[mzn:تبلت پی سی]]
[[nl:Tablet-pc]]
[[ja:タブレットPC]]
[[no:Notatblokk-PC]]
[[nn:Notatblokk-PC]]
[[pl:Tablet PC]]
[[pt:Tablet PC]]
[[ru:Планшетный персональный компьютер]]
[[sk:Tablet PC (všeobecne)]]
[[ta:தத்தல் தனிப்பயன் கணினி]]
[[te:టాబ్లెట్ PC]]
[[th:แท็บเล็ตคอมพิวเตอร์]]
[[tg:Лавҳроёна]]
[[tr:Tablet KB]]
[[uk:Планшетний комп'ютер]]
[[yi:טאוול קאמפיוטער]]
[[zh:平板電腦]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
