<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="154081" ns="0" title="Timothy Dalton"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Use British English|date=August 2011}}
{{Infobox person
| name         = Timothy Dalton
| birth_name   = Timothy Peter Dalton 
| image        = Timothy_dalton.jpg
| imagesize    = 
| birth_date   = {{Birth date and age|df=yes|1946|3|21}}
| birth_place  = [[Colwyn Bay]], [[Wales]]
| home_town    = [[Milford, Derbyshire]], [[England]]
| other_names  =
| known_for    = [[James Bond]], [[Alexei Volkoff]]
| occupation   = Actor
| years_active = 1967–present
}}
'''Timothy Peter Dalton''' (born 21 March 1946)&lt;ref&gt;Some sources gives his year of birth as 1944. His official sites{{Citation needed|date=July 2010}} and the official James Bond sites{{Citation needed|date=July 2010}} indicate his year of birth as 1946.&lt;/ref&gt; is a [[Wales|Welsh]] actor of film and television. He is known for portraying [[James Bond (character)|James Bond]] in ''[[The Living Daylights]]'' (1987) and ''[[Licence to Kill]]'' (1989), as well as Rhett Butler in the television miniseries ''[[Scarlett (TV miniseries)|Scarlett]]'' (1994), an original sequel to ''[[Gone with the Wind]]''. In addition, he is known for his roles as King Phillip II of France in the 1968 Academy-award winning [[The Lion in Winter (1968 film)|The Lion In Winter]], [[Emily Brontë]]’s ''[[Wuthering Heights (1970 film)|Wuthering Heights]]'' (1970), [[Charlotte Brontë]]'s ''[[Jane Eyre (1983 TV serial)|Jane Eyre]]'' (1983), [[Prince Barin]] in ''[[Flash Gordon (film)|Flash Gordon]]'' (1980), [[William Shakespeare|Shakespearean]] films and plays such as ''[[Romeo and Juliet]]'', ''[[King Lear]]'', ''[[Henry V (play)|Henry V]]'', ''[[Love's Labour's Lost]]'', ''[[Henry IV, Part 1]]'' and ''[[Henry IV, Part 2]]''. Recently, he had a voice acting part in ''[[Toy Story 3]]'' as Mr. Pricklepants&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.imdb.com/character/ch0160340/ Mr. Pricklepants (Character)&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt; and portrayed the recurring character of [[Alexei Volkoff]] in the US TV series [[Chuck (TV series)|''Chuck'']] and [[Rassilon]] in the [[Doctor Who]] two-parter [[The End of Time]].

== Early life ==
Dalton was born in [[Colwyn Bay]], North Wales to an English father, who was a captain in the [[Special Operations Executive]] during World War II and had become an advertising executive at the time of his son's birth, and an American mother of Italian and Irish descent.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.filmreference.com/film/39/Timothy-Dalton.html Timothy Dalton Film Reference bio]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Muir|first=Frank|authorlink=Frank Muir|title=A Kentish Lad|publisher=[[Corgi (publisher)#Random House, UK|Corgi]]|date =1 October 1998|pages=113–114|url=http://www.booksattransworld.co.uk/catalog/book.htm?command=Search&amp;db=twmain.txt&amp;eqisbndata=0552141372|isbn=0552141372
}}&lt;/ref&gt; Before his fourth birthday, the family moved back to England to Milford, a village near [[Belper]], [[Derbyshire]]. While in Milford, he attended the Herbert Strutt [[Grammar schools in the United Kingdom|Grammar School]]. As a teenager, he was a member of the [[Air Training Corps|Air Cadets]] but at age 16 saw ''[[Macbeth]]'' and Dalton's life changed. He left school in 1964 to enroll in the [[Royal Academy of Dramatic Art]] and tour with the [[National Youth Theatre]]. Dalton did not complete his RADA studies, leaving the academy in 1966 to join the ensemble of the [[Birmingham]] Repertory Theatre.

==Career==
Dalton quickly moved to television, working mainly with [[BBC]] and, in 1968, made his film debut as [[Philip II of France]] in ''[[The Lion in Winter (1968 film)|The Lion in Winter]]''. This was the first of several period dramas, which included a remake of ''[[Wuthering Heights (1970 film)|Wuthering Heights]]'' in 1970 in which he portrayed the tortured [[Heathcliff (Wuthering Heights)|Heathcliff]]. In 1968, [[Albert Broccoli]] asked the 22-year-old Dalton to take over for [[Sean Connery]] in the role of [[James Bond]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.mi6.co.uk/sections/bonds/dalton.php3 MI6 – The Home Of James Bond 007]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.jamesbondmm.co.uk/james-bond/timothy-dalton.php Multimedia Timothy Dalton (James Bond) images]&lt;/ref&gt; This would not be the last time Dalton turned the role down. After a few more films, Dalton took a break in 1971 to concentrate on the theatre, performing with the [[Royal Shakespeare Company]] and other troupes throughout the world.

With two notable exceptions, the films ''[[Mary, Queen of Scots (film)|Mary, Queen of Scots]]'' (1972) and ''[[Permission to Kill]]'' (1975), he remained a theatre actor until 1978. That year he starred in ''[[Sextette]]'' as the husband of 85-year-old [[Mae West]], hailing his return to cinema and the beginning of his American career. While in the United States, Dalton worked mainly in television, although he starred in several films. During this time, he played [[Prince Barin]] in the 1980 cult science fiction classic ''[[Flash Gordon (film)|Flash Gordon]]'' and played Mr. Rochester in the 1983 BBC serial of ''[[Jane Eyre (1983 TV serial)|Jane Eyre]]''. He also co-starred with [[Joan Collins]] in the miniseries, ''[[Sins (miniseries)|Sins]]'' (1986).

===James Bond (1987–1994)===
====Initial offers====
In 1986, Dalton was the first choice to replace the retiring [[Roger Moore]], but obligations to the film ''[[Brenda Starr (film)|Brenda Starr]]'' and the stage productions of ''[[Antony and Cleopatra]]'' and ''[[The Taming of The Shrew]]'' kept him from accepting the role. [[Sam Neill]] was then screen-tested for the part of Bond, but was ultimately rejected by [[Albert R. Broccoli]]. [[Pierce Brosnan]] was then approached for the role, but was forced by [[NBC]] to turn it down (after initially accepting it) because of his contractual commitments to the television series ''[[Remington Steele]]''. By this time, when Dalton completed the filming of ''Brenda Starr,'' he was now available to assume the role as James Bond.

Previously, Dalton had been considered for the role of James Bond four times. In 1968, he was asked to play Bond in ''[[On Her Majesty's Secret Service (film)|On Her Majesty's Secret Service]]'' (1969) after [[Sean Connery]] decided that ''[[You Only Live Twice (film)|You Only Live Twice]]'' (1967) would be his last Bond film. Dalton turned the offer down, feeling he was too young for the role; it finally went to [[George Lazenby]]. In a 1987 interview, Dalton said &quot;Originally I did not want to take over from Sean Connery. He was far too good, he was wonderful. I was about 24 or 25, which is too young. But when you've seen Bond from the beginning, you don't take over from Sean Connery.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite video|url=http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=amuodiP-8z4|title=Good Morning America – interview with Timothy Dalton – 1987!}}&lt;/ref&gt; During the late-1970s, he was approached again, but he did not favour the direction the movies were taking. As he explained, his idea of Bond was different.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|author=Lee Pfeiffer and Philip Lisa|year=1992|title=The Incredible World of 007: An Authorised Celebration of James Bond|publisher=[[Macmillan Publishers|Boxtree]]|isbn=1-85283-141-3}}&lt;/ref&gt; In a 1979 episode of the television series ''[[Charlie's Angels]]'', Dalton played the role of Damien Roth, a millionaire playboy described by [[David Doyle (actor)|David Doyle]]'s character as &quot;almost James Bond-ian&quot;, either an amusing coincidence, or a specific in-joke, since it was around that time that Dalton was also asked to star in ''[[For Your Eyes Only (film)|For Your Eyes Only]]'' (1981).

====Films====
Dalton's first appearance as 007, ''[[The Living Daylights]]'' (1987) was critically successful, and grossed more than the previous two Bond films with Moore, as well as contemporary box-office rivals such as ''[[Die Hard]]'' and ''[[Lethal Weapon]]''. However, his second film, ''[[Licence to Kill]]'' (1989), although almost as successful as its predecessor in most markets, did not perform as well at the U.S. box office, in large part due to a lacklustre marketing campaign, after the title of the film was abruptly changed from ''Licence Revoked''.
MGM executives believed that takings would be harmed due to most Americans not knowing what the word &quot;revoked&quot; meant.{{Citation needed|date=July 2011}} However, the main factor for the lack of success in the U.S. was that it was released at the same time as the hugely successful ''[[Indiana Jones and the Last Crusade]]'', Tim Burton's ''[[Batman (1989 film)|Batman]]'', and ''[[Lethal Weapon 2]]'', during the summer blockbuster season. Future Bond films, following the resolution of legal and other issues, were all released between 31 October and after mid December, in order to avoid the risk of a summer failure, as had happened to ''Licence To Kill''.

With a worldwide gross of $191&amp;nbsp;million, ''The Living Daylights'' became the fourth most successful Bond film at the time of its release. In 1998 the second Deluxe Edition of Bond's Soundtracks was released. ''The Living Daylights'' was one of the first soundtracks to receive Deluxe treatment. The booklet/poster of this CD contains MGM's quote about ''The Living Daylights'' being the [http://www.shrani.si/?2N/2t/PaUOR72/1/ld-gross.png fourth most successful Bond film].

Since Dalton was contracted for three Bond films,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title=60 Seconds: Timothy Dalton|date=15 February 2007|work=An interview in Metro Newspaper by Andrew Williams|url= http://www.metro.co.uk/fame/interviews/article.html?in_article_id=37497&amp;in_page_id=11}}&lt;/ref&gt; the pre-production of his third film began in 1990, in order to be released in 1991. It was rumoured that he would make ''The Property of a Lady'' (which is one of [[Ian Fleming|Ian Fleming's]] short stories and elements of which had been included in ''[[Octopussy]]''), but this was never confirmed. What was confirmed is that the story would deal with the destruction of a chemical weapons laboratory in [[Scotland]], and the events would take place in London, Tokyo and Hong Kong. However, the film was cancelled due to legal issues between UA/MGM and EON, which lasted for four years.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.mi6.co.uk/sections/articles/bond_17_elements.php3?t=&amp;s= The third outing of Timothy Dalton as James Bond]&lt;/ref&gt;

The legal battle ended in 1993, and Dalton was expected to return as James Bond in the next Bond film, which later became ''[[GoldenEye]]''. Despite his contract having expired, negotiations with him to renew it took place.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.mi6.co.uk/sections/articles/ge_roadtoproduction.php3 Goldeneye – The Road to production]&lt;/ref&gt; In an interview with the ''[[Daily Mail]]'' in August 1993, Dalton indicated that [[Michael France]] was writing the screenplay for the new film, and the production was to begin in January or February 1994.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title=Interview with Dalton|work=The Daily Mail |location=UK|date=6 August 1993}}&lt;/ref&gt; When the deadline was not met, Dalton surprised everyone on 12 April 1994 with the announcement that he would not return as James Bond. At this time, he was shooting the mini-series ''[[Scarlett (TV miniseries)|Scarlett]]''. The announcement for the new Bond came two months later, with [[Pierce Brosnan]] playing the role. Dalton reflected in 2007, &quot;I was supposed to make one more but it was cancelled because [[MGM]] and the film's producers got into a lawsuit which lasted for five years. After that, I didn't want to do it any more.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title=Timothy Dalton Reflects On 007|date=19 February 2007|url=http://www.mi6.co.uk/sections/articles/dalton_hot_fuzz.php3?t=&amp;s=|work=MI6 – The Home of James Bond|accessdate=21 February 2007}}&lt;/ref&gt;

====Dalton as Bond====
Unlike Moore, who had played Bond as more of a light-hearted playboy and admitted that he had read very little Fleming and found the books lacking in humour, Dalton's portrayal of Bond was darker, stiffer and more serious. Dalton pushed for renewed emphasis on gritty realism instead of fantasy plots and humour.&lt;ref name=&quot;rubin&quot;&gt;{{cite book|last=Rubin|first=Stephen Jay|title=The Complete James Bond Movie Encyclopedia|edition=Revised|year=1995|publisher=McGraw-Hill/Contemporary Books|ISBN=0809232685}}&lt;/ref&gt; Dalton stated in a 1989 interview: {{quote|''&quot;I think Roger was fine as Bond, but the movies had become too much techno-pop and had lost track of their sense of story. I mean, every movie seemed to have a villain who had to rule or destroy the world. If you want to believe in the fantasy on screen, then you have to believe in the characters and use them as a stepping-stone to lead you into this fantasy world. That's a demand I made, and Albert Broccoli agreed with me.”''&lt;ref name=&quot;rubin&quot; /&gt;}}

A fan of the literary character, often seen re-reading and referencing the novels on set, Dalton determined to approach the role and play truer to the original character described by Fleming. His 007, therefore, came across as a reluctant agent who did not always enjoy the assignments he was given, something only seen on screen before, albeit obliquely, in [[George Lazenby]]'s ''[[On Her Majesty's Secret Service (film)|On Her Majesty's Secret Service]]''. In ''The Living Daylights,'' for example, Bond tells a critical colleague, &quot;Stuff my orders! ... Tell [[M (James Bond)|M]] what you want. If he fires me, I'll thank him for it.&quot; In ''Licence to Kill,'' he resigns the Secret Service in order to pursue his own agenda of revenge. Stephen Jay Rubin writes in ''The Complete James Bond Movie Encyclopaedia'' (1995): {{quote|Unlike Moore, who always seems to be in command, Dalton's Bond sometimes looks like a candidate for the [[psychiatrist]]'s couch – a burned-out killer who may have just enough energy left for one final mission. That was Fleming's Bond – a man who drank to diminish the poison in his system, the poison of a violent world with impossible demands.... [H]is is the suffering Bond.&lt;ref name=&quot;rubin&quot; /&gt;}}

This approach proved to be a double-edged sword. Film critics and fans of Fleming's original novels welcomed a more serious interpretation after more than a decade of Moore's approach.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |title=The Bond of Colwyn Bay by Peredur Glyn|work=How is Timothy Dalton considered the best actor who portrayed Bond as it appeared in Ian Fleming's novels?|url=http://www.hmss.com/films/dalton/|accessdate=25 March 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; However, Dalton's films were criticised by many for their comparative lack of humour.&lt;ref name=&quot;rubin&quot; /&gt; Dalton's serious interpretation was not only in portraying the character, but also in performing most of the stunts of the action scenes himself.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Several Interviews with Timothy Dalton on his 007 portrayal|url=http://www.geocities.com/Hollywood/Film/7518/Bond_Eng/Bond_Eng.htm|archiveurl=http://www.webcitation.org/query?url=http://www.geocities.com/Hollywood/Film/7518/Bond_Eng/Bond_Eng.htm&amp;date=2009-10-25+08:04:00|archivedate=25 October 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===The post-Bond era===
After his Bond films, Dalton divided his work between stage, television and films, and diversified the characters he played. This helped him eliminate the 007 typecasting that followed him during the previous period. Dalton was nevertheless for a certain period considered to act in the Bond film '' [[GoldenEye]]''. Instead, he played the villainous matinee idol Neville Sinclair in 1991's ''[[The Rocketeer (film)|The Rocketeer]]'', and [[Rhett Butler]] in ''[[Scarlett (TV miniseries)|Scarlett]]'', the television [[miniseries]] sequel to ''[[Gone with the Wind (film)|Gone with the Wind]]''. He also appeared as criminal informant Eddie Myers in the acclaimed 1992 British miniseries ''Framed''.

During the second half of the 1990s he starred in several cable films, most notably the [[Provisional Irish Republican Army|Irish Republican Army]] drama, ''[[The Informant (film)|The Informant]]'', and the action thriller ''[[Made Men (film)|Made Men]]''. In the 1999 TV film ''[[Cleopatra (1999 film)|Cleopatra]]'' he played [[Julius Caesar]].

In 2003, he played a parody of James Bond named Damian Drake in the film ''[[Looney Tunes: Back in Action]]''. At the end of that year and the beginning of 2004, he returned to theatre to play [[Lord Asriel]] in the stage version of ''[[His Dark Materials]]''. In 2007, Dalton played Simon Skinner in the action/comedy film ''[[Hot Fuzz]]''.

Dalton returned once again to British television in a guest role for the ''[[Doctor Who]]'' 2009/10 two-part special &quot;[[The End of Time]]'’, playing [[Rassilon]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.bbc.co.uk/doctorwho/s4/news/latest/090728_news_o4 BBC – Doctor Who – New Years Day]&lt;/ref&gt; He was first heard in the role narrating a preview clip shown at the 2009 Comic Convention. As of 2010, he is currently a guest star on the American spy comedy ''[[Chuck (TV series)|Chuck]]'' as Alexei Volkoff.&lt;ref name = chuck&gt;{{cite news | last = Abrams  | first = Natalie | url = http://www.tvguide.com/News/Timothy-Dalton-Chuck-1022213.aspx | title = Timothy Dalton to Bond with Chuck | date = 26 August 2010 | work=[[TV Guide]] | accessdate =26 August 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Dalton voiced the character [[List of Toy Story characters#Mr Pricklepants|Mr. Pricklepants]] in ''[[Toy Story 3]]'', which was released on 18 June 2010.

==Personal life==
Dalton has one son, Alexander (born 7 August 1997), by [[Russia]]n model [[Oksana Grigorieva]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title=James Bond's Russian bride|url=http://english.pravda.ru/main/18/90/361/11480_Jamesbond.html|work=[[Pravda]]|date=8 December 2003}}. [http://www.webcitation.org/5rWIvFY6a WebCitation archive].&lt;/ref&gt; He was in a relationship with English actress [[Vanessa Redgrave]] (with whom he appeared in the 1971 motion picture ''Mary Queen of Scots'') between 1971 and 1986.{{Citation needed|date=July 2010}} Dalton is also a [[Manchester City F.C. supporters|Manchester City F.C. supporter]], and is often seen at the [[City of Manchester Stadium]] to watch his team play.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |title=Former James Bond Actor Timothy Dalton – Photo |url=http://uk.eurosport.yahoo.com/26122009/8/photo/former-james-bond-actor-timothy-dalton.html |publisher=http://uk.eurosport.yahoo.com |date=26 December 2009 |accessdate=4 January 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

He is one of 5 children from his mother Dorothy Dalton and father Peter Leggit Dalton. He is one of 3 brothers: himself,
Mark Dalton (father of Dominique Dalton), Stephen Dalton and he also has two sisters Annabelle Dalton and Suzzane Dalton (a perfume designer).{{cn|date=July 2011}}

==Filmography==
===Films===
{| class=&quot;wikitable&quot;
|-
! Year
! Title
! Role
! Notes
|-
| 1968
| ''[[The Lion in Winter]]''
| [[Philip II of France|Philip II]]
| Film debut
|-
| 1970
| ''[[Wuthering Heights (1970 film)|Wuthering Heights]]''
| [[Heathcliff (Wuthering Heights)|Heathcliff]]
|
|-
| 1970
| ''[[Cromwell (film)|Cromwell]]''
| [[Prince Rupert of the Rhine|Prince Rupert]]
|
|-
| 1970
| ''[[The Voyeur (film)|The Voyeur]]''
| Mark
|
|-
| 1971
|  ''[[Mary, Queen of Scots (film)|Mary, Queen of Scots]]''
| [[Henry Stuart, Lord Darnley|Henry – Lord Darnley]]
|
|-
| 1975
| ''[[Permission to Kill]]''
| Charles Lord
|
|-
| 1978
| ''[[Sextette]]''
| Sir Michael Barrington
|
|-
| 1978
| ''[[The Man Who Knew Love]]''
| Juan di Dios
|
|-
| 1979
| ''[[Agatha (film)|Agatha]]''
| Col. Archibald Christie
|
|-
| 1980
| ''[[Flash Gordon (film)|Flash Gordon]]''
| [[Prince Barin]]
|
|-
| 1981
| ''[[Chanel Solitaire]]''
| [[Boy Capel]]
|
|-
| 1985
| ''[[The Doctor and the Devils]]''
| Doctor Thomas Rock
|
|-
| 1987
| ''[[The Living Daylights]]''
| [[James Bond]]
| First role as Bond
|-
| 1988
| ''[[Hawks (film)|Hawks]]''
| Bancroft
|
|-
| 1989
| ''[[Brenda Starr (film)|Brenda Starr]]''
| Basil St. John
|
|-
| 1989
| ''[[License to Kill]]''
| [[James Bond]]
| Final role as Bond
|-
| 1990
| ''[[The King's Whore]]''
| Le Roi Vittorio Amadeo
|
|-
| 1991
| ''[[The Rocketeer (film)|The Rocketeer]]''
| Neville Sinclair
|
|-
| 1993
| ''[[Naked in New York]]''
| Elliot Price
|
|-
| 1996
| ''[[Salt Water Moose]]''
| Lester Parnell
|
|-
| 1997
| ''[[The Beautician and the Beast]]''
| Boris Pochenko
|
|-
| 1997
| ''[[The Informant (film)|The Informant]]''
| DCI Rennie
|
|-
| 1999
| ''[[Made Men]]''
| Sheriff Dex Drier
|
|-
| 1999
| ''[[The Reef (1999 film)|The Reef]]''
| Charles Darrow
|
|-
| 2000
| ''[[Time Share (2000 film)|Time Share]]'' (alt. title ''Bitter Suite'')
| Matthew &quot;Matt&quot; Farragher
|
|-
| 2001
| ''[[American Outlaws]]''
| [[Allan Pinkerton]]
|
|-
| 2003
| ''[[Looney Tunes: Back in Action]]''
| Damien Drake
|
|-
| 2006
| ''[[Tales from Earthsea (film)|Tales from Earthsea]]''
| Ged/Sparrowhawk
| Voice only
|-
| 2007
| ''[[Hot Fuzz]]''
| Simon Skinner
|
|-
| 2010
| ''[[Toy Story 3]]''
| [[Toy Story characters#Bonnie.27s toys|Mr. Pricklepants]]
| Voice only
|-
| 2010
| ''[[The Tourist (2010 film)|The Tourist]]''
| Chief Inspector Jones
|
|-
| 2011
| ''[[Hawaiian Vacation]]''
| Mr. Pricklepants
| Short film&lt;br /&gt;Voice only
|-
| 2011
| ''[[Clean Out]]''
| Kupfer
| '''''In production'''''
|-
| 2011
| ''[[Tinker Bell: Secret of the Wings]]''
| Lord Milori
| '''''In production'''''&lt;br /&gt;Voice only
|-
| 2011
| ''[[Small Fry (film)|Small Fry]]''
| Mr. Pricklepants
| Short film&lt;br /&gt;Voice only
|}

===Television===
* ''[[Sat'day While Sunday]]'' (TV series) (1967) .... Peter
* ''[[The Three Princes]]'' (TV) (1968) ...Ahmed
* ''[[Judge Dee: A Place of Great Evil]]'' (TV) (1969)
* ''[[Play of the Month: Five Finger Exercise]]'' (TV) (1970)
* ''[[Play of the Month: Candida]]'' (TV) (1971)
* ''[[Centennial (miniseries)|Centennial]]'' (TV [[miniseries]]) (1978) .... Oliver Seccombe
* ''[[The Flame Is Love]]'' (TV) (1979) .... Marquis de Guaita
* ''[[Charlie's Angels: Fallen Angel]]'' (TV) (1979) .... Damien Roth
* ''[[Antony and Cleopatra (1983 TV movie)|Antony and Cleopatra]]'' (TV) (1983) .... [[Mark Antony]]
* ''[[Jane Eyre (1983 BBC)|Jane Eyre]]'' (TV [[miniseries]]) (1983) .... Edward Fairfax Rochester
* ''[[Mistral's Daughter]]'' (TV [[miniseries]]) (1984) .... Perry Kilkullen
* ''[[The Master of Ballantrae]]'' (TV) (1984) .... Col. Francis Burke
* ''[[Florence Nightingale]]'' (TV) (1985) .... Richard Milnes
* ''[[Faerie Tale Theatre: The Emperor's New Clothes]]'' (TV) (1985) (voice)
* ''[[Sins (TV miniseries)|Sins]]'' (TV [[miniseries]]) (1986) .... Edmund Junot
* ''[[List of Tales from the Crypt episodes|Tales from the Crypt: Werewolf Concerto]]'' (TV) (1992) .... Lokai
* ''[[Framed (miniseries)|Framed]]'' (TV) (1992) .... Eddie Myers
* ''[[In the Wild: In Search of Wolves]] (TV) (1993) ...Host
* ''[[Lie Down with Lions (aka Red Eagle)]]'' (TV) (1994) .... Jack Carver
* ''[[Scarlett (TV miniseries)|Scarlett]]'' (TV [[miniseries]]) (1994) .... [[Rhett Butler]]
* ''[[Stories from My Childhood]]'' (TV) (1998) (voice) .... Prince Guidon
* ''ESU Emergency Services Unit'' (TV) (1998) (voice) ...Narrator
* ''[[Cleopatra (1999 film)|Cleopatra]]'' (TV) (1999) .... [[Julius Caesar]]
* ''[[Possessed (2000 film)|Possessed]]'' (TV) (2000) .... Fr. Willam Bowdern
* ''[[Dunkirk (TV series)|Dunkirk]]'' (TV) (2004) .... Narrator
* ''[[Hercules (TV miniseries)|Hercules]]'' (TV) (2005) .... Amphitryon
* ''[[The Sittaford Mystery|Marple: The Sittaford Mystery]]'' (TV) (2006) .... Clive Trevelyan
* ''[[Unknown Sender|Unknown Sender: If You're Seeing This Tape...]]'' ([[Strike.TV]]) (2008) ...Miles
* ''[[Doctor Who]]'' (TV) (2009/2010) .... Lord President of the Time Lords ([[Rassilon]]) / The Narrator&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.bbc.co.uk/doctorwho/s4/news/090728_news_o4 BBC – Doctor Who – New Years Day&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite |last=Anders |first=Charlie Jane |authorlink=Charlie Anders |title=Your First Look At Doctor Who's Next Big Guest Stars |url=http://io9.com/5291509/your-first-look-at-doctor-whos-next-big-guest-stars |date=15 June 2009 |publisher=[[io9]] |accessdate=16 June 2009|archiveurl=http://www.webcitation.org/5hgJMLX7S|archivedate=20 June 2009|deadurl=no}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* ''[[Chuck (TV series)|Chuck]]'' (2010/2011)
* ''Tinker Bell and the Mysterious Winter Woods (2011) ...Lord Milori

==Audiobook narration==
Novels by Benjamin Black (pseudonym of John Banville):
* &quot;[[Christine Falls]]&quot; (2007) AudioRenaissance
* &quot;{{Disambiguation needed|The Silver Swan|date=June 2011}}&quot; (2008) Macmillan Audio
* &quot;[[Elegy for April]]&quot; (2010) Macmillan Audio

==Stage work==

* ''[[A Game Called Arthur]]'' (1966)
* ''[[Little Malcolm And His Struggle Against The Eunuchs]]'' (1966)
* ''[[The Merchant of Venice]]'' (1966)
* ''[[Richard III (play)|Richard III]]'' (1966)
* ''[[As You Like It]]'' (1966)
* ''[[Love's Labour's Lost]]'' (1966)
* ''[[The Doctor's Dilemma (play)|The Doctor's Dilemma]]'' (1966)
* ''[[Saint Joan (play)|St. Joan]]'' (1966)
* ''[[Macbeth]]'' (1971)
* ''[[King Lear]]'' (1972)
* ''[[Love's Labour's Lost]]'' (1972)
* ''[[Henry V (play)|Henry V]]'' (1972)
* ''[[Romeo and Juliet]]'' (1972–1973)
* ''[[Henry IV, Part 1]]'' (1974)
* ''[[Henry IV, Part 2]]'' (1974)
* ''[[The Samaritan]]'' (1975)
* ''[[Black Comedy]]'' (1975)
* ''[[White Lies (film)|White Lies]]'' (1975)
* ''[[The Vortex]]'' (1976)
*''[[The Lunatic, the Lover and Poet]]'' (1977)
* ''[[The Romans (play)|The Romans]]'' (1977)
* ''[[Antony and Cleopatra(play)|Antony and Cleopatra]]'' (1981)
* ''[[Henry IV, Part 1]]'' (1982)
* ''[[Henry IV, Part 2]]'' (1982)
* ''[[Antony and Cleopatra]]'' (1986)
* ''[[The Taming of the Shrew]]'' (1986)
* ''[[A Touch of the Poet]]'' (1988)
* ''[[Love Letters (play)|Love Letters]]'' (1991)
* ''[[Star Crossed Lovers]]'' (1998)
* ''[[His Dark Materials]]'' (2003–2004) ... Lord Asriel

==References==
{{Reflist|2}}

{{S-start}}
{{Succession box
| title=Official James Bond Actor
| years=1987–1994
| before=[[Roger Moore]]&lt;br&gt;1973–1985
| after=[[Pierce Brosnan]]&lt;br&gt;1995–2004}}
{{end}}

==External links==
{{Wikiquote}}
{{Portal box|James Bond}}
* {{IMDb name|1096}}
* {{amg name|16690}}
* {{Screenonline name|id=492151}}
*[http://www.pelicanpromotions.com.au/dalton/biog.html Timothy Dalton's Biography at The Timothy Dalton Chat Group]
*[http://obr.lh.pl/timothydalton/index.html Timothy Dalton – Shakespearean James Bond]
*[http://www.bbc.co.uk/wales/northeast/guides/halloffame/showbiz/timothy_dalton.shtml Timothy Dalton's Biography at BBC North East Wales Showbiz]
*[http://www.bbc.co.uk/derby/features/famous_derby/timothy_dalton.shtml Timothy Dalton's Biography at BBC site]
*[http://www.timothydalton.org/ Timothy Dalton – Fan Site]
*[http://www.hmss.com/films/memory/ &quot;The Memory of Danger,&quot; article on Timothy Dalton and Ian Fleming's James Bond at HMSS.COM]

{{James Bond actors}}
{{Use dmy dates|date=August 2011}}

&lt;!-- Metadata: see [[Wikipedia:Persondata]] --&gt;
{{Persondata
 | NAME = Dalton, Timothy Peter
 | ALTERNATIVE NAMES = Dalton, Timothy
 | SHORT DESCRIPTION = English actor
 | DATE OF BIRTH = 21 March 1946
 | PLACE OF BIRTH = [[Colwyn Bay]], Wales, United Kingdom
 | DATE OF DEATH =
 | PLACE OF DEATH =
}}
{{DEFAULTSORT:Dalton, Timothy}}
[[Category:English film actors]]
[[Category:English stage actors]]
[[Category:English television actors]]
[[Category:Royal Shakespeare Company members]]
[[Category:English people of American descent]]
[[Category:English people of Italian descent]]
[[Category:English people of Irish descent]]
[[Category:Alumni of the Royal Academy of Dramatic Art]]
[[Category:People from Belper]]
[[Category:1946 births]]
[[Category:Living people]]
[[Category:People from Colwyn Bay]]

[[ar:تيموثي دالتون]]
[[ca:Timothy Dalton]]
[[cs:Timothy Dalton]]
[[cy:Timothy Dalton]]
[[da:Timothy Dalton]]
[[de:Timothy Dalton]]
[[et:Timothy Dalton]]
[[es:Timothy Dalton]]
[[eo:Timothy Dalton]]
[[eu:Timothy Dalton]]
[[fa:تیموتی دالتون]]
[[fr:Timothy Dalton]]
[[gl:Timothy Dalton]]
[[id:Timothy Dalton]]
[[it:Timothy Dalton]]
[[he:טימותי דלטון]]
[[sw:Timothy Dalton]]
[[hu:Timothy Dalton]]
[[nl:Timothy Dalton]]
[[ja:ティモシー・ダルトン]]
[[no:Timothy Dalton]]
[[nn:Timothy Dalton]]
[[pl:Timothy Dalton]]
[[pt:Timothy Dalton]]
[[ro:Timothy Dalton]]
[[ru:Далтон, Тимоти]]
[[sq:Timothy Dalton]]
[[simple:Timothy Dalton]]
[[sr:Тимоти Далтон]]
[[su:Timothy Dalton]]
[[fi:Timothy Dalton]]
[[sv:Timothy Dalton]]
[[th:ทิโมธี ดาลตัน]]
[[tr:Timothy Dalton]]
[[uk:Тімоті Далтон]]
[[zh:蒂莫西·道尔顿]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
