<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="1554010" ns="0" title="Menorah (Hanukkah)"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">[[File:Hanukkah_lamp.jpg|thumb|250px|right|[http://www.thejewishmuseum.org/onlinecollection/object_collection.php?objectid=8169&amp;ca=4&amp;areaSubmit_x=8&amp;areaSubmit_y=6 Hanukkah Lamp, Eastern Galicia or Western Ukraine, 18th to mid-19th century] from the collection of The [[Jewish Museum (New York)]]]]
[[File:Hanukkah Lamp - Lemberg F 5119.jpg|thumb|right|270|[http://www.thejewishmuseum.org/onlinecollection/object_collection.php?objectid=10680 Hanukkah Lamp, Lemberg (Lviv, Ukraine), 1867-72] from the collection of The [[Jewish Museum (New York)]]]]
[[Image:Chanukia.jpg|thumb|250px|right|Silver Hanukkah menorah.]]
The [[Hanukkah]] '''menorah''' ([[Hebrew]]: מנורת חנוכה ''m'noraht khanukkah'', pl. ''menorot'') (also {{lang-he|'''חַנֻכִּיָּה'''}} '''hanukiah''', or '''chanukkiyah''', pl. ''hanukiyot''/''chanukkiyot'', or [[Yiddish]]: חנוכּה לאמפּ ''khanike lomp'', [[Literal translation|lit.]]: Hanukkah lamp) is, strictly speaking, a nine-branched [[candelabrum]] lit during the eight-day [[Jewish holiday|holiday]] of Hanukkah, as opposed to the [[menorah (Temple)|seven-branched menorah]] used in the ancient Temple or as a symbol. The ninth holder, called the ''shamash'' (&quot;helper&quot; or &quot;servant&quot;), is for a candle used to light all other candles. The menorah is among the most widely produced articles of [[Jewish ceremonial art]]. The seven branched menorah is a traditional symbol of [[Judaism]], along with the [[Star of David]].&lt;ref&gt;Judaism A-Z Yacov Newman, Gavriel Sivan&lt;/ref&gt; 

==History==
===Background story===
[[File:RoyLindmanHanukkahMenorah.jpg|thumb|250px|Hanukkah Menorah with David's star]]
Hanukkah celebrates the re-dedication of the [[Holy Temple|Temple]] after the successful [[Maccabees|Jewish revolt]] against the [[Seleucid]] monarchy. The Jews found only enough ritually pure [[olive oil]] to light the menorah for one day, but the supply lasted eight days until a new supply could be obtained. In celebration of this miracle, the Hanukkah menorah has eight branches for eight candles or oil lamps.

===Lighting===
The Hanukkah menorah has a ninth branch for an auxiliary candle, the ''shamash''. The ''shamash'' is used to light the other candles. The holder for the ''shamash'' candle is distinguished in some way from the other eight, which must sit at the same height. Traditionally, the ''shamash'' is placed higher than the others, and often in the center, with four of the other candles on each side.

In addition to the ''shamash'', on the first night one candle is placed in the holder on the far right, and is lit using either the ''shamash'' or a different candle or match. Each night afterwards for the next seven nights, one additional candle is kindled. The night's [[Hannukah#Blessings_over_the_candles|blessings]] are started over the newest candle. So the candles are placed in the Hanukkah menorah from right to left and kindled from left to right.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.chabad.org/library/howto/wizard_cdo/aid/597137/jewish/Lighting-the-Menorah.htm|title=Lighting the Menorah|work=chabad.org|accessdate=December 11, 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt; The manner of lighting one additional candle each night follows the opinion of the [[House of Hillel]], which was accepted as [[halakha|Jewish law]]. The [[House of Shammai]] disagreed; it held that eight candles should be kindled the first night, seven the second night, and so on down to one candle on the last night.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.ou.org/chagim/chanukah/machloket.htm ''Hillel and Shammai - Two Opinions on the Lighting of the Menorah'' by Rabbi Pinchas Frankel]&lt;/ref&gt;

The lights can be candles or oil lamps. Electric lights are sometimes used and are acceptable in places where open flame is not permitted, such as a hospital room.

==Public displays==
{{main|Public menorah}}
[[File:Carter Menorah.jpg|thumb|left|150px|President Carter, Hanukkah Menorah Lighting, Lafayette Park, 1979.]]

The menorah is often displayed in public around Hanukkah time. [[Elected officials]] often participate in publicly lighting the menorah. The [[Chabad-Lubavitch]] movement is well associated with public lighting ceremonies, which it has done since a directive from their last [[Rebbe]], [[Menachem Mendel Schneerson]], in 1987.

{{main|White House Hanukkah Party}}

Since 1979, the [[White House]] has been represented at the lighting of a national menorah in celebration of Hanukkah, beginning with the attendance of President [[Jimmy Carter]] in the ceremony in Lafayette Park. In 2009, both White House [[Chief of Staff]] [[Rahm Emanuel]] and Governor [[Arnold Schwarzenegger]] lit the menorah.&lt;ref&gt;http://newsblaze.com/story/20091212111718zzzz.nb/topstory.html Schwarzenegger Joins Chanukah Celebration at Capitol Menorah Lighting Ceremony&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.google.com/hostednews/ap/article/ALeqM5gS8mxlE5ABJ06teq4Yubh6hMmcDgD9CIN6H81|title=Emanuel lights National Menorah at White House|date=2009-12-13|publisher=The Associated Press|accessdate=19 December 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt; Additionally, beginning with President [[Bill Clinton]] in 1993, a Hanukkah menorah was lit in the [[Oval Office]] of the White House, and in 2001, President [[George W. Bush]] began the annual tradition of a [[White House Hanukkah Party]] in the White House residence, which includes a menorah candle lighting ceremony. 

In the [[United Kingdom]], the [[House of Commons of the United Kingdom]] each years holds a menorah lighting at the home of the Speaker of the House of Commons.  The menorah currently used was commissioned by the Rt. Hon. [[Michael Martin, Baron Martin of Springburn|Michael J. Martin]] MP, former Speaker of the House of Commons.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.mplevene.co.uk/staticpage.aspx?spageid=101480|title=M.P. Levene Special Commissions|accessdate=19 December 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The world's largest menorah is in [[Manado]] in [[Indonesia]]; a country with a Jewish population of around 20 people only. It stands at 62 feet tall. &lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.nytimes.com/2010/11/23/world/asia/23indo.html|title= In Sliver of Indonesia, Public Embrace of Judaism |accessdate=17 January 2011 | work=The New York Times|first=Norimitsu|last=Onishi|date=22 November 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; Another big menorah is in [[New York City]] and stands at 32 feet and is lit at [[Fifth Avenue]] and 59th Street in [[Manhattan]] near [[Central Park]]. A 4,000-pound structure, it is the work of [[Israel|Israeli]] artist [[Yaacov Agam]]. Because of the menorah’s height, [[Consolidated Edison|Con Edison]] assists the lighting by using a [[Crane (machine)|crane]] to lift each person to the top.

===Legalities===
In the United States, the public display of menorot and [[Christmas tree]]s on public grounds has been the source of legal battles, due the [[separation of church and state]]. Specifically, in the 1989 ''[[County of Allegheny v. ACLU]]'' case,the majority of the [[US Supreme Court]] ruled that the public display of menorot and Christmas trees did not violate the [[Establishment Clause]] because the two symbols were not endorsements of the Jewish or Christian faith, rather the two items are part of the same [[winter-holiday season]], which the court found, had attained a secular status in U.S. society.

==Name==
In the English-speaking [[Jewish population|diaspora]], the lamp is most commonly called a &quot;Hanukkah menorah,&quot; or simply &quot;menorah&quot; for short, whereas in Modern Hebrew it is exclusively called a ''chanukkiyah'', and the Hebrew word ''menorah'' simply means &quot;lamp&quot;. The term ''chanukkiyah'' was coined at the end of the nineteenth century in [[Jerusalem]] by the wife of [[Eliezer Ben Yehuda]], the reviver of the [[Hebrew language]].

==Public collections==
[[File:Truman receives menorah.jpg|thumb|left|U.S. President [[Harry S. Truman]] in the [[Oval Office]], receiving a Hanukkah Menorah as a gift from the Prime Minister of Israel, [[David Ben-Gurion]] (center). To the right is [[Abba Eban]], the Ambassador of Israel to the United States.]]
Many museums have notable collections of Hanukkah menorot, including the [[Israel Museum]], the [[Metropolitan Museum of Art]],&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.metmuseum.org/special/se_event.asp?OccurrenceId=%7BF58FCE9C-DE58-11D5-9414-00902786BF44%7D]&lt;/ref&gt; and the [[Jewish Museum (London)|Jewish Museum]], which owns the [[Lindo lamp]].&lt;ref&gt;Jerusalem Post, Jul 21, 2009, London's Jewish Museum preparing to buy 300-year-old hanukkia for new location, Sarah Sechan  [http://fr.jpost.com/servlet/Satellite?pagename=JPost/JPArticle/ShowFull&amp;cid=1246443871704]&lt;/ref&gt; Outside of the [[Knesset]], or Israeli [[parliament]], there is a 5 metre high bronze menorah called the [[Knesset Menorah]].

==Modern menorah==
Modern menorot, menorot with less-traditional designs, are gaining in popularity with hundreds of new designs coming out since 2007.&lt;ref&gt;http://ifitshipitshere.blogspot.com/2008/11/mongo-modern-menorah-list-over-140-hip.html&lt;/ref&gt; There are websites dedicated to celebrating the modern menorah.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.moderntribe.com/judaica/modern_menorot&lt;/ref&gt; One popular type of modern menorah is the modular menorah: menorot made up of several different pieces which can be re-arranged each of the eight nights of Hanukkah. To be kosher, one candle holder sits higher than the others for the shamash, the worker candle, the one which is used to light the other candles.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.moderntribe.com/cms/modern_modular_menorot&lt;/ref&gt;

==Notes==
{{reflist}}

==See also==
*[[Kinara]]

==External Links==
*[http://www.nationalmenorah.org/ Yearly lighting of the Menorah at the White House in Washington DC]
* Various types of [http://www.judaicawebstore.com/menorahs-C106.aspx Hanukkah Menorah]
*[http://www.thejewishmuseum.org/onlinecollection/collection_results.php?jn=Hanukkah+Lamp&amp;judaicaSubmit.x=6&amp;judaicaSubmit.y=12 Hanukkah Lamps] from the collection of The [[Jewish Museum (New York)]]

{{Commonscat|Hanukiah}}
{{Jewish life}}
{{Hanukkah Footer}}

&lt;!--Categories--&gt;
[[Category:Jewish ritual objects]]
[[Category:Hanukkah]]
[[Category:Candelabra]]

&lt;!--Other languages--&gt;
[[bg:Ханукия]]
[[ca:Hanukkiyyà]]
[[cs:Chanukija]]
[[de:Chanukkia]]
[[fr:Hanoukkia]]
[[it:Chanukkià]]
[[he:חנוכייה]]
[[lad:Hanukkiya]]
[[nl:Chanoekia]]
[[ja:ハヌッキーヤー]]
[[nn:Hanukkijá]]
[[pl:Chanukija]]
[[pt:Chanukiá]]
[[ro:Hanuchia]]
[[ru:Ханукия]]
[[sk:Chanukija]]
[[sv:Chanukkia]]
[[tr:Hanukiya]]
[[uk:Ханукія]]
[[zh:再獻聖殿節燈臺]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
