<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="15621" ns="0" title="John Grierson"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{other persons}}
{{Infobox writer &lt;!-- for more information see [[:Template:Infobox writer/doc]] --&gt;
| name = John Grierson
| image = 
| imagesize = 190px
| caption = {{deletable image-caption|Saturday, 17 September 2011|date=October 2011}}
| pseudonym =
| birth_name = John Grierson
| birth_date = {{birth date|1898|4|26|df=y}}
| birth_place =  [[Deanston]], [[Stirling (council area)|Stirling]],&lt;br&gt;Scotland
| death_date = {{death date and age|df=yes|1972|2|19|1898|4|26}}
| death_place = [[Bath, Somerset]],&lt;br&gt;England
| occupation = Documentary maker
| nationality = 
| period =
| genre = 
| subject =
| movement =
| influences = 
| influenced =
| signature =
| website = 
}}

'''John Grierson''' (26 April 1898 &amp;ndash; 19 February 1972) was a pioneering Scottish documentary maker, often considered the father of British and Canadian [[documentary film]]. According to popular myth, in 1926, Grierson coined the term [[Documentary#Defining documentary|&quot;documentary&quot;]] to describe a non-fiction film.&lt;ref name=RFL&gt;Ann Curthoys, Marilyn Lake [http://books.google.com/books?id=JE6YM8jcRucC&amp;pg=PA151&amp;dq=john+grierson+documentary+1926&amp;hl=en&amp;ei=5wkUTcb5OMq7hAeixPW2Dg&amp;sa=X&amp;oi=book_result&amp;ct=result&amp;resnum=5&amp;ved=0CDoQ6AEwBA#v=onepage&amp;q=john%20grierson%20documentary%201926&amp;f=false Connected worlds: history in transnational perspective, Volume 2004] p.151. Australian National University Press&lt;/ref&gt;

==Early life==
Grierson was born in [[Deanston]], near [[Doune]], Scotland. His  father was a schoolmaster, his mother a [[suffragette]] and ardent [[UK Labour Party|Labour Party]] activist.  From an early age, both parents steeped their son in [[Liberalism|liberal]] politics, [[humanistic]] ideals, and [[Calvinist]] moral and religious philosophies, particularly the notion that education was essential to individual freedom and that hard and meaningful work was the way to prove oneself worthy in the sight of God.  

After service on [[minesweeper (ship)|minesweepers]] in the [[Royal Navy]] during [[World War I]], Grierson entered the [[University of Glasgow]], where he spent a good part of his academic career enmeshed in impassioned political discussion and leftist political activism. 

In 1924, after graduating from the university in English and Moral Philosophy, he received a [[Rockefeller Foundation|Rockefeller Research Fellowship]] to study in the United States at the [[University of Chicago]], and later at Columbia and the [[University of Wisconsin–Madison]]. His research focus was the [[psychology]] of [[propaganda]]--the impact of the press, film, and other mass media on forming public opinion.  Grierson was particularly interested in the popular appeal and influence of the [[yellow journalism|&quot;yellow&quot; (tabloid) press]], and the influence and role of these journals on the education of new American citizens from abroad.

==Social critic==
In his review of [[Robert Flaherty]]'s film ''[[Moana (film)|Moana]]'' (1926) in the ''[[New York Sun (historical)|New York Sun]]'' (8 February 1926), Grierson wrote that it had 'documentary' value.&lt;ref name=RFL/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.jonathanrosenbaum.com/?p=16639  1975 Review of Moana, by Jonathan Rosenbaum]&lt;/ref&gt;
In his essay &quot;First Principles of Documentary&quot; (1932), Grierson argued that the principles of documentary were that cinema's potential for observing life could be exploited in a new art form; that the &quot;original&quot; actor and &quot;original&quot; scene are better guides than their fiction counterparts to interpreting the modern world; and that materials &quot;thus taken from the raw&quot; can be more real than the acted article. In this regard, Grierson's views align with the Soviet filmmaker [[Dziga Vertov]]'s contempt for dramatic fiction as &quot;bourgeois excess&quot;, though with considerably more subtlety. Grierson's definition of documentary as &quot;creative treatment of actuality&quot; has gained some acceptance, though it presents philosophical questions about documentaries containing stagings and reenactments.

Like a number of other social critics of the time, Grierson was profoundly concerned about what he perceived to be clear threats to democracy.  In the US, he encountered a marked tendency toward political reaction, anti-democratic sentiments, and political apathy.  He read and agreed with the journalist and political philosopher [[Walter Lippmann]]'s book ''Public Opinion'' which blamed the erosion of democracy in part on the fact that the political and social complexities of contemporary society made it difficult if not impossible for the public to comprehend and respond to issues vital to the maintenance of democratic society.

In Grierson's view, a way to counter these problems was to involve citizens in their government with the kind of engaging excitement generated by the popular press, which simplified and dramatized public affair.  It was during this time that Grierson developed a conviction that motion pictures could play a central role in promoting this process.  (It has been suggested that some of Grierson's notions regarding the social and political uses of film were influenced by reading [[Vladimir Lenin|Lenin's]] writing about film as education and propaganda.)

Grierson's emerging view of film was as a form of social and political communication—a mechanism for social reform, education, and perhaps spiritual uplift.  His view of Hollywood movie-making was considerably less sanguine: 

:&quot;In an age when the faiths, the loyalties, and the purposes have been more than usually undermined, mental fatigue--or is it spiritual fatigue?--represents a large factor in everyday experience.  Our cinema magnate does no more than exploit the occasion.  He also, more or less frankly, is a [[cannabis|dope]] pedlar.&quot;

==Film critic==
Grierson's emerging and outspoken film philosophies caught the attention of [[New York City|New York]] film critics at the time.  He was asked to write criticism for the ''[[New York Sun]]''. At the ''Sun'', Grierson wrote articles on film aesthetics and audience reception, and developed broad contacts in the film world. According to popular myth, in the course of this writing stint, Grierson coined the term &quot;documentary&quot; in writing about [[Robert J. Flaherty]]'s film ''[[Moana (film)|Moana]]'' ([[1926 in film|1926]]): &quot;Of course ''Moana'', being a visual account of events in the daily life of a Polynesian youth and his family, has documentary value.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;''New York Sun'', 8 February 1926.&lt;/ref&gt; 

During this time, Grierson was also involved in scrutinizing the film industries of other countries. He may have been involved in arranging to bring [[Sergei Eisenstein]]'s groundbreaking film ''[[The Battleship Potemkin]]'' ([[1925 in film|1925]]) to US audiences for the first time.  Eisenstein's editing techniques and film theories, particularly the use of montage, would have a significant influence on Grierson's own work.

==Filmmaker==
Grierson returned to Great Britain in the late 1930s armed with the sense that film could be enlisted to deal with the problems of the [[Great Depression in the United Kingdom|Great Depression]], and to build national morale and national consensus.  Filmmaking for Grierson was an exalted calling; the Filmmaker a patriot. In all of this there was more than a little elitism, a stance reflected in Grierson's many dicta of the time:  &quot;The elect have their duty.&quot;  &quot;I look on cinema as a pulpit, and use it as a propagandist.&quot;  

In the US Grierson had met pioneering documentary filmmaker [[Robert Flaherty]]. Grierson respected Flaherty immensely for his contributions to documentary form and his attempts to use the camera to bring alive the lives of everyday people and everyday events.  Less commendable in Grierson's view was Flaherty's focus on exotic and faraway cultures. (&quot;In the profounder kind of way&quot;, wrote Grierson of Flaherty, &quot;we live and prosper each of us by denouncing the other&quot;). In Grierson's view, the focus of film should be on the everyday drama of ordinary people. As Grierson wrote in his diaries: &quot;Beware the ends of the earth and the exotic: the drama is on your doorstep wherever the slums; are, wherever there is malnutrition, wherever there is exploitation and cruelty.&quot; &quot;'You keep your savages in the far place Bob; we are going after the savages of Birmingham,' I think I said to him pretty early on. And we did.&quot;)

On his return to England, Grierson became Assistant Films Officer of the [[Empire Marketing Board]] (EMB), a governmental agency which had been established several years earlier to promote British world trade and British unity throughout the [[British Empire|empire]]. One of the major functions of the EMB was publicity, which the Board accomplished through exhibits, posters, and publications and films. It was within the context of this State funded organization that the &quot;documentary&quot; as we know it today really got its start.

In late 1929 Grierson and his cameraman, [[Basil Emmott]], completed his first film, ''[[Drifters (1929 film)|Drifters]]'', which he wrote, produced and directed. The film, which follows the heroic work of [[North Sea]] herring fishermen, was a radical departure from anything being made by the British film industry or Hollywood. A large part of its innovation lie in the fierce boldness in bringing the camera to rugged locations such as a small boat in the middle of a gale, while leaving relatively less of the action staged. The choice of topic was chosen less from Grierson's curiosity than the fact that he discovered that the Financial Secretary had made the herring industry his hobbyhorse. It premiered in a private film club in London on a double-bill with [[Sergei Eisenstein|Eisenstein's]] then controversial film ''[[The Battleship Potemkin]]'' (which was banned from general release in Britain until 1954), and received high praise from both its sponsors and the press.  

After this success, Grierson moved away from film direction into a greater focus on production and administration within the EMB.  He became a tireless organizer and recruiter for the EMB, enlisting a stable of energetic young filmmakers into the film unit between 1930 and 1933.  Those enlisted included filmmakers [[Basil Wright]], [[Edgar Anstey]], [[Stuart Legg]], [[Paul Rotha]], [[Sir Arthur Elton, 10th Baronet|Arthur Elton]], [[Humphrey Jennings]], [[Harry Watt (director)|Harry Watt]], and [[Alberto Cavalcanti]].  This group formed the core of what was to become known as the British [[Documentary Film Movement]]. [[Robert Flaherty]] himself also worked briefly for the unit. 

In 1933 the EMB Film Unit was disbanded, a casualty of Depression era economics.  Grierson's boss at the EMB moved to the [[General Post Office (United Kingdom)|General Post Office]] (GPO) as its first public relations officer, with the stipulation that he could bring the EMB film unit with him.   Grierson's crew were charged with demonstrating the ways in which the Post Office facilitated modern communication and brought the nation together, a task aimed as much at GPO workers as the general public.  During Grierson's administration, the [[GPO Film Unit]] produced a series of groundbreaking films, including ''[[Night Mail]]'' (dir. [[Basil Wright]] and [[Harry Watt (director)|Harry Watt]], 1936) and ''[[Coal Face]]'' (dir. [[Alberto Cavalcanti]], 1935). In 1934 he produced at the GPO Film Unit the award winning ''[[The Song of Ceylon]]'' (dir. [[Basil Wright]]) which was sponsored jointly by the Ceylon Tea Propagands Bureau and the EMB.

Grierson eventually grew restless with having to work within the bureaucratic and budgetary confines of government sponsorship.  In response, he sought out private industry sponsorship for film production. He was finally successful in getting the British gas industry to underwrite an annual film program.  Perhaps the most significant works produced during this time were ''Housing Problems'' (dir. [[Sir Arthur Elton, 10th Baronet|Arthur Elton]], [[Edgar Anstey]], [[John Taylor (documentary filmmaker)|John Taylor]], and Grierson's sister [[Ruby Grierson]], 1935). 

In 1938, Grierson was invited by the Canadian government to study the country's film production. He proposed that the government create a national coordinating body for the production of films. In 1939, Canada created the National Film Commission, which would later become the [[National Film Board of Canada]]. Grierson was the first Commissioner of the Board. When Canada entered [[World War II]] in 1939, the NFB focused on the production of [[propaganda]] films, many of which Grierson directed. After the war, it focused on producing documentaries that reflected the lives of Canadians. The NFB is recognized around the world for producing quality films, many of which have won [[Academy Awards]].

In 1945 Grierson was dismissed from his post as Commissioner of the NFB after allegations of communist sympathy regarding several of the films the Board had produced during the war.  Following his dismissal, and that of three of his coworkers, Grierson returned to Scotland.

During the 1950s he worked at [[Southall Studios]] in [[West London]].

From 1957 to 1967 Grierson hosted a successful weekly television program on [[Scotland|Scottish]] television, ''[[This Wonderful World]]'', which showed excerpts from outstanding documentaries. In 1957 he received a special [[Canadian Film Award]].

==Grierson Documentary Film Awards==
{{main|Grierson Awards}}
The Grierson Documentary Film Awards were established in 1972 to commemorate John Grierson and
are currently supervised by The Grierson Trust. The aim of the awards is to recognise ''outstanding films that demonstrate integrity, originality and technical excellence, together with social or cultural significance''.[http://www.griersontrust.org/past_awards.htm]

Grierson Awards are presented annually in nine categories:
*Best Documentary on a Contemporary Issue
*Best Documentary on the Arts
*Best Historical Documentary
*Best Documentary on Science or the Natural World
*The Frontier Post Award for Most Entertaining Documentary
*Best Drama Documentary
*Best International Cinema Documentary
*Best Newcomer
* Trustees' Award

==Filmography==
Filmography as director:
* ''[[Drifters (1929 film)|Drifters]]'' (1929; first screened at the British premiere of ''[[Battleship Potemkin]]'')
* ''[[Granton Trawler]]'' (1934)

Filmography as producer/creative contributor:

* ''[[O'er Hll and Dale]]'' (dir.  [[Basil Wright]] 1932)
* ''[[UP-STREAM: A Story of the Scottish Salmon Fisheries]]'' (dir.  [[Sir Arthur Elton, 10th Baronet|Arthur Elton]] 1932)
* ''[[Cargo from Jamaica]]''  (dir.  [[Basil Wright]] 1933)
* ''[[Industrial Britain]]''  (dir.  [[Robert Flaherty]] 1933)
* ''[[Cable Ship]]''  (dir. ([[Alexander Shaw (director)|Alexander Shaw]] and [[Stuart Legg]] 1933)
* ''[[Coming of the Dial]]''  (dir.  [[Stuart Legg]] 1933)
* ''[[Liner Cruising South]]''  (dir. [[Basil Wright]] 1933)
* ''[[Man of Aran]]''  (dir.  [[Robert Flaherty]] 1934)
* ''[[New Operator]]''  (dir. [[Stuart Legg]] 1934)
* ''[[Pett and Pott: A Fairy Story of the Suburbs]]''   (dir.  [[Alberto Cavalcanti]] 1934)
* ''[[Post Haste]]''  (dir.  [[Humphrey Jennings]] 1934)
* ''[[Spring Comes to England]]''  dir.  [[Donald Taylor]]{{dn|date=October 2011}} 1934)
* ''[[Six-thirty Collection]]''  (dir.  [[Harry Watt (director)|Harry Watt]] and [[Edgar Anstey]] 1934)
* ''[[Song of Ceylon]]''  (dir.  [[Basil Wright]] 1934)
* ''[[BBC: The Voice of Britain]]''  (dir.  [[Stuart Legg]] 1935)
* ''[[A Colour Box]]''  (dir.  [[Len Lye]] 1935)
* ''[[Housing Problems]]'' (dir.  [[Edgar Anstey]], [[Sir Arthur Elton, 10th Baronet|Arthur Elton]] 1935)
* ''[[Introducing the Dial]]'' (dir.  [[Stuart Legg]] 1935)
* ''[[Coal Face]]''  (dir. [[Alberto Cavalcanti]] 1935)
* ''[[B.B.C. Droitwich]]''  (dir.  [[Harry Watt (director)|Harry Watt]] 1935)
* ''[[Night Mail]]'' ( dir. ([[Basil Wright]], and [[Harry Watt (director)|Harry Watt]] 1936)
* ''[[Saving of Bill Blewitt]]''  (dir. [[Basil Wright]]  1936)
* ''[[Line To The Tschierva Hut]]''  (dir. [[Alberto Cavalcanti]]  1937)
* ''[[Children At School]]''  (dir. [[Basil Wright]]  1937)
* ''[[We Live In Two Worlds]]''  (dir. [[Alberto Cavalcanti]]  1937)
* ''[[Daily Round]]''  (dir. [[Richard Massingham]], [[Karl Urbahn]]  1937)
* ''[[Trade Tattoo]]''  (dir. [[Len Lye]]  1937)
* ''[[The Face of Scotland]]''  (dir. [[Basil Wright]]  1938)
* ''[[The Children's Story]]''  (dir. [[Alexander Shaw (director)|Alexander Shaw]]  1938)
* ''[[Scotland for Fitness]]''  (dir. [[Brian Salt]]  1938)
* ''[[They Made the Land]]''  (dir. [[Mary Field]]  1938)
* ''[[Sport in Scotland]]''  (dir. [[Stanley L. Russell]]  1938)
* ''[[Wealth of a Nation]]''  (dir. [[Donald Alexander]]  1938)
* ''[[Sea Food]]''  (1938)
* ''[[The Londoners]]''  (dir. [[John Taylor (director)]]  1939)
* ''[[Judgement Deferred]]''  (dir. [[John Baxter (director)|John Baxter]]  1951)
* ''[[Brandy for the Parson]]''  (dir. [[John Eldridge]]  1952)
* ''[[The Brave Don't Cry]]''  (dir. [[Philip Leacock]]  1952)
* ''[[Miss Robin Hood]]''  (dir. [[John Guillermin]]  1952)
* ''[[Time Gentlemen, Please!]]''  (dir. [[Lewis Gilbert]]  1952)
* ''[[You're Only Young Twice]]''  (dir. [[Terry Bishop]]  1952)
* ''[[Man of Africa]]''  (dir. [[Cyril Frankel]]  1953)
* ''[[Background (1953 film)|Background]]''  (dir. [[Daniel Birt]]  1953)
* ''[[Laxdale Hall]]''  (dir. [[John Eldridge]]  1953)
* ''[[The Oracle (film)|The Oracle]]''  (dir. [[C.M. Pennington-Richards]]  1953)
* ''[[Child's Play (1954 film)|Child's Play]]''  (dir. [[Margaret Thomson]]  1954)
* ''[[Devil on Horseback]]''  (dir. [[Cyril Frankel]]  1954)
* ''[[Rivers at Work]]''  (dir. [[Lew Davidson]]  1958)
* ''[[This Wonderful World]]''  (dir. various  1957-67)
* ''[[Seawards the Great Ships]]''  (dir. [[Hilary Harris]]  1960)
* ''[[The Heart of Scotland]]''  (dir. [[Laurence Henson]]  1961)
* ''[[The Creative Process]]''  (dir. [[Donald McWilliams]]  1961)
* ''[[Health of a City]]''  (dir. [[Derek Williams]]  1965)
* ''[[I Remember, I Remember]]''  (dir. [[James Sutherland]]  1968)

== Bibliographies ==
*[http://www.lib.berkeley.edu/MRC/documentarybib.html#grierson Grierson Bibliography at UC Berkeley]
*Gary Evans, ''John Grierson and the National Film Board: The Politics of Wartime Propaganda'' (University of Toronto Press, 1984)
*Joyce Nelson, ''The Colonized Eye: Rethinking the Grierson Legend'' (Between the Lines, 1988)

== Documentaries About Grierson ==
In a short film ''John Grierson at the NFT'' (1959) he recalls the British documentary film movement. This is included in the ''Land of Promise'' Region 2 DVD set (BFI 2008).
Grierson.[http://www.nfb.ca/trouverunfilm/fichefilm.php?id=10466&amp;v=h&amp;lg=en&amp;exp=${grierson}]  Produced and directed by [[Roger Blais]].  Montreal, Que.: [[National Film Board of Canada]], c. 1973.  59 min.

==See also==
* [[Edgar Anstey]]
* [[Sir Arthur Elton, 10th Baronet|Arthur Elton]]
* [[Robert Flaherty]]
* [[Humphrey Jennings]]
* [[Stuart Legg]]
* [[Paul Rotha]]
* [[Basil Wright]]

== References ==
{{reflist}}

== Sources ==
*[http://academy.ca/hist/history.cfm?categid=100008&amp;shownum=9&amp;winonly=0&amp;awards=4&amp;rtype=5&amp;curstep=4 Canada's Awards Database]

*Credits from:  British Film Institute Catalog (Film Index International)

==External links==
* [http://www.griersontrust.org/ The Grierson Trust]
*{{IMDb name|0340961}}
* [http://www.is.stir.ac.uk/libraries/collections/spcoll/media/grierson.php The John Grierson Archive at The University of Stirling]
* [http://www.screenonline.org.uk/people/id/454202/ Bfi Screenonline entry.]
* [http://www.latrobe.edu.au/screeningthepast/firstrelease/fr0799/ktfr7e.htm John Grierson in South Africa: Afrikaaner nationalism and the National Film Board]
* [http://www.nfb.ca/portraits/fiche.php?id=278&amp;v=h&amp;lg=en John Grierson's NFB biography]
* [http://www.hatii.arts.gla.ac.uk/MultimediaStudentProjects/98-99/9500048s/project/html/index.htm/  Online essay about Grierson and Flaherty from the University of Glasgow] (no link)
* [http://www.virtual-history.com/movie/person/2385/john-grierson Literature on John Grierson]
* [http://ssa.nls.uk/search.cfm?search_sort_order=Film.dateRelease%2CFilm.name&amp;search_sort_direction=ASC&amp;search_term=john+grierson&amp;search_fields=7&amp;search_join_type=Phrase&amp;search_fuzzy=yes&amp;videos_only=1&amp;search_mode=Advanced&amp;submit=Search+%3E%3E%3E National Library of Scotland: SCOTTISH SCREEN ARCHIVE] (selection of archive films relating to John Grierson)


{{s-start}}
{{s-culture}}
{{succession box|title=Government Film Commissioner and &lt;br&gt;Chairperson of the [[National Film Board of Canada]]|before=New position|after=[[Ross McLean (film producer)|Ross McLean]]|years=1939-1945}}
{{s-end}}

{{Persondata &lt;!-- Metadata: see [[Wikipedia:Persondata]]. --&gt;
| NAME              = Grierson, John
| ALTERNATIVE NAMES = 
| SHORT DESCRIPTION = Scottish filmmaker
| DATE OF BIRTH     = 26 April 1898
| PLACE OF BIRTH    = [[Deanston]], [[Stirling (council area)|Stirling]],&lt;br&gt;Scotland
| DATE OF DEATH     = 19 February 1972
| PLACE OF DEATH    = [[Bath, Somerset]],&lt;br&gt;England
}}
{{DEFAULTSORT:Grierson, John}}
[[Category:1898 births]]
[[Category:1972 deaths]]
[[Category:Scottish documentary filmmakers]]
[[Category:Scottish film directors]]
[[Category:Scottish film producers]]
[[Category:Scottish sailors]]
[[Category:Alumni of the University of Glasgow]]
[[Category:Canadian documentary filmmakers]]
[[Category:Canadian film directors]]
[[Category:Propaganda film directors]]
[[Category:Cinema pioneers]]
[[Category:People from Stirling (council area)]]
[[Category:Government Film Commissioners and Chairpersons of the National Film Board of Canada]]

[[de:John Grierson]]
[[es:John Grierson]]
[[fr:John Grierson]]
[[it:John Grierson]]
[[pt:John Grierson]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
