<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="15641" ns="0" title="Joseph Stalin"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Redirect|Stalin}}
{{pp-semi-indef}}{{pp-move-indef}}
{{Infobox officeholder
| name             = &lt;div class=&quot;center&quot;&gt;Joseph Stalin&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;center&quot; style=&quot;font-size:smaller&quot;&gt; Russian: Иосиф Виссарионович Сталин &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;center&quot; style=&quot;font-size:smaller&quot;&gt; Georgian: იოსებ ბესარიონის ძე სტალინი&lt;/div&gt;
| image        = StalinPortrait.jpg
| imagesize    = 
| caption      = Stalin in military fatigues, post-1943
| office       = [[Premier of the Soviet Union|Chairman]] of the [[Council of Ministers (Soviet Union)|Council of Ministers]]
| 1blankname   = [[First Deputy Premier of the Soviet Union|First&amp;nbsp;Deputies]]
| 1namedata    = [[Nikolai Voznesensky]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Vyacheslav Molotov]]
| term_start   = 6 May 1941
| term_end     = 5 March 1953
| predecessor  = [[Vyacheslav Molotov]]
| successor    = [[Georgy Malenkov]]
| office2      = [[General Secretary of the Communist Party of the Soviet Union|General Secretary]] of the [[Communist Party of the Soviet Union]]
| term_start2  = 3 April 1922
| term_end2    = 16 October 1952
| predecessor2 = [[Vyacheslav Molotov]]&lt;br /&gt;&lt;small&gt;(as [[General Secretary of the Communist Party of the Soviet Union|Responsible Secretary]])&lt;/small&gt;
| successor2   = [[Nikita Khrushchev]]&lt;br /&gt;&lt;small&gt;(office reestablished)&lt;/small&gt;
| office3      = [[Minister of Defence (Soviet Union)|People's Commissar for the Defense of the Soviet Union]]
| premier3     = Himself
| term_start3  = 19 July 1941
| term_end3    = 25 February 1946
| predecessor3 = [[Semyon Timoshenko]]
| successor3   = [[Nikolai Bulganin]]&lt;br /&gt;&lt;small&gt;after vacancy&lt;/small&gt;
| birth_date   = {{Birth date|1878|12|18|df=y}}
| birthname    = Ioseb Besarionis dze Jughashvili
({{lang-ka|იოსებ ბესარიონის ძე ჯუღაშვილი}})
| birth_place  = [[Gori, Georgia|Gori]], [[Tiflis Governorate]], [[Russian Empire]]
| death_date   = {{Death date and age|1953|3|5|1878|12|18|df=y}} (stroke)
| death_place  = [[Kuntsevo Dacha]] near Moscow, [[Russian SFSR]], [[Soviet Union]]
| party        = [[Communist Party of the Soviet Union]]
| nationality  = [[Soviet people|Soviet]]
| ethnicity    = [[Georgians|Georgian]]
| spouse       = [[Ekaterina Svanidze]] (1906–1907)&lt;br /&gt;[[Nadezhda Alliluyeva]] (1919–1932)
| children     = [[Yakov Dzhugashvili]], [[Vasily Dzhugashvili]], [[Svetlana Alliluyeva]]
| religion     = 
| allegiance   = {{flag|Soviet Union|1922}}
| branch       = [[Soviet Armed Forces]]
| serviceyears = 1943–1953
| rank         = [[Marshal of the Soviet Union]] (1943–1945) (de jure) &lt;br&gt; [[Generalissimus of the Soviet Union]] (1945–1953) (de facto)
| commands     = ''All'' (supreme commander)
| battles      = World War II
| awards       = 
| signature    = Stalin Signature.svg
}}

'''Joseph Vissarionovich Stalin''' (18 December 1878&lt;ref name=&quot;dob&quot;/&gt;&amp;nbsp;– 5 March 1953; born '''Iosif Vissarionovich Dzhugashvili''') was the [[Premier of the Soviet Union]] from 6 May 1941 to 5 March 1953. He was among the [[Bolshevik]] revolutionaries who brought about the [[October Revolution]] and had held the position of [[General Secretary of the Communist Party of the Soviet Union#List of General Secretaries|first General Secretary of the Communist Party of the Soviet Union's]] [[Central Committee of the Communist Party of the Soviet Union|Central Committee]] from 1922 until his death in 1953. While formally the office of the General Secretary was elective and was not initially regarded as the top position in the Soviet state, after [[Vladimir Lenin]]'s death in 1924, Stalin managed to consolidate more and more power in his hands, gradually putting down all opposition groups within the party. This included [[Leon Trotsky]], the [[Red Army]] organizer, proponent of [[world revolution]], and principal critic of Stalin among the early Soviet leaders, who was exiled from the Soviet Union in 1929. Instead, Stalin's idea of [[socialism in one country]] became the primary line of the Soviet politics.

In 1928, Stalin replaced the [[New Economic Policy]] of the 1920s with a highly centralised [[command economy]] and [[Five-Year Plans for the National Economy of the Soviet Union|Five-Year Plans]], launching a period of rapid industrialization and [[Collectivization in the Soviet Union|economic collectivization in the countryside]]. As a result, the USSR was transformed from a largely agrarian society into a great industrial power, and the basis was provided for its emergence as the world's second largest economy after World War II.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book | author=Wheatcroft, S. G.; Davies, R. W.; Cooper, J. M. | pages = 30–2 | title = Soviet Industrialization Reconsidered: Some Preliminary Conclusions about Economic Development between 1926 and 1941 | page = 264 | publisher=[[Economic History Review]] | year = 1986 | url = http://books.google.com/?id=m-voAAAAIAAJ&amp;dq | isbn = 9780719046001| volume = 39 | issue = 2 }}&lt;/ref&gt; However, during this period of rapid economic and social changes, millions of people were sent to [[Gulag|penal labor camps]],&lt;ref name=&quot;Getty&quot;&gt;Getty, Rittersporn, Zemskov. Victims of the Soviet Penal System in the Pre-War Years: A First Approach on the Basis of Archival Evidence. The American Historical Review, Vol. 98, No. 4 (Oct., 1993), pp. 1017–1049.&lt;/ref&gt; including many political convicts, and millions were [[Population transfer in the Soviet Union|deported and exiled]] to remote areas of the Soviet Union.&lt;ref name=&quot;Getty&quot;/&gt; The initial upheaval in the changing agricultural sector disrupted food production in the early 1930s, contributing to the catastrophic [[Soviet famine of 1932–1933]], one of the last major [[Droughts and famines in Russia and the Soviet Union|famines in Russia]]. In 1937–38, a campaign against former members of the communist opposition, potential rivals in the party, and other alleged enemies of the regime culminated in the [[Great Purge]], a period of mass repression in which hundreds of thousands of people were executed, including [[Case of Trotskyist Anti-Soviet Military Organization|Red Army leaders convicted]] in coup d'état plots.&lt;ref&gt;Abbott Gleason (2009). ''[http://books.google.com/books?id=JyN0hlKcfTcC&amp;pg=PA373&amp;dq&amp;hl=en#v=onepage&amp;q=&amp;f=false A Companion to Russian History]''. Wiley-Blackwell. p.373. ISBN 1-4051-3560-3&lt;/ref&gt;

In August 1939, after the failure to establish an Anglo-Franco-Soviet Alliance,&lt;ref name=&quot;carley&quot;&gt;Michael Jabara Carley. End of the 'Low, Dishonest Decade': Failure of the Anglo–Franco–Soviet Alliance in 1939. ''Europe-Asia Studies'', Vol. 45, No. 2 (1993), pp. 303–341&lt;/ref&gt; Stalin's USSR entered into a [[Molotov-Ribbentrop Pact|non-aggression pact with Nazi Germany]], dividing their spheres of influence in Eastern Europe. This pact allowed the Soviet Union to regain some of the former territories of the [[Russian Empire]] in [[Soviet invasion of Poland|Poland]], [[Winter War|Finland]], the [[Directive 02622ss/ov|Baltics]], [[Bessarabia]] and northern [[Bukovina]] during the early period of World War II. After Germany violated the pact by [[Operation Barbarossa|invading the Soviet Union]] in 1941 and thus opening the [[Eastern Front (World War II)|largest and bloodiest theatre of war in history]], the Soviet Union joined the [[Allies (World War II)|Allies]]. Despite heavy human and territorial losses in the initial period of war, the Soviet Union managed to stop the Axis advance in the battles of [[Battle of Moscow|Moscow]] and [[Battle of Stalingrad|Stalingrad]]. Eventually, the Red Army drove through Eastern Europe in 1944–45 and [[Battle of Berlin|captured Berlin]] in May 1945. Having played the decisive role in the Allied victory,&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|author=Weinberg, G.L.|title=A World at Arms: A Global History of World War II|isbn=0521558794|publisher=Cambridge University Press|page=264|year=1995}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Rozhnov, Konstantin, [http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/europe/4508901.stm Who won World War II?]. BBC.&lt;/ref&gt; the USSR emerged a recognized superpower after the war.&lt;ref&gt;
Superpower politics: change in the United States and the Soviet Union [http://books.google.com/books?id=XXcVAAAAIAAJ&amp;pg=PA4 Books.Google.com]&lt;/ref&gt;

Stalin headed the Soviet delegations at the [[Yalta Conference|Yalta]] and [[Potsdam Conference]]s, which defined the map of post-war Europe. Communist-dominated [[leftist]] governments loyal to the Soviet Union were installed in the [[Eastern Bloc]] [[satellite state]]s as the USSR entered a struggle for global dominance, known as the [[Cold War]], with the United States and [[NATO]]. In Asia, Stalin established good relations with [[Mao Zedong]] and [[Kim Il-sung]], and the Stalin-era Soviet Union in various ways served as a model for the newly formed People's Republic of China and [[North Korea|Democratic People's Republic of Korea (North Korea)]].

In power until his death in 1953, Stalin led the USSR during the period of post-war reconstruction, marked by the dominance of [[Stalinist architecture]] (most famously represented by the [[Stalin skyscrapers]]). The successful development of the [[Soviet nuclear program]] enabled the country to become the world's second [[Russia and weapons of mass destruction|nuclear weapons power]]; the [[Soviet space program]] was started as spin-off of the nuclear project. In his last years, Stalin also launched the so-called [[Great Construction Projects of Communism]] and the [[Great Plan for the Transformation of Nature]].

Following his death, Stalin and his regime have both been questioned on numerous occasions, the most significant of these being the [[20th Congress of the Communist Party of the Soviet Union]] in 1956, when Stalin's successor, [[Nikita Khrushchev]], [[On the Personality Cult and its Consequences|denounced his legacy]] and drove the process of [[de-Stalinization]] of the Soviet Union. Modern views of Stalin in the Russian Federation remain mixed, with some viewing him as a tyrant&lt;ref name=&quot;How Russia faced its dark past&quot;&gt;[http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/europe/2821281.stm How Russia faced its dark past], [[BBC News]] (5 March 2003)&lt;/ref&gt; while others consider him a capable leader.&lt;ref name=&quot;reuters.com&quot;&gt;[http://www.reuters.com/article/worldNews/idUSL2559010520070725?feedType=RSS&amp;rpc=22&amp;sp=true Russian youth: Stalin good, migrants must go: poll], [[Reuters]] (25 July 2007)&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;!--please do not remove, for ToC spacing--&gt;
{{TOC limit|limit=3}}

==Early life==
{{Main|Early life of Joseph Stalin}}
{{double image|right|Stalin 1894.jpg|100|Stalin 1902.jpg|120|Young Stalin, circa 1894, age 16, and Ioseb in his mid-twenties, c. 1902.}}
Stalin was born '''Ioseb Besarionis dze Jughashvili''' ({{lang-ka|იოსებ ბესარიონის ძე ჯუღაშვილი}}) on 18 December 1878&lt;ref name=dob/&gt; to [[Ketevan Geladze]] and [[Besarion Jughashvili]], a cobbler, in the town of [[Gori, Georgia|Gori]], Georgia. 
At the age of seven, he contracted [[smallpox]], which permanently scarred his face. At ten, he began attending church school where the Georgian children were forced to speak Russian. By the age of twelve, two horse-drawn carriage accidents left his left arm permanently damaged. At sixteen, he received a scholarship to a [[Georgian Orthodox and Apostolic Church|Georgian Orthodox]] [[seminary]], where he rebelled against the imperialist and religious order. Though he performed well there, he was expelled in 1899 after missing his final exams. The seminary's records suggest he was unable to pay his tuition fees.&lt;ref&gt;Montefiore, ''Young Stalin'', p. 61&lt;/ref&gt; The official Soviet version states that he was expelled for reading illegal literature and forming a Social Democratic study circle.&lt;ref&gt;Medvedev, ''Let History Judge'', p. 29&lt;/ref&gt;

Shortly after leaving the seminary, Stalin discovered the writings of [[Vladimir Lenin]] and decided to become a Marxist revolutionary, eventually joining Lenin's [[Bolsheviks]] in 1903. After being marked by the [[Okhranka]] (the Tsar's secret police) for his activities, he became a full-time revolutionary and outlaw. He became one of the [[Bolsheviks]]' chief operatives in the [[Caucasus]], organizing paramilitaries, inciting strikes, spreading propaganda and raising money through bank robberies, ransom kidnappings and extortion.

In the summer of 1906, Stalin married [[Ekaterina Svanidze]], who later gave birth to Stalin's first child, [[Yakov Dzhugashvili|Yakov]]. A year later she died of typhus in Baku.

Stalin was captured and sent to [[Siberia]] seven times, but escaped most of these exiles. He eventually adopted the name &quot;Stalin&quot;, from the Russian word for steel, which he used as an alias and pen name in his published works.

During his last exile, Stalin was conscripted by the Russian army to fight in World War I, but was deemed unfit for service because of his damaged left arm.&lt;ref&gt;Montefiore, ''Young Stalin'', p. 261&lt;/ref&gt;

==Revolution, Civil War, and Polish-Soviet War==
{{Main|Joseph Stalin in the Russian Revolution, Russian Civil War, and Polish-Soviet War}}

===Role during the Russian Revolution of 1917===
[[File:Stalin's Mug Shot.jpg|thumb|Prior to revolution Stalin played an active role in fighting the tsarist government. Here, he is shown on a 1911 information card from the files of the Tsarist secret police in Saint Petersburg.&lt;ref name=&quot;Young Stalin&quot;&gt;Simon Sebag Montefiore. Young Stalin. 2007. ISBN 9780297850687&lt;/ref&gt;{{page needed|date=February 2011}}]]
After returning to Saint Petersburg from exile, Stalin ousted [[Vyacheslav Molotov]] and [[Alexander Shlyapnikov]] as editors of ''[[Pravda]]''. He then took a position in favor of supporting [[Alexander Kerensky]]'s [[Russian Provisional Government|provisional government]]. However, after Lenin prevailed at the April 1917 Party conference, Stalin and ''Pravda'' supported overthrowing the provisional government. At this conference, Stalin was elected to the Bolshevik Central Committee. After [[Alexander Kerensky|Kerensky]] ordered the arrest of Lenin following the [[July Days]], Stalin helped [[Lenin]] evade capture.&lt;ref name=&quot;Young Stalin&quot; /&gt;{{page needed|date=February 2011}} After the jailed Bolsheviks were freed to help defend Saint Petersburg in October 1917, the Bolshevik Central Committee voted in favor of an insurrection. On 7 November, from the [[Smolny Institute]], Stalin, Lenin and the rest of the Central Committee coordinated the insurrection against Kerensky in the 1917 [[October Revolution]]. By 8 November, the Bolsheviks had stormed the [[Winter Palace]] and Kerensky's Cabinet had been arrested.

===Role in the Russian Civil War, 1917–1919===
[[File:Delegates VIII Congress of the RKP(b).jpg|thumb|right|A group of participants in the 8th Congress of the Russian Communist Party, 1919. In the middle are Stalin, [[Vladimir Lenin]], and [[Mikhail Kalinin]].]]
&lt;!--[[File:Stalin-Lenin-Kalinin-1919.jpg|thumb|right|Joseph Stalin, [[Vladimir Lenin]], and [[Mikhail Kalinin]] meeting in 1919. All three of them were &quot;[[Old Bolsheviks]]&quot;—members of the [[Bolshevik]] party before the [[Russian Revolution of 1917]].]]--&gt;
Upon seizing [[Petrograd]], Stalin was appointed People's Commissar for Nationalities' Affairs. Thereafter, [[Russian Civil War|civil war]] broke out in Russia, pitting [[Vladimir Lenin|Lenin's]] Red Army against the [[White Army]], a loose alliance of anti-Bolshevik forces. Lenin formed a five-member [[Politburo of the Central Committee of the Communist Party of the Soviet Union|Politburo]] which included Stalin and [[Leon Trotsky|Trotsky]]. In May 1918, Lenin dispatched Stalin to the city of [[Volgograd|Tsaritsyn]]. Through his new allies, [[Kliment Voroshilov]] and [[Semyon Budyonny]], Stalin imposed his influence on the military.{{Citation needed|date=February 2011}}

Stalin challenged many of the decisions of [[Leon Trotsky|Trotsky]], ordered the killings of many former Tsarist officers in the Red Army and counter-revolutionaries{{Citation needed|date=February 2011}} and burned villages in order to intimidate the peasantry into submission and discourage bandit raids on food shipments.{{Citation needed|date=February 2011}} In May 1919, in order to stem mass desertions on the Western front, Stalin had deserters and renegades publicly executed as traitors.&lt;ref&gt;Robert Service. ''Stalin: A Biography''. pg 172&lt;/ref&gt;

===Role in the Polish-Soviet War, 1919–1921===
After their [[Russian Civil War]] victory, the Bolsheviks moved to establish a sphere of influence in Central Europe, starting with what became the [[Polish–Soviet War]]. As commander of the southern front, Stalin was determined to take the Polish-held city of [[Lviv]]. This conflicted with general strategy set by Lenin and Trotsky, which focused upon the capture of [[Warsaw]] further north.

[[Trotsky]]'s forces engaged with those of Polish commander [[Władysław Sikorski]] at the [[Battle of Warsaw (1920)|Battle of Warsaw]], but Stalin refused to redirect his troops from Lviv to help. Consequently, the battles for both [[Lviv]] and [[Warsaw]] were lost, for which Stalin was blamed. Stalin returned to Moscow in August 1920, where he defended himself and resigned his military commission. At the Ninth Party Conference on 22 September, Trotsky openly criticized Stalin's behavior.

==Rise to power==
{{Main|Rise of Joseph Stalin}}
Stalin played a decisive role in engineering the 1921 [[Red Army invasion of Georgia]], following which he adopted particularly hardline, centralist policies towards [[Georgian SSR|Soviet Georgia]], which included the [[Georgian Affair]] of 1922 and other repressions.&lt;ref&gt;Knight, Ami W. (1991), Beria and the Cult of Stalin: Rewriting Transcaucasian Party History. ''[[Soviet Studies]]'', Vol. 43, No. 4, pp. 749–763&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Shanin, Teodor (July 1989), Ethnicity in the Soviet Union: Analytical Perceptions and Political Strategies. ''Comparative Studies in Society and History'', Vol. 31, No. 3, pp. 409–424&lt;/ref&gt; This created a rift with Lenin, who believed that all the Soviet states should stand equal.

Lenin still considered Stalin to be a loyal ally, and when he got mired in squabbles with Trotsky and other politicians, he decided to give Stalin more power. With the help of [[Lev Kamenev]], Lenin had Stalin appointed as [[General Secretary of the Communist Party of the Soviet Union|General Secretary]] in 1922.&lt;ref name=&quot;StalinRobertService&quot;&gt;Robert Service. Stalin: A Biography. 2004. ISBN 978-0-330-41913-0&lt;/ref&gt; This post allowed Stalin to appoint many of his allies to government positions.

Lenin suffered a stroke in 1922, forcing him into semi-retirement in [[Gorki Leninskiye|Gorki]]. Stalin visited him often, acting as his intermediary with the outside world.&lt;ref name=&quot;StalinRobertService&quot; /&gt; The pair quarreled and their relationship deteriorated.&lt;ref name=&quot;StalinRobertService&quot; /&gt; Lenin dictated increasingly disparaging notes on Stalin in what would become his testament. He criticized Stalin's rude manners, excessive power, ambition and politics, and suggested that Stalin should be removed from the position of General Secretary.&lt;ref name=&quot;StalinRobertService&quot; /&gt; During Lenin's semi-retirement, Stalin forged an alliance with Kamenev and [[Grigory Zinoviev]] against [[Leon Trotsky]]. These allies prevented [[Lenin's Testament]] from being revealed to the [[12th Congress of the Russian Communist Party (Bolsheviks)|Twelfth Party Congress]] in April 1923.&lt;ref name=&quot;StalinRobertService&quot; /&gt;

Lenin died of a heart attack on 21 January 1924. Again, Kamenev and Zinoviev helped to keep Lenin's Testament from going public. Thereafter, Stalin's disputes with [[Lev Kamenev]] and Zinoviev intensified. Trotsky, Kamenev and Zinoviev grew increasingly isolated, and were eventually ejected from the Central Committee and then from the Party itself.&lt;ref name=&quot;StalinRobertService&quot; /&gt; Kamenev and Zinoviev were later readmitted, but Trotsky was exiled from the Soviet Union.

The [[Northern Expedition]] in China became a point of contention over foreign policy by Stalin and Trotsky. Stalin followed a practical policy, ignoring communist ideology. He told the Chinese Communist Party to stop whining about the lower classes and follow the [[Kuomintang]]'s orders. Stalin, like Lenin, believed that the KMT bourgeoisie would defeat the western imperialists in China and complete the revolution. Trotsky wanted the Communist party to complete an orthodox proletarian revolution and opposed the KMT. Stalin funded the KMT during the expedition.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=OCI3gnzsYc0C&amp;pg=PA233|title=China in war and revolution, 1895–1949|author=Peter Gue Zarrow|year=2005|publisher=Psychology Press|isbn=0415364477|page=233|accessdate=1 January 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; Stalin countered Trotsky's criticism by making a secret speech in which he said that Chiang's right wing Kuomintang were the only ones capable of defeating the imperialists, that [[Chiang Kai-shek]] had funding from the rich merchants, and that his forces were to be utilized until squeezed for all usefulness like a lemon before being discarded.{{Citation needed|date=February 2011}} However, Chiang quickly reversed the tables in the [[Shanghai massacre of 1927]] by massacring the Communist party in Shanghai midway in the Northern Expedition.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=wjCsAAAAIAAJ&amp;pg=PA96|title=Moscow and Chinese Communists|author=Robert Carver North|year=1963|publisher=Stanford University Press|isbn=0804704538|page=96|accessdate=1 January 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=yMwdWFtgV0QC&amp;pg=PA282|title=A history of Russia: Since 1855|author=Walter Moss|year=2005|publisher=Anthem Press|isbn=1843310341|page=282|accessdate=1 January 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Stalin pushed for more rapid industrialization and central control of the economy, contravening Lenin's [[New Economic Policy]] (NEP). At the end of 1927, a critical shortfall in grain supplies prompted Stalin to push for collectivisation of agriculture and order the seizures of grain hoards from [[kulak]] farmers.&lt;ref name=&quot;StalinRobertService&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;RedTsar&quot;&gt;Simon Sebag Montefiore. ''Stalin: The Court of the Red Tsar'', Knopf, 2004 (ISBN 1-4000-4230-5)&lt;/ref&gt; [[Nikolai Bukharin|Bukharin]] and [[Premier of the Soviet Union|Premier]] [[Alexey Rykov]] opposed these policies and advocated a return to the NEP, but the rest of the Politburo sided with Stalin and removed Bukharin from the Politburo in November 1929. Rykov was fired the following year, and was replaced by [[Vyacheslav Molotov]] on Stalin's recommendation.

In December 1934, the popular [[Sergei Kirov]] was murdered. Stalin blamed Kirov's murder on a vast conspiracy of saboteurs and Trotskyites. He launched a massive purge against these internal enemies, putting them on rigged show trials and then having them executed or imprisoned in Siberian gulags. Among these victims were old enemies, including Bukharin, Rykov, Kamenev and Zinoviev. Stalin made the loyal [[Nikolai Yezhov]] head of the secret police, the [[NKVD]], and had him purge the NKVD of veteran Bolsheviks. With no serious opponents left in power, Stalin ended the purges in 1938. Yezhov was held to blame for the excesses of the Great Terror, and was dismissed and later executed.

==Changes to Soviet society, 1927–1939==
===Bolstering Soviet secret service and intelligence===
{{Main|Chronology of Soviet secret police agencies}}
{{Stalinism sidebar}}
Stalin vastly increased the scope and power of the state's secret police and intelligence agencies. Under his guiding hand, Soviet intelligence forces began to set up intelligence networks in most of the major nations of the world, including Germany (the famous ''[[Red Orchestra (spy)|Rote Kappelle]]'' spy ring), Great Britain, France, Japan, and the United States. Stalin made considerable use of the [[Comintern|Communist International]] movement in order to infiltrate agents and to ensure that foreign Communist parties remained pro-Soviet and pro-Stalin.

One of the best examples of Stalin's ability to integrate secret police and foreign espionage came in 1940, when he gave approval to the secret police to have Leon Trotsky assassinated in Mexico.&lt;ref&gt;[http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=950DE3DF133EF936A35752C0A96F948260 Soviet Readers Finally Told Moscow Had Trotsky Slain]. Published in the ''[[New York Times]]'' on 5 January 1989. Retrieved 4 October 2007&lt;/ref&gt;

===Cult of personality===
&lt;!-- Deleted image removed: [[File:Roses for Stalin by Vladimirskij.jpg|thumb|left|''Roses for Stalin'' (1949), painting by [[Boris Vladimirski]].|{{Deletable image-caption|1=Wednesday, 7 October 2009}}]] --&gt;
Stalin created a [[cult of personality]] in the Soviet Union around both himself and Lenin. Many personality cults in history have been frequently measured and compared to his. Numerous towns, villages and cities were renamed after the Soviet leader (see [[List of places named after Stalin]]) and the [[Stalin Prize]] and [[Stalin Peace Prize]] were named in his honor. He accepted grandiloquent titles (e.g., &quot;[[Coryphaeus]] of Science,&quot; &quot;Father of Nations,&quot; &quot;Brilliant Genius of Humanity,&quot; &quot;Great Architect of Communism,&quot; &quot;Gardener of Human Happiness,&quot; and others), and helped rewrite Soviet history to provide himself a more significant role in the revolution. At the same time, according to [[Nikita Khrushchev]], he insisted that he be remembered for &quot;the extraordinary modesty characteristic of truly great people.&quot; Statues of Stalin depict him at a height and build approximating [[Alexander III of Russia|Alexander III]]{{clarify|date=February 2011}}, while photographic evidence suggests he was between 5&amp;nbsp;ft 5&amp;nbsp;in and 5&amp;nbsp;ft 6&amp;nbsp;in (165–168&amp;nbsp;cm).&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.celebheights.com/s/Joseph-Stalin-3210.html|title=Joseph Stalin Height – Stalin's}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Trotsky criticized the cult of personality built around Stalin. It reached new levels during World War II, with Stalin's name included in the new [[National Anthem of the Soviet Union#1944|Soviet national anthem]]. Stalin became the focus of literature, poetry, music, paintings and film, exhibiting fawning devotion, crediting Stalin with almost god-like qualities, and suggesting he single-handedly won the Second World War. It is debatable as to how much Stalin relished the cult surrounding him. The Finnish communist [[Arvo Tuominen]] records a sarcastic toast proposed by Stalin at a New Year Party in 1935 in which he said &quot;Comrades! I want to propose a toast to our patriarch, life and sun, liberator of nations, architect of socialism [he rattled off all the appellations applied to him in those days]{{ndash}} Josef Vissarionovich Stalin, and I hope this is the first and last speech made to that genius this evening.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|authorlink=Arvo Tuominen|author=Tuominen, Arvo|title=The Bells of the Kremlin|page=162|isbn=0874512492}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In a 1956 speech, Nikita Khrushchev gave a denunciation of Stalin's actions: &quot;It is impermissible and foreign to the spirit of Marxism-Leninism to elevate one person, to transform him into a superman possessing supernatural characteristics akin to those of a god.&quot;{{Citation needed|date=February 2011}}

===Purges and deportations===
====Purges and executions====
{{Main|Great Purge}}
{{Multiple image
| align     = right
| direction = horizontal
| width     = 150
| image1    = Execute 346 Berias letter to Politburo.jpg
| image2    = Execute 346 Stalins resolution.jpg
| image3    = Execute 346 Politburo passes.jpg
| footer    = '''Left:''' [[Lavrenty Beria|Beria's]] January 1940 letter to Stalin, asking permission to execute 346 &quot;[[enemy of the people|enemies of the CPSU and of the Soviet authorities]]&quot; who conducted &quot;counter-revolutionary, right-Trotskyite plotting and spying activities&quot;&lt;br /&gt;'''Middle:''' Stalin's handwriting: &quot;за&quot; (support).&lt;br /&gt;'''Right:''' The Politburo's decision is signed by Secretary Stalin
}}

Stalin, as head of the [[Politburo of the Central Committee of the Communist Party of the Soviet Union|Politburo]], consolidated near-absolute power in the 1930s with a [[Great Purge]] of the party, justified as an attempt to expel 'opportunists' and 'counter-revolutionary infiltrators'.&lt;ref name=&quot;Figes&quot;&gt;[[Orlando Figes]] ''The Whisperers: Private Life in Stalin's Russia'', 2007, ISBN 08050-7461-9&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Social Catastrophe&quot;&gt;Lenin, Stalin, and Hitler: The Age of Social Catastrophe. By Robert Gellately. 2007. Knopf. ISBN 1400040051&lt;/ref&gt; Those targeted by the purge were often expelled from the party; however, more severe measures ranged from banishment to the Gulag [[labor camp]]s, to execution after trials held by [[NKVD troika]]s.&lt;ref name=&quot;Figes&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Ian Kershaw, Moshe Lewin, ''Stalinism and Nazism: Dictatorships in Comparison'', Cambridge University Press 1997, ISBN 0521565219, p. 300&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Leo Kuper, ''Genocide: Its Political Use in the Twentieth Century'', Yale University Press 1982, ISBN 0300031203&lt;/ref&gt;

In the 1930s, Stalin apparently became increasingly worried about the growing popularity of [[Sergei Kirov]]. At the [[17th Congress of the All-Union Communist Party (Bolsheviks)|1934 Party Congress]] where the vote for the new Central Committee was held, Kirov received only three negative votes, the fewest of any candidate, while Stalin received 1,108 negative votes.&lt;ref&gt;{{Harvnb|Brackman|2001|p=204}}&lt;/ref&gt; After the assassination of Kirov, which may have been orchestrated by Stalin, Stalin invented a detailed scheme to implicate opposition leaders in the murder, including [[Trotsky]], [[Kamenev]] and [[Grigory Zinoviev|Zinoviev]].&lt;ref name=&quot;brackman205&quot;&gt;{{Harvnb|Brackman|2001|pp=205–6}}&lt;/ref&gt; The investigations and trials expanded.&lt;ref name=&quot;brackman207&quot;&gt;{{Harvnb|Brackman|2001|p=207}}&lt;/ref&gt; Stalin passed a new law on &quot;terrorist organizations and terrorist acts&quot;, which were to be investigated for no more than ten days, with no prosecution, defense attorneys or appeals, followed by a sentence to be executed &quot;quickly.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;Overy 2004 p=182&quot;&gt;{{Harvnb|Overy|2004|p=182}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Thereafter, several trials known as the [[Moscow Trials]] were held, but the procedures were replicated throughout the country. [[Article 58]] of the legal code, listing prohibited anti-Soviet activities as counterrevolutionary crime was applied in the broadest manner.&lt;ref&gt;{{Harvnb|Tucker|1992|p=456}}&lt;/ref&gt; The flimsiest pretexts were often enough to brand someone an &quot;[[enemy of the people]]&quot;, starting the cycle of public persecution and abuse, often proceeding to interrogation, torture and deportation, if not death. The Russian word troika gained a new meaning: a quick, simplified trial by a committee of three subordinated to NKVD -[[NKVD troika]]- with sentencing carried out within 24 hours.&lt;ref name=&quot;Overy 2004 p=182&quot;/&gt; Stalin's hand picked executioner, [[Vasili Blokhin]], was entrusted with carrying out some of the high profile executions in this period.&lt;ref&gt;[[Timothy Snyder|Snyder, Timothy]]. ''Bloodlands: Europe Between Hitler and Stalin.'' [[Basic Books]], 2010. ISBN 0465002390 p. 137&lt;/ref&gt;
{{Multiple image
| align     = left
| direction = vertical
| width     = 220
| image1    = Voroshilov, Molotov, Stalin, with Nikolai Yezhov.jpg
| image2    = The Commissar Vanishes 2.jpg
| caption2  = [[Nikolai Yezhov]], walking with Stalin in the top photo from the 1930s, was killed in 1940. Following his execution, Yezhov was edited out of the photo by Soviet censors.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.newseum.org/berlinwall/commissar_vanishes/vanishes.htm|title=Newseum: The Commissar Vanishes|accessdate=19 July 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt; Such retouching was a common occurrence during Stalin's rule.
}}

Many military leaders were convicted of treason, and a large scale purging of [[Red Army]] officers followed.&lt;ref name=&quot;scale&quot;&gt;The scale of Stalin's purging of Red Army officers was exceptional—90% of all generals and 80% of all colonels were killed. This included three out of five Marshals, 13 out of 15 Army commanders, 57 of 85 Corps commanders, 110 of 195 divisional commanders and 220 of 406 brigade commanders as well as all commanders of military districts. (p.195, Carell, P. (1964) ''Hitler's War on Russia: The Story of the German Defeat in the East.'' translated from German by Ewald Osers, B.I. Publications New Delhi, 1974 (first Indian edition)&lt;/ref&gt; The repression of so many formerly high-ranking revolutionaries and party members led [[Leon Trotsky]] to claim that a &quot;river of blood&quot; separated Stalin's regime from that of Lenin.&lt;ref&gt;Tucker, Robert C., ''Stalinism: Essays in Historical Interpretation, '', American Council of Learned Societies Planning Group on Comparative Communist Studies, Transaction Publishers, 1999, ISBN 0765804832, p. 5&lt;/ref&gt; In August 1940, Trotsky was assassinated in Mexico, where he had lived in exile since January 1937; this eliminated the last of Stalin's opponents among the former Party leadership.&lt;ref&gt;{{Harvnb|Overy|2004|p=338}}&lt;/ref&gt;

With the exception of [[Vladimir Milyutin]] (who died in prison in 1937) and Joseph Stalin himself, [[Council of People's Commissars of the Russian Soviet Federative Socialist Republic#The original People's Commissars|all of the members of Lenin's original cabinet who had not succumbed to death from natural causes before the purge were executed]].

[[Mass operations of the NKVD]] also targeted &quot;national contingents&quot; (foreign ethnicities) such as Poles, ethnic Germans, Koreans, etc. A total of 350,000 (144,000 of them Poles) were arrested and 247,157 (110,000 Poles) were executed.&lt;ref name=&quot;RedTsar&quot; /&gt; Many Americans who had emigrated to the Soviet Union during the worst of the [[Great Depression]] were executed; others were sent to prison camps or [[gulags]].&lt;ref&gt;Tim Tzouliadis. [http://news.bbc.co.uk/today/hi/today/newsid_7537000/7537585.stm Nightmare in the workers paradise] [[BBC]], 2 August 2008 See also: Tzouliadis, Tim. ''The Forsaken: An American Tragedy in Stalin's Russia''. The [[Penguin Press]], 2008 (ISBN 1594201684)&lt;/ref&gt; Concurrent with the purges, efforts were made to rewrite the history in Soviet textbooks and other propaganda materials. Notable people executed by [[NKVD]] were removed from the texts and photographs as though they never existed. Gradually, the history of revolution was transformed to a story about just two key characters: [[Lenin]] and Stalin.

In light of revelations from the Soviet archives, historians now estimate that nearly 700,000 people (353,074 in 1937 and 328,612 in 1938) were executed in the course of the terror,&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|author=Barry McLoughlin|coauthors=Kevin McDermott(eds)|url=http://books.google.com/?id=8yorTJl1QEoC&amp;pg=PA141|title=Stalin's Terror: High Politics and Mass Repression in the Soviet Union|publisher=[[Palgrave Macmillan]]|year=2002|isbn=1403901198|page=141|date=4 February 2003}}&lt;/ref&gt; with the great mass of victims being &quot;ordinary&quot; Soviet citizens: workers, peasants, homemakers, teachers, priests, musicians, soldiers, pensioners, ballerinas, beggars.&lt;ref&gt;Hiroaki Kuromiya, ''The Voices of the Dead: Stalin's Great Terror in the 1930s.'' [[Yale University Press]], 24 December 2007. ISBN 0300123892 p. 4&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|author=Barry McLoughlin|coauthors=Kevin McDermott(eds)|url=http://books.google.com/?id=8yorTJl1QEoC&amp;pg=PA6|title=Stalin's Terror: High Politics and Mass Repression in the Soviet Union|publisher=[[Palgrave Macmillan]]|year=2002|isbn=1403901198|page=6|date=4 February 2003}}&lt;/ref&gt; Many of the executed were interred in [[Mass graves in the Soviet Union|mass graves]], with some of the major killing and burial sites being [[Bykivnia]], [[Kurapaty]] and [[Butovo firing range|Butovo]].&lt;ref&gt;[[Timothy Snyder|Snyder, Timothy]]. ''Bloodlands: Europe Between Hitler and Stalin.'' [[Basic Books]], 2010. ISBN 0465002390 p. 101&lt;/ref&gt;

Some Western experts believe the evidence released from the Soviet archives is understated, incomplete or unreliable.&lt;ref name=&quot;rosefielde&quot;&gt;Rosefielde, Stephen, [http://sovietinfo.tripod.com/RSF-New_Evidence.pdf Stalinism in Post-Communist Perspective: New Evidence on Killings, ''Forced Labour and Economic Growth in the 1930s''], Europe-Asia Studies, Vol. 48, No. 6, 1996&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://sovietinfo.tripod.com/CNQ-Comments_WCR.pdf Comment on Wheatcroft] by [[Robert Conquest]], 1999&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=Pipes&gt;Pipes, Richard, ''Communism: A History (Modern Library Chronicles)'', p. 67&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Harvnb|Applebaum|2003|p=584}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;John Keep. [http://chs.revues.org/index1014.html Recent Writing on Stalin's Gulag: An Overview]. 1997&lt;/ref&gt;

Stalin personally signed 357 [[proscription]] lists in 1937 and 1938 which condemned to execution some 40,000 people, and about 90% of these are confirmed to have been shot.&lt;ref name=&quot;Ellman&quot;/&gt; At the time, while reviewing one such list, Stalin reportedly muttered to no one in particular: &quot;Who's going to remember all this riff-raff in ten or twenty years time? No one. Who remembers the names now of the [[boyars]] [[Ivan the Terrible]] got rid of? No one.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Quoted in [[Dmitri Volkogonov]], ''Stalin: Triumph and Tragedy'' (New York, 1991), p.210&lt;/ref&gt; In addition, Stalin dispatched a contingent of NKVD operatives to [[Mongolian People's Republic|Mongolia]], established a Mongolian version of the [[NKVD troika]] and unleashed a [[Stalinist purges in Mongolia|bloody purge]] in which tens of thousands were executed as 'Japanese Spies.' Mongolian ruler [[Khorloogiin Choibalsan]] closely followed Stalin's lead.&lt;ref name=&quot;Kuromiya pg2&quot;&gt;Hiroaki Kuromiya, ''The Voices of the Dead: Stalin's Great Terror in the 1930s.'' [[Yale University Press]], 24 December 2007. ISBN 0300123892 p. 2&lt;/ref&gt;

During the 1930s and 40s the Soviet leadership sent NKVD squads into other countries to murder defectors and other opponents of the Soviet regime. Victims of such plots included [[Yevhen Konovalets]], [[Ignace Poretsky]], Rudolf Klement, [[Alexander Kutepov]], [[Evgeny Miller]], [[Leon Trotsky]] and the Workers' Party of Marxist Unification ([[POUM]]) leadership in [[Catalonia]] (e.g., [[Andreu Nin]]).&lt;ref&gt;Michael Ellman. ''[http://www.paulbogdanor.com/left/soviet/famine/ellman.pdf The Role of Leadership Perceptions and of Intent in the Soviet Famine of 1931–1934].'' Europe-Asia Studies, 2005. p. 826&lt;/ref&gt;

====Population transfer====
{{Main|Population transfer in the Soviet Union}}

&lt;!-- Please add factual material to the main article, and keep only summary here. --&gt;
Shortly before, during and immediately after World War II, Stalin conducted a series of [[Forced settlements in the Soviet Union|deportations]] on a huge scale which profoundly affected the ethnic map of the Soviet Union. It is estimated that between 1941 and 1949 nearly 3.3&amp;nbsp;million&lt;ref name=&quot;Boobbyer 2000 p=130&quot;&gt;{{Harvnb|Boobbyer|2000|p=130}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Pohl, Otto, ''Ethnic Cleansing in the USSR, 1937–1949'', ISBN 0313309213&lt;/ref&gt; were deported to [[Siberia]] and the Central Asian republics. By some estimates up to 43% of the resettled population died of [[infectious diseases|diseases]] and [[malnutrition]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.hawaii.edu/powerkills/USSR.TAB1B.GIF |title=Soviet Transit, Camp, and Deportation Death Rates |accessdate=25 June 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Separatism, resistance to Soviet rule and collaboration with the invading Germans were cited as the official reasons for the deportations, rightly or wrongly. Individual circumstances of those spending time in German-occupied territories were not examined.&lt;ref name=&quot;bullock904&quot;&gt;[[Alan Bullock]], pp. 904–905&lt;/ref&gt; After the brief Nazi occupation of the Caucasus, the entire population of five of the small highland peoples and the Crimean Tatars{{ndash}} more than a million people in total {{ndash}} were deported without notice or any opportunity to take their possessions.&lt;ref name=&quot;bullock904&quot;/&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

As a result of Stalin's lack of trust in the loyalty of particular ethnicities, such ethnic groups as the [[Koryo-saram|Soviet Koreans]], the [[Volga Germans]], the [[Crimean Tatars]], the [[Chechens]], and many [[Poles]] were forcibly moved out of strategic areas and relocated to places in the central Soviet Union, especially Kazakhstan in [[Soviet Central Asia]]. By some estimates, hundreds of thousands of deportees may have died en route.&lt;ref name=&quot;Boobbyer 2000 p=130&quot; /&gt;

According to official Soviet estimates, more than 14 million people passed through the ''Gulag'' from 1929 to 1953, with a further 7 to 8&amp;nbsp;million being [[Forced settlements in the Soviet Union|deported and exiled]] to remote areas of the Soviet Union (including the entire nationalities in several cases).&lt;ref&gt;Robert Conquest in ''Victims of Stalinism: A Comment.'' Europe-Asia Studies, Vol. 49, No. 7 (Nov. 1997), pp. 1317–1319 states:&quot;We are all inclined to accept the Zemskov totals (even if not as complete) with their 14 million intake to Gulag 'camps' alone, to which must be added 4–5&amp;nbsp;million going to Gulag 'colonies', to say nothing of the 3.5&amp;nbsp;million already in, or sent to, 'labour settlements'. However taken, these are surely 'high' figures.&quot;&lt;/ref&gt;

In February 1956, [[Nikita Khrushchev]] condemned the deportations as a violation of [[Leninism]], and reversed most of them, although it was not until 1991 that the Tatars, [[Meskheti]]ans and Volga Germans were allowed to return ''en masse'' to their homelands. The deportations had a profound effect on the peoples of the Soviet Union. The memory of the deportations played a major part in the separatist movements in the Baltic States, [[Tatarstan]] and [[Chechnya]], even today.

===Collectivization===
{{Main|Collectivization in the Soviet Union}}
Stalin's regime moved to force [[collective farming|collectivization]] of agriculture. This was intended to increase agricultural output from large-scale mechanized farms, to bring the peasantry under more direct political control, and to make tax collection more efficient. Collectivization meant drastic social changes, on a scale not seen since the abolition of serfdom in 1861, and [[wiktionary:alienate|alienation]] from control of the land and its produce. Collectivization also meant a drastic drop in living standards for many peasants, and it faced violent reaction among the peasantry.

In the first years of collectivization it was estimated that industrial production would rise by 200% and agricultural production by 50%,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.historyworld.net/wrldhis/PlainTextHistories.asp?HistoryID=ac14&amp;ParagraphID=qxe#qxe|accessdate=19 July 2008|title=The rise of Stalin: AD1921–1924|work=History of Russia|publisher=HistoryWorld}}&lt;/ref&gt; but these estimates were not met. Stalin blamed this unanticipated failure on [[kulaks]] (rich peasants), who resisted collectivization. (However, kulaks proper made up only 4% of the peasant population; the &quot;kulaks&quot; that Stalin targeted included the slightly better-off peasants who took the brunt of violence from the [[State Political Directorate|OGPU]] and the Komsomol. These peasants were about 60% of the population). Those officially defined as &quot;kulaks,&quot; &quot;kulak helpers,&quot; and later &quot;ex-kulaks&quot; were to be shot, placed into Gulag [[labor camp]]s, or deported to remote areas of the country, depending on the charge. Archival data indicates that 20,201 people were executed during 1930, the year of [[Dekulakization]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Kuromiya pg2&quot; /&gt;

The two-stage progress of collectivization—interrupted for a year by Stalin's famous editorials, &quot;Dizzy with success&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Stalin, Joseph, ''[http://www.marx2mao.com/Stalin/DS30.html Dizzy with success]'',''[[Pravda]]'', 2 March 1930&lt;/ref&gt; and &quot;Reply to Collective Farm Comrades&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Stalin, Joseph, [http://www.marx2mao.com/Stalin/RCFC30.html ''Reply to Collective Farm Comrades''], ''Pravda'', 3 April 1930&lt;/ref&gt;—is a prime example of his capacity for tactical political withdrawal followed by intensification of initial strategies.

===Famines===
[[Famine]] affected other parts of the USSR. The death toll from [[Droughts and famines in Russia and the Soviet Union|famine in the Soviet Union]] at this time is estimated at between five and ten million people.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;[http://www.bloomberg.com/apps/news?pid=20601085&amp;sid=akRdu1cuBPKg&amp;refer=europe Ukraine Irks Russia With Push to Mark Stalin Famine as Genocide]&quot;. Bloomberg.com. 3 January 2008&lt;/ref&gt; The worst crop failure of late tsarist Russia, in 1892, had caused 375,000 to 400,000 deaths.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://web.archive.org/web/20080202145721rn_1/www.overpopulation.com/faq/famine/the-soviet-famines-of-1921-and-1932-3/|title=Overpopulation.Com &quot; The Soviet Famines of 1921 and 1932-3}}&lt;/ref&gt; Most modern scholars agree that the famine was caused by the policies of the government of the [[Soviet Union]] under Stalin, rather than by natural reasons.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|url=http://www.timesonline.co.uk/tol/comment/letters/article4243813.ece |title=Ukraine's Holodomor|work=The Times |location=UK |accessdate=19 October 2008|date=1 July 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt; According to Alan Bullock, &quot;the total Soviet grain crop was no worse than that of 1931&amp;nbsp;... it was not a crop failure but the excessive demands of the state, ruthlessly enforced, that cost the lives of as many as five million Ukrainian peasants.&quot; Stalin refused to release large grain reserves that could have alleviated the famine, while continuing to export grain; he was convinced that the Ukrainian peasants had hidden grain away, and strictly enforced draconian new collective-farm theft laws in response.&lt;ref&gt;Alan Bullock, p. 269&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;davies-wheatcroft-2004&quot;&gt;{{cite journal|url=http://www2.warwick.ac.uk/fac/soc/economics/staff/faculty/harrison/reviews/davies-wheatcroft2004.pdf|title=The Industrialisation of Soviet Russia|volume=5 – The Years of Hunger: Soviet Agriculture, 1931–1933|publisher=Palgrave Macmillan|year=2004|format=PDF|accessdate=28 December 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt; Other historians hold it was largely the insufficient harvests of 1931 and 1932 caused by a variety of natural disasters that resulted in famine, with the successful harvest of 1933 ending the famine.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|url=http://www.as.wvu.edu/history/Faculty/Tauger/Tauger,%20Natural%20Disaster%20and%20Human%20Actions.pdf|title=Natural Disaster and Human Actions in the Soviet Famine of 1931–1933|journal=The Carl Beck Papers in Russian and East European Studies|format=PDF|accessdate=28 December 2008|ref=harv}}&lt;/ref&gt; Soviet and other historians have argued that the rapid collectivization of agriculture was necessary in order to achieve an equally rapid industrialization of the Soviet Union and ultimately win World War II. [[Alec Nove]] claims that the Soviet Union industrialized in spite of, rather than because of, its collectivized agriculture.{{Citation needed|date=February 2011}}

The USSR also experienced a [[Soviet Famine of 1947|major famine in 1947]] as a result of war damage and severe droughts, but economist Michael Ellman argues that it could have been prevented if the government did not mismanage its grain reserves. The famine cost an estimated 1 to 1.5&amp;nbsp;million lives as well as secondary population losses due to reduced fertility.&lt;ref&gt;According to Ellman, although the 1946 drought was severe, government mismanagement of its grain reserves largely accounted for the population losses. Michael Ellman, &quot;[http://www.paulbogdanor.com/left/soviet/famine/ellman1947.pdf The 1947 Soviet Famine and the Entitlement Approach to Famines],&quot; ''Cambridge Journal of Economics'' 24 (2000): 603–30. [[PDF]] file&lt;/ref&gt;

====Ukrainian famine====
{{Main|Holodomor}}
The Holodomor famine is sometimes referred to as the Ukrainian [[Genocide]], implying it was engineered by the Soviet government, specifically targeting the Ukrainian people to destroy the Ukrainian nation as a political factor and social entity.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|title=Findings of the Commission on the Ukraine Famine|url=http://www.faminegenocide.com/resources/findings.html|publisher=Famine Genocide|date=19 April 1988}} See also: {{cite web|url=http://www.skrobach.com/ukrhol.htm|title=Statement by Pope John Paul II on the 70th anniversary of the Famine|accessdate=23 August 2008|publisher=Skrobach}} See also: {{cite web|url=http://www.artukraine.com/famineart/uscongr4.htm|title=Expressing the sense of the House of Representatives regarding the man-made famine that occurred in Ukraine in 1932–1933|publisher=US House of Representatives|date=21 October 2003|accessdate=23 August 2008}} See also: {{Cite journal|author=Yaroslav Bilinsky|title=Was the Ukrainian Famine of 1932–1933 Genocide?|journal=Journal of Genocide Research|year=1999|volume=1|issue=2|pages=147–156|url=http://www.faminegenocide.com/resources/bilinsky.html|doi=10.1080/14623529908413948|ref=harv}}&lt;/ref&gt; While historians continue to disagree whether the policies that led to Holodomor fall under the [[Convention on the Prevention and Punishment of the Crime of Genocide|legal definition of genocide]], twenty six countries have officially recognized the Holodomor as such. On 28 November 2006, the Ukrainian Parliament approved a bill, according to which the Soviet-era forced famine was an act of genocide against the Ukrainian people.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|last=Lisova |first=Natasha |title=Ukraine Recognize Famine As Genocide |agency=Associated Press |date=28 November 2006 |url=http://www.ukemonde.com/holodomor/index.html}}&lt;/ref&gt; Professor Michael Ellman concludes that Ukrainians were victims of genocide in 1932–33, according to a more [[Genocide definitions|relaxed definition]], which is favored by some specialists in the field of genocide studies. He asserts that Soviet policies greatly exacerbated the famine's death toll (such as the use of torture and execution to extract grain (see [[Law of Spikelets]]), with 1.8&amp;nbsp;million tonnes of it being exported during the height of the starvation—enough to feed 5 million people for one year, the use of force to prevent starving peasants from fleeing the worst affected areas, and the refusal to import grain or secure international humanitarian aid to alleviate the suffering) and that Stalin intended to use the starvation as a cheap and efficient means (as opposed to deportations and shootings) to kill off those deemed to be &quot;counterrevolutionaries,&quot; &quot;idlers,&quot; and &quot;thieves,&quot; but not to annihilate the Ukrainian peasantry as a whole. He also claims that, while this is not the only Soviet genocide (e.g. The [[Polish operation of the NKVD]]), it is the worst in terms of mass casualties.&lt;ref name=&quot;Ellman&quot;&gt;[http://www1.fee.uva.nl/pp/mjellman/ Michael Ellman],
[http://www.paulbogdanor.com/left/soviet/famine/ellman1933.pdf Stalin and the Soviet Famine of 1932–33 Revisited] ''Europe-Asia Studies'', [[Routledge]]. Vol. 59, No. 4, June 2007, 663–693. [[PDF]] file&lt;/ref&gt;

Current estimates on the total number of casualties within Soviet Ukraine range mostly from 2.2&amp;nbsp;million&lt;ref name=Vallin2005&gt;France Meslé, Gilles Pison, Jacques Vallin [http://www.ined.fr/en/resources_documentation/publications/pop_soc/bdd/publication/47/ France-Ukraine: Demographic Twins Separated by History], ''Population and societies'', N°413, juin 2005&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=Vallinbook&gt;ce Meslé, Jacques Vallin Mortalité et causes de décès en Ukraine au XXè siècle + CDRom ISBN 2-7332-0152-2 CD online data (partially – [http://www.ined.fr/fichier/t_publication/cdrom_mortukraine/cdrom.htm Ined.fr]&lt;/ref&gt;
to 4 to 5 million.&lt;ref name=Naslidky4&gt;Stanislav Kulchytsky, Hennadiy Yefimenko. [http://web.archive.org/web/20070708024619/http://www.history.org.ua/kul/contents.htm Демографічні наслідки голодомору 1933 р. в Україні. Всесоюзний перепис 1937 р. в Україні: документи та матеріали] (Demographic consequence of Holodomor of 1933 in Ukraine. The all-Union census of 1937 in Ukraine), Kiev, Institute of History, 2003&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=Tragediya&gt;С. Уиткрофт (Stephen G. Wheatcroft), [http://lj.streamclub.ru/history/tragedy.html#add2 &quot;О демографических свидетельствах трагедии советской деревни в 1931—1933 гг.&quot;] (On demographic evidence of the tragedy of the Soviet village in 1931–1833), &quot;Трагедия советской деревни: Коллективизация и раскулачивание 1927–1939 гг.: Документы и материалы. Том 3. Конец 1930–1933 гг.&quot;, Российская политическая энциклопедия, 2001, ISBN 5-8243-0225-1, с. 885, Приложение № 2&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;britannica&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.britannica.com/EBchecked/topic/612921/Ukraine/30078/Soviet-Ukraine#ref=ref404577|location=Ukraine |title=The famine of 1932–33 |publisher=Britannica.com |accessdate=25 June 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;

A Ukrainian court found Josef Stalin and other leaders of the former Soviet Union guilty of genocide by &quot;organizing mass famine in Ukraine in 1932–1933&quot; in January 2010. However, the court &quot;dropped criminal proceedings over the suspects' deaths&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.kyivpost.com/news/city/detail/56954/ Kyiv court accuses Stalin leadership of organizing famine], [[Kyiv Post]] (13 January 2010)&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://en.rian.ru/exsoviet/20100113/157536602.html Ukraine court finds Bolsheviks guilty of Holodomor genocide], (13 January 2010)&lt;/ref&gt;

===Industrialization===
The [[Russian Civil War]] and [[wartime communism]] had a devastating effect on the country's economy. Industrial output in 1922 was 13% of that in 1914. A recovery followed under the [[New Economic Policy]], which allowed a degree of market flexibility within the context of socialism. Under Stalin's direction, this was replaced by a system of centrally ordained &quot;Five-Year Plans&quot; in the late 1920s. These called for a highly ambitious program of state-guided crash industrialization and the collectivization of agriculture.
[[File:Stalin kanal.jpg|thumb|240px|Stalin on building of [[Moscow Canal|Moscow-Volga canal]]. It was constructed from the year 1932 to the year 1937 by [[Gulag]] prisoners.]]
With seed capital unavailable because of international reaction to Communist policies, little [[international trade]], and virtually no modern infrastructure, Stalin's government financed industrialization both by restraining consumption on the part of ordinary Soviet citizens to ensure that capital went for re-investment into industry, and by ruthless extraction of wealth from the kulaks.

In 1933 workers' real earnings sank to about one-tenth of the 1926 level.{{Citation needed|date=July 2009}} Common and political prisoners in [[labor camp]]s were forced to do unpaid labor, and communists and [[Komsomol]] members were frequently &quot;mobilized&quot; for various construction projects. The Soviet Union used numerous foreign experts, to design new factories, supervise construction, instruct workers and improve manufacturing processes. The most notable foreign contractor was [[Albert Kahn (architect)|Albert Kahn's]] firm that designed and built 521 factories between 1930 and 1932. As a rule, factories were supplied with imported equipment.

In spite of early breakdowns and failures, the first two Five-Year Plans achieved rapid industrialization from a very low economic base. While it is generally agreed that the Soviet Union achieved significant levels of economic growth under Stalin, the precise rate of growth is disputed. It is not disputed, however, that these gains were accomplished at the cost of millions of lives. Official Soviet estimates stated the annual rate of growth at 13.9%; Russian and Western estimates gave lower figures of 5.8% and even 2.9%. Indeed, one estimate is that Soviet growth became temporarily much higher after Stalin's death.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|url=http://ipn.lexi.net/images/uploaded/12-402934626c558--charles_steele_chapter6.pdf|title=Sustainable Development: Promoting Progress or Perpetuating Poverty?|author=Charles N. Steele|publisher=Profile Books|year=2002|format=PDF|accessdate=28 December 2008}} See also: {{cite web|url=http://www.cepr.org/meets/wkcn/7/753/papers/brainerd.pdf|title=Reassessing the Standard of Living in the Soviet Union|publisher=Centre for Economic Policy Research|year=2002|accessdate=19 July 2008|format=PDF}}&lt;/ref&gt;

According to Robert Lewis the Five-Year Plan substantially helped to modernize the previously backward Soviet economy. New products were developed, and the scale and efficiency of existing production greatly increased. Some innovations were based on indigenous technical developments, others on imported foreign technology.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|author=Robert Lewis|title=The Economic Transformation of the Soviet Union|coauthors=ed. Mark Harrison, [[R.W. Davies]], [[S.G. Wheatcroft]]|page=188|publisher=Cambridge University Press|year=1994}}&lt;/ref&gt; Despite its costs, the industrialization effort allowed the Soviet Union to fight, and ultimately win, World War II.

===Science===
{{Main|Science and technology in the Soviet Union|Suppressed research in the Soviet Union}}
Science in the [[Soviet Union]] was under strict ideological control by Stalin and his government, along with art and literature. There was significant progress in &quot;ideologically safe&quot; domains, owing to the free [[Soviet education]] system and state-financed research. However, the most notable legacy during Stalin's time was his public endorsement of the Agronomist [[Trofim Lysenko]] who rejected [[Mendelian genetics]] as &quot;[[bourgeois pseudoscience]]s&quot; and instead supported Hybridization theories that caused widespread agricultural destruction and major setbacks in Soviet knowledge in biology. Although many scientists opposed his views, those who publicly came out were imprisoned and denounced. Some areas of physics were criticized.&lt;ref&gt;Oliver Freire Jr. ''[http://anikov.myweb.uga.edu/intel/freire.pdf Marxism and the Quantum Controversy: Responding to Max Jammer's Question]''&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Péter Szegedi ''[http://hps.elte.hu/~szegedi/cikkek/coldw.doc Cold War and Interpretations in Quantum Mechanics]''&lt;/ref&gt;

===Social services===
Under the Soviet government people benefited from some social liberalization. Girls were given an adequate, equal education and women had equal rights in employment,&lt;ref name=&quot;RedTsar&quot; /&gt;{{Page needed|date=February 2011}} improving lives for women and families. Stalinist development also contributed to advances in health care, which significantly increased the lifespan and quality of life of the typical Soviet citizen.&lt;ref name=&quot;RedTsar&quot; /&gt;{{Page needed|date=February 2011}} Stalin's policies granted the Soviet people universal access to healthcare and education, effectively creating the first generation free from the fear of [[typhus]], [[cholera]], and [[malaria]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Montefiore-Stalin&quot;&gt;Simon Sebag Montefiore. Stalin: The Court of the Red Tsar, Knopf, 2004 (ISBN 1-4000-4230-5)&lt;/ref&gt;{{Page needed|date=February 2011}} The occurrences of these diseases dropped to record low numbers, increasing life spans by decades.&lt;ref name=&quot;Montefiore-Stalin&quot; /&gt;{{Page needed|date=February 2011}}

Soviet women under Stalin were the first generation of women able to give birth in the safety of a hospital, with access to prenatal care.&lt;ref name=&quot;Montefiore-Stalin&quot; /&gt;{{Page needed|date=February 2011}} Education was also an example of an increase in standard of living after economic development. The generation born during Stalin's rule was the first near-universally literate generation. Millions benefitted from mass literacy campaigns in the 1930s, and from workers training schemes.&lt;ref name=&quot;Acton-Tsarist&quot;&gt;Acton, Edward, ''Russia, The Tsarist and Soviet Legacy'', Longmann Group Ltd (1995) ISBN 0-582-08922-0&lt;/ref&gt;{{Page needed|date=February 2011}} Engineers were sent abroad to learn industrial technology, and hundreds of foreign engineers were brought to Russia on contract.&lt;ref name=&quot;Montefiore-Stalin&quot; /&gt;{{Page needed|date=February 2011}} Transport links were improved and many new railways built. Workers who exceeded their quotas, ''[[Stakhanovite]]s'', received many incentives for their work;&lt;ref name=&quot;Acton-Tsarist&quot; /&gt;{{Page needed|date=February 2011}} they could afford to buy the goods that were mass-produced by the rapidly expanding Soviet economy.

The increase in demand due to industrialization and the decrease in the workforce due to World War II and repressions generated a major expansion in job opportunities for the survivors, especially for women.&lt;ref name=&quot;Acton-Tsarist&quot; /&gt;{{Page needed|date=February 2011}}

===Culture===
{{Main|Socialist Realism}}
Although he was Georgian by birth, Stalin became a [[Russia#Soviet_Russia|Russian nationalist]] and significantly promoted Russian history, language, and Russian national heroes, particularly during the 1930s and 1940s. He held the Russians up as the elder brothers of the non-Russian minorities.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite encyclopedia|title=Russia|year=2007|encyclopedia=[[Encyclopædia Britannica|Encyclopædia Britannica Online]]|url=http://www.britannica.com/EBchecked/topic/513251/Russia|accessdate=19 July 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt;

During Stalin's reign the official and long-lived style of [[Socialist Realism]] was established for painting, sculpture, music, drama and literature. Previously fashionable &quot;revolutionary&quot; [[expressionism]], [[abstract art]], and [[Russian avant-garde|avant-garde]] experimentation were discouraged or denounced as &quot;[[formalism (art)|formalism]]&quot;.

The degree of Stalin's personal involvement in general, and in specific instances, has been the subject of discussion.{{Citation needed|date=February 2011}} Stalin's favorite novel ''[[Pharaoh (novel)|Pharaoh]]'', shared similarities{{Citation needed|date=February 2011}} with [[Sergei Eisenstein]]'s film, ''[[Ivan the Terrible (film)|Ivan the Terrible]]'', produced under Stalin's tutelage.

In architecture, a [[Stalinist architecture|Stalinist Empire Style]] (basically, updated [[neoclassicism]] on a very large scale, exemplified by the [[Seven Sisters (Moscow)|Seven Sisters]] of Moscow) replaced the [[constructivist architecture|constructivism]] of the 1920s. Stalin's rule had a largely disruptive effect on indigenous cultures within the Soviet Union, though the politics of [[Korenizatsiya]] and forced development were possibly beneficial to the integration of later generations of indigenous cultures.
&lt;!-- Deleted image removed: [[File:Stalin church 1939.jpg|thumb|upright|Caricature of &quot;Stalin a great friend of religion&quot;, when churches were allowed to be opened during World War II.]] --&gt;

===Religion===
{{Main|Religion in the Soviet Union}}
Stalin followed the position adopted by Lenin that religion was an opiate that needed to be removed in order to construct the ideal communist society. To this end, his government promoted atheism through special atheistic education in schools, massive amounts of anti-religious propaganda, the antireligious work of public institutions (especially the [[Society of the Godless]]), discriminatory laws, and also a terror campaign against religious believers. By the late 1930s it had become dangerous to be publicly associated with religion.&lt;ref&gt;Dimitry V. Pospielovsky. A History of Soviet Atheism in Theory and Practice, and the Believer, vol 2: Soviet Anti-Religious Campaigns and Persecutions, St Martin's Press, New York (1988) p. 89&lt;/ref&gt;

Stalin's role in the fortunes of the [[Russian Orthodox Church]] is complex. Continuous persecution in the 1930s resulted in its near-extinction as a public institution: by 1939, active parishes numbered in the low hundreds (down from 54,000 in 1917), many churches had been leveled, and tens of thousands of priests, monks and nuns were persecuted and killed. Over 100,000 were shot during the purges of 1937–1938.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|authorlink=Alexander Nikolaevich Yakovlev|author=Alexander N. Yakovlev|url=http://books.google.com/?id=ChRk43tVxTwC&amp;pg=PA165|title=A Century of Violence in Soviet Russia|publisher=Yale University Press|year=2002|page=165|isbn=9780300103229|author2=Austin, Anthony|author3=Hollander, Paul|date=10 April 2004}} See also: {{Cite book|author=Richard Pipes|authorlink=Richard Pipes|title=Communism: A History|publisher=[[Modern Library Chronicles]]|year=2001|page=66|isbn=0679640509}}&lt;/ref&gt; During World War II, the Church was allowed a revival as a patriotic organization, and thousands of parishes were reactivated until a further round of suppression in [[Nikita Khrushchev|Khrushchev's]] time. The Russian Orthodox Church Synod's recognition of the Soviet government and of Stalin personally led to a schism with the [[Russian Orthodox Church Outside Russia]].

Just days before Stalin's death, certain religious sects [[Forced settlements in the Soviet Union#Religious persecution|were outlawed and persecuted]]. Many religions popular in the ethnic regions of the Soviet Union including the Roman Catholic Church (including the [[Eastern Catholic Churches]]), Baptists, Islam, Buddhism, Judaism, etc. underwent ordeals similar to the Orthodox churches in other parts: thousands of monks were persecuted, and hundreds of churches, synagogues, mosques, temples, sacred monuments, monasteries and other religious buildings were razed.

Stalin had a different policy outside of the Soviet Union, he supported the Communist [[Uyghur people|Uyghur]] Muslim separatists under [[Ehmetjan Qasim]] in the [[Ili Rebellion]] against the Anti Communist [[Republic of China]] regime. He supplied weapons to the Uyghur Ili army and Red Army support against Chinese forces, and helped them established the [[Second East Turkestan Republic]] of which Islam was the official state religion.

===Theorist===
{{Main|Stalinism}}
Stalin and his supporters have highlighted the notion that [[Socialism in One Country|socialism can be built and consolidated by a country]] as underdeveloped as Russia during the 1920s. Indeed this might be the only means in which it could be built in a hostile environment.&lt;ref&gt;Joseph V.Stalin. &quot;Voprosy leninizma&quot;, 2nd ed., Moscow, p. 589; (1951) &quot;Istoricheskij materializm&quot;, ed. by F. B. Konstantinov, Moscow, p. 402; P. Calvert (1982). &quot;The Concept of Class&quot;, New York, pp. 144–145&lt;/ref&gt; In 1933, Stalin put forward the theory of [[aggravation of class struggle under socialism|aggravation of the class struggle along with the development of socialism]], arguing that the further the country would move forward, the more acute forms of struggle will be used by the doomed remnants of exploiter classes in their last desperate efforts{{ndash}} and that, therefore, political repression was necessary.

In 1936, Stalin announced that the society of the Soviet Union consisted of two non-antagonistic classes: workers and [[kolkhoz]] peasantry. These corresponded to the two different forms of property over the [[means of production]] that existed in the Soviet Union: state property (for the workers) and collective property (for the peasantry). In addition to these, Stalin distinguished the stratum of [[intelligentsia]]. The concept of &quot;non-antagonistic classes&quot; was entirely new to Leninist theory. Among Stalin's contributions to Communist theoretical literature were &quot;[[Dialectical and Historical Materialism]],&quot; &quot;Marxism and the National Question&quot;, &quot;Trotskyism or Leninism&quot;, and &quot;The Principles of Leninism.&quot;

==Calculating the number of victims==
Researchers before the 1991 dissolution of the Soviet Union attempting to count the number of people killed under Stalin's regime produced estimates ranging from 3 to 60 million.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://users.erols.com/mwhite28/warstat1.htm#Stalin|title=Twentieth Century Atlas – Death Tolls}} See also: Aleksandr Solzhenitsyn: ''The Gulag Archipelago 1918–1956'', 1973–1976 ISBN 0-8133-3289-3&lt;/ref&gt; After the [[Dissolution of the Soviet Union|Soviet Union dissolved]], evidence from the Soviet archives also became available, containing official records of the execution of approximately 800,000 prisoners under Stalin for either political or criminal offenses, around 1.7&amp;nbsp;million deaths in the Gulags and some 390,000 deaths during kulak [[Forced settlements in the Soviet Union|forced resettlement]]{{ndash}} for a total of about 3 million officially recorded victims in these categories.&lt;ref&gt;Stephen G. Wheatcroft, &quot;Victims of Stalinism and the Soviet Secret Police: The Comparability and Reliability of the Archival Data. Not the Last Word&quot;, Source: Europe-Asia Studies, Vol. 51, No. 2 (Mar. 1999), pp. 315–345, gives the following numbers: During 1921–53, the number of sentences was (political convictions): sentences, 4,060,306; death penalties, 799,473; camps and prisons, 2,634397; excile, 413,512; other, 215,942. In addition, during 1937–52 there were 14,269,753 non-political sentences, among them 34,228 death penalties, 2,066,637 sentences for 0–1 year, 4,362,973 for 2–5 years, 1,611,293 for 6–10 years, and 286,795 for more than 10 years. Other sentences were non-custodial&lt;/ref&gt;

The official Soviet archival records do not contain comprehensive figures for some categories of victims, such as the those of [[Population transfer in the Soviet Union|ethnic deportations]] or of [[Expulsion of Germans after World War II|German population transfers]] in the aftermath of World War II.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|author=Simon Sebag Montefiore|authorlink=Simon Sebag Montefiore|title=Stalin: The Court of the Red Tsar|page=649|isbn=0753817667}}&lt;/ref&gt; Eric D. Weitz wrote, &quot;By 1948, according to [[The Black Book of Communism|Nicolas Werth]], the mortality rate of the 600,000 people deported from the Caucasus between 1943 and 1944 had reached 25%.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;&quot;''[http://books.google.com/books?id=W50Gg4o_2q4C&amp;pg=PA82 A century of genocide: utopias of race and nation]''&quot;. Eric D. Weitz (2003). [[Princeton University Press]]. p.82. ISBN 0691009139&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Nicholas Werth, &quot;A state against its people: violence, repression and terror in the Soviet Union&quot; in Stéphane Courtois, Mark Kramer. ''[http://books.google.com/books?id=H1jsgYCoRioC&amp;pg=PA223 The Black Book of Communism: Crimes, Terror, Repression]''. [[Harvard University Press]], 1999. pp. 33–268: p.223. ISBN 0-674-07608-7&lt;/ref&gt; Other notable exclusions from [[NKVD]] data on repression deaths include the Katyn massacre, [[NKVD prisoner massacres|other killings]] in the newly occupied areas, and the mass shootings of [[Red Army]] personnel (deserters and so-called deserters) in 1941. The Soviets executed 158,000 soldiers for desertion during the war,&lt;ref&gt;&quot;[http://www.washingtonpost.com/wp-dyn/content/article/2006/04/04/AR2006040401908.html Recording a Hidden History]&quot;. The Washington Post. 5 April 2006&lt;/ref&gt; and the &quot;blocking detachments&quot; of the NKVD shot thousands more.&lt;ref&gt;Roberts, Geoffrey. &quot;''[http://books.google.com/books?id=5GCFUqBRZ-QC&amp;pg=PA98 Stalin's wars: from World War to Cold War, 1939–1953]''&quot;. New Heaven, CT; London: Yale University Press, 2006 (ISBN 0300112041), p. 98&lt;/ref&gt; Also, the official statistics on Gulag mortality exclude deaths of prisoners taking place shortly after their release but which resulted from the harsh treatment in the camps.&lt;ref&gt;Ellman, Michael. ''[http://sovietinfo.tripod.com/ELM-Repression_Statistics.pdf Soviet Repression Statistics: Some Comments]'' Europe-Asia Studies. Vol 54, No. 7, 2002, 1151–1172&lt;/ref&gt; Some historians also believe the official archival figures of the categories that were recorded by Soviet authorities to be unreliable and incomplete.&lt;ref name=&quot;Harvnb|Applebaum|2003&quot;&gt;{{Harvnb|Applebaum|2003}}&lt;/ref&gt;{{Page needed|date=February 2011}}&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://sovietinfo.tripod.com/|title=Soviet Studies}} See also: Robert Gellately. ''Lenin, Stalin, and Hitler: The Age of Social Catastrophe.'' Knopf, 2007 ISBN 1400040051 p. 584: ''&quot;Anne Applebaum is right to insist that the statistics 'can never fully describe what happened.' They do suggest, however, the massive scope of the repression and killing.&quot;''&lt;/ref&gt; In addition to failures regarding comprehensive recordings, as one additional example, [[Robert Gellately]] and [[Simon Sebag-Montefiore]] argue the many suspects beaten and tortured to death while in &quot;investigative custody&quot; were likely not to have been counted amongst the executed.&lt;ref name=&quot;RedTsar&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Robert Gellately. ''Lenin, Stalin, and Hitler: The Age of Social Catastrophe.'' Knopf, 2007. ISBN 1400040051 p. 256&lt;/ref&gt;

Historians working after the Soviet Union's dissolution have estimated victim totals ranging from approximately 4 million to nearly 10&amp;nbsp;million, not including those who died in famines.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.etext.org/Politics/Staljin/Staljin/articles/AHR/AHR.html |title=Victims of the Soviet Penal System in the Pre-war Years|author=Getty, Rittersporn, Zemskov |archiveurl = http://web.archive.org/web/20080611064213/http://www.etext.org/Politics/Staljin/Staljin/articles/AHR/AHR.html |archivedate = 11 June 2008}} See also: {{Cite journal|url=http://sovietinfo.tripod.com/WCR-German_Soviet.pdf|title=The Scale and Nature of German and Soviet Repression and Mass Killings, 1930–45|author=Stephen Wheatcroft|year=1996|format=PDF|journal=Europe-Asia Studies|accessdate=28 December 2008|ref=harv}} and {{Cite journal|journal=Soviet Studies|url=http://sovietinfo.tripod.com/WCR-Scale_Repression.pdf|title=More light on the scale of repression and excess mortality in the Soviet Union in the 1930s|format=PDF|author=Stephen Wheatcroft|year=1990|accessdate=28 December 2008|ref=harv}}&lt;/ref&gt; Russian writer Vadim Erlikman, for example, makes the following estimates: executions, 1.5&amp;nbsp;million; gulags, 5 million; deportations, 1.7&amp;nbsp;million out of 7.5&amp;nbsp;million deported; and [[POWs]] and German civilians, 1 million{{ndash}} a total of about 9&amp;nbsp;million victims of repression.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|author=Vadim Erlikman|title=Poteri narodonaseleniia v XX veke: spravochnik|location=Moscow 2004|isbn=5-93165-107-1|year=2004|publisher=Russkai︠a︡ panorama}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Some have also included deaths of 6 to 8 million people in the [[Droughts and famines in Russia and the Soviet Union|1932–1933 famine]] as victims of Stalin's repression. This categorization is controversial however, as historians differ as to whether the famine was a deliberate part of the campaign of repression against kulaks and others,&lt;ref name=&quot;Ellman&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Ellman2005&quot;&gt;{{Cite journal| doi = 10.1080/09668130500199392| last = Ellman| first = Michael|title = The Role of Leadership Perceptions and of Intent in the Soviet Famine of 1931–1934|journal=Europe-Asia Studies|volume = 57|issue = 6|pages = 823–41|publisher=Routledge|year = 2005|month = 09|url = http://www.paulbogdanor.com/left/soviet/famine/ellman.pdf|format = PDF|accessdate =4 July 2008| ref = harv}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[[Norman Naimark|Naimark, Norman M.]] ''Stalin's Genocides (Human Rights and Crimes against Humanity).'' [[Princeton University Press]], 2010. pp. 134–135. ISBN 0691147841&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[[Steven Rosefielde|Rosefielde, Steven]]. ''[[Red Holocaust (2009 book)|Red Holocaust]].'' [[Routledge]], 2009. ISBN 0415777577 pg. 259&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[[Timothy Snyder|Snyder, Timothy]]. ''Bloodlands: Europe Between Hitler and Stalin.'' [[Basic Books]], 2010. ISBN 0465002390 pp. vii, 413&lt;/ref&gt; or simply an [[unintended consequence]] of the struggle over forced collectivization.&lt;ref name=&quot;davies-wheatcroft-2004&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref&gt;R. W. Davies, Stephen G. Wheatcroft: ''The Years of Hunger: Soviet Agriculture, 1931–1933'', 2004 ISBN 0-333-31107-8&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Andreev, EM, et al., ''Naselenie Sovetskogo Soiuza, 1922–1991.'' Moscow, Nauka, 1993. ISBN 5-02-013479-1&lt;/ref&gt;

Accordingly, if famine victims are included, a minimum of around 10 million deaths—6&amp;nbsp;million from famine and 4&amp;nbsp;million from other causes—are attributable to the regime,&lt;ref&gt;Steven Rosefielde. [http://www.paulbogdanor.com/left/soviet/rosefielde.pdf Documented Homicides and Excess Deaths: New Insights into the Scale of Killing in the USSR during the 1930s]. ''Communist and Post-Communist Studies'', Vol. 30, No. 3, pp. 321–333, 1997. [[University of California]]&lt;/ref&gt; with a number of recent historians suggesting a likely total of around 20 million, citing much higher victim totals from executions, gulags, deportations and other causes.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|author=Simon Sebag Montefiore|authorlink=Simon Sebag Montefiore|title=Stalin: The Court of the Red Tsar|page=649: ''&quot;Perhaps 20 million had been killed; 28&amp;nbsp;million deported, of whom 18&amp;nbsp;million had slaved in the Gulags.&quot;''|isbn=0753817667}} See also: {{Cite book|author=Dmitri Volkogonov|authorlink=Dmitri Volkogonov|title=Autopsy for an Empire: The Seven Leaders Who Built the Soviet Regime|pages=139: ''&quot;Between 1929 and 1953 the state created by Lenin and set in motion by Stalin deprived 21.5&amp;nbsp;million Soviet citizens of their lives.&quot;''|isbn=0684834200}} and {{Cite book|authorlink=Alexander Nikolaevich Yakovlev|author=Alexander N. Yakovlev|url=http://books.google.com/?id=ChRk43tVxTwC&amp;pg=PA234|title=A Century of Violence in Soviet Russia|publisher=[[Yale University Press]]|year=2002|page=234: ''&quot;My own many years and experience in the rehabilitation of victims of political terror allow me to assert that the number of people in the USSR who were killed for political motives or who died in prisons and camps during the entire period of Soviet power totaled 20 to 25 million. And unquestionably one must add those who died of famine{{ndash}} more than 5.5&amp;nbsp;million during the civil war and more than 5&amp;nbsp;million during the 1930s.&quot;''|isbn=9780300103229|author2=Austin, Anthony|author3=Hollander, Paul|date=10 April 2004}} and Robert Gellately. ''Lenin, Stalin, and Hitler: The Age of Social Catastrophe.'' [[Knopf]], 2007 ISBN 1400040051 p. 584: ''&quot;More recent estimations of the Soviet-on-Soviet killing have been more 'modest' and range between ten and twenty million.&quot;'' and [[Stéphane Courtois]]. ''[[The Black Book of Communism]]: Crimes, Terror Repression.'' [[Harvard University Press]], 1999. p. 4: ''&quot;U.S.S.R.: 20 million deaths.&quot;'' and Jonathan Brent, ''Inside the Stalin Archives: Discovering the New Russia''. Atlas &amp; Co., 2008 (ISBN 0977743330) [http://atlasandco.com/images/uploads/samples/pdf/InsideStalinArchives-web.pdf Introduction online] ([[PDF]] file): ''Estimations on the number of Stalin's victims over his twenty-five year reign, from 1928 to 1953, vary widely, but 20 million is now considered the minimum.'' and [[Steven Rosefielde]]. ''[[Red Holocaust (2009 book)|Red Holocaust]]''. [[Routledge]], 2009. ISBN 0415777577 p.17: ''&quot;We now know as well beyond a reasonable doubt that there were more than 13 million [[Mass killings under Communist regimes|Red Holocaust]] victims 1929–53, and this figure could rise above 20 million.&quot;'' and [[Norman Naimark]]. ''Stalin's Genocides (Human Rights and Crimes against Humanity).'' [[Princeton University Press]], 2010. p. 11: ''&quot;Yet Stalin's own responsibility for the killing of some fifteen to twenty million people carries its own horrific weight...&quot;&lt;/ref&gt; Adding 6–8&amp;nbsp;million famine victims to Erlikman's estimates above, for example, would yield a total of between 15 and 17 million victims. Researcher [[Robert Conquest]], meanwhile, has revised his original estimate of up to 30 million victims down to 20&amp;nbsp;million.&lt;ref&gt;Robert Conquest. The Great Terror: A Reassessment, Oxford University Press, 1991 (ISBN 0-19-507132-8)&lt;/ref&gt; In his most recent edition of [[The Great Terror]] (2007), Conquest states that while exact numbers may never be known with complete certainty, the various terror campaigns launched by the Soviet government claimed no fewer than 15 million lives.&lt;ref name=&quot;Conquest2007Reassessment&quot;&gt;Robert Conquest, ''The Great Terror: A Reassessment, 40th Anniversary Edition'', Oxford University Press, 2007, in Preface, p. xvi: &quot;Exact numbers may never be known with complete certainty, but the total of deaths caused by the whole range of Soviet regime's terrors can hardly be lower than some fifteen million.&quot;&lt;/ref&gt; Others maintain that their earlier higher victim total estimates are correct.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.hawaii.edu/powerkills/MEGA.HTM|title=Regimes murdering over 10 million people}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.distributedrepublic.net/archives/2006/05/01/how-many-did-stalin-really-murder/ How Many Did Stalin Really Murder?] by Professor [[R.J. Rummel]]&lt;/ref&gt;

==World War II, 1939–1945==
{{Main|Soviet Union in World War II}}
[[File:Bundesarchiv Bild 183-H27337, Moskau, Stalin und Ribbentrop im Kreml.jpg|thumb|upright|[[Joachim von Ribbentrop|Ribbentrop]] and Stalin at the signing of the Pact]]

===Pact with Hitler===
After a failed attempt to sign an anti-German military alliance with France and Britain&lt;ref name=&quot;roberts30&quot;&gt;{{Harvnb|Roberts|2006|pp=30–32}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;shirer510&quot;&gt;{{Harvnb|Shirer|1990|pp=510–535}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;murphy&quot;&gt;{{Harvnb|Murphy|2006|pp=24–28}}&lt;/ref&gt; and talks with Germany regarding a potential political deal,&lt;ref&gt;Lionel Kochan. ''The Struggle For Germany. 1914–1945''. New York, 1963&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;ericson57&quot;&gt;{{Harvnb|Ericson|1999|p=57}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Harvnb|Roberts|1992|p=64}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Vehviläinen, Olli, ''Finland in the Second World War: Between Germany and Russia'', Macmillan, 2002, ISBN 0333801490, p. 30&lt;/ref&gt; on 23 August 1939, the Soviet Union entered into a [[Molotov-Ribbentrop Pact|non-aggression pact]] with [[Nazi Germany]], negotiated by Soviet foreign minister [[Vyacheslav Molotov]] and German foreign minister [[Joachim von Ribbentrop]].&lt;ref name=&quot;roberts&quot;&gt;{{Harvnb|Roberts|1992|pp=57–78}}&lt;/ref&gt; Officially a non-aggression treaty only, an appended secret protocol, also reached on 23 August 1939, divided the whole of eastern Europe into German and Soviet [[spheres of influence]].&lt;ref name=&quot;britannicamr&quot;&gt;Encyclopedia Britanica, ''German-Soviet Nonaggression Pact'', 2008&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;mrtext&quot;&gt;[http://www.fordham.edu/halsall/mod/1939pact.html ''Text of the Nazi-Soviet Non-Aggression Pact''], executed 23 August 1939&lt;/ref&gt;

The eastern part of Poland, Latvia, Estonia, Finland and part of Romania were recognized as parts of the [[Soviet sphere of influence]],&lt;ref name=&quot;mrtext&quot; /&gt; with Lithuania added in a second secret protocol in September 1939.&lt;ref name=&quot;christie&quot;&gt;Christie, Kenneth, ''Historical Injustice and Democratic Transition in Eastern Asia and Northern Europe: Ghosts at the Table of Democracy'', RoutledgeCurzon, 2002, ISBN 0700715991&lt;/ref&gt; Stalin and Ribbentrop traded toasts on the night of the signing discussing past hostilities between the countries.&lt;ref name=&quot;shirer541&quot;&gt;Shirer, William L., ''The Rise and Fall of the Third Reich: A History of Nazi Germany'', Simon and Schuster, 1990 ISBN 0671728687, p. 541&lt;/ref&gt;

===Implementing the division of Eastern Europe and other invasions===
On 1 September 1939, the [[German invasion of Poland|German invasion]] of its agreed upon portion of Poland started World War II.&lt;ref name=&quot;roberts&quot; /&gt; On 17 September the [[Red Army]] [[Soviet invasion of Poland|invaded]] eastern Poland and occupied the Polish territory assigned to it by the Molotov-Ribbentrop Pact, followed by co-ordination with German forces in Poland.&lt;ref name=&quot;stalinswars43&quot;&gt;{{Harvnb|Roberts|2006|p=43}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;sanford&quot;&gt;{{Cite book|authorlink=George Sanford (scholar) |last=Sanford |first=George |year=2005 |title=Katyn and the Soviet Massacre Of 1940: Truth, Justice And Memory |location=London, New York |publisher=[[Routledge]] |isbn=0415338735}}&lt;/ref&gt; Eleven days later, the secret protocol of the Molotov-Ribbentrop Pact was modified, allotting Germany a larger part of Poland, while ceding most of Lithuania to the Soviet Union.&lt;ref name=&quot;wettig20&quot;&gt;{{Harvnb|Wettig|2008|p=20}}&lt;/ref&gt;
[[File:Ribbentrop-Molotov.svg|thumb|left|250px|Planned and actual territorial changes in Eastern and Central Europe 1939–1940 (click to enlarge)]]
After Stalin declared that he was going to &quot;solve the Baltic problem&quot;, by June 1940, Lithuania, Latvia and Estonia were [[Occupation of the Baltic states|merged into the Soviet Union]], after repressions and actions therein brought about the deaths of over 160,000 citizens of these states.&lt;ref name=&quot;wettig20&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;wettig21&quot;&gt;{{Harvnb|Wettig|2008|p=21}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;senn&quot;&gt;Senn, Alfred Erich, ''Lithuania 1940 : revolution from above'', Amsterdam, New York, Rodopi, 2007 ISBN 9789042022256&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|author=Simon Sebag Montefiore|authorlink=Simon Sebag Montefiore|title=Stalin: The Court of the Red Tsar|page=334|isbn=0753817667}}&lt;/ref&gt; After facing stiff resistance in an [[Winter War|invasion of Finland]],&lt;ref name=&quot;ckpipe&quot;&gt;Kennedy-Pipe, Caroline, ''Stalin's Cold War'', New York: Manchester University Press, 1995, ISBN 0719042011&lt;/ref&gt; an [[Moscow Peace Treaty|interim peace]] was entered, granting the Soviet Union the eastern region of Karelia (10% of Finnish territory).&lt;ref name=&quot;ckpipe&quot; /&gt;

After this campaign, Stalin took actions to bolster the Soviet military, modify training and improve propaganda efforts in the Soviet military.&lt;ref name=&quot;stalinswars53&quot;&gt;{{Harvnb|Roberts|2006|p=53}}&lt;/ref&gt; In June 1940, Stalin directed the Soviet annexation of [[Bessarabia]] and northern [[Bukovina]], proclaiming this formerly Romanian territory part of the [[Moldavian Soviet Socialist Republic]].&lt;ref name=&quot;brackman341&quot;&gt;{{Harvnb|Brackman|2001|p=341}}&lt;/ref&gt; But in annexing northern Bukovina, Stalin had gone beyond the agreed limits of the secret protocol.&lt;ref name=&quot;brackman341&quot; /&gt;

[[File:Matsuoka signs the Soviet–Japanese Neutrality Pact-1.jpg|thumb|right|Stalin and Molotov on the signing of the [[Soviet–Japanese Neutrality Pact]] with the [[Empire of Japan]], 1941]]
After the [[Tripartite Pact]] was signed by [[Axis Powers]] Germany, Japan and Italy, in October 1940, Stalin traded letters with Ribbentrop, with Stalin writing about entering an agreement regarding a &quot;permanent basis&quot; for their &quot;mutual interests.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;stalinswars58&quot;&gt;{{Harvnb|Roberts|2006|p=58}}&lt;/ref&gt; After a [[German–Soviet Axis talks|conference]] in Berlin between Hitler, Molotov and Ribbentrop, Germany presented the Molotov with a proposed written agreement for Axis entry.&lt;ref name=&quot;brackman341&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;brackman343&quot;&gt;{{Harvnb|Brackman|2001|p=343}}&lt;/ref&gt; On 25 November, Stalin responded with a proposed written agreement for Axis entry which was never answered by Germany.&lt;ref name=&quot;stalinswars59&quot;&gt;{{Harvnb|Roberts|2006|p=59}}&lt;/ref&gt; Shortly thereafter, Hitler issued a secret directive on the eventual attempts to invade the Soviet Union.&lt;ref name=&quot;stalinswars59&quot; /&gt; In an effort to demonstrate peaceful intentions toward Germany, on 13 April 1941, Stalin oversaw the signing of a neutrality pact with Axis power Japan.&lt;ref name=&quot;stalinswars63&quot;&gt;{{Harvnb|Roberts|2006|p=63}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Hitler breaks the pact===
During the early morning of 22 June 1941, [[Adolf Hitler|Hitler]] broke the pact by implementing [[Operation Barbarossa]], the German invasion of Soviet held territories and the Soviet Union that began the war on the [[Eastern Front (World War II)|Eastern Front]].&lt;ref name=&quot;stalinswars82&quot;&gt;{{Harvnb|Roberts|2006|p=82}}&lt;/ref&gt; Although Stalin had received warnings from spies and his generals,&lt;ref name=&quot;stalinswars67&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|url=http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E06E4D71638F931A25755C0A9639C8B63 |title=Stalin's Intelligence |work=The New York Times|first=Niall|last=Ferguson|date=12 June 2005|accessdate=7 May 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;stalinswars68&quot;&gt;{{Harvnb|Roberts|2006|p=68}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;murphyxv&quot;&gt;{{Harvnb|Murphy|2006|p=xv}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;yakovlev&quot;&gt;{{Cite book|title=A Century of Violence in Soviet Russia|url=http://yalepress.yale.edu/yupbooks/book.asp?isbn=0300103220|last=Yakovlev|first=Alexander|coauthors=Anthony Austin|year=2004|publisher=Yale University Press|location=New Haven, Connecticut |isbn=0300087608}}&lt;/ref&gt; he felt that Germany would not attack the Soviet Union until Germany had defeated Britain.&lt;ref name=&quot;stalinswars67&quot;&gt;{{Harvnb|Roberts|2006|p=67}}&lt;/ref&gt; In the initial hours after the German attack commenced, Stalin hesitated, wanting to ensure that the German attack was sanctioned by Hitler, rather than the unauthorized action of a rogue general.&lt;ref name=&quot;RedTsar&quot; /&gt;{{Page needed|date=February 2011}}

Accounts by [[Nikita Khrushchev]] and [[Anastas Mikoyan]] claim that, after the invasion, Stalin retreated to his dacha in despair for several days and did not participate in leadership decisions.&lt;ref name=&quot;stalinswars89&quot;&gt;{{Harvnb|Roberts|2006|p=89}}&lt;/ref&gt; However, some documentary evidence of orders given by Stalin contradicts these accounts, leading some historians to speculate that Khrushchev's account is inaccurate.&lt;ref name=&quot;stalinswars90&quot;&gt;{{Harvnb|Roberts|2006|p=90}}&lt;/ref&gt; By the end of 1941, the Soviet military had suffered 4.3&amp;nbsp;million casualties&lt;ref name=&quot;stalinswars116&quot;&gt;{{Harvnb|Roberts|2006|pp=116–7}}&lt;/ref&gt; and German forces had advanced 1,050 miles (1,690 kilometers).&lt;ref&gt;Glantz, David, ''The Soviet-German War 1941–45: Myths and Realities: A Survey Essay'', 11 October 2001, p. 7&lt;/ref&gt;

===Soviets stop the Germans===
While the Germans pressed forward, Stalin was confident of an eventual Allied victory over Germany. In September 1941, Stalin told British diplomats that he wanted two agreements: (1) a mutual assistance/aid pact and (2) a recognition that, after the war, the Soviet Union would gain the territories in countries that it had taken pursuant to its division of Eastern Europe with Hitler in the [[Molotov–Ribbentrop Pact]].&lt;ref name=&quot;stalinswars114&quot;&gt;{{Harvnb|Roberts|2006|pp=114–115}}&lt;/ref&gt; The British agreed to assistance but refused to agree upon the territorial gains, which Stalin accepted months later as the military situation deteriorated somewhat in mid-1942.&lt;ref name=&quot;stalinswars114&quot; /&gt; By December, Hitler's troops had advanced to within 20 miles of the [[Kremlin]] in Moscow.&lt;ref name=&quot;stalinswars88&quot;&gt;{{Harvnb|Roberts|2006|p=88}}&lt;/ref&gt; On 5 December, the Soviets launched a counteroffensive, pushing German troops back 40–50 miles from Moscow, the [[Wehrmacht]]'s first significant defeat of the war.&lt;ref name=&quot;stalinswars88&quot; /&gt;

In 1942, Hitler shifted his primary goal from an immediate victory in the East, to the more long-term goal of securing the southern Soviet Union to protect oil fields vital to a long-term German war effort.&lt;ref name=&quot;stalinswars117&quot;&gt;{{Harvnb|Roberts|2006|pp=117–8}}&lt;/ref&gt; While Red Army generals saw evidence that Hitler would shift efforts south, Stalin considered this to be a flanking campaign in [[Battle of Moscow|efforts to take Moscow]].&lt;ref name=&quot;stalinswars124&quot;&gt;{{Harvnb|Roberts|2006|p=124}}&lt;/ref&gt; During the war, [[Time (magazine)|''Time'' magazine]] named Stalin [[Time Person of the Year]] twice&lt;ref&gt;Time Magazine, [http://www.time.com/time/subscriber/personoftheyear/archive/stories/1942.html ''Josef Stalin''], 4 Jan. 1943&lt;/ref&gt; and he was also one of the nominees for [[Time Person of the Century]] title.{{Citation needed|date=February 2011}}

===Soviet push to Germany===
The Soviets repulsed the important [[Operation Blau|German strategic southern campaign]] and, although 2.5&amp;nbsp;million Soviet casualties were suffered in that effort, it permitted the Soviets to take the offensive for most of the rest of the war on the [[Eastern Front (World War II)|Eastern Front]].&lt;ref name=&quot;stalinswars155&quot;&gt;{{Harvnb|Roberts|2006|p=155}}&lt;/ref&gt;
[[File:Teheran conference-1943.jpg|thumb|left|The Big Three: Stalin, U.S. President [[Franklin D. Roosevelt]], and [[Prime Minister of the United Kingdom|British Prime Minister]] [[Winston Churchill]] at the [[Tehran Conference]], November 1943.]]
Germany [[Battle of Kursk|attempted an encirclement attack at Kursk]], which was successfully repulsed by the Soviets.&lt;ref name=&quot;stalinswars156&quot;&gt;{{Harvnb|Roberts|2006|p=156}}&lt;/ref&gt; Kursk marked the beginning of a period where Stalin became more willing to listen to the advice of his generals.&lt;ref name=&quot;stalinswars159&quot; /&gt; By the end of 1943, the Soviets occupied half of the territory taken by the Germans from 1941–1942.&lt;ref name=&quot;stalinswars159&quot;&gt;{{Harvnb|Roberts|2006|p=159}}&lt;/ref&gt; Soviet military industrial output also had increased substantially from late 1941 to early 1943 after Stalin had moved factories well to the East of the front, safe from German invasion and air attack.&lt;ref name=&quot;stalinswars163&quot;&gt;{{Harvnb|Roberts|2006|p=163}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In November 1943, Stalin met with Churchill and Roosevelt in [[Tehran Conference|Tehran]].&lt;ref name=&quot;stalinswars180&quot;&gt;{{Harvnb|Roberts|2006|p=180}}&lt;/ref&gt; The parties later agreed that Britain and America would launch a cross-channel invasion of France in May 1944, along with a separate invasion of southern France.&lt;ref name=&quot;stalinswars185&quot;&gt;{{Harvnb|Roberts|2006|p=185}}&lt;/ref&gt; Stalin insisted that, after the war, the Soviet Union should incorporate the portions of Poland it occupied pursuant to the [[Molotov-Ribbentrop Pact]] with Germany, which Churchill opposed.&lt;ref name=&quot;stalinswars186&quot;&gt;{{Harvnb|Roberts|2006|pp=186–7}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In 1944, the Soviet Union made significant advances across Eastern Europe toward Germany,&lt;ref name=&quot;stalinswars194&quot;&gt;{{Harvnb|Roberts|2006|pp=194–5}}&lt;/ref&gt; including [[Operation Bagration]], a massive offensive in [[Belorussia]] against the German Army Group Centre.&lt;ref name=&quot;stalinswars199&quot;&gt;{{Harvnb|Roberts|2006|pp=199–201}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Final victory===
By April 1945, Nazi Germany faced its last days with 1.9&amp;nbsp;million German soldiers in the East fighting 6.4&amp;nbsp;million Red Army soldiers while 1 million German soldiers in the West battled 4&amp;nbsp;million Western Allied soldiers.&lt;ref name=&quot;glantz.sgw&quot;&gt;Glantz, David, ''The Soviet-German War 1941–45: Myths and Realities: A Survey Essay'', 11 October 2001 [http://www.strom.clemson.edu/publications/sg-war41-45.pdf Clemson.edu]&lt;/ref&gt; While initial talk existed of a [[race to Berlin]] by the Allies, after Stalin successfully lobbied for Eastern Germany to fall within the Soviet &quot;sphere of influence&quot; at [[Yalta Conference|Yalta]], no plans were made by the [[Western Allies]] to seize the city by a ground operation.&lt;ref name=&quot;Beevor194&quot;&gt;Beevor, Antony, ''Berlin: The Downfall 1945'', Viking, Penguin Books, 2005, ISBN 0670886955, p. 194&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Williams, Andrew (2005). D-Day to Berlin. Hodder. ISBN 0340833971., pp. 310–1&lt;/ref&gt;

On 30 April, Hitler and [[Eva Braun]] committed suicide, after which Soviet forces found their remains, which had been burned at Hitler's directive.&lt;ref&gt;Bullock, Alan, ''Hitler: A Study in Tyranny'', Penguin Books, ISBN 0140135642, 1962, pp. 799–800&lt;/ref&gt; German forces surrendered a few days later. Despite the Soviets' possession of Hitler's remains, Stalin did not believe that his old nemesis was actually dead, a belief that remained for years after the war.&lt;ref name=&quot;kershaw&quot;&gt;Kershaw, Ian, ''Hitler, 1936–1945: Nemesis'', W. W. Norton &amp; Company, 2001, ISBN 0393322521, pp. 1038–39&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Dolezal, Robert, ''Truth about History: How New Evidence Is Transforming the Story of the Past'', Readers Digest, 2004, ISBN 0762105232, pp. 185–6&lt;/ref&gt;

Fending off the German invasion and pressing to victory in the East required a tremendous sacrifice by the Soviet Union.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;''[http://books.google.com/books?id=CDMVMqDvp4QC&amp;pg=PA242 Rulers and victims: the Russians in the Soviet Union]''&quot;. Geoffrey A. Hosking (2006). [[Harvard University Press]]. p.242. ISBN 0-674-02178-9&lt;/ref&gt; Soviet military casualties totaled approximately 35 million (official figures 28.2&amp;nbsp;million) with approximately 14.7&amp;nbsp;million killed, missing or captured (official figures 11.285&amp;nbsp;million).&lt;ref name=&quot;glantz13&quot;&gt;Glantz, David, ''The Soviet-German War 1941–45: Myths and Realities: A Survey Essay'', 11 October 2001, p. 13&lt;/ref&gt; Although figures vary, the Soviet civilian death toll probably reached 20&amp;nbsp;million.&lt;ref name=&quot;glantz13&quot; /&gt; One in four Soviets were killed or wounded.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;''[http://books.google.com/books?id=c9bMfZBI8-sC&amp;pg=PA204 The World's Wasted Wealth 2: Save Our Wealth, Save Our Environment]''&quot;. J. W. Smith (1994). p.204. ISBN 0-9624423-2-1&lt;/ref&gt; Some 1,710 towns and 70,000 villages were destroyed.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;''[http://books.google.com/books?id=JyN0hlKcfTcC&amp;pg=PA409 A Companion to Russian History]''&quot;. Abbott Gleason (2009). Wiley-Blackwell. p.409. ISBN 1-4051-3560-3&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Stephen J. Lee (2000). &quot;''[http://books.google.com/books?id=KnvJO9yfvEAC&amp;pg=PA86&amp;dq&amp;hl=en#v=onepage&amp;q=&amp;f=false European dictatorships, 1918–1945]''&quot;. Routledge. p.86. ISBN 0415230462&lt;/ref&gt; Thereafter, Stalin was at times referred to as one of the most influential men in human history.&lt;ref&gt;Hart, Michael H., [http://www.adherents.com/adh_influ.html ''The 100: A Ranking of the Most Influential Persons in History, Revised and Updated for the Nineties'' New York: Citadel Press Book, 1992]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://euroheritage.net/stalinshomegallery.shtml |title=Euroheritage.net |publisher=Euroheritage.net |accessdate=25 June 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Nobel Peace Prize nominations===
In 1945, he was mentioned by [[Halvdan Koht]] among seven candidates that were qualified for the [[Nobel Peace Prize]]. However, he did not explicitly nominate any of them. The person actually nominated was [[Cordell Hull]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url = http://nobelprize.org/nobel_prizes/peace/nomination/nomination.php?action=show&amp;showid=3323|accessdate =14 May 2010|title = Record from The Nomination Database for the Nobel Prize in Peace, 1901–1956|publisher=[[Nobel Foundation]]}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In 1948, he was officially nominated for the Nobel Peace Prize by [[Wladislav Rieger]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url = http://nobelprize.org/nobel_prizes/peace/nomination/nomination.php?action=show&amp;showid=2754|accessdate =14 May 2010|title = Record from The Nomination Database for the Nobel Prize in Peace, 1901–1956|publisher=[[Nobel Foundation]]}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Questionable tactics===
[[File:Katyn - decision of massacre p1.jpg|thumb|Part of 5 March 1940 memo from [[Lavrentiy Beria]] to Stalin proposing execution of Polish officers]]
After taking around 300,000 Polish prisoners in 1939 and early 1940,&lt;ref name=&quot;PWN&quot;&gt;{{pl icon}} [http://encyklopedia.pwn.pl/haslo.php?id=3949396 obozy jenieckie zolnierzy polskich] (Prison camps for Polish soldiers) [[Internetowa encyklopedia PWN|Encyklopedia PWN]]. Retrieved 28 November 2006&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Wojsko&quot;&gt;{{pl icon}} Edukacja Humanistyczna w wojsku. 1/2005. Dom wydawniczy Wojska Polskiego. ISNN 1734-6584. (Official publication of the Polish Army)&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Wojsko&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Молотов&quot;&gt;{{Ru icon}} Молотов на V сессии Верховного Совета 31 октября цифра «примерно 250 тыс.» (Please provide translation of the reference title and publication data and means)&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Отчёт&quot;&gt;{{Ru icon}} Отчёт Украинского и Белорусского фронтов Красной Армии, Мельтюхов, p. 367. (Report of the Ukrainian and Belorussian fronts of the Red Army, Melyukhov)&lt;/ref&gt; 25,700 Polish POWs were executed on 5 March 1940, pursuant to a note to Stalin from [[Lavrenty Beria]],&lt;ref name=&quot;Fischer&quot;&gt;[[Benjamin B. Fischer]], &quot;[https://www.cia.gov/library/center-for-the-study-of-intelligence/csi-publications/csi-studies/studies/winter99-00/art6.html The Katyn Controversy: Stalin's Killing Field]&quot;, ''[[Studies in Intelligence]]'', Winter 1999–2000&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;kmw_resolution&quot;&gt;Excerpt from the minutes No. 13 of the Politburo of the Central Committee meeting, shooting order of 5 March 1940 [http://web.archive.org/web/20050921034703/http://www.electronicmuseum.ca/Poland-WW2/katyn_memorial_wall/kmw_resolution.html Electronicmuseum.ca], last accessed on 19 December 2005, original in Russian with English translation&lt;/ref&gt; in what became known as the [[Katyn massacre]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Sanford&quot;&gt;[[George Sanford (scholar)|George Sanford]], [http://books.google.com/books?vid=ISBN0415338735&amp;id=PZXvUuvfv-oC&amp;pg=PA20 Katyn and the Soviet massacre of 1940: truth, justice and memory], Routledge, 2005, ISBN 0415338735 pp. 20–24&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Fischer&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.cia.gov/library/center-for-the-study-of-intelligence/kent-csi/vol43no3/pdf/v43i3a06p.pdf|title=Stalin's Killing Field|accessdate=19 July 2008|format=PDF}}&lt;/ref&gt; While Stalin personally told a Polish general they'd &quot;lost track&quot; of the officers in [[Manchuria]],&lt;ref name=&quot;Biuletyn&quot;&gt;{{pl icon}} Various authors. [http://www.udskior.gov.pl/kombatant/200306_spec.pdf Biuletyn „Kombatant” nr specjalny (148) czerwiec 2003] Special Edition of Kombatant Bulletin No.148 6/2003 on the occasion of the Year of General Sikorski. Official publication of the Polish government Agency of Combatants and Repressed&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=VIZH&gt;Ромуальд Святек, &quot;Катынский лес&quot;, Военно-исторический журнал, 1991, №9, {{ISSN|0042-9058}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Harvnb|Brackman|2001&quot;&gt;{{Harvnb|Brackman|2001}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Harvnb|Brackman|2001&quot;/&gt; Polish railroad workers found the mass grave after the 1941 Nazi invasion.&lt;ref name=&quot;BIPN1&quot;&gt;{{pl icon}} {{Cite journal|author=Barbara Polak|year =2005|title =Zbrodnia katynska|journal=Biuletyn [[Institute of National Remembrance|IPN]]pages =4–21|url =http://www.ceeol.com/aspx/getdocument.aspx?logid=5&amp;id=f4349d43-b13d-4c2c-a70d-056e8801493d|format =PDF|accessdate =22 September 2007|ref =harv}}&lt;/ref&gt; The massacre became a source of political controversy,&lt;ref name=&quot;Engel&quot;&gt;[[David Engel|Engel, David]]. &quot;[http://books.google.com/books?ie=UTF-8&amp;hl=en&amp;vid=ISBN0807820695&amp;id=a12WB1iknWwC&amp;pg=PA71 Facing a Holocaust: The Polish Government-In-Exile and the Jews, 1943–1945]&quot;. 1993. ISBN 0-8078-2069-5. p. 71&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Bauer&quot;&gt;Bauer, Eddy. &quot;The Marshall Cavendish Illustrated Encyclopedia of World War II&quot;. Marshall Cavendish, 1985&lt;/ref&gt; with the Soviets eventually claiming that Germany committed the executions when the Soviet Union retook Poland in 1944.&lt;ref name=&quot;Fischer&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Goebbels&quot;&gt;[[Joseph Goebbels|Goebbels, Joseph]]. The Goebbels Diaries (1942–1943). Translated by Louis P. Lochner. Doubleday &amp; Company. 1948&lt;/ref&gt; The Soviets did not admit responsibility until 1990.&lt;ref name=&quot;fa1990&quot;&gt;&quot;Chronology 1990; The Soviet Union and Eastern Europe.&quot; ''[[Foreign Affairs]]'', 1990, p. 212&lt;/ref&gt;

Stalin introduced controversial military orders, such as [[Order No. 270]], requiring superiors to shoot deserters on the spot&lt;ref&gt;[http://stalinism.ru/Stalin-i-Armiya/O-prikaze-270.html Text of Order No. 270]&lt;/ref&gt; while their family members were subject to arrest.&lt;ref name=&quot;stalinswars98&quot;&gt;{{Harvnb|Roberts|2006|p=98}}&lt;/ref&gt; Thereafter, Stalin also conducted a purge of several military commanders that were shot for &quot;cowardice&quot; without a trial.&lt;ref name=&quot;stalinswars98&quot; /&gt; Stalin issued [[Order No. 227]], directing that commanders permitting retreat without permission to be subject to a military tribunal,&lt;ref name=&quot;stalinswars132&quot;&gt;{{Harvnb|Roberts|2006|p=132}}&lt;/ref&gt; and soldiers guilty of disciplinary procedures to be forced into &quot;penal battalions&quot;, which were sent to the most dangerous sections of the front lines.&lt;ref name=&quot;stalinswars132&quot; /&gt; From 1942 to 1945, 427,910 soldiers were assigned to penal battalions.&lt;ref name=&quot;Krivosheev&quot;&gt;G. I. Krivosheev. Soviet Casualties and Combat Losses. Greenhill 1997 ISBN 1-85367-280-7&lt;/ref&gt; The order also directed &quot;blocking detachments&quot; to shoot fleeing panicked troops at the rear.&lt;ref name=&quot;stalinswars132&quot; /&gt;

In June 1941, weeks after the German invasion began, Stalin also directed employing a [[scorched earth]] policy of destroying the infrastructure and food supplies of areas before the Germans could seize them, and that partisans were to be set up in evacuated areas.&lt;ref name=&quot;stalinswars90&quot; /&gt; He also ordered the [[NKVD prisoner massacres|NKVD to murder]] around one hundred thousand political prisoners in areas where the Wermacht approached,&lt;ref&gt;Robert Gellately. ''Lenin, Stalin, and Hitler: The Age of Social Catastrophe.'' [[Knopf]], 2007 ISBN 1400040051 p. 391&lt;/ref&gt; while others were deported east.&lt;ref name=&quot;Harvnb|Applebaum|2003&quot;/&gt;{{Page needed|date=February 2011}}&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|author=[[Richard Rhodes]] |year=2002 |title=Masters of Death: The SS-Einsatzgruppen and the Invention of the Holocaust |publisher=Alfred A. Knopf |location=New York |isbn=0-375-40900-9 |pages=46–47}} See also: Allen Paul. ''Katyn: Stalin's Massacre and the Seeds of Polish Resurrection'', Naval Institute Press, 1996, (ISBN 1-55750-670-1), p. 155&lt;/ref&gt;

After the capture of Berlin, Soviet troops reportedly raped from tens of thousands to two million women,&lt;ref&gt;Schissler, Hanna ''The Miracle Years: A Cultural History of West Germany, 1949–1968''&lt;/ref&gt;{{Page needed|date=February 2011}} and 50,000 during and after the [[Battle of Budapest|occupation]] of [[Budapest]].&lt;ref&gt;Mark, James, ''&quot;Remembering Rape: Divided Social Memory and the Red Army in Hungary 1944–1945&quot;'', Past &amp; Present – Number 188, August 2005, p. 133&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;naimark71&quot;&gt;Naimark, Norman M., ''The Russians in Germany: A History of the Soviet Zone of Occupation, 1945–1949.'' Cambridge: Belknap, 1995, ISBN 0-674-78405-7, pp. 70–71&lt;/ref&gt; In former Axis countries, such as Germany, Romania and Hungary, Red Army officers generally viewed cities, villages and farms as being open to pillaging and looting.&lt;ref&gt;Beevor, Antony, ''Berlin: The Downfall 1945'', Penguin Books, 2002, ISBN 0-670-88695-5. Specific reports also include [http://historicaltextarchive.com/books.php?op=viewbook&amp;bookid=7&amp;post=3 Report of the Swiss legation in Budapest of 1945] and [[Hubertus Knabe]]: Tag der Befreiung? Das Kriegsende in Ostdeutschland (A day of liberation? The end of war in Eastern Germany), Propyläen 2005, ISBN 3549072457 German)&lt;/ref&gt;

In the [[Soviet Occupation Zone]] of [[Allied Occupation Zones in Germany|post-war Germany]], the Soviets set up [[NKVD special camps|ten NKVD-run &quot;special camps&quot;]] subordinate to the gulag.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|url=http://www.stiftung-bg.de/gums/en/geschichte/speziallager/spezial01.htm|title=The Soviet special camp No.7 / No. 1 1945–1950|accessdate=22 April 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt; These &quot;special camps&quot; were former [[Stalag]]s, prisons, or [[Nazi concentration camps]] such as [[Sachsenhausen concentration camp|Sachsenhausen (special camp number 7)]] and [[Buchenwald|Buchenwald (special camp number 2)]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A0CEFDA163EF934A25751C1A9679C8B63&amp;sec=&amp;spon=&amp;pagewanted=1 Ex-Death Camp Tells Story Of Nazi and Soviet Horrors] New York Times, 17 December 2001&lt;/ref&gt; According to German government estimates, &quot;65,000 people died in those Soviet-run camps or in transportation to them.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;[http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0CE6D61131F937A1575AC0A964958260&amp;sec=&amp;spon=&amp;scp=13&amp;sq=Sachsenhausen&amp;st=cse Germans Find Mass Graves at an Ex-Soviet Camp] New York Times, 24 September 1992&lt;/ref&gt;

According to recent figures, of an estimated four million POWs taken by the Soviets, including Germans, Japanese, Hungarians, Romanians and others, some 580,000 never returned, presumably victims of privation or the Gulags.&lt;ref&gt;Richard Overy, The Dictators Hitler's Germany, Stalin's Russia p.568–569&lt;/ref&gt; Soviet POWs and forced laborers who survived German captivity were sent to special &quot;transit&quot; or &quot;filtration&quot; camps to determine which were potential traitors.&lt;ref name=&quot;stalinswars202&quot; /&gt;

Of the approximately 4 million to be repatriated 2,660,013 were civilians and 1,539,475 were former POWs.&lt;ref name=&quot;stalinswars202&quot;&gt;{{Harvnb|Roberts|2006|p=202}}&lt;/ref&gt; Of the total, 2,427,906 were sent home and 801,152 were reconscripted into the armed forces.&lt;ref name=&quot;stalinswars202&quot; /&gt; 608,095 were enrolled in the work battalions of the defense ministry.&lt;ref name=&quot;stalinswars202&quot; /&gt; 272,867 were transferred to the authority of the NKVD for punishment, which meant a transfer to the Gulag system.&lt;ref name=&quot;stalinswars202&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref&gt;(&quot;Военно-исторический журнал&quot; (&quot;Military-Historical Magazine&quot;), 1997, №5. p. 32)&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Земское В.Н. К вопросу о репатриации советских граждан. 1944–1951 годы // История СССР. 1990. № 4 (Zemskov V.N. On repatriation of Soviet citizens. Istoriya SSSR., 1990, No.4&lt;/ref&gt; 89,468 remained in the transit camps as reception personnel until the repatriation process was finally wound up in the early 1950s.&lt;ref name=&quot;stalinswars202&quot; /&gt;

===Allied conferences on post-war Europe===
[[File:Yalta summit 1945 with Churchill, Roosevelt, Stalin.jpg|right|thumb|The Big Three: [[Prime Minister of the United Kingdom|British Prime Minister]] [[Winston Churchill]], U.S. President [[Franklin D. Roosevelt]] and Stalin at the [[Yalta Conference]], February 1945.]]
Stalin met in several [[List of World War II conferences|conferences]] with British Prime Minister [[Winston Churchill]] (and later [[Clement Attlee]]) and/or U.S. President [[Franklin D. Roosevelt]] (and later [[Harry Truman]]) to plan [[military strategy]] and, later, to discuss Europe's postwar reorganization. Very early conferences, such as that with British diplomats in [[Moscow Conference (1941)|Moscow in 1941]] and with Churchill and American diplomats in [[Moscow Conference (1942)|Moscow in 1942]], focused mostly upon war planning and supply, though some preliminary postwar reorganization discussion also occurred. In 1943, Stalin met with Churchill and Roosevelt in the [[Tehran Conference]]. In 1944, Stalin met with Churchill in the [[Moscow Conference (1944)|Moscow Conference]]. Beginning in late 1944, the [[Red Army]] occupied much of Eastern Europe during these conferences and the discussions shifted to a more intense focus on the reorganization of postwar Europe.

In February 1945, at the [[Yalta Conference|conference at Yalta]], Stalin demanded a Soviet sphere of political influence in Eastern Europe.&lt;ref name=&quot;stalinswars241&quot; /&gt; Stalin eventually was convinced by Churchill and Roosevelt not to dismember Germany.&lt;ref name=&quot;stalinswars241&quot; /&gt; Stalin also stated that the [[Polish government-in-exile]] demands for self-rule were not negotiable, such that the Soviet Union would keep the territory of eastern Poland they had already [[Soviet invasion of Poland|taken by invasion with German consent in 1939]], and wanted the pro-Soviet Polish government installed.&lt;ref name=&quot;stalinswars241&quot;&gt;{{Harvnb|Roberts|2006|pp=241–244}}&lt;/ref&gt; After resistance by Churchill and Roosevelt, Stalin promised a re-organization of the current [[Polish Committee of National Liberation|Communist puppet government]] on a broader democratic basis in Poland.&lt;ref name=&quot;stalinswars241&quot; /&gt; He stated the new government's primary task would be to prepare elections.&lt;ref name=&quot;wettig47&quot;&gt;{{Harvnb|Wettig|2008|pp=47–8}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The parties at Yalta further agreed that the countries of liberated Europe and former Axis satellites would be allowed to &quot;create democratic institutions of their own choice&quot;, pursuant to &quot;the right of all peoples to choose the form of government under which they will live.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;yaltareport&quot;&gt;11 February 1945 Potsdam Report, ''reprinted in'' Potsdam Ashley, John, Soames Grenville and Bernard Wasserstein, ''The Major International Treaties of the Twentieth Century: A History and Guide with Texts'', Taylor &amp; Francis, 2001 ISBN 041523798X&lt;/ref&gt; The parties also agreed to help those countries form interim governments &quot;pledged to the earliest possible establishment through free elections&quot; and &quot;facilitate where necessary the holding of such elections.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;yaltareport&quot; /&gt; After the re-organization of the [[Provisional Government of the Republic of Poland]], the parties agreed that the new party shall &quot;be pledged to the holding of free and unfettered elections as soon as possible on the basis of universal suffrage and secret ballot.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;yaltareport&quot; /&gt; One month after Yalta, the Soviet NKVD arrested 16 Polish leaders wishing to participate in provisional government negotiations, for alleged &quot;crimes&quot; and &quot;diversions&quot;, which drew protest from the West.&lt;ref name=&quot;wettig47&quot; /&gt; The [[Polish legislative election, 1947|fraudulent Polish elections]], held in January 1947 resulted in Poland's official transformation to undemocratic [[People's Republic of Poland|communist]] state by 1949.

[[File:Potsdam conference 1945-6.jpg|left|thumb|[[Prime Minister of the United Kingdom|British Prime Minister]] [[Winston Churchill]], U.S. President [[Harry S. Truman]] and Premiere Joseph Stalin at the [[Potsdam Conference]], July 1945.]]At the [[Potsdam Conference]] from July to August 1945, though Germany had surrendered months earlier, instead of withdrawing Soviet forces from Eastern European countries, Stalin had not moved those forces. At the beginning of the conference, Stalin repeated previous promises to Churchill that he would refrain from a &quot;Sovietization&quot; of Eastern Europe.&lt;ref name=&quot;stalinswars274&quot;&gt;{{Harvnb|Roberts|2006|pp=274–5}}&lt;/ref&gt; Stalin pushed for reparations from Germany without regard to the base minimum supply for German citizens' survival, which worried Truman and Churchill who thought that Germany would become a financial burden for Western powers.&lt;ref name=&quot;wettig90&quot; /&gt;

In addition to reparations, Stalin pushed for &quot;[[war booty]]&quot;, which would permit the Soviet Union to directly seize property from conquered nations without quantitative or qualitative limitation, and a clause was added permitting this to occur with some limitations.&lt;ref name=&quot;wettig90&quot;&gt;{{Harvnb|Wettig|2008|pp=90–1}}&lt;/ref&gt; By July 1945, Stalin's troops effectively controlled the Baltic States, Poland, Czechoslovakia, Hungary, Bulgaria and Romania, and refugees were fleeing out of these countries fearing a Communist take-over. The western allies, and especially Churchill, were suspicious of the motives of Stalin, who had already installed communist governments in the [[central European]] countries under his influence.

In these conferences, his first appearances on the world stage, Stalin proved to be a formidable negotiator. [[Anthony Eden]], the British Foreign Secretary noted: &quot;Marshal Stalin as a negotiator was the toughest proposition of all. Indeed, after something like thirty years' experience of international conferences of one kind and another, if I had to pick a team for going into a conference room, Stalin would be my first choice. Of course the man was ruthless and of course he knew his purpose. He never wasted a word. He never stormed, he was seldom even irritated.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|author=Anthony Eden|authorlink=Anthony Eden|year=1965|title=Memoirs: The Reckoning}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Post-war era, 1945–1953==
===The Iron Curtain and the Eastern Bloc===
After Soviet forces remained in Eastern and Central European countries, with the beginnings of communist puppet regimes in those countries, Churchill referred to the region as being behind an &quot;[[Iron Curtain]]&quot; of control from Moscow.&lt;ref&gt;Muller, James W., ''Churchill's &quot;Iron Curtain&quot; Speech Fifty Years Later'', University of Missouri Press, 1999, ISBN 0826212476, pp. 1–8&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[[John Lewis Gaddis|Gaddis, John Lewis]], ''We Now Know: Rethinking Cold War History'', Oxford University Press, Incorporated, 1998, ISBN 0198780710&lt;/ref&gt; The countries under Soviet control in Eastern and Central Europe were sometimes called the &quot;[[Eastern bloc]]&quot; or &quot;Soviet Bloc&quot;.
[[File:EasternBloc BasicMembersOnly.svg|right|thumb|The [[Eastern Bloc]] until 1989]]
In Soviet-controlled [[East Germany]], the major task of the ruling communist party in Germany was to channel Soviet orders down to both the administrative apparatus and the other bloc parties pretending that these were initiatives of its own,&lt;ref name=&quot;wettig95&quot;&gt;{{Harvnb|Wettig|2008|pp=95–100}}&lt;/ref&gt; with deviations potentially leading to reprimands, imprisonment, torture and even death.&lt;ref name=&quot;wettig95&quot; /&gt; Property and industry were nationalized.&lt;ref name=&quot;wettig95&quot; /&gt;

The [[German Democratic Republic]] was declared on 7 October 1949, with a new constitution which enshrined socialism and gave the Soviet-controlled [[Socialist Unity Party of Germany|Socialist Unity Party (&quot;SED&quot;)]] control. In Berlin, after citizens strongly rejected communist candidates in an election, in June 1948, the Soviet Union [[Berlin Blockade|blockaded West Berlin]], the portion of Berlin not under Soviet control, cutting off all supply of food and other items. The blockade failed due to the unexpected massive aerial resupply campaign carried out by the Western powers known as the [[Berlin Airlift]]. In 1949, Stalin conceded defeat and ended the blockade.

While Stalin had promised at the [[Yalta Conference]] that free elections would be held in Poland,&lt;ref name=&quot;yaltareport&quot; /&gt; after an election failure in &quot;[[Polish people's referendum, 1946|3 times YES]]&quot; elections,&lt;ref&gt;Curp, David, ''A Clean Sweep?: The Politics of Ethnic Cleansing in Western Poland, 1945–1960'', Boydell &amp; Brewer, 2006, ISBN 1580462383, pp. 66–69&lt;/ref&gt; [[electoral fraud|vote rigging]] was employed to win a majority in the carefully controlled poll.&lt;ref name=&quot;Britannica&quot;&gt;[http://www.britannica.com/eb/article-28216 &quot;Poland.&quot;] Encyclopædia Britannica. 2007. Encyclopædia Britannica Online. Retrieved on 7 April 2007&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Buchanan&quot;&gt;Tom Buchanan, [http://books.google.com/books?vid=ISBN0631221638&amp;id=zeqdrL3Wzy8C&amp;pg=RA1-PA84 ''Europe's Troubled Peace, 1945–2000: 1945–2000''], Blackwell Publishing, 2005, ISBN 0631221638, p.84&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;poloniatodayhistory&quot;&gt;[http://www.poloniatoday.com/history13.htm A brief history of Poland: Chapter 13: The Post-War Years, 1945–1990]. Polonia Today Online. Retrieved on 28 March 2007&lt;/ref&gt; Following the forged referendum, the Polish economy started to become [[nationalization|nationalized]].&lt;ref name=&quot;historybuffalo&quot;&gt;[http://info-poland.buffalo.edu/classroom/longhist6.html Poland – The Historical Setting: Chapter 6: The Polish People's Republic.] Polish Academic Information Center, University at Buffalo. Retrieved on 14 March 2007&lt;/ref&gt;

In Hungary, when the Soviets installed a communist government, [[Mátyás Rákosi]], who described himself as &quot;Stalin's best Hungarian disciple&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;sugar375&quot;&gt;Sugar, Peter F., Peter Hanak and Tibor Frank, ''A History of Hungary'', Indiana University Press, 1994, ISBN 025320867X, pp. 375–77&lt;/ref&gt; and &quot;Stalin's best pupil&quot;,&lt;ref name=&quot;matthews93&quot;&gt;Matthews, John P. C., ''Explosion: The Hungarian Revolution of 1956'', Hippocrene Books, 2007, ISBN 0781811740, pp. 93–4&lt;/ref&gt; took power. Rákosi employed &quot;[[salami tactics]]&quot;, slicing up these enemies like pieces of salami,&lt;ref&gt;Baer, Helmut David, ''The Struggle of Hungarian Lutherans Under Communism'', Texas A&amp;M University Press, 2006 ISBN 1585444804, p. 16&lt;/ref&gt; to battle the initial postwar political majority ready to establish a democracy.&lt;ref name=&quot;granville&quot;&gt;Granville, Johanna, ''The First Domino: International Decision Making during the Hungarian Crisis of 1956'', Texas A&amp;M University Press, 2004. ISBN 1-58544-298-4&lt;/ref&gt; Rákosi, employed Stalinist political and economic programs, and was dubbed the &quot;bald murderer&quot; for establishing one of the harshest dictatorships in Europe.&lt;ref name=&quot;granville&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Gati, Charles, ''Failed Illusions: Moscow, Washington, Budapest, and the 1956 Hungarian Revolt'', Stanford University Press, 2006 ISBN 0804756066, pp. 9–12&lt;/ref&gt; Approximately 350,000 Hungarian officials and intellectuals were purged from 1948 to 1956.&lt;ref name=&quot;granville&quot; /&gt;

During World War II, in Bulgaria, the Red Army crossed the border and created the conditions for a communist [[Bulgarian coup d'état of 1944|coup d'état]] on the following night.&lt;ref name=&quot;wettig50&quot;&gt;{{Harvnb|Wettig|2008|p=50}}&lt;/ref&gt; The Soviet military commander in Sofia assumed supreme authority, and the communists whom he instructed, including [[Kimon Georgiev]], took full control of domestic politics.&lt;ref name=&quot;wettig50&quot; /&gt;

In 1949, the [[Soviet Union]], [[People's Republic of Bulgaria|Bulgaria]], [[Czechoslovakia]], [[People's Republic of Hungary|Hungary]], [[People's Republic of Poland|Poland]], and [[Communist Romania|Romania]] founded the [[Comecon]] in accordance with Stalin's desire to enforce Soviet domination of the lesser states of Central Europe and to mollify some states that had expressed interest in the [[Marshall Plan]],&lt;ref name=&quot;loc-cs&quot;&gt;Germany (East), Library of Congress Country Study, [http://memory.loc.gov/frd/cs/germany_east/gx_appnb.html ''Appendix B: The Council for Mutual Economic Assistance'']&lt;/ref&gt; and which were now, increasingly, cut off from their traditional markets and suppliers in Western Europe.&lt;ref name=&quot;bideleaux&quot;&gt;{{Harvnb|Bideleux|Jeffries|1998}}&lt;/ref&gt; Czechoslovakia, Hungary, and Poland had remained interested in Marshall aid despite the requirements for a [[convertible currency]] and [[market economy|market economies]]. In July 1947, Stalin ordered these communist-dominated governments to pull out of the Paris Conference on the European Recovery Programme. This has been described as &quot;the moment of truth&quot; in the post–World War II division of Europe.&lt;ref name=&quot;bideleaux&quot; /&gt;

In Greece, Britain and the United States supported the anti-communists in the [[Greek Civil War]] and suspected the Soviets of supporting the Greek communists, although Stalin refrained from getting involved in Greece, dismissing the movement as premature. Albania remained an ally of the Soviet Union, but [[Yugoslavia]] [[Tito-Stalin split|broke with the USSR]] in 1948.

In Stalin's last year of life, one of his last major foreign policy initiatives was the 1952 [[Stalin Note]] for [[German reunification]] and [[Superpower disengagement]] from Central Europe, but Britain, France, and the United States viewed this with suspicion and rejected the offer.

===Sino-Soviet Relations===
[[File:Chinese stamp in 1950.jpg|thumb|Stalin and [[Mao Zedong]] on Chinese Postage stamp]]
In Asia, the Red Army had overrun [[Manchuria]] in the last month of the war and then also occupied Korea above the [[38th parallel north]]. [[Mao Zedong]]'s [[Communist Party of China]], though receptive to minimal Soviet support, defeated the pro-Western and heavily American-assisted [[Chinese Nationalist Party]] in the [[Chinese Civil War]].

There was friction between Stalin and Mao from the beginning. During World War II Stalin had supported the dictator of China, [[Chiang Kai-Shek]], as a bulwark against Japan and had turned a blind eye to Chiang's mass killings of communists. He generally put his alliance with Chiang against Japan ahead of helping his ideological allies in China in his priorities. Even after the war Stalin concluded a non-aggression pact between the USSR and Chiang's Kuomintang (KMT) regime in China and instructed Mao and the Chinese communists to cooperate with Chiang and the KMT after the war. Mao did not follow Stalin's instructions though and started a communist revolution against Chiang. Stalin did not believe Mao would be successful so he was less than enthusiastic in helping Mao. The USSR continued to maintain diplomatic relations with Chiang's KMT regime until 1949 when it became clear Mao would win.

Stalin supported the Turkic Muslims known today as [[Uyghur people|Uyghur]] in seeking their own state, [[Second East Turkestan Republic]] during the [[Ili Rebellion]] against the [[Republic of China]]. He backed the Uyghur Communist Muslim leader [[Ehmetjan Qasim]] against the anti Communist Chinese Kuomintang forces.

Stalin did conclude a new friendship and alliance treaty with Mao after he defeated Chiang. But there was still a lot of tension between the two leaders and resentment by Mao for Stalin's less than enthusiastic help during the civil war in China.

The Communists controlled mainland China while the Nationalists held a [[rump state]] on the island of Taiwan. The Soviet Union soon after recognized Mao's People's Republic of China, which it regarded as a new ally. The People's Republic claimed Taiwan, though it had never held authority there.
[[File:Mao, Bulganin, Stalin, Ulbricht Tsedenbal.jpeg|thumb|240 px|[[Mao Zedong|Mao]] at Stalin's 70th birthday celebration in Moscow, December 1949 ]]
Diplomatic relations between the Soviet Union and China reached a high point with the signing of the 1950 [[Sino-Soviet Treaty of Friendship and Alliance]]. Both countries provided military support to a new friendly state in North Korea. After various Korean border conflicts, war broke out with U.S.-allied South Korea in 1950, starting the [[Korean War]].

However, not surprisingly, the relations with the [[Kuomintang]] deteriorated. In 1951, in Taiwan, the [[Hui people|Chinese Muslim]] Kuomintang General [[Bai Chongxi]] made a speech broadcast on radio to the entire Muslim world calling for a war against Russia, claiming that the &quot;imperialist ogre&quot; leader Stalin was engineering World War III, and Bai also called upon Muslims to avoid the Indian leader [[Nehru]], accusing him of being blind to Soviet imperialism.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |title=Moslems Urged To Resist Russia|newspaper=Christian Science Monitor|date=25 Sep 1951|url=http://pqasb.pqarchiver.com/csmonitor_historic/access/275861742.html?dids=275861742:275861742&amp;FMT=CITE&amp;FMTS=CITE:AI&amp;date=Sep+25%2C+1951&amp;author=&amp;pub=Christian+Science+Monitor&amp;desc=Moslems+Urged+To+Resist+Russia&amp;pqatl=google}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |title=CHINESE ASKS ALL MOSLEMS TO FIGHT REDS|newspaper=Chicago Daily Tribune|date=24 Sep 1951|url=http://pqasb.pqarchiver.com/chicagotribune/access/497978032.html?dids=497978032:497978032&amp;FMT=CITE&amp;FMTS=CITE:AI&amp;type=historic&amp;date=Sep+24%2C+1951&amp;author=&amp;pub=Chicago+Tribune&amp;desc=CHINESE+ASKS+ALL+MOSLEMS+TO+FIGHT+REDS&amp;pqatl=google}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===North Korea===
Contrary to America's policy which restrained armament (limited equipment was provided for infantry and police forces) to South Korea, Stalin extensively armed [[Kim Il Sung]]'s North Korean army and air forces with military equipment (to include T-34/85 tanks) and &quot;advisors&quot; far in excess of those required for defensive purposes) in order to facilitate Kim's (a former Soviet Officer) aim of conquering the rest of the Korean peninsula.

The [[Korean People's Army|North Korean Army]] struck in the pre-dawn hours of Sunday, 25 June 1950, crossing the 38th parallel behind a firestorm of artillery, beginning their invasion of South Korea.&lt;ref name=&quot;Stokesbury1990&quot;&gt;{{Cite book|title= A Short History of the Korean War|last=Stokesbury |first= James L|year= 1990|publisher=Harper Perennial |location= New York|isbn= 0688095135}}&lt;/ref&gt; During the [[Korean War]], Soviet pilots flew Soviet aircraft from Chinese bases against United Nations aircraft defending South Korea. Post–Cold War research in Soviet Archives has revealed that the Korean War was begun by Kim Il-sung with the express permission of Stalin, though this is disputed by North Korea.{{Citation needed|date=June 2010}}

===Israel===
Stalin originally supported the creation of Israel in 1948. The USSR was one of the first nations to recognize the new country.&lt;ref&gt;See, ''e.g.'', Brown, Philip Marshall. &quot;The Recognition of Israel&quot;, ''American Journal of International Law'', Vol.&amp;nbsp;42, No.&amp;nbsp;3 (Jul. 1948), p.&amp;nbsp;620&lt;/ref&gt; [[Golda Meir]] came to Moscow as the first Israeli Ambassador to the USSR that year. However, after providing [[war materiel]] for Israel through Czechoslovakia, Stalin later changed his mind and came out against Israel.

===''Falsifiers of History''===
In 1948, Stalin personally edited and rewrote by hand sections of the cold war book ''[[Falsifiers of History]]''.&lt;ref name=&quot;roberts98&quot;&gt;{{Harvnb|Roberts|2002|p=98}}&lt;/ref&gt; ''Falsifiers'' was published in response to the documents made public in ''Nazi-Soviet Relations, 1939–1941: Documents from the Archives of The German Foreign Office'',&lt;ref name=&quot;henig67&quot;&gt;{{Harvnb|Henig|2005|p=67}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Roberts96&quot;&gt;{{Harvnb|Roberts|2002|p=96}}&lt;/ref&gt; which included the secret protocols of the [[Molotov-Ribbentrop Pact]] and other secret German-Soviet relations documents.&lt;ref name=&quot;henig67&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Harvnb|Department of State|1948|pp=80–358}}&lt;/ref&gt; ''Falsifiers'' originally appeared as a series of articles in ''[[Pravda]]'' in February 1948,&lt;ref name=&quot;Roberts96&quot; /&gt; and was subsequently published in numerous language and distributed worldwide.&lt;ref name=&quot;roberts97&quot;&gt;{{Harvnb|Roberts|2002|p=97}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The book did not attempt to directly counter or deal with the documents published in ''Nazi-Soviet Relations''&lt;ref name=&quot;roberts100&quot;&gt;{{Harvnb|Roberts|2002|p=100}}&lt;/ref&gt; and rather, focused upon Western culpability for the outbreak of war in 1939.&lt;ref name=&quot;roberts97&quot; /&gt; It argues that &quot;Western powers&quot; aided Nazi rearmament and aggression, including that American bankers and industrialists provided capital for the growth of German war industries, while deliberately encouraging Hitler to expand eastward.&lt;ref name=&quot;henig67&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;roberts97&quot; /&gt; It depicted the Soviet Union as striving to negotiate a collective security against Hitler, while being thwarted by double-dealing Anglo-French appeasers who, despite appearances, had no intention of a Soviet alliance and were secretly negotiating with Berlin.&lt;ref name=&quot;roberts97&quot; /&gt; It casts the [[Munich agreement]], not just as Anglo-French short-sightedness or cowardice, but as a &quot;secret&quot; agreement that was a &quot;a highly important phase in their policy aimed at goading the Hitlerite aggressors against the Soviet Union.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{Harvnb|Taubert|2003|p=318}}&lt;/ref&gt; The book also included the claim that, during the Pact's operation, Stalin rejected Hitler's offer to share in a division of the world, without mentioning the Soviet offers to join the Axis.&lt;ref name=&quot;nekrich202&quot;&gt;{{Harvnb|Nekrich|Ulam|Freeze|1997|pp=202–205}}&lt;/ref&gt; Historical studies, official accounts, memoirs and textbooks published in the Soviet Union used that depiction of events until [[dissolution of the Soviet Union|the Soviet Union's dissolution]].&lt;ref name=&quot;nekrich202&quot; /&gt;

===Domestic support===
Domestically, Stalin was seen as a great wartime leader who had led the Soviets to victory against the Nazis.

An increasingly nationalistic emphasis on Russian history and achievements became a salient feature of Soviet culture in the 1940s. At the end of May 1945, Stalin proposed a victory toast to the Soviet people, and to the virtues of the Russian majority in particular: {{cquote|&lt;blockquote&gt;I should like to propose a toast to the health of our Soviet people, and in the first place, the Russian people. (Loud and prolonged applause and shouts of 'Hurrah.')&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;I drink in the first place to the health of the Russian people because it is the most outstanding nation of all the nations forming the Soviet Union.&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;I propose a toast to the health of the Russian people because it has won in this war universal recognition as the leading force of the Soviet Union among all the peoples of our country.&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;I propose a toast to the health of the Russian people not only because it is the leading people, but also because it possesses a clear mind, a staunch character, and patience.&lt;ref&gt;Stalin, J. V. (1945). [http://www.marxists.org/reference/archive/stalin/works/1945/05/24.htm &quot;Toast to the Russian People at a Reception in Honour of Red Army Commanders Given by the Soviet Government in the Kremlin on Thursday, May 24, 1945&quot;.] In ''War Speeches, Orders of the Day and Answers to Foreign Correspondents During the Great Patriotic War''. Hutchinson &amp; Co., Ltd., London, 1946. [[Marxists Internet Archive]]. Retrieved 22 February 2011.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;}}

Various foreign scientific discoveries and inventions (such as the [[Wright Brothers]]' airplane) were attributed to Russians in post-war Soviet propaganda. Examples include the [[boiler]], reclaimed by father and son [[Yefim Alekseyevich Cherepanov|Cherepanov]]s; the [[electric light]], by [[Pavel Yablochkov|Yablochkov]] and [[Alexander Nikolayevich Lodygin|Lodygin]]; the radio, by [[Alexander Popov (physicist)|Popov]]; and the airplane, by [[Alexander Mozhaiski|Mozhaysky]]. Stalin's internal repressive policies continued (including in newly acquired territories), but never reached the extremes of the 1930s.

===&quot;Doctors' plot&quot;===
{{Main|Doctors' plot}}
The &quot;[[Doctors' plot]]&quot; was a plot outlined by Stalin and Soviet officials in 1952 and 1953 whereby several doctors (over half of whom were Jewish) allegedly attempted to kill Soviet officials.&lt;ref name=&quot;roi103&quot;&gt;Ro'i, Yaacov, ''Jews and Jewish Life in Russia and the Soviet Union'', Routledge, 1995, ISBN 0714646199, pp. 103–6&lt;/ref&gt; The prevailing opinion of many scholars outside the Soviet Union is that Stalin intended to use the resulting doctors' trial to launch a massive party purge.&lt;ref&gt;Encyclopedia Britannica, [http://www.britannica.com/EBchecked/topic/167427/Doctors-Plot ''The Doctors' Plot''], 2008&lt;/ref&gt; The plot is also viewed by many historians as an [[antisemitic]] provocation.&lt;ref name=&quot;roi103&quot; /&gt; It followed on the heels of the 1952 show trials of the [[Jewish Anti-Fascist Committee]]&lt;ref name=&quot;brackman384&quot;&gt;{{Harvnb|Brackman|2001|pp=384–5}}&lt;/ref&gt; and the secret execution of thirteen members on Stalin's orders in the [[Night of the Murdered Poets]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Pogrom&quot;&gt;[http://www.joshuarubenstein.com/stalinsecret/intro.html Stalin's Secret Pogrom: The Postwar Inquisition of the Jewish Anti-Fascist Committee] (introduction) by Joshua Rubenstein&lt;/ref&gt;

Thereafter, in a December [[Politburo]] session, Stalin announced that &quot;Every Jewish nationalist is the agent of the American intelligence service. Jewish nationalists think that their nation was saved by the United States (there you can become rich, bourgeois, etc.). They think they're indebted to the Americans. Among doctors, there are many Jewish nationalists.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;From the diary of Vice-Chair of the [[Sovmin]] V.A. Malyshev. See G. Kostyrchenko, ''Gosudarstvennyj antisemitizm v SSSR'', Moscow, 2005, pp. 461, 462&lt;/ref&gt; To mobilize the Soviet people for his campaign, Stalin ordered ''TASS'' and ''Pravda'' to issue stories along with Stalin's alleged uncovering of a &quot;[[Doctors Plot]]&quot; to assassinate top Soviet leaders,&lt;ref name=&quot;brent288&quot;&gt;{{Harvnb|Brent|Naumov|2004|p=288}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;gorlizki158&quot;&gt;Gorlizki, Yoram and Oleg Khlevniuk, ''Cold Peace: Stalin and the Soviet Ruling Circle 1945–1953'', Sourcebooks, Inc., 2005 ISBN 0195304209, p. 158&lt;/ref&gt; including Stalin, in order to set the stage for show trials.&lt;ref name=&quot;zuehlke99&quot;&gt;Zuehlke, Jeffrey, ''Joseph Stalin'', Twenty-First Century Books, 2005, ISBN 0822534215, pp. 99–101&lt;/ref&gt;

The next month, Pravda published stories with text regarding the purported &quot;Jewish [[bourgeois nationalism|bourgeois-nationalist]]&quot; plotters.&lt;ref name='Vicious Spies and Killers under the Mask of Academic Physicians'&gt;{{Cite news|title=Vicious Spies and Killers under the Mask of Academic Physicians|date=13 January 1953|url =http://www.cyberussr.com/rus/vrach-ubijca-e.html|work=Pravda|accessdate =1 March 2007}}&lt;/ref&gt; Nikita Khrushchev wrote that Stalin hinted him to incite anti-Semitism in the Ukraine, telling him that &quot;the good workers at the factory should be given clubs so they can beat the hell out of those Jews.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Pinkus, Benjamin, ''The Soviet Government and the Jews 1948–1967: A Documented Study'', Cambridge University Press, 1984, ISBN 0521247136, pp. 107–8&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;brackman390&quot;&gt;{{Harvnb|Brackman|2001|p=390}}&lt;/ref&gt; Stalin also ordered falsely accused physicians to be tortured &quot;to death&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.novayagazeta.ru/data/2008/gulag09/00.html &quot;Stalin's torture: 'Beat them to death'&quot;], ''Novaya Gazeta'', 2008. (Russian)&lt;/ref&gt; Regarding the origins of the plot, people who knew Stalin, such as Khrushchev, suggest that [[Stalin's antisemitism|Stalin had long harbored negative sentiments toward Jews]],&lt;ref name=&quot;roi103&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Montefiore, Simon Sebag, ''Young Stalin'', Random House, Inc., 2008, ISBN 1400096138, p. 165&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Kun, Miklós, ''Stalin: An Unknown Portrait'', Central European University Press, 2003, ISBN 9639241199, p. 287&lt;/ref&gt; and anti-Semitic trends in the Kremlin's policies were further fueled by the exile of [[Leon Trotsky]].&lt;ref name=&quot;roi103&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[[Helen Rappaport|Rappaport, Helen]], ''Joseph Stalin: A Biographical Companion'', ABC-CLIO, 1999 ISBN 1576070840, page297&lt;/ref&gt; In 1946, Stalin allegedly said privately that &quot;every Jew is a potential spy.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;roi103&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;brent184&quot;&gt;{{Harvnb|Brent|Naumov|2004|p=184}}&lt;/ref&gt; At the end of January 1953, Stalin's personal physician [[Miron Vovsi]] (cousin of [[Solomon Mikhoels]], who was assassinated in 1948 at the orders of Stalin)&lt;ref name=&quot;Pogrom&quot; /&gt; was arrested within the frame of the plot. Vovsi was released by Beria after Stalin's death in 1953, as was his son-in-law, the composer [[Mieczyslaw Weinberg]].

Some historians have argued that Stalin was also planning to send millions of Jews to four large newly built labor camps in Western Russia&lt;ref name=&quot;zuehlke99&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;brent295&quot;&gt;{{Harvnb|Brent|Naumov|2004|p=295}}&lt;/ref&gt; using a &quot;Deportation Commission&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;brackman388&quot;&gt;{{Harvnb|Brackman|2001|p=388}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;brent47&quot;&gt;{{Harvnb|Brent|Naumov|2004|pp=47–48 &amp; 295}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;eisenstadt&quot;&gt;Eisenstadt, Yaakov, ''Stalin's Planned Genocide'', 22 Adar 5762, 6 March 2002&lt;/ref&gt; that would purportedly act to save Soviet Jews from an engraged Soviet population after the Doctors Plot trials.&lt;ref name=&quot;brackman388&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;brent298&quot;&gt;{{Harvnb|Brent|Naumov|2004|pp=298–300}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Solzhenitzin, Alexander, ''The Gulag Archipelago'', 1973&lt;/ref&gt; Others argue that any charge of an alleged mass deportation lacks specific documentary evidence.&lt;ref name=&quot;gorlizki158&quot; /&gt; Regardless of whether a plot to deport Jews was planned, in his &quot;[[On the Personality Cult and its Consequences|Secret Speech]]&quot; in 1956, Soviet Premier [[Nikita Khrushchev]] stated that the Doctors Plot was &quot;fabricated ... set up by Stalin&quot;, that Stalin told the judge to beat confessions from the defendants&lt;ref name=&quot;secretspeech&quot;&gt;Khrushchev, Nikita, [http://www.uwm.edu/Course/448-343/index12.html ''Special Report to the 20th Congress of the Communist Party of the Soviet Union''], Closed session, 24–25 February 1956&lt;/ref&gt; and had told Politburo members &quot;You are blind like young kittens. What will happen without me? The country will perish because you do not know how to recognize enemies.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;secretspeech&quot; /&gt;

==Death and aftermath==
Stalin's health deteriorated towards the end of World War II. He suffered from [[atherosclerosis]] from his heavy smoking. He suffered a mild stroke around the time of the Victory parade, and a severe heart attack in October 1945.&lt;ref&gt;Zhores A. Medvedev, ''The unknown Stalin'' (2006) p. 6&lt;/ref&gt;

On the early morning hours of 1 March 1953, after an all-night dinner and a movie&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|title=Why Stalin loved Tarzan and wanted John Wayne shot |first=Simon |last=Sebag Montefiore |newspaper=[[The Daily Telegraph]] |date=4 June 2004 |url=http://www.telegraph.co.uk/culture/3618310/Why-Stalin-loved-Tarzan-and-wanted-John-Wayne-shot.html |accessdate=24 August 2010 |location=London}}&lt;/ref&gt; Stalin arrived at his [[Kuntsevo]] residence some 15&amp;nbsp;km west of Moscow centre with interior minister [[Lavrentiy Beria]] and future premiers [[Georgy Malenkov]], [[Nikolai Bulganin]] and [[Nikita Khrushchev]] where he retired to his bedroom to sleep. At dawn, Stalin did not emerge from his room, having probably suffered a stroke that paralyzed the right side of his body.

[[File:Stalin Grave.jpg|thumb|left|Stalin's Grave by the [[Kremlin Wall Necropolis]]]]
Although his guards thought that it was odd for him not to rise at his usual time, they were under strict orders not to disturb him and left him alone the entire day. At around 10&amp;nbsp;p.m. he was discovered by Peter Lozgachev, the Deputy Commandant of Kuntsevo, who entered his bedroom to check up on him and recalled a horrifying scene of Stalin lying on the floor of his room wearing [[pyjama]] bottoms and an undershirt with his clothes soaked in stale urine. A frightened Lozgachev asked Stalin what happened to him, but all he could get out of the Generalissimo was unintelligible responses that sounded like &quot;Dzhh.&quot; Lozgachev frantically called a few party officials asking them to send good doctors.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title=Последняя тайна Сталина|url=http://news.bbc.co.uk/hi/russian/press/newsid_2796000/2796261.stm|publisher=BBC  | date=25 February 2003}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[[Simon Sebag-Montefiore|Montefiore Sebag, Simon]]. ''Stalin: The Court of the Red Tsar''. p. 634; New York: Alfred A. Knopf, 2004 (ISBN 1-4000-4230-5); New York: Vintage, 2005&lt;/ref&gt; Lavrentiy Beria was informed and arrived a few hours afterwards, and the doctors only arrived in the early morning of 2 March in which they changed his bedclothes and tended to him. The bedridden Stalin died four days later, on 5 March 1953,&lt;ref name=dob/&gt; at the age of 74, and was embalmed on 9 March. Officially, the cause of death was listed as a [[cerebral hemorrhage]]. His body was preserved in [[Lenin's Mausoleum]] until 31 October 1961, when his body was removed from the Mausoleum and buried next to the Kremlin walls as part of the process of [[de-Stalinization]].

It has been suggested that Stalin was assassinated. The ex-Communist exile [[Abdurakhman Avtorkhanov|Avtorkhanov]] argued this point as early as 1975. The political memoirs of [[Vyacheslav Molotov]], published in 1993, claimed that Beria had boasted to Molotov that he poisoned Stalin: &quot;I took him out.&quot;

Khrushchev wrote in his memoirs that Beria had, immediately after the stroke, gone about &quot;spewing hatred against [Stalin] and mocking him&quot;, and then, when Stalin showed signs of consciousness, dropped to his knees and kissed his hand. When Stalin fell unconscious again, Beria immediately stood and spat.&lt;ref&gt;Simon Sebag Montefiore, ''Stalin'', 2003, p. 571&lt;/ref&gt;

===Later analysis of death===
In 2003, a joint group of Russian and American historians announced their view that Stalin ingested [[warfarin]], a powerful rat poison that inhibits coagulation of the blood and which predisposes the victim to hemorrhagic stroke (cerebral hemorrhage). Since it is flavorless, warfarin is a plausible weapon of murder. The facts surrounding Stalin's death will probably never be known with certainty.&lt;ref&gt;{{Harvnb|Brent|Naumov|2004}}&lt;/ref&gt;

His demise arrived at a convenient time for [[Lavrenty Beria]] and others, who feared being swept away in yet another purge. It is believed that Stalin felt Beria's power was too great and threatened his own.&lt;ref&gt;”Stalin was ‘afraid of Beria’, thought Khrushchev, ‘and would have been glad to get rid of him but didn’t know how to do it.’ Stalin himself confirmed this, sensing that Beria was winning support...”. Simon Sebag Montefiore, ''Stalin'', 2003, p. 548. Cf. Nikita Khrushchev, ''Khrushchev remembers'', 1971, pp. 250, 311&lt;/ref&gt;

===Reaction by successors===
[[File:Grutas Stalin.jpg|thumb|[[Grutas Park]] is home to a monument of Stalin, originally set up in [[Vilnius]].]]
[[File:Goristatue.JPG|thumb|Monument to Stalin stood in Gori, Georgia until 2010 when it was demolished.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.civil.ge/eng/article.php?id=22453 Stalin Statue Removed from Gori]. ''[[Civil Georgia]]''. 25 June 2010&lt;/ref&gt;]]
The harshness with which Soviet affairs were conducted during Stalin's rule was subsequently repudiated by his successors in the Communist Party leadership, most notably by Nikita Khrushchev's repudiation of Stalinism in February 1956. In his &quot;Secret Speech&quot;, ''[[On the Personality Cult and its Consequences]]'', delivered to a closed session of the [[20th Congress of the Communist Party of the Soviet Union]], [[Khrushchev Thaw|Khrushchev denounced Stalin]] for his cult of personality, and his regime for &quot;violation of Leninist norms of legality&quot;.

A 1974 Soviet work describes Stalin's leadership in the following manner:
{{Quote
| text = J. V. Stalin had held, since 1922, the post of General Secretary of the Communist Party Central Committee. He had made important contributions to the implementation of the Party’s policy of socialist construction in the USSR, and he had won great popularity by his relentless fight against the anti-Leninist groups of the Trotskyites and Bukharinites. Since the early 1930s, however, all the successes achieved by the Soviet people in the building of socialism began to be arbitrarily attributed to Stalin. Already in a letter written back in 1922 Lenin warned the Party Central Committee: &quot;Comrade Stalin,&quot; he wrote, &quot;having become General Secretary, has concentrated boundless authority in his hands, and I am not sure whether he will always be able to exercise that authority with sufficient discretion.&quot; During the first few years after Lenin’s death Stalin reckoned with his critical remarks. As time passed, however, he abused his position of General Secretary of the Party Central Committee more and more frequently, violating the principle of [[collective leadership]] and making independent decisions on important Party and state issues. Those personal shortcomings of which Lenin had warned manifested themselves with greater and greater insistence: his rudeness, capriciousness, intolerance of criticism, arbitrariness, excessive suspiciousness, etc. This led to unjustified restrictions of democracy, gross violations of socialist legality and repressions against prominent Party, government and military leaders and other people.
| sign = ''A Short History of the World In Two Volumes'' Vol. II.&lt;ref&gt;A.Z. Manfred (Ed.). ''A Short History of the World In Two Volumes'' Vol. II. Moscow: Progress Publishers. 1974. pp. 108–109.&lt;/ref&gt;
}}

===Views on Stalin in the Russian Federation===
Results of a controversial poll taken in 2006 stated that over 35% of Russians would vote for Stalin if he were still alive.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.foreignaffairs.org/20060101facomment85101/sarah-e-mendelson-theodore-p-gerber/failing-the-stalin-test.html|title=Modern Poll{{ndash}} Votes for Stalin}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|author=Walker, Shaun|date=14 May 2008|url=http://www.independent.co.uk/news/world/europe/the-big-question-why-is-stalin-still-popular-in-russia-despite-the-brutality-of-his-regime-827654.html|title=The Big Question: Why is Stalin still popular in Russia, despite the brutality of his regime?|work=The Independent |location=UK |accessdate=23 August 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt; Fewer than a third of all Russians regarded Stalin as a murderous tyrant;&lt;ref name=&quot;How Russia faced its dark past&quot;/&gt; however, a Russian court in 2009, ruling on a suit by Stalin's grandson, [[Yevgeny Dzhugashvili]], against the newspaper, ''[[Novaya Gazeta]]'', ruled that referring to Stalin as a &quot;bloodthirsty cannibal&quot; was not [[libel]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.nytimes.com/2009/10/14/world/europe/14briefs-Russiabf.html &quot;Russia: Court Rejects Libel Claim by Stalin's Grandson&quot;] [[Associated Press]] article in ''[[The New York Times]]'' 13 October 2009&lt;/ref&gt; In a July 2007 poll 54% of the Russian youth agreed that Stalin did more good than bad while 46% (of them) disagreed that Stalin was a cruel tyrant. Half of the respondents, aged from 16 to 19, agreed Stalin was a wise leader.&lt;ref name=&quot;reuters.com&quot;/&gt;

In December 2008 Stalin was voted third in the nationwide television project [[Name of Russia (Russia TV)|Name of Russia]] (narrowly behind 13th century prince [[Alexander Nevsky]] and [[Pyotr Stolypin]], one of Nicholas II's prime ministers), leading to accusations from [[Communist Party of the Russian Federation]] that the poll had been rigged in order to prevent him or Lenin being given first place.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|author=Tom Parfitt in Moscow |url=http://www.guardian.co.uk/world/2008/dec/29/stalin-name-of-russia |title=Greatest Russian poll |work=The Guardian |location=UK |date= 29 December 2008|accessdate=25 June 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;

On 3 July 2009, Russia's delegates walked out of an [[Organization for Security and Co-operation in Europe]] session to demonstrate their objections to a resolution for a remembrance day for the victims of both Nazism and Stalinism.&lt;ref name=&quot;oscevictims&quot;/&gt; Only eight out of 385 assembly members voted against the resolution.&lt;ref name=&quot;oscevictims&quot;&gt;{{Cite news|url=http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/europe/8133749.stm|publisher=BBC News   |title=Resolution on Stalin riles Russia|date=3 July 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In a Kremlin [[video blog]] posted on 29 October 2009, Russian President [[Dmitry Medvedev]] denounced the efforts of people seeking to rehabilitate Stalin's image. He said the mass extermination during the Stalin era cannot be justified.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|last=Galpin |first=Richard |url=http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/europe/8334009.stm |title= Medvedev blasts Stalin defenders|date=30 October 2009 |accessdate=25 June 2010|work=BBC News   }}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Personal life==
===Origin of name, nicknames and pseudonyms===
Stalin's original Georgian is transliterated as &quot;'''Ioseb Besarionis dze Jughashvili'''&quot; ([[Georgian language|Georgian:]] იოსებ ბესარიონის ძე ჯუღაშვილი). The Russian transliteration of his name Ио́сиф Виссарио́нович Джугашви́ли is in turn transliterated to English as &quot;'''Iosif Vissarionovich Dzhugashvili'''&quot;. Like other Bolsheviks, he became commonly known by one of his revolutionary ''[[nom de guerre|noms de guerre]]'', of which &quot;Stalin&quot; was only the last. Prior nicknames included &quot;'''Koba'''&quot;, &quot;'''Soselo'''&quot;, &quot;'''Ivanov'''&quot; and many others.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|last=Montefiore |first=Simon |authorlink=Simon Sebag Montefiore |title=Young Stalin |edition=2007 Costa biography winner |publisher=[[Weidenfeld &amp; Nicolson]] |location=Britain |isbn=0297850687 |page=395 |chapter=Epilogue |year=2007}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Stalin is believed to have started using the name &quot;K. Stalin&quot; sometime in 1912 as a pen name.

During Stalin's reign his nicknames included:

*&quot;Uncle Joe&quot;, by western media, during and after World War II.&lt;ref name=&quot;salon_20050505_monster&quot;&gt;&quot;[http://dir.salon.com/story/books/review/2005/05/05/stalin/ The Human Monster],&quot; p. 4. O'Hehir, A. ''[[Salon.com]]''. 5 May 2005&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;denson&quot;&gt;{{Cite book|last=Rico|first=Ralph|title=The Costs of War: America's Pyrrhic Victories|editor=Denson, John V.|publisher=Transaction Publishers|location=New Brunswick, N.J.|date=31 May 1997|edition=1st|page=258|chapter=Rethinking Churchill|isbn=1560003197|oclc=36011765|url=http://books.google.com/?id=WbJNNPgcrykC&amp;pg=PA258|accessdate=21 September 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*&quot;Kremlin Highlander&quot; ({{lang-ru|link=no|кремлевский горец}}), in reference his [[Caucasus Mountains]] origin, notably by [[Osip Mandelstam]] in his ''[[Stalin Epigram]]''.
*&quot;Dear father&quot; ({{lang-ru|link=no|батюшка}}, batyushka), as he was portrayed as the paternal figure of the Revolution.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |last=Rappaport |first=Helen |title=Joseph Stalin: A Biographical Companion |year=1999 |publisher=ABC-CLIO |isbn=9781576072080 |accessdate=22 March 2011 |url=http://books.google.com/books?id=lsKClpnX8qwC&amp;pg=PA264}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*&quot;Vozhd&quot;{{'}} ({{lang-ru|link=no|Вождь}}, &quot;the Chieftain&quot;), a term from pre-Tsarist times.

===Appearance===

While photographs and portraits portray Stalin as physically massive and majestic (he had several painters shot who did not depict him &quot;right&quot;),&lt;ref name=tolstoy/&gt; he was only five feet four inches high (160&amp;nbsp;cm).&lt;ref name=tolstoy&gt;{{Cite book| author=[[Nikolai Tolstoy]] |title=Stalin's Secret War| publisher=Holt, Rinehart, and Winston (1981), ISBN 0-03-047266-0| pages=19–21| isbn=0030472660}}&lt;/ref&gt; (President Harry S. Truman, who stood only five feet nine inches himself, described Stalin as &quot;a little squirt&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|url=http://books.google.com/?id=8fp1A2s6aQwC&amp;pg=PA507|page=507|title=Truman |publisher=Simon and Schuster |date=9 April 1952 |accessdate=25 June 2010|first=David|last=McCullough|isbn=9780743260299}}&lt;/ref&gt;) His mustached face was pock-marked from [[small-pox]] during childhood. After a carriage accident in his youth, his left arm was shortened and stiffened at the elbow, while his right hand was thinner than his left and frequently hidden.&lt;ref name=tolstoy/&gt; He could be charming and polite, mainly towards visiting statesmen.&lt;ref name=tolstoy/&gt; In movies, Stalin was often played by [[Mikheil Gelovani]] and, less frequently, by [[Aleksei Dikiy]].

===Marriages and family===
[[File:Ekaterina Svanidze.jpg|thumb|upright|Ekaterina &quot;Kato&quot; Svanidze, Stalin's first wife]]
[[File:Iosif &amp; Nadezhda.jpg|thumb|upright|right|Stalin and Nadezhda Alliluyeva]]

Stalin's son [[Yakov Dzhugashvili|Yakov]], whom he had with his first wife Ekaterina Svanidze, shot himself because of Stalin's harshness toward him, but survived. After this, Stalin said &quot;He can't even shoot straight&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;Simon Sebag Montefiore&quot;&gt;Simon Sebag Montefiore. Stalin: The Court of the Red Tsar, Knopf, 2004. page=11 (ISBN 1-4000-4230-5),&lt;/ref&gt; Yakov served in the Red Army during World War II and was captured by the Germans. They offered to exchange him for Field Marshal [[Friedrich Paulus]], who had surrendered after Stalingrad, but Stalin turned the offer down, stating &quot;You have in your hands not only my son Yakov but millions of my sons. Either you free them all or my son will share their fate.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news| url=http://www.time.com/time/magazine/article/0,9171,941216,00.html|work=Time|title=Historical Notes: The Death of Stalin's Son|date=1 March 1968|accessdate=7 May 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; Afterwards, Yakov is said to have committed suicide, running into an electric fence in [[Sachsenhausen concentration camp]], where he was being held.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.nytimes.com/2001/12/17/world/ex-death-camp-tells-story-of-nazi-and-soviet-horrors.html|title=Ex-Death Camp Tells Story of Nazi + Soviet Horrors|work=New York Times|date=17 December 2001|author=Desmond Butler}}&lt;/ref&gt; Yakov had a son [[Yevgeny Dzhugashvili|Yevgeny]], who is recently noted for defending his grandfather's legacy in Russian courts. Yevgeny is married to a Georgian woman, has two sons, and grandchildren.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news| url=http://articles.sfgate.com/2006-12-17/opinion/17326569_1_red-army-joseph-stalin-germans | work=The San Francisco Chronicle | first=Steven | last=Knipp | date=17 December 2006 | title=George Lenczowski – UC Professor, Middle East Expert}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Stalin had a son, [[Vasily Dzhugashvili|Vasiliy]], and a daughter, [[Svetlana Alliluyeva|Svetlana]], with his second wife [[Nadezhda Alliluyeva-Stalina|Nadezhda Alliluyeva]]. She died in 1932, officially of illness. She may have committed suicide by shooting herself after a quarrel with Stalin, leaving a suicide note which according to their daughter was &quot;partly personal, partly political&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;Koba the Dread, p. 133, ISBN 0786868767; Stalin: The Man and His Era, p. 354, ISBN 0807070017, in a footnote he quotes the press announcement as speaking of her &quot;sudden death&quot;; he also cites pp. 103–105 of his daughter's book, ''Twenty Letters to a Friend'', the Russian edition, New York, 1967&lt;/ref&gt; According to [[A&amp;E Network|A&amp;E]] Biography, there is also a belief among some Russians that Stalin himself murdered his wife after the quarrel, which apparently took place at a dinner in which Stalin tauntingly flicked cigarettes across the table at her. Historians also claim her death ultimately &quot;severed his link from reality.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=K2sugMM9y3Q|title=YouTube – Joseph Stalin Biography 1 of 2}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Vasiliy rose through the ranks of the Soviet air force, officially dying of alcoholism in 1962; however, this is still in question. He distinguished himself in World War II as a capable airman. Svetlana emigrated to the United States in 1967. In March 2001 Russian Independent Television NTV interviewed a previously unknown grandson living in [[Novokuznetsk]], Yuri Davydov, who stated that his father had told him of his lineage, but, was told to keep quiet because of the campaign against Stalin's cult of personality.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url=http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/europe/1245986.stm | title=Stalin grandson found in Siberia | date=March 27, 2001 | accessdate=November 28, 2011 | author=BBC}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Beside his suite in the [[Kremlin]], Stalin had numerous domiciles. In 1919 he started with a country house near Usovo, he added [[dacha]]s at Zuvalova and [[Kuntsevo]] (''[[Blizhny dacha]]'' built by [[Miron Merzhanov]]). Before World War II he added the [[Lipki, Tula Oblast|Lipki]] estate and [[Semyonovskaya]], and had at least four dachas in the south by 1937, including one near [[Sochi]]. A luxury villa near Gagri was given to him by Beria. In Abkhazia he maintained a mountain retreat. After the war he added dachas at Novy Alon, near [[Sukhumi]], in the [[Valdai]] Hills, and at Lake Mitsa. Another estate was near Zelyony Myss on the [[Black Sea]]. All these dachas, estates, and palaces were staffed, well furnished and equipped, kept safe by security forces, and were mainly used privately, rarely for diplomatic purposes.&lt;ref&gt;Nikolai Tolstoy, ibid., pp. 35–37&lt;/ref&gt; Between places Stalin would travel by car or train, never by air; he flew only once when attending the 1943 [[Tehran conference]].

In 1967 [[Svetlana Alliluyeva|Svetlana]] defected to the USA and later married [[William Wesley Peters]] and by him had a daughter Olga (surname now Evans).

===Habits===
Stalin enjoyed drinking, but could keep it under control.&lt;ref name = &quot;McCauley92&quot;&gt;{{Cite book|last=McCauley, |first=Martin |title=Stalin and Stalinism|publisher=[[Pearson Education]] |location=USA |isbn=1405874368 |page=92|year=2008}}&lt;/ref&gt; He would also often force those around him to join in.&lt;ref name = &quot;McCauley92&quot;/&gt; Stalin preferred [[Georgian wine]] over [[Russian vodka]], but usually ate traditional [[Russian food]].&lt;ref name = &quot;McCauley92&quot;/&gt;

Khrushchev reports in his memoirs that Stalin was fond of American [[cowboy movies]].&lt;ref name = &quot;Khrushchev115&quot;&gt;{{Cite book|last=Khrushchev, |first=Nikita |authorlink=Nikita Khrushchev |title=Memoirs of Nikita Khrushchev, vol. II|publisher=[[Penn State Press]] |location=USA |isbn=0271028610 |pages=115–116 |chapter=Economic Problems of Socialism in the USSR|year=2006}}&lt;/ref&gt; He would often sleep until evening in his dacha, and after waking up summon high-ranking Soviet politicians to watch foreign movies with him in the Kremlin movie theater.&lt;ref name = &quot;Khrushchev115&quot;/&gt; The movies, being in foreign languages, were given a running translation.&lt;ref name = &quot;Khrushchev115&quot;/&gt; After the movie had ended, Stalin often invited the audience for dinner, even though the clock was usually past midnight.&lt;ref name = &quot;Khrushchev115&quot;/&gt;

===Attitude to religion===
Stalin had a complex relationship with religious institutions in the Soviet Union.&lt;ref&gt;[[Hector Avalos|Avalos, Hector]], ''Fighting Words: The Origins Of Religious Violence''. by, p. 325&lt;/ref&gt; Historians Vladislav Zubok and Constantine Pleshakov have suggested that &quot;[Stalin's] atheism remained rooted in some vague idea of a God of nature.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|title=Inside the Kremlin's Cold War: From Stalin to Khrushchev|author=Vladislav Zubok|coauthors=Constantine Pleshakov|page=4|isbn=0674455312}}&lt;/ref&gt; One account states that Stalin's [[Stalin in World War II|reversal on bans against the church during World War II]] followed a sign that he believed he received from heaven.&lt;ref name=&quot;Raszinsky-Stalin&quot;&gt;(Radzinsky 1996, pp. 472–3)&lt;/ref&gt;

During the Second World War Stalin reopened the Churches. One reason could have been to motivate the majority of the population who had Christian beliefs. The reasoning behind this is that by changing the official policy of the party and the state towards religion, the Church and its clergymen could be to his disposal in mobilizing the war effort. On 4 September 1943, Stalin invited [[Patriarch Sergius I of Moscow|Metropolitan Sergius]], [[Patriarch Alexy I of Russia|Metropolitan Alexy]] and [[Metropolitan Nikolay of Krutitsy|Metropolitan Nikolay]] to the Kremlin and proposed to reestablish the [[Moscow Patriarchate]], which had been suspended since 1925, and elect the [[Patriarch of Moscow|Patriarch]]. On 8 September 1943, Metropolitan Sergius was elected Patriarch.

The CPSU Central Committee continued to promote atheism and the elimination of religion during the remainder of Stalin's lifetime after the 1943 concordat.&lt;ref&gt;Dimitry V. Pospielovsky. A History of Soviet Atheism in Theory, and Practice, and the Believer, vol 1: A History of Marxist-Leninist Atheism and Soviet Anti-Religious Policies, St Martin's Press, New York (1987) p.71&lt;/ref&gt; Stalin's greater tolerance for religion after 1943 was limited by party machinations. Whether persecutions after World War II were more aimed at certain sections of society over and above detractors is a disputed point.

[[File:May Day in London.jpg|270px|thumb|right|[[Communist Party of Great Britain (Marxist–Leninist)]] contingent at London May Day march in 2008, carrying a banner of Stalin.]]

==Hypotheses, rumors and misconceptions about Stalin==
There are conflicting [[Stalin before the Revolution|accounts of Stalin's birth]], who listed his birth year in various documents as being in 1878 before coming to power in 1922.&lt;ref name=&quot;dob&quot;&gt;Although there is an inconsistency among published sources about Stalin's year and date of birth, Iosif Dzhugashvili is found in the records of the Uspensky Church in Gori, Georgia as born on 18 December ([[Julian calendar|Old Style]]: 6 December) 1878. This birth date is maintained in his School Leaving Certificate, his extensive tsarist Russia police file, a police arrest record from 18 April 1902 which gave his age as 23 years, and all other surviving pre-Revolution documents. As late as 1921, Stalin himself listed his birthday as 18 December 1878 in a curriculum vitae in his own handwriting. However, after his coming to power in 1922, Stalin changed the date to 21 December 1879 ([[Old Style and New Style dates|Old Style date]] 9 December 1879). That became the day his birthday was celebrated in the [[Soviet Union]].{{cite web|url=http://state.rin.ru/cgi-bin/persona_e.pl?id=4140&amp;id_subcat=6&amp;r=8|publisher=State and Power in Russia|accessdate=19 July 2008|title=Prominent figures}}&lt;/ref&gt; The phrase &quot;death of one man is a tragedy, death of a million is a statistic&quot; is sometimes attributed to Stalin,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.religioustolerance.org/genocide0.htm |title=Mass crimes against humanity and genocide |publisher=Religioustolerance.org |accessdate=19 October 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt; but was actually made by the German writer and pacifist [[Erich Maria Remarque]].
In addition, hypotheses and popular rumors exist about Stalin's real father.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.logoi.com/notes/prejevalsky_stalin.html |title=Was Prejevalsky really the father of Joseph Stalin? |publisher=Logoi.com |accessdate=19 October 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt; Some Bolsheviks and others have accused Stalin of being an agent for the [[Okhrana]].&lt;ref&gt;Smith, Edward Ellis.''The Young Stalin.'' New York: Farrar, Straus and Giroux, 1967. p.77&lt;/ref&gt;

==Works==
{{see also|Stalin's poetry}}
*&quot;Anarchism or Socialism?,&quot; 1907
*&quot;Marxism and the National Question,&quot; 1913
*&quot;The Principles of Leninism,&quot; 1924
*&quot;Trotskyism or Leninism?,&quot; 1924
*&quot;[[Dialectical and Historical Materialism]],&quot; 1938
*&quot;The Questions of Leninism,&quot; 1946
*&quot;Marxism and Problems of Linguistics,&quot; 1950
*&quot;Economic Problems of Socialism in the U.S.S.R.,&quot; 1952
*''Works.'' Volume 1–13: Foreign Languages Publishing House, Moscow, 1950s/&quot;Volume 14&quot;: Red Star Press, London 1978

Stalin was also a well-regarded poet in his youth. Some of his poems were published in [[Ilia Chavchavadze]]'s journal ''Iveria'' and later anthologized.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |url=http://www.guardian.co.uk/books/2007/may/19/featuresreviews.guardianreview32 |title=Before the terror |author=Simon Sebag Montefiore  |date=19 May 2007 |work=The Guardian |location=London |accessdate=12 April 2011 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.foreignpolicy.com/articles/2011/04/08/bad_politics_worse_prose?page=0,3 |title=Bad Politics, Worse Prose |author=Suzanne Merkelson |date=8 April 2011 |work=Foreign Policy |accessdate=12 April 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Generalissimus== 
Any kind of Rank like [[Generalissimus of the Soviet Union|Generalissimus]] Stalin was denied (from [[History of the Communist Party of the Soviet Union|CPSU]]).

==See also==
{{Multicol}}
;[[Index of Soviet Union-related articles]]
*[[Stalinism]]
*[[Neo-Stalinism]]
*[[Stalin Society]]
*[[Anti-Stalinist left]]
*[[Stalinist architecture]]
*[[Stalin Peace Prize]]
{{Multicol-break}}
{{Portalbox|Georgia|Soviet Union|Biography|Politics}}
*[[Joseph Stalin Museum, Gori]]
*[[Stalin Monument in Budapest]]
*[[Stalin Monument (Prague)]]
*[[List of places named after Joseph Stalin]]
*[[Stalin's antisemitism]]
*[[Stalin Bloc – For the USSR]]
*[[Yanks for Stalin]]
{{Multicol-end}}

==References==
===Notes===
{{Reflist|colwidth=30em}}

===Bibliography===
{{Refbegin|colwidth=30em}}
*{{Cite book|last=Applebaum|first=Anne|title=Gulag: A History|publisher=Doubleday|year=2003|isbn= 0767900561|ref=harv}}
*{{Cite book|last1=Bideleux|first1=Robert|last2=Jeffries|first2=Ian|title=A History of Eastern Europe: Crisis and Change|publisher=Routledge|year=1998|isbn=9780203050248|ref=harv}}
*{{Cite book|last=Boobbyer|first=Phillip|title=The Stalin Era|publisher=Routledge|year=2000|isbn= 0767900561|ref=harv}}
*{{Cite book|last=Brackman|first=Roman|title=The Secret File of Joseph Stalin: A Hidden Life|publisher=Frank Cass Publishers|year=2001|isbn=0714650501|ref=harv}}
*{{Cite book|last1=Brent|first1=Jonathan|last2=Naumov|first2=Vladimir|title=Stalin's Last Crime: The Plot Against the Jewish Doctors, 1948–1953|publisher=HarperCollins|year=2004|isbn=0060933100|ref=harv}}
*{{Cite book|last=Fest|first=Joachim C.|title=Hitler|publisher=Houghton Mifflin Harcourt|year=2002|isbn=0156027542|ref=harv}}
*{{Cite book|last=Henig|first=Ruth Beatrice|title=The Origins of the Second World War, 1933–41|publisher=Routledge|year=2005|isbn=0415332621|ref=harv}}
*{{Cite book|last=Montefiore|first=Simon Sebag|title=Young Stalin|publisher=Weidenfeld &amp; Nicolson|year=2007|isbn=9780297850687|ref=harv}}
*{{Cite book|last=Murphy|first=David E.|title=What Stalin Knew: The Enigma of Barbarossa|publisher=Yale University Press|year=2006|isbn=030011981X|ref=harv}}
*{{Cite book|last=Overy|first=R. J.|title=The Dictators: Hitler's Germany and Stalin's Russia|publisher=W. W. Norton &amp; Company|year=2004|isbn=0393020304|ref=harv}}
*{{Cite book|last1=Nekrich|first1=Aleksandr Moiseevich|last2=Ulam|first2=Adam Bruno|last3=Freeze|first3=Gregory L.|title=Pariahs, Partners, Predators: German-Soviet Relations, 1922–1941|publisher=Columbia University Press|year=1997|isbn=0231106769|ref=harv}}
*{{Cite book|last=Roberts|first=Geoffrey |title=Stalin's Wars: From World War to Cold War, 1939–1953 |publisher=Yale University Press |year=2006 |isbn=0300112041|ref=harv}}
*{{Cite journal|last=Roberts|first=Geoffrey|title=Stalin, the Pact with Nazi Germany, and the Origins of Postwar Soviet Diplomatic Historiography|year=2002|volume=4|issue=4|ref=harv}}
*{{Cite journal|last=Roberts|first=Geoffrey|title=The Soviet Decision for a Pact with Nazi Germany|journal=Soviet Studies|year=1992|volume=55|issue=2|url=http://www.jstor.org/stable/152247|pages=57–78|publisher=Taylor &amp; Francis, Ltd.|ref=harv}}
*{{Cite journal|last=Soviet Information Bureau|title=Falsifiers of History (Historical Survey)|publisher=Foreign Languages Publishing House|place=Moscow|year=1948|id=272848|ref=harv}}
*{{Cite journal|last=Department of State|title=Nazi-Soviet Relations, 1939–1941: Documents from the Archives of The German Foreign Office|publisher=Department of State|year=1948|url=http://www.ibiblio.org/pha/nsr/nsr-preface.html|ref=harv}}
*{{Cite book|last=Taubert|first=Fritz|title=The Myth of Munich|publisher=Oldenbourg Wissenschaftsverlag|year=2003|isbn=3486566733|ref=harv}}
*{{Cite book|last=Tucker|first=Robert C.|title=Stalin in Power: The Revolution from Above, 1928–1941 |publisher=W. W. Norton &amp; Company|year=1992|isbn=0393308693|ref=harv}}
*{{Cite journal|doi=10.1080/713663077|last=Watson|first=Derek|title=Molotov's Apprenticeship in Foreign Policy: The Triple Alliance Negotiations in 1939|journal=Europe-Asia Studies|year=2000|volume=52|issue=4|url=http://www.jstor.org/stable/153322|pages=695–722|publisher=Taylor &amp; Francis, Ltd.|ref=harv}}
*{{Cite book|last=Wettig|first=Gerhard|title=Stalin and the Cold War in Europe|publisher=Rowman &amp; Littlefield|year=2008|isbn=0742555429|ref=harv}}
{{Refend}}

==Further reading==
{{Refbegin|colwidth=30em}}
*[[Anton Antonov-Ovseenko]]. ''The Time of Stalin: Portrait of a Tyranny''. [[Harpercollins]], 1983 (ISBN 0060390271)
*Brent, Jonathan. ''Inside the Stalin Archives: Discovering the New Russia''. Atlas &amp; Co., 2008 (ISBN 0977743330) [http://atlasandco.com/images/uploads/samples/pdf/InsideStalinArchives-web.pdf Introduction online]
*Brent, Jonathan; Naumov, Vladimir Pavlovich. ''Stalin's Last Crime: The Plot Against the Jewish Doctors, 1948–1953''. New York: HarperCollins, 2003 (ISBN 0-06-019524-X); as ''Stalin's Last Crime: The Doctor's Plot''. London: John Murray, 2004 (ISBN 0-7195-6508-1).
*Broekmeyer, Marius. ''Stalin, the Russians, and Their War, 1941–1945''. Madison, WI: University of Wisconsin Press, 2004 (ISBN 0-299-19590-2).
*Bullock, Alan. ''Hitler and Stalin: Parallel Lives''. London: HarperCollins, 1991 (ISBN 0002154943).
*Boterbloem, Kees. ''Life and Death under Stalin: Kalinin Province, 1945–1953''. Montreal, Quebec; Kingston, ON: McGill-Queen's University Press, 1999 (ISBN 0-7735-1811-8).
*[[Robert Conquest]]. ''The Great Terror: A Reassessment''. New York: Oxford University Press, 1990 (ISBN 0-19-507132-8).
*[[Robert Conquest]]. ''The Harvest of Sorrow: Soviet Collectivization and the Terror-Famine''. New York: Oxford University Press, 1986 (ISBN 0-19-505180-7).
*Davies, Sarah; Harris, James R. ''Stalin: A New History''. Cambridge: Cambridge University Press, 2005 (ISBN 0-521-85104-1).
*[[Isaac Deutscher]]. ''Stalin: A Political Biography''. New York: Oxford University Press, 1967 (ISBN 0-19-500273-3); London: Penguin Books, 1990 (ISBN 0140135049).
*[[Milovan Đilas]]. ''Conversations With Stalin''. Harcourt Trade Publishers New York, 1962 (ISBN 0151225907)
*[[Orlando Figes]]. ''The Whisperers: Private Life in Stalin's Russia''. Metropolitan Books, 2007 (ISBN 0805074619)
*Gellately, Robert. ''Lenin, Stalin, and Hitler: The Age of Social Catastrophe.'' [[Knopf]], August 2007 (ISBN 1400040051).
*Gill, Graeme. ''Stalinism'' (2nd ed.). New York: Palgrave Macmillan, 1998 (ISBN 0-312-17764-X).
*Jonge, Alex de. ''Stalin and the Shaping of the Soviet Union''. New York: William Morrow, 1986 (ISBN 0-688-04730-0); 1987 (ISBN 0688072917).
*Keep, John L.H.; Litvin, Alter L. ''Stalinism: Russian and Western Views at the Turn of the Millennium (Totalitarian Movements and Political Religions)''. New York: Routledge, 2004 (ISBN 0-415-35108-1)
*Kuromiya, Hiroaki. ''Stalin''. Harlow, UK: Longman, 2006 (ISBN 0-582-78479-4).
*Kuromiya, Hiroaki. ''The Voices of the Dead: Stalin's Great Terror in the 1930s.'' [[Yale University Press]], 24 December 2007. ISBN 0300123892
*''The Leader Cult in Communist Dictatorships: Stalin and the Eastern Bloc'', edited by Apor, Balázs; Jan C. Behrends, Polly Jones and E.A. Rees. Houndmills, UK; New York: Palgrave Macmillan, 2004 (ISBN 1-4039-3443-6).
*''The Lesser Evil: Moral Approaches to Genocide Practices (Totalitarian Movements and Political Religions)'', edited by Helmut Dubiel and Gabriel Motzkin. New York: Routledge, 2004 (ISBN 0-7146-5493-0).
*Laqueur, Walter. ''Stalin: The Glasnost Revelations''. New York: Scribner, 1990 (ISBN 0684192039).
*Mace, James E. &quot;The Man-Made Famine of 1933 in Soviet Ukraine&quot;, ''Famine in Ukraine 1932–1933: A Memorial Exhibition'', edited by Roman Serbyn and Bohdan Krawchenko. Edmonton, Alberta: Canadian Institute of Ukrainian Studies, 1986 (ISBN 0-920862-43-8), pp.&amp;nbsp;1–14.
*Mawdsley, Evan. ''The Stalin Years: The Soviet Union, 1929–53''. Manchester: Manchester University Press, 2003 (ISBN 0-7190-6377-9).
*McDermott, Kevin. ''Stalin: Revolutionary in an Era of War (European History in Perspective)''. New York: Palgrave Macmillan, 2006 (ISBN 0-333-71121-1).
*McLoughlin, Barry and McDermott, Kevin (eds). ''Stalin's Terror: High Politics and Mass Repression in the Soviet Union.'' [[Palgrave Macmillan]], 2002. ISBN 1403901198
*[[Roy Medvedev]]; [[Zhores Medvedev]] ''The Unknown Stalin: His Life, Death, and Legacy''. London: I.B. Tauris, 2003 (ISBN 1-86064-768-5)
*[[Simon Sebag Montefiore]]. ''Stalin: The Court of the Red Tsar''. New York: Alfred A. Knopf, 2004 (ISBN 1-4000-4230-5); New York: Vintage, 2005 (ISBN 1400076781).
*[[Simon Sebag Montefiore]]. ''Young Stalin''. London: Weidenfeld &amp; Nicolson, 2007 (ISBN 9780297850687). An [http://www.randomhouse.com/acmart/catalog/display.pperl?isbn=9781400044658&amp;view=excerpt excerpt].
*Murphy, David E. ''What Stalin Knew: The Enigma of Barbarossa''. Yale University Press, 2005 (ISBN 0300107803).
*[[Norman Naimark]] ''Stalin's Genocides (Human Rights and Crimes against Humanity).'' [[Princeton University Press]], 2010. ISBN 0691147841
*[[Richard Overy]]. ''Dictators: Hitler's Germany and Stalin's Russia''. Allen Lane, 2004 (ISBN 0-393-32797-3).
*Parrish, Michael. [http://isbndb.com/d/book/the_lesser_terror.html ''The Lesser Terror: Soviet state security, 1939–1953'']. Praeger Press, 1996 (ISBN 0275951138)
*[[Richard Pipes]]. ''Communism: A History''. [[Modern Library Chronicles]], 2001 (ISBN 0679640509)
*Priestland, David. ''Stalin and the Politics of Mobilization: Ideas, Power, and Terror in Inter-war Russia''. New York: Oxford University Press (U.S.), 2006 (ISBN 0-19-924513-4).
*[[Edvard Radzinsky]]. ''Stalin: The First In-Depth Biography Based on Explosive New Documents from Russia's Secret Archives''. Doubleday, 1996 (ISBN 0-385-47397-4). [http://www.washingtonpost.com/wp-srv/style/longterm/books/chap1/stalin.htm Chapter 1].
*[[Donald Rayfield|Rayfield, Donald]], ''[[Stalin and His Hangmen|Stalin and his Hangmen:  The Tyrant and Those Who Killed for Him]]'', (2005), Random House
*''Redefining Stalinism (Totalitarian Movements and Political Religions)'', edited by Harold Shukman. New York: Routledge, 2003 (ISBN 0-7146-5415-9).
*Ree, Erik van. ''The Political Thought of Joseph Stalin: A Study in Twentieth-Century Revolutionary Patriotism''. London; New York: Routledge Courzon, 2002 (ISBN 0-7007-1749-8).
*Roberts, Geoffrey. ''Stalin's Wars: From World War to Cold War, 1939–1953''. New Heaven, CT; London: Yale University Press, 2006 (ISBN 0300112041).
*[[Steven Rosefielde|Rosefielde, Steven]]. ''[[Red Holocaust (2009 book)|Red Holocaust]].'' [[Routledge]], 2009. (ISBN 0415777577)
*[[Rudolph Rummel]] ''Death By Government''. New Brunswick, N.J.: Transaction Publishers, 1994 (ISBN 1560001453).
*[[Rudolph Rummel]] ''Lethal Politics: Soviet Genocide and Mass Murder Since 1917''. New Brunswick, N.J.: Transaction Publishers, 1990 (ISBN 0887383335)
*Sandag, Shagdariin; Kendall, Harry H.; Wakeman, Frederic E. ''Poisoned Arrows: The Stalin-Choibalsan Mongolian Massacres, 1921–1941.'' Westview Press (October 1999). ISBN 0813337100
*[[Robert Service (historian)|Service, Robert]]. ''Stalin: A Biography''. Cambridge, MA: Belknap Press, 2005 (ISBN 0-674-01697-1).
*[[Timothy Snyder]]. ''[[Bloodlands: Europe Between Hitler and Stalin]].'' [[Basic Books]], 2010. ISBN 0465002390
*[[Boris Souvarine]]. ''Stalin: A Critical Survey of Bolshevism''. Whitefish, MT: Kessinger Publishing, 2005 (ISBN 1-4191-1307-0)[http://www.marxists.org/history/etol/writers/souvar/works/stalin/index.htm Online].
*''Stalin's Terror Revisited.'' Edited by Melanie Ilic and Stephen&amp;nbsp;G. Wheatcroft. New York: Palgrave Macmillan, 2006 (ISBN 1-4039-4705-8).
*[[Robert C. Tucker]] ''Stalin as Revolutionary, 1879–1929: A Study in History and Personality''. (W.W. Norton, 1973) [http://quod.lib.umich.edu/cgi/t/text/text-idx?c=acls;cc=acls;view=toc;idno=heb00811.0001.001 online edition]
*Robert C. Tucker ''Stalin in Power: The Revolution from Above, 1928–1941''. New York: W.W. Norton, 1990 (ISBN 0-393-02881-X).
*Tzouliadis, Tim. ''The Forsaken: An American Tragedy in Stalin's Russia''. The [[Penguin Press]], 2008 (ISBN 1594201684)
*Ulam, Adam Bruno. ''Stalin: The Man and His Era''. Boston: Beacon Press, 1989 (ISBN 0-8070-7005-X)
*Vaksberg, Arkady. ''The Murder of Maxim Gorky. A Secret Execution''. (Enigma Books: New York, 2007. ISBN 978-1-929631-62-9.)
*[[Dmitri Volkogonov]] (Author); Shukman, Harold (Editor, Translator). ''Autopsy for an Empire: the Seven Leaders Who Built the Soviet Regime''. Free Press, 1998 (ISBN 0684834200)
*Ward, Chris. ''The Stalinist Dictatorship''. London: Arnold Publishers, 1998 (ISBN 0-340-70640-6).
*Ward, Chris. &quot;Stalin Through Seventeenth-Century Eyes&quot;, ''Journal of European Studies'', Vol.&amp;nbsp;36, No.&amp;nbsp;2. (2006), pp.&amp;nbsp;181–200.
*[[Alexander Nikolaevich Yakovlev]] (Author); Austin, Anthony (Translator). ''A Century of Violence in Soviet Russia''. [[Yale University Press]], 2002 (ISBN 0300087608)
{{Refend}}

==External links==
{{Sister project links
| wikt    = Stalin
| commons = Иосиф Виссарионович Сталин
 |b       =Joseph Stalin
 |n       =Joseph Stalin
 |q       =Joseph Stalin
 |s       =Author:Joseph Stalin
 |v       =Joseph Stalin
| species = no
}}
{{Refbegin}}
*[http://www.marx2mao.com/Stalin/Index.html Stalin Library (with all 13 volumes of Stalin's ''works'' and &quot;volume 14&quot;)]
*[http://www.loc.gov/exhibits/archives/intro.html Library of Congress: Revelations from the Russian Archives]
*[http://www.marxists.org/reference/archive/stalin/ Electronic archive of Stalin's letters and presentations]
*[http://www.sovetika.ru/ Sovetika.ru{{ndash}} A site about the Soviet era] {{Ru icon}}
*&quot;Another view of Stalin&quot; [http://www.plp.org/books/book1.pdf][http://www.plp.org/books/book2.pdf][http://www.plp.org/books/book3.pdf] by [[Ludo Martens]], [[Progressive Labor Party (United States)|Progressive Labor Party]] website
*[http://www.marxists.org/archive/trotsky/1936/revbet/index.htm &quot;The Revolution Betrayed&quot; by Leon Trotsky]
*[http://www.historyguide.org/europe/cult.html Stalin and the 'Cult of Personality']
*[http://www.spartacus.schoolnet.co.uk/RUSstalin.htm Stalin Biography from Spartacus Educational]
*[http://www.worldfuturefund.org/wffmaster/Reading/Total%20Biblio/Stalin%20Bibliography.htm A List of Key Documentary Material on Stalin]
*&quot;[http://clogic.eserver.org/2005/furr.html Stalin and the Struggle for Democratic Reform, Part One]&quot; and &quot;[http://clogic.eserver.org/2005/furr2.html Part Two]&quot; by Grover Furr.
*''[http://images.library.pitt.edu/cgi-bin/i/image/image-idx?c=stalinka Stalinka: The Digital Library of Staliniana]''
*[http://www.fordham.edu/halsall/mod/1946stalin.html Modern History Sourcebook: Stalin's Reply to Churchill, 1946]
*[http://www.fordham.edu/halsall/mod/1956khrushchev-secret1.html Modern History Sourcebook: Nikita S. Khrushchev: The Secret Speech – On the Cult of Personality, 1956]
*[http://assets.cambridge.org/052182/6284/sample/0521826284WS.pdf The political economy of Stalinism: evidence from the Soviet secret archives / Paul R. Gregory]
*&quot;[http://www.polit.ru/research/2006/01/16/demography.html Demographic catastrophes of the 20th century]&quot;, chapter from ''Demographic Modernization in Russia 1900–2000'', ed. A. G. Vishnevsky, 2006 ISBN 5983790420&amp;nbsp;– estimates of the human cost of Stalin's rule
*[http://alsos.wlu.edu/qsearch.aspx?browse=people/Stalin,+Joseph Annotated bibliography for Joseph Stalin from the Alsos Digital Library for Nuclear Issues]
*[http://english.pravda.ru/main/18/90/363/16693_Stalin.html &quot;Secret documents reveal Stalin was poisoned&quot;] study by the Russian paper [[Pravda]] of events behind possible death by poisoning
*[http://www.webshots.com/page/leadin?u=http%3A%2F%2Fcommunity.webshots.com%2Fuser%2Fsummitphotographics%3Fvhost%3Dcommunity Over 2,000 original German WWII soldier photographs from the Eastern Front]
*Central Intelligence Agency, Office of Current Intelligence. [http://www.foia.cia.gov/CPE/CAESAR/caesar-02.pdf ''Death of Stalin''], 16&amp;nbsp;July 1953.
*[http://www.distributedrepublic.net/archives/2006/05/01/how-many-did-stalin-really-murder/ How Many Did Stalin Really Murder?] by Professor [[R.J. Rummel]]
*[http://www.hoover.org/publications/digest/3058571.html Death of the Butcher] by [[Hoover Institution|Hoover]] fellow [[Arnold Beichman]]
*[http://archive.southcoasttoday.com/daily/11-97/11-23-97/a02wn012.htm A secret revealed: Stalin's police killed Americans] (1997 [[Associated Press]] article)
*[http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=IkCXtMHCUTc Stalin giving a speech] in Russian with English subtitles
*[http://www.ditext.com/conquest/harvest.html ''The Harvest of Sorrow: Soviet Collectivization and the Terror-Famine'' (1986)]
*[http://www.nybooks.com/blogs/nyrblog/2011/jan/27/hitler-vs-stalin-who-was-worse/ Hitler vs. Stalin: Who Was Worse?] by [[Timothy Snyder]]
{{Refend}}

{{Normdaten|LCCN=n/80/44789}}
{{S-start}}
{{S-off}}
{{S-bef|before=None}}
{{S-ttl|title=[[People's Commissariat of Nationalities|People's Commissar of Nationalities]] of the [[Russian Soviet Federative Socialist Republic|RSFSR]]|years=1917–1923}}
{{S-aft|after=?}}
{{S-break}}
{{S-bef|before=[[Vyacheslav Molotov]]}}
{{S-ttl|title=[[Premier of the Soviet Union|Chairman]] of the [[Council of Ministers (Soviet Union)|Council of Ministers of the Soviet Union]]&lt;br /&gt;&lt;small&gt;Council of People's Commissars until 1946&lt;/small&gt;|years=1941–1953}}
{{S-aft|after=[[Georgy Malenkov]]}}
{{S-break}}
{{S-bef|before=[[Semyon Timoshenko]]}}
{{S-ttl|title=[[Minister of Defence of the Soviet Union]]&lt;br /&gt;&lt;small&gt;People's Commissar until 1946&lt;/small&gt;|years=1941–1947}}
{{S-aft|after=[[Nikolai Bulganin]]}}
{{S-break}}
{{S-bef|before=None}}
{{S-ttl|title=Chairman of the [[State Defense Committee]]|years=1941–1945}}
{{S-aft|after=None}}
{{S-break}}
{{S-ppo}}
{{S-break}}
{{S-bef|before=None}}
{{S-ttl|title=[[General Secretary of the Communist Party of the Soviet Union]]|years=1922–1953}}
{{S-aft|after=[[Nikita Khrushchev]]}}
{{S-break}}
{{S-mil}}
{{S-bef|before=None}}
{{S-ttl|title=[[Generalissimo of the Soviet Union]]|years=1945–1953}}
{{S-aft|after=None}}
{{S-end}}

{{Navboxes
| title = Articles and topics related to Joseph Stalin
| state = collapsed
| list1 = 
{{Joseph Stalin}}
{{Leaders of CPSU}}
{{USSRpremier}}
{{Marshals of the Soviet Union}}
{{Cold War}}
{{Cold War figures}}
{{Time Persons of the Year|27–50}}
}}
{{Use dmy dates|date=October 2011}}

{{Persondata
| NAME              = Stalin, Jossif Wissarionowitsch
| ALTERNATIVE NAMES = Josef Stalin, Иосиф Сталин (Russian), Jossif Wissarionowitsch Dschugaschwili, იოსებ ჯუღაშვილი ([[Georgian language|Georgian]] birthname)
| SHORT DESCRIPTION = Dictator of the [[Soviet Union]] (1927–1953)
| DATE OF BIRTH     = {{Birth date|1878|12|18|df=y}}
| PLACE OF BIRTH    = [[Gori, Georgia|Gori]], Georgia
| DATE OF DEATH     = {{Death date|1953|3|5|df=y}}
| PLACE OF DEATH    = Moscow, Russia
}}
{{DEFAULTSORT:Stalin, Joseph}}
[[Category:Anti-fascists]]
[[Category:Anti-Revisionists]]
[[Category:Atheism activists]]
[[Category:Former Eastern Orthodox Christians]]
[[Category:Cold War leaders]]
[[Category:Comintern people]]
[[Category:Deaths from stroke]]
[[Category:Double Heroes of the Soviet Union]]
[[Category:Generalissimos]]
[[Category:Communists from Georgia (country)]]
[[Category:People of World War II from Georgia (country)]]
[[Category:Russian people of Georgian descent]]
[[Category:Great Purge perpetrators]]
[[Category:Heads of government of the Soviet Union]]
[[Category:Heads of the Communist Party of the Soviet Union]]
[[Category:Heroes of Socialist Labour]]
[[Category:Holodomor perpetrators]]
[[Category:Joseph Stalin| ]]
[[Category:Marshals of the Soviet Union]]
[[Category:Marxist theorists]]
[[Category:Old Bolsheviks]]
[[Category:People buried in the Kremlin Wall Necropolis]]
[[Category:People from Gori]]
[[Category:People of the Russian Civil War]]
[[Category:Poets from Georgia (country)]]
[[Category:Politburo of the Central Committee of the Communist Party of the Soviet Union members]]
[[Category:Recipients of the Order of Victory]]
[[Category:Russian atheists]]
[[Category:Smallpox survivors]]
[[Category:Soviet Ministers of Defence]]
[[Category:Soviet people of World War II]]
[[Category:Soviet politicians]]
[[Category:World War II political leaders]]
[[Category:1878 births]]
[[Category:1953 deaths]]
[[Category:Folk saints]]

{{Link GA|sv}}
{{Link FA|he}}
{{Link FA|no}}
{{Link FA|zh}}

[[af:Josef Stalin]]
[[ang:Iosep Stalin]]
[[ar:جوزيف ستالين]]
[[an:Josef Stalin]]
[[arc:ܝܘܣܦ ܣܛܐܠܝܢ]]
[[ast:Yósif Stalin]]
[[az:İosif Stalin]]
[[bn:ইওসিফ স্তালিন]]
[[zh-min-nan:Iosif Stalin]]
[[be:Іосіф Вісарыёнавіч Сталін]]
[[be-x-old:Ёсіф Сталін]]
[[bcl:Josep Stalin]]
[[bg:Йосиф Сталин]]
[[bar:Josef Stalin]]
[[bs:Josif Visarionovič Džugašvili Staljin]]
[[br:Jozef Stalin]]
[[ca:Iósif Stalin]]
[[cv:Сталин Иосиф Виссарионович]]
[[cs:Stalin]]
[[cy:Joseff Stalin]]
[[da:Josef Stalin]]
[[de:Josef Stalin]]
[[et:Jossif Stalin]]
[[el:Ιωσήφ Στάλιν]]
[[es:Iósif Stalin]]
[[eo:Josif Stalin]]
[[ext:Josif Stalin]]
[[eu:Iosif Stalin]]
[[fa:ژوزف استالین]]
[[hif:Joseph Stalin]]
[[fr:Joseph Staline]]
[[fy:Stalin]]
[[ga:Iósaf Stailín]]
[[gd:Eòsaph Stalin]]
[[gl:Iosif Stalin]]
[[gan:斯大林]]
[[gu:સ્ટાલિન]]
[[ko:이오시프 스탈린]]
[[hy:Իոսիֆ Ստալին]]
[[hi:जोसेफ़ स्टालिन]]
[[hr:Josif Staljin]]
[[io:Yosif Stalin]]
[[id:Josef Stalin]]
[[ia:Josef Stalin]]
[[os:Сталин, Иосиф Виссарионы фырт]]
[[is:Jósef Stalín]]
[[it:Stalin]]
[[he:יוסיף סטלין]]
[[jv:Josef Stalin]]
[[kn:ಜೋಸೆಫ್ ಸ್ಟಾಲಿನ್]]
[[ka:იოსებ სტალინი]]
[[kk:Иосиф Виссарионович Сталин]]
[[sw:Josef Stalin]]
[[ku:Josef Stalin]]
[[la:Iosephus Stalin]]
[[lv:Josifs Staļins]]
[[lb:Josef Stalin]]
[[lt:Josifas Stalinas]]
[[li:Jozef Stalin]]
[[lmo:Josif Stalin]]
[[hu:Joszif Visszarionovics Sztálin]]
[[mk:Јосиф Сталин]]
[[ml:ജോസഫ് സ്റ്റാലിൻ]]
[[mt:Josif Stalin]]
[[mr:स्टॅलिन]]
[[arz:يوسيف ستالين]]
[[mzn:Istälin]]
[[ms:Joseph Stalin]]
[[mwl:Josef Staline]]
[[mn:Иосиф Сталин]]
[[my:စတာလင်, ဂျိုးဇတ်]]
[[nl:Jozef Stalin]]
[[ne:स्टालिन]]
[[ja:ヨシフ・スターリン]]
[[nap:Stalin]]
[[no:Josef Stalin]]
[[nn:Josef Stalin]]
[[oc:Ïosif Stalin]]
[[mhr:Сталин, Иосиф Виссарионович]]
[[pnb:جوزف سٹالن]]
[[ps:جوزف سټالين]]
[[pms:Josif Stalin]]
[[pl:Józef Stalin]]
[[pt:Josef Stalin]]
[[kaa:Yosif Stalin]]
[[ro:Iosif Vissarionovici Stalin]]
[[qu:Yosif Stalin]]
[[rue:Осиф Сталін]]
[[ru:Сталин, Иосиф Виссарионович]]
[[sah:Иосиф Сталин]]
[[sa:जोसेफ़ स्टालिन]]
[[sco:Joseph Stalin]]
[[sq:Stalini]]
[[scn:Giuseppi Stalin]]
[[simple:Joseph Stalin]]
[[sk:Josif Vissarionovič Stalin]]
[[sl:Josip Visarijonovič Džugašvili]]
[[szl:Josif Stalin]]
[[ckb:جۆزێف ستالین]]
[[sr:Јосиф Стаљин]]
[[sh:Josif Staljin]]
[[fi:Josif Stalin]]
[[sv:Josef Stalin]]
[[tl:Joseph Stalin]]
[[ta:ஜோசப் ஸ்டாலின்]]
[[tt:Иосиф Сталин]]
[[te:స్టాలిన్]]
[[th:โจเซฟ สตาลิน]]
[[tg:Иосиф Сталин]]
[[tr:Josef Stalin]]
[[uk:Сталін Йосип Віссаріонович]]
[[ur:جوزف استالن]]
[[ug:ستالىن]]
[[za:Joseph Stalin]]
[[vi:Iosif Vissarionovich Stalin]]
[[fiu-vro:Stalini Jossif]]
[[zh-classical:斯大林]]
[[war:Josef Stalin]]
[[wuu:史太林]]
[[yi:יאזעף סטאלין]]
[[yo:Joseph Stalin]]
[[zh-yue:史太林]]
[[diq:Joseph Stalin]]
[[bat-smg:Josips Stalėns]]
[[zh:斯大林]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
