<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="156576" ns="0" title="Ebenezer Scrooge"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Infobox character
| colour      = 
| colour text = 
| name        = Ebenezer Scrooge
| series      = [[A Christmas Carol|A Christmas Carol in Prose, Being a Ghost Story of Christmas]]
| image       = [[File:Marley's Ghost-John Leech, 1843.jpg|235px]]
| caption     = Ebenezer Scrooge encounters  &quot;Jacob Marley's ghost&quot; in Dickens's novel, ''A Christmas Carol''
| first       = 
| last        = 
| cause       = 
| creator     = [[Charles Dickens]]
| portrayer   = [[#Actors portraying Ebenezer Scrooge|See below]]
| episode     = 
| nickname    = 
| alias       = 
| species     = [[Human]]
| gender      = [[Male]]
| occupation  = [[Moneylender|Money-lender]]
| title       = 
| family      = '''Fred''' (nephew)&lt;br&gt;'''Fan''' (sister)
| ex-fiance   = '''Belle'''
| significantother = 
| children    = 
| relatives   = 
| religion    = 
| nationality = [[United Kingdom|British]]
}}

'''Ebenezer Scrooge''' is the principal character in [[Charles Dickens]]'s 1843 novel, ''[[A Christmas Carol]]''. At the beginning of the novel, Scrooge is a cold-hearted, tight-fisted and greedy man, who despises [[Christmas]] and all things which give people happiness. Dickens describes him thus:  &quot;The cold within him froze his old features, nipped his pointed nose, made his eyes red, his thin lips blue, and he spoke out shrewdly in his grating voice ...&quot; His last name has come into the [[English language]] as a byword for [[miser]]liness and [[misanthropy]], traits displayed by Scrooge in the exaggerated manner for which Dickens is well-known. The tale of his [[Redemption (theology)|redemption]] by the three Ghosts of Christmas ([[Ghost of Christmas Past]], [[Ghost of Christmas Present]], and [[Ghost of Christmas Yet to Come]]) has become a defining tale of the [[Christmas]] holiday. Scrooge's catchphrase, &quot;Bah, [[humbug]]!&quot; is often used to express disgust with many of the modern Christmas traditions.

==Origins==
In his diaries, Dickens states that Scrooge stems from a grave marker which he saw in 1841, while taking an evening walk in the [[Canongate Kirkyard]] in Edinburgh. The headstone was for the [[vintner]] Ebenezer Lennox Scroggie, a relative of [[Adam Smith]], who had won the catering contract for the [[visit of George IV to Edinburgh]] and the first contract to supply [[whisky]] to the [[Royal Navy]]. The marker identified Scroggie as a &quot;meal man&quot; (corn merchant), but Dickens misread this as &quot;mean man&quot;, due to the fading light and his mild [[dyslexia]]. Dickens wrote that it must have &quot;shrivelled&quot; Scroggie’s soul to carry &quot;such a terrible thing to eternity&quot;. The grave marker was lost during construction work at part of the kirkyard in 1932.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news| url=http://news.scotsman.com/scotland.cfm?id=1462612004 | location=Edinburgh | work=The Scotsman | first=Jim | last=Mcbeth | title=Revealed: the Scot who inspired Dickens' Scrooge | date=2004-12-24}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Several theories have been put forward as to where Dickens got additional inspiration for the character.
*One school of thought is that Dickens based Scrooge's views on the poor on those of [[demographer]] and [[political economist]] [[Thomas Malthus]].&lt;ref&gt;Frank W. Elwell, [http://www.faculty.rsu.edu/~felwell/Theorists/Malthus/reclaim.html Reclaiming Malthus], 2 November 2001, accessed 28 September 2006.&lt;/ref&gt;
*Another is that the minor character Gabriel Grub from ''[[The Pickwick Papers]]'' was worked up into a more mature characterization (his name stemming from an infamous [[Dutch people|Dutch]] miser, Gabriel de Graaf.)&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.upi.com/NewsTrack/Quirks/2007/12/25/real-life_scrooge_was_dutch_gravedigger/3411/ &quot;Real-life Scrooge was Dutch gravedigger&quot;].&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.telegraph.co.uk/news/main.jhtml;jsessionid=JXXWBDI5OQH4JQFIQMGCFGGAVCBQUIV0?xml=/news/2007/12/24/nscrooge124.xml &quot;Fake Scrooge 'was Dutch gravedigger'&quot;].&lt;/ref&gt;
*[[Jemmy Wood]], owner of the [[Gloucester Old Bank]] and possibly Britain’s first millionaire, was nationally renowned for his stinginess, and may have been another.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.livingheritagesouthwest.co.uk/main/en/FamousPeople/InventorsInnovators.cfm &quot;Jeremy Wood&quot;].&lt;/ref&gt;
*The man whom Dickens eventually mentions in his letters&lt;ref&gt;''The Letters of Charles Dickens'' by Charles Dickens, Madeline House, Graham Storey, Margaret Brown, Kathleen Tillotson, &amp; The British Academy (1999) Oxford University Press [Letter to George Holsworth, 18 January 1865] pp.7.&lt;/ref&gt; and who strongly resembles the character portrayed by Dickens's illustrator, [[John Leech (caricaturist)|John Leech]], was a noted [[British people|British]] eccentric and [[miser]] named [[John Elwes (politician)|John Elwes]] (1714–1789).

==Story==
The story of ''A Christmas Carol'' starts on [[Christmas Eve]] in 1840, with Scrooge at his place of business. The book says that Scrooge lives in London, England. Charles Dickens refers to Scrooge as &quot;...a squeezing, wrenching, grasping, scraping, clutching, covetous old sinner!&quot; It is usually assumed that he is a [[banker]] or professional money lender. Some recent versions portray him as a [[solicitor]]. Whatever his main business is, he seems to have [[usury|usurious]] relationships with people of little means. These relationships, along with his lack of charity and shabby treatment of his clerk, [[Bob Cratchit]], seem to be his major vices.

His nephew however, has great regard for Christmas and we are introduced to him early in the story where he unsuccessfully attempts to invite Scrooge to his Christmas dinner party only to be rebuffed by Scrooge with a repeatedly said sentence: &quot;Good afternoon&quot;. After his nephew leaves, two charitable men come in and ask Scrooge if he is willing to help them raise a fund to help the poor, but Scrooge refuses and makes unkind comments to the men about the poor: &quot;If they'd rather die they better do it now and decrease the surplus population.&quot; and angrily dismisses them.

Scrooge has only disgust for the poor, thinking the world would be better off without them, &quot;decreasing the surplus population,&quot; and praise for the [[Victorian era]] [[workhouse]]s. He has a particular distaste for the merriment of Christmas; his single act of kindness is to give his clerk, Bob Cratchit, the day off with pay. Done more as a result of social mores than kindness, Scrooge sees the practice akin to having his pocket picked on an annual basis.

After introducing Scrooge and showing his shabby treatment of his employee, business men, and only living relative, the novel resumes with Scrooge at his residence, intent on spending Christmas Eve alone. While he is preparing to go to bed, he is visited by the ghost of his deceased business partner, [[Jacob Marley]]. Marley (who had died seven years earlier on Christmas Eve) spent his life exploiting the poor and as a result is [[Hell in Christian beliefs|damned]] to walk the Earth for eternity bound in the chains of his own greed. Marley warns Scrooge that he risks meeting the same fate, and that as a final chance of escape he will be visited by three spirits: Past, Present, and Yet to Come. The rest of the novel acts as a biography and psychological profile, showing his evolution to his current state, and the way he is viewed by others.

As promised, the [[Ghost of Christmas Past]] visits Scrooge first and takes him to see his time as a schoolboy many years earlier. Here it is suggested that his father abandoned young Scrooge at his boarding school, even during Christmas. This is relevant to Scrooge, because it shows the beginnings of his lack of [[socialization]] and empathy. He does not socialize because he never experienced steady growth in a strong family unit. He does not empathize thanks to the way he was treated: as a child, he was the least of his father's concerns, and this in turn taught him not to feel for fellow humans. In some versions of the story, his father goes to jail for not paying debt&amp;nbsp;– it is hinted that he may have died while in prison. Later the ghost shows how his success in business made him become obsessive and develop a [[workaholic]] tendency. His money and work-obsessed personality traits eventually compel Scrooge's fiancée, Belle, to leave him, which further hardens his heart. The death of his younger sister Fan, the one relative who had a close relationship with him, also injures him greatly enough that he loses any love he had for the world. Scrooge has only his nephew left but doesn't particularly care for him, likely due to Scrooge blaming him for his sister's death following childbirth; in some versions Scrooge's father blames Ebenezer for causing his wife's death in childbirth with Fan as the older sibling. It is also shown that Scrooge was an apprentice for Mr. Fezziwig, a warehouse buisness owner.

The visit by the Ghost of Christmas Past also reveals the origin of Scrooge's [[neurosis|neurotic]] hatred of Christmas; most of the events that negatively affected Scrooge's character occurred during the Christmas holiday season.

One of the sources of his negative ways is the pain he feels for losing his love, Belle. Engaged to be married to her, he keeps pushing back the wedding until his finances are as healthy as he would like; something that, given his insatiable lust for money, he would probably never have. Realizing this, Belle calls off the engagement and eventually marries someone else, causing Scrooge to further withdraw from society and relationships.

[[File:A Christmas Carol - Scrooge and Bob Cratchit.jpg|thumb|right|Scrooge and [[Bob Cratchit]] illustrated by [[John Leech (caricaturist)|John Leech]] in 1843]]
Scrooge is then visited by the [[Ghost of Christmas Present]], who shows him the happiness of his nephew's middle-class social circle and the impoverished Cratchit family. The latter have a young son (Tiny Tim) who is lame, yet the family still manages to live happily on the pittance Scrooge pays his clerk.  When Scrooge, whose sense of compassion is rapidly resurfacing, asks if Tim will die, the ghost&amp;nbsp;–, confirms this, but uses Scrooge's past unkind comments to two charitable solicitors against him&amp;nbsp;– suggests &quot;they had better do it now, and decrease the surplus population&quot;.

The ghost also warns him of the evils of Ignorance and Want. As the spirit's robe is drawn back Scrooge is shocked to see these two aspects of the human psyche suddenly manifest before him as vicious, terrifying, little children, who are more animal than human in appearance.

The [[Ghost of Christmas Yet to Come]] shows Scrooge the final consequences of his actions one year later. Tiny Tim has died from his illness, leaving the entire Cratchit family in mourning. In addition, Scrooge's solitary life and disdain for those in need will ultimately lead others to find only comfort and happiness from his own death. No one will mourn his passing and his money and possessions will be stolen by the desperate and corrupt, the very people he condemned in life. The only people who feel any emotion are a young couple Scrooge was about to ruin financially. His death, however, allows them the small amount of extra time (while Scrooge's affairs were being settled) to raise the funds to pay off their debt to his estate. His final legacy will be that of a cheap tombstone in an unkempt graveyard. Scrooge then weeps over his own grave, begging the ghost for a chance to change his ways and re-embrace life, before awakening to find it is Christmas morning. He has been given an opportunity to repent after all. Scrooge does so and becomes a model of generosity and kindness, towards his nephew, his neighbours, and even the Cratchits. As the final narration states, &quot;Many laughed to see this alteration in him, but he let them laugh and little heeded them, for he knew that no good thing in this world ever happened, at which some did not have their fill of laughter. His own heart laughed and that was quite enough for him. And it was always said of him that he knew how to keep Christmas well if any man alive possessed the knowledge.&quot;

==Actors portraying Ebenezer Scrooge==
Scrooge has been portrayed by:

* [[Tom Ricketts]] in [[A Christmas Carol (1908 film)|1908]]
* [[Marc McDermott]] in [[A Christmas Carol (1910 film)|1910]]
* [[Seymour Hicks]] in [[Scrooge (1913 film)|1913]] and again in [[Scrooge (1935 film)|1935]]
* [[Rupert Julian]] in 1916
* [[Russell Thorndike]] in 1923
* [[Lionel Barrymore]] on radio throughout the 1930s and 1940s
* [[John Barrymore]] on radio, for ailing brother Lionel 1930s
* [[Reginald Owen]] in [[A Christmas Carol (1938 film)|1938]]
* [[John Carradine]] in 1947
* [[Malcolm Keen]] in 1947
* [[Taylor Holmes]] in 1949
* [[Bransby Williams]] in 1950
* [[Alastair Sim]] in [[Scrooge (1951 film)|1951]], and again in [[A Christmas Carol (1971 film)|1971]] (voice)
* [[Fredric March]] in 1954
* [[Basil Rathbone]] in 1956 and 1958
* [[Jim Backus]] (as [[Quincy Magoo]]) in ''[[Mister Magoo's Christmas Carol]]'', 1962
* [[Cyril Ritchard]] in 1964
* [[Wilfrid Brambell]] in a 1966 radio musical version (adapted from his Broadway role)
* [[Sid James]] in the ''[[Carry On Christmas Specials]]'', 1969
* [[Albert Finney]] in [[Scrooge (1970 film)|1970]]
* [[Marcel Marceau]] in 1973
* [[Michael Hordern]] in 1977
* [[Walter Matthau]] (voice) in ''The Stingiest Man in Town'', 1978
* [[Henry Winkler]] as Benedict Slade in ''An American Christmas Carol'', 1979
* [[Hoyt Axton]] as Cyrus Flint in ''Skinflint: A Country Christmas Carol'', 1979
* [[Alan Young]] (as [[Scrooge McDuck]]) in ''[[Mickey's Christmas Carol]]'', 1983
* [[George C. Scott]] in [[A Christmas Carol (1984 film)|1984]]
* [[Bill Murray]] as Frank Cross in ''[[Scrooged]]'', 1988
** [[Buddy Hackett]] (as himself) played Scrooge in the [[film-within-a-film]].
* [[Rowan Atkinson]] as Ebenezer Blackadder in ''[[Blackadder's Christmas Carol]]'', 1988
* [[Michael Caine]] in ''[[The Muppet Christmas Carol]]'', 1992
* [[Jeffrey Sanzel]] has appeared in more than 1,000 stage performances since 1992
* [[James Earl Jones]] in ''Bah, Humbug'', 1994
* [[Henry Corden]] (as [[Fred Flintstone]]) in ''[[A Flintstones Christmas Carol]]'', 1994
*[[Susan Lucci]] as Elizabeth &quot;Ebbie&quot; Scrooge in ''[[Ebbie]]'', 1995
*[[Beavis]] as Beavis Scrooge, 1995
* [[Cicely Tyson]] as Ebenita Scrooge in ''Ms. Scrooge'', 1997
* [[Tim Curry]] (voice) in 1997
* [[Jack Palance]] in ''Ebenezer'', 1997
* [[Patrick Stewart]] in [[A Christmas Carol (1999 film)|1999]]
* [[Vanessa L. Williams|Vanessa Williams]] as Ebony Scrooge in ''A Diva's Christmas Carol'', 2000
* [[Ross Kemp]] as Eddie Scrooge in 2000
* [[Dean Jones (actor)|Dean Jones]] in ''Scrooge and Marley'', 2001
* [[Tori Spelling]] as &quot;Scroogette&quot; Carol Cartman in ''[[A Carol Christmas]]'', 2003
* [[Kelsey Grammer]] in 2004
* [[Bill Bourne]] in ''The Carol Project'', 2006
* [[Joe Alaskey]] (as [[Daffy Duck]]) in ''[[Bah, Humduck! A Looney Tunes Christmas]]'', 2006
* [[Helen Fraser]] as Sylvia Hollamby in ''[[Bad Girls (TV series)|Bad Girls 2006 Christmas Special]]
* [[Morwenna Banks]] as Eden Starling in ''[[Barbie in a Christmas Carol]]'', 2008
* [[Jim Carrey]] in [[A Christmas Carol (2009 film)|2009]] (Carrey also played the three spirits haunting Scrooge).&lt;ref name= &quot;ann&quot;&gt;Fleming, Michael.  [http://www.variety.com/article/VR1117968136.html &quot;Jim Carrey set for 'Christmas Carol': Zemeckis directing Dickens adaptation&quot;], [[Variety (magazine)|Variety]], 2007-07-06. Retrieved on 2007-09-11.&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[Catherine Tate]] as Nan in &quot;[[Nan's Christmas Carol]]&quot;, 2009
* [[Christina Milian]] as Sloane Spencer in &quot;[[Christmas Cupid]],&quot; December 2010
* [[Eric Braeden]] as [[Victor Newman]] in &quot;Victor's Christmas Carol&quot; on ''[[The Young and the Restless]]'', December 2010
* [[Michael Gambon]] as Kazran Sardick in &quot;A Christmas Carol&quot; on ''[[Doctor Who]]'', December 2010.&lt;ref name=&quot;BBC Press&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.bbc.co.uk/pressoffice/proginfo/tv/2010/wk51/bbc_one.shtml#bbc_one_doctorwho|title=Doctor Who Christmas Special – A Christmas Carol|accessdate=22 November 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;XmasRT&quot;&gt;{{Cite journal|title=Christmas Day|journal=[[Radio Times]]|issue=volume 347, no. 4520|page=174|date=18-31 Dec 2010 (cover date)}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Scrooge and the English language==
The name &quot;Scrooge&quot; is used even outside of the UK and the US as a word for a person who is always complaining. Interestingly, it is almost always used in that context, and not as a person who changes from bad to good, despite the fact that his unpleasant side is only shown in its entirety within the first chapter, or &quot;stave&quot;.

The character is most often noted for exclaiming &quot;Bah! Humbug!&quot; in spite of uttering this phrase only twice in the entire book.  The word &quot;Humbug&quot; he uses on its own seven times, although on the seventh we are told that he &quot;stopped at the first syllable&quot; after realising Marley's ghost is real.  The word is never used again after that in the book.

The word &quot;Ebenezer&quot; comes from Hebrew and is actually two words pronounced together: Even Haezer.  It is usually transliterated as a proper name by dropping the definite article (Ha) from the Hebrew word for &quot;help&quot; (Ezer) and putting it together with the Hebrew word for &quot;stone&quot; (Even) to create: &quot;Ebenezer.&quot; The etymological roots of the word, thus defined, should demonstrate that an &quot;Ebenezer&quot; is, literally, a &quot;Stone of Help.&quot;  The Biblical Scripture reads as follows:
&lt;blockquote&gt;''“Then Samuel took a stone and set it up between Mizpah and Jeshanah, and named it Ebenezer; for he said, ‘Thus far the Lord has helped us.’ So the Philistines were subdued and did not again enter the territory of Israel; the hand of the Lord was against the Philistines all the days of Samuel. The towns that the Philistines had taken from Israel were restored to Israel, from Ekron to Gath; and Israel recovered their territory from the hand of the Philistines. There was peace also between Israel and the Amorites.”'' (1 Samuel 7:12-14 NRSV)&lt;/blockquote&gt;

A species of snail is named ''[[Ba humbugi]]'' after Scrooge's catchphrase.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.curioustaxonomy.net/puns/puns.html|accessdate=2008-12-23|title=Curiosities of Biological Nomenclature}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.nytimes.com/2005/02/20/weekinreview/20foun.html?ex=1266642000&amp;en=072f74ff6a4493dd&amp;ei=5088&amp;partner=rssnyt|title=Ba Humbugi! Let's Nameus That Speciesus|last=Fountain|first=Henry|date=2005-02-20|publisher=The [[New York Times]]|accessdate=2008-12-23}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Scrooge appears in [[Louis Bayard]]'s 2003 novel ''Mr. Timothy,'' which is told from Tim Cratchit's perspective.

== See also ==
*[[Grinch]]
*[[Scrooge McDuck]]

==References==
{{reflist}}

==External links==
*{{imdb character|0000500}}
*{{worldcat id|id=lccn-sh89-6283}}

{{A Christmas Carol}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Scrooge, Ebenezer}}
[[Category:Fictional characters introduced in 1843]]
[[Category:Christmas characters]]
[[Category:A Christmas Carol characters]]
[[Category:Fictional accountants]]
[[Category:Fictional businesspeople]]
[[Category:Fictional English people]]

[[es:Ebenezer Scrooge]]
[[id:Ebenezer Scrooge]]
[[it:Ebenezer Scrooge]]
[[nl:Ebenezer Scrooge]]
[[pl:Ebenezer Scrooge]]
[[pt:Ebenezer Scrooge]]
[[ru:Скрудж (персонаж)]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
