<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="1573262" ns="0" title="Eileen Atkins"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{lead too short|date=September 2010}}
{{Infobox person
| image =
| imagesize =
| caption = 
| birthname = Eileen June Atkins 
| birth_date = {{birth date and age|1934|6|16|df=yes}}
| birth_place = [[London|London, England]]
| spouse = [[Julian Glover]] (1957-1966)&lt;br&gt;Bill Shepherd (1978-present)
| laurenceolivierawards = '''[[Laurence Olivier Awards|Best Supporting Actress]]'''&lt;br&gt;1989 ''Cymbeline and Mountain Language''&lt;br&gt;'''[[Laurence Olivier Awards|Best Actress]]'''&lt;br&gt;1999 ''[[The Unexpected Man]]''&lt;br&gt;2004 ''[[Honour]]''
| sagawards = '''[[Screen Actors Guild Award for Best Cast in a Motion Picture|Best Cast - Motion Picture]]'''&lt;br&gt;2001 ''[[Gosford Park]]''
| baftaawards = '''[[BAFTA TV Award|Best TV Actress]]'''&lt;br&gt;2008 ''[[Cranford (TV series)|Cranford]]''
| emmyawards = '''[[Primetime Emmy Award|Best Supporting Actress&lt;br&gt;(Miniseries or Movie)]]'''&lt;br&gt;2008 ''[[Cranford (TV series)|Cranford]]''
}}

'''Dame Eileen June Atkins''', [[Order of British Empire|DBE]] (born 16 June 1934) is an English actress and occasional [[screenwriter]].

== Early life ==
Atkins was born in the ''Mothers' Hospital'' in [[Lower Clapton|Clapton]], a [[Salvation Army]] women's hostel in [[East End of London|East London]]. Her mother, Annie Ellen ([[married and maiden names|née]] Elkins), was a barmaid who was 46 when Eileen was born, and her father, Arthur Thomas Atkins, was a [[gas meter]] reader who was previously under-[[chauffeur]] to the [[Portugal|Portuguese Ambassador]]. Atkins attended [[the Latymer School]], [[Edmonton, London|Edmonton]] and the [[Guildhall School of Music and Drama]].

She was born in the East End, in the Clapton Salvation Army Home. They then moved to Tottenham (something called the White Hart Lane Estate). She described her circumstances then as &quot;pretty well the lowest form of living.&quot; She was the third child in the family and so her family qualified for a council home.&lt;ref&gt;Carole Zucker, ''In The Company of Actors: Reflections on the Craft of Acting'' (London: A &amp; C Black Publishers, 1999), p. 2. Retrieved from Google Books, 3 December 2011&lt;/ref&gt; 

Her father was an under-chauffeur and her mother worked for a time as a barmaid at the Trocadero Theatre. In her youth she worked really hard to get rid of her cockney accent.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;Upstairs Downstairs: BFI Screening&quot; (16 December 2010) in lifeofwylie.com. Retrieved 1 December 2011&lt;/ref&gt; She is, in fact, against the &quot;fashion&quot; in drama schools these days for students not to get rid of their &quot;basic accent.&quot; She says that such fashion is &quot;bad for those from the working-class areas&quot; as they will never get &quot;classical leading parts.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Anita Singh, &quot;Dame Eileen Atkins: why must actors have regional accents?&quot;  ''The Telegraph'' (9 December 2010) in www.telegraph.co.uk. Retrieved 1 December 2011&lt;/ref&gt;

Her mother was already nearing 40 when she met her father. Her father was an &quot;under-chauffeur&quot; and serviced the automobile of the Portuguese Ambassador. He did not, in fact, know how to drive and as under-chauffeur was responsible mainly for cleaning the car. Her mother had an abortion on her third pregnancy. An elder sibling of Atkins died at 2 from diphtheria. Her mother regarded this as divine punishment for what she did. At the time Atkins was born her mother was 47, worked in a factory the whole day and then as a barmaid in the Elephant &amp; Castle at night; while the father read gas meters. Her father had in fact &quot;undergone testicular surgery&quot; earlier. She was born in a Salvation Army Home in Clapton, north London. Until she died, her mother insisted that Atkins was born in a hospital, not in a home. When Atkins was three, a Gypsy came to their door selling lucky heather and clothes pegs. She saw Atkins and told the mother the her daughter would be a famous dancer. So her mother enrolled her in dance class. In 1939, she and her 12-year old brother, together with other children, were transported to a rural village in Essex. This was during the War to avoid enemy bombing. She was taken in by a woman, but Atkins was traumatised by this experience. She was later taken back by her mother and her career as &quot;Baby Eileen&quot; began: dancing and singing around the working men's club circuit for 15 shillings a pop. 
When she was 14, going on 15, she saw Robert Atkins' production of ''King John''. She wrote to him saying that the boy who played the prince was not good enough and that she could do better. Robert Atkins wrote back and asked that she come to see him. On the day they met, Robert Atkins thought she was a shop girl, and not a school girl. She gave a little prince speech and Robert Atkins told her to go back when she was grown up. She didn't get into RADA. Guildhall signed her up for a teaching course but &quot;she slipped herself in with the drama students and took up their curriculum as well.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Sally Vincent, &quot;A class act,&quot; ''The Guardian'' (Saturday, 9 December 2000). Retrieved from www.guardian.co.uk on 2 December 2011&lt;/ref&gt; 

She once said: &quot;Despite my screams, I never liked dancing. I studied that from 3 to 15 or 16. During the war I performed at London's Stage Door canteen for American troops. I was Baby Eileen, singing things like 'Yankee Doodle.'&quot; Rev. Michael Burton, one of her grammar school teachers who was &quot;a whiz at dramatics,&quot; detected her potential and &quot;rigorously drilled away her cockney accent.&quot; She studied under him for two years and finally won a scholarship to the Guildhall school of music and drama where she trained as a teacher. After graduation she worked at assorted jobs and was briefly an assistant stage manager at the Oxford Playhouse until Peter Hall fired her for impudence. At 21 she married actor Julian Glover. The marriage continued until 1965.&lt;ref&gt; William Glover, &quot;Eileen Atkins Stars in Another Ringing Triumph,&quot; ''The Evening News'' (Sat., Feb. 26, 1972). Retrieved from news.google.com on 2 December 2011&lt;/ref&gt;

Danced in working men's clubs from age 7 to 15. When she was in panto at 12 in Clapham and Kilburn, someone told her mother that Eileen had a Cockney accent. Her mother was appalled. Speech lessons were too expensive for the family. Fortunately, her divinity teacher in grammar school taught her for free.&lt;ref&gt;Jasper Rees, &quot;Theartdesk Q&amp;A: Actress Eileen Atkins,&quot; (Friday, 24 December 2010) in www.theartdesk.com. Retrieved, 3 December 2011&lt;/ref&gt;
 
From age 7 she tap-danced and sang &quot;incredibly sexy songs&quot; in working men's clubs. She earned fifteen shillings which helped the family budget and paid for her dancing classes. At one time she was attending dance class four or five times a week. A woman took interest in her and paid for her to be educated at Latymer's in Edmonton. By 12 or 13 she was a professional in panto at Clapham and Kilburn. This when her mother wanted her to be rid of the cockney accent. She was sent to a speech-training mistress but this was discontinued because it became too expensive for her family. Then a &quot;bizarre man who used to take us for religious instruction&quot; entered her life. He trained her to speak properly (dropping the accent) and introduced her to Shakespeare. She stayed in Latymer until 16. The teacher came to an agreement with her parents that he would get her a scholarship for one drama school and that if she did not get the scholarship he would arrange for her to do a teaching course in some other drama school. She missed the scholarship to RADA and so entered Guildhall on a teaching course. But while at Guildhall on a teaching course, she attended every drama class. It was not until her third year (when she was teaching once a week) that the principal discovered this. So she was actually doing two courses - teaching and drama - at Guildhall. In her last year she had to teach one day a week. Once she taught children a course on &quot;Free Drama.&quot; She did not like teaching. She was in Guildhall in the &quot;early '50s&quot; (p. 4). She hanged around two seasons for Stratford. When she went there she was not even allowed to understudy. She just went as the wife of Julian Glover, her then husband. She really learned about acting in Stratford. Before Stratford, she did &quot;a few seasons of weekly rep in dreadful places.&quot; She and Julian were in a rep together in a holiday camp in Skegness. They were both then 21 when they got married. Then Julian got a walk-on job at Stratford. She &quot;gradually went up the scale at Stratford:&quot; from being an usherette to finally acting on stage.&lt;ref&gt;Carole Zucker, ''In The Company of Actors: Reflections on the Craft of Acting'' (London: A &amp; C Black Publishers, 1999), pp. 2-5. Retrieved at Google Books on 2 December 2011&lt;/ref&gt; 

Attended Latymer's Grammar School - ca. 1945 - 1950 (when she turned 16 on 16 June 1950). She was certainly in Latymer's when she was 12 or 13 (1946/1947) and 14 or 15 (1948/1949). Entered Guildhall on teaching course - ca. September 1950 (aged 16). She was at Guildhall for (at least) three years (on teaching course but also attended drama courses) - graduated ca. 1953. 1950-1953 would certainly be &quot;early '50s.&quot; As soon as she left Guildhall she got her first job with Robert Atkins. First job with Robert Atkins: in 1953 as Jaquenetta in ''Love's Labours Lost'' at the Regent's Park Open Air Theatre with Robert Atkins directing. In an interview with Carole Zucker in October 1997, she said: &quot;I went nine years before I was working steadily.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Carole Zucker, ''In The Company of Actors: Reflections on the Craft of Acting'' (London: A &amp; C Black Publishers, 1999), p. 5. Retrieved in Google Books,3 December 2011&lt;/ref&gt; The &quot;nine years&quot; was probably from 1953 to 1962. In 1962, then with the Old Vic, she began getting steady stage roles and even appeared in theatre magazines. Married Julian Glover when both were 21: she turned 21 on 16 June 1955 and he turned 21 on 27 March 1956, so they were probably married April/May 1956.&lt;ref&gt;Reconstructed based on data from: (1) Carole Zucker, ''In The Company of Actors: Reflections on the Craft of Acting'' (London: A &amp; C Publishers, 1999); (2) Richard Digby Day, &quot;Delightful insight into life of actress,&quot; ''Newark Advertiser'' (Sunday, 23 October 2011 - Palace Theatre, Newark) in www.newarkadvertiser.co.uk; (3) &quot;Regent's Park Open Air Theatre: Our History&quot; in openairtheatre.org/history; (4) Production Notes of ''The Queen of Sheba's Pears, Last Chance Harvey'' and ''Robin Hood''; and (5)&quot;Atkins, Eileen 1934 -   &quot; in ''Contemporary Theatre, Film and Television'' (The Gale Group, Inc., 2004) retrieved in www.encyclopedia.com on 4 December 2011&lt;/ref&gt;

Her mother was told by a [[Romani people|gypsy]] that Eileen would be a great dancer, so she was sent to dancing classes from an early age, and appeared dancing in [[working men's club]]s as &quot;Baby Eileen&quot; throughout the war years.&lt;ref&gt;interview with [[Jonathan Ross]] on Friday Night with Jonathan Ross, BBC1, 13 June 2008&lt;/ref&gt;

She took dancing lessons when a gypsy came to her mother's door and said that she would be a good dancer. She danced in working men's clubs two to three nights a week. By 12 she hated dancing and began doing pantomine acting. Out of 300 applicants for a RADA scholarship, she got down to the last three but was not selected. So she did a three-year course on teaching and acting at the Guildhall instead. As soon as she left she got her first job with Robert Atkins whom she impressed back when she was 12. She met her first husband, Julian Glover, when he was doing repertory at Butlins  and he helped her enter the Royal Shakespeare Company.&lt;ref&gt;Richard Digby Day, &quot;Delightful Insight Into Life of Actress,&quot; ''Newark Advertiser'' (Sunday, 23 October 2011 - Palace Theatre, Newark) in www.newarkadvertiser.co.uk. Retrieved 30 November 2011&lt;/ref&gt;

She was taken to see ''King John'' at the Open Air Theatre in Regents Park when she was 12. She wrote to Robert Atkins, then director of the Royal Shakespeare Company, saying that the boy who played Prince Arthur was bad and that she would have been better. They met, she did a Prince Arthur speech and he told her to come back when an adult. She won the Shakespeare prize at the Guildhall School of Music and Drama.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;Eileen Atkins&quot; in The Telegraph (16 June 2001) at www.telegraph.co.uk. Retrieved 30 November 2011&lt;/ref&gt;

On her early years as an actress and Stratford: &quot;I went nine years before I was working steadily. It took me so long to get going, hanging around for two seasons at Stratford. When I first went there, they wouldn't even allow me to understudy. I just went as the wife of my then-husband, Julian Glover. I really started to learn about acting at Stratford. I'd done a few seasons of weekly rep in dreadful places, and then I married Julian. We'd been in rep together in a holiday camp in Skegness, and we were both 21. Then he'd got a walk-on job at Stratford . . . So he got into Stratford, and I'd given up by then: I had two terrible years, with only a few weeks of rep here and there, and I thought 'Well, I'll just go up and be a wife'. I gradually went up the scale at Stratford: I worked as an usherette, and then they asked me if I'd like to work on the postcard stand in the foyer, and I sold postcards of all the old actors, and answered questions about the theatre. I was so miserable. I so wanted to be backstage with the actors. That season, suddenly, they'd lost about five people, and they were thinning on the ranks of the walk-ons because everybody had moved up. My husband heard they were going to take on some more extras for a crowd scene, and he went to Glen Byam Shaw and said 'Look, my wife's here with me, and she's dying to be in it', and he said 'Listen old chap, we don't just take people's wives, because you want.' and my husband said 'I think she did an audition for you once.' He looked up my audition, and he said 'All right, she can come into the company, but she will not even be allowed to understudy. Okay?' I was allowed in the company. The thrill! I went in halfway through the season. And I'd only been there six weeks, and the girl who was playing Audrey in ''As You Like It'' - Dame Peggy Ashcroft was playing Rosalind - was taken to hospital for six weeks. Then ''her'' understudy was taken to hospital in the night with some kind of chest thing, she couldn't breath. And I thought 'She's the understudy, who is going to play Audrey tomorrow night? What if she's not better? So I stayed up all night and learned Audrey, and made sure I was in the theatre the next day, and they were all saying 'Oh my God, is there anyone who knows Audrey?' and I said 'Yes, I know it, I've played it.' I lied, and I went on as Audrey, and from then on they accepted me at Stratford. But you see, I was cunning.&quot;  &lt;ref&gt;Carole Zucker, In ''The Company of Actors: Reflections on the Craft of Acting'' (London: A &amp; C Black Publishers, 1999), p.5-6. Retrieved from Google Books, 3 December 2011&lt;/ref&gt;

==Career==
She joined the Guild Players Repertory Company in Bangor, Northern Ireland as a professional actress in 1952. Her first English stage appearance was at the [[Open Air Theatre, Regent's Park]] in 1953. She also appeared on-stage with [[Laurence Olivier]], [[John Thaw]] and [[James Bolam]] in ''[[Semi-Detached (play)|Semi-Detached]]'' (1962) by [[David Turner (dramatist)|David Turner]]. 

Atkins' London stage debut was as Jaquenetta in Robert Atkins' staging of ''Love's Labours Lost'' at the Open Air Theatre in Regent's Park. Seasons in repertory followed, including two years with the Royal Shakespeare Company at Stratford-upon-Avon.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;Eileen Atkins&quot; in www.filmbug.com. Retrieved 30 November 2011&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;&quot;Robin Hood&quot; (2010): Production Notes, p. 28. Retrieved from www.visualhollywood.com in PDF format on 2 December 2011&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;&quot;Last Chance Harvey:&quot; Production Notes, p. 14. Retrieved from thecia.com.au in Rich Text Format on 2 December 2011&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;&quot;The Queen of Sheba's Pearls:&quot; Production Notes. Retrieved from thecia.com.au as Rich Text Format on 30 November 2011&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Carole Zucker, ''In The Company of Actors: Reflections on the Craft of Acting'' (London: A &amp; C Black Publishers, 1999), p. 1. Retrieved from Google Books, 3 December 2011&lt;/ref&gt; In 1953, she appeared as an attendant in ''Love's Labours Lost''.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;Regent's Park Open Air Theatre: Our History&quot; in openairtheatre.org/history. Retrieved 30 November 2011&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;&quot;Atkins, Eileen 1934 -  &quot; in ''Contemporary Theatre, Film and Television'' (The Gale Group, Inc., 2004). Retrieved in www.encyclopedia.com on 4 December 2011&lt;/ref&gt; 

Laurence Olivier actually wanted to recruit her at the start of the National Theatre in 1963. She had auditioned for the part of Ophelia and both Olivier and Peter O'Toole had approved but she didn't get the part. 30 years later, she was told that John Dexter and Bill Gaskill did not think her sexy enough, while Olivier and O'Toole did.&lt;ref&gt;Jasper Rees, &quot;Theartsdesk Q&amp;A: Actress Eileen Atkins&quot; (Friday, 24 December 2010) at www.theartsdesk.com. Retrieved, 3 December 2011&lt;/ref&gt;

Among her accomplishments are the creation of two television series - along with [[Jean Marsh]] she created the concept for an original [[television series]], titled ''Behind the Green Baize Door'', which became the award-winning [[ITV]] series ''[[Upstairs, Downstairs]]'' (1971–75). Marsh played maid Rose for the duration of the series but Atkins was unable to accept a part due to stage commitments. The same team was also responsible for the [[BBC]] series ''[[The House of Eliott]]'' (1991–93).

As an actress her television work has included ''[[Three Sisters (1970 Messina film)|Three Sisters]]'' (1970), ''[[A Midsummer Night's Dream]]'' (1971), ''[[The Lady from the Sea]]'' (1974), ''[[Electra]]'' (1974), the villainess &quot;Vanity Fair&quot; in [[Dornford Yates]]' ''She Fell Among Thieves'' (1977), ''[[Sons and Lovers (1981 TV serial)|Sons and Lovers]]'' (1981), ''[[Oliver Twist]]'' (1982),  ''[[Smiley's People]]'' (1982),''[[Titus Andronicus]]'' (1985), ''The Burston Rebellion'' (1985), ''[[A Better Class of Person]]'' (1985), ''[[Roman Holiday (1987 film)|Roman Holiday]]'' (1987), ''[[The Lost Language of Cranes]]'' (1991), ''[[Cold Comfort Farm]]'' (1995), ''[[Talking Heads (plays)|Talking Heads]]'' (1998), ''[[Madame Bovary (2000 film)|Madame Bovary]]'' (2000), ''[[David Copperfield (2000 movie)|David Copperfield]]'' (2000), ''[[Wit (film)|Wit]]'' (2001) and ''[[Bertie and Elizabeth]]'' (2002).

Atkins has regularly returned to the life and work of [[Virginia Woolf]] for professional inspiration. She has played the writer on stage (''[[A Room of One's Own]]'' and ''Vita and Virginia'', winning the [[Drama Desk Award for Outstanding One-Person Show]] for the former) and screen (the 1990 television version of ''Room''); she also provided the screenplay for the 1997 film adaptation of Woolf's novel ''[[Mrs. Dalloway]]'' - starring [[Vanessa Redgrave]] (her stage costar in ''Vita and Virginia'') - and made a cameo appearance in the 2002 film version of [[Michael Cunningham]]'s Woolf-themed novel ''[[The Hours (novel)|The Hours]]''.

Her other films include ''[[I Don't Want to Be Born]]'' (1975), ''[[Equus (film)|Equus]]'' (1977), ''[[The Dresser]]'' (1983), ''[[Wolf (film)|Wolf]]'' (1994), ''[[Jack and Sarah]]'' (1995), ''[[Gosford Park]]'' (2001), ''[[Cold Mountain (film)|Cold Mountain]]'' (2003), ''[[Vanity Fair (2004 film)|Vanity Fair]]'' (2004) and ''[[Ask the Dust (film)|Ask the Dust]]'' (2006).

She has appeared in countless stage productions in and around London, including ''[[A Delicate Balance (play)|A Delicate Balance]]'' (1997), ''[[Cymbeline]]'' (1988), ''[[Honour]]'' (2003), ''[[John Gabriel Borkman]]'' (1996), ''[[Mountain Language]]'' (1988), ''[[The Night of the Iguana]]'' (1992), ''[[The Unexpected Man]]'' (1998) and ''[[The Birthday Party (play)|The Birthday Party]]'' (2005).

Atkins has appeared on Broadway many times as well, scoring four [[Tony Award|Tony]] nominations as Best Actress in a Play. Her debut was in 1966, in [[Frank Marcus]]' ''[[The Killing of Sister George]]''. Next was the Russian play ''[[The Promise (1965 play)|The Promise]]'' (which closed after less than a month in 1967). In 1972's premiere of [[Robert Bolt]]'s ''Vivat! Vivat Regina!'', she played Elizabeth I to [[Claire Bloom]]'s [[Mary, Queen of Scots]]. The [[Scandinavia]]n novelty ''The Night of the Tribades'' barely ran for two weeks in 1977. A bit more successful were 1995's new version of [[Jean Cocteau]]'s ''Indiscretions'' , directed by Sean Mathias (which co-starred [[Kathleen Turner]] and Broadway debutant [[Jude Law]]) and 2004's ''[[The Retreat from Moscow]]'', [[William Nicholson (writer)|William Nicholson]]'s play about a marriage in ruins, with co-stars [[John Lithgow]] and [[Ben Chaplin]].  

In January 2006, she took over the lead role in the Broadway production of [[John Patrick Shanley]]'s Pulitzer-prize winning play ''[[Doubt (play)|Doubt]]'' also featuring [[Ron Eldard]] and [[Jena Malone]]. Her off-Broadway work has included ''[[A Room of One's Own]]'' (1991) and ''[[The Unexpected Man]]'' (2001). 

In the autumn of 2007, she co-starred with [[Judi Dench]] and [[Michael Gambon]] in the BBC1 drama series ''[[Cranford (TV series)|Cranford]]'' playing the central role of Miss Deborah Jenkyns. This performance earned her the 2008 [[BAFTA Award]] for best actress, as well as the [[Emmy Award]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.bafta.org/awards/television/latest-winners-and-nominees,91,BA.html Television Awards 2008 winners] BAFTA web site, accessed 21 August 2011&lt;/ref&gt;

She returned to London's West End in January 2008 to play Mrs Rafi in [[Edward Bond]]'s ''[[The Sea (play)|The Sea]]'' at the [[Theatre Royal, Haymarket]]. The play closed in April 2008. Later in 2008, she appeared at the [[Vaudeville Theatre]] in ''[[The Female of the Species (play)|The Female of the Species]]'', a play which outraged the feminist [[Germaine Greer]] because of its connection with an incident in her life. The play was, however, generally very well received, with ''[[The Sunday Telegraph]]'' reviewer Tim Walker giving it five stars and describing it as &quot;great theatre.&quot;

Atkins was created a [[Order of the British Empire|Commander of the British Empire]] (CBE) in 1990, and raised to Dame Commander ([[Order of the British Empire|DBE]]) in 2001. In 2008 Atkins signed onto the 2009 dark comedy, ''[[Wild Target]]'', with such actors as [[Bill Nighy]], [[Emily Blunt]] and [[Rupert Grint]]. She will be playing Nighy's mother, Louisa.

She recently played the evil Nurse Edwina Kenchington in the [[BBC Two]] sitcom ''[[Psychoville]]'' starring [[Dawn French]]. Atkins replaced [[Vanessa Redgrave]] as Eleanor of Aquitaine in the blockbuster movie ''[[Robin Hood (2010 film)|Robin Hood]]'' starring [[Russell Crowe]], which was released in the UK in May 2010.

Atkins and [[Jean Marsh]], creators of the original 1970s series of ''[[Upstairs Downstairs]]'', are among the cast of a new BBC adaptation, shown over the winter of 2010/11. The new series is set in 1936. Marsh again played Rose while Atkins was cast as the redoubtable Lady Maud Holland. In August 2011, it was revealed that Atkins has decided not to take part in the new series, due to be shown in 2012, because she is reportedly unhappy with the direction the scripts are taking.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/entertainment-arts-14606953 &quot;Dame Eileen Atkins leaves Upstairs Downstairs&quot;] 21 August 2011, BBC News&lt;/ref&gt;

In September 2011, Atkins joined the cast of ITV comedy-drama series ''[[Doc Martin]]'' playing the title character's aunt, Ruth Ellingham.

Atkins will star with [[Matthew Rhys]] in an adaptation of [[Daphne du Maurier]]'s ''[[The Scapegoat (2012 film)|The Scapegoat]]'', to be shown in 2012.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.thestage.co.uk/news/newsstory.php/33868/eileen-atkins-to-star-in-itvs-the-scapegoat&lt;/ref&gt;

Her Royal Shakespeare Company performances include&lt;ref&gt;Royal Shakespeare Company Archive Catalogue in calm.shakespeare.org.uk. Retrieved 30 November 2011&lt;/ref&gt;:
1. unnamed parts in ''Cymbeline'' at the Shakespeare Memorial Theatre (Stratford-upon-Avon, 2 July 1957 press night)
2. unnamed parts in ''The Tempest'' at the Shakespeare Memorial Theatre (Stratford-upon-Avon, 13 August 1957 press night)
3. as Magdalen in ''The Vigil'' at the Shakespeare Memorial Theatre (Stratford-upon-Avon, 21 October 1957 press night)
4. unnamed parts in ''The Tempest'' at the Theatre Royal (Drury Lane, London, 5 December 1957 press night)
5. unnamed parts in ''Romeo and Juliet'' at the Shakespeare Memorial Theatre (Stratford-upon-Avon, 8 April 1958 press night)
6. as Lady in ''Hamlet'' at the Shakespeare Memorial Theatre (Stratford-upon-Avon, 3 June 1958 press night)
7. as Diana in ''Pericles'' at the Shakespeare Memorial Theatre (Stratford-upon-Avon, 8 July 1958 press night)
8. unnamed parts in ''Much Ado About Nothing'' at the Shakespeare Memorial Theatre (Stratford-upon-Avon, 26 August 1958 press night)
9. unnamed parts in ''Romeo and Juliet'' and as Lady in ''Hamlet'' on Tour (12 December 1958 press night, ran until 5 January 1959&lt;ref&gt;&quot;Theatricalia: Eileen Atkins&quot; in theatricalia.com. Retrieved 30 November 2011&lt;/ref&gt;)
10. as Suzanna Andler in ''Suzanna Andler'' at the Aldwych Theatre (London, 7 March 1973 press night)
11. as Rosalind in ''As You Like It'' at the Shakespeare Memorial Theatre (Stratford-upon-Avon, 12 June 1973 press night)
12. as Nell in ''Passion Play'' at the Aldwych Theatre (London, 13 January 1981 press night)
13. as the Woman in ''The Unexpected Man'' at the Pit (London, 15 April 1998 press night)
14. as the Woman in ''The Unexpected Man'' at the Duchess Theatre (London, 15 June 1998 press night)

In 1961 the Shakespeare Memorial Theatre Company became the Royal Shakespeare Company.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;Rob Wilton Theatricalia: Shakespeare Memorial Theatre, Stratford-upon-Avon&quot; in www.phyllis.demon.co.uk. Retrieved 30 November 2011&lt;/ref&gt;

When she was at Stratford for six weeks, coming in halfway through the season, the actress who was playing Audrey in ''As You Like It'' (Dame Peggy Ashcroft was playing Rosalind) was taken to a hospital for six weeks. Her understudy was also hospitalized the night before the performance. So she stayed up all night learning Audrey and made sure she was in the theatre the next day. The following day she went in as Audrey; and &quot;from then on they accepted me at Stratford.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Carole Zucker, ''In The Company of Actors: Reflections on the Craft of Acting'' (London: A &amp; C Black Publishers, 1999), p. 6. Retrieved in Google Books on 2 December 2011&lt;/ref&gt; ''As You Like It'' with Dame Peggy Ashcroft as Rosalind was performed at the Shakespeare Memorial Theatre in Stratford-upon-Avon in 1957 (press night: 2 April 1957).&lt;ref&gt;Royal Shakespeare Company Archive Catalogue in calm.shakespeare.org.uk. Retrieved on 2 December 2011&lt;/ref&gt; 

Her National Theatre performances include&lt;ref&gt;The National Theatre Archive Catalogue in worthing.nationaltheatre.org.uk. Retrieved 30 November 2011&lt;/ref&gt;: 
1. as Honor (title role) in ''Honour'' at the Cottesloe Theatre (21 February 2003 opening night)
2. as Reader in ''Hermione Lee on Virginia Woolf'' at the Cottesloe Theatre (18 October 1996 opening night)
3. as Elderly Woman in ''Mountain Language'' at the Lyttelton Theatre (17 October 1988 opening night)
4. as Mrs. Gunhild Borkman in ''John Gabriel Borkman'' at the Lyttelton Theatre (15 July 1996 opening night)
5. as Hannah Jelkes in ''The Night of the Iguana'' at the Lyttelton Theatre (31 January 1992 opening night)
6. as Queen wife to Cymbeline in ''Cymbeline'' at the Cottesloe Theatre (5 October 1988 opening night)
7. as Paulina wife to Antigonus in ''The Winter's Tale'' at the Cottesloe Theatre (5 February 1988 opening night)
8. as Hesione Hushabye in ''Heartbreak House'' at the Old Vic (20 February 1975 opening night)

She was in the 1961-1962 season of The Old Vic appearing in:&lt;ref&gt;&quot;Rob Wilton Theatricalia: Old Vic 1956-1963 Programmes etc.&quot; in www.phyllis.demon.co.uk. Retrieved 30 November 2011&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;&quot;The Queen of Sheba's Pearls: Production Notes&quot; retrieved in thecia.com.au in Rich Text Format on 30 November 2011&lt;/ref&gt;:
1. as Viola in ''Twelfth Night'' (2 October 1961)
2. as the Queen in ''Richard III'' (6 March 1962)
3. as Miranda in ''The Tempest'' (29 May 1962)

Also appeared as Beattie in Arnold Wesker's ''Roots'' at the Bristol Old Vic in 1960-1961 and ''Julius Caesar'' for the Old Vic Tour in 1961-1962.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;Atkins, Eileen 1934 -   &quot; in ''Contemporary Theatre, Film and Television'' (The Gale Group, Inc., 2004). Retrieved in www.encyclopedia.com on 4 December 2011&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;&quot;Theatricalia: Eileen Atkins&quot; in theatricalia.com. Retrieved 30 November 2011&lt;/ref&gt; With Paul Daneman, she was on the cover page of the April 1962 issue of ''Plays and Players'' magazine for her performance in ''Richard III''.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;Rob Wilton Theatricalia: Plays and Players Magazines: 1960s&quot; in www.phyllis.demon.co.uk. Retrieved 5 December 2011&lt;/ref&gt; She appeared in the Old Vic's Repertoire Leaflets of February-April 1962 and April-May 1962.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;Rob Wilton Theatricalia: Old Vic 1956-1963 Programmes etc&quot; in www.phyllis.demon.co.uk. Retrieved 4 December 2011.&lt;/ref&gt; Scenes from ''Twelfth Night'' at the Old Vic were featured in the March 1962 issue of ''Theatre World'' magazine. She was also on the cover page of the September 1965 issue of ''Theatre World'' magazine for ''The Killing of Sister George''.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;Rob Wilton Theatricalia: Theatre World magazines: 1960s&quot; in www.phyllis.demon.co.uk. Retrieved 5 December 2011&lt;/ref&gt;  She was also the girl in ''The Square'' at Bromley Theatre in 1961.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;Atkins, Eileen 1934 -  &quot; in ''Contemporary Theatre, Film and Television'' (The Gale Group, Inc., 2004). Retrieved in www.encyclopedia.com on 4 December 2011&lt;/ref&gt;

She was Juliette in ''Exit The King'' at the Edinburgh Festival and later at the Royal Court with Alec Guinness.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;Atkins, Eileen 1934 -  &quot; in ''Contemporary Theatre, Film and Television'' (The Gale Group, Inc., 2004). Retrieved in www.encyclopedia.com on 4 December 2011&lt;/ref&gt; Scenes from this performance were featured in the November 1963 issue of ''Plays and Players'' magazine (with Alec Guinness on the cover page).&lt;ref&gt;&quot;Other Works of Alec Guinness&quot; in www.imdb.com. Retrieved 3 December 2011&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;&quot;Rob Wilton Theatricalia: Plays and Players Magazines: 1960s&quot; in www.phyllis.demon.co.uk. Retrieved 2 December 2011&lt;/ref&gt;. For the Prospect Theatre Company in July 1963, she appeared as Lady Brute in Vanburgh's ''The Provok'd Wife'' with Toby Robertson directing at the Vaudeville Theatre.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;Ian McKellen Stage: Prospect, Prospect Theatre Company&quot; in www.mckellen.com. Retrieved 4 December 2011&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;&quot;Rob Wilton Theatricalia: Classic Plays: 1963&quot; in www.phyllis.demon.co.uk. Retrieved 5 December 2011&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;&quot;Atkins, Eileen 1934 -  &quot; in ''Contemporary Theatre, Film and Television'' (The Gale Group, Inc., 2004). Retrieved in www.encyclopedia.com on 4 December 2011&lt;/ref&gt; She was also Joan Middleton, the wife, in the first presentation of David Storey's ''The Restoration of Arnold Middleton'' at the Royal Court in 1966/1967.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;Atkins, Eileen 1934 -   &quot; in ''Contemporary Theatre, Film and Television'' (The Gale Group, Inc., 2004). Retrieved in www.encyclopedia.com on 4 December 2011&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Phyllis Hartnoll and Peter Found, &quot;Atkins, Eileen&quot; in ''The Concise Oxford Companion to the Theatre'' (1996). Retrieved in www.encyclopedia.com on 4 December 2011&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;John McGrath, ''Naked Thoughts That Roam About: Reflections on Theatre'', ed. Nadine Holdsworth (London: Nick Hern Books Limited, 2002), p. 25. Retrieved in Google Books on 4 December 2011&lt;/ref&gt;

Other notable stage performances include:&lt;ref&gt;&quot;Theatricalia: Eileen Atkins&quot; in theatricalia.com. Retrieved 30 November 2011&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;&quot;Atkins, Eileen 1934-   &quot; in ''Contemporary Theatre, Film and Television'' (The Gale Group, Inc., 2004). Retrieved in www.encyclopedia.com on 4 December 2011&lt;/ref&gt;:
1. as Eileen Midway in ''Semi-Detached'' at the Saville Theatre, London (5 December 1962 press night)
2. as Alice &quot;Childie&quot; McNaught in ''The Killing of Sister George'' at the Bristol Old Vic (1964-1965); this was also performed in 1965 with Beryl Reid at the Duke of York's and in 1966 with Beryl Reid again at St. Martin's&lt;ref&gt;&quot;Rob Wilton Theatricalia: Other Plays: 1960-1969&quot; in www.phyllis.demon.co.uk. Retrieved 5 December 2011&lt;/ref&gt;
3. as Queen Elizabeth I in ''Vivat!Vivat Regina!'' at the Piccadilly Theatre (8 October 1970 press night)
4. as St. Joan in ''St. Joan'' at the Old Vic Theatre (for the Prospect Theatre Co., 1977) - also for Prospect Production in 1977 at the Liverpool Playhouse&lt;ref&gt;&quot;Rob Wilton Theatricalia: Other Plays: 1970-1979&quot; in www.phyllis.demon.co.uk. Retrieved 5 December 2011&lt;/ref&gt;
5. as St. Joan in ''St. Joan'' at the Old Vic, Theatre Royal (Bath) and Bristol Hippodrome (1976-1978)
6. as Jennet Jourdemayne in ''The Lady's Not For Burning'', as Viola in ''Twelfth Night'' and in ''Ivanov'' all at the Old Vic (1978-1979)
7. as Mrs. Hitchcock in ''Serjeant Musgrave's Dance'' at the Old Vic (1983-1984)
8. as Medea (title role) in ''Medea'' at the Young Vic Theatre (1985-1986)
9. as Sally Kershaw in ''Exclusive'' (1988-1989) and as Virginia Woolf in ''A Room of One's Own'' (1990-1991) at the Theatre Royal (Bath)
10. as Virginia Woolf in ''Vita and Virginia'' for the Chichester Festival Theatre at the Minerva Theatre in Chichester (August-September 1992)
11. as Virginia Woolf in ''Vita and Virginia'' at the Ambassador's Theatre (London, 1993-1994)
12. in ''A Delicate Balance'' (with Dame Maggie Smith) at the Theatre Royal in Haymarket London) and at the Theatre Royal in Bath (1997-1998)
13. in ''Harold Pinter: A Celebration'' at the Olivier Theatre for the National Theatre (7 June 2009) 

She played Virginia Woolf in ''A Room of One's Own'' (1989) for which she won much acclaim. She toured the US with the show. She later taped a production for UK television at Girton College, Cambridge (the venue of Ms. Woolf's original lecture). She was Virginia Woolf again in 1992 in ''Vita and Virginia'' opposite Penelope Wilton (as Vita) for the UK stage and Vanessa Redgrave for the US stage.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;Eileen Atkins&quot; in www.filmbug.com. Retrieved 30 November 2011&lt;/ref&gt; Atkins actually wrote ''Vita and Virginia''.&lt;ref&gt;Carole Zucker, In ''The Company of Actors: Reflections on the Craft of Acting'' (London: A &amp; C Black Publishers, 1999), p. 1. Retrieved from Google Books, 3 December 2011&lt;/ref&gt;

Played Agnes in ''A Delicate Balance'', written by Edward Albee and directed by Anthony Page at the Haymarket Theatre from 21 October 1997 to 4 April 1988. Maggie Smith played her drunkard sister, Claire.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;Albemarle of London Archive Page for - A Delicate Balance&quot; at www.albemarle-london.com. Retrieved 3 December 2011&lt;/ref&gt;   

She also performed in the 1968 Chichester Festival Theatre production of ''The Cocktail Party'' as Celia Coplestone with Alec Guiness as co-performer and director and in Robert Bolt's ''Vivat!Vivat Regina!''with Sarah Miles at the Piccadilly in 1970 and 1971.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;Rob Wilton Theatricalia: Chichester Festival Theatre&quot; in www.phyllis.demon.co.uk. Retrieved 30 November 2011&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;&quot;Rob Wilton Theatricalia: Other Plays: 1970-1979&quot; in www.phyllis.demon.co.uk. Retrieved 5 December 2011&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;&quot;Atkins, Eileen 1934 -   &quot; in ''Contemporary Theatre, Film and Television'' (The Gale Group, Inc., 2004). Retrieved in www.encyclopedia.com on 4 December 2011&lt;/ref&gt; On 28 February 1965, she appeared as Mrs. Shannon in the first performance of Peter Gill's ''The Sleepers' Den'' at the Royal Court Theatre.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;Rachel Halliburton, &quot;The Sleepers Den&quot; in ''London Evening Standard'' (2 July 2001). Retrieved at www.thisislondon.co.uk on 1 December 2011&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;&quot;The Sleepers' Den by Peter Gill&quot; in ds.dial.pipex.com. Retrieved 4 December 2011&lt;/ref&gt; She also appeared in a Chichester Festival Theatre production of T.S. Elliot's ''Murder In The Cathedral'' in 1968 with Alec Guinness as co-actor and director.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;Other Works of Alec Guinness&quot; in www.imdb.com. Retrieved 3 December 2011&lt;/ref&gt; 

Her Broadway performances are:&lt;ref&gt;&quot;Eileen Atkins&quot; at the Internet Broadway Database, www.ibdb.com. Retrieved 30 November 2011&lt;/ref&gt;
1. as Alice &quot;Childie&quot; McNaught in ''The Killing of Sister George'' (5 October 1966 - 1 April 1967)
2. as Lika in ''The Promise'' (14 November - 2 December 1967)
3. as Elizabeth I in ''Vivat!Vivat Regina!'' (20 January - 29 April 1972)
4. as Marie Caroline David in ''The Night of the Tribades'' (13-22 October 1977)
5. as Leonie in ''Indiscretions'' (27 April - 4 November 1995)
6. as Alice in ''The Retreat From Moscow'' (23 October 2003 - 29 February 2004)
7. as Sister Aloysius in ''Doubt'' (10 January 2006 - ?)

She was made a Dame Commander of the British Empire (DBE) on her 67th birthday, 16 June 2001.&lt;ref&gt;BBC News World Edition, &quot;Dudley Moore celebrates CBE&quot; (Saturday, 16 June 2001) in news.bbc.co.uk. Retrieved 2 December 2011&lt;/ref&gt; On 23 June 2009 she was conferred a honorary Doctor of Letters degree by Oxford University.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;University of Oxford: Honorary Degrees&quot; in www.ox.ac.uk. Retrieved 4 December 2011&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;''University of Oxford Annual Review 2009/10'' (p. 23) in PDF format. Retrieved from www.ox.ac.uk, 4 December 2011&lt;/ref&gt;

==Personal life==
Atkins was married to [[Julian Glover]] in 1957; they divorced in 1966. She has been married to her current husband, Bill Shepherd, since 2 February 1978. Atkins was propositioned by [[Colin Farrell]] on location in 2004, shortly before she turned 70; she said the incident helped her pass that milestone far more easily than she otherwise would have expected.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.mirror.co.uk/news/tm_objectid=15478508&amp;method=full&amp;siteid=94762&amp;headline=night-colin-farrell-tried-to-seduce-me-name_page.html|title=The night Colin Farrell tried to seduce me|Cummins, Fiona|publisher=Daily Mirror|date=2005-05-05|accessdate=2008-06-12}}&lt;/ref&gt; ''[[The Oldie]]'' magazine awarded her the '''Refusenik'' of the Year' award for this incident.

Her father died aged 86 and her mother aged 94.&lt;ref&gt;Jasper Rees, &quot;Theartdesk Q&amp;A: Actress Eileen Atkins&quot; (Friday, 24 December 2010) at www.theartdesk.com. Retrieved, 3 December 2011&lt;/ref&gt;

Julian Glover and Eileen Atkins divorced in September 1968. A day after his divorce, Glover married actress Isla Blair. They are still married to date.&lt;ref&gt;Frances Hardy, &quot;I stalked my lover's wife!&quot; (22 July 2011) in www.dailymail.co.uk. Retrieved 30 November 2011.&lt;/ref&gt;

Is a life-long insomniac and takes sleeping pills every night. Was diagnosed with breast cancer in August 1995 but has apparently recovered.&lt;ref&gt;Mary Riddell, &quot;The Atkins method&quot; in ''The Daily Mail'' (7 May 2005). Retrieved in www.encyclopedia.com on 4 December 2011 &lt;/ref&gt;

==Selected filmography==
* ''[[Nelly's Version]]'' (1983)
* ''[[Gosford Park]]'' (2001)
* ''[[Vanity Fair (2004 film)|Vanity Fair]]'' (2004 film)
* ''[[Cranford]]'' (2006)
* ''[[Evening]]'' (2007)
* ''[[Last Chance Harvey]]'' (2008)

==References==
{{reflist}}

==External links==
*{{IMDb name|0040586}}
*{{IBDB name|30312}}
*[http://www.broadway.com/gen/Buzz_Story.aspx?ci=525231 Eileen Atkins interviewed by Beth Stevens about performing in Doubt on Broadway]
*[http://www.bris.ac.uk/theatrecollection/search/people_sub_plays_all?forename=Eileen&amp;surname=ATKINS&amp;job=Actor&amp;pid=1612&amp;x=17&amp;y=8  Performance details listed at the Theatre Collection archive, University of Bristol]
Zucker, Carole. ''In The Company of Actors: Reflections on the Craft of Acting''. &quot;Eileen Atkins,&quot; pp. 1-16. London: A &amp; C Black, 1999. 
{{Template group
|title = Awards for Eileen Atkins
|list =
{{British Academy Television Award for Best Actress 2000-present}}
{{DramaDesk PlayOutstandingFeaturedActress 1975-1999}}
{{DramaDesk One-Person Show 1984–2000}}
{{EmmyAward MiniseriesSupportingActress 2001-2025}}
{{OlivierAward PlayActress 1985–2000}}
{{OlivierAward PlayActress 2001–2025}}
}}
{{ShearsmithandPemberton}}


{{Persondata &lt;!-- Metadata: see [[Wikipedia:Persondata]]. --&gt;
| NAME              =Atkins, Eileen
| ALTERNATIVE NAMES =
| SHORT DESCRIPTION =
| DATE OF BIRTH     =16 June 1934
| PLACE OF BIRTH    =[[London|London, England]]
| DATE OF DEATH     =
| PLACE OF DEATH    =
}}
{{DEFAULTSORT:Atkins, Eileen}}
[[Category:1934 births]]
[[Category:Living people]]
[[Category:Actresses awarded British damehoods]]
[[Category:Alumni of the Guildhall School of Music and Drama]]
[[Category:BAFTA winners (people)]]
[[Category:Dames Commander of the Order of the British Empire]]
[[Category:Drama Desk Award winners]]
[[Category:Emmy Award winners]]
[[Category:English film actors]]
[[Category:English stage actors]]
[[Category:English television actors]]
[[Category:Actors from London]]
[[Category:Laurence Olivier Award winners]]
[[Category:Outstanding Performance by a Cast in a Motion Picture Screen Actors Guild Award winners]]
[[Category:Royal National Theatre Company members]]
[[Category:Royal Shakespeare Company members]]
[[Category:Shakespearean actors]]
[[Category:People educated at The Latymer School]]

[[de:Eileen Atkins]]
[[it:Eileen Atkins]]
[[he:איילין אטקינס]]
[[nl:Eileen Atkins]]
[[ja:アイリーン・アトキンス]]
[[sv:Eileen Atkins]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
