<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="157596" ns="0" title="FlightGear"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Infobox software
| name                   = FlightGear
| logo                   = [[File:FlightGear logo.png|100px|FlightGear's icon]]
| screenshot             =&lt;!-- Deleted image removed:  [[File:Flightgear-2.4.0-ec145.jpg|250px]] --&gt;
| caption                = A Eurocopter [[Eurocopter EC 130|EC-130]] in 2.4.0
| collapsible            =
| author                 = David Murr, Curt Olson, Michael Basler, Eric Korpela &lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url = http://www.flightgear.org/proposal-3.0.1 | title = FlightGear — Flight Simulator}}&lt;/ref&gt;
| developer              = FlightGear Developers &amp; Contributors
| released               = July 17, 1997
| latest release version = 2.4.0
| latest release date    = {{release date and age|2011|8|17}}
| latest preview version =
| latest preview date    =
| frequently updated     =
| programming language   = [[C++]]&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url = https://www.ohloh.net/p/flightgear/analyses/latest | publisher = Ohloh | title = FlightGear source anylases}}&lt;/ref&gt;
| operating system       = [[32-bit]] &amp; [[64-bit]] Windows&lt;br/&gt;Linux&lt;br/&gt;Mac OS X&lt;br/&gt;FreeBSD&lt;br/&gt;Solaris or IRIX
| platform               = [[Cross-platform]]
| language               = English
| status                 = Active (1996-)
| genre                  = [[Flight simulator]]
| license                = [[GNU General Public License]]
| website                = http://www.flightgear.org/
}}
'''FlightGear Flight Simulator''' (often shortened to FlightGear or FGFS) is a free, open-source multi-platform [[flight simulator]] developed by the FlightGear project since 1997.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | title = FlightGear takes off | first = Joe | last = Barr | date = 4 December 2006 | url = http://www.linux.com/articles/58579 | accessdate = 2007-06-25 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

David Murr started the project on April 8, 1996. The project had its first release in 1997 and continued in development, the most recent release being version 2.4.0 in August 2011.&lt;ref name=&quot;FAQ&quot;&gt;{{citation | publisher = Flight Gear | title = Flight Pro Sim | url = http://www.flightgear.org/flightprosim.html}}&lt;/ref&gt; It has specific builds for a variety of [[operating system]]s including [[Microsoft Windows]], [[Mac OS X]], [[Linux]], [[IRIX]], and [[Solaris (operating system)| Solaris]].
FlightGear code is released under the terms of the [[GNU General Public License]], thus being [[free software]].

The commercial products '''Flight Pro Sim''', '''Pro Flight Simulator''', and others, are direct copies of FlightGear.&lt;ref name=flightprosim /&gt;

==History==
{{Main|History of FlightGear}}

FlightGear started as an online proposal in 1996 by David Murr. He proposed a new flight simulator developed by volunteers over the internet. The flight simulator was created using custom 3D graphics code.&lt;ref&gt;[http://wiki.flightgear.org/index.php/FlightGear_History FlightGear History]&lt;/ref&gt;

FlightGear incorporated other open-source resources, including the LaRCsim flight model from NASA, and freely available elevation data. The first working binaries, using OpenGL for 3D graphic code, came out in 1997. Enthusiastic development of newer versions for several years resulted in progressively more stable and advanced versions. By 2001, the team was releasing new beta versions regularly, and by 2005, the maturity of software lead to more widespread reviews, and increased popularity. 2007 marked a formal transition out of beta development with the release of version 1.0.0, ten years after FlightGear's first release in 1997.

In 2008, version 1.9.0 of FlightGear included a major change from [[PLIB]] to [[OpenSceneGraph]], which caused the temporary loss of some features like 3D clouds and shadows, while newly added features, such as particles, imparted another degree of realism to the simulation.

==Software==
===Requirements===
FlightGear requires a reasonable hardware accelerated 3D card with [[OpenGL]] drivers to achieve smooth frame rates. Using only software rendering, FlightGear typically has frame rates of about several frames per second.{{Citation needed|date=February 2010}} With a 3D accelerated card you can expect much higher. On a 2–3&amp;nbsp;GHz CPU, frame rates in excess of 60 frame/s are reasonable to expect in most situations. The actual frame rate changes with the scene complexity (which changes from area to area and changes as your view direction changes) and your hardware. FlightGear had support for [[3dfx]] cards, but this was dropped as hardware requirements increased.

===Simulation engines===
The simulation engine in FlightGear is called [[SimGear]]. It is used both as an end-user application and in academic and research environments, for the development and pursuit of flight simulation ideas.

This customizability of FlightGear is illustrated by the wide range of [[aircraft]] models that are available in FlightGear, from [[Glider aircraft|Glider]]s to [[helicopter]]s, and from [[airliner]]s to fighter jets. These aircraft models have been contributed by many different people.

Currently only one terrain engine is used, TerraGear. Weather effects include 3D clouds, lighting effects, and time of day.

{{Quotation | Another huge advantage of FlightGear is that it is completely open source — it has a rich set of existing external interfaces, and most of the major configuration can be done with standard XML-based text files. We make no attempts to obfuscate or hide our internals. This is big win for people using FlightGear as an academic or research platform, or for those that want to interface it to their own home-built cockpits.&lt;ref name = &quot;LDC&quot;&gt;{{cite web | title = Flying the Open Skies with FlightGear| first = Howard | last = Wen | date = 11 December 2003 | publisher = O'Reilly Network  | url = http://www.linuxdevcenter.com/pub/a/linux/2003/12/11/flightgear.html | accessdate = 2008-03-04 }}&lt;/ref&gt; |Curtis L. Olson | ''O'Reilly Network'', 2003}}

===Flight Dynamics Models===
Flight Dynamics Models (FDM) are how the flight for an aircraft is simulated in the program. FlightGear uses a variety of internally written and imported flight model projects. Any aircraft must be programmed to use one of these models. Currently FlightGear is the only graphical flight simulator for which all the FDM are used. FlightGear aircraft use one of three main data models [[JSBSim]], YAsim, or UIUC as of version 0.9.10. UIUC and YASim were developed specifically for FlightGear.
Early versions of FlightGear used a FDM based on LaRCsim by [[NASA]], which was then replaced with more flexible FDM. Specialized FDM, such as lighter than air aircraft can be custom written, or external FDM sources can be used.

* [[JSBSim]] - the default flight dynamics model software since 2000. Started by  Jon Berndt.&lt;ref name = &quot;LDC&quot; /&gt;
* YASim - an FDM using different calculation methods. Introduced starting in 0.7.9 in 2002.  Developed by Andy Ross.&lt;ref name = &quot;LDC&quot;/&gt;  It is presently the only FlightGear FDM that provides simulation for [[rotorcraft]], a feature developed by Maik Justus.
* UIUC - another included FDM, developed by the UIUC Applied Aerodynamics Group at [[University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign]], also made use of LaRCsim.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | title = Aircraft Dynamics Models for Use with FlightGear | publisher = UIUC Applied Aerodynamics Group at University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign | url = http://www.ae.uiuc.edu/m-selig/apasim/Aircraft-uiuc.html | accessdate = 2007-06-26 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

===FlightGear dependencies===
Unlike proprietary software titles, the main output of the project is simply the release of a collection of software source code. To turn it into a usable program it must be compiled for a given platform. The software libraries used to create FlightGear have varied over time. The main one is [[SimGear]], which is the underlying simulation engine for FlightGear. TerraGear is not a dependency, but simply a name for the default terrain data program in FlightGear. [[OpenAL]] is used for sound/audio software, including support for SDL (since 0.9.5).&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | title = FlightGear v0.95 Released | publisher = LockerGnome | url = http://www.lockergnome.com/nexus/news/2004/08/03/flightgear-v095-released/ | accessdate = 2007-06-24 }}&lt;/ref&gt; [[PLIB]] is used for hardware support routines, formerly used for sound support also which was taken over by OpenAL. [[OpenGL]] is used for its integrated 3D graphics routines, and other hardware acceleration (namely DirectX) is not supported. [[OpenSceneGraph]] is also integrated into FlightGear. Finally, [[Simple DirectMedia Layer]] is a software library which is also used. Some of the dependencies vary depending on which platform the code is being compiled for. FlightGear users must either compile the code themselves, or find a third party to release a binary, if it is not among the ones available from the project.

===Networking and multi-display===
Several [[computer network|networking]] options allow FlightGear to communicate with other instances of FlightGear. A [[multiplayer]] [[protocol (computing)|protocol]] is available for using FlightGear on a [[local network]] in a multi aircraft environment. This could be used for [[Aerobatics|formation flight]] or [[control tower]] simulation. Multiplayer was soon expanded to allow playing over the internet. Other features include a [[Google maps]] based moving map that allows users to observe where other players are.&lt;ref name = &quot;FSM&quot;&gt;{{cite web | url = http://www.freesoftwaremagazine.com/articles/flightgear | title = Flying high with FlightGear | publisher = Free Software Magazine | issue = 14 | year = 2006}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Several instances of FlightGear can be synchronized to allow for a [[multi-monitor]] environment. If all instances are running at the same frame rate consistently, it is possible to get good and tight synchronization between displays.

===Additional software===
[[Image:Fgfs-and-photo.png|thumb|259px|A comparison between a FlightGear 1.0 screenshot in 2008 and a photo of San Francisco Airport]]

There are programs that are either integrated into FlightGear (dependencies) or perform a function with it. Some of these are included in the release of FlightGear for a specific platform but made by the project, while others are independently distributed but are hosted by the FlightGear project.

One major additional software is the actual interface for launching an executable of FlightGear. For most of its early life FlightGear was only run through command line interfaces. However, the FlightGear Launch Control has been included with the ''FG launcher'' front-end since 0.9.3 in 2003. ''KFreeFlight'' is a launcher/front-end for [[KDE]]. ''FGTools'' is an alternative windows launcher front-end. ''FGKicker'' is a [[GTK+]] based front-end.

Other significant programs include editors and projects for Terrain Data. ''Atlas'' is a chart/map support for FlightGear; ''Kelpie Flight Planner'' is a [[Java (programming language)|Java]] based flight planner for FlightGear. ''FlightGear Scenery Designer'' is a FlightGear scenery editor for working with terrain data. The ''World Custom Scenery Project'' is a project coordinating custom scenery efforts. ''Taxidraw'' is an editor for airport runways and taxiways. ''FGCom'' is a project for live VOIP simulating Radio traffic to air traffic control and other aircraft in Flightgear which now has its own GUI FGCOMgui.  FGCom uses the open source Asterix server.

==FlightGear code vs. binaries==
FlightGear is mostly written in the [[C++|C++ programming language]].&lt;ref&gt;{{citation | url = https://www.ohloh.net/p/flightgear/analyses/latest | publisher = Ohloh | title = FlightGear source analyses}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The actual source code is distributed via GIT and dates apply to standardized and stable release of code, which is then compiled into a executable program. Both the development, the code releases, and the binaries are all created by those who volunteer their time to FlightGear. To create a runnable program the code must be compiled, which requires several specific libraries (see section of [[#FlightGear dependencies]]), including some general ones and, in some cases some platform specific ones. However, since this too difficult for most mainstream users, other contributors will work to make binaries available for a specific platform and operating system. These packages vary in their stability, performance, dependencies, and how up to date they are with the code base. For example, some older binaries work on [[Mac OS 9]] but newer releases require specific Mac OS X versions.

For example, by late 2007 the latest code release was 0.9.11-pre1 (pre-release) and 0.9.10 (final). However, the actual binaries available vary significantly.  Examples of actual binaries available a year after the release of the 0.9.10 code release:

*Win32 has ~138 Mb package (v0.9.10) (For Windows 98, 2000, ME, 32-bit XP)
*Linux- pre-built packages for specific [[Linux distributions]]
**[[Slackware]] package (v0.9.10), [[Fedora (operating system)|Fedora Core]] [2,3,4] packages (v0.9.10), [[Pardus (operating system)|Pardus]] (v0.9.10), [[Debian]] (v0.9.9)
*[[Solaris (operating system)|Solaris]] packages either for it running on either [[SPARC]] or [[x86]] processors.
** SPARC (v0.9.8),  x86 (v0.9.9)
*[[Silicon Graphics]] [[IRIX]];at the time had SGI binaries for (v0.9.9)
*[[Mac OS X]] has a version for Mac OS X 10.4 (v0.9.10) and for Mac OS X 10.3 (v0.9.9)
*[[FreeBSD]] [[FreeBSD Ports Collection|Ports Collection]] (v0.9.10)&lt;ref&gt;{{citation | publisher = Fresh ports | url = http://www.freshports.org/games/flightgear/ | title = Flight Gear}}&lt;/ref&gt;
By early 2008, many versions for 1.0.0 became available although older releases remained for several aforementioned platforms. Increased hardware requirements for 1.0.0 reduced performance on older systems.
*Win-32 has a ~172 Mb package (v1.0.00) (For Windows 98, 2000, ME, XP, Vista)
*Linux- pre-built packages for specific [[Linux distributions]] included (v1.0.00) for [[Slackware]]  and [[Debian]]
*Mac OS X 10.4 (v1.0.00)
By early 2010, version 2.0.0 was released and binary packages became available for various environments by December 2010 were as follows:
*Win32 has a ~292 Mb package (v2.0.0) (For Windows 98, 2000, ME, XP, Vista and 7)
*Linux- pre-built packages for specific [[Linux distributions]] included (v2.0.0) for [[Slackware]]  and [[Debian]]
*Mac OS X 10.4 (v1.9.1)
*FreeBSD Ports

==Critical reception==
[[Image:FlightGear - 1903 Wright Flyer.jpg|thumb|250px|Wright Flyer in 0.9.9, which uses the UIUC FDM]]

Although not developed or typically analyzed solely as a game in the traditional sense, FlightGear has nevertheless undergone reviews in a number of online and offline publications, and received positive reviews as a flight simulator game.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | publisher = Flight Sim | url = http://www.flightsim.com/main/review/fltgear.htm | title = Review}}&lt;/ref&gt; FlightGear 1.0.0 was noted as being impressive for a game over a decade in the making, with a wide variety of aircraft and features.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | publisher = Tech Woo| url = http://techwoo.com/flightgear-100-released/ | title = FlighGear 1.00 released}}&lt;/ref&gt;

''FlightGear'' 0.9.10 received many reviews, being highlighted as an accurate simulation but requiring patience and some pre-game work.&lt;ref name = &quot;FSM&quot; /&gt; PC Magazine noted how it is designed to be easy to add new aircraft and scenery.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | title = FlightGear 0.9.10 | first = Tim | last = Smith | date = 1 September 2006 | publisher = PC Magazine (UK) | url = http://www.pcmag.co.uk/computeractive/downloads/2163376/flightgear | accessdate = 2007-06-29}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&quot;Flightgear&quot; 1.9.1 was also chosen by users of Softonic as the best free game.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | publisher = Softonic | url = http://en.softonic.com/awards2009 | title = The Best Programs of 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Models and aircraft==
FlightGear started out with an aircraft included in NASA's LaRCsim, a [[Ryan Navion|Navion]], which was replaced by a Cessna 172 by 2000. UIUC as well as JSBsim development brought several more aircraft with them, as did the development of YASim which have since become the main FDM used in FG.&lt;ref name = &quot;Manual&quot;&gt;''The Flight Gear Manual'' Version .9, April 2006&lt;/ref&gt; As of version 2.4.0 more than 400 aircraft are provided (some independently from the project), in over 550 unique liveries based on real life aircraft.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | title = FlightGear Liveries | url = http://liveries.flightgear.org | accessdate = September 21, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===1.0.0 and earlier aircraft===
[[Image:FlightGear - SeaHawk.jpg|thumb|250px|Hawker Sea Hawk in 0.9.9]]

The basic installer is limited to about 15 aircraft, with several dozen more official aircraft at varying states of development for download. The CD/DVD version includes all official aircraft and terrain data, though all the same material can also be downloaded for free. Non official aircraft from third-party sources also exist, but are not included here. Also included are a number of custom buildings, especially around San Francisco; a [[Nimitz class aircraft carrier]] is included as well (which aircraft can land on). In addition, several of the developmental UIUC aircraft developed in the late 1990s were still included but were not all maintained.

All official aircraft for 0.9.10, with flight data model type and cockpit type listed for some such as found on the 0.9.10 CD release of FlightGear. Some aircraft are FDM only, having no 3D visual model. Third party aircraft that do not have a [[GPL]] compatible license are excluded from the list but may be used with FlightGear.  Aircraft in 0.9.10 installer are noted with a *, and ** for the 1.0 installer. New or heavily re-worked aircraft up to 1.0 public release, including some that came out with the 0.9.11-pre1 FlightGear (pre-release version) as well as 9.10 aircraft. Many aircraft that have not been updated no longer work, such as ones before .7.x/.8.x/.9.x as well as a number in the later releases that were not maintained to the current version depending on the model and its dependencies. Includes from about 0.7.0 to 0.9.10 and 1.0.0.

==Applications and Usages==
{{Expand section|date=February 2010}}
FlightGear has been used in a range of projects in academia and industry (including [[NASA]]) and even home-built cockpits.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url= http://www.usenix.org/events/usenix04/tech/sigs/full_papers/perry/perry_html/Applications_Simulator.html |title= Applications for the Simulator|accessdate=2007-09-03}}&lt;/ref&gt;

A complete list is available at the [http://wiki.flightgear.org/index.php/Professional_and_educational_FlightGear_users Flightgear wiki].

==Commercial redistribution==
FlightGear Flight Simulator version 1.9.1 has been actively marketed over the [[Internet]] under several aliases and product names, including but not limited to ''Flight Pro Sim'', ''Pro Flight Simulator'', ''Earth Flight Sim'', ''Real Flight Simulator'' and ''Flight Simulator Plus''.&lt;ref name= flightprosim&gt;{{cite web| url= http://www.flightgear.org/flightprosim.html| publisher =FlightGear | title = FlightProSim statement| accessdate= 2010-12-04}}&lt;/ref&gt; Usually, $47 [[USD]] is charged for the main program and $67 USD is charged for the full World Scenery Package.  Numerous ads and review articles that are very similar in wording can also be found scattered across the Internet posted by &quot;affiliates.&quot;  A number of [[Facebook]] pages for these products have also been posted.

Because FlightGear is licensed under the [[GNU General Public License]], this is technically fully legal; however, the morals of these operations are questionable, as many customers who have purchased these products are very dissatisfied with what they receive and feel they have been scammed.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web| publisher = Source Forge | url = http://sourceforge.net/mailarchive/message.php?msg_id=26673022 | title =A post | first = Minton | last = Brooks | work = FlightGear mailing list| accessdate= 2010-12-14}}&lt;/ref&gt; Additionally, an investigation by a number of FlightGear developers has found virtually no difference between the source code made available by the FlightProSim, etc. websites and the official version of FlightGear 1.9.1.  In fact, FlightProSim, Pro Flight Simulator, etc. almost never recognize that their products are deriratives of FlightGear Flight Simulator, use images from the FlightGear wiki, and are not involved in any way with the FlightGear project.

The FlightGear developer team made an official statement/FAQ about the situation.&lt;ref name=&quot;FAQ&quot; /&gt;

{| class=&quot;wikitable&quot; style=&quot;width:100%;&quot;
|-
| ''FlightGear is an open-source flight simulator that was created in 1996. It is released under the GNU General Public License v2, and as such, it is free to use, modify and distribute with few restrictions. It has been developed with the collaboration of a large number of individuals over the last 14+ years. The complete FlightGear application and source code can be always downloaded for free from http://www.flightgear.org.'' 

''Flight Pro Sim is a commercial product that simply rebrands FlightGear. Investigation by a number of the FlightGear developers has found no difference between this and the FlightGear v1.9.1 release other than a change of name. Flight Pro Sim is in no way endorsed or supported by the core FlightGear development team.''
|}

==External links==
{{Commons category}}
* {{citation | url = http://www.flightgear.org/ | title = FlightGear | archivedate = 2010-12-23 | archiveurl = http://web.archive.org/web/*/http://www.flightgear.org}}.
* {{citation | url = http://wiki.flightgear.org/ | publisher = FlightGear | title = Wiki}}.
* {{citation | url = http://sourceforge.net/projects/flightgear/ | publisher = Sourceforge | title = FlightGear}}.
* {{citation | url = http://gitorious.org/fg/fgdata/ | title = Flightgear data | publisher = Gitorious}}.
* {{citation | url = http://gitorious.org/fg/flightgear/ | title = Flightgear source | publisher = Gitorious}}.
* {{citation | url = http://www.flightgear.org/download/aircraft-v2-4/ | title = Flightgear planes}}.
* {{citation | url = http://fgfs.i-net.hu/ | title = FlightGear}}.
* {{citation | url = http://macflightgear.sourceforge.net/home/ | title = FlightGear for Mac | publisher = Sourceforge}}.
* {{citation | url = http://www.flightgear.org/flightprosim.html | title = About FlightProSim, Flight Simulator Plus, ProFlightSimulator and EarthFlightSim | publisher = Flight gear}}.
* ''[http://www.flightsimulatorplus.org Flight Simulator Plus]''

==See also==
{{Portal box|Free software|Video games|Aviation}}
*[[Microsoft Flight Simulator]]
*[[X-Plane (simulator)]]
{{-}}

==References==
{{Reflist|2}}

{{open source video games}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Flightgear}}
[[Category:1997 software]]
[[Category:1997 video games]]
[[Category:2007 software]]
[[Category:Cross-platform software]]
[[Category:Flight simulation video games]]
[[Category:Free software programmed in C++]]
[[Category:General flight simulators]]
[[Category:Linux games]]
[[Category:Free, open source video games]]

[[ca:FlightGear]]
[[da:FlightGear]]
[[de:FlightGear]]
[[es:FlightGear]]
[[fr:FlightGear]]
[[it:FlightGear]]
[[lt:FlightGear]]
[[nl:FlightGear]]
[[ja:FlightGear]]
[[pl:FlightGear]]
[[pt:FlightGear]]
[[ru:FlightGear]]
[[fi:FlightGear]]
[[sv:FlightGear]]
[[zh:FlightGear]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
