<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="1577861" ns="0" title="Xgl"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">'''Xgl''' was an [[X Window System|X server]] architecture designed to take advantage of modern graphics cards via their [[OpenGL]] drivers, layered on top of [[OpenGL]] via [[Glitz (software)|glitz]]. It supported [[hardware acceleration]] of all X, OpenGL and [[XVideo]] applications and graphical effects by a [[compositing window manager]] such as [[Compiz]] or [[Beryl (window manager)|Beryl]]. The project was started by [[David Reveman]] of [[Novell]] and first released on January 2, 2006. It was removed&lt;ref&gt;[http://gitweb.freedesktop.org/?p=xorg/xserver.git;a=commit;h=d15b3790307053587df8daed1936ff6923881b63 XGL Version Info]&lt;/ref&gt; from the X.org server in favor of [[AIGLX]] on June 12, 2008.

== History==
Xgl was originally developed on public mailing lists, but for a long time, until January 2, 2006 most &lt;ref&gt;[http://lists.freedesktop.org/archives/xorg/2006-February/013306.html ALGIX, Nvidia, XGL and metacity]&lt;/ref&gt; development of Xgl was done behind closed doors. On that day the source to Xgl was re-opened to the public,&lt;ref&gt;[http://lists.freedesktop.org/archives/xorg/2006-January/011922.html Latest XGL Code]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://lwn.net/Articles/166081/ Novell's XGL Code posted]&lt;/ref&gt; and included in [[freedesktop.org]], along with major restructuring to allow a wider range of supported display drivers. X server backends used by Xgl include '''Xglx''' and '''Xegl'''. In February 2006 the server gained wide publicity after a public display where the [[Novell]] desktop team demonstrated a desktop using Xgl with several visual effects such as [[transparency (graphic)|translucent]] [[window (computing)|window]]s and a rotating 3D desktop.&lt;ref&gt;[http://linux.slashdot.org/linux/06/02/08/0624253.shtml Novell Public Release XGL Code]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://xgl.opensuse.org/ SUSE XGL]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.opensuse.org/Xgl OpenSUSE XGL resources]&lt;/ref&gt; 
The effects had first been implemented in a composite manager called [[glxcompmgr]] (not to be confused with xcompmgr), now deprecated because several effects could not be adequately implemented without tighter interaction between the window manager and the composite manager. As a solution David Reveman developed [[Compiz]], the first proper OpenGL [[compositing window manager]] for the X Window System. Later, in September 2006, the [[Beryl (window manager)|Beryl]] [[compositing window manager]] was released as a fork of the original Compiz. Compiz and Beryl have merged back in April 2007, which resulted in the development of [[Compiz Fusion]].

== Backends ==
OpenGL does not specify how to initialize a display and manipulate drawing contexts.  Instead these operations are handled by an API specific to the native windowing system.  So far there are two different backend approaches to solving this initialization problem. Most likely the majority of each backend will contain the same code and the differences will primarily be in the initialization portions of the servers.

===Xglx===
''Xglx'' was the first backend implemented for this architecture.  It requires an already existing X server to run on top of and uses [[GLX]] to create an OpenGL window which Xgl then uses, similar to [[Xnest]]. This mode is only intended to be used for development in the future, as it is redundant to require an X server to run Xgl on top of. 

At XDevConf 2006 (the 2006 X development conference), [[NVIDIA]] made a presentation arguing that this is the wrong direction to take because the layered server abstracts features of the cards away.  This makes driver specific capabilities like support for 3D glasses and dual monitor support much more difficult.&lt;ref&gt;http://download.nvidia.com/developer/presentations/2006/xdevconf/compositing-with-current-framework.pdf&lt;/ref&gt;

However, delegating initialization to an existing X server allows the developers to immediately focus on server functionality rather than dedicating substantial time to specifics of interfacing with numerous video hardware.
At the moment, Xglx does not officially support multiple monitors, although it has been achieved on Ubuntu Dapper / ATI / NVIDIA (twinview).

===Xegl ===
''Xegl'' was said{{by whom|date=May 2009}} to be the future of Xgl and a long term goal of X server development.&lt;ref&gt;http://jonsmirl.googlepages.com/graphics.html&lt;/ref&gt;  It shares much of the drawing code with the Xglx server, but the initialization of the OpenGL drawable and context management is handled by the EGL API developed by Khronos (EGL is a window system-independent equivalent to the GLX and WGL APIs, which respectively enable OpenGL support in X and Microsoft Windows).  The current implementation uses [[Mesa 3D|Mesa-solo]] to provide OpenGL rendering directly to the [[Linux framebuffer]] or [[Direct Rendering Infrastructure|DRI]] to the graphics hardware.  {{As of|2007|alt=As of July 2007}} Xegl can only be run using [[Radeon R200]] graphics hardware and development is currently stalled.&lt;ref&gt;http://gitweb.freedesktop.org/?p=xorg/xserver.git;a=history;h=master;hb=master;f=hw/xgl/egl/xegl.c&lt;/ref&gt;  It is likely that it will remain so until the Xglx server has proven itself and the closed source drivers add support for the EGL API, when it should be a transparent replacement for the nested Xglx server.

== Rationale ==
Structuring all rendering on top of OpenGL could potentially simplify video driver development. It removes the artificial separation of [[2D computer graphics|2D]] and [[3D computer graphics|3D]] [[hardware acceleration|acceleration]].  This is advantageous as 2D operations are frequently unaccelerated (which is counterintuitive, since 2D is a subset of 3D). {{Or|date=April 2010}}

It also removes all driver-dependent code from the X server itself, and allows for accelerated [[Compositing|Composite]] and [[XRender|Render]] operations independent of the graphics driver.

== Competitors ==
Hardware acceleration of 2D drawing operations has been a common feature of many window systems (including X11) for many years.  The novelty of Xgl and similar systems is the use of APIs specifically developed for 3D rendering for accelerating 2D desktop operations.  Prior to the adoption of anti-aliased drawing by X11, the use of 3D rendering APIs for 2D desktop rendering was undesirable because such APIs did not make the pixel accurate rendering guarantees that are part of the original X11 protocol definition.

Hardware-accelerated OpenGL window and desktop rendering, limited to using OpenGL for texture composition, has been in use in Mac OS X, in a technology called [[Quartz Compositor|Quartz Extreme]], since [[Mac OS X v10.2]]. [[Quartz 2D|Quartz 2D Extreme]] is an enhancement of this feature and more directly comparable to Xgl.  Like Xgl, Quartz 2D Extreme brings OpenGL acceleration to all 2D drawing operations (not just desktop compositing) and ships with [[Mac OS X v10.4]], but is disabled by default pending a formal declaration of production-readiness.  Core Animation is the extension of this effort for Leopard ([[Mac OS X v10.5]]).

Several desktop interfaces based on 3D APIs have been developed, more recently [[OpenCroquet]] and Sun Microsystems' [[Project Looking Glass]] [http://www.sun.com/software/looking_glass/details.xml]; these take advantage of 3D acceleration for software built within their own framework, but do not appear to accelerate existing 2D desktop applications rendered within their environment (often via mechanisms like [[VNC]]).

[[Microsoft]] developed a similar technology based on [[DirectX]], named the [[Desktop Window Manager|DWM]], as part of its [[Windows Vista]] operating system. This technology was first shown publicly at Microsoft's October [[2003]] PDC.

== Availability==

{{As of|2006|alt=As of May 2006}}, the Xgl [[X Window System protocols and architecture|X Server]] (and related components including the Compiz compositing manager and associated graphical config tools) ships as a non-default in one major Linux distribution, [[SUSE Linux distributions|SUSE]] 10.1, and is included in [[Frugalware|Frugalware Linux]] or [[SUSE Linux Enterprise Desktop]] 10. Xgl can be set up fairly easily for [[Ubuntu (operating system)|Ubuntu]] 6.06 LTS (Dapper Drake) and 6.10 (Edgy Eft) and for [[Freespire]] with binary packages from unofficial [[software repository|repositories]]. Xgl is also available as an overlayed package in [[Gentoo Linux]], and as a PKGBUILD for [[Arch Linux]].  

The latest [[Mandriva Linux]] 2007 includes official packages to run [[Compiz]], using Xgl and [[AIGLX]]. Mandriva provides '''drak3d''', a tool to configure a 3D Desktop in two clicks.

[[Ubuntu (operating system)|Ubuntu]] 6.10 &quot;Edgy Eft&quot; and later use [[AIGLX]], not Xgl, by default.

Xgl was removed from X11R7.5 in 2009 due to its being an unmaintained server variant.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.x.org/wiki/Releases/7.5 X.org Foundation Releases/7.5&lt;/ref&gt;

== See also ==
*[[X Window System]]
*[[AIGLX]]
*[[VirtualGL]]
*[[OpenGL]]
*[[Compiz]]
*[[Beryl (window manager)|Beryl]]

== References ==
{{Reflist|2}}

== External links ==
{{commons|Compiz}}
* [http://www.freedesktop.org/wiki/Software/Xgl Xgl]
* [http://www.freedesktop.org/wiki/Xegl Xegl]
* [http://lists.freedesktop.org/pipermail/xorg/2004-November/004358.html Announcement of Xgl on the xorg mailing list]
* [http://www.freesoftwaremagazine.com/articles/accelerated_x Accelerated X flame wars!—Maybe not] — an article about the differences between AIGLX and Xgl
* [http://www.khronos.org/egl/ EGL specifications]
* [http://jonsmirl.googlepages.com/graphics.html Article: The State of Linux Graphics] — overview of various approaches to replace the current X server

=== HOWTO, forums, support ===
* [http://en.opensuse.org/Xgl openSUSE wiki for Xgl]
* Xgl HowTos: [http://www.novell.com/coolsolutions/feature/17174.html Novell], [https://wiki.ubuntu.com/CompositeManager/Xgl Ubuntu], [http://sonique54.free.fr/xgl/xgl.htm Debian Etch], [http://gentoo-wiki.com/HOWTO_XGL Gentoo Linux]
* [http://nicofo.tuxfamily.org/dotclear/index.php/2007/02/23/25-automatic-installation-of-xgl-compiz-and-beryl-on-fedora How-to install XGL on '''Fedora''' 5/6/7] — Xgl Beryl and Compiz on Fedora

=== Screenshots, screencast, demo video ===
* [http://xgl.opensuse.org/ Novell Xgl announcement including video and screenshots]
* Novell Open Audio podcast [http://www.novell.com/podcast/Detailpage.jsp?id=55 Xgl with David Reveman] — 7 April 2006, discusses the basics and future of Xgl and Compiz
* [http://www.linuxedge.org/?q=node/55 Videos of Xgl on SUSE Linux Enterprise Desktop 10]
* [http://www.linuxedge.org/?q=node/58 Slides, screenshots and a video with more effects]
** [http://www.freedesktop.org/~davidr/xgl-demo1.xvid.avi the video demonstrating Compiz on Xgl]
* [http://youtube.com/watch?v=lawkc3jH3ws Another Xgl Video]
* [http://www.dailymotion.com/video/xb7sz_mandriva-linux-2007-3d-desktop Mandriva 3D Video]

{{XWinSys}}

[[Category:Freedesktop.org]]
[[Category:X Window extensions]]
[[Category:OpenGL]]

[[ca:Xgl]]
[[cs:Xgl]]
[[de:Xgl]]
[[es:Xgl]]
[[fr:Xgl]]
[[ko:Xgl]]
[[it:Xgl]]
[[he:Xgl]]
[[hu:Xgl]]
[[ja:Xgl]]
[[pl:XGL]]
[[pt:Xgl]]
[[ru:Xgl]]
[[sk:Xgl]]
[[sv:XGL]]
[[tr:Xgl]]
[[uk:Xgl]]
[[zh:Xgl]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
