<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="15777230" ns="0" title="Horsemen (2009 film)"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Infobox film
| name           = Horsemen
| image          = Horsemenposter.jpg
| image_size     = 215px
| alt            = 
| caption        = Theatrical release poster
| director       = [[Jonas Åkerlund]]
| producer       = [[Michael Bay]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Bradley Fuller|Brad Fuller]]&lt;br /&gt;Andrew Form
| writer         = [[David Callaham]]
| starring       = [[Dennis Quaid]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Zhang Ziyi]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Lou Taylor Pucci]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Clifton Collins Jr.]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Patrick Fugit]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Peter Stormare]] 
| music          = [[Jan A.P. Kaczmarek]]
| cinematography = Eric Broms
| editing        = Jim May&lt;br /&gt;Todd E. Miller
| studio         = [[Mandate Pictures]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Platinum Dunes]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Ted Field|Radar Pictures]]
| distributor    = [[Lions Gate Entertainment|Lionsgate]]
| released       = {{Film date|2009|3|6}}
| runtime        = 90 minutes
| country        = {{Film US}}
| language       = English 
| budget         = 
| gross          = $2,405,815 (foreign only)&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.boxofficemojo.com/movies/?id=horsemen.htm|title=The Horsemen (2009)|work=[[Box Office Mojo]]|publisher=[[Amazon.com]]|accessdate=2010-12-2}}&lt;/ref&gt;
}}
'''''Horsemen''''' is a 2009 American [[Thriller (genre)|thriller film]] directed by [[Jonas Åkerlund]] and starring [[Dennis Quaid]] and [[Zhang Ziyi]]. It follows Aidan Breslin ([[Dennis Quaid]]) a bitter and emotionally distracted detective who has grown apart from his two sons after the death of his devoted wife. While investigating a series of murders he discovers a terrifying link between himself and the suspects that seem to be based on the Biblical prophecies concerning the [[Four Horsemen of the Apocalypse]]: War, Famine, Pestilence and Death. The film was shot in [[Toronto]], [[Winnipeg]] and [[Chicago]], and was released on March 6, 2009.

==Plot==
An older man and his dog are out hunting, when they discover a serving tray on a stand in the middle of a frozen lake. He notices the words &quot;Come and See&quot; painted on several trees as he lifts the lid.

Detective Aidan Breslin ([[Dennis Quaid]]) is a [[widower]] who has become emotionally distanced from his two sons, Alex ([[Lou Taylor Pucci]]) and Sean ([[Liam James]]), following the death of his wife three years prior to the film's events. Due to his former dental forensics expertise, Aidan receives a call regarding the contents of the tray, where it is revealed that it contained human teeth. After analyzing the teeth, Breslin is able to match them to a man who had been reported missing. Aidan is once again called to investigate the bizarre murder of a woman named Mrs. Spitz, who was discovered hanging in her bedroom, eerily displayed and strung up on a series of hooks connected to a rig; the words &quot;Come and See&quot; displayed prominently on the walls. According to her autopsy report, she drowned in her own blood due to a precise stabbing. They also discover that Mrs. Spitz had been pregnant and the [[fetus]] was removed. Aidan speculates that there were four attackers and that they had used a camera to record the murder. After leaving the crime-scene, Breslin comforts one of the Spitz's three daughters, their adopted Asian daughter Kristen ([[Zhang Ziyi]]), reassuring her that he will do his best to solve the crime.

The next murder shares the same [[Modus operandi|M.O.]] with the Spitz murder; the similar hook contraption leads Breslin to a local tattoo parlor. There, he is informed that the owner constructed four devices in total. Yet another murder occurs, but this time no hook rig was involved and the message only appears on three of the room's walls. While Aidan reviews the evidence at his home, Sean stumbles on one of the photographs. Sean's insights point Breslin to the Bible, where he discovers that these killings are patterned after the Four Horsemen of the Apocalypse, with each room corresponding to a Horsemen; the &quot;Come and See&quot; message pertains to the lifting of the veil and the coming of the Apocalypse. When Kristen contacts Aidan unexpectedly, he goes to meet with her, and during their conversation Kristen produces the missing fetus, confessing to the murder. During her interrogation, Aidan discovers the darker side of Kristen's personality, one similar to the Horseman War.

Meanwhile, a [[Homosexuality|gay]] young man, Cory ([[Patrick Fugit]]), has a confrontation with his [[Homophobia|homophobic]] brother, Taylor ([[Eric Balfour]]). As Taylor drunkenly stumbles out to his car, Cory is accosted by another man in the parking lot. In response, Cory stabs the man, who survives the attack and later provides the police with Cory's description. The precision of the stab wound leads Aidan to assume that it was done by a Horseman (Death). Elsewhere, Taylor awakens to find himself hooked onto a rig with his eyes fixed open. Cory appears wielding a [[bone saw]], then proceeds to try to cut out his own heart, killing himself in the process. Later, Breslin goes over to Kristen's house where he and his partner, Stingray ([[Clifton Collins, Jr.]]), discover the video recording from the murders as well as some polaroids of Kristen posing sexually with Mr. Spitz ([[Peter Stormare]]). When Breslin confronts Kristen in jail, she claims to have been sexually abused for years and the murder of Mrs. Spitz served as punishment for her abuse. Following the interview, Breslin has Mr. Spitz arrested. 

Breslin, convinced that there may be another victim, asks Kristen if she represented the Horseman War and that the unrigged victim was Famine. She confirms this, but refuses to relinquish any information about their leader. Breslin comes to the conclusion that due to the nature of the first murder, he was meant to be assigned to the case all along, and becomes concerned that his family will be targeted next. Breslin asks Stingray to go on ahead and check his house. At the Breslin home, Stingray is attacked and knocked out. Aiden arrives later and enters Alex's room for the first time in three years. To his horror, everything in the room is white or painted white: the color of the Horseman Conquest or Righteousness (the leader). A clue points him to the Metropolitan Theatre, where Aidan first met his wife. When he arrives, he is knocked unconscious; when he comes to, he finds himself handcuffed to a seat as Alex dangles over the stage on the final hook rig. Alex starts bleeding to death, as he gives Breslin a speech regarding the Horsemen's emotional detachment from their families. As Alex succumbs to his injuries, Breslin rips his handcuffs off the seating and fires his gun to detach the rigging from the ceiling. Alex awakens as his father holds him.

At the Breslin home, Sean wakes up from a bad dream as Breslin comforts him. When he asks where Alex is, Breslin reassures him that Alex will be okay, his fate ultimately unknown.

==Cast==
* [[Dennis Quaid]] as Aidan Breslin, a widower detective trying to solve the &quot;Horsemen&quot; case&lt;ref name=&quot;Giddy-up&quot;&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.variety.com/article/VR1117953038.html?categoryid=1236&amp;cs=1|author=Michael Fleming|title=Thesp pair giddy-up for 'Horsemen'|publisher=[[Variety (magazine)|Variety]]|date=2007-10-31|accessdate=2008-02-15}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[Zhang Ziyi]]&lt;ref name=&quot;Giddy-up&quot;/&gt; as Kristen
* [[Clifton Collins, Jr.]]&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.variety.com/article/VR1117958226.html?categoryid=28&amp;cs=1|author=Stacy Dodd|title=Clifton Collins Jr.|publisher=[[Variety (magazine)|Variety]]|date=2007-01-28|accessdate=2008-02-15}}&lt;/ref&gt; as Stingray
* [[Peter Stormare]] as Mr. Spitz
* [[Eric Balfour]] as Taylor
* [[Patrick Fugit]] as Cory
* [[Chelcie Ross]] as Krupa
* [[Lou Taylor Pucci]] as Alex Breslin 
* [[Liam James]] as Sean Breslin 
* [[Deborah Odell]] as Ms. Bradshaw
* David Dastmalchian as Terrence
* [[Barry Shabaka Henley]] as Tuck
* [[Paul Dooley]] as Father Whiteleather
* [[Neal McDonough]] (''[[deleted scene]]s'') as Police Chief Krupa

==References==
{{reflist}}

==External links==
* {{imdb title|0892767|Horsemen}}
* {{amg movie|388946|Horsemen}}
* {{mojo title|horsemen|Horsemen}}
* {{rotten-tomatoes|1200863-horesmen|Horsemen}}
* {{metacritic film|horsemen|Horsemen}}

{{Platinum Dunes}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Horsemen}}
[[Category:2009 films]]
[[Category:2000s thriller films]]
[[Category:American films]]
[[Category:American LGBT-related films]]
[[Category:American mystery films]]
[[Category:American thriller films]]
[[Category:English-language films]]
[[Category:Films directed by Jonas Åkerlund]]
[[Category:Neo-noir]]
[[Category:Police detective films]]
[[Category:Psychological thriller films]]
[[Category:Platinum Dunes films]]
[[Category:Lions Gate Entertainment films]]

[[de:Horsemen]]
[[fr:Les Cavaliers de l'Apocalypse]]
[[it:The Horsemen]]
[[nl:Horsemen]]
[[ja:ホースメン (2009年の映画)]]
[[pl:Horsemen - jeźdźcy Apokalipsy]]
[[pt:The Horsemen]]
[[ru:Всадники (фильм, 2009)]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
