<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="1581616" ns="0" title="File synchronization"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Refimprove|date=July 2009}}
'''File synchronization''' (or '''syncing''') in computing is the process of ensuring that [[computer file]]s in two or more locations are updated via certain rules.{{Citation needed|date=July 2009}}

In ''one-way file synchronization'', also called [[mirror (computing)|mirroring]], updated files are copied from a 'source' location to one or more 'target' locations, but no files are copied back to the source location. In ''two-way file synchronization'', updated files are copied in both directions, usually with the purpose of keeping the two locations identical to each other. In this article, the term synchronization refers exclusively to ''two-way file synchronization''.

File synchronization is commonly used for home backups on external hard drives or updating for transport on [[USB flash drives]]. The automatic process prevents copying already identical files and thus can be faster and save much time versus a manual copy, and is less error prone.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite paper |author=A. Tridgell |authorlink=Andrew Tridgell |title=Efficient algorithms for sorting and synchronization |url=http://samba.org/~tridge/phd_thesis.pdf |date=February 1999 |version=PhD thesis |publisher=The Australian National University}}&lt;/ref&gt; However this suffers from the limit that the synchronized files must physically fit in the portable storage device. Synchronization software that only keeps a list of files and the changed files eliminates this problem (e.g. the &quot;snapshot&quot; feature in [[Beyond Compare]] or the &quot;package&quot; feature in [[Synchronize It]]!). It is especially useful for mobile workers, or others that work on multiple computers. It is possible to synchronize multiple locations by synchronizing them one pair at a time.

==Common features==

* [[Encryption]] for [[Internet security|security]], especially when synchronizing across the [[Internet]].
* [[data compression|Compressing]] any data sent across a network.
* ''Conflict detection'' where a file has been modified on both sources, as opposed to where it has only been modified on one. Undetected conflicts can lead to overwriting copies of the file with the most recent version, causing data loss. For conflict detection, the synchronization software needs to keep a database of the synchronized files. Distributed conflict detection can be achieved by [[version vector]]s.
* ''Open Files Support'' ensures data integrity when copying data or application files that are in-use or database files that are exclusively [[file locking|locked]]. 
* Specific support for using an intermediate storage device, such as a removable flash disc, to synchronize two machines. Most synchronizing programs can be used in this way, but providing specific support for this can reduce the amount of data stored on a device.
* The ability to preview any changes before they are made.
* The ability to view differences in individual files.

==See also==

* [[Comparison of file synchronization software]]
* [[Comparison of online backup services]]
* [[Data synchronization]]
* [[File comparison]]
* [[Mirror (computing)]]
* [[Backup software]]
* [[List of backup software]]
* [[Remote backup service]]
* [[Shared file access]]

== References ==
{{reflist}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:File synchronization}}
[[Category:Data synchronization|*]]
[[Category:Storage software]]

[[fr:Synchronisation de fichiers]]
[[nl:Bestandssynchronisatie]]
[[ja:ファイル同期]]
[[pt:Sincronização de ficheiros]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
