<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="158208" ns="0" title="Afrika Korps"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Refimprove|date=September 2008}}
{{Redirect|DAK}}
{{Infobox military unit
|unit_name = ''Deutsches Afrikakorps''
|image =
|caption =
|dates = 12 February 1941 – 13 May 1943
|country = {{flagicon|Nazi Germany}} [[Nazi Germany]]
|branch = [[Wehrmacht Heer]]
|type = [[Expeditionary warfare|Expeditionary Force]]
|role =
|size = [[Corps]]
|command_structure =
|garrison = [[Tripoli]], [[Italian Libya]]
|past_commanders =
|ceremonial_chief =
|notable_commanders = [[Erwin Rommel]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Ludwig Crüwell]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Walther Nehring]]
|identification_symbol = [[File:DAK.svg|150px]]
|identification_symbol_2 = Seal of the ''Deutsches Afrikakorps''
|nickname =
|patron =
|motto = ''Ritterlich im Kriege, wachsam für den Frieden''&lt;br /&gt;(&quot;Chivalrous in War, Vigilant for Peace&quot;)
|colors = Yellow, Brown
|march =
|mascot =
|battles = [[World War II]]
* [[North African Campaign]]
** [[Siege of Tobruk]]
** [[Battle of Gazala]]
** [[Second Battle of El Alamein|Battle of El Alamein]]
|anniversaries =
|decorations =
|battle_honors =
}}

The '''German Africa Corps''' ({{lang-de|Deutsches Afrikakorps}}, DAK {{Audio|De-Deutsches_Afrikakorps-pronunciation.ogg|&lt;small&gt;listen}}&lt;/small&gt;), or the '''''Afrika Korps''''' as it was popularly called, was the German [[Expeditionary warfare|expeditionary force]] in [[Libya]] and [[Tunisia]] during the [[North African Campaign]] of [[World War II]]. The reputation of the ''Afrika Korps'' is synonymous with that of its first commander [[Erwin Rommel]], who later commanded the &lt;ref&gt;''With Rommel in the Desert'' by Heinz Werner Schmidt&lt;/ref&gt; [[Panzer Army Africa]] which evolved into the German-Italian ''Panzer'' Army (''Deutsch-Italienische Panzerarmee'') and [[Army Group Africa]], all of which ''Afrika Korps'' was a distinct and principal component. Throughout the [[North African campaign]], the ''Afrika Korps'' fought against Allied forces until its surrender in May 1943.

==Organization==
The ''Afrika Korps'' was derived and formed upon [[Adolf Hitler]]'s personal choice of [[Erwin Rommel]] to its command on 12 February 1941 (Rommel himself landed on African soil in Libya on 14 February 1941 to begin leading his forces that would be brought into action).[[File:Rommel with his aides.jpg|200px|[[Erwin Rommel]] in North Africa|right|thumb]] The German Armed Forces High Command (''[[Oberkommando der Wehrmacht]]'', OKW) and Army High Command or (''[[Oberkommando des Heeres]]'', OKH) had decided to send a &quot;blocking force&quot; (''Sperrverband'') to [[Libya]] to support the Italian army. The Italian army group had been routed by Commonwealth Force's counter-offensive led by the British Eighth Army, in [[Operation Compass|Operation ''Compass'']]. The German &quot;blocking force&quot;, commanded by Rommel, at first consisted of only the 5./leichte &quot;''Afrika''&quot; ''[[Panzer]]'' [[Regiment]], which was quickly cobbled together from the second regiment of the 3./''Panzer'' Division and various other small units attached for water treatment and medical care. These elements were organized into the [[German 5th Light Division|5th Light Division]] when they arrived in Africa from 10 February – 12 March 1941. In late April and into May, the 5th Light Division was joined by transference of the various elements constituting the [[German 15th Panzer Division|15th ''Panzer'' Division]] from Italy, though it did not completely arrive until after Rommel had made a counter-offensive and re-taken most of [[Cyrenaica]] and then subsequently gone back over to the defensive. At this time, the ''Afrikakorps'' consisted of the two divisions plus various smaller supporting units, and was officially subordinated to the Italian chain of command in Africa (though Rommel had conducted his offensive without any authorization).

On 15 August 1941, the German 5./leichte &quot;''Afrika''&quot; Division was redesignated [[German 21st Panzer Division|21st ''Panzer'' Division]] (commonly written as 21./PD), still attached to the enlarged entity still known as the ''Afrikakorps''.

During the summer of 1941, the OKW and OKH invested more command structure in Africa by creating a new headquarters called [[German Panzer Group Africa|''Panzer'' Group Africa]] (''Panzergruppe Afrika''). On 15 August, ''Panzer'' Group Africa was activated with Rommel in command, and command of the ''Afrikakorps'' was turned over to [[Ludwig Crüwell]]. The ''Panzer'' Group controlled the ''Afrikakorps'' plus some additional German units that were sent to Africa, as well as two corps of Italian units. (A German &quot;group&quot; was approximately the equivalent of an [[army]] in other militaries, and in fact, ''Panzer'' Group Africa was redesignated as [[German Panzer Army Africa|''Panzer'' Army Africa]] (''Panzerarmee Afrika'') on 30 January 1942.)

After the defeat at [[El Alamein]] and the [[Allied]] invasion in Morocco and Algeria [[Operation Torch|Operation ''Torch'']], the OKW once more upgraded its presence in Africa by creating the [[German XC Army Corps|XC Army Corps]] in [[Tunisia]] on 19 November 1942, and then creating a new [[German Fifth Panzer Army|5th Panzer Army]] headquarters there as well on 8 December, under the command of Colonel-General [[Hans-Jürgen von Arnim]].

On February 23, 1943, ''Panzer'' Army Africa—now called the German-Italian ''Panzer'' Army—was redesignated as the [[Italian First Army|Italian 1st Army]] and put under the command of Italian general [[Giovanni Messe]], while Rommel was placed in command of a new [[Army Group Africa]] (''Heeresgruppe Afrika''), created to control both the Italian 1st Army and the 5th ''Panzer'' Army. The remnants of the ''Afrikakorps'' and other surviving units of the 1st Italian Army retreated into Tunisia. Command of the Army Group was turned over to von Arnim in March. On 13 May, remnants of the ''Afrikakorps'' surrendered, along with all other remaining Axis forces in North Africa.

==Composition and terminology==
[[File:Bundesarchiv Bild 101I-783-0142-22, Nordafrika, Soldat mit Panzerbüchse.jpg|thumb|German soldier in [[North Africa]] during [[World War II]]]]

&quot;''Afrika Korps''&quot; is derived from the original German name properly written as one word. Strictly speaking, the term refers to the original formation which, although not dissolved, became part of the ever-expanding German and Italian presence in North Africa for its February 1941–May 1943 role in the North African Campaign. However, it is sometimes used by the news media and veteran Allied soldiers as a name for all the German units in North Africa. Some notable attached units include the [[15th Panzer Division]], [[21st Panzer Division]], ''Afrika'' ''zbV'' (''zur besonderen Verwendung'', &quot;special purpose&quot;) Division, which was created as an [[infantry]] division and slowly upgraded to a fully motorized division, and then redesignated as the [[German 90th Light Afrika Division|90th Light ''Afrika'' Division]]; the [[German 164th Light Afrika Division|164th Light ''Afrika'' Division]], the 999 Light &quot;''Afrika''&quot; Division, also the 334th Infantry division; and the ''Luftwaffenjäger''-Brigade 1 or ''Fallschirmjäger''-Ramcke Brigade [[Ramcke Parachute Brigade]] (named after its commander [[Hermann-Bernhard Ramcke]]). There were also eight Italian divisions (out of the 10 Italian Divisions in North Africa) under Rommel's command in [[German Panzer Army Afrika|''Panzer'' Army ''Afrika'']], including two armored divisions, two motorized divisions, three infantry divisions, and the ''[[Folgore Parachute Brigade|Folgore]]'' parachute division. The army was supported by a number of smaller units from both the German and Italian armed forces.

The designation &quot;Light&quot; (German: ''Leicht'') did not refer to a standardized table of organization and equipment (TOE) for the various German divisions that bore that designation.

German unit organizations were based on tables of organization, (''Kriegsstärkenachweisungen'', or KStN). Every unit in the German Army raised had one, and all orders raising units indicated the corresponding KStN number and date which applied to them. For instance, the 5./''leichte'' &quot;''Afrika''&quot; or 5th Light &quot;''Africa''&quot; had an organizational structure that was missing specific elements to make it a complete ''Panzer'' &quot;Division&quot;, as did its late April to May 1941 arriving &quot;full complement&quot; partner division in Africa, the 15./Panzer Division. The 5./le. &quot;Africa&quot; Division eventually became at least partially expanded into the 21./PD or 21st Panzer Division. It was given German unit elements that were already on the ground in North Africa and some replacement equipment to meet the prescribed full ''Panzer'' Division KStN constraints (except for the Motorcycle Battalion component, which was never complete) and then renamed in August 1941. As the entire ''Afrikakorps'' organization was restructured and even renamed in August 1941, the nomenclature of ''Afrikakorps'' lasted less than six months. The famous force, with the short-lived name ''Afrikakorps'', became a major German component of ''Panzer'' Army Africa; ''Panzerarmee Afrika'', which evolved into the German-Italian ''Panzer'' Army (''Deutsch-Italienische Panzerarmee'') and then to Army Group Africa (''Heeresgruppe Afrika'') in the 27 months of the campaign for this force.{{Citation needed|date=September 2011}}

Additional German forces were sent to Africa and became components of the ''Panzer'' Army Africa, ''Panzerarmee Afrika''. Examples such as the 164./le. &quot;Africa&quot; or 164th Light ''Afrika'' Division was at first only a partially-motorized infantry division, and actually never had any tanks at all, only armored cars and reconnaissance vehicles. Various German divisions in Africa occasionally reorganized or re-equipped without a change of name, or conversely were redesignated with a new name without any substantial reorganization. None of the German Armies actually fielded for service in North Africa completely met the service KStNs directed for their completion because of battle losses, sinkings across the Mediterranenan while in transit and the tremendous wear on the vehicles.

===Ramcke Brigade===
The ''Luftwaffenjäger''-Brigade 1, known more commonly as the [[Ramcke Parachute Brigade]], worked alongside the ''Afrika Korps'' after [[Operation Hercules]] (the planned invasion of [[Malta]]) was cancelled and the Brigade was subsequently re-deployed to Germany.

==Internment in Mississippi==
Thousands of Korps POWs were held in camps at [[Camp Shelby]] in [[Mississippi]] after their capture.&lt;ref&gt;[http://books.google.com/books?id=ULiKL5r68eQC &quot;I Was There When It Happened&quot;], Jimmy Lee Beasley. Xlibris Corporation, 2010. ISBN 1453544577, 9781453544570. p. 262&lt;/ref&gt;

==Resurrection of units==
Certain divisions were resurrected in Europe after the cessation of fighting in Tunisia:
* 15./''Panzer'' Division
* 21./''Panzer'' Division (in France)
* [[Fallschirm-Panzer Division 1 Hermann Göring|Hermann Göring ''Panzer'' Division]] (in Sicily and Italy)

==''Afrika Korps'' marching songs==
[[Image:Bundesarchiv Bild 101I-783-0110-12, Nordafrika, Panzer II, Kraftfahrzeuge.jpg|thumb|350px|A ''Panzer'' II of the ''Afrika Korps''. Note the faded insignia on the front, left of the handle and just below the turret.]]

1st song: '''Panzer rollen in Afrika vor / Heiß über Afrikas Boden

&lt;poem&gt;''Heiß über Afrikas Boden die Sonne glüht''.
''Unsere Panzermotoren singen ihr Lied''!
''Deutsche Panzer im Sonnenbrand'',
''Stehen zum Kampf gegen England
''Es rasseln die Ketten, es dröhnt der Motor'',
''Panzer rollen in Afrika vor!''&lt;/poem&gt;

'''Translation'''
&lt;poem&gt;The sun shines hot over [[Africa]]n ground.
Our [[panzer]] engines are singing their song!
German panzers in the blazing sun,
As they stand ready for battle against England.
The tracks rattle, the engine roars,
Panzers rolling forwards in Africa.&lt;/poem&gt;

'''2nd Song: &quot;''Unser Rommel''&quot; (&quot;Our Rommel&quot;)'''&lt;ref&gt;Song text and MP3(not identical at the ending of the third verse) of ''[http://ingeb.org/Lieder/wirsinda.html Unser Rommel] Retrieved'' 2007-02-12&lt;/ref&gt;

1.
&lt;poem&gt;''Wir sind das deutsche Afrikakorps''
''Des Führers verwegene Truppe''
''Wir stürmen wie die Teufel hervor''
''Versalzen dem Tommy die Suppe''
''Wir fürchten nicht Hitze und Wüstensand''
''Wir trotzen dem Durst und dem Sonnenbrand''
''Marschieren beim Takt unserer Trommel''
''Vorwärts, vorwärts''
|:''Vorwärts mit unserem Rommel!'':|&lt;/poem&gt;

'''Translation of verse 1'''
&lt;poem&gt;We are the German Africa Korps
The [[Führer]]'s daring troops
We attack like the Devil
Make things hot for the Tommys
We fear neither heat nor desert sand
We brave the thirst and the blazing sun
Marching to the beat of our drum''
Forwards, forwards
|:Forwards with our Rommel!:|&lt;/poem&gt;

2.
&lt;poem&gt;''Die Briten fürchten uns wie die Pest''
''Sie sitzen auf glühenden Kohlen''
''Wir rächen Deutsch-Ost und rächen Südwest''
''Das einst sie uns feige gestohlen''
''Sind [[Winston Churchill|Churchill]] und [[Franklin Roosevelt|Roosevelt]] auch Wut entbrannt''
''Wir werfen die Feinde in jedem Land''
''Es schlägt Generalmarsch die Trommel''
''Vorwärts, vorwärts''
|:''Vorwärts mit unserem Rommel!'':|&lt;/poem&gt;

'''Translation of verse 2'''
&lt;poem&gt;The British fear us like the plague
They're like cats on a hot tin roof
We're taking revenge for [[German East Africa|German East]] (Africa) and for [[German South-West Africa|South-West]] (Africa)
Which were cowardly stolen from us
Churchill and Roosevelt are getting mad
We beat the enemy in every country
The drum beats 'get ready'{{r|group=Note|Generalmarsch}}
Forwards, forwards
|:Forwards with our Rommel!:|&lt;/poem&gt;

3.
&lt;poem&gt;''Mit uns im Kampf und im Siege vereint''
''Marschieren Italiens Scharen''
''Bis einst die Sonne des Friedens uns scheint''
''Und wieder gen Deutschland wir fahren.''
''Doch wenn mich die feindliche Kugel fand''
''So lasset mich ruhen im Wüstensand''
''Und rühret noch einmal die Trommel''
''Vorwärts, vorwärts''
|:''Vorwärts mit unserem Rommel!'':|&lt;/poem&gt;

'''Translation of verse 3'''
&lt;poem&gt;With us united in battle and in victory
Italy's cohorts are marching
Until one day the sun of peace will shine on us
And we will return to Germany.''
But if the enemy's bullet gets me
Then let me rest in the desert sand
Let the drum beat once more.
Forwards, forwards
|:Forwards with our Rommel!:|&lt;/poem&gt;

==See also==
{{Commons category}}
* [[Army Group Africa]]
* [[Erwin Rommel]]
* [[Panzer Army Africa]]
* ''[[Fliegerführer Afrika]]''
* [[Western Desert Campaign]]
* [[North African Campaign]]
* [[First Battle of El Alamein]] (1–27 July 1942)
* [[Second Battle of El Alamein]] (23 October – 4 November 1942)
* [[László Almásy]]
* [[Operation Salaam]]
* [[Hans von Luck]]
* [[Hans-Jürgen von Arnim]]
* [[Panzer Division]]
* [[Afrika Korps (game)]]
* ''[[German Army|Heer]]''
* [[Eastbourne Redoubt]], home of General [[Hans-Jürgen von Arnim]]'s Steyr 1500A ''Africa Korps'' Staff Car

==Notes==
{{reflist |group=Note |refs=
&lt;ref name=Generalmarsch&gt;A German military signal meaning: &quot;Attention! Assemble at your positions!&quot;&lt;/ref&gt;
}}

==References==
{{reflist}}
{{Refbegin}}
* Cooper, Matthew (1990). ''The German Army 1933–1945''. Scarborough House. Chelsea, MI, USA. ISBN 0-8128-8519-8.
* {{cite book | author=von Mellenthin, Major General F. W. | title=[[Panzer Battles (book)|Panzer Battles: A Study of the Employment of Armor in the Second World War]] | edition=First| year=1971 | location=New York | publisher=[[Ballantine Books]] | origyear=1956 | isbn=0-345-24440-0}}
* [http://www.AFRIKAKORPS.org AFRIKAKORPS.org/AANA Research Group]
* [http://www.afrikakorps.org/rommelskampfstaffel.htm Rommel's Kampfstaffel]
{{refend}}

==Further reading==
* Editor Major-General [[Alfred Toppe]] [http://www.cgsc.edu/carl/resources/csi/toppe/toppe.asp ''Desert warfare:German experiences in World War II]'', written with the assistance of nine German commanders who served in North Africa, the manuscript (translated by Mr. H. Heitman) represents a collaborative attempt to determine &quot;as many factors as possible which exerted a determining influence on desert warfare.&quot;
* [[Hans von Luck]]'s memoirs ''Panzer Commander: The Memoirs of Colonel Hans von Luck'' include chapters from his time in North Africa under Rommel.

==External links==
* [http://www.afrikakorps.org/ Afrika Korps History]{{Dead link|date=June 2010}}
* [http://www.afrikakorps.org/dakkommandeurs.htm Panzer-Armee &quot;AFRIKA&quot; Kommandeurs]{{Dead link|date=June 2010}}
* [http://www.afrikakorps.org/knightscrossna.htm Knight's Cross of the Iron Cross Holders: North Africa]{{Dead link|date=June 2010}}
* [http://www.afrikakorps.org/rommelskampfstaffel.htm Rommel's Kampfstaffel]{{Dead link|date=June 2010}}
* [http://www.afrikakorps.org/germanuniforms.htm Afrika Korps Uniforms]{{Dead link|date=June 2010}}
* [http://ingeb.org/Lieder/wirsinda.html Unser Rommel - Wir sind das deutsche Afrikakorps - in MP3 format]
* [http://www.historisches-tonarchiv.de/lieder.htm Deutsches Historisches Tonarchiv - see &quot;Lieder und Märsche des Afrika Korps&quot; (Commercial site with songs available on CD)]

{{German Army Corps of the Wehrmacht}}

[[Category:Corps of Germany in World War II]]
[[Category:German units in Africa]]
[[Category:Military units and formations established in 1941]]

[[ar:الفيلق الأفريقي]]
[[an:Deutsches Afrika Korps]]
[[bg:Немски африкански корпус]]
[[ca:Afrika Korps]]
[[cs:Afrikakorps]]
[[da:Afrikakorpset]]
[[de:Deutsches Afrikakorps]]
[[es:Afrika Korps]]
[[eu:Afrika Korps]]
[[fr:Deutsches Afrikakorps]]
[[fy:Afrikakorps]]
[[gl:Afrika Korps]]
[[hr:Afrički korpus]]
[[it:Deutsches Afrikakorps]]
[[he:קורפוס אפריקה]]
[[hu:Német Afrika-hadtest]]
[[nl:Afrikakorps]]
[[ja:ドイツアフリカ軍団]]
[[no:Afrikakorpset]]
[[pl:Afrika Korps]]
[[pt:Afrika Korps]]
[[ru:Африканский корпус]]
[[simple:Afrika Korps]]
[[sk:Deutsches Afrikakorps]]
[[sl:Nemški afriški korpus]]
[[sr:Немачки афрички корпус]]
[[fi:Deutsches Afrikakorps]]
[[sv:Afrikakåren]]
[[tr:Alman Afrika Kolordusu]]
[[uk:Корпус «Африка»]]
[[vi:Quân đoàn châu Phi của Đức]]
[[zh:德意志非洲军]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
