<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="1585834" ns="0" title="Metropolitan Transport Corporation (Chennai)"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Infobox Bus transit
| name            = Metropolitan Transport Corporation (Chennai)
| founded         = 1947
| headquarters    =  Pallavan House, Anna Salai, Chennai
| locale          = [[Chennai]]
| service_area    = [[Chennai Metropolitan Area]]
| service_type    = Normal, Limited-stop (LSS), Express, Deluxe and Volvo
| fleet           = 3421&lt;ref name=MTCWeb&gt;[http://www.mtcbus.org/]&lt;/ref&gt;
| ridership       = 55,840,00
| collection      = 2.6 crore/Day(Avg)&lt;ref&gt;http://www.deccanchronicle.com/channels/cities/chennai/good-and-bad-recent-hikes-tamil-nadu-426&lt;/ref&gt;
| operator        = [[Government of Tamil Nadu]]
| area served     = [[Chennai Metropolitan Area]]
| industry        = Public Transportation
| routes          = 724&lt;ref name=MTCWeb&gt;[http://www.mtcbus.org/]&lt;/ref&gt;
| employees       = 22792
| depots          = 25
| parent          = Pallavan Transport Corporation Ltd
| website         = [http://www.mtcbus.org// www.mtcbus.org]
}}
[[File:Chennai Openstreetmap Public Transport Density Map.png|thumb|Heatmap of the coverage of public transportation in Chennai City]]

The '''Metropolitan Transport Corporation''' ({{lang-ta|மாநகர் போக்குவரத்துக்கழகம்}}) (formerly known as '''Pallavan Transport Corporation Ltd.''') is the agency that operates the [[public transport]] [[bus]] service in [[Chennai]], [[India]]. It covers a maximum of 50&amp;nbsp;km radius around Chennai.

==History==
Metropolitan Transport Corporation ([[Chennai]] - Dn.I) Ltd was established on 1 January 1972 with a fleet strength of 1029 buses.  The operational [[jurisdiction]] is the [[Chennai]] Metropolitan area.  The Pallavan Transport Corporation was split into two and a new Corporation, namely, Dr. Ambedkar Transport Corporation Ltd. started functioning from 19 January 1994. Pallavan Transport Corporation was renamed as Metropolitan Transport Corporation (Chennai Division –1) Limited,   Dr. Ambedkar Transport Corporation was re-named as Metropolitan Transport Corporation (Chennai Division-II) Ltd., on 1 July 1997.  

In order to make the Corporations viable, and for better administrative control, Metropolitan Transport Corporation (Chennai Division II) was amalgamated with Metropolitan Transport Corporation (Chennai Division I) Ltd in 10 January 2001. The fleet strength of the [[Corporation]] at 1 March 2009 was 3260 with 25 depots, a body building unit at [[Chromepet]], a ticket printing press at [[K.K.Nagar]] and Reconditioning Unit at Patullos Road. During the year 2002-2003, 117 buses have been purchased for replacement. After 2007, thousands of number of buses are purchased for new services as well as replacement for old buses.

==Fleet==
[[Image:MTC-TataMarcopolo2.jpg|thumb|200 px|right|MTC's Tata Marcopolo Bus]]
[[Image:CityBus Vestibule.jpg|thumb|200 px|right|New vestibule bus with LCD display]]
[[File:Chennai Royapettah clock tower.jpg|thumb|200 px|right|An MTC Volvo Service]]
[[File:Mtc volvo.jpg|thumb|200 px|right|Another Volvo service]]
[[File:MTC Bus 21G.JPG|thumb|200 px|right|A MTC SLF plying route 21G]]
* [http://www.thehindu.com/multimedia/dynamic/00214/Ajai_214855e.jpg  Number of MTC buses as on 24/08/2010]

'''Single-deckers'''

All the buses in the MTC are from either [[Ashok Leyland]] or [[Tata Motors]], with the former having a vast majority. These buses were launched since 1990s and even today many of those old-fashioned buses continue to receive overwhelming response. Most of the buses are BS-III compliant while the newly ordered Ashok Leyland Viking SLFs are BS-IV Compliant.

'''Semi-Low floor buses'''

The corporation has also introduced huge number of semi [[low floored]] and deluxe buses with improved passenger amenities like  improved lighting, [[plastic moulded]] seats and driver operated pneumatic, doors into its fleet from February 2007. These buses are from Ashok Leyland, with the body built by various body building shops which Ashok Leyland has partnered with - Prakash Coach (SM Kannappa Automobiles, Bangalore), Veera Vahana Udyog Ltd, Irizar-TVS, G.S.Body works etc. and account for the majority of the buses. The newer range of these semi-low floor buses feature BS-III engines and LED display while the older buses are BS-II compliant. The total number of buses in this segment is over 1800.

'''Vestibule Services'''

Apart from the regular and low-floor buses, MTC also runs articulated buses from Ashok Leyland to traverse the most-congested routes. The fares are similar to those of ordinary and express services. These buses have 2 conductors, plastic moulded seats and LED boards (Some of these buses still continue to have regular boards). However these buses do not have pneumatic doors nor feature the chassis of the semi-low floor buses.

'''Air-conditioned buses'''

MTC has launched the Volvo AC Bus services in Chennai on selected routes. It is expected that the number of AC buses running in the city is likely to increase many folds in the upcoming years. These [[B7RLE]]s have high-tech features such as ABS, Retarders, Kneeling, etc. and relatively better interiors. There about 100 of these buses running on select routes at regular intervals. All the busses are Euro V compliant. These buses are so popular that a 30 of them have been transferred to [[TNSTC]] and make trips to [[Pondicherry]], [[Vellore]], [[Coimbatore]], [[Tiruchirapalli]] and [[Hosur]].

Advertising facilities are available on these buses, which can be availed at reasonable costs. Advertisements are mainly print visuals that can be arrayed in the interiors and the exteriors.

==Services==
MTC services are identified by the colour of the route board*:
{| class=&quot;wikitable&quot;
|-
! S.No. !! Board type !! Service !! Description !! Base fare (Rs.) + per 4&amp;nbsp;km
|-
|1
|style=&quot;background:white; color:black&quot;|White board
|Ordinary service - Replaced by M service||Stops at all bus stops||2+0.5	
|-
|2
|style=&quot;background:white; color:black&quot;|M
|M service||Same as ordinary with higher fare||3+1
|-
|3
|style=&quot;background:yellow; color:red&quot;|LSS
|Limited stop service||Stops at alternate bus stops||2.5+0.5	
|-
|4
|style=&quot;background:green; color:white&quot;|Express
|Express service||Stops at few bus stops||3+0.5	
|-
|5
|style=&quot;background:green; color:white&quot;|PP
|Point to point service||Similar to express||3+0.5	
|-
|6
|style=&quot;background:blue; color:white&quot;|Deluxe
|Deluxe service (Yellow/Blue/White/Orange lines) [[Line Services (MTC)|See list of deluxe routes]]||Stops at EXPRESS bus stops, deluxe buses||5+2	
|-
|7
|style=&quot;background:black; color:white&quot;|Black board
|Night service||LSS service after 10pm||4+1
|-
|8
|style=&quot;background:white; color:red&quot;|Ladies
|Ladies special||Ordinary services during peak hours for Ladies||2+0.5
|-
|9
|style=&quot;background:digital: color:red&quot;|LED board
|All Volvo buses||||10 + Stage
|-
|}

*''Note:Almost all new busses apart from Volvo A/C Coaches launched under the JnNurm Scheme has Digital LED boards, So specific fares cannot be alloted according to the color of the route board''

== MTC Commuters Suggestions and Complaints [Grievance Cell] ==

Commuters can lodge their complaints and suggestions to [http://www.mtcbus.org/Suggestions.asp  GRIEVANCE CELL]&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.mtcbus.org/Suggestions.asp  GRIEVANCE CELL]&lt;/ref&gt;, Metropolitan Transport Corporation Limited over the cell phone number +91-9383337639 round the clock. 

Complaints may also be lodged to the Wireless Control Room using Telephone Numbers +91-44-23455858, +91-44-23455859 or +91-44-23455801 - Extension - 239 between 10.00 hrs. to 17.45 hrs. 

== See also ==
* [[List of MTC deluxe routes]]
* [[Tamil Nadu State Transport Corporation]]-TNSTC
* [[State Express Transport Corporation (Tamil Nadu)]]-SETC

==References==
{{Reflist |refs=
}}

== External links ==
{{Commons category|Metropolitan Transport Corporation (Chennai)}}
* [http://mtcbus.org MTCBus.org - Official website]
* [http://www.tn.gov.in/rti/proactive/transport/handbook_mtc.pdf Operation details under RTI]
* [http://busroutes.in/chennai/ BusRoutes.In - Chennai bus and train route maps]
* [http://www.mtcbus.org/ACBusesTimeSchedule.asp MTC Volvo AC Bus Timings]
{{Chennai Topics|left}}

[[Category:Transport in Chennai]]
[[Category:State road transport corporations of India]]
[[Category:Bus companies of India]]
[[Category:Companies based in Chennai]]

[[ta:மாநகரப் போக்குவரத்துக் கழகம்]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
