<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="1591828" ns="0" title="Nova Southeastern University"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Infobox university
|image= [[Image:NSUcrestvector.png|160px]]
|caption           = [[Seal (device)|Seal]] of Nova Southeastern University
|name= Nova Southeastern University
|latin_name=fides, addo, factum
|motto=Engage, Inspire, Achieve
|established= 1964
|type= [[Private school|Private]]
|president= [[George L. Hanbury II]]&lt;ref name=&quot;Nova Southeastern Leadership succession&quot;&gt;[http://www.nova.edu/cwis/pubaffairs/news/oct-dec2009/leadership_succession.html] &quot;NSU leadership succession plan&quot;.Nova Southeastern University (nova.edu).Retrieved December 14, 2009.&lt;/ref&gt;
|chancellor=[[Ray F. Ferrero Jr.]]&lt;ref name=&quot;Nova Southeastern Leadership succession&quot; /&gt;
|provost= Frank DePiano, Ph.D.
|city= Main Campus:&lt;br /&gt;[[Davie, Florida|Davie]]
|state= Florida, US&lt;br /&gt;Satellite Campuses:&lt;br /&gt;[[Dania Beach, Florida|Dania Beach]]&lt;br /&gt;[[North Miami Beach, Florida|North Miami Beach]]
|students= 28,796&lt;ref name=&quot;Nova Southeastern University: Student Profile&quot;&gt;[http://colleges.usnews.rankingsandreviews.com/college/items/1509] ''Nova Southeastern University Statistics for 2008-2009'' Retrieved on July 14, 2009.&lt;/ref&gt;
|undergrad= 12,756&lt;ref name=&quot;Nova Southeastern University: Student Profile&quot; /&gt;
|postgrad= 16,040&lt;ref name=&quot;Nova Southeastern University: Student Profile&quot; /&gt;
|faculty= 2,083&lt;ref name=&quot;College Board Profile: Faculty/Staff&quot;&gt; [http://collegesearch.collegeboard.com/search/CollegeDetail.jsp?collegeId=625&amp;type=qfs&amp;skey=nova] ''Faculty and Staff numbers'' Retrieved on January 10, 2008.&lt;/ref&gt;
|staff= 4,319&lt;ref name=&quot;College Board Profile: Faculty/Staff&quot; /&gt;
|endowment= $383.1&amp;nbsp;Million USD&lt;ref name=&quot;Peterson's Endowment profiles&quot;&gt;[http://www.nova.edu/cwis/fop/forms/oe2007.pdf] ''NSU IRS 990 form'' Retrieved on August 23, 2008.&lt;/ref&gt;
|campus= [[Suburban]]&lt;br /&gt; {{convert|480|acre|km2}}
|athletics= [[National Collegiate Athletic Association|NCAA]] Division II [[Sunshine State Conference|SSC]]
|free_label= Newspaper
|free= [[The Current (NSU)|The Current]]
|nickname= [[NSU Sharks|Sharks]]
|mascot= Razor the Shark
|colors= [[Navy blue|Navy Blue]] &amp; [[Gray]] {{color box|#000080}} {{color box|#808080}}
|affiliations= [[American Association of Colleges of Osteopathic Medicine|AACOM]], [[American Association of Colleges of Pharmacy|AACP]], [[AACSB]], [[American Association for Marriage and Family Therapy|AAMFT]], [[American Bar Association|ABA]], [[American Dental Association|ADA]], [[American Optometric Association|AOA]], [[American Psychological Association|APA]], [[American Physical Therapy Association|APTA]], [[American Speech-Language-Hearing Association|ASHA]], [[Council on Education for Public Health|CEPH]], [[Independent Colleges and Universities of Florida|ICUF]], [[National Association for the Education of Young Children|NAEYC]], and [[Southern Association of Colleges and Schools|SACS]]
|website= [http://nova.edu/ nova.edu]
|logo= [[Image:Nsubottomlogo.png|210px]]
|}}
'''Nova Southeastern University''', commonly referred to as '''NSU''' or '''Nova''', is a [[private university|private]], [[coeducation]]al, [[nonsectarian]], [[research]] university located in [[Broward County, Florida]], with its main campus in the town of [[Davie, Florida|Davie]]. The university is the largest independent institution of higher education in the southeastern United States and is the [[List of largest United States university campuses by enrollment|seventh-largest]] [[non-profit|not-for-profit]] independent university nationwide. NSU operates three campuses in Southern Florida, the largest being a {{convert|480|acre|ha|-1}} campus located approximately {{convert|26|mi|km|0}} north of [[Downtown Miami|Downtown]] [[Miami, Florida|Miami]].

The university was founded as the Nova University of Advanced Technology on a former naval training airfield offering graduate degrees in the physical and social sciences.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.time.com/time/magazine/article/0,9171,837055,00.html?iid=chix-sphere Novel Ideas: Nova U.] TIME Magazine. Retrieved December 7, 2009.&lt;/ref&gt; [[Leo Goodwin, Sr.]] left a $16&amp;nbsp;million bequest to the university in 1971 which funded its expansion throughout the 1970s and 1980s. In 1994, the university merged with the Southeastern University of the Health Sciences and assumed its current name.

NSU currently consists of 18 colleges and schools offering over 175 programs of study with more than 250 majors. The university offers professional degrees in law, business, osteopathic medicine, pharmacy, dentistry, optometry, and nursing. Nova Southeastern enrolled 28,796 students in the 2008-2009 academic year and has produced over 110,000 alumni.

In 2008, the middle 50% of SAT scores submitted by the incoming [[freshman]] class was between 1010 and 1210 on the traditional SAT scale. With the addition of the writing section on the new SAT, the middle 50% of scores was between 1400 and 1700.&lt;ref name=&quot;Collegeboard&quot;&gt;[http://collegesearch.collegeboard.com/search/CollegeDetail.jsp?collegeId=625&amp;profileId=6] ''College Search'' Retrieved on June 15, 2009.&lt;/ref&gt; The freshmen acceptance rate for the first 2009 semester was 44%,&lt;ref&gt;[http://collegesearch.collegeboard.com/search/CollegeDetail.jsp?match=true&amp;collegeId=625&amp;searchType=college&amp;type=qfs&amp;word=nova%20south|College Board Admissions] retrieved on 4-23-2009.&lt;/ref&gt; continually dropping each year since 2005. The 2005 admission percentage was 54%. For the fall of 2009 15,098 prospective freshmen applied and 6,643 were accepted.  Out of the 59 colleges and universities in Florida Nova Southeastern's 45% acceptance rate makes NSU the fourth-most selective private university in the state and the sixth-most selective university in Florida overall.&lt;ref&gt;[[State University System of Florida|State University System Admissions]] Retrieved on January 22, 2009.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[[Independent Colleges and Universities of Florida|Independent Colleges and Universities Admissions]] Retrieved on January 22, 2009.&lt;/ref&gt;

NSU is classified as a Research University by the Carnegie Foundation, and is a first-tier research university as designated by the Florida Legislature.&lt;ref&gt;[http://carnegiefoundation.org/classifications/sub.asp?key=748&amp;subkey=13870&amp;start=782 NSU research profile]. Carnigie Foundation. Retrieved on September 29, 2009.&lt;/ref&gt; The university is accredited by the [[Southern Association of Colleges and Schools]]&lt;ref name=&quot;sacscoc.org&quot;&gt;http://www.sacscoc.org/pdf/weblist092606.pdf Retrieved on February 3, 2008.&lt;/ref&gt; and also has numerous additional specialized accreditations for its colleges and programs.&lt;ref name=&quot;About NSU Accreditation&quot;&gt;[http://www.nova.edu/cwis/about-nsu/accreditation.html About NSU Accreditation] Retrieved on February 3, 2008.&lt;/ref&gt;

NSU was ranked 535th among universities worldwide by the Webometrics Ranking of World Universities in June, 2010.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.webometrics.info/rank_by_country.asp?country=us&amp;offset=150&amp;zoom_highlight=nova+southeastern+university] Webometrics Ranking of World Universities, Cybermetrics Lab, Consejo Superior de Investigaciones Científicas (CSIC), Spain.  Retrieved on October 16, 2009.&lt;/ref&gt;

The [[NSU Sharks]] compete in the NCAA Division II [[Sunshine State Conference]] in seventeen intercollegiate athletic programs.&lt;ref&gt;[http://nsuathletics.nova.edu/ NSU Sharks Athletics] Retrieved on September 23, 2009.&lt;/ref&gt;

== History ==
[[Image:Westhallatnsu.jpg|thumb|left|160px|Farher West Hall]]

=== 1960s ===
[[File:NSU Main entrance.JPG|thumb|right|200px|Main Entrance of NSU]]
Originally named Nova University of Advanced Technology, the university was chartered by the state of Florida on December 4, 1964&lt;ref name=&quot;Grad Profiles&quot;&gt;[http://www.gradprofiles.com/nova-southeastern-ocean.html] &quot;Grad Profiles&amp;nbsp;— Nova Southeastern University Oceanography&quot; Retrieved on April 7, 2006.&lt;/ref&gt; as a graduate institution in the physical and social sciences.  The school was renamed Nova University in 1974. After a merger with Southeastern University for Health Sciences in 1994, the university was renamed Nova Southeastern University. The land occupied by the university was previously a naval training airfield during World War II named Forman Field.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.airfields-freeman.com/FL/Airfields_FL_FtLauderdale.htm#forman |title=Abandoned &amp; Little-Known Airfields: Florida&amp;nbsp;— Fort Lauderdale area |publisher=Airfields-freeman.com |date= |accessdate=2011-05-21}}&lt;/ref&gt; The remnants of the taxiway surrounding the airfield are still present in the form of roads used on the campus.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.sfec.org/formanfield/index.html |title=History of the South Florida Education Center SFEC |publisher=Sfec.org |date=1948-12-31 |accessdate=2011-05-21}}&lt;/ref&gt; After World War II, the federal government had promised the Forman family, from whom the land was purchased, that the land would only be used for educational purposes. This led the land to be used for the creation of the South Florida Education Center of which Nova Southeastern University is now a part.&lt;ref name=&quot;South Florida Education Center&quot;&gt;[http://www.sfec.org/history/index.html] ''South Florida Education Center'' Retrieved on May 4, 2006.&lt;/ref&gt;

=== 1970s ===
[[File:Horowitzfrontatnsu.jpg|thumb|right|200px|Front of Horvitz building]]
On June 23, 1970, the board of trustees voted to enter into a federation with the [[New York Institute of Technology]]. The president of NYIT, [[Alexander Schure]], Ph.D., became [[chancellor]] of Nova University.&lt;ref name=sunsentinel&gt;{{cite news|first=Scott|last=Travis |title=NSU's former chancellor, Alexander Schure, dies|url=http://www.sun-sentinel.com/news/broward/fl-schure-obit-20091123,0,1622342.story|work=[[South Florida Sun-Sentinel]]|publisher=|date=November 23, 2009 |accessdate=November 28, 2009|archiveurl=http://www.webcitation.org/5lcmDlJjU |archivedate=November 28, 2009|deadurl=no}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=autogenerated5&gt;{{cite web|author=Laurie P. Dringus |url=http://scis.nova.edu/nova/hci/top.html |title=HCI at NSU:Online |publisher=Scis.nova.edu |date= |accessdate=2011-05-21}}&lt;/ref&gt; Abraham S. Fischler became the second president of the university.  Also, the university charter was amended and “of Advanced Technology” was dropped from its corporate name.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|author=StudentsReview.com UltraForce team |url=http://www.studentsreview.com/FL/NSU.html |title=Nova Southeastern University (StudentsReview) - College Reviews Summary, Student Opinion, Tuition, Application, Sports |publisher=StudentsReview |date= |accessdate=2011-05-21}}&lt;/ref&gt; In 1971, Nova University was accredited by the Southern Association of Colleges and Schools (SACS). In 1972, the university introduced its first off-campus course of study in education. In 1974 the school changed its name to Nova University.  Along with the name change came other changes, on campus, undergraduate evening programs began for adults, while the law school was opened in 1974. In 1976, the university received a $16&amp;nbsp;million gift from the estate of [[Leo Goodwin, Sr.|Leo Goodwin Sr.]], and began extensive campus and program expansion.  Shortly after this, NSU dissolved its relationship with NYIT&lt;ref&gt;http://www.nyit.edu/about/general/index.html&lt;/ref&gt; and began to create a board of trustees filled by South Florida community leaders, putting the stewardship of Nova back in the hands of its own local board, which is how it remains today.&lt;ref name=autogenerated5 /&gt;

=== 1980s ===
The Nova University that emerged in 1985 was committed to incorporating new educational technologies, made possible by computers and telecommunications, into the teaching and learning process and into its delivery of education. In 1989, celebrating its 25th year, Nova University enrolled more than 8,000 students annually and had nearly 25,000 graduates, with revenues of nearly $70&amp;nbsp;million.&lt;ref name=&quot;Grad Profiles&quot;/&gt; Over the next five years, three new buildings were constructed and a campus-wide beautification campaign added landscaping that greatly changed the look of the campus.&lt;ref name=autogenerated5 /&gt;
[[File:NSU South entrance.JPG|200px|thumb|South Entrance of NSU]]

=== 1990s ===
In 1994, Nova University merged with Southeastern University of the Health Sciences to form Nova Southeastern University (NSU), adding the Colleges of Osteopathic Medicine, Pharmacy, Optometry and Allied Health to the university. The university continued its expansion of building projects and added new academic, clinical and community service programs.&lt;ref name=&quot;Grad Profiles&quot;/&gt; By 1999, at the 35th anniversary, the university was enjoying an era of sustained growth, facilitated by a healthy infusion of endowment funds and a nearly 1,000-student increase in enrollment between fall 1998 and fall 1999.&lt;ref name=&quot;Grad Profiles&quot;/&gt; NSU’s enrollment had increased approximately 42 percent; full-time members of the faculty, staff and administration expanded to almost 2,600; and minority representation among faculty and staff members and students continued to expand.&lt;ref name=autogenerated5 /&gt;
[[Image:terryatrium-nsu.jpg|200px|thumb|right|Morton &amp; Geraldine Terry Atrium]]

=== 2000s ===
The William and Norma Horvitz Administration Building, a {{convert|62000|sqft|m2|sing=on}} structure that houses the office of the president and numerous other administration departments for the university was constructed. The Alvin Sherman Library for Research and Information Technology Center was completed in 2001 and is the largest public library facility in the state of Florida.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.nova.edu/library/main/ |title=Alvin Sherman Library for Research and Information Technology Center |publisher=Nova.edu |date=2011-05-01 |accessdate=2011-05-21}}&lt;/ref&gt; The Carl DeSantis Building, housing the H. Wayne Huizenga School of Business and Entrepreneurship, opened its doors in 2004.  This $33-million building is a {{convert|261000|sqft|m2|sing=on}}, five-story facility, that is also home to the Graduate School of Computer and Information Sciences.&lt;ref&gt;[http://scis.nova.edu/inbrief_start2.html NSU's Graduate School of Computer and Information Sciences offers certificates, master's, and doctoral degrees on-campus and online in computer science, computer information systems, information systems / technology, technology in education, and information security&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt; The state-of-the-art, {{convert|366000|sqft|m2|sing=on}} University Center, which opened on August 24, 2006, features three NCAA competition courts in the main arena, as well as two intramural courts, group fitness and instruction rooms, cardio and weight training areas, squash courts, a rock climbing wall, and The Flight Deck.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.nova.edu/facilities/construction/UniversityCenter/Photos/0001.html University Center Construction Photos]{{dead link|date=May 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; In addition, five residence halls on the main campus serve undergraduate, graduate, health professions, and law students, with a capacity for housing up to 720 students in approximately {{convert|207000|sqft|m2}} of living space. The Commons, a new, 525-bed residence hall, opened for the Fall 2007 semester.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.nova.edu/facilities/construction/ResHall/Photos/0001.html Residence Hall Construction Photos]{{dead link|date=May 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Presidents ===
[[File:jimandjanmorancenter.jpg|thumb|200px|Jim &amp; Jan Moran Family Center]]
[[George L. Hanbury II]] is the sixth president of Nova Southeastern University and assumed the position of president in January 2010.  The president is the chief executive officer of the college and is responsible for the success of the college's mission in providing superior academic programs and research.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.nova.edu/cwis/president/aboutus.html |title=Office of the President |publisher=Nova.edu |date= |accessdate=2011-05-21}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.nova.edu/cwis/president/vpadmin.html |title=The Administrative Affairs of the President's Office |publisher=Nova.edu |date= |accessdate=2011-05-21}}&lt;/ref&gt;

{| class=&quot;wikitable&quot;
|-
! President
! Tenure
|-
|[[Warren J. Winstead]]
|1964–1969
|-
|[[Abraham S. Fischler]]
|1970–1991
|-
|[[Stephen Feldman]]
|1992–1993
|-
|[[Ovid C. Lewis]]
|1994–1997
|-
|[[Ray F. Ferrero Jr.]]
|1998–2009
|-
|[[George L. Hanbury II]]
|since 2010
|}

== Campuses ==
[[File:Shark sculpturefountainatnight.JPG|thumb|right|200px|Shark Fountain outside of the UC]]
Nova Southeastern University has three commonwealth campuses that are all located in Southern Florida. Specifically, they are located in Broward County and Miami-Dade County. Nova Southeastern University also has two international long-distance education centers, for students who study international business, which are located in both [[The Bahamas]] and [[Jamaica]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.nova.edu/cwis/sites.html NSU Locations] Retrieved on January 22, 2009.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.huizenga.nova.edu/IFS/guidelines.cfm International Field Seminar's] Retrieved on February 3, 2008.&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Davie Campus ===
Davie Campus is the main campus and it is located in the town of [[Davie, Florida]]. However, the campus's mailing address is in [[Fort Lauderdale, Florida]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.nova.edu/cwis/campusmaps/forms/campusmap.pdf main campus] Retrieved on February 3, 2008.&lt;/ref&gt; The main campus is over {{convert|300|acre|km2|1}}. The main campus includes administrative offices, classroom facilities, library facilities, health clinics, mental health clinics, [[The University Center at Nova Southeastern University|Don Taft University Center]], dorms, cafeterias, computer labs, the bookstore, athletic facilities and parking facilities.
[[File:NSU Shark Shuttle.JPG|thumb|200px|right|Shark Shuttle has services both on campus and between campuses.]]

=== Dania Beach Campus ===
{{See|Nova Southeastern University Oceanographic Center}}
Dania Beach Campus is also known as the Oceanographic Center.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.nova.edu/ocean/ NSU Oceanography center] Retrieved on January 22, 2009.&lt;/ref&gt; The Nova Southeastern University Oceanographic Center is a center for oceanographical research at Nova Southeastern University in Florida.

=== North Miami Beach Campus ===
[[File:mailman-hollywoodbuildingnsu.jpg|thumb|right|200px|Mailman-Hollywood Building]]
The North Miami Beach Campus is also known as the Southern Campus.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.schoolofed.nova.edu/ NSU North Miami Beach School of Education] Retrieved on January 22, 2009.&lt;/ref&gt;  The Southern Campus serves as the main location for the Fischler School of Education and Human Services. The campus is {{convert|20|acre|km2|1}} and serves approximately 5% of all NSU students. In 2007-2008 over 4,500 students were served by the North Miami Beach Campus. The North Miami Beach Campus constists of five academic buildings, a library,  and academic office buildings.  Although this is the smallest campus in size, it is one of the most active areas for the Nova Southeastern community.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.schoolofed.nova.edu/fgshome/inforequest.htm Information on the School of Education] Retrieved on January 22, 2009.&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Student Education Centers ===
Nova Southeastern operates Student Education Centers and satellite campuses in [[The Bahamas]], [[Fort Myers, Florida|Fort Myers]], [[Jacksonville]], [[Jamaica]], [[Kendall, FL]], [[Miramar, FL]], [[Orlando, Florida|Orlando]], [[Tampa, Florida|Tampa]], Ponce, Puerto Rico and [[West Palm Beach, Florida|West Palm Beach]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.nova.edu/sec/ Student Education Centers] Retrieved on July 13, 2009.&lt;/ref&gt; These centers serve students at a distance from the main campus with computer labs and [[videoconferencing]] equipment. In addition, the centers are staffed with full-time employees to help with registration, enrollment, and [[financial aid (educational expenses)|financial aid]]. The satellite campuses and student education centers comprise a total of {{convert|150|acre|km2|1}}. At all Student Educational Centers evening and weekend classes are offered. All Student Education Centers are technologically advanced with the fusion of technology and education being emphasized. All services provided on the main campuses are also available at all NSU Student Educational Centers.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.nova.edu/studentengagement/sec/index.html Student Outreach Information] Retrieved on January 22, 2009.&lt;/ref&gt;

=== The University School ===
The campus also hosts the [[University School of Nova Southeastern University]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://uschool.nova.edu/ |title=University School |publisher=Uschool.nova.edu |date=2010-04-24 |accessdate=2011-05-21}}&lt;/ref&gt; The University school is located on the Davie Campus. The University School is a fully accredited, independent, college preparatory school that serves grades Pre-Kindergarten through grade 12. This school, often referred to as just the &quot;University School&quot;, is broken up into three academic areas: the lower, middle, and upper schools. Respectively representing elementary, middle and high school divisions within the school.&lt;ref&gt;[http://uschool.nova.edu/ University School History] Retrieved on February 3, 2008.&lt;/ref&gt;

== Academics ==
[[File:Nova Library West.JPG||thumb|200px|the Alvin Sherman Library]]
The university awards [[associate's]], [[bachelor's]], [[master's]], [[Ed.S.|specialist]], [[doctoral]], and first-professional degrees in a wide range of fields, including [[business]], [[counseling]], [[computer science|computer]] and [[information science|information]] sciences, [[education]], [[Osteopathic medicine in the United States|osteopathic medicine]], [[dentistry]], various health professions, law, [[marine sciences]], [[psychology]], and other [[social sciences]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.nova.edu/academics/degrees.html Degrees awarded at Nova Southeastern] Retrieved on August 28, 2009.&lt;/ref&gt;

Nova Southeastern University has the only colleges of [[optometry]] and dental medicine in South Florida, and one of only two colleges of [[pharmacy]] (the other being [[Palm Beach Atlantic University]]).&lt;ref&gt;[http://optometry.nova.edu/admissions/optometry.html NSU Optometry info] Retrieved on January 30, 2009.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://dental.nova.edu/aboutus.html Dental Medicine: About Us] Retrieved on January 30, 2009.&lt;/ref&gt; It also has one of the only two doctoral programs for Conflict Analysis and Resolution in the United States.&lt;ref&gt;[http://shss.nova.edu/Academic_Programs/MastersPrograms/MSDCAR.htm Programs Offered SHSS] Retrieved on January 30, 2009.&lt;/ref&gt; The institution enjoys an excellent reputation for its programs for families offered through the Mailman Segal Institute for Early Childhood Studies and the [[University School of Nova Southeastern University]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.nova.edu/msi/ Mailman Segal Institute] Retrieved on January 30, 2009.&lt;/ref&gt; These include innovative [[parenting]], [[preschool]], [[primary education]], and [[secondary education]] programs.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.nova.edu/msi/elp.html Learning Programs] Retrieved on January 30, 2009.&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Health professions division ===
[[File:NSU Physical Sciences Building.JPG|thumb|200px|left|Parker Physical Sciences Building]]
[[File:HPDatnsu.jpg|thumb|200px|Terry Building - Administration for all of the Health Professions Division]]
[[File:NSU Health Care Center.JPG|thumb|200px|Sanford Ziff Emergency Room]]
The Health Professions Division complex, dedicated in June, 1996, is located on {{convert|21|acre|m2}} and encompasses over {{convert|900000|sqft|m2|-4}} of buildings.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://hpd.nova.edu/aboutus/history.html |title=About NSU's Health Professions Division History |publisher=Hpd.nova.edu |date=2007-09-17 |accessdate=2011-05-21}}&lt;/ref&gt; The Division comprises the:&lt;br /&gt;
The [[Nova Southeastern University College of Osteopathic Medicine|College of Osteopathic Medicine]] is part of the Health Professions Division of the university, a division that encompasses over 2,000 students. The Nova Southeastern University College of Osteopathic medicine was the first osteopathic medical school to be established in the [[southeastern U.S.|Southeastern United States]]. Graduates of NSU-COM are awarded the Doctor of Osteopathic Medicine (D.O.) degree.
[[Image:NSU College of Dental Medicine.JPG|left|College of Dental Medicine|thumb|200px]]
The [[Nova Southeastern University College of Pharmacy|College of Pharmacy]], led by Dean Andres Malave, has an entry level Doctor of Pharmacy program in three sites, an international program in Davie and a Post-Baccalaureate program for pharmacy graduates.  The College also hosts a number of post-graduate residency programs.
The College of Pharmacy admitted its first class in 1987 to become the only College of Pharmacy in South Florida. Because of the profession's demand for greater clinical specialization, the College has since discontinued its baccalaureate degree program.

The [[Nova Southeastern University College of Dental Medicine|College of Dental Medicine]] opened in the fall of 1997.  It was the first new [[dentistry|dental]] school to open in the United States in 24 years.&lt;ref name=autogenerated4&gt;http://www.nova.edu/cwis/firstlook.pdf&lt;/ref&gt;  With a class size of about 120, it is the largest dental school in Florida.  In recent years, it has received more applications for admittance than any other dental school in the United States. It offers a four year [[Doctor of Dental Medicine|D.M.D.]] program, along with [[postdoctoral]] programs in: Advanced Education in General Dentistry (AEGD), [[Endodontics]], [[Orthodontics]], [[Dentistry|Pediatric Dentistry]], [[Periodontology]], [[Prosthodontics]], [[Oral and Maxillofacial Surgery]], and Master of Science degrees in [[Craniofacial]] Research.&lt;ref name=autogenerated4 /&gt; EMS Education and Training, Master of Science in Medical Informatics, and Masters of Public Health are also offered.

The Nova Southeastern University [[Nova Southeastern University College of Optometry|College of Optometry]] is part of the Health Professions Division. Optometry students at Nova Southeastern University receive training in community, pediatric, primary, environmental and rehabilitative optometry, optics and health sciences. The program looks to promote quality optometric care, by preparing students with a combination of lectures and clinical experience.  The goal for the program is to give the students as much training as possible, so that when they take the state-board exams for Florida they are adequately prepared.

The [[Nova Southeastern University College of Medical Sciences|College of Medical Sciences]] is part of the Health Professions Division. For those students wishing to improve their academic credentials in the medical sciences, the College of Medical Sciences offers a two year program of study leading to a master's degree in Biomedical Sciences.  Each student's program is individually tailored to meet the student's needs and aspirations.  Those enrolled in this program take  basic science courses similar to those offered within the Health Professions Division during their first year.  During the second year, students continue their program of general studies.&lt;ref name=autogenerated4 /&gt; The Master of Biomedical Sciences degree program is accredited by the Southern Association of Colleges and Schools (SACS).
[[File:NSU Rolling Hills Graduate Housing.JPG|thumb|200px|Rolling Hills - Graduate housing]]
The [[Nova Southeastern University College of Allied Health and Nursing|College of Allied Health and Nursing]] is part of the Health Professions Division. The College of Allied Health and Nursing prepares professionals with the skills necessary for the diagnosis, treatment and prevention of diseases, for the support of the populace in maintaining proper health and safety, for the management of rehabilitative processes, and for the education of the community in understanding the interdependency of health, environment, social and political factors. The College of Allied Health endeavors to train both graduate and undergraduate professionals in the arts of improving the quality of life in the community.

The Health Professions Division is the evolution of what was once Southeastern University of the Health Sciences before its merger with Nova University in 1994. The facilities include space for students to participate in clinical work, lecture auditoriums, a library, cafeteria, seminar rooms, and faculty offices. State-of-the-art technology is integrated throughout the facilities. They are affiliated with ''The Rumbaugh-Goodwin Institute for Cancer Research''.

=== Other schools, colleges, and centers ===
[[File:NSU Student and Media Arts Center.jpg|left|thumb|200px|Farquhar College of Arts and Sciences with UC Arena in the background.]]
The [[Shepard Broad Law Center]], founded in 1974, is the law school of Nova Southeastern University.  The Law Center is housed in [[Leo Goodwin, Sr.|Leo Goodwin]] Sr. Hall, located on Nova Southeastern University's main campus in Davie, Florida and is named after university founder [[Shepard Broad]].The Law Center hosts over 1,000 students in both its day and evening programs. There is a full time faculty of 50, in addition to 65 adjuncts, many of whom are local judges.  The Law Center is accredited by the [[American Bar Association]].  According to the 2008 USNWR ranking of law schools, the Law Center's legal skills and values program (&quot;LSV&quot;) is among the top 30 such programs in the nation (ranked 22). In 2009, NSU Law students had the highest bar passer rating in South Florida and third highest bar passage rate in Florida.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.nova.edu/cwis/pubaffairs/news/july-sept2009/law_ranks_pass_rate.html NSU Law Grads]. NSU. Retrieved on September 29, 2009.&lt;/ref&gt;
[[File:NSU DeSantis Building.JPG|thumb|200px|DeSantis Building - Huizenga School]]
[[File:Nova Southeastern University Psychology Building.jpg|left|thumb|200px|the Maltz Psychology Building]]
[[Image:Huizinga BSchool Back.JPG|right|thumb|200px|the Dr. William Spears Atrium]]
The [[H. Wayne Huizenga School of Business and Entrepreneurship]] is housed in the Carl DeSantis building on the main campus. The '''H. Wayne Huizenga School of Business and Entrepreneurship''' serves over 6,600 bachelors, masters, and doctoral students in a variety of degree programs.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.huizenga.nova.edu/About/default.cfm About the Huizenga School] NSU retrieved on May 23, 2009.&lt;/ref&gt; The school is named after the local businessman and philanthropic [[H. Wayne Huizenga]]. The Huzienga School was also the pioneer in the cluster concept for graduate students and making field-based graduate programs easier and more accessible for the students.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.huizenga.nova.edu/About/RandolphAPohlman.cfm Letter from the Dean] NSU retrieved on May 23, 2009.&lt;/ref&gt; The school is accredited by Commission on Colleges of the Southern Association of Colleges and Schools and the University Council of Jamaica (UCJ) for its international student center in Jamaica. Additionally, the school holds membership in is in the initial accreditation phase for the [[AACSB|Association to Advance Collegiate Schools of Business - International]] (AACSB).&lt;ref&gt;[https://datadirect.aacsb.edu/public/profiles/profile.cfm?runReport=1&amp;unitid=54814&amp;userType=All AACSB membership profile of Nova Southeastern University] Retrieved on February 25, 2009.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.huizenga.nova.edu/About/Memberships.cfm About Huizenga School Membership] NSU retrieved on May 23, 2009.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.huizenga.nova.edu/About/Accreditation.cfm |title=Accreditation |publisher=Huizenga.nova.edu |date= |accessdate=2011-05-21}}&lt;/ref&gt;
[[File:NSU Arts Building.JPG|thumb|left|200px|University School Arts building]]

The [[Nova Southeastern University Graduate School of Computer and Information Sciences|Graduate School of Computer and Information Sciences]] is housed in the Carl DeSantis building on the main campus but also offers one of the widest range of online curriculum offered at NSU. The Nova Southeastern University Graduate School of Computer and Information Sciences(GSCIS) provides educational programs of distinction to prepare students for leadership roles in [[information technology]].

The [[Nova Southeastern University Graduate School of Humanities and Social Sciences]] is located on the Main Campus in the Maltz building, which is also shared with the Center for Psychological Studies. The goal of the school is to provide a better understanding of human social relations. It is a multi-disciplinary, multi-professional, and multi-cultural program. The vigorous curricula have deep interdisciplinary roots. The cutting-edge programs employ a variety of creative learning approaches and innovative education technologies.

[[Nova Southeastern University Center for Psychological Studies]] was organized in 1967. It is presently located in the Maltz building on the main campus. It serves to provide the highest-quality educational experience to current and future psychologists and counseling professionals through training experiences that provide individuals with a sophisticated understanding of psychological research and the delivery of the highest-quality mental health care. CPS is accredited by both the [[American Psychological Association]] and the [[Florida Department of Education]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=CPS Accreditation Page|url=http://cps.nova.edu/about/accreditation.html}}&lt;/ref&gt; 

The [[Farquhar College of Arts and Sciences]] currently offers two graduate degree programs... one in the area of writing and ther other in the area of experimental psychology.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.fcas.nova.edu/programs/graduate/ |title=NSU Farquhar College of Arts and Sciences Graduate Studies |publisher=Fcas.nova.edu |date= |accessdate=2011-05-21}}&lt;/ref&gt; The Farquhar College of Arts and Sciences at Nova Southeastern University provides foundational study in core and emerging disciplines and technologies to prepare students for graduate and professional study, career development, and responsible citizenship.

The College of Graduate Studies in the Arts and Sciences practices that through intensive major programs and strong general education programs, the Farquhar College of Arts and Sciences has built a vital and evolving foundation for undergraduate education. The Farquhar College of Arts and Sciences connects students with programs through traditional classroom and laboratory experiences and through innovative educational approaches that reach students far and wide. Programs are supported by an active faculty in three divisions: the Division of Humanities, the Division of Math, Science, and Technology, and the Division of Social and Behavioral Sciences.

== Enrollment and admissions ==
&lt;div  style=&quot;float:left; text-align:center;&quot;&gt;
&lt;big&gt;'''Fall freshman statistics'''&lt;/big&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://collegesearch.collegeboard.com/search/CollegeDetail.jsp?match=true&amp;collegeId=625&amp;searchType=college&amp;type=qfs&amp;word=Nova%20Southeastern%20University |title=NSU Freshman enrollment numbers |publisher=Collegesearch.collegeboard.com |date= |accessdate=2011-05-21}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://colleges.usnews.rankingsandreviews.com/best-colleges/search/title+nova%20South US News Admission percentage] USNews . Retrieved on December 9, 2009.&lt;/ref&gt;
{| class=&quot;wikitable&quot; style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;
|-
! &amp;nbsp; !! 2009 !! 2008 !! 2007 !! 2006 !! 2005
|-
! Applicants
| 15,098 || 14,627|| 13,051 || 12,745 || 12,589
|-
! Admits
| 6,643 || 6,582 || 6,656 || 6,628 || 6,798
|-
! % Admitted
| 44 || 45 || 51 || 52 || 54
|}

''This table does not account deferred&lt;br /&gt;applications or other unique situations.''&lt;/small&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

{| class=&quot;wikitable sortable&quot;  style=&quot;width:400px; float:right;&quot;
|| '''Ethnic enrollment, 2008'''&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.campusexplorer.com/colleges/A732EB15/Florida/Fort-Lauderdale/Nova-Southeastern-University/ NSU Student Demographics] Retrieved on November 10, 2008.&lt;/ref&gt; ||'''Percent'''||'''Total Population'''
|-
|[[Native Americans in the United States|American Indian]]
| 1%
|287
|-
|[[Asian American]]
| 6%
|1,727
|-
|[[Black American|Black (non-Hispanic)]]
| 14%
|4,031
|-
|[[Hispanic]]
| 27%
|7,774
|-
|[[White American|White (non-Hispanic)]]
| 43%
| 12,382
|-
|International, Other
| 9%
| 2,591
|-
|Total
| 100%
| 28,796
|}
Enrollment for fall 2008 consists of 28,796 students; which includes [[Undergraduate education|undergraduates]], [[Graduate school|graduate students]], and professional programs. For fall 2008, women accounted for 63% of student enrollment and minorities made up 67% of total undergraduate enrollment. Fall 2008 enrollment included students from all 50 U.S. states and more than 100 countries.&lt;ref&gt;[http://collegesearch.collegeboard.com/search/CollegeDetail.jsp?match=true&amp;collegeId=625&amp;searchType=college&amp;type=qfs&amp;word=Nova%20Southeastern%20University Student Body numbers] Retrieved on January 22, 2009.&lt;/ref&gt; The most popular college by enrollment are the Health Professions Division.&lt;ref&gt;[http://pharmacy.nova.edu/NewWebsite/StudentAffairs/Documents/Exhibit%20A%20and%20Exhibit%20B.pdf HPD Student Affairs and Enrollment numbers] Retrieved on January 22, 2009.&lt;/ref&gt;

In 2008, the middle 50% of SAT scores submitted by the incoming [[freshman]] class was between 910 and 1110 on the traditional SAT scale. With the addition of the writing section on the new SAT, the middle 50% of scores was between 1350 and 1650.&lt;ref name=&quot;Collegeboard&quot;/&gt; The freshmen acceptance rate for the first 2009 semester was 44%, continually dropping each year since 2005. The 2005 admission percentage was 54%. For the fall of 2009 15,098 prospective freshmen applied and 6,643 were accepted.

The [[Davie, Florida|Davie Campus]] accounted for 92% of the student population and 100% of housing students. The [[Miami Beach, Florida|Miami Beach Campus]] accounted for about 5% of the student population. For the Fall of 2008, the average age for undergraduates was 18 and 27 for graduate students.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.campusexplorer.com/colleges/A732EB15/Florida/Fort-Lauderdale/Nova-Southeastern-University/ Campus Explorer: Learning about Nova Southeastern] Retrieved on January 22, 2009.&lt;/ref&gt;

== Rankings and recognition ==
{{Infobox US university ranking
| ARWU_W =
| ARWU_N = 162
| ARWU_SCI = 87
| ARWU_ENG =
| ARWU_LIFE =
| ARWU_MED = 94
| ARWU_SOC = 107-137
| THES_W =
| USNWR_NU = 150-200
| USNWR_LA =
| USNWR_Bus = 75
| USNWR_Law = 125-150
| USNWR_Medr = 215
| USNWR_Medc = 193
| USNWR_Eng =
| USNWR_Ed = 250
| Wamo_NU = 157
| Wamo_LA =
| Forbes =
| FSPI =
}}
{| class=&quot;wikitable&quot;  style=&quot;width:300px; float:left; background:#9fc;&quot;
|-
! colspan=&quot;2&quot; | Nova Southeastern University Facts&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://colleges.usnews.rankingsandreviews.com/college/items/1509 |title=US News. retrieved on April 19, 2009 |publisher=Colleges.usnews.rankingsandreviews.com |date= |accessdate=2011-05-21}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://collegesearch.collegeboard.com/search/CollegeDetail.jsp?collegeId=625&amp;profileId=6 |title=College Board. retrieved on June 15, 2009 |publisher=Collegesearch.collegeboard.com |date= |accessdate=2011-05-21}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.princetonreview.com/schools/college/CollegeBasics.aspx?iid=1022853 |title=Princeton Review. Retrieved on June 2, 2009 |publisher=Princetonreview.com |date= |accessdate=2011-05-21}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|-
|Class of 2012 Applicants
|  style=&quot;text-align:center; background:#ccf;&quot;| 14,627
|-
|Class of 2012 Students
|  style=&quot;text-align:center; background:#ccf;&quot;| 2,994
|-
|Class of 2012 Accepted
|  style=&quot;text-align:center; background:#ccf;&quot;| 45%
|-
|Average GPA
|  style=&quot;text-align:center; background:#ccf;&quot;| 3.53/4.00
|-
|Middle 50% SAT
|  style=&quot;text-align:center; background:#ccf;&quot;| 1350–1640
|-
|Graduate Students
|  style=&quot;text-align:center; background:#ccf;&quot;| 17,740
|-
|Undergraduate Students
|  style=&quot;text-align:center; background:#ccf;&quot;| 11,056
|-
| Student:Faculty Ratio
|  style=&quot;text-align:center; background:#ccf;&quot;| 23:1
|-
|Programs of Study
|  style=&quot;text-align:center; background:#ccf;&quot;| 175
|-
|Majors Available
|  style=&quot;text-align:center; background:#ccf;&quot;| 250
|-
| Faculty with Terminal Degrees
|  style=&quot;text-align:center; background:#ccf;&quot;| 84%
|-
| Retention Rate
|  style=&quot;text-align:center; background:#ccf;&quot;| 79%
|-
| Classes taught by Faculty
|  style=&quot;text-align:center; background:#ccf;&quot;| 100%
|}

NSU is a ranked university in the second tier of the National Universities category, which ranks the top 275 research universities in the country, by [[U.S. News and World Report]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.usnews.com/usnews/edu/college/directory/brief/drglance_1509_brief.php USNews.com: America's Best Colleges 2009: Nova Southeastern University: At a glance] Retrieved on February 3, 2008.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://colleges.usnews.rankingsandreviews.com/best-colleges/ft.-lauderdale-fl/nova-1509 US News Nova Southeastern] Retrieved on August 17, 2010.&lt;/ref&gt; NSU is also ranked in the [[Washington Monthly]] rankings as the 157th best national university.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.washingtonmonthly.com/features/2006/0609.national.html] Washington Monthly retrieved on May 30, 2009.&lt;/ref&gt; The university is also listed as one of the best distance learning graduate schools in the country by the Princeton Review.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.lessonlab.com/nsu/nsu.cfm Nova Southeastern University Princeton Review] Retrieved on February 3, 2008.&lt;/ref&gt; Nova Southeastern University also was rated as one of the top universities for minority students by the [[Princeton Review]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.lessonlab.com/nsu/nsu.cfm Nova Southeastern University] Retrieved on February 3, 2008.&lt;/ref&gt; Additionally, Nova Southeastern University is considered the top university in the nation for diversity by the [[U.S. Department of Education]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.nova.edu/cwis/president/forms/annual_report.pdf NSU Annual Report] Retrieved on February 3, 2008.&lt;/ref&gt; The university is accredited by the [[Southern Association of Colleges and Schools]]&lt;ref name=&quot;sacscoc.org&quot;/&gt; and also has numerous additional specialized accreditations for its colleges and programs.&lt;ref name=&quot;About NSU Accreditation&quot;/&gt;

Many of Nova Southeastern's colleges and schools have achieved national recognition through U.S News and World Report, Princeton Review, U.S. Department of Education, and Carnegie Foundation.&lt;ref name=&quot;Nova Southeastern University: Colleges and Schools recognized&quot;&gt;[http://www.nova.edu/cwis/president/forms/pop2008.ppt] ''Nova Southeastern University: Colleges and Schools recognized'' Retrieved on November 26, 2008.&lt;/ref&gt;

The Shepard Broad Law School is considered to be the &quot;Most Wired&quot; college in the country.&lt;ref name=&quot;Nova Southeastern University: Colleges and Schools recognized&quot;/&gt;  It is also highly regarded as the 7th best law school for minorities.&lt;ref name=&quot;Nova Southeastern University: Colleges and Schools recognized&quot;/&gt;  The Shepard Broad Law Center was also recognized as consistently having the highest bar passage rating in South Florida and #3 in the state overall.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.nova.edu/cwis/pubaffairs/news/july-sept2009/law_ranks_pass_rate.html Bar passage rates]. NSU. Retrieved on Sept. 30, 2009.&lt;/ref&gt;

The College of Dental Medicine is one of only two Dental Colleges in the state of Florida.&lt;ref name=&quot;Nova Southeastern University: Colleges and Schools recognized&quot;/&gt;  It is also the nationally recognized as the #1 College of Dental Medicine in [[Stem Cell Research]]. The College of Dental Medicine has also been recognized as a leader in dental research and education.  It has received federal grants from to pursue the cloning of teeth from [[stem cells]]; the college is the first school in the nation to clone teeth.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.nova.edu/cwis/pubaffairs/sharkbytes/2009/sep23/cloned_teeth.html Teeth Cloning]. NSU. Retrieved on 9-30-2009.&lt;/ref&gt;

The College of Allied Health and Sciences is the #1 producer in Physician Assistants in the country and has the highest passer rating of nurses, with an average score of 97.4, which is the highest in the state of Florida and 15th best in the United States.&lt;ref name=&quot;Nova Southeastern University: Colleges and Schools recognized&quot;/&gt;
[[File:NSU Student Center.JPG|thumb|200px|Rosenthal Student Center]]
The College of Pharmacy is one of the largest pharmacy programs internationally. It is uniquely involved in the global community, with outreach and study abroad programs for students and faculty in Asia, the Middle East, South America, Western Europe and the Caribbean.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://pharmacy.nova.edu/aboutus/history.html |title=History of the College &amp;#124; NSU College of Pharmacy |publisher=Pharmacy.nova.edu |date= |accessdate=2011-05-21}}&lt;/ref&gt; The College of Osteopathic Medicine is Florida’s only fully accredited program in osteopathic medicine. Additionally, it is Florida’s only training Center for Bioterrorism and All-Hazards Preparedness (CBAP) and one of several geriatric education centers in Florida.

The H. Wayne Huizenga School is ranked in the Princeton Review's Top 296 Graduate Business Colleges.&lt;ref name=&quot;Nova Southeastern University: Colleges and Schools recognized&quot;/&gt;  It is also recognized as one of Barron's Best Buys in College.  The Huizenga School is also recognized by BusinessWeek for being a top MBA feeder school at #30 and having top business undergraduate and graduate programs, ranked at #59 and #84, respectively.&lt;ref&gt;[http://bwnt.businessweek.com/interactive_report/undergrad_bschool_2009/index.asp?sortCol=rankid&amp;sortOrder=1&amp;pageNum=1&amp;resultNum=51 Business News - Business Schools]. BusinessWeek. Retrieved on September 30, 2009.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://bwnt.businessweek.com/interactive_report/grad_bschool_2009/index.asp?sortCol=rankid&amp;sortOrder=1&amp;pageNum=1&amp;resultNum=51 Graduate Business News - Business Schools]. BusinessWeek. Retrieved on September 30, 2009.&lt;/ref&gt;

The Oceanography Center was recognized internationally in 2008 for its recent research.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.nova.edu/ocean/nsu_11icrs.html |title=Largest Coral Reef Symposium in the World |accessdate=December 4, 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt; Nova Southeastern along with the National Coral Reef Institute and the International Coral Reef Symposium conducted the largest Symposium in the world; the symposium hosted by the university had of over 75 different countries attend and participate in the event.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.nova.edu/ocean/nsu_11icrs.html |title=Largest Coral Reef Symposium in the World with  |accessdate=December 4, 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt; In 2010, the Oceanography Center was awarded $15&amp;nbsp;million from the United States government to build the United States largest coral reef research center. The reef will be used as the premiere research facility in the country and will also house numerous international coral reef researchers.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.nova.edu/cwis/pubaffairs/news/jan-march2010/oceanographic_15mil.html OCeanographic Grant] Nova Southeastern University retrieved on January 11, 2010.&lt;/ref&gt;

Nova Southeastern also received national attention for its unique scholarship award.  The university introduced the A. Gordon Rose scholarship which is awarded for studies of psychology on gay rights and homosexuality in society.&lt;ref name=&quot;Eve Rose Gay Scholarship&quot;&gt;[http://www.allbusiness.com/legal/labor-employment-law-discrimination-gender-sex/5711195-1.html Eve Rose Gay Scholarship] Retrieved on January 25, 2009.&lt;/ref&gt;  This unique scholarship was given high praise by the [[American Psychology Association]] and was considered the be the first ground breaking equality movement in scholarships and in awareness.&lt;ref name=&quot;Eve Rose Gay Scholarship&quot;/&gt; In addition to that the Maltz Psychology school is considered to be the nations leader in providing clinical services to the public.&lt;ref name=&quot;Nova Southeastern University: Colleges and Schools recognized&quot;/&gt;

[[File:NSU Physical Plant.JPG|200px|thumb|New Physical plant facilities]]
Along with all of its rankings and recognitions the university strives for academic research.  Nova Southeastern University is classified as Doctoral/Research University [[The Carnegie Foundation for the Advancement of Teaching|Carnegie Foundation]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web| url=http://classifications.carnegiefoundation.org/lookup_listings/view_institution.php?unit_id=136215&amp;start_page=institution.php&amp;clq={%22ipug2005_ids%22%3A%22%22%2C%22ipgrad2005_ids%22%3A%22%22%2C%22enrprofile2005_ids%22%3A%22%22%2C%22ugprfile2005_ids%22%3A%22%22%2C%22sizeset2005_ids%22%3A%22%22%2C%22basic2005_ids%22%3A%22%22%2C%22eng2005_ids%22%3A%22%22%2C%22search_string%22%3A%22nova+southeastern%22%2C%22first_letter%22%3A%22%22%2C%22level%22%3A%22%22%2C%22control%22%3A%22%22%2C%22accred%22%3A%22%22%2C%22state%22%3A%22%22%2C%22region%22%3A%22%22%2C%22urbanicity%22%3A%22%22%2C%22womens%22%3A%22%22%2C%22hbcu%22%3A%22%22%2C%22hsi%22%3A%22%22%2C%22tribal%22%3A%22%22%2C%22msi%22%3A%22%22%2C%22landgrant%22%3A%22%22%2C%22coplac%22%3A%22%22%2C%22urban%22%3A%22%22} |title=Carnegie Classification |accessdate=June 6, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;  The university also boasts that 95% of all its professors either have doctoral or terminal degrees in the their field of pedagogy.&lt;ref name=&quot;Nova Southeastern University: Colleges and Schools recognized&quot;/&gt;

=== Diversity ===
Nova Southeastern University is considered the most diverse university in the country by the U.S. Department of Education.&lt;ref name=&quot;Nova Southeastern University: State of the University&quot;&gt;[http://www.nova.edu/cwis/president/forms/pop2008.ppt] ''NSU annual state of the University'' Retrieved on November 26, 2008.&lt;/ref&gt; The university is #1 in many doctoral categories for diversity.  NSU awards the most doctoral degrees to African Americans, Hispanics, and Asian Americans in the United States.&lt;ref name=&quot;Nova Southeastern University: State of the University&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Nova Southeastern University: State of the University&quot;/&gt;  Nova Southeastern is also highly rated for diversity in awarding master's degrees.  The university is #2 in awarding master's degrees to Hispanics and #3 for awarding master's degrees to African Americans.&lt;ref name=&quot;Nova Southeastern University: State of the University&quot;/&gt;  The Fischler School of Education
and Human Services is the #1 college in the United States to award doctorates in Education and The Nova Southeastern University College of Pharmacy nation’s most culturally diverse pharmacy program.&lt;ref name=&quot;Nova Southeastern University: State of the University&quot;/&gt; The Princeton Review ranked the Shepard Broad Law School to be the top 7 universities in the country for minority students.&lt;ref name=&quot;Nova Southeastern University: State of the University&quot;/&gt;

== Campus life ==
[[Image:The Commons - NSU.jpg|200px|thumb|The Commons undergraduate housing]]

=== Student organizations ===
The Nova Southeastern's Undergraduate Student Government Association is the primary organization for the government of the undergraduate student body. The Office of Student Activities is responsible for a number of activities on campus, including homecoming, and regular extracurricular activities.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.nova.edu/studentactivities] Retrieved on December 29, 2010.&lt;/ref&gt;

Another large aspect of the universities campus life is the [[Greek Life]] system which comprises approximately 10% of the undergraduate student body.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.nova.edu/studentunion/greeks/index.html Greek Life at Nova] Retrieved on December 29, 2008.&lt;/ref&gt; There are a total of five fraternities on the campus and six sororities on the campus. Beyond Greek Life, there are another 60 undergraduate organizations on campus.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.nova.edu/ioc] Retrieved on December 29, 2010.&lt;/ref&gt;

The school's student-run newspaper, [[The Current (NSU)|''The Current'']], is published weekly.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.nsucurrent.com/home/generalinformation/ About The Current] Retrieved on December 29, 2008.&lt;/ref&gt; There is also a school-sponsored radio station called WNSU RADIO X which broadcasts in the evenings and weekends on 88.5 FM [[WKPX]], a station owned by [[Broward County Public Schools]]; Radio X airs from 7pm to 7 am, every night.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.nova.edu/radiox/ Radio-X] Retrieved on December 29, 2008.&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Athletics ===
{{Main|NSU Sharks}}
[[Image:dontaftuniversitycenter.jpg|200px|left|The Don Taft University Center|thumb]]
[[Image:Nsu alt.jpg|thumb|165px|right|NSU Athletics' Shark logo]]
The NSU Department of Athletics competes in Division II of the [[National Collegiate Athletic Association]] (NCAA) as members of the [[Sunshine State Conference]]. Nova Southeastern University offers 17 intercollegiate athletic programs consisting of ten women's and seven men's teams. Women's sports include basketball, [[cross country running|cross country]], [[golf]], [[Sport rowing|rowing]], [[soccer]], [[softball]], [[Swimming (sport)|swimming and diving]], tennis, [[track and field|track]] and [[volleyball]]. Male Student-Athletes can participate in baseball, basketball, cross country, golf, track, soccer, swimming and diving.&lt;ref&gt;[http://nsuathletics.nova.edu/ NSU Athletics] Retrieved on July 9, 2008.&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Image:dolphins training camp.jpg|thumb|200px|Miami Dolphins Training Facility on NSU's main campus]]
NSU Athletics has produced several SSC Players of the Year, NCAA All-Region selections and NCAA All-Americans, and have been nationally ranked in numerous sports since joining the NCAA beginning with the 2002-03 academic year. The [[Sunshine State Conference]] has been dubbed the Division II &quot;Conference of National Champions&quot;, as member institutions have won 83 national championships since the SSC was founded in 1975. Nova Southeastern University athletics has contributed to the SSC's 83 national championships, winning back-to-back championships in women's golf during the 2008-2009 and 2009-2010 seasons.

NSU baseball has seen a lot of their players make the transition into professional baseball. Since 1991 NSU has seen 24 players make baseball their profession, ranging from [[MLB]] to Independent Leagues.&lt;ref&gt;[http://nsuathletics.nova.edu/baseball/forms/prosharks.pdf Retrieved on July 9, 2008.]{{dead link|date=May 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; NSU athletes have also been successful outside of baseball. Much like many NSU baseball players, these other student-athletes, have also had the chance to pursue professional careers in both soccer and basketball.

Many athletic events at NSU take place at [[The University Center at Nova Southeastern University|University Center Arena]]. In 2005, students voted for a new school mascot, and the student body selected the Sharks. NSU's athletic teams had previously been known as the Knights.&lt;ref&gt;[http://nsuathletics.nova.edu/aboutus/index.cfm About the Sharks]  Retrieved on July 9, 2008.&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:Miniaci.jpg|thumb|200px|Miniaci Performing Arts Center]]

=== Student series ===
==== Distinguished speaker series ====
The [[Farquhar College of Arts and Sciences]] hosts the Distinguished Speaker Series. This series brings experts and notable persons from diverse fields to the campus. Past speakers have included [[Salman Rushdie]], Prime Minister [[Ehud Barak]], Film Maker [[Spike Lee]], [[Bob Woodward]], [[Elie Wiesel]], [[Paul Bremer]], [[Dr. Jack Kevorkian]],&lt;ref name=&quot;DSS&quot;&gt;[http://www.undergrad.nova.edu/articles/dss/jackkevorkian/] NSU.&quot;Distinguished Speaker Series&quot; Retrieved on January 8, 2008.&lt;/ref&gt; [[Desmond Tutu]]&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.fcas.nova.edu/articles/dss/desmondtutu/ Desmond Tutu speaking at NSU] NSU.&quot;Distinguished Speaker Series&quot; Retrieved on January 11, 2009.&lt;/ref&gt; and [[Tenzin Gyatso, 14th Dalai Lama|Tenzin Gyatso, The 14th Dalai Lama]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.undergrad.nova.edu/articles/dss Distinguished Speaker Series] Retrieved on July 9, 2008.&lt;/ref&gt;

==== Life 101 ====
The Life 101 series brings leaders from business, entertainment, politics and athletics to Nova Southeastern University. By meeting these guest speakers, students are educated and inspired by their life accomplishments and “life lessons” learned along the way. Past speakers have included [[Dwayne Johnson]], [[Wayne Huizenga]], [[Vanessa L. Williams]], [[Dan Abrams]], [[Jason Taylor (American football)|Jason Taylor]], [[Michael Phelps]], [[James Earl Jones]], [[Janet Reno]], [[Alyssa Milano]], and [[Ivanka Trump]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.nova.edu/life101/index.htm Life 101] Retrieved on July 9, 2008.&lt;/ref&gt;

==== Power lunch series ====
The Power Lunch series brings in local professionals and companies for a formal lunch and learn setting.  The Power Lunch series is supported through the H. Wayne Huizenga School of Business and Entrepreneurship.  The series is for all students of the Huizenga School and is promoted to help learn about working in the corporate setting as well as a networking tool for the students.  Past speakers and companies have included [[Geico]], [[BankAtlantic]], [[Miami Heat]], [[Florida Panthers]], [[Miami Dolphins]], [[T. Boone Pickens]], [[Wayne Huizenga]], [[DHL]], [[Samuel DiPiazza]], [[Frederick Henderson]] and other local [[South Florida]] companies.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.huizenga.nova.edu/CurrentStudents/Organizations/GBSA/GBSANewsEvents.cfm Power Lunch Series] Retrieved on July 9, 2008.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.huizenga.nova.edu/News/ Fritz Henderson and Mike Jackson] Retrieved on September 20, 2009.&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.nova.edu/cwis/pubaffairs/news/july-sept2009/gm_autonation.html Public Affairs September 2009] Retrieved on September 22, 2009.&lt;/ref&gt;

== Notable alumni ==
{{main|List of Nova Southeastern University alumni}}
Nova Southeastern University was established in 1964, but the school has quickly grown an active alumni base of over 120,000 alumni.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.nova.edu/cwis/about-nsu/presmessage.html President's Message addressing Alumni] Retrieved on January 22, 2009.&lt;/ref&gt; Many of the alumni have made many contributions to their fields of expertise.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.nova.edu/alumni/forms/alumninetwork.pdf Alumni Class notes] Retrieved on January 22, 2009.&lt;/ref&gt; The List includes alumni ranging from government officials to professional athletes. Nova Southeastern is also known for its contribution to Academia.  A large number of Nova Southeastern's doctoral degree recipients are actively pursuing research in their fields.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.nova.edu/alumni/maps.html Alumni Maps] Retrieved on January 22, 2009.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://nsuathletics.nova.edu/alumni/index.cfm Athletic Alumni] Retrieved on January 22, 2009.&lt;/ref&gt;

== See also ==
{{Portal box|Miami|University}}
* [[Independent Colleges and Universities of Florida]]
* [[List of largest United States university campuses by enrollment|Largest United States universities by enrollment]]
* [[Nova Southeastern University 2006 Workers Unionization Controversy|Workers Unionization Strike &amp; Controversy]]

== References ==
{{Reflist|colwidth=30em}}

== External links ==
{{Commons category|Nova Southeastern University}}
* [http://nova.edu/ Official website]
* [http://nsuathletics.nova.edu/ Official Athletics website]

{{Nova Southeastern University}}
{{Independent Colleges and Universities of Florida}}
{{Sunshine State Conference}}
{{Largest United States universities by enrollment}}
{{Use mdy dates|date=August 2010}}
{{Coord|26.0778954|-80.2418899|display=title}}

[[Category:Nova Southeastern University| ]]
[[Category:Universities and colleges in Broward County, Florida]]
[[Category:Universities and colleges in Florida]]
[[Category:Educational institutions established in 1964]]
[[Category:National Association of Independent Colleges and Universities members]]
[[Category:Universities and colleges accredited by the Southern Association of Colleges and Schools]]
[[Category:North Miami Beach, Florida]]

[[fa:دانشگاه نوا ساوت‌ایسترن]]
[[nl:Nova Southeastern-universiteit]]
[[no:Nova Southeastern University]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
