<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="15950685" ns="0" title="Akbar S. Ahmed"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve"> 
'''Akbar Salahuddin Ahmed''', [[Sitara-e-Imtiaz|Sitara-i-Imtiaz]], or '''Akbar Ahmed''', is currently the Ibn Khaldun Chair of Islamic Studies, [[American University]] in [[Washington, D.C.]], the First Distinguished Chair of Middle East and Islamic Studies at the [[US Naval Academy]], Annapolis,&lt;ref&gt;[https://www.usna.com/SSLPage.aspx?pid=6024 / U.S. Naval Academy]&lt;/ref&gt; and a Nonresident Senior Fellow at the Brookings Institution.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.brookings.edu/experts/ahmeda.aspx / Brookings Institute]&lt;/ref&gt; He is considered “the world’s leading authority on contemporary Islam” by the BBC.&lt;ref name=&quot;BBC&quot;&gt;[BBC Radio 2 &quot;Good Morning Sunday&quot;, October 24, 2004]&lt;/ref&gt; 

Ambassador Akbar Ahmed has advised world leaders including most recently General David Petraeus, Ambassador Richard Holbrooke, and Secretary Michael Chertoff on Islam and foreign policy. He is regularly interviewed by [[CNN]], [[CBS]], [[BBC]], and [[Fox News]] and has appeared several times on the ''[[Oprah Winfrey Show]]'' and has appeared on the Daily Show. He is the author of over a dozen award-winning books, including ''Discovering Islam'' (the basis for the BBC six-part TV series entitled “Living Islam”) and ''Journey into Islam''; his books have been translated into many languages, including Chinese and Indonesian. His latest project based in extensive fieldwork has resulted in a full length documentary, Journey into America, which has been shown at several film festivals and the book, Journey into America; the Challenge of Islam (Brookings Press, June 2010).&lt;ref name=&quot;Journey into America&quot; /&gt; &quot;A brilliant follow-up to Journey into Islam. Ahmed's insights should be required reading for anyone grappling with national security, national identity, and national cohesion in today s complex era.&quot;
— Colonel David Kilcullen, author of The Accidental Guerrilla.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.amazon.com/gp/product/0815703872/ref=pd_lpo_k2_dp_sr_1?pf_rd_p=486539851&amp;pf_rd_s=lpo-top-stripe-1&amp;pf_rd_t=201&amp;pf_rd_i=0316353299&amp;pf_rd_m=ATVPDKIKX0DER&amp;pf_rd_r=1PDMNXSWX4WTMJQ431FX#noop / Amazon]&lt;/ref&gt;

He joined the Civil Service of Pakistan (CSP), the elite cadre of the Central Superior Services of Pakistan in 1966, and held important posts in Pakistan and Bangladesh—including Commissioner, Quetta; Political Agent, South Waziristan Agency. He has also been the Ambassador from Pakistan to the UK.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.american.edu/sis/faculty/akbar.cfm / website link.]&lt;/ref&gt; 

Ambassador Ahmed is one of the world’s foremost anthropologists and was inducted into the legendary figures in Anthropology’s Hall of Fame as part of the &quot;Anthropological Ancestors&quot; audio-visual interview series at Cambridge University in July 2004. He has written extensively on the tribal areas of Pakistan, including his book Resistance and Control in Pakistan (1983), and the anthropology of Muslim societies. His most recent projects have been unprecedented large-scale anthropological studies and as one Harvard intellectual noted, he is “changing the face of anthropology.” &lt;ref name=&quot;Journey into America&quot;&gt;[http://journeyintoamerica.wordpress.com/ Journey into America.]&lt;/ref&gt;  

A prolific author, he is also a playwright and three of his plays were staged in the DC area: &quot;Noor&quot;, &quot;The Trial of Dara Shikoh&quot;, and &quot;From Waziristan to Washington: A Muslim at the Crossroads&quot;.  Two plays, &quot;[[Noor (play)]]&quot; and &quot;[[The Trial of Dara Shikoh]]&quot;, were published by [[Saqi Books]] in the summer of 2009.

Ambassador Akbar Ahmed has also been a leader in interfaith dialogue and tries to build bridges between civilizations. Along with Judea Pearl, father of slain journalist Daniel Pearl he has had public dialogues in an effort to dispel hate and ignorance. For their efforts they were awarded the prestigious Purpose Prize in 2007. Ambassador Ahmed was also the recipient of the first Gandhi Center Fellowship of Peace Award in 2004.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.gandhimemorialcenter.org/fellowship_of_peace/ http://www.gandhimemorialcenter.org/fellowship_of_peace]&lt;/ref&gt;

==Education==
Ahmed has been Visiting Professor at the [[Institute for Advanced Study]] in [[Princeton, New Jersey|Princeton]] and has taught at Princeton, Harvard and Cambridge Universities. Ahmed was awarded the Honorary Doctor of Laws by the [[University of Liverpool]], received his PhD at the School of Oriental and African Studies, [[London University]], MA and Diploma in Education from [[Cambridge University]], and Bachelor of Social Sciences (Honors) from [[Birmingham University]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.oralliterature.org/collections/amacfarlane001.html Video interview with Akbar Ahmed], Interviews with Anthropologists, World Oral Literature Project&lt;/ref&gt;

==New Book of Verse==
'''Suspended Somewhere Between''' &lt;ref&gt;[http://www.youtube.com/user/MediaHall1/ Some Poems on Youtube]&lt;/ref&gt; 

Author: Akbar Ahmed
Publisher: PM Press / Busboys and Poets &lt;ref&gt;[https://secure.pmpress.org/index.php?l=product_detail&amp;p=305/ PM Press]&lt;/ref&gt;
ISBN: 978-1-60486-485-4
Published April 2011
Format: Paperback
Size: 8 by 5
Page count: 152 Pages
Subjects: Poetry, Islam 

Akbar Ahmed’s Suspended Somewhere Between is a collection of poetry to published in April 15, 2011 from the man the BBC calls “the world’s leading authority on contemporary Islam.&quot; A mosaic of Ahmed’s life, which has traversed cultural and religious barriers, this book of verse is personal with a vocal range from introspective and reflective to romantic and emotive to historical and political. The poems take the reader from the forbidding valleys and mountains of Waziristan in the tribal areas of Pakistan to the think tanks and halls of power in Washington, DC; from the rustic tranquility of Cambridge to the urban chaos of Karachi.
 
The collection spans half a century of writing and gives the reader a front row seat to the drama of a world in turmoil. Can there be more drama than Ahmed’s first memories as a boy of four on a train through the killing fields of North India during the partition of the subcontinent in 1947? Or the breakup of Pakistan into two counties amidst mass violence in 1971? Yet, in the midst of change and uncertainty, there is the optimism and faith of a man with confidence in his fellow man and in the future, despite the knowledge that perhaps the problems and challenges of the changing world would prove to be too great. 
 
Ahmed’s poetry was a constant source of solace and renewal to which he escaped for inspiration and sanity. He loved poetry of every kind whether English, Urdu or Persian. Ahmed was as fascinated by Keats and Coleridge as he was by Rumi and Ghalib. For us, he serves as a guide to the inner recesses of the Muslim world showing us its very heart. Through the poems, the reader gets fresh insights into the Muslim world and its struggles. Above all, they carry the eternal message of hope and compassion.

'''Back Cover:'''

&quot;Anyone wanting to understand Islam today must read Akbar Ahmed's collection. We are given rare glimpses into the dilemmas, pain, and despair but ultimately love and hope of Muslims through the verses of this true renaissance man.&quot; 
—Greg Mortenson, author of Three Cups of Tea

&quot;Akbar Ahmed is a national treasure. Allow him to lead you through his tumultuous, thrilling life in this gorgeous collection of poems, written across five decades and three continents—a life of loss, despair, child-like wonder, and love.&quot;
—Daniel Futterman, actor (A Mighty Heart, as Daniel Pearl, 2007) and Oscar-nominated screenwriter (Capote, 2005).

“Ambassador Akbar Ahmed is a brilliant and wise authority on Islam, and now we have the chance to see what a beautiful soul he has. In these poems, we see the mix of the personal, political, historical, and lyrical. This book is deeply inspiring.”
—Walter Isaacson,  president and CEO of the Aspen Institute, author, former chairman and CEO of CNN, and former editor of TIME magazine.

==Journey into America: The Challenge of Islam==
His current project, “Journey into America,” is a study based in fieldwork of Muslims in America. It has resulted in a full length documentary, Journey into America, which has been shown at several film festivals and the book, Journey into America; the Challenge of Islam (Brookings Press, June 2010).

* Washington Post, A spiritual journey across America.&lt;ref&gt;[http://newsweek.washingtonpost.com/onfaith/guestvoices/2010/08/journey_across_america.html/ Washington Post, A spiritual journey across America.]&lt;/ref&gt;
* News Statesman, Jinnah and Pakistan.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.newstatesman.com/asia/2010/08/pakistan-jinnah-india-state/ News Statesman.]&lt;/ref&gt;
* Dawn Newspaper, by Reviewed By Karamatullah K. Ghori.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.dawn.com/wps/wcm/connect/dawn-content-library/dawn/in-paper-magazine/books-and-authors/making-peace00/pakistan-jinnah-india-state/ Dawn Newspaper, by Reviewed By Karamatullah K. Ghori.]&lt;/ref&gt;
* Ntional Review, by Clifford D. May.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.nationalreview.com/articles/243658/taboo-intellectuals-clifford-d-may/ Ntional Review, by Clifford D. May.]&lt;/ref&gt;
* BBC.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/world-us-canada-11076846/ BBC on Journey]&lt;/ref&gt;
* Foreign Policy’s review of Journey into America by Gerard Russell . Russell was in charge of the British government’s outreach to the Muslim world in 2001-2003. He is now an Afghanistan/Pakistan Fellow at the Harvard Kennedy School’s Carr Center for Human Rights.&lt;ref&gt;[http://afpak.foreignpolicy.com/posts/2010/06/03/the_challenge_of_islam / Foreign Policy’s review of Journey into America by Gerard Russell]&lt;/ref&gt;
* Fox News interview on Journey into America.&lt;ref&gt;[http://video.foxnews.com/v/4288589/muslim-misunderstanding/ Fox News interview on Journey into America]&lt;/ref&gt;
* On the Daily Show.&lt;ref&gt;[http://forums.thedailyshow.com/?page=ThreadView&amp;thread_id=29264/On the Daily Show with Akbar Ahmed]&lt;/ref&gt;
* Voice of America on Journey.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www1.voanews.com/english/news/usa/How-America-Looks-Through-Muslim-Eyes---99841659.html/ Voice of America on Journey]&lt;/ref&gt;
* U.S. Department of State on Journey.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.america.gov/st/peopleplace-english/2010/July/20100723164404kcsniggih0.6870233.html?CP.rss=true/ U.S. Department of State on Journey]&lt;/ref&gt;
* The Washington Post video interview with Akbar Ahmed.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.washingtonpost.com/wp-dyn/content/video/2010/06/30/VI2010063002697.html/ The Washington Post video interview with Akbar Ahmed]&lt;/ref&gt;
* The Washington Post article, by Akbar Ahmed.&lt;ref&gt;[http://newsweek.washingtonpost.com/onfaith/panelists/akbar_ahmed/2010/06/battle_for_heart_of_mcchrystal_mind_of_petraeus.html/ The Washington Post article, by Akbar Ahmed]&lt;/ref&gt;
* NPR on Journey.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.npr.org/templates/story/story.php?storyId=128545975/ NPR on Journey]&lt;/ref&gt;
* The Huffington Post, by John Milewski.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.huffingtonpost.com/john-milewski/in-search-of-muslim-ident_b_585923.html/ The Huffington Post, by John Milewski]&lt;/ref&gt;
* The Huffington Post, by Frankie Martin.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.huffingtonpost.com/frankie-martin/what-i-learned-about-amer_b_619534.html/ The Huffington Post, by Frankie Martin ]&lt;/ref&gt;
* The Washington Post, by Jeff Stein.&lt;ref&gt;[http://blog.washingtonpost.com/spy-talk/2010/05/pakistani_scholar_says_us_musl.html / The Washington Post, by Jeff Stein]&lt;/ref&gt;
* The book was discussed on BBC America and BBC World on May 31, at 7 pm, and again on June 10, at 12.15.&lt;ref&gt;[http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/programmes/world_news_america/8718340.stm / Journey into America on BBC ]&lt;/ref&gt;
* The U.K. Guardian Newspaper.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.guardian.co.uk/commentisfree/cifamerica/2010/may/31/islam-america-religion / The U.K. Guardian Newspaper on Journey into America]&lt;/ref&gt;
* National Cathedral Review of Journey into America - by The Rev. Dr. Carol M. Flett, Interfaith Programs Coordinator Washington National Cathedral, Washington, D.C.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.nationalcathedral.org/learn/bookReview201006.shtml   / National Cathedral Review of Journey into America]&lt;/ref&gt;
* News Chanell 8 with Akbar Ahmed.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.letstalklive.tv/search.cfm?k=akbar+ahmed&amp;submit=GO / News Chanell 8 with Akbar Ahmed]&lt;/ref&gt;
* Review of Journey into America by Dr. Maleeha Lodhi, former Pakistani Ambassador to the UK and US.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.khaleejtimes.com/DisplayArticleNew.asp?xfile=/data/opinion/2010/June/opinion_June56.xml&amp;section=opinion / Review of Journey into America by Dr. Maleeha Lodhi, former Pakistani Ambassador to the UK and US]&lt;/ref&gt;
* Common Ground News Service on Journey.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.khaleejtimes.com/DisplayArticleNew.asp?xfile=/data/opinion/2010/June/opinion_June56.xml&amp;section=opinion  / Common Ground News Service on Journey]&lt;/ref&gt;
* Pakistan Link on Journey.&lt;ref&gt;[http://pakistanlink.org/Opinion/2010/June10/25/02.HTM / Pakistan Link on Journey]&lt;/ref&gt;

==Selected Books==
* ''Journey into America; the Challenge of Islam'' (Brookings Press, June 2010).
* ''Journey into Islam: The Crisis of Globalization'', Brookings Press.
* ''Knowledge: Why Civilizations Rise and Fall, with Amineh Hoti'', under preparation, Polity Press, Cambridge.
* ''After Terror: Promoting Dialogue Among Civilizations''; Co-Edited by Brian Forst, Polity Press, 2005.
* ''Islam Under Siege: Living Dangerously in a Post-Honor World''; Polity Press, 2003.
* ''The Future of Anthropology: Its Relevance to the Contemporary World''; Co-Edited by Chris Shore, Athlone Press, 1999.
* ''Islam Today: A Short Introduction to The Muslim World''; I.B. Tauris, 1998.
* ''Jinnah, Pakistan and Islamic Identity''; Routledge, 1997.
* ''Islam, Globalization and Postmodernity''; Routledge, with Hastings Donnan, 1994.
* ''Discovering Islam: Making Sense of Muslim History and Society''; Routledge, 1993.
* ''Postmodernism and Islam: Predicament and Promise''; Routledge, 1992.
* ''Resistance and Control in Pakistan''; Routledge, 1991.
* ''Pakistan: The Social Sciences' Perspective''; Oxford University Press, 1990.
* ''Toward Islamic Anthropology: Definition, Dogma, and Directions''; Vanguard Books, 1987.
* ''Religion and Politics in Muslim Society: Order and Conflict in Pakistan''; Royal Book Co., 1987.
* ''Pieces of Green, the Sociology of Change in Pakistan, 1964-1974''; Royal Book Co., 1977.
* ''Social and economic change in the Tribal Areas, 1972-1976''; Oxford University Press, 1977.
* ''Mataloona: Pukhto Proverbs'', Oxford University Press, 1975.
* ''Mansehra: A Journey, Ferozsons, Pakistan'', 1973.

==Selected Plays==
* ''[[Noor (play)]]'', Saqi Books, London, 2009. Part of the summer Festival at Theater J in Washington, DC in 2007
* ''[[The Trial of Dara Shikoh]]'', The Buxton Initiative, Washington DC, Pakistan Link, 2008 and Saqi Books, London, 2009
* ''Waziristan to Washington: A Muslim at the Crossroads'', a “memoire monologue” was first performed by Akbar Ahmed at the Washington DC, Jewish Community Center, Dialogues and Public Affairs, on August 22 and October 2, and the Katzen Arts Center on December 18, 2008, and at Theater J on March 23, 2009.&lt;ref&gt;[http://pakistanlink.org/Commentary/2009/Nov09/20/03.HTM / Waziristan to Washington: A Muslim at the Crossroads, by Elise Alexander]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.washingtondcjcc.org/social-networks/public-affairs// ''Waziristan to Washington]&lt;/ref&gt;

==Selected Articles==
# 	“America has yet to grasp the cost of losing in Afghanistan”. Guardian Newspaper, October, 2009.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.guardian.co.uk/commentisfree/cifamerica/2009/oct/05/afghanistan-us-strategy-mcchrystal-troops / Guardian.co.uk]&lt;/ref&gt;
#	“Swat in the eye of the storm: Interview with Akbar Ahmed”. Anthropology Today, Volume 25 Issue 5, October, 2009.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www3.interscience.wiley.com/journal/122614640/abstract?CRETRY=1&amp;SRETRY=0 / Anthropology Today]&lt;/ref&gt;
#	“Islam in Today’s World: A Conversation with Akbar Ahmed”. Featured in Anthropology Today, Vol. 23, No. 1, in February 2007.
#	“Talking Can Stop Hate” was featured as the “Big Idea!” in AARP the Magazine, in the March/April 2007 issue.
#	“Bush Still Doesn’t Get It” featured in the Outlook section of the Washington Post July 22, 2007.

==Media==
#	Ahmed regularly appears on CNN  •  CBC  •  BBC  • ARY TV  •  CNBC  • Night Line  • Interfaith Voices, NPR .
#	Presented and narrated “Living Islam”, the six-part BBC television series, in 1993.
#	 Presented “The Glories of Islamic Art”, the three-part television series for Channel 5, UK, broadcast in 2006.
#	Appeared three times on the Oprah Winfrey Show.
#	Appeared on the Sir David Frost Show (along with Lord Owen) on Al Jazeera.
#	Newsnight including for the Annual Review 2007.
#	Initiated, developed and completed “The Jinnah Quartet” – a feature film  •  a documentary  •  two books on M.A. Jinnah, the founder of Pakistan.
#	Consultant and interviewed for “Rumi Returning”, a major television film on the mystic poet.
#	Panelist with the new online feature, “On Faith,” for the Washington Post and Newsweek
#	“Encountering Islam”, Audio CD series, NowYouKnow Media, Washington DC.
#	Senior Advisor to an innovative on-line project for an Islamic syllabus for Jones Knowledge Inc.

==Distinctions and Distinguished Lectures==
* Awarded the [[Star of Excellence]], one of Pakistan’s highest honors.
* Awarded Sir Percy Sykes Memorial Medal by the [[Royal Society for Asian Affairs]] in London.
* In 2005 the [[National Cathedral]] held a special Evensong Service to honor Ahmed.
* First Annual Bridge Builder’s Award, Interfaith Conference of Metropolitan Washington.
* Humanitarian Award, the highest honor of the Chapel of Four Chaplains.
* The Professor of the Year Award for Washington DC by the [[Carnegie Foundation for the Advancement of Teaching]] and the [[Council for Advancement and Support of Education]] (2004)
* The first Gandhi Center Fellowship of Peace Award.
* Invited to join the World Wisdom Council.
* Delivered the keynote address at the annual conference of the Council for a Parliament of the World’s Religions at Monterrey, Mexico, September 23, 2007.
* Joined the Global Advisory Council of PlayPumps International (2008).
* Centennial Honorary Chair of the Washington National Cathedral Centennial Celebration (along with Presidents Jimmy Carter, George H.W. Bush, and Justice Sandra Day O’Connor).
* Trustee since 2001 of the World Faiths Development Dialogue set up by the [[Archbishop of Canterbury]] and the president of the [[World Bank]].
* Trustee on the Board of the Council for a Parliament of the World’s Religions.
* Founding member of the First Abrahamic Summit, Washington DC, and continues to be a member of the Abrahamic Roundtable, organized by the National Cathedral.
* Board of Directors, Hollings Center, and member, Abrahamic Program Advisory Committee, Chautauqua Institution.
* Distinguished Senior Fellow of the Hasan Family Foundation
* Senior Fellow of The Case Foundation.
* Spoke at the Chairman’s Distinguished Speakers Lecture Series at the Pentagon.
* Inaugural lectures for the first Chair in Jewish-Muslim Studies at the [[University of Illinois-Chicago]].
* Along with Ambassador Doug Holladay founded the Buxton Initiative for Dialogue.
* Lectured at a [[World Affairs Council]] event along with Dick Cheney, Dr. Henry Kissinger and Bernard Lewis.
* Member of the host committee for [[Internews]]’ 25th anniversary celebration in May 2007.
* First muslim to lecture at the [[Holocaust Museum]] in Washington DC.
* Principal investigator for Islam in the Age of Globalization, a project supported by the [[Brookings Institution]], [[American University]] and the [[Pew Research Center]], and visiting fellow at Brookings in addition to his appointment at American University.
* Along with [[Judea Pearl|Dr. Judea Pearl]] delivered the keynote address at the Greater Kansas City Festival of Faiths in the Village Church November 2007.
* Keynote address at a conference on [[The Way Forward]] at the Centre for Muslim-Jewish Relations, Cambridge.
* Keynote address at the 60th Anniversary of the Independence of India and Pakistan, hosted by the [[University of Southampton]].
* Special lecture at the [[London School of Economics]] and invited as an expert to address the All-Parties Committee on Terrorism at the [[House of Commons of the United Kingdom]] in the summer of 2007.
* Keynote at the [[Drury University]], convention series, 2007-08.
* McMurrrin Lecture in Religion and Culture, [[University of Utah]], Tanner Humanities Center, 2008-09.
* President's Distinguished Lecture at the [[University of Vermont]] in 2008.
* Recommended speaker of the World Affairs Council of America.
* One of the 138 Muslim leaders who write to the [[Pope]] and other christian leaders suggesting dialogue and one of the original signatories of the Muslim letter to Jewish leaders circulated in 2008.
* Led a Muslim delegation to the [[Holocaust Museum]] in December 2006.
* Attended President Ford's funeral ceremony at the [[National Cathedral]] where he was part of the &quot;Procession Order&quot; as &quot;Representative of Faith&quot; escorting the casket, and delivered the invocation at the Mayor’s Inaugural Prayer Service in Washington DC.
* Non-Resident [[Senior Fellow]] at Brookings.
* Given the Key to the city of Houston and Portland, Maine, by the respective Mayors.
* Member of the [[Incident Management Team]] for the [[Department of Homeland Security]].
* Mentioned in “Congressional Record – Proceedings and Debates of the 109th Congress, Second Session, Washington, Friday, September 29, 2006, House of Representatives: Tribute to Dr. Judea Pearl and Dr. Akbar Ahmed”.
* Along with Dr. [[Judea Pearl]], Ahmed was finalist in the “Most Inspiring Person of the Year 2005” poll conducted by [[BeliefNet]].
* Awarded the first ever Purpose Prize Award in 2006.
* Honored at the [[National Cathedral]] in the fall.
* Received the 2008 Rumi Peace and Dialogue Award.
* Awarded the annual Abraham Joshua Herschel-Martin Luther King, Jr. Award for Interfaith Activism on January 19, 2009, Park Avenue Christian Church, New York.

==See also==
*[[Contemporary Islamic philosophy]]
*[[Islamism]]

==References==
&lt;references /&gt;

==External links==
*[http://www.american.edu/sis/faculty/akbar.cfm Faculty Biography at American University]
*[http://www.american.edu/sis/faculty/akbar.cfm Official website at American University]
*[http://islamfortoday.com/akbar.htm Articles on Islam by Professor Akbar S. Ahmad]
*[http://www.abc.net.au/foreign/stories/s372713.htm Interview with Professor Ahmed from the Foreign Correspondent, September 19, 2001]
*[http://www.islamfortoday.org/akbar04.htm &quot;Islam and Freedom of Thought&quot; by Akbar Ahmed and Lawrence Rosen]
*[http://pewforum.org/events/index.php?EventID=124 &quot;Five Years After 9/11, 'Dialogue' with Islam Cause for Hope&quot;: Q&amp;A with Akbar Ahmed by Mark O'Keefe]
*[http://www.publicschoolinsights.org/?storyId=8486 &quot;Globalization in our Public Schools&quot; by Akbar Ahmed posted 10/16/08]
*{{IMDb name|0014137}}

{{Persondata &lt;!-- Metadata: see [[Wikipedia:Persondata]]. --&gt;
| NAME              = Ahmed, Akbar
| ALTERNATIVE NAMES =
| SHORT DESCRIPTION =
| DATE OF BIRTH     =
| PLACE OF BIRTH    =
| DATE OF DEATH     =
| PLACE OF DEATH    =
}}
{{DEFAULTSORT:Ahmed, Akbar}}
[[Category:Year of birth missing (living people)]]
[[Category:Living people]]
[[Category:Alumni of the School of Oriental and African Studies]]
[[Category:Alumni of the University of Cambridge]]
[[Category:Alumni of the University of Birmingham]]
[[Category:Pakistani anthropologists]]
[[Category:Pakistani bureaucrats]]
[[Category:Pakistani diplomats]]
[[Category:Pakistani film producers]]
[[Category:Pakistani scholars]]
[[Category:Pakistani writers]]
[[Category:American anthropologists]]
[[Category:International relations scholars]]
[[Category:Islamic studies scholars]]
[[Category:Muhajir people]]
[[Category:Muslim scholars]]
[[Category:Muslim scholars of Islam]]
[[Category:American writers of Pakistani descent]]
[[Category:Sitara-i-Imtiaz]]
[[Category:Pakistani filmmakers]]
[[Category:American University people]]
[[Category:American dramatists and playwrights of Asian descent]]

[[ur:اکبر صلاح الدین احمد]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
