<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="1597271" ns="0" title="Netscape (version 7)"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Infobox software
| name                   = Netscape
| logo                   = [[Image:Netscape7Logo.png|50px]]
| screenshot             = [[Image:Netscape 7 En.PNG|250px]]
| caption                = Netscape 7.2 under Windows
| developer              = [[America Online|AOL]]
| released               = ?
| frequently_updated     = yes&lt;!-- Release version update? Don't edit this page, just click on the version number! --&gt;
| programming language   = ?
| operating system       = [[Cross-platform]]
| language               = ?
| genre                  = [[Internet suite]]
| license                =
| website                = [http://archive.netscape.com/ archive.netscape.com]
}}
'''Netscape 7''' was a series of [[proprietary software|proprietary]] [[cross-platform]] [[Internet suite]]s created by [[Netscape Communications Corporation]] and then in-house by [[America Online|AOL]] to continue the Netscape series after [[Netscape 6]]. There were three main editions released from the Netscape 7 series; being Netscape 7.0, 7.1 and 7.2. In the last version, it consisted of the following major components:

*a [[web browser]]
*an [[e-mail client|e-mail]] and [[news client]], ''[[Netscape Mail &amp; Newsgroups]]''
*an [[address book]]
*an [[HTML editor]], ''[[Netscape Composer]]''
*an [[IRC client]]
*an [[instant messaging]] client, ''[[AOL Instant Messenger]]''
*[[AOL Radio|Radio@Netscape]]

The suite was originally superseded by [[Netscape Browser]], later [[Netscape Navigator 9]], and its [[Netscape Mail &amp; Newsgroups|Mail &amp; Newsgroups]] client was succeeded by [[Netscape Messenger 9]] in 2007.

==History and development==
Netscape 7.0 was released in 2002. It was based on a more stable and notably faster [[Mozilla Application Suite|Mozilla]] 1.0 core and bundled with extras like integrated [[AOL Instant Messenger]], integrated [[ICQ]], [[AOL Radio|Radio@Netscape]], and new features such as tabbed browsing [http://www.pcworld.com/article/id,100564-page,1/article.html]. The market responded to what was essentially a repackaged version of [[Mozilla Application Suite]] (swollen with integrated tools to access proprietary services owned by AOL) by ignoring it. Competition from mature and competent non-Microsoft alternatives such as the [[Opera (web browser)|Opera]] browser and the regular Mozilla distribution was a major factor. A point release of version 7.1 (based on Mozilla 1.4) was similarly ignored.

AOL announced on July 15, 2003 that it was laying off all its remaining development staff working on the Netscape version of Mozilla. Combined with AOL's [[United States v. Microsoft|antitrust case]] court settlement with Microsoft to use Internet Explorer in future versions of the AOL software, this seemed to mark the effective end of development on Netscape Navigator, the open source projects notwithstanding. Many believed that no further versions of the browser would be released and that the Netscape [[brand name]] would live on only as the name of AOL's low-cost [[dial-up access|dial-up]] internet service.

Netscape 7.2 was released on August 17, 2004, though AOL did not restart the Netscape browser division (instead, they developed it in-house). It was very similar to Netscape 7.1 and the only new feature in it was the Netscape Toolbar, which was developed by [[mozdev.org]].

Though many had believed Netscape 7 would be the last version of Netscape to be released, AOL, in May 2005, came out with Netscape Browser version 8. It included improved security and the ability to natively use the [[Gecko (layout engine)|Gecko]] [[layout engine]] used by Mozilla and its derivatives. It also has Internet Explorer's [[Trident (layout engine)|Trident]] as a possible rendering engine to use, which enables the user to switch to its rendering system to display web pages that do not work well with Gecko. This use of the Trident engine allows the use of [[ActiveX]] controls and brings all ActiveX security problems associated with Internet Explorer.

[[Netscape 9]] superseded Netscape 8 in October 2007, but Netscape's browser was discontinued altogether on March 1, 2008.

===Release history===
* Netscape 7.0 PR1 &amp;ndash; Preview Release 1
* Netscape 7.0 &amp;ndash; August 29, 2002 (based on Mozilla 1.0.1)
* Netscape 7.01 &amp;ndash; December 10, 2002 (based on Mozilla 1.0.2)
* Netscape 7.02 &amp;ndash; February 18, 2003 (based on Mozilla 1.0.2)
* Netscape 7.1 &amp;ndash; June 30, 2003 (based on Mozilla 1.4)
* Netscape 7.2 &amp;ndash; August 17, 2004 (based on Mozilla 1.7)

==See also==
*[[Netscape]]
*[[Mozilla Application Suite]]

==References==
{{Reflist}}


{{sequence|
 prev=[[Netscape 6]]|
 list= [[Netscape 7]]|
 next=[[Netscape Browser]] (8)|
}}
{{Netscape}}

{{Use mdy dates|date=September 2010}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Netscape (Version 7)}}
[[Category:Netscape]]
[[Category:Internet suites]]
[[Category:Discontinued web browsers]]

[[ko:넷스케이프 (웹 브라우저)]]
[[pt:Netscape 7]]
[[zh:Netscape 7]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
