<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="16085301" ns="0" title="Kent Smetters"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Infobox scientist
|name              = Kent Smetters
|image             = Replace this image male.svg
|image_size       = 150px
|caption           =
|birth_date        =
|birth_place       =
|death_date        =
|death_place       =
|residence         = [[Philadelphia, PA]]
|citizenship       =
|nationality       =
|ethnicity         =
|field             = [[Economics]]
|work_institutions = [[University of Pennsylvania|University of Pennsylvania's]] [[Wharton School]]
|alma_mater        = [[Ohio State University]], [[Harvard University]]
|doctoral_advisor  =
|doctoral_students =
|known_for         = [[Insurance]], [[Risk Management]], [[Social Security (United States)|Social Security]] Policy
|influences        =
|influenced        =
|prizes            =
|religion          =
|footnotes         =
}}
'''Kent Smetters''' is an academic, entrepreneur, and former government official.
&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.j-bradford-delong.net/movable_type/2004_archives/000379.html Online Journal on Social Security Reform] retrieved March 4, 2008&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.upenn.edu/almanac/volumes/v55/n10/smetters.html University of Pennsylvania Almanac] retrieved October 28, 2008&lt;/ref&gt;

==Early years==
Smetters was raised in Ohio. He received his bachelor's degrees in [[Economics]] and [[Computer Science]] from the [[Ohio State University]] in 1990, and Master and PhD degrees in Economics from [[Harvard University]] in 1992 and 1995 respectively.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.wharton.upenn.edu/faculty/smetters.html Wharton School Faculty] retrieved on March 4, 2008&lt;/ref&gt;

== Career ==
=== Academics ===
Smetters is a Professor of [[Insurance]] and [[Risk Management]] at the [[University of Pennsylvania|University of Pennsylvania's]] [[Wharton School|Wharton School of Business]] and the Joseph E. and Ruth E. Boettner Professor of Financial Gerontology. [[Financial Gerontology]] is the study of aging and related financial and business impacts, applying the functionality of gerontology to the concepts of financial planning. Professor Smetters has written on government [[debt]] and [[Social Security (United States)|Social Security]] policy and has a strong interest in financial planning, analyzing relationships between the economic wellbeing of the elderly and their social, legal, psychological, physical, and environmental well-being. Smetters has also written about the need for insurance industry reform and supports the notion that the private sector should provide [[terrorism insurance]] or protection instead of government.&lt;ref&gt;[http://opim.wharton.upenn.edu/risk/downloads/04-13-HK.pdf Think Tank Publication] retrieved March 8, 2008&lt;/ref&gt; He has held visiting appointments with the Department of Economics at [[Stanford University]]. Smetters has also published several papers and chapters with the [[National Bureau of Economic Research]]&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.nber.org/authors/kent_smetters NBER Publications by Kent Smetters] retrieved October 7, 2010&lt;/ref&gt;., where he continues to be a Research Associate in Public Economics and Faculty Research Fellow for the Aging Program. Since 2000, he has been with the Michigan Retirement Research Center as a Research Associate.

=== Government and Policy ===
From 1995-1999, Smetters was an Economist at the [[Congressional Budget Office]]. In 1999, he served as a Consultant for the [[World Bank]]. He became Deputy Assistant Secretary for Economic Policy of the [[United States Treasury]] in 2001, where he stayed on for another year as a Consultant. He was also a Member of the Blue Ribbon Advisory Panel on Dynamic Scoring, [[U.S. Congress]] from 2002-2003. He is a visiting scholar of the [[American Enterprise Institute]] for Public Policy Research.

=== RotoHog ===
He co-founded Sports Composite DE, Inc. with [[David Wu (entrepreneur)|David Wu]] in 2006 which developed the [[RotoHog]] fantasy sports game. RotoHog is a digital platform developer that designs, implements and markets fantasy services for media and advertising partners. The company builds, delivers and manages co-branded fantasy sports games for major media companies, sports companies and professional sports leagues.

RotoHog is also the provider of nba.com's NBA Stock Exchange and commissioner games.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.nba.com/global/top_10_fantasy_picks_071011.html NBA reference to partnership with RotoHog] retrieved October 7, 2010&lt;/ref&gt; In 2009, RotoHog began to provide games for Fox Sports in Spanish and the AVP Pro Beach Volleyball tour.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.socaltech.com/rotohog_signs_fox_sports_on_latin_american_deal/s-0020575.html RotoHog Signs Fox Sports On Latin American Deal] retrieved October 7, 2010&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.mediapost.com/publications/?fa=Articles.showArticle&amp;art_aid=101626 Pro Beach Volleyball Taps RotoHog To Create Fantasy Game] retrieved October 7, 2010&lt;/ref&gt; Smetters is no longer with the company but serves on the Board of Advisors.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.toacorn.com/news/2007/0222/Sports/073.html Fantasy Sports' New Marketplace] retrieved March 4, 2008&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://investing.businessweek.com/research/stocks/private/person.asp?personId=36477744 Online Business Magazine Profile: Kent Smetters] retrieved March 4, 2008&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.entrepreneur.com/magazine/entrepreneur/2008/may/192752.html Entrepreneur Magazine: A Partnership Success Story] retrieved 21st April 2008&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Veritat Advisors, Inc ===
After several years in the financial industry, Smetters co-founded the company [[Veritat Advisors]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.veritat.com Veritat Advisors] retrieved October 6, 2010&lt;/ref&gt; Smetters is the President of Veritat Advisors.

Veritat positions itself as one of the first financial advisory firms to deliver full-service and objective [[financial planning]] &lt;ref&gt;[http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=EMDomYykgeg&amp;feature=youtu.be. Fox Business News: How Online Financial Planning Works] retrieved August 16, 2010&lt;/ref&gt; at an affordable price. A key competitive feature of Veritat is its simple and transparent pricing.&lt;ref&gt;[http://online.wsj.com/article/SB10001424052748703988304575413422740203834.html?mod=wsj_share_twitter Low-Cost Financial Planning: The Next Wave] retrieved August 7, 2010&lt;/ref&gt;

== Publications and Awards ==
=== Publications ===
* Ricardian Equivalence: Long-Run Leviathan. (Journal of Public Economics 73: 395-421, 1999).
* Co-author of Privatizing Social Security in the U.S. ­— Comparing the Options. (Review of Economic Dynamics 2: 532-574, 1999).
* Co-author of Simulating Fundamental Tax Reform in the U.S. (American Economic Review 91.3: 574-595 June, 2001).
* The Dynamic Properties of the Neoclassical Growth Model with CES Production. (Review of Economic Dynamics 6,3: 697-707 2003).
* Co-author of Fiscal and Generational Imbalances: New Budget Measures for New Budget Priorities (American Enterprise Institute Press, 2003)
* Co-editor with [[Olivia S. Mitchell|Dr. Olivia Mitchell]], of The Pension Challenge: Risk Transfers and Retirement Income Security (Oxford University Press, 2004).
* Co-author of Opting Out of Social Security (Journal of Public Economics 88: 1295-1306, 2004).
* Co-author of Consumption Taxes, Risk Sharing and Economic Efficiency (Journal of Political Economy 113(5): 1088–1115, October 2005).
* Sharing Financial Risks across Non-Trading Generations: A Decentralized Alternative to Government Ownership of Private Equities (Journal of Monetary Economics 53(7),2006)
* The Optimal Design of Social Security Benefits (Michigan Retirement Research Center, Paper No. 2008-197, September 2008)
* He has written extensively for The Wall Street Journal and other public media, in addition to dozens of academic research papers and book chapters.

=== Awards ===

* Fellowship, National Science Foundation, 1990–93;
* TIAA-CREF Paul A. Samuelson, Certificate of Excellence, 2002;
* Robert C. Witt Award for the best paper published in the Journal of Risk and Insurance, 2000

==References==
{{reflist}}

{{Persondata &lt;!-- Metadata: see [[Wikipedia:Persondata]]. --&gt;
| NAME              =Smetters, Kent
| ALTERNATIVE NAMES =
| SHORT DESCRIPTION =
| DATE OF BIRTH     =
| PLACE OF BIRTH    =
| DATE OF DEATH     =
| PLACE OF DEATH    =
}}
{{DEFAULTSORT:Smetters, Kent}}
[[Category:American economists]]
[[Category:Ohio State University alumni]]
[[Category:Harvard University alumni]]
[[Category:University of Pennsylvania faculty]]
[[Category:Living people]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
