<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="16084878" ns="0" title="Women in Turkey"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Wikify|date=October 2010}}
{{update|date=November 2010}}
{{Infobox Ethnic group
|image = &lt;div style=&quot;white-space:nowrap;&quot;&gt;&lt;!--If you swap out an image, change the &quot;x##px&quot; entry for EACH image in the row so that the width of the row lines up with the others--&gt;[[File:Mihrimah Sultan.jpg|x99px]][[File:Sabiha gökçen.jpg|x99px]][[File:Halide-edip-adivar-b3.jpg|x99px]]&lt;br /&gt;[[File:Feriha Tevfik.gif|x99px]][[File:Cahide Sonku.jpg|x99px]]&lt;br /&gt;[[File:Hadise Açıkgöz.jpg|x99px]]&lt;br /&gt;
[[Mihrimah Sultana]] • [[Sabiha Gökçen]] • [[Halide Edip Adıvar]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Feriha Tevfik]] • [[Cahide Sonku]] &lt;br /&gt;[[Hadise Açıkgöz]] 
}}
'''Women in [[Turkey]]''' continue to struggle with [[gender gap]], especially in the more conservative regions where traditional Islamic values are seen by some as impeding their social advancement.&lt;ref name=&quot;bbc-04-11&quot;&gt;[http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/world-europe-12675869 BBC News - Women in Turkey continue to struggle with gender gap]&lt;/ref&gt; There are only 65 [[women's shelter]]s in the country, many of them underfunded.&lt;ref name=&quot;amnesty&quot;/&gt;

== History ==
{{unreferenced section|date=October 2011}}
[[Image:Halide-edip-adivar-b3.jpg|thumb|Halide Edip Adıvar was a [[Turkish people|Turkish]] novelist and [[feminism|feminist]] political leader.]]
Although Women in [[Harem]] strongly influenced Ottoman Sultans on politics, Turkish women started to involve [[politics]] after [[Tanzimat]] era. [[Halide Edip Adıvar]] was one of the first women in [[Ottoman Empire]] interested in politics. In her novels she criticised the low social status of Turkish women and what she saw as the lack of interest of most women in changing their situation.

Thanks to Atatürk, the founder of the Republic, who believed in the necessity of complete equality between women and men, all the political rights considered to be the foundation of citizenship rights were recognized for women in Turkey in a very short period of time. Women in Turkey obtained the right to vote and be elected in municipal elections in 1930 and in parliamentary elections in 1934. Prior to that date, the number of countries where women had the right to vote and be elected as members of parliament was 28 and the number of countries where women actually were elected as members of parliament was 17. When it is taken into consideration that women obtained the right to vote in 1944 in France, in 1945 in Italy and in 1948 in Belgium, it appears that Turkey was way ahead compared with many countries.
A total of 18 women became members of parliament in 1935, which was the year when women members were represented at the highest ratio in the parliament with 4.6 percent. However, as of 1946, when the multi-party system was adopted, a decrease in the number of women deputies was observed. 

In 1980s, when women's movement gained impetus all over the world, there observed an increase in the number of voluntary women institutions established in Turkey. Through the mobilization of the general public, these women's institutions have played a significant part in leading the amendment and abolition of certain items discriminating women in both Civil Law and Penal Code and also have taken an active part in their consciousness-raising endeavors on women' problems. In recent years, alongside with the increase in the number of the centers for helping women who were victims of violence or abused, it is noticeable that the associations with special tasks of supporting and reinforcing the women's participation in politics have also come into being. The Foundation for the Advancement and Recognition of Turkish Women, The Women's Shelter Foundation of Purple Roof, the Association of Women's Rights Protection, the Association for the Support and Training of Women Candidates are just a few names among more than 150 voluntary women's organizations working nationwide.

The acceptance of women's issues as an independent political and planning problem was discussed for the first time in the Fifth Five Year Development Plan (1985–1990), and &quot;the General Directorate for the Status and Problems of Women&quot; was established as a national mechanism in 1990. The General Directorate, which was connected to the Prime Ministry in 1991, has been carrying out its activities under the responsibility of a State Ministry. It conducts a large variety of activities with the objective of protecting women's rights, of strengthening the position of women in social, economic, cultural and political life, and of providing the equal utilization of rights, opportunities and capacities. In 1993, [[Tansu Çiller]] became the first female Prime Minister of Turkey.

==Culture and laws==
The article 41 of the [[Turkish Constitution]] was recently{{when|date=November 2011}} revised to read that the family is &quot;based on equality between spouses&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;tk-ds&quot;&gt;[http://stopvaw.org/turkey.html Stop Violence Against Women website]&lt;/ref&gt; The new code also granted women equal rights to property acquired during marriage, which was supposedly meant to give economic value to women’s labor within the family household.&lt;ref name=&quot;tk-ds&quot;/&gt;
&lt;!-- Deleted image removed: [[Image:Ottoman Women.jpg|thumb|Ottoman Turkish women in a harem]] --&gt;
The minimum age for marriage was also raised to 18 (17 with parental consent).&lt;ref name=&quot;tk-ds&quot;/&gt; In cases of forced marriage, women have right to ask an annulment within the first 5 years of marriage.&lt;ref name=&quot;tk-ds&quot;/&gt; In 2004, an update to article 10 of the constitution placed the responsibility for establishing gender equality on the state: &quot;men and women have equal rights. The state shall have the obligation to ensure that this equality exists in practice&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;tk-ds&quot;/&gt;

In 2005, the Turkish penal code was changed to criminalize [[marital rape]] and harshen the sentences for those convicted of honor killings, which previousl carried reduced sentenced because of &quot;provocation&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;pbs&quot;/&gt; The  Human Rights Directorate reported that the number of honor killings committed in Turkey rose to 220 in 2007, with most of the killings occurring in major cities.&lt;ref name=&quot;pbs&quot;&gt;[http://www.pbs.org/newshour/indepth_coverage/europe/turkey/women.html In Turkey, Degrees of Change in Women's Rights -- November 6, 2008 | Online NewsHour | PBS]&lt;/ref&gt;

In [[Eastern Anatolia Region, Turkey|Eastern]] and [[Southeastern Anatolia Region, Turkey|Southeastern Anatolia]] regions, older attitudes prevail among the local [[Kurdish people|Kurdish]], [[Turkish people|Turkish]] and [[Arabic people|Arab]] populations, and women still face [[domestic violence]], forced marriages, and so-called [[honor killing]]s.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://articles.latimes.com/2007/jan/09/world/fg-honor9 |accessdate=2008-08-06 |title=Taking the 'honor' out of killing women |work=[[Los Angeles Times]] |date=2007-01-09 |first=Tracy |last=Wilkinson
}}&lt;/ref&gt; In 2008, critics have pointed out that Turkey has become a major market for foreign women who are coaxed and forcibly brought to the country by international mafia to work as [[Sexual slavery|sex slaves]], especially in big and touristic cities.&lt;ref&gt;[http://gvnet.com/humantrafficking/Turkey.htm Human Trafficking &amp; Modern-day Slavery - Turkey&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.newyorker.com/reporting/2008/05/05/080505fa_fact_finnegan?currentPage=all |title=The Countertraffickers: Rescuing the victims of the global sex trade |date=2008-05-05 |accessdate=2008-08-06 |work=[[The New Yorker|New Yorker]] |first=William |last=Finnegan
}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.iht.com/articles/2005/06/27/news/turkey.php |title=Turkey's sex trade entraps Slavic women |work=[[International Herald Tribune]] |first=Craig S |last=Smith |date=2005-06-28 |accessdate=2008-08-06
}}&lt;/ref&gt; The [[Headscarf controversy in Turkey|Islamic headscarf]] is banned in state offices, schools and universities, but is still worn by more than 60% of Turkish women.&lt;ref&gt;[http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/europe/7025294.stm BBC NEWS | Europe | Women condemn Turkey constitution]&lt;/ref&gt; 

According to report by the Turkish government dating from 2009, 42% of the surveyed women said they had been physically or sexually abused by their husband or partner.&lt;ref&gt;[http://articles.cnn.com/2011-07-24/world/turkey.women.protest_1_progressive-laws-turkish-government-protection-order?_s=PM:WORLD Marchers demand better protection for women in Turkey - CNN]&lt;/ref&gt; Almost half of them never speaking to anyone about this, and only 8% approach government institutions for support.&lt;ref name=&quot;amnesty&quot;/&gt; When they do approach them, police and gendarme sometimes prefer to attempt to “reconcile” the families rather than protecting them.&lt;ref name=&quot;amnesty&quot;/&gt; While the rates of violence are particularly high among poor, rural women, one third of the women in the highest economic brackets have also been subject to domestic violence.&lt;ref name=&quot;amnesty&quot;/&gt;

== Education and employment ==
{{seealso|Education in Turkey}}
Female [[illiteracy]] is a major issue in Turkey, with 1 out of 5 women being unable to read or write.&lt;ref name=&quot;glob-giv&quot;&gt;[http://www.globalgiving.org/projects/turkey-literacy-for-women/ Turkey literacy for women - GlobalGiving]&lt;/ref&gt; Illiteracy is particularly prevalent among rural women, who are often not sent to school as girls.&lt;ref name=&quot;glob-giv&quot;/&gt; Half of girls aged between 15 and 19 are neither in the education system nor in the workforce.&lt;ref name=&quot;hdn-2&quot;/&gt; The government and various other foundations are engaged in education campaigns in Southeastern [[Anatolia]] to improve the [[Literacy|rate of literacy]] and education levels of women.&lt;ref name=&quot;Literacy&quot;&gt;{{cite news|url = http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/europe/3753582.stm |title=Turkish girls in literacy battle|first=Jonny |last=Dymond|work=[[BBC News]]|accessdate=2006-12-11|date=2004-10-18}}&lt;/ref&gt; A 2008 poll by the Women Entrepreneurs Association of Turkey showed that almost half of urban Turkish women believe economic independence for women is unnecessary reflecting, in the view of psychologist Leyla Navaro, a heritage of patriarchy.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.turkishdailynews.com.tr/article.php?enewsid=116153 |accessdate=2008-09-24 |title=Half of women say they do not need economic independence |work=[[Turkish Daily News]] |date=2008-09-24
}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Women’s participation in the Turkish labor force is very low: out of 26 million employable women, only 5.9 million are in the labor force.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.hurriyetdailynews.com/n.php?n=turkey-needs-more-women-in-business-2011-09-30 Turkey needs more women in business - Hurriyet Daily News]&lt;/ref&gt; 23.4% of women have either been forced by men to quit their jobs or prevented from working.&lt;ref name=&quot;hdn-1&quot;&gt;[http://www.hurriyetdailynews.com/n.php?n=women-murder-victims-increase-snowballing-in-turkey-2011-02-20 Murder a fact of life for women in Turkey - Hurriyet Daily News]&lt;/ref&gt; The rate of women not covered by [[social security]] is 84% in the East and 87% in the Southeast.&lt;ref name=&quot;hdn-2&quot;/&gt;

Women’s employment has decreased since 2000 and the participation of women in the workforce lags behind some Islamic countries as well as western countries.&lt;ref name=&quot;hdn-2&quot;&gt;[http://www.hurriyetdailynews.com/n.php?n=inequalities-are-deep-in-turkey-and-women-suffer-the-most-2010-07-22 Inequalities run deep in Turkey and women suffer the most - Hurriyet Daily News]&lt;/ref&gt; One of the reasons for this is the increased migration of rural women, who would otherwise have been employed in the agriculture sector.&lt;ref name=&quot;hdn-2&quot;/&gt; Compared to other Islamic countries, including Saudi Arabia and Iran, Turkey is the only one with a a diminishing rate of women’s employment.&lt;ref name=&quot;hdn-2&quot;/&gt;

==Women's health==
Since 1985, Turkish women have the right to freely exercise [[Abortion in Turkey|abortions]] in the first 10 weeks of pregnancy and the right to [[Contraception|contraceptive medicine]] paid for by the Social Security. Modifications to the Civil Code in 1926 gave the right to women to initiate and obtain a [[divorce]]; a right still not recognized in Malta,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.guardian.co.uk/world/2005/apr/05/religion.catholicism |accessdate=2008-08-20 |title='If the inquisitor was working today, he would commit suicide' |work=[[The Guardian]] |date=2005-04-05 |first=Stephen |last=Moss | location=London}}&lt;/ref&gt; an EU country. Turkish prime minister [[Erdoğan]] argued that women should have at least three children.&lt;ref name=&quot;amnesty&quot;/&gt;

Undoubtedly no gender discrimination exists regarding the laws as well as their practice in the health sector in Turkey. On the other hand, prolific pregnancy and birth have a negative health impact on both the mother and the child. With the 1994 World Population and Development Conference, the Ministry of Health adopted a policy change which included the emotional, social and physical health of women and young girls with an integrated approach, rather than only reproductive health and family planning as it did in the past. Another initiative brought onto the agenda by the Ministry of Health after the Beijing Conference, is to ensure the participation of men in reproductive health and family planning. This is a positive step taken by the state towards the improvement of health services sensitive to gender.

==Political rights==
In the 1930s, Turkey became one of the first countries in the world to give full political rights to [[women]], including the right to elect and be elected locally (in 1930) and nationwide (in 1934). Therefore, the [[Constitution of Turkey|Constitution]] was amended.&lt;ref name=&quot;IHGD&quot;&gt;[http://sorular.rightsagenda.org/soru-cevap/?g=4 Questions and Answers on Women's Right] Turkish, prepared by the Human Rights Agenda Association; accessed on 14 October 2009&lt;/ref&gt;

Article 10 of the [[Constitution of Turkey|Turkish Constitution]] bans any [[discrimination]], state or private, on the grounds of [[sex]]. Turkey elected a female [[prime minister]], [[Tansu Çiller]] in 1995. It is also the first country which had a woman as the President of its [[Turkish Constitutional Court|Constitutional Court]], [[Tülay Tuğcu]]. In addition, [[Turkish Council of State]], the supreme court for [[administrative law|administrative cases]], also has a woman judge [[Sumru Çörtoğlu]] as its President.

However, representation of women in political and decision making bodies is low. In the [[Grand National Assembly of Turkey]] the percentage of women is 9.1 (17.3 percent is the average in the world).&lt;ref name=&quot;IHGD&quot; /&gt; In 1975 the percentage was 10.9 and in 2006 it was 16.3.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.bmkadinhaklari.org/unjp/web/gozlem.aspx?sayfaNo=66 UN Joint Program for the Development of Women and Children's Rights], Turkish: ''Türkiye'de Kadın Olmak''; accessed on 14 October 2009&lt;/ref&gt; Only 5.58 percent of mayors are women and in the whole of Turkey there is one governor (among 81) and 14 local governors.&lt;ref name=&quot;IHGD&quot; /&gt; The number of women in the [[Turkish parliament]] has increased to 14% after the [[Turkish general election, 2011]].&lt;ref name=&quot;amnesty&quot;&gt;[http://blog.amnestyusa.org/women/women-in-turkey-the-numbers-are-stacked-against-them-2/ Women in Turkey: The Numbers Are Stacked Against Them | Human Rights Now - Amnesty International USA Blog]&lt;/ref&gt;

== See also ==
{{Commons category|Women of Turkey}}
*[[Headscarf controversy in Turkey]]
*[[Secularism in Turkey]]

==References==
{{reflist|2}}
{{loc}} (Data as of January 1995.)

{{Europe topic|Women in}}
{{Asia topic|Women in}}
{{Use dmy dates|date=October 2010}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Women In Turkey}}
[[Category:Turkish society]]
[[Category:Turkish women]]
[[Category:Women by nationality|Turkey]]

[[de:Frauenrechte in der Türkei]]
[[tr:Türkiye'de kadın hakları]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
