<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="161139" ns="0" title="University of Scranton"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">  {{Infobox_University
|name           = The University of Scranton
|image_name     = University of Scranton seal.png
|motto          = Religio Mores Cultura
|established    = 1888
|type           = [[Private school|Private]]
|affiliation    = [[Jesuit]]
|president      = Rev. [[Kevin Quinn (academic)|Kevin P. Quinn]], [[Society of Jesus|S.J.]]&lt;br&gt;(since July 1, 2011)
|city           = [[Scranton, Pennsylvania|Scranton]]
|state          = [[Pennsylvania]]
|country        = [[United States|USA]]
|undergrad      = 4,084
|postgrad       = 1,076
|faculty        = 259 (total staff = 1057)
|campus         = [[urban area|Urban]], {{convert|58|acre|m2}}
|mascot         = Royals
|colors         = Purple and White {{colorbox|purple}} {{colorbox|white}}
|endowment      = $106 million&lt;ref name=nacubo&gt; {{cite news |first=|last=|title=U.S. and Canadian Institutions Listed by Fiscal Year 2010 Endowment Market Value and Percentage Change in Endowment Market Value from FY 2009 to FY 2010 |url=http://www.nacubo.org/Documents/research/2010NCSE_Public_Tables_Endowment_Market_Values_Final.pdf |work=National Association of College and University Business Officers |publisher=|date=2010|accessdate=2011-01-28}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|logo           =[[File:University of Scranton logo.png|200px]]
|website        = [http://www.scranton.edu/ www.scranton.edu]
}}

'''The University of Scranton''' is a private, co-educational [[Catholic]] and [[Society of Jesus|Jesuit]] [[university]], located in [[Scranton, Pennsylvania]], in the northeast region of the state. The school was founded in 1888 by Most Rev. [[William O'Hara]], the first [[Roman Catholic Diocese of Scranton|Bishop of Scranton]], as '''St. Thomas College'''. It was elevated to a university in 1938, taking the name the University of Scranton. The institution was operated by the Diocese, and later the [[Institute of the Brothers of the Christian Schools |Lasallian Christian Brothers]], from 1888 to 1942. In 1942, Bishop [[William Joseph Hafey]] invited the [[Society of Jesus]] to take charge of the university. Today, the University of Scranton is one of 28 member institutions of the [[Association of Jesuit Colleges and Universities]]. Around 30 Jesuits are normally in residence at Scranton.

The University is composed of four colleges: The College of Arts and Sciences, The Kania School of Management, The Panuska College of Professional Studies, and The College of Graduate and Continuing Education (a recent merger of the Graduate School and The Dexter Hanley College).

==Areas of Academic Study==
The University grants [[undergraduate degree]]s ([[Bachelor of Arts]] and [[Bachelor of Science]]) in 57 majors. Students may also utilize many pre-professional concentrations, such as pre-medical, pre-law, and pre-dental. The University also has an Honors Program, and the SJLA (Special Jesuit Liberal Arts) Program in which select students complete courses in moral [[philosophy]], [[ethics]], [[theology]], and the [[humanities]] in addition to their normal course load.

The University also grants [[graduate degree]]s ([[Master of Arts (postgraduate)|Master of Arts]], [[Master of Science]], [[Master of Business Administration]], [[Master of Science]] in [[Nursing]], [[Master of Health Administration]], Master of [[Occupational Therapy]], Master of Science in Education) in 24 fields, among them [[Accounting]], [[Chemistry]], [[Biochemistry]], [[Computing Sciences]], [[Counseling]] and Human Services, [http://www.uscranton.com/online-masters-curriculum/ Curriculum &amp; Instruction], [http://www.uscranton.com/online-educational-administration/ Educational Administration/], Elementary and [[Special Education]], [[Health Administration]], [[Human Resources]], [[Nursing]], [[Software Engineering]], and [[Theology]]. The University also offers a Doctor of [[Physical Therapy]] program. However, the University decided to phase out its masters degree program in history as of Fall 2008. All current history masters students are expected to graduate in the next six years.

==Curriculum==
The University offers a liberal arts program. Students are required to take the core courses in [[public speaking]], [[computer literacy]] and [[composition (language)|composition]]. Students are also required to take two [[theology]] courses, two [[philosophy]] courses, as well as an elective in one of these two areas. Filling out the general education requirements are 6 credits in [[science]] courses, 6 credits in writing intensive courses, 6 credits in cultural [[Multiculturalism|diversity]] courses, 3 credits in a [[mathematics]] course, 12 credits in [[humanities]] courses and 3 credits in [[physical education]].

==Ranking==
The University has been mentioned in several national [[publications]] including the [[Princeton Review]], [[Kaplan, Inc.|Kaplan's Publishing]], [[U.S. News &amp; World Report]] and [[Newsweek]].&lt;ref name=stimes&gt;{{cite news |first=|last=|title=College Briefs: Scranton among the ‘best’ colleges |url=http://www.thetimes-tribune.com/site/index.cfm?newsid=18750496&amp;BRD=2185&amp;PAG=461&amp;dept_id=590572&amp;rfi=8 |work= [[Scranton Times]] |publisher= |date=2007-08-26 |accessdate=2007-12-06}} {{Dead link|date=September 2010|bot=H3llBot}}&lt;/ref&gt; For 16 consecutive years, beginning in 1994, The University of Scranton has been ranked in the top 10 schools in [[U.S. News &amp; World Report]]'s rankings of the [[master's degree|Best Master's Universities]]-North.&lt;ref name=stimes/&gt; In the 2010 edition, Scranton  was named as one of 77 universities nationally on the &quot;Up and Coming List&quot; (fourth in the north) and one of 80 nationally recognized for &quot;A Strong Commitment to Teaching&quot; (third in the north).  The Princeton Review has named the University to its annual “The 371 Best Colleges,&quot; from 2002 to its most recent list in 2011.&lt;ref name=stimes/&gt; A combined 2008 Newsweek/Kaplan college guide also named the University of Scranton as one of the [[United States]]' “372 Most Interesting Schools” for the second straight year.&lt;ref name=stimes/&gt;  The University of Scranton was in the top 50 of universities listed in Kiplinger’s “Best Values in Private Colleges.”&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.kiplinger.com/tools/privatecolleges/privatecollege.php?schoollist=prv_univ&amp;sortby=RANK&amp;orderby=flip&amp;states%5B%5D=PA&amp;myschool%5B%5D=none&amp;outputby=table Rankings for 100 Best Values in Private Colleges&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt; In 2011 [[The Huffington Post]] recognized the University of Scranton as the sixth friendliest school in the United States.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|last=Dittman|first=Lindsay|title=The Friendliest Colleges|url=http://www.huffingtonpost.com/2011/07/13/the-friendliest-colleges_n_896867.html#s306874&amp;title=University_of_Scranton|accessdate=15 July 2011|newspaper=The Huffington Post|date=13 July 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Campus Buildings and Landmarks==
&lt;i&gt;Main Article: [[University of Scranton Buildings and Landmarks]]&lt;/i&gt;
[[File:Pilarz Hall.jpg|thumb|Pilarz Hall is part of the new Mulberry Street Complex, which includes housing, fitness facilities, and a food court.]]
===Retreat Center at Chapman Lake===
Retreats offered at Chapman Lake are usually offered and run by staff and students from the University of Scranton's Office of University Ministries.  They are very popular with the student body and are usually held several times a year, with around 40 students participating at a time.  The Freshman Retreat and the Search Retreats are among the most popular and are held multiple times each semester.  The Senior Retreat is usually held once a year during the Spring Semester for graduating seniors.

===Student Housing===
The University has 13 traditional residences, housing mostly for freshmen. Christopher and Margaret Condron Hall (2008), Francis E. Redington Hall, and John R. Gavigan Hall provide housing for upperclassmen students. The University owns over 20 additional houses and apartment buildings in the areas surrounding the campus, offering over 30 housing options for students, including Mulberry Plaza and Madison Square, two townhouse-style complexes featuring air conditioning, full kitchens, living areas and bedrooms.

==Athletics==
[[File:University of Scranton Royal Wolf.png|thumb|right|Athletics logo|]]
[[File:Scrantonrugby.jpg|right|200px|thumb|The [[Scranton Norseman Rugby]] team.]]
Scranton athletes compete at the [[National Collegiate Athletic Association|NCAA]] [[Division III (NCAA)|Division III]]. In 2007, Scranton joined the newly formed [[Landmark Conference]], which ended a long history with the Middle Atlantic/Freedom Conference.

The school offers 18 varsity sports and has won national championships in Men's Basketball in 1976 and 1983 and Women's Basketball in 1985. The University's basketball teams play at the John Long Center located in the heart of the campus. The University's soccer and field hockey teams play at Fitzpatrick Field, also on campus.

==Student life==
===The University of Scranton Alma Mater===

The hours too quickly slip away&lt;br&gt;
And mingle into years&lt;br&gt;
But memories of our Scranton days will last&lt;br&gt;
Whatever next appears.&lt;br&gt;
The legacy from those before&lt;br&gt;
Is briefly ours to hold,&lt;br&gt;
We leave the best behind for others&lt;br&gt;
As the coming years unfold.

With faith in lives that touch us here&lt;br&gt;
And paths that ours have crossed&lt;br&gt;
We know that reaching for the rising sun&lt;br&gt;
Is surely worth the cost.&lt;br&gt;
May God be ever at our side,&lt;br&gt;
May goodness fill our days.&lt;br&gt;
We hail as loving sons and daughters&lt;br&gt;
Alma mater ours always.

===Office of Student Activities and Orientation===

The mission of Student Activities and Orientation is to strive to be a center of excellence in providing experiential opportunities for students to learn and develop through leadership and event planning programs. Keeping the care of the whole person and the magis at the forefront, Student Activities and Orientation is a resource that emphasizes a welcoming environment to support a free flow of ideas to empower and challenge students and support their development while continuing the tradition of “men and women for others”.{cn}

Orientation is a pivotal process at Scranton. It is a two-day, overnight Orientation. Students split into small groups, take placement tests, and get importnant information about both the city of Scranton and the University.

==The University of Scranton Student Government==
===History of the Student Senate===
The Student Senate came about in the spring semester of 2002 with the ratification of its Constitution. On May 3, 2002 the first Student Senate meeting was held in the Office of Student Activities. Today, the Student Senate assembles for regular sessions on a biweekly basis and for emergency sessions as necessary.

The Student Senate is the main avenue of governance for the students. The Student Senate deals with pertinent issues that affect the day-to-day lives of students at the University of Scranton. The Senate is chaired by the Vice-President of Student Government who votes only in the case of a tie. The other Executive members of Student Government are the President, a nonvoting member with veto authority, as well as the Secretary and Treasurer, both non-voting members. The body of the Student Senate is made up of the non-voting executive positions, and four equal representatives from each class, two commuter representatives, two off-campus representatives, and two resident representatives for a total of 26 members, 22 of which have voting rights.

There are four standing committees formed out of the Senate: Safety and Crime Prevention, Student Life and Dining Services, Academic Affairs, and Appropriations. Proposed legislation is sent to the appropriate committee for research and development at the discretion of the Chair. The Executive Treasurer advises the Appropriations Committee; a Senator appointed by the Executive Council chairs each of the committees.

==Future of the University==

On April 26, 2008, the University held a public launch its new fundraising campaign. The campaign includes the DeNaples Center, Condron Hall, renovations to the Estate as a new home for admissions and the development of a new science facility. The building, now known as the Loyola Science Center, is in the planning stages with a tentative construction start date in Spring 2009 (according to October 2007 Provost's Report). Other campaign priorities include building endowment for financial aid, scholarships and faculty development and growing support in annual giving.

On October 26, 2009, the University began construction on a new science/humanities facility, the [http://matrix.scranton.edu/academics/sciencecenter/index.shtml Loyola Science Center].

On May 6, 2010, The University announced plans to build a new apartment style Residence Hall with a food option as well as a new fitness facility on the first floor. This will be located across the street from the DeNaples Center on the 900 block of Mulberry Street.

On August 30, 2010 President Scott Pilarz, S.J. announced that he would leave the University at the end of the academic year to become the president of Marquette University.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|last=Hofius Hall|first=Sarah|title=Pilarz to leave University of Scranton for Marquette|url=http://thetimes-tribune.com/pilarz-to-leave-university-of-scranton-for-marquette-1.985120|accessdate=1 September 2010|newspaper=The Times-Tribune|date=1 September 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;

On December 15, 2010 Christopher &quot;Kip&quot; Condron announced that Kevin Quinn, S.J. would become the [http://www.scranton.edu/25thpresident 25th President of the University of Scranton]. Quinn is originally from New York and is currently the executive director of the Ignatian Center for Jesuit Education. He was also a professor of law at Santa Clara University.&lt;ref&gt;http://matrix.scranton.edu/news/royalnews/articles/2010/12/15/Kevin-Quinn-President.shtml&lt;/ref&gt;

On May 11, 2011 it was announced that the West building of the new Mulberry Street Complex will be named &quot;Pilarz Hall&quot; in honor the outgoing president Rev. Scott Pilarz, S.J. It was dedicated on November 11, 2011.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Dedication of Pilarz Hall|url=http://matrix.scranton.edu/news/articles/2011/11/Pilarz-hall-dedication-video.shtml|publisher=University of Scranton|accessdate=21 November 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==University of Scranton Presidents==

List of Presidents since elevation to University status in 1938:&lt;ref name=uofspresidents&gt;{{cite news |first=|last=|title=Presidents of St. Thomas College, The University of Scranton
 |url=http://matrix.scranton.edu/about/ab_past_presidents.shtml|work= University of Scranton |publisher= |date= |accessdate=2007-12-06}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*'''Br. Denis Edward, [[F.S.C.]]''' - 1931 - 1940
*'''Br. Eliseus Leonard, F.S.C.''' - 1940 - 1942
*''Dr. Frank J. O'Hara, [[LL.D.]] (acting)'' - 1942
*'''[[Very Rev.]] W. Coleman Nevils, [[Society of Jesus|S.J.]]''' - 1942 - 1947
*'''Rev. J. Eugene Gallery, S.J.''' - 1947 - 1953
*'''Very Rev. John J. Long, S.J.''' - 1953 - 1963
*'''Rev. [[Edward J. Sponga]], S.J.''' - 1963 - 1965
*'''Rev. [[Aloysius C. Galvin]], S.J.''' - 1965 - 1970
*''Rev. Joseph A. Rock, S.J. (acting)'' - 1970
*'''Rev. Dexter L. Hanley, S.J., J.D.''' - 1970 - 1975
*''Rev. Edwin A. Quain, S.J. (acting)'' - 1975
*'''Rev. [[William J. Byron]], S.J., Ph.D.''' - 1975 - 1982
*'''Rev. Joseph Allen (J.A.) Panuska, S.J., Ph.D''' - July 1982 - 1998
*'''Rev. [[Joseph M. McShane, S.J.|Joseph M. McShane]], S.J., Ph.D.''' - 1998 - 2003
*'''Rev. [[Scott R. Pilarz]], S.J., Ph.D.''' - July 1, 2003 - July 1, 2011
*'''Rev. [[Kevin Quinn (academic)|Kevin Quinn]], S.J., J.D., Ph.D.''' - July 1, 2011

==Notable University of Scranton Alumni==
*'''[[James Donald Walsh]]''' - Diplomat and [[foreign service officer]],  [[United States Ambassador to Argentina]] 2000-2003
*'''[[Patrick J. Boland]]''' - [[U.S. Congressman]] from [[Pennsylvania]] and [[Majority Whip of the United States House of Representatives|Majority Whip]].
*'''[[Christopher F. Burne]]''' - [[U.S. Air Force]] Brigadier General
*'''[[John D. Butzner, Jr.]]''' - former [[United States federal judge]] - [[United States Court of Appeals for the Fourth Circuit]]
*'''[[Nestor Chylak]]''' - [[Baseball Hall of Fame]]r and [[American League]] [[Umpire (baseball)|umpire]] from 1954–1978
*'''Christopher &quot;Kip&quot; Condron''' - President and CEO of [[AXA]]
*'''Timothy Edward Connolly''' - Rear Tire Changer for NASCAR driver [[Tony Stewart]]
*'''[[Lieutenant General (United States)|Lt. Gen.]] [[Kevin Kiley|Kevin C. Kiley]], [[Doctor of Medicine|M.D.]] ''' - [[Surgeon General of the United States Army|Former Surgeon General]] of the [[United States Army]]
*'''[[Lieutenant General (United States)|Lt. Gen.]] [[John J. Cusick]],''' - [[Quartermaster General of the United States Army|Former Quartermaster General]] of the [[United States Army]]
*'''[[United States District Court for the Middle District of Pennsylvania#Judges of the District|Malachy E. Mannion]]''' - United States Magistrate Judge, United States District Court, Middle District of Pennsylvania
*'''[[Kalanidhi Maran]]''' - founder and Chairman of [[Sun Network]], one of India's largest media houses, majority owner of [[SpiceJet|SpiceJet Airways Private Limited]]&lt;ref name=hindu&gt; {{cite news |first= |last= |title=Kalanidhi Maran buys 37.7 p.c. stake in SpiceJet |url=http://www.thehindu.com/business/companies/article454226.ece|work=[[The Hindu]] |publisher= |date=2010-06-13 |accessdate=2010-08-08}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*'''[[Jason Miller (playwright)|Jason Miller]]''' - late film actor; [[Academy Awards|Academy Award]] nominee and [[Pulitzer Prize]]-winning playwright (''[[That Championship Season (1982 film)|That Championship Season]]''), best known for playing Father Damien in ''[[The Exorcist (film)|The Exorcist]]''.
*'''[[Bob Smith (New Jersey State Senator)|Sen. Bob Smith]]''' - Democratic [[New Jersey Senate|New Jersey State Senator]] representing NJ's [[New Jersey Legislative Districts, 2001 redistricting#District 17|17th Legislative District]]
*'''[[Sean Kearney (Head Coach Mens Basketball)|Sean Kearney]]''' - former Head Coach Mens Basketball at [[College of the Holy Cross]]
*'''[[Thom Loverro]]''', sports journalist, author, and radio personality
*'''[[Alex Beras]]''' - Professional baseball player drafted by the New York Mets in 2005.
*'''[[Ralph J. Lomma]]''' - Inventor of Mini-Golf,  original designers of windmills, castles, churches.

==Notable University of Scranton faculty==
*'''[[James A. Martin]]''', S.J. - former [[chairperson]] of the Department of [[Theology]] (1946–1949); world's oldest Jesuit until his death in 2007 at the age of 105.&lt;ref name=wp&gt;{{cite news |first=Matt|last=Schudel|title=James A. Martin, 105; World's Oldest Jesuit |url=http://www.washingtonpost.com/wp-dyn/content/article/2007/10/05/AR2007100502709.html|work= [[Washington Post]] |publisher= |date=2007-10-06 |accessdate=2008-01-17}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Notable Honorary Degree Recipients&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=List of Honorary Degree Recipients|url=http://matrix.scranton.edu/about/ab_degree_recipients.shtml|publisher=University of Scranton|accessdate=2 September 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;==

*'''[[William W. Scranton]]''', former Governor of the Commonwealth.
*'''[[Wycliffe Gordon]]''', trombonist.
*'''[[Chris Matthews]]''', host of MSNBC's ''Hardball with Chris Matthews''.
*'''[[Tim Russert]]''', former anchor of NBC's ''Meet the Press''.
*'''[[Avery Dulles]]''', theologian.
*'''[[John Joseph O'Connor]]''', Cardinal Archbishop of New York.
*'''[[Paul Sorvino]]''', film director.
*'''[[Mother Teresa]]''', founder of the Missionaries of Charity and Nobel Peace Prize recipient.
*'''[[Bob Hope]]''', actor and comedian.
*'''[[Wynton Marsalis]]''', trumpet player.
*'''[[Mary Higgins Clark]]''', author.
*'''[[Joseph Biden]]''', Former Democratic Senator from Delaware and current Vice President of the United States.
*'''[[J. William Fulbright]]''', senator and founder of Fulbright Fellowship Program.
*'''[[Richard Harris]]''', Irish actor.
*'''[[Oscar Arias Sanchez]]''', President of Costa Rica.
*'''[[Helmut Schmidt]]''', former Chancellor of West Germany.
*'''[[Dick Thornburgh]]''', former Pennsylvania governor and United States Attorney General

==University of Scranton Press==
The '''University of Scranton Press''' is a [[university press]] that is part of the University of Scranton.  Its publications include books on religious and philosophical issues and local ([[Northeastern Pennsylvania]]) history, including [[coal mining]].  In the summer of 2010 the University announced that it was no longer accepting submissions for publication and would discontinue the Press after all current projects were completed.

==External links==
*[http://www.scranton.edu/ University of Scranton]
*[http://www.scranton.edu/library/ The University of Scranton Weinberg Memorial Library]
*[http://www.wusrfm.com/ 99.5 WUSR:] The University's Radio Station
*[http://my.scranton.edu/ myScranton:]  University of Scranton's User Email and Database Home
*[http://matrix.scranton.edu/athletics/at.shtml Scranton Athletics] University of Scranton Athletics

==References==
{{Reflist}}

{{Association of Jesuit Colleges and Universities}}
{{Colleges and Universities in Pennsylvania}}
{{Northeastern Pennsylvania Colleges and Universities}}
{{Landmark Conference}}
{{ECHA}}
{{Associated New American Colleges}}

{{coord|41.406|-75.657|region:US-PA_type:edu|display=title}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Scranton, University Of}}
[[Category:University of Scranton| ]]
[[Category:Educational institutions established in 1888]]
[[Category:Jesuit universities and colleges in the United States]]
[[Category:Roman Catholic universities and colleges in the United States]]
[[Category:Council of Independent Colleges]]
[[Category:National Association of Independent Colleges and Universities members]]
[[Category:Scranton, Pennsylvania]]
[[Category:Middle States Association of Colleges and Schools]]
[[Category:Universities and colleges in Lackawanna County, Pennsylvania]]
[[Category:Visitor attractions in Scranton, Pennsylvania]]

[[de:University of Scranton]]
[[es:Universidad de Scranton]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
