<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="16118202" ns="0" title="Univision"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Infobox broadcasting network
|name           = Univision
|logo           = [[File:Univision logo.svg|98px]]
|type           = [[Terrestrial television|Broadcast Television Network]]
|branding       =
|airdate        =
|country        = {{flag|United States}} &lt;p&gt;Production: [[Doral, Florida]]|
|language       = [[Spanish language|Spanish]]
|available      = throughout the United States
|founded        =
|founder        =
|slogan         = {{*}}''Todos estamos con Univision''&lt;br /&gt;(&quot;We all are with Univision&quot;)&lt;br /&gt;{{*}}''Estás en Casa'' (&quot;You are at Home&quot;; used in Puerto Rico)&lt;br&gt;{{*}}''Siempre Contigo'' (&quot;Always With You&quot;)&lt;br /&gt;{{*}}''La Casa de Todos'' (&quot;The House of All&quot;)
|broadcast_area = [[United States]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Puerto Rico]]
|owner          = [[Univision Communications, Inc.]] 95% and [[Grupo Televisa]] 5%
|key_people     = {{*}}[[Cesar Conde]], President, Univision Networks
|foundation     =
|launch_date    = September 30, 1962
|dissolved      =
|picture format = [[480i]] (SD)&lt;br /&gt;[[720p]]/[[1080i]] (HD)
|former_names   = Spanish International Network (1962–1986)
|digital        =
|analog         =
|servicename1   =
|service1       =
|servicename2   =
|service2       =
|servicename3   =
|service3       =
|servicename4   =
|service4       =
|callsigns      =
|callsign_meaning =
|former_callsigns =
|affiliation    =
|affiliates     =
|groups         =
|former_affiliations =
|website        = [http://www.univision.com univision.com]
|footnotes      =
}}

{{Infobox TV channel
| name              =
| logofile          =
| logosize          =
| logocaption       =
| logoalt           =
| logo2             =
| launch            =
| closed date       =
| picture format    =
| share             =
| share as of       =
| share source      =
| network           =
| owner             =
| slogan            =
| country           =
| language          =
| broadcast area    =
| affiliates        =
| headquarters      =
| former names      =
| replaced names    =
| replaced by names =
| sister names      = [[Telefutura]]&lt;br&gt; [[Galavision (USA)|Galavision]]
| timeshift names   =
| web               =
| terr serv 1       = Available throughout the U.S.
| terr chan 1       = see [[List of Univision affiliates]]
| sat serv 1        = DirecTV (US)
| sat chan 1        = 402 Univision East (SD/HD)&lt;br&gt;403 Univision West&lt;br&gt;1402 Univision [[Video on demand|On Demand]]
| sat serv 2        = DirecTV (Latin America)
| sat chan 2        = 168 (via [[WLII-TV]] in [[Caguas, Puerto Rico]])
| sat serv 3        = Dish Network (US)
| sat chan 3        = 270 Univision East HD &lt;br&gt;828 Univision West
| cable serv 1      = Available on most cable systems
| cable chan 1      = Check local listings
| sat radio serv 1  =
| sat radio chan 1  =
| iptv serv 1       = [[AT&amp;T U-Verse]] 
| iptv chan 1       = 3002&amp;20
| online serv 1     =
| online chan 1     =
| 3gmobile serv 1   =
}}

'''Univision''' ({{IPA-es|uniβiˈsjon}}) is a Spanish-language television [[TV network|network]] in the United States. It has the largest audience of Spanish language television viewers according to [[Nielsen ratings]]. Randy Falco, (CEO as of June 29, 2011)  [[Chief operating officer|COO]], has been in charge of the company since the departure of [[Univision Communications]] president and [[CEO]] Joe Uva in April 2010.&lt;ref name=univision.com&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.univision.com/content/content.jhtml?cid=2197105 |title=Univision anuncia la creación de Univision Studios - Novedades |publisher=Univision.com |accessdate=2010-03-31}}&lt;/ref&gt; In recent years the network has reached parity with the U.S.'s five major English language television networks, and is often a strong fifth, outranking [[The CW Television Network|The CW]], with some fourth-place weekly placings during the summer months due to the network's consistent schedule of new telenovelas all 52 weeks of the year.

Univision is headquartered in [[New York City]], after years of being in [[Los Angeles]],&lt;ref name=&quot;herald&quot;&gt;[http://www.miamiherald.com/103/story/109381.html Miami Herald]{{Dead link|url=http://www.miamiherald.com/103/story/109381.html|date=January 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; and has its major studios, production facilities, and operations in [[Doral, Florida]], a suburb of [[Miami]]. In 2009, another television studio was announced, Univision Studios, to be built in Doral.&lt;ref name=univision.com/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.miamiherald.com/news/breaking-news/story/1369893.html Miami Herald]{{Dead link|url=http://www.miamiherald.com/news/breaking-news/story/1369893.html|date=July 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; Univision is available on cable and satellite in most of the country, with local stations in over 50 markets with large [[Hispanic and Latino Americans|Hispanic and Latino]] populations and a national [[cable network]] feed distributed in markets without either the availability or the demand for a locally-based station. Most of these stations air full local news and other local programming in addition to network shows, and in major markets such as Los Angeles, New York, and Miami, Univision [[owned-and-operated station]] (O&amp;O) newscasts are equally competitive with their English-language counterparts ratings-wise.

Univision was acquired on March 29, 2007 by a consortium led by [[Haim Saban]]'s [[Saban Capital Group]] (who had previously owned the entity [[Saban Entertainment]]), [[TPG Capital, L.P.]], [[Providence Equity Partners]], [[Madison Dearborn Partners]], and [[Thomas H. Lee Partners]] for $13.7 billion or $36.25 per share plus $1.4 billion in acquired debt.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.saban.com/html/press/070329.html|title=Broadcasting Media Partners Completes Acquisition of Univision|date=March 29, 2007 |work=Saban|accessdate=2009-02-19}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Univision&quot;&gt;[http://www.univision.net/corp/en/pr/Los_Angeles_27062006-0.html Univision]&lt;/ref&gt; The buyout left the company with a debt level of twelve times its annual cash flow, which was twice the norm in buyouts done over the previous two years.&lt;ref name=&quot;wsj&quot;&gt;{{cite news| url=http://online.wsj.com/article/SB118282461107748034.html | work=The Wall Street Journal | title=Behind Buyout Surge, A Debt Market Booms | first1=Serena | last1=Ng | first2=Henny | last2=Sender | date=June 26, 2007}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== History ==
=== Beginnings as Spanish International Network ===
In 1955, Raul Cortez founded [[KWEX-TV|KCOR-TV]], Channel 41, in [[San Antonio, Texas]]. The call letters were later changed to KUAL-TV. The station was not profitable, and in [[1961]] Cortez sold it to a group headed by his son-in-law Emilio Nicolas, Sr. and Mexican entertainment guru [[Emilio Azcárraga Vidaurreta]]. Nicolas had helped produce channel 41's variety shows, while Azcárraga was the owner of Telesistema Mexicano, forerunner of Televisa.

The new owners turned the station around, and in 1962 signed on [[KMEX-TV]], channel 34 in Los Angeles and in 1968 signed on [[WXTV]] channel 41 in [[Paterson, New Jersey]], serving the [[New York metropolitan area]].  This was the beginning of the '''Spanish International Network''', the first non-English-language television network in the United States.

Over the next 20 years, SIN would acquire other high-rated Spanish language television stations throughout the [[Western United States]], and then expand the market to [[WLTV-DT|WLTV]] in [[Florida]], [[KDTV-DT|KDTV]] in [[San Francisco]], and [[WSNS-TV]] in [[Chicago]]. In the mid-1970s the network also began to distribute their national signal via satellite, first as a 'super-station'-type feed of KWEX-TV San Antonio, then as a general feed allowing [[cable television]] operators to carry the network at little cost on their systems.

=== Rename to Univision ===
[[File:Univision1986.gif|left|thumb|SIN was renamed Univision in 1986, and its logo bore a resemblance to [[Televisa]]'s.]]
1986 was a pivotal year for the station group and the network. Nicolas sold his stake in the network to a partnership of [[Hallmark Cards]] and [[Televisa]]. The FCC had long wondered (and competitors to SIN had long proposed)that the relationship between SIN/SICC and the owners of Televisa was impermissably tight. Questions were asked and answered and the outcome was that the FCC and Justice department encouraged a sale of the service to a properly consitituted domestic organization. Thus began talks that ended with Hallmark Cards buying the stations, and forming a new relationship withg Televisa for programs.  

The new group changed the network's name to Univision. Univision's new CEO, Joaquin Blaya, was to sign the contracts for two programs that would change the network. Blaya signed [[Cristina Saralegui]], who became a famous talk show host, and Mario Kreutzberger, better known as [[Don Francisco (television host)|Don Francisco]], who brought from Chile his famous program ''[[Sábado Gigante]]''. Also, the network began production of its first morning television show. The program was ''Mundo Latino'', anchored by Lucy Pereda and Frank Moro, who were both Cuban. Moro left for Mexico to continue his career as a soap opera actor and the network brought in [[Jorge Ramos (news anchor)|Jorge Ramos]].

In 1988, the network began to produce television shows with a national audience in mind. The first production was titled ''TV Mujer'' (Woman TV), a magazine-styled show aimed at Hispanic women in the United States. At first anchored by Lucy Pereda and [[Gabriel Traversari]], the program was a mix of cooking and entertainment segments.

Pereda was replaced shortly after finishing her first year by Mexican-American Lauri Flores, who hailed from [[KXLN-TV]] in Houston, Texas, where she was director of programming, promotions, special events, and public information as well as producer and host of the local community affairs show ''Entre Nos''.  During Ms. Flores' time as host of ''TV Mujer'', the show remained the number one daytime show on Spanish-language television,&lt;ref&gt;Source: Strategy Research Corporation's (SRC) 1989 fall sweeps performed from May to November 1989&lt;/ref&gt; outperforming its time period competition by 33 percent. Telemundo's ''Dia a Dia'', launched before the arrival of ''TV Mujer'', saw its ratings diminishing.

A model from ''Sábado Gigante'', [[Jackie Nespral]] became the add-on host in TV Mujer's last year, hired to sit in while Flores was on maternity leave. Nespral became a formal host during the show's final season. ''TV Mujer'' begat a series of other programs, namely  ''Hola, America'' and ''Al Mediodia'', which never got the ratings of the original concept and were cancelled.

=== Revamp and competition with Telemundo in the 1990s ===
Univision then decided to expand its news programming in the afternoon and launched ''Noticias y Mas'' (News and More), with Nespral, Ambrosio Hernandez, Myrka Dellanos, and Raul Peimbert. In the early 1990s, Hernandez and Peimbert left Univision and joined [[Telemundo]], while Nespral joined the weekend edition of [[NBC]]'s ''[[Today (NBC program)|Today]]'' show. Univision had other plans for the moribund show—They revamped it, changed the name and the theme music, and installed a weekend reporter to be Dellanos' partner: Puerto Rican born [[María Celeste Arrarás]], who joined the now news program called ''[[Primer Impacto]]''.

In 1993, having purchased Univision from [[Hallmark]] a few months earlier, [[Jerry Perenchio]] appointed Miguel Banojian to turn around the operations of [[KMEX]]-34 in Los Angeles, the company's flagship station, which generated a big portion of the company's revenue. Banojian was then a 25-year-old executive from Univision's New York City headquarters, where he helmed [[WXTV]]'s (channel 41) newscasts. His outstanding results in Los Angeles positioned KMEX as the first Spanish language television station ever to outperform the English language networks, including [[NBC]], [[CBS]], [[American Broadcasting Company|ABC]], and [[Fox Broadcasting Company|Fox]], and overcame what had been Telemundo's competitive edge against Univision.

===2000s===
In 2002, Univision entered into a [[local marketing agreement]] (LMA) with [[Raycom Media]] to operate two television stations in Puerto Rico: [[WLII]] in [[Caguas, Puerto Rico|Caguas]] and WSUR in [[Ponce, Puerto Rico|Ponce]]. At the time, WLII had a longtime LMA with another Puerto Rican station, [[WSTE]], which Univision honored. It was also around this time that Univision resumed broadcast expansion by signing affiliation agreements with stations in [[Raleigh, North Carolina]] ([[WUVC-TV|WUVC]]), [[Cleveland, Ohio]] ([[WQHS-TV|WQHS]]), [[Philadelphia, Pennsylvania]] ([[WUVP-TV|WUVP]]), and [[Atlanta, Georgia]] ([[WUVG-TV|WUVG]]), among many others&amp;nbsp;— most of which were acquired from [[USA Broadcasting]] and had previously been affiliated with the [[Home Shopping Network]]. Both WLII and WSUR were sold to Univision in 2005. Plans for the network are that Univision will resume broadcast expansion by signing affiliation agreements with new stations in [[Indianapolis, Indiana]], [[Detroit, Michigan]], [[New Orleans, Louisiana]], and [[Nashville, Tennessee]].{{Citation needed|date=April 2010}}

In June 2002 it was announced that Univision would acquire Dallas, Texas-based Hispanic Broadcasting Corp., a multiple-station operation specializing in Spanish Radio stations like WADO New York, KLVE Los Angeles, KGSX San Antonio, and KESS Dallas. The approval was long and hard. The acquired group was renamed Univision Radio. (http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Univision_Radio) The negotiations to merge the two companies followed years of on again/off again negotiations in which each company would make a run at the other, as well as occasional stabs at other groups (HBC once attempted to broker a deal to merge with Spanish Broadcasting System, and HBC once tried to acquire Telemundo outright before Sony and Liberty actually pulled off a deal).

In late 2004, a feud began between Perenchio and the head of Televisa, [[Emilio Azcárraga Jean]].{{Citation needed|date=April 2008}} The dispute was about Univision's continual editing of Televisa's programming, and failure to pay for transmission of Televisa-produced sports and specials. The feud intensified to the point where Televisa's most famous stars have been banned from appearing on any Univision-produced shows and specials. In addition, Televisa has filed a lawsuit against Univision for [[breach of contract]]. In recent years, Univision also lost several key on-air personalities to Telemundo, including long time weekend news anchor [[Maria Antonieta Collins]], tabloid news anchor [[María Celeste Arrarás]], and sports announcer [[Andrés Cantor]].

Univision previously overtook the now-defunct English-language networks [[UPN]] and [[The WB Television Network|the WB]], now the [[The CW|CW Television Network]], as the fifth-most popular network overall, and in the 18-to-34-year-old and 18-to-49-year-old [[demographics]] it sometimes ranks higher than that. More advertising on TV is targeted toward those age groups than toward any other part of the viewing audience.

In the first week of September 2010 the network reached a milestone with a first-place ranking in the 18-49 demographic among all networks, English and Spanish, assisted by a primetime Mexico/Ecuador match and the finale of a popular telenovela, along with the English networks having traditionally weak programming that time of year.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news| url=http://weblogs.variety.com/on_the_air/2010/09/for-the-first-time-ever-univision-wins-the-week-in-adults-18-49-.html | work=Variety}}&lt;/ref&gt;

On April 7, 2005, Univision held a three-hour tribute concert for singer [[Selena]], entitled ''[[Selena ¡VIVE!]]''. The concert would earn a 35.9 [[Nielsen ratings|Nielsen household rating]], not only being the highest rated show of the night, but also being the highest-rated and most-watched Spanish-language program in [[Television in the United States|American television]] history.&lt;ref name=&quot;selena-ratings&quot;&gt;[http://www.univision.net/corp/en/pr/Houston_11042005-2.html Univision's ''Selena ¡Vive!'' Breaks Audience Records]. Univision, November 4, 2005. Retrieved on June 6, 2006.&lt;/ref&gt;
[[File:6.6.10CubanParadeUCByLuigiNovi9.jpg|thumb|left|A Univision float in the 2010 North Hudson Cuban Day Parade in [[Union City, New Jersey]].]]
On February 9, 2006, Univision Communications confirmed that it was putting itself up for sale. [[Rupert Murdoch]], chairman of [[News Corporation]], stated that his company was considering buying Univision, but backed off that position.&lt;ref name=&quot;bcable&quot;&gt;[http://www.broadcastingcable.com/article/CA6333711.html?display=Breaking+News B&amp;C Mobile]&lt;/ref&gt; Other expected bidders announced were [[Time Warner]], [[CBS]], [[Disney]], [[Grupo Televisa]] of Mexico (under a partnership, due to foreign ownership laws in the U.S.), [[Bill Gates]], and several private equity firms. [[Tribune Company]] was rumored to be interested in buying [[TeleFutura]], a subsidiary network of Univision.&lt;ref name=&quot;nyt0209&quot;&gt;
{{cite news| url=http://www.nytimes.com/2006/02/09/business/media/09network.html?_r=1&amp;oref=slogin | work=The New York Times | title=Univision Confirms It May Be for Sale | date=February 9, 2006 | accessdate=May 27, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;

On June 27, 2006, Univision announced that it accepted a $12.7 billion bid from a group of private equity investors led by [[TPG Capital]] and [[Thomas H. Lee Partners]]. The investor group also included [[Madison Dearborn]], Providence Equity, and children's television mogul [[Haim Saban]]. On March 27, 2007, federal regulators approved the sale.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.chron.com/disp/story.mpl/ap/fn/4666569.html &quot;Univision sale approved, Abercrombie &amp; Fitch to replace it on the S&amp;P 500,&quot;] accessed March 29, 2007. {{Dead link|date=October 2010|bot=H3llBot}}&lt;/ref&gt; According to the [[Los Angeles Times]], the deal was closed and the ownership change was made official on that same day.&lt;ref name=&quot;lat&quot;&gt;[http://www.latimes.com/business/printedition/la-fi-univision30mar30,1,7968164.story?coll=la-headlines-pe-business&amp;ctrack=1&amp;cset=true &quot;Univision's new ownership takes over,&quot;] ''Los Angeles Times'', March 30, 2007.&lt;/ref&gt;

However, Univision's shareholders filed two class-action lawsuits against the company and its board members to stop the buyout. One lawsuit claims that the board members structured the deal to only benefit the company's insiders and not the average stockholders. The other lawsuit was filed on behalf of a shareholder identified as L A Murphy, who claims that the board put its own personal interests and the interests of the winning bidder ahead of shareholders, and also failed to adequately evaluate the company's worth. In the meantime, more lawsuits were filed: one against Univision's records division for heavy-handed tactics, and the other by a winner of a ''[[¡Despierta América!]]'' $30,000 makeover contest who alleged that Univision broke its own contest rules. A long-awaited trial, it's expected to start in April 2008, at a Los Angeles court.&lt;ref name=&quot;merc&quot;&gt;[http://www.mercurynews.com/mld/mercurynews/news/local/states/california/northern_california/14932584.htm ''San Jose Mercury News'']&lt;/ref&gt;

Univision continues to gain broadcast penetration and has done so since 2004, with stations in Detroit, [[Seattle, Washington|Seattle]], [[Portland, Oregon]], [[Minneapolis, Minnesota|Minneapolis]] and Nashville, among many others.

On June 25, 2007, with the finale of ''[[La Fea Más Bella]]'', Univision led all U.S. television broadcasting networks, including English-language ones, with a 3.0 rating out of 9 share, which also made the show the second most watched of the week.&lt;ref name=&quot;variety&quot;&gt;[http://www.variety.com/article/VR1117967713.html?categoryid=1275&amp;cs=1 &quot;'La Fea' Makes Ratings History for Univision,&quot;] ''Variety''.&lt;/ref&gt; Later that year, Univision hosted the first Spanish-language presidential debate in the United States at the [[University of Miami]].&lt;ref name=&quot;afp&quot;&gt;[http://afp.google.com/article/ALeqM5gwLF-CrjIgLcd9iy0ezpo6FPlUwQ  &quot;Democratic presidential hopefuls hold TV debate in Spanish,&quot;] [[Agence France-Presse]].&lt;/ref&gt;

On April 5, 2008, Univision introduced a new [[Saturday morning cartoon]] block, ''[[Planeta U]]'', which features &quot;[[E/I|educational and informative]]&quot; programming such as ''[[Dora the Explorer]]'', ''[[Go, Diego, Go!]]'', ''[[Jakers! The Adventures of Piggley Winks]]'', ''[[Inspector Gadget's Field Trip]]'', and ''[[Beakman's World]]'', all dubbed in Spanish. The following month, [[Univision Music Group]] was sold to [[Universal Music Group]] and combined with the latter's Latin music label to become [[Universal Music Latin Entertainment]].

In 2009, the network sponsored a countdown in [[Times Square]], similar to the [[New Year's Eve]] event. On the night of June 12, at 11:59 PM (23:59) [[Eastern Daylight Time|EDT]], the [[Jumbotron]]-size screen ticked off the last 60 seconds of full-power [[analog TV]] in the Eastern [[time zone]], culminating in the message &quot;&lt;small&gt;BIENVENIDOS A LA ERA DIGITAL&lt;/small&gt;&quot; (&quot;welcome to the digital era&quot;). This was aired live by the network during ''Ultima Hora: Una Nueva Era''.  The ball was lighted in white but was not dropped, remaining at the bottom where the lighted &quot;2009&quot; sign also remained, despite the [[DTV Delay Act|four-month delay]] from February 17.

In October, 2010, Televisa agreed to take a 5% stake in Univision, which it can grow in the future, and to extend and expand the companies' long-term program license agreement. The new program license agreement will include Internet and mobile rights and cover key Mexican football (soccer) rights. The agreement will run through at least 2020, but more likely 2025 or later, compared with the previous deal's 2017 expiration.&lt;ref&gt;[http://i2.esmas.com/documents/2010/10/25/1193/televisa-y-univision-ampliaran-relacion-estrategica-en-eua.pdf GRUPO TELEVISA Y UNIVISION AMPLIARÁN RELACIÓN ESTRATÉGICA EN LOS ESTADOS UNIDOS DE AMÉRICA]&lt;/ref&gt;

==Univision HD==
'''Univision HD''' is a [[1080i]] [[HDTV|high definition]] simulcast feed of the main Univision network that began operations on January 1, 2010 at 12:02 a.m./ET on its New York and Los Angeles affiliates [[WXTV-DT]] and [[KMEX-DT]], respectively. Univision's first program to be televised in high definition was the [[Tournament of Roses Parade]], later that day.&lt;ref&gt;[http://hd.engadget.com/2009/12/05/univision-and-telefutura-en-hd-starting-monday/ Univision starting to broadcast in HD]&lt;/ref&gt;  On January 18, 2010 Univision began airing ''Hasta que el Dinero nos Separe'' in high definition, it becoming the first telenovela on the network to be so transmitted. The telenovelas ''Un Gancho Al Corazon'' and ''Sortilegio'' also began airing in high definition on that date. Most other telenovelas now air in HD as well. All of Univision's [[2010 FIFA World Cup]] coverage was also in HD. ''[[Noticiero Univision]]'', ''[[Primer Impacto]]'', ''[[¡Despierta América!]]'', ''[[Al Punto]]'', ''[[Mira Quien Baila]]'', and ''[[¡Viva la Familia!]]'' have began airing in HD as well. Some movies also air in HD. DirecTV added the East Coast HD feed on April 28, 2010.&lt;ref&gt;[http://dtv.client.shareholder.com/releasedetail.cfm?ReleaseID=464645 DIRECTV Launches Univision and TeleFutura in Crystal-Clear HD] DirecTV Press Release April 28, 2010&lt;/ref&gt; Dish Network has been broadcasting the HD feed since May 12, 2010.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.multichannel.com/article/452575-Dish_To_Launch_Galavision_HD.php Dish To Launch Galavision HD] ''Multichannel News'' May 12, 2010&lt;/ref&gt;

==Programming==&lt;!--PLEASE DO NOT ADD PROGRAM GUIDES, AS THESE WILL BE DELETED, PER [[WP:NOTDIR]]. THANK YOU.--&gt;
{{Main|List of programs broadcast by Univision|List of programs produced by Univision}}
The majority of Univision's programming consists of series produced and broadcast by Mexican broadcast network [[Televisa]] and Venezuelan broadcast network [[Venevision]], however much of Univision's telenovelas are produced by Televisa. The network's signature program, the Saturday night variety show ''[[Sabado Gigante]]'', hosted by Don Francisco, has aired on Univision since 1989; as such, Univision is one of only three American television networks that airs a first-run program during Saturday primetime (Fox and [[CBS]] are the only others). Situation comedies and variety shows largely make up Univision's weekend lineup.

Univision does produce a moderate amount of original programming including ''Sabado Gigante'', the talk shows ''El Show de Cristina'' and ''[[Casos de Familia]]'', the daily morning music video program ''[[Tu Desayuno Alegre]]'', the reality competition series ''[[Nuestra Belleza Latina]]'', and national news programming including the flagship [[Noticiero Univision]] newscast, ''[[Primer Impacto]]'' and the morning news program ''[[Despierta America]]''; Univision also operates its own television production firm launched in 2009, called Univision Studios, which produces original content for the network.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.prnewswire.com/news-releases/univision-announces-launch-of-univision-studios-78674827.html PR Newswire]&lt;/ref&gt; The network's weekend daytime schedule features a morning children's program block called ''[[Planeta U]]'', consisting of Spanish-dubbed versions of American children's programs that comply with the [[Federal Communications Commission|FCC]]'s [[E/I]] guidelines;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.allbusiness.com/entertainment-arts/broadcasting-industry/8938567-1.html AllBusiness]&lt;/ref&gt; and also typically airs telenovelas that appeal to teen or pre-teen audiences on early Saturday afternoons. The network also airs some films, generally in weekend timeslots; but unlike Telefutura and Telemundo, Univision does not air Spanish-dubbed English-language films. While Univision largely programs its affiliates schedules in a sense since the network's affiliates air the large majority of its programming, some Univision affiliates do produce locally-produced programs such as local evening newscasts and public-affairs programs; many affiliates that do produce newscasts generally air them only on Monday through Friday evenings and with only a few exceptions, do not carry weekend newscasts.

In 2004 Univision had a list of words it edited from programming to comply with United States federal regulators. The words affected had no negative connotations in some Spanish-speaking countries, but had obscene connotations in other countries.&lt;ref&gt;Shoer-Roth, Daniel and &quot;[http://www.highbeam.com/doc/1G1-118679986.html 'Censorship list' bans controversial words from Univision's on-air lexicon.]&quot; ''[[The Miami Herald]]'' at ''[[Knight Ridder/Tribune Business News]]''. June 28, 2004. Retrieved on March 30, 2010.&lt;/ref&gt; In June 2005 [[Grupo Televisa]] filed a lawsuit against Univision in a U.S. federal court accusing the network of several actions, including &quot;unauthorized editing&quot; of Televisa programming.&lt;ref&gt;Grover, Ronald. &quot;[http://www.businessweek.com/investor/content/jun2006/pi20060627_999458.htm Televisa and Univision: Stay Tuned!]&quot; ''[[Businessweek]]''. June 27, 2006. Retrieved on March 30, 2010.&lt;/ref&gt;

==See also==
* [[List of Univision affiliates]]
* [[List of United States television networks]]
* [[TeleFutura]]
* [[Univision Communications]]

==References==
{{Reflist}}

==External links and sources==
{{Commons category}}
*{{Official website|http://www.univision.com}} (in Spanish)
*[http://www.univision.net/corp/en/index.jsp Official Corporate Site] (in English)
*[http://www.sintv.org/ Spanish International Network] Historical site (in English)
*[http://www.museum.tv/archives/etv/U/htmlU/univision/univision.htm Univision], from the [[Museum of Broadcast Communications]] website
*[http://www.univision.net/corp/en/pr/Miami_10032005-1.html Univision Blows Competition Away with Explosive February Sweep Results], a March 2005 press release

{{Broadcast Television}}
{{Univision Communications}}
{{Sports television in the United States}}

[[Category:Spanish-language television networks in the United States]]
[[Category:Television channels and stations established in 1961]]
[[Category:Univision| ]]
[[Category:Texas Pacific Group companies]]

[[de:Univision]]
[[es:Univision]]
[[fr:Univision]]
[[nl:Univision]]
[[ja:ユニビジョン]]
[[pt:Univisión]]
[[ru:Univision]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
