<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="161366" ns="0" title="Tom Baker"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Other persons|Tom Baker}}

{{BLP sources|date=March 2010}}

{{Infobox person
| name         = Tom Baker
| image        = Tom Baker cropped.jpg
| caption      = Baker in 2008
| birth_name   = 
| birth_date   = {{Birth date and age|1934|01|20|df=y}}
| birth_place  = [[Liverpool]], [[England]]
| occupation   = [[Actor]]
| years_active = 1968–present&lt;ref name=&quot;imdb&quot;&gt;{{IMDb name|0048982}}&lt;/ref&gt;
| spouse       = Sue Baker ([[nee]] Jerrard) (1986–present)
| website      = http://www.tom-baker.co.uk}}

'''Thomas Stewart &quot;Tom&quot; Baker''' (born 20 January 1934) is a [[British people|British]] [[actor]]. He is best known for playing the [[Fourth Doctor|fourth incarnation]] of [[Doctor (Doctor Who)|the Doctor]] in the [[science fiction on television|science fiction television]] series ''[[Doctor Who]]'', a role he played from 1974 to 1981.

==Early life==
Baker was born in [[Scotland Road]], [[Liverpool]], the son of Mary Jane
([[married and maiden names|née]] Fleming), a cleaner and John Stewart Baker, a [[sailor]] who was rarely at home. His parents were [[working class]] [[Liverpudlian]]s. Baker left school at 15 to become a [[Roman Catholic]] [[monk]] and remained in the monastic life for six years, but left after losing his faith,&lt;ref&gt;[http://newhumanist.org.uk/865/alehouse-rock-laurie-taylor-interviews-tom-baker New Humanist website, ibid.]&lt;/ref&gt; and did his [[National Service#Peacetime service|National Service]] in the [[Royal Army Medical Corps]], serving for two years from 1955 until 1957. At the same time he took up acting, at first as a hobby.

==Career==
In the late 1960s and early 1970s Baker was part of [[Laurence Olivier]]'s [[Royal National Theatre|National Theatre]] company, and had his first big film break in 1971 with the role of [[Rasputin]] in the film ''[[Nicholas and Alexandra]]'' after Olivier recommended him for the part.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.imdb.com/title/tt0067483/trivia IMDb profile]&lt;/ref&gt; He also appeared in [[Pier Paolo Pasolini]]'s [[I Racconti di Canterbury|version]] of [[Geoffrey Chaucer|Chaucer's]] ''[[The Canterbury Tales]]'', released in 1972, as a younger husband of the [[The Wife of Bath's Prologue and Tale|Wife of Bath]].

===''Doctor Who'' (1974–1981)===
In 1974, Baker took on the role of [[Doctor (Doctor Who)|the Doctor]] from [[Jon Pertwee]].  He was recommended to producer [[Barry Letts]] by the BBC's Head of Serials, Bill Slater, who had directed Baker in ''[[Play of the Month]]''. Impressed by Baker on meeting him, Letts was convinced he was right for the part after seeing his performance in ''[[The Golden Voyage of Sinbad]]''.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.digitalspy.co.uk/cult/s7/doctorwho/news/a181678/a-tribute-to-doctor-who-legend-barry-letts.html |title=A tribute to 'Doctor Who' legend Barry Letts}}&lt;/ref&gt; Baker was working on a construction site at the time, as acting jobs were scarce. Initially he was dubbed &quot;[[boiler suit|Boiler Suit]] Tom&quot; by the media, as he had been supplied for a press conference with some old studio set clothes to replace his modest garments. {{Citation needed|date=March 2010}}

He quickly made the part his own.  As the Doctor, his eccentric style of dress and speech—particularly his trademark long [[scarf]] and fondness for [[jelly baby|jelly babies]]—made him an immediately recognisable figure, and he quickly caught the viewing public's imagination. Baker played the Doctor for seven consecutive seasons over a seven-year period, making him the longest-serving actor in the part on-screen. Baker himself suggested many aspects of the Fourth Doctor's personality. The distinctive scarf came about by accident: [[James Acheson]], the costume designer, had provided far more wool than was necessary to the knitter, Begonia Pope, and Ms. Pope knitted all the wool she was given; it was Baker who suggested that he wear the resulting—ridiculously over-long—scarf.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.shannonsullivan.com/drwho/serials/4a.html|title=Robot|accessdate=2007-03-18|last=Sullivan|first=Shannon Patrick|date=2006-05-02|work=A Brief History of Time (Travel)}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The manifestation played by Tom Baker (1974–1981) is often regarded as the most popular of the Doctors.  In polls conducted by ''[[Doctor Who Magazine]]'', Baker has lost the &quot;Best Doctor&quot; category only three times: Once to [[Sylvester McCoy]] in 1990, and twice to [[David Tennant]] in 2006 and 2009.&lt;ref name =&quot;best&quot;&gt;{{cite news|title=David Tennant named 'best Dr Who'|url=http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/entertainment/6211584.stm|work=[[BBC News]]|date=2006-12-06|accessdate=2007-02-25}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In a poll published by ''BBC Homes and Antiques'' magazine in January 2006, Baker was voted the fourth most eccentric star. He was beaten by [[Björk]], [[Chris Eubank]] and [[David Icke]].&lt;ref name =&quot;eccentric&quot;&gt;{{cite news|title=Bjork voted 'most eccentric' star|url=http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/entertainment/4594602.stm|work=[[BBC News]]|date=2006-12-06|accessdate=2007-04-14}}&lt;/ref&gt;

He continues to be associated with the Doctor, appearing on documentaries such as ''The Story of Doctor Who'' and ''[[Doctor Who Confidential]]'' and giving interviews about his time on the programme.  He reappeared as the Doctor for the 1993 charity special ''[[Dimensions in Time]]'' and audio for the PC game ''[[Destiny of the Doctors]]''.In 1996 he appraised his time on the show as the highlight of his life, and was proud of Oliver Read berating him as a publicity whore as they got drunk together in The Ivy.  It was the same night that Tom received his tattoo of a dolphin in lieu of playing Estragon in 'Waiting for Godot'.{{citation needed|date=September 2011}} He gets interviewed often in documentaries on the extras of [[Doctor Who DVD releases]] from his era as the Doctor and has recorded DVD commentaries for many of the stories.

In a 2004 interview regarding the series' revival, Baker suggested that he be cast as [[Master (Doctor Who)|the Master]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |first=Paul |last=English |title=OLD FATHER TIMELORD|url=http://www.dailyrecord.co.uk/news/tm_objectid=14629306&amp;method=full&amp;siteid=89488&amp;headline=old-father-timelord-name_page.html|work=[[Daily Record (Scotland)|Daily Record]]|date=2004-09-11|accessdate=2007-02-02}}&lt;/ref&gt; In a 2006 interview with ''[[The Sun (newspaper)|The Sun]]'' newspaper, he claims that he has not watched any episodes of the new series because he &quot;just can't be bothered&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|first=Dave|last=Masters|url=http://www.thesun.co.uk/article/0,,5-2006050033,00.html|title=Dr Who is alien to Tom|work=[[The Sun (newspaper)|The Sun]]|date=2006-02-01&lt;!--This date is approximate; if anyone can confirm the date of publication, please do so.--&gt;
 |accessdate = 2006-08-17}}&lt;/ref&gt; In June 2006, Baker once again expressed interest in the role in a guest column for ''[[Radio Times]]'', noting that he &quot;did watch a little bit of the new ''Doctor Who'' and I think the new fella, [[David Tennant|Tennant]], is excellent.&quot; {{Citation needed|date=March 2010}}

While [[Peter Davison]], [[Colin Baker]], [[Sylvester McCoy]] and [[Paul McGann]] have all reprised their roles for audio adventures produced since the 1990s by [[Big Finish Productions|Big Finish]] (and sometimes the BBC) Baker had until 2009 declined to voice the Doctor, saying he hadn't seen a script he liked. In July 2009, the BBC announced that Baker would return to the role for a series of five audio dramas, co-starring [[Richard Franklin]] as [[Captain Mike Yates]], which would begin release in September.  The five audios comprise a single linked story under the banner title ''[[Hornets' Nest (Doctor Who)|Hornets' Nest]]'', written by well-known author [[Paul Magrs]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title=Tom Baker Returns to Doctor Who after 28 Years|url=http://onceuponageek.com/2009/07/16/tom-baker-returns-to-doctor-who-after-28-years|work=[Once Upon a Geek]|date=2009-07-16|accessdate=2009-07-21}}&lt;/ref&gt; He returns with a sequel to ''Hornets' Nest'' called ''[[Demon Quest]]''.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.bbcshop.com/Science-Fiction/Doctor-Who-Demon-Quest-Volume-1/invt/9781408466674 &quot;Doctor Who&quot; Doctor Who: Demon Quest 1 The Relics of Time at BBC Shop&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt; Baker has also filmed inserts for a video release of the unfinished ''[[Shada]]'' and also provided narration for several BBC audio releases of old Doctor Who stories.

In March 2011 it was announced that Baker would be returning as the Fourth Doctor for two series of plays for Big Finish Productions. He will be starring alongside former companions Leela (Louise Jameson) and Romana I (Mary Tamm). The first series of six audios will be released starting from January 2012 &lt;ref&gt;http://bigf.eu/news/Tom-Baker-Joins-Big-Finish&lt;/ref&gt;

Baker has been involved in the reading of old [[List of Doctor Who novelisations|Target novelisations]] in the BBC Audio range of talking books, &quot;Doctor Who (Classic Novels)&quot;. ''Doctor Who and the Giant Robot'' was the first release in the range read by Baker, released on 5 November 2007, followed by Baker reading ''Doctor Who and the Brain of Morbius'' (released 4 February 2008), ''Doctor Who and the Creature from the Pit'' (released on 7 April 2008) and ''Doctor Who and the Pyramids of Mars'' (released 14 August 2008). In October 2009, Baker was interviewed for [[BBC Radio 4]]'s ''Last Word'' to pay tribute to the deceased former Doctor Who producer [[Barry Letts]]. He described Letts, who originally cast him in the role, as “the big link in changing my entire life”.

===Little Britain===
After his work on ''[[Lionel Nimrod's Inexplicable World]]'', in 2001 Baker was cast as a similar narrator of ''[[Little Britain]]'' on [[BBC Radio 4]], and remained in the role when it transferred to television. Baker has suggested that he was chosen for the part in ''Little Britain'' due to his popularity with Walliams and Lucas, part of the generation to whom he is the favourite Doctor. &quot;I am now being employed by the children who grew up watching me&quot;, he stated in a recent DVD commentary.&lt;ref&gt;Voice-over commentaries on the BBC DVD &quot;[[Robot (Doctor Who)|Robot]]&quot; (1974, 2007)&lt;/ref&gt;  Another trademark of Little Britain's narration is the deadpan quotation of old rap lyrics, usually in the opening credit sequence.

On 17 November 2005, to mark the start of Series 3 of ''Little Britain'', Baker read the [[Continuity (broadcasting)|continuity announcements]] on [[BBC One]] from 19:00 to 21:30 [[GMT]]. The scripts were written by the same writers as ''Little Britain'' ([[David Walliams]] and [[Matt Lucas]]) and Baker assumed his ''Little Britain'' persona. He used lines such as &quot;Hello, tellyviewers. You're watching the BBC One!&quot; and &quot;In half an hour, Jenny Dickens's classic serial ''[[Bleak House (2005 TV serial)|Bleak House]]''. But first let's see what the poor people are up to in the first of two visits this evening to the ''[[EastEnders]]''.&quot;

===Film===
Baker also appeared in the 1971 film ''Nicholas and Alexandra'' as [[Grigori Rasputin]]. He was nominated for two [[Golden Globes|Golden Globe Awards]] for his performance, one for Best Actor in a Supporting Role and another for Best Newcomer.

Baker appeared as Moore, an artist whose paintings are imbued with voodoo power, in ''[[The Vault of Horror (film)|The Vault of Horror]]'' (1973),  as Koura, the villainous sorcerer, in Ray Harryhausen's ''The Golden Voyage of Sinbad'' (1973); and as Halvarth, the Elven healer, in ''[[Dungeons &amp; Dragons (film)|Dungeons &amp; Dragons]]'' (2000).

In the late 1990s, it was reported that Baker was a candidate for the role of [[Gandalf]] in the ''[[The Lord of the Rings film trilogy|Lord of the Rings]]'' films.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.theonering.net/perl/newsview/1/940961808|title=Just Who on Earth is Tom Baker?|accessdate=2006-08-17|last=Regina|first=Michael|date=1999-10-26|work=TheOneRing.net}}&lt;/ref&gt; Baker has since stated that he was only approached for &quot;a role&quot; in the film, and when told that it would mean spending months away in [[New Zealand]], he turned down the offer. {{Citation needed|date=March 2010}}

===Voice acting===
Baker has appeared in various radio productions, including a role as &quot;Britain's most celebrated criminal barrister&quot;, Sir [[Edward Marshall-Hall]] in ''John Mortimer Presents the Trials of Marshall Hall'' (1996), and a part in the 2001 [[BBC Radio 4]] version of ''[[The Thirty-Nine Steps]]'' as [[Sir Walter Bullivant]]. He guest starred in ''[[The Further Adventures of Sherlock Holmes]]'' (a pastiche series written by [[Bert Coules]]) in the 2002 episode &quot;[[The Saviour of Cripplegate Square]]&quot;.

From 2000 to 2005 Tom voiced the character Max Bear in the Channel 4 (UK) Max Bear Productions animated series. More recently, he voiced the role of the villain [[ZeeBad]] in the 2005 computer-animated film version of ''[[The Magic Roundabout (film)|The Magic Roundabout]]''. In 2007 he voiced the character of Robert Baron in the BBC animated series The Secret Show. 

Baker narrates the children's computer animation series ''[[The Beeps]]'' which is shown on [[Five (channel)|Five's]] ''[[Milkshake!]]'' as well as narrating ''Tales of Aesop'' on [[BBC]], a television series based on Aesop's Fables with beautiful puppet animation.

===Video games===
Baker also returned to star as the ''Fourth Doctor'' in the video game ''[[Destiny of the Doctors]]'' in 1997. His voice has also featured in ''Ecco the Dolphin: Defender of the Future'' (2000) ''[[Warhammer 40,000: Fire Warrior]]'' (2003),''[[Cold Winter]]'' (2005), ''[[MediEvil: Resurrection]]'', ''[[Hostile Waters: Antaeus Rising]]'', ''[[Little Britain: The Video Game]]'' (2007) and &quot;[[Sudeki]]&quot; (2004)

===Narration===
Baker is a prolific and highly recognisable voiceover artist. In a 2005 survey of British adults, Baker's voice was found to be the fourth most recognisable after [[Elizabeth II of the United Kingdom|the Queen]], [[Tony Blair]] and [[Margaret Thatcher]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.dailyrecord.co.uk/news/tm_objectid=16637124&amp;method=full&amp;siteid=66633&amp;headline=bt-bring-in-voice-of-baker--name_page.html BT Bring in the voice of Baker]&lt;/ref&gt;
Tom Baker has also narrated an animation adventure of Doctor Who as the Fourth Doctor.
In 1992 and 1993 Baker narrated BBC radio comedy series ''[[Lionel Nimrod's Inexplicable World]]''. In 1994, Baker provided the narration for [[Channel 4]]'s ''[[Equinox (television)|Equinox]]'' [[rave]] documentary ''Rave New World''.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.imdb.com/title/tt0887478/ &quot;Equinox&quot; Rave New World (1994)&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt; In 2002 he had a speaking role in the critically acclaimed but commercially unsuccessful ''[[Hostile Waters (game)|Hostile Waters]]'' as the Narrator.

Baker has worked on a number of [[video game]]s, including ''[[Kult: Heretic Kingdoms]]'' (also known as ''Heretic Kingdoms: The Inquisition''), ''[[Hostile Waters (game)|Hostile Waters]]'' (2001), ''[[Cold Winter]]'' (2005), ''Medievil: Resurrection'' (2005), ''[[Warhammer 40,000: Fire Warrior]]'' (2003), and ''[[Ecco the Dolphin: Defender of the Future]]'' (2000). He provided the voiceover for the ''[[Perfect Dark]]'' (2000) TV commercials. He also voiced both the narrator and the god &quot;Tetsu&quot; in the role-playing game ''[[Sudeki]]'', but was uncredited.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |first=Greg|last=Howson|url=http://www.guardian.co.uk/computergames/story/0,,1290507,00.html|title=Games watch|work=[[The Guardian]]|date=2004-08-26|accessdate=2006-08-17}}&lt;/ref&gt;

During the first three months of 2006, his voice was used by [[BT Group|BT]] for spoken delivery of [[Short message service|text messages]] to landline phones. He recorded 11,593 phrases, containing every sound in the English language, for use by the text-to-speech service.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite press release|publisher=[[BT Group]]|date=2006-01-27|url=http://www.btplc.com/News/Articles/ShowArticle.cfm?ArticleID=a40cfaf2-043b-47a0-8543-bb216333707f|title=Voice of ''Little Britain'' becomes BT's voice of text|accessdate=2006-08-17}}&lt;/ref&gt;
The BT text message service returned from 1 December 2006 until  8 January 2007, with 2p from each text going to the charity [[Shelter (charity)|Shelter]]. Also a single &quot;sung&quot; by Baker's text voice, &quot;[[You Really Got Me]]&quot;, originally by [[The Kinks]], was released on 18 December 2006 with BT's proceeds going to the charity. The creator of the song was Mark Murphy, designer of the site.&lt;ref&gt;[http://tombakersays.com/ &quot;Tom Baker Says&amp;nbsp;...&quot;]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite press release|publisher=[[BT Group]]|date=2006-12-01|url=http://www.btplc.com/News/Articles/Showarticle.cfm?ArticleID=3f6046da-2f3c-42bb-89c2-eb136cd9b222|title=Tom Baker says… &quot;You really got me&quot;|accessdate=2006-12-04}}&lt;/ref&gt;

His voice may be heard at London's [[Natural History Museum]] narrating commentary to some of the exhibits that support [[Charles Darwin|Darwin's]] theory of [[natural selection]].

Baker has made three other brief forays into the world of music: he provides the monologue to the track &quot;Witness to a Murder (Part Two)&quot; on the album ''[[Six (Mansun album)|Six]]'' by [[Mansun]]; he appears on Technocat's single &quot;Only Human&quot; in 1995, and in 2002 he recorded the monologue to the track &quot;Megamorphosis&quot; on the album [http://www.andabrek.com '''''andabrek'''''] by Stephen James, although the album was not released until 2009. Baker provides narrative at two British tourist attractions: the [[Nemesis (roller coaster)|Nemesis roller coaster]] at [[Alton Towers]], [[Staffordshire]]; and the [[London Dungeon]], a museum depicting gory and macabre events in the capital, narrating the events leading up to and comprising [[The Great Fire of London]].

Tom Baker voiced the character &quot;Max Bear&quot;, a series of animated stories broadcast on Channel 4 (UK Terrestrial) from 2000 to 2005.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.imdb.com/title/tt0374421/ IMDb profile of ''Max Bear'']&lt;/ref&gt; He narrated Australian cartoonist [[Bruce Petty]]'s 2006 movie about world politics, ''Global Haywire''.

[[File:Tombaker1991london.jpg|thumb|Tom Baker and his [[Dalek]] friend in [[Trafalgar Square]] London, August 1991. This photocall tied in with the [[Reeltime Pictures]] VHS release, Who on Earth is Tom Baker?]]

==Television==
Baker played [[Puddleglum]], a &quot;marsh-wiggle&quot;, in the BBC adaptation of [[C.S. Lewis]]' ''[[The Silver Chair]]''.

Baker also portrayed [[Sherlock Holmes]] in a four part BBC miniseries version of ''[[The Hound of the Baskervilles]]'' in 1982. In the U.S., this production was telecast on [[A&amp;E Network|A&amp;E]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.imdb.com/title/tt0174399/ &quot;The Hound of the Baskervilles&quot; (1982)&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;  Baker also made a memorable appearance in ''[[Blackadder II]]'' as wild-eyed sea captain Redbeard Rum.

Tom Baker was also in the series ''[[Strange (TV series)|Strange]]'' in 2004 as a blind priest who possessed knowledge of the Devil.

He also appeared as a guest on the quiz show ''[[Have I Got News For You]]'' and was subsequently described by presenter [[Angus Deayton]] as the funniest guest in the show's history. A particular highlight of the show was when Baker gave an anecdotal account of how he, whilst entering a recording studio in Wales, was accosted by a member of the public who told Baker &quot;I will never forgive you, nor will my wife, for what you did to our grammar schools&quot;. Baker claimed that the initial benevolence he had first felt for the stranger completely evaporated and he responded with &quot;What are you talking about, you daft bugger?!?!&quot;, upon which the stranger replied &quot;I'm so sorry. For a moment I thought you were [[Shirley Williams]]&quot;.

According to the ''[[Daily Mirror]]'', Baker's appearance made him a cult figure once again and helped revive his career.&lt;ref name=weathers&gt;Helen Weathers, &quot;Who's got views for you&quot;, ''Daily Mirror'', December 30, 1998&lt;/ref&gt; He later returned to Have I Got News For You as a guest host in 2008.
Baker played the role of the Captain in the [[Challenge TV|Challenge]] version of ''[[Fort Boyard (TV series)|Fort Boyard]]'', and has also hosted the children's literature show, ''The Book Tower''. He has recorded a show called, 'Tom Baker - In Confidence' to be shown in April 2010.&lt;ref&gt;[http://tv.sky.com/tom-baker-in-confidence Tom Baker- In Confidence]&lt;/ref&gt;

==Books==
Baker's [[autobiography]], ''Who on Earth is Tom Baker?'' (ISBN 0-00-638854-X), was published in 1997. He has also written a short fairytale-style novel, ''[[The Boy Who Kicked Pigs]]'' (ISBN 0-571-19771-X), which is subtitled ''&quot;A Grotesque Masterpiece&quot;''.

==Personal life==
Baker's first marriage in 1961 was to Anna Wheatcroft (niece of the [[rose]] grower [[Harry Wheatcroft]]). They had two sons Daniel and Piers, but divorced in 1966 and Baker lost contact with his sons until a chance meeting with Piers in a pub in [[New Zealand]] allowed them to renew their relationship.&lt;ref name=weathers /&gt; In December 1980 he married [[Lalla Ward]] who had co-starred in ''Doctor Who'' (playing his companion [[Romana]]) with him for two years. However, the marriage lasted only 16 months.

In 1986, Baker married for a third time, this time to Sue Jerrard, who had been an assistant editor on ''Doctor Who''. They moved to The Bell House, a converted school in [[Boughton Malherbe]] near [[Maidstone]], [[Kent]] where they kept several [[cat]]s, before emigrating to [[France]] in January 2003.  They sold the property to [[Vic Reeves]], shortly after Baker had worked with him on ''[[Randall &amp; Hopkirk (Deceased)]]''.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.kentnews.co.uk/kent-news/Baker--I_d-do-Dr-Who-cameo-_if-they-ask-me-nicely_-newsinkent11102.aspx?news=local ''Kent News'' interview with Baker]&lt;/ref&gt; In November 2006, Baker returned to live in the UK, initially buying a house in [[Royal Tunbridge Wells|Tunbridge Wells]], before later moving to the [[East Sussex]] countryside.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.tom-baker.co.uk/ The Official Tom Baker Website]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.tom-baker.co.uk/pages/content/index.asp?PageID=152 Biodata]&lt;/ref&gt;

Baker has sceptical views on religion&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.bfi.org.uk/features/interviews/baker.html Transcript of Tom Baker interviewed by Mark Gatiss at the British Film Institute, 29 September 2001]&lt;/ref&gt; and describes himself as irreligious, or occasionally as [[Buddhist]], but not anti-religious. &quot;People are quite happy believing the wrong things. I wasn't unhappy believing all that s***. Now I'm not unhappy thinking about it because I can laugh at it.&quot;&lt;ref name=Herald&gt;Mark Smith, [http://www.heraldscotland.com/sport/spl/aberdeen/from-gallifrey-to-glenbogle-monk-soldier-time-lord-now-tom-baker-s-arrived-in-monarch-of-the-glen-and-he-s-loving-every-minute-by-mark-smith-1.75339 &quot;From Gallifrey to Glenbogle&quot;], ''The Herald'', 17 September 2004&lt;/ref&gt; Politically, Baker has expressed disdain for both the [[Conservative Party (UK)|Conservatives]] and the [[Labour (UK)|Labour Party]] saying, in 1998, &quot;When the Conservatives were in I cannot tell you how much I hated them. But I realise how shallow I am because I now hate the Labour Party as much.&quot;&lt;ref name=weathers /&gt;

==Works==
===Filmography===
* 1968 – ''The Winter's Tale'' – The Bear
* 1971 – ''[[Nicholas and Alexandra]]'' – [[Grigori Rasputin|Rasputin]]
* 1972 – ''[[The Canterbury Tales (film)]] (I racconti di Canterbury)'' – Jenkin
* 1973 – ''Cari Genitori (Dear Parents)'' – Karl
* 1973 – ''[[The Vault of Horror (film)]]'' – Moore
* 1973 – ''[[Luther (1973 film)]]'' – Tom's character, [[Pope Leo X]], doesn't appear in some versions of the film
* 1973 – ''[[Frankenstein: The True Story]] (TV film)'' – Sea Captain
* 1973 – ''[[The Golden Voyage of Sinbad]]'' – Koura
* 1974 – ''[[The Mutations|The Mutations (The Freakmaker)]]'' – Lynch
* 1984 – ''[[The Passionate Pilgrim (film)]] (short film)'' – Sir Tom
* 1984 – ''[[The Zany Adventures of Robin Hood]]'' – [[Sir Guy of Gisbourne|Sir Guy de Gisbourne]]
* 2000 – ''[[Dungeons &amp; Dragons (film)|Dungeons &amp; Dragons]]'' – Halvarth
* 2005 – ''[[The Magic Roundabout (film)|The Magic Roundabout]]'' – Zeebad

===Television===
* 1968 – ''[[Dixon of Dock Green]]'' – &quot;The Attack&quot; – The man
* 1968 – ''[[Market in Honey Lane]]'' (ATV soap opera) – &quot;The Matchmakers&quot; – Doorman
* 1968 – ''George and the Dragon'' (ATV sitcom) – &quot;The 10:15 Train&quot; – Porter
* 1968 – ''[[Z-Cars]]'' – &quot;Hudson's Way&quot; (two-part episode) – Harry Russell
* 1968 – ''[[Dixon of Dock Green]]'' – &quot;Number 13&quot; – Foreman
* 1969 – ''[[Thirty-Minute Theatre]]'' – &quot;The Victims: Frontier&quot; – Corporal Schabe
* 1970 – ''[[Softly, Softly (TV series)|Softly, Softly]]'' (aka, ''Softly Softly: Taskforce'') – &quot;Like any other Friday&quot; – Site Foreman
* 1972 – ''BBC [[Play of the Month]]'' – &quot;The Millionairess&quot; – Dr. Ahmed el Kabir
* 1973 – ''[[Arthur of the Britons]]'' – Series 2 episode &quot;Go Warily&quot; – Brandreth / Gavron
* 1974 – ''The Author of Beltraffio'' (TV film) – Mark Ambient
* 1974–1981 – ''[[Doctor Who]]'' – The [[Fourth Doctor]]
* 1978 – four episodes of the BBC2 series ''[[Late Night Story (TV series)|Late Night Story]]'' – Each episode was an eerie tale involving the theme of childhood. Episodes ran for fifteen minutes and were aired before the station closed for the night. One episode, &quot;[[Sredni Vashtar]]&quot;, which had been scheduled to start the series, went unscreened due to a writer's strike.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.screenonline.org.uk/tv/id/1155411/index.html screenonline: Late Night Story, 17 January 2008]&lt;/ref&gt;
* 1979 – ''[[The Book Tower]]'' (22 episodes) – Presenter (himself)
* 1980 – ''[[The Curse of King Tut's Tomb (1980 film)|The Curse of King Tut's Tomb]]'' – Hasan
* 1982 – BBC version of ''[[The Hound of the Baskervilles]]'' – [[Sherlock Holmes]]
* 1983 – ''Jemima Shore Investigates'' – &quot;Dr. Ziegler's Casebook&quot; – Dr. Norman Ziegler
* 1983 - ''[[Doctor Who]]'' episode &quot;[[The Five Doctors]]&quot; - Fourth Doctor
* 1984 – ''[[Remington Steele]]'' – &quot;Hounded Steele&quot; – [[Interpol]] agent Anatole Blaylock
* 1985 – ''[[Jackanory]] – The Iron Man'' by [[Ted Hughes]] – Storyteller (himself)
* 1986 – [[BBC]] adaptation of ''[[The Life and Loves of a She-Devil]]'' – Father Ferguson
* 1986 – ''[[Blackadder II]]'' episode &quot;[[Potato (Blackadder)|Potato]]&quot;  – Captain Redbeard Rum
* 1986 – ''The [[Kenny Everett]] Television Show'' – Season 4 episode 1 – Patient, aka John Thompson, aka Blu-Tac, aka Tom
* 1990 – ''[[The Silver Chair (1990)]]'' – [[Puddleglum]]
* 1990 – [[Douglas Adams]]'s [[futurology]] documentary ''[[Hyperland]]'' – Software Agent
* 1990 – ''Boom'' – Co-presenter
* 1991 – ''The Law Lord'' – Sir Lionel Sweeting
* 1991 – ''Selling Hitler'' – Manfred Fischer
* 1992 – ''[[Cluedo (game show)|Cluedo]]'' (series 3) – Professor Plum
* 1992–1995 – ''[[Medics (TV series)|Medics]]'' – Professor Geoffrey Hoyt
* 1993 – ''[[Doctor Who]] – [[Dimensions in Time]]'' – The [[Fourth Doctor]]
* 1994 – ''[[The Imaginatively Titled Punt &amp; Dennis Show]]'' – &quot;Actor in supermarket&quot; (11 second cameo)
* 1998 – ''[[Have I Got News For You]]'' – guest (himself)
* 2000 – ''[[This Is Your Life (UK TV series)|This Is Your Life]]'' – himself
* 2000–2001 – [[Randall &amp; Hopkirk (Deceased)|revival]] of ''[[Randall and Hopkirk (Deceased)]]'' – Wyvern
* 2001 – ''[[Fun at the Funeral Parlour]]'' – Quimby
* 2003 – ''[[Swiss Toni]]'' – &quot;Cars Don't Make You Fat&quot; – Derek Asquith
* 2003 – ''[[Strange (TV series)|Strange]]'' – &quot;Asmoth&quot; – Father Bernard
* 2003 – ''[[Fort Boyard (TV series)|Fort Boyard]]'' – The Captain
* 2003–2006 – ''[[Little Britain]]'' – Narrator
* 2004–2005 – ''[[Monarch of the Glen (TV series)|Monarch of the Glen]]'' (series 6 &amp; 7 only) – [[Donald Ulyses MacDonald|Donald MacDonald]]
* 2007 – ''[[Marple (TV series)|Marple]]'' – &quot;[[Towards Zero]]&quot; – Frederick Treves
* 2008 – ''[[Little Britain USA]]'' – Narrator
* 2008 – ''[[Have I Got News For You]]'' – guest presenter (himself)
* 2010 – ''Tom Baker – In Confidence'' ([[Sky Arts]]) – Tom interviewed by his old friend Professor [[Laurie Taylor (sociologist)|Laurie Taylor]]

===Audiography===
* 1994 – John Le Carre's The Russia House – Barley Blair (lead role)&lt;ref&gt;UPC: 9780563394730&lt;/ref&gt;
* 1999 – ''[[Marilyn Imrie#Nicholas Nickleby|Nicholas Nickleby]]'' – Tom played Vincent Crummles in this BBC Radio adaptation of Dickens' classic
* 2009 – ''Doctor Who: Hornets' Nest''
* 2010 – ''Doctor Who: Demon Quest''
* 2011 – ''Doctor Who: Serpent's Crest''

===Bibliography===
* 1997 – ''Who on Earth is Tom Baker?'' (ISBN 0-00-638854-X)
* 1999 – ''[[The Boy Who Kicked Pigs]]'' (ISBN 0-571–19771-X)

==In popular culture==
*British [[synthpop]] band [[The Human League]] recorded a tribute track to the actor entitled &quot;Tom Baker&quot;. In 1981 it was released as the B-side to their &quot;[[Boys and Girls (Human League song)|Boys and Girls]]&quot; single. The instrumental track was re-released on some CD versions of their ''[[Travelogue (Human League album)|Travelogue]]'' album.

*A cartoon Tom Baker, as one of the &quot;esteemed representatives of television&quot;, appeared as the fourth incarnation of The Doctor, in ''[[The Simpsons]]'' episodes &quot;[[Sideshow Bob's Last Gleaming]]&quot;, &quot;[[Treehouse of Horror X]]&quot; and &quot;[[Mayored to the Mob]]&quot;.

*His distinctive voice has become a gift for impressionists such as [[Jon Culshaw]], who regularly impersonates Baker in the comedy series ''[[Dead Ringers (comedy)|Dead Ringers]]'': in one episode, he makes a prank call to Baker in character as the Doctor, which prompts the memorable reaction from the real Baker: &quot;No, no, there must be a mistake, ''I'm'' the Doctor.&quot; Similarly, when Culshaw called another Doctor, [[Sylvester McCoy]], in character, he got the response: &quot;Tom? Is that you? Have you been down the pub?&quot;. Other typical &quot;in character&quot; send-ups for Culshaw would include asking a garage engineer to convert his TARDIS to unleaded and complaining of the 400-year journey time from Euston to Glasgow by train, on being told by National Rail enquiries that the 12.00 train arrived at 16.15.

*On the ''[[Leverage (TV series)|Leverage]]'' episode &quot;The Mile High Job&quot; Tom Baker, along with fellow former &quot;Doctors&quot; [[Sylvester McCoy]] and [[Peter Davison]], are mentioned as available fake IDs for the team to get on board an aircraft.

*In the first ''[[Family Guy]]'' [[Star Wars]] special, &quot;[[Blue Harvest (Family Guy)|Blue Harvest]]&quot;, the intro to the Fourth Doctor appears in a [[cutaway (filmmaking)|cutaway]].

==References==
{{Reflist}}

==External links==
{{Wikiquote}}
* {{official website|http://www.tom-baker.co.uk/}}
* {{IMDb name|48982}}
* {{tv.com|person/3321}}
* [http://www.screenonline.org.uk/people/id/462127/index.html Tom Baker Biography – British Film Institute]
{{Doctor Who actors}}

{{Persondata
|NAME=Baker, Tom
|ALTERNATIVE NAMES=Baker, Thomas Stewart
|SHORT DESCRIPTION=English actor
|DATE OF BIRTH=January 20, 1934
|PLACE OF BIRTH=[[Liverpool]], England
|DATE OF DEATH=
|PLACE OF DEATH=
}}
{{DEFAULTSORT:Baker, Tom}}
[[Category:Alumni of Rose Bruford College]]
[[Category:Audio book narrators]]
[[Category:English film actors]]
[[Category:English humanists]]
[[Category:English radio actors]]
[[Category:English television actors]]
[[Category:English voice actors]]
[[Category:English Buddhists]]
[[Category:Former Roman Catholics]]
[[Category:Actors from Liverpool]]
[[Category:People from Rye, East Sussex]]
[[Category:1934 births]]
[[Category:Living people]]

[[de:Tom Baker]]
[[fr:Tom Baker]]
[[it:Tom Baker]]
[[hu:Tom Baker]]
[[nl:Tom Baker]]
[[no:Tom Baker]]
[[pl:Tom Baker]]
[[ru:Бейкер, Том]]
[[simple:Tom Baker]]
[[fi:Tom Baker]]
[[sv:Tom Baker]]
[[uk:Том Бейкер]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
