<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="1614244" ns="0" title="Stretching (body piercing)"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">[[Image:Tribes woman with ear piercing.jpg|thumb|Thai [[Hill tribe (Thailand)|hill tribe]] woman with stretched earlobes]]
[[Image:Mursi woman.jpg|thumb|[[Mursi]] woman with stretched lip and earlobes]]

'''Stretching''', in the context of [[body piercing]], is the deliberate expansion of a healed [[fistula]] for the purpose of wearing [[body piercing jewelry]]. [[Ear piercing]]s are the most commonly stretched piercings,&lt;ref name=BJS&gt;{{cite web|title=Common body piercing problems|url=http://www.bodyjewelleryshop.com/body_piercing_information/common_body_piercing_problems.cfm|publisher=Body Jewellery Shop|accessdate=14 July 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; with [[Nose piercing#Nasal septum piercing|nasal septum piercings]], [[tongue piercing]]s and [[lip piercing]]s/[[lip plate]]s following close{{Citation needed|date=July 2010}} behind. While all piercings can be stretched to some degree, cartilage piercings are usually more difficult to stretch and more likely to form [[hypertrophic scar]]s if stretched quickly. [[Dermal punch]]ing is generally the preferred method for accommodating larger jewelry in cartilage piercings.&lt;ref name=Angel&gt;{{cite book|last=Angel|first=Elayne|title=Piercing Bible|year=2009|publisher=Random House Digital, Inc.|isbn=9781580911931|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=5dvC3w7JaPQC}}&lt;/ref&gt; 

Stretching is usually done in small increments to minimize the potential for damaging the healed fistula or creating scar tissue. In [[North America]], most stretching methods go up by a single even-sized [[American wire gauge|gauge]] at a time. In [[Europe]] and most of the rest of the world, jewelry is [[metric system|metric]], but the increments between standard sizes are similar.

==Health issues==
There are few health issues directly related to stretching piercings. Most stretching methods do not create a wound. If an individual's skin [[Elasticity (physics)|elasticity]] and [[Blood vessel|vascularity]] allow, most piercings can be stretched far beyond their initial size. Anywhere  from 2g ({{convert|6.5|mm|in|sigfig=1|sp=us}})&lt;ref name=&quot;Onetribe&quot;&gt;{{cite web|title=Ear Lobe Stretching FAQ|url=http://onetribe.nu/faqs/11|publisher=Onetribe|accessdate=3 August 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; to {{convert|13|mm|in|sigfig=1|sp=us}}&lt;ref name=BJS /&gt; is normally given as the &quot;point of no return&quot; for earlobe piercings, as over this size there is a significant risk that the hole will never shrink back to the size of the original piercing. Many variables affect whether or not a stretched piercing will return to its original size, such as the length of time taken to stretch and the amount of time the piercing is fully healed at a particular size.

==Jewelry for stretched piercings==
[[Image:Stretched.jpg|thumb|right|200px|Flesh tunnel (metal)]]
There is a large variety of jewelry available for stretched piercings. Many jewelry materials can be used in the manufacturing of jewelry for stretched piercings; materials that would ordinarily be too delicate or brittle to be inserted in smaller-gauge piercings are freely used. [[Rock (geology)|Stone]], [[fossil]]ized materials, [[wood]], [[bone]], [[horn (anatomy)|horn]], [[amber]], [[bamboo]], [[silicone]], and [[glass]] are not uncommon in stretched piercings. Some of these materials &quot;breathe&quot; better than [[metal]]s or [[plastic]]s, preventing the buildup of [[sebum]] in the enlarged ear lobe. Jewelry, however, is still often made of acrylic or metal.  There are dangers associated with wearing porous materials such as acrylic, stone, wood, bamboo, horn, bone, or other materials with small or microscopic holes, in a freshly stretched piercing.  These materials not only have microscopic holes that will trap bacteria and can cause infection, but also can not be autoclaved or properly sanitized, and are therefore unfit for a fresh stretch or piercing.  The best materials for a fresh stretch that is not vulnerable to bacteria are surgical steel, titanium, and glass.  This is because these materials are non porous and can withstand the heat and pressure of an autoclave, so they can be properly sanitized before insertion.

The typical jewelry worn in a large stretched piercing is a [[Plug (jewellery)|plug]]. It is solid and usually cylindrical, and may be flared out at one or both ends (saddle-shaped), or kept in place by [[o-ring]]s fastened around the ends. A variation on this is the [[flesh tunnel]], which is shaped in the same way, but hollow in the middle. Claw-, talon-, and spiral-shaped pieces are also commonplace.  Ear-weights in varying degrees of size are also worn, commonly made from silver or bronze, though other metals such as copper or brass are occasionally used. However, some people are easily irritated by some metals; therefore, care should be taken when metal jewelry is worn.  Ear cuffs (such as the gold ones utilized in South India provinces) or wrapped bead work (common amongst the Maasai of East Africa) are other options, though are not usually seen in modern Western contexts.

There are several common methods used to enlarge piercings, of various origins and appropriate for different circumstances.

*'''Tapering''' &amp;mdash; The most common professional technique for stretching piercings, tapering involves the use of a taper, a [[cone (geometry)|conical]] rod usually made specifically for this purpose. It is [[lubrication|lubricated]] and pushed through the fistula until the widest part of the taper is level with the skin surrounding the piercing.  Larger jewelry is then pushed through, parallel to the back of the taper.&lt;ref name=Angel /&gt; Tapers come in a variety of sizes and are usually identified by the [[American wire gauge|gauge]] of the large end.  They can vary in length, but most tapers are about {{convert|2|–|3|in|cm|sp=us}}. Most tapers are made of [[surgical steel]] or [[Polymethyl methacrylate|acrylic]] and some have threads extending from the wide end to allow the attachment of [[barbell (piercing)|barbell]] jewelry, to make insertion easier. Improvised objects like [[knitting needle]]s and porcupine quills or cocktail sticks are sometimes used as tapers by people stretching at home; however, this is not recommended by professionals, as their gauge cannot be exactly determined and sterile practices are rarely followed at home. Tapering is discouraged at sizes above 2g ({{convert|6|mm|in|sp=us}}).{{citation needed|date=July 2011}}

*'''Dead stretching''' &amp;mdash; Any stretching where no equipment is used and larger jewelry is forced through an existing piercing is considered dead stretching.&lt;ref name=Angel /&gt; This can lead to injury if the fistula is unready: either a tear of the skin, or a &quot;blowout&quot;, in which the fistula is pushed out through the back of the piercing.&lt;ref name=P&amp;M&gt;{{cite web|title=Ear Stretching Info|url=http://www.piercedandmodified.co.uk/viewinfo.asp?id=15|publisher=Pierced &amp; Modified|accessdate=15 July 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; A buildup of [[scar tissue]] may be created, which will weaken the fistula and can make it more difficult to stretch in the future. Some piercings will stretch slightly on their own and larger jewelry can be inserted without the potential for unpleasant side effects, especially piercings that see a lot of &quot;play&quot;, such as [[tongue piercing]]s.
[[Image:0 guage Septum Piercing.jpg|thumb|150px|right|A septum piercing stretched to 0 ga by a combination of dead stretching and tapering.]]

*'''Teflon tape stretching''' &amp;mdash; The existing jewelry is removed and a thin layer of non-[[adhesive]] [[Thread seal tape|Teflon tape]] (PFTE tape), which is inert and safe for piercing use, is wrapped around the jewelry. Non-adhesive [[bondage tape]] and [[heat-shrink tubing]] are also frequently used.&lt;ref name=Angel /&gt;  The jewelry is then re-inserted, and as the piercing adapts to the new diameter of jewelry, the process is repeated with increasingly thicker layers of tape.

*'''Weights''' &amp;mdash; Large, heavy jewelry or weighted objects can be used to stretch piercings.  This method is not widely used in modern-day, as it tends to cause piercings to [[piercing migration|migrate]] and can, especially in [[ear]]s, lead to a thinning of tissue that is disfiguring or requires [[reconstructive surgery]].  However, it is a method that has been traditionally utilized by various tribes, such as the [[Dayak people|Dayaks]] in [[Borneo]], that practice extreme earlobe elongation.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Rowthorn|first=Chris|title=Borneo|year=2008|publisher=Lonely Planet|isbn=9781740591058|pages=34|author=Cohen, Muhammad; Williams, China}}&lt;/ref&gt;

*'''[[Scalpelling]]''' &amp;mdash; Rather than expanding a healed fistula, this method involves extending the size of the piercing by using a [[scalpel]] to cut the edge of the fistula, expanding its [[diameter]]. It is often used in [[earlobe piercing]]s. This technique is also often used to alter the placement of a large piercing, combine two existing piercings into one larger one, or achieve a higher-gauge piercing when scar tissue is preventing stretching, or when tissue has thinned too much to make stretching too risky.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Ear Scalpelling|url=http://holier-than-thou.co.uk/modifications_scalpelling.htm|publisher=Holier Than Thou|accessdate=5 July 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=DeMello&gt;{{cite book|last=DeMello|first=Margo|title=Encyclopedia of Body Adornment|year=2007|publisher=ABC-CLIO|isbn=9780313336959|pages=234|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=s0122BsqrZwC}}&lt;/ref&gt;

*'''Scalpel and taper''' or '''pierce and taper''' &amp;mdash; After piercing or scalpelling, a large taper can be inserted directly after, allowing skin to instantly be stretched to large diameters; several inches can be achieved. This method is much rarer and can be extremely painful, causing formation of large amounts of scar tissue. Because of this, it is generally discouraged.&lt;ref name=Angel /&gt; The use of a dermal punch followed by tapering is also used in this procedure.

*'''Dermal Punch''' &amp;mdash; A circular razor of the desired diameter is pressed against the skin of the area (typically earlobe or cartilage). The blade is then pushed down upon and twisted by the piercer to &quot;punch&quot; out a small disk of skin. The razor is then pulled out of the skin and the jewelry (usually a non-flared or single-flared [[Pyrex]] Glass plug{{citation needed|date=July 2011}}) of the same size is inserted into the hole created by the razor. This is useful for achieving large-gauge cartilage piercings, and often discouraged for soft tissue that can easily be stretched.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last=Hudson|first=Karen L.|title=Body Art Glossary Definition - Dermal Punch|url=http://tattoo.about.com/cs/beginners/g/blglosdermalpun.htm|publisher=About.com|accessdate=15 July 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; It is also described as being less painful and less damaging to tissue than using a hypodermic needle of the same gauge.&lt;ref name=Angel /&gt; 

*'''Silicone Plugs''' &amp;mdash; These plugs are soft and malleable, allowing a relatively large plug to be inserted into the fistula.  Once folded and inserted into the ear, they expand, stretching the earlobe. However, stretching with silicone is often a dangerous decision. Its not recommended to use silicone plugs to stretch, due to the tacky, porous surface. The stretched fistula can adhere to the silicone if the lubricant used is pushed out by the pressure of the stretch, and an airtight seal can be created, trapping infection and causing it to spread internally. Also because silicone expands and contracts in temperature change, they can swell and potentially blow out a newly stretched fistula.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Frequently Asked Questions|url=http://www.kaossoftwear.com/index.php?main_page=faq&amp;faq_item=6|publisher=Kaos Softwear|accessdate=15 July 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== History and culture ==
Ear stretching has been practiced by people all over the world from ancient times. Bone, horn, wood, and stone were generally carved for ear stretching, but other organic materials that had the right shape naturally, from shells to teeth and claws, were also used.{{citation needed|date=August 2011}} 

===The Iceman===
Mummified bodies with stretched earlobes have been discovered, including the oldest mummified body discovered to date: [[Ötzi the Iceman]] (3300BC).&lt;ref name=Angel /&gt; This mummy had a stretch of somewhere between {{convert|7|–|11|mm|in|sp=us}} in diameter.

===Gautama Buddha===
[[Gautama Buddha]], an aristocratic and wealthy prince, had long stretched ears. He wore heavy gold earrings or [[precious stone]]s as a status symbol, and the weight stretched his ear lobes dramatically. When he finally renounced his wealth and discarded his jewelry, his ear lobes were permanently stretched.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Gray|first=Paul|title=The Rough Guide to Thailand's Beaches &amp; Islands|year=2002|publisher=Rough Guides|isbn=9781858288291|pages=442|author=Ridout, Lucy}}&lt;/ref&gt; As a way of remembering Buddha's act of personal self-sacrifice in walking away from his wealth, all succeeding images of Gautama Buddha show his stretched ear lobes sans jewelery.{{citation needed|date=July 2011}}

== Measuring systems ==

{| class=&quot;wikitable&quot;
|-
|14g  ||1.628mm ||.064in || -
|-
|12g  ||2.053mm ||.081in || -
|-
|10g  ||2.588mm ||.102in || -
|-
|8g   ||3.264mm ||.128in || -
|-
|6g   ||4.115mm ||.162in || -
|-
|4g   ||5.189mm ||.204in || -
|-
|2g   ||6.544mm ||.258in || -
|-
|0g   ||8.251mm ||.325in || -
|-
|00g  ||9.266mm ||.365in || -
|-
|000g |||11.11mm||.438in ||7/16&quot;
|-
|0000g||12.710mm||.5in   ||1/2&quot;
|-
| -   ||14.288mm||.563in ||9/16&quot;
|-
| -   ||15.875mm||.625in ||5/8&quot;
|-
| -   ||17.463mm||.688in ||11/16&quot;
|-
| -   ||19.06mm ||.75in  ||3/4&quot;
|-
| -   ||22.225mm||.875in ||7/8&quot;
|-
| -   ||23.813mm||.938in ||15/16&quot;
|-
| -   ||25.4mm  ||1in    ||1&quot;
|-
| -   ||26.988mm||1.063in||1 1/16&quot;
|-
| -   ||28.575mm||1.125in||1 1/8&quot;
|-
| -   ||31.75mm ||1.25in ||1 1/4&quot;
|-
| -   ||34.925mm||1.375in||1 3/8&quot;
|-
| -   ||38.1mm  ||1.5in  ||1 1/2&quot;
|-
| -   ||41.275mm||1.625in||1 5/8&quot;
|-
| -   ||44.45mm ||1.75in ||1 3/4&quot;
|-
| -   ||47.625mm||1.875in||1 7/8&quot;
|-
| -   ||50.8mm  ||2in    ||2&quot;
|}

==See also==
*[[Body modification]]
*[[Piercing]]
*[[American wire gauge]]

==References==
{{Reflist}}

==External links==
{{Commons category|Stretching (body piercing)}}
&lt;!--External links not complying with Wikipedia's non commercial guidelines will be removed.  Specifically, do not link to sites that sell supplies for body piercing.--&gt;
*[http://wiki.bmezine.com/index.php/Stretching BMEzine wiki article on stretching]
*[http://www.howtostretchyourears.com How to Stretch Your Ears]

{{body piercing}}
{{DEFAULTSORT:Stretching (Body Piercing)}}
[[Category:Body piercing]]

[[de:Dehnen von Piercings]]
[[it:Stretching (piercing)]]
[[simple:Stretching (body piercing)]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
