<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="16185563" ns="0" title="Zombie Nation (film)"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Infobox film
| name           = Zombie Nation
| image          = Ulli Lommel's Zombie Nation.jpg
| image size     = 200px
| caption        = US DVD released Cover
| director       = [[Ulli Lommel]]
| producer       = [[Ulli Lommel]]&lt;br/&gt;Nola Roeper
| writer         = [[Ulli Lommel]]
| narrator       =
| starring       = Brandon Dean&lt;br/&gt;Phil Lander&lt;br/&gt;Karen Maxwell&lt;br/&gt;Naidra Dawn Thomson&lt;br/&gt;Victoria Ullmann
| music          = Robert J. Walsh
| cinematography = Jürg V. Walther
| editing        = Christian Behm
| distributor    =
| released       = 5 October 2004
| runtime        = 81 minutes
| country        = [[United States]]
| language       = [[English language|English]]
| budget         =
| preceded by    =
| followed by    =
}}

'''''Zombie Nation''''' is a [[2004 in film|2004]] independent horror film directed by [[Ulli Lommel]].

== Plot outline ==
Police officer Joe Singer lives a secret night life in which he kidnaps women, and takes them bound to his warehouse loft, injects them with a mysterious liquid, and then murders them. During his day shift as a cop, Joe is angry and vitriolic on the job. He arrests a woman for jay walking and she ends up in the loft. A psychiatrist visits Joe and keeps repeating, &quot;Is it safe?&quot; A group of Voodoo priestesses perform a ritual that brings several of Joe's victims back to life as zombies. These girls attack and eat random people before they eventually find Joe.

== Reception ==
Reception of the film has been overwhelmingly negative. As of February 15, 2011, ''Zombie Nation'' is ranked #11 worst movie on [[IMDb]]'s Bottom 100&lt;ref&gt;http://www.imdb.com/chart/bottom&lt;/ref&gt;.

The following is an excerpt from IMDb's reviews page, an addition made by acclaimed film reviewer Timothy Morrissey:

&quot;I was not sure, at any stage, whether this film was made as a satirical portrayal of low-brow horror films, and the ridiculousness of this genre's position as a segue between proper dramatic film and naff obscenity, or whether it was the result of a group of cashed up wanna be directors/actors/cinematographers who, bursting with the ill gotten prestige of their celebrity parents, have put together a collection of their favourite storylines, scenes, and dramatic effects to create a monsterously absurd turd of a film, starring their friends and a group of pornographic actors.  I hope, for the love of God, that it is the former.&quot;

== References ==
{{Reflist}}

==External links==
*{{Imdb title|id=0463392|title=Zombie Nation}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Zombie Nation (Film)}}
[[Category:2004 films]]
[[Category:Zombie films]]
[[Category:2000s horror films]]
[[Category:Independent films]]
[[Category:American films]]
[[Category:English-language films]]
[[Category:Films directed by Ulli Lommel]]


{{2000s-horror-film-stub}}

[[de:Zombie Nation (Film)]]
[[es:Zombie Nation (película)]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
