<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="1618582" ns="0" title="University of Nebraska at Omaha"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Infobox University
|name            = University of Nebraska at Omaha
|image           =
|motto           = ''Connect-Collaborate-Create''
|established     = 1908
|type            = [[Public university|Public]] [[Space grant colleges|Space Grant]] [[University]]
|chancellor      = [[John Christensen (Academic administrator)|John Christensen]], [[PhD]]
|city            = [[Omaha, Nebraska|Omaha]]
|state           = [[Nebraska]]
|country         = [[United States]]
|campus          = [[Urban area|Urban]], {{convert|158|acre|ha}}
|students        = 14,093
|undergraduates  = 11,329
|postgraduates   = 2,764
|faculty         = 842
|students        = 14,903
|athletics = [[NCAA]] [[NCAA Division I|Division I]]
|affiliations    = [[The Summit League|Summit League]], [[Western Collegiate Hockey Association|WCHA]]  
|nickname        = [[Nebraska–Omaha Mavericks|Mavericks]]
|mascot          = Durango   
|colors          = [[Crimson]] and [[Black (color)|Black]] {{color box|	#C80000}}{{color box|#000000}}
|website         = [http://www.unomaha.edu/ www.unomaha.edu]
|logo            = [[Image:University of Nebraska at Omaha wordmark.svg|200px|University of Nebraska at Omaha]]

}}
{{coord|41|15|34.49|N|96|0|18.19|W|type:edu|display=title}} 
The '''University of Nebraska at Omaha''' ('''UNO''') is a four-year state university located in Omaha,&amp;nbsp;Nebraska, USA.  Founded in 1908 as Omaha&amp;nbsp;University, the institution became the public '''Municipal University of Omaha''' in 1931. It assumed its current name in 1968 following a merger into the University of Nebraska. The institution has a strong tradition of serving commuter students from within Omaha, but in recent years has developed student housing to better serve students from Nebraska, the United States, and the world for whom the commute is not convenient.  On October 8, 2008, the University of Nebraska at Omaha celebrated its 100th year of existence.&lt;ref&gt;(2008) [http://www.unomaha.edu/100/ University of Nebraska at Omaha Celebrates 100 Years.]&lt;/ref&gt;

==History==
===Omaha University===

The original Omaha University was founded in 1908 in the [[Kountze Place]] neighborhood of [[North Omaha]]. The first classes were located in the [[Redick Mansion]], once at North 24th and Pratt Streets, from 1909 through 1917. Established a few blocks north of the [[Presbyterian Theological Seminary]], most of the early faculty were recruited from Seminary teachers, as well as the faculty of [[Bellevue College]]. There were 26 students in the first year, most of whom graduated from [[Omaha Central High School|Omaha High School]]. Three of the University's first four presidents were ordained Presbyterian ministers.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.omahahistory.org/History%20at%20a%20Glance%209-2007.pdf &quot;History of Omaha at a glance&quot;], [[Douglas County Historical Society]]. Retrieved 4/10/08. p 65.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;(1993) [http://www.unoalumni.org/wfdata/frame2813-74/UNO_History_Chapter_1.pdf A History of UNO]. University of  Nebraska at Omaha. Retrieved 5/29/07.&lt;/ref&gt; Two other buildings on the original campus included Jacobs Hall, a gymnasium erected in 1910, and Joslyn Hall, a classroom building erected in 1917.

Jacobs Hall was a [[gym]]nasium facing North 24th Street that was built in 1910 with $14,000 received from the sale of land contributed by Lillian Maul. The land, the first donation to the University, was near the present West Dodge campus of the university. It was the first new building constructed on the university campus. Joslyn Hall was built with funds contributed by a well-known Omahan, [[George A. Joslyn]]. Donating $25,000 toward the building, Joslyn stipulated the school identify another $25,000 in a year. The building was located just north of [[Redick Hall]] and was finished in January 1917. Joslyn Hall had three stories and a basement with a total of thirty classrooms that accommodated 750 students. The building included chemistry and physics laboratories, an auditorium and music department.&lt;ref name=&quot;Old campus fades into oblivion&quot;&gt;[http://www.unoalumni.org/about_us/flashback/archive/206/ &quot;Old campus fades into oblivion&quot;], ''UNO Alumni Newsletter.'' August 1964. Retrieved 4/29/08.&lt;/ref&gt; Redick Hall was sold and moved in February 1917, to Minnesota where it became a resort.

In the early 1920s a proposed &quot;magnificent campus&quot; was slated for development between 21st and 25th Avenues, bounded by Kountze Park and the [[Carter Lake (Iowa-Nebraska)|Carter Lake Park]]. In 1927, businessmen formed the North Omaha Activities Association in order to redevelop [[Saratoga School]]'s playing field into a football field for the University's football team. With new bleachers built to accommodate a crowd of a thousand, the Saratoga Field was home to OU's football team until 1951.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.unoalumni.org/About_Us/Flashback/Archive/238/index.asp Saratoga Field] University of Nebraska at Omaha website.&lt;/ref&gt; The school also served as OU's science call from 1917 to 1926.&lt;ref name=&quot;unoalumni.org&quot;&gt;(1960) [http://www.unoalumni.org/about_us/flashback/archive/208/ &quot;West Dodge Campus Choice Gave Unique Building Design&quot;], ''The Gateway'' - UNO. Retrieved 3/26/08.&lt;/ref&gt;

Dr. [[Milo Bail]] became president of Omaha University in 1948 and served until 1965. During that time Omaha hotel magnate [[Eugene C. Eppley]]'s [[Eppley Foundation|foundation]] gave more than $1.2 million to the university. After Eppley's passing, the Eppley Foundation donated another $50,000 to recruit distinguished professors. The [[Eugene C. Eppley Administration Building|Eppley Administration Building]], designed by [[John Latenser, Sr.]],&lt;ref name=&quot;unoalumni.org&quot;/&gt; at the University of Nebraska at Omaha was named in recognition of the Foundation's giving.&lt;ref&gt;[http://media.www.unogateway.com/media/storage/paper968/news/2004/08/10/People/Theres.More.To.Uno.Buildings.Than.Just.A.Name-2548160.shtml &quot;There's more to UNO buildings that just a name&quot;], ''Gateway.'' July 10, 2004. Retrieved 2/3/08.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://media.www.unogateway.com/media/storage/paper968/news/2005/08/12/People/University.Buildings-2549234.shtml &quot;University buildings&quot;], ''UNO Gateway.'' Retrieved 2/4/08.&lt;/ref&gt; In 1952 the national [[Silver Wings]] student organization was founded at UO. In June 1964 Jacobs and Joslyn Halls were the last two original OU buildings at 24th &amp; Pratt Streets to be demolished.  In 1976 the [[Dr. C.C. and Mabel L. Criss Library]] replaced the Eppley Library.

The University moved from the [[North Omaha]] campus to its present main location at 60th and [[Dodge Street]] in 1938. The old campus buildings were used as apartments and offices, and were demolished to make way for a 12-story [[Omaha Housing Authority]] apartment building for the elderly, which was completed in 1965.&lt;ref name=&quot;Old campus fades into oblivion&quot;/&gt;

==Academics==
UNO is classified as a doctoral/research university in the latest [[Carnegie Classification of Institutions of Higher Education]].  UNO is the home of the [[Peter Kiewit Institute]] a $70 million state-of-the-art computer science facility and engineering facility, making it one of the premier computer science, management information systems (MIS) and bioinformatics programs in the region. PKI houses UNO's College of Information Science and Technology, [[University of Nebraska-Lincoln|UNL]]'s College of Engineering and Technology, and the [[Holland Computing Center]], which houses the [[Firefly (computer)| Firefly supercomputer]].&lt;ref&gt;Holland Computing Center. [http://hcc.unl.edu/main/index.php Holland Computing Center Website] Retrieved November 14, 2010.&lt;/ref&gt; The College of Information Science and Technology offers undergraduate/graduate degrees in Computer Science, Management Information Systems, Bioinformatics (graduate degree offered in collaboration with UNMC's Pathology's graduate program), Information Assurance, and Information Technology Innovation. 

The College of Business Administration's [[Masters in Business Administration]] students ranked in the top 5% nationally, while the undergraduate students ranked in the top 15% on a most recent standardized exam on business topics conducted by the [[Educational Testing Service]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.unomaha.edu/news/releases/2007/05/11_cba.php Press Release.] University of Nebraska at Omaha.&lt;/ref&gt;

UNO maintains a widely regarded online film journal called the ''[[Journal of Religion and Film]]''.

==Modern Campus==
[[Image:KanekoStudySpace.jpg|thumb|left|Kaneko-UNO Library Study space]]
Currently the University of Nebraska Omaha has two campuses: North Campus (Dodge Street) and South Campus (Pacific Street) which are separated by Elmwood Park, both in Midtown Omaha.  UNO also operates the [http://library.unomaha.edu/kaneko/ Kaneko-UNO Library], located at 12th and Jones streets in downtown Omaha.  The Kaneko-UNO focuses on stimulating creativity and offers research scientists, business leaders, teachers, visual artists, and students access to resources and materials they might not find in their day-to-day environment. 

===North Campus===
The North Campus is the largest and primary campus for the University of Nebraska at Omaha.  
The following colleges and their associated facilities are located on the North Campus:

[[File:University of Nebraska-Omaha campus-2.JPG|thumb|University of Nebraska-Omaha North campus]]

{| style='border:1px solid #dddddd; background-color:#fefefe; padding:3px; margin:0px'
|
* College of Arts and Sciences
* College of Communication, Fine Arts, and Media
* College of Education
* College of Public Affairs and Community Service
* Graduate Studies
* International Studies
* Service-Learning Academy
|}

Additionally, the North Campus is also the home to the [[Dr. C.C. and Mabel L. Criss Library]], the Strauss Performing Arts Center, the UNO Art Gallery, and the Black Box Theater, a state-of-the-art facility utilizing mobile seating units to allow for a customizable and trans-formative space.

University Village and Maverick Village student housing complexes, each composed of multiple variably sized buildings, are spread across the western edge of the North Campus (Additional housing is also present on South Campus).  

The HPER (Health, Physical Education, and Recreation) building is a recently renovated complex that houses the Athletic Department for the Division I [[Nebraska-Omaha Mavericks]] as well as student fitness areas.  Attached is the Sapp Field House and [[Al F. Caniglia Field]].  The Pep Bowl is located near Caniglia Field.

===South Campus===
The South Campus houses the primary facilities for the College of Business Administration and the College of Information Science and Technology, which includes the [[Peter Kiewit Institute]] and the [[Firefly (computer)| Firefly supercomputer]].  The Scott Technology Center incubator, which aims to assist start-up enterprises that offer products which are cutting-edge, high risk, and are of high quality scientific, technology or engineering nature, is also located on the South Campus.  The Scott Data Center and Scott Conference Center are other features of South Campus.  

Additional on-campus housing is provided on the South Campus via Scott Hall, and the multiple units which comprise Scott Village and Scott Court.  UNO plans to expand the South Campus via [[Aksarben Village]].  UNO has also recently purchased property south of Center Street, with possible intentions of developing further on-campus housing and for on-campus athletic facilities.

==Athletics==
&lt;!-- Deleted image removed: [[File:Newunomav.jpg|thumb|right|Athletics logo]] --&gt;
{{main|Nebraska–Omaha Mavericks}}
Nebraska-Omaha's sports teams have been nicknamed the Mavericks since 1971.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.unoalumni.org/about_us/flashback/archive/131/ UNO Alumni.org - excerpt from Summer 1971 yearbook, ''Tomahawk'']&lt;/ref&gt; The university currently operates 14 intercollegiate athletic programs which are currently in transition to NCAA Division I status and set to join [[The Summit League]].  In the process UNO has abandoned its football and wrestling programs.  Wrestling had been the school's most successful sport with [[NCAA Wrestling Team Championship|national championships]] in 1991, 2004, 2005, 2006, 2009, 2010 and 2011.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.americanchronicle.com/articles/yb/156765564&lt;/ref&gt;  The [[Nebraska–Omaha Mavericks men's ice hockey]] team competes in the Division I [[Western Collegiate Hockey Association]], joining the league in 2010-11, and is the only Division I hockey program in the state.  UNO has also added a men's soccer program in 2011, and is only the second division I men's soccer program in the state (the other being [[Creighton Bluejays|Creighton]]). 

Men's sports at UNO include tennis, baseball, basketball, soccer, golf and hockey. Women's sports include basketball, cross country, golf, soccer, softball, swimming and diving, tennis, track and volleyball.

==Fraternities/Sororities==

Fraternitites: 
*[[Pi Kappa Alpha]]
*[[Lambda Chi Alpha]]
*[[Sigma Phi Epsilon]]
*[[Theta Chi]]

Sororities:
*[[Chi Omega]]
*[[Alpha Xi Delta]]
*[[Sigma Kappa]]
*[[Zeta Tau Alpha]]

==Media==
[[KVNO| KVNO 90.7]] FM is produced and broadcast from UNO's North Campus.  The station's format is primarily classical music, although approximately 10% of its broadcast time is devoted to athletic and campus events.  

[http://unomavradio.com/pages/about.php MavRadio] (HD FM 90.7-2 and [http://unomavradio.com/pages/about.php online]) is a student produced college/indie station also produced and broadcast from UNO's North Campus. 

[http://www.unogateway.com The Gateway] is UNO's student newspaper which is published bi-weekly during the spring and fall academic semesters.   

==Administration==
As of 2010, the Chancellor of UNO is John Christensen, Ph.D., and the deans are:
* '''College of Arts and Sciences - J. David Boocker, Ph.D.'''
* '''College of Business Administration - Louis G. Pol, Ph.D.'''
* '''College of Communication, Fine Arts and Media - Gail F. Baker, Ph.D.'''''
* ''Associate Dean - Mike Hilt, Ph.D.''
* '''College of Education - Nancy A. Edick, Ed. D.'''
* '''College of Information Science and Technology - Hesham H. Ali, Ph.D.'''
* '''College of Public Affairs and Community Service - Burton J. Reed, Ph.D.'''
* '''Criss Library - Audrey DeFrank, M.L.S. [Acting Dean]'''
* '''Graduate Studies - Deborah S. Smith-Howell, Ph.D.'''
* '''International Studies and Programs - Thomas E. Gouttierre, M.A.'''
'''

==Fight song==&lt;!-- This section is linked from [[UNO Mavericks]] --&gt;

'''UNO Fight'''
 We will fight, fight, fight for our Mavericks,
 We will fight, fight, fight for our team.
 Everyone knows when that old whistle blows,
 We will shout, we will yell, we will scream.
 GO MAVS!
 We will fight, fight, fight for our Mavericks,
 we will cheer so all fans will know.
 Be it win or lose or draw,
 Everyone for Omaha,
 We will fight for U-N-O.

Composer, Dr. James Saker

==Notable alumni==
*[[Charles J. Adams]], United States Air Force Brigadier General
*[[Marlin Briscoe]], first black starting quarterback in modern [[Professional Football]] (the [[American Football League]]), attended and played for UNO from 1964-1967.
*[[Harold Dow]], CBS News correspondent and investigative reporter
*[[Dan Ellis]], NHL goalie
*[[Dick Fletcher]], Emmy Award-winning television meteorologist
*[[Peter Fonda]], actor, attended Omaha University, but did not complete his degree.
*[[Chuck Hagel]], [[U.S. Senator]]
*[[Jason Brilz]], mixed-martial artist who fights for the [[Ultimate Fighting Championship]].
*[[Jeff Koterba]], Editorial Cartoonist, [[Omaha World Herald]]
*[[James J. Lindsay]], United States Army General
*[[Zach Miller (American football b. 1984)|Zach Miller]], American football player for the [[Jacksonville Jaguars]].
*[[Conor Oberst]] of [[Bright Eyes (band)|Bright Eyes]] attended UNO, but did not complete his degree.
*[[Gene Okerlund]], Wrestling Announcer for notable companies like the [[AWA]], [[World Championship Wrestling|WCW]] and now [[World Wrestling Entertainment|WWE]]
*[[Penny Sackett]], Astronomer and [[Office of the Chief Scientist (Australia)|Chief Scientist of Australia]]
*[[Gerald Theunissen]], banker in [[Jennings, Louisiana|Jennings]], [[Louisiana]], who served from 1992-2008 in both houses of the [[Louisiana State Legislature]]
*[[Leslie J. Westberg]], United States Air Force Brigadier General
*[[James R. Young (UP)|James R. Young]], Chairman and President of Union Pacific Railroad.

==See also==
*[[Education in North Omaha, Nebraska]]
*[[Nebraska Review]]
*[[Dr. C.C. and Mabel L. Criss Library]]

==References==
{{reflist}}

==External links==
*[http://www.unomaha.edu/ University of Nebraska Omaha website]
*[http://gomavs.unomaha.edu/ UNO Mavericks - Athletic Department]

{{Colleges and universities in Nebraska}}
{{University of Nebraska}}
{{The Summit League}}
{{Western Collegiate Hockey Association}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:University Of Nebraska Omaha}}
[[Category:University of Nebraska at Omaha| ]]
[[Category:Universities and colleges in Nebraska|Nebraska Omaha, University of]]
[[Category:North Central Association of Colleges and Schools|Nebraska Omaha, University of]]
[[Category:American Association of State Colleges and Universities]]
[[Category:Educational institutions established in 1908|Nebraska Omaha, University of]]
[[Category:Education in Omaha, Nebraska]]
[[Category:Buildings and structures in Omaha, Nebraska]]
[[Category:Coalition of Urban and Metropolitan Universities]]

[[de:University of Nebraska at Omaha]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
