<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="16218924" ns="0" title="Tylluan Wen"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">&lt;!-- Deleted image removed: [[Image:Y-dylluan-wen-clawr.jpg|thumb|''Y Dylluan Wen'' Novel {{puic|Y-dylluan-wen-clawr.jpg|log=2009 October 3}}]] --&gt;
'''''Tylluan Wen''''' is a [[Welsh language]] [[film]] / [[television]]  drama produced in [[Wales]] in 1997 by Ffilmiau'r Nant and dircted by [[Alun Ffred Jones]].&lt;ref&gt;http://library.digiguide.tv/lib/programme/Tylluan+Wen-46180/Film/&lt;/ref&gt; It is set in [[Llan Ffestiniog]], [[Gwynedd]], as an adaptation of Angharad Jones' novel ''Y Dylluan Wen'' (''The White Owl''). The film is studied as part of the Welsh literature [[GCSE]] course.

The village scenes were filmed in [[Talysarn]], and scenes are set in [[Holyhead]], [[Blaenau Ffestiniog]], and on the [[Conwy Valley Railway]]. The &quot;Castell [[Blodeuwedd]]&quot; Scene was filmed at [[Tomen y Mur]] Roman Fort, Trawsfynydd, near to the coastal town of [[Porthmadog]]. 

The film was broadcast on the Welsh-language television channel [[S4C]].

== Characters and actors ==

{| class=&quot;wikitable&quot;
|-
! Character
! Actor
|-
| Martha/Eirlys
| [[Sian James]]
|-
| Ifor Preis
| [[John Ogwen]]
|-
| Meri Preis
| Betsan Llwyd
|-
| Roger
| Maldwyn John
|}

== Story line ==

Martha arrives at Blaenau, after travelling from Ireland, and leaving her baby behind. She comes seeking vengeance over her father's death. Ifor Price, she thinks, is responsible for her father's death, and she wants so get revenge on him. She tricks him in to having an affair with her. Her identity is kept hidden until the very end, where her real name is Eirlys, but she gives the false name of Martha. The old school cook, and Roger Price, discover her true identity, but it is too late. She ends up killing Ifor, and in doing so his daughter Gwen, runs to the road, and Martha herself is killed saving Gwen.

== Differences in the film and the novel ==

Some details are changed in the film and in the novel. Changes like not filming in the school, and Martha not coming from America are down to budget costs.  Also, The names are changes in the film, Myfi becomes Martha, Ifor Gruffyd becomes Ifor Price. Also, Meri and Ifor have a baby in the film, as there is no play in the film, she has no reason to be in the school, and babysitting seems a good excuse for Martha to spend time around the family. Another thing that has changed is in the novel, Ifor pursued Martha, whereas in the film, Martha seems to be forcing him to go along with the affair.

Another thing is that Martha herself dies in the film, and in the novel she escapes after the murder. The way in which she murders is also different, the film - throwing a harp at Ifor's head, the novel - whipping him to death, obviously this film had to be made suitable for people the ages of 14 and above, as it is on the curriculum for Welsh GCSE students.

The obvious choice of Martha being a singer and not an actress was because of the actress used, Sian James, she is a renowned Welsh singer, therefore the part fits, and fits in with the rest of the changes in the story.

== Symbolism ==

A lot of symbolism is used in this film. We see in the flashbacks of Eirlys being caned, the headmaster wears a cape, and Martha arrives wearing a cape, showing that she is now in control. Later there is a shot of Ifor Price wearing his cape in private, showing how he wants to regain control. In parts where Martha wants to be particularly menacing she wears red.

Throughout the film, close up shot are taken of a sound reel running out, this shows that some purpose of Martha has been achieved. Also, we see that there is a lot of repetitive music in the film, this shows something from the past is repeating itself and its building up tension to some climax at the end.

==References==
&lt;references/&gt;

[[Category:Welsh films]]
[[Category:Welsh-language films]]
[[Category:Television in Wales]]

[[cy:Tylluan Wen (ffilm)]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
