<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="16232619" ns="0" title="Roman Catholic Archdiocese of Cagayan de Oro"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Infobox diocese
| jurisdiction      = Archdiocese&lt;!-- Type of jurisdiction: i.e. Diocese or Archdiocese --&gt;
| name              = Cagayan de Oro
| latin             = Archidioecesis Cagayanus
| local             = Arkdiyosesis sa Cagayan de Oro
| image             = Arch Cagayande oro seal.png
| image_size        = 150px 
| image_alt         = 
| caption           = Seal of the Archdiocese of Cagayan de Oro
&lt;!---- Locations ----&gt;
| country           = [[Philippines]]
| metropolitan      = 
| territory         = 
| province          = [[Metro Cagayan de Oro]]
| coordinates       = &lt;!-- Use {{coord}} --&gt; 
&lt;!---- Statistics ----&gt;
| area_km2          = &lt;!-- Area in square kilometers, automatically converted --&gt; 
| population        = 1,397,000
| population_as_of  = 2006
| catholics         = &lt;!-- Number of Catholics in the diocese --&gt;
| catholics_percent = 
| parishes          = &lt;!-- Number of parishes in the diocese --&gt;
| churches          = &lt;!-- Number of churches in the diocese --&gt;
| congregations     = &lt;!-- Number of congregations in the diocese --&gt;
| schools           = &lt;!-- Number of church supported schools in the diocese --&gt;
| members           = &lt;!-- Number of members in the diocese --&gt;
&lt;!---- Information ----&gt;
| denomination      = [[Roman Catholic]]
| rite              = [[Roman Rite]] or [[Latin Rite]]
| established       = June 29, 1951
| cathedral         = St. Augustine Metropolitan Cathedral
| cocathedral       = 
| patron            = [[Augustine of Hippo|St. Augustine of Hippo]]
| priests           = &lt;!-- Number of priests in the diocese --&gt;
&lt;!---- Current leadership ----&gt;
| pope              = [[Benedict XVI]] 
| metro_archbishop  = [[Antonio Ledesma|Most Rev. Antonio J. Ledesma, S.J., D.D.]]
| coadjutor         = [[Jesus Tuquib|Most Rev. Jesus B. Tuquib, D.D., S.T.D.]]
| auxiliary_bishops = 
| vicar_general     = 
| emeritus_bishops  = [[Jesus Tuquib|Most Rev. Jesus B. Tuquib, D.D., S.T.D.]]
&lt;!---- Map ----&gt;
| map               = 
| map_alt           = 
| map_caption       = 
&lt;!---- Website ----&gt;
| website           = [http://www.cbcponline.net/cagayan_de_oro/ Official website]
| footnotes         = 
}}

'''Archdiocese of Cagayan de Oro''' ([[Latin]]: ''Archidioecesis Cagayanus'') is an [[Archdiocese]] of the [[Roman Catholic Church]] in the [[Philippines]]. It is a metropolitan see in the island of [[Mindanao]] which comprises three civil Provinces of [[Misamis Oriental]], [[Bukidnon]] and [[Camiguin]]. Today, it is headed by [[Archbishop]] [[Antonio Ledesma|Antonio J. Ledesma, S.J]] and its seat is located at Saint Augustine Metropolitan Cathedral&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.cbcponline.net/cagayan_de_oro/html/parishes.html|title=Parishes and Parochial Clergy|publisher=Catholic Bishops Conference of the Philippines}}&lt;/ref&gt; in [[Cagayan de Oro City]].

== History ==

[[Image:San Agustin Cathderal, CDO.jpg|thumb|210px|left|Saint Augustine Cathedral, Seat of the Archdiocese of Cagayan de Oro.]]

During the Spanish era there was only the Province of Misamis which included the present Provinces of [[Misamis Oriental]] and [[Misamis Occidental]], and was handled by the civil government from [[Cebu]]. The [[Order of Augustinian Recollects|Recollect]] Missionaries came down from [[Cebu]] and started a mission in the province. Civil government of its own started only in 1901. And because one part of it was separated from the main by Iligan Bay, the government decided to divide the province into two. [[Misamis Oriental]] is the bigger portion. Today the Diocesan Cathedral is one of the 12 Cathedrals that was founded by the [[Order of Augustinian Recollects]] in the [[Philippines]].

Before 1865, the whole of [[Mindanao]] island and [[Sulu Province|Sulu]] were part of the Diocese of Cebu. In 1865 the western half of [[Mindanao]] came under the jurisdiction of the Diocese of Jaro in Panay. Then [[Pope Leo XIII]] established the [[Diocese of Zamboanga]], separating it from Jaro and making it the first diocese in [[Mindanao]]. But it was [[Pope Pius X]] who executed this in 1910. Thus from 1910 [[Cagayan de Oro City]] became part of the Diocese of Zamboanga.

On January 20, 1933, [[Pope Pius XI]] created a second diocese in [[Mindanao]], that of [[Cagayan de Oro City]], separating it from [[Zamboanga City]] and giving it jurisdiction over the then Provinces of [[Surigao]], [[Misamis Oriental]], [[Misamis Occidental]], [[Bukidnon]] and part of the Province of Lanao. Together with Zamboanga it became a suffragan of the new Ecclesiastical Province of [[Cebu]].

In 1939, the Diocese of Cagayan de Oro was divided again with the creation of the Diocese of Surigao comprising the Provinces of Surigao and Agusan; and in 1951 was divided again with the creation of the Diocese of Ozamiz comprising the Provinces of Lanao and [[Misamis Occidental]].

On June 29, 1951, Pope Pius XI elevated [[Cagayan de Oro City]] to an archdiocese, coinciding with that of Jaro. The Archdiocese of Cagayan de Oro became the first archdiocese in [[Mindanao]], thereby separating [[Mindanao]] from the Ecclesiastical Province of [[Cebu]]. It had as its suffragans all the dioceses and prelatures then in [[Mindanao]] island: Surigao, Cotabato, Sulu, Davao, Ozamiz, and Zamboanga which had been its mother diocese. It became an archdiocese seven years ahead of its mother diocese.

Later, the Apostolic Prefecture of Sulu, the Prelature Nullius of Marbel, the Prelature Nullius of Tagum, the Diocese of Butuan, the Prelature Nullius of Malaybalay, the Prelature Nullius of Iligan and the Diocese of Tandag became suffragans of the Archdiocese of Cagayan de Oro.

Eventually four other archdioceses were established in [[Mindanao]] island: Zamboanga in 1958, Davao in 1970, Cotabato in 1979 and Ozamiz in 1983. Thus there are at present five ecclesiastical provinces in [[Mindanao]].

The first bishop and archbishop of Cagayan de Oro was the [[James Hayes (archbishop)|Most Reverend James Hayes, S.J., D.D.]], who established the Ateneo de Cagayan (now known as [[Xavier University – Ateneo de Cagayan]]) and among others. He was succeeded by Most Reverend Patrick Cronin, SSC, D.D. in 1971. Bishop Cronin established the St. John Vianney Theological Seminary. The third bishop was [[Jesus Tuquib|Most Reverend Jesus B. Tuquib, D.D., S.T.D.]], who was installed as Archbishop with right of Succession on May 31, 1984, and became the [[Archbishop]] of the Archdiocese of Cagayan de Oro on January 5, 1988. Today, the current Archbishop is the [[Antonio Ledesma|Most Reverend Antonio J. Ledesma, S.J., D.D.]], who was installed on March 4, 2006.

There are 46 diocesan priests manning the 46 parishes within the jurisdiction of the archdiocese, helped by 2 Jesuit and 5 Columban priests. Six others are doing non-parochial work and 3 others are in retirement. The rest of the Jesuits are in [[Xavier University – Ateneo de Cagayan]] or in the [[major]] seminary, and the rest of the Columbans, apart from the 5 involved in parish work, are in their procure house doing various apostolates such as hospital work and other activities. There are 18 religious institutes of women, one of which is a contemplative institute, the Carmelite nuns.

The archdiocese has its own diocesan college seminary, the San Jose de Mindanao Seminary that opened in 1955. It was constructed by Archbishop Hayes, was first administered by the Jesuits, then by Columban priests, and now by the diocesan clergy.

Also, within the archdiocese is a theology seminary - the [[St. John Vianney]] Theological Seminary, which is mainly for seminarians of the Ecclesiastical [[Metro Cagayan de Oro]]. This was started by Archbishop Cronin and finished by Archbishop Tuquib. It opened in 1985.

== Suffragan dioceses ==

* [[Roman Catholic Diocese of Butuan|Diocese of Butuan]]
* [[Roman Catholic Diocese of Malaybalay|Diocese of Malaybalay]]
* [[Roman Catholic Diocese of Surigao|Diocese of Surigao]]
* [[Roman Catholic Diocese of Tandag|Diocese of Tandag]]

== Ordinaries ==

{| class=&quot;wikitable&quot; 
|-
! colspan=2 |Archbishop!! Period in Office
|-
||1. ||[[James Hayes (archbishop)|James Hayes, S.J., D.D.]] || 1933-1970
|-
||2. ||[[Patrick Cronin (archbishop)|Patrick Cronin, S.S.C., D.D.]]|| 1971-1988
|-
||3.||[[Jesus Tuquib|Jesus Tuquib D.D., S.T.D.]]|| 1988-2006
|-
||4.&lt;!-- Deleted image removed:  [[Image:AntonioLedesma.jpg|99px| {{puic|AntonioLedesma.jpg|2010 February 28}}]] --&gt;||[[Antonio Ledesma|Antonio Ledesma S.J., D.D.]]|| 2006-present
|}

== Vision and mission ==

=== Vision ===

{{cquote|''A renewed community of believers fully knowing, loving and serving Christ, proclaiming the good news and actively participating in the building of a society of justice, peace and love.''&lt;ref name=&quot;cbcp&quot;/&gt;}}

=== Mission ===

{{cquote|''We, the servant-leaders of the Archdiocese of Cagayan de Oro, in collaboration with and in participation of the fullness of the Bishop's priesthood, and making our own the call of the Plenary Council of the Philippines II for renewal and transformation, commit ourselves:'' 
# ''to live a life that is rooted in Christ;'' 
# ''to live the life of evangelical poverty, celibacy and apostolic obedience;'' 
# ''to serve as pastoral leaders with the compassion and humility of the Good Shepherd;'' 
# ''to celebrate the Eucharist as authentic presiders and to proclaim the Word credibly;'' 
# ''to live as brothers respecting each one's freedom and fostering a sense of belonging;'' 
# ''to be in the midst of our people to know their plights, anguishes, hopes and aspirations;'' 
# ''to be imbued with deep love of preference for the poor, defending and vindicating their rights;'' 
# ''to nurture a filial devotion of Mary, the Mother of Jesus and our Mother.''&lt;ref name=&quot;cbcp&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.cbcponline.net/cagayan_de_oro/|title=The Archdiocese of Cagayan de Oro on CBCP.net|publisher=Catholic Bishops Conference of the Philippines|accessdate=2008-10-21}}&lt;/ref&gt;}}

== Parishes and chaplaincies ==

The Archdiocese of Cagayan de Oro is at present made up of 45 parishes and 8 chaplaincies, i.e., communities on the way of becoming full-pledged parishes (40 parishes and 8 chaplaincies in [[Misamis Oriental]] and [[Bukidnon]] and 5 parishes in Camiguin). Definitely more parishes will have to be opened in the future especially in the city because of the expanding population of the city due to its rapid economic growth and development attracting many people from all over the country.

The Chinese Catholics especially in the city proper also have their own personal parish, the San Lorenzo Ruiz Catholic Community.

== Priests in the Archdiocese: Diocesan and religious ==

There are now 88 diocesan priests incardinated to the archdiocese. By the end of the celebration of the Golden Jubilee there may be 6 or 7 more. Most of them are in the parishes but there are also others without a parish maybe because they are either in the seminary or are having diocesan or apostolate tasks. Some are outside the archdiocese either on study-leave, on mission, working in other dioceses, or just on leaves from the ministry, while some are now in retirement.

Most of the diocesan priests have become members of a society of diocesan priests founded by Archbishop [[Teofilo Bastida Camomot]]: the Society of St. John Vianney or SSJV. All the founding fathers, except Fr. Wang, are now dead.

Some religious priests who are now taking care of 3 parishes help the priests in the parishes. 

At present there are 9 male religious congregations in the Archdiocese
*[[Congregation of the Blessed Sacrament]] (SSS)
*[[Stigmatines|Congregation of the Sacred Stigmata of Our Lord Jesus Christ]] (CSS)
*[[Franciscan Friars of the Immaculate]] (FFI)
*[[Missionary Society of St. Columban]] (SSC)
*Mission Society of the Philippines (MSP)
*Poor Servants of Divine Providence (PSDP)
*[[Priests of the Sacred Heart|Priests of the Sacred Heart of Jesus]] (SCJ)
*[[Society of Jesus]] (SJ)
*[[Society of Saint Paul]] (SSP)

== Institute of Consecrates Life For Women ==

There are at present in the archdiocese, 1 institute of contemplative life (Carmelite nuns), 17 religious institute of active life:
*[[Angelic Sisters of St. Paul]] (ASSP)
*Augustinian Sisters of Our Lady (OSA)
*[[Canossians|Canossian Daughters of Charity]] (FDCC)
*[[Carmelites|Carmelite Missionaries]] (CM)
*Order of the Company of Mary Our Lady (ODN)
*[[Daughters of St. Paul]] (FSP)
*[[Franciscan Missionaries of Mary]] (FMM)
*[[Congregation of the Hijas de Jesús|Hijas de Jesus]] (FI)
*Missionary Congregation of Mary (MCM)
*[[Discalced Carmelites|Order of the Discalced Carmelite]] (OCD)
*Our Lady’s Missionaries (OLM)
*[[Religious of the Assumption]] (RA)
*Religious of the Good Shepherd (RGS)
*[[Religious Sisters of Mercy]] (RSM)
*[[Religious of the Virgin Mary]] (RVM)
*[[Siervas de Nuestra Señora dela Paz]] (SNSP)
*[[Sisters of Charity of St. Paul|Sisters of St. Paul de Chartres]] (SPC)
*Ursuline Missionaries of the Sacred Heart (UMSH)

==Pious Associations==
These are the groups of women on the way of becoming religious institutes of diocesan right 
*Missionary Sisters of the Holy Family (MSHF)
*Theresian Missionary of Mary TMM)
*Sisters of Social Apostolate (SSA)

The MSHF and the TMM are outgrowths of the original group founded by Archbishop Camomot and brought by him to [[Cagayan de Oro City]]: the Daughters of St. Teresa or DST, which group is now based in [[Cebu]].)  The Franciscan Missionaries of Mary or FMM used to have a house here.  And there is 1 lay association, the Teresiana.

The religious sisters are in various fields of apostolate (like running or administering schools, campus ministry, parish work, catechetics, family life, hospital work, running orphanages, taking care of young ladies, and others).

== Seminaries ==

There are two seminaries in the Archdiocese: a college seminary and a theology seminary.

The college seminary, named, '''San Jose de Mindanao Seminary''', is mainly for the seminarians of the Archdiocese, although it continues to receive seminarians from other ecclesiastical jurisdictions. It has a pre-college year and four years of college.  The seminarians used to study within the seminary but due to lack of personnel and other reasons, they now take their courses in [[Xavier University – Ateneo de Cagayan]], which is owned and run by the Jesuit Fathers.  This college seminary was founded by Archbishop Hayes and opened in 1956.

'''St. John Vianney Theological Seminary''' caters mainly to the seminarians of the Ecclesiastical [[Metro Cagayan de Oro]], although it also accepts seminarians from other ecclesiastical jurisdictions.  It has a Spiritual Pastoral Formation Year and four years of Theology. In consortium with [[Xavier University – Ateneo de Cagayan]], it now offers a Masters Degree in Pastoral Theology.  It is run mainly by the Jesuit Fathers though there are now many diocesan priests teaching in the seminary.  The construction of the seminary was begun by Archbishop Cronin and finished by Archbishop Tuquib.

The Archdiocese has been blessed with so many vocations that our seminaries even have to refuse entry to many applicants due to lack of space.

While older priests are products of either the UST Central Seminary (Manila), San Jose Seminary (Manila), [[San Carlos Seminary]] (Makati), or REMASE (Davao), most of the younger clergy are products St. John Vianney Theological Seminary.

== Lay religious organizations, movements, and covenant communities ==
While the archdiocese has many and varied traditional lay organizations, like the [[Knights of Columbus]], [[Catholic Women's League]], [[Legion of Mary]], [[Apostleship of Prayer]], [[Cursillo|Cursillos de Cristiandad]], and many others, it has also experienced here the blossoming of many lay groups and what they call now the covenant communities.  Thus, they have, for example, the [[Christian Family Movement]], the [[Charismatic Movement]] (in all its many expressions and forms), the [[Neocatechumenal Way]], the many so-called covenant communities, like the [[Couples for Christ]] and its many outreaches to widows and children, the Kahayag sa Dios (also with its many outreaches), and many others.  This emergence started after Vatican II.

== University, colleges and schools ==

To respond to the need for Catholic education, there is one university ([[Xavier University – Ateneo de Cagayan]], run by the Jesuits), and 6 colleges (Lourdes, St. Rita’s, [[Christ the King College, Gingoog City|Christ the King]], and [[St. Mary's Academy of Carmen|St. Mary’s]], run by the RVM Sisters; and Fatima College in [[Mambajao]], run by the [[Religious Sisters of Mercy]]). Most of the Catholic educational institutions were either founded by Archbishop Hayes himself or founded during his time.

There are 18 catholic high schools, most of which are run by Sisters. A group of Sisters, the [[Congregation of the Hijas de Jesús|Hijas de Jesus]], administers the only Chinese Catholic school in Cagayan de Oro, the Kong Hua School.

== Retreat centers ==

There are now 5 retreat centers or houses where people can go for recollections, days of prayer or solitude, or retreats.  The latest of these is the Cardinal Hoffner’s House of Prayer owned by the Archdiocese.

== Hospitals and Rehabilitation centers ==

For the physical, psychological, psychiatric or emotionally sickpeople, the archdiocese has: 1 hospital (Maria Reyna Xavier University Hospital, founded by Archbishop Hayes and owned by apartnership between the archdiocese, the [[Sisters of Charity of St. Paul|Sisters of St. Paul de Chartres]], and [[Xavier University – Ateneo de Cagayan]] (owned by the Jesuits))&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.xu.edu.ph/index.php/component/content/article/1-latest-news/465-xmruh-launches-new-er-or-complex|title= XMRUH launches new ER-OR complex|publisher=XU Website|accessdate=2011-01-15}}&lt;/ref&gt;; and 4 rehabilitation centers, the more known of which is the House of Hope of the Archdiocese for the mentally sick.

== See also ==
* [[Roman Catholicism in the Philippines]]
* [[Cagayan de Oro City]]

== References ==

{{reflist}}

== External links ==

* [http://www.cbcponline.net/cagayan_de_oro/ Archdiocese of Cagayan de Oro-CBCP]
* [http://www.catholic-hierarchy.org/diocese/dcado.html Archdiocese of Cagayan de Oro-Catholic Hierarchy]
* [http://www.cbcponline.net Catholic Bishops Conference of the Philippines]

{{Roman Catholic dioceses in the Philippines}}
{{coord missing|Philippines}}

[[Category:Religious organizations established in 1933]]
[[Category:Roman Catholic dioceses in the Philippines|Cagayan de Oro]]
[[Category:Roman Catholic dioceses and prelatures established in the 20th century]]

[[ceb:Arkidyosesis sa Cagayán de Oro]]
[[de:Erzbistum Cagayan de Oro]]
[[it:Arcidiocesi di Cagayan de Oro]]
[[ru:Архиепархия Кагаян-де-Оро]]
[[tl:Arkidiyosesis ng Cagayan de Oro]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
