<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="1625111" ns="0" title="Women as imams"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Refimprove|date=December 2010}}
{{original research|date=December 2008}}

{{Islam}}There is a current controversy among [[Muslim]]s regarding the circumstances in which women may act as [[imam]]s—that is, lead a congregation in ''[[salah]]'' (prayer). (Note that there are many types of [[Islamic religious leaders]] aside from imams, and [[women and Islam|Muslim women]] have [[Women_as_theological_figures#Islam|featured as theological figures]] throughout the [[history of Islam]].) Some [[Islamic schools and branches|schools of Islamic thought]] make exceptions for ''[[tarawih]]'' (optional [[Ramadan]] prayers) or for a congregation consisting only of close relatives. 

Historically, certain sects considered it acceptable for a woman to be imam. This was true not just in the Arab heartland of early Islam, but also in China hundreds of years ago. The debate has been reactivated recently, arguing that the spirit of the [[Koran]] and the letter of a disputed [[hadith]] indicate that women should be able to lead mixed congregations as well as single-sex ones, and that the prohibition of this developed as a result of sexism in the medieval environment and patriarchal interpretations of religious texts, not part of or reflective of true Islam.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.beliefnet.com/Faiths/Islam/2006/03/Score-One-More-For-Women-Imams.aspx/ &quot;Score One More for Women Imams&quot;], &quot;beliefnet&quot; by Pamela K. Taylor, 2006-02-28. Retrieved on 2008-12-13.]&lt;/ref&gt;

==Precedents==
The [[Quran]] does not address this issue; relevant precedents are therefore sought for in the ''[[hadith]]'', the traditions attributed to [[Muhammad]]; the ''[[sunnah]]'', his actions, including but not limited to hadith; and the principle of ''[[ijma]]'', consensus.

The only ''hadith'' that unequivocally states that women may not lead mixed congregations is [[Ibn Majah]] (''Kitab iqamat is-salat was-sunnati fiha'') #1134, narrated through [[Jabir ibn Abdullah]]: &quot;A woman may not lead a man in Prayer, nor may a [[Bedouin]] lead a believer of the [[Muhajirun]] or a corrupt person lead a committed [[Muslim]] in Prayer.&quot;

An indirectly relevant ''hadith'' is widely considered to be crucial, since the imam stands at the front of the congregation.{{Citation needed|date=April 2010}} The hadith in question is #881 of [[Sahih Muslim]]: &quot;[[Abu Huraira]] said: The best rows for men are the first rows, as opposed to the last ones, and the best rows for women are the last ones as opposed to the first ones.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.usc.edu/schools/college/crcc/engagement/resources/texts/muslim/hadith/muslim/004.smt.html|title=The Book of Prayers (Kitab Al-Salat)|publisher=[[University of Southern California]]|accessdate=2008-01-25}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The ''hadith'' of [[Umm Waraqa]] has given rise to debates among Islamic leaders on whether it is acceptable or not for women to lead prayers, including mixed-gender congregational prayer. Umm Waraqa bint Abdallah, an [[Ansari (nisbat)|Ansari]] woman, who was well versed in the [[Quran]], was instructed by Muhammad to lead ''ahl dariha'', which consisted of both men and women, in prayer. The Arabic phrase means &quot;the people of her home&quot;, but the ambiguity hangs on the exact translation of ''dar'', &quot;home&quot;, which can refer to one’s residence, neighborhood, or village. The &quot;people of Umm Waraqa’s home&quot; were so numerous that Muhammad appointed a [[muezzin]] to call them to prayer. Umm Waraqa was one of the few to hand down the Quran before it was recorded in writing.&lt;ref&gt;Women in Islam By Wiebke Walther published by Markus Wiener Publishing, 1981, p. 111 (citing Ibn Sad, Kitab al-Tabaqat al-Kabir, vol. 8, p. 335)&lt;/ref&gt;

The use of the word ''dar'' in the ''hadith'', when speaking of where the prayer was held, has resulted in different interpretations. A general translation is &quot;area&quot;, constituting the community around where Umm Waraqa lived. This idea is not accepted by many scholars. Another translation is ''dar'' is &quot;household&quot;, which would mean that Umm Waraqa led prayers in her home. Who was she leading? [[Imam Zaid]] presents three possibilities: the two servants of her household and the ''[[mu'ahdhin]]'', or the women of her surrounding “area”, or only the women of her household. Each of these possibilities requires certain assumptions, but the most accepted is that Umm Waraqa was leading the women of her household, thus leading to the conclusion that women are allowed to lead prayers of all-female congregations. Zaid insists that if the Prophet established a mosque in the household of a man, which was not uncommon, [[Itban b. Malik]], then he must also have set up women-only congregations.&lt;ref name=&quot;newislamicdirections.com&quot;/&gt;

With regard to women leading congregations of women, however, several ''hadith'' report that [[wives of Muhammad|two of Muhammad's wives]], [[Aisha]] and [[Umm Salamah]], did so, and as a result most ''[[madhhabs]]'' support this. According to [[Qaradawi]]:

: ''The hadith of `A’ishah and Umm Salamah (may Allah be pleased with them). `Abdur-Raziq (5086), Ad-Daraqutni (1/404) and Al-Bayhaqi (3/131) reported from the narration of Abu Hazim Maysarah ibn Habib from Ra’itah Al-Hanafiyyah from `A’ishah that she led women in Prayer and stood among them in an obligatory Prayer. Moreover, Ibn Abi Shaybah (2/89) reported from the chain of narrators of Ibn Abi Layla from `Ata’ that `A’ishah used to say the Adhan, the Iqamah, and lead women in Prayer while standing among them in the same row. Al-Hakim also reported the same hadith from the chain of narrators of Layth Ibn Abi Sulaim from `Ata’, and the wording of the hadith mentioned here is Al-Hakim’s. ''

: ''Furthermore, Ash-Shafi`i (315), Ibn Abi Shaybah (88/2) and `Abdur-Raziq (5082) reported from two chains of narrators that report the narration of `Ammar Ad-Dahni in which he stated that a woman from his tribe named Hujayrah narrated that Umm Salamh used to lead women in Prayer while standing among them in the same row. ''

: ''The wording of `Abdur-Raziq for the same hadith is as follows: “Umm Salamah led us (women) in the `Asr Prayer and stood among us (in the same row).” ''

: ''In addition, Al-Hafiz said in Ad-Dirayah (1/169), “Muhammad ibn Al-Husain reported from the narration of Ibrahim An-Nakh`i that `A’ishah used to lead women in Prayer during the month of Ramadan while standing among them in the same row. ''

: ''Further, `Abdur-Raziq reported (5083) from the narration of Ibrahim ibn Muhammad from Dawud ibn Al-Husain from `Ikrimah from Ibn `Abbas that the latter said, “A woman can lead women in Prayer while standing between them.”''

All of the hadiths state that the given woman leads the other women in prayers while standing among them in the same row, and not standing on the first row of the prayers as imams do. They further state that they were among only women, not male worshippers.

Aside from the ''hadith'', there are other sources to consider. The ''sunnah'' is a more general source of precedent; it is usually considered to count against women leading mixed congregations, as there are no reports of it happening in Muhammad's time, unless, as [[Amina Wadud]] suggested, the aforementioned Umm Waraqah hadith is interpreted to apply to her town rather than to her household alone.

A third source of precedent is the principle of ''[[ijma]]''—consensus—supported by the ''hadith'' &quot;My community will never agree upon an error.&quot; This is also generally quoted against it, since the consensus of the traditional jurists is overwhelmingly against it; however, supporters of the idea argue that this consensus is not universal.

==Women-only congregations==
Schools differ on whether a woman may be ''imam'' (leader) of a ''[[jama'ah]]'' (congregational) prayer if the congregation consists of women alone. Three of the four [[Sunni]] ''[[madhhab]]s''—[[Shafi'i]]s, [[Hanafi]]s, and [[Hanbali]]s—allow this, although Hanafis consider it to be ''[[makrooh]]'', a disliked act. (The fourth division, [[Maliki]]s, do not permit women to lead women in prayer.) Where it is allowed, the woman stands among the congregation in the front row, instead of alone in front of the congregation. In 2000, six ''[[marja]]''s among [[Iran]]'s Shia leadership declared that they too allowed women to lead a woman-only congregation, reversing a previous ban in that country.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/world/middle_east/861819.stm|title=Iranian women to lead prayers|publisher=BBC|accessdate=2008-02-11 | date=2000-08-01}}&lt;/ref&gt;

An unusual feature of [[Islam in China]] is the existence of ''nüsi'', [[mosque]]s solely for women. The imams and all the congregants are women and men are not allowed into the buildings. A handful of women have been trained as imams in order to serve these mosques.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/asia-pacific/3656180.stm|title=Chinese Muslims forge isolated path|publisher=BBC|accessdate=2008-02-11 | date=2004-09-15}}&lt;/ref&gt; However, in at least some communities where these mosques operated, women were not allowed in the men's mosques. In recent years, efforts have been made to establish similar mosques in India and Iran.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/south_asia/3429695.stm|title=Storm over Indian women's mosque|publisher=BBC|accessdate=2008-02-11 | date=2004-01-27}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Mixed-gender congregations==
[[File:Friday prayer in Tahrir (Women Ahead on men).jpg|thumb|[[2011 Egyptian revolution|Egyptian demonstrators]] in [[Tahrir Square]], [[Cairo]] at [[salah|prayer]]. Note that, highly unusually, the women are in front of the men.]]

Three Sunni schools accept that women can lead other women in prayer; however none of them see it as acceptable to lead men in prayers. In addition, the [[Hanbali]]s permitted that a woman leads men in [[taraweeh]] prayers.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.wluml.org/node/2329 International: The woman-led prayer - views from Europe]&lt;/ref&gt; A minority of the Hanbali school allow women to lead men in ''[[tarawih|tarāwīh]]'' in certain conditions, including the requirement that she remain behind the men during prayers. This is so that the men do not have to look at a woman ahead of them, which might make them aroused. According to [[Imam an-Nawawi]], “If a woman leads a man or men in a congregational prayer, the prayer of the men is invalid. As for her prayer, and the prayer of the women praying with her, it is sound.” 

Within the household, if no qualified man is present, is the one exception for women to lead men in prayers.&lt;ref name=&quot;newislamicdirections.com&quot;&gt;[http://www.newislamicdirections.com/nid/articles/female_prayer_leadership_revisited/ &quot;Female Prayer Leadership (Revisited)&quot;], ''New Islamic Directions'' by Imam Zaid, 2008-04-22. Retrieved on 2008-11-29.]&lt;/ref&gt; Modern Islamic scholars such as Dr. [[Yusuf Al-Qaradawi]], based on the Umm Waraqah ''hadith'' mentioned above, consider it permissible for a knowledgeable woman to lead mixed prayers within her own household,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last=al-Qaradawi|first=Yusuf|title=Women Acting as Imams in Prayer|url=http://www.islamonline.net/servlet/Satellite?cid=1119503549588&amp;pagename=IslamOnline-English-Ask_Scholar/FatwaE/FatwaEAskTheScholar|publisher=[[IslamOnline]]|accessdate=March 1, 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt; as he considers this to largely obviate the danger of the men being aroused by her presence.

In the early years of Islam, the [[Haruriyyah]] sect, a branch of the [[Kharijites]] movement, founded by [[Habib ibn-Yazīd al-Harūrī]], held that it was permissible to entrust the imamate to a woman if she were able to carry out the required duties. In 699 A.D. (77 A.H.), the founder's wife, [[Ghazala al-Haruriyya|Ghazāla al-Harūriyya]], even led her male warriors in prayer in [[Kufa]] after having controlled the city for a day, following the example of [[Abu Sufyan]]'s daughter [[Juwayriyya]] at the [[Battle of Yarmuk]]{{citation needed|date=January 2011}}. Not only did she lead Muslim men in prayer, she recited the two longest chapters in the Quran during that prayer.&lt;ref&gt;History of Messengers and Kings, By al-Tabari, 51:80; Ali Masudi, Gardens of Gold, Dar al-Andalus, Beirut, 1965, 3:139&lt;/ref&gt;

Well-known early jurists — including [[Abu Jafar Muhammad ibn Jarir al-Tabari|Al-Tabari]] (838–932), historian, exegete and founder of a now defunct juristic school; [[Abu Thawr]] (764–854), mufti of Iraq; [[Al-Muzani]] (791–878); and [[Ibn Arabi]] (1165–1240) — considered the practice permissible at least for optional (''[[nafl salat]]'') prayers.&lt;ref&gt;[http://ssrn.com/abstract=1735071 &quot;I Am One of the People’: A Survey and Analysis of Legal Arguments on Woman-Led Prayer in Islam&quot;, Journal of Law and Religion 26.1 2010-2011 by Ahmed Elewa and Laury Silvers]&lt;/ref&gt; Al-Muthani (d. 878), student of [[Shafii]] and contributor to the establishment of the Shafii juristic school,allowed women to unconditionally lead men in prayer{{citation needed|date=January 2011}}. However, the views of these scholars are not accepted by any major surviving group{{citation needed|date=January 2011}}.

A few ''[[fatwas]]'' exist permitting women to lead a mixed gender congregation regardless of familial relationship. For instance, Dr. [[Khaled Abou El Fadl]] recommends that the placement of the imam be made with greater modesty in mind for a female imam. Some traditional scholars caution against Yusuf Qaradawi's methodology and regard him as excessively lenient as he does not limit himself to the positions of the four [[Sunni]] schools of ''[[fiqh]]'.

Adding to the arguments in favor of woman-led prayer of mixed congregations, [[Laury Silvers]] and [[Ahmed Elewa]] recently published a detailed article in the '' [[Journal of Law and Religion]]'' arguing that female imams are permissible in all circumstances.  Their abstract reads:  
:This paper, written five years after the Wadud prayer, presents a survey and analysis of the various responses to female led mixed-gender congregational prayers as well as a legal argument for its default permissibility. We show that, in interpreting the Hadiths on woman-led prayer, Sunni schools of law hold a range of opinions on its permissibility. We discuss how Muslim jurists consider historical needs in their rulings, the role of female modesty in this debate, and the nature of juristic consensus. We present our own argument that unrestricted female prayer leadership is legal by default rather than an innovation as many critics have charged. Finally, we set out our own different positions on the propriety of Muslim women asserting their inclusion in the current situation.&lt;ref&gt;[http://ssrn.com/abstract=1735071  &quot;I Am One of the People’: A Survey and Analysis of Legal Arguments on Woman-Led Prayer in Islam&quot;, Journal of Law and Religion 26.1 2010-2011 by Ahmed Elewa and Laury Silvers]&lt;/ref&gt;

== In individual countries==
===Bahrain===
A woman disguised as a man attempted to deliver a ''[[Jum'ah]] [[khutbah]]'' but was detected by members of the congregation and arrested by the [[Bahrain]]i police. The incident occurred at one of the biggest mosques in the island state, in front of 7000 worshippers, on the last Friday of [[Ramadan]] in 2004. The would-be ''khatib'', wearing full male dress with a false beard and moustache, sat on the ''[[minbar]]'' just before speaking, at which point some worshippers realised that the new imam was a woman in disguise. They and the mosque's imam, [[Sheikh]] [[Adnan Al-Qattan]], handed the 40 year old woman over to the police.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.arabnews.com/?page=1&amp;section=0&amp;article=54523&amp;d=15&amp;m=11&amp;y=2004|title= Woman ‘Imam’ Held in Bahrain Mosque|publisher=Arab News|date=2004-11-15|accessdate=2008-06-09}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Canada===
[[Islam in Canada|Canadian Muslims]] have been active in the woman-led prayer movement since 2004.&lt;ref name=PostJul2&gt;Rachel Sa, &quot;Making history first mosque prayers led by a woman: Mixed-gender service&quot;, ''National Post'', July 2, 2005&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=GlobeJul2&gt;Jen Gerson, &quot;Woman leads Islamic prayers in mosque, a first for Canada -- Country could become the conscience of the religion, she says in Friday sermon&quot;, ''Globe &amp; Mail'', July 2, 2005&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=NewsweekWPprofile&gt;[http://newsweek.washingtonpost.com/onfaith/pamela_k_taylor/], ''Washington Post/Newsweek&lt;/ref&gt; The [[United Muslim Association]] (UMA) is committed to having women deliver the ''khutbah'' and lead the ''salah''.

In that year, 20-year-old [[Maryam Mirza]] delivered the second half of the ''[[Eid al-Fitr]]'' ''khutbah'' at the [[Etobicoke]] mosque in [[Toronto]], run by the UMA.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.tribuneindia.com/2004/20041116/world.htm First Muslim woman delivers sermon]&lt;/ref&gt;
Later the same year, [[Yasmin Shadeer]] led the night ''[[isha]]'' prayer with her male and female congregants.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.cbc.ca/thesundayedition/media/sisterhood_se050227.ram|title=One for the Sisterhood: A documentary by Karin Wells|publisher=[[CBC.ca|CBC]]|year=2005|accessdate=2008-03-21}}&lt;/ref&gt; - the first recorded occasion in contemporary times where a woman led a congregation in prayer in a mosque. 

In April 2005, [[Raheel Raza]] led Toronto's first woman-led mixed-gender Friday service, delivering the ''khutbah'' and leading the prayers of the congregation. The event was organized by the [[Muslim Canadian Congress]] to celebrate [[Earth Day]], and was held in the backyard of the downtown Toronto home of activist [[Tarek Fatah]].&lt;ref&gt;[www.muslimcanadiancongress.org/20050423.pdf Woman leads mixed-gender prayers for city Muslims]&lt;/ref&gt; The former [[Mufti of Marseille]], [[Soheib Bencheikh]], requested that either Raza&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.raheelraza.com|title=Raheel Raza - Profile|accessdate=2008-03-21}}&lt;/ref&gt; or [[Pamela Taylor]] lead him in prayer during a visit to Canada in February 2006. The prayers were sponsored by the Muslim Canadian Congress and held in a private venue with a mixed gender congregation.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.wluml.org/zh-hans/node/2747 Canada: French Islamic Scholar to join woman-led prayer in Toronto]&lt;/ref&gt; In 2008, Taylor, a Muslim convert since 1986, gave the Friday ''khutbah'' and led the mixed-gender prayers at the UMA Toronto mosque at the invitation of the [[Muslim Canadian Congress]] on [[Canada Day]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.awid.org/eng/Issues-and-Analysis/Library/Woman-led-prayer-honours-IWD Woman-led prayer honours IWD]&lt;/ref&gt; In addition to leading the prayers, Taylor also gave a sermon on the importance of equality among people regardless of gender, race, sexual orientation, and/or disability.&lt;ref&gt;[http://pluralism.org/reports/view/111 The Pluralism Project - Research Report]&lt;/ref&gt;

From 2008, the [[Noor Cultural Centre]] in Toronto has included women on their Board of Khatibs, and women and men alternate giving the call to prayer each week . Women regularly give full length sermons prior to the second ''[[adhan]]'', with a male ''khatib'' delivering the Arabic portion in brief after the second call. In 2009, academic Laury Silvers and activist lawyer [[El-Farouk Khaki]] founded the [[El-Tawhid Juma Circle]] in downtown Toronto. The circle is gender-equal, homosexual-friendly, and religiously non-discriminatory. All Muslims are welcome to lead the prayer and give the sermon.&lt;ref name=&quot;PostJul2&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;GlobeJul2&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;NewsweekWPprofile&quot;/&gt; It helps set up similar circles when asked; the first sister circle was founded in Washington D.C., in early 2011 (see USA section below).

Muslims for Progressive Values Canada, an affiliate of Muslims for Progressive Values USA, founded in 2010 by Shahla Khan Salter (chair) leads mixed congregational prayers in Ottawa, Canada. Prayers for MPV Canada have been led by women, including Farhat Rehman and by Zeinab A.

The El Tawhid Unity Mosque in Toronto founded by Dr. Laury Silvers regularly conducts Friday prayers led by women in a mixed congregation. The person delivering the khutbah may be a woman or a man. 

===China===
A unique feature of [[Islam in China]] is the presence of female-only mosques. Among the [[Hui people]], but not other Muslim ethnic minorities such as the [[Uyghur people|Uyghurs]], Quranic schools for girls evolved into woman-only mosques and women acted as imams as early as 1820.&lt;ref name=&quot;npr.org&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.npr.org/templates/story/story.php?storyId=128628514|title=Female Imams Blaze Trail Amid China's Muslims|Female Imams Blaze Trail Amid China's Muslims|accessdate=2010-07-22}}&lt;/ref&gt; These imams are called ''Nu Ahong'', and they guide female Muslims in worship and prayer.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |title=Muslim women do it their way in Ningxia|author=AP , WUZHONG, CHINA|newspaper=Taipei Times|page=9|date=Wed, Dec 20, 2006|url=http://www.taipeitimes.com/News/editorials/archives/2006/12/20/2003341218|accessdate=May 29, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Morocco ===
Kathleen O'Connor noted in 2009 that a [[madrasa]] in [[Morocco]] had started training women as imams.&lt;ref&gt;
{{Citation
  | last = O'Connor
  | first = Kathleen M.
  | contribution = imam
  | year = 2009
  | title = Encyclopedia of Islam
  | editor-last = Campo
  | editor-first = Juan Eduardo
  | pages = 348
  | publisher = Infobase Publishing
  | isbn = 9780816054541
  | quote = [...] women have begun to be trained as imams at a recently established madrasa (legal college) in Morocco.
}}
&lt;/ref&gt;

===South Africa===
[[Islam in South Africa|South African Muslims]] heard their first female-led ''Jum'ah khutbah'' in 1994 when African-American Islamic studies professor [[Amina Wadud]] spoke at the [[Claremont Main Road Mosque]] in [[Cape Town]],&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.upenn.edu/gazette/0306/voices.html One Faith, Many Fragments] By Amina Wadud for the University of Pennsylvania (2006)&lt;/ref&gt; an experience she discusses in ''Inside the Gender Jihad''. Since then, both that mosque and Masjidul Islam in [[Johannesburg]] often have women speakers for ''jum'ah''. Amongst them are [[Ai'sha Jennifer Roberts]], [[Farhana Ismail]], [[Moefidah Jaffer]] and [[Zakiya Seguro]].

From 1995 to 1997, a congregation in Johannesburg met every Friday for the ''jum'ah'' prayer, and every night in Ramadan for the tarāwīh prayer, in a building owned by the [[Muslim Youth Movement of South Africa]] (MYM). The ''khutbah'' was delivered by either a male or female ''khatib'' and the imams who led the prayer also included men and women. [[Farid Esack]] refers to this in his book ''Qur'an, Liberation and Pluralism''. One of the prime movers behind this congregation was Muslim women's rights activist [[Shamima Shaikh]]. In January 1998, as per her wishes, one of her four funeral prayers was led by a woman friend, Farhana Ismail.

In 2003, a new venue for Eid prayer was established in [[Durban]], designed to allow families to attend the Eid prayer together in a pleasant and comfortable atmosphere. It is run by [[Taking Islam to the People]]. At each Eid ''salaah'' there are two ''khutbahs'' delivered, one by a male and one by a female. Over the seven years from 2003–2010, fourteen women have offered ''khutbah'', including Dr. [[Lubna Nadvi]], [[Zaytun Suleyman]], [[Fatima Seedat]], [[Fatima Hendricks]] and Dr [[Mariam Seedat]].&lt;ref&gt;http://web.uct.ac.za/depts/religion/documents/ARISA/2002_M5_farhana.pdf&lt;/ref&gt;

In 2005, Farhana Ismail first officiated at a ''[[nikah]]'' (wedding) ceremony. She has trained other women to do so; since 2006, Fatima Seedat has officiated at three such ceremonies.

In May 2007, as a guest of the Muslim Youth Movement, the American visitor, Laury Silvers, gave the Friday sermon at the Claremont Road Mosque in Cape Town and an associated mosque in Johannesburg.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.raheelraza.com/med.htm Pray Hear: Muslim Women want Larger Roles] By Karla Bruning for Columbia News Service&lt;/ref&gt;

===Spain===
[[Islam in Spain|Spanish Muslims]] have been some of the greatest supporters of the woman-led prayer movement. Spanish imam Abdennur Prado responded immediately to the controversial prayer by American [[Amina Wadud]] (see USA section) with a supportive legal opinion. He was one of the organisers of the October 2005 [[Islamic feminism]] conference in Barcelona, the first attended by men and women from around the world, at which Wadud led a mixed gender congregational prayer.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.muslimwakeup.com/main/archives/2005/10/amina-wadud-lea.php Amina Wadud Leads Mixed Gender Friday Prayer in Barcelona]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.guardian.co.uk/world/2005/oct/31/gender.religion Muslim women launch international 'gender jihad']&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.nodo50.org/csca/agenda08/palestina/arti338.html ¿Qué es el feminismo musulmán? Por la promoción de un cambio cultural en favor de la igualdad de géneros] (Spanish)&lt;/ref&gt; In 2010, another visiting academic, South African Dr. [[Sa'diyya Sheikh]], gave the ''khutbah'' and led the Friday prayer for a mixed congregation.

===Turkey ===
[[Islam in Turkey|Turkish Muslims]] are conscious of their influence in modernising Islam. The state-run mosques have trained hundreds of women as ''vaizes'', a term translated by the [[BBC]] as &quot;senior imams&quot;&lt;ref&gt;[http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/world/europe/7264903.stm &quot;Turkey in radical revision of Islamic texts&quot;. 26 February 2008. By [[Robert Pigott]].]&lt;/ref&gt; and by the ''[[Washington Times]]'' as &quot;female preachers&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.washingtontimes.com/news/2006/may/02/20060502-122646-8010r/ Turkey’s ‘vaizes’ expedite reform 2 May 2006]&lt;/ref&gt; The WT says, &quot;As well as being preachers, women now have the right to lead groups on the annual pilgrimage to Mecca, and 15 Turkish provinces have women serving as deputy muftis — specialists on religious law who monitor the work of imams in mosques. Significantly, given that 70 percent of requests for advice come from women, the assistant muftis have the right to issue fatwas, or religious opinions.&quot; According to the ''[[Christian Science Monitor]]'', in 2005 &quot;[[Diyanet]], a government body that oversees the country's mosques and trains religious leaders, added 150 women preachers across Turkey&quot; and has moved on to &quot;selecting a group of women who will serve as deputies to muftis, or expounders of religious law. From this post, they'll monitor the work being done by imams in local mosques, particularly as it relates to women.&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.csmonitor.com/2005/0427/p04s01-woeu.html &quot;In Turkey, Muslim women gain expanded religious authority&quot;. By Yigal Schleifer, Correspondent of The Christian Science Monitor / April 27, 2005]&lt;/ref&gt;

===United Kingdom===
[[Islam in the United Kingdom|British Muslims]] had their first chance to hear a female-led mixed-gender ''salah'' in 2008, when the American scholar [[Amina Wadud]] performed the Friday prayer at [[Oxford University|Oxford]]'s [[Wolfson College]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.guardian.co.uk/commentisfree/2008/oct/17/religion-islam-women-prayers It's Muslim men we must modernise]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.naplesnews.com/news/2006/dec/02/islams_gender_boundaries_being_pushed/ Islam's gender boundaries being pushed]&lt;/ref&gt; In 2010 [[Raheel Raza]] became the first Muslim-born woman to lead a mixed-gender British congregation through Friday prayers.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.independent.co.uk/news/uk/home-news/first-woman-to-lead-friday-prayers-in-uk-1996228.html First woman to lead Friday prayers in UK]&lt;/ref&gt;

===United States===
[[Image:Amina Wadud.JPG|thumb|200px|right|American imam [[Amina Wadud]] [http://books.google.com/books?id=xKsLCx2VmcwC&amp;pg=PA358&amp;lpg=PA358&amp;dq=%22imam+amina+wadud%22&amp;source=bl&amp;ots=EDDUY_Vd8P&amp;sig=1UiF74ppMPAO38cAKaha_Qd9jOM&amp;hl=en&amp;ei=DGg6TMayDYGB8gbBgOWmBg&amp;sa=X&amp;oi=book_result&amp;ct=result&amp;resnum=9&amp;ved=0CDoQ6AEwCA#v=onepage&amp;q=%22imam%20amina%20wadud%22&amp;f=false] ]]

In 2005, African-American Islamic scholar [[Amina Wadud]] led a congregation in Friday prayer and gave a sermon in New York City. Another woman sounded the call to prayer, while not wearing a headscarf, and no curtain divided the men and women.&lt;ref name=&quot;nytimes.com&quot;&gt;{{cite news| url=http://www.nytimes.com/2005/03/19/nyregion/19muslim.html | work=The New York Times | title=Woman Leads Muslim Prayer Service in New York | first=Andrea | last=Elliott | date=March 19, 2005}}&lt;/ref&gt; This was not the first woman-led mixed-gender congregational prayer (see the above noted events), but it was the first to gain national and international attention. See [[Amina_Wadud#Friday_prayer]] for fuller information. 

The [[Progressive Muslim Union]] followed the Wadud prayer with a woman-led prayer initiative. The initiative sought to bring together the varied progressive opinions on the prayer as well as engage more conservative Muslims by encouraging further debate, highlighting legal opinions in support of the prayer (as well as giving space to the overwhelming negative opinions), facilitating Muslims who would like to organize future prayers, and documenting those events as they heard of them. Progressives and others sympathetic to bringing about a transformation of gender privilege in Islam continue to work for the establishment of woman-led prayer.

Many perceived the Wadud prayer to be an inevitable reaction to the deplorable situation of women in mosques in North America. The attention garnered by the event forced more conservative Muslim organizations to publicly acknowledge the situation and call for changes. [[ISNA]] responded with guidelines for women-friendly mosques.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.ildc.net/ildc-news/2005/6/22/isna-endorses-new-guidelines-for-women-friendly-mosques.html|title=ISNA Endorses New Guidelines for Women Friendly Mosques|publisher=[[Islamic Society of North America]]|date=2005-06-22|accessdate=2008-06-16}}&lt;/ref&gt; Scholars such as [http://www.newislamicdirections.com/ Imam Zaid Shakir] and Dr. [[Louay M. Safi]] have been calling attention to and working to change mosque conditions for years. Progressives and others would argue, though, that mosque conditions are merely a symptom of a widespread sense of male entitlement following centuries of male privilege in the intellectual and political power centers of Islam.

Women continue to lead prayers in the United States in their communities with or without media coverage: [[Nakia Jackson]] led Eid prayers in 2006 and 2007, with [[Laury Silvers]] giving the ''khutba''. 

Since early 2006, [[Muslims for Progressive Values]] has had a continuous gender-equal prayer space in [[West Hollywood]], [[California]]. Both men and women are allowed to lead prayers and deliver a ''khutba''. Although congregants may choose to position themselves wherever they like, there is no gender segregation policy during prayer.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.meetup.com/LAmpvusa/&lt;/ref&gt;  The first dedicated gender-equal prayer space in the United States was founded by [[Fatima Thompson]] and Imam [[Daayiee Abdullah]] in Washington D.C., as a sister mosque to the El-Tawhid Juma Circle founded two years previously in Toronto (see above).

==See also==
* [[Feminism#Effect on religion|Effect of feminism on religion]]
* [[Imam]]
* [[Liberal movements within Islam]]
* [[Shia Imam]]
* [[Sex segregation in Islam]]
* [[Tynetta Muhammad]]
* [[Women in Islam]]

==Notes==
&lt;!--&lt;nowiki&gt;
See http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Wikipedia:Footnotes for an explanation of how to generate footnotes using the &lt;ref&gt; and &lt;/ref&gt; tags, and the template below. 
&lt;/nowiki&gt;--&gt;
{{Reflist|2}}

==External links==
* [http://www.imow.org/wpp/stories/viewStory?storyId=125 International Museum of Women Feature on Women Spiritual Guides in Morocco]
* [http://www.islaam.net/main/display.php?id=1383&amp;category=7 ruling] by [[Zarabozo]] (includes Arabic quotes)
* [http://www.irfi.org/articles/articles_101_150/religious_conservatism.htm Religious conservatism: Feminist theology as a means of combating injustice toward women in Muslim communities/cculture] by [[Riffat Hasan]]
* [http://www.iio.org/filemgmt_data/files/female%20imam.pdf ''An Examination of the Issue of Female Prayer Leadership''] by Imam [[Zaid Shakir]]
* [http://www.scholarofthehouse.org/onwolepr.html Dr. Khaled Abou el-Fadl's fatwa on women leading prayer]
* [http://www.themodernreligion.com/women/recognition.html In Recognition of Women]
* [http://www.nytimes.com/2005/03/19/nyregion/19muslim.html?_r=1 Woman leads Muslim prayer service in New York]
* [http://www.mwlusa.org/topics/rights/polirights.html Women in Society: Political Participation]
* [http://papers.ssrn.com/sol3/papers.cfm?abstract_id=1735071/ &quot;I Am One of the People’: A Survey and Analysis of Legal Arguments on Woman-Led Prayer in Islam&quot;, Journal of Law and Religion 26.1 2010-2011 by Ahmed Elewa and Laury Silvers]
* [http://www.mpvottawa.com]

{{DEFAULTSORT:Women As Imams}}
[[Category:Islam-related controversies]]
[[Category:Women's rights in religious movements]]
[[Category:Ordination of women]]
[[Category:Islam and women]]
[[Category:Liberal and progressive movements within Islam]]

[[ar:المرأة والإمامة]]
[[de:Mourchida]]
[[it:Donne come imam]]
[[ms:Wanita sebagai imam]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
