<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="16270154" ns="0" title="Per-Olov Kindgren"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Orphan|date=February 2009}}
{{Infobox musical artist
| name = Per-Olov Kindgren
| image =
| caption =
| image_size = 
| background = non_vocal_instrumentalist
| birth_name =
| alias = 
| Born = {{Birth date and age|1956|06|10}}&lt;br&gt;[[Bogotá]], [[Colombia]]
| death_date = 
| origin = [[Stockholm]], [[Sweden]]
| instrument = [[Classical guitar]]
| genre = [[classical music|Classical]]
| occupation = [[Guitarist]], [[Composer]] and [[Music teacher]]
| years_active =
| label = Per-Olov Kindgren Music Online
| associated_acts = 
| website = [http://www.per-olovkindgren.com/ www.per-olovkindgren.com]
}}

'''Per-Olov Kindgren''' (born June 10, 1956 in [[Bogotá]], [[Colombia]]) is a [[Sweden|Swedish]] [[classical guitar]]ist, [[composer]] and [[music teacher]] known for his [[classical guitar]] playing ranging from [[Johann Sebastian Bach|Bach]] to [[The Beatles]].

==Biography==
===Early life===
Kindgren was born in [[Bogotá]], [[Colombia]] to a [[Sweden|Swedish]] father and a [[Denmark|Danish]] mother. Per-Olov's father Owe, an engineer, worked for the Colombian branch of [[Ericsson|LM Ericsson]] installing telephone stations. The family returned to [[Stockholm]] when Per-Olov was three years old. He lived there from 1960 till 1970. At the age of six Per-Olov was fascinated by a bright red electric guitar in a shop window. The Beatles became his heroes, and he especially admired [[Paul McCartney]]. His parents acquired a [[classical guitar]] for his seventh birthday present. In 1970 he saw a documentary about [[John Williams (guitarist)|John Williams]] broadcast on Danish national television, and from that day on, he knew what he wanted to become. When Per-Olov was 14 years old, his family moved to the border town [[Helsingør]] in [[Denmark]]. In doing so he could more easily attend a Swedish high school in [[Helsingborg]], where he met his first classical guitar teacher [[Torvald Nilsson]].

===Professional life===
In 1976 he began to study at [[The Royal Danish Academy of Music]] in [[Copenhagen]], where he moved during his studies and where he lives and works today. He studied there for 7 years with professor [[Per-Olof Johnson]] until his graduation in 1983. Even while continuing his studies, he became a music teacher, teaching at both music schools in [[Vallensbæk]] and [[Gentofte]] for 24 years. Presently Kindgren only works as a music teacher at the music school in Gentofte. His work as a music teacher provides him with a steady living along with the concerts he performs. In 1979 he joined with three other guitarists, [[Steffen Broe Christensen]], [[Dag Egil Berge]] and [[Torsten Borbye Nielsen]], forming the Nordic Guitar Quartet. which performed more than 400 concerts throughout the years. Per-Olov composes pieces for [[solo (music)|solo]] guitar, as well as for [[duet (music)|duets]], [[trio (music)|trios]], [[quartet]]s up till [[septet]]s and [[octet (music)|octets]] for guitar. In 1998 he composed pieces for [[choir]], [[orchestra]] and a [[Rock band#Rock and pop bands|rock band]] for the 25th anniversary of the Vallensbæk music school and in 2000 he composed a Christmas [[Oratorio]] for [[organ (music)|organ]], [[guitar]], [[flute]]s, choir and [[narrator]]. In 2009, the great French [[guitarist]] and composer [[Jean Marie RAYMOND]] wrote for him a beautiful music piece, a little jewel called [http://www.productionsdoz.com/c378004449p17576611.1.html &quot;As always&quot;].

==Musical style==
Kindgren's style is mainly classical, with influences from [[jazz]], [[blues]] and [[easy listening]]. In addition to his classical repertoire Per-Olov also plays works of The Beatles. Kindgren likes to describe his own compositions as songs without words.

==Gear==
===Instrument===
*[[Classical guitar]] by [[luthier]] ''Per Hallgren'', 2011
*Per-Olov previously played a [[classical guitar]] built by [[Switzerland|Swiss]] [[luthier]] ''Philippe Jean-Mairet'', which he bought in 1987. A friend of his, Jørgen, had bought a guitar from the Swiss luthier whom he had met in [[Bern]] during his studies and loved its superb quality. Per-Olov asked his friend to order a guitar for him and nine months later he was able to visit Philippe Jean-Mairet in Switzerland to test his new guitar. Previously he owned a Martin Fleeson guitar which he had bought in [[Manchester]], [[England]] in 1986 for 25,000 [[Danish Krone|DKK]] (about [[Euro|€]]3,350 or [[United States dollar|$]]4,400 at the time). One year later Per-Olov bought his Jean-Mairet instrument.
*He also plays a 7 string classical guitar given to him by John and Judy Rogerson.

===Guitar Support===
Per-Olov can be seen in his videos, using a ''Gitano guitar support'' on his left lap.

==Discography==
* 1992 - Images, Nordic Guitar Quartet ''(Primaveramusic)''
* 2008 - After Silence ''(Villa Luisa Records)''
* 2010 - Distant Love
* 2011 - AIR

==References==
&lt;references /&gt;

==External links==
* [http://www.per-olovkindgren.com/ Per-Olov Kindgren's official site]
* [http://www.youtube.com/user/AndanteLargo Per-Olov Kindgren's YouTube Profile]

{{Classical guitar}}

{{Persondata &lt;!-- Metadata: see [[Wikipedia:Persondata]]. --&gt;
| NAME              = Kindgren, Per-Olov
| ALTERNATIVE NAMES =
| SHORT DESCRIPTION =
| DATE OF BIRTH     = June 10, 1956
| PLACE OF BIRTH    =
| DATE OF DEATH     =
| PLACE OF DEATH    =
}}
{{DEFAULTSORT:Kindgren, Per-Olov}}
[[Category:Living people]]
[[Category:Swedish composers]]
[[Category:Swedish classical guitarists]]
[[Category:1956 births]]

[[nl:Per-Olov Kindgren]]
[[sv:Per-Olov Kindgren]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
