<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><redirects><r from="List of Noir albums" to="Noir (anime)" tofragment="Soundtrack" /></redirects><pages><page pageid="53891" ns="0" title="Noir (anime)"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Infobox animanga/Header
| name            = Noir
| image           = [[File:Noir vol 1.jpg|230px]]
| caption         = North American cover of the first DVD volume
| ja_kanji        = ノワール
| ja_romaji       = Nowāru
| genre           = [[Neo-noir]], [[Girls with guns]], [[Action film|Action]]
}}
{{Infobox animanga/Video
| type            = tv series
| director        = [[Koichi Mashimo]]
| producer        =
| writer          = Ryoe Tsukimura
| music           = [[Yuki Kajiura]]
| studio          = [[Bee Train]]
| licensor        = {{flagicon|Australia}} {{flagicon|New Zealand}} [[Madman Entertainment]] &lt;br/&gt;{{flagicon|Canada}}{{flagicon|United States}} [[Funimation Entertainment]]
| network         = [[TV Tokyo]], Bandai Channel
| network_en      = {{flagicon|United States}} [[Anime Network]]
| network_other   = {{flagicon|France}} [[Canal+]] &lt;br /&gt;{{flagicon|Spain}} La sexta &lt;br /&gt;{{flagicon|Germany}} [[Viva (TV station)|VIVA]] &lt;br /&gt;{{flagicon|Brazil}} Animax
| first           = April 6, 2001
| last            = September 27, 2001
| episodes        = 26
| episode_list    = List of Noir episodes
}}
{{Infobox animanga/Footer}}

{{nihongo|'''''Noir'''''|ノワール|Nowāru}} is a 26-episode Japanese [[anime]] [[television series]] produced in 2001 by the [[Bee Train]] animation studio. [[Kōichi Mashimo]] directed ''Noir'', it was written by Ryoe Tsukimura, and the [[soundtrack]] was composed by [[Yuki Kajiura]]. The [[DVD]] version was released by [[ADV Films]] in North America and the United Kingdom and by [[Madman Entertainment]] in Australia and New Zealand.

The series follows the story of two young female [[assassination|assassins]] who embark together on a personal journey to seek answers about mysteries from their past. While at first they seem to be only vaguely related to each other, there are clues and hints given throughout the series that there are more than meets their eyes. During the course of the series, they are lured into more and more traps by a secret organization named ''Les Soldats'' (&quot;The Soldiers&quot; in [[French language|French]]).

''Noir'' was followed by two [[spiritual successor]]s, ''[[Madlax]]'' and ''[[El Cazador de la Bruja]]''. Together, these series constitute a [[trilogy]] exploring the &quot;[[girls with guns|girls-with-guns]]&quot; genre.

== Plot ==
{{See also|List of Noir episodes}}
The series follows the story of two young female assassins, the [[Corsica]]n Mireille Bouquet and the Japanese amnesiac Yumura Kirika, who embark together on a personal journey to seek answers about mysteries concerning their past. While at first they seem to be only vaguely related to each other, there are clues and hints given throughout the series that there is more going on behind the scenes than at first glance.

In their journey to learn more about Yumura's lost memories and her connection to Bouquet, the two form an alliance and begin performing assassinations under the code name &quot;Noir.&quot; During the course of the series, they are lured into more and more traps by a secret organization named ''Les Soldats'' (&quot;The Soldiers&quot; in [[French language|French]]). Les Soldats are a secret organization that has been a part, yet separate group of humanity. It is this hidden group that created and once completely controlled the deadly duo &quot;Noir.&quot; Each time that Les Soldats soldiers are sent to kill Bouquet and Yumura, it is considered a test as to whether or not the young women are suitable to carry the title &quot;Noir.&quot;

== Characters ==
[[File:NoirFourWomen.jpg|left|250px|thumb|The main characters; clockwise from top: Altena, Chloe, Kirika, and Mireille]]

*{{nihongo|Kirika Yuumura&lt;ref name=&quot;Yuumura&quot; group=&quot;n&quot;&gt;The email Mireille receives from Kirika in episode 1 romanizes her surname as &quot;Yuumura&quot; (with two ''u''). In addition, the [http://www.projectnoir.com/characters/kirika.shtml official English ''Noir'' website] also use this naming convention.&lt;/ref&gt;|夕叢霧香|Yūmura Kirika}} is a teenage girl with [[amnesia]]; the only things she remembers are the word ''Noir'' and her killing skills. When creating the characters for ''Noir'', its producer [[Shigeru Kitayama]] wanted the image of Kirika to be &quot;sweet and fragile&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;pnep2&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.projectnoir.com/episodes/episode02.shtml|title=Project Noir - Episodes - Episode 2|work=Project Noir|publisher=[[ADV Films]]|accessdate=October 5, 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt; In the Japanese version, she is voiced by [[Hōko Kuwashima]], and by [[Monica Rial]] in the English dub.

*{{nihongo|Mireille Bouquet|ミレイユ・ブーケ|Mireiyu Būke}} is a [[Corsica]]n woman born into a powerful crime family, Mireille and her uncle are the sole survivors of a brutal attack on her family, whereafter he trained her to become an assassin.{{ref|4|ep.14}} When creating the character for ''Noir'', Kitayama imagined Mireille as &quot;a lithe female panther&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;pnep2&quot;/&gt; According to producer [[Shigeru Kitayama]], [[Kotono Mitsuishi]]'s voicing of Mireille was a continuation of the working relationship they had from creating ''[[Excel Saga]]'', where Mitsuishi voiced the protagonist Excel, while the first thing she was told was that Excel and Mireille are completely opposite characters.&lt;ref name=&quot;pnep2&quot;/&gt; When creating their English [[Dubbing (filmmaking)|dub]], wherein she is voiced by [[Shelley Calene-Black]], ADV Films decided against giving Mireille a [[Corsican language|Corsican]] accent to avoid confusion in viewers unfamiliar with the language.&lt;ref name=&quot;ADV Films&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.projectnoir.com/episodes/index.shtml|title=Project Noir - Episodes - Episode 1|work=Project Noir|publisher=[[ADV Films]]|accessdate=October 5, 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt;

*{{nihongo|Chloe|クロエ|Kuroe&lt;ref name=&quot;Kuroe&quot; group=&quot;n&quot;&gt;Note the homophony to ''kuroi'', the Japanese word for ''black''.&lt;/ref&gt;}} is a skilled assassin who uses throwing and handheld knives instead of guns. Like Kirika and Mireille, Chloe is a candidate to become Noir. Chloe idolizes Kirika for her exceptional killing skills, and believes that she and Kirika are destined to become Noir together. She is the personal favorite character of ''Noir'''s composer [[Yuki Kajiura]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite album-notes|title=Noir: Original Soundtrack I|albumlink=Noir (anime)#Soundtrack|bandname=[[Yuki Kajiura]]|year=2001|notestitle=More Melody!|format=CD booklet|publisher=[[Victor Entertainment]]}}&lt;/ref&gt; Her Japanese voice was provided by [[Aya Hisakawa]]. In the English version, [[Hilary Haag]] performed the part.

*{{nihongo|Altena|アルテナ|Arutena}} is the high priestess of the Soldats. She believes that the Soldats have been corrupted by power and greed, and attempts to return the Soldats to its &quot;original state&quot; by reviving Noir. She lives a medieval lifestyle in a place the Soldats consider as their holy site called &quot;The Manor&quot;, located somewhere on the border between France and Spain, where she raised and trained Chloe. Voiced by [[Tarako]] in the Japanese version, her English voice was provided by [[Tiffany Grant]].

== Setting ==
Unlike its [[spiritual successor]] ''[[Madlax]]'', ''Noir'' is mainly about [[reality|reality's]] [[criminal|criminal underworld]] while ''Madlax'' is about [[supernatural]] events. [[Mireille Bouquet|Mireille]] and [[Kirika Yuumura|Kirika]], in episode four, check the profile of a fifteen-year-old [[student]] named Rosaly Hammond, discovering that she was born in 1994.  As Rosaly would be turning sixteen, Noir thus takes place approximately between 2009 and 2010.&lt;ref name=&quot;ep04&quot;&gt;''Noir'', episode 4 (11:11): When [[Kirika Yuumura|Kirika]] checks Rosaly Hammond's profile.&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Les Soldats ===
''Les Soldats'' (&quot;The Soldiers&quot; in [[French language|French]]) is a mysterious organisation in ''Noir''.
According to [[Altena (Noir)|Altena]], a thousand years ago, a group of people who had survived a bloody war that cost a numerous lives, formed a group called ''Les Soldats'' to protect the weak and take revenge on the [[world]].&lt;ref name=&quot;ep20&quot;&gt;''Noir'', episode 20: Altena tells Chloe about Soldats' history.&lt;/ref&gt; When Kirika travels to a Soldats' village, she finds out that during the late tenth century, ''Les Soldats'' has taken place in every social part of [[humankind]]. For example, Soldats were witnessed the birth of the Greone's [[mafia|mafia family]] which was created 200 years ago from the time the series began.&lt;ref name=&quot;ep09&quot;&gt;''Noir'', episode 09: Intocabile Act II.&lt;/ref&gt; Near the end of the series, Altena states that &quot;Les Soldats&quot; has been consumed by the very greed they once swore to undo, and thus had become like the world itself.{{Or|date=January 2011}}

Although the Soldats were founded by a united group, in ''Noir'' its members were separated into two groups: Altena's followers and her opposers, the Soldats' Council members. For easy identification, Altena's followers are mostly people who dress up as nuns&lt;ref name=&quot;ep24&quot;&gt;''Noir'', episode 24: Dark Return.&lt;/ref&gt; and common villagers who are skilled at fighting&lt;ref name=&quot;ep22&quot;&gt;''Noir'', episode 22: Journey's End.&lt;/ref&gt; while her opposers are mainly men in black suits. The Soldats' Council are the people who disagreed with Altena's opinions; while Altena and Chloe are trying to protect Mireille and Kirika, the Council is trying to do the opposite. It contains five members,&lt;ref name=&quot;ep26&quot;&gt;''Noir'', episode 26: Rebirth.&lt;/ref&gt; and one of them, Remy Brefford, invites Mireille to join their ranks, and he has his own building in [[Paris]].&lt;ref name=&quot;ep23&quot;&gt;''Noir'', episode 23: Mireille attacks Brefford's building.&lt;/ref&gt; The Council perhaps ironically has the power and force to punish those who fail them, even Altena.{{Or|date=January 2011}}

Altena's followers are mostly nuns and priestesses; though they often appear to be ordinary, petite women, they are capable of using guns and other lethal weapons. Altena lives in a manor not located on any map but is near the [[border]] of [[France]] and [[Spain]].&lt;ref name=&quot;ep22&quot;&gt;''Noir'', episode 22: Kirika's conversation with a Soldats' villager.&lt;/ref&gt; It is known by name &quot;the place which has been forgotten by time.&quot;{{Citation needed|date=January 2011}} The manor's structure is similar to those of [[Ancient Greece]] and [[ancient Rome|Rome]]. Separated from the manor by mountains, there is a village which belongs to Altena, and their ancient task is to guard her manor.{{Or|date=January 2011}}

=== Noir ===
''Noir'' is the [[French language|French]] word for &quot;black&quot;. In ''Noir'', it is known as the name of the two maidens who govern death. Pictures and sculptures of the two maidens can be seen on Mireille's father's watch and on Soldats' churches. To the [[mafia|underworld]], it is known as the &quot;One Thousand Year&quot; darkness of [[Europe]]. According to Altena's story, when the Soldats went under, two hands were left on the surface, so their ancient task is to retrieve the two maidens known as &quot;Noir&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;ep20&quot;/&gt; The ritual to become Noir takes place under Altena's manor, an underground temple in the style of ancient Greek ruins.

Throughout the series, the only three candidates for &quot;Noir&quot; are [[Mireille Bouquet]], [[Kirika Yuumura]] and [[Chloe (Noir)|Chloe]]. Of all the three, Mireille was the only who was predicted to be neglected, and Kirika probably is the only who can turn into ''True Noir''.&lt;ref name=&quot;ep24&quot;&gt;''Noir'', episode 24: Altena's conversation with Borne.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;ep22&quot;&gt;''Noir'', episode 22: Kirika became True Noir after witnessed the assault on the village.&lt;/ref&gt; When one has fallen, the remaining two shall become Noir.

== Production ==
According to the director Kōichi Mashimo, he envisioned ''Noir'' and ''Madlax'' as part of a trilogy exploring the [[girls with guns|girls-with-guns]] genre, and soon after the release of the latter, he confirmed having plans to produce the third installment,&lt;ref name=&quot;Wong&quot;&gt;{{cite journal|last=Wong|first=Amos|title=Inside Bee Train|journal=[[Newtype USA]]|pages=8–15|year=2005|month=March}}&lt;/ref&gt; which would later become ''[[El Cazador de la Bruja]]''.&lt;ref name=&quot;NTUSA_Apr07&quot;&gt;{{cite journal|title=Interview with Kōichi Mashimo|journal=[[Newtype USA]]|year=2007|volume=7|issue=4|month=April|quote=During an interview, I accidentally blurted out something about [''Noir'' and ''Madlax'' being part of] a 'trilogy', which forced me to follow through and actually make a third installment!}}&lt;/ref&gt;

For Mireille's personal sidearm, Mashimo wanted a gun with &quot;a more modern image&quot;, therefore the production staff decided on the [[Walther P99]].&lt;ref&gt;http://www.projectnoir.com/armes/index.shtml&lt;/ref&gt; After considering several compact pistols, including the [[Walther PPK]] and the [[Glock 26]], for Kirika's personal sidearm, the [[Beretta M1934]] became the weapon of choice, because of its &quot;classic, European feel&quot; that suited the premise of the series' story.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.projectnoir.com/armes/beretta.shtml&lt;/ref&gt; Because of the organization's premise, European guns were chosen for the members of Les Soldats. The assassins in black suits that are sent after the protagonists throughout the series all carry the [[SIG Pro 2340]], which at the time of production was the newest model of its line, while other members were given increasingly older weapons, depending on the member's rank.&lt;ref name=&quot;ADV Films&quot;/&gt;

According to producer [[Shigeru Kitayama]], [[Kotono Mitsuishi]]'s voicing of Mireille was a continuation of the working relationship they had from creating ''[[Excel Saga]]'', where Mitsuishi voiced the protagonist Excel.&lt;ref name=&quot;pnep2&quot;/&gt;

== Media ==
=== Anime series ===
The 26 episodes of the ''Noir'' anime series initially ran from April 6 through September 27, 2001 on [[TV Tokyo]] in Japan&lt;ref name=&quot;ep1date&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.projectnoir.com/episodes/index.shtml|title=Project Noir - Episodes - Episode 1|work=Project Noir|publisher=[[ADV Films]]|accessdate=September 30, 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.animenewsnetwork.com/news/2003-08-18/noir-finale-nuku-nuku-no.1-dates|publisher=[[Anime News Network]]|date=August 18, 2003|accessdate=October 2, 2009|title=Noir finale, Nuku Nuku #1 dates}}&lt;/ref&gt; and was released on DVD and VHS in 13 compilations, each containing two episodes, by [[Victor Entertainment]] between July 25, 2001 and March 21, 2002.&lt;ref name=&quot;japrel&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.jvcmusic.co.jp/m-serve/tv/noir/dvd.html|title=｢ノワール｣ビデオカセット・DVD|trans_title='Noir' Videocassette・DVD|language=Japanese|publisher=[[Victor Entertainment]]|accessdate=September 30, 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt; After giving hints, announcements, and retractions for almost a year,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.animenewsnetwork.com/news/2002-04-20/acen-adv-acquisitions|title=ACEN - ADV Acquisitions|publisher=[[Anime News Network]]|date=April 20, 2002|accessdate=October 2, 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[ADV Films]] released the series in English in seven DVD compilations, the first containing five episodes, the others containing three or four episodes, between February 18 and October 28, 2003.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.amazon.com/dp/B00007KK2K/ |title=Noir - Shades of Darkness (Vol. 1)|publisher=[[Amazon.com]]|accessdate=September 30, 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.amazon.com/dp/B0000C9JET/ |title=Noir - End of the Matter (Vol. 7)|publisher=[[Amazon.com]]|accessdate=September 30, 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt; Prior to that, the first episode was included on the DVD insert of the January 2003 issue of ''[[Newtype USA]]''.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.projectnoir.com/news/press02.shtml|title=Sneak Preview in ''Newtype USA''!|publisher=[[ADV Films]]|work=Project Noir|accessdate=October 4, 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt;  As of November 1, 2010, the series is now licensed by [[Funimation Entertainment]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.animenewsnetwork.com/news/2010-11-03/funimation-adds-excel-saga-noir-bubblegum-crisis|title=Funimation Adds Excel Saga, Noir, Bubblegum Crisis|publisher= Anime News Network|date=2010-11-03}}&lt;/ref&gt;, which will re-release the series as a part of their Anime Classics line on August 9, 2011.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.rightstuf.com/1-800-338-6827/catalogmgr/vW9eFhCyGZGLosfFcj/browse/item/90811/4/0/0|title=Noir Complete Collection - Classic Line|publisher= Right Stuf.com|accessdate=2011-01-08}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The series makes use of two pieces of [[theme music]]. {{nihongo3||コッペリアの柩|&quot;Coppelia no Hitsugi&quot;|lit. &quot;Coppelia's Casket&quot;}} by ALI Project is used as opening theme, while {{nihongo3||きれいな感情|&quot;Kirei na Kanjo&quot;|lit. &quot;Beautiful Emotions&quot;}} by [[Akino Arai]] serves as ending theme.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite episode|title=黒き手の処女たち [Maidens with Black Hands]|episodelink=List of Noir episodes#ep01|series=Noir|network=[[TV Tokyo]]|airdate=April 6, 2001|number=1}}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Soundtrack ===
Like with many of studio Bee Train's other works, the entire ''Noir'' soundtrack was composed by the acclaimed [[Yuki Kajiura]], accompanied by primary vocalist Yuriko Kaida, secondary vocalist [[Yuri Kasahara]], and Kajiura's band [[See-Saw]].{{Citation needed|date=November 2009}}

[[Victor Entertainment]] published a single and three [[original soundtrack]] albums for the series. The single, {{nihongo3|lit. ''Coppelia's Casket''|コッペリアの柩|Kopperia no Hitsugi}} by [[Ali Project]], was published on May 23, 2001.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://ranking.oricon.co.jp/free_contents/search/detail.asp?itemcd=441668&amp;samecd=1|publisher=[[Oricon]]|accessdate=October 5, 2009|title=コッペリアの柩|trans_title=Kopperia no Hitsugi}}&lt;/ref&gt; The first and second soundtracks, called ''Noir: Original Soundtrack I'' and ''Noir: Original Soundtrack II'', were released on June 21 and October 3, 2001, respectively.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://ranking.oricon.co.jp/free_contents/search/detail.asp?itemcd=444820&amp;samecd=1|publisher=[[Oricon]]|accessdate=October 3, 2009|title=Noir Original Soundtrack I}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://ranking.oricon.co.jp/free_contents/search/detail.asp?itemcd=456567&amp;samecd=1|publisher=[[Oricon]]|accessdate=October 3, 2009|title=Noir Original Soundtrack II}}&lt;/ref&gt; The third soundtrack, called {{nihongo|''Blanc dans Noir''|〜黒の中の白〜|Kuro no Naka no Shiro|English: ''White in Black''}}, was released on November 7, 2001.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://ranking.oricon.co.jp/free_contents/search/detail.asp?itemcd=459955&amp;samecd=1|publisher=[[Oricon]]|accessdate=October 3, 2009|title=Noir Blanc dans Noir〜黒の中の白〜|trans_title=Noir: Blanc dans Noir: White in Black}}&lt;/ref&gt;

{{Track listing
| collapsed       = yes
| headline        = Kopperia no Hitsugi
| total_length    = 8:18
| title1          = Kopperia no Hitsugi
| note1           = {{nihongo3||コッペリアの柩|&quot;Coppélia's Casket&quot;}}
| length1         = 3:59
| title2          = Après le Noir
| length2         = 4:17
}}

{{Track listing
| collapsed       = yes
| headline        = Noir: Original Soundtrack I
| total_length    = 56:06
| title1          = Kopperia no Hitsugi
| note1           = {{nihongo3||コッペリアの柩|&quot;Coppélia's Casket&quot;}}, performed by [[Ali Project]], lyrics by Arika Hōno, composed by Mikiya Katakura
| length1         = 3:59
| title2          = Les Soldats
| length2         = 2:26
| title3          = Snow
| length3         = 2:11
| title4          = Canta per me
| length4         = 3:13
| title5          = Corsican Corridor
| length5         = 3:47
| title6          = Ode to Power
| length6         = 2:54
| title7          = Solitude by the Window
| length7         = 3:08
| title8          = Romance
| length8         = 3:43
| title9          = Silent Pain
| length9         = 2:01
| title10         = Lullaby
| length10        = 3:16
| title11         = Melodie
| length11        = 1:58
| title12         = Chloe
| length12        = 2:24
| title13         = Whispering Hills
| length13        = 3:32
| title14         = Zero Hour
| length14        = 2:36
| title15         = Liar You Lie
| length15        = 3:14
| title16         = Sorrow
| length16        = 2:41
| title17         = Salva Nos
| length17        = 4:29
| title18         = Kirei na Kanjou
| note18          = {{nihongo3||きれいな感情|&quot;Beautiful Emotions&quot;}}, vocals, lyrics, and composition by [[Akino Arai]], arranged by Hokari Hisaaki
| length18        = 4:16
}}

{{Track listing
| collapsed       = yes
| headline        = Noir: Original Soundtrack II
| extra_column    =
| total_length    = 59:03
| title1          = Le Grand Retour
| length1         = 6:24
| title2          = Secret Game
| note2           = vocals by [[Yuri Kasahara]]
| length2         = 3:44
| title3          = Fake Garden
| length3         = 2:01
| title4          = Les Soldats II
| length4         = 3:27
| title5          = In Memory of You
| length5         = 3:54
| title6          = Colosseum
| length6         = 3:46
| title7          = Salva Nos II
| length7         = 2:46
| title8          = Maze
| note8           = vocals by [[Yuri Kasahara]]
| length8         = 2:14
| title9          = In Peace
| length9         = 2:27
| title10         = Despair
| length10        = 1:58
| title11         = Power Hungry
| length11        = 2:16
| title12         = Black Is Black
| length12        = 2:42
| title13         = Canta per me II
| length13        = 3:21
| title14         = At Dusk
| length14        = 1:51
| title15         = Premonition
| length15        = 3:18
| title16         = Killing
| length16        = 2:56
| title17         = A Farewell Song
| length17        = 3:34
| title18         = Kirei na Kanjou - Piano Version
| note18          = {{nihongo3||きれいな感情-piano ver.|&quot;Beautiful Emotions&quot; - Piano Version}}, composed by Akino Arai
| length18        = 1:46
| title19         = Indio
| note19          = vocals by Chikai
| length19        = 6:25
}}

{{Track listing
| collapsed       = yes
| headline        = Blanc dans Noir (CD 1)
| total_length    = 36:54
| title1          = Aka to Kuro
| note1           = {{nihongo3||赤と黒|&quot;Red and Black&quot;}}, vocals by ALI Project, lyrics by Arica Hōno, composed by Mikiya Katakura
| length1         = 4:52
| title2          = Prelude
| length2         = 0:56
| title3          = Canta per me - Japanese Version
| note3           = vocals by [[Kirika Yuumura]] ([[Hōko Kuwashima]])
| length3         = 3:15
| title4          = Lullaby - Japanese Version
| note4           = vocals by [[Altena (Noir)|Altena]] ([[Tarako]])
| length4         = 3:16
| title5          = Em More
| note5           = {{nihongo3||エム・モア|Emu Moa}}, vocals by Kirika Yuumura (Hōko Kuwashima), lyrics by Kenzo Saeki, composed by Hirofumi Asamoto
| length5         = 4:17
| title6          = Himitsu
| note6           = {{nihongo3||秘密|&quot;Secret&quot;}}, vocals by [[Chloe (Noir)|Chloe]] ([[Aya Hisakawa]])
| length6         = 5:03
| title7          = Salva Nos - Dialogue Remix
| note7           = vocals by Yuriko Kaida and [[Mireille Bouquet]] ([[Kotono Mitsuishi]])
| length7         = 4:26
| title8          = Love
| note8           = vocals by Chiaki
| length8         = 4:59
| title9          = Gensou Rakuen
| note9           = {{nihongo3||幻想楽園|&quot;Garden of Illusion&quot;}}
| length9         = 5:41
}}

{{Track listing
| collapsed       = yes
| headline        = Blanc dans Noir (CD 2)
| extra_column    =
| total_length    = 18:02
| title1          = Guest B
| length1         = 1:04
| title2          = Melodie - Salva Nos Version
| length2         = 3:03
| title3          = Jealousy
| length3         = 2:52
| title4          = At Dawn
| length4         = 1:37
| title5          = Black Society
| length5         = 2:45
| title6          = Family Affection
| length6         = 2:52
| title7          = Church
| length7         = 1:51
| title8          = At Ease
| length8         = 1:50
}}

==Live-Action Remake==
A possible live action feature based on the anime series has been planned for development by the cable television network [[Starz (TV channel)|Starz]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.hollywoodreporter.com/blogs/live-feed/starz-nabs-assassin-project-sam-44664|title=Starz Nabs Assassin Project From Sam Raimi|publisher= [[The Hollywood Reporter]]|date=2010-11-11|accessdate=2010-11-12}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Sam Raimi]] and [[Rob Tapert]] (''[[Xena: Warrior Princess]], [[Legend of the Seeker]]'') are the executive producers for the project. [[Stephen Lightfoot]] will also serve as executive producer and writer.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.animenewsnetwork.com/news/2010-11-11/starz-develops-live-action-tv-remake-of-noir-anime|title=Starz Develops Live-Action Remake of Noir Anime|publisher= Anime News Network|date=2010-11-11|accessdate=2010-11-12}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In June 2011, Starz gave a greenlight to the show with a straight to series order. The number of episodes of the first season has yet to be determined, though some speculated it will likely be in the 8-13 episode range.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url = http://www.animenewsnetwork.com/news/2011-06-18/live-action-noir-tv-series-green-lit-at-starz | title = ''Noir'' Anime Gets Live-Action TV Series Green-Lit at Starz | publisher = Anime News Network | date = June 18, 2011 | accessdate = June 18, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Reception==
{{Expand section|date=May 2008}}
The ''[[Newtype Magazine]]'' ranked ''Noir'' second in its top 10 list of anime of the year 2001.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.animenewsnetwork.com/news/2001-08-12/newtype-top-10-anime|title=Newtype top 10 Anime|accessdate=December 24, 2007|publisher=[[Anime News Network]]}}&lt;/ref&gt; ''Noir'' also made a top three place in the top 20 anime in Japan chart by [http://east.sakura.ne.jp/aniba/ ''Anihabara!''] in October 2001.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.animenewsnetwork.com/news/2001-10-29/top-anime-in-japan|title=Top Anime in Japan|publisher=[[Anime News Network]]|date=October 29, 2001|accessdate=October 2, 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt; In the June 2002 issue of ''[[Animage]]'', ''Noir'' was voted by the magazine's readers onto a shared 10th place in the best 20 new anime of 2001 in Japan.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.animenewsnetwork.com/news/2002-05-10/june-animage-ranks-anime|title=June Animage Ranks Anime|publisher=[[Anime News Network]]|date=May 10, 2002|accessdate=October 2, 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Josh Mohs of [[Active Anime]] comments that &quot;''Noir'' doesn't fail to deliver mystery, action, and drama.&quot; Though he laments &quot;some pacing problems, especially towards the beginning of the series,&quot; he lauds the character interactions as well as the series' &quot;job of tying together all its inherent sub-plots&quot; and the director's &quot;bold move&quot; in leaving &quot;the ending open to viewer interpretation.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;Mohs&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.activeanime.com/html/content/view/3636/57/|title=Noir Complete Series|accessdate=September 30, 2009|publisher=[[Active Anime]]|first=Josh|last=Mohs|date=July 29, 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt; In a review of the first DVD compilation by [[ADV Films]], Jeremy Conrad of [[IGN]] lauded the series for being &quot;stylistic&quot;, stating that &quot;It oozes style&quot;, and for its &quot;extremely cool&quot; fight choreography and &quot;great&quot; shootouts, saying that &quot;What ''Noir'' does right is its action.&quot; He also noted the series' character design as being &quot;solid&quot; and the series' soundtrack as being &quot;excellent&quot;, reminiscent of &quot;[[Eric Serra]]'s stuff in movies such as ''[[Nikita (film)|La Femme Nikita]]''&quot;, but lamented about the slowed pace at the end of the volume, stating that &quot;some of the story stuff they were trying to do [in the fourth and fifth episodes] was snooze inducing.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://uk.dvd.ign.com/articles/382/382548p1.html|title=Noir - Shades of Darkness|publisher=[[IGN]]|accessdate=October 1, 2009|first=Jeremy|last=Conrad|date=January 13, 2003}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Josh Mohs of [[Active Anime]] comments that ''Noir'''s &quot;strong character interactions are usually enough to pull you through&quot; the pacing problems he saw with the series and further states that, along with the series' &quot;unique twists&quot;, the &quot;intriguing character dynamic definitely elevate[s] it above the rest of the competition.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;Mohs&quot;/&gt;

Kirika had been voted with Mireille as two of the top ten female anime characters by [[Newtype (magazine)|Newtype Japan]] in 2001.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.animenewsnetwork.com/news/2001-08-12/newtype-top-10-anime Newtype top 10 Anime - Anime News Network&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Anime News Network]]'s Theron Martin, ten years after the show's original run, commented that ''Noir'' &quot;was at least to some degree an influential title&quot; and &quot;is still recognized as one of the preeminent titles of its type because it redefined what a 'girls with guns' title could be.&quot; He went on to praise the show for its &quot;sleek, elegant story&quot; and called it &quot;anime's most pronounced homage to classic film noir&quot;. He named Mireille and Kiraka &quot;one of anime's most iconic female teams&quot; along with the ''[[Dirty Pair]]'' and credited Kirika as &quot;a precursor of the [[Moe (slang)|moe]] craze that came along later in the decade.&quot; He named &quot;The Lost Kitten&quot; as the series' episode with the best story content, and the double episode &quot;The Intoccabile&quot; as having the worst, noting its &quot;hackneyed look into the Cosa Nostra&quot;. He lamented repetitiveness in action sequences and excessive reuse of scenes especially in early episodes as well as the absence of blood in light of the show's high body count. He showed himself unimpressed with the animation quality, but lauded the show's good looks, in particular those of the environments. He named the &quot;tendency for repetitiveness&quot; of its first half as the soundtrack's &quot;only real flaw&quot; and praised the pieces &quot;Salva Nos&quot; and &quot;Canta Per Me&quot; as &quot;stand[ing] among the all-time great anime themes&quot;. About the English version, he commented that the &quot;casting choices fit and match up well against the original performances&quot; and that the &quot;script stays tight enough to avoid garnering any accuracy complaints&quot;. In conclusion, he said &quot;the series works in the ways that it is supposed to work and should keep viewers thoroughly involved through to the end.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.animenewsnetwork.com/review/noir/dvd-complete-collection-classic-line|title=Noir DVD – Review|publisher=[[Anime News Network]]|date=September 21, 2011|author=Theron, Martin|accessdate=September 22, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Notes ==
&lt;references group=&quot;n&quot;/&gt;

== References ==
{{reflist|2}}

*{{cite video|date=June 24, 2003|title=Noir: Death Warrant|medium=DVD|publisher=[[ADV Films]]|oclc=52850346|ref=endnote_4}}&lt;!--contains episodes 13-16--&gt;

==External links==
{{wikiquote|Noir}}
* [http://www.jvcmusic.co.jp/m-serve/tv/noir/ Official website] of [[JVC]] {{ja icon}}
* [http://www.funimation.com/noir Official website] of [[Funimation Entertainment]]
* [http://www.projectnoir.com/ Official website] of [[ADV Films]]
* {{tv.com|14979|Noir}}
* {{imdb title|0294154|Noir}}
* {{ann|type=anime|id=407|title=Noir|noparen=true}}

{{Bee Train}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Noir (Anime)}}
[[Category:Noir (anime)| ]]
[[Category:2001 television series debuts]]
[[Category:2001 television series endings]]
[[Category:ADV Films]]
[[Category:Action anime and manga]]
[[Category:Crime anime and manga]]
[[Category:Funimation Entertainment]]
[[Category:Mystery anime and manga]]
[[Category:Neo-noir]]
[[Category:Anime of 2001]]
[[Category:Anime with original screenplays]]
[[Category:Bee Train]]

[[de:Noir (Anime)]]
[[es:Noir (anime)]]
[[fa:نوآر (انیمه)]]
[[fr:Noir (anime)]]
[[hr:Noir (anime)]]
[[it:Noir (anime)]]
[[kk:Noir]]
[[ja:NOIR]]
[[pl:Noir (anime)]]
[[pt:Noir (anime)]]
[[ru:Нуар (аниме)]]
[[fi:Noir]]
[[sv:Noir (anime)]]
[[tr:Noir]]
[[vi:Noir (anime)]]
[[zh:NOIR]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
