<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="16402043" ns="0" title="MediaImpact Media Center"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Orphan|date=February 2009}}
{{Infobox_Company
| company_name  = MediaImpact
| company_type  = [[Private company]]
| foundation    = 2007
| location      = [[Louisville, Kentucky]], USA
| industry      = Digital/ Audio Entertainment
| products      = MediaImpact Media Centers
| homepage      = [http://www.mediaimpactlive.com www.mediaimpactlive.com]

}}

The '''MediaImpact Media Center''' is a variety of systems designed to store, manage, and access all forms of digital media in the home. Based on [[MythTV]] software, it provides user managed libraries for music, photos, and all forms of video from recorded television programs to DVDs.










== Features ==

MI Media Centers are available in three models: the MC150, MC500, MCDT, and MCR.  These systems are built on the [[Linux]] OS [[Ubuntu (operating system)|Ubuntu]].  All models (except for the MCR which is a receiver only) are configured with [[Hauppauge Computer Works|Hauppauge]] analog tuners and PcHDTV digital tuners.  With the use of a home network the media centers can communicate with each other and share recordings, videos, music, and photos.

MI Media Centers are offered with full high definition television [[HDTV]] capabilities.  Being considered a home theater appliance, the traditional [[Home theater PC|media center]] system tag cannot be applied.



== History ==

In 2002, Isaac Richards began a project to build a new type of [[Home theater PC|Media Center]].  Hence, [[MythTV]] was born.  Being built on the [[Linux]] OS made it very difficult for the average user to configure so, the spread of [[MythTV]] has been limited.   This has made way for the emergence of companies capable of producing and selling pre-configured systems that are user friendly and only charge for parts, labor, and support.  I chose the MediaImpact Media Center because it does not require you to have a keyboard or mouse.  Everything can be done from the remote control.

[[Category:Companies established in 2007]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
