<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="16458225" ns="0" title="Shadow banking system"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Financial market participants}}

The '''shadow banking system''' is the infrastructure and practices which support financial transactions that occur beyond the reach of existing state sanctioned monitoring and regulation. It includes entities such as [[hedge funds]], [[money market funds]] and [[Structured investment vehicle]]s.  Investment banks may conduct much of their business in the shadow banking system (''SBS''), but they are not SBS institutions themselves. The core activities of investment banks are subject to regulation and monitoring by central banks and other government institutions - but it has been common practice for investment banks to conduct many of their transactions in ways that dont show up on their conventional balance sheet accounting and so are not visible to regulators.

The volume of transactions in the shadow banking system grew dramatically after the year 2000. By late 2007 the size of the SBS in the U.S. exceeded $10,000 billion.  By late 2009  the SBS had shrunk to under $6,000bn due to increased regulation, changes in business practice,  and pressure from investors who in some cases no longer wanted their funds to be used in the shadow banking system.


==Entities that make up the system==
Shadow institutions do not accept deposits like a depository bank and therefore are not subject to the same regulations.  Complex legal entities comprising the system include [[hedge funds]], [[structured investment vehicle|SIV]]s, [[Special purpose entity|conduits]], [[money fund]]s,  and other [[non-bank financial institution]]s.

Shadow banking institutions are typically intermediaries between investors and borrowers. For example, an [[institutional investor]] like a [[pension fund]] may be willing to lend money, while a corporation may be searching for funds to borrow. The shadow banking institution will channel funds from the investor(s) to the corporation, profiting either from fees or from the difference in interest rates between what it pays the investor(s) and what it receives from the borrower.

==Importance==

Many &quot;shadow bank&quot; like institutions and vehicles have emerged in American and European markets, between the years 2000 and 2008, and have come to play an important role in providing credit across the global financial system.&lt;ref name=&quot;ft.com&quot;&gt;[http://www.ft.com/cms/s/0/42827c50-abfd-11dc-82f0-0000779fd2ac.html?nclick_check=1 Out of the shadows: How banking’s secret system broke down] By Gillian Tett and Paul J Davies,December 16 2007 18:33 &lt;/ref&gt;

In a June 2008 speech, U.S. Treasury Secretary [[Timothy Geithner]], then President and CEO of the NY Federal Reserve Bank, described the growing importance of the shadow banking system: &quot;In early 2007, asset-backed commercial paper conduits, in structured investment vehicles, in auction-rate preferred securities, tender option bonds and variable rate demand notes, had a combined asset size of roughly $2.2 trillion. Assets financed overnight in triparty repo grew to $2.5 trillion. Assets held in hedge funds grew to roughly $1.8 trillion. The combined balance sheets of the then five major investment banks totaled $4 trillion. In comparison, the total assets of the top five bank holding companies in the United States at that point were just over $6 trillion, and total assets of the entire banking system were about $10 trillion.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;GeithnerSpeechReducing&quot;&gt;[http://www.newyorkfed.org/newsevents/speeches/2008/tfg080609.html Geithner-Speech Reducing Systemic Risk in a Dynamic Financial System]&lt;/ref&gt; In other words, lending through the shadow banking system slightly exceeded lending via the traditional banking system based on outstanding balances.

==Risks or vulnerability==
[[File:Securitization Market Activity.png|thumb|350px|right|Securitization markets were impaired during the crisis]]
Shadow institutions are not subject to the same prudential regulations as depository banks, so that they do not have to keep as high financial reserves relative to their exposure. Thus they can have a very high level of [[financial leverage]], with a high ratio of debt relative to the liquid assets available to pay immediate claims. High leverage magnifies profits during boom periods and losses during downturns.

Shadow institutions like ''SIVs'' and ''conduits'', typically controlled by investment banks, borrowed from investors in short-term, liquid markets (such as the [[money market]] and [[commercial paper]] markets), so that they would have to repay and borrow again from these investors at frequent intervals. On the other hand, they used the funds to lend to corporations or to invest in longer-term, less liquid (i.e. harder to sell) assets. In many cases, the long-term assets purchased were [[mortgage-backed securities]], sometimes called &quot;toxic assets&quot; or &quot;legacy assets&quot; in the press. These assets declined significantly in value as housing prices declined and foreclosures increased during 2007-2009. 

In the case of investment banks, this reliance on short-term financing required them to return frequently to investors in the [[capital markets]] to refinance their operations. When the housing market began to deteriorate and their ability to obtain funds from investors through investments such as [[mortgage-backed securities]] declined, these investment banks could not refinance themselves. Investor refusal or inability to provide funds via the short-term markets was a primary cause of the failure of [[Bear Stearns]] and [[Lehman Brothers]] during 2008.

In technical terms, these institutions are subject to market risk, [[credit risk]] and especially [[liquidity risk]], since their liabilities are short term while their assets are more long term and illiquid. This creates a problem, as they are not depositary institutions and do not have direct or indirect access to the support of their central bank in its role as [[lender of last resort]]. Therefore, during periods of market illiquidity, they could go bankrupt if unable to refinance their short-term liabilities. They were also highly leveraged. This meant that disruptions in credit markets would make them subject to rapid deleveraging, meaning they would have to pay off their debts by selling their long-term assets. 
&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.ft.com/cms/s/0/622acc9e-87f1-11dd-b114-0000779fd18c.html FT Roubini - The Shadow Banking System is Unraveling]&lt;/ref&gt;

The securitization markets frequently tapped by the shadow banking system started to close down in the spring of 2007 and nearly shut down in the fall of 2008. More than a third of the private credit markets thus became unavailable as a source of funds.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|author= |url=http://www.city-journal.org/2009/19_1_credit.html |title=Nicole Gelinas-Can the Fed's Uncrunch Credit? |publisher=City-journal.org |date= |accessdate=2009-02-27}}&lt;/ref&gt; In February 2009, [[Ben Bernanke]] stated that securitization markets remained effectively shut, with the exception of conforming mortgages, which could be sold to [[Fannie Mae]] and [[Freddie Mac]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|author= |url=http://www.federalreserve.gov/newsevents/testimony/bernanke20090224a.htm|title=Bernanke|date= |accessdate=2009-02-24}}&lt;/ref&gt;

U.S. Treasury Secretary [[Timothy Geithner]] stated that the &quot;combined effect of these factors was a financial system vulnerable to self-reinforcing asset price and credit cycles.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;GeithnerSpeechReducing&quot; /&gt;

==History==

The term &quot;shadow banking system&quot; is attributed to [[Paul McCulley]] of [[PIMCO]], who coined it at the 2007 [[Jackson Hole]] conference, where he defined it as &quot;the whole alphabet soup of levered up non-bank investment conduits, vehicles, and structures.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.pimco.com/LeftNav/Featured+Market+Commentary/FF/2007/GCBF+August-+September+2007.htm Teton Reflections], by [[Paul McCulley]], August/September 2007&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://money.cnn.com/2007/11/27/news/newsmakers/gross_banking.fortune/ Beware our shadow banking system, Bill Gross, November 28 2007]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.pimco.com/LeftNav/Featured+Market+Commentary/FF/2009/Global+Central+Bank+Focus+April+2009+Money+Marketeers+Solitaire+McCulley.htm Comments Before the Money Marketeers Club: ''Playing Solitaire with a Deck of 51, with Number 52 on Offer''], [[Paul McCulley]]&lt;/ref&gt; McCulley identifies the birth of the shadow banking system with the development of [[money market fund]]s in the 1970s – money market accounts function largely as bank deposits, but money market funds are not regulated as banks.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.pimco.com/LeftNav/Featured+Market+Commentary/FF/2010/Global+Central+Bank+Focus+May+2010+After+the+Crisis+Planning+a+New+Financial+Structure.htm After the Crisis: Planning a New Financial Structure: ''Learning from the Bank of Dad''] [[Paul McCulley]], May 2010&lt;/ref&gt;

The concept of credit growth by unregulated institutions, though not the term &quot;shadow banking system&quot;, date at least to [http://mises.org/books/hayekcollection.pdf Prices and Production], by [[Friedrich Hayek]], 1935, in which he states:

{{quote|There can be no doubt that besides the regular types of the circulating medium, such as coin, notes and bank deposits, which are generally recognised to be money or currency, and the quantity of which is regulated by some central authority or can at least be imagined to be so regulated, there exist still other forms of media of exchange which occasionally or permanently do the service of money....

The characteristic peculiarity of these forms of credit is that they spring up without being subject to any central control, but once they have come into existence their convertibility into other forms of money must be possible if a collapse of credit is to be avoided.&lt;ref&gt;[http://zerohedge.blogspot.com/2009/05/chasing-shadow-of-money.html Chasing The Shadow Of Money], May 17, 2009, Zero Hedge&lt;/ref&gt;}}

The full extent of the shadow banking system was not widely recognised until work was published in 2010 by Manmohan Singh and James Aitken of the [[International Monetary Fund]], showing that when the role of [[Rehypothecation]] was considered, the U.S. SBS  had grown to over $10 trillion, about twice as much as previous estimates. &lt;ref name = &quot;IMFpaper&quot;&gt;
{{cite web 
|url=http://www.imf.org/external/pubs/ft/wp/2010/wp10172.pdf
|title= The (sizable) Role of Rehypothecation in the Shadow Banking System
|author= Manmohan Singh and James Aitken
|publisher=[[International Monetary Fund]]
|accessdate= 2010-08-31
|date = 2010-07-01
}}
&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name = &quot;Gill&quot;&gt;{{cite web 
 |url= http://www.ft.com/cms/s/0/112ff210-a62b-11df-9cb9-00144feabdc0.html
 |title= Web of shadow banking must be unravelled
 |publisher= [[The Financial Times]] 
 |author= [[Gillian Tett]]
 |date = 2010-08-12
 |accessdate=2010-08-31}} 
&lt;/ref&gt; 

=== Examples ===
During 1998, hedge fund [[Long-term Capital Management]] failed and was bailed out by several major banks at the request of the government, which was concerned about possible damage to the broader financial system. It was highly leveraged and unregulated.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book | title = [[When Genius Failed: The Rise and Fall of Long-Term Capital Management]] | last = Lowenstein | first = Roger | year = 2000 | isbn = 0-375-50317-X | publisher = Random House | postscript = .}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Structured investment vehicles (SIVs) first came to public attention at the time of the [[Enron scandal]]. Since then, their use has become widespread in the financial world. In the years leading up to the crisis, the top four U.S. depository banks moved an estimated $5.2 trillion in assets and liabilities [[off-balance sheet|off their balance sheets]] into [[special purpose entity|special purpose vehicles]] or similar entities. This enabled them to bypass regulatory requirements for minimum capital ratios, thereby increasing leverage and profits during the boom but increasing losses during the crisis. New accounting guidance was planned to require them to put some of these assets back onto their books during 2009, with the effect of reducing their capital ratios. One news agency estimated the amount of assets to be transferred at between $500 billion and $1 trillion. This transfer was considered as part of the stress tests performed by the government during 2009.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.bloomberg.com/apps/news?pid=20601039&amp;sid=akv_p6LBNIdw&amp;refer=home Bloomberg-Banks $1 trillion purge]&lt;/ref&gt;

The shadow banking system also conducts an enormous amount of trading activity in the [[Over the counter (finance)|OTC]] derivatives market, which grew rapidly in the decade up to the 2008 financial crisis, reaching over US$650 trillion in notional contracts traded (see the Bank for International Settlements (BIS.org) bi-annual report). This rapid growth mainly arose from credit derivatives. In particular these included:
*[[collateralised debt obligation]]s (CDO)
*interest rate obligations derived from bundles of mortgage securities
* a variety of customized or synthetic innovations on the CDO model; and
*[[credit default swaps]] (CDS), a form of quasi-insurance against the default risk inherent in the assets underlying the CDO).

The market in CDS, for example, was insignificant in 2004 but rose to over $60 trillion in a few short years&lt;ref&gt;BIS.org&lt;/ref&gt;. Because credit default swaps were not regulated as insurance contracts, companies selling them were not required to maintain sufficient capital reserves to pay potential claims. Demands for settlement of hundreds of billions of dollars of credit default swaps contracts issued by [[American International Group|AIG]], the largest [[insurance company]] in the world, led to its financial collapse. Despite the prevalence and volume of this activity, it attracted little outside attention before 2007, and much of it was off the balance sheets of the contracting parties' affiliated banks. The uncertainty this created among counterparties  contributed to the deterioration of credit conditions.

Since then the shadow banking system has been blamed&lt;ref name=&quot;ft.com&quot;/&gt; for aggravating the [[subprime mortgage crisis]] and helping to transform it into a global [[credit crunch]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.newleftreview.org/?getpdf=NLR28403&amp;pdflang=en Blackburn - Subprime Crisis]&lt;/ref&gt;

==Contribution to the 2007–2010 financial crisis==
The shadow banking system has been implicated as significantly contributing to the [[financial crisis of 2007–2010]].&lt;ref&gt;Harvey, David (2010). ''The Enigma of Capital: And the Crises of Capitalism''. Oxford: [[Oxford University Press]]. ISBN: 978-0-19-975871-5 &lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[[Gary Gorton|Gorton, Gary]], ''Slapped by the Invisible Hand: The Panic of 2007'' (2010) ISBN 978-0-19973415-3&lt;/ref&gt; In a June 2008 speech, U.S. Treasury Secretary [[Timothy Geithner]], then President and CEO of the NY Federal Reserve Bank, placed significant blame for the freezing of credit markets on a &quot;run&quot; on the entities in the shadow banking system by their counterparties. The rapid increase of the dependency of bank and non-bank financial institutions on the use of these off-balance sheet entities to fund investment strategies had made them critical to the credit markets underpinning the financial system as a whole, despite their existence in the shadows, outside of the regulatory controls governing commercial banking activity. Furthermore, these entities were vulnerable because they borrowed short-term in liquid markets to purchase long-term, illiquid and risky assets. This meant that disruptions in credit markets would make them subject to rapid deleveraging, selling their long-term assets at depressed prices.&lt;ref name=&quot;GeithnerSpeechReducing&quot; /&gt;

Economist [[Paul Krugman]] described the run on the shadow banking system as the &quot;core of what happened&quot; to cause the crisis. &quot;As the shadow banking system expanded to rival or even surpass conventional banking in importance, politicians and government officials should have realized that they were re-creating the kind of financial vulnerability that made the [[Great Depression]] possible—and they should have responded by extending regulations and the financial safety net to cover these new institutions. Influential figures should have proclaimed a simple rule: anything that does what a bank does, anything that has to be rescued in crises the way banks are, should be regulated like a bank.&quot; He referred to this lack of controls as &quot;malign neglect.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book 
| last = Krugman 
| first = Paul 
| year = 2009 
| title = The Return of Depression Economics and the Crisis of 2008 | publisher = W.W. Norton Company Limited 
| isbn = 978-0-393-07101-6}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==See also==
*[[Long-term Capital Management]]
*[[Recession]]
*[[Structured investment vehicle]]
*[[Subprime mortgage crisis]]
*[[Subprime crisis background information]]
*[[Subprime mortgage crisis solutions debate]]

{{2008 economic crisis}}

==References==
{{reflist}}

[[Category:Finance]]
[[Category:United States housing bubble]]

[[de:Schattenbank]]
[[fr:Finance de l'ombre]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
