<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><redirects><r from="Microsoft Binder" to="Microsoft Office shared tools" tofragment="Microsoft Binder" /></redirects><pages><page pageid="32804579" ns="0" title="Microsoft Office shared tools"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{multiple issues|cleanup=August 2011|copyedit=August 2011|linkrot=August 2011|refimprove = August 2011}}

'''Microsoft Office shared tools''' are software components that are (or were) included in all [[Microsoft Office]] products.

== Clip Organizer ==
'''Microsoft Clip Organizer''' is [[Microsoft]]'s [[clip art]] organizing software to find drawings, photographs, sounds, videos, and other media clips with presentations, publications, and other Office documents. It is also comes with a variety of stock media clips and offers more selection on the [[Microsoft Office Online]] website as well.

== Graph ==
'''Microsoft Graph''' (also known as '''Microsoft Chart''') is an [[Object Linking and Embedding|OLE]] application that is deployed by a number of the [[Microsoft Office]] programs such as [[Microsoft Excel|Excel]] and [[Microsoft Access|Access]] to create charts and graphs. The program can also be hosted as an OLE application object in [[Visual Basic]]. Microsoft Graph supports many different types of charts, however, it is a legacy application and the charts produced are not modern-looking and polished. Office 2003 was the last version to use Microsoft Graph for hosting charts inside Office applications as OLE objects. [[Office 2007]], specifically, Excel 2007 includes a new integrated high-quality charting engine and the charts created are native to the applications. The new engine supports advanced formatting, including 3D rendering, transparencies and shadows. Chart layouts can also be customized to highlight various trends in the data. Microsoft Graph still exists for compatibility reasons, but the entry points are removed.

===History===
The first software sold, under the name Microsoft Chart, was an attempt from Microsoft to compete with the successful [[Lotus 1-2-3]] by adding a companion to Microsoft [[Multiplan]], the company's spreadsheet in the early 1980s. 

Ms/Chart shared with Multiplan the box design and the two lines menu at the bottom of the screen, and could import Multiplan data. The simple graphs (pies, bars, lines) were drawn on the screen by switching the display mode of the [[IBM PC]] Compatibles to graphics (which was not available to entry level models), or could be printed on some dot matrix devices.

The main drawback of the Microsoft solution at this time was the necessity to quit the spreadsheet and then load Ms/Chart to compose and draw a graph, as [[MS/DOS]] was not a multitasking operating system. Thus, Lotus 1-2-3 maintained its market share until the release of [[Microsoft Excel]] by Microsoft.

In the early 1990s, Microsoft Chart was renamed to Microsoft Graph.

== Equation Editor ==
'''Equation Editor''' is a [[formula editor]] developed by [[Design Science (company)|Design Science]] that allows users to construct math and science equations in a [[WYSIWYG]] environment. Equation Editor was developed by Design Science and is included in [[Microsoft Office]]  and several other commercial applications. It is a simplified version of Design Science [[MathType]]. It can be used as a standalone program or it can also be used from within applications that support [[Object Linking and Embedding|OLE]] as an embedded object. Its feature set has not changed significantly since its introduction in Word for Windows, version 2.0.

In certain [[Microsoft Office 2007]] applications (including Word), and in all [[Microsoft Office 2010]] applications, Equation Editor is no longer the default method of creating equations, and is kept for compatibility with old documents only.&lt;ref&gt;http://office.microsoft.com/en-us/word-help/where-is-equation-editor-HA101988786.aspx&lt;/ref&gt; Instead, a reengineered equation editor is included, which is built into the document-editing part of the interface rather than being operated through a separate dialog and being treated as an [[Object Linking and Embedding|OLE]] object in the document.&lt;ref&gt;[http://blogs.msdn.com/murrays/archive/2006/09/13/752206.aspx High-quality editing and display of mathematical text in Office 2007]&lt;/ref&gt;

== Picture Manager ==
{{Main|Microsoft Office Picture Manager}}

== WordArt ==
[[File:WordArt styles.PNG|thumb|The formatting effects as seen in Office 2010 and 2007]]
'''WordArt''' is a text-styling feature that is available in the Microsoft Office suite of products. It allows users to create stylized text with various &quot;special effects&quot; such as textures, outlines, and many other manipulations that are not available through the standard font formatting. For example, one can create shadows, rotate, &quot;bend&quot; and &quot;stretch&quot; the shape of the text.  WordArt is  available in 30 different preset styles on [[Microsoft Word]], however, it is fully customisable using the tools available on the WordArt toolbar and Drawing toolbar, or on the WordArt tools tab on [[Microsoft Office 2007]] and [[Microsoft Office 2010]]. It is also available in [[Microsoft Excel]], [[Microsoft PowerPoint]] and [[Microsoft Publisher]]. WordArt in Microsoft Office 2010, users can apply formatting effects such as shadow, bevel, glow, gradient glow, and reflection to their text. 

In Office 2007, WordArt was given a complete overhaul in Microsoft Excel and Microsoft PowerPoint, with new styles, new effects and the ability to apply WordArt to regular text boxes. The new styles have been included in Microsoft Word 2010. As well as this, Office 2010 includes the new PowerPoint &amp; Excel styles in Microsoft Word, replacing the old versions.

== Discontinued ==
=== Microsoft Binder ===
'''Microsoft Binder''' was an application originally included with [[Microsoft Office 95]], [[Microsoft Office 97|97]] and [[Microsoft Office 2000|2000]] designed to allow users to include several different types of [[Object Linking and Embedding|OLE 2.0]] objects (e.g., [[Microsoft Word]] documents, [[Microsoft Excel]] spreadsheets, and [[Microsoft PowerPoint]] presentations) integrated in one file. Originally a test host for OLE 2.0, it was not widely used, and was discontinued after Office 2000.

The [[filename extension]] for Microsoft Binder files was .OBD, and the Office binder template format was .OBT. A Microsoft Office Binder Wizard used the extension .OBZ.

Binder files can still be opened in later versions of Microsoft Office up until version 2003, with the Microsoft Binder Support add-in, called Unbind which can be installed through the Add and Remove programs menu, by selecting Microsoft Office, click change, add it and update. According to Microsoft, Unbind is not included with Office 2007. However, Office 97 Unbind is available for download from the Microsoft website.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.microsoft.com/downloads/details.aspx?FamilyID=bb8ef813-80e3-493f-a914-7add36d84b8a&amp;displaylang=en Office 97 Unbind]&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Microsoft Data Analyzer ===
'''Microsoft Data Analyzer''' 2002 was a data analysis software for [[Microsoft Office XP]]. Microsoft originally purchased the software as part of an acquisition of the intellectual property of Maximal Innovative Intelligence - Maximal had a product called &quot;Max&quot; which was rebranded as Microsoft Data Analyzer. The developers behind Microsoft Data Analyzer have been working in Office since the acquisition and are currently working on [[Excel Services]]&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.pcmag.com/article2/0,1895,21272,00.asp]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.windowsmarketplace.com/details.aspx?itemid=250911]&lt;/ref&gt; Even though it was a stand alone application and was not available in any Office XP bundle, it was a part of the Office XP suite. However, it was not updated beyond version 3.5.&lt;ref&gt;[http://office.microsoft.com/en-us/downloads/CD010225721033.aspx]&lt;/ref&gt;

Microsoft Data Analyzer allows analyzing and visualizing data and data trends, and is integrated with [[SQL Server Analysis Services]]. Reports and graphs generated could be saved as HTML, Microsoft Excel or Microsoft PowerPoint files.

=== Microsoft Office Document Imaging ===
{{Main|Microsoft Office Document Imaging}}

=== Microsoft Office Document Scanning ===
'''Microsoft Office Document Scanning''' (''MODS'') is a scanning and [[Optical character recognition]] (OCR) software application introduced first in Office XP.  The OCR engine is based upon Nuance's OmniPage.  Microsoft Office Document Scanning is suited for creating archival copies of documents.

Microsoft Office Document Scanning is closely tied with [[Microsoft Office Document Imaging]], the application that manipulates [[Microsoft Document Imaging Format]] (MDI) files. The application can also create [[TIFF]] files.

Notably, this application can also embed OCR data into both MDI and TIFF files. This enables some sort of automated text searchability on the files, which is integrated into the Windows shell Search function.

Microsoft Office Document Scanning, like Office Document Imaging is no longer available in [[Office 2010]].

=== Office Assistant ===
{{Main|Office Assistant}}

=== Microsoft PhotoDraw ===
{{Main|Microsoft PhotoDraw}}

=== Microsoft Photo Editor ===
{{Main|Microsoft Photo Editor}}

=== Office Web Components ===
'''Office Web Components''' (OWC) are a group of [[Object Linking and Embedding]] (OLE) components (allows embedding and linking to documents) implemented as [[ActiveX control]] in Microsoft Office 2000, Office XP and Office 2003. These ActiveX Controls can be plugged into web pages, [[Visual Basic]] and [[Visual Basic for Applications]] (VBA) forms, [[Windows Forms]] or programmed in-memory. The OWC can be used by any COM-compliant [[Component Object Model]] programming language. Applications like Microsoft Excel, [[Microsoft Access]] and [[Microsoft FrontPage]] allowed creating interactive web pages using Office Web Components.

The following components are included:
* Spreadsheet
* Chartspace
* Pivot table
* Data source component

The Office Web Components have been discontinued in [[Office 2007]], and are not included, except as a part of Office Project Server 2007.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
  |url=http://blogs.msdn.com/excel/archive/2006/07/17/668544.aspx
  |title=Office Web Components &quot;Roadmap&quot;
  |author=David Gainer
  |date=July 17, 2006
  |accessdate=2006-09-10
  |work=Microsoft Excel 2007 (nee Excel 12)
  |publisher=MSDN Blogs
  }}&lt;/ref&gt; However, they will still be available for download from Microsoft's website. Microsoft has not yet offered a complete replacement for the Office Web Components. However, programmers can use a combination of third party products, [[Excel Services]] or [[Visual Studio Tools for Office]] to provide similar functionality.

The Pivot Table web component does not function on Windows 7.&lt;ref&gt;[http://support.microsoft.com/kb/2067463 Webpage on Windows 7 does not render the OWC Pivot Table]&lt;/ref&gt;

There are currently four books in print on programming the OWC.
* The O.W.C Black Book 2nd Edition - Alvin Bruney 2007
* The Microsoft Office Web Components Black Book with .NET - Alvin Bruney 2005
* Professional ASP Programming Guide for Office Web Components: With Office 2000 and Office XP - Qimao Zhang 2001
* Programming Microsoft Office 2000 Web Components - Dave Stearns 2000

==References==
{{Reflist|30em}}

==External links==
;Equation Editor
*[http://www.dessci.com/products/mathtype/ MathType Homepage]
*[http://www.codecogs.com/components/equationeditor/equationeditor.php CodeCogs Online LaTeX Equation Editor] - add equations to any website
*[http://www.dessci.com/en/products/mathtype/faqs.htm#mt_v_ee MathType and Equation Editor]
*[http://blogs.msdn.com/murrays/ Math in Office blog]
*[http://www.grindeq.com/ GrindEQ] Converts from MathType OLE objects to Equation Editor 3.0 object.
*[http://blogs.msdn.com/microsoft_office_word/archive/2006/10/04/Equations-in-Word-2007.aspx Equations in Word 2007]
*[http://www.dragmath.bham.ac.uk DragMath] an open source Java applet.

;WordArt
*[http://support.microsoft.com/default.aspx?scid=kb;en-us;312802&amp;sd=tech How to insert and modify WordArt in MS Word]
*[http://www.stampitnet.com/Blog/small-business-document-management-for-microsoft%c2%ae-word-users/#more-134 How to Use WordArt for Document Identification and marking]
*[http://www.scottmeyer.com How to be a tool for Document Making]
*[http://www.wordartgenerator.com A free program to design and create WordArt]

;Binder
*[http://www.microsoft.com/downloads/details.aspx?FamilyID=bb8ef813-80e3-493f-a914-7add36d84b8a&amp;displaylang=en Office 97 Unbind]
*[http://filext.com/file-extension/obd File Extension Details for .OBD]
*[http://filext.com/file-extension/obt File Extension details for .OBT]
*[http://office.microsoft.com/en-us/assistance/HP030849741033.aspx Open an Microsoft Binder document in Office 2003]
*[http://support.microsoft.com/?kbid=843147 FAQ on Microsoft Binder 97]

;Microsoft Data Analyzer
*[http://office.microsoft.com/en-us/downloads/CD010225721033.aspx Microsoft Data Analyzer]
*[http://www.microsoft.com/presspass/press/2001/nov01/11-01dataanalysispr.mspx Press Release]

;Office Web Components
* [http://support.microsoft.com/kb/319793 How to find Office Web Components (OWC) programming documentation and samples]
* [https://addons.mozilla.org/en-US/firefox/addon/web-page-fixer/ The Unofficial Office Web Components plugin for Firefox]
* [http://www.microsoft.com/downloads/details.aspx?FamilyID=7287252c-402e-4f72-97a5-e0fd290d4b76&amp;DisplayLang=en Office 2003 Web Components]
* [http://www.microsoft.com/downloads/details.aspx?FamilyID=982b0359-0a86-4fb2-a7ee-5f3a499515dd&amp;DisplayLang=en Office XP Web Components]
* [http://www.microsoft.com/downloads/details.aspx?FamilyID=beb5d477-2100-4586-a13c-50e56f101720&amp;DisplayLang=en Office XP Web Component toolpack containing samples and walkthroughs]
* [http://www.microsoft.com/downloads/details.aspx?FamilyID=faaddc0a-a281-4eec-8935-83b6541c80a3&amp;DisplayLang=en Office XP Web Components Animated Walkthrough]

{{Microsoft Office}}

[[Category:Microsoft Office]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
