<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="16485676" ns="0" title="Uno buses route S4"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Notability|date=April 2011}}
{{Infobox UK bus route
|number                =             S4 
|operatorlogo          =             
|start                 =             Mile House
|end                   =             Cottonmill
|via                   =             City Centre, Cottonmill Lane, Maynard Drive
|frequency             =             30 mins at all times (0630-2230 daily)
|pvr                   =             1
|length                =             5.4 miles
|operator              =             [[Uno (bus comany)|Uno]]
|garage                =             [HF] Hatfield Business Park
|previousoperator      =             [[Centrebus]], [[Sovereign Buses]], [[London Country]]
|vehicle               =             [[Dennis Dart|Mini Pointer Dart]]
|otherroutes           =             [[Uno buses route S5|S5]]
}}

'''[[Uno (bus company)|Uno]] bus route S4''' is a local bus service in [[St Albans]], [[Hertfordshire]], [[England]], linking Cottonmill to St Albans city centre (and at business hours [[St Albans railway station]]). It operates together with route [[Uno buses route S5|S5]].

==History==
S4 was one of six new local routes introduced in [[St Albans]] by [[London Country Bus Services]] in October 1976&lt;ref&gt;&quot;London Country&quot; Laurie Akehurst and David Stewart August 2001&lt;/ref&gt;. They replaced a variety of earlier routes and were unusual for the time in being numbered with a lettered prefix (S) to designate the town or city they operated in rather than in the 3xx or 8xx series normally used for services in the area.&lt;br /&gt;
Upon the privatisation of [[London Country Bus Services]] in September 1986, the St Albans area network passed to successor company [[London Country North East]]. London Country North East was in turn divided into two companies, with [[Sovereign Bus &amp; Coach]] acquiring the St Albans, Welwyn Hatfield and Stevenage local networks and various rural services connecting these towns. [[Bus deregulation in Great Britain|Bus deregulation]] a month later largely left the network unchanged with the daytime services being registered commercially and the evening services being tendered.&lt;br /&gt;
Sovereign itself was acquired by [[Blazefield Group|Blazefield Holdings]] and significant investment in the St Albans network was undertaken with a new fleet of Dennis Dart buses. During this period the services underwent frequent changes until the current pattern of the S4 (and its sister route S5) only serving the area to the south west of the City Centre (in place of providing cross-City links) was established. However, Blazefield could not make an adequate financial return on its Hertfordshire operations and began to dispose of them in favour of concentrating on its core [[Lancashire]] and [[Yorkshire]] businesses in late 2003/2004. &lt;br /&gt;
The St Albans local network, along with various services connecting St Albans to other Hertfordshire towns, was sold to Leicestershire firm [[Centrebus]] who already had a small presence in the town on rural services run from its Luton base. Services largely remained unchanged and Centrebus kept all of the S4's designated vehicles (KC03 PGK and KC03 PGU), albeit repainting them a few times. &lt;br /&gt;However, the City network remained problematic both operationally and financially and [[Uno (bus company)|Uno]] took over all services operated from Centrebus' St Albans depot on 4 March 2008. Initially the fleet retained Centrebus livery, but during summer 2008 they were repainted into the [[Best Impressions]] designed livery to match the rest of the Uno buses.

==Route (one direction only)==
S4 operates every 30 minutes on Monday to Saturday daytimes and is jointly timetabled with [[Uno buses route S5]] to provide a combined 15 minute frequency. &lt;br /&gt;
*[[St Albans railway station]] (business hours only)
*[[St Albans]] ''St Peters Street''
*[[St Albans]] 'London Road', ''The Peahen [[Pub|PH]]''
*Cottonmill Lane (for [[Sopwell House]], [[Sopwell Priory]], The [[River Ver]] and The [[Alban Way]])
*Trumpington Drive Shops ([[SPAR]], [[Londis]])
*Maynard Drive
*Doggetts Way
*Abbey View Retail Park (for [[Premier Foods]] Offices, [[Sainsbury's]] and [[McDonald's]])
*[[St Albans Abbey railway station]]
*Holywell Hill
*[[St Albans Abbey]]
Back to ''St Peters Street''.
&lt;br /&gt;On evenings and Sundays, a half hourly service operates but operates across St Albans linking with route sections served by routes S2 and S3 during daytimes. The evening and Sunday services are financially subsidised by [[Hertfordshire County Council]].

==See also==
*[[Uno (bus company)]]
*[[St Albans]]
*[[Uno buses route S5]]

==References==
{{reflist}}

==External links==
*http://www.unobus.info
*http://www.intalink.org.uk

{{DEFAULTSORT:S4, Uno}}
[[Category:Bus routes in England]]
[[Category:Transport in Hertfordshire]]
[[Category:Transport in St Albans]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
