<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="16485758" ns="0" title="Studio Disney UK"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Infobox Television
| show_name = Studio Disney
| image =  
| caption = The final logo while Studio Disney was on air. The show was on the [[Disney Channel]] Network.
| genre = [[Children's Television]]
| creator = 
| starring  = [[Nigel Mitchell]] &lt;br&gt;[[Emma Lee]]&lt;br&gt;Jean Anderson&lt;br&gt;[[James McCourt]]&lt;br&gt;Ollie of Freefaller&lt;br&gt;Jemma Forte&lt;br&gt;[[Mark Rumble]]&lt;br&gt; Amy Garcia
| theme_music_composer = 
| opentheme = 
| country = [[United Kingdom]]
| language = [[English language|English]]
| num_episodes = 
| executive_producer = 
| location = [[Chiswick]], [[London]]
| camera = [[Multiple-camera setup]]
| runtime = Usual: 4 Hours
| network = [[Disney Channel (UK &amp; Ireland)|Disney Channel UK]]
| picture_format = [[576i]] ([[SDTV]])
| first_aired = September 1, 1997
| last_aired = July 1, 2005
| website = 
}}

''Studio Disney'' was a live TV show, broadcast on [[Disney Channel (UK &amp; Ireland)|Disney Channel UK]]. It launched in September 1997 as ''Disney Channel UK Live'', and relaunched as ''Studio Disney'' on 23 April 2001. Some of the presenters included; [[Nigel Mitchell]], [[Emma Lee]], [[Jean Anderson]], [[Mark Rumble]], Amy Garcia, Ollie from Freefaller, [[James McCourt (TV host)|James McCourt]], Jemma James (now Jemma Forte). Studio Disney ran on weekdays, usually from 16:00 to 19:00, in direct competition with similar services offered by [[CBBC]], [[CITV]] and [[Nickelodeon (UK &amp; Ireland)|Nickelodeon]]. The show featured a team of between two and six presenters who came on air between programmes, giving viewers the opportunity to call in, interact and win prizes. Studio Disney also produced many of its own short programmes, including ''Wish Upon a Star'' and ''Junior Journo'', which were aired during the block itself and between programmes at other times. Studio Disney bowed out on 1 July 2005,  in line with the disappearance of afternoon in-vision presentation on CITV and Nickelodeon the previous year and leaving the channel with a format similar to that of its [[Disney Channel|American counterpart]]. 

The live presentation of the show, would also run competitions in which viewers could win holidays, and other prizes.
Special holiday competitions would be run, [[New Year]], [[Easter]], [[Mother's Day]], [[Father's Day]], [[Chinese New Year]], [[Christmas]], etc.

(i.e. Mother's Day - Competition of 2003 involved [[Emma Lee]] surprising four entrants and their mothers to a special get-away.
(i.e. Father's Day - Competition of 2004 involved [[James McCourt]] and [[Nigel Mitchell]] treating one lucky dad to a day at [[Silverstone Circuit|Silverstone Grand Prix]] track.

At other times of day, pre-recorded presentation was used, typically recorded in such a manner that viewers would believe that it was live. An example of this was breakfast segment ''Up'' (and later called ''Zoom!''), which was hosted out-of-vision by [[Capital Disney]] presenter, and managing director [[Will Chambers]]. Another example originated from the ''Monster March'' event that ran throughout March [[2002]], during which the schedule featured many [[monster]]-themed shows and movies. Pre-recorded sketches featuring a [[Mexican people|Mexican]] [[dinosaur]] [[puppet]] named ''Raoul'' were inserted between programmes, and as this proved popular{{Citation needed|date=February 2007}}, Raoul was given a number of his own segments on the channel over the next few years, including ''The Raoul Show'', ''Good Morning Raoul'' and ''The Raoul Summer''. The best sketches from The Raoul Show were made into a series of short programmes entitled ''The Best of Raoul''. Raoul was even the subject of a question on the 20th Anniversary edition of [[Trivial Pursuit]][http://www.dandytv.com/].

In 2002, Studio Disney created its own music talent show called ''&quot;Star Ticket&quot;'' which aimed to create a five piece pop band, aged between 11-14, to perform at the Disney Channel Kids Awards 2002. Auditions were held in [[Edinburgh]], [[London]], [[Cardiff]] and [[Liverpool]]. The viewing public were able to vote for their desired band members, the name of the band and the name of the song they would be performing. The winning group, called X5 (pronounced ''times'' five), went on to record the song &quot;Beyond the Stars&quot; plus a music video. It has been presumed that they had split as nothing was heard from the band since the award ceremony. The show was presented by David &quot;Ollie&quot; Oliver and Jemma Forte.

== External links ==
* {{imdb title|0913274|Studio Disney}}

[[Category:Television series by Disney]]
[[Category:1990s British television series]]
[[Category:2000s British television series]]
[[Category:1997 television series debuts]]
[[Category:2005 television series endings]]

[[es:Zapping Zone]]
[[fr:Zapping Zone]]
[[pt:Zapping Zone]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
