<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="16493037" ns="0" title="Cricket Samoa"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">'''the Samoa International Cricket Association (SICA)''' is the official [[Sport governing body|governing body]] of the sport of [[cricket]] in [[Samoa]]. Cricket Samoa is Samoa's representative at the [[International Cricket Council]] and is an affiliate member and has been a member of that body since [[2000]]. It is also a member of the [[East Asia-Pacific Cricket Council]]. 
{{Infobox Country
| native_name              = ''Malo Sa'oloto Tuto'atasi o Samoa''
&lt;br /&gt;Independent State of Samoa
| common_name              = Samoa
| image_flag               = Flag of Samoa.svg
| image_coat               =  
| symbol_type              = Coat of arms
| image_map                = LocationSamoa.png
| national_motto           = ''Fa'avae i le Atua Samoa''&lt;br /&gt;({{lang-en|Samoa is founded on God}})&lt;ref name=&quot;DB&quot;&gt;{{cite news | first= | last= | coauthors= | title=Samoa an Overview | url =http://www.donbosco.asn.au/Bulletins/2004/mar/overview.htm | work =donbosco.asn.au | pages = | accessdate = 26 November 2007 | language = |archiveurl = http://web.archive.org/web/20071120020749/http://www.donbosco.asn.au/Bulletins/2004/mar/overview.htm &lt;!-- Bot retrieved archive --&gt; |archivedate = 20 November 2007}}&lt;/ref&gt; {{Dead link|date=December 2008}}
| national_anthem          = ''[[The Banner of Freedom]]''
| official_languages       = [[Samoan language|Samoan]], English
| demonym                  = [[Samoans|Samoan]]
| capital                  = [[Apia, Samoa|Apia]]
| latd                     = 13
| latm                     = 50
| latNS                    = S
| longd                    = 171
| longm                    = 45
| longEW                   = W
| largest_city             = [[Apia, Samoa|Apia]]
| government_type          = [[Parliamentary republic]]
| leader_title1            = [[O le Ao o le Malo]]&lt;br /&gt;(Head of State)
| leader_name1             = [[Tufuga Efi]]
| leader_title2            = [[Prime Minister of Samoa|Prime Minister]]
| leader_name2             = [[Tuilaepa Aiono Sailele Malielegaoi]]
web|url=http://www.imf.org/external/pubs/ft/weo/2010/01/weodata/weorept.aspx?sy=2007&amp;ey=2010&amp;scsm=1&amp;ssd=1&amp;sort=country&amp;ds=.&amp;br=1&amp;c=862&amp;s=NGDPD%2CNGDPDPC%2CPPPGDP%2CPPPPC%2CLP&amp;grp=0&amp;a=&amp;pr.x=76&amp;pr.y=13 |title=Samoa|publisher=International Monetary Fund|accessdate=2010-04-21}}

==References==
{{Reflist}}

==External links==
*[http://content-usa.cricinfo.com/other/content/team/141.html Cricinfo-Samoa]
SICA Official Website *[http://www.sportingpulse.com/assoc_page.cgi?c=2-1359-0-0-0&amp;sID=148652]

==Background==
Cricket in the Samoan islands has a colourful history since it was introduced in 1884 by the visit of the British Royal Navy vessel, the HMS Diamond. Since this time, not too much is known of organised cricket in the islands but from 1964, a band of locals and hardy expats would gather together as the Wanderers to play against passing cruise ships and other visitors. Ad hoc cricket fixtures and tournaments were the norm around Samoa until the late 1990s when an Association and committee was formed to take cricket to the next level.

===ICC Affiliate===
In 2000 the '''Samoa International Cricket Association''' (SICA) became an Affiliate member of the '''ICC'''. This affiliation provides annual funding support for SICA and also ensures that Samoa participates in regular '''ICC''' international fixtures and tournaments across the region and beyond. '''SICA''' also enjoys a strong partnership with '''Auckland Cricket''', who provide professional assistance and training in all areas of cricket including coaching, umpiring and administration.

==Association Structure==
'''SICA''' has a dedicated administration which is run by an experienced committee and headed by local cricket legend and leading businessman, '''Seb Kohlhase'''.  Seb, who played first class cricket in New Zealand and Australia, is well known in sporting circles in the region and his passion for cricket was one of the main reasons for his receiving an ICC award in 2006 for Lifetime Services to Cricket. 

The chairman of SICA is the Honourable Prime Minister Tuilaepa Lupesoliai Sailele Malielegoai.  The Prime Minister’s strong support of cricket has helped the sport maintain a high profile in Samoa and ensures that cricket continues to grow and develop.  For the second year in a row, cricket will be played at Samoa's premier cultural carnival, the '''Teuila Festival''', inextricably linking the sport with Samoan culture.

==Competitions==
In September 2009 Samoa hosted the '''Pepsi ICC East-Asia Pacific Trophy''' 
In May 2010 Samoa's National Women's team ''Nafanua'' competed in the '''East Asia Pacific Trophy''' held in Japan finishing a close Third.

===Annual Competitions===
===Teuila National Village Championships===
Held in September during Samoa's premier cultural carnival, the '''Teuila Festival.''' Over 30 teams compete for a ticket in the week long festival.  In 2010 eight men's teams and six women's teams competed for the honor of being crowned the 2010 National Village Champions. 
===Senior Mens League=== A two tiered relegation based competition Hosting 8 - 12 Senior Teams over a 20 week competition. A Senior Women's League is planned for 2011

===Upolu Rural Championships===
===Savaii Rural Championships===
===Primary Schools Championships===
===Secondary Schools Championships===
===ANZAC Day Exhibition===
In the tradition of ANZAC Day the exhibition match is battled out between Australian and Kiwi expats

===Independence Day Exhibition===
The National Samoan Team matches up against the top international players on the island.

===Business House Competition===
Sixteen corporate organisations compete in a five week competition full of fun and networking opportunities.
 

{{Affiliate Members of the International Cricket Council}}

[[Category:Cricket administration]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
