<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="165543" ns="0" title="Open Sound System"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Infobox software
| name                   = Open Sound System
| logo                   =
| screenshot             =
| caption                =
| collapsible            =
| author                 = Hannu Savolainen
| developer              = [[4Front Technologies]]
| released               = 1992
| latest release version = 4.2 Build 2005
| latest release date    = {{release date and age|2011|08|05}}&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.4front-tech.com/forum/viewtopic.php?f=19&amp;t=4391 |title=OSS v4.2 Build 2005 |accessdate=2011-08-14 }}&lt;/ref&gt;
| latest preview version =
| latest preview date    =
| frequently updated     =
| programming language   =
| operating system       = [[Cross-platform]]
| platform               =
| size                   =
| language               =
| status                 =
| genre                  = Audio
| license                = [[BSD License]]&amp;nbsp;/ [[Common Development and Distribution License]]&amp;nbsp;/ [[GNU General Public License]]&amp;nbsp;/ [[Proprietary software|Proprietary]]
| website                = [http://www.opensound.com/ www.opensound.com]
}}

The '''Open Sound System''' (OSS) is an interface for making and capturing sound in [[Unix]] or [[Unix-like]] operating systems.  It is based on standard Unix [[device node|devices]] (i.e. [[POSIX]] read, write, ioctl, etc.).  The term also sometimes refers to the software in a Unix kernel that provides the OSS interface; it can be thought of as a device driver, or a collection of device drivers for sound controller hardware. The goal of OSS is to allow the writing of sound-based applications that are agnostic of the underlying sound hardware.

OSS was created in 1992 by [[Hannu Savolainen]] and is available in 11 major [[Unix-like]] operating systems. OSS is distributed under four license options, three of which are [[free software licences]], thus making OSS [[free software]].&lt;ref name=&quot;OSS-liberated-2007&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.linuxpr.com/releases/9766.html |title=4Front technologies releases the source code for open sound system }}&lt;/ref&gt;

==API==

The API is designed to use the traditional Unix framework of open(), read(), write(), and ioctl(), via special devices. For instance, the default device for sound input and output is '''/dev/dsp'''. Examples using the shell:

 cat [[/dev/urandom]] &gt;/dev/dsp # plays [[white noise]] through the speaker
 cat /dev/dsp &gt;a.a # reads data from the microphone and copies it to file a.a

==Free, proprietary, free==

The project was initially [[free software]], but following the project's success, Savolainen was contracted by the company [[4Front Technologies]] and made his support for newer sound devices and improvements [[proprietary software|proprietary]].  In response, eventually the Linux community abandoned the OSS/free implementation included in the kernel (an outdated 3.x version, while 4front continued working on 4.x&lt;ref&gt;[http://4front-tech.com/hannublog/?p=5]&lt;/ref&gt;) and development effort switched to the replacement [[Advanced Linux Sound Architecture]] (ALSA).  Many free software operating systems such as [[Linux]] and [[FreeBSD]] continued to distribute previous versions of OSS, and continued to maintain and improve these versions.

In July 2007, 4Front Technologies released sources for OSS under [[CDDL]] for [[OpenSolaris]] and [[GPL]] for [[Linux]].&lt;ref name=&quot;OSS-liberated-2007&quot; /&gt; In January 2008, 4Front Technologies released OSS for [[FreeBSD]] (and other [[BSD]] systems) under the [[BSD License]].&lt;ref name=&quot;OSS-BSD-2008&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.opensound.com/press/2008/oss-bsd.txt |title=4Front Technologies releases OSS for FreeBSD under the BSD license }}&lt;/ref&gt;

== OSS in relation to ALSA ==
In the [[Linux kernel]], there have historically been two uniform sound APIs used.  One is OSS;
the other is ALSA (''[[Advanced Linux Sound Architecture]]'').  ALSA is available for Linux only, and as there is only one implementation of the ALSA interface, ALSA refers equally to that implementation and to the interface itself.

OSS is the only audio API in Linux up through the 2.4 series of official (kernel.org) Linux kernels.  ALSA was added starting with 2.5, and in those versions, Linux kernel authors marked OSS as deprecated.  4Front continued to develop OSS outside of the Linux kernel.

ALSA provides an optional OSS emulation mode that appears to programs as if it were OSS. Similarly, there was an [http://www.opensound.com/wiki/index.php/Tips_And_Tricks#ALSA_Emulation ALSA emulation] mode in the Linux implementation of OSS.

According to some,{{Who|date=June 2011}} OSS is better documented than ALSA and its API is much simpler and easier to use.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://insanecoding.blogspot.com/2007/05/sorry-state-of-sound-in-linux.html |title=The Sorry State of Sound in Linux }}&lt;/ref&gt;

==OSS/3D==
OSS/3D is a plugin for music players, which acts as an audio postprocessing engine. Supported players include Winamp, Windows Media Player (9 or later), musicmatch, Sonique, Foobar2000, JetAudio, XMMS. It is ported to Windows and Linux platforms. Unlike the OSS, it is shareware.

4Front OSS3D was later renamed to Joesoft Hear&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.yohng.com/obsolete.html yohng.com &amp;middot; Obsolete product reference]&lt;/ref&gt;.

== Criticism ==

OSS both as API and as software has been criticized openly and vocally by many free software developers, such as [[Paul Davis (programmer)|Paul Davis]] and [[Lennart Poettering]]. Often heard arguments against OSS are: the API is practically impossible to virtualize, it lacks support for modern audio features such as timer-based scheduling or proper surround sound support, inability of its developers to work with the Linux kernel community, lack of integration with modern kernel features such as the device model, too low-level interface, as well as general rejection of its design with moving a lot of signal processing code into the kernel.

Most of these criticisms {{Which|date=November 2011}} have been addressed in OSS version 4.

== Other implementations ==
[[FreeBSD]] contains an independently developed implementation of the OSS API, which includes, among other things, in-kernel resampling, mixing (vchans), equalizer, and independent volume control for each application.  It also supports bit-perfect mode.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.freebsd.org/cgi/man.cgi?sound&lt;/ref&gt;

[[NetBSD]] supports a compatibility mode for the OSS API, by providing the &lt;code&gt;soundcard.h&lt;/code&gt; header file and the &lt;code&gt;libossaudio&lt;/code&gt; library, which internally operate using the native NetBSD Sun-like audio interface.&lt;ref&gt;http://netbsd.gw.com/cgi-bin/man-cgi?ossaudio+3+NetBSD-current&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Solaris (operating system)|Solaris]] and [[OpenSolaris]] uses a fork of OSS4 call Boomer. It combines the OSS4 framework (audio and mixer) together with Sun's earlier SADA(/dev/audio) API.
&lt;ref&gt;http://4front-tech.com/hannublog/?page_id=17&lt;/ref&gt;

== See also ==
{{Portal|Free software}}
* [[Advanced Linux Sound Architecture]]

==References==
{{Reflist|2}}

==External links==
*[http://www.opensound.com/ Open Sound System - Home page]
*[http://www.4front-tech.com/wiki/index.php/Building_OSSv4_from_source Building the Open Sound System From Source]
*[http://insanecoding.blogspot.com/2009/06/state-of-sound-in-linux-not-so-sorry.html State of sound in Linux not so sorry after all]

[[Category:Free audio software]]
[[Category:Audio libraries]]
[[Category:Application programming interfaces]]
[[Category:Cross-platform software]]

[[cs:Open Sound System]]
[[de:Open Sound System]]
[[es:Open Sound System]]
[[fr:Open Sound System]]
[[ko:오픈 사운드 시스템]]
[[it:Open Sound System]]
[[hu:Open Sound System]]
[[ja:Open Sound System]]
[[nn:Open Sound System]]
[[pl:Open Sound System]]
[[pt:Open Sound System]]
[[ru:Open Sound System]]
[[fi:Open Sound System]]
[[sv:Open Sound System]]
[[zh:OSS]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
