<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="1656053" ns="0" title="Reza Aslan"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Primary sources|date=November 2007}}
{{Infobox writer &lt;!-- for more information see [[:Template:Infobox writer/doc]] --&gt;
| name        = Reza Aslan
| image       = Reza_aslan_-_august_2009.jpg
| imagesize   = 200px
| nationality = [[United States|American]]
| birth_date  = {{birth date and age|df=yes|1972|5|3}}
| birth_place = [[Tehran]], [[Tehran Province]], [[Iran]]
| occupation  = Writer, Islamic thinker
| spouse = [[Jessica Jackley]]
}}
'''Reza Aslan''' ([[Persian language|Persian]] رضا اصلان, born May 3, 1972) is an [[Iranian-American]] activist, a nationally acclaimed writer of religions. He is on the faculty at the [[University of California, Riverside]], and is a contributing editor for ''[[The Daily Beast]]''. His books include the international bestseller, ''[[No god but God|No god but God: The Origins, Evolution, and Future of Islam]]'', which has been translated into thirteen languages, and named one of the 100 most important books of the last decade. He is also the author of ''How to Win a Cosmic War'', published in paperback as ''Beyond Fundamentalism: Confronting Religious Extremism in a Globalized Age''. He is also editor of ''Tablet &amp; Pen: Literary Landscapes from the Modern Middle East'', published by [[W. W. Norton]], and co-editor with Aaron Hahn-Tapper of Muslims and Jews in America: Commonalities, Contentions, and Complexities, published by Palgrave Macmillan. Dr. Reza Aslan is CEO of Aslan Media Inc., whose holdings include BoomGen Studios, the first ever motion picture studio entirely focused on entertainment content about the Greater Middle East and its Diaspora communities. His non-profit organization Aslan Media Initiatives (AslanMedia.com) utilizes social media technology to provide news and information about the Middle East to young people all over the world.

==Background==
Aslan's family came to the [[United States]] from [[Tehran]] in 1979, fleeing the [[Iranian Revolution]]. He grew up in the [[San Francisco Bay Area]]. In the early 1990s, Aslan taught courses at [[De La Salle High School (Concord, California)|De La Salle High School]] in [[Concord, California]].  Iranian singer Leila Forouhar is his aunt.

Aslan has a Bachelor of Arts in religions from [[Santa Clara University]], a [[Master of Theological Studies]] from [[Harvard Divinity School]], a PhD in the Sociology of Religions from the [[University of California, Santa Barbara]], and a Master of Fine Arts from the [[University of Iowa]]'s [[Iowa Writers' Workshop|Writers' Workshop]], where he was named the Truman Capote Fellow in Fiction. He is a member of the [[Council on Foreign Relations]], the Los Angeles Institute for the Humanities, and the [[Pacific Council on International Policy]]. He has served as Legislative Assistant for the [[Friends Committee on National Legislation]] in Washington D.C., and was elected President of the World Conference of Religions for Peace, Harvard Chapter. He serves on the board of directors of the Ploughshares Fund, which gives grants for peace and security issues; Abraham's Vision, an interfaith, educational conflict transformation organization; PEN USA, which champions the rights of writers under siege around the world; and he serves on the national advisory board of the [[Levantine Cultural Center]], building bridges between Americans and the Arab/Muslim world.

As Contributing Editor, Aslan has written numerous articles for ''[[The Daily Beast]]''. He has also written for various newspapers and periodicals, including ''[[The Christian Science Monitor]]'', the ''[[Los Angeles Times]]'', ''[[The New York Times]]'', [[Slate Magazine|Slate]], ''[[The Boston Globe]]'', ''[[The Washington Post]]'', ''[[The Guardian]]'', the ''[[Chicago Tribune]]'', and ''[[The Nation]]''. He has made numerous appearances on TV and radio, including [[National Public Radio]] (NPR), [[PBS]], ''[[The Rachel Maddow Show (TV series)|The Rachel Maddow Show]]'', ''[[Meet the Press]]'', ''[[The Daily Show with Jon Stewart]]'', ''[[The Colbert Report]]'', ''[[Anderson Cooper 360°]]'', ''[[Hardball with Chris Matthews|Hardball]]'', ''[[Nightline]]'', ''[[Real Time with Bill Maher]]'', and ''[[Fareed Zakaria GPS]]''.

===Currently===
Aslan is President and CEO of Aslan Media Inc., whose holdings include BoomGen Studios, a mini-motion picture and media company focused entirely on entertainment about the Greater Middle East and its Diaspora communities. Dr. Aslan currently lives in Hollywood, California where he is Associate Professor of Creative Writing at the University of California, Riverside. In addition, he is a Research Associate at the University of Southern California's Center on Public Diplomacy.
Dr. Reza Aslan has been the Contributing Editor for the Daily Beast since 2008.
He is working on a biography of Jesus of Nazareth and a historical novel, set a thousand years ago, about a caravan traveling from the Arabian Peninsula to India.
Aslan Media followers can obtain up to date news, information and join discussions on the Aslan Media Inc.'s official page, [[YouTube]], [[Facebook]], [[GoodReads]] and [[Twitter]].
Dr. Reza Aslan launched his Twitter presence - @aslanmedia-with the vision of changing how news and information on the Middle East is provided. Working to engage with Muslims and non-Muslims on what's happening in the region, the Aslan Media TweetWire on Twitter has since grown steadily on the idea that it's possible to stay updated on Middle East news with just 140 characters.

==Written and spoken works==
{{Wikify section|date=April 2011}}
{{BLP unsourced section|date=April 2011}}
His first book, ''[[No god but God]]'' (Random House, 2005), has been translated into thirteen languages, was short-listed for the Guardian (UK) First Book Award, and nominated for a PEN USA award for research Non-Fiction. In ''[[No god but God]]'', Aslan challenges the &quot;clash of civilizations&quot; mentality that has distorted our view of Islam and explains this critical faith in all its complexity, beauty, and compassion. Aslan begins with a vivid account of the social and religious milieu from which the Prophet Muhammad arose. The revelations that Muhammad received in Mecca and Medina, and which were recorded in the Quran, became the foundation of a radically egalitarian community, the likes of which had never been seen before.  [[No god but God]]''  also examines how, in the shadow of European colonialism, Muslims developed conflicting strategies to reconcile traditional Islamic values with the social and political realities of the modern world. With the emergence of the Islamic State in the 20th century, this contest over the future of Islam has become a passionate, sometimes violent battle between those who seek to enforce a rigid and archaic legal code on society and those who struggle to harmonize the teachings of the Prophet with contemporary ideals of democracy and human rights. According to Dr. Reza Aslan, we are now living in the era of &quot;the Islamic Reformation.&quot; [[No god but God]]'' is a persuasive and elegantly written account of the origins, evolution, and future of Islam.

On April 20, 2009, his book ''How to Win a Cosmic War: God, Globalization, and the End of the War on Terror'' (Random House, 2009) was released. ''How to Win a Cosmic War'' provides both an in-depth study of the ideology behind [[al-Qaeda]], the [[Taliban]], and like-minded militants throughout the Muslim world, and an exploration of the tradition of religious violence found in Judaism, Christianity, and Islam. Surveying the global scene from Israel to Iraq and from New York to the Netherlands, Aslan argues that religion is a stronger force today than it has been in a century. At a time when religion and politics are increasingly sharing the same vocabulary and functioning in the same sphere, Aslan writes that we must strip this ideological conflict of its religious connotations and address the actual grievances that fuel the Jihadist movement. How to Win a Cosmic War was the subject of an interview by Jon Stewart on The Daily Show. Aslan discussed its themes—the intrinsic irrationality of fundamentalist Islamic objectives, the dangers posed by the lack of understanding of Jihadists by the American military and the Christian evangelical movement, and the utility of free elections and participatory democracy in containing the spread of Jihadist movements (a goal for which he complimented George W. Bush). The book was published in paperback as Beyond Fundamentalism: Confronting Religious Extremism in the Age of Globalization.

''Tablet &amp; Pen: Literary Landscapes From the Modern Middle East'', edited by Dr. Reza Aslan, is a 600-plus page anthology that takes a broad view of 20th century Arabic, Persian, Turkish and Pakistani history and culture through the filter of the written word. This book uses the work of 69 writers to make a strong case for the power of fiction, poetry and essays to connect us at the level of the heart. &quot;If the purpose of literature is to provide a window into other worlds,&quot; Dr. Aslan notes, &quot;then the individual pieces collected in this anthology are mere porthole glimpses into the kaleidoscopic world of the modern Middle East. Dr. Aslan brings a historian's vision to ''Tablet &amp; Pen'', arranging the collection in three chronological sections, and geographically within them. Dr. Aslan's goal is to create &quot;not an anthology to be tasted in disparate bits but rather a single sustained narrative to be consumed as a whole.&quot;
As well as books, Aslan has written numerous articles, commentaries (for broadcast, print and new media), and book reviews internationally. He often appears on broadcast media radio and television, including many documentaries on Islam and the Muslim Prophet Muhammad. He tours in U.S. and internationally giving talks and has written many press articles.

==Other publications==
*'The Struggle for Islam's Soul', essay in ''With All Our Might: A Progressive Strategy for Defeating Jihadism and Defending Liberty'', Will Marshall, ed. Rowman &amp; Littlefield Publishers, Inc., 2006.
*'From Here to Mullahcracy', essay in ''My Sister, Guard Your Veil; My Brother, Guard Your Eyes: Uncensored Iranian Voices'', Lila Azam Zanganeh, ed. Beacon Press, 2006.
*'Forward', ''Ritual: Perspectives and Dimensions'', Catherine Bell, Oxford University Press, 2009.
*'Losing the War', ''The New World Reader'', Gilbert H Muller, ed., CUNY Press, 2010.
*'Preface', ''Reframing 9/11: Film, Popular Culture and the War on Terror'', Jeff Birkenstein, Anna Froula, and Karen Randell, eds. Continuum, 2010.
*'Preface'. ''Religion and the New Atheism: A Critical Appraisal'', Amarnath Amarasingam, ed. Brill, 2010.

==Television appearances==
{{BLP unsourced section|date=April 2011}}
* &quot;Reza Aslan on Real Time with Bill Maher&quot;
Air date: May 20, 2011

* &quot;The Colbert Report with Stephen Colbert&quot;
Thursday, March 10, 2011 on Comedy Central
Discussion about Congressman Peter King's hearings on Islamic radicalization

* &quot;Reza Aslan on Tavis Smiley&quot;
December 10, 2010
Reza Aslan discusses US relations with Iran

* &quot;The Colbert Report with Stephen Colbert&quot;
Monday, November 8, 2010 on Comedy Central
Discussion about Tablet &amp; Pen: Literary Landscapes From the Modern Middle East,&quot;

* &quot;Meet the Press&quot;
Sunday, September 12, 2010
Guests:  David Axelrod, Rudy Giuliani, Dee Dee Myers, Dr. Reza Aslan, Mike Murphy, Ron Brownstein

* &quot;The Daily Show with Jon Stewart&quot;
Monday April 5, 2010 on Comedy Central
U.S. and the War in Afghanistan

* &quot;Campbell Brown, CNN&quot;
July 14, 2010 on CNN
Mosque at Ground Zero, Growing Controversy, Debate- AIFD President Dr. Zuhdi Jasser and Dr. Reza Aslan

* &quot;Middle East Peace Talks&quot;
Monday, May 17, 2010 Dr. Reza Aslan featured on ABC News (Australian Broadcasting Corporation)

* &quot;Reza Aslan on MSNBC's Hardball on Iran Nuclear Politics&quot;
Aired Friday June 12, 2009

* &quot;Reza Aslan on Tavis Smiley&quot;
Air date: May 20, 2009
Iran, US and the Middle East

* &quot;Reza Aslan on Real Time with Bill Maher&quot;
Air date: May 8, 2009

* &quot;Reza Aslan on The Daily Show with Jon Stewart&quot;
June 24, 2009
Iran's reform movement and the fight for the future of the Islamic Republic.

* Iran and “potential” democracy.
Thursday May 10, 2007

* Interview with Iranian-American Channel, BebinTV
The author of &quot;No God but God&quot; talks to exclusively to Bebin.tv
June 6, 2008

* Reza Aslan - The Future of Religious Nationalism
FORA.tv's bi-weekly video podcast on issues in religion.

* Debate with Irshad Manji on Muslim Reform
The Economist magazine and The Culture Project present Irshad Manji and Reza Aslan debating Muslim reform. Note that the above link is to the first file of five on YouTube.com. The remaining parts can be found here: Part 2, Part 3, Part 4, Part 5

* Debate between Sam Harris and Reza Aslan
February 12, 2007.
BookTV, CSPAN2: Debate on Religion and Reason with Sam Harris, &quot;Letter to a Christian Nation,&quot; and Dr. Reza Aslan, &quot;No god but God&quot;

* CBS News: Impact Of Saddam's Execution
Aired on January 3, 2007.
CBS Middle East consultant Dr. Reza Aslan, a fellow at the USC Center on Public Diplomacy, talks with Russ Mitchell about the impact Saddam Hussein's execution will have around the world.

* CBS News: Mideast Analyst On Papal Visit
Aired on November 28, 2006.
CBS News Middle East analyst Dr. Reza Aslan discusses Pope Benedict's visit to Istanbul and reactions from Muslims with Harry Smith.

* CBS News: Pope Speaks With Muslim Envoys
Aired on September 25, 2006.
Pope Benedict XVI held meetings outside Rome today with Muslim officials to try and make amends for comments he made last week. Middle East analyst Dr. Reza Aslan discusses the issue with Hannah Storm.

* Real Time with Bill Maher
Aired on September 22, 2006.
Note that the above link is to the first file of six on YouTube.com. The remaining five parts can be found here: Part 2, Part 3, Part 4, Part 5, Part 6

* CBS News: Muslim Anger At Pope
Aired on September 20, 2006.
The Rev. Jonathan Morris, vice-rector of the Legionnaires of Christ Seminary in Rome, CBS News Middle East analyst Dr. Reza Aslan and Julie Chen discuss the Muslim reaction to Pope Benedict's remarks.

New Media  Interviews/Discussions
* Gabrielle Calvocoressi interviews Reza Aslan
	Guernica Magazine, January 2011

* Column by Ed Leibowitz Think Again
	Los Angeles Magazine, December 2010

* Should France ban the burqa?
July 15, 2010
HLN's Joy Behar talks with Dr. Reza Aslan and Irshad Manji about France's plan to ban the wearing of the burqa in public

* Mosque at Ground Zero - Growing Controversy
July 14, 2010
Campbell Brown discusses the Ground Zero mosque and the controversy over its funding with Dr. Zuhdi Jasser (AIFD President) and Dr. Reza Aslan—a very interesting debate between Muslims on this issue.

* FORA.tv - United Nations Alliance of Civilizations
Debate: Future of Western Relations with the Muslim World

* YouTube - Reza Aslan at CSU part 1
March 10, 2010
An amateur video of Dr. Reza Aslan 's speaking engagement at Colorado State University in the Spring of 2010.

* YouTube - Episode 23: Interview with Reza Aslan
May 14, 2010
In the 23rd episode of The Week in Green, author and journalist Dr. Reza Aslan discusses nuclear politics in the Middle East and the way in which the Green Movement has changed perceptions of Iran among young Americans.

* Reza Aslan: Iran, the burqa, and Israel - theage.com.au
May 19, 2010
Religious Affairs writer Jacqueline Maley interviews author and Middle East commentator Dr. Reza Aslan, a guest of the 2010 Sydney Writers' Festival.

* Beyond Fundamentalism: Confronting Religious Extremism in the Age of Globalization
April 27, 2010
Dr. Reza Aslan joins the Rumi Forum to discuss the modern &quot;war on terror&quot; and giving it context.

* Festival 2010 - Sydney Writers' Festival 2010
May, 2010
Dr. Reza Aslan was the opening speaker at the 2010 Sydney Writers' Festival. See the gallery from the event.

==Quotes==
{{Copy to Wikiquote|section=yes}}

*&quot;I believe we are living in the time of the Islamic reformation. In fact, I think we are living in the twilight of that reformation. For me, the word reform is defined by its inevitability. This process cannot be stopped; it can be slowed down for a time but reform is inevitable. It's an historic reformation taking place within Islam — it's adapting itself to the realities of the world around it. I think we'll see the same process we saw in the Christian reformation from doctrinal absolutism to doctrinal relativism; toward a truly indigenous Islamic enlightenment. And it's up to us as Muslims in the US to give voice to that for our brothers and sisters who don't have the voice or the same ability to speak out as we do.&quot;
*&quot;It is pluralism—the peaceful coexistence and legal equality between different ethnic, religious or political ideologies—that defines democracy, not secularism.&quot;
*&quot;The veil is seen as a symbol of Islam but like all symbols, it's meaningless unless interpreted. The veil is as much a symbol of oppression of women as it is an expression of Muslim femininity. The strangeness of this is that if you go to a country where the veil is either mandatory or there is a lot of pressure to wear it, you'll find the vast majority of women are against it. But, if you go to a country like Turkey where the veil is outlawed in much of the public realm — in the latest polls, 70 percent of the Muslim women want to remove that law.&quot;
*&quot;Iraq should look to Israel for a model that combines democracy and religious belief.&quot;
*&quot;Despite the apartheid state that has resulted from over half a century of bloody territorial conflicts with its neighboring Palestinian territories, few would deny that the state of Israel is a democracy. At the same time, Israel is a country founded upon an exclusivist Jewish moral framework, which offers all the world's Jews — regardless of their nationality — immediate citizenship, providing them with a host of benefits and privileges over its non-Jewish citizens. It is a country in which the Orthodox rabbinical courts have jurisdiction over all matters relating to Judaism (including who is a Jew); where religious schools (yeshivas) are subsidized by the state, and marriages are religious, rather than civil affairs (meaning no official will marry a Jew to a non-Jew); and the government is dominated by religious parties such as the ultra-Orthodox Shas, the Yahadut Hatorah, and of course the ruling Likud.&quot;
*&quot;If we don't figure out a way to strip these conflicts of their religious connotations, then we will never figure out a way to put an end to them. Because as long as these remain cosmic conflicts, they will go on for eternity.&quot;
*&quot;A lot of scholars, myself included, believe the future of Islam, especially Islamic democracy, rests in the Shia world. It's Iran and Iraq where the most exciting experiments are being carried out.&quot;
*&quot;Iraq’s 2,000-year-old Christian community is on the brink of extinction, its members targeted by al Qaeda attacks and fleeing abroad... This silence cannot stand. Americans of all faiths must band together and pressure the State Department to do something about the wanton murder of Iraqi Christians before it's too late and there are no more Christians in Iraq to protect. What is happening in Iraq is genocide, plain and simple. It must be stopped now.&quot;
*&quot;The fact of the matter is that Islam, like all religions, has been in a constant state of evolution for 1400 years. It has been constantly adapting to the spiritual, the cultural, the political, the social realities and the landscape in which it finds itself, which is why there is such a wide diversity of belief and practices within the Muslim world.&quot;

==See also==
*''[[No God but God]]'' (book)
*[[List of Islamic scholars]]
*[[Extremism]]
*[[List of Muslim reformers]]

==References==
{{reflist}}

==External links==
*[http://www.aslanmedia.com/ Official website]
*[http://asiasociety.org/node/11346/ Reza Aslan speaks at Asia Society, November 2010 (w/ video)]
*[http://www.levantinecenter.org/center/whos-who at Levantine Cultural Center]
* [http://www.ushmm.org/museum/exhibit/focus/antisemitism/voices/transcript/?content=20080103 Interview with Reza Aslan] from the U.S. Holocaust Memorial Museum
*[http://community.livejournal.com/rezaaslan  Reza Aslan's Intellectual Groupie's on Livejournal]
*[http://www.parstimes.com/books/reza_aslan.html His biography]
*[http://www.madrid11.net/articles/aslan280307 The Islamic reformation] Reza Aslan speaks with Madrid11.net
*[http://www.laweekly.com/la-people-2006/the-muslim-hipster/13219/ LA Weekly Interview]
*[http://www.islamicamagazine.com/content/view/168/59/ Reza Aslan Interview with Islamica Magazine]
*[http://uscpublicdiplomacy.com/index.php/newsroom/pdblog_main/author/Reza_Aslan/ Aslan's articles in the Public Diplomacy Blog]

===Video and audio===
*[http://www.gulenconference.net/index.php/component/content/article/36-headlines/108-invitation Reza Aslan is a keynote speaker in the upcoming conference] December 4–6, 2009 Los Angeles, USC CA
*[http://www.hotpotatomash.com/2008/04/video-exclusive.html Reza Aslan interviewed by Bree Walker] March 30, 2008
*[http://fora.tv/fora/showthread.php?t=89 Reza Aslan talks about The Future of U.S./Iran Relations (video)]
*[http://video.google.com/videoplay?docid=-1393002645436679402&amp;q=reza%20aslan&amp;hl=en Reza Aslan in Conversation with Jack Miles (video)]
*[http://video.google.com/videoplay?docid=8386232589075342922# Reza Aslan vs. Sam Harris Debate]
*[http://bloggingheads.tv/search/?participant1=Aslan,%20Reza Video debates featuring Aslan] on [[Bloggingheads.tv]]
*[http://www.kuow.org/defaultProgram.asp?ID=12298 Raza's talk, ''&quot;How to Get Out of the Cosmic War in the Middle East.&quot;'']
*[http://www.theyoungturks.com/story/2009/6/29/22532/9904 Reza talks to Cenk Uygur of The Young Turks.]

{{Persondata  &lt;!-- Metadata: see [[Wikipedia:Persondata]] --&gt;
|NAME= Aslan, Reza
|ALTERNATIVE NAMES=
|SHORT DESCRIPTION= Writer, scholar
|DATE OF BIRTH= May 3, 1972
|PLACE OF BIRTH= [[Tehran]], [[Tehran Province]], [[Iran]]
|DATE OF DEATH=
|PLACE OF DEATH=
}}
{{DEFAULTSORT:Aslan, Reza}}
[[Category:Islamic studies scholars]]
[[Category:American people of Iranian descent]]
[[Category:Iranian emigrants to the United States]]
[[Category:Iranian writers]]
[[Category:American Muslims]]
[[Category:Muslim reformers]]
[[Category:American Middle Eastern studies]]
[[Category:Naturalized citizens of the United States]]
[[Category:Harvard Divinity School alumni]]
[[Category:Santa Clara University alumni]]
[[Category:People from Tehran]]
[[Category:University of California, Santa Barbara alumni]]
[[Category:University of Iowa alumni]]
[[Category:1972 births]]
[[Category:Living people]]
[[Category:University of California, Riverside faculty]]
[[Category:University of Iowa faculty]]
[[Category:Iowa Writers' Workshop alumni]]
[[Category:Writers from California]]

[[ar:رضا أصلان]]
[[fa:رضا اصلان]]
[[nl:Reza Aslan]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
