<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="16629" ns="0" title="KDE"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{two other uses|the free software community|the desktop and others graphical environment|KDE Plasma Workspaces|}}

{{Infobox Non-profit
| Non-profit_name    = KDE
| Non-profit_logo    = [[Image:KDE logo.svg|100px]]
| founder            = [[Matthias Ettrich]]
| founded_date       = 14 October 1996
| Non-profit_type    = Community
| key_people         =
| focus              = [[Free software]]
| products           = [[KDE Software Compilation]], [[Calligra Suite]], [[KDevelop]], [[Amarok (software)|Amarok]], etc
| method             = Artwork, Development, Documentation, Promotion, and Translation.
| non-profit_slogan  = Experience Freedom!
| homepage           = {{url|http://kde.org/}}
}}

'''KDE''' ({{IPAc-en|icon|ˌ|k|eɪ|d|iː|ˈ|iː}}) is an international [[free software]] community producing an integrated set of [[cross-platform]] applications designed to run on [[Linux]], [[FreeBSD]], [[Microsoft Windows]], [[Solaris (operating system)|Solaris]] and Mac OS X systems. It is best known for its [[KDE Plasma Workspaces|Plasma Desktop]], a [[desktop environment]] provided as the default working environment on many Linux distributions, such as [[Kubuntu]], [[Pardus (operating system)|Pardus]] and [[openSUSE]].&lt;ref&gt;
{{cite news
| title = OpenSUSE community konfesses love for KDE, makes it default
| author = Ryan Paul
| url = http://arstechnica.com/open-source/news/2009/08/opensuse-community-konfesses-love-for-kde-makes-it-default.ars
| agency = Ars technica
| publisher = Condé Nast Digital
| date = 2009-08-21
|accessdate=2010-11-28
}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The goal of the community is to provide basic desktop functions and applications for daily needs as well as tools and documentation for developers to write stand-alone applications for the system. In this regard, the KDE project serves as an umbrella project for many standalone applications and smaller projects that are based on KDE technology. These include [[Calligra Suite]], [[digiKam]], [[Rekonq]], [[K3b]] and many others.

KDE software is based on the [[Qt (framework)|Qt]] framework. The original [[GNU General Public License|GPL]] version of this toolkit only existed for the [[X11]] platform, but with the release of Qt 4, [[GNU Lesser General Public License|LGPL]] versions are available for all platforms. This allows KDE software based on Qt 4 to also be distributed to Microsoft Windows and [[Mac OS X]].&lt;ref&gt;
{{cite news
| author=Ryan Paul
| title=KDE goes cross-platform with Windows, Mac OS X support
| date=January 23, 2008
| url =http://arstechnica.com/news.ars/post/20080123-kde-goes-cross-platform-with-windows-mac-os-x-support.html
| work =Ars Technica
| accessdate = 2010-12-04
}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== History ==
=== Origins ===
[[Image:Matthias Ettrich LinuxTag 2005-06-23.jpg|150px|thumb|Matthias Ettrich, Founder of KDE]]
KDE was founded in 1996 by [[Matthias Ettrich]], who was then a student at the [[Eberhard Karls University of Tübingen]]. At the time, he was troubled by certain aspects of the [[Unix]] desktop. Among his concerns was that none of the [[application software|applications]] looked, felt, or worked alike. He proposed the creation of not merely a set of applications but a desktop environment in which users could expect things to look, feel, and work consistently. He also wanted to make this desktop easy to use; one of his complaints about desktop applications of the time was that his girlfriend could not use them. His initial [[Usenet]] post spurred a lot of interest, and the KDE project was born.&lt;ref name=&quot;New Project: Kool Desktop Environment (KDE)&quot;&gt;
{{cite newsgroup
| title = New Project: Kool Desktop Environment (KDE)
|url=http://groups.google.com/group/de.comp.os.linux.misc/msg/cb4b2d67ffc3ffce
|first= Matthias
|last=Ettrich
|newsgroup= de.comp.os.linux.misc
|id=53tkvv$b4j@newsserv.zdv.uni-tuebingen.de
|date=14 October 1996
|accessdate=2010-12-04}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The name ''KDE'' was intended as a wordplay on the existing [[Common Desktop Environment]], available for Unix systems. CDE was an X11-based user environment jointly developed by HP, IBM, and Sun through the [[X/Open]] consortium, with an interface and productivity tools based on the [[Motif (widget toolkit)|Motif]] graphical widget toolkit. It was supposed to be an intuitively easy-to-use desktop computer
environment.&lt;ref&gt;
{{cite web
|url=http://bubl.ac.uk/ARCHIVE/subject/computing/misc/coseup6.htm
|title=COSE Update FYI
|accessdate= 2010-11-06
}}&lt;/ref&gt; The ''K'' was originally suggested to stand for &quot;[[wiktionary:kool|Kool]]&quot;, but it was quickly decided that the K should stand for nothing in particular. The ''KDE'' initialism is therefore expanded to ''&quot;K Desktop Environment&quot;''.

=== Product releases ===
{{main|KDE Software Compilation}}
[[Image:KDE 4.png|thumb|KDE Plasma Desktop 4.7, showing Gwenview and KRunner]]
Matthias Ettrich chose to use [[Trolltech|Trolltech’s]] Qt framework for the KDE project.&lt;ref&gt;
{{cite web
| url = http://events.kde.org/info/kastle/presentations/kastle-history/index.html
| title = history of the KDE project
| date = August 2003
| accessdate = 2010-12-02
}}&lt;/ref&gt; Other programmers quickly started developing KDE/Qt applications, and by early 1997, a few applications were being released. On 12 July 1998 the first version of the desktop environment, called KDE 1.0, was released.

{| class=&quot;wikitable&quot;
|-
!Version
!Date
!Information
|-
!
|October 14, 1996
|KDE development announced
|-
|style=&quot;background:#DCDCDC&quot;|'''1.0'''
|July 12, 1998
|
|-
|style=&quot;background:#DCDCDC&quot;|'''2.0'''
|October 23, 2000
|
|-
|style=&quot;background:#DCDCDC&quot;|'''3.0'''
|April 3, 2002
|
|-
|style=&quot;background:#DCDCDC&quot;|'''4.0'''
|January 11, 2008
|
|}

=== Licensing ===
In November 1998, the Qt framework was dual-licensed under the [[free and open source software|free and open source]] [[Q Public License]] (QPL) and a commercial license for proprietary software developers. The same year, the KDE Free Qt foundation was created which guarantees that Qt would fall under a variant of the very liberal [[BSD license]] should Trolltech cease to exist or no free version of Qt be released during 12 months.&lt;ref&gt;
{{cite web
|url=http://kde.org/community/whatiskde/kdefreeqtfoundation.php
|title=KDE Free Qt Foundation
|publisher=KDE
|accessdate=2010-11-13
}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Debate continued about compatibility with the GNU General Public License (GPL), hence in September 2000 Trolltech made the Unix version of the Qt libraries available under the GPL in addition to the QPL which eliminated the concerns of the [[Free Software Foundation]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news
|url = http://qt.nokia.com/about/news/archive/00000043
|title = Trolltech offers a choice in licensing with the addition of GPL licensing for the upcoming release of Qt
| date = 2000-09-05
| accessdate=2010-11-28
}}&lt;/ref&gt; Trolltech continued to require licenses for developing [[proprietary software]] with Qt. The core libraries of KDE are collectively licensed under the GNU LGPL but the only way for proprietary software to make use of them was to be developed under the terms of the Qt proprietary license.

Starting with Qt 4.5, Qt was also made available under the LGPL version 2.1,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news
| title = LGPL License Option Added to Qt
| author = Ryan Paul
| url = http://qt.nokia.com/about/news/lgpl-license-option-added-to-qt
| publisher = Nokia
| date =
| accessdate = 2010-11-13
}}&lt;/ref&gt; now allowing proprietary applications to legally use the open source Qt version.

=== Brand repositioning ===
On 24 November 2009 the KDE Marketing Team announced an official [[rebranding]] of the KDE project components, motivated by the perceived shift from building a desktop environment to a complete project around a community of &quot;people who create software&quot;. The rebranding focused on de-emphasizing the desktop environment as  &quot;just another product&quot;, and emphasizing both the community and the other technologies provided as KDE software. After the repositioning, the name ''KDE'' no longer stands for ''K Desktop Environment'', as it now acts as an umbrella brand for software produced by the community. What would have been previously known as KDE 4.4 will now be referred as &quot;KDE Software Compilation 4.4&quot; (abbreviated &quot;KDE SC 4.4&quot;). Regardless, many users still refer to it as KDE 4.&lt;ref&gt;
{{cite news
| title=Repositioning the KDE Brand
| url=http://dot.kde.org/2009/11/24/repositioning-kde-brand
| author = Stuart Jarvis
| agency = KDE.NEWS
| publisher = KDE
| date = 2009-11-24
| accessdate=2010-11-13
}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Community structure ==
=== Organization ===
The financial and legal matters of KDE are handled by [[KDE e.V.]], which is a German non-profit organization, and help organizing the conferences and meetings of the community members.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
| url = http://ev.kde.org/whatiskdeev.php
| title = KDE e.V. - What is KDE e.V.
|publisher= KDE e.V. Board
| accessdate = 2011-01-02}}&lt;/ref&gt; KDE e.V. helps running the servers needed by the KDE community. It owns the [[trademark]] on ''KDE'' and the logo. It pays for travel to meetings, and subsidizes events.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
| url = http://ev.kde.org/activities/
| title = KDE e.V. - KDE e.V. Activities
|publisher = KDE e.V. Board
| accessdate = 2011-01-08}}&lt;/ref&gt; The working groups are a structure which will formalize some roles within KDE and enhance coordination within KDE, communication between parts of KDE.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
|url= http://ev.kde.org/reports/2005-working-groups-discussion.php
|title= KDE Working Groups Discussion
|publisher=KDE e.V.
|accessdate=2011-01-02}}&lt;/ref&gt; KDE e.V. has no influence on development. KDE e.V. logo has been contributed by [[David Vignoni]]. The three flags on top of the logo represent the three main tasks of the KDE e.V.: supporting the community, representing the community, and governing the community.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news
| url = http://dot.kde.org/2008/08/12/kde-ev-endorses-community-working-group-code-conduct
| title = KDE e.V. Endorses Community Working Group, Code of Conduct
| author = Sebastian Kuegler
| date = 2008-08-12
| agency = KDE.NEWS
| publisher = KDE
| accessdate = 2010-12-24}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The KDE community's developer meetings, servers and related events are frequently [[sponsor (commercial)|sponsor]]ed by individuals, universities, and businesses.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
|url= http://kde.org/community/donations/past_sponsors.php
|title= KDE – Sponsorship Thanks
|accessdate=2010-11-13}}&lt;/ref&gt; The ''supporting members'' of the KDE e.V. are extraordinary members supporting the KDE through financial or material contributions.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
|url= http://ev.kde.org/corporate/statutes.php
|title= Articles of Association
|accessdate=2010-11-28}}&lt;/ref&gt; Supporting members are entitled to display the ''&quot;Member of KDE&quot;'' logo on their website or in printed materials. The ''Patron of KDE'' is the highest level of supporting member. The patrons of KDE also are entitled to display the exclusive ''&quot;Patron of KDE&quot;'' logo on their website or in printed materials.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
|url=http://ev.kde.org/getinvolved/supporting-members.php
|title= Become a Supporting Member of the KDE e.V.
|accessdate=2010-11-12}}&lt;/ref&gt; On 15 October 2006, it was announced that [[Mark Shuttleworth]] had become the first ''Patron of KDE''.&lt;ref name=&quot;kdepatron&quot;&gt;{{cite news
| url = http://dot.kde.org/2006/10/15/mark-shuttleworth-becomes-first-patron-kde
| title = Mark Shuttleworth Becomes the First Patron of KDE
| author = Danny Allen
| date = 2006-10-16
| agency = KDE.NEWS
| publisher = KDE
| accessdate = 2010-11-13}}&lt;/ref&gt; On 7 July 2007, it was announced that Intel Corporation and Novell had also become patrons of KDE.&lt;ref&gt;
{{cite news
| url = http://dot.kde.org/2007/07/07/intel-and-novell-become-patrons-kde
| title = Intel and Novell Become Patrons of KDE
| author = Francis Giannaros
| date = 2007-07-07
| agency = KDE.NEWS
| publisher = KDE
| accessdate = 2010-11-13}}&lt;/ref&gt; In January 2010, Google became a supporting member. On 9 June 2010, KDE e.V. launched the &quot;Join the Game&quot; campaign. This campaign promotes the idea of becoming a supporting member for individuals. It is made available for those who would like to support KDE, but do not have enough time to do so. [[Georg Greve]], founder of the [[Free Software Foundation Europe]] (FSFE) was first to 'join the game'.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news
| url = http://dot.kde.org/2010/06/09/announcing-kde-ev-supporting-membership
| title = Announcing the KDE e.V. Supporting Membership
| author = Jos Poortvliet
| date = 2010-06-09
| agency = KDE.NEWS
| publisher = KDE
| accessdate = 2010-12-24}}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Local community ===
In many countries, KDE has local branches. These are either informal organizations (KDE India) or like the KDE e.V., given a legal form (KDE France). The local organizations hosts and maintains a regional website, and organising local events, such as tradeshows, contributor meetings and social community meetings.

[[Image:KDE-AR Official Logo.png|right|80px|thumb|KDE-AR Logo]]
KDE-AR (KDE Argentina) is the group of KDE developers and users in Argentina, was officially opened in 22 November 2008 at the meeting in IRC channel. They can organize release parties on holidays to celebrate released of new version of the KDE SC since 4.2. KDE-AR has their own mailing lists and IRC channel.

KDE Brasil is composed by several local groups in Brazil, like KDE-MG, Live Blue, KDE Piauí, and KDE-RS. The main goals of local groups are regional promotion and direction of contributions of members, and still maintaining harmony with the KDE Brazil community. KDE-MG is a local group in [[Minas Gerais]]. The idea of structuring the group was arose during the FISL (Fórum Internacional Software Livre) 10. Live Blue is a KDE working group in [[Bahia]]. KDE Piauí is a group of users and contributors of KDE in the [[Piauí]]. The ideia was born during the Software Freedom Day Teresina 2009 and has concretized during the Akademy-Br 2010, where the group was officially created. KDE-RS is a group of KDE users from [[Rio Grande do Sul]]. KDE Lovelace is a Brazilian female group of users and contributors in KDE.

KDE España was registered as an association under the Spanish law in 2009. The aim is stimulating the development and use of the KDE software in Spain. The supreme governing body is general assembly, which is ordinary or extraordinary. The ordinary general assembly is held at least once a year. The extraordinary general assembly is held as necessary. The board consists of president, vice president, secretary, treasurer and members. Current board are Albert Astals Cid (president), Alejandro Fiestas Olivares (vice president), Aleix Pol i Gonzàlez (secretary), and José Millán Soto (treasurer).&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
| url = http://www.kde-espana.es/junta.php
| title = KDE España-Junta Directiva
|publisher = KDE España
| accessdate = 2011-07-24}}&lt;/ref&gt; In addition, KDE España is the official representative of KDE e.V. in Spain.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
| url = http://ev.kde.org/announcements/2010-07-14-kde-espania.php
| title = KDE España to represent KDE e.V. in Spain
|publisher=KDE e.V. Board
| accessdate = 2010-11-13}}&lt;/ref&gt;

KDE.in (KDE India) was founded in 2005, provide Indian KDE developers and users with a community hub to coordinate with and support each other. Besides making efforts in the internationalization and localization, a major aim is to foster the creation and adaptation of KDE applications to needs specific to India.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news
| url = http://dot.kde.org/2005/12/10/kaun-banega-kde-hacker-kde-india-founded
| title = Kaun Banega KDE Hacker: KDE India Founded
| author = Daniel Molkentin
| date = 2005-12-10
| agency = KDE.NEWS
| publisher = KDE
| accessdate = 2011-05-04}}&lt;/ref&gt;

{{nihongo|Japan KDE Users' Group|JKUG/日本 KDE ユーザ会|Nihon KDE Yūzakai}} is Japanese local users' group of KDE. The membership type of the association are {{nihongo|corporate members|法人会員|hōjin kaiin}} and {{nihongo|individual members|個人会員|kojin kaiin}}. About 15 member is active staff. The officers include one {{nihongo|president|会長|kaichō}}, two {{nihongo|vice presidents|副会長|fuku-kaichō}} and one accountant. Currently, president is {{nihongo|Daisuke Kameda|亀田大輔|Kameda Daisuke}}, vice presidents are {{nihongo|Taiki Komoda|菰田泰生|Komoda Taiki}} and {{nihongo|暁 Satō|佐藤暁|Satō 暁}}&lt;!-- 暁 can be read &quot;Akatsuki&quot;, &quot;Akira&quot; or &quot;Satoru&quot; when it is a given name. Which one is it here? --&gt;. The association will hold an annual general assembly in December.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
| url = http://www.kde.gr.jp/
| title = Japan KDE Users' Group website
|publisher= 日本 KDE ユーザ会
| accessdate = 2011-02-03}}&lt;/ref&gt; It's activities include message translation to Japanese, making patch for multilingualization, and exchanging information about KDE/Qt.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news
| url = http://dot.kde.org/2008/04/17/japan-kde-users-group-interview
| title = Japan KDE Users Group Interview
| author = Jonathan Riddell
| date = 2008-04-17
| agency = KDE.NEWS
| publisher = KDE
| accessdate = 2011-04-20}}&lt;/ref&gt;

KDE GB is a KDE community with a constitution in Britain. At October 2010 meeting they agreed to register as a charity.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
| url = http://community.kde.org/KDE_GB
| title = KDE GB - KDE Community Wiki
|publisher=
| accessdate = 2011-02-12}}&lt;/ref&gt; KDE-ir (فارسی KDE) is a Persian KDE community. Korean KDE Users Group was started in 1999. The group's work is mostly translation.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news
| url = http://dot.kde.org/2008/04/28/kde-korea
| title = KDE in Korea
| author = Jonathan Riddell
| date = 2008-04-28
| agency = KDE.NEWS
| publisher = KDE
| accessdate = 2011-04-23}}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Communication ===
The communication within the community takes place via mailing lists, IRC, blogs, forums, news announcements, [[wiki]]s, and conferences. The community has the ''Code of Conduct'' for acceptable behaviour within the community.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
|url= http://www.kde.org/code-of-conduct/
|title= KDE Community Code of Conduct
|accessdate=2010-11-28}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The [[mailing list]]s are one of the main communication channels, and most problems are discussed on here. The community has several mailing lists, has two general user lists: ''Kde'' for discussion of users, and ''Kde-announce'' for version updates, security patches and other changes. And two general development lists: ''Kde-devel'', for communication of application developers, and ''Kde-core-devel'' for communication of development of [[KDE Platform]]. Many applications also have specific mailing lists.

KDE Community Forums is also activity in discuss. The forums have ''Brainstorm'' for user submit ideas to developers. The wish can be approved or disapproved by other users. Every few months, the highest-voted features will then be submitted to the developers.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news
| url = http://dot.kde.org/2009/03/20/kde-brainstorm-get-your-ideas-kde
| title = KDE Brainstorm: Get Your Ideas Into KDE!
| author = Luca Beltrame
| date = 2009-03-20
| agency = KDE.NEWS
| publisher = KDE
| accessdate = 2010-12-18}}&lt;/ref&gt; The forums have IRC bots that can announce new threads and posts on IRC channels, briding forum posts to mailinglist messages and offering RSS feeds.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news
| url = http://dot.kde.org/2008/10/12/kde-launches-user-forums
| title = KDE Launches User Forums
| author = Sebastian Kuegler
| date = 2008-10-12
| agency = KDE.NEWS
| publisher = KDE
| accessdate = 2011-01-01}}&lt;/ref&gt;

KDE has three wikis: UserBase, TechBase and Community Wiki. UserBase provides documentation for end user. It contains tutorials, links to where to get more help, as well as an application catalogue. The logo is designed by Eugene Trounev.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news
| url = http://dot.kde.org/2008/09/19/userbase-goes-live
| title = UserBase Goes Live!
| author = Lydia Pintscher
| date = 2008-09-19
| agency = KDE.NEWS
| publisher = KDE
| accessdate = 2010-12-24}}&lt;/ref&gt; TechBase provides technical documentation for developers and system administrators.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
|url= http://www.kde.org/support/
|title= KDE-Support
|publisher=KDE
|accessdate=2010-11-28}}&lt;/ref&gt; Community Wiki provides a place for coordinating community teams. It is used for publishing and sharing community-internal information.

And [[Internet Relay Chat|IRC]] channels is real-time discuss way. Planet KDE is made from the blogs of KDE's contributors. [[KDE Dot News|KDE.News]] is the website of office news announcements.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news
| url = http://news.kde.org/2000/09/21/kde-dot-news-goes-live
| title = KDE Dot News goes live!
| author = Navindra Umanee
| date = 2000-09-21
| agency = KDE.NEWS
| publisher = KDE
| accessdate = 2011-01-02}}&lt;/ref&gt; KDE Buzz tracks identi.ca, Twitter, Picasa, Flickr and YouTube to show social media activity concerning KDE.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news
| url = http://dot.kde.org/2009/08/04/new-kde-buzz
| title = New KDE Buzz
| author = Will Stephenson
| date = 2009-08-04
| agency = KDE.NEWS
| publisher = KDE
| accessdate = 2010-12-24}}&lt;/ref&gt; KDE Pastebin allows for posting of source code snippets and uses syntax highlighting which adds ease to reviewing code. The pastes can be password protected. And use RSS notification to get aware of new posts.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news
| url = http://www.linux-magazine.com/Online/News/KDE-s-Pastebin
| title = KDE's Pastebin
| author = Amber Graner
| date = 2010-12-28
| agency = Linux Magazine
| publisher = Linux New Media
| accessdate = 2011-02-01}}&lt;/ref&gt; KDE Bug Tracking System provides anyone, who report bugs that was found in the software. Bug tracking uses [[Bugzilla]]. Behind KDE is a site that interviews contributor of KDE.

=== Identity ===
[[Image:Konqi svg.svg|right|120px|thumb|Konqi, mascot of the KDE community]]

The KDE community’s [[mascot]] is a green dragon named [[Konqi]].&lt;ref&gt;
{{cite web
|url=http://www.kde.org/stuff/clipart.php
|title= KDE-Clipart page
|accessdate=2010-11-20
}}&lt;/ref&gt; Konqi has a girlfriend named Katie. Konqi and Katie made their costumed appearance at the KDE 4.0 Release Event and Camp KDE 2010.&lt;ref&gt;
{{cite news
| url = http://dot.kde.org/2010/01/25/camp-kde-2010-wrapup
| title = Camp KDE 2010 Wrapup
| author = Troy Unrau
| date = 2010-01-25
| agency = KDE.NEWS
| publisher = KDE
| accessdate = 2011-03-05
}}&lt;/ref&gt; Konqi also appeared on the KDE software's about dialog. [[Konqi#Kandalf|Kandalf the wizard]] was the former mascot for the KDE community during its 1.x and 2.x versions, but he was dropped owing to copyright issues (his resemblance to [[Gandalf]]).

KDE has community identity guidelines (CIG) for definitions and recommendations which help the community to establish a unique, characteristic, and appealing design.&lt;ref&gt;
{{cite web
|url= http://techbase.kde.org/Development/Guidelines/CIG
|title= Community Identity Guidelines
|accessdate=2010-12-01
}}&lt;/ref&gt; The KDE official logo displays the white trademarked K-Gear shape on a blue square with mitred corners.Copying of the KDE Logo is subject to the LGPL.&lt;ref&gt;
{{cite web
|url= http://techbase.kde.org/Development/Guidelines/CIG/KDE_Logo
|title= The KDE CIG Logo page
|date= September 28, 2006
|accessdate=2010-11-06
}}&lt;/ref&gt; Some local community logos are derivations of the official logo. The KDE software labels are used by producers of software to show that they are part of the KDE community or that they use the KDE Platform. There are three labels available. The ''Powered by KDE'' label is used to show that an application derives its strength from the KDE community and from the KDE development platform. The ''Built on the KDE Platform'' label indicates that the application uses the KDE platform. The ''Part of the KDE family'' label is used by application authors to identify themselves as being part of the KDE community.&lt;ref&gt;
{{cite news
| title= Introducing Your KDE Software Labels
| url= http://dot.kde.org/2010/06/21/introducing-your-kde-software-labels
| author = Stuart Jarvis
| agency = KDE.NEWS
| publisher = KDE
| date = 2010-06-21
| accessdate=2010-11-13
}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;gallery perrow=&quot;6&quot;&gt;
Image:KDE Logo Official Lineart Detailed.svg|Line art logo
Image:KDE logo.svg|Oxygen Logo
Image:Klogo-official-crystal.svg|Crystal logo, used during KDE 3 releases.
Image:KDE-AR Official Logo.png|KDE-AR Official Logo
Image:KDE Chile Logo Official Oxygen.svg|KDE Chile Official Logo
&lt;/gallery&gt;

Many KDE applications have a ''K'' in the name, mostly as an initial letter. The ''K'' in many KDE applications is obtained by spelling a word which originally begins with ''C'' or ''Q'' differently, for example [[Konsole]] and [[Kaffeine]]. Also, some just prefix a commonly used word with a ''K'', for instance [[KGet]]. Among KDE SC 4 applications and technologies, however, the trend is not to have a ''K'' in the name at all, such as [[Calligra Stage|Stage]] and [[Dolphin (software)|Dolphin]].

== Contributors ==
{| class=&quot;wikitable&quot; border=&quot;1&quot; align=&quot;right&quot;
|- style=&quot;background:#efefef;&quot;
! colspan=&quot;2&quot; | Featured Partners
|- style=&quot;background:#efefef;&quot;
! Name !! Work
|-
| [[Nuno Pinheiro (artist)|Nuno Pinheiro]] || Oxygen
|-
| [[David Vignoni]] ||Oxygen
|-
| [[Eugene Trounev]] ||Artists
|-
| [[Aaron Seigo]] ||Develop
|-
| [[David Faure]] ||Develop
|-
| [[Duncan Mac-Vicar Prett]] || Develop
|-
| [[Dirk Müller (programmer)|Dirk Müller]] || Release, Develop
|-
| [[George Staikos]] || Develop
|-
| [[Lars Knoll]] || Develop
|-
| [[Volker Krause]] || Develop
|-
| [[Waldo Bastian]] || Develop
|-
|[[Sebastian Kügler]] || Marketing team liaison
|-
|[[Stuart Jarvis]] || Marketing and public relations
|}
Like many free/open source software projects, KDE is primarily a volunteer effort, although various companies, such as [[Novell]], [[Nokia]], and [[Mandriva]], employ developers to work on the project. Since a large number of individuals contribute to KDE in various ways (e.g. code, translation, artwork), organization of such a project is complex.

=== Development ===
The overall direction of the [[KDE Platform]] is made on the ''KDE Core Team''. These are developers who have made significant contributions to KDE over a long period of time. This team communicates using the ''kde-core-devel'' mailing list, which is publicly archived and readable, but joining requires approval. KDE does not have a single central leader who can veto important decisions. Instead, the KDE core team consisting of several dozen contributors takes decisions. The decisions do not take a formal vote, but through discussions.&lt;ref&gt;
{{cite web
| url = http://www.kde.org/community/whatiskde/management.php
| title = Project Management
| accessdate = 2010-11-13}}&lt;/ref&gt; The Developers also organize alongside topical teams. For example, the ''[[KDE Education Project|KDE Edu team]]'' develops free educational software. While these teams work mostly independent and do not all follow a common release schedule. Each team has its own messaging channels, both on IRC and on the mailinglists. And they have mentor program which helps beginner to get start.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
|url = http://www.kde.org/community/getinvolved/development/
|title= Becoming a KDE Developer
|accessdate = 2011-01-01}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal
| author = George Kuk
| title = Strategic Interaction and Knowledge Sharing in the KDE Developer Mailing List
| journal = Management Science
| year = 2006
| volume = 52
| pages = 1031–1042
| doi =
| url = http://mansci.journal.informs.org/cgi/reprint/52/7/1031
| issue=7
}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Currently KDE community uses the [[Git (software)|Git]] repository. KDE Projects site gives an overview of all projects within Git repository. QuickGit is another repository browser. It shows all the git repositories. ReviewBoard site gives patch review. Commitfilter will send an email with each commit for the projects you want to watch, without either getting tons of mails or getting infrequent and redundant information. English Breakfast Network (EBN) is a collection of machines that do automated KDE source artifact quality checking. The EBN provides KDE API documentation validation, user documentation validation, source code checking. It is operated by [[Adriaan de Groot (Software developer)|Adriaan de Groot]] and Allen Winter. Commit-Digest site gives a weekly overview of the development activity. LXR indexes classes and methods used in KDE.

Season of KDE (SoK) is a program for people could not get accepted into Google Summer of Code. They will have a mentor from the KDE community to help them if any question arises or if they do not know how to continue.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
|url= http://developer.kde.org/seasonofkde/
|title= Season of KDE 2006
|accessdate=2011-05-04}}&lt;/ref&gt;

On 20 July 2009, KDE announced that the one millionth commit has been made to its Subversion repository.&lt;ref name=&quot;KDE Reaches 1,000,000 Commits in its Subversion Repository&quot;&gt;{{cite news
| url = http://dot.kde.org/2009/07/20/kde-reaches-1000000-commits-its-subversion-repository
| title = KDE Reaches 1,000,000 Commits in its Subversion Repository
| author = Jeff Mitchell
| agency = KDE.NEWS
| publisher = KDE
| date = 2009-07-20
| accessdate = 2010-11-13}}&lt;/ref&gt; On October 11, 2009, [[Cornelius Schumacher]], a main developer within KDE,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
|url= http://www.behindkde.org/node/403
|title= People Behind KDE: Cornelius Schumacher
|date= February 4, 2002
|accessdate=2010-11-18}}&lt;/ref&gt; wrote about the estimated cost (using the [[COCOMO]] model with SLOCCount) to develop KDE software package with 4,273,291 [[Lines of Code|LoC]], which would be about US$175,364,716.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news
| url = http://www.linuxpromagazine.com/Online/News/Code-Statistics-KDE-Costs-175-Million-Dollars
| title = Code Statistics: KDE Costs 175 Million Dollars
| author = Marcel Hilzinger
| agency = Linux Magazine
| publisher =
| date = 2009-10-12
| accessdate = 2010-12-30}}&lt;/ref&gt; This estimation does not include Qt, [[Calligra Suite]], [[Amarok (software)|Amarok]], [[Digikam]], and other applications that are not part of KDE core.

The work can be measured in figures:
* Over 6 million lines of code. This does not include [[Qt (framework)|Qt]].&lt;ref name=&quot;kde-press-page&quot;&gt;{{cite web
| url     = http://www.kde.org/presspage/
| title   = KDE – Press page
| publisher = KDE
|accessdate=2010-12-30}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* More than 1800 contributors help develop KDE.&lt;ref name=&quot;kde-press-page&quot; /&gt; About 20 new developers contribute their first code each month.&lt;ref name=&quot;KDE Reaches 1,000,000 Commits in its Subversion Repository&quot; /&gt;
* KDE is translated in over 108 languages.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
|url= http://i18n.kde.org/stats/gui/stable-kde4/essential/
|title= KDE Localization statistics
|date= 5 November 2010
|accessdate=2010-11-06}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* KDE has more than 114 official FTP mirrors in over 34 countries.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
|url= http://download.kde.org/mirrorstatus.html
|title= the status of KDE mirrors
|accessdate=2010-11-06}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* The KDE community is the second largest Free Software community behind the Linux kernel community.&lt;ref name=&quot;kde-press-page&quot; /&gt;

=== Other groups ===
The KDE community has many smaller teams working towards specific goals. The ''[[KDE Accessibility Project|Accessibility team]]'' make KDE accessible to all users, including those with physical handicaps.&lt;ref&gt;
{{cite web
|url = http://www.kde.org/community/getinvolved/accessibility/
|title= Getting Started with KDE Accessibility
|accessdate = 2011-01-01
}}&lt;/ref&gt; The ''Artists team'' has designed most of the artwork used by the software like icons, wallpapers and themes. They have also produced graphics for t-shirts and websites. Discuss of the team is most active on the IRC channel.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
|url=http://kde.org/community/getinvolved/art/
|title=Becoming a KDE Artist
|publisher=KDE
|accessdate=2010-11-13}}&lt;/ref&gt; The ''Bugsquad team'' keeps track of incoming bugs. They verify that a
bug exists, that it is reproducible, and that the reporter has given enough
information. The goal is to help developers notice valid bugs quicker, and to save their time.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
|url= http://techbase.kde.org/Contribute/Bugsquad
|title= Contribute/Bugsquad
|accessdate=2010-12-31}}&lt;/ref&gt; The ''Documentation team'' writing documentation for application.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
|url=http://kde.org/community/getinvolved/documentation/
|title= Get Involved with KDE Documentation
|publisher=KDE
|accessdate=2010-11-28}}&lt;/ref&gt; The team uses the [[DocBook]] format and custom tools to create documentation.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
|url = http://l10n.kde.org/docs/tools.php
|title = The KDE DocBook XML toolchain
|accessdate = 2010-11-28}}&lt;/ref&gt; The ''Localization team'' translate KDE software into many different languages. This team works beside the Documentation team.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
|url= http://kde.org/community/getinvolved/translation/
|title= KDE – Get Involved with KDE Translation
|accessdate=2010-11-22}}&lt;/ref&gt; The ''Marketing and Promotion team'' manages marketing and promotion. The team writes news articles, release announcements and other webpages on KDE websites. The articles of KDE.News is submitted by the team. It also has channels at social media sites for communication and promotion. They also attend conference events.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
|url=http://kde.org/community/getinvolved/promotion/
|title= Get Involved with KDE Promotion
|accessdate=2010-11-13}}&lt;/ref&gt; The ''Research team'' is to improve the collaboration with external parties to achieve more funded research. They support community members by providing information, navigating bureaucracies, and matching research partners. The ''usability team'' has written a [[human interface guidelines|Human Interface Guideline]] (HIG) for the developers and they do regular reviews of KDE applications. The HIG provides a standardized layout.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
|url= http://techbase.kde.org/Projects/Usability/HIG
|title= KDE Human Interface Guidelines
|accessdate=2010-12-01
}}&lt;/ref&gt; The ''Web team'' maintains KDE’s web presence. The ''KDE Women'' help women to contribute and encourage women to give talks at conferences.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal
| author = Yixin Qiu, Katherine J. Stewart, and Kathryn M. Bartol
| title = Joining and Socialization in Open Source Women’s Groups: An Exploratory Study of KDE-Women
| journal = IFIP Advances in Information and Communication Technology
| year = 2010
| volume = 319
| pages = 239–251
| doi = 10.1007/978-3-642-13244-5_19
| url =
}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The ''Release team'' defines and executes the official software releases. The Team is responsible for setting release schedules for the official releases. This includes release dates, deadlines for individual release steps and restrictions for code changes. The Release Team coordinates release dates with the marketing and press efforts of KDE. The release team is composed of Module Coordinators, Marketing Team liaison, and the people who actually do the work of tagging and creating the releases.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
|url=http://techbase.kde.org/Projects/Release_Team
|title= Projects/Release Team
|accessdate=2010-11-22}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Activities ==
The two most important conferences of KDE are ''Akademy'' and ''Camp KDE''. Each event is on a large scale, both thematically and geographically. ''Akademy-BR'' and ''Akademy-es'' are local community events.

=== Akademy ===
[[File:Akademy 2008 logo.png|right|150px|thumb|Akademy 2008 logo]]

''[[Akademy]]'' is the annual world summit, held each summer at varying venues in Europe.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
| url     = http://ev.kde.org/akademy/
| title   = KDE e.V. - Akademy
| publisher = KDE e.V.
| accessdate=2010-11-13}}&lt;/ref&gt; The primary goals of Akademy are to act as a community building event, to communicate the achievements of community, and to provide a platform for collaboration with community and industry partners. Secondary goals are to engage local people, and to provide space for getting together to write code. [[KDE e.V.]] assist with procedures, advice and organization. Akademy including conference, KDE e.V. general assembly, marathon coding sessions, BOFs ([[Birds of a Feather (computing)|birds of a feather]] sessions) and social program. BOFs are meet to discuss specific sub-projects or issues.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
| url     = http://ev.kde.org/akademy/requirements.php
| title   = Requirements for Akademy Location
| publisher = KDE e.V.
| accessdate = 2010-11-13}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The KDE community held KDE One that was first conference in [[Arnsberg]], Germany in 1997 to discuss the first KDE release. Initially, each conference was numbered after the release, and not regular hold. Since 2003 the conferences were hold one a year. And they were named Akademy since 2004.

The yearly Akademy conference gives ''Akademy Awards'', are awards that the KDE community gives to KDE contributors. Their purpose is to recognize outstanding contribution to KDE. There are three awards, best application, best non-application and jury's award. As always the winners are chosen by the winners from the previous year.&lt;ref&gt;
{{cite news
| title= Akademy Awards 2009
| url= http://dot.kde.org/2009/07/06/akademy-awards-2009
| author = Jonathan Riddell
| agency = KDE.NEWS
| publisher = KDE
| date = 2009-07-06
| accessdate=2011-01-07
}}&lt;/ref&gt; First winners received a framed picture of [[Konqi]] signed by all attending KDE developers.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news
| title= First KDE Appreciation Awards Announced
| url= http://dot.kde.org/2005/08/30/first-kde-appreciation-awards-announced
| author = Daniel Molkentin
| agency = KDE.NEWS
| publisher = KDE
| date = 2005-08-30
| accessdate=2011-01-07}}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Camp KDE ===
{|- class=&quot;wikitable&quot; align=&quot;right&quot;
|- style=&quot;background:#efefef;&quot;
!Year
!Venue
!Date
|-
!2009
|[[Negril]], [[Jamaica]]
| 1/17-1/18
|-
!2010
|[[La Jolla]], [[USA]]
| 1/15-1/22
|-
!2011
|[[San Francisco]], USA
| 4/4-4/5
|-
|}

''Camp KDE'' is another annual contributor’s conference of the KDE community. The event provides a regional opportunity for contributors and enthusiasts to gather and share their experiences. It's free to all participants. It is intended to ensure that KDE in the world is not simply seen as being Euro-centric. The KDE e.V. helps travel and accommodation subsidies for presenters, BoF leaders, organizers or  core contributor. It is held in the North America since 2009.

In January 2008, KDE 4.0 Release Event was held at the Google headquarters in Mountain View, California, USA to celebrate the release of KDE SC 4.0. The community realized that there was a strong demand for KDE events in the Americas, therefore Camp KDE was produced.

Camp KDE 2009 was the premiere meeting of the KDE Americas, was held at the Travellers Beach Resort in Negril, Jamaica, sponsored by Google, Inte, iXsystem, KDE e.V. and Kitware. The event included 1-2 days of presentations, BoF meetings and [[hackathon]] sessions.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news
| title= Camp KDE 2009 Presentations Announced
| url= http://dot.kde.org/2008/11/30/camp-kde-2009-presentations-announced
| author = Wade Olson
| agency = KDE.NEWS
| publisher = KDE
| date = 2008-11-30
| accessdate=2010-11-28}}&lt;/ref&gt; Camp KDE 2010 took place at the [[University of California San Diego]] (UCSD) in La Jolla, USA. The schedule included presentations, BoFs, hackathons and a day trip. It started with a short introduction by Jeff Mitchell, who was the principal organizer of the conference, talked a bit of history about Camp KDE and some statistics about the KDE community. The talks of the event were relatively well attended, and an increase over the previous year to around 70 people. On 1/19, the social event was a tour of a local brewery.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news
| title= Announcing Camp KDE 2010!
| url= http://dot.kde.org/2009/08/07/announcing-camp-kde-2010
| author = Jeff Mitchell
| agency = KDE.NEWS
| publisher = KDE
| date = 2009-08-07
| accessdate=2010-11-28}}&lt;/ref&gt; Camp KDE 2011 was held at Hotel Kabuki in San Francisco, USA, was co-located with the Linux Foundation Collaboration Summit. The schedule included presentations, hackathons and a party at Noisebridge. The conference opened with a introduction spoken by [[Celeste Lyn Paul]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news
| title= Camp KDE 2011 Announced
| url= http://news.kde.org/2011/02/05/camp-kde-2011-announced
| author = Celeste Lyn Paul
| agency = KDE.NEWS
| publisher = KDE
| date = 2011-02-05
| accessdate=2011-01-07}}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Akademy-es ===
{|- class=&quot;wikitable&quot; align=&quot;right&quot;
|- style=&quot;background:#efefef;&quot;
!Year
!Venue
!Date
|-
!2006
|[[Barcelona]]
| 3/3-3/5
|-
!2007
|[[Zaragoza]]
| 11/17-11/18
|-
!2008
|[[A Coruña]]
| 11/21-11/23
|-
!2009
|[[Gran Canaria]]
| 7/10-7/11
|-
!2010
|[[Bilbao]]
| 5/7-5/9
|-
!2011
| Barcelona
| 5/20-5/22
|-
|}

''Akademy-es'' is a conference for Spanish community since 2006, aimed at Spanish speakers. The event is organized by Spanish local organization. KDE España organizes the event since 2008. The annual KDE España Assembly took place during the event.

Akademy-es 2006 was held at Espai Jove Bocanord in Barcelona, organized by Badopi.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news
| url = http://dot.kde.org/2006/02/09/akademy-es-2006-barcelona
| title = aKademy-es 2006 in Barcelona
| author = Antonio Larrosa
| date = 2006-02-09
| agency = KDE.NEWS
| publisher = KDE
| accessdate = 2011-01-03}}&lt;/ref&gt; Akademy-es 2007 was hosted by Hispalinux, Wireless Zaragoza, and the Zaragoza council.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news
| title= Akademy-es 2007 in Zaragoza Spain
| url= http://dot.kde.org/2007/11/22/akademy-es-2007-zaragoza-spain
| author = Aleix Pol Gonzalez
| agency = KDE.NEWS
| publisher = KDE
| date = 2007-11-22
| accessdate=2010-11-28}}&lt;/ref&gt; Akademy-es 2008 was held at [[University of A Coruña]], was organized by the KDE España and GPUL, sponsored by Oficina de Software Libre de la Universidad de Coruña, Mancomun, Igalia, Qt Software and eyeOs.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news
| title= Akademy-es 2008 in A Coruña
| url= http://dot.kde.org/2008/11/15/akademy-es-2008-coru%C3%B1
| author = Albert Astals Cid
| agency = KDE.NEWS
| publisher = KDE
| date = 2008-11-15
| accessdate=2011-01-02}}&lt;/ref&gt; Akademy-es 2009 was held in the [[University of Las Palmas de Gran Canaria]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news
| title= Akademy-es 2009
| url= http://dot.kde.org/2009/07/23/akademy-es-2009
| author = Albert Astals Cid
| agency = KDE.NEWS
| publisher = KDE
| date = 2009-07-23
| accessdate=2010-11-17}}&lt;/ref&gt; Akademy-es 2010 was held in the Engineering Technical School of Bilbao, was organized by KDE España and Itsas. There were approximately 80 participants. The KDE España Assembly elected the new board consists of Albert Astals Cid (president), Rafael Fernández López (vice president), Aleix Pol (secretary), and José Millán Soto (treasurer).&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news
| title= Akademy-es 2010
| url= http://dot.kde.org/2010/03/09/akademy-es-2010
| author = Albert Astals Cid
| agency = KDE.NEWS
| publisher = KDE
| date = 2010-03-09
| accessdate=2011-01-03}}&lt;/ref&gt; Akademy-es 2011 was organized by KDE España, was sponsored by Google and Nokia, and was supported by the Linux and Todo-Linux magazines. The event was held in the in two different locations: the Polytechnic University of Catalunya for presentations of fist day, The School of Sant Marc de Sarrià for last two day.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news
| title= KDE Spain announces Akademy-es 2011
| url= http://news.kde.org/2011/04/08/kde-spain-announces-akademy-es-2011
| author = Albert Astals Cid
| agency = KDE.NEWS
| publisher = KDE
| date = 2011-04-08}}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Other community events ===
''Akademy-BR'' is addressed to Brazilian community since 2010. The purpose of the meeting is to gather and organize ideas Brazilian developers on how to help KDE in Brazil. Akademy-BR 2010 was organized by the local group named LiveBlue. There were thirty participants from all over the Brazil.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book
|author = Danny Allen, Artur Souza, Claudia Rauch, Torsten Thelke, Jos Poortvliet, Justin Kirby
|url= http://ev.kde.org/reports/ev-quarterly-2010Q2.pdf
|title= KDE e.V. Quarterly Report 2010Q2 (Issue 14)
|date= 24 August  2010
| pages = 5
| publisher = KDE e.V.
|accessdate=2011-01-01}}&lt;/ref&gt; Akademy-BR 2011 is organized by KDE-MG.

{|- class=&quot;wikitable&quot;
|- style=&quot;background:#efefef;&quot;
! colspan=&quot;3&quot; | Akademy-BR
|- style=&quot;background:#efefef;&quot;
!Year
!Venue
!Date
|-
!2010
|[[Salvador, Bahia|Salvador]]
| 4/9-4/11
|-
!2011
|[[São Paulo]]
| 11/12-11/15
|-
|}

{|- class=&quot;wikitable&quot; align=&quot;right&quot;
|- style=&quot;background:#efefef;&quot;
! colspan=&quot;3&quot; | conf.KDE.in
|- style=&quot;background:#efefef;&quot;
!Year
!Venue
!Date
|-
!2011
|[[Bengaluru]]
| 3/9-3/13
|-
|}

''conf.KDE.in'' is the first KDE and Qt conference in India. The conference was organized by KDE India, was held at [[R.V. College of Engineering]] in Bengaluru, India. The first three days of the event had talks, tutorials and interactive sessions. The last two days were a focused code sprint.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news
| title= conf.KDE.in: First KDE Conference in India
| url= http://dot.kde.org/2010/12/28/confkdein-first-kde-conference-india
| author = Shantanu Tushar
| agency = KDE.NEWS
| publisher = KDE
| date = 2010-12-28
| accessdate=2011-01-03}}&lt;/ref&gt; The conference was opened by its main organiser Pradeepto Bhattacharya, over 300 people were at the opening talks. The Lighting of the Auspicious Lamp ceremony was performed to open the conference. The first session was by Lydia Pintscher who talk &quot;So much to do – so little time&quot;. At the event, Project Neon announced return on Mar 11, 2011, provides nightly builds of the KDE Software Compilation.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news
| title= conf.kde.in: Project Neon Returns With Bleeding Edge KDE Software
| url= http://dot.kde.org/2011/03/11/confkdein-project-neon-returns-bleeding-edge-kde-software
| author = Valorie Zimmerman
| agency = KDE.NEWS
| publisher = KDE
| date = 2011-03-11
| accessdate=2011-05-30}}&lt;/ref&gt; Closing the conference was keynote speaker and old-time KDE developer Sirtaj.

''Día KDE'' (KDE Day) is a Argentinian event focused on KDE. It gives talks and workshops. The purpose of the event are: spread the free software movement among the population of Argentina, bringing to it the KDE community and environment developed by it, to know and strengthen KDE-AR, and generally bring the community together to have fun. The event is free.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news
| title= Salió la versión candidata de KDE SC 4.7
| url= http://kde.org.ar/node/104
| date = 2011-06-28
}}&lt;/ref&gt;

{|- class=&quot;wikitable&quot;
|- style=&quot;background:#efefef;&quot;
! colspan=&quot;3&quot; | Día KDE
|- style=&quot;background:#efefef;&quot;
!Year
!Venue
!Date
|-
!2011
|[[Rosario]]
|8/27
|-
|}

''Release party'' is a party, which celebrates released of new version of the KDE SC (twice a year).&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news
| title= KDE Partying Around the World for New Release
| url= http://dot.kde.org/2010/03/21/kde-partying-around-world-new-release
| author = Jos Poortvliet
| agency = KDE.NEWS
| publisher = KDE
| date = 2010-03-21
}}&lt;/ref&gt; KDE also participates other conferences that around free software.

=== Developer Sprints ===
In addition to ''Camp KDE'' and ''Akademy'' there are other conferences, which is called ''Developer Sprints''. The Developer Sprints are focused gatherings of developers to work on a specific part of KDE. Usually there are 2–3 days meetings of around 10-15 people. The Developer Sprints include core people, but also least one or two newbie quota to get fresh developers into the community. They are supported by KDE e.V. financially and organizationally. It will also provide help and advice where needed and appropriate. The results of meetings are documented on the [[KDE Dot News|KDE.News]]. They also create a sprint landing page on the community wiki, which give a brief summary of the sprint and link to relevant material.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
|url= http://ev.kde.org/activities/devmeetings/
|title= KDE e.V. - KDE e.V. supported developer meetings
|accessdate=2011-01-08}}&lt;/ref&gt;

{|- class=&quot;wikitable&quot; align=&quot;right&quot;
|- style=&quot;background:#efefef;&quot;
! colspan=&quot;3&quot; | Promo sprint
|- style=&quot;background:#efefef;&quot;
!Year
!Venue
!Date
|-
!2009&lt;ref&gt;
{{cite news
| title= Booth, Web and Marketing Sprint
| url= http://dot.kde.org/2009/11/20/booth-web-and-marketing-sprint
| author = Stuart Jarvis
| agency = KDE.NEWS
| publisher = KDE
| date = 2009-11-20
}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|[[Stuttgart]], Germany
|
|-
!2011&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news
|title= Promo Sprint 2011
|url= http://news.kde.org/2011/05/16/promo-sprint-2011
| author = Justin Kirby
| agency = KDE.NEWS
| publisher = KDE
| date = 2011-05-16
| accessdate = 2011-05-20}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|[[Southampton]], [[England]]
| 5/6-5/8
|-
|}

''KDE PIM Meeting'' is the annual meeting of [[KDE-PIM|KDE PIM]] team, held in [[Osnabrück]], Germany since 2003.&lt;ref&gt;
{{cite news
| title= 9th Annual PIM Meeting Renews Commitment to Innovation
| url= http://dot.kde.org/2011/03/15/9th-annual-pim-meeting-renews-commitment-innovation
| author = Stephen Kelly
| agency = KDE.NEWS
| publisher = KDE
| date = 2011-03-15
}}&lt;/ref&gt; ''Akonadi Sprint'' is anther meeting of KDE PIM team since 2007; it focus on [[Akonadi]]. ''Calligra Sprint'' is the meeting of designers and developers of [[Calligra Suite]].&lt;ref&gt;
{{cite news
| title= KOffice 2009 Sprint In Berlin
| url= http://dot.kde.org/2009/06/13/koffice-2009-sprint-berlin
| author = Boudewijn Rempt
| agency = KDE.NEWS
| publisher = KDE
| date = 2009-06-13
}}&lt;/ref&gt; Usually the meetings are held in [[Berlin]], Germany. ''Krita Sprint'' is the meeting of [[Krita]] team since 2009.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news
| title= Second Krita Sprint Ends With Tea
| url= http://dot.kde.org/2010/03/15/second-krita-sprint-ends-tea
| author = Boudewijn Rempt
| agency = KDE.NEWS
| publisher = KDE
| date = 2010-03-15
}}&lt;/ref&gt; ''KDE Education Meeting'' is the meeting of [[KDE Education Project|KDE Edu team]].&lt;ref&gt;
{{cite news
| title= Report from Successful Multimedia and Edu Sprint in Randa
| url= http://dot.kde.org/2010/06/19/report-successful-multimedia-and-edu-sprint-randa
| author = Frederik Gladhorn
| agency = KDE.NEWS
| publisher = KDE
| date = 2010-06-19
}}&lt;/ref&gt; ''KDE Marble sprint'' is the meeting of [[Marble (software)|Marble]] team, held in [[Nürnberg]], Germany.&lt;ref&gt;
{{cite news
| title= KDE's Marble Team Holds First Contributor Sprint
| url= http://dot.kde.org/2010/11/10/kdes-marble-team-holds-first-contributor-sprint
| author = Torsten Rahn
| agency = KDE.NEWS
| publisher = KDE
| date = 2010-11-15
}}&lt;/ref&gt; ''KDE Games Sprint'' is the meeting of [[KDE Games]] team. ''KDE Imaging Sprint'' is a sprint for KDE photography applications.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book
|author = Adriaan de Groot, Artur Souza, Claudia Rauch, Eugene Trounev, Jenny Yeung, Jos Poortvliet, Justin Kirby, Rob Oakes, Stuart Jarvis
|url= http://ev.kde.org/reports/ev-quarterly-2010Q3.pdf
|title= KDE e.V. Quarterly Report 2010Q3 (Issue 15)
|date=
| pages = 5
| publisher = KDE e.V.
|accessdate=2011-04-08}}&lt;/ref&gt; ''Tokamak'' is the meeting of designers and developers of [[KDE Plasma Workspaces|Plasma]], [[KWin]], and [[Oxygen Project|Oxygen]] since 2008.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news
| title= Tokamak Sprint Turns Plasma Upside-Down
| url= http://dot.kde.org/2008/04/21/tokamak-sprint-turns-plasma-upside-down
| author = Sebastian Kuegler
| agency = KDE.NEWS
| publisher = KDE
| date = 2008-04-21
| accessdate=2011-03-16}}&lt;/ref&gt; ''KDE Finances Sprint'' is the meeting of developers from [[KMyMoney]], Kraft and Skrooge.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news
| title= Successful KDE Finances Sprint Held
| url= http://dot.kde.org/2010/07/15/successful-kde-finances-sprint-held
| author = Guillaume DE BURE
| agency = KDE.NEWS
| publisher = KDE
| date = 2010-07-15
| accessdate=2011-06-01}}&lt;/ref&gt; ''Promo sprint'' is the meeting, which discuses KDE Marketing and Promo.

== Technology platform ==
[[Image:KDE brand map.svg|right|300px|thumb|KDE brand map]]
The KDE technology platform consists of three parts: KDE Development Platform, KDE Workspace and KDE Applications.

=== KDE Platform ===
[[KDE Platform]] consists of the libraries and services needed to run KDE applications. libraries include: [[Solid (KDE)|Solid]], [[NEPOMUK (framework)|Nepomuk]], [[Phonon (KDE)|Phonon]], etc. Packages include: kdelibs, kdepimlibs and kdebase-runtime. The libraries must be licensed under one of the LGPL, BSD license, [[MIT License]] and X11 license.&lt;ref&gt;
{{cite web
|url= http://techbase.kde.org/index.php?title=Policies/Licensing_Policy
|title= KDE Licensing Policy
|accessdate=2010-11-06
}}&lt;/ref&gt; While the Platform is mainly written in C++, it includes bindings for other programming languages.&lt;ref&gt;
{{cite web
|url= http://www.kde.org/developerplatform/
|title= The KDE development platform
|accessdate=2010-11-26}}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Plasma Workspaces ===
[[File:Screenshot of KDE 4.4 plasma-netbook.png|thumb|250px|KDE Plasma Netbook]]
The [[KDE Plasma Workspaces|Plasma Workspaces]] provide the environment for running and managing applications.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
|url= http://www.kde.org/workspaces/
|title= The KDE Workspaces
|accessdate=2010-12-04}}&lt;/ref&gt; They include many components such as [[KWin]], [[KDE Display Manager|KDM]], Plasma core libraries, [[Klipper]], [[KDE System Guard|KSysguard]], and [[System Settings]]. There are different available [[GUI]] environments: ''Plasma Desktop'' for desktop computers, ''Plasma Netbook'' for netbooks, ''Plasma Mobile'' for smartphones and ''Plasma Tablet'' for Tablet PCs.&lt;ref&gt;
{{cite news
|title= KDE's Mobile Team Meets for First Sprint
|url= http://dot.kde.org/2010/12/03/kdes-mobile-team-meets-first-sprint
| author = Artur Souza
| agency = KDE.NEWS
| publisher = KDE
| date = 2010-12-03
| accessdate = 2011-01-01
}}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== KDE Applications ===
[[List of KDE applications|KDE Applications]] are built on top of the KDE Platform like [[Okular]], [[KTorrent]], [[Kexi]] and [[KDE Partition Manager]]. KDE applications can potentially be portable between operating systems and independent of a particular workspace or desktop environment. Some brands identify application suites built up from several applications, such as [[Kdenetwork|KDE Network]], [[Kdegraphics|KDE Graphics]] and [[Kdeutils|KDE Utilities]]. Some applications are part of the regular Software Compilation releases, others are part of Extragear and release to their own schedule.

== Implementation ==
Most KDE software uses the Qt framework which runs on most Unix and [[Unix-like]] systems, Mac OS X, and Microsoft Windows. {{As of | 2011}} [[CMake]] serves as the build tool. This allows KDE to support a wider range of platforms, including Microsoft Windows.&lt;ref&gt;
{{cite news
| url = http://dot.kde.org/2007/02/21/road-kde-4-cmake-new-build-system-kde
| title = The Road to KDE 4: CMake, a New Build System for KDE
| author = Troy Unrau
| agency = KDE.NEWS
| publisher = KDE
| date = 2007-02-22
| accessdate = 2010-11-13}}
&lt;/ref&gt; [[GNU gettext]] is used for translation. [[Doxygen]] is used to generate api documentation.&lt;ref name=&quot;Software Engineering Framework&quot;&gt;{{cite web
|url= http://techbase.kde.org/Development/Software_Engineering_Framework
|title= Software Engineering Framework
|date= 29 October 2010
|accessdate=2010-11-28}}&lt;/ref&gt;

* [[KDE Software Compilation]]: KDE Software Compilation (KDE SC) is the coordinated releases of new software versions, gathering elements from the previous components to build an integrated core of software. The KDE SC is not a product as a single entity.
* [[Calligra Suite]]: Integrated office suite.
* [[Kdewebdev|KDEWebdev]]: Web development tools.
* [[Extragear|KDE-Extragear]]: Extragear is a collection of applications associated with KDE. Those applications are not part the official software compilation, but they are still part of the project.
* KDE-Playground: This package contains pre-release and unstable software. It is a place for applications to mature.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
|url= http://www.kde.org/community/whatiskde/softwarecompilation.php
|title= KDE Software Compilation
|accessdate=2010-11-20}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Collaborations with other organizations ==
=== Wikimedia ===
{{wikinews|Wikipedia founder Jimmy Wales announces cooperation between KDE Group and Wikimedia}}
[[image:Amarok 2 3 0.png|right|200px|thumb|Amarok with information retrieved from Wikipedia.]]

On 23 June 2005, chairman of the Wikimedia Foundation announced that the KDE community and the Wikimedia Foundation have begun efforts towards cooperation.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news
|title= KDE and Wikipedia Announce Cooperation
|url= http://dot.kde.org/2005/06/23/kde-and-wikipedia-announce-cooperation
| author = Sven Krohlas
| agency = KDE.NEWS
| publisher = KDE
| date = 2005-06-23
| accessdate = 2010-11-13}}&lt;/ref&gt; Fruits of that cooperation are [[MediaWiki]] syntax highlighting in [[Kate (text editor)|Kate]] and accessing [[Wikipedia]] content within KDE applications, such as [[Amarok (software)|Amarok]] and [[Marble (software)|Marble]].

On 4 April 2008, the [[KDE e.V.]] and Wikimedia Deutschland have opened shared offices in [[Frankfurt]].&lt;ref&gt;
{{cite web
| url  = http://www.kde.org/announcements/kde-and-wikimedia-collaborate.php
| title = KDE and Wikimedia Start Collaboration
| date = April 4, 2008
| accessdate = 2010-11-13
}}&lt;/ref&gt; In September 2009 KDE e.V. moved to shared offices with [[Free Software Foundation Europe]] in Berlin, so Wikimedia Foundation now uses the Frankfurt offices for themselves.&lt;ref name=&quot;fsfeoffice&quot; /&gt;

=== Free Software Foundation Europe ===
In May 2006, KDE e.V. became an ''Associate Member'' of the [[Free Software Foundation Europe]] (FSFE).&lt;ref name=&quot;fsfeoffice&quot;&gt;
{{cite web
| url = http://www.kde.org/announcements/fsfe-associate-member.php
| date = May 9, 2006
| title = KDE e.V. Becomes Associate Member of FSFE
| accessdate=2010-11-06
}}&lt;/ref&gt;

On 22 August 2008, KDE e.V. and FSFE announced that after working with FSFE’s ''Freedom Task Force'' one and a half years KDE adopts FSFE’s ''Fiduciary Licence Agreement''. Using that, KDE developers can – on a voluntary basis – assign their copyrights to KDE e.V.&lt;ref&gt;
{{cite web
| url     = http://ev.kde.org/announcements/2008-08-22-fsfe-welcomes-fla.php
| date = 22 August 2008
| title   = FSFE welcomes KDE’s adoption of the Fiduciary Licence Agreement (FLA)
| accessdate=2010-11-06
}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In September 2009, KDE e.V. and FSFE moved into shared offices in Berlin.&lt;ref&gt;
{{cite web
| url     = http://fsfe.org/events/
| date = 12 December 2009
| title   = FSFE: Events. Office warming party, Berlin, Germany
| accessdate=2010-11-26
}}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Commercial enterprises ===
Several companies actively contribute to KDE, like Collabora, Erfrakon, Intevation GmbH, Kolab Konsortium, Klarälvdalens Datakonsult AB (KDAB), and KO GmbH.

Nokia use [[Calligra Suite]] as base for their ''Office Viewer'' application for [[Maemo]]/[[MeeGo]].&lt;ref&gt;
{{cite news
| title= KOffice Based Office Viewer Launched for Nokia N900
| url= http://dot.kde.org/2010/01/21/koffice-based-office-viewer-launched-nokia-n900
| author = Jonathan Riddell
| agency = KDE.NEWS
| publisher = KDE
| date = 2010-01-21
}}&lt;/ref&gt; They have also been contracting KO GmbH to bring MS Office 2007 file format filters to Calligra.&lt;ref&gt;
{{cite news
| title= Nokia Announces MS Office 2007 Import Filters for KOffice
| url= http://www.koffice.org/news/nokia-announces-ms-office-2007-import-filters-for-koffice/
| author = Inge Wallin
| date = 2009-10-11
}}&lt;/ref&gt; Nokia also employs several KDE developers directly – either to use KDE software for MeeGo (e.g. ''KCal''&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news
| title= KDE PIM Stabilization Sprint
| url= http://dot.kde.org/2010/06/03/kde-pim-stabilization-sprint
| author = Stephen Kelly
| agency = KDE.NEWS
| publisher = KDE
| date = 2010-06-03
}}&lt;/ref&gt;) or as sponsorship.

The software development and consulting companies Intevation GmbH of Germany and the Swedish KDAB use Qt and KDE software – especially [[Kontact]] and [[Akonadi]] for [[Kolab]] – for their services and products, therefore both employ KDE developers.

=== Others ===
KDE participates in [[freedesktop.org]], an effort to standardize Unix desktop interoperability.

Since 2009, [[GNOME]] and KDE co-host their conferences Akademy and [[GNOME_Users_And_Developers_European_Conference|GUADEC]] every two years under the ''Desktop Summit'' label.

In December 2010 KDE e.V. became a licensee of the [[Open Invention Network]].&lt;ref&gt;
{{cite news
|title= KDE e.V. Joins Open Invention Network
|url= http://news.kde.org/2010/12/21/kde-ev-joins-open-invention-network
| author = Aaron J. Seigo
| agency = KDE.NEWS
| publisher = KDE
| date = 2010-12-21
| accessdate = 2010-12-23
}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Many [[Linux distribution]]s and other free operating systems are involved in the development and distribution of the software, and are therefore also active in the KDE community. These include commercial distributors such as Novell, Mandriva, Red Hat, or Canonical, but also government-funded non-commercial organizations such as the [[Scientific and Technological Research Council of Turkey]] with its Linux distribution Pardus.

== Notable uses ==
Brazil’s primary school education system operates computers running KDE software, includes more than 42,000 schools in 4,000 cities, serving nearly 52 million children. The base distribution is called Educational Linux, which is based on Kubuntu.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web
|url=https://lwn.net/Articles/455972/
|title= LinuxCon: The world's largest Linux desktop deployment
|accessdate=
|date=2011-08-22 
}}&lt;/ref&gt; Besides this, a thousand more students in Brazil use KDE products in their universities. KDE software is also running on computers in Portuguese and Venezuelan schools, with respectively 700 thousand and one million systems reached.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book
|editor =KDE promo team
|url=http://community.kde.org/index.php?title=File:Kde_booklet_ver8.pdf
|title= KDE promo booklet
|accessdate=2011-02-26}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Germany uses KDE software in its embassies around the world, representing around 11,000 systems. Through use of Pardus, a local Linux distribution, many sections of the Turkish government make use of KDE software, including the [[Turkish Armed Forces]]&lt;ref name =&quot;radikal&quot;&gt;{{Cite web
|url=http://www.radikal.com.tr/Radikal.aspx?aType=RadikalDetay&amp;ArticleID=937471&amp;Date=01.07.2009&amp;CategoryID=105 
|title= Pardus 2009 yolda  
|accessdate=2009-05-25 
|date=2009-05-25 
|language=Turkish 
}}&lt;/ref&gt;, [[Ministry of Foreign Affairs (Turkey)|Ministry of Foreign Affairs]]&lt;ref name =&quot;radikal&quot;/&gt;, [[Ministry of National Defence (Turkey)|Ministry of National Defence]]&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web
|url=http://www.ntvmsnbc.com/id/24956827/ 
|title= MSB, Pardus ile 2 milyon dolar tasarruf etti
|accessdate=2009-04-14 
|date=2009-04-14 
|language=Turkish 
}}&lt;/ref&gt;, [[Turkish Police]]&lt;ref name =&quot;radikal&quot;/&gt;, and the SGK (Social Security Institution of Turkey)&lt;ref name =&quot;radikal&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.ntvmsnbc.com/id/24956271/ |title=SGK, Pardus'a göç etmeye hazırlanıyor |accessdate=2009-04-13 |date=2009-04-13 |language=Turkish }}&lt;/ref&gt;, although these departments often do not exclusively use Pardus as their operating system. The [[CERN]] (European Organization for Nuclear Research) built the [[Large Hadron Collider]] in Switzerland, one of the world’s largest science experiments, using KDE software.&lt;ref&gt;
{{cite news
| title= KDE Congratulates CERN's Large Hadron Collider
| url= http://dot.kde.org/2008/09/10/kde-congratulates-cerns-large-hadron-collider
| author = Jonathan Riddell
| date = 2008-09-10
}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== See also ==
{{Portal|Free software}}
* [[List of KDE applications]]
* [[Free software community]]

==References==
{{Reflist|3}}

==External links==
{{Sister project links}}
*[http://www.kde.org The KDE website]
*[http://news.kde.org/ KDE.News], news announcements
*[http://techbase.kde.org/ KDE TechBase]

{{KDE}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Kde}}
[[Category:KDE| ]]
[[Category:Community]]
[[Category:Free software projects]]
[[Category:Free and open source software organizations]]

[[af:KDE]]
[[als:KDE]]
[[ar:كدي]]
[[ast:KDE]]
[[bn:কেডিই]]
[[bar:K Desktop Environment]]
[[bs:KDE]]
[[bg:KDE]]
[[ca:KDE]]
[[cs:KDE]]
[[da:KDE]]
[[de:KDE]]
[[et:KDE]]
[[el:KDE]]
[[es:KDE]]
[[eo:KDE]]
[[eu:KDE]]
[[fa:کی‌دی‌ای]]
[[fr:KDE]]
[[fy:KDE]]
[[gl:KDE Software Compilation]]
[[ko:KDE]]
[[hi:केडीई]]
[[hr:KDE]]
[[id:KDE]]
[[is:KDE]]
[[it:KDE]]
[[he:KDE]]
[[ku:KDE]]
[[lv:KDE]]
[[lb:K Desktop Environment]]
[[lt:KDE]]
[[hu:KDE]]
[[mk:KDE]]
[[ml:കെ.ഡി.ഇ.]]
[[mr:केडीई (लिनक्स)]]
[[ms:KDE]]
[[nl:KDE]]
[[ja:KDE]]
[[no:K Desktop Environment]]
[[nn:KDE]]
[[km:Kde]]
[[nds:K Desktop Environment]]
[[pl:K Desktop Environment]]
[[pt:KDE]]
[[ro:KDE]]
[[ru:KDE]]
[[se:KDE]]
[[simple:KDE]]
[[sk:KDE]]
[[sl:KDE]]
[[sr:КДЕ]]
[[fi:KDE]]
[[sv:KDE]]
[[te:KDE]]
[[th:KDE]]
[[tr:KDE]]
[[uk:KDE]]
[[vec:KDE]]
[[vi:KDE]]
[[zh:KDE]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
