<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="1664357" ns="0" title="John Howard (British Army officer)"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Other people2|John Howard (disambiguation)}}

{{Infobox military person
|name=John Howard
|image= 
|caption=The [[formation patch]] of the airborne forces
|birth_date= 8 December 1912
|death_date= 5 May 1999
|birth_place= [[West End of London]], [[England]]
|death_place=
|placeofburial=
|nickname=
|allegiance={{flag|United Kingdom}}
|branch=[[British Army]]
|serviceyears=1932&amp;ndash;1938&lt;br/&gt;1939&amp;ndash;1946
|rank=[[Major (United Kingdom)|Major]]
|unit=[[Oxfordshire and Buckinghamshire Light Infantry]]
|commands=
|battles=[[Second World War]]
*[[Operation Deadstick]]
|awards=[[Distinguished Service Order]]&lt;br/&gt;[[Croix de Guerre|Croix de Guerre avec Palme]] (France)
}}

[[Major (United Kingdom)|Major]] '''(Reginald) John Howard''' [[Distinguished Service Order|DSO]] (8 December 1912 – 5 May 1999) was a [[British Army]] officer who led a glider-borne assault on two bridges between Bénouville and Ranville in [[Normandy]], France on 6 June 1944 as part of the [[D-Day]] landings during the [[Second World War]]. These bridges spanned the [[Canal de Caen à la Mer|Caen Canal]] and the adjacent [[River Orne]] (about 500 yards to the east), and were vitally important to the success of the D-Day landings. Since the war the bridge over the canal has become known as &quot;[[Pegasus Bridge]]&quot;, as a tribute to the men who captured it, while the bridge over the River Orne later became known as Horsa Bridge after the Horsa gliders that had carried the troops to the bridges.

Howard initially joined the British Army before the war, serving as a private and then a non-commissioned officer for six years before discharging in 1938 and joining the [[Oxford]] City [[Police]]. In 1939 he was recalled to the army following the outbreak of the war and quickly rose through the ranks to become a regimental sergeant major in the [[King's Shropshire Light Infantry]]. In 1940 he was commissioned as a [[second lieutenant]] and eventually rose to be a major in 1942, at which time he took over command of 'D' Company, 2nd Battalion, [[Oxfordshire and Buckinghamshire Light Infantry]]. Before D-Day, Howard's company was selected to carry out the assault on the Caen and Orne River bridges and he became personally responsible for their training and the planning of the assault. During D-Day he led the company in a successful [[Coup de main|coup-de-main]] assault that gained control of the bridges and then held them until relieved. After D-Day, Howard commanded his company until September 1944 when they were withdrawn from the line. Due to the injuries he sustained in a car accident in November 1944, he took no further part in the war and was eventually invalided out of the army in 1946.  After this he became a public servant before he retired in 1974. 

His role in the assault on the bridges was detailed in a number of books and films since the war, and after he retired he gave a number of lectures in Europe and the United States on tactics and on the assault itself. He died in 1999, at the age of 86.

==Early life==
Reginald John Howard was born on 8 December 1912 to Jack and Ethel Howard, who lived in London's [[West End of London|West End]].&lt;ref name=Ambrose2122&gt;Ambrose 1985, pp. 21–22.&lt;/ref&gt; The eldest of nine children, Howard's family background was working class. His father worked as a barrelmaker for a brewery after serving in the trenches in France during [[World War I]], while his mother kept the house and looked after the children.&lt;ref name=Ambrose2122/&gt; During his formative years, Howard was active member of the [[The Scout Association|Boy Scouts]], he also enjoyed attending school and did very well, earning a [[scholarship]] to attend [[secondary school]]. However, the economic situation at the time was hard and at the age of fourteen he began full-time work, working as a clerk at a broker's firm.&lt;ref name=Ambrose22&gt;Ambrose 1985, p. 22.&lt;/ref&gt; In order to further his education he took evening classes and continued with the Scouts. In 1931, however, he found himself out of work, after the brokerage firm that he was working for went out of business.&lt;ref name=Ambrose22/&gt;

In 1932, Howard enlisted in the British Army and undertook recruit training at [[Shrewsbury]] and was assigned to the King's Shropshire Light Infantry.&lt;ref name=Ambrose23&gt;Ambrose 1985, p. 23.&lt;/ref&gt; He excelled at physical training and did consistently well on army exams. He became a company clerk and later a physical training instructor. On the basis of his education he applied for a [[Officer (armed forces)|commission]] but was rejected, although he was promoted to [[corporal]].&lt;ref name=Ambrose23/&gt; 

In June 1938, he was discharged from the army, having served his six year enlistment period, and joined the Oxford City Police.&lt;ref&gt;Ambrose 1985, p. 24.&lt;/ref&gt; On 28 October 1939 he married Joy Bromley—whom he had met in 1936&lt;ref name=Ambrose25&gt;Ambrose 1985, p. 25.&lt;/ref&gt;—and with whom he would later have two children, Terry and Penny.&lt;ref name=Ambrose193&gt;Ambrose 1985, p. 193.&lt;/ref&gt;

On 2 December 1939, following the outbreak of the war, he rejoined the SLI as a corporal, however, he was quickly promoted to [[Company Sergeant Major]] and within five months of joining was the [[Regimental Sergeant Major]].&lt;ref name=Ambrose25/&gt; Offered the opportunity of a commission he went to 166th Officer Cadet Training Unit in mid-1940. On graduation he was commissioned as a second lieutenant in 2nd Battalion, Oxfordshire and Buckinghamshire Light Infantry (Ox &amp; Bucks) on 9 November 1940.&lt;ref name=Ambrose25/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{LondonGazette|issue=35008|supp=yes|startpage=6924|endpage=6925|date=3 December 1940|accessdate=4 June 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt; He rose to [[Captain (British Army and Royal Marines)|captain]] commanding a [[Company (military unit)|company]].&lt;ref name=Ambrose25/&gt; When the Ox and Bucks was marked for conversion to airborne in 1942, Howard volunteered, accepting demotion to lieutenant and command of a [[Platoon (military unit)|platoon]].&lt;ref group=&quot;Note&quot;&gt;Only about half of the Ox and Bucks made the transition; their places were filled by volunteers from other units of the Army.&lt;/ref&gt; He was subsequently promoted, becoming a major in May 1942 and became company commander of 'D' Company.&lt;ref&gt;Ambrose 1985, p. 27.&lt;/ref&gt;

==D-Day landings==
{{see also|Operation Deadstick}}
The Orne river formed the eastern, or left, flank of the [[Allies|Allied]] [[Normandy Landings|landings at Normandy]] on 6 June 1944.&lt;ref name=Ambrose40&gt;Ambrose 1985, p. 40.&lt;/ref&gt; Control of both bridges was vital because Allied forces needed the Orne as a geographic barrier against an immediate counter attack against the allied flank by [[Germany|German]] forces, and because access to a lateral road would ensure supplies from [[Sword Beach]] to the [[6th Airborne Division]], which had been dropped to the east of Caen.&lt;ref name=Ambrose52&gt;Ambrose 1985, p. 52.&lt;/ref&gt; Supplies of [[ammunition]], [[fuel]] and rations were essential if the 6th Airborne was to effectively protect the left flank of the Allied invasion force.&lt;ref name=Ambrose52/&gt; Furthermore, the crossings had to be held, undamaged, so as to serve as causeways from the beach landing areas, when the Allies moved forward.{{Citation needed|date=May 2009}}  

[[Image:Pegasus Bridge 1944.jpg|right|250px|thumb|Pegasus Bridge in 1944]] 

Howard led 'D' Company and an [[Royal Engineers|engineer]] detachment, in a gliderborne assault in the early hours of 6 June 1944.&lt;ref name=&quot;Ambrose 1985&quot;&gt;Ambrose 1985.&lt;/ref&gt; Released at 8,000 feet over the Normandy coast, three gliders, each carrying about 28 heavily armed troops—in total 90 men, pilots included—clipped the tops of a group of poplar trees skirting a very small field and a dangerous pool and bounced to a halt only a few yards from each other, at precisely 0016 hours.&lt;ref group=&quot;Note&quot;&gt;Double British Summertime = 23:16 local time.&lt;/ref&gt; All gliders were brought to an immediate halt, almost on top of the objectives&lt;ref name=Ambrose96-113&gt;Ambrose 1985, pp. 96–113.&lt;/ref&gt;&amp;mdash;the nose was &quot;buried in barbed wire and almost on the bridge&quot;, in the words of a soldier under Howard.&lt;ref&gt;Private Bill Gray, quoted in Ryan 1959, p. 109&lt;/ref&gt;  The assault troops engaged their objectives almost from the moment they stepped outside of the wreckage of their aircraft.  The German defenders were taken completely by surprise for they had almost no time to react, form, and attempt a defence of the objectives;&lt;ref name=Ambrose96-113/&gt; some were caught asleep in their gun pits. Only one German soldier was able to fire a [[Very pistol]] to try to warn soldiers on the Orne bridge a few hundred yards away, but by the time he fired, the other bridge had been overrun.&lt;ref&gt;Ryan 1959, pp. 109&amp;ndash;110&lt;/ref&gt; There was no time to attempt to blow the bridge,&lt;ref name=Ambrose96-113/&gt; and even if there had been, the explosives needed for the job had never been fitted to the bridge.&lt;ref&gt;Ryan 1959, p. 110&lt;/ref&gt;

At least two armed German halftracks belonging to an engineer company and followed by [[panzergrenadiers]] tried to attack the bridge at 01:30 a.m., but the first was destroyed by a [[PIAT]].&lt;ref name=Ambrose129130&gt;Ambrose 1985, pp. 129&amp;ndash;130.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref group=&quot;Note&quot;&gt;According to Ambrose a German tank was destroyed but British eyewitness reports from 6 June daytime as well as Sergeant Thornton's Military Medal citation refer to it as an armoured carrier, most likely a halftrack armed with cannon; note by drs. Carles Wolterman, Amstelveen, Holland&lt;/ref&gt; The other Panzers thought they were up against a bigger enemy force armed with a 6 pounder anti-tankgun and so immediately retreated. A more forceful German counter-attack came in the early hours of D-Day, when German divisional headquarters realised the bridges had been taken intact. By that time, Howard and his glider troops had been bolstered by both fresh airborne [[parachute]] landings&lt;ref name=Ambrose164168&gt;Ambrose 1985, pp. 164–168.&lt;/ref&gt; and a detachment of commandos led by [[Simon Fraser, 15th Lord Lovat|Simon Fraser]], who marched to the bridge to the tune of [[Bill Millin]]'s bagpipes.&lt;ref&gt;Ryan 1959, p. 292&lt;/ref&gt; With these reinforcements, they were able to hold Pegasus Bridge against an attack by elements of the [[German 21st Panzer Division|21st Panzer Division]], strongly supported by [[artillery]].&lt;ref name=Ambrose164168/&gt;

Following the attack on the bridges on D-Day, instead of being removed from the line to commence training for further operations 'D' Company was used as a normal infantry company.&lt;ref&gt;Ambrose 1985, p. 172.&lt;/ref&gt; Howard was nominated for the [[Distinguished Service Order]] for his leadership during the capture of the bridges, and on 16 July 1944, Howard was presented with the medal by Field Marshal [[Bernard Montgomery, 1st Viscount Montgomery of Alamein|Bernard Montgomery]],&lt;ref&gt;Ambrose 1985, p. 182.&lt;/ref&gt; although the award was not officially confirmed until 31 August.&lt;ref&gt;{{LondonGazette|issue=36679|supp=yes|startpage=4044|date=29 August 1944|accessdate=4 June 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt; 'D' Company remained in Normandy fighting until 5 September 1944, after 91 days of continuous fighting.&lt;ref&gt;Ambrose 1985, p. 186.&lt;/ref&gt;

Upon return to Bulford, Howard began to reform and reorganise his company in preparation for future operations.&lt;ref name=Ambrose190191&gt;Ambrose 1985, pp. 190–192.&lt;/ref&gt; They were not withdrawn from the line in time to take part in [[Operation Market Garden]] and in the end it had been decided not to employ a coup-de-main assault on the bridges at Nijmegen and Arnhem.&lt;ref&gt;Ambrose 1985, p. 190.&lt;/ref&gt; Nevertheless, Howard began the process of training 'D' Company in the hope of returning to combat, however, it was not to be. On 13 November 1944, he was involved in a car accident and was badly injured. He would take no further part in the war and remained in hospital until March 1945.&lt;ref&gt;Ambrose 1985, p. 191.&lt;/ref&gt; 'D' Company would, however, go on to fight during the [[Battle of the Bulge]] and the subsequent crossing of the Rhine in [[Operation Varsity]].&lt;ref&gt;Ambrose 1985, pp. 191–192.&lt;/ref&gt;

==Later life==
In 1946, despite wishing to continue serving, Howard was invalided out of the Army as a result of injuries that he received in the accident, and he went to work for the [[Ministry of Agriculture]].&lt;ref&gt;Ambrose 1985, pp. 191–193.&lt;/ref&gt; In 1954 he was awarded the [[Croix de Guerre|Croix de Guerre avec Palme]] by the French government.&lt;ref&gt;Ambrose 1985, p. 192.&lt;/ref&gt;  On 6 June 1959, [[Cornelius Ryan]] published ''[[The Longest Day (book)|The Longest Day]]'', in which 'D' Company's assault on the bridges was detailed. In 1962, Howard's experiences on D-Day were re-enacted by actor [[Richard Todd]]—who had himself participated in D-Day, serving in the [[7th Parachute Battalion]],&lt;ref name=Ambrose105&gt;Ambrose 1985, p. 105.&lt;/ref&gt; sent to reinforce Howard's coup-de-main party—in the film ''[[The Longest Day (film)|The Longest Day]]'', which was largely based on Ryan's book, although it was a dramatised account.&lt;ref name=obit&gt;{{cite news|url=http://web.archive.org/web/20080704213441/http://www.io.com/tog/howardobit.html|title=Major John Howard, DSO, Obituary|last=|date=|work=The Times, 7 May 1999|accessdate=2009-06-04}}&lt;/ref&gt; In 1985, [[Stephen Ambrose]] published a book on the assault on the bridges, called ''Pegasus Bridge''.&lt;ref name=&quot;Ambrose 1985&quot;/&gt;

In 1974 Howard retired from the public service and he and his wife Joy moved to the village of Burcot, near Oxford.&lt;ref name=Ambrose193&gt;Ambrose 1985, p. 193.&lt;/ref&gt; Later he moved to an old country house in Surrey&lt;ref&gt;Ambrose 1985, p. 207.&lt;/ref&gt; and in 1986 his wife, Joy, died.&lt;ref name=obit/&gt; Nevertheless, in his later life Howard returned to Normandy 6 June every year to lay a wreath at the location where the gliders landed and was involved in the creation and maintenance of an airborne forces museum near the bridge.&lt;ref name=obit/&gt; He also lectured cadets in Sweden, the United States and many other NATO countries.&lt;ref&gt;Ambrose 1985, p. 208.&lt;/ref&gt; In the 1960s, Howard met and befriended [[Hans von Luck]], a senior officer in the 21st Panzer Division who had been unable to assist in the defence of Pegasus Bridge on 6 June.&lt;ref&gt;Von Luck 1989, p. 331&lt;/ref&gt; 

Howard died on 5 May 1999, at the age of 86.&lt;ref name=obit/&gt; The new Memorial Pegasus museum was opened by the Prince of Wales on 4 June 2000.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web| url=http://www.memorial-pegasus.org/mmp/pegasus_bridge/index.php|title=Pegasus Memorial Bridge|author=Mémorial Pegasus |accessdate=2009-06-05}}&lt;/ref&gt; In 2006, his daughter, Penny, published Howard's private papers, titled ''Pegasus Diaries''.&lt;ref group=&quot;Note&quot;&gt;See [[#Further reading|&quot;Further reading&quot;]] section for the full bibliographic details of these works.&lt;/ref&gt;

==References==
===Footnotes===
{{reflist|group=Note}}

===Citations===
{{reflist}}

==Bibliography==
* {{cite book|last=Ambrose|first=Stephen E.|title=Pegasus Bridge|year=1985 [2003]|publisher=Simon and Schuster|location=London|isbn=0-7434-5068-X}}
* {{cite book |last=Ryan |first=Cornelius |authorlink=Cornelius Ryan |title=[[The Longest Day (book)|The Longest Day; June 6, 1944]] |year=1959 |publisher=Simon and Schuster |location=New York |id=671-20814-1&lt;!-- The number is its &quot;SBN&quot;, though I don't know what is. --&gt; |oclc=1175409}}
*{{cite book
  | last = Von Luck
  | first = Hans
  | title = Panzer Commander: The Memoirs of Colonel Hans Von Luck
  | publisher = Dell Publishing
  | year = 1989
  | isbn = 7100900799}}

==Further reading==
* {{cite book|last=Edwards|first=Dennis|title=The Devil's Own Luck: From Pegasus Bridge to the Baltic|year=1999|publisher=Leo Cooper|location=|isbn=978-0-85052-667-7}}
* {{cite book|last=Howard|first=John|coauthor=Bates, Penny|title=The Pegasus Diaries: The Private Papers of Major John Howard DSO|year=2006|publisher=Pen &amp; Sword Books|location=|isbn=978-1-84415-446-3}}
* {{cite book|last=Parr|first=Barry|title=What D'ya Do in the War, Dad?|year=2007|publisher=Trafford Publishing|location=|isbn=978-142511-073-4}}

==External links==
*[http://www.io.com/tog/howardobit.html Obituary, The Times Newspaper, 7 May 1999.] Dead link
*[http://www.normandy1944.com/index_content.php Memorial Pegasus Museum - Ranville-Bénouville (Normandy) France]

{{Persondata &lt;!-- Metadata: see [[Wikipedia:Persondata]]. --&gt;
| NAME              = Howard, John
| ALTERNATIVE NAMES =
| SHORT DESCRIPTION =
| DATE OF BIRTH     = 8 December 1912
| PLACE OF BIRTH    = [[West End of London]], [[England]]
| DATE OF DEATH     = 5 May 1999
| PLACE OF DEATH    =
}}
{{DEFAULTSORT:Howard, John}}
[[Category:1912 births]]
[[Category:1999 deaths]]
[[Category:Oxfordshire and Buckinghamshire Light Infantry officers]]
[[Category:Operation Overlord people]]
[[Category:Companions of the Distinguished Service Order]]
[[Category:British Army personnel of World War II]]
[[Category:Recipients of the Croix de Guerre (France)]]

[[ca:John Howard (oficial britànic)]]
[[da:John Howard (officer)]]
[[de:John Howard (Soldat)]]
[[fr:John Howard (major)]]
[[lb:John Howard (Zaldot)]]
[[sv:John Howard (soldat)]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
