<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="166419" ns="0" title="Omar Bradley"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{for|the American politician|Omar Bradley (politician)}}
{{Refimprove|date=January 2008}}

{{Infobox military person
|name=Omar Nelson Bradley
|birth_date={{birthdate|1893|2|12}}
|death_date={{dda|1981|4|8|1893|2|12}}
|birth_place=[[Randolph County, Missouri]]
|death_place=[[New York City|New York]], [[New York]]
|placeofburial=[[Arlington National Cemetery]]&lt;br/&gt;[[Arlington, Virginia]]
|image=[[File:General of the Army Omar Bradley.jpg|225px]]&lt;br/&gt;[[File:Omar N Bradley Signature.svg|200px]]
|caption=General of the Army Omar Bradley in 1950
|nickname=&quot;Brad,&quot; &quot;The G.I.'s General&quot;
|allegiance=[[United States of America]]
|serviceyears=1915–1953
|rank=[[File:US-O11 insignia.svg|20px]] [[General of the Army (United States)|General of the Army]]
|branch=[[United States Army]]
|commands=[[File:Flag of the Chairman of the US Joint Chiefs of Staff.svg|35px]][[Chairman of the Joint Chiefs of Staff]] &lt;br/&gt;[[File:Flag US Army Chief of Staff.svg|35px]][[Chief of Staff of the United States Army]]&lt;br/&gt;[[U.S. 82nd Airborne Division|82nd Infantry Division]]&lt;br/&gt;[[28th Infantry Division (United States)|28th Infantry Division]]&lt;br/&gt;[[U.S. II Corps]]&lt;br/&gt;[[U.S. First Army|First Army]]&lt;br/&gt;[[U.S. 12th Army Group|12th Army Group]] 
|battles=[[World War II]]&lt;br/&gt;[[Korean War]]
|awards=[[Distinguished Service Medal (Army)|Army Distinguished Service Medal]]&lt;br/&gt;[[Navy Distinguished Service Medal]]&lt;br/&gt;[[Silver Star]]&lt;br/&gt;[[Legion of Merit]]&lt;br/&gt;[[Bronze Star Medal|Bronze Star]]&lt;br/&gt; [[Mexican Border Service]] &lt;br/&gt; [[Knight Commander of the British Empire]]&lt;br/&gt;[[Order of Polonia Restituta]]&lt;br/&gt;[[Presidential Medal of Freedom]]&lt;br/&gt;[[Order of Suvorov]]&lt;br/&gt;[[Order of Kutuzov]]
|laterwork= 
}}

'''Omar Nelson Bradley''' (February 12, 1893 &amp;ndash; April 8, 1981) was a senior [[United States Army|U.S. Army]] field commander in North Africa and Europe during [[World War II]], and a [[General of the Army (United States)|General of the Army]] in the [[United States Army]].  He was the last surviving [[five-star rank|five-star]] commissioned officer of the United States and the first general to be selected [[Chairman of the Joint Chiefs of Staff]].

==Early life and career==
Bradley, the son of [[teacher|schoolteacher]] John Smith Bradley (1868-1908) and Mary Elizabeth Hubbard (1875-1931), was born into poverty in rural [[Randolph County, Missouri|Randolph County]], near [[Clark, Missouri]], He attended country schools where his father taught. When Omar was 13 his father, with whom he credited passing on to him a love of books, baseball and shooting, died. His mother moved to [[Moberly, Missouri|Moberly]] and remarried. Bradley graduated from Moberly High School in 1910, an outstanding student and captain of both the baseball and football teams. 

[[File:Omarbradleywestpoint.jpg|left|thumb|Bradley at West Point]]
Bradley was working as a boiler maker at the Wabash Railroad when he was encouraged by his Sunday school teacher at Central Christian Church in [[Moberly, Missouri|Moberly]] to take the entrance examination for the [[U.S. Military Academy]] at [[West Point, New York|West Point, NY]] Bradley had been planning on saving his money to enter the [[University of Missouri]] in [[Columbia, Missouri|Columbia]], where he intended to study [[law]]. He finished second in the West Point placement exams at [[Jefferson Barracks Military Post]] in [[St. Louis, Missouri|St. Louis]]. The first place winner was unable to accept the Congressional appointment, deferring instead to Bradley. While at the academy, Bradley's focus on sports prevented him from excelling academically. He was a baseball star, though, and often played on semi-pro teams for no remuneration (to ensure his eligibility to represent the academy). He was considered one of the most outstanding college players in the nation his junior and senior seasons at West Point, noted as both a power hitter and an outfielder with one of the best arms in his day.  While at West Point, Bradley joined the local Masonic Lodge in [[Highland Falls, New York]]. 

Bradley's first wife, Mary Quayle, grew up across the street from him in Moberly.  The pair attended Central Christian Church and Moberly High School together. Moberly called Bradley its favorite son and throughout his life Bradley called Moberly his hometown and his favorite city in the world. He was a frequent visitor to Moberly throughout his career, was a member of the Moberly Rotary Club, played near handicap golf regularly at the local course and had a &quot;Bradley pew&quot; at Central Christian Church. When a flag project opened in 2009 in the Moberly cemetery, General Bradley and his first son-in-law and West Point graduate, the late Major Henry Shaw Bukema, were memorialized with flags in their honor from grateful citizens.

==U.S. Army==
At West Point Bradley lettered in baseball three times, including the 1914 team, from which every player remaining in the army became a general. He graduated from West Point in 1915 as part of a class that contained many future generals, and which military historians have called &quot;[[the class the stars fell on]]&quot;. There were ultimately 59 generals in that graduating class, with Bradley and [[Dwight D. Eisenhower|Dwight Eisenhower]] attaining the rank of [[General of the Army (United States)|General of the Army]].

Bradley was commissioned into the infantry and was first assigned to the [[U.S. 14th Infantry Regiment|14th Infantry Regiment]]. He served on the [[U.S.-Mexico border]] in 1915. When war was declared, he was promoted to captain and sent to guard the [[Butte, Montana]] copper mines. 

Bradley joined the [[19th Infantry Division (United States)|19th Infantry Division]] in August 1918, which was scheduled for European deployment, but the [[Spanish flu|influenza pandemic]] and the armistice prevented it.

Between the wars, he taught and studied. From 1920–24, he taught mathematics at West Point. He was promoted to [[Major (United States)|major]] in 1924 and took the advanced infantry course at [[Fort Benning, Georgia]]. After a brief service in Hawaii, he studied at the [[United States Army Command and General Staff College|Command and General Staff School]] at [[Fort Leavenworth]] in 1928–29. From 1929, he taught at West Point again, taking a break to study at the [[U.S. Army War College|Army War College]] in 1934. He was promoted to [[Lieutenant Colonel (United States)|lieutenant colonel]] in 1936 and worked at the [[United States Department of War|War Department]]; after 1938 he was directly under [[Chief of Staff of the United States Army|Army Chief of Staff]] [[George Marshall]]. In February 1941, he was promoted to [[Brigadier General (United States)|brigadier general]] (bypassing the rank of [[Colonel (United States)|colonel]])&lt;ref&gt;Hollister, Jay. &quot;[http://history.sandiego.edu/GEN/WW2Timeline/bradley3.html General Omar Nelson Bradley]&quot;. [[University of San Diego]] History Department. May 3, 2001. Retrieved on May 14, 2007.&lt;/ref&gt; and sent to command Fort Benning (the first from his class to become a general officer). In February 1942, he took command of the [[U.S. 82nd Airborne Division|82nd Infantry Division]] before being switched to the [[28th Infantry Division (United States)|28th Infantry Division]] in June.

==World War II==
Bradley did not receive a front-line command until early 1943, after [[Operation Torch]]. He had been given [[VIII Corps (United States)|VIII Corps]], but instead was sent to [[North Africa]] to be Eisenhower's front-line troubleshooter. At Bradley's suggestion, [[II Corps (United States)|II Corps]], which had just suffered the devastating loss at the [[Kasserine Pass]], was overhauled from top to bottom, and Eisenhower installed [[George S. Patton]] as corps commander. Patton requested Bradley as his deputy, but Bradley retained the right to represent Eisenhower as well.&lt;ref&gt;Weigley, p.81&lt;/ref&gt;

Bradley succeeded Patton as head of II Corps in April and directed it in the final Tunisian battles of April and May.  Promoted to the rank of lieutenant general, Bradley commanded the Second Corps in the invasion of Sicily.

===Normandy 1944===
Bradley moved to London as commander in chief of the American ground forces preparing to invade France in 1944.  For D-Day, Bradley was chosen to command the [[First United States Army|US 1st Army]], which alongside the British Second Army made up General Montgomery's 21st Army Group.

[[File:Cherbourg 1944 s191143.jpg|right|thumb|Lt Gen Omar Bradley (left), Commanding General, U.S. First Army, listens as Maj Gen [[J. Lawton Collins]], Commanding General, [[VII Corps (United States)|US VII Corps]], describes how the city of [[Cherbourg]] was taken. (c. June 1944)]]
On 10 June, General Bradley and his staff debarked to establish a headquarters ashore. During [[Operation Overlord]], he commanded three corps directed at the two American invasion targets, [[Utah Beach]] and Omaha Beach. Later in July, he planned [[Operation Cobra]], the beginning of the breakout from the Normandy beachhead.  Operation Cobra called for the use of strategic bombers using huge bomb loads to attack German defensive lines.  After several postponements due to weather, the operation began on July 25, 1944 with a short, very intensive bombardment with lighter explosives, designed so as not to create greater rubble and craters that would slow Allied progress.  Unfortunately, Bradley's failure to properly coordinate attack plans with strategic bombing forces resulted in hundreds of American casualties, including the death of a field officer, General Lesley McNair.&lt;ref&gt;James Jay Carafano, ''After D-Day: Operation Cobra and the Normandy Breakout'' (2000); Cole C. Kingseed, &quot;Operation Cobra: Prelude to breakout.&quot;   ''Military Review;'' July 1994, Vol. 74 Issue 7, p64-67, online at EBSCO.&lt;/ref&gt;  However, the bombing was successful in knocking out the German communication system, leading to confusion and ineffectiveness, and opened the way for the ground offensive by attacking infantry.  Bradley sent in three infantry divisions—the 9th, 4th and 30th—to move in close behind the bombing.  The infantry succeeded in cracking the German defenses, opening the way for advances by armored forces commanded by General Patton to sweep around the German lines. 

As the build-up continued in Normandy, the [[Third United States Army|3rd Army]] was formed under Patton, Bradley's former commander, while General Hodges succeeded Bradley in command of the 1st Army; together, they made up Bradley's new command, the [[12th Army Group]]. By August, the 12th Army Group had swollen to over 900,000 men and ultimately consisted of four field armies. It was the largest group of American soldiers to ever serve under one field commander.

===Falaise Pocket===
Hitler's refusal to allow his army to flee the rapidly advancing Allied pincer movement created an opportunity to trap an entire German Army Group in northern France.&lt;ref&gt;Blumenson, Martin, ''General Bradley's decision at Argentan (13 August 1944)'', University of Michigan Press (1990), pp. 407-413&lt;/ref&gt; After the German attempt to split the US armies at [[Mortain]] ([[Operation Lüttich]]), Bradley's Army Group and XV Corps became the southern pincer in forming the ''[[Falaise Pocket]]'', trapping the [[German Seventh Army]] and [[Fifth Panzer Army]] in Normandy. The northern pincer was formed of Canadian forces, part of British General Sir [[Bernard L. Montgomery]]'s 21 Army Group.  On August 13, 1944, concerned that American troops would clash with Canadian forces advancing from the north-west, Bradley overrode Patton's orders for a further push north towards Falaise, while ordering XV Corps to 'concentrate for operations in another direction'.&lt;ref&gt;Essame, Herbert, ''Patton: As Military Commander'', Combined Publishing, Da Capo Press, ISBN 0938289993 (1998), p. 168&lt;/ref&gt;  Any American troops in the vicinity of Argentan were ordered to be withdrawn.&lt;ref&gt;Essame, Herbert, ''Patton: As Military Commander'', p. 168: Bradley was supported in his decision by General Eisenhower.&lt;/ref&gt;  This order effectively halted the southern pincer movement of General Haislip's XV Corps.&lt;ref&gt;Essame, Herbert, ''Patton: As Military Commander'', p. 182&lt;/ref&gt;  Though General Patton protested the order, he obeyed it, leaving an exit - a 'trap with a gap' - for the remaining German forces.&lt;ref&gt;Essame, Herbert, ''Patton: As Military Commander'', p. 182&lt;/ref&gt;  Around 20-50,000 German troops (leaving almost all of their heavy material)&lt;ref&gt;Blumenson, Martin, ''General Bradley's decision at Argentan (13 August 1944)'', University of Michigan Press (1990), pp. 416-417: Blumenson concluded that while the failure to quickly complete the encirclement was mainly due to Bradley's actions in halting XV Corps, the result was still a victory, since the German armies that escaped had almost no equipment, tanks, or other weapons.&lt;/ref&gt; escaped through the gap, avoiding encirclement and almost certain destruction.&lt;ref&gt;Essame, Herbert, ''Patton: As Military Commander'', p. 182&lt;/ref&gt;  They would later be reorganized and rearmed in time to slow the Allied advance into Holland and Germany.&lt;ref&gt;Essame, Herbert, ''Patton: As Military Commander'', p. 182&lt;/ref&gt;  Most of the blame for this outcome has been placed on Bradley.&lt;ref&gt;Wilmot, Chester, and McDevitt, Christopher, ''The Struggle For Europe'', London: Wordsworth Editions Ltd., ISBN 1853266779 (1952), p. 417&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Essame, Herbert, ''Patton: As Military Commander'', Combined Publishing, Da Capo Press, ISBN 0938289993 (1998), p. 182: German General [[Hans Speidel]], Chief of Staff of Army Group B, stated that all of Army Group B would have been completely eliminated if Patton's 5th Armored Division had been allowed to advance, sealing off German exit avenues.&lt;/ref&gt;  Bradley had incorrectly assumed, based on [[Ultra (cryptography)|Ultra]] decoding transcripts, that most of the Germans had already escaped encirclement, and he feared a German counterattack as well as possible friendly fire casualties.&lt;ref&gt;Blumenson, Martin, ''General Bradley's decision at Argentan (13 August 1944)'', University of Michigan Press (1990), pp. 410-411&lt;/ref&gt;  Though admitting a mistake had been made, Bradley placed the blame on General Montgomery for moving the Commonwealth troops too slowly, though the latter were in direct contact with a large number of SS Panzer, [[3rd Parachute Division (Germany)|Fallschirmjaeger]], and other elite German forces.&lt;ref&gt;Blumenson, Martin, ''General Bradley's decision at Argentan (13 August 1944)'', University of Michigan Press (1990), p. 412&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Jarymowycz, Roman, ''Tank Tactics; from Normandy to Lorraine'', Lynne Rienner, ISBN 1-55587-950-0 (2001), p. 196&lt;/ref&gt;

===Germany===
The American forces reached the 'Siegfried Line' or 'Westwall' in late September. The success of the advance had taken the Allied high command by surprise. They had expected the German ''[[Wehrmacht]]'' to make stands on the natural defensive lines provided by the French rivers, and had not prepared the logistics for the much deeper advance of the Allied armies, so fuel ran short. 

[[File:Marshall arnold and bradley.jpg|left|thumb|[[Chief of Staff of the United States Army|Army Chief of Staff]] General [[George Marshall]] (center) and [[United States Army Air Forces|Army Air Forces]] Commander General [[Henry H. Arnold]] confer with Bradley on the beach at Normandy in 1944.]]
Eisenhower faced a decision on strategy. Bradley favored an advance into the [[Saarland]], or possibly a two-thrust assault on both the Saarland and the [[Ruhr Area]]. Montgomery argued for a narrow thrust across the Lower Rhine, preferably with all Allied ground forces under his personal command as they had been in the early months of the Normandy campaign, into the open country beyond and then to the northern flank into the Ruhr, thus avoiding the [[Siegfried Line]]. Although Montgomery was not permitted to launch an offensive on the scale he had wanted, George Marshall and [[Hap Arnold]] were eager to use the [[First Allied Airborne Army]] to cross the Rhine, so Eisenhower agreed to [[Operation Market-Garden]].  Bradley opposed Operation Market Garden, and bitterly protested to Eisenhower the priority of supplies given to Montgomery, but Eisenhower, mindful of British public opinion regarding damage from V-1 missile launches in the north, refused to make any changes. 

Bradley's Army Group now covered a very wide front in hilly country, from the [[Netherlands]] to [[Lorraine (région)|Lorraine]].  Despite having the largest concentration of Allied army forces, Bradley faced difficulties in prosecuting a successful broad-front offensive in difficult country with a skilled enemy.  General Bradley and his First Army commander, General [[Courtney Hodges]] eventually decided to attack through a corridor known as the Aachen Gap towards the German township of Schmidt.  The only nearby military objectives were the Roer River flood control dams, but these were not mentioned in contemporary plans and documents.&lt;ref&gt;Whiting, Charles, ''The battle of Hurtgen Forest'', p. 69&lt;/ref&gt;  Bradley and Hodges' original objective may have been to outflank German forces and prevent them from reinforcing their units further north in the [[Battle of Aachen]].  After the war, Bradley would cite the Roer dams as the objective.&lt;ref&gt;Whiting, Charles, ''The battle of Hurten Forest, p. 44&lt;/ref&gt;  Since the Germans held the dams, they could also unleash millions of gallons of water into the path of advance.  The campaign's confused objectives, combined with poor intelligence&lt;ref&gt;Whiting, Charles, ''The battle of Hurten Forest'', p. 44: None of the senior commanders appear to have considered the potential danger to U.S. forces if the Germans released large amounts of water from the Roer dams, flooding the area and channeling U.S. forces into zones heavily defended by the German army.&lt;/ref&gt; resulted in the costly series of battles known as the [[Battle of Hurtgen Forest]], which cost some 33,000 American casualties.&lt;ref&gt;D'Este, Carlo, ''Eisenhower: A Soldier's Life'', p. 627&lt;/ref&gt;  At the end of the fighting in the Hurtgen, German forces remained in control of the Roer dams in what has been described as &quot;the most ineptly fought series of battles of the war in the west.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;D'Este, Carlo, ''Eisenhower: A Soldier's Life'', p. 627&lt;/ref&gt;   Further south, Patton's Third Army, which had been advancing with great speed, was faced with last priority (behind the U.S. First and Ninth Armies) for supplies, gasoline and ammunition.  As a result, the Third Army lost momentum as German resistance stiffened around the extensive defenses surrounding the city of [[Metz]].  While Bradley focused on these two campaigns, the Germans were in the process of assembling troops and materiel for a surprise winter offensive.

===Battle of the Bulge===
Bradley's command took the initial brunt of what would become the [[Battle of the Bulge]].  For logistical and command reasons, General Eisenhower decided to place Bradley's 1st and Ninth Armies under the temporary command of Field-Marshal Montgomery's 21st Army Group on the northern flank of the Bulge.  Bradley was incensed, and began shouting at Eisenhower: &quot;By God, I cannot be responsible to the American people if you do this.  I resign.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Ambrose, Stephen, ''Eisenhower, soldier and president'', New York: Simon &amp; Schuster, ISBN 9780671701079 (1990), p. 174.&lt;/ref&gt;  Eisenhower turned red, took a breath and replied evenly &quot;Brad, I - not you, am responsible to the American people.  Your resignation therefore means absolutely nothing.&quot;.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Ambrose, Stephen, ''Eisenhower, soldier and president'', p. 174.&lt;/ref&gt;   Bradley paused, made one more protest, then fell silent as Eisenhower concluded &quot;Well, Brad, those are my orders.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Ambrose, Stephen, ''Eisenhower, soldier and president'', p. 174.&lt;/ref&gt;  At least one historian has attributed Eisenhower's support for Bradley's subsequent promotion to four-star general was based in part on a desire to compensate him for the way in which he had been sidelined during the Battle of the Bulge.&lt;ref&gt;D'Este, Carlo, ''Eisenhower: A Soldier's Life'', p.668&lt;/ref&gt;  Others point out that both Secretary of War Stimson and General Eisenhower had desired to reward General Patton with a fourth star for his string of accomplishments in 1944, but that Eisenhower could not promote Patton over Bradley, [[Jacob L. Devers|Devers]], and other senior commanders without upsetting the chain of command.&lt;ref&gt;Jordan, Jonathan W., ''Brothers, Rivals, Victors: Eisenhower, Patton, Bradley, and the Partnership that drove the Allied Conquest in Europe '', New York: Penguin Group, ISBN 9781101475249(2011)&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Patton, G.S. and Blumenson, M., ''The Patton Papers, 1940-1945'', Cambridge MA: Da Capo Press, ISBN 0306807173 (1974) p. 655&lt;/ref&gt;

===Victory===
Bradley used the advantage gained in March 1945—after Eisenhower authorized a difficult but successful Allied offensive ([[Operation Veritable]] and [[Operation Grenade]]) in February 1945—to break the German defenses and cross the Rhine into the industrial heartland of the Ruhr. Aggressive pursuit of the disintegrating German troops by the Ninth Armored Division resulted in the capture of a bridge across the [[Rhine|Rhine River]] at [[Remagen]].  Bradley quickly exploited the crossing, forming the southern arm of an enormous [[pincer movement]] encircling the German forces in the Ruhr from the north and south. Over 300,000 prisoners were taken. American forces then met up with the Soviet forces near the [[Elbe]] River in mid-April. By [[V-E Day]], the 12th Army Group was a force of four armies (1st, 3rd, 9th, and 15th) that numbered over 1.3 million men.

===Command style===
Unlike some of the more colorful generals of World War II, Bradley was polite and courteous in his public appearances.  A reticent man, Bradley was first favorably brought to public attention by [[war correspondent]] [[Ernie Pyle]], who was urged by General Eisenhower to &quot;go and discover Bradley&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;D'Este, Carlo, ''Eisenhower: A Soldier's Life'', New York: Henry Holt &amp; Co. (2002), p. 404&lt;/ref&gt;  Pyle subsequently wrote several dispatches in which he referred to Bradley as the ''GI's general'', a title that would stay with Bradley throughout his remaining career.&lt;ref&gt;Nichols, David, ''Ernie's War: The Best of Ernie Pyle's World War II Dispatches'', New York: Simon &amp; Schuster Inc. (1986), p. 358&lt;/ref&gt;  [[Will Lang Jr.]] of ''[[Life (magazine)|Life]]'' magazine said &quot;The thing I most admire about Omar Bradley is his gentleness. He was never known to issue an order to anybody of any rank without saying 'Please' first.&quot;

While the public at large never forgot the image created by newspaper correspondents, a different view of Bradley was offered by combat historian [[S.L.A. Marshall]], who knew both Bradley and George Patton, and had interviewed officers and men under their commands.  Marshall, who was also a critic of George S. Patton,&lt;ref&gt;Marshall, S.L.A., ''Great Georgie Redone'', The Charleston Gazette, Vol. 4, 21 March 1970, p. 4: &quot;My own view of him [Patton] was that he was touched by the sun, as were [[Orde Wingate]] and [[Stonewall Jackson]].&quot;&lt;/ref&gt; noted that Bradley's 'common man' image &quot;was played up by Ernie Pyle...The GI's were not impressed with him.  They scarcely knew him.  He's not a flamboyant figure and he didn't get out much to troops.  And the idea that he was idolized by the average soldier is just rot.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;D'Este, Carlo. ''Patton: A Genius For War'', New York: HarperCollins, ISBN 0060164557 (1995), p. 467&lt;/ref&gt;

While Bradley retained his reputation as the ''GI's general'', he was criticized by some of his contemporaries for other aspects of his leadership style, sometimes described as 'managerial' in nature.&lt;ref&gt;Lewis, Adrian R., ''Omaha Beach, A Flawed Victory'', University of North Carolina Press, ISBN 0807854697 (2001), p. 263&lt;/ref&gt;  British General [[Bernard Montgomery]]'s assessment of Bradley was that he was &quot;dull, conscientious, dependable, and loyal&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;Hamilton, Nigel, ''Master of the Battlefield: Monty's Wary Years, 1942-1944'', New York: McGraw-Hill (1983), p. 658&lt;/ref&gt;  He had a habit of peremptorily relieving senior commanders who he felt were too independent, or whose command style did not agree with his own, such as the colorful and aggressive General [[Terry de la Mesa Allen, Sr.|Terry Allen]], commander of the [[U.S. 1st Infantry Division]].&lt;ref&gt;D'Este, Carlo, ''Patton'', p. 467-468: Patton recorded that Bradley was &quot;too prone to cut off heads.  This will make division commanders lose their confidence.&quot;&lt;/ref&gt;  While Patton is often viewed today as the prototype of the intolerant, impulsive commander, Bradley actually sacked far more generals and senior commanders during World War II, whereas Patton relieved only one general from his command - [[Orlando Ward]] - for cause during the entire war (and only after giving General Ward two warnings).&lt;ref&gt;D'Este, Carlo, p. 467&lt;/ref&gt;

==Post-war==
[[File:Omar Bradley, official military photo, 1949.JPEG|thumb|right|General Omar Bradley, 1949]]

===Veterans Administration===
President Truman appointed Bradley to head the [[United States Department of Veterans Affairs|Veterans Administration]] for two years after the war. He is credited with doing much to improve its health care system and with helping veterans receive their educational benefits under the [[G. I. Bill of Rights]]. Bradley's influence on the VA is credited with helping shape it into the agency it is today. He was a regular visitor to Capitol Hill and lobbied on behalf of veterans' benefits in testimony before various congressional veteran affairs committees.

===Chairman of the Joint Chiefs of Staff===
Bradley became the [[Chief of Staff of the United States Army|Army Chief of Staff]] in 1948.  After assuming command, Bradley found a U.S. military establishment badly in need of reorganization, equipment, and training.  As Bradley himself put it, &quot;the Army of 1948 could not fight its way out of a paper bag.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Dunford, J.F. (Lt. Col.) The Strategic Implications of Defensive Operations at the Pusan Perimeter July–September 1950, Carlisle, PA: U.S. Army War College (7 April 1999) p. 6&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Bradley, Omar, and Blair, Clay, ''A General's Life: An AutoBiography by General of the Army Omar N. Bradley'', p. 474&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Blair, Clay, The Forgotten War: America in Korea, 1950-1953, Naval Institute Press (2003), p. 290&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Hofmann, George F., ''Tanks and the Korean War: A case study of unpreparedness'', Armor, Vol. 109 Issue 5 (Sep/Oct 2000), pp. 7-12&lt;/ref&gt; 
 
On August 11, 1949, President [[Harry S Truman]] appointed Bradley the first [[Chairman of the Joint Chiefs of Staff]].  After his initial 1948 plan to expand the Army and modernize its equipment was rejected by the Truman Administration, Bradley reacted to the increasingly severe postwar defense department budget cutbacks imposed by Secretary of Defense [[Louis A. Johnson]] by publicly supporting Johnson's decisions, going so far as to tell Congress that he would be doing a &quot;disservice to the nation&quot; if he asked for a larger military force.&lt;ref&gt;Bradley, Omar, and Blair, Clay, ''A General's Life: An AutoBiography by General of the Army Omar N. Bradley'', pp. 486-487&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Blair, Clay, The Forgotten War: America in Korea, 1950-1953, Naval Institute Press (2003), p. 290&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Hofmann, George F., ''Tanks and the Korean War: A case study of unpreparedness'', Armor, Vol. 109 Issue 5 (Sep/Oct 2000), pp. 7-12&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Davis, Vincent, ''The Post-imperial Presidency'', New Brunswick: Transaction Press ISBN 0878557474 (1980), p. 102&lt;/ref&gt;  Bradley also suggested that [[Revolt of the Admirals|official Navy protests]] of Secretary Johnson's actions in cancelling construction of its supercarrier, the [[USS United States (CVA-58)|USS United States]] were due to improper personal or political, even [[Mutiny|mutinous]] motives, calling Navy admirals &quot;fancy dans who won't hit the line with all they have on every play unless they can call the signals&quot;, and who were in &quot;open rebellion against the civilian control.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Axlerod, Alan, ''Bradley'', New York:Palgrave MacMillan, ISBN 9780230600188 (2008), p. 174&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Blechman, Barry M., ''The American military in the twenty-first century'', Henry L. Stimson Center, New York: St. Martin's Press, ISBN 0312103695 (1993), p. 14&lt;/ref&gt;  

In his second memoir, Bradley would later state that not arguing more forcefully in 1948 and 1949 for a sufficient defense department budget &quot;was a mistake...perhaps the greatest mistake I made in my postwar years in Washington.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Bradley, Omar, and Blair, Clay, ''A General's Life: An AutoBiography by General of the Army Omar N. Bradley'', p. 487&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;''Testimony by Army Chief of Staff Omar N. Bradley before the Senate Armed Services Committee'', 25 March 1948, Army Digest 3, No. 5 (May 1948), pp. 61-63&lt;/ref&gt; 

On September 22, 1950,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url = http://usmilitary.about.com/library/milinfo/armyorank/blgoa.htm | title = GENERAL OF THE ARMIES OF THE UNITED STATES AND GENERAL OF THE ARMY OF THE UNITED STATES | accessdate = 2009-09-28 | author = | last = | first = | authorlink = | coauthors = | date = | work = | publisher = | pages = | language = | doi = | archiveurl = | archivedate = | quote = General of the Army Omar N. Bradley, appointed Sep 22, 50. Deceased Apr 81. (General Bradley appointed pursuant to PL 957, on Sep 18, 1950.)}}&lt;/ref&gt; he was promoted to the rank of [[General of the Army (United States)|General of the Army]], the fifth — and last — man to achieve that rank.  That same year, Bradley was made the first [[Chairman of the NATO Military Committee]]. He remained on the committee until August 1953, when he left active duty. During his service, Bradley visited the White House over 300 times and was frequently featured on the cover of TIME magazine.

===Korea===
As Chairman of the Joint Chiefs of Staff, Bradley was the senior military commander at the outset of the [[Korean War]].  When North Korea invaded South Korea in June 1950, Bradley was faced with re-organizing and deploying an American military force that was a shadow of its World War II counterpart.&lt;ref&gt;Blair, Clay, ''The Forgotten War: America in Korea, 1950-1953'', Naval Institute Press (2003), p. 290&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Hofmann, George F., ''Tanks and the Korean War: A case study of unpreparedness'', Armor, Vol. 109 Issue 5 (Sep/Oct 2000), pp. 7-12: In 1948, the U.S. Army had to impose an 80 percent reduction in equipment requirements, deferring any equipment modernization. When the Joint Chiefs of Staff submitted a $30 billion total defense budget for FY 1948, the administration capped the DOD budget at the $14.4 billion set in 1947 and progressively reduced in succeeding fiscal years until January 1950, when it was reduced again to $13.5 billion.&lt;/ref&gt;  The impact of the Truman administration's defense budget cutbacks were now keenly felt, as poorly equipped American troops, lacking sufficient tanks, anti-tank weapons, or artillery were driven down the Korean peninsula to [[Pusan]] in a series of costly rearguard actions.&lt;ref&gt;Dunford, J.F. (Lt. Col.) ''The Strategic Implications of Defensive Operations at the Pusan Perimeter July–September 1950'', Carlisle, PA: U.S. Army War College (7 April 1999) pp. 6-8, 12&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Zabecki, David T., ''Stand or Die - 1950 Defense of Korea's Pusan Perimeter'', Military History (May 2009):  The inability of U.S. forces to stop the 1950 North Korean summer offensive cost the Eighth Army 4,280 killed in action, 12,377 wounded, 2,107 missing and 401 confirmed captured between July 5 and September 16, 1950, in addition to the lives of tens of thousands of South Korean soldiers and civilians.&lt;/ref&gt;  In a postwar analysis of the unpreparedness of U.S. Army forces deployed to Korea during the summer and fall of 1950, Army Major General [[Floyd L. Parks]] stated that &quot;Many who never lived to tell the tale had to fight the full range of ground warfare from offensive to delaying action, unit by unit, man by man...[T]hat we were able to snatch victory from the jaws of defeat...does not relieve us from the blame of having placed our own flesh and blood in such a predicament.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Lewis, Adrian R., ''The American culture of war'', New York: Taylor &amp; Francis Group, ISBN 9780415979757 (2007), p. 82&lt;/ref&gt;

Bradley was the chief military policy maker during the Korean War, and supported Truman's original plan of 'rolling back' Communist aggression by conquering all of North Korea.  When Chinese Communists entered North Korea in late 1950 and again drove back American forces, Bradley agreed that rollback had to be dropped in favor of a ''containment'' strategy of North Korea.  The containment strategy was subsequently adopted by the Truman administration for North Korea, and applied to communist expansion worldwide.  Never an admirer of General [[Douglas MacArthur]], Bradley was instrumental in convincing Truman to dismiss MacArthur as the overall commander in the Korean theatre&lt;ref&gt;MacArthur actually held several titles: he was the Allied Commander of United Nations Forces in the Far East, [[Supreme Commander of the Allied Powers]] (SCAP) in Japan, and Commander, [[U.S. Army Forces Far East]] (USAFFE)&lt;/ref&gt; after MacArthur resisted administration attempts to scale back strategic objectives in the Korean War.   

In testimony to Congress Bradley strongly rebuked MacArthur for his support of victory at all costs in Korea.  Soon after Truman relieved MacArthur of command in April 1951, Bradley said in Congressional testimony, &quot;Red China is not the powerful nation seeking to dominate the world. Frankly, in the opinion of the Joint Chiefs of Staff, this strategy would involve us in [[the wrong war, at the wrong place, at the wrong time, and with the wrong enemy]].&quot;

==Retirement==
[[File:Omar Bradley Portrait.jpg|General Omar Nelson Bradley|thumb|left|General Omar N. Bradley Portrait]]
In retirement Bradley held a number of positions in commercial life, among them [[Chair (official)|Chairman of the Board]] of the [[Bulova|Bulova Watch Company]] from 1958 to 1973.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;[http://www.bulova.com/about/history.aspx The History of Bulova]&quot;. [[Bulova]]. Retrieved on May 14, 2007.&lt;/ref&gt;

His memoirs, ''A Soldier's Story'' (ghostwritten by [[A.J. Liebling]]), appeared in 1951; a fuller autobiography ''A General's Life: An Autobiography'' (coauthored  by [[Clay Blair]]) appeared in 1983)  He took the opportunity to attack Field Marshal Montgomery's 1945 claims to have won the Battle of the Bulge. Bradley spent his last years in [[Texas]] at a special residence on the grounds of the [[William Beaumont Army Medical Center]], part of the complex which supports [[Fort Bliss]].

On December 1, 1965, Bradley's wife, Mary, died of [[leukemia]]. He met Esther Dora &quot;Kitty&quot; Buhler and married her on September 12, 1966; they were married until his death. 

As a horse racing fan, Bradley spent much of his leisure time at racetracks in California and often presented the winners trophies. He also was a lifetime sports fan, especially of college football.  He was the 1948 [[Grand Marshal of the Tournament of Roses]] and attended several subsequent Rose Bowl games (his black limousine with personalized CA license plate &quot;ONB&quot; and a red plate with 5 gold stars was frequently seen driving through Pasadena streets with police motorcycle escort toward the Rose Bowl on New Year's Day), and was prominent at the Sun Bowl in El Paso, Texas, and the Independence Bowl in Shreveport, Louisiana in later years.

Bradley also served as a member of President Lyndon Johnson's [[The Wise Men#Vietnam war era|Wise Men]], a high-level advisory group considering policy for  the [[Vietnam War]]. Bradley was a hawk and recommended against withdrawal from Vietnam&lt;ref&gt;Frank Everson Vandiver, ''Shadows of Vietnam: Lyndon Johnson's wars'' (1997) [http://books.google.com/books?id=pkLBm-P-5EAC&amp;pg=PA327&amp;dq=vietnam+Bradley+hawks&amp;lr=&amp;as_drrb_is=q&amp;as_minm_is=0&amp;as_miny_is=&amp;as_maxm_is=0&amp;as_maxy_is=&amp;num=20&amp;as_brr=3&amp;ei=LJgLTMbdKo2kkAT3h_TzDA&amp;cd=3 p 327 online]&lt;/ref&gt; 

In 1970, Bradley served as a consultant for the film ''[[Patton (film)|Patton]]'', though the extent of his active participation is largely unknown.  Screenwriters [[Francis Ford Coppola]] and [[Edmund H. North]] wrote most of the film based on two biographies, Bradley's ''A Soldier's Story'' and ''Patton: Ordeal and Triumph'' by [[Ladislas Farago]].  As the film was made without access to General Patton's diaries or any information from his family, it largely relied upon observations by Bradley and other military contemporaries when attempting to reconstruct Patton's thoughts and motives.&lt;ref&gt;Marshall, S.L.A., ''Great Georgie Redone'', The Charleston Gazette, Vol. 4, 21 March 1970, p. 4&lt;/ref&gt; In a review of the film ''Patton'', S.L.A. Marshall, who knew both Patton and Bradley, stated that &quot;The Bradley name gets heavy billing on a picture of [a] comrade that, while not caricature, is the likeness of a victorious, glory-seeking buffoon...Patton in the flesh was an enigma.  He so stays in the film...Napoleon once said that the art of the general is not strategy but knowing how to mold human nature...Maybe that is all producer Frank McCarthy and Gen. Bradley, his chief advisor, are trying to say.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Marshall, S.L.A., ''Great Georgie Redone'', The Charleston Gazette, Vol. 4, 21 March 1970, p. 4&lt;/ref&gt;  While Bradley knew Patton personally, it was also well known that the two men were polar opposites in personality, and that Bradley despised Patton both personally and professionally.&lt;ref&gt;Bradley, Omar N., ''A Soldier's Story'', p. 109&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;D'Este, Carlo. ''Patton: A Genius For War'', New York: HarperCollins, ISBN 0060164557 (1995), pp. 466-467&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;D'Este, Carlo, Eisenhower: A Soldier's Life, New York: Henry Holt &amp; Co. (2002), pp. 403-404&lt;/ref&gt;  Bradley's role in the film remains controversial to this day.

Bradley attended the 30th anniversary of D-Day at Normandy, France on June 6, 1974, participating in various parades.

On January 10, 1977, Bradley was presented with the [[Presidential Medal of Freedom]] by President [[Gerald Ford]].

One of Bradley's last public appearances was at the festivities surrounding the inauguration of President [[Ronald Reagan]] in January 1981.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.presidency.ucsb.edu/ws/index.php?pid=43669 Statement of Ronald Reagan in memory of Omar Bradley]&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:OmarBradleyTombstone.jpg|thumb|General Bradley's headstone in Arlington Cemetery]]
Omar Bradley died on April 8, 1981 in New York City of a [[cardiac arrhythmia]], just a few minutes after receiving an award from the National Institute of Social Sciences. He is buried at [[Arlington National Cemetery]], next to his two wives.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.arlingtoncemetery.net/omarnels.htm Omar Nelson Bradley, General of the Army]&lt;/ref&gt;

==Recognition==
Bradley's posthumous autobiography, ''A General's Life'', was published in 1983; the book was begun by Bradley himself, who found writing difficult, and so [[Clay Blair]] was brought in to help shape the autobiography; after Bradley's death, Blair continued the writing, making the unusual choice of using Bradley's first-person voice.  The resulting book is highly readable, and based on extremely thorough research, including extensive interviews with all concerned, and Bradley's own papers.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Bradley|first=Omar|coauthors=Clay Blair|title=A General's Life|isbn=978-0671410247}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Bradley is known for saying, &quot;Ours is a world of nuclear giants and ethical infants. We know more about war than about peace, more about killing than we know about living.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url = http://www.bartleby.com/66/26/8126.html | title = Quotation 8126 | accessdate = 2008-06-25 | author = Omar Bradley | last = | first = | authorlink = | coauthors = | date = 1948-11-11 | work = The Columbia World of Quotations. Copyright © 1996 
|publisher = Columbia University Press. | pages = | language = | doi = | archiveurl = | archivedate = | quote = The Columbia World of Quotations.  1996. NUMBER:  8126  QUOTATION:  We have grasped the mystery of the atom and rejected the Sermon on the Mount.... The world has achieved brilliance without wisdom, power without conscience. Ours is a world of nuclear giants and ethical infants.  ATTRIBUTION:  Omar Bradley (1893–1981), U.S. general. speech, November 11, 1948, Armistice Day. Collected Writings, vol. 1 (1967).
}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The U.S. Army's [[M2/M3 Bradley Fighting Vehicle|M2 Bradley infantry fighting vehicle and M3 Bradley cavalry fighting vehicle]] are named after General Bradley.

Bradley's hometown, Moberly, Missouri, is planning a library and museum in his honor. Two recent Bradley Leadership Symposia in Moberly have honored his role as one of the American military's foremost teachers of young officers. On February 12, 2010, the U.S. House of Representatives, the Missouri Senate, the Missouri House, the County of Randolph and the City of Moberly all recognized Bradley's birthday as General Omar Nelson Bradley Day. The ceremony marking the day was held at his high school alma mater and featured addresses by the current Congressional representative, Blaine Luetkemeyer, and Moberly High School Principal Aaron Vitt.

On May 5, 2000, the [[United States Postal Service]] issued a series of ''Distinguished Soldiers'' stamps in which Bradley was honored.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;[http://shop.usps.com/webapp/wcs/stores/servlet/ProductDisplay?catalogId=10152&amp;storeId=10001&amp;productId=16810&amp;langId=-1&amp;parent_category_rn=13370 Distinguished Soldiers]&quot;. United States Postal Service. Retrieved on May 16, 2007.&lt;/ref&gt;

==Summary of service==
===Dates of rank===
{|class=&quot;wikitable&quot; style=&quot;background:white&quot;
|-
|align=&quot;center&quot; |''No pin insignia in 1915''
|[[Second Lieutenant#United States|Second Lieutenant]], [[United States Army]]: June 12, 1915
|-
|align=&quot;center&quot; |[[File:US-OF1A.svg|13px]]
|[[First Lieutenant#United States|First Lieutenant]], United States Army: October 13, 1916
|-
|align=&quot;center&quot; |[[File:US-O3 insignia.svg|33px]]
|[[Captain (U.S. Army)|Captain]], United States Army: August 22, 1917
|-
|align=&quot;center&quot; |[[File:US-O4 insignia.svg|40px]]
|[[Major (United States)|Major]], [[National Army (USA)|National Army]]: July 17, 1918
|-
|align=&quot;center&quot; |[[File:US-O3 insignia.svg|33px]]
|Captain, [[Regular Army (United States)|Regular Army]] (reverted to permanent rank): November 4, 1922
|-
|align=&quot;center&quot; |[[File:US-O4 insignia.svg|40px]]
|Major, Regular Army: June 27, 1924
|-
|align=&quot;center&quot; |[[File:US-O5 insignia.svg|40px]]
|Lieutenant Colonel, Regular Army: July 22, 1936
|-
|align=&quot;center&quot; |[[File:US-O6 insignia.svg|60px]]
|Colonel, Regular Army: November 13, 1943
|-
|align=&quot;center&quot; |[[File:US-O7 insignia.svg|33px]]
|[[Brigadier general (United States)|Brigadier General]], [[Army of the United States]]: February 24, 1941
|-
|align=&quot;center&quot; |[[File:US-O8 insignia.svg|66px]]
|[[Major general (United States)|Major General]], Army of the United States: February 18, 1942
|-
|align=&quot;center&quot; |[[File:US-O9 insignia.svg|100px]]
|[[Lieutenant general (United States)|Lieutenant General]], Army of the United States: June 9, 1943
|-
|align=&quot;center&quot; rowspan=&quot;2&quot; |[[File:US-O10 insignia.svg|133px]]
|[[General (United States)|General]], Army of the United States: March 29, 1945
|-
|General rank made permanent in the Regular Army: January 31, 1949
|-
|align=&quot;center&quot; |[[File:US-O11 insignia.svg|95px]]
|[[General of the Army (United States)|General of the Army]], Regular Army: September 22, 1950
|}

===Orders, decorations and medals===
{|
|-
|{{ribbon devices|number=3|type=oak|ribbon=Distinguished Service Medal ribbon.svg|width=60}}
|[[Distinguished Service Medal (Army)|Army Distinguished Service Medal]] (With three [[oak leaf cluster]]s)
|-
|[[File:Navy Distinguished Service ribbon.svg|60px]]
|[[Navy Distinguished Service Medal]]
|-
|[[File:Silver Star ribbon.svg|60px]]
|[[Silver Star]]
|-
|{{ribbon devices|number=1|type=oak|ribbon=Legion of Merit ribbon.svg|width=60}}
|[[Legion of Merit]] (w/oak leaf cluster)
|-
|[[File:Bronze Star ribbon.svg|60px]]
|[[Bronze Star Medal|Bronze Star]]
|-
|[[File:Mexican Border Service Medal ribbon.svg|60px]]
|[[Mexican Border Service Medal]]
|-
|[[File:World War I Victory Medal ribbon.svg|60px]]
|[[World War I Victory Medal (United States)|World War I Victory Medal]]
|-
|[[File:American Defense Service ribbon.svg|60px]]
|[[American Defense Service Medal]]
|-
|{{ribbon devices|number=8|type=service-star|ribbon=European-African-Middle Eastern Campaign ribbon.svg|width=60}}
|[[European-African-Middle Eastern Campaign Medal]] with one silver and three campaign stars
|-
|[[File:World War II Victory Medal ribbon.svg|60px]]
|[[World War II Victory Medal]]
|-
|[[File:Army of Occupation ribbon.svg|60px]]
|[[Army of Occupation Medal]] with Germany clasp
|-
|[[File:National Defense Service Medal ribbon.svg|60px]]
|[[National Defense Service Medal]] with star
|-
|[[File:Order of the Bath UK ribbon.png|60px]]
|British Honorary Knight Commander of the [[Order of the Bath]]
|-
|[[File:Polonia Restituta Komandorski.jpg|60px]]
|Commander's Cross of the [[Order of Polonia Restituta]]
|-
|[[File:CdG45.gif|60px]]
|[[Croix de guerre 1939-1945 (France)|French ''Croix de guerre'' with palm]]
|-
|[[File:Order kutuzov1 rib.png|60px]]
|[[Order of Kutuzov|Order of Kutuzov (1st class)]]
|-
|[[File:Order suvorov1 rib.png|60px]]
|[[Order of Suvorov|Order of Suvorov (1st class)]]
|-
|[[File:LUX Croix de Guerre ribbon.svg|60px]]
|[[Luxembourg War Cross]]
|-
|[[Image:Presidential Medal of Freedom (ribbon).png|60px]]
|[[Presidential Medal of Freedom]]
|}

===Assignment history===
[[File:Omar Bradley.jpg|right|frame|Omar Bradley]]
*1911: Cadet, United States Military Academy
*1915: 14th Infantry Regiment
*1919: ROTC professor, [[South Dakota State University|South Dakota State College]]
*1920: Instructor, [[United States Military Academy]] (West Point)
*1924: Infantry School Student, Fort Benning, Georgia
*1925: Commanding Officer, 19th and 27th Infantry Regiments
*1927: Office of National Guard and Reserve Affairs, Hawaiian Department
*1928: Student, Command and General Staff School
*1929: Instructor, Fort Benning, [[United States Army Infantry School|Infantry School]]
*1934: Plans and Training Office, USMA West Point
*1938: War Department General Staff, G-1 Chief of Operations Branch and Assistant Secretary of the General Staff
*1941: Commandant, Infantry School Fort Benning
*1942: Commanding General, 82nd Infantry Division and 28th Infantry Division
*1943: Commanding General, II Corps, North Africa and Sicily
*1943: Commanding General, Field Forces European Theater
{{Portal box|United States Army|Military of the United States}}
*1944: Commanding General, First Army (Later 1st and 12th U.S. Army Groups)
*1945: Administrator of Veterans Affairs, Veterans Administration
*1948: United States Army Chief of Staff
*1949: Chairman of the Joint Chiefs of Staff
*1953: Retired from active service

==Notes==
{{Reflist|2}}

==References==
*Blair, Clay, ''The Forgotten War: America in Korea, 1950-1953'', Naval Institute Press, ISBN 1591140757, 9781591140757 (2003)
* Blumenson, Martin, ''General Bradley's decision at Argentan (13 August 1944)'', University of Michigan Library Press (1990)
* Blumenson, Martin. ''The battle of the generals: the untold story of the Falaise Pocket, the campaign that should have won World War II'' (1993)
* Bradley, Omar N. and Blair, Clay. ''A General's Life: An Autobiography'', New York: Simon &amp; Schuster, ISBN 9780671410230 (1983). 752 pp.
* Bradley, Omar N., ''A Soldier's Story'', New York: Holt Publishing Co., ISBN 0375754210 (1951)
* D'Este, Carlo. ''Patton: A Genius for War'' (1995)
* Jordan, Jonathan W., &quot;Brothers Rivals Victors: Eisenhower, Patton, Bradley, and the Partnership that Drove the Allied Conquest in Europe&quot; NAL: 2011, ISBN 0451232127
*[[Russell F. Weigley]] ''Eisenhower's Lieutenants: The Campaign of France and Germany 1944-1945'' Bloomington, IN: Indiana University Press, 1981. ISBN 0-253-20608-1
*Whiting, Charles, ''The battle of Hurtgen Forest'', Cambridge, MA: Da Capo Press, ISBN 1580970559 (2000)

==Further reading==
*{{cite book|url = http://www.history.army.mil/brochures/bradley/bradley.htm| title = Omar Nelson Bradley, The Centennial| publisher= [[United States Army Center of Military History]]}}

==External links==
{{Commons|Omar N. Bradley}}
{{wikiquote}}
*[http://www.arlingtoncemetery.net/omarnels.htm Omar Nelson Bradley, General of the Army], Arlington National Cemetery profile.
*[http://www.presidency.ucsb.edu/ws/index.php?pid=5550 The American Presidency Project]
*{{Find a Grave|125|accessdate=2008-07-31}}

{{s-start}}
{{s-mil}}
{{succession box 
|before = Gen. [[George Grunert]] 
|title = Commanding General of the [[First United States Army]] 
|years = 1943–1944 
|after = Gen. [[Courtney Hodges]]}}
{{succession box 
|before = Gen. [[Dwight Eisenhower]] 
|title = [[Chief of Staff of the United States Army]] 
|years = 1948–1949 
|after = Gen. [[J. Lawton Collins]]}}
{{succession box
|before = Adm. [[William D. Leahy]]&lt;br/&gt;&lt;small&gt;as ''Chief of Staff to the Commander in Chief''&lt;/small&gt;
|title = [[Chairman of the Joint Chiefs of Staff]]
|years = 1949–1953 
|after = Adm. [[Arthur W. Radford]]}}
{{succession box
|before = None
|title = [[Chairman of the NATO Military Committee]]
|years = 1949–1951 
|after = Lt. Gen. [[Etienne Baele]]}}
{{s-ach}}
{{succession box
|before = [[Billy Graham (evangelist)|Billy Graham]]
|title = [[Sylvanus Thayer Award|Sylvanus Thayer Award recipient]]
|years = 1973
|after = [[Robert Daniel Murphy]]}}
{{s-end}}

{{JCS}}
{{VAAdmins}}
{{NCAA Theodore Roosevelt Award}}
{{Chairmen of the NATO Military Committee}}

{{Persondata
|NAME=Bradley, Omar Nelson
|ALTERNATIVE NAMES=
|SHORT DESCRIPTION=[[United States Army]] field commander during [[World War II]]
|DATE OF BIRTH=February 12, 1893
|PLACE OF BIRTH=[[Clark, Missouri]]
|DATE OF DEATH=April 8, 1981
|PLACE OF DEATH=[[New York City]], [[New York]]
}}
{{DEFAULTSORT:Bradley, Omar Nelson}}
[[Category:1893 births]]
[[Category:1981 deaths]]
[[Category:American 5 star officers]]
[[Category:Chairmen of the Joint Chiefs of Staff]]
[[Category:United States Army Chiefs of Staff]]
[[Category:Operation Overlord people]]
[[Category:American people of World War II]]
[[Category:Army Black Knights baseball players]]
[[Category:Army Black Knights football players]]
[[Category:Presidential Medal of Freedom recipients]]
[[Category:Recipients of the Silver Star]]
[[Category:Recipients of the Bronze Star Medal]]
[[Category:Recipients of the Distinguished Service Medal (United States)]]
[[Category:Recipients of the Legion of Merit]]
[[Category:Commanders of the Order of Polonia Restituta]]
[[Category:Recipients of the Croix de Guerre (Luxembourg)]]
[[Category:Recipients of the Order of Suvorov]]
[[Category:Recipients of the Order of Kutuzov]]
[[Category:Honorary Knights Commander of the Order of the Bath]]
[[Category:United States Army Command and General Staff College alumni]]
[[Category:United States Army War College alumni]]
[[Category:People from Randolph County, Missouri]]
[[Category:Burials at Arlington National Cemetery]]

[[ar:عمر برادلي]]
[[bg:Омар Брадли]]
[[ca:Omar Bradley]]
[[cs:Omar Bradley]]
[[da:Omar Bradley]]
[[de:Omar N. Bradley]]
[[es:Omar Nelson Bradley]]
[[fr:Omar Bradley]]
[[gl:Omar Bradley]]
[[ko:오마 브래들리]]
[[hr:Omar Bradley]]
[[id:Omar Bradley]]
[[it:Omar Bradley]]
[[he:עומר בראדלי]]
[[hu:Omar Bradley]]
[[nl:Omar Bradley]]
[[ja:オマール・ブラッドレー]]
[[no:Omar Bradley]]
[[pl:Omar Bradley]]
[[pt:Omar Bradley]]
[[ro:Omar Bradley]]
[[ru:Брэдли, Омар]]
[[sk:Omar Bradley]]
[[sl:Omar Nelson Bradley]]
[[sr:Омар Бредли]]
[[sh:Omar Bradley]]
[[fi:Omar Bradley]]
[[sv:Omar Bradley]]
[[tr:Omar Bradley]]
[[uk:Омар Бредлі]]
[[vi:Omar Bradley]]
[[zh:奥马尔·布拉德利]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
