<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="166740" ns="0" title="Cirrocumulus cloud"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Infobox Cloud
| name = Cirrocumulus cloud
| image location = Cirrocumulus 20040830.jpg
| image name = Cirrocumulus floccus
| genus= Cirro- (''curl of hair'')&lt;br /&gt;-cumulus (''heaped'')
| species=
| variety= 
| altitude_m = Above 6000
| altitude_ft = 20,000
| level = high
| appearance = Small, high, patched clouds, in rows&lt;ref name=&quot;GATech&quot;&gt;{{cite web|title=Cirrocumulus Clouds|url=http://nenes.eas.gatech.edu/Cloud/Clouds.pdf|work=Cloud Microphysics Webpage|publisher=Georgia Tech University|accessdate=6 February 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;
| precipitation = Occasionally [[virga]]&lt;ref name=&quot;GATech&quot;/&gt;. May descend into altocumulus, stratocumulus and rain-bearing nimbostratus if cold front is approaching.
| abbreviation = CC&lt;ref name=&quot;ahrens-120&quot;/&gt;
}}
'''Cirrocumulus''' clouds are one of the three main types of high-altitude clouds, which also includes [[cirrus cloud]]s and [[cirrostratus cloud]]s.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last=Funk|first=Ted|title=Cloud Classifications and Characteristics|url=http://www.crh.noaa.gov/lmk/soo/docu/cloudchart.pdf|work=The Science Corner|publisher=NOAA|accessdate=6 February 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; They usually occur at an altitude of {{convert|5|km|ft}} to {{convert|12|km|ft}}. Like other [[cumulus clouds]], cirrocumulus clouds signify [[convection]]. Unlike other [[cirrus cloud]]s, cirrocumulus include a small amount of liquid water droplets, although these are in a [[supercooled]] state. Ice crystals are the predominant component, and typically, the ice crystals cause the supercooled water drops in the cloud to rapidly freeze, transforming the cirrocumulus into [[cirrostratus]]. This process can also produce precipitation in the form of a [[virga]] consisting of ice or snow. Thus cirrocumulus clouds are usually short-lived.&lt;ref name=gpp&gt;{{harvnb|Prector-Pinney|p=21}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Properly, the term cirrocumulus refers to each cloud, but is typically also used to refer to an entire patch of cirrocumulus. When used in this way, each cirrocumulus element is referred to as a &quot;cloudlet&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Cirrocumulus - Meteorology/Climate|url=http://ian.umces.edu/imagelibrary/displayimage-search-0-6309.html|work=Integration and Application Network|publisher=University of Maryland Center for Environmental Science|accessdate=6 February 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Appearance==
A cirrocumulus is typically a large, white patch or tuft without a gray shadow. Each cloudlet appears no larger than a finger held at arms length.&lt;ref name=&quot;gpp&quot;/&gt; It occurs in patches or sheets along with other cirrocumulus. These often are organized in rows like other cumulus, but since they are so small, cirrocumulus patches take on a finer appearance, sometimes also referred to colloquially as &quot;herringbone&quot; or &quot;mackerel&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;ahrens-120&quot;&gt;{{harvnb|Ahrens|2006|p=120}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The cirrocumulus is distinguished from the not so similar [[altocumulus]] in several ways, although the two cloud types can occasionally occur together with no clear demarcation between them. Cirrocumulus generally occur at higher altitudes than altocumulus, and thus the &quot;cloudlets&quot; appear smaller as they are more distant from observation at ground level. They are also colder. Cirrocumulus clouds never cast self-shadows and are translucent to a certain degree. They are also typically found amongst other cirrus clouds in the sky, and are usually themselves seen to be transforming into these other types of cirrus.&lt;ref name=&quot;gpp&quot;/&gt;
[[Image:Cirrocumulus Clouds July 2010.jpg|300px|thumb|right|Cirrocumulus clouds on a summer afternoon]]

Cirrocumulus clouds tend to reflect the red and yellow colors during a sunset and sunrise, and thus they have been referred to as &quot;one of the most beautiful clouds&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;ahrens-120&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;usatoday-cumulus&quot;&gt;{{cite web|last=Palmer|first=Chad|title=Cumulus clouds|url=http://www.usatoday.com/weather/wcumulus.htm|publisher=USA Today|accessdate=6 February 2011|date=October 16, 2005}}&lt;/ref&gt;  This occurs because they reflect the unscattered rays of light from the early morning or evening sun, and those rays are yellow, orange, and red.&lt;ref name=&quot;ahrens-98&quot;&gt;{{harvnb|Ahrens|2007|p=98}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Forecast==
Cirrocumulus usually only forms in patches. If it forms in patches with cirrus or cirrostratus and the clouds spread across the sky, it usually means rain in 6 to 8 hours (can be more if front is slow moving). If there are only small patches of cirrocumulus and perhaps some wisps of cirrus, it usually means a continuation of good weather and if it is seen after rain it usually means improving weather. 

==References==
;Footnotes
{{Reflist}}

;Bibliography
*{{cite book|title=The Cloud Collector's Handbook|first=Gavin|last=Pretor-Pinney|isbn=978-0-340-91943-9}}
*{{cite book|last=Ahrens|first=C. Donald|title=Meteorology Today: an Introduction to Weather, Climate, and the Environment|year=2006|publisher=Brooks Cole|isbn=978-0-495-01162-0|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=SpGfKb23Y9QC&amp;pg=PA120&amp;lpg=PA120&amp;dq=%2Bcirrocumulus+cloud#v=onepage&amp;q=%2Bcirrocumulus%20cloud&amp;f=false|edition=8|accessdate=6 February 2011|page=120|format=eBook|month=February}}
*{{cite book|last=Ahrens|first=C. Donald|title=Essentials of Meteorology: An Invitation to the Atmosphere|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=2Yn29IFukbgC&amp;pg=PA98&amp;lpg=PA98&amp;dq=%2Bcirrocumulus+cloud#v=onepage&amp;q=%2Bcirrocumulus%20cloud&amp;f=false|publisher=Brooks Cole|isbn=978-0-495-11558-8|month=January|year=2007|pages=97–99|edition=5}}

== External links ==
{{Commons category|Cirrocumulus clouds}}
*[http://nephology.eu/cirrocumulus International Cloud Atlas - Cirrocumulus]

{{cloud types}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Cirrocumulus Cloud}}
[[Category:Cloud types]]

[[be:Перыста-кучавыя воблакі]]
[[ca:Cirrocumulus]]
[[cs:Cirrocumulus]]
[[de:Cirrocumulus]]
[[et:Kiudrünkpilved]]
[[el:Θυσανοσωρείτες]]
[[es:Cirrocúmulo]]
[[eo:Cirokumuluso]]
[[eu:Zirrokumulu]]
[[fr:Cirrocumulus]]
[[gl:Cirrocumulus]]
[[ko:권적운]]
[[is:Maríutása]]
[[it:Cirrocumulo]]
[[lv:Spalvu gubumākoņi]]
[[lt:Plunksniniai kamuoliniai debesys]]
[[hu:Cirrocumulus]]
[[nl:Cirrocumulus]]
[[ja:巻積雲]]
[[no:Cirrocumulus]]
[[nn:Cirrocumulus]]
[[pl:Cirrocumulus]]
[[pt:Cirrocumulus]]
[[ru:Перисто-кучевые облака]]
[[sk:Cirokumulus]]
[[sl:Cirokumulus]]
[[sr:Цирокумулус]]
[[fi:Palleropilvi]]
[[sv:Cirrocumulus]]
[[uk:Перисто-купчасті хмари]]
[[vi:Mây ti tích]]
[[zh:卷积云]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
