<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="166842" ns="0" title="Safari (web browser)"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Infobox web browser
| name                   = Safari
| logo                   = [[File:Apple Safari.png|100px|Apple Safari icon]]
| screenshot             = [[File:Safari_in_Lion.png|300px|Safari Screenshot]]
| caption                = Safari 5.1 on [[Mac OS X Lion]]
| developer              = [[Apple Inc.]]
| released               = {{release date|2003|01|07}}
| frequently updated     = Yes
| programming language   = [[C++]],&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=The WebKit Open Source Project|url=http://webkit.org/coding/coding-style.html}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Objective-C]]
| operating system       = [[Mac OS X Snow Leopard]] and [[Mac OS X Lion|Lion]]&lt;br&gt;[[Windows XP]], [[Windows Vista|Vista]], and [[Windows 7|7]]&lt;br&gt;[[IOS (Apple)|iOS]]
| engine                 = [[WebKit]] (Based on [[KHTML]])
| status                 = Active
| genre                  = [[Web browser]]
| license                = [[Proprietary software|Proprietary]]; some components [[GNU Lesser General Public License|GNU LGPL]]
| website                = [http://www.apple.com/safari/ apple.com/safari]
}}

'''Safari''' is a [[web browser]] developed by [[Apple Inc.]] and included with the [[Mac OS X]] and [[IOS (Apple)|iOS]] operating systems. First released as a [[Beta (software)|public beta]] on January 7, 2003&lt;ref&gt;{{cite press release |url=http://www.apple.com/pr/library/2003/jan/07safari.html |title=Apple Unveils Safari |publisher=[[Apple Inc.]] |date=2007-01-07 |accessdate=2008-01-03}}&lt;/ref&gt; on the company's [[Mac OS X]] [[operating system]], it became Apple's default browser beginning with [[Mac OS X Panther|Mac OS X v10.3]] &quot;Panther&quot;. Safari is also the native browser for iOS. A version of Safari for the [[Microsoft Windows]] operating system, first released on June 11, 2007, supports [[Windows XP]], [[Windows Vista]], and [[Windows 7]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite press release |title=Apple Introduces Safari for Windows |publisher=[[Apple Inc.]] |date=2007-06-11 |url=http://www.apple.com/pr/library/2007/06/11safari.html |accessdate=2008-06-12}}&lt;/ref&gt; The latest stable release of the browser is 5.1.1, which is available as a free download for both [[Mac OS X]] and [[Microsoft Windows]]. According to [[Net Applications]], Safari accounted for 62.17 percent of mobile web browsing traffic and 5.43 percent of desktop traffic in October 2011, giving a combined market share of 8.72 percent.&lt;ref name=&quot;stats&quot;&gt;{{cite news |url=http://arstechnica.com/microsoft/news/2011/11/the-end-of-an-era-internet-explorer-drops-below-50-percent-of-web-usage.ars |title=The end of an era: Internet Explorer drops below 50% of Web usage |date=November 2, 2011 |accessdate=November 22, 2011 |publisher=[[Condé Nast Publications|Condé Nast]] |author=Peter Bright |work=[[Ars Technica]]}}&lt;/ref&gt; Safari is the fourth most popular web browser, behind [[Internet Explorer]] (49.59 percent), [[Mozilla Firefox]] (21.20), and [[Google Chrome]] (16.60).&lt;ref name=&quot;stats&quot; /&gt;

==History and development==
{{See also|Safari version history}}
Until 1997, [[Macintosh|Apple Macintosh]] computers were shipped with the [[Netscape Navigator]] and [[Cyberdog]] web browsers only. [[Internet Explorer for Mac]] was later included as the default web browser for [[Mac OS 8|Mac OS 8.1]] and onwards,&lt;ref name=&quot;apple-macos8.1&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://docs.info.apple.com/article.html?artnum=30345#English|title=Mac OS 8.1 Update Document and Software|date=2003-08-14|publisher=[[Apple Inc.]]|accessdate=2009-06-10}}&lt;/ref&gt; as part of a five year agreement between Apple and Microsoft. During that time, Microsoft released three major versions of Internet Explorer for Mac that were bundled with Mac OS 8 and [[Mac OS 9]], though Apple continued to include Netscape Navigator as an alternative. Microsoft ultimately released a Mac OS X edition of Internet Explorer for Mac, which was included as the default browser in all Mac OS X releases from Mac OS X DP4&lt;ref name=&quot;apple-macosxdp4&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.apple.com/pr/library/2000/may/15macosx.html|title=Apple Releases Mac OS X Developer Preview 4 with Final API Specs|date=2000-05-15|publisher=[[Apple Inc.]]|accessdate=2009-06-10}}&lt;/ref&gt; until [[Mac OS X v10.2]].&lt;ref name=&quot;adc-java131&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://developer.apple.com/releasenotes/Java/Java131MOSX10.2RN/applets/chapter_2_section_2.html|title=Java 1.3.1 for Mac OS X version 10.2 Release Notes|date=2002-07|work=developer.apple.com|publisher=[[Apple Inc.]]|accessdate=2009-06-10}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Safari 1===
On January 7, 2003, at [[Macworld Conference &amp; Expo|Macworld]] San Francisco, [[Steve Jobs]] announced that Apple had developed their own web browser, called Safari. It was based on Apple's internal [[Fork (software development)|fork]] of the [[KHTML]] [[Layout engine|rendering engine]], called [[WebKit]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |first=Andreas |last=Pour |title=Apple Announces New &quot;Safari&quot; Browser |url=http://dot.kde.org/1041971213/ |work=[[KDE Dot News]] |date=2003-01-07 |accessdate=2006-01-04}}&lt;/ref&gt; Apple released the first beta version for OS X that day. A number of official and unofficial beta versions followed, until [http://support.apple.com/kb/HT2964 version 1.0] was released on June 23, 2003. Initially only available as a separate download for Mac OS X v10.2, it was included with the Mac OS X v10.3 release on October 24, 2003 as the default browser, with Internet Explorer for Mac included only as an alternative browser. 1.0.3, released on August 13, 2004 was the last version to support Mac OS X v10.2, while 1.3.2, released on January 12, 2006 was the last version to support Mac OS X v10.3. However, 10.3 received security updates through 2007.

===Safari 2===
In April 2005, [[Dave Hyatt]], one of the Safari developers at Apple, documented his progress in fixing specific [[Software bug|bugs]] in Safari, thereby enabling it to pass the [[Acid2]] test developed by the [[Web Standards Project]]. On April 27, 2005, he announced that his development version of Safari now passed the test, making it the first web browser to do so.&lt;ref name=&quot;acid2&quot;&gt;{{cite web |first=Dave |last=Hyatt |title=Safari Passes the Acid2 Test |url=http://weblogs.mozillazine.org/hyatt/archives/2005_04.html |work=Surfin' Safari |publisher=MozillaZine |date=2005-04-27 |accessdate=2005-04-28}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Safari 2.0 was released on April 29, 2005 as the only web browser included with [[Mac OS X v10.4]]. This version was touted by Apple as possessing a 1.8x speed boost over version 1.2.4, but did not yet include the Acid2 bug fixes. The necessary changes were not initially available to [[End-user (computer science)|end-users]] unless they downloaded and compiled the WebKit [[source code]] themselves or ran one of the nightly automated builds available at [[Darwin (operating system)#OpenDarwin|OpenDarwin.org]].&lt;ref name=&quot;nightly builds&quot;&gt;{{cite web |first=Dave |last=Hyatt |title=Nightly Builds |url=http://webkit.org/blog/29/nightly-builds/ |work=Surfin' Safari |publisher=OpenDarwin.org |date=2005-10-12 |accessdate=2006-10-29}}&lt;/ref&gt; Apple eventually released version 2.0.2 of Safari, which included the modifications required to pass Acid2, on October 31, 2005.

In June 2005, after some criticism from KHTML developers over lack of access to change logs, Apple moved the development source code and bug tracking of [[WebKit#WebCore|WebCore]] and [[WebKit#JavaScriptCore|JavaScriptCore]] to OpenDarwin.org. WebKit itself was also released as open source. The source code for non-renderer aspects of the browser, such as its [[Graphical user interface|GUI]] elements, remains proprietary.

The final stable version of Safari 2, Safari 2.0.4, was released on January 10, 2006 for Mac OS X. It was only available as part of Mac OS X Update 10.4.4. This version addresses layout and CPU usage issues, among others.&lt;ref&gt;[http://support.apple.com/kb/HT2343 About the Mac OS X 10.4.4 Update (Delta)]&lt;/ref&gt; Safari 2.0.4 was the last version to be released exclusively on Mac OS X.

===Safari 3===
On January 9, 2007, at Macworld SF, Jobs announced Apple's [[iPhone]], which would use a mobile version of the Safari browser.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.apple.com/pr/library/2007/01/09iphone.html Apple Reinvents the Phone with iPhone]&lt;/ref&gt;

On June 11, 2007, at the [[Apple Worldwide Developers Conference]], Jobs announced Safari 3 for [[Mac OS X v10.5]], Windows XP, and Windows Vista. During the announcement, he ran a benchmark based on the [[iBench]] browser test suite comparing the most popular Windows browsers,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |first=Mark |last=Wilton-Jones |title=Is Safari faster? |url=http://www.howtocreate.co.uk/safaribenchmarks.html |accessdate=2008-06-12}}&lt;/ref&gt; hence claiming that Safari was the fastest browser. Later third-party tests of [[Hypertext Transfer Protocol|HTTP]] load times would support Apple's claim that Safari 3 was indeed the fastest browser on the Windows platform in terms of initial data loading over the Internet, though it was found to be only negligibly faster than [[Internet Explorer 7]] and [[Mozilla Firefox]] when loading static content from local cache.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |first=Michae |last=Czeiszperger |title=Safari 3 Windows Performance Analysis |url=http://www.webperformanceinc.com/library/reports/Safari%20Benchmarks/index.html |publisher=Web Performance |date=2007-10-20 |accessdate=2007-07-24}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The initial Safari 3 beta version for Windows, released on the same day as its announcement at WWDC 2007, had several known bugs&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |first=David |last=Maynor |title=Niiiice... |url=http://erratasec.blogspot.com/2007/06/niiiice.html |publisher=Errata Security |date=2007-06-11 |accessdate=2008-06-12}}&lt;/ref&gt; and a [[zero day attack|zero day]] exploit that allowed remote execution.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |first=Thor |last=Larholm |title=Safari for Windows, 0day exploit in 2 hours |url=http://larholm.com/2007/06/12/safari-for-windows-0day-exploit-in-2-hours/ |date=2007-06-12 |accessdate=2008-06-12}}&lt;/ref&gt; The addressed bugs were then corrected by Apple three days later on June 14, 2007, in version 3.0.1 for Windows. On June 22, 2007, Apple released Safari 3.0.2 to address some bugs, performance issues and other security issues. Safari 3.0.2 for Windows handles some fonts that are missing in the browser but already installed on Windows computers, such as Tahoma, Trebuchet MS, and others.

The [[iPhone]] was formally released on June 29, 2007.  It includes a version of Safari based on the same WebKit rendering engine as the desktop version, but with a modified feature set better suited for a mobile device.  The version number of Safari as reported in its [[User agent|user agent string]] is 3.0,&lt;ref&gt;[http://the.taoofmac.com/space/com/Apple/iPhone/Safari Mobile Safari]&lt;/ref&gt; in line with the contemporary desktop versions of Safari.

The first stable, non-beta release of Safari for Windows, Safari 3.1, was offered as a free download on March 18, 2008. In June 2008, Apple released version 3.1.2,&lt;ref&gt;[http://support.apple.com/kb/HT2092 About the security content of Safari 3.1.2 for Windows]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Keizer, Gregg. [http://www.computerworld.com/action/article.do?command=viewArticleBasic&amp;taxonomyName=macintosh_os&amp;articleId=9101239&amp;taxonomyId=123 Apple does about-face, fixes Safari's 'carpet bomb' bug], ''[[ComputerWorld]]'' (June 19, 2008).&lt;/ref&gt; addressing a security vulnerability in the Windows version where visiting a malicious web site could force a download of executable files and execute them on the user's desktop.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |title=Microsoft Security Advisory (953818) |url=http://www.microsoft.com/technet/security/advisory/953818.mspx |publisher=[[Microsoft]]}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Safari 3.2, released on November 13, 2008, introduced anti-[[phishing]] features and [[Extended Validation Certificate]] support. The final version of Safari 3 is 3.2.3, released on May 12, 2009.

===Safari 4===
On June 2, 2008, the WebKit development team announced SquirrelFish,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |first=Geoffrey |last=Garen |title=Announcing SquirrelFish |url=http://webkit.org/blog/189/announcing-squirrelfish/ |date=2008-06-02 |accessdate=2008-06-11}}&lt;/ref&gt; a new [[JavaScript engine]] that vastly improves Safari's speed at interpreting scripts.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |first=Vygantas |last=Lipskas |title=Apple Safari 4 |url=http://www.favbrowser.com/apple-safari-4/ |date=2008-06-11 |accessdate=2008-06-11}}&lt;/ref&gt; The engine is one of the new features in Safari 4, released to developers on June 11, 2008. The new JavaScript engine quickly evolved into SquirrelFish Extreme, featuring even further improved performance over SquirrelFish,&lt;ref&gt;[http://webkit.org/blog/214/introducing-squirrelfish-extreme/ Introducing SquirrelFish Extreme]&lt;/ref&gt; and was eventually marketed as Nitro. A public beta of Safari 4 was released on February 24, 2009, with new features such as the Top Sites tool (similar to [[Opera (web browser)|Opera]]'s [[Features of the Opera web browser#Speed Dial|Speed Dial]] feature), which displays the user's most visited sites on a 3D wall.&lt;ref&gt;[http://arstechnica.com/apple/news/2009/02/hands-on-safari-4-beta-fast-mixes-polish-rough-ui-edges.ars Hands on: Safari 4 beta fast, mixes polish, rough UI edges]&lt;/ref&gt; [[Cover Flow]], a feature of Mac OS X and [[iTunes]], was also implemented in Safari. In the public beta versions, [[Tab (GUI)|tabs]] were placed in the title bar of the window, similar to [[Google Chrome]]. The tab bar was moved back to its original location, below the [[Uniform Resource Locator|URL]] bar, in the final release.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://theappleblog.com/2009/06/08/apple-releases-safari-4/|title=Apple Releases Safari 4|last=Dempsey|first=James|date=2009-06-09|work=TheAppleBlog|publisher=The GigaOM Network|accessdate=2009-06-09}}&lt;/ref&gt; The Windows version adopted a native Windows [[Theme (computing)|theme]], rather than the previously employed Mac OS X-style interface. Also Apple removed the blue progress bar located in the address bar (later reinstated in Safari 5). Safari 4.0.1 was released for Mac on June 17 and fixed problems with Faces in [[iPhoto]] '09. Safari 4 in [[Mac OS X v10.6]] &quot;Snow Leopard&quot; has 64-bit support, which can make [[JavaScript]] loading up to 50% faster. It also has built-in crash resistance unique to Snow Leopard; crash resistance will keep the browser intact if a plug-in like [[Flash player]] crashes, such that the other tabs or windows will be unaffected.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.apple.com/macosx/what-is-macosx/safari.html Apple - Mac OS X - What is Mac OS X - Safari]&lt;/ref&gt; Safari 4.0.4, released on November 11, 2009 for both OS X and Windows, further improves JavaScript performance.&lt;ref&gt;[http://support.apple.com/kb/DL877 Safari 4.0.4]&lt;/ref&gt;

Safari was one of the twelve [[BrowserChoice.eu|browsers offered]] to [[EU]] users of [[Microsoft Windows]] in 2010. It is also one of the five browsers displayed on the first page of browser choices along with Chrome, Firefox, Internet Explorer and Opera.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/technology/8537763.stm|title=Microsoft offers browser choices to Europeans|publisher=[[BBC]]|date= March 1, 2010|accessdate=March 1, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://arstechnica.com/microsoft/news/2010/02/microsofts-eu-browser-ballot-approved-arrives-march-1.ars|title=Microsoft's EU browser ballot approved, arrives March 1|work=[[Ars Technica]]|publisher=[[Condé Nast Publications|Condé Nast]]|author=Peter Bright|date=February 19, 2010|accessdate=March 1, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Safari 5===
[[image:Safari Reader on Mac OS X 10.6.png|right|thumb|Safari displaying its Reader view of a Wikipedia article.]]
Apple released Safari 5 on June 7, 2010, featuring the new Safari Reader for reading articles on the web without distraction (based on Arc90's Readability tool&lt;ref name=&quot;Safari 5: Another Step Towards Better Reading On The Web&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url=http://blog.arc90.com/2010/06/07/safari-5-another-step-towards-better-reading-on-the-web |title=Safari 5: Another Step Towards Better Reading On The Web |author=Rich Ziade  |date=June 7, 2010  |work= |publisher= |accessdate=2010-06-08}}&lt;/ref&gt;), and a 30 percent Javascript performance increase over Safari 4. Safari 5 includes improved developer tools and supports more than a dozen new HTML5 technologies, focused on interoperability. With Safari 5, developers can now create secure Safari Extensions to customize and enhance the browsing experience.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.prnewswire.com/news-releases/apple-releases-safari-5-95812499.html |title=Apple Releases Safari 5 |author=Apple |year=2010  |work= |publisher= |accessdate=2010-12-09}}&lt;/ref&gt;  Apple also re-added the progress bar behind the address bar in this release. Safari 5.0.1 enabled the Extensions PrefPane by default; previously, users had to enable it via the Debug menu.

Apple also released Safari 4.1 concurrently with Safari 5, exclusively for [[Mac OS X Tiger]]. The update included the majority of the features and security enhancements found in Safari 5. It did not, however, include Safari Reader or Safari Extensions.
Together with Mac OS X 10.7 Lion, Apple released Safari 5.1 for both Windows and Mac on July 20, 2011, with the new function 'Reading List' and a faster browsing experience. Apple simultaneously released Safari 5.06 for Mac OS X 10.5 Leopard, excluding Leopard users from the new functions in Safari 5.1.

==WebKit2==
On April 9, 2010, Apple announced WebKit2.&lt;ref name=webkit2_announcement/&gt; This was integrated into Safari as of version 5.1.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://trac.webkit.org/browser/releases/Apple/Safari%205.1/WebKit2?rev=91373| title=Source code repository for public parts of Safari 5.1|publisher=The WebKit Open Source Project| accessdate=July 20,2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&quot;WebKit2 is designed from the ground up to support a split process model, where the Web content (JavaScript, HTML, layout, etc) lives in a separate process,&quot;  wrote Apple developer Anders Carlsson to WebKit's public mailing list on April 8, 2010. &quot;This model is similar to what Google Chrome offers, with the major difference being that we have built the process split model directly into the framework, allowing other clients to use it.&quot;&lt;ref name=webkit2_announcement&gt;{{cite web| url=https://lists.webkit.org/pipermail/webkit-dev/2010-April/012235.html| title=Announcing WebKit2| publisher=Anders Carlsson| accessdate=April 10, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The &quot;process split&quot; model to which Carlsson refers is the architecture that enables processes spawned by the browser, including add-ons and Web apps, to be run as separate processes in the operating system while still being protected by the browser's [[sandbox (computer security)|sandbox]]. Google's Chromium team developed the first such model in working form for its [[Google Chrome|Chrome browser]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web| url=http://blog.chromium.org/2008/09/multi-process-architecture.html| title=Multi-process Architecture| publisher=Charlie Reis| date=September 11, 2008| accessdate=April 10, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|author=Chromium Developer Documentation| title=Process Models|url=http://dev.chromium.org/developers/design-documents/process-models| accessdate=April 10, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Features==
Safari offers numerous features, including:
{{div col}}
*Ability to save webpage clips for viewing on the [[Dashboard (Mac OS)|Apple Dashboard]] (Mac OS X only)
*A resizable web-search box in the toolbar which allows choice among [[Google]], [[Yahoo!]] or [[Bing]] only
*Automatic filling in of [[Form (web)|web forms]] (&quot;[[autofill]]&quot;)
*Bookmark integration with [[Address Book (application)|Address Book]]
*Bookmark management
*Built-in password management via [[Keychain (Mac OS)|Keychain]]  (Mac OS X only)
*[[Web browsing history|History]] and bookmark search
*Expandable text boxes
*[[International Color Consortium|ICC]] color profile support
*Inline [[Portable Document Format|PDF]] viewing (Mac OS X only)
*[[iPhoto]] integration (Mac OS X only)
*[[Mail (application)|Mail]] integration (Mac OS X only)
*[[Pop-up ad]] blocking
*[[Privacy mode|Private browsing]]
*[[Quartz (graphics layer)|Quartz]]-style [[Font rasterization|font smoothing]]
*Reader mode, for viewing an uncluttered version of Web articles
*[[Spell checker|Spell checking]]
*Subscribing to and reading [[web feed]]s
*Support for [[Cascading Style Sheets|CSS]] [[Cascading Style Sheets#CSS 3|3]] [[Web typography|web fonts]]
*Support for CSS animation
*Support for [[HTML5]]
*Support for [[Transport Layer Security]] protocol (version unknown)
*Tabbed browsing
*[[Incremental find|Text search]]
*Web Inspector, a [[DOM Inspector]]-like utility that lets users and developers browse the [[Document Object Model]] of a web page&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|first=Timothy |last=Hatcher |title=Introducing the Web Inspector|url=http://webkit.org/blog/41/introducing-the-web-inspector/|accessdate=2007-06-20}}&lt;/ref&gt;
{{div col end}}

[[image:Safari Web Inspector.png|right|thumb|Safari's Web Inspector, showing the [[Document Object Model|DOM]] tree for this page.]]
On Mac OS X, Safari is a [[Cocoa (API)|Cocoa]] application.&lt;ref&gt;Apple Developer Connection: &quot;[http://developer.apple.com/documentation/Cocoa/Conceptual/CocoaFundamentals/WhatIsCocoa/WhatIsCocoa.html What Is Cocoa?]&quot; (&quot;Most of the applications you see on Mac OS X and iPhone OS, including Mail and Safari, are Cocoa applications.&quot;). Accessed 2009-08-19.&lt;/ref&gt; It uses Apple's WebKit for rendering web pages and running JavaScript. WebKit consists of WebCore (based on [[Konqueror]]'s KHTML engine) and JavaScriptCore (originally based on [[KDE's JavaScript engine]], named KJS). Like KHTML and KJS, WebCore and JavaScriptCore are [[free software]] and are released under the terms of the [[GNU Lesser General Public License]]. Some Apple improvements to the KHTML code are merged back into the Konqueror project. Apple also releases additional code under an [[open source]] 2-clause [[BSD license|BSD-like license]].

It includes a built-in [[web feed]] [[feed aggregator|aggregator]] that supports the [[RSS]] and [[Atom (standard)|Atom]] standards. Other features include Private Browsing (a mode in which no record of information about the user's web activity is retained by the browser),&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://lifehacker.com/#!102146/safaris-private-porn-browsing-mode|title=Safari's private (porn) browsing mode|date=4 May 2005|publisher=[[lifehacker]]|accessdate=2008-10-14}}&lt;/ref&gt; the ability to archive web content in the proprietary [[Webarchive]] format, the ability to e-mail complete web pages directly from a browser menu, and the ability to search bookmarks.

=== New features in Safari 4 ===
Beginning with Safari 4, the address bar has been completely revamped:
[[File:Safari 4 on Windows XP.png|thumb|225px|Safari 4 on Windows XP]]
*The blue inline progress bar is replaced with a spinning bezel and a loading indicator attached to it.
*The button to add a bookmark is now attached to the address bar by default.
*The reload/stop button is now superimposed on the right end of the address bar.
These modifications make Safari on Mac OS X and Windows look more similar to Safari on iPhone than previous versions.

Safari 4 also includes the following new features:
*Completely passes the [[Acid3]] standards test
*Cover Flow browsing for History and Bookmarks
*Improved developer tools, including Web Inspector, CSS element viewing, JavaScript debugger and profiler, offline table and database management with [[SQL]] support, and resource graphs
*Nitro JavaScript engine that executes JavaScript up to eight times faster than [[Internet Explorer 8]] and more than four times faster than Firefox 3&lt;ref name=&quot;apple.com&quot;&gt;[http://www.apple.com/safari/whats-new.html What's new in Safari 4.]&lt;/ref&gt;
*Native Windows look on Windows ([[Windows Aero|Aero]], [[Luna (theme)|Luna]], Classic, etc., depending on OS and settings) with standard Windows font rendering and optional Apple font rendering
*Support for CSS image retouching effects
*Support for CSS Canvas
*Speculative loading, where Safari loads the documents, scripts, and style information that are required to view a web page ahead of time
*Support for [[HTML5]]
*Top Sites, which displays up to 24 thumbnails of a user's most frequently-visited pages on startup

=== New features in Safari 5===
{{expand list|date=February 2011}}
Safari 5 includes the following new features:
*[[Full-text search]] through the browser history&lt;ref name='nextweb-safari5'&gt;{{cite web|url=http://thenextweb.com/apple/2010/06/08/breaking-apple-releases-safari-5/|accessdate=28 October 2010|date=8 June 2010|title=Apple Releases Safari 5… with Extensions!|work=The Next Web}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*Safari Reader, which removes formatting and ads from webpages.&lt;ref name=&quot;Whatsnew-Safari5&quot;&gt;[http://www.apple.com/safari/whats-new.html]&lt;/ref&gt;
*Smarter address field, where the address bar autocomplete will match against titles of web page in history or bookmarks.
*Extensions, which are add-ons that customize the web browsing experience.&lt;ref name=&quot;safari-extensions&quot;&gt;[http://extensions.apple.com/]&lt;/ref&gt;
*Improved support for HTML5, including full screen video, closed caption, geolocation, EventSource, and WebSocket.
*Improved Web Inspector.
*Faster Nitro Javascript Engine.
*DNS prefetching, where Safari finds links and looks up addresses on the web page ahead of time.
*[[Bing]] search.
*Improved graphics hardware acceleration on Windows.

Additionally, the blue inline progress bar has returned to the address bar, in addition to the spinning bezel and loading indicator introduced in Safari 4. Top Sites view now has a button to switch to Full History Search. Other features include Extension builder for developers of Safari Extensions, which are built using web standards such as HTML5, CSS3, and Javascript.

===iOS-specific features===

[[File:Wikipedia on iPod Touch's Safari.PNG|thumb|320px|Safari 4.2 on the iPhone and iPod Touch in the Landscape view. The icon at the bottom center changed because of [[AirPrint]].]]
[[File:IPadSafari.png|320px|thumb|right|Safari 5.1 on the iPad 2 in Landscape view.]]

iOS-specific features for Safari enable:
*Bookmarking links to particular pages as &quot;Web Clip&quot; icons on the Home screen.{{Citation needed|date=November 2010}}
*[[Multiple document interface|MDI]]-style browsing (with up to 8 pages open concurrently, limited by cache storage).{{Citation needed|date=November 2010}}
*Opening specially-designed pages in full-screen mode.{{Citation needed|date=November 2010}}
*Pressing on an image for 3 seconds to save it to the photo album.{{Citation needed|date=November 2010}}
*Support for HTML5 new input types.{{Citation needed|date=November 2010}}

====New in iOS 4.2====
*Find feature built into search box.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://arstechnica.com/apple/news/2010/11/apple-releases-ios-42-with-free-find-my-phone-for-some.ars|title=Apple releases iOS 4.2 with free Find My Phone for some|date=22 November 2010|accessdate=29 November 2010|publisher=Condé Nast|work=Ars Technica}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*Ability to print the current webpage using [[AirPrint]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.apple.com/ipad/features/airprint.html Apple AirPrint Product Page]&lt;/ref&gt;

====New in iOS 4.3====

*Integration of the Nitro JavaScript engine for faster page loads (only available to iPhone 3GS, 3rd Generation iPod Touch, iPad and above) This feature was discovered to only work in the MobileSafari app, and not in the integrated viewer that many apps use.

====New in iOS 5====

*True tabbed browsing, similar to the desktop experience, only for the iPad and iPad 2.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.apple.com/ios/ios5/features.html#safari]&lt;/ref&gt;
*[[Reading List (Apple)|Reading List]], a bookmarking feature that allows tagging of certain sites for reading later, which syncs across all Safari browsers (mobile and desktop) via Apple's [[iCloud]] service.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.apple.com/ios/ios5/features.html#safari]&lt;/ref&gt;
*[[Reader (Apple)|Reader]], a reading feature that can format text and images from a web page into a more readable format, similar to a PDF document, while stripping out web advertising and superfluous information.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.apple.com/ios/ios5/features.html#safari]&lt;/ref&gt;

==System requirements==
Safari 5.1 requires either a Mac running Mac OS X v10.6.8, or a [[IBM PC compatible|PC]] running Windows XP SP2, Windows Vista, or Windows 7. Official minimum hardware requirements for Windows state a 500&amp;nbsp;MHz [[Pentium compatible processor|Pentium]] processor with 256&amp;nbsp;MB of RAM for Windows. Cover Flow and Top Sites require a graphics card that is [[Quartz_Compositor#Quartz Extreme|Quartz Extreme]]-compatible with 16&amp;nbsp;MB or more video memory for Mac or [[DirectX]] 9-compatible with 64&amp;nbsp;MB or more video memory for Windows.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.apple.com/safari/download/ Download Safari 5.1]&lt;/ref&gt;

Safari 5.0.6 requires a Mac running on Mac OS X 10.5.8.&lt;ref&gt;[http://support.apple.com/kb/DL1422 Safari 5.0.6 for Leopard]&lt;/ref&gt;

===64-bit builds===
The version of Safari included in Mac OS X v10.6 is now [[Compiler|compiled]] for [[64-bit]] architecture. Apple claims that running Safari in 64-bit mode will increase rendering speeds by up to 50%.

==Criticism==
[[File:Wikimedia browser share pie chart.png|thumb|right|[[Usage_share_of_web_browsers#Wikimedia_.28April_2009_to_present.29|Web browser usage]] on [[Wikimedia]] servers]]
===Distribution through Apple Software Update===
An earlier version of [[Apple Software Update]] (bundled with Safari, [[QuickTime]], and iTunes for Microsoft Windows) selected Safari for installation from a list of Apple programs to download by default, even when a pre-existing installation of Safari was not detected on a user's machine. [[John Lilly]], CEO of [[Mozilla]], stated that Apple's use of its updating software to promote its other products was &quot;a bad practice and should stop.&quot; He argued that the practice &quot;borders on malware distribution practices&quot; and &quot;undermines the trust that we're all trying to build with users.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;webware lilly&quot;&gt;{{cite web |first=Martin |last=LaMonica |title=Mozilla CEO says Apple's Safari auto-update 'wrong' |url=http://news.cnet.com/8301-17939_109-9901006-2.html |publisher=[[CNET Networks]] |date=2008-03-21 |accessdate=2008-06-12}}&lt;/ref&gt; Apple spokesman Bill Evans responded to Lilly's statement, saying that Apple was only &quot;using Software Update to make it easy and convenient for both Mac and Windows users to get the latest Safari update from Apple.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.informationweek.com/news/internet/webdev/showArticle.jhtml?articleID=206905039 Apple Distributes Safari Via Software Update]&lt;/ref&gt; Apple also released a new version of Apple Software Update that puts new software in its own section, though still selected for installation by default.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |first=Gregg |last=Keizer |title=Apple makes minor concession on pushing Safari to Windows users |url=http://www.computerworld.com/action/article.do?command=viewArticleBasic&amp;articleId=9078738 |work=[[Computerworld]] |publisher=[[IDG]] |date=2008-04-17 |accessdate=2008-04-19}}&lt;/ref&gt; In a newer update, Apple Software Update no longer selected new installation items in the new software section by default (as of late 2008).{{Citation needed|date=January 2010}}

On September 22, 2009, Apple once again checked &quot;Install Safari 4&quot; as a default setting with their update to iTunes v9.0.1.{{Citation needed|date=December 2009}}

===Browser exploits===
In the [[Pwn2Own|PWN2OWN]] contest at the 2008 CanSecWest security conference in Vancouver, British Columbia, a successful exploit of Safari caused Mac OS X to be the first OS to fall in a hacking competition. Participants competed to find a way to read the contents of a file located on the user's desktop, in one of three operating systems: Mac OS X Leopard, Windows Vista SP1, and [[Ubuntu (operating system)|Ubuntu]] 7.10. On the second day of the contest, when users were allowed to physically interact with the computers (the prior day permitted only network attacks), [[Charlie Miller (security researcher)|Charlie Miller]] compromised Mac OS X through an unpatched vulnerability of the [[Perl Compatible Regular Expressions|PCRE library]] used by Safari.&lt;ref name=&quot;miller&quot;&gt;{{cite news |first=Robert |last=McMillan |title=Mac hack contest bug had been public for a year |url=http://www.networkworld.com/news/2008/042208-mac-hack-contest-bug-had.html |work=[[Network World]] |publisher=[[IDG]] |date=2008-04-22 |accessdate=2008-06-12}}&lt;/ref&gt; Miller had been aware of the flaw prior to the beginning of the conference and worked to exploit it unannounced, as is the common approach in these contests.&lt;ref name=&quot;miller&quot; /&gt; The exploited vulnerability was patched in Safari 3.1.1, among other flaws.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.computerworld.com/s/article/9078399/Update_Apple_patches_Safari_s_10_000_bug_fixes_other_flaws Update: Apple patches Safari's $10,000 bug, fixes other flaws]&lt;/ref&gt;

In the 2009 PWN2OWN contest, Charlie Miller performed another successful exploit of Safari to hack into a Mac. Miller again acknowledged that he had advance knowledge of the security flaw prior to the competition, and had done considerable research and preparation work on the exploit.&lt;ref&gt;[http://arstechnica.com/apple/news/2009/03/pwn2own-winner-says-macs-are-more-safe-though-less-secure.ars Pwn2Own winner says Macs are more safe, though less secure]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://news.softpedia.com/news/Charlie-Miller-Wins-Pwn2Own-Again-Thanks-to-Safari-Flaw-107269.shtml |title=Charlie Miller Wins Pwn2Own Again Thanks to Safari Flaw |date=2009-03-19}}&lt;/ref&gt; Apple released a patch for this exploit and others on May 12, 2009 with Safari 3.2.3.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://support.apple.com/kb/HT3550|title=About the security content of Safari 3.2.3|date=2009-05-12|publisher=[[Apple Inc.]]|accessdate=2009-12-22}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.mxlogix.net/securitynews/web-security/apple-issues-patches-for-mac-os-x265.cfm Apple issues patches for Mac OS X]&lt;/ref&gt;

===Software license agreement===
The original [[software license agreement]] for Safari on Windows was unusually restrictive for several months,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |first=Cade |last=Metz |title=Apple forbids Windows users from installing Safari for Windows |url=http://www.theregister.co.uk/2008/03/26/apple_safari_eula_paradox/ |work=[[The Register]] |publisher= |date=2008-03-26 |accessdate=2008-06-13}}&lt;/ref&gt; reading in part:
&lt;blockquote&gt;This License allows you to install and use one copy of the Apple Software on a single Apple-labeled computer at a time.&lt;ref name=&quot;cnet&quot;&gt;{{cite news |first=Martin |last=LaMonica |title=Safari for Windows: Only for 'Apple-labeled' computers? |url=http://news.cnet.com/8301-10784_3-9904445-7.html |work=CNET News |publisher=[[CNET Networks]] |date=2008-03-27 |accessdate=2008-06-13}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
As most personal computers running Windows are not Apple-labeled computers, it was impossible for most Windows users to use the software and abide by the license agreement, with the exception of Intel-based Mac computers running Windows. Within hours of the story breaking about the long-unnoticed anomaly, Apple changed the agreement as posted on their website to read:&lt;ref name=&quot;cnet&quot; /&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;This license allows you to install and use one copy of the Apple Software on each computer owned or controlled by you.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |title=Software License Agreement for Safari for Windows |url=http://www.apple.com/safari/download/terms_win.html |format=PDF |date=2008-03-27 |accessdate=2008-06-13}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
However, the Safari installer was not immediately updated and still contained the old license.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |title=Apple grants Windows PCs the right to run Safari for Windows |url=http://www.theregister.co.uk/2008/03/27/apple_updates_safari_eula/ |publisher=[[The Register]] |date=2008-03-27 |accessdate=2008-06-13}}&lt;/ref&gt; Later installers include corrected copies of the license.

===Malware Blocking===

In recent analysis, the stable version of Safari blocked 13% of malicious URLS.  In contrast, Internet Explorer 9 blocked 92% of malware with its URL-based filtering, and a full 100% with Application-based filtering enabled. Internet Explorer 8, in second place, blocked 90% of malware..&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://arstechnica.com/microsoft/news/2011/07/internet-explorer-9-utterly-dominates-malware-blocking-stats.ars|title=Internet Explorer 9 utterly dominates malware-blocking stats |date=2011-07-16 |publisher=[[ArsTechnica]] |first=Peter|last=Bright|accessdate=2011-07-16}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.nsslabs.com/research/endpoint-security/browser-security/web-browser-group-test-socially-engineered-malware-europe-q2-2011.html |title=Web Browser Group Test Socially-Engineered Malware |date=2011-07-16 |publisher=[[NSS Labs]]}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==See also==
* [[Acid3#Browsers that pass|Browsers that pass Acid3]]
* [[Comparison of feed aggregators]]
* [[Comparison of web browsers]]
* [[Cyberdog]], Apple's [[OpenDoc]]-based Internet suite
* [[iOS (Apple)|iOS]], Apple's mobile operating system that includes a version of Safari built-in
* [[List of feed aggregators]]
* [[Month of Bugs]]
* [[Safari version history]]
* [[WebKit]], underlying engine of Safari and other web browsers

==References==
{{Reflist|colwidth=30em}}

==External links==
*[http://www.apple.com/safari/ Safari website]
*[http://michelf.com/projects/multi-safari/ Multi-Safari], downloadable older versions of Safari for web testing
*[http://extensions.apple.com/ Safari Extensions]

{{Apple software on Windows}}
{{Web browsers}}
{{Aggregators}}
{{Mac OS X}}
{{iPhone}}
{{Apple software}}
{{Apple}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Safari (Web Browser)}}
[[Category:2003 software]]
[[Category:Atom (standard)]]
[[Category:Mac OS X]]
[[Category:Apple Inc. software]]
[[Category:IOS software]]
[[Category:Mac OS X web browsers]]
[[Category:Windows web browsers]]
[[Category:Mobile browsers]]
[[Category:Software based on Webkit]]
[[Category:News aggregators]]

[[ar:سفاري (متصفح ويب)]]
[[az:Safari]]
[[bg:Сафари (браузър)]]
[[ca:Safari (navegador web)]]
[[cs:Safari (webový prohlížeč)]]
[[da:Safari (browser)]]
[[de:Safari (Browser)]]
[[et:Safari (brauser)]]
[[el:Safari]]
[[es:Safari (navegador)]]
[[eo:Safari (retumilo)]]
[[eu:Safari (nabigatzailea)]]
[[fa:سافاری]]
[[fr:Safari (logiciel)]]
[[gl:Safari (navegador)]]
[[ko:사파리 (웹 브라우저)]]
[[hi:सफ़ारी वेब ब्राउज़र]]
[[hr:Safari]]
[[id:Safari (peramban web)]]
[[ia:Safari (navigator del web)]]
[[it:Safari (browser)]]
[[he:ספארי (דפדפן)]]
[[ka:Safari]]
[[la:Safari (navigatrum)]]
[[lv:Safari (pārlūkprogramma)]]
[[lt:Safari]]
[[hu:Safari]]
[[mk:Apple Safari]]
[[ml:സഫാരി (വെബ് ബ്രൗസര്‍)]]
[[mr:अ‍ॅपल सफारी#मोबाइल]]
[[ms:Safari (pelayar web)]]
[[nl:Safari (webbrowser)]]
[[ja:Safari]]
[[no:Safari (nettleser)]]
[[uz:Safari]]
[[pl:Safari (program)]]
[[pt:Safari]]
[[ro:Safari (browser)]]
[[ru:Safari]]
[[simple:Safari (web browser)]]
[[sk:Safari (webový prehliadač)]]
[[sl:Safari (brskalnik)]]
[[sr:Safari (internet pregledač)]]
[[fi:Safari (selain)]]
[[sv:Safari (webbläsare)]]
[[te:సఫారి (వెబ్ బ్రౌజర్)]]
[[th:ซาฟารี (เว็บเบราว์เซอร์)]]
[[tr:Safari (web tarayıcısı)]]
[[uk:Safari]]
[[vi:Safari]]
[[yi:סאפארי]]
[[zh-yue:Safari]]
[[zh:Safari]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
