<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="16823208" ns="0" title="Iraqi parliamentary election, 2010"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Infobox election
|election_name      = Iraqi parliamentary election, 2010
|country            = Iraq
|type               = parliamentary
|ongoing            = no
|previous_election  = Iraqi parliamentary election, December 2005
|previous_year      = 2005 (Dec)
|next_election      = Iraqi parliamentary election, 2014
|next_year          = 2014
|seats_for_election = All 325 seats to the [[Council of Representatives of Iraq|Council of Representatives]] &lt;br&gt; 163 seats were needed for a majority
|election_date      = 7 March 2010
|image1             = [[File:Allawi1.jpg|85px]]
|leader1            = [[Ayad Allawi]]
|party1             = Iraqi National Movement
|seats1             = 91
|seat_change1 = {{increase}}54*
|popular_vote1      = 2,849,612
|percentage1        = 24.7%
|last_election1     = 37
|image2             = [[File:Nouri al-Maliki with Bush, June 2006, cropped.jpg|110px]]
|leader2            = [[Nouri al-Maliki]]
|party2             = State of Law Coalition
|seats2             = 89
|seat_change2 = {{increase}}89*
|popular_vote2      = 2,792,083
|percentage2        = 24.2%
|last_election2     = -
|image3             = [[File:Ibrahim al-Jaafari2.jpg|118px]]
|leader3            = [[Ibrahim al-Jaafari]]
|party3             = National Iraqi Alliance
|seats3             = 70
|seat_change3 = {{decrease}}58*
|popular_vote3      = 2,092,066
|percentage3        = 18.2%
|last_election3     = 128
| map_image       = 2010_Iraqi_election_map.png
| map_size        = 325px
| map_caption     = Colours denote which party won the most votes in every governorate
|title              = [[Prime Minister of Iraq|Prime Minister]]
|before_election    = Nouri al-Maliki
|before_party       = State of Law Coalition
|after_election     = Nouri al-Maliki
|after_party        = State of Law Coalition
}}

A '''parliamentary election''' was held in [[Iraq]] on 7 March 2010. The election decided the 325 members of the [[Council of Representatives of Iraq]] who will elect the Iraqi [[Prime Minister of Iraq|Prime Minister]] and [[President of Iraq|President]]. The election resulted in a partial victory for the [[Iraqi National Movement]], led by former Interim Prime Minister [[Ayad Allawi]], which won a total of 91 seats, making it the largest alliance in the Council.  The [[State of Law Coalition]], led by incumbent Prime Minister [[Nouri Al-Maliki]], was the second largest grouping with 89 seats.

The election has been controversial.&lt;ref&gt;{{citation | title= Iraq Recount Mired in a New Dispute | work= [[New York Times]] | date= 3 May 2010 | url= http://www.nytimes.com/2010/05/04/world/middleeast/04iraq.html }}&lt;/ref&gt; Prior to the election, the Supreme Court in Iraq ruled that the existing electoral law/rule was unconstitutional,&lt;ref&gt;[http://gulfanalysis.wordpress.com/2009/11/24/the-2005-election-law-seen-as-unconstitutional-seat-distribution-key-in-doubt/ The 2005 Election Law Seen as Unconstitutional; Seat Distribution Key in Doubt]&lt;/ref&gt; and a new elections law made changes in the electoral system.&lt;ref&gt;[http://online.wsj.com/article/SB125770031185936775.html Iraq Passes Key Election Law and Prepares for January Vote ]&lt;/ref&gt; On 15 January 2010, the [[Independent High Electoral Commission]] (IHEC) banned 499 candidates from the election due to alleged links with the Ba'ath Party.&lt;ref name=&quot;baathists&quot;&gt;{{citation | title= Iraqi election commission bans 500 candidates | publisher= BBC News | date= 15 January 2010| url= http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/8461275.stm }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;us-surrender&quot;&gt;{{citation | title= US to surrender Iraq to extremists | publisher= [[Press TV]] | date= 24 January 2010 | url= http://www.presstv.com/detail.aspx?id=116947&amp;sectionid=351020201 }}&lt;/ref&gt; Before the start of the campaign on 12 February 2010, IHEC confirmed that the appeals by banned candidates had been rejected and thus all 456 banned candidates would not be allowed to run for the election.&lt;ref name=&quot;ihec-no-go&quot;&gt;{{citation | title= Iraq election officials confirm Sunni candidate ban | publisher= Reuters | date= 13 February 2010 | url= http://in.reuters.com/article/worldNews/idINIndia-46143820100213 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

There were numerous allegations of fraud,&lt;ref name=&quot;fraud_claims&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;fraud_delays&quot;/&gt; and a recount of the votes in Baghdad was ordered on 19 April 2010.&lt;ref name=&quot;baghdad-recount&quot;&gt;{{citation | title= Baghdad recount throws Iraq election wide open | publisher= [[Agence France Presse]] | date= 19 April 2010 | url= http://www.google.com/hostednews/afp/article/ALeqM5gK93GrzFIRSaZgVzTB8hwO0fxArw }}&lt;/ref&gt; On 14 May IHEC announced that after 11,298 ballot boxes had been recounted, there was no sign of fraud or violations.&lt;ref name=&quot;no-fraud&quot;&gt;{{citation | title= No sign of fraud after Iraq vote recount | publisher= [[Press TV]] | url= http://www.presstv.com/detail.aspx?id=126481&amp;sectionid=351020201 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

The new parliament opened on 14 June 2010.&lt;ref name=&quot;par_open&quot;/&gt; After months of fraught negotiations, an agreement was reached on the formation of a new government on 11 November.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news| url=http://www.nytimes.com/aponline/2010/11/10/world/middleeast/AP-ML-Iraq-Politics.html?partner=rss&amp;emc=rss | work=The New York Times}}&lt;/ref&gt; Talabani would continue as president, Al-Maliki would stay on as prime minister and Allawi would head a new security council.

==Electoral system==
{{wikinews|Iraqi parliament approves delayed election law}}
The necessary election law was only passed on 8 November 2009, and the [[UNAMI|UN Mission in Iraq]], which is helping with the elections, estimated that it needed 90 days to plan for the election.&lt;ref name=&quot;LawPassed&quot;&gt;{{citation | title= Obama hails Iraq's approval of 2010 election law | url= http://www.timesoftheinternet.com/126728.html | publisher= [[Agence France Presse]] | date= 9 November 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;NYTDead&quot;/&gt; The electoral commission asked for a delay from the original date of 15 January.&lt;ref name=&quot;Delay&quot;&gt;{{citation | title= Iraq election body seeks vote delay due to law row | publisher= Reuters | date= 6 November 2009 | url = http://in.reuters.com/article/worldNews/idINIndia-43743520091106?pageNumber=2&amp;virtualBrandChannel=0&amp;sp=true }} {{Dead link|date=October 2010|bot=RjwilmsiBot}}&lt;/ref&gt; Iraqi Vice President [[Tariq Al-Hashimi]] vetoed the election law on 18 November 2009, delaying the election, which was originally scheduled for 21 January.&lt;ref name=&quot;VPVeto&quot;/&gt;

Prior to the election, the Supreme Court in Iraq ruled that the existing electoral rule was unconstitutional.{{Citation needed|date=May 2010}} The [[Council of Representatives of Iraq|parliament]] therefore set about drafting a new electoral law.&lt;ref name=&quot;NYTDead&quot;&gt;{{citation | title= Deadlock over election law in Iraq | work= [[New York Times]] | date= 21 October 2009 | url = http://www.nytimes.com/2009/10/22/world/middleeast/22iraq.html?hpw | first=Rod | last=Nordland}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The Iraqi cabinet approved a draft elections law in September 2009. However, it took two months and ten delays for the law to pass in the Council of Representatives. The main areas of dispute concerned the &quot;open list&quot; electoral system and the voters roll in [[Kirkuk Governorate]], which Arab and Turkmen parties alleged had been manipulated by the [[Kurdistan Regional Government]] of Iraq.&lt;ref name=&quot;LawPassed&quot;/&gt;

[[File:Stemmen2.jpg|left|thumb|Example open list ballot paper from the Netherlands with parties across the top and individuals listed down the page]]

===Open lists===
[[UNAMI]] advised the electoral system was changed to allow people to vote for individuals as well as party lists under the [[open list]] form of [[proportional representation]]. The last national elections had used a [[closed list]] system, but the [[Iraqi governorate elections of 2009]] had used open lists.&lt;ref&gt;{{citation | title= Iraq cabinet approves draft elections law | publisher= Reuters | date= 12 September 2009 | url= http://www.reuters.com/article/middleeastCrisis/idUSLC318417 | first=Khalid | last=al-Ansary}}&lt;/ref&gt; The move was initially supported by parliamentarians from [[Islamic Supreme Council of Iraq|ISCI]], and the most senior Iraqi Shiite cleric, Ayatollah [[Ali al-Sistani]], warned that failure to adopt the open list system would have &quot;''negative impacts on the democratic process''&quot; and would reduce turnout and aides said he may call for a boycott of the polls if closed lists were used again.&lt;ref name=&quot;open-voting&quot;&gt;{{citation | title= Top Shiite cleric supports open voting in Iraq's national polls | publisher= [[Xinhua]] | date= 6 October 2009 | url= http://news.xinhuanet.com/english/2009-10/06/content_12188647.htm }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{citation | title= Iraq's top Shiite cleric may urge vote boycott | publisher= [[Agence France Presse]] | date= 6 October 2009 | url= http://www.dailystar.com.lb/article.asp?edition_id=10&amp;categ_id=2&amp;article_id=107192 }}&lt;/ref&gt; Over 1,000 people demonstrated against closed lists throughout the country.&lt;ref&gt;{{citation | title= Iraqis rally amid Ayatollah's call for open voting | publisher= [[Press TV]] | date= 10 October 2009 | url= http://www.presstv.ir/detail.aspx?id=108336 }}&lt;/ref&gt; In the end, all parties except for the [[Kurdistani Alliance]] agreed to support open lists which was adopted.&lt;ref name=&quot;LawPassed&quot;/&gt;

===Kirkuk governorate===
{{Politics of Iraq}}
In [[Kirkuk Governorate]], it was proposed to use old 2004 electoral rolls. However,  Kurds protested about this, given the large number of Kurdish people who had settled there since then. [[UNAMI]] then proposed that Kirkuk be divided into two or more ethnic constituencies, with the Kurdish constituency given an automatic quota of 50% plus one. When put to parliament, this proposal was blocked by Arab MPs, causing a deadlock. The issue was referred to the Political Council for National Security, which comprises the President, Prime Minister and party leaders.&lt;ref&gt;{{citation | title= Iraq election law delayed over Kirkuk | publisher= [[Press TV]] | date= 21 October 2009 | url= http://www.presstv.ir/detail.aspx?id=109236&amp;sectionid=351020201 }}&lt;/ref&gt; The Council proposed to combine the electoral rolls from 2004 and 2009, but when this was put to parliament, it was blocked by Kurds. UNAMI then proposed using the 2009 records but revisiting for future elections.&lt;ref&gt;{{citation | title= Legislators in Iraq Block a Deal on Elections | publisher= New York Times | date= 28 October 2009 | url= http://www.nytimes.com/2009/10/28/world/middleeast/28iraq.html | first=John | last=Leland}}&lt;/ref&gt; When put to a vote the Kurdish MPs walked out, leaving the parliament without a quorum.&lt;ref&gt;{{citation | title= Iraq MPs fail to reach quorum for election law vote | publisher= [[Agence France Presse]] | date= 29 October 2009 | url= http://www.france24.com/en/node/4912793 }}&lt;/ref&gt; The final law said that the results in Kirkuk - and other governorates where the rolls were deemed &quot;dubious&quot; - would be provisional, subject to review within the first year by a committee formed out of the electoral commission, parliament, government and UNAMI, which could cancel fraudulent ballots. The law was passed by a vote of 141 to 54, with 80 members absent.&lt;ref name=&quot;LawPassed&quot;/&gt;

===Seat allocation===
The law increased the size of the Council from 275 to 325 members - equal to one seat per 100,000 citizens, as specified in the [[Constitution of Iraq]].&lt;ref name=&quot;NewChal&quot;&gt;{{citation | title= election law faces new challenges | publisher= Niqash | date= 13 November 2009 | url= http://niqash.org/content.php?contentTypeID=75&amp;id=2570&amp;lang=0 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[[Constitution of Iraq]], Article 49&lt;/ref&gt; As with the December 2005 election, seats will be allocated by governorate with additional &quot;compensatory&quot; seats allocated to those parties whose national share of the vote isn't reflected in the seats won at the governorate level. The votes of Iraqis living abroad would originally have been counted in the compensatory seats, which were reduced from 45 seats to 16 and eight of these 16 seats were allocated to specific national minorities - five for [[Iraqi Christians]] and one each for [[Yazidi]]s, [[Shabak people|Shabak]] and [[Mandaean]]s.&lt;ref name=&quot;NewChal&quot;/&gt;

Iraqi Vice-President [[Tariq al-Hashimi]] said the small number of compensatory seats discriminated against the estimated 2 million Iraqi refugees, many of whom are Sunni Arabs like al-Hashimi.&lt;ref name=&quot;NewChal&quot;/&gt; He demanded that the number of compensatory seats be increased to 15% (48) and went on national television to say he would veto the law if it weren't amended.&lt;ref name=&quot;VPVeto&quot;&gt;{{citation | title= Iraq VP threatens to veto vote law over refugees | publisher= Reuters | date= 15 November 2009 | url= http://www.reuters.com/article/middleeastCrisis/idUSLF235172 | first=Waleed | last=Ibrahim}}&lt;/ref&gt; Sunni Arab parliamentarian [[Saleh al-Mutlaq]] said 30 seats should be allocated to Iraqis abroad to reflect their numbers. President [[Jalal Talabani]] also supported the increase to 15%, after receiving a letter from Kurdish regional MPs saying their allies from minority groups would be unfairly treated.&lt;ref&gt;{{citation | title= Presidency’s demands put Iraq January vote in doubt | publisher= [[Agence France Presse]] | date= 16 November 2009 | url= http://www.gulf-times.com/site/topics/article.asp?cu_no=2&amp;item_no=326665&amp;version=1&amp;template_id=37&amp;parent_id=17 }}&lt;/ref&gt; In the event President Talabani and Vice-President [[Adel Abdul Mahdi]] signed the law despite their concerns, but Hashimi followed through his threat and vetoed it.&lt;ref&gt;{{citation | title= Will disputes derail Iraq's election | publisher= BBC News | date= 18 November 2009 | url= http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/world/middle_east/8367507.stm | first=Jim | last=Muir}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Parliament asked the Supreme Federal Court for advice, and it issued a statement saying that &quot;''all Iraqis, whether they live in the country or outside its borders, should be represented in the parliament.''&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{citation | title= Iraq struggles over election law dispute | publisher= The Guardian | date= 19 November 2009 | url= http://www.guardian.co.uk/world/feedarticle/8817184 | location=London}}&lt;/ref&gt; There was some confusion over this statement with the head of the legal affairs committee interpreted this as annulling the veto. However, [[Ayad al-Samarrai]], the parliamentary speaker said the statement was not binding on parliament because it was advice rather a ruling in response to a complaint.&lt;ref&gt;{{citation | title= Elections thrown off track | publisher= [[Asia Times]] | date= 21 November 2009 | url= http://www.atimes.com/atimes/Middle_East/KK21Ak02.html }}&lt;/ref&gt; Parliament therefore met to consider the law again. Hundreds of supporters of the Prime Minister held demonstrations against the veto in [[Najaf]], [[Basra]] and [[Wasit]].&lt;ref&gt;{{citation | title= Wassit residents protest election law veto | publisher= [[Aswat al-Iraq]] | date= 21 November 2009 | url= http://en.aswataliraq.info/?p=122311 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{citation | title= Demonstration in Basra against election law veto | publisher= [[Aswat al-Iraq]] | date= 20 November 2009 | url= http://en.aswataliraq.info/?p=122268 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{citation | title= مظاهرات ضد النقض.. والمرجعية الشيعية «قلقة» من احتمال إرجاء الاقتراع | language= [[Arabic language|Arabic]] | publisher= [[Voice of Iraq]] | date= 21 November 2009 | url= http://www.sotaliraq.com/iraqnews.php?id=52314 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

The President of Iraqi Kurdistan, [[Massoud Barzani]], then threatened to boycott the election if the representation of the three provinces in Kurdistan wasn't increased. The provinces had only gained three of the 77 additional seats.&lt;ref&gt;{{citation | title= Kurds Threaten Boycott of Iraqi National Elections | publisher= [[Voice of America]] | date= 17 November 2009 | url= http://www.voanews.com/english/2009-11-17-voa27.cfm }}&lt;/ref&gt;

When the Iraqi Parliament met again they amended the law to provide that Iraqis abroad would vote in the governorate they lived before they left the country.&lt;ref&gt;{{citation | title= Iraqi Parliament approves amended electoral law | publisher= [[Press TV]] | date= 23 November 2009 | url= http://www.presstv.ir/detail.aspx?id=111979 }}&lt;/ref&gt; The number of seats per governorate was then changed to increase all governorates by a fixed 2.8% over the 2005 population figures - meaning Kurdish areas got more seats but Sunni Arab areas got fewer.&lt;ref&gt;{{citation | title= Iraq's newly-approved electoral law to face veto | publisher= [[Press TV]] | date= 23 November 2009 | url= http://www.presstv.ir/detail.aspx?id=111996&amp;sectionid=351020201 }}&lt;/ref&gt; Analysts said Hashemi had &quot;''played poker and lost''&quot; and an MP from a rival Sunni Arab party said he should go and apologize to the governorates that had lost out.&lt;ref&gt;{{citation | title= Iraq's Sunni VP played election poker and lost, experts say | publisher= [[Agence France Presse]] | date= 29 November 2009 | url= http://www.france24.com/en/node/4936283 }}&lt;/ref&gt; Tribal leaders in the Sunni Arab city of [[Tikrit]] threatened to call for a poll boycott if the amended law went through and Hashemi said he would veto again.&lt;ref&gt;{{citation | title= Iraq MPs miss poll law deadline | publisher= [[Al Jazeera]] | date= 6 December 2009 | url= http://english.aljazeera.net/news/middleeast/2009/12/2009126125538181648.html }}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Internally displaced people]] will only be allowed to vote where their ration card was issued, a provision that Taha Daraa, MP in [[Diyala Governorate|Diyala]], said discriminated against them and was unconstitutional. He called on the constitutional court to strike down the provision.&lt;ref name=&quot;NewChal&quot;/&gt;

Head of IHEC, [[Faraj Al Haydari]], announced that curfew will be imposed and airports closed on the day of elections.&lt;ref name=&quot;AlS&quot;&gt;{{citation | title= Iraq elections: Preparations in progress | publisher= [[Al Sumaria]] | date= 6 December 2009 | url= http://www.alsumaria.tv/en/Iraq-News/1-26972-Iraq-elections-preparations-in-progress.html }}&lt;/ref&gt; The head of the IHEC electoral directorate, [[Haydar Al Abboudi]], said he hoped to announce the results of elections three days later.&lt;ref name=&quot;AlS&quot;/&gt;

The council agreed to increase the number of seats from 275 to 325. With this, the number of seats allocated to each governorate were changed from 2005 elections.&lt;ref&gt;{{citation | title=  مفوضية الانتخابات: 19 مليون عراقي ينتخبون 323 نائبا | language= [[Arabic language|Arabic]] | publisher= PUK Media | date= 6 December 2009 | url= http://www.sotaliraq.com/iraqnews.php?id=51663 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{citation | title= IFES Fact sheet | publisher= UNAMI Office of Electoral Assistance | url= http://www.uniraq.org/documents/ElectoralMaterial/221209/Apportionment%20of%20Council%20of%20Representatives%20Seats.pdf }}&lt;/ref&gt;

{| class=wikitable
|-
! Governorate !! Seats 2010  !! Seats 2005 !! In/de-creased by !! Percentage in/de-crease!!  Registered voters !! Votes Cast
|-
| [[Al Anbar Governorate]] || 14 || 9 || 5 || 55.6 %||802,000||472,603
|-
| [[Babil Governorate]] || 16 || 11 || 5 || 45.5 %||961,000||586,281
|-
| [[Baghdad Governorate]] || 68 || 59 || 9 || 15.3 %||4,599,000 || 2,541,766
|-
| [[Basra Governorate]] || 24 || 16 || 8 || 50.0 %||1,466,000||814,810
|-
| [[Dahuk Governorate]] || 10 || 7 || 3 || 42.9 %||574,000||424,715
|-
| [[Dhi Qar Governorate]] || 18 || 12 || 6 || 50.0 %||993,000||572,177
|-
| [[Diyala Governorate]] || 13 || 10 || 3 || 30.0 %||840,000 ||502,896
|-
| [[Erbil Governorate]] || 14 || 13 || 1 || 07.7 %||917,000||680,408
|-
| [[Karbala Governorate]] || 10 || 6 || 4 || 66.7 %||564,000||333,434
|-
| [[Kirkuk Governorate]] || 12 || 9 || 3 || 33.3 %||787,000||556,384
|-
| [[Maysan Governorate]] ||  10 || 7 || 3 || 42.9 %||561,000||272,818
|-
| [[Al Muthanna Governorate]] || 7 || 5 || 2 || 40.0 %||379,000||229,141
|-
| [[Najaf Governorate]] || 12 || 8 || 4 || 50.0 %||696,000||411,424
|-
| [[Ninawa Governorate]] || 31 || 19 || 12 || 63.2 %||1,702,000||1,054,798
|-
| [[Al-Qādisiyyah Governorate]] || 11 || 8 || 3 || 37.5 %||619,000||373,339
|-
| [[Salah ad Din Governorate]] || 12 || 8 || 4 || 50.0 %||696,000 || 488,865
|-
| [[As Sulaymaniyah Governorate]] || 17 || 15 || 2 || 13.3 %||1,098,000||833,631
|-
| [[Wasit Governorate]] || 11 || 8 || 3 || 37.5 %||638,000 ||376,922
|-
| Compensatory seats || 7 || 45 || -38 || -84.4 % || ||
|-
| Minorities || 8 || 0 || 8 || 100 % || ||
|-
| '''Total'''|| 325 || 275 || 50 || 18.2 % ||18,892,000||11,526,412
|}

==Coalitions==
[[File:Iraqi legislative election of Dec 2005 with logos.png|thumb|left|Previous election result]]

The [[United Iraqi Alliance]], made up primarily of religious [[Shi'ite]] parties, won 128 out of 275 seats in the [[Iraqi legislative election, December 2005|previous election]] and was the largest party in the parliament. The list split into two lists for this election: the [[State of Law Coalition]] of Prime Minister [[Nouri al-Maliki]] and the [[National Iraqi Alliance]], which included most of the other parties. In total 160 regular parties as well as 36 independents and 10 minority parties and candidates took part in the election, see here &lt;ref&gt;[http://www.ihec.iq/content/file/House_of_Representatives_elections/PE%20Report%20and%20Minority_Eng_11.pdf ]{{dead link|date=August 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; for a full list of the participants.

===National Iraqi Alliance (NIA) - List 316===
The [[National Iraqi Alliance]] (NIA or INA) is a coalition of mainly Shi'a parties. It was first mooted in August 2009 and is made up of the principal remaining components of the United Iraqi Alliance: The [[Islamic Supreme Council of Iraq]] (ISCI) &amp; affiliated [[Badr Organization]], the [[Sadr Movement]], Ex-Prime Minister [[Ibrahim al-Jaafari]] (who became the group's chairman) and his [[National Reform Trend]] (Islah), the [[Islamic Fadhila Party]] and an [[Islamic Dawa Party - Iraq Organisation]] (Tanzim al-Iraq) breakaway faction: the [[Islamic Dawa Party - Domestic Faction]] (Tanzim al-Dakhli) headed by [[Abdul Karim al-Anizi]]. ISCI was reported to have offered to split the coalition's seats four ways - 25% to ISCI &amp; Badr, 25% to the Sadrists, 25% to [[Prime Minister of Iraq|Prime Minister]] [[Nouri al-Maliki]]'s [[Islamic Dawa Party]] and 25% to minor parties and independents.&lt;ref name=&quot;AFP&quot;&gt;{{citation | title= Iraq PM set to break with Shiite coalition in January polls | publisher= [[Agence France Presse]] | date= 13 August 2008 | url= http://www.dailytelegraph.com.au/news/iraq-pm-set-to-break-with-shiite-coalition-in-january-polls/story-e6freuy9-1225760976765 }}&lt;/ref&gt; However, Maliki demanded half the seats - reflecting the results of the [[Iraqi governorate elections of 2009]] which were won by Maliki's [[State of Law Coalition]] - and a guarantee of another term as Prime Minister.&lt;ref&gt;{{citation | title= New Iraqi Shiite coalition coming together | language= [[Arabic language|Arabic]] | publisher= [[Informed Comment]] | url= http://www.juancole.com/2009/08/new-iraqi-shiite-coalition-coming.html }}, quoting [[Azzaman]]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{citation | title= Maliki plots his next move | publisher= [[Asia Times]] | date= 16 September 2009 | url= http://www.atimes.com/atimes/Middle_East/KI16Ak02.html }}&lt;/ref&gt; He also wanted Sunni Arab parties like the [[Awakening movements]] to be included as primary members of the coalition to form what his spokesman termed &quot;''a truly national alliance''&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;AFP&quot;/&gt; In September the coalition was formally announced without the Islamic Dawa Party.&lt;ref name=&quot;NIA&quot;&gt;{{citation | title= Shiite Fundamentalist Coalition Announced Al-Maliki Might Not win Second Term | publisher= [[Informed Comment]] | date= 25 August 2009 | url= http://www.juancole.com/2009/08/shiite-fundamentalist-coalition.html }}, quoting [[Al-Zaman]]&lt;/ref&gt; Despite it's religious Shi'a character the alliance claims to represent all of Iraq and it also includes some Secular parties such as former Oil Minister [[Ahmad Chalabi]]'s [[Iraqi National Congress]] and Sunni parties such as [[Hamid Hayes]]' [[Tribes of Iraq Coalition]], an al-Anbar Awakening Council splinter group.&lt;ref name=&quot;ReuFact&quot;&gt;{{citation | title= Political alliances ahead of Iraq's 2010 election | publisher= Reuters | date= 21 October 2009 | url= http://www.reuters.com/article/latestCrisis/idUSLF559498 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

===State of Law Coalition (SLC) - List 337===
After negotiations between Prime Minister Nouri al-Maliki and [[Ammar al-Hakim]]'s Islamic Supreme Council for the National Iraqi Alliance broke down, al-Maliki decided to run with the [[State of Law Coalition]] (SLC or SLA) which was built around his Islamic Dawa Party for the 2009 local elections.{{clarify|date=November 2010}} The State of Law Coalition's largest component are members of al-Maliki's Dawa party and members of the incumbent al-Maliki led government. Other major notable components are the Islamic Dawa Party - Tanzim al-Iraq and Oil Minister [[Hussain al-Shahristani]]'s &quot;Independent Bloc&quot;. While it is a mainly Shi'a alliance, State of Law is officially a national, non-sectarian, multi-ethnic coalition. It includes several minor Sunni, Christian, Kurdish and Turkmen parties and independent candidates such as [[Abbas al-Bayati]]'s [[Islamic Union of Iraqi Turkoman]] and Sheikh [[Ali Hatem al-Suleiman]]'s [[Anbar Salvation National Front]], an Anbar Awakening Council splinter group.&lt;ref&gt;{{citation | title= BBC - Guide to groups competing in Iraqi polls | publisher= BBC News | date= 8 March 2010| url= http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/middle_east/8540347.stm }}&lt;/ref&gt; The State of Law Coalition was the winner of the [[Iraqi governorate elections, 2009]], where they became the largest list, winning 126 out of 440 local seats and becoming the largest list in 8 of the 9 Shi'a provinces and Baghdad.&lt;ref&gt;[[Iraqi governate elections, 2009]]&lt;/ref&gt;

===al-Iraqiyya (INM) - List 333===
The [[Iraqi National Movement]] (INM), more commonly known as al-Iraqiyya, is the main secular, non-sectarian and [[Arab Nationalims|Nationalist]] list, it is headed by former Prime Minister [[Ayad Allawi]]. In the 2005 election Allawi's [[Iraqi National List]] won 8% of the vote, winning votes among secular Shi'a and Sunnis. In 2009 Vice-President [[Tariq al-Hashimi]] left the Sunni [[Iraqi Islamic Party]] (which was at the time, Iraq's main Sunni party), and launched a new party called the [[Renewal List]].&lt;ref&gt;{{citation | title= Disunity Threatens Sunni Iraq | publisher= Wall Street Journal | date= 28 September 2009 | url= http://online.wsj.com/article/SB125409363151844891.html | first=Gina | last=Chon}}&lt;/ref&gt; Hashimi's party  joined the al-Iraqiyya. Also joining was the [[Iraqi National Dialogue Front]] (Hiwar) led by former [[Ba'ath Party]] member [[Saleh al-Mutlak]]. The list includes most of the country's main Sunni-based, Nationalist parties: [[al-Hadba]], [[National Movement for Development and Reform|al-Hal]], ex-President [[Ghazi al-Yawer]]'s [[The Iraqis]], [[Adnan Pachachi]]'s [[Assembly of Independent Democrats]] and Deputy Prime Minister [[Rafi al-Issawi]]'s party, as well as the country's largest Turkmen party, the [[Iraqi Turkmen Front]].&lt;ref&gt;{{citation | title= Iraq VP forms coalition with Mutlak, Allawi | publisher= [[Al Sumaria]] | date= 29 October 2009 | url= http://www.alsumaria.tv/en/Iraq-News/1-39666-Iraq-VP-forms-coalition-with-Mutlak%2C-Allawi.html }}&lt;/ref&gt;

In January 2010 the De-Baathification Commission barred al-Mutlak from the election due to his previous membership of the Iraqi Ba'ath Party. The al-Iraqiyya List threatened to boycott the election unless the decision was reversed.&lt;ref name=&quot;boycot&quot;&gt;{{citation | title= Influential Group Threatens To Boycott Iraq Election | publisher= [[Radio Liberty]] | date= 9 January 2010 | url= http://www.rferl.org/content/Influential_Group_Threatens_To_Boycott_Iraq_Election/1924762.html }}&lt;/ref&gt; al-Mutlaq however eventually decided his party would run in the election despite the fact that he had been banned as candidate.&lt;ref name=&quot;presstv.com&quot;&gt;{{citation | title= No party to boycott Iraq elections | publisher= [[Press TV]] | date= 25 February 2010 | url= http://www.presstv.com/detail.aspx?id=119514&amp;sectionid=351020201 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

===al-Tawafuq - List 338===
The [[Iraqi Accord Front]], more commonly known as al-Tawafuq is a Sunni Islamist list which was the main Sunni coalition in 2005, winning 15% and 44 seats as an alliance between the [[Iraqi Islamic Party]], the General Council for the People of Iraq (Iraqi People's Gathering) and the Iraqi National Dialogue Council.&lt;ref&gt;{{citation | url= http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/middle_east/4511450.stm | publisher= BBC News | title= Guide to Iraqi political parties | date= 20 January 2006 | accessdate= 5 May 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; Since then the Iraqi National Dialogue Council left the alliance and after disappointing results in 2009, the Iraqi Islamic Party's leader Tariq al-Hashemi resigned from his position and left the party to create his own party and join al-Iraqiyya. The alliance still includes several independent candidates and the Sunni Islamist, Turkmen Justice Party. In 2009 Tawafuq was still the largest Sunni list with 32 seats however they received less than 25% of the votes they received in 2005 and lost in their main stronghold, the al-Anbar governorate. Meanwhile the parties which would later form al-Iraqiyya won over 70 seats .&lt;ref&gt;{{citation | title= Iraqi elections 2010 - Iraqi Accord | publisher= [[Carnegie Endowment for International Peace]] | date= | url= http://www.carnegieendowment.org/publications/special/misc/iraqielections2010/index.cfm?fa=ia }}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Iraq's Unity - List 348===
[[Ahmed Abu Risha]], the head of the [[Awakening movement]] party that won the most seats in the [[Al Anbar governorate election, 2009]], formed a coalition with Interior Minister [[Jawad al-Bolani]]'s [[Iraqi Constitutional Party]] and [[Ahmed Abdul Ghafour al-Samarrai]]'s [[Sunni Endowment Party|Sunni Endowment]] called the [[Unity Alliance of Iraq]], also known as Iraq's Unity or Iraqi Unity.&lt;ref name=&quot;ReuFact&quot;/&gt; Abu Risha had previously held talks with Maliki on joining the State of Law Coalition.&lt;ref&gt;{{citation | title= Trouble in former Qaeda heartland bodes ill for Iraq | publisher= Reuters | date= 24 August 2009 | url= http://www.reuters.com/article/featuredCrisis/idUSLM425070 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{citation | title= Iraqi Constitutional Party demonstrates for open-slate election | publisher= [[Aswat al-Iraq]] | date= 10 October 2009 | url= http://en.aswataliraq.info/?p=120148 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Kurdistani List - List 372 and other Kurdish Lists===
The [[Kurdistani List|Kurdistan Alliance]] called for a single pan-Kurdish list, including the Islamist parties and the opposition [[Gorran Movement]], which had gained a quarter of the seats in the [[Iraqi Kurdistan legislative election of 2009]]. However, the Gorran Movement said the two main Kurdistani Alliance parties - the [[President of Iraq|Iraqi President]] [[Jalal Talabani]]'s [[Patriotic Union of Kurdistan]] (PUK) and [[President of Kurdistan|Kurdish President]] [[Massoud Barzani]]'s [[Kurdistan Democratic Party of Iraq]] (KDP) - tended to &quot;monopolize&quot; power, and competing separately would &quot;secure their own powers&quot; in Baghdad. The [[Kurdistan Islamic Union]] (KIU) also said it would compete separately, as it had in December 2005, and rejected a pan-Islamist coalition with the [[Islamic Movement of Kurdistan]] (IMK) and the [[Kurdistan Islamic Group]] (IGK). Therefore Gorran, the KIU and the IGK all three ran in separate lists, while the PUK and KDP ran in a joint &quot;Kurdistani List&quot; together with several minor parties including the [[Kurdistan Communist Party - Iraq|Kurdistan Communist Party]], Qadir Aziz's [[Kurdistan Toilers' Party]] and the IMK. Though a mainly Kurdish List, the Kurdistan List also includes the [[Turkmen Brotherhood Movement|Turkmen Brotherhood]]&lt;ref&gt;{{citation | title= kurds seek unity in struggle with baghdad | publisher= Niqash | date= 29 October 2009 | url= http://niqash.org/content.php?contentTypeID=75&amp;id=2559&amp;lang=0 }}&lt;/ref&gt; In 2005 the [[Democratic Patriotic Alliance of Kurdistan]] had won 21.7% of the votes and 53 out of 275 seats with the [[Kurdistan Islamic Union]] winning 1.3% of the votes and 5 seats.&lt;ref&gt;[[Iraqi parliamentary election, December 2005]]&lt;/ref&gt; In the 2009 Kurdistan general elections the Kurdistani List had won 59 out of 100 Kurdish seats, Gorran winning 25 and the Islamist list of the KIU and IGK winning 13 seats.&lt;ref&gt;{{citation | title= iraq's kurdistan region: looking back at the events of 2009 | publisher= Niqash | date= 26 December 2009 | url= http://www.niqash.org/content.php?contentTypeID=75&amp;id=2578&amp;lang=0 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Opinion polls==
In February 2010 the National Media Center, a government agency conducted a survey among 5,000 Iraqis from 18 different provinces. When people were asked who they would vote for the poll gave the following results:&lt;ref name=&quot;opinion poll&quot;&gt;{{citation | title= Foes Maliki, Allawi 'top contenders in Iraq poll' | publisher= [[France 24]] | date= 24 February 2010 | url= http://www.france24.com/en/20100224-foes-maliki-allawi-top-contenders-iraq-poll }}&lt;/ref&gt;
*[[State of Law Coalition]]: 29.9%
*[[Iraqi National Movement]]: 21.8%
*[[National Iraqi Alliance]]: 17.2%
*[[Kurdistani List]] 10%
*[[Iraqi Unity]]: 5%
*[[Iraqi Accord Front]]: 2.7%
*Other: 6.3%
*No Opinion 4.9%
*No Response 2.2%

When asking if people would vote or not two-thirds said they would vote. Among Shi'a Muslims 63% said they would vote, among Sunni Muslims this was 58%. 57% of the Arabs said they would vote while 67% of the Kurds said they would vote. Of those asked 47% supported the candidate ban, 38% opposed it and 15% had no opinion.&lt;ref name=&quot;opinion poll&quot;/&gt;

According to the Sadrists, they expected the National Iraqi Alliance to be the largest Shi'a List, winning 70 to 80 seats in the government, where from the Sadr Movement would win at least 35. Spokesmen from Da'awa were skeptical about these claims.&lt;ref&gt;[[MSNBC]] [http://www.msnbc.msn.com/id/35566905/ns/world_news-mideastn_africa/ Anti-U.S. bloc gains ahead of Iraq vote], Feb. 24, 2010&lt;/ref&gt;

==Pre-election controversies==
===Candidate ban===
On 15 January 2010 Iraq's electoral commission banned 499 candidates, mostly Sunni Muslims, from the election due to alleged links with the Ba'ath Party.&lt;ref name=&quot;baathists&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;us-surrender&quot;/&gt; Several prominent Sunni politicians were among the banned, including [[Iraqi Front for National Dialogue]] leader [[Saleh al-Mutlaq]], Iraqi Defence Minister [[Qadir Obeidi]]&lt;ref name=&quot;baathists&quot;/&gt; and [[Iraqi Accordance Front]] chairman Dhafer al-Ani.&lt;ref name=&quot;us-surrender&quot;/&gt; Among the banned candidates 216 were former members of the [[Ba'ath Party]] (including 13 mid-ranking members), 182 were members of the paramilitary [[Fedayeen Saddam]] and the [[Iraqi Intelligence Service|Mukhabarat]] (Saddam's intelligence service), a further 105 of them were officers from the [[Old Iraqi army]], including several ex-generals.&lt;ref name=&quot;candidates-linked&quot;&gt;{{citation | title= Banned Iraq candidates linked to Saddam | publisher= [[Press TV]] | date= 19 January 2010 | url= http://www.presstv.com/detail.aspx?id=116565&amp;sectionid=351020201 }}&lt;/ref&gt;
Among the banned candidates 60% were Sunni Muslims and 40% were Shi'a&lt;ref name=&quot;Abu Risha&quot;&gt;{{citation | title= Iraqi sheik threatens boycott over ballot purge | publisher= The Washington Post | date= 30 January 2010 | url= http://www.washingtonpost.com/wp-dyn/content/article/2010/01/30/AR2010013000454.html }} {{Dead link|date=August 2010|bot=RjwilmsiBot}}&lt;/ref&gt; however all of the banned candidates are members of secular and liberal parties and not a single member of a Sunni or Shi'a religious party was banned.&lt;ref&gt;{{citation | title= What Do We Know About The Election Crisis In Iraq? | publisher= [[Radio Free Europe/Radio Liberty]] | date= 28 January 2010 | url= http://www.rferl.org/content/What_Do_We_Know_About_The_Election_Crisis_In_Iraq_/1942557.html}}&lt;/ref&gt; According to [[Sheikh Abu Risha]] 7 of the banned candidates were members of his [[Anbar Salvation Council]] and 70 were members of the Iraq Unity list, a major Sunni list led by Abu Risha and Jawad al-Bolani.&lt;ref name=&quot;Abu Risha&quot;/&gt;

The electoral commission was criticized for alleged partiality and ties to Shi'a religious parties and some fear this decision will lead to sectarian tensions.&lt;ref name=&quot;baathists&quot;/&gt; Sunni Muslims largely boycotted the [[Iraqi legislative election, January 2005|January 2005 elections]] and it was feared they would boycott this election as well, since the dominant Sunni list-the Iraqi National Movement-threatened to boycott the elections if the decision was not reversed.&lt;ref name=&quot;boycot&quot;/&gt; Al-Mutlaq himself said he would resort to the United Nations and the international community if he is banned from the next election calling the decision a political decision &quot;linked to foreign desire&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{citation | title= Saleh al Mutlaq: Decision to Ban Taking Part in Elections is Political | publisher= [[Asharq Al-Awsat]] | date= 9 January 2010 | url= http://www.asharq-e.com/news.asp?section=1&amp;id=19450 }}&lt;/ref&gt; Sheikh Ahmed Abu Risha, head of the Awakening councils threatened he might boycott the 2010 elections as well if the 70 banned candidates of his list were not unbanned.&lt;ref name=&quot;Abu Risha&quot;/&gt; Earlier, Massoud Barzani had threatened Kurds might boycott the elections over the seat allocations.&lt;ref&gt;{{citation | title= Kurds threaten Iraq election boycott | publisher= CNN | date= 17 November 2009 | url= http://www.cnn.com/2009/WORLD/meast/11/17/iraq.election.law/index.html }}&lt;/ref&gt; Kurds however decided not to boycott after more seats were allocated to them.&lt;ref name=&quot;appeal&quot;&gt;{{citation | title= Iraq government condemns Baathist election ban repeal | publisher= BBC News | date= 4 February 2010 | url= http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/middle_east/8498111.stm }}&lt;/ref&gt;

Iraqi President [[Jalal Talabani]] called on the Supreme Court to settle the dispute over the banned candidates saying: &quot;We should not be unjust with them.&quot; In Najaf however, demonstrations were held in support of the ban where people called the Ba'athists [[Nazis]].&lt;ref&gt;{{citation | title= Talabani asks court to settle elections dispute | publisher= [[Press TV]] | date= 22 January 2010 | url= http://www.presstv.com/detail.aspx?id=116767&amp;sectionid=351020201 }}&lt;/ref&gt; American Vice President [[Joe Biden]] travelled to Iraq on 23 January to try resolve the matters of the election ban.&lt;ref&gt;{{citation | title= Biden waltzes into Iraq over ex-Baathists | publisher= [[Press TV]] | date= 23 January 2010 | url= http://www.presstv.com/detail.aspx?id=116825&amp;sectionid=351020201 }}&lt;/ref&gt; In response on 25 January, Iraq dropped the ban on 59 out of 150 candidates who had appealed their ban. A total of 458 however remained banned from the elections.&lt;ref&gt;{{citation | title= Iraq reinstates 59 election candidates | publisher= [[Agence France Presse]] | work= [[Google News]] | date= 25 January 2009 | url= http://www.google.com/hostednews/afp/article/ALeqM5iJGz55dJrnOzzejqmBj6QTolyydg }}&lt;/ref&gt; On 3 February the appeals court has temporarily lifted the ban on the candidates allowing them to run,&lt;ref&gt;{{citation | title= Iraq suspends election ban on 500 'ex-Baathists' | publisher= [[Press TV]] | date= 12 February 2010 | url= http://www.presstv.com/detail.aspx?id=117811&amp;sectionid=351020201 }}&lt;/ref&gt; which the Iraqi government condemned the decision by the court calling it &quot;illegal and unconstitutional&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;appeal&quot;/&gt; The suspending of the ban is meant to allow the candidates to run, the Supreme Court said they will then review the candidates after the election. The government however ordered the Supreme Court to make their final ruling on the candidates before the election.&lt;ref&gt;{{citation | title= Iraqi court to rule on eligibility of 500 candidates | publisher= [[Press TV]] | date= 7 February 2010 | url= http://www.presstv.com/detail.aspx?id=118060&amp;sectionid=351020201 }}&lt;/ref&gt; However out of 511 candidates most had been replaced by their parties (and 59 had been unbanned), only 177 candidates appealed their ban. According to IHEC spokesman [[Khalid al-Shami]] only 37 of those appealed their ban correctly, the other 140 remain banned.&lt;ref&gt;{{citation | title= Most disqualified Iraqi candidates failed to appeal | publisher= [[Press TV]] | date= 9 February 2010 | url= http://www.presstv.com/detail.aspx?id=118271&amp;sectionid=351020201 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

US Ambassador Christopher Hill said that by lifting the ban the elections would become credible. Iraqi Prime Minister Nouri al-Maliki however said they would not allow Hill to go beyond his diplomatic mission and that Iraq would not bow to any US-pressure. He also insisted that the ban on the alleged Ba'athist candidates must be implemented. Maliki called on the countries high court for a final decision and also called for a parliamentary meeting to discuss the issue.&lt;ref&gt;{{citation | title= Maliki 'won't allow US meddling in election row' | publisher= [[Press TV]] | date= 5 February 2010 | url= http://www.presstv.com/detail.aspx?id=117933&amp;sectionid=351020201 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

Before the start of the campaign on 12 February 2010, the IHEC confirmed that the appeals by banned candidates had been rejected and thus all 456 banned candidates would not be allowed to run for the election.&lt;ref name=&quot;ihec-no-go&quot;/&gt; The Iraqi National Movement (al-Iraqiyya list) suspended their election campaign in response.&lt;ref name=&quot;al-Qaeda&quot;&gt;{{citation | title= Iraq coalition halts poll campaign | publisher= [[Al Jazeera English]] | date= 14 February 2010 | url= http://english.aljazeera.net/news/middleeast/2010/02/201021463242489398.html }}&lt;/ref&gt; Later Saleh al-Mutlaq's Iraqi National Dialogue Front (a part of the Iraqiyya list) withdrew from the elections and called on other parties to boycott the elections as well.&lt;ref&gt;{{citation | title= Major Iraqi party pulls out of March elections | publisher= [[Press TV]] | date= 20 February 2010 | url= http://www.presstv.com/detail.aspx?id=119081&amp;sectionid=351020201 }}&lt;/ref&gt; Later however al-Mutlaq changed his mind and decided his party should join the election anyway despite himself being banned.&lt;ref name=&quot;presstv.com&quot;/&gt;

===Election violence===
On 13 February, the day the election campaign started, there were several bombings. The first bomb struck a political office of [[Saleh al-Mutlaq]], a second bomb was thrown into a building in West-Baghdad used by Sunni scholars and election candidates, while a third bomb damaged the National Iraqi Alliance's headquarters in Eastern Baghdad, a fourth blast struck the headquarters of the [[Moderate Movement list]], injuring two people, a fifth blast struck a building used by [[Nehru Mohammed Abdul Karim al-Kasanzani]]'s list, injuring one person.&lt;ref name=&quot;al-Qaeda&quot;/&gt;
On 15 February, [[Abu Omar al-Baghdadi]] the leader of the [[Islamic State of Iraq]], an umbrella organisation which includes [[al-Qaeda in Iraq]] released an internet message calling for a Sunni boycott against the election. He was quoted as saying: &quot;Sunni participation in this election will certainly lead to the establishment of the principle that Sunnis in Iraq are a minority who have to be ruled by the rejectionists&quot; (a term used by radical Sunnis to describe Shi'a Muslims), he also said that his group would use &quot;primarily military means to prevent these elections&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;al-Qaeda&quot;/&gt;
On 16 and 17 February campaign workers for the secular [[Ahrar party]] were attacked in Baghdad and Maysan governorates when trying to hang up posters.&lt;ref&gt;{{citation | title= Secular political party under attack in Iraq | publisher= True/Slant | date= 17 February 2010 | url= http://trueslant.com/michaelhastings/2010/02/17/exclusive-secular-political-campaign-under-attack-in-iraq }}&lt;/ref&gt; Also between 14 and 17 February at least four Christians were killed by Sunni inusrgents.&lt;ref&gt;{{citation | title= Fourth Christian killed in northern Iraq | publisher= [[Agence France Presse]] | work= [[Google News]] | date= 17 February 2010 | url= http://www.google.com/hostednews/afp/article/ALeqM5iL8VZjDPD8eGnaYK_2HyCOEqT2Ig }}&lt;/ref&gt; While on 18 February an al-Qaeda suicide bomber struck a government headquarters in [[Ramadi]], al-Anbar, as part of their campaign to paralyze the elections.&lt;ref&gt;{{citation | url=http://www.nytimes.com/2010/02/19/world/middleeast/19iraq.html | work=The New York Times | title=Iraq Suicide Bomber Strikes in Anbar | date=19 February 2010 | accessdate=5 May 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;
26 February four civilians were injured as a massive blast struck Iraq's finance ministry.&lt;ref&gt;{{citation | title= Blast hits Iraq's Finance Ministry | publisher= [[Press TV]] | date= 26 February 2010 | url= http://www.presstv.com/detail.aspx?id=119533&amp;sectionid=351020201 }}&lt;/ref&gt; A car bomb targeted an election convoy for Sunni candidate Ashur Hamid al-Karboul, in [[Al Khaldiya, Iraq|Khaldiyah]] in al-Anbar. A campaign worker and a bystander were killed.&lt;ref&gt;{{citation | title= Fatal car bomb targets Iraqi election convoy | publisher= Associated Press | work= [[Toronto Sun]] | date= 28 February 2010 | url= http://www.torontosun.com/news/world/2010/02/28/13057751-ap.html }}&lt;/ref&gt;

On 3 March, two car bombs exploded in the city of [[Baquba]], Diyala, killing 33 people and injuring 55. This was one of the deadliest bombings of the year.&lt;ref&gt;{{citation | title= 33 killed, 55 injured on Iraq's black Wednesday | publisher= [[Press TV]] | date= 3 March 2010 | url= http://www.presstv.com/detail.aspx?id=119931&amp;sectionid=351020201 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

One of the hardest hit communities during the election period is the [[Christianity in Iraq|Assyrian community]]. Attacks against the Assyrians began in December in [[Mosul]], Iraq's second largest city. It led to the assassination of over 20 Christians and the bombings of different churches in Mosul. The attacks led to 680 Christian families flying Mosul to [[Nineveh plains]].&lt;ref&gt;{{citation | title=اكثر من 680 عائلة من ابناء شعبنا مهجرة من مدينة الموصل باتجاه المناطق الامنة | language= [[Arabic language|Arabic]] | publisher= [[Ishtar TV]] | date= 28 February 2010 | url= http://ishtartv.com/viewarticle,27849.html }}&lt;/ref&gt;

On election day, Islamist insurgents distributed leaflets in Sunni neighbourhoods of Baghdad warning people not to go to the polls,&lt;ref&gt;{{citation | title= Iraq parliamentary election hit by insurgent attacks | publisher= BBC News | date= 7 March 2010 | url= http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/middle_east/8553929.stm }}&lt;/ref&gt; they mostly used rockets, mortars and explosive-filled plastic bottles hidden under trash to target those who did vote, this was due to a vehicle ban the government had enforced to stop car-bombings.&lt;ref name=&quot;huffingtonpost&quot;&gt;{{citation | title= Iraq Election: Major Turnout At Polls Despite Insurgent Violence | publisher= Huffington Post | date= 8 March 2010 | url= http://www.huffingtonpost.com/2010/03/07/iraq-election-polling-sta_n_488996.html }}&lt;/ref&gt; Attacks killed 42 people&lt;ref name=&quot;icasualties&quot;&gt;{{citation | title= Iraqi Deaths March 2010 | publisher= [[iCasualties.org]] | date= March 2010 | url= http://icasualties.org/Iraq/iraqideaths.aspx?hndPeriod=Mar-10 }}&lt;/ref&gt; and wounded at least 110.&lt;ref name=&quot;timesofindia.indiatimes.com&quot;&gt;{{citation | title= 38 killed in Iraq election day violence: Interior ministry | publisher= [[Times of India]] | date= 7 March 2010 | url= http://timesofindia.indiatimes.com/world/middle-east/38-killed-in-Iraq-election-day-violence-Interior-ministry/articleshow/5655030.cms }} {{Dead link|date=May 2011|bot=RjwilmsiBot}}&lt;/ref&gt; In Baghdad Katyusha rockets killed at least 4 people and wounded 16 in the neighbourhoods of Qreiat and [[al-Hurriya]], while roadside bombs killed 7 people in Baghdad.&lt;ref name=&quot;icasualties&quot;/&gt; In [[Mahmoudiyah, Iraq|Mahmoudiyah]], a city near Baghdad, a policemant was killed and 11 people were injured when two mortars struck a polling center.&lt;ref name=&quot;huffingtonpost&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;icasualties&quot;/&gt; One woman was killed and 36 people were injured during attacks on polling centers in the insurgent stronghold of [[Mosul]]. But the largest attack came in Baghdad when a Katyusha rocket hit a flat in [[Hay Ur|Ur neighbourhood]], killing 25 people and injuring 20.&lt;ref name=&quot;icasualties&quot;/&gt; Non-fatal attacks on election day were reported in [[Tikrit]], [[Baquba]], [[Samarra]] and [[Fallujah]].&lt;ref&gt;{{citation | title= 24 Iraqis killed in terror attacks since polls opened | publisher= [[Press TV]] | date= 7 March 2010 | url= http://www.presstv.com/detail.aspx?id=120255&amp;sectionid=351020201 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

According to the [[Iraq Body Count]], from 12 February (when the campaigning started) until 7 March (election day), at least 228 people were killed. Another 176 people were killed in the period between election day and the release of the final results.&lt;ref&gt;{{citation | title= Iraq Body Count database | publisher= [[Iraqi Body Count]] | date= | url= http://www.iraqbodycount.org/database/recent/0/ }}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Results==
[[File:2010 Iraqi election map.png|thumb|400px|Map showing the list which won the most votes for every governorate.]]

{{Iraqi parliamentary election, 2010}}

===Results per governorate===

{| class=&quot;wikitable&quot; style=&quot;text-align:right&quot;
|-
! Governorate
! [[State of Law Coalition|State of Law]]
! [[National Iraqi Alliance|NIA]]
! [[al-Iraqiya]]
! [[Kurdistan List]]
! [[Gorran Movement|Gorran]]
! [[Iraqi Accord Front|Tawafuq]]
! [[Unity Alliance of Iraq|Unity]]
! [[Kurdistan Islamic Union|KIU]]
! [[Islamic Group of Kurdistan|KIG]]
! Total Seats
|-
|align=&quot;left&quot;| '''[[al-Anbar]]''' ||0||0||'''11'''||-||-||2||1||-||-||'''14'''
|-
|align=&quot;left&quot;| '''[[Babil]]''' ||'''8'''||5||3||0||-||0||0||-||-||'''16'''
|-
|align=&quot;left&quot;| '''[[Baghdad Governorate|Baghdad]]''' ||'''26'''||17||24||0||0||1||0||0||-||'''68'''
|-
|align=&quot;left&quot;| '''[[Basra Governorate|Basra]]''' ||'''14'''||7||3||-||-||-||0||-||-||'''24'''
|-
|align=&quot;left&quot;| '''[[Dahuk Governorate|Dahuk]]''' ||-||0||-||'''9'''||0||-||-||1||0||'''10'''
|-
|align=&quot;left&quot;| '''[[Dhi Qar]]''' ||8||'''9'''||1||0||-||-||0||-||-||'''18'''
|-
|align=&quot;left&quot;| '''[[Diyala Governorate|Diyala]]''' ||1||3||'''8'''||1||0||0||0||0||-||'''13'''
|-
|align=&quot;left&quot;| '''[[Erbil Governorate|Hewler]]''' ||-||0||-||'''10'''||2||-||-||1||1||'''14'''
|-
|align=&quot;left&quot;| '''[[Karbala Governorate|Karbala]]''' ||'''6'''||3||1||-||-||-||0||-||-||'''10'''
|-
|align=&quot;left&quot;| '''[[Kirkuk Governorate|Kerkuk]]''' ||0||0||'''6'''||'''6'''||0||0||-||0||0||'''12'''
|-
|align=&quot;left&quot;| '''[[Maysan]]''' ||4||'''6'''||0||-||-||-||0||-||-||'''10'''
|-
|align=&quot;left&quot;| '''[[Muthanna]]''' ||'''4'''||3||0||0||-||0||0||-||-||'''7'''
|-
|align=&quot;left&quot;| '''[[Najaf Governorate|Najaf]]''' ||'''7'''||5||0||0||-||-||0||-||-||'''12'''
|-
|align=&quot;left&quot;| '''[[Ninawa]]''' ||0||1||'''20'''||8||0||1||1||0||0||'''31'''
|-
|align=&quot;left&quot;| '''[[Al-Qādisiyyah Governorate|Qadisiyyah]]''' ||4||'''5'''||2||0||-||-||0||-||-||'''11'''
|-
|align=&quot;left&quot;| '''[[Salah ad Din Governorate|Salaheddin]]''' ||0||0||'''8'''||0||0||2||2||-||-||'''12'''
|-
|align=&quot;left&quot;| '''[[Sulaymaniyah Governorate|Silemani]]''' ||-||0||-||'''8'''||6||-||-||2||1||'''17'''
|-
|align=&quot;left&quot;| '''[[Wasit Governorate|Wasit]]''' ||'''5'''||4||2||0||-||-||0||-||-||'''11'''
|-
|align=&quot;left&quot;| '''Compensatory''' ||'''2'''||'''2'''||'''2'''||1||0||0||0||0||0||'''7'''
|-
|align=&quot;left&quot;| '''Minority''' ||0||0||0||0||0||0||0||0||0||'''8'''
|-
|align=&quot;left&quot;| '''Total''' ||89||70||'''91'''||43||8||6||4||4||2||'''325'''
|}

[http://historiae.org/uncertified.asp '''Source''']

===Candidate Votes===

{| class=&quot;wikitable&quot; style=&quot;border:1px solid #8888aa; background:#f8f8f8; padding:0; font-size:90%;&quot;
|-
!#
!Candidate
!Party
!Election List
!Governorate
!Votes
|-
|1.||[[Nouri al-Maliki]]||[[Islamic Da'awa Party]]||[[State of Law Coalition]]||[[Baghdad Governorate|Baghdad]]||622,961&lt;ref name=&quot;Baghdad Vote&quot;&gt;[[Independent High Electoral Commission|IHEC]] [http://www.ihec-iq.com/ftpar/baghdad.pdf Baghdad Results]&lt;/ref&gt;
|-
|2.||[[Ayad Allawi]]||[[Iraqi National Accord]]||[[al-Iraqiyya]]||[[Baghdad Governorate|Baghdad]]||407,537&lt;ref name=&quot;Baghdad Vote&quot;/&gt;
|-
|3.||[[Usama al-Nujayfi]]||[[al-Hadba]]||[[al-Iraqiyya]]||[[Ninawa Governorate|Ninawa]]||274,741&lt;ref&gt;[[Independent High Electoral Commission|IHEC]] [http://www.ihec-iq.com/ftpar/nenawa.pdf Ninawa Results]&lt;/ref&gt;
|-
|4.||[[Tariq al-Hashemi]]||[[Renewal List]]||[[al-Iraqiyya]]||[[Baghdad Governorate|Baghdad]]||200,963&lt;ref name=&quot;Baghdad Vote&quot;/&gt;
|-
|5.||[[Ibrahim al-Jaafari]]||[[National Reform Trend]]||[[National Iraqi Alliance]]||[[Baghdad Governorate|Baghdad]]||101,053&lt;ref name=&quot;Baghdad Vote&quot;/&gt;
|-
|6.||[[Nawshirwan Mustafa]]||[[Gorran Movement]]||[[Gorran List]]||[[As Sulaymaniyah Governorate|Silemani]]||93,196&lt;ref name=&quot;Silemani Vote&quot;&gt;[[Independent High Electoral Commission|IHEC]] [http://www.ihec-iq.com/ftpar/sulaminea.pdf Silemani Results]&lt;/ref&gt;
|-
|7.||[[Rafi al-Issawi]]||[[National Future Gathering]]||[[al-Iraqiyya]]||[[al-Anbar Governorate|al-Anbar]]||83,145&lt;ref&gt;[[Independent High Electoral Commission|IHEC]] [http://www.ihec-iq.com/ftpar/anbar.pdf al-Anbar Results]&lt;/ref&gt;
|-
|8.||[[Baqir Jabr al-Zubeidi]]||[[Islamic Supreme Council of Iraq]]||[[National Iraqi Alliance]]||[[Baghdad Governorate|Baghdad]]||68,822&lt;ref name=&quot;Baghdad Vote&quot;/&gt;
|-
|9.||[[Khalid Shwani]]||[[Patriotic Union of Kurdistan]]&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://pukmedia.com/english/index.php?option=com_content&amp;task=view&amp;id=1404&amp;Itemid= |title=Shwani: We never relinquish rights of Kurdistani people |publisher=Pukmedia.com |date=2010-02-22 |accessdate=2010-08-21}}&lt;/ref&gt;||[[Kurdistani List]]||[[Kirkuk Governorate|Kerkuk]]||68,522&lt;ref name=&quot;Kerkuk Vote&quot;&gt;[[Independent High Electoral Commission|IHEC]] [http://www.ihec-iq.com/ftpar/karkuk.pdf Kerkuk Results]&lt;/ref&gt;
|-
|10.||[[Arshad al-Salihi]]||[[Iraqi Turkmen Front]] &lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://standardkurd.org/Direje_E.aspx?Cor=BirwrayNwseran&amp;Jimare=362 |title=Standard website |publisher=Standardkurd.org |date= |accessdate=2010-08-21}}&lt;/ref&gt;||[[al-Iraqiyya]]||[[Kirkuk Governorate|Kerkuk]]||59,732&lt;ref name=&quot;Kerkuk Vote&quot;/&gt;
|-
|11.||[[Ali Bapir]]||[[Islamic Group of Kurdistan]]||[[Islamic Group of Kurdistan|IGK List]]||[[Erbil Governorate|Hewler]]||50,116&lt;ref name=&quot;Hewler Vote&quot;&gt;[http://www.ihec-iq.com/ftpar/arbel.pdf Hewler Results]&lt;/ref&gt;
|}

===Fraud allegations===
Prior to the elections there were already claims that Prime Minister Nouri al-Maliki's list was planning to rig elections.&lt;ref name=&quot;atimes_suspicions&quot;&gt;{{citation | title= Suspicions swell as Iraq elections near | publisher= [[Asia Times]] | date= 2 March 2010 | url= http://www.atimes.com/atimes/Middle_East/LC02Ak01.html }}&lt;/ref&gt; The fact that the government printed 26 million ballots, 35% more than are needed for all eligible voters led to claims by Ayad Allawi and his al-Iraqiiya list that these ballots were going to be used to commit fraud.&lt;ref name=&quot;atimes_suspicions&quot;/&gt; According to the National Iraqi Alliance al-Maliki was abusing his powers as Prime Minister by distributing government land and plantations freely to tribal leaders to secure their votes, Maliki was also said to be giving expensive guns with gold emblems on them, to visitors.&lt;ref name=&quot;atimes_suspicions&quot;/&gt; Ibrahim al-Jaafari's [[Islah]] party accused the Maliki government of registering 800,000 fabricated names in rural areas and Baghdad so the government could use their names to vote in favour of Maliki while these people do not exist.&lt;ref name=&quot;atimes_suspicions&quot;/&gt; The Sadr Movement complained that the government was arresting and detaining their supporters in the days prior to the elections to prevent them from voting.&lt;ref name=&quot;atimes_suspicions&quot;/&gt;

Leaders of al-Iraqiyya listed a series of alleged violations by Maliki claiming some of their votes had been removed from boxes and replaced by other ballots. A spokesman from the alliance released this statement: &quot;Insistence in manipulating these elections forces us to question whether the possibility of fraudulent results would make the final results worthless. We will not stand by with our arms crossed,&quot; however analysts claimed Allawi might have listed these complaints for tactical reasons.&lt;ref name=&quot;fraud1&quot;&gt;{{citation | title= Early Iraq poll results suggest close contest | publisher= BBC News | date= 12 March 2010 | url= http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/8562570.stm }}&lt;/ref&gt; Iraqiyya candidate [[Inistar Allawi]] also accused the Kurdistan Alliance of fraud in Kirkuk.&lt;ref&gt;{{citation | title= Iraqi PM leads Baghdad elections | publisher= [[Irish Times]] | date= 13 March 2010 | url= http://www.irishtimes.com/newspaper/breaking/2010/0313/breaking12.html }}&lt;/ref&gt; On the other hand the Kurdish Gorran List alleged that Allawi's al-Iraqiya list had committed fraud in the city of Mosul.&lt;ref name=&quot;aina.org&quot;&gt;{{citation | title= Kurds Declare Victory in Iraq Elections | publisher= [[Assyrian International News Agency]] | date= 11 March 2010 | url= http://www.aina.org/news/20100310191005.htm }}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Ali al-Adeeb]], a candidate for Maliki's State of Law Coalition alleged an election official has manipulated election results in favour of a rival candidate.&lt;ref name=&quot;fraud_claims&quot;&gt;{{citation | title= Iraqi elections hit with claims of fraud by opposing parties | publisher= [[The Guardian]] | date= 16 March 2010 | url= http://www.guardian.co.uk/world/2010/mar/16/iraqi-election-vote-rigging-claims | first=Martin | last=Chulov | location=London}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Meanwhile the Iraqi National Alliance voiced concerns that the US was trying to manipulate the country's election results. INA candidate [[Entifadh Qanbar]] told [[Press TV]]: &quot;The concern is that how the ballots from each voting center are going to be processed in the computer center inside the Electoral Commission, the reason we are insisting on this issue is that we are afraid there is some sort of American intervention inside the Electoral Commission in processing these numbers and may be altering these numbers. We will not accept any election results without putting the ballots out to prove that the ballots have been processed and entered in the computer system in a proper way.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{citation | title= 'US might manipulate Iraq election results' | publisher= [[Press TV]] | date= 10 March 2010 | url= http://www.presstv.com/detail.aspx?id=120547&amp;sectionid=351020201 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

Iraqi Kurdish politician [[Khalid Shenawi]], accused election workers in Arab areas in the city of Kirkuk of manipulating the results in Allawi's favour. Meanwhile Arab and Turkmen politicians accused the Kurds of stacking voter rolls in their favour.&lt;ref name=&quot;fraud_delays&quot;&gt;{{citation | title= Iraq poll results delayed again, amid mounting fraud claims | publisher= [[Earth Times]] | date= 15 March 2010 | url= http://www.earthtimes.org/articles/show/314210,iraq-poll-results-delayed-again-amid-mounting-fraud-claims--summary.html }}&lt;/ref&gt; Shenawi said that loudspeakers of mosques were used to encourage people to vote and expressed doubt over the 93% turnout in Kirkuk's Arab districts al-Zab, al-Abbasi, al-Riad.&lt;ref name=&quot;niqash.org&quot;&gt;{{citation | title= claim and counterclaim in kirkuk | publisher= Niqash | date= 18 March 2010 | url= http://niqash.org/content.php?contentTypeID=75&amp;id=2636&amp;lang=0 }}&lt;/ref&gt; In the Arabic neighbourhood of al-Houija there was even a turnout of 130%.&lt;ref&gt;{{citation | title= 'Grootschalige fraude in Kerkuk' | language= [[Dutch language|Dutch]] | publisher= Rudaw.NL | date= 18 March 2010 | url= http://www.rudaw.nl/index.php?option=com_content&amp;view=article&amp;id=3337:koerden-fraude-in-kerkuk&amp;catid=153:verkiezingen-irak&amp;Itemid=566 }}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Ala Talabani]] said the Kurdistani List had submitted 40 notices of appeal against fraud by al-Iraqiya. Turkmen nationalist politician [[Arshid Al-Salihi]], who stood as part of the al-Iraqiya list however claimed they had proof of al-Iraqiyya votes being thrown in the garbage, alleging fraud by the Kurdistan List. However, contradictingly he also claimed that &quot;Everyone who loses in elections accuses their rivals of fraud&quot; in reference to claims by the Kurdistan Alliance.&lt;ref name=&quot;niqash.org&quot;/&gt;

Pro-Western candidate [[Mithal al-Alusi]], who's [[Mithal al-Alusi List]] won one seat during last elections for Mithal al-Alusi himself, claimed the elections were rigged against liberals like himself, by [[Iran]] and [[Saudi Arabia]] as he lost his seat in parliament. Alusi claimed there were major discrepancies between the vote count according IHEC and his own monitors. He also claimed village directors prevented women from voting in rural areas. He called on the United States to launch an investigation to the allegedly fixed election results.&lt;ref&gt;{{citation | title= Mithal al-Alusi, Iraq's Maverick, Charges Iraqi Elections Were Corrupt | publisher= Huffington Post | date= 3 April 2010 | url= http://www.huffingtonpost.com/heather-robinson/mithal-al-alusi-iraqs-mav_b_524477.html }}&lt;/ref&gt;

After an appeal by incumbent Prime Minister Nouri al-Maliki a recount of the votes in Baghdad was ordered on 19 April 2010.&lt;ref name=&quot;baghdad-recount&quot;/&gt; The recount began on 3 May 2010.&lt;ref&gt;{{citation | url=http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/middle_east/8657705.stm | work=[[BBC News]] | title=Iraqi election recount under way | date=3 May 2010 | accessdate=5 May 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; On 14 May IHEC announced that after 11,298 ballot boxes had been recounted, there was no sign of fraud or violations.&lt;ref name=&quot;no-fraud&quot;/&gt;

==Analysis==
Some analysts argued that a new government would need to have at least a component that represents minority ethnicities in order to try and &quot;heal old sectarian wounds.&quot; This would mean excluding Iraqiya could anger its Sunni vote-base and &quot;reinvigorate a Sunni backlash.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;[http://english.aljazeera.net/news/middleeast/2010/11/201011811522332422.html Iraqi leaders begin coalition talks - Middle East - Al Jazeera English&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;

==Government formation==
In the aftermath of the election, great attention was given to the decision on who should be the next Iraqi PM. Both al-Iraqiyya's Allawi and the State of Law coalition's al-Maliki laid claim to the post, so it was seen as up to the Kurdish parties and the [[Iraqi National Alliance]] to decide this matter.

One of the two main components of the INA, the [[Supreme Iraqi Islamic Council]], stated it would not join any government that did not include former PM Allawi; the other main component, the [[Sadrist Movement]], held an unofficial referendum on 2 and 3 April 2010 on who should be PM. The possible choices were Allawi, al-Maliki, former PM Ibrahim al-Jaafari, [[Adel Abdel Mahdi]] from the SIIC, and [[Jaafar al-Sadr]] (a little-known MP from al-Maliki's [[Dawa Party]], son of its ideological founder [[Mohammad Baqir al-Sadr]]).&lt;ref&gt;{{citation | url=http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/middle_east/8601292.stm | work=[[BBC News]] | title=How Sadrist vote could anoint new Iraq PM | date=2 April 2010 | accessdate=5 May 2010 | first=Jim | last=Muir}}&lt;/ref&gt; On 7 April 2010, results were announced, according to which al-Jaafari had won with 24% of the vote.&lt;ref&gt;{{citation | url= http://english.people.com.cn/90001/90777/90854/6943390.html | work= [[People's Daily]] | title= Ex-Shiite PM wins Sadr grouping referendum for future PM | date= 7 April 2010 | accessdate= 26 May 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; Jaafari had originally been a member of al-Maliki's [[Dawa Party]], but had left it in 2008 to found his own party, the [[National Reform Trend]], as whose lone MP he was elected in this election.

The full results of the 1.43 million ballots cast in the unofficial Sadrist referendum were as follows:&lt;ref&gt;{{citation | url= http://www.presstv.ir/detail.aspx?id=122782&amp;sectionid=351020201 | work= [[Press TV]] | title= Ex-Iraqi PM Jaafari wins Sadrist referendum | date= 8 April 2010 | accessdate= 26 May 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{citation | url=http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/middle_east/8609722.stm | work=[[BBC News]] | title=Iraqi water still muddy after Sadr vote | date=8 April 2010 | accessdate=5 May 2010 | first=Jim | last=Muir}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{citation | url= http://www.boston.com/news/world/middleeast/articles/2010/04/08/sadr_followers_spurn_front_runners_in_iraq/ | work= [[boston.com]] | title= Sadr followers spurn front-runners in Iraq | date= 8 April 2010 | accessdate= 26 May 2010 | first=Hamid | last=Ahmed}}&lt;/ref&gt;

{|width=&quot;70%&quot; class=&quot;wikitable sortable collapsible collapsed&quot;
|-
!Candidate
!Party
!Election List
!Percentage
|-
|'''[[Ibrahim al-Jaafari]]'''||[[National Reform Trend]] ||[[National Iraqi Alliance]]||24%
|-
|'''[[Jaafar al-Sadr]]'''||[[Islamic Da'awa Party]]||[[State of Law Coalition]]||23%
|-
|[[Qusay al-Suhail]]||[[Sadr Movement]]||[[National Iraqi Alliance]]||17%
|-
|'''[[Nouri al-Maliki]]'''||[[Islamic Da'awa Party]]||[[State of Law Coalition]]||10%
|-
|'''[[Ayad Allawi]]'''||[[Iraqi National Accord]] ||[[al-Iraqiyya]]||9%
|-
|[[Baha Araji]]||[[Sadr Movement]]||[[National Iraqi Alliance]]||5%
|-
|[[Ahmad Chalabi]]||[[Iraqi National Congress]]||[[National Iraqi Alliance]]||3%
|-
|'''[[Adil Abd al-Mahdi]]'''||[[Islamic Supreme Council of Iraq]]||[[National Iraqi Alliance]]||2%
|-
|[[Rafi al-Issawi]]||[[National Future Gathering]]||[[al-Iraqiyya]]||2%
|-
|Other||—||—||5%
|}

After months of negotiations the National Iraqi Alliance and the State of Law Coalition agreed to merging into one parliamentary bloc of 159 seats, the bloc would be 4 seats short of a majority but would have the right for government formation.&lt;ref&gt;{{citation | url= http://www.rferl.org/content/Iraqs_Shiite_Announce_Alliance/2032919.html | work= [[Radio Free Europe/Radio Liberty]] | title= Iraq's Leading Shi'ite Blocs Agree To Form Parliamentary Coalition | date= 4 May 2010 | accessdate= 26 May 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; However the bloc has to date still not appointed a prime ministerial candidate.&lt;ref&gt;{{citation | url= http://www.ft.com/cms/s/0/e68e5eca-6d8b-11df-bde2-00144feabdc0.html | work= [[Financial Times]] | title= Iraq court ratifies election results | date= 1 June 2010 }}&lt;/ref&gt; The bloc, called the [[National Alliance (Iraq)|National Alliance]], was formally formed on 11 June 2010. The new parliament opened on 14 June 2010.&lt;ref name=&quot;par_open&quot;&gt;{{cite news| url=http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/world/middle_east/10294271.stm | work=BBC News | title=Iraq merger forms big Shia bloc | date=11 June 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; However, talks between the National Iraqi Alliance and al-Iraqiyya continued.&lt;ref&gt;{{citation | url= http://www.businessweek.com/news/2010-07-20/iraq-s-allawi-sadr-meet-in-syria-for-cabinet-talks.html | work= [[Business Week]] | title= Iraq’s Allawi, Sadr Meet in Syria for Cabinet Talks | date= 20 July 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; On 3 September 2010 the National Iraqi Alliance nominated [[Adil Abdul-Mahdi]] as the coalition's nominee for Prime Minister, making it unclear which candidate the National Alliance bloc would ultimately choose.&lt;ref&gt;{{citation | url= http://articles.latimes.com/2010/sep/03/world/la-fg-iraq-politics-20100904 | work= [[Los Angeles Times]] | title= Maliki's chief Shiite rivals choose candidate to vie for his job | date= 3 September 2010 | accessdate= 9 September 2010 | first1=Ned | last1=Parker | first2=Raheem | last2=Salman}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The President of Iraqi Kurdistan Massoud Barzani announced the four major Kurdish lists: the Kurdistani List, the Gorran List, the Kurdistan Islamic Union and the Islamic Group of Kurdistan agreed to merging into one parliamentary bloc of 57 seats, called the Coalition of Kurdistan Lists or [[Kurdistan Blocs Coalition]] (KBC).&lt;ref&gt;{{citation | url= http://www.kurdishglobe.net/displayArticle.jsp?id=A3FFBEC74FEA824E413590B68F5A8C4B | work= [[The Kurdish Globe]] | title= President Barzani announces Coalition of Kurdistan Lists | date= 12 May 2010 | accessdate= 26 May 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; On 30 October, however the Nawshirwan Mustafa's Gorran Movement (announced their withdrawal from the KBC due to a dispute between Gorran and the ruling KDP-PUK coalition in the Kurdistan Autonomous Republic. This reduced the bloc to 49 seats&lt;ref&gt;{{citation | url= http://www.aknews.com/en/aknews/4/192009/ | work= AKNews ([http://www.aknews.com/ www.aknews.com]) | title= Gorran announced withdrawal from the KBC | date= 30 October 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;
In August the KBC announced 19 demands which would have to be agreed upon by al-Maliki or Allawi for them to join their government.&lt;ref&gt;{{citation | url= http://www.ekurd.net/mismas/articles/misc2010/8/state4137.htm | work= Kurd Net ([http://www.ekurd.net/ www.ekurd.net]) | title= Kurds send 19 conditions to Allawi and Maliki | date= 18 August 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; The Islamic Supreme Council of Iraq then agreed to all 19 demands.&lt;ref&gt;{{citation | url= http://gulfanalysis.wordpress.com/2010/10/29/for-sale-al-iraq-market-update/ | work= Iraq and Gulf Analysis ([http://gulfanalysis.wordpress.com gulfanalysis.wordpress.com]) | title= For Sale: Al-Iraq | date= 29 October 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; Incumbent Prime Minister Nouri al-Maliki agreed to 18 out of 19 demands (including implementation of [[Article 140 of the Iraqi Constitution|article 140]]), only disagreeing with the demand that the government were to resign if the Kurdistan Alliance withdraws.&lt;ref&gt;{{citation | url= http://theiraqidinar.com/2010/10/06/malikis-dawa-party-surprised-and-agrees-to-all-conditions-of-the-kurdistan-alliance/ | work= Dinar Daddy's Tidbits ([http://theiraqidinar.com/ theiraqidinar.com]) | title= Maliki’s Dawa Party, Surprised and Agrees to All Conditions of the Kurdistan Alliance | date= 6 October 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; Al-Iraqiya, however, rejected 9 of the Kurdish demands, including the demands for a Kurdish presidency, Iraqi government funding of the Peshmerga and for the [[Kirkuk status referendum|implementation of article 140 of the Iraqi constitution]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.ekurd.net/mismas/articles/misc2010/11/state4330.htm Al-Iraqiya rejected 9 out of 19 Kurdish demands, says lawmaker]&lt;/ref&gt;

Incumbent Prime Minister Nuri al-Maliki also visited Iran amid drawn out coalition talks.&lt;ref&gt;{{citation | url= http://www.almanar.com.lb/newssite/NewsDetails.aspx?id=158247&amp;language=en | work= [[Al-Manar]] | title= Maliki to Visit Iran as Coalition Talks Hot Up | date= 16 October 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; The trip came amid reports from the ''[[Los Angeles Times]]'' and the ''[[The Guardian|Guardian]]'' that Iran had been directly involved trying to bring about a [[Shia]] coalition by convincing [[Muqtada al-Sadr]] to back an al-Maliki-led government, and thus increase Iran's influence in Iraq against those supported by the [[West]]. Iyad Allawi's bloc, which won a plurality, would then be sidelined. As such Allawi claimed to ''[[CNN]]'' that Iran was &quot;trying to wreak havoc on the region, [by] trying to destabilise the region by destabilising Iraq, and destabilising Lebanon and destabilising the Palestinian issue. This is where unfortunately Iraq and the rest of the greater Mideast is falling victim to these terrorists who are definitely Iran-financed and supported by various governments in the region.&quot; His deputy was also alleged to have said &quot;Iranian involvement amounts to a takeover of Iraq.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{citation | url= http://english.aljazeera.net/news/middleeast/2010/10/2010101854658131883.html | work= [[Al Jazeera English]] | title= Iraqi PM courts Iran during visit | date= 19 October 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; While the West expressed worry about Iran's growing influence and potential influence in Iraq, Iran's [[Supreme Leader]] Ayatollah [[Ali Khamenei]] said, in responding to al-Maliki description that mutual relations were strategic and amicable, &quot;Despite relative stability in Iraq, the country is still suffering from insecurity and part of this insecurity is resulted from the pressures that are exerted by some powers whose political interests lie in creating insecurity in Iraq.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{citation | url= http://www.almanar.com.lb/newssite/NewsDetails.aspx?id=158421&amp;language=en | work= [[Al-Manar]] | title= Sayyed Khamenei to Maliki: West Benefits from Iraq's Insecurity | date= 18 October 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; Following his visit to Iran, al-Maliki also visited Syria, Jordan and Egypt, where he said a new government could be imminent as &quot;discussions are taking place, we are now at the end of the tunnel, at the end of the road. If God allows, this government will emerge soon.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{citation | url= http://www.almanar.com.lb/newssite/NewsDetails.aspx?id=158876&amp;language=en | work= [[Al-Manar]] | title= Iraq PM Maliki Predicts New Government 'Very Soon' | date= 20 October 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; A few days later, Iranian President [[Mahmoud Ahmadinejad]] talked to his Iraqi counterpart [[Jalal Talabani]] and said he &quot;hope[s] that with the formation of a new Iraqi government, bilateral ties will expand in different areas, especially in the economic and political fields.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{citation | url= http://www.almanar.com.lb/newssite/NewsDetails.aspx?id=159436&amp;language=en | work= [[Al-Manar]] | title= Iran, Iraq Leaders Discuss Boosting Ties: State TV | date= 25 October 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Saudi Arabia also offered to host an all-party conference in November to break the deadlock in government formation. However, al-Maliki's bloc turned down the proposal amid concerns over foreign interference.&lt;ref&gt;[http://english.aljazeera.net/news/middleeast/2010/10/2010103183433616942.html Iraqi Shia bloc rejects Saudi offer - Middle East - Al Jazeera English&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt; The National Alliance issued a statement saying: &quot;Though we express our appreciation to Saudi Arabia for its concern about the situation in Iraq and its willingness to provide support, we would like to confirm Iraqi leaders are continuing their meetings to reach a national consensus.&quot; a statement issued by the alliance, said. The Kurdish Alliance also reportedly supported the statement. While Iraqiya welcomed the Saudi initiative. &quot;We ask all political blocs to welcome the initiative, preventing Iraq's security situation from deteriorating.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.almanar.com.lb/newssite/NewsDetails.aspx?id=160279&amp;language=en Al-ManarTV:: Several Iraqi Blocs Reject Saudi Offer to Host Talks in Riyadh 31/10/2010&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt; The United States also called for an &quot;inclusive government.&quot; It said that Allawi and others from Iraqiya, as well as all the &quot;winning blocs&quot; should hold &quot;leadership posts&quot; in a new government.&lt;ref&gt;[http://english.aljazeera.net/news/middleeast/2010/11/20101111194314466785.html US urges inclusive Iraq government - Middle East - Al Jazeera English&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:Iraq Talabani w al-Nujeifi 11nov10 lowres.jpg|thumb|right|250px|Iraq's President Jalal Talabani, center left, shakes hands with newly elected speaker of parliament, Osama al-Nujayfi, center right, during a session of parliament on 11 November 2010]]

In early October the National Alliance (consisting of State of Law and the NIA) nominated Nouri al-Maliki as their Prime Minister candidate after [[Muqtada al-Sadr]] and al-Maliki struck a deal together.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.muslimnews.co.uk/news/news.php?sub=2044 The Muslim News&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.alsumaria.tv/en/Iraq-News/1-54089-Sadr-Front-to-accept-Al-Maliki-win.html Sadr Front to accept Al-Maliki win | Iraq News | Alsumaria Iraqi Satellite TV Network&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt; This however led to a split within the National Alliance (159 seats) as the ISCI-bloc (which including [[Badr Organisation|Badr]] and [[Hezbollah Movement in Iraq|Hezbollah]] holds 19 seats), the [[Fadhila|Islamic Fadhila Party]] (6 seats) and the [[Gathering of Justice and Unity]] (1 seat)&lt;ref&gt;[http://gulfanalysis.wordpress.com/2010/10/13/three-competing-paths-to-the-next-iraqi-government/ Three Competing Paths to the Next Iraqi Government « Iraq and Gulf Analysis&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt; left the alliance to create an alliance with Ayad Allawi's al-Iraqiyya (91 seats).&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.thenation.com/blog/155337/iraq-new-alliance-takes-shape-against-maliki-sadr-bloc Iraq: New Alliance Takes Shape Against Maliki-Sadr Bloc | The Nation&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt; The Iraqiyya led bloc nominated prominent ISCI politician and at the time Vice-President Adil Abd al-Mahdi as Prime Minister.&lt;ref&gt;[http://gulfanalysis.wordpress.com/2010/10/10/iraqiyya-and-the-surprise-endorsement-of-abd-al-mahdi-some-legal-problems/ Iraqiyya and the “Surprise” Endorsement of Abd al-Mahdi: Some Legal Problems « Iraq and Gulf Analysis&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt; Meanwhile the two minor Sunni blocs, [[Unity Alliance of Iraq]] and the [[Iraqi Accord Front]] merged into one 10-seat bloc, called the [[Center Current]], which entered into negotiations with both major blocs for coalition partnerships.&lt;ref&gt;[http://aawsat.com/english/news.asp?section=1&amp;id=22954 King Abdullah's Initiative is Sincere- Iraqi Interior Minister Asharq Alawsat Newspaper (English)&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt; However, both blocs needed the support of Kurdish parties to gain a parliamentary majority, this support was eventually given to al-Maliki's bloc after he agreed to all 19 Kurdish demands, which led to the re-uniting of the National Alliance.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.rferl.org/content/Iraqs_Kurdish_Bloc_Looks_For_Coalition_Offer/2185167.html Iraq's Kurdish Bloc Looks For Coalition Offer - Radio Free Europe / Radio Liberty © 2010&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;

On 24 October, the [[Supreme Court of Iraq]] ordered the parliament to reconvene and elect a new speaker.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.almanar.com.lb/newssite/NewsDetails.aspx?id=159384&amp;language=en Al-ManarTV:: Iraq Court Orders Parliament To Convene, Choose Speaker 24/10/2010&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title=Iraq's Supreme Court orders parliament members to convene|url=http://www.washingtonpost.com/wp-dyn/content/article/2010/10/24/AR2010102403136.html|date=25 October 2010|newspaper=[[Washington Post]]|first=Ernesto|last=Londono}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title=Iraq parliament ordered to get back to work|url=http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/world-middle-east-11615047|date=24 October 2010|newspaper=[[BBC News]]}}&lt;/ref&gt; The court ordered a parliamentary speaker to be chosen on 8 November&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.almanar.com.lb/newssite/NewsDetails.aspx?id=160770&amp;language=en Al-ManarTV:: Iraq Parliament to Elect Speaker on Monday 03/11/2010&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt; The day before the vote for parliamentary speaker, a power-sharing accord was agreed to that would allow al-Maliki to continues as PM. As talks to form a new government reached a climax al-Maliki and Allawi were scheduled to attend a ceremony in Arbil, the capital of the autonomous region of Kurdistan, to make a formal announcement in regards to the agreement. Iraqiya MP Jamal al-Butikh then said an agreement was reached after assurances that &quot;no political decision would be made without its agreement.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.almanar.com.lb/newssite/NewsDetails.aspx?id=161315&amp;language=en Al-ManarTV:: Finally, Iraqi Rivals Clinch Deal: Maliki to Remain PM, Allawi to Choose Speaker 07/11/2010&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt; At one point, Iraqiya staged a walkout after al-Nujaifi declined a request to vote on the removal of three parliament members' names because of affiliation to the deposed [[Saddam Hussein]]'s Ba'ath party.&lt;ref name=autogenerated1&gt;[http://english.aljazeera.net/news/middleeast/2010/11/2010111273623573512.html Iraq pact heralds new political era - Middle East - Al Jazeera English&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt; They later said the walkout was a misunderstanding.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news| url=http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/world-middle-east-11750780 | work=BBC News | title=Iraqi parties confirm commitment to power-sharing deal | date=13 November 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;

During the parliamentary session on 11 November, [[Osama al-Nujaifi]], a Sunni Arab from Iraqiya's [[al-Hadba Party]] was elected to be parliamentary speaker, with prominent Sadrist leader [[Qusay al-Suhail]] chosen as his first deputy and [[Arif Tayfur]] (a leading member of Massoud Barzani's Kurdistan Democratic Party&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.usf-iraq.com/?option=com_content&amp;task=view&amp;id=19&amp;Itemid=10 Leaders | United States Forces - Iraq&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;) was re-elected to the post of second deputy speaker.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.iraqoilreport.com/politics/national-politics/maliki-talbani-in-after-iraqiya-walk-outs-5126/ Maliki, Talibani in after Iraqiya walk-outs - Iraq Oil Report&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt; Patriotic Union of Kurdistan leader [[Jalal Talabani]] was re-elected as President, al-Maliki was re-elected as prime minister and Allawi had reportedly agreed to head a new security council.&lt;ref name=autogenerated1 /&gt; [[Massoud Barzani]], the president of Kurdistan region said that it was a great victory for the Iraqi people, which came at a late stage.&lt;ref&gt;[http://english.aljazeera.net/news/middleeast/2010/11/201011119329394717.html Power-sharing deal reached in Iraq - Middle East - Al Jazeera English&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt; A third session of the new parliament on 21 November still did not come to an agreement on who would run the new government.&lt;ref&gt;[http://english.aljazeera.net/news/middleeast/2010/11/20101121133148855591.html Iraqi parliament holds new session - Middle East - Al Jazeera English&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;

===New parliamentary blocs===
During the government formation process numerous lists fused together to form larger parliamentary blocs.
{|width=&quot;100%&quot; class=&quot;wikitable sortable collapsible collapsed&quot;
|-
!Parliamentary Bloc
!Alliances
!Leader
!Seats
!Percentage
!Source
|-
|[[National Alliance (Iraq)|National Alliance]]||[[State of Law Coalition]],&lt;br&gt;[[National Iraqi Alliance]]||[[Ibrahim al-Jaafari]]||159||48.92%||[http://www.rferl.org/content/Iraqs_Shiite_Announce_Alliance/2032919.html]
|-
|[[al-Iraqiya]]||[[al-Iraqiyya]]||[[Hasan Khalaf al-Jibburi]]||91||28%||
|-
|[[Kurdistan Blocs Coalition]]||[[Kurdistani List]],&lt;br&gt;[[Kurdistan Islamic Union]],&lt;br&gt;[[Islamic Group of Kurdistan]]||[[Fuad Masum]]||49||15.08%||[http://www.aknews.com/en/aknews/4/192009/]
|-
|[[Center Current]]||[[al-Tawafuq]],&lt;br&gt;[[Unity Alliance of Iraq]]||[[Iyad al-Samara'i]]||10||3.08%||[http://aawsat.com/english/news.asp?section=1&amp;id=22954]
|-
|[[Gorran Movement|Gorran Bloc]]||[[Gorran Movement]]||[[Shorsh Haji]]&lt;ref&gt;[http://azady.nl/?p=13513 Al-Iraqiya brengt oppositie en Talabani dichterbij elkaar | Azady.nl&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;||8||2.46%||[http://www.aknews.com/en/aknews/4/192009/]
|-
|[[National Rafidain List]]||[[Assyrian Democratic Movement]]||[[Yonadam Kanna]]||3||0.92%||[http://gulfanalysis.wordpress.com/2010/03/25/the-pro-kurdish-minority-vote/]
|-
|[[Chaldean Syriac Assyrian Popular Council|CSAPC]]||[[Chaldean Syriac Assyrian Popular Council|Chaldean Syriac Assyrian&lt;br&gt;Popular Council]]||[[Sarkis Aghajan]]||2||0.65%||[http://gulfanalysis.wordpress.com/2010/03/25/the-pro-kurdish-minority-vote/]
|-
|Independents||—||—||3||—||
|}

===New government===
{{Citations missing|date=July 2011}}
{{main|Al Maliki II Government}}
On December 22, parliament unanimously approved al-Maliki's new government. Twenty-nine ministers were approved, including Shias, Sunnis and Kurds. In reaction, al-Maliki issued his new government's programme and also vowed to make Iraq a &quot;truly democratic state that respects human rights.&quot; However, he criticised the lack of any female nominees and warned that &quot;given the circumstances it has been created under, this government does not satisfy the people nor the needs of our country. The effort and the will to make it work in the best possible way it can is there.&quot;

The new government would consist of al-Maliki as acting Minister of Defence, Interior and National Security &quot;until appropriate candidates are found.&quot; Former Oil Minister Hussein Shahristani would become Deputy Prime Minister for Energy. The former Deputy Prime Minister Rafi al-Issawi would become Finance Minister. Foreign Minister [[Hoshyar Zebari]] will continue in his post. [[Saleh al-Mutlaq]] was also controversially appointed a Deputy Prime Minister after a ban on him taking part in politics as a former [[Ba'ath Party|Baath]]ist. Thirteen more ministerial posts had acting ministers as al-Maliki said &quot;The formation of national unity government in Iraq is a difficult and hard task because we need to find place in the government for all those who participated and won in the elections.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;[http://english.aljazeera.net/news/middleeast/2010/12/201012211373655244.html Iraq gets a new government - Middle East - Al Jazeera English&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;

{{Al-Maliki II Government}}

;Repercussions
Following the formation of a government and his blocs strong showing [[Muqtada al-Sadr]] returned to Najaf from exile in Iran in early January 2011.&lt;ref&gt;http://english.aljazeera.net/news/middleeast/2011/01/2011151418794320.html&lt;/ref&gt;

====Aftermath====
In July 2011 al-Maliki agreed to cut 12 ministries from his cabinet, which was a compromise from his originial proposal to cut 16 ministerial portfolios. The agreement comes amid debate over whether or not a US military contingent would remain beyond a 31 December, 2011 deadline for their withdrawal.&lt;ref&gt;http://english.aljazeera.net/news/middleeast/2011/07/201173091043376586.html&lt;/ref&gt;

==See also==
*[[National Pact (Lebanon)]]

==References==
{{Commons category|2010 Iraqi parliamentary election}}
{{reflist|colwidth=30em}}

{{Iraqi elections}}
{{Use dmy dates|date=November 2010}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Iraqi Parliamentary Election, 2010}}
[[Category:2010 elections in Asia]]
[[Category:2010 elections in Iraq]]
[[Category:2010 in Iraq|Legislative election]]

[[ar:الانتخابات البرلمانية العراقية، 2010]]
[[de:Irakische Parlamentswahlen 2010]]
[[fa:انتخابات مجلس نمایندگان عراق ۲۰۱۰]]
[[fr:Élections législatives irakiennes de 2010]]
[[pl:Wybory parlamentarne w Iraku w 2010 roku]]
[[pt:Eleições parlamentares no Iraque em 2010]]
[[ru:Парламентские выборы в Ираке (2010)]]
[[ckb:ھەڵبژاردنی ئەنجوومەنی نوێنەرانی ئێراق، ٢٠١٠]]
[[sv:Parlamentsvalet i Irak 2010]]
[[tr:2010 Irak parlamento seçimleri]]
[[uk:Парламентські вибори в Іраку 2010]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
