<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="16855" ns="0" title="Kansas State University"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Infobox university
|name = Kansas State University 
|image_name = Kansas State University seal.png
|motto = Rule by Obeying Nature's Laws
|established = 1863
|type = [[Public university|Public]], [[State university system (United States)|State]], [[Land-grant university|Land-grant]], [[University]]
|president = [[Kirk Schulz|Kirk H. Schulz]]
|city = [[Manhattan, Kansas|Manhattan]]
|state = [[Kansas]]
|country = [[United States|U.S.]]
|students = 23,863 (Fall 2011)&lt;ref name = Enrollment&gt;{{cite web | title = UP AGAIN: K-STATE SETS NEW ENROLLMENT RECORD, SURPASSING LAST FALL'S RECORD YEAR | url = http://www.k-state.edu/media/newsreleases/sept11/fallenroll92711.html | format = English | accessdate = 2011-09-27}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|undergrad = 19,205&lt;ref name= Factbook&gt;{{cite web | title =Kansas State University Fact Book 2010 | url =http://www.k-state.edu/pa/statinfo/factbook/student/totdemo.pdf | format = English | accessdate =2011-08-15}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|postgrad = 3,921&lt;ref name= Factbook/&gt;
|faculty = 1,251&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | title =Kansas State University Fact Book 2010 | url =http://www.k-state.edu/pa/statinfo/factbook/faculty/totaldemo.pdf | format = English | accessdate =2011-08-15}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|endowment = [[United States dollar|$]]277.6 million&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | title = 2010 NACUBO Endowment Study  | publisher = National Association of College and University Business Officers  
|url = http://www.nacubo.org/Documents/research/2010NCSE_Public_Tables_Endowment_Market_Values_Final.pdf  | format = PDF  | accessdate = 2011-04-30}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|campus= [[College town]]&lt;br/&gt;[[urban area|Urban]]; 668 acres (main campus)
|athletics =[[NCAA Division I]]&lt;br/&gt;[[Big 12 Conference]]
|sports = 14 Varsity Teams
|nickname = [[Kansas State Wildcats|Wildcats]] 
|colors = {{color box|#461D7C}} [[Purple (color)|Royal purple]]
|affiliations = [[Association of Public and Land-Grant Universities|APLU]], [[Association of Southeast Asian Institutions of Higher Learning|ASAIHL]]
|website = [http://www.k-state.edu/ www.k-state.edu]
|logo = 
|}}
'''Kansas State University''', commonly shortened to '''K-State''', is an institution of higher learning located in [[Manhattan, Kansas|Manhattan]], [[Kansas]], in the [[United States]].  Kansas State is the oldest public university in the state of Kansas, and saw a record high enrollment of 23,588 students for the Fall 2011 semester.&lt;ref name = Enrollment/&gt;

A branch campus is located in [[Salina, Kansas]], housing the [[Kansas State University - Salina|College of Technology and Aviation]].  Another branch campus, known as the Olathe Innovation Campus, is presently under construction in [[Olathe, Kansas]].  When completed, the Olathe facility will be the academic research presence within the Kansas Bioscience Park, and will research bioenergy, animal health, plant science and food safety and security.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | title = K-State Olathe Innovation Campus, Inc. | url = http://kstateoic.ksu.edu/ | format = English  | accessdate = 2009-04-30}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The university is classified as a research university with high research (RU/H) by the [[Carnegie Classification of Institutions of Higher Education]].

== History ==
Kansas State University, originally named '''Kansas State Agricultural College''', was founded on February 16, 1863, during the [[American Civil War]], as a [[land-grant university|land-grant institution]] under the [[Morrill Land-Grant Colleges Act|Morrill Act]].&lt;ref name=Willard&gt;{{cite book | last = Willard | first = Julius | title = History of Kansas State College of Agriculture and Applied Science | publisher = Kansas State College Press | year = 1940 | url = http://hearth.library.cornell.edu/cgi/t/text/pageviewer-idx?c=hearth;cc=hearth;rgn=full%20text;idno=5725255;didno=5725255;view=image;seq=0003;node=5725255%3A3 }}&lt;/ref&gt; The school was the first land-grant college created under the Morrill Act.&lt;ref name=Willard/&gt;&lt;ref name= Nation&gt;{{Cite journal | title = The National Schools of Science | journal = The Nation | pages = 409 | date = November 21, 1867 | url = http://books.google.com/?id=Mf0xAQAAIAAJ&amp;pg=PA409&amp;lpg=PA409&amp;dq=land+grant+kansas+february+16,+1863+pennsylvania+April#v=onepage&amp;q=land%20grant%20kansas%20february%2016%2C%201863%20pennsylvania%20April&amp;f=false | postscript = &lt;!-- Bot inserted parameter. Either remove it; or change its value to &quot;.&quot; for the cite to end in a &quot;.&quot;, as necessary. --&gt;{{inconsistent citations}} }}&lt;/ref&gt; K-State is the fourth-oldest school in the [[Big 12 Conference]] and the oldest public university in the state of Kansas.

The effort to establish the school began in 1861, when [[Kansas]] was admitted to the [[United States of America|United States]].  One of the new state [[Kansas Legislature|legislature's]] top priorities involved establishing a state university. That year, the delegation from Manhattan introduced a bill to convert the old [[Blue Mont Central College]] (a private college incorporated in Manhattan in 1858) into the state university.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | last = Willard | first = Julius | title = Bluemont Central College, the Forerunner of Kansas State College | journal = Kansas Historical Quarterly | date = May 1945 | url = http://www.kshs.org/publicat/khq/1945/45_6_willard.htm | accessdate = 2008-01-29}}&lt;/ref&gt;  But the bill establishing the university in Manhattan was controversially [[veto]]ed by Governor [[Charles L. Robinson]] of Lawrence, and an attempt to override the veto in the Legislature failed by two votes.&lt;ref name=Griffin&gt;{{cite web| last =Griffin | first =C.S. | title =The University of Kansas and the Years of Frustration, 1854–64 | url =http://www.kshs.org/publicat/khq/1966/66_1_griffin.htm | accessdate =2006-10-06}}&lt;/ref&gt;  In 1862, another bill to make Manhattan the site of the state university failed by one vote.&lt;ref name=Griffin/&gt;  Finally, upon the third attempt on February 16, 1863, the state accepted Manhattan's offer to donate the Blue Mont College building and grounds and established the state's land-grant college at the site – the institution that would become Kansas State University.&lt;ref name=Griffin/&gt;

When the college opened for its first session on September 2, 1863, it became only the [[List of mixed-sex colleges and universities in the United States|second public institution of higher learning to admit women and men equally]] in the United States.  Enrollment for the first session totaled 52 students: 26 men and 26 women.&lt;ref name=Willard/&gt;

=== 19th century ===
[[File:Kansas State University 1878.jpg|thumb|The college in 1878]]
The early years of the institution witnessed debate over whether the college should provide a focused agricultural education or a full [[liberal arts]] education. During this era, the tenor of the school shifted with the tenure of university presidents.  For example, President [[John Alexander Anderson|John A. Anderson]] (1873–1879) favored a limited education and President [[George Fairchild|George T. Fairchild]] (1879–1897) favored a classic liberal education.&lt;ref name=Willard/&gt;&lt;ref name=Cyclopedia&gt;{{cite book | title = Kansas: A Cyclopedia of State History | publisher = Standard Publishing Co. | year = 1912 | url = http://skyways.lib.ks.us/genweb/archives/1912/a/agricultural_college.html | accessdate = 2009-01-13}}&lt;/ref&gt;  Fairchild was credited with saying, &quot;Our college exists not so much to make men farmers as to make farmers men.&quot;&lt;ref name=Willard/&gt;

During this era, in 1873, Kansas State helped pioneer the academic teaching of [[home economics]] for women, becoming one of the first two colleges to offer the program of study.&lt;ref name=HomeEc&gt;{{cite book | last = Craig | first = Hazel | last2 = Stover | first2 = Blanche | title = The History of Home Economics | year = 1946 | url = http://hearth.library.cornell.edu/cgi/t/text/pageviewer-idx?c=hearth;cc=hearth;rgn=full%20text;idno=5725268;didno=5725268;view=image;seq=7;node=5725268%3A5;page=root;size=s;frm=frameset; | pages = 5 | accessdate = 2009-09-01 | isbn = 0585061998}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | title = History of the K-State College of Human Ecology | url = http://www.humec.k-state.edu/about/history-college.php | accessdate = 2009-09-01}}&lt;/ref&gt;  In 1874, the college also became the first in the United States to offer printing courses, which led to journalism courses being launched in 1910; thus, today's A.Q. Miller School of Journalism &amp; Mass Communications, though no longer teaching printing, has the nation's longest continuously offered curriculum in mass communication.{{citation needed|date=November 2011}}

=== Recent history ===
The name of the school changed in 1931 to &quot;Kansas State College of Agriculture and Applied Science&quot;.  In 1959, the Kansas legislature changed the name again to &quot;Kansas State University of Agriculture and Applied Science&quot; to reflect a growing number of graduate programs, though, even in Kansas state legal matters, it is interchangeably referred to as Kansas State University.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | title = University Archives Facts and Flyers  | url = http://www.lib.k-state.edu/depts/spec/flyers/ | accessdate = 2008-03-05}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;http://kansasstatutes.lesterama.org/Chapter_76/Article_4/&lt;/ref&gt; [[Milton S. Eisenhower]] served as president of the university from 1943 to 1950, and Dr. James McCain succeeded him, serving from 1950 to 1975. Several buildings, including [[residence hall]]s and a student union, were added to the campus in the 1950s. The 1960s witnessed demonstrations against the [[Vietnam War]], though fewer than at other college campuses. Enrollment was relatively high through most of the 1970s, but the university endured a downward spiral from approximately 1976 to 1986, when enrollment decreased to 17,570 and a number of faculty resigned. In 1986, [[Jon Wefald]] assumed the presidency of Kansas State University. During his tenure, enrollment and donations increased.
[[Image:PostcardHorticulturalHallManhattanKA1907.jpg|thumb|[[Dickens Hall]], from a 1907 postcard]]
On June 15, 2009, [[Kirk Schulz]] became the 13th president of Kansas State University.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.kstatecollegian.com/schulz-begins-new-term-1.1763672 Kansas State Collegian] ''Schulz begins new term''&lt;/ref&gt; In March 2010 he announced his K-State 2025 plan.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.k-state.edu/media/newsreleases/mar10/kstate202530510.html K-State News Services] &quot;K-State beginning ambitious plan for next 15 years to be a top 50 public university&quot;&lt;/ref&gt; The initiative is designed to elevate K-State to a top 50 nationally recognized research university by 2025.

=== Historic buildings ===
{{seealso|List of oldest buildings on Kansas colleges and universities}}
The university moved from the location of Blue Mont Central College to its present site in 1875.&lt;ref name=Willard/&gt; The original site is now occupied by Central National Bank of Manhattan, Kansas, and Founders Hill Apartments. Holtz Hall, built in 1876, was the first new building erected after the move and is now the oldest free-standing building on campus.&lt;ref name=Willard/&gt;  The signature building at Kansas State University, [[Anderson Hall (Kansas State)|Anderson Hall]], developed in three stages between 1877 and 1885.  Anderson Hall, now listed on the [[National Register of Historic Places]], has housed the university's administrative offices for more than a century.

==Academic profile==
{{Infobox US university ranking
| ARWU_W = 301-400
| Forbes = 153
| QS_W = 
| THES_W = 351-400
| USNWR_NU = 143
| Wamo_NU = 189
}}
[[Image:KSU Anderson Hall.jpg|thumb|upright|left|[[Anderson Hall (Kansas State)|Anderson Hall]]]]
Since 1986, Kansas State ranks first nationally among state universities in its total of [[Rhodes Scholarship|Rhodes]], [[Marshall Scholarship|Marshall]], [[Truman Scholarship|Truman]], [[Goldwater Scholarship|Goldwater]], and Udall scholars with 124 recipients.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | title = Top Scholar Rankings 1986–2008 | url = http://www.k-state.edu/media/achievements/scholarstop10of5pub.pdf | format = English | accessdate = 2008-05-12}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Kansas State University has 65 academic departments in nine colleges: [[Kansas State University College of Agriculture|agriculture]]; [[Architecture]], planning and design; arts and sciences; [[business administration]]; [[education]]; [[engineering]]; [[human ecology]]; [[technology]] and [[aviation]]; and [[veterinary medicine]].  The graduate school offers nearly 100 master's degree programs and nearly 50 doctoral programs.

In 1991, the former Kansas Technical Institute in [[Salina, Kansas]] was merged with Kansas State University by an act of the [[Kansas]] legislature.  The College of Technology and Aviation is located at the Salina campus, and is commonly referred to as [[Kansas State University - Salina|K-State Salina]].

K-State is also known for several distinguished lecture series: Landon Lecture, Lou Douglas Lecture, Huck Boyd Lecture, and Dorothy L. Thompson Civil Rights Lectures. In recent years, the Landon Lecture Series has had high profile speakers, including President George W. Bush, President Bill Clinton, Former Mexican President Vicente Fox and Associate Justice Sonia Sotomayor.

K-State implemented an academic [[honor code]] in 1999.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | title=  KSU Honor Code| url=http://www.k-state.edu/honor| accessdate =2007-03-02}}&lt;/ref&gt;  When students are admitted, it is implied that they will adhere to the Honor Pledge: &quot;On my honor, as a student, I have neither given nor received unauthorized aid on this academic work.&quot;

==Research and cultural resources==
[[Image:KSU Hale library.jpg|thumb|[[Hale Library]]]]

===Agriculture===
The university has had a long-standing interest in [[agriculture]], particularly native [[Great Plains]] plant and animal life. The [[Kansas State University Gardens]] is an on-campus [[horticulture]] display garden that serves as an educational resource and learning laboratory for K-State students and the public. The [[Konza Prairie]] is a native tallgrass prairie preserve located south of Manhattan, which is co-owned by [[The Nature Conservancy]] and Kansas State University and operated as a field research station by the department of biology.  The university also owns an additional {{convert|18000|acre|km2}} in cities across the state that it operates as Agricultural Experiment Stations in research centers in Hays, Garden City, Colby, and Parsons.

===Arts and culture===
The university is home to several museums, including the Marianna Kistler Beach Museum of Art, the K-State Insect Zoo, the KSU Historic Costume and Textiles Museum, and the Chang, Chapman, and Kemper galleries which feature faculty and student artwork. The university also offers an annual cycle of performance art at McCain Auditorium, including concerts, plays and dance.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | title= McCain Auditorium website | url=http://www.k-state.edu/mccain/ |accessdate =2007-09-20}}&lt;/ref&gt;
[[Image:Waters Quad1.jpg|thumb|Waters Quad just North of Hale Library]]

===The Biosciences===
In 2006, K-State dedicated the Biosecurity Research Institute.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.k-state.edu/media/webzine/safetyandsecurity/BRI.html K-State News Services] &quot;K-State's Biosecurity Research Institute to provide research, training space for food safety and security efforts&quot;&lt;/ref&gt; The BRI, in Pat Roberts Hall, is a safe and secure location in which scientists and their collaborators can study high-consequence pathogens. It was designed and constructed for biosafety level 3 (BSL-3) and biosafety level 3 agriculture (BSL-3Ag) research.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | title= Biosecurity Research Institute website | url= http://www.bri.k-state.edu/Aboutus/tabid/71/Default.aspx/ | format= English | accessdate =2010-07-26}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The availability of the BRI was part of what attracted the National Bio and Agro-Defense Facility to K-State and Manhattan.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.ktka.com/news/2010/may/25/nbaf-officials-say-they-plan-do-research-bri/ 49 News KTKA] &quot;NBAF officials say they plan to do research at the BRI&quot;
&lt;/ref&gt; The NBAF will feature about {{convert|500000|sqft|m2}} of research and support space.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | title= National Bio and Agro-Defense Facility website | url= http://www.dhs.gov/files/labs/gc_1181072257904.shtm/ | format= English | accessdate =2010-07-26}} {{Dead link|date=September 2010|bot=H3llBot}}&lt;/ref&gt; Construction of the NBAF will cost an estimated $650 million and should be complete by 2016.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | title= NBAF in Kansas website | url= http://www.nbafinkansas.org/FAQ.aspx#q1/ | format= English | accessdate =2010-07-26}}&lt;/ref&gt; It will stand just north of K-State's College of Veterinary Medicine and east of the BRI.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | title= National Bio and Agro-Defense Facility website | url= http://www.dhs.gov/files/labs/gc_1188509623607.shtm/ | format= English | accessdate =2010-07-26}} {{Dead link|date=September 2010|bot=H3llBot}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Following the NBAF decision, leaders at two additional federal facilities announced they are coming to K-State. The Arthropod-Borne Animal Disease Research Unit, or ABADRU, specializes in animal and plant diseases transmitted by insects. The lab is relocating from Laramie, Wyo., to K-State in order to fully realize its research mandate.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.kstatecollegian.com/news/city-officials-announce-relocation-of-federal-lab-1.2048467/ K-State Collegian] &quot;City officials announce relocation of federal lab&quot;
&lt;/ref&gt; The Center of Excellence for Emerging and Zoonotic Animal Diseases, or CEEZAD, will research foreign animal, zoonotic and newly discovered pathogens that can have a consequential economic impact on U.S. agriculture, homeland security and human and animal health. It will be led by K-State's Dr. Juergen Richt.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | title= CEEZAD Focuses on Zoonotic Diseases website | url= http://www.k-state.edu/perspectives/documents/Perspectives-Winter_2011.pdf | format= English | accessdate =2011-01-18}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Landon Lecture Series===
Kansas State University offers the Landon Lecture Series for students, faculty and the community.  The lecture series' name honors former Kansas governor and presidential candidate [[Alfred Landon]].

The series has featured many prominent speakers –– primarily current or former political or government leaders. For example, on Jan. 23, 2006, U.S. President [[George W. Bush]] delivered the university's 143rd Landon Lecture at [[Bramlage Coliseum]]. On March 2, 2007, his predecessor, [[Bill Clinton]], delivered the 149th Landon Lecture.&lt;ref name = LandonList&gt;{{cite web | title= Landon Lecture Series – Past Speakers | url=http://ome.ksu.edu/lectures/landon/past.html |accessdate = 2008-10-16}}&lt;/ref&gt;  Also, on September 23, 2008, former Mexican president [[Vicente Fox]] gave the 152nd Landon Lecture.&lt;ref name = LandonList/&gt; Overall, six [[President of the United States of America|U.S. presidents]] and three foreign presidents have given Landon Lectures at K-State.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | title= Landon Lecture Series – New Speakers| url=http://ome.ksu.edu/lectures/landon/new.html|accessdate =2007-03-02}}&lt;/ref&gt;  There are approximately four speakers per year. In January 2011, Supreme Court Justice Sonia Sotomayor spoke at the lecture.

===Engineering &amp; Physics===
The university's extensive list of research facilities includes the James R. Macdonald Laboratory for research in atomic, molecular and optical physics and the [[NASA]] Center for Gravitational Studies in Cellular and Developmental Biology. The [[excimer laser]], which made [[LASIK]] eye surgery possible, is a technology developed by Kansas State researchers.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | title =Kansas State University Achievements  | url =http://www.mediarelations.k-state.edu/WEB/News/NewsReleases/priorasaccomplishments.html | format = English  | accessdate =2006-09-25 |archiveurl = http://web.archive.org/web/20060905163446/http://www.mediarelations.k-state.edu/WEB/News/NewsReleases/priorasaccomplishments.html &lt;!-- Bot retrieved archive --&gt; |archivedate = 2006-09-05}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Other research facilities include:
*Institute for Environmental Research
*The National Gas Machinery Laboratory
*[http://www.mne.ksu.edu/research/centers/reactor TRIGA Mark II Nuclear Research Facility]
*[http://www.mne.ksu.edu/research/centers/SMARTlab Semiconductor Materials and Radiological Technologies (S.M.A.R.T.) Laboratory]
*Center for Complex Fluid Flows

== Intercollegiate athletics ==
[[File:KSUWildcats logo.svg|right|thumb|170px|Kansas State Wildcats &quot;Powercat&quot; logo]]
{{Main|Kansas State Wildcats}}
Kansas State's sports teams are called the Wildcats.  They participate in the NCAA's [[Division I (NCAA)|Division I]] and the [[Big 12 Conference]].  The [[School colors|official school color]] is Royal Purple, making Kansas State one of very few schools (alongside [[Syracuse University|Syracuse]] and [[Harvard University|Harvard]]) that have only one official color.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | title = Kansas State Traditions | url = http://www.kstatesports.com/ViewArticle.dbml?DB_OEM_ID=400&amp;KEY=&amp;ATCLID=37671 | format = English | accessdate = 2008-11-30}} {{Dead link|date=September 2010|bot=H3llBot}}&lt;/ref&gt;  White and silver are commonly used as complementary colors, with white mentioned with purple in the university's fight song &quot;Wildcat Victory.&quot; The athletics logo is a stylized wildcat head in profile usually featured in the school color. 

Sports sponsored by the school include [[American football|football]], [[basketball]], [[cross country running|cross country]] and [[track and field|track]], [[baseball]], [[golf]], [[tennis]], [[rowing (sport)|rowing]], [[equestrianism|equestrian]] and [[volleyball]].  The head football coach is [[Bill Snyder]], the head men's basketball coach is [[Frank Martin (basketball coach)|Frank Martin]], the head women's basketball coach is [[Deb Patterson]] and the head baseball coach is [[Brad Hill (baseball)|Brad Hill]].

==Notable alumni==
{{Main|List of Kansas State University people}}
Beginning with the first graduating class in 1867,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book | title = Record of the Alumni of the Kansas State Agricultural College | year = 1914 | url =http://skyways.lib.ks.us/genweb/education/ksu/ksugrads1.html}}&lt;/ref&gt; a number of Kansas State alums have gone on to distinguished careers.  Presently, the [[Governor of Kansas]] and one [[United States Congressional Delegations from Kansas|U.S. Senator from Kansas]] are graduates of Kansas State University.  Other graduates currently serve as the vice-president of [[Liberia]], the [[University president|president]] of the [[Georgia Institute of Technology]], and the chief White House photographer.  Kansas State alums have been enshrined in the [[Rock and Roll Hall of Fame]] and the [[College Football Hall of Fame]], served as Chairman of the Joint Chiefs of Staff, and have earned [[Emmy Award]]s and [[Olympic Games|Olympic]] gold medals.
[[Image:KSU Campus.jpg|thumb|Northern Campus in October]]

== Foundations ==
The Kansas State University Foundation was established in 1944 as the official fundraising arm of Kansas State University. Its mission is to secure and prudently manage private gifts in support of Kansas State University and foster a culture that unites philanthropic desires with university priorities. 

The foundation is a separate, independent organization chartered by the state of Kansas as a 501(c)(3) nonprofit education corporation. A volunteer board of trustees governs the foundation. A 15-member board of directors elected from the membership of the board meets quarterly and is authorized to act on the trustees' behalf. 

Foundation staff members work in close partnership with university administrators, deans, faculty, the K-State Alumni Association and K-State Athletics to secure charitable contributions from individuals, corporations and foundations to support identified priorities for the university. 

== Campus ==
The main campus of Kansas State University in Manhattan covers {{convert|668|acre|km2}}.  Since 1986, Kansas State has added over 2 million square feet (186,000 m²) of buildings to the campus, including a new library, art museum and plant sciences building.

Several of the buildings on campus were heavily damaged by an EF4 [[tornado]] on [[June 2008 tornado outbreak sequence|June 11, 2008]]. Damage estimates totaled more than $20 million.&lt;ref&gt;[http://blogs.kansas.com/weather/2008/06/12/ Wichita Eagle-Beacon] ''Tornadoes rip Manhattan, KSU damage more than $20 million''&lt;/ref&gt; K-State paid a deductible of $5 million for their insurance to repair all damages.

=== Main campus buildings ===
{{col-begin}}
{{col-3}}
*Ackert Hall
*[[Ahearn Field House]]
*[[Anderson Hall (Kansas State)|Anderson Hall]]
*[[Mariana Kistler Beach Museum of Art|Beach Museum of Art]]
*[[Bill Snyder Family Football Stadium]]
*[[Bluemont Hall]]
*Boyd Hall
*[[Bramlage Coliseum]]
*Brandeberry Indoor Complex
*Burt Hall
*Bushnell Hall
*Call Hall
*[[Calvin Hall (building)|Calvin Hall]]
*Campus Creek Complex
*[[Cardwell Hall]]
*Chalmers Hall
*Chemistry &amp; Biochemistry Building
*Chester E. Peters Recreation Complex
*Coles Hall
*[[College Court Building]]
*Danforth &amp; All Faiths Chapels
*Davenport Building
*[[Derby Dining Center]]
*[[Dickens Hall]]
*Dole Hall
*[[Durland Hall]]
{{col-3}}
*Dykstra Hall
*Edwards Hall
*Eisenhower Hall
*English/Counseling Services
*Environmental Research Lab
*Extension Forestry Facilities
*Fairchild Hall
*Feed Technology
*[[Fiedler Hall]]
*[[Ford Hall]]
*Gen. Richard B. Myers Hall
*[[Goodnow Hall (Kansas State University)|Goodnow Hall]]
*Greenhouse D – Conservatory
*[[Hale Library]]
*[[Haymaker Hall]]
*Hoeflin Stone House
*Holton Hall
*Holtz Hall
*International Student Center
*Jardine Terrace Apartments
*Justin Hall &lt;!-- Justin Hall is name of person, should be [[Justin Hall (Kansas State)|Justin Hall]] --&gt;
*Kansas Artificial Breeding Service Unit
*K-State Student Union
*Kedzie Hall
*King Hall &lt;!-- King Hall is name of school, should be [[King Hall (Kansas State)||King Hall]] --&gt;
*Kramer Food Center
*Leadership Studies Building
{{col-3}}
*Leasure Hall
*Margaret Ahlborn/Ula Dow Cottage
*[[Marlatt Hall]]
*McCain Auditorium
*[[Memorial Stadium (Kansas State)|Memorial Stadium]]
*[[Moore Hall (Kansas State University)|Moore Hall]]
*Mosier Hall
*[[Nichols Hall]]
*Pat Roberts Hall
*Pittman Building
*Power Plant
*Putnam Hall
*[[Rathbone Hall]]
*[[Seaton Hall]]
*Shellenberger Hall
*Straube House, UFM Community Learning Center
*Thompson Hall
*Throckmorton Hall
*Trotter Hall
*Umberger Hall
*Van Zile Hall
*Ward Hall &lt;!-- Ward Hall is a Georgetown, KY mansion, should be [[Ward Hall (Kansas State)||Ward Hall]] --&gt;
*Waters Hall
*Weber Hall
*[[West Hall (Kansas State University)|West Hall]]
*Willard Hall &lt;!-- Willard Hall is name of person, should be [[Willard Hall (Kansas State)||Willard Hall]] --&gt;
*Wind Erosion Laboratory (damaged by [[June 2008 tornado outbreak sequence|June 11th, 2008 tornado]])
{{col-end}}

==Student life==
[[Image:KSU Bluemont Bell and Dickens.jpg|thumb|Bluemont Bell and Dickens Hall]]

=== Residential life ===
K-State has 10 residence halls on campus: Boyd Hall, [[Ford Hall]], [[Goodnow Hall (Kansas State University)|Goodnow Hall]], [[Haymaker Hall]], [[Marlatt Hall]], [[Moore Hall (Kansas State University)|Moore Hall]], [[West Hall (Kansas State University)|West Hall]], Putnam Hall, Van Zile Hall, and Smurthwaite, as well as Jardine Apartments. Smurthwaite, Ford, and Boyd Halls are all female. Haymaker and Marlatt Halls were all-male residence halls until the fall semesters of 2002 and 2009 respectively, when they became co-educational.&lt;ref&gt;http://housing.k-state.edu/rsvp/faq.php#a5&lt;/ref&gt;  The residence halls are divided into three complexes: Derby, Kramer, and Strong.&lt;ref&gt;[http://housing.k-state.edu/reshalls/compare.php K-State Housing and Dining Services&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;

===Student organizations===
Kansas State has more than 400 student organizations.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.k-state.edu/directories/orgs.html Student organizations&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;

The Student Governing Association is the largest organization of student leaders, composed of elected and appointed officials. The Student Governing Association follows the model of the [[Federal government of the United States|U.S. government]], with [[Executive (government)|executive]], [[Legislature|legislative]] and [[Judiciary|judicial]] branches.

The Association of Residence  Halls (KSUARH) is the second largest organization of student leaders working towards better the on-campus living experience for students living in the Residence Halls around campus.

GSA is the Graduate Student Association, and members include K-State's graduate-level business students. GSC is the Graduate Student Council, open to graduate-level students of all disciplines.

Kansas State University also offers Army ROTC (Reserve Officers' Training Corps) and Air Force ROTC programs.

===Student media===
*Radio Station: [[KSDB-FM]] The Wildcat 91.9 Student Radio
*Newspaper: [[Kansas State Collegian]]
*Yearbook: [[Royal Purple Yearbook]]
*Television: &quot;Purple Power Hour,&quot; &quot;Manhattan Matters,&quot; &amp; &quot;Wildcat Watch&quot;

===School Songs===

'''''Alma Mater''''' is the name of the official school song of [[Kansas State University]]. In 1888, when the University was still Kansas State Agricultural College, H.W. Jones submitted the song as part of a school-wide contest. It was originally a four-stanza song and, over the years, some lyrics have changed.&lt;ref name=KS&gt;[http://www.kstatesports.com/ViewArticle.dbml?DB_OEM_ID=400&amp;KEY=&amp;ATCLID=37671 Kansas State Traditions - Kansas State University Wildcats Official Athletics Site]&lt;/ref&gt; The song is sung at most K-State sporting events by fans, students and alumni.

[[Wildcat Victory]] and [[Wabash Cannonball]] are both commonly used as fight songs. Wildcat Victory is used by many high schools as their fight song.

==References==
{{reflist}}
*{{cite book |last=Carey |first=James C. |title=Kansas State University: The Quest for Identity |year=1977 |publisher=The Regents Press of Kansas |location=[[Lawrence, Kansas]] |isbn=0700601562}}

==External links==
{{Commons category|Kansas State University}}
*[http://www.k-state.edu/ Official website]
*[http://www.k-statesports.com/ Official Athletics website]

{{Kansas State}}
{{Public colleges and universities in Kansas}}
{{Big 12 Conference}}

{{Coord|39|11|30|N|96|34|51|W|type:edu_region:US-KS_scale:10000|display=title}}

[[Category:Kansas State University]]
[[Category:Land-grant universities and colleges]]
[[Category:Association of Public and Land-Grant Universities]]
[[Category:North Central Association of Colleges and Schools]]
[[Category:Public universities]]
[[Category:Education in Riley County, Kansas]]
[[Category:Universities and colleges in Kansas]]
[[Category:Educational institutions established in 1863]]
[[Category:Buildings and structures in Riley County, Kansas]]
[[Category:Visitor attractions in Riley County, Kansas]]

[[de:Kansas State University]]
[[es:Universidad Estatal de Kansas]]
[[fa:دانشگاه ایالتی کانزاس]]
[[fr:Université d'État du Kansas]]
[[it:Università dello Stato del Kansas]]
[[ja:カンザス州立大学]]
[[no:Kansas State University]]
[[pt:Universidade Estadual do Kansas]]
[[simple:Kansas State University]]
[[ta:கேன்சஸ் மாநிலப் பல்கலைக்கழகம்]]
[[th:มหาวิทยาลัยแคนซัสสเตต]]
[[tr:Kansas Devlet Üniversitesi]]
[[zh:堪薩斯州立大學]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
