<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="16863278" ns="0" title="6th Airlanding Brigade (United Kingdom)"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{good article}}
{{Use British English|date=August 2011}}
{{Infobox Military Unit
|unit_name= 6th Airlanding Brigade
|image= [[File:2nd Ox and Bucks.jpg|300px]]
|caption=Men of the brigade in Normandy, June 1944
|dates=1943–1946
|country= [[United Kingdom]]
|allegiance=
|branch= [[British Army]]
|type=[[Glider infantry]]
|role=[[Airborne forces]]{{#tag:ref|The British Army's airborne forces consisted of parachute and glider-borne troops.&lt;ref&gt;Peters and Buist, p.5&lt;/ref&gt;|group=nb}}
|size=[[Brigade]] ~3,500 men
|command_structure=[[6th Airborne Division]]
|garrison=
&lt;!-- Commanders --&gt;
|current_commander=
|ceremonial_chief=
|colonel_of_the_regiment=
|notable_commanders=[[Brigadier]] [[Hugh Kindersley, 2nd Baron Kindersley|Hugh Kindersley]]
&lt;!-- Insignia --&gt;
|identification_symbol=[[File:British Airborne Units.gif|200px]]
|identification_symbol_label=Emblem&lt;br /&gt;of the&lt;br /&gt;British&lt;br /&gt;airborne&lt;br /&gt;forces
&lt;!-- Culture and history --&gt;
|nickname=''Red Devils''  {{#tag:ref|The 1st Parachute Brigade had been called the &quot;Rote Teufel&quot; or &quot;Red Devils&quot; by the German troops they had fought in North Africa. The title was officially confirmed by General [[Harold Alexander]] and henceforth applied to all British airborne troops.&lt;ref&gt;Otway, p.88&lt;/ref&gt;|group=nb}}
|patron=
|motto=
|colors=
|march=
|mascot=
|battles=[[Invasion of Normandy]]&lt;br&gt;[[Operation Mallard]]&lt;br&gt;[[Battle of the Bulge]]&lt;br&gt;[[Operation Varsity]]&lt;br&gt;[[6th Airborne Division in Palestine|Palestine]]
|anniversaries=
|decorations=
|battle_honours=
}}

The '''6th Airlanding Brigade''' was a [[glider infantry]] [[brigade]] forming part of the British [[airborne forces]] during the [[Second World War]]. Composed of three infantry [[battalion]]s and supporting units, it was assigned to the [[6th Airborne Division (United Kingdom)|6th Airborne Division]].

During the [[Normandy landings]] on 6&amp;nbsp;June&amp;nbsp;1944, the brigade took part in [[Operation Mallard]], holding the southern flank of the bridgehead over the [[Orne River]]. In August 1944, along with the rest of the 6th Airborne Division, it took part in the advance to the [[River Seine]]. Withdrawn to England in September, the brigade returned to mainland Europe to counter the surprise German offensive in the [[Ardennes]], better known as the [[Battle of the Bulge]]. Their final airborne mission of the war was [[Operation Varsity]] in March 1945, an assault crossing of the [[River Rhine|Rhine]], after which they advanced through Germany, reaching the [[Baltic Sea]] at [[Wismar]] by the end of the war.

The brigade was withdrawn from Germany at the end of May 1945 and was sent, together with the rest of 6th Airborne Division, to [[Mandate Palestine|British Palestine]] to provide [[internal security]]. Following the arrival of the [[1st Parachute Brigade (United Kingdom)|1st Parachute Brigade]], however, the 6th Airlanding Brigade was no longer needed there and was returned to normal infantry duties, renamed the 31st&amp;nbsp;Independent Infantry Brigade.

==Background==
Impressed by the success of German airborne operations during the [[Battle of France]], the British [[Prime Minister of the United Kingdom|Prime Minister]], [[Winston Churchill]], directed the [[War Office]] to investigate the possibility of creating a force of 5,000 parachute troops.&lt;ref&gt;Otway, p.21&lt;/ref&gt; As a result, on 22 June 1940, [[No. 2 Commando]] assumed parachute duties, and on 21 November was re-designated the 11th Special Air Service Battalion, with a parachute and glider wing.&lt;ref&gt;Shortt and McBride, p.4&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Moreman, p.91&lt;/ref&gt;

On 21 June 1940 the [[No.1 Parachute Training School RAF|Central Landing Establishment]] was formed at [[RAF Ringway|Ringway airfield]] near [[Manchester]]. Although tasked primarily with training parachute troops, it was also directed to investigate the use of gliders to transport troops into battle.&lt;ref&gt;Otway 1990, pp. 28–29&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Smith7&quot;&gt;Smith, p.7&lt;/ref&gt; At the same time, the Ministry of Aircraft Production contracted [[General Aircraft Ltd]] to design and produce a glider for this purpose.&lt;ref name=&quot;Flint73&quot;&gt;Flint, p.73&lt;/ref&gt; The result was the [[General Aircraft Hotspur]], an aircraft capable of transporting eight soldiers, that was used for both assault and training purposes.&lt;ref&gt;Lynch, p.31&lt;/ref&gt;

The success of the first British airborne raid, [[Operation Colossus]], prompted the War Office to expand the airborne force through the creation of the [[Parachute Regiment (United Kingdom)|Parachute Regiment]], and to develop plans to convert several infantry battalions into parachute and glider battalions.&lt;ref&gt;Harclerode, p. 218&lt;/ref&gt; On 31 May 1941, a joint [[British Army|army]] and [[Royal Air Force|air force]] memorandum was approved by the [[Chiefs of Staff Committee|Chiefs-of-Staff]] and Winston Churchill; it recommended that the British airborne forces should consist of two parachute brigades, one based in England and the other in the [[Middle East]], and that a glider force of 10,000 men should be created.&lt;ref&gt;Tugwell p.123&lt;/ref&gt;

==Formation==

On 23&amp;nbsp;April&amp;nbsp;1943, the British [[War Office]] gave permission to raise a second airborne division, the 6th Airborne.&lt;ref name=harc223&gt;Harclerode, p.223&lt;/ref&gt; The division comprised the [[3rd Parachute Brigade (United Kingdom)|3rd]] and [[5th Parachute Brigade (United Kingdom)|5th Parachute Brigades]] and the 6th Airlanding Brigade, giving it two parachute and one airlanding brigades, which became the standard British complement for an airborne division.&lt;ref name=harc223/&gt; In May [[Brigadier]] [[Hugh Kindersley]] was appointed as the airlanding brigade's first [[commanding officer]]. Under his command he had two experienced [[battalion]]s transferred from the [[1st Airlanding Brigade (United Kingdom)|1st Airlanding Brigade]]: the 2nd Battalion [[Oxfordshire and Buckinghamshire Light Infantry]] (2nd OBLI) and the 1st Battalion [[Royal Ulster Rifles]] (1st RUR). They were joined by a unit newly transferred to [[airborne force]]s, the 12th Battalion [[Devonshire Regiment]] (12th Devons), as the brigade's third infantry battalion.&lt;ref&gt;Harcerlode, pp.223–224&lt;/ref&gt; Other units assigned around the same time were the [[53rd (Worcestershire Yeomanry) Airlanding Light Regiment]] [[Royal Artillery]], the 249th (Airborne) Field Company [[Royal Engineers]] and the [[195th (Airlanding) Field Ambulance]] [[Royal Army Medical Corps]].&lt;ref name=paradata&gt;{{cite web|accessdate=10 August 2011|publisher=Para Data|title=6th Airlanding Brigade|url=http://www.paradata.org.uk/units/6th-airlanding-brigade}}&lt;/ref&gt;{{#tag:ref|By 1944, the 53rd (Worcestershire Yeomanry) Airlanding Light Regiment was removed from the brigade order of battle and became a divisional asset.&lt;ref name=mod6june/&gt;|group=nb}}

[[File:Airspeed Horsa interior.jpg|thumb|The interior of the [[Airspeed Horsa]] glider, which made up the great majority of the brigade's glider transport]]

The airlanding brigade was an important part of the airborne division, its strength being almost equal to that of the two parachute brigades combined.&lt;ref&gt;Guard, p.37&lt;/ref&gt; In particular, its infantry battalions were the &quot;most heavily armed in the British Army.&quot;&lt;ref name=mod6june&gt;{{cite web|accessdate=11 August 2011|publisher=[[Ministry of Defence (United Kingdom)]]|date=22 November 2005|title=The British Airborne Assault|url=http://webarchive.nationalarchives.gov.uk/+/http://www.mod.uk/aboutus/dday60/airborne.htm}}&lt;/ref&gt; Each airlanding battalion had an establishment of 1034 men, serving in four rifle [[company (military)|companies]], a support and a headquarters company.&lt;ref name=greg50/&gt; A rifle company was sub-divided into four [[platoon]]s, the support company into six: two [[anti-tank warfare|anti-tank]] platoons with four [[Ordnance QF 6 pounder|6&amp;nbsp;pounder guns]] in each, two [[mortar (weapon)|mortar platoons]] with twelve [[Ordnance ML 3 inch Mortar|3&amp;nbsp;inch mortars]] between them, and two [[Vickers machine gun]] platoons with four guns in each platoon.&lt;ref name=peters55&gt;Peters and Buist, p.55&lt;/ref&gt; The headquarters company had [[Signals (military)|signals]], [[assault pioneer]], [[Military transport|transport]] and [[Military administration|administration]] platoons.&lt;ref name= greg50&gt;Gregory, p.50&lt;/ref&gt;

Air transport for the brigade was normally the [[Airspeed Horsa]] glider, piloted by two soldiers from the [[Glider Pilot Regiment]].&lt;ref&gt;Tugwell, p.39&lt;/ref&gt; With a wingspan of {{convert|88|ft}} and a length of {{convert|67|ft}}, the Horsa had a maximum load capacity of {{convert|15,750|lb}}—space for two pilots, and a maximum of either 28 troops or two [[Willys MB|jeeps]], one jeep and a 6&amp;nbsp;pounder gun, or one jeep with a trailer.&lt;ref&gt;Fowler, p.9&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Peters and Buist, p.9&lt;/ref&gt; It required 62 Horsas and one [[General Aircraft Hamilcar]] glider to transport an airlanding battalion into action. The Hamilcar carried the battalion's two [[Universal Carrier]]s, which were used to support the mortar and machine-gun platoons.&lt;ref name=peters55/&gt;

At the end of the war in 1945, the Devonshire battalion, formed during the war, was disbanded, and replaced by the [[regular army]] 1st Battalion [[Argyll and Sutherland Highlanders]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Wilson5&quot;&gt;Wilson, p.5&lt;/ref&gt; Brigadier [[Roger Bower]] was also appointed to command the brigade for service in [[Palestine]].&lt;ref&gt;Wilson, p.32&lt;/ref&gt;
The 6th Airlanding Brigade had always been an integral part of the 6th Airborne Division, but when the [[1st Airborne Division (United Kingdom)|1st Airborne Division]] was disbanded, and its [[1st Parachute Brigade (United Kingdom)|1st Parachute Brigade]] was assigned to the 6th Airborne Division, the 6th Airlanding Brigade became surplus to the division's requirements. On 15&amp;nbsp;April&amp;nbsp;1946, the brigade ceased being part of the British airborne forces, and was renumbered the 31st Independent Infantry Brigade.&lt;ref&gt;Wilson, p.43&lt;/ref&gt;

==Operational history==

From June to December 1943, the brigade as part of the 6th Airborne Division prepared for operations, and trained at every level from [[section (military unit)|section]] up to division by day and night.&lt;ref name=harc225&gt;Harclerode, p.225&lt;/ref&gt; Airborne soldiers were expected to fight against superior numbers of the enemy equipped with artillery and tanks. So training was designed to encourage a spirit of self-discipline, self-reliance and aggressiveness. Emphasis was given to physical fitness, [[marksman]]ship and [[fieldcraft]].&lt;ref name=guard225&gt;Guard, p.225&lt;/ref&gt; A large part of the training consisted of [[assault course]]s and [[route marching]]. [[Military exercise]]s included capturing and holding airborne bridgeheads, road or rail bridges and coastal fortifications.&lt;ref name=guard225/&gt; At the end of most exercises, the troops would march back to their barracks, usually a distance of around {{convert|20|mi}}.&lt;ref name=harc225/&gt; An ability to cover long distances at speed was expected: airborne platoons were required to cover a distance of {{convert|50|mi}} in 24 hours, and battalions {{convert|32|mi}}.&lt;ref name=guard225/&gt;

In April 1944, under the command of [[1st Airborne Corps (United Kingdom)|1st Airborne Corps]], the brigade took part in Exercise Mush. This was a three day exercise in the counties of [[Gloucestershire]], [[Oxfordshire]] and [[Wiltshire]], during which the entire 6th Airborne Division was landed by air. Unknown to the troops involved, the exercise was a full scale rehearsal for the division's involvement in the imminent [[Normandy invasion]].&lt;ref&gt;Gregory, p.100&lt;/ref&gt; In the invasion, the division's two parachute brigades would land in the early hours of 6 June in [[Operation Tonga]]; the airlanding brigade would not arrive until almost dusk on the same day. Their objective was to secure the left flank of the invasion area, between the rivers [[River Orne|Orne]] and [[River Dives|Dives]].&lt;ref&gt;Gregory, p.101&lt;/ref&gt;

===Normandy===
{{see|Operation Deadstick|Operation Mallard}}
[[File:Landing zone 'N' 7 June 1944.jpg|thumb|[[Airspeed Horsa]] gliders on Landing Zone 'N', 7&amp;nbsp;June&amp;nbsp;1944]]

One of the first [[Allied powers|Allied]] units to land in Normandy was 'D' Company 2nd OBLI, commanded by [[Major]] [[John Howard]]. The company, attached to the [[5th Parachute Brigade (United Kingdom)|5th Parachute Brigade]], carried out Operation Deadstick, a [[coup de main]] assault on two bridges crossing the [[Caen Canal]] and the River Orne.&lt;ref name=howard&gt;{{cite web|accessdate=11 August 2010|publisher=''[[The Independent]]''|title=Obituary, Major John Howard|date=11 May 1999|last=Arthur|first=Max|url=http://www.independent.co.uk/arts-entertainment/obituary-major-john-howard-1092864.html}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Almost 21 hours later the 6th Airlanding Brigade's main air assault on [[Normandy]], Operation Mallard, began. Included in the operation was the brigade, the 6th Airborne Division's [[6th Airborne Reconnaissance Regiment|reconnaissance regiment]], and one of its [[howitzer]] [[artillery battery|batteries]]. The combined force crossed the [[English Channel]] in 250 gliders, arriving at their landing zones at 21:00 6&amp;nbsp;June&amp;nbsp;1944.&lt;ref&gt;Tugwell, p.218&lt;/ref&gt;

The gliders carrying the brigade headed for two separated landing areas, Landing Zone 'W' (LZ-W) to the east of [[Saint-Aubin-d'Arquenay]] and Landing Zone 'N' (LZ-N) to the north of [[Ranville]].&lt;ref&gt;Ford and Zaloga, pp.216–217&lt;/ref&gt; The gliders landing on LZ-W contained the remaining men of the 2nd OBLI, and 'A' Company, 12th Devons landed at LZ-W. Given the limited availability of aircraft, the remainder of the Devons battalion and the divisional troops were transported by sea, arriving at [[Sword beach]] on 7&amp;nbsp;June.&lt;ref name=mod6june/&gt; The brigade headquarters and 1st RUR landed at LZ-N.&lt;ref name=morgan95&gt;Morgan and Hughes, p.95&lt;/ref&gt; LZ-N was still within range of the German defenders, and the disembarking troops were subjected to light [[machine gun]] and [[Mortar (weapon)|mortar]] fire,&lt;ref name=morgan95/&gt; however they only lost one man, who was killed by a [[sniper]].&lt;ref&gt;Morgan and Hughes, p.96&lt;/ref&gt;

At 22:30 Brigadier Kindersley briefed the two battalion commanding officers, ordering the 2nd OBLI to capture the village of [[Escoville]] {{convert|3|mi}} to the south of [[Ranville]], and the 1st RUR to capture [[Longueval]],  {{convert|2.5|mi}} south-west of the Le Bas de Ranville, and [[Sainte-Honorine-la-Chardonne|Sainte-Honorine]].&lt;ref&gt;Harclerode, p.338&lt;/ref&gt;

By 04:30 7&amp;nbsp;June the 2nd OBLI had reached [[Herourvillette]]. Finding the village unoccupied they left a company behind to defend it, and at 08:30 the rest of the battalion headed for Escoville. They arrived at the village at 11:00 having only been confronted by sniper fire.&lt;ref name=harc339&gt;Harclerode, p.339&lt;/ref&gt; The Germans assembling on the heights overlooking the village attacked at 15:00. Fighting at [[Close quarters combat|close quarters]] and [[house to house]], by 16:00 the battalion was forced to withdraw back to Herourvillette. The battle cost them 87 casualties, including the commanding officer.&lt;ref name=harc339/&gt;

It was not until 09:00 that the 1st RUR were in position to carry out a [[left flanking]] attack on Longuerval. The village was clear of Germans so they pressed on towards Sainte-Honorine. When between the two villages, the battalion was engaged by German mortar, artillery and [[assault gun]] fire, and suffered several casualties. Two companies managed to reach Sainte-Honorine, but with no artillery [[fire support]] of their own, and out of radio contact with their battalion headquarters, they were forced to withdraw back to Longueval.&lt;ref&gt;Harclerode, pp.338–339&lt;/ref&gt;

Around the same time, the 12th Devons had arrived in the divisional area from the landing beaches and were ordered to take over the defence of the Bas de Ranville from the [[12th (Yorkshire) Parachute Battalion]].&lt;ref&gt;Harclerode, p.340&lt;/ref&gt; Because they were positioned behind the brigade front line, they were not directly attacked, but from 11:00 to 18:30 on 8&amp;nbsp;June they were subjected to a constant artillery bombardment.&lt;ref&gt;Harclerode, p.341&lt;/ref&gt;

On 9&amp;nbsp;June the 2nd OBLI sent a company back to Escoville to confirm if it was still held by the Germans. Finding it occupied by infantry with armour support, they withdrew back to Herourvillette. At 18:30 the battalion was attacked by [[Messerschmitt Bf 109]] aircraft and at 19:00 the whole brigade's position was bombarded by German artillery and mortar fire. This was followed by an infantry and tank assault. Supported by their own and the division's anti-tank guns and artillery, the battalion stopped the attack around {{convert|100|yd}} from their lines. By 21:30 the attack was over, and the Germans withdrew having lost eight tanks, two [[Armored car (military)|armoured cars]]  and two [[self-propelled gun]]s.&lt;ref&gt;Harclerode, p.343&lt;/ref&gt;

At the same time, German tanks and infantry attacked the 12th Devons. By 20:30 they had advanced to within {{convert|50|yd}} of the battalion's positions. With the airborne artillery regiment busy assisting the 2nd OBLI, the Devons had to call on the artillery from the [[3rd Infantry Division (United Kingdom)|3rd Infantry Division]] to break up the attack.&lt;ref&gt;Harclerode, p.342&lt;/ref&gt; Activity over the next few days was limited to skirmishes and patrol activity, until the night of the 13&amp;nbsp;June when the brigade was relieved by units of the [[51st (Highland) Infantry Division]]. The brigade was repositioned in the area of [[Bréville-les-Monts|Breville]] between the 5th Parachute Brigade and the [[British Commandos|commandos]] of the [[1st Special Service Brigade]]. Here they remained in a defensive position until mid August, conducting patrols to hold the Germans' attention.&lt;ref&gt;Harclerode, p.348&lt;/ref&gt;

===Advance to the Seine===
{{see|6th Airborne Division advance to the River Seine|Operation Paddle}}
[[File:Glider troops June 1944.jpg|thumb|Men of the brigade in France, 1944]]

On 7&amp;nbsp;August the 6th Airborne division was ordered to prepare to move over to the offensive, with its objective being the mouth of the [[River Seine]].&lt;ref&gt;Otway, pp.187–188&lt;/ref&gt; The division began to advance as the Germans retreated from France following their defeat in the [[Battle of Falaise]]. The 6th Airlanding Brigade, now commanded by Brigadier Edward Flavell, had the [[1st Belgian Infantry Brigade]] and the [[Royal Netherlands Motorized Infantry Brigade]] under its command. Together they would form the left flank of the division's advance, moving along the French coast, while the remainder of the division advanced further inland.&lt;ref name=harc351&gt;Harclerode, p.351&lt;/ref&gt;

The 6th Airlanding Brigade advance started on 17&amp;nbsp;August along two axes, with the 12th Devons on the left, the 2nd OBLI on the right, and the 1st RUR in reserve.&lt;ref name=harc351/&gt; At [[Longuemare]] the 12th Devons had to fight through the German rearguard, and the 1st RUR took over the advance on the left and reached [[Cabourg]] without meeting any further resistance.&lt;ref&gt;Harclerode, p.352&lt;/ref&gt;

The brigade group was moved to an area east of [[Troarn]] on 21&amp;nbsp;August. With the 12th Devons leading they advanced again, occupying [[Branville]], [[Vauville, Calvados|Vauville]] and [[Deauville]] on 22&amp;nbsp;August.&lt;ref&gt;Harclerode, pp.353 359&lt;/ref&gt; Attempts to cross the [[River Touques]] were repulsed by a force estimated to be around 1,200 men.&lt;ref name=harc360&gt;Harclerode, p.360&lt;/ref&gt; Outflanking the German position, the 2nd OBLI crossed the river at [[Touques, Calvados|Touques]] on 24&amp;nbsp;August. Keeping the pressure on the retreating Germans on 25&amp;nbsp;August, [[Le Correspondence]], [[Petreville]] and [[Malhortie]] were captured.&lt;ref name=harc360/&gt; However, the Germans had retained control of the bridge outside Malhortie and the high ground at [[Manneville-la-Raoult]]. The 2nd OBLI attacked and captured the bridge intact, but Mannerville-la-Raoult was only taken at dusk, at the cost of several casualties.&lt;ref&gt;Harclerode, pp.360–361&lt;/ref&gt; The next day, 26&amp;nbsp;August, the battalion captured [[Foulbec]] on the River Seine at 19:00, although not before the Germans had destroyed the bridge,&lt;ref&gt;Harclerode, pp.361&lt;/ref&gt; and earlier that day the 1st RUR had captured [[Berville-sur-Mer]].&lt;ref&gt;Harclerode, p.362&lt;/ref&gt; On 27&amp;nbsp;August the division was ordered to concentrate in the area between [[Honfleur]] and [[Pont Audemer]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Harclerode&quot;&gt;Harclerode, p.363&lt;/ref&gt;

In nine days of fighting the 6th Airborne Division had advanced {{convert|45|mi}},&lt;ref name=Otway191&gt;Otway, p.191&lt;/ref&gt; despite, as the divisional commander [[Major-General (United Kingdom)|Major-General]] [[Richard Nelson Gale|Richard Gale]] put it, his infantry units being &quot;quite inadequately equipped for a rapid pursuit&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;Gale, p.126.&lt;/ref&gt; The division had captured {{convert|400|sqmi|km2}} of territory and taken over 1,000 German soldiers prisoner. Since landing on 6&amp;nbsp;June the division's casualties were 4,457, of which 821 were killed, 2,709 wounded and 927 missing.&lt;ref name=&quot;Harclerode&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref name=Otway191/&gt; The 6th Airlanding Brigade suffered 115 men killed during the campaign.&lt;ref&gt;Hagerman, p.164&lt;/ref&gt; The division was withdrawn from France, and embarked for England at the beginning of September.&lt;ref name=Otway191/&gt;

===Ardennes===
{{see|Battle of the Bulge}}

In England the brigade went into a period of recruitment and training, concentrating on house to house street fighting in the bombed areas of [[Southampton]] and [[Birmingham]]. The training programme culminated in Exercise Eve, an assault on the [[River Thames]], which was intended to simulate the [[River Rhine]] in Germany.&lt;ref name=saunders279&gt;Saunders, p.279&lt;/ref&gt;

By December the brigade was preparing for Christmas leave, when news of the German offensive in the [[Ardennes]] broke. As part of the [[First Allied Airborne Army]], 6th Airborne Division was available as a component of the strategic reserve for the Allied forces in northwest Europe. The other two divisions available in reserve, the American [[82nd Airborne Division|82nd]] and [[101st Airborne Division|101st Airborne]], were already at [[Rheims]] in northern France, and the 6th Airborne was sent by sea to Belgium to assist the defence.&lt;ref&gt;Hastings, p.239&lt;/ref&gt;. With 29 German and 33 Allied divisions involved, the Battle of the Bulge was the largest single battle on the [[Western Front (World War II)|Western Front]] during the war.&lt;ref&gt;Gregory, p.118&lt;/ref&gt; On [[Christmas Day]] the division moved up to take position in front of the spearhead of the German advance; by [[Boxing Day]] they had reached their allocated places in the defensive line between [[Dinant]] and [[Namur (city)|Namur]].&lt;ref name=saunders279/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;harc549&quot; /&gt; The 3rd Parachute Brigade were on the left, 5th Parachute Brigade on the right, and the airlanding brigade in reserve.&lt;ref name=harc549&gt;Harclerode, p.549&lt;/ref&gt; Over the next days the German advance was halted and forced back, until at the end of January 1945, the brigade crossed into Holland.&lt;ref name=&quot;harc549&quot;/&gt; Here the division was made responsible for the area along the [[River Maas]], between [[Venlo]] and [[Roermond]]. The brigade carried out patrols, on both sides of the river, against their opponents from the German [[7th Parachute Division (Germany)|7th Parachute Division]]. Near the end of February the division returned to England to prepare for another airborne mission, to cross the River Rhine into Germany.&lt;ref&gt;Saunders, p.283&lt;/ref&gt;

===Rhine===
{{see|Operation Varsity}}
[[File:Paras hamminkeln 25 march 1945.jpg|thumb|Airborne troops marching through [[Hamminkeln]], 25&amp;nbsp;March&amp;nbsp;1945]]

Whereas all other Allied airborne landings had been a surprise for the Germans, the Rhine crossing was expected, and their defences were reinforced in anticipation. The airborne operation was preceded by a two day round-the-clock bombing mission by the Allied air forces. Then on 23&amp;nbsp;March 3,500 artillery guns targeted the German positions. At dusk [[Operation Plunder]], an assault river crossing of the Rhine by the [[21st Army Group]], began.&lt;ref&gt;Gregory, p.85&lt;/ref&gt; For their part in Operation Varsity, the 6th Airborne Division was assigned to the American [[XVIII Airborne Corps (United States)|XVIII Airborne Corps]] alongside the United States [[17th Airborne Division (United States)|17th Airborne Division]].&lt;ref&gt;Harclerode, p.551&lt;/ref&gt;

The 6th Airlanding Brigade, now commanded by Brigadier Hugh Bellamy, was given several objectives in the operation. The 2nd OBLI, landing in the north, had to secure the bridges over the [[River Issel]]. The 1st RUR had the main road bridge over the river from [[Hamminkeln]] to [[Brunen]] as their objective, and the 12th Devons were to capture the town of Hamminkeln.&lt;ref&gt;Gregory, pp.83–84&lt;/ref&gt;

As in Normandy, the division's two parachute brigades were already on the ground before the 6th Airlanding Brigade started landing at 10:30 24&amp;nbsp;March&amp;nbsp;1945.&lt;ref&gt;Anderson, p.229&lt;/ref&gt; The German defenders had been alerted, and the gliders were met by a concentrated anti-aircraft barrage. This caused the brigade around 40 per cent casualties in men and 50 per cent in equipment.&lt;ref&gt;Cole, p.166&lt;/ref&gt;{{#tag:ref|The landings cost the brigade over 472 dead; 2nd OBLI had 103 dead and over 100 wounded, 1st RUR had 259 dead, and 12th Devons had 110 dead and 30 wounded.&lt;ref&gt;Harclerode, pp.563 565 566&lt;/ref&gt; Only five of the sixty-three gliders transporting 1st RUR landed completely intact.&lt;ref&gt;Hastings, p.428&lt;/ref&gt;|group=nb}} Nevertheless, by 11:00 the 2nd OBLI and 1st RUR had captured their objectives.&lt;ref&gt;Tugwell, p.275&lt;/ref&gt; The 12th Devons landed amongst a German armoured formation, but managed to gather enough men together to begin their attack on Hamminkeln at 11:35, and had secured the town by 12:00.&lt;ref name=harc564&gt;Harclerode, p.564&lt;/ref&gt;

At midnight the 2nd OBLI were attacked by a force of tanks and infantry. One of the battalion positions at the eastern side of the road bridge was overrun, and had to be recaptured with a counter-attack. Another attack two hours later was in danger of capturing the bridge, so Brigadier Bellamy ordered it blown up.&lt;ref name=harc564/&gt; German infantry attempted to infiltrate the brigade's positions throughout the night. At 05:30 German armour was detected approaching and the brigade called in [[close air support]] from [[Royal Air Force]] [[Hawker Typhoon|Typhoon]] [[Fighter-bomber|fighter bombers]], which destroyed several tanks.&lt;ref name=harc567&gt;Harclerode, p.567&lt;/ref&gt; The main road bridge, held by 1st RUR, was attacked at 07:00 by infantry and two tanks. The attack failed when the tanks were destroyed by the division's anti-tank guns.&lt;ref name=harc567/&gt; Later that day infantry from the [[15th Scottish Infantry Division]], supported by tanks, had advanced to the divisional area and took over the brigade's position. At the same time the division was ordered to prepare to advance eastwards from dawn on 26 March.&lt;ref&gt;Harclerode, p.568&lt;/ref&gt;

===Germany===

On 26&amp;nbsp;March the brigade advanced further into Germany, with the 1st RUR and the 12th Devons leading. The only opposition was German [[rearguard]] actions, and they reached [[Rhade]] by that evening and [[Limbeck]] the following day.&lt;ref&gt;Cole, p.172&lt;/ref&gt; They crossed the [[Dortmund–Ems Canal]] at dawn on 2&amp;nbsp;April, unopposed except for artillery fire. Later that day there was more resistance when they reached [[Lengerich, Lower Saxony|Lengerich]]. By 4&amp;nbsp;April the brigade was moving forward as fast as possible, supported by the 4th Armoured Battalion [[Grenadier Guards]], part of the [[6th Guards Tank Brigade (United Kingdom)|6th Guards Tank Brigade]].&lt;ref&gt;Cole, p.173&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Ferguson, p.30&lt;/ref&gt; [[Steinhuder Meer]] was reached on the 10&amp;nbsp;April, then in the following days [[Ulzen]] and [[Lüneburg]] were captured.&lt;ref&gt;Cole, pp.174–175&lt;/ref&gt; By 2&amp;nbsp;May they had reached the [[River Elbe]]. Expecting it to be defended in force, the division attacked at once, trying to catch the defenders unaware. The attack was successful and the river was crossed over a [[pontoon bridge]] left intact by the retreating Germans. That afternoon the leading troops of the [[3rd Parachute Brigade (United Kingdom)|3rd Parachute Brigade]] reached [[Mecklenburg]] and made contact with the leading men from the [[Soviet]] [[Red Army]] advancing from the east.&lt;ref&gt;Cole, p.175&lt;/ref&gt; Later that day the brigade reached [[Wismar]] on the [[Baltic Sea]], and remained there until 7&amp;nbsp;May when news was received of the German surrender.&lt;ref&gt;Cole, pp.175–176&lt;/ref&gt;

===Post war===
{{see|6th Airborne Division in Palestine}}

At the end of May 1945, the division was pulled out of Germany and returned to England. It was initially intended to send them to India to form an airborne corps with the [[44th Indian Airborne Division]].&lt;ref&gt;Gregory, p.125&lt;/ref&gt; The division’s advance party, formed around the 5th Parachute Brigade, had already arrived in India.&lt;ref&gt;Wilson, p.3&lt;/ref&gt; Following the Japanese surrender, all these plans changed. The post-war British Army only needed one airborne division, and the 6th Airborne was chosen to remain on strength. Reinforced by the [[2nd Parachute Brigade (United Kingdom)|2nd Parachute Brigade]], the division was sent to the [[Middle East]] as the Imperial Strategic Reserve.&lt;ref&gt;Wilson, p.4&lt;/ref&gt;

On 10&amp;nbsp;October&amp;nbsp;1945, the brigade arrived at the port of [[Haifa]], and after disembarking moved to [[Gaza]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Wilson5&quot; /&gt; After a short period of acclimatisation, the 6th Airlanding Brigade was deployed in the [[Samaria]] region, with the brigade headquarters at [[Ben Gurion International Airport|Lydda airfield]]. At the same time, the 6th Battalion [[Gordon Highlanders]], based at [[Tulkarm]], came under the brigade's command.&lt;ref&gt;Wilson, p.22&lt;/ref&gt; The first incident in the brigade area was on 31 October, when parties of armed Jews planted explosives on rail lines, which killed four and wounded eight when they exploded.&lt;ref&gt;Wilson, pp.24–25&lt;/ref&gt; Following attacks on [[coastguard]] stations, believed to be by members of the [[Palmach]], over the night of 24/25&amp;nbsp;November, the brigade carried out two operations to search settlements for those responsible.&lt;ref&gt;Wilson, pp.30–31&lt;/ref&gt; On 29&amp;nbsp;March&amp;nbsp;1946 the brigade was relocated to [[Jerusalem]] in preparation for leaving the division. On 3&amp;nbsp;April the 1st Parachute Brigade, which had been assigned to the division, arrived in Palestine. Their arrival made the glider formation surplus to requirements, so on 15&amp;nbsp;April the brigade was renumbered 31st Independent Infantry Brigade, and was no longer part of the British airborne forces.&lt;ref&gt;Wilson, pp.42–43&lt;/ref&gt;

==Order of battle==
;Commanders
*[[Brigadier]] [[Hugh Kindersley]]
*Brigadier [[Edwin William Conquest Flavell|Edward Flavell]]
*Brigadier [[Hugh Bellamy]]
*Brigadier [[Roger Bower]]

;Units assigned
*2nd Battalion, [[Oxfordshire and Buckinghamshire Light Infantry]]
*1st Battalion, [[Royal Ulster Rifles]]
*12th Battalion, [[Devonshire Regiment]]
*1st Battalion, [[Argyll and Sutherland Highlanders]]
*[[53rd (Worcestershire Yeomanry) Airlanding Light Regiment]]&amp;nbsp;– [[Royal Artillery]]
*249th (Airborne) Field Company&amp;nbsp;– [[Royal Engineers]]
*[[195th (Airlanding) Field Ambulance]]&amp;nbsp;– [[Royal Army Medical Corps]]

;Units attached
*[[1st Belgian Infantry Brigade]]
*[[Royal Netherlands Motorized Infantry Brigade]]
*6th Battalion, [[Gordon Highlanders]]

==Notes==
;Footnotes
{{reflist|group=nb}}
;Citations
{{reflist|3}}

==References==
{{refbegin}}
*{{cite book|last=Anderson|first=Duncan|title=The fall of the Reich–The Campaigns of World War II|publisher=Zenith Imprint|location=Minneapolis, MN|year=2000|isbn=9780760309223}}
*{{cite book|last=Cole|first=Howard N|title=On Wings of Healing: The Story of the Airborne Medical Services 1940–1960|publisher=William Blackwood|location=Edinburgh, UK|year=1963|oclc=29847628}}
*{{cite book|last=Flint|first=Keith|title=Airborne Armour: Tetrarch, Locust, Hamilcar and the 6th Airborne Armoured Reconnaissance Regiment 1938–1950|location=Solihull, UK|publisher=Helion &amp; Company Ltd|year=2006|isbn=187462237X}}
*{{cite book|last1=Ford|first1=Ken|last2=Zaloga|first2=Steven J|authorlink2=Steven Zaloga|title=Overlord the D-Day Landings|publisher=Osprey Publishing|location=Oxford, UK|year=2009|isbn=9781846034244}}
*{{cite book|last=Fowler|first=Will|title=Pegasus Bridge&amp;nbsp;— Benouville, D-Day 1944|series=Raid Series|publisher=Osprey Publishing|location=Oxford, UK|year=2010|isbn=1846038480}}
*{{cite book|last=Gale|first=Richard Nelson|authorlink=Richard Nelson Gale|title=With the 6th Airborne Division in Normandy|publisher=Sampson Low, Marston &amp; Co Ltd|location=Great Missenden, UK|year=1948|oclc=464063862}}
*{{cite book|last1=Gregory|first1=Barry|last2=Batchelor|first2=John|title=Airborne Warfare, 1918–1945|publisher=Exeter Books|year=1979|location=Exeter, UK|isbn=978-0896730250}}
*{{cite book|last1=Guard|first1=Julie|title=Airborne: World War II Paratroopers in Combat|publisher=Osprey Publishing|location=Oxford, UK|year=2007|isbn=1846031966}}
*{{cite book|last=Hagerman|first=Bart|title=USA Airborne: 50th Anniversary|publisher=Turner Publishing Company|year=1990|isbn=9780938021902|location=New York}}
*{{Cite book|last=Harclerode|first=Peter|title=Wings Of War&amp;nbsp;– Airborne Warfare 1918–1945|publisher=Weidenfeld &amp; Nicolson|location=London|year=2005|isbn=0304367303}}
*{{cite book|last=Hastings|first=Max|authorlink=Max Hastings|title=Armageddon: The Battle for Germany 1944-45|date=2005|publisher=Macmillan|isbn= 0-330-49062-1}}
*{{cite book|last=Lynch|first=Tim|title=Silent Skies: Gliders At War 1939–1945|location=Barnsley, UK|publisher=Pen &amp; Sword Military|year=2008|isbn=0750306335}}
*{{cite book|last=Moreman|first=Timothy Robert|title=British Commandos 1940–46|publisher=Osprey Publishing|location=Oxford, UK|year=2006|isbn=184176986X}}
*{{cite book|last1=Morgan|last2=Hughes|first1=Gerald|first2=Gavin|title=Southern Ireland and the Liberation of France: New Perspectives|publisher=Peter Lang publishing Group|year=2010|isbn=9783034301909|location=New York}}
*{{cite book| last=Otway| first=Lieutenant-Colonel T.B.H| title=The Second World War 1939–1945 Army&amp;nbsp;– Airborne Forces| publisher=Imperial War Museum|location=London|year= 1990| isbn=0901627577}}
*{{cite book|last1=Peters|first1=Mike|first2=Luuk|last2=Buist|title=Glider Pilots at Arnhem|publisher=Pen &amp; Sword Books|location=Barnsley, UK|year=2009|isbn=1844157636}}
*{{cite book|last=Saunders|first=Hilary Aidan St. George|title=The Red Beret: the Story of the Parachute Regiment at War, 1940–1945|edition=4|publisher=New English Library|location=London|year=1978|oclc=2927434}}
*{{Cite book|last1=Shortt|first1=James|authorlink=James Shortt|last2=McBride|first2=Angus|title=The Special Air Service|publisher=Osprey Publishing|location=Oxford, UK|year=1981|isbn=0850453968}}
*{{cite book|last=Smith|first=Claude|title=History of the Glider Pilot Regiment|location=London|publisher=Pen &amp; Sword Aviation|year=1992|isbn=1844156265}}
*{{cite book|last=Tugwell|first=Maurice|title=Airborne to Battle: A History of Airborne Warfare, 1918–1971|publisher=Kimber|location=London|year=1971|isbn=0718302621}}
*{{cite book|last=Wilson|first=Dare|title=With the 6th Airborne Division in Palestine 1945–1948|year=2008|publisher=Pen and Sword Military|location=Barnsley, UK|isbn=9781844157716}}
{{refend}}
{{British parachute units of the Second World War}}

{{Use dmy dates|date=June 2011}}

[[Category:Military units and formations established in 1943]]
[[Category:Military units and formations disestablished in 1946]]
[[Category:Airborne infantry brigades of the United Kingdom]]
[[Category:Airborne warfare]]
[[Category:Brigades of the British Army in World War II]]
[[Category:Operation Overlord]]
[[Category:Brigades of the British Army in World War II|6 Airlanding]]

[[de:6. Britische Luftlandedivision]]
[[es:6ª División Aerotransportada (Reino Unido)]]
[[fr:6e division aéroportée (Royaume-Uni)]]
[[he:כלניות]]
[[nl:6th Airborne Division (Verenigd Koninkrijk)]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
