<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="16893264" ns="0" title="Svayam Bhagavan"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">:''This article is about a Hindu theological concept: the original or absolute manifestation of God. For other meanings, see [[Krishna (disambiguation)]] and [[Bhagavan (disambiguation)]].''

{{Hindu philosophy}}
'''Svayam Bhagavan''' ([[IAST]] ''{{IAST|svayam bhagavān}}''), &quot;'''The Lord'''&quot; or '''Lord Himself''', is a [[Sanskrit]]  theological term. The term refers to the concept of absolute representation of the monotheistic God as ''[[Bhagavan]]'' within [[Hinduism]].

It is most often used in [[Gaudiya Vaishnava]] Krishna-centered theology as referring to [[Krishna]]. The title ''Svayam Bhagavan'' is used exclusively to designate Krishna,&lt;ref name=Gupta2007 /&gt; while there are conflicting semantics or other usages in the [[Bhagavata Purana]]. Traditions of Gaudiya Vaishnavas, the [[Nimbarka Sampradaya]] and followers of [[Vallabha]] consider him to be the source of all [[avatar]]s,&lt;ref name = jsn/&gt; and the source of [[Vishnu]] and [[Narayana]] himself. As such, he is therefore regarded as ''Svayam Bhagavan''.&lt;ref name = &quot;Delmonico2004&quot;&gt;{{cite journal
| author = Delmonico, N.
| year = 2004
| title = The History Of Indic Monotheism And Modern Chaitanya Vaishnavism
| journal = The Hare Krishna Movement: the Postcharismatic Fate of a Religious Transplant
| url = http://books.google.com/?id=mBMxPdgrBhoC&amp;pg=PA31&amp;dq=Vaisnava+monotheism
| accessdate = 2008-04-12
| publisher = Columbia University Press
| isbn = 9780231122566
| ref = harv
}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name = &quot;Elkman1986&quot;&gt;{{cite book
| author = Elkman, S.M.
| coauthors = Gosvami, J.
| year = 1986
| title = Jiva Gosvamin's Tattvasandarbha: A Study on the Philosophical and Sectarian Development of the Gaudiya Vaishnava Movement
| publisher = Motilal Banarsidass Pub
| isbn =
}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name = Dimock1989/&gt;

The term is seldom used to refer to other forms of Krishna and/or [[Vishnu]] within the context of certain religious texts such as the [[Bhagavata Purana]], and also within other sects of Vaishnavism.

Though Krishna is recognized as ''Svayam Bhagavan'' by many,&lt;ref name = &quot;RKm&quot;/&gt; he is also perceived and understood from an eclectic assortment of perspectives and viewpoints.&lt;ref name=Mahony1987&gt;{{cite journal
| author = Mahony, W.K.
| year = 1987
| title = Perspectives on Krishna's Various Personalities
| journal = History of Religions
| volume = 26
| issue = 3
| pages = 333–335
| jstor = 198702)
| doi = 10.1086/463085
| ref = harv
}}&lt;/ref&gt;  When [[Krishna]] is recognized to be ''Svayam Bhagavan'', it can be understood that this is the belief of [[Gaudiya Vaishnavism]],&lt;ref name=Kennedy1925&gt;{{cite book
| author = Kennedy, M.T.
| year = 1925
| title = The Chaitanya Movement: A Study of the Vaishnavism of Bengal
| publisher = H. Milford, Oxford university press
| isbn =
}}&lt;/ref&gt; the [[Vallabha Sampradaya]],&lt;ref name = &quot;flood&quot;&gt;{{cite book
| author = Flood, Gavin D.
| authorlink = Gavin Flood
| title = An introduction to Hinduism
| publisher = Cambridge University Press
| location = Cambridge, UK
| year = 1996
| pages = 341
| isbn = 0-521-43878-0
| url = http://books.google.com/?id=KpIWhKnYmF0C&amp;printsec=frontcover&amp;dq=gavin+flood
| accessdate = 2008-04-21
}}&quot;Early Vaishnava worship focuses on three deities who become fused together, namely Vasudeva-Krishna, Krishna-Gopala, and Narayana, who in turn all become identified with Vishnu. Put simply, Vasudeva-Krishna and Krishna-Gopala were worshiped by groups generally referred to as Bhagavatas, while Narayana was worshipped by the Pancaratra sect.&quot;&lt;/ref&gt; and the [[Nimbarka Sampradaya]], where Krishna is accepted to be the source of all other avatars, and the source of [[Vishnu]] himself. This belief is drawn primarily &quot;from the famous statement of the Bhagavatam&quot;&lt;ref name=Gupta2007 /&gt;(1.3.28).&lt;ref name = Rosen&gt;''Essential [[Hinduism]]'' S. Rosen, 2006, Greenwood Publishing Group [http://books.google.com/books?id=VlhX1h135DMC&amp;pg=PA124&amp;dq=Krishna+is+the+original+Personality+of+Godhead&amp;client=firefox-a&amp;sig=2Yojs3j3lTcocPQ7RaIqBnpLrq0 p.124] ISBN 0275990060&lt;/ref&gt;

A different viewpoint differing from this theological concept is the concept of [[Krishna]] as an ''[[avatar]]'' of [[Narayana]] or [[Vishnu]]. It should be however noted that although it is usual to speak of Vishnu as the source of the avataras, this is only one of the names of the God of [[Vaishnavism]], who is also known as [[Narayana]], [[Vasudeva]] and Krishna and behind each of those names there is a divine figure with attributed supremacy in [[Vaishnavism]].&lt;ref name = Krishna4&gt;
{{Harvnb|Matchett|2000|p=4}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Meaning==

The theological interpretation of ''{{IAST|svayam bhagavān}}'' differs with each tradition and the literal translation of the term has been understood in several distinct ways. Translated from the [[Sanskrit language]], the term literary means &quot;[[Bhagavan]] Himself&quot; or &quot;directly [[Bhagavan]]&quot;.&lt;ref name=Gupta2007 /&gt; [[Gaudiya Vaishnava]] tradition often translates it within its perspective as ''primeval Lord'' or ''original Personality of Godhead'', but also considers the terms such as ''Supreme Personality of Godhead'' and ''Supreme God'' as an equivalent to the term ''Svayam Bhagavan'', and may also choose to apply these terms to  Vishnu, [[Narayana]] and many of their associated [[Avatar]]s.&lt;ref name=Knapp2005&gt;{{cite book
| author = Knapp, S.
| year = 2005
| title = The Heart of Hinduism: The Eastern Path to Freedom, Empowerment and Illumination -
| publisher = iUniverse
| isbn =
}} &quot;Krishna is the primeval Lord, the original Personality of Godhead, so He can  expand Himself into unlimited forms with all potencies.&quot; [http://books.google.com/books?id=a2KPChj7lTwC&amp;pg=PA161 page 161]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name= ICJKnott&gt;{{cite journal
| author = Dr. Kim Knott,
| year = 1993
| title = Contemporary Theological Trends In The Hare Krishna Movement: A Theology of Religions
| url = http://content.iskcon.com/icj/1_1/knott.html
| accessdate = 2008-04-12
| ref = harv
}}...&quot;''Bhakti'', the highest path, was that of surrender to Lord Krishna, the way of pure devotional service to the Supreme Personality of Godhead&quot;.&lt;/ref&gt;

Early commentators of [[Bhagavata Purana]] such as [[Madhvacharya]] translated the term ''Svayam Bhagavan'' as &quot;he who has ''bhagavata''&quot;; meaning &quot;he who has the quality of possessing all good qualities&quot;.&lt;ref name = Dimock1989&gt;{{cite book
| author = Dimock Jr, E.C.
| coauthors = Dimock, E.C.
| year = 1989
| title = The Place of the Hidden Moon: Erotic Mysticism in the Vaisnava-Sahajiya Cult of Bengal
| publisher = University Of Chicago Press
| isbn =
}} [http://books.google.com/books?id=EAYa1BtUTm0C&amp;pg=PA132&amp;dq=Svayam+bhagavan&amp;sig=jcyEA-4tyPoddQmWg-FnYKDBgEY page 132]&lt;/ref&gt; Others have translated it simply as &quot;the [[Bhagavan|Lord]] Himself&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;KK&quot;&gt;{{cite book |author=K. Klostermaier |title=The Charles Strong Trust Lectures, 1972-1984 |publisher=Brill Academic Pub |location= |year=1997 |pages=206 |isbn=90-04-07863-0 |quote= For his worshippers he is not an avatara in the usual sense, but Svayam Bhagavan, the Lord himself.|url= http://books.google.com/?id=F_0UAAAAIAAJ&amp;pg=PA109&amp;dq=Svayam+bhagavan |accessdate= | others = Crotty, Robert B.}} p.109 Klaus Klostermaier translates it simply as &quot;the Lord Himself&quot;&lt;/ref&gt; Followers of Vishnu-centered [[sampradaya]]s of Vaishnavism rarely address this term, but believe that it refers to their belief that Krishna is among the highest and fullest of all ''[[Avatar]]s''&lt;ref name = Pal1958/&gt; and is considered to be the &quot;''paripurna avatara''&quot;, complete in all respects and the same as the original.&lt;ref&gt;
{{cite web
|url=http://www.tirumala.org/sapthagiri/122002/purana.htm
|title=Sapthagiri
|publisher=www.tirumala.org
|accessdate=2008-05-03
|last=
|first=
}} Parashara Maharishi, [[Vyasa]]'s father had devoted the largest Amsa (part) in Vishnu Purana to the description of Sri Krishna Avatara the ''Paripoorna Avatara''. And according to Lord Krishna's own (instructions) ''upadesha'', &quot;he who knows (the secrets of) His (Krishna's) Janma (birth) and Karma (actions) will not remain in [[samsara]] (''punar janma naiti- maam eti'') and attain Him after leaving the mortal coil.&quot; (BG 4.9). [[Parasara]] Maharishi ends up Amsa 5 with a phalashruti in an identical vein ([[Vishnu Purana]] .5.38.94)&lt;/ref&gt; According to them [[Krishna]] is described in the [[Bhagavata Purana]] as the ''purnavatara'' (or complete manifestation) of the Bhagavan, while other incarnations are called partial. &quot;Krishna being the Bhagavan Himself, the mind of man fixed on him intensely, whatever be the motive and however ignorantly it might be.&quot;(p.&amp;nbsp;334)&lt;ref name = &quot;RKm&quot;/&gt; Generally there is a universal acceptance of the uniqueness of Krishna incarnation throughout [[Hinduism]], as well as the principles involved in His life and personality for which He has been described as ''Svayam Bhagavan''.&lt;ref name = &quot;RKm&quot;&gt;{{cite book
|author=Mepathur Narayana Bhattatiri
|title=Narayaneeyam-Bhagavata, Condensed Edition
|publisher=Sri Ramakrishna Math
|location=
|year=2003
|pages=
|isbn=81-7120-419-8
|oclc=
|doi=
}}pp.234-239&lt;/ref&gt;

==Perspectives==
===Supporting Views===
There is an element of countenance in many Krishna centered traditions to the subordination of Krishna to Vishnu. The reasons for that are given that it was the easiest way to accommodate Krishna's human story within the composite [[Vaishnava]] theological perspective. These &quot;core texts assert and defend the ultimacy of Krsna's identity&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{Harvnb|Valpey|2006|p=154}}&lt;/ref&gt; However inclusion of Krishna in the list of avataras does not necessarily subordinated him to Vishnu as one of the latter's expansions.&lt;ref name = Krishna182&gt;
{{cite book
|author=Matchett, Freda
|title=Krsna, Lord or Avatara? the relationship between Krsna and Visnu: in the context of the Avatara myth as presented by the Harivamsa, the Visnupurana and the Bhagavatapurana
|publisher=Routledge
|location=Surrey
|year=2000
|pages=254
|isbn=0-7007-1281-X
|oclc=
|doi=
|accessdate=
|url=http://books.google.com/?id=1oqTYiPeAxMC&amp;printsec=frontcover
}}
p. 182-183&lt;/ref&gt; Early authors, such as 12th century [[Jayadeva]] considered [[dasavatara]] to be principal incarnations of Kirshna, rather than Vishnu.

The prime supporters of the Krishna-centered theology, [[Gaudiya Vaishnavas]] and followers of the [[Vallabha Sampradaya]] [[Nimbarka Sampradaya]], use the [[Gopala Tapani Upanishad]],&lt;ref name=Trip&gt;{{cite book |author=B. V. Tripurari |title=Gopala-tapani Upanisad |publisher=Audarya Press |location= |year=2004 |pages= |isbn=1-932771-12-3 |oclc= |doi=}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Vedanta Sutras]]&lt;ref name=Gupta2007 /&gt; and other Hindu scriptures&lt;ref name = Bhaktivinda/&gt; such as the [[Bhagavata Purana]] and the [[Brahma Vaivarta Purana]], among others, to support their view that Krishna is indeed the ''Svayam Bhagavan''. This belief was summarized by the 16th century author [[Jiva Goswami]] in some of his works, such as ''Krishna-sandarbha''.&lt;ref name=Gupta2007&gt;{{cite book
| author = Gupta, Ravi M.
| coauthors =
| year = 2007
| title = Caitanya Vaisnava Vedanta of Jiva Gosvami
| publisher = Routledge
| isbn = 0415405483
}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=Gupta2004&gt;{{cite book
| author = Gupta, Ravi M.
| coauthors =
| year = 2004
| title = Caitanya Vaisnava Vedanta: Acintyabhedabheda in Jiva Gosvami's Catursutri tika
| publisher = University Of Oxford
| isbn =
}}&lt;/ref&gt; While Krishna himself if mentioned in one of the earliest texts of [[Vedic]] literature - [[Rig-Veda]].&lt;ref&gt;
Sunil Kumar Bhattacharya ''Krishna-cult in Indian Art''. 1996
M.D. Publications Pvt. Ltd. ISBN 8175330015 p.126:  &quot;According to (D.R.Bhadarkar), the word Krishna referred to in the expression 'Krishna-drapsah' in the Rig- Veda, denotes the very same Krishna&quot;.&lt;/ref&gt; 

In the sixth book of the [[Hindu epic]] [[Mahābhārata]], the ''Bhishma Parva'' (where the ''[[Bhagavad Gita]]'' is part of), Krishna offers numerous quotations that reaffirm the belief that he himself is the ''Svayam Bhagavan''. Verse [http://www.asitis.com/7/7.html 7.7] of the [[Bhagavad Gita]], is often used to support the opinion that Krishna himself is the ''Svayam Bhagavan'', and that no impersonal form of [[Brahman]] supersedes his existence, as it is an common view that [[Bhagavad Gita]] was propounding Krishna-theism before first major proponents of [[Advaita Vedanta|monism]].&lt;ref name = &quot;IST&quot;&gt;{{cite book
|author=
|authorlink=
|editor = S. Devadas Pillai
|others=
|title=Indian Sociology Through Ghurye: A Dictionary
|edition=
|language=
|publisher=South Asia Books
|location=Columbia, Mo
|year=1997
|origyear=
|pages=403
|quote=
|isbn=81-7154-807-5
|oclc=
|doi=
|url=http://books.google.com/?id=P3uD22Ghqs4C&amp;pg=PA283
|accessdate=
}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Other two pervading understandings of the position of ''Svayam Bhagavan'' asserted in the Gita are connected to other, not Krishna-centered, traditions. One tradition follows predominately the views of [[Sankaracharya]] commentary on [[Brahma Sutras]] and is referred as ''[[mayavada|maya-vad]]''&lt;ref name = &quot;IST&quot;/&gt; which justifies ''Svayam Bhagavan'' supremacy by a concept of illusion or [[maya (illusion)|maya]].

The second alternative understanding of the evident supremacy of  ''Svayam Bhagavan'' in the Gita, is a popular view on Krishna being the highest and fullest [[Avatar]] of the Lord, [[Vishnu]] or [[Narayana]].&lt;ref name = Pal1958&gt;{{cite book
| author = Bipin Chandra Pal
| year = 1964, 132 pages
| title = Shree Krishna: Letters Written to a Christian Friend
| publisher = Yugayatri/New India Printing
&amp; Publishing Co.
| quote = First edition published in 1938 under the title of 'Europe asks: who is Shree Krishna'.
| isbn =
}}p. 31:  Shree Krishna stands at the top of this series. He is therefore called by his votaries as Purna Avatara or the highest and fullest incarnation of the Lord.&lt;/ref&gt; &quot;The Bhagavad Gita depicts Krishna not only as [[Brahman]] but also as an 'Avatar of Vishnu and the friend of [[Arjuna]].&quot;&lt;ref&gt;[http://books.google.com/books?id=dys3AAAAIAAJ&amp;dq=Avatara+of+Narayana+purna++Krishna+Gita Panjab University Journal of Medieval Indian Literature. Page 56] Panjab University Sheikh Baba Farid Dept. of Medieval Indian Literature&lt;/ref&gt; In summary in accordance with this view ''Svayam Bhagavan'' Krishna is considered to be the ''purna-avatara'' (full incarnation) of [[Vishnu]] or, according to some, of the universal [[Narayana]] who transcends even [[Brahman]].&lt;ref name = jsn&gt;''Bhagawan Swaminarayan bicentenary commemoration volume, 1781-1981.'' p. 154: ...Shri Vallabhacharya [and] Shri Swaminarayan... Both of them designate the highest reality as Krishna, who is both the highest avatara and also the source of other avataras. To quote R. Kaladhar Bhatt in this context. &quot;In this transcendental devotieon (Nirguna Bhakti), the sole Deity and only&quot; is Krishna. [http://books.google.com/books?id=_Q0YAAAAIAAJ&amp;q=Avatara+Swaminarayan+Krishna+origina%3B&amp;dq=Avatara+Swaminarayan+Krishna+origina%3B New Dimensions in Vedanta Philosophy - Page 154], Sahajānanda, [http://books.google.com/books?q=+subject:%22Vedanta%22 Vedanta]. 1981&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;ref name = Divine&gt;{{cite book
| author = Sri Swami Chidananda
| year = 1964, 132 pages
| title = The Divine Name and Its Practice: Souvenir on the Occasion of the Double
| publisher = [http://books.google.com/books?q=inpublisher:%22Divine+Life+Society%22&amp;cad=0 Divine Life Society]
&amp; Publishing Co.
| quote = Preface Sri Swami Krishnananda
| isbn =
}}p. 24&lt;/ref&gt;

Supremacy or a concept of ''originality'' is often referred to the words pf Krishna himself, as for example, [[Abhinavagupta]] of yet another tradition of Hinduism, introduces a quotation from the [[Bhagavad-gita]] that 'I', referring to [[Krishna]], is the highest self who transcends the perishable and imperishable.&lt;ref name=&quot;Flood150&quot;&gt;{{Harvnb|Flood|2006|p=150}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Other Vaishnava views===

The Sri Vaishnavas identify [[Vishnu]] with the [[Brahman]], while [[Krishna]]-centered traditions will associate [[Para Brahman]] with Krishna as Svayam Bhagavan. According to [[Ramanujacharya]], Brahman is [[personal god|personal]]. Indeed, he is the ''supreme'' person, creator and Lord, who leads souls to salvation. Far from having no (positive) attributes, as some [[Advaita Vedanta]] followers maintain, Brahman is the ''sum'' of all “noble attributes” — i.e. omniscient, omnipotent, omnipresent, and all-merciful, all qualities attributed to Vishnu by all Vaishavas. According to South Indian traditions he is also ''advitya'' ([[Sanskrit]] meaning without rival). To Vaishnavas, [[Shiva]], [[Brahma]], and the other gods of the [[Hindu]] pantheon are viewed as Brahman's agents or [[servant of God|servants]], created and commissioned by him. Some Vaishnavas consider them to be or see that they have the same status that of [[angels]] have in the western religious traditions.&lt;ref&gt;
{{cite web
|url=http://www.seop.leeds.ac.uk/entries/monotheism/#7.3
|title=Monotheism (Stanford Encyclopedia of Philosophy) ''Nov 1, 2005''
|publisher=www.seop.leeds.ac.uk
|accessdate=2008-07-26
}}
&lt;/ref&gt;

“The entire complex of intelligent and non-intelligent beings - is viewed as real and constitutes the form, i. e., the body of the highest Brahman”.&lt;ref&gt;Ramanuja (1962) p. 88&lt;/ref&gt; A soul-body relationship, according to Ramanujacharya, is “entirely subordinate” to its soul, having no independent reality or value.&lt;ref&gt;Ramanuja (1962) p. 424&lt;/ref&gt; However Ramanujacharya himself did not stress a subordination of the 'puravatara' Krishna to Vishnu.

However, [[Vaishnava]] traditions do not adhere to the concept of ''Svayam Bhagavan'' with the same views as those who support the concept.&lt;ref name=Tapasyananda1990&gt;{{cite book
| author = Tapasyananda, S.
| year = 1982
| title = Śrīmadbhāgavatam-Srimad Bhagavata, the Holy Book of God
| publisher = Sri Ramakrishna Math, Madras
| isbn =
}}Page xxvi{{Verify credibility|date=July 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt;{{Verify credibility|date=July 2008}}
To support their view they quote the 149th chapter of  ''Anushāsanaparva'' in the epic [[Mahabharata]], [[Bhisma]] which states, with [[Krishna]] present, that mankind will be free from all sorrows by chanting the ''[[Vishnu sahasranama]]''', which are the thousand names of the all-pervading [[supreme being]] [[Vishnu]], who is the master of all the worlds, supreme over the ''[[Deva (Hinduism)|devas]]'' and who is one with [[Brahman]].&lt;ref&gt;see, Ganguli English translation of Mahabharata, Chapter 148, at http://www.sacred-texts.com/hin/m13/m13b113.htm&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;For Sanskrit text and translation, see: Tapasyananda, Vishnu Sahasrnama, Ramakrishna Mission pp. 3-4.{{Verify credibility|date=July 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt; This seems to indicate that Krishna is identical with Vishnu. Indeed, [[Krishna]] himself said, &quot;Arjuna, one may be desirous of praising by reciting the thousand names. But, on my part, I feel praised by one [[shloka]]. There is no doubt about it.” &lt;ref&gt;[http://www.srivaishnavan.com/tomcat/visnu.html Srivaishnavism&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;

Many Vaishnava schools have different interpretation of the concept as for example followers of the [[Swaminarayan Sampraday]] believe that Lord [[Narayana]] manifested himself as [[Lord Swaminarayan]].&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web | url=http://www.swaminarayanwales.org.uk/Murtis/murtis.asp | title=Lord Narayan manifested himself as Lord Swaminarayan}}&lt;/ref&gt; This view is only supported within their particular tradition.

===Comparison===

Some early schools of thought, such as Pancaratra in particular, refer to Vasudeva-Krishna (Krishna, the son of Vasudeva) as the source of all incarnations and as no different from the ultimate and absolute reality, and as non-distinct from Vasudeva and any other manifestations of the supreme self.&lt;ref name = Flood2006&gt;{{cite book
 | author = Flood, G.D.
 | year = 2006
 | title = The Tantric Body: The Secret Tradition of Hindu Religion
 | publisher = IB Tauris
 | isbn = 1845110129
}} p.102-105 - describes  Vasudeva-Krishna, (Krishna son of Vasudeva) as the source of all or as the same the ultimate reality, non-distinct from Vasudeva and other manifestations. Having a hundred-fold radiance of fire from whom all other forms of [[Purusha]], Achuta and Satya emanate.&lt;/ref&gt;

==Krishnaism==
{{main|Krishnaism}}
The term Krishnaism has been used to describe the cults of Krishna, reserving the term &quot;Vaishnavism&quot; for cults focusing on Vishnu in which [[Krishna]] is an Avatar, rather than a transcended being.&lt;ref&gt;Flood  p. 117&lt;/ref&gt;

&quot;Greater Krishnaism&quot; corresponds to the second and dominant phase of [[Vaishnavism]], revolving around the cults of [[Vasudeva]], Krishna, and [[Gopala]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://philtar.ucsm.ac.uk/encyclopedia/hindu/devot/vaish.html Vaishnava] University of Cumbria website Retrieved on 5-21-2008&lt;/ref&gt; Today the faith has a significant following outside of India as well.&lt;ref name=&quot;Princeton&quot;&gt;{{cite book
|author=Graham M. Schweig
|title=Dance of Divine Love: The Rڄasa Lڄilڄa of Krishna from the Bhڄagavata Purڄa. na, India's classic sacred love story
|publisher=Princeton University Press
|location=Princeton, N.J
|year=2005
|pages=Front Matter
|isbn=0-691-11446-3
|oclc=
|doi=
}}&lt;/ref&gt; Supremacy of Krishna is the key concept of [[Krishnaism]]. [[Gaudiya]] is one of the main traditions worshiping [[Radha Krishna]] that developed this concept.
[[File:Krishna as Svayam Bhagavan in relation to Vishnu.png|thumb|400px|Relationship between different forms of Krishna as [[avatar|paripurna avatara]] of [[Vishnu]] and as ''svayam bhagavan'' being direct representation of ''svayam rupa''.]]

==Gaudiya Vaishnava perspective==
===Theory of avataras===
Primary theology of Caitanyaite or [[Gaudiya]] traditions is based and presented in [[Bhagavata Purana]] and [[Caitanya Caritamrita]].&lt;ref name = &quot;Valpey&quot;&gt;{{cite book
|author=Valpey, Kenneth Russell
|title=Attending {{IAST|Kṛṣṇa}}'s image: {{IAST|Caitanya Vaiṣṇava}} mūrti-sevā as devotional truth
|publisher=Routledge
|location=New York
|year=2006
|pages=
|isbn=0-415-38394-3
|oclc=
|doi=
}}Ch. 1&lt;/ref&gt;''Svayam'' in ''Svayam rupa''  does not imply one and only, and all conceptions by previous [[Vaishnava]] traditions, according to the [[Gaudiya Vaishnavas]] beliefs, fall under a second category, ''tad ekatma rupa''&lt;ref name = beck/&gt; (meaning: one that ''one'' and ''not different'').&lt;ref&gt;
{{cite web
|url=http://vedabase.net/cc/madhya/20/165/en
|title=Sri Caitanya Caritamrta Madhya-lila Chapter 20 Verse 165
|publisher=[[Bhaktivedanta Book Trust]]
|accessdate=2008-05-07
|last=Swami Prabhupada
|first=A.C. Bhaktivedanta
}}
&lt;/ref&gt; 'Svayam' as a term means ''not depending on others''  or ''being himself''.
&lt;ref name=Gupta2004&gt;{{cite book
| author = Gupta, Ravi M.
| coauthors =
| year = 2004
| title = Caitanya Vaisnava Vedanta: Acintyabhedabheda in Jiva Gosvami's Catursutri tika
| publisher = University Of Oxford
| isbn =
}}Chapter: Caitanya Vaishnava Hermeneutics.&lt;/ref&gt; In his instruction to Sanatana Goswami, at Kasi, Chaitanya Mahaprabhu explains the implications of the ''vadanti'' verse: &quot;The word ''brahman'' refers to ''Svayam Bhagavan'', who has one consciousness without a second, and without whom there is nothing else.&quot; (Gupta 2007, p 36).&lt;ref name=Gupta2007 /&gt;

[[File:UdupiTulasiKrsna.jpg|thumb|left|The deity of Tulasi Krishna at [[Udupi]]. Krishna is the main deity worshipped by the followers of [[Madhvacharya]].]]
[[Rupa Goswami|Rūpa Gosvāmī]] has described the ''{{IAST|svayaṁ-rūpa}}'' in his ''{{IAST|Laghu-bhāgavatāmṛta}}'':&lt;ref&gt;[[Rupa Goswami]], ''{{IAST|Laghu-bhāgavatāmṛta}}'' ({{IAST|Pūrva-khaṇḍa}},verse 12) Kusakrathadasa, 1990, [http://books.google.ie/books?q=inpublisher:%22Krsna+Institute%22&amp;client=firefox-a&amp;source=gbs_summary_r&amp;cad=0 Krsna Institute], ISBN 156130008X
:[http://vedabase.net/cc/madhya/20/165/en ''{{IAST|ananyāpekṣi yad rūpaṁ svayaṁ-rūpaḥ sa ucyate}}''].&lt;/ref&gt; &quot;The form of the Supreme Personality of Godhead that does not depend on other forms is called ''{{IAST|svayaṁ-rūpa}}'', the original form.&quot;&lt;ref name = beck&gt;{{Harvnb|Beck|2005|p=39|loc=page 39 'According to Ortodox Gaudiya.. Krishnas svarupa, or true form manifests in three ways. His svayam-rupa or transcendent form is self-existent, not dependent on anything. His tadekatma rupa is identical in essence to his true form, though it differs in appearance (and would include such forms of Krishna as Narayana and Vasudeva). His avesa form has Krishna appearing though in varying degrees of possession'}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name = rupa1990/&gt;

The ''tad-ekātma-rūpa'' forms&lt;ref name = beck/&gt; are also described in the {{IAST|Laghu-bhāgavatāmṛta}} &lt;ref name  = rupa1990&gt;Srila [[Rupa Gosvami]]'s ''Sri Laghu-Bhagavatamrta'', Translated by Kusakrathadasa, 1990, [http://books.google.ie/books?q=inpublisher:%22Krsna+Institute%22&amp;client=firefox-a&amp;source=gbs_summary_r&amp;cad=0 Krsna Institute], ISBN 156130008X&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Rupa Goswami, ''{{IAST|Laghu-bhāgavatāmṛta}}'' ({{IAST|Pūrva-khaṇḍa}}, verse 14)
: ''{{IAST|yad rūpaṁ tad-abhedena svarūpeṇa virājate}}''
: ''{{IAST|ākṛtyādibhir anyādṛk sa tad-ekātma-rūpakaḥ}}''
“The tad-ekātma-rūpa forms exist simultaneously with the {{IAST|svayaṁ-rūpa}} form and are nondifferent. At the same time, their bodily features and specific activities appear to be different.” quoted in {{cite web
|url=http://vedabase.net/cc/madhya/20/165/en
|title=Sri Caitanya Caritamrta Madhya-lila Chapter 20 Verse 165
|publisher=[[Bhaktivedanta Book Trust]]
|accessdate=2008-05-07
|last=Swami Prabhupada
|first=A.C. Bhaktivedanta
}}
&lt;/ref&gt;
&quot;The'' tad-ekātma-rūpa ''forms simultaneous to ''{{IAST|svayaṁ-rūpa}}'' form and are non-different.&lt;ref name = beck/&gt; At the same time by their bodily features and specific activities they appear to be different.&quot;

Two best known Vedic descriptions of the creation are [[purusha sukta]] and [[nasadiya sukta]].  One hymn addresses to Vishvakarma, The one who makes all. To beliefs of [[Vaishnavas]],&lt;ref&gt;Klaus K. Klostermaier, ''A Survey of Hinduism''.  Page 113, 1994, ISBN 0791421090&lt;/ref&gt; the ''Visvakarma Sukta'' of [[Rig Veda]] (10.82) refers to {{IAST|Garbhodakasayi Viṣṇu}} indirectly as the Supreme God: The waters verily first retained the embryo in which all the gods were aggregated, single deposited on the navel of the unborn (ajah), in which all beings abide.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.sacred-texts.com/hin/rigveda/rv10082.htm Rg.10.082.06] Ralph T.H. Griffith, [1896] translates it &quot;The waters, they received that germ primeval wherein the Gods were gathefed all together. It rested set upon the Unborn's navel, that One wherein abide all things existing.&quot;&lt;/ref&gt; and according to the Gaudiyas, falls under category of ''tad-ekātma-rūpa'',&lt;ref name = beck/&gt;

According to the [[Gaudiya Vaishnava]] interpretation, it is also confirmed in the Bhagavad-gītā (7.7), which says, ''{{IAST|mattaḥ parataraṁ nānyat}}'': &quot;There is no truth superior to Me.&quot;  Where Krishna is 'bhagavan' himself, whose partial manifestations are the other gods. This idea is reflected in the [[Bhagavata Purana]]. The [[Brahma Vaivarta Purana]] tells us Krishna is the ultimate source from which [[Brahma]], [[Vishnu]], [[Shiva]] and [[Prakriti]] originate. He is ''Svayam Bhagavan'' while other incarnation are his partial manifestations. The comments of [[Sridhara Svami]] (an early Sankara sect commentator), bring out uniqueness of Krishna. According to him Krishna is perfect as all potencies are observed to be full in him.&lt;ref name = Gosvami1986&gt;{{cite book
| author = Gosvami, J.
| coauthors = Chatterjee, C.
| year = 1986
| title = Srikrsnasandarbha and its critical study
| publisher = [http://books.google.ie/books?q=inpublisher:%22Jadavpur+University Jadavpur University]
| isbn =
}} p xvii-xviii&lt;/ref&gt; In ''Atharvavedasamhita'', Krishna is described as having slain the giant Kesi, Keshava. The ''Kaustiki Brahmana'' (30.9) alludes to Krishna Angirasa, who is an object of evening ceremony in connection with Brahmanaacchamsin priest. The Aitareya Aranyaka speaks of two Krishnas of Harita Gotra.&lt;ref name = Gosvami1986&gt;{{cite book
| author = Gosvami, J.
| coauthors = Chatterjee, C.
| year = 1986
| title = Srikrsnasandarbha and its critical study
| publisher = [http://books.google.ie/books?q=inpublisher:%22Jadavpur+University Jadavpur University]
| isbn =
}} p vi&lt;/ref&gt; However the south Indian [[Vaishnavism]] makes very little stress on Krishna and altogether ignored [[Radha]] in contrast with the other traditions.&lt;ref name = Gosvami1986&gt;{{cite book
| author = Gosvami, J.
| coauthors = Chatterjee, C.
| year = 1986
| title = Srikrsnasandarbha and its critical study
| publisher = [http://books.google.ie/books?q=inpublisher:%22Jadavpur+University Jadavpur University]
| isbn =
}} p iv&lt;/ref&gt; 

To the views of the Gaudiya Sampradaya, the [[Bhagavad-gita]]&lt;ref name = BG16&gt;[http://www.asitis.com/18/64.html BG 18.64 &quot;sarva-guhya-tamam—the most confidential of all&quot;] [[Prabhupada|Purport]] states : &quot;This essence is not understood by a common man, but by one who is actually very dear to {{IAST|Kṛṣṇa}}&quot;&lt;/ref&gt; states that this ''bhakti-yoga'' is secretive:&lt;ref name = &quot;Klostermaier1974&quot;&gt;{{cite journal
| author = Klostermaier, K.
| year = 1974
| title = The Bhaktirasamrtasindhubindu of Visvanatha Cakravartin
| journal = Journal of the American Oriental Society
| volume = 94
| issue = 1
| pages = 96–107
| doi = 10.2307/599733
| jstor = 599733
| publisher = American Oriental Society
| ref = harv
}}&lt;/ref&gt;  - &quot;Just hear from Me again about the most confidential part of the instructions in [[Bhagavad-gītā]].&quot;&lt;ref name = BG16/&gt; It is also described as such in [[Bhagavata Purana]]&lt;ref&gt;[http://srimadbhagavatam.com/2/9/35/en SB 2.9.35: {{IAST|yathā mahānti bhūtāni bhūteṣūccāvaceṣv anu praviṣṭāny apraviṣṭāni tathā teṣu na teṣv aham}}]&lt;/ref&gt; Vashnavas of [[ISKCON]] often stress their view that in both cases Krishna is speaking about himself, ''aham'' and ''me'' in [[Sanskrit]] mean, ''I am'' and ''Me'' respectively. While some commentators derive secondary meanings,&lt;ref name=Hiltebeitel1984&gt;{{cite journal
| author = Hiltebeitel, A.
| year = 1984
| title = The Two Krishnas on One Chariot: Upanisadic Imagery and Epic Mythology
| journal = History of Religions
| volume = 24
| issue = 1
| pages = 1–26
| jstor = 198408)
| doi = 10.1086/462971
| ref = harv
}}&lt;/ref&gt; all major Sanskrit dictionary accept that the direct meaning of ''aham'' and ''me'', refers to Krishna himself.&lt;ref name=Sivananda1958&gt;{{cite book
| author = Sivananda, S.
| year = 1958
| title = God Exists.
| publisher = Yoga-Vedanta Forest University
| isbn =
}}Quote: “Aham” means “I” in Sanskrit. “Idam” means “this.”&lt;/ref&gt;
[[File:Krishna meets parents.jpg|thumb|200px|right|[[Krsna|Krishna]] and [[Balarama]] meet their father and mother - [[Vasudeva]] and Devaki. Thus a personal name of Krishna as Vaasudeva or ''son of Vasudeva'', and Devakinandana, ''son of Devaki''. Painting by [[Raja Ravi Varma]]]]

===Lakshmi===

When Gaudiya Vaishnavas present their views on Krishna being ''Svayam Bhagavan'',
&lt;ref name = harekrsna&gt;
{{cite web
|url=http://www.veda.harekrsna.cz/bhaktiyoga/vaisnavism.htm
|title=VEDA - Vedas and Vedic Knowledge Online - Vedic Encyclopedia, Bhakti-yoga in vedas, Library
|publisher=www.veda.harekrsna.cz
|accessdate=2008-05-04
|last=
|first=
}}
&lt;/ref&gt; they present a number of perspectives some include comparison with other forms such as [[Vishnu]], that are considered supreme in other sampradayas.  The  [http://www.saragrahi.org/Header%20Links/Bhagavat%20Sandarbha/Contents.htm Bhagavat Sandarbha] and the  [http://www.saragrahi.org/Header%20Links/Tattva%20Sandarbha/Tattva%20Sandarbha%20Contents.htm Tattva Sandabha] are among quoted works by [[Jiva Goswami]],&lt;ref name=Gupta2007 /&gt; &quot;Vaishnavas don't argue among themselves if Krishna or Vishnu is the Supreme. They consider it a matter of one's relationship with the Lord. Someone has a relationship with Vishnu, someone with Rama, someone with Krishna, etc. as per rasa theology.&quot; In the [[Caitanya Caritamrita]] &lt;ref&gt;[http://vedabase.net/cc/madhya/9/108/en Caitanya Caritamrita 2.9.108]&lt;/ref&gt; Chaitanya discusses this in a joking mood with [[Venkatta Bhatta]] from [[Sri sampradaya]].&lt;ref name = hk&gt;
{{cite web
|url=http://www.veda.harekrsna.cz/bhaktiyoga/vaisnavism.htm
|title=VEDA - Vedas and Vedic Knowledge Online - Vedic Encyclopedia, Bhakti-yoga in vedas, Library
|publisher=www.veda.harekrsna.cz
|accessdate=2008-05-04
|last=Jan
|first=Marez
}}
&lt;/ref&gt; While [[Pustimarga]] tradition predates Gaudiya Vaisnavism in Radha worship.
&lt;ref name = Brzezinski1992&gt;{{cite journal
| author = Brzezinski, J.K.
| year = 1992
| title = Prabodhananda, Hita Harivamsa and the&quot; Radharasasudhanidhi
| journal = Bulletin of the School of Oriental and African Studies, University of London
| volume = 55
| issue = 3
| pages = 472–497
| ref = harv
| jstor=620194
| doi=10.1017/S0041977X00003669
}}&quot;identify Radha as the supreme Laksmi..&quot;&lt;/ref&gt;
When Chaitanya traveled through South India in 1509-10, he stayed at the house of Venkata Bhatta, the father of [[Gopala Bhatta]], priest of [[Srirangam]]. Venkata and his two brothers, Gopala's uncles Trimalla and [[Prabodhananda Sarasvati]] &quot;were converted from their [[Sri Vaishnava]] faith in [[Lakshmi]]-[[Narayana]] as supreme to one in [[Radha]] [[Krishna]]&quot; as Svayam Bhagavan.&lt;ref name = Brzezinski1992/&gt; The dialog of this conversion is recorded in 16 c. Caitanya Caritamrita biography by [[Krishna dasa Kaviraja]].&lt;ref name = hk/&gt;

In the Madhya lila of the Chaitanya charitamrita a presentation is given,&lt;ref&gt;[http://vedabase.net/cc/madhya/9/113/en Madhya 9.113-114]: &quot;Just to associate with {{IAST|Kṛṣṇa}}, [http://vedabase.net/l/laksmi {{IAST|Lakṣmī}}] abandoned all transcendental happiness in [http://vedabase.net/v/vaikuntha {{IAST|Vaikuṇṭha}}] and for a long time accepted vows and regulative principles and performed unlimited austerities.&quot;&lt;/ref&gt;  with a reference to the particular verse of the tenth canto of [[Bhagavata Purana]] as to the reason why [[Lakshmi]] also known as [[Sri]] (thus the name of Sri Sampradaya) is burning with desire and still not capable of entering to the realm of [[Vrindavana]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://vedabase.net/sb/10/16/36/en SB 10.16.36]&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Prabodhananda Sarasvati]] who was a Sri Sampradaya [[sannyasi]] was converted as to supreme position of Radha-Krishna being Svayam Bhagavan instead of Lakshmi-Narayana. He as well apparently came to appreciate the supremacy of Radha worship from Caitanya.&lt;ref name = Brzezinski19922&gt;{{cite journal
| author = Brzezinski, J.K.
| year = 1992
| title = Prabodhananda Sarasvati: From Benares to Braj
| journal = Bulletin of the School of Oriental and African Studies, University of London
| volume = 55
| issue = 1
| pages = 52–75
| doi = 10.1017/S0041977X00002640
| ref = harv
| jstor=620476
}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Cosmological perspective===
The view of South Indian Vaishnava groups on ''sarga'', or subtle creation, is based upon scriptural adherence to [[Narayana]] or Vishnu being the cause of creation&lt;ref&gt;The Eleventh Canto of ''Śrīmad-Bhāgavatam'' [http://srimadbhagavatam.com/11/4/3/en(11.4.3-4) describes Lord {{IAST|Mahāpuruṣa}}: ''{{IAST|bhūtair yadā pañcabhir ātma-sṛṣṭaiḥ  puraṁ virājaṁ viracayya tasmin svāṁśena viṣṭaḥ puruṣābhidhānam  avāpa nārāyaṇa ādi-devaḥ}}'' &quot;When the primeval Lord {{IAST|Nārāyaṇa}} created His universal body out of the five elements produced from Himself, and then entered within that universal body by His own plenary portion, He thus became known as the {{IAST|Puruṣa}}.]&lt;/ref&gt; expanding into Viraja and then {{IAST|Maha-Viṣṇu}} glancing over ''pradhana'', and that is the start of actual function of creation. This view is not contradicted by Krishna-centered Vashnavism and does not appear to be in contradiction with ''Svayam Bhagavan'' who as [[Vasudeva]] (son of Vasudeva, Krishna) is according to Pancaratra is at the source of creation.

Pancaratra sources are accepted by all of Vaishnava traditions, and confirmed by [[Yamunacarya]] who preceding in the line of [[Ramanuja]], summarizing in his ''Agamapramanya'', a defense of the revelation of the ''tantric'' Vaishnava Pancaratra, defending whole body of the texts being part of the Veda: &quot;The Pancadratra Tantra is authoritative like the Vedic sentences ordaining sacrifice on the grounds that it is based on knowledge free from all defects&quot;. Amalananda, also defends Pancaratra and while confirming that [[Āgama (Hinduism)|Agamas]] do not have the same self-authenticating validity, as the four Vedas, but the authenticity of it assured because Veda bear witness to the omniscience of [[Vasudeva]]. This position also forms the basis of [[Bhagavata Purana]] based theology.&lt;ref name=2Flood2006&gt;&quot;self-authenticating validity as the Veda, but their authenticity is nevertheless assured because the Veda bear witness to the omniscience of Vasudeva.&quot; p. 53-54, Flood. 2006&lt;/ref&gt;

It is also a view of [[Gaudiya Vaishnava]]s that [[Sanatana Goswami]]s ''Brihad Bhagavatamrita'',  has illustrated this principle, not just in terms of comparative cosmology or ''avatara'' hierarchy as in Vaishnava Pancaratra, but also in terms of cosmology of ''adi-rasa''.&lt;ref name=KDasa&gt;{{cite journal
| author = K Dasa,
| year = 2006
| title = The Life and Teachings of Krishna dasa Baba
| url = http://blazingsapphirepress.com/krsna-das-baba/krsna-das-baba-sample.pdf
| accessdate = 2008-04-13
| ref = harv
}}&lt;/ref&gt; The cosmological principle of the four dhamas (with a separate place for the last two: ''Vaikuntha'' - abode of Vishnu or [[Narayana]], ''tad-ekatma rupa'', in transcendence, and ''Goloka'' as abode of ''Svayam Bhagavan'' in transcendence) is the key of the graphical presentation, but it is also an answer to the dilemma.&lt;ref&gt;
{{cite web
|url=http://www.ramanuja.org/sv/bhakti/archives/apr2000/0168.html
|title=krushNAstu bhagavAn swayam
|publisher=www.ramanuja.org
|accessdate=2008-04-29
|last=Anand Karalapakkam
|first=Bhakti List : Archives Wed Apr 19 2000
}}
&lt;/ref&gt;  In accordance with the cosmology of the ''Brihad Bhagavatamrita'' Krishna is believed being the original and most complete in all ''[[Rasa (theology)|rasas]]'' or tastes is in fact not engaged and non engaging, is his independence, he does not even, at least in this his original form, carry symbols of {{IAST|Viṣṇu}}, he only carries his own flute, and that is the pleasure of his devotees.&lt;ref name=&quot;GPD&quot;&gt;{{cite book
|author=Dāsa, {{IAST|Gopīparāṇadhana}}; Sanātana Gosvāmī
|title=Śrī Brhad Bhāgavatāmrta of Śrīla Sanātana Gosvāmī: translated from the original Sanskrit, with a summary of the author's Dig-darśinī commentary
|publisher=Bhaktivedanta Book Trust
|location=Los Angeles
|year=2002
|pages=920
|isbn=0-89213-345-7
|oclc=
|doi=
}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Original Purusha of the Vedas===

{{See also|Gopala Tapani Upanishad|l1=Dating of early Tapani Upanishads}}

The form of [[Narayana]] is linked with the concept of sacrifice in the earliest known references to him. In Vedic sources such as the [[Purusha Sukta]], Narayana is given as the name of the self-offering of the great cosmic sacrifice of the [[Rig Veda]].&lt;ref&gt;Rig Veda 10.90&lt;/ref&gt; Narayana is not mentioned in Rig Veda itself, but came to be regarded as the seer who authored the [[hymn]]. It is possible that the sage who composed the Purusha Sukta hymn has been assimilated to the Purusha whose praise he had sung, and he himself became the object of worship. Mentions of a divine sage named [[Nara-Narayana|Narayana, along with counterpart Nara]], appears in many [[Puranas|Puranic]] texts.&lt;ref name = Krishna5&gt;
{{cite book
|author=Matchett, Freda
|title=Krsna, Lord or Avatara? the relationship between Krsna and Visnu: in the context of the Avatara myth as presented by the Harivamsa, the Visnupurana and the Bhagavatapurana
|publisher=Routledge
|location=Surrey
|year=2000
|pages=254
|isbn=0-7007-1281-X
|oclc=
|doi=
|accessdate=
|url=http://books.google.com/?id=1oqTYiPeAxMC&amp;printsec=frontcover
}}
p. 5&lt;/ref&gt; ''Purusha'' is also identified with Vishnu in the [[Rig Veda]] and interpreted accordingly by many [[sampradayas|traditions]] of [[Vaishnavism]]. In the Bhagavata he is  recognized as &quot;the Lord whose being is sacrifice, Yajna [[Purusha]]&quot;&lt;ref name = Bhaktivinda&gt;[[Gaudiya]] scholar, [[Bhaktivinoda Thakura]] in his ''Dasa Mula Tattva'' Ch.3: '{{IAST|Śrī Kṛṣṇa}}—The Supreme Absolute Truth', Part: ''Vedic Evidences of {{IAST|Śrī Kṛṣṇa}} ’s Divinity'' states:

In the {{IAST|Ṛg-Veda}} ({{IAST|Ṛg.}} 1.22.23): 

: ''{{IAST|tad viṣṇoḥ paramaṁ padaṁ sadā paśyanti sūrayaḥ}}''
: ''{{IAST|divīva cakṣur ātataṁ viṣṇor yat paramaṁ padam}}''

&quot;The Personality of Godhead, {{IAST|Viṣṇu}}, is the Absolute Truth whose lotus feet all the demigods are always eager to see. His lotus-feet are only visible to those endowed with spiritual vision, for they are completely transcendental and supreme like {{IAST|Śrī Kṛṣṇa}}, Himself.&quot;

Again, in the {{IAST|Ṛg-Veda}} (1.22.164 sūkta 31) we find this verse:

: ''{{IAST|apaśyaṁ gopām anipadyamāna mā ca parā ca pathibhiś carantam}}''
: ''{{IAST|sa sadhrīcīḥ sa viṣucīr vasāna avarīrvati bhuvaneṣv antaḥ}}''

&quot;I saw a young cowherd boy, who never falls from His position. Sometimes He is near, sometimes He is far away; in this manner, He moves in various ways. Sometimes, He is clothed in many robes and at other times differently dressed; in this way, He is repeatedly appearing and disappearing in this universe.&quot; 

The next verse establishes the eternal aspect of {{IAST|Śrī Kṛṣṇa}}'s transcendental pastimes as found in the {{IAST|Ṛg Veda}} (1.54.6):

: ''{{IAST|tā vāṁ vāstuny uśmasi gamadhyai yatra gavo bhūri sṛṅga ayāsaḥ}}''
: ''{{IAST|atrāha tad urugāyasya viṣṇoḥ parama-padam avabhāti bhuri}}''

&quot;I desire to attain Your (Śrī Rādhikā and {{IAST|Śrī Kṛṣṇa}}'s) abode where the wish-fulfilling cows, known as kāmadhenu, are decorated with gracefully long horns. The eternal residence of {{IAST|Śrī Kṛṣṇa}}, the fulfiller of His devotees' desires, is pre-eminently exhibiting itself in all grandeur.&quot;&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Bhagavata Purana 3.13.23&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name = Krishna194&gt;{{Harvnb|Matchett|2000|p=194}}''bhagavan yajñapuruso''&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book
|author=Matchett, Freda
|title=Krsna, Lord or Avatara? the relationship between Krsna and Visnu: in the context of the Avatara myth as presented by the Harivamsa, the Visnupurana and the Bhagavatapurana
|publisher=Routledge
|location=Surrey
|year=2000
|pages=254
|isbn=0-7007-1281-X
|oclc=
|doi=
|accessdate=
|url=http://books.google.com/?id=1oqTYiPeAxMC&amp;printsec=frontcover
}}
p.74-75&lt;/ref&gt; Some believe that thus this verse of the [[Rig Veda]] is a foundation of Vaishnava tradition. In the [[Gopala Tapani Upanishad]]  the Rig Veda verse(1.22.20) was addressed paraphrasing the original of the Vedic hymn in accordance with the beliefs of the [[Gaudiya Vaishnava]]:&lt;ref&gt;

:''etad visnoh paramam padam ye nityodyuktah samyajante na kaman
:''tesam asau gopa-rupah prayatnat prakasayad atma-padam tadaiva''- &quot;To they who always diligently worship Lord {{IAST|Viṣṇu}}'s transcendental form, the Lord, in His original form as a cowherd boy, shows His lotus feet.&quot;{{cite book |author=B. V. Tripurari |title=Gopala-tapani Upanisad |publisher=Audarya Press |location= |year=2004 |pages= |isbn=1-932771-12-3 |oclc= |doi=}}&lt;/ref&gt;  It outlines a specific view held by the [[Gaudiya Vaishnava]] and [[Vallabha Sampradaya]], that the conclusion of Vishnu worship is meditation on ''gopa-rupah'' or specific form of [[Krishna]].&lt;ref name=Trip /&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://books.google.ie/books?id=mehE5hn7ircC&amp;dqSree Krishna, the Lord of Love]. Bábá Premánand Bhárati, 1904&lt;/ref&gt;

''Krishna Upanishad'' supports this conclusion of Gopala Tapani,&lt;ref name = yoga&gt;{{cite book |author=Wood, Ernest |title=Great Systems of Yoga (Forgotten Books) |publisher=Forgotten Books |location= |year=2008 |pages= |isbn=1-60506-644-3 |oclc= |doi= }} [http://books.google.ie/books?id=87cxkdlOA0sC&amp;pg=PA85 &quot;Once the sages came to the great Brahma and asked: 'Who is the supreme God?... He replied Shri Krishna verily is the supreme God. Death is afraid of Godinda.&quot;]&lt;/ref&gt; and refers to the original &quot;the most divine form of bliss dwells in the supremacy of love of Lord Krishna&quot;,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |author=Stephen Knapp |title=The Heart of Hinduism: The Eastern Path to Freedom, Empowerment and Illumination |publisher=iUniverse, Inc |location=[United States] |year=2005 |pages= |isbn=0-595-35075-5 |oclc= |doi= }} p.16: &quot;the Krishna Upanishad that directly reveals that the most divine form of bliss dwells in the supremacy of love of Lord Krishna.&quot;&lt;/ref&gt; ''saksad'', Hari as ''gopa-rüpa''. (1.10-12):
&lt;ref&gt;
: ''{{IAST|gopa-rūpo hariḥ sakṣan  maya-vigraha-dharaṇaḥ}}''
: ''{{IAST|durbodhaṁ kuhakaṁ tasya  mayayā mohitaṁ jagat}}''
: ''{{IAST|durjayā sa suraiḥ sarvair  dhṛṣṭi-rūpo bhaved dvijaḥ}}''
: ''{{IAST|rudro yena kṛto vaṁsas  tasya māyā jagat katham}}''
: ''{{IAST|balaṁ janaṁ suraṇaṁ vai  teṣāṁ janaṁ hṛtaṁ kṣaṇat}}''
: ''{{IAST|śeṣa-nago bhaved ramaḥ  kṛṣṇo brahmaiva sasvatam}}''
{{cite book |author=Vyasadeva, Baladevavidyabhusana |title=Sri Krsna Upanisad and Other Vaisnava Upanisads |publisher=[http://books.google.ie/books?q=inpublisher:%22Krsna+Institute%22&amp;cad=0 Krsna Institute] |location=[United States] |year=1992 |pages= |isbn=1561300780 |oclc= |doi= }}&lt;/ref&gt;
:&quot;The Supreme Personality of Godhead appeared in His original form as a cowherd boy. Cheated and bewildered by His illusory potency, the world could not understand His true identity.
:&quot;Even all the demigods cannot defeat the Lord's Maya potency. By the Lord's Yogamaya potency Brahma became a stick and Siva became a flute. How did the Lord's Maya potency manifest the entire universe?
:&quot;Knowledge is the strength of the demigods. The Lord's Maya potency steals away that knowledge in a single moment. Lord Sesanaga appeared in His original form as Lord Balarama. The eternal Supreme Personality of Godhead appeared in His original form as Lord Krishna.&quot;&lt;ref name = Trip/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |author=Vyasadeva, Baladevavidyabhusana |title=Sri Krsna Upanisad and Other Vaisnava Upanisads |publisher=[http://books.google.ie/books?q=inpublisher:%22Krsna+Institute%22&amp;cad=0 Krsna Institute] |location=[United States] |year=1992 |pages= |isbn=1561300780 |oclc= |doi= }}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Gaudiya Vaishnava]] believe that Krishna possesses qualities that are absent in other forms and they relate to his sweetness in [[Vrindavana lila]]. Krishna is himself Narayana.&lt;ref&gt;''Cyclopædia of India and of Eastern and Southern Asia'', Edward Balfour. Published 1871, Scottish and Adelphi Presses. p.604: Krishna indeed, himself is Narayana;&lt;/ref&gt;  [[Narayana]] is often identified with supreme, however, when his beauty and ''sweetness'' (madhurya) overshadow his majesty, he is known as ''Krishna'', i.e. ''Svayam Bhagavan''.&lt;ref name = HKM&gt;[http://books.google.ie/books?id=mBMxPdgrBhoC The Hare Krishna Movement: The Postcharismatic Fate of a Religious Transplant], Edwin Bryant, Maria Ekstrand, 2004, 448 pages, Page 151: known as Narayana and is served in awe and reverence. However, when his beauty  and sweetness (madhurya) overshadow his majesty, he is known as Krishna...]&lt;/ref&gt; As Friedhelm Hardy says, the concept of Bhagavan, &quot;a single, all-powerful, eternal, personal and loving God ... is an empty slot, to be filled by concrete characteristics&quot; and these characteristics culminate in Krishna.&lt;ref name = Krishna2&gt;
{{Harvnb|Matchett|2000|p=2}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Paribhasa-sutra of Bhagavata Purana===

{{See also|Bhagavata Purana|l1=Dating of the Bhagavata Purana}}
[[File:JivaGoswami.jpg|thumb|200px|right|[[Jiva Gosvami]]’s [[Bhajan Kutir]] at [[Radha-kunda]]. Jiva Goswamis ''Sandarbhas'' summarize Vedic sources of [[Gaudiya Vaishnava]] tradition's accretion  of the concept ''{{IAST|bhagavān svayam}}'' based on paribhasa-sutra of [[Bhagavata Purana]] &lt;br/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book
| author = Gupta, Ravi M.
| coauthors =
| year = 2007
| title = [[Caitanya]] [[Vaisnava]] [[Vedanta]] of [[Jiva Gosvami]]
| publisher = Routledge
| isbn = 0415405483
}}&lt;/ref&gt;]]
In [[Gaudiya Vaishnava]], [[Vallabha Sampradaya]] [[Nimbarka sampradaya]] and old [[Bhagavata]] school,  Krishna believed to be fully represented in his original form in the [[Bhagavata Purana]], that at the end of the list of ''avataras'' concludes with the following text:&lt;ref name = Krishna153&gt;
{{Harvnb|Matchett|2000|p=153}}Bhag. Purana  1.3.28
: ''{{IAST|ete cāṁśa-kalāḥ puṁsaḥ kṛṣṇas tu bhagavān svayam}}'' :''{{IAST|indrāri-vyākulaṁ lokaṁ mṛḍayanti yuge yuge}}''&lt;/ref&gt;
{{Quotation|All of the above-mentioned incarnations are either plenary portions or portions of the plenary portions of the Lord, but Sri Krishna is the original Personality of Godhead (''Svayam Bhagavan'').&lt;ref&gt;[http://srimadbhagavatam.com/1/3/28/en 1.3.28] {{cite web
|url=http://srimadbhagavatam.com/1/3/28/en
|title=Srimad Bhagavatam Canto 1 Chapter 3 Verse 28
|publisher=[[Bhaktivedanta Book Trust]]
|accessdate=2008-05-07
|last=Swami Prabhupada
|first=A.C. Bhaktivedanta
}}
&lt;/ref&gt;}}

Not all commentators on the Bhagavata Purana stress this verse, however a majority of Krishna-centered and contemporary commentaries highlight this verse as a significant statement.&lt;ref&gt;
{{cite web
|url=http://www.stephen-knapp.com/sri_krishna.htm
|title=Sri Krishna
|publisher=www.stephen-knapp.com
|accessdate=2008-04-30
|last=
|first=
}}
&lt;/ref&gt;[[Jiva Goswami]] has called it ''Paribhasa-sutra'', the “thesis statement” upon which the entire book or even theology is based.&lt;ref&gt;
{{cite book
|author=Dhanurdhara Swami
|title=Waves of Devotion
|publisher=Bhagavat Books
|location=
|year=2000
|pages=
|isbn=0-9703581-0-5
|oclc=
|doi=
}} - {{cite web
|url=http://www.wavesofdevotion.com/wod/an.html
|title=Waves of Devotion |publisher=www.wavesofdevotion.com
|accessdate=2008-05-04
|last=
|first=
}}In [[Hari-namamr†a-vyakarana]], [[Jiva Gosvami]] defines paribhasa-sutra as ''aniyame niyama-karini paribhasa'': “A ''paribhasa-sutra'' implies a rule or theme where it is not explicitly stated.” In other words, it gives the context in which to understand a series of apparently unrelated statements in a book.&lt;/ref&gt;

In another place of the [[Bhagavata Purana]] 10.83.5-43 those who are named as wives of Krishna all explain to Draupadi how the 'Lord himself' (''Svayam Bhagavan'', [[Bhagavata Purana]] 10.83.7) came to marry them. As they relate these episodes, several of the wives speak of themselves as Krishna's devotees.&lt;ref name = Krishna141&gt;
{{Harvnb|Matchett|2000|p=141}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Many Krishna-centered traditions believe that ''Svayam Bhagavan'' personally carries his unalloyed devotees (''vahamy aham'') like a husband carries his bride across the threshold into the house of ''prema bhakti''.&lt;ref&gt;Bg 9.22&lt;/ref&gt; Badarayana [[Vyasa]] says in his [[Brahma Sutras]], ''visesam ca darsayati'', implying that the scripture declares a difference with regard to the passing from the world of ''nirapeksa'' or unflinching devotees.&lt;ref&gt;
{{cite web
|url=http://www.vnn.org/editorials/ET9902/ET09-2981.html
|title=VNN Editorial - 'Uttarayana', The Path Of Light And Darkness
|publisher=www.vnn.org
|accessdate=2008-05-03
|last=
|first=
}}
&lt;/ref&gt;

===Source of Para-Vasudeva===

[[Baladeva Vidyabhusana]] in his commentary on [[Gopala Tapani Upanishad]] states: Glory to the ''[[Gopala Tapani Upanishad]]'', which to the pious reveals Lord Krishna, the original Personality of Godhead, the Supersoul near to all moving and unmoving creatures.&lt;ref name = Tripp&gt;{{cite book |author=B. V. Tripurari |title=Gopala-tapani Upanisad |publisher=Audarya Press |location= |year=2004 |pages= |isbn=1-932771-12-3 |oclc= |doi=}}''Śrī Gopāla Tapanī bhāśya'' 1.1: 
:''gopala-tapanim naumi ya krsnam svayam isvaram
:''kara-stharava-sankasam sandarsayati sad-dhiyah''&lt;/ref&gt;

The word used is ''krsna svayam isvaram'', the paraphrase of the Bhagavata Purana verse 1.3.28 that [[Jiva Goswami]] has called a key ''sutra'',&lt;ref name = Gupta2004&gt;{{IAST|Kṛṣṇa sandarbha}} 29.4-5&lt;/ref&gt; not only to the [[Bhagavata Purana]] but to [[Vedanta]] and thus all the Vedas.&lt;ref name = Gupta2004&gt;{{IAST|Kṛṣṇa sandarbha}} 29.104&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=Gosvami1995&gt;{{cite book
| author = Gosvami, J.
| coauthors = Dasa, S.N.; Dasa, K.; Dasa, K.; Dasa, G.; Dasa, D.
| year = 1995
| title = Sri Tattva-sandarbha: The First Book of the Sri Bhagavata-Sandarbha Also Known as Sri-sandarbha
| publisher = Jiva Institute for Vaisnava Studies
| isbn =
}}&lt;/ref&gt;

According to the Upanishads its believed that when [[Brahma]], who is said to be original created being, was approached by the sages [[Four Kumaras]] he was presented with critical question:  – Who is Supreme God? Who does death fears?  – By knowing Whom, does everything else gets realized?   – Who is that person, who is behind the repetition of creation of this Universe?&lt;ref name = Tipp/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.celextel.org/108upanishads/gopalatapaniya.html alternative translation of Gopala-tapani Upanisad]&lt;/ref&gt; His own original or sweet form, ''{{IAST|Sva-bimbaṁ}}'' to the is not manifested very often in the Universe, ''loka-locanam''.&lt;ref&gt;SB 3.2.11&lt;/ref&gt; [[Gaudiya Vaishnavas]] quote sources that claim that it happens only ones in a universal day of [[Brahma]], and its only at that time its believed, once every fourteen [[manvantara]]s, each seventy one [[yuga|divya-yugas]] duration.&lt;ref&gt;[http://vedabase.net/cc/adi/3/10/en Chaitanya Charitamrita ''Adi'' 3.10]&lt;/ref&gt; Some religions do not even consider it possible to see the God. To answer four Kumaras Brahma needed to relate this secret word of the ''seed'' mantra.&lt;ref name=Rosen2006&gt;{{cite book
| author = Rosen, S.J.
| year = 2006
| title = Essential Hinduism
| publisher = Praeger Publishers
| isbn =
}}&lt;/ref&gt;
And this is believed to be the answer to the question, who is supreme god and how he creates this world.&lt;ref name = Tipp&gt;
:''krsno vai paramam daivatam govindan mrtyur bibheti
:''gopijanavallabha-jnanena taj jnatam bhavati  svahayedam samsarati''&lt;/ref&gt;
Brahma replied to the sages: &quot;Krisna is the Supreme Personality of Godhead. Death fears Govinda. By knowing Gopijanavallabha everything becomes realized. By pronouncing the word &quot;svaha&quot; the Personality of Godhead created the world.&lt;ref&gt;Svähä is the mantra by which offerings are made into the sacrificial fire.5 It is derived from the root ä(hu with the prefix su meaning “well-done,” meaning “according to the vidhi.” This etymology is tentatively accepted by Monier-Williams. The verb root vah is only used in the perfect tense. “to say, speak, state.” Monier-Williams gives the following meanings for svähä: “hail! hail to! May a blessing rest on” As a noun: “an oblation, oblation personified.” Both svähuti and svähväna are found in Rg.&lt;/ref&gt; In the wider context of the Bhagavata's total perspective, Krishna is &quot;not one among many but the Lord himself&quot;.&lt;ref name = Krishna184&gt;
{{Harvnb|Matchett|2000|p=184}}&lt;/ref&gt;

''Sanat-Kumara Samhita'' confirms the belief that this ''Kama Gayatri'' is the foundational structure of the [[Goloka]], believed to be the abode of Krishna, who is the original Vaasudeva&lt;ref&gt;om namo bhagavate sarva-bhutatmane vasudevaya sarvatma-samyoga-yoga-padma-pithatmane namah - &quot;I offer my respectful obeisances unto Lord Vasudeva, the all-pervading Supreme Personality of Godhead who resides in His own transcendental abode, which resembles a lotus flower.&quot;&lt;/ref&gt;:
&quot;In the whorl of the [[lotus flower]] which is Lord Krishna's transcendental abode, the Gopala [[mantra]] is written.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;
: ''karnikayam likhed vahni-
: ''putitam mandala-dvayam
: ''tasya madhye likhed bijam
: ''sadhyakhyam karma samyutam''
&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=Cult1927&gt;{{cite journal
| author = Cult, P.C.S.
| year = 1927
| title = An Introduction To The Post-chaitanya Sahajia Cult
| journal = Journal
| ref = harv
}} - refers to Kama Gayatri in the practice of Post-chaitanya Sahajia Cult and ortodox Gaudiya.&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;ref name=Mukherjee1979&gt;{{cite book
| author = Mukherjee, P.
| year = 1979
| title = History of the Chaitanya Faith in Orissa
| publisher = Manohar
| isbn =
}} refers to practice of Gopal mantra and its significance&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=Rosen2004&gt;{{cite journal
| author = Rosen, S.J.
| year = 2004
| title = Who Is Shri Chaitanya Mahaprabhu?
| journal = The Hare Krishna Movement: the Postcharismatic Fate of a Religious Transplant
| url = http://books.google.com/?id=mBMxPdgrBhoC&amp;pg=PA63&amp;dq=%22Gopala+mantra%22+Gaudiya
| accessdate = 2008-04-19
| publisher = Columbia University Press
| isbn = 9780231122566
| ref = harv
}}&quot;he was given the ten-syllable Gopala mantra, a confidential incantation&quot;&lt;/ref&gt;

==Related historical records==
[[File:Heliodoruspillar.gif|thumb|300px|The first inscription of the [[Heliodorus pillar]] that was made by Heliodorus [[110 BCE]].&lt;br/&gt;This Garuda-standard of [[Vasudeva]], the God of Gods was erected here by the devotee Heliodoros,]]
While some place Krishna-centered worship as ''Svayam Bhagavan'' in the medieval times of Indian history, there is some evidence suggesting the opposite. In the antiquity Krishna images were worshiped at many places. Quoting Curtius, Dr. D.C. Sircar says that an image of Herakles (i.e. Vasudeva-Krishna according to Sircar) was being carried in front of the Paurava army, as it advanced against the Greeks led by Alexander the Great (''The Cultural Heritage of India'', vol. 4. p.&amp;nbsp;115) An interesting terracotta plague showing Vasudeva carrying the infant Krishna over his head across the flooded Yamuna river, belonging to c. first century is housed in the Mathura Museum. A Mora stone inscription of about the same time refers to some images of Bhagavata Vrshni Panchaviras, Sankarshana, Vasudeva, Pradyumna, Samba and Aniruddha - which were very beautifully carved in stone.&lt;ref name = Krsnat&gt;[http://books.google.com/books?id=vNiKM-ky3DQC Chapter: ''Krishna and His Cult''. Krishna Theatre in India By M.L. Varalpande], p.6; 2002. ISBN 8170171512&lt;/ref&gt; A [[Gupta period]] research makes a &quot;clear mention of [[Vasudeva]] as the exclusive object of worship of a group of people,&quot; who are referred as [[bhagavatas]].&lt;ref name=1Banerjea1966&gt;Banerjea, 1966, page 20&lt;/ref&gt;

Verifying the antiquity of the exclusive worship of ''Svayam Bhagavan'', Krishna, the early [[Jainism|Jaina]] texts repeatedly stress two categories of [[Baladeva]]s and [[Vasudeva]]s that clearly can not be attributed to the Buddhist tradition, and can not be traced to the earlier strata of the Jaina canon itself. The introduction of these novel categories in the Jaina tradition, therefore, can hardly be explained without references to the legends surrounding the two popular figures of the early Vaishnava tradition, namely [[Balarama]] and [[Krishna]] of Mathura.&lt;ref name = &quot;Doniger&quot;/&gt; 

Archaeological remains found in the region of [[Mathura, Uttar Pradesh|Mathura]] support the fact that the popularity of these two divine figures had reached its zenith in the [[Mauryan]] and the [[Sunga]] period and associated Bhagavata religion had become widespread throughout Mathura and Western India areas. This period coincides with the large migrations of Jainas from Magadha to [[Mathura, Uttar Pradesh|Mathura]]. Baladeva is referred to by Jaina Puranas as Halabhrit, without any support from Brahminical texts. All the Vasudevas are modeled after the description of Krishna found in the [[Purana]]s. They are called blue-black (nila) in complexion and are designated by several names that are normally applied exclusively to Krishna e.g. Keshava, Madhava, Govinda, Vishnu and Narayana (which is used as synonym for the name Vasudeva). List of opposites (or ''prati'' categories) include most of the names associated with [[Asuras]] in Puranas.&lt;ref name = &quot;Doniger&quot;&gt;
{{cite book
|author=Doniger, Wendy
|title={{IAST|Purāṇa perennis}}: reciprocity and transformation in Hindu and Jaina texts
|publisher=State University of New York Press
|location=Albany, N.Y
|year=1993
|pages=331
|isbn=0-7914-1381-0
|oclc=
|url=http://books.google.com/?id=KI5D5aexThoC&amp;printsec=frontcover
|accessdate=
}}p.210-212&lt;/ref&gt;
According to an opinion of some scholars in Patanjali's time identification of Krishna with Vasudeva is an established fact as is surmised from a passage of the Mahabhasya - (''jaghana kamsam kila vasudevah'').&lt;ref name = Shastri&gt;A Corpus of Indian Studies: Essays in Honour of Professor Gaurinath Sastri, Page 150, 1980 - 416 pages.&lt;/ref&gt; This &quot;supposed earliest phase is though to have been established from the sixth to the fifth centuries BCE at the time of Panini, who in his Astadhyayi explained the word ''vasudevaka'' as a bhakta, devotee, of Vasudeva and its believed that [[Bhagavata]] religion with the worship of Vasudeva Krishna were at the root of the Vaishnavism in Indian history.&quot;&lt;ref name = Kakati53&gt;Page 76 of 386 pages: The Bhagavata religion with the worship of Vasudeva Krishna as the ... of Vasudeva Krishna and they are the direct forerunners of Vaisnavism in India.{{cite journal
| author = Ehrenfels, U.R.
| year = 1953
| title = The University Of Gauhati
| journal = Dr. B. Kakati Commemoration Volume
| ref = harv
}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Page 98: In the Mahabharata, Vasudeva-Krishna is identified with the highest God.{{cite book
| author = Mishra, Y.K.
| year = 1977
| title = Socio-economic and Political History of Eastern India
| publisher = Distributed by DK Publishers' Distributors
| isbn =
}}&lt;/ref&gt;
Not just Indian [[Gupta period]] but also some historical records of the Greeks show existence of the bhakti tradition to Krishna-Vaasudeva,&lt;ref name=Vaidisa1987&gt;{{cite journal
| author = Vaidisa, B.
| coauthors = Wessanagar, V.; Others,
| year = 1987
| title = The Impact Of Vaisnavism—excavated Remains From Vidisha (mp)
| journal = Vaisnavism in Indian Arts and Culture: Collected Papers of the University Grants Commission National Seminar on&quot; Impact of Vaisnavism on the Indian Arts&quot;
| ref = harv
}}&lt;/ref&gt; it needs to be noted that, even Panini gives some support to the ancient root of Krishna-Vaasudeva bhakti - (''{{IAST|vāsudeva arjunābhyāṁ}}'', or related to [[Arjuna]]),&lt;ref&gt;{{IAST|bhaktiḥ}} | 4.3.96 {{IAST|acittāt adeśakālāt ṭhak}} | 4.3.97 {{IAST|mahārājāt ṭhañ}} | 4.3.98 {{IAST|vāsudeva arjunābhyāṁ vun}} | Panini 4.3.95&lt;/ref&gt; its is however only much later (2nd century BC) [[Patanjali]] who refer in his definition of the ''devotee'' or ''bhakta'' as &quot;the follower of Vasudeva, God of gods.&quot;&lt;ref name = Shastri/&gt;&lt;ref name = Singh2007&gt;{{cite book
| author = Singh, R.R.
| year = 2007
| title = Bhakti And Philosophy
| publisher = Lexington Books
| isbn = 0739114247
}} p. 10: &quot;[Panini's] term Vaasudevaka, explained by the second century B.C commentator Patanjali, as referring to &quot;the follower of Vasudeva, God of gods.&quot;&lt;/ref&gt;

==Other uses==
In the [[Bhagavata purana]] the term is used for other forms of God, including [[Dhanvantari]],&lt;ref&gt;Bhag.P. 2.7.21: ''{{IAST|dhanvantariś ca bhagavān svayam eva kīrtir nāmnā nṛṇāṁ puru-rujāṁ ruja āśu hanti}}
{{IAST|yajñe ca bhāgam amṛtāyur-avāvarundha}}
{{IAST|āyuṣya-vedam anuśāsty avatīrya loke}}.'' The Lord in His incarnation of Dhanvantari very quickly cures the diseases of the ever-diseased living entities simply by his fame personified, and only because of him do the demigods achieve long lives. Thus the Personality of Godhead becomes ever glorified. He also exacted a share from the sacrifices, and it is he only who inaugurated the medical science or the knowledge of medicine in the universe.&lt;/ref&gt; [[Vamana]],&lt;ref&gt;Bhag. P. 5.24.27: ''{{IAST|tasyānucaritam upariṣṭād vistariṣyate yasya bhagavān svayam akhila-jagad-gurur nārāyaṇo dvāri gadā-pāṇir avatiṣṭhate nija-janānukampita-hṛdayo yenāṅguṣṭhena padā daśa-kandharo yojanāyutāyutaṁ dig-vijaya uccāṭitaḥ.}}'' Śukadeva Gosvāmī continued: My dear King, how shall I glorify the character of Bali Mahārāja? The Supreme Personality of Godhead, the master of the three worlds, who is most compassionate to His own devotee, stands with club in hand at Bali Mahārāja's door. When {{IAST|Rāvaṇa}}, the powerful demon, came to gain victory over Bali Mahārāja, Vāmanadeva kicked him a distance of eighty thousand miles with His big toe. I shall explain the character and activities of Bali Mahārāja later [in the Eighth Canto of Śrīmad-Bhāgavatam].&lt;/ref&gt; [[Vishnu]],&lt;ref&gt;Bhag. P. 7.1.1 ''{{IAST|samaḥ priyaḥ suhṛd brahman bhūtānāṁ bhagavān svayam indrasyārthe kathaṁ daityān avadhīd viṣamo yathā}}'' King {{IAST|Parīkṣit}} inquired: My dear {{IAST|brāhmaṇa}}, the Supreme Personality of Godhead, {{IAST|Viṣṇu}}, being everyone's well-wisher, is equal and extremely dear to everyone. How, then, did He become partial like a common man for the sake of Indra and thus kill Indra's enemies? How can a person equal to everyone be partial to some and inimical toward others?&lt;/ref&gt; [[Vaikuntha]]deva.&lt;ref&gt;Bhag. P. 8.5.4 ''{{IAST|patnī vikuṇṭhā śubhrasya
vaikuṇṭhaiḥ sura-sattamaiḥ}}
{{IAST|tayoḥ sva-kalayā jajñe}}
{{IAST|vaikuṇṭho bhagavān svayam}}'' From the combination of Śubhra and his wife, {{IAST|Vikuṇṭhā}}, there appeared the Supreme Personality of Godhead, {{IAST|Vaikuṇṭha}}, along with demigods who were His personal plenary expansions.&lt;/ref&gt; Although the term appears in the text referring to other forms, these references do not form a part of the [[Krishnology|Krishna-centered theology]] on which the reference to [[Krishna]] is based.

The [[Brahma Vaivarta Purana]] and [[Garga Samhita]] often refer to Krishna as  {{IAST|''paripūrṇatama''}},  the term used in Gaudiya Vaishnava tradition by [[Bhaktivinoda Thakura]] in his ''Amnaya Sutra''  -  ''krishnas tu paripurnatma sarvatra sukha-rupakah'' translated as 'original Supreme Personality of Godhead'.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;In that devotional liberation the spiritual senses of the spiritual form of the liberated soul are filled.  There Lord Krishna, the original Supreme Personality of Godhead, enjoys blissful pastimes.&quot; [http://nitaaiveda.com/All_Scriptures_By_Acharyas/Bhaktivinoda_Thakura/Amnaya_Sutra.htm Amnaya Sutra] 3.5 Sampatti-prakarana, Sutra 114&lt;/ref&gt;

==See also==
{{Commons category|Krishna}}
{{refbegin|3}}
*[[Acintya Bheda Abheda]]
*[[Bhagavata]]
*[[Gopala Tapani Upanishad]]
*[[International Society for Krishna Consciousness|Hare Krishna]]
*[[Krishna]]
*[[Krishnology]]
*[[Narayana]]
*[[Para Brahman]]
*[[Radha]]
*[[Vasudeva]]
*[[Vedanta]]
*[[Vishnu]]
{{refend}}

==Notes==
{{reflist|2|120%}}

==References==

* {{cite book
| author = Elkman, S.M.
| coauthors = Gosvami, J.
| year = 1986
| title = Jiva Gosvamin's Tattvasandarbha: A Study on the Philosophical and Sectarian Development of the Gaudiya Vaisnava Movement
| publisher = Motilal Banarsidass Pub
| isbn =
}}
*{{cite book
| author = Flood, G.D.
| authorlink = Gavin Flood
| year = 2006
| title = The Tantric Body: The Secret Tradition of Hindu Religion
| publisher = IB Tauris
| isbn = 1845110129
}}
* {{cite book
| author = Kennedy, M.T.
| year = 1925
| title = The Chaitanya Movement: A Study of the Vaishnavism of Bengal
| publisher = H. Milford, Oxford university press
| isbn =
}}
* {{cite journal
| author = Ramanuja
| coauthors = George Thibaut (trans.)
| year =  1962
| title =  The Vedanta Sutras with the Commentary by Ramanuja
| publisher = Delhi: Motilal Banarsidass
| ref = harv
}}
* {{cite journal
| author = Richard Thompson, Ph. D.
| year =  December         1994
| title =     Reflections               on the Relation Between Religion               and Modern Rationalism
| url = http://content.iskcon.com/icj/1_2/12thompson.html
| accessdate = 2008-04-12
| ref = harv
}}
* {{cite book
| author = Gupta, Ravi M.
| authorlink = Ravi Gupta
| year = 2004
| title = Caitanya Vaisnava Vedanta: Acintyabhedabheda in Jiva Gosvami's Catursutri tika
| publisher = University Of Oxford
| isbn =
}}
* {{cite book
| author = Gupta, Ravi M.
| coauthors =
| year = 2007
| title = Caitanya Vaisnava Vedanta of Jiva Gosvami's Catursutri tika
| publisher = Routledge
| isbn = 0415405483
}}
*{{cite book
| author = Ganguli, K.M.
| year = 1883 -1896
| title = The Mahabharata of Krishna Dwaipayana Vyasa
| publisher = Kessinger Publishing
| isbn =
}}

*{{cite book
| author = Kaviraja, K.
| coauthors = Prabhupada, A.C.B.S.; Bhaktivedanta, A.C.
| year = 1974
| title = Sri Caitanya-Caritamrta of Krsnadasa Kaviraja
| publisher = [[Bhaktivedanta Book Trust]]
| isbn =
}}
* {{Cite document | title = The Qualities of Sri Krsna | author = S.D. Goswami| authorlink = Satsvarupa dasa Goswami | publisher = GNPress | year = 1998 | pages  = 152 pages | isbn = 0911233644 | ref = harv | postscript = &lt;!--None--&gt;}}
* ''Garuda Pillar of Besnagar'', Archaeological Survey of India, Annual Report (1908–1909). Calcutta: Superintendent of Government Printing, 1912, 129.
* {{cite journal
| author = Rowland Jr, B.
| year = 1935
| title = Notes on Ionic Architecture in the East
| journal = American Journal of Archaeology
| volume = 39
| issue = 4
| pages = 489–496
| doi = 10.2307/498156
| jstor = 498156
| publisher = Archaeological Institute of America
| ref = harv
}}
* {{Cite journal
| author = Delmonico, N.
| year = 2004
| title = The History Of Indic Monotheism And Modern Chaitanya Vaishnavism
| journal = The Hare Krishna Movement: the Postcharismatic Fate of a Religious Transplant
| url = http://books.google.com/?id=mBMxPdgrBhoC&amp;pg=PA31&amp;dq=Vaisnava+monotheism
| accessdate = 2008-04-12
| publisher = Columbia University Press
| isbn = 9780231122566
| ref = harv
}}
* {{cite journal
| author = Mahony, W.K.
| year = 1987
| title = Perspectives on Krsna's Various Personalities
| journal = History of Religions
| volume = 26
| issue = 3
| pages = 333–335
| jstor = 1062381
| ref = harv
| doi=10.1086/463085
}}
* {{cite journal
| author = D Hudson
| year = 1993
| title = Vasudeva Krsna in Theology and Architecture: A Background to Srivaisnavism
| journal = Journal of Vaisnava Studies
| volume =
| issue = 2
| pages =
| url =
| accessdate = | ref = harv
}}

* {{Cite book | title =Alternative Krishnas: Regional and Vernacular Variations on a Hindu Deity | last = Beck| first = Guy L. (Ed.) | authorlink = Guy Beck |url = http://books.google.com/?id=0SJ73GHSCF8C | publisher = SUNY Press | year = 2005 | isbn =0791464156 | ref =harv | postscript =&lt;!--None--&gt;}}

*{{cite book
|author=Matchett, Freda
|title=Krsna, Lord or Avatara? the relationship between Krsna and Visnu: in the context of the Avatara myth as presented by the Harivamsa, the Visnupurana and the Bhagavatapurana
|publisher=Routledge
|location=Surrey
|year=2000
|pages=254
|isbn=0-7007-1281-X
|oclc=
|doi=
}}
*{{cite book
|author=Valpey, Kenneth Russell
|title=Attending {{IAST|Kṛṣṇa}}'s image: {{IAST|Caitanya Vaiṣṇava mūrti-sevā}} as devotional truth
|publisher=Routledge
|location=New York
|year=2006
|pages=
|isbn=0-415-38394-3
|oclc=
|doi=
}}
&lt;/div&gt;

==Further reading==
*{{cite book
| author = Ganguli, K.M.
| year = 1896
| title = Bhagavad-Gita ([http://www.sacred-texts.com/hin/m06/m06025.htm XXV]-[http://www.sacred-texts.com/hin/m06/m06042.htm XLII]). [http://www.sacred-texts.com/hin/maha/index.htm The Mahabharata], Book 6
| publisher = Calcutta: Bharata Press
| isbn =
}}

* {{cite book
| author = Prabhupada, A.C.
| year = 1988
| title = Srimad-Bhagavatam
| url = http://www.vedabase.org/sb/
| publisher = Bhaktivedanta Book Trust
| isbn =
}}

==External links==
*[http://www.stephen-knapp.com/sri_krishna.htm Sri Krishna - Differences in Realisation &amp; Perception of the Supreme] (stephen-knapp.com)
*[http://srimadbhagavatam.com/1/3/28/en1 The full text of the Bhagavata Purana (Srimad-Bhagavatam)] (srimadbhagavatam.com)

&lt;br&gt;
{{Krishna|state=collapsed}}

[[Category:Krishna]]
[[Category:Sanskrit words and phrases]]
[[Category:Vaishnavism]]
[[Category:Hindu philosophical concepts]]
[[Category:Gaudiya Vaisnava philosophical concepts]]
[[Category:Titles and names of Krishna]]
[[Category:Monotheism]]
[[Category:Names of God in Hinduism]]

[[bn:স্বয়ং ভগবান]]
[[id:Swayam Bhagawan]]
[[kn:ಸ್ವಯಂ ಭಗವಾನ್]]
[[mk:Свајам-багаван]]
[[ru:Сваям-бхагаван]]
[[uk:Сваям-бхагаван]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
