<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="1690431" ns="0" title="Ron Darling"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Infobox MLB player
|name=Ron Darling
|position=[[Pitcher]]
|image=Ron Darling, April 2009 cropped.jpg
|caption=Ron Darling on September 28, 2008
|bats=Right
|throws=Right
|birth_date={{Birth date and age|mf=yes|1960|8|19}}
|birth_place=[[Honolulu, Hawaii]]
|debutdate=September 6
|debutyear=1983
|debutteam=New York Mets
|finaldate=August 15
|finalyear=1995
|finalteam=Oakland Athletics
|stat1label=[[Win–loss record (pitching)|Win–Loss record]]
|stat1value=136–116
|stat2label=[[Earned run average]]
|stat2value=3.87
|stat3label=[[Strikeouts]]
|stat3value=1,590
|teams=&lt;nowiki&gt;&lt;/nowiki&gt;
* [[New York Mets]] ({{By|1983}}–{{By|1991}})
* [[Montreal Expos]] ({{By|1991}})
* [[Oakland Athletics]] ({{By|1991}}–{{By|1995}})
|highlights=&lt;nowiki&gt;&lt;/nowiki&gt;
* [[Major League Baseball All-Star Game|All-Star]] selection ([[1985 Major League Baseball All-Star Game|1985]])
* [[World Series]] champion ({{wsy|1986}})
* [[Gold Glove Award]] winner (1989)
}}
'''Ronald Maurice Darling, Jr.''' (born August 19, 1960) is an American former right-handed [[starting pitcher]] in [[Major League Baseball]] who played for the [[New York Mets]], [[Oakland Athletics]] and [[Montreal Expos]]. Darling currently works as a [[color commentator]] for national baseball coverage on [[Major League Baseball on TBS|TBS]] as well as for the Mets on both [[SportsNet New York|SNY]] and [[WPIX-TV|WPIX]].

During his 13-year career, Darling amassed a 136–116 won-loss record, with 13 [[shutout]]s. He threw 1,590 strikeouts and had a 3.87 ERA. In 1985, he was picked for the [[Major League Baseball All-Star Game|All-Star team]]. 

Darling's weak point was control; he finished seasons in the top four in [[base on balls]] three times. He was considered one of the better fielding pitchers of the time, and won a [[Gold Glove Award]] in 1989. Darling had one of the best [[pickoff]] moves among right-handers. An above-average athlete, he was sometimes used as a [[pinch runner]]. In 1989, he hit [[home run]]s in two consecutive starts.

==Early life ==
Born in [[Honolulu, Hawaii]] to a [[Chinese immigration to Hawaii|Hawaiian-Chinese]] mother and [[French-Canadian]] father, Darling speaks fluent [[Chinese language|Chinese]] and [[French language|French]]. After growing up in [[Millbury, Massachusetts]], he attended [[St. John's High School (Massachusetts)|St. John's High School]] in [[Shrewsbury, Massachusetts]].  

==College==
He later attended [[Yale University]], where he had a dual major in French and [[Southeast Asian]] history. He was set to graduate in December 1982, but was drafted in June 1981.&lt;ref name=&quot;YaleGrad&quot;&gt;{{cite web
  |url=http://www.yaleherald.com/archive/xxviii/1999.12.03/sports/p21darling.html
  |title=Ron Darling
  |publisher=[[The Yale Herald]]
  |accessdate=October 17, 2006
  |date=December 3, 1999
  |last=Diskant
  |first=Ted
}}&lt;/ref&gt; 

At Yale, Darling began his college career for the [[Yale Bulldogs]] in the [[Ivy League]] as a position player, and did not pitch regularly until his sophomore season. On May 21, 1981, Darling faced future Mets teammate [[Frank Viola]], then of [[St. John's University (New York City)|St. John's University]], and had a [[no-hitter]] through 11 innings. In the 12th inning, St. John's broke up the no-hitter and then scored on a double-[[Stolen base|steal]] to beat Darling 1–0. Darling's performance remains the longest no-hitter in [[NCAA Baseball|NCAA]] history, and the game is considered by some to be the best in college baseball history.&lt;ref name=&quot;YaleNoHit&quot;&gt;{{cite web
  |url=http://yalebulldogs.cstv.com/facilities/facyalefield.html
  |title=Yale Field
  |publisher=[[Yale University]]
  |accessdate=June 17, 2006}}
&lt;/ref&gt;

Darling went on to play more games in major-league baseball than any Yale alumnus since 19th-century pitcher [[Bill Hutchinson (baseball)|Bill Hutchinson]].&lt;ref name=&quot;CollegePos&quot;&gt;{{cite episode
  |title=Mets game broadcast
  |airdate=2006-06-17
  |credits=Ron Darling
  |network=[[WPIX]] TV}}
&lt;/ref&gt;

Darling was the last former Yale Bulldog to reach the major leagues until pitcher [[Craig Breslow]] made his debut in {{By|2005}}, and was not followed by another Yale player until catcher [[Ryan Lavarnway]] in 2011.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last=Kerzel |first=Pete |url=http://web.minorleaguebaseball.com/news/article.jsp?ymd=20100518&amp;content_id=10160490&amp;vkey=news_milb&amp;fext=.jsp |title=Carolina League notebook |publisher=minorleaguebaseball.com |date=May 19, 2010 |accessdate=August 20, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | title=Breslow Joins The Tribe | url=http://www.cstv.com/sports/m-basebl/stories/040208abb.html | accessdate=April 16, 2009 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Minor leagues==
He was selected in the 1st round (9th overall) of the {{By|1981}} MLB draft by the [[Texas Rangers (baseball)|Texas Rangers]]. He put up mediocre numbers with the AA [[Tulsa Drillers]] and, before the {{By|1982}} season began, he and [[Walt Terrell]] were traded to the Mets for [[Lee Mazzilli]] in an ill-advised trade. For the Mets, Darling and Terrell would eventually combine for seven double-digit win seasons. They traded Terrell three seasons later for [[Howard Johnson (baseball player)|Howard Johnson]]. For Texas, Mazzilli never regained his limited glory of the late 1970s.

Darling would have compiled decent numbers with the AAA [[Tidewater Tides]] in 1982 and {{By|1983}} except for very high [[base on balls]] counts during both seasons. Despite that, Darling was called up to the majors in late 1983. The Mets had the worst record in the National League and second-worst in the majors when Darling debuted on September 6, 1983. He was impressive in that start but left the game down 1–0 and the Mets lost 2–0. The Mets were also last in offense in the N.L. Darling's 0–3 start were all in decent pitching performances. He finished his season with a [[complete game]] victory and was in the majors for good.

==New York Mets==
===Building to a championship===
In {{By|1984}}, Darling won a spot in the starting rotation and maintained a spot there almost uninterrupted until {{By|1990}}. While his early walk percentages were poor — he even led the league in walks in {{By|1985}} — he never again showed the terrible walk percentages he had at AAA.

With Darling and Terrell each getting their first long-term chance in the majors and with the debut of young star and eventual [[MLB Rookie of the Year Award|Rookie of the Year]] [[Dwight Gooden]], the Mets went from second-worst in the majors in 1983 to fourth-best in the majors in 1984 — but also second-best in the division thereby missing the postseason. Darling had difficulty pitching on the road in 1984 compared to pitcher-friendly [[Shea Stadium]] including an [[Earned run average|ERA]] more than 50% higher. He had a streak of seven wins in seven starts in June (5–0) and July (1.88 ERA) including a pair of [[complete game]] four-hit [[shutout]]s but the other two-thirds of the season were not nearly as successful. The Mets were in first place at the end of July but Darling's 2–6 record the rest of the way was little help and the [[Chicago Cubs]] won the division by 6 ½ games. Darling finished 12–9 overall with an ERA of 3.81.

1985 was an improvement for Darling despite a career-high 114 walks. His April included a one-hit seven-inning no-decision and a five-hit shutout with 11 strikeouts. On July 4, Darling pitched on one day's rest making the only relief appearance of his first seven seasons during a marathon 19-inning 16–13 win. Darling finished the legendary game in which 13 runs were scored in the extra innings alone and the Mets blew four leads and nearly blew a fifth. After starting 9–2, he was selected to his only [[Major League Baseball All-Star Game|All-Star team]] but did not participate in the game. Overall, he posted his career-best winning percentage with a 16–6 record. His record could have been even better but, in eight of his starts, he received seven no-decisions and a loss despite allowing less than two earned runs each time. On October 1, Darling pitched nine shutout innings on only four hits but the game was scoreless until the 11th. The Mets narrowly missed the postseason but Darling established himself as a clear number-two starter behind Gooden's untouchable 24–4 season.

===Pitches===
Ron Darling has five pitches in his repetoir which include: A slider, curveball , circle change up, splitter, and a four seam fastball.

===World series===
In {{By|1986}}, everything came together for the Mets and Darling was no exception. He finished with a 15–6 record and posted his career-best 2.81 ERA which was third-best in the N.L. He also received the only [[Cy Young Award]] votes of his career, finishing fifth behind [[Mike Scott (baseball)|Mike Scott]] who had his best season. The Mets led the way most of the season and their top four starters all received Cy Young votes. On May 27, Darling tied his career-high with 12 strikeouts in a five-hit complete game victory which, despite a poor April, raised his record to 6–0. He was good on the road but even better at home with a 10–2 record at Shea. His worst blemish was off the field when, on July 19, he and teammates [[Bob Ojeda]], [[Rick Aguilera]] and [[Tim Teufel]] were arrested outside a bar in [[Houston, Texas]] for fighting with security guards (who were also off-duty police officers). All four were released in time for the following game and the worst results were $200 fines but the incident fed into the Mets' reputation as a rowdy crew that season. Despite the run-in, Darling was featured on the cover of the August 25 issue of [[Sports Illustrated]] magazine.

The [[1986 National League Championship Series]] was tied 1–1 when Darling started Game 3 but he pitched poorly and left losing 4–0. The Mets recovered to win both the game and eventually the series. Darling opened the [[1986 World Series|World Series]] against the [[Boston Red Sox]]. He pitched extremely well in Game 1 allowing only a single unearned run but lost a hard-luck 1–0 game to [[Bruce Hurst]]. With the Mets in danger of falling into a 3–1 series deficit, Darling started Game 4 and extended his 0.00 ERA to 14 innings as the Mets won easily, 6–2. After Game 6, [[Bill Buckner]] and the Sox bounced back in Game 7, scoring three early runs against Darling. Shaky into the fourth inning, Darling was relieved but the Mets recovered to win their second World Championship.

===Post-championship decline===
Darling went 12–8 in {{By|1987}} but had to battle most of the way, as did the rest of the team. Darling's April ERA was over six and he didn't win a game in either May or June, going 0–4 with eight no-decisions between victories. He rebounded to win six consecutive starts after the All-Star break but a good second half only lowered his ERA to 4.29 — the worst of his first seven seasons. On June 28, Darling had a [[no-hitter]] through seven innings but the Mets wound up losing the game. They were poised for a run at the division in mid-September when Darling went out with one of the few injuries of his career. He missed the last couple weeks of the season and the Mets missed the postseason.

In {{By|1988}}, Darling bounced back with a career high 17 wins. He started quickly with two shutouts in his first four games. A first-half 10–5 record with three shutouts and a 2.70 ERA were not enough to earn an All-Star spot. On the season, he compiled a career-high four shutouts but also suffered one of his worst games, getting knocked out in the first inning of an 11–2 loss on July 19. Darling's home-versus-road discrepancy was enormous as he went 14–1 at Shea and only 3–8 on the road with an ERA more than twice as high. He finished the season strong winning his last five decisions and the Mets coasted into the playoffs but Darling pitched poorly in the [[1988 National League Championship Series]] against the [[Los Angeles Dodgers]]. With the series tied 1–1, he fell into an early 3–0 hole but the Mets bounced back twice to win 8–4. In the deciding Game 7, Darling was again matched against 1988's best pitcher, [[Orel Hershiser]], but was overmatched. Darling gave up six runs and was knocked out in the second inning while Hershiser pitched a five-hit shutout shocking the Mets and winning the series' [[Most Valuable Player]] award. The one-sided game was the last postseason appearance for the Mets until 1999.

After their 100-win 1988 season ended, the Mets started a decline that lasted well into the 1990s. Darling's {{By|1989}} started as poorly as 1988 had ended when he lost his first three starts with an ERA of 11.57. He recovered with a good May but was inconsistent for the entire season, finishing 14–14 with a 3.52 ERA. Darling's five losses in his last seven starts contributed to the Mets missing the postseason. Darling did become the first Mets pitcher to win the [[Gold Glove Award]]. He was also the last N.L. pitcher to win the award before [[Greg Maddux]]'s remarkable streak of 13 consecutive Gold Gloves. On August 10, 1989, Darling won his 83rd game with the Mets to move him past [[Jon Matlack]] into fourth on the Mets' all-time wins list where he remains today (behind [[Tom Seaver]], [[Dwight Gooden]] and [[Jerry Koosman]]).

In {{By|1990}}, the Mets were in transition and [[Manager (baseball)|manager]] [[Davey Johnson]]'s job was in jeopardy. Darling was sent to the bullpen part-time for the first time in his career. His first relief performance in late April went well but was followed by three terrible starts. The rest of his season was a mix of starting and relief. With an ERA of 4.60 in late August, Darling was in the bullpen for the next month. He made two starts to close out his season and won them both but the Mets could not catch the [[Pittsburgh Pirates]]. In total, 1990 was Darling's first losing season (7–9) and was his worst ERA to-date.

==Trade and American League==
Darling was back in the New York Mets' starting rotation in {{By|1991}}. Although his pitching was improved over 1990, he was still inconsistent, winning three games with scoreless pitching but getting hit hard in many other games. Unlike previous seasons, Darling posted poor numbers at Shea Stadium while pitching well on the road. He pitched scoreless two-hit ball over eight innings in Montreal in his last pre-All-Star break game but pitched only once more before being traded.

Darling's Mets career came to an end on July 15, 1991 when he was traded with a minor leaguer to the [[Montreal Expos]] (the team he had two-hit less than two weeks earlier) for former [[Closer (baseball)|closer]], [[Tim Burke (baseball)|Tim Burke]]. Burke pitched well for the Mets but their 28–48 record after the trade was the worst in the majors. Burke was out of the majors after {{By|1992}} and the Mets were terrible for the next several years (though more due to ill-advised expensive acquisitions than the Darling trade). Darling's three starts for Montreal were poor with an ERA of 7.41. The Expos re-traded Darling to the [[Oakland Athletics]] on July 31, 1991 for two minor leaguers. After the Darling trades, the Expos were left with three minor leaguers, none of whom played more than two games in the majors.

With Oakland, Darling immediately logged two seven-inning scoreless starts and won his first three decisions. Then, his poor control returned and Darling lost seven straight decisions including his last six starts. In three of those losses, he allowed two or fewer runs. Oakland, coming off its third consecutive league pennant, was barely above .500 before acquiring Darling. His acquisition did little to affect that.

After the 1991 season, Darling became a [[free agent]] and re-signed with Oakland. In {{By|1992}}, he had his last quality year, finishing with over 200 [[innings pitched]], a 3.66 ERA and 15 wins. Inconsistent for most of the season, Darling also showed flashes of brilliance, including three complete game two-hit shutouts — the only two-hitters of his career. He was the victim of poor run support including a no-decision seven-inning one-hitter that was nearly a loss, an eight-inning two-hitter that turned into a no-decision after an unearned run, and two other games where he allowed one earned run and took the loss. Darling finished with the best record on the team percentage-wise. Oakland coasted into the postseason with little trouble and Darling was called to start Game 3 with the series tied. He pitched well but gave up two costly home runs and took the loss. The A's went on to lose Games 4 and 6 as well and Darling never again pitched in the postseason. Similar to the Mets, the A's descended into a postseason drought that lasted seven seasons.

Darling re-signed with Oakland again after 1992, this time a multi-year deal for over $2 million per season, but he was unable to repeat his 1992 performance. {{By|1993}} was awful for Darling. Through July, his ERA hovered around six and he was relegated to long relief for over a week. He pitched better after July lowering his ERA to 5.16 but lost five of his last six decisions.

Outside of July, Darling's {{By|1994}} would have been as bad as 1993. In July, he won five starts with one no-decision with an ERA under three. It was Darling's last hurrah. He stumbled through two starts in August before the [[1994 Major League Baseball strike]] ended the season. With his torrid July, Darling reached double digits in wins once again but finished under .500 with a 4.50 ERA. Darling led the [[American League]] with 25 games started despite pitching that was average at best.

When the strike lasted into {{By|1995}}, Darling started terribly, logging an ERA over nine in his four starts without making it through the fifth inning in any of them. His only complete game of the season ended with a 1–0 loss on May 30. Darling won only four games with an ERA of 6.23. After a bad loss, Oakland released him on August 19, 1995 (his birthday) bringing his playing career to an end.

==Post-retirement==
Since 2000, Darling has been active in television. He worked as a broadcaster for the A's, had a [[Fox Broadcasting Company|FOX]] show called ''Baseball Today'' and appeared on ''[[The Best Damn Sports Show Period]]''.&lt;ref name=&quot;BlackAthlete&quot;&gt;{{cite web
  |url=http://www.blackathlete.net/artman/publish/article_01057.shtml
  |last=Peay
  |first=Carla
  |title=Not A Television Darling? Perhaps He Should Be
  |publisher=Black Athlete Sports Network
  |accessdate=June 17, 2006
  |date=September 7, 2005}}
&lt;/ref&gt; He also provided baseball analysis for the [[YES Network]], [[Fox Sports Net]] and, in 2004, [[CBS College Sports Network|CSTV]].&lt;ref name=&quot;BaseballAmerica&quot;&gt;{{cite web
  |url=http://www.baseballamerica.com/today/college/040603tv.html
  |last=Manuel
  |first=John
  |title=Regionals Exposure On TV Grows
  |publisher=[[Baseball America]]
  |accessdate=June 17, 2006
  |date=June 3, 2004}}
&lt;/ref&gt;

Darling appeared on the [[Baseball Hall of Fame balloting, 2001|Hall of Fame balloting for 2001]], receiving one vote.

In 2005, Darling was involved in banking ventures in [[Southern California]].&lt;ref name=&quot;AddictSports&quot;&gt;{{cite web
  |url=http://www.addictsports.com/baseball/showthread.php?p=364709
  |last=Marchand
  |first=Andrew
  |title=Former Mets Avoid 'Roids'
  |publisher=[[New York Post]]
  |accessdate=June 17, 2006
  |date=February 27, 2005}}
&lt;/ref&gt;  He was then hired to be the television [[color commentator]] for the inaugural season of the [[Washington Nationals]]. Darling worked alongside veteran [[play-by-play]] announcer [[Mel Proctor]] on the [[Mid-Atlantic Sports Network]], which suffered from low viewership due to legal battles between [[Baltimore Orioles]] owner [[Peter Angelos]] and [[Comcast]] cable television.&lt;ref name=&quot;WashPostTV&quot;&gt;{{cite web
  |url=http://www.washingtonpost.com/wp-dyn/content/article/2005/06/27/AR2005062701515_pf.html
  |last=Dwyer
  |first=Timothy
  |title=Nats Caught in a TV Rundown
  |publisher=The Washington Post
  |accessdate=June 17, 2006
  |date=June 28, 2005}}
&lt;/ref&gt; Darling and Proctor were not asked back by the Nationals for 2006.

In 2006, Darling was hired by [[SportsNet New York]] as a color commentator and studio analyst for the Mets, joining veteran [[Gary Cohen]] and former Mets teammate [[Keith Hernandez]].  Darling also appears on some of the SNY-produced [[WPIX]] broadcasts in the [[New York Metropolitan Area]]. He won an Emmy Award as &quot;Best Sports Analyst&quot; for his work on the Mets broadcasts. Darling currently lives in Manhattan.&lt;ref name=&quot;residence&quot;&gt;{{cite web
  |url=http://www.sny.tv/announcers/mets_onair.jsp#darling
  |title=Mets On-Air Talent
  |publisher=[[SportsNet New York]]
  |accessdate=July 4, 2007}}
&lt;/ref&gt; He appeared in a [[Sovereign Bank]] commercial in 2008, which is frequently shown on SNY and is often joked about between the three Mets broadcasters during games.

Because of their popularity, Darling along with Cohen and Hernandez have created a website ([http://www.pitchinforagoodcause.org www.pitchinforagoodcause.org]), where the net profit from the merchandise sold by the website goes to charity; specifically, the Cobble Hill Health Center, Juvenile Diabetes Research Center, and The Danbury Women's Center.

Darling had small roles in the films ''[[Shallow Hal]]'' and ''[[The Day After Tomorrow]]''. He also played himself in ''[[Mr. 3000]]''.

He threw out the ceremonial first pitch during Game 7 of the [[2006 National League Championship Series|2006 NLCS]]

In 2007, Darling was a color analyst for [[Major League Baseball on TBS|TBS]]' coverage of the 2007 MLB playoffs. He was paired with play-by-play man [[Dick Stockton]]. As of 2008, he provides commentary for the network's regular-season coverage, paired with [[Chip Caray]]. During the playoffs, he joined Caray's other regular partner, [[Buck Martinez]].

As of 2011, Darling is still a color analyst for TBS.

==The Complete Game: Reflections on Baseball, Pitching, and Life on the Mound==
In March 2009, Alfred A. Knopf published Darling's book [http://www.randomhouse.com/knopf/catalog/display.pperl?isbn=9780307269843 The Complete Game: Reflections on Baseball, Pitching, and Life on the Mound].
The Book is a compilation of a number of innings throughout Darling's career. It is his attempt to bring the reader's mind into the mind of a major league pitcher. He breaks down and explains what is going through his head at various points in time during his career.

Chapter 1 – First Inning – Getting Started – September 6, 1983: [[Philadelphia Phillies]] vs [[New York Mets]]

Chapter 2 – Second Inning – Finding My Way – October 22, 1986: [[New York Mets]] vs [[Boston Red Sox]]

Chapter 3 – Third Inning – Dealing with Adversity – April 22, 1984: [[New York Mets]] vs [[Philadelphia Phillies]]

Chapter 4 – Fourth Inning – On the Defensive – April 1, 2008: [[New York Mets]] vs [[Florida Marlins]]

Chapter 5 – Fifth Inning – The Longest Walk – August 7, 1984:[[New York Mets]] vs [[Chicago Cubs]]

Chapter 6 – Sixth Inning – Taking Chances – September 11, 1987: [[St. Louis Cardinals]] vs [[New York Mets]]

Chapter 7 – Seventh Inning – Righty-Lefty-Righty – June 16, 2008:[[New York Mets]] vs [[Los Angeles Angels of Anaheim]]

Chapter 8 – Eighth Inning – On a Roll – July 12, 1992:[[Oakland Athletics]] vs [[Toronto Blue Jays]]&lt;ref&gt;http://www.retrosheet.org/boxesetc/1992/B07120TOR1992.htm&lt;/ref&gt;

Chapter 9 – Ninth Inning – Clincher – September 22, 1988: [[Philadelphia Phillies]] vs [[New York Mets]]

Chapter 10 – Extra Innings – The Old College Try – May 21, 1981:St. John's Redmen vs Yale Bulldogs

Chapter 11 – Post Game – Done

==Personal==
He was married to [[Irish people|Irish]] [[Wilhelmina Models|Wilhelmina]] model [[Antoinette O'Reilly]], with whom he had two children, Tyler Darling and Jordan Darling. She had small roles on television and in movies, sometimes using her married name, [[Toni Darling]]. During their marriage, they appeared in numerous magazine features together.

In 2004, he married Joanna Last, a makeup artist for [[Fox Sports (USA)|Fox Sports]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://insideweddings.com/real-weddings/9/thats-amore/ Inside Weddings – Real Weddings – That's Amore&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;

Ron's cousin, Gary Darling, is a MLB [[umpire]].&lt;ref&gt;http://mlb.mlb.com/mlb/official_info/umpires/bio.jsp?id=3047&lt;/ref&gt;

==Pop culture==
Game 6 of the '86 World Series, broadcast by [[NBC]], ran so long that the network chose not to air ''[[Saturday Night Live]]'' rather than show it after the game. When it was shown for the first time two weeks later, Darling filmed a special introduction, apologizing on behalf of the Mets for pre-empting SNL.

Ron is mentioned in the ''[[Law &amp; Order|Law and Order]]'' episode &quot;Under God&quot;.  [[Lennie Briscoe]] is telling [[Ed Green]] how he blurts out Darling's first name for no reason, as the pitcher reminds Lennie Briscoe of his daughter Cathy, who was killed in 1998. Cathy had a crush on the pitcher during the 1986 season, when she was a teenager.

==See also==
*[[List of Major League Baseball leaders in career wins]]
*[[List of Washington Nationals broadcasters]]

==References==
*{{cite book|last=Darling|first=Ron|title=The Complete Game: Reflections on Baseball, Pitching, and Life on the Mound|location=New York|publisher=Alfred A. Knopf|year=2009}}

==Notes==
{{reflist}}

==External links==
*[http://mlb.mlb.com/NASApp/mlb/news/article.jsp?ymd=20060113&amp;content_id=1295290&amp;vkey=news_nym&amp;fext=.jsp&amp;c_id=nym Darling chats about role as Mets analyst (chat transcript)]
*{{Baseballstats |mlb= |espn= |br=d/darliro01 |fangraphs=1002989 |cube=ron-darling|brm=darlin001ron}}
*[http://www.garykeithandron.com Gary Cohen, Keith Hernandez, and Ron Darling's Charity website]
*[http://ultimatemets.com/profile.php?PlayerCode=0345 Ron Darling on the Ultimate Mets Database]
*[http://insideweddings.com/real-weddings/joanna-last-ron-darling INSIDE WEDDINGS featured Ron Darling's wedding to Joanna Last.]

&lt;!--spacing, please do not remove--&gt;

{{s-start}}
{{succession box
| before = [[Orel Hershiser]]
| title = [[List of NL Gold Glove winners at pitcher|National League Gold Glove Award (P)]]
| years = {{By|1989}}
| after = [[Greg Maddux]]}}
{{s-end}}

{{Texas Rangers first-round draft picks}}
{{1986 New York Mets}}
{{NL P Gold Glove Award}}
{{Major League Baseball on TBS}}

{{Persondata &lt;!-- Metadata: see [[Wikipedia:Persondata]]. --&gt;
| NAME              = Darling, Ron
| ALTERNATIVE NAMES =
| SHORT DESCRIPTION =
| DATE OF BIRTH     = August 19, 1960
| PLACE OF BIRTH    = Honolulu, Hawaii
| DATE OF DEATH     =
| PLACE OF DEATH    =
}}
{{DEFAULTSORT:Darling, Ron}}
{{SportsNet New York}}
[[Category:1960 births]]
[[Category:Living people]]
[[Category:American sportspeople of Chinese descent]]
[[Category:Gold Glove Award winners]]
[[Category:Major League Baseball announcers]]
[[Category:Major League Baseball pitchers]]
[[Category:Baseball players from Hawaii]]
[[Category:Montreal Expos players]]
[[Category:National League All-Stars]]
[[Category:Native Hawaiian sportspeople]]
[[Category:New York Mets broadcasters]]
[[Category:New York Mets players]]
[[Category:Oakland Athletics players]]
[[Category:Washington Nationals broadcasters]]
[[Category:Yale Bulldogs baseball players]]
[[Category:Yale University alumni]]
[[Category:American people of Canadian descent]]
[[Category:American people of French-Canadian descent]]
[[Category:Tulsa Drillers players]]
[[Category:Tidewater Tides players]]
[[Category:SNY]]
[[Category:MASN]]

[[fr:Ron Darling]]
[[ja:ロン・ダーリング]]
[[fi:Ron Darling]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
