<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="1691838" ns="0" title="HijackThis"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Infobox software
 |name =  HijackThis
 |logo = [[Image:HijackThis-logo.png|48px]]
 |caption = HijackThis 2.0.2 screenshot
 |screenshot = [[Image:HijackThis.png|250px]]
 |developer = [[Trend Micro]]
 |latest_release_version = 2.0.4
 |latest_release_date = {{release date|2010|04|21}}
 |latest preview version = 2.0.5 beta
 |latest preview date    = {{start date and age|2011|02|11}}
 |operating_system = [[Microsoft Windows]]
 |genre = [[Malware]] diagnostics
 |license = [[Freeware]]
 |website = [http://free.antivirus.com/hijackthis/ free.antivirus.com]
}}

'''HijackThis''' ('''HJT''') is a [[freeware]] enumerating tool for [[Microsoft Windows]] originally created by Merijn Bellekom, and later sold to [[Trend Micro]]. The program is notable for targeting [[Browser hijacking|browser-hijacking]] ''methods'', rather than relying on a [[database]] of known spyware. It scans a user's computer quickly, and displays browser hijacking locations, showing what entries are there. HijackThis is used primarily for diagnosis of browser hijacking, as uninformed use of its removal facilities can cause significant software damage to a computer. HijackThis does not remove or detect spyware; it lists most common locations where browser hijacking activity can occur. Browser hijacking can cause malware to be installed on a computer.

==Use==
HijackThis can generate a [[Plain text|plain-text]] logfile detailing all entries it finds, and some entries can be fixed by HijackThis. Inexperienced users are often advised to exercise caution, or to seek help when using the latter option, as HijackThis does not discriminate between legitimate and unwanted items, with the exception of a small whitelist of legitimate entries, thus allowing a user unintentionally to prevent important programs from operating, which may cause the computer or its peripherals to stop working. HijackThis attempts to create backups of the files and registry entries that it fixes, which can be used to restore the system in the event of a mistake.

A common use is to post the logfile to a [[Internet forum|forum]] where more experienced users can help decipher which entries need to be removed. Automated tools also exist that analyze saved logs and attempt to provide recommendations to the user, or to clean entries automatically.&lt;ref name=&quot;automated&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.hijackthis.de|title=HijackThis log analyzer site|accessdate=2008-11-02}}&lt;br /&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.computerhope.com/cgi-bin/process.pl|title=Computer Hope log tool|accessdate=2010-02-02}}&lt;/ref&gt; Use of such tools, however, is generally discouraged by those who specialize in manually dealing with HijackThis logs: they consider the tools dangerous for inexperienced users, and neither accurate nor reliable enough to substitute for consulting with a trained human analyst.

Later versions of HijackThis include such additional tools as a [[task manager]], a [[Hosts file|hosts-file]] editor, and an [[Fork (filesystem)|alternate-data-stream]] scanner.

==Hijack Pro==
During 2002 and 2003, IT entrepreneur Glenn Bluff (owner of [[Computer Hope]] UK) made several attempts to buy Hijackthis.  This led to the joint development of Hijackpro.  A professional version of Hijackthis with the built in capabilities to kill processes similar to [[killbox]].  Hijackpro had 2.3 million downloads from an illegal download site in 2003 and 2004 and was being found on sites claiming it was hijackthis and was free.  [[Hijackpro]] was sold to [[Touchstone software]] now [[Phoenix Technologies]] in 2007 to be integrated into [[DriverAgent.com]] along with Glenn Bluff's other company [[Drivermagic.com]]

== References ==
{{reflist}}
* [http://www.bilisimplatformu.com/forum/forum-hijackthis-tr HijackThis Log Analyse Turkey]

== External links ==
* {{Official website|http://free.antivirus.com/hijackthis}}

[[Category:Spyware removal]]
[[Category:Windows-only freeware]]
[[Category:Portable software]]

[[de:HijackThis]]
[[es:HijackThis]]
[[fr:HijackThis]]
[[it:HijackThis]]
[[nl:HijackThis]]
[[pl:HijackThis]]
[[pt:HijackThis]]
[[ro:HijackThis]]
[[ru:HijackThis]]
[[tr:HijackThis]]
[[zh:HijackThis]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
