<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="169126" ns="0" title="Gauche (Scheme implementation)"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Infobox Software
| name = Gauche
| logo =
| screenshot =
| caption =
| developer = Shiro Kawai
| latest_release_version = 0.9.1
| latest_release_date = December 12, 2010
| operating_system = [[Cross-platform]]
| genre = [[Programming language]]
| license = [[BSD License]]
| website = [http://practical-scheme.net/gauche/ practical-scheme.net/gauche/]
}}

'''Gauche''' is an R5RS [[Scheme (programming language)|Scheme]] implementation.  It is designed for [[Scripting language|scripting]] in a production environment.  It is intended to allow programmers and system administrators to write scripts in support of daily operations. Quick startup, built-in system interface, native multilingual support are some of its key design goals.

Gauche is [[free software]] under the [[BSD License]].  It is primarily developed by Shiro Kawai.



==Features==
*Quick startup - Gauche includes common features in its executable, while less common functions are in libraries which are loaded on demand.
*Module system - A simple module system, API compatible to [[STklos]].
*Object system - [[CLOS]]-like object system with [[metaobject protocol]]. Almost API compatible to STklos. It is also similar to [[GNU Guile|Guile]]'s object system.
*Native multilingual support - Strings are represented by multibyte string internally. You can use UTF-8, EUC-JP, Shift-JIS or no multibyte encoding.  Conversion between native coding system and external coding system is supported by port objects.
*Multibyte regexp - Regular expression matcher is aware of multibyte string; you can use multibyte characters both in patterns and matched strings.
*Built-in system interface - Gauche has built-in support for most POSIX.1 system calls.
*Network interface - Has API for socket-based network interface, including IPv6 if the OS supports it.
*Multithreading - Multithreading is supported on top of pthreads. Scheme-level API conforms to SRFI-18.
*DBM interface - Interfaces to dbm, ndbm and/or gdbm.
*XML parsing - Oleg Kiselyov's SXML tools are included.

==References==
*R. Kelsey, W. Clinger, J. Rees (eds.), Revised^5 Report on the Algorithmic Language Scheme, Higher-Order and Symbolic Computation, 11(1), September, 1998 and ACM SIGPLAN Notices, 33(9), October, 1998. 
*Carl Bruggeman, Oscar Waddell and R. Kent Dybvig, Representing control in the presence of one-shot continuations, in Proceedings of SIGPLAN '96, pp. 99-107, 1996.
*Eugene Myers, An O(ND) Difference Algorithm and Its Variations, Algorithmica Vol. 1 No. 2, pp. 251-266, 1986.
*Gregor Kiczales, Jim Des Rivieres, Daniel Bobrow, The Art of Metaobject Protocol, The MIT Press. 
*Kim Barrett, Bob Cassels, Paul Haahr, David A. Moon, Keith Playford, P. Tucker Withington, A Monotonic Superclass Linearization for Dylan, in Proceedings of OOPSLA 96, October 1996.
==External links==
*[http://practical-scheme.net/gauche/ Gauche home page]
*[http://practical-scheme.net/gauche/man/gauche-refe.html Gauche reference manual]
*[http://practical-scheme.net/gauche/devinfo.html Gauche development progress &amp; plan]
*[http://practical-scheme.net/gauche/features.html Standards conformance and platform list]
*[http://practical-scheme.net/docs/jlugm2000.html Shooting A Moving Target - An Experience in Developing a Production Tracking Database]
*[http://users.lava.net/~shiro/Private/essay/gdc2002.html Tracking Assets in the Production of 'Final Fantasy: The Spirits Within']
*[http://practical-scheme.net/docs/ILC2002.html Gluing Things Together - Scheme in a Real-time CG Content Production]

[[Category:Scheme interpreters]]
[[Category:Scheme implementations]]
[[Category:Free compilers and interpreters]]
[[Category:Cross-platform software]]

{{free-software-stub}}
{{compu-prog-stub}}</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
