<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="16982989" ns="0" title="Business models for open source software"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">There are several different types of [[business model]]s for making profit using [[open source software]] (OSS).

== Introduction ==
[[Open source software]] can be sold and used commercially.  It is a part of the [[software industry]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book
  | authors = Karl M. Popp and Ralf Meyer
  | title = Profit from Software Ecosystems: Business Models, Ecosystems and Partnerships in the Software Industry
  | year = 2010
  | publisher = BOD
  | location = Norderstedt, Germany
  | isbn = 3839169836}}&lt;/ref&gt;  The financial return on open source software can also come from selling services, such as training and support, rather than the software itself.  The use of [[dual-licensing]] provides an offer of the software under an [[open source license]] but also under separate proprietary license terms.  Customers can be attracted to a no-cost and open source edition, then be part of an [[up-selling|up-sell]] to a commercial enterprise edition.

Further, customers will learn of open source software in a company's portfolio and offerings but generate business in other proprietary products and solutions, including commercial [[technical support]] contracts and services.  Another possibility is offering open source software in [[source code]] form only, while providing [[executable]] binaries to paying customers only.  With permissive software, any company can distribute the package without the source or [[Free software definition|software freedoms]].

Some companies provide the latest version available only to paying customers.  Companies provide proprietary extensions, modules, plugins or add-ons to an open source package.  Independent developers often accept donations.  [[SourceForge]], for example, lets users donate money to hosted projects which have chosen to accept donations.  Users of a software may come together and pool money into a bounty for the implementation of a desired feature or functionality.

Other financial situations include partnerships with other companies.  Sometimes a commercial version may be sold to finance the continued development of the free version.

Sell [[subscription business model|subscriptions]] for online accounts and server access.  Combine desktop software with a service, [[software plus services]].

Governments, companies or other non-governmental organizations may develop internally or hire a contractor for custom in-house modifications to software, then release that code under an open source license.

== Hybrid ==
A vendor forks a non-copyleft software project then adds closed-source additions to it and sells the resulting software. After a fixed time period the patches are released back upstream under the same license as the rest of the codebase.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.phoronix.com/scan.php?page=article&amp;item=sprewell_licensing Phoronix - Towards A Real Business Model For Open-Source Software]&lt;/ref&gt;

== Examples ==

Much of the Internet runs on open source software tools and utilities such as [[Linux]], [[Apache HTTP Server|Apache]], [[MySQL]], and [[PHP]], known as the [[LAMP (software bundle)|LAMP stack]] for web servers. Using open source appeals to software developers for three main reasons: low or no cost, access to [[source code]] they can tailor themselves, and a shared community that ensures a generally robust code base, with quick fixes for any new issues that surface. 

Despite doing much business in proprietary software, some companies like [[Oracle Corporation]] and [[IBM]] participated in developing free and open source software to deter from [[monopoly|monopolies]] and take a portion of [[market share]] for themselves.  See [[Commercial open source applications]] for the list of current commercial open source offerings.  [[Netscape]]'s actions were an example of this, and thus [[Mozilla Firefox]] has become more popular, stealing market share from Internet Explorer.&lt;ref&gt;[[Netscape Navigator#The fall of Netscape]]&lt;/ref&gt;

* [[Active Agenda]] is offered for free, but requires all extensions to be shared back with the world community. The project sells a &quot;Non-Reciprocal Private License&quot; to anyone interested in keeping module extensions private.
* [[Adobe Systems]] offers [[Adobe Flex|Flex]] for free, while selling the [[Adobe Flash Builder|Flash Builder]] [[Integrated development environment|IDE]].
* [[Apple Inc.]] offers [[Darwin (operating system)|Darwin]] for free, while selling [[Mac OS X]].
* [[Canonical Ltd.]] offers [[Ubuntu (operating system)|Ubuntu]] for free, while they sell commercial technical support contracts.
*Francisco Burzi offers [[PHP-Nuke]] for free, but the latest version is offered commercially.
* [[Ingres (database)|Ingres]] is offered for free, but services &amp; support are offered as part of a subscription.  The Ingres Icebreaker Appliance is also offered as a commercial database appliance.
* Linspire, Inc. offers [[Freespire]] for free, while selling [[Linspire]].
* [[Mandriva]] offers [[Mandriva Linux]] Free and Mandriva Linux One for free, while selling Mandriva Linux 2008.
* [[Mozilla Foundation]] have a partnership with [[Google]] and other companies which provides revenue for inclusion of search engines in [[Mozilla Firefox]].
* [[MySQL]] is offered for free, but with the enterprise version includes support and additional features.
* [[Novell]] offers [[openSUSE]] for free through the [[openSUSE Project]], while selling [[SUSE Linux Enterprise]] (SLE).
* [[OpenSearchServer]] offers its community Edition on Sourceforge and a Enterprise Edition with Professional services to Enterprises with a paid license
* [[Oracle Corporation|Oracle]] - [[VirtualBox]] is free and open-source to anyone, but the [[Virtualbox#Features_only_available_with_the_extension_pack|VirtualBox extension pack]] can only be used for free at home, therefore requiring payment for business
* [[Red Hat]] offers the [[Fedora (Linux distribution)|Fedora]] for free through the [[Fedora Project]], while selling [[Red Hat Enterprise Linux]] (RHEL).
* [[Sun Microsystems]] offer [[OpenOffice.org]] for free, while selling [[StarOffice]].
* [[Untangle]] provides its Lite Package for free, whilst selling its Standard and Premium Packages by subscription.
* [[Zend Technologies]] offers [[Zend Server CE]] and [[Zend Framework]] for free, but sells [[Zend Server]] with support and additional features.

== See also ==
{{Portal box|Business and Economics|Software}}
* [[Commercial open source applications]]
* [[François Letellier]] - expert on open source and innovation, with extensive work on business models
* [[Open business]]
* [[Open source bounty]]
* [[Professional open-source]]

== References ==
{{reflist}}

== External links ==
* [http://www.gnu.org/philosophy/selling.html Selling Free Software], Free Software Foundation
* [http://firstmonday.org/htbin/cgiwrap/bin/ojs/index.php/fm/article/viewArticle/1470/1385 The Emerging Economic Paradigm of Open Source] - Bruce Perens
* [http://ftacademy.org/materials/fsm/5 Economic aspects and business models of Free Software] - Free Technology Academy (2010)
* &quot;[http://www.it-inwent.org/e2484/e3407/index_eng.html FOSS Business Models in Developing countries]&quot; - compilation of material and sources

[[Category:Business models]]
[[Category:Free software culture and documents]]
[[Category:Software industry]]

[[pl:Otwarte oprogramowanie#Modele biznesowe dla otwartego oprogramowania]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
