<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="16986" ns="0" title="Kent State University"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{about|the university in Ohio|the 1970 shootings of anti-war protesters|Kent State shootings}}
{{Infobox university
| name = Kent State University
| image = [[File:KSU seal.png|180px]]
| motto = Excellence In Action
| established = 1910
| alumni = 196,000
| type = [[Public university|Public]]
| endowment = $109.1 Million&lt;ref name=endowment&gt;{{cite news |url=http://kentwired.com/ksu-endowment-rebounds-from-economy/ |title=KSU endowment rebounds from economy |accessdate=February 14, 2011 |date=February 8, 2011 |work=Kentwired.com}}&lt;/ref&gt;
| president = [[Lester Lefton]]&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url= http://www.kent.edu/Administration/President/|title= Welcome to the Office of the President|accessdate=February 29, 2008 |author= Lefton, Lester |year=2008 |work=Kent.edu |publisher=Kent State University}}&lt;/ref&gt;
| city = [[Kent, Ohio|Kent]]
| state = [[Ohio]]
| country = [[USA]] |
|coor = {{coord|41|8|47.08|N|81|20|30.28|W|region:US-OH_type:edu|display=inline,title}}|
campus = [[Suburban]] [[college town]]&lt;br/&gt;{{convert|1347|acre|ha|0}} (Main campus)&lt;ref name=&quot;petersons&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url= http://www.petersons.com/collegeprofiles/Profile.aspx?inunid=7021&amp;reprjid=12&amp;sponsor=1&amp;orderLineNum=1148841-3&amp;tabid=10001|title= Kent State University At a Glance |accessdate=September 18, 2009 |date=December 15, 2007 |work=Petersons.com |publisher=Petersons}}&lt;/ref&gt; |
|affiliations = [[University System of Ohio]], [[North Central Association of Colleges and Schools|NCACS]],  [[Association of Public and Land-Grant Universities|APLU]]
| students = 27,855 (Kent Campus)&lt;br&gt; 42,185 (all campuses)
| undergrad = 22,260 (Kent Campus)&lt;br&gt; 36,521 (all campuses)
| postgrad = 5,595 (Kent Campus)&lt;br&gt; 5,664 (all campuses)
| faculty = 2,458&lt;ref name=staff&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.kent.edu/rpie/data/index.cfm |title= Research, Planning and Institutional Effectiveness |work=Kent.edu/RPIE |publisher=Kent State University |year=2010 |accessdate=September 13, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; (September 2010, all campuses)
| staff = 2,799&lt;ref name=staff/&gt; (September 2010, all campuses)
| mascot = Flash the Golden Eagle|
|colors= [[Navy Blue]] and [[Gold (color)|Gold]]&lt;br/&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;background-color:#0A0D6F;width:50px;border:1px solid #000000&quot;&gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/span&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;span style=&quot;background-color:#FFAB1B;width:50px;border:1px solid #000000&quot;&gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/span&gt;
|nickname              = [[Kent State Golden Flashes|Golden Flashes]]
|athletics             = [[National Collegiate Athletic Association|NCAA]] [[Division I (NCAA)|Division I]] [[Division I (NCAA)#Football Bowl Subdivision|FBS]]&lt;br/&gt;[[Mid-American Conference]]&lt;br/&gt;16 varsity teams
|website = http://www.kent.edu
|logo = [[File:KSU logo.png|220px]]
}}

'''Kent State University''' (also known as '''Kent''', '''Kent State''', and '''KSU''') is a [[Public university|public]] research [[university]] located in [[Kent, Ohio]], [[United States]].  The university has eight campuses around the [[Greater Cleveland|northeast Ohio]] region with the main campus in Kent being the largest.  Other campuses are located in [[Ashtabula, Ohio|Ashtabula]], [[Burton, Ohio|Burton]], [[East Liverpool, Ohio|East Liverpool]], [[Jackson Township, Stark County, Ohio|Jackson Township]], [[New Philadelphia, Ohio|New Philadelphia]], [[Salem, Ohio|Salem]], and [[Warren, Ohio]].

As of September 2011, Kent State is one of the largest universities in Ohio with an enrollment of 42,185 students in the eight-campus system and 27,855 students at the main campus in Kent.&lt;ref name=fall10&gt;{{cite web |title= Fifteenth Day Enrollment Statistics|url= http://www.kent.edu/rpie/enrollment/index.cfm |date= September 2011|work= Kent.edu/RPIE |publisher= Kent State University |accessdate=13 September 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;  It is ranked by the Carnegie Foundation as one of the top 77 public research universities in the US and one of the top 76 in community engagement.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |title= Academics|url= http://www.kent.edu/academics/index.cfm|date= 19 August 2009|work= Kent.edu|publisher= Kent State University|accessdate=22 September 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt; In 2010, Kent State was ranked as one of the top 200 universities in the world by ''[[Times Higher Education]]''.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |url=http://www.timeshighereducation.co.uk/world-university-rankings/2010-2011/top-200.html |title=World University Rankings 2010 |year=2010 |accessdate=February 14, 2011 |magazine=[[Times Higher Education]]}}&lt;/ref&gt; Kent State offers over 300 degree programs, among them 250 [[Bachelor's degree|baccalaureate]], 40 [[Associate's degree|associate's]], 50 [[Master's degree|master's]], and 23 [[Doctoral degree|doctoral]] programs of study,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |title= Graduation Planning System|url= http://www.kent.edu/gps/|date= 22 September 2009|work= Kent.edu|publisher= Kent State University|accessdate=22 September 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt; which include such notable programs as nursing, [[liquid crystal]]s, business, history, [[library science]], aeronautics, journalism and fashion design.

The university was established in 1910 as the Kent Normal School as a teacher-training school.  The first classes were held in 1912 at various locations and in temporary buildings in Kent.  Since then, the university has grown to include several additional baccalaureate and graduate programs of study in the arts and sciences, research opportunities, as well as over {{convert|1000|acres|0|abbr=on}} and 119 buildings on the Kent campus.  During the late 1960s and early 1970s, the university was known internationally for its student activism in opposition to US involvement in the Vietnam war, due mainly to the [[Kent State shootings|massacre of May 4, 1970]].

==History==
===Early history===
[[File:Kenthallbw.jpg|thumb|right|300px|Front of Kent Hall, built in 1915, one of the oldest buildings on campus.]]
What would become Kent State University was established in 1910 as an institution for training public school teachers.  It was part of the [[Lowry bill|Lowry Bill]] which also created a sister school in [[Bowling Green, Ohio]] – now known as [[Bowling Green State University]]. It was initially known under the working name of the '''[[Ohio State Normal College At Kent]]''',&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book |editor-last=Johannesen |editor-first=Eric |title=National Register of Historic Places Inventory - Nomination Form: Ohio State Normal College At Kent| publisher=United States Department of the Interior|date=30 May 1975 |postscript=&lt;!--None--&gt;}}
&lt;/ref&gt; but was named '''Kent State Normal School''' in 1911 in honor of William S. Kent (son of [[Kent, Ohio]], namesake [[Marvin Kent]]), who donated the {{convert|53|acre|ha|0}} used for the original campus.  As such, it is the only public university in Ohio named for an individual.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |first= F. Robert|last= Treichler|title= A History of Kent Hall|url= http://dept.kent.edu/psychology/documents/KentHallHistory.pdf|date= |work= Kent State Psychology Department website |publisher= Kent State University|accessdate=23 September 2009|page= 6|format= PDF|quote= Kent State is unique among Ohio's state-supported schools in being named for an individual.}}&lt;/ref&gt;{{Dubious|Only Ohio public university named for an individual?|date=June 2011}}  The first president was [[John Edward McGilvrey]], who served from 1912 to 1926.&lt;ref name=mcgilvrey&gt;{{cite web |title= John Edward McGilvrey, Papers, 1890-1945|url= http://speccoll.library.kent.edu/faculty/mcgilvrey.html|date= 14 December 2005|work= Kent State University Special Collections and Archives|publisher= Kent State University}}&lt;/ref&gt; McGilvrey had an ambitious vision for the school as a large university, instructing architect [[George F. Hammond]], who designed the original campus buildings, to produce a master plan.&lt;ref&gt;Treichler, p. 1; ''&quot;President McGilvery, always a visionary, harbored the prospect that Kent would one day become a great university, and he instructed [[George F. Hammond|George Hammond]] to generate an architectural master plan to reflect that goal.&quot;''&lt;/ref&gt;  Classes began in 1912 before any buildings had been completed at the campus in Kent.  These classes were held at extension centers in 25 cities around the region.  By May 1913, classes were being held on the campus in Kent with the opening of Merrill Hall.&lt;ref name=memories1&gt;{{cite book |title=A Book of Memories |last=Hildebrand |first=William H. |coauthors=Dean H. Keller, Anita Dixon Herington |year=1993 |publisher=Kent State University Press |location= |isbn=0873384881 |pages= 18–20}}&lt;/ref&gt;  The school graduated 34 students in its first commencement on July 29, 1914.  In 1915, the school was renamed '''Kent State Normal College'''&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |title= Special Collections FAQ |url= http://speccoll.library.kent.edu/scfaq.html#ksu |date= |work= Kent State University Special Collections and Archives FAQ |publisher= Kent State University|accessdate=22 September 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt; due to the addition of four-year degrees.  By then additional buildings had been added or were under construction.  Kent State's enrollment growth was particularly notable during its summer terms.  In 1924, the school's registration for summer classes was the largest of any teacher-training school in the United States.&lt;ref name=memories1/&gt;  In 1929, the state of Ohio changed the name to '''Kent State College''' as it allowed the school to establish a college of arts and sciences.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |title= The History of Kent|last= Grismer|first= Karl |year= 1932|publisher= Record Publishing (1932); Kent Historical Society (2001)|location= [[Kent, Ohio]]|page= 187|accessdate= 22 September 2009 |edition= 2001 Revision |unused_data= edition 2001 Revision}}&lt;/ref&gt;

McGilvrey's vision for Kent was not shared by many others outside the school, particularly at the state level and at other state schools.  His efforts to have the state funding formula changed created opposition, particularly from [[Ohio State University]] and its president [[William Oxley Thompson]].  This resulted in a 1923 &quot;credit war&quot; where Ohio State refused Kent transfer credits and spread to several other schools taking similar action. It was this development – along with several other factors – which led to the firing of McGilvrey in January 1926.&lt;ref name=memories1/&gt;  McGilvrey was succeeded first by David Allen Anderson (1926–1928) and James Ozro Engleman from 1928–1938, though he continued to be involved with the school for several years as president emeritus and as head of alumni relations from 1934-1945.&lt;ref name=mcgilvrey/&gt;  He was present in [[Columbus, Ohio|Columbus]] on May 17, 1935, when [[Kent, Ohio|Kent]] native Governor [[Martin L. Davey]] signed a bill that allowed Kent State and [[Bowling Green State University|Bowling Green]] to add schools of business administration and graduate programs, giving them each university status.&lt;ref name=memories1/&gt;

===1940s-1960s===
Beginning in 1944, the University was led by President George Bowman, who led until 1963.  During his tenure, the student senate, faculty senate and graduate council were organized.  Although it had served Stark County from the 1920s, in 1946, the University's first regional campus, the [[Kent State University Stark Campus|Stark Campus]], was established in [[Canton, Ohio]].  In the fall of 1947, Bowman appointed [[Oscar W. Ritchie]] as a full-time faculty member. Ritchie's appointment to the faculty made him the first [[African American]] to serve on the faculty at Kent State and also made him the first African American professor to serve on the faculty of any state university in Ohio. In 1977, the former Student Union, which had been built in 1949, was rededicated as Oscar Ritchie Hall in his honor.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |first= Curtis T.|last= Clingman|title= Dr. Oscar W. Ritchie|url= http://hierographics.org/owritchiebio.htm|newspaper= Spectrum|publisher= HieroGraphics Online |date= 17 September 1979|edition= 1998 Revision|accessdate=23 September 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt; Recently renovated, Oscar Ritchie Hall currently houses the department of [[Pan-African Studies]] and the Pan-African Cultural Center.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |first= Melissa|last= Elder |title= Renovations for Oscar Ritchie on Track|url= http://einside.kent.edu/?type=art&amp;id=86728|newspaper= eInside|publisher= Kent State University|date= 11 February 2008|accessdate=23 September 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The 1950s and 1960s saw continued growth in both enrollment and in the physical size of the campus.  Several new dorms and academic buildings were built during this time, including the establishment of additional regional campuses in [[Warren, Ohio|Warren]] (1954), [[Kent State University Ashtabula Campus|Ashtabula]] (1957), [[New Philadelphia, Ohio|New Philadelphia]] (1962), [[Salem, Ohio|Salem]] (1962), [[Burton, Ohio|Burton]] (1964), and [[Kent State University East Liverpool Campus|East Liverpool]], [[Ohio]] (1965).&lt;ref&gt;Hildebrand, Herrington, &amp; Keller; pp. 267-270&lt;/ref&gt; In 1961, grounds superintendent Larry Wooddell and Biff Staples of the [[Davey Tree Expert Company]] released ten cages of [[black squirrel]]s obtained from [[Victoria Park, London (Ontario)|Victoria Park]] in [[London, Ontario]], [[Canada]], onto the Kent State campus.  By 1964 their estimated population was around 150 and today they have spread in and around Kent and have become unofficial mascots of both the city and university.  Since 1981, the annual Black Squirrel Festival is held every fall on campus.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web |url= http://www.victoria-park.com/ksu.htm|title= London Black Squirrels Take Over Kent State University|accessdate=23 September 2009 |work= Victoria-Park.com|publisher= Victoria-Park.com|year= 2002}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Hildebrand, Herrington, &amp; Keller; p. 258&lt;/ref&gt;

In 1965, chemistry professor Glenn H. Brown established the [[Liquid Crystal Institute]],&lt;ref name=KHS&gt;{{cite book|title=Kent Ohio: The Dynamic Decades|coauthors=Kent Historical Society Book Committee|editor= Darrow, Ralph |year=1999|publisher=Kent Historical Society|location=[[Kent, Ohio]]|page=123}}&lt;/ref&gt; a world leader in the research and development the multibillion-dollar [[liquid crystal]] industry.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |last= Johnson|first= Christopher |date= 1 August 2005|title= Liquid Crystal Institute blazes new trails at Kent State|journal= Inside Business|publisher=Great Lakes Publishing |url= http://www.highbeam.com/doc/1G1-160029070.html|accessdate=2009-09-23 |quote= ...the world's No. 1 liquid crystal research center is at Kent State University: the Liquid Crystal Institute (LCI).}}&lt;/ref&gt; James Fergasen invented and patented the basic liquid crystal in the 1970s&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |last= Johnson|first= Christopher |date= 10 May 1999|title= Liquid Lessons: The Missed Opportunity of Liquid Crystal Technology isn't Lost on Researchers Striving to Establish a MEMS Industry Here|journal= Crain's Cleveland Business |publisher=Crain Communications|url= http://www.highbeam.com/doc/1G1-54607677.html|accessdate=2009-09-23 |quote= in the 1970s, soon after Kent State University researcher James Fergason first invented the basic liquid crystal.}}&lt;/ref&gt; and ten liquid crystal companies have been spun off from the Institute.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |last= Pettypiece|first= Shannon |date= 29 August 2005|title= Crystal clear; Kent State playing lead role in exploring medical, anti-bioterror uses for liquid crystal technology.|journal= Crain's Cleveland Business| publisher=Crain Communications|url= http://www.highbeam.com/doc/1G1-135711290.html|accessdate=2009-09-23 |quote= Since that time, the university has spun off 10 companies developing liquid crystal technology.}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In 1967, Kent State became the first university to run an independent, student-operated Campus Bus Service. It was unique in that it provided jobs for students, receiving funding from student fees rather than bus fares.  Campus Bus Service was the largest such operation in the country until it merged with the [[Portage Area Regional Transportation Authority]] in 2004.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |title= Kent State University Campus Bus Service: History 1965-2004|url= http://www.partaonline.org/pdfs/CBShistory.pdf|year= 2004|work= PARTAonline.org|publisher= [[Portage Area Regional Transportation Authority|PARTA]]|accessdate=23 September 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt;  1969 saw the opening of a [[Dix Stadium|new Memorial Stadium]] on the far eastern edge of campus and the closure and dismantling of the [[Memorial Stadium (Kent)|old Memorial Stadium]].
[[File:May4thMemorial.JPG|thumb|left|300px|Main May 4th Memorial]]

===Kent State shootings===
{{main|Kent State shootings}}
Kent State gained international attention on May 4, 1970, when an [[Ohio Army National Guard]] unit fired at students during an anti-war protest on campus, killing four and wounding nine. The Guard had been called into Kent after several protests in and around campus had become violent, including a riot in downtown Kent and the burning of the [[Reserve Officers' Training Corps|ROTC]] building. The main cause of the protests was the United States' [[Cambodian Campaign|invasion of Cambodia]] during the [[Vietnam War]].&lt;ref&gt;Hildebrand, Herrington, &amp; Keller; pp. 165-166&lt;/ref&gt;  The shootings caused an immediate closure of the campus with students and faculty given just 60&amp;nbsp;minutes to pack belongings.  Around the country, many college campuses canceled classes or closed for fear of similar violent protests.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |title= Kent State Shootings|url= http://www.ohiohistorycentral.org/entry.php?rec=1595&amp;nm=Kent-State-Shootings|date= 1 July 2005|work= Ohio History Central|publisher= Ohio Historical Society|accessdate=23 September 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt;  In Kent, schools were closed and the National Guard restricted entry into the city limits, patrolling the area until May 8.  With the campus closed, faculty members came up with a variety of solutions — including holding classes in their homes, at public buildings and places, via telephone, or through the mail — to allow their students to complete the term, which was only a few weeks away at the time.&lt;ref&gt;Hildebrand, Herrington, &amp; Keller; pp. 181-183&lt;/ref&gt;  In 1971, the University established the Center for Peaceful Change, now known as the Center for Applied Conflict Management, as a &quot;living memorial&quot; to the students who had died.  It offers degree programs in Peace and Conflict Studies&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |title= Center for Applied Conflict Management|url= http://www.kent.edu/cacm/|date= 15 May 2008|work= Kent.edu |publisher= Kent State University|accessdate=23 September 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt; and Conflict Resolution and is one of the earliest such programs in the United States.

===1970s-1980s===
Also in 1970, the university opened its 12-story library, moving from the previous home of Rockwell Hall to the tallest building in [[Portage County, Ohio|Portage County]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |first= Michelle|last= Poje |title= PERC up: research papers aren't so bad with help from library |url= http://media.www.kentnewsnet.com/media/storage/paper867/news/2005/08/24/News/Perc-Up.Research.Papers.Arent.So.Bad.With.Help.From.Library-1517541.shtml|newspaper= Daily Kent Stater|publisher= KentNewsNet.com|date= 24 August 2005 |accessdate=23 September 2009|quote= With its 12 floors of resources and well-known status as the tallest building in Portage County...}}&lt;/ref&gt;  Dedicated in 1971, the library became a member of the [[Association of Research Libraries]] in 1973.&lt;ref&gt;Hildebrand, Herrington, &amp; Keller; p. 187&lt;/ref&gt;  Kent State joined with the [[University of Akron]] and [[Youngstown State University]] in establishing the [[Northeastern Ohio Universities Colleges of Medicine and Pharmacy|Northeastern Ohio Universities College of Medicine]] in 1973.  It was the world's first medical consortium.&lt;ref&gt;Darrow, p. 17&lt;/ref&gt;  Today it includes a college of [[pharmacy]] and [[Cleveland State University]] as an additional consortium member.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |title= About NEOUCOM: Universities|url= http://www.neoucom.edu/audience/about/consortium/Universities|date= |work= NEOUCOM.edu |publisher= [[Northeastern Ohio Universities Colleges of Medicine and Pharmacy]]|accessdate=23 September 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Kent State was again in the national spotlight in 1977 when construction was set to begin on the Memorial Gym Annex, adjacent to the area where the [[Kent State shootings]] had occurred in 1970. Protesters organized a [[Tent city#Kent State University|tent city]] in May, which lasted into July. Several attempts were made to block construction even after the end of the tent city, including an appeal to the [[United States Congress]] and the [[United States Department of the Interior|Department of the Interior]] to have the area declared a [[National Historic Landmark]], which ended up being unsuccessful. Additional rallies were held that year, including one attended by [[Joan Baez]] on August 20.  After several additional unsuccessful legal challenges, construction finally began on September 19 and was finished in 1979.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |title= Tent City Chronology (Gym Annex Controversy) |author= Slobodinski, Mikhail &amp; Schrager, Jennifer |url= http://speccoll.library.kent.edu/4May70/citychron.html|date= |work= Kent State University Special Collections and Archives |publisher= Kent State University|accessdate=23 September 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===1990s-Present===
In March 1991, Kent State once again made history by appointing [[Carol Cartwright]] as president of the University, the first female to hold such a position at any state university in Ohio.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |title= Carol A. Cartwright|url= http://www.npr.org/templates/story/story.php?storyId=2101541|year= 2009|work= NPR.org|publisher= National Public Radio|accessdate=23 September 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt;  In 1994, Kent State was named a &quot;Research University II&quot; by the Carnegie Foundation.  Today it is classified as a [[Research I university|Doctoral/Research University-Extensive]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |title= Carnegie Doctoral/Research Universities-Extensive|url= http://www.washington.edu/tools/universities.html#O|date= 3 October 2007|work= University of Washington Reference Tools |publisher= [[University of Washington]]|accessdate=23 September 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |title= Kent State University|url= http://www.ohiohistorycentral.org/entry.php?rec=737|date= 1 July 2005|work= Ohio History Central|publisher= Ohio Historical Society|accessdate=23 September 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt;  Beginning in the late 1990s, the University began a series of building renovations and construction, which included the complete renovation of the historic original campus,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |title= Franklin Hall|url= http://kentstate.kent.edu/directions/kent/building.asp?Building=9|date= 26 October 2007|work= Directions &amp; Maps|publisher= Kent State University|accessdate=23 September 2009|quote= Franklin Hall rehabilitation marks the last phase of major projects to restore the historic front campus to its former splendor...}}&lt;/ref&gt; the construction of several new dormitories, a student recreation center, and additional academic buildings on the Kent Campus and at the regional campuses.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |title= News Briefs|url= http://einside.kent.edu/?type=art&amp;id=91617#construction|newspaper= eInside|publisher= Kent State University|date= 2 March 2009|accessdate=23 September 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt;  In September 2010, the university announced its largest student body ever, with a total enrollment of 41,365.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |first=Matt |last=Fredmonsky |title=KSU enrollment breaks record |url=http://www.recordpub.com/news/article/4894856 |newspaper= Record-Courier |date=15 September 2010 |accessdate=15 September 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Campuses==
[[File:KSUGatewayArchNew.JPG|thumb|left|200px|Kent State Gateway Arch on Kent Campus]]
Kent State University is an eight-campus system in northeastern Ohio, with the main administrative center in [[Kent, Ohio|Kent]].  Within the Kent State University system, the main campus is officially referred to as the &quot;Kent Campus&quot;.&lt;ref name=regional&gt;{{cite web |url= http://www.kent.edu/Campuses/|title= Welcome to Kent State's Eight-Campus System |accessdate=2008-06-27 |work= Kent State University website|publisher= Kent State University|date= 2008-06-11}}&lt;/ref&gt;  The Kent Campus is a landscaped [[suburban]] environment, covering approximately {{convert|866|acre|km2|1}} which house over 100 buildings, gardens, bike trails, and open greenery. There are also thousands of additional acres of bogs, marshes, and wildlife refuges adjacent to or near the campus.&lt;ref name=regional/&gt;  While the university's official mascot is Flash the [[Golden Eagle]], the campus also has an unofficial mascot in the [[Black Squirrel]], which were brought to Kent in 1961 and can be found on and around the campus. The campus is divided into North, South, and East sections but many areas have come to be referred to as Front Campus, Residential Campus, and Science Row. The main hub of activity and central point is the Student Center and Risman Plaza, which is adjacent to the twelve-story main library. The university also operates the 18-hole Kent State Golf Course and Centennial Research Park just east of campus in [[Franklin Township, Portage County, Ohio|Franklin Township]] and the {{convert|219|acre|km2|1|sing=on}} [[Kent State University Airport]] in [[Stow, Ohio|Stow]].

===Regional campuses===
[[File:Regionalksu.png|thumb|left|450px|Map of KSU campuses.]]
In addition to the Kent Campus, there are seven regional campuses. The system is one of the largest and oldest regional campus systems in the United States. The regional campuses provide a small, liberal-arts college feel as opposed to the large university feel of the Kent Campus.  Students at the regional campuses can begin any of Kent State's majors at their respective campus and each campus offers its own unique programs and opportunities that may or may not be available in Kent.  Regional campuses include:

====Ashtabula====
{{Main|Kent State University Ashtabula Campus}}
The Ashtabula Campus is made up of three buildings: Main Hall, a library, and a technology and art building. It is on a {{convert|125|acre|km2|adj=on}} site along the shores of [[Lake Erie]] in [[Ashtabula, Ohio]]. Kent State-Ashtabula is noted locally for its nursing program.  Seventy-five percent (75%) of [[registered nurse]]s working in [[Ashtabula County, Ohio|Ashtabula County]] graduated with an [[Associate's degree]] in nursing from Kent State-Ashtabula.  On July 17, 2007, ground was broken for a new Health and Science building, which is being constructed for use mainly by the growing nursing and allied health programs.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |first= |last= |title= Ashtabula Campus Breaks Ground for a Healthier Northeast Ohio on July 17
|url=http://einside.kent.edu/?type=art&amp;id=83469&amp;|work= eInside|publisher= Kent State University|date= 2007-07-16|accessdate=2008-06-21 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

====East Liverpool====
{{Main|Kent State University at East Liverpool}}

The [[East Liverpool, Ohio|East Liverpool]] Campus occupies a downtown site overlooking the [[Ohio River]]. It is composed of the Main Building, Memorial Auditorium, Mary Patterson Building, and a Commons area.

====Geauga====
Located in [[Burton, Ohio]], Kent State's Geauga Campus is at the heart of Ohio's maple syrup country in [[Geauga County, Ohio|Geauga County]]. The campus provides easy access to urban, suburban and rural areas. The Geauga Campus also includes the Twinsburg Center, a small extension located in [[Twinsburg, Ohio]].

====Salem====
Kent State's [[Salem, Ohio|Salem]] Campus is located just south of the city. It features a lake, an {{convert|25|acre|m2|adj=on}} outdoor classroom, and nature walk. In addition to the Salem Campus, Kent State University Salem owns and operates the old Salem Middle School called the &quot;City Center&quot; in which administrative offices, classes, and student services are located.

====Stark====
{{Main|Kent State University at Stark}}
The Stark Campus is the largest regional campus of Kent State University, serving around 10,300 students each year (5,300 in academic programs, 5,000 in executive and graduate education). It is located on {{convert|200|acre|km2|1}} in [[Jackson Township, Stark County, Ohio|Jackson Township]] just five minutes from the [[Akron-Canton Regional Airport]]. It is composed of seven major buildings and a natural pond and offers three masters and 12 complete bachelor degree programs. Baccalaureate programs include: applied communication, business management, English, general studies, history, justice studies, mathematics, middle childhood education, and nursing, as well as pre-law, technology and psychology degrees.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url= http://www.stark.kent.edu/Academics/AcademicPrograms.cfm|title= Majors &amp; Degree Programs|accessdate=2008-06-20 |work= Kent State University Stark Campus website|date= |publisher= Kent State University}}&lt;/ref&gt; Additionally, there are three associate degrees offered: arts, justice studies, and science. The campus also offers three masters level programs: a professional M.B.A degree and a M.A. or M.Ed. in Curriculum and Teaching Studies. Ninety percent of Kent State Stark's full-time faculty hold the highest academic credentials in their field. The Stark campus includes the Professional Education and Conference Center; an advanced meeting, training, and events facility that is one of only ten such centers in the state of Ohio affiliated with the International Association of Conference Centers.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url= http://www.stark.kent.edu/conferencecenter/|title= Welcome to the Professional Education and Conference Center
|accessdate=2008-06-20 |work= Kent State University Stark Campus website|date= |publisher= Kent State University}}&lt;/ref&gt;  The Center also serves as a home to the Office of Corporate and Community Services, which provides intense training and learning exercises for area businesses and organizations.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url= http://www.stark.kent.edu/campusinfo/|title= About Kent State University Stark|accessdate=2008-06-20 |work= Kent State University Stark Campus website|date= |publisher= Kent State University}}&lt;/ref&gt;

====Trumbull====
Kent State's Trumbull Campus is located in [[Warren, Ohio]] just north of the [[Ohio State Route 5|SR 5]] bypass on [[Ohio State Route 45|SR 45]]. It offers programs in 170 majors at the freshman and sophomore level, as well as 18 certificates and 15 associate degree programs. In addition, there is upper division coursework for baccalaureate degree completion in nursing, justice studies, technology, business management, and English, as well as general studies and psychology degrees. In 2004 the campus opened a {{convert|68000|sqft|m2|-2|sing=on}} Technology Building that includes the Workforce Development and Continuing Studies Center and an Adaptive Technology Lab for individuals with special needs.

====Tuscarawas====
The Tuscarawas Campus in [[New Philadelphia, Ohio]] offers 19 associate degrees, six bachelor's degrees, and the Master of Technology Degree. Bachelor's degrees are offered in business management, general studies, justice studies, industrial technology, nursing and technology 2+2. The Science and Advanced Technology Center provides {{convert|50000|sqft|m2|-3}} of laboratory and classroom space for science, nursing and workforce development. The Tuscarawas Campus has constructed a {{convert|55000|sqft|m2|-2|sing=on}}, $13.5 million Fine and Performing Arts center that will enable the campus to expand academic and cultural programming.

===Additional facilities===
In addition to the eight campuses in northeast Ohio, Kent State operates facilities for study-abroad programs in [[Florence]], Italy; New York City; Cleveland, Ohio; and Shanghai, China.

====Florence Center====
[[File:KSUFlorence.JPG|thumb|right|150px|Inside main foyer of KSU Florence facility]]
[[File:KSUFlorence2.JPG|thumb|right|150px|Ceiling of Main Lecture Room at KSU Florence Facility]]
KSU-Florence opened its doors to International Studies Abroad in a collaboration that grants students the opportunity to study in historic Florence at its newly renovated Palazzo dei Cerchi. [[Palazzo dei Cerchi]] is a prestigious and ancient building located in the heart of Florence, at the corner of Via della Condotta and Vicolo dei Cerchi, next to the famous [[Piazza della Signoria]] and the birthplace of literary genius [[Dante Alighieri]]. Kent State acquired this facility in 2003 and undertook its complete renovation. The original exterior was maintained and reflects [[Florence]] as it was in the 13th century. The restoration carefully preserved the original structure while creating an efficient space for academic purposes, with an interior that houses state-of-the-art classrooms.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |first= |last= |title= Kent State University in Florence
|url=http://www.studiesabroad.com/programs/country/italy/city/florence/viewUniversity|work= studiesabroad.com|publisher= International Studies Abroad Inc.|date= |accessdate=2008-07-12 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

====New York City Studio====
The New York City Studio is located in the heart of New York City's Garment District. Surrounded by fabric and accessory shops, fashion showrooms, and designer studios; one-third of all clothing manufactured in the USA is designed and produced in this neighborhood. The District is home to America's world-renowned fashion designers, including [[Oscar de la Renta]], [[Calvin Klein]], [[Donna Karan]], [[Liz Claiborne]], and [[Nicole Miller]]. The facility is a state-of-the-art, {{convert|4500|sqft|m2|adj=on}} space and includes a 50-person lecture room, 12-station computer lab with instructor station, and a fashion design studio fully outfitted with professional equipment. The NYC studio gives Kent State students the advantage of working within the heart of the fashion, dance and theater industry.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |first= |last= |title= Kent State Meets the Big Apple: NYC Studio Announces Official Opening October 11
|url=http://einside.kent.edu/?type=art&amp;id=79099&amp;|work= einside |publisher= Kent State University |date=2006-10-09 |accessdate=2008-07-12 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

====Cleveland Urban Design Center====
Kent State's Cleveland Urban Design Center is located at 1309 Euclid Ave in downtown Cleveland's Theater District neighborhood, just off of East 14th Street. The Urban Design Center was created in 1983 under the sponsorship of the Urban University Program, which supports the outreach and community service efforts of Ohio's state universities working in urban areas. Under its founding director, Foster Armstrong, the Center expanded on the existing outreach and public service activities of Kent State's [[architecture]] school, focusing primarily on historic preservation and the problems of Northeast Ohio's smaller towns and cities. In 2003, the CUDC began a collaboration with the [[Dresden University of Technology]], Kent State's sister university in Germany, with a joint vision on the revitalization of the lower [[Cuyahoga Valley]] in [[Cleveland, Ohio|Cleveland]]. Since then, there have been a number of faculty exchanges as the two universities seek to pool their expertise both to enhance students' experiences and to better serve their respective regions.&lt;ref&gt;
{{cite web
 |first=
 |last=
 |title=Cleveland Urban Design Collaborative
 |url=http://www.cudc.kent.edu/a-WhoWeAre/whoweare2.html
 |work= CUDC
 |publisher= Kent State University
 |date=
 |accessdate=2008-07-12
}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Academic divisions==
[[File:KentStateHonorsCollege.JPG|thumb|right|300px|KSU Honors College Complex]]
Kent State has colleges of:
* [[Architecture]] and Environmental Design
* Arts (focusing on fine/performing arts and fashion-related studies)
* [[Kent State University College of Arts and Sciences|Arts and Sciences]]
* [[Business Administration]]
* Communication and Information
* Education, Health, and Human Services
* [[Nursing]]
* [[Kent State University College of Public Health|Public Health]]
* Technology
The university has an Honors College and interdisciplinary programs in Biomedical Sciences, Financial Engineering, and Information Architecture and Knowledge Management.

==Notable programs==
{{refimprove|section|date=January 2010}}
[[File:FranklinHallKSUNew.JPG|thumb|right|300px|Franklin Hall, Home of the School of Journalism and Mass Communication and Student Media]]
* The College of Technology offers four aeronautics degrees; Flight Technology, Aviation Management, Air Traffic Control and Aeronautical Engineering. In 2008, the University began offering a [[flight training]] certificate program through an affiliation with [[Premier Flight Academy]] in Akron.&lt;ref name=&quot;KSU&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url = http://einside.kent.edu/?type=art&amp;id=88835| title = Kent State and Premier Flight Academy Launch Innovative Flight Training Certificate Program|publisher = Kent State University|accessdate = 2009–10–08}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;International&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url = http://www.premierflightacademy.com/international-flight-training/default.aspx| title = International Student Program|publisher = Premier Flight Academy|accessdate = 2009–10–08}}&lt;/ref&gt;
::''See also: [[Kent State University Airport]].''
* The Shannon Rodgers and Jerry Silverman School of [[Fashion design|Fashion Design]] and Merchandising is in the top tier of fashion education in the nation by the [[Council of Fashion Designers of America]], with programs in Florence, Hong Kong, and New York City, and affiliations in Paris and London.  It was named a top-ten fashion school in the United States by ''Runway Magazine''.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |title= Top 10 Fashion Schools|author= Rogers, Emily|magazine= Runway Magazine|date= 11 October 2009|url= http://www.runwaylive.com/fashion/3012-runway-magazine-fashion-schools.html|accessdate= 14 January 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* The [[Liquid Crystal Institute]], founded 1965, is a leader in advanced research and development of liquid crystal optoelectronic materials, technology, and consumer products in connection with the [[National Science Foundation]] as part of ALCOM.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.lci.kent.edu/history.html Kent.edu]&lt;/ref&gt;
* The Hugh A Glauser School of Music offers degrees in music education, music performance, music theory and composition, ethnomusicology, chamber music, and a new minor in jazz studies. The School of Music is one of the few colleges in the US that offer a BM, a MM, and a PhD in music education.
* The Kent/Blossom Music program partners with the [[Cleveland Orchestra]] each summer for one of the nation's major classical music festivals.
* The Center for the Study of World Musics is one of the primary centers for [[ethnomusicology]] in the United States.
* The [[School Psychology]] Program (SPSY) [http://www.educ.kent.edu/EFSS/programs/SP/] is the only program in the state accredited by [[American Psychological Association|APA]] and [[National Association of School Psychologists|NASP]]. The SPSY program is a 'flagship' training program in Ohio (graduates comprise about 18% of all SPSY professionals in the state).
* The Visual Communication Design Program (VCD [http://vcd.kent.edu/]) is one of the most respected in the US. Accredited by the National Association of Schools of Art and Design (NASAD) it is home to Glyphix [http://www.kentglyphix.org/], an award-winning student-staffed design studio.
* Kent State University is one of few universities with graduate programs in Information Architecture and Knowledge Management (IAKM [http://iakm.kent.edu/]) and an online certificate program in [[Knowledge Management]].
* The only institution in Ohio to offer a degree in [[Library Science|Library and Information Science]], Kent is ranked 20th by ''[[U.S. News &amp; World Report]]''.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |title= Library and Information Studies |magazine= [[US News &amp; World Report]]|year= 2009|url= http://grad-schools.usnews.rankingsandreviews.com/best-graduate-schools/top-library-information-science-programs/rankings|accessdate= 14 January 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* Kent's Business School is nationally known and the Financial Engineering program is ranked 13th in the country.
* The College of Architecture and Environmental Design offers one of the most demanding undergraduate architecture programs in the country. The interior design program is one of the top twelve in the nation.
[[File:MathandScienceBuildingKSU.JPG|thumb|right|300px|Kent State Math and Computer Science Building]]
* Kent State has a complete undergraduate, master's, and doctoral sequence in translation and the only dual masters degree program in the nation.&lt;ref name=&quot;eInside Translation Program&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url= http://einside.kent.edu/?type=art&amp;id=88597#board |title= Board Establishes Nation's First Dual Master's Degree Program in Language Translation|accessdate=2008-06-25 |author= |date= |work= www.kent.edu|publisher=Kent State University}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* Faculty, staff and students collaborate at The Institute for the Study and Prevention of Violence (ISPV)[http://dept.kent.edu/ispv/], bringing together local and national expertise to develop multidisciplinary research that informs the development and implementation of best practices and policy.
* The Center for Peaceful Change, a response to the [[Kent State shootings]] of 1970, was established in 1971 &quot;as a living memorial to the events of May 4, 1970.&quot;[http://www.kent.edu/cacm/] Now known as The Center for Applied Conflict Management (CACM), it developed one of the earliest [[conflict resolution]] undergraduate degree programs in the United States.
* Pan-African Studies is one of the oldest African American programs in the nation.
* Kent State offers the only B.A. in [[American Sign Language]] in the U.S. east of the [[Mississippi River]].
* The Wick Poetry Center is one of only ten poetry centers in the nation.
* In conjunction with the [[University of Akron]] and [[Youngstown State University]], Kent State is a member of the [[Northeastern Ohio Universities College of Medicine and Pharmacy]] program, a six year medical program, one of only 17 combine BS/MD programs in the country.
* Kent State offers the only [[Kent State University College of Public Health|Bachelor of Science in Public Health (B.S.P.H.)]] degree in the state of Ohio.

==Student life==
The university offers a large number of opportunities for student involvement at all its campuses, including student and professional associations, service organizations, performing ensembles, student publications, student government, and intramural and club athletics.

===Greek life===
Greek life at Kent State is overseen by the Center for Student Involvement located in the Kent Student Center. Sorority houses are primarily located on Fraternity Drive located across the street from the main library and fraternity houses are located throughout the city of Kent. Recently, the university has set aside land for the development of a fraternity Greek village.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.kent.edu/media/2009NewsReleases/trustees3182009.cfm Kent.edu]&lt;/ref&gt; [[Sigma Nu]] recently has built a new chapter house on this land located near the Student Recreation and Wellness Center, but is now property of the Kappa Sigma fraternity.&lt;ref&gt;[http://media.www.kentnewsnet.com/media/storage/paper867/news/2008/09/19/News/Sigma.Nu.Makes.Greek.Village.Debut-3438231.shtml Kentnewsnet.com]&lt;/ref&gt; Kent State's Greek life claims numerous famous and well-known figures in society including [[Lou Holtz]], a brother of the Kent [[Delta Upsilon]] chapter and [[Drew Carey]], a brother of the Kent [[Delta Tau Delta]] chapter.

[[File:KentStateStudentCenter.JPG|thumb|right|450px| Kent Student Center which Houses many of the student organizations and activities]]
{| class=&quot;wikitable&quot; border=&quot;1&quot;
|-
! Social Fraternities
! Social Sororities
! Honorary &amp; Service Societies
|-
|[[Alpha Tau Omega]]
|[[Alpha Phi]]
|[[Alpha Kappa Delta]]
|-
|[[Alpha Epsilon Pi]]
|[[Alpha Xi Delta]]
|[[Alpha Phi Sigma]]
|-
|[[Delta Lambda Phi]]
|[[Delta Gamma]]
|[[Alpha Phi Omega]]
|-
|[[Delta Sigma Phi]]
|[[Delta Zeta]]
|[[Beta Alpha Psi]]
|-
|[[Delta Tau Delta]]
|[[Chi Omega]]
|Chi Sigma Iota
|-
|[[Delta Upsilon]]
|[[Sigma Sigma Sigma]]
|Eta Sigma Gamma
|[[Delta Sigma Pi]]
|-
|[[Kappa Sigma]]
|-
|[[Lambda Chi Alpha]]
! African American Fraternities
|[[Kappa Kappa Psi]]
|-
|[[Phi Delta Theta]]
|[[Kappa Alpha Psi]]
|Kappa Phi
|-
|[[Phi Kappa Tau]]
|[[Kappa Sigma]]
|[[Phi Beta Sigma]]
|[[Pi Mu Epsilon]]
|-
|[[Phi Sigma Kappa]]
|[[Omega Psi Phi]]
|[[Phi Alpha Theta]]

! African American Sororities
|[[Phi Delta Epsilon]]
|-
|[[Sigma Chi]]
|[[Delta Sigma Theta]]
|[[Sigma Gamma Rho]]
|[[Phi Sigma Iota]]
|-
|[[Sigma Phi Epsilon]]
|[[Lambda Pi Eta]]
|-
|[[Sigma Nu]]
|[[Zeta Phi Beta]]
|[[Phi Sigma Pi]]
|-
|[[Sigma Tau Gamma]]
|
|Sigma Alpha Lambda
|-
|[[Tau Kappa Epsilon]]
|
|[[Sigma Tau Delta]]
|-
|
|
|[[Tau Beta Sigma]]
|-
|
|
|Tau Sigma
|-
|
|
|[[Psi Chi]]
|-
|}

===Performing arts===
Through the Hugh A. Glauser School of Music and the School of Theatre and Dance, the university offers numerous performance opportunities in the performing arts, including five concert bands (Wind Ensemble, Symphonic Band, Concert Band, University Band, and Communiversity Band), Athletic Bands (Marching Golden Flashes and Flasher Brass), three jazz ensembles (Jazz Ensemble I, Jazz Ensemble II, and Jazz Lab Band), six choral ensembles (Kent Chorus, KSU Chorale, Women's Chorus, Men's Chorus, Gospel Choir, and Ars Nova Singers), two orchestras (KSU Symphony Orchestra and Chamber Strings), World Music Ensembles, as well as theater and dance opportunities.  Each regional campus also offers their own performing arts opportunities.

===Student events and programming===
Kent State Student Center Programming offers a variety of programs and events that are free for students across campus. The Black Squirrel Festival, Rock the Runway, Jack Hanna's Animals are just a few of the larger events that take place throughout the year. Karaoke is held every Thursday in the Rathskeller and various tournaments (8-ball, Euchre, Poker) are held at various times throughout the semester.

===Student government===
* Kent Interhall Council (KIC)
* Undergraduate Student Government (USG)
* Graduate Student Senate (GSS)

===Student media===
[[File:Tritowersksu.jpg|thumb|right|300px| Tri-Towers Residence Hall Complex]]
* The ''Daily Kent Stater'', colloquially known as the &quot;Stater&quot;, is a student newspaper publishing student and guests editorials Monday-Friday during the fall and spring semesters and weekly as the Summer Kent Stater during the summer.  Stater staff is entirely students, primarily in the journalism school. Most editors hold their positions for one semester.

* [[Black Squirrel Radio]] is Kent State's student-run radio station, which has nearly 120 students on its staff. The station streams constantly online and is also available through iTunes and on campus TV. The station plays urban, rock, and local music, and also broadcasts KSU basketball and football home games live.

* ''[[Fusion Magazine (Kent State University)|Fusion Magazine]]'' is published twice a year by KSU students in print and on the Internet. The magazine strives to unify people of different backgrounds through education and awareness. [[Fusion Magazine (Kent State University)]] addresses sexual minority issues within the general population using illustrative photo essays and in-depth feature articles.

* ''Uhuru Magazine'' is Kent State University's magazine dedicated to minority issues and topics and concentrates on African American issues and topics more specifically.

* ''Artemis Magazine'' is Kent State University's magazine dedicated to women's issues and topics.

* TV2 KSU is Kent State's student-run television station, produced solely by students with live Monday through Friday 5:30&amp;nbsp;pm news. Other student-created shows include Sports Corner; The Blurb, an entertainment news show; The Agenda, a [[comedy]]/[[satire]] show; talk shows and more, including [[Public administration|public affairs]] programming and election coverage. TV2 KSU programming is available on Kent State University [[cable TV]] Channel 2, Portage County [[Time Warner Cable]] Channel 16 and on-demand online or via [[iTunes]] podcasts. HD Streaming is available at studio.jmc.kent.edu.

===Campus living===
[[File:KSU Eastway Dining Hall.jpg|thumb|left|300px|Eastway Center at Night]]
Kent State operates twenty-five on-campus residence halls and a nine-building apartment complex, all of which are located on the main campus in Kent. Each hall is a part of a larger group, usually bound by a common name or a common central area.  They are:
* '''Twin Towers''': Beall and McDowell
* '''Tri-Towers''': Koonce, Leebrick, Wright and Korb
* '''Loop Road''': Van Campen
* '''Eastway''': Allyn, Clark, Fletcher, and Manchester. These halls plus Korb serve as the '''First Year Experience''' residence halls.
* '''New Front''': Prentice, Verder, Dunbar, and Engleman
* '''Centennial Court''': Six buildings lettered A - F
* '''Quad''': Lake, Olson, Johnson, and Stopher
* '''Allerton''': Twelve apartment buildings for family student housing

Dining halls are in Eastway, Tri-Towers, and Prentice, as well as multiple locations in the Student Center. Each of the residence hall dining locations also houses small grocery stores where students may use their board plan.

====Learning communities====
[[File:Centatnight.jpg|thumb|right|300px| Centennial Court B at Night]]
Within the halls are 11 Learning Communities based on area of study:
* A Community of Entrepreneurs (ACE)
* Accelerated Bachelor of Business Administration (A-BBA)
* Accounting Freshman Interest Group (AFIG)
* Arts and Sciences Residential College (CAS)
* College of Business Colleagues (CBC)
* CCI Commons
* Education Health &amp; Human Services Residential College (EHHS)
* EXCEL
* Honors Halls
* International Village Experience (IVE)
* Physical Education Professional Learning Community (PEPLC)

==Athletics==
{{Main|Kent State Golden Flashes}}
[[File:KentStateGoldenFlashes.png|right|thumb|200px|The current Kent State athletic logo]]

Kent State's athletic teams are called the ''Golden Flashes''. Their colors are Navy Blue and Gold. They compete in the [[National Collegiate Athletic Association|NCAA]]'s Division I ([[NCAA Division I-A national football championship|Bowl Subdivision]] for football), and the [[Mid-American Conference]] East division. Kent State fields 16 varsity athletic teams and one club team.

[[File:KentAkron.jpg|left|thumb|200px|The Kent defense lines up against Akron at [[Dix Stadium]] on September 30, 2006]]

The Flashes had success in the Mid-American Conference, earned the Mid-American Conference's Reese Cup for best men's athletic program in 2000, 2002 and 2006 and the Jacoby Cup for best women's athletic program in 1989, 1996, 1997, 1999, 2004 and 2005.[http://www.kentstatesports.com/ViewArticle.dbml?DB_OEM_ID=11400&amp;ATCLID=919608]. In 2002 the [[Kent State Golden Flashes basketball|Men's Basketball team]] advanced to NCAA &quot;Elite Eight&quot;, while the baseball team, women's basketball, gymnastics, men's golf, and women's golf teams have won numerous MAC titles and advanced to NCAA tournament play. Some notable athletic alumni include: [[Missouri Tigers football under Gary Pinkel|Missouri Tigers]] head football coach [[Gary Pinkel]], 2003 [[British Open]] Champion and current PGA member [[Ben Curtis (golfer)|Ben Curtis]], former [[New York Yankees]] catcher [[Thurman Munson]], [[Thomas Jefferson (athlete)]] 1984 200m Olympic bronze medalist, former [[Pittsburgh Steelers]] linebacker [[Jack Lambert (American football)|Jack Lambert]], Pittsburgh Steelers linebacker [[James Harrison (American football)|James Harrison]], ESPN Analyst and former college football coach [[Lou Holtz]], [[San Diego Chargers]] tight end [[Antonio Gates]] (who played basketball at KSU, not football), [[Cleveland Browns]] return specialist [[Joshua Cribbs]], former [[San Diego Padres]] pitcher [[Dustin Hermanson]], [[Tampa Bay Rays]] pitcher [[Andy Sonnanstine]], [[Los Angeles Dodgers]] pitcher [[Matt Guerrier]], and [[Alabama Crimson Tide]] head [[American football|football]] coach [[Nick Saban]], [[New England Patriots]] Wide Receiver [[Julian Edelman]].

The Golden Flashes compete in the following sports:
&lt;table&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td width=&quot;25%&quot; valign=top&gt;
* '''Fall Sports'''
** Men's [[Cross country running|Cross Country]]
** Women's Cross Country
** Men's [[Rugby union|Rugby]] (club team)
** Women's Rugby (club team)
** [[Field Hockey]]
** [[American football|Football]]
** Men's [[Golf]]*
** Women's Golf*
** [[Women's Soccer]]
** Women's [[Volleyball]]
&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td width=&quot;25%&quot; valign=top&gt;
* '''Winter Sports'''
** Men's [[Basketball]]
** Women's Basketball
** Women's [[Gymnastics]]
** Mixed [[Fencing]] (club team)
** Men's [[Ice hockey]] (club team)
** Men's [[Track and field|Track and Field]] (Indoor season)
** Women's Track and Field (Indoor season)
** [[Collegiate wrestling|Wrestling]]
&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td width=&quot;25%&quot; valign=top&gt;
* '''Spring Sports'''
** [[Baseball]]
** Men's Golf*
** Women's Golf*
** [[Softball]]
** Men's Track and Field (Outdoor season)
** Women's Track and Field (Outdoor season)
&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/table&gt;
''*=the golf teams' season begins in the fall, but continues through most of the school year, culminating in the league and NCAA tournaments in the spring.''

==Alma Mater and fight song==
[[File:Cementkent.jpg|thumb|right|300px|Cement Kent on Front Campus]]
'''Alma Mater:'''&lt;br /&gt;
From the beauty land Ohio comes a universal praise,&lt;br&gt;
'Tis the song of Alma Mater that her sons and daughters raise. &lt;br&gt;
'Tis a Hail to Kent forever, on the Cuyahoga shore,&lt;br&gt;
Now we join the loving thousands as they sing it o'er and o'er. &lt;br&gt;
Hail to Thee, our Alma Mater. &lt;br&gt;
O, how beautiful Thou art,&lt;br&gt;
High enthroned upon the hilltop, &lt;br&gt;
Reigning over every heart.

'''Fight Song:'''&lt;br /&gt;
Fight on for KSU &lt;br&gt;
Fight for the Blue and Gold! &lt;br&gt;
We're out to beat the foe; &lt;br&gt;
Fight on brave and bold! &lt;br&gt;
Fight on for victory, &lt;br&gt;
Don't stop until we're through. &lt;br&gt;
We're all together, &lt;br&gt;
Let's go forward, K-S-U!

==University Press==
[[File:May4thmem.jpg|thumb|left|225px| May 4 Memorial at Night]]
The Kent State University Press is the publishing arm of Kent State University. Their mission is &quot;to advance knowledge through publishing&quot; and is controlled by an Editorial Board of Kent faculty. As a member of the Association of American University Presses, it is included in the select group of more than 100 university-sponsored scholarly presses, whose outstanding programs make them an important segment of the publishing and academic community.

The Press began in 1965 under the direction of Howard Allen and published in the University faculty strengths in literary criticism. In 1972 Paul Rohmann became the Press's second director and expanded the Press's publishing program to include regional studies and ethnomusicology. In 1985 historian John Hubbell assumed the directorship and for fifteen years saw the staff and publishing program grow to include widely regarded lists in [[American Civil War|Civil War]] history and Ohio history. Today, under director Will Underwood, the Press publishes 30 to 35 titles a year and reaches a large and appreciative audience.

==Notable alumni==
&lt;!-- Please do not add any additional names to this section as it is a summary of a much larger list.  Instead, make sure they have been added to the &quot;List of Kent State University alumni&quot; article. If you feel a name should be added here due to very high notability, please discuss on the talk page.--&gt;
[[File:Rockwellhall.jpg|thumb|right|300px| Rockwell Hall, Fashion Museum and School of Fashion]]
[[File:KSULibrary09NEW.JPG|thumb|right|300px| Main Library via Esplanade]]
{{Main|List of Kent State University alumni}}
Kent State counts 196,000 alumni as of 2010.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |title= Prosperity by Degrees|magazine= Kent State Magazine|date= Spring 2010|url= http://www.kent.edu/president/econimpact/index.cfm|page= 3}}&lt;/ref&gt;  It has produced a number of individuals in the entertainment industry including comedian and current ''[[Price is Right]]'' host [[Drew Carey]], comedian and talk show host [[Arsenio Hall]], actors [[John de Lancie]], [[Michael Keaton]], and [[Ray Wise]], actresses [[Alaina Reed Hall]] and [[Alice Ripley]], ''[[Phenomenon (TV series)|Phenomenon]]'' star Angela Funovits, boxing promoter [[Don King (boxing promoter)|Don King]], ''[[30 Rock]]'' producer [[Jeff Richmond]], and ''[[That 70s Show]]'' creator [[Bonnie and Terry Turner|Bonnie Turner]].  Musicians from Kent State include several members of the band [[Devo]], which was formed at Kent State in 1973, including [[Mark Mothersbaugh]], [[Bob Lewis (musician)|Bob Lewis]], and [[Gerald Casale]].  Additional musicians include singers [[Chrissie Hynde]], [[Jeff Timmons]] of [[98 Degrees]], and [[Debra Byrd]] of ''[[American Idol]]'', guitarist [[Joe Walsh]], and drummer [[Chris Vrenna]].

In politics and government, several politicians in Ohio attended Kent State including former judge and United States Representative [[Robert E. Cook]], former minority leader [[C.J. Prentiss]], current [[United State House of Representatives]] member [[Betty Sutton]], former representative and Lieutenant Governor [[Nancy Hollister]], and [[Supreme Court of Ohio]] justice [[Terrence O'Donnell]].  Other politicians include [[Allen Buckley]] of [[Georgia (U.S. State)|Georgia]], [[Pennsylvania]] state representative [[Allen Kukovich]], and [[George Petak]] of [[Wisconsin]].  Politician activists from Kent State include anti-war activist [[Alan Canfora]] and former [[Students for a Democratic Society (1960 organization)|Students for a Democratic Society]] leaders [[Ken Hammond]] and [[Carl Oglesby]].

Literary and journalism alumni include ''[[Funky Winkerbean]]'' and ''[[Crankshaft (comic strip)|Crankshaft]]'' writer [[Tom Batiuk]], ''[[Captain Underpants]]'' author [[Dav Pilkey]], [[Pulitzer Prize]]-winning columnist [[Connie Schultz]], and Pulitzer Prize nominated columnist [[Regina Brett]].  Television journalism alumni include [[CNN]] anchor [[Carol Costello]], [[Cleveland]] anchors [[Wayne Dawson]] and [[Catherine Bosley]], and [[ESPN]] [[Dream Job]] winner [[Dave Holmes (sportscaster)|Dave Holmes]].

A number of professional athletes are Kent State alumni including current [[National Football League]] players [[Joshua Cribbs]], [[James Harrison (American football)|James Harrison]], [[Antonio Gates]], and [[Usama Young]].  Former NFL players include [[Don Nottingham]], [[Pro Football Hall of Fame]] member [[Jack Lambert (American football)|Jack Lambert]] along with [[Canadian Football League]] standouts [[Jay McNeil]], [[Tony Martino]], and [[Canadian Football Hall of Fame]] and former [[Kent State Golden Flashes football|Kent State football]] head coach [[Jim Corrigall]].  [[College football]] coaches [[Nick Saban]] of the [[Alabama Crimson Tide football|University of Alabama]], [[Gary Pinkel]] of the [[Missouri Tigers football|University of Missouri]], and former coach and current ESPN analyst [[Lou Holtz]] are also Kent State alumni.

[[Major League Baseball]] players to come from Kent State include current players [[Emmanuel Burriss]], [[Matt Guerrier]], [[Andy Sonnanstine]], [[Dirk Hayhurst]] and [[Dustin Hermanson]].  Past MLB players include [[Gene Michael]], [[Rich Rollins]], [[Cy Young Award]] winner [[Steve Stone (baseball player)|Steve Stone]], and [[MLB Rookie of the Year Award|Rookie of the Year]], and [[MLB Most Valuable Player Award|Most Valuable Player]] winner [[Thurman Munson]].  Additional athletic alumni include Canadian professional golfers [[Jon Mills]] and [[Ryan Yip]] as well as American and 2003 [[The Open Championship|British Open]] champion [[Ben Curtis (golfer)|Ben Curtis]], and Olympians [[Betty-Jean Maycock]] in gymnastics and [[Gerald Tinker]] in track and field.

==References==
{{Reflist}}

==Further reading==
* {{cite book |title=A Book of Memories: Kent State University, 1910-1992 |last=Hildebrand |first=William H. |authorlink= |coauthors=Dean H. Keller, Anita Dixon Herington |year=1993 |publisher=Kent State University Press |location= |isbn=0873384881 |pages= }}
* {{cite book |title=A most noble enterprise: the story of Kent State University, 1910-2010 |last=Hildebrand |first=William H. |authorlink= |coauthors= |year=2009 |publisher=Kent State University Press |location= |isbn=1606350307 |pages= }}

==External links==
{{Commons category}}
* [http://www.kent.edu Official website]

{{Kent State University|campuses}}
{{Mid-American Conference}}
{{CSCHL}}
{{Public universities in Ohio}}

[[Category:Educational institutions established in 1910]]
[[Category:Kent State University| ]]
[[Category:Association of Public and Land-Grant Universities]]
[[Category:Education in Portage County, Ohio]]
[[Category:Universities and colleges in Ohio]]
[[Category:Mid-American Conference]]
[[Category:Kent, Ohio]]
[[Category:North Central Association of Colleges and Schools]]
[[Category:Aviation schools]]
[[Category:Buildings and structures in Portage County, Ohio]]
[[Category:Visitor attractions in Portage County, Ohio]]

[[de:Kent State University]]
[[fa:دانشگاه ایالتی کنت]]
[[fr:Université d'État de Kent]]
[[ja:ケント州立大学]]
[[no:Kent State University]]
[[pt:Universidade de Kent (Estados Unidos)]]
[[simple:Kent State University]]
[[fi:Kentin osavaltionyliopisto]]
[[sv:Kent State University]]
[[th:มหาวิทยาลัยเคนต์สเตต]]
[[zh:肯特州立大學]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
