<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="169909" ns="0" title="Stetson University"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Infobox University
 |name              = Stetson University
 |native_name       = 
 |image_name        = Stetson Univ Seal.svg
 |image_size        = 
 |caption           = 
 |latin_name        = 
 |motto             = ''Pro Deo et Veritate''
 |mottoeng          = For God and Truth
 |established       = 1883
 |closed            = 
 |type              = Private
 |affiliation       = 
 |endowment         = $123 million&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.nacubo.org/Documents/research/2010NCSE_Public_Tables_Endowment_Market_Values_Final.pdf nacubo.org]&lt;/ref&gt;
 |officer_in_charge = 
 |chairman          = 
 |chancellor        = 
 |president         = Wendy B. Libby
 |vice-president    = 
 |superintendent    = 
 |provost           = 
 |vice_chancellor   = 
 |rector            = 
 |principal         = 
 |dean              = 
 |director          = 
 |head_label        = 
 |head              = 
 |faculty           = 200
 |staff             = 
 |students          = 2,200
 |undergrad         = 
 |postgrad          = 
 |doctoral          = 
 |other             = 
 |city              = [[DeLand, Florida|DeLand]]
 |state             = [[Florida]]
 |province          = 
 |country           = United States
 |coor              = {{coord|29.03528|-81.30361|display=inline, title}}
 |campus            = Suburban, 174 acres (668,000 m²)
 |former_names      = 
 |free_label        = 
 |free              = 
 |sports            = 
 |colors            = [[Green (color)|Green]] and [[White (color)|White]]&lt;br /&gt;{{color box|#006000}} {{color box|#FFFFFF}}
 |colours           = 
 |nickname          = Hatters
 |mascot            = 
 |athletics         = [http://www.gohatters.com www.gohatters.com]
 |affiliations      = 
 |website           = [http://www.stetson.edu www.stetson.edu]
 |logo              = 
 |footnotes         = 
}}'''Stetson University''' is a private university with four colleges and schools located across the [[Interstate 4|I-4]] corridor in [[Central Florida]]. The primary undergraduate campus is located in [[DeLand, Florida|DeLand]], [[Florida]], USA. In the 2012 ''[[U.S. News and World Report]]'s'' guide to America's Best Colleges, Stetson ranks third in the category of Southern Masters-granting institutions.&lt;ref&gt;[http://colleges.usnews.rankingsandreviews.com/best-colleges/stetson-university-1531 US News: Universities-Master's (South): Top Schools]&lt;/ref&gt; 
Other recent recognitions include being ranked No. 23 nationally in ''[[Washington Monthly]]'' magazine’s “Top 50 Master’s Universities.”&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.washingtonmonthly.com/college_guide/rankings_2010/masters_universities_rank.php Washington Monthly 2010 Master's Universities]&lt;/ref&gt; The School of Music was named to ''[[Parade Magazine]]’s'' national “College A-List” in the category highlighting Arts Programs&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.parade.com/news/2010/08/22-college-a-list-arts-programs.html?index=19 Parade Magazine, Aug. 22, 2010]&lt;/ref&gt; and the School of Business Administration was named one of the nation's 300 best by Princeton Review.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.princetonreview.com/StetsonUniversitySchoolofBusinessAdministration.aspx Princeton Review: &quot;Best 300 Business Schools&quot;]&lt;/ref&gt; Stetson, the only university affiliated with the [[Bonner Foundation|Corella and Bertram F. Bonner Foundation]] in Florida, is also nationally recognized for its commitment to service and social justice-based community engagement and community-engaged learning.&lt;ref&gt;[https://www.stetson.edu/secure/apps/wordpress/?p=6248 discover.stetson.edu]&lt;/ref&gt;

==History==
{| class=&quot;toccolours&quot; cellspacing=&quot;3px&quot; style=&quot;width: 24em; float: right; margin: 0 0 1em 1em; text-align:left;&quot;
|The first charter stated that the objective of the university should be &quot;to promote the general interests of education, and to qualify its students to engage in the learned professions or other employments of society, and to discharge honorably and usefully the various duties of life.&quot;
|}According to [[Gilbert Lycan]], a Stetson history professor who wrote the university's official centennial history in 1983, Stetson University is Florida's first university, public or private. Stetson University was founded in 1883 by [[Henry Addison DeLand]], a New York philanthropist, as '''DeLand Academy'''. In 1887, the [[Florida Legislature]] enacted the Charter of DeLand University as an independent institution of higher learning. [[Rollins College]] was founded and chartered in 1885, thus making it the oldest recognized college, public or private.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.myfloridahouse.gov/Sections/Documents/loaddoc.aspx?FileName=_h9069__.doc&amp;DocumentType=Bill&amp;BillNumber=9069&amp;Session=2004 myfloridahouse.gov]&lt;/ref&gt; 

'''DeLand University''''s name was changed in 1889 to honor hat manufacturer [[John B. Stetson]], a benefactor of the university, who served with town founder, Henry A. DeLand, and others as a founding trustee of the university.

Stetson University was affiliated with the Florida Baptist Convention until the early 1990s, when the university and convention ended their relationship.

==Campus==
[[File:220stetson-delandhall-DSC0145.jpg|thumb|DeLand Hall]]
[[File:220-stetson-reshall-DSC03996.jpg|thumb|University Village Apartments and clubhouse]]
[[File:220stetson-flagler-exterior.jpg|thumb|Flagler Hall]]
The university's College of Arts &amp; Sciences, School of Business Administration, School of Music, and most graduate programs are housed at the DeLand campus, located just north of the downtown area of [[DeLand, Florida]]. More than 60 undergraduate majors and minors are offered.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.stetson.edu/academics/programs.php stetson.edu]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.uscollegesearch.org/stetson-university.html uscollegesearch.org]&lt;/ref&gt; 

Stetson's campus is just north of the downtown area of DeLand, roughly halfway between [[Orlando, Florida|Orlando]] and [[Daytona Beach, Florida]]. The {{convert|175|acre|km2|sing=on}} campus is nationally designated by the [[National Register of Historic Places]] as the [[Stetson University Campus Historic District]] for Florida's oldest collection of education-related buildings. DeLand Hall, which houses the Office of the President and the offices of other administrators, was constructed in 1884 and is the oldest building in Florida in continuous use for higher education.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.stetson.edu/other/125years/ Transformations: 125 Years at Stetson]&lt;/ref&gt; 

In 2003, the Lynn Business Center — housing much of the university's School of Business — was Florida's first [[green building]] certified by the [[U.S. Green Building Council]].

Elizabeth Hall, named after [[John B. Stetson]]'s wife, houses a number of departments in the College of Arts &amp; Sciences. The School of Music performs in Lee Chapel in the south of the building. The [[cupola]] atop Elizabeth Hall — modeled after the one on [[Independence Hall]] in [[Philadelphia]] — is used as the official symbol of the undergraduate campus.

In 2010, Stetson became a pet-friendly campus,&lt;ref&gt;[https://www.stetson.edu/secure/apps/wordpress/?p=15013 Stetson University news]&lt;/ref&gt; and the university also invested $6.5 million to renew landscaping in the campus core, upgrade classrooms and add energy-saving lighting, all at the DeLand campus.&lt;ref&gt;[https://www.stetson.edu/secure/apps/wordpress/?p=15609 Stetson University news]&lt;/ref&gt; Improvements included a new coffeehouse. In the past 3 years, over $17 million in new construction took place at the DeLand campus. Sage Hall, home of the departments of natural sciences, received an $8.5 million renovation, while the Homer and Dolly Hand Art Center, the Rinker Environmental Learning Center, and Mary B. McMahan Hall — rehearsal space for the School of Music — were new constructions. Along with student exhibitions, the university's extensive collection of paintings by American modernist [[Oscar Bluemner]] are housed in the Hand Art Center. 

The university also includes the [[Stetson University College of Law]], the first law school in Florida. It was relocated in 1954 from DeLand to [[Gulfport, Florida]], a suburb of [[St. Petersburg, Florida|St. Petersburg]]. 

There are also two satellite centers:
*The Stetson University Center at [[Celebration, Florida]], which opened in 2004.
*The Tampa Law Center, which opened in 2004, in downtown [[Tampa, Florida]].

Stetson's campus has been used as a filming location for a number of films and television shows. These include the Adam Sandler film ''[[The Waterboy]]'',&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.imdb.com/title/tt0120484/locations imdb.com]&lt;/ref&gt; ''[[Ghost Story (film)|Ghost Story]]'',&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.imdb.com/title/tt0082449/locations imdb.com]&lt;/ref&gt; ''From Earth to the Moon'',&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.imdb.com/title/tt0120570/locations imdb.com]&lt;/ref&gt; ''First of May'', and ''Estás nominado: Cuando la realidad supera a la ficción''.

===Residential life===
There are nine residence halls at Stetson University. These include:
* Carson-Hollis Hall
* Chaudoin Hall
* Conrad Hall
* Emily Hall
* Gordis Hall
* Nemec Hall
* Residence Hall A
* Smith Hall

Students may also reside at the University Village Apartments. In addition to the residence halls, a Foreign Language House and Greek Houses (both fraternity and sorority) provide student housing. The fraternity houses were renovated in 2009. The Wellness House serves as housing for students who wish to abstain from any substance use, including alcohol and tobacco. Nemec Hall is a pet-friendly residence hall. Smith, Gordis and Carson-Hollis halls are used primarily for first-year students. Conrad and Chaudoin Halls are all-female housing.

==Admissions==
Stetson University had an acceptance rate of 55.3% for the class of 2014.  Ultimately 565 first-year students enrolled.  Applicants’ mid-range SAT scores were 1000–1220.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.stetson.edu/iro Stetson Institutional Research Office]&lt;/ref&gt; 

In fall 2010, there were 2,134 undergraduates and 485 graduate and post-Bacc students enrolled at Stetson's DeLand and Celebration campuses (not including the College of Law), from 36 states and 36 countries. 42.6% are male, 57.3% female. 72% of undergraduates live on campus (90% of first-year students).

Stetson’s peer schools include [[University of Richmond]], [[Furman University]], [[Washington and Lee University]], [[Trinity University]]{{dn|date=November 2011}} and [[Rollins College]].

==Academics==
There are more than 60 majors and minors leading to the Bachelor of Arts, Bachelor of Science, Bachelor of Music, Bachelor of Music Education, or Bachelor of Business Administration degrees. Master's degrees are offered by the School of Business Administration in Accounting and Business Administration, and by the College of Arts &amp; Sciences in Education, English and Counseling. The Juris Doctor and a Master of Laws in International Law and Business are offered by the Stetson College of Law, which guarantees admission to Stetson undergraduates who meet certain academic requirements.

The university is accredited by the Commission on Colleges of the Southern Association of Colleges and Schools.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.stetson.edu/bulletin/media/intro.pdf  Stetson University Bulletin]&lt;/ref&gt; Stetson has 195 full-time faculty teaching undergraduate courses, with 95% of those faculty holding Ph.D. or equivalent degrees. The student-faculty ratio is 11–1.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.stetson.edu/iro/factbooks.php Stetson Institutional Research Office Fact Books]&lt;/ref&gt;

===College of Arts &amp; Sciences===
Since its founding in 1883, Stetson's College of Arts &amp; Sciences has prepared students for informed, compassionate, and accomplished lives. A core curriculum in liberal studies develops breadth of understanding and serious engagement with principles of ethical decision-making. 
Additionally, all students in the College of Arts &amp; Sciences are required to complete a &quot;Senior capstone project,&quot; also known as &quot;Senior research&quot; or a &quot;Senior thesis,&quot; before a degree can be awarded.

===School of Music===
The School of Music combines a music conservatory education with being part of a university grounded in the liberal arts tradition. The enrollment is 200 undergraduate music majors.  There are 47 artist-faculty members. Performance opportunities for students include the symphony orchestra, band, choirs, opera, musical theater, jazz, chamber music, and solo recitals. The curriculum includes degree options in performance, education, theory, and composition. Music students may combine music study with business, pre-law, and many other fields. The School of Music has been an accredited member of the National Association of Schools of Music since 1938.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.stetson.edu/music/home/index.php School of Music]&lt;/ref&gt;

Music students can opt for the Bachelor of Music in Music Technology, and a Bachelor of Arts in Digital Arts-Sound is also available.  Through the collaboration of the music and business schools, students can earn an undergraduate music degree and a graduate business degree in five years.

===School of Business Administration===
The School of Business Administration features a range of traditional and non-traditional majors.  Each major offers a customized field of study for a specific business discipline.  Undergraduate majors include accounting, management, finance, international business, management information systems, marketing, family business, and general business.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www2.stetson.edu/business/#/undergrad/ School of Business Administration]&lt;/ref&gt; Masters programs include MBA, EMBA, and Macc.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www2.stetson.edu/business/#/graduate/ SoBA graduate programs]&lt;/ref&gt; All programs are accredited by AACSB International-The Association to Advance Collegiate Schools of Business.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.stetson.edu/bulletin/media/intro.pdf  Stetson University Bulletin]&lt;/ref&gt;

===Special programs===
A variety of special academic programs are available to students, such as the Roland George Investments Program, where business students manage a real portfolio of more than $2.8 million, the Honors Program, where students and faculty collaborate in an interdisciplinary community, the Nina B. Hollis Institute for Education Reform, which attempts to improve education from preschool through college, the Stetson Institute for Social Research, which provides services to outside agencies, and the Family Enterprise Center, offering a major in Family Business. 

The Sullivan Creative Writing Program is an undergraduate initiative for students with a passion for the English language.

Stetson University also offers special programs for students up through 9th grade. Working in collaboration with the Belin-Blank International Center for Gifted Education and Talent Development at the University of Iowa, Stetson University sponsors the HATS (High Achieving Talented Students) Program.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.stetson.edu/hats|title=Stetson University HATS Program&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;}}&lt;/ref&gt; HATS serves K-9th grade students who participate in gifted programs or have scored at or above the 95th percentile on any subject area on the FCAT, ITBS, CTBS, or other standardized test. HATS offers Saturday and summer enrichment programs, scholarships, and above-level testing.

===International education===
Stetson University offers study abroad programs at a number of universities in Spain, France, Germany, Mexico, England, Scotland, Russia, Austria, and China, as well as an option for study in Washington, D.C.

===Undergraduate research===
In addition to the completion of a &quot;Senior thesis&quot; project compulsory for graduation, students have the opportunity to develop their own research projects and be involved in faculty research.  Two distinct programs foster undergraduate research: the SURE (Stetson Undergraduate Research Experience) Grant competition, which provides summer stipends and faculty mentors for selected student research projects; and SURCAS (Stetson Undergraduate Research and Creative Arts Symposium), a day-long event that encourages all undergraduates to share their research with the Stetson community.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.stetson.edu/other/research/ Stetson Undergraduate Research]&lt;/ref&gt;

===Guest lecturers===
Stetson has hosted a number of notable lecturers, some through the Stetson Institute for Christian Ethics. Notable lecturers include Ralph Nader, [[Archbishop Desmond Tutu]], former United States President [[Jimmy Carter]], author [[Elie Wiesel]], scientists [[E.O. Wilson]] and [[Jane Goodall]], journalists [[Bill Moyers]] and [[William F. Buckley Jr.]], and playwright [[Eve Ensler]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www2.stetson.edu/~ljguenth/group Institute for Christian Ethics]&lt;/ref&gt; 

Other visitors have included [[Buckminster Fuller]], [[Stokely Carmichael]] (Kwame Ture) and [[Robert Frost]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.stetson.edu/125years/guest.php 125 Famous Visitors, Transformations: 125 Years of Stetson]&lt;/ref&gt;

===Continuing Education===
The university has a department of continuing education that specializes in services to organizations outside of the Stetson community.

* The [[Elderhostel]] program — now known as Road Scholar — held primarily at the end of the fall semester into the beginning of the spring semester, as well as during the summer, allows individuals older than the traditional university age to attend classes on campus and in the region for a week, with specialized courses taught throughout the university's curriculum.
* Each February, the departments of Continuing Education and Religious Studies co-host the Florida Winter Pastors’ School, which in 2010 celebrated its 25th anniversary.
* Each summer, week-long Destination Science camps are offered for youth ages 6–11, who attend sessions such as &quot;Robots vs. Aliens&quot; and &quot;'G' Force Rockets and Moon Blasters.&quot;

==Student life==
Stetson has approximately 20 honorary academic and professional organizations and over 100 other student organizations on campus, including [[Phi Beta Kappa]] (first private university in Florida to be granted a chapter);&lt;ref&gt;[http://www2.stetson.edu/pbk/history.php PBK Gamma of Florida]&lt;/ref&gt; the Floyd M. Riddick Model United States Senate program; ''The Reporter'', Florida's oldest college newspaper; [[Model United Nations]]; a philosophy club; [[Phi Alpha Delta]] Pre-Law Professional Fraternity; [[Alpha Kappa Psi]] Business Professional Fraternity; [[Omicron Delta Kappa]] national leadership fraternity; Poetry at an Uncouth Hour (a poetry reading club); Hatter Harvest (organic community garden); ''Touchstone'', the student literary magazine, and many others.

There are several religious organizations on campus as well, including the Cooperative Collegiate Ministry, the [[Lutheran]] Campus Ministries, the [[Roman Catholicism|Catholic]] Campus Ministry, the Wesley House ([[Methodist]] Ministry), the Canterbury House ([[Episcopal Church (United States)|Episcopal]]), the [[Muslim American]] Student Organization, and the Hillel/[[Jewish]] Student Organization. 

There are also a number of multicultural and social justice organizations on campus, including the Black Student Association, the Hispanic Organization for Latin American Awareness (HOLA), Organization for Students Actively Pursuing Equality (OSAPE), STAND (the student-run branch of the Genocide Intervention Network), and Kaleidoscope (the [[LGBT]] alliance on campus). 

There is also an [[United States Army|Army]] [[Reserve Officers' Training Corps]] (ROTC) unit that students can participate in on-campus through [[Embry-Riddle Aeronautical University]]. Successful completion of the ROTC program allows University students to be commissioned in the United States Army as a [[Second Lieutenant#United States|Second Lieutenant]], and requires a service commitment.

There are five social sororities on campus: [[Alpha Chi Omega]], [[Alpha Xi Delta]], [[Delta Delta Delta]], [[Pi Beta Phi]], and [[Zeta Tau Alpha]], and six social fraternities: [[Delta Sigma Phi]], [[Phi Sigma Kappa]], [[Pi Kappa Alpha]], [[Pi Kappa Phi]], [[Sigma Nu]], and [[Sigma Phi Epsilon]].

Stetson is also home to chapters from [[Phi Mu Alpha Sinfonia]], a music fraternity for men, and [[Sigma Alpha Iota]], a music fraternity for women.

===Student Government===
Established in 1908, the Stetson University Student Government Association is the representative and executive decision-making body for all undergraduate students in the Stetson community.
Student governance at Stetson consists of two branches, an executive and a unicameral legislative branch. The executive branch consists of the Student Body President, the Student Body Vice President, the Secretary of Communication, the Secretary of Finance, and the Secretary of Student Involvement. The Student Body President and Student Body Vice President are elected annually in the spring.  After installment, the Student Body President appoints the Secretaries of Communication, Finance, and Student Involvement.

===Floyd M. Riddick Model United States Senate===
Stetson University hosts the nation's first and oldest college-level Model United States Senate program (established in 1970) every year in March.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www2.stetson.edu/modelsenate Floyd M. Riddick Model United States Senate]&lt;/ref&gt; Each year, students from colleges and universities around the nation gather at Stetson for the three-day event. The Model Senate reproduces the actual procedures and activities of the U.S. Senate in an effort to provide experience and education for the student participants. Each student is assigned as a Senator in one of five legislative committees and is responsible for researching a variety of bills, and crafting appropriate amendments. In addition, the Model Senate attracts national speakers and lecturers, including former and sitting U.S. Senators.

===Athletics===
{| class=&quot;infobox&quot; cellpadding=&quot;2&quot; cellspacing=&quot;2&quot; style=&quot;font-size: 90%;&quot; 
|+ style=&quot;font-size: 1.25em;&quot; |'''Intercollegiate athletics'''
|-
| colspan=&quot;2&quot; align=&quot;center&quot; |  [[Image:StetsonHatters.png|150px]]
|-
|'''Men’s Teams'''&lt;br /&gt;[[College baseball|Baseball]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Basketball]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Rowing (sport)|Crew]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Cross country running|Cross Country]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Golf]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Soccer]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Tennis]]&lt;br /&gt;[[American football|Football]]
|'''Women’s Teams'''&lt;br /&gt;[[Basketball]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Rowing (sport)|Crew]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Cross country running|Cross Country]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Golf]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Soccer]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Softball]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Tennis]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Volleyball]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Lacrosse]]
|}

====Intercollegiate athletics====
Stetson is a member of the [[National Collegiate Athletic Association]], and both men’s and women’s teams compete on a Division I level in the [[Atlantic Sun Conference]]. The school's mascot is the Stetson Hatter.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.gohatters.com/ViewArticle.dbml?DB_OEM_ID=14600&amp;KEY=&amp;ATCLID=702199 The Stetson Hatter]&lt;/ref&gt; The basketball, baseball, men's and women's tennis, women’s golf, men's and women's soccer and softball teams have either earned conference championships or, gained national rankings or recognition. In 2011, football and women's lacrosse programs were added. Both will play their first games in 2013.

''History''&lt;br&gt;
One of the high profile sports at Stetson is baseball. Since 1970 the baseball program has earned seven Atlantic Sun Conference championships and 16 trips to the NCAA Regionals. Stetson participated in football from 1901 until 1956 achieving an all-time record of 155–127–27 (.545). The football team earned its 100th victory in 1935. In 2010, university officials gathered information and evaluating the feasibility of starting a [[Football Championship Subdivision]] (formerly Division I-AA) non-scholarship program.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.news-journalonline.com/sports/college/2010/02/19/stetson-considers-bringing-back-football-program.html news-journalonline.com]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://collegesportsinfo.com/2010/02/19/stetson-university-considers-football/ collegesportsinfo.com]&lt;/ref&gt; On March 14, 2011, SU President Wendy B. Libby announced the return of Hatter Football&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.stetson.edu/administration/pr/football/index.php stetson.edu]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.news-journalonline.com/breakingnews/2011/03/deland-approves-stadium-upgrades-stetson-annouces-football-is-back.html news-journalonline.com]&lt;/ref&gt; and the addition of women's lacrosse. Stetson will play in the [[Pioneer Football League]], with the first game in 2013. In July, 2011, Stetson named Roger A. Hughes&lt;ref&gt;[https://www.stetson.edu/secure/apps/wordpress/?p=16942 sttson.edu]&lt;/ref&gt; as head coach. The first game in the NCAA Division I program in women's lacrosse also will be played in 2013.  

''Rivalries''&lt;br&gt;
Stetson's main rivals include the [[University of Central Florida]], [[Jacksonville University]], and [[Mercer University]].

====Club Sports====
The Club Sports program was launched at Stetson in 2010.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.gohatters.com/ViewArticle.dbml?DB_OEM_ID=14600&amp;KEY=&amp;ATCLID=204888287 Stetson Athletics: Club Sports]&lt;/ref&gt; The competition level of club sports falls between intramural sports and intercollegiate athletic. There are 15 club sports available to men and women at Stetson: [[Aikido]], [[croquet]], [[equestrianism]], [[fishing]], Hatter [[table tennis]], Hatter [[tennis]], Lady Hatter [[women's lacrosse]], men's [[lacrosse]], [[mixed martial arts]] (MMA), [[sand volleyball]], [[shooting]], [[surfing]], [[swimming (sport)|Swimming]], [[ultimate Frisbee]], and most recently skydiving. Students may apply to form new clubs.

====Intramural Program====
The Intramural Program offers students the opportunity to manage, officiate, direct and participate in physical activities. The following sports are available to both men and women: [[basketball]], [[indoor volleyball]], [[swimming (sport)|swimming]], [[bowling]], [[soccer]], [[indoor soccer]], [[kickball]], [[ultimate Frisbee]], [[dodge ball]], [[sand volleyball]], [[flag football]], [[softball]], [[golf]], [[wiffleball]].

===Athletic facilities===
* [[Edmunds Center|The J. Ollie Edmunds Center]] – ''basketball and volleyball'', 4,000-seat multipurpose arena, athletic offices, weight room
* Patricia Wilson Softball Field, the 2009 Softball Field of the Year&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.stma.org/professionalism/docs/stma-mr-tab3-1268.htm  Sports Turf Managers Association]&lt;/ref&gt;
* The Wilson Athletic Center – sport and exercise science department, fitness and activity rooms
* Mandy Stoll Tennis Center – next to the soccer field
* [[Melching Field at Conrad Park]] – ''baseball stadium'' (off campus)
* Victoria Hills Golf Club (off campus)&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.gohatters.com/ViewArticle.dbml?DB_OEM_ID=14600&amp;KEY=&amp;ATCLID=714159|title=gohatters.com Athletics Facilities}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* Soccer Field
* [[Hollis Center]]
*[[Spec Martin Stadium]]--6,000 seat off campus stadium which is the former and future home of Stetson Hatters football.

==Awards and Certifications==
The [[Carnegie Foundation for the Advancement of Teaching]] awarded its Community Engagement classification to Stetson in 2008.&lt;ref&gt;[https://www.stetson.edu/secure/apps/wordpress/?p=6248 discover.stetson.edu]&lt;/ref&gt;  For the past three consecutive years, Stetson has been named by the [[Corporation for National and Community Service]] to the President’s Higher Education Community Service Honor Roll With Distinction for exemplary service initiatives.&lt;ref&gt;[https://www.stetson.edu/secure/apps/wordpress/?p=10343 discover.stetson.edu]&lt;/ref&gt; Stetson also works with the [[Jimmy &amp; Rosalynn Carter Partnership Foundation]] on the CASE (Carter Academic Service Entrepreneur) program and other JRCPF initiatives, and partners with JRCPF and the W.K.Kellogg Foundation on a service-based scholarship program.&lt;ref&gt;[https://www.stetson.edu/secure/apps/wordpress/?p=9803 discover.stetson.edu]&lt;/ref&gt; In 2009, Stetson introduced a Certificate of Community Engagement program for undergraduates.&lt;ref&gt;[https://www.stetson.edu/secure/apps/wordpress/?p=14026 discover.stetson.edu]&lt;/ref&gt;

==Notable alumni==
{{alum/start
|ilist=
[[Image:Cleland.jpg|thumb|right|100px|[[Max Cleland]]]]
[[Image:E Clay Shaw.png|thumb|right|100px|Official photo of former U.S. Representative [[E. Clay Shaw, Jr.]]]]
|alist=
{{Alum|name=V.Inez Archibald|year=1985|nota=Deputy Governor, [[British Virgin Islands]]|ref=}}
{{Alum|name=[[Gus Bilirakis]]|year=|nota=U.S. Representative, Florida's 9th Congressional District.|ref=}}
{{Alum|name=[[Jeff Bowen]]|year=|nota=Author and star of Broadway play ''[[title of show]]''|ref=}}
{{Alum|name=[[Brian Bocock]]|year=|nota=Major League Baseball Player – [[Philadelphia Phillies]]|ref=}}
{{Alum|name=[[Wilma Burgess]]|year=|nota=American Country Music singer; charted six singles on Billboard country charts in the 1960s and 1970s.|ref=}}
{{Alum|name=[[Doyle E. Carlton]] |year=1909|nota=(b.1885, d.1972) 25th Governor of Florida, 1929–1933.|ref=}}
{{Alum|name=[[Ted Cassidy]] |year=|nota=Actor who played [[Lurch (The Addams Family)|Lurch]] on the TV show, ''[[The Addams Family (TV series)|The Addams Family]]''|ref=}}
{{Alum|name=[[Max Cleland]]|year=|nota=Secretary, [[American Battle Monuments Commission]]; former U.S. Senator|ref=}}
{{Alum|name=[[Mack Cleveland]]|year=1949, Law 1951|nota=Seminole County lawyer and member of both houses of the Florida State Legislature from 1953 to 1965, general counsel for Stetson University prior to 2004|ref=&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://mysanfordherald.com/pages/full_story_obits/push?article-Mack+Cleveland+Jr-+state+legislator-+%E2%80%98Southern+gentleman-%E2%80%99+dies+at+86-%20&amp;id=9980935&amp;instance=obituaries_page|title=Mack Cleveland Jr., state legislator, ‘Southern gentleman,’ dies at 86|publisher=''Sanford Herald'', October 2010|accessdate=September 6, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;}}
{{Alum|name=Joe Cooper|year=1979,1982|nota=Executive vice president, [[Big Lots]]|ref=}}
{{Alum|name=[[Craig Crawford]] |year=|nota=Television political commentator, writer, and columnist for the [[Congressional Quarterly]] (1978)|ref=}}
{{Alum|name=[[Andy Dehnart]]|year=1998|nota=Blogger and [[reality television]] critic|ref=}}

{{Alum|name=[[Melodee DeVevo]]|year=1998|nota=member of Dove Award-winning band [[Casting Crowns]]|ref=}}
{{Alum|name=[[Lenny DiNardo]]|year=|nota=Major League Baseball player – [[Kansas City Royals]]|ref=}}
{{Alum|name=Dr. Frank Farmer|year=|nota=Florida Surgeon General|ref=}}
{{Alum|name=[[Roy Geiger]]|year=|nota=United States Marine Corps general|ref=}}
{{Alum|name=Avantika Hari|year=2002|nota=Filmmaker; writer and director of the award-winning [[Land Gold Women]]|ref=}}
{{Alum|name=[[Mike Haridopolos]]|year=1992|nota=Florida Senate President 2010–2012|ref=}}
{{Alum|name=Glen W. Hauenstein|year=|nota=Executive vice president of [[Delta Air Lines]]|ref=}}
{{Alum|name=[[Joseph Edwards Hendricks]]|year=|nota=Former [[United States Representative]] from Florida|ref=}}
{{Alum|name=Shephard W. Hill|year=1975|nota=President, [[Boeing International]]|ref=}}
{{Alum|name=Thomas A. James|year=|nota=CEO of [[Raymond James]]|ref=}}
{{Alum|name=Lewis M. Kling|year=1971|nota=Executive vice chairman, [[Flowserve]] Corp.|ref=}}
{{Alum|name=Laurette T. Koellner|year=1980|nota=Retired (2008) president, [[Boeing International]]|ref=}}
{{Alum|name=[[Suzanne Kosmas]]|year=|nota=Former US Congresswoman, elected November 2008|ref=}}
{{Alum|name=Davis Mallory|year=|nota=Cast member of MTV's ''Real World Denver''|ref=}}
{{Alum|name=[[Richard J. McKay]]|year=|nota=President and general manager, [[Atlanta Falcons]]|ref=}}
{{Alum|name=Lewis M. Kling|year=1971|nota=Executive vice chairman, [[Flowserve]] Corp.|ref=}}
{{Alum|name=[[Charles E. Merrill]]|year=|nota=Founder of [[Merrill Lynch]]|ref=}}
{{Alum|name=[[James Merritt]] |year=|nota=Former president of the [[Southern Baptist Convention]], current pastor and CEO of television show ''Touching Lives''|ref=}}
{{Alum|name=Gordon H. &quot;Nick&quot; Mueller|year=1961|nota=President and CEO, [[National World War II Museum]]|ref=}}
{{Alum|name=[[Joe Negron]] |year=|nota=Florida State Senator, District 28|ref=}}
{{Alum|name=[[Kevin Nicholson (baseball)|Kevin Nicholson]]|year=|nota=Former Major League Baseball player and 2004 Olympian|ref=}}
{{Alum|name=[[Gary Lee Noffke]]|year=|nota=American artist and silversmith|ref=}}
{{Alum|name=[[Scott Plakon]]|year=|nota=Florida State Representative, District 37|ref=}}
{{Alum|name=[[Jessica Rafalowski]]|year=|nota=[[Miss Florida USA]] 2008|ref=}}
{{Alum|name=[[Adrian Rogers]]|year=|nota=American pastor, conservative, author, and a three-term president of the [[Southern Baptist Convention]]|ref=}}
{{Alum|name=[[E. Clay Shaw, Jr.]]|year=|nota=Former U.S. Representative|ref=}}
{{Alum|name=[[Yevgeni Starikov]]|year=|nota=Soccer forward for [[FC Tom Tomsk]]|ref=}}
{{Alum|name=[[George Tsamis]]|year=|nota=Former Major League Baseball player, current manager of the St. Paul Saints|ref=}}
{{Alum|name=Wesley Whatley|year=2002|nota=Composer; creative manager for Macy's Thanksgiving Day Parade|ref=}}
{{Alum|name=[[Emmett Wilson]]|year=|nota=Former [[U.S. Representative]] from Florida|ref=}}
{{Alum|name=[[George Winston]]|year=|nota=New age recording artist|ref=}}
{{Alum|name=Michael H. Yeargan|year=1969|nota=Broadway set designer, winner of 2 [[Tony Award]]s|ref=}}
}}

==See also==
*''[[Ghost Story (film)|Ghost Story]]'', a feature film that was filmed on campus.
*[[Model United Nations]]
*[[Stetson University College of Law]]

==References==
{{reflist|2}}

==Additional reading==
{{cite book|title=Stetson University: The First 100 Years|last=Lycan|first=Gilbert L.|authorlink=|coauthors=|year=1983|publisher=Stetson University Press|location=DeLand, FL|isbn=|oclc=|page=|pages=|url=|accessdate=}}

==External links==
{{commons}}
*{{Official website|http://www.stetson.edu }}

{{Independent Colleges and Universities of Florida}}
{{Atlantic Sun Conference}}
{{Divison1floridacolleges}}

[[Category:Stetson University|*]]
[[Category:Universities and colleges in Florida]]
[[Category:Universities and colleges in Volusia County, Florida]]
[[Category:Educational institutions established in 1883]]
[[Category:Music schools in Florida]]
[[Category:National Association of Independent Colleges and Universities members]]
[[Category:Universities and colleges accredited by the Southern Association of Colleges and Schools]]

[[ja:ステッソン大学]]
[[simple:Stetson University]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
