<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="1706886" ns="0" title="Purkinje effect"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">[[File:Red geranium photoic mesopic scotopic.jpg|thumb|right|Simulated appearance of a red geranium and foliage in normal bright-light ([[photopic]]) vision, dusk ([[mesopic]]) vision, and night ([[scotopic]]) vision]]

The '''Purkinje effect''' (sometimes called the '''Purkinje shift''', or '''dark adaptation''' and named after the [[Czechs|Czech]] [[anatomist]] [[Jan Evangelista Purkyně]]) is the tendency for the peak [[luminance]] sensitivity of the [[human eye]] to shift toward the [[blue]] end of the [[color spectrum]] at low [[illumination (lighting)|illumination]] levels.&lt;ref name=&quot;frisby1980&quot;&gt;{{Cite book| author=Frisby JP | title=Seeing: Illusion, Brain and Mind | publisher=Oxford University Press : Oxford | year=1980}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;purkinje1825&quot;&gt;{{Cite book| author=Purkinje JE | title=Neue Beiträge zur Kenntniss des Sehens in Subjectiver Hinsicht | publisher=Reimer : Berlin | year=1825 | pages = 109–110}}&lt;/ref&gt;{{Page needed|date=September 2010}}

This effect introduces a difference in color [[contrast (vision)|contrast]] under different levels of illumination. For instance, in bright [[sunlight]], [[Pelargonium|geranium]] [[flower]]s appear bright red against the dull [[green]] of their [[leaf|leaves]], or adjacent blue flowers, but in the same scene viewed at [[dusk]], the contrast is reversed, with the red [[petal]]s appearing a dark red or black, and the leaves and blue petals appearing relatively bright.

The sensitivity to light in [[scotopic vision]] varies with wavelength, though the perception is essentially [[black-and-white]].  The Purkinje shift is the relation between the absorption maximum of [[rhodopsin]], reaching a maximum at about 500&amp;nbsp;nm, and that of the [[opsin]]s in the long-wavelength and medium-wavelength cones that dominate in [[photopic vision]], about 555&amp;nbsp;nm.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;Eye, human.&quot; ''[[Encyclopædia Britannica 2006 Ultimate Reference Suite DVD]]''&lt;/ref&gt;

In visual [[astronomy]], the Purkinje shift can affect visual estimates of [[variable star]]s when using comparison stars of different colors, especially if one of the [[star]]s is red.

==Physiology==
The effect occurs because the color-sensitive [[cone cell|cones]] in the [[retina]] are most sensitive to [[yellow]] light, whereas the [[rod cell|rods]], which are more light-sensitive (and thus more important in low light) but which do not distinguish colors, respond best to green-blue light.&lt;ref name=&quot;cornsweet1970&quot;&gt;{{Cite book| author=Cornsweet TN | title=Visual Perception | publisher=Academic Press : New York | year=1970 | pages = 145–148 | url = http://books.google.com/?id=4QJrAAAAMAAJ&amp;q=purkinje+intitle:visual+inauthor:cornsweet&amp;dq=purkinje+intitle:visual+inauthor:cornsweet | authorlink= Tom N. Cornsweet}}&lt;/ref&gt; This is why we become virtually color-blind under low levels of illumination, for instance [[moonlight]].

The Purkinje effect occurs at the transition between primary use of the [[Photopic vision|photopic]] (cone-based) and [[Scotopic vision|scotopic]] (rod-based) systems, that is, in the [[mesopic]] state: as intensity dims, the rods take over, and before color disappears completely, it shifts towards the rods' top sensitivity.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web| title = Human eye – anatomy | work = Britannica online | url = http://www.britannica.com/EBchecked/topic/1688997/human-eye |  quote = The Purkinje shift has an interesting psychophysical correlate; it may be observed, as evening draws on, that the luminosities of different colours of flowers in a garden change; the reds become much darker or black, while the blues become much brighter. What is happening is that, in this range of luminosities, called mesopic, both rods and cones are responding, and, as the rod responses become more pronounced – ''i.e.,'' as darkness increases – the rod luminosity scale prevails over that of the cones. }}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Use of red lights==
The insensitivity of rods to long-wavelength light is related to the use of red lights under certain special circumstances – for example, in the control rooms of submarines, in research laboratories, or during naked-eye astronomy.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book
 | title = Astronomy Hacks: Tips and Tools for Observing the Night Sky
 | author = Barbara Fritchman Thompson
 | publisher = O'Reilly
 | year = 2005
 | isbn = 9780596100605
 | pages = 82–86
 | url = http://books.google.com/?id=piwP9HXtpvUC&amp;pg=PA81&amp;dq=mesopic+color
 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

Under conditions where it is desirable to have both the photopic and scotopic systems active, red lights provide a solution.  Submarines are dimly lit to preserve the night vision of the crew members working there, but the control room must be lit to allow crew members to read instrument panels.  By using red lights, or wearing red goggles, the cones can receive enough light to provide photopic vision (namely the high-acuity vision required for reading).  Because the rods are not saturated by bright light and are not sensitive to long-wavelength red light, however, the crew member remains dark adapted, in case they need to look out the periscope at night, for example.&lt;ref&gt;
{{Cite journal
 | journal = Popular Science
 | author1 = Corporation, Bonnier
 | title = On the Prowl with Polaris
 | pages = 59–61
 |  url = http://books.google.com/?id=DSEDAAAAMBAJ&amp;pg=PA59&amp;dq=red-lights+goggles+submarine+night-vision
 | date = September 1962
 | volume = 181
 | issue = 3
 | issn = 0161-7370
}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Red lights are also often used in research settings.  Many research animals (such as rats and mice) have limited photopic vision -  as they have far fewer cone photoreceptors.&lt;ref&gt;
Jeon et al. (1998) J. Neurosci 18, 8936
&lt;/ref&gt;
By using red lights, the animal subjects remain &quot;in the dark&quot; (the active period for [[nocturnal]] animals), but the human researchers, who have one kind of cone that is sensitive to long wavelengths, are able to read instruments or perform procedures that would be impractical even with fully dark adapted (but low acuity) scotopic vision.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book
 | title = The mouse in biomedical research: Normative Biology, Husbandry, and Models
 | author = James G. Fox, Stephen W. Barthold, Muriel T. Davisson, and Christian E. Newcomer
 | publisher = Academic Press
 | year = 2007
 | isbn = 9780123694577
 | page = 291
 | url = http://books.google.com/?id=vnRpW-gI9JMC&amp;pg=RA2-PA291&amp;dq=red-lights+mice+dark-phase
 }}&lt;/ref&gt;
For the same reason, zoo displays of nocturnal animals often are illuminated with red light.

==History==
The effect was discovered in 1819 by [[Jan Evangelista Purkyně]]. Purkyně was a [[polymath]]&lt;ref name=wade/&gt; who would often meditate at dawn during long walks in the blossomed [[Bohemia]]n fields. Purkinje noticed that his favorite flowers appeared bright red on a sunny afternoon, while at dawn they looked very dark. He reasoned that the eye has not one but two systems adapted to see colors, one for bright overall light intensity, and the other for dusk and dawn.

Purkinje wrote in his ''Neue Beiträge:''&lt;ref name=wade&gt;{{Cite book| title = Purkinje's Vision | author = Nicholas J. Wade and Josef Brožek | publisher = Lawrence Erlbaum Associates | year = 2001 | page = 13 | isbn = 9780805836424 | url = http://books.google.com/?id=8wKFG4ntpqAC&amp;pg=PA13&amp;dq=purkinje+red+blue+yellow+green }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;As quoted in: {{Cite journal| journal = Psychological Monograph Supplements | volume = X | issue = 3 | author = Grace Maxwell Fernald | title = The Effect of Achromatic Conditions on the Color Phenomena of Peripheral Vision | publisher = Baltimore : The Review Publishing Company | year = 1909 | page = 9 | url = http://books.google.com/?id=8HoCAAAAYAAJ&amp;pg=RA2-PA9&amp;dq=purkinje+neue-beitrage}}&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;Objectiv hat der Grad der Beleuchtung grossen Einfluss auf die Intensität der Farbenqualität. Um sich davon recht lebendig zu überzeugen, nehme man vor Anbruch des Tages, wo es eben schwach zu dämmern beginnt, die Farben vor sich. Anfangs sieht man nur schwarz und grau. Gerade die lebhaftesten Farben, das Roth und das Grün, erscheinen am schwärzesten. Das Gelb kann man von Rosenroth lange nicht Unterscheiden. Das Blau war mir zuerst bemerkbar. Die rothen Nüancen, die sonst beim Tageslichte am hellsten brennen, nämlich carmen, zinnobar und orange zeigen sich lange am dunkelsten, durchaus nicht in Verhältnisse ihrer mittleren Helligkeit. Das Grün erscheint mehr bläulich, und seine gelbe Tinte entwickelt sich erst mit zunehmenden Tage.&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;Objectively, the degree of illumination has a great influence on the intensity of color quality.  In order to prove this most vividly, take some colors before daybreak, when it begins slowly to get lighter.  Initially one sees only black and grey.  Particularly the brightest colors, red and green, appear darkest.  Yellow cannot be distinguished from a rosy red.  Blue became noticeable to me first.  Nuances of red, which otherwise burn brightest in daylight, namely carmine, cinnabar and orange, show themselves as darkest for quite a while, in contrast to their average brightness.  Green appears more bluish to me, and its yellow tint develops with increasing daylight only.&lt;/blockquote&gt;

==See also==
* [[Kruithof curve]]
* Dark [[Adaptation (eye)|adaptation]]

==References==
&lt;references/&gt;

==External links==
* [http://www.visualillusion.net/Chap09/Page07.php  Color Optical Illusions, Purkinje Effect]

{{Appearance phenomena}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Purkinje Effect}}
[[Category:Color appearance phenomena]]
[[Category:Visual perception]]

[[de:Purkinje-Effekt]]
[[fr:Effet Purkinje]]
[[nl:Purkinje-effect]]
[[ja:プルキニェ現象]]
[[pl:Zjawisko Purkiniego]]
[[ru:Эффект Пуркинье]]
[[zh:薄暮現象]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
