<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="1709522" ns="0" title="TV3 (Malaysia)"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Infobox TV channel
| name              = TV3
| logofile          = TV3 (Malaysia).svg
| logosize          = 200px
| logoalt           = TV3 logo
| launch            = 1 June 1984
| picture format    = [[576i]] [[16:9]] ([[SDTV]])&lt;br&gt;[[1080i]] ([[HDTV]])
| share             = 48.5%
| share as of       = 1 January 2008
| owner             = [[Media Prima Berhad]]
| network           = [[New Straits Times Press]]
| country           = [[Malaysia]]
| broadcast area    = Nationwide, receivable in [[Singapore]] and [[Brunei]]
| headquarters      = Sri Pentas, [[Bandar Utama]], [[Petaling Jaya]], [[Selangor]]
| sister names      = [[ntv7|NTV7]]&lt;br/&gt;[[8TV (Malaysia)|8TV]]&lt;br/&gt;[[TV9 (Malaysia)|TV9]]
| web               = [http://www.tv3.com.my/ www.tv3.com.my]
| terr serv 1       = [[Analog television|Analogue]]
| terr chan 1       = Normally tuned to 3 on [[VHF]] and [[UHF]], [[VHF]] Channel 12, [[UHF]] Channel 29 ([[Kuala Lumpur]] and surrounding area)
| terr serv 2       = [[Digital television|Digital]]
| terr chan 2       = [[Digital Multimedia Broadcasting|DMB-T]], Band L (Damansara/[[Kuala Lumpur]] metro area only)
| sat serv 1        = [[Astro (Malaysian satellite television)|Astro]]&lt;br /&gt;&lt;small&gt;(Malaysia)&lt;small&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
| sat chan 1        = Channel 103
| adsl serv 1       = [[UniFi]]&lt;br /&gt;&lt;small&gt;(Malaysia)&lt;small&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
| adsl chan 1       = Channel 103
| slogan            = Berita Terkini Hiburan Sensasi (''First News Best Entertainment'')
}}

'''Sistem Televisyen Malaysia Berhad''' ('''STMB''') or '''TV3''' began broadcasting on 1 June 1984 as [[Malaysia]]’s first commercial [[television station]]. It is part of [[Media Prima Berhad]] group of companies. It now transmits opened broadcasting business private 24-hours a day, 7 days a week since 1 January 2010. Its television broadcasting stations and corporate headquarters centres are at [[Kuala Lumpur|Sri Pentas]], [[Bandar Utama|Persiaran Bandar Utama]], [[Petaling Jaya]].

==History==
TV3 officially began broadcasting  on 1 June 1984 at 18:00 [[Time in Malaysia|local time]], launched by then [[Prime Minister of Malaysia|Prime Minister]] [[Mahathir bin Mohamad|Tun Dr. Mahathir bin Mohamad]] and broadcasts from Kuala Lumpur. This broadcast area was only limited to [[Klang Valley]] area  during its early years.

On 28 July 1987, TV3 became the first commercial channel in collaboration with [[Radio Televisyen Malaysia|RTM]]  bringing Malaysians the live coverage of the [[1987 Southeast Asian Games|Jakarta Southeast Asian Games]]. The same thing was also done in [[1997 Southeast Asian Games|1997]] (failed, now [[Radio Televisyen Malaysia|RTM]] [[TV1 (Malaysia)|TV1]]) and [[2011 Southeast Asian Games|2011]] (passed, all matches now [[Radio Televisyen Malaysia|RTM]] [[TV1 (Malaysia)|TV1]]).

On 28 July 1984, TV3 became the first commercial channel in collaboration with RTM  bringing Malaysians the live coverage of the [[1984 Summer Olympics|Los Angeles Olympics]]. The same thing was also done in [[1988 Summer Olympics|1988]] and [[1992 Summer Olympics|1992]].

On 1 January 1985, TV3 launched its first [[teletext]] service known as ''[[Infonet|Beriteks]]''. In 1996 the service's name was changed to ''Infonet''. It was shut down on 1 January 2008.

On 1 January 1987, TV3 television audio stereo transmissions began in the West Coast of [[Peninsular Malaysia]]. It was the first channel in Malaysia to adopt stereo broadcasting. It transmits using the [[Zweikanalton]] stereo transmission system over TV3's UHF broadcast in the Klang Valley. Later in the 1990s, the stereo transmission was introduced into their VHF broadcast. TV3 was also experimenting with bilingual transmission over Zweikanalton for a short period of time in the 1990s.

Until late-2009, TV3 broadcasts for 19 hours a day, then 21 hours, and finally adopting 24-hour broadcasting on 31 December 2009.

==Features==
Ever since its launch, TV3 has been the leading television station in Malaysia and has twice reached 51% of audience share, the highest audience share ever achieved by a [[Malaysia|Malaysian]] television station. In terms of advertising revenue, the company retains its leadership position and continues to produce strong revenue growth from advertisements. TV3 continues to upgrade its equipment for production and transmission, and its employees receive continuous exposure and training in television production. This has enabled TV3 to remain as the premier private commercial broadcaster.

TV3, together with 8TV and local [[English language]] daily the '''[[New Straits Times]]''' and [[Malay language]] daily '''[[Berita Harian]]''' form the largest media group in Malaysia collectively known as [[Media Prima Berhad]]. It is currently headed by Ahmad Izham Omar.

With Malaysia on the track to economic recovery, there has been a correspondingly steady demand for local [[television program|programmes]], whether it be [[news]], [[Portal:current events|current affairs]], [[magazine]]s, [[talk show]]s, [[sports]], [[Documentary film|documentaries]], [[drama]]s or [[film]]s. With a strong base of television producers have revolutionized local content production to admiral levels in the broadcast industry. The station has been a trendsetter by producing quality local production and has caught the attention and loyalty of Malaysians. Believing in the precept that local content is the way to go, TV3 continues to invest in people and equipment to produce quality local content. However, the station also broadcast a balance of quality foreign content [[Film|movies]], dramas, situation comedy, documentaries and sports. The station has a strong market position and reinforces its brand awareness amongst its viewers through various on air and ground events.

TV3 currently broadcasts under [[UHF]] (Ultra High) Frequency, although it is also available in the Klang Valley under [[VHF]] (Very High) Frequency band III Channel 12 (TV3 initially started transmission in the Klang Valley on VHF Band III Channel 12). In the Klang Valley, the UHF channel is 29. It is widely seen as favouring the government and not giving enough coverage for the opposition. TV3 is also currently testing digital broadcasting, using the Chinese DMB-T/H system. The coverage is limited to Kuala Lumpur City area only, as opposed to both Radio Televisyen Malaysia's DVB and DMB signals which are available throughout the Klang Valley.

TV3 is also available over [[Astro (Malaysian satellite television)|Astro]] on Channel 103.

==Criticism and controversy==
TV3 has brought some controversies to the Malaysian entertainment sphere, especially with the excessive advertisement space which lead to the anger of the audience.

In [[Singapore]], the channel ran into controversy because it broadcast programmes in [[Standard Cantonese|Cantonese]]. The Singapore government has a policy to promote [[Mandarin Chinese]] in favour of other [[Chinese language]] dialects in broadcast media and has prevented local newspapers and magazines from carrying listings for the channel, even though these were available for the other Malaysian channels. TV3 was available on '''[[StarHub TV]]''' Singapore's only [[Cable television|cable TV]] operator, until it was removed in 1 January 2002.

On 1 January 2007 a reality television programme which broadcasted on TV3 called Sensasi was banned. This was because, one of the judges on this show touched on sensitive issues relating to [[Islam]]. The judge's comment made a huge controversy. All live and recorded telecast of this show were also banned from viewing. This also occurred on another reality television show called ''Teleskop'' on 1 January 1994.

==Trivia==
* TV3 was awarded the 1 January 2008 Asia Pacific Entrepreneurship Award for Responsible Entrepreneurship organized by [[Enterprise Asia]] for its significant contribution towards [[corporate social responsibility]].

* On 1 January 2008, TV3 began testing digital transmission. However they chose a different system, DMB-T/H, instead of the DVB-T system RTM uses. As such, viewers already owning a DVB-T receiver cannot pick up TV3's digital signal. The government has since moved to support both systems. However, DMB-T receivers remain scarce in Malaysia.

* TV3 is frequently mistaken as '''RTM TV3''' or '''Malaysia Televisyen Tiga'''.

==See also==
* [[List of Malaysian television stations]]
* [[TV9 (Malaysia)|TV9]]
* [[8TV (Malaysia)|8TV]]
* [[Ntv7]]
* [[Media Prima Berhad]]
* [[New Straits Times]]
* [[Berita Harian]]

==References==
&lt;references/&gt;

==External links==
*[http://www.tv3.com.my Official Site]
*[http://malaysiantv.blogspot.com/ Malaysian TV Listing Blog]

{{Template:Malaysia_tv}}
{{Media Prima}}
{{Programs}}

{{Use dmy dates|date=August 2010}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Tv3 (Malaysia)}}
[[Category:Media Prima]]
[[Category:Television stations in Malaysia]]
[[Category:Television channels and stations established in 1984]]

[[ak:TV3 (Malaysia)]]
[[id:TV3]]
[[ms:TV3]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
