<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="1709749" ns="0" title="Ntv7"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{pp-semi|small=yes}}
{{lowercase}}
{{Infobox Network |
network_name = Natseven TV Sdn Bhd&lt;br&gt;(NTV7)|
network_logo = [[File:thenewntv7 logo.jpg|150px]]|
country      = [[Malaysia]]|
broadcast_area = Glenmarie Industrial Park, [[Shah Alam]], [[Selangor]], [[Malaysia]]|
headquarters = Sri Pentas, Bandar Utama, [[Petaling Jaya]], [[Selangor]], [[Malaysia]]|
network_type = [[Terrestrial television|Private broadcast]] [[terrestrial television]]|
available    = National|
owner        = [[Media Prima Berhad]]|
key_people   = Airin Zainul (GM)|
launch_date  = 7 April 1998|
founder      = |
slogan       = Saluran Ceria Anda ''(Your Home Of Feel Good, 感觉美好)''
motto        = '''Menyediakan Kandungan unggul dan berkualiti untuk penonton setianya''' |
past_names = |
website      = [http://www.ntv7.com.my/ www.ntv7.com.my]|
}}

'''Natseven TV Sdn Bhd''' or better known as '''ntv7''' is a [[terrestrial television]] channel in [[Malaysia]]. It was launched nationwide on 7 April 1998 and was the country's third private free-to-air TV station after [[TV3 (Malaysia)|TV3]] and [[Astro (satellite TV)|Astro]]. Its mission is to promote a happier and more enlightened Malaysia. Believing strongly in the provision of wholesome [[entertainment]], good family and community values, good corporate citizenship, and the promotion of national integration, the station works on an appointment-based programming concept reflecting its philosophy of being '''Saluran Ceria Anda''' (&quot;''Your Home Of Feel Good''&quot;, “''感觉美好''“). 

== Background ==

As such, ntv7 is different from others in the Malaysian broadcasting industry in that it falls into the category of being a media brand rather than a [[television station]] (ironically Astro falls into the same category while balancing its role as the pay-TV provider). [[television program|Programmes]] are treated as products under relevant brands - more commonly referred to as programming belts, and are managed by a team of brand managers.

The appointment-based concept is also new to the Malaysian broadcasting industry, where factors, such as who watches what and when, define when a programme is slotted in the TV schedule. The station, which broadcasts on the UHF frequency band, offers a combination of [[Malay language|Malay]], [[English language|English]], and [[Chinese language|Chinese]] programmes, produced locally as well as some from overseas.

Offering a wide variety of programming, ntv7's line-up includes dramas, situational comedies ([[Situation comedy|sitcoms]]), entertainment programmes, [[game show]]s, children programmes, [[anime]], and [[Film|movies]]. In addition, there are also the station's news bulletins in Malay, English and Mandarin which aim to be independent and relevant at all times.

== History ==
After being in operation since 7 April 1998, ntv7 is proud of its achievement in building a strong following amongst Malaysian television audiences. So much so that the public's perception is that the station has been around for much longer than this. Broadcast signals go through a network of 10 transmitters dotted around the country. Daily transmission begins at 7:00 am until 1:00 am the next day. 

In October 2005, [[Media Prima Berhad]] announced its acquisition of ntv7. Media Prima also owns 3 other private TV stations in Malaysia - [[TV3 (Malaysia)|TV3]], [[8TV (Malaysia)|8TV]] and [[TV9 (Malaysia)|TV9]] as well as a controlling stake in [[New Straits Times|The New Straits Times Press (Malaysia) Bhd]]. 

The acquisition of ntv7 by Media Prima Berhad was completed on 30 December 2005 and repositioned the station as a preferred channel among the affluent urban family households. This was complemented by the introduction of a new vibrant logo in July 2006 that reaffirmed ntv7's aim to provide superior and quality content to its discerning viewers. ntv7 is targeted towards the urban and English speaking viewers. In 2009, ntv7's refreshing content of wholesome family, entertainment, current affair and sport programmes hit the right chord with the Chinese and Urban audiences 

ntv7 currently broadcasts under [[UHF]] (Ultra High) Frequency. A [[VHF]] (Very High) Frequency transmission is also available in the Klang Valley on Channel 7. In the [[Klang Valley]], the UHF channel is 37.

ntv7 is also available over [[Astro (satellite TV)|Astro]] on Channel 107.

==Criticism and controversy==
ntv7 has been criticized in the past for not taking certain programming seriously and even taking some programs off-the-air without letting it finish the season run. 

==Programmes==
{{see also|List of programmes broadcast by ntv7}}

;Daytime programmes

Weekdays
*Urban: Talk Shows
*The Breakfast Show
*Rachel Ray Show 
*Martha Stewart Show 
*Oprah Winfrey Show 
*Bella 
*Urban/Hong: Korean Drama  

;Hong Dramas

*Local Dramas 
*Hong Kong Dramas  
*FTV Taiwan Hokkien Dramas  
*SET TV Taiwan Hokkien Dramas 
*Singaporean Dramas

==Slogan==
Previous and current slogans of the channel are listed below in [[Malay language|Malay]], [[English language|English]] and [[Chinese language|Chinese]].&lt;br&gt;

'''Saluran Ceria Anda'''&lt;br /&gt;(1998-present)&lt;br&gt;
'''Your Feel Good Channel'''&lt;br /&gt;(2002-2010)&lt;br&gt;
'''Your Home Of Feel Good'''&lt;br /&gt;(2010-present)&lt;br&gt;
'''您的欢乐频道'''&lt;br /&gt;(2008-2010)&lt;br&gt;
'''感觉美好'''&lt;br /&gt;(2010-present)&lt;br&gt;

== See also ==
* [[List of Malaysian television stations]]
** [[8TV (Malaysia)|8TV]]
** [[RTM1]]
** [[RTM2]]
** [[TV3 (Malaysia)|TV3]]
** [[TV9 (Malaysia)|TV9]]
* [[Circle 7 logo]]

==External links==
* [http://www.ntv7.com.my Official Site]

{{Template:Malaysia_tv}}
{{Media Prima}}
{{Chinese language television in Southeast Asia}}
{{List of Astro Channels}}
{{ntv7local}}

[[Category:Television stations in Malaysia]]
[[Category:Television channels and stations established in 1998]]

[[id:Ntv7]]
[[ms:Ntv7]]
[[zh:Ntv7]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
