<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="17167963" ns="0" title="LOUD"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Notability|products|date=March 2009}}
{{Refimprove|date=March 2009}}
{{Infobox OS
| name                   = LOUD (LCSEE Optimized Ubuntu Distribution)
| logo                   =  [[Image:Loudlogo.png|175px|LOUD logo]]
| screenshot             = 
| caption                = 
| website                = [http://launchpad.net/loud-platform http://launchpad.net/loud-platform]
| developer              = West Virginia University Lane Department of Computer Science and Electrical Engineering
| family                 = [[Unix-like]]
| source_model           = [[Free and open source software]]
| released               = 
| latest_release_version = ljaunty
| latest_release_date    = {{release date and age|2009|07|01}}
| latest_test_version    = 
| latest_test_date       = 
| marketing_target       = 
| language               = English
| kernel_type            = Monolithic kernel
| ui                     = [[GNOME]]
| license                = Mainly the [[GNU GPL]] / Various others
| working_state          = current
| supported_platforms    = [[i386]]
| updatemodel            = 
| package_manager        = [[Synaptic Package Manager]]
}}

'''LOUD''' (LCSEE Optimized Ubuntu Distribution) is a modified version of the  [[Ubuntu (operating system)|Ubuntu]] Linux distribution used within [[West Virginia University]]'s computer science department. In addition to the standard Ubuntu packages, the department also maintains several packages containing software and scripts for use in the department's classes. 

LOUD also utilizes its own WVU-branded [[GNOME]] theme, wallpapers, and login manager.

== LOUD platform ==

One of the 2007-2008 as well as the 2008-2009, senior project groups developed a virtualized platform using the LOUD distribution. The goal of the LOUD Platform Project was to make it easy to run LOUD in a virtual machine. This allows users to install and use LOUD without disturbing the underlying operating system. LOUD Platform gives users a fully customized out of the box environment that mimics the exact setup used in the LCSEE computing labs. This group produced a complete proof-of-concept. Within the next couple of years, the department plans to provide all new students with a DVD containing the LOUD Platform.{{Citation needed|date=June 2010}}

LOUD Platform marks one of the first times that a university has attempted to make exactly the same environment used in the classroom and laboratories available to every student.

== History ==

LOUD started after a decision was made to give the LCSEE public and teaching computer labs an easily maintained standard development environment. The obvious choice for such an endeavor was to make the platform Linux based. This is because Linux is completely open source and totally customizable.

The first distribution of LOUD was called LOUD Version I Fully Automated Install (FAI). FAI was based on Debian and could be installed via imaging remotely that included software that met most class’s development needs. The next distribution was called Version II Hoary-LOUD. Hoary-LOUD was based on Hoary Hedgehog from the up and coming Linux distribution, Ubuntu. “Ubuntu is a predominantly desktop-oriented Linux distribution, based on Debian GNU/Linux but with a stronger focus on usability, regular releases, and ease of installation.” Ubuntu was primarily chosen because of its packaging system and emphasis on usability.{{Citation needed|date=March 2009}}

After Hoary-LOUD, LCSEE started trying to build and release LOUD regularly with distribution releases of Ubuntu. They adopted the policy of releasing LOUD versions that are based on Ubuntu distributions with Long Term Support (LTS). Since Hoary the naming scheme has changed and been finalized. There have been three releases since Hoary. Version III L-Dapper (based on Ubuntu’s release of Dapper Drake) and Version IV L-Fiesty (based on Ubuntu’s release of Fiesty Fawn). The LOUD Platform Project completed version V, L-Gutsy, and the LCSEE Systems Staff is currently working on version VI, L-Hardy.

== Awards ==

* Winner, Best Presentation (WVU Senior Design Expo 2008)
* Tie, Closest to Ideal (WVU Senior Design Expo 2008)
* Tie, Most Professional (WVU Senior Design Expo 2008)
* Tie, Most Complete (WVU Senior Design Expo 2008)

== See also ==
*[[Ubuntu (operating system)|Ubuntu]]

== References ==

&lt;references/&gt;

== External links ==
*[http://launchpad.net/loud-platform LOUD official website]
*[https://blueprints.launchpad.net/loud-platform/ LOUD Whitepages/Documentation]
*[http://loud.wvuopensource.org LOUD development portal]

{{Ubuntu-distro}}
{{Linux-distro}}

[[Category:Ubuntu (operating system) derivatives]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
