<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="17163934" ns="0" title="List of minor recurring characters in Star Trek: The Next Generation"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Cleanup|date=August 2009}}
{{In-universe|subject=Star Trek|category=Star Trek|date=October 2009}}
This is a list of minor characters from the [[science fiction]] television series '''''[[Star Trek: The Next Generation]]'''''. Characters are ordered alphabetically by family name, and only characters who played a significant recurring role in the series are listed.

{{TOC left}}

==Jack Crusher==
{{Infobox Star Trek character|if=
|bgcolor     = #ccccff
|Title       =Jack Crusher
|Image       = 
|Caption     = 
|Species     = [[Human]]
|Gender      = male
|Planet      = [[Earth]]
|Affiliation = [[United Federation of Planets]]&lt;br/&gt;[[Starfleet]]
|Posting     = [[USS Stargazer]]
|Rank        = [[Lieutenant commander (Star Trek)|Lieutenant commander]]
|portrayer   = [[Family (Star Trek: The Next Generation)|Doug Wert]]
}}
[[Lieutenant Commander]] '''Jack R. Crusher''', a [[fictional character|character]] in the [[Star Trek]] [[fictional universe]], is the late husband to [[Beverly Crusher]] and the father of [[Wesley Crusher]]. Throughout ''[[Star Trek: The Next Generation]]'', the character is played by actor [[Family (Star Trek: The Next Generation)|Doug Wert]].

Jack Crusher was the second officer (third in command) aboard the [[USS Stargazer|USS ''Stargazer'']], [[Jean-Luc Picard]]'s first command. He was killed while on a mission, which Picard blamed himself for and was troubled by it until he met Beverly Crusher when she first reported on the [[USS Enterprise (NCC-1701-D)|USS ''Enterprise'']]. Crusher assured Picard she had signed on the ''Enterprise''-D voluntarily and not due to Picard's influence.

The exact circumstances of Jack's death have never been made clear in official Trek canon.

Jack Crusher once made a [[holography|holographic]] recording of himself, where he explained his life and recent happenings to his son Wesley shortly after his birth. Jack originally intended this to be the first in a series of messages, one every couple of years, but due to a twist of fate, this was the only recording he ever got a chance to make. By the time Wesley first got to view the recording, Jack was already long dead.

===Appearances===
While he is mentioned in several episodes throughout the series, [[Lieutenant Commander]] Crusher appears in the following ''Star Trek: The Next Generation'' [[List of Star Trek: TNG episodes|episodes]]:
* &quot;[[Family (TNG episode)|Family]]&quot;, episode # 402
* &quot;[[Violations (TNG episode)|Violations]]&quot;, episode # 512
* &quot;[[Journey's End (TNG episode)|Journey's End]]&quot;, episode # 720

===External links===
{{memoryalpha|Jack Crusher}}
*[http://www.startrek.com/startrek/view/library/character/bio/1119493.html  Startrek.com biography]
*{{imdb name|id=0921582|name=Doug Wert}}

{{-}}

==Guinan==
{{Infobox Star Trek character|if=|Title = Guinan
|bgcolor     = #ddddff
|Image       =  
|Caption     = Guinan in Ten Forward on the Enterprise-D
|Species     = [[El Aurian|El-Aurian]]
|Gender      = [[Female]]
|Planet      = [[El-Auria (Star Trek)|El Auria]]
|Posting = [[USS Enterprise (NCC-1701-D)|USS ''Enterprise'']]-D [[Ten-Forward]] bartender
|portrayer   = [[Whoopi Goldberg]]
}}

'''Guinan''', played by [[Whoopi Goldberg]], is a [[recurring character]] on ''[[Star Trek: The Next Generation]]''. She also appears in the TNG films ''[[Star Trek Generations]]'' and ''[[Star Trek Nemesis]]'' but is uncredited in both.  

The character first appears in the second-season opening episode &quot;[[The Child (TNG episode)|The Child]]&quot;, and she appears several times over the course of the next 4 seasons; she does not appear at all in the seventh season. She is said to have the closest relationship with [[Jean-Luc Picard]], which is &quot;beyond friendship&quot; and &quot;beyond family&quot;.

===Casting===
{{Ref improve section|date=June 2009}}
According to Whoopi Goldberg, she approached the producers of ''TNG'' with her desire to be on the show, due to her childhood admiration of [[Uhura]], a character from the original ''[[Star Trek]]'', played by actress [[Nichelle Nichols]].&lt;ref name=&quot;25th&quot;&gt;{{cite video | people=Beck, Donald R. (Director) |date=1991| title=Star Trek: 25th Anniversary Special}}&lt;/ref&gt; At first they did not think a suitable role for such a highly rated actress could be created, until Goldberg said that she did not care how big or small the role was, even if she just swept the floor in the background. It was from this they decided to give her the role of a bartender.

===Overview===
Guinan is originally from [[El-Auria (Star Trek)|El-Auria]]. When she was a child, she had a Tarkassian razorbeast as an imaginary friend (&quot;[[Imaginary Friend (Star Trek: The Next Generation)|Imaginary Friend]]&quot;).

As a refugee aboard the El-Aurian vessel ''Lakul'', she is rescued from the [[The Nexus (Star Trek)|Nexus]] by the [[USS Enterprise (NCC-1701-B)|USS ''Enterprise''-B]]. Her people, the [[El-Aurians]], sometimes called &quot;listeners,&quot; had been scattered throughout the galaxy after the [[Borg (Star Trek)|Borg]] invaded their homeworld. The subsequent [[diaspora]] and reintegration of her people, and even their traditional clothing that Guinan still wears are interpreted as a reference to questions about race and colonization.&lt;ref&gt;Hastie, A. ''Fabricated Space: Assimilating the Individual on Star Trek: The Next Generation'' in ''Enterprise Zones: Critical Positions on Star Trek''. Eds. Harrison ''et al.'' (Westview Press: Boulder, 1996).&lt;/ref&gt;

Her species is long-lived, and she is somewhere between 500 and 700 years old when she joins the ''Enterprise''-D. &quot;[[Time's Arrow (TNG episode)|Time's Arrow, Part I]]&quot; reveals that she visited Earth in 1891, and &quot;[[Rascals (TNG episode)|Rascals]]&quot; establishes that her father was 700 years old during that episode.

Guinan reveals in ''[[Star Trek Nemesis]]'' that she has been married 23 times. She states in &quot;[[Evolution (TNG episode)|Evolution]]&quot; that she has many children, including a son who went through a phase when &quot;he wouldn't listen to anybody&quot; – something unusual &quot;in a species of listeners&quot;.

Her wise counsel occasionally proves to be quite valuable to the crew. In particular, she and Picard are especially close, to where they trust one another implicitly, although the full nature of their connection is never revealed. She does indicate that Picard stood by her at a time when she was in serious trouble and that their relationship is &quot;beyond friendship, beyond family&quot; (&quot;[[The Best of Both Worlds (Star Trek: The Next Generation)|Best of Both Worlds, Part 2]]&quot;). Also, she reveals that one of the first things she notices in men are their heads, having a fondness for bald men.

While by no means hostile or belligerent, she keeps an energy rifle of alien design (which she claims to have acquired on Magus III) behind the bar in Ten-Forward, which she used in the episode &quot;[[Night Terrors (Star Trek: The Next Generation)|Night Terrors]]&quot; to quell a rowdy bar brawl. She also has exceptional aim, as seen when she was able almost effortlessly to out-shoot Worf during a target practice session in the episode &quot;[[Redemption (Star Trek: The Next Generation)|Redemption]]&quot;.

In &quot;[[Yesterday's Enterprise (TNG episode)|Yesterday's Enterprise]],&quot; which involves the timeline being altered, Guinan is able to [[List of superhuman features and abilities in fiction#Cross-dimensional awareness|sense the disruption]], even though everyone else believes it is the natural course of events – in the ''Generations'' novelization, it is heavily implied that her unusual abilities regarding the flow of time might be related to her connection to the Nexus.

In &quot;[[Q Who? (TNG episode)|Q Who?]],&quot; [[Q (Star Trek)|Q]] retorts, after hearing her called &quot;Guinan&quot; in the Enterprise-D's Ten-Forward lounge, &quot;'Guinan' – is that your name now?&quot;  He claims that Guinan, &quot;is not what she appears to be.&quot;  As well, when Q reaches out his hand towards Guinan and offers to Picard her extradition from the Enterprise, Guinan holds her two hands up at Q in a threatening manner, perhaps suggesting she may have some hidden powers she has not displayed openly. Of course, as Picard suggested, Q may only be speaking of himself, since Guinan has been nothing but a courteous bartender and a valued friend to the ''Enterprise'' crew.

===External links===
{{memoryalpha|Guinan}}
*[http://www.startrek.com/startrek/view/library/character/bio/1112466.html Startrek.com biography]

{{-}}

==Kurn==
{{In-universe|subject=Star Trek|category=Star Trek|date=October 2009}}
{{Infobox Star Trek character|if=|Title = Kurn
|bgcolor     = #ff0000
|Caption     = 
|Species     = [[Klingon]]
|Gender      = [[Male]]
|Planet      = [[Qo'noS]]
|Posting = [[USS Enterprise (NCC-1701-D)|USS ''Enterprise''-D]] executive officer (temporary)&lt;br /&gt;IKS ''Hegh'ta'' commanding officer&lt;br /&gt;Klingon High Council&lt;br /&gt;[[Deep Space Nine (space station)|Deep Space Nine]] security officer (temporary)
|Affiliation = [[Klingon|Klingon Empire]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Bajoran|Bajoran Militia]] (temporary)
|portrayer   = [[Tony Todd]]
}}

'''Kurn''', played by [[Tony Todd]], is [[Worf]]'s brother and a Commander in the Klingon Defense Force in ''[[Star Trek: The Next Generation]]'' and ''[[Star Trek: Deep Space Nine]]''.

===Officer exchange===
Commander Kurn is introduced in the episode &quot;[[Sins of the Father (TNG episode)|Sins of the Father]]&quot;, where, as part of an officer exchange program, he is posted to the ''Enterprise'' (in exchange for [[William Riker|Riker]]'s earlier placement on a Klingon ship, depicted in &quot;[[A Matter of Honor (TNG episode)|A Matter of Honor]]&quot;).  Kurn specifically requested the ''Enterprise'', and was assigned on a temporary basis as a first officer.  Kurn did this so that he could observe Worf closely.  Eventually, he revealed that he was Worf's younger brother.

He told Worf it was decided that he did not need to go to [[Khitomer]]. Worf had always thought that his entire family had died there. The Starfleet officer who rescued Worf had been told by the Klingon government that he had no living relatives. But Kurn was taken in by his father's closest friend, Lorgh, and raised as his son. At the age of ascension, Kurn was informed of his true bloodlines.

Kurn also informed Worf that the council had judged Mogh and his family to be traitors, that Mogh had betrayed Khitomer to the Romulans. The ''Enterprise'' went to [[Qo'noS]] so that Worf could challenge the accusation. Duras, the son of Mogh's greatest rival Ja'rod, led the prosecution of Worf. Duras tried to have Kurn assassinated, but Kurn was rescued by the Enterprise personnel, and made a full recovery. The Enterprise crew soon discovered that it was truly Ja'rod who collaborated with the Romulans. But [[K'mpec]] refused to clear Mogh, and was prepared to execute Worf. Worf agreed to accept [[discommendation]] on the condition that Kurn's true bloodlines be kept secret, and that he be allowed to continue to serve.

===Gowron's ascension===
Worf met with Kurn again right before the Klingon Civil War, in the two-part episode &quot;[[Redemption (TNG episode)|Redemption]]&quot;. By this time, Kurn was a captain, and had his own vessel. When the two brothers saved Gowron's life, Gowron returned to Worf his honor and that of his family.  Both brothers served with distinction in the war.

After the Klingon Civil War, Kurn became a member of the [[Klingon High Council]]. He served in this position until the breakdown in relations between the Klingons and the Federation following the Klingon invasion of Cardassian space. When Worf refused to join Gowron, Gowron cast him out of Klingon society. When that happened, Kurn was forced from his seat on the council. Kurn became concerned over the future of the family since he had no male heirs, which made Worf's son Alexander the next leader of the house. Kurn was worried that Alexander would not be ready to lead the house when the time came.

===Deep Space Nine===
Kurn next appears in the ''Deep Space Nine'' episode &quot;[[Sons of Mogh (DS9 episode)|Sons of Mogh]]&quot;.

After being forced from the council, Kurn found that he had lost the will to live.  Kurn then went to [[Deep Space Nine (space station)|Deep Space Nine]], to ask his brother to kill him in order to restore his honor. Worf tried to fulfill Kurn's request, but was stopped by [[Jadzia Dax]] and [[Odo (Star Trek)|Odo]]. Captain Sisko was furious over this, and forbade Worf from taking Kurn's life. Worf was then forced to try to get Kurn to regain his will to live. Odo agreed to make Kurn a member of the station security force. Kurn soon discovered a visitor was smuggling illegal items, the smuggler raised his gun at Kurn. In a twist of [[suicide by cop]], despite having the ability to easily disarm the criminal, Kurn did nothing, and allowed himself to be shot. Because a man with a death wish was a danger to himself and everyone else, Odo dismissed him from the security force. At about the same time, the Klingons were discovered attempting to mine the Bajoran system. Worf recruited Kurn to go onto a Klingon ship docked at the station, and they were able to uncover information about the mining program.

Realizing that his brother would never recover from his losses, Worf allowed Dr. [[Julian Bashir]] to erase most of Kurn's memory. The procedure was a success, Kurn remembered nothing of his past life when he woke up. Worf contacted an old family friend, Noggra, who agreed to take Kurn in as his son. Noggra told Kurn that he had suffered an accident that erased most of his memory, and that his name is '''Rodek'''.

A subsequent non-canon novel series (''[[I.K.S. Gorkon]]'') shows Kurn, in his new identity, continuing to serve the Klingon Empire on a ship named for Chancellor Gorkon.

===External links===
{{memoryalpha|Kurn}}

{{-}}

==Lore==
{{Infobox Star Trek character|if=|Title = Lore
|Image       = 
|Caption     = 
|bgcolor     = #ececec
|Species     = [[Android (robot)|Android]]
|Gender      = [[Male]]
|Planet      = [[Omicron Theta]]
|portrayer   = [[Brent Spiner]]
}}

'''Lore''' (played by [[Brent Spiner]]) is a prototype android and the brother of main character [[Data (Star Trek)|Data]] and of [[B-4 (Star Trek)|B-4]]. However, while Data is virtuous and B-4 is primitive, Lore is sophisticated, clever, jealous and self-serving, making him the [[evil twin]] brother of the group.

Lore was introduced in the episode &quot;[[Datalore]]&quot;, the episode in which he was activated. He returned in &quot;[[Brothers (TNG episode)|Brothers]]&quot; and in both parts of &quot;[[Descent (Star Trek: The Next Generation)|Descent]]&quot;, at the end of which he was deactivated and dismantled permanently.

===Overview===
Lore was constructed and activated before his brother, Data, on [[Omicron Theta]]. Unlike Data, Lore was programmed with emotions but became emotionally unstable and developed megalomaniac tendencies. Lore perceived himself as superior to the human colonists and felt that they resented him due to his perceived superiority. His &quot;father&quot;, Dr. [[Noonien Soong]] would later deactivate and disassemble Lore and construct a &quot;less-perfect android&quot; - Data - without emotions or the capacity to use linguistic contractions. Soong planned on repairing Lore after building and testing Data, but before he could do that the colony was destroyed by the [[Crystalline Entity]] and Soong was forced to flee. Unknown to Soong or the colonists at the time, it was Lore himself who had contacted and attracted the Crystalline Entity to the colony to destroy it.

Lore's body parts were discovered in Soong's lab in the episode &quot;Datalore&quot;, and he was rebuilt and reactivated. Although Lore initially appeared as inquisitive and harmless as Data, his true nature was gradually revealed during the episode. Lore secretly contacts the Crystalline Entity again, offering it the crew of the [[USS Enterprise (NCC-1701-D)|USS ''Enterprise'']] as sustenance. However, Data foils his plans and transports Lore into space before the Crystalline Entity can attack, saving the ship.

In the episode &quot;[[Brothers (Star Trek: The Next Generation)|Brothers]]&quot;, Soong summons Data to Terlina III in order to give him an emotion chip. However, the same signal summons Lore, who had been found drifting in space and rescued by a group of [[Pakleds]]. Lore incapacitates Data and poses as him while Soong installs the chip. He then fatally wounds Soong before fleeing.

In &quot;[[Descent (Star Trek: The Next Generation)|Descent, Part II]]&quot;, Lore revealed that he later encountered a group of [[Borg (Star Trek)|Borg]] struggling with individuality following the ''Enterprise'' crew's actions in &quot;[[I, Borg]]&quot;, and became their leader. Lore uses Soong's emotion chip to control Data until [[Geordi La Forge]], [[Jean-Luc Picard]] and [[Deanna Troi]] manage to reactivate Data's ethical programming. Data shoots Lore at the end of the episode and then deactivates him permanently (retrieving his emotion chip afterwards). His final words to Data are ''&quot;I love you... brother.&quot;''

===Filming===
Brent Spiner played Lore (and also Soong), except in some instances where a shooting double was necessary. In one scene in &quot;Datalore&quot;, Lore puts down a glass of champagne that Data then picks up. This was achieved by the use of a moving [[split screen (film)|split screen]].{{Citation needed|date=August 2008}}

===External links===
{{memoryalpha|Lore}}

{{-}}

==Lursa and B'Etor{{anchor|Duras sisters}}==
{{Infobox Star Trek character|if=|Title = Duras sisters
|bgcolor     = #ececec
|Image       = 
|Caption     = 
|Species     = [[Klingon]]
|Gender      = female
|Planet      = [[Klingon#Homeworld|Qo'noS]]
|portrayer   = ''Lursa'' - [[Barbara March]]&lt;br&gt;''B'Etor'' - [[Gwynyth Walsh]]
}}
The [[Klingon]] sisters '''Lursa''' (played by [[Barbara March]]) and '''B'Etor''' (played by [[Gwynyth Walsh]]) are collectively known as the '''Duras sisters''', first appearing in ''TNG''&lt;nowiki&gt;'s&lt;/nowiki&gt; &quot;[[Redemption (Star Trek: The Next Generation)|Redemption, Part I]].&quot; The pair are daughters of [[Ja'rod]] and sisters of [[Duras, son of Ja'rod|Duras]]. Like the other members of the House of Duras, they are villains; throughout their appearances, the characters attempt to destabilize the Klingon High Council and its relations with the [[United Federation of Planets]]. 
In ''[[Star Trek: Deep Space Nine]]'s'' &quot;[[Past Prologue]]&quot;, Lursa and B'Etor work with a [[Bajoran]] terrorist. Lursa is pregnant in &quot;[[Firstborn (Star Trek: The Next Generation)|Firstborn]]&quot;, but the child's fate is not told. 

In the film ''[[Star Trek Generations]]'', the sisters align with Dr. Tolian Soran and attack the [[USS Enterprise (NCC-1701-D)|USS ''Enterprise''-D]].  After capturing Chief Engineer Geordi La Forge and placing a surveillance device inside his VISOR, they are able to exploit the Enterprise's defenses and severely damage the ship, leading to the destruction of the ship's stardrive section and crash-landing of the saucer section, but they are killed in the battle.

They are known among &quot;Star Trek&quot; fans for their distinctive costumes, which include holes in their armor to display their cleavage.

===Appearances===
;''Star Trek: The Next Generation''
*&quot;[[Redemption (Star Trek: The Next Generation)|Redemption, Parts 1 and 2]]&quot;
*&quot;[[Firstborn (Star Trek: The Next Generation)|Firstborn]]&quot;
;''Star Trek: Deep Space Nine''
*&quot;[[Past Prologue]]&quot;
;Feature Films
*&quot;''[[Star Trek Generations]]''&quot;

===External links===
* [http://www.startrek.com/startrek/view/features/documentaries/article/3563.html The House of Duras Timeline] at the official site StarTrek.com
* [http://www.startrek.com/startrek/view/library/character/bio/1071402.html Lursa] and [http://www.startrek.com/startrek/view/library/character/bio/1071383.html B'Etor] biographies at StarTrek.com
* [http://memory-alpha.org/wiki/Lursa Lursa] and [http://memory-alpha.org/wiki/B'Etor B'Etor] at Memory Alpha, a Star Trek Wiki

{{-}}

==Alyssa Ogawa==
{{Infobox Star Trek character|if=|Title = Alyssa Ogawa
|bgcolor     = #ccccff
|Image       = |
|Caption     = Nurse Alyssa Ogawa
|Species     = [[Human]]
|Gender      = [[Female]]
|Planet      = [[Earth]]
|Affiliation = [[United Federation of Planets]]&lt;br/&gt;[[Starfleet]]
|Posting     = [[USS Enterprise (NCC-1701-D)|USS ''Enterprise''-D]] nurse&lt;br /&gt;[[USS Enterprise (NCC-1701-E)|USS ''Enterprise''-E]] nurse
|Rank        = [[Ensign (Star Trek)|Ensign]]&lt;br&gt;[[Lieutenant junior grade (Star Trek)|Lieutenant junior grade]]
|portrayer   = [[Patti Yasutake]]
}}

'''Alyssa Ogawa''', played by [[Patti Yasutake]], is a character in the fictional [[Star Trek]] universe. The character appears in ''[[Star Trek: The Next Generation]]'' and the film ''[[Star Trek Generations]]'' as a nurse aboard the [[USS Enterprise (NCC-1701-D)|USS ''Enterprise''-D]] and in ''[[Star Trek: First Contact]]'' as a nurse aboard the [[USS Enterprise (NCC-1701-E)|USS ''Enterprise''-E]].

She joins the USS ''Enterprise''-D in 2367 as an [[ensign (Star Trek)|ensign]] in the medical department. In 2370, upon recommendation of Dr. [[Beverly Crusher]], she is promoted to [[lieutenant junior grade (Star Trek)|lieutenant junior grade]] (''TNG'': &quot;[[Lower Decks (TNG episode)|Lower Decks]]&quot;). She marries [[Lieutenant (Star Trek)|Lieutenant]] Andrew Powell in that year. Shortly after she reveals she is pregnant, Ogawa reports to the senior staff when an injury incapacitates Crusher (''TNG'': &quot;[[Genesis (TNG episode)|Genesis]]&quot;).  She was still pregnant by the [[series finale]] (''TNG'': &quot;[[All Good Things...]]&quot;), and her baby's birth was never shown or referred to on television; while said finale depicted her losing her unborn baby due to the effects of an &quot;anti-time&quot; anomaly, this was part of an alternate timeline that Captain [[Jean-Luc Picard]] ultimately prevented from coming to pass.  In an alternate timeline in the episode 'Parallels', she makes a brief appearance as the ship's doctor with the apparent rank of Commander.

According to the non-[[canon (Star Trek)|canon]] ''[[Star Trek: Titan]]'' book series, Ogawa works in ''Titan''&lt;nowiki&gt;'&lt;/nowiki&gt;s sickbay. She married Andrew Powell on Enterprise D. Powell was killed at the Battle of Rigel during the Dominion war. Ogawa and her young son transferred to the USS Titan under command of Captain Riker to serve in the sickbay.

===Appearances===
Ogawa appears in seasons 4-7 of [[Star Trek: The Next Generation]] and the films [[Star Trek Generations]] and [[Star Trek: First Contact]].

===External links===
{{memoryalpha|Alyssa Ogawa}}

{{-}}

==Alexander Rozhenko==
{{Infobox Star Trek character|if=|Title = Alexander Rozhenko
|bgcolor     = #ccccff
|Image       =
|Caption     =
|Species     = Three-quarters [[Klingon]],&lt;br&gt;One-quarter [[Human]]
|Gender      = [[Male]]
|Father      = [[Worf]]
|Mother      = [[k'Ehleyr]]
|Planet      = [[Earth]]
|portrayer   = [[Jon Paul Steuer]]&lt;br&gt;[[Brian Bonsall]]&lt;br&gt;[[James Sloyan]]&lt;br&gt;[[Marc Worden]]
}}

'''Alexander Rozhenko''' is the son of Worf and Ambassador [[k'Ehleyr]]. He was conceived during the events of [[The Emissary (Star Trek: The Next Generation)|The Emissary]] and first introduced to his father during [[Reunion (Star Trek: The Next Generation)|Reunion]].  After the death of his mother, he was sent to live with Worf's adoptive parents, Sergey and Helena Rozhenko, until becoming a troublesome youth in need of his father.  He was reunited with Worf aboard the Enterprise until the end of the series at which time he returned to Earth.  He later joined the Klingon military in its battle against the Dominion where he ended up serving under his father, who was General Martok's XO aboard the ''IKS Rotarran''.

===Appearances===
;''Star Trek: The Next Generation''
* &quot;[[Reunion (Star Trek: The Next Generation)|Reunion]]&quot; - [[K'Ehleyr]] returns to the ''Enterprise'' with Alexander. K'Ehleyr dies, leaving Worf to look after Alexander (Worf later asks his human foster parents to look after his son)
* &quot;[[New Ground (Star Trek: The Next Generation)|New Ground]]&quot; - Worf has to quickly learn about parenting when Alexander arrives to join him on the Enterprise
* &quot;[[Ethics (Star Trek: The Next Generation)|Ethics]]&quot; - Worf suffers a broken back and Alexander must come to terms with facing his father's death
* &quot;[[Cost of Living (Star Trek: The Next Generation)|Cost of Living]]&quot; - [[Deanna Troi]]'s mother, [[Lwaxana Troi|Lwaxana]], arrives on the ''Enterprise'' and leads Alexander astray
* &quot;[[Imaginary Friend (Star Trek: The Next Generation)|Imaginary Friend]]&quot; - Alexander receives the blame when an (invisible) imaginary friend starts causing havoc
* &quot;[[Rascals (Star Trek: The Next Generation)|Rascals]]&quot; - When [[Captain Picard]] and some other crew members are turned into children, Alexander helps them re-take the ship from intruders
* &quot;[[A Fistful of Datas (Star Trek: The Next Generation)|A Fistful of Datas]]&quot; - Alexander, [[Worf]] and [[Deanna Troi]] take part in a [[Western (genre)|Western]] recreation on the holodeck
* &quot;[[Firstborn (Star Trek: The Next Generation)|Firstborn]]&quot; - Alexander's future self travels back in time to convince the young Alexander to embrace his Klingon warrior heritage

;''Star Trek: Deep Space Nine''
* &quot;[[Sons and Daughters (Star Trek: Deep Space Nine)|Sons and Daughters]]&quot; - An estranged Alexander is reunited with his father and they are initiated into the house of Martok.
* &quot;[[You are Cordially Invited... (Star Trek: Deep Space Nine)|You are Cordially Invited...]]&quot; - Alexander takes part in the wedding of his father, Worf, to [[Jadzia Dax]]


===External links===
{{memoryalpha|Alexander Rozhenko}}
*[http://www.startrek.com/startrek/view/library/characters/TNG/bio/1114489.html Alexander Rozhenko] Official Biography at [[StarTrek.com]]

{{-}}

==Lwaxana Troi==
{{Infobox Star Trek character|if=|Title = Lwaxana Troi
|bgcolor     = #ccccff
|Image       = 
|Caption     = 
|Species     = [[Betazoid]]
|Gender      = [[Female]]
|Planet      = [[Betazed]]
|portrayer   = [[Majel Barrett]]
}}

'''Lwaxana Troi''' (played by the late [[Majel Barrett-Roddenberry]], wife of Star Trek creator Gene Roddenberry) is Enterprise Counselor Deanna Troi's Betazoid mother. Her complete title is &quot;Lwaxana Troi, Daughter of the Fifth House, Holder of the Sacred Chalice of Rixx, Heir to the Holy Rings of Betazed&quot;. She always had romantic inclination towards Captain Jean-Luc Picard. Her interactions with Alexander Rozhenko suggest that she has an agreeable effect on young children.

Troi is the widow of [[Ian Andrew Troi]] and mother of [[Deanna Troi]]. Deanna often feels embarrassed by her mother's overbearing personality and garish fashion sense.

She serves as the [[Betazoid]] ambassador to the Federation. As a Betazoid, she possesses [[Telepathy (Star Trek)|telepathic]] abilities. She has visited the [[USS Enterprise (NCC-1701-D)|USS ''Enterprise-D'']] on several occasions. Her appearances often involve her search for a husband, fixing her sights at various times on a [[diplomatic minister]], an alien scientist forced to die by a mandatory cultural requirement, and Captain [[Jean-Luc Picard]].

Another plot line revolved around Deanna's older sister Kestra, who died in a childhood accident when Deanna was an infant. This also explains why Lwaxana refers to Deanna as, 'little one.' When Lwaxana becomes comatose, Deanna explores her mother's mind and discovers the memories of Kestra.

In addition to Deanna and Kestra, Lwaxana Troi also has a son whose father is a Tavnian named Jeyal. She briefly marries [[Odo (Star Trek)|Odo]] in order to void Jeyal's claim to the child.

===Appearances===
;''Star Trek: The Next Generation''
* &quot;[[Haven (TNG episode)|Haven]]&quot; - arrives to attend Deanna's wedding to Wyatt Miller, which ends up not happening
* &quot;[[Manhunt (TNG episode)|Manhunt]]&quot; - looks for new husband
* &quot;[[Ménage à Troi]]&quot; - kidnapped by a Ferengi
* &quot;[[Half a Life (TNG episode)|Half a Life]]&quot; - discovers a scientist she's developed feeling for is required to end his own life
* &quot;[[Cost of Living (TNG episode)|Cost of Living]]&quot; - deals with mid-life crisis; mentors Alexander Rozhenko
* &quot;[[Dark Page]]&quot; - falls into a coma; Deanna aids in her recovery and in the process, learns of her sister, Kestra and Kestra's death

;''Star Trek: Deep Space Nine''
* &quot;[[The Forsaken (DS9 episode)|The Forsaken]]&quot; - helps Odo deal with personal problems
* &quot;[[Fascination (DS9 episode)|Fascination]]&quot; - becomes involved in a Bajoran love festival
* &quot;[[The Muse (DS9 episode)|The Muse]]&quot; - marries Odo temporarily, to protect custody of her unborn son

===Mr. Homn===
In most of her ''Star Trek: The Next Generation'' appearances, Troi travels with her extremely tall manservant, Mr. Homn ([[Carel Struycken]]). In &quot;The Ceremony of Innocence is Drowned&quot;, part of the ''[[List of Star Trek novels|Tales of the Dominion War]]'' short story anthology, Homn is killed when the [[Jem'Hadar]] invade [[Betazed]]. Homn rarely ever spoke. His sole line of dialogue is in &quot;Haven&quot; where he says &quot;Thank you for the drinks.&quot;

===External links===
{{Memoryalpha|Lwaxana Troi}}
{{Memoryalpha|Homn|Mr. Homn}}

==References==
{{Reflist}}

==See also==
*[[List of Star Trek characters: A-F]]
*[[List of Star Trek characters: G-M]]
*[[List of Star Trek characters: N-S]]
*[[List of Star Trek characters: T-Z]]
*[[List of minor recurring characters in Star Trek: Deep Space Nine]]
*[[List of minor recurring characters in Star Trek: Enterprise]]
*[[List of minor recurring characters in Star Trek: The Original Series]]
*[[List of minor recurring characters in Star Trek: Voyager]]
*[[List of Star Trek episodes|List of ''Star Trek'' episodes]]

{{Star Trek recurring characters}}
{{Star Trek TNG}}
{{Star Trek}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:List Of Minor Recurring Characters In Star Trek: The Next Generation}}
[[Category:Lists of Star Trek characters|The Next Generation]]
[[Category:Star Trek: The Next Generation]]
[[Category:Lists of minor fictional characters|Star Trek The Next Generation]]

[[sv:Lista över rollfigurer i Star Trek]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
