<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="1721638" ns="0" title="Yukon College"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{primary sources|date=November 2010}}
{{Coord|60|45|1.20|N|135|5|55.49|W|display=title|type:edu}}
{{Infobox University
|name = '''Yukon College'''
|image = 
|type = Public [[community college]] 
|established = 1983
|chancellor = Rolf Hougen
|President = Terry Weninger
|campus = [[urban area|urban]] &amp; [[suburban]] bluff overlooking the river valley
|undergraduate = 1st &amp; 2nd year university transfer
|staff = 220 (est. July 2010)
|city = [[Whitehorse, Yukon|Whitehorse]]
|state = [[Yukon]]
|country = [[Canada]]
|colours = [[Blue (color)|blue]] {{color box|#072B61}} &amp; [[White (color)|White]]  {{color box|#FFFFFF}} 
|affiliations = [[University of the Arctic|UArctic]], [[Association of Canadian Community Colleges|ACCC]], [[Association of Canadian Universities for Northern Studies]], [[Canadian Colleges Athletic Association|CCAA]], [[British Columbia Council on Admissions and Transfer]], [[University of Regina]], [[University of British Columbia]], [[Canadian Bureau for International Education|CBIE]], [[University of Northern British Columbia]], [[University of Alaska Southeast]].
|website = http://www.yukoncollege.yk.ca/
}}

'''Yukon College''' is a [[community college]] in the [[Canada|Canadian]] territory of [[Yukon]].  Its main campus is in [[Whitehorse, Yukon]].  The college was founded in 1983, replacing the Yukon Vocational and Technical Training Centre, which had been in operation since the 1960s.  The chancellor is Rolf Hougen (term renewed July 2010).

==Overview==
Yukon College traces its history to the Yukon Vocational and Technical Training Centre founded in 1963. College status was granted in the spring of 1983 and since that time Yukon College has grown to include 13 campuses throughout the Yukon Territory.

Yukon College offers certificates, diplomas and degrees through 5 academic areas - the School of Access, School of Science, Trades and Technology, School of Health, Education and Human Services, School of Liberal Arts, and the School of Management, Tourism and Hospitality. The college also provides the first two years of university transfer and is a respected member of the BC Council on Admissions and Transfer.

This broad range of programming allows Yukoners to stay in the north while pursuing postsecondary studies. It also accommodates contract training demands by local industry and government in a range of specialties. Programming is delivered from campus to campus, across the Yukon, through video-conferencing and on-line learning technology. The President’s Committee on First Nation Initiatives with representatives from all fourteen Yukon First Nations, influences programming and services delivered at the college.

With respect to research and development, the College is leading the way as home to the Yukon Cold Climate Innovation Centre and the Northern Research Institute, conducting innovative research and development specific to Canada’s north.

Yukon College is an integral part of the community, social, cultural and economic life of Yukon.

==Campus==
[[Image:Panorama for the Yukon College Roof.jpg|right|thumb|Panorama from the Yukon College Roof]]
The Yukon College is located on a bluff overlooking the river valley and the mountains to the east of [[Whitehorse, Yukon]].  

Yukon College campuses include: Faro Campus, Whitehorse Correctional Centre Campus, Teslin Campus, Watson Lake Campus, Mayo Campus, Ross River Campus, Pelly Crossing Campus, Carmacks Campus, Haines Junction Campus, Carcross Campus, Old Crow Campus, Ayamdigut Campus (in Whitehorse) and Dawson City Community Campus. The Yukon Native Language Centre is housed at Yukon College's Ayamdigut Campus.

==Partnership==
The college participates in the [[University of the Arctic]] and cooperates with several universities to deliver degree programming.

==First Nation Initiatives==

The First Nation Initiatives department (FNI) is an arm of the President’s Office within Yukon College. It exists in order to focus on the partnerships with all Yukon First Nations in order to better serve Yukoners, with respect to programs and services offered at Yukon College. FNI works with all departments at Yukon College in order to encourage and support student success.

FNI is a voice within Yukon College that is dedicated to integrating an understanding and awareness of the culture, traditions, and history of Yukon First Nations. The development of programming and its associated curriculum is essential to development of education and training services that meet the needs of First Nations.

PACFNI
Under the umbrella of FNI is the President’s Advisory Committee on First Nation Initiatives (PACFNI), which continues to grow and develop with the support and participation from each First Nation. PACFNI, composed of educational representatives from each Yukon First Nation, plays an important role by assisting Yukon College in its goal to increase the effectiveness of programs and services offered, with the ultimate goal being the success of all Yukon College students.

PACFNI has a mission to provide strategic direction to Yukon College, specifically the Board of Governors’ and the senior executive council. This high profile committee plays an important role by assisting Yukon College with its goal to increase the effectiveness of programs and services, as well as helping to support Yukon First Nations build capacity and implement their final agreements. FNI aims to enhance the profile of First Nations by encouraging and supporting their involvement within the institution. Enhancing the role of First Nations and developing First Nation partnerships is a prime reason for the establishment and operation PACFNI and a main goal of the FNI department.

FNI will continue to focus on building relationships, crossing cultural boundaries, embracing differences, and increasing understanding between Yukon First Nations and Yukon College.

==See also==
{{portal|University of the Arctic}}
*[[List of colleges in Canada's Territories]]
*[[Higher education in Yukon]]

==References==

&lt;references/&gt;
All facts, unless otherwise stated, are from Yukon College's web site: 
[http://www.yukoncollege.yk.ca Yukon College]

==External links==
{{Commons}}
*[http://www.yukoncollege.yk.ca/ Yukon College Website]
{{Can-terr-colleges}}

[[Category:Colleges in the territories of Canada]]
[[Category:Education in Yukon|College]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
