<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="1721668" ns="0" title="Aurora College"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{distinguish2|[[Aurora University]], formerly known as Aurora College}}
{{for|the New Zealand high school|Aurora College (Invercargill)}}
{{Coord|68|21|33.00|N|133|43|5.55|W|display=title|type:edu}}

{{Infobox_University
|name            = '''Aurora College'''
|native_name     = 
|image_name      = Aurora College.jpg
|image_size      = 220px
|caption         =
|latin_name      = 
|motto           =
|tagline         = The future is now. It all starts here at Aurora College.
|established     = 1981 (as Thebacha College)  1984 (as Arctic College) 1995 (as Aurora College)
|type            = public college of arts and technology
|endowment       = 
|staff           = 200
|faculty         = 50
|president       = Sarah Wright-Cardinal
|provost         = 
|principal       = 
|rector          = 
|chancellor      = 
|vice_chancellor = 
|dean            = 
|head_label      = 
|head            = 
|students        = 
|undergrad       = available
|postgrad        = not available
|doctoral        = 
|profess         = 
|city            = Box 1290, 50 Conibear Crescent [[Fort Smith, Northwest Territories]]
|state           = serves [[Northwest Territories]], [[Saskatchewan]], [[Manitoba]]
|country         = [[Canada]] X0E 0P0 
|campus          = small, remote communities
|free_label      = 
|free            = 
|colours         = [[Blue (color)|blue]] {{color box|#072B61}} &amp; [[White (color)|White]]  {{color box|#FFFFFF}} 
|colors          = 
|mascot          = 
|fightsong       = 
|nickname        = 
|affiliations   = [[Association of Universities and Colleges of Canada|AUCC]], [[Canadian Colleges Athletic Association]], [[Association of Canadian Community Colleges]] [[International Association of Universities|IAU]], [[Canadian Interuniversity Sport|CIS]], [[University of the Arctic|UArctic]], [[Association of Commonwealth Universities|ACU]]
|footnotes       = 
|website         = [http://www.auroracollege.nt.ca www.auroracollege.nt.ca]
|address         = Aurora Campus #87 Gwich’in Road, Box 1008 Inuvik, NT X0E 0T0;  Thebacha Campus 50 Conibear Crescent, Box 600 Fort Smith, NT X0E 0P0;  Yellowknife Campus, 5004-54th Street, Northern United Place, Bag Service 9700 Yellowknife, NT X1A 2R3
|publictransit   = varies
|telephone       = 1-866-287-2655 (Aurora); 1-866-291-4866 (Yellowknife); 1-866-266-4966 (Thebacha)
|coor            = 
|logo            = 
}}

'''Aurora College''', formerly Arctic College, is a [[college]] in the [[Northwest Territories]], [[Canada]] with [[campus]]es in [[Inuvik, Northwest Territories|Inuvik]], [[Fort Smith, Northwest Territories|Fort Smith]] and [[Yellowknife, Northwest Territories|Yellowknife]]. They have learning centres in 23 communities in the NWT.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.auroracollege.nt.ca/pdf/AC_Calendar_09-10.pdf&lt;/ref&gt; The head office for Aurora College is located in Fort Smith.

==Mission==
*Aurora College is dedicated to excellence, leadership and innovation in Northern education and research. Aurora College focuses on Student Success and supports the development of our Northern society through excellence in education, training and research. Aurora College aims to be culturally sensitive and responsive to the people the institution serves. 

==Programs==
*Aurora College delivers programs at three Campuses, 31 Community Learning Centres and other community sites in the Northwest Territories. Aurora university delivers community-centred post-secondary programs that accurately reflect Northern culture and the needs of the Northern labour market. Aurora offers several certificate and diploma programs as well as the Bachelor of Education Degree Program and the Bachelor of Science in Nursing Program.

==Athletics==
*Aurora College provides intramural sports, such as basketball, volleyball, soccer, badminton and hockey and recreational programs. The Aurora College Campus gymnasium in Inuvik is the largest in the Northwest Territories. 

==Residence==
*Aurora College provides a limited supply of accommodation for single students and for those with families.

==Aurora College Community Learning Centres==
*The Aurora College administers Community Learning Centres in other communities depending on demand and funding. Affiliated with the Aurora Campus, Community Learning Centres are located in [[Aklavik]], [[Deline]], [[Fort Good Hope]], [[Fort McPherson]], [[Ulukhaktok, Northwest Territories|Holman]], [[Inuvik]], [[Norman Wells]], [[Paulatuk]], [[Sachs Harbour]], [[Tulita, Northwest Territories|Tulita]], [[Tuktoyaktuk]], [[Tsiigehtchic]], and [[Colville Lake, Northwest Territories|Colville Lake]]. Affiliated with the Thebacha Campus, Community Learning Centres are located in [[Fort Providence]], [[Fort Resolution]], [[Fort Simpson]], [[Hay River, Northwest Territories|Hay River]], [[Lutsel K’e]], [[Fort Liard]] and [[Hay River Reserve]]. Affiliated with the Yellowknife campus, Community Learning Centres are located in [[Behcho Ko]], [[Wha Ti]], [[Gameti]], [[Wekweti]], and [[Dettah]]/[[N'Dilo]].

==Partnerships==
[[File:Fort Providence Aurora College.jpg|thumb|Aurora College in Fort Providence]]
*Aurora programs prepare students for further education through university partners.

==History==
*Aurora College was created on January 1, 1995 in the Western Arctic from Arctic College. The Science Institute of the Northwest Territories was amalgamated with Aurora College in January, 1995. The portion which is a division of Aurora College is called the Aurora Research Institute. In 1984, Arctic college was established with campuses in Fort Smith and Iqaluit. The College grew to include campuses in each region of the Northwest Territories. The mandate was to deliver adult and post-secondary education. In 1981, the Adult Vocational Training Centre (AVTC) was declared a college and renamed Thebacha College. In the 1970s, the Adult Vocational Training Centre (AVTC) was established.  

==Research Institutes==
*The [[Aurora Research Institute]], a division of Aurora College, has three Research Centres since science must be accessible to people and relevant to their everyday lives. Aurora Research Institute is dedicated to the advancement of indigenous  knowledge and the joining of  indigenous knowledge with western science. Aurora Research Institute offers licensing and research assistance in the [[Northwest Territories]]. The institute provides logistical support in the form of laboratory facilities, office space, storage, accommodation and equipment rentals for visiting researchers and promotes science in northern schools.

==See also==
{{portal|University of the Arctic}}
*[[Higher education in Nunavut]]
*[[List of colleges in Canada's Territories]]

==References==
{{Reflist}}
All facts, unless otherwise stated, are from Aurora College's web site.

== External links ==
*[http://www.auroracollege.nt.ca Official website]

{{Commons category}}
{{Can-terr-colleges}}

[[Category:Colleges in the territories of Canada]]
[[Category:Education in the Northwest Territories]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
