<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><redirects><r from="Windows Stop Error" to="Blue Screen of Death" /></redirects><pages><page pageid="18909256" ns="0" title="Blue Screen of Death"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{refimprove|date=December 2010}}
{{original research|date=February 2011}}
[[File:Windows XP Blue Screen of Death (PAGE FAULT IN NONPAGED AREA).svg|thumb|Blue Screen of Death as seen in [[Windows NT]], [[Windows XP]], [[Windows Vista]], and [[Windows 7]]]]

The '''Blue Screen of Death''' (also known as '''BSoD''', '''Blue Screen''', or '''bluescreen'''), known officially as a '''Stop Error''' &lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://pcsupport.about.com/od/termsb/g/bsodbluescreen.htm |title=Blue Screen of Death (STOP Message) |publisher= |date= |accessdate=2011-07-20}}&lt;/ref&gt; or a [[bug check]], is the [[error screen]] displayed by the [[Microsoft Windows]] family of operating systems upon encountering a critical error, of a non-recoverable nature, that causes the system to [[Crash (computing)|crash]]. The term is named after the color of the screen generated by the error. In Unix-based operating systems, a similar term is [[kernel panic]].

Stop errors are hardware or driver related, causing the computer to stop responding in order to prevent damage to the hardware or data. In the later versions of Windows ([[Windows NT]] and later) the screen presents information for diagnostic purposes that was collected as the operating system performed a bug check.

== History ==
The term ''Blue Screen of Death'' originated during development of the IBM [[OS/2]] operating system at [[Lattice Inc]], the makers of early Windows and OS/2 [[compiler]]s.{{Citation needed|date=August 2010}} Developers encountered the error screen when bugs in the operating system's software (typically [[null pointer]]s) slipped through the net during beta testing. In feedback to [[IBM]], a company known informally as 'Big Blue', the developers humorously described the Stop screen as the 'Blue Screen of Death' in consequence of its color, of the association of that color with IBM, and of the finality of the error (which caused the computer to hang without any possibility of recovery, requiring a manual restart).{{Citation needed|date=June 2008}}

== Details ==
If configured to do so, the computer will perform a &quot;[[core dump]]&quot; and save all data in memory in raw form to a disk file (known as a &quot;dump file&quot;) for later retrieval, to assist in the analysis by an expert technician of the causes of the error.

Blue screens are typically caused by software errors in device drivers: in [[Windows NT|NT-based]] Windows systems by poorly-written [[device driver]]s, and in the [[Windows 9x]] family of operating systems by incompatible [[Dynamic-link library|DLL]] driver files or bugs in the software [[Kernel (computer science)|kernel]] of the operating system.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://myweb.tiscali.co.uk/bridip/recovery.htm#sectionC |title=SECTION C: ERROR MESSAGES |publisher= |date= |accessdate=2011-07-20}}&lt;/ref&gt; They can also be caused by physical hardware faults, such as faulty RAM [[memory (computers)|memory]] or power supplies, overheating of components, or hardware which is run beyond its specification limits (&quot;overclocking&quot;).

These errors have been present in all Windows-based operating systems since [[History of Microsoft Windows|Windows 3.1]]. [[OS/2]] suffered from the [[Black Screen of Death]] (also BSOD), and early builds of [[Windows Vista]] displayed a [[Red Screen of Death]] due to a [[boot loader]] error.

=== Windows 1.0 and 2.0 ===
[[File:Windows 1 0 crash.png|thumb|[[Windows 1.0]]]]
The earliest blue screen of death was encountered upon booting into [[Windows 1.0]], and subsequently [[Windows 2.0]], and consisted of seemingly &lt;!-- Note that nothing a computer does is truly random. --&gt;random data (&quot;mess&quot;) composed of [[code page 437]] symbols, presented against a blue background.{{Citation needed|date=August 2010}} When Windows 1.0 encountered any [[MS-DOS]] related critical system errors, it displayed a [[Black Screen of Death|black screen of death]] instead.{{Citation needed|date=February 2011}}

=== Windows 3.x, 95, 98, and ME ===
[[File:Windows 9X BSOD.png|thumb|Blue screen of death as seen in [[Windows 9x]]]]
The first blue screen that resembled an error screen was in the [[Windows 3.x]] series. Similar error screens appeared in [[Windows 95]], [[Windows 98]] and [[Windows ME]]. These presented an error message against an all-blue background, in 80-column 25-line text mode. The error screen was displayed when there was a critical startup error (such as accessing a hardware driver file that no longer existed), or in the case of some other serious fault such as an unhandled error occurring inside a [[VxD]] hardware driver file. The BSOD also occurred during system use if a device driver had to present a [[modal dialog]] to the user, such as where a removable disk was removed from the drive whilst a file was being read or written. 

During a demonstration of a beta version of Windows 98 by Microsoft's [[Bill Gates]], at [[COMDEX]] on April 20, 1998, a BSOD incident occurred in public. The computer crashed with a blue screen when his assistant (Chris Capossela, currently Microsoft's Chief Marketing Officer) connected a scanner to demonstrate Windows 98's support for [[Plug and Play]] devices. This brought applause from the crowd, and Gates replied after a pause: &quot;That must be... er... that must be why we're not shipping Windows 98 yet!&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web |url = http://www.techrepublic.com/blog/geekend/video-bill-gates-meet-the-blue-screen-of-death/623 |title = Video: Bill Gates, meet the Blue Screen of Death |work = [[TechRepublic]] |publisher = CBS Interactive |date = April 13, 2007 |accessdate = 12 November 2011 |first1 = Jay |last1 = Garmon }}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Windows NT ===
[[File:DeLaRue_ATM_Crash.jpg|thumb|left|Windows-based [[automatic teller machine]] displaying a stop error]]
[[File:BSoD in Windows 8.png|thumb|Blue screen of death in [[Windows 8]]]]
In [[Windows NT]]-based operating systems, the Stop error occurs when the [[kernel (computer science)|kernel]], or a driver running in [[kernel mode]], encounters any error from which it cannot recover. This is usually caused by an [[general protection fault|illegal operation]] being performed, where the only safe action the operating system can take is to restart the computer. As a result data may be lost, since the user is not given an opportunity to save any unsaved data to disk.&lt;ref name=&quot;BSOD-Technet&quot; /&gt;

The text on the error screen contains an error code along, four other codes whose meanings depend on the error code itself, and an error name. Depending on the error code, it may display the memory address at which the problem occurred, together with identifying details of the driver file loaded at that address. Under Windows NT and 2000, the second and third sections of the screen may list all the currently-loaded drivers and display all memory data (a &quot;stack dump&quot;), respectively. The driver information will list the disk address of the driver file, the file's creation date (as a [[Unix timestamp]]), and the name of the file.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book| author=Microsoft Corporation| title=Microsoft Windows NT Workstation Resource Kit| edition=1st edition| date=1996-10-29| publisher=[[Microsoft Press]]| location=Redmond, WA| id=ISBN 1-57231-343-9}}&lt;/ref&gt;

By default, Windows NT based systems create a [[memory dump]] file when a Stop error occurs. Depending on the operating system version, this can range from a 64&amp;nbsp;kB mini-dump to a complete dump of memory that saves the entire active contents of the [[RAM]]. The resulting file can thus be analyzed later. A kernel [[debugger]] software program may be used in order to obtain a [[call stack|stack]] trace (identifying certain memory information) to find the true cause of the error, as the on-screen information is limited and may conceal the true cause.

A Stop error can also be caused by a critical boot loader error, where the operating system is unable to start from the bootable drive due to the presence of an incorrect disk driver, a damaged [[file system]], or a similar problem. In such cases no memory dump is saved.

===Windows 8===
A new version of the error screen has been seen in the developer preview of [[Windows 8]], released in September 2011. Rather than displaying detailed technical information about the error, it simply displays a short explanation that system needs to restart, the technical name of the error and a sad [[emoticon]]. Also it contains a lighter shade of [[blue]] in the background. &lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|last=Opam|first=Kwame|title=Windows 8’s Blue Screen of Death Is Like a Sad Girl Texting You|url=http://gizmodo.com/5840136/windows-8s-blue-screen-of-death-is-like-a-sad-girl-texting-you|accessdate=13 October 2011|newspaper=[[Gizmodo]]|date=14 September 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;
{{Clear}}

== Meanings ==
The NT-style BSOD displays error codes that explain what just happened inside the kernel. The STOP error displays five error codes in the following general form:
&lt;blockquote&gt;STOP: 0x#### (0x####, 0x####, 0x####, 0x####) Error Name&lt;/blockquote&gt;

For example:&lt;ref name=&quot;BSOD-Technet&quot; /&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;STOP: 0x00000019 (0x00000000, 0xC00E0FF0, 0xFFFFEFD4, 0xC0000000) BAD_POOL_HEADER&lt;/blockquote&gt;

The first code represents a specific error, while the others are additional data whose meaning depends on the error code.&lt;ref name=&quot;BSOD-Technet&quot;&gt;{{cite web| url=http://technet.microsoft.com/en-us/library/cc750081.aspx#XSLTsection124121120120| title=Demystifying the 'Blue Screen of Death'| year=2011| publisher=Microsoft| last=| accessdate=6/30/11}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== See also ==
*[[Kernel panic]] - the equivalent on [[Unix-like]] systems
*[[Fatal system error]]
*[[Screen of death]]

== References ==
{{Reflist}}

== Further reading ==
{{Wikibooks|Transwiki:List of Windows bugcheck codes}}
{{Commons|BSoD|Blue Screen of Death}}
{{Refbegin}}
* {{cite web| url=http://msdn.microsoft.com/en-us/library/hh406232%28v=VS.85%29.aspx | title=Bug Checks (Blue Screens) Codes Reference |work = [[Microsoft Developer Network]] |publisher=Microsoft |date = 7 September 2011 |accessdate=25 October 2011}}
* {{cite news|last=Russinovich|first=Mark|authorlink=Mark Russinovich|title=A Bluescreen By Any Other Color|url=http://blogs.technet.com/b/markrussinovich/archive/2010/12/14/3374820.aspx|work=Mark's Blog||agency=[[Microsoft TechNet#Blogs|TechNet Blogs]] | publisher=Microsoft Corporation|accessdate=13 October 2011|date=14 December 2010}}
*{{cite web |title=Demystifying the ‘Blue Screen of Death’ |url=http://technet.microsoft.com/en-us/library/cc750081.aspx |work = Microsoft TechNet |publisher = Microsoft Corporation |accessdate = 9 November 2011}}
*{{cite web |title=FAT32 Hard Disk : Backup, Repair and Data Recovery |url=http://myweb.tiscali.co.uk/bridip/recovery.htm#sectionC |at = Section C: Error Messages |first1 = Stephen |last1 = Poppitt |date = 19 August 2011 |accessdate = 9 November 2011}}
*{{cite web |title = How To Fix a Blue Screen of Death |url=http://pcsupport.about.com/od/fixtheproblem/ht/stoperrors.htm |work =About.Com PC Support |publisher = About.com |first1 = Tim |last1 = Fisher |accessdate = 9 November 2011}}
*{{Cite web |first1 = Mark |last1 = Russinovich |authorlink1 = Mark Russinovich |title = BlueScreen Screen Saver v3.2 |url = http://technet.microsoft.com/en-us/sysinternals/bb897558 |date = November 1, 2006 | accessdate = 9 November 2011 |work = Microsoft TechNet |publisher = Microsoft Corporation}}
{{Refend}}

{{Screens of death}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Blue Screen Of Death}}
[[Category:Computer errors]]
[[Category:Windows administration]]
[[Category:Screens of death]]

[[ar:شاشة الموت الزرقاء]]
[[az:BSOD]]
[[bg:Син екран на смъртта]]
[[ca:Pantalla blava de la mort]]
[[cs:Modrá obrazovka smrti]]
[[da:Blå Skærm]]
[[de:Blue Screen (Fehlermeldung)]]
[[et:Sinine surmaekraan]]
[[el:Μπλε Οθόνη του Θανάτου]]
[[es:Pantalla azul de la muerte]]
[[fa:صفحه آبی مرگ]]
[[fr:Écran bleu de la mort]]
[[ko:블루스크린]]
[[id:Blue Screen of Death]]
[[it:Schermata blu d'errore]]
[[he:מסך המוות הכחול]]
[[hu:Kék halál]]
[[ms:Skrin biru mati]]
[[nl:Blue screen of death]]
[[ja:ブルースクリーン]]
[[pl:Blue Screen of Death]]
[[pt:Tela azul da morte]]
[[ro:Blue Screen of Death]]
[[ru:Синий экран смерти]]
[[simple:Stop error screen]]
[[sk:Modrá obrazovka smrti]]
[[sl:Modri zaslon]]
[[fi:BSoD]]
[[sv:Blåskärm]]
[[tl:Blue Screen of Death]]
[[th:จอฟ้ามรณะ]]
[[tr:Mavi ekran]]
[[uk:BSOD]]
[[zh:蓝屏死机]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
