<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="17345999" ns="0" title="Organic food"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">[[Image:pepperseggplants.jpg|right|thumb|200px|Organic vegetables at a farmers' market in Argentina]]

'''Organic foods''' are foods that are produced using methods that do not involve modern synthetic inputs such as synthetic [[pesticides]] and [[chemical fertilizers]], do not contain [[genetically modified organisms]], and are not processed using [[irradiation]], industrial solvents, or chemical [[food additives]].&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|editors=Allen, Gary J. &amp; Albala, Ken|title=The business of food: encyclopedia of the food and drink industries|publisher=ABC-CLIO|year=2007|isbn=9780313337253|page=288|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=gNzmOUyiFRAC&amp;pg=PA288}}&lt;/ref&gt;

For the vast majority of human history, agriculture can be described as organic; only during the 20th century was a large supply of new synthetic chemicals introduced to the food supply. The organic farming movement arose in the 1940s in response to the [[industrialization]] of [[agriculture]] known as the [[Green Revolution]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|author=Drinkwater, Laurie E.|chapter=Ecological Knowledge: Foundation for Sustainable Organic Agriculture|editor=Francis, Charles|title=Organic farming: the ecological system|publisher=ASA-CSSA-SSSA|year=2009|isbn=9780891181736|page=19|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=8HMfbQpNq60C&amp;pg=PA19}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The weight of the available scientific evidence has not shown a significant difference between organic and more conventionally grown food in terms of safety, nutritional value, or taste.

Organic food production is a heavily regulated industry, distinct from [[Kitchen garden|private gardening]]. Currently, the European Union, the United States, Canada, Japan and many other countries require producers to obtain [[Organic certification|special certification]] in order to market food as organic within their borders. In the context of these regulations, organic food is food made in a way that complies with organic standards set by national governments and international organizations. In the United States, organic production is a system that is managed in accordance with the Organic Foods Production Act (OFPA) of 1990 and regulations in Title 7, Part 205 of the Code of Federal Regulations to respond to site-specific conditions by integrating cultural, biological, and mechanical practices that foster cycling of resources, promote ecological balance, and conserve biodiversity.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.ams.usda.gov/AMSv1.0/nop&lt;/ref&gt; If livestock are involved, the livestock must be reared with regular access to pasture and without the routine use of antibiotics or [[Bovine somatotropin|growth hormones]].&lt;ref&gt;http://www.ams.usda.gov/AMSv1.0/getfile?dDocName=STELPRDC5082653&amp;acct=noprulemaking&lt;/ref&gt; In the United States, a food can be labelled as &quot;organic&quot; if it contains a minimum of 95% organic ingredients.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.ams.usda.gov/AMSv1.0/ams.fetchTemplateData.do?template=TemplateC&amp;navID=NationalOrganicProgram&amp;leftNav=NationalOrganicProgram&amp;page=NOPConsumers&amp;description=Consumers&amp;acct=nopgeninfo&lt;/ref&gt; In most countries, organic produce may not be genetically modified. It has been suggested that the application of [[nanotechnology]] to food and agriculture is a further technology that needs to be excluded from certified organic food.&lt;ref name=&quot;Paull&quot;&gt;Paull, J. &amp; Lyons, K. (2008) , [http://orgprints.org/13569/01/13569.pdf Nanotechnology: The Next Challenge for Organics], Journal of Organic Systems, 3(1) 3–22&lt;/ref&gt; The [[Soil Association]] (UK) has been the first organic certifier to implement a nano-exclusion.&lt;ref name=&quot;Paull&quot; /&gt;

==Meaning and origin of the term==
In 1939, [[Walter James, 4th Baron Northbourne|Lord Northbourne]] coined the term ''organic farming'' in his book ''Look to the Land'' (1940), out of his conception of &quot;the farm as organism,&quot; to describe a holistic, ecologically-balanced approach to farming—in contrast to what he called ''chemical farming'', which relied on &quot;imported fertility&quot; and &quot;cannot be self-sufficient nor an organic whole.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|author=John, Paull|title=The Farm as Organism: The Foundational Idea of Organic Agriculture|journal = Elementals: Journal of Bio-Dynamics Tasmania|volume=80|year=2006|pages=14–18|url=http://orgprints.org/10138/01/10138.pdf|format=PDF}}&lt;/ref&gt; This is different from the scientific use of the term &quot;organic,&quot; to refer to a [[organic compound|class of molecules that contain carbon]], especially those involved in the chemistry of life.  This class of molecules includes many chemicals that would not be used in organic farming.

==Identifying organic food==
[[Image:Organic mixed beans shoots.jpg|thumb|150px|right|Mixed organic [[sprouting|bean sprouts]]]]

* ''See also: [[Organic farming]] for information on the production of organic food.''

Processed organic food usually contains only organic ingredients. If non-organic ingredients are present, at least a certain percentage of the food's total plant and animal ingredients must be organic (95% in the United States,&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.ams.usda.gov/AMSv1.0/getfile?dDocName=STELDEV3004323&amp;acct=nopgeninfo Labeling: Preamble&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt; Canada, and Australia) and any non-organically produced ingredients are subject to various agricultural requirements. Foods claiming to be organic must be free of artificial [[food additives]], and are often processed with fewer artificial methods, materials and conditions, such as [[SmartFresh|chemical ripening]], [[food irradiation]], and [[genetically modified]] ingredients. Pesticides are allowed so long as they are not synthetic.

Early consumers interested in organic food would look for non-chemically treated, non-use of unapproved pesticides, fresh or minimally processed food. They mostly had to buy directly from growers: &quot;Know your farmer, know your food&quot; was the motto. Personal definitions of what constituted &quot;organic&quot; were developed through firsthand experience: by talking to farmers, seeing farm conditions, and farming activities. Small farms grew vegetables (and raised livestock) using [[organic farming]] practices, with or without certification, and the individual consumer monitored. As demand for organic foods continued to increase, high volume sales through mass outlets such as supermarkets rapidly replaced the direct farmer connection. Today there is no limit to organic farm sizes and many large corporate farms currently have an organic division. However, for supermarket consumers, food production is not easily observable, and product labeling, like &quot;certified organic&quot;, is relied on. Government regulations and third-party inspectors are looked to for assurance.

The [[United States Department of Agriculture|USDA]] carries out routine inspections of farms that produce USDA Organic labeled foods.&lt;ref&gt;Nestle, Marion. 2006. What to Eat. NY: North Point Press.&lt;/ref&gt; Of the 30 third party inspectors 15 of them have been placed under probation after an audit.{{Citation needed|date=June 2011}} On April 20, 2010, the Department of Agriculture said that it would begin enforcing rules requiring the spot testing of organically grown foods for traces of pesticides, after an auditor exposed major gaps in federal oversight of the organic food industry.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.organicconsumers.org/articles/article_20459.cfm&lt;/ref&gt;

===Legal definition===
[[Image:National Organic Program.jpg|thumb|200px|The [[National Organic Program]] (run by the USDA) is in charge of the legal definition of ''organic'' in the United States and does [[organic certification]].]]

{{Main|Organic certification}}

{{See also|List of countries with organic agriculture regulation}}

To be '''certified organic''', products must be grown and manufactured in a manner that adheres to standards set by the country they are sold in:

* Australia: [http://www.bfa.com.au/index.asp?Sec_ID=135 Australian Organic Standard] and [http://www.nasaa.com.au/steps1.html NASAA Organic Standard]
* Canada: [http://canadagazette.gc.ca/archives/p2/2006/2006-12-21-x6/html/extra-eng.html Canada Gazette, Government of Canada]
* European Union: [[EU-Eco-regulation]]
** Sweden: [http://www.krav.se/sv/System/Spraklankar/In-English/ KRAV]
** United Kingdom: [http://www.defra.gov.uk Department for Environment, Food and Rural Affairs (DEFRA)]
* Norway: [http://www.debio.no/ Debio Organic certification]
* India:  [http://www.apeda.com/organic/ NPOP, (National Program for Organic Production)]
* Japan: [http://www.maff.go.jp/soshiki/syokuhin/hinshitu/e_label/specificJAS-organic.htm JAS Standards]
* United States: [[National Organic Program|National Organic Program (NOP)]] Standards

==Environmental impact==
Several surveys and studies have attempted to examine and compare conventional and organic systems of farming. The general consensus across these surveys&lt;ref&gt;Stolze, M.; Piorr, A.; Häring, A.M. and Dabbert, S. (2000) Environmental impacts of organic farming in Europe. Organic Farming in Europe: Economics and Policy Vol. 6. Universität Hohenheim, Stuttgart-Hohenheim.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|last=Hansen|first=Birgitt|coauthors=Alrøe, H. J. &amp; Kristensen, E. S.|title=Approaches to assess the environmental impact of organic farming with particular regard to Denmark|journal = Agriculture, Ecosystems &amp; Environment| volume = 83|issue=1-2|pages = 11–26|month=  January | year=  2001| doi = 10.1016/S0167-8809(00)00257-7}}&lt;/ref&gt; is that organic farming is less damaging for the following reasons:
*Organic farms do not consume or release synthetic pesticides into the environment—some of which have the potential to harm soil, water and local terrestrial and aquatic wildlife.
* Organic farms are better than conventional farms at sustaining diverse ecosystems, ''i.e.'', populations of plants and insects, as well as animals.
* When calculated per unit area, organic farms use less energy and produce less waste, ''e.g.'', waste such as packaging materials for chemicals.

A 2003 investigation by the Department for Environment Food and Rural Affairs in the UK found, similar to other reports, that organic farming &quot;can produce positive environmental benefits&quot;, but that some of the benefits were decreased or lost when comparisons are made on &quot;the basis of unit production rather than area&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | author= Department for Environment Food and Rural Affairs | title= Assessment of the environmental impacts of organic farming | url=http://www.defra.gov.uk/foodfarm/growing/organic/policy/research/pdf/env-impacts2.pdf | accessdate=2009-09-29}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The environmental impact of pesticides as well as the impact to the health of farm workers are reasons given for purchasing organic food.{{Citation needed|date=June 2011}}

However,  critics of organic farming methods believe that the increased land needed to farm organic food could potentially destroy the rainforests and wipe out many ecosystems.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | author= Bob Goldberg | title= The Hypocrisy of Organic Farmers | work=AgBioWorld | url=http://www.agbioworld.org/biotech-info/articles/biotech-art/hypocrisy.html | accessdate=2007-10-10}}&lt;/ref&gt; &lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | author= Andrew Leonard | title= Save the rain forest -- boycott organic? | work=How The World Works | url=http://www.salon.com/tech/htww/2006/12/11/borlaug/ | accessdate=2007-10-10}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Yield===
One study found a 20% smaller yield from organic farms using 50% less fertilizer and 97% less pesticide.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | author=Mader, et al. | title=Soil Fertility and Biodiversity in Organic Farming | journal=Science | year=2002 | volume=296 | issue= 5573| pages=1694–1697 | url=http://www.sciencemag.org/cgi/content/full/296/5573/1694  | doi=10.1126/science.1071148 | pmid=12040197 | last2=Fliessbach | first2=A | last3=Dubois | first3=D | last4=Gunst | first4=L | last5=Fried | first5=P | last6=Niggli | first6=U}}&lt;/ref&gt;  Studies comparing yields have had mixed results.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | author=Welsh, Rick | title=Economics of Organic Grain and Soybean Production in the Midwestern United States | journal=Henry A. Wallace Institute for Alternative Agriculture | year=1999 | volume= | pages= | url=http://www.winrock.org/wallacecenter/documents/pspr13.pdf}}&lt;/ref&gt; Supporters claim that organically managed soil has a higher quality&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | author=Johnston, A. E. | title=Soil organic-matter, effects on soils and crops | journal=Soil Use Management | year=1986 | volume=2 | issue=3 | pages=97–105 | doi=10.1111/j.1475-2743.1986.tb00690.x}}&lt;/ref&gt; and higher water retention. This may help increase yields for organic farms in drought years.

One study from the Danish Environmental Protection Agency found that, area-for-area, organic farms of potatoes, sugar beet and seed grass produce as little as half the output of conventional farming.&lt;ref&gt;The Bichel Committee. 1999. Report from the main committee. Danish Environmental Protection Agency. Conclusions and recommendations of the Committee: 8.7.1 Total phase-out. Report not available in print but posted online at: http://www.mst.dk/udgiv/Publications/1998/87-7909-445-7/html/kap08_eng.htm#8.7.1.  [Excerpt] &quot;A total abolition of pesticide use would result in an average drop in farming yields of between 10% and 25%, at the farm level; the smallest losses would occur in cattle farming. On farms that have a large proportion of special crops, such as potatoes, sugar beet and seed grass, the production losses in terms of quantity would be closer to 50%. These crops would probably be ousted by other crops.&quot;&lt;/ref&gt; [[Michael Pollan]], author of ''[[The Omnivore's Dilemma]]'', responds to this by pointing out that the average yield of world agriculture is substantially lower than modern sustainable farming yields. Bringing average world yields up to modern organic levels could increase the world's food supply by 50%.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news | author=Michael Pollan| title=Chief farmer| work=New York Times| url=http://www.nytimes.com/2008/10/12/magazine/12policy-t.html?pagewanted=5&amp;ei=5070&amp;emc=eta1|accessdate=2008-11-15 | date=2008-10-12}}&lt;/ref&gt;

A 2007 study&lt;ref&gt;Perfecto et al., in Renewable Agriculture and Food Systems (2007), 22: 86–108 Cambridge University Press: cited in New Scientist 13:46 12 July 2007&lt;/ref&gt; compiling research from 293 different comparisons into a single study to assess the overall efficiency of the two agricultural systems has concluded that &lt;blockquote&gt;
...organic methods could produce enough food on a global per capita basis to sustain the current human population, and potentially an even larger population, without increasing the agricultural land base. (from the abstract)
&lt;/blockquote&gt;The researchers also found that while in developed countries, organic systems on average produce 92% of the yield produced by conventional agriculture, organic systems produce 80% more than conventional farms in developing countries, because the materials needed for organic farming are more accessible than synthetic farming materials to farmers in some poor countries.  On the other hand, communities that lack sufficient manure to replenish soils would struggle with organic farming, and the soil would degrade rapidly.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news| url=http://www.economist.com/daily/columns/greenview/displayStory.cfm?story_id=11911706 | work=The Economist | title=Stuck in the mud | date=2008-08-11}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Energy efficiency===
A study of the sustainability of [[apple]] production systems showed that in comparing a conventional farming system to an organic method of farming, the organic system is more [[Efficient energy use|energy efficient]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | author=Reganold et al. | title=Sustainability of three apple production systems | journal=Nature | month=April | year=2001 | volume=410 | pages=926–930 | doi=10.1038/35073574 | pmid=11309616 | last2=Glover | first2=JD | last3=Andrews | first3=PK | last4=Hinman | first4=HR | issue=6831}}&lt;/ref&gt; A more comprehensive study compared efficiency of agriculture for products such as grain, roughage crops, and animal husbandry. While the study did not investigate specific additional requirements of [[arable land]] or numbers of farm laborers to produce total yields for organic farming vs. conventional farming, leaving open the question of overall capacity of organic farming to meet current and future agricultural needs, it concluded that organic farming had a higher yield per unit of energy over multiple crops and for livestock. However, conventional farming had higher total yield.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | author=Dalgaard et al. | title=A model for fossil energy use in Danish agriculture used to compare organic and conventional farming | journal=Agriculture, Ecosystems and Environment | year=2001 | volume=87 | pages=51=65}}&lt;/ref&gt; Conversely, another study noted that organic wheat and corn production was more energy efficient than conventional methods while organic apple and potato production was less energy efficient than conventional methods.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | author=Pimental et al. | title=Energy efficiency of farming systems: Organic and conventional agriculture | journal=Agriculture, Ecosystems &amp; Environment | year=1983 | volume=9 | pages=359–372}}&lt;/ref&gt; A long-term study, spanning two decades, noted that crop yields were 20% lower in organic systems while fertilizer plus energy input was 34% to 53% lower. However, pesticide input was reduced by 97% in organic farm systems.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | author=Maeder et al. | title=Soil Fertility and Biodiversity in Organic Farming | journal=Science | year=2002 | volume=296 | pages=1694–1697 | doi=10.1126/science.1071148 | pmid=12040197}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Consumer safety==

There is widespread belief that organic food is significantly safer for consumption than food grown conventionally, based mainly on [[anecdotal evidence]] and [[testimonials]] rather than scientific evidence, which has fueled increased demand for organic food despite higher prices.&lt;ref name=MagkosSafety&gt;{{cite journal |author=Magkos F, Arvaniti F, Zampelas A |title=Organic food: buying more safety or just peace of mind? A critical review of the literature |journal=Crit Rev Food Sci Nutr |volume=46 |issue=1 |pages=23–56 |year=2006 |pmid=16403682 |doi=10.1080/10408690490911846 |url=}}&lt;/ref&gt;  [[Literature review|Reviews]] of the available body of scientific literature comparing the safety of organic to conventional foods have found neither to be significantly more safe than the other.&lt;ref name=MagkosSafety/&gt;&lt;ref name=Bourn&gt;{{cite journal |author=Bourn D, Prescott J |title=A comparison of the nutritional value, sensory qualities, and food safety of organically and conventionally produced foods |journal=Crit Rev Food Sci Nutr |volume=42 |issue=1 |pages=1–34 |year=2002 |month=January |pmid=11833635 |doi= 10.1080/10408690290825439|url=}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=Kouba&gt;{{cite journal|last=Kouba|first=M|title=Q uality of organic animal products|journal=Livestock Production Science|year=2003|volume=80|pages=33–40|doi=10.1016+/S0301-6226(02)00318-4}}&lt;/ref&gt; Firm conclusions about the relative safety of organic foods has been hampered by the difficulty in proper [[study design]] and relatively small number of studies directly comparing organic food to conventional food.&lt;ref name=MagkosSafety /&gt;

Claims of improved safety of organic food has largely focused on [[pesticide residue]]s.  While studies have shown organically grown fruits and vegetables have significantly lower pesticide residue levels, the significance of this finding on actual health risk reduction is debatable as both conventional foods and organic foods generally have pesticide levels well below government established guidelines for what is considered safe.&lt;ref name=MagkosSafety /&gt; This view has been echoed by the [[U.S. Department of Agriculture]]&lt;ref name=USDA&gt;{{cite web|last=Gold|first=Mary|title=Should I Purchase Organic Foods?|url=http://www.nal.usda.gov/afsic/pubs/faq/BuyOrganicFoodsC.shtml|publisher=USDA|accessdate=5 March 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; and the UK [[Food Standards Agency]].&lt;ref name=FSA&gt;{{cite web|title=Organic food|url=http://www.food.gov.uk/foodindustry/farmingfood/organicfood/|publisher=UK Food Standards Agency|accessdate=5 March 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; Claims of increased risk related to pesticide residue and rates of [[infertility]] or lower [[Semen analysis#Sperm count|sperm counts]] have not been supported by the evidence in the medical literature.&lt;ref name=MagkosSafety /&gt;  Reviews have noted that the risks from [[microbiological]] sources or natural [[toxin]]s are likely to be much more significant than short term or chronic risks from pesticide residues.&lt;ref name=MagkosSafety /&gt;&lt;ref name=Kouba /&gt;

Some focus has been placed on the amount of [[nitrogen]] content in certain vegetables, especially green [[leafy vegetables]] and [[tuber]]s when grown organically as compared to conventionally.  While these vegetables, when grown organically, have been found to have lower nitrogen content, there is no consensus as to whether consumption of lower levels of nitrogen translates to improved health risk.  When evaluating environmental toxins such as [[Heavy metal (chemistry)|heavy metal]]s, the USDA noted that organically raised [[chicken]] may have lower [[arsenic]] levels,&lt;ref name=USDA /&gt; while a literature review found no significant evidence that levels of arsenic, [[cadmium]] or other heavy metals differed significantly between organic and conventional food products.&lt;ref name=MagkosSafety /&gt;

In looking at possible increased risk to safety from organic food consumption, reviews have found that although there are theoretical increased risk from microbiological contamination due to increased [[manure]] use as fertilizer from organisms like [[Escherichia coli O157:H7|''E. coli'' O157:H7]] during organic produce production, there does not exist sufficient evidence of actual incidence of outbreaks that can be clearly tied to organic food production to draw any firm conclusions.&lt;ref name=MagkosSafety /&gt;&lt;ref name=Bourn /&gt;  Other possible sources of increased safety risk from organic food consumption like use of [[biological pesticides]] or the theoretical risk from [[mycotoxins]] from fungi grown on products due to the lack of effective organic compliant [[fungicides]] have likewise not been confirmed by rigorous studies in the scientific literature.&lt;ref name=MagkosSafety /&gt;&lt;ref name=Kouba/&gt;

==Nutritional value and taste==
According to the UK's [[Food Standards Agency]], &quot;Consumers may choose to buy organic fruit, vegetables and meat because they believe them to be more nutritious than other food. However, the balance of current scientific evidence does not support this view.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;[http://extras.timesonline.co.uk/organicfood2.pdf The Food Standards Agency’s Current Stance]&lt;/ref&gt; A 12-month systematic review commissioned by the FSA in 2009 and conducted at the [[London School of Hygiene &amp; Tropical Medicine]] based on 50 years' worth of collected evidence concluded that &quot;there is no good evidence that consumption of organic food is beneficial to health in relation to nutrient content.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
|url=http://www.thisislondon.co.uk/standard/article-23725592-details/article.do
|title=Organic food 'no healthier' blow
|author=Sophie Goodchild
|date=2009-07-
|accessdate=2009-07-29
|publisher=[[London Evening Standard]]
}}&lt;/ref&gt; Other studies have found no proof that organic food offers greater nutritional values, more consumer safety or any distinguishable difference in taste.&lt;ref&gt;Bourn D, Prescott J. January 2002. [http://www.misa.umn.edu/vd/bourn.pdf A comparison of the nutritional value, sensory qualities, and food safety of organically and conventionally produced foods] Critical Reviews in Food Science Nutrition. 42(1): 1–34.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Williams, C. M. February 2002. Nutritional quality of organic food: shades of grey or shades of green? Proceedings of the Nutrition Society. 61(1): 19–24&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Canadian Produce Marketing Association (CPMA). Organically Grown Produce: Does organic produce taste better? &amp; Is organic produce more nutritious?&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Sir John Krebs. June 5, 2003. Is organic food better for you? Speech given by the then-chair of the [[Food Standards Agency]] (UK), Sir John Krebs, to the Cheltenham Science Fair on June 5, 2005. Posted on the Food Standards Agency website: http://www.food.gov.uk/news/newsarchive/2003/jun/cheltenham&lt;/ref&gt; A review of nutrition claims showed that organic food proponents are unreliable information sources which harm consumers, and that consumers are wasting their money if they buy organic food believing that it contains better nutrients.&lt;ref&gt;Rosen, &quot;A Review of the Nutrition Claims Made by Proponents of Organic Food&quot;, Comprehensive Reviews In Food Science And Safety, [http://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/10.1111/j.1541-4337.2010.00108.x/full]&lt;/ref&gt;

Although it is commonly claimed that organically grown food tastes better than conventionally grown food, reviews of the literature that looked at the sensory qualities of the two have not found convincing evidence that there is any significant differences.&lt;ref name=Kouba/&gt;&lt;ref name=Bourn/&gt;

==Organic baby products==
'''Organic baby products''' are commercially produced [[infant formula]]s and [[baby food]]s that have obtained [[organic certification]]. They are often recommended as substitutes for conventionally marketed baby foods in order to reduce the amount of chemical exposure for rapidly developing [[infant]]s. Since babies' bodies are smaller and their brains grow faster, they are more vulnerable to environmental toxins as they absorb more pesticides per pound of body weight than adults.&lt;ref&gt;''Raising Baby Green: The Earth-Friendly Guide to Pregnancy, Childbirth and Baby Care'', Alan Greene, MD, page 137. ISBN 978-0787996222&lt;/ref&gt;

In many countries mothers who are not [[breastfeeding]] can find organic versions of infant formulas and baby foods using various substances (e.g. [[soy]], dairy [[milk]], wheat) through various channels (e.g. hospitals, grocery stores, mail order). However the marketing of organic baby products for newborns and infants under six months of age, just like the marketing of other breastmilk substitutes, has met with increasing skepticism and controversy (see [[International Code of Marketing of Breast-milk Substitutes]]). The [[World Health Organization]], [[UNICEF]] and many national health departments recommend that infants should be [[breastfeeding#Exclusive breastfeeding|exclusively breastfed]] for the first six months of life to achieve optimal health, growth and development.&lt;ref&gt;World Health Organization. [http://www.who.int/features/qa/57/en/index.html Online Q&amp;A: What is the recommended food for children in their very early years?] Accessed 5 August 2011.&lt;/ref&gt; 

Organic baby products are more expensive to produce and get certified, therefore often priced higher than conventional goods and not as accessible to middle and lower income families.{{citation needed|date=August 2011}} The [[International Federation of Organic Agriculture Movements]] (IFOAM) says that while prices have been declining, there are reasons the costs of certified organic products remain higher than conventional products. They include limited supply as compared to demand, greater labor and transportation costs per unit produced. The smaller number of units involved also means marketing and distribution costs have to be spread out over a smaller number of units. As demand for organic food and products increases, technological innovations and economies of scale should reduce costs of production, processing, distribution and marketing for organic produce.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.ifoam.org/sub/faq.html&lt;/ref&gt;

==Economics==
Demand for organic foods is primarily concern for personal health and concern for the environment.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|chapter=|editor=Filho, Walter Leal|title=Ecological agriculture and rural development in Central and Eastern European countries|publisher=IOS Press|year=2004|isbn=9781586034399|pages=147–148|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=_AZuoJQOmi8C&amp;pg=PA147|author=Conflicting demands of agricultural production and environmental conservation: consumers' perception of the quality and safety of food}}&lt;/ref&gt; Organic products typically cost 10 to 40% more than similar conventionally produced products.&lt;ref&gt;Winter, CK and SF Davis, 2006 &quot;Organic Foods&quot; Journal of Food Science 71(9):R117–R124.&lt;/ref&gt; According to the USDA, Americans, on average, spent $1,347 on groceries in 2004;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.ers.usda.gov/Publications/EIB23/ Food Spending in American Households, 2003-04]&lt;/ref&gt; thus switching entirely to organics would raise their cost of groceries by about $135 to $539 per year ($11 to $45 per month) assuming that prices remained stable with increased demand.  Processed organic foods vary in price when compared to their conventional counterparts.

While organic food accounts for 1–2% of total food sales worldwide, the organic food market is growing rapidly, far ahead of the rest of the food industry, in both developed and developing nations.

* World organic food sales jumped from US $23 billion in 2002&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | author= | year=2002 | title=The Global Market for Organic Food &amp; Drink | work=Organic Monitor | url=http://www.organicmonitor.com/700140.htm | accessdate=2006-06-20}}&lt;/ref&gt; to $52 billion in 2008.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | author= | year=2009 | title=Food: Global Industry Guide | work=Datamonitor| url=http://www.researchandmarkets.com/research/18f9c2/food_global_indus | accessdate=2008-08-28}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* The world organic market has been growing by 20% a year since the early 1990s, with future growth estimates ranging from 10%–50% annually depending on the country.

===North America===
: '''[[United States]]'''
:* Organic food is the fastest growing sector of the American [[food marketplace]].&lt;ref&gt;http://www.barackobama.com/issues/pdf/EnvironmentFactSheet.pdf&lt;/ref&gt;{{Dead link|date=February 2011}}
:* Organic food sales have grown by 17 to 20 percent a year for the past few years&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | author=Hansen, Nanette | year=2004 | title=Organic food sales see healthy growth | work=MSNBC | url=http://www.msnbc.msn.com/id/6638417/ | accessdate=2006-06-20}}&lt;/ref&gt; while sales of conventional food have grown at only about 2 to 3 percent a year.&lt;ref&gt;Warner, Melanie. [http://www.nytimes.com/2005/11/01/business/01organic.html?hp&amp;ex=1130907600&amp;en=1a66fec0344c8870&amp;ei=5094&amp;partner=homepage &quot;What Is Organic? Powerful Players Want a Say&quot;]. ''[[New York Times]]'': Nov. 1, 2005.&lt;/ref&gt;

:* In 2003 organic products were available in nearly 20,000 natural food stores and 73% of conventional grocery stores.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | author=Catherine Greene and Carolyn Dimitri | year=2003 | title=Organic Agriculture: Gaining Ground | work=USDA Economic Research Service | url=http://www.ers.usda.gov/publications/aib777/ | accessdate=2006-06-20}}&lt;/ref&gt;

:* Organic products accounted for 3.7% of total food and beverage sales, and 11.4% of all fruit and vegetable sales in the year 2009.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | title = Industry Statistics and Projected Growth | publisher = Organic Trade Association  | date = June 2010 | url = http://www.ota.com/organic/mt/business.html  | accessdate = 2011-05-28 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

:* Two thirds of [[organic milk]] and [[cream]] and half of organic cheese and [[yogurt]] are sold through conventional supermarkets.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | author=Dryer, Jerry | year=2003 | title=Market Trends: Organic Lessons | work=Prepared Foods | url=http://www.preparedfoods.com/CDA/Archives/d403da4af1788010VgnVCM100000f932a8c0____ | accessdate=2006-06-20}}&lt;/ref&gt;

: '''[[Canada]]'''
:* Organic food sales surpassed $1 billion in 2006, accounting for 0.9% of food sales in Canada.&lt;ref name=&quot;Macey, Anne 2007&quot;&gt;{{cite web | author=Macey, Anne| year=2007 | title=Retail Sales of Certified Organic Food Products in Canada in 2006| format=pdf | work=Organic Agriculture Center of Canada | url=http://www.organicagcentre.ca/Docs/RetailSalesOrganic_Canada2006.pdf | accessdate=2008-04-09}}&lt;/ref&gt;
:* Organic food sales by grocery stores were 28% higher in 2006 than in 2005.&lt;ref name=&quot;Macey, Anne 2007&quot;/&gt;
:* British Columbians account for 13% of the Canadian population, but purchased 26% of the organic food sold in Canada in 2006.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | author=Macey, Anne| year=2007 | title=Retail Sales of Certified Organic Food Products in Canada in 2006. Organic food is not all organic. only food labeled with a 100% organic sticker are pesticide-free/| format=pdf | work=Organic Agriculture Center of Canada | url=http://www.organicagcentre.ca/Docs/RetailSalesOrganic_Canada2006.pdf | accessdate=2008-04-09}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Europe===
In the European Union ([[EU25#2004 Enlargement|EU25]]) 3.9% of the total utilized agricultural area was used for organic production in 2005. The countries with the highest proportion of organic land were Austria (11%) and Italy (8.4), followed by the Czech Republic and Greece (both 7.2%). The lowest figures were shown for Malta (0.1%), Poland (0.6%) and Ireland (0.8%).&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
| title=Eurostat press release 80/2007
| url=http://epp.eurostat.ec.europa.eu/pls/portal/docs/PAGE/PGP_PRD_CAT_PREREL/PGE_CAT_PREREL_YEAR_2007/PGE_CAT_PREREL_YEAR_2007_MONTH_06/5-12062007-EN-BP.PDF
| accessdate=2007-10-07
| author=European Commission&amp;nbsp;– Eurostat
| pages=1
| format=PDF}}&lt;/ref&gt;

: '''[[Austria]]'''
:* 11.6% of all farmers produced organically in 2007.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
| title=FAQ
| url=http://www.biolebensmittel.at/article/archive/12548
| accessdate=2007-11-13
| author=Austrian Ministry of Agriculture
| pages=
}}&lt;/ref&gt; The government has created incentives to increase the figure to 20% by 2010.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
| title=Obmann-Wechsel bei Bio Austria
| url=http://www.agrarnet.info/netautor/napro4/appl/na_professional/parse.php?id=20000%2C%2C900161%2C
| accessdate=2007-04-26
| author=Austrian chamber of agriculture
| pages=
}}&lt;/ref&gt;

:* In 2006, 4.9% of all food products sold in Austrian supermarkets (including discount stores) were organic.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
| title=RollAMA Bioanteile LEH 2003–2006
| url=http://www.biolebensmittel.at/filemanager/download/20165/
| accessdate=2007-10-07
| author=Agrarmarkt Austria
| pages=2
}}&lt;/ref&gt; In the same year, 8,000 different organic products were available.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
| title=Wirtschaftlicher Durchbruch für Bio-Fachhandel im Jubiläumsjahr
| url=http://www.bio-austria.at/presse/presseinfo_archiv/pressemeldung__4
| accessdate=2007-11-13
| author=BIO AUSTRIA
| pages=
}}&lt;/ref&gt;

: '''[[Italy]]'''
:* Since 2000, the use of some organic food is compulsory in Italian schools and hospitals. A 2002 law of the [[Emilia Romagna]] region implemented in 2005, explicitly requires that the food in nursery and primary schools (from 3 months to 10 years) must be 100% organic, and the food in meals at schools, universities and hospitals must be at least 35% organic.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web| title=Italian Law Calls for All Organic Foods in Nation's Schools| url=http://www.organicconsumers.org/organic/italy062804.cfm| accessdate=2007-11-13| author=Organic Consumers Association| pages=}}&lt;/ref&gt;

: '''[[Poland]]'''
:* In 2005 168,000 ha of land were under organic management. 7 percent of Polish consumers buy food that was produced according to the EU-Eco-regulation. The value of the organic market is estimated at 50 million Euros (2006).&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web| title=The organic food market in Poland: Ready for take-off|url=http://www.sixtytwo.biz/en/__organicfood1.htm| accessdate=2007-10-08| author=SixtyTwo International Consultants| pages=
|archiveurl = http://web.archive.org/web/20070927035437/http://www.sixtytwo.biz/en/__organicfood1.htm &lt;!-- Bot retrieved archive --&gt; |archivedate = 2007-09-27}}&lt;/ref&gt;

: '''[[UK]]'''
:* Organic food sales increased from just over £100 million in 1993/94 to £1.21 billion in 2004 (an 11% increase on 2003).&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web| title=Organic statistics&amp;nbsp;– the shape of organic food and farming| url=http://www.organic.aber.ac.uk/statistics/index.shtml| accessdate=2007-10-08| author=Organic Centre Wales| pages=}}&lt;/ref&gt;{{Where|date=July 2011}}

===Latin America===
: '''[[Cuba]]'''
:* After the collapse of the [[Soviet Union]] in 1991, agricultural inputs that had previously been purchased from [[Eastern bloc]] countries were no longer available in Cuba, and many Cuban farms converted to organic methods out of necessity.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
| title=Farming with Fidel
| url=http://www.sustainabletimes.ca/articles/cubanfarms.htm
| accessdate=2007-10-08
| author=Alison Auld
| pages=
}}&lt;/ref&gt; Consequently, organic agriculture is a mainstream practice in Cuba, while it remains an alternative practice in most other countries. Although some products called organic in Cuba would not satisfy certification requirements in other countries (crops may be [[genetically modified]], for example&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
| title=Cuban GMO Vision
| url=http://www.pugwash.org/reports/ees/cuba2004/03%20Pugwash/02_Rebecca.pdf
| accessdate=2007-10-08
| author=Center for Genetic Engineering and Biotechnology
| pages=
| format=PDF}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
| title=DirecciÓn de Investigaciones Agropecuarias
| url=http://www.cigb.edu.cu/pages/iap.htm
| accessdate=2007-10-08
| author=Centro de Ingeniería Genética y Biotecnología de Cuba
| pages=
|archiveurl = http://web.archive.org/web/20070927170658/http://www.cigb.edu.cu/pages/iap.htm &lt;!-- Bot retrieved archive --&gt; |archivedate = 2007-09-27}}&lt;/ref&gt;), Cuba exports organic citrus and citrus juices to EU markets that meet EU organic standards. Cuba's forced conversion to organic methods may position the country to be a global supplier of organic products.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
| title=Cuba’s Food &amp; Agriculture Situation Report
| url=http://www.fas.usda.gov/itp/cuba/CubaSituation0308.pdf
| accessdate=2008-09-04
| author=Office of Global Analysis, FAS, USDA
| pages=
| format=PDF}}&lt;/ref&gt;

: '''[[Mexico]]'''
:* Although certification seals have become more common on Mexican produce, mainly for export, there have been strong internal movements to block GMOs and decrease pesticide practice. As the country does not have as long a history of using pesticides as developed nations, it is striving to regain the purity of much of its [[arable land]].
:* Much of its internal and domestic produce consumption is not [[Organic certification|labeled]] as organic, even when the practice is sustainable. This is mainly due to cultural differences.

==See also==
{{Commons}}
&lt;div style=&quot;-moz-column-count:2; column-count:2;&quot;&gt;

* [[Genetically modified food]]
* [[Kosher foods]]
* [[Organic Beans|Organic beans]]
* [[Natural foods]]
* [[Organic clothing]]
* [[Organic farming]]
* [[Soil Association]]
* [[Whole foods]]

&lt;/div&gt;

==References==
{{reflist|colwidth=35em}}

==Further reading==
&lt;!-- * {{cite book|author=|title=|publisher=|year=|isbn=|url=}} --&gt;

* {{cite book|editors=Canavari, Maurizio &amp; Olson, Kent D.|title=Organic food: consumers' choices and farmers' opportunities|publisher=Springer|year=2007|isbn=9780387395814|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=UDUDtv9UWhAC}}
* {{cite book|author=Duram, Leslie A.|title=Encyclopedia of Organic, Sustainable, and Local Food|publisher=ABC-CLIO|year=2010|isbn=9780313359637|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=YtldfGaOJ5IC}}
* {{cite book|author=Givens, D. Ian et al.|title=Health Benefits of Organic Food: Effects of the Environment|publisher=CABI|year=2008|isbn=9781845934590|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=Oz9yevQIDswC}}
* {{cite book | author=[[Joan Dye Gussow|Gussow, Joan Dye]] | title=This Organic Life: Confessions of a Suburban Homesteader | publisher=Chelsea Green Publishing | year=2002 | isbn=1-931498-24-5}}
* {{cite book | author=Guthman, Julie | title=Agrarian Dreams: The Paradox of Organic Farming in California | publisher=University of California Press | year=2004 | isbn=0-520-24095-2}}
* {{cite book | author=Hamilton, Denis; Crossley, Stephen (editors) | title=Pesticide residues in food and drinking water | publisher=J. Wiley | year=2004 | isbn=0-471-48991-3}}
* {{cite book | author=Hond, Frank et al. | title=Pesticides: problems, improvements, alternatives | publisher=Blackwell Science | year=2003 | isbn=0-632-05659-2}}
* {{cite book|author=Nestle, Marion|title=Food Politics: How the Food Industry Influences Nutrition and Health|publisher=University of California Press|year=2007|isbn=9780520254039|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=zvzTIUV9XNwC}}
* {{cite book|author=PAN-UK|title=Pesticides on a Plate|publisher=PAN-UK (UK)|year=2008|isbn=978-0-9549542-6-0}}
* {{cite journal|author=Pretty, J. N., et al.|title=Resource-Conserving Agriculture Increases Yields in Developing Countries|journal=Environmental Science and Technology | year=2006 | volume=40 | pages=1114–1119 | doi=10.1021/es051670d|pmid=16572763 | issue=4 | url=http://pubs.acs.org/subscribe/journals/esthag/40/i04/html/021506news2.html}}
* {{cite book|editors=Scialabba, Nadia &amp;&amp; Hattam, Caroline|title=Organic agriculture, environment and food security|publisher=FAO, United Nations|year=2002|isbn=9789251048191|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=ZeGpgERESvkC}}
* {{cite journal|author=Stokstad, Erik|title=Organic Farms Reap Many Benefits|journal=Science|month=May|year=2002|volume=296|issue=5573| pmid=12040154|pages=1589|url=http://sciencenow.sciencemag.org/cgi/content/full/2002/530/1 | doi=10.1126/science.296.5573.1589a | format= }} {{dead link|date=March 2010}}
* {{cite book|author=Watson, David H. (editor)|title=Pesticide, veterinary and other residues in food|publisher=Woodhead Publishing|year=2004|isbn=1-85573-734-5}}
* {{cite book|author=Wargo, John|title=Our Children's Toxic Legacy: How Science and Law Fail to Protect Us from Pesticides|publisher=Yale University Press|year=1998|isbn=0-300-07446-8}}
* {{cite conference|author=Williams, Christine|title=Nutritional quality of organic food: shades of grey or shades of green?|booktitle=Proceedings of the Nutrition Society|year=2002|pages=19–24}}


==External links==
* [http://www.organicconsumers.org Organic Consumers Association]
*[http://www.Organic.org Organic Information Center]
*[http://orgprints.org/19535/1/Paull%26Hennig2011EJSS.pdf  A World Map of Organic Agriculture]
* [http://www.ams.usda.gov/AMSv1.0/ams.fetchTemplateData.do?template=TemplateA&amp;navID=NationalOrganicProgram&amp;leftNav=NationalOrganicProgram&amp;page=NOPNationalOrganicProgramHome&amp;acct=nop USDA National Organic Program] Responsible for administering organic food production &amp; labeling standards in the United States
* [http://www.food.gov.uk/foodindustry/farmingfood/organicfood &quot;Organic Food&quot;], [[UK Food Standards Agency]]
* [http://www.epa.gov/pesticides/food/brochure.pdf &quot;Pesticide and Food&quot;] (pdf) -- U.S. Environmental Protection Agency (EPA)
* [http://www.epa.gov/pesticides/food/viewtols.htm &quot;Pesticide Residue Limits on Food&quot;] -- EPA
* [http://orgprints.org/18860/1/Paull2011OlympiadJSDS.pdf &quot;Organics Olympiad 2011: Global Indices of Leadership in Organic Agriculture&quot;] -- Journal of Social and Development Sciences


{{DEFAULTSORT:Organic Food}}
[[Category:Organic food| ]]
[[Category:Sustainable food system]]
[[Category:Product certification]]

[[ar:أطعمة عضوية]]
[[bs:Organska hrana]]
[[ca:Aliment ecològic]]
[[cs:Bioprodukt]]
[[de:Bio-Lebensmittel]]
[[es:Alimentos orgánicos]]
[[eo:Ekologia manĝaĵo]]
[[eu:Elikagai biologiko]]
[[fa:خوراک زیستی]]
[[fr:Aliment biologique]]
[[hi:जैविक खाद्य पदार्थ]]
[[he:מזון אורגני]]
[[kn:ಜೈವಿಕ ಆಹಾರ]]
[[mk:Органска храна]]
[[ms:Makanan organik]]
[[ja:有機農産物]]
[[pl:Żywność ekologiczna]]
[[ru:Органические продукты]]
[[sk:Biopotravina]]
[[sr:Еколошка храна]]
[[fi:Luomutuote]]
[[sv:Ekologisk mat]]
[[te:సేంద్రీయ ఆహారం]]
[[uk:Органічні продукти]]
[[yi:ארגאניש עסן]]
[[zh:有機食品]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
