<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="17351775" ns="0" title="University of Sydney Faculty of Engineering and Information Technologies"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Infobox_University
|image_name     = University of Sydney new logo stacked.png
|image_size     = 
|name           = Faculty of Engineering and Information Technologies
|established    = 1920
|type           = [[Public]]
|dean           = Archie Johnston
|city           = [[Camperdown, New South Wales|Camperdown]] / [[Darlington, New South Wales|Darlington]]
|state          = [[New South Wales]]
|country        = [[Australia]]
|affiliations   = [[University of Sydney]]
|students       =
|staff          =
|campus         =
|website        = [http://sydney.edu.au/engineering/ sydney.edu.au/engineering]
}}

The '''Faculty of Engineering and Information Technologies''' is a constituent body of the [[University of Sydney]], [[Australia]]. It was established in 1920 and is Australia's oldest engineering school and one of the most prestigious.

The school has an excellent academic reputation with its programs being ranked in 2011 by the QS World University Rankings by Subject at 21st in world for Civil Engineering and 27th in the world for Mechanical Engineering. Programs at the school are accredited by professional bodies including Engineers Australia, The Australian Institute of Project Management and the Australian Computer Society

In 2011 it had a student enrolment of 4,645 (9.5% of all students), thus making it the University's fourth-largest.&lt;ref&gt;http://sydney.edu.au/strategic_planning/statistics/enrol/enrol.php?ci=3&amp;type=fac&amp;yr=2011&lt;/ref&gt;

==History==
Teaching of engineering at the University began in 1883 within the [[Sydney Faculty of Science|Faculty of Science]] established just a year prior. The Faculty of Engineering itself was established in 1920.

Inially engineering classes were taught in The Quad, however in 1909 the P.N. Russell School of Engineering was completed. This building, an outcome of the P.N. Russell benefactions was formally opened by the Governor on 20 September 1909. With the expansion in student numbers in the 1950s and early 1960s, new purpose built facilities were constructed in the Darlington extension area across City Road and since the mid seventies all departments have been accommodated in this area, although a wind tunnel in the Woolley Building is still in use by Aeronautical Engineering.

The new SciTech Library opened in the Darlington engineering precinct in 2010, as the amalgamation of the Architecture, Engineering, Madsen and Mathematics libraries, brought together as part of the Campus 2010 project.

[[File:Usyd_School_of_IT.jpg|thumb|right|The School of IT building]]

==Constituent Schools==
* School of Aerospace, Mechanical and Mechatronic Engineering
* School of Chemical and Biomolecular Engineering
* School of Civil Engineering
* School of Electrical and Information Engineering
* School of Information Technology
* Graduate School of Engineering and IT

==Research Centres==
* Warren Centre
* ACIIC
* AGSEI
* Chemical Engineering Foundation
* Australian Centre of Advanced Risk and Reliability Engineering
* Electrical Engineering Foundation
* The Civil and Mining Engineering Foundation
* Centre for Geotechnical Research
* Centre for Advanced Structural Engineering
* Mechanical Engineering Foundation
* Centre for Advanced Materials Technology
* Cooperative Research Centre in Aerospace Structures

==Notable Alumni==
* [[John Bradfield (engineer)|John Bradfield]] - designer of Sydney Harbour Bridge
* Paul Scully-Power - Australia's first Astronaut
* Michael Hintze - billionaire hedge fund manager and philanthropist
* David Higgins - CEO of Network Rail and former CEO of Lend Lease
* John Grills - billionaire founder of WorleyParsons

==References==
{{Reflist}}

==External links==
* [http://www.eng.usyd.edu.au/ University of Sydney Faculty of Engineering and Information Technologies]
* [http://www.aeromech.usyd.edu.au/AMME4111/Seminar%20Day%20Timetable%20Semester%202%202009%20Final.pdf] {{dead link|date=January 2011}}

{{University of Sydney}}


[[Category:Faculties of the University of Sydney|Engineering and Information Technologies, Faculty of]]


{{Australia-university-stub}}</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
