<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="17351809" ns="0" title="University of Sydney Faculty of Veterinary Science"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Infobox_University
|image_name     = University of Sydney new logo stacked.png
|image_size     = 
|name           = Faculty of Veterinary Science
|established    = 1910
|type           = [[Public]]
|dean           = Rosanne Taylor
|city           = [[Camperdown, New South Wales|Camperdown]], [[New South Wales]], [[Australia]] &lt;br /&gt; 
                  [[Camden, New South Wales|Camden]], [[New South Wales]], [[Australia]]
|state          = 
|country        = 
|affiliations   = [[University of Sydney]]
|students       = 760 (2010)&lt;/small&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;faculty&quot;/&gt;
|staff          = 98 (2010)&lt;/small&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;faculty&quot;/&gt;
|campus         = [[urban area|Urban]], [[Park]]s. [[Farm]]
|website        = [http://sydney.edu.au/vetscience/ sydney.edu.au/vetscience]
}}

The '''Faculty of Veterinary Science''' is a constituent body of the [[University of Sydney]], [[Australia]]. Initially established on 22 March 1910&lt;ref name=&quot;vethistory1&quot; /&gt;, it is the second oldest established veterinary school in Australia, the longest running veterinary school in Australia&lt;ref name=&quot;vethistory1&quot; /&gt; and one of two universities offering veterinary degrees in New South Wales. The faculty is mainly established across both Camperdown and Camden campuses with two undergraduate degrees offered by the faculty – the Bachelor of Veterinary Science and the Bachelor of Animal and Veterinary Bioscience. The faculty is usually associated with the Roundhouse or Centaur as a logo and recently celebrated its centenary in 2010.

==History==
The Faculty of Veterinary Science officially opened in 1910 with a student enrolment of 16 students&lt;ref name=&quot;vethistory1&quot; /&gt; and James Douglas Steward appointed as Director. Without proper facilities, teaching was done in the then Fisher Library of the Main Quadrangle but relocated to the J.D. Stewart Building in 1913 after its completion.&lt;ref name=&quot;vethistory1&quot; /&gt;

In 1920, the Veterinary School obtained full faculty status with Professor J.D. Stewart as Dean. Under Stewart, student enrolments gradually increased from 25 in 1928 to over 100 in 1935. In 1930 and during WWII, Sydney University became solely responsible for veterinary education in Australia after temporary closures of both Melbourne University and Queenland University’s veterinary schools respectively.&lt;ref name=&quot;vethistory1&quot; /&gt; 

In 1954, the acquisition of land by the university in Camden paved way for large animal teaching and subsequently the erection of the Evelyn Williams Building and R.M.C. Gunn Building in the Camperdown precinct. More recently new facilities include the Veterinary Science Conference Centre in 1998, the Valentine Charlton Cat Centre and the Canine Teaching Hospital. 
In 2005, the faculty introduced the Bachelor of Animal and Veterinary Bioscience and in 2009, Rossane Taylor became the first female Dean of the faculty.&lt;ref name=&quot;vethistory2&quot; /&gt;

==Degrees==
===Undergraduate===
====Bachelor of Veterinary Science (BVSc)====
The Bachelor of Veterinary Science has been offered since the conception of the faculty. Students must undertake 5 years of full-time study with the fourth year on Camden Campus and fifth on rotational intern positions.  The degree is recognized by the Veterinary Surgeons’ Board in every state of Australia and also recognised internationally by the Royal College of Veterinary Surgeons in the United Kingdom and the accredited by the American Veterinary Medical Association (AVMA) in the United States. 
====Bachelor of Animal and Veterinary Bioscience (AVBS)====
The Bachelor of Animal and Veterinary Bioscience was introduced in 2005&lt;ref name=&quot; vethistory1 &quot; /&gt; and focuses more on the production and research aspects of animals. The degree extends across 4 years (full-time) with a research task based on the final year.

==Facilities and Heritage buildings==
===Camperdown Campus===
====J.D. Stewart Building====
The J.D. Stewart Building is the first veterinary building built for the university and named after the faculty’s founder and first Dean, James Douglas Steward. Completed in 1913, three years after the faculty’s first students; it was granted heritage listing in 1976&lt;ref name=&quot; vethistory1 &quot; /&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot; vetheritage &quot; /&gt;. Today, it houses the faculty office, Veterinary Society office and anatomy dissection labs.
====The Roundhouse====
The Roundhouse is a black wooden, heritage-listed rotunda located on the Vet lawns of the Camperdown campus. It was designed by Professor Lesley Wilkinson in 1920 and completed around 1924&lt;ref name=&quot; vethistory1 &quot; /&gt;. Originally utilised as an equine observation box, the Roundhouse is no longer in use and was refurbished by the university in 2009. &lt;ref name=&quot; vethistory1 &quot; /&gt; It is commonly used as a symbol for the faculty and prominently featured for the faculty’s centenary.
====Veterinary Science Conference Centre==== 
The Veterinary Science Conference Centre (VSCC) is a triple-storey building that mainly houses Webster Lecture Theatre.
====Sydney University Veterinary Teaching Hospital====
The Sydney University Veterinary Teaching Hospital is a general practice veterinary clinic consisting of the Valentine Charlton Cat Centre and the Canine Teaching Hospital. The hospital contains CT, MRI, digital radiology and ultrasound imaging and diagnostic equipment as well as 24 hour emergency and intensive care. The facility also caters as a teaching hospital for veterinary students to learn professional aspects of the degree.

===Camden Campus===
The Camden campus is located approximately 65 km away from the Camperdown campus. Located on campus includes teaching space, farms and student accommodation. The campus’ main purpose is to provide large animal handling skills for undergraduate students and research for post-graduates. The Camden campus is also the site where the world’s first robotic rotary dairy was opened and is the home for fourth year BVSc and AVBS students. &lt;ref name=&quot; robotmilk &quot; /&gt;

==Student Societies and Publications==
===University of Sydney Veterinary Society (VetSoc)===
The Veterinary Society, more commonly known as VetSoc by students, is the University of Sydney’s second-oldest student run society on campus&lt;ref name=&quot; vetsoc&quot; /&gt; and represents students of both the Bachelor of Veterinary Science and the Bachelor of Animal and Veterinary Bioscience. The society plans social events for faculty students and publishes The Chiron quarterly. In 2010, VetSoc was voted as the best student society in the university. The official logo is the Centaur. 

===Animal Welfare Society===
The Animal Welfare Society is a society that aims to promote and address issues in animal welfare both domestically and internationally. Although head mainly by veterinary faculty students, it is open to all students across the faculties of the university. 

==Notable Alumni==
* Chris Brown&lt;ref name=&quot;brownbio&quot;/&gt; – Co-stars on Bondi Vet and regular on the 7PM Project
* Lisa Chimes&lt;ref name=&quot;chimesbio&quot;/&gt; – Co-stars on Bondi Vet
* Harry Cooper - Co-starred on Harry's Practice
* Katrina Warren – Co-starred on Harry's Practice and current TV Presenter

==External links==
* [http://www.vetsci.usyd.edu.au/ University of Sydney Faculty of Veterinary Science]

==References==
{{Reflist|refs=
&lt;ref name=&quot;vethistory1&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://sydney.edu.au/vetscience/about/history.shtml|title=Our History - About the Faculty - The University of Sydney|publisher=The University of Sydney|accessdate=19 February 2011}} &lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;ref name=&quot;vethistory2&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://sydney.edu.au/vetscience/centenary/timeline.shtml#2000|title=Historical Timeline 1910-2010|publisher=The University of Sydney|accessdate=19 February 2011}} &lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;ref name=&quot;vetrecogn&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://sydney.edu.au/vetscience/future_students/undergraduate/recognition_bvsc.shtml|title=Is the Degree Recognised?|publisher=The University of Sydney|accessdate=19 February 2011}} &lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;ref name=&quot;vetheritage&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url= http://sydney.edu.au/vetscience/future_students/undergraduate/recognition_bvsc.shtml|title=Heritage:J.D. Stewart Building |publisher=Campus Infrastructure Heritage - The University of Sydney|accessdate=19 February 2011}} &lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;ref name=&quot;vetsoc&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url= http://sydney.edu.au/vetscience/vetsoc/
l|title=Sydney University Veterinary Society page |publisher=VetSoc|accessdate=19 February 2011}} &lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;ref name=&quot;robotmilk&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url= http://www.thefarmtrader.com.au/articles/world-first-robotic-dairy |title=World First Robotic Dairy |publisher=The Farm Trader|accessdate=19 February 2011}} &lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;ref name=&quot;brownbio&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url= http://ten.com.au/bondi-vet-dr-chris-brown.htm|title=Dr. Chris Brown's Biography|publisher=Network Ten|accessdate=19 February 2011}} &lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;ref name=&quot;chimesbio&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url= http://ten.com.au/bondi-vet-8744.htm|title=Dr. Lisa Chimes' Biography|publisher=Network Ten|accessdate=19 February 2011}} &lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;ref name=&quot;faculty&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url= http://sydney.edu.au/about/publications/undergraduate_prospectus/2010/prospectus2010_veterinary.pdf
|title=Veterinary Science Prospectus 2010|publisher=Faculty of Veterinary Science, University of Sydney|accessdate=19 February 2011}} &lt;/ref&gt;

}}
{{University of Sydney}}


[[Category:Faculties of the University of Sydney|Veterinary Science, Faculty of]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
