<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="17355166" ns="0" title="Princeton Tigers"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Infobox college athletics
| logo     =  Princeton Tigers Logo.svg
| logo_width = 150
| name     = Princeton Tigers
| university = [[Princeton University]]
| conference = [[Ivy League]]&lt;br&gt;[[ECAC Hockey]]&lt;br&gt;[[Eastern Association of Rowing Colleges]]&lt;br&gt;[[Eastern Association of Women's Rowing Colleges]]&lt;br&gt;[[Eastern Intercollegiate Volleyball Association]]&lt;br&gt;[[Eastern Intercollegiate Wrestling Association]]
| association = [[National Collegiate Athletics Association|NCAA]]
| division = [[Division I (NCAA)|Division I]]
| director = [[Gary Walters]]
| city     = Princeton
| state    = New Jersey
| stateabb = NJ
| teams    = 31 teams
| stadium  = [[Princeton University Stadium]]
| baseballfield  = [[Clarke Field]]
| soccerstadium  = [[Roberts Stadium (Princeton)|Roberts Stadium]]
| lacrossestadium = [[Class of 1952 Stadium]]
| arena    = [[Jadwin Gymnasium]]
| arena2   = [[Baker Rink]]&lt;br/&gt;[[Shea Rowing Center]]
| symbol   = 
| mascot   = The Tiger
| nickname = Tigers
| fightsong= [[Princeton Cannon Song]]
| color1 = [[Orange (colour)|Orange]]
| hex1   = FF6600
| color2 = [[black]]
| hex2   = 000000
| pageurl  = http://www.goprincetontigers.com/?DB_OEM_ID=10600
| pagename = Princeton Tigers
}}

The '''Princeton Tigers''' are the [[college athletics|athletic]] teams of [[Princeton University#Athletics|Princeton University]]. The school sponsors 31 [[varsity team|varsity]] [[sports]]. The school has won several [[National Collegiate Athletic Association|NCAA]] national championships, including one in [[NCAA Fencing team championship|men's fencing]], six in [[NCAA Men's Lacrosse Championship|men's lacrosse]], three in [[NCAA Women's Lacrosse Championship|women's lacrosse]], and eight in [[NCAA Division I Men's Golf Championships|men's golf]]. Princeton's men's and women's crews have also won numerous national rowing championships.

==Teams==
*'''Men's''' Sports: | Baseball | Basketball | Crew - Heavyweight | Crew - Lightweight | Cross Country | Fencing | Football | Golf | Hockey | Lacrosse | Rugby | Soccer | Sprint Football | Squash | Swimming &amp; Diving | Tennis | Track &amp; Field | Volleyball | Water Polo | Wrestling
*'''Women's''' Sports: | Basketball | Crew - Lightweight | Crew - Open | Cross Country | Fencing | Field Hockey | Golf | Hockey | Lacrosse | Rugby | Soccer | Softball | Squash | Swimming &amp; Diving | Tennis | Track &amp; Field | Volleyball | Water Polo

===Baseball===
===Basketball===
====Men's basketball====
{{main|Princeton Tigers men's basketball}}
Princeton's [[college basketball|basketball]] team is perhaps the best-known team within the Ivy League. It is nicknamed the &quot;perennial giant killer,&quot; a nickname that it acquired during [[Pete Carril]]'s coaching career from 1967–1996. Its most notable upset was the 1996 defeat of defending NCAA champion [[UCLA]] in the tournament's opening round, Carril's final collegiate victory. In 1989, the team almost became the only #16 seed to win, losing to Georgetown 50-49,&lt;ref&gt;John Branch, &quot;Carril is Yoda to Notion of Perpetual Motion,&quot; ''New York Times'', March 30, 2007&lt;/ref&gt; after leading 29–21 at the half. During that 29-year span, Pete Carril won thirteen Ivy League championships and received eleven NCAA berths and two NIT bids. Princeton placed third in the 1965 NCAA Tournament and won the NIT championship in 1975. The deliberate &quot;[[Princeton offense]]&quot; is a legacy of his coaching career. It is employed by a number of other collegiate basketball teams.

From 1992–2001, a nine-year span, the men's basketball team entered the NCAA tournament four times. Notably, the Ivy League has never had an [[at-large berths|at-large entry]] in the NCAA tournament. For the last half-century, Princeton and the [[University of Pennsylvania]] have traditionally battled for men's basketball dominance in the Ivy League; Princeton had its first losing season in 50 years of Ivy League basketball in 2005. Princeton tied the record for fewest points in a Division I game since the 3-point line started in 1986–87 when they scored 21 points in a loss against [[Monmouth University]] on December 14, 2005.

====Women's basketball====
===Crew===
[[File:TigersHenley2009b.jpg|thumb|300px|The varsity lightweight men celebrate winning the Temple Cup at Henley Royal Regatta, July 2009.]]
Rowing was introduced to Princeton in 1870 by a handful of undergraduates who bought two old boats with their own funds and formed an impromptu &quot;navy&quot; on the [[Delaware and Raritan Canal]].&lt;ref&gt;Leitch, Alexander (1978). ''A Princeton Companion''. Princeton University Press.&lt;/ref&gt; The construction of [[Lake Carnegie]] in 1906 enabled the sport to expand and laid the foundation for today's rowing program at Princeton. More recently, an $8 million upgrade and expansion of the existing boathouse in 2000 formed [[Shea Rowing Center]], one of the finest rowing facilities in the country.

With 150 athletes, 60 rowing shells, and 12 coaches, trainers, and boat riggers, crew is the largest varsity sport at Princeton, and one of the most successful. In recent years, from 2000 through 2010, Princeton varsity crews (both men's and women's) won a total of 14 [[Eastern Sprints]], [[Intercollegiate Rowing Association|IRA]] (national), and [[NCAA Rowing Championship|NCAA]] championships, as well as two international events at [[Henley Royal Regatta]].

The Princeton boathouse is often a summer base for U.S. national teams in training, and many Princeton rowers and coaches have gone on to compete at the World Rowing Championships and the Olympics.

====Men's heavyweight crew====

*[[National Collegiate Rowing Championship]]: 2345

====Men's lightweight crew ====
:''See also: [[Eastern Association of Rowing Colleges]] (EARC) and [[Goldthwait Cup]]''

''Main article under construction: Princeton Tigers Men's Lightweight Crew''

====Women's open crew====
:''See also: [[Eastern Association of Women's Rowing Colleges]] (EAWRC)''

====Women's lightweight crew ====
===Fencing===
====Men's====
====Women's====
===Football===
&lt;!--  Commented out: [[Image:Firstfootballgame.jpg|right|thumb|200px|Drawing from the [[1869 college football season|first football game played]] between Rutgers and Princeton.]] --&gt;
[[File:Princeton Tigers vs Lehigh.jpg|thumb|200px|Princeton vs. Lehigh, September 2007]]
{{main|Princeton Tigers football}}
The [[college football|football]] team has competed since 1869 and played in the [[1869 college football season|first game]] against [[Rutgers University]].  They have won 24 [[NCAA Division I FBS National Football Championship|national championships]] when the school competed in what is now known as the [[Football Bowl Subdivision|FBS]].&lt;ref&gt;http://www.cfbdatawarehouse.com/data/national_championships/mel_smith/football_style.php&lt;/ref&gt;  Twenty-one former players have been inducted into the [[College Football Hall of Fame]].

The first [[football]] game played between teams representing American colleges was an unfamiliar ancestor of today's [[college football]] because it was played under [[soccer]]-style London Football Association rules. The game, between Rutgers College (now [[Rutgers University]]) and the College of New Jersey (now Princeton University), took place on November 6, 1869 at College Field (now the site of the College Avenue Gymnasium at Rutgers University) in New Brunswick, New Jersey. Rutgers won by a score of six &quot;runs&quot; to Princeton's four. The [[1869 New Jersey vs. Rutgers football game|1869 game]] between Rutgers and Princeton is notable because it is the first documented game of any sport called &quot;football&quot; between two American colleges. It is also noteworthy because it occurred two years before a codified rugby game would be played in England. The Princeton/Rutgers game was significantly different from American rules football today but, nonetheless, it was the first inter-collegiate football contest in the United States. Another similar game took place between [[Rutgers]] and [[Columbia University]] in 1870 and a third notable game took place between [[Tufts University]] and [[Harvard University]] in 1875.  The popularity of intercollegiate competition in football would spread throughout the country shortly thereafter. {{Citation needed|date=May 2009}}

Though Princeton is no longer a part of [[Division I (NCAA)|Division I]] [[Football Bowl Subdivision]], the Tigers have the most overall national championships of any team in major college football history with 24 consensus and non-consensus national championships dating all the way back to their first one, shared with Rutgers, in 1869.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.cfbdatawarehouse.com/data/national_championships/nchamps_team.php|publisher=College Football Data Warehouse|title=Recognized National Championships by Team|accessdate=2009-08-01}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Since 1901, however, they have 4 consensus national championships, which ranks as tied for 11th all time.{{Citation needed|date=November 2008}}

Princeton's football helmets are also the basis for [[Michigan Wolverines football]]'s famed winged helmets, as introduced by [[Fritz Crisler]], the coach at Princeton before he was hired as the coach of [[The University of Michigan]].

===Golf===
===Ice hockey===
====Men's ice hockey====
{{main|Princeton Tigers men's ice hockey}}

====Women's ice hockey====
{{main|Princeton Tigers women's ice hockey}}

===Lacrosse===
====Men's lacrosse====
{{main|Princeton Tigers men's lacrosse}}
The university's men's [[lacrosse]] team has enjoyed significant success since the early 1990s and is widely recognized as a perennial powerhouse in the Division I ranks. The team has won thirteen [[Ivy League]] titles (1992, 1993, 1995–2004, 2006) and six [[NCAA Men's Lacrosse Championship|national titles]] (1992, 1994, 1996–1998, 2001).&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.princeton.edu/~lacrosse/ Welcome to the World of Princeton Lacrosse&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;

====Women's lacrosse====
The Princeton Tigers women's lacrosse team has enjoyed much success, winning 3 NCAA championships, tied for 3rd place with Virginia in the number of NCAA championships won.They won NCAA division 1 titles in 1994, 2002, and 2003. Their record in the NCAA tournament finals is 3-4.

===Rugby===
{{main|Princeton Rugby}}
====Men's Rugby====
Ivy League Champions in 2004, 1979, 1977, 1973, 1971 and 1969.
====Women's Rugby====
National champions in 1995 and 1996. Princeton women advanced to the Final Four in 1997, 1999, 2000, 2001, 2004 and 2005. 32 Princeton women have been named All-Americans.

===Soccer===
====Men's soccer====
Before the NCAA began its tournament in 1951, the annual national champion was declared by the [[Intercollegiate Soccer Football Association|Intercollegiate Association Football League]] (IAFL) — from 1911 to 1926 — and then the [[Intercollegiate Soccer Football Association]] (ISFA), from 1927 to 1958. From 1911 to 1958, Princeton won seven national championships.

====Women's soccer====
In 2004, the women's soccer team went to the Final Four in the NCAA tournament. It became the only Ivy League team (men's or women's) to do so in a 64-team tournament.{{Citation needed|date=May 2009}}

===Squash===
Princeton's men's and women's [[Squash (sport)|squash]] teams have earned a strong reputation during the past decade.

====Men's squash====
The men have won the Ivy League championship from 2006–2008 and have placed second nationally in five of the past seven championships.{{Citation needed|date=May 2009}}

====Women's squash====
===Track and field===
====Men's track and field====
====Women's track and field====
Princeton's women's track &amp; field team has also enjoyed great success under Head Coach Peter Farrell.

===Volleyball===
====Men's volleyball====
{{see also|Eastern Intercollegiate Volleyball Association}}

====Women's volleyball====
The Princeton women's volleyball team has won thirteen Ivy League titles and, in 1998, its men's volleyball team became the first non-scholarship school to make the NCAA Final Four in 25 years.{{Citation needed|date=May 2009}}

===Wrestling===
{{see also|Eastern Intercollegiate Wrestling Association}}


==Facilities==
:''See footnote''&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.goprincetontigers.com/ViewArticle.dbml?DB_OEM_ID=10600&amp;ATCLID=295010 Princeton Facilities]. GoPrincetonTigers.com (Princeton University Athletics official website). Princeton University. Retrieved 2011-09-10.&lt;/ref&gt;

The stadium is [[Princeton University Stadium]], which replaced [[Palmer Stadium]]. Baseball is played at [[Clarke Field]]. Basketball is played at [[Jadwin Gymnasium]]. Ice hockey is played at [[Baker Rink]]. Soccer is played at [[Roberts Stadium (Princeton)|Roberts Stadium]]. Lacrosse is played at [[Class of 1952 Stadium]]. The men's and women's volleyball teams and the wrestling team compete at [[Dillon Gymnasium]]. All crews train at [[Shea Rowing Center]] and compete on [[Lake Carnegie]]. The Rugby Team plays at Rickerson Field on West Windsor Fields.

==Top athletes of the decade==
===2000-2009===
:''See footnote''&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |title=Top 10 Male and Female Athletes of the Decade |publisher=Princeton Athletic Communications |date=December 15, 2009 |url=http://www.goprincetontigers.com/ViewArticle.dbml?DB_OEM_ID=10600&amp;ATCLID=204848843 |accessdate=2010-02-02}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==See also==
*[[List of college athletic programs in New Jersey, USA#Division I]]

==References==
{{reflist}}

==External links==
*[http://www.goprincetontigers.com Princeton Tigers] official website

{{Princeton}}
{{Ivy League}}
{{ECAC Hockey League}}
{{Eastern Association of Rowing Colleges}}
{{Eastern Intercollegiate Volleyball Association}}
{{NewJerseysports}}

[[Category:Princeton Tigers|* ]]
[[Category:College sports teams in New Jersey]]
[[Category:College sports teams in the United States by team]]

[[es:Princeton Tigers]]
[[fr:Tigers de Princeton]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
