<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="173555" ns="0" title="Shortstop"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{refimprove|date=April 2011}}
[[Image:Baseball SS.svg|thumb|right|The position of the shortstop]]

'''Shortstop''', abbreviated '''''SS''''', is the [[baseball positions|baseball fielding position]] between [[second base|second]] and [[third base]]. Shortstop is often regarded as the most dynamic [[Defense (sports)|defensive]] position in baseball, because there are more [[Right-handedness|right-handed]] hitters in baseball than [[Left-handedness|left-handed]] hitters, and most hitters have a tendency to pull the ball slightly, so more balls go to the shortstop than any other position. In the numbering system used to record defensive plays, the shortstop is assigned the number 6.

==Positioning==
In practice the shortstop ordinarily positions himself to the third-base side of second base, but ordinarily much closer to second base than toward third base.  Against an extreme pull hitter the shortstop may tend to a position about halfway between second base and third base for a right-hand hitter, and even on the first-base side of second base for a left-hand hitter.  Because the shortstop typically fields some of the [[ground ball]]s that have traveled farthest in the [[infield]] and has a longer throw to first base from the point at which he fields the ball than any infielder other than a third baseman and less time in which to make a throw, a shortstop must have one of the strongest throwing arms on the field. Because balls hit to or near the shortstop position are usually hit harder than to almost any other base, a shortstop must be extremely agile. On some bunt plays, the shortstop often must make a run to third base so that the third baseman can field the bunt and throw to third base in a [[fielder's choice]] play in which the shortstop makes the play at third base. Such makes the position unusually difficult to fill. Shortstops have included some of the weakest hitters in baseball, including [[Mario Mendoza]], for whom [[George Brett (baseball)|George Brett]] coined the eponymous [[Mendoza Line]] to describe the lowest batting average among players who have significant time in the major leagues. 

In practice, a marginal fielder as a shortstop who hits well can be moved to almost any other position, especially second base or third base, whether early in their careers (examples: George Brett and [[Mike Schmidt]] were both tried early in their careers as shortstops)&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.baseball-reference.com/players/b/brettge01.shtml |title=George Brett Statistics and History |publisher=Baseball-Reference.com |date= |accessdate=February 13, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.baseball-reference.com/players/s/schmimi01.shtml |title=Mike Schmidt Statistics and History |publisher=Baseball-Reference.com |date= |accessdate=February 13, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; or later due to diminished [[fielding range]], slower reflexes, weaker throwing arms, increased risk of injury, or co-existence with another dominant shortstop, as with [[Ernie Banks]], [[Cal Ripken, Jr.]], [[Alex Rodríguez]], [[Michael Young (baseball)|Michael Young]], or [[Miguel Tejada]].           

Shortstops are required to [[covering a base|cover second base]] in [[double play]] situations when the ball is hit to the [[second baseman]], [[first baseman]], [[pitcher]], or [[catcher]].  They cover second when a runner is attempting a [[stolen base]], but only when a left-handed hitter is batting. This is because the chances of a ball being hit to the left side of the infield are almost cut in half.  They also must cover third at various times, including the rotation play; that is, when there are runners on first and second and a [[sacrifice bunt]] is attempted.  Shortstops generally are given precedence on catching pop-ups in the [[infielder|infield]] as well, so they end up calling off other players many times, although on deep pop-ups they fall back when called off by an [[outfielder]]. They often become the cutoff man on balls to any part of the outfield that are being directed towards third base and all balls to left and right field that are destined to second base. Depending on the system the shortstop may cut balls from left field heading home however, this is usually the role of a third basemen.

==Significant shortstops==
===[[List of members of the Baseball Hall of Fame#Members|Shortstops inducted to the Baseball Hall of Fame]]===
[[File:Ozzie Smith 1983.jpg|thumb|right|180px|upright=3.|[[St. Louis Cardinals|Cardinals]] great [[Ozzie Smith]]]]

The year in which the player was inducted is given in brackets after his name.
{{Div col}} 
*[[Luis Aparicio]]
*[[Luke Appling]]
*[[Dave Bancroft]]
*[[Ernie Banks]] (played shortstop for the first half of his career and first base for the remainder)
*[[Lou Boudreau]]
*[[Joe Cronin]]
*[[George Davis (shortstop)|George Davis]]
*[[Travis Jackson]]
*[[Hughie Jennings]] (1945)
*[[John Henry Lloyd|John Henry &quot;Pop&quot; Lloyd]] *
*[[Rabbit Maranville]]
*[[Pee Wee Reese]]
*[[Cal Ripken, Jr.]]
*[[Phil Rizzuto]]
*[[Joe Sewell]]
*[[Ozzie Smith]]
*[[Joe Tinker]]
*[[Arky Vaughan]]
*[[Honus Wagner]] (1936)
*[[Bobby Wallace (baseball)|Bobby Wallace]]
*[[John Montgomery Ward]]
*[[Willie Wells]] *
*[[George Wright (sportsman)|George Wright]] (elected as a pioneer, but also starred as a shortstop in the 1860s &amp; 70s)
*[[Robin Yount]] (moved to the outfield for his last nine seasons)
 {{Div col end}}
[[Image:Jetershortstop.JPG|thumb|right|200px|[[Derek Jeter]], a shortstop, getting ready to field his position in 2007]]

===Multiple Gold Glove Award winners===
{{see also|List of Gold Glove Award winners at shortstop}}
{{Div col}} 
*[[Ozzie Smith]]: 13
*[[Omar Vizquel]]: 11
*[[Luis Aparicio]]: 9
*[[Mark Belanger]]: 8
*[[Dave Concepción]]: 5
*[[Derek Jeter]]: 5
*[[Tony Fernández]]: 4
*[[Alan Trammell]]: 4
*[[Barry Larkin]]: 3
*[[Roy McMillan]]: 3
*[[Rey Ordóñez]]: 3
*[[Jimmy Rollins]]: 3
*[[Gene Alley]]: 2
*[[Larry Bowa]]: 2
*[[Orlando Cabrera]]: 2
*[[Don Kessinger]]: 2
*[[Edgar Rentería]]: 2
*[[Cal Ripken, Jr.]]: 2
*[[Alex Rodríguez]]: 2
*[[Zoilo Versalles]]: 2
*[[Maury Wills]]: 2
 {{Div col end}}

===All-time single season assist leaders among shortstops===
#[[Ozzie Smith]]: 621 (St. Louis Cardinals, 1980)
#[[Glenn Wright]]: 601 (Pittsburgh Pirates, 1924)
#[[Dave Bancroft]]: 598 (Philadelphia Phillies/New York Giants, 1920)
#[[Tommy Thevenow]]: 597 (St. Louis Cardinals, 1926)
#[[Iván DeJesús]]: 595 (Chicago Cubs, 1977)
#[[Cal Ripken, Jr.]]: 583 (Baltimore Orioles, 1984)
#[[Whitey Wietelmann]]: 581 (Boston Braves, 1943)
#[[Dave Bancroft]]: 579 (New York Giants, 1922)
#[[Rabbit Maranville]]: 574 (Boston Braves, 1914)
#[[Don Kessinger]]: 573 (Chicago Cubs, 1968)

===All-time single season putout leaders among shortstops===
# [[Donie Bush]]: 425 (Detroit Tigers, 1914)
# [[Hughie Jennings]]: 425 (Baltimore Orioles [National League], 1895)
# [[Joe Cassidy (baseball)|Joe Cassidy]]: 408 (Washington Senators, 1905)
# [[Rabbit Maranville]]: 407 (Boston Braves, 1914)
# [[Dave Bancroft]]: 405 (New York Giants, 1922)
# [[Eddie Miller (baseball infielder)|Eddie Miller]]: 405 (Boston Braves, 1940)
# [[Monte Cross]]: 404 (Philadelphia Phillies, 1898)
# [[Dave Bancroft]]: 396 (New York Giants, 1921)
# [[Mickey Doolan]]: 395 (Philadelphia Phillies, 1906)
# [[Buck Weaver]]: 392 (Chicago White Sox, 1913)

==See also==
*Gold Glove award winners: [[List of AL Gold Glove Winners at Shortstop|AL]], [[List of NL Gold Glove Winners at Shortstop|NL]]
*[[List of Gold Glove middle infield duos]]
*[http://www.straightdope.com/classics/a1_299b.html One theory of how the shortstop position got its name]

==References==
{{Reflist}}

{{Baseball positions}}

[[Category:Baseball positions]]

[[da:Baseballpositioner#Shortstop (SS)]]
[[de:Shortstop]]
[[es:Shortstop]]
[[fr:Arrêt-court]]
[[ko:유격수]]
[[it:Interbase]]
[[nl:Korte stop]]
[[ja:遊撃手]]
[[pt:Interbases]]
[[simple:Shortstop]]
[[sv:Shortstop]]
[[zh:游擊手]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
