<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="1743138" ns="0" title="H. Sophie Newcomb Memorial College"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Infobox university
|name            = Tulane University
|image_name      = TulaneSealColor.png
|image_size      = 150px
|caption         = [[Seal (device)|Seal]] of Tulane University
|motto           = ''Non Sibi Sed Suis'' ([[Latin]])
|mottoeng        = &quot;Not for oneself, but for one's own&quot;
|established     = 1834
|type            = [[Private university|Private]]
|president       = [[Scott Cowen]]
|faculty         = 1,132&lt;ref name=&quot;facts&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://tulane.edu/about/facts.cfm|title=Tulane University Facts| year=2006| publisher= tulane.edu| accessdate=2007-04-16}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|undergrad       = 6,749
|postgrad        = 4,408
|endowment       = [[United States dollar|US $]] 807 million (as of June 30, 2009)&lt;ref name=&quot;tef&quot;&gt;[http://tulane.edu/tef/ Investment Office Overview] from the Tulane University website, retrieved September 11, 2009&lt;/ref&gt;
|city            = [[New Orleans]]
|state           = [[Louisiana]]
|country         = [[United States]]
|coor            = {{Coord|29.935344|N|90.122687|W|region:US-LA_type:edu|display=inline,title}}
|campus          = [[Urban area|Urban]]
|former_names    = Medical College of Louisiana (1834-1847),&lt;ref name=&quot;facts&quot; /&gt; University of Louisiana (1847-1884)
|athletics       = [[National Collegiate Athletic Association|NCAA]] [[Division I (NCAA)|Division I]] [[Conference USA]]
|sports       = [[Baseball]], [[basketball]], [[Cross country running|cross-country]], [[American football|football]], [[golf]], [[tennis]], [[volleyball]]
|nickname        = [[Tulane Green Wave|Green Wave]]   
|mascot        = Riptide the [[Pelican]]
|colors          = [[Olive (color)|Olive Green]] and [[Sky Blue]] {{color box|#808000}}{{color box|skyblue}}
|affiliations    = [[Association of American Universities|AAU]]
|website         = [http://tulane.edu/ tulane.edu]
|logo              = [[Image:Tulane web header.png|center|200px|alt=Tulane Shield and wordmark]]
}}
{{main|Tulane University}}

'''H. Sophie Newcomb Memorial College''', or '''Newcomb College''', was the coordinate [[Women's Colleges in the Southern United States|women's college]] of [[Tulane University]] located in [[New Orleans, Louisiana|New Orleans]], [[Louisiana]].  It was founded by [[Josephine Louise Newcomb]] in 1886 in memory of her daughter.  

Newcomb was the first women's coordinate college within a United States university. This model was later used in partnerships such as [[Pembroke College (Brown University)|Pembroke College]] at [[Brown University]] and [[Barnard College]] at [[Columbia University]]. 

In 2006, Newcomb College was merged into other Tulane undergraduate colleges, as part of Tulane's Renewal Plan following the major losses and damage of [[Hurricane Katrina]] in 2005.  Alleged heirs of Mrs. Newcomb sued, challenging Tulane on the issue of donor intent and seeking to preserve Newcomb as a separate coordinate college within the university, but the lawsuit ended in 2011 after appellate court rulings in support of the university's position.

== History ==
Josephine Louise Newcomb (born Josephine Louise Le Monnier, 1816–1901) established the college as a memorial to her daughter Sophie, who died in 1870 at the age of 15.  Following an initial donation of $100,000, she made gifts totaling $3 million.  She wanted to support a liberal academic education for young white women.  Newcomb was influenced by [[Ida Richardson]] and the college was associated with the [[Progressive Movement]] from its earliest years. 

Until its move in 1918 to its Broadway campus, Newcomb College was made up mostly of day students.  Its move to its current site on the uptown campus of Tulane was also the occasion of development of dormitories and more campus life.  Students at Newcomb College became increasingly sophisticated and the school's reputation grew.

The university had recruited [[Brandt V.B. Dixon]] as the first president of Newcomb College.  To ensure girls and young women were academically prepared for college, Dixon established the Newcomb High School, which operated from 1888 to 1920.  The preparatory school ensured that girls were ready to study at the college level, as some parents tried to send girls to Newcomb who were as young as 13 or 14, with little academic preparation.  Dixon worked with faculty and students to continue to raise academic standards.  By 1916, Newcomb had achieved a strong regional reputation and become &quot;one of seven Southern schools which held a standard college designation within the Southern Association of College Women.&quot; &lt;ref name=&quot;tulane.edu&quot;&gt;[http://www.tulane.edu/~wc/text/newcomb.html Georgen Coyle and Susan Tucker, &quot;Newcomb: A Brief History of the College&quot;], Tulane University, accessed 17 Jan 2009&lt;/ref&gt;  

Out of its art school, the college created the business of what became the renowned [[Newcomb Pottery]].  This reflected both a progressive interest in craft and parents' desire for their daughters to learn a practical, &quot;industrial&quot; skill in the economically difficult postwar years.  It was first headed by Mary Given Sheerer, previously associated with the [[Rookwood Pottery]] in Cincinnati.  While the pottery did not employ that many women, some did find work there.  [[Angela Gregory]] was artist-in-residence at Newcomb College. It produced more than 70,000 pieces before the pottery program closed in 1939.  During these years, the college's art program expanded to include other arts and crafts, such as illustrated [[bookplate]]s, [[jewelry]], [[embroidery]], and hand-bound books, the latter often given embossed leather covers and elaborate [[clasp]]s.&lt;ref name=&quot;tulane.edu&quot;/&gt;  

Newcomb contributed greatly to the early development of [[basketball]] and other sports for women, which added to its reputation.  The college was one of the first women's colleges to compete in national basketball games, along with northern women's colleges such as [[Smith College|Smith]], [[Mount Holyoke College|Mount Holyoke]], and [[Vassar College|Vassar]].  

In 1895, Newcomb's physical education instructor [[Clara Gregory Baer]] published the handbook ''Basketball Rules for Women and Girls''.  The book described both the one-handed shot and the [[Jump shot (basketball)|jump shot]], which would not be adopted by men's basketball until 1936.  The college had the first women's team to wear [[bloomers (clothing)|bloomers]], a better solution for sports.  On March 13, 1895, Newcomb students played the first public basketball game in [[American South|the South]] before 560 other women at the Southern Athletic Club.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.newcomb.tulane.edu/new_hist.html][http://www.foxnews.com/story/0,2933,187115,00.html]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.ncaasports.com/basketball/womens/results/3953]&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Newcomb ball]], a game played as an [[volleyball variations|alternative]] to [[volleyball]], originated at Newcomb College and bears its name.  The sport was very popular in the 1920s.&lt;ref name=&quot;newcomb&quot;&gt;[http://www.aafla.org/SportsLibrary/JSH/JSH1996/JSH2302/jsh2302f.pdf  Paul, Joan, &quot;A Lost Sport: Clara Gregory Baer and Newcomb Ball,&quot; ''Journal of Sport History'', Vol. 23, No. 2 (Summer 1996)]&lt;/ref&gt; The game is still played in various forms across the world.

As it grew, the college reflected many social changes, such as the wider roles of women during and after [[World War II]].  Married women were included in admissions.  The college began to offer more coeducational classes with Tulane University.  After the U.S. [[Supreme Court of the United States|Supreme Court]] ruling in ''Brown v. Board of Education'' (1954), in the early 1960s both the university and college integrated to adjust to a new moral imperative.  The focus of the curriculum changed over the years, and women were offered more science and business classes.&lt;ref name=&quot;tulane.edu&quot;/&gt;

== Restructuring ==
In December 2005 the Tulane University [[board of directors]] announced that the university would be reorganized on July 1, 2006, to accommodate needed changes due to losses following Hurricane Katrina.&lt;ref&gt;[http://renewal.tulane.edu/traditions.shtml Tulane Renewal Plan]&lt;/ref&gt; The board also approved the recommendation of a special Tulane Renewal task force to name a revised, [[co-education]]al, single [[undergraduate]] college '''[[Tulane University Newcomb-Tulane College|Newcomb-Tulane College]]'''.  The new college within the university is not strictly a successor to Newcomb College.

This followed years of talk about restructuring.  Some of the faculty had believed that Newcomb's separate status had adversely affected promotions, for instance, as well as other academic opportunities and had long encouraged a realignment within Tulane University.  Since social changes of the 1970s, college and university discussions had centered on a different arrangement within the university.&lt;ref name=&quot;tulane.edu&quot;/&gt;

=== Lawsuits ===
Arguing the &quot;renewal&quot; plan violated the donor's original intention of the gift, Newcomb's heirs filed and lost two suits against the university to invoke the restrictions of Newcomb's lifetime gifts and bequest in her will. The university stated that by naming Tulane her universal legatee in her will, Josephine Louise Newcomb placed no conditions on the use of her donations, but entrusted her gifts to the discretion of the Administrators of Tulane University.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www2.tulane.edu/article_news_details.cfm?ArticleID=7343 Tulane's ''The New Wave''], May 9, 2007.&lt;/ref&gt; 

After working its way through the Louisiana courts, the initial case filed in May 2006, ''Howard v. Tulane'', was heard by the Louisiana Supreme Court.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.nola.com/news/t-p/metro/index.ssf?/base/news-28/1211380807310560.xml&amp;coll=1 &quot;Justices scrutinize Newcomb's intent in opening college&quot;] ''The Times-Picayune''. May 21, 2008&lt;/ref&gt;  The court ruled on July 1, 2008, that the &quot;successors&quot; of a testator have standing to enforce the terms of a predecessor's will, though it did not rule specifically on the merits of the interpretation of Mrs. Newcomb's will. Instead the court returned the case to the trial court to require the plaintiffs to prove they are heirs. The plaintiffs dismissed their case.

Based on the Supreme Court's definition of &quot;successor&quot;, a subsequent action, ''Montgomery v. Tulane'', was filed in 2008 by Susan Henderson Montgomery, another great niece of Mrs. Newcomb and the plaintiff claiming to be a successor. After losing in New Orleans civil district court, the plaintiff filed an appeal to the state. On October 13, 2010, a state appeals court sided 3-2 with Tulane University.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.nola.com/education/index.ssf/2010/10/tulane_wins_appeal_in_newcomb.html &quot;Tulane wins appeal in Newcomb suit&quot;] ''The Times-Picayune''. October 13, 2010&lt;/ref&gt; On February 18, 2011, the Louisiana Supreme Court voted, 4 to 2, with one abstention, to let a lower court's ruling in favor of Tulane stand.&lt;ref&gt;[http://chronicle.com/article/Tulane-U-Wins-Donor-Intent/126465/ Tulane U. Wins Donor-Intent Lawsuit Over Closing of Women's College],  ''The Chronicle of Higher Education'', February 21, 2011.&lt;/ref&gt; The plaintiffs in the case said that the lack of federal issues meant that the case would not be appealed to the U.S. Supreme Court and that the lawsuits were over.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.insidehighered.com/news/2011/02/22/tulane_wins_legal_battle_over_donor_intent Donor Intent vs. Current Realities], ''Inside Higher Ed'', February 22, 2011.&lt;/ref&gt;

=== H. Sophie Newcomb Memorial College Institute ===

'''Newcomb College Institute''' is an umbrella organization that runs programs (for women) that were formerly operated by the H. Sophie Newcomb Memorial College.  In its first year (2006–07), under the leadership of founding Interim Executive Director Rebecca Mark (Tulane Department of English), the non-academic Newcomb College Institute hosted 104 speakers and 110 different programs for women, men and guests at Tulane. 

In May 2007, NCI inaugurated &quot;Under the Oaks,&quot; a Commencement awards ceremony recognizing the accomplishments of students involved in Newcomb programs.  It maintained some traditions, such as the Daisy Chain, in which rising female seniors dress in white and carry a rope of greenery and fresh-cut daisies.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.nola.com/timespic/stories/index.ssf?/base/library-125/117955715776540.xml&amp;coll=1 ''The Times Picayune'', May 19, 2007]&lt;/ref&gt;

Under the hand of a new Provost Michael Bernstein, Rebecca Mark was removed from the helm of NCI two years into her appointment, and Molly Travis (Tulane Department of English) was appointed as the second Interim Executive Director at NCI, serving 2008-2009.{{cn|date=March 2011}} Sally J. Kenney (formerly of the [[Hubert H. Humphrey School of Public Affairs|Humphrey Institute of Public Affairs]] at the [[University of Minnesota]]) was named the official first permanent executive director of the Newcomb College Institute in June 2009, and arrived on campus January 2010.&lt;ref&gt;[http://tulane.edu/news/newwave/012810_kenney.cfm '''Newcomb Institute Leader Dedicated to Women’s Education''', ''The New Wave'', January 28, 2010]&lt;/ref&gt;

==See also==
*[[Tulane University Newcomb-Tulane College|Newcomb-Tulane College]]
*[[Women's colleges in the Southern United States]]
*[[Timeline of women's colleges in the United States]]

== References ==
{{Reflist|2}}

== External links ==
* [http://newcomb.tulane.edu/ H. Sophie Newcomb Memorial College Institute]
* [http://www.tulane.edu/~wc/ Newcomb College Center for Research on Women]
* [http://www.newcombartgallery.tulane.edu/ Newcomb Art Gallery]
* [http://newcomblives.com/ The Future of Newcomb College, Inc.], organized to preserve Newcomb College as a women’s degree-granting institution.
* [http://women.tulane.edu/ &quot;Enriching Education for All Women&quot;], university website to answer questions about Newcomb College and the Newcomb College Institute.
*[http://www.justartpottery.com/collectors_pottery/newcomb_pottery_history.htm Newcomb College Pottery]
*[http://www.artpotteryblog.com/art_pottery_blog/2006/10/necomb_college_.html Newcomb Pottery Marks]

{{Tulane University}}
{{Women's Colleges that are Coeducational}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Newcomb}}
[[Category:Defunct universities and colleges in Louisiana]]
[[Category:Educational institutions established in 1886]]
[[Category:Educational institutions disestablished in 2006]]
[[Category:Embedded educational institutions]]
[[Category:Former women's universities and colleges in the United States]]
[[Category:Tulane University]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
