<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><redirects><r from="Nfs pro street" to="Need for Speed: ProStreet" /></redirects><pages><page pageid="9269516" ns="0" title="Need for Speed: ProStreet"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Infobox VG
|title= Need for Speed: ProStreet
|image= [[File:Nfsps-win-cover.jpg|256px|Cover art for ''Need for Speed: ProStreet'']]
|caption=
|developer= [[EA Canada|EA Black Box]]&lt;br&gt;[[Exient Entertainment]] &lt;small&gt;(DS)&lt;/small&gt;
|publisher= [[Electronic Arts|EA]] &lt;br&gt; [[Electronic Arts|EA Mobile]]
|distributor= [[Electronic Arts|EA Distribution]]
|designer=
|series= ''[[Need for Speed]]''
|engine=
|version= 1.1 (2007-12-18)
|released= {{vgrelease|NA=November 14, 2007&lt;ref name=&quot;new website&quot; &gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.ea.com/prostreet/home.jsp?locale=us |title=New website |publisher=Electronic
Arts |accessdate=2007-09-28 }}&lt;/ref&gt;}}{{vgrelease|EU=November 23, 2007&lt;ref name=&quot;ign reldate&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url=http://xbox360.ign.com/objects/904/904767.html |title=IGN: Need for Speed: ProStreet |publisher=IGN |accessdate=2007-09-29 }}&lt;/ref&gt;}}{{vgrelease|JP=January 31, 2008}}
|genre= [[Racing game|Racing]]
|modes= [[Single player]], [[multiplayer]]
|ratings= [[Entertainment Software Rating Board|ESRB]]: E10+&lt;br /&gt;[[Entertainment Software Rating Board|ESRB]]: E ([[Nintendo DS|DS]]/[[PlayStation Portable|PSP]])&lt;br /&gt;[[Pan European Game Information|PEGI]]: 3+&lt;br /&gt;[[Office of Film and Literature Classification (Australia)|OFLC]]: G
|platforms= [[PlayStation 3]], [[PlayStation 2]], [[PlayStation Portable]], [[Wii]], [[Nintendo DS]], [[Xbox 360]], [[Microsoft Windows]], [[Mobile phone|Mobile]]
|media=[[Compact Disc|CD]], [[DVD]], [[Blu-ray Disc]], [[EA Link]] download, [[Wii Optical Disc]], [[Universal Media Disc|UMD]], [[Cartridge (electronics)|Nintendo DS card]], [[Cartridge (electronics)|Cartridge]]
|requirements=
'''Windows'''
* Windows [[Windows XP|XP]] / [[Windows Vista|Vista]]
* 2.6&amp;nbsp;GHz [[central processing unit|CPU]] (2.8&amp;nbsp;GHz for Vista)
* 512 MB [[RAM]] (1 GB for Vista)
* 8.1 GB [[hard disk]] space
* [[DirectX]] 9.0 with [[Shader]] 2.0 support compatible 128 MB [[graphics card]] with one of these chipsets [[GeForce FX|GeForce FX 5950]]; [[Radeon 9500]]
* [[DirectX]] 9.0 compatible [[sound card]]
* 8X [[DVD-ROM]]
* 512 kbit/s Internet connection for online play
|input= [[Personal computer|PC]]: Keyboard, Mouse and racing wheel&lt;br&gt;[[Video game console|Home console]]: [[Gamepad]] (Wireless/Wired) and [[Racing wheel]], [[Wii Remote|Wii Remote, Nunchuk, Classic controller and Wii Wheel]] &lt;br&gt;[[Handheld console]]: [[PlayStation Portable|PSP]] buttons with analog stick and [[Multitouch]] ([[Nintendo DS|NDS]])
|resolution = [[720p]] ([[HDTV]])&lt;br&gt;[[480p]]/[[576p]] ([[EDTV]])&lt;br&gt;[[480i]]/[[576i]] ([[SDTV]])
}}
'''''Need for Speed: ProStreet''''' is the 11th installment of [[Electronic Arts]]' popular [[racing game]] series ''[[Need for Speed]]''. On May 21, 2007, [[Electronic Arts]] published a [[teaser trailer]] of ''ProStreet'', and officially announced it ten days later.&lt;ref name=&quot;announcement&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.electronicarts.co.uk/news/13119/ |title=EA Shifts Gears with Need for Speed ProStreet |date=2007-05-31 |publisher=Electronic Arts |accessdate=2007-06-01 }}&lt;/ref&gt; It was released worldwide in November 2007.&lt;ref name=&quot;new website&quot; /&gt; Its action footage was used in [[American Le Mans Series]]. ''ProStreet'' was the first [[PlayStation 3]] game with [[DualShock 3]] rumble support.

The demo, featuring two races, one speed challenge and one grip race, appeared on [[Xbox Live]] on October 26, 2007, on [[PlayStation Store]] on November 1, 2007, and on [[Personal computer|PC]] on November 2, 2007. The PC version is the last in the series to use CD-ROMs, which are succeeded by the usage of DVDs for the rest of the series. ''ProStreet'' is preceded by ''[[Need for Speed: Carbon]]'' and is followed by ''[[Need for Speed: Undercover]]''.

==Plot==
The game begins where a former street racer known as '''Ryan Cooper''' enters a challenge day and wins it with a [[Nissan 240SX]]. Ryan is mocked by '''Ryo Watanabe''', the ''Showdown King'' .

He then moves on to ''Battle Machine'', a famous race organization, and dominates it. He then moves onto ''Showdown Chicago'', promoted by ''Super Promotion'' and the best organization is introduced, the '''Super Promotion'''; there are other organizations in each specific event such as the '''Noise bomb''' for drift, '''G Effect''' that are a circuit crew, '''ROGUE SPEED''' which is for drag, and '''Nitrocide''' for speed runs. Each organization has a top race team, '''Apex Glide''', '''Touge Union''', '''Grip Runners''', '''Aftermix''', and '''Boxcut''', respectively. Ryan dominates the showdown and moves onto '''React Team Sessions'''. He then moves onto another ''Showdown'' again promoted by &quot;Super Promotion&quot; and dominates it. He then receives invites to elite organizations of the four ''Kings'' of Drag, Drift, Grip and Speed challenge after breaking a certain amount of specific records in each race mode. He beats them and earns their crowns and dominates enough organizations and showdowns to face Ryo who drives a [[Mitsubishi Lancer Evolution X]]. Ryan beats him and the '''Apex Glide''' team leaves Ryo. Ryan then becomes ''Street King'' by beating the kings and Ryo.

==Gameplay==
&lt;!-- PLEASE READ [[WP:NOT#IINFO]] - Wikipedia is not a game guide
Therefore, only describe the gameplay elements, do not give details such as bosses or specific car ratings, handling, acceleration, or a very detailed description of how such-and-such works or how it is different from other games.--&gt;
''Need for Speed: ProStreet'' has taken the series in a different direction of gameplay. All racing in ''ProStreet'' takes place solely on closed tracks, making ''ProStreet'' the first game in the series since ''[[Need for Speed II]]'' that doesn't animate [[Street racing|illegal racing]]. Rather, the type of racing appears to be Clubman Racing{{{fact|date=August 2011}}. The [[performance tuning]] feature is enhanced, compared to previous versions, especially [[Need for Speed: Carbon#Car customization|Autosculpt]]. Unlike [[Need for Speed: Carbon|Carbon]], where only certain [[body kit]]s can be autosculpted, this can now be applied to all body kits, including stock bumpers and wide body kits. Furthermore, some adjustments through autosculpt impact the car's aerodynamics.&lt;ref name=&quot;announcement&quot; /&gt;

In ProStreet there are four different game modes: Drag (a race in a drag strip, point to point), Grip (similar to Circuit races but with four different types of Grip races available), Speed (similar to a Sprint race) and Drift.

*Drag race is a simple straight away race that has three heats.  There are three types of drag races, 1/4 and 1/2 mile drag races where the fastest time, out of three runs, wins. There is also a wheelie competition where the longest wheelie on the 1/4 mile track wins.
*In Grip races, there are four different modes (Normal Grip, Grip Class (all versions except for the [[PS2]] and [[Wii]] versions), Sector Shootout and Time Attack), the player has a choice to race rough, such as ramming, smashing, or blocking the opponent in order to win the race, or race cleanly and follow the given racing lines. '''Normal Grip''' races feature 2 to 4 laps around a circuit track with up to 7 other racers. First driver to cross the finish line wins. '''Grip Class''' races take 8 racers and divide them into two even groups. The racers are placed into the groups based on their vehicles performance potential. Group A starts about 10 seconds ahead of group B, both groups race on the same course but are only competing against the 3 drivers in their group. In '''Time Attack''', the driver with the fastest overall single lap time wins the event. In '''Sector Shootout''' the track is divided into several segments, with drivers attempting to complete these sectors in the shortest possible time. Extra points are awarded to drivers who 'dominate' the course by holding the fastest time for every segment of the track.
*In Speed Challenge races, players must cross the finish line first to win the race. Players have to be cautious in Speed Challenge at speeds exceeding 200&amp;nbsp;mph.
*In Top Speed Run races, there are 3 to 9 checkpoints and at the instant a player crosses a checkpoint their speed is clocked and added to that player's score, the player with the highest cumulative speed wins. This is similar to the Speedtrap events in [[Need for Speed: Most Wanted]].
*In Drift, players drift to emerge as the driver with the most points scored in the event. Points are scored based on speed, angle, and how long the drift is held.

Other than game play itself, ''ProStreet'' features detailed damage modeling, unlike previous ''Need for Speed'' games (except for ''[[Need for Speed: High Stakes|High Stakes]]'' and ''[[Need for Speed: Porsche Unleashed|Porsche Unleashed]]'') where damage is relatively little or non-existent altogether. The new damage system introduces more depth of damage (except on the [[PlayStation 2]], [[PlayStation Portable]], [[Nintendo DS]] and [[Wii]] versions, where the damage modeling has been scaled down due to the limited processing power, so the damage is similar to the previous titles) where any object in the game world has the potential to inflict cosmetic damage breaking off pieces of the car such as the hood,bumpers,side view mirrors, light damage, or heavy damage which reduces performance of a car, and even has the potential to total a car immediately after impact.&lt;ref name=&quot;announcement&quot; /&gt;

''ProStreet'' features customization of cars.  The changes affect the aerodynamics of the cars, and players can test them in an enclosed chamber called the &quot;Wind Tunnel&quot; (only on the [[PlayStation 3]], [[Personal Computer|PC]] and [[Xbox 360]] versions).

The ''Speedbreaker'' does not return for ''ProStreet'' (as the game lacks a police presence; the ''Speedbreaker'' was mostly intended for police evasion, however it returns for the [[Nintendo DS]] version of the game).

===Customization===
Players have a wide variety of decals, vinyls, and paint colors, all very similar to the previous games in the series. Additional extras have been added as well. Players have a huge variety of body modifications, such as rims, hoods, body kits, exhaust tips, spoilers and roof scoops.
The ''Autosculpt'' feature, which was first introduced in [[Need for Speed: Carbon]], is featured in ProStreet and plays a significant role in terms of car performance. Although there are more parts to autosculpt in the car, the autosculpting method is for the most part the same.  The hood, roof scoop, front bumper and spoiler can all change how a car performs in a race. Autosculpt can affect everything, from a car's handling to its downforce. ProStreet now allows you to modify stock and wide [[body kits]] as well as [[hood (vehicle)|hoods]], roof scoops, [[wheel]]s, [[Spoiler (automotive)|spoilers]] etc. A new feature called the [[Windtunnel]] is introduced on the PC, [[PlayStation 3]] and [[Xbox 360]] versions of the game. It is not available on [[Wii]] and [[PlayStation 2]]  versions. The Windtunnel, along with Autosculpt, can affect a car's performance.

===Locations===
Many of the races take place on well-known roads. Locations include Chicago ([[Meigs Field]] Airport; now disused), [[Nevada]], Europe, Tokyo Docklands (Daikoku Futo parking area), and the [[Autobahn]] (A100 Berlin ring road). The [[Texas World Speedway]], a real track in Texas used by the [[SCCA]] and in the 70s [[NASCAR]], and also the [[Infineon Raceway]], available in the [[NASCAR]] configuration as &quot;GP Circuit&quot; and [[American Motorcyclist Association|AMA]] configuration as &quot;Long Circuit&quot;. The game also includes many other real world tracks such as [[Portland International Raceway]] and [[Willow Springs International Motorsports Park]] in the USA, [[Autopolis]] and [[Ebisu Circuit]] in Japan, and [[Mondello Park]] in Ireland. The tracks are the same in all versions of ''ProStreet''.

===Online===
Online modes are not featured in the [[PlayStation 2]] and [[Wii]] versions.  However the [[PlayStation Portable]], [[Nintendo DS]], [[Xbox 360]], [[PlayStation 3]] and [[Microsoft Windows|Windows PC]] versions feature online mode. Unlike previous ''Need for Speed'' titles, it is much more integrated into the game; as long as a player is connected to the [[Internet]] and logged in, his/her in-game progress is recorded for the purpose of online leaderboards. A player's custom-built car can also be shared online via ''blueprints'', with the creator being given credit whenever their car setup is used for a leaderboard.&lt;ref name=&quot;online&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url=http://uk.gamespot.com/video/939664/6180305/need-for-speed-prostreet-official-movie-10 |title=GameSpot Video: Need for Speed ProStreet Official Movie 10 |date=2007-10-08 |publisher=Electronic Arts |accessdate=2007-10-08 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Development==
The official title was leaked several months before the official announcement. '''Soft Club''', the Russian distributor of the game, unveiled the name and release date of the game in February 2007.&lt;ref name=&quot;Russia3&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.ag.ru/news/07-02-2007#16824 |title=Soft Club leaks about EA releases |date=2007-02-07 |publisher=AG |language=Russian |accessdate=2007-04-29 }}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Electronic Arts|EA]] had not until the official announcement on May 31, 2007, given any clue about the game's title.

==Features==
===Cars===
There are a total of 46 driveable cars in ''ProStreet'' (76 with add-ons). Like previous iterations, the cars are organized into 3 categories: Tuners, Muscle and Exotic. Cheats can unlock 4 more.

The '''Collector's Edition''' for [[Personal computer|PC]], [[Xbox 360]] and [[PlayStation 3]] adds another 5 new cars. It is available via download. In December 2007 EA released a booster pack (expansion pack) that added another 16 cars that were made available via download. The Booster Pack was a free download available for [[Personal computer|PC]], [[Xbox 360]] and [[PlayStation 3]]. On [[Nintendo DS|NDS]] version, muscle cars will be generic cars.

===Tire manufacturers===
*[[Kumho Tires]]
*[[Dunlop Tires]] (not available on [[PlayStation 2]] and [[Wii]])
*[[Michelin]]
*[[Yokohama Rubber Company|Yokohama]]
*[[Hankook Tire|Hankook]] (not available on  [[PlayStation 2]] and [[Wii]])
*[[toyo tire]]

===Characters===
In ''ProStreet'', the player is Ryan Cooper, a former illegal street racer and a newcomer to the legal side of racing. He is seen only in the very beginning, during showdowns, and after defeating a ''King''; however, his face is never seen, as he wears a helmet all the time in the footage. He also never speaks, much like the main character in the games from [[Need for Speed: Underground]] to [[Need for Speed: Carbon]]. Ryan Cooper is also mentioned in [[Need for Speed: Undercover]], where a police officer claims to have Ryan in his car, but he will not speak or take off his helmet, like in ProStreet.

''ProStreet'' features some girls cast as characters in the game:
*[[Krystal Forscutt]], a former [[Big Brother Australia]] contestant,
*and [[Sayoko Ohashi]] are starting girls.

All three announcers voices heard throughout ProStreet's career mode are real-life, professional race commentators :
*Jarod DeAnda (Big-Jay Battle Machine &amp; Noise Bomb) is an announcer [[Formula D]] events,
*[[John Hindhaugh]] (Roger Evans from R3act Team Sessions &amp; G-Effect) is the long-term host of [[Radio Le Mans]],
*JBird (J-Mack from Super Promotion, Noise Bomb &amp; Rogue Speed) is the official voice of [http://www.nopi.net/ NOPI].

In ''ProStreet'', there are five ''Kings'' that Ryan must defeat in a set of challenges to become the ''Street King''.

===Expansions===
The Collector's Edition is available at the [[EA Store]] for the [[Personal computer|PC]], [[Xbox 360]] and [[PlayStation 3]] unlocking 5 more cars and 4 more career race days.&lt;ref name=&quot;eastore&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url=http://eastore.ea.com/servlet/ControllerServlet?Action=DisplayPage&amp;Env=BASE&amp;Locale=en_US&amp;SiteID=ea&amp;id=ProductDetailsPage&amp;productID=83514100 |title=EA Store: Prostreet Collector's Edition |date=2008-03-16 |publisher=Electronic Arts |accessdate=2008-03-16 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

An expansion pack branded by Energizer Lithium is also available.  It adds 16 cars (2 free and 14 purchase) and 2 tracks. This also disables all cheats for the game.&lt;ref name=&quot;eastore2&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.ea.com/prostreet/downloads.jsp?locale=us&amp;skip_intro=1 |title=EA Store: Prostreet Downloads |date=2008-03-16 |publisher=Electronic Arts |accessdate=2008-03-16 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Reception==
{{Video game multiple console reviews
|DS  = true
|PC  = true
|PS2 = true
|PS3 = true
|X360= true
|WII = true
|PSP= true
|GR_X360 =&lt;center&gt;72.17%&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web |url=http://www.gamerankings.com/xbox360/939664-need-for-speed-prostreet/index.html |title=Need for Speed ProStreet for Xbox 360 Reviews |publisher=[[GameRankings]] |accessdate=2011-10-04}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
|GR_PS3 =&lt;center&gt;72.87%&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web |url=http://www.gamerankings.com/ps3/939739-need-for-speed-prostreet/index.html |title=Need for Speed ProStreet for PlayStation 3 Reviews |publisher=[[GameRankings]] |accessdate=2011-10-04}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
|GR_WII =&lt;center&gt;64.18%&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web |url=http://www.gamerankings.com/wii/939803-need-for-speed-prostreet/index.html |title=Need for Speed ProStreet for Wii Reviews |publisher=[[GameRankings]] |accessdate=2011-10-04}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
|GR_PSP =&lt;center&gt;60.38%&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web |url=http://www.gamerankings.com/psp/939805-need-for-speed-prostreet/index.html |title=Need for Speed ProStreet for PSP Reviews |publisher=[[GameRankings]] |accessdate=2011-10-04}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
|GR_DS =&lt;center&gt;74.83%&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web |url=http://www.gamerankings.com/ds/939806-need-for-speed-prostreet/index.html |title=Need for Speed ProStreet for DS Reviews |publisher=[[GameRankings]] |accessdate=2011-10-04}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
|GR_PS2 =&lt;center&gt;60.64%&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web |url=http://www.gamerankings.com/ps2/939804-need-for-speed-prostreet/index.html |title=Need for Speed ProStreet for PlayStation 2 Reviews |publisher=[[GameRankings]] |accessdate=2011-10-04}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
|GR_PC =&lt;center&gt;69.12%&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web |url=http://www.gamerankings.com/pc/941615-need-for-speed-prostreet/index.html |title=Need for Speed ProStreet for PC Reviews |publisher=[[GameRankings]] |accessdate=2011-10-04}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
|MC_X360 =&lt;center&gt;72/100&lt;/center&gt;
|MC_PS3 =&lt;center&gt;73/100&lt;/center&gt;
|MC_WII =&lt;center&gt;61/100&lt;/center&gt;
|MC_PSP =&lt;center&gt;57/100&lt;/center&gt;
|MC_DS  =&lt;center&gt;74/100&lt;/center&gt;
|MC_PS2 =&lt;center&gt;62/100&lt;/center&gt;
|MC_PC =&lt;center&gt;70/100&lt;/center&gt;
|1UP_X360 =&lt;center&gt;A-&lt;/center&gt;
|1UP_PS3 =&lt;center&gt;A-&lt;/center&gt;
|1UP_PSP =&lt;center&gt;C+&lt;/center&gt;
|1UP_PC =&lt;center&gt;B+&lt;/center&gt;
|GSpot_X360 =&lt;center&gt;7/10&lt;/center&gt;
|GSpot_PS3 =&lt;center&gt;7/10&lt;/center&gt;
|GSpot_WII =&lt;center&gt;6.5/10&lt;/center&gt;
|GSpot_PSP =&lt;center&gt;4/10&lt;/center&gt;
|GSpot_PS2 =&lt;center&gt;6.5/10&lt;/center&gt;
|GSpot_PC =&lt;center&gt;6.5/10&lt;/center&gt;
|EuroG_PS3 =&lt;center&gt;5/10&lt;/center&gt;
|EuroG_X360 =&lt;center&gt;5/10&lt;/center&gt;
|GT_X360 =&lt;center&gt;7.7/10&lt;/center&gt;
|GT_PS3 =&lt;center&gt;7.7/10&lt;/center&gt;
|GT_PC =&lt;center&gt;7.7/10&lt;/center&gt;
|IGN_X360 =&lt;center&gt;6.8/10&lt;/center&gt;
|IGN_PS3 =&lt;center&gt;6.8/10&lt;/center&gt;
|IGN_WII =&lt;center&gt;6.2/10&lt;/center&gt;
|IGN_PSP =&lt;center&gt;5/10&lt;/center&gt;
|IGN_DS =&lt;center&gt;7.9/10&lt;/center&gt;
|IGN_PS2 =&lt;center&gt;6.2/10&lt;/center&gt;
|IGN_PC =&lt;center&gt;6.9/10&lt;/center&gt;
}}

''ProStreet'' has received mixed reviews from critics. [[Game Informer]] and [[GameSpot]] have cited the lack of police in the game, the handling of cars being unrealistic, and the fact that ''ProStreet'' strays away from its traditional roots of street racing as reasons for the ratings, as well &quot;an overload of [[in-game advertising]] and a higher hardware requirement (causing poor sales on the Windows version).&quot; [[IGN]].com mentioned the common complaint that all of the cars had shoddy performance and terribly unrealistic handling. ''[[videoGaiden]]'' lambasted the game in its 2007 Christmas special, having harshly criticised its predecessors in the previous two years. The main criticism was that the game was as lacking in substance as the previous installments, but also lacked the high production values of those titles. These were the lowest ratings ever in the series despite higher sales of the next game, ''Undercover''.

The [[PlayStation 2]] and [[Wii]] versions were also criticized due to missing content, downgraded graphics and frame rate issues.

==Soundtrack==
On September 7, 2007 [[DJ]], [[record producer]] and [[Musician]] [[Junkie XL]] released a single entitled &quot;More&quot; in conjunction with [[Electronic Arts|EA]]'s ''Need For Speed: ProStreet'' videogame.&lt;ref&gt;[http://music.ign.com/articles/818/818659p1.html Junkie XL]&lt;/ref&gt; JXL was asked to compose the score of the game, the game also included 34 songs as part of its soundtrack.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.dmwmedia.com/news/2007/09/28/ea-details-soundtrack-junkie-xl-score-for-need-for-speed-prostreet EA Details Soundtrack, Junkie XL Score for &quot;Need for Speed ProStreet&quot; | Digital Media Wire&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;.

==Controversy==
===Models controversy===
The advertisement of the game has recently come under critical fire for featuring topless models in certain ads. UK promotional material for the game featured in ''[[The Sun (newspaper)|The Sun]]'' advertised the game with its [[Page Three Girl]]s, [[Becky Rule]] and [[Amii Grove]]
posing topless.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.n4g.com/News-87954.aspx N4G.com : Topless girls used to promote The Need For Speed Pro Street in the UK&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt; Electronic Arts claims that  the ads &quot;slipped through the proper EA approval process.&quot; As a result, the ads have been removed.&lt;ref name=&quot;models&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.joystiq.com/2007/11/27/ea-repents-use-of-topless-models-in-need-for-speed-ads/ |title=EA repents use of topless models in Need for Speed ads |date=2007-11-27 |publisher=Joystiq |accessdate=2007-11-27 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

==References==
{{reflist}}

==External links==
* [http://www.ea.com/prostreet Official ''NFS:PS'' website]
* [http://www.needforspeed.com/ Official ''NFS'' franchise website]

{{Need for Speed series}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Need For Speed: Prostreet}}
[[Category:2007 video games]]
[[Category:Electronic Arts games]]
[[Category:Mobile phone games]]
[[Category:Need for Speed games|* 11]]
[[Category:Nintendo DS games]]
[[Category:PlayStation 2 games]]
[[Category:PlayStation 3 games]]
[[Category:PlayStation Portable games]]
[[Category:Video games developed in Canada]]
[[Category:Video games set in Chicago, Illinois]]
[[Category:Video games set in Tokyo]]
[[Category:Wii games]]
[[Category:Windows games]]
[[Category:Xbox 360 games]]

[[ca:Need for Speed: ProStreet]]
[[da:Need for Speed: ProStreet]]
[[de:Need for Speed: ProStreet]]
[[et:Need for Speed: ProStreet]]
[[es:Need for Speed: ProStreet]]
[[fa:جنون سرعت: پرو استریت]]
[[fr:Need for Speed: ProStreet]]
[[ko:니드 포 스피드: 프로스트리트]]
[[it:Need for Speed: ProStreet]]
[[lv:Need for Speed: ProStreet]]
[[lt:Need for Speed: ProStreet]]
[[nl:Need for Speed: Pro Street]]
[[ja:ニード・フォー・スピード プロストリート]]
[[no:Need for Speed: ProStreet]]
[[pl:Need for Speed: ProStreet]]
[[pt:Need for Speed: ProStreet]]
[[ru:Need for Speed: ProStreet]]
[[sr:Need for Speed: ProStreet]]
[[fi:Need for Speed: ProStreet]]
[[sv:Need for Speed: Prostreet]]
[[zh:極速快感：職業街頭]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
