<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><redirects><r from="Contra Informação" to="RTP1" /></redirects><pages><page pageid="2636100" ns="0" title="RTP1"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Infobox TV channel
| name             = RTP1
| logofile         = RTP1.PNG
| logosize         = 250px
| logoalt          = 
| launch           = March 7, 1957 
| picture format= '''Resolution:'''&lt;br&gt;[[576i]] ([[PAL]])&lt;br&gt;'''Aspect Ratio:'''&lt;br&gt;[[4:3]]
| share            = 19.7%
| share as of      = Oct '11
| share source     = [http://www.marktest.com/wap/a/n/id~1892.aspx]
| owner            = [[Rádio e Televisão de Portugal]]
| former names     = RTP &lt;small&gt;(March 7, 1957 - December 24, 1968)&lt;/small&gt;&lt;br&gt;RTP Canal 1 &lt;small&gt;(December 25, 1968 - September 17, 1990)&lt;/small&gt;&lt;br&gt;Canal 1 &lt;small&gt;(September 17, 1990 - April 29, 1996)&lt;/small&gt;
| sister names     = [[RTP2]]&lt;br&gt;[[RTP HD]]
| headquarters     = [[Lisbon]]
| slogan           =''Saia da rotina. Entre na RTP1.'' &lt;small&gt;Leave the routine. Get in the RTP1.&lt;/small&gt;
| timeshift names  = 
| web              = [http://rtp.pt www.rtp.pt]
| terr serv 1      = Analogue
| terr chan 1      = Channel 1 (Until 2012)
| terr serv 2      = [[Digital Terrestrial Television in Portugal|Digital]]
| terr chan 2      = Channel 1 (Channel 2 in Madeira and Azores)
| sat serv 1       = [[ZON Multimédia|ZON TV]] 
| sat chan 1       = Channel 1
| sat serv 3       = [[Meo (Portugal)|meo satélite]]
| sat chan 3       = Channel 1
| cable serv 1     = [[ZON Multimédia|ZON TV]]
| cable chan 1     = Channel 1
| cable serv 3     = [[Cabovisão]]
| cable chan 3     = Channel 1
| sat radio serv 1 = 
| sat radio chan 1 = 
| adsl serv 1      = [[Meo (Portugal)|meo]]
| adsl chan 1      = Channel 1
| adsl serv 2      = [[Optimus Clix|Optimus Clix TV]]
| adsl chan 2      = Channel 1
| adsl serv 3      = [[Vodafone Portugal|Vodafone Casa TV]]
| adsl chan 3      = Channel 1
| country          = [[Portugal]]
| broadcast area   = Portugal
| network_type     = [[Terrestrial television|Terrestrial]], [[Cable television|Cable]], [[Satellite television|Satellite]] and [[IPTV]] [[television network]]|  
}}

'''RTP1''' is the first [[television network]] of [[Rádio e Televisão de Portugal]], the [[Portugal|Portuguese]] [[public broadcasting]] corporation. The first television network (treated by many as a station) ever launched in Portugal, RTP1 was launched in [[1957]] as RTP (and today it is still sometimes marketed as such), and also having a brief period while it was known and marketed as '''Canal 1''' (Channel 1). It is one of the most watched television networks in the country. The network became a 24-hours service in [[2002]].

RTP1 has a generalist programming, composed mainly of news and talk shows, sports, factual, national and international fiction, such as films and TV series. Unlike sister channel [[RTP2]], RTP1 broadcasts commercial advertising, which, along with government grants, finances the network.

==Identity==
[[File:RTP1 old logo.svg|100px|thumb|left|RTP1's former logo (2002-2004)]]
[[File:Rtp1ident2009.jpg|200px|thumb|right|RTP1 current ident layout, in use since 7.1.2009]]
RTP1's logotype has been changed various times over the years. In 1990, RTP1 was renamed TV1, later Canal 1, and a permanent, opaque and coloured [[Digital on-screen graphic|DOG]] &quot;'''C·1'''&quot; was introduced in the upper-right corner of the channel until September 1991, when a smaller &quot;'''C·1'''&quot; was placed on the upper-left corner. The logotype consisted of blue, [[Three-dimensional space|3D]] characters with a golden [[armillary sphere]] inside the &quot;C&quot;. Most Canal 1 idents were [[Computer-generated imagery|CGI]], accompanied by a voice-over chorus singing the name of the channel, and featured several motifs in a short space of time, such as British and American skylines, playing cards, roulettes, riots and astronauts.
On April 29, 1996, Canal 1 was again renamed RTP1, and the new logotype consisted of a white &quot;1&quot; in a light blue background, with the letters &quot;RTP&quot; underneath in white, overlaid in a dark blue background. RTP1 idents consisted mainly on a tridimensional representation of the logo in a blue moving curtain background, with the channel tune played in piano and organ as the background music.

In January 2002, RTP1's logo changed again, and the idents featured it forming from snow, fire and sand.

Since the logo was again changed on March 7, 2004, RTP1 has only used one ident at any period of time, instead of having a collection of idents (sister channel RTP2, for example).

On January 7, 2009, the channel changed its identity. Now it is a variety of mini-films reproduced inside the RTP logo on a black background.

==Programs==
===News===
* Bom Dia Portugal (Good Morning Portugal)
* [[Telejornal (Portugal)|Telejornal]] (Telejournal)
* Jornal da Tarde (Midday News)
* Portugal em Direto (Portugal Live)
* Especial Informação
* Linha da Frente

===Shows===
* '''Praça Da Alegria''' (Merriness Square), a daily variety talk-show broadcast on weekdays between 10 a.m. and 1 p.m. It targets the more elderly and illiterate part of the population, with human interest stories, performances by [[pimba]] musicians and [[redneck]] comedy skits. It is broadcast continuously since [[1995]]. Doesn't broadcast on Summer.
* '''Portugal no Coração''' (Portugal in the Heart), another daily variety talk-show also broadcast on weekdays between 3 p.m. and 6 p.m. Also features interviews, live performances and human interest stories, but with a broader target and appeal. These two talk-shows are often criticized for their long running time, less educated target demographics and for competing with other private television stations with the same format, at the same times of the day. Doesn't broadcast on Summer.
* '''Top +''', a weekly music chart show similar in concept to [[Top of the Pops]]. It is broadcast continuously on Saturday afternoons since 1991, and is commissioned by the Associação Fonográfica Portuguesa, the chart organization of the country. It features live performances, music videos, music festivals coverage and interviews.
* '''Programa das Festas''', it's broadcast every Saturday, covering a local festivity in a Portuguese town. Doesn't broadcast on Summer.
* '''Verão Total''', it's a Summer show used to fill in for &quot;Praça da Alegria&quot;, &quot;Portugal no Coração&quot; and &quot;Programa das Festas&quot;, The show it's broadcast from a different town everyday.

===TV Series===
====Portuguese====
* ''Maternidade'' (Sundays at 7:00pm WET)&lt;sup&gt;HD&lt;/sup&gt;
* ''Viver é Fácil'' (New comedy Coming Soon)
* ''Voo Directo'' (Fridays at 9:00pm WET)&lt;sup&gt;HD&lt;/sup&gt;
* ''Liberdade 21'' (Sundays at 10:00pm WET)&lt;sup&gt;HD&lt;/sup&gt;
* ''A Sagrada Família'' (Wednesdays at 10:30pm WET)

====Foreign====
* ''[[Alarm für Cobra 11 – Die Autobahnpolizei]]'' (Alerta Cobra) - Coming Soon
* ''[[Human Target]]'' (Alvo Humano) - Fridays at 11:30pm
* ''[[Vampire Diaries]]'' (Diários do Vampiro) - Sundays at 3:30pm
* ''[[Lost (TV series)|Lost]]'' (Perdidos) - out of the air, season 6 finale aired on 9th May 2011, at 1:00am
* ''[[True Blood]]'' (Sangue Fresco) - Out of the air, season 2 ended. Season 3 coming soon.
* ''[[V (2009 TV series)|V]]'' - Out of the air, season 1 ended.
* ''[[Undercovers_(TV_series)|Undercovers]]'' (Infiltrados) - Saturdays 4:00pm
* ''[[Californication_(TV_series)|Californication]]'' - Saturdays 11-11:30pm - Season 3 finale on 23rd July 2011.
* ''[[Brothers_%26_Sisters_(2006_TV_series)|Brothers &amp; Sisters]]'' (Irmãos e Irmãs) - Season 5 premiere on 11th July 2011 - Mondays, Tuesdays, Thursdays and Fridays 1:00 am

===Game Shows===
* O Preço Certo  ([[The Price is Right]])
* [[Quem quer ser milionário?|Quem Quer Ser Milionário: Alta Pressão]] (Who Wants to Be a Millionaire?: Hot Seat)

===Soap Operas===
* [[Ribeirão do Tempo]]
* [[Revelação]]

===Late-night Talk Shows===
*Nico à Noite
*Herman 2011

===Comedy Shows===
*Último a Sair (a parody to reality shows, in similar schema to [[Big Brother (TV series)|Big Brother]])
*Estado de Graça

===[[RTP Desporto|Sports Events and Shows]]===
* [[UEFA Champions League]]&lt;sup&gt;HD&lt;/sup&gt;
* [[Portugal_national_football_team#Recent_results_and_forthcoming_fixtures|Portugal national football team qualifying and friendly matches]]&lt;sup&gt;HD&lt;/sup&gt;
* [[Portugal_national_under-21_football_team#Recent_results_and_forthcoming_fixtures|Portugal national under-21 football team qualifying and friendly matches]]
* [[Meia-Maratona de Lisboa]]
* [[Meia-Maratona do Porto]]
* [[Volta a Portugal]]
* [[2012 Olympic Games]]&lt;sup&gt;HD&lt;/sup&gt;
* [[UEFA Euro 2012]]&lt;sup&gt;HD&lt;/sup&gt;

&lt;sup&gt;HD&lt;/sup&gt; - Programming that is or will be broadcast in HD.

==External links==
*[http://rtp.pt Official Site] {{pt icon}}
*[http://www.telesport24.com/tv/35/RTP-1.html RTP1 Live] 

{{Rádio e Televisão de Portugal}}
{{Portuguese television stations}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Rtp1}}
[[Category:Television stations in Portugal]]
[[Category:Television channels and stations established in 1957]]
[[Category:Portuguese-language television stations]]
[[Category:1957 establishments in Portugal]]
[[Category:Rádio e Televisão de Portugal]]

[[ca:RTP1]]
[[es:RTP1]]
[[fr:RTP1]]
[[it:RTP1]]
[[pt:RTP1]]
[[fi:RTP 1]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
