<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><redirects><r from="Colonel Olrik" to="Blake and Mortimer" /></redirects><pages><page pageid="971343" ns="0" title="Blake and Mortimer"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Infobox comic book title
 
| title = Blake and Mortimer &lt;br/&gt; (Les Aventures de Blake et Mortimer)
| image = Blake and Mortimer.png
| caption = 
| schedule = 
| format = 
| publisher = ''[[Tintin (magazine)]]''&lt;br/&gt;''[[Le Lombard|Editions du Lombard]]''&lt;br/&gt;''[[Média-Participations|Editions Blake et Mortimer]]'' &lt;br/&gt; [[Cinebook Ltd]] (in English)
| date = 1946–Present
| genre = [[Science-Fiction]]&lt;br/&gt;[[Adventure]]
| issues = 
| main_char_team = Blake &lt;br/&gt; Mortimer &lt;br/&gt; Olrik
| language = [[French]]
| writers = [[Edgar P. Jacobs]]&lt;br/&gt;[[Jean Van Hamme]]&lt;br/&gt;[[Yves Sente]]
| artists = [[Edgar P. Jacobs]]&lt;br/&gt;[[Bob de Moor]]&lt;br/&gt;[[Ted Benoît]]&lt;br/&gt;[[André Juillard]]
| pencillers = 
| inkers = 
| colorists = 
| creative_team_month = 
| creative_team_year = 
| language = [[French]]
| creators = [[Edgar P. Jacobs]]
}}
'''''Blake and Mortimer''''' is a [[Belgian comics]] series created by the [[Belgium|Belgian]] [[comic book creator|writer]] and [[comics artist]] [[Edgar P. Jacobs]]. It was one of the first series to appear in the [[Franco-Belgian comics magazines|Belgian comics magazine]] ''[[Tintin (magazine)|Tintin]]'' in 1946, and was subsequently published in book form by [[Le Lombard|Les Editions du Lombard]].

The main protagonists of the adventures are Philip Mortimer, a leading [[United Kingdom|British]] scientist, and his friend Captain Francis Blake of [[MI5]]. The main antagonist is their sworn enemy, Colonel Olrik, who has appeared in all but one of the books. Their confrontations take them into the realms of [[detective fiction|detective investigation]] and [[science-fiction]], dealing with such themes as time travel, [[Atlantis]] and [[espionage]].

The books by Jacobs himself are generally set in the very period of their writing, but those authored by others after his death are explicitly set in the 1950s only. 

Since the death of Jacobs, new books have been published by two separate teams of artists and writers. A television series based upon the series was produced in 1997, entitled ''[[Blake and Mortimer (TV series)|Blake and Mortimer]]''.

==Publication history==

===Jacobs===
When ''[[Tintin magazine]]'' was launched on September 26, 1946, it included the story, ''Le secret de l’Espadon'' (''[[The Secret of the Swordfish]]'') which introduced the characters of Captain Francis Blake of the British Intelligence Service, his friend Professor Philip Mortimer, a leading physicist, and their sworn enemy Colonel Olrik.&lt;ref name=BDO-t1&gt;{{Cite web|last=BDoubliées|title=Tintin année 1946|url=http://bdoubliees.com/tintinbelge/annees/1946.htm|language=French}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The epic of the ''Swordfish'' ended in 1949 but Olrik, Blake and Mortimer continued their conflict through a whole series of science-fiction/detective stories that saw them go all the way from the lost continent of [[Atlantis]] to the [[Catacombs of Paris]]

After Jacobs’ death in 1987, [[Bob de Moor]] completed his unfinished last story. In the mid-1990s the series was continued by the Jacobs Studios with two teams of writers and artists: [[Jean Van Hamme|Van Hamme]]/[[Ted Benoit|Benoit]] and [[Yves Sente|Sente]]/[[André Juillard|Juillard]]. The series was still firmly set in the 1950s and included many new regular supporting characters, most notably Blake's colleagues in the security services.

===Post-Jacobs===
From 1987, the Jacobs [[Estate (law)|estate]], centred around the still-going Jacobs Studios, republished all of Jacobs’s works. In the 1990s, after much debate about story authenticity, [[Dargaud]] got permission to revive the ''Blake and Mortimer'' series with a set of new stories by a new team of author/draughtsman. Famous scenarist [[Jean Van Hamme]] provided the storylines while [[Ligne claire]] specialist draughtsman [[Ted Benoit]] (whose style resembles the later Jacobs's) was contracted for the artwork.

1996 saw the publication of ''The Francis Blake Affair''. Purists immediately objected to the choice of Van Hamme and, upon publication, went on to discover some typical Van Hamme plot twists they disliked. Jacobs' science-fiction was noticeably absent with the story focusing on espionage. However the book became a relative success and the publisher decided to continue the line. In the meantime however both Benoit and Van Hamme were tied up on other projects and work on the next book started to lag. As an interim solution, writer  [[Yves Sente]] and artist [[André Juillard]] were contracted to publish another adventure, ''The Voronov Plot'' (1998) which took its theme from the [[Cold War]].

Finally, Van Hamme and Benoit managed to finish their album and ''The Strange Encounter'' appeared in 2001, with Blake and Mortimer confronting mysterious alien creatures.

This was followed by Sente and Juillard's two-book adventure: ''The Sarcophagi of the Sixth Continent'' (volume 1,''The Universal Threat'' in 2003; volume 2, ''Battle of the Minds'' in 2004) which also dealt with Blake and Mortimer's youth and how they first met in pre-independence [[India]].

In 2008 Sente and Juillar released another book entitled ''[[The Gondwana Shrine]]'' which chronologically follows the events of ''[[The Sarcophagi of the Sixth Continent]]''.

The next adventure in the series, ''[[The Curse of the Thirty Denarii]]'', is divided in two volumes and is written by Jean Van Hamme. The first volume, titled ''Le Manuscript de Nicodemus'' (''The Manuscript of Nicodemus''), was drawn by René Sterne who suddenly died on November 15, 2006, delaying the publication of the book. Sterne's girlfriend Chantal De Spiegeleer eventually completed his work which was published on the 20th November 2009. Aubin Frechon drew the second volume of the adventure, which was published 26 November 2010.

==Main characters==
The three main characters of the series were already present in slightly different form in the unrelated, first full length [[comic strip]] by Jacobs, ''[[Le Rayon U]]'' (''The U-Ray'', 1943), which took a lot of its inspiration from [[Flash Gordon]]. The characters of Lord Calder, Professor Marduk and Captain Dagon can be connected to Blake, Mortimer and Olrik respectively.{{Citation needed|date=February 2010}}

In the original Jacobs' version it is not specified that Blake and Mortimer are Welsh and Scottish. They are simply two proud Britons serving HM's Government. The post-Jacobs title, ''The Sarcophagi of the Sixth Continent'', dwells on their early lives, showing how they met in [[colony|colonial]] [[India]].
*'''Professor Philip Angus Mortimer''' — a leading [[physicist]] of [[Scotland|Scottish]] descent, he grew up in [[British Raj]] and is the [[archetype|archetypical]] [[United Kingdom|British]] [[gentleman]] [[scholar]].
*'''Captain Francis Percy Blake''' — [[Wales|Welsh]]-born [[officer (armed forces)|officer]] in [[Elizabeth II of the United Kingdom|Her Majesty]]'s [[army|armed forces]]. He studied at [[University of Oxford|Oxford]]&lt;ref&gt;mentioned in a newspaper article about him in ''[[The Mystery of the Great Pyramid, Volume 1: Manetho's Papyrus|The Mystery of the Great Pyramid]]''&lt;/ref&gt; and later became head of the British Security Service [[MI5]] but is still very active in the field. He is a master of disguise, even fooling Mortimer on occasion.
[[File:Olrik.png|thumb|120px|'''Colonel Olrik''']]
*'''Colonel Olrik''' — the perennial [[villain]] from the first instalment onwards. Of the original series there was only one book that did not feature him in one capacity or other: ''[[The Time Trap (comic book)|Le Piège diabolique]]'' (''The Time Trap''). Olrik started out in ''The Secret of the Swordfish '' as the head of [[Intelligence (information gathering)|intelligence]] for [[Far East|Oriental]] [[dictator]] Basam Damdu. His activities have since ranged from [[mercenary]], [[spy]], [[smuggler]] and general [[crime|criminal]] [[adventurer]].

Philip Mortimer was based upon a friend and sometimes collaborator of Jacobs, [[Jacques Van Melkebeke]]. There was one imaginative addition by Jacobs since Van Melkebeke had no beard. Francis Blake was modeled by another friend and sometimes collaborator of Jacobs, Jacques Laudy, with added mustache. Olrik was a self-portrait of Jacobs.

==Story characteristics==
Although the series is (no doubt for reasons of [[euphony]]) called ''Blake and Mortimer'', it is Professor Mortimer who is the main [[protagonist]]. In the original series, it is mainly he who, through his impulsive character, gets entangled in adventurous circumstances. Blake is the straight man, the serious army officer who comes to the rescue. On the bad-guy side, Colonel Olrik combines characteristics of both heroes.

Blake and Mortimer are sometimes shown to live in the same house, sharing an [[apartment]] in the same manner as [[Sherlock Holmes]] and [[John Watson (Sherlock Holmes)|Doctor Watson]]. Many Belgian comics have had similar themes of confirmed bachelors living together, including [[Tintin (character)|Tintin]] and [[Captain Haddock]], [[Spirou &amp; Fantasio]] and [[Tif et Tondu|Tif &amp; Tondu]].

Jacobs always drew his stories as being contemporary, and so the first few titles have a 1950s look and feel while the last installment looks decidedly 1970s. One exception to this rule is, again, ''Time Trap'', which starts in the present (i.e. early sixties) but whose action, due to a [[malfunction]]ing [[Time travel|time machine]], largely takes place in the 51st century, and includes a short ventures in [[Middle Ages|medieval times]] and a stopover in the [[Jurassic]] period. Post-Jacobs stories are based in the 1950s.

The layout in most of the stories include some similarities: when the adventure begins certain important but unseen events have already taken place: at the beginning of ''The Yellow Mark'', for instance, the titular character has already made himself known through various activities which the reader only learns about when Mortimer reads a newspaper about these events.

Some of the adventures also end with the characters reflecting on what they have learned from their experiences: after his travels through time in ''Time Trap'', Mortimer concludes that rather than dwell on the &quot;good old days&quot; or look forward to a &quot;brighter future&quot;, one should be content with the present.

==List of titles==
[[File:Blake and m.jpg|thumb|200px|English translation ''The Yellow '&quot;M&quot;'']]
[[File:The Francis Blake Affair.png|200px|thumb|The thirteenth book in the series, ''The Francis Blake Affair'', the first book not to be written by Jacobs.]]
Writers’ credits:&lt;br /&gt;
1-11: story and images by [[Edgar P. Jacobs]]&lt;br /&gt;
12: story by Edgar P. Jacobs, images by [[Bob de Moor]]&lt;br /&gt;
13, 15: story by [[Jean Van Hamme]], images by [[Ted Benoit]]&lt;br /&gt;
14, 16-17, 18: story by [[Yves Sente]], images by [[André Juillard]]&lt;br /&gt;
19: story by [[Jean Van Hamme]], images by [[René Sterne]] &amp; [[Chantal De Spiegeleer]]&lt;br /&gt;
20: story by [[Jean Van Hamme]], images by [[Aubin Frechon]]

{{col-begin|width=}}
{{col-break}}
:1. '''''[[The Secret of the Swordfish|The Secret of the Swordfish Volume 1: Ruthless Pursuit]]''''', 1950
:2. '''''[[The Secret of the Swordfish|The Secret of the Swordfish Volume 2: Mortimer's Escape]]''''', 1953
:3. '''''[[The Secret of the Swordfish|The Secret of the Swordfish Volume 3: SX1 Counterattacks]]''''', 1953
:4. '''''[[The Mystery of the Great Pyramid, Volume 1: Manetho's Papyrus]]''''', 1954
:5. '''''[[The Mystery of the Great Pyramid Volume 2: The Chamber of Horus]]''''', 1955
:6. '''''[[The Yellow &quot;M&quot;]]''''', 1956
:7. '''''[[Atlantis Mystery]]''''', 1957
:8. '''''[[S.O.S. Meteors: Mortimer in Paris]]''''', 1959
:9. '''''[[The Time Trap (comic book)|The Time Trap]]''''', 1962
:10. '''''[[The Necklace Affair (comics)|The Necklace Affair]]''''', 1967
:11. '''''[[Professor Sató's Three Formulae, Volume 1: Mortimer in Tokyo]]''''', 1977
:12. '''''[[Professor Sató's Three Formulae, Volume 2: Mortimer vs. Mortimer]]''''', 1990
:13. '''''[[The Francis Blake Affair]]''''', 1996
:14. '''''[[The Voronov Plot]]''''', 2000
:15. '''''[[The Strange Encounter]]''''', 2001
:16. '''''[[The Sarcophagi of the Sixth Continent, Volume 1: The Universal Threat]]''''', 2003
:17. '''''[[The Sarcophagi of the Sixth Continent, Volume 2: Battle of the Minds]]''''', 2004
:18. '''''[[The Gondwana Shrine]]''''', 2008
:19. '''''[[The Curse of the Thirty Denarii]], Volume 1: The manuscript of Nicodemus''''', 2009
:20. '''''[[The Curse of the Thirty Denarii]], Volume 2: The gate of Orpheus''''', 2010

&lt;br&gt;&lt;center&gt;&lt;small&gt;&lt;/small&gt;
{{col-end}}
Additionally, the storyboard sketches by Jacobs of Volume 12, left incomplete at the time of his death, have been re-issued in 1996 outside of the series as ''Dossier Mortimer contre Mortimer'' (ISBN 2-87097-022-6).

==Timeline==
in progress
{| class=&quot;wikitable&quot;
|-
! Volume (first publication) !! New volume !! Time references !! Recurring persons
|-
|YellowM  || ||  p24, p35, p53: The Mega Wave, 1920–1922  || 
|-
|  ||SarcoSC ||  1922 ? Shimla, India, Mortimer youth || Sarah Summertown
|-
| || || WWII: 1 September 1939 - 14 August 1945 || 
|-
| SSwordf &lt;br /&gt;
26. Sept. 1946-49 
|
|
p5: &quot;3 years of cold war&quot;&lt;br /&gt;
p9: &quot;...Luftwaffe, Berlin, ... reduced once more to rubble&quot; ref to WWII &lt;br /&gt;
StEnc p41: date of war given as 1946
 | Olrik, Basam Damdu, Le Bezendjas &lt;br /&gt;
Nasir
|-
| || || 15 August 1947: Independence of India and Pakistan || 
|-
| MGPyr&lt;br /&gt;
24 Mar 1950-51
|
|
p5: ref to SSwordf&lt;br /&gt;
End: Olrik lost his mind, staggers into the desert.  
| Olrik, Sharkey, Jack, Razul (p31) Le Bezendjas &lt;br /&gt;
Nasir
|-
| YellowM&lt;br /&gt;
6. Aug 1953-54
| 
| 
p5: ref to WWII &quot;El Alamein&quot;&lt;br /&gt;
p14: 18 Dec&lt;br /&gt;
p51: ref to SSwordf, MGPyr&lt;br /&gt;
p54: How Olrik is picked up in Sudan* &lt;br /&gt;
p55: &quot;Luftwaffe&quot;, ref to WWII&lt;br /&gt;
p70: Christmas&lt;br /&gt;
| Olrik &lt;br /&gt;
Nasir, Mrs. Benson, Chief Inspector Glenn Kendall
|-
| || AFBlake || p15: Chacmool, ref to AtlantM? 
p37: 10. June 1954
| 
Olrik, Jack &lt;br /&gt;
Mrs. Benson, David Honeychurch, Chief Inspector Glenn Kendall
|-
| || StEnc || p5: 15 Sept. 1954 &lt;br /&gt;
p6: ref to SSwordf &lt;br /&gt;
p26: ref to YellowM &lt;br /&gt;
p50, 52: 17 Oct. 1954 (Comet Tempel) &lt;br /&gt;
End: Olrik in prison
|
Olrik, Basam Damdu &lt;br /&gt;
John Calloway, Jessie Wingo, Géronimo Ramirez
|-
| || CTDenar || p3: 27 Aug&lt;br /&gt;
p5, p7: ref to StEnc
p5: 2 weeks later, Olrik escapes from prison&lt;br /&gt;
p22, p39: refs to WWII (von Stahl, Nazis)&lt;br /&gt;
vol.II p55: 1955 (military coup in Greece 12 years later, i.e. 1967) 
|
Olrik, Jack &lt;br /&gt;
John Calloway, Jessie Wingo
|-
| AtlantM&lt;br /&gt;
19 Oct 1955-56 
|
| 
|
Olrik, Sharkey (?, 1 panel only)
|-
|  || VoronP  || p3: 16 Jan. p8: 25 Mar. p11: 15 Apr. &lt;br /&gt;
p10: ref to SSwordf &lt;br /&gt;
p14: 20 Apr. p17: 2 May. p35: 5 May. p42: 20 May. p45: 21 June, 25 June&lt;br /&gt;
p46, p52: 750th anniversary of Liverpool's charter (1957)&lt;br /&gt;
p26: 26 June. p50: 1 July. p52: 6 July. p59: 10 July. &lt;br /&gt;
p60: 19 Aug 1957, 2 Sept 1957, 27 Sept 1957&lt;br /&gt;
p61: 3 Oct. p62: 4 Oct, Sputnik (1957)&lt;br /&gt;
p61: Olrik tries to escape from KGB
|
Olrik, Major Varitch&lt;br /&gt;
Nastasia Wardynska, Chief Inspector Glenn Kendall, David Honeychurch
|-
| ||SarcoSC || Follows VoronP
Olrik taken from gulag, 
story start 1. Feb. 1958&lt;br /&gt;
Expo 58 in Belgium: 17 April to 19 Oct 1958 
|
Olrik, Major Varitch&lt;br /&gt;
Nasir, Mrs. Benson, Géronimo Ramirez, Prof. Labrousse
|-
|  || GondS  || p6: follows directly to SarcoSC, p9: about 3 months after preparation for Expo 58 =&gt; 1958 &lt;br /&gt;
p6: ref to SarcoSC. p7: ref to VoronP. p8: ref to YellowM&lt;br /&gt;
| Olrik, Razul le Bezendjas, Youssef&lt;br /&gt;
Sarah Summertown, Nastasia Wardinska, Mrs. Benson, David Honeychurch
Prof. Labrousse
|-
| SOSMet 8. Jan 1958  || || p3: 20. Feb, 22. Feb, 6 May, H-Bomb (November 1, 1952) &lt;br /&gt;
End: Olrik, Sharkey arrested 

Based on a detailed analysis of weather and cars, the story should take place in 1958 ([http://www.sosmeteores.net www.sosmeteores.net]),
although this is not possible anymore, since SarcoSC and GondS take place in 1958
|
Olrik, Sharkey, Prof. Miloch&lt;br /&gt;
Inspector Pradier, Prof. Labrousse
|-
| TimeT 22. Sept 1960 || || p3: ref to SOSMet &lt;br /&gt;
p6: Miloch survived several months after SOSMet. Story follows SOSMet.&lt;br /&gt;
p63: 10 Nov.
 | Prof. Miloch &lt;br /&gt;
Inspector Pradier
|-
| NeckA 23. March 1965 || || p3: &quot;178 after the affair in 1785&quot; =&gt; 1963&lt;br /&gt;
p4: Olrik escapes from prison&lt;br /&gt;
p7: ref to SOSMet
|
Olrik, Sharkey&lt;br /&gt;
Inspector Pradier
|-
| SatosTF 5. Oct 1971 (start work 1967) || || || Olrik, Sharkey
|}

&lt;nowiki&gt;*&lt;/nowiki&gt; Major inconsistency, since Olrik was supposed to be picked up before WWII/SSwordf, which happens before MGPyr.

==English translation and publication==
Like many Franco-Belgian comics, ''Blake and Mortimer'' initially had limited publication in English. [[Cinebook Ltd]] have now published the majority of the series. 

The Blake and Mortimer Editions published English translations of all three parts of ''The Secret of the Swordfish'' in 1986, both parts of ''The Mystery of the Great Pyramid'' in 1987 and ''The Yellow &quot;M&quot;'' in 1988.

[[Catalan Communications]], under its 'Comcat' line of books, published two books in inexpensive trade paperback copies in the US. They released:
#''The Time Trap'' (''Le Piège diabolique'') (1989)
#''Atlantis Mystery'' (''L'Énigme de l'Atlantide'') (1990)

There were also plans to release ''Secret of the Great Pyramid'' in 2 volumes, and then ''The Yellow Mark'', but the company went under before they could get a chance to realize them.

[[Cinebook Ltd]] have been publishing English language translations of ''Blake and Mortimer'' since 2007. The following volumes have been released to date:&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url = http://www.cinebook.co.uk/index.php?cPath=156 |title = Cinebook catalogue - Blake and Mortimer |accessdate = 2008-10-08 |last = Cinebook: The 9th Art Publisher }}&lt;/ref&gt;
*''The Yellow ‘M’'' (published January 2007) &lt;small&gt; ISBN 9781905460212&lt;/small&gt;
*''The Mystery of the Great Pyramid Part 1: The Papyrus of Manethon'' (published November 2007) &lt;small&gt; ISBN 9781905460373&lt;/small&gt;
*''The Mystery of the Great Pyramid Part 2: The Chamber of Horus'' (published January 2008) &lt;small&gt; ISBN 9781905460380&lt;/small&gt;
*''The Francis Blake Affair'' (published September 2008) &lt;small&gt; ISBN 9781905460632&lt;/small&gt;
*''The Strange Encounter'' (published January 2009) &lt;small&gt; ISBN 9781905460755&lt;/small&gt;
*''S.O.S. Meteors'' (published September 2009) &lt;small&gt; ISBN 9781905460977&lt;/small&gt;
*''The Affair of the Necklace'' (published January 2010) &lt;small&gt; ISBN 9781849180375&lt;/small&gt;
*''The Voronov Plot'' (published October 2010) &lt;small&gt; ISBN 9781849180481&lt;/small&gt;
*''The Sarcophagi of the Sixth Continent, part 1'' (published January 2011) &lt;small&gt;ISBN 1849180679&lt;/small&gt;
*''The Sarcophagi of the Sixth Continent, part 2'', (published April 2011) &lt;small&gt;ISBN 9781849180771&lt;/small&gt;
*''The Gondwana Shrine'', (published September 2011) &lt;small&gt;ISBN 9781849180948&lt;/small&gt;
Further volumes are scheduled as follows:&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |last=Van Hamme |first=Jean |authorlink=Jean Van Hamme |coauthors=[[Ted Benoit]] |others=Trans. Jerome Saincantin |title=The Strange Encounter |series=Blake and Mortimer |year=2009 |publisher=Cinebook |location=London |isbn=978-1-905460-75-5 |pages=67 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

*''Atlantis Mystery'', (to be published January 2012)
*''Curse of the 30 Pieces of Silver, part 1'', (to be published April 2012)
*''Curse of the 30 Pieces of Silver, part 2'', (to be published September 2012)

==Adaptations==
===Television series===
'' Main article [[Blake and Mortimer (TV series)]]''
In 1997, the company [[Ellipse Programmé|Ellipse]] made an animated series containing 26 episodes, which made up 13 stories, 4 of which were entirely new and not based on existing books.

===Film adaptations===
Several attempts have been made to make films of ''The Yellow M'', though none have been successful. Spanish director [[Álex de la Iglesia]], however, has announced that he is working on an adaptation of the comic to be released around 2010. It has been said that [[Hugh Laurie]] and [[Kiefer Sutherland]] will be Blake and Mortimer.&lt;ref&gt;Álex de la Iglesia is interviewed in &quot;Noches como ésta&quot; http://pluton.rtve.es/alex-de-la-iglesia-entrevistado-en-en-noches-como-esta.html&lt;/ref&gt;

===Parodies===
Caricatures of ''Blake and Mortimer'' often appear in other comic book series as background or supporting characters, usually when the plot includes a British Empire storyline. For example, they make a one-off appearance in the [[Valérian and Laureline|Valérian]] adventure ''[[On the False Earths]]'' when the hero visits a [[Victorian era|Victorian]] London club.

Another example is the popular Belgian comic series concerning the adventures of [[MI5]] agent [[Clifton (comics)|Colonel Clifton]]. Clifton once featured in a story entitled ''Jade'', published in 2003. In it he meets two characters called Blake and Mortimer, though even as caricatures they bear little resemblance (perhaps deliberately) to Jacob's originals. The story includes elements from the original books, such as the entrance to the secret passage from ''S.O.S. Météores'' and the cave that doubles as a [[submarine]] base in ''L'Affaire Francis Blake''.&lt;ref&gt;''Jade'' ISBN 2-80361-669-6, by [[Bob de Groot]] (writer) and [[Michel Rodrigue]] (artist), published in 2003&lt;/ref&gt;

In 2005 [[Dargaud]] published a parody entitled ''Menaces sur l'Empire'' (&quot;The Empire Under Threat&quot;). This was a humorous presentation of the adventures of Blake and Mortimer and was certainly not part of the [[Canon (fiction)|canon]] (in fact, the space reserved for the series' title reads &quot;Les Aventures de Philip et Francis&quot; as opposed to &quot;Les Aventures de Blake et Mortimer&quot;). Jokes included:
*Mortimer's attempts to break his diet, which his Indian manservant always thwarts, even from a long distance;
*confusion over whether they are working for [[MI5]] or [[MI6]];
*the heroes catching [[Prime Minister of the United Kingdom|Prime Minister]] [[Winston Churchill]] in bed with a young woman who is not his wife;
*a send-up of [[Bruce Lee]]'s ''[[Game of Death]]''.&lt;ref&gt;''Menaces sur l'Empire'' ISBN 2-205-05457-0, by Pierre Veys (writer) and Nicolas Barral (artist)), published in 2005&lt;/ref&gt;

''Tigresse Blanche'' (''White Tigress'') by [[Yann (comics)|Yann]] and [[Conrad (comics)|Conrad]] is another Belgian comic series featuring the adventures of a [[Chinese Communist]] woman spy in post-[[World War II]] [[China]]. It features a British agent, Sir Francis Flake, whose friend (based on Mortimer) gets drunk on the announcement of [[India]]n independence.

==See also==
{{portal|Novels}}
*[[Le Monde's 100 Books of the Century|''Le Monde'''s 100 Books of the Century]]

==Sources==
{{Refbegin}}
*Guyard, Jean-Marc. ''Le baryton du neuvième art''. Brussels: Éditions Blake et Mortimer, 1996. ISBN 2-87328-000-X
*[[Edgar Pierre Jacobs|Jacobs, Edgar P.]] ''Un opéra de papier: Les mémoires de Blake et Mortimer''. Paris: Gallimard, 1981. ISBN 2-07-056090-2
*Lenne, Gérard. ''L'affaire Jacobs''. Paris:  Megawave, 1990. ISBN 2-908910-00-4
*Mouchart, Benoit.  ''A l'ombre de la ligne claire: Jacques Van Melkebeke, le clandestin de la B.D.'' Paris:  Vertige Graphic, 2002. ISBN 2-908981-71-8
*[http://bdoubliees.com/tintinbelge/series1/blakemortimer.htm ''Blake et Mortimer'' publications in Belgian ''Tintin''] and [http://bdoubliees.com/journaltintin/series1/blakemortimer.htm French ''Tintin''] BDoubliées {{fr_icon}}
{{Refend}}
;Footnotes
{{Reflist}}

==External links==
*[http://www.blakeetmortimer.com/ Blake et Mortimer official site] {{fr_icon}}
*[http://www.marquejaune.com/ MarqueJaune] {{fr_icon}}
*[http://www.cinebook.co.uk/index.php?cPath=156 English publisher of Blake and Mortimer - Cinebook Ltd]
*[http://www.fumetti.org/b&amp;m/ Blake et Mortimer in Italy], website by [[Gianfranco Goria]]

{{Blake and Mortimer}}

[[Category:Franco-Belgian comics]]
[[Category:1946 comic debuts]]
[[Category:Comics characters introduced in 1946]]
[[Category:Comics characters]]
[[Category:Belgian comics titles]]
[[Category:Blake and Mortimer| ]]
[[Category:Fictional duos|Blake and Mortimer]]
[[Category:Lombard Editions titles]]

[[br:Blake ha Mortimer]]
[[de:Blake und Mortimer]]
[[es:Blake y Mortimer]]
[[eo:Blake kaj Mortimer]]
[[fa:بلیک و مورتیمر]]
[[fr:Blake et Mortimer]]
[[id:Blake et Mortimer]]
[[it:Blake e Mortimer]]
[[nl:Blake en Mortimer]]
[[pt:Blake &amp; Mortimer]]
[[fi:Blake ja Mortimer]]
[[sv:Blake och Mortimers äventyr]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
