<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><redirects><r from="The ‘Manitoba’ No Reply" to="Jo, Zette and Jocko" /></redirects><pages><page pageid="2779684" ns="0" title="Jo, Zette and Jocko"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{More footnotes|date=April 2010}}
{{Supercbbox|  &lt;!--Wikipedia:WikiProject Comics--&gt;
  title = Jo, Zette and Jocko
| comic_color =background:#c0c0c0
| noimage=yes
| image =
| caption =
| schedule =
| format =
| publisher =
| date = 1935-1958
| issues =
| main_char_team = Jo &lt;br&gt; Zette &lt;br&gt; Jocko
| past_current_color=background:#ff9275
| writers = [[Hergé]]
| artists = [[Hergé]]
| pencillers =
| inkers =
| colorists =
| creative_team_month =
| creative_team_year =
| creators =
}}

'''''The Adventures of Jo, Zette and Jocko''''' is a [[comic book]] (or ''[[Franco-Belgian comics|bande dessinée]]'') series created by [[Hergé]], the [[Belgium|Belgian]] writer-artist who was best known for ''[[The Adventures of Tintin]]''. The heroes of the series are two young children, brother and sister '''Jo and Zette Legrand''' and their pet [[monkey]] '''Jocko'''.

Jo, Zette and Jocko appear on the rear covers of some editions of ''[[The Adventures of Tintin]]'' series but never appear in the stories, while there are a few cheeky allusions to the cosmos of the Tintin adventures within the Jo, Zette and Jocko albums.

==Publication history==
In 1935, six years after ''Tintin'' had first appeared in the pages of ''[[Le Petit Vingtième]]'', Hergé was approached by Father Courtois, director of the weekly French newspaper ''Coeurs Vaillants'' (''Valiant Hearts''). ''Coeurs Vaillants'' also published Tintin's adventures, but while Father Courtois enjoyed ''Tintin'', he wanted a set of characters that would embody classical family values &amp;mdash; a young boy, with a father who works, a mother, a sister and a pet &amp;mdash; in contrast to the more independent Tintin who, the whole of his career, has had no mention of relatives at all.

Inspired by a toy monkey called Jocko, Hergé created Jo Legrand, his sister Zette and their pet monkey Jocko as well as their engineer father, Jacques, and housewife mother. Their first adventure, ''The Secret Ray'' appeared in the pages of ''Coeurs Vaillants'' on January 19, 1936 and ran until June 1937.{{Citation needed|date=June 2007}} It was also published in ''[[Le Petit Vingtième]]'' itself.

Between 1936 and 1957, three complete ''Jo, Zette and Jocko'' adventures would be published, spread across five albums. Hergé however often felt restricted by the family set-up: whereas the older, more independent Tintin could just head off on any adventure, either alone or with [[Captain Haddock]] or [[Professor Calculus]], this was not possible for Jo, Zette and Jocko whose parents had to figure large in any adventure &amp;mdash; usually to act as their rescuers. The stories also lacked the [[Ideology of Tintin|social and political messages of the Tintin stories]]. In the end, these constraints led him to eventually abandon ''Jo, Zette and Jocko'' in the late-1950s.

==Bibliography==
===''The Secret Ray''===
{| border=0
| [[Image:Manitoba.jpg|thumb|none]] ||
1. ''[[The ‘Manitoba’ No Reply]]''&lt;br/&gt;(''Le Manitoba ne répond plus'')&lt;br/&gt;(Volume 1 of ''The Secret Ray'')&lt;br/&gt;
The [[Transatlantic crossing|transatlantic]] [[Ocean liner|liner]] ''Manitoba'' breaks down on its way to [[England]] and then the passengers and crew fall strangely asleep. When they wake up it is to find that they have all been robbed of their valuables. Later, while on holiday at the seaside, Jo, Zette and Jocko, playing in a rowing boat, get lost at sea when a thick fog comes down. Rescued by a [[submarine]], they are taken to a secret undersea base where a mad scientist has plans for the two young children.
|----
| [[Image:Karamako.jpg|thumb|none]] ||
2. ''[[The Eruption of Karamako]]''&lt;br/&gt;(''L’Eruption du Karamako'')&lt;br/&gt;(Volume 2 of ''The Secret Ray'')&lt;br/&gt;
Jo, Zette and Jocko escape the undersea base in an amphibious tank, and end up on an island. But their problems are far from over. They have to deal with [[cannibals]], modern-day [[Piracy|pirates]], an erupting [[volcano]], [[gangsters]], the [[Mass media|media]] and there is still the mad scientist who wants them for his evil plans.&lt;br/&gt;(In one scene Zette is harassed by a representative of Cosmos Pictures which was run by Tintin's enemy [[Rastapopoulos]].)
|}

===''Mr. Pump’s Legacy''===
{| border=0
| [[Image:PumpsLegacy.jpg|thumb|none]] ||
3. ''[[Mr. Pump’s Legacy]]''&lt;br/&gt;(''Le Testament de Monsieur Pump'')&lt;br/&gt;(Volume 1 of ''The Stratoship H.22'')&lt;br/&gt;
Killed while exercising his love for speed in a racing car, millionaire John Archibald Pump leaves behind ten million dollars (a staggeringly large sum for those days). It will go to the builders of the first aeroplane to fly from Paris to New York at 1000 kilometres per hour. Jo and Zette's father sets about designing such a plane, but the project comes under threat from a gang of [[saboteurs]] led by William and Fred Stockrise, Pump's passed-over nephews, who go to all lengths, from theft to bombing, to prevent it.&lt;br/&gt;(A framed photo of Captain Haddock can be seen hanging on the wall of the Legrand living-room just before Mr Legrand switches on the light to confront intruders.)
|----
| [[Image:DestinationNewYork.jpg|thumb|none]] ||
4. ''[[Destination New York]]''&lt;br/&gt;(''Destination New York'')&lt;br/&gt;(Volume 2 of ''The Stratoship H.22'')&lt;br/&gt;
When the Stratoship H.22, designed by their father, is the subject of an attempted bombing from the air, Jo and Zette fly it out of its [[hangar]] but are unable to get back. Crash-landing near the [[North Pole]] they face a race against time to get the plane back home and win the trans-Atlantic challenge. But the Stockrise brothers and their gang are still determined to thwart the operation even if it is successful.
|}

===The Valley of the Cobras===
{| border=0
| &lt;!-- [[Image:valcob.jpg]] --&gt; ||
5. ''[[The Valley of the Cobras]]''&lt;br/&gt;(''La Vallée des cobras'')&lt;br/&gt;
The [[Maharajah]] of Gopal is a bad-tempered sort of person, whose behaviour ranges from the childish to the eccentric, and his long-suffering secretary Badalah is usually on the receiving end. Nevertheless, Jo and Zette's father agrees to build him a bridge in his kingdom. The problem is there is a group of scoundrels led by Prime Minister Ramahjuni and the evil fakir Rabindah who aren't too keen on the idea.
|}

==Influence on other works==
Aspects of the animated film ''[[Tintin and the Lake of Sharks]]'' (1972), which was not produced by Hergé himself but issued under his name, appears to borrow some elements from the Jo, Zette and Jocko adventure ''The Secret Ray'':
*like in ''The ‘Manitoba’ No Reply'', two children, Niko and Nushka, attempt to escape from an underwater base in a [[tank]]-like vehicle;
*like in ''The Eruption of Karamako'', the underwater compound is destroyed by its evil leader in an attempt to drown his pursuers;
*there is the interaction of children and adults during the final escape;
*and the friends waiting above water and thinking the heroes have been killed when the compound explodes.

==''Le Thermozéro''==
''[[Le Thermozéro]]'' is the sixth, incomplete, Jo, Zette and Jocko adventure. It began in 1958 as a Tintin adventure of the same name. Hergé had asked the French comic book creator [[Greg (comics)|Greg]] (Michel Regnier) to provide a scenario for a new Tintin story. Greg came up with two potential plots: ''Les Pilules'' (''The Pills'') and ''Le Thermozéro''. Hergé made sketches of the first eight pages of ''Le Thermozéro'' &lt;ref&gt;[http://www.angelfire.com/space/u_line/greg.htm Tintin &amp; Greg&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt; before the project was abandoned in 1960 – Hergé deciding that he wished to retain sole creative control of his work.

Sometime after this, Hergé sought to resurrect ''Le Thermozéro'' as a Jo, Zette and Jocko adventure and instructed his long time collaborator [[Bob de Moor]] to work on an outline. Bernard Tordeur of the Hergé Foundation has suggested, at the World of Tintin Conference held at the [[National Maritime Museum]], [[Greenwich]] on May 15, 2004, that a complete draft outline (similar to what survives of ''[[Tintin and Alph-Art]]'') was completed before the project was terminated &lt;ref&gt;[http://www.tintinologist.org/forums/index.php?action=vthread&amp;forum=3&amp;topic=180. Jo, Zette and Jocko: Le ThermoZéro - Tintinologist.org Forums (1)&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt; This draft version of the book apparently survives in the Tintin Archives.{{Citation needed|date=June 2007}}
&lt;!-- OR paragraph until sourced
==Fictional settings==
* [[Gopal]]: fictional country in the Himalayas, where Jo and Zette's father builds a build for the king and keeps the preace. Based on the real life Gopala the founder of the Pala Dynasty of Bengal. (more info needed)
--&gt;

==English translations==
''The Valley of the Cobras'' was the first ''Jo, Zette and Jocko'' adventure to be translated and published in [[English language|English]] in 1986. ''Mr Pump’s Legacy'' and ''Destination New York'' followed in 1987.

''The ‘Manitoba’ No Reply'' and ''The Eruption of Karamako'' remained unpublished (possibly due to Hergé’s unsympathetic depiction of the primitive natives of the island of Karamako, similar to ''[[Tintin in the Congo]]'') until 1994 when they were published together in a single limited-edition double volume titled ''The Secret Ray''.

==Sources==
{{refbegin}}
* [http://bdoubliees.com/tintinbelge/series3/jozettejoko.htm ''Jo, Zette et Jocko'' publications in Belgian ''Tintin''] and [http://bdoubliees.com/journaltintin/series3/jozette.htm French ''Tintin''] BDoubliées {{fr_icon}}
{{refend}}
;Footnotes
{{Reflist}}

==External links==
* [http://www.jockosjungle.co.uk/ Jocko’s Jungle – fan site]
* [http://www.hergeandtintin.tk/ Herge &amp; Tintin - see 'JZJ section']

{{Tintin and Hergé}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Jo, Zette And Jocko}}
[[Category:Belgian comics titles]]
[[Category:Works by Hergé]]

[[es:Las aventuras de Jo, Zette y Jocko]]
[[fr:Jo, Zette et Jocko]]
[[id:Petualangan Yo, Susi dan Yokko]]
[[nl:Jo, Suus en Jokko]]
[[fi:Veikko, Tette ja Jykke]]
[[sv:Johan, Lotta &amp; Jocko]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
