<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="1752170" ns="0" title="Flag of the African Union"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">[[File:Flag of the African Union 2010.svg|thumb|right|200px|Flag of the African Union]]
The current '''flag of the African Union''' was adopted at its 14th Ordinary Session of the Assembly of Heads of State and Government taking place in Addis Ababa on 31 January 2010. &lt;ref&gt;http://www.africa-union.org/root/au/Conferences/2010/January/summit/pr/en/en%20pr%2024AU%20NEW%20FLAG%20(2).doc&lt;/ref&gt; &lt;ref&gt;http://www.africa-union.org/root/AU/Conferences/2010/january/summit/14thsummit.html&lt;/ref&gt;

During the 8th [[African Union]] Summit which took place in [[Addis Ababa]] on 29 and 30 January 2007, the Heads of State and Government decided to launch a competition for the selection of a new flag for the Union. They prescribed a green background for the flag symbolising hope of Africa and stars to represent Member States.

Pursuant to this decision, the [[African Union Commission]] (AUC) organised a competition for the selection of a new flag for the African Union. The AUC received a total of 106 entries proposed by citizens of 19 African countries and 2 from the Diaspora. The proposals were then examined by a panel of experts put in place by the African Union Commission and selected from the five African regions for short listing according to the main directions given by the Heads of State and Government.

It contains a [[green (color)|green]] background symbolising hope of [[Africa]] and 53 [[gold (color)|gold]] stars to represent Member States.

==Previous flag==
[[File:Flag of the African Union.svg|thumb|right|200px|Previous flag]]
The previous flag of the African Union was composed of a broad [[green (color)|green]] horizontal stripe at the top followed by a narrow band of [[gold (color)|gold]]. Below is a broad [[white (color)|white]] stripe bearing the then [[emblem of the African Union]] at its centre followed by a narrow gold band and broad green stripe at the bottom.

Although when the AU was formed, a competition was announced for designing a new emblem and flag, the Assembly of the African Union decided at the Addis Ababa session of 2004 to retain the emblem and flag of its predecessor, the [[Organisation of African Unity]], and adopt them as the new AU flag and emblem.&lt;ref&gt;{{PDFlink|[http://www.africa-union.org/AU%20summit%202004/Assm/Assembly%20Decisions%20-Final.pdf Assembly of the African Union: Third Ordinary Session, 6–8 July 2004, Addis Ababa, Ethiopia]}}, p.&amp;nbsp;15.&lt;/ref&gt;

The colour symbolism of the old flag is as follows:&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.africa-union.org/AU%20symbols/ausymblos.htm African Union Symbols], AU website.&lt;/ref&gt;
*The colour [[green]] symbolises African hopes and aspiration to unity.
*The colour [[gold (color)|gold]] stands for African wealth and bright future.
*The colour [[white]] represents the purity of Africa's desire to have genuine friends throughout the world.
*The colour [[red]] (of the rings (in the centre)) stand for African solidarity and the blood shed for liberation of Africa.

==See also==
*[[Emblem of the African Union]]
*[[Pan-African colours]]
*[[Pan-African flag]]

==References==
&lt;references/&gt;

{{DEFAULTSORT:African Union, Flag of the}}
[[Category:African Union|Flag]]
[[Category:International flags]]
[[Category:Flags of organizations]]

{{Africa-flag-stub}}
{{AfricanUnion-stub}}

[[ar:علم الاتحاد الأفريقي]]
[[ca:Bandera de la Unió Africana]]
[[cs:Vlajka Africké unie]]
[[de:Flagge der Afrikanischen Union]]
[[el:Σημαία της Αφρικανικής Ένωσης]]
[[es:Bandera de la Unión Africana]]
[[eo:Flago de la Afrika Unio]]
[[fr:Drapeau de l'Union africaine]]
[[hsb:Chorhoj Afriskeje unije]]
[[it:Bandiera dell'Unione Africana]]
[[he:דגל האיחוד האפריקאי]]
[[hu:Az Afrikai Unió zászlaja]]
[[nl:Vlag van de Afrikaanse Unie]]
[[ja:アフリカ連合の旗]]
[[no:Den afrikanske unions flagg]]
[[nn:Det afrikanske flagget]]
[[pl:Flaga Unii Afrykańskiej]]
[[pt:Bandeira da União Africana]]
[[ru:Флаг Африканского союза]]
[[zh:非洲联盟旗帜]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
