<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><redirects><r from="Tintin tv series" to="The Adventures of Tintin (TV series)" /></redirects><pages><page pageid="1576168" ns="0" title="The Adventures of Tintin (TV series)"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">: ''Not to be confused with the older animated series [[Hergé's Adventures of Tintin]].''
{{infobox television |
 | show_name = The Adventures of Tintin
 | image = [[Image:The Adventures of Tintin (TV).jpg]]&lt;!-- Deleted image removed: [[Image:AdventuresOfTintinTitle.png|center|200px]] --&gt;
 | caption = The Adventures of Tintin title card .
 | format = [[Animated Series]]
 | genre = [[Adventure]] &lt;br /&gt; [[Mystery fiction|Mystery]] &lt;br /&gt; [[Comedy-drama]]
 | runtime = 25 minutes (approx. per episode)
 | creator = [[Hergé]] (characters)
 | starring = '''([[English language|English]] version)'''&lt;br /&gt;
[[Colin O'Meara]]&lt;br /&gt;[[David Fox (actor)|David Fox]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Wayne Robson]]&lt;br /&gt;[[John Stocker (voice actor)|John Stocker]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Dan Hennessey]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Susan Roman]]
 | company = [[Ellipse Programmé]]&lt;br&gt;[[Nelvana Limited]]
 | country = [[France]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Canada]]
 | network = [[HBO]] (USA)&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title= Tintin finds his way to America's HBO|publisher= Baltimore Sun|date=|url= http://articles.baltimoresun.com/1991-11-16/features/1991320079_1_adventures-of-tintin-tin-tin-herge|accessdate=2010-08-25}}&lt;/ref&gt; &lt;br/&gt; [[Family (TV channel)|Family]] (Canada) &lt;br /&gt; [[Global TV]] (Canada)
[[NHK]] (Japan)
 | first_aired = 1991
 | last_aired = 1992
 | num_seasons = 3
 | num_episodes = 39
 |}}
'''''The Adventures of Tintin''''' is an [[animated]] [[television series]] based on ''[[The Adventures of Tintin]]'', a series of books by [[Hergé]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title= Tintin Searches for a U.S. Audience|publisher= The New York Times|date=1991-12-24|url= http://www.nytimes.com/1991/12/24/news/tintin-searches-for-a-us-audience.html?scp=4&amp;sq=babar%20hbo&amp;st=cse|accessdate=2010-08-25 | first=Peter C. T. | last=Elsworth}}&lt;/ref&gt; It debuted in 1991, and 39 half-hour episodes were produced over the course of three seasons. It is the best-known adaptation of the books.

== History ==
The television series was directed by Stephen Bernasconi, with [[Peter Hudecki]] as Canadian unit director, and produced by [[Lé Studio Ellipse|Ellipse]] (France), and [[Nelvana Limited|Nelvana]] (Canada), on behalf of the [[Hergé Foundation]].   It was the [[Hergé's Adventures of Tintin|first television adaptation of Hergé's books]] for over twenty years (previously, the Belgian animation company [[Belvision]] had been responsible for their loose adaptations). [[Philippe Goddin]], an expert in Hergé and Tintin acted as consultant to the producers. Writers for the series included Toby Mullally, Eric Rondeaux, Martin Brossolet, Amelie Aubert, Dennise Fordham and Alex Boon.

==Production==
Traditional animation techniques were used on the series.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title= Popular Belgian comic-strip character 'Tintin' to get mega-boost on U.S. cable TV|publisher= Baltimore Sun|date=|url= http://articles.baltimoresun.com/1994-11-25/news/1994329050_1_tintin-belgium-fictional-heroes|accessdate=2010-08-25}}&lt;/ref&gt;  The books were closely adhered to during all stages of production, with some frames from the original albums being transposed directly to screen. In the episodes ''[[Destination Moon (Tintin)|Destination Moon]]'' and ''[[Explorers on the Moon]]'', [[3-D computer graphics|3D]] animation was used for the Moon rocket - an unusual step in 1989. The rocket was animated in 3D, each frame of the animation was then printed and recopied onto [[celluloid]] and hand painted in [[gouache]], and laid onto a painted background. The rocket seen in the title sequence is animated using 3D techniques. 

Artistically, the series chose a constant look, unlike the books (drawn over a course of 47 years, Hergé's style developed throughout from early works like ''[[The Blue Lotus]]'' and later ones such as ''[[Tintin and the Picaros]]''). However, later televised episodes such as the Moon story and ''[[Tintin in America]]'' clearly demonstrate the artists' development during the course of the series. The series was filmed in English, with all visuals (road signs, posters and settings) remaining in French.

==Changes from the books==
Inevitably, certain areas of the stories posed difficulties for the producers, who had to adapt features of the books to a more modern young audience. Nevertheless, this series was far more faithful to the books than ''[[Hergé's Adventures of Tintin]]'', which had been made from 1958 to 1962.

The high amount of violence, death and the use of firearms were toned down or removed completely.

Haddock's penchant for [[whisky]] posed a problem for audience sensitivities. While the original books did not promote [[alcohol]], they featured it heavily, with much humor based around it and the results of drinking. However, in many countries where the producers hoped to sell the series, alcoholism is a sensitive issue. Therefore, international versions of the series had some alterations. Haddock is seen drinking, but not as heavily as in the books. ''[[The Crab with the Golden Claws]]'' is the only adventure where Haddock's drunken state is not reduced. Also Tintin finds the Japanese Policeman earlier, chained to a post on the ship and gagged. However he is told to leave as he cannot free him in time. In ''[[Tintin in Tibet]],'' Haddock is seen taking a nip from a flask of whisky in order to set up a scene in which Snowy is tempted to lap up some spilled whisky and subsequently falls over a cliff. In ''[[Tintin and the Picaros]]'', Haddock is the only person taking wine with dinner, foreshadowing the use of Calculus' tablets to &quot;cure&quot; the drunken Picaros. Haddock is also seen drinking in ''[[The Calculus Affair]]'' and in ''[[Explorers on the Moon]]'', setting up the scene where he leaves the rocket in a drunken state. It should be noted that he does not hide the bottle in a book of Astronomy, like he did in the book, but keeps the bottle in the refrigerator, making it less obvious for young viewers that it's alcohol. 

Throughout the books, Snowy is frequently seen to be &quot;talking&quot;. It is understood that his voice is only heard through the &quot;[[fourth wall]]&quot;, but this verbal commentary is completely absent in the television series. The only time it's maintained is in the ending of &quot;Flight 714&quot; and he &quot;speaks&quot; with Tintin's voice.

Smaller changes were made due to the necessity for simplification or audience requirements. In ''[[The Calculus Affair]]'', the [[Syldavia]]n group who tries to snatch [[Professor Calculus]] from the [[Borduria]]ns in the original book is removed for simplicity. Also, in the original book, Calculus was kidnapped earlier in the story. It's not clear why they made that change. 

In ''[[The Red Sea Sharks]]'', the original book dealt with the topic of modern [[slavery]], but the television episode was centered around smuggling of refugees. Surprisingly, they are Arabs instead of Africans. They were not meant to be sold, but killed after handing over all their money. Furthermore, while the Africans in the book volunteered to be simply stokers for the ship that Captain Haddock has command of, the television version makes a point of having the characters doing more sophisticated work on the ship. Also, [[Piotr Skut]] has already known Tintin and Captain Haddock when they saved him while they have not met each other in the original story. Mullpacha/Dr. Mueller's role is expanded, and he becomes the leader of the attempted [[coup d'état]] rather than just being one of Bab El Ehr's military commanders. Bab El Ehr himself is entirely deleted from the storyline. Also, the scene in which the Mosquitoes bomb the [[armored car (military)|armored car]]s is rewritten - in the book, Muller is safely inside the command quarters and talks to the General via telephone, whereas in the TV version, Muller is in one of the vehicles and communicates via walkie-talkie. 

In ''[[Tintin and the Picaros]]'', Hergé presents a less naive Tintin who refuses to go with Haddock and Calculus to rescue Castafiore and the detectives, knowing it's a setup. He only joins them later, after his conscience gets the better of him.  Many fans felt it was out of character for Tintin to refuse to go to [[South America]]. In the series however, Tintin is all for rescuing his friends and goes with Haddock and Calculus early in the adventure. In the original comic, Tintin wore [[jeans]] throughout the book, which was in contrast with the [[plus-fours]] he had always worn previously. In the episode, his plus-fours have returned.

''[[Tintin in America]]'' was the most altered episode, amounting to almost a completely new story. The [[Native Americans in the United States|Native American]] aspect was completely removed, and the [[gangster]] element given the main focus. [[Bobby Smiles]], in the book the head of a rival gang to [[Al Capone]], becomes an &quot;employee&quot; of Capone's in the televised episode. All the criminals are led by Al Capone, who is captured at the end. Artistically, the episode was produced to the same standard as the others, with backgrounds having greater detail and more cinematic shots.

In ''[[King Ottokar's Sceptre]]'', the impostor of the professor smokes while the latter does not; the reverse is true in the book.  And in the book, Tintin got chased by border guards and accidentally crossed the border because he got hungry while the latter Tintin accidentally crossed the border because he found a [[Borduria]]n airfield, and Tintin did not get hungry and got chased by border guards.  In the book, Tintin got the clue that the camera was faked from a toy store while the latter Tintin got the clue by looking outside Krowpow Castle and found some cannons.  

In ''[[The Secret of the Unicorn]]'', the [[Great Dane]], Brutus, is not shown.  Also, when Haddock takes Tintin out of the latter's [[apartment]] to show him the painting of the ''Unicorn'', someone is shown watching them and then breaking into Tintin's apartment, whereas in the book it is only revealed that there was a robbery when Tintin arrives home and finds his model ''Unicorn'' missing. Finally, a change was made to the scene in which Tintin is kidnapped and taken to Marlinspike Hall: rather than two unknown &quot;delivery men&quot;, as depicted in the book, it is the Bird brothers (Max and Gustav) themselves who kidnap him.

In ''[[Red Rackham's Treasure]]'', the changes are made solely for time such as the only consequence of the press exposure is their meeting with Calculus.  In addition, Tintin has a smooth voyage in the shark submarine as opposed to the book where Tintin is in peril when the vehicle is snarled with [[seaweed]].  Furthermore, the treasure hunters never return to the island to dig around a large wooden [[cross]] on a mistaken idea of where the treasure could be.

In ''[[The Black Island]]'', the [[gorilla]] Ranko crushes the rock Tintin throws at him, something he did not do in the book. Also, the counterfeiting gang based in the castle comprises just [[Puschov]], [[Dr. J.W. Muller|Dr. Muller]], and Ivan, whereas in the book, it was made of two more anonymous members, and Ivan was portrayed as Puschov's unnamed assistant. 

In ''[[Cigars of the Pharaoh]]'', the mental hospital cell is a padded cell; in the book it has a bed. Also, Dr. Finney is a member of the gang so he wrote a letter saying that Tintin was mad. In the book, the fakir copied the doctor's handwriting and wrote the letter. In the book, an unnamed Japanese person is a member of the gang. In the TV series, the unnamed Japanese is replaced by Allan Thompson, whom Tintin recognizes. Following the chronology of the books, Tintin does not see Thompson until ''[[The Crab with the Golden Claws]]'', but as the TV series episodes of ''[[The Crab with the Golden Claws]]'' aired before ''[[Cigars of the Pharaoh]]'', Tintin's recognition of Thompson is credible when the episodes are viewed in that order. Furthermore, there could exist the possibility that in the series Tintin had briefly seen Allan when he was inside the [[sarcophagus]], in Allan's boat, though in the book he's unconscious all along. In the TV episode when Thompson and Thomson come into Tintin's cabin, Tintin already knows them; in the book he does not.  Tintin is not recaptured by the asylum; instead the [[maharajah]]'s son finds him.

In ''[[The Blue Lotus]]'', Mitsuhirato's manservant is shown to be a [[double agent]] in the service of the Sons of the Dragon, and it is he who replaces the Rajaijah Juice with a harmless substitute and delivers the real poison to his employers. In the book, this was done by another agent. Gibbons is not shown at all, and Dawson's role is much reduced, as he is only shown as the police commissioner who calls in Thompson and Thomson, and does not appear to be in league with Mitsuhirato (this creates a subsequent continuity error in ''The Red Sea Sharks'', as Tintin mentions having a &quot;run-in&quot; with Dawson despite not encountering him in this story). At the end of the storyline, Rastapopoulos tries to flee through the Blue Lotus club when the other villains are apprehended, but is himself caught by Thompson and Thomson. In the book, Rastapopoulos was apprehended along with Mitsuhirato. Also, this episode, unlike the book, does not reveal Mitsuhirato's fate.

In ''[[Tintin and the Broken Ear]]'', Tortilla is completely missing from the plot, and is replaced by Walker's aide, Lopez (who is not mentioned as a half-caste). Further, Colonel-turned-Corporal Diaz is completely absent from the story, as are the numerous assassination attempts perpetrated by himself and R.W. Trickler. The entire subplot involving the rivaling [[petroleum]] companies is removed, and accordingly, Tintin never falls out of favour with General Alcazar, and Alonzo and Ramon never find Tintin in the Amazon. Instead, they disappear from the storyline after Tintin escapes from them in San Theodoros, and do not appear again until the climax. Also in the book, Tintin disguises himself as a [[blackface]]d [[African]] to spy on Ramon and Alonzo, while in the episode, Tintin's disguise is that of a [[Steward's Assistant|steward]] wearing a false moustache, glasses, and a black wig. While in the book, Tintin walks back to Sanfacion, Nuevo Rico, alone, after being caught by Alonzo and Ramon, he is instead escorted (off screen) by Walker and the Arumbayas to San Theodoros. At the end of the episode, Tintin saves Ramon and Alonzo, whereas in the book they drown and disappear into [[Hell]], though it is speculated this may be an imaginary scene or hallucination.

In ''[[Flight 714]]'', Rastapopolous and his gang use [[dynamite]] instead of explosives to destroy the statue as in the book.  Also, Rastapopolous says that he was planning to shoot Dr. Krollspell, whereas in the book he merely says &quot;eliminate&quot;, and does not reveal plans for the other crew members or the Sondinesians.  In the end, the astroship drops Dr. Krollspell off in [[India]]; in the book it drops him off in [[Cairo]]. The group is hypnotized after they get on the spaceship, this is perhaps more believable as the volcano was about to explode.

===Stories not Adapted to the series===
Four stories were not adapted to the animated series. These were:

# ''[[Tintin in the Land of the Soviets]]'' - because it was in an original black and white state but mostly because it was offensive for [[Russia]]&lt;br /&gt;
# ''[[Tintin in the Congo]]'' -  due to its unavailability in English at the time and mostly due to questionable (Colonialism and racism) content&lt;br /&gt;
# ''[[Tintin and Alph-Art]]'' - because it is unfinished&lt;br /&gt;
# ''[[Tintin and the Lake of Sharks]]'' - Because it's not written by [[Hergé]] and it was originally a movie that was latter adapted to comics using still images.

==Music==
The underscore music and the main title theme for the series was written by composers Ray Parker and Tom Szczesniak. The music was recorded by engineer James Morgan. Excerpts from the score were released by [[Lé Studio Ellipse|Ellipse]] on CD and cassette in conjunction with [[Universal Music Group|Universal]], on the [[StudioCanal]] label. It is now out of print in both formats.

==Hergé's cameo appearances==
[[Hergé]], the creator of Tintin, makes a number of [[List of Hitchcock cameo appearances|Hitchcock-like cameo appearances]] in the cartoon series &amp;mdash; as he often did in the original books. Most of the time he is just a passing figure in the street, such as when he is checking his watch in ''The Blue Lotus'' or a reporter (''The Broken Ear'') or a technician (''Explorers on the Moon''). These brief appearances are not sporadic throughout the episodes, rather, he is featured in all of the episodes. His letter box can even be seen next to Tintin's in ''The Crab with the Golden Claws''. Other cameos are less flattering: he is a gangster in ''Tintin in America'' and an inmate at the [[lunatic asylum]] in ''Cigars of the Pharaoh'', along with his fellow artist and collaborator [[Edgar P. Jacobs]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.tintinologist.org/guides/lists/hergecameos.html Hergé's Cameo Appearances / Blond Man Spotting at tintinologist.org]&lt;/ref&gt;

==Broadcasts and releases==
===Broadcasts===
*{{flagicon|Canada}} In [[Canada]], the series originally aired on [[Family (TV channel)|Family Channel]] and [[Global Television Network]], and on [[Radio-Canada]] in [[Quebec]]. with reruns subsequently aired on [[YTV (TV channel)|YTV]], Canal à Moi and [[Teletoon (Canada)|Teletoon]].
*{{flagicon|Brazil}} In [[Brazil]], the series originally aired on public broadcasting channel TV Cultura during most of the 1990s and 2000s. It was dubbed to [[Brazilian Portuguese|Portuguese]] by [[Herbert Richers]].
*{{flagicon|Sri Lanka}} In [[Sri Lanka]], the series was dubbed in Sinhala and broadcast by [[Sirasa TV]] and [[Sri Lanka Rupavahini Corporation|Rupavahini]], along with Lake of Sharks and Temple of the Sun.
*{{flagicon|USA}} In the [[United States]], the series originally aired on [[HBO]] with reruns subsequently aired on [[Nickelodeon (TV channel)|Nickelodeon]].
*{{flagicon|UK}} In the [[United Kingdom]], the series originally aired on [[Channel Four]] on terrestrial television, and [[Challenge TV|Family Channel]], a channel based on [[ABC Family|CBN's Family Channel]] available through the original [[British Sky Broadcasting|Sky]] system. It was later broadcast on [[Sky One]] until the series was purchased by [[Five (TV)|Five]].
*{{flagicon|Israel}} In [[Israel]], the series was dubbed into [[Hebrew]] by [http://www.elrstudio.com/ Elrom Studios], and broadcasted on the Israeli Channel 2, and later on [[Israel Broadcasting Authority]](Channel 1). Children and Teenagers devoted shows. Tintin became very popular among kids and adults in Israel. The show was aired for several years, rerunning many times.
*{{flagicon|Italy}} In [[Italy]], [[Rai 1]] [[Italia 1]]  broadcasted the series.
*{{flagicon|Australia}} In [[Australia]], the series was broadcast by the [[Australian Broadcasting Corporation]] as part of their [[ABC Kids (Australia)|ABC Kids]] programming block as well as on the [[ABC2]] digital channel.  It has been shown in its complete run at least twice, leading to screenings of the [[Belvision]] [[The Adventures of Tintin|Tintin]] films. As of October 2010, it is currently being aired on [[Boomerang (Australian TV channel)|Boomerang]].
*{{flagicon|New Zealand}} In [[New Zealand]], the series was originally aired on [[TV2 (New Zealand)]] of [[TVNZ|Television New Zealand]]. It continued to re-run on TV2 for a few years afterwards. It then featured on [[Cartoon Network]].
*{{flagicon|South Africa}} In [[South Africa]], the series was broadcast by KTV, a daily children's programme, on [[M-Net]].
*{{flagicon|India}} In [[India]], the series was broadcast by [[Cartoon Network]] in the summer of 2000. The original run was followed by many reruns. [[Doordarshan]] and Zee Alpha Bangla also showed the series with dubbing.
*{{flagicon|Arab League}} It has also aired in [[Arabic language|Arabic]] in several networks broadcast from Arabic speaking regions. Although the Arabic dubbing was performed in [[Lebanon]], they dubbed it using [[Modern Standard Arabic|standard Arabic]] narrative, and was then syndicated. This is a usual treatment of most Arabic dubs of children's productions.
*{{flagicon|Bulgaria}} In [[Bulgaria]], it premiered on July 18, 2005 on [[BNT Channel 1|Kanal 1]] and aired every Monday to Friday at 16:20. Reruns started on December 24, 2005 every Saturday and Sunday at 08:10 and ending on April 30, 2006 and later once more during the summer of 2006.
*{{flagicon|Indonesia}} In [[Indonesia]], it was broadcast by [[SCTV (Indonesia)|SCTV]], and is aired in B Channel
*{{flagicon|Philippines}} In the [[Philippines]], it was aired in [[GMA-7]] in the mid-1990s as part of the afternoon cartoon schedule.
*In [[Southeast Asia]], the series was aired in [[Cartoon Network]] up to about 2004.
*{{flagicon|Portugal}} In [[Portugal]], the series was aired in [[Canal Panda]] until late 2003.
*{{flagicon|Denmark}} In [[Denmark]] the series was aired in the 1990s on the Danish chanel, DR1 and again by [[DR Ramasjang]] from 2009 and on.
*{{flagicon|Saudi Arabia}} In [[Saudi Arabia]], during the 1990s the series was broadcast by the State TV, in English, on [[channel 2]]. Later it was broadcast in Arabic on state TV, [[channel 1]].
*{{flagicon|Germany}} In [[Germany]], it was dubbed to [[German language|German]] in the 1990s by ATLAS Film. The series was aired on public kids channel [[KiKa]] during most of the mid 2000's.
*{{flagicon|Sweden}} In [[Sweden]], the series was first aired (dubbed in Swedish) on Swedish Channel 1 (Kanal 1; now [[SVT1]]) between September 1994 and April 1995. It was then broadcast in the original series episode order. When it was later published in a Scandinavian DVD box (with Danish, Norwegian, Finnish and Swedish dubbings), the episodes were arranged in the original album order (for instance, putting the episode &quot;Tintin in America&quot; as the first episode, even though it was the last one in the series).

===Video and DVD releases===
&lt;!-- Deleted image removed: [[Image:TintinDVDR2.png|left|150px|frame|Region 2 English DVD release]] --&gt;
The full series has been available three times on video, with individual episodes released by [[Lumiere]] in 1994 and Mollin Video in 2000, while [[Anchor Bay Entertainment|Anchor Bay]] released a series of five videos, containing four episodes on each (and five on the last one) in 2002&amp;ndash;2003.

The series has also been released twice on [[DVD region code|Region 2 DVD]] by Anchor Bay, but unfortunately with no subtitles or extra features. The first was as an exclusive 5-disc DVD release for [[HMV Group plc|HMV]] with soundtracks in [[English language|English]], [[French language|French]] and [[Spanish language|Spanish]]. The second was a general 10-disc release but with the soundtrack only in [[English language|English]]. The 10-disc set is in the canonical order, although the limited edition 5-disc set places ''[[The Blue Lotus]]'' first (presumably from looking at the back of one of the books). On 10 October 2011, Anchor Bay re-released the series in a 5 disc DVD set and released it for the first time on [[Blu-ray]], also in a 5 disc set. 

In [[France]], the full series has been available for years on video, produced by Citel. At the beginning of 2006, Citel also released the series on [[DVD region code|Region 2 DVD]]. The DVDs are packaged in two ways. In one packaging, there are 21 DVDs with one episode per DVD and audio in [[French language|French]] and [[English language|English]] but no subtitles. A full set was issued in a wooden box. The second packaging has two episodes on each DVD (3 on one). These have audio in [[French language|French]], [[English language|English]] and [[Spanish language|Spanish]] and subtitles in the same three languages plus French for the hard of hearing. Some of them also have subtitles in [[Portuguese language|Portuguese]]. Recently the series was issued as a [[partwork]] by Éditions Atlas in France, with an accompanying booklet featuring information about the episode and behind-the-scenes artwork.

In [[Canada]], the series has been released on [[DVD region code|Region 1 DVD]] on two 5-disc box sets (with all discs individually available), with French and English language tracks with subtitles. Each DVD contains two episodes, arranged in two boxed sets of ten episodes each. ''[[Tintin in America]]'' is not planned for release. Except for the episodes which, joined together, form story arcs (''[[The Seven Crystal Balls]]''/''[[Prisoners of the Sun]]'', ''[[Destination Moon (Tintin)|Destination Moon]]''/''[[Explorers on the Moon]]'' and ''[[The Secret of the Unicorn]]''/''[[Red Rackham's Treasure]]''), the episodes have no specific order on the discs.  It is more French than English; for on-screen text, English subtitles automatically appear. The Canadian editions were released in the US on August 18, 2009.

In [[New Zealand]] &amp; [[Australia]], a 6-disc [[DVD]] [[box set]] of the series was released by [[Madman Entertainment]] in 2004, in the order in which the comics were released.  The first three discs had four episodes, the last three had three episodes.  Each disc comes with information on the comic books, character profiles, and no subtitles.

In [[India]], the series has been released on both DVD and VCD by Moser Baer Home Entertainment once before. Now the series is available in two formats on DVD and VCD from Eagle Home Entertainment. First is the boxed format, in which there are 21 DVDs with one episode per DVD and audio in [[English language|English]] with English subtitles. The full set was issued in a wooden box as part of 80th anniversary celebration by Eagle. The second format is individual episodes sold separately with audio in [[English language|English]] with English subtitles. The DVDs are region free in both cases.

In [[Brazil]], the series has been released on DVD in July 2008. Each season has been released separately on 3 box-sets. There's also a special deluxe collector's edition box-set with all 39 episodes on 9 discs. The series has been released by Log On Multimedia and the region-free DVDs contains audio in English and Portuguese and subtitles in [[Portuguese language|Portuguese]].

In [[Germany]], a Video version was distributed in the 1990s by ATLAS Film. In 2004 it was released on [[DVD region code|Region 2 DVD]], on two 4-disc box sets (with all discs individually available), with German and French language tracks. In 2005 a anniversary edition, with all 39 episodes on 8-disc's came out.

On May 11, 2011, [[Shout! Factory]] announced that they had acquired the rights (under license from [[Nelvana]]) to release the series on DVD in Region 1.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.tvshowsondvd.com/news/Adventures-Tintin-DVDs-Planned/15385&lt;/ref&gt;  They subsequently announced that Season 1 will be released on November 22, 2011.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.tvshowsondvd.com/news/Adventures-Tintin-Season-1/15774&lt;/ref&gt;  Season 2 will be released on February 21, 2012.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.tvshowsondvd.com/news/Adventures-Tintin-Season-2/16221&lt;/ref&gt;

==Voice artists==
===English===
* [[Colin O'Meara]] - Tintin
* [[Susan Roman]] - Snowy
* [[David Fox (actor)|David Fox]] - Captain Haddock
* [[Wayne Robson]] - Professor Calculus
* [[Dan Hennessey]] - Thomson
* [[John Stocker (voice actor)|John Stocker]] - Thompson
* [[Julie Lemieux]] - Chang
* [[Yank Azman]] - additional voices
* Paul Haddad - additional voices
* [[Keith Knight (actor)|Keith Knight]] - additional voices
* [[Graham Halley]] - additional voices

===Danish===
* [[Søren Sætter-Lassen]]- Tintin
* [[Kjeld Nørregaard]]- Kaptain Haddock
* [[Lars Thisegaard]]- Dupond Og Dupont

===Norwegian===
* [[Åsleik Engmark]] - Tintin
* [[Trond Brænne]]

===French===
* [[Thierry Wermuth]] - Tintin
* [[Susan Roman]] - Milou
* [[Christian Pelissier]] - Capitaine Haddock
* [[Henri Labussiere]] - Professeur Tournesol
* [[Yves Barsacq]] - Détective Dupont
* [[Jean-Pierre Moulin]] - Détective Dupond

===Dutch===
* [[Michael Pas]] - Kuifje
* [[Luk De Koninck]] - Kapitein Haddock
* [[Bert Struys]] - Professor Zonnebloem
* [[David Davidse]] - Jansen
* [[Paul Codde]] - Janssen

===Portuguese===
* Carla Carreiro
* [[Carlos Macedo]]
* Frederico Trancoso
* Luís Barros
* Paulo Simões
* Rui de Sá
* Vitor Emanuel

===Brazilian Portuguese===
* [[Oberdan Júnior]] - Tintim
* [[Isaac Bardavid]] - Capitão Haddock
* [[Orlando Drummond]] - Professor Girassol
* [[Darcy Pedrosa]] - Detetive Dupond
* [[Márcio Simões]] - Detetive Dupont
* [[Paulo Flores]] - Rastapopoulos
* [[Selma Lopes]] - Bianca Castafiore

===Swedish===
* [[Mats Quiström]] - Tintin
* [[Kenneth Milldoff]] - Kapten Haddock, Rastapopoulos
* [[Dan Bratt]] - Professor Kalkyl
* [[Håkan Mohede]] - Dupond &amp; Dupont, Nestor
* [[Anja Schmidt]] - Bianca Castafiore

===Finnish===
* [[Jarkko Tamminen]] - Tintti
* [[Pekka Lehtosaari]] - Kapteeni Haddock
* [[Antti Pääkkönen]] - Professori Teophilus Tuhatkauno
* [[Veikko Honkanen]] - Dupond &amp; Dupont
* [[Rauno Ahonen]] - Rastapopoulos

===Hungarian===
* [[Bolba Tamás]] / [[Lippai László]] - Tintin
* [[Melis Gábor]] - Haddock kapitány
* [[Harsányi Gábor]] - Calculus Teofil professzor
* [[Barbinek Péter]] - Kováts
* [[Forgách Péter]] - Kovács
* [[Susan Roman]] - Ponpon

===Japanese===
* ([[Takeshi Kusao]]1994-1995) ([[Kiyomi Asai]] 2002) ([[Natsumi Yanase]] 2001) ([[Daisuke Namikawa]] 2011) - Tintin
* ([[Keiichi Nanba]] 2002) - Rastapopoulos
* ([[Tesshō Genda]] 2001-2002) - Captain Haddock

===Italiano===
* [[S. Onofri]] - Tintin
* [[Gusso]] - Haddock
* [[Lopez]] - Girasole

===Spanish (Spain-European)===
* [[Juan D'Ors]] - Tintín
* [[José Ángel Juanes]] - Capitán Haddock
* [[Eduardo Moreno]] - Professor Silvestre Tornasol
* [[Francisco Andrés Valdivia]] - Hernández
* [[Miguel Ángel Varela]] - Fernández
* [[María Romero]] - Bianca Castafiore
* [[Raquel Cubillo]] - Bianca Castafiore (when singing)
* [[Pedro Sempson]] - Néstor
* [[Ángel Amorós]] - General Alcázar

==Episodes==
Running order of the TV Series as [http://www.imdb.com/title/tt0179552/episodes#season-1 per original broadcast schedule]

===Season 1===
# [[The Crab with the Golden Claws]] Part 1
# The Crab with the Golden Claws Part 2
# [[The Secret of the Unicorn]] Part 1
# The Secret of the Unicorn Part 2
# [[Red Rackham's Treasure]]
# [[Cigars of the Pharaoh]] Part 1
# Cigars of the Pharaoh Part 2
# [[The Blue Lotus]] Part 1
# The Blue Lotus Part 2
# [[The Black Island]] Part 1
# The Black Island Part 2
# [[The Calculus Affair]] Part 1
# The Calculus Affair Part 2

===Season 2===
# [[The Shooting Star]]
# [[The Broken Ear]] Part 1
# The Broken Ear Part 2
# [[King Ottokar's Sceptre]] Part 1
# King Ottokar's Sceptre Part 2
# [[Tintin in Tibet]] Part 1
# Tintin in Tibet Part 2
# [[Tintin and the Picaros]] Part 1
# Tintin and the Picaros Part 2
# [[Land of Black Gold]] Part 1
# Land of Black Gold Part 2
# [[Flight 714]] Part 1
# Flight 714 Part 2

===Season 3===
# [[The Red Sea Sharks]] Part 1
# [[The Seven Crystal Balls]] Part 1
# [[Prisoners of the Sun]] Part 1
# [[The Castafiore Emerald]] Part 1
# [[Destination Moon (Tintin)|Destination Moon]] Part 1
# [[Explorers on the Moon]] Part 1
# [[Tintin in America]]

==See also==
* ''[[Blake and Mortimer (TV series)|Blake and Mortimer]]''
* [[Jean-Marc Lofficier|Lofficier]], Jean-Marc &amp; Randy (2002) ''The Pocket Essential Tintin'' - ISBN 1-904048-17-X

== References ==
{{Cleanup-link rot|date=October 2011}}
{{Reflist|30em}}

==External links==
* ''Les Aventures de Tintin en DVD'' (2003) : issues 1,2,5,6
* ''The Adventures of Tintin'' - 5-disc DVD set (2003)
* [http://www.citelvideo.com/ Citel Video]
* {{imdb title|id=0179552|title=The Adventures of Tintin}}
* {{tv.com|19627|The Adventures of Tintin}}
* [http://www.tintinologist.org/guides/screen/ Guide to screen adaptions of &quot;Tintin&quot;] at Tintinologist.org

{{Tintin and Hergé}}
{{HBONetwork Series}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Adventures Of Tintin, The}}
[[Category:Tintin]]
[[Category:French children's television series]]
[[Category:Canadian children's television series]]
[[Category:HBO network shows]]
[[Category:Television series by Nelvana]]
[[Category:Family (TV channel) shows]]
[[Category:Global Television Network shows]]
[[Category:Television programs based on comic strips]]
[[Category:1991 Canadian television series debuts]]
[[Category:1992 Canadian television series endings]]
[[Category:French animated television series]]
[[Category:Canadian animated television series]]
[[Category:Television series based on Belgian comics]]
[[Category:Radio-Canada network shows]]
[[Category:YTV shows]]
[[Category:HBO Family]]
[[Category:1990s animated television series]]

[[bn:দুঃসাহসী টিন‌টিন]]
[[ca:Tintín]]
[[fr:Les Aventures de Tintin (série télévisée d'animation)]]
[[id:Petualangan Tintin (seri televisi)]]
[[it:Le avventure di Tin Tin]]
[[nl:De avonturen van Kuifje (tekenfilmserie)]]
[[pl:Przygody Tintina (serial animowany)]]
[[pt:As Aventuras de Tintim (série de TV)]]
[[fi:Tintin seikkailut (animaatiosarja)]]
[[sv:Tintin (TV-serie)]]
[[vi:Những cuộc phiêu lưu của Tintin (phim hoạt hình)]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
