<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><redirects><r from="Recurring characters in Asterix" to="List of Asterix characters" /></redirects><pages><page pageid="3320634" ns="0" title="List of Asterix characters"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{citations missing|date=December 2010}}
{{original research|date=December 2010}}
[[Image:Asterix - Cast.png|thumb|right|400px|Some characters of ''Asterix''. In the front row are the main [[Gauls|Gaulish]] characters, plus [[Julius Caesar]] and [[Cleopatra]].]]
This is a list of characters in the '''[[Asterix]]''' comics.

==Main characters==
Asterix, Obelix, and Dogmatix are the first characters with short descriptions usually listed at the beginning of each of the Asterix  books (after the map of Gaul). They each have separate articles containing more information. Unless otherwise stated, this article uses the names chosen for the English translations of the books.

=== Asterix ===
{{Main|Asterix (character)}}
'''Asterix''' is the main character. He is a brave, shrewd warrior of somewhat diminutive size, who eagerly volunteers for all perilous missions.
* [[French language|French]]: ''Astérix'' (from ''{{lang|fr|astérisque}}'', meaning &quot;[[asterisk]]&quot;, which is the typographical symbol '''*''' indicating a footnote, or from the Greek word αστήρ (''aster''), meaning a &quot;star&quot;). His name is usually left unchanged in translations, aside from accents and the use of local [[alphabet]]s: for example, in [[Esperanto]], [[Polish language|Polish]], [[Slovene language|Slovene]], [[Latvian language|Latvian]] and [[Turkish language|Turkish]] it is ''Asteriks'', although in Turkish he was first named ''Bücür'' meaning &quot;shorty&quot;, but the name was then changed. An exception is in [[Icelandic language|Icelandic]], in which he is known as ''Ástríkur'' (&quot;Rich of love&quot;).
*In [[Sinhalese Language|Sinhalese]] — සිංහල (''Soora Pappa'') Which could be interpreted as &quot;[[Hero]]&quot;.

===Obelix===
{{Main|Obelix}}
'''Obelix''' is Asterix's closest friend and works as a [[menhir]] sculptor and delivery man. He is a tall, [[obese]] man with two notable attributes: his phenomenal strength and his voracious appetite for food. His strength results from having fallen into Getafix's magic potion cauldron as a boy. As a consequence, Getafix will not let him take additional potion for fear of side effects (for example, turning into stone, as shown in ''Asterix and Obelix all at Sea''), something that Obelix finds immensely unfair. The only exception was in ''Asterix and Cleopatra'' when they were trapped in a [[pyramid]].  Obelix's size is often the brunt of many jokes. In ''Asterix and the Big Fight'' a druid mistakes Obelix for a patient with an [[eating disorder]]. At the end of the book, Obelix decides to go on a diet but quickly goes back to eating huge quantities of [[boar]].

* [[French language|French]]: ''Obélix'': meaning either &quot;[[obelisk]]&quot;, a massive monument, or the [[dagger (typography)|typographical symbol]] ('''&lt;big&gt;†&lt;/big&gt;''') (also called an ''obelus'' in English) which is sometimes used to indicate a second footnote if the first footnote is indicated by an asterisk. His name is also almost never changed in official translations (not counting orthographical variations such as ''Obeliks'' in e.g. [[Esperanto]], [[Polish language|Polish]] and [[Slovene language|Slovene]]). However there is a notable exception in [[Turkish language|Turkish]], in which he is ''Hopdediks'', ''{{lang|tr|Hop dedik!}}'' being a phrase uttered when someone overdoes something. In recent comic albums, he has been ''Oburiks'' — ''{{lang|tr|obur}}'' means &quot;gluttonous&quot;.
* In Icelandic his name is ''Steinríkur'', roughly meaning &quot;rich in stone&quot;, due to Obelix's fascination with stones.
*In [[Sinhalese Language|Sinhalese]] — සිංහල (''Jim Pappa'') which means &quot;[[mighty]]&quot; and/or &quot;[[wikt:strong|strong]]&quot;.

===Getafix===
'''Getafix''' is the village [[druid]]. In appearance he is tall with a white [[beard]], white robe, red cloak. He is usually seen in possession of a small golden [[sickle]]. While his age is never stated, in the story of Asterix' birth (in which all but the oldest villagers are seen as small children) he appears unchanged. In ''[[Asterix and the Big Fight]]'' the druid Psychoanalytix (who appears quite old) refers to him as his elder and teacher.

Although known for his strength-enhancing magic potion, he has many other magical and medicinal potions at his disposal — including a potion to make hair grow quickly, a potion to cure a man who has been poisoned with a drug that would kill him in a matter of days, and a potion that restores a person to full health after injury (although this potion also causes the person who takes it to lose their recent memories while also interacting badly with the magic potion) — and acts as the village doctor and occasional teacher. Asterix (and most other villagers) will consult him whenever anything strange occurs. He does not engage normally himself in combat, whereas most of the villagers enjoy a good punch-up (even with each other). One exception is one of the stories explaining Gaulish women, with using Mrs. Geriatrix as an example, with a fight sparked by Impedimenta. The final cut is shown with all the male villagers and two females, Impedimenta and Bacteria included, with Getafix running to stop the punch up, with a piece of fish flying towards him. His most notable brawl is when, passing himself as a cook in ''The Great Divide'', he makes some magic potion (passing it off as soup) to free the enslaved men from the divided village, captured by the romans — and doing a test run on the present slaves — and then starts distributing slaps with obvious enjoyment.

As the only individual able to produce the &quot;magic potion&quot; upon which the villagers rely for their strength, he is the focus of many stories- ranging from the Romans attempting to put him out of commission in some manner to requesting that Asterix and Obelix help him find some missing ingredient-, and the conscience of the village. On a few occasions, he has refused to make the potion when the villagers become too selfish, most notably in ''[[Asterix and Caesar's Gift]]'' where he refused to provide the potion for anyone while the village was divided by an upcoming vote for a new chief, only to provide them with it once again when Vitalstatistix asked Getafix to provide the potion for Orthopedix, the man he had been running against for chief. He has also occasionally been taken prisoner by hostile forces to get access to the potion, only to be freed again thanks to Asterix and Obelix. Finding ingredients for his potions has also sent Asterix on several adventures. The full recipe of the magic potion itself has never been revealed, but known ingredients are mistletoe (which must be cut with a golden sickle), a whole lobster (an optional ingredient that improves the flavour), fish, salt, and petroleum (called rock oil in the book), which is later replaced by beetroot juice. Replenishing the stores of ingredients for the magic potion has led to some adventures for Asterix and Obelix, including [[Asterix and the Great Crossing]], [[Asterix and the Golden Sickle]] and [[Asterix and the Black Gold]].

Getafix is very similar to many [[wise old man|wise old men]] who act as mentors and father-figures to the heroes, including [[Merlin]], [[Gandalf]], [[Obi-Wan Kenobi]] and [[Albus Dumbledore]]. In Goscinny's earlier works, however, Getafix came across more as just a friend of the protagonists rather than a wise old counselor. He was also, from the very beginning, shown as a figure of fun and had a wonderful sense of humour: in ''[[Asterix the Gaul]]'' he'd cut his finger while using his [[sickle]] and roar with uncontrollable laughter at Asterix' teasing of the Roman Centurion; in ''[[Asterix and the Big Fight]]'' he was shown as going literally crazy.

*[[French language|French]]: ''[[:fr:Panoramix|Panoramix]]'' (&quot;panoramic&quot; or &quot;wide view&quot; or &quot;he who sees everything&quot;) — in most European translations this name is used, including [[Bulgarian language|Bulgarian]] [[Dutch language|Dutch]], [[Italian language|Italian]], [[Latin language|Latin]], [[Polish language|Polish]], [[Portuguese Language|Portuguese]], [[Slovene language|Slovene]], [[Spanish Language|Spanish]], [[Indonesian Language|Indonesian]], [[Czech language|Czech]] and [[Greek language|Greek]].
*In [[English language|English]], the name is a pun on &quot;getting a fix&quot; — a dose of a drug taken by an addict; the phrase can also mean to perceive or to get a solid sense of something. In the short-lived American version of the series, he was called ''Magigimmix'' (&quot;magic gimmicks&quot;). He was called ''[[RMC Group|Readymix]]'' (the name of a British cement firm) in newspaper comics during the 1970s, as ''Getafix'' was considered inappropriate for children. In the English version of the ''Asterix the Gaul'' film, he has been called ''Panoramix''.
*In [[Danish language|Danish]], [[German language|German]], [[Norwegian language|Norwegian]], and [[Swedish language|Swedish]] he is called ''Miraculix'' a pun on &quot;miracle&quot;.
*In [[Serbian language|Serbian]], he is known as Аспириникс (''Aspiriniks''), from the drug [[Aspirin]].
*In [[Croatian language|Croatian]], he is known as ''Čudomiks'' (pronounced {{respell|chu|do-mix}}), from ''{{lang|hr|čudo}}'' (&quot;miracle&quot;) and ''{{lang|hr|miks}}'' (&quot;mix&quot;).
*In [[Finnish language|Finnish]], he is ''Akvavitix'', from &quot;[[akvavit]]&quot;, a [[Scandinavia]]n [[distilled beverage]] (derived from ''[[Aqua vitae]]'').
*In [[Esperanto]], he is ''Miraklomiks'', from ''{{lang|eo|miraklo}}'' (&quot;miracle&quot;) and ''{{lang|eo|mikso}}'' (&quot;mix&quot;)
*In [[Turkish language|Turkish]], his name is ''Büyüfiks'' (''{{lang|tr|büyü}}'' meaning &quot;magic&quot;). Previously it was ''Hokusfokus'', from the [[magic word]] ''Hocus Pocus''.
*In [[Hindi Language|Hindi]], he is हकीम वैधिक्स (''Hakeem Vaidhix''), Hindi for a &quot;village doctor&quot;.
*In [[Hungarian Language|Hungarian]], he is ''Magicoturmix'', which is a composition of &quot;magic&quot; and &quot;shake&quot;, thus meaning &quot;Shake of Magic&quot;. Actually this is a reference to the potion he is brewing, which gives the villagers their wondrous superhuman strength.
*In [[Bengali Language|Bengali]], he is ''Etashetamix'' (এটাসেটামিক্স), meaning &quot;mix this and that&quot;.
*In [[Icelandic language|Icelandic]], he is ''Sjóðríkur'', roughly meaning &quot;one who boils&quot;. In comparison, Asterix is ''Ástríkur'', &quot;one who loves&quot;.
*In [[Hebrew Language|Hebrew]], אשפיקס (''Ashafix''), meaning &quot;master of the craft&quot;.
*In [[Welsh Language|Welsh]], he is ''Crycymalix'', a pun on the phrase ''{{lang|cy|cryd cymalau}}'' which means &quot;arthritis&quot; or &quot;rheumatism&quot;, referring to his old age.
*In [[Sinhalese Language|Sinhalese]] — සිංහල (''Vedha Pappa'') which means a &quot;[[druid]]&quot; or &quot;[[witch]]&quot;.
*In Malaysia, the English version that was released in the newspapers, he was &quot;Medix&quot; due to the strict laws in the country against drug abuse.

===Dogmatix===

{{Main|Dogmatix}}

:First appearance: ''[[Asterix and the Banquet]]'' (book 5 in France), page 8.
'''Dogmatix''' is Obelix's pet dog. Unlike his immense master, Dogmatix is very tiny, but he can have a nasty temper. Dogmatix loves nature and hates to see trees suffer. (Obelix once mentions that this is because Dogmatix likes to urinate on them.) Dogmatix met Asterix and Obelix in Lutetia (in ''Asterix and the Banquet'') and followed them all the way around Gaul until Obelix finally noticed him. Since then, Obelix has become very affectionate toward Dogmatix. In ''Asterix and the Chieftain's Shield'', Obelix gets mad at hungry people who try to take Dogmatix's bone and insists they will be punished if they try to take advantage of his dog. Dogmatix is relatively intelligent, but is useless when it comes to sniffing out a trail. When given a trail to follow, he will follow the scent to menhirs.&lt;ref&gt;Asterix and the Normans p. 20&lt;/ref&gt; In ''Asterix and the Black Gold'', the trio are wandering in the desert when Dogmatix starts to dig. Asterix and Obelix hope he has found water but Dogmatix actually discovers oil. While this does not solve the trio's problem of thirst, it does complete their original mission to find oil.
* [[French language|French]]: ''Idéfix'' (''{{lang|fr|idée fixe}}'', a &quot;fixed idea&quot; or &quot;obsession&quot;, also a &quot;prejudice&quot;). Most translations use some variant of this original name (e.g. ''Ideafix'' in [[Spanish language|Spanish]] and ''Idefiks'' in [[Esperanto]] and [[Polish language|Polish]]).
*In [[Danish language|Danish]], [[German language|German]], [[Swedish language|Swedish]], [[Dutch language|Dutch]], [[Norwegian language|Norwegian]] and [[Finnish language|Finnish]], ''Idefix''
*In [[English language|English]], ''Dogmatix'' comes from ''[[dogma]]tic'' — clinging to an unchanging set of beliefs. The pun is extended because the name also contains the word &quot;dog&quot;.
*[[Hindi language|Hindi]] — In the मधु मुस्कान (''[[Madhu Muskan]]'') translations, Dogmatix has been called ''Kutta Bhaunkix'' (&quot;the dog who barks&quot;)
*In [[Bengali language|Bengali]] — he is known as ''Gnoyartumix'' (গোঁয়ার্তুমিক্স) — compare the Bengali term ''{{lang|bn-Latn|gNyoyartumi}}'', which means &quot;being dogmatic&quot; .
*In [[Hebrew language|Hebrew]], מבריקס (''Mavrix'') means &quot;bright&quot;.
*In [[Hungarian language|Hungarian]], it is ''Töpszlix'' which refers to his small size.
*In [[Serbian language|Serbian]], it is Идефикс (''Idefiks'' — directly taken from the French ''Idéfix'') or Гаровикс (''Garoviks'', from ''{{lang|sr|garov}}'', a common name for a dog of indeterminable breed)
*In [[Greek language|Greek]] early translations he was called ''Katrulix'' (Κατρουλίξ) meaning &quot;he who pees himself&quot;. However this was considered too demeaning by the readers, and thus was changed to ''Idefix'' (Ιντεφίξ)
*In [[Portuguese language|Portuguese]], ''Ideiafix'', a Portuguese variation (''Ideia Fixa'') of the original French name
*In [[Sinhalese Language|Sinhalese]] — In the සිංහල ''Chuti Kuku'' which is a name for a dog
*In [[Italian language|Italian]] — ''Idefix'' but in the movie ''Asterix and Cleopatra'' he is called ''Ercolino'' (&quot;Little Hercules&quot;)
*In [[Icelandic language|Icelandic]] — ''Krílríkur''

==Major recurring characters==
At the beginning of most of the Asterix books, immediately after the map of Gaul, and before the narrative starts, there is a standard description of the main characters above, as well as Getafix, Cacofonix and Vitalstatistix (regardless of their importance in that particular book).

:The '''first appearance''' of all the major characters is in ''[[Asterix the Gaul]]'' unless otherwise noted. Notes are given for languages which have translations of 90% or more of the albums — primarily European languages along with [[Brazilian Portuguese]]. ([[Indonesian language|Indonesian]] also falls in this category, but it leaves the French names unchanged.  Languages which do not use the &quot;x&quot; (such as those of [[Eastern Europe]] like [[Polish language|Polish]], [[Baltic languages]], [[Turkish language|Turkish]] and [[Esperanto]]) substitute &quot;ks&quot; in translations; &quot;c&quot; is also not used in some (such as Polish, Greek and Basque) which substitute &quot;k&quot; or &quot;z&quot; for hard and soft &quot;c&quot; respectively in names that are otherwise unaltered.

===Vitalstatistix===

'''Chief Vitalstatistix''' is the leader of the [[Gaul]]ish village. He is a middle-aged, overweight man with red hair, [[pigtail]]s and a huge [[moustache]]. He is generally reasonable, well-informed, fearless, (comparatively) even-tempered and unambitious — the last much to the chagrin of his wife [[#Impedimenta|Impedimenta]]. His major failings are his love of good food and drink (it is unlikely to be a coincidence that his wife is the best cook in the village) — which has led to health problems — and his pride. As a Gaulish chief he prefers to travel on a [[shield]], carried by two shield bearers (they say pride comes before a fall... and he finds creative new ways to fall off the shield in almost every book). The names of the shield bearers are never mentioned.

Vitalstatistix fought at the battle of Alesia where Caesar (almost) completed his conquest of Gaul, before becoming chief of the village. In ''[[Asterix and the Chieftain's Shield]]'' it was revealed that the shield he is carried on originally belonged to the legendary Gaulish warrior chief [[Vercingetorix]].&lt;ref&gt;Asterix and the Chieftain's Shield, p. 5&lt;/ref&gt; His father was the village chief before him. He has a brother, [[Doublehelix (character)|Doublehelix]], in Lutetia who has a young daughter and a son, [[#Gauls|Justforkix]].

The introduction to each story states that Vitalstatistix has only one fear &quot;that the sky may fall on his head tomorrow&quot;; however, he rarely alludes to this in an actual story, and then only as a rallying cry: ''&quot;We have nothing to fear but ...&quot;''.  This characteristic is based on a real historical account where Gallic chieftains were asked by Alexander the Great what they were most afraid of in all the world, and replied that their worst fear was that the sky might fall on their heads.&lt;ref&gt;Arrian, Campaigns of Alexander, p. 49&lt;/ref&gt;

Although the chief of the village, his role in most plots is usually minor, commonly featuring him granting Asterix and Obelix permission to go on their latest missions, although he has shown a greater involvement in stories such as ''[[Asterix in Belgium]]'', where he travelled to Belgium to defend his honour when Caesar apparently proclaimed that the Belgians were the bravest of all the Gaulish peoples, or ''[[Asterix and Caesar's Gift]]'', where he ran against a new arrival in the village for the position of chief.

* [[French language|French]]: ''Abraracourcix'' (''{{lang|fr|à bras raccourcis}}'' — &quot;with arms up ready to fight&quot;) — this is the same in Italian, Portuguese, Spanish and (original) Dutch (although the &quot;o&quot; is usually dropped).
*In [[English language|English]], his name is a pun on [[Vital statistics (government records)|Vital statistics]] — the government birth and death records of a region and also an expression for a person's measurements (a comment on his size). In the American translation, he was ''Macroeconomix'' from [[macroeconomics]]. NOTE: In the English version of the ''Asterix the Gaul'' film, he also appears to have been called ''Tonabrix'', and in the American dub of the ''Asterix and the Big Fight'' film he is called ''Bombastix''.
*In Catalan, he is ''Copdegarròtix''  (''{{lang|ca|cop de garrot}}'' — &quot;club hit&quot;).
*In [[German language|German]], Greek, [[Latin language|Latin]] and [[North Germanic languages|Scandinavian]], he is ''Majestix'' from &quot;majestic&quot;; similarly in new Dutch translations he is ''Heroix'' from &quot;heroic&quot;.
*In [[Esperanto]] he is ''Moŝtiks'' (''{{lang|eo|via moŝto}}'' — ''your highness'').
*In [[Finnish language|Finnish]] he is ''Aladobix'', referring to ''{{lang|fi|aladobi}}'', a Finnish jelly-like dish containing meat (from the French ''{{lang|fr|à la daube}}'').
*In [[Hungarian language|Hungarian]], he is ''Hasarengazfix'', which means &quot;His belly surely shakes&quot;.
*In [[Polish language|Polish]], he is ''Asparanoiks'', referring to [[paranoia]], the fear of the sky falling on his head.
*In Turkish, ''Toptoriks'', alluding to his roundness.
*In Brazilian Portuguese, his name is usually shortened to ''Abracurcix''.
*In Hindi translation, his name is mentioned as मुखिया मोटुमालिक्स (''Mukhiya Motumallix''), which literally means 'The Fat Chief'.
*In [[Bengali language|Bengali]], the chief has a name phonetically similar to some extent to his English one: ''Bishalakritix'' (বিশালাকৃতিক্স), taken from the root ''bishalakriti'', which aptly means &quot;of huge proportions&quot;.
*In [[Hebrew language|Hebrew]], his name is לוחמאמיקס (''lokhem-amix''), meaning &quot;brave warrior&quot;.
*In [[Serbian language|Serbian]], He is Дрматорикс (''Drmatoriks''), from ''{{lang|sr|drmator}}'', a slang term for Communist era movers and shakers (''{{lang|sr|drmati}}'' means &quot;to shake&quot;).
*In [[Welsh Language|Welsh]], he is ''Einharweinix'', from ''ein harweinydd'' (our leader).
*In [[Greek language|Greek]] film variations he was called Χοντρομπαλίξ (''Khontrobalix''), from χοντρομπαλάς (''khontrobalás'', dubbing a man &quot;fat ball&quot;), but is currently referred to as Μαζεστίξ (''Mazestix'', from French ''{{lang|fr|majestueux}}'': &quot;majestic&quot;). He was also formerly called Μοναρχίξ (''Monarchix'') from the word μονάρχης (''monárchēs'': &quot;monarch&quot;) but the name changed in the later book translations after 1991.
*In [[Sinhalese Language|Sinhalese]] — සිංහල (''Loku Pappa'') which means big or head/leader.
*In [[Slovene language|Slovene]], he is ''Ataaufbix''. ''{{lang|sv|Ata}}'' means &quot;dad&quot; or &quot;father&quot; and ''{{lang|sv|aufbiks}}'' is a folk invitation to a fight.

====Chief's shieldbearers====

From ''[[Asterix and Caesar's Gift]]'' onward Vitalstatistix has had the same (unnamed) bearers carry (and drop) him; prior to that he had different bearers in each album. In ''[[Asterix in Switzerland]]'' he fires both his shield bearers after he tells them that it's a lovely day, and they look up, tipping the shield back and dropping the chief in the process. He then goes and hires new shield bearers including Asterix, Geriatrix, Fulliautomatix and Obelix (in these cases the shield is horribly tilted so he is forced to stand on a slant, and Obelix carried him with one hand like a waiter).

====Impedimenta====

:First appearance: ''[[Asterix and the Big Fight]]'' (but not named until ''[[Asterix and the Chieftain's Shield]]'').
'''Impedimenta''' is the matriarchal wife of [[#Vitalstatistix|chief Vitalstatistix]], leader of the village wives and the best cook in the village. She is often disappointed with the other villagers (calling them barbarians) and wishes Vitalstatistix was more ambitious. Consequently she zealously defends and flaunts every privilege due to her as first lady of the village, such as skipping the queue at the fishmongers. She frequently says she wants to go back to [[Lutetia]] and live with her successful merchant brother, [[#Gauls|Homeopathix]] — the one member of the family her husband openly dislikes.

She nicknamed Vitalstatistix &quot;Piggywiggy&quot; when they were courting, and starts doing this again in ''[[Asterix and the Soothsayer]]'' as a plan to make Asterix and Obelix erupt in hysterical laughter when she calls him by that name in front of them, thus irritating him and making him punish them by forcing them to stay in the village, away from the soothsayer.&lt;ref&gt;''[[Asterix and the Soothsayer]]'', p. 15&lt;/ref&gt;

On occasion she has an antagonistic rivalry with Mrs. Geriatrix that has erupted into violence.  One such occasion was in ''[[Asterix and the Magic Carpet]]'' where the two beat each other with fish from Unhygenix's store over the fakir Watziznehm's carpet.

Her name appears to derive directly from the Latin military term &quot;impedimenta&quot; — &quot;baggage&quot;.

* [[French language|French]]: ''Bonemine'' (''{{lang|fr|bonne mine}}'', meaning &quot;good looking&quot;) — also used in Swedish or Esperanto, and in Greek Μπονεμίνα (''Bonemina'') or Μιμίνα (''Mimina'').
*In [[English language|English]], the name is derived from ''[[wiktionary:impediment|impediment]]'', an obstacle, but possibly also a reference to the Latin ''impedimenta'', meaning ''baggage''; (in the American translations: ''Belladonna'' — a poisonous plant used in cosmetics whose name means ''beautiful lady'').
*In [[Italian language|Italian]], she is ''Beniamina''.
*In Spanish, she is ''Karabella '' (meaning &quot;beautiful face&quot;).
*In Portuguese, she is called Bonemine in some stories and Caralinda in others (Portuguese ''{{lang|pt|cara linda}}'', &quot;beautiful face&quot;).
*In the Brazilian translation she is ''[[naphthalene|Naftalina]]''.
*In [[Dutch language|Dutch]], she is ''Bellefleur'' (&quot;beautiful flower&quot; in French).
*In [[German language|German]], she is ''Gutemine''; Danish and Norwegian, ''Godemine'', presumably from the old saying ''{{lang|de|Gute Miene zum bösen Spiel machen}}'' (German), ''{{lang|da|At holde gode miner til slet spil}}'' (Danish): &quot;To keep up appearances in the face of bad deeds&quot;), and mirroring the French ''{{lang|fr|bonne mine}}''.
*In [[Hungarian language|Hungarian]], she is ''Hengerlice''; which means &quot;tumbler pigeon&quot;, a pun on her being a little fat.
*In Turkish, she is ''Dediğimdediks''. ''{{lang|tr|Dediğim dedik}}'' refers to someone who insists on getting their way.
*In [[Finnish language|Finnish]], she is ''Smirgeline'' (a pun on the Finnish word ''{{lang|fi|smirgeli}}'' meaning &quot;emery&quot;, by way of the Finnish [[dysphemism]] for a &quot;shrew&quot; being a grinder)
*In [[Polish language|Polish]], she is ''Dobromina'' (most likely a pun on the Polish saying ''{{lang|pl|robić dobrą minę do złej gry}}'', which has the same meaning as the German/Danish/Norwegian translation above, and the [[old Polish]] female given name ''Dobromira'' (&quot;the one that values goodness and peace&quot;) or ''Dobromiła'' (&quot;the one that is good and nice&quot;).
*In Catalan, she is sometimes called ''Bonemina'', but more usually ''Karabella''.
*In Hindi, she is referred to as प्यारी सिरर्ददा (''Pyari Sirdarda''), the beloved, who causes Headache.
*In Hebrew she is called זיופנים (''Zivpanim''), meaning &quot;bright face&quot;.

===Cacofonix===
[[Image:Parc Asterix 43.jpg|thumb|right|Cacofonix's hut in Parc Asterix]]
'''Cacofonix''' is the village [[bard]]. He is usually only a supporting character, but has a major part in the plots of some albums (see ''[[Asterix and the Normans]]'', ''[[Asterix the Gladiator]]'', ''[[Asterix and the Magic Carpet]]'' and ''[[Asterix and the Secret Weapon]]''). He loves singing and playing his [[lyre]], and jumps at every opportunity to do so. He also plays the [[bagpipes]], [[drum]] and a Celtic [[trumpet]] resembling a boar called a [[Carnyx]]. While he can accompany traditional dances, and conducts a village band, his singing is unbearable. In [[Asterix and the Normans]] it is so unbearable that it teaches the fearless Normans the meaning of fear. In recent albums his music is so spectacularly horrible that it actually starts thunderstorms (even indoors), because of an old French saying that bad singing causes rain.

For his part, Cacofonix considers himself a genius and a superb singer, and he is angrily offended when people criticize his singing, to the point of dismissing them as barbarians. He is  slightly effeminate, often seen smoothing back his hair and holding his head up high. 

Some villagers go to extreme lengths to avoid hearing Cacofonix's music. Most notably, Fulliautomatix, the village smith, bangs him on the head at the merest hint of breaking into a song, and has destroyed his lyre on a number of occasions, at one point being called the &quot;ancestor of music critics&quot;. As a [[running gag]], Cacofonix is generally tied up and gagged during the banquet at the end of most albums to allow the other villagers to have a good time without having to keep him from singing. He is nonetheless well liked when not singing.

In contrast to the villagers, some of the younger outsiders whom Cacofonix has met do appreciate his &quot;talent&quot;: Justforkix (in ''[[Asterix and the Normans]]'') actually encouraged Cacofonix to think seriously about moving to [[Lutetia]] where he claimed the bard's way with music would be enjoyed; Pepe (in ''[[Asterix in Spain]]'') liked it because it reminded him of home (the goats bleating in his village); and Princess Orinjade (in ''[[Asterix and the Magic Carpet]]'') expressed similar enthusiasm, though it was perhaps in gratitude for his music having saved her from being sacrificed.

Unlike the other villagers, whose [[hut (dwelling)|hut]]s are on the ground, Cacofonix's hut is perched up in a tree. Ostensibly this is so that he can act as a lookout to warn the other villagers of imminent invasion, but the real reason is to let him practise his music as far from everyone as possible: it is a tall tree!  It has been felled several times but has been replanted, or restored by Getafix's magic acorns (in ''[[The Mansions of the Gods]]'').

In the English and American adaptations of the series, he speaks in an effeminate voice.

He and Getafix are the village's teachers, as only bards and druids are allowed to teach in school. He is rarely seen fighting the Romans except when his personal honour is impugned — his voice apparently does not mix well with the magic potion, although in ''[[Asterix and the Magic Carpet]]'' it actually restores him to full voice.  The fact that he is incredibly arrogant may also be partly to blame, as in at least one volume (''[[Asterix and the Roman Agent]]'') he is shown to have not even noticed the other villagers are fighting the Romans and is actually shown asking Getafix what's going on (however, he had been suffering from a lost voice earlier in this volume and may have simply been staying in his hut while waiting to recover).

* [[French language|French]]: ''Assurancetourix'' (''{{lang|fr|Assurance tous risques}}'' meaning &quot;comprehensive insurance&quot;) — also in [[Spanish language|Spanish]] (''Asuranceturix''), [[Catalan language|Catalan]] (''Assegurançatórix''), [[Italian language|Italian]], [[Portuguese language|Portuguese]] and original [[Dutch language|Dutch]] translations.
*In [[English language|English]], ''Cacofonix'' is derived from [[cacophony|cacophonic]] (describing &quot;harsh and unpleasant sounds&quot;), from Greek κακός (''kakos'', meaning &quot;bad&quot;) and φωνή (''phonē'', meaning &quot;voice&quot;). In the American version of the series, he was called ''Malacoustix'', which refers to &quot;bad acoustics&quot;. In the English dub of the film ''Asterix the Gaul'' he is called ''Stopthemusix'' (a pun on the phrase &quot;stop the music&quot;) and in the American dub of the ''Asterix and the Big Fight'' film he is called ''Franksinatrix'' (a pun on [[Frank Sinatra]]).
*In [[Greek language|Greek]] he is Κακοφωνίξ (''Kakofonix'') and similarly ''Kakofonix, Kakofoniks'' in Polish, Turkish and in new Dutch translations.
*In [[Serbian language|Serbian]], his name is Тамбурикс (''Tamburiks''). The name comes from [[tambura]]. He doesn't actually play a tambura, but the instrument is very popular in [[Serbia]]. ''Tamburati'' (&quot;to play tambura&quot;), interestingly enough, is a Serbian slang meaning &quot;to beat someone up&quot;. At the end of many albums, ''Tamburiks'' often gets beaten up, gagged and tied to a tree.
*In [[German language|German]] and [[Swedish language|Swedish]], he is ''Troubadix''; In [[Danish language|Danish]], [[Norwegian language|Norwegian]] and [[Finnish language|Finnish]] ''Trubadurix'' (a pun on &quot;[[troubadour]]&quot;, a word for &quot;bard&quot;).
*In the Brazilian translation he is ''Chatotorix'' (meaning &quot;annoying&quot; or &quot;the very dull one&quot;).
*In [[Hindi language|Hindi]] translation he is गवैयाँ बेसुरीक्स (''Gavaiyañ Besurix'') meaning &quot;one who sings out of tune&quot;.
*In [[Bengali language|Bengali]] this bard is known as ''Kawlorobix'' (কলরবিক্স) — the root being (''{{lang|bn-Latn|kawlorob}}'') — meaning &quot;making a lot of noise for no purpose&quot;
*In [[Hungarian language|Hungarian]] translation he is ''Hangjanix'', which means &quot;He absolutely has no voice&quot;.
*Similarly, the [[Esperanto]] name ''Malmuziks'' means &quot;the contrary of music&quot;.
*In [[Hebrew language|Hebrew]], חמשיריקס (''Khamshirix'') which can be literally translated back as ''Limerix'' (from &quot;[[Limerick (poetry)|limerick]]&quot;).
*In [[Icelandic language|Icelandic]] he is ''Óðríkur'', meaning &quot;Rich in Odes&quot;. A music-making competition in one of Iceland's most prestigious pre-colleges is named in his honour.
*In [[Welsh Language|Welsh]], he is ''Odlgymix'', from ''{{lang|cy|odl gymysg}}'' (&quot;mixed rhyme&quot;, a metre of Welsh verse).
*In [[Sinhalese Language|Sinhalese]] — In සිංහල (''Caco Pappa'') similar to ''Cacofonix''
*In [[Latin Language|Latin]], he is ''Cantorix'', from ''{{lang|la|canto}}'': &quot;to sing&quot;.

===Geriatrix===
:First Appearance: ''[[Asterix the Gladiator]]''&lt;ref&gt;Asterix the Gladiator&lt;/ref&gt; but first '''named''' in ''[[Asterix at the Olympic Games]]''
'''Geriatrix''' is the oldest inhabitant of Asterix's village: he is mentioned as 93 years old in  ''[[Asterix at the Olympic Games]]'' (while drunk, he says he feels ten years younger, to which Asterix replies, &quot;Well, that makes you 83, and it's time you were in bed&quot;). Some translations make him no more than 80.

As an elder, Geriatrix demands respect (generally more than he is given). Nonetheless he dislikes being treated as old and will attack anyone who comments to that effect. In particular he often beats up Fulliautomatix for refusing to fight back due to his age, and actually cries out to be attacked. Geriatrix is seen to sit on the village council at times, on the face of it an entitlement deriving from being the oldest in the community. An example is on p.&amp;nbsp;11 of '''Asterix and the Cauldron''' where he sits with Vitalstatistix, Cacofonix and Getafix, in deciding on Asterix's punishment for having violated their honor code. In ''[[Asterix and the Roman Agent]]'' he acquires a club which he later uses to knock down ''[[The Mansions of the Gods]]''.

Geriatrix is against foreigners who are not from his village. He is a veteran of the [[Battle of Gergovia]] and the [[Battle of Alesia]], and refers to them when excited (&quot;It'll be just like Gergovia all over!&quot;) or distraught (&quot;It's just like Alesia all over again!&quot;).
He has an eye for the young ladies and has a very young and beautiful wife (who appears to be in her twenties) of whom he is very possessive — particularly when Obelix is around.

In [[prequels]] such as ''[[How Obelix Fell into the Magic Potion When he was a Little Boy]]'', in which most of the characters are children and Vitalstatistix is a slim young man, Geriatrix, along with Getafix, is unchanged.
* [[French language|French]]: ''Agecanonix'' (''{{lang|fr|Âge canonique}}'', meaning &quot;very old age&quot;) (also in [[Portuguese language|Portuguese]], as well as ''Decanonix'' — from ''{{lang|pt|Decano}}'', &quot;dean&quot;).
*In [[English language|English]], the name comes from [[Geriatrics]], the branch of medicine dealing with old age. He is also known as ''Arthritix'' in the American translations.
*In [[Spanish language|Spanish]], he is ''Edadepiedrix'' and ''Edatdepèdrix'' in Catalan (meaning &quot;Stone Age&quot;).
*In [[Finnish language|Finnish]] and  [[North Germanic languages|the Scandinavian languages]], he is ''Senilix'' (from [[senile]]).
*In [[Italian language|Italian]], he is ''Matusalemix'', from ''Matusalem'' ([[Methuselah]]), the biblical &quot;old man&quot;, similarly in [[German language|German]], ''Methusalix'' and in [[Greek language|Greek]] he is Μαθουσαλίξ (''Mathousalix''), formerly Παλαιοντολογίξ (''Palaiontologix'').
* In [[Serbian language|Serbian]], he is Дедовикс (''Dedoviks''), from Serbian ''{{lang|sr|deda}}'' (&quot;grandfather&quot;).
*In [[Hebrew language|Hebrew]], מתושלחיקס, אשמאיקס, קשישניקס (''Methushelakhix'', ''Ashmaix'' (Asterix at the Olympic Games), ''Kashishnix'' (Animated films)).
*In [[Dutch language|Dutch]], he is ''Nestorix'' (after [[Nestor (mythology)|Nestor]]).
*In [[Esperanto]], he is ''Dojeniks'' (from ''{{lang|eo|dojeno}}'' — doyen, wise old man)
*In [[Polish language|Polish]], he is ''Ramoliks'' (&quot;grumpy old man&quot;) or ''Długowieczniks'' (&quot;long living&quot;).
*In [[Hungarian language|Hungarian]], he is ''Sokadikix'' (&quot;umpteenth decade&quot;) or ''Tatix'' (from ''{{lang|hu|tata}}'', an informal way to address old men) or ''Rozogavénix'' (&quot;rickety old&quot;) or  ''Matuzsálemix'' (Methuselah)
*In the Brazilian translation he is ''Veteranix''.
*In the Hindi translation he is बुड्ढिक्स (''Buddhix''), which means &quot;the old man&quot;.
*In [[Turkish language|Turkish]] he is ''Eskitopraks'' meaning &quot;old timer&quot;.
*In Indonesian he is ''Capeloyonix'' which loosely translates to &quot;old hunched man who is easily tired&quot;. (Cape - pronounced as Chapeh: meaning tired; Loyo; meaning weak)

====Mrs. Geriatrix====
:First Appearance: ''[[Asterix and the Roman Agent]]''
'''Mrs. Geriatrix''' enjoys her husband's devotion and also her status as wife of the village's most senior inhabitant, which makes her one of the inner circle of village wives. Her youthful appearance suggests that she is less than half her husband's age; she is also a lot taller. Although as ambitious and gossip-prone as the other wives, she has also shown herself to be very quick-witted. She is an excellent seamstress but has Geriatrix do most of the housework. She rules her home and marriage, and regularly tells her husband what to do even in direct contradiction of his own stated opinions. She does seem to be happily married, however, and the only serious conflict in her marriage is her occasional apparent interest in [[Obelix]] which makes her husband insanely jealous. On one occasion, she is offered the magic potion. She does not appear to be interested and says that it's very fattening, while staring at Obelix. She appears to be in favour of women's rights, as shown in ''Asterix and the Secret Weapon''. She eagerly accepted the radical changes in the village that occurred in this story. She and Impedimenta cause a gigantic fight in Mini Midi Maxi.
* She has never been officially named and is always referred to by [[Mrs#Equivalents in other languages|the local title for wife]] and the translation of her husband's name ([[Uderzo]] has stated she is partially based on his own wife and he wishes to retain an air of mystery). In ''[[Asterix and the Soothsayer]]'', Impedimenta appears to address her as ''Myopia'' (which, given her choice of spouse would be extremely appropriate), but equally this may have been an invocation to a Gaulish Goddess (of short-sightedness) thus a '''[[double entendre]]'''.

===Unhygienix===

:First appearance: ''[[Asterix in Spain]]''
'''Unhygienix''' is the village [[fishmonger]], as was his father Unhealthix before him{{Citation needed|date=May 2009}}.
His fish do not come from the sea near the village even though he has a fishing boat; instead they are transported all the way from [[Paris|Lutetia]] (and from [[Marseilles|Massilia]] in the German translations) as he believes they are of finer quality. He does not notice their smell, but most of the other villagers do and a lot of fights are caused by his stale fish, as when the blacksmith Fulliautomatix says: &quot;Anyway, it [the fight] wouldn't have happened if they [the fish] were fresh!&quot; and then Unhygenix slaps him with his fish.
He regularly has fights about his fish with his friend [[#Fulliautomatix|Fulliautomatix]], the village blacksmith, which often escalate to involve most of the village. Fulliautomatix says the fish are stale, Unhygienix throws a fish at him, he throws it back, it hits someone else, etc., and the whole village gets into a fight. This rivalry is a family tradition — their fathers also fought, and their children are continuing it. Despite this, his catch phrase is a scream to his wife, &quot;Bacteria! Get the fish inside!&quot; or &quot;Save the sales!&quot;, in fights on the village he doesn't want to enter (i.e. fights that are not about his fish), when villagers buy or steal his fish to fight with.
* [[French language|French]]: ''Ordralfabétix'' (''{{lang|fr|Ordre alphabétique}}'', meaning &quot;alphabetical order&quot;) — this is essentially the same in Spanish (Ordenalfabétix), Portuguese, Catalan and Italian (''Ord'''in'''alfabetix''), as well as Hebrew (לפיסדראלפאבטיקס, ''Lefisederalphabetix'')
*In [[English language|English]], he is ''Unhygienix'' (&quot;unclean&quot; from &quot;[[hygiene|unhygienic]]&quot;), and in the ''Asterix and the Big Fight'' film he is called Fishstix.
*In [[Dutch language|Dutch]], he is ''Kostunrix'' (&quot;costs a riks&quot;, ''{{lang|nl|riks}}'' being an old name for 2.50 [[Dutch guilder]]s)
*In [[German language|German]], he is ''Verleihnix''  (''{{lang|de|Verleih' nichts}}'' — &quot;(I) do not lend anything&quot;)
*In [[Swedish language|Swedish]], he is ''Crabbofix'' (close to &quot;crab and fish&quot;)
*In [[Danish language|Danish]], he is ''Hørmetix'' (''{{lang|da|Hørme}}'' means &quot;to stink&quot;)
*In [[Norwegian language|Norwegian]], he is ''Hermetix'' (''{{lang|no|Hermetikk}}'' refers to the food contained in [[hermetic seal|hermetic]] [[tin can]]s)
*In [[Polish language|Polish]], he is ''Szykalfabetiks'' (&quot;alphabetical order&quot;) '''or''' ''Ahigieniks'' (&quot;unhygienic&quot;)
*In [[Hungarian language|Hungarian]], he is ''Messesaglix'' (&quot;stinks far&quot;)
*In [[Serbian language|Serbian]], he is Аеробикс (''Aerobiks'') — a pun on the word &quot;[[aerobics]]&quot;
*In [[Portuguese language|Portuguese]], he is &quot;Ordenalfabetix&quot; (&quot;alphabetic order&quot;)
*In [[Esperanto]], his name is ''Fiŝaĉiks'' [&quot;fishachix&quot;] (''{{lang|eo|fiŝaĉo}}'' — ''rotten fish'')
*In [[Finnish language|Finnish]], he is ''Amaryllix''.
*In [[Greek language|Greek]], he is Αλφαβητίξ (''Alfavētix'') meaning &quot;alphabet&quot; — formerly Καταλφαβητίξ (''Katalfavētix'') meaning &quot;in alphabetical order&quot;.
*In [[Turkish language|Turkish]], he is ''Palamutiks''. ''{{lang|tr|Palamut}}'' is Turkish for [[Bonito]].
*In [[Sinhala language|Sinhala]], he is ''කුණු මාලුවා''(''kunu maaluwa'') meaning &quot;The man with the rotten fish&quot;.
*In Malaysia, the English version that was released in the newspapers, he was &quot;Fishmix&quot; maybe because of the negative implication that Unhygienix gives to the eating of fish.

====Bacteria====

:First appearance: ''[[Asterix in Spain]]''
'''Bacteria''' is the wife of Unhygienix. She is one of the inner circle of village wives. She is quiet and easy-going, but doesn't hesitate to say exactly what she thinks. She helps her husband run his shop, selling fish of dubious quality, and is unperturbed by the bizarre uses to which they are sometimes put. They have two sons (whose names have not been mentioned) — one with blonde hair in ''Asterix in Corsica'', and the other with red hair in ''Asterix and the Secret Weapon''.
In ''Asterix and Obelix's Birthday: The Golden Book'' the blonde son is seen having taken over the shop but rather than to import the fish from Lutetia, he gets the fish he sells from the nearby sea. This displeases his father who fears that the &quot;good name of the shop will go to waste&quot; that way.

* [[French language|French]]: ''Iélosubmarine'' (a pun on &quot;[[Yellow Submarine (song)|Yellow Submarine]]&quot;) — a variant of this is used in most translations.
*In [[English language|English]], [[bacteria]] is the name for a [[biological kingdom|kingdom]] of microorganisms, some of which are responsible for various diseases, keeping the same unsanitary character as her husband's name.
*In [[Dutch language|Dutch]], she is ''Forentientje'' (''{{lang|nl|voor een tientje}}'' means &quot;for a ten-guilder bill&quot;, keeping the same monetary nature as the translation of her husband's name).
*In [[North Germanic languages|Scandinavian]], she is ''Remouladine''. (After the dressing, [[remoulade]], popular in Scandinavia and often eaten along with fish.){{citation needed |date=June 2011 |reason=but her name is never used in Swedish!}}
* In [[Polish language|Polish]] she is ''Jelousubmarina'', which is &quot;yellow submarine&quot; written according to Polish pronunciation and with a female ending.

===Fulliautomatix===
'''Fulliautomatix''' is the village [[Smith (metalwork)|smith]]. His father, '''Semiautomatix''', was the village smith before him. He is tall and [[wikt:robust|robust]], and very [[wikt:strong|strong]] — he is one of the strongest characters, perhaps second only to Obelix, and a bit of a bully. Fulliautomatix's first appearance was in the first volume, ''[[Asterix the Gaul]]'', where the [[ancient Rome|Roman]] spy was amazed that he used his fists to forge [[iron]]. However, he is subsequently shown using a normal [[hammer]] and is now rarely seen without one.
A very different looking Fulliautomatix appeared in ''[[Asterix and the Banquet]]'' in which he and Obelix argue as to who should be entitled to punch the Roman that they are both engaged in hitting anyway.

Fulliautomatix often interacts with [[#Unhygienix|Unhygienix]], the fishmonger, with whom he has a friendly rivalry. Fulliautomatix claims the [[fish]] he sells are stale, and this often results in Unhygienix throwing a fish at his face, causing a fight (sometimes the other villagers join in just for fun).&lt;ref&gt;Asterix in Belgium&lt;/ref&gt;
Fulliautomatix also takes great pleasure in bullying, breaking the lyre of [[#Cacofonix|Cacofonix]] the bard, threatening him and hitting him on the head at the merest hint of breaking into a song (the songs are so bad that the other villagers do not object) — this happens so frequently that Cacofonix only protests about it if he hadn't intended to sing in the first place (such as in [[Asterix and Cleopatra]], where it turned out Cacofonix just wanted to tell Fulliautomatix that he was standing on Cacofonix's foot). It has been stated that he is perhaps the ancestor of all music critics. On the other hand, he is occasionally beaten up by [[#Geriatrix|Geriatrix]] when he is provoked by some comment the smith makes. When this happens he will often take out his frustration on the nearest convenient bystander (Cacofonix for preference) on the grounds that he does not feel he can fight back against someone so old, which only helps to further incense the old man. He could possibly be Geriatrix's grandson. On p.&amp;nbsp;15 of the English version of ''[[Asterix at the Olympic Games]]'' ''Fulliautomatix'' calls ''Geriatrix'' &quot;Grandpa!&quot;. However the term is often used in informal English as a derogatory term for any old man by a younger person.

''Fulliautomatix'' also has two unnamed children who have appeared in separate comics — a son with blond hair in ''Asterix in Corsica'', and a daughter with blonde hair in ''Asterix and the Secret Weapon''. In ''[[Asterix and the Great Divide]]'' he is shown as having an [[apprentice]], though it is not indicated whether or not they are related; some speculate that he is the young son grown to teenage years. In [[Asterix and Obelix's Birthday: The Golden Book]] Fulliautomatix is seen as an elderly man with his now adult son having taken over business; the scene begins with his son making steel dentures for Fulliautomatix who has gone toothless over the years.

* [[French language|French]]: ''Cétautomatix'' (''{{lang|fr|c'est automatique}}'', meaning &quot;it is automatic&quot;) — the languages of Iberia follow fairly literally: ''Esautomátix'' in Spanish, ''Esautomàtix'' in Catalan and ''Zetautomatix'' in Basque; in Portuguese ''Ceutautomatix'' or ''Éautomatix''.
*In [[English language|English]], the name is a pun on &quot;fully automatic&quot;
*In [[German language|German]] and [[Italian language|Italian]] he is simply ''Automatix''.
*In [[Greek language|Greek]] he is Αυτοματίξ (''Automatix'')
*In [[Polish language|Polish]], he is ''Automatiks'', or ''Tenautomatiks''.
*In [[Esperanto]], his name is ''Tutaŭtomatiks''.
*In [[Dutch language|Dutch]], he is ''Hoefnix'' — a double pun: ''{{lang|nl|hoef}}'' means &quot;hoove&quot; and the phrase ''{{lang|nl|ik hoef niks}}'' means &quot;I don't need/have to do anything&quot;.
*In [[Brazilian Portuguese]], he is just ''Automatix.''
*In [[Danish language|Danish]], [[Norwegian language|Norwegian]] and [[Latin]], he is ''Armamix'' — in Latin, ''{{lang|la|armo}}'' means to provide arms, to equip with weapons.
*In Icelandic versions, he is ''Ryðríkur''. Ironically, ''{{lang|is|Ryð}}'' means &quot;[[rust]]&quot; in Icelandic.
*In [[Swedish language|Swedish]] versions, ''Smidefix'' (as a pun on the words &quot;smith&quot; and &quot;fix&quot;)
*In [[Turkish language|Turkish]], he is ''Tamotomatiks'', meaning &quot;fully automatic&quot;.
*In [[Finnish language|Finnish]], he is ''Caravellix'', possibly as a pun on the boat model Karaveli, meaning [[Caravel]]. It also could be a reference to the French-built [[Sud Aviation Caravelle]] jetliners.
*In [[Serbian language|Serbian]], he is Металопластикс (''Metaloplastiks''), as a pun on the words &quot;[[metal]]&quot; and &quot;[[plastics]]&quot;, but also on the name of the famous [[team handball|handball]] team [[RK Metaloplastika|Metaloplastika]] from [[Šabac]]
*In Hindi translation, he is बदबोलिक्स लोहातोडिक्स (''Badbolix Lohatodix''), which means &quot;ill-spoken iron-breaker&quot;
*In Hebrew, נשקאוטומאטיקס (''Neshek-Otomatix'') means &quot;automatic weapon&quot;.

====Mrs. Fulliautomatix====
:First appearance: ''[[Asterix and the Roman Agent]]''
'''Mrs. Fulliautomatix''' is one of the inner circle of village wives. One of the shortest women in the village, and possessing of a steep and pointy nose, she takes no nonsense and dominates her much larger husband. Although she appears often, she has never been named in the stories. She has been known to beat up Cacofonix on occasion as well, in ''[[Asterix and the Secret Weapon]]''. She has a brother, as mentioned by her husband in [[Asterix and the Black Gold]].

===Julius Caesar===
:''Main article: [[Julius Caesar]]'' (historical)
'''Julius Caesar''' (Jules César) is the Roman dictator and main [[antagonist]] of the comics. Many of the stories involve his schemes finally to conquer this last Gaulish village holding out against his legions. At other times, the village has (indirectly) come to his aid, but more often it is a major embarrassment to him in the [[Roman senate]] — in at least one book, the entire senate is laughing at him after a failed plan. Despite this, there is always a mutual respect shown between him and Asterix, and the feeling that he's not such a bad guy (aside from trying to conquer them). He is also shown to be a man of honour, since whenever Asterix and Obelix somehow end up helping Caesar, Caesar always grants them any favour they ask. He goes so far as to rebuild the entire Gaulish village when it was destroyed by [[Marcus Junius Brutus|Brutus]] who was trying to kidnap Caesar's son, whom Asterix returned safely to his family (''[[Asterix and Son]]''). The appearance of Caesar is based on portraits found on ancient Roman coins.

===The Pirates===
[[Image:Redbeard vs asterix.jpg|thumb|180px|right|''Asterix'' parodies on the left, ''[[Redbeard (comics)|Barbe Rouge]]'' originals at right]]

In the course of their travels, Asterix and Obelix regularly cross paths with — and beat up — a group of [[pirate]]s. The Gauls then proceed to sink their ship, causing the pirates severe financial difficulties. The pirates make their first appearance in the fourth album (''[[Asterix the Gladiator]]''), and feature in almost every subsequent album.

On one occasion (in ''[[Asterix the Legionary]]'') after the wreck the pirates were depicted in a scene similar to [[Théodore Géricault]]'s ''[[Raft of the Medusa]]''. In the English version of this scene, the captain also refers to an ancient Gaulish artist called &quot;Jericho&quot;, an alternative spelling of the name Géricault.

Such is the fear that the pirates have for the Gauls that, having unknowingly taken them aboard, they fled their own ship in the middle of the night while the subjects of their fear were sound asleep (''[[Asterix in Corsica]]''). At other times, it is Asterix and Obelix who have boarded the pirates' vessel and captured booty, thus reversing their roles of hunter and prey. This has happened mainly in the quest for food in an empty ocean (''[[Asterix in Spain]]''). On another occasion, Asterix and Obelix take all the food on the ship, leaving the pirates with a single sausage for the Captain's birthday (''[[Asterix and the Great Crossing]]''). It happened again (in ''[[Asterix and the Magic Carpet]]'') with Asterix leaving a single coin for payment; the Captain told his depressed crew that it was better than nothing and that at least they still had the ship, but then their lookout proudly announced that he had upheld their honour and scuttled the ship himself. The other pirates were not impressed.

This &quot;honorable suicide-sinking&quot; has actually happened in earlier Asterix adventures, such as in ''[[Asterix and Cleopatra]]'' when the captain himself sank the ship, reasoning that that would be the eventual outcome and doing it themselves would spare them a punch-up. Curiously enough, at the end of the same adventure, he and his crew were having to work as rowers aboard the very [[galley]] taking the Gauls back home and he announced the unusual determination to hunt them down and get his revenge. On another occasion, the pirates destroyed their ship simply at the sight of Asterix and all his fellow villagers in another vessel taking them to the [[Asterix at the Olympic Games|Olympic Games]]. In this event, though, the villagers did not attack since the captain of their ship announced that attacking the pirates would cost them extra.

On two occasions, Asterix also forced the Captain to spend all his hard-won loot on the merchandise of Ekonomikrisis the Phoenician merchant (''[[Asterix and the Black Gold]]''). On one occasion (''[[The Mansions of the Gods]]'') the Pirates appear on land, as part of the group of slaves (later freed) in the story. However, in one story so far - ''[[Asterix and the Cauldron]]'' - they end up happy for a change when a cauldron full of money that Asterix has been chasing throughout the story is tipped over a cliff and lands in their laps.

The main pirates are:
* '''Redbeard''' (''Barbe Rouge'') — captain of the pirates.
* '''Pegleg''' (''Triple Patte'') — an old pirate with a wooden leg who makes classical quotations in Latin.
* '''The Unnamed Pirate Lookout''' (''Baba'') — the [[Africa]]n pirate in the [[crow's nest]]. He also has a cousin who is a gladiator (see ''[[Asterix and the Cauldron]]''). In the original French and some other language versions he fails to pronounce the letters 'R' and 'L', leaving blanks in his speech. Early English translations also had him speaking something that resembled [[Jamaican Patois]] but this has been replaced by standard [[British English]] in re-editions, his manner of speaking no longer being a source of humour.
* '''Erix''' — the captain's son. Seen in ''[[Asterix and the Banquet]]'', he is mentioned in ''[[Asterix and Cleopatra]]'' as being left as a deposit on a new ship.

In addition a number of members of the pirate crew are [[sight gag]]s, some of whom have appeared on more than one occasion such as [[Frankenstein|Frankenstein's Monster]] and a [[Mongols|Mongol warrior]].

It should also be noted that in the films where the pirates are seen, Erix replaces Pegleg on the [[jetsam]] with Redbeard.

====Inspiration====
The main pirates are based on the French comic series ''[[Redbeard (comics)|Barbe Rouge]]'' (1959 and continuing). The adventures of Barbe Rouge (Redbeard) and his son Eric were published in the comic ''[[Pilote]]'', where Asterix's adventures were also published prior to appearing in book form.

Although Barbe Rouge is a popular character in his own right in continental Europe, the popularity of Asterix's pirates is one of the few occasions when parody figures have overshadowed their originals.

==Minor recurring characters==
:Original (''[[France|French]]'') name is given in parentheses when different.

===Historical figures===

[[File:Siege-alesia-vercingetorix-jules-cesar.jpg|thumb|right|200px|The surrender of [[Vercingetorix]] to Caesar, by [[Lionel-Noël Royer]].]]
* '''[[Cleopatra VII of Egypt|Queen Cleopatra]]''' (''Cléopâtre'') — Queen of Egypt. Other characters often make remarks about her beautiful nose. She appears on the cover of ''Asterix and Cleopatra'', where Asterix, Obelix and Getafix are asked for aid from an Egyptian architect to build a palace in three months, as Cleopatra has a bet with Caesar to show the greatness of the Egyptians and has threatened to feed the architect to the [[crocodile]]s if he fails. She is also in ''[[Asterix and Son]]''—where she sends her son by Caesar to Asterix for safekeeping as Brutus has tried to kill him—and ''[[Asterix and Obelix All at Sea]]'', where she is in Rome with Caesar, is less tanned and has a differently shaped nose. Her appearance in the comic is seemingly based on [[Elizabeth Taylor]]'s screen depiction of the historical figure.
* '''[[Marcus Junius Brutus|Brutus]]''' — Marcus Junius Brutus, Caesar's adopted son. Constantly plays with a knife, a reference to him being one of Caesar's assassins in real life. This is alluded to in [[Asterix and the Soothsayer]], where a [[soothsayer]] tells Caesar that if he keeps Brutus near he will come to no harm. Caesar often uses the [[Shakespeare]]an quote: &quot;{{lang|la|[[Et tu, Brute?]]}}&quot; to him for various purposes. Brutus appears in minor roles in various books, and has a major role in ''[[Asterix and Son]]'', where his plot to kill Caesar and Cleopatra's infant son to secure his place as Caesar's heir prompts him to attack the village when Cleopatra sends her son there for safety, causing Caesar to send him to Upper [[Germania]]. Brutus's physical appearance is arguably different in each of his appearances.
* '''[[Pompey]]''' (''Pompée'') — Caesar's greatest enemy and a former [[consul of Rome]]. He is mentioned in ''Asterix the Gladiator'', ''Asterix the Legionary'' and ''Asterix and the Roman Agent'' and appears in person in ''Asterix and the Actress'', where he is the book's antagonist, seeking valuable pieces of armour that have been given to Asterix and Obelix as birthday presents.
* '''[[Metellus Scipio]]''' (''Scipion'') — Another of Caesar's enemies, allied to Pompey. Caesar defeated him in the [[Battle of Thapsus]], as depicted in ''Asterix the Legionary''. Note that Pompey doesn't make an appearance there, as he was assassinated before these events took place (though he anachronistically surfaces in ''Asterix and the Actress'' later).
* '''[[Caesarion]]''' — Caesar and Cleopatra's baby boy. Appears in ''[[Asterix and Son]]'' where he is sent to the village for safety. He drinks magic potion twice, causing trouble for the villagers and the Romans sent to capture him, but it has worn off by the end and he is reunited with his family. He shows a liking for sleeping under trees.
* '''[[Spartacus]]''' — Gladiator and rebellion leader, resembling [[Kirk Douglas]] in ''[[Spartacus (1960 film)|Spartacus]]''. Appears in ''[[Asterix and Obelix All at Sea]]'' although in the album he is a Greek named ''Spartakis'', and is accompanied by a group of multi-national slaves after stealing Caesar's own galley. By the end the slaves have decided to stay in [[Atlantis]], and become children like most of the other inhabitants due to the magic of the Priest there.
* '''[[Vercingetorix]]''' — [[Arverni]]an chieftain, who is shown as a historical figure surrendering Gaul in various books by throwing his arms at the feet of Caesar, which comically hurt Caesar's feet. His shield is at the centre of ''[[Asterix and the Chieftain's Shield]]''.
* '''[[Cassivellaunus]]''' — British chieftain who resists the Roman invasion.&lt;ref&gt;Asterix in Britain, p. 3&lt;/ref&gt; Appears in ''[[Asterix in Britain]]''. After Asterix makes a fake magic potion which gives the village the [[morale]] to beat the Romans, Cassivellaunus says they will make the fake potion their national drink; it is later revealed to be tea.

===Villagers===
* '''Monosyllabix''' and '''Polysyllabix''' (''Petitélégrafix'') — Villagers that appear together, first in ''[[Obelix and Co.]]'', where they appear on the cover. They also appear in ''[[Asterix in Belgium]]'' and ''[[Asterix and the Secret Weapon]]''.
* '''Obese lady''' — another of [[#Impedimenta|Impedimenta]]'s inner circle of village wives, however unlike the others her husband and name are unknown.
* '''Soporifix''' (''Plantaquatix'') — father of Panacea who is mentioned in ''[[Asterix the Legionary]]'', but not seen until ''[[Asterix and the Actress]]''.
*'''''Other villagers''''' mentioned by name (and ''presumed'' to be recurring part of crowd scenes):
**'''Operatix''' (''Boulimix''), '''Acoustix''' (''Aventurepix''), '''Harmonix''' (''Allegorix''), '''Polyfonix''' (''Porquepix'') and '''Polytechnix''' (''Elevedelix'') in ''[[Asterix and the Normans]]''
**'''Pacifix''' (''Linguistix''), '''Atlantix''' (''Arrierboutix''), '''Baltix''' (''Harenbaltix''), '''Adriatix''' (''Choucroutgarnix'') and '''Analgesix''' (''Analgésix'') in ''[[Obelix and Co.]]''
**'''Bucolix''' (''Deboitemendumenix'') and '''Photogenix''' (''Bellodalix'') in ''[[Asterix and Son]]'', and briefly in ''Obelix and Co.''&lt;ref&gt;Obelix and Co, p. 8&lt;/ref&gt;
**'''Tenansix''' (''Cétyounix'') in ''[[Asterix the Gaul]]''
**'''[[Pick 'n' mix|Picanmix]]''' (''Keskonrix''), a youngster in ''[[Asterix the Gladiator]]''. Also appears in Asterix and Cleopatra&lt;ref&gt;Asterix and Cleopatra p. 48&lt;/ref&gt;
**'''Scarlatina''' (''Galantine'') in &quot;[[Asterix and the Class Act#For Gaul Lang Syne|For Gaul Lang Syne]]&quot;
*'''Chanticleerix''' (''Chanteclairix'') — the village's [[rooster]]. Has a crush on Vitalstatistix's helmet.

===Gauls===
* '''Postaldistrix''' (''Pneumatix'') — Postman. His first appearance is in ''[[Asterix and the Normans]]'', when he gives a letter to Vitalstatistix, also in ''[[Asterix the Legionary]]'' when he brings Tragicomix's letter to Panacea (see below). He also appears in the &quot;[[Asterix and the Class Act#Notes|Obelix: As Simple as ABC]]&quot; short story, later included in ''[[Asterix and Obelix's Birthday: The Golden Book]]''.
* '''Panacea''' (''Falbala'') — A beautiful young lady who is the daughter of [[#Villagers|Soporifix]]. She went to school, and now lives, in [[Condate (disambiguation)|Condatum]]. Obelix has a crush on her. First appears in ''[[Asterix the Legionary]]''; also &quot;[[Asterix and the Class Act#For Gaul Lang Syne|For Gaul Lang Syne]]&quot;, ''[[Asterix and Obelix All at Sea]]'' — although this is only a brief appearance — ''[[Asterix and the Actress]]'' (although the majority of her appearances are that of an impersonator). She sends Obelix a letter and appears in [[Asterix and Obelix's Birthday: The Golden Book]]. Along with Tragicomix, she appears in the animated film [[Asterix Versus Caesar]]. The same couple appear on the live-action film [[Asterix and Obelix vs Caesar]], played by [[Laetitia Casta]] and [[Hardy Krüger Jr.]]
* '''Tragicomix''' — Tall, handsome and muscular boyfriend — later husband — of Panacea. He runs a livery stable in Condatum. Appears in ''[[Asterix the Legionary]]'' and ''[[Asterix and the Actress]]''. He has a golden-white body and blonde hair and often appears bare-chested.
* '''Justforkix''' (''Goudurix'') — Nephew of [[#Vitalstatistix|Vitalstatistix]]. He is a major character in ''[[Asterix and the Normans]]'' in which he is kidnapped by them. He also appears in the movie adaptation ''[[Asterix and the Vikings]]'' as well as several [[List of Asterix games#Gamebooks|Asterix game books and video games]].
* '''Orthopaedix''' — An innkeeper from Arausio who appears in ''[[Asterix and Caesar's Gift]]''. He and his family move to the village after buying the deeds from Tremensdelirius (who had only been given the deeds by Caesar as a punishment). His wife Angina pressures him into challenging Vitalstatistix for leadership. In the film [[Asterix and the Vikings]] his daughter is Influenza (Zaza for short) &lt;ref&gt;Asterix and Caesar's Gift (p. 32)&lt;/ref&gt; can be seen when the villagers dance.&lt;ref&gt;Asterix and the Vikings (p. 10)&lt;/ref&gt;
*'''Instantmix''' — Gaulish restaurant owner who helps Asterix and Obelix in ''[[Asterix the Gladiator]]''. He later appears in ''[[Asterix in Corsica]]''.
*'''Seniorservix''' — Sea captain from [[Gesoriacum]] who appears in ''[[Asterix and the Banquet]]'' and ''[[Asterix in Corsica]]''.
* '''Homeopathix''' (''Homéopatix'') — Brother of [[#Impedimenta|Impedimenta]] and a successful merchant in Lutetia. He first appears in ''[[Asterix and the Laurel Wreath]]'' and is often mentioned in later albums as a figure she would like her husband to emulate (much to his disgust). He has a wife named Tapioca (''Galantine'').
*'''Prolix''' — A traveling [[quack]] claiming to be able to predict the future, deceiving most of the villagers save Asterix until Getafix returns and proves him a fake; appears in ''[[Asterix and the Soothsayer]]'', the cartoon [[Operation Getafix]] and the live action film [[Asterix and Obelix vs Caesar]].
*'''''Asterix &amp; Obelix's' ' parents''' — They appear in ''[[Asterix and the Actress]]'' and short stories &quot;[[Asterix and the Class Act#Birth of Asterix|Birth of Asterix]]&quot; and &quot;[[How Obelix Fell into the Magic Potion When he was a Little Boy]]&quot;. They are former villagers who now live in Condatum and run a &quot;modernities&quot; shop together.
** '''Astronomix''' — Asterix's father
** '''[[Sarsaparilla]]''' (''Praline'') — Asterix's mother
** '''Obeliscoidix''' (''Obélodalix'') — Obelix's father
** '''[[Vanilla]]''' (''Gelatine'') — Obelix's mother
*'''Whosmoralsarelastix''' — The chief of a neighbouring Gaulish village. He is a mean and greedy man who often does business with the Romans. Appears in ''[[Asterix and the Cauldron]]'' when he tries to trick the Gauls into paying his taxes for him, though by the end he has lost the money he regained.

=== Romans ===
* '''Gracchus Armisurplus''' (''Gracchus Nenjetepus'') — Centurion of Compendium (''Petibonum'') for ''[[Asterix the Gladiator]]'' and ''[[Asterix and the Banquet]]''; however his name is translated differently in each album.
* '''Tremensdelirius''' (''Roméomontaigus'') — An old, drunken Roman legionary veteran; he causes trouble in ''[[Asterix and Caesar's Gift]]'' and in ''[[Asterix and the Actress]]''. He is the first &quot;one-shot&quot; background character to reappear in the series after a decade-long absence.
*'''Caius Fatuous''' — A gladiator trainer who is a major character in ''[[Asterix the Gladiator]]'' and is mentioned in ''[[Asterix and the Banquet]]''
*'''Jailer''' — A fat bald man with a big nose and [[whip]] who wears a leather [[kilt]] and fetish-style cross straps. He appears in ''[[Asterix and the Laurel Wreath]]'', ''[[The Mansions of the Gods]]'' (as a slave driver) and in the movie ''[[The 12 Tasks of Asterix]]''.
*'''Ignoramus''' — Centurion sent to relieve Scrofulus' garrison in Obelix and Co. He also appears in Asterix in Corsica but looks slightly different.
*'''Crismus Bonus''' — A [[centurion]] who appears in [[Asterix the Gaul]] and [[Asterix and Obelix vs Caesar]].  In the animated version of ''Asterix the Gaul'', he is named '''Phonus Balonus'''
*'''Magnumopus''' — Appeared in [[Asterix and the Roman Agent]] as a Roman legionary. He is very big and strong and misunderstands the meaning of psychological warfare; he does not use a pilum or a sword, but a club instead. His small head and helmet make the villagers think a small Roman attacked a villager.
*'''Infirmofpurpus''' — Appeared in [[Asterix and the big fight]] and the film [[Operation Getafix]] as a Roman legionary. He is leading a Roman patrol when he is hit by a flying cauldron.
*'''Obsequilis''' — Appears in [[Asterix in Spain]], and speaks with a [[lisp]] after being punched by the commander-in-chief who has stolen magic potion from Asterix.
*'''Tortuous Convolvulus''' (''Lucius Détritus'') — Roman agent sent to stir up dissensions among the Gauls, and succeeds in making the Gauls (and accidentally some of the Romans) think the Romans have the magic potion. Appears in ''[[Asterix and the Roman Agent]]'' and the live action film [[Asterix and Obelix vs Caesar]].
*Centurions '''Dubious Status''' and '''Nefarious Purpus''' command the unit of Roman infantry which Asterix and Obelix join in [[Asterix the Legionary]].
*'''Vitriolix''' is Caesar's spy in [[Asterix the Legionary]].

=== Others ===
* '''Anticlimax''' (''Jolitorax'') — Asterix's first cousin, once removed. He lives in a British village holding out against the Romans in ''[[Asterix in Britain]]'' (he appears on the cover). He also appears in ''[[Asterix in Corsica]]'' and has a nephew who is an escaped galley slave in ''[[Asterix and Obelix All at Sea]]''.
* '''[[My kingdom for a horse|Mykingdomforanos]]''', '''McAnix''' and '''O'veroptimistix''' — British chieftains representing England, Scotland and Ireland respectively who appear in ''[[Asterix in Britain]]'' and ''[[Asterix in Corsica]].''
*'''Petitsuix''' — Swiss innkeeper who appears in Asterix in Switzerland and Asterix in Corsica. His name is a pun on [[Petit suisse (cheese)|petit suisse]], a French cheese.
* '''Pepe''' (''Pépé'') — Young spoiled son of the chief of an Iberian village holding out against the Romans; he appears on the cover of ''[[Asterix in Spain]]'' in which he is taken hostage by Caesar, but rescued and returned by Asterix and Obelix. He makes life difficult for the Gauls as well as for the Romans, though even Obelix is upset when they finally part. He is one of the few people who likes Cacofonix's music, and also has a soft spot for Dogmatix. He visits the village again in ''[[Asterix in Corsica]]''.
* '''Ekonomikrisis''' (''Epidemaïs'') — a Phoenician merchant who appears in ''[[Asterix the Gladiator]]'' and also ''[[Asterix and the Black Gold]]'', helping Asterix and Obelix travel to and from Rome and Tyre respectively. He also appeared in the animated adaptation of ''Asterix In Britain'', but not by name.
* '''Edifis''' (''Numérobis'') — an Egyptian architect and old friend of Getafix.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.asterix.co.nz/take_a_look/cleopatra/index.html |title=Asterix and Cleopatra |publisher=Asterix NZ |date=  |accessdate=2010-12-31 }}{{Dead link |date=June 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; His personality is extended in the movie ''[[Asterix &amp; Obelix: Mission Cleopatra]]'' by making him not only younger but much more eccentric. This version appears with a small role in the movie ''[[Asterix at the Olympic Games (film)|Asterix at the Olympic Games]]''.
*'''Olaf Timandahaf''' (''Olaf Grossebraf'') — [[Viking]] chieftain who kidnaps Justforkix in ''[[Asterix and the Normans]]''. In the film adaption, he has a wife named [[Ikea]] and a daughter named [[Abba]] who ends up as Justforkix's wife.

== Caricatures ==
*'''[[Annie Cordy]]''' — Belgian actress who is caricatured as chief Beefix's wife in ''[[Asterix in Belgium]]''.
*'''[[Arnold Schwarzenegger]]''' — was the inspiration for the super-clones in ''[[Asterix and the Falling Sky]]''.
*'''[[Benito Mussolini]]''' — As the centurion Nebulus Nimbus in ''[[Asterix and the Big Fight]]''. Like the real Mussolini he's bald, fat and shouts all the time.&lt;ref&gt;Asterix and the big fight&lt;/ref&gt;
*'''[[Boadicea]]''' — Appears in ''[[Asterix in Britain]]'' as a housewife. She confronts Asterix, Obelix and Anticlimax after they mistakenly break down her door.
*'''Cassius Ceramix''' (''Aplusbegalix'') — Gaulish chief collaborating with the Romans who challenges Vitalstatistix for leadership. [[ceramics|Ceramix]] is a pun on [[Muhammed Ali]]'s birth name, Cassius Clay, and like him is a skilled boxer. Another famous athlete, the [[cyclist]] [[Eddy Merckx]], appears as a messenger in ''[[Asterix in Belgium]]''.
*'''[[Charles Laughton]]''' — as the villainous [[prefect]] Surplus Dairiprodus.
*'''[[Charlton Heston]]''' (as [[Ben-Hur (1959 film)|Ben Hur]]) can be seen arguing with another driver in ''[[Asterix and the Golden Sickle]]''.
* '''Cartoon characters''' — Hoodunnit from ''[[Asterix and the Magic Carpet]]'' is the cousin of [[Iznogoud]], another cartoon character created by Goscinny.&lt;ref&gt;Asterix and the magic carpet, p. 43&lt;/ref&gt; In [[Asterix and the Falling Sky]] the alien '''Toon''' resembles a purple [[Mickey Mouse]]. His home planet (Tadsilweny) is an anagram of [[Walt Disney]].
*'''[[Goscinny]] and [[Uderzo]]''' have cameo appearances in many books including ''[[Asterix in Britain]]'' and ''[[Obelix and Co.]]''&lt;ref&gt;Obelix and Co p. 6&lt;/ref&gt;
*'''[[Guy Lux]]''' — As a [[gameshow]] host in the Mansions of the Gods.
*'''[[Jacques Chirac]]''' — The economist who buys Obelix's menhirs in ''[[Obelix and Co.]]''.
*'''[[Jean Richard]]''' — As a [[lion tamer]] in Asterix and the Laurel Wreath
*'''[[Kirk Douglas]]''' — in &quot;[[Asterix and Obelix All at Sea]]&quot; as Spartakis the Greek, leader of a multi-national, multi-cultural band of mutinous slaves who've escaped after commandeering Caesar's personal galley.
*'''[[Laurence Olivier]] and [[Alec Guinness]]''' — As actors in Asterix and the Cauldron.
*'''[[Lino Ventura]]''' — Appears as the centurion in ''[[Asterix and the Roman Agent]]''.
*'''[[Louis de Funès]]'''
*'''Napoleon''' — as the Corsican chief Boneywasawarriorwayayix (''Ocatarinetabellatchitchix'' in the original French). Alternatively, this may also be a caricature of [[Ricardo Montalban]]. Also appears in Asterix and the Big Fight (differently) as one of Psychoanalytix's patients.
*'''[[Otto von Bismarck]]''' — As the [[Goth]] chieftain Metric.
*'''[[Pierre Tchernia]]''' — Pierre Tchernia has made various cameos throughout the books, always as a Roman Legionary. He first appears in ''[[Asterix the Legionary]]'' as one of the generals discussing tactics with Caesar, then ''[[Asterix in Corsica]]'' as Centurion Hippopotamus, the commanding officer of Totorum. Later, he appears in ''[[Obelix &amp; Co.]]'' as a drunk legionary who has to be carried out of the forfeited camp by caricatures of Goscinny and Uderzo. He appears again as a legionary in ''[[Asterix and Caesar's Gift]]'' and ''[[Asterix in Belgium]]''.
*'''Pontius Pilate''' — Roman governor of [[Iudaea Province|Judaea]] (called Pontius Pi'''r'''ate in the comics) who appears in ''[[Asterix and the Black Gold]]''. In reality the historical [[Pontius Pilate]] wasn't even born at the time Asterix is set.
*'''[[Raimu]]''' — As a [[bartender]] in Asterix and the Banquet.
*'''[[Sean Connery]]''' — As the spy Doubleosix (an obvious parody of [[James Bond]]) in ''[[Asterix and the Black Gold]]''.
*'''[[Sigmund Freud]]''' — As Psychoanalytix the druid in ''[[Asterix and the Big Fight]]''. He runs a mental health clinic with patients including a shy [[barbarian]], a man who thinks he's a [[wild boar]] and [[Napoleon Bonaparte]].
*'''[[Stan Laurel]] and [[Oliver Hardy]]''' — As legionaries in [[Obelix and Co.]]&lt;ref&gt;Obelix and Co, p. 27&lt;/ref&gt;
*'''Sylvie Uderzo''' — As Orthopaedix's young daughter Influenza in Asterix and Caesar's Gift.
*'''[[Thomson and Thompson]]''' — Identical twin detectives from ''[[The Adventures of Tintin]]''. They appear in ''[[Asterix in Belgium]]''.
*'''[[Winston Churchill]]''' (with a red wig and moustache) appears in Asterix in Britain as the chieftain Mykingdomforanos.
*'''[[Valéry Giscard d'Estaing]]''' — as a Roman tax collector.
*'''Various pop stars''' — [[The Beatles]] appear in ''[[Asterix in Britain]]'' while the [[Rolling Stones|Rolling Menhirs]] and [[Elvis Presley|Elvis Preslix]] are mentioned in ''[[Asterix and the Normans]]''. In addition, Cacofonix's hairstyle is based on Elvis's.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.asterix.co.nz/characters/gauls/cacofonix.htm |title=New Zealand Asterix fans website |publisher=Asterix NZ |date= |accessdate=2010-12-31}}{{Dead link|date=June 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== References ==
{{reflist}}

== External links ==
* [http://www.asterix.co.nz/characters.htm Asterix NZ: Asterix Characters] — Further Information on the main recurring characters in Asterix {{Dead link|date=June 2011}}
* [http://asterix.wikia.com The Asterix Projest] — Asterix page on [[Wikia]].

{{Asterix|Characters in Asterix, Recurring|type=chars}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Asterix}}
[[Category:Comics characters]]
[[Category:Ancient Gauls|Asterix]]
[[Category:Asterix| ]]
[[Category:Lists of comics characters]]

[[de:Figuren aus Asterix]]
[[el:Αστερίξ (κύριοι χαρακτήρες)]]
[[es:Anexo:Personajes de Astérix]]
[[fr:Liste des personnages d'Astérix]]
[[nl:Lijst van personages in de verhalen van Asterix]]
[[fi:Luettelo Asterix seikkailee -sarjakuvien hahmoista]]
[[sv:Figurer i Asterix]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
