<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><redirects><r from="Pedro Fernandes" to="Pedro Fernandes de Queirós" /></redirects><pages><page pageid="318031" ns="0" title="Pedro Fernandes de Queirós"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{redirect|Queirós|other people|Queiroz (surname)}}
[[Image:Pedro Fernández de Quirós.JPG|thumb|Pedro Fernandes de Queirós]]
'''Pedro Fernandes de Queirós''' ({{lang-es|'''Pedro Fernández de Quirós'''}}), (1565–1614) was a [[Portugal|Portuguese]] navigator best known for his involvement with Spanish voyages of discovery in the [[Pacific Ocean]], in particular the 1595-1596 voyage of [[Alvaro de Mendaña de Neira]], and for leading a 1605-1606 expedition which crossed the Pacific in search of [[Terra Australis]].

==Early life==
Queirós was born in [[Évora]], [[Portugal]] in 1565. As a young man he entered [[Spain|Spanish]] service and became an experienced seaman and navigator. In April 1595 he joined [[Álvaro de Mendaña de Neira]] on his voyage to colonise the [[Solomon Islands]], serving as pilot. After Mendaña’s death in October 1595 he is credited with taking command and saving the only remaining ship of the expedition, arriving in the [[Philippines]] in February 1596.&lt;ref name=adb&gt;[http://www.adb.online.anu.edu.au/biogs/A020311b.htm Australian Dictionary of Biography online]&lt;/ref&gt;

==The Search for Terra Australis==
In 1598 Queirós returned to Spain and petitioned King [[Philip III of Spain|Philip III]] to support another voyage into the [[Pacific]]. A devout Catholic, Queirós also visited [[Rome]] in 1600, where he obtained the support of the Pope, [[Clement VIII]], for further explorations. He greatly impressed the Spanish Ambassador in [[Rome]], the Duke of Sesa, who described him as a “man of good judgement, experienced in his profession, hard working, quiet and disinterested.” &lt;ref name=&quot;adb&quot; /&gt; While in Rome Queirós also first wrote his ''Treatise on Navigation'' as a letter to the king, further reinforcing his reputation as a navigator.  In March 1603 Queirós was finally authorized to return to [[Peru]] to establish another expedition, with the intention of finding [[Terra Australis]], the mythical &quot;great south land,&quot; and claiming it for [[Spain]] and the Church. Queirós's party of 160 men on three ships, ''San Pedro y San Pablo'' (150 tons),  ''San Pedro''  (120 tons) and the tender (or launch) ''Los Tres Reyes'' left [[Callao]] on 21 December 1605.&lt;ref&gt;Estensen, M. (2006) ''Terra Australia Incognita; The Spanish Quest for the Great South Land'' p.111-113. Allen &amp; Unwin, Australia ISBN 978 1741750546&lt;/ref&gt; 

In January 1606 the expedition discovered [[Henderson Island (Pitcairn Islands)|Henderson Island]] and [[Ducie Island]].
In May 1606 the expedition reached the islands later called the [[New Hebrides]] and now the independent nation of [[Vanuatu]]. Queirós landed on a large island which he took to be part of the southern continent, and named it ''La Austrialia &lt;ref&gt;No, not a typo! See accounts of the voyage cited, eg Estensen, M (2006)&lt;/ref&gt; del Espiritu Santo'' (The Austrian Land of the Holy Spirit), for King [[Philip III of Spain|Philip III]], who was of Austrian descent. The island is still called [[Espiritu Santo]]. Here he stated his intention to establish a colony, to be called Nova Jerusalem.

Queirós's religious fervour found expression with the founding of a new Order of Chivalry, the Knights of the Holy Ghost. The Order’s purpose was to protect the new colony.  However, within weeks the idea of a colony was abandoned due to the hostility of the Ni-Vanuatu and to disagreements among the crew. 

After six weeks Queirós's ships put to sea to explore the coastline. On the night of June 11, 1606 Queirós in the ''San Pedro y San Pablo'' became separated from the other ships in bad weather and was unable (or so he later said) to return to safe anchorage at [[Espiritu Santo]]. He then sailed to [[Acapulco]] in [[Mexico]], where he arrived in November 1606. In the account of Diego de Prado y Tovar,  which is highly critical of Queirós, mutiny and poor leadership is given as the reason for Queirós's disappearance.&lt;ref name=prado&gt;[http://www.sl.nsw.gov.au/discover_collections/history_nation/voyages/voya_spanishQuest.html  Prado's Account can be read online]&lt;/ref&gt;  

Two weeks later, his second-in-command, [[Luis Váez de Torres]], after searching in vain for Queirós and assuming his ship was wrecked, left [[Espiritu Santo]]. Torres successfully reached [[Manila]], the center of the [[Spanish East Indies]] in May 1607, charting the southern coastline of [[New Guinea]] on the way and in doing so sailing through the strait that now bears his name.

==Queirós in later life==
Pedro de Queirós returned to Madrid in 1607. Regarded as a crank, he spent the next seven years writing numerous accounts of his voyage and begging King [[Philip III of Spain|Philip III]] for money for a new voyage. He was finally despatched to [[Peru]] with letters of support, but the king had no real intention of funding another expedition. Queirós died on the way, in [[Panama]], in 1614. He had married Dona Ana Chacon of [[Madrid]] in 1589, who bore him one son and one daughter.

==Accounts of Queirós's Voyage==
There are a number of documents describing the Queirós – Torres voyages still in existence. Most significant are
* Queiros's many subsequent Memorials to the King [[Philip III of Spain|Philip III]] regarding the voyage,&lt;ref name=loc&gt;[http://memory.loc.gov/service/rbc/rbdk/d0404/02951422.jpg  A copy at the Library of Congress can be read online]&lt;/ref&gt;
* Torres brief account to the king (1607),&lt;ref&gt;See Chapter XII of Collingridge,G.(1895) ''The First Discovery of Australia'', for part of Torres account at [http://www.gutenberg.org/files/17022/17022-h/17022-h.htm#maps-col-05] A longer translation is included in his 1895 book ''The Discovery of Australia'', Golden Press reprint, 1983. ISBN 085558 9566&lt;/ref&gt;
*  Prado’s narrative ''Relacion Sumaria''&lt;ref name=&quot;prado&quot; /&gt; (first written in 1608) and 4 charts of New Guinea &lt;ref&gt;For colour photos of the charts, see Hilder, B.(1980) ''The Voyage of Torres'' University of Queensland Press, St. Lucia, ISBN 07022 1275x. Also see Collingridge’s  The ''First Discovery of Australia'', 1895, which includes Collingridge’s own copies of three of the charts [http://www.gutenberg.org/files/17022/17022-h/17022-h.htm#ch-12] The charts are the coloured maps 5,6 and 9.(Map 9 is incorrectly titled “Moresby's Map of the Islands at the South-east end of New Guinea” . It is in fact based on Prado’s Mappa III  - showing Orangerie Bay, New Guinea.)&lt;/ref&gt;
* Juan Luis Arias de Loyola’s memorial to King [[Philip IV of Spain|Philip IV]]  (written about 1630 and based on discussions between Queirós and Loyola ) &lt;ref&gt;Hilder, B (1980) p.175-176&lt;/ref&gt;

Most documents of [[Luis Váez de Torres]]'s discoveries were not published but filed away in Spanish archives, including Prado’s lengthy account and accompanying charts.  

1617 may be the date of the first English translation of one of Queirós's memorials, as ''Terra Australis Incognita'', or ''A New Southerne Discoverie''.&lt;ref&gt;The [[State Library of Victoria|La Trobe Library of Victoria]] lists a copy of this as one of its rare books [http://calisto.slv.vic.gov.au/latrobejournal/issue/latrobe-47-48/t1-g-t7.html]&lt;/ref&gt;
A short account of Queirós's voyage and discoveries was published in English by Samuel Purchas in 1625 in ''Haklvytvs posthumus'', or, ''Pvrchas his Pilg''rimes, vol. iv, p.&amp;nbsp;1422-1432. This account also appears to be based on a letter by Queirós to the King in 1610, the eighth on the matter.&lt;ref name=&quot;loc&quot; /&gt;

Some time between 1762 and 1765, written accounts of the Torres expedition were seen by British Admiralty Hydrographer [[Alexander Dalrymple]]. Dalrymple provided a sketch map which included the Queirós -Torres voyages to [[Joseph Banks]] who undoubtedly passed this information to [[James Cook]].&lt;ref&gt;Hilder, B (1980) p.31&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Estensen, M.(2006)p.222&lt;/ref&gt;

==Theory that Queirós discovered Australia==
In the 19th century some Australian Catholics, living under a Protestant ascendancy, claimed that Queirós had in fact discovered Australia, in advance of the Protestants [[Willem Janszoon]], [[Abel Tasman]] and [[James Cook]]. The Archbishop of [[Sydney]] from 1884 to 1911, [[Patrick Francis Moran]], asserted this to be a fact, and it was taught in Catholic schools for many years.&lt;ref&gt;Moran, cited in Richardson, W.A.R. (2006) ''Was Australia charted before 1606?'' p. 20. National Library of Australia ISBN 0642 276420&lt;/ref&gt; He claimed that the real site of Queirós's New Jerusalem was near [[Gladstone, Queensland|Gladstone]] in [[Queensland]].&lt;ref&gt;Cardinal Moran's ''Discovery of Australia by de Queirós in the Year 1606'' [http://gutenberg.net.au/ebooks06/0600641h.html]&lt;/ref&gt;

==Queirós in modern literature==
Building on this tradition, the Australian  poet [[James McAuley]] (1917–76) wrote an epic called ''Captain Quiros'' (1964), in which he depicted Queirós as a martyr for the cause of Catholic Christian civilisation (although he did not repeat the claim that Queirós had discovered Australia). The heavily political overtones of the poem caused it to be coldly received at a time when much politics in Australia was still coloured by Catholic-Protestant sectarianism. 

&quot;Bitter indeed the chalice that he drank&lt;br&gt;
For no man's pride accepts to cheap a rate&lt;br&gt;
As not to call on Heaven to vindicate&lt;br&gt;
His worth together with the cause he served.&quot;

(James McAuley, ''Captain Quiros'')

The Australian writer John Toohey published a novel, ''Quiros'', in 2002.&lt;ref&gt;''Quiros'', Toohey, J. (2002) Duffy &amp; Snellgrove; Potts Point, N.S.W, ISBN 1876631244&lt;/ref&gt;

==References==
{{reflist}}

==External links==
*[http://www.sl.nsw.gov.au/discover_collections/history_nation/voyages/voya_spanishQuest.html Diego de Prado y Tovar's account of the Quirós and Torres voyage, with English translation, at the State Library of New South Wales]
*[http://gutenberg.net.au/ebooks06/0600641h.html ''Discovery of Australia by de Quirós in the Year 1606'' by Patrick F. Cardinal Moran, Archbishop of Sydney]
*[http://www.win.tue.nl/~engels/discovery/index.html  Discoverer’s Website project]
*[http://memory.loc.gov/cgi-bin/ampage?collId=rbdk&amp;fileName=d0404//rbdkd0404.db&amp;recNum=304&amp;itemLink=r%3Fintldl%2Frbdkbib%3A@field%28NUMBER%2B@od1%28rbdk%2Bd0404%29%29&amp;linkText=0 ''Hakluytus Posthumus - Purchas his Pilgrimes Vol 4'' by Samuel Purchas, Page 1432]
*[http://gutenberg.net.au/ebooks05/0501051h.html ''The First Discovery of Australia and New Guinea'' by George Collingridge, Chapter XI]

{{Persondata &lt;!-- Metadata: see [[Wikipedia:Persondata]]. --&gt;
| NAME              = Fernandes De Queiros, Pedro
| ALTERNATIVE NAMES =
| SHORT DESCRIPTION =
| DATE OF BIRTH     = 1565
| PLACE OF BIRTH    =
| DATE OF DEATH     = 1614
| PLACE OF DEATH    =
}}
{{DEFAULTSORT:Queiros, Pedro Fernandes de}}
[[Category:Explorers of the Pacific]]
[[Category:Portuguese explorers]]
[[Category:17th-century explorers]]
[[Category:1565 births]]
[[Category:1614 deaths]]
[[Category:16th-century Portuguese people]]
[[Category:16th-century Spanish people]]
[[Category:17th-century Portuguese people]]
[[Category:17th-century Spanish people]]
[[Category:Spanish conquistadors]]
[[Category:Spanish East Indies]]

[[bg:Педро Фернандес де Кирос]]
[[ca:Pedro Fernández de Quirós]]
[[cs:Pedro Fernandes de Queirós]]
[[de:Pedro Fernández de Quirós]]
[[es:Pedro Fernández de Quirós]]
[[fr:Pedro Fernandes de Queirós]]
[[gl:Pedro Fernandes de Queirós]]
[[hr:Pedro Fernández de Quirós]]
[[it:Pedro Fernandes de Queirós]]
[[nl:Pedro Fernandes de Queirós]]
[[ja:ペドロ・フェルナンデス・デ・キロス]]
[[no:Pedro Fernandes de Queirós]]
[[pl:Pedro Fernández de Quirós]]
[[pt:Pedro Fernandes de Queirós]]
[[ru:Кирос, Педро Фернандес]]
[[sv:Pedro Fernández de Quirós]]
[[uk:Педро Фернандес де Кірос]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
