<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><redirects><r from="F-Secure Internet Security 2008" to="F-Secure" /></redirects><pages><page pageid="1107998" ns="0" title="F-Secure"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Infobox company
| company_name     = F-Secure Corporation
| company_logo     = [[Image:F-Secure-logo.PNG|250px|F-Secure]]
| company_slogan   = Protecting the irreplaceable
| company_type     = [[Public company|Public]] ({{OMX|HEX24270|FSC1V}})
| foundation       = 1988
| founder          = Petri Allas and Risto Siilasmaa
| location         = [[Helsinki]], [[Finland]]
| key_people       = [[Risto Siilasmaa]], founder &amp; [[chairman]]&lt;br /&gt; Kimmo Alkio, [[Chief executive officer|CEO]]&lt;br /&gt; [[Mikko Hyppönen]], Chief Research Officer
| industry         = [[Computer industry|Computer]]
| products         = F-Secure Internet Security&lt;br /&gt;F-Secure Anti-Virus&lt;br /&gt;F-Secure Anti-Virus for Mac&lt;br /&gt;F-Secure Online Backup&lt;br /&gt;F-Secure Mobile Security&lt;br /&gt;F-Secure Free Anti-Theft for Mobile&lt;br /&gt;F-Secure Mobile Security for Business&lt;br /&gt;F-Secure Protection Service for Business&lt;br /&gt;F-Secure Business Suite&lt;br /&gt;F-Secure Anti-Virus for Servers&lt;br /&gt;F-Secure Policy Manager&lt;br /&gt;F-Secure Protection Service for Email&lt;br /&gt;F-Secure Client Security&lt;br /&gt;F-Secure Protection for consumers&lt;br /&gt;F-Secure Protection for business&lt;br /&gt;F-Secure Protection for mobile&lt;br /&gt;F-Secure Content Enabler
| revenue          =
| operating_income =
| net_income       =
| num_employees    =
| parent           =
| subsid           =
| owner            =
| homepage         = [http://www.f-secure.com/ www.f-secure.com]
| footnotes        =
}}
&lt;!-- Deleted image removed: [[Image:FSIS08.jpg|thumb|right|300px|The user interface of F-Secure Internet Security 2009.|{{pufc|1=FSIS08.jpg|log=2009 April 10}}]] --&gt;

'''F-Secure Corporation''' (formerly '''Data Fellows''') is an [[anti-virus software|anti-virus]] and [[computer security]] software company based in [[Helsinki]], [[Finland]]. The company has 18 country offices and a presence in more than 100 countries, with Security Lab operations in Helsinki, Finland and in Kuala Lumpur, Malaysia. Through more 200 operator partners globally, millions of broadband customer use F-Secure services. F-Secure Corp. is publicly traded on the [[Helsinki Stock Exchange]] under the symbol FSC1V.

F-Secure claims that it was the first antivirus vendor to establish a presence on the World Wide Web. The F-Secure [http://www.f-secure.com/weblog/ Labs weblog] tracks global internet and mobile security threats.

F-Secure has been listed twice, 2003 and 2006, on &quot;Finland's best places to work&quot; list published by Great Place to Work® Institute, Inc.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.greatplacetowork.fi/&lt;/ref&gt; Technology Academy of Finland named Pirkka Palomäki, F-Secure's Chief Technology Officer, as CTO of the Year 2011.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.technologyacademy.fi/cto-of-the-year-award.html&lt;/ref&gt;

==History==

F-Secure was first established under the name Data Fellows by [[Petri Allas]] and [[Risto Siilasmaa]] in 1988. Data Fellows trained computer users and built customized databases. Three years later, the company launched its first major [[software]] project and developed the first heuristic scanner for [[antivirus]] products. F-Secure’ first antivirus product for Windows PCs was launched in 1994. Data Fellows became F-Secure in 1999.
F-Secure was the first company that developed an Anti-[[rootkit]] technology called BlackLight in 2005 {{citation needed|date=March 2010}}.

In July 2009, F-Secure purchased [[Steek_(brand)|Steek]], a French company specialized in [[online storage]] and [[backup]] services for consumers.&lt;ref&gt;http://eu.techcrunch.com/2009/07/15/f-secure-pays-e275-million-for-french-storage-startup-steek/&lt;/ref&gt;

F-Secure received the product of the year award in 2010 from AV-Comparatives, as it got the least false alarms (2). This put F-Secure ahead of Panda Software (98) and other anti-virus companies.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.av-comparatives.org/en/comparativesreviews/false-alarm-tests&lt;/ref&gt;

==Products==

The current line of home-user products from F-Secure includes F-Secure Internet Security, F-Secure Anti-Virus, F-Secure Anti-Virus for Mac, F-Secure Mobile Security, F-Secure Online Backup and F-Secure Free Anti-theft for Mobile. 

F-Secure’s business products include F-Secure Protection Service, F-Secure Business Suite, F-Secure Client Security, F-Secure Anti-Virus for Servers, F-Secure Protection Service for Email, F-Secure Policy Manager, F-Secure Mobile Security for Business, F-Secure Messaging Security Gateway and F-Secure for Exchange.

White-labeled versions of F-Secure’s security software are also available through operators around the world via monthly or yearly subscription plans. F-Secure is the global leader in providing software as a service through operators with over 200 operator partners worldwide including AT&amp;T, Vodafone and Telefonica.

== Technology==

F-Secure is having OEM agreements with several security vendors to integrate detection technology engines in its own offerings.

DeepGuard, now in its 4.0 incarnation, is an F-Secure in-house developed HIPS or advanced system monitoring technology, which detects new or unknown malware intrusions based on unusual, suspicious changes in the Windows system and automatically blocks processes caught in the act. DeepGuard is resource intensive and requires fairly strong hardware to work without affecting customer experience (1GHz+ CPU and 512MB RAM or better recommended).{{Citation needed|date=June 2011}}

In July 2009 F-Secure bought French company Steek SA which provides software for online storage and data management solutions to fixed line and mobile operators. Steek SA is being fully integrated into F-Secure as the Storage and Digital Content business unit.

==Academia==

In co-operation with [[Aalto University School of Science and Technology]], F-Secure runs a one semester course for future virus analysts, with some material available on-line. [http://www.tml.tkk.fi/Opinnot/T-110.6220/]

==Policy on detecting government spying programs==

After the media coverage of [[Magic Lantern (software)]] and claims by some AV vendors to purposefully leave a backdoor for it in their products, F-Secure announced their policy on detecting these spying programs:

&quot;F-Secure Corporation would like to make known that we will not leave such backdoors to our F-Secure Anti-Virus products, regardless of the source of such tools. We have to draw a line with every sample we get regarding whether to detect it or not. This decision-making is influenced only by technical factors, and nothing else, but within the applicable laws and regulations, in our case meaning EU laws.

We will also be adding detection of any program we see that might be used for terrorist activity or to benefit organized crime. We would like to state this for the record, as we have received queries regarding whether we would have the guts to detect something obviously made by a known violent mafia or terrorist organization. Yes we would.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=F-Secure Corporation's policy on detecting spying programs developed by various governments|url=http://www.f-secure.com/virus-info/bdtp.shtml|publisher=F-Secure|accessdate=25 June 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; 

==See also==
*[[List of antivirus software]]
*[[ Mikko Hyppönen]]

==References==
{{Reflist}}

==External links==
*[http://www.f-secure.com/ Official website]
*[http://www.f-secure.com/en_EMEA-Corp/ Corporate website]
*[http://www.f-secure.com/en_EMEA-Labs/index.html Labs website]
*[https://analysis.f-secure.com/ Sample Analysis System]
*[http://www.f-secure.com/weblog Labs weblog]
*[http://safeandsavvy.f-secure.com/ Safe and Savvy weblog]
*[http://community.f-secure.com/t5/Welcome/ct-p/EN F-Secure Community]

[[Category:Antivirus software]]
[[Category:Software companies established in 1988]]
[[Category:Software companies of Finland]]
[[Category:Companies based in Helsinki]]
[[Category:Companies listed on the Helsinki Stock Exchange]]
[[Category:Computer security software companies]]

[[de:F-Secure]]
[[et:F-Secure]]
[[fa:اف‌سکیور]]
[[fr:F-Secure]]
[[it:F-Secure]]
[[he:F-Secure]]
[[ja:F-Secure インターネットセキュリティ]]
[[no:F-Secure]]
[[pl:F-Secure]]
[[pt:F-Secure]]
[[ro:F-Secure]]
[[fi:F-Secure]]
[[sv:F-Secure]]
[[zh:F-Secure]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
