<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="17692779" ns="0" title="Userful"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Infobox Company
|company_name = Userful Corporation
|company_type = [[Privately held company|Private]]
|foundation = 1999
|location_city =  [[Calgary, Alberta]]
|location_country = Canada
|key_people =  Timothy Griffin (President and CEO) &lt;/BR&gt; Alan McNaughton (VP and General Manager) &lt;/BR&gt; Beverley Gallagher (VP Strategic Partnerships) &lt;/BR&gt; Daniel Griffin (VP Multiplied Computing)
|num_employees = Approximately 40
|homepage = [http://userful.com www.userful.com]}}

'''Userful''' is a [[desktop virtualization]] company that develops software to create Linux-based remotely managed [[virtual desktops]] that enable up to 10 users to simultaneously share one computer. The company’s approach is similar to [[thin client]]s but promises better streaming video and audio performance at lower costs.&lt;ref name=&quot;Macworld&quot;&gt;{{cite news | author=Eric Lai | url=http://www.macworld.co.uk/education/news/index.cfm?newsid=25059&amp;pagtype=allchandate | title=Linux firm to supply 357,000 Brazilian schools desktops | publisher=Macworld.com | date=2009-02-19 | accessdate=2009-03-10 }}&lt;/ref&gt;
Userful, based in [[Calgary, Alberta]] is a privately held for-profit company with resellers.&lt;ref name=&quot;CIOL&quot;&gt;{{cite news | author=DQChannels | url=http://www.ciol.com/Channel-News/News-Reports/Userful-plans-Indian-entry/1908109791/0/ | title=Userful plans Indian entry | publisher=CIOL.com | date=2008-09-01 | accessdate=2009-03-10 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

In February 2009, Userful announced what is claimed to be the world's largest desktop virtualization deployment, 356,800 virtual desktops in Brazil.&lt;ref name=&quot;Feb09BrazilPressRelease&quot;&gt;{{cite web | url = http://www.userful.com/company/linux-desktop-virtualization | title= Userful and ThinNetworks today announce that they have been selected to supply 356,800 virtualized desktops to schools in all of Brazil's 5,560 municipalities. | work = Userful.com |accessdate= Feb 17 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==History==

Current President and CEO, Timothy Griffin founded Userful Corporation in 1999. The company commenced work on a kernel-based approach to a multi-station platform computer, but later abandoned the idea due to a problem with multiple video card support. Initially a software development company, issues with the duplication and time consumption involved in setting up users on multiple computers, along with installing multiple programs for each computer, led to development of the one-step, multiseat computing technology that is the core Userful product, Userful Multiplier.&lt;ref name=&quot;TechRev&quot;&gt;{{cite web | url=http://www.techrev.ca/techrev/bins/content_page.asp?cid=10298 | title=Success Stories - Userful - Managed Desktops Done Right | work = Techrev.ca | accessdate=2009-03-10 }}&lt;/ref&gt; Userful's mission is to bring sustainable desktop computing to the world.&lt;ref name=&quot;AVAC&quot;&gt;{{cite web | url=http://www.avacltd.com/case-studies/case-studies-userful | title=AVAC Helps Userful Make Computers Accessible and Sustainable | accessdate=2009-03-10 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

Since the release of Desktop Multiplier in 2002, Userful Corporation has focused primarily on schools, public libraries, military, and oilfields for deployment. Userful is based in Calgary, Alberta, Canada with a second office located in Victoria, BC, Canada.&lt;ref name=&quot;userful&quot;&gt;{{cite web | url = http://www.linux.com/articles/48475 | title= Userful GNU/Linux multi-station software suits general desktop users | work = Linux.com |accessdate= April 23, 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Linux Adoption and Education==

Since 2002, Userful has played an integral role in mass [[Linux adoption]] in schools with over 750,000 seats deployed worldwide in over 30,000 schools.&lt;ref name=&quot;TechVibes&quot;&gt;{{cite news | author=Sarah Blue | url=http://www.techvibes.com/blog/calgarys-userful-way-ahead-of-microsoft-in-the-multiseat-space | title=Calgary’s Userful Way Ahead of Microsoft in the Multiseat Space | publisher=TechVibes.com | date=2010-02-24 | accessdate=2010-09-30 }}&lt;/ref&gt; Key factors for Linux OS adoption in schools are that Linux is free, there is increased security with its usage, and that it supports free open source software. Some examples of governments who have started to switch from using proprietary operating systems to Linux include USA, Germany, Spain, France, Mexico amongst others.&lt;ref name=&quot;50Places&quot;&gt;{{cite web | url=http://www.focus.com/fyi/information-technology/50-places-linux-running-you-might-not-expect/ | title=50 Places Linux is Running That You Might Not Expect | accessdate=2010-10-05 }}&lt;/ref&gt; A Linux-based [[multiseat]] solution, Userful Multiplier is compatible with a wide array of open source and free software &lt;ref name=&quot;EChan&quot;&gt;{{cite news | author=Mark Cox | url=http://www.echannelline.com/usa/story.cfm?item=25455 | title=Userful Upgrades Multi-Seat Linux Desktop Virtualization Solution  | publisher=EChannelLine.com | date=2010-02-18 | accessdate=2010-10-07 }}&lt;/ref&gt; By supporting multiple student stations from one host computer, Userful Multiplier reduces hardware costs, and electricity use, in addition to the software cost savings of Linux and open source software.&lt;ref name=&quot;ITwire&quot;&gt;{{cite news | author=Stephen Withers | url=http://www.itwire.com/business-it-news/open-source/40652-userful-prepackages-linux-and-applications-for-multiseat-educational-use | title=Userful prepackages Linux and applications for multiseat educational use | publisher=ITwire.com | date=2010-07-26 | accessdate=2010-10-07 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Green Computing==

Shared resource computing has environmentally friendly benefits such as reducing electronic waste, lowering energy consumption, and reducing C02 emissions. Userful users saved over 200,000 tonnes of CO2 in 2009 through use of their [[multiseat]] software.&lt;ref name=&quot;GreenPC&quot;&gt;{{cite web | url=http://www.userful.com/green-pcs | title=Userful is the Green Solution: Reduce CO2 Emissions and Electronic Waste | accessdate=2010-10-01 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Products==
===Userful MultiSeat Linux 2011===

Userful MultiSeat Linux 2011 is an Edubuntu OS based software bundle solution for schools that includes Userful MultiSeat shared resource computing software, as well as iTALC classroom computer management software. It is due for commercial release in Q4 2010  It leverages USB multiseat devices to turn a monitor, keyboard and mouse into a complete computer station. It supports HP T100, and MCT MWS 8820 USB multiseat devices. [[Edubuntu]] OS, comes with education applications for subjects including: Astronomy, Chemistry, Languages, Mathematics, and Planning, and more. A sneak preview of the product was released in July 2010,&lt;ref name=&quot;ChanPro&quot;&gt;{{cite news | author=Geoffrey Oldmixon | url=http://www.channelprosmb.com/article/19777/Preview-Release-of-Userful-s-Linux-Multiseat-2010-Suite-Hits-the-Channel/ | title=Preview Release of Userful's Linux Multiseat 2010 Suite Hits the Channel | publisher=channelprosmb.com | date=2010-07-28 | accessdate=2010-10-03 }}&lt;/ref&gt; and a beta version was released in November 2010.&lt;ref name=&quot;Document Management News&quot;&gt;{{cite news | url=http://www.documentmanagementnews.com/the-news/general-news/828-the-linux-alternative-to-microsoft-windows-multipoint-server-2010-goes-into-beta.html | title=The Linux Alternative To Microsoft Windows MultiPoint Server 2010 Goes Into Beta  | publisher=documentmanagementnews.com | date=2010-11-02 | accessdate=2010-11-07 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Userful Multiplier===

Userful Multiplier is a commercial Linux-based [[multiseat configuration]] software package developed by Userful.  It allows multiple independent users to connect to a single host PC at the same time, each with their own monitor, keyboard, mouse, and applications. Depending on the hardware used, up to 10 fully operable, independent computer stations can run from a single computer.  Userful Multiplier leverages off basic dual-head GPU technology and USB inputs to turn a monitor, keyboard and mouse into a complete computer station.&lt;ref name=&quot;Multiplier&quot;&gt;{{cite web | url= http://www.userful.com/products/userful-multiplier | title=Userful Multiplier - Multiseat Linux Desktop Virtualization Software Turns 1 Computer Into 10 | accessdate=2010-10-10 }}&lt;/ref&gt; It works with most graphics cards supported by X.Org/XFree86 and has been tested on most major distributions, including Debian, Fedora, Mandriva Linux, SLED, SuSE and Ubuntu.  Userful Multiplier is available in 64-bit and 32-bit packages in both RPM and DEB formats.&lt;ref name=&quot;Multiplier2&quot;&gt;{{cite web | url=http://support.userful.com/wiki/index.php/Manuals/UMx/ReadMe/v.3.8 | title=Userful Multiplier Evaluation Version 3.8: Release Notes  | accessdate=2010-10-10 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Userful Desktop===

Userful Desktop is a [[Linux]]-based [[multiseat]] [[operating system]] that combines a mixture of proprietary administrative tools, and a modified [[Red Hat]] distribution, with a [[GNOME]] desktop.&lt;ref name=&quot;UserfulGNU&quot;&gt;{{cite news | author=Bruce Byfield | url= http://www.linux.com/archive/articles/48475 | title=Userful GNU/Linux multi-station software suits general desktop users | publisher=Linux.com | date=2005-10-12 | accessdate=2010-10-12 }}&lt;/ref&gt;  The product is specifically designed as a full public computing solution for kiosks and public access computers.  Desktop settings are managed by session profiles which are created and stored through a central Web-portal.  Some key features are time management, Internet filtering, privacy protection, automated clean-up, and print-job costing, as well as remote monitoring and an administration website.   The  software includes over 40 applications supporting over 30 languages. Userful Desktop is locked-down and tamper-proof. When a user logs off, the station is cleared of browser histories and downloaded files.&lt;ref name=&quot;UDesktop&quot;&gt;{{cite web | url= http://www.userful.com/products/userful-desktop | title=Userful Desktop: Secure Managed Desktops with One Installation | accessdate=2010-10-10 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

Userful Desktop is delivered as a full solution, that includes software, web portal access, standard hardware, monitors, keyboards, mice, dual-head video cards and [[USB]] hubs with various options for further customization, such as including an external USB diskette drive.&lt;ref name=&quot;Turn-key&quot;&gt;{{cite web | url=http://library.userful.com/easy-for-staff.php | title=Userful Libraries – Easy for Staff: Automate Your Library's Public Computers | accessdate=2010-10-10 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

Userful Desktop can be described as a [[multi-station]] system, consisting of a system unit, with one or more stations attached, plus Userful Desktop system software. The result is a [[thin client]] application that creates as many as 10 station terminals from a single PC.&lt;ref name=&quot;UDesktop&quot;/&gt;

Userful's software can be customized through a Web portal called Userful Manager that allows administrators to adjust hundreds of settings, from putting a time limit on the computer's use, to privacy protectors that clean the computer when a person logs out. Settings and updates are automatically rolled out to every computer linked to the system. Usage reports allow administrators to see how the system is running as a whole or drill down to one individual station to see how it is being used.&lt;ref name=&quot;Manager&quot;&gt;{{cite web | url=http://library.userful.com/online-administration.php | title=Userful Libraries – Online Administration: Userful Manager | accessdate=2010-10-10 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

The system's foundation is strong user permissions, multiple-user login and Security Enhanced Linux ([[SE Linux]]).  To ensure precautionary safety measures, only the default kernel is in the boot menu, enabling the computer to boot only from the hard drive. A command line is not supplied on the desktop. Although disk and flash drives are automatically mounted on the desktop, this general security risk is secured by limiting the time of login for each user and deleting the users’ home directories once log out occurs. The system is claimed to be virus-free.&lt;ref name=&quot;UserfulGNU&quot;/&gt;

===Userful Pre-Book===

Pre-Book is an open source [[PC reservation system]] consisting of both a Linux based server and Windows and Linux client management software.  

The software enables enforcement of equitable time usage on publicly accessible computers. Key features include the ability to set up user grace periods, no-show penalties, holiday hours, and PAM authentication. Users are able to book time from remote locations as well as on the computers themselves.  The client software is available for Windows as well as a [[multiseat]] locked-down Linux distro (Userful Desktop).&lt;ref name=&quot;Pre-Book&quot;&gt;{{cite web | url=http://www.userful.com/products/userful-pre-book | title=Free Open Source PC Booking and Reservation Computer Software: Pre-Book Linux Server and Windows Client | accessdate=2010-10-10 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Product Competitors==

Userful MultiSeat Linux 2011 and Userful Multiplier software are the Linux-based equivalents of [[Windows MultiPoint]] Server 2010 for multiseat solutions in the education sector.&lt;ref name=&quot;MultiPoint&quot;&gt;{{cite news | author=Tom Warren | url=http://www.neowin.net/news/microsoft-launches-windows-multipoint-server-2010?showcomments=true | title=Microsoft Launches Windows MultiPoint Server 2010=neowin.net | date=2010-02-24 | accessdate=2010-11-07 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

==See also==
*[[Multiseat configuration|Multiseat]]
*[[NComputing]]

==References==
{{Reflist|2}}

==External links==
*[http://userful.com Userful website]

[[Category:Operating system distributions bootable from read-only media]]
[[Category:Linux]]
[[Category:Privately held companies of Canada]]

[[es:Userful]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
