<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="17816878" ns="0" title="KQLA"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Infobox Radio Station 
| name      = KQLA 
| city      = [[Junction City, Kansas|Junction City]] 
| branding  = ''&quot;Q 103.5&quot;''
| slogan    = &quot;Junction City and Manhattan's Lite Rock&quot;
| airdate   = [[1986 in radio|1986]]
| frequency = 103.5 ([[megahertz|MHz]])
| format    = [[Adult contemporary music|Adult contemporary]] ([[Christmas music]] is aired from [[Thanksgiving]] to [[Christmas Day]])
| erp       = 50,000 [[Watt]]s
| class     = 
| owner     = [[Platinum Broadcasting]] (sale to Eagle Communications pending [[Federal Communications Commission|FCC]] approval)
| website   = http://www.kqla.com
|}}

'''KQLA''' &quot;Q 103.5&quot; is an [[Adult contemporary music|AC]] formatted radio station licensed to [[Ogden, KS]]. It broadcasts to the Junction City-Manhattan-Fort Riley area broadcasting on 103.5 mHz with an ERP of 41,000 watts. The station is owned by Platinum Broadcasting, Inc. of Junction City, which also owns stations [[KJCK (AM)|KJCK]] &quot;1420 KJCK The Talk of JC&quot; and [[KJCK-FM]] &quot;Power Hits 97.5&quot;.

On October 6, 2011, Platinum Broadcasting announced it was ceasing operations, and that the station, along with its sister stations, will be sold to [[Hays, Kansas|Hays]]-based Eagle Communications, pending [[Federal Communications Commission|FCC]] approval &lt;ref&gt;http://www.eaglecom.net/2011NewsReleases/KJCK-KQLAAcquisitionOct2011.pdf&lt;/ref&gt;.

==History==
KQLA went on the air in 1986 with a Top 40 format and competed against (now sister station) [[KJCK-FM]]. It was owned by Kaw Valley Broadcasting Company. It moved over to the Hot AC format sometime in August 1997 when the station was sold to Platinum Broadcasting (97.5's owners) on August 1, 1997. It featured the &quot;Young AC&quot; programming from [[Citadel Media|ABC Radio]], which was satellite-fed. This lasted until 2005 when the owners cut the satellite feed and focused on local DJs and moved towards an Adult Contemporary format, which is continued today. The satellite-fed format, known as &quot;Today's Best Hits&quot;, could be heard on [[KCKS]] &quot;94.9 Kiss FM&quot; (which can be reached in the Junction City area), until 2010 when that station went towards a local presentation and was renamed &quot;NCK 94-9&quot;. 

The station airs [[Christmas music]] between [[Thanksgiving]] and [[Christmas Day]].

The station started relying more on satellite-fed programming in 2009. Most of it airs during the weekends, but there are a few shows that are on during weekdays, such as John Tesh and Tom Kent's programs.

==Ratings==
Currently, the station is ranked at # 13.

==Sister stations==
*[[KJCK (AM)|KJCK]] &quot;1420 KJCK The Talk of JC&quot;
*[[KJCK-FM]] &quot;Power Hits 97.5&quot;

==References==
&lt;references /&gt;

==External links==
*[http://www.kqla.com Official website]
*[http://www.todaysbesthits.com Former satellite-fed Hot AC format, provided by ABC Radio]
{{FM station data|KQLA}}

{{Salina-Manhattan Radio}}

[[Category:Radio stations in Kansas|QLA-FM]]
[[Category:Adult contemporary radio stations in the United States]]

{{Kansas-radio-station-stub}}</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
