<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><redirects><r from="The Black Mages discography" to="The Black Mages" /></redirects><pages><page pageid="1136192" ns="0" title="The Black Mages"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Infobox musical artist
| name = The Black Mages
| background = group_or_band
| origin = Tokyo, Japan
| genre = [[Instrumental rock]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Progressive metal]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Symphonic rock]]&lt;br /&gt;
| years_active = 2002–2010
| label = [[DigiCube]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Square Enix]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Universal Music Group]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Dog Ear Records]]
| associated_acts = Earthbound Papas
| current_members = [[Nobuo Uematsu]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Kenichiro Fukui]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Tsuyoshi Sekito]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Keiji Kawamori]]&lt;br /&gt;Arata Hanyuda&lt;br /&gt;Michio Okamiya
| past_members = 
| notable_instruments = 
}}
'''The Black Mages''' were a Japanese [[instrumental rock]] band formed in 2002 by [[Nobuo Uematsu]], [[Kenichiro Fukui]] and [[Tsuyoshi Sekito]] - three composers for [[Square Enix]]. The band arranged Uematsu's [[Final Fantasy|''Final Fantasy'' video game series]]-based compositions in a rock style often similar to [[progressive metal]], achieved with the additional use of [[synthesizer]]s.&lt;ref name=&quot;u-1&quot;/&gt; Since its inception, the band had expanded to six members with the addition of [[Keiji Kawamori]], Michio Okamiya and Arata Hanyuda. On August 7, 2010, Nobuo Uematsu announced the band had disbanded, but he would continue to perform rock arrangements of his music as a part of another band, the Earthbound Papas.

The band has released three studio albums. Their first was released [[eponym]]ously as ''The Black Mages'' in 2003, and contained arrangements of ''Final Fantasy'' battle themes. The second album, ''The Black Mages II: The Skies Above'', was released in 2004 and featured additional pieces besides battle themes including the group's first original song, &quot;Blue Blast ~Winning the Rainbow&quot;, which was created for Japanese [[K-1]] fighter Takehiro Murahama. The third album, ''The Black Mages III: Darkness and Starlight'', was released on March 19, 2008. Music from the group has also appeared in other albums, including one track in ''Dark Chronicle Premium Arrange'', an album of arranged music from the video game ''[[Dark Chronicle]]'', a piece in the animated film ''[[Final Fantasy VII Advent Children]]'' and its [[Discography of the Final Fantasy VII series#Advent Children|corresponding soundtrack album]], and one track on ''[[Discography of Final Fantasy III#Final Fantasy III Original Soundtrack|Final Fantasy III Original Soundtrack]]'', the soundtrack album for the [[Nintendo DS]] version of ''[[Final Fantasy III]]''.

The Black Mages did not tour as a band, but performed several concerts to promote their album releases. For their first album they performed in [[Shibuya, Tokyo|Shibuya]] and [[Kanagawa Prefecture|Kanagawa]], Japan in 2003 and later released a live video of the first concert on DVD exclusively to Uematsu fanclub members. They repeated this for the release of their second album, performing in [[Kawasaki, Kanagawa|Kawasaki]] and [[Osaka]], Japan in 2005 and similarly released on DVD to fanclub members. The third album saw a performance in [[Yokohama]], Japan in 2008; a DVD of the show was released commercially on March 25, 2009. In addition to these concerts, The Black Mages made live appearances at two [[Final Fantasy concerts|''Final Fantasy'' concerts]], [[Final Fantasy concerts#More Friends: Music from Final Fantasy|More Friends: Music from Final Fantasy]] and [[Final Fantasy concerts#Voices - Music from Final Fantasy|Voices - Music from Final Fantasy]], as well as another [[video game music]] event, Extra: Hyper Game Music Event 2007.

== History ==
[[File:Nobuo Uematsu.jpg|thumb|left|Nobuo Uematsu - composer, producer and keyboardist for The Black Mages]]
In 2000, Square Enix employees [[Kenichiro Fukui]] and [[Tsuyoshi Sekito]] formed an experimental partnership to compose music for the video game ''[[All Star Pro-Wrestling]]'' in a rock style. After the game's success, the two continued to compose in the same style. In 2002, Fukui and Sekito decided to [[arrangement|arrange]] some of the compositions of [[Nobuo Uematsu]], the primary composer for the [[music of the Final Fantasy series|music of the ''Final Fantasy'' series]]. Uematsu, a fan of rock music, enjoyed these arrangements, and Fukui and Sekito asked him to join them in making a rock band. Declining at first due to feeling too busy with his composing duties and attempts to become a music producer with his [[Smile Please]] label, Uematsu agreed to join them in a single live performance as a keyboardist. At the performance, Uematsu felt a &quot;mix of stage fright and excitement, [with] all the crowds cheering, the audience paying full attention&quot;, and decided to join the two in making a band; Fukui and Sekito had refused to start one if Uematsu was not involved as one of the musicians.&lt;ref name=&quot;u-2&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;DitL interview&quot;/&gt;

{{Listen|filename=J-E-N-O-V-A (The Black Mages).ogg|title=J-E-N-O-V-A|description=Short sample of &quot;J-E-N-O-V-A&quot; from ''The Black Mages''&amp;nbsp;— 102 KB|filename2=The Skies Above.ogg|title2=The Skies Above|description2=Short sample of &quot;The Skies Above&quot; from ''The Black Mages II: The Skies Above''&amp;nbsp;— 85 KB}}

The group has said they were &quot;nervous&quot; about forming a rock band, as they were all &quot;middle-aged&quot;, but decided after the performance it would not be a problem. The name &quot;The Black Mages&quot; was chosen by an employee at Square Enix, Mr. Matsushita, and was decided to be in English because it &quot;wouldn't stand out&quot; in Japanese.&lt;ref name=&quot;DitL interview&quot;/&gt; Square Enix owns the name &quot;The Black Mages&quot;, which means while using that name the band was essentially limited to playing ''Final Fantasy'' music and original pieces rather than arranging music from other game series that were not owned by the company.&lt;ref name=&quot;u-3&quot;/&gt;

In 2003, Uematsu decided the band should produce an album of ''Final Fantasy'' arrangements.&lt;ref name=&quot;DitL interview&quot;/&gt; The trio arranged, interpreted, and [[music sequencer|sequenced]] ten battle themes from various ''Final Fantasy'' titles, with Uematsu as producer; the album was released eponymously on February 19, 2003. To celebrate the success, Uematsu decided to organize a concert in tribute to the album; Uematsu and Fukui served as the keyboardists, while Sekito was the guitarist. They needed more people to perform the arrangements live, however, and as such, several other members from Square Enix joined. [[Keiji Kawamori]] joined to play the bass guitar, Michio Okamiya to play the guitar, and Arata Hanyuda to play the drums.&lt;ref name=&quot;u-4&quot;/&gt; Since then, The Black Mages have released two additional albums, with all six members participating. The group performed concerts to promote both of these albums, and also participated in [[video game music]]-themed concerts.

On August 7, 2010, Uematsu announced the band had formally disbanded. He did not directly state the reason for the decision, though in previous interviews he had noted the band was increasingly finding it difficult to find time to rehearse together. In an April 2011 interview he said the main reason was because The Black Mages had been formed as a &quot;Square Enix&quot; band, they were unable to perform arrangements of work he had composed after leaving Square Enix or to focus on original pieces.&lt;ref name=&quot;SEMOnuint&quot;&gt;{{cite web |last=Diener |first=Matt |title=Interview with Nobuo Uematsu on the Earthbound Papas (April 2011) |url=http://squareenixmusic.com/features/interviews/nobuouematsu4.shtml |publisher=Square Enix Music Online |accessdate=2011-04-11 |date=April 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; Uematsu continues to play rock arrangements of his music as a part of the band the Earthbound Papas, which performed at the Distant Worlds II concert in 2010.&lt;ref name=&quot;BMdisband&quot;&gt;{{cite web|last=Greening |first=Chris |title=Exclusive: The Black Mages Have Been Disbanded |url=http://squareenixmusic.com/musicnews2.php?subaction=showfull&amp;id=1281190773&amp;archive=&amp;start_from=&amp;ucat=2&amp; |publisher=Square Enix Music Online |accessdate=2010-09-07 |date=2010-09-07}}&lt;/ref&gt; He has been joined by fellow Black Mages band-mates Michio Okamiya and Arata Hanyuda, both continuing on guitar and drums, respectively. They had also left Square Enix; Uematsu built the new band to not include any current Square Enix employees so as to avoid the trademark and licensing problems of The Black Mages.&lt;ref name=&quot;SEMOnuint&quot;/&gt;
{{-}}

== Discography ==
=== ''The Black Mages'' ===
{{Infobox album
| Name = The Black Mages
| Type = studio
| Artist = The Black Mages
| Cover = The Black Mages album.jpg
| Released = February 19, 2003&lt;br /&gt;May 10, 2004 &lt;small&gt;(''re-release'')&lt;/small&gt;
| Recorded = 
| Genre = [[Progressive metal]]
| Length = 51:29
| Label = [[DigiCube]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Square Enix]] &lt;small&gt;(''re-release'')&lt;/small&gt;
| Producer = [[Nobuo Uematsu]]
| Italic title= no
}}
''The Black Mages'' is an arranged soundtrack album of video game music from the ''Final Fantasy'' series of role-playing video games. The album contains a selection of musical tracks from the games, arranged and performed in a hybrid of [[power metal]] and [[progressive metal]] by The Black Mages. All the selected tracks are &quot;battle&quot; music from the games. The pieces have been described as &quot;hard-rock&quot; with &quot;blazing [[synthesizer]]s and guitars&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;RPGFBM&quot;/&gt; It was first released on February 19, 2003, by [[DigiCube]], and subsequently re-released on May 10, 2004, by [[Square Enix]]. It spans ten tracks and covers a duration of 51:29.&lt;ref name=&quot;RPGFBM&quot;/&gt;

The album reached #43 on the Japan [[Oricon]] charts.&lt;ref name=&quot;ORITBM&quot;/&gt; It was well-received by critics like Andy Byus of RPGFan, who termed it &quot;addicting&quot; and &quot;powerful&quot;. He criticized the overuse of synthesizer as opposed to live instruments in some tracks, and that some of the arrangements stayed too close to the original tracks, especially &quot;Dancing Mad&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;RPGFBM&quot;/&gt; Tetra of Square Enix Music Online also enjoyed the album, saying &quot;all of the members are strong musicians, and Sekito and Fukui were equally strong arrangers&quot;. His primary complaint with the album was he felt many of the songs followed the same general pattern in their arrangements.&lt;ref name=&quot;SEMOTBM&quot;/&gt;

{{tracklist
| collapsed = no
| headline = Track listing
| title1 = Battle Scene
| note1 = from ''Final Fantasy I - Battle''
| length1 = 4:19
| title2 = Clash on the Big Bridge
| note2 = from ''Final Fantasy V - Battle on the Big Bridge''
| length2 = 4:16
| title3 = Force Your Way
| note3 = from ''Final Fantasy VIII - Force Your Way''
| length3 = 3:51
| title4 = Battle, Scene II
| note4 = from ''Final Fantasy II - Battle Scene 2''
| length4 = 3:52
| title5 = The Decisive Battle
| note5 = from ''Final Fantasy VI - The Decisive Battle''
| length5 = 4:02
| title6 = Battle Theme
| note6 = from ''Final Fantasy VI - Battle''
| length6 = 3:21
| title7 = J-E-N-O-V-A
| note7 = from ''Final Fantasy VII - JENOVA''
| length7 = 6:08
| title8 = Those Who Fight Further
| note8 = from ''Final Fantasy VII - Fight On!''
| length8 = 4:25
| title9 = Dancing Mad
| note9 = from ''Final Fantasy VI - Dancing Mad''
| length9 = 12:04
| title10 = Fight With Seymour
| note10 = from ''Final Fantasy X - Fight With Seymour''
| length10 = 5:05
}}

=== ''The Black Mages II: The Skies Above'' ===
{{Infobox album
| Name = The Black Mages II: The Skies Above
| Type = studio
| Artist = The Black Mages
| Cover = The Black Mages II.jpg
| Released = December 22, 2004
| Recorded = 
| Genre = [[Progressive metal]]
| Length = 50:56
| Label = [[Universal Music Group]]
| Producer = [[Nobuo Uematsu]]
| Italic title= no
}}
''The Black Mages II: The Skies Above'' is an arranged soundtrack album of video game music from the ''Final Fantasy'' series of role-playing video games. Like the previous album, it contains a selection of musical tracks from the games, arranged and performed in a hybrid of power metal and progressive metal by The Black Mages. Unlike their first album, ''The Skies Above'' includes other pieces besides battle themes; the album also features songs, which were performed by [[Kazco Hamano]], credited as &quot;KAZCO&quot;, and [[Tomoaki Watanabe]], or &quot;Mr. Goo&quot;. It also includes a non-''Final Fantasy'' track, &quot;Blue Blast&amp;nbsp;— Winning the Rainbow&quot;, an original piece that was created for Japanese [[K-1]] fighter Takehiro Murahama. ''The Skies Above'', as opposed to the first album, features real drums rather than sequenced drums, as the band had expanded from its original three members, none of whom played drums.&lt;ref name=&quot;u-5&quot;/&gt; The line &quot;Maybe I'm a Lion&quot; in the track of the same name was spoken by [[Alexander O. Smith]], a translator for Square Enix and close friend of Okamiya, one of the new members.&lt;ref name=&quot;GSWSmithint&quot;/&gt; It was released on December 22, 2004, by [[Universal Music Group]]. The album spans eleven tracks, and covers a duration of 50:56.&lt;ref name=&quot;RPGFBM2&quot;/&gt;

The album received mixed reviews from critics; Jesse Jones of RPGFan said that he was &quot;simply amazed&quot; by the album, though it was not without flaws. While terming the music overall as &quot;excellent&quot;, he disliked the vocal arrangements in &quot;Otherworld&quot; and &quot;The Skies Above&quot;, finding that the voices of the singers did not match with the songs' instrumentals.&lt;ref name=&quot;RPGFBM2&quot;/&gt; Zane of Square Enix Music Online was less approving of the album, calling it &quot;passable&quot; and saying that the new arrangements gave &quot;mixed results&quot;. He blamed the &quot;intolerable vocals&quot; and occasional poor choices in instruments as the problems with the album, concluding that the second Black Mages album was inferior to the first.&lt;ref name=&quot;u-6&quot;/&gt;

{{tracklist
| collapsed = no
| headline = Track listing
| title1 = The Rocking Grounds
| note1 = from ''Final Fantasy III - Battle 2''
| length1 = 3:56
| title2 = Zeromus
| note2 = from ''Final Fantasy IV - Zeromus''
| length2 = 3:56
| title3 = Vamo' Alla Flamenco
| note3 = from ''Final Fantasy IX - Vamo Alla Flamenco''
| length3 = 4:25
| title4 = Hunter's Chance
| note4 = from ''Final Fantasy IX - Hunter's Chance''
| length4 = 4:44
| title5 = Otherworld
| note5 = from ''Final Fantasy X - Otherworld''
| length5 = 3:14
| title6 = Matoya's Cave
| note6 = from ''Final Fantasy I - Matoya's Cave''
| length6 = 4:44
| title7 = The Man with the Machine Gun
| note7 = from ''Final Fantasy VIII - The Man with the Machine Gun''
| length7 = 4:17
| title8 = Maybe I'm a Lion
| note8 = from ''Final Fantasy VIII - Maybe I'm a Lion''
| length8 = 5:34
| title9 = Battle with the Four Fiends
| note9 = from ''Final Fantasy IV - Battle with the Four Fiends''
| length9 = 3:58
| title10 = The Skies Above
| note10 = from ''Final Fantasy X - To Zanarkand''
| length10 = 7:18
| title11 = Blue Blast&amp;nbsp;— Winning the Rainbow
| note11 = original track
| length11 = 4:49
}}

=== ''The Black Mages III: Darkness and Starlight'' ===
{{Infobox album
| Name = The Black Mages III: Darkness and Starlight
| Type = studio
| Artist = The Black Mages
| Cover = The Black Mage III.jpg
| Released = March 19, 2008
| Recorded = 
| Genre = [[Progressive metal]]
| Length = 60:40
| Label = [[Dog Ear Records]]
| Producer = [[Nobuo Uematsu]]
| Italic title= no
}}
''The Black Mages III: Darkness and Starlight'' is the third arranged soundtrack album of video game music from the ''Final Fantasy'' series of role-playing video games. The album contains a selection of musical tracks from the games, arranged and performed in a hybrid of power metal and progressive metal by The Black Mages in a similar manner to their previous albums. It was released on March 19, 2008, by Uematsu's [[Dog Ear Records]], spanning ten tracks and a duration of 60:40.&lt;ref name=&quot;RPGFBM3&quot;/&gt; The Black Mages sing the chorus for the song &quot;Darkness and Starlight&quot;, the only vocal track on the album.&lt;ref name=&quot;u-7&quot;/&gt; The album has been described as being composed of a mix of &quot;intense&quot; [[symphonic metal]] pieces and [[rock opera]]. Like the previous album, ''Darkness and Starlight'' features an original piece, &quot;Life ~&amp;nbsp;in memory of KEITEN&amp;nbsp;~&quot;, which was composed by Uematsu for Yoshitaka Tagawa, a boy he had met who died of [[leukemia]].&lt;ref name=&quot;RPGFBM3&quot;/&gt;

The album was well-received by websites like RPGFan, which said the album was &quot;very much worth the over three year wait&quot; and described the tracks as &quot;enjoyable&quot; and &quot;inspiring&quot;. He had few complaints with the album, only describing &quot;Opening ~ Bombing Mission&quot; and &quot;Assault of the Silver Dragons&quot; as &quot;bland&quot;, but still worth listening to.&lt;ref name=&quot;RPGFBM3&quot;/&gt; Square Enix Music Online was even more positive in its review of the album, calling it &quot;a masterpiece&quot; and &quot;The Black Mages' finest effort to date&quot;, wishing only the album had been longer.&lt;ref name=&quot;u-8&quot;/&gt;

{{tracklist
| collapsed = no
| headline = Track listing
| title1 = Opening ~ Bombing Mission
| note1 = from ''Final Fantasy VII''&amp;nbsp;– &quot;Opening ~ Bombing Mission&quot;
| length1 = 4:39
| title2 = Neo EXDEATH
| note2 = from ''Final Fantasy V''&amp;nbsp;– &quot;The Final Battle&quot;
| length2 = 4:39
| title3 = The Extreme
| note3 = from ''Final Fantasy VIII''&amp;nbsp;– &quot;The Extreme&quot;
| length3 =  5:51
| title4 = Assault of the Silver Dragons
| note4 = from ''Final Fantasy IX''&amp;nbsp;– &quot;Assault of the Silver Dragons&quot;
| length4 = 5:01
| title5 = KURAYAMINOKUMO
| note5 = from ''Final Fantasy III''&amp;nbsp;– &quot;This is The Last Battle&quot;
| length5 = 4:56
| title6 = Distant Worlds
| note6 = from ''Final Fantasy XI''&amp;nbsp;– &quot;Distant Worlds&quot;
| length6 = 7:32
| title7 = Premonition
| note7 = from ''Final Fantasy VIII''&amp;nbsp;– &quot;Premonition&quot;
| length7 = 5:23
| title8 = Grand Cross
| note8 = from ''Final Fantasy IX''&amp;nbsp;– &quot;The Final Battle&quot;
| length8 = 5:34
| title9 = Darkness and Starlight
| note9 = from ''Final Fantasy VI''&amp;nbsp;– &quot;Overture&quot;, &quot;Aria di Mezzo Carattere&quot;, &quot;Wedding Waltz~Duel&quot;
| length9 = 15:32
| title10 = Life ~ in memory of KEITEN ~
| note10 = original track
| length10 = 1:38
}}

=== Other appearances ===
In addition to their own albums, pieces from The Black Mages have appeared on several other albums. The first of these was &quot;Flame Demon Monster Gaspard&quot; on ''Dark Chronicle Premium Arrange'', an album of arranged music from the video game ''[[Dark Chronicle]]'' originally composed by [[Tomohito Nishiura]]. The album was released on April 21, 2004, by [[Team Entertainment]].&lt;ref name=&quot;u-9&quot;/&gt; Their next appearance was in the animated film ''[[Final Fantasy VII Advent Children]]'' and its [[Music of the Final Fantasy VII series#Advent Children|corresponding soundtrack album]], where they played—together with orchestration conducted by Koji Haijima—&quot;Advent: One-Winged Angel&quot;, an arrangement of &quot;One-Winged Angel&quot; from ''[[Final Fantasy VII]]'' originally composed by Uematsu and arranged by [[Shirō Hamaguchi]].&lt;ref name=&quot;u-10&quot;/&gt; Their third appearance was on the soundtrack album for the [[Nintendo DS]] version of ''[[Final Fantasy III]]'', entitled ''[[Music of Final Fantasy III#Final Fantasy III Original Soundtrack|Final Fantasy III Original Soundtrack]]'', with one track then titled &quot;Last Battle -THE BLACK MAGES Ver.-&quot;, but later re-titled &quot;KURAYAMINOKUMO&quot; on the ''Darkness and Starlight'' album.&lt;ref name=&quot;u-11&quot;/&gt;

== Concerts ==
While The Black Mages never toured as a band, they participated in several concert events. These include promotional concerts for the release of their three albums and appearances at orchestral concerts devoted to ''Final Fantasy'' music.

=== Promotional concerts ===
The Black Mages held a concert to promote their first album on April 26, 2003, in the [[Shibuya-AX]] concert hall in [[Shibuya, Tokyo|Shibuya]], Tokyo, Japan. This overnight concert featured the full setlist from the album, and introduced the track &quot;Matoya's Cave&quot;, which would be featured in their next album. While the band members were being introduced, Okamiya performed the [[Chocobo]] theme and Uematsu performed the intro to [[Deep Purple]]'s &quot;[[Smoke on the Water]].&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;SEMOTBML&quot;/&gt; A DVD recording of the show was made and given to Uematsu fanclub members that year.&lt;ref name=&quot;u-12&quot;/&gt; The concert was repeated on November 3, 2003, at [[Kanagawa University]] in [[Kanagawa Prefecture|Kanagawa]], Japan. This free concert was part of the Kanagawa Jindai Festa. As Uematsu graduated from Kanagawa University, The Black Mages all wore the school's student uniform.&lt;ref name=&quot;SEMOTBML&quot;/&gt;

For their second album, The Black Mages performed two promotional concerts. They performed all the songs from their second album, along with &quot;The Decisive Battle&quot;, &quot;Those Who Fight Further&quot; and &quot;Clash on the Big Bridge&quot; from their first album. These concerts featured [[Kenji Ito]], who performed piano renditions of pieces from the ''[[SaGa (series)|SaGa]]'' series. Also featured were muZik, a group who performed seven [[techno]] and [[pop music|pop]]-style ''Final Fantasy'' arrangements.&lt;ref name=&quot;u-13&quot;/&gt; The first concert set was at Club Citta in [[Kawasaki, Kanagawa|Kawasaki]], Japan on January 22 and January 23, 2005, and the second one at Namba Hatch in [[Osaka]], Japan on January 28, 2005.&lt;ref name=&quot;u-14&quot;/&gt; A DVD recording of the Kawasaki show was made and given to Uematsu fanclub members on February 1, 2006.&lt;ref name=&quot;u-15&quot;/&gt;

A live concert was performed for the release of The Black Mages' third album as for their previous albums. Performed at the Yokohama Blitz in [[Yokohama]], Japan, on August 9, 2008, the concert featured all the pieces from the album with the exception of &quot;Life ~ in memory of KEITEN ~&quot; and with the addition of &quot;Maybe I'm a Lion&quot; and &quot;Clash on the Big Bridge&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;u-16&quot;/&gt; A DVD recording of the show was made and released commercially in 2009, a first for the band.&lt;ref name=&quot;u-16&quot;/&gt;

=== Other concerts ===
In addition to their own concerts, The Black Mages made appearances at official [[Final Fantasy concerts|''Final Fantasy'' concerts]]. The first of these was the [[Final Fantasy concerts#More Friends: Music from Final Fantasy|More Friends: Music from Final Fantasy]] event, held in the [[Gibson Amphitheatre]] in Los Angeles, California, on May 16, 2005;&lt;ref name=&quot;u-18&quot;/&gt; the concert was The Black Mages' first appearance in North America.&lt;ref name=&quot;u-19&quot;/&gt; The band performed &quot;The Rocking Grounds&quot; and &quot;Maybe I'm a Lion&quot; from their second album, and joined with the orchestra for &quot;Advent: One-Winged Angel&quot; as an encore to the concert. [[List of Final Fantasy compilation albums#More Friends: Music from Final Fantasy|A recorded album]] was released on February 15, 2006, by Square Enix, and included the pieces by The Black Mages.&lt;ref name=&quot;u-20&quot;/&gt;

The second ''Final Fantasy'' concert The Black Mages performed at was the [[Final Fantasy concerts#Voices - Music from Final Fantasy|Voices - Music from Final Fantasy]] concert held in Yokohama, Japan on February 18, 2006. This concert featured performances of various ''Final Fantasy'' songs. The Black Mages played &quot;Advent: One-Winged Angel&quot; at the end of the concert along with the Prima Vista Philharmonic Orchestra; the song was played a second time as an encore.&lt;ref name=&quot;u-21&quot;/&gt; A DVD of the concert was released on June 21, 2006, and included an interview with Uematsu.&lt;ref name=&quot;u-22&quot;/&gt;

On July 7, 2007, The Black Mages appeared at the Extra: Hyper Game Music Event at [[AgeHa|Shinkiba Studio Coast]] in Tokyo. They were the last of thirteen artists and groups to play at the six-hour event, and performed &quot;Last Battle&quot;, &quot;Those Who Fight Further&quot;, &quot;Maybe I'm a Lion&quot; and &quot;Clash on the Big Bridge&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;u-23&quot;/&gt; The music performed by The Black Mages did not appear on the official album for the concert.&lt;ref name=&quot;u-24&quot;/&gt;

== Band members ==
* [[Nobuo Uematsu]]&amp;nbsp;– [[electronic keyboard|keyboards]] (2002–2010)
* [[Kenichiro Fukui]]&amp;nbsp;– keyboards (2002–2010)
* [[Tsuyoshi Sekito]]&amp;nbsp;– [[guitar]] (2002–2010)
* [[Keiji Kawamori]]&amp;nbsp;– [[bass guitar]] (2003–2010)
* Arata Hanyuda&amp;nbsp;– [[drum kit|drums]] (2003–2010)
* Michio Okamiya&amp;nbsp;– guitar (2003–2010)

== References ==
{{reflist|2|refs=

&lt;ref name=&quot;u-1&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://na.square-enix.com/uematsu/black_mages/index.html|title=Uematsu's Music|publisher=[[Square Enix]]|accessdate=2009-06-18}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;u-2&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.gameinformer.com/News/Story/200905/N09.0527.1612.59659.htm?Page=3|title=Nobuo Uematsu: The Man Behind The Music|work=[[Game Informer]]|first=Meagan |last=VanBurkleo|date=2009-05-27|accessdate=2009-06-16}} {{dead link| date=June 2010 | bot=DASHBot}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;DitL interview&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.1up.com/do/feature?pager.offset=0&amp;cId=3166165|title=A Day in the Life of Final Fantasy's Nobuo Uematsu|publisher=[[1UP.com]]|first=James| last=Mielke|date=2008-02-15|accessdate=2008-08-05}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;u-3&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.destructoid.com/destructoid-interview-final-fantasy-composer-nobuo-uematsu-128986.phtml|title=Destructoid interview: Final Fantasy composer Nobuo Uematsu|publisher=Destructoid|first=Dale|last=North|date=2009-04-17|accessdate=2009-04-28}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;u-4&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.squareenixmusic.com/companies/blackmages/history.shtml|title=The Black Mages :: History|publisher=Square Enix Music Online|author=Chris|date=2007-12-21|accessdate=2009-06-30}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;RPGFBM&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://rpgfan.com/soundtracks/ffbm/index.html|title=Final Fantasy ~ The Black Mages|publisher=RPGFan|first=Andy|last=Byus|date=2003-03-19| accessdate=2008-06-06}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;ORITBM&quot;&gt;{{cite web| url = http://www.oricon.co.jp/prof/artist/67810/products/music/500669/1/| publisher = [[Oricon]]| title = ＴＨＥ　ＢＬＡＣＫ　ＭＡＧＥＳ |language = Japanese | accessdate=2010-06-24}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;SEMOTBM&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.squareenixmusic.com/reviews/tetra/ffblackmages.shtml|title=The Black Mages :: Review by Tetra|publisher=Square Enix Music Online|author=Tetra|accessdate=2009-06-18}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;u-5&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.cocoebiz.com/report/tbminterview.html|title=The Black Mages Exclusive Interview With Cocoebiz|publisher=Cocoebiz|date=2005-01-22|accessdate=2009-06-16}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;GSWSmithint&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.gamesetwatch.com/2009/11/localization_tactics_kajiya_productions.php|title=GameSetInterview: 'Localization Tactics Advance - Kajiya Productions on Translating Final Fantasy'|last=Smith|first=Alexander|date=2009-11-09|publisher=GameSetWatch|accessdate=2009-11-16}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;RPGFBM2&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://rpgfan.com/soundtracks/ffbm2/index.html|title=Final Fantasy ~ The Black Mages II: The Skies Above|publisher=RPGFan|first=Jesse|last=Jones |date=2005-01-29|accessdate=2008-06-06}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;u-6&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url= http://www.squareenixmusic.com/reviews/zane/ffblackmages2.shtml|title=The Black Mages II ~The Skies Above~ :: Review by Zane|publisher=Square Enix Music Online|author=Zane|accessdate=2009-06-24}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;RPGFBM3&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://rpgfan.com/soundtracks/ffbm3/index.html|title=Final Fantasy ~ The Black Mages III: Darkness and Starlight|publisher=RPGFan|first=Logan|last=Castonguay|date=2008-03-25|accessdate=2008-06-06}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;u-7&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.squareenixmusic.com/musicnews2.php?subaction=showfull&amp;id=1203116698&amp;archive=&amp;start_from=&amp;ucat=2&amp;|title=New The Black Mages III Video Released|publisher=Square Enix Music Online|author=Chris|date=2008-02-15|accessdate=2008-06-06}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;u-8&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.squareenixmusic.com/reviews/chris/ffblackmages3.shtml|title=The Black Mages III ~Darkness and Starlight~ :: Review by Chris|publisher=Square Enix Music Online|author=Chris|accessdate=2009-06-30}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;u-9&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://rpgfan.com/soundtracks/darkchron-pa/index.html|title= Dark Chronicle Premium Arrange|publisher=RPGFan|first=Patrick|last=Gann|date=2005-01-01|accessdate=2009-06-15}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;u-10&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.rpgfan.com/soundtracks/ff7ac/index.html|title=Final Fantasy VII: Advent Children OST|publisher=RPGFan|first=Patrick|last=Gann|date=2005-10-30|accessdate=2008-07-28}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;u-11&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://rpgfan.com/soundtracks/ff3-ds/index.html|title=Final Fantasy III OST|publisher=RPGFan|first=Patrick|last=Gann|date=2006-10-05|accessdate= 2008-03-27}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;SEMOTBML&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.squareenixmusic.com/concerts/blackmages.shtml|title=The Black Mages Live :: Concert Information|publisher=Square Enix Music Online|accessdate=2009-06-30}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;u-12&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.squareenixmusic.com/albums/dvds/blackmages.shtml|title=The Black Mages Live DVD :: Album Information|publisher=Square Enix Music Online|accessdate= 2009-06-30}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;u-13&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url= http://www.squareenixmusic.com/concerts/blackmages2.shtml|title=The Black Mages Live &quot;Above the Sky&quot; :: Concert Information|publisher=Square Enix Music Online|accessdate=2009-06-30}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;u-14&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.square-enix.co.jp/music/sem/page/uematsu/tbm2/live_01.html|title=植松伸夫です。|publisher=[[Square Enix]]|language=Japanese|accessdate=2009-06-18}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;u-15&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.squareenixmusic.com/albums/dvds/blackmages2.shtml|title=The Black Mages Live &quot;Above the Sky&quot; DVD :: Album Information|publisher=Square Enix Music Online|accessdate=2009-06-30}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;u-16&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url= http://dogearrecords.blog92.fc2.com/blog-category-0.html|title=Dog Ear Records Blog|publisher=[[Dog Ear Records]]|language= Japanese|accessdate=2008-06-02}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;u-18&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://na.square-enix.com/uematsu/concert/more_friends.html|title= Uematsu's Music|publisher=[[Square Enix]]|accessdate=2009-06-04}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;u-19&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://music.ign.com/articles/608/608247p1.html| title=Final Fantasy&amp;nbsp;— More Friends, More Music|publisher=[[IGN]]|date=2005-04-28|accessdate=2009-06-09}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;u-20&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://rpgfan.com/soundtracks/ffmorela/index.html|title=More Friends music from Final Fantasy ~Los Angeles Live 2005~|publisher=RPGFan|first=Patrick|last=Gann|date= 2006-04-05|accessdate=2008-05-20}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;u-21&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.squareenixmusic.com/concerts/voices.shtml|title=VOICES&amp;nbsp;— Music from Final Fantasy|publisher=Square Enix Music Online|accessdate=2009-06-04}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;u-22&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.squareenixmusic.com/albums/dvds/voices.shtml|title= VOICES&amp;nbsp;— Music from Final Fantasy DVD|publisher=Square Enix Music Online|accessdate=2009-06-07}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;u-23&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.squareenixmusic.com/concerts/extra.shtml|title=Extra: Hyper Game Music Event 2007 :: Concert Information|publisher=Square Enix Music Online|accessdate=2009-06-30}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;u-24&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.squareenixmusic.com/albums/e/extra.shtml|title=Extra&amp;nbsp;— Official Compilation :: Album Information|publisher=Square Enix Music Online|accessdate=2009-06-30}}&lt;/ref&gt;
}}

== External links ==
* [http://na.square-enix.com/uematsu/black_mages/index.html The Black Mages Square Enix website]
* [http://www.dogearrecords.com/tbm3_eg/index.htm The Black Mages Dog Ear Records website]

{{good article}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Black Mages, The}}
[[Category:Final Fantasy music]]
[[Category:Japanese rock music groups]]
[[Category:Progressive metal musical groups]]
[[Category:Video game music cover bands]]
[[Category:Video game musicians]]
[[Category:Musical sextets]]
[[Category:Musical groups established in 2002]]
[[Category:Musical groups disestablished in 2010]]

[[de:The Black Mages]]
[[es:The Black Mages]]
[[fr:The Black Mages]]
[[it:The Black Mages]]
[[nl:The Black Mages]]
[[ja:THE BLACK MAGES]]
[[pl:The Black Mages]]
[[pt:The Black Mages]]
[[ru:The Black Mages]]
[[sq:The Black Mages]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
