<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><redirects><r from="Diciopédia" to="Porto Editora" /></redirects><pages><page pageid="3500209" ns="0" title="Porto Editora"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{primary sources|date=August 2009}}

'''Porto Editora''' is the leading educational publisher in Portugal, in the areas of educational books, dictionaries and multimedia products – off and on-line.  	 

Porto Editora was founded in 1944 in Porto by a group of teachers within different areas of education.

Since its involvement in Multimedia in 1994, Porto Editora has published dozens of educational [[CD-ROM]]s and DVD-ROMs, several of which – such as “Diciopédia”, have become well-known, and best-selling multimedia products in Portugal. 	 
  	  	  	  	 
At the same time, Porto Editora has been developing a full project for the Internet aiming at a range of different targets: students of all ages, parents and teachers. For children between the ages of 5–11, www.sitiodosmiudos.pt for learning the first numbers, letters and words, while taking the first steps in the Internet; www.edusurfa.pt is a teen site, where topics like cinema, theater, music or books live together with school subjects; for parents, teachers and the whole educational community, www.educare.pt offers a full news coverage of the Portuguese educational reality, and also articles, files and reports signed by some of the most reputed personalities in pedagogy, psychology, pediatrics and other education-related areas.

On [[Electronic commerce|e-commerce]], www.wook.pt is a very successful project implemented by Porto Editora. Here can be found all the books, multimedia products and videogames published and released in Portugal. Webboom.pt is the most renowned Portuguese bookstore on-line being frequently distinguished with prizes and positively mentioned in the media.

==References==
{{Reflist}}

==External links==
*[http://www.portoeditora.pt Porto Editora]
*[http://www.wook.pt Wook]
*[http://www.educare.pt Educare]
*[http://www.edusurfa.pt Edusurfa]
*[http://www.diciopedia.pt Diciopédia]
*[http://www.infopedia.pt Infopédia]
*[http://www.escolavirtual.pt Escola Virtual]


[[Category:Bookstores of Portugal]]
[[Category:Book publishing companies of Portugal]]


[[pt:Porto Editora]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
