<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><redirects><r from="Live update" to="Norton LiveUpdate" /></redirects><pages><page pageid="30865839" ns="0" title="Norton LiveUpdate"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Cleanup|date=March 2009}}

{{Expert-subject-multiple|Software|Computer Security|date=June 2009}}
{{Infobox Software
| name = Norton LiveUpdate
| screenshot = [[Image:LiveUpdate.png|center|310px]]
| caption = LiveUpdate running in [[Norton Internet Security|Norton Internet Security 2012]]
| developer = [[Symantec Corporation]]
| operating_system = [[Microsoft Windows]], [[Mac OS X]]
| license = [[Proprietary software|Proprietary]]
| website = [http://www.symantec.com/ Symantec.com]
}}

'''Norton LiveUpdate''' is an application developed by [[Symantec Corporation]] that downloads and installs security updates (such as spyware, firewall, or antivirus signature files) and software patches.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://service1.symantec.com/SUPPORT/sharedtech.nsf/0/d59068009e7f27b965257287005fd39d?OpenDocument|accessdate=2009-05-14|title=Is LiveUpdate Notice a Symantec product?|publisher=Symantec Corporation}}&lt;/ref&gt; LiveUpdate can only apply updates for a particular version of Norton; it cannot however upgrade a version of Norton to a later version (for example Norton Internet Security 2006 to 2009). To upgrade the product to the latest version, one would have to go to a separate website.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url = http://www.symantec.com/home_homeoffice/support/special/upgrade2007/vista/select_product.jsp?site=nuc|accessdate=2009-03-18|title=The Norton Update Center|publisher=Symantec Corporation}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In the past, Norton LiveUpdate was a separate software that is installed with all Symantec products.  However, with all Norton product since 2009 , it is an integrated part of the Norton product.

==How it works==
A valid subscription is required to use Symantec LiveUpdate. Symantec LiveUpdate can be run in Interactive Mode or in Express Mode. In Interactive mode, users decide which updates to download and apply. Express mode will download and apply all applicable updates. LiveUpdate also runs in Express mode silently in the background. Once all updates are downloaded, Symantec LiveUpdate will begin the process of installing them. If a restart is required, LiveUpdate will notify the user. Users can restart within the LiveUpdate interface. 

Norton 2006 through 2008 products included a [http://service1.symantec.com/SUPPORT/sharedtech.nsf/0/d59068009e7f27b965257287005fd39d?OpenDocument LiveUpdate Notice] component, which notifies users of new product versions and subscription status.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://service1.symantec.com/SUPPORT/sharedtech.nsf/0/d59068009e7f27b965257287005fd39d?OpenDocument|accessdate=2009-05-08|title=Is LiveUpdate Notice a Symantec product?|publisher=Symantec Corporation}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Intelligent Updater==
Intelligent Updater is an alternate delivery method for virus definitions, which consists of an executable file that can be downloaded and run manually.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.symantec.com/business/security_response/definitions.jsp|accessdate=2009-05-08|title=Virus Definitions &amp; Security Updates|publisher=Symantec Corporation}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.symantec.com/business/support/index?page=content&amp;id=TECH106037|accessdate=2011-11-22|title=How to update virus definitions and other content for Symantec antivirus products|publisher=Symantec Cooperation}}&lt;/ref&gt; It is used to update virus definitions only. To install other updates a user must run LiveUpdate.

==Removal==
Norton 2008 and previous versions include a separate LiveUpdate component, which must be separately uninstalled, or removed using the Norton Removal Tool.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.pcworld.com/reviews/product/30828/review/norton_internet_security_2008.html PCWorld|accessdate=2009-05-08|title=How to update virus definitions and other content for Symantec antivirus products|publisher=Symantec Cooperation}}&lt;/ref&gt; Norton 2009 does not bundle a separate LiveUpdate component.

==References==
{{reflist}}

==External links==
* [http://www.symantec.com/ Symantec Home Page]
* [https://www-secure.symantec.com/norton-support/jsp/help-solutions.jsp?docid=v57903068_EndUserProfile_en_us&amp;lg=english&amp;ct=united+states&amp;entsrc=direct_pubweb Download the newest Symantec LiveUpdate program here]

{{Symantec}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Norton Liveupdate}}
[[Category:Symantec software]]

[[de:LiveUpdate]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
