<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><redirects><r from="Tintin film" to="The Adventures of Tintin (film)" /></redirects><pages><page pageid="11400848" ns="0" title="The Adventures of Tintin (film)"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Use mdy dates|date=April 2011}}
{{sprotect|small=yes}}
{{About|the film|the video game based on this film|The Adventures of Tintin: The Secret of the Unicorn (video game)}}
{{Infobox film
| name = The Adventures of Tintin
| image = The Adventures of Tintin - Secret of the Unicorn.jpg
| image_size = 215px
| alt = 
| caption = Teaser poster
| director = [[Steven Spielberg]]
| producer = [[Peter Jackson]]&lt;br /&gt;Steven Spielberg&lt;br /&gt;[[Kathleen Kennedy (film producer)|Kathleen Kennedy]]
| screenplay = [[Steven Moffat]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Edgar Wright]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Joe Cornish (comedian)|Joe Cornish]] 
| based on = {{Based on|''[[The Adventures of Tintin]]''|[[Hergé]]}}
| starring = [[Jamie Bell]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Andy Serkis]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Simon Pegg]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Nick Frost]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Daniel Craig]]
| music = [[John Williams]]&lt;!--http://www.gsamusic.com/Composers/WLLMS-JN.pdf--&gt;
| cinematography = [[Janusz Kamiński]]
| editing = [[Michael Kahn (film editor)|Michael Kahn]]
| studio = [[Amblin Entertainment]]&lt;br /&gt;[[The Kennedy/Marshall Company]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Nickelodeon Movies]]&lt;br /&gt;[[WingNut Films]]
| distributor = [[Paramount Pictures]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Columbia Pictures]]&lt;ref name=&quot;sonypictures&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.movieweb.com/news/sony-pictures-teams-up-with-paramount-for-tintin|title=Sony Pictures Teams Up with Paramount for Tintin|publisher=MovieWeb|date=November 2, 2008|accessdate=April 7, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;
| released = {{Film date|2011|10|26|United Kingdom|2011|12|21|United States}}
| runtime = 107 minutes&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=''The Adventures of Tintin - The Secret of the Unicorn'' (PG)|url=http://www.bbfc.co.uk/BFF279229/|work=[[Steven Spielberg]]|publisher=[[British Board of Film Classification]]|accessdate=2011-10-13}}&lt;/ref&gt;
| country = {{Film US}}&lt;br&gt;{{Film NZ}}
| language = English
| budget = $135 million &lt;ref name=thompson &gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.variety.com/article/VR1117993747?refCatId=2508|title=Films up in the air after studios split|work=[[Variety]]|date=10/09/2008|first=Anne|last=Thompson|accessdate=18 de junho de 2011 }}&lt;/ref&gt;
| gross =  $221,600,000&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=The Adventures of Tintin|url=http://boxofficemojo.com/movies/?id=tintin.htm}}&lt;/ref&gt; 
}}
'''''The Adventures of Tintin''''' (also known as '''''The Adventures of Tintin: The Secret of the Unicorn'''''&lt;ref name=&quot;BBFC&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.bbfc.co.uk/AFF279229/|title=THE ADVENTURES OF TINTIN - THE SECRET OF THE UNICORN|publisher=BBFC|date=October 12, 2011|accessdate=November 2, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;) is a 2011 American [[performance capture]] [[3D film]] based on ''[[The Adventures of Tintin]]'', a series of comic books created by [[Belgium|Belgian]] artist [[Hergé|Hergé (Georges Remi)]]. Directed by [[Steven Spielberg]], produced by [[Peter Jackson]], and written by [[Steven Moffat]], [[Edgar Wright]] and [[Joe Cornish (comedian)|Joe Cornish]], the film is based on three of the original comic books: ''[[The Crab with the Golden Claws]]'' (1941), ''[[The Secret of the Unicorn]]'' (1943), and ''[[Red Rackham's Treasure]]'' (1944).&lt;ref name=empire/&gt;

Spielberg first acquired rights to produce a film based upon the ''Adventures of Tintin'' series following Hergé's death in 1983, and re-optioned them in 2002. Filming was due to begin in October 2008 for a 2010 release, but release was delayed to 2011 after [[Universal Studios|Universal]] opted out of producing the film with [[Paramount Pictures|Paramount]], who provided $30&amp;nbsp;million on pre-production. [[Sony Pictures Entertainment|Sony]] chose to co-produce the films. The delay resulted in [[Thomas Sangster]], who had been cast as Tintin, departing from the project. Producer Peter Jackson, whose company [[Weta Digital]] is providing the [[computer animation]], intends to direct a sequel. Spielberg and Jackson also hope to co-direct a third film.&lt;ref name=raiders/&gt;

The first press-screening was held on October 10, 2011 and the world première took place on October 22, 2011 in Brussels.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title=Tintin Has World Premiere In His Hometown|url=http://www.npr.org/templates/story/story.php?storyId=141619935|accessdate=2011-10-22|newspaper=NPR|date=2011-10-22|agency=Associated Press}}&lt;/ref&gt;  The film is set to be released in North American theaters on December 21, 2011 in [[Digital 3D]] and [[IMAX 3D|IMAX]].&lt;ref name=&quot;reldates&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.us.movie.tintin.com |title=The Adventures of Tintin Official Movie Site |publisher=Paramount Pictures |accessdate=2011-10-13}}&lt;/ref&gt; The release date in Australia is 26 December.

== Plot ==
Tintin, a young journalist, and his dog Snowy are browsing in an outdoor market in a European town. Tintin buys a model of a three-masted sailing ship, the [[Unicorn (ship)|Unicorn]], on the cheap, but is then immediately accosted by the sinister [[Ivan Ivanovitch Sakharine]], and the mysterious figure of Barnaby, who both try to buy the model from Tintin, without success. Tintin takes the ship home, but it is broken during a fight between Snowy and a neighbour's cat. As it breaks, a parchment scroll slips out of the ship's mast. Snowy spots it but is unable to alert Tintin. Meanwhile, incompetent detectives [[Thomson and Thompson]] are on the trail of a pickpocket, [[Aristides Silk]]. Tintin visits Sakharine in [[Marlinspike Hall]], where he learns that there are at least two model ships.

Later, Tintin is shot at, then abducted by accomplices of Sakharine, and imprisoned on the SS Karaboudjan. On board, Tintin escapes and meets the ship's nominal captain, Haddock. Haddock has been supplied with whisky by first mate Allan, who is working for Sakharine, and the captain is permanently drunk, and doesn't know what's happening on board his ship. Tintin and Haddock (and Snowy) eventually escape from the Karaboudjan in a lifeboat. Sakharine sends a [[seaplane]] to find them, but Tintin is able to capture the plane, and fly towards the (fictitious) Moroccan port of [[Settings in The Adventures of Tintin|Bagghar]], but they crash in the desert.

Dehydrated in the heat, and suffering from a sudden lack of alcohol, Haddock hallucinates, and starts to remember stories about his ancestor, Sir Francis Haddock(e), who was captain of the Unicorn during the 17th century. Sir Francis' treasure-laden ship was attacked by a pirate ship, led by the masked [[Red Rackham]], and, after a fierce battle and eventual surrender, Sir Francis chose to sink the Unicorn, and most of the treasure, rather than allow it to fall into Rackham's hands. It transpires that there were three models of the Unicorn, each containing a scroll. Together, the scrolls will reveal the location of the sunken Unicorn, and its treasure.

In Bagghar, Tintin and the Captain find out that the third model ship is in the possession of the wealthy [[Omar Ben Salaad]], but it is encased in a bullet-proof glass display case. Sakharine's plan is to stage a concert involving famous diva [[Bianca Castafiore]], the &quot;Milanese nightingale&quot;, whose penetrating singing voice will be able to shatter the glass case, allowing Sakharine's trained hawk to fly down and steal the third scroll. After a chase down to the harbour, pursued by Tintin and Haddock, Sakharine finally escapes with all three scrolls. Tintin chases him back to Europe and arranges a police reception for him on the dockside. Haddock and Sakharine, who is revealed to be the descendant of Red Rackham, replay their ancestors' swashbuckling sword fight, using dockside cranes, and Haddock is eventually victorious.

With the three scrolls in their possession, Tintin and Haddock find that the indicated location is Marlinspike Hall, and that the hall had been built originally by Sir Francis Haddock. There, in the cellar, they find some of the treasure, and a clue to the location of the sunken Unicorn.

== Cast ==
* [[Jamie Bell]] as [[Tintin (character)|Tintin]].&lt;ref name=pr&gt;{{cite news|title=Paramount Pictures and Sony Pictures Entertainment Announce the January&amp;nbsp;26 Start of Principal Photography on the 3D Motion Capture Feature 'The Adventures of Tintin: Secret of the Unicorn' Directed by Steven Spielberg and Starring Jamie Bell and Daniel Craig|publisher=[[PR Newswire]]|url=http://news.prnewswire.com/ViewContent.aspx?ACCT=109&amp;STORY=/www/story/01-26-2009/0004960578&amp;EDATE=|accessdate=January 26, 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt; Bell replaced [[Thomas Sangster]], who dropped out when filming was delayed in October 2008.&lt;ref name=delay/&gt; Jackson suggested Bell take on the role, having cast him as [[Jimmy (King Kong)|Jimmy]] in his ''[[King Kong (2005 film)|King Kong]]'' remake.&lt;ref name=dig/&gt;
* [[Andy Serkis]] as [[Captain Haddock]]. Serkis played [[Gollum]] in Jackson's [[The Lord of the Rings film trilogy|''The Lord of the Rings'']] and [[King Kong]] in the 2005 remake, which were both roles requiring [[motion capture]]. Serkis joked he was concerned that Jackson wanted him to play Tintin's dog Snowy,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title=The Cottage – Andy Serkis interview|work=indieLondon|year=2007|url=http://www.indielondon.co.uk/Film-Review/the-cottage-andy-serkis-interview|accessdate=September 4, 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt; who will be animated traditionally, i.e., without motion capture.&lt;ref name=raiders/&gt; Serkis remarked upon reading the comics again for the role that they had a surreal [[Monty Python|Pythonesque]] quality.&lt;ref name=go/&gt; Serkis also plays Haddock's ancestor [[Sir Francis Haddock]] in flashbacks.&lt;ref name=interpol&gt;{{cite news|author=Jay A. Fernandez, Borys Kit|title=Daniel Craig to star in &quot;Tintin&quot;|work=[[The Hollywood Reporter]]|date=January 27, 2009|url=http://www.hollywoodreporter.com/hr/content_display/news/e3ic323ae8a6486e91c8f3aab35cbff3722|accessdate=January 27, 2009}} {{Dead link|date=October 2010|bot=H3llBot}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[Simon Pegg]] and [[Nick Frost]] as [[Thomson and Thompson]], bumbling detectives who are almost identical. Spielberg invited Pegg to the set and offered him the role after he had completed ''[[How to Lose Friends &amp; Alienate People (film)|How to Lose Friends &amp; Alienate People]]''.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|author=Stephen Armstrong|title=Simon Pegg: He’s Mr Popular|work=The Sunday Times |location=UK|date=September 21, 2008|url=http://entertainment.timesonline.co.uk/tol/arts_and_entertainment/film/article4774264.ece|accessdate=September 21, 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt; Pegg also stars alongside Serkis in John Landis' [[Burke and Hare (film)|''Burke and Hare'']], released in Autumn 2010. Co-writer Edgar Wright, a long time collaborator with Pegg and Frost, is believed to have provided dialogue for their characters.
* [[Daniel Craig]] as [[List of The Adventures of Tintin characters#Sakharine|Ivan Ivanovitch Sakharine]] and [[Red Rackham]], Sakharine being the descendant of Red Rackham, the pirate who attacked the ''[[Unicorn (ship)|Unicorn]]'', the ship captained by Sir Francis Haddock.&lt;ref name=pr/&gt; Craig collaborated with Spielberg on ''[[Munich (film)|Munich]]'', Toby Jones in ''[[Infamous (film)|Infamous]]'' and Bell in ''[[Defiance (2008 film)|Defiance]]''.
* [[Tony Curran]] as Lieutenant Delacourt, an ally of Tintin.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|author=Barry Johnston|title=Scots star Tony Curran on his dream role in Spielberg's new Tintin movie|work=[[Daily Record (Scotland)|Daily Record]]|date=April 18, 2009|url=http://www.dailyrecord.co.uk/entertainment/showbiz-news/celebrity-interviews/2009/04/18/scots-star-tony-curran-on-his-dream-role-in-spielberg-s-new-tintin-movie-86908-21286945/|accessdate=April 23, 2009}} {{Dead link|date=October 2010|bot=H3llBot}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[Toby Jones]] plays [[Aristides Silk]], a pickpocket.&lt;ref name=interpol/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|author=Dominic Cavendish|title=Toby Jones takes the lead in Tom Stoppard's classic Every Good Boy Deserves Favour|work=The Daily Telegraph |location=UK|date=January 9, 2009|url=http://www.telegraph.co.uk/culture/culturecritics/dominiccavendish/4208197/Toby-Jones-takes-the-lead-in-Tom-Stoppards-classic-Every-Good-Boy-Deserves-Favour.html|accessdate=January 9, 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[Gad Elmaleh]] as [[Omar Ben Salaad]].&lt;ref name=interpol/&gt;
* [[Mackenzie Crook]] and [[Daniel Mays]] play Ernie and Allan, smugglers aboard the Karaboudjan.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|author=Baz Bamigboye|title=Baz Bamigboye on coffee with Jessica Alba, Tintin's secrets and school with Keira Knightley|work=Daily Mail |location=UK|date=March 6, 2009|url=http://www.dailymail.co.uk/tvshowbiz/article-1159822/Baz-Bamigboye-coffee-Jessica-Alba-Tintins-secrets-school-Keira-Knightley.html}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[Sebastian Roché]] as Pedro.
* [[Cary Elwes]] and [[Phillip Rhys]] appear as seaplane pilots.
* [[Ron Bottitta]] as Unicorn Lookout.

== Production ==
=== Development ===
Spielberg has been an avid fan of ''The Adventures of Tintin'' comic books, which he discovered in 1981 when a review compared ''[[Raiders of the Lost Ark]]'' to Tintin. His secretary bought him French-language editions of each book, but Spielberg did not have to understand them: he immediately fell in love with its art.&lt;ref name=raiders&gt;{{cite news | author=Ruben V. Nepales | title = Spielberg may co-direct next with Peter Jackson | work=[[Philippine Daily Inquirer]] | date = May 18, 2008 | url = http://showbizandstyle.inquirer.net/entertainment/entertainment/view/20080518-137261/Spielberg-may-co-direct-next-with-Peter-Jackson | accessdate=May 18, 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt; Meanwhile, the comics' creator [[Hergé]], who didn't like the previous live action film versions and the [[Hergé's Adventures of Tintin|cartoon]], became a fan of Spielberg. [[Michael Farr]], author of ''Tintin: The Complete Companion'', recalled Hergé &quot;thought Spielberg was the only person who could ever do Tintin justice&quot;.&lt;ref name=moguls&gt;{{cite news|author=Jeff Dawson|title=Tintin and the Movie Moguls?|work=The Sunday Times |location=UK|date=May 27, 2007|url=http://entertainment.timesonline.co.uk/tol/arts_and_entertainment/film/article1830463.ece|accessdate=September 3, 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt; Spielberg and his production partner [[Kathleen Kennedy (film producer)|Kathleen Kennedy]] of [[Amblin Entertainment]] were scheduled to meet with Hergé in 1983 while filming ''[[Indiana Jones and the Temple of Doom]]'' in London. Hergé died that week, but his widow decided to give them the rights.&lt;ref name=raiders/&gt; A three-year long option to film the comics was finalized in 1984,&lt;ref name=moguls/&gt; with Universal as distributor.&lt;ref name=uni/&gt;

Spielberg commissioned ''[[E.T. the Extra-Terrestrial]]'' writer [[Melissa Mathison]] to script a film where Tintin battles [[ivory]] hunters in Africa.&lt;ref name=moguls/&gt; Spielberg saw Tintin as &quot;[[Indiana Jones]] for kids&quot; and wanted [[Jack Nicholson]] to play Haddock.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://washingtontimes.com/news/2008/dec/29/culture-briefs-88727919/|work=The Washington Times |title=Culture Briefs|date=December 29, 2008|accessdate=December 31, 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt; Unsatisfied with the script, Spielberg continued with production on ''[[Indiana Jones and the Last Crusade]]''. The rights returned to the [[Hergé Foundation]]. [[Claude Berri]] and [[Roman Polanski]] became interested in filming the property, while [[Warner Bros.]] negotiated long and hard for the rights, but they could not guarantee the &quot;creative integrity&quot; that the Foundation found in Spielberg.&lt;ref name=moguls/&gt; In 2001, Spielberg revealed his interest in depicting Tintin with [[computer animation]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|author=Paul Davidson|title=Enfin, a Tintin Movie|work=[[IGN]]|date=August 29, 2001|url=http://uk.movies.ign.com/articles/305/305331p1.html|accessdate=September 3, 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt; In November 2002, his studio [[DreamWorks]] reestablished the option to film the series.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news | title = Tintin 'to become movie hero' |work=BBC News Online | date = November 22, 2002 | url = http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/entertainment/film/2502495.stm | accessdate=October 10, 2007}}&lt;/ref&gt; Spielberg said he would just produce the film.&lt;ref name=age&gt;{{cite news | author=Steve Head | url = http://movies.ign.com/articles/380/380514p1.html | title = An Interview with Steven Spielberg | work=[[IGN]] | date = December 17, 2002 | accessdate = June 30, 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt; In 2004, the French magazine ''[[Capital (French magazine)|Capital]]'' reported Spielberg was intending a trilogy based on ''Secret of the Unicorn'' / ''Red Rackham's Treasure'', ''[[The Seven Crystal Balls]]'' / ''[[Prisoners of the Sun]]'' and ''[[The Blue Lotus]]'' / ''[[Tintin in Tibet]]'' (which are not a single story, but both feature the [[Chang Chong-Chen]] character).&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|author=Paul Davidson|title=Spielberg Planning Tintin Trilogy?|work=[[IGN]]|date=January 14, 2004|url=http://uk.movies.ign.com/articles/463/463162p1.html|accessdate=September 3, 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt; By then, Spielberg had reverted to his idea of a live-action adaptation, and called [[Peter Jackson]] to ask if [[Weta Digital]] would create a computer-generated Snowy.&lt;ref name=empire&gt;{{cite news|title=News Etc.|work=[[Empire (magazine)|Empire]]|date=June 2009|pages=20–25}}&lt;/ref&gt;

{{Quote box|width=40%|quote=We're making them look photorealistic; the fibres of their clothing, the pores of their skin and each individual hair. They look exactly like real people – but real Herge people!|source=Peter Jackson explains the film's look&lt;ref name=real/&gt;}}

Jackson, a longtime fan of the comics,&lt;ref name=back&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.latimes.com/entertainment/news/movies/la-ca-tintinfilm22-2009mar22,0,603817.story?track=rss|title='Tintin' project brings moguls together|work=Los Angeles Times |date=March 22, 2009|author=Rachel Abramowitz|accessdate=March 23, 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt; had used [[motion capture]] in ''[[The Lord of the Rings film trilogy|The Lord of the Rings]]'' and ''[[King Kong (2005 film)|King Kong]]''. He suggested that a live action adaptation would not do justice to the comic books and motion capture was the best way of representing Hergé's world of Tintin.&lt;ref name=empire/&gt; A week of filming took place in November 2006 in [[Playa Vista, Los Angeles, California]], on the stage where [[James Cameron]] shot ''[[Avatar (2009 film)|Avatar]]''.&lt;ref name=future&gt;{{cite news|author=Sharon Waxman|title=Top Directors See the Future, and They Say It’s in 3-D|work=The New York Times |date=May 22, 2007|url=http://www.nytimes.com/2007/05/22/movies/22dime.html?_r=1&amp;ei=5070&amp;en=d97d3fc56f20c686&amp;ex=1183780800&amp;oref=slogin&amp;pagewanted=all|accessdate=September 4, 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Andy Serkis]] had been cast, while Jackson stood in for Tintin.&lt;ref name=go/&gt; Cameron and [[Robert Zemeckis]] were present during the shoot.&lt;ref name=empire/&gt; The footage was transmitted to [[Weta Digital]],&lt;ref name=future/&gt; who produced a twenty-minute test reel that demonstrated a photorealistic depiction of the characters.&lt;ref name=real/&gt; Spielberg said he would not mind filming it digitally because he saw it as an animated film, and reiterated his live action work would always be filmed traditionally.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|author=Eric Vespe|title=Holy Smoke!!! Quint visits with Steven Spielberg on the INDIANA JONES 4 set!!! Plus news on TINTIN &amp; TRANSFORMERS 2!!!|work=[[Ain't It Cool News]]|date=October 9, 2007|url=http://www.aintitcool.com/node/34376|accessdate=February 8, 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt;

An official announcement about the collaboration was made in May 2007, although both filmmakers had to wait to film it: Spielberg was preparing ''[[Indiana Jones and the Kingdom of the Crystal Skull]]'' and Jackson was planning ''[[The Lovely Bones (film)|The Lovely Bones]]''.&lt;ref name=real&gt;{{cite news |author=Pamela McClintock, [[Anne Thompson (film critic)|Anne Thompson]]|url = http://www.variety.com/article/VR1117964927.html?categoryid=13&amp;cs=1&amp;query=tintin |title = 	
Spielberg, Jackson team for Tintin |work=Variety  |date= May 14, 2007 |accessdate = May 24, 2007}}&lt;/ref&gt; In October 2007, [[Steven Moffat]] was announced as having signed on to write the screenplays for two of the ''Tintin'' films.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news | author=Carly Mayberry | title = Scribe Moffat on 'Tintin' case | work=[[The Hollywood Reporter]] | date = October 2, 2007 | url = http://www.hollywoodreporter.com/hr/content_display/news/e3ia426500233e132c7ae7d566d04f0282e | accessdate=October 2, 2007 |archiveurl = http://web.archive.org/web/20071018011523/http://www.hollywoodreporter.com/hr/content_display/news/e3ia426500233e132c7ae7d566d04f0282e &lt;!-- Bot retrieved archive --&gt; |archivedate = October 18, 2007}}&lt;/ref&gt; Moffat said he was &quot;[[love bombing|love bombed]]&quot; by Spielberg into accepting the offer to write the films, with the director promising to shield him from studio interference with his writing.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://entertainment.timesonline.co.uk/tol/arts_and_entertainment/film/article4072239.ece|title=Police deployed against paparazzi|author=John Harlow|work=The Times |location=UK|date=June 8, 2008|accessdate=June 12, 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt; Moffat finished the first script,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.dailymail.co.uk/tvshowbiz/article-1036567/500-000-Mr-Spielberg-Sorry-Ive-got-date-Beeb-says-new-Dr-Who-writer.html|title=£500,000 Mr Spielberg? Sorry, I've got a date with the Beeb, says the new Dr Who writer|work=Daily Mail |location=UK|author=Caroline Graham|date=July 19, 2008|accessdate=October 15, 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt; but could not complete the second because of the [[2007–2008 Writers Guild of America strike]]. He then became executive producer of ''[[Doctor Who]]'', leading Spielberg and Jackson (the latter of whom is a fan of the show) to allow him to leave and fulfil his duty to the series.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title=Dr Who writer denies Tintin row|work=BBC News Online |date=July 21, 2008|url=http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/entertainment/7517423.stm|accessdate=September 3, 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Edgar Wright]] and [[Joe Cornish (comedian)|Joe Cornish]] rewrote the script.&lt;ref name=pr/&gt;

More filming took place in March 2008.&lt;ref name=go&gt;{{cite news|title=Tintin a Go-go|work=[[Empire (magazine)|Empire]]|date=September 3, 2008|page=22}}&lt;/ref&gt; But in August 2008, a month before [[principal photography]] would have begun, [[Universal Studios|Universal]] turned down their option to co-produce the film, citing the low box office of ''[[Monster House (film)|Monster House]]'' and ''[[Beowulf (2007 film)|Beowulf]]'' as well as the directors' usual request for 30% of the gross. [[Paramount Pictures]] (DreamWorks' distributor) had hoped to partner with Universal on the project having spent $30&amp;nbsp;million on pre-production. Spielberg gave a ten-minute presentation of footage, hoping they would approve filming to begin in October. Paramount offered to produce if the directors opted out of their gross percentage deals: Spielberg and Jackson declined,&lt;ref name=delay&gt;{{cite news|author=Anne Thompson|title=Films up in the air after studios split|work=Variety |date=October 9, 2008|url=http://www.variety.com/article/VR1117993747.html?categoryid=2508&amp;cs=1|accessdate=October 15, 2008|authorlink=Anne Thompson (film critic)}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=uni&gt;{{cite news|author=Claudia Eller|title=Studio says no to Steven Spielberg, Peter Jackson|work=Los Angeles Times |date=September 19, 2008|url=http://www.latimes.com/business/la-fi-tintin19-2008sep19,0,5882061.story|accessdate=September 19, 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt; and negotiated with [[Sony Pictures Entertainment|Sony]] to co-finance and distribute the first film by the end of October.&lt;ref name=rivals&gt;{{cite news|author=Michael Cieply|title=Rivals in Talks to Finance ‘Tintin’ Films|work=The New York Times |date=November 1, 2008|url=http://www.nytimes.com/2008/11/01/business/media/01tintin.html?em|accessdate=November 1, 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=sony&gt;{{cite news | author=Anne Thompson | url = http://www.variety.com/article/VR1117995106 | title = Sony/Paramount financing 'Tintin' |work=Variety  | date = October 31, 2008 | accessdate = November 1, 2008 | authorlink = Anne Thompson (film critic)}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|author=Claudia Eller|title=Paramount and Sony might co-parent &quot;Tintin&quot;|work=Los Angeles Times |date=October 31, 2008|url=http://latimesblogs.latimes.com/entertainmentnewsbuzz/2008/10/paramount-and-s.html|accessdate=November 1, 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt; Sony only agreed to finance two films, though Jackson said a third film may still happen.&lt;ref name=empire/&gt;

=== Filming ===
Filming began on January 26, 2009, and the release date was moved from 2010 to 2011.&lt;ref name=pr/&gt; Spielberg finished his film – after 32 days of shooting – in March 2009. Jackson was present for the first week of filming and supervised the rest of the shoot via a bespoke [[videoconferencing]] program.&lt;ref name=back/&gt; Simon Pegg said Jackson's voice would &quot;be coming over the [[Tannoy]] like God.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|author=Nick Setchfield|title=Simon Pegg Exclusive|work=[[SFX magazine]]|date=April 1, 2009|url=http://www.sfx.co.uk/page/sfx?entry=simon_pegg_exclusive|accessdate=April 6, 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt; During filming, various directors including [[Guillermo del Toro]], [[Stephen Daldry]] and [[David Fincher]] visited. Spielberg would try to treat the film like live-action, moving his camera around.&lt;ref name=empire/&gt; He revealed, &quot;Every movie I made, up until ''Tintin'', I always kept one eye closed when I've been framing a shot,&quot; because he wanted to see the movie in 2-D, the way viewers would. &quot;On ''Tintin'', I have both of my eyes open.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|author=[[Josh Quittner]]|title=3-D: The Future of Movies|work=TIME|date=March 19, 2009|url=http://www.time.com/time/magazine/article/0,9171,1886541-2,00.html|accessdate=March 20, 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt; Jackson took the hands-on approach to directing Weta Digital during post-production, which Spielberg supervised through video conferencing. Jackson will also begin development for the second film for which he will be officially credited as director.&lt;ref name=dig&gt;{{cite news|author=Tatiana Siegel|title=Spielberg, Jackson dig into 'Tintin'|work=Variety |date=March 6, 2009|url=http://www.variety.com/article/VR1118000923.html|accessdate=March 7, 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt; Spielberg says &quot;there will be no cell phones, no TV sets, no modern cars. Just timeless Europe.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.darkhorizons.com/news/15831/spielberg-jackson-talk-more-tintin-/ Spielberg, Jackson Talk More &quot;Tintin&quot;]&lt;/ref&gt; His cinematographer [[Janusz Kamiński]] serves as lighting consultant for Weta, and Jackson said the film will look &quot;[[film noir]]ish, very atmospheric.&quot; Spielberg finished six weeks of additional motion-capture filming in mid-July.&lt;ref name=empire/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news | last = DiOrio | first = Carl | title = King of the motion capture | work=The Hollywood Reporter | date = July 16, 2009 | pages = 1, 13 | url = http://www.hollywoodreporter.com/hr/content_display/film/news/e3ia13021641b2079d289fc3dc3a2865694 | accessdate = September 6, 2009}} {{Dead link|date=October 2010|bot=H3llBot}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Release ==
[[File:Spielberg and Tintin 2011.jpg|thumb|[[Steven Spielberg]] at the film's [[premiere]] in Paris, 22 October 2011.]]
The first press-screening was held in Belgium on October 10, 2011.&lt;ref name=&quot;la libre&quot;&gt;{{cite web|title=Les Aventuriers de la Licorne Perdue|url=http://www.lalibre.be/culture/cinema/article/691191/les-aventuriers-de-la-licorne-perdue.html|publisher=La Libre|accessdate=October 12, 2011|language=French|date=October 12, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; The world première was held in [[Brussels]], Belgium on October 22, 2011, with the Paris première later the same day.&lt;ref name=&quot;DT&quot;&gt;{{cite web|title=Tintin fans flock to Belgian film premiere|url=http://www.telegraph.co.uk/culture/film/film-news/8844394/Tintin-fans-flock-to-Belgian-film-premiere.html|publisher=Daily Telegraph|accessdate=October 31, 2011|date=October 22, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; Sony released the film during late October and early November 2011 in Europe, Latin America, and India. The film is expected to be released in [[Quebec]] on December 9, 2011.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|last=Lauzon|first=François|title=Tintin to hit Quebec screens Dec. 9|url=http://www.montrealgazette.com/entertainment/movie-guide/Tintin+Quebec+screens/5606797/story.html|accessdate=October 26, 2011|newspaper=Montreal Gazette|date=October 26, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; Paramount will distribute the film in Asia, New Zealand, the UK and all other English-speaking territories. They will release the film in the United States on December 23, 2011.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title=The Adventures of Tintin Hits Theaters on Dec.&amp;nbsp;23, 2011|work=ComingSoon.net|date=May 29, 2009|url=http://www.comingsoon.net/news/movienews.php?id=55875|accessdate=May 29, 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.tintin-movie.net/international/ |title=Worldwide Release Dates |publisher=Paramount Pictures |accessdate=2011-05-25}}&lt;/ref&gt; Spielberg hopes that thereby there will be a word-of-mouth effect coming from Europe - where ''Tintin'' has always been a huge success - that will attract the American audience, which is unfamiliar with ''Tintin''.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Le reporter à la houppette est quasi inconnu en Amérique|url=http://www.7sur7.be/7s7/fr/1528/Cinema/article/detail/1333976/2011/10/14/Le-reporter-a-la-houppette-est-quasi-inconnu-en-Amerique.dhtml|publisher=7sur7|accessdate=October 26, 2011|language=French|date=October 14, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Box office===
On its first day, the film opened in the [[UK]], [[France]] and [[Belgium]], earning $8.5 million. In Belgium, Tintin's country of origin, the film made $510,000, while France provided $4.5 million, a number higher than other similar Wednesday débuts.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title=Steven Spielberg's 'Adventures of Tintin' Soaring in Overseas Debut|url=http://www.hollywoodreporter.com/news/steven-spielberg-tintin-box-office-254232|publisher=[[The Hollywood Reporter]]|first=Pamela|last=McClintock|accessdate=October 27, 2011|date=October 27, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; In France, it is the second best debut of the year for its first day after ''[[Harry Potter and the Deathly Hallows – Part 2]]''.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Tintin : Il démarre en fanfare|url=http://www.francesoir.fr/loisirs/cine/tintin-il-demarre-en-fanfarre-151156.html|publisher=France Soir|accessdate=October 27, 2011|language=French|date=October 27, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; On its first weekend it topped the overseas box office with $56.2 million from 21 countries. It earned the top spot in many major markets like France and the [[Maghreb]] region ($21 million) [where it set a record opening weekend for an animated title], the [[UK]], [[Ireland]] and [[Malta]] ($10.9 million), [[Spain]] ($6.67 million) and [[Germany]] ($4.8 million).&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title=Foreign Box Office: Spielberg's 'Adventures Of Tintin' Opens Solid No. 1 Overseas|url=http://www.hollywoodreporter.com/news/foreign-box-office-spielberg-adventures-tintin-255081|publisher=[[The Hollywood Reporter]]|first=Frank|last=Segers|accessdate=November 1, 2011|date=October 30, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; 

The movie grossed {{INRConvert|12|c}} within two weeks following its November 11, 2011 release in [[India]], making it Steven Spielberg's highest ever opening in India. The movie also released with over 350 prints, the highest ever for an animated film.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://timesofindia.indiatimes.com/entertainment/hollywood/news-interviews/Tintin-is-Spielbergs-biggest-Indian-opening/articleshow/10728044.cms |title=Tintin is Spielberg's biggest Indian opening! |publisher=[[The Times of India]] |date=14 November 2011 |accessdate=26 November 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=The adventures of Tin Tin was very steady|url=http://www.boxofficeindia.com/boxdetail.php?page=shownews&amp;articleid=3734&amp;nCat=|work=26 November 2011|publisher=BoxOfficeIndia.Com|accessdate=26 November 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Reception==
=== Critical reception===
The film currently scores 86% on [[Rotten Tomatoes]], the film review aggregate site.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|accessdate=November 16, 2011|url=http://www.rottentomatoes.com/m/the_adventures_of_tintin/|title=The Adventures of Tintin (2011)|publisher=Rotten Tomatoes }}&lt;/ref&gt; Belgian newspaper ''[[Le Soir]]''{{'}}s film critics Daniel Couvreur and Nicolas Crousse called the film &quot;a great popular adventure movie&quot;, stating &quot;[the film's] enthusiasm and childhood spirit are unreservedly infectious&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=On a vu Tintin : un grand film d'aventures populaire.|url=http://www.lesoir.be/culture/cinema/2011-10-11/on-a-vu-tintin-un-grand-film-d-aventures-populaire-869135.php|publisher=Le Soir|accessdate=October 11, 2011|author=Daniel Couvreur|coauthors=Nicolas Crousse|language=French|date=October 11, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; ''[[Le Figaro]]'' praised the film &quot;[which is] crammed with action, humor and suspense&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last=Delcroix|first=Olivier|title=On a vu Tintin, &quot;un grand ouf de soulagement&quot;|url=http://www.lefigaro.fr/cinema/2011/10/12/03002-20111012ARTFIG00467-on-a-vu-tintin-un-grand-ouf-de-soulagement.php|publisher=Le Figaro|accessdate=October 12, 2011|language=French|date=October 12, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; Jordan Mintzer of ''[[The Hollywood Reporter]]'' was also very positive about the film, describing it as &quot;a good ol' fashioned adventure flick that harkens back to the filmmaker's action-packed, tongue-in-cheek swashbucklers of the 1980s. Steven Spielberg's ''The Adventures of Tintin: The Secret of the Unicorn'' is a visually dazzling adaptation.&quot;. Comparing it to another film, Mintzer said ''Tintin'' has &quot;an altogether more successful [[Motion capture|mocap]] experience than earlier efforts like ''[[The Polar Express (film)|The Polar Express]]''&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last=Mintzer|first=Jordan|title=The Adventures of Tintin: The Secret of the Unicorn: Film Review|url=http://www.hollywoodreporter.com/review/spielberg-adventures-tintin-secret-unicorn-film-249116|work=The Hollywood Reporter|accessdate=October 17, 2011|date=October 16, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Variety (magazine)|''Variety'']] wrote &quot;Clearly rejuvenated by his collaboration with producer Peter Jackson, and blessed with a smart script and the best craftsmanship money can buy, Spielberg has fashioned a whiz-bang thrill ride that's largely faithful to the wholesome spirit of his source but still appealing to younger, Tintin-challenged [[Audience|auds]].&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last=Felperin|first=Leslie|title=Film reviews - The Adventures of Tintin: The Secret of the Unicorn|url=http://www.variety.com/review/VE1117946357/|work=Variety|accessdate=October 17, 2011|date=October 16, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; 

''[[La Libre Belgique]]'' was, however, a little less enthusiastic, its film critic Alain Lorfèvre calling the film &quot;a technical success, [with] a Tintin vivid as it should be [and] a somewhat excessive Haddock&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;la libre&quot; /&gt; ''[[The Guardian]]''{{'}}s Xan Brooks gave the film two stars out of five, stating: &quot;while the big set pieces are often exuberantly handled, the human details are sorely wanting. How curious that Hergé achieved more expression with his use of ink-spot eyes and humble line drawings than a bank of computers and an army of animators were able to achieve.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=The Adventures of Tintin: Review|url=http://www.guardian.co.uk/culture/2011/oct/16/tintin-adventures-secret-of-unicorn|publisher=The Guardian|accessdate=17 October 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; ''[[Blog Critics]]'' writer Ross Miller said, &quot;author Hergé's wonderfully bold and diverse array of characters are a mixed bag when it comes to how they've been translated to the big-screen&quot; and that while the mystery might be &quot;perfectly serviceable&quot; for the film, &quot;the execution of it at times feels languid and stodgy, like it's stumbling along from one eye-catching setpiece to the next.&quot; However, he summed it up as, &quot;an enjoyable watch with some spectacular set-pieces, lavish visuals and some fine motion-capture performances.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Movie Review: The Adventures of Tintin|url=http://blogcritics.org/video/article/movie-review-the-adventures-of-tintin/|publisher=BlogCritics|accessdate=26 October 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The author of a study of the Tintin books described Hollywood's treatment in this film of its characters and stories as &quot;truly execrable&quot;, especially in the way it ignores the books' key idea of inauthenticity. The themes of fakeness and phoniness and counterfeit that drive  many of the original plots are replaced in the film with messages that feel &quot;as though we have wandered into a seminar on monetisation through self-empowerment ... It's like making a biopic of Nietzsche that depicts him as a born-again Christian, or of Gandhi as a trigger-happy Rambo blasting his way through the Raj.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last=McCarthy|first=Tom|title=Tintin gets the Hollywood treatment|url=http://www.smh.com.au/entertainment/movies/tintin-gets-the-hollywood-treatment-20111031-1mrvy.html|publisher=The Sydney Morning Herald|accessdate=2011-11- 01}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Accolades===
The film received two nominations for the [[Satellite Awards]] for [[Satellite Award for Best Animated or Mixed Media Feature|Best Motion Picture, Animated or Mixed Media]] and [[Satellite Award for Best Adapted Screenplay|Best Adapted Screenplay]].&lt;ref&gt;http://www.pressacademy.com/award_cat/current-nominees/&lt;/ref&gt;

==Sequel==
Depending on the film's success, two more Tintin movies could be produced. The first of these was originally planned to be based on ''[[The Seven Crystal Balls]]'' and ''[[Prisoners of the Sun]]'',&lt;ref name=&quot;sequel mtv&quot;&gt;{{cite web|last=Wigler|first=Josh|title=Jackson To Direct ‘Tintin’ Sequel|url=http://movienight.mtv.ca/2011/10/peter-jackson-will-direct-tintin-sequel/|publisher=MTV|accessdate=October 26, 2011|date=October 26, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; however screenwriter [[Anthony Horowitz]] has since called this into question, suggesting these films would be the second sequel and another story would become the first sequel.&lt;ref name=&quot;Tintin 2: Horowitz says story 'still under discussion'&quot;&gt;{{cite web|last=Tim|first=Masters|title=Tintin 2: Horowitz says story 'still under discussion'|url=http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/entertainment-arts-15553417|publisher=BBC|accessdate=14 November, 2011|date=2 November 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; Peter Jackson also confirmed he will direct it once he has finished [[The Hobbit (2012 film)|''The Hobbit'']].&lt;ref name=&quot;sequel mtv&quot; /&gt; The second would be co-directed by Jackson and Spielberg. However, regarding those rumours Spielberg stated they had not talked about that.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Spielberg &amp; Jackson up for Tintin 2|url=http://www.google.com/hostednews/ukpress/article/ALeqM5h3_xl4gSAo2zIvTa56YnVrt2wWyA?docId=N0287381319628509028A|work=The Press Association|publisher=Google|accessdate=October 26, 2011|date=Spielberg &amp; Jackson up for Tintin 2}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Video game ==
A video game entitled ''[[The Adventures of Tintin: The Secret of the Unicorn (video game)|The Adventures of Tintin: The Secret of the Unicorn ]]'' has been released to coincide with the release date of the film. Game developer/editor [[Ubisoft]] acquired the rights.&lt;ref name=Ubisoft&gt;{{cite news | author=Rob Crossley | title = Ubisoft to develop Spielberg’s Tintin| date = June 2, 2009 | url = http://www.develop-online.net/news/32040/Ubisoft-to-develop-Spielbergs-Tintin | accessdate=October 28, 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Gameloft]] released a game for [[iOS (Apple)|iOS]] devices to coincide with the film's European launch.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | work = IGN | title = First Look: The Adventures of Tintin (iOS) | date = August 17, 2011 | url = http://uk.wireless.ign.com/articles/118/1188418p1.html | accessdate=August 17, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==See also==
* [[The Adventures of Tintin (TV series)|''The Adventures of Tintin'' (TV series)]]

== References ==
{{Reflist|2}}

== External links ==
* {{Official website|http://www.us.movie.tintin.com}}
* {{IMDb title|0983193|The Adventures of Tintin}}
* {{rotten-tomatoes|the_adventures_of_tintin|The Adventures of Tintin}}
* {{Bcdb title|110709|The Adventures of Tintin}}
* [http://www.tintinologist.org/guides/screen Guide to other screen adaptations of ''Tintin''] at Tintinologist.org

{{Tintin and Hergé}}
{{Steven Spielberg}}
{{Peter Jackson}}
{{Nickelodeon Movies}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Adventures Of Tintin: Secret Of The Unicorn}}
[[Category:2011 films]]
[[Category:2010s 3D films]]
[[Category:2010s fantasy films]]
[[Category:Computer-animated films]]
[[Category:American films]]
[[Category:English-language films]]
[[Category:Films directed by Steven Spielberg]]
[[Category:Screenplays by Steven Moffat]]
[[Category:Tintin films]]
[[Category:Treasure hunt films]]
[[Category:Children's fantasy films]]
[[Category:Paramount Pictures films]]
[[Category:Amblin Entertainment films]]
[[Category:The Kennedy/Marshall Company films]]
[[Category:Nickelodeon films]]
[[Category:WingNut Films productions]]
[[Category:Performance capture in film]]

[[bn:দি অ্যাডভেঞ্চার্স অফ টিনটিন (চলচ্চিত্র)]]
[[ca:Les aventures de Tintín: El secret de l'Unicorn]]
[[cs:Tintinova dobrodružství (film)]]
[[da:Tintin: Enhjørningens hemmelighed]]
[[de:Die Abenteuer von Tim und Struppi – Das Geheimnis der Einhorn]]
[[es:Las aventuras de Tintín: el secreto del Unicornio]]
[[fa:ماجراهای تن‌تن (فیلم)]]
[[fr:Les Aventures de Tintin : Le Secret de La Licorne]]
[[id:The Adventures of Tintin: Secret of the Unicorn]]
[[is:Ævintýri Tinna (kvikmynd)]]
[[it:Le avventure di Tintin - Il segreto dell'Unicorno]]
[[he:הרפתקאותיו של טינטין: סודו של חד הקרן]]
[[nl:The Adventures of Tintin: The Secret of the Unicorn]]
[[ja:タンタンの冒険/ユニコーン号の秘密]]
[[pl:Przygody Tintina (film)]]
[[pt:As Aventuras de Tintim: O Segredo do Licorne]]
[[ro:Aventurile lui Tintin: Secretul Licornului]]
[[ru:Приключения Тинтина: Тайна «Единорога»]]
[[fi:Tintin seikkailut: Yksisarvisen salaisuus]]
[[sv:Tintins äventyr: Enhörningens hemlighet]]
[[tr:Tenten'in Maceraları (film)]]
[[uk:Пригоди Тінтіна: Таємниця «Єдинорога»]]
[[zh:丁丁历险记：独角兽号的秘密]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
