<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="17908647" ns="0" title="Foresight Linux"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Infobox OS
| name = Foresight
| logo = [[Image:Foresight Linux Logo.png|200px]]
| screenshot = [[File:Foresight-linux-2.1.1-with-GNOME-about-dialog.png|300px]]
| caption = The Foresight Linux 2.1.1 desktop with [[GNOME]] 2.26.1
| website = [http://www.foresightlinux.org/ www.foresightlinux.org]
| developer = Foresight Community
| family = [[Linux]]
| source_model = Mixed source
| latest_release_version = ([[Rolling release]]) 2.5.0
| latest_release_date = {{release date and age|2011|3|27}}
| latest_test_version =
| latest_test_date =
| marketing_target =
| language =
| kernel_type = [[Monolithic kernel|Monolithic]] ([[Linux kernel|Linux]])
| ui = [[GNOME]], [[KDE]], [[XFCE]]
| license =
| working_state = Current
| supported_platforms = [[IA-32]], [[x86-64]]
| updatemodel = [[PackageKit]] [http://www.packagekit.org/] (gnome-packagekit)
| package_manager = [[Conary (package manager)|Conary]]
}}
'''Foresight Linux''' is an [[operating system]] comprising [[free software|free]] and [[proprietary software]] with the stated{{Citation needed|date=February 2010}} goal of showcasing the latest in Linux desktop technologies. Foresight is developed by the Foresight community and follows a [[rolling release]] cycle, instead of a time based release schedule.

== History ==
Foresight was created by Ken VanDine as a [[Linux distribution]] to showcase the most current releases of [[GNOME]] while working on the GNOME Marketing team.&lt;ref name=&quot;Creating the GNOME 2.18 Live Media: An interview with Ken VanDine&quot;/&gt;

Since then it has undergone change through generally minor revisions (via rolling release). This is in contrast to the system of major changes with each version number employed by many other distributions. However, there have been occasional major changes, most notably the transition from Foresight 1.x to Foresight 2. Along the way several original deficiencies have been cured as well, among them the lack of 64 bit support, which was introduced in Foresight 2, and the lack of a graphical package manager, which was filled by [[PackageKit]].

After the release of Foresight 2, the developers held a packaging contest within the community in order to boost the number of applications available for the new release, either by porting them from Foresight 1, or packaging them afresh. The contest was sponsored by [[Shuttle Inc.]], Foresight's OEM partner, in the form of computers (Shuttle's KPC) and peripherals for the winners.&lt;ref name=&quot;Foresight Contest Announcement&quot;/&gt; Though originally planned to last one month, the contest was extended to two near the end of the first so that a greater number of packages could be completed. The process of testing all of the completed packages {{as of  | 2009
| alt=is currently underway}}, and no official announcements have been made as to the winner.

While originally a GNOME-based distribution, from version 2.5.0 [[XFCE]] and [[KDE]] desktops have been introduced.

Foresight was the recipient of the Ovatio Award for 2008 ''Distro of the Year'' by Ars Technica.&lt;ref name=&quot;The 2008 Ovatio Awards, by Ars Technica&quot;/&gt;

== Features ==

Foresight focuses on delivering the latest in desktop technologies. It usually has current packages for the GNOME desktop environment, sometimes even within a day of their release. Projects such as [[GNOME Do]], [[Banshee (media player)|Banshee]] and [[PackageKit]] are delivered in the default Foresight installation. Beyond the existing GNOME Edition, Xfce and KDE Edition are available. These two editions have the same focus of delivering the latest desktop technologies for the respective desktop environments.

Foresight uses the [[Conary (package manager)|Conary]] package management system. This system only updates those specific files in packages which need to be updated, in contrast to other package managers such as [[RPM Package Manager|RPM]] and [[dpkg]] which install whole packages. Conary also has the advantage of very granular dependency resolution, and a relatively easy packaging process, with [[Software repository|repositories]] provided to the community, free of charge, by [[RPath|rPath, Inc.]]

All packages are updated in a rolling release style, i.e. as updates are released upstream, or packagers get to them. Packages move between three branches of the foresight repositories, originating usually at the development branch or in the personal repositories of packagers, after which they are promoted to the Quality Assurance branch, and finally to the Stable branch, intended for users. [[Snapshot (computer storage)|Snapshots]] are taken every few months, and new [[ISO image]]s are produced.

== Vendor support ==
Foresight is available pre-installed on the [[Shuttle Inc.|Shuttle]]'s light-weight KPC system.&lt;ref name=&quot;KPC Specifications&quot;/&gt;

==References==
{{reflist|refs=
&lt;ref name=&quot;Creating the GNOME 2.18 Live Media: An interview with Ken VanDine&quot;&gt;{{ cite web |title = Creating the GNOME 2.18 Live Media: An interview with Ken VanDine |url = http://www.gnomejournal.org/article/57/creating-the-gnome-218-live-media-an-interview-with-ken-vandine }}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Foresight Contest Announcement&quot;&gt;{{ cite web |title = Foresight Contest Announcement |url = http://www.foresightlinux.org/contest.html }}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;The 2008 Ovatio Awards, by Ars Technica&quot;&gt;{{ cite web |title = The 2008 Ovatio Awards, by Ars Technica |url = http://arstechnica.com/articles/culture/ars-awards-2008.ars/7 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;KPC Specifications&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url=http://us.shuttle.com/KPC/techspecs.html |title=KPC Specifications |accessdate=2008-05-26 |publisher=[[Shuttle Inc.]] |archiveurl = http://web.archive.org/web/20080518034750/http://us.shuttle.com/KPC/techspecs.html &lt;!-- Bot retrieved archive --&gt; |archivedate = 2008-05-18}}&lt;/ref&gt;
}}

== External links ==
* [http://www.foresightlinux.org/ Project home page]
* [http://us.shuttle.com/kpc/index.htm Shuttle KPC home page]

{{Linux-distro}}

[[Category:Conary-based Linux distributions]]
[[Category:X86-64 Linux distributions]]

[[de:Foresight Linux]]
[[es:Foresight Linux]]
[[fr:Foresight Linux]]
[[ko:포어사이트 리눅스]]
[[it:Foresight Linux]]
[[nl:Foresight Linux]]
[[ja:Foresight Linux]]
[[pl:Foresight Linux]]
[[pt:Foresight Linux]]
[[ro:Foresight Linux]]
[[sv:Foresight Linux]]
[[tr:Foresight Linux]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
