<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="17929761" ns="0" title="Esperanza Spalding"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{pp-semi|small=yes}}
{{Infobox musical artist &lt;!-- See Wikipedia:WikiProject Musicians --&gt;
| name         = Esperanza Spalding
| image        = Esperanza spalding.jpg
| caption      = Spalding performing at the [[Newport Jazz Festival]] on August 10, 2008
| image_size   = &lt;!--Only for images smaller than 220px! --&gt;
| background   = solo_singer
| Born         = {{Birth date and age|1984|10|18}}&lt;br /&gt;[[Portland, Oregon]], [[United States|U.S.]]
| genre        = [[Jazz]], [[jazz fusion]], [[bossa nova]], [[neo soul]]
| occupation   = [[Musician]], [[composer]], [[educator]], [[bandleader]]
| instrument   = [[Singing|Vocals]], [[Double bass|upright bass]], [[bass guitar]], [[violin]], [[oboe]], [[clarinet]]
| years_active = 2000-present&lt;ref name=BERKLEE_PRESS_JUL142003&gt;Balkin, Nicholas (July 14, 2003). - [http://www.berklee.edu/opi/2003/0714.html &quot;Jazz at the Fort: Press Release&quot;]. - Berklee College of Music. Retrieved 2011-02-17.&lt;/ref&gt;
| associated_acts = [[Stanley Clarke]], [[Patti Austin]], Noise for Pretend
| label        = [[Heads Up International]], [[Hush Records|Hush]], [[Merge Records|Merge]]
| website      = {{URL|http://www.esperanzaspalding.com/}}
}}

'''Esperanza Spalding''' (born October 18, 1984)&lt;ref name=ibn-110214/&gt; is an [[United States|American]] [[multi-instrumentalist]] best known as a [[jazz]] [[bassist]] and [[singer]], who draws upon many genres in her own compositions. In 2011, she won the [[Grammy Award for Best New Artist]] at the [[53rd Grammy Awards]],&lt;ref name=2011Grammy&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.grammy.com/NOMINEES |title=Nominees and Winners |publisher=GRAMMY.com |date= |accessdate=2011-08-17}}&lt;/ref&gt; making her the first jazz artist to win the award.&lt;ref name=&quot;IBT&quot;&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.ibtimes.com/articles/112385/20110215/spalding-has-made-history-in-winning-best-new-artist-award.htm|title=Spalding has made history for winning best new artist award|last=Allen|first=Floyd|date=February 14, 2011|work=International Business Times|accessdate=2011-02-15}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://smoothjazzbuzz.wordpress.com/2011/02/14/esperanza-spalding-has-won-the-grammy®-award-for-best-new-artist/ Esperanza Spalding has won the GRAMMY® Award for Best New Artist]. ''Smooth Jazz Buzz''. February 14, 2011. Retrieved 2011-02-15.&lt;/ref&gt;

==Early life and early education==
Spalding grew up in the [[King, Portland, Oregon|King neighborhood]] of [[Portland, Oregon]],&lt;ref name=BancudM-TPT-2001-12-14&gt;{{cite news|last=Bancud|first=Michaela|date=December 14, 2001|title=Esperanza in the Wings|url=http://thevig.portlandtribune.com/features/story.php?story_id=8102|newspaper=[[Portland Tribune]]|accessdate=2011-02-14}}&lt;/ref&gt; a neighborhood she describes as &quot;[[ghetto]]&quot; and &quot;pretty scary&quot;.&lt;ref name=Jazzreview&gt;Symister-Masterson, Cheryl K., (September 2006). - [http://www.jazzreview.com/article/review-4970.html &quot;Esperanza Spalding: It's Natural&quot;]. - ''[[Jazz Review]]''.&lt;/ref&gt; Her mother raised her and her brother as a single parent.&lt;ref name=official&gt;[http://www.esperanzaspalding.com/cms/?page_id=10 &quot;Biography&quot;]. - Esperanza Spalding Official Web Site.&lt;/ref&gt;

Spalding has a diverse ethnic background.&lt;ref name=Jazzreview/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Ramírez, Deborah (August 14, 2008). &quot;Touching Bass - Jazz Phenom Sings, Plays and Talks Norah Jones&quot;. ''[[South Florida Sun-Sentinel]]''.&lt;/ref&gt; She notes, &quot;My mom is Welsh, Hispanic, and Native American, and my father is black.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;X-Factor BassPlayer&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.bassplayer.com/article/only-24-jazz/may-08/35479|title=At Only 24, Jazz Phenom Esperanza Spalding Has the Ultimate 'X-Factor'|last=Booth|first=Philip |year=2009 |work=Bass Player|publisher=New Bay Media, LLC|accessdate=2010-06-28}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=PCOLPopmatters&gt;Morales, Ed (June 23, 2008). [http://www.popmatters.com/pm/article/esperanza-spaldings-debut-picks-up-where-jazz-fusion-of-the-1970s-left-off &quot;Esperanza Spalding's debut picks up where jazz fusion of the 1970s left off&quot;]. PopMatters.com.&lt;/ref&gt; She also has an interest in the music of other cultures, including that of [[Brazil]],&lt;ref name=CarpenterE-TNYT-2008-07-27&gt;Carpenter, Ellen (July 27, 2008). [http://www.nytimes.com/2008/07/27/fashion/27nite.html &quot;Up to Her Ears: A Night Out with Esperanza Spalding&quot;]. ''[[The New York Times]]''.&lt;/ref&gt; commenting, &quot;With [[Portuguese people|Portuguese]] songs the phrasing of the melody is intrinsically linked with the language, and it’s beautiful&quot;.&lt;ref name=Booth&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.bassplayer.com/article/esperanza-spalding/dec-06/24264 |title=Esperanza Spalding |accessdate=2008-06-13 |last=Booth |first=Philip |year=2006 |month=December |work=Bass Player }}&lt;/ref&gt;

Her mother shares Spalding's interest in music, having nearly become a touring singer herself.&lt;ref name=official /&gt;&lt;ref name=PenaT-ES-JM-2008-05-28&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.jazz.com/features-and-interviews/2008/5/28/in-conversation-with-esperanza-spalding |title=In Conversation with Esperanza Spalding |accessdate=2008-06-13 |last=Peña |first=Tomas |coauthors=Spalding, Esperanza |date=2008-05-28 |work=Jazz Magazine (c/o Jazz.com)}}&lt;/ref&gt; But while Spalding cites her mother as a powerful influence who encouraged her musical expansion, she attributes her inspiration for pursuing a life in music to watching classical [[cello|cellist]] [[Yo-Yo Ma]] perform on an episode of ''[[Mister Rogers’ Neighborhood]]'' when she was four.&lt;ref name=official/&gt;

By the time Spalding was five, she had taught herself to play the [[violin]] and was playing with the Chamber Music Society of Oregon.&lt;ref name=official/&gt; Spalding stayed with the Chamber Music Society of Oregon until she was fifteen and left as concertmaster.&lt;ref name=official/&gt; Due to a lengthy illness when she was child, Spalding spent much of her [[elementary school]] years being [[Homeschooling|homeschooled]],&lt;ref name=official/&gt; but also attended King Elementary School in Northeast Portland.&lt;ref name=BancudM-TPT-2001-12-14 /&gt; During this time she also found the opportunity to pick up instruction in music by listening to her mother's college teacher instruct her mother in [[guitar]].&lt;ref name=Booth /&gt; According to Spalding, when she was about 8 her mother briefly studied jazz guitar in college; Spalding says, &quot;Going with her to her class, I would sit under the piano. Then I would come home and I would be playing her stuff that her teacher had been playing.&quot;&lt;ref name=Booth/&gt; Spalding also played [[oboe]] and [[clarinet]] before discovering the [[double bass|bass]] in high school.&lt;ref name=official/&gt;&lt;ref name=leggett/&gt; She is able to sing in English, Spanish and Portuguese.&lt;ref&gt;Dickens, Tad (February 4, 2009). &quot;Pop, Funk and All That Jazz&quot;. ''[[The Roanoke Times]]''.&lt;/ref&gt;

==Discovering the bass==
[[File:Esperanza Spalding2.jpg|thumb|right|250px|Spalding performing at the [[Umbria Jazz Festival]] in Perugia, Italy on July 12, 2007]]
Spalding had intended to play [[cello]],&lt;ref name=Booth/&gt; but discovered the bass during a one-year stint at age 14 at the prestigious performing arts high school, [[The Northwest Academy]], to which she had won a scholarship.&lt;ref name=Murphy&gt;Murphy, Sarah (April 2004). - [http://www.berklee.edu/profiles/spalding.html &quot;Esperanza Spalding&quot;]. - Berklee College of Music.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=DeBarrosP-TST-2008-01-15&gt;De Barros, Paul (January 15, 2008). &quot;A Hopeful Outlook for Jazz - Esperanza Spalding&quot;. ''[[The Seattle Times]]''.&lt;/ref&gt; The school was not a good fit, but the bass was.&lt;ref name=Murphy/&gt; Spalding found high school &quot;easy – and boring&quot; and dropped out. When asked in 2008 why she plays the bass instead of some other instrument, Spalding said that it wasn't a choice, but the bass &quot;had its own arc&quot; and resonated with her.&lt;ref name=Knight&gt;Knight, Nokware (July 30, 2008). [http://blog.nu-soulmag.com/?p=234 &quot;Esperanza Spalding Interview&quot;]. ''Nu-Soul Magazine''.&lt;/ref&gt; Spalding says that for her discovering the bass was like &quot;waking up one day and realizing you’re in love with a co-worker&quot;.&lt;ref name=Booth/&gt; By the time she randomly picked up the bass in music class and began experimenting with it, she had grown bored with her other instruments.&lt;ref name=Murphy/&gt;&lt;ref name=norris&gt;{{cite news |first=Michele |last=Norris |authorlink=Michele Norris |title=Esperanza Spalding: Voice of the Bass |url=http://www.npr.org/templates/story/story.php?storyId=90478162 |format=radio |work=[[All Things Considered]] |publisher=[[National Public Radio]] |date=2008-05-15 |accessdate=2008-06-13 }}&lt;/ref&gt; Her band teacher showed her a blues line for the bass which she later used to secure her first gig.&lt;ref name=Murphy/&gt; After that, she went in to play the bass daily and gradually fell in love.&lt;ref name=Booth/&gt;

When she was 15 or 16 years old, Spalding started writing lyrics for music for the local indie rock/pop group Noise for Pretend, touching on any topic that came to mind.&lt;ref name=Knight/&gt; Although she had taken a few private voice lessons which taught her how to protect her voice, her primary singing experience had come from &quot;singing in the shower&quot;, she said,&lt;ref name=Knight/&gt; before she started performing vocals for Noise for Pretend.&lt;ref name=Booth/&gt; Her desire to perform live evolved naturally out of the compositional process, when she would sing and play simultaneously to see how melody and voice fit together, but she acknowledges that performing both roles can be challenging.&lt;ref name=Booth/&gt;&lt;ref name=PCOLAmoeblog&gt;Billyjam (June 27, 2008). [http://www.amoeba.com/blog/2008/06/jamoeblog/amoeblog-interview-with-esperanza-spalding.html &quot;Amoeblog Interview with Esperanza Spalding&quot;]. Amoeblog.&lt;/ref&gt; In a 2008 interview, she said, &quot;[W]hat can be difficult is being a singer, in the sense that you are engaged with the audience, and really responsible for emoting, and getting into the lyrics, melody, etc and being an effective bassist/band leader.&quot;&lt;ref name=PCOLAmoeblog /&gt;

==Education and career==
Spalding left high school at 16 and, after completing her [[General Educational Development|GED]], enrolled on a music scholarship in the music program at [[Portland State University]], where she remembers being &quot;the youngest bass player in the program.&quot;&lt;ref name=official/&gt; Although she lacked the training of her fellow students, she feels that her teachers nevertheless recognized her talent.&lt;ref name=official/&gt; She decided to instead apply to [[Berklee College of Music]] on the encouragement of her bass teacher, and did well enough in her audition to receive a full scholarship.&lt;ref name=PenaT-ES-JM-2008-05-28 /&gt;&lt;ref name=Murphy/&gt; In spite of the scholarship, Spalding found it a challenge meeting living expenses, so her friends arranged a benefit concert that paid her airfare and a little extra.&lt;ref name=Booth/&gt;&lt;ref name=Murphy/&gt;

Spalding's savings did not last long. Broke and exhausted,&lt;ref name=Humprhies&gt;Humphries, Stephen (May 30, 2008). [http://www.csmonitor.com/2008/0530/p15s01-almp.html &quot;Jazz prodigy Esperanza Spalding, still eager to teach – and learn&quot;]. ''[[The Christian Science Monitor]]''.&lt;/ref&gt; she considered leaving music and entering political science,&lt;ref name=PenaT-ES-JM-2008-05-28 /&gt; a move jazz guitarist and composer [[Pat Metheny]] discouraged, telling Spalding she had &quot;the 'X Factor'&quot; and could make it if she applied herself.&lt;ref name=PenaT-ES-JM-2008-05-28 /&gt; During her time at Berklee, her primary bass instructor was John Lockwood.{{Citation needed|date=February 2011}}

===Touring===
Spalding had begun performing live in clubs in Portland, Oregon as a teenager,&lt;ref name=CarpenterE-TNYT-2008-07-27 /&gt; securing her first gig at 15 in a blues club when she could only play one line on bass.&lt;ref name=Murphy/&gt; One of the seasoned musicians with which she played that first night invited her to join the band's rehearsals &quot;so she could actually learn something&quot;, and her rehearsals soon grew into regular performances spanning almost a year.&lt;ref name=Murphy/&gt; According to Spalding, it was a chance for her to stretch as a musician, reaching and growing beyond her experience.&lt;ref name=Booth/&gt; Her early contact with these &quot;phenomenal resources&quot;, as she calls the musicians who played with her,&lt;ref name=Booth/&gt; fostered her sense of rhythm and helped nurture her interest in her instrument.&lt;ref name=Murphy/&gt;

[[Patti Austin]] hired Spalding to tour with her internationally after Spalding's first semester at Berklee,&lt;ref name=Murphy/&gt; where Spalding supported the singer on the [[Ella Fitzgerald]] tribute tour &quot;For Ella&quot;.&lt;ref name=Booth/&gt; In 2008, Spalding recalled the tour as educational, helping her learn to accompany a vocalist and also how to sustain energy and interest playing the same material nightly.&lt;ref name=Booth/&gt; She continued to perform with Austin periodically for three years.&lt;ref name=Booth/&gt; During the same period, while at Berklee, Spalding studied under saxophonist [[Joe Lovano]] before eventually touring with him.&lt;ref name=Booth/&gt; They began as a trio, expanding into a quartet before joining quintet US5 and traveling across the United States from New York to California.&lt;ref name=Booth/&gt;

She does not consider herself a musical prodigy.&lt;ref name=Knight/&gt; &quot;I am surrounded by prodigies everywhere I go, but because they are a little older than me, or not a female, or not on a major label, they are not acknowledged as such,&quot; says Spalding.&lt;ref name=Knight/&gt;

===Teaching===
Spalding was the 2005 recipient of the Boston Jazz Society scholarship for outstanding musicianship.&lt;ref name=official/&gt; Almost immediately after graduation from college later the same year, Spalding was hired by [[Berklee College of Music]], becoming one of the youngest professors in the institution's history,&lt;ref name=booth&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.bassplayer.com/article/only-24-jazz/may-08/35479 |title=At Only 24, Jazz Phenom Esperanza Spalding Has The Ultimate 'X-Factor' |accessdate=2008-06-13 |last=Booth |first=Philip |year=2008 |month=May |work=Bass Player }}&lt;/ref&gt; at age 20.&lt;ref name=&quot;''EarlyShow'' &quot;Grooves&quot;&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=ZNw46j0nNOs&amp;feature=related|title=Esperanza Spalding, &quot;Grooves&quot;|date=August 23, 2008|work=The Early Show's &quot;The Second Cup Café&quot; television programme|publisher=CBS|accessdate=28 June 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; As a teacher, Spalding tries to help her students focus their practice through a practice journal which can help them recognize their strengths and what they need to pursue.&lt;ref name=Booth/&gt; As of 2008, she was also in the process of developing several courses for students at Berklee, including one that focuses &quot;on transcribing as a tool for learning harmony and theory&quot;.&lt;ref name=Booth/&gt; Since that time, Spalding currently lives in [[Austin, Texas|Austin]], [[Texas]].&lt;ref name=ColapintoJ-TO-&gt;{{cite web|last=Colapinto |first=John |url=http://www.newyorker.com/reporting/2010/03/15/100315fa_fact_colapinto |title=The populist jazz of Esperanza Spalding |publisher=The New Yorker |date=2009-01-07 |accessdate=2011-08-17}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Solo records and collaborations===
[[File:Esperanze Spalding at North Sea Jazz 2009.jpg|left|thumb|200|Spalding performing at the Northsea Jazz Festival, 2009]]
Spalding has recorded three albums ''[[Junjo]]'' (2006), ''[[Esperanza (Esperanza Spalding album)|Esperanza]]'' (2008) and ''[[Chamber Music Society]]'' (2010).&lt;ref name=Knight/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |first=Doug |last=Levine |title=Debut Album Shows Off Esperanza Spalding's Multiple Talents |date=May 27, 2008 |publisher=Voice of America |url=http://voanews.com/english/archive/2008-05/2008-05-27-voa77.cfm |work=VOA News |accessdate=2009-01-03}}&lt;/ref&gt; The first was created to display the dynamic that she felt among her trio.&lt;ref name=Knight/&gt; Though ''Junjo'' was released solely under her name, Spalding considers it &quot;a collaborative effort.&quot;&lt;ref name=Booth/&gt; With ''Esperanza'', Spalding's material was meant to be more reflective of herself as an artist, with musicians selected to best present that material.&lt;ref name=Knight/&gt; Ed Morales wrote in [[PopMatters]] on June 23, 2008 that ''Esperanza'' is &quot;a sprawling collage of jazz fusion, Brazilian and even a touch of hip-hop.&quot;&lt;ref name=PCOLPopmatters/&gt; Siddhartha Mitter wrote in ''[[The Boston Globe]]'' on May 23, 2008 that &quot;the big change&quot; in ''Esperanza'' &quot;is the singing..... This makes [''Esperanza''] a much more accessible album, and in some ways more conventional.&quot;&lt;ref name=PCOLBostonglobe&gt;Mitter, Siddhartha (May 23, 2008). - [http://www.boston.com/ae/music/articles/2008/05/23/making_a_statement &quot;Making a statement: Bassist Spalding adds lyrics to her many jazz talents&quot;]. - ''[[The Boston Globe]]''.&lt;/ref&gt; In ''Chamber Music Society'', inspiration from her earlier days as a concertmaster is apparent in her fusion of three-piece string ensemble with piano, keyboards, drums and percussion. As Patrick Jarenwattananon wrote for [[NPR Music]], &quot;the finished product certainly exudes a level of sophisticated intimacy, as if best experienced with a small gathering in a quiet, wood-paneled room.&quot;&lt;ref name=PCOLNPR&gt;Jarenwattananon, Patrick (August 8, 2010). - [http://www.npr.org/templates/story/story.php?storyId=129003770 &quot;First Listen: Esperanza Spalding, 'Chamber Music Society'&quot;]. - ''[[NPR Music]]''. Retrieved 2011-02-16&lt;/ref&gt;

In addition to these albums, Spalding has collaborated with [[Fourplay]], [[Stanley Clarke]], [[Christian Scott]], [[Donald Harrison]], [[Joe Lovano]], [[Niño Josele]], Nando Michelin, and Theresa Perez.&lt;ref name=PCOLAmoeblog/&gt;

Spalding collaborated with Tineke Postma on the track &quot;Leave Me A Place Underground&quot; from the album ''The Dawn Of Light'' in 2011.&lt;ref name=TheDawnOfLight&gt;Challenge Records (March 2011). [http://www.challenge.nl/product/1291373451 &quot;Tineke Postma - The Dawn Of Light&quot;]&lt;/ref&gt;

Her next project, scheduled for release in late 2011, is an album currently titled ''Radio Music Society'', which she hopes will showcase jazz musicians in an accessible manner suitable for mainstream radio.&lt;ref name=&quot;GrammyWin&quot; /&gt; She plans to record ''Radio Music Society'' in May. With ''Radio Music Society'', she hopes to incorporate her own musical compositions with covers of such artists as the [[Beach Boys]] and [[Wayne Shorter]]. She also plans to record an album with [[Milton Nascimento]] in the future.&lt;ref&gt;Graff, Gary (March 1, 2011). - [http://www.billboard.com/news/esperanza-spalding-to-record-radio-music-1005051982.story#/news/esperanza-spalding-to-record-radio-music-1005051982.story &quot;Esperanza Spalding to Record 'Radio Music Society' Album in May&quot;]. - ''[[Billboard Magazine]]''. Retrieved 2011-04-28&lt;/ref&gt; In February 2011, she released a vinyl version of her ''[[Chamber Music Society]]'' album which included a bonus track titled &quot;Morning&quot; that will be included on her new ''Radio Music Society'' album.&lt;ref&gt;Gerson, Robbie (June 8, 2011). - [http://www.audaud.com/article.php?ArticleID=9009 &quot;Grammy award winning artist releases breakthrough album on vinyl&quot;]. - ''Audiophile Audition''. Retrieved 2011-07-3&lt;/ref&gt;

==Critical reception==
[[Gary Burton]], Executive Vice President at Berklee, said in 2004 that Spalding had &quot;a great time feel, she can confidently read the most complicated compositions, and she communicates her upbeat personality in everything she plays.&quot;&lt;ref name=Murphy/&gt;
Ben Ratliff wrote in ''[[The New York Times]]'' on July 9, 2006 that Spaldings voice is &quot;light and high, up in [[Blossom Dearie]]'s pitch range, and she can sing quietly, almost in a daydream&quot; and that Spalding &quot;invents her own feminine space, a different sound from top to bottom.&quot;&lt;ref name=PCOLBenratliff&gt;Ratliff, Ben (July 9, 2006). [http://www.nytimes.com/2006/07/09/arts/music/09play.html &quot;Suite for Gas Pump and Coffin Lid&quot;]. ''[[The New York Times]].&lt;/ref&gt;

Ratliff wrote in ''The New York Times'' again, two years later, on May 26, 2008 that one of Spalding's central gifts is &quot;a light, fizzy, optimistic drive that's in her melodic bass playing and her elastic, small-voiced singing&quot; but that &quot;the music is missing a crucial measure of modesty.&quot;&lt;ref name=PCOLRatliff&gt;Ratliff, Ben (May 26, 2008). [http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E05E0DC1430F935A15756C0A96E9C8B63 &quot;Critics' Choice; That Ladies' Man With Some New Lines&quot;]. ''[[The New York Times]]''.&lt;/ref&gt; He added, &quot;It's an attempt at bringing this crisscrossing [of [[Stevie Wonder]] and [[Wayne Shorter]]] to a new level of definition and power, but its vamps and grooves are a little obvious, and it pushes her first as a [[singer-songwriter]], which isn't her primary strength.&quot;&lt;ref name=PCOLRatliff/&gt;
[[Pat Metheny]] said in 2008 it was immediately obvious &quot;that she had a lot to say and was also unlike any musician I had ever run across before. Her unique quality is something that goes beyond her pretty amazing musical skills; She has that rare 'x' factor of being able to transmit a certain personal kind of vision and energy that is all her own.&quot;&lt;ref name=Humprhies /&gt;

Andrés Quinteros wrote in the Argentinian periodical, ''26Noticias'' on October 28, 2008 that Spalding is one of the greatest new talents on the jazz scene today.&lt;ref name=PCOL26notcias&gt;Quinteros, Andrés (October 28, 2008).[http://www.26noticias.com.ar/esperanza-spalding-y-su-jazz-en-buenos-aires-77286.html &quot;Esperanza Spalding y su jazz en Buenos Aires&quot;]. - ''26Noticias''. - {{es}}.&lt;/ref&gt;

In February 2011, at the [[53rd Grammy Awards]], Spalding won the &quot;Best New Artist&quot; award.&lt;ref name=&quot;GrammyWin&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://music-mix.ew.com/2011/02/14/esperanza-spalding-best-new-artist|title=Esperanza Spalding: Who is the surprise Best New Artist? |last=Vozick-Levinson|first=Simon|date=February 14, 2011|work=[[Entertainment Weekly]]|accessdate=2011-02-15}}&lt;/ref&gt; In November 2011, Spalding won &quot;Jazz Artist of the Year&quot; at the [[Boston Music Awards]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.allaboutjazz.com/php/news.php?id=90004|title=Esperanza Spalding Wins Jazz Artist of the Year at Boston Music Awards |last=|first=|date=November 22, 2011|work=allaboutjazz.com|accessdate=2011-11-28}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Influences and attitude toward music and jazz==
Spalding cites jazz bassists [[Ron Carter]] and [[Dave Holland]] as important influences on her music; Carter for the &quot;orchestration&quot; of his playing and Holland for the way his compositional method complements his personal style.&lt;ref name=Booth/&gt; She has described the saxophone player [[Wayne Shorter]],&lt;ref name=PenaT-ES-JM-2008-05-28 /&gt; and singer-songwriter [[Milton Nascimento]], as heroes.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=uk-oJGAXSjA/ |title=&quot;Chamber Music Society: The Making Of&quot; |publisher=Youtube.com |date= |accessdate=2011-08-17}}&lt;/ref&gt; She has also noted her preference for the [[music of Brazil]].&lt;ref name=PenaT-ES-JM-2008-05-28 /&gt;

Spalding says she loves [[Fusion (music)|fusion music]] and was influenced by a &quot;wonderful arc that started 40 years ago where people kept incorporating modern sounds into their music.&quot;&lt;ref name=PCOLPopmatters/&gt; She has expressed concerns that jazz has wandered from its roots, suggesting that jazz has lost its street value and its relevance to &quot;the Black experience to the Black Diaspora and beyond&quot; now that has been co-opted by the &quot;seasoned 'art' community.&quot;&lt;ref name=Jazzreview/&gt; She notes that in its early days, jazz was &quot;popular dance music&quot; and &quot;the music of young people who considered themselves awfully hip&quot;, and believes &quot;[[hip-hop]], or [[neo-soul]] ... is our 'jazz' now as far as the role these genres play in the music genre lineage....&quot;&lt;ref name=Jazzreview/&gt;

[[File:Nobel Peace Price Concert 2009 Esperanza Spalding1.jpg|thumb|170px|right|Spalding performing on December 10, 2009 at the [[Nobel Peace Prize|Nobel Peace Prize Concert]] of 2009]]
Spalding, who has expressed a desire to be judged for her musicianship rather than her sex appeal, believes that female musicians must take responsibility to avoid oversexualizing themselves.&lt;ref name=PCOLPopmatters/&gt;&lt;ref name=PenaT-ES-JM-2008-05-28 /&gt; and that in order to write original music, one must read and stay informed about the world.&lt;ref name=PenaT-ES-JM-2008-05-28 /&gt; She has said she models her career on those of [[Madonna (entertainer)|Madonna]] and [[Ornette Coleman]].&lt;ref name=&quot;booth&quot;/&gt;

==Performances==
Some of Spalding's high-profile performances include:
;2009 Nobel Peace Prize Ceremony and Concert
On December 10, at the 2009 [[Nobel Peace Prize]] ceremonies, Spalding performed at Oslo City Hall in honor of the 2009 Laureate [[President of the United States|President]] [[Barack Obama]] and again at the [[Nobel Peace Prize Concert]] the following day. She was personally selected by Obama, as per the tradition of one laureate-invited-artist to perform.&lt;ref name=&quot;NYT-surprise&quot;&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.nytimes.com/2011/02/15/arts/music/15grammy.html?_r=1&amp;hpw|title=CRITIC’S NOTEBOOK; Esperanza Spalding Is a Surprise Winner at the Grammys|last=Chinen|first=Nate|date=February 15, 2011|work=The New York Times|accessdate=2011-02-15}}&lt;/ref&gt;

;2009 Park City Jazz Festival
Spalding also was the featured final act for the opening night of the 2009 [[Park City Jazz Festival]] in [[Park City, Utah|Park City]], [[Utah]], one of the top jazz festivals in the country. She closed the show with a number along with bass artists [[Brian Bromberg]] and Sean O'Bryan Smith, who also performed earlier that day.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://blog.parkcity.tv/2009/05/pc-jazz-fest-announces-lineup.html|title=Notes from PCTV: PC Jazz Fest Announces Lineup|date=May 4, 2009|publisher=Park City TV|accessdate=2011-02-15}}&lt;/ref&gt;

;2010 BET Awards
As a tribute to [[Prince (musician)|Prince]], Spalding was invited to sing along with [[Patti LaBelle]], [[Alicia Keys]], and [[Janelle Monáe]]. Spalding performed the 1987 hit single &quot;[[If I Was Your Girlfriend]].&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;NYT-surprise&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://gossiponthis.com/2010/06/28/patti-labelle-janelle-monae-esperanza-spalding-prince-bet-awards/|title=Patti Labelle, Janelle Monae &amp; Esperanza Spalding Honor Lifetime Achievement Award Winner Prince with Tribute Performances at the 2010 BET Awards|date=June 28, 2010|publisher=GossipOnThis.com|accessdate=2011-02-15}}&lt;/ref&gt;

;2010 Austin City Limits (PBS-TV)
On February 7, 2010, Spalding became the most searched person and second most searched item on [[Google Search|Google]] as a result of her appearance the previous evening on the [[Public Broadcasting Service|PBS]] television program ''[[Austin City Limits]]''.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.insidelux.com/2010/02/07/esperanza-spalding-the-trediest-artist-according-to-google/ &quot;InsideLux: Esperanza Spalding: The trendiest artist according to Google&quot;], February 7, 2010&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://video.pbs.org/video/1397474775/ &quot;Austin City Limits: Esperanza Spalding / Madeleine Peyroux (Full Episode)&quot;], ''[[Austin City Limits]]'', PBS, February 5, 2010&lt;/ref&gt;

;2011 Roots Picnic
On June 4, 2011, Spalding performed at The Roots Picnic in Philadelphia, sharing the stage with The Roots, Nas and Wiz Khalifa.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|author=Ngozi Odita |url=http://www.societyhae.com/video/esperanza-spaldingthe-roots |title=The Roots Picnic: Esperanza Spaulding performance and interview |publisher=Societyhae.com |date=2010-12-15 |accessdate=2011-08-17}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Discography==
===Solo albums===
{| class=&quot;wikitable&quot;
|-
!Original release date
!Album
!Label
|-
|April 18, 2006
|''[[Junjo]]''&lt;ref group=&quot;n&quot;&gt;Accompanied by Cuban pianist and drummer.&lt;/ref&gt;
|Ayva Music
|-
|May 20, 2008
|''[[Esperanza (Esperanza Spalding album)|Esperanza]]''&lt;ref group=&quot;n&quot; name=&quot;ex02&quot;&gt;Accompanied by flamenco guitar guitarist [[Niño Josele]], percussionist [[Jamey Haddad]], drummer [[Horacio Hernandez|Horacio &quot;El Negro&quot; Hernández]], saxophonist Donald Harrison and others.&lt;/ref&gt;
|Heads Up International
|-
|August 17, 2010
|''[[Chamber Music Society]]''
|Heads Up International
|-
|Q1 2012
|''Radio Music Society''&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web| last = Reich| first = Howard| title = Can Esperanza Spalding lure new audiences to jazz?| work = [[The Chicago Tribune]]| date = October 4, 2011| url = http://www.chicagotribune.com/entertainment/music/ct-ent-1005-esperanza-spalding-20111005,0,6377603.column?page=2| accessdate = October 10, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|Heads Up International
|}

====Notes====
&lt;references group=&quot;n&quot;/&gt;

===With Noise for Pretend===
{| class=&quot;wikitable&quot;
|-
!Original release date
!Album
!Label
|-
|October 30, 2001
|''Blanket Music/Noise For Pretend''
|[[Hush Records]]
|-
|July 2, 2002
|''Happy You Near''
|[[Hush Records]]
|}

===With Stanley Clarke===
{| class=&quot;wikitable&quot;
|-
!Original release date
!Album
!Label
|-
|October 16, 2007
|''The Toys of Men''
|[[Heads Up International]]
|}

===With Nando Michelin===
{| class=&quot;wikitable&quot;
|-
!Original release date
!Album
!Label
|-
|November 21, 2006
|''Duende''
|Fresh Sound New Talent
|-
|January 4, 2010
|''Reencontro''
|Blue Music Group
|}

===With M. Ward===
{| class=&quot;wikitable&quot;
|-
!Original release date
!Album
!Label
|-
|March 18, 2003
|''Transfiguration of Vincent''
|[[Merge Records]]
|}

===With Mike Stern===
{| class=&quot;wikitable&quot;
|-
!Original release date
!Album
!Label
|-
|August 11, 2009
|''[[Big Neighborhood]]''
|[[Heads Up International]]
|}

==References==
{{reflist|30em|refs=
&lt;ref name=leggett&gt;{{cite web |url={{Allmusic|class=artist|id=p514023/biography|pure_url=yes}} |title=Biography |accessdate=2008-06-13 |last=Leggett |first=Steve |work=[[Allmusic]] |publisher=[[All Media Guide]] }}&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;ref name=ibn-110214&gt;{{cite web|url=http://ibnlive.in.com/news/esperanza-spalding-10-things-you-didnt-know/143321-19.html|title=Esperanza Spalding: 10 things you didn't know|date=February 14, 2011|publisher=[[IBN]]|accessdate=May 1, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;
}}

==Further reading==
* Murphy, Sarah, [http://www.berklee.edu/profiles/spalding.html &quot;Student Profile: Esperanza Spalding&quot;], Berklee College of Music, April 2004
*{{cite journal |last=Colapinto |first=John |authorlink=John Colapinto |date=March 15, 2010 |title=Profiles: New Note |journal=[[The New Yorker]] |volume=86 |issue=4 |pages=32–39|url=|accessdate=}}

==External links==
{{commons category}}
* [http://esperanzaspalding.com/ Official website]
* [http://interviews.onthegig.com/2010/10/esperanza-spalding-jazz-bassist.html Esperanza Spalding interview for OnTheGig.com]
* [http://www.allaboutjazz.com/php/news.php?id=28671 Esperanza Spalding interview for allaboutjazz.com]
* [http://www.thestar.com/entertainment/music/grammys/article/938328--who-is-esperanza-spalding-and-how-did-she-beat-justin-bieber?bn=1 Who is Esperanza Spalding and how did she beat Justin Bieber?] - includes interview for Billboard.com (2011).
* [http://www.societyhae.com/video/esperanza-spaldingthe-roots VIDEO: Esperanza Spalding Performance and Interview at The Roots Pinic (2011)]

{{s-start}}
{{s-ach}}
{{succession box
| title = [[Grammy Award for Best New Artist]]
| before = [[Zac Brown Band]]
| after = ''incumbent''
| years = 2011
}}
{{s-end}}
{{Grammy Award for Best New Artist}}

&lt;!-- Metadata: see [[Wikipedia:Persondata]] --&gt;
{{Persondata
|NAME = Spalding, Esperanza
|ALTERNATIVE NAMES =
|SHORT DESCRIPTION = Bassist, singer
|DATE OF BIRTH = October 18, 1984
|PLACE OF BIRTH = [[Portland, Oregon]]
|DATE OF DEATH =
|PLACE OF DEATH =
}}
{{DEFAULTSORT:Spalding, Esperanza}}
[[Category:1984 births]]
[[Category:African American musicians]]
[[Category:American jazz double-bassists]]
[[Category:American jazz singers]]
[[Category:American musicians of Mexican descent]]
[[Category:Berklee College of Music alumni]]
[[Category:Berklee College of Music faculty]]
[[Category:Grammy Award winners]]
[[Category:Living people]]
[[Category:Musicians from Portland, Oregon]]
[[Category:Women in jazz]]

[[de:Esperanza Spalding]]
[[es:Esperanza Spalding]]
[[fr:Esperanza Spalding]]
[[it:Esperanza Spalding]]
[[hu:Esperanza Spalding]]
[[nl:Esperanza Spalding]]
[[ja:エスペランサ・スポルディング]]
[[pl:Esperanza Spalding]]
[[pt:Esperanza Spalding]]
[[ru:Сполдинг, Эсперанса]]
[[sv:Esperanza Spalding]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
