<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="17930296" ns="0" title="List of starships in Stargate"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Over detailed|date=August 2011}}
{{Non-free|date=March 2011}}&lt;!--See [[Wikipedia:Non-free content#Non-free image use in list articles]]. Screenshots of space battles such as in &quot;Camelot&quot; show more than one type of ship and can lower the number of non-free images here significantly without sacrificing quality.--&gt;
{{Multiple issues
| in-universe=February 2010
| primarysources=February 2010
}}

This is a list of '''starships in the ''[[Stargate]]'' franchise'''.

{{TOC limit|2}}
==Ancient starships==
The [[Ancient (Stargate)|Ancients]] are one of the most technologically advanced races in ''Stargate'', and this is reflected in their starships. Duplicates of these ships are utilized by their nanite creations, the [[Asuran]]s, as they also possess knowledge of Ancient technology.

===Gateship===
[[Image:Puddlejumper.jpg|thumb|A gateship in motion.]]
A '''gateship''', commonly referred by its nickname '''puddle jumper''' (usually just &quot;jumper&quot;),&lt;ref name=&quot;Rising&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;The Return&quot;&gt;{{sgcite|The Return|Atlantis|show=ref}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Moebius&quot;&gt;{{sgcite|Moebius|show=ref}}&lt;/ref&gt; is a small spacecraft created by the [[Ancient (Stargate)|Ancients]]. Several of these ships are located in [[Atlantis (Stargate)|Atlantis]], and are used by the [[Atlantis Expedition]] to travel to other planets. The nickname &quot;puddle jumper&quot; was coined by [[John Sheppard (Stargate)|John Sheppard]] in {{sgcite|Rising|Atlantis}}. Gateships are cylindrical ships with an angled front and rear that can fit through a Stargate. The interior is divided in two parts, cockpit and aft section; the bulkhead door between the two is airtight and can hold even against the pressure of deep ocean.&lt;ref name=&quot;Grace Under Pressure&quot;&gt;{{sgcite|Grace Under Pressure|Atlantis|show=ref}}&lt;/ref&gt; Access to the jumper is provided by a rear ramp-hatch. Gateships have built-in [[DHD]]s that can dial Stargates in both the Milky Way and in Pegasus.&lt;ref name=&quot;Rising&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Moebius&quot;/&gt; The original cockpit console from the first season was made out of [[plexiglass]],&lt;ref&gt;[[Peter DeLuise]] in the audio commentary for &quot;[[Moebius (Stargate SG-1)|Moebius (Part 2)]]&quot;&lt;/ref&gt; while different console designs are seen in later seasons. As with many pieces of Ancient technology, operating a gateship requires the [[ATA gene]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Rising&quot;/&gt; Commands can be given mentally,&lt;ref name=&quot;Moebius&quot;/&gt; or by using physical controls. Information is given to the pilot via a [[holographic]] [[Head-up display|HUD]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Rising&quot;/&gt;

During normal flight, a gateship is propelled by two sublight engine pods that extend from the hull; these pods are retracted when the ship is landed or needs to move through a Stargate.&lt;ref name=&quot;Thirty-Eight Minutes&quot;&gt;{{sgcite|Thirty-Eight Minutes|Atlantis|show=ref}}&lt;/ref&gt; Jumpers can operate underwater.&lt;ref name=&quot;Grace Under Pressure&quot;/&gt; They have inertial dampers that negate [[g-force]]s inside,&lt;ref name=&quot;Suspicion&quot;&gt;{{sgcite|Suspicion|Atlantis|show=ref}}&lt;/ref&gt; which can also be used to change the ship's weight.&lt;ref name=&quot;The Storm&quot;&gt;{{sgcite|The Storm|Atlantis|show=ref}}&lt;/ref&gt; After having his mind enhanced by an Ancient device, [[Rodney McKay]] developed an experimental hyperdrive for the gateships; though he left the work unfinished, research was later completed.&lt;ref name=&quot;Tao of Rodney&quot;&gt;{{sgcite|Tao of Rodney|Atlantis|show=ref}}&lt;/ref&gt; The modified jumper is used to steal a [[ZPM]] from Asuras, though the hyperdrive has a range of only 2,000 light-years and McKay believed they would be lucky to complete two jumps in it.&lt;ref name=&quot;Adrift&quot;&gt;{{sgcite|Adrift|Atlantis|show=ref}}&lt;/ref&gt; Gateships are armed with [[drone weapon]]s housed in two retractable pods forward of the engines. They normally do not have shields, but are equipped with a [[cloaking device]] to evade enemies which renders the ship effectively invisible to both the eye and most sensors.&lt;ref name=&quot;Rising&quot;/&gt; A gateship's cloaking generator can be set to create a shield instead, but this drains the gateship's power very quickly.&lt;ref name=&quot;Grace Under Pressure&quot;/&gt; McKay has also modified the cloaking generator to generate an [[Ancient technology in Stargate#Replicator Disruptor|Replicator disruptor field]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Lifeline&quot;&gt;{{sgcite|Lifeline|Atlantis|show=ref}}&lt;/ref&gt; Gateships used by the Atlantis Expedition are stocked with Earth equipment, including various weapons, emergency supplies, and tools.&lt;ref name=&quot;Thirty-Eight Minutes&quot;/&gt; The Ancient, Janus, created at least two gateships capable of traveling through time.&lt;ref name=&quot;Before I Sleep&quot;&gt;{{sgcite|Before I Sleep|Atlantis|show=ref}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;It's Good To Be King&quot;&gt;{{sgcite|It's Good To Be King|show=ref}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===''Aurora''-class battleship===
[[Image:Orion hyperspace (No Man's Land).jpeg|thumb|The ''Orion'' prepares to enter hyperspace.]]
The '''''Aurora''-class battleship'''&lt;ref name=&quot;Inferno&quot;&gt;{{sgcite|Inferno|Atlantis|show=ref}}&lt;/ref&gt; is a warship used by the [[Ancient (Stargate)|Ancients]] at the time of their war with the [[Wraith (Stargate)|Wraith]],&lt;ref name=&quot;Progeny&quot;&gt;{{sgcite|Progeny|Atlantis|show=ref}}&lt;/ref&gt; first seen in {{sgcite|Aurora|Atlantis}}. In that episode, the ''Aurora'' is a crippled battleship whose crew have preserved themselves in stasis pods, which self-destructs to avoid falling into the hands of the Wraith. The [[Atlantis Expedition]] gains control of an ''Aurora''-class battleship discovered by the Taranians in {{sgcite|Inferno|Atlantis}}; it is named ''Orion'' by [[John Sheppard (Stargate)|John Sheppard]] (who dislikes its original name ''Hippaforalkus''). The ''Orion'' is barely operational when it is called upon to intercept two [[#Hive ship|Wraith hive ship]]s heading for Earth. Maj. [[Evan Lorne|Lorne]] commands the &quot;Orion&quot; at this point. Dr. [[Radek Zelenka|Zelenka]] brings the weapons online at the cost of the shields, and the ''Orion'' manages to destroy one hive ship before being destroyed herself.&lt;ref name=&quot;No Man's Land&quot;/&gt; The battleship ''Tria'' is encountered along with its Ancient crew in {{sgcite|The Return|Atlantis}}. The Travelers take control of a derelict battleship with Sheppard's help in {{sgcite|Travelers|Atlantis}}.&lt;ref name=&quot;Travelers&quot;&gt;{{sgcite|Travelers|Atlantis|show=ref}}&lt;/ref&gt; Later destroyed as a result of a stargate explosion in episode {{sgcite|The Lost Tribe|Atlantis}}.&lt;ref name=&quot;The Lost Tribe&quot;&gt;{{sgcite|The Lost Tribe|Atlantis|show=ref}}&lt;/ref&gt; In season 4, it is revealed that the [[Asuran]]s have built 38 ''Aurora''-class battleships for their war with the Wraith. The ''Daedalus'' and the ''Apollo'' destroyed a few of them, and the rest are destroyed in the explosion of Asuras. Another battleship is known to exist, was commanded by a duplicate [[Elizabeth Weir (Stargate)|Elizabeth Weir]].&lt;ref name=&quot;This Mortal Coil&quot;&gt;{{sgcite|This Mortal Coil|Atlantis|show=ref}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Be All My Sins Remember'd&quot;&gt;{{sgcite|Be All My Sins Remember'd|Atlantis|show=ref}}&lt;/ref&gt; which was dismantled to create a base in an ill fated attempt to engineer their way to ascension {{sgcite|Ghost in the Machine|Atlantis}}

''Aurora''-class battleships are much larger than an Earth ''Daedalus''-class battlecruiser and are substantially superior to Wraith hive ships. They are armed with [[drone weapon]]s and are protected by energy shields.&lt;ref name=&quot;No Man's Land&quot;&gt;{{sgcite|No Man's Land|Atlantis|show=ref}}&lt;/ref&gt; Large turrets line the ship, which are seen in action in &quot;[[Be All My Sins Remember'd]]&quot;. They have intergalactic hyperdrives though they are not designed for such long trips,&lt;ref name=&quot;Aurora&quot;&gt;{{sgcite|Aurora|Atlantis|show=ref}}&lt;/ref&gt; and their sublight engines can accelerate the ship to 99.9% of the [[speed of light]]&lt;ref name=&quot;The Return&quot; /&gt; if powered by a [[Zero Point Module]].&lt;ref name=&quot;The Return&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Spoils of War&quot;&gt;{{sgcite|Spoils of War|Atlantis|show=ref}}&lt;/ref&gt; The ship can project [[hologram]]s remotely for communication purposes.&lt;ref name=&quot;The Return&quot;/&gt; They contain numerous stasis pods, which can be connected to allow the crew to interact in a virtual environment.&lt;ref name=&quot;Aurora&quot; /&gt; The ship has hangar bays that can accommodate [[puddle jumper (Stargate)|puddle jumper]]s&lt;ref name=&quot;Be All My Sins Remember'd&quot;/&gt; or [[Wraith dart]]s.&lt;ref name=&quot;Search and Rescue&quot;&gt;{{sgcite|Search and Rescue|Atlantis|show=ref}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===City ship===
[[Image:Ancient City Ship.jpg|thumb|An Asuran city ship in space over Lantea.]]
{{Main|Atlantis (Stargate)}}
An '''Ancient city ship''' is a city-sized spaceship constructed by the [[Ancient (Stargate)|Ancients]]. The best-known Ancient city ship is [[Atlantis (Stargate)|Atlantis]], once the Ancients' capital in the Pegasus galaxy and the main setting for ''Stargate Atlantis''. The Ancients abandoned Atlantis 10,000 years ago due to Wraith attacks; the city resided at the bottom of the ocean on Lantea until it is occupied by the [[Atlantis Expedition]] from Earth in {{sgcite|Rising|Atlantis}}. A city ship is a snowflake-shaped platform dotted with buildings, with an internal volume comparable to every building in [[Manhattan]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Hot Zone&quot;&gt;{{sgcite|Hot Zone|Atlantis|show=ref}}&lt;/ref&gt; They are powered by three [[Zero Point Module]]s.&lt;ref name=&quot;Rising&quot;&gt;{{sgcite|Rising|Atlantis|show=ref}}&lt;/ref&gt; The main defensive systems of a city ship are [[drone weapon]]s,&lt;ref name=&quot;The Siege&quot;&gt;{{sgcite|The Siege|Atlantis|show=ref}}&lt;/ref&gt; and an all-encompassing shield.&lt;ref name=&quot;The Storm&quot; /&gt; The massive ventral stardrive allows city ships to launch into space and traverse galaxies via hyperspace.&lt;ref name=&quot;Rising&quot;/&gt; The city itself is not airtight, so its shield must be active during space flight to hold in the atmosphere.&lt;ref name=&quot;Adrift&quot; /&gt; City ships carry a complement of smaller ships, dubbed &quot;[[puddle jumper (Stargate)|puddle jumpers]]&quot; by John Sheppard.&lt;ref name=&quot;Rising&quot;/&gt; The Atlantis Expedition has discovered a multitude of advanced technologies on Atlantis, including long-range sensors,&lt;ref name=&quot;The Brotherhood&quot;&gt;{{sgcite|The Brotherhood|Atlantis|show=ref}}&lt;/ref&gt; internal transporters,&lt;ref name=&quot;Hide and Seek&quot;&gt;{{sgcite|Hide and Seek|Atlantis|show=ref}}&lt;/ref&gt; and sophisticated computer systems.&lt;ref name=&quot;Hot Zone&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;The Siege&quot;/&gt;

In {{sgcite|The Tower|Atlantis}}, the Atlantis team discovers a second city ship on another planet. Although largely buried with much of its structure collapsed except for the central spire, some systems are still operational and the city's drone weapons and puddle jumpers are transferred to Atlantis. The [[Asuran]]s were created in a city ship that was leveled when the Ancients deemed their experiment a failure. The Asurans rebuilt the ship, and in {{sgcite|Progeny|Atlantis}} it is launched by [[Oberoth]] to attack Atlantis. The city ship is destroyed over Lantea when the Atlantis team overload its [[ZPM]]s. Another Asuran city ship, a duplicate of Atlantis created by [[Asuran#Rebels|Niam's followers]], appears in {{sgcite|This Mortal Coil|Atlantis}} and in a prescient vision in {{sgcite|The Seer|Atlantis}}. It is destroyed by an ''Aurora''-class battleship sent by Oberoth.

===''Destiny''===
[[Image:SGU Destiny ep5.jpg|thumb|The ''Destiny'' as it approaches a star in the episode &quot;[[List of Stargate Universe episodes#ep5|Light]]&quot;.]]
{{See also|Stargate Universe}}
''Stargate Universe'' is set aboard the Ancient ship ''Destiny'', a massive vessel which was part of an Ancient experiment to seed the galaxies with [[Stargate (device)|Stargates]] millions of years ago. Their plan to return to the ship after it finished its journey never came about due to their [[ascension (Stargate)|ascension]]. The ship was sent on auto-pilot, preceded by other automated ships which seeded the habitable worlds along its route with Stargates. It uses an unidentified form of superluminal propulsion, said to be faster than light but &quot;not hyperdrive.&quot; ''Destiny'' is reached through its on-board Stargate from any other location, using a unique nine-[[Chevron (Stargate)|chevron]] address that acts as a code, dialed on a Stargate with sufficient power supply (only power source sufficient enough so far has been a planet with a [[Naquadah#Naquadria|Naquadria]] core, that is far greater than a [[Ancient_technology_in_Stargate#Zero_Point_Module|ZPM]] is able to provide), the plausibility of which was previously unknown.&lt;ref name=&quot;revealed&quot;&gt;{{cite web |author=Sumner, Darren &amp; Read, David |url=http://www.gateworld.net/news/2008/04/istargate_universei_revealed.shtml |title=''Stargate Universe'' Revealed! |publisher=''[[GateWorld]]'' |date=April 5, 2008 |accessdate=2008-04-05}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The series begins when a team of ''80+''&lt;ref&gt;Air, Pt. 1 and 2&lt;/ref&gt; soldiers and scientists from Earth are forced to flee through the Stargate when their base is attacked. They find themselves on ''Destiny'';&lt;ref name=gw_crossroads&gt;{{cite web |last=Read |first=David |url=http://www.gateworld.net/interviews/crossroads.shtml |title=Crossroads &amp;ndash; GateWorld talks with Martin Gero |publisher=''[[GateWorld]]'' |month=December |year=2008 |accessdate=2008-12-08}}&lt;/ref&gt; unable to return to Earth, they must fend for themselves aboard the ship as it takes them to the far reaches of the universe.&lt;ref name=&quot;reut8&quot;&gt;{{cite news |publisher=[[Reuters]] |title=&quot;Stargate&quot; stays open with new series |first=James |last=Hibberd |url=http://www.reuters.com/article/televisionNews/idUSN2228963820080822 |date=August 22, 2008 |accessdate=2008-08-22}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Carlyle to star in Stargate show&quot;&gt;{{cite web |author= |url=http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/entertainment/7785467.stm |title=Carlyle to star in Stargate show |publisher= [[BBC News]] |date=December 16, 2008 |accessdate=2008-12-16}}&lt;/ref&gt; According to [[Brad Wright]], the show will focus mostly on the people aboard the ship.&lt;ref name=jm_090102&gt;{{cite web |last=Mallozzi |first=Joseph |authorlink=Joseph Mallozzi |url=http://josephmallozzi.wordpress.com/2009/01/02/january-2-2009-brad-wright-answers-your-questions/ |title=January 2, 2009: Brad Wright Answers Your Questions |publisher=josephmallozzi.wordpress.com |date=January 2, 2009 |accessdate=2009-01-03}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The ''Destiny'' has three shuttle landing pads and at least two shuttles, one of which had a hull breach until &quot;[[List of Stargate Universe episodes#ep13|Faith]]&quot;. In this episode, the shuttle was repaired but its engines could not generate sufficient thrust to leave a planet's gravity well after landing, so it was left behind.

The ''Destiny'' has an extensive array of energy weapons, including point-defense turrets located on strategic points all over the ship and a main cannon turret located on the underside of the ship.  The point-defense turrets are used to defend against small, agile targets while the larger main cannon is used against capital ships.  The larger main cannon can also be adapted for orbital bombardment.

''Destiny'' also has energy shielding to seal hull breaches and to protect against solar radiation and energy weapons.  It does this by operating a randomized shield pattern, which continuously cycles through various shield frequencies.  The operations of the randomized shield pattern can be manually overridden to operate at a specific, small range of frequencies.  The shielding strength can be attenuated to allow solid matter to pass through or increased to protect against impact from large objects.  The energy shielding must be engaged to cover the entire ship before it can jump into FTL travel.  ''Destiny'' can jump into FTL travel with energy shielding capacity as low as five percent.

The ''Destiny'' FTL drive system is composed of 16 separate modules.  One of these modules had degraded over the years to the point where it brought down overall engine efficiency of the FTL drive system.  This same module was later damaged by an act of sabotage and eventually disconnected and removed from the FTL drive system.  After the removal of the damaged module, the FTL drive system efficiency was greatly improved.  A minimum of three hours have to elapse between the end of one FTL jump and the start of the next.  Once the ship is in FTL travel, it must maintain it for a minimum of four hours.  Shortening an FTL jump or returning to FTL travel too early will cause cumulative damage to the FTL drive system.

The ''Destiny'' is fueled by plasma from stars.  The ship skims over a star's photosphere and uses an array of retractable ram-scoops on the underside of the hull (located towards the rear of the ship) to scoop in plasma to recharge its power reserves.  ''Destiny'' normally refuels itself from cool K- and M-[[Stellar_classification#Harvard_spectral_classification|spectral class]] stars.  Surface temperatures of these stars are low enough (less than 5200 K) for the ship's energy shielding to protect the crew and the ship's vital systems.
However, the ship can be manually commanded to refuel from stars as hot as O-spectral class.  But such a procedure will raise internal ship temperatures beyond habitability.

Initial details of ''Destiny''{{'}}s mission are revealed in &quot;[[List of Stargate Universe episodes#ep27|The Greater Good]]&quot;, when Dr. Rush is forced to reveal that he has cracked the master code and thus has control over the ship. It is stated that the Ancients had discovered a possibly artificial pattern to the [[cosmic microwave background radiation]] said to be a remnant of the [[Big Bang]]. This discovery suggested the possibility of life prior to or immediately following the Big Bang, and ''Destiny'' was launched to study this possibility.
* [http://stargate.mgm.com/photosynth/index.html Silverlight Virtual Tour of the Destiny]

====''Destiny'' shuttle====
''Destiny'' initially carried two shuttles which were used extensively to survey planets and defend against attacking aliens. One ship lost the capability to fly into space so it was left on a planet with a few of Destiny's crew, who wanted to remain on the planet. Another is destroyed when Dr. Rush has a team explore a planet with a harsh atmosphere that causes the ship to crash into a mountain killing a crew member. However, later on in the season the ship left on the planet appears right next to Destiny after dropping out of FTL. This perplexes all aboard ''Destiny'' because the shuttle is unable to go into FTL, and it was too badly damaged to even fly outside of the atmosphere. Everyone on board came to the conclusion that it was the alien race that built the planet that ''Destiny'' came across earlier in the series who brought the shuttle to them. This shuttle was not only repaired, but restored to its original factory condition. A copy of the recovered shuttle was encountered some time later, after the expedition encountered a &quot;time loop&quot;. The crew attempted to enact a modified plan to dial Destiny's stargate while the ship was recharging in a star in order to successfully dial back to Earth. This plan ultimately failed and resulted in the apparent loss of most of the crews live's and Destiny itself being sent back in time approximately twelve hours. With the crew gone and the ship itself having suffered critical damage, Rush abandoned Destiny aboard its shuttle and subsequently encountered a second version of himself, Destiny and its crew because of the time anomaly. Thus, Destiny was given a second shuttle in equally new condition as the first. However, in the series finale, after all other options were exhausted, the crew devised a plan to utilize the shuttle remotely as a diversion to lure the berserker drones and their control ship away from Destiny's location long enough for a team to gate to a planet with resources needed to effect repairs. By setting the shuttle up to emit a subspace pulse similar to the pulse that a stargate emits upon activation, the control ship traced the signal to the shuttle's location and the drones engaged it. However, upon Eli's suggestion, the shuttle's engines were set to overload and the shuttle was remotely piloted into the control ship while the engines simultaneously detonated, destroying the control ship and rendering its drones inactive. Though, Destiny was again left with a single shuttle.

In spite of the shuttle's small size, its firepower is significant. With two aft-mounted energy weapons, one port and one starboard respectively, the shuttle is an effective multirole transport/fighter craft. In several engagements, the shuttle has been utilized to assist Destiny in neutralizing smaller enemy craft that Destiny's point-defense weapons may otherwise have missed. As a defensive/offensive countermeasure, the shuttle possesses a stealth mode which allows it to become a decent reconnaissance craft. Additionally, each shuttle can accommodate up to five crew members (with a minimum of one necessary to pilot the craft), and up to twelve passengers. When not toting passengers the shuttle makes for a respectable cargo transport when gate travel is impractical or impossible.

===Minor ships===
*'''Seed ship''' A vessel type smaller than [[Destiny (Stargate)|Destiny]] but of similar design. The Seed ships were sent out before Destiny and are thus also millions of years old. Their purpose was to scout ahead and identify habitable worlds, once a suitable world was detected they would drop off a [[Stargate (device)|Stargate]] there, after finding and collecting materials to build Stargates and then building them. This class of ship is capable of docking with the Destiny and initiating both information and power transfers. The Seed ships seem to possess significant energy reserves stored in capacitors.
*'''Science vessel''' One of these ships, the ''Adaris'', suffered severe damage fifteen thousand years ago in an encounter with a [[coronal mass ejection]] from the Lantean sun. The entire crew was killed except for the pilot, who managed to reach Atlantis and warn them.&lt;ref name=&quot;Echoes&quot;&gt;{{sgcite|Echoes|Atlantis|show=ref}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*'''Transport ship''' These vessels are mentioned in {{sgcite|Before I Sleep|Atlantis}} as carrying the last offworld Ancients to Atlantis for evacuation. They are equipped with cloaking devices, shields, and weapons. The last of these ships is destroyed by the Wraith over Atlantis, with over three hundred people onboard.
*'''Escape ship''' In Ark of Truth, when the Ancients decided not to use the ark, they left Celestis in a diamond shaped vessel. This type of vessel is never seen again.

==Asgard starships==
The starships of the [[Asgard (Stargate)|Asgard]] are among the most advanced ever encountered by the [[Stargate Command|SGC]]. All Asgard vessels in the series are depicted as being operated by only a single Asgard, although [[Asgard (Stargate)#Thor|Thor]] makes a reference to evacuating his crew in &quot;[[Nemesis (Stargate SG-1)|Nemesis]]&quot;.

===Mothership===
[[Image:Beliskner.jpg|thumb|An Asgard mothership, from &quot;Small Victories&quot;.]]
The '''Asgard mothership''' is the first type of Asgard vessel seen in the series. In &quot;[[Thor's Chariot]]&quot;, the ''Beliskner'' is the ship of [[Thor (Stargate)|Thor]], Supreme Commander of the Asgard Fleet. It appears near the end of the episode to remove the forces of the [[Goa'uld]] [[Goa'uld characters in Stargate#Minor characters|Heru'ur]] from [[Cimmeria (Stargate)|Cimmeria]]. The ''Beliskner'' is destroyed in the third season episode &quot;[[Nemesis (Stargate SG-1)|Nemesis]]&quot;, where SG-1 crashes it into Earth's ocean after it becomes infested with Replicators. Several ships of this type also appear in &quot;[[Small Victories (Stargate SG-1)|Small Victories]]&quot;, some of which are controlled by the Replicators.

Asgard motherships are equipped with intergalactic hyperdrives, two rear thrusters for sublight propulsion, and a forward-mounted deceleration drive to control planetary reentry.&lt;ref name=&quot;Nemesis&quot;&gt;{{sgcite|Nemesis|show=ref}}&lt;/ref&gt; They are also equipped with Asgard beaming technology.&lt;ref name=&quot;Thor's Chariot&quot;&gt;{{sgcite|Thor's Chariot|show=ref}}&lt;/ref&gt; The ship is powered by four neutrino ion generators.&lt;ref name=&quot;Nemesis&quot;/&gt; Armed with advanced energy weapons and protected by powerful shields, Asgard motherships can comfortably expect victory against [[Goa'uld]] [[Ha'tak]]s even if outnumbered. However, [[Goa'uld characters in Stargate#Anubis|Anubis]] develops enhanced shielding based on Ancient technology that is resistant to the mothership's weaponry.&lt;ref name=&quot;Revelations&quot;&gt;{{sgcite|Revelations|show=ref}}&lt;/ref&gt; Asgard motherships utilize cloaking devices that render them invisible to [[radar]],&lt;ref name=&quot;Fair Game&quot;&gt;{{sgcite|Fair Game|show=ref}}&lt;/ref&gt; and have internal dampening fields that prevent explosives from detonating inside the ship. Each ship has automated medical treatment systems, including medical stasis pods that can be used in dire emergencies. There are advanced AI systems onboard that allow the ship to be operated by a single crew member, and the main computer stores all the collected knowledge of the Asgard.&lt;ref name=&quot;Nemesis&quot;/&gt;

===''O'Neill''-class vessel===
[[Image:O'Neill class.jpg|thumb|The ''O'Neill'' under construction, from &quot;Small Victories&quot;]]
The '''''O'Neill''''' class is the most advanced starship constructed by the Asgard to date, incorporating all of their latest technology, and is designed specifically to fight the Replicators. Its hull is composed of an alloy of [[trinium]], [[carbon]] and [[naqahdah]],&lt;ref name=&quot;Small Victories&quot;&gt;{{sgcite|Small Victories|show=ref}}&lt;/ref&gt; and its armaments and defenses are, as such, substantially superior to earlier Asgard motherships.&lt;ref name=&quot;Revelations&quot;/&gt; The first ship of this type, also named ''O'Neill'' (named after Colonel [[Jack O'Neill]] of [[SG-1]] in recognition of his actions on the behalf of the Asgard against the Replicators) was meant as a last defense against a Replicator invasion. Rather than fighting the replicators with it, however, [[Samantha Carter]] suggests using the unfinished ''O'Neill'' as bait to draw the Replicators away, giving the Asgard time to evacuate their civilization. The Replicators pursue the ''O'Neill'' into hyperspace, where they are destroyed when the ''O'Neill'' self-destructs.&lt;ref name=&quot;Small Victories&quot;/&gt; More ''O'Neill''-type ships appear in later episodes; three ships of this type force [[Anubis (Stargate)|Anubis]] to retreat in {{sgcite|Revelations}}, and six ships, led by the ''Valhalla'', ambush [[Replicator (Stargate)#Fifth|Fifth]]'s Replicator ship over Orilla.&lt;ref name=&quot;New Order&quot;&gt;{{sgcite|New Order|show=ref}}&lt;/ref&gt; The last appearance of this ship is in battle against the Ori in {{sgcite|Camelot}}. The ship's fate is unknown, though its pilot Kvasir survived.

===Science vessel===
The '''Asgard science vessel''' is first seen in {{sgcite|Fragile Balance}}, used by the renegade Asgard scientist [[Loki (Stargate)|Loki]]. Another ship of this type, the ''Daniel Jackson'', is Thor's ship in {{sgcite|New Order}}. Due to a Replicator threat, Thor takes the ''Daniel Jackson'' to Earth for Jack O'Neill and the knowledge of the [[Ancient (Stargate)|Ancients]] in his mind, from which he synthesizes a [[Ancient technology in Stargate#Replicator Disruptor|Replicator disruptor]] and incorporates it into the ''Daniel Jackson'' to eliminate all the Replicators on Orilla. Thor and the ''Daniel Jackson'' return in {{sgcite|Reckoning}}, to assist SG-1 during the Replicator invasion of the Milky Way. The ship is infested by Replicators, and Thor sends it into deep space to protect Earth before abandoning it. The science vessel is comparable in size to a [[Goa'uld]] [[Ha'tak]].&lt;ref name=&quot;New Order&quot; /&gt; Like other Asgard vessels the ship is equipped with beaming technology, intergalactic hyperdrives, and shields, though they are ineffective against Replicator blocks.&lt;ref name=&quot;New Order&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Reckoning&quot;&gt;{{sgcite|Reckoning|show=ref}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Minor ships===
*The '''Vanir starships''' seen in the ''Stargate Atlantis'' episodes {{sgcite|First Contact|Atlantis}} and {{sgcite|The Lost Tribe|Atlantis}} was used by a splinter group of Asgard named Vanir in the Pegasus galaxy who were willing to experiment on humans to solve their species' genetic deterioration. Their ships are hyperspace-capable, can pass through the Ancient shields of Atlantis (though a modification to the shields soon afterward rendered this impossible), and are equipped with energy weapons. It is mentioned that their ships are limited to interstellar hyperspace travel, the intergalactic vessels having been destroyed by the Wraith. They appear to be much weaker than regular Asgard ships with two being destroyed in battle with a Traveler ship and a third forced to flee.

==Earth starships==
{{Main|Earth starships in Stargate}}
Throughout ''Stargate SG-1'', a progression of Earth-built spacecraft incorporating alien technologies have been depicted. By season ten of the show, Earth possesses a small fleet of hyperspace-capable warships and spaceworthy fighters equipped with technology from the [[Goa'uld]], [[Asgard (Stargate)|Asgard]], [[Ancient (Stargate)|Ancients]], and other sources.

===X-301===
The X-301 is Earth's first fighter capable of space travel, built using parts from two scavenged [[Goa'uld]] [[Death Glider]]s. It is featured in &quot;[[Tangent (Stargate SG-1)|Tangent]]&quot;. A recall program embedded in the alien computers takes over navigation and flies the fighter back to the Goa'uld, thus forcing the SGC to abandon it after rescuing the pilots.

===F-302===
The F-302 is the successor to the X-301, being based on a Death Glider but built from the ground up by humans, thereby avoiding the problems faced with the original. It is introduced in &quot;[[Redemption (Stargate SG-1)|Redemption]]&quot;, and becomes the mainstay of Earth's space force. It is capable of both atmospheric flight and space travel. The original X-302 prototype featured a hyperdrive, but it was far too unstable, and it was removed from the design.

===''Prometheus''===
The X-303 is Earth's first experimental spacefaring warship, first seen in &quot;[[Prometheus (Stargate SG-1)|Prometheus]]&quot;. It uses both Earth and alien technologies, and has been upgraded several times in the series, notably by the Asgard. Upgrades included defensive shields, followed by reliable hyperdrive engines, and beaming technology.

On the maiden voyage, an overload caused by gravity waves destroyed the naquadriah powered hyperdrive's buffer, leading to the ejection and destruction of the hyperdrive generator. The hyperdrive engines of a Goa'uld Al'kesh are used to return the ship to Earth and eventually upgraded by the Asgard. The ship is destroyed in the ninth season episode &quot;[[Ethon (Stargate SG-1)|Ethon]]&quot; by an Ori satellite.

===Daedalus''-class battlecruiser''===
The BC-304 is Earth's second-generation line of starships was originally planned to be a sister ship of the Prometheus but it was instead redesigned to better integrate the alien technologies that had been tested on the ''Prometheus''. The first ship of the class, the ''Daedalus'', appeared in the Stargate Atlantis episode &quot;[[The Siege, Part 3]]&quot;.  Other ships of its class include the ''Odyssey'', ''Apollo'', and ''Korolev''.  The ''Sun Tzu'' is mentioned in the last episode of ''[[Stargate Atlantis]]'' as well as the ''George Hammond'' (named in honor of the late [[General Hammond]]), which was under construction at the time. The ''George Hammond'' later appears in the pilot episode of [[Stargate Universe]]. The ''Korolev'' is the only ''Daedalus''-class ship known to have been destroyed, though it was rushed through the production-line months early, and operated by the Russians who had not experienced piloting this craft. Other BC-304s have been severely damaged, but not destroyed.

==Goa'uld starships==
The [[Goa'uld]] operate a variety of starships. The control systems of Goa'uld ships are based on crystals,&lt;ref name=&quot;Exodus&quot;/&gt; a feature copied by the Earth ship ''Prometheus''.&lt;ref name=&quot;Prometheus&quot;&gt;{{sgcite|Prometheus|show=ref}}&lt;/ref&gt; Since the collapse of the Goa'uld order in {{sgcite|Reckoning}}, most of their fleet have fallen into the hands of the [[Free Jaffa Nation]]&lt;ref name=&quot;Stronghold&quot;&gt;{{sgcite|Stronghold|show=ref}}&lt;/ref&gt; and the [[Lucian Alliance]].&lt;ref name=&quot;The Ties That Bind&quot;&gt;{{sgcite|The Ties That Bind|show=ref}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Death glider===
&lt;!-- Deleted image removed: [[Image:SGDeathglider.jpg|thumb|A death glider in the ''Stargate'' film.]] --&gt;
The Goa'uld '''death glider''' is a fast [[Fighter aircraft|attack fighter]] capable of operating in an [[atmosphere]],&lt;ref name=&quot;Movie&quot;&gt;''[[Stargate (film)|Stargate]]''&lt;/ref&gt; in [[outer space|space]],&lt;ref name=&quot;The Serpent's Lair&quot;&gt;{{sgcite|The Serpent's Lair|show=ref}}&lt;/ref&gt; and even underwater.&lt;ref name=&quot;Descent&quot;&gt;{{sgcite|Descent|show=ref}}&lt;/ref&gt; Its shape resembles the symbolic winged [[Dung beetle|scarab beetle]] of [[ancient Egypt]]. Death gliders first appear in the [[Stargate (film)|''Stargate'' movie]]. Gliders lack hyperdrives and are usually carried by [[Ha'tak]]s into battle; their wings can be folded for more compact storage.&lt;ref name=&quot;The Serpent's Lair&quot;/&gt; They are armed with two [[staff cannon]]s.&lt;ref name=&quot;Movie&quot;/&gt; Different death glider variants have been depicted: some carry only one pilot&lt;ref name=&quot;Movie&quot;/&gt; while others have room for two.&lt;ref name=&quot;The Serpent's Lair&quot;/&gt; An especially large glider is seen in {{sgcite|Children of the Gods}}, fitted with a [[ring transporter]]. Earth's [[F-302]] fighters are derived from the death glider design.&lt;ref name=&quot;Tangent&quot;&gt;{{sgcite|Tangent|show=ref}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Fallen&quot;&gt;{{sgcite|Fallen|show=ref}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Tel'tak===
[[Image:Stargate SG-1 - Tel'tak.jpg|thumb|A Tel'tak taking off.]]
The '''Tel'tak''', also called a '''Goa'uld cargo ship''' or '''Goa'uld scoutship''', is a versatile spacecraft first seen in {{sgcite|Deadman Switch}} and in the remastered version of the pilot episode. In ''Stargate SG-1'', they are often used by the [[Tok'ra]] and the [[Jaffa (Stargate)|rebel Jaffa]] for missions into Goa'uld territory due to their unobtrusive nature;&lt;ref name=&quot;Jolinar's Memories&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Redemption&quot;&gt;{{sgcite|Redemption|show=ref}}&lt;/ref&gt; the [[Stargate Command|SGC]] also makes use of Tel'taks in the earlier seasons, when Earth does not yet possess its own hyperspace-capable ships.&lt;ref name=&quot;Fail Safe&quot;&gt;{{sgcite|Fail Safe|show=ref}}&lt;/ref&gt; The Tel'tak is equipped with shields and a hyperdrive. The configuration of the ship changes when in flight. It has two main sections: a cockpit in front and a cargo section in the back with a [[ring transporter]].&lt;ref name=&quot;The Devil You Know&quot;&gt;{{sgcite|The Devil You Know|show=ref}}&lt;/ref&gt; There are four escape pods that can be ejected from the bottom of the ship. Tel'taks are usually unarmed,&lt;ref name=&quot;Jolinar's Memories&quot;&gt;{{sgcite|Jolinar's Memories|show=ref}}&lt;/ref&gt; though many are equipped with a cloaking device for protection.&lt;ref name=&quot;Deadman Switch&quot;&gt;{{sgcite|Deadman Switch|show=ref}}&lt;/ref&gt; A heavily modified Tel'tak with hidden compartments, a pulse wave generator, and the ability to create sensor decoys appears in {{sgcite|The Ties That Bind}}. Another modified Tel'tak with two [[staff cannon]]s is seen in {{sgcite|Bounty}}.

===Al'kesh===
An '''Al'kesh''' is a [[Goa'uld]] medium-range [[bomber]]&lt;ref name=&quot;Exodus&quot;&gt;{{sgcite|Exodus|show=ref}}&lt;/ref&gt; used for ground support and as scouts.&lt;ref name=&quot;Continuum&quot;&gt;''[[Stargate: Continuum]]''&lt;/ref&gt; Its armaments consist of paired staff cannons on a belly turret for ship-to-ship combat&lt;ref name=&quot;Exodus&quot;/&gt; and explosive energy devices for ground bombardment.&lt;ref name=&quot;Summit&quot;&gt;{{sgcite|Summit|show=ref}}&lt;/ref&gt; Al'kesh are equipped with hyperdrives, allowing independent operation, and are highly maneuverable.&lt;ref name=&quot;Exodus&quot;/&gt; They do have shields,&lt;ref name=&quot;48 Hours&quot;&gt;{{sgcite|48 Hours|show=ref}}&lt;/ref&gt;  for example in ''[[Stargate: Continuum]]''. Some Al'kesh are equipped with cloaking devices and/or [[Technology in Stargate#Asgard technology|beaming technology]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Endgame&quot;&gt;{{sgcite|Endgame|show=ref}}&lt;/ref&gt; Al'kesh appear in several episodes supporting Goa'uld attacks.&lt;ref name=&quot;Summit&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Heroes&quot;&gt;{{sgcite|Heroes|show=ref}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Lost City&quot;&gt;{{sgcite|Lost City|show=ref}}&lt;/ref&gt; The Lucian Alliance has modified some Al'kesh into cargo haulers.&lt;ref name=&quot;Bounty&quot;&gt;{{sgcite|Bounty|show=ref}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Ha'tak===
[[Image:Hatak.jpg|thumb|A Ha'tak in space, from &quot;Enemies&quot;.]]
A '''Ha'tak''' or '''Goa'uld mothership''' is a large starship used by the Goa'uld. In the series, it usually refers to a class of ship consisting of a superstructure with a large, golden tetrahedron or square pyramid (i.e. Ra's Mother ship) at the center, first shown onscreen briefly in {{sgcite|Singularity}}. The word &quot;ha'tak&quot;, first used in the episode {{sgcite|Exodus}}, literally means &quot;pyramid ship&quot;, and so can also refer generically to all the types of Goa'uld motherships. Ha'taks are shaped to land on [[pyramid]]s,&lt;ref name=&quot;Movie&quot;/&gt; although anything similar will suffice (on two occasions a Ha'tak lands on [[Cheyenne Mountain]]).&lt;ref name=&quot;There But For the Grace of God&quot;&gt;{{sgcite|There But For the Grace of God}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Point of View&quot;&gt;{{sgcite|Point of View|show=ref}}&lt;/ref&gt; Ha'taks are equipped with hyperdrives and can travel over 32,000 times the speed of light.&lt;ref&gt;[[Selmak]] states in {{sgcite|Exodus}} that a Ha'tak can travel over 4 million light-years in 125 years.&lt;/ref&gt; The command center of a Ha'tak is known as the pel'tak.

Along with carrying squadrons of death gliders and other support ships, as well as thousands of [[Jaffa (Stargate)|Jaffa]] troops, Ha'taks can also assault planets directly from orbit.&lt;ref name=&quot;Continuum&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;There But For the Grace of God&quot;/&gt; They are armed with [[staff cannon]]s scattered over the hull.&lt;ref name=&quot;Exodus&quot;/&gt; In the episode {{sgcite|There But For the Grace of God}}, the attacking Ha'tak vessels bombard the [[East Coast of the United States]] with blasts equal to 200-megaton nuclear warheads. They are protected by powerful energy shields capable of repelling conventional, nuclear, and energy weapons.&lt;ref name=&quot;The Serpent's Lair&quot;/&gt; The shields can protect the ship's crew from the radiation of a [[blue giant]] [[star]]'s [[corona]] for up to 10 hours.&lt;ref name=&quot;Enemies&quot;/&gt; In {{sgcite|The Serpent's Venom}}, [[Apophis (Stargate)|Apophis]] is shown to have devised a way to cloak an entire fleet of motherships. This technology has not been seen since.  After the fall of the Goa'uld, these ships fell into the hands of the Lucian Alliance who use them now for their own purposes.

Several Goa'uld mothership variants have been encountered:

*'''Ra's mothership''' The first pyramid ship seen in ''Stargate'', operated by Ra. When landed, the top of the ship can open to expose the interior to the atmosphere. In the [[Stargate (film)|film]], the ship is destroyed by a nuclear device teleported to the ship by [[Jack O'Neill (Stargate)|Jack O'Neill]] and [[Daniel Jackson (Stargate)|Daniel Jackson]] using a [[ring transporter]]. The same type of starship was owned by [[Heru-ur (Stargate)|Heru-ur]], Ra's son, as it was seen in episode ''[[Stargate SG-1 (season 2)|Secrets]]'' (but in fact re-used scenes with the ship from the movie)
*'''Apophis' prototype mothership''' A ship seen under construction on PX9-757 in {{sgcite|Upgrades}}, with several enhancements over a standard Ha'tak. It is destroyed by [[SG-1]], who overwhelm the defenses using Atanik armbands.
*'''Apophis' flagship''' The flagship of Apophis, first seen in {{sgcite|The Serpent's Venom}}. Its weapons are capable of penetrating the shields of a standard Ha'tak at full power.&lt;ref name=&quot;Enemies&quot; /&gt; The ship escapes the supernova of Vorash's sun in {{sgcite|Exodus}} but is hurled into another galaxy. It is attacked and infested by Replicators, and soon self-destructs.&lt;ref name=&quot;Enemies&quot;&gt;{{sgcite|Enemies|show=ref}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*'''Anubis' flagship''' A mothership with advanced technology used by [[Anubis (Stargate)|Anubis]]. Its centerpiece is a superweapon powered by the six Eyes, powerful enough to destroy multiple Ha'taks or obliterate land masses with a single shot.&lt;ref name=&quot;Full Circle&quot;&gt;{{sgcite|Full Circle|show=ref}}&lt;/ref&gt; The ship is destroyed by the combined fleet of the System Lords in {{sgcite|Homecoming}} in the atmosphere of Langara, where its shields are only 40% effective. As the ship breaks apart, it releases an escape ship that enters hyperspace. A reconstructed version of the ship leads Anubis' attack on Earth in {{sgcite|Lost City}}, and is destroyed by [[Ancient technology in Stargate#Drone weapon|Ancient drone weapons]] fired from Antarctica. A version of this ship appears as [[Ba'al (Stargate)|Ba'al]]'s flagship in ''[[Stargate Continuum]]''.

===Minor ships===
*'''&quot;Escape ship&quot;''' An interstellar vessel seen under construction in {{sgcite|Nightwalkers}}. It is being built by the townspeople of Steveston, Oregon, who have been implanted with cloned [[Goa'uld]] symbiotes by the NID, who hope to claim the ship once it's finished.
*'''&quot;Anubis' escape ship&quot;''' A hyperspace capable detachment from his flagship used to facilitate his escape when the flagship is being destroyed by rival Goa'uld.
*'''&quot;Needle threader&quot;''' An old type of fighter designed to fit through the Stargate, a maneuver known as &quot;threading the needle&quot;. The design was abandoned because few pilots could master it. Master [[Bra'tac]] hid one on Chulak &quot;some hundred years ago&quot;. In {{sgcite|Into the Fire}}, General Hammond and [[Teal'c]] use the fighter to attack Hathor's defenses on a mission to rescue [[SG-1]]. The ship is equipped with two large staff weapons.
*'''&quot;Osiris' ship&quot;''' A ship with a large extensible spike on the bottom, hidden near the temple where Osiris and Isis were imprisoned. It is used by Osiris to escape Earth in {{sgcite|The Curse}}.
*'''Troop transport''' A large vessel designed to carry [[Jaffa (Stargate)|Jaffa]] ground troops into battle. It is heavily armored and can shrug off a direct strike from a [[FIM-92 Stinger]] missile.&lt;ref name=&quot;Full Circle&quot; /&gt; Troop transports have only been seen amongst [[Anubis (Stargate)|Anubis]]' forces; they first appear in {{sgcite|Summit}}, in Zipacna's attack on the main [[Tok'ra]] base at Revanna. They are also seen in {{sgcite|Redemption}} on Anubis' planet, in {{sgcite|Full Circle}} landing troops on Abydos, and in {{sgcite|Lost City}} transporting Anubis to P3X-449.

==Ori starships==
The [[Ori (Stargate)|Ori]] order their followers to begin constructing a fleet of ships after learning of the existence of the Milky Way galaxy in {{sgcite|Origin}}. Due to their advanced technology, their ships pose a considerable threat.

===Fighter===
An '''Ori fighter''' is a small dart-shaped attack vessel first seen in &quot;[[Flesh and Blood (Stargate SG-1)|Flesh and Blood]]&quot;, where they defeat a number of [[Death Glider]]s and [[Al'kesh]] over [[Chulak]]. Carried by Ori motherships, they are deployed from a ventral bay and are armed with powerful energy weapons. In &quot;[[Line in the Sand (Stargate SG-1)|Line in the Sand]]&quot;, one is shown carrying a [[ring transporter]] platform that it drops to the ground, allowing troops to be deployed from the mothership.

===Ori Mothership===
[[Image:Oriarmada.jpg|thumb|Ori motherships in &quot;Camelot&quot;.]]
'''Ori motherships''' first appear under construction in the episode &quot;[[Crusade (Stargate SG-1)|Crusade]]&quot;. Four ships invade the [[Milky Way]] galaxy in the following episode &quot;[[Camelot (Stargate SG-1)|Camelot]]&quot;, where they decimate a combined [[Asgard (Stargate)|Asgard]], [[Earth starships in Stargate|Earth]], [[Jaffa (Stargate)|Jaffa]], [[Lucian Alliance]], and [[Tok'ra]] fleet at P3Y-229 without taking any appreciable damage. In &quot;[[Flesh and Blood (Stargate SG-1)|Flesh and Blood]]&quot;, the ships proceed to conquer [[Chulak]] before splitting up. In the episode &quot;[[The Pegasus Project (Stargate SG-1)|The Pegasus Project]]&quot;, [[Teal'c]] lures an Ori mothership into the unstable vortex of the activating Supergate, destroying it. In {{sgcite|The Shroud}}, [[Daniel Jackson (Stargate)|Daniel Jackson]]/[[Moros (Stargate)|Merlin]] commandeers a mothership in order to send the [[Sangraal (Stargate)|Sangraal]] to the Ori galaxy. However, his plan requires that the Supergate be reopened, and shortly after six more Ori motherships enter the galaxy. In the ''Stargate SG-1'' finale &quot;[[Unending]]&quot;, the Asgard equip the Earth battlecruiser ''Odyssey'' with plasma beam weapons that are effective against the shields of Ori motherships. Nevertheless, the ''Odyssey'' is outnumbered and only escapes the Ori through the creative use of a time dilation field. In ''[[Stargate: The Ark of Truth]]'', all the Ori motherships stand down after the activation of the [[Ancient technology in Stargate#Other 2|titular object]].

One of the most formidable warships seen in ''Stargate'', an Ori mothership's main weapon can destroy a [[Goa'uld]] [[Ha'tak]] in a single shot. It also has smaller energy weapons scattered around the hull. The ship is protected by shields that are impervious to all but the most powerful attacks.&lt;ref name=&quot;Camelot&quot;&gt;{{cite episode|title=[[Camelot (Stargate SG-1)|Camelot]]|series=[[Stargate SG-1]]}}&lt;/ref&gt; The ship carries numerous fighters and can also land directly on a planetary surface.&lt;ref name=&quot;Flesh and Blood&quot;&gt;{{cite episode|title=[[Flesh and Blood (Stargate SG-1)|Crusade]]|series=[[Stargate SG-1]]}}&lt;/ref&gt; The mothership is equipped with an intergalactic hyperdrive,&lt;ref name=&quot;Unending&quot;&gt;{{cite episode|title=[[Unending (Stargate SG-1)|Unending]]|series=[[Stargate SG-1]]}}&lt;/ref&gt; but it must use a Supergate to reach the Milky Way from the Ori home galaxy.&lt;ref name=&quot;Beachhead&quot;&gt;{{cite episode|title=[[Beachhead (Stargate SG-1)|Beachhead]]|series=[[Stargate SG-1]]}}&lt;/ref&gt; The technology of the Ori mothership must be &quot;activated&quot; by a Prior,&lt;ref name=&quot;Crusade&quot;&gt;{{cite episode|title=[[Crusade (Stargate SG-1)|Crusade]]|series=[[Stargate SG-1]]}}&lt;/ref&gt; and only they (or the Orici) can control a mothership, which involves some degree of mental command.&lt;ref name=&quot;Counterstrike&quot;&gt;{{cite episode|title=[[Counterstrike (Stargate SG-1)|Counterstrike]]|series=[[Stargate SG-1]]}}&lt;/ref&gt; Inside, the ship contains prayer rooms, armories, and quarters for the ordinary human warriors of the Ori.&lt;ref name=&quot;Flesh and Blood&quot; /&gt; The power source is located inside a large enclosed chamber and is of unknown design.&lt;ref name=&quot;Counterstrike&quot; /&gt;

==Replicator starships==
The [[Replicator (Stargate)|Replicators]] typically infiltrate and take over the ships of other races for their own purposes. In the process, they can enhance the technology of those ships to perform better than the originals, using knowledge they have previously assimilated. Replicator-controlled [[Goa'uld]] [[Ha'tak]]s appear in &quot;[[Enemies (Stargate SG-1)|Enemies]]&quot; and &quot;[[Reckoning (Stargate SG-1)|Reckoning]]&quot;, and Replicator-controlled Asgard motherships appear in &quot;[[Small Victories (Stargate SG-1)|Small Victories]]&quot;. A Replicator-controlled vessel of unknown design appears in &quot;[[Enemies (Stargate SG-1)|Enemies]]&quot; and &quot;[[Unnatural Selection (Stargate SG-1)|Unnatural Selection]]&quot;. The vessel engages [[Goa'uld characters in Stargate#Apophis|Apophis]]' mothership with an energy beam weapon and is apparently destroyed, but not before infesting Apophis' ship.

In &quot;[[New Order (Stargate SG-1)|New Order]]&quot;, the humanoid Replicator [[Fifth (Stargate)|Fifth]] creates a ship made entirely of Replicator blocks with which to escape the time dilation field on Halla. The ship is equipped with shields, beaming technology, and intergalactic hyperdrives, and can fire projectiles made of Replicators to infiltrate other ships. Its interior can reconfigure according to Fifth's wishes. The ship is destroyed over the new Asgard homeworld Orilla as it exits hyperspace, though its fragments land on Orilla and reform into Replicators. Fifth escapes Orilla and the Replicator Disruptor by forming a smaller spider-like ship out of Replicators. In &quot;[[Gemini (Stargate SG-1)|Gemini]]&quot;, Fifth has reformed the larger Replicator ship and arrives in the Milky Way along with [[Replicator Carter]], who conspires to have that ship and Fifth destroyed by a Replicator disruptor satellite. Replicator Carter herself creates a third version of the Replicator ship, from which she commands the full-scale invasion of the Milky Way in &quot;[[Reckoning (Stargate SG-1)|Reckoning]]&quot;. The ship and all other Replicators in the galaxy are disintegrated into their component parts by the [[Dakara superweapon]] at the end of that episode.

==Wraith starships==
In ''[[Stargate Atlantis]]'', the [[Wraith (Stargate)|Wraith]] are the dominant race in the Pegasus galaxy, with a large fleet based around enormous hive ships. Their ships lack shields and are generally less powerful than the ships of their defeated enemies, the [[Ancient (Stargate)|Ancients]].&lt;ref name=&quot;No Man's Land&quot;/&gt; Wraith ships have a hybrid organic nature; they are grown, not built, and may have some degree of self-awareness. They begin with a pathogen that infects a human, and uses energy to convert both organic and non-organic matter nearby into a biopolymer similar to a polysaccharide, but with organometallic compounds mixed in. The polymer is initially soft and malleable but eventually hardens into a dense substance that is resistant to heat, pressure, and radiation. The growing process can be stopped if the human nucleus is freed from the pathogen.&lt;ref name=&quot;The Seed&quot;&gt;{{sgcite|The Seed|Atlantis|show=ref}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Dart===
&lt;!-- Deleted image removed: [[Image:Stargate Atlantis - Wraith Dart.jpg|thumb|A Wraith dart in flight.]] --&gt;
The '''Wraith dart''' is a small, one-man attack craft capable of fitting through a [[Stargate (device)|Stargate]], first seen in {{sgcite|Rising|Atlantis}}. They generate a loud, distinctive sound when flying in an atmosphere.&lt;ref name=&quot;Rising&quot;/&gt; Darts lack hyperdrives and rely on Stargates or larger vessels to travel around the galaxy.&lt;ref name=&quot;The Gift&quot;&gt;{{sgcite|The Gift|Atlantis|show=ref}}&lt;/ref&gt; The dart's main role is to capture humans for feeding, dematerializing them using a [[Technology in Stargate#Wraith technology|culling beam]] mounted on its underside.&lt;ref name=&quot;Rising&quot;/&gt; Large numbers of darts are carried by Wraith hive ships &lt;ref name=&quot;Letters from Pegasus&quot;&gt;{{sgcite|Letters from Pegasus|Atlantis|show=ref}}&lt;/ref&gt; and cruisers.&lt;ref name=&quot;Search and Rescue&quot;/&gt; In ship-to-ship combat, they are deployed as dogfighters and as point defense against missiles. If a dart's mothership is destroyed, they will perform kamikaze attacks on nearby enemy targets.&lt;ref name=&quot;The Siege, Part 3&quot;&gt;{{sgcite|The Siege, Part 3|Atlantis|show=ref}}&lt;/ref&gt; Like other Wraith ships, darts are partially organic. The canopy of a Wraith dart is composed of energy and is opaque when active, functioning as a giant [[Head-up display|HUD]].&lt;ref name=&quot;The Lost Boys&quot;&gt;{{sgcite|The Lost Boys|Atlantis|show=ref}}&lt;/ref&gt; Darts are armed with a pair of forward-firing energy weapons, capable of destroying a [[Ancient starships in Stargate#Puddle jumper|puddle jumper]] with a direct hit.&lt;ref name=&quot;The Gift&quot;/&gt; Sustained [[machine gun]] fire is sufficient to bring down a dart.&lt;ref name=&quot;Rising&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Duet&quot;&gt;{{sgcite|Duet|Atlantis|show=ref}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[John Sheppard (Stargate)|John Sheppard]] learns how to fly a dart in the season 2 episode {{sgcite|The Lost Boys|Atlantis}}.

===Cruiser===
A '''Wraith cruiser''' is medium-sized warship first seen in {{sgcite|Letters from Pegasus|Atlantis}}. Like hive ships, Wraith cruisers incorporate organic technology and lack shields. Their armaments consist of energy weapons, which can conduct orbital bombardments.&lt;ref name=&quot;The Siege&quot; /&gt; They are equipped with sub-light engines and hyperdrives,&lt;ref name=&quot;Letters from Pegasus&quot; /&gt; and are also capable of flying in an atmosphere&lt;ref name=&quot;Condemned&quot;&gt;{{sgcite|Condemned|Atlantis|show=ref}}&lt;/ref&gt; and landing on a planet surface.&lt;ref name=&quot;Michael&quot;&gt;{{sgcite|Michael|Atlantis|show=ref}}&lt;/ref&gt; They carry numerous darts in a ventral bay.&lt;ref name=&quot;Search and Rescue&quot;/&gt; Several cruisers escort the three hive ships headed for Atlantis, but retreat after the hive ships are destroyed.&lt;ref name=&quot;The Siege&quot;/&gt; In {{sgcite|The Siege, Part 3|Atlantis}}, a Wraith cruiser attempts to dock with the ''Daedalus'' for boarding. A Wraith cruiser attacks the Olesians in &quot;[[Condemned (Stargate Atlantis)|Condemned]]&quot;. The episode {{sgcite|Submersion|Atlantis}} shows that a cruiser served as the flagship for the Wraith Queen who led the first siege of Atlantis. That vessel was downed by the Ancients and came to rest on the ocean floor, where it remained largely intact and somewhat functional for 10,000 years. A cruiser serves as the base for the renegade Wraith [[Wraith (Stargate)#&quot;Michael&quot;|Michael]]. It evades the plasma beams of the battlecruiser ''Daedalus'' in {{sgcite|The Kindred|Atlantis}} but is destroyed by the ''Daedalus'' in {{sgcite|Search and Rescue|Atlantis}}.

===Hive ship===
'''Wraith hive ships''' are one of the largest spacecraft in the ''Stargate'' universe and the centers of [[Wraith (Stargate)|Wraith]] civilization. One first appears in {{sgcite|Rising|Atlantis}}, where it was not recognizable as a ship as it had rested on a planet for so long that tall trees grew on its back. There were over sixty hive ships in the Pegasus galaxy when the Atlantis expedition arrived.&lt;ref name=&quot;Underground&quot;/&gt; Due to internecine strife amongst the Wraith over an inadequate human food supply, most hive ships barely tolerate one another's presence, with open hostilities being more common in the later seasons.&lt;ref name=&quot;Spoils of War&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;The Hive&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Allies&quot;/&gt; Notable exceptions occur in {{sgcite|The Siege, Part 3|Atlantis}}, where twelve hive ships cooperate to attack [[Atlantis (Stargate)|Atlantis]], and in {{sgcite|Be All My Sins Remember'd|Atlantis}}, where seven hive ships ally with Atlantis to defeat the [[Asuran]]s. Over the course of ''Stargate Atlantis'', a number of hive ships have been destroyed in various conflicts. Many hives are without Queens and cannot replenish their losses, making the Wraith more reluctant to commit them to battle.&lt;ref name=&quot;Be All My Sins Remember'd&quot; /&gt;

Hive ships contain untold numbers of stasis pods for hibernating Wraith,&lt;ref name=&quot;Rising&quot;/&gt; as well as pods in which human victims are preserved for future feeding in cocoons.&lt;ref name=&quot;Underground&quot;&gt;{{sgcite|Underground|Atlantis|show=ref}}&lt;/ref&gt; Hive ships are partially organic and lack shields, though they are capable of regeneration.&lt;ref name=&quot;Allies&quot;&gt;{{sgcite|Allies|Atlantis|show=ref}}&lt;/ref&gt; They can withstand a hit from a Mark III tactical nuclear weapon, though not without suffering major damage.&lt;ref name=&quot;No Man's Land&quot;/&gt; Hive ships are equipped with hyperdrives, though they must make periodic stops to allow their organic components to recover from hyperspace radiation.&lt;ref name=&quot;No Man's Land&quot; /&gt; Hive ships mount numerous energy weapons throughout their hull and wield massive firepower.&lt;ref name=&quot;The Siege, Part 3&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;The Hive&quot;&gt;{{sgcite|The Hive|Atlantis|show=ref}}&lt;/ref&gt; They also function as carriers, launching huge numbers of [[Wraith dart]]s and supported by [[Wraith cruiser]]s.&lt;ref name=&quot;Letters from Pegasus&quot; /&gt; However, the launch bays represent a vulnerable area where damage can lead to secondary internal explosions.&lt;ref name=&quot;No Man's Land&quot;/&gt; Shortly after encountering the offensive use of [[Asgard (Stargate)|Asgard]] beaming technology by the ''Daedalus'', hive ships initiate countermeasures to prevent Earth ships from beaming onto their ships.&lt;ref name=&quot;The Siege, Part 3&quot;/&gt; A hive ship's consoles require telepathic control; [[Teyla Emmagan]] (who has trace amounts of Wraith DNA) can somewhat operate a hive ship with great effort.&lt;ref name=&quot;Misbegotten&quot;&gt;{{sgcite|Misbegotten|Atlantis|show=ref}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Super Hive ship===
A super hive is the natural result of providing a growing hive ship with the power it needs to exceed it's normal size limits. The only known super hive uses a captured ZPM to vastly enhance firepower, armour and sensors. This vessel is only seen once in the final episode of SGA where it proves superior to the Daedalus class battlecruiser dispatching 3 before it is destroyed. There is no reference to such a vessel being produced by the wraith prior to this; however, it is not inconceivable that such a vessel was grown and destroyed during the Ancients war with the wraith. The knowledge and ability to grow more super hives could have been lost in a single battle much like it was in SGA.

===Minor ships===
*'''Scout''' A vessel larger than a dart but much smaller than a cruiser, capable of some degree of independent operation. One appears off-screen in &quot;[[Aurora (Stargate Atlantis)|Aurora]]&quot;, where it investigates the derelict Ancient battleship and is destroyed by the ''Daedalus''. Concept art from that episode shows a bat-like look for the scout ship.&lt;ref&gt;[http://stargate.mgm.com/stills.php?series_id=3&amp;season=2#anc2 MGM Stargate Stills]&lt;/ref&gt; The scout first appears on-screen with a different design in &quot;[[Allies (Stargate Atlantis)|Allies]]&quot;, where it carries a Wraith Queen and her retinue from her hive-ship to Atlantis. [[Todd (Stargate)|Todd]] is later seen using one of this type of ship in {{sgcite|The Lost Tribe|Atlantis}}.
*'''Supply ship''' A ship comparable to a cruiser in size, used by the Wraith to transport large numbers of human victims during their war with the Ancients. One appears crashed on a planet in {{sgcite|The Defiant One|Atlantis}}. McKay theorizes that the ship model has been discontinued.

==Miscellaneous starships==
*'''Asuran ship''' Warships equipped with cloaking devices and drone weapons, appearing in &quot;[[Lifeline (Stargate Atlantis)|Lifeline]]&quot; and &quot;[[This Mortal Coil (Stargate Atlantis)|This Mortal Coil]]&quot;. They may originally be of Ancient design, as with other [[Asuran]] ships.
*'''Gadmeer terraformer''' A massive ship two miles across, seen in &quot;[[Scorched Earth (Stargate SG-1)|Scorched Earth]]&quot;. It is designed to [[terraform]] a suitable planet to serve as the new Gadmeer homeworld, and carries biological, historical, and cultural records with which to resurrect the Gadmeer civilization. The ship chooses planets based on 2,634 criteria; unfortunately the planet it eventually chooses is where [[SG-1]] had recently resettled Enkaran refugees.&lt;ref name=&quot;Scorched Earth&quot;&gt;{{sgcite|Scorched Earth|SG-1|show=ref}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*'''''Oran''''' A Hebridian ship that participates in the Loop of Kon Garat, from &quot;[[Space Race (Stargate SG-1)|Space Race]]&quot;. It is commanded by smuggler Golon Jarlath.&lt;ref name=&quot;Space Race&quot;&gt;{{sgcite|Space Race|SG-1|show=ref}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*'''''Seberus''''' A [[Serrakin]] prison transport commanded by Warrick, discovered crashed on a planet by SG-1 in &quot;[[Forsaken (Stargate SG-1)|Forsaken]]&quot;. In the episode, SG-1 helps Warrick recover the ship from the escaped prisoners. The ''Seberus'' is equipped with an ion propulsion system and sonic weapons, and uses liquid nitrogen for fuel.&lt;ref name=&quot;Forsaken&quot;&gt;{{sgcite|Forsaken|SG-1|show=ref}}&lt;/ref&gt; In &quot;[[Space Race (Stargate SG-1)|Space Race]]&quot;, Warrick enters the ''Seberus'' in the Loop of Kon Garat, a prestigious race, and enlists Samantha Carter for assistance in exchange for allowing her to examine the ship's technology.&lt;ref name=&quot;Space Race&quot; /&gt;
*'''Ship from &quot;The Daedalus Variations&quot;''' A hostile ship encountered by the Atlantis team in an alternate universe in {{sgcite|The Daedalus Variations|Atlantis}}. It attacks the alternate Atlantis and launches fighters against the ''Daedalus'' after Sheppard disables its main weapons.&lt;ref name=&quot;The Daedalus Variations&quot;&gt;{{sgcite|The Daedalus Variations|Atlantis|show=ref}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*'''''Stromos''''' One of three automated sleeper ships launched by the Talthuns for their new homeworld of Ardena, from the episode &quot;[[Lifeboat (Stargate SG-1)|Lifeboat]]&quot;. The ''Stromos'' crashed on P2A-347, and with power failing Pharrin, one of the officers, begins saving the consciousnesses of the passengers by transferring them into his own mind, and later into the mind of Daniel Jackson. The SGC helps the Talthuns revive by providing them with a [[Tau'ri technology in Stargate#Naqahdah generator|naqahdah generator]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Lifeboat&quot;&gt;{{sgcite|Lifeboat|SG-1|show=ref}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*'''Traveler ship''' Hyperspace-capable vessels that house the nomadic [[Mythology of Stargate#Travelers|Travelers]] of the Pegasus galaxy, first seen in &quot;[[Travelers (Stargate Atlantis)|Travelers]]&quot;. They are equipped with shields and energy weapons. In &quot;[[Be All My Sins Remember'd]]&quot;, several Traveler ships join the Atlanteans and the Wraith in fighting the Asurans, with one of the ships destroyed in the battle.
*'''Mystery ship''' In [[Grace (Stargate SG-1)|Grace]], the Prometheus comes under fire by a mysterious alien ship. Its shielding capabilities are unknown since its weapons destroyed all of the Prometheus' missiles before they came into contact with the ship. The ship beamed everyone off the Prometheus except Major Carter. Carter was later able to negotiate the return of the crew in exchange for telling the aliens how to escape from the nebula that it and the Prometheus was trapped.&lt;ref name=&quot;Grace&quot;&gt;{{sgcite|Grace|SG-1|show=ref}}&lt;/ref&gt; The motives of the ship in this episode is unknown and no contact with that race was made again.
*'''&quot;Blueberry alien&quot; Fighter'''&lt;ref name=&quot;mallozzi100504&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url=http://josephmallozzi.wordpress.com/2010/05/04/may-4-2010-victory-is-sweet-and-peanut-buttery-too-artwork-schematics-and-set-pics-from-stargate-universe-episode-11-space/ |title=Victory is sweet! And peanut buttery too! Artwork, schematics, and set pics from Stargate: Universe episode #11, Space! |work=Josephmallozzi.wordpress.com |first=Joseph |last=Mallozzi |date=May 4, 2010 |accessdate=July 26, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; First seen in the SGU episode 'Air Part3' and later seen in 'Space' attacking the Destiny.  These ships are designed to attack and board ships.
*'''&quot;Blueberry alien&quot; Mothership'''&lt;ref name=&quot;mallozzi100504&quot; /&gt; First seen in the SGU episode 'Space' this ship carries an unknown number of fighters and crew members.  It's equipped with labs and rooms designed to hold captured enemies in water tanks.  This ship is also equipped with faster than light engines and advanced weapons.  This ship was first seen during an attack on the Destiny.  This ship is operated by an unknown race.
*'''Ursini 'Seedship alien' Mothership''' From SGU this vessel most likely belongs to the Ursini who were found on the damaged seed ship early in season two, it carries several of the same pods seen on the seed ship that are known to belong to these aliens. It's capabilities are unknown as it is derelict when discovered with very few functional systems and low power reserves. The seed ship that the aliens had boarded was too far behind the damaged Mothership to have been responsible for the massive damage indicating either it fought another seed ship later or more likely was attacked by another starship not of ''[[Ancient (Stargate)|Ancient]]'' origin.
*'''Automated attack drones''' From SGU these vessels are controlled by a central control ship. They do not have shields and they have energy weapons comparable to that of Destiny's shuttle. The Ursini are at war with them after they accidentally activated the ships. They are very fast and maneuverable. Their most important advantage is their numbers. Many are destroyed by Destiny after Col. Telford comes to Destiny's aid in a Ursini captured &quot;ancient seed ship&quot;, and both of the ships fly through the nearest star the drones follow and are destroyed.
*'''Novus Evacuation Ship''' From Season two of SGU these vessels were built and launched to transport the remaining population of the plant Novus to a safe world as theirs was soon to be destroyed. These ships travel slower than light and are expected to take centuries to reach their destination, as such the evacuation transports are likely either sleeper ships or generation ships. There is a slim possibility that they use near light speed time dilation to achieve a journy time of only a few years ship-time. However, this near light speed travel has only been achieved with use of a ZPM aboard an ancient warship and even the Daedalus class can't match that speed using sub-light engines.
*'''''Remorseless Angel''''' A small ship that is operated by Vala Mal Doran in the comic series. This vessel is armed with advanced weapons and technologies and is known to operate out of the hanger of the Earth starship ''Eos'' also from the comics.

==References==
{{Reflist|3}}

{{Stargate}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:List Of Starships In Stargate}}
[[Category:Stargate technology]]
[[Category:Fictional spacecraft]]

[[cs:Vesmrn lod v serilu Hvzdn brna]]
[[fr:Vaisseaux de Stargate]]
[[it:Astronavi di Stargate]]
[[pl:Statki (Gwiezdne Wrota)]]
[[ro:List de nave din Stargate]]
[[ru:     ]]
[[sv:Lista ver rymdfarkoster i Stargate]]
[[uk:  ( )]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
