<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="179842" ns="0" title="Xandros"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{infobox OS
| screenshot             = [[Image:Xandros41OCE.png|300px]]
| caption                = Xandros Desktop 4.1 OCE
| developer              = Xandros Incorporated
| family                 = [[Unix-like]]
| source_model           = [[Free and open source software|Free and open source]] mixed with [[closed source]]
| latest_release_version = 4.2
| latest_release_date    = {{release date|2007|07|26}}
| kernel_type            = [[Monolithic kernel|Monolithic]]
| ui                     = [[KDE]]
| license                = [[GNU GPL]] with some [[proprietary software]]
| working_state          = Discontinued&lt;ref&gt;http://distrowatch.com/table.php?distribution=xandros&lt;/ref&gt;
| website                = [http://www.xandros.com/ www.xandros.com]
}}
'''Xandros''' is the name of both a line of [[operating system]]s and '''Xandros Corporation''', the company which creates them. '''Xandros Desktop''' was a [[Linux]] [[Linux distribution|distribution]]. The name Xandros is derived from the [[X Window System]] and the [[Greece|Greek]] island of [[Andros]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url=http://forums.xandros.com/viewtopic.php?p=64889#64889 | title=Xandros is an acronym? | author=Andrew | date=2005-01-18 | accessdate=2007-06-05}}&lt;/ref&gt;
The co-creator of the now popular netbook, Xandros was founded in May 2001 by Linux Global Partners (Will Roseman and Dr. Frederick Berenstein),&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.xandros.com/news/press/release1.html|title=Xandros Announces Strategic Licensing Agreement with Corel Corporation|publisher=Xandros|date=2001-08-21|accessdate=2008-04-29 |archiveurl = http://web.archive.org/web/20080329161315/http://www.xandros.com/news/press/release1.html &lt;!-- Bot retrieved archive --&gt; |archivedate = 29 March 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt; the company is [[headquarters|headquartered]] in [[New York City]].

Xandros Desktop was based on [[Corel Linux]], a [[Debian]]-based distribution which was acquired along with the development team behind the product from [[Corel Corporation]] in August 2001 after Corel decided to sell the Linux distribution market.&lt;ref name=&quot;Corporate Background&quot;&gt;{{cite web | url=http://www.xandros.com/about/corporatebackground.html | title=Xandros Corporate Background | publisher=Xandros | accessdate=2007-06-05}}&lt;/ref&gt; Xandros is a founding member of the [[Desktop Linux Consortium]] and member of the Interop Vendor Alliance.&lt;ref&gt;http://interopvendoralliance.org/Directory.aspx&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;!-- Broken 20100705--&gt;

In July 2007, Xandros bought [[Scalix]], a Linux-based email and collaboration product, based on [[HP OpenMail]].&lt;ref&gt;http://www.theregister.co.uk/2008/11/04/open_xchange_funding/&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Scalix Bought by Xandros&quot;&gt;{{cite web | url=http://richi.co.uk/blog/2007/07/scalix-bought-by-xandros.html | title=Scalix Bought by Xandros | accessdate=2007-07-18}}&lt;/ref&gt;
In July 2008, Xandros acquired [[Linspire]].

==Products==
Xandros makes products for both the consumer and business markets. While the distributions include many packages licensed as [[free software]] and [[open-source]], Xandros was criticized for inclusion of [[proprietary software]] developed in-house by the Xandros Corporation.

===Commercial editions===
==== Xandros Desktop Home Edition ====
This edition came with a 30-day trial of [[CrossOver|Crossover Office]]. It also included an &quot;Applications CD&quot; which includes extra programs which can be installed via Xandros Networks. As opposed to Home Edition Premium, the Home Edition did not include the photo manager, music manager, security suite, wireless profiles, or the ability to write to [[NTFS]] partitions.

==== Xandros Desktop Home Edition Premium ====
This edition came with a full version of Crossover Office Standard Edition, and a second CD (the &quot;Applications CD&quot;) which included extra applications which could be installed via Xandros Networks. Despite its name, Xandros Desktop Home Edition Premium did not include a Xandros Networks Premium Membership.

Xandros Corporation offered a 30-day trial version of Xandros Home Edition Premium as a free download for evaluation purposes.

==== Xandros Desktop Professional ====
Formerly known as Xandros Desktop Business Edition, this edition was basically the same as Xandros Desktop Home Edition Premium, but it included the ability to authenticate to Windows PDC and [[Active Directory]] Domains, used [[Point-to-Point Tunneling Protocol|PPTP]] VPN to connect remotely to the office, and used [[wireless broadband|broadband wireless]] connectivity with [[3G]], [[GSM]] and [[Universal Mobile Telecommunications System|UMTS]] support. Xandros Desktop Professional was officially released on 28 November 2006.

As with Home Edition Premium, Xandros Corporation also offered a 30-day trial version of Xandros Professional.

==== Presto ====
Introduced in 2009, Presto was a lightweight &quot;instant-on&quot; operating system which uses the lightweight [[Xfce#Version_4|Xfce 4.6]] [[desktop environment]]. Similar to [[Canonical Software|Canonical]]'s [[Wubi]] installer for [[Ubuntu (operating system)|Ubuntu]], it was installed inside of Microsoft Windows, with Windows XP as the earliest supported version. It also had access to an &quot;application store&quot; based on [[CNR (software)|CNR]], which was acquired through Xandros' acquisition of [[Linspire]] in mid-2008.

==== Xandros Moblin ====
In 2009, Xandros announced that it would develop a new netbook operating system based on [[Moblin|Moblin v2]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url=http://www.xandros.com/news/press_releases/Xandros_Creates_Enhanced_User_Experience.html | title=Xandros Creates Enhanced User Experience for Netbook Users with Moblin V2}}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Server systems ===
Xandros Desktop Management Server (xDMS) was available. It easily set up repositories as it deploys customized Xandros Desktop configurations across a large organization.{{Citation needed|date=February 2009}}

Xandros Server was designed to run on [[Server (computing)|servers]]. It was officially launched at the 2006 [[LinuxWorld Conference and Expo]] in [[Toronto]], on 25 April 2006, and officially released for purchase at the Xandros website on 1 May 2006, at a [[suggested retail price|MSRP]] of [[USD]] 450. Xandros Server 2.0 has been released in May 2007.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.xandros.com/news/press_releases/Xandros_releases_server2.html|title=Xandros Releases Xandros Server Standard Edition 2, Offering Enterprise-Grade Features to Windows-Centric SMBs|publisher=Xandros|date=2007-05-08|accessdate=2008-04-29}}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Previous editions ===
Xandros Open Circulation Edition (OCE) was a freely redistributable edition for non-commercial use, with a limited set of additional software. Soon after the 4.0 version was released as a DVD shrinkwrapped with Linux magazines, the torrent was pulled from Xandros' servers and all references to OCE removed from the Xandros website without explanation. Previous versions of Xandros OCE were generally released about 4&amp;nbsp;months after the release of the commercial versions.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url=http://forums.xandros.com/viewtopic.php?t=28362 | title=OCE 4 - Prerelease information | author=BoyLinux | date=2006-12-20 | accessdate=2007-06-05}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Xandros Desktop OS Standard Edition was basically the same as the Open Circulation Edition, but it included full-speed CD/DVD burning. This product was replaced by Home Edition.

Xandros Desktop OS Deluxe Edition included an &quot;applications CD&quot; which included extra programs which could be installed via Xandros Networks. This product was replaced by Home Edition Premium.

Xandros Desktop OS Surfside Edition was basically the same as Xandros Desktop OS Standard Edition, however the Surfside Edition also included a Plantronics USB headset and 120&amp;nbsp;minutes of [[Skype]]Out service.

According to [[DistroWatch]], Xandros Desktop is discontinued.[http://distrowatch.com/table.php?distribution=xandros] DistroWatch made the decision because no new official version or official updates to Xandros Desktop have been released since November 2006.[http://distrowatch.com/weekly.php?issue=20100426#news]

When Xandros purchased Linspire, they announced plans to retain [[Freespire]] as a Debian-based free community distribution and to base future editions of Xandros Desktop Professional - Home Edition and Home Edition Premium were to be discontunued - on Freespire. (This would be similar to the way [[Novell]] bases [[SUSE Linux Enterprise Desktop]] on their free [[openSUSE]] and to the way [[Redhat]] bases [[Redhat Enterprise Linux]] on their free [[Fedora (operating system)|Fedora]].) However, according to one website, Xandros has discontinued Freespire.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.itpro.co.uk/622528/the-lost-world-of-the-xandros-desktop/ |title=The Lost World of the Xandros Desktop |publisher=Richard Hillesley |date=2010-04-20 |accessdate=2010-08-09}}&lt;/ref&gt; In addition, the DistroWatch website has added Freespire to its list of discontinued distributions.

== Look and feel ==
[[Image:Xandros 4.1 Full.png|thumb|200px|Xandros 4.1 OCE (KDE) running Xandros File Manager, Xandros Networks, Control Centre and the Xandros Launch Menu]]

The Xandros [[Graphical user interface|GUI]] used a modified version of [[KDE]], which included replacing [[Konqueror]] with its own proprietary file manager called Xandros File Manager. It also used a package manager known as Xandros Networks, which handles installation of software. Installation of Xandros was done by a wizard that asks questions about partitioning and the administrator (root) password.

It was possible to install and use the [[GNOME]] and [[Xfce]] desktop environments on Xandros.{{elucidate|date=March 2011}}{{citation needed|date=March 2011}}

== BridgeWays for Microsoft Systems Center ==

In June 2007, a &quot;broad collaboration agreement&quot; between Xandros and Microsoft was announced.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite press release | url=http://www.microsoft.com/presspass/press/2007/jun07/06-04XandrosPR.mspx | title=Microsoft, Xandros Broad Collaboration Agreement Extends Bridge Between Commercial Open Source and Microsoft Software | publisher=[[Microsoft]] | date=2007-06-04 | accessdate=2007-06-04}}&lt;/ref&gt;{{verify credibility|date=February 2011}} The agreement included &quot;patent covenants, similar to the agreement that Microsoft reached with [[Novell]].

In 2009, Xandros BridgeWays released the first of many Management Packs for Systems Center.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.pr.com/press-release/190492 see press release&lt;/ref&gt;{{verify credibility|date=February 2011}}
The BridgeWays Management Pack Suite of products includes:
*VMware ESX virtualization and HyperV Extensions;
*JBoss, Apache, IBM WebSphere, Oracle WebLogic application development environments;
*Oracle, IBM DB2, MySQL database products;
*Apache web servers and more.

In 2010 BridgeWays is “Extending System Center”, by expanding the scope and market potential for Systems Center, with Windows, Linux, UNIX and VMware application environment monitoring. BridgeWays’ only focus is on building, selling and supporting Management Packs for System Center. See BridgeWays users can now track their alerts through System Center Service Manager 2010

BridgeWays does not compete with Microsoft. This group works closely with the Microsoft System Center R&amp;D, Sales and Marketing teams to maximize value to System Center customers. In addition Xandros Bridgeways System Center resells direct and through its partner network of Distributors, ISVs, and  SI MVPs worldwide as a contributing member of the System Center community.

== ASUS Eee PC ==
In a collaboration of ASUS hardware and the Xandros operating system, the first &quot;netbook&quot; came into being. The [[ASUS Eee PC]] came with Xandros installed as well as [[Windows XP]]. The installed version of Xandros is tab based, built from scratch using Xlib and the [[Qt (toolkit)|Qt 4.5 toolkit]]. The full desktop version (or &quot;Advanced Mode&quot;) may be installed&amp;mdash;but not always easily&amp;mdash;through a set of administrative command prompts.&lt;ref&gt;http://wiki.eeeuser.com/howto:getkde&lt;/ref&gt; The full desktop version features a [[KDE]] 3 desktop with a few modifications performed by Xandros. This desktop mode also provides access to the [[Synaptic Package Manager]] which can be used to update and manage the [[Eee PC]]'s software.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url=http://wiki.eeeuser.com/guidebooks:how_linux_software_installation_works | title= How Linux software installation works}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url=http://i246.photobucket.com/albums/gg102/holyprop/fulldesktopversion1.png | title=Xandros full KDE desktop on EeePC}}(screenshot of the full desktop version of Xandros running on the EEE PC)&lt;/ref&gt;

In February 2009 it was announced Xandros is porting its Eee PC Linux distribution to 2 [[ARM processor]]-based (Freescale [[i.MX|i.MX515]] &amp; the Qualcomm [[Snapdragon (processor)|Snapdragon]] CPU) platforms for netbooks &amp; other mobile devices.&lt;ref&gt;[http://eeepc.itrunsonlinux.com/the-news/1-latest-news/270-xandros-linux-os-available-for-arm-devices Xandros Linux OS available for ARM devices]&lt;/ref&gt;{{Update after|2010|11|13|date=November 2010}}

== References ==
{{Reflist|2}}

==External links==
{{Wikibooks|Xandros}}
* [http://www.xandros.com/ Product home page]
* {{DistroWatch|xandros|NAME=Xandros Desktop OS}}
* [http://www.bridgeways.ca/ BridgeWays]

{{Linux distributions}}
{{Use dmy dates|date=October 2010}}

[[Category:Linux companies]]
[[Category:Debian-based distributions]]
[[Category:Companies based in Ottawa]]
[[Category:Companies based in New York City]]
[[Category:2001 establishments]]
[[Category:Linux distributions used in appliances]]

[[ar:زاندروس]]
[[de:Xandros]]
[[es:Xandros]]
[[fr:Xandros]]
[[id:Xandros]]
[[it:Xandros]]
[[lv:Xandros]]
[[lt:Xandros Desktop]]
[[hu:Xandros]]
[[nl:Xandros Desktop OS]]
[[ja:Xandros]]
[[no:Xandros]]
[[pl:Xandros]]
[[pt:Xandros]]
[[ro:Xandros]]
[[ru:Xandros]]
[[sk:Xandros]]
[[sv:Xandros]]
[[tr:Xandros]]
[[uk:Xandros]]
[[vi:Xandros]]
[[zh:Xandros]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
