<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><redirects><r from="Acer Inc" to="Acer Inc." /></redirects><pages><page pageid="397169" ns="0" title="Acer Inc."><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Use dmy dates|date=July 2011}}
{{Infobox company
| company_name      = Acer Incorporated&lt;br&gt;{{lang|zh-Hant|宏碁股份有限公司}}
| company_logo      = [[File:Acer_2011.svg|250px|Acer company logo]]
| vector_logo       =
| company_type      = Public company
| traded_as  = {{Lse|ACID}} {{Tse|2353}}
| foundation        = 1976 (as Multitech)
| founder           = [[Stan Shih]] et al.
| predecessor       = Multitech International
| location_city     = [[Xizhi]], [[New Taipei]]
| location_country  = [[Taiwan]]
| area_served       = Worldwide
| key_people        = Zhentang Wang&lt;br&gt;&lt;small&gt;([[Chairman]] and [[Chief executive officer|CEO]])
| industry          = [[Computer systems]] &lt;br&gt; [[Computer hardware]] &lt;br&gt;[[Electronics]]
| products          = [[desktop computer|Desktops]], [[laptops]], [[netbook]]s, [[server (computing)|servers]], [[smartphone]]s, [[tablet computer]]s, [[computer storage|storage]], [[handheld electronics|handhelds]], [[computer monitor|monitors]], televisions, [[video projector]]s, [[e-business]] 
| revenue           = {{profit}} {{USD|20.01}} billion &lt;small&gt;(2010)&lt;/small&gt;&lt;ref name=FG500&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.forbes.com/companies/acer/|title=Fortune Global 500 #436: Acer|date=20 July 2011|publisher=[[Fortune (magazine)|Fortune]]|accessdate=27 November 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt; 
| operating_income  = 
| market_cap        = $6.49 billion &lt;small&gt;(2010)&lt;/small&gt;&lt;ref name=FG500/&gt;  
| net_income        = {{profit}} {{USD|479}} million &lt;small&gt;(2010)&lt;/small&gt;&lt;ref name=FG500/&gt;
| num_employees     = 7,757 &lt;small&gt;(March 2011)&lt;/small&gt;&lt;ref name=FG500/&gt;
| parent            =
| subsid            = Acer America Corporation&lt;br&gt;Acer Computer Australia&lt;br&gt;Acer India&lt;br&gt;[[Gateway, Inc.]]&lt;br&gt;[[Packard Bell]]&lt;br&gt;[[eMachines]]&lt;br&gt;[[E-TEN]]&lt;br&gt;[[Aopen]]
| homepage          = {{URL|http://www.acer.com|Acer.com}}
| footnotes         =
}}
'''Acer Incorporated''' ({{IPAc-en|icon|ˈ|eɪ|s|ər}}; {{zh|t=宏碁股份有限公司|p=Hóngqi Gǔfèn Yǒuxiàn Gōngsī}}, lit. ''Hongqi Corporation'') ({{Lse|ACID}}, {{Tse|2353}}) is a [[Multinational corporation|multinational]] information technology and electronics corporation headquartered in [[Xizhi]], [[New Taipei City]], [[Republic of China|Taiwan]]. Acer's products include [[desktop computer|desktop]] and [[laptop]] PCs, [[Tablet computer|tablet computers]], [[server (computing)|servers]], storage devices, displays, [[smartphone]]s and peripherals. It also provides e-business services to businesses, governments and consumers.

In the early 2000s, Acer implemented a new business model, shifting from a manufacturer to a designer, marketer and distributor of products, while performing production processes via contract manufacturers.&lt;ref name=&quot;CentRes&quot;&gt;[[Centre for Research on Multinational Corporations]], Bart Sleb, 2005&lt;/ref&gt; {{Citation needed|All of Acer's products are now made by [[original equipment manufacturer]]s in the [[People's Republic of China]].|date=June 2011}}

In addition to its core business, Acer also owns the largest franchised computer retail chain in [[Taipei]], [[Taiwan]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url = http://global.acer.com/about/milestones.htm | title = About Acer – Milestones | publisher=Acer | accessdate = 2007-07-07 |archiveurl=http://web.archive.org/web/20060708175102/http://global.acer.com/about/milestones.htm|archivedate=2006-07-08}}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:Acer Building in Oriental Science Park right-front.jpg|thumb|upright=600px|Acer Headquarters in [[New Taipei, Taiwan|New Taipei]]]]

==History==
Acer was founded by [[Stan Shih]] (施振榮), his wife [[Carolyn Yeh]], and a group of five others as Multitech in 1976, headquartered in [[Hsinchu City]], Taiwan.

It began with eleven employees and US$25,000 in capital.  Initially, it was primarily a distributor of electronic parts and a consultant in the use of microprocessor technologies. It produced the [[Micro-Professor MPF-I]] training kit, then two [[Apple II clone]]s; the [[Microprofessor II]] and [[Microprofessor II|III]] before joining the emerging [[IBM PC compatible market]]—and over time becoming a significant PC manufacturer. The company was renamed Acer in 1987.

In 1993, Acer posted record profits of $75 million; 43 percent of that year's net was generated by the DRAM joint venture, considered &quot;the most efficient in the DRAM industry&quot; by some observers. Total sales grew to $3.2 billion in 1994, and net income increased to $205 million, as Acer America turned its first annual profit in the 1990s.  From 1994 to 1995, Acer advanced from 14th to ninth among the world's largest computer manufacturers, surpassing Hewlett-Packard, Dell, and Toshiba.

In 1995, the Aspire PC was unveiled. In 1996, Acer expanded into consumer electronics, introducing many new, inexpensive videodisc players, video telephones, and other devices to boost global market share,&lt;ref name=CentRes/&gt; and in 1997 extended its laptop efforts by buying [[Texas Instruments]]' [[Texas Instruments#Consumer electronics and computers|mobile PC division]].

===Spinning-off===
{| class=&quot;toccolours&quot; style=&quot;float:right; margin-left:1em; font-size:90%; line-height:1.4em; width:220px;&quot;
! colspan=&quot;2&quot; style=&quot;text-align: center;&quot; | '''Acer Inc. logo history'''
|-
| '''Logo'''|| '''Years'''
|-
| colspan=&quot;2&quot; |&lt;hr&gt;
|-
| &lt;center&gt;[[File:Acer-old-logo.gif|100px]]&lt;/center&gt; || 1987–March 2001
|-
| &lt;center&gt;[[File:Acer Logo.svg|100px]]&lt;/center&gt;|| March 2001-2011
|-
| &lt;center&gt;[[File:Acer 2011.svg|85px]]&lt;/center&gt; || 2011–present
|}
In 1998, Acer reorganized into five groups: Acer International Service Group, Acer Sertek Service Group, Acer Semiconductor Group, Acer Information Products Group, and Acer Peripherals Group. Two years later that corporate restructuring did not appear to have made a significant impact on the company overall, and stock prices were falling. Shih restructured again. To dispel complaints from clients that Acer competed with its own products and to alleviate the competitive nature of the branded sales vs. contract manufacturing businesses, Shih spun off the contract business, renaming it Wistron Corporation. The restructuring resulted in two primary units: brand name sales and contract manufacturing. The restructuring also resulted in Acer breaking off several of its smaller operations, including semiconductor design, consumer electronics, and liquid-crystal displays.&lt;ref name=&quot;EncycBus2&quot;&gt;Encyclopedia of Business, 2nd ed.&lt;/ref&gt;

Early signs indicated that the spinoff strategy had worked well, especially in Europe, where Acer became a popular PC brand. In 2003, company sales increased 48 percent to $4.6 billion, and helped Acer surpass Japan's Toshiba and [[NEC]], making it the world's fifth largest maker of PCs.&lt;ref name=EncycBus2/&gt;

Acer increased worldwide sales while simultaneously reducing its labor force by identifying and using marketing strategies that best utilized their existing distribution channels.  By 2005, Acer employed a scant 7,800 people worldwide.  Revenues rose from US$4.9 billion in 2003&lt;ref name=&quot;Gianfranco Tutti&quot;&gt;{{cite web
| url = http://www.acer.co.in/press/New_President.pdf
| title = Gianfranco Lanci is appointed President of Acer Inc., effective January 2005
| publisher=Acer
| date = 2004-09-01
| accessdate = 2007-04-27
| format = PDF
|archiveurl = http://web.archive.org/web/20070403125915/http://www.acer.co.in/press/New_President.pdf |archivedate = 2007-04-03}}&lt;/ref&gt; to US$11.31 billion in 2006.

Acer's North American market share has slipped over the past few years, while in contrast, the company's European market share has risen.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
| url = http://news.com.com/PC+market+surged+in+2005,+will+settle+in+2006/2100-1003_3-6028454.html
| title = PC market surged in 2005, will settle in 2006
| publisher=cnet
| date = 2006-01-18
| accessdate = 2007-07-07
}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Acquisitions===
On 27 August 2007, Acer announced plans to acquire its US-based rival [[Gateway Inc.]] for US$710 million. Acer's chairman, [[J.T. Wang]], stated that the acquisition &quot;completes Acer's global footprint, by strengthening our United States presence.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|author=6:00&amp;nbsp;p.m. ET|url=http://www.msnbc.msn.com/id/20458321/|title=Taiwan's Acer to buy PC maker Gateway - World business |publisher=MSNBC|date=2007-08-27|accessdate=2009-04-07}}&lt;/ref&gt; Included in this acquisition was the [[eMachines]] brand.

In January 2008, Acer announced that it had acquired a controlling interest of 75% of [[Packard Bell]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.washingtonpost.com/wp-dyn/content/article/2008/01/31/AR2008013101390.html|title=Acer Buys 75 Percent of Packard Bell making it the 2nd largest computer maker in the world|work=Washington Post|accessdate=2009-04-07 | date=2008-01-31| archiveurl = http://www.webcitation.org/5mqx42YJw | archivedate = 2010-01-17| deadurl=no}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In 2009, Acer acquired: [[E-TEN]] and 29.9% of [[Olidata]].

In October 2009, Acer passed [[Dell]] as the world's number 2 PC maker.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.businessweek.com/globalbiz/blog/eyeonasia/archives/2009/10/acer_passes_del.html|title=http://www.businessweek.com/globalbiz/blog/eyeonasia/archives/2009/10/acer_passes_del.html|work=Business Week |accessdate=2010-04-23 | date=2009-10-15}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In August 2010, Acer and [[Founder Technology]] signed a memorandum of mutual understanding to strengthen their long term PC business cooperation.

In July 2011, Acer Inc. will buy iGware Inc. for $320 million to try possible potentially lucrative cloud market.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.theglobeandmail.com/report-on-business/international-news/acer-to-buy-cloud-computing-firm-igware/article2104667/?utm_medium=Feeds%3A%20RSS%2FAtom&amp;utm_source=Home&amp;utm_content=2104667 Acer to buy cloud computing firm iGware - The Globe and Mail]&lt;/ref&gt; iGware creates cloud software and infrastructure tools for devices. &lt;ref&gt; Don Reisinger, CNET. &quot;[http://news.cnet.com/8301-13506_3-20081409-17/acer-to-acquire-cloud-service-provider-igware/ Acer to acquire cloud-service provider iGware].&quot; July 21, 2011. Retrieved July 22, 2011.&lt;/ref&gt;

===Figures===
'''29 April 2010'''&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |title=Acer to Launch Full Line of Mobile Internet Devices in May |author=Dan Nystedt |url=http://www.pcworld.com/article/195202/acer_to_launch_full_line_of_mobile_internet_devices_in_may.html |newspaper=PCWorld |publisher=IDG News |date=2010-04-29 |accessdate=2011-02-17}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* Acer announced [[revenue]] in Q1 rose 36 percent year-on-year to NT$162.1 billion (US$5.2 billion) and its [[net profit]] increased 63 percent to 3.29 billion New Taiwan dollars (US$104.7 million); 27 percent of [[revenue]] comes from the U.S.
* Gianfranco Lanci announced that Acer will launch 4 new smartphones by Q3 2010, and a series of &quot;Internet Devices&quot; by the end of May which will run version 4.0 of its Shell user interface.
* According to Gartner and IDC, Acer now ranks #1 worldwide in notebook shipments.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |title=Acer Profit Climbs After Overtaking H-P in Laptop Market Share |author=Tim Culpan |url=http://www.businessweek.com/news/2010-04-29/acer-profit-climbs-after-overtaking-h-p-in-laptop-market-share.html |newspaper=Businessweek |publisher=Bloomberg |date=2010-04-29 |accessdate=2011-02-17}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Operations==
===North America===
[[File:Acer-America-Offices.jpg|thumb|220px|Right|Headquarters of Acer America at San Carlos St. San Jose, CA]]
Acer America Corporation, headquartered in San Jose, California, is a member of the Acer Group. Acer's R&amp;D, engineering, manufacturing and marketing operations in the United States and Canada are handled by Acer America. In September 1990, Acer acquired Altos Computer Systems, one of the top manufacturers of multi-user and networked [[Unix]] computer systems for commercial markets. In February 1997, Acer acquired [[Texas Instruments]] Mobile Computing business, including the award-winning TravelMate and Extensa notebook lines, making Acer the fourth-leading notebook manufacturer in the United States. In 2007 Acer acquired PC maker [[Gateway, Inc.|Gateway]]. The acquisitions marked Acer’s return to the US consumer market that it abandoned in 1999 after losing $45m struggling to build brand awareness. Acer America's Canadian office, in Mississauga, Ontario, handles repair of Acer, Gateway, and E-Machine Notebooks and Desktop PCs for Eastern Canada. Acer has several facilities in Temple, Texas including a repair facility, a parts warehouse, and a call center. In the words of its Chief Executive, J.T. Wang, “Building a brand is very different in the US. The investment at the initial stage has to be very big—otherwise there is almost no impact”.&lt;ref&gt;quoted in Einhorn, 2009&lt;/ref&gt;

===Australia===
The Australian subsidiary of Acer is Acer Computer Australia (ACA). The subsidiary was established in 1990, and is currently Australia's third largest personal computer vendor, behind Hewlett-Packard Australia and Dell Australia and New Zealand. Acer Computer Australia has Australia's highest overall market share in notebook PC and tablet PC sales. The company is also Australia's leading PC vendor in government and education markets. Acer Computer Australia has 480 employees as of 2006.

===India===
Acer's subsidiary in India is '''Acer India (Pvt) Limited''', and was incorporated as a wholly owned subsidiary of Acer Computer International, Ltd. in 1999. It is a notable vendor in key segments such as education, desktop computers and low profile notebooks for education. The headquarters are in [[Bangalore]], India. It has however been extensively criticized for poor after sales service and multiple other issues that have plagued its customers.

==Linux==
Acer has shipped some of their notebooks and more recently netbooks, with various [[Linux]] [[operating system]] distributions including [[Ubuntu (operating system)|Ubuntu]], [[Linpus Linux|Linpus]], [[Android (operating system)|Android]] (in a dual boot environment with [[Windows XP]]), and [[Google Chrome OS]]. They have also launched a line of smartphones and [[Acer Tablet|tablets]] with Android.

==Products==
[[File:Acer Aspire 8920 Gemstone by Georgy.JPG|thumb|Acer Aspire 8920G Notebook]]
[[File:Acer Chromebook.jpg|thumb|Acer AC700 Chromebook]]
[[File:aceraspire3610.JPG|thumb|Acer Aspire 3610 Notebook]]
[[File:Acer Aspire 5520 laptop.JPG|thumb|Acer Aspire 5520 Notebook]]
[[File:Acer Aspire 4520.JPG|thumb|Acer Aspire 4520 Notebook]]
[[File:Guang Hua Digital Plaza Launch Acer Aspire One.jpg|thumb|Acer Aspire One]]

;Chromebook
On 11 April 2011, Google announced that Acer will be offering [[Chromebook]] laptops starting 15 June. [[Acer AC700|Acer's Wi-Fi only Chromebook]] costs $349. The devices have been available for sale in the U.S. from Amazon and Best Buy since July 2011. &lt;ref&gt;[http://us.acer.com/ac/en/US/content/ac700-home AC700 Home]&lt;/ref&gt;
;Consumer Desktops
* [[Acer Aspire Desktop]] series
* [[Acer Aspire Predator]] series
;Business Desktops
* [[Acer Veriton]] series
;Consumer Notebooks
* [[Acer Aspire Notebook]] series
* [[Acer Aspire Timeline]] series
* [[Acer Ferrari products]] series
* [[Acer Iconia]]
;Business Notebooks
* [[Acer TravelMate]] series
* [[Acer Extensa]] series
;Tablet
* [[Acer Tablet]] series
;Netbook
* [[Acer Aspire One]]
* [[Acer Ferrari products#Acer Ferrari One|Ferrari One]]
;Nettop
* [[AspireRevo]]
;Mobile phones
* [[Acer Tempo]] series
* [[Acer Liquid]]
* [[Acer beTouch]]
* [[Acer neoTouch]]
* [[Acer Stream]]
* [[Acer E110]]
;Home Network Solution
* [[Acer Clear.fi]]
;Computer displays
* G Series
* P Series
* H Series
* X Series
* B Series
* V Series
* S Series
* T Series
* D Series
* MO Monitor TV series
;Projectors
* Professional Series
* Home Series
* [[Travel Series]]
* Value Series
;Television
* [[AT Series]]
;Servers and storage
* Acer server F1 series
* Tower series: T110 F1, T115 F1, T150 F1, T310 F1, T350 F1;
* Rack series: R160 F1, R180 F1, R320 F1, R360 F1, R380 F1, R385 F1, R585 F1;
* Blade series: B2x285 F1, B2x280 F1, B460 F1;
* Gemini series: B1170 F1, B2170 F1, B2170t, B2175 F1
* Home Server Series: H340, H341, H342, Altos Easystore M2
* Acer storage series
* N500 F1, N1600 F1, HNAS3080, GS2040, AMS2100, AMS2300
;Other (discontinued devices)
* [[Digital camera]]s
* Personal digital assistants
* Automotive navigation systems
* [[Acer PICA]]

==Brands==
* '''Acer'''
* [[eMachines]]
* [[Gateway, Inc.|Gateway]]
* [[Packard Bell]]
* [[E-TEN]]

==Environmental record==

In 2005, Acer published its first environmental report, for which the company used the GRI guidelines.&lt;ref&gt;The Global Reporting Initiative (GRI) is a multi-stakeholder process and independent institution whose mission is to develop and disseminate globally applicable Sustainability Reporting Guidelines.&lt;/ref&gt; All of Acer’s tier-one suppliers have acquired ISO 14001 certification.&lt;ref&gt;ISO 14001 was released in 1996 with the intent that companies manage all of the activities, products and services that can significantly impact the environment&lt;/ref&gt;

In November 2011, Acer was ranked 12th place out of 15 in [[Greenpeace]]’s re-launched Guide to Greener Electronics, with the a score of 2.9 points out of 10. The Guide ranks electronics makers according to their policies and practices to reduce their impact on the climate, produce greener products, and make their operations more sustainable.&lt;ref name=&quot;Guide to Greener Electronics&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.greenpeace.org/international/en/campaigns/climate-change/cool-it/Guide-to-Greener-Electronics/ |title=Guide to Greener Electronics - Greenpeace International|accessdate= November 16 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; 

Greenpeace criticized the company for not setting out targets to reduce greenhouse gas (GHG) emissions as intended in 2010 and for not providing external verification for the GHG emissions it reports for its operations and business travel. It also scored badly on the Products criteria receiving no points on product life cycle while Greenpeace noted that a higher percentage of its products need to meet or exceed Energy Star standards in order for it to score more points.&lt;ref name=&quot;Guide to Greener Electronics&quot;/&gt;  

It received some praise for launching new products which are free from polyvinyl chloride plastic (PVC) and brominated flame retardants (BFRs) and the company informed Greenpeace 
that the majority of its products will be PVC/BFR free in the near future. Acer also scored well on chemical management for lobbying for restrictions on organo-halogens and was commended for reporting on GHG emissions from its first tier suppliers and investigating its second tier. &lt;ref name=&quot;Guide to Greener Electronics&quot;/&gt;

==Sponsorships==
===Sports===&lt;!-- [[Acer (engine)]] redirects here. If the title of this section is changed, please update the redirect --&gt;
Acer sponsored the [[British American Racing|BAR]]-[[Honda Racing F1|Honda]] [[Formula One]] racing team in the year {{F1|2000}}.&lt;ref&gt;[http://global.acer.com/about/news.asp?id=6816 About Acer – News Release]{{Dead link|date=April 2009|bot=H3llBot}}&lt;/ref&gt;
In {{F1|2001}}, Acer provided sponsorship to the [[Prost Grand Prix]] Formula One team, and the team's [[Scuderia Ferrari|Ferrari]] engines were badged as Acers.

Acer currently sponsors the [[Scuderia Ferrari|Ferrari]] Formula 1 team and it's Top Sponsor of FC Internazionale – Milano (Inter Milan) Football Club. From 2007 to 2009 Acer has been Official Supplier of [[FC Barcelona]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://global.acer.com/about/news.asp?id=6745 About Acer – News Release] {{Wayback |url=http://global.acer.com/about/news.asp?id=6745 |date=20070219200301 |bot=H3llBot}}&lt;/ref&gt; On 19 March 2007, Acer announced it will sponsor the Factory Fiat Yamaha Team for the 2007 [[MotoGP]] World Championship season. From 2009, Packard Bell (that it is part of Acer Group) is the sponsor of Yamaha Factory Racing Team.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.packardbell.com/NR/rdonlyres/841AAED9-A03E-43F4-812F-0B76FE4F387D/1061/pb_yamaha_sponsorship.pdf|title=02.02.2009 Packard Bell sponsor of Yamaha Factory Racing Team : Changeover of sponsorship from Acer|format=PDF|accessdate=2009-04-07}} {{Dead link|date=June 2010|bot=H3llBot}}&lt;/ref&gt; since 2010 Acer support  [[Army United F.C.]] the Thai football team of the [[Thai Premier League]]

Acer also currently sponsors professional gaming team SK Gaming.

Acer has been Worldwide TOP Partners for both the Vancouver 2010 Olympic Winter Games and Singapore Youth Olympic Games. Acer will be TOP Partner of next London [[2012 Summer Olympics]].

===Other===
[[Acer Arena]], at Sydney Olympic Park, NSW, is the largest indoor live entertainment and sporting arena in Australia. It was formerly named the [[Sydney Superdome]].

Designed and constructed by Abigroup Ltd in conjunction with [[Obayashi Corporation]], the venue is acknowledged by experts as equal to the finest indoor arenas in the world today.

One of the major venues for the [[2000 Sydney Olympics]] and [[Paralympic Games]], Acer Arena hosted artistic gymnastics, trampoline, the basketball finals and wheelchair basketball.

The $200 million complex was designed and constructed to set new benchmarks in urban design, access for people with disabilities, spectator comfort, operation efficiency and Olympic serviceability.

The project comprises three subsites:
* Acer Arena, a 21,000 seat fully enclosed arena built under a 'Build, Own, Operate &amp; Transfer' (B.O.O.T.) contract: $190 million
* 3400 space [[car park]] designed for high volume traffic entry and egress under a design and construct contract: $25 million
* Plaza and external works covering over 32,000m² under a management contract then converted to a lump sum: $25 million

Acer Arena was designed and constructed with very high environmental values and was awarded the prestigious national [[Banksia Award]] for Construction Practices in 1999.

Officially opened by the former [[Premier of New South Wales]], [[Bob Carr]], in November 1999 with a gala performance by Luciano Pavarotti, Acer Arena has hosted events including [[Supercross]], tennis, rock concerts, arena musicals, religious services, school spectaculars and banquets.

==See also==
* [[Microprofessor I]], Acer's first product
* [[BenQ]], formerly Acer CM
* [[ALi]], formerly Acer Laboratories Incorporated
* [[AOpen]], formerly AcerOpen
* [[ACC (computer company)]]
* [[List of computer system manufacturers]]
* [[List of companies in Taiwan]]
* [[eMachines]]
* [[Gateway, Inc.]]
* [[Packard Bell]]
* [[E-TEN]]

==References==
{{Reflist|colwidth=35em}}

==External links==
{{Portal box|Taiwan|Companies}}
{{Commons category|Acer computers}}
* {{official website|http://www.acer.com}}
* [http://www.acer-group.com/public/ Acer Group] ([http://www.acer-group.com/public/chinese/index.htm Chinese])
* [http://gateway.com/ Gateway]
* [http://packardbell.com/ Packard Bell]
* [http://www.emachines.com/ eMachines]
* [http://glofiish.com/ Glofiish]
* [http://www.etencorp.com/ E-TEN]

{{Open Handset Alliance Members}}
{{Major information technology companies}}
[[Category:Acer Inc.]]
[[Category:Companies established in 1976]]
[[Category:Computer hardware companies]]
[[Category:Electronics companies of Taiwan]]
[[Category:Portable audio player manufacturers]]
[[Category:Taiwan brands]]
[[Category:Netbook manufacturers]]
[[Category:Display technology companies]]
[[Category:Mobile phone manufacturers]]

[[ar:إيسر]]
[[bn:এসার ইনকর্পোরেটেড]]
[[bg:Ейсър]]
[[bs:Acer Inc.]]
[[ca:Acer (empresa)]]
[[cs:Acer (firma)]]
[[da:Acer Inc.]]
[[de:Acer]]
[[es:Acer (empresa)]]
[[fa:ایسر]]
[[fr:Acer (entreprise)]]
[[ko:에이서]]
[[hy:Acer]]
[[id:Acer (perusahaan)]]
[[it:Acer (azienda)]]
[[lt:Acer Inc.]]
[[hu:Acer]]
[[ml:എയ്സർ]]
[[ms:Acer (syarikat)]]
[[my:အေဆာ အင်ကော်ပိုရေးတစ်]]
[[nl:Acer (bedrijf)]]
[[ja:エイサー (企業)]]
[[no:Acer]]
[[uz:Acer]]
[[pl:Acer]]
[[pt:Acer (empresa)]]
[[ro:Acer]]
[[ru:Acer]]
[[sah:ACER]]
[[sk:Acer (počítačová firma)]]
[[fi:Acer (yhtiö)]]
[[sv:Acer Inc.]]
[[ta:ஏசர்]]
[[th:เอเซอร์]]
[[tr:Acer]]
[[uk:Acer]]
[[vi:Acer Inc.]]
[[wuu:宏碁电脑]]
[[zh:宏碁]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
