<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><redirects><r from="Unmaintained computer software" to="Abandonware" /></redirects><pages><page pageid="18933176" ns="0" title="Abandonware"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Refimprove|date=June 2009}}
'''Abandonware''' are discontinued products for which no product support is available, or whose [[copyright]] ownership may be unclear for various reasons. Abandonware may be [[computer software]] or physical devices which are usually computerised in some fashion, such as [[personal computer games]], [[Office suite|productivity applications]], [[utility software]], or [[mobile phones]].

Definitions of &quot;abandoned&quot; vary; generally it refers to a product that is no longer available for legal purchase, over the age where the product creator feels an obligation to continue to support it, or where [[Operating Systems]] or [[hardware platforms]] have evolved to such a degree that the creator feels continued support cannot be financially justified.  Software companies and manufacturers may change their names, go bankrupt, enter into mergers, or cease to exist for a variety of reasons. When this happens, product rights are usually transferred to another company that may elect not to sell or support products acquired.

In most cases, software classed as abandonware is not in the [[public domain]], as it has never had its original [[copyright]] revoked and some company or individual still owns exclusive rights. Therefore, sharing of such software is usually considered [[copyright infringement]], though in practice copyright holders rarely enforce their abandonware copyrights.

==History==
People have distributed old software since shortly after the beginning of [[Personal computer|personal computing]], but the activity remained low-key until the advent of the [[Internet]].  While trading old games has taken many names and forms, the term &quot;abandonware&quot; was coined by Peter Ringering in late 1996.{{Citation needed|date=June 2007}} Ringering found classic game websites similar to his own, contacted their webmasters, and formed the original ''Abandonware Ring'' in February 1997.&lt;ref name=&quot;ARingFAQ&quot;&gt;{{cite web | title =The Abandonware Ring FAQ | work = | publisher =The Official Abandonware Ring | date =2006 | url =http://www.abandonwarering.com/?Page=FAQ | accessdate = March 8, 2007 }}&lt;/ref&gt; This original [[webring]] was little more than a collection of sites linking to adventureclassicgaming.com. Another was a site indexing them all to provide a rudimentary search facility. In October 1997, the [[Interactive Digital Software Association]] sent [[cease and desist]] letters to all sites comprising the Abandonware Ring, which led to most shutting down. An [[unintended consequence]] (called the [[Streisand effect]] in internet [[parlance]]) was that it spurred others to create new abandonware sites and organizations that came to outnumber the original Ring members. Sites formed after the demise of the original Abandonware Ring include [[Abandonia]] and [[Home of the Underdogs]].

Rarely has any abandonware case gone to court. In November 2006 the [[Library of Congress]] approved an exemption to the [[Digital Millennium Copyright Act|DMCA]] that permits the cracking of [[copy protection]] on software no longer being sold or supported by its copyright holder so that they can be archived and preserved without fear of retribution. It is still unlawful to distribute copies of old copyrighted software and games, with or without compensation, in any [[Berne Convention for the Protection of Literary and Artistic Works|Berne Convention]] signatory country.&lt;ref name=&quot;Joystiq&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url= http://www.joystiq.com/2006/11/23/us-copyright-office-grants-abandonware-rights/ | title=US Copyright Office grants abandonware rights |first=Ross|last=Miller |accessdate = January 2, 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Archives==
Several websites archive abandonware for download, including old versions of applications which are difficult to find by any other means. Much of this software fits the definition of &quot;software that is no longer current, but is still of interest&quot;, but the line separating the use and distribution of abandonware from [[copyright infringement]] is blurry, and the term ''abandonware'' could be used to distribute software without proper notification of the owner.

The [[Internet Archive]] has created an archive of what it describes as &quot;vintage software&quot;, as a way to preserve them.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.archive.org/details/clasp |title=The Internet Archive Classic Software Preservation Project | publisher=[[Internet Archive]] |accessdate=October 21, 2007}}&lt;/ref&gt; The project advocated for an exemption from the United States [[Digital Millennium Copyright Act]] to permit them to bypass copy protection, which was approved in 2003 for a period of 3 years.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web| url=http://www.archive.org/about/dmca.php| title=Internet Archive Gets DMCA Exemption To Help Archive Vintage Software| accessdate=October 21, 2007}}&lt;/ref&gt; The exemption was renewed in 2006, and {{As of|2009|October|27|lc=on}}, has been indefinitely extended pending further rulemakings.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |url=http://www.copyright.gov/fedreg/2009/74fr55138.pdf |date=28 October 2009 |title=Exemption to Prohibition on  Circumvention of Copyright Protection Systems for Access Control Technologies |author=[[Library of Congress]] [[Copyright Office]] |journal=[[Federal Register]] |volume=27 |issue=206 |pages=55137&amp;ndash;55139 |format=PDF |accessdate=December 17, 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt;  The Archive does not offer this software for download, as the exemption is solely &quot;for the purpose of preservation or archival reproduction of published digital works by a library or archive.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |url=http://www.copyright.gov/fedreg/2006/71fr68472.html |title=Exemption to Prohibition on Circumvention of Copyright Protection Systems for Access Control Technologies |journal=[[Federal Register]] |volume=71 |issue=227 |pages=68472–68480 |date=November 27, 2006 |author=[[Library of Congress]] [[Copyright Office]] |accessdate=October 21, 2007 |quote=Computer programs and video games distributed in formats that have become obsolete and that require the original media or hardware as a condition of access, when circumvention is accomplished for the purpose of preservation or archival reproduction of published digital works by a library or archive. A format shall be considered obsolete if the machine or system necessary to render perceptible a work stored in that format is no longer manufactured or is no longer reasonably available in the commercial marketplace.}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Types==
The term &quot;abandonware&quot; is broad, and encompasses many types of old software.

* '''Commercial software unsupported but still owned by a viable company''': The availability of the software depends on the company's attitude toward the software. In many cases, the company which owns the software rights may not be that which originated it, or may not recognize their ownership. Some companies, such as [[Borland]], make some software available online,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://bdn.borland.com/museum|title=CDN » Museum|accessdate=October 21, 2007}}&lt;/ref&gt; in a form of [[freeware]]. Others do not make old versions available for free use and do not permit people to copy the software.

* '''Commercial software owned by a company no longer in business''': Often, no entity defends the copyright if such software is put onto abandonware websites. An example of this is [[Digital Research]]'s original [[PL/I]] compiler for [[DOS]]. The rights to the software can not be bought by another company, therefore there is no possibility for a lawsuit.

* '''[[Shareware]] whose author still makes it available''': Finding historical versions, however, can be difficult since most shareware archives remove past versions with the release of new versions. Authors may or may not make older releases available. Some websites collect and offer for download old versions of shareware, freeware, and (in some cases) commercial applications. In some cases these sites had to remove past versions of software, particularly if the company producing that software still maintains it, or if later software releases introduce [[Digital Rights Management]], whereby old versions could be viewed as DRM circumvention.{{Citation needed|date=August 2011}}

* '''Unsupported or unmaintained shareware''': Again, finding historical versions may be possible, but very difficult.

* '''[[Open source]] and freeware programs that have been abandoned''': In some cases, source code remains available, which can prove a historical artifact. An interesting case is [[PC-LISP]], still found online, which implements the [[Franz Lisp]] dialect. The DOS based PC-LISP still runs well within emulators and on [[Microsoft Windows]].

==Abandoning software==
Software can be considered abandoned when it can only be used with obsolete technologies, such as [[Apple II series|pre-Macintosh]] Apple computers. Companies do sometimes voluntarily relinquish copyright on software, putting it into the [[public domain]], or re-license it as [[free software]] or as [[freeware]]. [[Id Software]] is an early proponent of this practice, releasing the source code for the [[game engine]]s (but not the actual game content, such as levels or textures) of some older titles under a [[free software license]]. Other examples include [[Amstrad]], which supports emulation and free distribution of [[Amstrad CPC|CPC]] and [[ZX Spectrum]] hardware ROMs and software, and [[Revolution Software]], which released their game ''[[Beneath a Steel Sky]]'' as freeware and gave the engine's source code to the authors of [[ScummVM]] to add support for the game. Transfer of public domain or freely licensed software is perfectly legal, distinguishing it from abandonware which still has full copyright restrictions.

There are groups that lobby companies to release their software as freeware. These efforts have met with mixed results.  One example is the library of educational titles released by [[MECC]]. MECC was sold to [[Brøderbund]], which was sold to [[The Learning Company]]. When TLC was contacted about releasing classic MECC titles as freeware, the documentation proving that TLC held the rights to these titles could not be located, and therefore the rights for these titles are &quot;in [[limbo]]&quot; and may never be legally released.&lt;ref name=&quot;CanAbandonware&quot;&gt;{{cite web | last =Savetz | first =Kevin | title =Can &quot;Abandonware&quot; Revive Forgotten Programs? | work = | publisher =byte.com | date = September 17, 2001 | url =http://www.savetz.com/articles/byte-abandonware.php?sort=date | accessdate = March 8, 2007 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

The [[Chilling_effect_%28law%29|chilling effect]] of drawing a possible lawsuit can discourage release of [[source code]]. Efforts to persuade [[IBM]] to release [[OS/2]] as [[open source software]] were ignored since some of the code was co-developed by [[Microsoft]].

===Enforcement of copyright===
Old copyrights are usually left undefended. This can be due to intentional non-enforcement by owners due to software age or obsolescence, but sometimes results from a [[Corporation|corporate]] copyright holder going out of business without explicitly transferring ownership, leaving no one aware of the right to defend the copyright.

Even if the copyright is not defended, copying of such software is still unlawful in most jurisdictions when a copyright is still in effect. Abandonware changes hands on the assumption that the resources required to enforce copyrights outweigh benefits a copyright holder might realize from selling software licenses. Additionally, abandonware proponents argue that distributing software for which there is no one to defend the copyright is morally acceptable, even where unsupported by current law. Companies that have gone out of business without transferring their copyrights are an example of this; many hardware and software companies that developed older systems are long since out of business and precise documentation of the copyrights may not be readily available.

Often the availability of abandonware on the Internet is related to the willingness of copyright holders to defend their copyrights. For example, unencumbered games for [[Colecovision]] are markedly easier to find on the Internet than unencumbered games for [[Mattel]] [[Intellivision]] in large part because there is still a company that sells to Intellivision games while no such company exists for the Colecovision.

===Case for preservation===
Proponents of abandonware argue that it is more ethical to make copies of such software than new software that still sells.  Those ignorant of copyright law have incorrectly taken this to mean that abandonware is legal to distribute, although no software written since 1964 is old enough for copyright to have expired in the US.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://digital-law-online.info/lpdi1.0/treatise17.html |title=Copyright of Computer Programs | year=2002 | first=Lee |last=Hollaar |accessdate=August 7, 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt; Even in cases where the original company no longer exists, the rights usually belong to someone else, though no one may be able to trace actual ownership, including the owners themselves.

Abandonware advocates also frequently cite historical preservation as a reason for trading abandoned software.&lt;ref name=&quot;ARingFAQ&quot;/&gt; Older computer media are fragile and prone to rapid deterioration, necessitating transfer of these materials to more modern, stable media and generation of many copies to ensure the software will not simply disappear. Users of still-functional older computer systems argue for the need of abandonware because re-release of software by copyright holders will most likely target modern systems or incompatible media instead, preventing legal purchase of compatible software.

Those who oppose these practices argue that distribution denies the copyright holder potential sales, in the form of re-released titles, official emulation, and so on. Likewise, if people can acquire an old version of a program for free, they may be less likely to purchase a newer version if the old version meets their needs.

===US copyright law===
Copyright law does not recognize the term or concept of &quot;abandonware&quot;. There is a long held concept of abandonment in [[trademark law]] as a direct result of the infinite term of trademark protection. Currently, a copyright can be released into the public domain if the owner clearly does so in writing; however this formal process is not considered abandoning, but rather releasing. Those who do not own a copyright cannot merely claim the copyright abandoned and start using protected works without permission of the copyright holder, who could then seek [[legal remedy]].

Hosting and distributing copyrighted software without permission is illegal. Copyright holders, sometimes through the [[Entertainment Software Association]], send cease and desist letters, and some sites have shut down or removed infringing software as a result. However, most of the Association's efforts are devoted to new games, due to those titles possessing the greatest value.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web| url= http://www.wired.com/gaming/gamingreviews/news/2002/01/49723?currentPage=1 | title = Abandonware: Dead Games Live On | publisher = [[Wired (magazine)|Wired]] | last = King | first = Brad | date = January 19, 2002 | accessdate = April 2, 2007}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Copyright expiration===
{{main|List of countries' copyright length}}
Once the copyright on a piece of software has expired, it automatically falls into public domain. Such software can be legally distributed without restrictions. However, due to the length of copyright terms in most countries, this has yet to happen for most software. All countries that observe the [[Berne Convention for the Protection of Literary and Artistic Works|Berne Convention]] enforce copyright ownership for at least 50 years after publication or the author's death. However, individual countries may choose to enforce copyrights for longer periods. In the United States, copyright durations are determined based on authorship. For most published works, the duration is 70 years after the author's death. However, for anonymous works, works published under a pseudonym or works made for hire, the duration is 120 years after publication. In France, copyright durations are 70 years after the relevant date (date of author's death or publication) for either classes.

However, because of the length of copyright enforcement in most countries, it is likely that by the time a piece of software defaults to public domain, it will have long become obsolete, irrelevant, or incompatible with any existing hardware. Additionally, due to the relatively short commercial, as well as physical, lifespans of most digital media, it is entirely possible that by the time the copyright expires for a piece of software, it will no longer exist in any form. However, since the largest risk in dealing with abandonware is that of distribution, this may be mitigated somewhat by private users (or organizations such as the Internet Archive) making private copies of such software, which would then be legally redistributable at the time of copyright expiry.

==See also==
* [[Free-to-play]]
* [[List of commercial games released as freeware]]
* [[Orphaned technology]]
* [[Orphan works]]

==References==
{{Reflist|2}}

==External links==
&lt;!--Abandonware sites have illegal software available, intentionally or unknowingly, so links to such sites can not provided here. They also do not meet Wikipedia standards for external links, which should be educational and not mere web directories--&gt;
* {{cite web| url=http://www.adventureclassicgaming.com/index.php/site/features/160/| title=Abandonwarez: the pros outweigh the cons}}
* {{cite web| url=http://www.gamespot.com/gamespot/features/pc/abandonware/| title=Flashbacks For Free: The Skinny On Abandonware}}

{{software distribution}}

[[Category:Video game culture]]

[[ca:Programari descatalogat]]
[[cs:Abandonware]]
[[de:Abandonware]]
[[et:Hülgvara]]
[[el:Abandonware]]
[[es:Abandonware]]
[[fa:رهاافزار]]
[[fr:Logiciel abandonné]]
[[gl:Abandonware]]
[[ko:어밴던웨어]]
[[it:Abandonware]]
[[he:Abandonware]]
[[hr:Abandonware]]
[[hu:Abandonware]]
[[nl:Abandonware]]
[[ja:アバンダンウェア]]
[[pl:Abandonware]]
[[pt:Abandonware]]
[[ru:Abandonware]]
[[fi:Abandonware]]
[[sv:Abandonware]]
[[uk:Abandonware]]
[[zh:老软件]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
