<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="18013637" ns="0" title="Taukei ni Waluvu"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">'''Taukei ni Waluvu'''  is the [[Fiji]]an picturesque phrase for &quot;Native of the Flood.&quot; It is the traditional chiefly title of the warrior hill clan Siko-Natabutale of Nairukuruku village. The history of the clan from the mid- nineteenth century, represent the  social structures of the chiefly system,religion and western culture that supported colonialism in  Fiji. Tradition,Christianity and British indirect rule were  combined to legitimize what was accepted as the right way to govern. Condemned by some modern day critics as exploitative, the Fijian chiefly system was the medium of native  social interdependence and a traditional contract shared by the indigenous clans of pre-colonial Fiji, that was justly utilized for colonial rule. Since Independence the chiefly system has had to adapt to the demands of modernity.  Anthropologist Arthur Capell in his study of early tribal migration within Fiji made the point that, &quot;the history of Fiji is the history of chiefly families.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;A. Capell, Oceania, &quot;Local Divisions and Movement in Fiji&quot;, Vol X1 No. 4, Jun 1941, p.327.&lt;/ref&gt;The phrase in fact  emphasized  the hierarchical nature of Fijian traditional society where chiefly power was held sacred. The relationship between Chiefs and Westerners in especially Missionaries thus became a focal point for gathering insight into Fijian culture and tradition in the nineteenth century.  
James Turner  a latter  anthropologist found, &quot;The chiefly families of Nairukuruku were the first in the eastern highlands of Viti Levu to declare their allegiance to the central government and as a result of this support their influence expanded through out the area&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;James W Turner, &quot;The Sins of the Father: Rank and Succession in a Fijian Chiefdom&quot;, Oceania, 57:2, Dec 1986, p.128.&lt;/ref&gt;

== The Legend ==

''While I was in Vunidawa, news came through, first communicated by messages on lalis (hollowed- out wooden drums) beaten from village to village that Ratu Manasa the Taukei ni Waluvu (Native or Owner of the Floods), highest chief of Waima, Matailobau and Nagonenicolo districts had died in Nairukuruku... It was standard belief that with the death of the holder of the hereditary title floods would follow for a fortnight. I had to go to the ceremony of reguregu and have presented on my behalf by my matanivanua a whale’s tooth for mourning. It had been fine up till now but on the day after the news the heavens opened with torrents. The river swept up at a forbidding level and with menacing currents''.&lt;ref&gt;Philip Snow, “The Years Of Hope: Cambridge, Colonial Administration In The South Seas And Cricket”, Radcliffe Press, 1997,p. 218,.&lt;/ref&gt;  

- [[United Kingdom|British]] Colonial administrator Philip Snow, 1944. 


[[File:Fiji Pre-Colonial States.PNG |thumb|right| Map of Fiji Pre-Colonial States]]

The Taukei ni Waluvu traditionally  is the leading chief of the chiefdom of Nabena, [[Matailobau District]] that originally consisted of twelve tribes, in [[Naitasiri Province]]. Turner, observed the cultural transformation, where, the high chief of Nabena is not removed from his subjects, but sits in  a more egalitarian rather than a hierarchical village  structure. An outsider's initial impression is that he is ''primus inter pares'' in his district.&lt;ref&gt;Turner, 1986:129.&lt;/ref&gt; [[Matailobau District]] being one of the Pre-Colonial States of Eastern [[Viti Levu]] Island and formerly of Colo East hill province.&lt;ref&gt;Fiji Meuseum, Publication ''Domodomo'', 1984 Vol. 2, No.4.&lt;/ref&gt; In  1945 Colo East merged with [[Naitasiri Province]].  The other Eastern Viti Levu Pre-Colonial States being Verata, Waimaro, [[Bau (island)|Bau]], [[Rewa]], [[Naitasiri]] and [[Namosi]].&lt;ref&gt;Fiji Meuseum Publication, ''Domodomo'', 1986 Vol 4, No.3 .&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:Seruepenisacakobau.jpg|thumb|right|Ratu Seru Apenisa Cakobau Vunivalu of Bau 1852-1883]]
‎
Arriving in Fiji at Lakeba Lau in 1858, zealous Methodist missionary Reverend Frederick Langham, then  stationed on Bau island, had journeyed via Nalawa district Ra, up the Wainimala river headwaters of Viti Levu to Nakorosule-Waimaro. He was then advised by the Nakorosule chief, Rotavisoro and also the nephew of the Taukei ni Waluvu,  that traditional protocol necessitated his uncle Rodavetanivalu, known then as the Taukei Waiburebure of Navaulele be first converted. 

Reverend Wallace Deane quoted the Nakorosule chief saying, ''&quot;If I embrace the religion which you bring, my relatives will be angry with me. My advice is: go to the Taukei Waiburebure at Navaulele. He is my chiefly uncle. If he desires the Lotu (religion), I will accept it also.&quot;'' &lt;ref&gt;Rev W Deane, ''The Strange Adventures of a Whales Tooth, p. 127 ''&lt;/ref&gt; As documented in Fiji Methodist history, Ratu Meli Rodavetanivalu II accepted the ''Lotu'' and  became a nominal Christian through Langham on the 14th September 1862 and was later baptized in 1867. Baun kinship politics through the Tui Nalawa was instrumental in the Taukei ni Waluvu's conversion.

Tradition records that [[Ratu Seru Cakobau]], the [[Vunivalu of Bau]] and [[Tui Viti]], honoured Rodavetanivalu II, Vunivalu of Navaulele for being a staunch ally of his [[Christianization]] and pacification campaigns of the hill tribes by conferring on him the title ‘Owner of the Floods’ or ''Taukei-ni-Uwaluvu'' from his earlier title ''Taukei Waiburebure''. As recorded by Sir John Thurston in April 1868,Ratu  Cakobau in retaliation for the Reverend Thomas Baker massacre, launched a two pronged pacification campaign of the hill tribes- up the Rewa River and from the Ra Coast  with the Soloira and Matailobau tribes as allies&lt;ref&gt;  Deryck Scarr, ‘I the Very Bayonet’, ANU Press, 1973, 1971,pp.76-78.&lt;/ref&gt;. 

[[File:Rev Fredrick Langham.png|thumb|right|Reverend Frederick Langham circa 1890s]]

In a  cabinet memorandum from King Cakobau's  private secretary Henry Milne to his Minister of Native Affairs, Robert Swanston, is evidence of Cakobau's close relations with the Taukei ni Waluvu during the pacification campaign of hill tribes. The memorandum  dated 19 May 1873, announced,&quot; ''The king is now at Matailobau, and has  in conjunction with the chiefs assembled there, determined to go through Viti Levu. The Matailobau as you are aware are very old allies of the king ''&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Memo from the Cabinet to Hon Minister of Native Affairs, Vunisamaloa, Ba Province, 19 May 1873, Pacific Manuscript Bureau, Swanston Collection,  Ra and Ba Military Campaign, Fiji, 1873. Australian National Library.&lt;/ref&gt; Apparently Cakobau's traditional links to the Taukei ni Waluvu can be traced to the Vunivalu's ancestors, the Nadurucoko in Wainibuka and Ra. 

Cakobau's Christianization campaign or ''Valu ni Lotu'' was as  recountered by Robert Nicole, ''&quot;In 1873  the fledgling Cakobau government embarked on a campaign of subjugation in the north and west ( especially Qaliyalatini, Naloto, Magodro, Yakete, Vaturu, Sabeto and Navatusila) and in the central and eastern parts of the interior( especially Nadawarau, Muaira, Waikalou, Soloira, Nalawa, and Nasau).&quot; ''&lt;ref name=&quot;Robert Nicole 2011, p.18&quot;&gt;Robert Nicole, ''Disturbing History:resistance in early colonial Fiji'', University Hawaii Press,2011, p.18&lt;/ref&gt; Nicole continued, ''&quot; With the capture and execution of  numerous Colo chiefs during this campaign, interior districts to the East and North were severely weakened&quot;''.&lt;ref name=&quot;Robert Nicole 2011, p.18&quot;/&gt; 

The campaign was effectively over when Nubutautau, stronghold of the Magodro fell on 11 September 1873 to Cakobau's forces.&lt;ref&gt;David Rutledge, ''Matanitu: the struggle for power in early Fiji'', Institute of Pacific Studies, USP, 1985, p.176.&lt;/ref&gt;

In 1998, a ''meke -i- wau'' (traditional club dance) of Bukuya village in Magodro district in the Province of [[Ba, Fiji|Ba]] performed for the Prime Minister [[Sitiveni Rabuka]],  recounted  the Taukei ni Waluvu’s tribal skirmishes in that part of Viti Levu’s western highlands. 

'''Image''': '''Reverend Frederick Langham''' (1833–1903), Physically impressive with leonine hair and beard, Langham believed himself the champion of the Fijians and  encouraged annexation by Britain. Nicknamed the 'Cardinal',  he lived on Bau Island from 1861 where he won repute among colonists as Cakobau's adviser.

 
According to Fiji [[Wesleyan]] church authority, the more exalted ''Taukei-ni- Waluvu'' title, now bestowed upon the chiefly patron of [[Wesleyan]] [[Christianity]] in the interior of [[Viti Levu]], was metaphorical to the biblical account of Noah's divine commission prior to the great floods.&lt;ref&gt;Book of Genesis, Chp 6-9.&lt;/ref&gt;

Most probably, the title change by [[Ratu Seru Cakobau]] was consistent with Bauan tradition where honorific titles were proclaimed on warriors to signify chivalrous deeds. The [[Vunivalu of Bau]] is said to have embellished his ally’s renown as the traditional rainmaker in preferring the title. In pre-Christian times such a power was credited to the Taukei Waiburebure. This mystical power is thought to still remain with the Taukei ni Waluvu today through the Chiefly clan's ''bete'' (priests) of Nabena village.&lt;ref&gt;''Fiji Times'' feature article, ' The Rainmakers', 29 Jul 2003.&lt;/ref&gt; 

Commodore Goodenough in his journey up the Wainimala river  to Nairukuruku On 21 January 1874, with Reverend Langham and Ratu Timoci Tavanavanua, son of Ratu Cakobau, met  with [Ratu Meli], &quot;the Governor of the twelve tribes of Matailobau, who was the first to ''Lotu'' in these parts.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Commodore J. G. Goodenough, &quot;Memoir and Journal of Commodore Goodenough&quot;, Henry S. King, Co Ltd. London, UK, pp.218-219&lt;/ref&gt; The twelve tribes were made up of  the old tikinas of Lutu, Waima, Matalobau and Nagonenicolo. Furthermore recording that the former heathen chief's, &quot; ''left ear lobe is distended enough to carry a stick from one and a half to two inches in diameter''&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;Commodore J. G. Goodenough, &quot;Memoir and Journal of Commodore Goodenough&quot;, Henry S. King, Co Ltd. London, UK, pp.218-219&lt;/ref&gt; According to Brewster this disfiguring was the fashion of the highlanders where small prized articles were secured in the distended ear lobes.&lt;ref&gt;Brewster,'The Hill Tribes',1922,p.288.&lt;/ref&gt;. 

Ratu Meli Rodavetanivalu II had two sons Ratu Drekenavere and Ratu Isikeli. Ratu Drekenavere  had a daughter Adi Vaciseva who was given firstly to the Tui Namosi, Romatanitobua as a bride though later married the Vunivalu Rara. Their issue, a son Ratu Ilaitia Baleinaivalu, was later Buli Lomaivuna. Ratu Isikeli  was once  Buli Nalawa in Ra Province. He  had a son, Ratu Sailosi (1898-1932),raised on Bau Island as a youth, he  died heirless. Ratu Meli hence  did not have  any surviving male issue. 
Legend has it, that, Ratu Meli had a canine pet named ''Tui Colo'', which probably was a gift from Reverend Langham.&lt;ref&gt;http://adbonline.anu.edu.au/biogs/A050067b.htme&lt;/ref&gt; The black dog, possibly the first canine recorded in the hills, was a status symbol for the chief. Ratu Meli died during the measles epidemic that ravished [[Fiji]] and indeed  the hill tribes from January to June 1875. Tui Colo was buried alive with his fallen master in his grave mound at Navunitavola-Navaulele. A probable Christian compromise to heathen burial rites where in former times, the high chief's wives would have been strangled to accompany him to the underworld.
On Ratu Meli Davetanivalu II's  demise, his elder brothers- Rovucago III and Rinabobo II descendants according to  chiefly succession tradition have held the title ''Taukei ni Waluvu''.

[[File:FijianChiefs.jpg|thumb|right|High Chiefs of Fiji 1880s.]]

'''Image: Chiefs of Fiji.1880s''' Ratu Isikeli Roraqoca Davetanivalu - ''Turaga Buli'' and son of Taukei ni Waluvu Ratu Meli Davetanivalu II seated first left in second row.
A photograph showing a group of Fijian chiefs, sitting in two rows in front of the verandah of Government House at Suva. The occasion is not certain. It is most probable the chiefs as  Roko Tui’s -head provincial administrators were invited by the Governor to celebrate either the Golden Jubilee of the Methodist Church in Fiji in 1885 or  Queen Victoria’s Golden Jubilee on 20 June 1887. All were High Chiefs in their own right.

Sir Arthur Gordon Fiji’s first substantive Governor in establishing colonial rule from 1875 to 1878, had  originally created 12 Provinces headed by Roko Tui’s and two hill Provinces on Viti Levu- Colo East and Colo West headed by  respective Governor's Commissioners.&lt;ref&gt;Deryck Scarr, 'A Roko Tui for Lomaiviti: The Question of Legitimacy in the Fijian Administration 1874-1900, ' The Journal Of Pacific History, vol 5, 1970, p.4.&lt;/ref&gt;  In 1893 another Commissionship, Colo North was created from these two Colo Provinces and from areas of Ra, Ba and the Yasawa group. 

1-6 left to right, front row: 1. Ratu Kinivuai Nacagilevu Roko Tui Kadavu; 2. Ratu Kinijoji Katonivere, Rokotui Macuata; 3. Ratu Vuniani Vuki, Rokotui Ba; 4. Ratu Epeli Nailatikau, Rokotui Tailevu ; 5. Ratu Marika Toroca, Rokotui Lomaiviti; 6. Ratu Joji Vakawalitabua  Rokotui Bua.

7-13 left to right, back row: 7. Buli from Colo East Ratu Isikeli Roragoca Davetanivalu; 8. Ratu Peni Tanoa, Rokotui Naitasiri; 9. Buli from Colo West (Taukei Noikoro?); 10. Ratu Luke Nakulanikoro, Rokotui Nadroga; 11. Ratu Tevita Rasuraki Rokotui Ra; 12. Ratu Timoci Tavanavanua, Rokotui   Rewa; 13. Ro Matanitobua, Rokotui Namosi. 

Missing are Rokotui Cakaudrove Province, Ratu Josefa Lalabalavu and Rokotui Lau Province, Roko Eroni Loganimoce. Originally Tailevu and Naitasiri counted for one Province with Ratu Epeli Nailatikau as Roko Tui. In 1882 the Province was split in two with Ratu Peni Tanoa as Rokotui Naitasiri. In 1877 Serua Province was carved from Rewa Province under a ‘Buli- Roko’ Ratu Kinijoji Gagabokola.

== History and ethnology ==
According to Adolf Brewster,(see [[Joske's Thumb]]), Commissioner Colo East 1884-90, and elaborated by Arthur Capell, the genealogies of the hill tribes tend to go back some eleven or twelve generations from the time of Brewster's research. [[Basil Thomson]] and Brewster had worked on a basis of thirty years to a generation. So granting it, the founder seems to in each case to have lived about AD 1600.&lt;ref&gt;''The Hill Tribes of Fiji'', p. 71 and Oceania:1941:p.324&lt;/ref&gt;

The Taukei ni Waluvu clan trace their ancestry to Rokowai who founded their tokatoka Natabutale lineage at Nakamarusi around 1600 AD.&lt;ref name=&quot;NLC Tukutuku Raraba 1924&quot;&gt;NLC Tukutuku Raraba, Yavusa Siko, Dec 1924.&lt;/ref&gt; Rokowai's ancestry through his father Rokovucago high chief of Navunidakua is traced back to Robonowai, the son with mystical powers of the Tui Nalawa in [[Ra]] and the Nakauvadra migration. Clan folklore tells that Rokowai, who was the insolent and audacious youngest son in the chiefly household, had to flee the village as his brothers led by Nayacakuru had hatched a plot to harm him. The young chief fled with members of the chiefly clan’s ''bati'', ''sauturaga'', ''matanivanua'' and ''bete'' who were loyal to him. Their  descendants still reside with the Taukei ni Waluvu in Nairukuruku and its older stronghold sister village Taulevu.
The Taukei ni Waluvu as head of Yavusa Siko includes the mataqalis: Siko Natabutale (Nairukuruku), Siko Navunisalusalu of Taulevu village (Matailobau District), Siko Navunidakua of Naqara village (Waima District) and Siko Koroqele of Nakorovatu village (Waima District).

[[File:Spear meke.jpg|thumb|right|''Meke Wesi''- Spear Dance, Nakorovatu, Matailobau 1881.]]

'''Image''': A  group of traditionally dressed Matailobau warriors with charcoal blackened faces in three lines grasping their spears and leaning forward on their war clubs. Most are wearing turban like head gear. Behind them are densely thatched village buildings, and two groups of people sitting watching from a distance at Nakorovatu, Matailobau, 1881.

Rokowai's older brothers were Nayacakuru, Rosauturaga and Rovakacodrowai.&lt;ref name=&quot;NLC Tukutuku Raraba 1924&quot;/&gt;  Rokowai's wife Kororava was from the Vunimoli clan of Waidracia village. Rokowai had five sons :Rokotokalau, Rorairuku, Rotabuwaiwai, Rocaginidaveta( no issue) and Iranaqarikau. Clan legend also narrates, that Rokowai’s manna was manifested when a fire burnt only the  thatching of his great ''bure'' without destroying its wooden framed structure. The Clans founding ancestor's ''yavu'' was thus bestowed the name ''Nakamarusi'' or ‘burnt thatching’. Celebrated female author [[Constance Gordon-Cumming]] describes Nakamarusi on her visit to the village stronghold on 27 December 1875, “the village of Nakamerousi [sic] had attracted my especial admiration. It is perched on a steep bank, and looks right along a broad reach of the river to a beautiful mountain range.”&lt;ref&gt;C. F. Gordon Cummings, ''Home in Fiji'', Pub. William Blackwood &amp; Sons London, 1885, p. 108.&lt;/ref&gt; 

The clan's movements is traced from Navunidakua (district of Waima) to Nakamarusi, then onto the hill features: Taulevu, Ulira and Navaulele respectively, and finally to present Nairukuruku.&lt;ref&gt;NLC Tukutuku Raraba, Yavusa Siko, Dec 1924&lt;/ref&gt; Rokowai's youngest son Iranaqarikau's sons were : Iranabobo I, Naitege, Tabuadunaki and Rovucago II. Iranaqarikau's wife was Ro Ligatabua from Nasautoka. Their youngest son Rovucago II was installed at Navaulele as Taukei Waiburbure and Vunivalu by the clans of Nabubuco, Navitilevu and Vusovuso.

Navaulele and Ulira were the hill fortifications and pre-Christian villages of the Taukei ni Waluvu, situated just a kilometer due west from present Nairukuruku across the Wainimala river. From these two strategic locations, the clan's influence and power were projected into the Waimaro and Navitilevu tribal heartlands of eastern [[Viti Levu]]. Both these koro ni valu (war villages) were heavily fortified and sat surrounded by ringed dry moats to protect from other marauding and warring hill tribes. The other Siko clan’s fortified village close to Nairukuruku of Taulevu where the ''yavu'' (bure foundation) of ''Natabutale'' is built, looks east into the Wainibuka and Verata heartlands.

The chiefly clan had moved out of its hill fortification onto the Nairukuruku river plain after the conversion to Christianity by Reverend Frederick Langham of chief Ratu Meli Davetanivalu at Navaulele on September 14, 1862.
As recountered by Reverend Deane, two Nalawa chiefs, Sogonaivi and Naqari who accompanied Rev. Langham played a part in Ratu Meli, the Taukei ni Waluvu's, conversion to [[Christianity]].
The relocation from Navaulele to the present spectacular Nairukuruku river valley was only possible in post Christian times after belligerent surrounding tribes shunning [[Christianity]] and colonial encroachment were subdued and converted.

Taukei ni Waluvu, Roraiova I, son of Rovucago II, in his tribal wars known as the 'Valu ni Lulu', is credited for spreading the clan's power and influence throughout Tholo East, up to Vatusekiyasawa village on the northern coast of [[Viti Levu]] to include an alliance with the Tui [[Bua]]&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.fijitimes.com/story.aspx?id=115705 |title=For Fiji ever Fiji - Fiji Times Online |publisher=Fijitimes.com |date=2009-03-02 |accessdate=2010-03-06}}&lt;/ref&gt; on [[Vanua Levu]]. Roraiova's son Roradibi was  skilled in the use of musketry firearms that was a marked advantage over traditional hand weapons in these inter tribal skirmishes.

The Taukei ni Waluvu and his subject hill tribes are warriors (bati balavu) foremost to the ancient tribal state of [[Verata]] and later also to the pre-colonial states of Waimaro, [[Namosi]] and [[Bau (island)|Bau]]. With these pre-colonial states the Taukei ni Waluvu has the traditional ''veibatiki'' relationship which is still extant today.

[[File:Meke iri-bitu.jpg|thumb|right|''Meke iri-bitu''-Nakorovatu, Matailobau1881.]]

'''Image''': Fan and Bamboo War Dance, Nakorovatu, 1881.
Formal photograph of two lines of traditionally dressed men holding circular fans. Many wear turban like head gear, and two have feathery head dresses. All are wearing necklaces or a variety of pendants, some in the form of large circular chest ornaments. Beyond them can be seen people watching, and beyond them the buildings of the village.

[[Arthur Maurice Hocart]] the noted anthropologist from 1909-14 did field research into the kinship relationships in the highlands of Colo East and Colo West. He studied the familial relationships of Nairukuruku chief and Taukei ni Waluvu, Ratu Alipate Baledrokadroka and the neighbouring chief of Nakorosule, Tui Waimaro and published what is known today as the Principle of Alternate Generations such as the ''Tako-Lavo'' relationship of the hill tribes of Viti Levu.&lt;ref name=&quot;jstor1&quot;&gt;http://www.jstor.org/pss/2789558&lt;/ref&gt;

By tribal migration movements and marital linkages the more prominent ancient hill tribes such as the Yavusa: Nasautoka, Navitilevu,Burenitu,Noemalu, Navatusila, Waimaro, Nabubuco, Nabukebuke, Nacobicibici, Dreketi, Rara, Viria and Vuna are traditionally blood linked to the Yavusa Siko of the Taukei ni Waluvu.  Hence pre-christian  names of renowned Vunivalu’s such as Rovucago of   the Noemalu tribe, Robatiratu of the Nabukebuke tribe and Roragoca of the Soloira tribe were all bestowed on generations of Taukei ni Waluvu chiefs known as ''vaka toka yaca.'' In pre-Christian days, the name of a chief was sacred and in later generations his name was  only bestowed on a close blood relative.

[[File:Meke Wau nakorovatu,1881.jpg|thumb|right|''Meke Wau''- Nakorovatu,Matailobau 1881.]]

'''Image''': Formally grouped men in traditional dress, most of them shouldering war clubs, and some wearing necklaces. A number also have turban-like hats on their heads. Behind them are Fijian village buildings of dense thatch at Nakorovatu, Matailobau, 1881.

== Nairukuruku - totemism, Christianity and political ascendancy ==
[[File:14-L.jpg|thumb|right|Nairukuruku Village Christmas Day 1875.]]
The picturesque village of Nairukuruku, home of the Taukei ni Waluvu in the district of Matailobau, was inhabited around 1872.That year fighting had broken out between the converted Matailobau tribes and the ''tevoro'' Lomai Colo tribes causing this re-location from Navaulele.
&quot;Nairukuruku&quot; - translated means - &quot;an entrance&quot;, probably due to its strategic location into the highlands by river and by land. Moreover, the entry and spread of Christianity into the eastern highlands of Viti Levu from this village is well documented.
A contending interpretation of the word &quot;rukuruku&quot; is taken from the native indigenous Naga religious cult with that of bygone ceremonies.&lt;ref name=&quot;A. Brewester, p. 95&quot;&gt;A. Brewester, ''The Hill Tribes of Fiji'', p. 95&lt;/ref&gt; The cult of ''Visina'' corresponded with that of [[Baal]] and ''Rukuruku'' with [[Ashtoreth]], the ancient deities signifying the creative and the productive powers of nature - eg ruku (the feminine) and sina (native spear grass) the masculine symbol.&lt;ref name=&quot;A. Brewester, p. 95&quot;/&gt; Thus the name ''Nairukuruku'' has a relationship and significance to the clans creative totemic symbols towards the feminine fertility.

'''Image''':'''Nairukuruku Village''' in foreground,on  Christmas Day 1875.Looking south-west from Taulevu ridge with Wainimala river flowing from right to left. Highest  feature is Nariko  peak  in left farground. Other features shown are Nacau and Ulira peaks in right mid-ground. Established a few years earlier after re-locating from  Navaulele, the village is surrounded by a dry  moat. The large ''bure'' within the village is the church. Notably two homesteads outside the village  to the west are that of the native minister and Ratu Viliame Batiratu's residence by the river named ''yavu- ni-turaga levu''. Artist: Constance Gordon-Cumming (1837–1924).
 
The chiefly clan's totemic plant and animal, the ''Vico'' - native spear grass and the ''Vo loa'' - black mud fish is the living heathen symbols to the tribes masculinity and warrior class. Traditionally the Yavusa Siko is ''bati'' and protectors of the feminine totemic tribes representing fertility such as the Waimaro clan of the eastern highlands. The Siko Natabutale clan's treasured feminine ''Radiniwaimaro'' statuette in Taulevu village attests to this.&lt;ref&gt;A Brewester, ''The Hill Tribes of Fiji''&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Rev. W. DEANE&quot;Fijian society; or, The sociology and psychology of the Fijians&quot;, 1921, Chap VII pp 69-71.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;http://www.jstor.org/pss/25169337&lt;/ref&gt;


According to Methodist history, Reverend [[Thomas Baker (missionary)]], on his fateful journey spreading the gospel through the hills of Navosa in July 1867, passed through the Taukei ni Waluvu's Christian enclave on the east bank of the Wainimala river. In Methodist  folklore, the tabua (whales tooth) sealing the plot to ambush Reverend Baker, had preceded him along the  non Christian west bank of the Wainimala river.&lt;ref&gt;Rev Elimeleki Susu, ‘The history of Methodist Theological education in Fiji until 1973’ Pacific Theological College, Suva, Fiji, 2009.&lt;/ref&gt; 

 
Deed of Cession Commissioner Commodore G. J. Goodenough&lt;ref&gt;http://adbonline.anu.edu.au/biogs/A040297b.htm&lt;/ref&gt; and Reverend Frederick Langham also visited Nairukuruku on 21–22 January 1874 which was then the foremost Christianized village in the upper Wainimala river of Colo East. At Nairukuruku Goodenough makes a proclamation prohibiting white settlers the use of native Fijians especially the belligerent 'Kai Colos' as plantation slave labour. According to Siko Natabutale clan history Ratu Viliame Batiratu representing his uncle the Taukei ni Waluvu, Ratu Meli Davetanivalu who was frail, was part of the [[Vunivalu of Bau]], Ratu Seru Cakobau’s entourage to Levuka Ovalau for cession on 10 October 1874. 
As a village loyal to the new religion of Christianity and later central government, Nairukuruku was a potential target for attack by non-Christian neighbours resisting Cakobau's interference in their affairs.&lt;ref&gt;Turner, 1986:134&lt;/ref&gt; Nairukuruku became known as ‘''na Bau ni Colo’'' or ‘the [[Bau (island)|Bau]] (island) of the highlands’ due to its rise as the seat of political power. It became the call centre for all [[Colony|Colonial]] visitors into the eastern highlands of [[Viti Levu]].

[[File:Constance Frederica Gordon-Cumming.jpg‎|thumb|right|Constance Frederica Gordon-Cumming.

]]

The first [[Europe]]an females to visit Nairukuruku and indeed the highlands were writer [[Constance Gordon-Cumming]] and Reverend Fredrick Langham's wife Ann Elizabeth, who had accompanied the minister to the Christian enclave village where they spent Christmas in 1875.&lt;ref&gt;C. F. Gordon Cummings, ''Home in Fiji'', Pub. William Blackwood &amp; Sons London, 1885. pp 85-107.&lt;/ref&gt; Ms Gordon-Cumming mused, “indeed we are the first specimens of the race whom they have seen!”&lt;ref&gt;C. F. Gordon Cummings, ''Home in Fiji'', Pub. William Blackwood &amp; Sons London, 1885. p.86&lt;/ref&gt; During her three day Christmas stay at Nairukuruku she also captures in her annals, a mass Christian marriage ceremony, a mass native school examination and native life in general that was coming into contact with western civilization. Her water-colour painting of Nairukuruku village and its spectacular surrounds on Christmas Day 1875 is a rare depiction of  Viti Levu's eastern highlands landscape.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.internationalartcentre.co.nz/auctions/auctionDetail.lsd?a=201003&amp;p=14&amp;-session=Artcentre:96CBE6210f5be1D5F6vkjs2B48B9&lt;/ref&gt;

In November 1979 anthropologist James W. Turner conducted a 17 month field research into [[Fijian]] customs and traditions in Nairukuruku village. He published his observations  in academic journals titled : ‘True Food and First Fruits: Rituals of Increase in Fiji', 1984, ‘Owners of the Path: Cognatic Kinship Categories in Matailobau, Fiji', 1986, ‘The Sins of the Father: Rank and Succession in a Fijian Chiefdom', 1986, 'The water of life:kava ritual and the logic of sacrifice', 1986, 'Blessed to Give and Receive: Ceremonial Exchange in Fiji', 1987, 'A Sense of Place: Locus and Identity in Matailobau, Fiji', 1988 and 'Rituals, Habitus and Hierarchy in Fiji,’1992.

In  'Rituals, Habitus and Hierarchy in Fiji', Turner studied the Fijian hierarchical system in Nairukuruku through the social interaction where the ''Yagona'' ritual is clearly implicated in the reproduction of hierarchy reinforcing the clans status.&lt;ref&gt;James W Turner, ‘Rituals, Habitus and Hierarchy in Fiji’, Ethnology, Vol 31, No. 4, Oct 1992, pp. 291-302.&lt;/ref&gt;



With a population of 300, five mataqali’s or clans reside together in Nairukuruku village. They are namely: Siko Natabutale(chiefly clan), Nawaita (warriors), Nabubuco (chief’s elders), Nakorowaqa (heralds), and Navitilevu (warriors).

== Cakobau's Christian wars ==
One of the better known of Cakobau’s Christian conversion wars was at Nasorovakawalu.&lt;ref&gt;A B Brewster, Hiil Tribes of Fiji, 1922, p.64.&lt;/ref&gt; Both Ratu Cakobau and Ratu Meli were present at Nakorovatu for the final assault on the heathen stronghold across the Wainimala river. Imbued with religious fervour, some 1500 warriors of Matailobau, Naloto, Lomaiviti, Suva, Sabeto [[Nadi]] and even students of the [[Methodist]] Training School, Navuloa Bau laid siege on this last heathen hill fort in the highlands. In May 1873, the stronghold was finally given up  after  months of  siege warfare. Brewster recounts, &quot; Heralds were sent in with strings of Whales' teeth to ''soro'' or beg his majesty's pardon and sue humbly for peace.&quot; Cakobau accepted the overtures as he thought his army had done enough for honour and glory.&lt;ref&gt;Brewster, p.65&lt;/ref&gt; A local Matailobau account stated that,  Ratu Cakobau had ordered his musketmen perched up trees with Snider rifles to fire volleys simultaneously in support of the final eighth assault. In celebration of this victory the bure that was built for Ratu Cakobau at Nakorovatu was given the yavu name ''Na- ka- u- kaya'' (as I ordered).

After this successful siege, in May 1873, a Christianization campaign or ''Valu ni Lotu'' was launched across the highlands of Viti Levu by Cakobau's Christian forces from Nakorovatu Matailobau which included the Taukei ni Waluvu's forces.

[[File:Batiratu.jpg|thumb|right|Ratu Viliame Batiratu and Family 1881.]]
[[File:Vuravura.jpg|thumb|right|'' Vuravura''- Ratu Viliame's great ''bure'', Nakorovatu, 1881.]]

Ratu Viliame Batiratu, The Colo Lieutenant Governor in Cakobau's Government and later  the Buli Matailobau, with his tribal army played a supporting role in Major James Harding's Wainimala pacification campaign of Muaira, Noimalu and Nagonenicolo in 1874. The beligerant tribes of the Lomai Colo led by the Vunivalu of Noemalu, Rovucago, put up  stirling resistance but were finally overpowered by well drilled soldiers. The Lomai Colo tribes then sued for peace.  Ratu Viliame was to play a prominent role in the administration of Colo East province as the leading Buli or 'Turaga Levu' (Great Chief), from 1874 and resigning from government services in 1896 though remaining on the payroll until 1908.&lt;ref&gt;Turner, 1986:136.&lt;/ref&gt;

'''Image''': '''Ratu Viliame Batiratu''' Taukei ni Waluvu 
and  Buli Matailobau with wife Adi Kelera 
Romaramanitabua
and niece Roeseta.Most unlike Fijian custom of the day,this is a rare photograph of a nineteenth century Fijian chief taken with his wife. Further more  as in European etiquette the chief’s wife is sitting  whilst he stood.  

The measles epidemic of 1875 raised suspicion within the hill tribes of a foreign conspiracy given that they were still practising old native beliefs and ways. This event could be said to be the second chapter in the clash of cultures between Fijian traditional belief and western contact.
Peace ensued when, on October 28, 1876, Governor Sir [[Arthur Hamilton-Gordon, 1st Baron Stanmore]] issued a proclamation pardoning all belligerent hill tribes, bringing to a close the third chapter of the clash of cultures - one of tribal versus colonial rule in the highlands of [[Viti Levu]].

'''Image''': '' Vuravura''- Ratu Viliame's great ''bure'', Nakorovatu, 1881. Ms Constance Gordon-Cumming in her description of its interior in December 1875 effused, &quot;Eight large trees form the main pillars, 
while upwards of one hundred fine tree-ferns have been sacrificed 
to make the small black pillars on either side. The walls are of 
double reeds, crossed ; very beautiful patterns of fine sinnet-work 
(i.e., coloured string), on the lintels, and hanging curtains of long 
grass&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;Constance Gordon-Cumming, ''At Home in Fiji'', p.84.&lt;/ref&gt;
[[File:Sir Arthur Hamilton Gordon.jpg|thumb|right|'''Sir Arthur Gordon''' First Governor of Fiji (1875–1880)]]

As a symbolic token of Batiratu’s suzerainty, a basket of earth from the districts under his rule as Colo Governor prior to Cession from as far as Nailega on the Wainibuka river  to Nagone-ni-colo on the Wainimala river, were brought to form the foundation of his great bure ''Vuravura'' at Nakorovatu.

== Colo East merges with Naitasiri ==
When the Wainimala campaign of 1874 and the &quot;little war&quot; of 1876 in central Viti Levu were finished, Sir Arthur Gordon thought that the lately subjugated hill tribes, were scarcely fitted then for the rigidity of British Law.
He therefore caused an Ordinance to be passed in the Legislative Council of the colony to provide for the jurisdiction of the &quot;lately disturbed districts of [[Viti Levu]]&quot;, as the preamble put it.

For administrative purposes the lately disturbed districts were divided into two provinces- Colo West and Colo East.&lt;ref&gt;''The Hill Tribes of Fiji'', p. 47&lt;/ref&gt; Colo  North was later carved out of these two hill provinces and Ra, Ba and Yasawa provinces in 1893. Colo East was made up of the districts of Nailega, Nasautoka, Lutu, Waima, Matailobau, Soloira, Nadaravakawalu, Muaira, Nagonenicolo, Noemalu and later Nabubuco.
Nairukuruku is the leading village in [[Matailobau District]]. Ratu Viliame Batiratu-the first Buli Matailobau chose to name his district, Matailobau in recognition of the clan who gave shelter to Rokowai - the Siko Natabutale clans founding ancestor who fled the ancestral village of Navunidakua.

[[File:Colo Viti Levu Fiji Map.jpg|thumb|right|'''Map of Colo Provinces''', Viti Levu, Fiji. Scale: 1:517625
]]

 
[[File:Andsell expedition Navuniyasi.jpg|thumb|right|Andsell Expedition at Navuniyasi Village 1881.]]
In 1945, due to colonial native administrative restructure initiated by Ratu Sir [[Lala Sukuna]], Colo East province with nine tikinas including Matailobau and Vunidawa government station as its centre was merged into [[Naitasiri]] province. The two Wainibuka tikinas of Colo East-Nailega and Nasautoka were separately joined to [[Tailevu]] province. After the provincial merger five districts or tikinas of: Naitasiri, Matailobau, Waimaro Wainimala and Lomaivuna were created. Ratu Isikeli Roraqoca the eldest grand son of Ratu Viliame Robatiratu became the ''Turaga Buli'' Matailobau from 1945-62 stationed at Nakorovatu village, Vunidawa. The only reminder of the Colo East hill province at Vunidawa today is the prominent stone memorial to its illustrious son and Taukei ni Waluvu Doctor Ratu Jemesa Bonowai(1866–1937) atop the government station hill.

The 1881 Gerrard Ansdell expedition of Colo East via the Wainimala and Wainibuka rivers is most revealing of all aspects of life in the hill province as many photographs were taken that is preserved in the Alexander Turnbull Library New Zealand today.&lt;ref&gt;see http://timeframes.natlib.govt.nz&lt;/ref&gt;


'''Image''': Andsell expedition at Navuniyasi Village, on Wainimala river, 1881.The Dreketi and Nasautoka clans reside in this Matailobau village.




[[File:Cms Fiji 1888.jpg|thumb|right|Central Medical School,Fiji-first native graduates 1888.]]

== Methodist Church - Matailobau/Wainimala Division ==
The conversion to Christianity and allegiance to Baun hegemony came at a price for Ratu Meli Davetanivalu II and his clan.
Reverend Wallace Deane in ''The strange adventures of a whales tooth'', gives a detailed account of the tribal skirmishes of the Taukei ni Waluvu from 1862-1874. For amongst belligerent heathen hill tribes, the Taukei ni Waluvu and his warrior people were a major influence in the spread of Christianity and British colonialism in the hills of the main island of [[Viti Levu]].

'''Image''': '''Ratu Jemesa Robonowai'''(1866–1937), Taukei ni Waluvu, standing third from right. Seated centre cross legged is Ratu Feretariki Lagamu Temesia, grandson of Ratu Seru Cakobau, one of  first three graduates of Central Medical School in 1888. Also  seated below Ratu Jemesa is Dr W Mcgregor, the head of CMS.


The alliance that Ratu Meli made with [[Ratu Seru Cakobau]], sat oddly with his 'bati' role to Verata and blood links to other hill tribes. However this propelled him and his clan as the leading Colo East entity for Bauan, Christian and colonial domination. Davetanivalu's stronghold village Navaulele then Nairukuruku thus became  the seat of the Methodist church divisional superintendent for Matailobau/Wainimala division with a lay persons training centre. Previously the Matailobau division came under the Bau division. 

According to Rev. Deane, some of the Christian teachers from coastal villages who laboured spreading the gospel amongst the heathen tribes and paid the ultimate sacrifice for their faith at Navaulele were: Taitusi, from Nairai; Pita from Rewa, Rupeni from Dravo, Nafitalai from Namuka, Solomoni from Nakoroivau, Nemani, from Waikete, and Nasoni, from Buretu. Reverend Setareki Nasilivata of the warrior clan- Nawaita was Nairukuruku's first Methodist minister from 1914-45.


[[File:Nairukuruku School 1881.jpg|thumb|right|Nairukuruku Methodist School 1881.]]

As a glowing credit to the Wesleyan missions life and village advancement at Nairukuruku in 1884, Brewester observed &lt;blockquote&gt;About four miles further up the Wainimala from Vunidawa was Nairukuruku, the seat of Ratu Jona the native minister in charge of my province. He had a small preparatory school where aspirants for the ministry received their preliminary training. Order and discipline were combined with good native customs and the students whilst being educated, were self supporting, maintained their own food supply and kept their houses neat and tidy. When I got hipped and bored by the life on the station, I would frequently go over to Nairukuruku and spend the day. Sometimes when Naval Officers and others visited me I took them over there to hear the students choir sing Moody and Sankey's hymns. We use to ride over and return by water for the sake of the fun of canoe travelling, shooting the rapids and getting a pot at the ducks. Ratu Jona's wife was an excellent cook, and generally regalled her guests with savory dishes of chicken stewed with yams and shallots.&lt;ref&gt;''Hill tribes of Fiji'', p. 148.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt; 

'''Image''':Nairukuruku School, 1881. Formal school group, the teachers standing at the back, the children sitting in front. Behind them is part of the roof and walls of a large densely thatched building probably the church and community hall( see Nairukuruku painting 1875). The teachers are wearing clothing of white cotton fabric in the form of sulu vaka viti, skirts, short sleaved tops and long sleaved shirts.

Rev Ratu Jona Uluinaceva of Kadavu was native pastor of Matailobau circuit from 1881-1893. He was preceded by Rev Taito Rauluni (1876–1881) and Rev Rusiate Vunivalu (?-1875). Rev Jona Uluinaceva was succeeded by Reverends: Nasoni Tuisinu (1894–1903), Rev Pita Tuidela (1903–06) and Rev Filimone Waqaniveitaqavi (1906-?) respectively.  Distinguished graduates of Nairukuruku preparatory school were Taukei ni Waluvu Doctor Ratu Jemesa Robonowai (1866–1937) who was one of the first Fijian native medical practitioners in 1888, Doctor Ratu Jone Roraiova (1904–34) and Doctor Ratu Waisea Radibi (1901–32).

[[File:Taito Rauluni.jpg|thumb|right|Rev Taito Rauluni and Family, Native Minister at Nairukuruku, 1881.]]
 
In 1885, the fiftieth anniversary of [[Methodism]] in Fiji, a prominent contingent of Australian Methodists visited Nairukuruku to witness first hand the spread of Christianity in the highlands of Fiji. In addition to church festivities, they were treated to a spectacle of native dances and an insight into hill people tribal culture by the Taukei ni Waluvu and Buli Matailobau Ratu Viliame Batiratu.

== Cultivation and Viti Kabani ==
In the 1900s, the surrounding Nairukuruku river plains were cultivated with bananas as the major cash crop. The village banana farmers became exponents of the Viti Kabani movement and the quest by its enigmatic founder Apolosi Ranawai for native indigenous commercial enterprise against the wishes of colonial administrators.&lt;ref&gt;Robert Nicole, ''Disturbing History: Resistance in Early Colonial Fiji'', University Of Hawaii Press, 2011, pp.70-97.&lt;/ref&gt; Ranawai had  founded  his Company at Nakorovatu, Matailobau where in 1912, as a carpenter he  was building a church.&lt;ref&gt;Robert Nicole, ''Disturbing History: Resistance in Early Colonial Fiji'', University Of Hawaii Press, 2011, p.86.&lt;/ref&gt;  Ratu Esira Rovucago V (1870–1934) of Nairukuruku was the secretary for the Viti Kabani in Colo East at the height of its popularity from 1913-1917. With the demise of the banana industry many villagers left to seek employment in the gold mines of [[Vatukoula]] and the tourism industry of western [[Viti Levu]]. Today subsistence market farming is the major village income earner with many families having left for urban living.

==Chiefly Dualism of Tui and Vunivalu  fused in title of  Taukei ni Waluvu==
 
Arthur Hocart and Marshall Shalin studied the diarchic relationship between the sacred king known as  ''Tui'' and the warlord known as ''Vunivalu'' in Fijian traditional society. Both Anthropologists  examined the chiefly dualism of the Kubuna clan between the Rokotui Bau and the Vunivalu Tui Kaba and the Burebasaga clan between the Rokotui Dreketi and the Vunivalu of Rewa. Christina Toren also examined  the distinct antithetical nature  of  traditional Fijian leadership.&lt;ref&gt;see C Toren, Oceania 64:3 (1994), 199 'All things go in pairs or the sharks will bite'&lt;/ref&gt; In Fijian hierarchical society, the ''Vunivalu'' was the war lord and  second in chiefly status to the ''Tui'' or sacred king. The distinct title Ratu or Ro was the honorific prefix to the names of descendants of the Tui and Vunivalu. Through the martial exploits of the Vunivalu, the extension of a powerful tribe’s authority  over other tribes formed the Vanua and Matanitu or pre-colonial state.

In the clan  of Nabukebuke Namosi however, this dualism is morphed in the paramount chief holding both titles, Tui Namosi and Vunivalu. Robatiratu was the vunivalu at the yavutu of Nabukebuke at Wailase in the  Wainimala highlands.&lt;ref&gt;A Capell and R Lester, 'Local Divisions and Movements in Fiji', Oceania, Jun 1941, vol xi, no.4, p.332.&lt;/ref&gt; 
Under the leadership of  Ronawaqaliva and his brother Rodrodrolagi, the clan then moved to Nairairaikinabukebuke, Mount Voma where they built a village  on the left bank of the Waidina river and called it Namosi. The Vunivalu  of the Nabukebuke clan was also installed  Tui Namosi at this village. 

In the senior division of the Waimaro clan of Soloira, Colo East, the practice of chiefly dualism was also witnessed by Brewster in the 1880s stating, “The head chief at Serea was Roraqoca. He was the Vunivalu or fighting chief of his clan. Associated with him was Tui Waikalou or the Lord of Waikalou.”&lt;ref&gt;AB Brewster, The Hill Tribes of Fiji, 1922, pp.226-227.&lt;/ref&gt;

Roraiova I of the yavusa Siko Natabutale was renowned for his martial exploits amongst the hill tribes of Colo East. His tribal skirmishes became known as the Valu ni Lulu. The Vanua of Matailobau was formed through the exploits of Roraiova I.  

Roraiova I was the son of Rovucago II who was installed with the moniker Taukei Waiburebure and who was the grandson of Rokowai (circa1600 AD) the founder of the Natabutale clan. Rokowai’s father was Rovucago I, chief of the yavutu of Navunidakua. Rokovucago I chiefly lineage is traced to the Tui Nalawa in Ra through his son Robonowai. From about the mid nineteenth century the bestowing of the sacred leadership or Tui of the Siko Natabutale clan was handed down  by Rodavetanivalu I of Taulevu to his namesake Ratu Meli Rodavetanivalu II of Navaulele. 

Rodavetanivalu I  the great grandson of Rokowai at Taulevu fortress on being struck with leprosy had sent for  his namesake Davetanivalu II from Navaulele fortress  to handover the sacred king title and leadership of the clan.&lt;ref&gt;Tukutuku Raraba Yavusa Siko, 2 December 1924, p.107.&lt;/ref&gt; Rodavetanivalu I's father was Robaledrokadroka I also of Taulevu.

After the death of Davetanivalu II in 1875 the two chiefly titles of Tui and Vunivalu has rested within the tokatoka’s of: Nakamarusi, Dakui, Navaulele, Nakacadakui and Vuravura of the matagali turaga –Siko Natabutale. The choice of a hereditary chief to the office of Taukei ni Waluvu was according to male seniority or ''veitarataravi vaka veitacini''. Ones mother’s chiefly status or ''vasu turaga taukei'' and the elders advice ''na nodra rai na qase ni vanua'' were also taken into account. After the establishment of Christianity, being born within wedlock or ''luve ni vaka mau'' became important for a chiefs claim to leadership within most clans. 

Furthermore within Siko Natabutale clan tradition,in line with its founding ancestor Rokowai, the younger lineage inherited the ancestral spirit and wisdom or ''kalougata kei na mana'' as Tui. This tradition also conforms to the principle of alternate generation as practiced within the hill tribes  where a grandchild is a brother to his grandfather (tutua). As evidenced 
Ratu Meli Davetanivalu II  was the fourth of Roraiova’s I five sons- in descending order-Radibi, Rinabobo II, Rovucago III, Meli Davetanivalu II and Navia (died young). 

Ratu Meli Davetanivalu II of Navaulele as sacred king or Taukei Waiburebure (later title changed to Taukei ni Waluvu) is renowned for his conversion to Christianity through Reverend Langham in 1862. He was also alive when Fiji was ceded to Britain and died during the measles epidemic in early 1875. In Ratu Meli’s old age his youngest nephew and later Buli Colo East Ratu Viliame Batiratu was often acting on his behalf with Ratu Cakobau and his government from 1871-1873.

[[File:Vakamisinari Nakorovatu,1881..jpg|thumb|right|'Vaka Missionary' gathering Nakorovatu 1881.]]

'''Image''':Fijians and some Europeans gathered in an open space in Korovatu village, Matailobau at 'Vaka Missionary' gathering. Near the front of the image stand a line of men in traditional dress shouldering clubs, preparing to meke (dance). Most of the other people are sitting. Centre left background stands a Fijian ''bure'' building.

Rovucago III’s sons were in decending order-Roraiova II, Robaledrokadroka II, Ratu Manasa Davetanivalu III, Ratu Viliame Batiratu and  Roragoca. Ratu Manasa and Ratu Viliame Batiratu’s mother was Rokamanalagi from  the powerful Navitilevu clan. 

Ratu Manasa married Adi Sereana Radinisiko of the Siko clan’s yavutu Navunidakua. Ratu Manasa was killed in the attack of the Muaira clans on his fort at Ulira around 1873. Ratu Manasa had two sons Ratu Jemesa Robonowai II and Ratu Esira Rovucago V (1870–1934) and two daughters Adi Vani Rolikubai and Roeseta Likumotovai. Doctor Ratu Jemesa Robonowai II (1866–1937) Ratu Manasa's eldest son was named after the mythical child god and the ancestor of Rovucago I of Navunidakua. Robonowai  I as previously mentioned was the son of the Tui Nalawa from Ra and the great Nakauvadra migration. 

Ratu Manasa Davetanivalu III, the third son of Rovucago III, was anointed as Tui and named after Davetanivalu II with his yavu given the name Nakamarusi in honour of the clan’s vu or founding ancestor Rokowai’s great bure foundation. In addition the Nabubuco and Korowaqa clans are ''qase and tamata  ni vale'' to Nakamarusi.

Decendants of Ratu Manasa Davetanivalu III of Nakamarusi have been known as ''gone kalou'' or child god such as the names bestowed on his son Robonowai and his younger son Rokovucago IV’s eldest daughter Adi Lagamu (named after Rev Langham) Lomalagi Lewaturaga who was born in 1903 the year of Reverend Frederick Langham’s death. Rev Langham is revered in Taukei ni Waluvu history as converting Ratu Meli and his clan to Christianity in 1862.

Ratu Samuela Ranarogo (1855–1931) held the Vunivalu title of the clan after Ratu Alipate Baledrokadroka II. Ratu Samuela at the time of the ''Veitarogi Vanua'' on 2 December 1924 gave sworn testimony of the clans origins. Ratu Samuela died without a male issue. Ratu Jese Ronaitege (1871–1931) a younger brother  to Ratu Samuela  and his descendants carries on this line. Their residence- Dakui is named after the vunivalu of Bau’s residence on Bau Island. In addition the bati or warrior clan of Nawaita is also ''gase and tamata ni vale'' (elders) to Dakui.

With the Siko Natabutale clan of Navaulele-Nairukuruku, the  chiefly dualism relationship also became fused in the title of Taukei ni Waluvu. After the death of Ratu Samuela Ranarogo in 1931 as Vunivalu, the title  of Vunivalu and  Tui became one in the moniker Taukei ni Waluvu. This was due to the '' turaga vasu i taukei'' and  also ''vasu levu'' to Navunidakua, Dr Ratu Jemesa Robonowai, aceding to the title Taukei ni Waluvu.

== Title holder ==

As chief of Matailobau district, the Taukei ni Waluvu, Ratu Meli Koroitamana who replaced his cousin Ratu Alipate Baledrokadroka (1933–2005) was traditionally installed on 22 March 2008. He is a retired airport ground staff and sits on Fiji’s [[Great Council of Chiefs]]. He is a former Fiji rugby representative of the 1964 tour of UK and France.
Ratu Alipate was a pioneering Fijian scholar of the newly established [[Marist Brothers High School (Fiji)]], Suva in 1949. He was one of the first Fijian students to matriculate in the Senior Cambridge exams in 1952 following his father Dr Ratu Jone Raiova (1904–33) footsteps, who matriculated from Marist St John's college, Cawaci on Ovalau Island in 1922, to the Central Medical School, Suva. Ratu Meli died on 07 Oct 2009 after a short illness.

[[File:Ratu Alipate Baledrokadroka.png|thumb|right|Ratu Alipate MBHS Student 1949.]]

'''Images''': '''Ratu Alipate Baledrokadroka IV, ''' Taukei ni Waluvu, (1997–2005) as Form III student Marist Brothers High School, Suva, 1949, and the &quot;Rainmaker&quot; at Naitasiri Provincial Council Meeting, Navuso, Naitasiri, December 2000.

[[File:Ratu Alipate Baledrokadroka 1.png|thumb|right|Ratu Alipate at Naitasiri Provincial Council Meeting,Navuso, 2000.]]

The chiefly households of: Nakamarusi, Vuravura, Dakui, Navaulele, Nadawadamana, Nasirivatu, Navakabatiyavu, Nakacadakui, Navunisalusalu and Nacagabuli will decide the next title holder who is usually the oldest male in the Siko Natabutale clan of Nairukuruku village. There is pressure however on the choice of leadership through this exclusive  traditional system due to the changes in village life and culture brought about by modernity. As today’s communal quest for development and good governance is realized through a leader’s education and moral integrity.

== Past title holders ==
(in order of succession) &lt;ref&gt;NLC ''Tukutuku Raraba'', Yavusa Siko, Colo East, Dec 1924 pp 105-111.&lt;/ref&gt;

'''Vunivalu''' '''Taukei Waiburebure'''
* Robonowai I (Nalawa)
* Rokovucago I (Navunidakua)
* Nayacakuru (Navunidakua)
* Rokowai I(c.1600 AD Nakamarusi)
* Rokotokalau (Ulira)
* Ronaiteqe (Taulevu)
* Iranabobo I(Ulira)
* Rovucago II (Navaulele)
* Roraiova I,(Valu ni Lulu- Navaulele)
* Robaledrokadroka I, (Taulevu)
* Rodavetanivalu I, (Taulevu)
* Iranabobo II(Ulira)

'''Vunivalu Vuniduba'''
* Asaeli Tabuavula

'''Vunivalu ''' '''Taukei ni Waluvu'''                                 

* Ratu Meli Davetanivalu II, Navaulele (?-1875).
* Ratu Jone Roraiova II,&lt;ref&gt;..''Happily in our case the feasts
are generally divided by Johnny, the head boatman, who, being himself a chief of this district, is well informed on all such matters. We are amusingly reminded of his nobility by hearing the clapping 
of hands, with which an admiring circle invariably proclaim the close of his meals''. C. F. Gordon Cummings, Home in Fiji, Pub. William Blackwood &amp; Sons London, 1885, pp. 97-8.&lt;/ref&gt; (Taukei Nakacadakui)
* Ratu Viliame Robatiratu I(?-1908) (Taukei Vuravura, Buli Colo East, GCC Member)
* Ratu Alipate Baledrokadroka II,&lt;ref name=&quot;jstor1&quot;/&gt; (Taukei Navaulele)
* Ratu Samu Ranarogo (1855–1931).
* Dr. Ratu Jemesa Robonowai II, NMP, (Taukei Nakamarusi, 1866–1937, GCC Member)
* Ratu Taito Rauluni (1880–1948).
* Ratu Manasa Davetanivalu II,(1893–1944, GCC Member)
* Ratu Isikeli Roraqoca (Buli Matailobau) (1906–62, GCC Member)
* Ratu Anare Roraqoca (1903–74, GCC Member)
* Ratu Joseva Koroitamana (1909–87).
* Ratu Esira Rovucago VI(1911–77).
* Ratu Emosi Vakatawabai (1915–79, GCC Member)
* Ratu Jope Rokowai (1923–97, GCC Member)
* Ratu Alipate Raiova Baledrokadroka IV, (1933–2005, Taukei Nacagabuli, Senator, GCC Member)
* Ratu Meli Ronaiteqe Koroitamana (1935–2009, GCC Member)

== Prominent Yavusa ''Siko'' Persons ==
* Ratu Meli Davetanivalu II Taukei ni Waluvu, First Colo Chief converted to Christianity (?-1875).
* Ratu Viliame Batiratu, Buli Matailobau, leading Colo East Chief. GCC member(?-1908).
* Ratu Isikeli Roragoca Davetanivalu, Buli Nalawa, Ra.
* Mr William Scott, European Settler.
* Mr Henry Scott, European Settler.
* Dr. Ratu Jemesa Robonowai, NMP. GCC Member. (1866–1937).
* Dr. Ratu Waisea Radibi, NMP.
* Dr. Ratu Jone Roraiova, MP. (1904–34).
* Ratu Isikeli Roraqoca, Buli Matailobau, GCC Member.
* Ratu Viliame Batiratu, World War II Veteran Soldier.
* Ratu Alipate Baledrokadroka III, Vatukoula Mines Union and Naitasiri Community Rep.
* Rev. Setareki Nasilivata, Methodist Minister.
* Semi Nate, 1920-40s Heavyweight Champion Boxer of  Fiji and the Pacific, Native Magistrate.
* Inspector Ratu Leone Lautabui,First native gazetted Police Officer.Author of the ''Sherlock Holmes of Fiji.''
* Major Josefa S George, Military Officer, 1FIR Malaya, Company Commander and NLC Officer.
* Colonel Livai Nasilivata, Military Cross, Govt Minister, Senator, Teacher, Army Officer.
* Inoke Nasilivata, Teacher, Nausori Town Councillor.
* Superintendent P. Turaga, Police Officer.
* Sgt Ratu  Asesela Rokotulou, World War II, US Silver Star medal.
* Ratu Alipate Baledrokadroka IV, (1933–2005) Accountant, Senator, GCC Member.
* Ratu Meli Koroitamana, Fiji Rugby Rep to UK 1964, GCC Member.
* Adi Kelera Royalotama Nasilivata, (1937–2007) Teacher.
* Ratu Jope Rorinabobo, Head Teacher Vunidawa.
* Ratu Meli Rinakorovatu, ex-Tuirara Matailobau Wainimala division.
* Ratu Emosi Rosakuwai - USP Administrator, Founder Naitasiri Rugby- Suva, Nasinu, Kalabu Zone.
* Adi Lagamu Takiveikata, President Naitasiri Soqosoqo vaka Marama, Businesswomen, Senator.
* Colonel Ratu [[Jone Baledrokadroka]] Roraiova, Founding President Naitasiri Rugby Union (1998–2002), GCC Member.
* Ratu Jope Paul Baledrokadroka, Teacher, Kelston Boys High, Auck, NZ.
* Adi Vasiti Baledrokadroka, FIT Senior Lecturer.
* Peniasi Nasilivata - Min of Planning and Finance.
* Setareki Nasilivata - Army Officer.
* Ratu Jemesa Baledrokadroka, Lawyer.
* Ratu Jope Davetanivalu, Dir Min. of Environment.
* Ratu Emosi Davetanivalu, Min. Planning and Finance.
* Adi Vani Nasedra, Teacher.
* Isoa Nasedra, Ast Native Lands Commissioner.
* Eroni Tubuitamana, Teacher.
* Atunaisa Tabua, Ast Roko Naitasiri.
* Adi Kelera Baledrokadroka, Agriculturist.
* Ratu Feretariki Naqaliwai, Teacher.
* Ratu Manasa Davetanivalu, British Army Officer, UK.
* Ratu Levani. Rosovalevu, Nurse.
* Mikaele Aciriciri Turaga, Journalist.
* Akusita. Nasilivata, Teacher.
* Maria Turaga, Radio Announcer.

== References ==

{{reflist|colwidth=30em}}
* Wallace Deane, ''The Strange Adventures of a whale's tooth, missionary story from Fiji for young people and others'', KI'Worth Printing and Publishing House 218 Castlereagh St., 1919.
*---------------------, ''Fijian society or the sociology and psychology
of the Fijians'', Macmillan and co. limited, London, 1921. 
* A. Capell, Oceania, &quot;Local Divisions and Movement in Fiji&quot;, Vol X1 No. 4, Jun 1941.
* Tevita Baleiwaqa, ''Rerevaka na Kalou ka Doka na Tui'', Australian National University Thesis, 2003.
* Winston Halapua, ''Tradition, Lotu and Militarism in Fiji'', Fiji Institute  of Applied Studies,2003.
* Philip Snow, ''The Years Of Hope: Cambridge, Colonial Administration In The South Seas And Cricket'', p.&amp;nbsp;218, Radcliffe Press, 1997.
* NLC &quot;Tukutuku Raraba&quot;: Yavusa - Siko, Colo East, 02 Dec. 1924.
* AB Brewster, ''The Hill Tribes of Fiji'', Davidson Press, 2009.
* -------------------, &quot;Genealogies and histories of the Matanitu or tribal governments of Central Vitu Levu (Great Fiji)&quot; 1923
* C. F. Gordon Cummings, ''At Home in Fiji'', Pub. William Blackwood &amp; Sons London, 1885.
* James W. Turner, &quot;The Sins Of The Father : Rank and succession in a Fijian Chiefdom&quot;, Oceania, Dec 1986.
* -----------------------, &quot;True Food&quot; and First Fruits: Rituals of Increase in Fiji,&quot; Ethnology, Vol. 23, No. 2, April, 1984.
* -----------------------, ‘Rituals, Habitus and Hierarchy in Fiji’, Ethnology, Vol 31, No. 4, Oct 1992
* Nicole, Robert Emmanuel, ''Disturbing history: aspects of resistance in early colonial Fiji, 1874–1914'', University of Hawaii Press,2011.
* Fergus Clunie, Director Fiji Museum, ''Domodomo'' (Fiji Museum Quartertly, back cover), Pre Colonial States of FijiSuva, Government Press 1985.
* Andrew Thornley, ''Exodus of the I Taukei Lako Yani ni Kawa i Taukei, The Story of Methodism in Fiji from 1848–78'' (2002).
* -----------------------, ''Fijian Methodism 1874-1945'', Australian National University Thesis, 1979.
* Jane Roth and Steven Hooper, &quot;Fiji Journals of Baron Anatole von Hugel&quot;, Fiji Museum, 1991.

{{DEFAULTSORT:Taukei Ni Waluvu}}
[[Category:Fijian chiefs]]
[[Category:Fijian nobility]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
