<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="1806412" ns="0" title="Fort Calhoun Nuclear Generating Station"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Infobox power station
| name                = Fort Calhoun Nuclear Power Plant
| image               = Calhoun-plant1.jpg
| image_caption       = Fort Calhoun in 2002
| location_map        = USA Nebraska
| country             = United States
| locale              = [[Washington County, Nebraska|Washington County]], near [[Blair, Nebraska|Blair]], [[Nebraska]]
| lat_d   = 41
| lat_m   = 31
| lat_s   = 13
| lat_NS  = N
| long_d  = 96
| long_m  = 4
| long_s  = 38
| long_EW = W
| coordinates_type    = type:landmark_region:US-NE
| coordinates_display = title
| owner               =
| operator            = [[Omaha Public Power District]]
| construction_began  = 1966
| commissioned        = August 9, 1973
| decommissioned      =
| reactor_supplier    = [[Combustion Engineering]]
| reactor_type        = [[Pressurized water reactor|Pressurized Water Reactor (PWR)]]
| reactors_operate_mw = 1 x 476 MW
| reactors_decom_mw   =
| reactors_const_mw   =
| reactors_planned_mw =
| installed_capacity  = &lt;!--(MW)--&gt;
| average_annual_gen  = 4,170
| net_generation_year = 2007
| net_generation      =
| status              = O
| generation_units    =
| architect           = Gibbs &amp; Hill &amp; Durham &amp; Richardson
| cost                =
| licence_expires     = 2033
| nrc_region          = [[Nuclear Regulatory Commission Region IV|Region 4]]
| website             = [http://www.oppd.com/AboutUs/22_002696 www.oppd.com/AboutUs/22_002696]
| as_of               = 2008-11-15
}}
[[File:Corp of Eng. 6-16-11A 267.JPG|thumb|250px|Corps of Engineers photo of the plant on June 16, 2011 during the 2011 Missouri River Floods]]
The '''Fort Calhoun Nuclear Generating Station''' is a [[nuclear power plant]] located on {{convert|660|acre}} between [[Fort Calhoun, Nebraska|Fort Calhoun]], and [[Blair, Nebraska]] adjacent to the [[Missouri River]] between mile markers 645.6 and 646.0.  The utility has an [[easement]] for another {{convert|580|acre}} which is maintained in a natural state. The power plant is owned and operated by the [[Omaha Public Power District]] of [[Omaha, Nebraska]] and accounts for 25 percent of OPPD's net generation capabilities.&lt;ref name=&quot;omaha1&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.omaha.com/article/20110713/NEWS01/707139880#oppd-flood-costs-so-far-26-million |title=OPPD flood bill so far: $26M |publisher=Omaha.com |date= |accessdate=2011-07-13}}&lt;/ref&gt;

This plant has one [[Combustion Engineering]] [[pressurized water reactor]] generating 484&amp;nbsp;megawatts of electricity.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Fort Calhoun Station|url=http://www.oppd.com/AboutUs/22_002696 www.oppd.com/AboutUs/22_002696|publisher=Omaha Public Power District|accessdate=28 June 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; This is currently the smallest rated capacity among all operating commercial power reactors in North America, and as a single-unit plant, this also qualifies it as the smallest rated capacity nuclear power plant. OPPD's two [[Nebraska City, Nebraska|Nebraska City]] coal-fired plants at 682 (opened 2009) and 649 (opened 1979) MW are both significantly larger.&lt;ref name=&quot;omaha1&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.oppd.com/AboutUs/22_002695 |title=Nebraska City Station - Omaha Public Power District |publisher=Oppd.com |date= |accessdate=2011-07-13}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Fort Calhoun houses [[spent fuel rod]]s in a 40 foot deep [[spent fuel pool]] next to the reactor, and when the pool had nearly reached capacity in 2006, OPPD began to store spent fuel rods above ground in [[dry cask storage]] as well.  In total, the Ft. Calhoun reactor has 600,000 to 800,000 pounds of high level nuclear waste.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|author=Michio Kaku on July 1, 2011, 1:00 AM |url=http://bigthink.com/ideas/39108 |title=United States Hit With a Triple Nuclear Threat - How Dangerous is it? (Part 1/2) &amp;#124; Dr. Kaku's Universe |publisher=Big Think |date= |accessdate=2011-07-02}}&lt;/ref&gt; The storage was not designed to house spent fuel permanently, but when plans for [[Yucca Mountain nuclear waste repository]] were terminated, OPPD stated that they are &quot;prepared to safely store material on-site as long as necessary&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|author=Saturday, July 2, 2011 |url=http://www.enterprisepub.com/news/article_c622e2ac-55a5-5c14-b1b2-d8adfe92484a.html |title=Fort Calhoun plant may store spent fuel rods permanently - Washington County Enterprise and Pilot Tribune: |publisher=Enterprisepub.com |date=2011-06-25 |accessdate=2011-07-02}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The plant underwent refurbishment in 2006 by having its [[Steam generator (nuclear power)|steam generators]], pressurizer, [[Reactor vessel#Reactor Vessel Head|reactor vessel head]], low pressure turbines and main transformer replaced. In 2003, the plant had its operating license renewed for an additional twenty years.  With the renewal, the license for Fort Calhoun was extended from August 9, 2013, to August 9, 2033.&lt;ref name=NRC03_143&gt;{{cite press release|title=NRC renews license for fort Calhoun nuclear power plant for an additional 20 years|url=http://pbadupws.nrc.gov/docs/ML0330/ML033080359.pdf|format=PDF|publisher=U.S. Nuclear Regulatory Commission|date= November 4, 2003}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The [[2011 Missouri River floods]] surrounded the plant with flood water, an unprecedented event for a U.S. nuclear power plant due to both the level of flooding and  the anticipated period of time the flood is expected to persist.&lt;ref name=test&gt;{{cite news|last=Gaarder|first=Nancy|title=Flood test not over for nuke plant|url=http://www.omaha.com/article/20110627/NEWS01/706279901/1101|accessdate=28 June 2011|newspaper=Omaha World Herald|date=June 27, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Surrounding population==
The [[Nuclear Regulatory Commission]] defines two emergency planning zones around nuclear power plants: a plume exposure pathway zone with a radius of about {{convert|10|mi}}, concerned primarily with exposure to, and inhalation of, airborne radioactive contamination, and an ingestion pathway zone of about {{convert|50|mi}}, concerned primarily with ingestion of food and liquid contaminated by radioactivity.&lt;ref&gt;{{citation | title=Backgrounder on emergency preparedness at nuclear power plants|publisher=U.S. Nuclear Regulatory Commission|type=fact sheet| url=http://www.nrc.gov/reading-rm/doc-collections/fact-sheets/emerg-plan-prep-nuc-power-bg.html}}&lt;/ref&gt;  In 2010, the population within 10 miles of Fort Calhoun was 20,639; the population within 50 miles was 953,410. The closest major city is Omaha, with a population of 408,958, whose center is {{convert|18|mi}} from the plant.&lt;ref name=dedman1&gt;{{cite news | last=Dedman | first=Bill | author-link=Bill Dedman|title=Nuclear neighbors: Population rises near US reactors|source=msnbc.com|source-link=msnbc.com|date=April 14, 2011|url=http://www.msnbc.msn.com/id/42555888/ns/us_news-life/|accessdate=May 1, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{citation|author=U.S. Census Bureau|editor-last=Drozd|editor-first=David|url=http://www.unomaha.edu/~cpar/documents/CityPopDisplay.pdf|format=PDF|title=Nebraska incorporated place census populations with changes and percent changes: 1980 to 2010|publisher=Center for Public Affairs Research, University of Nebraska|place=Omaha|  accessdate=May 4, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Seismic risk==
The Nuclear Regulatory Commission's estimate of the risk each year of an earthquake intense enough to cause core damage to the reactor at Fort Calhoun was 1 in 76,923, according to a NRC study published in August 2010.&lt;ref name=dedman2&gt;{{cite news|first=Bill|last=Dedman|author-link=Bill Dedman|title=What are the odds? US nuke plants ranked by quake risk|source=msnbc.com|source-link=msnbc.com|date=March 17, 2011|url=http://www.msnbc.msn.com/id/42103936/|accessdate=April 19, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{citation|url=http://msnbcmedia.msn.com/i/msnbc/Sections/NEWS/quake%20nrc%20risk%20estimates.pdf|type=Memorandum to: Brian W. Sheron, Director, Office of Nuclear Regulatory Research|title=Safety/risk assessment results for generic issue 199, &quot;Implications of updated probabilistic seismic hazard estimates in central and eastern United States on existing plants&quot; |last=Hiland|first=Patrick|others=Safety/risk assessment panel for generic issue 199|date=September 2, 2010|accessdate=June 17, 1011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Flooding risk==
A flood assessment performed by the Nuclear Regulatory Commission in 2010 indicated that the Fort Calhoun Nuclear Generating Station, &quot;did not have adequate procedures to protect the intake structure and auxiliary building against external flooding events.&quot;&lt;ref name=ler&gt;{{cite web| title = Licensee event report| publisher = U.S. Nuclear Regulatory Commission| date = May 16, 2011| url = http://pbadupws.nrc.gov/docs/ML1113/ML111370123.pdf| format = PDF| accessdate = Jiune 3, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; The assessment also indicated that the facility was not adequately prepared for a &quot;worst-case&quot; flooding scenario. A number of potential flood water penetration points were discovered that could have impacted the raw feed water supply to the cooling system, the auxiliary water supply and main switchgear (electrical) room. By early 2011, corrective measures had been implemented.&lt;ref name=ler/&gt; In 2009 the NRC did a flood risk assessment which found that the protection measures were only designed to handle floods to {{convert|1009|ft}} above sea level which was below the NRC mandated elevation of {{convert|1014|ft}} for the plant. The risk assessment stated that at {{convert|1010|ft}}, flooding would have &quot;led to a 100 percent chance of a fuel damage if the emergency gasoline pumps didn't work.&quot;&lt;ref name=test/&gt;

==Events==
{{see also|2011 Missouri River Floods}}

On June 6, 2011 the Omaha Public Power District, as required by Nuclear Regulatory Commission guidelines, declared a Notification of Unusual Event&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=NRC: Event notification report for June 6th, 2011|url=http://www.nrc.gov/reading-rm/doc-collections/event-status/event/2011/20110606en.html#en46929|publisher=Nuclear Regulatory Commission|accessdate=19 June 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;classification1&quot;&gt;{{cite web|title=NRC: Emergency classification|url=http ://www.nrc.gov/about-nrc/emerg-preparedness/about-emerg-preparedness/emerg-classification.html|publisher=Nuclear Regulatory Commission|accessdate=19 June 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; (minimal level on a [[Nuclear safety in the United States#Emergency Classifications|4 level taxonomy]]) due to flooding of the Missouri River.&lt;ref name=js&gt;{{Cite news | title = Low-level emergency declared at nuclear power plant| newspaper = JournalStar.com| location = Lincoln, Nebraska| date = June 6, 2011| url = http://journalstar.com/news/state-and-regional/nebraska/article_d2b85355-0bc8-5733-b3ad-6997395d23 a6.html| accessdate =2011-06-07 }}&lt;/ref&gt; The Missouri River is above flood stage and is expected to rise further and remain above flood stage for several weeks to a month. Contractors have been busy installing sandbags and earthen berms to protect the facility from flooding.&lt;ref name=js/&gt; According to officials, the plant was built to withstand a [[100-year flood|500 year flood]]ing event and though by June 14, 2011, much of the facility was surrounded by the swollen Missouri River, Omaha Public Power District officials were confident that enough redundancies were in place to ensure adequate safety.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|last=Smollen|first=Gary|title=Fort Calhoun flood defenses|url=http://www.wowt.com/home/headlines/Ft_Calhoun_Flood_Defenses_123878599.html|accessdate=15 June 2011|newspaper=WOWT.com|date=June 14, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; It was reported on June 17, 2011 that the plant was in &quot;safe cold shutdown&quot; mode for refueling and the anticipation of flooding,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|author=June 28, 2011 |url=http://public-blog.nrc-gateway.gov/2011/06/28/a-first-hand-look-at-the-flooding/ |title=A First Hand Look at the Flooding « U.S. NRC Blog |publisher=Public-blog.nrc-gateway.gov |date=2011-06-28 |accessdate=2011-07-02}}&lt;/ref&gt; and that four weeks worth of additional fuel had been brought in to power backup generators, should they be needed. The [[United States Army Corps of Engineers|Army Corps of Engineers]] indicated that with average precipitation, the Missouri River would not go above {{convert|1008|ft}} above sea level and OPPD officials stated that the current flood protection efforts would protect the plant to {{convert|1010|-|1012|ft}} feet above sea level. Officials indicated the spent fuel pool is at {{convert|1038.5|ft}} above sea level.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|last=Gaarder|first=Nancy|title=NRC: No flood danger at reactor|newspaper = Omaha World Herald| location = Omaha, Nebraska| date = June 17, 2011
|url=http://www.omaha.com/article/20110617/NEWS01/706179913/0#nrc-no-flood-danger-at-reactor|accessdate=2011-06-17}}&lt;/ref&gt; 

On June 7, 2011, an electrical component in a switch gear room caused a small fire with Halon extinguisher activation which forced a partial evacuation.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|last= Tracy|first=Ryan| title = Nebraska nuclear plant lost cooling system after fire | newspaper = Wall Street Journal| location = Omaha, Nebraska| date = June 8, 2011| url = http://online.wsj.com/article/SB10001424052702304778304576374011963022284.html|accessdate = 2011-06-16}}&lt;/ref&gt; The fire was no longer burning when the on site fire brigade arrived and according to officials, the public was never in any danger. The fire impacted pumping of coolant water through the spent fuel pool. Cooling was interrupted for 90 minutes while the estimated time for the pool to reach boiling temperature was over 88 hours.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|last= Cole|first=Kevin| title =Nuke plant lost spent fuel pump in suspected fire| newspaper = KETV news| location = Omaha, Nebraska| date = June 8, 2011| url = http://www.ketv.com/news/28172754/detail.html | accessdate = 2011-06-08}}&lt;/ref&gt; In response, the Omaha Public Power District declared an alert&lt;ref name=&quot;classification1&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web| title = NRC: Event notification report for June 8, 2011| publisher = Nuclear regulatory Commission| date = June 7, 2011| url = http://www.nrc.gov/reading-rm/doc-collections/event-status/event/2011/20110608en.html#en46932| accessdate = 2011-06-09}}&lt;/ref&gt; (second level on a [[Nuclear safety in the United States#Emergency Classifications|4 level taxonomy]]). The evacuation was the first at the facility since 1992, when {{convert|20000|USgal}} (ca. 76 [[Tonne|t]]) of coolant leaked into a containment building from the reactor.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news | title = Smoke causes scare at nuclear plant| newspaper = KETV news| location = Omaha, Nebraska| publisher = Hearst| date = June 7, 2011| url = http://www.ketv.com/news/28163138/detail.html| accessdate = 2011-06-07}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|last= Cole|first=Kevin| title = Smoke triggers nuclear plant alarm| newspaper = Omaha World-Herald| location = Omaha, Nebraska| date = June 7, 2011| url = http://www.omaha.com/article/20110607/NEWS01/110609814/0#smoke-triggers-nuclear-plant-alarm  | accessdate = 2011-06-07}}&lt;/ref&gt;

On June 23 a helicopter contracted by OPPD to survey transmission lines made an unplanned landing 1.5 miles south of the plant.  Reports described it as an unplanned landing although photographs showed it on its side in a field.  Nobody was injured.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.wowt.com/news/headlines/124434274.html |title=No one hurt in emergency helicopter landing |publisher=Wowt.com |date=2011-06-23 |accessdate=2011-06-27}}&lt;/ref&gt; The [[Federal Aviation Administration]] had declared a &quot;temporary flight restriction,&quot; in a two nautical mile radius, centered on the Fort Calhoun nuclear facility.  This restriction went into effect on June 6, 2011, at 4:31 PM, and remains in effect &quot;until further notice.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;[http://tfr.faa.gov/save_pages/detail_1_6523.html Federal Aviation Administration], &quot;''FDC 1/6523 NOTAM Details'',&quot; (June 6th, 2011 - retrieved on June 19th, 2011).&lt;/ref&gt;  Officials noted that the June 6 FAA directive was actually a reminder to a standing order creating no flight zones over all U.S. nuclear power plants which had been in effect after the 2001 [[9/11 attacks]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.kansascity.com/2011/06/28/2981543/nebraska-nuclear-plant-threatened.html |title=Nebraska nuclear plant threatened by flooding is safe, scientists group finds |publisher=KansasCity.com |date= |accessdate=2011-07-02}}&lt;/ref&gt;

On June 26, at 1:30 a.m., a {{convert|8|ft}} high, {{convert|2000|ft}} long water filled rubber flood berm surrounding portions of the plant, was punctured by a small earth mover (&quot;Bobcat&quot;) and collapsed.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news| url=http://www.nytimes.com/2011/06/28/us/28nuke.html?_r=2 | work=The New York Times | first=Matthew L. | last=Wald | title=Nebraska Nuclear Plant's Vital Equipment Remains Dry, Officials Say | date=June 27, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; The collapse of the flood berm allowed flood waters to surround the auxiliary and containment buildings at the plant, and also forced the temporary transfer of power from the external electricity grid to backup electrical generators.&lt;ref name=test/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://nrc.gov/reading-rm/doc-collections/event-status/event/2011/20110627en.html#en46988 NRC: Event Notification Report for June 27, 2011]&lt;/ref&gt; It was reported more than {{convert|2|ft}} of water rushed in around buildings and electrical transformers.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|author=Updated 104 minutes ago 6/27/2011 12:09:19 PM +00:00 |url=http://www.msnbc.msn.com/id/43540933 |title=Flood berm collapses at Nebraska nuclear plant – US news – Environment – msnbc.com |publisher=MSNBC |date= |accessdate=2011-06-27}}&lt;/ref&gt; Backup generators were then used to ensure the facility maintained electrical power for cooling.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last=Kerley |first=David |url=http://abcnews.go.com/US/minot-north-dakota-floods-community/story?id=13932406&amp;cid=ESPNheadline |title=Nebraska residents in no danger after floods hit nuke plant: Waters breach berm at Fort Calhoun nuclear station – ABC News |publisher=Abcnews.go.com |date= |accessdate=2011-06-27}}&lt;/ref&gt; The rupturing of the flood berm also resulted in approximately {{convert|100|USgal}} of petroleum being released into the river as many fuel containers were washed out. The fuel/oil containers were staged around the facility to supply fuel for pumps which remove water within the flood containment barriers.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=NRC: Offsite notification due to petroleum release to the Missouri River|url=http://www.nrc.gov/reading-rm/doc-collections/event-status/event/2011/20110627en.html#en46989|publisher=Nuclear Regulatory Commission|accessdate=2011-06-27}}&lt;/ref&gt; The rubber berm was a secondary measure not mandated by the NRC and was put in place by OPPD to provide additional room for work immediately outside the reactor buildings.&lt;ref name=test/&gt;  According the NRC, the water-filled berm &quot;protects several pieces of equipment that have been brought onsite, including an additional emergency diesel generator for supplying AC electrical power, water pumps, firefighting equipment and sandbagging supplies&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|author=June 22, 2011 |url=http://public-blog.nrc-gateway.gov/2011/06/22/the-rising-river-puts-flood-preparations-to-the-test/ |title=The Rising River Puts Flood Preparations to the Test « U.S. NRC Blog |publisher=Public-blog.nrc-gateway.gov |date=2011-06-22 |accessdate=2011-07-02}}&lt;/ref&gt;

According to OPPD, the plant is designed to withstand waters up to 1,014 feet above mean sea level. The river is not expected to exceed 1,008 feet.  NRC officials were at the plant at the time and NRC statements said the plant remains safe.  NRC Chairman [[Gregory Jaczko]] confirmed the plant's safety when he visited the plant on June 27.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|author=By Josh Funk, Associated Press &amp;ndash; 20 hours ago |url=http://www.google.com/hostednews/ap/article/ALeqM5hwsIdVXW-V7xE60P0dUnI_qSIaIw?docId=252989d1dda94c1d83ee47ba8907e484 |title=The Associated Press: Flood berm collapses at Nebraska nuclear plant |publisher=Google.com |date= |accessdate=2011-06-27}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|author=By the CNN Wire Staff |url=http://www.cnn.com/2011/US/06/26/nebraska.flooding/ |title=Flood berm bursts at Nebraska nuclear plant |publisher=CNN.com |date= June 27, 2011|accessdate=2011-06-27}}&lt;/ref&gt; 

On June 30 one of the pumps used to remove seepage caught fire when a worker was refilling it with gasoline.  The worker put the fire out with a fire extinguisher but was burned on his arms and face and he was airlifted via helicopter to [[Lincoln, Nebraska]].  OPPD said the fire was in an auxiliary security building area and not in the reactor area and that the plant was never in danger.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|author=POSTED: 5:15 pm CDT June 30, 2011 |url=http://www.ketv.com/r/28412417/detail.html |title=Worker Burned At Nuclear Plant - Omaha News Story - KETV Omaha |publisher=Ketv.com |date=2011-02-07 |accessdate=2011-07-02}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://nrc.gov/reading-rm/doc-collections/event-status/event/2011/20110701en.html#en47001 NRC: Event Notification Report for July 1, 2011]&lt;/ref&gt;

On July 11 OPPD installed a new 8 foot inflatable berm to replace the one that was punctured and failed on June 26.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.omaha.com/article/20110711/NEWS01/707119933#the-latest-on-flooding-july-11 |title=The latest on flooding: July 11 |publisher=Omaha.com |date= |accessdate=2011-07-13}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The NRC gave the plant a &quot;D&quot; rating in early September 2011 due to the 2009 flood mitigation and control issues (flood preparedness) and for a faulty electrical connector issue from 2010. Though flood waters from the 2011 Missouri River flood had subsided, the plant would remain shutdown until federal regulators were convinced that OPPD had demonstrated improved compliance. The plant may still be under a &quot;D&quot; rating and still be allowed to operate. NRC officials were confident OPPD would be able to operate the plant safely.

== References ==
{{reflist|colwidth=30em}}

==External links==
{{commons category|Fort Calhoun Nuclear Generating Station}}
*{{cite web
 | url= http://www.eia.doe.gov/cneaf/nuclear/page/at_a_glance/reactors/fort_calhoun.html
 | title= Fort Calhoun nuclear power plant, Nebraska
 | date= September 29, 2008 |work= | publisher= [[U.S. Department of Energy]] (DOE)
 | accessdate= 2008-11-15 }}
*{{cite web
 | url= http://www.nrc.gov/info-finder/reactor/fcs.html
 | title= Fort Calhoun pressurized water reactor
 | date= February 14, 2008 | work= Operating Nuclear Power Reactors
 | publisher= U.S. [[Nuclear Regulatory Commission]] (NRC)
 | accessdate= 2008-11-15 }}

{{U.S. Nuclear Plants}}

[[Category:Buildings and structures in Washington County, Nebraska]]
[[Category:Nuclear power stations in the United States|Nuclear power stations in the United States]]
[[Category:Nuclear power plants in Nebraska]]
[[Category:Nuclear power stations using pressurized water reactors]]

[[br:Kreizenn nukleel Fort Calhoun]]
[[de:Kernkraftwerk Fort Calhoun]]
[[es:Central nuclear de Fort Calhoun]]
[[fr:Centrale nucléaire de Fort Calhoun]]
[[ja:フォートカルフーン原子力発電所]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
