<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="18102941" ns="0" title="Bapunagar"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Multiple issues|orphan =June 2008|unreferenced =July 2008}}
{{Infobox Indian Jurisdiction
|type               = town
|native_name        = Bapunagar
|other_name         =
|district           = Ahmadabad
|state_name         = Gujarat
|nearest_city       =
|parliament_const   =
|assembly_const      =
|civic_agency       = 
|skyline            =  
|skyline_caption    = 
|latd = |latm = |lats = 
|longd= |longm= |longs= 
|locator_position   = right
|area_total         = 
|area_magnitude     = 
|altitude           = 
|population_total   =
|population_as_of   = 
|population_density =
|sex_ratio          = 
|literacy           = 
|area_telephone     = 
|postal_code        = 
|vehicle_code_range = 
|climate=
|website=
}}

'''Bapunagar''' ({{lang-gu|બાપુનગર}}, [[Hindi]]: बापुनगर) is a neighbourhood in [[Ahmedabad]], [[Gujarat]], [[India]]. It is located in the eastern part of the city, in the Rakhial ward. Its name derives from the word &quot;Bapu&quot;, which refers to [[Gandhi]], who was popularly called 'Bapu', or Father.

== History ==
Bapunagar was established in the early 1960s, in the vicinity of the city of Ahmedabad, as a residential area for the poor mill workers, when Ahmedabad was a flourishing textile centre in India. Many of these mills had closed by the late 1980s, reducing the now unemployed mill workers to home businesses, such as making incense sticks or candles. The present day detergent giant [[Nirma]] began as just one such home industry; the owner started by making household detergents and selling them door to door.

== Industry/Business ==
In the early 1990s, diamond cutting arose as an industry in the absence of the textile mills. At present, Bapunagar ranks second in India as a diamond cutting centre, after only Surat. Diamond cutting has absorbed many of the workers who used to be employed by textile mills, and attracted additional people from the [[Saurashtra (region)|Saurashtra]]. This influx of new residents caused a resultant increase in the housing sector and construction is causing a second more recent employment boom.

== Landmark ==
Maleksaban, or Lal Bahadur Shastri Stadium, was the first sports stadium in Ahmedabad, but due to insufficient use and funding, it was converted into a sports complex, Sardar Patel Stadium. It is occasionally used for military drills and informal cricket games.

Vijay Chowk is a square which divides the old and new portions of Bapunagar, and serves as a site for political gatherings and speeches, particularly when election campaigns are underway.

The city also serves as a source of agricultural products such as mangoes and chilis.

==Diversity==

Bapunagar has a diverse population, but is nicknamed &quot;''Mini-Saurashtra''&quot;, as majority of its population have roots in the Amreli, Bhavnagar, Junagadh and other districts of the Saurashtra region of Gujarat. This area is considered communally sensitive and has witnessed some of the worst post-independence violence, primarily struggles between the Hindu majority and the Muslim minority. The 1969 riots were the worst riots of that period, with about 1,100 lives lost, and the Godhra riots in 2001 took about 300 lives.

The firebrand VHP leader [[Dr. Pravin Togadia]] started his professional as well as political career from here.

This area has seen significant commercial growth in the wake of the revived diamond cutting and construction industries.

Bapunagar also has a sizeable population of out of state immigrants like bhaiyajis, marwaris and huge number of marathis.

Many of the local retailers, franchises, restaurants and other businesses have observed the significant development that has taken place in the last decade. The general consensus being that to restore the branch in Bapunagar would be a benefit for all.

Bapunagar also now has some huge multispecialty hospital units like “Sardar Hospital” and “Kakadia Hospital” and some decent sized health clubs/gymnasiums.

Just like rest of Ahmedabad, Bapunagar too has significant levels of atmospheric pollution, some very bad traffic problem and is in urgent need of attention from authorities.

This is also one of the fastest-developing areas of the city. Bapunagar is surrounded by areas like Odhav, Saraspur, Naroda, Gomtipur, and Asarwa.

Retrieved from &quot;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bapunagar&quot;

{{coord missing|Gujarat|date=December 2010}}

[[Category:Neighbourhoods in Ahmedabad]]
[[Category:Cities and towns in Ahmedabad district]]
[[Category:Memorials to Mohandas Karamchand Gandhi]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
