<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="18170732" ns="0" title="Rewards Network"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Infobox Company
| name             = Rewards Network
| logo             = [[File:RN-Logo.jpg]]
| type             = [[Private company|Private]]
| genre            = 
| foundation       = 1984
| founder          = Mel Chasen
| location_city    = [[Chicago]], [[Illinois]]
| location_country = [[United States]]
| location         = 
| locations        = 
| area_served      = [[North America]]
| key_people       = Ron Blake&lt;br /&gt;
(President and CEO)&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
Megan Flynn&lt;br /&gt;
(SVP, Business Development and Partner Management)&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
Ed Job&lt;br /&gt;
(VP Credit and Collections)&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
Shane Kern&lt;br /&gt;
(VP of Financial Planning and Analysis)&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
Evan Makela&lt;br /&gt;
(SVP General Counsel and Secretary)&lt;ref&gt;http://www.faqs.org/sec-filings/101028/REWARDS-NETWORK-INC_8-K/dex21.htm&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
Andre Zardini&lt;br /&gt;
(SVP, Chief Information Officer)&lt;ref&gt;http://terracotta.box.net/embed/3cistacai3z8va0.swf&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
| industry         = Internet

| num_employees    = 375 (2011)&lt;ref&gt;http://www.sec.gov/Archives/edgar/data/78536/000119312510058414/d10k.htm&lt;/ref&gt;
| parent           = 
| divisions        = 
| subsid           = 
| homepage         = [http://www.rewardsnetwork.com www.rewardsnetwork.com]
| footnotes        = 
| intl             = 
}}

'''Rewards Network''' is a restaurant marketing company that provides restaurants with access to 3.4 million frequent diners who belong to various dining rewards programs. Over 10,000 restaurants currently take advantage of Rewards Network marketing services, which include email campaigns; mobile access via an app compatible with the major brands of smartphones; and individual dining websites. Rewards Network also provides restaurants secret shopper like diner feedback, diner traffic analysis, and access to funding.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.rewardsnetwork.com/&lt;/ref&gt;

==Rewards Network Tools for Restaurants==
===E-mail===
Rewards Network sends their network of diners geo-targeted emails promoting network restaurants. This email marketing features network restaurant listings, new network restaurants, special offers, and promotional incentives that encourage increased dining activity.
&lt;ref&gt;http://www.rewardsnetwork.com/_how-we-work/&lt;/ref&gt; 

===Mobile App===
Rewards network has developed a downloadable mobile app that works on [[BlackBerry]]®, [[Android (operating system)]]™ and [[iPhone]]®. The app gives users immediate access to menus, descriptions, reviews, directions and photo slide shows for network restaurants. This mobile app uses proximity targeting, which means any participating network restaurant around their current location will display on their smartphone.
&lt;ref&gt;http://www.rewardsnetwork.com/_our-offerings/_marketing-services/_mobile-apps/&lt;/ref&gt; 
&lt;ref&gt;http://www.rnmobiledining.com/&lt;/ref&gt;

===Websites===
Rewards Network provides network restaurants with a web presence on each of the dining program websites that is accessible to respective program diners through emails, an online directory, banner ads, mobile apps and a dining search engines. Each web presence contains a restaurant description; ratings and reviews; hours of operation and directions; menus, features and specials; a calendar of rewards availability for diners; and a photo slide show.
&lt;ref&gt;http://www.rewardsnetwork.com/_our-offerings/_marketing-services/_websites/&lt;/ref&gt;

===Diner Feedback===
Program diners who have eaten at a network restaurant can provide feedback on that restaurant. Rewards Network emails a survey to diners after network restaurant visits. The survey includes questions about food quality, service, and restaurant ambiance. This review is shared with the network restaurant and other program diners, and gives network restaurants the ability to respond directly to that diner. &lt;ref&gt;http://www.rewardsnetwork.com/_our-offerings/_marketing-services/_diner-feedback/&lt;/ref&gt; The program diner is like a secret shopper because network restaurants have no indication they have visited until after seeing the review. The surveys also give program diners an opportunity to post their reviews on their Facebook page, furthering the reach of that review. &lt;ref&gt;http://www.rewardsnetwork.com/_our-offerings/_marketing-services/_social-media/&lt;/ref&gt;

===Analysis===
Rewards Network provides restaurants with detailed performance reports, summaries and statements analyzing program diner visits and spend. Network restaurants can use the data to learn the geographical origin of program diners that have visited; evaluate program diner spend against other diners; measure new and repeat business; and track their performance against other local and national Rewards Network restaurants. &lt;ref&gt;http://www.rewardsnetwork.com/_our-offerings/_marketing-services/_analysis/&lt;/ref&gt;

===Funding===
Member restaurants have an opportunity to qualify for funding from Rewards Network. They provide qualifying restaurants funding based on a wholesale purchase of food and drink. Network restaurants can receive payment for menu items before they have made a dish or served a customer. Qualifying restaurants can use the funds for expansion, improvements or however they see fit. &lt;ref&gt;http://www.rewardsnetwork.com/_our-offerings/_prepurch/&lt;/ref&gt;

==The Dining Programs==
Rewards Network's program diners come from dining rewards programs that provide incentives such as airline miles, points on hotel stays, and college savings for dining at network restaurants. 

===Airline Miles===
Program diners can earn airline miles for dollars spent in network restaurants.

Mileage Plan Dining ([[Alaska Airlines]])- A Rewards Network airline miles program
http://mileageplan.rewardsnetwork.com/join.htm

AAdvantage DiningSM ([[American Airlines]])- A Rewards Network airline miles program
http://aa.rewardsnetwork.com/join.htm

SkyMiles Dining ([[Delta Air Lines]])- A Rewards Network airline miles program
http://skymiles.rewardsnetwork.com/join.htm

Rapid Rewards Dining ([[Southwest Airlines]])- A Rewards Network airline miles program
http://www.rapidrewardsdining.com/join.htm

Mileage Plus DiningSM ([[United Airlines]])- A Rewards Network airline miles program
http://mpdining.rewardsnetwork.com/

Dividend Miles Dining ([[US Airways]])- A Rewards Network airline miles program
http://usairways.rewardsnetwork.com/join.htm

===Retail Points===
Program diners receive points that they can use toward retail merchandise such as electronics, movies and music for every dollar they spend in network restaurants.

Rewardzone Dining ([[Best Buy]])- A Rewards Network retail points program
https://www.rewardzonedining.com/join.htm

===Hotel Points===
Program diners receive points they can use at major hotels for every dollar they spend at network restaurants.

HHonors Dining ([[Hilton Hotels &amp; Resorts]]) - A Rewards Network hotel points program
https://www.hhonorsdining.com/join.htm

Priority Club Rewards Dining ([[InterContinental Hotels Group]]) - A Rewards Network hotel points program
https://priorityclub.rewardsnetwork.com/join.htm

===Reward Cards===
Program diners can receive up to 15% back on their bill when dining at network restaurants. Once benefits accumulate to a minimum of $20, diners are reimbursed with American Express Rewards cards.

IDine ([[American Express]]) - A Rewards Network hotel points program
https://www.idine.com/join.htm

===Community Fund Raising===
Program diners can contribute a portion of their bills to their favorite community groups when dining out at network restaurants.

Escrip Dining - A Rewards Network community fund raising program

===College Savings Programs===
Program diners can have a portion of their bill put into a college savings program when dining out at network restaurants.

UPromise Dining - A Rewards Network college savings program
http://www.upromise.com/welcome/how-it-works

==History==
Mel Chasen founded rewards Network in September 1984 as Transmedia Network Inc in New York City. Mr. Chasen – an entrepreneur and former president of Caesar’s Palace in Las Vegas – identified an untapped opportunity to introduce diners to restaurants through a unique media barter platform that offered &quot;advertising–for–services&quot; exchanges between radio stations, magazines, and restaurant owners. The company started with 41 restaurants and 225 members. They soon grew to a reported $1 million in sales revenues by 1987. Within five years the roster had grown to 500 restaurants and 25 thousand members with sales of $33 million. By the year 2000, Transmedia was the worlds largest dining rewards program with over 2 million members and 8,000 restaurants. In 2002, Transmedia changed its name to iDine Rewards Network. At that time, sales where at $285 million with 2.3 million active members and 9,500 participating restaurants. In 2003, they shortened the name to Rewards Network. &lt;ref&gt;http://www.rewardsnetwork.com/_footer-links/about-rewards-network.php&lt;/ref&gt; Today Rewards Network has over 3.4 million members that in 2010, spent over $600,000,000 dollars in network restaurants. &lt;ref&gt;http://www.rewardsnetwork.com/_who-we-target/_members/&lt;/ref&gt;

==References==
{{Reflist}}
The Company was taken private in December, 2010.

==External links==
* [http://www.rewardsnetwork.com/ Rewards Network]
* [http://investor.rewardsnetwork.com/phoenix.zhtml?c=63758&amp;p=irol-IRHome Rewards Network Investor Relations &amp; Corporate Profile]
* [http://www.dishkebab.com/ DishKebab], Rewards Network's dining blog
* [http://www.rnmobiledining.com/ Rewards Network Mobile Apps]
* [http://www.idine.com/ iDine], Rewards Network's Reward Card dining program
* [http://www.iDineDeals.com/ iDine Deals]

[[Category:Companies based in Chicago, Illinois]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
