<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="181824" ns="0" title="War of Attrition"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Other uses}}
{{Infobox military conflict
|conflict=War of Attrition
|partof=the [[Arab-Israeli conflict]]
|image=[[File:Suez canal map.jpg|300px]]
|caption=The Israeli-Egyptian war of Attrition was centered largely on the [[Suez Canal]]
|date=July 1967&amp;nbsp;– August 7, 1970 ([[ceasefire]])
|place=[[Sinai Peninsula]] (Israeli control)
|casus=Arab defeat in [[Six-Day War|1967 War]] and Egyptian refusal to recognize Israel under the terms of the [[Khartoum Resolution]]
|territory=
|result=
*Both sides claim victory
*Continued Israeli occupation of [[Sinai]]
|combatant1='''{{flagcountry|Israel}}'''
|combatant2='''{{flagcountry|Egypt|UAR}}'''&lt;br/&gt;{{flagcountry|Soviet Union}}&lt;br /&gt;{{flagicon|Palestine}} [[Palestine Liberation Organization|PLO]]&lt;br /&gt;{{flagcountry|Jordan}}&lt;br /&gt;{{flagcountry|Syria|1963}}
|commander1={{flagicon|Israel}} [[Levi Eshkol]]&lt;br /&gt;{{flagicon|Israel}} [[Yigal Allon]]&lt;br /&gt;{{flagicon|Israel}} [[Zalman Shazar]]&lt;br /&gt;{{flagicon|Israel}} [[Haim Bar-Lev]]&lt;br /&gt;{{flagicon|Israel}} [[Mordechai Hod]]&lt;br /&gt;{{flagicon|Israel}} [[Uzi Narkiss]]
|commander2={{flagicon|Egypt|UAR}} [[Gamal Abdel Nasser]]&lt;br /&gt;{{flagicon|Egypt|UAR}} [[Ahmad Ismail Ali]]&lt;br /&gt;{{flagicon|Egypt|UAR}} [[Anwar El Sadat]]&lt;br /&gt;{{flagicon|Egypt|UAR}} [[Saad El Shazly]]&lt;br /&gt;{{flagicon|Egypt|UAR}} [[Abdul Munim Riad]]{{KIA}}
|strength1=275,000 (including reserves)
|strength2=[[Egypt]]ian: 200,000&lt;br /&gt;[[Soviet Union|Soviet]]: 10,700–15,000&lt;ref&gt;Russian Aviation and Air Power in the Twentieth Century, Robin D. S. Higham, John T. Greenwood, Von Hardesty, Routledge, 1998, p.227&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;br /&gt;[[Jordan]]ian: 15,000&lt;ref&gt;Fruchter-Ronen I, (2008), pp. 244-260&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;br /&gt;[[Palestine Liberation Organization|PLO]]: 900-1,000&lt;ref&gt;Morris (1999), p. 368&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Wallach, Jedua; Ayalon, Avraham; Yitzhaki, Aryeh (1980). &quot;Operation Inferno&quot;. in Evyatar Nur. ''Carta's Atlas of Israel'', Volume 2&lt;/ref&gt;
|casualties1=594–1,424 soldiers killed&lt;br /&gt;127 civilians killed&lt;br /&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Schiff (1974)&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=JewishVirtualLibrary /&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;MFA&quot;&gt;{{cite web
| url = http://www.mfa.gov.il/MFA/History/Modern+History/Centenary+of+Zionism/The+Arab-Israeli+Wars.htm 2,000+ solder and 700 civilian wounded
| title = The Arab-Israeli Wars
| accessdate = 2007-03-03
| date = 2003-09-02
| last = Lorch
| first = Netanel
| publisher = Israeli Ministry of Foreign Affairs
}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;br /&gt;2000–3,000 wounded&lt;br /&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Herzog (1982)&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.jewishvirtuallibrary.org/jsource/History/casualty_table.html The War of attrition, 1967-1970]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;br /&gt;14-30 aircraft&lt;ref name=&quot;Benny Morris 2001, Page 362&quot;&gt;Benny Morris, Righteous victims: a history of the Zionist-Arab conflict, 1881-2001, Random House (1999), Page 362&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;nicolle32-33&quot;&gt;Nicolle and Cooper, 32-33&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;br /&gt;1 destroyer&lt;br /&gt;4 tanks&lt;br /&gt;2 half-tracks&lt;br /&gt;2 armored cars
|casualties2='''Egypt''':&lt;br /&gt;2,882&lt;ref&gt;Shazli, ''The Crossing of Suez.'' p.195. ISBN 978-0-9604562-2-2.&lt;/ref&gt;-10,000&lt;ref name=&quot;Benny Morris 2001, Page 362&quot;/&gt; soldiers and civilians killed&lt;br /&gt;6,285 wounded&lt;ref&gt;Uri Bar, ''The Watchman Fell Asleep: The Surprise Of Yom Kippur And Its Sources''. p.15. ISBN 978-0-7914-6482-3.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;br /&gt;60–114 aircraft lost&lt;ref name=nicolle32-33/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Insight Team of the London Sunday Times, Yom Kippur War, Double Day &amp; Company (1974) Page 42&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;br /&gt;'''PLO''':&lt;br /&gt;1,828 killed&lt;br /&gt;2,500 captured&lt;ref&gt;Zeev Schiff, History of the Israeli Army 1870-1974, Straight Arrow Books (1974)
ISBN 087932077, page 246&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;br /&gt;'''Jordan''':&lt;br /&gt;84 killed&lt;br /&gt;250 wounded&lt;br /&gt;4 captured&lt;br /&gt;30 tanks&lt;br /&gt;2 aircraft&lt;br /&gt;'''Soviet Union''':&lt;br /&gt;58 dead&lt;br /&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.hubara-rus.ru/heroes.html A list of known Soviet army losses of manpower during The War of attrition, Russian.]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;br /&gt;4-5 aircraft&lt;br /&gt;'''Syria''':&lt;br /&gt;Hundreds of casualties&lt;ref name=autogenerated1&gt;[http://dover.idf.il/NR/rdonlyres/0771A94F-B23C-43E6-8955-9630D34B8076/0/WarofAttrition40Years.ppt#262,6, The War: Lebanon and Syria]&lt;/ref&gt;
}}
{{Campaignbox War of Attrition}}

The '''War of Attrition''' ({{lang-ar|حرب الاستنزاف}} ''Ḥarb al-Istinzāf'', {{lang-he|מלחמת ההתשה}} ''Milhemet haHatashah'') was a [[limited war]] fought between [[Israel]] and [[Egypt]] from 1967 to 1970. Following the 1967 [[Six Day War]], there were no serious diplomatic efforts to resolve the issues at the heart of the Arab-Israeli conflict. In September 1967 Arab states formulated the &quot;[[Khartoum Resolution|Three Nos]]&quot; policy, barring peace, recognition or negotiations with Israel. Egyptian President [[Gamel Abdel Nasser]] believed only military initiative would compel Israel or the international community to force a full Israeli withdrawal from Sinai,&lt;ref name=&quot;dunstan&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal |title = Egypt Will Fight, Nasser Shouts|publisher=[[Pittsburgh Post-Gazette]]|date=November 24, 1967|url=http://news.google.com/newspapers?nid=1129&amp;dat=19671124&amp;id=iy4NAAAAIBAJ&amp;sjid=mmwDAAAAIBAJ&amp;pg=7156,4781952|page=2 |postscript = }}&lt;/ref&gt; and hostilities soon resumed along the [[Suez Canal]]. These initially took the form of limited artillery duels and small scale incursions into Sinai, but by 1969 the [[Egyptian Army]] was prepared for larger scaled operations. On March 8, 1969, Nasser proclaimed the official launch of the War of Attrition, characterized by large scale shelling along the Canal, extensive aerial warfare and commando raids.&lt;ref name=&quot;dunstan&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Mirages&quot;&gt;{{cite book|last=Aloni|first=Shlomo|title=Israeli Mirage and Nesher Aces|publisher=Osprey|year=2004|pages=46–53}}&lt;/ref&gt; Hostilities continued until August 1970 and ended with a ceasefire, the frontiers remaining the same as when the war began, with no real commitment to serious peace negotiations.

==Egyptian front==
[[Israel]]'s victory in the [[Six-Day War]] left the entirety of the [[Egypt]]ian [[Sinai Peninsula]] up to the eastern bank of the Suez Canal under [[Israel]]i occupation.  Egypt was determined to regain Sinai, and also sought to mitigate the severity of its defeat. Sporadic clashes were taking place along the cease-fire line, and Egyptian missile boats sank the Israeli destroyer ''[[HMS Zealous (R39)|INS Eilat]]'' on October 21 of the same year.

Egypt began shelling Israeli positions along the [[Bar Lev Line]], using heavy artillery, deep-penetration raids into Sinai, [[MiG]] aircraft and various other forms of [[Soviet Union|Soviet]] assistance with the hope of forcing a war-weary Israeli government into concessions.&lt;ref name=&quot;Britannica&quot;&gt;{{cite web
| url = http://www.britannica.com/eb/article-219430/Israel
| title = Israel: The War of Attrition
| accessdate = 2007-03-03
| publisher = Encyclopædia Britannica
}}&lt;/ref&gt; Israel responded with aerial bombardments, airborne raids on Egyptian military positions, and aerial strikes against strategic facilities in Egypt.

The rationale of the Egyptian President, [[Gamal Abdel Nasser]], was explained by journalist [[Mohamed Hassanein Heikal]]:{{Citation needed|date=February 2011}}

{{quotation
| &quot;If the enemy succeeds in inflicting three-thousand casualties in this campaign, we can go on fighting nevertheless, because we have manpower reserves.  If we succeed in inflicting ten-thousand casualties, he will unavoidably find himself compelled to stop fighting, because he has no manpower reserves.&quot;
}}

The international community and both countries attempted to find a diplomatic solution to the conflict.  The [[Jarring Mission]] of the [[United Nations]] was supposed to ensure that the terms of [[UN Security Council Resolution 242]] would be observed, but by late 1970 it was clear that this mission had been a failure.  Fearing the escalation of the conflict into an &quot;[[Warsaw Pact|East]] vs. [[NATO|West]]&quot; confrontation during the tensions of the mid-[[Cold War]], the [[USA|American]] President, [[Richard Nixon]], sent his [[US Secretary of State|Secretary of State]], [[William Rogers]], to formulate the [[Rogers Plan]] in view of obtaining a ceasefire.

In August 1970, Israel, [[Jordan]], and Egypt agreed to an &quot;in place&quot; ceasefire under the terms proposed by the Rogers Plan.  The plan contained restrictions on missile deployment by both sides, and required the cessation of raids as a precondition for peace.  The Egyptians and their Soviet allies rekindled the conflict by violating the agreement shortly thereafter, moving their missiles near to the Suez Canal, and constructing the largest anti-aircraft system yet implemented at that point in history.&lt;ref name=&quot;JewishVirtualLibrary&quot;&gt;{{cite web
| url = http://www.jewishvirtuallibrary.org/jsource/myths/mf8.html
| title = Myths &amp; Facts Online: The War of Attrition, 1967–1970
| accessdate = 2007-03-03
| last = Gard
| first = Mitchell
| publisher = Jewish Virtual Library
}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=Britannica /&gt;

The Israelis responded with a policy which their [[Prime Minister]], [[Golda Meir]], dubbed “[[Asymmetric warfare|asymmetrical response]]”, wherein Israeli retaliation was disproportionately large in comparison to any Egyptian attacks.&lt;ref name=Britannica /&gt;

Following Nasser’s death in September 1970, his successor, [[Anwar Al-Sadat]], ceased current hostilities with Israel, focusing instead on rebuilding the [[Egyptian army]] and planning a full-scale attack on the Israeli forces occupying the eastern bank of the Suez Canal. These plans would materialize three years later in the [[1973 Yom Kippur War]]. Ultimately, Israel would return Sinai to Egypt after the two nations signed a [[Egyptian-Israeli Peace Treaty|peace treaty]].

Commenting on the war, historian Simon Dunstan stated:&lt;ref name=&quot;dunstan&quot;/&gt;

{{quotation
| &quot;The War of Attrition had sapped Israel's morale. Nevertheless, the IDF held the Bar-Lev Line and brought the Egyptians to the negotiating table. This, however, led to a dangerous complacency within the Israeli High Command about the resolve of the Egyptian armed forces and the strength of the Bar-Lev Line ... In contrast, the Egyptians regarded the War of Attrition as a great success, in spite of the thousands of casualties their army and air force had sufferred and the mauling their air defence system has received. They had not buckled and from this they drew considerable confidence, not least in their ability to counter the weapon that had destroyed them in 1967—the Israeli Air Force.&quot;}}

==Timeline==

'''July 1, 1967''': [[Egyptian Army]] artillery fires on an Israeli armored infantry company near the Suez Canal. The Israeli unit commander is killed and thirteen Israeli troops are wounded.&lt;ref&gt;Herzog and Gazit, p. 196&lt;/ref&gt; An Egyptian force of around thirty commandos supported by artillery defeated a mixed Israeli force of ten tanks and mechanized infantry in repeated attacks at Ras Al-'Ish, south of [[Port Fouad]]. The victory is a significant morale boost for the Egyptians in the aftermath of defeat. Port Fouad and its vicinity is the only part of Sinai to remain in Egyptian hands.&lt;ref name=&quot;dunstan&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Shazly, p.84&quot;&gt;Saad El Shazly, ''The Crossing of the Suez'' p.84&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Gamasy, p.99&quot;&gt;El Gamasy, ''The October War, 1973'' p.99&lt;/ref&gt;

'''July 2, 1967''': The [[Israeli Air Force]] bombs Egyptian artillery positions that had supported the commandos at Ras Al-'Ish.&lt;ref name=&quot;Gamasy, p.99&quot;/&gt;

'''July 4, 1967''': [[Egyptian Air Force]] jets strike several Israeli targets in Sinai. An Egyptian [[Mikoyan-Gurevich MiG-17|MiG-17]] is shot down.&lt;ref name=&quot;acig&quot;&gt;[http://www.acig.org/artman/publish/article_263.shtml War of Attrition, 1969-1970&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;

'''July 8, 1967''': An [[Egyptian Air Force]] [[Mikoyan-Gurevich MiG-21|MiG-21]] is shot down by Israeli air defenses while on a reconnaissance mission over el-Qanatra. Two [[Sukhoi Su-7|Su-7]]s equipped with cameras are then sent out to carry out the mission, and manage to complete several turns over Sinai without any opposition. Two other Su-7s are sent for another reconnaissance mission hours later, but are attacked by [[Israeli Air Force]] fighter jets. One Su-7 is shot down.&lt;ref name=&quot;acig&quot;/&gt;

'''July 11–12, 1967''': [[Israeli Navy]] destroyer [[HMS Zealous (R39)|INS ''Eilat]] and two [[torpedo boat]]s sink two [[Egyptian Navy]] torpedo boats off the Rumani coast.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.jewishvirtuallibrary.org/jsource/Society_&amp;_Culture/navywar.html The Israel Navy Throughout Israel's Wars&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;

'''July 14–15, 1967''': On July 14, ten [[Egyptian Air Force]] [[Mikoyan-Gurevich MiG-17|MiG-17]] fighter-bombers escorted by ten [[Mikoyan-Gurevich MiG-21|MiG-21]] fighters, attack Israeli tank and armored concentrations in the southern sector of the canal and shoot down two Israeli aircraft attempting to intervene, while suffering no losses. A second airstrike takes place the following day, with a successful outcome.&lt;ref&gt;El Gamasy, ''The October War, 1973'' p.99-100&lt;/ref&gt;

'''August, 1967''': Another Israeli attempt to capture [[Port Fouad]] is stopped at Ras Al-'Ish by Egyptian commandos.&lt;ref name=&quot;Shazly, p.84&quot;/&gt;

'''October 21, 1967''': The [[Egyptian Navy]] sinks the Israeli destroyer INS ''Eilat'', killing forty-seven sailors.&lt;ref name=JewishVirtualLibrary /&gt;

'''October, 1967''': In retaliation to the sinking of the Eilat, Israeli artillery bombards oil refineries and depots near [[Suez]]. In a series of artillery exchanges throughout October, the Egyptians sustain civilian casualties. Egypt evacuates a large number of the civilian population in the canal region.&lt;ref&gt;El Gamasy, ''The October War, 1973'' p.101&lt;/ref&gt;

'''March 21, 1968''': In response to persistent PLO raids against Israeli civilian targets, Israel [[Battle of Karameh|attacks]] the town of [[Karameh]], [[Jordan]], the site of a major PLO camp, but is met with resistance by Jordanian and PLO forces. Despite hours of fighting, Israeli troops consolidate their hold on the Karameh camp with the aid of artillery and airstrikes, blowing up 175 houses. They then fight their way back to Israeli territory, taking with them as much military equipment as they can, along with 120-150 prisoners. Both sides suffered significant casualties and material losses, but Jordanian and PLO losses were far greater than Israeli ones.

'''June 1968''': The war &quot;officially&quot; begins, with sparse Egyptian artillery bombardment of the Israeli front line on the east bank of the Suez Canal. More artillery bombardments in the following months cause Israeli casualties.&lt;ref name=Britannica /&gt;

'''September 8, 1968''': An Egyptian artillery barrage kills 10 Israeli soldiers and injures 18. Israel responds by shelling [[Suez]] and [[Ismailia]].&lt;ref name=&quot;acig&quot;/&gt;

'''October 30, 1968''': Israeli [[Helicopter|heli]]-borne [[Sayeret Matkal]] commandos carry out [[Operation Helem]] (Shock), destroying an Egyptian electric transformator station, two dams along the [[Nile River]] and a bridge.&lt;ref name=&quot;acig&quot;/&gt; The blackout causes Nasser to cease hostilities for a few months while fortifications around hundreds of important targets are built. Simultaneously, Israel reinforces its position on the east bank of the Suez Canal by construction of the [[Bar Lev Line]].&lt;ref name=&quot;SIS: Book Review: At Noon The Myth Was Shattered&quot;&gt;{{cite web
| url = http://www.sis.gov.eg/En/Pub/magazin/fall1998/110208000000000003.htm
| title = Book Review: At Noon The Myth Was Shattered
| accessdate = 2007-03-04
| publisher = Egyptian State Information Service
}}&lt;/ref&gt;

'''November 3, 1968''': Egyptian MiG-17s attack Israeli positions, and are met by Israeli interceptors. One Israeli plane is damaged.&lt;ref name=&quot;acig&quot;/&gt;

'''December 1, 1968''': Israeli heli-borne commandos destroy four bridges near [[Amman]], [[Jordan]].&lt;ref name=&quot;acig&quot;/&gt;

'''December 3, 1968''': The [[Israeli Air Force]] bombs PLO camps in [[Jordan]]. The Israeli jets are intercepted by [[Hawker Hunter]]s of the [[Royal Jordanian Air Force]], and an Israeli fighter jet is damaged during the brief air battle.&lt;ref name=&quot;acig&quot;/&gt;

'''March 3, 1969''': Nasser officially voids the ceasefire of October 1968.{{Citation needed|date=March 2010}}

'''March 8, 1969''': Egypt strikes the Bar Lev Line with artillery fire and airstrikes, causing heavy casualties. Israel retaliates with raids deep into Egyptian territory, causing severe damage.&lt;ref name=Britannica /&gt;

'''March 9, 1969''': Egyptian Chief of Staff [[Abdul Munim Riad]] is killed in an Israeli mortar attack while visiting the front lines along the Suez Canal.

'''May–July 1969''': Heavy fighting takes place between Israeli and Egyptian forces. Egypt takes heavy casualties and material losses, while the Israel loses 47 dead and 157 wounded. Despite its losses, Egypt maintains its aggressive stance.

'''July 18, 1969''': Egyptian commandos raid Israeli military installations in Sinai.&lt;ref name=&quot;acig&quot;/&gt;

'''July 19–20, 1969''': [[Operation Bulmus 6]] -  Israeli [[Shayetet 13]] and [[Sayeret Matkal]] commandos raid [[Green Island (Egypt)|Green Island]], resulting in the total destruction of the Egyptian facility. Six Israeli soldiers and 80 Egyptian soldiers are killed. Some Egyptian casualties are caused by their own artillery.

'''July 20–28, 1969''': [[Operation Boxer]] - Nearly the entire [[Israeli Air Force]] attacks the northern sector of the Canal, destroying anti-aircraft positions, tanks and artillery, and shooting down eight Egyptian aircraft. An estimated 300 Egyptian soldiers are killed. It also manages to reduce the artillery bombardment somewhat. However, shelling with lighter weapons, particularly [[Mortar (weapon)|mortars]], continues.

'''August 1969''': The Israeli Air Force flies about 1,000 combat sorties against Egypt, destroying dozens of SAM sites and shooting down 21 aircraft. Three Israeli aircraft are lost.&lt;ref name=&quot;acig&quot;/&gt;

'''September 9, 1969''': [[Operation Raviv]] - Israeli forces raid Egypt's Red Sea coast. The raid is preceded by [[Operation Escort]], with [[Shayetet 13]] naval commandos sinking a pair of Egyptian torpedo boats that could have threatened the Israeli raiding party. Three commandos are killed when an explosive device detonates prematurely. Israeli troops backed up by aircraft and captured Egyptian armor, destroy 12 Egyptian outposts. The Egyptians suffer 100-200 casualties, and a [[Soviet Union|Soviet]] general serving as a consultant to the Egyptians is also killed, while one Israeli soldier is lightly injured. An Israeli plane is shot down during the raid, and the pilot's fate becomes unknown.

'''September 11, 1969''': The [[Egyptian Air Force]] launches an air raid on Israeli positions in Sinai, employing 107 aircraft in the strike. One MiG-17 is shot down by Israeli antiaircraft fire, while the Israeli Air Force claims to have shot down five MiG-21s and a [[Sukhoi Su-7]] in aerial combat for the loss of a single [[Dassault Mirage III]]. Egypt claims the destruction of three Israeli aircraft.&lt;ref&gt;Nicolle and Cooper, 2004, pp. 30-31&lt;/ref&gt;

'''October 17, 1969''': The United States and Soviet Union begin diplomatic talks to end the conflict.

'''December 9, 1969''': The Rogers Plan is publicized. It calls for Egyptian &quot;commitment to peace&quot; in exchange for the Israeli withdrawal from Sinai. Both parties strongly reject the plan.  President Nasser instead opts to plead for more sophisticated weaponry from the Soviet Union to withstand the IAF bombings. The Soviets initially refuse to deliver the requested weapons.&lt;ref name = &quot;MFA: 9 Statement by Secretary of State Rogers- 9 December 1969&quot;&gt;{{cite web
| url = http://www.mfa.gov.il/MFA/Foreign+Relations/Israels+Foreign+Relations+since+1947/1947-1974/9+Statement+by+Secretary+of+State+Rogers-+9+Decemb.htm
| title = 9 Statement by Secretary of State Rogers- 9 December 1969
| accessdate = 2007-03-04
| publisher = Israeli Ministry of Foreign Affairs
}}&lt;/ref&gt; In an engagement that day, the Egyptians, supplied with newly delivered [[P-15 radar]]s, hold technological superiority to some degree over the Israelis for once. Two Mirages were spotted by one such radar, and the Mirages promptly turned off their airborne radars to remain electronically invisible. A pair of MiG-21s arriving to intercept came up against the Mirages head-on, and opened fire with their 23&amp;nbsp;mm cannons. The Mirages made a climbing turn and lost sight of the MiGs, who were in fact below them. The MiG-21s fired their missiles and shot down both Mirages. Later in the evening, EAF Lt. Ahmed Atef shot down an Israeli [[F-4 Phantom II]], making him the first Egyptian pilot to shoot down an F-4 in combat.&lt;ref&gt;Nicolle and Cooper, 31&lt;/ref&gt;

'''26–27 December 1969''': Israel launchers Operation [[Operation Rooster 53|Rooster 53]], carried out by paratroopers transported by [[Sikorsky CH-53 Sea Stallion|Sikorsky CH-53E]] and [[Super Frelon]] helicopters. The operation results in the capture of an Egyptian [[P-12 radar|P-12]] radar at [[Ras Gharib]] and carrying it to Israel by 2 [[CH-53 Sea Stallion]] Helicopters. The operation enabled Israeli and American learning of the latest radar technology of the [[Soviet Union|Soviet]], and caused a huge morale impact on the Egyptians.

'''January 22, 1970''': President Nasser secretly flies to [[Moscow]] to discuss the situation.  His request for new [[Surface-to-air missile|SAM]] batteries (including the [[3M9 Kub]] and [[Strela-2]]) is approved.  Their deployment requires qualified personnel along with squadrons of aircraft to protect them.  In effect, he needs [[Red Army]] in large numbers, something the [[Kremlin]] did not want to provide. Nasser then threatens to resign, implying that Egypt might turn to the United States for help in the future. The Soviets had invested heavily in President Nasser's regime, and so, the Soviet leader, [[General Secretary of the Communist Party of the Soviet Union|General-Secretary]] [[Leonid Brezhnev]], finally obliged. The Soviet presence was to increase from 2,500–4,000 in January to 10,600–12,150 (plus 100–150 Soviet pilots) by June 30.

'''22 January 1970''': [[Operation Rhodes]]. Israeli paratroopers and naval commandos are transported by IAF [[Super Frelon]] helicopters to [[Shadwan|Shadwan Island]] where they kill 70 Egyptian soldiers and take 62 more prisoner at the loss of 3 dead and 7 wounded. The soldiers dismantle an Egyptian radar and other military equipment for transport back to Israel. IAF aircraft sink two Egyptian P-183 [[torpedo boat]]s during the operation.&lt;ref&gt;Chaim Herzog, The Arab-Israeli Wars, Random House New York (1982) p.214 ISBN 0-394-50379-1&lt;/ref&gt;

'''February, 1970''': Egyptian Navy frogmen sink Israeli boats in Port of Eilat.&lt;ref&gt;[http://middleeast.about.com/od/arabisraeliconflict/f/war-of-attrition.htm The War of Attrition - What Was the War of Attrition Between Egypt and Israel 1968-1970&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;

'''March 15, 1970''': The first fully operational Soviet SAM site in Egypt is completed. It is part of three brigades which the Soviet Union sends to Egypt.&lt;ref name=ACIG /&gt; Israeli [[F-4 Phantom II]] jets repeatedly bomb Egyptian positions in Sinai. On 9 February, an air battle takes place, with each side losing one plane.&lt;ref name=&quot;acig&quot;/&gt;

'''April 8, 1970''': Israeli Air Force [[F4 Phantom II]] jets kill forty-seven Egyptian schoolchildren at an elementary school in what is known as [[Bahr el-Baqar incident]]. The single-floor school was hit by five bombs and two air-to-ground missiles.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news | first= | last= | coauthors= |authorlink= | title=The Innocent Dead | date=1970-04-20 | publisher= | url =http://www.time.com/time/magazine/article/0,9171,944025,00.html | work =Time Magazine | pages = | accessdate = 2009-04-18 | language = }}&lt;/ref&gt; This put a definite end to the campaign, and the Israelis instead then concentrate upon Canal-side installations. The respite gives the Egyptians time to reconstruct its SAM batteries closer to the canal.  Soviet flown MiG fighters provide the necessary air cover. Soviet pilots also begin approaching IAF aircraft during April 1970, but Israeli pilots have orders not to engage these aircraft, and break off whenever Soviet-piloted MiGs appear.

'''May, 1970''': During the final days of the month, the IAF launch major air raids against [[Port Said]], believing a large amphibious force is assembling in the town. On the 16th an Israeli aircraft is shot down in air combat, probably by a MiG-21.&lt;ref&gt;Nicolle and Cooper, 32&lt;/ref&gt;

'''June 1970''': Israeli armored raid on Syrian military positions results in &quot;hundreds of Syrian casualties.&quot;

'''June 25, 1970''': An Israeli [[A-4 Skyhawk]], in an attack sortie against Egyptian forces on the Canal, is pursued by a pair of Soviet-piloted [[MiG-21]]s into Sinai. According to the Soviets, the plane was shot down, while the Israelis claim that it was damaged and forced to land at a nearby airbase.&lt;ref name=&quot;ACIG&quot;&gt;{{cite web
| url = http://www.acig.org/artman/publish/article_263.shtml
| title = War of Attrition
| last = Cooper
| first = Tom
| date = 2003-09-24
| publisher = Air Combat Information Group
| accessdate = 2007-03-07
}}&lt;/ref&gt;

'''June 27, 1970''': The EAF continued to launch air raids across the canal. On June 27 around eight Egyptian [[Su-7]]s and MiG-21s attack Israeli rear areas in Sinai. According to Israel, two Egyptian aircraft were shot down. An Israeli Mirage was shot down, and the pilot was captured.&lt;ref&gt;Nicolle and Cooper, 33&lt;/ref&gt;

'''July 18, 1970''': An Israeli airstrike on Egypt causes casualties among Soviet military personnel.

'''June 30, 1970''': Soviet air defenses shoot down two Israeli F-4 Phantoms. Two pilots and a navigator are captured, while a second navigator is rescued by helicopter the following night.&lt;ref name=&quot;acig&quot;/&gt;

'''July 30, 1970''': - A large-scale dogfight occurs between Israeli and Soviet aircraft, codenamed ''[[Operation Rimon 20|Rimon 20]]'', involving twelve to twenty-four Soviet MiG-21s (besides the initial twelve, other MiGs are &quot;scrambled&quot;, but it is unclear if they reach the battle in time), and twelve Israeli [[Dassault Mirage III]]s and four [[F-4 Phantom II]] jets, takes place west of the Suez Canal. Ambushing their opponents, the Israelis shoot down four of the Soviet-piloted MiGs. A fifth is possibly hit and later crashes en route back to base. Four Soviet pilots are killed, while the IAF suffers no losses except a damaged Mirage.&lt;ref name=ACIG/&gt; Following the Soviets' direct intervention, known as &quot;Operation Kavkaz&quot;,&lt;ref name=ACIG /&gt; Washington fears an escalation and redoubles efforts toward a peaceful resolution to the conflict.

'''Early August, 1970''': Despite their losses, the Soviets and Egyptians manage to press the air defenses closer and closer to the canal, shooting down a number of Israeli aircraft. The SAM batteries allow the Egyptians to move in artillery which in turn threatens the Bar Lev Line.

'''August 7, 1970''': A cease-fire agreement is reached, forbidding either side from changing &quot;the military status quo within zones extending 50&amp;nbsp;kilometers to the east and west of the cease-fire line.&quot;  Minutes after the cease-fire, Egypt begins moving SAM batteries into the zone even though the agreement explicitly forbids new military installations.&lt;ref name=&quot;dunstan&quot;/&gt;  By October there are approximately one-hundred SAM sites in the zone.

'''September 28, 1970''': President Nasser dies of a [[myocardial infarction|heart attack]], and his Vice President, [[Anwar Sadat]], takes the reins. Sadat agrees to end the War of Attrition and almost immediately begins planning the [[Yom Kippur War]], which would take place three years later.

==Casualties==
{{Main|Israeli casualties of war}}

According to military historian [[Zeev Schiff]], some 721 Israelis, of which 594 were soldiers and the remainder civilians, were killed on all three fronts.&lt;ref name=&quot;Schiff 1974 p246&quot;&gt;Schiff (1974) p246&lt;/ref&gt; [[Chaim Herzog]] notes a slightly lower figure of just over 500 killed and some 2000 wounded &lt;ref&gt;Chaim Herzog, The Arab-Israeli Wars, Random House New York, (1982) p.220 ISBN 0-394-50379-1&lt;/ref&gt; while Netanel Lorch, states that 1,424 soldiers were killed in action between the period of 15 June 1967 and 8 August 1970. Between 14&lt;ref name=&quot;Morris 1999 p362&quot;&gt;Morris (1999) p362&lt;/ref&gt; and 16&lt;ref name=&quot;London Sunday Times 1974 p42&quot;&gt;Insight Team of the London Sunday Times (1974) p42&lt;/ref&gt; Israeli aircraft were shot down. A Soviet estimate notes aircraft losses of 30. One destroyer, the ''INS Eilat'', was sunk.

As with the previous Arab-Israeli wars of [[1948 Arab-Israeli war|1948]], [[Operation Kadesh|1956]] and [[Six-day war|1967]], Arab losses far exceeded those of Israel but precise figures are difficult to ascertain because official figures were never disclosed. The lowest estimate comes from the former Egyptian Army Chief of Staff, [[Saad El Shazly]], who notes Egyptian casualties of 2,882 killed and 6,285 wounded. Historian [[Benny Morris]] states that a more realistic figure is somewhere on the scale of 10,000 soldiers and civilians killed. [[Zeev Schiff]] notes that at the height of the war, the Egyptians were losing some 300 soldiers daily and aerial reconnaissance photos revealed at least 1,801 freshly dug graves near the Canal zone during this period. Among Egypt's war dead was the Egyptian Army Chief of Staff, [[Abdul Munim Riad]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Schiff 1974 p246&quot;/&gt; Between 98&lt;ref name=&quot;Morris 1999 p362&quot;/&gt; and 114&lt;ref name=&quot;London Sunday Times 1974 p42&quot;/&gt; Egyptian aircraft were shot down though a Soviet estimate notes air losses of 60. A number of Egyptian naval vessels were sunk. The PLO suffered 1,828 killed and 2,500 captured.&lt;ref name=&quot;Schiff 1974 p246&quot;/&gt; Jordan’s intervention on behalf of the PLO during the [[Battle of Karameh]] cost it 84 killed and two aircraft lost. An undisclosed number of Soviet military personnel were killed. At least four Soviet pilots were confirmed killed during [[Operation Rimon 20]]. Five Soviet piloted [[MiG-21]] aircraft were shot down during this engagement. Syrian casualties are unknown but an armored raid by Israel forces against Syrian positions in June 1970 led to &quot;hundreds of Syrian casualties.&quot;&lt;ref name=autogenerated1 /&gt;

==See also==
'''Conflicts'''
* [[Black September in Jordan]]
* [[List of modern conflicts in the Middle East]]

'''Politics'''
* [[1978 Camp David Peace Accords between Egypt and Israel]]
* [[Israel-Egypt Peace Treaty|1979 Israel-Egypt Peace Treaty]]

'''People'''
* [[Ahmad Ismail Ali]]
* [[Saad El Shazly]]
* [[Chaim Bar-Lev]]
* [[Leonid Brezhnev]]
* [[Moshe Dayan]]
* [[Mohammed Fawzi]]
* [[Gunnar Jarring]]
* [[Pavel Kutakov]]
* [[Uriel Menuhin]]
* [[Abdul Tarek]]
* [[Gamal Abdel Nasser]]
* [[Nikolai Podgorny]]
* [[Yitzhak Rabin]]
* [[Abdul Munim Riad]]
* [[William P. Rogers|William Rogers]]
* [[Anwar Sadat]]
* [[Ariel Sharon]]
* [[Joseph Sisco]]
* [[Matvei Vasilievich Zakharov]]
* [[Fouad Zikri]]

==References==
{{reflist|colwidth=30em|refs=
&lt;ref name=&quot;dunstan&quot;&gt;[[#citeDunstan|Dunstan 2003]], pp. 7-14&lt;/ref&gt;
}}

==Bibliography==
* Bar-Simon Tov, Yaacov. ''The Israeli-Egyptian War of Attrition, 1969–70''. New York: Columbia University Press, 1980.
*&lt;cite id=citeDunstan&gt;{{cite book|first=Simon|last=Dunstan|title=Yom Kippur War 1973: The Sinai Campaign|isbn=978-1-84176-221-0|publisher=Osprey|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=1BYk_sXT6tsC|year=2003}}&lt;/cite&gt;
* Herzog, Chaim and Gazit Shlomo. ''The Arab-Israeli Wars: War and Peace in the Middle East''. New York: Vintage Books, 2004.
* {{cite book | first=Benny|last=Morris | title=Righteous Victims: A History of the Zionist-Arab Conflict, 1881–1999 | publisher=Knopf | year=1999 | isbn=978-0-679-42120-7 }}
* {{Cite book| edition = First| publisher = Osprey Publishing| isbn = 978-1-84176-655-3| page = 96| last = Nicolle| first = David| last2=Cooper| first2=Tom| title = Arab MiG-19 and MiG-21 Units in Combat| year = 2004}}
* {{cite book | last=Rabinovitch| title=The Yom Kippur War: The Epic Encounter That Transformed the Middle East.| year=2004| isbn=978-0-8052-4176-1}}
* Schiff, Zeev, History of the Israeli Army 1870-1974, Straight Arrow Books (1974) ISBN 087932077
* {{cite book |author=Whetten, Lawrence L. |title=The Canal War: Four-Power Conflict in the Middle East |publisher=MIT Press |location=Cambridge, Mass |year=1974 |isbn=978-0-262-23069-8}}
* Insight Team of the ''London Sunday Times'', Yom Kippur War, Double Day &amp; Company (1974)

==External links==
* [http://www.acig.org/artman/publish/article_263.shtml War of Attrition, 1969–1970], ACIG, retrieved January 2, 2007
* [http://www.us-israel.org/jsource/Society_&amp;_Culture/69iaf.html Jewish Virtual Library]
* [http://weekly.ahram.org.eg/archives/67-97/sup8.htm The Three Year War, General Mohamed Fawzi]
* [http://dover.idf.il/NR/rdonlyres/0771A94F-B23C-43E6-8955-9630D34B8076/0/WarofAttrition40Years.ppt#256,1,Slide 40 Years Since The War of Attrition]

{{Israeli wars}}
{{Arab–Israeli conflict}}
{{Cold War}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:War Of Attrition}}
[[Category:War of Attrition]]

[[ar:حرب الاستنزاف]]
[[cs:Opotřebovací válka]]
[[cy:Y Rhyfel Athreuliol]]
[[da:Udmattelseskrigen]]
[[de:Abnutzungskrieg]]
[[es:Guerra de Desgaste]]
[[fr:Guerre d'usure]]
[[id:Perang Atrisi]]
[[it:Guerra d'attrito]]
[[he:מלחמת ההתשה]]
[[arz:حرب الاستنزاف]]
[[nl:Uitputtingsoorlog (1967-1970)]]
[[no:Utmattelseskrigen]]
[[pl:Wojna na wyczerpanie]]
[[pt:Guerra de Desgaste]]
[[ru:Война на истощение]]
[[sk:Opotrebovávacia vojna (Arabsko-izraelský konflikt)]]
[[sr:Рат исцрпљивања]]
[[fi:Suezin kanavasota]]
[[ur:جنگ استنزاف]]
[[zh:埃以消耗战争]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
