<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="18273" ns="0" title="Lotus 1-2-3"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Infobox software
| name                   = Lotus 1-2-3
| logo                   = [[Image:Lotus 1-2-3 9.8 icon.png]]
| screenshot             = [[Image:Lotus 1-2-3 9.8 Windows.png|300px]]
| caption                =
| collapsible            =
| developer              = [[IBM]]
| status                 = Discontinued
| latest release version = 9.8
| latest release date    = 2002
| operating system       = [[Microsoft Windows]], [[Mac OS]]
| genre                  = [[Spreadsheet]]
| license                = [[Proprietary software|Proprietary]]
| website                = [http://www.ibm.com/software/lotus/products/123/  www.ibm.com]
}}

'''Lotus 1-2-3''' is a [[spreadsheet]] program from [[Lotus Software]] (now part of [[International Business Machines|IBM]]). It was the [[IBM PC]]'s first &quot;[[killer application]]&quot;; its huge popularity in the mid-1980s contributed significantly to the success of the IBM PC in the corporate environment.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.crn.com/it-channel/18818026 Acquired 2007-10-31&lt;/ref&gt;

==Beginnings==
[[Image:Lotus-123-3.0-dos.png|thumb|250px|Lotus 1-2-3 3.0 for DOS.]]
The Lotus Development Corporation was founded by [[Mitchell Kapor]], a friend of the developers of [[VisiCalc]]. 1-2-3 was originally written by [[Jonathan Sachs]], who had written two spreadsheet programs previously while working at Concentric Data Systems, Inc.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.ibm.com/developerworks/lotus/library/ls-NDHistory/ 2007-10-31&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.cbi.umn.edu/oh/pdf.phtml?id=340 Oral history interview with Jonathan Sachs], [[Charles Babbage Institute]], University of Minnesota.&lt;/ref&gt; To aid its growth, in the UK, and possibly elsewhere, Lotus 1-2-3 was the very first computer software to use television consumer advertising.{{Citation needed|date=March 2008}}

1-2-3 was released on January 26, 1983, started outselling then-most-popular [[VisiCalc]] the very same year, and for a number of years was the leading spreadsheet for [[DOS]]. Unlike Microsoft [[Multiplan]], it stayed very close to the model of VisiCalc, including the &quot;A1&quot; letter and number cell notation, and slash-menu structure. It was free of notable bugs, and was very fast because it was programmed entirely in [[x86 assembly language]] and bypassed the slower DOS screen input/output functions in favor of writing directly to memory-mapped video display hardware.

This reliance on the specific hardware of the IBM PC led to 1-2-3 being utilized as one of the two litmus test applications for true 100% compatibility when [[IBM PC compatible|PC clones]] started to appear in the early- to mid- 80s. 1-2-3 was used to test general application compatibility, with [[Microsoft Flight Simulator]] being used to test graphics compatibility. Because all of a spreadsheet needs to be resident in memory, it also drove the race to utilize more memory, and [[extended memory]] and [[expanded memory]] techniques were needed to overcome the DOS limit of 640KB to allow larger spreadsheets - this was so important that a memory used/remaining indicator was displayed on-screen.

==User features==
The name &quot;1-2-3&quot; stemmed from the product's integration of three main capabilities. Along with being a spreadsheet, it also offered integral charting/graphing and rudimentary database operations.

Data features included sorting data in any defined rectangle, by order of information in one or two columns in the rectangular area. Justifying text in a range into paragraphs allowed it to be used as a primitive word processor.

It had keyboard-driven pop-up menus as well as one-key commands, making it fast to operate. It was also user-friendly, introducing an early instance of [[context-sensitive help]] accessed by the F1 key.

[[Macro (computer science)|Macros]] in version one and add-ins (introduced in version 2.0) contributed much to 1-2-3's popularity, allowing dozens of outside vendors to sell macro packages and add-ins ranging from dedicated financial worksheets like [[F9 Financial Reporting|F9]] to full-fledged [[word processor]]s. (In the single-tasking [[MS-DOS]], 1-2-3 was sometimes used as a complete environment.) Lotus 1-2-3 supported [[Enhanced Graphics Adapter|EGA]] graphics on the [[PC/AT]] and [[VGA]] graphics on the [[IBM Personal System/2|PS/2]]. Early versions used the [[filename extension]] &quot;WKS&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.fileinfo.com/extension/wks WKS File Extension - Open .WKS files&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt; In version 2.0, the extension changed first to &quot;WK1&quot;,&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.fileinfo.com/extension/wk1 WK1 File Extension - Open .WK1 files&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt; then &quot;WK2&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.fileinfo.com/extension/wk2 WK2 File Extension - Open .WK2 files&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt; This later became &quot;WK3&quot; for version 3.0&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.fileinfo.com/extension/wk3 WK3 File Extension - Open .WK3 files&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt; and &quot;WK4&quot; for version 4.0.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.fileinfo.com/extension/wk4 WK4 File Extension - Open .WK4 files&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;!-- Unsourced image removed: [[Image:Kapor.gif|thumb|left|Mitch Kapor of Lotus Development]] --&gt;
Version 2 introduced macros with syntax and commands similar in complexity to an advanced [[BASIC]] interpreter, as well as string variable expressions. Later versions supported multiple worksheets and were written in [[C (programming language)|C]].  The charting/graphing routines were written in [[Forth (programming language)|Forth]] by [[Jeremy Sagan]] (son of [[Carl Sagan]]) and the printing routines by Paul Funk (founder of [[Funk Software]]).{{Citation needed|date=May 2008}}

There is also a version of 1-2-3 for the [[HP 200LX]], a [[palmtop]] released by Hewlett-Packard, a port for Tandy's [[Deskmate]] and for Apple's [[Mac OS]] in 1991.

==Rivals==
Lotus 1-2-3 inspired imitators, the first of which was Mosaic Software's &quot;The Twin&quot;, written in the fall of 1985 largely in the C language, followed by [[VP-Planner]], which was backed by [[Adam Osborne]]. These were able to not only read 1-2-3 files, but also execute many or most macro programs by incorporating the same command structure. Copyright law had first been understood to only cover the source code of a program. After the success of lawsuits which claimed that the very &quot;[[look and feel]]&quot; of a program were covered, Lotus sought to ban any program which had a compatible command and menu structure. Program commands had not been considered to be covered before, but the commands of 1-2-3 were embedded in the words of the menu displayed on the screen. 1-2-3 won its case against Mosaic Software. However when they sued [[Borland]] over its [[Quattro Pro]] spreadsheet, the courts ruled that it was not a copyright violation to merely have a compatible command menu or language. In 1995, the First Circuit found that command menus are an uncopyrightable &quot;method of operation&quot; under section 102(b) of the [[Copyright Act]]. The 1-2-3 menu structure (example, slash File Erase) was itself an advanced version of single letter menus introduced in [[VisiCalc]].

==Decline==
The rise of [[Microsoft Windows]] in the personal computer market was accompanied by the rise in [[Microsoft]]'s competing spreadsheet, [[Microsoft Excel|Excel]], which gradually surpassed the position of 1-2-3.  Lotus initially planned a complete rewrite of the product to overtake Excel, but this project dissolved.  1-2-3 for Windows is still simply a graphical wrapper around the original product. Additionally, several versions of 1-2-3 had different functionalities and slightly different interfaces.

1-2-3's intended successor, [[Lotus Symphony for DOS|Lotus Symphony]], was Lotus's entry into the anticipated &quot;[[integrated software]]&quot; market.  It intended to expand the rudimentary all-in-one 1-2-3 into a fully-fledged spreadsheet, graph, database and word processor for DOS, but none of the integrated packages ever really succeeded.  1-2-3 migrated to the Windows platform, where it remains available as part of [[Lotus SmartSuite]].  By release 9 of [[Lotus SmartCenter]], 1-2-3 had matched the capabilities of [[Microsoft Excel|Excel]].

==See also==
{{Portalbox|Computer science}}
*[[Lotus Dev. Corp. v. Borland Int'l, Inc.|Lotus v. Borland]]
*[[As Easy As]]
*[[Comparison of office suites]]

==References==
{{Reflist|2}}

==External links==
* [http://www.lotus.com/ Lotus website]
* [http://library.thinkquest.org/C0130462/main-1983_lotus.htm 1983 The PC Era--Lotus 1-2-3]
* [http://www.aresluna.org/attached/computerhistory/articles/spreadsheets/lotus123review Review of Lotus 123 version 1.0] from December 1982 [[Byte magazine]]
* [ftp://ftp.lotus.com/pub/lotusweb/product/smartsuite/Kvlotus.exe Free viewer for Lotus SmartSuite products (EXE)]
* [http://www.schnarff.com/file-formats/index.html#lotus File Format Documentation for Lotus 1-2-3]
* [http://www.cbi.umn.edu/oh/display.phtml?id=356 Oral history interview with Jonathan Sachs] discusses the development of Lotus 1-2-3, Charles Babbage Institute, University of Minnesota
* [http://www.knubbelmac.de/bildschau.html?basis=lotus-1-2-3 Screenshots of Lotus 1-2-3 V.1.00 for Mac OS]

{{Spreadsheets}}
{{Lotus Software}}

[[Category:DOS software]]
[[Category:Windows software]]
[[Category:Spreadsheet software]]
[[Category:Lotus Software software|1-2-3]]
[[Category:Lotus SmartSuite|1-2-3]]
[[Category:1983 software]]

[[ar:لوتس 1-2-3]]
[[ca:Lotus 1-2-3]]
[[cs:Lotus 1-2-3]]
[[da:Lotus 1-2-3]]
[[de:Lotus 1-2-3]]
[[es:Lotus 1-2-3]]
[[eo:Lotus 1-2-3]]
[[fr:Lotus 1-2-3]]
[[ko:로터스 1-2-3]]
[[it:Lotus 1-2-3]]
[[he:לוטוס 1-2-3]]
[[mr:लोटस १-२-३]]
[[nl:Lotus 1-2-3]]
[[ja:Lotus 1-2-3]]
[[no:Lotus 1-2-3]]
[[pl:Lotus 1-2-3]]
[[pt:Lotus 1-2-3]]
[[ru:Lotus 1-2-3]]
[[si:Lotus 1-2-3]]
[[fi:Lotus 1-2-3]]
[[sv:Lotus 1-2-3]]
[[th:โลตัส 1-2-3]]
[[zh:Lotus 1-2-3]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
