<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="1828331" ns="0" title="Hearts and Minds (film)"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Infobox film
| name           = Hearts and Minds
| image          = HeartsandMindsDVD.jpg
| director       = [[Peter Davis (director)|Peter Davis]]
| producer       = [[Bert Schneider]]&lt;br&gt;Peter Davis
| studio         = [[BBS Productions]]
| distributor    = [[Rialto Pictures]]
| released       = 1974
| runtime        = 112 minutes
| country        = {{Film US}}
| language       = English
| budget         = $1 million
}}
'''''Hearts and Minds''''' is a 1974 American [[documentary film]] about the [[Vietnam War]] directed by [[Peter Davis (director)|Peter Davis]]. The film's title is based on a quote from President [[Lyndon B. Johnson]]: &quot;the ultimate victory will depend on the hearts and minds of the people who actually live out there&quot;.&lt;ref name=TheAge/&gt; The movie was chosen as [[Academy Award for Best Documentary Feature]] at the [[47th Academy Awards]] presented in 1975.&lt;ref name=&quot;NY Times&quot;&gt;{{cite news |url=http://movies.nytimes.com/movie/21924/Hearts-and-Minds/details |title=NY Times: Hearts and Minds |accessdate=2008-11-15|work=NY Times}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The film premiered at the 1974 [[Cannes Film Festival]]. Commercial distribution was delayed in the United States due to legal issues, including a temporary [[restraining order]] obtained by one of the interviewees, former [[National Security Advisor (United States)|National Security Advisor]] [[Walt Rostow]] who had claimed through his attorney that the film was &quot;somewhat misleading&quot; and &quot;not representative&quot; and that he had not been given the opportunity to approve the results of his interview.&lt;ref name=Dugas&gt;Dugas, David via [[United Press International]]. [http://access.newspaperarchive.com/Viewer.aspx?img=104779837&amp;firstvisit=true&amp;src=search&amp;currentResult=0 &quot;Viet War Film Late, Or Maybe Just in Time&quot;], ''[[Stars and Stripes (newspaper)|Pacific Stars and Stripes]]'' via [[Newspaper Archive]], February 25, 1975. Accessed August 15, 2008.&lt;/ref&gt; [[Columbia Pictures]] refused to distribute the picture and the producers had to purchase back the rights and released it by other means. The film was shown in Los Angeles for the one week it needed to be eligible for consideration in the 1974 Academy Awards.

[[World Movies]], the [[Australia]]n subscription TV channel, included ''Hearts and Minds'' in its 2007 series of ''25 Docs You Must See Before You Die''.&lt;ref&gt;{{citeweb |url=http://www.worldmovies.net/25docs/ |title=25 Docs You Must See Before You Die |publisher=[[World Movies]] |accessdate=January 27, 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Featured individuals==
[[Image:Gen William C Westmoreland.jpg|thumb|right|General [[William Westmoreland]], [[Chief of Staff of the United States Army|United States Army Chief of Staff]]]]
A scene described as one of the film's &quot;most shocking and controversial sequences&quot; shows the funeral of an [[Army of the Republic of Vietnam|ARVN]] soldier and his grieving family, as a sobbing woman is restrained from climbing into the grave after the coffin.&lt;ref&gt;Dittmar, Linda; and Michaud, Gene. [http://books.google.com/books?id=HrYrtkMU_t4C&amp;pg=PA273&amp;lpg=PA273&amp;dq=westmoreland+%22life+is+cheap%22+%22hearts+and+minds%22&amp;source=web&amp;ots=B4O6O8knvX&amp;sig=Xm_H2d3k7muE1mqQMgPNzc53x7w&amp;hl=en&amp;sa=X&amp;oi=book_result&amp;resnum=4&amp;ct=result ''From Hanoi to Hollywood: The Vietnam War in American Film''], [[Rutgers University Press]], 1990
via [[Google Books]], p. 273. ISBN 0813515874.&lt;/ref&gt; The funeral scene is juxtaposed with an interview with General [[William Westmoreland]] — commander of American military operations in the Vietnam War at its peak from 1964 to 1968 and [[Chief of Staff of the United States Army|United States Army Chief of Staff]] from 1968 to 1972 — telling a stunned Davis that &quot;The Oriental doesn't put the same high price on life as does a Westerner. Life is plentiful. Life is cheap in the Orient.&quot; After an initial take, Westmoreland indicated that he had expressed himself inaccurately. After a second take ran out of film, the section was reshot for a third time, and it was the third take that was included in the film.&lt;ref&gt;{{citeweb |author=Jackson, Derrick Z. |url=http://www.iht.com/articles/2005/07/21/opinion/edjackson.php |title=Derrick Z. Jackson: The Westmoreland mind-set&quot; |publisher=''[[International Herald Tribune]]'' |date=July 22, 2005 |accessdate=January 26, 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=WashPost/&gt;  Davis later reflected on this interview stating, &quot;As horrified as I was when General Westmoreland said, 'The Oriental doesn’t put the same value on life,' instead of arguing with him, I just wanted to draw him out... I wanted the subjects to be the focus, not me as filmmaker.&quot;&lt;ref name='KATZ'&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.centerforsocialmedia.org/artists/peter_davis |title=An Interview With Peter Davis |accessdate=2010-04-03 |last=Katz |first=Sarah |date=January, 2008 |publisher=[[Center for Social Media]] }} {{Dead link|date=October 2010|bot=H3llBot}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The film also includes clips of [[George Thomas Coker]], a [[United States Navy]] aviator held by the North Vietnamese as a [[prisoner of war]] for 6½ years, including more than two years spent in solitary confinement.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.pbs.org/wgbh/amex/honor/filmmore/pt.html ''Return With Honor'' Transcript], [[Public Broadcasting Service|PBS]]. Accessed August 11, 2008.&lt;/ref&gt; One of the film's earliest scenes details a homecoming parade in Coker's honor in his hometown of [[Linden, New Jersey]], where he tells the assembled crowd on the steps of city hall that if the need arose, that they must be ready to send him back to war.&lt;ref name=&quot;Anderegg&quot;&gt;{{cite book |last =Anderegg |first = Michael A. |url=http://books.google.com/?id=kGyDjkIbifEC&amp;pg=PA284&amp;lpg=PA284&amp;dq=coker+%22hearts+and+minds%22+linden |title=Inventing Vietnam: The War in Film and Television |publisher=[[Temple University Press]]. |accessdate=2008-01-10 |isbn =9780877228622 |year =1991}}&lt;/ref&gt; Answering a student's question about Vietnam at a school assembly, Coker responds that &quot;If it wasn't for the people, it was very pretty. The people there are very backwards and primitive and they make mess out of everything.&quot;&lt;ref name=WashPost/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;TNYquote&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.newyorker.com/archive/2004/11/01/041101crci_cinema?currentPage=2|title=Aftermaths: Enduring Love, Hearts and Minds|last=Lane|first=Anthony|date=2004-11-01|publisher=The New Yorker|accessdate=2008-07-29}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |first= |last= |authorlink= |coauthors= |title=Terror and trauma. |url=http://film.guardian.co.uk/features/featurepages/0,4120,1644711,00.html |publisher=[[The Guardian]] |date=November 18, 2005 |accessdate=2008-01-27 | location=London}}&lt;/ref&gt; In a 2004 article on the film, [[Desson Thomson]] of ''[[The Washington Post]]'' comments on the inclusion of Coker in the film, noting that &quot;When he does use people from the pro-war side, Davis chooses carefully.&quot;&lt;ref name=WashPost&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.washingtonpost.com/ac2/wp-dyn/A51347-2004Oct21|title='Hearts And Minds' Recaptured |accessdate=2007-12-23|publisher=[[The Washington Post]]|author=[[Desson Thomson]] | date=October 22, 2004}}&lt;/ref&gt; ''[[Time (magazine)|Time]]'' magazine's [[Stefan Kanfer]] noted the lack of balance in Coker's portrayal, &quot;An ex-P.O.W.'s return to New Jersey is played against a background of red-white-and-blue-blooded patriots and wide-eyed schoolchildren. The camera, which amply records the agonies of South Vietnamese political prisoners, seems uninterested in the American lieutenant's experience of humiliation and torture.&quot;&lt;ref name=Time&gt;Kanfer, Stefan. [http://www.time.com/time/magazine/article/0,9171,912958,00.html &quot;War-Torn'], ''[[Time (magazine)]]'',March 17, 1975. Accessed August 11, 2008.&lt;/ref&gt;

The film also features Vietnam war veteran and anti-war activist [[Bobby Muller]], who later founded the [[Vietnam Veterans of America]].&lt;ref name=WashPost/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.washingtonpost.com/ac2/wp-dyn/A32492-2004Oct14 &quot;Scores of Reasons to See These Silent Films&quot;], ''[[The Washington Post]]'', October 15, 2004. Accessed August 6, 2008.&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Daniel Ellsberg]], who had released the ''[[Pentagon Papers]]'' in 1971, discusses his initial gung-ho attitude toward the war in Vietnam.&lt;ref name=canby&gt;[[Vincent Canby|Canby, Vincent]]. [http://movies.nytimes.com/movie/review?res=9C01E0DE103AE03BBC4C51DFB566838E669EDE &quot;'Hearts and Minds,' a Film Study of Power&quot;], ''[[The New York Times]]'', March 24, 1975. Accessed August 6, 2008.&lt;/ref&gt;

The concluding interview features US Vietnam veteran Randy Floyd, stating &quot;We've all tried very hard to escape what we have learned in Vietnam. I think Americans have worked extremely hard not to see the criminality that their officials and their policy makers exhibited.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{citeweb |author=Monaco, James.  |url=http://direct.bl.uk/bld/PlaceOrder.do?UIN=133218452&amp;ETOC=RN&amp;from=searchengine |title=Hearts &amp; Minds |publisher=''[[Cineaste (magazine)]]'' |date=Summer, 2003 |accessdate=November 15, 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The film includes images of [[Phan Thị Kim Phúc]] in sections of a film shot of the aftermath of a napalm attack which shows Phúc at about age nine running naked on the street after being severely burned on her back.&lt;ref name=WashPost/&gt;

==Critical reception==
''Hearts and Minds'' has attracted extensive critical attention, almost all of it either glowingly positive or damningly negative, but rarely anything in between, with reviewers tending to treat it either as a masterpiece in political documentary film making or as a hatchet job anti-Vietnam War propaganda film, one that has received &quot;passionately opposing views&quot;.&lt;ref name=NewSchool/&gt;

Vietnam War films from the 1960s to the 1970s reflected deep divisions at home over the war. Some reflected pro-war sentiments and vilified anti-war protesters, while others stood at the opposite end and criticized government officials and policies. &quot;Hearts and Minds&quot; was one of the first of the latter to have been produced and released before the war's end in 1975.&lt;ref name=&quot;Schulzinger, Robert D. page 155&quot;/&gt; 

[[Vincent Canby]] of ''[[The New York Times]]'' called it an &quot;epic documentary ... [that] recalls this nation's agonizing involvement in Vietnam, something you may think you know all about, including the ending. But you don't.&quot;&lt;ref name=canby/&gt; Canby included the film among his ten best of 1975, calling it a &quot;fine, complex, admittedly biased meditation upon American power&quot; and a movie &quot;that will reveal itself as one of the most all-emcompassing records of the American civilization ever put into one film.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Canby, Vincent. [http://select.nytimes.com/gst/abstract.html?res=F10712F63D5916768FDDA10A94DA415B858BF1D3&amp;scp=1&amp;sq=ten%20best%20films%201975&amp;st=cse &quot;FILM VIEW; The Ten Best Films of 1975&quot;], ''[[The New York Times]]'', December 28, 1975. Accessed August 14, 2008.&lt;/ref&gt; [[Desson Thomson]] of ''[[The Washington Post]]'' described it as &quot;one of the best documentaries ever made, a superb film about the thoughts and feelings of the era, the whole festering, spirited animus of it.&quot;&lt;ref name=WashPost/&gt; [[Rex Reed]] called it that year's &quot;best film at the Cannes Film Festival&quot; and stated that &quot;[t]his is the only film I have ever seen that sweeps away the gauze surrounding Vietnam and tells the truth.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;[[Rex Reed|Reed, Rex]]. [http://access.newspaperarchive.com/Viewer.aspx?img=49687636&amp;firstvisit=true&amp;src=search&amp;currentResult=0 &quot;A film Americans nay not see&quot;], ''[[Long Beach Press-Telegram|Independent Press-Telegram]]'', via [[Newspaper Archive]], August 18, 1974. Accessed August 15, 2008.&lt;/ref&gt;

Other reviewers have criticized the movie for its biased presentation. [[Roger Ebert]] for the ''[[Chicago Sun Times]]'' wrote: &quot;Here is a documentary about Vietnam that doesn't really level with us ... If we know something about how footage is obtained and how editing can make points, it sometimes looks like propaganda ... And yet, in scene after scene, the raw material itself is so devastating that it brushes the tricks aside.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |first= |last= |authorlink= |coauthors= |title=Hearts and Minds  |url=http://rogerebert.suntimes.com/apps/pbcs.dll/article?AID=/19740101/REVIEWS/401010317/1023 |quote= |work=[[Chicago Sun Times]] |date=January 1, 1974 |accessdate=2008-08-11}}&lt;/ref&gt;
Walter Goodman of ''The New York Times'' in an article titled ''False Art of the Propaganda Film'', pointed out Davis' technique of showing only one side of the interview, pointing out that [[Walt Rostow]]'s response may have been in response to &quot;some provocation, a gesture, a facial expression, a turn of phrase&quot; from his interrogator.&lt;ref&gt;Goodman, Walter. [http://select.nytimes.com/gst/abstract.html?res=F30F1EF635581A738DDDAA0A94DB405B858BF1D3&amp;scp=4&amp;sq=%22walt%20rostow%22%20%22hearts%20and%20minds%22&amp;st=cse &quot;The False Art of the Propaganda Film&quot;], ''[[The New York Times]]'', March 23, 1975. Accessed August 14, 2008.&lt;/ref&gt;  To this criticism, actress [[Shirley MacLaine]] responded, &quot;[Mr. Goodman] displays the very deception and distortion that is usually associated with the pejorative meaning of propaganda.  For example, Mr. Goodman starts out by claiming that in most countries, propaganda is a monopoly of the state, but that in the United States the most notable examples of propaganda 'come from the state's adversaries.'  This is ridiculous. In America, the state spends millions of dollars every year on propaganda.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |author=MacLaine, Shirley.  |url=http://select.nytimes.com/gst/abstract.html?res=F10D15FE3A5C107B93C4A9178FD85F418785F9&amp;scp=1&amp;sq=Propaganda%27%20is%20What%20You%20Don%27t%20Agree%20With&amp;st=cse |title='Propaganda' is What You Don't Agree With |publisher=''[[The New York Times]]'' |date=April 6, 1975 |accessdate=November 15, 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt;

David Dugas of [[United Press International]], in a 1975 review printed in ''[[Stars and Stripes (newspaper)|Pacific Stars and Stripes]]'', saw that &quot;Davis' approach clearly is one-sided and is not likely to impress Vietnam hawks. But his film is brilliantly assembled, biting and informative.&quot;&lt;ref name=Dugas/&gt;

Colin Jacobson wrote in his review of the movie for the DVD Movie Guide: &quot;Probably the biggest criticism one can level at [Hearts and Minds] stems from its editorial bent. Without question, it takes the anti-war side of things, and one could argue it goes for a pro-Vietnamese bent as well....In the end, Hearts and Minds remains a flawed film that simply seems too one-sided for its own good.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;DVDmg&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.dvdmg.com/heartsandminds.shtml|title=Hearts and Minds: Criterion (1974)|last=Jacobson|first=Colin|year=1974|publisher=DVD Movie Guide|accessdate=2008-06-24}}&lt;/ref&gt; In his review, David Ng of the online ''Images: A Journal of Film and Popular Culture'' wrote: &quot;The documentary is clearly anti-war in both tone and content.&quot;&lt;ref name=Ng&gt;{{citeweb |author=Ng, David. |url=http://www.imagesjournal.com/2002/reviews/heartsminds/ |title=''Images: A Journal of Film and Popular Culture'' |date=2002. |accessdate=2007-12-22}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[M. Joseph Sobran, Jr.]] of the conservative magazine ''[[National Review]]'', wrote: &quot;... blatant piece of propaganda ... disingenuously one-sided ...&quot; and goes on to show the cinematic techniques used by the producers to achieve this effect.&lt;ref name=&quot;National Review&quot;&gt;{{cite journal|last=Sobran Jr.|first=M. J. |authorlink=Joseph Sobran |date=1975-06-06|title=Heartless and Mindless|journal=[[National Review]] |publisher=via EBSCO|volume=27|issue=21|pages=621|issn=0028-0038|url=http://search.ebscohost.com/login.aspx?direct=true&amp;db=mth&amp;AN=6046063&amp;site=ehost-live|accessdate=2008-06-24}}&lt;/ref&gt; Stefan Kanfer of ''[[Time (magazine)|Time]]'' magazine notes that &quot;Throughout, Hearts and Minds displays more than enough heart. It is mind that is missing. Perhaps the deepest flaw lies in the method: the Viet Nam War is too convoluted, too devious to be examined in a style of compilation without comment.&quot;&lt;ref name=Time/&gt; 

[[Michael Moore]] has cited ''Hearts and Minds'' as the one movie that inspired him to become a film maker, calling it &quot;not only the best documentary I have ever seen, it may be the best movie ever&quot;.&lt;ref name=TheAge&gt;Schwartz, Larry. [http://www.theage.com.au/news/tv--radio/inside-the-body-of-a-war-zone/2007/09/12/1189276775955.html &quot;Inside the body of a war zone&quot;], ''[[The Age]]'', September 13, 2007. Accessed August 11, 2008.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Kennedy, Lisa. [http://nl.newsbank.com/nl-search/we/Archives?p_product=DP&amp;p_theme=dp&amp;p_action=search&amp;p_maxdocs=200&amp;p_topdoc=1&amp;p_text_direct-0=10649BCEDBE15C03&amp;p_field_direct-0=document_id&amp;p_perpage=10&amp;p_sort=YMD_date:D&amp;s_trackval=GooglePM &quot;``Hearts and Minds'' run has new appeal&quot;], ''[[Denver Post]]'', November 9, 2004. Accessed August 11, 2008.&lt;/ref&gt; Many of the cinematic techniques used in ''Hearts and Minds'' are similar to Moore's 2004 documentary ''[[Fahrenheit 9/11]]''.&lt;ref name=&quot;NewSchool&quot;&gt;{{cite journal|last=Wilder|first=Carol|year=2005|title=Separated at Birth: Argument by Irony in Hearts and Minds and Fahrenheit 9/11|journal=Atlantic Journal of Communication|publisher=[[The New School]]|issue=Summer 2005|url=http://homepage.newschool.edu/~wilder/ArgumentbyIrony.html|quote=What can the striking similarities and differences of these pictures tell us about the media environments of their respective times? What do they reveal about the architecture of cinematic argument? About the eternal verities of war rhetoric?| accessdate=2008-06-25}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Academy Award==
After [[Columbia Pictures]] refused to distribute the picture, the producers [[Bert Schneider]] and [[Henry Jaglom]] purchased back the rights and released the film in March 1975 through [[Warner Bros.]] A planned December 18, 1974 opening in [[Los Angeles, California]] was canceled after the production company had been unable to pay the $1 million needed to buy the rights from Columbia Pictures. The film was ultimately shown in Los Angeles for the one week it needed to be eligible for consideration in the 1974 Academy Awards.&lt;ref&gt;[http://select.nytimes.com/gst/abstract.html?res=F30B17F835551A7493CBA81789D95F408785F9 &quot;Documentary on Vietnam Fails to Open; 'Somewhat Misleading&quot;], ''[[The New York Times]]'', December 19, 1974. Accessed August 11, 2008.&lt;/ref&gt;

During his acceptance of the Academy Award ceremonies on April 8, 1975, co-producer [[Bert Schneider]] said, &quot;It's ironic that we're here at a time just before Vietnam is about to be liberated&quot; and then read a telegram containing &quot;Greetings of Friendship to all American People&quot; from Ambassador Dinh Ba Thi of the [[National Front for the Liberation of South Vietnam|Provisional Revolutionary Government (Viet Cong)]] &lt;ref&gt;Biskind, ''Easy Riders, Raging Bulls'', p. 275.&lt;/ref&gt; delegation to the [[Paris Peace Accords]].&lt;ref&gt;Robinson, George. [http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9507EEDE1738F937A35750C0A9679C8B63&amp;sec=&amp;spon=&amp;pagewanted=all Sometimes A Thank You Isn't Enough&quot;], ''[[The New York Times]]'', March 4, 2001. Accessed May 29, 2008.&lt;/ref&gt; The telegram thanked the anti-war movement &quot;for all they have done on behalf of peace&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;Schulzinger, Robert D. page 155&quot;&gt;Schulzinger, Robert D., &quot;A Time for Peace: The Legacy of the Vietnam War&quot;, page 155, Oxford University Press, Oxford &amp; New York, 2006&lt;/ref&gt; [[Frank Sinatra]] responded later by reading a letter from [[Bob Hope]], another presenter on the show, &quot;The academy is saying, 'We are not responsible for any political references made on the program, and we are sorry they had to take place this evening.'&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Efron, Eric. [http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A0DE7DC1439F933A05750C0A9659C8B63 &quot; The World: Acting Out; At the Oscars, a Cause and Effect&quot;], ''[[The New York Times]]'', March 30, 2003. Accessed May 29, 2008.&lt;/ref&gt;

==See also==
*[[Hearts and Minds (Vietnam)]]
*[[This Bloody Blundering Business]]

==References==
{{Reflist|2}}

*[[Peter Biskind]]. ''[[Easy Riders, Raging Bulls|Easy Riders, Raging Bulls: How the Sex-Drugs-and Rock 'N Roll Generation Saved Hollywood]]'', New York: Simon and Schuster, 1998. pp. 178ff., plate x.

==External links==
* [http://vva.org/blog/?p=278 Arts of War on the Web review of DVD and film, April 5, 2009]
* {{imdb title|id=0071604|title=Hearts and Minds}}
* {{Amg movie|21924|Hearts and Minds}}
&lt;!--*[http://www.criterion.com/asp/release.asp?id=156&amp;eid=228&amp;section=essay Criterion Collection essay by Judith Crist]
*[http://www.criterion.com/asp/release.asp?id=156&amp;eid=230&amp;section=essay Criterion Collection essay by George Herring]
*[http://www.criterion.com/asp/release.asp?id=156&amp;eid=231&amp;section=essay Criterion Collection essay by Ngo Vinh Long]
*[http://www.criterion.com/asp/release.asp?id=156&amp;eid=232&amp;section=essay Criterion Collection essay by Robert K. Brigham]--&gt;

{{AcademyAwardBestDocumentaryFeature1961-1980}}

[[Category:1974 films]]
[[Category:American films]]
[[Category:American documentary films]]
[[Category:Documentary films about the Vietnam War]]
[[Category:English-language films]]
[[Category:Films shot in Vietnam]]
[[Category:French-language films]]
[[Category:Best Documentary Feature Academy Award winners]]
[[Category:Documentary films about American politics]]
[[Category:Opposition to the Vietnam War]]
[[Category:Vietnamese-language films]]
[[Category:Anti-war films about the Vietnam War]]
[[Category:1970s documentary films]]

[[pt:Hearts and Minds]]
[[sv:Hearts and Minds]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
