<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="183050" ns="0" title="Viacom"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{About|the post-2005 Viacom|the company known as Viacom prior to 2006 (and was known as [[CBS Corporation]])|Viacom (1971–2005)}}
{{Infobox company
| name              =  Viacom, Inc.
| logo              =  [[File:Viacom logo.svg|200px]]
| caption           =  
| type              =  Public company
| traded_as         = {{NYSE|VIA}} {{NYSE|VIAB}} {{NYSE|VNV}} {{Nasdaq|VIA}}  
| predecessor       =  [[Viacom (1971–2005)]]
| successor         =
| foundation        =  {{Start date|1971}} &lt;small&gt;(Original Viacom founding)&lt;/small&gt; &lt;br /&gt; {{Start date|2005}} &lt;small&gt;(current incarnation, as a result of the CBS/Viacom split)&lt;/small&gt;
| founder           =
| defunct           =
| location_city     =  New York City, New York
| location_country  =  United States
| locations         =
| area_served       =  Worldwide
| key_people        =  [[Sumner Redstone|Sumner M. Redstone]]&lt;br&gt;&lt;small&gt;([[Chairman|Executive Chairman]])&lt;/small&gt; &lt;br /&gt;[[Philippe Dauman|Philippe P. Dauman]]&lt;br&gt;&lt;small&gt;([[President]] and CEO)&lt;/small&gt;
| industry          = [[Media conglomerate]]
| products          =
| services          =
| revenue           =  {{loss}} US$ 9.34&amp;nbsp;billion (2010)&lt;ref name=&quot;ref&quot;&gt;[http://phx.corporate-ir.net/External.File?item=UGFyZW50SUQ9NDEyMDk2fENoaWxkSUQ9NDIyODEzfFR5cGU9MQ==&amp;t=1 Press release: &quot;VIACOM REPORTS FISCAL 2011 FIRST QUARTER RESULTS&quot;] Viacom&lt;/ref&gt;
| operating_income  =  {{profit}} US$ 2.21&amp;nbsp;billion (2010)&lt;ref name=&quot;ref&quot;/&gt;
| net_income        =  {{loss}} 854 million (2010)&lt;ref name=&quot;ref&quot;/&gt;
| aum               =
| assets            =  {{profit}} US$ 22.96&amp;nbsp;billion (2010)&lt;ref name=&quot;ref&quot;/&gt;
| equity            =  {{profit}} US$ 9.258&amp;nbsp;billion (2010)&lt;ref name=&quot;ref&quot;/&gt;
| owner             =
| num_employees     =  10,900 (2010)&lt;ref name=&quot;ref&quot;/&gt;
| parent            =  [[National Amusements]] (~80%)
| divisions         =  [[MTV Networks]] &lt;br /&gt; [[BET Networks]] &lt;br /&gt; [[Paramount Pictures|Paramount Pictures Corporation]]
| subsid            =
| homepage          =  {{URL|viacom.com}}
| footnotes         =
| intl              =
}}

'''Viacom Inc.''' ({{nyse|VIA}}) ({{nyse|VIAb}})({{nyse|VNV}}), short for &quot;'''Vi'''deo &amp; '''A'''udio '''Com'''munications&quot;, is an American [[media conglomerate]] with interests primarily in, but not limited to, cinema and cable television. As of 2010, it is the world's fourth-largest media conglomerate, behind [[The Walt Disney Company]], [[Time Warner]] and [[News Corporation]].&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|url=http://money.cnn.com/magazines/fortune/global500/2009/industries/145/index.html |title=Global 500 2009: Industry |publisher=CNN  |date=July 20, 2009 |accessdate=May 1, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.viacom.com/investorrelations/Investor_Relations_Docs/Q407%20Web%20Deck%20FINAL.pdf |title=2007 Results  |format=PDF |date=February 28, 2008 |accessdate=May 1, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|last=Siklos |first=Richard |url=http://money.cnn.com/2009/02/09/news/companies/disney_dreamworks.fortune/?postversion=2009020914 |title=Why Disney wants DreamWorks |publisher=CNN  |date=February 9, 2009 |accessdate=May 1, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.newscorp.com/Report2007/AnnualReport2007/HTML2/news_corp_ar2007_0069.htm News Corporation – Annual Report 2007]. Newscorp.com (June 30, 2007). Retrieved on July 13, 2011.&lt;/ref&gt;

The current Viacom was created on December 31, 2005 as a spinoff from [[CBS Corporation]], which [[company renaming|changed its name]] from [[Viacom (1971–2005)|Viacom]] to CBS at the same time. CBS, not Viacom, retains control of the over-the-air broadcasting, TV production, outdoor advertising, subscription pay television (Showtime) and publishing assets (Simon &amp; Schuster) formerly owned by the larger company. However, National Amusements, through [[Sumner Redstone]], retains majority control of Viacom. Predecessor firms of CBS Corporation include Gulf + Western, which later became Paramount Communications Inc., and [[Westinghouse Electric (1886)|Westinghouse Electric Corporation]].

Comprising BET Networks, MTV Networks, and Paramount Pictures, Viacom connects with audiences through television, motion pictures, mobile platforms and online in more than 160 countries and territories. Viacom operates approximately 170 media networks reaching more than 600&amp;nbsp;million global subscribers and more than 500 branded digital media properties.&lt;ref name=&quot;ref&quot; /&gt;

==History==
[[File:Viacom-old.svg|thumb|The 1990-2006 logo of Viacom. It was used in tandem with the current logo, especially in the Paramount Pictures logo until 2010.]]

===Early years===
In March 2005, the [[Viacom (1971–2005)|prior Viacom]] announced plans of looking into splitting the company into two publicly traded companies. The company was not only dealing with a stagnating stock price, but also the rivalry between [[Leslie Moonves]] and [[Tom Freston]], longtime heads of [[MTV Networks]].

After the departure of [[Mel Karmazin]] in 2004, [[Sumner Redstone]], who served as Chairman and Chief Executive Officer, decided to split the offices of [[President]] and Chief Operating Officer between Moonves and Freston. Redstone was set to retire in the near future, and a split was seen as a creative solution to the matter of replacing him. It was also intended to provide alternative investments that would be more appealing to different investors – one a high cash flow, lower growth company that could afford to pay a substantial dividend and the other a growing company that would have greater investment opportunities and therefore would not be expected to pay a dividend. {{Citation needed|date=September 2010}}

A new company, the present Viacom, was created and was headed by Freston. It comprises [[BET Networks]], [[MTV Networks]], and [[Paramount Pictures|Paramount Pictures Corporation]].

===2005===
In June, Viacom announced its purchase of [[Neopets]], a virtual pet website, along with GameTrailers, GoCityKids, and IFILM. That December, Paramount announced it would acquire [[DreamWorks]]. All indications are that the whole of DreamWorks—both live-comedy film and TV studios, albeit not the DreamWorks archive—which was sold to a group led by [[George Soros]] in March 2006 (nor the [[DreamWorks Animation|animated unit]], which was not part of the deal) will remain owned by Viacom, even though CBS acquired Paramount's own TV studio.

===2006===
On February 1, Paramount completed its long-awaited acquisition of DreamWorks. On April 24, Viacom obtained [[Xfire]]. In August, just hours before announcing its most recent quarterly earnings, Viacom announced that it had acquired [[Atom Entertainment]] for $200&amp;nbsp;million. In September, Viacom acquired game developer [[Harmonix]] for $175&amp;nbsp;million.

===2007===
In February, Viacom ordered leaked copyrighted video clips be taken off the videosharing service [[YouTube]] for copyright reasons. On February 21, Viacom publicly announced they would be offering free online access to their own material through Silicon Valley's distributor [[Joost]] thanks to a thorough content licensing deal.

On May 21, Viacom entered into a 50–50 joint venture with Indian media company [[Global Broadcast News]] to form [[Viacom-18]] which will house Viacom's existing channels in India: MTV, VH1 and Nick as well as [[Network 18]]'s [[Bollywood]] movie business. All future Viacom content for India and new ventures such as a [[Hindi]] entertainment channel and a [[Hindi]] movie channel would be housed in this joint venture.

On November 8, Viacom announced that MTV Tempo would be sold to founder and Viacom Deputy General Council Frederick Morton, Jr., becoming [[Tempo TV|Tempo Networks]].

On December 19, Viacom signed a five year, $500&amp;nbsp;million contract with [[Microsoft]] that included content sharing and advertisement. The deal allowed Microsoft to license many shows from Viacom owned cable television and film studios for use on [[Xbox Live]] and [[MSN]]. The deal also made Viacom a preferred publisher partner for casual game development and distribution through MSN and [[Microsoft Windows|Windows]]. On the advertisement side of the deal, Microsoft's Atlas ad-serving division became the exclusive provider of previously unsold advertising inventory on Viacom owned web sites. Also, Microsoft purchased a large amount of advertising on Viacom owned broadcasts and online networks. Finally, Microsoft will also collaborate on promotions and sponsorships for MTV and [[Black Entertainment Television|BET]] award shows, two Viacom owned cable networks.

===2008===
On December 4, three weeks before Christmas, Viacom announced layoffs of 850 personnel, or 7% of their workforce.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://gawker.com/5101825/the-dreaded-viacom-layoffs-850-people |title=The Dreaded Viacom Layoffs: 850 People}}&lt;/ref&gt; At the end of the year, [[Time Warner Cable]] (along with partner [[Bright House Networks]]) and Viacom's [[MTV Networks]] could not come to terms for the renewal of any Viacom channel beyond the end of year.&lt;ref&gt;Fixmer, Andy. (2008-12-31) [http://www.bloomberg.com/apps/news?pid=20670001&amp;refer=us&amp;sid=algojFpM7.Ho Viacom May Pull Channels Off Time Warner Cable in Contract Spat]. Bloomberg. Retrieved on 2011-07-13.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web| url=http://www.msnbc.msn.com/id/28440958/ |title=Time Warner may cut ‘Colbert,’ ‘Spongebob’ |publisher=MSNBC}}&lt;/ref&gt; Time Warner Cable's operations include New York City and Los Angeles, with Bright House including the Tampa Bay and Orlando markets, both top-20 markets. This blackout was narrowly avoided when a zero-hour deal was reached shortly after 12 Midnight ET on January 1, 2009.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.latimes.com/business/la-fi-viacom2-2009jan02,0,1305999.story: &quot;Viacom, Time Warner Cable settle contract dispute&quot;], January 1, 2009. ''Los Angeles Times''{{dead link|date=July 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===2009===
On December 7, '''Viacom''' sold its stake in [[MTV Brasil]] for the [[Grupo Abril]] along with rights to the brand. The deal was not announced.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www2.uol.com.br/canalexecutivo/notasemp09/emp081220093.htm|title=Abril compra ações da Viacom na MTV Brasil|date=2009-12-07|accessdate=2010-5-30|language={{pt}}}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===2010===
On May 5, 2010, ''[[The Hollywood Reporter]]'' revealed that Viacom's Comedy Central &quot;is developing a whole animated series around [[Jesus Christ]]&quot; who, according to the network, wants to escape the shadow of his &quot;powerful but apathetic father.&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;[http://livefeed.hollywoodreporter.com/2010/05/comedy-central-developing-jesus-christ-cartoon-series.html &quot;Comedy Central developing Jesus Christ cartoon&quot;], May 5, 2010. ''Hollywood Reporter''. (November 30, 2010). Retrieved on July 13, 2011.&lt;/ref&gt;

===2011===

In February 2011, [[Hulu]] and Viacom announced the return of &quot;The Daily Show with Jon Stewart&quot; and &quot;The Colbert Report&quot; to Hulu, along with shows from the Viacom library. Nickelodeon's shows are not part of this deal.

Also that month, Viacom invested in the [[Rainbow Group]]{{dn|date=September 2011}}.

Later, in October of 2011, Viacom purchased a majority stake in [[Bellator Fighting Championships]]. Spike TV plans to air Bellator in 2013, after the rights to the UFC library ends in 2012.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news| url=http://www.usatoday.com/sports/mma/post/2011-10-26/viacom-buys-bellator-plans-2013-start-on-spike/558003/1 | work=USA Today | title=Updated monthly | date=October 26, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Copyright complaints against YouTube==
{{Main|Viacom International Inc. v. YouTube, Inc.}}
In February 2007, Viacom sent upwards of 100,000 [[Digital Millennium Copyright Act|DMCA]] takedown notices to the video-sharing site YouTube. Of the 100,000 notices, approximately 60–70 non-infringing videos were removed under the auspices of copyright infringement.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.foxnews.com/story/0,2933,252798,00.html Media Companies Blast YouTube for Anti-Piracy Policy]. Foxnews.com (February 19, 2007). Retrieved on July 13, 2011.&lt;/ref&gt;

On March 13, 2007, Viacom filed a US$1&amp;nbsp;billion legal claim ([[Viacom International Inc. v. YouTube, Inc.]]) against [[Google]] and YouTube alleging massive [[copyright infringement]], alleging that users frequently uploaded copyrighted material to YouTube—enough to cause a hit in revenue for Viacom and a gain in advertisement revenue for YouTube.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news| url=http://online.wsj.com/public/resources/documents/ViacomYouTubeComplaint3-12-07.pdf | work=The Wall Street Journal}}&lt;/ref&gt;
The complaint contended that almost 160,000 unauthorized clips of Viacom’s programming were made available on YouTube and that these clips had collectively been viewed more than 1.5&amp;nbsp;billion times. 

In July 2008, the case generated controversy when District Judge [[Louis Stanton]] ruled that YouTube was required to hand over data detailing the viewing habits of every user who had ever watched videos on the site.&lt;ref name=privacy_bbc&gt;{{Cite news | title = Google must divulge YouTube Log | date = July 3, 2008 |publisher=BBC News  | url = http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/technology/7488009.stm}}&lt;/ref&gt;
Judge Stanton rejected Viacom's request for YouTube to hand over the [[source code]] of its [[search engine (computing)|search engine]] system, saying that the code was a [[trade secret]].&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|title=Google Told to Turn Over User Data of YouTube |last=Helft |first=Miguel |newspaper=The New York Times |url=http://www.nytimes.com/2008/07/04/technology/04youtube.html |date=July 4, 2008 |postscript=&lt;!--None--&gt; }}&lt;/ref&gt;
Google and Viacom later agreed to allow Google to anonymize all the data before handing it over to Viacom.
&lt;ref name=privacy_guardian&gt;{{Cite news|title=Google and Viacom reach deal over YouTube user data |last=Sweeney |first=Mark |newspaper=[[The Guardian]]|url=http://www.guardian.co.uk/media/2008/jul/15/googlethemedia.digitalmedia |date=July 15, 2008 |postscript=&lt;!--None--&gt; |location=London}}&lt;/ref&gt;

On June 23, 2010, Judge Stanton ruled in Google's favor in a motion for summary judgment, holding that Google was protected by provisions of the [[Digital Millennium Copyright Act]], notwithstanding evidence of intentional copyright infringement. Viacom announced its intention to appeal the ruling.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news| title = US judge tosses out Viacom copyright suit against YouTube |author=Lefkow, Chris|agency=AFP  | url = http://www.google.com/hostednews/afp/article/ALeqM5h_AfErLSMMGD417l8aR0CYib0aNQ|accessdate= June 24, 2010 | date=June 23, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Viacom International==
{{Main|Viacom International}}
As with the old Viacom, the current company owns Viacom International, which is the formal owner of copyrights associated with Viacom's corporate website and its cable networks. This division now owns the rights to a majority of [[Elvis Presley]] films made for Paramount Pictures, such as ''[[Blue Hawaii]]'' and ''[[King Creole]]''.

It also continues to focus on its own in-house productions made for its various networks (MTV, [[VH1]], [[Nickelodeon (TV channel)|Nickelodeon]], etc.) – these programs include ''[[Dora the Explorer]]'', ''[[Pinky Dinky Doo]]'', ''[[Invader Zim]]'', ''[[The Hills (TV series)|The Hills]]'', ''[[SpongeBob SquarePants]]'',  ''[[Behind the Music]]'', ''[[Big Time Rush]]'' and ''[[iCarly]]''.

==Corporate governance==
The previous board of directors of Viacom were [[George S. Abrams]], [[David Andelman]], [[Joseph A. Califano, Jr.|Joseph Califano, Jr.]], [[William Cohen]], [[Philippe Dauman]], [[Alan Greenberg]], [[Charles Phillips (businessman)|Charles Phillips]], [[Shari Redstone]], [[Sumner Redstone]], [[Frederic Salerno]], William Schwartz, and [[Robert D. Walter]].

Following the Viacom/CBS split, the Viacom board consisted of [[George S. Abrams]], Philippe Dauman, [[Thomas E. Dooley]], [[Ellen V. Futter]], [[Robert Kraft]], Alan Greenberg, Charles Phillips, Sumner Redstone (Chairman), Shari Redstone (non-executive Vice-Chair), Frederic Salerno, and William Schwartz. As of 2010, the Board consists of George Abrams, Philippe Dauman, [[Thomas E. Dooley]], Alan Greenberg, [[Robert Kraft]], [[Blythe McGarvie]], Charles Phillips, Shari E. Redstone, Sumner M. Redstone, Frederic Salerno, and William Schwartz.

==Assets==
{{Main|List of assets owned by Viacom}}
*'''Film production and distribution''': [[Viacom International]], [[Paramount Pictures]], [[MTV Films]], [[Nickelodeon Movies]]
*'''Television networks''': [[Comedy Central]], [[Logo (TV channel)|Logo]], [[Black Entertainment Television|BET]], [[Spike (TV channel)|Spike]], [[TVLand|TV Land]], [[Nick@Nite]], [[Nickelodeon (TV channel)|Nickelodeon]], [[TeenNick]], [[Nick Jr. (TV channel)|Nick Jr.]], [[MTV]], [[VH1]], [[MTV2]], [[Tr3́s]], [[Country Music Television|CMT]], [[Palladia]]
*'''Video gaming''':  [[GameTrailers]], [[Neopets]]
*'''New media''': [[MTV New Media]]

==See also==
{{Portal box|New York City|Companies}}
* [[List of conglomerates]]
* [[Viacom (1971–2005)]]
{{-}}

==References==
{{Reflist}}

==External links==
*{{Official website|http://www.viacom.com/}}
*[http://www.ketupa.net/viacom.htm Ketupa.net – Viacom]
*[http://hoovers.com/viacom/--ID__143020--/free-co-factsheet.xhtml Viacom information] by [[Hoover's]]
*[http://finance.yahoo.com/q/pr?s=VIA-B Viacom profile] by [[Yahoo!]]
*[http://www.viacom.com/pdf/forms4.PDF Split documentation] – [[SEC filing]] on [[Form S-4]] from October 5, 2005 describing the split.

{{Viacom}}
{{CATV America}}

[[Category:Viacom|*]]
[[Category:Viacom subsidiaries]]
[[Category:Companies based in New York City]]
[[Category:Media companies of the United States]]
[[Category:Companies established in 2006]]

[[ast:Viacom]]
[[be:Viacom]]
[[br:Viacom]]
[[ca:Viacom]]
[[cs:Viacom]]
[[cy:Viacom]]
[[de:Viacom]]
[[el:Viacom]]
[[es:Viacom]]
[[fr:Viacom]]
[[ko:바이어컴]]
[[id:Viacom]]
[[it:Viacom]]
[[he:ויאקום]]
[[ms:Viacom]]
[[nl:Viacom]]
[[ja:バイアコム]]
[[no:Viacom]]
[[pl:Viacom]]
[[pt:Viacom]]
[[ro:Viacom]]
[[ru:Viacom]]
[[sah:Viacom]]
[[sq:Viacom]]
[[simple:Viacom]]
[[sk:Viacom (od 2006)]]
[[fi:Viacom]]
[[sv:Viacom]]
[[tr:Viacom]]
[[vi:Viacom]]
[[zh:維亞康姆]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
