<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="183051" ns="0" title="Sumner Redstone"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Infobox person
| name        = Sumner Redstone
| image       =
| birth_name  = Sumner Murray Rothstein
| birth_date  = {{birth date and age|1923|5|27}}
| birth_place = [[Boston]], [[Massachusetts]], [[United States|USA]]
| death_date  =
| death_place =
| occupation  =  [[Chairman]] of [[National Amusements]]
                 
| networth    = {{loss}} {{US$|3.8 [[1,000,000,000 (number)|billion]]|link=yes}} &lt;small&gt;(2011)&lt;/small&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.forbes.com/profile/sumner-redstone Sumner Redstone - Forbes] Forbes.com. Retrieved March 2011.&lt;/ref&gt;
| spouse      = Phyllis Gloria Raphael (1944–1999)&lt;br/&gt;Paula Fortunato (2002–2009)
| children    = [[Shari Redstone]], [[Brent Redstone]]
| Religion    = [[Judaism]]
| website     =
}}
'''Sumner Murray Redstone''' (born '''Sumner Murray Rothstein'''; May 27, 1923) is an American [[Business magnate|media magnate]]. He is the [[majority owner]] and [[Chairman|Chairman of the Board]] of the [[National Amusements]] theater chain.  Through National Amusements, Sumner Redstone and his family are majority owners of [[CBS Corporation]], [[Viacom]], [[MTV Networks]], [[Black Entertainment Television|BET]], and the film studio [[Paramount Pictures]], and are equal partners in [[MovieTickets.com]].

==Early life and career==
Sumner was born in [[Boston, Massachusetts]] to Belle ([[married and maiden names|née]] Ostrovsky) and [[Michael Redstone|Michael Rothstein]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.filmreference.com/film/89/Sumner-Redstone.html Sumner Redstone Biography (1923-)&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt; His family's name was changed from the [[Jewish surname]] Rothstein to Redstone when Sumner was 17.  His father was the owner of the Northeast Theater Corporation in [[Dedham, Massachusetts]] – the forerunner of [[National Amusements]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9907E0D61738F935A35757C0A9659C8B63 Weddings/Celebrations: Paula Fortunato, Sumner M. Redstone], [[The New York Times]], April 6, 2003&lt;/ref&gt; He also owned the Boston branch of the [[Latin Quarter (nightclub)|Latin Quarter Nightclub]].&lt;ref&gt;http://www.highbeam.com/doc/1P2-8005517.html&lt;/ref&gt;

Redstone attended the [[Boston Latin School]], where he graduated first in his class.  He then attended [[Harvard College]], where he completed his B.A. in three years. Later, Redstone served in [[World War II]], with a team that decoded [[Japan]]ese messages for the [[United States Army]].&lt;ref&gt;Cf. &quot;The Highwaymen&quot; by Ken Auletta. Auletta also wrote that Redstone finished his Harvard undergraduate degree in two and a half years.&lt;/ref&gt; Upon completion of his Army service, he worked in [[Washington, D.C.]] and attended [[Georgetown University Law School]]. He transferred to [[Harvard Law School]] and received his [[LL.B.]], later amended to a [[Juris Doctor]], from that institution.

After completing law school, Redstone worked for the [[United States Department of Justice Tax Division]] in Washington, D.C. and San Francisco, and then went into private practice. After a few years in practice, he joined his father's theater chain.

As [[National Amusements]] grew, Redstone believed that content would become more important than distribution mechanisms. There would always exist channels of distribution (albeit in varied forms), but content was always going to be necessary (he coined the phrase &quot;content is king!&quot;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.bu.edu/phpbin/buniverse/videos/view/?dept=&amp;id=128] A Conversation with Sumner Redstone&lt;/ref&gt;). He then made [[investment]]s in [[Columbia Pictures]], [[20th Century Fox|Twentieth Century Fox]], [[Orion Pictures Corporation|Orion Pictures]], and [[Paramount Pictures]] (the latter of the four of which Redstone's Viacom would buy in the 1990s-see below), all of which turned over huge profits when he chose to sell the [[stock]] in the early 1980s.

In 1979, he suffered severe burns in a fire at the [[Copley Plaza]] hotel, in Boston, but survived after extensive surgery at [[Massachusetts General Hospital]].&lt;ref&gt;Fabrikant, Geraldine, &quot;[http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B0DE7DB103BF936A25750C0A961948260&amp;sec=&amp;spon=&amp;partner=permalink&amp;exprod=permalink His Toughest Challenge Yet]&quot;, ''New York Times'', March 15, 1987&lt;/ref&gt;

==Viacom==
Looking for a new business venture, he set his sights on [[Viacom|Viacom International]], a company which he had already been buying stock in as an investment and was a spin-off of [[CBS]] in 1971 after the [[Federal Communications Commission|FCC]] ruled that [[television network]]s could not [[Television syndication|syndicate]] programs they produced. Viacom syndicated most of CBS's programs, but also made a lot of money from syndicating other programs, including most of [[Carsey-Werner Productions]]' shows (''[[The Cosby Show]]'', ''[[Roseanne (TV series)|Roseanne]]'', and ''[[A Different World (TV series)|A Different World]]''), as well as syndicating shows for other companies ([[Columbia Pictures Television]]'s ''[[All in the Family]]'' was one notable example), and cable channels ([[Nickelodeon (TV channel)|Nickelodeon]]'s ''[[Double Dare (1986 game show)|Double Dare]]'' and ''[[Finders Keepers (1987 TV series)|Finders Keepers]]'' (co-syndicated with [[20th Television]]) were two examples).

Viacom also owned [[MTV Networks]] (formerly known as Warner-AMEX Satellite Entertainment), which owned [[MTV]] and [[Nickelodeon (TV channel)|Nickelodeon]]. In addition, other included properties included Showtime Networks (a similar pay-television network to [[HBO]] and [[Cinemax]]) and [[The Movie Channel]]. Viacom acquired MTV Networks in 1985 for $550 million from [[Steve Ross (Time Warner CEO)|Steve Ross]]' [[Warner Communications]]. (WCI bought American Express' share and then sold the entire entity to Viacom, as they felt that they could not make a lot of money from the venture and the bias of a studio owning cable channels would be a conflict of interest. The studio's stance changed in 1995, when as [[Time Warner]] it bought [[Turner Broadcasting]].)

After a [[hostile takeover]] in 1987,&lt;ref&gt;[http://articles.latimes.com/1987-03-05/business/fi-7618_1_takeover-battle]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://articles.latimes.com/1996-01-18/business/fi-25989_1_frank-biondi?pg=2]&lt;/ref&gt; Redstone won voting control of Viacom and led a series of acquisitions to make Viacom one of the top players in modern media (along with [[Bertelsmann]], [[General Electric]] &amp; [[Vivendi]]'s [[NBC Universal]], [[News Corporation]], [[Time Warner]], [[Sony]], and [[The Walt Disney Company|Disney]]).

==Paramount Pictures==
Redstone's next acquisition came in the form of the purchase of Paramount Communications (previously [[Gulf+Western]]), parent of [[Paramount Pictures]], in 1993, which he fought over with [[Barry Diller]] (former board member of Vivendi Universal and CEO of [[IAC/InterActiveCorp]]) and [[John Malone]] (president of [[TCI]]/[[Liberty Media]]), where he had to raise his bid three times. Some say that Redstone overpaid, but after he shed certain assets (the [[Madison Square Garden]] properties (which included the NBA's NY Knicks and the NHL's NY Rangers)to [[Charles Dolan]]'s [[Cablevision]] and [[Simon &amp; Schuster]]'s educational publishing units to [[Pearson plc]] for almost $4 billion), Redstone turned Viacom's expenditure into a substantial profit. Under Redstone's leadership, Paramount went on an almost ten-year streak of record performance, producing such films as ''[[Saving Private Ryan]]'', ''[[Titanic (1997 film)|Titanic]]'' (one of the highest grossing film of all time and Best Picture Academy Award winner),&lt;ref&gt;http://www.boxofficemojo.com/movies/?id=titanic.htm&lt;/ref&gt; ''[[Braveheart]]'' (Best Picture Academy Award),&lt;ref&gt;http://www.boxofficemojo.com/oscar/movies/?id=braveheart.htm&lt;/ref&gt; and ''[[Forrest Gump]]'' (also a Best Picture winner)&lt;ref&gt;http://www.boxofficemojo.com/oscar/movies/?id=forrestgump.htm&lt;/ref&gt; and the creation of the hugely successful ''[[Mission: Impossible (film series)|Mission: Impossible]]''&lt;ref&gt;http://www.boxofficemojo.com/movies/?id=missionimpossible.htm&lt;/ref&gt; series of pictures.

Redstone replaced the team of Jonathan Dolgen and [[Sherry Lansing]] in 2004 after their nine-year winning streak ended.&lt;ref&gt;http://articles.latimes.com/2004/nov/02/business/fi-paramount2&lt;/ref&gt; Along with the strong slate of films they oversaw, Dolgen and Lansing’s accomplishments included: doubling the size of Paramount's music publishing division, Famous Music; expanding UCI Cinemas into 13 foreign countries; creating the Digital Cinema Initiatives standards body for the new digital film technology; introducing the DVD; and launching the UPN Network (later part of CBS and now called the CW). The current Paramount Pictures consists only of the movie studio, the other groups having been sold or parceled out to other divisions.

Since arriving at Paramount in 2005, Chairman and Chief Executive Officer Brad Grey has led a return to fortune at the box office.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.nytimes.com/2009/12/14/business/media/14paramount.html?pagewanted=1&amp;ref=bradgrey]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://boxofficemojo.com/studio/]&lt;/ref&gt;  He has overseen the creation or revitalization of several major franchises, including &quot;Transformers,&quot; &quot;Star Trek&quot; and &quot;Paranormal Activity.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;http://www.nypost.com/p/news/business/viacom_vision_aOcL8ogsg4gDuFrabNJU3O&lt;/ref&gt; Paramount has also forged productive relationships with top-tier filmmakers and talent including J.J. Abrams,&lt;ref&gt;http://www.variety.com/article/VR1118001694?refCatId=1236&lt;/ref&gt; Michael Bay&lt;ref&gt;http://weblogs.variety.com/bfdealmemo/2009/10/bay-brings-genre-label-to-paramount.html&lt;/ref&gt; and Martin Scorsese&lt;ref&gt;http://www.nytimes.com/2006/11/08/business/media/08films.html?_r=1&amp;scp=1&amp;sq=martin%20scorsese%20and%20paramount&amp;st=cse&lt;/ref&gt;). The 2010 Paramount slate achieved much success with ''[[Shutter Island (film)|Shutter Island]]'' and a ''[[True Grit (2010 film)|True Grit]]'' remake, reaching the biggest box office totals in the storied careers of Martin Scorsese and the Coen Brothers, respectively.&lt;ref&gt;http://boxofficemojo.com/news/?id=2783&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;http://www.cinemovie.tv/cinemovie_new/interviews/72-celebrity-interviews-movies-new-box-office-articles/1133-true-grit-joel-ethan-coen-film-history&lt;/ref&gt; In addition, during Grey’s tenure, Paramount launched its own worldwide releasing arm, Paramount Pictures International, and has released acclaimed films such as ''[[An Inconvenient Truth]]'', ''[[Up in the Air (film)|Up in the Air]]'', and ''[[There Will Be Blood]]''.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.prnewswire.co.uk/cgi/news/release?id=152949&lt;/ref&gt;

The Paramount acquisition was only the tip of the iceberg.  He purchased [[Blockbuster Entertainment]], which included [[Aaron Spelling]]'s production company and a huge library of films, much of which has been merged into Paramount Pictures. Blockbuster has now been spun off into its own independent entity. Redstone acquired CBS Corporation in 2000 and then spun it off as a separate company in 2005, taking with it all of Paramount's television shows and catalog. Following the CBS and Blockbuster Spinoffs, Viacom consists of MTV Networks (MTV, Nickelodeon, VH1, Noggin etc.), music publishing (Famous Music) and Paramount Pictures.

In December 2005, Redstone announced that Paramount had agreed to buy [[DreamWorks SKG]] for an estimated $1.6 billion. The acquisition was completed on February 1, 2006. A subsequent financing brought Viacom's investment down to $700 million. The animation studio, [[DreamWorks Animation]], was not included in the deal as it has been its own company since late 2004.  However, Paramount now has the rights to distribute films by DreamWorks Animation.

==CBS==
One of Redstone's largest acquisitions came in the form of Viacom's former parent, CBS. Former Viacom President &amp; COO [[Mel Karmazin]] (who was then the President of CBS) proposed a merger to Redstone on favorable terms and after the merger completed in 2000, Viacom had some of the most diversified businesses imaginable. Viacom had assets in the form of broadcast networks (CBS and [[UPN]]), [[cable television]] networks ([[MTV]], [[VH1]], [[Nickelodeon (TV network)|Nickelodeon]], [[MTV2]], [[Comedy Central]], [[Black Entertainment Television|BET]], [[Nick at Nite]], [[Noggin (TV channel)|Noggin]]/[[The N]], [[TV Land]], [[Country Music Television|CMT]], and [[Spike TV]]), [[pay television]] ([[Showtime (TV network)|Showtime]] and [[The Movie Channel]]), [[Radio programming|radio]] ([[Infinity Broadcasting]], which produced the immensely popular [[Howard Stern]]' [[Talk radio|radio show]]s), [[outdoor advertising]],  motion pictures ([[Paramount Pictures]]), and [[television production]] ([[Spelling Entertainment]], [[Paramount Television]], and [[Big Ticket Entertainment]]), and [[King World Productions]] (a syndication unit, which notably syndicates the runaway daytime hit, ''[[The Oprah Winfrey Show]]'', as well as ''[[Dr. Phil (TV series)|Dr. Phil]]'', ''[[Wheel of Fortune (American game show)|Wheel of Fortune]]'', and ''[[Jeopardy!]]''), among others.

After CBS and Viacom split in late 2005, Redstone remained chairman of both companies.

==Succession==
Redstone's trusts make it clear that his daughter, [[Shari Redstone]] (Vice-Chairwoman of the Board of Viacom and CBS as well as President of National Amusements), is set to assume his role upon his death.  However, a November 22, 2006, ''[[New York Times]]'' article indicated that Redstone was reconsidering his daughter's role.  Recently they have been feuding publicly over issues of corporate governance and the future of the cinema chain.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.boston.com/business/globe/articles/2007/09/19/redstone_says_he_relies_on_his_instinct/ Redstone says he relies on his instinct - The Boston Globe&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt; There have also been numerous articles stating that Sumner's marriage is in trouble.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.deadlinehollywooddaily.com/redstone-family-woes-now-his-marriage/ Nikki Finke’s Deadline Hollywood Daily » Redstone Family Woes: Now His Marriage&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.laobserved.com/biz/2007/08/redstone_marriage_in.php LA Biz Observed: Redstone marriage in trouble?&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;

Documents have recently been made public which verify that, as part of a settlement from Sumner's first divorce, all of Sumner's stock is in [[Trust Law|irrevocable trusts]] that will be left for his grandchildren.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.latimes.com/entertainment/news/business/la-fi-shari1oct01,1,4236064.story?coll=la-headlines-business-enter Redstone family rift may not be healed - Los Angeles Times&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt; On March 1, 2010, Sumner publicly announced that all of his stock will be left for his grandchildren.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.cnbc.com/id/15840232?video=1428207331&amp;play=1]&lt;/ref&gt;

Redstone made arrangements to step down as CEO of Viacom in 2006.  After Mel Karmazin resigned in 2004, two heirs apparent were named: Co-President &amp; Co-COO [[Leslie Moonves]] (who was #2 to Karmazin at CBS; he was the former head of [[Warner Bros. Television]] and before that, [[Lorimar Television]]) and Co-President &amp; Co-COO [[Tom Freston]] (who had been President &amp; CEO of MTV Networks since 1987 and had been with the company since the formation of MTV Networks' precursor company, Warner-AMEX Satellite Entertainment). Since the Viacom split, Moonves has headed CBS, and Freston had headed the new Viacom, Inc.

When Moonves was promoted to Co-President &amp; Co-COO with Tom Freston, there was speculation that he was on the short list of executives to replace [[Michael Eisner]] at the [[Walt Disney Company]] whose contract expired in 2006.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.bloomberg.com/apps/news?pid=10000103&amp;sid=ahBw0yOHsTgE&amp;refer=us Bloomberg.com: U.S&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt; Redstone has confirmed publicly in ''[[Vanity Fair (magazine)|Vanity Fair]]'' that he originally offered the position only to Freston who initially turned it down and later relented when Redstone made it clear he was going to ask Moonves next.

On September 5, 2006, Redstone removed [[Tom Freston]] as President and CEO of [[Viacom]] and replaced him with director and former Viacom counsel [[Philippe Dauman]].  He also brought back former CFO Tom Dooley.  This was surprising to many, as Freston had been seen by many as Redstone's heir apparent and that Redstone touted that Freston would run the company after he retired.  Redstone publicly stated that he let Freston go because of Viacom's lack of aggressiveness in the digital/online arena, lack of contact with investors, and a lackluster upfront (coupled with falling viewership) at [[MTV Networks]].&lt;ref&gt;http://www.viacom.com/press.tin?ixPressRelease=80704186 Press Release&lt;/ref&gt;

The company split was approved by the Viacom board on June 14, 2005.

==Holdings==
{{BLP sources|date=October 2010|section}}
Currently{{when|date=November 2010}}, Redstone owns over seventy percent of the [[voting stock]] of Viacom, which, in actuality, is a not wholly owned subsidiary of [[National Amusements]], which is his privately held, family-owned company. CBS Corporation, likewise, is controlled by Redstone through National Amusements. Redstone sold his holdings of [[Midway Games]], of over eighty-nine percent, in December 2008.

==Personal==

In 1999 Redstone was divorced from his first wife of 55 years, Phyllis Gloria Raphael. He is the father of [[Shari Redstone]] and [[Brent Redstone]].  Three years after his divorce, he married Paula Fortunato, a former primary school teacher who is 39 years his junior. Sumner Redstone filed for divorce from Paula on Friday, October 17, 2008.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.tmz.com/2008/10/21/sumner-redstone-pulls-trigger-on-marriage/]&lt;/ref&gt; Their divorce was finalized on January 22, 2009.

Redstone owns a house in the [[Beverly Park]] area of [[Beverly Hills, California]], which he purchased in 2002 for $14,500,000.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.bergproperties.com/blog/76m-mansion-goes-on-the-market-near-san-diego-just-after-vanna-whites-ex-puts-a-beverly-hills-ca-estate-on-the-block-for-50m]&lt;/ref&gt;

In July 2010, Redstone was caught on tape, trying to find the source of an apparently embarrassing leak within his own MTV. Redstone offered money and protection to a journalist if he would give up his source. Apparently Mr. Redstone had been pushing MTV management to give more airtime to a girl band called the [[Electric Barbarellas]]. 'On the message, Redstone tells the reporter that &quot;we're not going to kill&quot; the source, adding: &quot;We just want to talk to him.&quot; The 87-year-old Redstone also tells the reporter he will be &quot;well rewarded and well protected&quot; if he gives up the source.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.thedailybeast.com/blogs-and-stories/2010-07-20/sumner-redstone-tries-to-get-peter-lauria-to-tell-him-the-electric-barbarellas-leak/]&lt;/ref&gt; Lauria told NBC's &quot;Today&quot; show Wednesday he wouldn't do it. Viacom Inc. spokesman Carl Folta confirmed to &quot;Today&quot; that it was Redstone's voice on the message and said the mogul had made a mistake.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.mail.com/intl/Article.aspx/entertainment/0/APNews/General-Entertainment/20100721/U_US-Redstone-Source?pageid=1]&lt;/ref&gt; A Viacom source tells the Post today, &quot;Sumner wants to be consequential. Sumner is really proud of what he did. This guy is loving it ... He likes people to know he's still alive.&quot;
&lt;ref&gt;[http://nymag.com/daily/entertainment/2010/07/sumner_redstone_delighted_to_b.html]&lt;/ref&gt;

==Books==
Redstone's autobiography, ''A Passion To Win''&lt;ref&gt;[http://books.simonandschuster.com/Passion-to-Win/Sumner-Redstone/9780684862248 ''A Passion to Win'' by Sumner Redstone with Peter Knobler (2001)]&lt;/ref&gt; (co-written with author [[Peter Knobler]]), was published in 2001 by Viacom's [[Simon &amp; Schuster]]. This book details everything from Redstone's life as a young boy in Boston to the difficult takeover of Viacom and the problems he overcame in purchasing and managing both Blockbuster Video and Paramount Pictures. The book also recounts the legendary CBS merger (Viacom was a spin-off company of CBS to syndicate its programs, and the subsidiary bought the parent almost 30 years later).

Viacom's broadcasting properties at the time of ''A Passion To Win'''s release included several radio stations and two TV stations: [[WBZ-TV|WBZ CBS 4]], which had just become a CBS O&amp;O through a merger with Westinghouse four years before Viacom and CBS merged, and [[WSBK-TV|WSBK UPN 38]] in Redstone's hometown, Boston.

==Net worth==
In 2007 he was ranked #86 on [[Forbes|Forbes magazine]]'s list of the hundred richest people in the world, with an estimated worth of [[US dollar|US$]] 9 [[1000000000 (number)|billion]]. The declining stock market of late 2008 impacted his wealth. Recently, with the partial recovery of the stock market, Sumner Redstone's net worth is again on the rise.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.marketwatch.com/investing/multi?tickers=via,via.b,cbs,cbs.a&lt;/ref&gt; In March 2011, Forbes estimated Sumner's net worth to be 3.8 billion dollars.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.forbes.com/profile/sumner-redstone&lt;/ref&gt;

==Political views==
While claiming to be a [[Democratic Party (United States)|Democratic]] supporter, and having a history of donating to many Democratic campaigns, including regular donations to the late [[Ted Kennedy]], [[John Kerry]], and former [[Party leaders of the United States Senate|Senate Majority Leader]] [[Tom Daschle]],&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.newsmeat.com/billionaire_political_donations/Sumner_Redstone.php]&lt;/ref&gt; he endorsed [[Republican Party (United States)|Republican]] [[George W. Bush]] over Kerry in the [[United States presidential election, 2004|2004 Presidential election]], allegedly because he argued that Bush would be better for his company and the economy.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.opinionjournal.com/extra/?id=110005669 Redstone supports Bush-WSJ&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]{{Dead link|date=December 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; Despite this public endorsement, he donated money to John F Kerry during the primaries.

==Philanthropy==
In April 2007, Sumner M. Redstone announced a commitment of $105 million in charitable grants to fund research and patient care advancements in cancer and burn recovery at three major non-profit healthcare organizations. The cash contributions of $35 million each will be paid out over five years to FasterCures/The Center for Accelerating Medical Solutions, based in Washington D.C.; the Cedars-Sinai Prostate Cancer Center in Los Angeles, California; and the [[Massachusetts General Hospital]] in [[Boston]], [[Massachusetts]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.medicalnewstoday.com/articles/68549.php Sumner M. Redstone Commits $105 Million To Fund Cancer And Burn Recovery Research And Patient Care&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt; 

Sumner is a philanthropist.  He recently contributed $500,000 (the largest donation the charity could accept) to the Cambodian Children's Fund, a nonprofit program that provides a wide range of critical health and educational services to impoverished and abused children in the capital city of [[Phnom Penh]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.variety.com/article/VR1117966201.html?categoryid=18&amp;cs=1&amp;query=Redstone Redstone to help Cambodian kids - Entertainment News, Business News, Media - Variety&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt; Redstone's contribution will be used to create the Sumner M. Redstone Child Rescue Center, a stand-alone facility scheduled to open during the fall of 2007 for children 5 to 16.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.variety.com/article/VR1117966201.html?categoryid=1236&amp;cs=1 Redstone to help Cambodian kids - Entertainment News, Los Angeles, Media - Variety&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;

In early 2010, Autism Speaks announced that Sumner Redstone made a $1 million donation to be applied to scientific research into autism's causes, improved treatments, and, ultimately, its cures. Part of the gift will support Autism Speaks' programs for children, adults and families. While Redstone has supported Autism Speaks since 2007, this is his largest gift to date.

In July 2010, Redstone donated $24 million to the [[Keck School of Medicine]] of the [[University of Southern California]] to support cancer research.&lt;ref&gt;[http://uscnews.usc.edu/health/keck_school_receives_24_million_gift.html?view=full Keck School Receives $24 Million Gift]&lt;/ref&gt;

==References==
{{reflist|2}}

==Further reading==
*Auletta, Ken, &quot;The Highwaymen&quot;, Harvest Books, 1998. ISBN 0-15-600573-5
*[http://www.nypost.com/seven/09072006/business/sumners_fall__frestons_firing_costs_him_113m_business_tim_arango.htm &quot;Sumner's Fall: Freston's Firing Costs Him $113M&quot;] by Tim Arango, [[New York Post]], September 7, 2006.

{{Viacom}}
{{CBS}}

==External links==
{{Portal|Biography}}
*[http://www.viacom.com/sumner.tin Biography from Viacom]
*[http://www.forbes.com/static/bill2005/LIRKJHY.html?passListId=10&amp;passYear=2004&amp;passListType=Person&amp;uniqueId=KJHY&amp;datatype=Person Forbes.com: Forbes World's Richest People]

===Photos===
*[http://images.forbes.com/media/peopletracker/241/240682_TS.jpg Sumner Redstone image at Forbes magazine people tracker]
*[http://www.surferess.com/CEO/assets/images/apviacom-SumnerRedstone.jpg Sumner Redstone image at CEO Central]

{{Persondata
| NAME              =Redstone, Sumner
| ALTERNATIVE NAMES =
| SHORT DESCRIPTION =
| DATE OF BIRTH     =May 27, 1923
| PLACE OF BIRTH    =[[Boston, Massachusetts]], USA
| DATE OF DEATH     =
| PLACE OF DEATH    =
}}
{{DEFAULTSORT:Redstone, Sumner}}
[[Category:1923 births]]
[[Category:Living people]]
[[Category:American billionaires]]
[[Category:American Jews]]
[[Category:American entertainment industry businesspeople]]
[[Category:American mass media owners]]
[[Category:American media executives]]
[[Category:American military personnel of World War II]]
[[Category:Boston Latin School alumni]]
[[Category:Businesspeople from Massachusetts]]
[[Category:Harvard Law School alumni]]
[[Category:Georgetown University Law Center alumni]]
[[Category:Keck School of Medicine of USC people]]
[[Category:People from Boston, Massachusetts]]
[[Category:Viacom]]

[[de:Sumner Redstone]]
[[fr:Sumner Redstone]]
[[nl:Sumner Redstone]]
[[fi:Sumner Redstone]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
