<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="183221" ns="0" title="Ideology of Tintin"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{unencyclopedic|date=June 2008}}
&lt;!--&lt;nowiki&gt;
See http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Wikipedia:Footnotes for an explanation of how to generate footnotes using the &lt;ref&gt; and &lt;/ref&gt; tags, and the template below.
&lt;/nowiki&gt;--&gt;
{{reflist}}

[[Hergé]] started drawing his comics series ''[[The Adventures of Tintin]]'' in 1929 for ''[[Le Petit Vingtième]]'', the children's section of the [[Belgium|Belgian]] newspaper ''Le Vingtième Siècle'', run by the Abbé [[Norbert Wallez]], an avid supporter of social [[Roman Catholic Church|Catholicism]], a right-wing movement. During [[World War II]], Tintin appeared in the [[Brussels]] daily pro-[[Nazi Germany|German]] ''[[Le Soir]]''; after the war he appeared in his own magazine, ''[[Tintin (magazine)|Tintin]]'' (founded by a member of the [[Resistance during World War II|Resistance]], Raymond Leblanc) until Hergé's death in 1983.

As a young artist Hergé was influenced by his mentors, specifically the Abbé Wallez, who encouraged Hergé to use Tintin as a tool for Catholic propaganda to influence Belgian children. This shows in his earlier works within the Tintin series. As a result, European stereotypes pervade Hergé's early catalogue. A breakthrough came in 1934,  when the cartoonist was introduced to [[Zhang Chongren]], a Chinese student, who explained Chinese politics, culture, language, art, and philosophy to him, which Hergé used to great effect in ''[[The Blue Lotus]]''. From this point onward, the artist developed ideologically, amidst the collapse of his country and the Second World War, and so did the series: the general trend of the postwar stories is to become more progressive and universalist. Though, the very last frame of the last completed adventure suggests a cynical view that the poor will suffer, no matter who rules the state. (See [[#Post-war|Post-war]] section below.)

== First albums ==
The first Tintin book, ''[[Tintin in the Land of the Soviets]]'', was crafted on the orders of Hergé's superiors, to be anti-[[Soviet Union|Soviet]] propaganda of limited outlook. Nonetheless, Hergé worked willingly: &quot;I was sincerely convinced of being on the right path&quot;, he said later.  His only source was ''Moscou sans voiles'' (&quot;Moscow without veils&quot;), a book written in 1928 by [[Joseph Douillet]], former [[consul]] of [[Belgium]] in the [[USSR]]. In this book, appearing not much more than a decade after the [[October Revolution]], Douillet denounced the communist system for producing [[poverty]], [[famine]], and [[state terrorism|terror]]. The secret police maintained order and the [[propaganda]] deceived foreigners. Nonetheless, the anti-totalitarian theme of this first book would persist throughout the series.

Hergé wanted the second book to take place in the [[United States]], which fascinated him. Wallez disagreed: he distrusted the USA, the country of [[protestantism]], [[liberalism]], of easy money, and of gangsters. Instead, he asked Hergé to draw a book about the [[Belgian Congo]]: the colony needed white workers at the time.&lt;ref&gt;Benoît Peeters, &lt;i&gt;Tintin and the World of Hergé&lt;/i&gt;, 1988, p. 29-30&lt;/ref&gt;

''[[Tintin in the Congo]]'' reflected the dominant [[colonialist]] ideology at that time.  As put by Hergé in a later interview, &quot;This was in 1930.  All I knew about the Congo was what people were saying about it at the time: 'The Negroes are big children, it's fortunate for them that we're there, etc'&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;Numa Sadoul, &lt;i&gt;Entretiens avec Hergé&lt;/i&gt;, Casterman, 1989, p. 74&lt;/ref&gt;

Later, for the 1946 color edition of the book, Hergé toned down or removed some of the worst excesses: for instance, the Belgian history class given by Tintin to black students was changed into a mathematics class.{{Citation needed|date= October 2011}}

The paternalistic description of the indigenous people of Belgian Congo was more naive than racist, and Hergé developed an important theme of Tintin in this book: international trafficking.&lt;ref&gt;Benoît Peeters, &lt;i&gt;Tintin and the World of Hergé&lt;/i&gt;, 1988, p. 31&lt;/ref&gt;

==Turn-around from ''Tintin in America'' (1931–1932) to ''The Black Island'' (1937–1938)==
At last, with his next book, Hergé could send Tintin to the United States. ''Tintin in America'' (1932) represents a significant change in tone.  Of course, this story was, like the previous ones, very caricatured, because of Hergé's limited knowledge of the country: America was the land of [[Al Capone]], [[cowboys]], [[gigantism]]... But Hergé also took the defense of the [[American Indians in the United States|American Indians]], blacks and blue-collar workers.  He criticized lynching, the theft of Indian lands, and American business rapacity.

Even more striking is the fifth book, ''[[The Blue Lotus]]'' (1934–1935), set in China.  For this story Hergé was put in touch with [[Zhang Chongren]], a Chinese student then studying in Brussels, whose name may have been the basis for the name of character Chang Chong-Chen. Hergé was very concerned with portraying the country accurately, and the adventure can be read as anti-[[imperialism|imperialist]].  It criticizes [[Japan]]ese and [[Western world|Western]] involvement in [[China]], including the international concessions and the Japanese invasion of [[Manchuria]], and shows with great disapproval Westerners making [[racist]] or ignorant remarks about the Chinese. The Japanese themselves are portrayed with little sympathy; most of those shown are soldiers or government agents involved in the invasion of Manchuria.

''[[The Broken Ear]]'' (1935–1936) is set mainly in the fictional South American republic of [[San Theodoros]] and takes a critical view of western businessmen conspiring to provoke a war over what they think will be profitable oil fields.  They go about this using [[bribery]], [[Political corruption|corruption]], and the sale of arms to both sides.  It then simply requires a border confrontation to be blown out of proportion in order to begin the conflict, much like the [[Mukden Incident]] shown in ''The Blue Lotus''. The war over the Grand Chapo oil plains was based on the [[Chaco War]] of the early 1930s.  It also depicted the [[Shuar people|Shuar]] indigenous people, famous for their ''[[tsantsa]]s'' (&quot;shrunken heads&quot;), according to the classic [[barbarian]] stereotype.{{Citation needed|date= October 2011}}

At first glance, ''[[The Black Island]]'' (1937–1938) is a simple thriller with Tintin in pursuit of money [[Counterfeit|forgers]], with the chase to [[Scotland]] giving it a feel of [[Alfred Hitchcock]]'s movie version of ''[[The 39 Steps (1935 film)|The Thirty-Nine Steps]]''. Dr. J.W. Muller is a German villain and can be read as a clear parody of the Germans at the time.

== The Second World War ==
Several stories were influenced by the menace of a second world war, and then by the war itself and the Nazi occupation of Belgium.

Despite the fact that Hergé was in favor of the neutrality of Belgium, ''[[King Ottokar's Sceptre]]'' (1938–1939) could be read as anti-[[Nazism|Nazi]]: Müsstler (a possible contraction of ''Mussolini'' and ''Hitler'') is the leader of a conspiracy that seeks to merge the kingdom of [[Syldavia]] with its old enemy [[Borduria]].  The story could have been influenced by the [[Anschluss]] in [[Austria]] in 1938. Müsstler is the head of the Iron Guard, a name implying a pro-fascist paramilitary group which were common in Europe between the wars. An actual fascist and anti-Semitic group called the [[Iron Guard]] was very active in Romania in the years leading up to the Second World War. The Romanian Iron Guard was often in violent conflict with the King of Romania, King [[Carol II]], who they accused of corruption and being influenced by his Jewish mistress. In fact the year the repression of the Iron Guard commenced was 1938, the year ''King Ottokar's Sceptre'' was first serialised.{{Citation needed|date= October 2011}} The leader of the Iron Guard, [[Codreanu]], was executed shortly thereafter for treason by the Romanian government. The Iron Guard briefly formed the government in 1940 under [[Horia Sima]] after the King's abdication but Hitler ended up backing the more conservative General [[Antonescu]] in January 1941 and the Iron Guard was eliminated from government and purged. Thus, in the foreign policy of the Third Reich the Romanian monarchy and other authoritarian figures were supported over the local fascist party. These historical complexities and ambiguities may explain why the story was not censored by the German occupation authorities.{{Citation needed|date= October 2011}}

The early and unfinished version of ''[[Land of Black Gold]]'' (1939–1940) alluded to the mobilization of Nazi war power. This unfinished adventure is set in the [[British Mandate of Palestine]] with [[United Kingdom|British]] soldiers and officials. The beginning of the war and the defeat of Belgium prevented Hergé from finishing this version, though it did come out in 1950. He later rewrote it, setting the action in the fictional Arab Kingdom of Khemed and replacing the conflict between [[Arab]]s and [[Jew]]s by a civil conflict between two Arab factions.&lt;ref&gt;Benoît Peeters, &lt;i&gt;Tintin and the World of Hergé&lt;/i&gt;, 1988, p. 86-89&lt;/ref&gt;

During the war, Hergé worked for ''Le Soir'', a newspaper which collaborated with the German occupiers. To avoid controversy during the Nazi occupation of Belgium, Tintin's adventures now focused mainly on non-political issues such as drug smuggling (''[[The Crab with the Golden Claws]]''), intrigue and treasure hunts (''[[The Secret of the Unicorn]]'' and ''[[Red Rackham's Treasure]]''), and a mysterious curse (''[[The Seven Crystal Balls]]'').

Somewhat controversial though, was ''[[The Shooting Star]]'', which was about a race between two crews trying to reach a [[meteorite]] which had landed in the [[Arctic]].  Hergé chose the subject to be as fantastic as possible, to avoid trouble from the censors.  Nonetheless politics intruded in that the crew Tintin joined was composed of Europeans from Axis or neutral countries, while their underhanded rivals were Americans. Tintin also flies in a German plane in the book (an [[Arado Ar 196]]).

Most damaging of all for Hergé was that these stories were published in ''Le Soir'', a [[Collaborationism|collaborationist]] newspaper.  After the war he and other members of its staff faced lengthy investigations into their wartime allegiances.  Hergé expressed his regrets in an 1973 interview: ''&quot;I recognise that I myself believed that the future of the West could depend on the New Order. For many, democracy had proved a disappointment, and the New Order brought new hope.  In light of everything which has happened, it is of course a huge error to have believed for an instant in the New Order&quot;''.&lt;ref&gt;Haagse Post. March 1973&lt;/ref&gt;

== Post-war ==
The post-war stories are less controversial, developing several recurring themes:

* [[Humanism]] and [[anti-racism]] in ''[[The Castafiore Emerald]]'', which takes the side of the [[Roma (Romani subgroup)|Roma]];

* [[Totalitarianism]]: ''[[The Calculus Affair]]'' is anti-[[Stalinism|Stalinist]], but also shows the lengths to which both sides of the [[Cold War]] went to acquire [[weapons of mass destruction]];

* International trafficking and [[slavery]] in ''[[The Red Sea Sharks]]'';

* [[Big Oil|Oil multinationals]] and their influence in ''[[Land of Black Gold]]'' (and previously in ''[[The Broken Ear]]''); and

* The arms trade in ''[[The Red Sea Sharks]]'' and ''[[Flight 714]]''. The millionaire Laszlo Carreidas in Flight 714 is evidently based on French aircraft industrialist [[Marcel Dassault]].&lt;ref&gt;Benoît Peeters, &lt;i&gt;Tintin and the World of Hergé&lt;/i&gt;, 1988, p. 129&lt;/ref&gt; As Dassault was born Jewish, the album has been considered as anti-semitic by some, but there is no reference to the religion of Carreidas. In ''The Broken Ear'' (before the war), Hergé had already caricatured a real arms merchant, [[Basil Zaharoff]].&lt;ref&gt;Numa Sadoul, &lt;i&gt;Entretiens avec Hergé&lt;/i&gt;, Casterman, 1989, p. 144&lt;/ref&gt;

Hergé was however criticized {{By whom| date= October 2011}} for his depiction of the black victims in ''[[The Red Sea Sharks]]''; in the first edition they speak pidgin French and seem rather simple-minded.  He rewrote their dialogue in later editions.&lt;ref&gt;Benoît Peeters, &lt;i&gt;Tintin and the World of Hergé&lt;/i&gt;, 1988, p. 107&lt;/ref&gt;

The last controversial album is ''[[Tintin and the Picaros]]'', which has been seen both as left-wing and right-wing. In it, Tintin goes through profound changes.  For the first time, Tintin seems to be flesh and blood, and perhaps even has weaknesses; for instance, he is at first uncharacteristically unwilling to travel to San Theodoros, where his friends have been accused of war crime based on false charges.  At the end he intervenes dramatically through [[revolution]]. But as Benoît Peeters puts it, &quot;it is quite clear that this is no real revolution but a palace coup.  Tapioca is backed by Borduria, Alcazar by the International Banana Company; as for ordinary people, they remain impoverished in the shantytowns.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Benoît Peeters, &lt;i&gt;Tintin and the World of Hergé&lt;/i&gt;, 1988, p. 127&lt;/ref&gt;

==Alleged sexism==
Hergé has also been accused of sexism, due to the almost complete lack of female characters in his books. The only woman character of importance is [[Bianca Castafiore]], who is potrayed to be foolish and nearly oblivious to all negative reactions to her behaviour — though she does show loyalty, presence of mind and quick wit when hiding Tintin and Haddock from [[Colonel Sponsz]] in ''[[The Calculus Affair]]''.

Hergé himself denied being a misogynist, saying that &quot;for me, women have nothing to do in a world like Tintin's, which is the realm of male friendship&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;Numa Sadoul, &lt;i&gt;Entretiens avec Herge&lt;/i&gt;, Casterman, 1989, p. 93&lt;/ref&gt;

Other reasons were because he believed that sentimentality had little to do in Tintin's stories, which are mainly about men getting into all sorts of &quot;misadventures rather than adventures&quot;, and wherein &quot;mocking women would not be nice&quot;. He also felt that a man slipping on a banana skin, providing he does not break a leg, is much funnier than if it happened to a woman. As a female interviewer put it, &quot;It has nothing to do with the [[misogynist]] world of the [[boy scout]],&quot;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=ugL1NhFH0e8&amp;feature=related Interview with Hergé] available on [[youtube]]&lt;/ref&gt; referring to the fact that Hergé was a scout in his youth.

==Tintin and the Jews==
Some aspects of Tintin's adventures have resulted in accusations of [[anti-Semitism]] being levelled at Hergé&lt;ref&gt;[http://blogs.forward.com/bintel-blog/119123/ Hergé, Creator of Tintin: Antisemitism for all Ages], Benjamin Ivry, ''The Jewish Daily Forward,'' November 17, 2009&lt;/ref&gt;, accusations that are often connected to his work during [[World War II]]  for ''[[Le Soir]]'', a newspaper that collaborated with the [[Nazi Germany|Nazis]] during the German occupation of Belgium.

Before the war, there were some instances of sinister Jewish-looking figures in Tintin's adventures. In ''[[The Broken Ear]]'' (1935–7), Tintin questions a shopkeeper who is selling copies of the [[totem|fetish]] he is looking for: the man wears a [[kippah]], speaks in broken French and rubs his hands with &quot;invisible soap&quot;.

As the war began, the first version of ''[[Land of Black Gold]]'' (1939–40) was being published. This version was set in the [[British Mandate of Palestine]] and featured Jewish [[terrorist]]s led by a [[Rabbi]]. The story was suspended due to its political nature, but completed after the war.

[[image:Herge cartoon - Tintin and the Jews.jpg|thumb|right|Jews appearing in a scene in ''The Shooting Star'' which appeared in the original newspaper edition.&lt;br/&gt;
&quot;Did you hear that, Isaac?... The end of the world!... What if it were true?...&quot;&lt;br/&gt;
&quot;Tee, hee!... Zat vould be a nice little teal, Salomon!... Ikh howe 50,000 Francs to my zurppliers... Zat vay ikh zould not be avle to pay...&quot;]]

The most serious instance of alleged anti-Semitism, however, featured in ''[[The Shooting Star]]'' (1941), which appeared during the German occupation. In a scene that appeared in ''Le Soir'' on 11 November 1941, two evil-looking Jewish men, Isaac and Salomon, watch [[List of The Adventures of Tintin characters#Philippulus|Philippulus the Prophet]] inform Tintin that the end of the world is nigh. One of them, speaking in very twisted French, looks forward to this as it means that he will not be obliged to pay off his [[creditor]]s.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.bbc.co.uk/ww2peopleswar/stories/73/a7812173.shtml|author=Joris Goedbloed|title='The Shooting Star'|work=WW2 People's War|date=16 December 2005|accessdate=2007-11-17}}&lt;/ref&gt; In addition, the sponsor of the rival expedition sent to find the meteorite is called Blumenstein, is given the appearance of a stereotypical Jewish businessman and uses underhand and potentially lethal methods to delay Tintin's ship. His bank is located in New York and his crew attempts to plant the American flag on the meteorite.

After the war and the exposure of the [[Jewish Holocaust|Holocaust]], Jewish people became noticeably absent from Tintin's adventures. ''Land of Black Gold'' was redrawn at the request of Hergé's British publishers who felt that it was out-of-date now that the state of [[Israel]] had been established. The terrorists in the Middle East were replaced by Arabs. The scene with Isaac and Salomon was left out of the book editions of ''The Shooting Star'', while &quot;Blumenstein&quot; was renamed &quot;Bohlwinkel&quot; and relocated to the fictional country of [[São Rico]]. According to Hergé, both the original and the later name were honest mistakes:&lt;ref&gt;Tintin, Hergé &amp;amp; his creation, Thompson, 1991, ISBN 978-0340564622&lt;/ref&gt; he thought Blumenstein was a common American name, and chose Bohlwinkel because it sounded like &quot;bollewinkel&quot;, a candy store.

Hugo Frey has argued that anti-Semitism continued in the post-war ''[[Flight 714]]''. Tintin's old nemesis and the mastermind of the plot in the book is the evil [[Rastapopoulos]], who Frey argues is an example of anti-Semitic caricature,&lt;ref&gt;Hugo Frey, &quot;Trapped in the Past: Anti-Semitism in Hergé's Flight 714&quot; in Mark McKinney, ed., ''History and Politics in French-Language Comics and Graphic Novels'' at p.31&lt;/ref&gt; though other writers argue against this, pointing out that Rastapopoulos is not Jewish and surrounds himself with explicitly German-looking characters: Kurt, the submarine commander of ''[[The Red Sea Sharks]]'', Doctor Krollspell, whom Hergé himself referred to as a former concentration camp official and Hans Boehm, the sinister-looking navigator and co-pilot, both from ''[[Flight 714]]''.&lt;ref&gt;''The Metamorphoses of Tintin: or Tintin for Adults'' by Jean-Marie Apostolidès, Jocelyn Hoy, published in 2009 by Stanford University Press&lt;/ref&gt; Another possible interpretation of Rastapopoulos, whose name is clearly of Greek origin, is that the character is a subtle reference to Aristoteles Onassis.{{Citation needed|date= October 2011}}

In other works, Hergé showed much sympathy for oppressed peoples, such as the [[Chinese people|Chinese]] in ''[[The Blue Lotus]]'', the black [[African]] [[Muslim|Muslims]] about to be traded as slaves in ''[[The Red Sea Sharks]]'' and the [[Romani people|Gypsies]] of ''[[The Castafiore Emerald]]'' falsely accused of theft.

==Big Business==
Much of Hergé's criticism was directed at big businesses and the ways they would affect the lives of ethnic minorities and the affairs of nations just for the sake of money. He also accused them of using unethical methods and being a cover for criminal activities.

These attacks started as early as ''[[Tintin in America]]'' following the discovery of oil on land occupied by Blackfoot tribespeople. Tintin is then surrounded by businessmen offering him tens of thousands of dollars for the rights to the oil. When Tintin announces that it belongs to the local native Americans, the chief of the tribe is, in comparison, given a mere $25 and half-an-hour to vacate the premises. An hour later the Indians are forced away by soldiers armed with rifles and bayonets; by the next day a whole city has been built on the site. A factory that Tintin later visits produces tinned &quot;rabbit&quot; meat out of stray cats, dogs, and rats.

Oil also came into play in ''[[The Broken Ear]]''. Western businesses like General American Oil and British-South American Petrol get the states of [[San Theodoros]] and Nuevo Rico to go to war over territory which turns out not to have oil after all. This part of the story was inspired by the real-life [[Chaco War]] of 1932–35. One of the businessmen, [[Characters in The Adventures of Tintin#R.W. Trickler|Trickler]], uses [[bribery]], [[Police corruption|corruption]], and false evidence in order to get his way. Arms dealer Basil Bazarov, who sells weapons to both sides, is based on the real-life [[Basil Zaharoff]].

A similar situation occurred in ''[[Land of Black Gold]]'', in which two rival oil companies, Arabex and Skoil Petroleum, separately support [[Emir]] [[Ben Kalish Ezab]] and [[Sheikh]] [[Bab El Ehr]] respectively.

Big business was also shown as a cover for illegal activities: [[Rastapopoulos]] for example is a respected businessman who mixes with people in high places, but is also the leader of major [[smuggling]] operations: [[opium]] in ''[[The Blue Lotus]]'' and [[Slavery|slaves]] in ''[[The Red Sea Sharks]]''. In ''The Blue Lotus'' is [[Mitsuhirato]], a Japanese man who owns a fashion shop and an opium den, which cover his activities as a drug smuggler and saboteur. Rastapopoulos and Mitsuhirato have an Arabic counterpart in [[Characters in The Adventures of Tintin#Omar Ben Salaad|Omar Ben Salaad]] of ''[[The Crab with the Golden Claws]]''.

The sponsor of the rival expedition in ''[[The Shooting Star]]'' is the head of a major banking organisation, who uses unethical methods to delay the progress of Tintin and Haddock's ship. These include sabotage with [[dynamite]] and fake distress messages. Controversially, in his original version, Hergé gave the man a [[Jewish]]-sounding name and had him based in [[New York City|New York]]. These were changed in later editions.

Following the [[World War II|war]], Herge's attacks on big business was suspended as he focused more on espionage (the [[Destination Moon (Tintin)|Moon adventures]] and ''[[The Calculus Affair]]''); but it returned with a vengeance in ''[[The Red Sea Sharks]]''. In this story Rastapopoulos becomes the Marquis di Gorgonzola, a [[media baron]], [[airline]] owner, and [[arms dealer]], who entertains influential people on board his luxury yacht. This serves as the cover of his business as a [[slave trader]]. When Emir Ben Kalish Ezab threatens to expose this for personal reasons, Rastapopoulos engineers his overthrow in favour of the Emir's enemy Sheikh Bab El Ehr.

Tintin has a knack of meeting businessmen who appear friendly at first, but turn out to be far from ethical and can also be villains. Rastapopoulos and Mitsuhirato are two such examples; but there is also [[Minor characters in The Adventures of Tintin#Laszlo Carreidas|Laszlo Carreidas]] of ''[[Flight 714]]''. At first shown as a friendly if eccentric person, Carreidas was revealed to be a cunning individual with a long history of unscrupulous behaviour not limited to the business world. A large part of his personal fortune was in a [[Swiss bank]] account under a false name and signature, presumably for [[taxation]]-related purposes.

Hergé's attack on big business and its interference in national politics went all the way to the final completed story, ''[[Tintin and the Picaros]]''. In this adventure, [[guerrilla]] leader [[General Alcazar]] had the support of the International Banana Company. Hergé's notes also reveal that Alcazar's wife was on the board of a company that kept him supplied with arms; a fact that may explain his marriage. To counter the rebels, Alcazar's enemy [[General Tapioca|Tapioca]] struck a deal with Loch Lomond whisky and parachuted large amounts of their brand into the jungle, making the rebels too drunk to stage a coup. Loch Lomond also sponsored the local carnival.

== References ==
{{Portalbox|Belgium|Comics}}
&lt;references&gt;&lt;/references&gt;

{{reflist}}
* Numa Sadoul, ''Entretiens avec Hergé'', Casterman, 1989.  ISBN 2-203-01708-2.
* Benoît Peeters, ''Tintin and the World of Hergé'', Bullfinch Press, 1992 (French ed. 1988).  ISBN 0-316-69752-4.
* Anders Østergaard, ''http://www.pbs.org/pov/pov2006/tintinandi/update.html''.

{{Tintin and Hergé}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Ideology Of Tintin}}
[[Category:Tintin]]

[[id:Ideologi Tintin]]
[[tr:Tenten'in İdeolojisi]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
