<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="18408" ns="0" title="LAME"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{About|the audio encoder|other uses|Lame (disambiguation){{!}}Lame}}
{{Technical|date=July 2010}}
{{Infobox software
| name                   = LAME
| logo                   = [[File:Lamelogo.svg|center|200px]]
| caption                = LAME official logo
| developer              = [http://lame.sourceforge.net/developers.html The LAME development team]
| released               = 1998
| latest_release_version = 3.99.3
| latest_release_date    = {{Start date and age|2011|11|26|df=yes}}
| operating_system       = [[Cross-platform]]
| genre                  = [[Codec]]
| license                = [[GNU Lesser General Public License]]
| website                = [http://lame.sourceforge.net/ lame.sourceforge.net]
}}

'''LAME''' is a [[free software]] [[codec]] used to [[Audio compression (data)|encode/compress]] audio into the [[Lossy compression|lossy]] [[MP3]] file format. 

==History==
{{oneref|section|date=January 2011}}
The name '''LAME''' is a [[recursive acronym]] for &quot;'''L'''AME '''A'''in't an '''M'''P3 '''E'''ncoder&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;http://lame.sourceforge.net/about.php&lt;/ref&gt;  Around mid-1998, Mike Cheng created LAME 1.0 as a set of modifications against the &quot;8Hz-MP3&quot; encoder source code. After some quality concerns raised by others, he decided to start again from scratch based on the &quot;dist10&quot; MPEG reference software sources. His goal was only to speed up the dist10 sources, and leave its quality untouched. That branch (a patch against the reference sources) became Lame 2.0. The project quickly became a team project. Mike Cheng eventually left leadership and started working on [[tooLAME]] (an MP2 encoder).

Mark Taylor then started pursuing increased quality in addition to better speed, and released version 3.0 featuring gpsycho, a new [[psychoacoustic model]] he developed. 

A few key improvements, in chronological order:
*May 1999: a new psychoacoustic model (gpsycho) is released along with LAME 3.0.
*June 1999: The first variable bitrate implementation is released. Soon after this, LAME also became able to target lower sampling frequencies from MPEG-2.
*November 1999: LAME switches from a GPL license to an LGPL license, which allows using it with closed-source applications.
*May 2000: the last pieces of the original ISO demonstration code are removed. LAME is not a patch anymore, but a full encoder.
*December 2003: substantial improvement to default settings, along with improved speed. LAME no longer requires user to use complicated parameters to produce good results.
*May 2007: default variable bitrate encoding speed is vastly improved.

[[File:Commandline Output of LAME command, on Mac OS X 10.7.2.png|thumb|LAME being run on a Mac OS X 10.7.2 terminal with &lt;ref&gt;git://gist.github.com/1386737.git the command  `lame -m s -a --preset 64 --lowpass 3.4 --highpass 0.42 in.mp3 out.mp3`&lt;/ref&gt;, which results in a sound file being output that has an evocative degree of distortion, like that of being broadcast over a POTS telephone system.]]
==Patents and legal issues==
Like all MP3 encoders, LAME implements some technology covered by [[patent]]s owned by the [[Fraunhofer society|Fraunhofer Society]] and other entities.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.mp3licensing.com/ mp3licensing.com - Home&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt; The developers of LAME do not themselves license the technology described by these patents. Distributing compiled binaries of LAME, its libraries, or programs that derive from LAME in countries that recognize those patents may be patent infringing.

The LAME developers state that, since their code is only released in source code form, it should only be considered as an educational description of an MP3 encoder, and thus does not infringe any patent by itself when released as source code only. At the same time, they advise users to obtain a patent license for any relevant technologies that LAME may implement before including a compiled version of the encoder in a product.&lt;ref&gt;http://lame.sourceforge.net/tech-FAQ.txt&lt;/ref&gt; Some software is released using this strategy:  companies use the LAME library, but obtain patent licenses.

In November 2005, there were reports that the [[Extended Copy Protection]] [[rootkit]] included on some [[Sony]] [[Compact Disc]]s included portions of the LAME library without complying with the terms of the [[LGPL]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.foxnews.com/story/0,2933,176021,00.html|title=Sony BMG Software May Contain Open-Source Code|date=2005-11-21|authors=Reuters|publisher=foxnews.com|accessdate=2011-11-26}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.the-interweb.com/serendipity/index.php?/archives/52-Is-Sony-in-violation-of-the-LGPL-Part-II.html Is Sony in violation of the LGPL?]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://hack.fi/~muzzy/sony-drm/ Sony's XCP DRM]&lt;/ref&gt;

==See also==
{{Portal|Free software}}
*[[List of codecs]]

==References==
{{Reflist}}

==External links==
*{{official|http://lame.sourceforge.net/}}
*[http://lame.buanzo.com.ar/ LAME library for Audacity] For use with the GNU GPL [[Audacity]] audio editor.
*[http://wiki.hydrogenaudio.org/index.php?title=LAME LAME at HydrogenAudio Wiki]
*[http://gabriel.mp3-tech.org/mp3infotag.html LAME Mp3 Info Tag revision 1 Specifications]

{{Compression software implementations}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Lame}}
[[Category:1998 software]]
[[Category:MP3]]
[[Category:Free multimedia codecs, containers, and splitters]]
[[Category:Audio codecs]]
[[Category:Cross-platform software]]

[[de:LAME]]
[[es:LAME (codificador)]]
[[eu:LAME]]
[[fr:LAME]]
[[ko:LAME]]
[[it:LAME]]
[[hu:LAME]]
[[nl:LAME]]
[[ja:LAME]]
[[pl:LAME]]
[[pt:LAME]]
[[ru:LAME]]
[[sv:LAME]]
[[zh:LAME]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
