<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="1840325" ns="0" title="Shippensburg University of Pennsylvania"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Infobox University
|image_name     = Shippensburg University seal.png
|name           = Shippensburg University of Pennsylvania
|motto          = 
|established    = 1871
|type           = [[State university system|Public]]
|president      = [[Dr. William Ruud]]
|city           = [[Shippensburg, Pennsylvania|Shippensburg]]
|state          = [[Pennsylvania]]
|country        = [[United States|USA]]
|undergrad      = 6,579 full-time
|postgrad       = 1,074 full-time
|faculty        = 302 full time&lt;br /&gt;130 part time
|campus         = [[Rural]], 200 acres (810,000 m²)
|affiliations   = [[NCAA]] [[Division II (NCAA)|D-II]]; [[Pennsylvania State Athletic Conference|PSAC]]
|nickname       = Raiders 
|mascot         = &quot;Big Red&quot;
|endowment      = US$27.9 million&lt;ref&gt;As of June 30, 2009.  {{Cite web | title = U.S. and Canadian Institutions Listed by Fiscal Year 2009 Endowment Market Value and Percentage Change in Endowment Market Value from FY 2008 to FY 2009| work = 2009 NACUBO-Commonfund Study of Endowments | publisher = National Association of College and University Business Officers | url = http://www.nacubo.org/Documents/research/2009_NCSE_Public_Tables_Endowment_Market_Values.pdf| format = PDF | accessdate = February 16, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|website        = [http://www.ship.edu www.ship.edu]
|logo=[[File:Shippensburg University of Pennsylvania Logo.gif|250px]]
}}
'''Shippensburg University of Pennsylvania''', commonly known as '''Ship''', or '''SU''', is a public [[university]] located in [[Shippensburg, Pennsylvania]], 40 miles (64&amp;nbsp;km) west-southwest of [[Harrisburg, Pennsylvania|Harrisburg]]. It is one of the 14 state universities that compose the [[Pennsylvania State System of Higher Education]] (PASSHE).

Shippensburg University is accredited by the [[Middle States Association of Colleges and Schools]] (MSACS).

==History==
[[Image:shipoldmain.JPG|left|thumb|Old Main]]

Shippensburg University of Pennsylvania was established in 1870, contrary to popular belief that the university was founded in 1871 which Shippensburg's main entrance gates even displays, as the Cumberland Valley State Normal School.  The school received official approval by the state on February 21, 1873, and was admitted its first class of 217 students on April 15, 1873.  In 1917 the school was purchased by the Commonwealth of Pennsylvania.

On June 4, 1926, the school was authorized to grant the bachelor of science in education degree in elementary and junior high education. The school received a charter on October 12, 1926, making it the first normal school in Pennsylvania to become a state teachers college. On June 3, 1927, the State Council of Education authorized the school to change its name to the State Teachers College at Shippensburg.

The business education curriculum was approved on December 3, 1937. On December 8, 1939, Shippensburg State Teachers College became the first teachers college in Pennsylvania and the fourth in the United States to be accredited by the Middle States Association of Colleges and (Secondary) Schools.

[[Image:Shipluhrs.JPG|right|thumb|Luhrs Performing Art Center was completed in Fall of 2005.]]

The State Council of Education approved graduate work leading to the master of education degree on January 7, 1959. On January 8, 1960, the name change to Shippensburg State College was authorized.

The arts and sciences curriculum was authorized by the State Council of Education on April 18, 1962, and the bachelor of science in business administration degree program was initiated on September 1, 1967.

On November 12, 1982, the governor of the Commonwealth signed Senate Bill 506 establishing the State System of Higher Education. Shippensburg State College was designated Shippensburg University of Pennsylvania effective July 1, 1983.

In 1985, many of the original historic buildings of the campus, including Old Main, were listed on the [[National Register of Historic Places]].&lt;ref name=&quot;arch&quot;&gt;{{cite web| url=http://www.archiplanet.org/wiki/Cumberland_Valley_State_Normal_School_Historic_District| year=2006| title=Cumberland Valley State Normal School Historic District|first=| last=| publisher=archiplanet.org/| accessdate=2007-01-08}}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Image:Shiplehmanlibrary.JPG|left|thumb|Lehman Library]]

==Academics==
*52 undergraduate programs are offered in the College of Arts and Sciences, the College of Education and Human Services, and the John L. Grove College of Business.
*8 pre-professional programs are offered, including pre-vet and pre-med in addition to 7 affiliate programs whereby students can earn combined undergraduate and graduate degrees through accelerated programs. Shippensburg is known for the educational department.
*17 programs are offered by the School of Graduate Studies and 3 Post Master's Programs.
*Shippensburg is accredited by Middle States Association of Colleges and Schools, National Council for the Accreditation of Teacher Education, AACSB International, American Chemical Society, Council on Social Work Education, Council for the Accreditation of Counseling and Related Educational Programs, International Association of Counseling Services, National Council for the Accreditation of Teachers, and Council for Exceptional Children. 
*The [http://webspace.ship.edu/geog/ Department of Geography &amp; Earth Science] offers major, minor, and certificate programs in [http://webspace.ship.edu/geog/GIS/ Geographic Information Science].

===Colleges===
*Arts and Sciences
*Education and Human Services
*[[John L. Grove College of Business]]
*School of Academic Programs and Services
*School of Graduate Studies

The Division of Extended Studies also offers a variety of courses, workshops, training sessions, continuing education, and credit and non-credit courses.

==Rankings==
The ''[[U.S. News &amp; World Report]]'' again ranked Shippensburg University among the top public universities in the North in its book &quot;America's Best Colleges 2009.&quot; In the annual rankings, Shippensburg is tied for 58th among all institutions in the North region. It was named one of the 100 best values among public colleges in &quot;[[Kiplinger's Personal Finance]]&quot;. Ship was also included in the 2007 edition of [[The Princeton Review]]'s &quot;The Best Northeastern Colleges.&quot;{{Fact|date=February 2007}}

==Library==
The '''[http://www.ship.edu/library/ Ezra Lehman Memorial Library]''' provides Web access to: its holdings, the holdings of the [[State Library of Pennsylvania|State Library]] and 24 other academic libraries, a variety of full text databases, electronic books, and Internet sites. The library collection includes over 2 million items, including bound volumes, micro-form pieces, periodicals, audiovisual titles, government documents, and University archives.  The Information and Computing Technologies Center maintains a campus network with a number of computer labs for student use. Each student at SU receives an email account and access to the Internet.  At the end of the 2009 school year, the Ezra Lehman Memorial Library first floor was completely renovated with new work stations, computers, and a new look.

==Athletics==
[[Image:Ship_Only_Trans.gif|left|thumb|Athletic Logo]]
Shippensburg University is an [[National Collegiate Athletic Association|NCAA]] [[Division II (NCAA)|Division II]] school and one of fourteen schools to compete in the [[Pennsylvania State Athletic Conference]]. The home venue of the universities [[Football (American)|football]] and [[track and field]] programs is [[Seth Grove Stadium]]. The school maintains intercollegiate programs for [[baseball]], [[basketball]] (Men &amp; Women), [[cross country running|cross country]] (Men &amp; Women), [[field hockey]], football, [[lacrosse]] (Men &amp; Women), [[soccer]] (Men &amp; Women), [[softball]], track &amp; field (Men &amp; Women), [[swimming (sport)|swimming]] (Men &amp; Women), [[tennis]] (Women), [[volleyball]] (Women) and [[collegiate wrestling|wrestling]]. Several club sports, such as [[College rugby|rugby]] (Men &amp; Women), Ultimate Frisbee and the [[Shippensburg Roller Hockey|inline hockey]] team, also participate in independent leagues. The women's rugby club won intercollegiate Division II national titles in 2008 and 2009. &lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | title=  National Small College Rugby Organization: Brackets &amp; Results | url =   http://www.eteamz.com/NSCRO/handouts/ | accessdate =2009-08-29}}&lt;/ref&gt; The team name is the Red Raiders, although there was a rumor they were going to change it due to a new NCAA policy. The team colors are blue and red. The mascot is &quot;Big Red,&quot; a red-tail hawk wearing a pirates hat. Shippensburg University has won several regional athletic championships. The Dixon trophy is awarded to the top athletic program in the 16 university Pennsylvania State Athletic Conference. Shippensburg has won the trophy seven times, the most by any PSAC member. Their titles came in 1998, 1999, 2003, 2004, 2005, 2010, and 2011.  mos&lt;ref name=&quot;sports&quot;&gt;{{cite web| url=http://www.shipraiders.com/| year=2007| title=About Shippensburg Athletics|first=| last=| publisher=Shippensburg University| accessdate=2007-02-08}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Notable alumni==
===Athletics===
*[[Clyde Barnhart]], former [[Major League Baseball]] player
*[[Rob Davis (football player)|Rob Davis]], former [[National Football League]] long-snapper; current Director of Player Development, [[Green Bay Packers]]
*[[Brent Grimes]], current [[National Football League]] cornerback for the [[Atlanta Falcons]]
*[[Ron Johnson (defensive end)|Ron Johnson]], former [[National Football League]] defensive end, [[Philadelphia Eagles]]
*[[Ethan Kilmer]], (attended) retired [[National Football League]] safety, [[Miami Dolphins]] and [[Cincinnati Bengals]]
*[[John Kuhn]], current [[National Football League]] fullback, [[Green Bay Packers]]
*[[Steve Spence]], former United States Olympic Long Distance Runner, [[1992 Summer Olympics]]; Bronze Medalist, 1991 [[IAAF World Championships in Athletics]]

===Government===
*[[Richard Alloway]], Pennsylvania State Senator
*[[Lisa Baker (Pennsylvania politician)|Lisa Baker]], Pennsylvania State Senator 
*Lieutenant General [[William G. Boykin]], the United States Deputy Undersecretary of Defense for Intelligence
*[[Jeffrey W. Coy]], former Pennsylvania State Representative; Commissioner, Pennsylvania Gaming Control Board (current)
*Ambassador [[Dell L. Dailey]], Coordinator for Counterterrorism, U.S. Department of State
*[[Clay Ford]], Member, Florida House of Representatives
*[[John Kline (politician)|John Kline]], U.S. Congressman from [[Minnesota]]
*[[Todd Platts]], U.S. Congressman from [[Pennsylvania]]
*[[Arthur Ringwalt Rupley]] (1868-1920), U.S. Congressman from Pennsylvania (1913-1915)
*[[Andrew A. Serafini]], Member, [[Maryland House of Delegates]]
*[[Jeanne Shaheen]], first woman to be elected [[Governor]] of [[New Hampshire]] (1997 - 2003) and U.S. Senator from New Hampshire (2009-present)

===Entertainment===
*[[Don Falcone]], musician and producer
*[[Chris Raab]] a.k.a. &quot;Raab Himself&quot;, cast member of ''[[Viva La Bam]]'', ''[[Jackass: The Movie]]'' and regular of the [[CKY crew]]

===Military===
*[[John N. Abrams]], former Commanding General of the United States Army’s Training and Doctrine Command
*Lieutenant General [[George R. Christmas]], United States Marine Corps (Ret.)
*[[Pat Foote]], retired US Army Brigadier General
*General [[Tommy Franks]], former Commander-in-Chief of [[United States|American]] occupation forces in [[Iraq]]
*[[Jay Garner]], former Director of [[Office for Reconstruction and Humanitarian Assistance|Reconstruction and Humanitarian Assistance]] for [[Iraq]]
*[[John Grimes]], former Assistant Secretary of Defense for Networks and Information Integration and Department of Defense Chief Information Officer
*General [[David D. McKiernan]], four star general in the U.S. Army currently serving as commander of U.S. Army forces in Europe
*[[Dennis Reimer]], [[Chief of Staff of the United States Army]] from 1995 to 1999
*[[Andrew M. Schuster]], retired U.S. National Guard Brigadier General
*[[John W. Shannon]], former [[United States Secretary of the Army]] &amp; [[ United States Under Secretary of the Army]]
*Maj. Gen. [[Michael S. Tucker]], Deputy Chief of Staff Operations, NATO; former Deputy Commanding General of Walter Reed Army Medical Center

===Literature===
*[[Dean Koontz]], author &amp; [[ New York Times Bestseller]]

===Business/Education===
*Sister [[Candace Introcaso]], President, [[La Roche College]] 
*[[J.E. Keeny]], president emeritus of [[Louisiana Tech University]]  
*[[Kevin J. Manning]], Ph.D., President, [[Stevenson University]]

==References==
{{Reflist}}

==External links==
*[http://www.ship.edu/ Shippensburg University of Pennsylvania]
*[http://www.shipunderground.com ShipUnderground:  Professor, Local Restaurant Reviews]
*[http://education.yahoo.com/college/facts/8629.html Yahoo! Education Profile: Shippensburg University]
*[http://www.usnews.com/usnews/edu/college/directory/brief/drglance_3326_brief.php USNews.com: America's Best Colleges]
*[http://webspace.ship.edu/psych/shipcampus.html Campus photos]
*[http://www.shipraiders.com  Shippensburg University Athletics]
{{Pennsylvania State Athletic Conference}}
{{Pennsylvania State System of Higher Education}}
{{National Register of Historic Places in Pennsylvania}}


{{coord|40.061|-77.522|region:US-PA_type:edu|display=title}}

[[Category:Middle States Association of Colleges and Schools]]
[[Category:American Association of State Colleges and Universities]]
[[Category:Universities and colleges in Pennsylvania]]
[[Category:Eastern Pennsylvania Rugby Union]]
[[Category:Educational institutions established in 1871]]
[[Category:Pennsylvania State Athletic Conference]]
[[Category:Shippensburg University of Pennsylvania]]
[[Category:Universities and colleges in Cumberland County, Pennsylvania]]
[[Category:Universities and colleges in Franklin County, Pennsylvania]]
[[Category:Schools on the National Register of Historic Places in Pennsylvania]]

[[es:Universidad Shippensburg]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
