<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="18426501" ns="0" title="Harvard University"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{pp-semi|small=yes}}
{{Redirect|Harvard}}
{{Infobox university
|name = Harvard University
|image_name = Harvard_Wreath_Logo_1.svg
|caption = [[Seal (device)|Seal]] of Harvard University
|motto = ''Veritas''&lt;ref&gt;Appearing as it does on the coat of arms itself, ''Veritas'' is not a motto in the usual [[heraldry|heraldic]] sense. Properly speaking, rather, Harvard's [http://www.hcs.harvard.edu/~gsascf/shield.html original motto is ''Veritas Christo et Ecclesiae'' (&quot;Truth for Christ and the Church&quot;)] as shown on [http://etc.usf.edu/clipart/55900/55996/55996_harvard_seal.htm Harvard's original shield] or [[seal (device)|seal]]. This legend is otherwise not used today. &lt;/ref&gt;
|established = 1636&lt;ref name=founding&gt;An appropriation of £400 toward a &quot;school or college&quot; was voted on October 28, 1636 (OS), at a meeting which initially convened on September 8 and was adjourned to October 28. Some sources consider October 28, 1636 (OS) (November 7, 1636 NS) to be the date of founding. Harvard's 1936 tercentenary celebration treated September 18 as the founding date, though 1836 bicentennial was celebrated on September 8, 1836. Sources: meeting dates, {{Cite book|first=Josiah|last=Quincy|title=History of Harvard University|year=1860|publisher=Crosby, Nichols, Lee and Co.|location=117 Washington Street, Boston}}, [http://books.google.com/books?vid=OCLC11636583&amp;id=KynqxH_4lGUC&amp;pg=RA1-PA586&amp;lpg=RA1-PA586 p. 586], &quot;At a Court holden September 8th, 1636 and continued by adjournment to the 28th of the 8th month (October, 1636)... the Court agreed to give £400 towards a School or College, whereof £200 to be paid next year....&quot; Tercentenary dates: {{Cite news|url=http://www.time.com/time/magazine/printout/0,8816,756722,00.html|date=1936-09-28|accessdate=2006-09-08|publisher=Time Magazine|title=Cambridge Birthday}}: &quot;Harvard claims birth on the day the Massachusetts Great and General Court convened to authorize its founding. This was Sept. 8, 1637 under the Julian calendar. Allowing for the ten-day advance of the Gregorian calendar, Tercentenary officials arrived at Sept. 18 as the date for the third and last big Day of the celebration;&quot; &quot;on Oct. 28, 1636 ... £400 for that 'school or college' [was voted by] the Great and General Court of the [[Massachusetts Bay Colony]].&quot; Bicentennial date: {{cite web|url=http://www.news.harvard.edu/gazette/2003/10.02/02-history.html|publisher=Harvard University|title=Harvard Gazette: This Month in Harvard History|date=2003-09-02|accessdate=2006-09-15|author=Marvin Hightower}}, &quot;Sept. 8, 1836 - Some 1,100 to 1,300 alumni flock to Harvard's Bicentennial, at which a professional choir premieres &quot;Fair Harvard.&quot; ... guest speaker Josiah Quincy Jr., Class of 1821, makes a motion, unanimously adopted, 'that this assembly of the Alumni be adjourned to meet at this place on the 8th of September, 1936.'&quot; Tercentary opening of Quincy's sealed package: ''The New York Times,'' September 9, 1936, p. 24, &quot;Package Sealed in 1836 Opened at Harvard. It Held Letters Written at Bicentenary&quot;: &quot;September 8th, 1936: As the first formal function in the celebration of Harvard's tercentenary, the Harvard Alumni Association witnessed the opening by President Conant of the 'mysterious' package sealed by President Josiah Quincy at the Harvard bicentennial in 1836.&quot;&lt;/ref&gt;
|mottoeng = Truth
|type = [[Private university|Private]]
|calendar = Semester
|endowment = [[United States dollar|US$]]32.0 [[1000000000 (number)|billion]]&lt;ref name=&quot;Harvard Management Company&quot;&gt;{{cite web|last=Mendillo|first=Jane L.|title=September 2011 Harvard Management Company Endowment Report|url=http://www.hmc.harvard.edu/docs/Sept%2021%20Draft-Annual%20Report.pdf|publisher=Harvard Management Company|accessdate=23 September 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;ref name=&quot;NACUBO&quot;/&gt;
|Harvard Corporation Chairman = [[James R. Houghton]]
|president = [[Drew Gilpin Faust]]
|students = 21,225
|undergrad = 7,181 total&lt;br /&gt;6,655 College&lt;br /&gt;526 Extension
|postgrad = 14,044
|staff = 2,497 non-medical&lt;br /&gt;10,674 medical
|faculty = 2,107&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|last=Office of Institutional Research.|title=Harvard University Fact Book|year=2009|chapter=Faculty|url=http://www.provost.harvard.edu/institutional_research/Provost_-_09_18-19facuni.pdf}} (&quot;Unduplicated, Paid Instructional Faculty Count: 2,107. Unduplicated instructional faculty count is the most appropriate count for general reporting purposes.&quot;)&lt;/ref&gt;
|city = [[Cambridge, Massachusetts|Cambridge]]
|state = [[Massachusetts]]
|country = [[United States|U.S.]]
|campus = [[Urban area|Urban]]&lt;br /&gt;{{convert|210|acre|ha}} (Main campus)&lt;br /&gt;{{convert|22|acre|ha}} (Medical campus)&lt;br/&gt;{{convert|359|acre|ha}} (Allston campus)&lt;ref name=&quot;Campus&quot;/&gt;
|athletics =41 Varsity Teams&lt;br /&gt;[[Ivy League|Ivy&amp;nbsp;League]]&lt;br /&gt;[[National Collegiate Athletic Association|NCAA]] [[Division I (NCAA)|Division I]]
|colors = [[Crimson]] {{color box|#991122}}
|free_label = Newspaper
|free = ''[[The Harvard Crimson]]''
|nickname = [[Harvard Crimson]]
|website= [http://www.harvard.edu/ harvard.edu]
|logo = [[Image:Harvard University logo.PNG|Harvard University logo]]
|publictransit = [[Harvard (MBTA station)]]
}}
'''Harvard University''' is a [[private university|private]] [[Ivy League]] [[research university|university]] located in [[Cambridge, Massachusetts|Cambridge]], [[Massachusetts]], [[United States]], established in 1636 by the [[Massachusetts General Court|Massachusetts legislature]]. Harvard is the [[Colonial Colleges|oldest]] institution of higher learning in the United States&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|first1=Frederick |last1=Rudolph |title=The American College and University |year=1961 |page=3 |isbn=0820312851 |publisher=University of Georgia Press}}&lt;/ref&gt; and the first [[corporation]] (officially ''The President and Fellows of Harvard College'') chartered in the country. Harvard's history, influence, and wealth have made it one of the most prestigious universities in the world.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|title=Making Harvard Modern: The Rise of America's University |last1=Keller |first1=Morton |last2=Keller |first2=Phyllis |publisher=Oxford University Press |isbn=0195144570 |quote=Harvard's professional schools... won world prestige of a sort rarely seen among social institutions. (...) Harvard's age, wealth, quality, and prestige may well shield it from any conceivable vicissitudes. |year=2001 |pages=463–481}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|title=How Harvard Rules: Reason in the Service of Empire |quote=...[Harvard's] tremendous institutional power and prestige (...) Within the nation's (arguably) most prestigious institution of higher learning... |chapter=Sexual Shakedown |pages=326–336 |year=1989 |publisher=South End Press |isbn=0896082849 |editor1-first=John |last=Spaulding |first=Christina |editor-last=Trumpbour}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Harvard was named after its first benefactor, [[John Harvard (clergyman)|John Harvard]]. Although it was never formally affiliated with a church, the college primarily trained [[Congregational church|Congregationalist]] and [[Unitarianism|Unitarian]] clergy. Harvard's curriculum and students became increasingly secular throughout the 18th century and by the 19th century had emerged as the central cultural establishment among [[Boston Brahmin|Boston elites]].&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|title=Harvard and the Boston Brahmins: A Study in Institutional and Class Development, 1800–1865 |last=Story |first=Ronald |journal=Journal of Social History |volume=8 |issue=3 |year=1975 |pages=94–121|doi=10.1353/jsh/8.3.94}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|last=Farrell |first=Betty G. |title=Elite Families: Class and Power in Nineteenth-Century Boston |year=1993 |isbn=0791415937 |publisher=State University of New York Press}}&lt;/ref&gt; Following the [[American Civil War]], President [[Charles W. Eliot]]'s forty year tenure (1869–1909) transformed the college and affiliated professional schools into a centralized [[research university]], and Harvard became a founding member of the [[Association of American Universities]] in 1900.&lt;ref name=&quot;AAU&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.aau.edu/about/article.aspx?id=5476 |title=Member Institutions and years of Admission |publisher=Association of American Universities |accessdate=August 28, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[James Bryant Conant]] led the university through the [[Great Depression]] and [[World War II]] and began to reform the curriculum and liberalize admissions after the war. The undergraduate college became coeducational after its 1977 merger with [[Radcliffe College]]. [[Drew Gilpin Faust]] was elected the 28th president in 2007 and is the first woman to lead the university. Harvard has the [[List of colleges and universities in the United States by endowment|largest]] [[financial endowment]] of any academic institution in the world, standing at $32 billion as of September 2011.&lt;ref name=&quot;NACUBO&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.nacubo.org/Documents/research/2009_NCSE_Public_Tables_Endowment_Market_Values.pdf |title=U.S. and Canadian Institutions Listed by Fiscal Year 2009 Endowment Market Value |publisher=National Association of College and University Business Officers and Commonfund Institute |accessdate=August 27, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The university comprises eleven separate academic units&lt;!--there seem to be 14 listed later--&gt; — ten faculties and the [[Radcliffe Institute for Advanced Study]] — with campuses throughout the Boston metropolitan area.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.provost.harvard.edu/institutional_research/09_03OrgChtFac.pdf |title=Faculties and Allied Institutions |publisher=Office of the Provost, Harvard University |accessdate=August 27, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; Harvard's {{convert|210|acre|ha|adj=on}} main campus is centered on [[Harvard Yard]] in Cambridge, approximately {{convert|3.4|mi|km}} northwest of downtown [[Boston]]. The [[Harvard Business School|business school]] and athletics facilities, including [[Harvard Stadium]], are located across the [[Charles River]] in [[Allston, Massachusetts|Allston]] and the [[Harvard Medical School|medical]], [[Harvard School of Dental Medicine|dental]], and [[Harvard School of Public Health|public health]] schools are located in the [[Longwood Medical and Academic Area|Longwood Medical Area]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Campus&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.provost.harvard.edu/institutional_research/Provost_-_FB2009_10_Sec03_4_Plant.pdf |title=Faculties and Allied Institutions |year=2009 |publisher=Office of the Provost, Harvard University |accessdate=August 27, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;

As of 2010, Harvard employs about 2,100 faculty to teach and advise approximately 6,700 undergraduates ([[Harvard College]]) and 14,500 graduate and professional students.&lt;ref name=Headcount2010&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.harvard.edu/about/glance.php|title=Harvard at a Glance|publisher=Harvard University |accessdate=November 28, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; Eight [[List of Presidents of the United States by education|U.S. presidents]] have been graduates, and [[List of Nobel laureates by university affiliation|75 Nobel Laureates]] have been student, faculty, or staff affiliates. Harvard is also the [[alma mater]] of sixty-two living [[billionaires]], the most in the country.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|url=http://www.forbes.com/2010/08/11/harvard-stanford-columbia-business-billionaires-universities.html?boxes=businesschannelsections | title=Billionaire Universities|author=Janhavi Kumar Sapra|date=August 11, 2010|accessdate=August 31, 2010|work=[[Forbes]]}}&lt;/ref&gt; The [[Harvard University Library]] is the largest academic library in the United States, and one of the largest in the world.&lt;ref name=&quot;largestlibs&quot;/&gt;&lt;!--cite needed for one-of-in-world--&gt;

The [[Harvard Crimson]] competes in 41 intercollegiate sports in the [[National Collegiate Athletic Association|NCAA]] [[Division I (NCAA)|Division I]] [[Ivy League]]. Harvard has an intense athletic rivalry with [[Yale University]] traditionally culminating in ''[[Harvard–Yale football rivalry|The Game]]'', although the [[Harvard–Yale Regatta]] predates the football game. This rivalry, though, is put aside every two years when the Harvard and Yale [[Track and Field]] teams come together to compete against a combined [[Oxford University]] and [[Cambridge University]] team, a competition that is the oldest continuous international amateur competition in the world.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Yale and Harvard Defeat Oxford/Cambridge Team|url=http://www.yalebulldogs.com/sports/w-track/recaps/041009aac.html|publisher=Yale University Athletics|accessdate=9/13/2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==History==
{{Main|History of Harvard University}}

===Colonial===
[[File:A Westerly View of the Colledges in Cambridge New England by Paul Revere.jpeg|thumb|Engraving of [[Harvard College]] by [[Paul Revere]], 1767]]
Harvard was founded in 1636 by vote of the Great and General Court of the [[Massachusetts Bay Colony]], making it the oldest institution of higher learning in the United States. Initially called &quot;New College&quot; or &quot;the college at New Towne&quot;, the institution was renamed ''[[Harvard College]]'' on March 13, 1639. It was named after [[John Harvard (clergyman)|John Harvard]], a young English [[clergyman]] from [[Southwark]], [[London]], an alumnus of the [[University of Cambridge]] (after which Cambridge, Massachusetts is named), who bequeathed the College his library of four hundred books and [[Pound sign|£]]779 [[pounds sterling]], which was half of his estate.&lt;ref name=&quot;JH facts&quot;&gt;{{cite web
| title = John Harvard Facts, Information.
| url = http://www.encyclopedia.com/topic/John_Harvard.aspx
| publisher = The Columbia Encyclopedia, Sixth Edition. 2008
| accessdate = 2009-07-17
| quote = He bequeathed £780 (half his estate) and his library of 320 volumes to the new established college at Cambridge, Mass., which was named in his honor.}}&lt;/ref&gt; The charter creating the corporation of Harvard College came in 1650. In the early years, the College trained many Puritan ministers.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.news.harvard.edu/guide/intro/index.html |title=The Harvard Guide: The Early History of Harvard University |publisher=News.harvard.edu |date= |accessdate=2010-08-29}}&lt;/ref&gt; The college offered a classic academic course based on the English university model—many leaders in the colony had attended [[Cambridge University]]—but one consistent with the prevailing [[Puritan]] philosophy. The college was never affiliated with any particular denomination, but many of its earliest graduates went on to become clergymen in Congregational and Unitarian churches throughout New England.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|author=Harvard Office of News and Public Affairs |url=http://www.hno.harvard.edu/guide/intro/index.html |title=Harvard guide intro |publisher=Web.archive.org |date=2007-07-26 |accessdate=2010-08-29 |archiveurl = http://web.archive.org/web/20070726133429/http://www.hno.harvard.edu/guide/intro/index.html |archivedate = 2007-07-26}}&lt;/ref&gt; An early brochure, published in 1643, described the founding of the college as a response to the desire &quot;to advance learning and perpetuate it to posterity, dreading to leave an illiterate ministry to the churches&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|first=Louis B. |last=Wright |title=The Cultural Life of the American Colonies |year=2002 |page=116|isbn=978-0-486-42223-7}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The leading Boston divine [[Increase Mather]] served as president from 1685 to 1701. In 1708, [[John Leverett the Younger|John Leverett]] became the first president who was not also a clergyman, which marked a turning of the College toward intellectual independence from Puritanism.

===19th century===
====Religion and philosophy====
The takeover of Harvard by the [[Unitarianism|Unitarians]] in 1805 resulted in the [[secularization]] of the American college. By 1850 Harvard was the &quot;Unitarian Vatican.&quot; The &quot;liberals&quot; (Unitarians) allied themselves with [[Federalist Party|high Federalists]] and began to create a set of private societies and institutions meant to shore up their cultural and political authority, a movement that prefigured the emergence of the [[Boston Brahmin]] class. On the other hand, the theological conservatives used print media to argue for the maintenance of open debate and democratic governance through a diverse public sphere, seeing the liberals' movement as an attempt to create a cultural oligarchy in opposition to Congregationalist tradition and republican political principles.&lt;ref&gt;Neil Brody Miller, &quot;'Proper Subjects for Public Inquiry': the First Unitarian Controversy and the Transformation of Federalist Print Culture&quot;, ''Early American Literature'' 2008 43(1): 101–135&lt;/ref&gt;

In 1846, the natural history lectures of [[Louis Agassiz]] were acclaimed both in New York and on the campus at Harvard College. Agassiz's approach was distinctly idealist and posited Americans' 'participation in the Divine Nature' and the possibility of understanding 'intellectual existences.' Agassiz's perspective on science combined observation with intuition and the assumption that one can grasp the 'divine plan' in all phenomena. When it came to explaining life-forms, Agassiz resorted to matters of shape based on a presumed archetype for his evidence. This dual view of knowledge was in concert with the teachings of [[Common Sense Realism]] derived from Scottish philosophers [[Thomas Reid]] and Dugald Stewart, whose works were part of the Harvard curriculum at the time. The popularity of Agassiz's efforts to 'soar with Plato' probably also derived from other writings to which Harvard students were exposed, including Platonic treatises by Ralph Cudworth, John Norris, and, in a Romantic vein, [[Samuel Coleridge]]. The library records at Harvard reveal that the writings of Plato and his early modern and Romantic followers were almost as regularly read during the 19th century as those of the 'official philosophy' of the more empirical and more deistic Scottish school.&lt;ref&gt;David K. Nartonis, &quot;Louis Agassiz and the Platonist Story of Creation at Harvard, 1795–1846&quot;, ''Journal of the History of Ideas'' 2005 66(3): 437-449, [http://www.jstor.org/stable/3654189 in JSTOR]&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Charles W. Eliot]], president 1869–1909, eliminated the favored position of Christianity from the curriculum while opening it to student self-direction. While Eliot was the most crucial figure in the secularization of American higher education, he was motivated not by a desire to secularize education, but by [[Transcendentalism|Transcendentalist]] [[Unitarianism|Unitarian]] convictions. Derived from [[William Ellery Channing]] and [[Ralph Waldo Emerson]], these convictions were focused on the dignity and worth of human nature, the right and ability of each person to perceive truth, and the indwelling God in each person.&lt;ref&gt;Stephen P. Shoemaker, &quot;The Theological Roots of Charles W. Eliot's Educational Reforms&quot;, ''Journal of Unitarian Universalist History'' 2006–2007 31: 30-45,&lt;/ref&gt;

===20th century===
[[File:Rummell, Richard_Harvard University.jpg|thumb|right|290px|Richard Rummell's 1906 watercolor landscape view, facing northeast. &lt;ref name=&quot;http://grahamarader.blogspot.com/2011/07/iconic-college-view-harvard-university.html&quot;&gt;[http://grahamarader.blogspot.com/2011/07/iconic-college-view-harvard-university.html &quot;Arader Galleries Iconic College Views&quot;],  ''Rummell, Richard'', Littig &amp; Co. 1915&lt;/ref&gt;]]
During the 20th century, Harvard's international reputation grew as a burgeoning endowment and prominent professors expanded the university's scope. Explosive growth in the student population continued with the addition of new graduate schools and the expansion of the undergraduate program. [[Radcliffe College]], established in 1879 as sister school of Harvard College, became one of the most prominent schools for women in the United States.

====Meritocracy====
[[James Bryant Conant]] (president, 1933–1953) reinvigorated creative scholarship to guarantee its preeminence among research institutions. He saw higher education as a vehicle of opportunity for the talented rather than an entitlement for the wealthy, so Conant devised programs to identify, recruit, and support talented youth. In 1943, he asked the faculty make a definitive statement about what general education ought to be, at the secondary as well as the college level. The resulting ''Report'', published in 1945, was one of the most influential manifestos in the history of American education in the 20th century.&lt;ref&gt;Anita Fay Kravitz, &quot;The Harvard Report of 1945: An historical ethnography&quot;, Ph.D. dissertation, University of Pennsylvania, 1994, 367 pages; AAT 9427558&lt;/ref&gt;

In 1945–1960 admissions policies were opened up to bring in students from a more diverse applicant pool. No longer drawing mostly from rich alumni of select New England prep schools, the undergraduate college was now open to striving middle class students from public schools; many more Jews and Catholics were admitted, but few blacks, Hispanics or Asians.&lt;ref&gt;Malka A. Older. (1996). [http://www.thecrimson.com/article.aspx?ref=217911 Preparatory schools and the admissions process]. [[The Harvard Crimson]], January 24, 1996&lt;/ref&gt;

====Women====
Women remained segregated at Radcliffe, though more and more took Harvard classes. Nonetheless, Harvard's undergraduate population remained predominantly male, with about four men attending Harvard College for every woman studying at Radcliffe. Following the merger of Harvard and Radcliffe admissions in 1977, the proportion of female undergraduates steadily increased, mirroring a trend throughout higher education in the United States. Harvard's graduate schools, which had accepted females and other groups in greater numbers even before the college, also became more diverse in the post-World War II period.

In 1999, [[Radcliffe College]], founded in 1879 as the &quot;Harvard Annex for Women&quot;,&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|first=Sally |last=Schwager |chapter=Taking up the Challenge: The Origins of Radcliffe |title=Yards and Gates: Gender in Harvard and Radcliffe History |editor=Laurel Thatcher Ulrich (ed.) |location=New York |publisher=Palgrave Macmillan |year=2004 |isbn=1403960984 |page=115}}&lt;/ref&gt; merged formally with Harvard University, becoming the [[Radcliffe Institute for Advanced Study]].

[[Drew Gilpin Faust]], the Dean at Radcliffe, became the first woman president of Harvard in 2007.
[[File:Harvard square harvard yard.JPG|thumb|[[Harvard Yard]] as seen from the Holyoke Center]]

====Liberalism====
Harvard and its affiliates, like many American universities,&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|first1=Mack D. |last1=Mariani |first2=Gordon J. |last2=Hewitt |title=Indoctrination U.? Faculty Ideology and Changes in Student Political Orientation |journal=PS: Political Science &amp; Politics |volume=41 |issue=4 |pages=773–783 |year=2008 |doi=10.1017/S1049096508081031|ref=harv}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|title=Professor Is a Label That Leans to the Left |date=January 17, 2010 |last=Cohen |first=Patricia |newspaper=The New York Times |url=http://www.nytimes.com/2010/01/18/arts/18liberal.html?pagewanted=print|ref=harv|postscript=&lt;!--None--&gt;}}&lt;/ref&gt; are considered by some to be politically [[Liberalism in the United States|liberal]] (left of center).&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|title=The Conservative Influence of the Federalist Society on the Harvard Law School Student Body |last=Hicks, Jr. |first= George W. |year=2006 |journal=Harvard Journal of Law &amp; Public Policy |volume=29 |url=http://www.law.harvard.edu/students/orgs/jlpp/Vol29_No2_Hicks.pdf |issue=2|ref=harv}}&lt;/ref&gt; Conservative author [[William F. Buckley, Jr.]] quipped that he would rather be governed by the first 2000 names in the Boston phone book than by the Harvard faculty,&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|title=William F. Buckley, Jr., 82, Godfather of Modern Conservatism |newspaper=New York Sun |last=Miller |first=Stephen |date=February 28, 2008 |url=http://www.nysun.com/obituaries/william-f-buckley-jr-82-godfather-of-modern/72002/?print=0367121721|ref=harv|postscript=&lt;!--None--&gt;}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Richard Nixon]] famously referred to Harvard as the &quot;[[Moscow Kremlin|Kremlin]] on the [[Charles River|Charles]]&quot; around 1970,&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|last=Currie |first=Duncan |date=July 28, 2004 |title=&quot;Kremlin on the Charles&quot; No More? |magazine=The Weekly Standard |url=http://www.weeklystandard.com/print/Content/Public/Articles/000/000/004/394emjiy.asp|ref=harv|postscript=&lt;!--None--&gt;}}&lt;/ref&gt; and Vice President [[George H.W. Bush]] disparaged what he saw to be Harvard's liberalism during the [[United States presidential election, 1988|1988 presidential election]].&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|url=http://www.nytimes.com/1988/06/11/us/bush-traces-how-yale-differs-from-harvard.html |title=Bush Traces How Yale Differs From Harvard |newspaper=The New York Times |last=Dowd |first=Maureen |date=June 11, 1988}}&lt;/ref&gt; Republicans remain a small minority of faculty, and the University has refused to officially recognize the [[Harvard ROTC|Harvard Reserve Officers' Training Corps]] (ROTC) program—forcing students to commission through nearby MIT.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last=Flow |first=Christian B. |url=http://www.thecrimson.com/printerfriendly.aspx?ref=522609 |title=Will ROTC Return?|work=The Harvard Crimson |date=2008-03-18 |accessdate=2010-02-22}}&lt;/ref&gt; The Harvard College Handbook explains, &quot;Current federal policy of excluding known lesbian, gay, and bisexual individuals from admission to ROTC or of discharging them from service is inconsistent with Harvard’s values as stated in its policy on discrimination.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;[http://webdocs.registrar.fas.harvard.edu/ugrad_handbook/current/ugrad_handbook_single.pdf Harvard College Handbook]{{dead link|date=October 2011}}, page 59.&lt;/ref&gt; In 2011, Harvard announced that it will reinstate the ROTC program, following the [[Don't ask, don't tell#Repeal|repeal of &quot;don't ask, don't tell&quot;]].&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|url=http://www.washingtonpost.com/wp-dyn/content/article/2011/03/03/AR2011030306129.html |title=Harvard welcoming ROTC back to campus |newspaper=The Washington Post |last=Lauerman |first=John |date=March 4, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

President [[Lawrence Summers]] resigned his presidency in 2006. His resignation came just one week before a second planned vote of no confidence by the Harvard Faculty of Arts and Sciences. Former president [[Derek Bok]] served as interim president. Members of Harvard's Faculty of Arts and Sciences, which instructs graduate students in GSAS and undergraduates in Harvard College, had passed an earlier motion of &quot;lack of confidence&quot; in Summers' leadership on March 15, 2005 by a 218–185 vote, with 18 abstentions. The 2005 motion was precipitated by comments about the causes of gender demographics in academia made at a closed academic conference and leaked to the press.&lt;ref&gt;Bombardieri, M. (2005). [http://www.boston.com/news/education/higher/articles/2005/01/17/summers_remarks_on_women_draw_fire/ Summers' remarks on women draw fire]. [[The Boston Globe]], January 17, 2005.&lt;/ref&gt; In response, Summers convened two committees to study this issue: the Task Force on Women Faculty and the Task Force on Women in Science and Engineering. Summers had also pledged $50 million to support their recommendations and other proposed reforms. [[Drew Gilpin Faust]] is the 28th president of Harvard. An [[History of the United States|American historian]], former dean of the [[Radcliffe Institute for Advanced Study]], and Lincoln Professor of History at Harvard University, Faust is the first female president in the university's history.&lt;ref name=&quot;crimson-pres&quot;&gt;[http://www.thecrimson.com/article.aspx?ref=516910 &quot;Faust Expected To Be Named President This Weekend,&quot;] ''[[The Harvard Crimson]]'', 8 February 2007&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;harvard-pres&quot;&gt;[http://web.archive.org/web/20080430103231/http://www.news.harvard.edu/gazette/2007/02.15/99-president.html &quot;Harvard names Drew Faust as its 28th president,&quot;] ''Office of News and Public Affairs'', 11 February 2007&lt;/ref&gt;

==Administration and organization==
[[File:Harvard University map (older, date unknown).jpg|thumb|upright|Harvard University campus (circa 1938)]]

A faculty of approximately 2,410 professors, lecturers, and instructors serve as of school year 2009–10,&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|last=Office of Institutional Research.|title=Harvard University Fact Book 2009–2010|year=2009|url=http://www.provost.harvard.edu/institutional_research/Provost_-_Harvard_Fact_Book_2009-10_FINAL_new.pdf}} (&quot;Faculty&quot;)&lt;/ref&gt; with 7,180 [[undergraduate]] and 13,830 [[graduate school|graduate]] students.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|last=Harvard University.|title=Financial Report, Fiscal Year 2010|year=2010|url=http://cdn.wds.harvard.edu/fad/2010_full_fin_report.pdf}} p. 20.&lt;/ref&gt; The school color is [[crimson]], which is also the name of the Harvard sports teams and the daily newspaper, ''[[The Harvard Crimson]]''. The color was unofficially adopted (in preference to [[magenta]]) by an 1875 vote of the student body, although the association with some form of red can be traced back to 1858, when [[Charles William Eliot]], a young graduate student who would later become Harvard's 21st and longest-serving president (1869–1909), bought red bandanas for his crew so they could more easily be distinguished by spectators at a regatta.

[[File:John Harvard statue at Harvard University.jpg|thumb|left|The [[John Harvard (clergyman)|John Harvard]] statue in [[Harvard Yard]] is occasionally a target of humorous decorations, such as the colorful [[Lei (Hawaii)|lei]] shown above.]]

Harvard has a friendly rivalry with the [[Massachusetts Institute of Technology]], which dates back to 1900 when a merger of the two schools was frequently discussed and at one point officially agreed upon (ultimately canceled by Massachusetts courts). Today, the two schools cooperate as much as they compete, with many joint conferences and programs, including the [[Harvard-MIT Division of Health Sciences and Technology]], the Broad Institute, the Harvard-MIT Data Center and formerly the [[Dibner Institute for the History of Science and Technology]]. In addition, students at the two schools can [[cross-registration|cross-register]] in undergraduate or graduate classes without any additional fees, for credits toward their own school's degrees.

===Organization===
Harvard is governed by a combination{{clarify|date=October 2011}} of its [[Harvard Board of Overseers|Board of Overseers]] and the [[President and Fellows of Harvard College]] (also known as the Harvard Corporation), which in turn appoints the [[President of Harvard University]]. There are 16,000 staff and faculty.&lt;ref&gt;Burlington Free Press, June 24, 2009, page 11B, &quot;&quot;Harvard to cut 275 jobs&quot; Associated Press&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:Massachusetts Hall, Harvard University.JPG|thumb|[[Massachusetts Hall, Harvard University|Massachusetts Hall]] (1720) is the oldest building in the Harvard campus.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.college.harvard.edu/icb/icb.do?keyword=k61161&amp;tabgroupid=icb.tabgroup85886|title=A Brief History of Harvard College|author=[[Harvard College]]|publisher=Harvard College|accessdate=2011-07-25}}&lt;/ref&gt;]]
[[File:harvard yard winter 2009j.JPG|thumb|Harvard Yard in the winter, with [[List of Harvard dormitories|freshman dorms]] in the background]]

Harvard has the following faculties:
* The [[Harvard Faculty of Arts and Sciences|Faculty of Arts and Sciences]], which is primarily responsible for instruction in:
** [[Harvard College]] (founded 1636)
** The [[Harvard Graduate School of Arts and Sciences|Graduate School of Arts and Sciences]] (organized 1872)
** The [[Harvard Division of Continuing Education]], including [[Harvard Summer School]] (1871) and [[Harvard Extension School]] (1910)
* [[Harvard Medical School]] (1782)
* [[Harvard School of Dental Medicine]] (1867)
* [[Harvard Divinity School]] (1816)
* [[Harvard Law School]] (1817)
* [[Harvard Business School]] (1908)
* [[Harvard Graduate School of Design|Graduate School of Design]] (1914)
* [[Harvard Graduate School of Education]] (1920)
* [[Harvard School of Public Health]] (1922)
* [[Harvard Kennedy School]] (1936)
* [[Radcliffe Institute for Advanced Study]] (1999)
* [[Harvard School of Engineering and Applied Sciences]] (2007)

===Endowment===
Harvard has the largest [[List of colleges and universities in the United States by endowment|university endowment]] in the world. At the end of June 2009, it was worth $25.7 billion, about 30% less than at the same time in 2008.&lt;ref name=&quot;NACUBO&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|url = http://www.boston.com/business/markets/articles/2010/01/28/harvard_endowment_leads_others_down/ |title= Harvard endowment leads others down |author= Beth Healy |date= January 28, 2010 |newspaper= The Boston Globe |accessdate=2 September 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; In December 2008, Harvard announced that its endowment had lost 22% (approximately $8 billion) from July to October 2008, necessitating budget cuts.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|work=Wall Street Journal|first=John|last=Hechinger|title=Harvard Hit by Loss as Crisis Spreads to Colleges|page=A1|date=2008-12-04}}&lt;/ref&gt; Later reports&lt;ref name=&quot;vanity&quot;&gt;{{cite web|last=Munk |first=Nina |url=http://www.vanityfair.com/politics/features/2009/08/harvard200908?printable=true&amp;currentPage=all |title=Nina Munk on Hard Times at Harvard |publisher=Vanityfair.com |date= |accessdate=2010-08-29}}&lt;/ref&gt; suggest the loss was actually more than double that figure,  a reduction of nearly 50% of its endowment in the first four months alone. Forbes in March 2009 estimated the loss to be in the range of $12 billion.&lt;ref name=&quot;ForbesUndEnd&quot;&gt;{{Cite news|author=Andrew M. Rosenfield |url=http://www.forbes.com/2009/03/03/harvard-university-investment-opinions-contributors_endowment_print.html |title=Understanding Endowments, Part I |publisher=Forbes.com |date= March 4, 2009|accessdate=2010-08-29}}&lt;/ref&gt; One of the most visible results of Harvard's attempt to re-balance its budget was their halting&lt;ref name=&quot;vanity&quot;/&gt; of construction of the $1.2 billion Allston Science Complex that had been scheduled to be completed by 2011, resulting in protests from local residents.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|accessdate=February 10, 2011 |url = http://www.thecrimson.com/article/2009/3/5/residents-protest-vacancies-in-allston-span/ |date = March 5, 2009 |title = Residents Protest Vacancies in Allston |newspaper = Harvard Crimson |author = Vidya B. Viswanathan and Peter F. Zhu}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Campus==
[[File:Harvard architects.png|thumb|upright|Map showing the architects and dates of construction for the buildings of the main campus near Harvard square, as of 2005. Information on other notable nearby buildings is also included.]]
Harvard's {{convert|210|acre|ha|adj=on}} main campus is centered on [[Harvard Yard]] in Cambridge, approximately {{convert|3.4|mi|km}} northwest of downtown [[Boston]] and extends into the surrounding [[Harvard Square]] neighborhood. Harvard Yard itself contains the central administrative offices and [[Harvard University Library|main libraries of the university]], academic buildings including [[Sever Hall]] and [[University Hall (Harvard University)|University Hall]], Memorial Church, and the majority of the [[List of Harvard dormitories|freshman dormitories]]. Sophomore, junior, and senior undergraduates live in twelve [[Harvard College#House system|residential Houses]], nine of which are south of Harvard Yard along or near the [[Charles River]]. The other three are located in a residential neighborhood half a mile northwest of the Yard at the [[Quadrangle (Harvard)|Quadrangle]] (commonly referred to as the Quad), which formerly housed [[Radcliffe College]] students until Radcliffe merged its residential system with Harvard. The [[Harvard (MBTA station)|Harvard MBTA station]] provides public transportation via bus service and the [[Red Line (MBTA)|Red Line subway]].

The Harvard Business School and many of the university's athletics facilities, including [[Harvard Stadium]], are located on a {{convert|359|acre|ha|adj=on}} campus opposite the Cambridge campus in [[Allston, Massachusetts|Allston]]. The [[John W. Weeks Bridge]] is a pedestrian bridge over the [[Charles River]] connecting both campuses. The [[Harvard Medical School]], [[Harvard School of Dental Medicine]], and the [[Harvard School of Public Health]] are located on a {{convert|22|acre|ha|adj=on}} campus in the [[Longwood Medical and Academic Area]] approximately {{convert|3.3|mi|km}} southwest of downtown Boston and {{convert|3.3|mi|km}} south of the Cambridge campus.&lt;ref name=&quot;Campus&quot;/&gt; A private shuttle bus connects the Longwood campus to the Cambridge campus via [[Massachusetts Avenue (Boston)|Massachusetts Avenue]] making stops in the [[Back Bay, Boston|Back Bay]] and at [[MIT]] as well.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.masco.org/transit/ptsM2.htm |title=M2 Cambridge Shuttle |publisher=MASCO |accessdate=August 28, 2010}}{{dead link|date=October 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Each residential house contains rooms for undergraduates, House masters, and resident tutors, as well as a dining hall, library, and various other student facilities. The facilities were made possible by a gift from [[Yale University]] alumnus [[Edward Harkness]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.exeter.edu./documents/Exeter_Bulletin/FA06_Men_Behind_the_Plan.pdf Biography] in the [http://www.exeter.edu/news_and_events/news_events_2086.aspx Exeter Bulletin]{{dead link|date=October 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:harvard memorial church winter 2009.JPG|thumb|left|upright|Memorial Church in the winter]]
Radcliffe Yard, formerly the center of the campus of Radcliffe College (and now home of the Radcliffe Institute), is adjacent to the [[Harvard Graduate School of Education|Graduate School of Education]] and the [[Cambridge Common]].

From 2006 - 2008, Harvard University reported on-campus crime statistics that included 48 forcible sex offenses, 10 robberies, 15 aggravated assaults, 750 burglaries, and 12 cases of motor vehicle theft.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.american-school-search.com/safety/harvard-university |title=Harvard University - Safety Report |publisher=American School Search |date= |accessdate=2010-06-30}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Satellite facilities===
Apart from its major Cambridge/Allston and Longwood campuses, Harvard owns and operates
[[Arnold Arboretum]], in the [[Jamaica Plain, Massachusetts|Jamaica Plain]] area of Boston;
the [[Dumbarton Oaks Research Library and Collection]], in [[Washington, D.C.]]; the [[Harvard Forest]] in [[Petersham, Massachusetts]]; and the Villa I Tatti research center&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.itatti.it/ |title=Villa I Tatti: The Harvard University Center for Italian Renaissance Studies |publisher=Itatti.it |date= |accessdate=2010-06-30}}&lt;/ref&gt; in [[Florence]] and the Harvard Shanghai Center in China.

===Major campus expansion===
Throughout the past several years, Harvard has purchased large tracts of land in [[Allston, Boston, Massachusetts|Allston]], a walk across the Charles River from Cambridge, with the intent of major expansion southward.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.allston.harvard.edu/ |title=Harvard University Allston Initiative Home Page |publisher=Allston.harvard.edu |date= |accessdate=2010-08-29}}&lt;/ref&gt; The university now owns approximately fifty percent more land in Allston than in Cambridge. Various proposals to connect the traditional Cambridge campus with the new Allston campus include new and enlarged bridges, a shuttle service and/or a [[tram]]. Ambitious plans also call for sinking part of [[Storrow Drive]] (at Harvard's expense) for replacement with park land and pedestrian access to the [[Charles River]], as well as the construction of bike paths, and an intently planned fabric of buildings throughout the Allston campus. The institution asserts that such expansion will benefit not only the school, but surrounding community, pointing to such features as the enhanced transit infrastructure, possible shuttles open to the public, and park space which will also be publicly accessible.

One of the foremost driving forces for Harvard's pending expansion is its goal of substantially increasing the scope and strength of its science and technology programs. The university plans to construct two 500,000 square foot (50,000 m²) research complexes in Allston, which would be home to several interdisciplinary programs, including the Harvard Stem Cell Institute and an enlarged [[Engineering]] department.

In addition, Harvard intends to relocate the [[Harvard Graduate School of Education]] and the [[Harvard School of Public Health]] to Allston. The university also plans to construct several new undergraduate and graduate student housing centers in Allston, and it is considering large-scale museums and performing arts complexes as well. Unfortunately the large drop in endowment has halted these plans for now.

===Sustainability===
In 2000, Harvard hired a full-time campus [[sustainability]] professional and launched the Harvard Green Campus Initiative,&lt;ref name=&quot;Harvard Green Campus Initiative&quot;&gt;{{cite web
 | title =Office for Sustainability: History
 | publisher =Harvard University
 | url = http://www.green.harvard.edu/ofs/history
 | accessdate = 2009-10-30 }}&lt;/ref&gt; since institutionalized as the Office for Sustainability (OFS).&lt;ref name=&quot;Office for Sustainability&quot;&gt;{{cite web
 | title =Office for Sustainability: Mission
 | publisher =Harvard University
 | url = http://www.green.harvard.edu/ofs/mission
 | accessdate = 2009-10-30 }}&lt;/ref&gt;
With a full-time staff of 25, dozens of student interns, and a $12 million Loan Fund for energy and water conservation projects, OFS is one of the most advanced campus sustainability programs in the country.&lt;ref name=&quot; America's Greenest Colleges&quot;&gt;{{Cite news
 | title =America's Greenest Colleges
 | publisher =Forbes Magazine
 | url = http://www.forbes.com/2008/05/02/college-harvard-uvm-biz-energy-cx_bw_0502greenu_slide_5.html?thisSpeed=15000
 | accessdate = 2008-05-21
| first=Brian
| last=Wingfield}}&lt;/ref&gt; Harvard was one of 27 schools to receive a grade of &quot;A-&quot; from the Sustainable Endowments Institute on its College Sustainability Report Card 2010, the highest grade awarded.&lt;ref name=&quot;Sustainable Endowments Institute Report Card&quot;&gt;{{cite web
 | title =College Sustainability Report Card 2010
 | publisher =Sustainable Endowments Institute
 | url =http://www.greenreportcard.org/report-card-2010/
 | accessdate = 2009-10-30 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Academics==
Harvard is a large, highly residential research university.&lt;ref name=&quot;Carnegie&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://classifications.carnegiefoundation.org/lookup_listings/view_institution.php?unit_id=166027 |title=Carnegie Classifications - Harvard University |publisher=The Carnegie Foundation for the Advancement of Teaching |accessdate=August 28, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; The university has been [[accreditation|accredited]] by the [[New England Association of Schools and Colleges]] since 1929.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://cihe.neasc.org/about_our_institutions/roster_of_institutions/ |publisher=Commission on Institutions of Higher Education, New England Association of Schools and Colleges |title=Roster of Institutions |accessdate=August 28, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; The university offers 46 undergraduate concentrations (majors),&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.handbook.fas.harvard.edu/icb/icb.do?keyword=k69286&amp;tabgroupid=icb.tabgroup106995 |title=Fields of Concentration |publisher=Handbook for Students, Harvard College |accessdate=August 28, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; 134 graduate degrees,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.gsas.harvard.edu/images/stories/pdfs/handbook.pdf |title=Degree Programs |publisher=Graduate School of Arts and Sciences Handbook |pages=28–30 |format=PDF |accessdate=August 28, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; and 32 professional degrees.&lt;ref name=&quot;Degrees&quot;/&gt; For the 2008–2009 academic year, Harvard granted 1,664 baccalaureate degrees, 400 masters degrees, 512 doctoral degrees, and 4,460 professional degrees.&lt;ref name=&quot;Degrees&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.provost.harvard.edu/institutional_research/Provost_-_FB2009_10_Sec02_Completions.pdf |title=Degrees Conferred by Program: Academic Year 2008–2009 |publisher=Institutional Research, Office of the Provost, Harvard University |accessdate=August 28, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The four year, full-time undergraduate program comprises a minority of enrollments at the university and emphasizes instruction with an &quot;arts &amp; sciences focus&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;Carnegie&quot;/&gt; Between 1978 and 2008, entering students were required to complete a &quot;Core Curriculum&quot; of seven classes outside of their concentration.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://isites.harvard.edu/icb/icb.do?keyword=k69286&amp;pageid=icb.page343094 |title=Academic Information - The Core Curricilum Requirement |publisher=Handbook for Students, Harvard College |accessdate=August 28, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; Since 2008, undergraduate students have been required to complete courses in eight General Education categories: Aesthetic and Interpretive Understanding, Culture and Belief, Empirical and Mathematical Reasoning, Ethical Reasoning, Science of Living Systems, Science of the Physical Universe, Societies of the World, and United States in the World.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://isites.harvard.edu/icb/icb.do?keyword=k69286&amp;pageid=icb.page343093 |title=Academic Information - Program in General Education Requirement |publisher=Handbook for Students, Harvard College |accessdate=August 28, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; Harvard offers a comprehensive doctoral graduate program and there is a high level of coexistence between graduate and undergraduate degrees.&lt;ref name=&quot;Carnegie&quot;/&gt; [[The Carnegie Foundation for the Advancement of Teaching]], ''[[The New York Times]]'', and some students have criticized Harvard for its reliance on [[teaching assistant|teaching fellows]] for some aspects of undergraduate education; they consider this to adversely affect the quality of education.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|last=Hicks |first=D. L. |url=http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9803E5D71130F933A1575AC0A9649C8B63 |title=Should Our Colleges Be Ranked? |date=September 20, 2002 | work=The New York Times}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last=Merrow |first=J. |year=2004 |url=http://www.carnegiefoundation.org/perspectives/perspectives2004.June.htm |title=Grade Inflation: It's Not Just an Issue for the Ivy League |work=Carnegie Perspectives |publisher=[[The Carnegie Foundation for the Advancement of Teaching]]}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Harvard's academic programs operate on a [[Semester#Collegiate calendars|semester calendar]] beginning in early September and ending in mid-May.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.registrar.fas.harvard.edu/fasro/common/calendar.jsp?cat=ugrad&amp;subcat=calendar |title=5 Year Academic Calendar |publisher=Registrar's Office, Harvard University |accessdate=August 28, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; Undergraduates typically take four half-courses per term and must maintain a four-course rate average to be considered full time.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://isites.harvard.edu/icb/icb.do?keyword=k69286&amp;pageid=icb.page343175 |title=Academic Information - Rate of Work |publisher=Handbook for Students, Harvard College |accessdate=August 28, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; In many concentrations, students can elect to pursue a basic program or a honors-eligible program requiring a senior thesis and/or advanced course work.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://isites.harvard.edu/icb/icb.do?keyword=k69286&amp;pageid=icb.page343095 |title=Academic Information - The Concentration Requirement |publisher=Handbook for Students, Harvard College |accessdate=August 28, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; Students graduating in the top 4-5% of the class are awarded degrees ''summa cum laude'', students in the next 15% of the class are awarded ''magna cum laude'', and the next 30% of the class are awarded ''cum laude''.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://isites.harvard.edu/icb/icb.do?keyword=k69286&amp;pageid=icb.page343182 |title=Academic Information - Requirements for Honors Degrees |publisher=Handbook for Students, Harvard College |accessdate=August 28, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; Harvard has chapters of academic honor societies such as [[Phi Beta Kappa]] and various committees and departments also award several hundred named prizes annually.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://isites.harvard.edu/icb/icb.do?keyword=k65741&amp;pageid=icb.page301813 |title=Prize Descriptions |publisher=Office of the Secretary, Harvard University |accessdate=August 28, 2010}}{{dead link|date=October 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; Harvard, along with other universities, has been accused of [[grade inflation]],&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|title=Doesn't Anybody Get a C Anymore? |last=Primack |first=Phil |date=October 5, 2008 |url=http://www.boston.com/bostonglobe/magazine/articles/2008/10/05/doesnt_anybody_get_a_c_anymore/ |newspaper=The Boston Globe}}&lt;/ref&gt; although there is evidence that the quality of the student body and its motivation have also increased.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|last=Kohn |first=A |url=http://www.alfiekohn.org/teaching/gi.htm |title=The Dangerous Myth of Grade Inflation |newspaper=[[The Chronicle of Higher Education]] |date=November 8, 2002}}&lt;/ref&gt; Harvard College reduced the number of students who receive [[Latin honors]] from 90% in 2004 to 60% in 2005. Moreover, the honors of &quot;John Harvard Scholar&quot; and &quot;Harvard College Scholar&quot; will now be given only to the top 5 percent and the next 5 percent of each class.&lt;ref&gt;No author given. (2003). [http://www.harvardmagazine.com/on-line/0103128.html Brevia]. [[Harvard Magazine]], January–February 2003.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Milzoff, R. M., Paley, A. R., &amp; Reed, B. J. (2001). [http://web.archive.org/web/20050204131059/http://www.thecrimson.com/fmarchives/fm_03_01_2001/article4A.html Grade Inflation is Real]. ''Fifteen Minutes'' March 1, 2001.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Bombardieri, M. &amp; Schweitzer, S. (2006). &quot;At Harvard, more concern for top grades.&quot; ''[[The Boston Globe]]'', February 12, 2006. p. B3 (Benedict Gross quotes, 23.7% A/25% A- figures, characterized as an &quot;all-time high.&quot;).&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[[Associated Press]]. (2004). [http://www.usatoday.com/news/education/2004-04-26-princeton-grades_x.htm Princeton becomes first to formally combat grade inflation]. [[USA Today]], April 26, 2004.&lt;/ref&gt;

Undergraduate tuition for the 2009–2010 school year was $33,696 and the total cost with fees, room, and board was $48,868.&lt;ref name=&quot;Tuition&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.provost.harvard.edu/institutional_research/Provost_-_FB2009_10_Sec03_Tuition.pdf |title=Tuition at Harvard Schools: FY1990 – FY2010 |publisher=Institutional Research, Office of the Provost, Harvard University |accessdate=August 28, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; Under financial aid guidelines adopted in 2007, parents in families with incomes of less than $60,000 will no longer be expected to contribute any money to the cost of attending Harvard for their children, including room and board. Families with incomes in the $60,000 to $80,000 range contribute an amount of only a few thousand dollars a year. In December 2007, Harvard announced that families earning between $120,000 and $180,000 will only have to pay up to 10% of their annual household income towards tuition.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|url=http://www.nytimes.com/2007/12/10/education/10cnd-harvard.html |title=Harvard Steps Up Financial Aid |newspaper=The New York Times |date=December 10, 2007 |first1=Sara |first2=Alan |last1=Rimer |last2=Finder}}&lt;/ref&gt; In 2009, Harvard offered grants totaling $414.1 million across all 11 divisions; $339.5 million came from institutional funds, $35.3 million from federal support, and $39.2 million from other outside support. Grants total 87.7% of Harvard's aid for undergraduate students, with aid also provided by loans (8.4%) and work-study (3.9%).&lt;ref name=&quot;Tuition&quot;/&gt;

===Rankings===
{{Infobox US university ranking
| ARWU_W = 1
| ARWU_N =1
| BW =3
| EC = 5
| FT =3
| GUR =6
| THES_W = 2
| THES_N = 2
| USNWR_NU = 1
| CGC_NU = 1
| Wamo_NU =6
| WSJ =14
| Forbes =6
| QS_W = 2
| URAP = 1
}}
Harvard's undergraduate program is ranked first among &quot;National Universities&quot; by ''[[U.S. News &amp; World Report]]''&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://colleges.usnews.rankingsandreviews.com/best-colleges/national-universities-rankings |title=National University Rankings - Best Colleges 2011 |publisher=[[US News and World Report]] |accessdate=August 28, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; and sixth by ''[[Forbes]]''.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|url=http://www.forbes.com/top-colleges/list/#p_2 |title=America's Best Colleges |work=Forbes.com |accessdate=August 3, 2011 |date=August 3, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; The university is ranked sixth nationally by ''[[The Washington Monthly]]''.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.washingtonmonthly.com/college_guide/rankings_2011/national_university_rank.php |title=National University Rankings 2011 |work=[[The Washington Monthly]] |accessdate=September 1, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Internationally, Harvard is tied with [[Stanford University]] for second in the [[Times Higher Education World University Rankings]] and is second in the [[QS World University Rankings]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.timeshighereducation.co.uk/world-university-rankings/2011-2012/top-400.html|publisher=[[Times Higher Education]]|title=Top 400 - World University Rankings 2011-2012|date=2011|accessdate=October 6, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.topuniversities.com/university-rankings/world-university-rankings/2011|title=Top 700|publisher=[[QS World University Rankings]]|date=2011|accessdate=October 6, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;BBC&quot;&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/education-11227693|title=Cambridge knocks Harvard off top of university table|author=Katherine Sellgren|date=September 8, 2010|accessdate=September 9, 2010|work=[[BBC News]]}}&lt;/ref&gt; When the two lists were published in partnership between 2004 and 2009 as the [[Times Higher Education-QS World University Rankings]], Harvard was ranked first each year.&lt;ref name=&quot;BBC&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.pbn.com/detail/45410.html|title=Brown slips in world university rankings|work=[[Providence Business News]]|date=October 9, 2009|accessdate=August 31, 2010|author=Ted Nesi}}&lt;/ref&gt;  Harvard is ranked first by the [[Academic Ranking of World Universities]] (ARWU), a position it has held since the first ARWU rankings were released in 2003.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.france24.com/en/20100813-harvard-tops-chinese-university-rankings-2|title=Harvard tops Chinese university rankings |work=[[Agence France-Presse]]|date=August 13, 2010|accessdate=August 31, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; In its individual subject tables, ARWU ranked Harvard first in natural sciences and mathematics,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.arwu.org/FieldSCI2010.jsp |title=Academic Ranking of World Universities in Natural Sciences and Mathematics - 2010|publisher=Shanghai Jiao Tong University |accessdate=August 28, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; life and agricultural sciences,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.arwu.org/FieldLIFE2010.jsp |title=Academic Ranking of World Universities in Life and Agriculture Sciences - 2010 |publisher=Shanghai Jiao Tong University |accessdate=August 28, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; clinical medicine and pharmacy,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.arwu.org/FieldMED2010.jsp |title=Academic Ranking of World Universities in Clinical Medicine and Pharmacy - 2010 |publisher=Shanghai Jiao Tong University |accessdate=August 28, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; social sciences,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.arwu.org/FieldSOC2010.jsp |title=Academic Ranking of World Universities in Social Sciences - 2010 |publisher=Shanghai Jiao Tong University |accessdate=August 28, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; and 42nd in engineering/technology and computer sciences.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.arwu.org/FieldENG2010.jsp |title=Academic Ranking of World Universities in Engineering/Technology and Computer Sciences - 2010 |publisher=Shanghai Jiao Tong University |accessdate=August 28, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; In individual fields in 2010, Harvard is ranked first in Physics and Economics/Business, second in Chemistry, third in Mathematics, and ninth in Computer Science in the world.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.arwu.org/Institution.jsp?param=Harvard%20University |title=&amp;#124;Harvard University |publisher=Arwu.org |date= |accessdate=2011-10-28}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In the 2009 [[QS Global 200 Business Schools Report]], Harvard was ranked first in North America.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.topmba.com/mba-rankings/global-200-business-schools-report/top-business-schools-2009/north-america |title=QS Global 200 Business Schools Report 2009 North America}}{{dead link|date=October 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In 2010, according to University Ranking by Academic Performance (URAP), Harvard is the best overall university in the world.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.urapcenter.org/2010|title=URAP - University Ranking by Academic Performance}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Research===
* [[Berkman Center for Internet &amp; Society]]
* [[Broad Institute|Broad Institute of MIT and Harvard]]
* Harvard Clinical Research Institute
* Harvard Institute of Economic Research
* [[Harvard Ukrainian Research Institute]]
* [[Institute for Quantitative Social Science]]&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://iq.harvard.edu/ |title=Harvard's home for social science research |author= |date= |work= |publisher=iq.harvard.edu |accessdate=28 September 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* Laboratory for Nanomedicine (at the Harvard Medical School-affiliated [[Brigham and Women's Hospital]])
* [[Radcliffe Institute for Advanced Studies]] (one of Harvard's 14 schools)
* [[Real Colegio Complutense]] at Harvard University, a Post-Doctoral Research Institute founded by Harvard University and [[Complutense University]] in 1990, jointly Chaired by the Presidents of both Universities.
* Schepens Eye Research Institute
* [[W. E. B. Du Bois Institute|W. E. B. Du Bois Institute for African and African-American Research]]
* [[Wyss Institute for Biologically Inspired Engineering]]
;Research centers attached to schools and departments
* Department of Psychology: [[Prosopagnosia]] Research Centers at Harvard University and University College London&lt;ref&gt;[http://faceblind.com/]{{Dead link|date=April 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* Graduate School of Design:&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.gsd.harvard.edu/research/index.html |title=Research &amp; Publications |publisher=Gsd.harvard.edu |date= |accessdate=2010-02-22}}{{dead link|date=October 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; Center for Alternative Futures, Joint Center for Housing Studies, Center for Technology &amp; the Environment
* Harvard Law School:&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.law.harvard.edu/programs/ |title=Research Programs and Centers |publisher=Law.harvard.edu |date= |accessdate=2010-02-22}}&lt;/ref&gt; Charles Hamilton Houston Institute for Race and Justice, Institute for Global Law &amp; Policy (former European Law Research Center), John M. Olin Center of Law, Economics and Business
;Independent organizations affiliated to the university
* [[The Forsyth Institute]]

===Libraries and museums===
[[File:widener library 2009.JPG|thumb|The [[Widener Library|Harry Elkins Widener]] Memorial Library]]
The [[Harvard University Library]] System is centered in [[Widener Library]] in [[Harvard Yard]] and comprises over 80 individual libraries holding some 15 million volumes.&lt;!--what about other-than-books?--&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;lib&quot;&gt;See the [http://hul.harvard.edu/hgproject/faq.html FAQ on the Harvard-Google partnership].&lt;/ref&gt; According to the [[American Library Association]], this makes it the largest academic library in the United States, and one of the largest in the world.&lt;ref name=&quot;largestlibs&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.ala.org/ala/professionalresources/libfactsheets/alalibraryfactsheet22.cfm|title=The Nation's Largest Libraries: A Listing By Volumes Held|date=2009-05|accessdate=2009-08-19|publisher=American Library Association}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Cabot Science Library, Lamont Library, and Widener Library are three of the most popular libraries for undergraduates to use, with easy access and central locations. There are rare books, [[manuscripts]] and other special collections throughout Harvard's libraries;&lt;ref name=&quot;specialcolls&quot;&gt;See the library portal listing of archives and special collections [http://lib.harvard.edu/archives/index.html Harvard Libraries : Archives and Special Collections Listed Alphabetically by Name].&lt;/ref&gt; Houghton Library, the Arthur and Elizabeth Schlesinger Library on the History of Women in America, and the Harvard University Archives consist principally of rare and unique materials. America's oldest collection of maps, gazetteers, and atlases both old and new is stored in Pusey Library and open to the public. The largest collection of [[East Asia|East-Asian]] language material outside of East Asia is held in the [[Harvard-Yenching Library]].

[[Image:University Museum at Harvard 001.jpg|thumb|upright|University Museum]]

[[Image:Henry Moore sculpture, Harvard University.jpg|thumb|[[Henry Moore]]'s sculpture ''Large Four Piece Reclining Figure'' near Lamont Library]]
Harvard operates several arts, cultural, and scientific museums:
* '''The [[Carpenter Center for the Visual Arts]]''', designed by [[Le Corbusier]], is home to the University's film archive and the department of Visual and Environmental Studies.
* The '''[[Harvard Art Museums]]''', including:
** '''The [[Arthur M. Sackler Museum]]''', which includes ancient, Asian, Islamic and later Indian art
** '''The [[Busch-Reisinger Museum]]''', formerly the Germanic Museum, covers central and northern European art.
** '''The [[Fogg Museum of Art]]''', with galleries featuring history of Western art from the Middle Ages to the present. Particular strengths are in Italian [[Early Renaissance painting|early Renaissance]], British [[pre-Raphaelite]], and 19th century French art
* The '''[[Harvard Museum of Natural History]]''' complex, including:
** '''The [[Harvard Mineralogical Museum]]'''
** '''The [[Harvard University Herbaria]]''', which contains the famous [[Leopold and Rudolf Blaschka|Blaschka]] [[Glass Flowers]] exhibit
** '''The [[Museum of Comparative Zoology]]'''
* '''The [[Peabody Museum of Archaeology and Ethnology]]''', specializing in the cultural history and civilizations of the Western Hemisphere
* '''The [[Semitic Museum]]'''.

==Students==
In the last six years, [http://www.provost.harvard.edu/institutional_research/Provost_-_Harvard_Fact_Book_2009-10_FINAL_new.pdf Harvard's student population] ranged between 19,000 and 21,000, across all programs. Harvard enrolled 6,655 students in undergraduate programs, 3,738 students in graduate programs, and 10,722 students in professional programs.&lt;ref name=&quot;Head count&quot;/&gt; The undergraduate population is 51% female, the graduate population is 48% female, and the professional population is 49% female.&lt;ref name=&quot;Head count&quot;/&gt;

Undergraduate admission to Harvard is characterized by the Carnegie Foundation as &quot;more selective, lower transfer-in&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;Carnegie&quot;/&gt; Harvard College received 27,462 applications for admission to the Class of 2013, 2,175 were admitted (7.9%), and 1,658 enrolled (76.2%).&lt;ref name=&quot;CDS&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.provost.harvard.edu/institutional_research/Provost_-_CDS2008_2009_Harvard_for_Web_Clean.pdf |format=PDF |title=Common Data Set 2008–09 |publisher=Institutional Research, Office of the Provost, Harvard University |accessdate=August 28, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; The [[interquartile range]] on the [[SAT]] was 2080–2370 and 95% of first year students graduated in the top tenth of their high school class.&lt;ref name=&quot;CDS&quot;/&gt; Harvard also enrolled 266 [[National Merit Scholar]]s, the most in the nation.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://chronicle.com/article/Chart-Colleges-With-the-Mo/124012/ |title=Colleges With the Most Freshman Merit Scholars, 2009 |publisher=The Chronicle of Higher Education |accessdate=August 28, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; 88% of students graduate within 4 years and 98% graduate within 6 years.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://members.ucan-network.org/harvard |title=U-CAN: Harvard University |publisher=University and College Accountability Network |accessdate=August 28, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;

{| style=&quot;text-align:center; font-size:85%; margin-left:2em; margin:auto;&quot; class=&quot;wikitable&quot;
|+ ''Demographics of student body''&lt;ref name=&quot;Head count&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.provost.harvard.edu/institutional_research/Provost_-_FB2009_10_Sec02_Enrollments.pdf |title=Degree Student Head Count: Fall 2009 |publisher=Office of the Provost, Harvard University |accessdate=August 27, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;See [[Demographics of the United States]] for references.&lt;/ref&gt;
! !! Undergraduate !! Graduate !! Professional !! U.S. Census
|-
! Black/Non-Hispanic
| 8% || 3% || 6% || 12.1%
|-
! Asian/Pacific Islander
| 17% || 9% || 12% || 4.3%
|-
! White/Non-Hispanic
| 42% || 42% || 43% || 65.8%
|-
! Hispanic
| 7% || 3% || 5% || 14.5%
|-
! Native American
| 1% || 0.2% || 0.6% || 0.9%
|-
! International Students
| 11% || 33% || 22% || N/A
|}
Harvard College accepted 6.9% of applicants for the class of 2014, a record low for the school's entire history.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.usnews.com/blogs/paper-trail/2009/03/31/top-colleges-see-record-low-acceptance-rates.html |title=Top Colleges See Record-Low Acceptance Rates - The Paper Trail |publisher=usnews.com |date=  |accessdate=2010-04-03}}&lt;/ref&gt; The number of acceptances was lower for the class of 2013 partially because the university anticipated increased rates of enrollment after announcing a large increase in financial aid in 2008.{{Citation needed|date=August 2010}} Harvard College ended its early admissions program in 2007 as the program was believed to disadvantage low-income and under-represented minority applicants applying to selective universities.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|url=http://www.nytimes.com/2006/09/12/education/12harvard.html |title=Harvard Ends Early Admission |newspaper=[[The New York Times]] |first1=Alan |last1=Finder |first2=Karen W. |last2=Arenson |date=September 12, 2006}}&lt;/ref&gt; However, undergraduate admissions office's [[legacy preferences|preference for children of alumni]] policies have been the subject of scrutiny and debate as it primarily aids whites and the wealthy.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|url=http://online.wsj.com/public/resources/documents/golden3.htm |title=Admissions Preferences Given to Alumni Children Draws Fire |last=Golden |first=Daniel |date=January 15, 2003 |newspaper=The Wall Street Journal}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|title=The Price of Admission: How America's Ruling Class Buys Its Way into Elite Colleges — and Who Gets Left Outside the Gates |last=Golden |first=Daniel |year=2006 |isbn=1400097967}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Athletics==
{{Main|Harvard Crimson}}
[[File:Harvard stadium 2009h.JPG|thumb|left|[[Harvard Stadium]], home of [[Harvard Crimson]] and the [[Boston Cannons]]]]
Harvard's athletic rivalry with [[Yale University|Yale]] is intense in every sport in which they meet, coming to a climax each fall in their annual [[football (American)|football]] meeting, which dates back to 1875 and is usually called simply &quot;[[Harvard-Yale football games (The Game)|The Game]]&quot;. While Harvard's football team is no longer one of the country's best as it often was a century ago during football's early days (it won the [[Rose Bowl Game|Rose Bowl]] in 1920), both it and Yale have influenced the way the game is played. In 1903, [[Harvard Stadium]] introduced a new era into football with the first-ever permanent reinforced concrete stadium of its kind in the country. The stadium's structure actually played a role in the evolution of the college game. Seeking to reduce the alarming number of deaths and serious injuries in the sport, the Father of Football, [[Walter Camp]] (former captain of the Yale football team), suggested widening the field to open up the game. But the state-of-the-art Harvard Stadium was too narrow to accommodate a wider playing surface. So, other steps had to be taken. Camp would instead support revolutionary new rules for the 1906 season. These included legalizing the [[forward pass]], perhaps the most significant rule change in the sport's history.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.newsdial.com/sports/football/football-history.html |title=History of American Football |publisher=Newsdial.com |date= |accessdate=2010-08-29}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Nelson, David M., ''Anatomy of a Game: Football, the Rules, and the Men Who Made the Game'', 1994, pp. 127–128&lt;/ref&gt;

Harvard has several athletic facilities, such as the [[Lavietes Pavilion]], a multi-purpose arena and home to the Harvard basketball teams. The Malkin Athletic Center, known as the &quot;MAC&quot;, serves both as the university's primary recreation facility and as a satellite location for several varsity sports. The five story building includes two cardio rooms, an [[Olympic-size swimming pool]], a smaller pool for aquaerobics and other activities, a mezzanine, where all types of classes are held at all hours of the day, and an indoor cycling studio, three weight rooms, and a three-court gym floor to play basketball. The MAC also offers personal trainers and specialty classes. The MAC is also home to Harvard volleyball, fencing, and wrestling. The offices of several of the school's varsity coaches are also in the MAC.

[[Weld Boathouse]] and Newell Boathouse house the women's and men's rowing teams, respectively. The men's crew also uses the Red Top complex in Ledyard, Connecticut, as their training camp for the annual [[Harvard-Yale Regatta]]. The Bright Hockey Center hosts the Harvard hockey teams, and the Murr Center serves both as a home for Harvard's squash and tennis teams as well as a strength and conditioning center for all athletic sports.

As of 2006, there were 41 Division I intercollegiate [[varsity team|varsity]] sports teams for women and men at Harvard, more than at any other NCAA Division I college in the country. As with other Ivy League universities, Harvard does not offer [[athletic scholarships]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|author=Harvard Office of News and Public Affairs |url=http://www.hno.harvard.edu/guide/students/stu6.html |title=The Harvard Guide: Financial Aid at Harvard |publisher=Web.archive.org |date=2006-09-02 |accessdate=2010-08-29 |archiveurl = http://web.archive.org/web/20060902182731/http://www.hno.harvard.edu/guide/students/stu6.html |archivedate = 2006-09-02}}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:harvard crimsons v brown 2009.JPG|thumb|Harvard v [[Brown Bears|Brown]], September 25, 2009]]
Older than ''The Game'' by 23 years, the [[Harvard-Yale Regatta]] was the original source of the athletic rivalry between the two schools. It is held annually in June on the Thames river in eastern Connecticut. The Harvard crew is typically considered to be one of the top teams in the country in [[rowing (sport)|rowing]]. Today, Harvard fields top teams in several other sports, such as the [[Harvard Crimson men's ice hockey]] team (with a strong rivalry against [[Cornell University|Cornell]]), [[squash (sport)|squash]], and even recently won NCAA titles in Men's and Women's [[Fencing]]. Harvard also won the [[Intercollegiate Sailing Association National Championships]] in 2003.

Harvard's men's ice hockey team won the school's first NCAA Championship in any team sport in 1989. Harvard was also the first Ivy League institution to win a NCAA championship title in a women's sport when its women's lacrosse team won the NCAA Championship in 1990.

''[[Harvard Undergraduate Television]]'' has footage from historical games and athletic events including the 2005 pep-rally before the Harvard-Yale Game. Harvard's official athletics website has more comprehensive information about Harvard's athletic facilities.

===Song===
Harvard has several fight songs, the most played of which, especially at football, are &quot;[[Ten Thousand Men of Harvard]]&quot; and &quot;[[Harvardiana]].&quot; While &quot;[[Fair Harvard]]&quot; is actually the [[alma mater]], &quot;Ten Thousand Men&quot; is better known outside the university. The [[Harvard University Band]] performs these fight songs, and other cheers, at football and hockey games. These were parodied by Harvard alumnus [[Tom Lehrer]] in his song &quot;[[Fight Fiercely, Harvard]],&quot; which he composed while an undergraduate.

==Notable people==
===Faculty and staff===
{{Expand section|date=August 2010}}
Prominent conservative and prominent liberal voices are among the faculty of the various schools, such as [[Martin Feldstein]], [[Harvey Mansfield]], [[Greg Mankiw]], Baroness Shirley Williams, and [[Alan Dershowitz]]. [[Leftists]] like [[Michael Walzer]] and Stephen Thernstrom and [[libertarianism|libertarians]] such as [[Robert Nozick]] have in the past graced its faculty. Between 1964 and 2009, a total of 38 faculty and staff members affiliated with Harvard or its teaching hospitals were awarded Nobel Prizes (17 during the last quarter century, 6 the last 25 years).&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|last=Nobel Foundation|title=Nobel laureates and universities|year=2009|url=http://nobelprize.org/nobel_prizes/lists/universities.html}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Alumni===
{{See also|List of Harvard University people|Notable non-graduate alumni of Harvard}}

Among the best-known people who have attended Harvard University are American political leaders [[John Hancock]], [[John Adams]], [[John Quincy Adams]], [[Rutherford B. Hayes]], [[Theodore Roosevelt]], [[Franklin Roosevelt]], [[John F. Kennedy]], [[Al Gore]], [[George W. Bush]] and [[Barack Obama]]; Canadian Governor General [[David Lloyd Johnston]], Canadian Prime Ministers [[Mackenzie King]] and [[Pierre Trudeau]], and Canadian political leader [[Michael Ignatieff]]; Secretary of Housing and Urban Development [[Shaun Donovan]]; religious leader, businessman &amp; philanthropist [[Aga Khan IV]]; businessman &amp; philanthropist [[Bill Gates]]; philanthropist [[Huntington Hartford]];  Mexican Presidents [[Felipe Calderón]],&lt;ref name=&quot;Harvard Alum apparent new president of Mexico&quot;&gt;{{Cite news| title = Alum is Apparent Winner of Presidential Election in Mexico| url = http://www.hks.harvard.edu/news-events/news/articles/alum-is-apparent-winner-of-presidential-election-in-mexico |author=Doug Gavel |publisher = Harvard KSG| date = July 7, 2006| accessdate = July 25, 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Carlos Salinas de Gortari]] and [[Miguel de la Madrid]]; Chilean President [[Sebastian Piñera]]; Colombian President [[Juan Manuel Santos]]; Costa Rican President [[José María Figueres]]; Businessman and Financier [[Scott Mead]]; Taiwanese President [[Ma Ying-jeou]]; Israeli Prime Minister [[Benjamin Netanyahu]] and Israeli Supreme Court President [[Aharon Barak]]; Peruvian President [[Alejandro Toledo]]; Albanian Prime Minister [[Fan S. Noli]]; UN Secretary General [[Ban Ki-moon]]; philosopher [[Henry David Thoreau]]; authors [[Ralph Waldo Emerson]] and [[William S. Burroughs]]; educator [[Harlan Hanson]]; poets [[Wallace Stevens]], [[T. S. Eliot]] and [[E. E. Cummings]]; conductor [[Leonard Bernstein]]; cellist [[Yo Yo Ma]]; comedian and television show host and writer [[Conan O'Brien]]; actors [[Fred Gwynne]], [[Jack Lemmon]], [[Natalie Portman]], [[Mira Sorvino]], [[Ashley Judd]], [[Tatyana Ali]], [[Elisabeth Shue]], [[Rashida Jones]], [[Scottie Thompson]], [[Hill Harper]], [[Matt Damon]] and [[Tommy Lee Jones]]; film directors [[Darren Aronofsky]], [[Mira Nair]], [[Whit Stillman]], and [[Terrence Malick]]; television executive [[Brian Graden]]; architect [[Philip Johnson]]; musicians [[Rivers Cuomo]], [[Tom Morello]], and [[Gram Parsons]]; musician, producer and composer [[Ryan Leslie]]; Facebook creator [[Mark Zuckerberg]]; unabomber [[Ted Kaczynski]]; programmer and activist [[Richard Stallman]]; NFL quarterback [[Ryan Fitzpatrick]]; and civil rights leader [[W. E. B. Du Bois]], Sachin H Jain.

Among its most famous current faculty members are biologist [[E. O. Wilson]], cognitive scientist [[Steven Pinker]], physicists [[Lisa Randall]] and [[Roy Glauber]], chemists [[Elias Corey]], [[Dudley R. Herschbach]] and [[George M. Whitesides]], Shakespeare scholar [[Stephen Greenblatt]], writer [[Louis Menand]], critic [[Helen Vendler]], historians [[Henry Louis Gates, Jr.]] and [[Niall Ferguson]], economists [[Amartya Sen]], [[N. Gregory Mankiw]], [[Robert Barro]], [[Stephen A. Marglin]], [[Don M. Wilson III]] and [[Martin Feldstein]], political philosophers [[Harvey Mansfield]] and [[Michael Sandel]], political scientists [[Robert Putnam]], [[Joseph Nye]], and [[Stanley Hoffmann]], scholar/composers [[Robert D. Levin|Robert Levin]] and [[Bernard Rands]].

Seventy-five [[Nobel Prize]] winners are affiliated with the university. Since 1974, 19 [[Nobel Prize]] winners and 15 winners of the American literary award, the [[Pulitzer Prize]], have served on the Harvard faculty.

Professors Dr. Richard Alpert, later known as [[Ram Dass]], and Dr. [[Timothy Leary]] were fired from Harvard in May 1963. Popular opinion attributes their discharge to their activism involving psychedelics, and the popularization and dispensation of [[psilocybin]] to students.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|last=Russin|first=J. S.|coauthors=Weill, A. T.|date=1963, May 28|title=The Crimson takes Leary, Alpert to task. (Editorial)|journal=Harvard Crimson| url=http://www.thecrimson.com/article.aspx?ref=495775|ref=harv}} (He [Alpert] and his associate, Timothy F. Leary, have been as much propagandists for the drug experience as investigators of it. They have violated the one condition Harvard placed upon their work: that they not use undergraduates as subjects for drug experiments.)&lt;/ref&gt;

==In fiction and popular culture==
The perception of Harvard as a center of either elite achievement, or elitist privilege,{{cn|date=November 2011}}&lt;!-- cn for both aspects, possibly separate but better one discussing both --&gt;
has made it a frequent literary backdrop.

===In literature===

* ''[[The Accidental Billionaires]]'' by [[Ben Mezrich]] is a narrative account of Facebook's founding set partially at Harvard
* ''Hacking Harvard'' is novel by [[Robin Wasserman]], a Harvard University alumna.
*In ''[[The Handmaid's Tale]]'', [[Margaret Atwood]]'s [[post-apocalyptic]] novel, much of the action takes place in Cambridge, with vaguely recognizable Harvard landmarks occasionally making their way into the narrator's place descriptions.
* [[Erich Segal]]'s ''[[Love Story (1970 film)|Love Story]]'' (1970), which concerns a romance between a wealthy hockey player ([[Ryan O'Neal]]) and a brilliant Radcliffe student of modest means ([[Ali MacGraw]]),&lt;ref&gt;Rogers, M. F. (1991). ''Novels, Novelists, and Readers: Toward a Phenomenological Sociology of Literature''. SUNY Press, ISBN 0-7914-0603-2.&lt;/ref&gt; is screened annually for incoming freshmen.{{citation needed|date=October 2011}} Segal's ''[[The Class (Erich Segal novel)|The Class]]'' (1985) and ''[[Doctors (novel)|Doctors]]'' (1988) are also set at Harvard.
*''[[The Paper Chase (novel)|The Paper Chase]]'' by [[John Jay Osborn, Jr.]], a 1970 novel adapted for a film and a television series.
*''[[The Physick Book of Deliverance Dane]]'', a 2009 bestselling novel by [[Katherine Howe]], prominently features the university and several of its buildings .
* ''[[Prozac Nation]]'' is an autobiography by Harvard College graduate [[Elizabeth Wurtzel]]
*''The Second Happiest Day'' (1953) by &quot;John Phillips&quot; (John P. Marquand, Jr.) depicts the Harvard of the World War II generation.
* ''[[The Sound and the Fury]]'', by [[William Faulkner]], features Quentin Compson's experiences at Harvard.
*''[[The Women's Room]]'', by [[Marilyn French]], largely features protagonist Mira's experiences at Harvard
* [[Pamela Thomas-Graham]]'s series of mystery novels (''Blue Blood'', ''Orange Crushed'', and ''A Darker Shade Of Crimson''), protagonist Nikki Chase is an African-American Harvard economics professor.
*[[Cecilia Tan]]'s romance novel series, commonly known as the &quot;Magic University series&quot; and including the books ''The Siren and the Sword'' and ''The Tower and the Tears'', is set at the magical university hidden inside Harvard known as &quot;Veritas&quot;.

===Onscreen===
''Because Harvard generally forbids filming on its property, most scenes set at Harvard (especially indoor shots, but excepting aerial footage and shots of public areas such as Harvard Square) are in fact shot elsewhere.&lt;ref&gt;Nathaniel L. Schwartz,[http://www.thecrimson.harvard.edu/article/1999/9/21/university-hollywood-relationship-not-always-a/ &quot;University, Hollywood Relationship Not Always a 'Love Story'&quot;], ''[[Harvard Crimson]]'', 21 September 1999.&lt;/ref&gt;''

* ''[[The Great Debaters]]''
* ''[[Good Will Hunting]]''
* ''[[Harvard Man]]''
* ''[[How High]]''
*''[[Ivory Tower (Harvard Undergraduate Television)|Ivory Tower]]'' - a student-produced [[Harvard Undergraduate Television]] show&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.ivorytowersoap.com/ |title=The Ivory Tower |publisher=Ivorytowersoap.com |date= |accessdate=2010-08-29}}&lt;/ref&gt; about fictional Harvard students.
* ''[[Legally Blonde]]''
* ''[[The Paper Chase (film)|The Paper Chase]]'' (1973 film) and ''[[The Paper Chase (TV series)|The Paper Chase]]'' (1978–79, 1983–86 TV series)
* ''[[The Social Network]]''
* ''[[Soul Man (film)|Soul Man]]'' (film)
* ''[[Stealing Harvard]]''
* ''[[With Honors (film)|With Honors]]''

==See also==
{{Portal box|Boston|University}}
* [[Academic regalia of Harvard University]]
* [[Harvard University Police Department]]
* [[Outline of Harvard University]]
* [[Secret Court of 1920]]

==References==
{{Reflist|30em}}

==Further reading==
{{refbegin}}
* Abelmann, Walter H., ed. ''The Harvard-MIT Division of Health Sciences and Technology: The First 25 Years, 1970–1995'' (2004). 346 pp.
* Beecher, Henry K. and Altschule, Mark D. ''Medicine at Harvard: The First 300 Years'' (1977). 569 pp.
* Bentinck-Smith, William, ed. ''The Harvard Book: Selections from Three Centuries'' (2d ed.1982). 499 pp.
* Bethell, John T.; Hunt, Richard M.; and Shenton, Robert. ''Harvard A to Z'' (2004). 396 pp. [http://www.amazon.com/dp/0674012887 excerpt and text search]
* Bethell, John T. ''Harvard Observed: An Illustrated History of the University in the Twentieth Century'', Harvard University Press, 1998, ISBN 0-674-37733-8
* Bunting, Bainbridge. ''Harvard: An Architectural History'' (1985). 350 pp.
* Carpenter, Kenneth E. ''The First 350 Years of the Harvard University Library: Description of an Exhibition'' (1986). 216 pp.
* Cuno, James et al. ''Harvard's Art Museums: 100 Years of Collecting'' (1996). 364 pp.
* Elliott, Clark A. and Rossiter, Margaret W., eds. ''Science at Harvard University: Historical Perspectives'' (1992). 380 pp.
* Hall, Max. ''Harvard University Press: A History'' (1986). 257 pp.
* Hay, Ida. ''Science in the Pleasure Ground: A History of the Arnold Arboretum'' (1995). 349 pp.
* Hoerr, John, ''We Can't Eat Prestige: The Women Who Organized Harvard;'' [[Temple University Press]], 1997, ISBN 1-56639-535-6
* Howells, Dorothy Elia. ''A Century to Celebrate: Radcliffe College, 1879–1979'' (1978). 152 pp.
* Keller, Morton, and Phyllis Keller. ''Making Harvard Modern: The Rise of America's University'' (2001), major history covers 1933 to 2002 [http://www.questia.com/read/106186126?title=Making%20Harvard%20Modern%3a%20%20The%20Rise%20of%20America%27s%20University online edition]
* [[Harry R. Lewis|Lewis, Harry R.]] ''Excellence Without a Soul: How a Great University Forgot Education'' (2006) ISBN 1586483935
* Morison, Samuel Eliot. ''Three Centuries of Harvard, 1636–1936'' (1986) 512pp; [http://books.google.com/books?id=ZUUf7ssp1u4C&amp;dq=intitle:harvard+inauthor:morison&amp;lr=&amp;as_drrb_is=q&amp;as_minm_is=0&amp;as_miny_is=&amp;as_maxm_is=0&amp;as_maxy_is=&amp;as_brr=0 excerpt and text search]
* Powell, Arthur G. ''The Uncertain Profession: Harvard and the Search for Educational Authority'' (1980). 341 pp.
* Reid, Robert. ''Year One: An Intimate Look inside Harvard Business School'' (1994). 331 pp.
* Rosovsky, Nitza. ''The Jewish Experience at Harvard and Radcliffe'' (1986). 108 pp.
* Seligman, Joel. ''The High Citadel: The Influence of Harvard Law School'' (1978). 262 pp.
* Sollors, Werner; Titcomb, Caldwell; and Underwood, Thomas A., eds. ''Blacks at Harvard: A Documentary History of African-American Experience at Harvard and Radcliffe'' (1993). 548 pp.
* &lt;span id=&quot;Trumpbour&quot;&gt;Trumpbour, John, ed.&lt;/span&gt;, ''How Harvard Rules. Reason in the Service of Empire'', Boston: South End Press, 1989, ISBN 0-89608-283-0
* Ulrich, Laurel Thatcher, ed. ''Yards and Gates: Gender in Harvard and Radcliffe History'' (2004). 337 pp.
* Winsor, Mary P. ''Reading the Shape of Nature: Comparative Zoology at the Agassiz Museum'' (1991). 324 pp.
* Wright, Conrad Edick. ''Revolutionary Generation: Harvard Men and the Consequences of Independence'' (2005). 298 pp.
{{refend}}

==External links==
{{EB1922 Poster}}
{{Commons-inline}}
* {{Official website|http://www.harvard.edu/}}
* [http://m.harvard.edu/home/ Harvard mobile site]
{{Coord|42|22|28|N|71|07|01|W|region:US_type:edu|display=title}}
{{Harvard}}
{{Ivy League}}
{{Template group
|title = Links to related articles
|titlestyle = background:#FFFFFF;color:#991111;border:1px solid #991111;
|list =
{{Colonial Colleges}}
{{Ivy League Presidents}}
{{Colleges and universities in metropolitan Boston}}
&lt;!-- main campus in --&gt;
&lt;!-- business and medical campuses in --&gt;
{{Association of American Universities}}
{{Universities Research Association}}
{{ECAC Hockey League}}
{{Eastern Association of Rowing Colleges}}
{{Eastern Intercollegiate Volleyball Association}}
{{Massachusetts Sports}}
|state =autocollapse
}}

[[Category:Harvard University| ]]
[[Category:1636 establishments in the Thirteen Colonies]]
[[Category:Association of American Universities]]
[[Category:Colonial Colleges]]
[[Category:Educational institutions established in the 1630s]]
[[Category:Ivy League]]
[[Category:National Association of Independent Colleges and Universities members]]
[[Category:New England Association of Schools and Colleges]]
[[Category:Association of Independent Colleges and Universities in Massachusetts members]]
[[Category:Universities and colleges in Cambridge, Massachusetts]]
[[Category:Universities and colleges in Massachusetts]]

[[als:Harvard-Universität]]
[[ar:جامعة هارفارد]]
[[ast:Universidá de Harvard]]
[[az:Harvard Universiteti]]
[[bn:হার্ভার্ড বিশ্ববিদ্যালয়]]
[[zh-min-nan:Harvard Tāi-ha̍k]]
[[be:Гарвардскі ўніверсітэт]]
[[be-x-old:Гарвардзкі ўнівэрсытэт]]
[[br:Skol-veur Harvard]]
[[bg:Харвардски университет]]
[[ca:Universitat de Harvard]]
[[cv:Харвăрт Университечĕ]]
[[cs:Harvardova univerzita]]
[[cy:Prifysgol Harvard]]
[[da:Harvard]]
[[de:Harvard University]]
[[et:Harvardi ülikool]]
[[el:Πανεπιστήμιο Χάρβαρντ]]
[[es:Universidad de Harvard]]
[[eo:Universitato Harvard]]
[[eu:Harvard Unibertsitatea]]
[[fa:دانشگاه هاروارد]]
[[fo:Harvard University]]
[[fr:Université Harvard]]
[[ga:Ollscoil Harvard]]
[[gd:Oilthigh Harvard]]
[[gl:Universidade Harvard]]
[[hak:Harvard Thai-ho̍k]]
[[ko:하버드 대학교]]
[[hi:हार्वर्ड विश्वविद्यालय]]
[[hr:Sveučilište Harvard]]
[[id:Universitas Harvard]]
[[is:Harvard-háskóli]]
[[it:Università di Harvard]]
[[he:אוניברסיטת הרווארד]]
[[jv:Universitas Harvard]]
[[kn:ಹಾರ್ವರ್ಡ್ ವಿಶ್ವವಿದ್ಯಾನಿಲಯ]]
[[ka:ჰარვარდის უნივერსიტეტი]]
[[sw:Chuo Kikuu cha Harvard]]
[[ku:Zanîngeha Harvardê]]
[[la:Universitas Harvardiana]]
[[lv:Hārvarda universitāte]]
[[lb:Harvard Universitéit]]
[[lt:Harvardo universitetas]]
[[hu:Harvard Egyetem]]
[[mk:Харвард]]
[[mr:हार्वर्ड विद्यापीठ]]
[[ms:Harvard University]]
[[my:ဟားဗတ် တက္ကသိုလ်]]
[[nl:Harvard-universiteit]]
[[ja:ハーバード大学]]
[[no:Harvard University]]
[[oc:Universitat de Harvard]]
[[pnb:ہارورڈ یونیورسٹی]]
[[pl:Harvard University]]
[[pt:Universidade Harvard]]
[[ro:Universitatea Harvard]]
[[qu:Harvard Yachay Suntur]]
[[ru:Гарвардский университет]]
[[sa:हार्वर्ड् विश्वविद्यालयः]]
[[sq:Harvard]]
[[scn:Univirsitati di Harvard]]
[[simple:Harvard University]]
[[sk:Harvardova univerzita]]
[[sl:Univerza Harvard]]
[[sr:Харвард]]
[[sh:Univerzitet Harvard]]
[[fi:Harvardin yliopisto]]
[[sv:Harvard University]]
[[ta:ஹார்வர்டு பல்கலைக்கழகம்]]
[[tt:Harvard universitetı]]
[[te:హార్వర్డ్ విశ్వవిద్యాలయం]]
[[th:มหาวิทยาลัยฮาร์วาร์ด]]
[[tr:Harvard Üniversitesi]]
[[uk:Гарвардський університет]]
[[ur:جامعہ ہارورڈ]]
[[ug:خارۋارد ئۇنىۋېرسىتېتى]]
[[vi:Đại học Harvard]]
[[yi:הארווארד אוניווערסיטעט]]
[[yo:Yunifásítì Harvard]]
[[zh:哈佛大学]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
