<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="184605" ns="0" title="Radford University"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Infobox university
|name            = Radford University
|image_name      = Radford University seal.png
|image_size      = 146px
|established     = 1910 
|tuition &amp; board = $13,776/year in-state
|type            = [[Public university]] 
|endowment       = US $27.4 million&lt;ref&gt;As of June 30, 2009.  {{Cite web | title = U.S. and Canadian Institutions Listed by Fiscal Year 2009 Endowment Market Value and Percentage Change in Endowment Market Value from FY 2008 to FY 2009| work = 2009 NACUBO-Commonfund Study of Endowments | publisher = National Association of College and University Business Officers | url = http://www.nacubo.org/Documents/research/2009_NCSE_Public_Tables_Endowment_Market_Values.pdf| format = PDF | accessdate = February 15, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; 
|president       = [[Penelope W. Kyle|Penelope &quot;Penny&quot; W. Kyle]]
|provost         = Dr. Joseph Scartelli, Interim
|city            =  [[Radford, Virginia|Radford]] 
|state           = [[Virginia]] 
|country         = [[United States|U.S.]]
|faculty         = 403
|students        = 8,878
|undergrad       = 7,773
|postgrad        = 1,005
|campus          = {{convert|177|acre|km2}}
|colors          = [[Red]], and [[White]]&lt;br /&gt;{{color box|#C60C30}} {{color box|white}} 
|nickname        = Highlanders
|mascot          = The Highlander
|athletics       = [[National Collegiate Athletic Association|NCAA]] [[Division I (NCAA)|Division I]], [[Big South Conference]]
|website         = [http://www.radford.edu/ www.radford.edu]
|logo=  
}}

'''Radford University''' is one of Virginia's eight doctoral-degree granting public [[universities]].   Originally founded in 1910, Radford offers comprehensive curricula for [[undergraduates]] in more than 100 fields, and graduate programs including the [[Master of Fine Arts|M.F.A.]], [[M.B.A.]] and specialized [[Doctor of Philosophy|doctoral program]]s in health-related professions.&lt;ref name=&quot;RUdoc&quot;&gt;{{cite web | url =http://www.runet.edu/%7Epsyc-web/psyd/index.htm |title=Doctor of Psychology |publisher=Radford University |accessdate =2008-04-13}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Academics ==
Radford's undergraduate programs emphasize the liberal arts, business, and teacher education. The graduate and undergraduate programs in business administration offered by the College of Business and Economics at Radford University are accredited by the [[AACSB]] International &amp;mdash; The Association to Advance Collegiate Schools of Business.  Radford is among the 9 percent of the world’s (Top 10% in the United States) business schools that have achieved business and/or accounting accreditation from AACSB.   

The university has a student/faculty ratio of 19:1 with an average class size of 30 to 40. Graduate students teach less than 5% of classes, so undergraduates work more closely with senior faculty than they might at a larger research university.&lt;ref name=&quot;RUfacts&quot;&gt;{{cite web | url =http://www.radford.edu/NewsPub/rufacts.html |title=RU Facts and Figures |publisher=Radford University |accessdate =2008-04-13}}&lt;/ref&gt;
 
The university is organized into six undergraduate colleges: Humanities and Behavioral Sciences, Business and Economics, Education and Human Development, Health and Human Services, Science and Technology, and Visual and Performing Arts. Within the colleges, some fields are designated as &quot;Schools,&quot; such as the School of Nursing and School of Social Work (in the College of Health and Human Services) and the School of Communication (in the College of Humanities &amp; Behavioral Sciences). The latter brings together former departments of media studies (journalism, broadcasting, Web design and advertising) and communication (speech and public relations).

The College of Graduate and Extended Education offers 19 degree programs in fields including art, business, communication, counseling, criminal justice, education, English, music, nursing, occupational therapy, physical therapy, psychology and social work.[http://gradcollege.asp.radford.edu/] The State Council of Higher Education for Virginia has authorized three doctoral programs at Radford, in counseling psychology, physical therapy and nursing practice. The Doctor of Psychology (Psy.D.) program in Counseling Psychology admitted its first students in the fall of 2008. The doctorate in physical therapy program was scheduled to start in summer 2009. The university said its first Doctor of Nursing Practice students would begin studies in an online format in the fall of 2010.&lt;ref name=&quot;RUdoc2&quot;&gt;{{cite web | url =http://nurs-web.asp.radford.edu/news/0108dnp.html |title=Doctor of Nursing Practice Degree |publisher=Radford University |accessdate =2009-03-08}}&lt;/ref&gt; 
 
More than 80 percent of faculty members hold [[doctorates]] or other terminal degrees (M.F.A., etc.) in their fields. Eight Radford professors have received Virginia’s highest honor for faculty since the inception of the state’s Outstanding Faculty Award in 1986. One of them, Radford anthropology professor Donna Boyd, was named 2006 U.S. Professor of the Year for master’s level universities and colleges by the Council for Advancement and Support of Education and the Carnegie Foundation for Advancement of Teaching. Since 1981, nine Radford faculty members have been selected as [[Fulbright Scholars]] to teach or research in other countries.

Special programs include Study Abroad, Honors Academy, RU Connections freshmen living/learning communities, internships, co-ops, practica and service learning, Army [[ROTC]], leading to commission in the [[U.S. Army]], undergraduate research opportunities.

Radford was the first university in Virginia to integrate [[wireless technology]] campus wide.

Nearly 93 percent of Radford graduates obtain employment or enroll in graduate school within 3 to 8 months of graduation from the university.

In 2007, the Radford University Board of Visitors approved the University’s Strategic Plan, dubbed &quot;7-17, Forging a Bold New Future,&quot; with a goal of establishing Radford as one of the top 50 master's degree granting universities in the nation by 2017.

In 2009 Radford University underwent an internally directed and budget-driven academic program review resulting in the elimination of some liberal arts courses as well as smaller academic departments such as anthroplogy and geology. Students enrolled in such programs were permitted to finish their study in those areas, but no new students may enroll.

== Community and campus ==

Radford University is an {{convert|177|acre|km2|sing=on}} campus located in a residential area of Radford, Virginia. The town is located in the Virginia Highlands, between the [[Blue Ridge Mountains|Blue Ridge]] and [[Allegheny Mountains|Allegheny]] mountains at a double bend in the [[New River (West Virginia)|New River]]. Nearly all of the 35 administrative, academic, student services, and residence halls, many built in a red-brick Georgian style, are located on three quadrangles and a new pedestrian thoroughfare in a {{convert|76|acre|m2|adj=on}} area, while a large adjoining area along the New River holds a variety of the university's athletic facilities.   

Radford is located on exits 105 and 109 of [[Interstate 81]], with accessibility to nearby [[I-77]].

Bordering the [[Little River (New River)|Little River]], and about five miles from campus, is the [http://www.radford.edu/conf-serv/Selu.htm Selu Conservancy], a {{convert|376|acre|km2|sing=on}} preserve and conference center owned by the University Foundation.

[[image:Muse Hall at Radford University 2008.jpg|thumb|Clocktower of the residence hall Muse Hall]]

==Student life==

3,150 students live on campus in 15 residence halls. There are more than 200 clubs and organizations. Radford has events, performances, and lectures throughout the academic year.

Radford also has a wide variety of Greek life that is increasing in popularity among the students. Among it are chapters such as [[Alpha Chi Rho]], [[Alpha Kappa Psi]], [[Alpha Sigma Alpha]], [[Alpha Sigma Tau]], [[Alpha Sigma Phi]], [[Delta Chi]], [[Delta Zeta]], [[Kappa Sigma]], [[Kappa Delta Rho]], [[Pi Lambda Phi]], [[Phi Sigma Kappa]], [[Phi Sigma Sigma]], [[Sigma Kappa]], [[Sigma Pi]], [[Sigma Sigma Sigma]], [[Theta Chi]], and [[ Pi Kappa Phi]].

== Enrollment ==
===Fall 2009 semester statistics===
&lt;br /&gt;Number of students: 8,878
&lt;br /&gt;88% undergraduate, 12% graduate
&lt;br /&gt;60% female, 40% male
&lt;br /&gt;42 states and 50 countries represented

== History ==
Radford was founded in 1910 by Dr. [[John Preston McConnell]] as a [[Women's colleges in the United States|women's college]] as the State Normal and Industrial School for Women at Radford. The college was a [[normal school]] and offered a two-year degree in &quot;rural arts&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;RUhist&quot;&gt;{{cite web | url =http://lib.radford.edu/Archives/ruhistory.htm |work=Radford University History|title=RU History |publisher=Radford University |accessdate =2008-04-17}} {{Dead link|date=September 2010|bot=H3llBot}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In 1924 the school was renamed the State Teachers College at Radford and began an evolution toward a true college.  Its primary focus was on training teachers for the rural [[Appalachian]] region nearby.  In 1943 the college was renamed the Women's Division of the Virginia Polytechnic Institute and merged into what is now known as the [[Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University|Virginia Tech]] which was {{convert|15|mi|km}} away in [[Blacksburg, Virginia]].  

As the 1960s began, Virginia began to desegregate its gender specific schools, and Virginia Tech began to admit women on its main campus.  This led to a separation in 1964 and a renaming as Radford College.  Over the next decade, the &quot;finishing school&quot; atmosphere of the college was dismantled.  In 1972 the college began to admit men and developed a graduate school.

In 1979 the school became Radford University.  Today, the school is a comprehensive state university. About 45% of the students come from southwestern Virginia, 40% from other parts of Virginia, and 15% from out-of-state. [[Penelope W. Kyle]], J.D., M.B.A., became Radford's sixth president June 1, 2005, after a career in business and government, most notably as director of the state lottery. 

In 1913, Radford University's school colors started off as purple and gray.  In the 1970s, the colors were changed to the MacFarlane tartan of red, white, blue and green, to go with the school's Scottish theme.  More recently, despite opposition from some students and alumni, the university administration abandoned the unique tartan scheme and adopted red and white as the school's athletic colors.   
&lt;!-- Image with unknown copyright status removed: [[Image:Pic1-1-.jpg]] --&gt;

== Athletics ==
{{main|Radford Highlanders}}
[[Image:RadfordHighlanders.png|thumb|right|Radford Highlanders logo]]
The university's teams remain known as the Highlanders (in honor of the region's [[Ulster-Scots|Scots-Irish]] heritage) and compete in the [[Big South Conference]]. Radford offers 19 [[NCAA]] varsity sports for men and women. The Radford men's [[basketball]] team won the Big South Conference tournament in 1998 and 2009. Radford also won the Big South Conference Men's [[Tennis]] Championship in 2007, 2008 and 2009 as well as the Big South [[Softball]] Championship in 2009.

Led by Margot Hinchey, the Radford men's [[Rugby union|Rugby]] club team won the Division 2 National Championship in 2003 and 2008. Margot Rantool Hinchey known as &quot;The Flying stograM&quot; or &quot;the Bulldozer&quot; scored the most trys in team history. Student athletes have exclusive use of the recently renovated [[Dedmon Center]], a recreational and convocation complex that opened in 1981. The Dedmon Center features a 1/6-mile indoor [[jogging]] track, five [[racquetball]] courts, a [[weight-training]] room, locker rooms, and several team rooms. The main arena features a main basketball floor and a secondary [[volleyball]] arena for intercollegiate competition and four recreational courts for basketball or volleyball. The complex features adjoining facilities, including [[intermural]] [[soccer]], [[American football]] and [[softball]] fields, and intercollegiate fields and courts for [[baseball]], softball, [[field hockey]] and tennis.  The [[Patrick D. Cupp Stadium]] adds an intercollegiate soccer, lacrosse and [[track and field]] complex.

==Accolades==
Radford was recognized in a national study as an &quot;Institution of Excellence in the First College Year&quot; for the breadth of quality of programs that assist student in their transition to college life. 

''[[U.S.News &amp; World Report]]'' has ranked Radford in the South's top 25 master's level public universities in its Guide to America's Best Colleges.

==Notable alumni==
* [[June Atkinson]] - State Superintendent of Public Instruction, [[North Carolina]]
* [[Danielle Banks]] - On Camera Meteorologist, [[The Weather Channel]]
* [[Frank Beamer]] - Head football coach, [[Virginia Tech]]
* [[Maria Odulio de Guzman]] - Lexicographer
* [[Nelson Harris]] - Former mayor of [[Roanoke, Virginia]]
* [[Randal J. Kirk]] - Founder of New River Pharmaceuticals, winner of Virginia’s Outstanding Industrialist of 2008&lt;ref name=&quot;rukirk&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.radford.edu/NewsPub/February08/0202kirk.html|title=Radford University's Randal J. Kirk Receives Prestigious State Award|date=2008-02-02|publisher=Radford University Office of University Relations|accessdate=2009-03-15}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[Scott Long]] - Human Rights Activist, currently working at the [[Human Rights Watch]]
* [[David Mattingly (radio)|Dave Mattingly]] - [[National Public Radio]] producer and newscaster&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.npr.org/templates/story/story.php?storyId=5035239|title=Dave Mattingly|work=npr|publisher=NPR|accessdate=5 April 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[Jayma Mays]] - Actress, stars as Emma Pilsbury in the [[Fox Broadcasting Company|Fox]] series ''[[Glee (TV series)|Glee]]''
* [[Goran Nava]] - Olympian for [[Serbia]] in the 1500 meter run in the [[2008 Olympics]]&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://rutoday.radford.edu/july08/073008.html|title=Former Highlander Nava Qualifies for 2008 Summer Olympics|date=July 30, 2008|work=RU Toady|publisher=Radford University|accessdate=5 April 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[Steve Robinson (basketball coach)|Steve Robinson]] - [[University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill]] Assistant Coach&lt;ref name=&quot;steverobinson&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://tarheelblue.cstv.com/sports/m-baskbl/mtt/robinson_steve00.html|title=North Carolina Official Athletic Site|accessdate=2009-03-20}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[Martin Sayer]] - Assistant Men's Tennis Coach for Radford University, member of the [[Hong Kong Davis Cup team]] , former RU tennis player, 4 time Big South Player of the Year&lt;ref&gt;http://www.radfordathletics.com/coaches.aspx?rc=192&amp;path=mten&lt;/ref&gt;
* Marty Smith - ESPN NASCAR Analyst&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.espnmediazone3.com/us/2009/12/smith_marty/|title=Marty Smith • NASCAR Reporter|date=December 16, 2009|work=ESPN Media Zone|publisher=ESPN MediaZone|accessdate=5 April 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[Ryan Speier]] - Pitcher, [[Washington Nationals]]
* [[Diane Stupar-Hughes]] - Co-host of talk radio show Elliot in the Morning.
* [[Dante Washington]] - TV Soccer Color Analyst for the [[Columbus Crew]] of [[Major League Soccer|MLS]], first team [[All-American]] Soccer player in 1991, played for the United States in the [[1992 Summer Olympics]] Games

==Administration==
;Richard S. Alvarez: Vice President for Finance and Administration and Chief Financial Officer
;Danny M. Kemp: Vice President for Information Technology and Chief Information Officer
;Jo Ann Kiernan: Special Assistant to the President
;Mark G. Shanley: Vice President for Student Affairs
;Dr. Sam Minner: Provost
;Don Appiarius: Dean of Students

===Board of Visitors===
Radford University is governed by a 13-member board that was created under Virginia state law. Eleven of the members are appointed by the Governor of the Commonwealth and serve four-year terms. Each year the Board also selects a student and a faculty member to serve as advisory representatives on the Board.

===Office of the President===

*Dr. [[John Preston McConnell]], 1911–1937
*Dr. David Wilbur Peters, 1938–1951
*Dr. Charles Knox Martin Jr., 1952–1972, Chancellor, 1972–73, President Emeritus, 1973–1987
*Dr. [[Donald Dedmon|Donald Newton Dedmon]], 1972–1994
*Dr. Douglas Covington, 1995–2005
*[[Penelope Ward Kyle]], 2005–Present

===Office of the Provost===
*Dr. Ivelaw Lloyd Griffith
*Dr. Wilbur Stanton, July 1, 2007–2009

==References==
{{Reflist}}
*2007-08 Catalog and resource books provided by Radford University.

==External links==
{{commonscat}}
*[http://www.radford.edu/ Radford University official website]
*[http://music.asp.radford.edu/ Radford University Music]
*[http://www.thetartan.com/ The Tartan Radford University school newspaper]
*[http://www.wvru.org/ Public Radio WVRU official website]
*[http://www.ruwhim.net/ Whim (RU's student-run online magazine)]
*[http://www.hometeamsonline.com/visit/?u=IHC-CLB&amp;sport=hockey&amp;t=c Radford University Ice Hockey]
*[https://php.radford.edu/~csat/ Radford University College of Information Science and Technology]
*[http://cobe-web.asp.radford.edu/ Radford University College of Business and Economics]
*[http://bac.asp.radford.edu/ Center for Entrepreneurship and Economic Development]
*[http://intlprog.asp.radford.edu/ International Education Center at Radford University]
*[https://php.radford.edu/%7emes/index.php Radford University Museum of the Earth Sciences]
*[http://planetarium.radford.edu Radford University Planetarium]
*[http://rumuseum.asp.radford.edu/Current/current.htm Radford University Art Museum]
*[http://www.ruhighlanders.com/ Radford University Highlanders athletics website]
*[http://www.radford.edu/police RU Police website]

{{Radford University}}
{{Colleges and universities in Virginia}}
{{Big South Conference}}
{{Women's Colleges that are Coeducational}}

{{Coord|37.13870|N|80.55759|W|source:placeopedia|display=title}}

[[Category:Radford University]]
[[Category:Education in Radford, Virginia]]
[[Category:Educational institutions established in 1910]]
[[Category:Former women's universities and colleges in the United States]]
[[Category:American Association of State Colleges and Universities]]
[[Category:Universities and colleges in Virginia]]
[[Category:Public universities]]
[[Category:Universities and colleges accredited by the Southern Association of Colleges and Schools]]
[[Category:Buildings and structures in Radford, Virginia]]

[[de:Radford University]]
[[ja:ラドフォード大学]]
[[sv:Radford University]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
