<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="185059" ns="0" title="CodeWeavers"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Infobox company
| company_name = CodeWeavers
| company_logo = [[Image:Codeweavers logo.png]]
| company_type = 
| foundation = 1996
| location = [[Saint Paul, Minnesota]]
| key_people = Jeremy White, Founder and CEO&lt;br /&gt;[[Alexandre Julliard]], Chief Technology Officer&lt;br /&gt;Jonathan Parshall, Chief Operating Officer&lt;br /&gt;James Ramey, VP Sales
| industry = [[Computer software]]
| products = [[CrossOver Linux]], [[CrossOver Mac]], [[CrossOver Server]]
| revenue = 
| operating_income = 
| net_income = 
| num_employees = approx. 30
| parent =
| subsid =
| homepage = [http://www.codeweavers.com www.codeweavers.com]
| footnotes =
}}

'''CodeWeavers''' is a company that sells a [[proprietary software|proprietary]] version of [[Wine (software)|Wine]] called [[CrossOver]], for running [[Microsoft Windows|Windows]] [[application software|applications]] on [[Mac OS X]] and [[Linux]]. The company was founded in 1996 as a consultancy, eventually moving entirely over to Wine development and support. The CrossOver version of Wine is regularly refreshed with the latest free Wine patches; likewise, patches from the company's employees are sent back to the project almost immediately.  This distinguishes the company from [[TransGaming]], which develops a [[fork (software development)|forked]] version of Wine called [[Cedega (software)|Cedega]], and no longer returns contributions to free Wine.  CodeWeavers is a major contributor to the Wine project, a [[free software]] / [[open-source software]] project that helps Windows applications run on different x86-based operating systems, and employs the project's maintainer, [[Alexandre Julliard]], as their CTO. 

The Company's products include '''CrossOver Pro Linux''', '''CrossOver Pro Mac''', '''CrossOver Games for Linux''', and '''CrossOver Games for Mac'''. '''CrossOver Server''' was discontinued in 2007 as CrossOver Pro replaced its functionality. The company's products have traditionally focused on making [[Microsoft]] software staples like [[Microsoft Office]], [[Microsoft Office Word|MS Word]], and [[Microsoft Excel|MS Excel]] run on Linux.  With the addition of CrossOver Pro Mac the company has also begun focusing on games and other applications not available natively on the Mac platform, such as [[Microsoft Office Visio|MS Visio]] and [[Microsoft Office Project|MS Project]]. CrossOver Games was introduced in March 2008 and is intended to allow gaming-related patches from Wine to be incorporated into CrossOver much faster. The CrossOver Pro product line will focus on stability and in-depth testing with supported productivity software, such as Microsoft Office, and will have a slower release cycle.

CodeWeavers also provides implementation and consulting services around [[Wine (software)|Wine]] and other [[Open Source|open-source]] software projects. [[Google]] has paid CodeWeavers to improve support for [[Adobe Photoshop]] and add functionality to [[Wine (software)|Wine]]&lt;ref&gt;http://google-opensource.blogspot.com/2008/02/google-sponsors-wine-improvements.html&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;http://apcmag.com/google_behind_photoshops_new_linux_compatibility.htm&lt;/ref&gt;.

CodeWeavers is also a founding member of the [[Desktop Linux Consortium]].

==Great American Lame Duck Presidential Challenge==
In July 2008, CodeWeavers launched the ''Great American Lame Duck Presidential Challenge''&lt;ref&gt;[http://lameduck.codeweavers.com The CodeWeavers Great American Lame Duck Presidential Challenge] - October 27, 2008&lt;/ref&gt; to encourage President Bush to make the most of his remaining days in office by accomplishing a major economic or political goal by January 20, 2009. 

The goals focused on President Bush making specific positive accomplishments in areas such as the economy, home values, the stock market, the war on terror and other key issues. Specifically, one goal called for President Bush to help bring down average gasoline prices in the [[Twin Cities]] to $2.79 a gallon.

On October 14, gas prices in Minneapolis and St. Paul did just that. CodeWeavers were true to their word{{Clarify|date=October 2011}}, and on October 28, a combination of Slashdot and Digg took down their website as people rushed to get the gratis software. According to CodeWeavers, &quot;You will be able to unlock your serial number that was emailed to you for an extended time, (an additional 48 hours), due to this downtime. We will simply stop giving out new serial numbers at 23:59 (Midnight) Central Standard Time.&quot; &lt;ref&gt;http://down.codeweavers.com/&lt;/ref&gt;

Additionally, CodeWeavers updated their site @ ~ 9:00 AM CST (GMT - 6) to reflect the statement: &quot;Please check back again for registration code information later today. We will be deploying a streamlined serial code generation process shortly.&quot; At the same time, they also added an &quot;about Wine&quot; paragraph. 

The streamlined process came to pass, but customers were told to expect to wait &quot;several days&quot; to receive their serial number. In the interim, fully unlocked (full builds) of four different CodeWeavers packages became available for immediate download, but only on October 28, 2008.&lt;ref&gt;http://codeweavers.com/&lt;/ref&gt;

==References==
{{reflist}}

==External links==
*[http://www.codeweavers.com/ CodeWeavers home page]
*[http://madpenguin.org/cms/index.php?m=show&amp;id=1512 Jeremy White interview] (Mad Penguin)

{{DEFAULTSORT:Codeweavers}}
[[Category:Linux companies]]
[[Category:Companies based in Saint Paul, Minnesota]]
[[Category:Companies established in 1996]]

[[es:CodeWeavers]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
