<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><redirects><r from="VMware Inc" to="VMware" /></redirects><pages><page pageid="312018" ns="0" title="VMware"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Infobox company
| company_name  =  VMware Inc.
| company_logo  =  [[File:Vmware.svg|200px|VMware Inc Logo]]
| company_type  =  [[Public company|Public]] 
| traded_as  = {{nyse|VMW}}
| foundation  =  [[Palo Alto, California]], [[United States|USA]], 1998
| location  =  Palo Alto, California, USA
| key_people  =  [[Paul Maritz]] (President &amp; CEO) &lt;br /&gt; [[Diane Greene]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Mendel Rosenblum]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Edouard Bugnion]]
| parent  =  [[EMC Corporation]]
| num_employees     =  {{formatnum:8200}}
| revenue           = {{increase}} [[United States dollar|US$]] 2.9 Billion &lt;small&gt;(2010)&lt;/small&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;VMware Reports Fourth Quarter and Full Year 2010 Results&quot;&gt;{{cite web | url=http://www.vmware.com/company/news/releases/vmw-earnings-q410.html | title=VMware Reports Fourth Quarter and Full Year 2010 Results  | publisher=VMware, Inc  | date=January 24, 2011 | accessdate=2011-10-12}}&lt;/ref&gt;
| industry  =  [[software|Computer software]]
| products  =  [[VMware vSphere]]&lt;br /&gt;[[VMware ESX Server]]&lt;br /&gt;[[VMware ESXi Server]]&lt;br /&gt;[[VMware Workstation]]&lt;br /&gt;[[VMware Fusion]]&lt;br /&gt;[[VMware Player]]&lt;br /&gt;[[VMware Server]]&lt;br /&gt;VMware Service Manager&lt;br/&gt;[[VMware ThinApp]]&lt;br /&gt;[[VMware View]]&lt;br /&gt;VMware ACE&lt;br /&gt;VMware Lab Manager&lt;br /&gt;[[VMware Infrastructure]]&lt;br /&gt;VMware Converter&lt;br /&gt;VMware Site Recovery Manager&lt;br /&gt;VMware Stage Manager&lt;br /&gt;VMware vCenter Orchestrator&lt;br /&gt;[[VMware VMFS]]
| homepage  =  [http://www.vmware.com/ VMware.com]
}}

'''VMware, Inc.''' ({{nyse|VMW}}) is a company providing [[Platform virtualization|virtualization]] software&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.hostreview.com/icontent/the-blog/vmware-leader-virtualization-market |title=VMware leader in virtualization market}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.nytimes.com/2009/08/31/technology/business-computing/31virtual.html?pagewanted=2&amp;_r=2&amp;partner=rss&amp;emc=rss |title=VMware market share more than 80% | work=The New York Times | first=Steve | last=Lohr | date=2009-08-31 | accessdate=2010-05-27}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://searchservervirtualization.techtarget.com/news/article/0,289142,sid94_gci1369150,00.html |title=VMware, Hyper-V virtualization leave others in the dust}}&lt;/ref&gt; founded in 1998 and based in [[Palo Alto, California]], USA.  The company was acquired by [[EMC Corporation]] in 2004, and operates as a separate software subsidiary .

VMware's desktop software runs on [[Microsoft Windows]], [[Linux]], and [[Mac OS X]], while VMware's [[enterprise software]] [[hypervisor]]s for servers, [[VMware ESX]] and [[VMware ESXi]], are bare-metal [[embedded hypervisor]]s that run directly on [[server (computing)|server]] hardware without requiring an additional underlying [[operating system]].&lt;ref name=&quot;ESXArch&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url= http://www.vmware.com/support/esx21/doc/esx21_admin_system_architecture.html |title=ESX Server Architecture |publisher=Vmware.com |date= |accessdate=2009-10-22}} {{Dead link|date=October 2010|bot=H3llBot}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== History ==

In 1998 VMware was founded by [[Diane Greene]], [[Mendel Rosenblum]], Scott Devine, Edward Wang and [[Edouard Bugnion]]. Greene and Rosenblum, who are married, first met while at the [[University of California, Berkeley]].&lt;ref&gt;{{ cite news|url=http://money.cnn.com/magazines/fortune/fortune_archive/2007/10/15/100536853/index.htm|author=Adam Lashinksky|date=2007-10-02|title=50 Most Powerful Women in Business - Full speed ahead|publisher=CNN | quote = In 1988 she picked up a second master's, in computer science, at the University of California at Berkeley, where she met Rosenblum }}&lt;/ref&gt; Edouard Bugnion remained the chief architect and CTO of VMware until 2005,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url=http://www.infoworld.com/article/04/01/23/04FEctoedouard_1.html?s=feature|title=Edouard Bugnion lives in the virtual world}}&lt;/ref&gt; and went on to found Nuova Systems (now part of [[Cisco Systems|Cisco]]).

VMware developed a range of products, most notable of which are their [[hypervisor]]s.  VMware became well known for their first type 2 hypervisor known as GSX.  This product has since evolved into two hypervisor products lines, VMware's type 1 hypervisors running directly on hardware, along with their hosted type 2 hypervisors.  

The company has its headquarters in Palo Alto, California, United States, and established an R&amp;D Center in Cambridge, Massachusetts, as well as one at the [[Time Warner Center]] in [[New York City]], in 2005. 

VMware operated throughout 1998 in [[stealth mode]] with roughly 20 employees by the end of that year. The company was launched officially in February 1999 at the [[DEMO Conference]] organized by [[Chris Shipley]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
 |url=http://www.vmware.com/company/mediaresource/milestones.html
 |title= VMware Milestones
}}&lt;/ref&gt;

VMware delivered its first product, [[VMware Workstation]], in May 1999&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url=http://www.vmware.com/company/mediaresource/milestones.html | title=VMware company history}}&lt;/ref&gt; and entered the server market in 2001 with VMware GSX Server (hosted) and VMware ESX Server (hostless).&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
 |url=http://news.cnet.com/2100-1001-242656.html
 |title=VMware ready to capitalize on hot server market
 |date=June 30, 2000
}}&lt;/ref&gt;
In 2003 VMware launched VMware Virtual Center, the  VMotion and Virtual SMP technology. 64-bit support appeared in 2004. The company was also acquired by EMC Corporation that same year for $625 million.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.vmware.com/company/news/releases/emc2.html&lt;/ref&gt;

In June 2006, VMware acquired privately-held Akimbi Systems.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
 |url=http://www.vmware.com/company/news/releases/software_lifecycle.html
 |title=VMware Advances Software Lifecycle Management
}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In August 2007, EMC Corporation released 10% of the company's shares in VMware in an [[initial public offering]] on the New York Stock Exchange.  The stock debuted at [[United States dollar|US$]]29 per share and closed the day at $51.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |last=Mullins |first=Robert |date=2007-08-14 |url=http://www.infoworld.com/article/07/08/14/VMware-the-bright-spot-on-a-gray-Wall-Street-day_1.html |title=Update: VMware the bright spot on a gray Wall Street day |publisher=IDG News Service |accessdate=2007-08-15}}&lt;/ref&gt;

On July 8, 2008, VMware co-founder, president and CEO Diane Greene was unexpectedly fired by the VMware Board of Directors and replaced by [[Paul Maritz]], a retired 14-year Microsoft veteran who was heading EMC's [[cloud computing]] business unit.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |author=Savitz, Eric |url= http://blogs.barrons.com/techtraderdaily/2008/07/08/vmware-ousts-ceo-diane-greene-cuts-08-guidance/ |title=VMware ousts CEO Diane Greene; cuts '08 guidance |work=Barron’s |date=2008-07-08 |accessdate=2009-07-01}}&lt;/ref&gt;  In the same news release VMware stated that 2008 revenue growth will be &quot;modestly below the previous guidance of 50% growth over 2007.&quot; As a result, market price of VMware dropped nearly 25%. Then on September 10, 2008, Rosenblum, the company's chief scientist, resigned.

On September 16, 2008, VMware announced that they are collaborating with [[Cisco]] to provide joint data center solutions.  One of the first results of this is the Cisco [[Nexus 1000V]], a distributed virtual software switch that will be an integrated option in the VMware infrastructure.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.vmware.com/files/pdf/technology/cisco_vmware_virtualizing_the_datacenter.pdf |title=Virtual Networking Features of the VMware vNetwork Distributed Switch and Cisco Nexus 1000V Series Switches}}&lt;/ref&gt;

VMware acquired Tungsten Graphics, a company with core expertise in 3D graphics driver development on November 26, 2008.&lt;ref name=tungsten&gt;{{cite |author=David Marshall |date=2008-12-16 |title=VMware's year end acquisition of Tungsten Graphics |publisher=[[InfoWorld]] |url=http://www.infoworld.com/d/virtualization/vmwares-year-end-acquisition-tungsten-graphics-196 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

On August 10, 2009, VMware announced the acquisition of [[SpringSource]], a leader in enterprise and web application development and management.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.vmware.com/company/news/releases/springsource.html|title=VMware to Acquire SpringSource}}&lt;/ref&gt; The acquisition is seen by the industry as a strategic move of VMware to become a leader in offering [[platform as a service]] (PaaS). The acquisition also resulted in the expansion of VMware's education services portfolio by the inclusion of SpringSource University and its authorized training partner, [http://www.springpeople.com SpringPeople Technologies].

On January 12, 2010, VMware acquired [[Zimbra]], an open-source collaboration software tool, from [[Yahoo]]. On May 6, 2010, VMware acquired [[GemStone Systems|GemStone]], to be operated under VMware's SpringSource division.

On 12 April 2011, they released an [[open source]] platform-as-a-service system called [[Cloud Foundry]], and a hosted version of the service. This supports application deployment for [[Java (programming language)|Java]], [[Ruby on Rails]], [[Sinatra (software)|Sinatra]], [[Node.js]] and support for [[MySQL]], [[MongoDB]] and [[Redis]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite |url=http://cloudfoundry.com/faq |title=Cloud Foundry Frequently Asked Questions}}&lt;/ref&gt;

On 26 April 2011, VMware acquired [[SlideRocket]] a startup which developed a SaaS application for building business presentations that are stored online. Through a Web-based interface, users can handle all parts of the process, from designing slides and compiling content, to reviewing documents and publishing and delivering them

On 31 May 2011, VMware acquired [[Socialcast]], a group workstream service.

== Core product design ==
{{Ref improve section|date=September 2009}}
VMware software provides a completely [[Platform virtualization|virtualized]] set of hardware to the guest operating system.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.extremetech.com/article2/0,2845,1624080,00.asp |title=How does VMWare Work? |publisher=Extremetech.com |date=2009-06-22 |accessdate=2009-07-01}}&lt;/ref&gt; VMware software virtualizes the hardware for a video adapter, a network adapter, and hard disk adapters. The host provides pass-through drivers for guest USB, serial, and parallel devices. In this way, VMware virtual machines become highly portable between computers, because every host looks nearly identical to the guest. In practice, a system administrator can pause operations on a virtual machine guest, move or copy that guest to another physical computer, and there resume execution exactly at the point of suspension. Alternatively, for enterprise servers, a feature called vMotion allows the migration of operational guest virtual machines between similar but separate hardware hosts sharing the same storage. Each of these transitions is completely transparent to any users on the virtual machine at the time it is being migrated.

VMware Workstation, Server, and ESX take a more optimized path to running target operating systems on the host than [[emulator]]s (such as [[Bochs]]) which simulate the function of each CPU instruction on the target machine one-by-one, or [[dynamic recompilation]] which compiles blocks of machine-instructions the first time they execute, and then uses the translated code  directly when the code runs subsequently ([[Microsoft Virtual PC]] for [[Mac OS X]] takes this approach.) VMware software does not emulate an [[instruction set]] for different hardware not physically present. This significantly boosts performance,&lt;ref name=sanvsdas&gt;{{cite web | title=Benchmarking VMware ESX Server 2.5 vs Microsoft Virtual Server 2005 Enterprise Edition | url=http://capitalhead.com/articles/benchmarking-vmware-esx-server-25-vs-microsoft-virtual-server-2005-enterprise-edition.aspx | work=Virtualization Benchmark Review | date=2006-04-19 | accessdate=2009-06-11}}&lt;/ref&gt; but can cause problems when moving virtual machine guests  between hardware hosts using different instruction-sets (such as found in 64-bit [[Intel]] and [[AMD]] CPUs), or between hardware hosts with a differing number of CPUs. Stopping the virtual-machine guest before moving it to a different CPU type generally causes no issues.

VMware's products predate the virtualization extensions to the x86 instruction set, and do not require virtualization-enabled processors.  On such older processors, they use the CPU to run code directly whenever possible (as, for example, when running [[user space|user-mode]] and [[virtual 8086 mode]] code on x86). When direct execution cannot operate, such as with kernel-level and [[real mode|real-mode]] code, VMware products re-write the code dynamically, a process VMware calls &quot;binary translation&quot; or BT. The translated code gets stored in spare memory, typically at the end of the [[address space]], which [[Segmentation (memory)|segmentation]] mechanisms can  protect and make invisible. For these reasons, VMware operates dramatically faster than emulators, running at more than 80% of the speed that the virtual guest operating-system would run directly on the same hardware. In one study VMware claims a slowdown over native ranging from 0–6 percent for the VMware ESX Server.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web| title=A Performance Comparison of Hypervisors| url=http://www.vmware.com/pdf/hypervisor_performance.pdf}}&lt;/ref&gt;

VMware's approach avoids some of the difficulties of virtualization on x86-based platforms. Virtual machines may deal with offending instructions by replacing them, or by simply running kernel-code in user-mode. Replacing instructions runs the risk that the code may fail to find the expected content if it reads itself; one cannot protect code against reading while allowing normal execution, and replacing in-place becomes complicated. Running the code unmodified in user-mode will also fail, as most instructions which just read the machine-state do not cause an exception and will betray the real state of the program, and certain instructions silently change behavior in user-mode. One must always rewrite; performing a simulation of the current [[program counter]] in the original location when necessary and (notably) remapping hardware code [[breakpoint]]s.

Although VMware virtual machines run in user-mode, VMware Workstation itself requires the installation of various [[device driver|driver]]s in the host operating-system, notably to dynamically switch the [[Global Descriptor Table|Global Descriptor Table (GDT)]] and the [[Interrupt Descriptor Table|Interrupt Descriptor Table (IDT)]].

The VMware product line can also run different operating systems on a dual-boot system simultaneously by booting one partition natively while using the other as a guest within VMware Workstation.

== Technology Architecture ==

&lt;gallery&gt;
Image:DiagramESXMemMgmt.gif|VMware ESX Memory Management and Monitoring&lt;ref&gt;&quot;[http://www.hypervizor.com/wp-content/plugins/download-monitor/download.php?id=8 Diagram: VMware ESX Memory Management and Monitoring]&quot;&lt;/ref&gt;
Image:VMW FT.gif|VMware Fault Tolerance&lt;ref&gt;&quot;[http://www.hypervizor.com/wp-content/plugins/download-monitor/download.php?id=3 Diagram: VMware Fault Tolerance]&quot;&lt;/ref&gt;
Image:VMW DiagramHighAvailability.gif|VMware High Availability&lt;ref&gt;&quot;[http://www.hypervizor.com/wp-content/plugins/download-monitor/download.php?id=7 Diagram: VMware High Availability]&quot;&lt;/ref&gt;
Image:VMW VDS.gif|VMware vNetwork Distributed Switch&lt;ref&gt;&quot;[http://www.hypervizor.com/wp-content/plugins/download-monitor/download.php?id=2 Diagram: VMware vNetwork Distributed Switch]&quot;&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;/gallery&gt;

== Products ==

[[Image:VSphere Enterprise Diagram V1.gif|thumb|250px|VMware vSphere, a holistic view]]

{| width=&quot;700&quot; cellspacing=&quot;0&quot; cellpadding=&quot;3&quot; border=&quot;1&quot;
|-
| rowspan=&quot;2&quot; | 
vCenter Server ($) 

(license manager) 
| align=&quot;center&quot; rowspan=&quot;2&quot; | 
Server 

hardware 
| colspan=&quot;3&quot; | 
ESX ($) 

(vMotion, DRS, HA, Storage vMotion)
| 
Guest OS 

Guest OS 

Guest OS... 
|-
| colspan=&quot;3&quot; | 
ESXi (freeware) &lt;br&gt;
(ESXi freeware is managed by the Virtual Infrastructure (or vSphere) Client)&lt;br&gt;
ESXi ($) &lt;br&gt;
(vMotion, DRS, HA, Storage vMotion)
| 
Guest OS 

Guest OS 

Guest OS... 
|-
| align=&quot;center&quot; colspan=&quot;2&quot; rowspan=&quot;3&quot; | 
Workstation 

hardware 
| rowspan=&quot;3&quot; | 
Windows or 

Linux OS 
| colspan=&quot;2&quot; | 
[[VMware Server]] (freeware) 
| rowspan=&quot;2&quot; | 
Guest OS 

Guest OS 

Guest OS... 
|-
| rowspan=&quot;2&quot; | 
User 

session 
| 
[[VMware Workstation]] ($) 

[[VMware Player]] (freeware) 
|-
| colspan=&quot;2&quot; | vSphere Client for managing ESX(i) hosts (freeware)&lt;br&gt;
|}

&lt;br&gt;
{{details|List of VMware software}}

=== Desktop software ===
* [[VMware Workstation]] (first product launched by VMware in 1999). This software suite allows users to run multiple instances of [[x86 architecture|x86]] or [[x86-64]] -compatible operating systems on a single physical [[personal computer|PC]].
* [[VMware Fusion]] provides similar functionality for users of the [[Apple–Intel architecture|Intel Mac]] platform, along with full compatibility with virtual machines created by other VMware products.
* [[VMware Player]] is for users without a license to use VMware Workstation or VMware Fusion. VMware offers this software as a freeware product for personal use. While initially not able to create virtual machines, this limitation was removed in version 3.0.1.

=== Server software ===
VMware markets two virtualization products for [[Server (computing)|server]]s:

* [[VMware ESX]] (formerly called &quot;ESX Server&quot;), an [[enterprise software|enterprise-level]] product, can deliver greater performance than the [[freeware]] VMware Server, due to lower system [[Computational overhead|overhead]]. VMware ESX is a &quot;bare-metal&quot; product, running directly on the server hardware, allowing virtual servers to also use hardware more or less directly. In addition, VMware ESX integrates into [[VMware vCenter]], which offers extra services to enhance the reliability and manageability of a server deployment, such as
** VMotion - the capability to move a running virtual machine from one ESX host to another and faster than some other editions
** Storage VMotion - the capability to move a running virtual machine from one storage device to another
** DRS - Distributed Resource Scheduler - automatic load balancing of a ESX cluster using VMotion
** HA - High Availability - In case of hardware failure in a cluster, the virtual servers will automatically restart on another host in the cluster

* [[VMware_ESX#VMware_ESXi| VMware ESXi]] (formerly called &quot;VMware ESX 3i&quot;), is quite similar to ESX, but differentiates in that the Service Console is removed, and replaced with a minimal [[BusyBox]] installation. Disk space requirements are much lower than for ESX and the [[memory footprint]] is reduced. ESXi is intended to be run from flash disks in servers but can be run from normal disks. VMware ESXi hosts can't be managed directly from the console, all management is performed through a VirtualCenter Server.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.vmware.com/files/pdf/vmware_esxi_architecture_wp.pdf|title=The Architecture of VMware ESXi|publisher=VMware}}&lt;/ref&gt;  In July 2008, VMware decided to give away ESXi for free.

* [[VMware Server]] (formerly called &quot;GSX Server&quot;, now both obsolete&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.vmware.com/support/policies/lifecycle/general/index.html|title=VMware Products Life Cycle Policies|publisher=VMware}}&lt;/ref&gt;) is also provided as freeware for non-commercial use, like [[VMware Player]], and it is also possible to create virtual machines with it. It is a &quot;hosted&quot; application, which runs within an existing [[Linux]] or [[Microsoft Windows|Windows]] [[operating system]].

=== Other products ===
[[Image:VMware ThinApp.png|thumb|250px|[[VMware ThinApp]], one of the most recent products from the company]]
''VMware vCenter Converter'' (VMware Converter) comes in both Enterprise ($, bundling and entitlement with vCenter Server) and Standalone (free) versions and is designed primarily for the following tasks:&lt;ref&gt;[http://vmware.com/products/converter/ VMware Converter]. Retrieved 2008-03-31.&lt;/ref&gt; 
*Convert a physical machine into a virtual machine; referred to as [[Physical-to-Virtual]] or P2V.
*Convert a virtual machine of one type into another (V2V)
*Run automated configuration tasks on VMware ESX/ESXi servers.

Converted VMs are compatible with VMware ESX/ESXi, VMware Server and VMware Workstation. A P2V conversion can be done from any physical machine running Microsoft Windows (XP or later) or Linux based (Linux only works on Standalone version). Conversions can be managed from a centralized console allowing for multiple conversions at the same time (using the Enterprise version). VMware vCenter Converter {{As of|2007|alt=replaces}} the older VMware products &quot;P2V Assistant&quot; and &quot;Importer&quot;. P2V Assistant allowed users to convert physical machines into virtual machines; and Importer allowed the import of virtual machines from other products into VMware Workstation.

''VMware Capacity Planner'', an [[information technology]] (IT) [[capacity planning]] tool, collects utilization-data in heterogeneous computing environments and compares it to [[Technical standard|industry-standard]] reference-data to provide analysis and [[decision support|decision-support]] modeling.

''[[VMware_Workstation#VMware_ACE|VMware ACE]]'' provides a means of distributing secured virtual desktops to networked client PCs.

''[[VMware ThinApp]]'', formerly Thinstall, is a virtualization suite capable of creating portable software (&quot;[[portable apps]]&quot;). This software enables applications to execute without being previously installed.

''[[VMware Infrastructure]]'' is a collection of VMware products used to manage a VMware ESX/ESXi server environment.

''[[VMware vSphere]]'' is a &quot;cloud OS&quot;. VMware vSphere 4 was originally named VMware Virtual Infrastructure (VI) 4 and is capable of managing large pools of infrastructure, including software and hardware&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.vmware.com/products/vsphere/|title=VMware vSphere|publisher=VMware}}&lt;/ref&gt; both from internal and external networks.

The ''VMware Tools'' package adds drivers and utilities to improve the graphical performance for different guest operating systems, including mouse tracking. The package also enables some integration between the guest and host systems, including shared [[directory (file systems)|folder]]s, [[plug-and-play]] devices, [[clock]] [[synchronisation]], and [[Cut, copy, and paste|cutting-and-pasting]] across environments. VMware Inc makes VMware Tools available for [[Microsoft Windows]], [[Linux]], [[Solaris (operating system)|Sun Solaris]], [[FreeBSD]], and [[Novell NetWare]] guest systems.&lt;ref&gt;
{{cite web | url = http://www.vmware.com/pdf/ws6_manual.pdf | title = Installing and Upgrading VMware Tools | work = Workstation User’s Manual | publisher = VMware, Inc. | accessdate = 2007-11-02 | date = 2007-09-20 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

On September 11 at VMworld 2007, VMware announced that large portions of VMware Tools for Linux, Solaris, and FreeBSD guests were released under GPL and GPL-compatible licenses. They also announced the creation of the Open Virtual Machine Tools (&quot;open-vm-tools&quot;) project on Sourceforge.net.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://lxer.com/module/newswire/view/92570/index.html |title=VMware Unveils VMware Tools as Open Source Software |publisher=LXer |date= |accessdate=2009-07-01}}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Image:VMware HQ campus 3401 Hillview entrance.JPG|thumb|VMware's promontory headquarters at 3401 Hillview Avenue in Palo Alto, California]]

== See also ==
* [[Comparison of platform virtual machines]]
* [[List of VMware software]]
* [[Platform virtualization|Virtualization]]
* [[VMware VMFS]]
* [[Hypervisor]]

{{clear}}

== References ==
{{reflist|colwidth=30em}}

== External links ==
{{Commons category}}
* [http://www.vmware.com Company home page]
* [http://maps.google.com/maps?f=q&amp;source=s_q&amp;hl=en&amp;geocode=&amp;q=Vmware+Inc,+Hillview+Avenue,+Palo+Alto,+CA&amp;aq=0&amp;sll=35.675147,-95.712891&amp;sspn=79.838745,155.742188&amp;ie=UTF8&amp;hq=&amp;hnear=V+Mware+Inc,+3305+Hillview+Ave,+Palo+Alto,+California+94304-1204&amp;ll=37.401009,-122.143394&amp;spn=0.007093,0.009506&amp;t=h&amp;z=18 Google Maps view of VMware headquarters]
* VMware [http://digitalfuel.com/ IT Virtualization] Solutions 
&lt;!--
Please do not add your site to the external links section! It is considered linkspam, and will be reverted. If your site is good enough, Wikipedians will add the site for you. If the site is not already in the list, it is most likely not notable enough. If so, please add the link to the article's talk page and we will discuss the addition with you. Thanks.
--&gt;

{{DEFAULTSORT:Vmware}}
[[Category:VMware]]
[[Category:Software companies of the United States]]
[[Category:Companies established in 1998]]
[[Category:Companies based in Palo Alto, California]]
[[Category:EMC Corporation]]
[[Category:Cloud computing providers]]

[[ar:في إم وير]]
[[ca:VMware]]
[[cs:VMware]]
[[de:VMware]]
[[es:VMware]]
[[fr:VMware]]
[[ko:VM웨어]]
[[id:VMware]]
[[it:VMware Inc.]]
[[he:VMware]]
[[hu:VMware]]
[[nl:VMware]]
[[ja:VMware]]
[[no:VMware]]
[[pl:VMware]]
[[pt:VMware]]
[[ro:VMware]]
[[ru:VMware]]
[[simple:VMware]]
[[fi:VMware]]
[[sv:VMware]]
[[tr:VMware]]
[[uk:VMware]]
[[vi:VMware]]
[[zh:VMware]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
