<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><redirects><r from="Dpkg-deb" to="Dpkg" /></redirects><pages><page pageid="187483" ns="0" title="Dpkg"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Unreferenced|date=October 2008}}
{{lowercase|title=dpkg}}
{{Infobox software
| name = dpkg
| logo =
| screenshot =
| caption =
| author = [[Ian Murdock]]
| developer = The dpkg team
| released =
| latest release version = 1.15.7.2
| latest release date =
| latest preview version = 1.15.8.4
| latest preview date =
| operating system = [[Unix-like]]
| programming language = [[C (programming language)|C]]
| platform =
| language =
| genre = [[Package management system]]
| license = [[GNU General Public License]]
| website = [http://www.debian.org/doc/FAQ/ch-pkgtools.en.html www.debian.org/doc/FAQ/ch-pkgtools.en.html]
}}
'''dpkg''' is the [[software]] at the base of the [[Debian]] [[package management system]]. &lt;code&gt;dpkg&lt;/code&gt; is used to install, remove, and provide information about [[deb (file format)|.deb]] [[software package (installation)|package]]s.

&lt;code&gt;dpkg&lt;/code&gt; itself is a low level tool; higher level tools, such as [[Advanced Packaging Tool|APT]], are used to fetch packages from remote locations or deal with complex package relations. Tools like [[Aptitude (program)|aptitude]] or [[synaptic (software)|synaptic]] are more commonly used than &lt;code&gt;dpkg&lt;/code&gt; on its own, as they have a more sophisticated way of dealing with package relationships and a friendlier interface.

The Debian package &quot;dpkg&quot; provides the &lt;code&gt;dpkg&lt;/code&gt; program, as well as several other programs necessary for run-time functioning of the packaging system, including &lt;code&gt;dpkg-statoverride&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;dpkg-divert&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;update-alternatives&lt;/code&gt;. It also includes the programs such as start-stop-daemon and install-info, and the latter is kept mostly due to [[backwards compatibility]] (it is developed and distributed separately nowadays). The Debian package &quot;dpkg-dev&quot; includes the numerous build tools described below.

==History==

dpkg was originally created by [[Matt Welsh (computer scientist)|Matt Welsh]], Carl Streeter and [[Ian Murdock]], first as a [[Perl]] program, and then later the main part was rewritten in [[C (programming language)|C]] by [[Ian Jackson]] in 1993. The name ''dpkg'' was originally the short for &quot;Debian package&quot;, but the meaning of that phrase has evolved significantly, as dpkg the software is orthogonal to the [[deb (file format)|deb package format]] as well as the Debian Policy which defines how Debian packages behave.

==Example use==

To install a .deb package:
 dpkg -i ''debFileName''

where ''debFileName'' is the name of the Debian software package.

The list of installed packages can be obtained with:
 dpkg -l ''[optional pattern]''

To remove an installed package:
 dpkg -r ''packagename''

== Development tools ==
dpkg-dev contains a series of development tools required to unpack, build and upload Debian source packages. These include:
*'''dpkg-source''' packs and unpacks the source files of a Debian package.
*'''dpkg-gencontrol''' reads the information from an unpacked Debian tree source and generates a binary package control package, creating an entry for this in Debian/files.
*'''dpkg-shlibdeps''' calculates the dependencies of runs with respect to libraries.
*'''dpkg-genchanges''' reads the information from an unpacked Debian tree source that once constructed creates a control file (.changes).
*'''dpkg-buildpackage''' is a control script that can be used to construct the package automatically.
*'''dpkg-distaddfile''' adds a file input to debian/files.
*'''dpkg-parsechangelog''' reads the changes file (changelog) of an unpacked Debian tree source and creates a conveniently prepared output with the information for those changes.

==See also==
{{Portal|Free software}}

* [[Advanced Packaging Tool]]
* [[alien (software)]]
* [[Debian build toolchain]]
* dpkg is similar to [[RPM Package Manager|RPM]].
* [[ipkg]] is a dpkg-inspired package management system for storage-constrained Linux installations.

==External links==
* [http://packages.debian.org/dpkg Debian's dpkg package]
* [http://lists.debian.org/debian-dpkg/ Debian dpkg mailing list]
* [http://manpages.debian.net/cgi-bin/man.cgi?query=dpkg&amp;apropos=0&amp;sektion=0&amp;manpath=Debian+Sid&amp;format=html&amp;locale=en dpkg(8)] [[manual page (Unix)|manual page]]
* [http://www.hadrons.org/~guillem/debian/docs/origin.proposal General Origin handling].

{{Debian}}

[[Category:Debian]]
[[Category:Dpkg| ]]
[[Category:Free software programmed in C]]

[[ar:نظام إدارة حزم دبيان]]
[[az:Dpkg]]
[[bn:ডিপিকেজি]]
[[ca:Dpkg]]
[[de:Debian Package Manager]]
[[es:Dpkg]]
[[fr:Dpkg]]
[[it:Dpkg]]
[[nl:Dpkg]]
[[ja:Dpkg]]
[[no:Dpkg]]
[[pl:Dpkg]]
[[pt:Dpkg]]
[[ru:Dpkg]]
[[simple:Dpkg]]
[[te:Dpkg]]
[[tr:Dpkg]]
[[zh:Dpkg]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
