<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="1856025" ns="0" title="1973 Israeli raid on Lebanon"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{coord|33.9|35.53|display=title}}
{{Refimprove|date=January 2008}}
{{Infobox Military Conflict
|conflict= Operation Spring of Youth
|partof=the [[Operation Wrath of God]]
|image=
|caption=
|date=April 9–10 1973
|place=[[Beirut]] and [[Sidon]], [[Lebanon]]
|casus=[[Palestinian]] attacks against Israel
|result=[[Israel Defense Forces|IDF]] special forces achieved their objective
|combatant1={{flag|Israel}}
* [[Sayeret Matkal]]
* [[Shayetet 13]]
* [[Sayeret Tzanhanim]]
|combatant2= {{flagicon|Palestine}} [[Palestine Liberation Organization|PLO]]&lt;br /&gt;{{flagicon image|PFLP flag smoothed.svg}} [[Popular Front for the Liberation of Palestine|PFLP]]
|commander1=
|commander2=
|strength1=
|strength2=
|casualties1=2 killed
|casualties2=12–100 killed
|casualties3=3 civilian casualties
}}{{Campaignbox Israel-Lebanon conflict}}
{{Campaignbox Wrath of God}}
The '''1973 Israeli raid on Lebanon''' (known as '''Operation ''Spring of Youth''''', part of '''Operation ''Wrath of God''''') took place on the night of April 9 and early morning of April 10, 1973 when [[Israel Defense Forces]] [[special forces]] units attacked several [[Palestine Liberation Organization]] (PLO) targets in [[Beirut]] and [[Sidon]], [[Lebanon]]. &lt;ref&gt;[http://books.google.co.uk/books?id=1zmZyr-ExYMC&amp;pg=PA137&amp;dq=operation+wrath+of+god+september+9+1972&amp;lr=&amp;cd=16#v=onepage&amp;q=operation%20wrath%20of%20god%20september%209%201972&amp;f=false J. Bowyer Bell, Irving Louis Horowitz (2005) ''Assassin: Theory and Practice of Political Violence'', pp137, Transaction Publishers, ISBN 1-4128-0509-0 ] Retrieved 2010 May 4&lt;/ref&gt;

The operation is generally considered to be part of the retaliation for the [[Munich Massacre]] at the Summer Olympics in 1972.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news| url=http://www.nytimes.com/2005/12/15/books/15masl.html | work=The New York Times | title=A Massacre in Munich, and What Came After | first=Janet | last=Maslin | date=2005-12-15 | accessdate=2010-04-20}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The Israeli [[Sayeret Matkal]] forces arrived at the Lebanese beaches in [[Zodiac Group|Zodiac]] boats launched from missile ships offshore. [[Mossad]] agents awaited the forces on the beaches with cars rented the previous day, and then drove them to their targets and later back to the beaches for extraction.

During the operation, three of the highest-level PLO leaders, surprised at home, were killed, along with other PLO members (reports of actual number killed range up to 100){{Citation needed|date=August 2009}}. Several Lebanese security people and civilian neighbors were also killed. Two Israeli soldiers were killed.

==Main target==
The primary target of the operation was a pair of seven-story buildings in the fashionable neighborhood of Verdun in West Beirut. These buildings were residential housing for both British and Italian families along with Arab families. The building housed Muhammad Youssef Al-Najjar (Abu Youssef). The second seven-story building was on the opposite side of the road and was residential. There were two targets in this building, Kamal Adwan and Kamal Nasser.

The team attacking the target was composed predominantly of [[Sayeret Matkal]] commandos, led by then unit-commander [[Ehud Barak]] (Barak later became [[Ramatkal|IDF Chief of Staff]] and subsequently [[Prime Minister of Israel|Prime Minister]]). The attacking team also included [[Yonatan Netanyahu]], who became unit commander two years later and became known for leading the [[Operation Entebbe|hostage rescue operation in Entebbe]] in which he was killed. The team approached the buildings disguised as civilians (Barak was disguised as a [[brunette]] woman).&lt;ref&gt;Jean Genet, ''Prisoner of Love''. London: Pan Books, 1989. ISBN 0-330-29962-X. pp. 157–161. Describes the attackers who killed Kamal Adwan as: 'two English-speaking hippies with fair curly hair ...their arms around one another's necks, laughing and exchanging kisses...The guards shouted insults at the two shocking queers... etc'.&lt;/ref&gt; In the building, the team killed three PLO and Black September leaders:
* [[Muhammad Youssef al-Najjar]] (Abu Youssef) – an operations leader in the terrorist group [[Black September (group)|Black September]], the group responsible for the 1972 [[Munich massacre]]. He was also a PLO veteran, previously head of the Lebanese [[Fatah]] branches, head of Fatah internal intelligence organization. His latest duties were head of the PLO's political department and one of [[Yasser Arafat]]'s deputies (third in line of Fatah's leadership).
* [[Kamal Adwan]] – a PLO chief of operations, responsible for armed terrorist activities against Israel in the West Bank and the Gaza strip.
* [[Kamal Nasser]] – Poet, PLO spokesman and member of the PLO Executive Committee.&lt;ref&gt;Alan Hart, ''Arafat, terrorist or peacemaker?''. London: Sidgwick &amp; Jackson, 1984. ISBN 978-0-283-99008-3. pp. 361–363. Quotes Abu Iyad on the killing of Kamal Nasser:'Because Kamal was our spokesman they finished him off by spraying bullets around his mouth. And before they left the Israelis laid out his body as though he was hanging on a cross.'[Nasser was a Christian].&lt;/ref&gt;

During the operation, four others were also killed: an Italian woman who lived in the building, Abu Youssef's wife, and two Lebanese police officers.

==Secondary targets==
A separate nearby target was a multi-story building which housed militants of the [[Popular Front for the Liberation of Palestine]]. The Israeli team had 14 commandos, mainly Sayeret Tzanhanim Commando [[Paratroopers Brigade|paratroopers]] led by [[Amnon Lipkin-Shahak]], who later succeeded Barak as IDF Chief of Staff. The Israeli team met strong resistance early on, and two of its soldiers were killed. Despite this resistance, the force was able to bomb the building. Lipkin-Shahak was also decorated for bravery for his conduct in this operation.

==Popular culture==
Operation Spring of Youth was featured in the film ''[[Munich (film)|Munich]]''.

==See also==
* [[United Nations Security Council Resolution 332]]
* [[Operation Wrath of God]]
* [[Palestinian casualties of war]]
* [[Israeli casualties of war]]

==References==
&lt;references /&gt;

==External links==
* Bregman, Ahron (2002). ''Israel's Wars: A History Since 1947''. London: Routledge. ISBN 0-415-28716-2
* [http://www.jewishvirtuallibrary.org/jsource/History/opspring.html &quot;Jewish Virtual Library&quot;]: Detailed Israeli viewpoint and eyewitness accounts
* [http://www.specialoperations.com/Counterterrorism/operation_wrath_of_god.html &quot;Journal of Counterterrorism &amp; Security International&quot;]: Includes background material on the 1972 Munich Olympic Massacre and Israel's hunt for its perpetrators.
* Simon, Bob. [http://www.cbsnews.com/stories/2001/11/20/60II/main318655.shtml &quot;An Eye For An Eye: Should The U.S. Use This As A Model?&quot;], ''CBS News'', 21 November 2001. Includes short testimonies by Barak and Adwan's daughter.
* [http://www.palestine-encyclopedia.com/EPP/Chapter17_3of6.htm &quot;Encyclopedia of the Palestine Problem&quot;]: History of IDF operations vs. Palestinians from a Palestinian viewpoint, including this operation.

{{Israeli-Palestinian Conflict}}
{{Arab-Israeli Conflict}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:1973 Israeli Raid On Lebanon}}

[[Category:Assassinations]]
[[Category:Military responses by Israel to the Munich Massacre]]

[[ar:عملية فردان]]
[[cs:Operace Jaro mládí]]
[[de:Operation Frühling der Jugend]]
[[es:Operación Primavera de Juventud]]
[[he:מבצע אביב נעורים]]
[[ms:Serangan Israel ke atas Lubnan 1973]]
[[no:Operasjon Ungdommens Vår]]
[[ru:Операция «Весна молодости»]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
