<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><redirects><r from="Ultimate Edition (operating system)" to="List of Linux distributions" tofragment="Ubuntu-based" /></redirects><pages><page pageid="620709" ns="0" title="List of Linux distributions"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Refimprove|date=September 2009}}
This page provides general information about [[Wikipedia:Notability|notable]] [[Linux distributions]] in the form of a categorized list. Distributions are organized into sections by the major distribution they are based on, or the [[package management system]] they are based around.

[[Image:gldt1106.svg|thumb|right|[http://futurist.se/gldt], timeline representing the development of various Linux distributions.]]

==Debian-based==
[[Debian]] GNU/Linux is a distribution that emphasizes [[free software]]. It is supported on many hardware platforms. Debian and distributions based on it use the [[deb (file format)|.deb]] package format and the [[dpkg]] package manager.

{| class=&quot;wikitable&quot;
!   Distribution   !! Description
|-
| [[64 Studio]]
| Attempts to specialize in audio and video production on [[x86-64]] workstations.
|-
| [[aptosid]]
|  Multilingual desktop-oriented Live CD based on Debian unstable. Formerly ''sidux''.
|-
| [[BeatrIX]]
| A compact distribution from the Czech Republic that focuses on providing a user-friendly desktop environment.
|-
| [[Bharat Operating System Solutions]]
| This software is also known by the acronym BOSS GNU/Linux or simply BOSS Linux.
|-
| [[Canaima (operating system)]]
| A Venezuelan distribution.
|-
| [[Caixa Mágica]]
| A Portuguese distribution.
|-
| [[Corel Linux]]
| Commercial. Short-lived desktop distribution, bought by [[Xandros]] Linux.
|-
| [[CrunchBang Linux]]
| A formerly Ubuntu based distribution, now based on Debian Stable, featuring either the [[Openbox]] window manager or the [[Xfce]] desktop environment, with [[GTK+]] applications.
|-
| [[Dreamlinux]]
| A Brazilian Linux distribution.
|-
| [[Elive]]
| A Live CD and Distribution featuring Enlightenment as the only window manager. Aims to be intuitive and easy to use.
|-
| [[Finnix]]
| A small system administration Live CD that is available for multiple architectures.
|-
| [[Freespire]]
| A community-driven and -supported project tied to the commercial Linspire distribution. Defunct since 2007. Website offline since early 2011.
|-
| [[Gibraltar (operating system)|Gibraltar]]
| Commercial. Router/firewall distribution.
|-
| [[gnuLinEx]]
| A distribution promoted by the government of [[Extremadura]], Spain.
|-
| [[grml]]
| Live CD for system recovery
|-
| [[Hikarunix]]
| A distribution solely for studying and playing the game of [[Go (board game)|Go]]. Based on Damn Small Linux.
|-
| [[Kanotix]]
| An installable live CD for desktop usage using KDE, focusing on convenient scripts and GUI for ease of use.
|-
| [[Knoppix]]
| The first Live CD (later DVD) version of Debian GNU/Linux.
|-
| [[Kurumin]]
| Earlier, it was a version of the Knoppix distribution, modified with Debian and designed for [[Brazil]]ian users.
|-
| [[LEAF Project]]
| The Linux Embedded Appliance Framework.  A tiny primarily floppy-based distribution for routers, firewalls and other appliances.
|-
| [[LiMux]]
| An [[ISO 9241]] industry workplace certified Linux distribution, deployed at the [[Munich|City of Munich]], Germany.
|-
| [[Linspire]]
| Commercial. Desktop-oriented distribution, previously called Lindows.  Focuses on a proprietary software application manager obtained via a paid (CNR) subscription. Bought by [[Xandros]] Linux, and effectively defunct since 2007.
|-
|[[Linux Mint Debian Edition]]
|Linux Mint Debian Edition (LMDE) is a rolling distribution based on Debian Testing. It is available in both 32 and 64-bit as a live DVD with a Gnome desktop. The purpose of LMDE is to look identical to the main Linux Mint edition and to provide the same functionality while using Debian as a base.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.linuxmint.com/download_lmde.php Linuxmint.com]&lt;/ref&gt;
|-
| [[Linux Router Project]]
| A defunct floppy-based distribution for routers and firewalls. Supplanted by [[LEAF Project]].
|-
| [[Maemo]]
| A development platform for hand held devices such as the [[Nokia N800]], [[Nokia N810|N810]] and [[Nokia N900]] Internet Tablets and other Linux-based devices.
|-
| [[MEPIS]]
| Focuses on ease of use. Also includes lightweight variant called antiX. antiX is meant to be used on older computers with limited hardware.
|-
| [[MintPPC]]
| For PowerPC computers. Though MintPPC uses some Mint LXDE code, it is not Linux Mint.
|-
| [[Neopwn]] || Debian-based network [[Penetration test|penetration-testing]] distribution for mobile phones.
|-
| [[NepaLinux]]
| A Debian and Morphix based distribution focused for desktop usage in Nepali language computing.
|-
| [[OpenZaurus]]
| Debian packages and ROM image for the [[Sharp Zaurus]] [[Personal digital assistant|PDA]]. Replaced by [[Ångström distribution]].
|-
| [[Parsix]]
| Optimized for personal computers and laptops. Built on top of Debian testing branch and comes with security support.
|-
| [[Progeny Linux Systems|Progeny Componentized Linux]]
| Distribution from [[Progeny Linux Systems]] which was also founded by Debian founder [[Ian Murdock]].
|-
| [[PureOS]]
|Based on Debian Testing.
|-
| [[Pixart#Rxart|Rxart]]
| Desktop-oriented distribution. Focused on providing proprietary software.
|-
| [[Sacix]]
| A [[Debian Pure Blend]] originally created to support the educational and free software diffusion goals of the Telecentres project of the city of São Paulo, Brazil.
|-
| [[Skolelinux]]
| A distribution from Norway.  It is provided as a [[thin client]] distribution for schools.
|-
| [[Sunwah Linux]]
| A Chinese distribution
|-
| [[Symphony OS]]
| Includes the [[Mezzo (desktop environment)|Mezzo]] desktop environment. Previous versions were based on Knoppix.
|-
| [[Ubuntu (operating system)|Ubuntu]]
| A distribution sponsored by [[Canonical Ltd.]] as well as receiving major funding from South African [[Mark Shuttleworth]]. Aims to offer a complete and polished desktop on a single CD.
|-
| [[Ulteo]]|| Virtual desktop project
|-
| [[UserLinux]]
| Commercial distribution that would have included GNOME. Short-lived.
|-
| [[Vyatta]]
| Commercial open source network operating system includes routing, firewall, VPN, intrusion prevention and more. Designed to be an open source Cisco replacement.
|-
| [[Xandros|Xandros Open Circulation Edition]]
| Based on Xandros 3.0 Standard Edition. DVD burning is disabled and CD burning is restricted to a maximum speed of 4X.
|-
| [[Xebian]]
| For the Xbox home gaming console.
|}

===Knoppix-based===
[[Knoppix]], itself, is based on Debian.

{| class=&quot;wikitable&quot;
!   Distribution   !! Description
|-
| [[Feather Linux]]
| It boots from either a CD or a [[USB flash drive]]. Uses [[Knoppix]]-based hardware detection and the [[Fluxbox]] window manager.
|-
| [[Damn Small Linux]]
| It is designed to be a small distro designed to run on older hardware. It is commonly used on virtual machines due to low memory requirements.
|-
| [[Kaella]]
| The French translation of Knoppix.
|-
| [[Musix GNU/Linux]]
| A [[Knoppix]]/[[Debian]] based distribution, intended for music production, graphic design, audio, video editing, and other tasks. It is built with only [[free software]].
|}

===Ubuntu-based===
[[Ubuntu (operating system)|Ubuntu]] is a distribution based on [[Debian]].

====Official distributions====
These Ubuntu variants simply install a set of packages different from the original Ubuntu, but since they draw additional packages and updates from the same repositories as Ubuntu, all of the same software is available for each of them.

{| class=&quot;wikitable&quot;
!   Distribution   !! Description
|-
| [[Edubuntu]]
| A complete Linux-based operating system targeted for [[Primary education|primary]] and [[secondary education]]. It is freely available with community based support. The Edubuntu community is built on the ideas enshrined in the Edubuntu Manifesto: that software, especially for education, should be available [[Gratis versus Libre|free of charge]] and that software tools should be usable by people in their local language and despite any disabilities. Since version 8.04, Edubuntu has now been named '''Ubuntu Education Edition''' and has been made as an add-on for the Ubuntu operating system.
|-
| [[Gobuntu]]
| Gobuntu was an official derivative of the Ubuntu operating system, aiming to provide a distribution consisting entirely of [[free software]]. It was officially announced by Mark Shuttleworth on July 10, 2007, and daily builds of Gobuntu 7.10 began to be publicly released. The project ended around the release of 8.04 and has since merged into mainline Ubuntu as a 'free software' option.
|-
| [[Kubuntu]]
| An official derivative of Ubuntu using [[KDE]] instead of the [[GNOME]] or Unity interfaces used by default in Ubuntu.
|-
| [[Lubuntu]]
| Lubuntu is a project that is an official derivative of the [[Ubuntu (operating system)|Ubuntu]] [[operating system]] that is &quot;lighter, less resource hungry and more energy-efficient&quot;, using the [[LXDE]] [[desktop environment]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Distrowatch11May09&quot;&gt;{{Cite web|url = http://distrowatch.com/weekly.php?issue=20090511#news|title = Another day, another Ubuntu derivative.|accessdate = 2009-05-21|last = Smart|first = Chris|authorlink = |year = 2009|month = May}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;LXDEBlog&quot;&gt;{{Cite web|url = http://blog.lxde.org/?p=208|title =Lubuntu? LXDE Meet up with Mark Shuttleworth in Berlin|accessdate = 2009-05-21|last = [[LXDE]]|authorlink = |year = 2009|month = February}}&lt;/ref&gt; Requires cmov instruction capable processor to run (not all older machines support this).
|-
| [[Ubuntu JeOS]]
| &quot;Just Enough OS&quot; - described as &quot;an efficient variant [...] configured specifically for [[virtual appliance]]s&quot;.
|-
| [[Ubuntu Mobile]]
| An embedded operating system designed for use on [[mobile device]]s. The operating system will use [[Hildon]] from [[maemo]] as its [[Graphical user interface|graphical frontend]].
|-
| [[Ubuntu Netbook Edition]]&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://news.cnet.com/8301-13580_3-9950552-39.html|title=Ubuntu to announce its mobile Linux in June}}&lt;/ref&gt;
| Released in 2008, Netbook Edition is an official derivative of Ubuntu designed for [[netbook]]s using the [[Intel Atom]] processor. Starting from [[Ubuntu 11.04]], Ubuntu Netbook Edition has been merged into the desktop edition.
|-
| [[Ubuntu Server Edition]]
| An official derivative made for use in servers. Ubuntu Server handles mail, controls printers, acts as a fileserver, can host [[LAMP (software bundle)|LAMP]] and more.
|-
| [[Xubuntu]]
| An official derivative of Ubuntu using [[Xfce]]. Xubuntu is intended for use on less-powerful computers or those who seek a highly efficient desktop environment on faster systems, and uses mostly [[GTK+]] applications.
|-
|}

====Contributed distributions====
{|class=&quot;wikitable&quot;
|-
!Distribution!!Description
|-
|[[Mythbuntu]]|| Based on Ubuntu and [[MythTV]], providing applications for recording TV and acting as a media center.
|-
|[[Ubuntu Studio]]|| Based on Ubuntu, providing open-source applications for multimedia creation aimed at the audio, video and graphic editors.
|}

====Third-party distributions {{anchor|Unofficial distributions}} ====
Unofficial variants and derivatives are not controlled or guided by [[Canonical Ltd.]] and generally have different goals in mind:
{|class=&quot;wikitable&quot;
|-
!Distribution!!Description
|-
| [[Aurora (operating system)|Aurora]]|| Specifically for the Eee PC range of netbooks,  based on Debian. Previously named Eeebuntu and based on Ubuntu.
|-
| [[Beowulf (computing)#Operating systems|ABC GNU/Linux]]|| An Ubuntu-based distribution for building Beowulf clusters
|-
| [[Asturix]]|| Ubuntu-based distribution dedicated to novel people in linux.
|-
| [[Baltix]]||Ubuntu-based distribution for Lithuanian and Latvian people. Supported languages are Lithuanian, Latvian, Estonian, Russian, English, Norwegian and other around Baltic region. Main language is Lithuanian.
|-
| [[BackTrack]]
| Developed by Remote Exploit and designed for penetration testing.
|-
| [[BlankOn]]||Ubuntu-based distribution for users in Indonesia.
|-
| [[Buildix]]||An Ubuntu-based Linux distribution, developed by Global IT professional services firm, [[ThoughtWorks]]. For agile developers.
|-
| [[Bodhi Linux]]||An Ubuntu-based Linux distribution featuring the [[Enlightenment (window manager)|Enlightenment]] window manager and targeting users who want minimum of preinstalled software or low system requirements.
&lt;!--
Chromium OS is NOT based on Ubuntu. The cited links say nothing about it and Google Chrome OS is based on Gentoo.
--&gt;
&lt;!--
Canaima is based on Debian, not Ubuntu, according to their website.
--&gt;
|-
| [[dyne:bolic]]
| [[Live CD]] geared toward multimedia (audio and video) production, but comes with other non-media specific application (e.g.: word processor, desktop publisher).
|-
| [[EasyPeasy]]|| Fork of Ubuntu designed for netbooks
|-
| [[Element OS]]
| Based on [[Xubuntu]], made for [[Home theater PC]]s
|-
| [[Fluxbuntu]]||Light-weight and featuring the [[Fluxbox]] window manager
|-
| [[gNewSense]] ||Designed for users who wish to use only [[free software]]. It is officially sponsored and recommended by the [[Free Software Foundation]]. The project has also produced a set of scripts that allow anyone to create a free distribution. In 2011, gNewSense will be based on Debian and no longer on Ubuntu.
|-
| [[Goobuntu]] ||An Ubuntu-based distribution used internally by [[Google]]. Not available outside of [[Google]].
|-
| [[gOS (operating system)|gOS]]||Uses the GNOME desktop environment with user interface  enhancements to make it work more like [[Mac OS X]], it also features [[Google Apps]], [[Picasa]], [[Google Gadgets]] and other web-based applications, and comes with [[Wine (software)|Wine 1.0]] pre-installed
|-
| [[Guadalinex]]|| Ubuntu-based distribution promoted by the local government of [[Andalucia]], Spain, for home users and schools.
|-
| [[Hiweed]] || Chinese Linux distribution, based on Ubuntu. Its features include preconfigured Chinese applications, such as Chinese (simplified) input method, Chinese-English and English-Chinese dictionaries, and Chinese (simplified) true-type fonts.
|-
| [[Joli OS]]
| Joli OS (formely named Jolicloud) is in development and Pre-beta testing. Joli OS is built upon Debian and Ubuntu 9.10, but is tweaked to be more suitable for computers that have weaker specifications in terms of disk storage, memory and screen size. It is designed to run on relatively low-powered netbook computers.
|-
| [[Mobile Internet Experience|HP Mi]]|| Based on Ubuntu 8.04 LTS, designed by Canonical and HP for use on the HP Mini 1000 and 110 series netbooks.&lt;ref name=&quot;Brown 2008, HP Linux&quot;&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.linuxfordevices.com/c/a/News/HP-netbook-boasts-homegrown-Linux-distro/|title=HP netbook boasts homegrown Linux distro|last=Brown|first=Eric|date=2008-10-29 |work=LinuxDevices.com|publisher=[[Ziff Davis|Ziff Davis Enterprise Holdings Inc.]]|accessdate=2009-07-12}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|-
| [[Impi Linux]] ||[[South Africa]]n and focuses on the enterprise and government sector.
|-
| [[Karoshi (operating system)|Karoshi]] || A formerly [[PCLinuxOS]]-based distribution designed for use in schools.
|-
| [[Kuki Linux]] || Lightweight Ubuntu-based Linux distribution founded by João Ferro, built to be a replacement for the [[Linpus Linux Lite]] distribution on the [[Acer Aspire One]].
|-
| [[Leeenux Linux]]
| Based on Ubuntu, for Asus Eee PC with 7&quot; screen
|-
| [[Linux Mint]]|| Linux Mint synchronizes its release-cycle with Ubuntu's, and is tailored to user-friendliness for desktop users. Also features a Debian-based edition.
|-
| [[LinuxMCE]] (Linux Media Center Edition)|| Kubuntu based distribution that provides in-depth HTPC functionality as well as home automation.
|-
| [[LinuxTLE]]|| A Thai Linux distribution.
|-
| [[LliureX]]|| A distribution by the [[Generalitat Valenciana]]
|-
| [[LOUD]] (LCSEE Optimized Ubuntu Distribution)||An Ubuntu distribution used at [[West Virginia University]]. It contains several specialized educational packages as well as its own themes and login manager.
|-
| [[Macbuntu]]
| Macintosh OS X style derivative.
|-
| [[MAX (operating system)|MAX]]||Stands for '''MA'''drid Linu'''X'''.
|-
| [[Minimal Desktop for Ubuntu]]
| A slimmed version of the [[GNOME]]-based Ubuntu install, with a similar version for [[KDE]] and [[Fluxbox]]. It is targeted at experienced, but learning, Linux users.
|-
| [[Molinux]] ||Ubuntu based initiative to introduce the [[Castile-La Mancha]] community in Spain to the information society.
|-
| [[Moon OS]] ||Moon OS uses the Enlightenment [[window manager]] and also has an LXDE version, and is based on the LTS release.
|-
| [[Nova (operating system)|Nova]]
| [[Cuba]]n state-sponsored distribution developed at the [[University of Information Science]], [[Havana]]. Formerly based on Gentoo.
|-
| [[nUbuntu]] (Network Ubuntu)||Based on Ubuntu. Available as a [[Live CD]] and Full Install with tools needed for [[Penetration test|penetration-testing]] servers and networks.
|-
| [[OpenGEU]]|| Ubuntu based distribution with Enlightenment window manager, previously known as Geubuntu.
|-
| [[Peppermint OS]]
| A light-weight LXDE distribution for [[cloud application]]s through [[Mozilla Prism]]. Based on [[Lubuntu]]&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.peppermintos.com/release-notes/|title=About Peppermint OS}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|-
| [[PC/OS]]
| Its primary interface is Xfce but there is also a GNOME release available. There is also a release that is geared towards web centric applications.
|-
| [[Poseidon Linux]] ||For academic and scientific use. Based on Ubuntu, but enhanced by e.g. GIS/maps, numerical modelling, 2D/3D/4D visualization, statistics, tools for creating simple and complex graphics, programming languages.
|-
| [[Linux for PlayStation 3|PSUbuntu]]|| Ubuntu distribution intended for the PlayStation 3.
|-
| [[puredyne]]
|puredyne is a [[live distro]] developed to provide media artists with a complete set of tools for realtime audio and video processing.
|-
| [[Qimo 4 Kids]]|| educational games for children aged 3 and up. Ubuntu-based with easy to use interface.
|-
| [[Sabily]] ||Ubuntu based distribution for Muslims (formerly Ubuntu Muslim Edition).
|-
| [[Spri]]
| Lightweight Ubuntu derivative replacing [[GNOME]] desktop environment with lightweight [[IceWM]] window manager. Designed for aging and low powered computer hardware. Evaporated by 2011
|-
| [[Super OS]]||Aiming to provide an ‘out of the box’ experience, containing various enhancements over Ubuntu.
|-
| [[Trisquel]]
| Fully [[free software]], based on Ubuntu.
|-
| [[TurnKey Linux Virtual Appliance Library]]||Open source project developing a family of free, Ubuntu-based appliances optimized for ease of use in server-type usage scenarios.
|-
| [[U-lite]]|| Has the main goal to be very light consuming hardware resources. The last version uses the [[LXDE]] desktop environment. It was previously called ''Ubuntulite''.
|-
| [[UberStudent]]|| For higher education and advanced secondary students, those who teach them, and lifelong learners.
|-
| [[Vinux]]
| A Linux distribution designed for [[visual impairment|visually impaired]] users.
|-
| [[XBMC Live]]|| An embedded operating system with [[XBMC Media Center]] designed to make any computer into a dedicated [[Home theater PC|media center]] appliance.
|-
| [[Ylmf OS]] || Based on Ubuntu and uses a Windows XP-like design.
|-
| [[Zentyal]] || (Formely named eBox) Ubuntu Server with web based interface targeted at small business ; Router/Firewall and NAS/PDC
|-
| [[ZevenOS]] || Similar to [[BeOS]], with some extra tools.
|}

==Gentoo-based==
[[Gentoo Linux|Gentoo]] is a distribution designed to have highly optimized and frequently updated software. Distributions based on Gentoo use the [[Portage (software)|Portage]] package management system with [[Portage (software)#Emerge|emerge]] or one of the alternative package managers.

{| class=&quot;wikitable&quot;
!   Distribution   !! Description
|-
| [[Calculate Linux]]
| Calculate Linux is a family of distributions.
|-
| [[funtoo]]
| Based on Gentoo.
|-
| [[Gentoox]]
| An adaptation of Gentoo for the [[Xbox]].
|-
| [[Knopperdisk]]
| A new distribution aimed at USB sticks.
|-
| [[Pentoo]]
| Penetration-testing Live CD.
|-
| [[Sabayon Linux]]
| An installable Live DVD with multiple desktop environments. Like Gentoo, Sabayon uses the [[rolling release]] model; it uses a customized version of Red Hat's Anaconda Installer and includes a Media Center application.
|-
| [[SystemRescueCD]]
| System rescue Live CD version of Gentoo.
|-
| [[Tin Hat Linux]]
| Based on hardened Gentoo.
|-
| [[Ututo]]
| Made in [[Argentina]].
|-
| [[VidaLinux]]
| Uses [[Anaconda installer|Anaconda]] as its installer.
|-
| [[Chromium OS]]&lt;ref name=chrome&gt;{{cite web|url=https://sites.google.com/a/chromium.org/dev/chromium-os/developer-guide|title=Chromium OS Developers Guide|accessdate=May 22, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;
| [[Google Chrome OS|Google's OS]]&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.chromium.org/chromium-os/how-tos-and-troubleshooting/developer-faq|title=Chromium Project FAQ}}&lt;/ref&gt; to be used on various [[tablet computer]]s as well as netbooks and nettops. It is primarily Internet-based, launching each app within the Chrome browser. The OS uses a user interface very similar-looking to the [[Chromium (web browser)|Chrome]] internet browser instead of [[GNOME]], [[KDE]], etc.
|-
| [[Google Chrome OS]]&lt;ref name=chrome /&gt;
| Designed by Google. Available through submission of a pilot application, though source code and directions to manually build it (under the name &quot;Chromium-Based OS&quot;) are available. The Cr-48 netbook-style prototype is now available for those interested in the pilot program.  The company from which it was created is unknown, but uses intel processors. Both Chromium OS and Google Chrome OS are not directly based on Gentoo, but they use Gentoo's package managing system, [[portage (software)|portage]].&lt;ref name=chrome /&gt;
|}

==Pacman-based==
[[Pacman (package manager)|Pacman]] is a package manager that is capable of resolving dependencies and automatically downloading and installing all necessary packages. In theory, a user need only run a single command to completely update the system.

{| class=&quot;wikitable&quot;
!   Distribution   !! Description
|-
| [[Arch Linux]]
| An [[i686]]- and [[x86-64]]-optimized distribution targeted at experienced users. Arch runs on a [[rolling release]] system and uses the [[Pacman (package manager)|pacman]] utility for package management.
|-
| [[DeLi Linux]]
| A desktop based mini distribution with office suite, web browser and other graphical programs to run on a [[486]]. Built from scratch with some influences from [[Slackware]] and [[CRUX]].
|-
| [[Frugalware Linux]]
| A general purpose Linux distribution designed for intermediate users. Has some influences from Slackware, and uses a heavily modified version of the [[Pacman (package manager)|Pacman]] package manager, Pacman-G2, a fork of a [[Concurrent Versions System|cvs]] version of the complete rewrite of Pacman-G1 by Aurelien Foret (the old monolithic Pacman-G1 is written by [[Judd Vinet]]). The packages are [[tar (file format)|tar]] archives that are compressed using [[bzip2]].
|-
| [[KnoppMyth]]
| Based on Arch Linux and MythTV, providing applications for recording TV and acting as a sound and video center.
|-
| [[Parabola GNU/Linux-libre]]
| Based on Arch Linux, but provides only [[Free software|free]] packages.&lt;ref&gt;https://parabolagnulinux.org&lt;/ref&gt;
|-
|}

==RPM-based==
[[Red Hat Linux]] and [[SUSE Linux distributions|SUSE Linux]] were the original major distributions that used the [[RPM Package Manager|RPM file format]], which is today used in several package management systems.  Both of these later divided into commercial and community-supported distributions. Red Hat Linux divided into a community-supported distribution sponsored by [[Red Hat]] called [[Fedora (operating system)|Fedora]], and a commercially supported distribution called [[Red Hat Enterprise Linux]].

{| class=&quot;wikitable&quot;
!   Distribution   !! Description
|-
| [[aLinux]]
| Formerly known as Peanut Linux
|-
| [[ALT Linux]]
| Several distributions including Master, Compact, and Junior, Server, Terminal.
|-
| [[Ark Linux]]
| Ark Linux is meant to be easy enough for the new Linux user while powerful enough for long-time veterans and developers.
|-
| [[Caldera OpenLinux]]
| A distribution originally introduced by [[Caldera (company)|Caldera]] and later developed by its subsidiary [[Caldera Systems]], the later [[Caldera International]], who bought SCO and then renamed into [[The SCO Group]] and no longer produces a Linux distribution. Last release: 3.1.1 - Jan. 30, 2002
|-
| [[cAos Linux]]
| A general purpose distribution. Designed to have low overhead, run on older hardware, and be easily customizable.
|-
| [[Fedora (operating system)|Fedora]]
| Community-supported distribution sponsored by [[Red Hat]]. It usually features cutting-edge Linux technologies.
|-
| [[Linkat]]
| A distribution promoted by the government of [[Catalonia]], Spain.
|-
| [[Lycoris (company)|Lycoris]] Desktop/LX
|-
| [[Mandriva Linux]]
| Easy to use system through its unique Control Center.
|-
| [[PCLinuxOS]]
| A [[rolling release]] Live CD distribution. Originally based on Mandrake 9.2. Later rebased on [[Mandriva Linux|Mandriva]] 2007.
|-
| [[Red Hat Linux]]
| Split into [[Fedora (operating system)|Fedora Core]] and [[Red Hat Enterprise Linux]]. The last official release of the unsplit distribution was Red Hat Linux 9 in March 2003.
|-
| [[SUSE Linux distributions|SUSE Linux]]
| A [[Desktop computer|desktop]]-oriented Linux distribution by [[Novell, Inc.]], popular in Europe.
::* [[openSUSE]] - A community-developed branch, sponsored by [[Novell]]. It maintains a strict policy of ensuring all code in the standard installs will be from [[free software|Free/Libre/Open-Source Software]] solutions, including [[Linux]] kernel Modules. Novell's enterprise [[Linux]] products are all based on the codebase that comes out of the openSUSE project.
::* [[SUSE Linux Enterprise Server]] - A server-oriented Linux distribution supplied by [[Novell, Inc.]] and targeted at the business market.
::* [[SUSE Linux Enterprise Desktop]] (previously branded [[Novell Linux Desktop]]) - A desktop-oriented Linux distribution supplied by [[Novell, Inc.]] and targeted at the enterprise market.
::* SUSE Linux Enterprise Real Time - A specialized version of the SUSE distribution from Novell designed to support low latency for time critical operations.
|-
| [[Subuntu]]
| Operating system created in SUSE Studio designed to feel like [[Ubuntu (operating system)|Ubuntu]].
|-
|[[Turbolinux]]
| Based on Red Hat Linux.
|-
| [[Vine Linux]]
| A Japanese distribution based on Red Hat Linux.
|-
| [[YOPER]]
| A [[rolling release]] desktop distribution from [[New Zealand]] that focuses on optimizing system performance for workstation use.
|-
|}

===Fedora-based===
{| class=&quot;wikitable&quot;
!   Distribution   !! Description
|-
| [[Aurora SPARC Linux]]
| For Sun's SPARC architecture
|-
| [[Berry Linux]]
| A medium-sized Fedora-based distribution that provides support in Japanese and English.
|-
| [[BLAG Linux and GNU]]
| Fully [[free software]]
|-
| [[EduLinux]]
| For educational purposes
|-
| [[EnGarde Secure Linux]]
| Server-only distribution designed to be secure.&lt;ref&gt;[http://distrowatch.com/table.php?distribution=engarde DistroWatch.com: EnGarde Secure Linux]&lt;/ref&gt;
|-
| [[Fuduntu]]
| Designed to fit in somewhere between Fedora and Ubuntu.
|-
| [[Fusion Linux]]
| Distribution that has desktop usability, ease of use and latest features as top priority.&lt;ref&gt;http://fusionlinux.org/&lt;/ref&gt;
|-
| [[Hanthana (operating system)|Hanthana]]
| Designed to cater the needs of Sri Lankan computer users who are unable to access Internet frequently, with many most-wanted applications built in.
|-
| [[K12LTSP]]
| A distribution for educational purpose. Comes with [[Linux Terminal Server Project|LTSP]] support.
|-
| [[Kororaa]]
| Initially aimed at easy installation of a Gentoo system by using install scripts instead of manual configuration. Now based on Fedora.
|-
| [[Linpus Linux]]
| Focused on the Chinese market, along with Linpus Lite focused on the [[netbook]] market.
|-
| [[Moblin]]
| Built around the Intel Atom processor; supplanted by Meego when Intel and (temporarily) Nokia combined activities
|-
| [[MythDora]]
| Specialized distribution for easy setup of the MythTV PVR software, similar to KnoppMyth, based on Fedora.
|-
| [[Network Security Toolkit]]
| A Live CD/DVD with security and networking tools to perform routine security and networking diagnostic and monitoring tasks.
|-
| [[Ojuba Linux]]
| Focused on providing the best Arabic support, as well as some Islamic tools such as Hijra (Hijri calendar) and Minbar (prayer time indicator).
|-
| [[Red Hat Enterprise Linux]]
| [[Red Hat]]'s officially supported distribution. Meant for enterprise use.
|-
| [[Russian Fedora Remix]]
| A remix of Fedora.
|-
| [[Trustix]]
| A distribution focused on security.&lt;ref&gt;[http://distrowatch.com/table.php?distribution=trustix DistroWatch.com: Trustix Secure Linux]&lt;/ref&gt;
|-
| [[Xange]]
| Xange (formerly ''Simplis'', formerly ''Vixta'') is a distribution that tries to emulate the appearance of [[Windows Vista]]. It is based on [[KDE]].
|-
| [[Yellow Dog Linux]]
| For the [[PowerPC]] platform.
|}

====Red Hat Enterprise Linux-based====
{{See also|Red Hat Enterprise Linux derivatives|Commercial products based on Red Hat Enterprise Linux}}

{| class=&quot;wikitable&quot;
!   Distribution   !! Description
|-
| [[Asianux]]
| A distribution co-developed between [[Red Flag Linux|Red Flag Software]] Co., Ltd., [[Miracle Linux]] Corp. and [[Haansoft]], INC., focused on Chinese, Japanese and Korean support.
|-
| [[CentOS]]
| Community-supported distribution that aims to be compatible with Red Hat Enterprise Linux without the inclusion of proprietary software.
|-
| [[ClearOS]]
| Small Business Server. File, Print, Messaging, UTM, VPN.
|-
| [[Fermi Linux LTS]]
| Based on Scientific Linux.&lt;ref&gt;[http://distrowatch.com/table.php?distribution=fermi DistroWatch.com: Fermi Linux]&lt;/ref&gt;
|-
| [[Miracle Linux]]
| Developed by Japanese software vendor Miracle Linux Co., Ltd
|-
| [[Oracle Linux]]
| Supported by [[Oracle Corporation|Oracle]]. Aims to be fully compatible with Red Hat Enterprise Linux.
|-
| [[Red Flag Linux]]
| A distribution developed in China and optimized for the Chinese market. Based on Asianux.
|-
| [[Rocks Cluster Distribution]]
| A distribution for building a High-Performance Computing computer cluster, with a recent release supporting Cloud computing. It is based on [[Red Hat Enterprise Linux]] but with extensions to support large multi-node heterogeneous systems for clusters (HPC), Cloud, and Data Warehousing (in development).
|-
| [[Scientific Linux]]
| A distribution co-developed by [[Fermilab|Fermi National Accelerator Laboratory]] and the [[CERN|European Organization for Nuclear Research]] (CERN), which aims to be compatible with and based on [[Red Hat Enterprise Linux]].
|-
| [[SME Server]]
| Based on CentOS and targeting Small and Medium Enterprises.
|-
| [[TrixBox]]
| A Voice Over IP (VoIP) distribution based on CentOS.
|-
|}

===Mandriva Linux-based===
{| class=&quot;wikitable&quot;
!   Distribution   !! Description
|-
| [[Annvix]]
| A security-focused server distribution. Originally based on [[Mandriva Linux|Mandrake 9.2]] but has diverged a lot. Discontinued.
|-
| [[Mageia]]
| A community fork of Mandriva Linux
|-
| [[MCNLive]]
| A Mandriva-based distribution designed to run from CD or USB Flash Drive, focused on multimedia, internet, graphics.
|-
| [[Trinity Rescue Kit]]
| Aimed specifically at offline operations for Windows and Linux systems such as rescue, repair, password resets and disk cloning
|-
| [[Unity Linux]]
| Meant to be a base for custom distributions.
|}

==Slackware-based==
[[Slackware]] is known as a highly customizable distribution that stresses ease of maintenance and reliability over cutting-edge software and automated tools. Generally considered a distribution for advanced users, it is often suggested to those who want to learn the inner workings of a Linux operating system.

{| class=&quot;wikitable&quot;
!   Distribution  !! Description
|-
| [[AUSTRUMI]]
| An 108 MB bootable [[live CD]] as of version 1.9.3
|-
| [[BasicLinux]]
| A mini Linux designed to run in old PCs (386). Has a certain degree of compatibility with Slackware packages.
|-
| [[HostGIS]]
| HostGIS Linux is a Slackware based distribution specifically made for handling [[GIS]] information.
|-
| [[KateOS]]
| A desktop distribution aimed at intermediate users. It uses [[Xfce]] as its default desktop environment.
|-
| [[MuLinux]]
| Floppy-based distribution with replaceable modules.
|-
| [[NimbleX]]
| Completely customizable through the NimbleX website.
|-
| [[Recovery Is Possible]]
| [[Live CD]] for system maintenance and recovery.&lt;ref&gt;[http://distrowatch.com/table.php?distribution=rip DistroWatch.com: RIPLinuX]&lt;/ref&gt;
|-
| [[Salix OS]]
| Uses [[Xfce]] or [[LXDE]] as its default desktop environment.
|-
| [[Sentry Firewall]]
| A firewall, server or [[intrusion detection system]] distribution.
|-
| [[simpleLinux| simpleLinux GNU/Linux]]
| simpleLinux is a GNU/Linux distributions that uses LZMA compression to compress its system files. The project started on year 2007 by a group of Malaysian developer. simpleLinux is a Slackware-based distribution that comes in both Live CD or Persistence version that can be installed to a medium. simpleLinux GNU/Linux comes to be a multi-tasking operating system that runs the X Window.
|-
| [[Slackintosh]]
| An unofficial port of Slackware to the [[PowerPC]] architecture.
|-
| [[Slamd64]]
| An unofficial port of Slackware to the [[x86-64]] architecture.
|-
| [[Slax]]
| A [[live CD]] which aims to provide a complete desktop for general use. Permanent installation of Slax is not recommended or supported; it is designed for &quot;live&quot; use only. Also can be run from a usb flash drive.
|-
| [[STUX]]
| [[Live CD]]
|-
| [[SuperGamer]]
| A [[Live DVD]] Linux Distribution focused on [[Linux gaming|gaming]].
|-
| [[Topologilinux]]
| Designed to run from within [[Microsoft Windows]], Topologilinux can be installed without any changes to the user's hard disk.
|-
| [[VectorLinux]]
| A lightweight distribution designed to be easy to use even for new users. Generally considered well-suited for older hardware.
|-
| [[Wolvix]]
| A desktop-oriented Linux distribution based on Slackware, mainly targeted at home users, featuring [[Xfce]].
|-
| [[Zenwalk]]
| Originally a minimal version of Slackware, Zenwalk has evolved into a very different operating system; however, compatibility with Slackware is still maintained.
|-
| [[ZipSlack]]
| A lightweight and portable version of Slackware
|-
|}

===Slax-based===
Slax's modularity and reputation of quality have made it a popular base for other [[live CD]] projects.

{| class=&quot;wikitable&quot;
!   Distribution   !! Description
|-
| [[Emnix]]
| A Slax-based distribution focused around portability and practicality. Production has ceased and Emnix replaced with Project Esma.
|-
| [[DAVIX]]
| A live CD for data analysis and visualization.
|-
| [[DNALinux]]
| A small distribution designed for running [[bioinformatics]] software, including [[BLAST]] and [[EMBOSS]].
|}

==Others==
The following distributions are simply not categorized under the preceding sections.

{| class=&quot;wikitable&quot;
!   Distribution   !! Description
|-
| [[Alpine Linux]]
| A security-oriented, lightweight Linux distribution based on uClibc and BusyBox.
|-
| [[Bifrost (operating system)|Bifrost]]
| Small, for networking
|-
| [[Billix]]
| A live CD or live USB system administration toolkit and multi-boot distribution with the ability to install any of the included distributions.
|-
| [[Coyote Linux]]
| Router/firewall distribution.
|-
| [[CRUX]]
| CRUX is a lightweight, [[i686]]-optimized distribution targeted at experienced users. The focus is &quot;[[KISS principle|keep it simple]]&quot;, which is reflected in a simple [[tar.gz]]-based package system, [[BSD]]-style initscripts, and a relatively small collection of trimmed packages
|-
| [[DD-WRT]]
| Embedded firewall distribution.
|-
| [[Devil-Linux]]
| Router/firewall/server distribution running from CD or USB. Configuration held on USB or floppy disk.
|-
| [[DSLinux]]
| Version of Linux designed for the [[Nintendo DS]].
|-
| [[ELinOS]]
| Distribution for [[embedded system]]s by [[SYSGO]]. [[ELinOS]] focuses on industrial application and provides [[Real-time computing|real-time extensions]].
|-
| [[Endian Firewall]]
| Specializes in Routing/Firewalling and Unified Threat Management.
|-
| [[Familiar Linux]]
| Distribution for iPAQ handhelds.
|-
| [[Foresight Linux]]
| A [[rolling release]] distribution built around the [[Conary (package manager)|Conary]] package manager.
|-
| [[FREESCO]]
| A free replacement for proprietary routers supporting up to 10 network cards and up to 10 modems.
|-
| [[GeeXboX]]
| [[Live CD]] media center distribution, mainly to play special-encoded video files (e.g.: .ogg, XVID) on home theater.
|-
| [[GoboLinux]]
| An alternative distribution which redefines the [[file system]] hierarchy by installing everything belonging to one application in one folder under /Programs, and using symlinks from /System and its subfolders to point to the proper files.
|-
| [[IPCop]]
| Router/firewall distribution.
|-
| [[Iskolinux]]
| A GNU/Linux distribution packaged and maintained by UP Manila's (UPM) Information Management System as part of University of the Philippines' thrust to migrate to Linux.
|-
| [[Jlime]]
| Distribution for the [[Hewlett-Packard|HP]] [[Jornada (PDA)|Jornada]] 6xx and 7xx and [[NEC]] [[MobilePro#MobilePro_900|MobilePro 900(c)]] handhelds.
|-
| [[Lunar Linux]]
| A source code-based distribution descended from [[Sorcerer GNU/Linux]].
|-
| [[MCC Interim Linux]]
| MCC Interim Linux, possibly the first Linux distribution. Created by the Manchester Computing Centre in February 1992.
|-
| [[MkLinux]]
| A legacy distribution for [[PowerPC]] systems that runs the Linux kernel as a server on top of the [[Mach microkernel]].
|-
| [[Mobilinux]]
| By [[Montavista]] for smartphones.
|-
| [[MontaVista Linux]]
| Embedded systems distribution by [[MontaVista|MontaVista Software]].
|-
| [[NASLite]]
| a floppy-based Linux designed to turn an old computer into a simple Network Attached Storage device.
|-
| [[Nitix]]
| Developed by Net Integration Technologies Inc., Nitix claims to be the first [[Autonomic system (computing)|autonomic]] Linux-based server operating system.
|-
| [[OpenWrt]]
| Embedded firewall distribution.
|-
| [[Paldo GNU/Linux]]
| Paldo GNU/Linux uses the UPKG Package manager. Using UPKG makes Paldo a mix of a source and a binary distribution.
|-
| [[Pardus (operating system)|Pardus]]
| Developed by [[Turkish National Research Institute of Electronics and Cryptology]]. It uses PISI as package manager, COMAR as configuration framework.
|-
| [[Linux for PlayStation 2|PS2 Linux]]
| [[Sony Computer Entertainment]] distribution released officially for the [[PlayStation 2]] [[video game]] console.
|-
| [[Puppy Linux]]
| A mini distribution which runs well under low-end PCs - even under 32 MB RAM.
|-
| [[rPath]]
| A distribution built around the [[Conary (package manager)|Conary]] package manager.
|-
| [[SliTaz GNU/Linux]]
| A small desktop distribution. The [[ISO]] is under 30 MB; runs entirely in RAM; uses its own tazpkg package system.
|-
| [[Smallfoot]]
| Embedded, Gaming and Point of Sale distribution.| Developed by the Santa Cruz Operation ( SCO UNIX / SCO Group ), formerly Caldera - based on Caldera OpenLinux 3.x and 4.x binaries.
|-
| [[SmoothWall]]
| Router/firewall distribution.
|-
| [[Softlanding Linux System]]
| One of the earliest distributions, developed from 1992–1994; [[Slackware]] was originally based on it.
|-
| [[Sorcerer (operating system)|Sorcerer]]
| A source code-based distribution.
|-
| [[Source Mage GNU/Linux]]
| A source code-based distribution, descended from [[Sorcerer (Linux distribution)|Sorcerer]].
|-
| [[Stable Hybrid Release]]
| For smartphones, offering [[Enlightenment (window manager)|Enlightenment]]'s Illume user interface. It is based on FSO.
|-
| [[Thinstation]]
| Thin client distribution supporting all major connectivity protocols.
|-
| [[Tinfoil Hat Linux]]
| Bootable floppy distribution focusing on extreme security
|-
| [[Tiny Core Linux]]
| Tiny Core Linux is a minimalist (around 10 MB) Linux system focusing on providing a base system with BusyBox, FLTK and other minimalist software.
|-
| [[TinyMe]]
| Based on Unity Linux, targeted to be as lightweight as possible.
|-
| [[tomsrtbt]]
| Root boot disk.
|-
| [[Tor-ramdisk]]
| An [[i686]] [[uClibc]]-based micro Linux distribution (about 5 MB) that runs in [[Computer memory|system memory]] and whose only purpose is to host a [[Tor anonymity network|Tor]] server in an environment that maximizes security and privacy.
|-
| [[xPUD]]
| Small distribution, aimed at being simple and usable.
|-
| [[Yggdrasil Linux/GNU/X]]
| One of the oldest Linux distributions, not updated since 1995.
|}

==See also==
{{Portal|Free software}}
*[[Comparison of Linux distributions]]
*[[Comparison of netbook-oriented Linux distributions]]
*[[DistroWatch]]
*[[List of Linux distributions endorsed by the Free Software Foundation]]
*[[List of live CDs]]
*[[List of router or firewall distributions]]

==References==
{{Reflist}}

==External links==
*[http://www.thecodingstudio.com/opensource/linux/screenshots/ The Coding Studio OS Screenshots] - Screen captures of most Linux distributions
*[http://www.operating-system.org/betriebssystem/_english/os-liste.htm Operating-System.org] - Lists all known Linux distributions at a glance.

{{Linux distributions}}
{{Linux}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:List Of Linux Distributions}}
[[Category:Lists of software|Linux Distributions]]
[[Category:Linux distributions| ]]

[[ar:ملحق:قائمة توزيعات لينكس]]
[[bn:লিনাক্স ডিস্ট্রিবিউশনসমূহের তালিকা]]
[[bs:Spisak Linux distribucija]]
[[cs:Seznam distribucí Linuxu]]
[[de:Liste von Linux-Distributionen]]
[[es:Anexo:Distribuciones Linux]]
[[fa:فهرست توزیع‌های گنو/لینوکس]]
[[fr:Liste des distributions Linux]]
[[hu:Linux-disztribúciók listája]]
[[ml:ലിനക്സ് വിതരണങ്ങളുടെ പട്ടിക]]
[[ms:Senarai edaran Linux]]
[[nl:Lijst van Linuxdistributies]]
[[pt:Anexo:Lista de distribuições de Linux]]
[[ru:Список дистрибутивов Linux]]
[[simple:List of Linux distributions]]
[[sk:Zoznam distribúcií Linuxu]]
[[sl:Seznam Linux distribucij]]
[[fi:Luettelo Linux-jakelupaketeista]]
[[uk:Список дистрибутивів Лінукса]]
[[vi:Danh sách phiên bản Linux]]
[[zh:Linux发行版列表]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
