<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="1858821" ns="0" title="Ayman Nour"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Refimprove|date=August 2010}}
{{infobox officeholder
|name        = Ayman Abd El Aziz Nour&lt;br /&gt;&lt;small&gt;{{lang|ar|أيمن عبد العزيز نور}}&lt;/small&gt;
|image       = Ayman Noor.jpg
|imagesize   =
|office1     = Member of the [[People's Assembly of Egypt|Majilis Al-Sha’ab]]
|term_start1 = 1995
|term_end1   = 2005
|order1      = 
|birth_date  = {{bda|1964|12|5|df=y}}
|birth_place = [[El Mansoura, Egypt]]
|party       = [[el-Ghad]]
|religion    = [[Islam]]
|alma_mater  = [[Mansoura University]]
}}

'''Ayman Abd El Aziz Nour''' ({{lang-ar|أيمن عبد العزيز نور}}, {{IPA-arz|ˈʔæjmæn ʕæbdelˈʕaziːz ˈnuːɾ|IPA}}; born 5 December 1964) is an [[Egyptians|Egyptian]] [[politician]], a former member of the Egyptian [[People's Assembly of Egypt|Parliament]] and [[chairman]] of the [[Tomorrow Party|El Ghad]] party.

He was imprisoned in  January 2005 by the government of [[President of Egypt|President]] [[Hosni Mubarak]]. Nour was released on health grounds on February 18, 2009.&lt;ref name=&quot;Egypt's Nour released from jail&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/world/middle_east/7897703.stm|title=Egypt's Nour released from jail|date=18 February 2009|work=[[BBC News]]|publisher=[[BBC]]|accessdate=18 February 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt; Following the fall of Mubarak in the [[Egyptian Revolution of 2011|2011 Revolution]], Nour stated his intention to run for the vacant presidency.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |url=http://www.time.com/time/world/article/0,8599,2048789,00.html |title=Ruling Egypt After Mubarak: Presidential Contenders Emerge |work=TIME |date=February 12, 2011 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

In February 2011, Nour spoke of the [[1979 Israel-Egypt Peace Treaty]] and stated that &quot;[[Camp David Accords|Camp David]] is over&quot; and that the agreement should be revised because &quot;it is an old treaty and its terms must correspond with Egypt's interests.&quot; &lt;ref&gt;http://exciledpalestiniane.wordpress.com/2011/02/14/ayman-nour-calls-for-revision-of-israel-peace-treaty/&lt;/ref&gt;

== Background ==

Nour was born in the city of [[El Mansoura, Egypt|Mansoura]] in 1964. His father was a lawyer and a former Member of Parliament and his mother established and supervised a number of charity projects in Mansoura. He had been married to Gamila Ismail who also served as the vice president to the [[El-Ghad Party]].&lt;ref&gt;Gaweesh, Mahmoud [http://www.almasryalyoum.com/en/news/nour-have-coptic-woman-vp Nour to have Coptic woman for VP] al-Masry al-Youm. 6 April 2010&lt;/ref&gt;

== Formation of El Ghad ==

'''The El Ghad''' party was formally recognized by the Egyptian government on October 27, 2004. Following its creation, Nour was elected president of the party at its first convention a few days later. His prominence as an independent MP made him the star of the party and one of the driving forces behind its organization. Nour fought hard to get the party recognized; its application was rejected three times before official status was finally granted.

The party was created to represent a [[liberal democrat]]ic perspective, with a strong interest in [[human rights]] issues. Nour used the party as a platform to call for constitutional reform, limiting the president's powers and opening presidential elections to multiple candidates.

== Arrest and imprisonment ==

Nour was stripped of his [[parliamentary immunity]] and arrested on January 29, 2005. He was charged with forging PAs (Powers of Attorney) to secure the formation of the el-Ghad party. Nour vehemently denied the charges (from prison).

The arrest, occurring in an election year, was widely criticized by governments around the world as a step backwards for Egyptian democracy. Few seem to regard the charges as legitimate. Nour remained active despite his imprisonment, using the opportunity to write critical articles and make his case and cause better known.

In February 2005, [[Condoleezza Rice]] abruptly postponed a visit to Egypt, reflecting U.S. displeasure at the jailing of Nour, who was reported to have been brutally interrogated.&lt;ref&gt;Kessler, Glen [http://www.washingtonpost.com/wp-dyn/articles/A54613-2005Feb25.html Rice Drops Plans for Visit to Egypt] Washington Post February 26, 2005; Retrieved March 15, 2007&lt;/ref&gt; That same month, the government announced the following month that it would open elections to multiple candidates.

In March 2005, following a strong intervention in Cairo by a group of Members of the European Parliament led by Vice-President Edward McMillan-Scott (UK, Conservative), Nour was freed and began a campaign for the Egyptian presidency.&lt;ref&gt;Williams, Daniel [http://www.washingtonpost.com/wp-dyn/articles/A29477-2005Mar12.html Egypt Frees An Aspiring Candidate Presidential Hopeful Is Released on Bail] The Washington Post March 13, 2005; Retrieved March 20, 2007&lt;/ref&gt;

Nour was the first runner-up in the [[Egyptian presidential election, 2005|2005 presidential election]] with 7% of the vote according to government figures and estimated at 13% by independent observers, although no independent observers were allowed to monitor the elections.

On December 24, 2005 he was sentenced to five years in jail. Though [[diabetes|diabetic]], Nour engaged in a two-weeks long hunger strike to protest his trial.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.globalsecurity.org/wmd/library/news/egypt/egypt-051224-voa01.htm Former Egyptian Presidential Candidate Sentenced to 5 Years Hard Labor] Voice of America December 24, 2005&lt;/ref&gt;

Nour's verdict and sentencing made global headlines and were the first item of news on most international news broadcasts, including the [[BBC]].

On the day of Nour's guilty verdict and sentencing, the [[White House Press Secretary]] released the following statement denouncing the government's action:&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |title=Statement on Conviction of Egyptian Politician Ayman Nour |url=http://georgewbush-whitehouse.archives.gov/news/releases/2005/12/20051224-1.html |date=2005-12-24 |publisher=[[National Archives and Records Administration|U.S. National Archives]] |accessdate=2009-06-06}}&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;The United States is deeply troubled by the conviction today of Egyptian politician Ayman Nour by an Egyptian court. The conviction of Mr. Nour, the runner-up in Egypt's 2005 presidential elections, calls into question Egypt's commitment to democracy, freedom, and the rule of law. We are also disturbed by reports that Mr. Nour's health has seriously declined due to the hunger strike on which he has embarked in protest of the conditions of his trial and detention.
The United States calls upon the Egyptian government to act under the laws of Egypt in the spirit of its professed desire for increased political openness and dialogue within Egyptian society, and out of humanitarian concern, to release Mr. Nour from detention.&lt;/blockquote&gt;

In February 2006, Rice visited [[Hosni Mubarak]] yet never spoke Nour's name publicly. When asked about him at a news conference, she referred to his situation as one of Egypt's setbacks. Days later, Mubarak told a government newspaper that Rice &quot;didn't bring up difficult issues or ask to change anything.&quot; From prison, Nour stated &quot;I pay the price when [Rice] speaks [of me], and I pay the price when she doesn't,&quot; Nour said. &quot;But what's happening to me now is a message to everybody.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Spolar, Christine [http://search.ebscohost.com/ Egypt reformer feels iron hand of the law] Chicago Tribune (IL); 03/06/2006, Retrieved March 20, 2007&lt;/ref&gt;

In June 2007 President Bush, speaking at a conference of dissidents in the Czech Republic, revisited the issue of Ayman Nour, saying:&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |title=President Bush Visits Prague, Czech Republic, Discusses Freedom |url=http://georgewbush-whitehouse.archives.gov/news/releases/2007/06/20070605-8.html |date=2007-06-05 |publisher=U.S. National Archives |accessdate=2009-06-06}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;blockquote&gt;There are many dissidents who couldn't join us because they are being unjustly imprisoned or held under house arrest. I look forward to the day when a conference like this one include Alexander Kozulin of Belarus, Aung San Suu Kyi of Burma, Oscar Elias Biscet of Cuba, Father Nguyen Van Ly of Vietnam, Ayman Nour of Egypt. (Applause.) The daughter of one of these political prisoners is in this room. I would like to say to her, and all the families: I thank you for your courage. I pray for your comfort and strength. And I call for the immediate and unconditional release of your loved ones.
...
I have asked Secretary Rice to send a directive to every U.S. ambassador in an un-free nation: Seek out and meet with activists for democracy. Seek out those who demand human rights.&lt;/blockquote&gt;

Nour was released on health grounds on 18 February 2009.&lt;ref name=&quot;Egypt's Nour released from jail&quot;/&gt; He was injured in the Egyptian protests of January 28 2011, where he received a stone in the head. He is being currently treated in a hospital in [[Agouza]].

== Party leadership ==

Soon after, some members of the Tomorrow Party removed Nour from the presidency (a move which is supported by the Egyptian government and Nour's political opponents), but Nour is still the official president of &quot;El Ghad Party&quot;. Today, the Council of the State is looking into the case filed by the divided party, taking into consideration that Nour is still officially the president and the other members were expelled from the party three days before their actions (which included claiming that they are the leaders of &quot;El Ghad Party&quot; and issuing a party newspaper opposing the law of press production and also entering the parliament elections under the &quot;El Ghad&quot; name despite the fact that they were expelled).

In November 2007, Gamila Ismail, wife of Ayman Nour, announced her resignation from her position as deputy chairman of the party without giving much more detail.&lt;ref&gt;El-Masry El-Youm. [http://www.almasry-alyoum.com/article.aspx?ArticleID=82364 Gamila Ismail resigns].&lt;/ref&gt;

== Current life ==

Nour currently resides in Egypt. He was recently attacked after another attempt for running for presidency.{{Citation needed|date=February 2011}}

== See also == 

{{Portal box|Egypt|Human rights}}

* [[Asmaa Mahfouz]]
* [[Kefaya]]
* [[Tomorrow Party]]
* [[Saad Eddin Ibrahim]]
* [[Nonviolent resistance]]
* [[2011 Egyptian protests]]

== Notes ==

{{Reflist}}

== External links ==

{{Commons category|Ayman Nour}}

* [http://www.freeaymannour.org/ Petition to free Ayman Nour]
* [http://www.elghad.org/ &quot;El Ghad&quot; website]
* [http://www.meforum.org/article/753 Dissident Watch Profile]
* [http://hrw.org/english/docs/2005/12/07/egypt12161.htm Human Rights watch: Ayman Nur Trial Badly Flawed; Judge Jails Opposition Leader, Others, Without Explanation]
* [http://www.metimes.com/storyview.php?StoryID=20070123-052001-9488r Egypt's Nur says government wants him to die in jail]
* [http://en.qantara.de/webcom/show_softlink.php/_c-311/_lkm-2887/i.html Ayman Nour Released: New Impetus for Egypt's Opposition?] (Qantara.de)
* [http://www.qantara.de/webcom/show_article.php/_c-476/_nr-1125/i.html Interview with Ayman Nour: &quot;I Won't Wait for the Regime to Give Me Its Blessings!&quot;]

{{Egyptian Revolution of 2011}}
{{2010–2011 Middle East and North Africa protests}}
{{Egypt topics}}
{{Persondata &lt;!-- Metadata: see [[Wikipedia:Persondata]]. --&gt;
| NAME              = Nour, Ayman
| ALTERNATIVE NAMES = 
| SHORT DESCRIPTION = Egyptian politician
| DATE OF BIRTH     = December 5, 1964
| PLACE OF BIRTH    = [[El Mansoura, Egypt]]
| DATE OF DEATH     = 
| PLACE OF DEATH    = 
}}
{{DEFAULTSORT:Nour, Ayman}}
[[Category:Articles created via the Article Wizard]]
[[Category:Members of the People's Assembly of Egypt]]
[[Category:Egyptian democracy activists]]
[[Category:1964 births]]
[[Category:Living people]]
[[Category:Egyptian prisoners and detainees]]
[[Category:Prisoners and detainees of Egypt]]
[[Category:El-Ghad Party politicians]]
[[Category:People of the 2011 Egyptian revolution]]
[[Category:Egyptian presidential candidates, 2005]]

[[ar:أيمن نور]]
[[ca:Ayman Nour]]
[[de:Aiman Nur]]
[[es:Ayman Nour]]
[[eo:Aiman Nur]]
[[fa:ایمن نور]]
[[fr:Ayman Nour]]
[[id:Ayman Nour]]
[[it:Ayman Nur]]
[[arz:ايمن نور]]
[[ms:Ayman Nour]]
[[no:Ayman Nour]]
[[fi:Ayman Nour]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
