<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><redirects><r from="List of software license violations" to="Copyright infringement" /></redirects><pages><page pageid="18948365" ns="0" title="Copyright infringement"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve"> {{For|information on handling copyright concerns in Wikipedia|Wikipedia:Copyright violations}}
{{redirect|Illegal Music|the record label|Illegal Musik}}
[[Image:Copyrightpirates.jpg|thumb|right|An advertisement for copyright and patent [[Legal document assistant|preparation services]] from 1906, when copyright registration formalities were still required in the US.]]

'''Copyright infringement''' is the unauthorized or prohibited use of works under [[copyright]], infringing the copyright holder's [[exclusive right]]s, such as the right to reproduce or perform the copyrighted work, or to make [[derivative work]]s.

== &quot;Piracy&quot; ==
The practice of labelling the infringement of exclusive rights in creative works as &quot;piracy&quot; predates statutory copyright law. Prior to the [[Statute of Anne]] 1709, the [[Stationers' Company]] of London in 1557 received a [[Royal Charter]] giving the company a [[monopoly]] on publication and tasking it with enforcing the charter. Those who violated the charter were labelled pirates as early as 1603.&lt;ref&gt;T. Dekker Wonderfull Yeare 1603 [http://www.luminarium.org/renascence-editions/yeare.html University of Oregon]&lt;/ref&gt; After the establishment of copyright law with the 1709 [[Statute of Anne]] in Britain, the term &quot;piracy&quot; has been used to refer to the unauthorized manufacturing and selling of works in copyright.&lt;ref name=Panethiere_p2&gt;{{Cite web| last = Panethiere| first = Darrell| title = The Persistence of Piracy: The Consequences for Creativity, for Culture, and for Sustainable Development| publisher = UNESO e-Copyright Bulletin| date = July – September 2005| pages=2| url = http://portal.unesco.org/culture/en/files/28696/11513329261panethiere_en.pdf/panethiere_en.pdf}}&lt;/ref&gt; Article 12 of the 1886 [[Berne Convention for the Protection of Literary and Artistic Works]] uses the term &quot;piracy&quot; in relation to copyright infringement, stating &quot;Pirated works may be seized on importation into those countries of the Union where the original work enjoys legal protection.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web| last = Panethiere| first = Darrell| title = The Persistence of Piracy: The Consequences for Creativity, for Culture, and for Sustainable Development| publisher = UNESO e-Copyright Bulletin| date = July – September 2005| pages = 14| url = http://portal.unesco.org/culture/en/files/28696/11513329261panethiere_en.pdf/panethiere_en.pdf}}&lt;/ref&gt; Article 61 of the 1994 [[Agreement on Trade-Related Aspects of Intellectual Property Rights]] (TRIPs) requires [[criminal]] procedures and penalties in cases of &quot;wilful trademark counterfeiting or copyright piracy on a commercial scale&quot;.&lt;ref name=Xuan_p208&gt;{{Cite book| last = Correa| first = Carlos Maria| coauthors = Li, Xuan| title = Intellectual property enforcement: international perspectives| publisher = Edward Elgar Publishing | year = 2009| pages = 208| url = http://books.google.com/books?id=bN3o1uwpKF4C&amp;dq=copyright+infringement+international+acta&amp;source=gbs_navlinks_s| isbn = 9781848446632 }}&lt;/ref&gt; Piracy traditionally refers to acts intentionally committed for financial gain, though more recently, copyright holders have described online copyright infringement, particularly in relation to [[peer-to-peer file sharing]] networks, as &quot;piracy.&quot;&lt;ref name=Panethiere_p2/&gt;

== &quot;Theft&quot; ==
[[Image:Piracy is a crime - Unskippable Anti-Piracy track.png|thumb|An unskippable anti-piracy film included on some movie [[DVD]]s equates copyright infringement with [[theft]].]]
Copyright holders frequently refer to copyright infringement as &quot;theft&quot;. In copyright law, infringement does not refer to actual [[theft]], but an instance where a person exercises one of the exclusive rights of the copyright holder without authorization.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book| last = Clough| first = Jonathan | title = Principles of Cybercrime | publisher = Cambridge University Press | year = 2010| pages = 221| url = http://books.google.com/books?id=JVPnCqEuTksC&amp;dq=copyright+infringement+theft&amp;source=gbs_navlinks_s| isbn = 9780521728126 }}&lt;/ref&gt; Courts have distinguished between copyright infringement and theft, holding, for instance, in the [[Supreme Court of the United States|United States Supreme Court]] case ''[[Dowling v. United States (1985)|Dowling v. United States]]'' ([[1985]]) that bootleg phonorecords did not constitute stolen property and that &quot;...interference with copyright does not easily equate with theft, [[Conversion (law)|conversion]], or fraud. The Copyright Act even employs a separate term of art to define one who misappropriates a copyright... 'an infringer of the copyright.'&quot; In the case of copyright infringement the province guaranteed to the copyright holder by copyright law is invaded, i.e. exclusive rights, but no control, physical or otherwise, is taken over the copyright, nor is the copyright holder wholly deprived of using the copyrighted work or exercising the exclusive rights held.&lt;ref&gt;''Dowling v. United States'' (1985), 473 U.S. 207, pp. 217–218.&lt;/ref&gt;

== Enforcement responsibility ==
The enforcement of copyright is the responsibility of the copyright holder.&lt;ref name=Xuan_p211&gt;{{Cite book| last = Correa| first = Carlos Maria| coauthors = Li, Xuan| title = Intellectual property enforcement: international perspectives| publisher = Edward Elgar Publishing | year = 2009| pages = 211| url = http://books.google.com/books?id=bN3o1uwpKF4C&amp;dq=copyright+infringement+international+acta&amp;source=gbs_navlinks_s| isbn = 9781848446632 }}&lt;/ref&gt; Article 50 of the [[Agreement on Trade-Related Aspects of Intellectual Property Rights]] (TRIPs) requires that signatory countries enable [[courts]] to remedy copyright infringement with injunctions and the destruction of infringing products, and award damages.&lt;ref name=Xuan_p208&gt;{{Cite book| last = Correa| first = Carlos Maria| coauthors = Li, Xuan| title = Intellectual property enforcement: international perspectives| publisher = Edward Elgar Publishing | year = 2009| pages = 208| url = http://books.google.com/books?id=bN3o1uwpKF4C&amp;dq=copyright+infringement+international+acta&amp;source=gbs_navlinks_s| isbn = 9781848446632 }}&lt;/ref&gt; Copyright holders have started to demand through the [[Anti-Counterfeiting Trade Agreement|ACTA trade agreement]] that states act to defend copyright holders' rights and enforce copyright law through active policing of copyright infringement&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web| title = The Anti-Counterfeiting Trade Agreement – Summary of Key Elements Under Discussion| work = transparency paper| publisher = Swiss federation of Intellectual Property| date = Status November 2009| url = https://www.ige.ch/fileadmin/user_upload/Juristische_Infos/e/transparency_paper.pdf| format = pdf| accessdate = 8 June 2010 }}&lt;/ref&gt;. It has also been demanded that states provide criminal sanctions for all types of copyright infringement and pursue copyright infringement through administrative procedures, rather than the judicial due process required by TRIPs.&lt;ref name=Xuan_p211/&gt;

== Criminal liability ==
Article 61 of the [[Agreement on Trade-Related Aspects of Intellectual Property Rights]] (TRIPs) requires that signatory countries establish [[criminal]] procedures and penalties in cases of &quot;willful trademark counterfeiting or copyright piracy on a commercial scale&quot;.&lt;ref name=Xuan_p208/&gt; Copyright holders have demanded that states provide criminal sanctions for all types of copyright infringement.&lt;ref name=Xuan_p211/&gt;

== Online intermediary liability ==
Whether or not internet intermediaries have liability for copyright infringement by users, and without the intermediaries' authorisation, has been subject to debate and court cases in a number of countries.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web| last = Edwards| first = Lilian | last2 = Waelde| first2 = Charlotte| title = Online Intermediaries and Liability for Copyright Infringement| work = Keynote paper at WIPO Workshop on Online Intermediaries and Liability for Copyright, Geneva| publisher = World Intellectual Property Organisation (WIPO)| year = 2005| page = 2| url = http://www.era.lib.ed.ac.uk/bitstream/1842/2305/1/wipo-onlineintermediaries.pdf| format = pdf| accessdate = September 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; Liability of online intermediaries has been one of the earliest legal issues surrounding the internet. Early court cases focused on the liability of [[internet service providers]] (ISPs) for hosting, transmitting or publishing content that could be actioned under civil or criminal law, such as [[libel]], [[defamation]], or [[pornography]].&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web| last = Edwards| first = Lilian | last2 = Waelde| first2 = Charlotte| title = Online Intermediaries and Liability for Copyright Infringement| work = Keynote paper at WIPO Workshop on Online Intermediaries and Liability for Copyright, Geneva| publisher = World Intellectual Property Organisation (WIPO)| year = 2005| page = 4| url = http://www.era.lib.ed.ac.uk/bitstream/1842/2305/1/wipo-onlineintermediaries.pdf| format = pdf| accessdate = September 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; As different content was considered in different legal systems and in the absence of common definitions for &quot;ISPs&quot;, &quot;bulletin boards&quot; or &quot;online publishers&quot;, early law on online intermediaries' liability is widely different from country to country. The first laws on online intermediaries' liability were passed from the mid 1990s onwards and the debate has shifted away from questions about whether internet intermediaries are liable for different content, such as libellous content or copyright infringing content, towards a debate on whether online intermediaries should generally be made responsible for content accessible through their services or infrastructure.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web| last = Edwards| first = Lilian | last2 = Waelde| first2 = Charlotte| title = Online Intermediaries and Liability for Copyright Infringement| work = Keynote paper at WIPO Workshop on Online Intermediaries and Liability for Copyright, Geneva| publisher = World Intellectual Property Organisation (WIPO)| year = 2005| page = 5| url = http://www.era.lib.ed.ac.uk/bitstream/1842/2305/1/wipo-onlineintermediaries.pdf| format = pdf| accessdate = September 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Image:Torrentcomp small.gif|thumb|300px|alt=Animation showing 7 remote computers exchanging data with an 8th (local) computer over a network. |The [[BitTorrent (protocol)|BitTorrent protocol]]: In this animation, the colored bars beneath all of the 7 clients in the upper region above represent the file, with each color representing an individual piece of the file. After the initial pieces transfer from the seed (large system at the bottom), the pieces are individually transferred from client to client. The original ''seeder'' only needs to send out one copy of the file for all the clients to receive a copy. &lt;small&gt;''To stop animation, click browser's Stop or hit ESC key.&lt;/small&gt;]]
Internet intermediaries used to be understood primarily in terms of [[internet service providers]] (ISPs), however, internet intermediaries are now also understood to be [[internet portals]], software and games providers, those providing virtual information such as interactive forums and comment facilities with or without a [[moderation system]], [[aggregator (disambiguation)|aggregators]], [[universities]], [[libraries]] and [[archives]], [[web search engines]], [[chat rooms]], [[web blogs]], [[mailing lists]], and any website which provides access to third party content through, for example, [[hyperlinks]]. Questions of liability have emerged in relation to internet communications infrastructure intermediaries other than ISPs, including internet backbone providers, cable companies and mobile communications providers.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web| last = Edwards| first = Lilian | last2 = Waelde| first2 = Charlotte| title = Online Intermediaries and Liability for Copyright Infringement| work = Keynote paper at WIPO Workshop on Online Intermediaries and Liability for Copyright, Geneva| publisher = World Intellectual Property Organisation (WIPO)| year = 2005| pages = 5–6| url = http://www.era.lib.ed.ac.uk/bitstream/1842/2305/1/wipo-onlineintermediaries.pdf| format = pdf| accessdate = September 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The US [[Digital Millennium Copyright Act]] (1998) and the European [[E-Commerce Directive]] (2000) provide online intermediaries with [[safe harbor]] provisions, known as mere conduit principle in the Directive. Online intermediaries who host content that infringes copyright are not liable, so long as they do not know about it and take actions once the infringing content is brought to their attention. However, questions have arisen in relation to online intermediaries that are not hosts, particularly in the context of copyright infringement through [[peer-to-peer file sharing]] networks. Such intermediaries may be regarded as enabling or assisting in the downloading and uploading of files by users, and may include the writer of a [[peer-to-peer]] software, the websites that allow users to download peer-to-peer software, and in the case of the [[BitTorrent (protocol)|BitTorrent protocol]] the torrent site website and the [[torrent tracker]]. These intermediaries do not host or transmit the files that infringe copyright, though they may be considered to be &quot;pointing to&quot; the files. Since the late 1990s copyright holders have taken legal actions against a number of peer-to-peer intermediaries, such as [[Napster]], [[Grokster]], [[eMule]], [[SoulSeek]] and [[BitTorrent (company)|BitTorrent]], and case law on the liability of internet service providers (ISPs) in relation to copyright infringement has emerged primarily in relation to these cases.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web| last = Edwards| first = Lilian | last2 = Waelde| first2 = Charlotte| title = Online Intermediaries and Liability for Copyright Infringement| work = Keynote paper at WIPO Workshop on Online Intermediaries and Liability for Copyright, Geneva| publisher = World Intellectual Property Organisation (WIPO)| year = 2005| page = 7| url = http://www.era.lib.ed.ac.uk/bitstream/1842/2305/1/wipo-onlineintermediaries.pdf| format = pdf| accessdate = September 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The decentralised structure of [[peer-to-peer networks]] does not sit easily with existing laws on online intermediaries' liability. The BitTorrent protocol established an entirely decentralised network architecture in order to distribute large files effectively and recent developments in [[peer-to-peer]] technology towards more complex network configurations are said to have been driven by a desire to avoid liability as intermediaries under existing laws.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web| last = Edwards| first = Lilian | last2 = Waelde| first2 = Charlotte| title = Online Intermediaries and Liability for Copyright Infringement| work = Keynote paper at WIPO Workshop on Online Intermediaries and Liability for Copyright, Geneva| publisher = World Intellectual Property Organisation (WIPO)| year = 2005| page = 9| url = http://www.era.lib.ed.ac.uk/bitstream/1842/2305/1/wipo-onlineintermediaries.pdf| format = pdf| accessdate = September 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; While ISPs and other organisations acting as online intermediaries, such as libraries, have been given protection under existing safe harbor provisions in relation to copyright infringement, [[peer-to-peer file sharing]] intermediaries have been denied access to the safe harbor provisions in relation to copyright infringement. Legal action in relation to copyright infringement against peer-to-peer intermediaries, such as [[Napster]], are generally brought in relation to principles of [[secondary liability]] for copyright infringement, such as [[contributory liability]] and [[vicarious liability]].&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web| last = Edwards| first = Lilian | last2 = Waelde| first2 = Charlotte| title = Online Intermediaries and Liability for Copyright Infringement| work = Keynote paper at WIPO Workshop on Online Intermediaries and Liability for Copyright, Geneva| publisher = World Intellectual Property Organisation (WIPO)| year = 2005| page = 10| url = http://www.era.lib.ed.ac.uk/bitstream/1842/2305/1/wipo-onlineintermediaries.pdf| format = pdf| accessdate = September 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Countries where sharing files without profit is legal===
Downloading copied music is legal in some countries, such as [[Canada]],&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url = http://www.cbc.ca/news/yourinterview/2008/04/michael_geist.html | title = Your Interview: Michael Geist | date = 2008-04-07 | publisher = [[Canadian Broadcasting Corporation]]}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[The Netherlands]],&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | title = In depth: Downloading music | url = http://www.cbc.ca/news/background/internet/downloading_music.html | date = 2006-05-01 | publisher = [[Canadian Broadcasting Corporation]]}}&lt;/ref&gt; Spain,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web| title = La red P2P es legal | url = http://www.bufetalmeida.com/upload/file/sentenciaelrincondejesus.pdf| format = pdf| accessdate = May 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; and Panama, provided that the songs are not sold.

===Russian law===
Downloading music and films for home use is legal due to exception provided by section 1273 of Russian Federation Civil Code. A special 1% compensatory levy intended for copyright holders is collected from the price of certain goods (like computers or clean CD-RW disks). {{citation needed|date=November 2010}} The compensation mechanism is unclear, though, and left entirely in the hands of the collecting agency established at the same time, with Nikita Mikhalkov, a prominent film director and political figure, at its helm.

== See also ==
{{too many see alsos|date=November 2011}}
For a substantial discussion of copyright infringement in the domain of computer programs, see [[copyright infringement of software]].
{{div col|3}}
* [[Anti-Counterfeiting Trade Agreement]] (ACTA)
* [[Anti-piracy]]
* [[Bootleg recording]]
* [[Chan Nai-ming]]
* [[Copyfraud]]
* [[Copyright, Designs and Patents Act 1988]]
* [[Copyrighted content on file sharing networks]]
* [[Counterfeit]]
* [[Don't Copy That Floppy]]
* [[Fair Use]]
* [[Federation Against Copyright Theft]] (FACT)
* [[Home Taping is Killing Music]]
* [[International Federation of the Phonographic Industry|IFPI]] (International Federation of Phonogram and Videogram Producers)
* [[Impact of illegal downloading on the film industry]]
* [[Intellectual property infringement in the People's Republic of China]]
* [[Internet Privacy Act]]
* [[Online Copyright Infringement Liability Limitation Act]] in the United States
* [[Plagiarism]]
* [[R2C2]]
* [[Radio music ripping]]
* [[Substantial similarity]]
* [[Warez]]
* [[World Anti-Piracy Observatory]] (WAPO)
* [[You can click, but you can't hide]]
* [[Center for Copyright Information]]
{{div col end}}

==References==
&lt;!-- ----------------------------------------------------------
  See http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Wikipedia:Footnotes for a
  discussion of different citation methods and how to generate
  footnotes using the &lt;ref&gt;, &lt;/ref&gt; and  &lt;reference /&gt; tags
----------------------------------------------------------- --&gt;
{{reflist|2}}

==Further reading==
* Johns, Adrian: ''Piracy. The Intellectual Property Wars from Gutenberg to Gates''. [[The University of Chicago Press]], 2009, ISBN 978-0-226-40118-8
* {{cite book | last = Rosen | first = Ronald | title = Music and Copyright | publisher = Oxford University Press | location = Oxford Oxfordshire | year = 2008 | isbn = 0195338367 }}
* {{cite book|editor=Joe Karaganis|title=[[Media Piracy in Emerging Economies]]|year=2011|publisher=Social Science Research Council|isbn=978-0-9841257-4-6}}

==External links==
* [http://archive.salon.com/tech/feature/2000/06/14/love/print.html A 2000 Salon.com article by Courtney Love addressing copyright infringement of music]
* [http://www.baen.com/library/palaver4.htm A 2001 reprint of two speeches given by Thomas Macaulay in Parliament in 1841, when the issue of copyright was being hammered out.]
* [http://www.cluas.com/music/features/piracy_china.htm A 2003 article on CD Piracy in China from the music webzine www.CLUAS.com]
* [http://www.tweakguides.com/Piracy_1.html A 2008 article illustrating the effect of piracy on video games]
* [http://www.plagiarismchecker.com/plagiarism-vs-copyright.php An article for students explaining the difference between plagiarism and copyright infringement]
* [http://www.commondreams.org/views02/0119-04.htm How Corporate Law Inhibits Social Responsibility]
* [http://www.mp3newswire.net/stories/6002/250billion.html Movie and Record Industry Piracy Figures Incendiary, But Not Fact.] – June 2006 [[MP3 Newswire]] article challenges inflated copyright infringement claims by media companies
* [http://www.copyright.gov/title17/92chap5.html US Copyright Office]

{{Intellectual property activism}}
{{Copyright law by country}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Copyright Infringement}}
[[Category:Copyright law|Infringement]]
[[Category:Crimes]]
[[Category:Organized crime]]
[[Category:Tort law]]
[[Category:Copyright infringement|*]]

[[ar:انتهاك حقوق الطبع والنشر]]
[[az:Müəllif hüquqlarının pozulması]]
[[ca:Pirateria]]
[[da:Piratkopiering]]
[[de:Urheberrechtsverletzung]]
[[es:Infracción de copyright]]
[[ext:Pirateria (derechus d'autol)]]
[[fr:Infraction au droit d'auteur]]
[[gl:Piratería (dereito de autor)]]
[[he:הפרת זכויות יוצרים]]
[[ko:저작권 침해]]
[[ms:Cetak rompak]]
[[nl:Piraterij (intellectuele eigendomsrechten)]]
[[ja:著作権侵害]]
[[no:Illegal kopiering]]
[[nn:Piratkopi]]
[[pt:Pirataria moderna]]
[[pl:Piractwo medialne]]
[[ru:Нарушение авторского права]]
[[simple:Copyright infringement]]
[[sl:Kršitev avtorskih pravic]]
[[fi:Tekijänoikeusloukkaus]]
[[sv:Piratkopiering]]
[[th:การละเมิดลิขสิทธิ์]]
[[uk:Піратство (інтелектуальна власність)]]
[[vi:Vi phạm bản quyền]]
[[zh-yue:版權侵害]]
[[zh:盗版]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
