<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="1859" ns="0" title="Arizona State University"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Infobox university
|name         = Arizona State University
|image_name   = Arizona State University seal.svg
|caption      = [[Seal (device)|Seal]] of Arizona State University
|image_size   = 200px
|established  = February 26, 1885
|type         = [[Public university|Public]] [[research university]]
|former_names = Tempe Normal School,&lt;br&gt;Arizona State College
|calendar     = Semester
|president    = [[Michael M. Crow]]
|provost      = [[Elizabeth D. &quot;Betty&quot; Capaldi|Elizabeth D. Capaldi]]
|city         = [[Phoenix metropolitan area]]
|state        = [[Arizona]]
|country      = [[United States|U.S.]]
|endowment    = [[United States dollar|$]]441 [[1000000 (number)|million]] &lt;ref name=Foundation&gt;[http://annualreport.asu.edu/financials-endowments-supporting-asu.html Arizona State University]&lt;/ref&gt;
|faculty      = 2,862 &lt;ref name=Employees&gt;[http://www.asu.edu/uoia/pubs/factbook/Employ.pdf ASU Employees]. 2007. Accessed May 2, 2008.&lt;/ref&gt;
|students     = 70,440 (Total) &lt;ref name=enroll10/&gt;
|undergrad    = 56,562 &lt;ref name=enroll10/&gt;
|postgrad     = 13,878 &lt;ref name=enroll10/&gt;
|campus       = [[Urban design|Urban]]&lt;br /&gt;Tempe: {{convert|631.6|acre|km2}}&lt;ref name=&quot;Tempe land&quot;&gt;ASU University Office of Institutional Analysis. September 24, 2008&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Polytechnic: {{convert|612.99|acre|km2}}&lt;ref name=&quot;West land&quot;&gt;ASU University Office of Institutional Analysis. September 24, 2008.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;br /&gt;West: {{convert|277.92|acre|km2}}&lt;ref name=&quot;West land&quot;/&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Downtown Phoenix: {{convert|27.57|acre|m2}}&lt;ref name=&quot;West land&quot;/&gt;
|colors       = ASU Maroon &amp; ASU Gold&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://commguide.asu.edu/elements/color|title=Color Palette|work=Communication Guide|publisher=Arizona State University|accessdate=2009-08-05}}&lt;/ref&gt; {{color box|#990033}}&amp;nbsp;{{color box|#FFB310}}
|free_label   = Newspaper
|free         = [[The State Press]]
|nickname     = [[Arizona State Sun Devils|Sun Devils]]
|mascot       = [[Sparky (Arizona State Mascot)|Sparky]]
|athletics    = [[Pacific-12 Conference|Pac-12]], [[National Collegiate Athletic Association|NCAA]] [[Division I (NCAA)|Division I]]
|affiliations = [[Arizona Board of Regents|ABOR]]
|website      = [http://www.asu.edu/ asu.edu]
|logo         = &lt;center&gt;[[Image:Arizona State University signature.svg|139px|Arizona State University signature]]&lt;/center&gt;
}}

'''Arizona State University''' ('''ASU''' or '''Arizona State''') is a [[public university|public]] [[research university]]&lt;ref&gt;[http://classifications.carnegiefoundation.org/lookup_listings/view_institution.php?unit_id=104151&amp;start_page=institution.php&amp;clq={%22first_letter%22:%22A%22}] The Carnegie Foundation for the Advancement of Teaching. Retrieved August 13, 2010&lt;/ref&gt; located in the [[Phoenix Metropolitan Area]] of the [[Arizona|State of Arizona]].&lt;ref name=oneuniversity&gt;{{cite web |url=http://campus.asu.edu/ |title=ASU – One University in Many Places |publisher= Arizona State University |accessdate=2008-06-02 }}&lt;/ref&gt; With an enrollment of 70,440 students in Fall 2010, it is the [[List of United States university campuses by enrollment|largest public university in the United States by enrollment]].{{Cref|b}}

Founded in 1885 as the [[Normal School|Tempe Normal School]] for the [[Arizona Territory]], the school came under control of the [[Arizona Board of Regents]] in 1945 and was renamed ''Arizona State College.''&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.asu.edu/about/history/more.html History of ASU] Arizona State University&lt;/ref&gt; A 1958 statewide ballot measure gave the university its present name.

ASU offers programs in the [[liberal arts|liberal arts and sciences]], [[Ira A. Fulton School of Engineering|engineering]], [[journalism]], [[business school|business]], [[law school|law]], [[nursing]], and [[public policy]]. The university is broadly organized into 14 divisions and is spread across four campuses: the original [[Arizona State University at the Tempe campus|Tempe campus]], the [[Arizona State University at the West campus|West campus]] in northwest [[Phoenix, Arizona|Phoenix]], the [[Arizona State University at the Polytechnic campus|Polytechnic campus]] in eastern [[Mesa, Arizona|Mesa]], and the [[Arizona State University at the Downtown Phoenix campus|Downtown Phoenix campus]]. All four campuses are accredited as a single institution by the [[Higher Learning Commission]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.ncahlc.org/index.php?option=com_directory&amp;Itemid=192&amp;Action=ShowBasic&amp;instid=1002 Accreditation status of Arizona State University] Higher Learning Commission&lt;/ref&gt;

ASU's athletic teams compete in [[Division I (NCAA)|Division I]] of the [[National Collegiate Athletic Association|NCAA]] and are collectively known as the [[Arizona State Sun Devils]]. They are members of the [[Pacific-12 Conference]] and have won 23 national championships.

==History==
{{Main|History of Arizona State University}}

===1880–1929===
[[File:ASU mall.jpg|thumb|left|250px|ASU mall from Old Main, 2009]]
Originally named the ''Tempe Normal School'', the institution was founded on March 12, 1885, after John Samuel Armstrong first introduced House Bill 164, &quot;An Act to Establish a [[Normal school]] in the [[Territory of Arizona]] to the [[13th Arizona Territorial Legislature|13th Legislative Assembly]] of the [[Arizona Territory]]. Instruction was instituted on February 8, 1886 under the supervision of Principal Hiram Bradford Farmer. Land for the school was donated by [[Tempe, Arizona|Tempe]] residents George and Martha Wilson, allowing 33 students to meet in a single room.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.asu.edu/about/history/more.html More ASU History]&lt;/ref&gt;

At the beginning of the 20th century, the school's name was changed from Tempe Normal School to the ''Normal School of Arizona''. Before becoming a college, the [[Normal School]] enrolled high school students with no other secondary education facilities. Under the 30 year tenure of president Arthur John Matthews the school was given all-college student status. The first dormitories built in the state were constructed under his supervision. Of the 18 buildings constructed while Matthews was president, six are still currently in use. Matthews envisioned an &quot;evergreen campus,&quot; with many shrubbery brought to the campus. He also implemented the planting of [[Palm Walk]], now one of the feature landmarks of the Tempe campus. His legacy is being continued to this day with the main campus having the honor of being declared a nationally recognized arboretum.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.asu.edu/fm/arboretum.htm The Arboretum at Arizona State University]&lt;/ref&gt;

During the [[Great Depression]], Ralph W. Swetman was hired as president for a three-year term.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.asu.edu/lib/archives/preslist.htm Archives &amp; Special Collections, Principals and Presidents of Arizona State University]&lt;/ref&gt; Although enrollment increased by almost 100% during his tenure due to the depression, many faculty were terminated and faculty salaries were cut.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;[http://www.asu.edu/lib/archives/asustory/pages/11lead.htm Eighth President Ralph Waldo Swetman 1930–1933]&quot;&lt;/ref&gt;

===1930–1989===
[[Image:FLW Gammage Auditorium ASU PHX AZ 20186.JPG|thumb|250px|right|ASU's [[Gammage Auditorium]], designed by [[Frank Lloyd Wright]]]]
In 1933, [[Grady Gammage]], then president of Arizona State Teachers College at [[Flagstaff, Arizona|Flagstaff]], became president of ''Arizona State Teachers College at Tempe'', a tenure that would last for nearly 28 years. Like his predecessor, Gammage oversaw the construction of a number of buildings on the Tempe campus. Dr. Gammage oversaw the development of the university, graduate programs, and the renaming of the ''Arizona State College'' to Arizona State University in 1958.

By the 1960s, with the presidency of Dr. [[G. Homer Durham]], Arizona State University began to expand its academic curriculum by establishing several new colleges and beginning to award [[Doctor of Philosophy]] and other doctoral degrees.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.asu.edu/lib/archives/asustory/pages/16lead.htm ASU Libraries: The New ASU Story: Leadership]&lt;/ref&gt;

The next three presidents—Harry K. Newburn, 1969–71, John W. Schwada, 1971–81, and J. Russell Nelson, 1981–89—and Interim President Richard Peck, 1989, led the university to increased academic stature, creation of the [[Arizona State University at the West campus|West Campus]], and rising enrollment.

===1990–present===
Under the leadership of Dr. Lattie F. Coor, from 1990 to June 2002, ASU grew to serve the Valley of the Sun through the creation of the [[Arizona State University at the Polytechnic campus|Polytechnic campus]] and extended education sites. His commitment to diversity, quality in [[undergraduate education]], research, and economic development underscored the university's significant gains in each of these areas over his 12-year tenure. Part of Dr. Coor's legacy to the university was a successful fund-raising campaign. Through private donations, primarily from the local community, more than $500 million was invested in targeted areas that significantly impact the future of ASU. Among the campaign's achievements were the naming and endowing of the [[Barrett, The Honors College|Barrett Honors College]], the [[Herberger College of the Arts|Katherine K. Herberger College of Fine Arts]], and the Morrison School of Agribusiness and Resource Management at the Polytechnic campus; the creation of many new endowed faculty positions; and hundreds of new scholarships and fellowships.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.asu.edu/lib/archives/asustory/pages/21lead.htm ASU Libraries: The New ASU Story: Leadership]&lt;/ref&gt;
[[Image:Asubiodesign.jpg|thumb|250px|right|ASU's [[Biodesign Institute]] in Tempe campus]]
On July 1, 2002, [[Michael M. Crow|Michael Crow]] became the university's 16th president. At his inauguration, President Crow outlined his vision for transforming ASU into a &quot;New American University&quot;—one that would be open and inclusive. As the only [[research university]] serving the metropolitan Phoenix area (and one of only two in Arizona), Crow stated that ASU is in a unique position to evolve together with the city into one of the great intellectual institutions in the world. Further, Crow initiated the idea of transforming ASU into &quot;One University in Many Places&quot; by merging ASU's several campuses into a single institution, sharing students, faculty, staff and accreditation.

Under Crow's leadership, and aided by hundreds of millions of dollars in donations, ASU embarked on an aggressive years-long research facility capital building effort, resulting in the completion of the [[Biodesign Institute]] and several large interdisciplinary research buildings. Along with the research facilities, the university faculty was expanded, including the addition of three [[Nobel Laureates]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://asunews.asu.edu/20091012_ostrom_nobel Nobel Prize Winners] ASU News&lt;/ref&gt; In addition, ASU's [[Arizona State University at the Downtown Phoenix campus|Downtown Phoenix]] campus was vastly expanded. Several of the University's colleges and schools were relocated to the downtown campus, and new programs, such as a biomedical collaboration with the [[University of Arizona]] were established in downtown Phoenix.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.asu.edu/news/research/biomed_pressconf_082704.htm ASU, UA join forces on biomedical campus plan&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;

The [[Late-2000s recession|economic downturn]] that began in 2008 took a particularly hard toll on Arizona, resulting in large cuts to ASU's budget.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.azcentral.com/news/articles/2009/01/16/20090116capitol-budget0116.html Budget Cuts Proposal] Arizona Republic&lt;/ref&gt; In response to these cuts, ASU underwent several rounds of reorganizations,&lt;ref&gt;[http://asunews.asu.edu/20090121_reorg Academic Reorganization]&lt;/ref&gt; combining academic departments, consolidating colleges and schools, and reducing university staff and administrators.

==Campuses and Locations==
ASU's academic programs are spread across four campuses in the [[Phoenix Metropolitan Area]]; however, unlike most multi-campus institutions, ASU describes itself as &quot;one university in many places,&quot; meaning that it is not a [[university system]] with separate campuses, and not one main campus with branch campuses.&lt;ref&gt;[http://campus.asu.edu One University in Many Places] Arizona State University&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name = &quot;xvjbbz&quot;&gt;[http://www.asu.edu/provost/about/oneuniversity.html One University in Many Places] Explanation of the ASU campus organization&lt;/ref&gt; Inter-campus shuttles and [[light rail]] allow students and faculty to easily travel between the campuses. In addition to the physical campuses, ASU includes a fifth &quot;virtual campus&quot; for [[online education|online]] and extended education.

===Tempe campus===
[[File:Asu campus 1.jpg|thumb|right|250px|Overlooking the Tempe campus from atop [[Hayden Butte]]]]
{{Main|Arizona State University at the Tempe campus}}
ASU's Tempe campus is located in downtown [[Tempe, Arizona]], about eight miles (13&amp;nbsp;km) east of downtown Phoenix. The campus is considered urban, and is approximately {{convert|642|acre|km2|1}} in size. The campus is arranged around broad pedestrian malls and is completely encompassed by an arboretum.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.asu.edu/asuwebrw/entrance/tempe/ ASU's Tempe campus]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.azarboretum.org/ Arizona Arboretums And Botanical Gardens]&lt;/ref&gt; The Tempe campus is also the largest of ASU's campuses, with 58,371{{Cref|a}} students enrolled in at least one class on campus.&lt;ref name=enroll10&gt;[http://asunews.asu.edu/20100909_enrollment ASU Enrollment]. 2010. Retrieved Sep 10, 2010.&lt;/ref&gt;

The Tempe campus is ASU's original campus, and [[Old Main (Arizona State University)|Old Main]], the first building constructed, still stands today. There are many notable landmarks on campus, including [[Grady Gammage Memorial Auditorium]], designed by [[Frank Lloyd Wright]], Palm Walk, which is lined by 111 palm trees,&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.vpsa.asu.edu/UGA/360/campus.asp?campusid=1 Arizona State University: Virtual Tour]&lt;/ref&gt; Charles Trumbull Hayden Library, the University Club Building, and University Bridge. In addition, the campus has an extensive public art collection, considered one of the ten best among university public art collections in America according to ''Public Art Review''.&lt;ref name=&quot;PAR&quot;&gt;{{cite journal|date=Spring/Summer 2006|title=Big Ten|journal=Public Art Review|volume=17|issue=2|pages=24–5|issn=1040-211X}}&lt;/ref&gt; Against the northwest edge of campus is the Mill Avenue district (part of [[Tempe, Arizona|downtown Tempe]]) which has a college atmosphere that attracts many students to its restaurants and bars. The Tempe campus is also home to all of the university's athletic facilities.

===West campus===
[[File:Asu fletcher lib.JPG|thumb|250px|right|Fletcher Library, West campus]]
{{Main|Arizona State University at the West campus}}
The West campus was established in 1984 by the Arizona Legislature and sits on {{convert|250|acre|km2}} in a suburban area of northwest Phoenix. The West campus lies about {{convert|12|mi|km}} northwest of downtown Phoenix, and about {{convert|18|mi|km}} northwest of the Tempe campus. The West campus is designated as a [[Phoenix Points of Pride|Phoenix Point of Pride]],&lt;ref name=&quot;Point of Pride&quot;&gt;[http://phoenix.gov/NEWSREL/ARCHIVE/2008/MARCH/2803newpride.html 2008 Phoenix Points of Pride]&lt;/ref&gt; and is nearly completely powered by a 4.6[[megawatt|MW]] [[solar array]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://asu.edu/fm/documents/oua/campus_solarization_status_update.pdf Campus Solarization Update] Campus Solarization Project January, 2011&lt;/ref&gt; This campus is home to the [[New College of Interdisciplinary Arts and Sciences]], the [[Mary Lou Fulton Teachers College]], and selected programs of the [[W.P. Carey School of Business]].

===Polytechnic campus===
[[File:ASU Poly - West - 2009-02-25.jpg|thumb|right|250px|Picacho Hall (left) and Peralta Hall (right) at the Polytechnic campus]]
{{Main|Arizona State University at the Polytechnic campus}}
Founded in 1996 as &quot;ASU East,&quot; the ASU Polytechnic campus serves 9,752 students and is home to more than 40 bachelor’s, master’s and doctoral degrees in professional and technical programs through the College of Technology and Innovation, and selected programs of the [[W.P. Carey School of Business]]/Morrison School of Agribusiness and Resource Management, [[Mary Lou Fulton Teachers College]], the School of Letters and Sciences, and College of Nursing and Health Innovation. The {{convert|600|acre|km2|adj=on}} campus located in southeast [[Mesa, Arizona]], approximately {{convert|25|mi|km}} southeast of the [[Arizona State University at the Tempe campus|Tempe campus]], and {{convert|33|mi|km}} southeast of downtown Phoenix. The Polytechnic campus sits on the former [[Williams Air Force Base]].

===Downtown Phoenix campus===
[[Image:ASUDowntown1.jpg|thumb|250px|right|The Walter Cronkite School of Journalism, Downtown Phoenix campus]]
{{Main|Arizona State University at the Downtown Phoenix campus}}
The newest of ASU's four campuses, the Downtown Phoenix campus was established in 2006 on the north side of [[Downtown Phoenix]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.asu.edu/downtownphoenix/academics/colleges-schools.html ASU]&lt;/ref&gt; The campus has an [[urban design]], with several large modern academic buildings intermingled with commercial and retail office buildings. In addition to the new buildings, the campus included the [[adaptive reuse]] of several existing structures, including a 1930's era Post Office that is on the [[National Register of Historic Places]]. Serving 13,567&lt;ref name=enroll10/&gt; students, the campus houses the College of Nursing and Health Innovation, [[ASU College of Public Programs|College of Public Programs]], [[Walter Cronkite School of Journalism and Mass Communication]], and School of Criminology and Criminal Justice.&lt;ref&gt;[http://copp.asu.edu/college-news/college-embraces-new-school-and-departments College embraces new school and departments — College of Public Programs&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;

===Colleges @ ASU===
{{Main|Colleges@ASU}}
In response to demands for lower-cost public higher education in Arizona, ASU is developing a number of small, undergraduate-only college locations throughout Arizona. Colleges @ ASU locations will be teaching-focused, and will provide a selection of popular undergraduate majors. The first is being planned for [[Lake Havasu City]] with programs available as early as fall 2012.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.azcentral.com/arizonarepublic/local/articles/2011/02/18/20110218arizona-state-university-lake-havasu-campus.html Arizona State University campus in Lake Havasu City gains momentum] [[Arizona Republic]]&lt;/ref&gt;

===Online Degree Programs===
ASU offers more than 30 undergraduate and graduate degree programs through an entirely [[online education|online]] program, known as ASU Online. The degree programs delivered online hold the same accreditation as the university's traditional face-to-face programs, and students earn many of the same degrees as those who attended courses in person. As of spring 2010, more than 3,000 students were enrolled at ASU Online. ASU Online is headquartered at ASU's [[Skysong, the ASU Scottsdale Innovation Center|Skysong]] campus in [[Scottsdale, Arizona|Scottsdale]], Arizona.

==Academics==
===Admissions===
[[Image:A-Mountain Sunset.jpg|thumb|250px|right|[[Hayden Butte]], also known as &quot;A Mountain&quot;]]
Admission to any of the public universities in Arizona is ensured to residents in the top 25% of their high-school class with at a weighted secondary GPA of 2.5 GPA, or anyone with 24 credits of community college work with a 2.0 GPA minimum.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.abor.asu.edu/3_for_students/admin_stds.html Tri-University Admission Standards] Arizona Board of Regents&lt;/ref&gt; In 2009–2010, ASU admitted 91% of its first-time freshmen applicants.&lt;ref&gt;[http://nces.ed.gov/collegenavigator/?s=AZ&amp;ct=1&amp;id=104151#admsns Arizona State University] US Department of Education IPEDS&lt;/ref&gt; As of Fall 2008, the average first time freshman SAT/ACT scores were 1082 and 23.5, respectively, and 31% of first time freshmen were ranked in the top 10% of their high school class.&lt;ref&gt;[http://uoia.asu.edu/sites/default/files/factbook/STUDENT_CHARACTERISTICS_08.pdf ASU Student Characteristics] Arizona State University&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Barrett, The Honors College]] serves as its own college-within-a-university, and maintains much more strict admissions standards and provides a more rigorous curriculum with smaller classes and increased faculty interaction.&lt;ref&gt;[http://honors.asu.edu/w-About_Barrett-170.aspx Barrett, The Honors College – Arizona State University]&lt;/ref&gt; Although there are no set minimum admissions criteria for Barrett College, the average GPA of incoming freshmen was 3.84, with average SAT scores of 1308/1600 and ACT scores of 29.&lt;ref&gt;[http://barretthonors.asu.edu/home/category/1-about/5-facts-and-figures/ Barrett Honors College Admissions FAQ]&lt;/ref&gt; The Honors college enrolls nearly 3000 undergraduate students, about 540 of whom are [[National Merit Scholars]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://honors.asu.edu/w-Facts___Figures-30.aspx Barrett Honors College Enrollment Summary]&lt;/ref&gt;

===Academic programs===
[[Image:Asuhayden.jpg|thumb|250px|right|The subterranean entrance to [[Hayden Library]], Tempe campus]]
{{Main|List of colleges and schools of Arizona State University}}
ASU offers over 250 majors to undergraduate students, and more than 100 graduate programs leading to numerous [[Masters degree|masters]] and [[doctorate|doctoral]] degrees in the [[liberal arts|liberal arts and sciences]], [[engineering]], [[journalism]], [[business school|business]], [[law school|law]], [[public policy]]. These programs are divided into 15 colleges and schools which are spread across ASU's four campuses.

===Libraries===
ASU's faculty and students are served by two dedicated general-topic libraries: Hayden Library, which is the largest of the ASU libraries and is located on the Tempe campus, and Fletcher Library, located on the west campus. In addition, the Ross-Blakley Law Library and the Noble Science Library are housed in dedicated facilities on the Tempe campus. Music and Architecture collections are housed in facilities within the schools of Music and Architecture, respectively. Smaller library facilities are also located on the Polytechnic and Downtown campuses.&lt;ref&gt;[http://lib.asu.edu ASU Libraries]&lt;/ref&gt; As of 2009, ASU's libraries held 4.4 million volumes.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.arl.org/bm~doc/09tables.xls List of Library Holdings] Association of Research Libraries&lt;/ref&gt;

===Rankings===
{{Infobox US university ranking
| ARWU_W               = 78
| ARWU_N               = 45
| USNWR_NU             = 132
| THES_W               = 161
| Wamo_NU              = 115
}}
ASU's undergraduate program is ranked 132nd of 262 &quot;national universities&quot; by the 2012 ''[[US News and World Report]]'' ranking of US colleges and universities; and, for the fourth year in a row, ASU was ranked as one of the top &quot;Up and Coming&quot; universities in the US, for substantial improvements to academics and facilities.&lt;ref&gt;[http://colleges.usnews.rankingsandreviews.com/college/national-uc-rank Up and Coming Universities 2012] [[US News and World Report]]&lt;/ref&gt; In addition, ASU is ranked 78th in the world by the [[Academic Ranking of World Universities]] and was named as one of &quot;America's Best College Buys&quot; by ''[[Forbes]]'' magazine.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.forbes.com/2009/08/02/best-buys-colleges-opinions-value.html Forbes Magazine College Rankings 2010]&lt;/ref&gt;

For its efforts to be a national leader in campus sustainability, ASU was named one of the top 20 &quot;cool schools&quot; by the [[Sierra Club]],&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.sierraclub.org/sierra/200909/coolschools/top20.aspx Top 20 Cool Schools]&lt;/ref&gt; was named to the &quot;Green Honor Roll&quot; by the [[Princeton Review]],&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.princetonreview.com/green-honor-roll.aspx Green Honor Roll] Princeton Review 2009&lt;/ref&gt; and earned an &quot;A-&quot; grade on the 2010 College Sustainability Report Card.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.greenreportcard.org/report-card-2010/schools/arizona-state-university-tempe Arizona State University]&lt;/ref&gt;

Several of ASU's graduate schools also appear among the top of the US News &amp; World Report rankings, including the 27th-ranked [[W. P. Carey School of Business]]&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://grad-schools.usnews.rankingsandreviews.com/best-graduate-schools/top-business-schools/mba-rankings/page+2 |title=Best Business School Rankings &amp;#124; MBA Program Rankings &amp;#124; US News |publisher=Grad-schools.usnews.rankingsandreviews.com |date= |accessdate=2011-10-06}}&lt;/ref&gt; (along with its 4th-ranked program in [[Supply Chain Management]] and the 15th-ranked program in [[Information Systems]]), the 47th-ranked [[Ira A. Fulton School of Engineering]] (including five individual programs ranked in the top 30),&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.fulton.asu.edu/fulton/school/index.php Ira A. Fulton School of Engineering at Arizona State University]&lt;/ref&gt; the 40th-ranked [[Sandra Day O'Connor College of Law]],&lt;ref&gt;[http://grad-schools.usnews.rankingsandreviews.com/best-graduate-schools/top-law-schools/law-rankings/page+2 US News and World Report 2012 Law School Rankings]&lt;/ref&gt; the 25th-ranked [[ASU School of Public Affairs|School of Public Affairs]],&lt;ref&gt;[http://grad-schools.usnews.rankingsandreviews.com/best-graduate-schools/top-public-affairs-schools/rankings/ Top Public Affairs Schools] US News and World Report 2010&lt;/ref&gt; the 35th-ranked [[Mary Lou Fulton Teachers College]],&lt;ref&gt;[http://grad-schools.usnews.rankingsandreviews.com/best-graduate-schools/top-education-schools/edu-rankings/page+2 US News Education School Rankings]&lt;/ref&gt; and the 21st-ranked College of Nursing.&lt;ref&gt;[http://grad-schools.usnews.rankingsandreviews.com/best-graduate-schools/top-health-schools/nursing-rankings Nursing School rankings] US News and World Report 2012.&lt;/ref&gt; In addition, the individual Ph.D. programs in [[Psychology]] (36th of 240),&lt;ref&gt;[http://grad-schools.usnews.rankingsandreviews.com/best-graduate-schools/top-psychology-schools/rankings/page+2 Psychology Graduate Program Rankings] U.S. News and World Report Best Graduate Schools 2009&lt;/ref&gt; [[Earth Science]] (17th of 108),&lt;ref&gt;[http://grad-schools.usnews.rankingsandreviews.com/best-graduate-schools/top-science-schools/earth-sciences-rankings] US News and World Report&lt;/ref&gt; and [[Criminology]] (12th)&lt;ref&gt;[http://grad-schools.usnews.rankingsandreviews.com/best-graduate-schools/top-criminology-schools/rankings] US News and World Report 2009 Criminology Graduate Rankings&lt;/ref&gt; also earned high rankings.

==Athletics==
[[File:ASUDrillFormation crop.jpg|thumb|right|250px|Athletic Event at Sun Devil Stadium]]
{{Main|Arizona State Sun Devils}}
Arizona State University's [[NCAA Division I|Division I]] athletic teams are called the [[Arizona State Sun Devils|Sun Devils]], which is also the nickname used to refer to students and alumni of the university. They compete in the [[Pacific-12 Conference|Pac-12 Conference]] in 20 varsity sports. Historically, the university has shown great athletic dominance in men's, women's, and mixed [[archery]]; men's, women's, and mixed [[badminton]]; women's [[golf]]; women's [[swimming (sport)|swimming]] and [[diving]]; and [[baseball]]. The Sun Devils have played in the [[Fiesta Bowl]] five times, and in 1987 the [[ASU]] football team won the [[Rose Bowl (game)|Rose Bowl]], defeating the [[University of Michigan]] 22–15. Arizona State University's [[NCAA Division I-A]] program competes in 9 varsity sports for men and 11 for women. The Sun Devil mascot is named [[Sparky (Arizona State Mascot)|Sparky]]. The university is a member of the [[Pacific-12 Conference]] in all varsity sports. ASU's current athletic director is [[Lisa Love (coach)|Lisa Love]], formerly senior associate athletic director at the [[University of Southern California]], and in her tenure is responsible for hiring new coaches [[Herb Sendek]], the men's basketball coach, and [[Dennis Erickson]], the men's football coach.
[[File:Wellsfargo.jpg|thumb|left|250px|Wells Fargo Arena in ASU Tempe campus]]
ASU has won 23 national collegiate team championships in the following sports: baseball (5), men's golf (2), women's golf (7), men's gymnastics (1), softball (2), men's indoor track (1), women's indoor track (2), men's outdoor track (1), women's outdoor track (1), and wrestling (1).&lt;ref&gt;http://fs.ncaa.org/Docs/stats/champs_records_book/summaries/combined.pdf&lt;/ref&gt;

In September 2009 criticism over the seven-figure salaries earned by various coaches at Arizona's public universities (including ASU) prompted the Arizona Board of Regents to re-evaluate the salary and benefit policy for athletic staff.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.azcentral.com/sports/ua/articles/2009/09/20/20090920athleticsalaries0919-CP.html ASU, UA Coaching Salaries Reviewed] Arizona Republic, September 20, 2009.&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Arizona State Sun Devils football]] was founded in 1897 under coach [[Fred Irish]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://thesundevils.cstv.com/sports/m-footbl/archive/history/asu-m-footbl-headcoaches.html History :: The Arizona State University Sun Devils – Official Athletic Site]&lt;/ref&gt; Currently, the team has played in the 2007 [[Holiday Bowl]], 1997 [[Rose Bowl Game|Rose Bowl]] and also won the Rose Bowl in 1987 as well as the [[Fiesta Bowl]] in 1982, 1975, 1973, 1972, and 1971. In 1970 they were co-champions of the [[NCAA Division I FBS National Football Championship]]. Additionally, the Sun Devils were Pac-10 Champions in 1986, 1996, and 2007.

==Student activities==
===Extracurricular programs===
[[Image:Music Auditorium ASU Tempe AZ 220398.JPG|thumb|250px|right|Music Auditorium in ASU Tempe campus]]
Arizona State University has an active [[extracurricular]] involvement program (Sun Devil Involvement Center) with over 600 registered clubs and organizations on campus.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.asu.edu/studentaffairs/mu/clubs/ Memorial Union – Student Organizations]&lt;/ref&gt; Located on the 3rd floor of the [[Memorial Union (Arizona State)|Memorial Union]], the Sun Devil Involvement Center (SDIC) provides opportunities for student involvement through clubs, [[sororities]], [[fraternities]], [[community service]], leadership, [[student government]], and [[Co-curricular activity|co-curricular]] programming.

&quot;ASU Cares&quot; is the largest community service project sponsored by the university. It is an annual event that allows students to give back some time by helping residents and communities clean up, rebuild, and/or serve each other. Faculty, staff, alumni, members of the community and their families and guests are also invited to be part of this large ASU effort to help residents of the various communities surrounding the metropolitan area.&lt;ref&gt;[https://asucares.asu.edu/ ASU Cares]&lt;/ref&gt;

The Freshman Year Residential Experience (FYRE) and the [[Fraternities and sororities|Greek]] community (Greek Life) at Arizona State University have been important in binding students to the university, and providing social outlets. The Freshman Year Residential Experience at Arizona State University was developed to improve the freshman experience at Arizona State University and increase student retention figures. FYRE provides advising, computer labs, free walk-in tutoring, workshops, and classes for students. In 2003, ''[[U.S. News and World Report]]'' ranked FYRE as the 23rd best first year program in the nation.

===Student media===
[[Image:asupalms.jpg|thumb|upright|The Palm Walk is frequented by ASU students.]]
''The [[State Press]]'' is a daily paper published on Monday through Friday during the fall and spring semesters, and weekly during the summer sessions. The State Press covers news and events on all four ASU campuses. Student editors and managers are solely responsible for the content of the State Press newspaper and its associated website. These publications are overseen by an independent board and guided by a professional adviser employed by the University.

''@west news'' is an independent, student-run newspaper covering news and events on ASU's west campus.

ASU has two radio stations. [[KASC]] The Blaze 1330 AM, is a broadcast station that is owned and funded by the Cronkite School of Journalism, and is completely student-run save for a faculty and professional adviser. The Blaze broadcasts local, alternative and independent music 24 hours a day, and also features news and sports updates at the top and bottom of every hour.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.blazeradioonline.com/ kasc – the blaze 1330 am – asu's original alternative]&lt;/ref&gt; [[W7ASU]] is an [[amateur radio]] station that was first organized in 1935. W7ASU has about 30 members that enjoy amateur radio, and is primarily a [[contesting]] club.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.asu.edu/clubs/amateur_radio_society/ W7ASU – Amateur Radio Society at Arizona State University]&lt;/ref&gt;

===Student government===
Associated Students of Arizona State University (ASASU) is the [[student government]] at Arizona State University.&lt;ref&gt;[http://asasu.net ASASU Website]&lt;/ref&gt; It is composed of the Undergraduate Student Government and the Graduate &amp; Professional Student Association (GPSA). Members and officers of ASASU are elected annually by the student body.

The [[Residence Hall Association]] (RHA) of Arizona State University is the student government for every ASU student living on-campus. Each ASU campus has an RHA that operates independently of each other. The purpose of RHA is to enhance the quality of residence hall life and provide a cohesive voice for the residents by addressing the concerns of the on-campus populations to university administrators and other campus organizations; providing cultural, diversity, educational, and social programming; establishing and working with individual hall councils.

==People==
===Alumni===
{{Main|List of Arizona State University alumni}}

===Faculty===
ASU faculty have included former [[CNN]] host [[Aaron Brown]], [[meta-analysis]] developer [[Gene V. Glass]], and [[Pulitzer Prize]] winner and ''[[The Ants]]'' author [[Bert Hölldobler]]. [[Donald Johanson]], who discovered the 3.18 million year old fossil hominid [[Lucy (Australopithecus)]] in Ethiopia, is also a professor at ASU, as well as [[George Poste]], Chief Scientist for the [[Complex Adaptive Systems Initiative]]. [[Nobel laureate]] faculty include [[Leland Hartwell]],&lt;ref&gt;[http://asunews.asu.edu/20090908_hartwell Nobel Prize in Physiology or Medicine ASU News Release] 09/08/09&lt;/ref&gt; [[Edward C. Prescott]], and [[Elinor Ostrom]].{{Citation needed|date=May 2011}}

==Notes==
{{Cnote|a|Campus emrollment figures at ASU are defined by the number of students taking at least one course offered by a department housed on a particular campus. Students who are enrolled in classes on more than one campus (estimated to be 13,269) are counted within each campus's total.}}

{{Cnote|b|ASU is the [[List of United States colleges and universities by enrollment|largest research university in the US]] under a single administration (one President, Provost, VPs, etc.). In addition ASU's Tempe campus is the [[List of United States university campuses by enrollment|largest single university campus]] in the US.}}

==References==
{{Reflist|colwidth=30em}}

==External links==
{{Portal box|Arizona|University}}
* {{Official website|http://www.asu.edu}}
* [http://thesundevils.cstv.com Official athletics website]
* [http://www.asu.edu/lib/archives/asustory/chrono.htm ASU Chronology]

{{ASU}}
{{Colleges and Universities in Arizona}}
{{Template group
|title = Links to related articles
|titlestyle = background:#FFB310;color:white;border:1px solid #990033;
|list =
{{Largest United States universities by enrollment}}
{{Largest United States universities by undergraduate enrollment}}
{{Universities Research Association}}
{{Pacific-12 Conference}}
{{CDIO}}
|state =autocollapse
}}

{{Coord|33|25|16|N|111|55|54|W|display=title|region:US_type:edu_source:dewiki}}

[[Category:Arizona State University| ]]
[[Category:Association of Public and Land-Grant Universities]]
[[Category:Universities and colleges in Phoenix, Arizona|State University]]
[[Category:Educational institutions established in 1885]]
[[Category:Public universities in the United States]]
[[Category:Public universities and colleges in Arizona]]
[[Category:Consortium for North American Higher Education Collaboration]]
[[Category:North Central Association of Colleges and Schools]]

[[de:Arizona State University]]
[[es:Universidad Estatal de Arizona]]
[[fa:دانشگاه ایالتی آریزونا]]
[[fr:Université d'État de l'Arizona]]
[[ko:애리조나 주립 대학교]]
[[is:Ríkisháskólinn í Arizona]]
[[it:Università statale dell'Arizona]]
[[he:אוניברסיטת המדינה של אריזונה]]
[[ja:アリゾナ州立大学]]
[[no:Arizona State University]]
[[pnb:ایریزونا سٹیٹ یونیورسٹی]]
[[pl:Arizona State University]]
[[pt:Universidade do Estado do Arizona]]
[[ru:Университет штата Аризона]]
[[simple:Arizona State University]]
[[sv:Arizona State University]]
[[th:มหาวิทยาลัยแอริโซนาสเตต]]
[[zh:亞利桑那州立大學]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
