<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="18616324" ns="0" title="UCD Library"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{infobox library
| library_name       = UCD Library&lt;BR&gt;'''Leabharlann UCD'''
| name_en            = 
| library_logo       =  
| image              = 
| caption            = 
| country            = [[Republic of Ireland|Ireland]]
| type               = [[Academic library]]
| scope              = 
| established        = 
| ref_legal_mandate  = 
| location           = [[Belfield, Dublin|Belfield]],&lt;BR&gt;[[Dublin 4]]
| coordinates        = 
| branch_of          = 
| num_branches       = 5
| items_collected    = 
| collection_size    = 1,300,000 print volumes
| criteria           = 
| legal_deposit      = 
| req_to_access      = 
| annual_circulation = 
| pop_served         = 24,000
| members            = 
| budget             = 
| director           = 
| num_employees      = 140
| website            = [http://www.ucd.ie/library/ ucd.ie/library]
| phone_num          = 
| references         = 
}}

'''UCD Library''' dates from the establishment of [[University College Dublin]] (UCD) as a constituent college of the [[National University of Ireland]] in 1908. It supports the learning, teaching and research needs of some 24,000 students and academic staff in a wide range of disciplines including agriculture &lt;ref name=&quot;ucd.ie&quot;&gt;[http://www.ucd.ie/agandvet/ UCD School of Agriculture, Food Science &amp; Veterinary Medicine]&lt;/ref&gt;, architecture &lt;ref&gt;[http://www.ucd.ie/arcel/index.html UCD School of Architecture, Landscape &amp; Civil Engineering]&lt;/ref&gt;, arts and humanities &lt;ref&gt;[http://www.ucd.ie/acshs/ UCD Arts, Celtic Studies and Human Sciences Programme Office]&lt;/ref&gt;, business studies &lt;ref name=&quot;UCD College of Business and Law&quot;&gt;[http://www.ucd.ie/businessandlaw/index.html UCD College of Business and Law]&lt;/ref&gt;, engineering&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.ucd.ie/engscience/index.html/ UCD College of Engineering, Mathematical &amp; Physical Sciences]&lt;/ref&gt;, law &lt;ref name=&quot;UCD College of Business and Law&quot;/&gt;, medicine &lt;ref&gt;[http://www.ucd.ie/medicine/index.html UCD School of Medicine &amp; Medical Science]&lt;/ref&gt;, science &lt;ref&gt;[http://www.ucd.ie/science/ UCD Science Programme Office]&lt;/ref&gt;, social sciences &lt;ref&gt;[http://www.ucd.ie/sociology/index.html UCD School of Sociology]&lt;/ref&gt; and veterinary medicine &lt;ref name=&quot;ucd.ie&quot;/&gt;. 
[[University College Dublin]] (UCD) is the [[Republic of Ireland]]'s largest [[university]], with over 1,300 faculty and 22,000 students. It is located in [[Dublin]], capital of Ireland.

==Buildings and locations==
There are 5 UCD libraries: the James Joyce Library at [[Belfield, Dublin|Belfield]] is the administrative centre of the library system: it accommodates the central services and 85% of the stock; the Health Sciences library (for medicine, nursing and physiotherapy) is located in the UCD Health Sciences Centre at Belfield; Architecture (for architecture, landscape and planning) is in the Richview precinct at Belfield; Veterinary Medicine, located in the Veterinary Sciences Centre at Belfield; the [[Michael Smurfit Graduate School of Business|UCD Michael Smurfit School of Business]] library &lt;ref&gt;[http://www.smurfitschool.ie/ UCD Michael Smurfit School of Business]&lt;/ref&gt; at the [[Blackrock, Dublin|Blackrock]] Campus.
Accommodation for readers consists of some 3,000 reading and study places, including some single and group study rooms. Almost all study places are wireless and power enabled. The James Joyce Library has a purpose-built assistive learning area for students with disabilities.

==Information resources==
The Library as a whole contains about 1,300,000 print volumes, with substantial collections in other print and non-print formats, including 400,000 [[e-books]]. Almost 80% of stock is on open access. Approximately 15,000 purchased [[monographs]], and 2,500 donations or [[legal deposit]] items are added to stock each year, and 32,000 current [[Academic journal|journal]] titles and databases are available, the vast majority of which are [[electronic journal|e-journals]]. The Library is a [[European Documentation Centre]], a national depository for [[United States Government Printing Office|United States government publications]], and a legal deposit library for Irish publications. A small but significant holding of some 50,000 early printed books and special collections is housed in a separate bookstack with independent environmental control.

==Library management system==
Library routines and processes are fully computerised, using the [[Talis Group|Talis]] [[Integrated library system|library management system]].

==Services==
Lending (including self-service lending), [[Interlibrary loan|document supply]], information skills training, and reference and information services are available in all library locations. Periodicals, reference materials, official publications, theses, and special collections materials are not available for loan. A charge is made for [[interlibrary loan]] and document supply. The University Printing and Copying service provides copying facilities, on a self-service basis, in the libraries and in other University buildings.
The James Joyce and Health Sciences libraries provide a laptop loan service. This service enables students and staff to borrow laptops on a short-term basis within the confines of the library. ref&gt;[http://www.ucd.ie/library/services_&amp;_facilities/laptop/index.html Laptop loans]&lt;/ref&gt;
The Short Loan collection in the James Joyce library uses [[Radio-frequency identification|RFID]] technology. This allows readers to borrow and return books without the assistance of library staff. Opening hours &lt;ref&gt;[http://www.ucd.ie/library/about/opening_hours/summer_opening_hours/index.html UCD Library opening hours]&lt;/ref&gt; in each of the five UCD libraries vary throughout the year, but during the academic session the James Joyce Library is open for 94 hours per week, including Saturdays and Sundays.
Online access is provided on a 24/7 basis to an extensive range of [[database]]s, information services, electronic journals, and subject guides.
Innovative resource discovery tools are being implemented to hyperlink citations and full-text (findit@UCDLibrary) &lt;ref&gt;[http://www.ucd.ie/library/electronic_resources/article_linker/index.html findit@UCDLibrary]&lt;/ref&gt;, and to facilitate searching across a range of databases (crossearch@UCDLibrary) &lt;ref&gt;[http://jq6am9xs3s.cs.serialssolutions.com/ crossearch@UCDLibrary]&lt;/ref&gt;
A number of services based on [[Web 2.0]] technologies are also provided. These include several [[blogs]] aimed at specific user groups or relating to specific service aspects; an [[instant messaging]] service, an embryonic service in the virtual world [[Second Life]] and a page on [[Facebook]]. More details of these are available from the library projects and pilots page &lt;ref&gt;[http://www.ucd.ie/library/about/projects/index.html UCD Library pilots and projects]&lt;/ref&gt; on the website.

==Staffing==
There are 103 full-time permanent staff of whom 33 are professionally qualified [[librarians]]. These are supplemented by a further 80 contract staff
The Library provides leadership, and office space, for the Irish Virtual Library and Archive Project &lt;ref&gt;[http://www.ucd.ie/ivrla/ Irish Virtual Library and Archive Project ]&lt;/ref&gt;, the aim of which is to provide a researcher-oriented web interface to the digitised content of separate repositories in UCD Library&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.ucd.ie/ivrla/ Irish Virtual Library and Archive Project]&lt;/ref&gt;, UCD Archives&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.ucd.ie/archives/ UCD Archives]&lt;/ref&gt;, and the UCD School of Irish, Celtic, Studies, Irish Folklore and Linguistics&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.ucd.ie/icsifl/index.html UCD School of Irish, Celtic, Studies, Irish Folklore and Linguistics]&lt;/ref&gt;. This is a five-year project (2004–2009) funded through the Programme for Research in Third-Level Institutions under the aegis of the UCD Humanities Institute of Ireland &lt;ref&gt;[http://www.ucd.ie/hii/ UCD Humanities Institute of Ireland ]&lt;/ref&gt;.

==Liaison with other libraries and organizations==
There is a strong collaborative ethos among the Irish university libraries, and UCD Library participates in a number of collaborative initiatives and projects. These include IReL &lt;ref&gt;[http://www.irelibrary.ie/default.aspx IReL]&lt;/ref&gt; (the Irish e-Library, an initiative funded by the [[Higher Education Authority]] &lt;ref&gt;[http://www.hea.ie/ Higher Education Authority of Ireland]&lt;/ref&gt; and [[Science Foundation Ireland]] to provide a world-class portfolio of e-journals to support research), IRIS (a company which manages the IReL initiative and which also aims to provide a virtual union catalogue of the holdings of the Irish university libraries), ALCID &lt;ref&gt;[http://www.ucd.ie/library/about/admission_to_the_library/access_other_libraries/ ALCID]&lt;/ref&gt; (a reciprocal access scheme for academic staff and postgraduate research students), ANLTC (the Academic and National Library Training Co-operative)&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.anltc.ie/ ANLTC - the Academic and National Library Training Co-operative]&lt;/ref&gt;, which provides a regular staff training and development programme, and the Open Access to Research Output Project, funded through the Higher Education Authority’s Strategic Innovation Fund &lt;ref&gt;[http://www.hea.ie/en/sif/ Higher Education Authority of Ireland, Strategic innovation fund]&lt;/ref&gt; to provide e-repositories in each university, and a national portal, for open-access research publications.
Internationally, the Library has participated in the past in a number of research projects funded through the [[European Commission]]'s FRAMEWORK Programmes, and, as a member of the NEREUS Consortium &lt;ref&gt;[http://www.nereus4economics.info/ NEREUS Consortium]&lt;/ref&gt;, is currently participating in the NEEO (Network of European Economists Online) &lt;ref&gt;[http://nereus4economics.info/about_neeo.html/ NEEO]&lt;/ref&gt; project, funded by the [[eContentplus]] Programme, to establish a multilingual portal to the full-text research outputs of 500 top researchers in the partner institutions.
UCD Library was a partner with the Library of the [[Queen’s University, Belfast|Queen’s University]] of Belfast in the PADDI (Planning Architecture Design Database Ireland) project and both libraries continue to jointly operate the PADDI Database service. 
UCD Library is an institutional member of [[SCONUL]], CONUL&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.conul.ie/ CONUL]&lt;/ref&gt;, IATUL&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.iatul.org/ IATUL]&lt;/ref&gt;, [[IFLA]] and LIBER&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.libereurope.eu/ LIBER]&lt;/ref&gt;.

==See also==

*[[Libraries in Second Life]]

==References==
&lt;references/&gt;

==External links==
*[http://www.ucd.ie/library/ UCD Library]
*[http://udprism01.ucd.ie/TalisPrism/ Search the library catalogue]
*[http://www.ucd.ie/library/about/blogs/index.html UCD Library Blogs page]
*[http://www.ucd.ie// University College Dublin]

{{coord|53.306816|N|6.222995|W|type:landmark_region:IE|display=title}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Ucd Library}}
[[Category:Academic libraries in Ireland]]
[[Category:Research libraries]]
[[Category:University College Dublin]]
[[Category:Libraries in the Republic of Ireland]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
