<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="18621845" ns="0" title="Jean-Luc Picard"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Infobox Star Trek character
| Image       = Jean-Luc Picard.jpg
| Caption     = Jean-Luc Picard played by Patrick Stewart
| Species     = [[Human (Star Trek)|Human]]
| Gender      = Male
| Planet      = [[Earth]] ([[La Barre, Haute-Saône|La Barre]], [[France]])
| Birth       = July 13, 2305
| Affiliation = [[United Federation of Planets]]&lt;br/&gt;[[Starfleet]]
| Rank        = [[Starfleet ranks and insignia#Captain|Captain]]
| Actor       = [[Patrick Stewart|Sir Patrick Stewart]]
}}

Captain '''Jean-Luc Picard''' ({{pron-en|ˌʒɔːn ˌluːk piˈkɑrd}}) is a ''[[Star Trek]]'' [[fictional character|character]] portrayed by [[Patrick Stewart]]. He appears in the [[television series]] ''[[Star Trek: The Next Generation]]'' and the feature films ''[[Star Trek Generations]]'', ''[[Star Trek: First Contact]]'', ''[[Star Trek: Insurrection]]'', and ''[[Star Trek Nemesis]]''. He also made an appearance in the [[Emissary (DS9 episode)|pilot episode]] of ''[[Star Trek: Deep Space Nine]]''.

Depicted as deeply moral, highly logical and intelligent, Picard is a master of [[diplomacy]] and [[debate ]] who resolves seemingly intractable issues between multiple parties with a [[Solomon]]-like wisdom. Though such resolutions are usually peaceful, Picard is also shown using his remarkable tactical cunning in situations when it is required. Picard has a fondness for [[detective stories]], [[Shakespeare|Shakespearean drama]], and [[archeology]]. He is frequently shown drinking [[Earl Grey tea]] and issuing an order by saying &quot;Make it so.&quot;

==Casting and design==
After the success of the contemporary ''[[Star Trek]]'' [[Star Trek films|feature films]], a new [[television series]] featuring a new cast was announced on October 10, 1986.&lt;ref&gt;''[[The Washington Post]]''. October 13, 1986, Monday, Final Edition. BYLINE: John Carmody, Washington Post Staff Writer. SECTION: STYLE; PAGE B8; THE TV COLUMN&lt;/ref&gt; ''Star Trek'' creator [[Gene Roddenberry]] named Picard for one or both of the twin brothers [[Auguste Piccard]] and [[Jean Piccard|Jean Felix Piccard]], 20th-century Swiss scientists.&lt;ref name=UCBerkeley&gt;{{cite web | author= University of California, Berkeley et al. [and informal sources on Jean Piccard talk page] | title= Living With A Star: 3: Balloon/Rocket Mission: Scientific Ballooning | publisher=The Regents of the University of California | year= 2003 | url= http://ds9.ssl.berkeley.edu/LWS_GEMS/3/scien.htm
}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | last= Piccard|first=Elizabeth | title= Talk of the Nation: Science on Stage | publisher= [[National Public Radio]] | date=2004-01-23| url= http://www.npr.org/templates/story/story.php?storyId=1614132 | accessdate= 2007-01-29}}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Patrick Stewart]], who has a background of [[theatre]] at the [[Royal Shakespeare Company]],&lt;ref&gt;Phillip Brochbank, ed., ''Players of Shakespeare'' Cambridge: Cambride University Press (1995)&lt;/ref&gt; was initially considered for the role of [[Data (Star Trek)|Data]];&lt;ref name=&quot;Hatfield&quot;&gt;James Hatfield, George Burt, ''Patrick Stewart: The Unauthorized Biography'' New York: Kensington Publishing (1996)&lt;/ref&gt; he has said that he would not have been interested in taking a supporting role &quot;to sit around&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;bbcstewart&quot;&gt;{{cite web | url=http://www.bbc.co.uk/cult/st/interviews/stewart/printpage.html | title=Patrick Stewart - Jean Luc Picard, Captain of the Enterprise | publisher=BBC | accessdate=May 07, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; Roddenberry did not want to cast Stewart as Picard, however; he envisioned an actor who was &quot;masculine, virile, and had a lot of hair&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;bbcjustman&quot;&gt;{{cite web | url=http://www.bbc.co.uk/cult/st/interviews/justman/printpage.html | title=Robert Justman - Co-Producer Co-Creator of Star Trek | publisher=BBC | accessdate=May 07, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; Roddenberry's first choice was [[Stephen Macht]], and it took &quot;weeks of discussion&quot; with [[Robert H. Justman]], [[Rick Berman]], and the casting director to convince him that &quot;Stewart was the one they had been looking for to sit in the captain's chair&quot;; Roddenberry agreed after auditioning every other candidate for the role.{{r|bbcjustman}}&lt;ref&gt;Adam Schrager, &quot;Patrick Stewart: Thespian on the Bridge&quot; ''The Finest Crew in the Fleet: The Next Generation's Cast On Screen and Off''. New York: Wolf Valley Books (1997): 23. This book gives the actor's name as &quot;Steven Mocked&quot;.&lt;/ref&gt; Stewart himself was uncertain why the producers would cast &quot;a middle-aged bald English Shakespearean actor&quot; as captain of the ''[[USS Enterprise (NCC-1701-D)|Enterprise]]''.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.deadline.com/2010/08/emmys-qa-with-supporting-tv-movieminiseries-actor-nominee-patrick-stewart/|title=EMMYS: Q&amp;A With Supporting TV Movie/Miniseries Actor Nominee Patrick Stewart|first=Nikki|last=Finke|date=2010-08-12|accessdate=2010-10-19|authorlink=Nikki Finke}}&lt;/ref&gt; He had his toupee delivered from London to meet with Paramount executives but Roddenberry ordered Stewart to remove the &quot;awful looking&quot; hairpiece. His stentorian voice impressed the executives, who  immediately approved the casting.{{r|bbcjustman}} Roddenberry sent Stewart [[C. S. Forrester]]'s [[Horatio Hornblower]] novels, saying the Picard character was based on Hornblower,&lt;ref name=&quot;trekmovieinterview&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://trekmovie.com/2010/06/22/video-patrick-stewart-on-how-he-expected-tng-to-fail-roddenberry-v-berman-star-trek-albatross-more/|title=VIDEO: Patrick Stewart On Expecting TNG To Fail, Roddenberry v Berman, Star Trek ‘Albatross’ + more|date=2010-06-22|accessdate=2010-97-25}}&lt;/ref&gt; but Stewart was already familiar with Hornblower, having read the books as a child.{{r|bbcstewart}}

As the series progressed, Stewart exercised more control over the character's development. By the time production began on the first ''Next Generation'' film, &quot;it was impossible to tell where Jean Luc started and Patrick Stewart ended&quot;,&lt;ref name=&quot;trekmovieinterview&quot; /&gt; and by the fourth film, he stated that

{{quote|I find myself talking a lot about Picard and one of the things that I’ve come to understand is that as I talk a lot about Picard what I find is I’m talking about myself.

There was a sort of double action that occurred. In one sense Picard was expanding like this and at the same time he was also growing closer and closer to me as well and in some respect I suppose even had some influence on me. I became a better listener than I ever had been as a result of playing Jean Luc Picard because it was one of the things that he does terrifically well.{{r|bbcstewart}}}}

Stewart stated, however, that he is not nearly as serious or brooding as his alter ego.&lt;ref name=journalarts&gt;[http://www.elliottsweb.co.uk/brentspiner/bios/patrickinter2.htm The Journal Arts: Patrick Stewart]&lt;/ref&gt;

Stewart also stated, &quot;One of the delights of having done this series and played this role is that people are so attracted to the whole idea of ''Star Trek''... several years after the series has ended... I enjoy hearing how much people enjoyed the work we did... It's always gratifying to me that this bald, middle-aged [[Englishman]] seems to connect with them.&quot;&lt;ref name=journalarts/&gt; Stewart has also commented that his role has helped open up [[William Shakespeare|Shakespeare]] to [[science fiction]] fans. He has noted the &quot;regular presence of [[Trekkies]] in the audience&quot; whenever he plays theatre, and added: &quot;I meet these people afterwards, I get letters from them and see them at the stage door... And they say, 'I've never seen Shakespeare before, I didn't think I'd understand it, but it was wonderful and I can't wait to come back.'&quot;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.bbc.co.uk/london/content/articles/2007/09/27/theatre_patrick_stewart_interview_feature.shtml Patrick Stewart interview (BBC)]&lt;/ref&gt;

==Depiction==

Jean-Luc Picard was born to Maurice and Yvette Picard&lt;ref name=&quot;chain of command&quot; http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Chain_of_Command_(Star_Trek:_The_Next_Generation)&gt; Mentioned in the episode chain of command part 1&lt;/ref&gt; in [[La Barre, Haute-Saône|La Barre]], [[France]], on July 13, 2305, and dreamed of joining [[Starfleet]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Encyc&quot;&gt;{{cite book|title=[[The Star Trek Encyclopedia]]|author=[[Michael Okuda|Okuda, Mike]] and Denise Okuda, with Debbie Mirek|publisher=Pocket Books|isbn=0-671-53609-5|year=1999}}&lt;/ref&gt; He failed his first [[Starfleet Academy]] entrance exam, but was subsequently admitted and became the first [[freshman]] to win the Academy [[marathon (sport)|marathon]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Encyc&quot; /&gt; His academic training in [[archaeology]] is mentioned in numerous ''[[Star Trek: The Next Generation|TNG]]'' episodes and he continues to pursue archaeology as a hobby; he also remarks at one point that he failed a semester of [[organic chemistry]]. Shortly after graduation, Picard was stabbed in the [[heart]] by a [[Nausicaan]], leaving the organ irreparable and requiring replacement with a [[artificial heart|parthenogenetic implant]]; this would prove near-fatal [[Tapestry (Star Trek: The Next Generation)|later]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Encyc&quot; /&gt; Picard eventually served as first officer aboard the [[USS Stargazer|USS ''Stargazer'']], which he later commanded.&lt;ref name=&quot;Encyc&quot; /&gt; During that time, he invented a starship evade and attack tactic that would become known as the [[Picard Maneuver]].

''[[Star Trek: The Next Generation]]'' depicts Picard's command of the [[USS Enterprise (NCC-1701-D)|USS ''Enterprise'' (NCC-1701-D)]].&lt;ref name=&quot;tngcompanion&quot;&gt;{{cite book|title=Star Trek: The Next Generation Companion|publisher=Pocket Books|year=2003|author=Nemeck, Larry|id=ISBN 0-7434-5798-6}}&lt;/ref&gt; The [[Encounter at Farpoint|pilot episode]] shows the ship's mission to investigate a problem at Farpoint Station, which  becomes sidetracked when [[Q (Star Trek)|Q]] makes Picard &quot;representative&quot; in a trial charging humanity with being a &quot;dangerously savage child-race&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;tngcompanion&quot; /&gt; Picard persuades Q to test humanity, and Q chooses as the test's first stage the crew's performance at Farpoint.&lt;ref name=&quot;tngcompanion&quot; /&gt; The trial &quot;ends&quot; seven years later (when Q reminds Picard that it never does), in the [[All Good Things...|series finale]], when humanity is absolved by Picard's demonstration that the species has the capacity to explore the &quot;possibilities of existence&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;tngcompanion&quot; /&gt;

The third season finale, &quot;[[The Best of Both Worlds (Star Trek: The Next Generation)|The Best of Both Worlds, Part I]]&quot;, depicts Picard being assimilated by the [[Borg (Star Trek)|Borg]] to serve as a bridge between humanity and the Borg; Picard's assimilation and recovery are a critical point in the character's development, and provided [[backstory]] for the film ''[[Star Trek: First Contact]]'' and the development of [[Benjamin Sisko]], the [[protagonist]] of ''[[Star Trek: Deep Space Nine]]''.&lt;ref name=&quot;tngcompanion&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|title=Star Trek: Deep Space Nine Companion|isbn=1-0671-5010-62|first=Terry J.|last=Erdmann |coauthors=Paula M. Block|publisher=[[Pocket Books]]|year=2000}}&lt;/ref&gt; Stewart asked Roddenberry to keep Picard a Borg for a few more episodes beyond the third season finale, as he thought that would be more interesting than simply restoring Picard in Part II.&lt;ref name=&quot;Hatfield&quot; /&gt; It is later revealed in ''First Contact'' that parts of Borg machinery were removed from inside Picard, but that he retains traumatic memories of assimilation (which becomes a pivotal plot twist in ''Star Trek: First Contact'').

The fourth-season episode &quot;[[Family (Star Trek: The Next Generation)|Family]]&quot; reveals that Picard has a brother, Robert, who took charge of the family vineyards in La Barre after Picard joined Starfleet. Robert and his wife have a young son, René, who is Picard's nephew. During the film ''[[Star Trek Generations]]'', Picard learns that Robert and René have both died in a fire. The fate of Robert's wife, Marie, is not revealed.

Picard joins forces with legendary ''Enterprise'' captain [[James T. Kirk]] in ''Star Trek Generations'' to fight the film's villain, Dr. Tolian Soran. Commanding the new [[USS Enterprise (NCC-1701-E)|USS ''Enterprise''-E]] (after the ''Enterprise''-D is destroyed in ''Generations''), Picard again confronts the Borg in ''First Contact.'' Later, he fights a species' forced relocation in ''[[Star Trek: Insurrection]]'', and encounters Shinzon, a [[Romulan]]-made [[cloning|clone]] of himself, in ''[[Star Trek Nemesis]]''.

==Reception==
{{rquote|right|Captain Kirk was the man of action right down to the very end. They had him off punching out the bad guy...and meantime they had Captain Picard as the intellectual trying to dismantle the missile by doing it through the computer screen...That was Kirk versus Picard, right there in a nutshell.|Dan Cray, ''Los Angeles Times'', on ''Star Trek: Generations''&lt;ref name=&quot;bbccray&quot;&gt;{{cite web | url=http://www.bbc.co.uk/cult/st/interviews/cray/printpage.html | title=Dan Cray - LA Times journalist and Star Trek pundit | publisher=BBC | accessdate=May 07, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;}}
The character's acclaim among fans of the Next Generation version of the show is near universal, and he is usually considered one of the top two characters to have been Captain on a Starfleet vessel in the series.  There are often lengthy and serious debates over who was the &quot;best&quot; Starfleet captain - Picard, or [[James Tiberius Kirk]]. A 1991 ''[[TV Guide]]'' cover story was titled &quot;It's Kirk vs. Picard: Experts and fans debate who's best.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;brady19920405&quot;&gt;{{cite news | url=http://news.google.com/newspapers?id=UlhPAAAAIBAJ&amp;sjid=SgMEAAAAIBAJ&amp;pg=5604%2C1577738 | title=In Step With: Patrick Stewart | work=Parade | date=1992-04-05 | accessdate=April 28, 2011 | author=Brady, James | pages=21}}&lt;/ref&gt; Picard is deemed the ultimate delegator of authority, knowing &quot;how to gather and use data better than any other ''Star Trek'' captain.&quot; His leadership style &quot;is best suited to a large, process-centric, either geographically identical or diverse team&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;Kimmerly&quot;&gt;Paul Kimmerly &amp; David R. Webb, &quot;[http://www.stsc.hill.af.mil/crossTalk/2006/10/0610KimmerlyWebb.html Leadership, The Final Frontier: Lessons From the Captains of Star Trek]&quot; ''CrossTalk: The Journal of Defense Software Engineering'' Oct. 2006&lt;/ref&gt; Kirk and Picard are considered to be attentive to the needs of their respective crews.&lt;ref&gt;John D. W. Beck &amp; Neil M. Yeager, ''The Leader's Window: Mastering the Four Styles of Leadership to Build High-Performing Teams'' New York: Wiley (1994): 38&lt;/ref&gt; When Stewart and [[William Shatner]] were asked in 1991 how their characters would have dealt with Saddam Hussein, however, Shatner stated that Kirk would &quot;have told him to drop dead&quot; while Stewart joked that Picard &quot;would still be talking.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;teitelbaum19910505&quot;&gt;{{cite news | url=http://articles.latimes.com/print/1991-05-05/magazine/tm-2100_1_star-trek | archiveurl=http://www.webcitation.org/5ybc7Wqbr | archivedate=2011-05-11 | title=How Gene Roddenberry and his Brain Trust Have Boldly Taken 'Star Trek' Where No TV Series Has Gone Before : Trekking to the Top | work=Los Angeles Times | publisher=Tribune Company | date=1991-05-05 | pages = 16 | accessdate=April 27, 2011 | author=Teitelbaum, Sheldon}}&lt;/ref&gt; 

[[UGO Networks]] listed Picard as one of their best heroes in entertainment, saying, &quot;He doesn't have Kirk's sense of panache, but he did have a tendency to take everything really, really seriously for years&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.ugo.com/games/best-heroes-of-all-time?page=8|title=Best Heroes of All Time|publisher=UGO Networks|date=21 January 2010|accessdate=3 April 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==References==
{{Reflist|colwidth=30em}}

==External links==
{{wikiquote|Jean-Luc Picard}}
*[http://www.startrek.com/database_article/picard-jean-luc Biography of Jean-Luc Picard] at the official Star Trek website
{{Memoryalpha}}

{{Star Trek ships named Enterprise}}
{{Star Trek TNG}}
{{Star Trek navbox}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Picard, Jean-Luc}}
[[Category:Star Trek: The Next Generation characters]]
[[Category:Star Trek: Deep Space Nine characters]]
[[Category:Star Trek film characters]]
[[Category:Starfleet officers]]
[[Category:Fictional diplomats]]
[[Category:Fictional archaeologists]]
[[Category:Fictional French people]]
[[Category:Starfleet captains]]
[[Category:Fictional characters introduced in 1987]]
[[Category:Fictional speakers of Klingon]]

[[bg:Жан-Люк Пикар]]
[[ca:Jean-Luc Picard]]
[[cs:Jean-Luc Picard]]
[[da:Jean-Luc Picard]]
[[de:Figuren im Star-Trek-Universum#Captain Jean-Luc Picard]]
[[es:Jean-Luc Picard]]
[[fo:Jean-Luc Picard]]
[[fr:Jean-Luc Picard]]
[[ko:쟝 룩 피카드]]
[[hr:Jean-Luc Picard]]
[[id:Jean-Luc Picard]]
[[it:Jean-Luc Picard]]
[[hu:Jean-Luc Picard]]
[[nl:Jean-Luc Picard]]
[[ja:ジャン＝リュック・ピカード]]
[[no:Jean-Luc Picard]]
[[pl:Jean-Luc Picard]]
[[pt:Jean-Luc Picard]]
[[ro:Jean-Luc Picard]]
[[ru:Жан-Люк Пикар]]
[[simple:Jean-Luc Picard]]
[[sk:Jean-Luc Picard]]
[[fi:Jean-Luc Picard]]
[[sv:Jean-Luc Picard]]
[[zh:让-吕克·皮卡尔]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
