<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="186639" ns="0" title="Jimmy Swaggart"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">&lt;!-- Please cite any new material before adding it, as this subject is likely to be highly controversial. See WP:BLP and WP:CITE for more information. --&gt;
{{Infobox person
| name        = Jimmy Lee Swaggart
| image       =  
| image_size  =  
| caption     = 
| birth_date  = {{birth date and age|mf=no|1935|3|15}}
| birth_place = [[Ferriday, Louisiana|Ferriday]], [[Louisiana]], USA
| death_date  = 
| death_place = 
| occupation  = [[Televangelist]], [[preacher]], singer, musician, writer
| religion    = [[Pentecostalism|Pentecostal]] [[Christianity]]
| salary      =
| networth    =
| website     = [http://www.jsm.org/ www.jsm.org]
}}
'''Jimmy Lee Swaggart''' (born March 15, 1935) is a [[Pentecostal]] [[United States|American]] [[pastor]], [[teacher]], [[musician]], [[presenter|television host]], and [[televangelist]]. He has preached to crowds around the world  through his weekly telecast. According to the official website for Jimmy Swaggart Ministries, his 1980s telecast was transmitted to over 3,000 stations and cable systems each week.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.jsm.org Jimmy Swaggart Ministries]&lt;/ref&gt;

Swaggart's television ministry, which began in 1975, continues (as of May 2011) airing nationally and internationally. The weekly ''Jimmy Swaggart Telecast'' and ''A Study in the Word'' programs are seen nationwide and abroad on 78 channels in 104 countries as well as live over the [[Internet]].

In February 1988, Swaggart stirred controversy after a private investigation found he had solicited a prostitute. Initially, Swaggart denied the accusations; but, as a media investigation proceeded, he acknowledged that some allegations were true. He later apologized for the acts in a televised broadcast.

==Early life==
Swaggart was born in [[Ferriday, Louisiana]], to Willie Leon (a.k.a., &quot;Son&quot;) and Minnie Belle (née Herron) Swaggart. He is the cousin of [[rock'n'roll]] pioneer [[Jerry Lee Lewis]] and [[country music]] star [[Mickey Gilley]]. With his parents, Swaggart attended a small, 25-member [[Assemblies of God USA|Assemblies of God]] congregation in Ferriday. At the age of nine, he began to preach on street corners and lead congregations in singing.{{Citation needed|date=January 2010}} On October 10, 1952, Swaggart married Frances Anderson. Their son, Donnie, was born in 1954. Swaggart worked several part-time odd jobs in order to support his young family and also began singing [[Southern Gospel]] music at various [[Baptist]] and [[Pentecostal]] churches.

According to his biography, Swaggart, along with his wife and son, lived in poverty during the 1950s as he preached throughout rural [[Louisiana]], struggling to survive on [[US$|US$30]] a week. Being too poor to own a home, the Swaggarts lived in church basements, pastors' homes, and small motels. [[Sun Records]] producer [[Sam Phillips]] wanted Swaggart to take part in a [[Gospel Music|gospel]] line of music for Sun as the label's first gospel artist. Swaggart's cousin, [[Jerry Lee Lewis]], who had previously signed with Sun, was reportedly making [[US$|$]]20,000 per week at the time. Although the offer meant a promise for significant income for his family, Swaggart turned him down, stating that he was called to preach the gospel.&lt;ref&gt;Jimmy Swaggart, To Cross a River, Logos International, 1977&lt;/ref&gt;

==Ordination and early career==
Preaching from a flatbed trailer donated to him, Swaggart began full-time evangelistic work in 1955.  It was then that Swaggart began developing a revival-meeting following throughout the American South. Swaggart began attending Bible college in 1957.  In 1960, he began recording gospel music record albums while building up another audience via Christian radio stations. In 1961, after graduating from Bible college, Swaggart was ordained by the Assemblies of God; one year later, Swaggart began his radio ministry. By 1969, Swaggart's radio program, “The Camp Meeting Hour,” was being aired over numerous radio stations throughout the American [[Bible Belt]].{{Citation needed|date=January 2010}}  In the late 1960s, Swaggart founded what was then a small church named the Family Worship Center in [[Baton Rouge, Louisiana]]; the church eventually became district-affiliated with the [[Assemblies of God USA|Assemblies of God]].  The Family Worship Center grew from barely 40 members in 1970 to over 500 by 1975 and over 1000 by 1980.{{Citation needed|date=September 2009}} During the 1970s the church grew from a one room church to a more modern building with new additions being built every couple years.

In the late 1960s, Swaggart began airing a weekly 30-minute telecast over various local television stations in that city and also purchased a local AM radio station WLUX in [[Baton Rouge, Louisiana|Baton Rouge]] (now [[WPFC (AM)|WPFC]]).  The station broadcast Christian features stories, preaching and teaching from various [[Christian fundamentalism|fundamentalist]] and Pentecostal denominations and played a blend of [[Black Gospel]], [[Southern gospel]], and inspirational music. As [[Contemporary Christian Music]] became more prevalent, the station avoided playing it. Swaggart would ultimately sell his radio stations gradually throughout the 1980s and early 1990s.

==Shifting to television==
By 1975, Swaggart's television ministry had expanded to more stations around the [[United States|US]]; it was at this time that he decided to use television as his primary preaching venue. In 1978, Swaggart's weekly telecast was expanded to an hour. 

In 1980, Swaggart began a daily weekday telecast featuring Bible study and music while the weekend, hour-long telecast would feature a sermon from either the Family Worship Center or an on-location crusade. In the early 1980s, Swaggart's crusades expanded to major cities nationwide. By 1983, more than 250 TV station featured Swaggart's telecast.  Multitudes of people around the world were converted to Christianity receiving Jesus Christ as their Lord.  

==Controversies, scandals and criticisms==
{{Ref improve section|date=January 2009}}
In 1988, Swaggart was implicated in a sex scandal involving a prostitute that resulted initially in his suspension and ultimately Swaggart was [[defrocked]] and removed from the ministry by the [[Assemblies of God]].  Three years later, Swaggart was again implicated in a sex scandal involving a prostitute.  As a result, Swaggart's current ministry is non-affiliated, non-denominational and considerably smaller than before the scandals were revealed.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |title=Encyclopedia of American religion and politics |last=Djupe |first=Paul A. |coauthors=Olson, Laura R. |year=2008 |publisher=Checkmark Books |isbn=978-0816075553 |page=430 |url=http://books.google.com.au/books?id=frt7RDOT1PUC&amp;pg=PA430&amp;dq=jimmy+swaggart+prostitute#v=onepage&amp;q=jimmy%20swaggart%20prostitute&amp;f=false |accessdate=March 13, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===1988 scandal===
====Background====
Swaggart's exposure came as retaliation for an incident in 1986 when Swaggart exposed fellow [[Assemblies of God USA|Assemblies of God]] minister Marvin Gorman, who had been accused of having several affairs. &lt;!-- [commenting out unsourced and potentially libelous sentence] --&gt; &lt;!-- [commented out speculative and unsourced sentence] --&gt;Once exposed, Gorman was defrocked from the Assemblies of God, with his ministry all but ended. As a retaliatory move, Gorman hired his son Randy and son-in-law Garland Bilbo to stake out the [[Travel Inn]] on Airline Highway in [[New Orleans]]. A camera with a [[telephoto lens]] was placed in the window of the motel's Room 12 and draped with a black cloth. When Swaggart arrived, he reportedly went into Room 7. Randy Gorman and Garland Bilbo proceeded to let the air out of Swaggart's tires and called Marvin Gorman, whose church was located nearby. The two had taken photos of Swaggart outside of Room 7 with Debra Murphree, a local prostitute. Gorman showed up at the Travel Inn a short while later and asked Swaggart what he was doing there. 

According to, ''Swaggart: The Unauthorized Biography of an American Evangelist'' by Ann Rowe Seaman, Gorman secured a promise from Swaggart that he would publicly apologize to Gorman and start the process of Gorman's reinstatement to the Assemblies of God. &lt;!-- [commented out private detective- it was his son in law] --&gt; &lt;!-- [commented out &quot;and took pictures of the tyrst- he took pictures of Swaggart outside the hotel room] --&gt; Gorman offered to remain silent if Swaggart would state publicly that he lied about Gorman's affairs. Gorman waited almost a year, then hand delivered a note to Swaggart informing him his time was up, but Swaggart did not respond.  On February 16, 1988, Gorman contacted James Hamil, one of the 13 man Executive Presbytery of the Assemblies of God. Hamill in turn called Raymond Carlson, the Assemblies Superintendent. He summoned Hamill and Gorman to fly to Springfield and arranged for an emergency meeting of the presbyters. Carlson was shown photos of several men coming in and going out of Room 7 at the Travel Inn Motel in New Orleans. This was done in order to establish the fact that the room was being used for prostitution. One of the men seen leaving Room 7 was Jimmy Swaggart.   &lt;!-- [commented out &quot;he Gorman presented Swaggart with the photos in a blackmail attempt to force Swaggart to come clean, but Swaggart refused&quot; it is not a true statement] --&gt; The presbytery leadership of the Assemblies of God decided that Swaggart should be suspended from broadcasting his television program for three months.

According to the [[Associated Press]], Murphree, who claimed to have posed nude for Swaggart, failed a [[polygraph test]] administered by a [[New York City Police Department]] polygraph expert.&lt;ref&gt;Associated Press. ''[[Ocala Star-Banner]]'', 27 February 1988.&lt;/ref&gt; The test administrator concluded that Murphree had failed to tell the truth on all key questions concerning her statement. The test was administered after Murphree offered to sell the story to the ''[[National Enquirer]]'' for $100,000. Paul Levy, senior editor for the ''Enquirer'', stated that the polygraph examiner had concluded Murphree was not truthful on six key questions, including one in which she was reportedly asked if she had fabricated the story. Levy stated that the ''Enquirer'' decided not to print her story due to the test results, her drug use, and the fact that she had arrest warrants in three states. Murphree failed questions about whether she was paid or promised money to &quot;set up&quot; Swaggart, and whether she made up the story in order to make money from it.&lt;ref&gt;''[[Toronto Star]]'', 27 February 1988.&lt;/ref&gt; Both times she answered no; this was determined by the polygraph examiner to be a lie.

====Swaggart's confession and fallout====
[[File:Swaggart confession screenshot.png|thumb|right|Swaggart's confession]]
On February 21, 1988, without giving any details regarding his transgressions, Swaggart gave his now infamous &quot;I Have Sinned&quot; speech as he tearfully spoke to his family, congregation and TV audience, saying, &quot;I have sinned against You, my Lord, and I would ask that Your precious blood would wash and cleanse every stain until it is in the seas of God's forgiveness.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://americanrhetoric.com/speeches/jswaggartapologysermon.html |title=Reverend Jimmy Swaggart: Apology Sermon |accessdate=2007-01-25 |last=Swaggart |first=Jimmy |work=americanrhetoric.com }}&lt;/ref&gt; On a New Orleans morning news show four days later, Murphree stated that while Swaggart was a regular customer, they had never engaged in sexual intercourse.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://everything2.com/title/Jimmy%2520Swaggart |title=Jimmy Swaggart@Everything2.com}}&lt;/ref&gt;  The clip of Swaggart's confession was played repeatedly on news and tabloid television programs.

The [[Louisiana]] presbytery of the [[Assemblies of God USA|Assemblies of God]] initially suspended Jimmy Swaggart from the ministry for three months. The national presbytery of the Assemblies of God soon extended the suspension to their standard two-year suspension for sexual immorality. His return to the pulpit coincided with the end of a three-month suspension originally ordered by the Assemblies. Believing that Swaggart was not genuinely repentant in not submitting to their authority, the hierarchy of the Assemblies of God immediately defrocked him, removing his credentials and ministerial license. It was then that Swaggart decided he would be an independent, non-denominational Pentecostal minister and the Family Worship Center would become non-denominational.  The Jimmy Swaggart Bible College would lose many of its students by the end of May 1988.

===1991 scandal===
On October 11, 1991, Swaggart was found, for the second time, in the company of a prostitute, Rosemary Garcia,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news | title=Swaggart Plans to Step Down | date=October 15, 1991 | url=http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0CE5DA1E3BF936A25753C1A967958260 | work =The New York Times | accessdate = 2007-01-25 }}&lt;/ref&gt; when he was pulled over by the [[California Highway Patrol]] in [[Indio, California]], for driving on the wrong side of the road. According to Garcia, Swaggart stopped to proposition her on the side of the road. When the patrolman asked Garcia why she was with Swaggart, she replied, &quot;He asked me for sex. I mean, that's why he stopped me. That's what I do. I'm a prostitute.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;[http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0CE5DA1E3BF936A25753C1A967958260 Swaggart Plans to Step Down] ''New York Times''&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.ntskeptics.org/1991/1991november/november1991.htm The Newsletter of The North Texas Skeptics&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt; Rather than confessing to his congregation, Swaggart told those at Family Worship Center that &quot;The Lord told me it's flat none of your business.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.time.com/time/magazine/article/0,9171,974120,00.html American Notes Scandals]''Time''&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.pittsburghlive.com/x/pittsburghtrib/opinion/columnists/datelinedc/s_558619.html The arrogance of power] ''Pittsburgh Tribune-Review''&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news| url=http://news.bbc.co.uk/onthisday/hi/dates/stories/february/21/newsid_2565000/2565197.stm | work=BBC News | title=1988: TV evangelist quits over sex scandal | date=February 21, 1988 | accessdate=May 6, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; Swaggart's son then announced to the stunned audience that his father would be temporarily stepping down as head of Jimmy Swaggart Ministries for &quot;a time of healing and counseling.&quot;

===Criticism of Christian rock and metal music===
Swaggart wrote a book criticizing the [[Christian rock]] and [[Christian metal|metal]] movements titled ''Religious Rock n' Roll&amp;nbsp;– A Wolf in Sheep's Clothing'' in 1987. The book criticized the scene for using heavy metal music to preach the gospel of Christianity, calling rock music the music of [[the devil]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Rock_for_the_King_1&quot;&gt;{{cite web | last = | first = | url = http://www.metalfortheking.kit.net/thocrm.htm | title = History of Christian Rock/Metal part 1 | work = Rock for the King | publisher = Ope Publishing | accessdate = 2007-12-19|language=Portuguese}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Rock_for_the King_2&quot;&gt;{{cite web | last = | first = | url = http://www.metalfortheking.kit.net/thocrm02.htm | title = History of Christian Rock/Metal part 2| work = Rock for the King | publisher = Ope Publishing | accessdate = 2007-12-19|language=Portuguese}}&lt;/ref&gt; Swaggart also criticized [[Larry Norman]] (the &quot;father of Christian rock&quot;), [[Petra (band)|Petra]], [[Mylon LeFevre]], [[Steve Taylor]] and other notable Christian rock and metal bands.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.guidetopetra.com/tributes.html?ID=67 A Guide to Petra: Petra Retirement Tribute Page - post your thoughts on Petra's retirement announcement&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;

In 1986, Swaggart called rock music &quot;the new [[pornography]].&quot;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.cas.sc.edu/socy/faculty/deflem/zzcens97.htm Rap, Rock, and Censorship by Mathieu Deflem]&lt;/ref&gt;

==Ministries==
Jimmy Swaggart Ministries, worth multiple millions of dollars, mainly comprises the Family Worship Center, ''The Jimmy Swaggart Telecast'',&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.jsm.org/explore.cfm/tvprogramming/cablesatellites |title=Jimmy Swaggart Ministries&amp;nbsp;— TV Programming |accessdate=2007-01-28 |archiveurl = http://web.archive.org/web/20070123133753/http://www.jsm.org/explore.cfm/tvprogramming/cablesatellites &lt;!-- Bot retrieved archive --&gt; |archivedate = 2007-01-23}}&lt;/ref&gt; radio and television programs called ''A Study in the Word'', (SonLife Radio Network),&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.jsm.org/explore.cfm/sonliferadio/programminglog |title=Jimmy Swaggart Ministries&amp;nbsp;— SonLife Radio|accessdate=2007-02-22 |archiveurl = http://web.archive.org/web/20070202204930/http://www.jsm.org/explore.cfm/sonliferadio/programminglog &lt;!-- Bot retrieved archive --&gt; |archivedate = 2007-02-02}}&lt;/ref&gt; and a website, JSM.org. 

Swaggart's wife Frances hosts a television program ''Frances and Friends'' which is seen daily on the SonLife Broadcasting Network.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.francesandfriends.com |title=Frances and Friends}}&lt;/ref&gt; His son Donnie preaches at the Family Worship Center and also preaches in churches across the US and abroad.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.donnieswaggart.com |title=Donnie Swaggart}}&lt;/ref&gt; Donnie's son Gabriel is a [[youth pastor]] who leads the Family Worship Center's youth ministry, Crossfire.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web| url=http://www.crossfireyouthministry.org |title=CrossFire}}&lt;/ref&gt; 

The newest outreach, Sonlife Broadcasting Network, can be watched 24/7 on [[DirecTV]] channel 344, [[Dish Network]] channel 257, and [[Glorystar]] channel 125. Sonlife Broadcasting Network television channel is also available on IPTV [[Sky Angel]] channel 125.

===Music ministry===
Swaggart's first album, ''Some Golden Daybreak'', was created to give people at his early revivals. Swaggart's wife began encouraging him to contact radio stations. [[Disc jockey]] Chuck Cossin is credited with playing the first Jimmy Swaggart recording on WMUZ in [[Detroit]].{{Citation needed|date=September 2009}}

In 1974 Swaggart was voted Favorite Gospel Music Artist by readers of the magazine ''Singing News''.  In 1977 ''Record World'' magazine honored him as Male Vocalist of the Year. In that same year Swaggart was a [[Dove Award]] finalist in three categories: Male Vocalist of the Year, TV Program of the Year, and Instrumentalist of the Year.  Again in 1978 Swaggart became a [[Dove Award|Dove]] finalist as Instrumentalist of the Year.  In 1980, Swaggart became a Dove Award finalist in four categories:  Children's Album of the Year for ''Color Me a Story'', Instrumentalist of the Year, Year's best Traditional Album for ''Homeward Bound'', and Best Gospel Album of the Year for ''Worship''. The secular [[Grammy Awards]] nominated Swaggart's album ''Live from Nashville'' for Best Gospel Album in 1976. And again in 1980, Swaggart's album, ''Worship'', became a [[Grammy]] finalist.

===Radio ministry===
Swaggart originated Sonlife Radio on the noncommercial [[FM band|FM]] band. Unlike his previous stations, Sonlife was commercial free and would not sell time to outside ministries and the preaching and teaching would all be produced &quot;in house&quot;. The music played was primarily [[Southern Gospel]]. Sonlife Radio is heard in 22 states.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.jsm.org/explore.cfm/sonliferadio/stationlist|title=SonLife station list}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Television ministry===
In 1973, Swaggart wanted to create a television program which would include a fairly large music segment, a short sermon, and time for talking about current ministry projects. After two faltering attempts to tape the half-hour program in [[Baton Rouge, Louisiana|Baton Rouge]] and [[New Orleans, Louisiana]], Swaggart went to television producers in [[Nashville, Tennessee]] with his proposal. They accepted and within weeks the ''Jimmy Swaggart Telecast'' was being broadcast into television markets around the United States.

In 1981 Jimmy Swaggart launched a daily television program titled ''A Study in the Word''.  In the 1980s the program was aired on over 160 channels throughout the U.S., [[Canada]] and abroad and is still seen today on over 78 stations in 104 countries.{{Citation needed|date=September 2009}} From the beginning, the primary cable channels the program was aired on were [[CBN Cable]] (now [[ABC Family]]), [[Trinity Broadcasting Network|TBN]], and [[PTL Satellite Network|PTL]] (now [[Inspiration Network]]).

Sonlife Broadcasting Network, can be watched 24/7 on [[DirecTV]] channel 344, [[Dish Network]] channel 257, [[Glorystar]] channel 125 and on IPTV [[Sky Angel]] channel 125.

===World Evangelism Bible College===
In the fall of 1984, Swaggart opened Jimmy Swaggart Bible College - now known as World Evangelism Bible College, or WEBC. The college began as a means of preparing young men and women for Christian ministry and is still considered by Swaggart to be a vital extension of Jimmy Swaggart's World Wide Ministry. Many students never returned for the fall semester after the scandal in 1988. Currently, WEBC offers three levels of degrees: (1) Intensive short term certificate programs, (2) Associate of Arts degree programs, and (3) a four year [[Bachelor's Degree]] program.

===Print===
Swaggart is the author of about 20 Christian books offered through his ministry.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.goodreads.com/author/list/268010.Jimmy_Swaggart&lt;/ref&gt; He is the author of the &quot;Expositor's Study Bible,&quot;&lt;ref&gt;http://www.amazon.com/Expositors-Study-Bible-KJVersion-Concordance/dp/0976953005&lt;/ref&gt; 13 Study Guides and 30 Commentaries on the Bible.

==Family==
Swaggart is married to Frances (née Anderson) Swaggart and has one son, [[Donnie Swaggart]].  Donnie was named for Swaggart's brother who died in infancy. He has three grandchildren, Jennifer, Gabriel and Matthew Swaggart, and three great-grandchildren, Samantha, Abby and Ryder Swaggart.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.jsm.org/about_jimmy_swaggart.php |title=Jimmy Swaggart Ministries&amp;nbsp;— About Jimmy Swaggart |accessdate=2010-07-19 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

==In popular culture==
{{trivia|date=August 2011}}
*The Swaggart sex scandal was satirized by musician [[Frank Zappa]] in a three-song medley referred to by band members as the &quot;Texas Motel Medley&quot;, consisting of three songs by [[the Beatles]] with the lyrics changed to reflect the events, and in the songs &quot;What Kind of Girl?&quot; and &quot;Jesus Thinks You're A Jerk&quot;.

*Swaggart was parodied on ''[[Saturday Night Live]]'' (Season 13, Ep. 13, February 27, 1988) by a tearful [[Phil Hartman]] in a &quot;Church Chat&quot; sketch, hosted by [[The Church Lady]].

*On the American [[sitcom]] ''[[Married... with Children]]'', Swaggart was parodied by Rev. [[Al Bundy]], and his sham Church of NO MA'AM, when he was exposed to his [[Misogyny|misogynistic]] congregation that he had a loving relationship with his wife [[Married..._With_Children#Peggy_Bundy|Peg Bundy]].

*Swaggart is [[sampling (music)|sampled]] thundering &quot;No sex until marriage!&quot; on the [[Front 242]] track &quot;Welcome to Paradise&quot; -- released, ironically, in 1988, the year his first sex scandal broke.

*The band [[Electric Hellfire Club]] sampled Swaggart's &quot;I have sinned against you, my Lord&quot; in a song called &quot;Hypochristian&quot; released on the ''Electronomicon'' album.

*Swaggart is referenced in a 1988 episode of ''[[The Golden Girls]]'' titled &quot;Rose's Big Adventure.&quot;

*Swaggart is referenced in a 1992 episode of ''[[The Fresh Prince of Bel-Air]]'' titled &quot;Eyes on the Prize.&quot;

*Swaggart was played by actor [[Alec Baldwin]] in the 1989 Jerry Lee Lewis biopic ''[[Great Balls of Fire! (film)|Great Balls of Fire!]]''.

*Swaggart, along with cousins [[Mickey Gilley]] and [[Jerry Lee Lewis]], is an inductee of the [[Delta Music Museum]] Hall of Fame in [[Ferriday, Louisiana]].

*Swaggart is referenced in [[The Tractors]] song &quot;[[Baby Likes to Rock It]]&quot;.

*Swaggart is referenced as &quot;Jimmy the Reptile&quot; in the [[Iron Maiden]] song &quot;[[Holy Smoke (song)|Holy Smoke]]&quot;.

*Swaggart is mentioned in the [[Lou Reed]] song &quot;[[Strawman]]&quot;, on the album ''[[New York (album)|New York]]''.

*Swaggart is referenced in the [[Cinderella (band)|Cinderella]] song &quot;Shelter Me&quot;.  In the video for the song, Swaggart is depicted bursting out of a closet surrounded by skeletons, and also sobbing behind a flaming pulpit.

*Swaggart was parodied by [[Jim Carrey]] on ''[[In Living Color]]''.

*[[Ozzy Osbourne's]] song &quot;Miracle Man&quot;, on the 1988 album ''[[No Rest for the Wicked (Ozzy Osbourne album)|No Rest For The Wicked]]'', is about the Swaggart's 1988 [[Jimmy Swaggart#Sex scandals|prostitution scandal]] and the general hypocrisy, in Osbourne's eyes, of &quot;[[televangelism|televangelists]]&quot;. 

*Swaggart is referenced in the [[Dr. Dre]] song &quot;[[Lyrical Gangbang]]&quot;, on the album ''[[The Chronic]]''.

*Swaggart is mentioned in [[XTC]] song &quot;Merely a Man&quot; on their album ''[[Oranges and Lemons]]''. During their U.S. acoustic radio tour for the aforementioned album in 1989, [[XTC]] altered their song [[Dear God (XTC song)|&quot;Dear God&quot;]] to include Swaggart's name.

*[[Skinny Puppy]] sampled Swaggart's &quot;I am clean&quot; speech on the song &quot;Hexonxonx&quot; on their ''[[Rabies (Skinny Puppy album)|Rabies]]'' album.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |title=Skinny Puppy Sample Source List |url=http://www.tomstation.net/Skinny_Puppy_Sample_Sources.rtf |accessdate=2010-01-14}}&lt;/ref&gt;

*Christian Rock pioneer [[Larry Norman]], who had been criticized by Swaggart, wrote a song &quot;Selah&quot;, which he released in 1989, that refers obliquely to Swaggart.

*Swaggart was referenced in the [[Big L]] song &quot;Danger Zone&quot;, on the album ''[[Lifestylez Ov Da Poor &amp; Dangerous]]''.

==See also==
* [[List of Christian evangelist scandals]]

==References==
{{Reflist}}

==External links==
* [http://www.jsm.org Jimmy Swaggart Ministries]
* [http://www.who2.com/jimmyswaggart.html Jimmy Swaggart in Who2]
* [http://www.fmh-child.org/mycatholicfriends.html Jimmy Swaggart's A Letter To My Catholic Friends]
* [http://www.jsmpodcast.info Jimmy Swaggart Podcast Information]
* {{imdb name|0841438}}

{{PTL scandal}}

{{Persondata &lt;!-- Metadata: see [[Wikipedia:Persondata]]. --&gt;
| NAME              =Swaggart, Jimmy
| ALTERNATIVE NAMES =
| SHORT DESCRIPTION =
| DATE OF BIRTH     =mf=no
| PLACE OF BIRTH    =[[Ferriday, Louisiana]], USA
| DATE OF DEATH     =
| PLACE OF DEATH    =
}}
{{DEFAULTSORT:Swaggart, Jimmy}}
[[Category:American evangelists]]
[[Category:American Pentecostals]]
[[Category:American television evangelists]]
[[Category:Religious scandals]]
[[Category:People from Ferriday, Louisiana]]
[[Category:1935 births]]
[[Category:Living people]]
[[Category:Assemblies of God clergy]]
[[Category:Pentecostal clergy]]
[[Category:Pentecostal writers]]
[[Category:American Christian clergy]]
[[Category:Criticism of Islam]]
[[Category:Anti-Catholicism in the United States]]
[[Category:American Pentecostal clergy]]

[[ar:جيمي سواجارت]]
[[de:Jimmy Swaggart]]
[[es:Jimmy Swaggart]]
[[pt:Jimmy Swaggart]]
[[simple:Jimmy Swaggart]]
[[fi:Jimmy Swaggart]]
[[sv:Jimmy Swaggart]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
