<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="1868387" ns="0" title="Daphne Ashbrook"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{BLP sources|date=January 2010}}
{{Infobox person
| name            = Daphne Ashbrook
| image           =
| imagesize       =
| caption         =
| birthname       = Daphne Lee Ashbrook
| birth_date       = {{birth date and age|1963|1|30}}
| birth_place      = [[Long Beach, California|Long Beach]], [[California]]
| yearsactive     = 1983-present
| othername       = Daphne Lee Ashbrook &lt;br&gt; Dapne Lee Ashbrook
| spouse          =
| domesticpartner = [[Lorenzo Lamas]] 1 daughter
| website         = http://www.DaphneAshbrook.com
}}

'''Daphne Lee Ashbrook''' (born January 30, 1963) is an [[United States|American]] [[actress]].

==Personal life==
Daphne Ashbrook was raised in the San Diego, CA area. Her parents are San Diego theatre actress D'Ann Paton and late actor/Director Buddy Ashbrook. Her siblings are actor [[Dana Ashbrook]] and director Taylor Ashbrook.

In 1988, Ashbrook had a daughter, Paton (Peyton) Lee Ashbrook, with former boyfriend [[Lorenzo Lamas]]. Paton is also an actress.

==Career==
Known for both her comic timing and deep emotional portrayals, she has appeared in many television and film roles including ''[[Star Trek: Deep Space Nine]]'' (as the [[List of Star Trek: Deep Space Nine characters#Pazlar, Melora|titular character]] in &quot;[[Melora (DS9 episode)|Melora]]&quot;) and the ''[[Doctor Who]]'' [[Doctor Who (1996)|telemovie]], in which she played the role of Doctor [[Grace Holloway]]. Her portrayal as Grace in ''Doctor Who'' caused consternation among some of that show's fans because she was the first character to romantically kiss [[Doctor (Doctor Who)|the Doctor]], setting a precedent for the more sexually charged nature of the new ''Doctor Who'' series that began in 2005.

A 2004 trip to the United Kingdom was filmed for the 2005 documentary ''Daphne Ashbrook in the UK''. This DVD documentary followed her work with ''Doctor Who'', including her role as Perfection in the [[Big Finish Productions]] audio play ''[[The Next Life]]''. She performed opposite [[Paul McGann]] for first time since the 1996 telemovie. In 2006, she played Charlotte Howell in the audio drama ''[[Dark Shadows: The Book of Temptation]]'' for the same company. She has been to the UK twice thus far for ''Doctor Who'' convention events. She was featured in extensive interviews on the ''Doctor Who'' podcast [[Doctor Who: DWO Whocast]] and ''Doctor Who'' podcast [[Doctor Who: Podshock]]. Additionally, she featured in other Doctor Who podcasts

She was notable as being one of only ten actors—and the only woman—to be credited in both the ''[[Star Trek]]'' and ''Doctor Who'' franchises.&lt;ref&gt;http://memory-alpha.org/en/wiki/Daphne_Ashbrook&lt;/ref&gt; until the appearance of [[Nana Visitor]] on [[Torchwood: Miracle Day]] in 2011, 15 years later. &lt;ref&gt;http://www.imdb.com/name/nm0000684/&lt;/ref&gt;

Her past TV work includes Cold Case, CSI, Crossing Jordan, JAG, Murder She Wrote, Judging Amy, the Profiler, Guardian, [[The O.C.]] and Cupid. She also starred in one episode of [[Street Hawk]] titled, &quot;Dog Eat Dog&quot; which aired in February 1985. Her recent roles include a part in David Ondaatje's 2009 motion picture &quot;The Lodger&quot; starring Alfred Molina, Shane West, Simon Baker and Hope Davis, and guest starring roles in [[The Ghost Whisperer]], with Jennifer Love Hewitt, and [[Without a Trace]] with Anthony LaPaglia and Steven Weber. She guest starred as a dancer visiting from (the former) Czechoslavakia in the third season of Fame.

Hirst Publishing, a UK-based publishing house, has announced it will be releasing an autobiography by Ashbrook, ''Dead Woman Laughing'', at the end of 2011.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.hirstpublishing.com/Dead+Woman+Laughing+-+Daphne+Ashbrook/p384445_2636749.aspx Hirst Publishing - Dead Woman Laughing], accessed Feb. 10, 2011&lt;/ref&gt;

==References==
{{Reflist}}

==External links==
*[http://www.DaphneAshbrook.com Daphne Ashbrook website] Artist's website with sections on Doctor Who &amp; Star Trek Deep Space Nine.
*{{IMDb name|0038695}}
*{{Amg name|2508}}

{{memoryalpha}}

{{Persondata
|NAME=Ashbrook, Daphne
|ALTERNATIVE NAMES=
|SHORT DESCRIPTION=United States actor
|DATE OF BIRTH=January 30
|PLACE OF BIRTH=Long Beach, California, United States
|DATE OF DEATH=
|PLACE OF DEATH=
}}
{{DEFAULTSORT:Ashbrook, Daphne}}
[[Category:American television actors]]
[[Category:American film actors]]
[[Category:Actors from California]]
[[Category:People from San Diego, California]]
[[Category:1963 births]]
[[Category:Living people]]

[[de:Daphne Ashbrook]]
[[it:Daphne Ashbrook]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
