<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="18753783" ns="0" title="IPFW Mastodons"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Infobox college athletics
|name             = IPFW Mastodons
|logo             = IPFWMastodons.png 
|university       = [[Indiana University – Purdue University Fort Wayne]]
|conference       = [[The Summit League]] &lt;br&gt; [[Midwestern Intercollegiate Volleyball Association|MIVA Conference]]
|division         = [[Division I (NCAA)|Division I]]
|director         = Tommy Bell
|city             = Fort Wayne
|state            = Indiana
|stateabb         = IN
|teams            = 15
|stadium          = N/A
|arena            = [[Allen County War Memorial Coliseum]]
|mascot           = Don the Mastodon
|nickname         = Mastodons
|fightsong        = Go 'Dons!
|color1           = Royal Blue
|color2           = White
|hex1             = 4169E1
|hex2             = FFFFFF
|pageurl          = http://gomastodons.cstv.com/
|pagename         = gomastodons.cstv.com//
}}

The '''IPFW Mastodons''' are the athletic teams of [[Indiana University - Purdue University Fort Wayne]]. The Mastodons compete as an [[National Collegiate Athletic Association]] [[Division I (NCAA)|Division I]] school in the [[The Summit League]] for most sports and in the [[Midwestern Intercollegiate Volleyball Association]] for men's volleyball. The university participates in 15 men’s and women’s sports. Before joining NCAA Division I athletics, IPFW competed in the [[Great Lakes Valley Conference]] in the [[NCAA]] [[Division II (NCAA)|Division II]].

== Athletics ==
The university participates in 15 men’s and women’s sports:
{{col-begin}}{{col-2}}
===Men's sports===
*[[College baseball|Baseball]]
*[[College basketball|Basketball]]
*[[Cross country running|Cross country]]
*[[Golf]]
*[[College soccer|Soccer]]
*[[Tennis]]
*[[Volleyball]]
{{col-break}}
===Women's sports===
*[[College basketball|Basketball]]
*[[Cross country running|Cross country]]
*[[Golf]]
*[[College soccer|Soccer]]
*[[Softball]]
*[[Tennis]]
*[[Track and Field]] (indoor and outdoor)
*[[Volleyball]]
{{col-end}}

=== Basketball (men's) ===
{{Main|IPFW Mastodons men's basketball}}
Before joining [[NCAA]] Division I athletics, IPFW competed in the [[Great Lakes Valley Conference]] in some sports in the [[NCAA]] Division II, where in 1993, the men’s basketball team led by brothers Sean and Shane Gibson achieved the ranking of #4 in the country in [[NCAA]] Division II competition. Dane Fife was named the IPFW men’s basketball head coach during summer 2005. Fife, who remains the helm, was the youngest [[NCAA]] Division I head coach at the time of his appointment, at the age of 26.
 
=== Men's volleyball ===
IPFW’s men’s volleyball team has gained national exposure repeatedly, based on its showing in several NCAA Final Four tournaments. Men’s Volleyball Head Coach [[Arnie Ball]], who has led the Volleydons for 30 years, began the 2009–10 school year with more than 460 wins as an [[NCAA]] Division I coach. His teams have made six [[NCAA]] Final Four appearances, finishing fourth in 1992 and 1994, third in 1991, 1999, and 2006, and second in 2007. Ball is the father of [[Lloy Ball|Lloy]], a one-time Volleydon, who has achieved [[Olympic Games|Olympic]] success, having served as the U.S. [[Olympic Games|Olympic]] volleyball team captain in 1996, 2000, and 2004 and becoming a gold medalist in 2008. Fundraising for the $1 million Arnie Ball Legacy Endowment Fund was completed by January 2010. The university will match this amount. IPFW has become the first American university to establish a men's volleyball program whose scholarships are fully funded from an endowment.

== Venues ==
IPFW has no football team. Although IPFW has no arena or stadium of its own, the venue for IPFW's large-attendance indoor athletic events is the [[Allen County War Memorial Coliseum]] which is adjacent to the portion of the IPFW campus on the west side of the Saint Joseph River. For example, IPFW hosted the 2000 NCAA Men's Division-I [[volleyball]] championship matches at the Coliseum. Smaller athletic events are held at the [[Hilliard Gates Sports Center]] on the IPFW campus.

== Mascot and Monikers ==
[[Image:IPFWMastodons.png|right|thumb|IPFW Mastodons logo]]
In 1968 a large bone was discovered during the installation of a farm pond near Angola, [[Indiana]], about 40 miles north of Fort Wayne. The farmer contacted professors in the Indiana University–Purdue University Fort Wayne geology department, who identified his discovery as the leg bone of a mastodon. Faculty and students from the geology department excavated the greater part of an adult mastodon, including the skull and tusks. The bones were cleaned, preserved, and placed on permanent display at IPFW. In 1970 members of the geology club, led by professors who oversaw the excavation, successfully lobbied the student government committee charged with choosing a name for the university mascot to select the mastodon. And thus, the IPFW Mastodons were born [9]. In addition to serving as a mascot, “mastodon” is used as the athletic moniker for team members and school-spirited references to the student body. The selection of the mastodon as mascot—as well as a tongue-in-cheek borrowing of the term “don” from its academic British English use—lends itself to be a suffix to refer to the athletics teams as well, such as Volleydons for the volleyball teams. In a related reference, the Mastodon STOMP pep band instills school spirit among the fans during home matches and games.

== References ==
{{Reflist}}

== External Links ==
* [http://gomastodons.cstv.com/ gomastodons.cstv.com]
* [http://www.ipfw.edu Official university website]]

{{The Summit League}}
{{MIVA Conference}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Ipfw Mastodons}}
[[Category:IPFW Mastodons]]
[[Category:Midwestern Intercollegiate Volleyball Association]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
