<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="18758407" ns="0" title="Wimpy (restaurant)"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{About|hamburger chain||Wimpy (disambiguation){{!}}Wimpy}}
{{Infobox company
| name = Wimpy
| logo = [[Image:Wimpy logo.svg|200px]]
| type = Wholly owned subsidiary
| parent = [[Famous Brands Limited]]
| industry = Restaurants
| foundation = Chicago (USA) (1930s) [http://www.worthpoint.com/worthopedia/old-wimpy-chicago-hamburger-coffee-cup-restaurant]. Coventry Street, London (UK) (1954)
| founder = Eddie Gold (USA), [[J. Lyons and Co]] (UK)
| homepage = [http://www.wimpy.uk.com/ UK website], [http://www.wimpy.co.za/ South African Website]
| products = Fast Food&lt;br/&gt;([[hamburgers]]{{•}}chicken{{•}}[[french fries]])
}}

'''Wimpy''' is the brand name of a chain of fast-food [[hamburger]] restaurants based in the United Kingdom.

==History==
[[File:Wimpy in Huddersfield.jpg|thumb|left|A Wimpy restaurant in [[Huddersfield]], West Yorkshire]]

The Wimpy brand was created in the 1930s. The name was inspired by the character of [[J. Wellington Wimpy]] from the [[Popeye]] cartoons created by [[E. C. Segar]]. Eddie Gold was running 12 restaurants by the early 1950s, when the concept of fast food came to the attention of the directors of [[J. Lyons and Co]]. Lyons licensed the brand for use in the United Kingdom and in 1954 the first &quot;Wimpy Bar&quot; Lyons was established at the [[Lyons Corner House]] in Coventry Street, London.&lt;ref name=moments&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.wimpy.uk.com/moments.htm |title=Wimpy Moments |accessdate=1 July 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; Originally the bar was a special fast-food section within the more traditional Corner House restaurants, but the success soon led to the establishment of separate Wimpy restaurants serving only hamburger based meals. By 1970 the business had expanded to over a thousand restaurants in 23 countries.&lt;ref name=moments /&gt;

In 1977, the business was acquired by [[United Biscuits]]. By the late 1980s, Wimpy was beginning to lose ground to [[McDonald's|McDonald’s]], who had opened their first UK restaurant in 1974, and so the new management of Wimpy began to streamline the business by converting some of the traditional [[table service]] restaurants to counter service. In 1989, the business was sold to [[Grand Metropolitan]] (now [[Diageo]]). Grand Metropolitan had acquired [[Burger King]] the previous year and they began to convert the “[[counter service]]” restaurants to Burger King restaurants. In 1990, the remaining 220 “table service” restaurants were purchased by a management buy-out backed by [[3i]]. A second management buy-out occurred in 2002.

Although Wimpy has decreased in numbers in the United Kingdom, it is still found in some towns and cities and at the Dundee [[Megabowl]]&lt;ref&gt;http://www.dundeemegabowl.co.uk/ {{dead link|date=January 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; and Namco Funscape Newcastle (XS Super Bowl) bowling alleys.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.namcofunscape.com/#/newcastle/food-drink/&lt;/ref&gt; The branches at the Roadchef and bowling alley locations typically have an 'express' counter service as opposed to a table service format.

Wimpy is the only major fast food chain that offers [[Quorn]] burgers on the menu.

On 27 February 2007, Famous Brands, which owns the Wimpy franchise in South Africa, announced that it had acquired Wimpy UK.  Having acquired the brand, Famous Brands has re-branded Wimpy in the UK to bring it in line with Wimpy South Africa.  The &quot;new&quot; logo is actually one used by Wimpy UK from the 1960s until the 1980s.

Wimpy is currently re-branding and refreshing all its restaurants, an operation which commenced on 22 October 2007 with the launch of the new format at the [[South Benfleet|Benfleet]], Essex branch. Wimpy features new décor, seating and signage and a return to the original Wimpy colours of red and white. Supporting the new look is an improved menu and a significant marketing campaign.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.wimpy.uk.com/press-embargo.htm |title=Wimpy New Format |publisher=Wimpy.uk.com |date=22 October 2007 |accessdate=25 January 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Outside the United Kingdom==
===Egypt and Morocco===
{{Copy edit|section|date=March 2011}}
{{unreferenced section|date=March 2011}}
Wimpy used to have many branches in [[Egypt]] and Morocco. It was the first international burger restaurant in Egypt and it was Morocco's second. However, both businesses were closed by 1998 in both countries.

In Egypt, there was a network of branches which covered almost all districts in [[Cairo]] and [[Alexandria]]. The [[Mohandissein]] branch was owned and managed directly by the agent in Egypt. Wimpy was expanded in Egypt through signing several [[Franchising|franchise]] contracts with [[Egpytians|Egyptian]] investors. Part of those franchise branches are: 'Maryland branch' in [[Heliopolis (Cairo suburb)|Heliopolis]], [[Pyramids]] Branch, Shooting Club branch, [[Hoda Shaarawi]] branch, [[Talaat Harb]] branch, [[Nasser City]] branch, [[Manshyet El Bakry]] branch and many others. [[Maryland]] branch in [[Heliopolis (Cairo suburb)|Heliopolis]] was found by [[Raafat Sadek Zahran]] and his sons [[Bahaa El Din]], [[Samir]] and [[Ahmed Raafat Zahran]]. Raafat Sadek Zahran was also one of the founders of [[Saudi Elevator Co.]] [[(Schindler Elevators)]]. Raafat Sadek Zahran was also the head of [[Zahran]] Family in [[Mansoura]]. Ahmed Raafat Zahran is an Egyptian [[consultant]] in the field of [[Human Resources]] [[Management]] and [[Training and development|Development]], as well as [[Organizational Development]]. [[Ahmed Raafat Zahran]] worked on several [[restructuring]] assignments for the benefits of the [[Egyptian Government]]: [[Information and Decision Support Centre]],  [[Foreign Trade Training Centre]], [[Capital Market Authority (Egypt)|Capital Market Authority]].  The branch of [[Huda Shaarawi]] in Down Town area and Shooting Club branch in [[Giza]] was found by [[Mostafa El-Shorbagi]].

There is only one branch still functioning in Cairo, which is the Nasser City branch.

===India===
Wimpy was one of the first fast-food restaurants to open in [[India]]'s [[Economic liberalisation in India|post-liberalised economy]]. With a run of initial success, Wimpy was often touted as the first icon of '[[westernization]]' in India. A few of the remaining restaurants still in business are in [[New Delhi]] - [[Connaught Place, New Delhi|Connaught Place]]

===Ireland===
Wimpy has been in Ireland on two occasions, in the 1960s and more recently in the early 2000s.

In the 2000s, petrol station chain operator [[Petrogas]] took on the master franchise for Ireland,&lt;ref name=&quot;caterersearch&quot;&gt;&quot;[http://www.caterersearch.com/Companies/33925/wimpy-international-ltd.html Information on Wimpy's Franchise]&quot;,''Caterer Search''. Retrieved on 29 January 2008.&lt;/ref&gt; and operated a large number of sites, but they have since ceased to operate these.&lt;ref&gt;http://asp-gb.secure-zone.net/v2/index.jsp?id=666/1326/2833&amp;lng=en&lt;/ref&gt; Most have been replaced by &quot;Grill'n'Fill&quot; own-branded areas selling virtually identical products, or [[Burger King]] which Petrogas are now are franchiser for.

===Japan===
Wimpy was the first overseas fast-food chain to open in Japan; the first branch opened in 1970 in Shinsaibashi, Osaka. In 1992 Wimpy formed a business partnership with Russell's Restaurant Inc. to open a new Russell's chain of hamburger restaurants, but the company withdrew from Japan in 1998.

===Kuwait===
Wimpy opened in Al-duiya in [[Kuwait]] in the 1970s. It is now only in [[Nuzha|Al-Nuzha]], Kuwait.

===New Zealand===
Wimpy had branches in [[New Zealand]] including [[Hamilton, New Zealand|Hamilton]], Paraparaumu and [[Taupo, New Zealand|Taupo]] but have now closed. One store remained in [[Rotorua]] but this was put up for sale in 2008 and has since closed.

===South Africa===
Wimpy opened in South Africa in [[Durban]] in 1967. The business was sold to Bakers SA Ltd in the late 1970s and later to the [[Famous Brands Limited]].

===Other countries===
In 1976, Wimpy opened their first restaurant in [[Bogotá]], Colombia. Branches trading as Wimpy in Germany preceded the U.S. based chains.  Other countries with Wimpy restaurants include Guatemala, Norway, Lithuania, Kuwait, Egypt, Cyprus, Saudi Arabia, United Arab Emirates, Kenya, [[Beirut]] Lebanon, India, Nepal, Pakistan, Bangladesh, Botswana, and Japan.

It is now owned by Famous Brands that recently completed a takeover of Wimpy within the UK. {{Clarify|date=March 2011}}

==In popular culture==

=== ''Tinker, Tailor, Soldier, Spy'' ===

In the 2011 film adapdation of the novel, some of the characters are seen eating in a Wimpy restaurant.

=== ''Bedazzled'' ===

The main character of the 1967 [[Peter Cook]] and [[Dudley Moore]] comedy film ''[[Bedazzled (1967 film)|Bedazzled]]'' works as a cook at a Wimpy bar.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Bedazzled|url=http://movies.zap2it.com/movies/bedazzled/3366|accessdate=21 August 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== ''Genesis'' ===
The song '' 'Dancing with the Moonlit Knight' '' from the album [[Selling England by the Pound]] features the lyrics ''Chewing through their Wimpy dreams, they eat without a sound. Digesting England by the pound.''

=== ''Jethro Tull'' ===
In the song '' 'Up to me' '' on the album [[Aqualung (Jethro Tull album)|Aqualung]] by Jethro Tull, ''leave you in a Wimpy bar'' is part of the lyrics.

=== ''Mr. Wimpy'' ===
[[File:Mr. Wimpy Coverart.png|thumb|right|120px|Mr. Wimpy computer game]]
During the 1980s, advertising for the Wimpy chain featured a cartoon character called Mr. Wimpy. He was almost entirely hidden under a large hat, and only a nose and a smile were visible. His physical appearance was a [[visual pun]], as his costume was the red dress uniform of the [[Yeomen Warders|Beefeaters at the Tower Of London]], playing on the beef-oriented nature of the chain's menu. In certain branches, a member of staff would dress up in a Mr. Wimpy costume for pre-arranged children's parties.

Mr. Wimpy also appeared in [[Mr. Wimpy|an official computer game]] by [[Ocean Software]], released in 1984 on the [[ZX Spectrum]], [[Commodore 64]] and other formats.

Although the Wimpy chain's name was originally inspired by [[J. Wellington Wimpy|the Wimpy cartoon character in Popeye]], the chain's own Mr. Wimpy bore no resemblance to Popeye's Wimpy.

==References==
{{Reflist}}

== External links ==
{{Commons category|Wimpy}}
* [http://www.wimpy.uk.com/ Wimpy UK]
* [http://www.wimpy.co.za/ Wimpy South Africa]

&lt;!--spacing--&gt;

{{UK Food}}
{{Restaurant chains in Ireland}}
{{Use dmy dates|date=March 2011}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Wimpy (Restaurant)}}
[[Category:3i Group companies]]
[[Category:Fast-food chains of Ireland]]
[[Category:Fast-food chains of the United Kingdom]]
[[Category:Fast-food hamburger restaurants]]

[[af:Wimpy]]
[[fr:Wimpy]]
[[sw:Wimpy (Mikahawa)]]
[[pl:Wimpy]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
