<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="1877499" ns="0" title="Gratis versus libre"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Redirect|Free as in freedom|the book|Free as in Freedom: Richard Stallman's Crusade for Free Software{{!}}''Free as in Freedom: Richard Stallman's Crusade for Free Software''}}
{{original research|date=March 2011}}
[[File:Free Beer.jpg|thumb||Free beer is ''gratis'', but might not be ''libre'' like [[free software]].]]
'''Gratis versus libre''' is the distinction between two meanings of the English [[adjective]] &quot;free&quot;; namely, &quot;for zero price&quot; (''gratis'') and &quot;with little or no restriction&quot; (''libre''). The ambiguity of &quot;free&quot; can cause issues where the distinction is important, as it often is in dealing with laws concerning the use of information, such as [[copyright]] and [[patents]].

The terms are largely used to categorise [[intellectual property]], particularly  [[computer program]]s, according to the [[license]]s and legal restrictions that cover them, in the [[free software community|free software and open source communities]], as well as the broader [[free culture movement]]. For example, they are used to distinguish [[freeware]] ([[software]] ''gratis'') from [[free software]] (software ''libre'').

[[Richard Stallman]] summarised the difference in a slogan: &quot;Think free as in free speech, not free beer.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |last=Lessig|first=Lawrence|url=http://www.wired.com/wired/archive/14.09/posts.html?pg=6|title=Free, as in beer|accessdate=2009-03-18 |date=September 2006 |publisher=[[Wired (magazine)|Wired]]}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== ''Gratis'' ==
{{Main|Gratis}}

'''Gratis''' in English is a [[colloquialism]] adopted from the various [[Romance languages|Romance]] and [[Germanic language|Germanic]] [[language]]s, ultimately descending from the plural [[ablative]] and [[dative]] form of the first-[[declension]] [[noun]] ''grātia'' in [[Latin]]. It means &quot;free of charge&quot;, &quot;at zero price&quot;, &quot;free&quot;, in the sense that some good or service is supplied without payment, even though it may have value.

== ''Libre'' {{Anchor|libre|Libre|liber|Liber}} ==
{{redirect|Libre}}
'''Libre''' ({{IPAc-en|icon|ˈ|l|iː|b|r|ə}}) in English is adopted from the various [[Romance languages]], ultimately descending from the [[Latin language|Latin]] word ''lībere''; its origin is closely related to ''liberty''. It denotes &quot;the state of being free&quot;, as in &quot;liberty&quot; or &quot;having freedom&quot;.&lt;!-- {{cn}}  --&gt; The ''[[Oxford English Dictionary]]'' (OED) considers ''libre'' to be obsolete,&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.oed.com/viewdictionaryentry/Entry/107929 OED.com], OED definition of ''libre'': &quot;Obs. Of the will: Free&quot;. Access to the OED is libre, but not gratis.&lt;/ref&gt; but the word has come back into limited&lt;ref name=numbers/&gt; use.&lt;!-- {{cn}}  --&gt; Unlike ''[[wiktionary:gratis|gratis]]'', ''[[wiktionary:libre|libre]]'' appears in few English dictionaries,&lt;ref name=numbers&gt;[http://www.onelook.com/ The Onelook dictionary website] finds about 5 monoglot English dictionaries including &quot;libre&quot;; about 30 include &quot;gratis&quot;&lt;/ref&gt; although there is no other English single-word adjective signifying &quot;liberty&quot; exclusively, without also meaning &quot;at no monetary cost&quot;.&lt;!-- {{cn}}  --&gt;

== &quot;Free beer&quot; vs &quot;free speech&quot; distinction {{Anchor|beer|Beer|Free as in free beer}} ==

In software development, where the cost of mass production is relatively small, it is common for developers to make software available at no cost. One of the early and basic forms of this model is called [[freeware]]. With freeware, software is licensed free of charge for regular use: the developer does not gain any monetary compensation.

With the advent of the [[free software]] movement, license schemes were created to give developers more freedom in terms of code sharing, commonly called [[Open source software|open source]] or [[free and open source software]] (called FLOSS, FOSS, or F/OSS). As the English adjective ''free'' does not distinguish between &quot;for zero price&quot; and &quot;liberty&quot;, the phrases &quot;free as in free beer&quot; (''gratis'', freeware) and &quot;free as in free speech&quot; (''libre'', free software) were adopted. Many in the free software movement feel strongly about the freedom to use the software, make modifications, etc., whether or not this freely usable software is to be exchanged for money. Therefore, this distinction became important.

{{quote|&quot;Free software is a matter of liberty, not price. To understand the concept, you should think of free as in free speech, not as in free beer.&quot; &lt;br&gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;—Richard Stallman&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.gnu.org/philosophy/free-sw.html Free software philosophy] at GNU.org&lt;/ref&gt;}}

These phrases have become common, along with ''gratis'' and ''libre'', in the software development and computer law fields for encapsulating this distinction.&lt;ref&gt;For example, the [[free software]] [http://www.gnu.org/philosophy/free-sw.html definition] clarifies the distinction in this way.&lt;/ref&gt; The distinction is similar to the distinction made in [[political science]] between [[negative liberty]] and [[positive liberty]]. Like &quot;free beer&quot;, positive liberty promises equal access by all without cost or regard to income, of a given good (assuming the good exists). Like &quot;free speech&quot;, negative liberty safeguards the right to use of something (in this case, speech) without regard to whether in each case there is a cost involved for this use (you still have free speech even though it costs money to open a newspaper).&lt;ref&gt;A quote from the Gnu free software definition was used in a section on positive and negative liberty by [[Guinevere Nell]] in ''Rediscovering Fire: Basic Economic Lessons From the Soviet Experiment'', Algora, 2010.&lt;/ref&gt;

== Generalizing the &quot;Gratis/Libre&quot; distinction to the Open Access movement ==

The original Gratis/Libre distinction concerns software (i.e., code), with which users can potentially do two kinds of things: ('''1''') ''access and use it'' and ('''2''') ''modify and [[Code reuse|re-use]] it''. &quot;Gratis&quot; pertains to being ''able'' to access and use the code, without a price-barrier, and &quot;Libre&quot; pertains to being ''allowed'' to modify and re-use the code, without a permission barrier. The target ''content'' of the [[Open access (publishing)|Open Access]] movement, however, is not software but published, [[Peer review|peer-reviewed]] research journal article texts. 

'''1. Code (text) accessibility and use.''' For published research articles, the case for making their text accessible free for all online (Gratis) is even stronger than it is for software code, because in the case of software, some developers may wish to give their code away for free, while others may wish to sell it, whereas in the case of published research article texts, ''all'' their authors, without exception, give them away for free: None seek or get royalties or fees from their sale.&lt;ref&gt;[[Stevan Harnad|Harnad, Stevan]] (2003) [http://eprints.ecs.soton.ac.uk/5944/1/resolution.html#1.1 For Whom the Gate Tolls] ''Journal of Postgraduate Medicine'' 49: 337-342&lt;/ref&gt; On the contrary, any access-denial to potential users means loss of potential research impact ([[Citation impact|downloads, citations]]) for the author's research—and researcher-authors' employment, salary, promotion and funding depends in part on the [[Scientometrics|uptake and impact]] of their research. So whereas not all programmers may want their software to be accessible Gratis, all researchers want their articles to be accessible Gratis.

'''2. Code (text) modifiability and re-use.''' For published research articles, the case for allowing text [[Code reuse|modification and re-use]] is much weaker than for software code, because, unlike software, the ''text'' of a research article is not intended for modification and re-use. (In contrast, the ''content'' of research articles is and always was intended for modification and re-use: that is how research progresses.) There are no copyright barriers to modifying, developing, building upon and re-using an author's ideas and findings, once they have been published, as long as the author and published source are credited—but modifications to the published text are another matter. Apart from verbatim [[quotation]], scholarly/scientific authors are not in general interested in allowing other authors to create &quot;[[Mashup (book)|Mashup]]s&quot; of their texts. Researcher-authors are all happy to make their texts available for [[Web harvesting|harvesting]] and [[Index (search engine)|indexing]] for [[Search engine technology|search]] as well as [[Data mining|data-mining]], but not for [[Code reuse|re-use]] in altered form (without the permission of the author). 

The formal [[analogy]], and the generalization of the Gratis/Libre distinction from [[Open software|Open Software]] to [[Open access (publishing)]], have been made.&lt;ref&gt;[[Peter Suber|Suber, Peter]] (2008) [http://www.earlham.edu/~peters/fos/newsletter/08-02-08.htm#gratis-libre Gratis and libre open access] ''SPARC Open Access Newsletter'', August 2, 2008&lt;/ref&gt; However, because of the substantive disanalogies regarding (1) and (2) noted above, the analogy needs to be treated with some caution.&lt;ref&gt;[[Stevan Harnad|Harnad, Stevan]] (2003) [http://listserver.sigmaxi.org/sc/wa.exe?A2=ind03&amp;L=american-scientist-open-access-forum&amp;F=l&amp;P=55522 On the Deep Disanalogy Between Text and Software and Between Text and Data Insofar as Free/Open Access is Concerned]. ''American Scientist Open Access Forum''. August 16, 2003&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[[Stevan Harnad|Harnad, Stevan]] (2010) [http://openaccess.eprints.org/index.php?/archives/691-On-Open-Access-Gratis-and-Libre.html On Open Access: &quot;Gratis&quot; and &quot;Libre&quot;]. ''Open Access Archivangelism'' 691, January 21, 2010&lt;/ref&gt;

==See also==
{{Portal|Free software}}
*[[Alternative terms for free software]]
*[[Free software community]]
*[[Libre knowledge]]
*[[List of FSF approved software licences]]
*[[Open-source license|List of open source licenses]]

==Footnotes==
{{Reflist}}

==References==
{{more footnotes|date=September 2010}}
{{Refbegin}}
*[http://freeasinspeechandbeer.com/ ''Free as in Speech and Beer''], book by Darren Wershler-Henry
*[http://communities.libre.org/philosophy/saylibre &quot;Say 'Libre{{' &quot;}}], and [http://www.wikieducator.org/Say_Libre related discussion] regarding knowledge and learning resources.
*[http://c2.com/cgi/wiki?FreeAsInBeer Stallman's discussion of FreeAsInBeer]
{{Refend}}

== External links ==
{{Wiktionary|libre}}
{{Wiktionary|gratis|free of charge}}
* [http://www.earlham.edu/~peters/fos/newsletter/08-02-08.htm#gratis-libre Gratis and libre open access].  An article by Peter Suber (August 2008) borrowing the gratis/libre distinction from the domain of software and applying it to the domain of peer-reviewed research articles.

{{FOSS}}
&lt;!-- The following interwikis are already linked on [[Gratis]]. --&gt;&lt;!--
[[ms:Percuma]]
--&gt;

&lt;!--[[nl:Gratis]] wrong iw--&gt;

[[Category:English phrases]]
[[Category:Free software culture and documents]]
[[Category:Libre]]

[[da:Gratis contra libre]]
[[fr:Gratuité (économie)]]
[[ms:Percuma]]
[[nl:Gratis versus libre]]
[[ja:無料]]
[[sv:Gratis]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
