<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="188378" ns="0" title="Phosphoric acid"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{About|orthophosphoric acid|other acids commonly called &quot;phosphoric acid&quot;|Phosphoric acids and phosphates}}
{{chembox
| Verifiedfields = changed
| verifiedrevid = 409759369
| ImageFile = Phosphoric-acid-2D-dimensions.png
| ImageSize = 180px 
| ImageName = Structural formula of phosphoric acid, showing dimensions
| ImageFile1 = Phosphoric-acid-3D-balls.png
| ImageSize1 = 150px 
| ImageName1 = Ball-and-stick model
| IUPACName = trihydroxidooxidophosphorus&lt;br/&gt;phosphoric acid
| OtherNames = Orthophosphoric acid
| Section1 = {{Chembox Identifiers
| PubChem = 1004
| UNII_Ref = {{fdacite|correct|FDA}}
| UNII = E4GA8884NN
| KEGG_Ref = {{keggcite|correct|kegg}}
| KEGG = D05467
| InChI = 1/H3O4P/c1-5(2,3)4/h(H3,1,2,3,4)
| InChIKey = NBIIXXVUZAFLBC-UHFFFAOYAI
| ChEBI_Ref = {{ebicite|changed|EBI}}
| ChEBI = 26078
| SMILES = OP(=O)(O)O
| ChEMBL_Ref = {{ebicite|correct|EBI}}
| ChEMBL = 1187
| StdInChI_Ref = {{stdinchicite|correct|chemspider}}
| StdInChI = 1S/H3O4P/c1-5(2,3)4/h(H3,1,2,3,4)
| StdInChIKey_Ref = {{stdinchicite|correct|chemspider}}
| StdInChIKey = NBIIXXVUZAFLBC-UHFFFAOYSA-N
| CASNo = 7664-38-2
| CASNo_Ref = {{cascite|correct|CAS}}
| CASOther = &lt;br/&gt;16271-20-8 (hemihydrate)
| ChemSpiderID_Ref = {{chemspidercite|correct|chemspider}}
| ChemSpiderID = 979
| EINECS = 231-633-2
| UNNumber = 1805
| RTECS = TB6300000
}}
| Section2 = {{Chembox Properties
| Formula = H&lt;sub&gt;3&lt;/sub&gt;PO&lt;sub&gt;4&lt;/sub&gt;
| MolarMass = 98.00 g/mol
| Appearance = white solid or colourless, viscous liquid (&gt;42 °C)
| Density = 1.885 g/mL (liquid)&lt;br/&gt;1.685 g/mL (85 % solution)&lt;br/&gt;2.030 g/mL (crystal at 25 °C)
| MeltingPt = 42.35 °C (anhydrous)&lt;br/&gt;29.32 °C (hemihydrate)
| BoilingPt = 158 °C (decomp)
| Solubility = 5.48 g/mL
| pKa = 2.148, 7.198, 12.375
| Viscosity = 2.4–9.4 [[Poise|cP]] (85% aq. soln.)&lt;br/&gt;147 [[Poise|cP]] (100 %)
}}
| Section7 = {{Chembox Hazards
| ExternalMSDS = [http://www.inchem.org/documents/icsc/icsc/eics1008.htm ICSC 1008]
| EUIndex = 015-011-00-6
| EUClass = Corrosive ('''C''')
| NFPA-H = 2
| NFPA-R = 0
| NFPA-F = 0
| NFPA-O = COR
| RPhrases = {{R34}}
| SPhrases = {{S1/2}} {{S26}} {{S45}}
| FlashPt = Non-flammable
}}
| Section8 = {{Chembox Related
| OtherFunctn = [[Hypophosphorous acid]]&lt;br/&gt;[[Phosphorous acid]]&lt;br/&gt;[[Pyrophosphoric acid]]&lt;br/&gt;[[Triphosphoric acid]]&lt;br/&gt;[[Perphosphoric acid]]&lt;br/&gt;[[Permonophosphoric acid]]
| Function = [[phosphorus]] [[oxoacid]]s
}}
}}

'''Phosphoric acid''', also known as '''orthophosphoric acid''' or '''phosphoric(V) acid''', is a [[mineral acid|mineral (inorganic) acid]] having the [[chemical formula]] [[Hydrogen|H]]&lt;sub&gt;3&lt;/sub&gt;[[Phosphorus|P]][[Oxygen|O]]&lt;sub&gt;4&lt;/sub&gt;. Orthophosphoric [[acid]] molecules can combine with themselves to form a variety of compounds which are also referred to as '''phosphoric acids''', but in a more general way. The term ''phosphoric acid'' can also refer to a [[chemical]] or [[reagent]] consisting of phosphoric acids, usually orthophosphoric acid.

==Orthophosphoric acid chemistry==
Pure [[anhydrous]] phosphoric acid is a white solid that melts at 42.35 °C to form a colorless, viscous liquid.

Most people and even chemists refer to orthophosphoric acid as ''phosphoric acid'', which is the IUPAC name for this compound. The prefix ''[[ortho]]'' is used to distinguish the acid from other phosphoric acids, called polyphosphoric acids two(ii). Orthophosphoric acid is a non-[[toxic]], [[inorganic]], rather weak triprotic [[acid]], which, when pure, is a [[solid]] at room [[temperature]] and [[pressure]]. The [[chemical structure]] of orthophosphoric acid is shown above in the data table. Orthophosphoric acid is a very [[Chemical polarity|polar]] [[molecule]]; therefore it is highly soluble in water. The [[oxidation state]] of [[phosphorus]] (P) in ortho- and other phosphoric acids is +5; the oxidation state of all the [[oxygen]] atoms (O) is −2 and all the [[hydrogen]] atoms (H) is +1. Triprotic means that an orthophosphoric acid molecule can dissociate up to three times, giving up an H&lt;sup&gt;+&lt;/sup&gt; each time, which typically combines with a [[Water (molecule)|water molecule]], H&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;O, as shown in these [[chemical reaction|reactions]]:

:H&lt;sub&gt;3&lt;/sub&gt;PO&lt;sub&gt;4&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;sub&gt;(s)&lt;/sub&gt; &amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;+ H&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;O&lt;sub&gt;(l)&lt;/sub&gt; {{eqm}} H&lt;sub&gt;3&lt;/sub&gt;O&lt;sup&gt;+&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;sub&gt;(aq)&lt;/sub&gt; + H&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;PO&lt;sub&gt;4&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;sup&gt;−&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;sub&gt;(aq)&lt;/sub&gt; &amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp; ''K''&lt;sub&gt;a1&lt;/sub&gt;= 7.25×10&lt;sup&gt;−3&lt;/sup&gt;

:H&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;PO&lt;sub&gt;4&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;sup&gt;−&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;sub&gt;(aq)&lt;/sub&gt;+ H&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;O&lt;sub&gt;(l)&lt;/sub&gt; {{eqm}} H&lt;sub&gt;3&lt;/sub&gt;O&lt;sup&gt;+&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;sub&gt;(aq)&lt;/sub&gt; + HPO&lt;sub&gt;4&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;sup&gt;2−&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;sub&gt;(aq)&lt;/sub&gt; &amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp; ''K''&lt;sub&gt;a2&lt;/sub&gt;= 6.31×10&lt;sup&gt;−8&lt;/sup&gt;

:HPO&lt;sub&gt;4&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;sup&gt;2−&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;sub&gt;(aq)&lt;/sub&gt;+ H&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;O&lt;sub&gt;(l)&lt;/sub&gt; {{eqm}} H&lt;sub&gt;3&lt;/sub&gt;O&lt;sup&gt;+&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;sub&gt;(aq)&lt;/sub&gt; + &amp;nbsp;PO&lt;sub&gt;4&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;sup&gt;3−&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;sub&gt;(aq)&lt;/sub&gt; &amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp; ''K''&lt;sub&gt;a3&lt;/sub&gt;= 3.98×10&lt;sup&gt;−13&lt;/sup&gt;

The [[anion]] after the first dissociation, H&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;PO&lt;sub&gt;4&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;sup&gt;−&lt;/sup&gt;, is the ''dihydrogen phosphate'' anion. The anion after the second dissociation, HPO&lt;sub&gt;4&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;sup&gt;2−&lt;/sup&gt;, is the ''hydrogen phosphate'' anion. The anion after the third dissociation, PO&lt;sub&gt;4&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;sup&gt;3−&lt;/sup&gt;, is the '''[[phosphate]]''' or '''orthophosphate''' anion. For each of the dissociation reactions shown above, there is a separate [[acid dissociation constant]], called ''K''&lt;sub&gt;a1&lt;/sub&gt;, ''K''&lt;sub&gt;a2&lt;/sub&gt;, and ''K''&lt;sub&gt;a3&lt;/sub&gt; given at 25 °C. Associated with these three dissociation constants are corresponding p''K''&lt;sub&gt;a1&lt;/sub&gt;=2.12 , p''K''&lt;sub&gt;a2&lt;/sub&gt;=7.21 , and p''K''&lt;sub&gt;a3&lt;/sub&gt;=12.67 values at 25 °C. Even though all three [[hydrogen]] (H) atoms are equivalent on an orthophosphoric acid molecule, the successive ''K''&lt;sub&gt;a&lt;/sub&gt; values differ since it is energetically less favorable to lose another H&lt;sup&gt;+&lt;/sup&gt; if one (or more) has already been lost and the molecule/ion is more negatively-charged.

Because the triprotic dissociation of orthophosphoric acid, the fact that its [[conjugate base]]s (the phosphates mentioned above) cover a wide [[pH]] range, and, because phosphoric acid/phosphate [[solution]]s are, in general, non-toxic, mixtures of these types of phosphates are often used as [[buffering agents]] or to make [[buffer solution]]s, where the desired pH depends on the proportions of the phosphates in the mixtures. Similarly, the non-toxic, [[anion]] [[salt]]s of triprotic [[organic compound|organic]] [[citric acid]] are also often used to make buffers. Phosphates are found pervasively in biology, especially in the compounds derived from phosphorylated [[sugar]]s, such as [[DNA]], [[RNA]], and [[adenosine triphosphate]] (ATP). There is a separate article on [[phosphate]] as an anion or its salts.

Upon heating orthophosphoric acid, condensation of the phosphoric units can be induced by driving off the water formed from condensation. When one molecule of water has been removed for each two molecules of phosphoric acid, the result is [[pyrophosphoric acid]] (H&lt;sub&gt;4&lt;/sub&gt;P&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;O&lt;sub&gt;7&lt;/sub&gt;). When an average of one molecule of water per phosphoric unit has been driven off, the resulting substance is a glassy solid having an empirical formula of '''HPO&lt;sub&gt;3&lt;/sub&gt;''' and is called '''metaphosphoric acid'''.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.bartleby.com/65/ph/phsphracid.html phosphoric acid. The Columbia Encyclopedia, Sixth Edition. 2001-05]&lt;/ref&gt; Metaphosphoric acid is a singly anhydrous version of orthophosphoic acid and is sometimes used as a water- or moisture-absorbing reagent. Further [[dehydration|dehydrating]] is very difficult, and can be accomplished only by means of an extremely strong [[desiccant]] (and not by heating alone). It produces ''[[phosphoric anhydride]]'', which has an empirical formula P&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;O&lt;sub&gt;5&lt;/sub&gt;, although an actual molecule has a chemical formula of P&lt;sub&gt;4&lt;/sub&gt;O&lt;sub&gt;10&lt;/sub&gt;. Phosphoric anhydride is a solid, which is very strongly moisture-absorbing and is used as a [[desiccant]].

===Composition and pH of a phosphoric acid aqueous solution===
For a given total acid concentration [A] = [H&lt;sub&gt;3&lt;/sub&gt;PO&lt;sub&gt;4&lt;/sub&gt;] + [H&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;PO&lt;sub&gt;4&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;sup&gt;−&lt;/sup&gt;] + [HPO&lt;sub&gt;4&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;sup&gt;2−&lt;/sup&gt;] + [PO&lt;sub&gt;4&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;sup&gt;3−&lt;/sup&gt;] ([A] is the total number of moles of pure H&lt;sub&gt;3&lt;/sub&gt;PO&lt;sub&gt;4&lt;/sub&gt; which have been used to prepare 1 liter of solution), the composition of an aqueous solution of phosphoric acid can be calculated using the equilibrium equations associated with the three reactions described above together with the [H&lt;sup&gt;+&lt;/sup&gt;][OH&lt;sup&gt;−&lt;/sup&gt;] = 10&lt;sup&gt;−14&lt;/sup&gt; relation and the electrical neutrality equation. Possible concentrations of polyphosphoric molecules and ions is neglected. The system may be reduced to a fifth degree equation for [H&lt;sup&gt;+&lt;/sup&gt;] which can be solved numerically, yielding:

{| border=&quot;1&quot; cellspacing=&quot;0&quot; cellpadding=&quot;4&quot; style=&quot;margin: 0 0 0 0.5em; background: {{{bgc|white}}}; border-collapse: collapse; border-color: {{{bc|#C0C090}}};&quot;
|-
|width=&quot;60&quot; align=&quot;center&quot; bgcolor=&quot;E0E0E0&quot;|'''[A] (mol/L)'''
|width=&quot;50&quot; align=&quot;center&quot; bgcolor=&quot;E0E0E0&quot;|'''pH'''
|width=&quot;110&quot; align=&quot;center&quot; bgcolor=&quot;E0E0E0&quot;|'''[H&lt;sub&gt;3&lt;/sub&gt;PO&lt;sub&gt;4&lt;/sub&gt;]/[A] (%)'''
|width=&quot;110&quot; align=&quot;center&quot; bgcolor=&quot;E0E0E0&quot;|'''[H&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;PO&lt;sub&gt;4&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;sup&gt;−&lt;/sup&gt;]/[A] (%)'''
|width=&quot;110&quot; align=&quot;center&quot; bgcolor=&quot;E0E0E0&quot;|'''[HPO&lt;sub&gt;4&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;sup&gt;2−&lt;/sup&gt;]/[A] (%)'''
|width=&quot;110&quot; align=&quot;center&quot; bgcolor=&quot;E0E0E0&quot;|'''[PO&lt;sub&gt;4&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;sup&gt;3−&lt;/sup&gt;]/[A] (%)'''
|-
|1||1.08||'''91.7'''||8.29||6.20×10&lt;sup&gt;−6&lt;/sup&gt;||1.60×10&lt;sup&gt;−17&lt;/sup&gt;
|-
|10&lt;sup&gt;−1&lt;/sup&gt;||1.62||'''76.1'''||23.9||6.20×10&lt;sup&gt;−5&lt;/sup&gt;||5.55×10&lt;sup&gt;−16&lt;/sup&gt;
|-
|10&lt;sup&gt;−2&lt;/sup&gt;||2.25||'''43.1'''||'''56.9'''||6.20×10&lt;sup&gt;−4&lt;/sup&gt;||2.33×10&lt;sup&gt;−14&lt;/sup&gt;
|-
|10&lt;sup&gt;−3&lt;/sup&gt;||3.05||10.6||'''89.3'''||6.20×10&lt;sup&gt;−3&lt;/sup&gt;||1.48×10&lt;sup&gt;−12&lt;/sup&gt;
|-
|10&lt;sup&gt;−4&lt;/sup&gt;||4.01||1.30||'''98.6'''||6.19×10&lt;sup&gt;−2&lt;/sup&gt;||1.34×10&lt;sup&gt;−10&lt;/sup&gt;
|-
|10&lt;sup&gt;−5&lt;/sup&gt;||5.00||0.133||'''99.3'''||0.612||1.30×10&lt;sup&gt;−8&lt;/sup&gt;
|-
|10&lt;sup&gt;−6&lt;/sup&gt;||5.97||1.34×10&lt;sup&gt;−2&lt;/sup&gt;||'''94.5'''||5.50||1.11×10&lt;sup&gt;−6&lt;/sup&gt;
|-
|10&lt;sup&gt;−7&lt;/sup&gt;||6.74||1.80×10&lt;sup&gt;−3&lt;/sup&gt;||'''74.5'''||25.5||3.02×10&lt;sup&gt;−5&lt;/sup&gt;
|-
|10&lt;sup&gt;−10&lt;/sup&gt;||7.00||8.24×10&lt;sup&gt;−4&lt;/sup&gt;||'''61.7'''||'''38.3'''||8.18×10&lt;sup&gt;−5&lt;/sup&gt;
|}

For large acid concentrations, the solution is mainly composed of H&lt;sub&gt;3&lt;/sub&gt;PO&lt;sub&gt;4&lt;/sub&gt;. For [A] = 10&lt;sup&gt;−2&lt;/sup&gt;, the pH is close to p''K''&lt;sub&gt;a1&lt;/sub&gt;, giving an equimolar mixture of H&lt;sub&gt;3&lt;/sub&gt;PO&lt;sub&gt;4&lt;/sub&gt; and H&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;PO&lt;sub&gt;4&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;sup&gt;−&lt;/sup&gt;. For [A] below 10&lt;sup&gt;−3&lt;/sup&gt;, the solution is mainly composed of H&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;PO&lt;sub&gt;4&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;sup&gt;−&lt;/sup&gt; with [HPO&lt;sub&gt;4&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;sup&gt;2−&lt;/sup&gt;] becoming non negligible for very dilute solutions. [PO&lt;sub&gt;4&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;sup&gt;3−&lt;/sup&gt;] is always negligible. Note that the above analysis does not take into account ion activity coefficients; as such, the pH and molarity of a real phosphoric acid solution may deviate substantially from the above values.

==Chemical reagent==
Pure 75–85% [[aqueous]] [[solution]]s (the most common) are clear, colourless, odourless, non-[[Volatility (chemistry)|volatile]], rather viscous, syrupy [[liquid]]s, but still pourable. Phosphoric acid is very commonly used as an [[aqueous]] solution of 85% phosphoric acid or H&lt;sub&gt;3&lt;/sub&gt;PO&lt;sub&gt;4&lt;/sub&gt;. Because it is a concentrated acid, an 85% solution can be [[corrosive]], although nontoxic when diluted. Because of the high percentage of phosphoric acid in this reagent, at least some of the orthophosphoric acid is condensed into polyphosphoric acids in a temperature-dependent [[chemical equilibrium|equilibrium]], but, for the sake of labeling and simplicity, the 85% represents H&lt;sub&gt;3&lt;/sub&gt;PO&lt;sub&gt;4&lt;/sub&gt; as if it were all orthophosphoric acid. Other percentages are possible too, even above 100%, where the phosphoric acids and water would be in an unspecified equilibrium, but the overall elemental [[mole (unit)|mole]] content would be considered specified. When aqueous solutions of phosphoric acid and/or phosphate are dilute, they are in or will reach an equilibrium after a while where practically all the phosphoric/phosphate units are in the ortho- form.

===Preparation of hydrogen halides===
Phosphoric acid reacts with halides to form the corresponding hydrogen halide gas (steamy fumes are observed on warming the reaction mixture). This is a common practice for the laboratory preparation of hydrogen halides.
:{|
| NaCl(s) || + H&lt;sub&gt;3&lt;/sub&gt;PO&lt;sub&gt;4&lt;/sub&gt;(l) → NaH&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;PO&lt;sub&gt;4&lt;/sub&gt;(s) || + HCl(g)
|-
| NaBr(s) || + H&lt;sub&gt;3&lt;/sub&gt;PO&lt;sub&gt;4&lt;/sub&gt;(l) → NaH&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;PO&lt;sub&gt;4&lt;/sub&gt;(s) || + HBr(g)
|-
| NaI(s) || + H&lt;sub&gt;3&lt;/sub&gt;PO&lt;sub&gt;4&lt;/sub&gt;(l) → NaH&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;PO&lt;sub&gt;4&lt;/sub&gt;(s) || + HI(g)
|}

===Rust removal===
Phosphoric acid may be used as a &quot;rust converter&quot;, by direct application to rusted iron, steel tools, or surfaces. The phosphoric acid converts reddish-brown [[iron(III) oxide]], Fe&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;O&lt;sub&gt;3&lt;/sub&gt; ([[rust]]) to black [[Iron(III) phosphate|ferric phosphate]], FePO&lt;sub&gt;4&lt;/sub&gt;.

&quot;Rust converter&quot; is sometimes a greenish liquid suitable for dipping (in the same sort of acid bath as is used for [[Pickling (metal)|pickling metal]]), but it is more often formulated as a [[gel]], commonly called '''naval jelly'''. It is sometimes sold under other names, such as &quot;rust remover&quot; or &quot;rust killer&quot;. As a thick gel, it may be applied to sloping, vertical, or even overhead surfaces. 

After treatment, the black ferric-phosphate coating can be scrubbed off, leaving a fresh metal surface. Multiple applications of phosphoric acid may be required to remove all rust. The black phosphate coating can also be left in place, where it will provide moderate further corrosion resistance  (such protection is also provided by the superficially similar [[Parkerize|Parkerizing]] and [[bluing (steel)|blued]] electrochemical [[conversion coating]] processes).

==Processed food use==
{{unreferenced section|date=October 2010}}
Food-grade phosphoric acid (additive [[E number|E338]]) is used to acidify foods and beverages such as various [[cola]]s, but not without controversy regarding its health effects. It provides a tangy or sour taste and, being a mass-produced chemical, is available cheaply and in large quantities. The low cost and bulk availability is unlike more expensive seasonings that give comparable flavors, such as [[citric acid]] which is obtainable from [[lemon]]s and [[Lime (fruit)|limes]]. However, most citric acid in the food industry is not extracted from citrus fruit, but fermented by ''[[Aspergillus niger]]'' mold from scrap [[molasses]], waste [[starch]] [[hydrolysis|hydrolysates]] and phosphoric acid.

===Biological effects on bone calcium and kidney health===
Phosphoric acid, used in many soft drinks (primarily [[cola]]), has been linked to lower bone density in epidemiological studies. For example, a study&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |author=Katherine L Tucker, Kyoko Morita, Ning Qiao, Marian T Hannan, L Adrienne Cupples and Douglas P Kiel |journal=Am. J Clin. Nut.|year=2006 |pmid=17023723 |volume=84 |issue=4 |pages=936–42 |title=Colas, but not other carbonated beverages, are associated with low bone mineral density in older women: The Framingham osteoporosis study}}&lt;/ref&gt; using dual-energy X-ray absorptiometry rather than a questionnaire about breakage, provides reasonable evidence to support the theory that drinking cola results in lower bone density. This study was published in the [[American Journal of Clinical Nutrition]]. A total of 1672 women and 1148 men were studied between 1996 and 2001. Dietary information was collected using a food frequency questionnaire that had specific questions about the number of servings of cola and other carbonated beverages and that also made a differentiation between regular, caffeine-free, and diet drinks. The paper cites significant statistical evidence to show that women who consume cola daily have lower bone density. Total phosphorus intake was not significantly higher in daily cola consumers than in nonconsumers; however, the calcium-to-phosphorus ratios were lower. 

On the other hand, another study suggests that insufficient intake of [[phosphorus]] leads to lower [[bone density]]. The study does not examine the effect of phosphoric acid, which binds with [[magnesium]] and [[calcium]] in the digestive tract to form salts that are not absorbed, but rather studies general phosphorus intake.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |author=S. Elmståhl, B. Gullberg, L. Janzon, O. Johnell and B. Elmståhl |title=Increased incidence of fractures in middle-aged and elderly men with low intakes of phosphorus and zinc |year=1998 |journal=Osteoporosis International |volume=8 |issue=4 |pages=333–340 |doi=10.1007/s001980050072 |pmid=10024903}}&lt;/ref&gt;

A clinical study by Heaney and Rafferty using calcium-balance methods found no impact of carbonated soft drinks containing phosphoric acid on calcium excretion.&lt;ref name=&quot;heaney&quot;&gt;{{cite journal |author=Heaney R.P. and Rafferty K. |title=Carbonated beverages and urinary calcium excretion |year=2001 |journal=Am. J. Clin. Nutr.|volume=74 |issue=3 |pages=343–347 |pmid=11522558}}&lt;/ref&gt; The study compared the impact of water, milk, and various soft drinks (two with caffeine and two without; two with phosphoric acid and two with citric acid) on the calcium balance of 20- to 40-year-old women who customarily consumed ~3 or more cups (680 mL) of a carbonated soft drink per day. They found that, relative to water, only milk and the two caffeine-containing soft drinks increased urinary calcium, and that the calcium loss associated with the caffeinated soft drink consumption was about equal to that previously found for caffeine alone. Phosphoric acid without caffeine had no impact on urine calcium, nor did it augment the urinary calcium loss related to caffeine. Because studies have shown that the effect of caffeine is compensated for by reduced calcium losses later in the day,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |author=Barger-Lux M.J., Heaney R.P. and Stegman M.R. |title=Effects of moderate caffeine intake on the calcium economy of premenopausal women [published erratum appears in Am. J. Clin. Nutr. 1991 Jan;'''53'''(1):182] |year=1990 |journal=[[Am. J. Clin. Nutr.]] |volume=52 |issue=4 |pages=722–725 |pmid=2403065}}&lt;/ref&gt; Heaney and Rafferty concluded that the net effect of carbonated beverages—including those with caffeine and phosphoric acid—is negligible, and that the skeletal effects of carbonated soft drink consumption are likely due primarily to milk displacement.

Other chemicals such as [[caffeine]] (also a significant component of popular common cola drinks) were also suspected as possible contributors to low bone density, due to the known effect of caffeine on [[calciuria]]. One other study, involving 30 women over the course of a week, suggests that phosphoric acid in colas has no such effect, and postulates that caffeine has only a temporary effect, which is later reversed. The authors of this study conclude that the skeletal effects of carbonated beverage consumption are likely due primarily to milk displacement&lt;ref name=&quot;heaney&quot;/&gt; (another possible [[confounding factor]] may be an association between high soft drink consumption and sedentary lifestyle). 

Cola consumption has also been associated with chronic kidney disease and [[kidney stones]] through medical research.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |author=Tina M. Saldana, Olga Basso, Rebecca Darden, and Dale P. Sandler |title=Carbonated beverages and chronic kidney disease |year=2007 |journal=[[Epidemiology (journal)|Epidemiology]] |volume=18 |issue=4 |pages=501–6 |doi=10.1097/EDE.0b013e3180646338 |pmid=17525693}}&lt;/ref&gt; The preliminary results suggest that cola consumption may increase the risk of chronic kidney disease.

==Medical use==
Phosphoric acid is used in [[dentistry]] and [[orthodontics]] as an [[etch]]ing solution, to clean and roughen the surfaces of teeth where dental appliances or fillings will be placed.
Phosphoric acid is also an ingredient in over-the-counter anti-nausea medications that also contain high levels of [[sugar]] ([[glucose]] and [[fructose]]). This acid is also used in many teeth whiteners to eliminate plaque that may be on the teeth before application.

==Preparation==
Phosphoric acid can be prepared by three routes – the thermal process, the wet process and the dry kiln process.

===Thermal phosphoric acid===


This very pure phosphoric acid is obtained by burning elemental [[phosphorus]] to produce [[phosphorus pentoxide]] and dissolving the product in dilute phosphoric acid. This produces a very pure phosphoric acid, since most impurities present in the rock have been removed when extracting phosphorus from the rock in a furnace. The end result is food-grade, thermal phosphoric acid; however, for critical applications, additional processing to remove arsenic compounds may be needed.

Elemental [[phosphorus]] is produced by an electric furnace. At a high temperature, a mixture of phosphate ore, silica and carbonaceous material  (coke, coal etc...) produces calcium silicate, phosphorus gas and carbon monoxide. The P and CO off-gases from this reaction are cooled under water to isolate solid phosphorus. Alternatively, the P and CO off-gases can be burned with air to produce [[phosphorus pentoxide]] and carbon dioxide.

===Wet phosphoric acid===
{{See also|Nitrophosphate process}}
Wet process phosphoric acid is prepared by adding [[sulfuric acid]] to [[tricalcium phosphate]] rock, typically found in nature as [[apatite]].

The reaction is:

:Ca&lt;sub&gt;5&lt;/sub&gt;(PO&lt;sub&gt;4&lt;/sub&gt;)&lt;sub&gt;3&lt;/sub&gt;X + 5 H&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;SO&lt;sub&gt;4&lt;/sub&gt; + 10 H&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;O → 3 H&lt;sub&gt;3&lt;/sub&gt;PO&lt;sub&gt;4&lt;/sub&gt; + 5 CaSO&lt;sub&gt;4&lt;/sub&gt;·2H&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;O + HX

:where X may include OH, F, Cl, and Br

The initial phosphoric acid solution may contain 23–33% P&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;O&lt;sub&gt;5&lt;/sub&gt;, but can be concentrated by the evaporation of water to produce ''commercial-'' or ''merchant-grade'' phosphoric acid, which contains about 54% [[P2O5|P&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;O&lt;sub&gt;5&lt;/sub&gt;]]. Further evaporation of water yields ''superphosphoric acid'' with a P&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;O&lt;sub&gt;5&lt;/sub&gt; concentration above 70%.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite patent |US |4721519}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://msds.simplot.com/datasheets/12002.pdf |title=Super Phosphoric Acid 0-68-0 Material Safety Data Sheet |publisher= J.R. Simplot Company |accessdate=4 May 2010 |date=May 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Digestion of the phosphate ore using sulfuric acid yields the insoluble [[calcium sulfate]] (gypsum), which is filtered and removed as [[phosphogypsum]]. Wet-process acid can be further purified by removing fluorine to produce animal-grade phosphoric acid, or by solvent extraction and arsenic removal to produce food-grade phosphoric acid.

==Other applications==
* Phosphoric acid is used as an external standard for [[phosphorus]]-31 [[Nuclear magnetic resonance]] (NMR).
* Phosphoric acid is used for [[high-performance liquid chromatography]]. 
* Phosphoric acid is used as a chemical oxidizing agent for [[activated carbon]] production, as used in the Wentworth Process.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|author = C. Toles, S. Rimmera and J. C. Hower|title = Production of activated carbons from a Washington lignite using phosphoric acid activation|journal = [[Carbon (journal)|Carbon]]|year = 1996|volume = 34|issue = 11|pages = 1419–1426|doi = 10.1016/S0008-6223(96)00093-0}}&lt;/ref&gt;

* Phosphoric acid is used as the [[electrolyte]] in [[phosphoric acid fuel cell]]s. 
* Phosphoric acid is used with distilled water (2–3 drops per gallon) as an electrolyte in oxyhydrogen (HHO) generators.
* Phosphoric acid is used as an [[electrolyte]] in [[copper]] [[electropolishing]] for burr removal and circuit board planarization.

* Phosphoric acid is used as a [[flux (metallurgy)|flux]] by hobbyists (such as model railroaders) as an aid to [[soldering]].
* In [[compound semiconductor]] processing, phosphoric acid is a common wet etching agent: for example, in combination with hydrogen peroxide and water it is used to etch [[Indium gallium arsenide|InGaAs]] selective to [[indium phosphide|InP]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://terpconnect.umd.edu/~browns/wetetch.html Wet chemical etching.]&lt;/ref&gt;
* Hot phosphoric acid is used in [[microfabrication]] to etch [[silicon nitride]] (Si&lt;sub&gt;3&lt;/sub&gt;N&lt;sub&gt;4&lt;/sub&gt;). It is highly selective in etching Si&lt;sub&gt;3&lt;/sub&gt;N&lt;sub&gt;4&lt;/sub&gt; instead of SiO&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;, [[silicon dioxide]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Wolf&quot;&gt;{{cite book |title =Silicon processing for the VLSI era: Volume 1 - Process technology |last = Wolf |first = S. |coauthors = R.N. Tauber |year=1986 |pages=534 |isbn=0961672161}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* Phosphoric acid is used as a cleaner by [[construction]] trades to remove mineral deposits, cementitious smears, and hard water stains. 
* Phosphoric acid is also used as a [[chelation|chelant]] in some household cleaners aimed at similar cleaning tasks.

* Phosphoric acid is also used in [[hydroponics]] pH solutions to lower the pH of nutrient solutions. While other types of acids can be used, phosphorus is a nutrient used by plants, especially during flowering, making phosphoric acid particularly desirable.
* Phosphoric acid is used as a pH adjuster in cosmetics and skin-care products.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|publisher = Paula's Choice|title = Ingredient dictionary: P|work = Cosmetic ingredient dictionary|accessdate = 2007-11-16|url = http://www.cosmeticscop.com/learn/cosmetic_dictionary.asp?id=21&amp;letter=P}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* Phosphoric acid can be used as a dispersing agent in detergents and leather treatment.
* Phosphoric acid can be used as an additive to stabilize acidic aqueous solutions within a wanted and specified pH range
* Phosphoric acid is the ingredient that provides acidity to [[Coca-Cola]] and [[Pepsi]] sodas.

==See also==
* Phosphate [[fertilizer]]s, such as [[ammonium phosphate]] fertilizers

==References==
{{reflist|2}}

==External links==
{{Commons category|phosphoric acid}}
*[http://www.inchem.org/documents/icsc/icsc/eics1008.htm International chemical safety card 1008]
* [http://www.npi.gov.au/database/substance-info/profiles/71.html National pollutant inventory – Phosphoric acid fact sheet]
* [http://www.cdc.gov/niosh/npg/npgd0506.html NIOSH Pocket guide to chemical hazards]
* [http://www2.iq.usp.br/docente/gutz/Curtipot_.html Excel spreadsheet containing phosphoric acid titration curve, distribution diagram and buffer pH calculation]

{{Hydrogen compounds}}

{{Use dmy dates|date=October 2010}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Phosphoric Acid}}
[[Category:Mineral acids]]
[[Category:Flavors]]
[[Category:Food acidity regulators]]
[[Category:Food antioxidants]]
[[Category:Glassforming liquids and melts]]
[[Category:Phosphates]]
[[Category:Phosphorus oxoacids]]
[[Category:Hydrogen compounds]]

[[ar:حمض الفوسفوريك]]
[[bs:Fosfatna kiselina]]
[[bg:Фосфорна киселина]]
[[ca:Àcid fosfòric]]
[[cs:Kyselina fosforečná]]
[[cy:Asid ffosfforig]]
[[da:Fosforsyre]]
[[de:Phosphorsäure]]
[[el:Φωσφορικό οξύ]]
[[es:Ácido fosfórico]]
[[fa:فسفریک اسید]]
[[fr:Acide phosphorique]]
[[ko:인산]]
[[hi:फोस्फोरिक अम्ल]]
[[it:Acido fosforico]]
[[he:חומצה זרחתית]]
[[la:Acidum phosphoricum]]
[[lv:Ortofosforskābe]]
[[lt:Fosforo rūgštis]]
[[hu:Foszforsav]]
[[mk:Фосфорна киселина]]
[[ms:Asid fosforik]]
[[nl:Fosforzuur]]
[[ja:リン酸]]
[[no:Fosforsyre]]
[[oc:Acid fosforic]]
[[pl:Kwas fosforowy]]
[[pt:Ácido fosfórico]]
[[ro:Acid fosforic]]
[[ru:Ортофосфорная кислота]]
[[simple:Phosphoric acid]]
[[sk:Kyselina trihydrogenfosforečná]]
[[sl:Fosforna kislina]]
[[sr:Фосфорна киселина]]
[[fi:Fosforihappo]]
[[sv:Fosforsyra]]
[[ta:பாசுபாரிக் காடி]]
[[th:กรดฟอสฟอริก]]
[[uk:Ортофосфорна кислота]]
[[vi:Axít phốtphoric]]
[[zh:磷酸]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
