<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="18853459" ns="0" title="Characters of Crash Bandicoot"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">This is a list of '''characters''' from the '''Crash Bandicoot''' video game. [[Crash Bandicoot (series)|Crash Bandicoot]] is a series of [[Platform game|platform video games]] published by [[Activision]]. The series was formerly developed by [[Naughty Dog]] from 1996 to 1999, and by [[Traveller's Tales]], [[Eurocom]] and [[Vicarious Visions]] from 2000 to 2004. The series features a large cast of distinctively quirky characters designed by numerous different artists, the most notable of which include Charles Zembillas and Joe Pearson. In addition, it features an all-star cast of veteran voice actors.

The series centers around the conflicts between a mutated bandicoot named Crash Bandicoot and his creator, Doctor Neo Cortex. Crash acts as the main playable character of the series, though other characters have had occasional player access, most notable Coco Bandicoot and Doctor Neo Cortex. Out of the numerous characters in the series (numbering over sixty), only a few have significantly contributed to the story of the series.

==Main protagonists==
===Crash Bandicoot===
{{main|Crash Bandicoot (character)}}

===Aku Aku===
{{redirect|Aku Aku|the book by Thor Heyerdahl|Aku-Aku}}
'''Aku Aku''' is the guardian of the Wumpa Islands and the father figure of Crash and his friends. He is voiced by [[Mel Winkler]] in his English speaking appearances up to ''Crash Twinsanity'', and by [[Greg Eagles]] in ''Crash of the Titans'' and ''Crash: Mind over Mutant''. He is voiced by [[Kenichi Ogata (voice actor)|Kenichi Ogata]] in the Japanese versions of his speaking appearances up to ''Crash Twinsanity''.

Aku Aku is the spirit of an ancient [[witch doctor]] encased in a floating, wooden mask.&lt;ref name=&quot;Crash1ManualAku&quot;&gt;{{cite book |title=''Crash Bandicoot'' Instruction Booklet |year=1996 |publisher=[[Sony Computer Entertainment]] |pages=22}}&lt;/ref&gt; When he sensed Crash's mission to stop Doctor Cortex, he scattered copies of himself throughout the Wumpa Islands in an effort to aid him in his mission.&lt;ref name=&quot;Crash1ManualAku&quot;/&gt; Whenever Crash possesses an Aku Aku mask, he will be shielded from one enemy attack or contact. Collecting three Aku Aku masks gives Crash temporary invulnerability from all minor dangers.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |title=''Crash Bandicoot'' Instruction Booklet |year=1996 |publisher=[[Sony Computer Entertainment]] |pages=9}}&lt;/ref&gt; In ''[[Crash Bandicoot 3: Warped]]'', Aku Aku's evil younger brother Uka Uka is introduced when the ruins of Cortex's space station crash into Earth and set Uka Uka free. Aku Aku tells Crash and Coco the story of how he locked Uka Uka up in an underground prison many eons ago.&lt;ref name=&quot;UndergroundPrison&quot;&gt;{{cite video game |title=Crash Bandicoot 3: Warped |developer=Naughty Dog |publisher=Sony Computer Entertainment |date=November 3, 1998 |platform=PlayStation |level=Opening sequence |quote='''Aku Aku:''' After many eons, my evil twin Uka Uka has been freed from his underground prison. Long ago, I locked him there to protect the world from his malice.}}&lt;/ref&gt; He then gives the two the assignment of gathering Crystals that lay scattered throughout time and keep them from the hands of Uka Uka and Doctor Cortex.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite video game |title=Crash Bandicoot 3: Warped |developer=Naughty Dog |publisher=Sony Computer Entertainment |date=November 3, 1998 |platform=PlayStation  |level=Opening sequence |quote='''Aku Aku:''' Children, Uka Uka and Cortex plan on using this Time-Twisting Machine to gather Crystals that lay scattered across time. I have brought you here to gather the Crystals before they do so.}}&lt;/ref&gt; During Crash's final fight against Doctor Neo Cortex, Aku Aku fends off Uka Uka's attacks while the fight is in session. Aku Aku appears in ''Crash Team Racing'' as a tutor for the characters Crash, Coco, Polar and Pura, giving them useful tips and tricks throughout the game. He also appears as a power-up during the races, protecting the said characters from all attacks and obstacles while giving them a speed boost.&lt;ref name=&quot;MaskTeamRacing&quot;&gt;{{cite book |title=''Crash Team Racing'' Instruction Booklet |year=1999 |publisher=[[Sony Computer Entertainment]] |pages=22}}&lt;/ref&gt; However, he cannot protect the characters from chasms and deep water.&lt;ref name=&quot;MaskTeamRacing&quot;/&gt; In ''Crash Bash'', in order to resolve his constant fighting with Uka Uka, Aku Aku summons Crash and Coco as part of a contest between his players against Uka Uka, Aku Aku is later allowed to have Tiny and Dingodile into his team as to even out the number of players between them. During the course of the tournament, Aku Aku begins to suspect that Uka Uka is using the tournament to disguise a secret plot of his own. He discovers this plot to steal Crystals just in time for his team to win. Aku Aku locks the Crystals up into a secret cabinet for safekeeping, and banishes Uka Uka into the vacuum of space as punishment for trying to abuse the power of the Crystals.

When disasters ravage the world in ''Crash Bandicoot: The Wrath of Cortex'', Aku Aku discovers that Uka Uka and Doctor Cortex have unleashed a group of destructive masks known as the Elementals, and calls upon Crash and Coco Bandicoot to gather Crystals and return the Elementals to their hibernation state. In ''Crash Bandicoot 2: N-Tranced'', Aku Aku saves Crash from being kidnapped by Nefarious Tropy and N. Trance, and sends him off to gather Crystals so that he may be able to reach the villains. Aku Aku reprises his role from ''Crash Team Racing'' in ''Crash Nitro Kart'', giving useful advice and acting as a power-up for the characters Crash, Coco and Crunch. In ''Crash Twinsanity'', Aku Aku convinces Uka Uka to join him in order to defeat the Evil Twins, but both are easily defeated when they attempt this.

Aku Aku has a cameo appearance in ''Crash Tag Team Racing'' as the tiki masks in the &quot;Tiki Turbo&quot; track. He also appears as the tutor in ''Crash Boom Bang!'', giving the player instructions on how to play the game. In ''Crash of the Titans'', Aku Aku is captured by Doctor Neo Cortex, but is rescued by Crash Bandicoot. Throughout the game, Aku Aku gives the player basic instructions, shields Crash from enemy attacks, and transforms into a skateboard to help Crash traverse slippery terrain. He reprises this role for ''Crash: Mind over Mutant''. Aku Aku is one of the only two characters in the game unable to be controlled by Cortex's NV device, as the device is too small to fit on his head.
&lt;br clear=&quot;all&quot; /&gt;

====Reception====
A reviewer for [[Game Revolution]] compared the mechanics of the Aku Aku masks to the shields of the ''[[Sonic the Hedgehog (series)|Sonic the Hedgehog]]'' series.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |title=''Crash Bandicoot'' review for the PS |url=http://www.gamerevolution.com/review/sony/crash_bandicoot |publisher=[[Game Revolution]] |date=June 4, 2004 |accessdate=June 3, 2009 |quote=There is only one type of powerup, an old Maori mask that protects you much the way the shield does in Sonic the Hedgehog, but it works well enough for the game.}}&lt;/ref&gt; John Scalzo of [[Gaming Target]] commented that the &quot;booooo-ahhhhhh!&quot; chant made by Aku Aku is &quot;pretty slick&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |author=John Scalzo |title=''Crash Bandicoot'' PSOne Review @ Gaming Target |url=http://www.gamingtarget.com/article.php?artid=1018&amp;gameid=16 | publisher=[[Gaming Target]] |date=August 16, 2002 |accessdate=June 3, 2009 |quote=It's almost a shame the sound never rises above generic platform effects. Although the booooo-ahhhhhh! tiki mask effect is pretty slick.}}&lt;/ref&gt; The sound quality of Aku Aku's voice in ''Crash Team Racing'' was praised by SolidSnake of PSX Extreme,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |author=SolidSnake |title=PlayStation Game Reviews: ''Crash Team Racing'' |url=http://www.psxextreme.com/ps1-reviews/9.html |publisher=[[PSX Extreme]] |date=November 5, 1999 |accessdate=June 3, 2009 |quote=When Aku-Aku speaks to you, the quality of speech is very very good, never any break up and the sound always stays crisp and clear.}}&lt;/ref&gt; while Arnold Katayev, in his review of ''Crash Bandicoot: The Wrath of Cortex'', negatively described Aku Aku's voice as &quot;melodramatic&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |author=Arnold Katayev |title=PS2 Game Reviews: ''Crash Bandicoot: The Wrath of Cortex'' |url=http://www.psxextreme.com/ps2-reviews/98.html |publisher=[[PSX Extreme]] |date=November 11, 2001 |accessdate=June 3, 2009 |quote=Although, at times it seems like Aku-Aku's voice-actor just doesn't sound right. It's rather melodramatic, if you will.}}&lt;/ref&gt; Steven Rodriguez, in his [[Nintendo World Report]] review of ''Crash Nitro Kart'', described Aku Aku's voice when giving advice between races as &quot;sexy&quot; and cited it as the best part of the game's audio, but admitted that &quot;even he gets rather annoying.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;NWRNGC&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.nintendoworldreport.com/forums/?catid=7&amp;threadid=7308 |title=''Crash Nitro Kart'' Review |accessdate=January 24, 2010 |author=Steven Rodriguez |date=December 14, 2003 |publisher=[[Nintendo World Report]] |quote=The best part about the game's audio is that sexy talking mask that gives you advice between races, but even he gets rather annoying.}}&lt;/ref&gt; In his review of ''Crash of the Titans'', Brian Rowe of Game Revolution, while citing the ability to &quot;slap Aku Aku’s face into the ground and ride it like a surfboard&quot; as &quot;harshly inconsiderate&quot;, considered it &quot;payback for his gratingly poor impersonations of that other floating head of wisdom – [[Aqua Teen Hunger Force|Frylock]].&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |author=Brian Rowe |title=''Crash of the Titans'' review for the XBOX360 |url=http://www.gamerevolution.com/review/xbox360/crash_of_the_titans | publisher=[[Game Revolution]] |date=January 21, 2008 |accessdate=June 3, 2009 |quote=By the fourth level, Crash can slap Aku Aku’s face into the ground and ride it like a surfboard. It seemed harshly inconsiderate, but I considered it payback for his gratingly poor impersonations of that other floating head of wisdom – Frylock.}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Coco Bandicoot===
{{summarize-section}}
Coco's inclusion as a playable character in ''Crash Bandicoot: The Wrath of Cortex'' was met with a generally lukewarm response among critics. Hilary Goldstein of [[IGN]] felt that Coco was a &quot;less powerful&quot; and &quot;less enjoyable&quot; character than Crash and that &quot;she was just not fun the way Crash is&quot;. On the subject, Hilary added that &quot;Crash is a silly creature to look at. He's almost absurd, which works great with his various animations. Coco isn't really silly at all. The game isn't called ''Crash and Coco'' so why must I be forced to play her? Rather than add variety, Coco detracts from the only real selling point of the game -- Crash Bandicoot.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://xbox.ign.com/articles/358/358095p1.html |title=IGN: ''Crash Bandicoot: The Wrath of Cortex'' Review |accessdate=March 22, 2009 |author=Hilary Goldstein |date=April 26, 2002 |work= |publisher=[[IGN]] |quote=Crash isn't alone in fighting the forces of evil. He's assisted by Coco, a less powerful and less enjoyable playable character. Coco pops into specific levels and must be used to pass that area. She's just not fun the way crash is. Crash is a silly creature to look at. He's almost absurd, which works great with his various animations. Coco isn't really silly at all. The game isn't called ''Crash and Coco'' so why must I be forced to play her? Rather than add variety, Coco detracts from the only real selling point of the game -- Crash Bandicoot.}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Before the events of the series, Coco was an ordinary bandicoot until she was taken from the jungle and genetically enhanced by Doctor Neo Cortex.&lt;ref name=&quot;WrathProfile&quot;/&gt; Coco is first seen in ''Crash Bandicoot 2: Cortex Strikes Back'' living on N. Sanity Island with Crash. One day, when the battery for her laptop runs out, she sends Crash off to find a replacement battery for her.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite video game|title=Crash Bandicoot 2: Cortex Strikes Back |developer=Naughty Dog |publisher=Sony Computer Entertainment |date=October 31, 1997 |platform=PlayStation |level=Opening sequence |quote='''Coco Bandicoot:''' Crash, my battery's fried. Make yourself useful, big brother, and go get an extra battery for me.}}&lt;/ref&gt; When Coco discovers that Crash is gathering Crystals for Cortex, she becomes suspicious of Cortex and decides to hack into Cortex's computer and see what he's really up to. What she finds are detailed schematics for an improved Cortex Vortex and a suspicious-looking space station.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite video game|title=Crash Bandicoot 2: Cortex Strikes Back |developer=Naughty Dog |publisher=Sony Computer Entertainment |date=1997-10-31 |platform=PlayStation |version= |level=Third Warp Room  |isolang= |quote='''Coco Bandicoot:''' Crash, thank goodness. I've hacked into Cortex's computer and found detailed schematics for an improved Cortex Vortex and a suspicious looking space station. I'm not sure, but Cortex might be trying to...}}&lt;/ref&gt; She learns of Cortex's real plan just as Crash has gathered all the Crystals, and reveals Cortex's intentions to Crash before he can give the Crystals to Cortex.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite video game|title=Crash Bandicoot 2: Cortex Strikes Back |developer=Naughty Dog |publisher=Sony Computer Entertainment |date=1997-10-31 |platform=PlayStation |version= |level=Fifth Warp Room  |isolang= |quote='''Coco Bandicoot:''' Crash, Cortex isn't going to use the Crystals to contain the planet's energy! He's going to harness the force and use it to power the Super Cortex Vortex he has built on his space station! One blast of the ray will cover the entire world, turning everyone into Cortex's mindless slaves! Crash, don't let him have those Crystals!}}&lt;/ref&gt; After Cortex's plan is foiled, Coco is called upon by [[Characters of Crash Bandicoot#Aku Aku|Aku Aku]] in ''[[Crash Bandicoot 3: Warped]]'' to use [[Characters of Crash Bandicoot#Doctor Nefarious Tropy|Doctor Nefarious Tropy]]'s Time-Twisting Machine and gather the powerful Crystals in their original places before Cortex does so. Coco helps by gathering the Crystals in 17th century [[China]], the 18th century [[Pacific Ocean]], and [[World War I]] [[Europe]]. She is also responsible for the defeat of Cortex's right-hand man [[Characters of Crash Bandicoot#Doctor N. Gin|Doctor N. Gin]] on the Moon, with her new pet tiger [[Characters of Crash Bandicoot#Pura|Pura]] assisting her.

When the Elementals wreak havoc on the Earth in ''Crash Bandicoot: The Wrath of Cortex'', Coco activates a new Portal Chamber for Crash to use. She helps Crash gather the Power Crystals needed to stop the Elementals by collecting them in a tsunami-ravaged China and an avalanche zone. She also stops an armada of Cortex's space stations from striking Earth. Near the end, she helps Crash and [[Characters of Crash Bandicoot#Crunch Bandicoot|Crunch]] escape from Cortex's malfunctioning space station. In ''Crash Twinsanity'', Coco is ambushed by Doctor Neo Cortex, who disguises himself as her in order to lure Crash into a trap. Many moments later, Coco believes that Cortex kidnapped Crash, and travels to the Iceberg Lab to confront him. With a swift kick, she attacks Cortex and sends the Power Crystals he was holding flying into the Psychetron. The resulting chain reaction leaves Coco paralyzed until the end of the game.

In ''Crash of the Titans'', Coco is on the verge of creating a device that will be able to [[Recycling|recycle]] [[butter]] when she is captured along with Aku Aku by Doctor Neo Cortex. When Nina replaces Cortex, Coco is brainwashed and is forced to finish the Doominator. She ends up completing the Doominator, but is rescued by Crash and is able to stop it at the end of the game. In the Nintendo DS version of the game, she appears as a vendor selling upgrades for Crash's abilities. Coco is a playable character in the cooperation mode of the Wii and Xbox 360 versions of ''Crash: Mind over Mutant''. At the beginning of the game, Coco converts the Doominator's eye into an entertainment system.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite video game|title=Crash: Mind over Mutant |developer=Radical Entertainment |publisher=Activision |date=2008-10-07 |platform=Multiplatform |level=Worst Contact |quote='''Coco Bandicoot:''' If I get this Doominator eye working, we'll have the best entertainment system of all time!}}&lt;/ref&gt; After seeing an infomercial advertising the &quot;NV&quot;, a do-anything personal digital assistant, she receives an NV along with Crunch and quickly becomes addicted. Soon enough, the NV, which Dr. N. Brio filled with negative Mojo, transforms her into a ferocious beast who tries to kill Crash using a giant basketball-launching machine. After being defeated and informed (to her disappointment) that the NV had a negative influence on her,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite video game|title=Crash: Mind over Mutant |developer=Radical Entertainment |publisher=Activision |date=2008-10-07 |platform=Multiplatform |version= |level=Klepto-Brainiac |isolang= |quote='''Aku Aku:''' The NV loaded you up with some sort of dark Mojo. I could feel my brother's influence pervading you. / '''Coco Bandicoot:''' Ohh, but it was so cool! Are you sure it wasn't nefarious? / '''Aku Aku:''' Oh, yeah. You practically grew horns. / '''Coco Bandicoot:''' Oh, fudge! Well, now I'm mad! The best gizmo in ages is evil!}}&lt;/ref&gt; she uses the Doominator's eye to access Cortex's blog and learn what Cortex is planning.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite video game|title=Crash: Mind over Mutant |developer=Radical Entertainment |publisher=Activision |date=2008-10-07 |platform=Multiplatform |version= |level=Klepto-Brainiac |isolang= |quote='''Coco Bandicoot:''' I'll use the eye to hack into the villain's network. Just gimme a sec. I think I've got something. There's a video posted in Cortex's blog. / '''Aku Aku:''' Cortex has a blog? / '''Coco Bandicoot:''' Oh yeah. All the cool kids do it now. Well, they did two years ago, anyway.}}&lt;/ref&gt; She is accessible as the second player's character from that point on.

Coco is a playable character in ''Crash Team Racing'' and ''Crash Bash''. The epilogue of ''Crash Team Racing'' states that Coco opened up her own Internet dating service after the events of the game.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite video game |title=Crash Team Racing |developer=Naughty Dog |publisher=Sony Computer Entertainment |platform=PlayStation |level=Epilogue  |quote='''Text:''' Coco went on to start her own Internet dating service. Although her company is still in the red, the share prices are going through the roof!}}&lt;/ref&gt; In ''[[Crash Bandicoot: The Huge Adventure]]'', Coco builds a device that reverses the effects of Cortex's Planetary Minimizer. In ''[[Crash Bandicoot 2: N-Tranced]]'', Coco is abducted by N. Trance and is brainwashed alongside Crunch and Fake Crash. Coco battles Crash in a large battleship inside an active volcano, with Crash attacking the craft while it is reloading its weaponry. Upon snapping out of N. Trance's control, Coco becomes a playable character, gathering two Crystals in space while escaping the wrath of a fireball created by N. Tropy. Coco is a playable character in ''Crash Nitro Kart'' as well. In one cutscene, she uses her hacking skills to put the hyperactive [[Characters of Crash Bandicoot#Nash|Nash]] to sleep. In ''[[Crash Bandicoot Purple: Ripto's Rampage]]'', Coco teams up with the Professor to track down Ripto and Doctor Cortex. Later in the game, they're both kidnapped by Doctor Cortex's niece, [[Characters of Crash Bandicoot#Nina Cortex|Nina Cortex]], who keeps them locked up in cages. After being freed from her cage, Coco suggests that Crash and Spyro put a tracer on Cortex and Ripto as to allow the heroes to track the villains back to their hideout.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite video game|title=Crash Bandicoot Purple: Ripto's Rampage |developer=Vicarious Visions |publisher=Vivendi Universal Games |date=2004-06-03 |platform=Game Boy Advance |version= |level=After the battle against Nina Cortex |isolang= |quote='''Coco Bandicoot:''' If we can lure the two of them out, maybe we can put a tracer on them and follow them back to their base. Then we can stop them for good!}}&lt;/ref&gt; Coco's last major contribution to the story is constructing a portal to Cortex's and Ripto's lair. Coco is a playable character in ''Crash Tag Team Racing''. In the game's story, Coco discovers the sole clue to whoever stole MotorWorld's Power Gems, which is Wumpa Whip.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite video game |title=Crash Tag Team Racing |developer=Radical Entertainment |publisher=Sierra Entertainment |date=2005-10-19 |platform=Multiplatform |version= |level=Midway  |isolang= |quote='''Coco Bandicoot:''' Well, the pattern I've concluded from deductive reasoning is that whoever stole the Power Gems has some connection to... Wumpa Whip!}}&lt;/ref&gt; Because of Crash's high consumption of the beverage, she briefly believes (along with the others) that Crash is the culprit, despite the fact that Willie Wumpa Cheeks is the park's lone source of Wumpa Whip. At the end of the game, Coco returns the park's deed to Von Clutch, to whom it belongs.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite video game |title=Crash Tag Team Racing |developer=Radical Entertainment |publisher=Sierra Entertainment |date=2005-10-19 |platform=Multiplatform |version= |level=I Hate Chicken  |isolang= |quote='''Coco Bandicoot:''' This is really cool and stuff, but we'd like to return the park ownership to where it belongs: to Ebenezer Von Clutch.}}&lt;/ref&gt; Coco plays a central role in ''Crash Boom Bang!'', in which she is invited by the Viscount to the World Cannonball Race in his search for the Super Big Power Crystal.

Coco's availability as a playable character in ''[[Crash: Mind over Mutant]]'' was omitted from the PlayStation 2 version of the game due to her distinct animations taking up much of the console's memory.&lt;ref name=&quot;Gamershell&quot;&gt;{{cite web |publisher=Gamer's Hell |title=Overview: ''Crash: Mind over Mutant'' Q&amp;A |url=http://www.gamershell.com/infosheets/454094.html |accessdate=March 22, 2009 |quote=The only thing we weren't able to squeeze into the game was Coco as the second playable character in coop mode. It's not her character model that's the problem, but animations. To make Coco believable as a platforming, fighting character we felt she needed her own combat style and moves. It would have looked too weird if she moved the exact same way Crash does. And so she has her own animations. She looks great, but animations take a lot of memory.}}&lt;/ref&gt; In the PlayStation 2 version, she is replaced by a white-furred version of her brother named &quot;Carbon Crash&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;Joystiq&quot;&gt;{{cite web |publisher=Joystiq |last=Stern |first=Zack |date=2008-04-28 |title=Joystiq impressions: ''Crash Bandicoot: Mind over Mutant'' (Wii) |url=http://www.joystiq.com/2008/04/28/joystiq-impressions-crash-bandicoot-mind-over-mutant/ |accessdate=2009-03-22 |quote=A friend can join in on the same system, too, with drop-in cooperative play. In this mode, they can play a second Crash-like character or his sister, Coco.}}&lt;/ref&gt; Coco is voiced by Vicki Winters in ''[[Crash Bandicoot 2: Cortex Strikes Back]]'',&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.gamespot.com/ps/action/crashbandicoot2csb/tech_info.html |title=''Crash Bandicoot 2: Cortex Strikes Back'' for PlayStation - Technical Information, Game Information, Technical Support - GameSpot |accessdate=March 22, 2009 |publisher=[[GameSpot]]}}&lt;/ref&gt; by [[Hynden Walch]] in ''[[Crash Team Racing]]''&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.gamespot.com/ps/driving/crashteamracing/tech_info.html |title=''Crash Team Racing'' for PlayStation - Technical Information, Game Information, Technical Support - GameSpot |accessdate=March 22, 2009 |publisher=[[GameSpot]]}}&lt;/ref&gt; and by [[Debi Derryberry]] from ''[[Crash Bandicoot: The Wrath of Cortex]]'' onwards.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.gamespot.com/ps2/action/crashbandicootthewoc/tech_info.html |title=''Crash Bandicoot: The Wrath of Cortex'' for PlayStation 2 - Technical Information, Game Information, Technical Support - GameSpot |accessdate=March 22, 2009 |publisher=[[GameSpot]]}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.gamespot.com/ps2/driving/crashnitrokart/tech_info.html |title=''Crash Nitro Kart'' for PlayStation 2 - Technical Information, Game Information, Technical Support - GameSpot |accessdate=March 22, 2009 |publisher=[[GameSpot]]}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.gamespot.com/ps2/action/crashtwinsanity/tech_info.html |title=''Crash Twinsanity'' for PlayStation 2 - Technical Information, Game Information, Technical Support - GameSpot |accessdate=March 22, 2009 |publisher=[[GameSpot]]}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.gamespot.com/ps2/driving/crashtagteamracing/tech_info.html |title=''Crash Tag Team Racing'' for PlayStation 2 - Technical Information, Game Information, Technical Support - GameSpot |accessdate=March 22, 2009 |publisher=[[GameSpot]]}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.gamespot.com/wii/action/crashofthetitans/tech_info.html |title=''Crash of the Titans'' for Wii - Technical Information, Game Information, Technical Support - GameSpot |accessdate=March 22, 2009 |publisher=[[GameSpot]]}}&lt;/ref&gt; In the Japanese version of the series, she is voiced by [[Haruna Ikezawa]] in the [[PlayStation]] games, by [[Ema Kogure]] in ''Crash Bandicoot: The Wrath of Cortex'', ''[[Crash Nitro Kart]]'' and ''[[Crash Twinsanity]]'', by [[Satomi Arai]] in ''[[Crash Tag Team Racing]]'' and by [[Risa Tsubaki]] in ''[[Crash Boom Bang!]]''.

===Crunch Bandicoot===
'''Crunch Bandicoot''' is a genetically altered bandicoot who was originally created by Doctor Cortex to destroy Crash Bandicoot. After his defeat to Crash, Crunch had a change of heart and now tries to be a positive role model to children. He is Crash and Coco's little brother and protects them from harm. He is voiced by [[Kevin Michael Richardson]] in ''Crash Bandicoot: The Wrath of Cortex'' and ''Crash Nitro Kart'', and by [[Chris Williams (actor)|Chris Williams]] (in the style of [[Mr. T]]) in the Radical Entertainment games. In the Japanese version of the series, he is voiced by [[Yūji Kishi]] in ''Crash Bandicoot: The Wrath of Cortex'' and ''Crash Nitro Kart'', by [[Masafumi Kimura]] in ''Crash Tag Team Racing'', and by [[Shinya Fukumatsu]] in ''Crash Boom Bang!''.

Crunch was created by Doctor Cortex in private as a superweapon that would be capable of frightening power. Doctor N. Gin and [[Characters of Crash Bandicoot#Doctor Nefarious Tropy|Doctor Nefarious Tropy]] (who only had a slight understanding of the project) were the only other individuals who knew about the weapon. During a bad guy convention held by Uka Uka, Tropy and N. Gin reveal the weapon in desperation for one good plan to defeat Crash Bandicoot, whom Uka Uka wants eliminated.&lt;ref name=&quot;SecretWeapon&quot;&gt;{{cite video game |title=Crash Bandicoot: The Wrath of Cortex |developer=Traveller's Tales |publisher=Sony Computer Entertainment America |platform=Multiplatform  |level=Opening sequence |quote='''Doctor Nefarious Tropy:''' There must be something we can come up with! Say, Doctor. Haven't you been tinkering with some kind of new secret weapon in your laboratory? / '''Doctor Neo Cortex:''' I don't know what you're talking about, N. Tropy! / '''Doctor N. Gin:''' Doctor Cortex! I think he's referring to the super-secret weapon you've been laboring over day and night since the last time Crash defeated you!}}&lt;/ref&gt; Doctor Cortex formally announces the superweapon, but reveals that it is still missing a power source.&lt;ref name=&quot;PowerSource&quot;&gt;{{cite video game |title=Crash Bandicoot: The Wrath of Cortex |developer=Traveller's Tales |publisher=Sony Computer Entertainment |platform=Multiplatform |lev

el=Opening sequence |quote='''Doctor Neo Cortex:''' Well, in my scientific endeavors, I've been able to create a superweapon of unbelievable strength. But the power source... is the final missing crucial element.}}&lt;/ref&gt; Hearing the word &quot;element&quot;, Uka Uka brings up the Elementals, a group of destructive masks that could create enough energy to bring the secret weapon to life. The weapon, who is Crunch Bandicoot, attempts to defeat Crash with the aid of the Elemental masks, but when Crunch is defeated in Cortex's space station, he snaps out of Doctor Cortex's control. Although his first instinct is to introduce his fist to Cortex's face, Aku Aku informs Crunch of the space station's imminent destruction, and the group decides to flee back to Earth.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite video game |title=Crash Bandicoot: The Wrath of Cortex |developer=Traveller's Tales |publisher=Sony Computer Entertainment |platform=Multiplatform  |level=Ending sequence |quote='''Crunch Bandicoot:''' That annoying scientist doesn't have control over me anymore! Where is that pathetic twerp? / '''Aku Aku:''' There's no time for that now, Crunch.}}&lt;/ref&gt; Back on Earth, Crunch shows his gratitude toward the Bandicoots, and becomes part of the Bandicoot family.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite video game |title=Crash Bandicoot: The Wrath of Cortex |developer=Traveller's Tales |publisher=Sony Computer Entertainment |platform=Multiplatform |level=Ending sequence |quote='''Crunch Bandicoot:''' Crash. Coco. Aku Aku. I'm grateful to all of you. If it wasn't for you, I'd still be under the control of Doctor Cortex. Thank you for believing in me, guys.}}&lt;/ref&gt; In ''Crash Bandicoot 2: N-Tranced'', Crunch is abducted by N. Trance and is brainwashed alongside Coco and Fake Crash. Crash battles Crunch on a flying carpet over the skies of Saudi Arabia, with Crash firing shots of energy at Crunch whenever the latter is stunned by exploding Nitro crates. Upon snapping out of N. Trance's control, Crunch becomes a playable character in some of the Atlasphere levels. Crunch is a playable character in ''Crash Nitro Kart'' as well. In ''Crash Twinsanity'', Crunch has a cameo in Crash's &quot;birthday party&quot;, which is a gathering of past ''Crash'' villains. While Crunch is in the gathering, he actually believes that it is really Crash's birthday, donning a green paper crown and holding a slice of cake. Crunch has a minor appearance in ''Crash Bandicoot Purple: Ripto's Rampage'', aiding Crash in the &quot;Weighlift&quot; segments of the game.

Crunch appears as a playable character in [[Crash Nitro Kart]] ''Crash Tag Team Racing'' and ''Crash Boom Bang!''. In ''Crash of the Titans'', Crunch is ambushed by Doctor Cortex during the beginning of the first episode, leaving him frozen from the neck down. He stays this way until the end of the game, in which the Doominator's collapse is able to set Crunch free. Crunch does not appear in the DS version of the game. In the Game Boy Advance version, Crunch is taken prisoner by Tiny Tiger by order of Neo Cortex. He is freed upon Tiny's defeat. Crunch appears in ''Crash: Mind over Mutant'' and becomes addicted to the NV device alongside Coco to the point where he is unable to help Crash and Aku Aku when they are attacked by N. Gin's Ratnician army.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite video game|title=Crash: Mind over Mutant |developer=Radical Entertainment |publisher=Activision |date=October 7, 2008 |platform=Multiplatform |level=N Coming Message |quote='''Aku Aku:''' C'mon, everyone! We've got company. / '''Crunch Bandicoot:''' Can't talk! Watching monkeys! Look at that monkey! Oh, right in its own mouth.}}&lt;/ref&gt; He is later mutated by the bad Mojo transmitted by the NV and runs off, leaving a mutated Coco to fend off Crash. He is later found at the Junkyard, where Nitrus Brio commands Crunch to attack Crash. He is soon freed from the NV's control, but continues to be beaten up by an unaware Crash for a short time. He then decides to go back home and get some sleep.
&lt;br clear=&quot;all&quot; /&gt;

==Main antagonists==
===Doctor Neo Cortex===
{{main|Doctor Neo Cortex}}

===Doctor N. Gin===
Doctor N. Gin, spelled &quot;N-Gin&quot; in the Radical Entertainment games, was the right-hand man of Doctor Neo Cortex, replacing Doctor Nitrus Brio after [[Crash Bandicoot (character)|Crash Bandicoot]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Crash2Sketches&quot;&gt;{{cite web |publisher=Naughty Dog |title=[ Crash Gallery – Character Sketches – ''Crash 2'' &lt;nowiki&gt;]&lt;/nowiki&gt; |url=http://www.naughtydog.com/crash/crash/c2-character.htm |accessdate=August 10, 2008 |archiveurl = http://web.archive.org/web/20080730003110/http://www.naughtydog.com/crash/crash/c2-character.htm &lt;!-- Bot retrieved archive --&gt; |archivedate = July 30, 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt; He has since been replaced by the person he succeeded, Nitrus Brio. He is voiced by [[Brendan O'Brien (voice actor)|Brendan O'Brien]] in the Naughty Dog games, by [[Corey Burton]] in ''Crash Bandicoot: The Wrath of Cortex'', by [[Quinton Flynn]] in ''Crash Nitro Kart'' and ''Crash Twinsanity'', and by [[Nolan North]] (in the style of [[Peter Lorre]]) in the Radical Entertainment games. In the Japanese version of the series, he is voiced by [[Kazuhiro Nakata]] in the games up to ''Crash Twinsanity'', and by [[Mitsuru Ogata]] in &quot;Crash Tag Team Racing&quot;. His name is a wordplay on the word &quot;engine&quot;.

As a child, N. Gin was a classmate of Neo Cortex and Nitrus Brio in Madame Amberley's Academy of Evil.&lt;ref name=&quot;AcademyOfEvilClassmates&quot;&gt;{{cite web |publisher=Crash Mania |title=&quot;Crash Twinsanity&quot; concept art depicting Doctor Neo Cortex, Doctor N. Gin, and Doctor Nitrus Brio as children in the Academy of Evil |url=http://crashmania.net/?menu=ts&amp;page=concepts-7 |accessdate=August 10, 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt; After working at a [[stapler]] factory for a time,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite video game |title=Crash of the Titans |developer=Amaze Entertainment |publisher=Sierra Entertainment |platform=Game Boy Advance |level=Weapons Factory Caves |quote='''Aku Aku:''' Perhaps there is some good in you yet, N. Gin. If you promise to change your ways and go back to your old desk job at the stapler factory, then all is forgiven.}}&lt;/ref&gt; N. Gin went on to become a world-renowned [[physicist]] in the [[defense industry]]. However, due to a budget cut,&lt;ref name=&quot;Crash2Sketches&quot;/&gt; one of his missile projects ended up faulty and, as a result, went awry, lodging itself into N. Gin's head.&lt;ref name=&quot;Crash2Sketches&quot;/&gt; With his intellect, N. Gin was able to stabilize the weapon and reconstruct it as a life support system at the cost of his [[sanity]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |title=''Crash Bandicoot 2: Cortex Strikes Back'' Instruction Booklet |year=1997 |publisher=[[Sony Computer Entertainment]] |location= |isbn= |pages= }}&lt;/ref&gt; Because the [[missile]] is still live, it activates whenever N. Gin is stressed or angry, leaving him with a large [[headache]] (a trait inspired by creator [[Jason Rubin]]'s own chronic migraine headaches).&lt;ref name=&quot;Crash2Sketches&quot;/&gt; Shortly after the missile incident, Doctor N. Gin was taken in by Doctor Neo Cortex to replace the double-crossed Doctor Nitrus Brio.&lt;ref name=&quot;Crash2Sketches&quot;/&gt; Studying a large Crystal found by Cortex after his defeat to Crash Bandicoot, N. Gin discovers that 25 smaller &quot;Slave Crystals&quot; are needed alongside this &quot;Master Crystal&quot; in order to power Cortex's new &quot;Cortex Vortex&quot; device.&lt;ref name=&quot;MasterCrystal&quot;&gt;{{cite video game|title=Crash Bandicoot 2: Cortex Strikes Back |developer=Naughty Dog |publisher=Sony Computer Entertainment |date=October 31, 1997 |platform=PlayStation |level=Opening sequence |quote='''Doctor N. Gin:''' But Doctor Cortex, to reach full power, we need not only your &quot;Master Crystal&quot;, but also there are as many as 25 &quot;Slave Crystals&quot; on the surface.}}&lt;/ref&gt; When Crash is ordered by Doctor Cortex to give the Crystals he has gathered to N. Gin, N. Gin attempts to take the Crystals by force, only to be sent spiraling into the vacuum of space when Crash destroys his prized [[mecha]]. After the destruction of this mecha, N. Gin constructed a superior model: a suit of mobile armor that could transform into a space fighter and dock with a huge weapon platform.&lt;ref name=&quot;Crash3Sketches&quot;&gt;{{cite web |publisher=Naughty Dog |title=[Crash Gallery – Character Sketches – ''Crash 3'' &lt;nowiki&gt;]&lt;/nowiki&gt; |url=http://www.naughtydog.com/crash/crash/c3-character.htm |accessdate=2008-08-11 |archiveurl = http://web.archive.org/web/20080730001459/http://www.naughtydog.com/crash/crash/c3-character.htm &lt;!-- Bot retrieved archive --&gt; |archivedate = 2008-07-30}}&lt;/ref&gt; N. Gin uses this machine to confront Coco Bandicoot on the Moon in &quot;[[Crash Bandicoot 3: Warped]]&quot;, only to fail once again. N. Gin appears as a playable character in &quot;Crash Team Racing&quot; and as an obstacle in a &quot;Ballistix&quot; level in &quot;Crash Bash&quot;. The epilogue of &quot;Crash Team Racing&quot; states that N. Gin opened a custom auto parts store in [[Toledo, Ohio]], only to have it close down after a massive recall due to the damage caused by his patented &quot;Clear-the-Road&quot; missile system.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite video game |title=Crash Team Racing |developer=Naughty Dog |publisher=Sony Computer Entertainment |platform=PlayStation |level=Epilogue  |quote='''Text:''' N. Gin opened a custom auto parts store in Toledo, Ohio. The store closed after a massive recall when his patented &quot;Clear-the-Road&quot; missile system sparked havoc on the nation's freeways.}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In ''Crash Bandicoot: The Wrath of Cortex'', N. Gin is an attendee of Uka Uka's bad guy convention, and is ultimately the one who reveals the secret of Crunch Bandicoot, Cortex's new superweapon.&lt;ref name=&quot;SecretWeapon&quot;/&gt; For the rest of the game, N. Gin serves as an obstacle in some of the levels. In ''Crash Bandicoot: The Huge Adventure'', N. Gin battles Crash in the skies with a weapon platform similar to the one he piloted in ''Crash Bandicoot 3: Warped''. He is later merged with Doctor Cortex, Tiny and Dingodile, and becomes Mega-Mix. After chasing Crash down a space station hall, Mega-Mix is left inside the space station, which explodes with the villains in it. N. Gin is a playable character in ''Crash Nitro Kart''. In one cutscene, N. Gin considers creating cybernetic sharks as new henchmen after racing Nash.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite video game |title=Crash Nitro Kart |developer=Vicarious Visions |publisher=Sony Computer Entertainment America |platform=Multiplatform  |level=Beat Nash |quote='''Doctor N. Gin:''' Cybernetic sharks? We should try that! Yes, yes, they would make... great henchmen! / '''Doctor Neo Cortex:''' But this one lost. / (''N. Gin and Cortex see Tiny picking a large ball of lint out of his belly button, sniffing it, and eating it.'') / '''Doctor N. Gin:''' It appears to me he'd fit right in!}}&lt;/ref&gt; In ''Crash Twinsanity'', N. Gin appears during the first boss battle, piloting the Mecha-Bandicoot in an attempt to eliminate Crash. When all of its weapons are destroyed, the Mecha-Bandicoot stomps a hole into the floor and falls into a cavern. N. Gin is later seen as the captain of his own battleship. At the [[crow's nest]], N. Gin tries to destroy Crash with a barrage of missiles, occasionally tossing a TNT Crate. This leads to the eventual collapse of the crow's nest, causing N. Gin to land on his head onto a pile of TNT Crates, creating a large explosion that sinks the battleship. N. Gin is last seen teamed up with N. Tropy and N. Brio, with all of them trying to steal the Evil Twins' riches. However, they are driven out by [[Spyro (series)#Heroes|Spyro the Dragon]].

N. Gin is a playable character in ''Crash Tag Team Racing''. In the game's story, N. Gin convinces Neo Cortex to join in the search for Von Clutch's missing Power Gems so that he can use Von Clutch's theme park as a new base of operations (although Cortex later claims the idea as his own).&lt;ref&gt;{{cite video game |title=Crash Tag Team Racing |developer=Radical Entertainment |publisher=Sierra Entertainment |platform=Multiplatform  |level=Von Clutch Makes a Deal |quote='''Doctor N. Gin:''' Perhaps this is the answer to our dilemma. This strange theme park is fertile grounds for us to plant a new seed... of ''evil!!''}}&lt;/ref&gt; He has a cameo appearance in the &quot;Silhouette Quiz&quot; minigame in ''Crash Boom Bang!''. In ''Crash of the Titans'', N. Gin opposes Doctor Cortex's replacement by praising Cortex's stationery.&lt;ref name=&quot;Stationery&quot;&gt;{{cite video game |title=Crash of the Titans |developer=Radical Entertainment |publisher=Sierra Entertainment |platform=Multiplatform  |level=Episode 4: The Temple of Zoom |quote='''Doctor Neo Cortex:''' You can't replace me. My name's on the stationery! / '''Doctor N. Gin:''' ''(giggles)'' That's right, tough guy! Unless you want to buy a new stationery, you respect the master!! / '''Tiny Tiger:''' It's really nice stationery, too. / '''Doctor N. Gin:''' Oh, I know! Glossy!}}&lt;/ref&gt; N. Gin is next seen in his weapons factory, which appears on the outside as a version of the [[Statue of Liberty]] modelled after N. Gin. This factory constantly bombards the surrounding area with all kinds of explosives in an attempt to hinder Crash. Inside the factory, N. Gin communicates to his workers through the factory intercom, making announcements, singing inspirational songs, or alerting the workers of Crash's presence. In the factory's crown, N. Gin spends his days performing on his enormous pipe organ. When confronted by Crash and Aku Aku, N. Gin indirectly reveals to them that he has mixed feelings over Cortex's replacement to Nina. One side likes Doctor Cortex and the abuse he brings to him and wishes for his return, while another side approves of Nina's new way of doing things, believing that she is a more efficient leader than Cortex. Eventually, the two sides reach a compromise, and tell Crash of Uka Uka's whereabouts in hopes that he will also free Cortex, planning to shower them with doom later on.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite video game |title=Crash of the Titans |developer=Radical Entertainment |publisher=Sierra Entertainment |platform=Multiplatform  |level=Episode 13: Doomraker |quote='''Aku Aku:''' Well, what do we have here? You'll tell us where Coco is, won't you? / '''Doctor N. Gin:''' Of course not. Disgusting, filthy bandicoots! I hate them with cheese. / '''&quot;Neo&quot; N. Gin:''' They made it here! Now they'll help us save Doctor Cortex! / '''&quot;Nina&quot; N. Gin:''' Don't be ridiculous, you stupid hominid!! We're with Nina now! We're with the winner. / '''&quot;Neo&quot; N. Gin:''' But Doctor Cortex is our friend! / '''&quot;Nina&quot; N. Gin:''' You don't have any friends!! He always kicked you in the tokus, and other... very... gentle spots!! / '''&quot;Neo&quot; N. Gin:''' But I liked it when he did that! ''(Crash and Aku Aku look on confusedly)'' / '''&quot;Nina&quot; N. Gin:''' It was kind of fun. Listen. We make a deal with this filthy rodent and pie-nuts-face, and they help us save the master... then we shower them with doom! / '''&quot;Neo&quot; N. Gin:''' ''(giggling)'' Yes! We shower them good! Right in the eyes! ''(N. Gin continues to giggle until Crash yanks at his head rocket, causing him to yelp in pain.)''}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite video game |title=Crash of the Titans |developer=Radical Entertainment |publisher=Sierra Entertainment |platform=Multiplatform  |level=Episode 13: Doomraker |quote='''Doctor N. Gin:''' That's right, stupids! You need to go to Uka Uka's lab and stop him! That's where they make all the delicious mutants! Maybe your revolting sister is there, too. Eugh... girls...}}&lt;/ref&gt; In ''Crash: Mind over Mutant'', N. Gin leads an attack on Crash Bandicoot when Coco and Crunch become addicted to Cortex's and Brio's personal digital assistant, fleeing to a small [[observatory]] on Wumpa Island afterwards. When Crash and Aku Aku catch up to him, N. Gin reveals that ever since Doctor Cortex escaped the Doominator, he has been secretly watching the Bandicoot family and collecting information on them, hoping to be rewarded with the ownership of Wumpa Island if Cortex is triumphant in his current plot. After Crash fends off N. Gin's army of Ratnicians, N. Gin is sternly told by Aku Aku to leave the island, to which N. Gin reluctantly complies.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite video game|title=Crash: Mind over Mutant |developer=Radical Entertainment |publisher=Activision |date=2008-10-07 |platform=Multiplatform |version= |level=N is for Evil |isolang= |quote='''Aku Aku:''' I'm only gonna say this once, N. Gin: get off our island. / '''Doctor N. Gin:''' I'm sorry. I'm not here to take your message right now. Please leave a message after the beep. Beep! (''Crash snarls at N. Gin'') I'm going, I'm going! It was worth a shot.}}&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;br clear=&quot;all&quot; /&gt;

===Doctor Nitrus Brio===
'''Doctor Nitrus Brio''' is a scientist who formerly worked under Doctor Neo Cortex. Brio was created by Naughty Dog as a foil for Doctor Cortex: &quot;meek to Cortex's strength, logical to Cortex's emotional, successful (his inventions work) to Cortex's failure.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;Crash1Sketches&quot;/&gt; Brio is voiced by [[Brendan O'Brien (voice actor)|Brendan O'Brien]] in the English versions of ''Crash Bandicoot'', ''Crash Bandicoot 2: Cortex Strikes Back'' and ''Crash Bash'', and by [[Maurice LaMarche]] in ''Crash: Mind over Mutant''. He is voiced by [[Mitsuru Ogata]] in the Japanese version of the series up to ''Crash Bash''.  His name is often abbreviated to &quot;N. Brio&quot;, a wordplay on &quot;embryo&quot;.

As a child, Nitrus Brio was a classmate of Neo Cortex and N. Gin in Madame Amberly's Academy of Evil.&lt;ref name=&quot;AcademyOfEvilClassmates&quot;/&gt; Brio is responsible for creating the first fully functional Evolvo-Ray.&lt;ref name=&quot;Crash1ManualBrio&quot;&gt;{{cite book |title=''Crash Bandicoot'' Instruction Booklet |year=1996 |publisher=[[Sony Computer Entertainment]] |pages=20}}&lt;/ref&gt; However, his lack of self-esteem allowed Doctor Cortex to take credit for the creation.&lt;ref name=&quot;Crash1ManualBrio&quot;/&gt; Brio is the penultimate boss of the first game, transforming himself into a hulking beast (through use of his trademark mutagenic agent), to combat Crash. After his failure, Brio left Cortex to become a bartender. Whilst away, he plotted to destroy Cortex for good with the use of a giant laser. Brio manages to convince Crash to gather the 42 Gems needed for the laser to be operational, and gives him the honor of activating the weapon, destroying Cortex's space station. While Brio does not appear in ''Crash Team Racing'', a brand of beakers used as weapons during the races feature his name. Brio reunites with Cortex as a playable character in ''Crash Bash''.

In ''Crash Twinsanity'', Brio teams up with Doctor Nefarious Tropy to defeat Cortex and gain the Evil Twins Treasure. He appears alongside Tropy in a boss fight, immediately following Crash's escape from N. Gin's battleship, in which Brio (after being instructed by N. Tropy to &quot;get changed&quot;) drinks a potion to transform himself into a large, green frog-like monster. He then appears (in his human form) alongside N. Tropy and N. Gin again in the Evil Twins' fortress, claiming the Twins' treasure for themselves. However, they are thwarted by Spyro the Dragon, who had been trapped in the Twins' vault.

Brio reunites with Neo Cortex once more in ''Crash: Mind over Mutant'', in which he aids in the development of the NV, a personal digital assistant that can control both mutants and bandicoots. He uses recycled parts from the Sludge Junkyard to mass-produce NVs and create a new space station for Doctor Cortex. Throughout the game, he claims to be the inventor of numerous things, including [[recycling]],&lt;ref&gt;{{cite video game|title=Crash: Mind over Mutant |developer=Radical Entertainment |publisher=Activision |date=October 7, 2008 |platform=Multiplatform |level=Abuse, Misuse, Recycle |quote='''Doctor Nitrus Brio:''' Recycling shall destroy the world, and I, as its inventor, shall get the credit.}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Slinky|Slinkies]]&lt;ref&gt;{{cite video game|title=Crash: Mind over Mutant |developer=Radical Entertainment |publisher=Activision |date=October 7, 2008 |platform=Multiplatform |level=Abuse, Misuse, Recycle |quote='''Doctor Nitrus Brio:''' I invented Slinkies!! Stop playing with them because they're mine!!}}&lt;/ref&gt; and endings (though he does acknowledge he did not invent LiteBrite).&lt;ref name=&quot;BrioInventedEndings&quot;&gt;{{cite video game|title=Crash: Mind over Mutant |developer=Radical Entertainment |publisher=Activision |date=October 7, 2008 |platform=Multiplatform |level=Crunch Get |isolang= |quote='''Aku Aku:''' And you! You clear out. You're not welcome. Come on, Crash. Let's go find my brother. / '''Doctor Nitrus Brio:''' This isn't the end! I invented endings! Why don't people take me seriously?}}&lt;/ref&gt; He is found in the Junkyard with a brainwashed Crunch Bandicoot by Crash and Aku Aku, who are then attacked by Crunch under Brio's orders. When Crunch is broken free from the NV's control, Brio is forced to reveal the whereabouts of Uka Uka, who is acting as the source of the negative Mojo needed to control those wearing NVs. He is then told to leave the island, but promises that it is not the end.&lt;ref name=&quot;BrioInventedEndings&quot;/&gt;
&lt;br clear=&quot;all&quot; /&gt;

===Uka Uka===
'''Uka Uka''' is the evil younger twin brother of Aku Aku. Uka Uka was created by Naughty Dog as a presence that was able to cause even Neo Cortex to cower in fear.&lt;ref name=&quot;Crash3Sketches&quot;/&gt; He was voiced by [[Clancy Brown]] from 1998 to 2003, by [[Alex Fernandez (actor)|Alex Fernandez]] in ''Crash Twinsanity'', and by [[John DiMaggio]] in ''Crash of the Titans'' and ''Crash: Mind over Mutant''. He is voiced by [[Ryūzaburō Ōtomo]] in the Japanese versions of his appearances up to ''Crash Twinsanity''.

Several eons before the events of the series, Uka Uka was locked away by Aku Aku in an underground prison due to his malevolent nature.&lt;ref name=&quot;UndergroundPrison&quot;/&gt; Several millennia after his incarceration, Uka Uka recruits Doctor Cortex to fulfill his desire to enslave humanity, only to have Doctor Cortex lose the Crystals and the Gems, and have his space station destroyed.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite video game |title=Crash Bandicoot 3: Warped |developer=Naughty Dog |publisher=Sony Computer Entertainment America |platform=PlayStation |quote='''Uka Uka:''' From deep inside my temple prison, I sent you simple instructions to follow, but you lost the Gems, you lost the Crystals, and I have lost my patience!}}&lt;/ref&gt; The rubble of the ruined space station eventually crash-lands onto Earth, destroying the underground prison, and finally freeing Uka Uka. Upset with Cortex's failure to retrieve the Crystals and the Gems, Uka Uka recruits Doctor Nefarious Tropy, who has created the Time Twister, which will allow them to collect the Crystals and the Gems in their original places. And, since Cortex's failure also managed to set him free, Uka Uka still felt a sense of gratitude and generosity. When Crash intervenes and destroys the Time Twister, Uka Uka is trapped inside a time prison with Doctor Cortex and N. Tropy, who have been turned into infants. Uka Uka appears in ''Crash Team Racing'' as a tutor for the characters Cortex, N. Gin, Tiny, and Dingodile, giving them useful tips and tricks throughout the game. He also appears as a power-up during the races, protecting the said characters (along with Ripper Roo, Papu Papu, Komodo Joe, Pinstripe Potoroo and Doctor Nefarious Tropy) from all attacks and obstacles while giving them a speed boost.&lt;ref name=&quot;MaskTeamRacing&quot;/&gt; However, he cannot protect the characters from chasms and deep water.&lt;ref name=&quot;MaskTeamRacing&quot;/&gt; In ''Crash Bash'', in order to resolve his constant fighting with Aku Aku, Uka Uka summons Cortex, Brio, Tiny, Dingodile, Koala Kong, and Rilla Roo as part of a contest between his players against Aku Aku. Uka Uka is later forced to relinquish Tiny and Dingodile to Aku Aku's team to even out the number of players between them.

In ''Crash Bandicoot: The Wrath of Cortex'', Uka Uka scolds Cortex and the rest of the villains for their less-than-impressive evil productivity. Fed up with Cortex's incompetence, Uka Uka concludes that if global domination is to ever be achieved, Crash should be handled with personally.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite video game|title=Crash Bandioot: The Wrath of Cortex |developer=Traveller's Tales |publisher=Sony Computer Entertainment |date= |platform=Multiplatform |version= |level=Opening sequence |isolang= |quote='''Uka Uka:''' I will not let anything stand in the way of evil, especially not a brainless orange marsupial! Crash must be eliminated!}}&lt;/ref&gt; Deciding to use Cortex's new super-weapon to wipe out Crash Bandicoot, he revives the Elementals to act as the super-weapon's source of power and bring it to life. When Crash imprisons the Elementals, defeats the super-weapon, and brings it to their side, Uka Uka holds Cortex responsible and fires an energy blast at him out of anger, but in doing so causes their newly built space station to overload, forcing Cortex and Uka Uka to evacuate. Their escape pod lands in the depths of Antarctica, stranding them both on a sheet of ice. Uka Uka oversees the evil plots of both Neo Cortex and Nefarious Tropy in ''Crash Bandicoot: The Huge Adventure'' and ''Crash Bandicoot 2: N-Tranced'' respectively, becoming annoyed when both of them fail. Uka Uka reprises his role from ''Crash Team Racing'' in ''Crash Nitro Kart'', giving useful advice and acting as a power-up for the characters Neo Cortex, N. Gin, Tiny Tiger and N. Tropy. In ''Crash Twinsanity'', Uka Uka is freed from a wall of ice, but is enraged to see that Cortex has teamed up with Crash in order to defeat the Evil Twins, and transforms into an Ice [[Titan (mythology)|Titan]] in order to kill both of them, considering that he still held a grudge against Cortex for his past failures. When he is defeated, Uka Uka attempts to flee, but Aku Aku stops him and tells him about the Evil Twins' plot to destroy the Earth. Opposed to the fact that someone else is trying to destroy the world (a job that he believes is his), Uka Uka temporarily teams up with his twin brother, only to be defeated alongside him by the Evil Twins' ability to warp reality.

Uka Uka has a cameo appearance in ''Crash Boom Bang!'' as a purchaseable power-up. In ''Crash of the Titans'', Uka Uka teaches Doctor Cortex a new process called &quot;Mojo mutations&quot;, which uses a magical substance known as Mojo to mutate any living creature into a loyal minion of Cortex. At the Temple of Zoom, Uka Uka leaves Doctor Cortex to destroy Crash and Aku Aku while he returns to the base with an enormous amount of stolen Mojo and Coco Bandicoot at tow.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite video game|title=Crash of the Titans |developer=Radical Entertainment |publisher=Sierra Entertainment |date=2007-10-04 |platform=Multiplatform |version= |level=Episode 4: The Temple of Zoom |isolang= |quote='''Uka Uka:''' Cortex, deal with Crash and my pathetic brother. I will take the Mojo and bandicoot female back to our base.}}&lt;/ref&gt; When Cortex fails to defeat Crash, Uka Uka becomes furious, and announces that he is replacing Doctor Cortex, much to the shock of his minions. In a lab on the island's giant tree, Uka Uka expresses his relief with Nina Cortex's higher competence, but begins to sense Aku Aku's presence nearby, and decides to stay in the lab and kill Crash Bandicoot himself. Uka Uka confronts Crash as the penultimate boss by using Doctor Cortex's Evolvo-Ray on himself, giving him a gargantuan body made from the tree's wood. When the Evolvo-Ray is destroyed, Uka Uka claims that he will have the last laugh, as Nina is about to launch the Doominator, threatening the existence of Wumpa Island. Uka Uka is absent in the Nintendo DS version of the game. In ''Crash: Mind over Mutant'', Uka Uka is subdued and placed in a milking machine by Doctor Neo Cortex and Doctor Nitrus Brio so that he can be used as a source of the bad Mojo needed to control those using the mass-produced NV device. He is eventually freed by Crash and Aku Aku, and promises to take the two to Cortex's new space station if his magical bones are returned to him. When this task is completed, Uka Uka keeps his promise and warps Crash and Aku Aku to Cortex's space station as an act of vengeance against Cortex.
&lt;br clear=&quot;all&quot; /&gt;

===Tiny Tiger===
'''Tiny Tiger''', erroneously named '''Taz Tiger''' in the pause screen of the North American version of ''Crash Bandicoot 2: Cortex Strikes Back'', is a minion of Doctor Neo Cortex. He is voiced by [[Brendan O'Brien (voice actor)|Brendan O'Brien]] in the PlayStation games, by [[John DiMaggio]] in ''Crash Nitro Kart'' by Chris Williams (in the style of [[Mike Tyson]]) in ''Crash of the Titans'' and ''Crash: Mind over Mutant'', and by Nolan North in the [[Nintendo DS]] version of ''Crash of the Titans''. In the Japanese version of the series, he is voiced by [[Fumihiko Tachiki]] in the PlayStation games, and by Masafumi Kimura in ''Crash Nitro Kart''.

It is implied in at least two instruction manuals that Tiny was Doctor Cortex's first foray into genetic alteration.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |title=''Crash Bandicoot: The Wrath of Cortex'' Instruction Booklet |year=2001 |publisher=[[Sony Computer Entertainment]]}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |title=''Crash Bandicoot: The Huge Adventure'' Instruction Booklet |year=2002 |publisher=[[Sony Computer Entertainment]] |pages=19}}&lt;/ref&gt; However, this conflicts with what was established by Naughty Dog, who confirmed that [[Characters of Crash Bandicoot#Ripper Roo|Ripper Roo]] was Cortex's first serious creation.&lt;ref name=&quot;Crash1Sketches&quot;&gt;{{cite web |publisher=Naughty Dog |title=[ Crash Gallery – Character Sketches – ''Crash 1'' &lt;nowiki&gt;]&lt;/nowiki&gt; |url=http://www.naughtydog.com/crash/crash/c1-character.htm |accessdate=2008-08-10 |archiveurl = http://web.archive.org/web/20080805014708/http://www.naughtydog.com/crash/crash/c1-character.htm &lt;!-- Bot retrieved archive --&gt; |archivedate = 2008-08-05}}&lt;/ref&gt; Following the orders of Doctor Nitrus Brio, Tiny attempts to eliminate Crash as the third boss of ''Crash Bandicoot 2: Cortex Strikes Back'', but is unsuccessful in the end. By ''Crash Bandicoot 3: Warped'', Tiny has joined forces with Doctor Neo Cortex and Uka Uka. His first duty working under Cortex is attempting to take whatever Crystals Crash and Coco have gathered and bringing them to Cortex in the [[Colosseum]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite video game |title=Crash Bandicoot 3: Warped |developer=Naughty Dog |publisher=Sony Computer Entertainment America |platform=PlayStation  |level=Warp Room #1 |quote='''Tiny Tiger:''' Uka Uka and Cortex want Tiny get Crystals, and bring them to big Colosseum in Rome. Crash, leave them for Tiny, or Crash get crushed!!}}&lt;/ref&gt; Tiny is once again unsuccessful, as a fight against Crash in the Colosseum proves fruitless. Tiny appears as a playable character in ''Crash Team Racing'' and ''Crash Bash''. The epilogue of ''Crash Team Racing'' states that Tiny moved to [[Beverly Hills]] and founded a chain of fitness clubs after the events of the game.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite video game |title=Crash Team Racing |developer=Naughty Dog |publisher=Sony Computer Entertainment |platform=PlayStation |level=Epilogue  |quote='''Text:''' Tiny Tiger moved to Beverly Hills and founded the popular chain of &quot;Pain 'N Gain&quot; fitness clubs. His Tiny-Bo exercise video made millions on infomercials around the globe.}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In ''Crash Bandicoot: The Wrath of Cortex'', Tiny is an attendee in Uka Uka's bad guy convention, not speaking a single line in the entire game. He later serves as an obstacle in certain levels, literally standing in Crash's way in an attempt to hinder him, as well as operating various flying vehicles in levels involving planes or spaceships. In ''Crash Bandicoot: The Huge Adventure'', Tiny serves as the third boss, fighting Crash near a large waterfall. He is later merged with Doctor Cortex, N. Gin, and Dingodile, and becomes Mega-Mix. After chasing Crash down a space station hall, Mega-Mix is left inside the space station, which explodes with the villains in it. Tiny is a playable character in ''Crash Nitro Kart''. In the game's story, Tiny is seen playing [[checkers]] with himself (and later, attempting to assist N. Gin) when the tower the villains are standing in is abducted. When Emperor Velo is defeated, Tiny, Cortex, and N. Gin are teleported to Terra, where Tiny gains the respect of the inhabitants. Tiny has a cameo appearance (along with other ''Crash'' villains) in ''Crash Twinsanity'' during Crash's &quot;birthday party&quot;. In the crossover game ''Crash Bandicoot Purple: Ripto's Rampage'', Tiny acts as the second boss, attempting to obliterate Crash in a frozen tundra with a tank.

Tiny has a cameo appearance in ''Crash Boom Bang!'', appearing in the &quot;Silhouette Quiz&quot; minigame. In ''Crash of the Titans'', Tiny protests Neo Cortex's replacement alongside Doctor N. Gin by praising Cortex's stationery.&lt;ref name=&quot;Stationery&quot;/&gt; Tiny is the one in charge of the mining operations seen in Episodes 5 through 7, responsible for destroying a portion of the jungle and obtaining minerals from the volcano. When Crash distrupts these operations, Tiny confronts Crash directly and voices his displeasure in both Crash's antics and the fact that he wasn't invited to ''Crash Tag Team Racing''.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite video game |title=Crash of the Titans |developer=Radical Entertainment |publisher=Sierra Entertainment |platform=Multiplatform  |level=Episode 7: The Blizzard of Claws |quote='''Tiny Tiger:''' Crash, I really am cross with you! I'm just trying to do my job, and you go and cause all this chaos! I'm sorry, but... I'm gonna have to eat your face. ''(Crash panics)'' Yeah, I'm really sorry about that. I wish some sort of reconciliation was possible here, and frankly, I'm still mad about the last game. You didn't even invite me! That really hurt!}}&lt;/ref&gt; When Crash confronts Tiny with the Shellephant, Tiny decides to reveal the whereabouts of Crash's sister.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite video game |title=Crash of the Titans |developer=Radical Entertainment |publisher=Sierra Entertainment |platform=Multiplatform  |level=Episode 7: The Blizzard of Claws |quote='''Tiny Tiger:''' Stop! No more, please! You're just too stupendous and fantabulous! Honestly, you are just awesome. / '''Crash Bandicoot:''' Uh huh. / '''Tiny Tiger:''' I'll tell you where they go! Nina took Coco to the factory on the beach. / '''Crash Bandicoot:''' Nina? Howjibeduvuh? / '''Aku Aku:''' Nina? You mean Doctor Cortex, don't you? / '''Tiny Tiger:''' No, Nina! Uka Uka and her got rid of Cortex. They were tired of Cortex failing all the time.}}&lt;/ref&gt; Although Tiny isn't seen physically in ''Crash: Mind over Mutant'', his voice can be heard in the game's credits when he tries to correct Crunch when he mixes up his metaphors.
&lt;br clear=&quot;all&quot; /&gt;

===Dingodile===
'''Dingodile''' is a minion of Doctor Neo Cortex. Dingodile was created when Naughty Dog member [[Joe Labbe]] asked for a character that was a cross between a [[dingo]] and a [[crocodile]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Crash3Sketches&quot;/&gt; Dingodile is voiced by [[William Hootkins]] in ''Crash Bandicoot 3: Warped'', by Chip Chinery in ''Crash Team Racing'', by [[Dwight Schultz]] in ''Crash Nitro Kart'' and ''Crash Twinsanity'', and by Nolan North in the Nintendo DS version of ''Crash of the Titans''. In the Japanese version of the series, he is voiced by [[Keisuke Ishida]] in the PlayStation games, and by [[Hajime Iijima]] in ''Crash Nitro Kart'' and ''Crash Twinsanity''.

Dingodile made his debut in the video game ''Crash Bandicoot: Warped'' as the second boss of the game. Here, he is seen serving under Uka Uka and Doctor Cortex, attempting to take whatever Crystals Crash has gathered and bringing them to Cortex during the Ice Age under his orders.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite video game |title=Crash Bandicoot 3: Warped |developer=Naughty Dog |publisher=Sony Computer Entertainment America |platform=PlayStation |level=Warp Room #2 |quote='''Dingodile:''' G'day, mates! Dingodile's the name, and Uka Uka and Cortex gave me orders to bring the Crystals to them during the Ice Ages. So gimme the goods, and shove off! Or I'll roast yaz!}}&lt;/ref&gt; Crash encounters Dingodile as he is about to kill a penguin, who runs away upon Crash's arrival. When Dingodile is defeated, he warns Crash of the more powerful enemies he will face ahead as the penguin he tried to kill earlier hops up and down on his charred body.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite video game |title=Crash Bandicoot 3: Warped |developer=Naughty Dog |publisher=Sony Computer Entertainment America |platform=PlayStation  |level=Dingodile |quote='''Dingodile:''' You thrashed me, mate. No worries, but soon you'll be up against much worse...}}&lt;/ref&gt; Dingodile is a playable character in ''Crash Team Racing'' and ''Crash Bash''. The epilogue of ''Crash Team Racing'' states that Dingodile created an animal breeding program to create unique and interesting pets.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite video game |title=Crash Team Racing |developer=Naughty Dog |publisher=Sony Computer Entertainment |platform=PlayStation |level=Epilogue  |quote='''Text:''' Dingodile went on to found an animal breeding program for the creation of unique and interesting pets. His motto &quot;Combine them all&quot; spurred such successes as the Gir-bat, Kanga-rooster, and the Dino-Rilla.}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Dingodile appears as an attendee of Uka Uka's bad guy convention.  He later serves as an obstacle in certain levels, firing spurts of flamethrower ammo in an attempt to stop Crash. In ''Crash Bandicoot: The Huge Adventure'', Dingodile serves as the first boss. He fights Crash in a [[shark]]-infested underwater cavern, and fires torpedoes at the cavern ceiling in an attempt to impale Crash with the falling stalactites, but eventually manages to impale himself, leaving him open for attack. He is later merged with Doctor Cortex, N. Gin and Tiny Tiger, and becomes Mega-Mix. After chasing Crash down a space station hall, Mega-Mix is left inside the space station, which explodes with the villains in it. Dingodile is a playable character in ''Crash Nitro Kart''. In the game's story, Dingodile is seen assisting Doctor N. Gin when the tower the villains are standing in is abducted. The next time he is seen, he is brainwashed by N. Trance and racing under N. Trance's team, which drives green vehicles. In ''Crash Twinsanity'', Dingodile is seen as one of the attendees of Crash's &quot;birthday party&quot; (which is really a gathering of past villains in the ''Crash'' series). After watching the ensuing boss battle, he discusses lunch with Ripper Roo. Later, he is seen reading inside a small shack, but is interrupted when a large snowball (containing Crash and Cortex) crushes the shack with him in it. As Cortex laments his humiliation, Dingodile learns of the Evil Twins' treasure,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite video game |title=Crash Twinsanity |developer=Traveller's Tales |publisher=Sony Computer Entertainment America |platform=PlayStation 2  |level=High-Seas Hijinks |quote='''Doctor Neo Cortex:''' I've never been so humiliated! No amount of treasure would ever be able to compensate. / '''Dingodile:''' (''emerging from the ruins of his shack'') Treasure, eh? Bonzai!}}&lt;/ref&gt; and secretly follows Crash and Cortex to the boiler room of Madame Amberly's Academy of Evil, where he tries to kill Crash for the treasure, believing he already has it. However, with the help of the boiler room's emergengy sprinkler system, Crash is able to disable Dingodile's flamethrower and beat him into submission. Dingodile is last seen laying unconscious in the boiler room.

While Dingodile doesn't appear in the console version of ''Crash of the Titans'', he appears as the first boss in the [[Nintendo DS]] and [[Game Boy Advance]] versions on the game. In the Nintendo DS version, Dingodile is assigned to stalling Crash Bandicoot while the other villains gather materials and build Neo Cortex's new CortexBot. Dingodile attempts to defeat Crash with a new water cannon, but ultimately fails. In the Game Boy Advance version, Dingodile is given the task of sending barrels of oil from Wumpa Island to Tiki Island. He is defeated by Crash, who attacks him with inhabited bee hives.
&lt;br clear=&quot;all&quot; /&gt;

===Doctor Nefarious Tropy===
'''Doctor Nefarious Tropy''' is a henchman of Uka Uka and the self-proclaimed master of time. He was created by Naughty Dog as a time traveling boss that would fit in a time traveling plot.&lt;ref name=&quot;Crash3Sketches&quot;/&gt; Tropy is voiced by [[Michael Ensign]] in all his speaking appearances excluding ''Crash Bandicoot: The Wrath of Cortex'', in which he is voiced by [[Corey Burton]]. He is voiced by [[Masaru Ikeda]] in the Japanese versions of ''Crash Bandicoot 3: Warped'', ''Crash Team Racing'' and ''Crash Bandicoot: The Wrath of Cortex'' and by [[Haruo Satō]] in the Japanese versions of ''Crash Nitro Kart'' and ''Crash Twinsanity''.  His name is abbreviated as N. Tropy, which is a play on &quot;[[entropy]]&quot;, a comment on his clock like form, and such is usually mentioned or unlocked from the time challenge awards inside games (Relic Races and Time Trials)

Doctor Nefarious Tropy is introduced by Uka Uka in ''Crash Bandicoot 3: Warped'' as the creator of the Time-Twisting Machine, a device that will aid Neo Cortex in his quest to gather the Crystals in their original places in time. He later acts as the third boss of the game, battling Crash with his gigantic tuning fork. When Cortex is defeated, the Time-Twisting Machine implodes on itself, trapping Cortex, Uka Uka and Tropy in a time prison, where they are transformed into infants. Tropy appears in ''Crash Team Racing'' as the player's opponent during the Time Trial races and later as an unlockable playable character. The game's epilogue states that Tropy resumed his time machine hobby after the events of the game, and was last seen entering an ancient rainforest.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite video game |title=Crash Team Racing |developer=Naughty Dog |publisher=Sony Computer Entertainment America |date=September 30, 1999 |platform=PlayStation |level=Epilogue |quote='''Text:''' N. Tropy began tinkering with his time machine hobby again. He was last seen entering a time warp ball traveling to some ancient rain forest. Alas, rust is timeless.}}&lt;/ref&gt;

N. Tropy has a minor appearance in ''Crash Bandicoot: The Wrath of Cortex'', in which he is an attendee of Uka Uka's convention and an occasional enemy in the game, attempting to hinder Crash's progress. He is the main antagonist of ''Crash Bandicoot 2: N-Tranced'', in which he kidnaps Crunch, Coco and Fake Crash and hypnotizes them into working for him. He is later defeated by Crash and is forced to take a group picture with the Bandicoots. Tropy is an unlockable character in ''Crash Nitro Kart'', where he races under Neo Cortex's team. Tropy appears again in ''Crash Twinsanity'', where he works with Doctor Nitrus Brio in order to learn the whereabouts of the treasure of the Evil Twins. When interrogating Crash proves fruitless, the duo attack him, sending him back to Cortex's Iceberg Lab. They eventually reach the treasure trove of the Evil Twins, but are chased out by Spyro the Dragon. Tropy also has a cameo appearance in the &quot;Silhouette Quiz&quot; minigame in ''Crash Boom Bang!''

==Other characters==
===Polar===
'''Polar''' is Crash Bandicoot's pet [[polar bear]] cub. He lets Crash ride him in ''Crash Bandicoot 2: Cortex Strikes Back'', helping him through some snow levels and helping him escape from a larger polar bear. There was a secret easter egg in ''Cortex Strikes Back'', in which Crash would continuously bounce on top of him in the second warp room, revealing multiple extra lives. He appears in the opening sequence of ''Crash Bandicoot 3: Warped'' as a resident of Crash's home and is a playable character in ''Crash Team Racing'' and ''Crash Nitro Kart''. In Crash Team Racing, he is seen in the options screen, reading an upside-down racing manual. He has been hypnotised by N Trance in Crash Nitro Kart. The epilogue of Crash Team racing says he became an ice cream tester. He appears in &quot;Crash Bash&quot; in the polar push minigames where characters ride on him. He also makes cameo appearances in ''Crash Twinsanity'' as a guest at Crash's &quot;birthday party&quot; (during which he stands upright and wields a baseball bat) and in ''Crash Boom Bang!'' in the &quot;Silhouette Quiz&quot; minigame. Polar is voiced by [[Debi Derryberry]] in ''Crash Nitro Kart'' and by [[Satomi Kōrogi]] in the Japanese versions of ''Crash Team Racing'' and ''Crash Bash''.

===Pura===
'''Pura''' is Coco Bandicoot's pet [[tiger cub]]. Originally, Pura was going to be a panda but Naughty Dog decided to make him a tiger to show a clear difference between [[Characters of Crash Bandicoot#Polar|Polar]] and himself. He made his debut in ''Crash Bandicoot 3: Warped'', helping Coco across the Great Wall of China. He is a playable character in ''Crash Team Racing'', ''Crash Nitro Kart'' and ''Crash Boom Bang!''. He makes a cameo appearance in &quot;Crash Bandicoot: The Wrath of Cortex&quot; as a resident of the bandicoot's house. Pura is voiced by [[Paul Greenberg]] in ''Crash Nitro Kart''. He is voiced by [[Taeko Kawata]] in his Japanese speaking appearances excluding ''Crash Nitro Kart'', and by [[Asuka Tanii]] in ''Crash Boom Bang!''.

===Nina Cortex===
'''Nina Cortex''' is the niece of Doctor Neo Cortex. She sometimes aids her uncle in his quest for world domination, though they have had a recent falling-out due to a failed plot headed by her and Cortex's boss Uka Uka. Nina Cortex was originally created by Traveller's Tales as a playable character in ''Crash Nitro Kart'' before development duties of the game were transferred to Vicarious Visions. During her conception it was undecided whether she would be Neo Cortex's daughter or niece, hence the deliberate discrepancies regarding her relationship with Cortex in ''Crash Twinsanity''. Her appearance was based on one of the designers working at Traveller's Tales. An early design of her depicted her wearing a white lab coat similar to Neo Cortex's.&lt;ref name=&quot;NinaDevelopment&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url=http://crashmania.net/?menu=ts&amp;page=concepts-1 |title=SpaceCat's Topic Regarding Unused Ideas |accessdate=March 26, 2009 |author=SpaceCat |date=January 7, 2005 |publisher=Crash Mania}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Nina is known to be more ambitious and egotistical than her uncle;&lt;ref name=&quot;CrashVillage&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url=http://village.crashbandicoot.com/us/index.php |title=Welcome to Crash Village |accessdate=March 26, 2009 |publisher=[[Sierra Entertainment]]}}&lt;/ref&gt; even Aku Aku believes that Nina is &quot;a lot smarter than Cortex ever could be.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite video game |title=Crash of the Titans |developer=Radical Entertainment |publisher=Sierra Entertainment |date=October 4, 2007 |platform=Wii |level=Episode 7: The Blizzard of Claws |quote='''Aku Aku:''' This isn't good, Crash. Nina's a lot smarter than Cortex ever could be.}}&lt;/ref&gt; Despite her self-admittedly [[Antisocial personality disorder|antisocial]] demeanor,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite video game |title=Crash Tag Team Racing |developer=Radical Entertainment |publisher=Sierra Entertainment |platform=Multiplatform |level=Race |quote='''Nina Cortex:''' Who says it's not fun being antisocial?}}&lt;/ref&gt; she is said to have a love for animals.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://crashmania.net/index.php?menu=ts&amp;page=concepts-3 |title=SpaceCat's Topic Regarding Unused Ideas |accessdate=March 26, 2009 |author=SpaceCat |date=March 5, 2005 |publisher=Crash Mania}}&lt;/ref&gt; Nina's most distinguishing features are her spring-loaded steel bionic hands, which were given to her by her uncle Doctor Cortex.&lt;ref name=&quot;CrashVillage&quot;/&gt;  Nina stands about four feet and eleven inches (1.5 meters) and weighs 110 pounds (50 kilograms).&lt;ref&gt;{{cite video game |title=Crash of the Titans |developer=Amaze Entertainment |publisher=Sierra Entertainment |platform=Nintendo DS |level=Nina Cortex profile}}&lt;/ref&gt;

When Nina Cortex started to show signs of a kind heart, Doctor Cortex modified her arms with bionic parts and enrolled her in Madame Amberly's Private Academy, which he himself attended as a child. She doesn't see her uncle again until the Evil Twins threaten the existence of the N. Sanity Island in ''Crash Twinsanity'', during which Doctor Cortex sneaks her out of the school to assist him in defeating the Evil Twins. When Crash, Cortex and Nina travel to the Tenth Dimension, Nina is kidnapped by the feral Evil Crash and taken to his house for a tea party, where Cortex soon rescues Nina.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite video game |title=Crash Twinsanity |developer=Traveller's Tales |publisher=Sony Computer Entertainment America |platform=Multiplatform  |level=Bandicoot Pursuit |quote='''Doctor Neo Cortex:''' There they are. Let her go! Take me instead! (''Evil Crash chases Cortex down'')}}&lt;/ref&gt; She later helps in defeating the Evil Twins by destroying the power sources of their Deathbot.

In ''Crash of the Titans'', when Cortex fails to dispose of Crash Bandicoot, Nina is called upon by Uka Uka to replace her uncle as the main antagonist of the story. In the Nintendo DS version of the game, Nina attempts to take over Cortex's plot on her own accord when she realizes that she's merely a henchman. When Crash confronts her inside the Doominator, Nina boards her giant Arachnina Titan and battles Crash, only to lose. When the Doominator is disabled, she is rescued from the falling contraption by Doctor Cortex, who reveals that he is proud that she betrayed him,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite video game |title=Crash of the Titans |developer=Radical Entertainment |publisher=Sierra Entertainment |date=2007-10-04 |platform=Wii |level=Episode 20: Revengeance 2 — The Revengicide |quote=Why did you rescue me? I betrayed you, took over your evil plan... then failed. / '''Doctor Neo Cortex:''' Oh, Nina. Betraying me is the most vile, evil thing you could've ever done! You're a skank. I'm... just so proud of you right now. / '''Nina Cortex:''' Hooray!}}&lt;/ref&gt; but proceeds to drop her off at his public school as punishment for doing so, as seen in ''Crash: Mind over Mutant''. When she is eventually visited by Crash and Aku Aku, she angrily accuses Crash of ruining her life and refuses to help them stop Cortex's ongoing plot. When Crash and Aku Aku get desperate, she forces the two to kiss each other and save her science fair project.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite video game|title=Crash: Mind over Mutant |developer=Radical Entertainment |publisher=Activision |date=2008-10-07 |platform=Multiplatform |version= |level=Forbidden Love |isolang= |quote='''Aku Aku:''' Please, Nina! We'll do anything! / '''Nina Cortex:''' Anything? Really... / '''Aku Aku:''' (''sighs'') Yes. / '''Nina Cortex:''' Kiss. / '''Aku Aku:''' What?! / '''Nina Cortex:''' Yeah. Kiss. Right now. It will amuse me.}}&lt;/ref&gt; She then uses the said project to determine the location of Crunch and Brio, who are at the Sludge's Junkyard.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite video game|title=Crash: Mind over Mutant |developer=Radical Entertainment |publisher=Activision |date=2008-10-07 |platform=Multiplatform |version= |level=Evil Public School |isolang= |quote='''Nina Cortex:''' Uncle Cortex made up with his old lab partner, N. Brio. / '''Aku Aku:''' N. Brio?! / '''Nina Cortex:''' Uncie Cortex talks some big game, but N. Brio's the guy who actually built everything. And luckily for you, my science project thingy tells me exactly where he is. Now, run along to the other side of the island. I've got new evil plans to start.}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In ''Crash Bandicoot Purple: Ripto's Rampage'' and ''Spyro Orange: The Cortex Conspiracy'', Nina is recruited by Doctor Cortex to kidnap Coco Bandicoot and the Professor.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite video game|title=Crash Bandicoot Purple: Ripto's Rampage |developer=Vicarious Visions |publisher=Vivendi Universal Games |date=2004-06-03 |platform=Game Boy Advance |version= |level= |isolang= |quote='''Doctor Neo Cortex:''' Enough! I have someone better in mind who can get the job done. Niiinaaa!!! / '''Nina Cortex:''' Yay! Nina wants to play! / '''Doctor Neo Cortex:''' Niece, I have a very important job for you... / (''Later'') '''Spyro the Dragon:''' Blinky! What's up? / '''Blinky:''' Spyro! Crash! Nina has kidnapped the Professor and Coco!}}&lt;/ref&gt; When Spyro and Crash arrive to save Coco and the Professor, Nina chases down Crash, only to soon be captured in a cage. Nina is a playable character in ''Crash Tag Team Racing'', in which she aids Doctor Cortex and N. Gin in trying to take over Von Clutch's MotorWorld.

====Reception====
Nina's introduction in ''Crash Twinsanity'' was met with a positive response among critics. James B. Pringle of [[IGN]] said that Nina &quot;almost steals the show with her sassy skip and her ''[[Bionic Commando]]''{{Disambiguation needed|date=June 2011}}-like extension arm&quot; and admitted that he &quot;actually wouldn't mind seeing more of Nina in the future.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://ps2.ign.com/articles/554/554364p1.html |title=IGN: ''Crash Twinsanity'' Review |accessdate=2009-03-26 |author=James B. Pringle |date=2004-10-05 |work= |publisher=[[IGN]]}}&lt;/ref&gt; Nick Valentino of [[GameZone]] praised her as &quot;an inventive character&quot;, a &quot;very welcome addition to the series&quot; and &quot;one of the many highlights this game has to offer&quot;. He also compared her bionic arms to ''Bionic Commando''.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://xbox.gamezone.com/gzreviews/r23742.htm |title=''Crash Twinsanity'' Review – Xbox |accessdate=2009-03-26 |author=Nick Valentino |date=2004-10-08 |work= |publisher=[[GameZone]]}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Ripper Roo===
'''Ripper Roo''' is a boss character in the first and second games in the series. He is a [[kangaroo]] who was mutated by Doctor Neo Cortex and now has a demented personality (emptily wide-open eyes, hanging tongue, bound to a straitjacket) and distinctive laughter. He mainly attacks through the use of his razor-sharp toenails and laying down TNT and Nitro tiles. As of the second game, he has a second personality that is much more sane than his dominant one; however, an explosion is enough to get him back to his old, hopping mad self. He has additional appearances in &quot;Crash Team Racing&quot; as a boss character and &quot;Crash Bash&quot; as an obstacle. In &quot;Crash Twinsanity&quot;, he appears with the rest of Dr. Cortex's minions just before Crash starts battling against Dr. Cortex. Ripper Roo is voiced by [[Katsumi Suzuki]] in the Japanese version of &quot;Crash Team Racing&quot;. His laugh was taken from a hyena laughing in [[Lady and the Tramp]]; the laugh was voiced by [[Dallas McKennon]].

===Nitros Oxide===
'''Nitros Oxide''' is an extraterrestrial who claims to be the fastest racer in the galaxy. He is named after the anesthetic gas [[nitrous oxide]]. Oxide is unlockable boss playable character in the Special Edition of ''Crash Team Racing'' and starter playable character in ''Crash Nitro Kart'', attempting to turn Earth into a concrete parking lot. After being thwarted in this plan, he fled back to his native Gasmoxia and only returned to racing after years of seclusion and therapy.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite video game |title=Crash Team Racing |developer=Naughty Dog |publisher=Sony Computer Entertainment America |date=1999-09-30 |platform=PlayStation |level=Epilogue |quote='''Text:''' Nitros Oxide went back to the planet Gasmoxia a broken alien. After years of therapy, Oxide emerged from seclusion to begin racing again. Unfortunately, the unicycle was a poor vehicle choice, and his resulting accident was too gruesome to detail here}}&lt;/ref&gt; He subsequently appears in ''Crash Bash'' as the final boss of the game's story mode. He returns as the main antagonist in ''[[Crash Bandicoot Nitro Kart 3D]]'' in which he teams up with Doctor Neo Cortex and Ripper Roo in an attempt to banish Crash Bandicoot and his friends from N. Sanity Island. Oxide made a brief cameo in the beginning scene of the menu in [[Crash Bandicoot 4|Crash Bandicoot: The Wrath of Cortex]] and in the beginning of Crash Twinsanity at Crash's birthday party. Oxide is voiced by [[David Anthony Pizzuto]] in ''Crash Team Racing'' and by [[Quinton Flynn]] in ''Crash Nitro Kart''. He is voiced by [[Junpei Takiguchi]] and [[Chafurin]] in the Japanese versions of these respective games.

===Papu Papu===
'''Papu Papu''' is the obese chief of the native tribe of N. Sanity Island. He is neither on Crash's nor Cortex's side, but will capture and/or eat anything that steps into his territory. He possesses a large staff which he tries to defeat Crash with. He first appears as the first boss in the original game, and later as a boss in both ''Crash Team Racing'' and ''Crash Bash'', where he uses the staff to summon miniature versions of Crash. In [[Crash Twinsanity]], he captured Cortex. Papu Papu is voiced by [[Michael Gollom]] in ''Crash Team Racing'' and by [[Dwight Schultz]] in ''Crash Twinsanity''. He is voiced by [[Yū Shimaka]] in the Japanese version of &quot;Crash Team Racing&quot;.

===Pinstripe Potoroo===
'''Pinstripe Potoroo''' is a boss character in the first ''Crash Bandicoot'' game. He is a mutated [[potoroo]] who wears a red pinstripe suit and wields a fully loaded Tommy gun. The game's last non-human boss, he is perhaps the most intelligent of Cortex's early creations, CEO of his corporation on Wumpa Island. After Crash defeated him, he began his own nuclear power plant and industrial corporation, replacing Cortex as the island's top man. He also won the heart of Crash's former girlfriend Tawna. He also acts as a boss character in ''Crash Team Racing''. He also appeared in Crash Twinsanity as a [[Cameo appearance|cameo]] at Crash's fake birthday party. Pinstripe is voiced by [[Brendan O'Brien (voice actor)|Brendan O'Brien]] in all of his speaking appearances.

===Tawna===
'''Tawna''' was the former girlfriend of Crash Bandicoot. She made her debut on the [[Crash Bandicoot (video game)|first ''Crash Bandicoot'' game]], being trapped for observation on Neo Cortex's castle after being experimented on. Crash then invades Cortex's castle, defeats him and saves her. The marketing director of Universal Interactive Studios objected to Tawna's initial design on &quot;basic sexist principles&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;AndyGavin6&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url=http://all-things-andy-gavin.com/2011/02/07/making-crash-bandicoot-part-6/ |title=Making ''Crash Bandicoot'' - part 6 |author=Andy Gavin |date=February 7, 2011 |publisher=All Things Andy Gavin |accessdate=March 2, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; The director's behavior concerning the issue unnerved the president of Universal Interactive so much that he requested Andy Gavin and Jason Rubin to change the character to the director's specifications. The incident proved to be such an unpleasant experience that Tawna was omitted from future ''Crash Bandicoot'' titles.&lt;ref name=&quot;JasonInterview&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url=http://crashmania.net/?page=interviewjason |title=Interview with Jason Rubin |accessdate=March 8, 2010 |publisher=Crash Mania |date=August 16, 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt; Tawna would later make cameos in ''[[Crash Bandicoot 3: Warped|Crash Bandicoot 3]]'' and ''[[Crash Bandicoot: The Wrath of Cortex]]'', at a photo on Crash's house; in ''[[Crash Twinsanity]]'', at the sign of Cortex-owned nightclub Moulin Cortex; and at a poster on Crash's house in ''[[Crash: Mind over Mutant]]''. But it was not until ''[[Crash Boom Bang!]]'' that she became a playable character. ''Crash Boom Bang!'' is the only game in which she speaks, being voiced by [[Akiko Toda]].

===Koala Kong===
'''Koala Kong''' is a boss character in the first ''Crash Bandicoot'' game. He is a mutated [[koala]] who tosses around boulders using his superhuman strength. He was defeated by Crash at the summit of Wumpa Island's volcano. After his defeat, he became a Hollywood movie star. He is a playable character in ''Crash Bash''. He also appears in ''Crash Twinsanity'' at Crash's fake birthday party thrown by cortex.

===Fake Crash===
'''Fake Crash''' (a.k.a. Trash Bandicoot) is a [[cloning|clone]] of Crash Bandicoot with thick eyebrows and an [[overbite]]. He is a hidden character in much of the games beginning with ''Crash Bandicoot 3: Warped''. He is a playable character in ''Crash Team Racing'' and the Japanese version of ''Crash Bash''. Fake Crash is voiced by Michael Connor in ''Crash Team Racing'' and by [[Dwight Schultz]] in ''Crash Nitro Kart''. He is voiced by [[Kappei Yamaguchi]] in the Japanese versions of the games up to ''Crash Nitro Kart'', and by [[Makoto Ishii]] in ''Crash Boom Bang!''. In ''Crash Bandicoot 2: N-Tranced'', Dr. N. Tropy attempts to abduct Crash Bandicoot, but Aku Aku intervenes and Fake Crash is abducted instead.

===The Komodo Brothers===
'''Joe''' and '''Moe''', known collectively as '''The Komodo Brothers''', are a duo of anthropomorphized [[Komodo dragon]]s who dress in ancient [[Turkey|Turkish]]-like outfits and attack with [[scimitar]]s. They initially appeared as bosses in ''[[Crash Bandicoot 2: Cortex Strikes Back]]''.

Joe is the thinner brother, being the smartest and the fastest of them. Moe is the fatter one, and although he is not very smart, he is considerably stronger and more violent than Joe. Joe appears, alone, as a boss in ''[[Crash Team Racing]]''. The two Komodo Brothers then appeared together as bosses in ''[[Crash Bash]]''. Joe is voiced by David Anthony Pizzuto in the English-speaking version of ''Crash Team Racing'', and by [[Wataru Takagi]] in the Japanese version.

===Evil Crash===
'''Evil Crash''' is an evil and ferocious version of Crash Bandicoot from the Tenth Dimension. He first appeared in ''[[Crash Twinsanity]]'', acting firstly as a villain (kidnapping Nina Cortex and chasing Doctor Cortex), but ironically ends up a hero, devouring the Evil Twins. He has a cameo appearance in ''[[Crash Tag Team Racing]]'' as an alternate costume called Nega Crash.

Evil Crash has a cameo appearance in the &quot;Silhouette Quiz&quot; minigame in Crash Boom Bang!

===Bearminator===
The Bearminator is a [[polar bear]] who appears in ''[[Crash Bash]]'' as the second boss. He is the captain of a small submarine that fires cannonballs and mechanical polar bear cubs, which are armed with missiles on their backs. It is sometimes believed that the Bearminator appeared first in ''Crash Bandicoot 2: Cortex Strikes Back'', since he looks very similar to the polar bears that chase Crash in some levels in that game. He may have also appeared in ''Crash Team Racing'' as a large bear frozen in ice on the racetrack, Polar Pass.

===The Elementals===
'''The Elementals''', consisting of '''Rok-Ko the Earth Elemental''', '''Wa-Wa the Water Elemental''', '''Py-Ro the Fire Elemental''', and '''Lo-Lo the Air Elemental''', are a group of evil masks revived by Uka Uka in ''Crash Bandicoot: The Wrath of Cortex'' to act as a power source for Crunch Bandicoot. They were sealed away once more by the efforts of Crash and Coco Bandicoot. Rok-Ko was voiced by [[Thomas F. Wilson]] in the English version and by [[Toshiaki Kuwahara]] in the Japanese version. Wa-Wa was voiced by [[R. Lee Ermey]] in the English version and by [[Kappei Yamaguchi]] in the Japanese version. Py-Ro was voiced by [[Mark Hamill]] in the English version and by [[Toshitaka Shimizu]] in the Japanese version. Lo-Lo was voiced by [[Jess Harnell]] in the English version and by [[Masaru Ikeda]] in the Japanese version.

===The Evil Twins===
'''Victor''' and '''Moritz''', known collectively as '''The Evil Twins''', are mutated [[parrot]]s who formerly belonged to Neo Cortex as a child. During Cortex's first experiments with the Evolvo-Ray, the parrots were accidentally sent to the Tenth Dimension,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite video game|title=Crash Twinsanity |developer=[[Traveller's Tales|Traveller's Tales Oxford]] |publisher=[[Vivendi Games|Vivendi Universal Games]] |date=September 28, 2004 |platform=Multiplatform |level=Academy of Evil |quote='''Doctor Neo Cortex:''' It was my first experiment with the Evolvo-Ray, Phase One in my plan of creating an army of superanimals! The main subjects: my two pet parrots, Victor and Moritz — the only two creatures I didn't loathe or eat. The experiment was proceeding as planned, when suddenly... my parrots were gone, lost amongst the infinite dimensions!}}&lt;/ref&gt; a gloomy and twisted [[mirror universe]] version of the [[Earth]]. The ultra-dimensional radiaction gave them [[psychokinesis|psychokinetic]] and [[reality warping|reality-warping]] powers.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite video game|title=Crash Twinsanity |developer=[[Traveller's Tales|Traveller's Tales Oxford]] |publisher=[[Vivendi Games|Vivendi Universal Games]] |date=September 28, 2004 |platform=Multiplatform |level=Twinsanity Island |quote='''Victor:''' The severe reverso-radioactive conditions here sharpened our skills and warped our fragile eggshell minds.}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In ''[[Crash Twinsanity]]'' they act as the main antagonists. The Twins leave their dimension in order to get their revenge on Cortex and destroy the Wumpa Islands. However, with the use of the Psychetron, Crash Bandicoot, Neo Cortex and Nina Cortex travel to the Tenth Dimension in order to stop the Twins' plans. They attack the trio with a mech, but fail. They flee, but are eaten by Crash Bandicoot's Tenth-Dimensional counterpart, [[#Evil Crash|Evil Crash]], soon after.

Victor is the most serious and sinister-looking of the duo, while Moritz serves as the duo's [[comic relief]], and is seen constantly asking for food. Their names derive from the fictional scientist Victor Moritz, a character of [[James Whale]]'s [[1931 in film|1931]] film ''[[Frankenstein (1931 film)|Frankenstein]]''.

Both of the Twins are voiced by [[Quinton Flynn]] in the [[English language|English-speaking]] version of ''[[Crash Twinsanity]]''; however, in the [[Japanese language|Japanese]] dub, Victor is voiced by [[Shinpachi Tsuji]] and Moritz is voiced by [[Setsuji Satō]].

===Madame Amberley===
'''Madame Amberley''' is the headmistress of the Academy of Evil, and the former teacher of Neo and Nina Cortex. She is a humongously [[obesity|obese]], [[monocle]]-wearing [[German language|German]]-accented woman who needs iron cables attached to her back to locomote, and has a letter &quot;A&quot; tattooed on her forehead, in a way similar as Neo and Nina do. She also has the ability of manipulating electricity.

In ''[[Crash Twinsanity]]'', she serves as the penultimate boss of that game. Cortex returns to his former school in order to fetch his niece, and meets Amberley at her [[pipe organ|organ]] room. After being mistaken for a [[barber]] by her,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite video game|title=Crash Twinsanity |developer=[[Traveller's Tales|Traveller's Tales Oxford]] |publisher=[[Vivendi Games|Vivendi Universal Games]] |date=September 28, 2004 |platform=Multiplatform |level=Academy of Evil |quote='''Madame Amberley:''' So, cry-baby Cortex is all grown-up. I see you have found employment as a barber.}}&lt;/ref&gt; he has a  emotional breakdown and decides to get his revenge for the constant verbal abuse he suffered from her during his student days, and, with the use of his [[raygun]], destroys the iron cables attached to Amberley's back, making her plummet into a green toxic substance. It is unknown if she survived the fall or not, since she only appeared in ''Twinsanity''.

She was voiced by [[Susan Silo]] in the [[English language|English]] dub of the game, and by [[Noriko Suzuki]] in the [[Japanese language|Japanese]] version.

===N. Trance===
'''N. Trance''' is a subordinate of Doctor Nefarious Tropy. He is an egg-like being who is the self-proclaimed Master of Hypnotism. He first appeared in ''Crash Bandicoot 2: N-Tranced'', in which he brainwashed Crash's comrades and forced them to battle Crash. In ''Crash Nitro Kart'', he brainwashes Polar, Pura and Dingodile into racing for his team. He is voiced by Tom Bourdon in the English version of ''Crash Nitro Kart'' and by [[Setsuji Satō]] in the Japanese version.

===Rilla Roo===
'''Rilla Roo''' is a hybrid of a [[gorilla]] and a [[kangaroo]]. His only appearance is as a playable character in ''Crash Bash''. Rilla Roo is voiced by [[Mitsuru Ogata]] in the Japanese version of ''Crash Bash''.

===Emperor Velo XXVII===
'''Emperor Velo XXVII''' is the organizer of the Galaxy Circuit. He appears as a hologram for much of ''Crash Nitro Kart'', and only appears in person for the final race against him. His true form, '''The Real Velo''', is exceedingly short, and is a playable character. Both forms are voiced by [[Steven Blum]] in the English version of ''Crash Nitro Kart''. Emperor Velo is voiced by [[Haruo Satō]] in the Japanese version, while the Real Velo is voiced by [[Kōki Miyata]].

===Krunk===
'''Krunk''' is the racing champion of his native Terra. He challenges Earth's racers on the grounds that Earth is a copy of his Terra. When he loses to Crash's team, he confesses that Terra actually copied Earth. Krunk is voiced by [[Marshall R. Teague]] in the English version of ''Crash Nitro Kart'', and by [[Kōsei Hirota]] in the Japanese version.

===Nash===
'''Nash''' is a cybernetic shark from the planet Barin, where he is the racing champion. He has been engineered to always move, never stopping to even sleep. He is finally put to sleep when Coco hacks into his helmet. Nash is voiced by [[Billy West]] in the English version of ''Crash Nitro Kart'', and by [[Mitsuaki Madono]] in the Japanese version.

===Norm===
'''Norm''' is a book-loving mime who can split into his original self and a larger version of himself. He is the racing champion of Fenomena, but when he loses he is punished by Velo, who suggested he needed &quot;new ways to motivate Norm, like taking his books away&quot;. The large Norm is voiced by [[André Sogliuzzo]] in the English dub.

===Geary===
'''Geary''' is an effeminate robot and the racing champion of Teknee. The pinnacle of robotics, he is punished by Velo upon losing to Earth's racers by being forced to clean the entirety of Velo's Coliseum. He is voiced by [[Paul Greenberg]] in the English version of ''Crash Nitro Kart'' and by [[Hiroshi Isawaki]] in the Japanese version.

===Zem===
'''Zem''' is a large, vulgar creature who races alongside Oxide. He is voiced by [[André Sogliuzzo]] in the English version of ''Crash Nitro Kart'' and by [[Yasuhiro Takato]] in the Japanese version.

===Zam===
'''Zam''' is a dog-like creature, assumably the pet of Zem,  who races alongside Oxide. He is voiced by [[Billy West]].

===Ebenezer Von Clutch===
'''Ebenezer Von Clutch''' is a German-accented [[cyborg]], owner of the amusement park MotorWorld. He appears in ''[[Crash Tag Team Racing]]'' (being also a playable character), asking Crash and his friends to find the Power Gems who keep the park up and running and his own Black Power Gem, his vital battery. He is also very fond of the [[Crash Bandicoot (series)|''Crash Bandicoot'' series]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite video game|title=Crash Tag Team Racing |developer=Radical Entertainment |publisher=Sierra Entertainment |platform=Multiplatform |level=Von Clutch Makes a Deal |quote='''Doctor Neo Cortex:''' What is the meaning of this?! Have you any idea with whom you are dealing? / '''Ebenezer Von Clutch:''' Ze vorld-renowned evil-doer Doctor Neo Perivinkle Cortex! I have all your games...}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In the English-speaking version of ''Crash Tag Team Racing'', he is voiced by [[Danny Mann]], while in the Japanese port he is voiced by [[Hiroshi Ōtake]].

===Pasadena O'Possum===
'''Pasadena O'Possum''' is, as her surname says, an anthropomorphized [[opossum]] girl who speaks with a [[hillbilly]] accent. She is an employee at Ebenezer Von Clutch's amusement park MotorWorld in ''[[Crash Tag Team Racing]]'', and as the game's plot follows on, she starts to develop a crush on Crash Bandicoot.

She is voiced by [[Shanelle Workman]] in the English-speaking dub of ''Crash Tag Team Racing'', and by Iho Matsukubo in the Japanese dub.

===Willie Wumpa Cheeks===
'''Willie Wumpa Cheeks''' is the mascot of Ebenezer Von Clutch's amusement park MotorWorld, and the producer of the Wumpa Whip drink in ''[[Crash Tag Team Racing]]''. He is an anthropomorphized Wumpa Fruit with a [[tap (valve)|tap]] for a nose, and he speaks mostly through [[limerick (poetry)|limericks]] and [[riddle]]s.

As the game's story develops, it is revealed that he stole Von Clutch's Black Power Gem, although it is never specified why he did it. As Crash and his friends are about to discover why he stole Von Clutch's Gem and where he hid it, Willie is liquefied by Neo Cortex and his allies.

Willie is voiced by [[Roger L. Jackson]] in the [[English language|English-speaking]] dub of ''[[Crash Tag Team Racing]]'', and by Masato Funaki in the [[Japanese language|Japanese]] dub.

===Chick and Stew===
'''Chick''' and '''Stew''' are a pair of veteran sportscasters who serve as the tutors of ''Crash Tag Team Racing''. Chick is the calmer of the two, while Stew is more tense, frequently changes his hairstyle, and has a frightening wife. In one of the gags, stew squashes Crash and kicks him away. Chick is voiced by [[Quinton Flynn]] in the English version and by [[Keiichi Takahashi]] in the Japanese version. Stew is voiced by [[Duane Shepard]] in the English version, and by [[Keiji Himeno]] in the Japanese version.

Chick and Stew's personalities are based on [[Howard Cosell]] and [[George Foreman]], respectively.

====Reception====
Reception of Chick and Stew was generally positive. [[Alex Navarro]] of [[GameSpot]] described the &quot;woefully underutilized&quot; pair as &quot;great fun&quot;, and compared the two to [[Howard Cosell]] and [[Charles Barkley]] respectively.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | author=[[Alex Navarro]] | title=''Crash Tag Team Racing'' Review for PlayStation 2 | url=http://www.gamespot.com/ps2/driving/crashtagteamracing/review.html | publisher=[[GameSpot]] | date=October 27, 2005 | accessdate=June 3, 2009 |quote=Bits of the henchmen dialogue in particular is great fun, as are the woefully underutilized pair of chicken commentators, who sound like send-ups of Howard Cosell and Charles Barkley.}}&lt;/ref&gt; Cole and Vaughn of [[Cheat Code Central]], also comparing Chick to Howard Cosell, said that the two not only &quot;provide some entertaining dialogue but they also explain how to play the game which is often overlooked in many of todays kids games.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | author=Cole and Vaughn | title=''Crash Tag Team Racing'' Review / Preview for Xbox (XB) | url=http://cheatcc.com/xb/rev/crashtagteamracing.html | publisher=[[Cheat Code Central]] | accessdate=June 3, 2009 |quote=The game is littered with colorful characters and color commentary provided by a Howard Cossel sound-a-like chicken and his hip partner. Not only do they provide some entertaining dialogue but they also explain how to play the game which is often overlooked in many of todays kids games.}}&lt;/ref&gt; Rob Byron of [[AceGamez]] praised the commentators as &quot;a fantastic parody of the many commentary pairings that are synonymous with American televised sport. They add their own sharp wit and humour that has become a major selling point of the ''Crash'' series, as well as providing detailed in-game hints on the various controls of the game.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | author=Rob Byron | title=''Crash Tag Team Racing'' Microsoft Xbox Video Game Review by AceGamez |archiveurl = http://web.archive.org/web/20080529001933/http://www.acegamez.co.uk/reviews_xbox/Crash_Tag_Team_Racing_Xbox.htm | url=http://www.acegamez.co.uk/reviews_xbox/Crash_Tag_Team_Racing_Xbox.htm | publisher=[[AceGamez]] | archivedate=May 29, 2008 | accessdate=June 3, 2009 |quote=Two new additions are the commentators, a fantastic parody of the many commentary pairings that are synonymous with American televised sport. They add their own sharp wit and humour that has become a major selling point of the ''Crash'' series, as well as providing detailed in-game hints on the various controls of the game.}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Park Drones===
'''The Park Drones''' are the gas mask-wearing laborers of Von Clutch's MotorWorld. They sell Power Crystals and costumes to Crash Bandicoot and they have mini games. The English voices of the Park Drones are provided by [[Bill Farmer]], Chris Coppola, Charles Dennis, [[Jess Harnell]], and [[Roger L. Jackson]], while the Japanese voices are provided by [[Takaya Kuroda]], [[Kazuhiro Anzai]], [[Yasumichi Kushida]], [[Keiichi Takahashi]] and [[Masato Funaki]].

===The Viscount===
{{nihongo|The Viscount|ビスカント・デビル|Bisukanto Debiru}} is an extremely wealthy [[Tasmanian Devil]] who tricks Crash and his friends into searching for the Super Big Power Crystal for him in ''Crash Boom Bang!''.

===Yaya===
Yaya is a friendly [[Giant Panda]] who appears in ''Crash Bandicoot Nitro Kart 3D'' and &quot;Crash Bandicoot Nitro Kart 2. She teams up with Crash and Coco to help win the racing tournament Nitrous Oxide, Dr Neo Cortex and Ripper Roo have set up.

===Penta Penguin===
Penta Penguin is a [[penguin]] that makes three minor appearances in the Crash Bandicoot series. The first is in Crash Bandicoot 3: Warped, when he makes a brief appearance before the Dingodile boss fight. The second appearance is in ''Crash Team Racing'', where he is unlockable by a special code, and his third appearance is as a sleeping penguin in the center of a snow level, on ''Crash Bash''.

===Carbon Crash===
Carbon Crash is a playable character in [[Crash of The Titans]] and PlayStation 2 version of [[Crash: Mind over Mutant]]. White skin and green shirt version of [[Crash Bandicoot (character)|Crash Bandicoot]].

===Spyro the Dragon===
The main protagonist in the Spyro the Dragon series of video games, the sister series of the Crash Bandicoot games. Spyro is a small purple dragon who constantly saves the dragon realms from evil forces. Spyro had a cameo in [[Crash Twinsanity]], was playable in the GameBoy Advance version of [[Crash Nitro Kart]] and was the protagonist of [[Crash Bandicoot Purple: Ripto's Rampage and Spyro Orange: The Cortex Conspiracy|Spyro: Orange]], a game set in the Crash Bandicoot universe and featuring the Crash Bandicoot cast. Crash in turn appeared in [[Crash Bandicoot Purple: Ripto's Rampage and Spyro Orange: The Cortex Conspiracy|Crash: Purple]], a game set in Spyro's universe and featuring the Spyro cast. Crash has also had cameo appearances in 4 other Spyro games.

==Main series, racing, party and other appearances==
This table shows the major characters in the Crash Bandicoot series and which games from the main series they appeared in. All of these characters have appeared in numerous other Crash Bandicoot games such as the racing series and some relevant characters to the series have not been included on the table due to them exclusively appearing in such games. This table includes minor cameos as game appearances such as [[Tiny Tiger]]'s minor appearances in ''Twinsanity'' and ''Mind over Mutant''.      

{| class=&quot;wikitable sortable&quot; border=&quot;1&quot;
|-
! Character !! ''[[Crash Bandicoot (video game)|Crash Bandicoot]]'' !! ''[[Crash Bandicoot 2: Cortex Strikes Back|Cortex Strikes Back]]'' !! ''[[Crash Bandicoot 3: Warped|Warped]]'' !! ''[[Crash Team Racing|CTR]]'' !! ''[[Crash Bash|Bash]]'' !! ''[[Crash Bandicoot: The Wrath of Cortex|The Wrath of Cortex]]'' !! ''[[Crash Bandicoot: The Huge Adventure|XS]]'' !! ''[[Crash Bandicoot 2: N-Tranced|2: N-Tranced]]'' !! ''[[Crash Nitro Kart|CNK]]'' !! ''[[Crash Twinsanity|Twinsanity]]'' !! ''[[Crash Tag Team Racing|CTTR]]'' !! ''[[Crash Boom Bang!|CBB!]]'' !! ''[[Crash of the Titans|Titans]]'' !! ''[[Crash: Mind over Mutant|Mind Over Mutant]]''
|-
| Crash Bandicoot || {{yes}} || {{yes}} || {{yes}} || {{yes}} || {{yes}} || {{yes}} || {{yes}} || {{yes}} || {{yes}} || {{yes}} || {{yes}} || {{yes}} || {{yes}} || {{yes}}
|-
| Aku Aku || {{yes}} || {{yes}} || {{yes}} || {{yes}} || {{yes}} || {{yes}} || {{yes}} || {{yes}} || {{yes}} || {{yes}} || {{yes}} || {{yes}} || {{yes}} || {{yes}}
|-
| Doctor Neo Cortex || {{yes}} || {{yes}} || {{yes}} || {{yes}} || {{yes}} || {{yes}} || {{yes}} || {{no}} || {{yes}} || {{yes}} || {{yes}} || {{yes}} || {{yes}} || {{yes}}
|-
| Coco Bandicoot || {{no}} || {{yes}} || {{yes}} || {{yes}} || {{yes}} || {{yes}} || {{yes}} || {{yes}} || {{yes}} || {{yes}} || {{yes}} || {{yes}} || {{yes}} || {{yes}}
|-
| Doctor N. Gin || {{no}} || {{yes}} || {{yes}} || {{yes}} || {{yes}} || {{yes}} || {{yes}} || {{no}} || {{yes}} || {{yes}} || {{yes}} || {{yes}} || {{yes}} || {{yes}}
|-
| Tiny Tiger || {{no}} || {{yes}} || {{yes}} || {{yes}} || {{yes}} || {{yes}} || {{yes}} || {{no}} || {{yes}} || {{yes}} || {{no}} || {{yes}} || {{yes}} || {{no}}
|-
| Uka Uka || {{no}} || {{no}} || {{yes}} || {{yes}} || {{yes}} || {{yes}} || {{yes}} || {{yes}} || {{yes}} || {{yes}} || {{no}} || {{yes}} || {{yes}} || {{yes}}
|-
| Crunch Bandicoot || {{no}} || {{no}} || {{no}} || {{no}} || {{no}} || {{yes}} || {{no}} || {{yes}} || {{yes}} || {{yes}} || {{yes}} || {{yes}} || {{yes}} || {{yes}}
|-
| Nina Cortex || {{no}} || {{no}} || {{no}} || {{no}} || {{no}} || {{no}} || {{no}} || {{no}} || {{no}} || {{yes}} || {{yes}} || {{no}} || {{yes}} || {{yes}}
|-
| Doctor Nitrus Brio || {{yes}} || {{yes}} || {{no}} || {{no}} || {{yes}} || {{no}} || {{no}} || {{no}} || {{no}} || {{yes}} || {{no}} || {{no}} || {{no}} || {{yes}}
|-
| Doctor Nefarious Tropy  || {{no}} || {{no}} || {{yes}} || {{yes}} || {{no}} || {{yes}} || {{no}} || {{yes}} || {{yes}} || {{yes}} || {{no}} || {{yes}} || {{no}} || {{no}}
|-
| Dingodile || {{no}} || {{no}} || {{yes}} || {{yes}} || {{yes}} || {{yes}} || {{yes}} || {{no}} || {{yes}} || {{yes}} || {{no}} || {{no}} || {{Yes}} || {{no}}
|-
| Ripper Roo || {{yes}} || {{yes}} || {{no}} || {{yes}} || {{yes}} || {{no}} || {{no}} || {{no}} || {{no}} || {{yes}} || {{no}} || {{no}} || {{no}} || {{no}}
|-
| Polar || {{no}} || {{yes}} || {{yes}} || {{yes}} || {{yes}} || {{no}} || {{yes}} || {{no}} || {{yes}} || {{yes}} || {{no}} || {{yes}} || {{no}} || {{no}}
|-
| Pura || {{no}} || {{no}} || {{yes}} || {{yes}} || {{no}} || {{yes}} || {{no}} || {{no}} || {{yes}} (Consoles version only) || {{no}} || {{no}} || {{yes}} || {{no}} || {{no}}
|-
| Papu Papu || {{yes}} || {{no}} || {{no}} || {{yes}} || {{yes}} || {{no}} || {{no}} || {{no}} || {{no}} || {{yes}} || {{no}} || {{no}} || {{no}} || {{no}}
|-
| Tawna Bandicoot || {{yes}} || {{no}} || {{no}} || {{no}} || {{no}} || {{no}} || {{no}} || {{no}} || {{no}} || {{no}} || {{no}} || {{yes}} || {{no}} || {{no}}
|-
| Nitros Oxide || {{no}} || {{no}} || {{no}} || {{yes}} (Playable in Special Edition version only) || {{yes}} || {{yes}} || {{no}} || {{no}} || {{yes}} || {{yes}} || {{no}} || {{no}} || {{no}} || {{no}}
|-
| Pinstripe Potoroo || {{yes}} || {{no}} || {{no}} || {{yes}} || {{no}} || {{no}} || {{no}} || {{no}} || {{no}} || {{yes}} || {{no}} || {{yes}} || {{no}} || {{no}}
|-
| Komodo Bros. || {{no}} || {{yes}} || {{no}} || {{yes}} || {{yes}} || {{no}} || {{no}} || {{no}} || {{no}} || {{no}} || {{no}} || {{no}} || {{no}} || {{no}}
|-
| Koala Kong || {{yes}} || {{no}} || {{no}} || {{no}} || {{yes}} || {{no}} || {{no}} || {{no}} || {{no}} || {{yes}} || {{no}} || {{no}} || {{no}} || {{no}}
|-
| Fake Crash || {{no}} || {{no}} || {{yes}} || {{yes}} || {{yes}} (Playable in Japanese version only) || {{no}} || {{no}} || {{yes}} || {{yes}} || {{no}} || {{no}} || {{yes}} || {{no}} || {{no}}
|-
| Penta Penguin || {{no}} || {{yes}} || {{yes}} || {{yes}} (All 5/5 stats in Europe version only) || {{yes}} || {{no}} || {{no}} || {{no}} || {{no}} || {{no}} || {{no}} || {{no}} || {{no}} || {{no}}
|-
| N. Trance || {{no}} || {{no}} || {{no}} || {{no}} || {{no}} || {{no}} || {{no}} || {{yes}} || {{yes}} || {{no}} || {{no}} || {{no}} || {{no}} || {{no}}
|-
| Carbon Crash || {{no}} || {{no}} || {{no}} || {{no}} || {{no}} || {{no}} || {{no}} || {{no}} || {{no}} || {{no}} || {{no}} || {{no}} || {{yes}} || {{yes}} (Playable in PlayStation 2 version only)
|-
| Spyro the Dragon || {{no}} || {{no}} || {{no}} || {{no}} || {{no}} || {{no}} || {{no}} || {{no}} || {{yes}} (Playable in GameBoy Advance version only) || {{yes}} || {{no}} || {{no}} || {{no}} || {{no}}
|-
| Ebenezer Von Clutch || {{no}} || {{no}} || {{no}} || {{no}} || {{no}} || {{no}} || {{no}} || {{no}} || {{no}} || {{no}} || {{yes}} || {{no}} || {{no}} || {{no}}
|-
| Pasadena Possomun || {{no}} || {{no}} || {{no}} || {{no}} || {{no}} || {{no}} || {{no}} || {{no}} || {{no}} || {{no}} || {{yes}} || {{no}} || {{no}} || {{no}} 
|-
| Willie E. Wumpa || {{no}} || {{no}} || {{no}} || {{no}} || {{no}} || {{no}} || {{no}} || {{no}} || {{no}} || {{no}} || {{yes}} || {{no}} || {{no}} || {{no}} 
|-
| Evil Crash || {{no}} || {{no}} || {{no}} || {{no}} || {{no}} || {{no}} || {{no}} || {{no}} || {{no}} || {{yes}} || {{no}} || {{no}} || {{no}} || {{no}} 
|-
| Victor and Mortiz || {{no}} || {{no}} || {{no}} || {{no}} || {{no}} || {{no}} || {{no}} || {{no}} || {{no}} || {{yes}} || {{no}} || {{no}} || {{no}} || {{no}} 
|}

==References==
{{reflist|2}}

{{Crash Bandicoot series}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Characters Of Crash Bandicoot}}
[[Category:Crash Bandicoot]]
[[Category:Lists of video game characters|Crash Bandicoot]]
[[Category:Crash Bandicoot characters]]
[[Category:Fictional anthropomorphic characters]]

[[da:Figurer fra Crash Bandicoot]]
[[es:Anexo:Personajes de Crash Bandicoot]]
[[fr:Personnages de Crash Bandicoot]]
[[it:Nitros Oxide]]
[[pt:Anexo:Lista de personagens de Crash Bandicoot]]
[[ru:Список персонажей Crash Bandicoot]]
[[fi:Luettelo Crash Bandicoot -pelisarjan hahmoista]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
