<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="18854450" ns="0" title="Flip TV"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Infobox TV channel|
 name      = Flip TV|
 logofile  = FlipTV.jpg|
 logocaption = Flip TV logo|
 logosize  = 200px|
 launch    = March 28, 2007|
 owner     = Tri-Axis Entertainment Group Inc.|
 slogan    = |
 web       = |
 sat serv 1   = [[GV Broadcasting Systems, Inc.|GV Sat]]|
 sat chan 1   = Channel 1|
 cable serv 1 =|
 cable chan 1 =|
 cable serv 2 =|
 cable chan 2 =|
 cable serv 3 =|
 cable chan 3 =|
 cable serv 4 =|
 cable chan 4 =|
}}

'''Flip TV''' is a cable and satellite channel owned by Tri-Axis Entertainment Group, Inc. and launched on March 28, 2007, which broadcasts Filipino productions accessible from the Mabuhay Satellite. Flip TV's main office is located at Unit 1101 Atlanta Center Condominium, #33 Annapolis St., Greenhills, [[San Juan City]].

==Corporate Brief==
Tri-Axis Entertainment Group is a wholly owned Filipino corporation founded in January 2007 primarily established to provide cable television programming that features all-Filipino productions through its channel FLIP. FLIP’s first broadcast via satellite was on April of the same year.

==Current Shows==
===Flip TV Originals===
====Flip Jokes====

A filler that features upcoming Filipino comedians reenacting classic and fresh jokes. The show is being aired between TV series and movies.

CAST:

Julius Falco, Via , Erwin , Lei , Leo
====Pinoy Airsofter====

An extreme sport program that caters to war-game enthusiasts that features everything about Airsoft from various teams and game sites to guns and accessories.

HOST:

Abby Asistio
====Rock Republik====

A music oriented show focusing on the alternative side of the music industry. Rock Republik features upcoming Filipino bands.

HOST:

Yab
====Flip Dolls====

A show that reveals more than what men wanna see. Flip Dolls exposes everything that happens in a photo shoot, from set lighting to make-up preparations are shown.

====Washappenin====

A show featuring the latest events with hosts Pompi and Ced. Oh yes, what happens in washappennin, stays in washappennin.

====Movies====
* Flip Movies

====Other Shows====
* Musik Planet
* Gay Boxing ''(soon)''

===Flip TV Classics===
Note: Some of the programs are formerly aired on [[Radio Philippines Network|RPN 9]] and one from [[GMA Network|GMA]].

====Drama Series==== 
* [[Agila]] (soon) 
* Anna Luna
* Bisperas ng Kasaysayan
* Boracay
* Cebu 
* [[Coney Reyes on Camera]] (soon) 
* Davao, Ang Gintong Pag-Asa
* De Buena Familia
* [[Heredero]] 
* [[Lovingly Yours, Helen]]
* Mommy ko si Tita
* [[Valiente]] (soon) 
* Young Love, Sweet Love

====Comedy Series====
* ATM 
* Barangay Unang Sigaw
* Buddy en Sol
* Champoy
* D'on po sa Amin
* Gabi ni Dolphy
* [[John En Marsha]]
* Puruntong
* Ready na Direk

====Lifestyle &amp; Travel====
* Better Home Ideas
* Road Trip

==See also==
* [[List of Philippine television shows]]
{{programs}}
{{Philippine cable channels}}

{{GFDLlegacy|sourcepath=http://en.wikipilipinas.org/index.php?title=Flip_TV|revision=231815345|source=WikiPilipinas|sourcearticle=Flip TV}}

[[Category:Television channels and stations established in 2007]]
[[Category:Television in the Philippines]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
