<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="18880361" ns="0" title="Boston College Eagles men&#039;s ice hockey"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Infobox College Ice Hockey Team
|current=2011–12 Boston College Eagles men's ice hockey season
|team_name = Boston College Eagles ice hockey
|CurrentSeason = 2011-2012 Boston College Eagles men's ice hockey team
|image = BostonCollegeEagles.svg‎ 
|image_size = 175px
|university = Boston College
|conference = Hockey East
|conference_short = Hockey East
|division = 
|location = Chestnut Hill, Massachusetts
|coach = [[Jerry York]]
|coach_year = 18th
|coach_wins = 424
|coach_losses = 217
|coach_ties = 59&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.uscho.com/team/boston-college/mens-hockey/]&lt;/ref&gt;
|captains = Tommy Cross (C)&lt;br&gt;Paul Carey (A)&lt;br&gt;Barry Almeida (A)
|arena = [[Conte Forum|Kelley Rink (Conte Forum)]]
|capacity = 7,884
|color1 = Maroon	
|color2 = Gold
|fontcolor = F0E68C
|hex1 = 8B0000
|hex2 = F0E68C
|NCAAchampion = 1949, 2001, 2008, 2010
|NCAAfrozenfour = 1948, 1949, 1950, 1954, 1956, 1959, 1963, 1965, 1968, 1973, 1978, 1985, 1990, 1998, 1999, 2000, 2001, 2004, 2006, 2007, 2008, 2010
|NCAAtourneys = 1948, 1949, 1950, 1954, 1956, 1959, 1963, 1965, 1968, 1973, 1978, 1984, 1985, 1986, 1987, 1989, 1990, 1991, 1998, 1999, 2000, 2001, 2003, 2004, 2005, 2006, 2007, 2008, 2010, 2011
|conference_tournament = 1965, 1978, 1987, 1990, 1998, 1999, 2001, 2005, 2007, 2008, 2010, 2011
|conference_season = 1980, 1985, 1986, 1987, 1989, 1990, 1991, 2001, 2003, 2004, 2005, 2011
|mascot =  Baldwin the Eagle
|rivals = [[Boston University Terriers men's ice hockey|Boston University]]&lt;br&gt;[[Notre Dame Fighting Irish men's ice hockey|Notre Dame]]
|fight_song = [[For Boston]]
|uniform_image = HE-Uniform-BC.png
}}

The '''Boston College Eagles''' are a Division I college hockey program that represent [[Boston College]] in [[Chestnut Hill, Massachusetts]]. The team has competed in [[Hockey East]] since 1984, having previously played in the [[ECAC Hockey|ECAC]]. The Eagles have won four national championships and the most current coming in 2010. Home games have been played at [[Conte Forum|Kelley Rink]], named after legendary coach [[John Kelley (ice hockey)|John &quot;Snooks&quot; Kelley]], since 1988, having previously played at [[McHugh Forum]].  The Eagles are coached by [[Jerry York]], BC '67.

==Boston College Hockey History==
Boston College is among the top [[college hockey]] programs in the country.  Beginning with legendary coach [[John &quot;Snooks&quot; Kelley]], who led the Eagles to their first national championship in 1949, Boston College has established itself as a perennial powerhouse in both regular season and post-season play.  Former coach [[Len Ceglarski]] and current coach [[Jerry York]], both Boston College alums, continue to build upon the success began by Kelley.  Both York and Ceglarski have at least 500 career wins.  York to date has 889 career wins, which is second all-time only to [[Ron Mason]], and is first among all active coaches.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.uscho.com/stats/coach-alltime.php/gender,m.html&lt;/ref&gt;


To date, BC has won twelve conference tournament titles, including ten [[Hockey East]] titles, a conference record.   Their most recent triumph in 2011 came after beating [[Merrimack Warriors men's ice hockey|Merrimack]] 5-3 in the championship game, Merrimack's first appearance in the final. 
[[File:BC wins 2011 Beanpot.jpg|thumb|On ice celebrations after BC defeated Northeastern in the 2011 Beanpot final.]]

===The Beanpot===
BC also competes in the annual [[Beanpot (ice hockey)|Beanpot]] tournament with fellow [[Boston, Massachusetts|Boston]]-area schools [[Boston University Terriers men's ice hockey|Boston University]], [[Harvard_Crimson#Athletics|Harvard]], and [[Northeastern_Huskies#Men.27s_hockey|Northeastern]]. The Eagles have won sixteen Beanpots, their most recent being the 2011 tournament that saw the Eagles down Northeastern 7-6 in OT, with junior forward Jimmy Hayes netting the game-winner and sophomore [[Chris Kreider]] winning the tournament MVP.  BC has won the Beanpot in: 1954, 1956, 1957, 1959, 1961, 1963, 1964, 1965, 1976, 1983, 1994, 2001, 2004, 2008, 2010 and 2011.

===Post-Season and Frozen Four===
Boston College has made thirty NCAA tournament appearances, reaching the tournament's [[Frozen Four]] twenty-two times.

Under John &quot;Snooks&quot; Kelley, BC advanced to the NCAA tournament three straight years from 1948-1950 (when the field was only four teams), winning the National Championship in 1949 after defeating [[Dartmouth College|Dartmouth]] 4-3 in Colorado Springs, CO.

After Jerry York took over as head coach in 1994, the Eagles began to work their way back to the NCAA tournament, having not qualified since 1991, and not having been to a Frozen Four since 1990. In 1998, four years after York became head coach, the Eagles were back in the National Championship game, losing to the [[Michigan Wolverines]] in [[Boston]]. BC was back in the national championship game in 2000, facing the [[North Dakota Fighting Sioux]]. They lost the game 4-2, but returned the favor a year later in 2001, beating the Sioux 3-2 in overtime thanks to a  sensational [[Krystofer Kolanos|Krys Kolanos]] goal. This was the Eagles first National Championship since 1949.  The championship was all the more satisfying for BC as the Eagles defeated in the process the three teams that had eliminated them from the previous three tournaments ([[Michigan Wolverines]], [[Maine Black Bears]], [[North Dakota Fighting Sioux]]).  The 2001 National Championship team contained current [[National Hockey League|NHL]] standouts [[Brian Gionta]], [[Brooks Orpik]], and [[Chuck Kobasew]], 

The Eagles returned to the National Championship game in 2006, facing the [[Wisconsin Badgers]] in [[Milwaukee, WI]].  The Eagles lost 2-1. A [[Brian Boyle]] shot was denied by the post as time expired, securing the win for the Badgers. The Eagles made it back to the National Championship game in 2007, riding on the heels of a thirteen-game winning streak. However, they came up short again, losing a heart-breaker 3-1 to the [[Michigan State Spartans]].
[[File:1949-2001-2008 BC Championship Banners.jpg|thumb|BC's National Championship banners at Kelley Rink prior to the 2010 championship.]]

BC got back to the National Championship game in 2008, disposing of [[Minnesota Golden Gophers|Minnesota]], [[Miami RedHawks|Miami (OH)]], and North Dakota in the Frozen Four semifinals along the way. The [[2008 NCAA Men's Division I Ice Hockey Tournament|2008 Tournament]] marked the third year in a row that the Eagles ending Miami's season, beating the top seeded Red Hawks 4-3 in overtime thanks to an acrobatic goal by freshman Joe Whitney. In the National Championship game, the Eagles met the [[Notre Dame Fighting Irish]], who had upset Michigan in the other semifinal. The Eagles won the contest by a score of 4-1, behind an MVP performance by Nathan Gerbe. The defeat of the Irish by BC has added fuel to the growing rivalry between Boston College and [[University of Notre Dame|Notre Dame]], carrying over to the ice what has been being fought on the [[Gridiron football|gridiron]] for years between the two schools [[American football|football]] teams in the [[Holy War (Boston College vs. Notre Dame)|Holy War]].

After missing out on the [[2009 NCAA Men's Division I Ice Hockey Tournament|2009 Tournament]], BC returned in [[2010 NCAA Men's Division I Ice Hockey Tournament|2010]] as a number one seed.  The Eagles defeated [[Alaska Nanooks men's ice hockey|Alaska]] and [[Yale Bulldogs men's ice hockey|Yale]] in the Northeast Regional in [[Worcester, MA|Worcester]], earning them a berth in the Frozen Four to be played at [[Ford Field]] in [[Detroit]].  BC defeated Miami (OH) 7-1 in the national semifinal, the fourth time in five years that the Eagles ended the RedHawks' season in the NCAA Tournament.  BC would face Wisconsin in the championship, a rematch of the 2006 title game.  The Eagles avenged that loss by defeating the Badgers 5-0 behind a two goal effort from sophomore [[Cam Atkinson]] and an MVP performance by senior Ben Smith, who would be named the Frozen Four's Most Outstanding Player.  Junior John Muse became just the fourth goalie to record a shutout in a title game.  The game was played before a record crowd of 37,592, the largest to attend an indoor hockey game.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.uscho.com/recaps/20092010/m/04/10/bc-uw.php&lt;/ref&gt;  

Since 1998, the Eagles have qualified for the NCAA tournament twelve times, making it to nine Frozen Fours, seven National Championship games, and have won three national titles.

==Championships==
===National Championships===
{| class=&quot;wikitable sortable&quot; style=&quot;text-align: center;&quot;
! Year !! Champion !! Score !! Runner-up !! City !! Arena
|-
|[[1949 NCAA Men's Division I Ice Hockey Tournament|1949]]||Boston College||4&amp;ndash;3||Dartmouth||Colorado Springs, CO||Broadmoor Arena
|-
|[[2001 NCAA Men's Division I Ice Hockey Tournament|2001]]||Boston College||3&amp;ndash;2 (OT)||North Dakota||Albany, NY||Pepsi Arena
|-
|[[2008 NCAA Men's Division I Ice Hockey Tournament|2008]]||Boston College||4&amp;ndash;1||Notre Dame||Denver, CO||Pepsi Center
|-
|[[2010 NCAA Men's Division I Ice Hockey Tournament|2010]]||Boston College||5&amp;ndash;0||Wisconsin||Detroit, MI||Ford Field
|}

Runner-up in 1965, 1978, 1998, 2000, 2006, and 2007

===Hockey East Tournament Championships===
{| class=&quot;wikitable sortable&quot; style=&quot;text-align: center;&quot;
! Year !! Champion !! Score !! Runner-up !! Notes
|-
|1987||Boston College||4&amp;ndash;2||Maine||Hockey East Regular Season Champions
|-
|1990||Boston College||4&amp;ndash;3||Maine||Hockey East Regular Season Champions
|-
|1998||Boston College||3&amp;ndash;2||Maine||lost to Michigan in National Championship game
|-
|1999||Boston College||5&amp;ndash;4 (OT)||New Hampshire||lost to Maine in Frozen Four
|-
|2001||Boston College||5&amp;ndash;3||Providence||defeated North Dakota in National Championship game
|-
|2005||Boston College||3&amp;ndash;1||New Hampshire||Hockey East Regular Season Champions
|-
|2007||Boston College||5&amp;ndash;2||New Hampshire||lost to Michigan State in National Championship game
|-
|2008||Boston College||4&amp;ndash;0||Vermont||defeated Notre Dame in National Championship game
|-
|2010||Boston College||7&amp;ndash;6 (OT)||Maine|| defeated Wisconsin in National Championship game
|-
|2011||Boston College||5&amp;ndash;3||Merrimack|| Hockey East Regular Season Champions
|}

Runner-up in 1985, 1986, 1989, 2000, and 2006

===ECAC Tournament Championships===
{| class=&quot;wikitable sortable&quot; style=&quot;text-align: center;&quot;
! Year !! Champion !! Score !! Runner-up !! Notes
|-
|1965||Boston College||6&amp;ndash;2||Brown||lost to Michigan Tech in National Championship game
|-
|1978||Boston College||4&amp;ndash;2||Providence||lost to Boston University in National Championship game
|}

Runner-up in 1963, 1968, and 1973

===Beanpot Championships===
{| class=&quot;wikitable sortable&quot; style=&quot;text-align: center;&quot;
! Year !! Champion !! Score !! Runner-up !! Coach
|-
|1954||Boston College||4&amp;ndash;1||Harvard||[[John &quot;Snooks&quot; Kelley]]
|-
|1956||Boston College||4&amp;ndash;2||Harvard||John &quot;Snooks&quot; Kelley
|-
|1957||Boston College||5&amp;ndash;4 (OT)||Boston University||John &quot;Snooks&quot; Kelley
|-
|1959||Boston College||7&amp;ndash;4||Boston University||John &quot;Snooks&quot; Kelley
|-
|1961||Boston College||4&amp;ndash;2||Harvard||John &quot;Snooks&quot; Kelley
|-
|1963||Boston College||3&amp;ndash;1||Harvard||John &quot;Snooks&quot; Kelley
|-
|1964||Boston College||6&amp;ndash;5||Boston University||John &quot;Snooks&quot; Kelley
|-
|1965||Boston College||5&amp;ndash;4||Boston University||John &quot;Snooks&quot; Kelley
|-
|1976||Boston College||6&amp;ndash;3||Boston University||[[Len Ceglarski]]
|-
|1983||Boston College||8&amp;ndash;3||Northeastern||Len Ceglarski
|-
|1994||Boston College||2&amp;ndash;1 (OT)||Harvard||Steve Cedorchuck
|-
|2001||Boston College||5&amp;ndash;3||Boston University||[[Jerry York]]
|-
|2004||Boston College||2&amp;ndash;1 (OT)||Boston University||Jerry York
|-
|2008||Boston College||6&amp;ndash;5 (OT)||Harvard||Jerry York
|-
|2010||Boston College||4&amp;ndash;3||Boston University||Jerry York
|-
|2011||Boston College||7&amp;ndash;6 (OT)||Northeastern ||Jerry York

|}

Runner-up in 1955, 1970, 1973, 1979, 1980, 1981, 1982, 1986, 1991, 1995, 1997, 2000, 2003, 2006, and 2007

==Rivals==
===Boston University Terriers===
{{main|Green Line Rivalry}}

Boston College's chief and most hated rival is the [[Boston University Terriers]], separated by a mere four miles on Boston's [[Commonwealth Avenue]].&lt;ref name=&quot;collegehockeynews.com&quot;&gt;http://www.collegehockeynews.com/news/2006/02/08_college.php&lt;/ref&gt;  The rivalry is often referred to as the [[Green Line Rivalry]], as the [[MBTA]] Green Line is the principal mode of transportation between the two schools. BC-BU is considered one of the top rivalries in college sports as well as the number one rivalry in college hockey.&lt;ref name=&quot;collegehockeynews.com&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref&gt;http://media.www.miamistudent.net/media/storage/paper776/news/2006/11/10/Sports/Presenting.Nations.Top.10.Rivalries-2451882-page2.shtml&lt;/ref&gt; The schools regularly meet in Hockey East play three times each season. Besides meeting in conference play, the two schools often meet in the annual Beanpot tournament. Boston University has traditionally dominated the tournament. The Eagles beat the Terriers 3-2 in overtime during the semifinals of the 2011 tournament, the most recent meeting between the schools in the tournament.  
[[File:BC-BU Jan 22 2010.jpg|thumb|BC and BU before the start of a game at Kelley Rink on January 22, 2010.]]

The two schools have also met in NCAA tournament play.  In their most recent meeting, Boston College skated to a memorable 5-0 victory against the top seeded Terriers in the [[2006 NCAA Men's Division I Ice Hockey Tournament]] Northeast Regional Final.  The Eagles and Terriers have met once in the NCAA Tournament championship game in 1978, with BU winning 5-3 in [[Providence, Rhode Island|Providence, RI]].  BC and BU have combined for nine national championships.

Games between the two schools are also highlighted by the intensity of the two school's student sections, the BC Superfans and the BU Dog Pound.  The BU students often sing their infamous &quot;BC Sucks&quot; song while the Superfans often chant &quot;Safety School&quot;, &quot;Sucks to BU&quot;, or &quot;BC Rejects&quot; at their counterparts.

Boston University leads the all-time series 127-113-17.  In their most recent meeting on December 3, 2011, BC defeated BU 6-1 at [[Agganis Arena]] in Hockey East play.

Boston College and Boston University faced off in Hockey East play at [[Fenway Park]] on January 8, 2010.  The game was the first men's college hockey game played at Fenway Park, with a women's game between Northeastern and New Hampshire played earlier in the day.  BU edged BC for a 3-2 win.

===North Dakota Fighting Sioux===
Boston College has developed a national rivalry with the [[North Dakota Fighting Sioux]], a rivalry fueled by each teams post-season success. Boston College ended North Dakota's season in three straight [[Frozen Four]]s, most recently winning 6-1 in 2008 en route to a National Championship, while in the [[2005 NCAA Men's Division I Ice Hockey Tournament|2005 tournament]] the Sioux beat the Eagles in the East Regional finals, 6-3.

In [[2000 NCAA Men's Division I Ice Hockey Tournament|2000]], the Sioux triumphed over BC 4-2 in the National Championship game in [[Rhode Island]]. A year later, in [[2001 NCAA Men's Division I Ice Hockey Tournament|2001]], the Eagles and Sioux met again in [[Albany, NY|Albany]], this time with BC prevailing 3-2 in overtime.  In [[1963 NCAA Men's Division I Ice Hockey Tournament|1963]], the Sioux beat Boston College by a score of 8-2 in the National Semifinal game. Two years later in [[1965 NCAA Men's Division I Ice Hockey Tournament|1965]], Boston College defeated North Dakota 4-3 in the National Semifinal game. 

On October 10, 2007, the two teams squared off in a regular season match best remembered for the unusual circumstances in which the game ended.  Midway through the second period, the power went out at BC's Conte Forum.  When power was restored, the ice surface began to melt, leading to the game being called after two periods due to the hazardous playing conditions.  The game ended 0-0.&lt;ref&gt;http://hockeyeastonline.com/men/recaps08.php?mbc_ndk1.o19&lt;/ref&gt;

The Eagles and Sioux last meet in the championship game of the 2011 Ice Breaker Tournament at the [[Ralph Engelstad Arena]], with BC defeating North Dakota 6-2.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.hockeyeastonline.com/men/recaps12.php?mbc_ndk1.o08 BOSTON COLLEGE CAPTURES ICE BREAKER WITH 6-2 WIN OVER NORTH DAKOTA]&lt;/ref&gt;

===New Hampshire Wildcats===
The rivalry between Boston College and [[New Hampshire Wildcats|New Hampshire]] has grown in recent years due to the success of the two programs.  UNH leads the all-time Hockey East regular season series over BC.  The Eagles, however, hold a distinct advantage in Hockey East tournament play, holding an 8-3 record.  Most recently, in the 2009 Hockey East Tournament, UNH hosted BC in the quarterfinals on their home ice at the Whittemore Center.  UNH had the chance to end BC's season and their hopes of reaching the NCAA tournament to defend their national title.  BC won the best-of-three series 2-0.

During the 2007-2008 season, the Wildcats swept the season series and won the Hockey East regular season championship.  The two teams met in the semifinals of the Hockey East tournament, with the top-seeded and favored UNH squad jumping out to a 4-1 midway through the second period.  The Eagles mounted a comeback, however, and won the game 5-4 in triple overtime.

Both UNH and BC have also competed closely for the Hockey East regular season championship.  In the 2009-2010 season, the Wildcats cemented the title on the final weekend of the season, earning a 3-3 tie against the Eagles at the Whittemore Center in the penultimate game season after BC jumped out to a 3-0 lead.  In the 2010-2011 season, the regular season title was again decided on the final weekend, with the Eagles, sitting in second place, sweeping a home-and-home series against the Wildcats, earning their eleventh regular season championship.

===Notre Dame Fighting Irish===
{{main|Holy War on Ice}}

Boston College and Notre Dame first met on the ice in 1969, and have faced-off annually since 1994.  BC leads the all-time series 16-12-2, including beating the Irish in the [[2008 NCAA Division I Men's Ice Hockey Tournament|2008 National Championship game]], as the Eagles captured their third national title in a 4-1 victory.  The Irish have won five of the last six regular season meetings since 2003. Notre Dame won the most recent match-up in 2011, beating Boston College 3-2 in overtime in South Bend. 

The rivalry is commonly referred to as &quot;The Holy War on Ice,&quot; a take on the name of the football rivalry between the two schools.&lt;ref&gt;[http://insidehockey.com/holy-war-on-ice-continues Holy War on Ice Continues]&lt;/ref&gt;

==Awards and Honors==
{{col-begin}}
{{col-2}}
'''[[Hobey Baker Award|Hobey Baker Memorial Award]]'''
*[[Mike Mottau]], D: 2000
*[[David Emma]], F: 1991

'''[[Spencer Penrose Award]]'''
*[[Len Ceglarski]]: 1973, 1985
*[[John &quot;Snooks&quot; Kelley]]: 1959, 1972

'''USCHO Coach of the Year'''
*[[ Jerry York]]: 2010

'''USA Hockey National College Player of the Year'''
*[[Nathan Gerbe]], F: 2008
*Mike Mottau, D: 2000

'''NCAA Tournament Most Outstanding Player'''
*[[Ben Smith]], F: 2010
*Nathan Gerbe, F: 2008
*[[Chuck Kobasew]], F: 2001

'''Hockey East Coach of the Year'''
*Jerry York: 2003-04, 2010-2011
*Len Ceglarski: 1984-85

'''Hockey East Player of the Year'''
*[[Chris Collins (ice hockey)|Chris Collins]], F: 2005-06
*[[Patrick Eaves]], F: 2004-05
*[[Ben Eaves]], F: 2002-03 (Shared with [[Mike Ayers]], New Hampshire)
*[[Brian Gionta]], F: 2000-01
*[[Mike Mottau]], D: 1999-00 (Shared with [[Ty Conklin]], New Hampshire)
*David Emma, F: 1990-91
*[[Greg Brown (hockey player)|Greg Brown]], D: 1988-89, 1989-90
*[[Brian Leetch]], D: 1986-87
*Scott Harlow, F: 1985-86

'''ECAC Player of the Year'''
*[[Tom Mellor]], D: 1972-73
*[[Timothy Sheehy (ice hockey)|Tim Sheehy]], F: 1969-70
*[[John Cunniff]], F: 1964-65

'''Hockey East Rookie of the Year'''
*[[Chuck Kobasew]], F: 2000-01
*[[Brian Gionta]], F: 1997-98
*[[Marty Reasoner]], F: 1995-96
*[[Ian Moran]], D: 1991-92 (shared with Craig Darby, Providence)
*Brian Leetch, D: 1986-87
*[[Ken Hodge, Jr.]], F: 1984-85

'''ECAC Rookie of the Year'''
*[[Paul Skidmore]], G: 1975-76
*Tom Mellor, D: 1969-70
*John Cunniff, F: 1963-64

{{col-2}}
'''Hockey East Tournament MVP'''
*[[Cam Atkinson]], F: 2011
*Matt Lombardi, F: 2010
*Nathan Gerbe, F: 2008
*[[Brock Bradford]], F: 2007
*[[Brian Boyle]], F: 2005
*Chuck Kobasew, F: 2001
*[[Blake Bellefeuille]], F: 1999
*Marty Reasoner, F: 1998
*[[Scott LaGrand]], G: 1990
*Brian Leetch, D: 1987

'''AHCA First Team All-Americans'''
*2010-11: [[Brian Dumoulin]], D; [[Cam Atkinson]], F
*2007-08: Nathan Gerbe, F
*2006-07: Brian Boyle, F
*2005-06: Chris Collins, F; Peter Harold, D; [[Cory Schneider]], G
*2004-05: [[Andrew Alberts]], D; Patrick Eaves, F
*2003-04: Andrew Alberts, D; [[Tony Voce]], F
*2002-03: Ben Eaves, F
*2000-01: [[Bobby Allen]], D; Brian Gionta, F
*1999-00: [[Jeff Farkas]], F; Brian Gionta, F; Mike Mottau, D
*1998-99: Brian Gionta, F; Mike Mottau, D
*1997-98: Marty Reasoner, F
*1990-91: David Emma, F
*1989-90: [[Greg Brown (ice hockey)|Greg Brown]], D; David Emma, F; [[Steve Heinze]], F
*1988-89: Gred Brown, D
*1986-87: [[Craig Janney]], F; Brian Leetch, D
*1985-86: [[Scott Harlow]], F
*1979-80: Bill Army, F
*1978-79: [[Joe Mullen]], F
*1977-78: Joe Mullen, F
*1972-73: [[Tom Mellor]], D
*1969-70: [[Timothy Sheehy (ice hockey)|Tim Sheehy]], F
*1968-69: [[Paul Hurley]], D; Tim Sheehy, F
*1966-67: Jerry York, F
*1965-66: John Cunniff, F
*1964-65: John Cunniff, F
*1962-63: Jack Leetch, F
*1961-62: Bill Hogan, F
*1960-61: Red Martin, D
*1959-60: Red Martin, D
*1958-59: Joe Jangro, D
{{col-end}}

==Records==
*Current [[Montreal Canadiens|Montreal Canadien]] captain [[Brian Gionta]] is BC's all time leading goal-scorer, netting 123 goals in his college career.&lt;ref name=&quot;hockeydb.com&quot;&gt;http://www.hockeydb.com/ihdb/stats/display_players.php?tmi=4920&lt;/ref&gt;
*[[Mike Mottau]] is BC's all time assists leader, with 130 in his career at the Heights.&lt;ref name=&quot;hockeydb.com&quot; /&gt;
*[[David Emma]] is BC's all time leading scorer, with 239 points in his four years.&lt;ref name=&quot;hockeydb.com&quot; /&gt;
*[[Los Angeles Kings]] defenseman [[Rob Scuderi]] has played in the most games at BC, appearing in an Eagles uniform 168 times in his four year career at Boston College.&lt;ref name=&quot;hockeydb.com&quot; /&gt;
*[[Chuck Kobasew]] is tied for first place in the number of game-winning-goals scored in a season with ten in 2000-01.&lt;ref&gt;http://insidecollegehockey.com/6History/ncaarec_indoffseas.htm&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;small&gt;For more Boston College stats, visit [http://www.hockeydb.com/ihdb/stats/display_players.php?tmi=4920 Boston College on Internet Hockey Database.]&lt;/small&gt;
*On March 16, 1985, BC goalie Scott Gordon and Chris Terreri (playing with Providence College) both placed water bottles on the top of their nets. This would be the first time ever that goalies would place water bottles on the top of nets in a hockey game. &lt;ref&gt;Hockey’s Book of Firsts, p.12, James Duplacey, JG Press, ISBN 978-1-57215-037-9&lt;/ref&gt;

==Head Coaching Records==
{| cellpadding=&quot;1&quot; border=&quot;1&quot; cellspacing=&quot;0&quot; width=&quot;80%&quot;
!bgcolor=&quot;#8B0000&quot;| &lt;font color=#F0E68C&gt;Tenure
!bgcolor=&quot;#8B0000&quot;| &lt;font color=#F0E68C&gt;Coach
!bgcolor=&quot;#8B0000&quot;| &lt;font color=#F0E68C&gt;Years
!bgcolor=&quot;#8B0000&quot;| &lt;font color=#F0E68C&gt;Record
|- align=&quot;center&quot;
| 1917-1919 || Robert Fowler || 2 || 4-2
|- align=&quot;center&quot;
| 1919-1920 || Walter Falvey || 1 || 5-1-1
|- align=&quot;center&quot;
| 1920-1923 || Fred Rocque || 3 || 23-6-2
|- align=&quot;center&quot;
| 1923-1925 || Charles Foote || 2 || 12-13-3
|- align=&quot;center&quot;
| 1925-1927 || Fred Rocque || 2 || 9-10-1 (31-16-3)
|- align=&quot;center&quot;
| 1927-1929 || James Foley || 2 || 6-11-1 
|- align=&quot;center&quot;
| 1932-1942 || [[John Kelley (ice hockey)|John “Snooks” Kelley]] || 10 || 82-38-5 
|- align=&quot;center&quot;
| 1942-1943 || John Temple || 1 || 7-2
|- align=&quot;center&quot;
| 1945-1946 || Joseph Glavin || 1 || 1-2
|- align=&quot;center&quot;
| 1946-1972 || John “Snooks” Kelley || 25 || 404-195-9 (486-233-14)
|- align=&quot;center&quot;
| 1972-1992 || [[Len Ceglarski]] || 20 || 419-224-27
|- align=&quot;center&quot;
| 1992-1994 || Steve Cedorchuck || 2 || 24-40-10
|- align=&quot;center&quot;
| 1994-present || [[Jerry York]] || 18 || 424-217-59 
|}

==Current roster==
{{Boston College Eagles men's ice hockey roster}}
Eric Vargas F

==Current NHL Eagles==
&lt;small&gt;As of October 11, 2011&lt;/small&gt;
*[[Andrew Alberts]], D: [[Vancouver Canucks]]
*[[Cam Atkinson]], F: [[Columbus Blue Jackets]]
*[[Brian Boyle]], C: [[New York Rangers]]
*[[Scott Clemmensen]], G: [[Florida Panthers]]
*[[Patrick Eaves]], F: [[Detroit Red Wings]]
*[[Benn Ferriero]], C: [[San Jose Sharks]]
*[[Nathan Gerbe]], F: [[Buffalo Sabres]]
*[[Brian Gionta]], F: [[Montreal Canadiens]]
*[[Peter Harrold]], D: [[Los Angeles Kings]]
*[[Chuck Kobasew]], F: [[Colorado Avalanche]]
*[[Ben Lovejoy]], F: [[Pittsburgh Penguins]]
*[[Mike Mottau]], D: [[New York Islanders]]
*[[Ryan Murphy (ice hockey b. 1983)|Ryan Murphy]], F: [[Carolina Hurricanes]]
*[[Brooks Orpik]], D: Pittsburgh Penguins
*[[Marty Reasoner]], F: New York Islanders
*[[Cory Schneider]], G: Vancouver Canucks
*[[Rob Scuderi]], D: Los Angeles Kings
*[[Ryan Shannon]], F: [[Tampa Bay Lightning]]
*[[Ben Smith (ice hockey b. 1988)|Ben Smith]], F: [[Chicago Blackhawks]]

==See also==
*[[Boston College Eagles women's ice hockey]]

==References==
{{reflist|2}}

==External links==
*[http://bceagles.collegesports.com/sports/m-hockey/bc-m-hockey-body.html BC Men's Hockey Home Page]
*[http://www.uscho.com/m/boston-college-eagles/mens-college-hockey/team,bc.html BC Men's Hockey Page on USCHO]

{{Boston College}}
{{Boston College Eagles men's ice hockey}}
{{Hockey East}}
{{Newenglandsports}}

[[Category:Boston College Eagles men's ice hockey| ]]
[[Category:College men's ice hockey teams in the United States]]
[[Category:Ice hockey teams in Massachusetts]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
