<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="18938683" ns="0" title="GNU General Public License"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Redirect|GPL}}
{{For|the GPL license template for use on Wikipedia|Template:GPL}}

{{Infobox software license
| name         = GNU General Public License
| image        = [[File:GNU General Public License 3 Logo.svg|200px]]
| caption      = GNU GPLv3 Logo
| author       = [[Free Software Foundation]]
| version      = 3
| copyright    = Free Software Foundation, Inc.
| date         = June 29, 2007 &lt;br&gt;
| OSI approved = Yes&lt;ref name=&quot;osilicenselist&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url=http://opensource.org/licenses/alphabetical |title=Licenses by Name | Open Source Initiative |publisher=Open Source Initiative |accessdate=10 December 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt;
| Debian approved = Yes&lt;ref name=&quot;debianlicenses&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.debian.org/legal/licenses/ |title=Debian – License information |publisher=Software in the Public Interest, Inc. |accessdate=10 December 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt;
| copyfree        = No&lt;ref&gt;Copyfree [http://copyfree.org/rejected Rejected Licenses]&lt;/ref&gt;
| Free Software   = Yes&lt;ref name=&quot;fsflicenselist&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.fsf.org/licensing/licenses/index_html#GPLCompatibleLicenses |title=Licenses – Free Software Foundation |publisher=Free Software Foundation |accessdate=10 December 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt;
| copyleft        = Yes&lt;ref name=&quot;fsflicenselist&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;fsfcopyleft&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.fsf.org/licensing/essays/pragmatic.html |title=Copyleft: Pragmatic Idealism – Free Software Foundation |publisher=Free Software Foundation |accessdate=10 December 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt;
| linking         = No (except for linking GNU AGPLv3 with GNU GPLv3 – [[#Compatibility and multi-licensing|see section]])
| website         = [http://www.gnu.org/licenses/gpl.html www.gnu.org/licenses/gpl.html]
}}
The '''GNU General Public License''' ('''GNU GPL''' or simply '''GPL''') is the most widely used&lt;ref name=widelyused/&gt; [[free software license]], originally written by [[Richard Stallman]] for the [[GNU Project]].

The GPL is the first [[copyleft]] license for general use, which means that derived works can only be distributed under the same license terms. Under this philosophy, the GPL grants the recipients of a [[computer program]] the rights of the [[The Free Software Definition|free software definition]] and uses copyleft to ensure the freedoms are preserved, even when the work is changed or added to. This is in distinction to [[permissive free software licenses]], of which the [[BSD licenses]] are the standard examples.

The text of the GPL is not itself under the GPL. The license's copyright disallows modification of the license. Copying and distributing the license is allowed since the GPL requires recipients get &quot;a copy of this License along with the Program&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.gnu.org/copyleft/gpl.html |accessdate=21 July 2009 |title=The GNU General Public License Version 3 |publisher=[[Free Software Foundation]] |date=29 June 2007}}&lt;/ref&gt; According to the GPL FAQ, anyone can make a new license using a modified version of the GPL as long as he or she uses a different name for the license, does not mention &quot;GNU&quot;, and removes the preamble, though the preamble can be used in a modified license if permission to use it is obtained from the [[Free Software Foundation|Free Software Foundation (FSF)]].

{{TOC limit|limit=3}}

==History==
The GPL was written by Richard Stallman in 1989 for use with programs released as part of the GNU project. The original GPL was based on a unification of similar licenses used for early versions of [[GNU Emacs]], the [[GNU Debugger]] and the [[GNU Compiler Collection|GNU C Compiler]].&lt;ref name=&quot;history of gpl&quot;&gt;{{cite web | url=http://www.free-soft.org/gpl_history/ | title=The History of the GPL | accessdate=24 November 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; These licenses contained similar provisions to the modern GPL, but were specific to each program, rendering them incompatible, despite being the same license.&lt;ref name=&quot;gplv3conf&quot;&gt;{{cite web | url=http://fsfeurope.org/projects/gplv3/fisl-rms-transcript.en.html#before-gnu-gpl | first=Richard | last=Stallman | date=21 April 2006 | title=Presentation at the second international GPLv3 conference, held in Porto Alegre}}&lt;/ref&gt; Stallman's goal was to produce one license that could be used for any project, thus making it possible for many projects to share code.

As of August 2007, the GPL accounted for nearly 65% of the 43,442 [[free software]] projects listed on [[Freshmeat]],&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://freshmeat.net/stats/ |title=Freshmeat's statistics page}}&lt;/ref&gt; and {{As of|2006|alt=as of January 2006}}, about 68% of the projects listed on [[SourceForge.net]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.dwheeler.com/frozen/sourceforge-stats-20031110.html |title=SourceForge.net: Software Map |publisher=Dwheeler.com |date= |accessdate=17 November 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt; Similarly, a 2001 survey of [[Red Hat Linux]] 7.1 found that 50% of the source code was licensed under the GPL&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.dwheeler.com/sloc/redhat62-v1/redhat62sloc.html |title=Estimating GNU/Linux's Size |author=David A. Wheeler}}&lt;/ref&gt; and a 1997 survey of [[Ibiblio|MetaLab]], then the largest free software archive, showed that the GPL accounted for about half of the software licensed therein.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web| url=http://www.dwheeler.com/essays/gpl-compatible.html | title=Make Your Open Source Software GPL-Compatible. Or Else | author=[[David A. Wheeler]]}}&lt;/ref&gt; Prominent free software programs licensed under the GPL include the [[Linux kernel]] and the [[GNU Compiler Collection]] (GCC). Some other free software programs ([[MySQL]] is a prominent example) are [[multi-licensing|dual-licensed]] under multiple licenses, often with one of the licenses being the GPL.

It's believed that the [[copyleft]] provided by the GPL was crucial to the success of GNU/Linux, giving the programmers who contributed to it the assurance that their work would benefit the whole world and remain free, rather than being exploited by software companies that would not have to give anything back to the community.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
|url=http://www.dwheeler.com/blog/2006/09/01/#gpl-bsd |title=Why the GPL rocketed GNU/Linux to success |quote=So while the BSDs have lost energy every time a company gets involved, the GPL'ed programs gain every time a company gets involved.}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The second version of the license, version 2, was released in 1991. Over the following 15 years, members of the [[free software community|FOSS (Free and Open Source Software) community]] became concerned over problems in the GPLv2 license which allowed GPL-licensed software to be exploited in ways that were contrary to the intentions of the license.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url=http://gplv3.fsf.org/rms-why.html  | title=Why Upgrade to GPL Version 3 --GPLv3 | publisher=Fsf.org | accessdate=17 March 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; These problems included [[tivoization]] (the inclusion of GPL-licensed software in hardware that will refuse to run modified versions of its software); incompatibility issues like with the [[AGPL|Affero General Public License]] license; and patent deals between [[Microsoft]] and distributors of GNU/Linux which was viewed as an attempt to use patents as a weapon against the GNU/Linux community.

Version 3 was developed to attempt to address these concerns. It was officially released on 29 June 2007.&lt;ref name=&quot;gpl3launch&quot;&gt;{{cite web | url=http://www.fsf.org/news/gplv3_launched | title=FSF releases the GNU General Public License, version 3 — Free Software Foundation — working together for free software | publisher=Fsf.org | accessdate=15 January 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Versions==
===Version 1===
Version 1 of the GNU GPL,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url=http://www.gnu.org/licenses/old-licenses/gpl-1.0.html | title= GNU General Public License, version 1}}&lt;/ref&gt; released in February 1989, prevented what were then the two main ways that software distributors restricted the freedoms that define free software. The first problem was that distributors may publish [[binary file]]s only – executable, but not readable or modifiable by humans. To prevent this, GPLv1 said that any vendor distributing binaries must also make the machine-readable source code available under the same licensing terms (sections 3a and 3b of the license).

The second problem was the distributors might add additional restrictions, either by adding restrictions to the license, or by combining the software with other software which had other restrictions on its distribution. If this was done, then the union of the two sets of restrictions would apply to the combined work, thus unacceptable restrictions could be added. To prevent this, GPLv1 said that modified versions, as a whole, had to be distributed under the terms in GPLv1 (sections 2b and 4 of the license). Therefore, software distributed under the terms of GPLv1 could be combined with software under more permissive terms, as this would not change the terms under which the whole could be distributed, but software distributed under GPLv1 could not be combined with software distributed under a more restrictive license, as this would conflict with the requirement that the whole be distributable under the terms of GPLv1.

===Version 2===
According to Richard Stallman, the major change in GPLv2 was the &quot;Liberty or Death&quot; clause, as he calls it&amp;nbsp;— Section 7.&lt;ref name=&quot;gplv3conf&quot;/&gt; This section says that if somebody has restrictions imposed that ''prevent'' him or her from distributing GPL-covered software in a way that respects other users' freedom (for example, if a legal ruling states that he or she can only distribute the software in binary form), he or she cannot distribute it at all. The hope is, that this will make it less tempting for companies to use patent threats to require a fee from the free software developers.

By 1990, it was becoming apparent that a less restrictive license would be strategically useful for the C library and for software libraries that essentially did the job of existing proprietary ones;&lt;ref&gt;For the reasoning see [http://www.gnu.org/gnu/thegnuproject.html The GNU project].&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;!-- It would be nice to have the original page instead of this newer one --&gt; when version 2 of the GPL (GPLv2) was released in June 1991, therefore, a second license — the [[GNU Lesser General Public License|Library General Public License]] — was introduced at the same time and numbered with version 2 to show that both were complementary. The version numbers diverged in 1999 when version 2.1 of the LGPL was released, which renamed it the GNU Lesser General Public License to reflect its place in the philosophy.

=== Version 3 ===&lt;!-- This section is linked from [[Software patent]] --&gt;
[[image:Stallman GPLv3 launch MIT 060116.jpg|thumb|[[Richard Stallman]] at the launch of the first draft of the GNU GPLv3. MIT, Cambridge, Massachusetts, USA|right]]
In late 2005, the [[Free Software Foundation]] (FSF) announced work on version 3 of the GPL (GPLv3). On 16 January 2006, the first &quot;discussion draft&quot; of GPLv3 was published, and the public consultation began. The public consultation was originally planned for nine to fifteen months but finally stretched to eighteen months with four drafts being published. The official GPLv3 was released by FSF on 29 June 2007. GPLv3 was written by Richard Stallman, with legal counsel from [[Eben Moglen]] and [[Software Freedom Law Center]].&lt;ref name=&quot;fosdem2006stallman&quot;&gt;{{cite web | url=http://www.ifso.ie/documents/rms-gplv3-2006-02-25.html | first=Richard | second=Stallman | date=25 February 2006 | title=Presentation in [[Brussels]], [[Belgium]] – the first day of that year's [[FOSDEM]] conference.}}&lt;/ref&gt;

According to Stallman, the most important changes are in relation to [[Software patents and free software|software patents]], [[free software license]] compatibility, the definition of &quot;source code&quot;, and [[hardware restrictions]] on software modification (&quot;[[tivoization]]&quot;).&lt;ref name=&quot;fosdem2006stallman&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;FSMag-RMS-Interview&quot;&gt;[http://www.freesoftwaremagazine.com/articles/interview_with_richard_stallman Interview with Richard Stallman], Free Software Magazine, 23 January 2008.&lt;/ref&gt; Other changes relate to internationalization, how license violations are handled, and how additional permissions can be granted by the copyright holder.

Other notable changes include allowing authors to add certain conditions or requirements to their contributions. One of those new optional requirements, sometimes referred to as the Affero clause, is intended to fulfill a request regarding [[software as a service]]; adding this clause produces the [[GNU Affero General Public License]] version 3.

It also adds a provision that 'strips' DRM of its legal value, so people can break the DRM on GPL software without breaking laws like the [[DMCA]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.gnu.org/licenses/quick-guide-gplv3.html#neutralizing-laws-that-prohibit-free-software-but-not-forbidding-drm |title=A Quick Guide to GPLv3 - GNU Project - Free Software Foundation (FSF) |publisher=Free Software Foundation}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The public consultation process was coordinated by the Free Software Foundation with assistance from Software Freedom Law Center, [[Free Software Foundation Europe]],&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://fsfeurope.org/projects/gplv3/ |title=GPLv3: Drafting version 3 of the GNU General Public License |publisher=Free Software Foundation Europe}}&lt;/ref&gt; and other free software groups. Comments were collected from the public via the gplv3.fsf.org web portal.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://gplv3.fsf.org/comments/gplv3-draft-4.html |title=gplv3.fsf.org comments for discussion draft 4}}&lt;/ref&gt; That portal runs purpose-written software called [[stet (software)|stet]]. These comments were passed to four committees comprising approximately 130 people, including supporters and detractors of FSF's goals. Those committees researched the comments submitted by the public and passed their summaries to Stallman for a decision on what the license would do.

During the public consultation process, 962 comments were submitted for the first draft.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://gplv3.fsf.org/comments/gplv3-draft-1 |title=gplv3.fsf.org comments for draft 1|quote=Showing comments in file 'gplv3-draft-1' [...] found 962}}&lt;/ref&gt; By the end, a total of 2,636 comments had been submitted.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
|url=http://gplv3.fsf.org/comments/gplv3-draft-2.html |title=gplv3.fsf.org comments for draft 2 |quote=Showing comments in file 'gplv3-draft-1' [...] found 727 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://gplv3.fsf.org/comments/gplv3-draft-3 |title=gplv3.fsf.org comments for draft 3 |quote=Showing comments in file 'gplv3-draft-3' [...] found 649
}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://gplv3.fsf.org/comments/gplv3-draft-4.html |title=gplv3.fsf.org comments for draft 4 |quote=Showing comments in file 'gplv3-draft-4' [...] found 298}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The third draft was released on 28 March 2007.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url=http://gplv3.fsf.org/gpl3-dd3-guide | title=Guide to the third draft of GPLv3}}&lt;/ref&gt; This draft included language intended to prevent patent cross-licenses like the controversial [[Microsoft-Novell agreement|Microsoft-Novell patent agreement]] and restricts the anti-tivoization clauses to a legal definition of a &quot;User&quot; or &quot;consumer product&quot;. It also explicitly removed the section on &quot;Geographical Limitations&quot;, whose probable removal had been announced at the launch of the public consultation.

The fourth discussion draft,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url=http://gplv3.fsf.org/gpl-draft-2007-05-31.html | title=Final Discussion Draft | accessdate=4 June 2007}}&lt;/ref&gt; which was the last, was released on 31 May 2007. It introduced [[Apache License]] compatibility, clarified the role of outside contractors, and made an exception to avoid the perceived problems of a Microsoft–Novell style agreement, saying in section 11 paragraph 6 that

{{quote|You may not convey a covered work if you are a party to an arrangement with a third party that is in the business of distributing software, under which you make payment to the third party based on the extent of your activity of conveying the work, and under which the third party grants, to any of the parties who would receive the covered work from you, a discriminatory patent license [...]}}

This aims to make future such deals ineffective. The license is also meant to cause Microsoft to extend the patent licenses it grants to Novell customers for the use of GPLv3 software to ''all'' users of that GPLv3 software; this is possible only if Microsoft is legally a &quot;conveyor&quot; of the GPLv3 software.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url=http://gplv3.fsf.org/dd3-faq GPLv3 | title=GPL version 3 FAQ | accessdate=4 June 2007}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url=http://gplv3.fsf.org/gpl3-dd4-rationale.pdf | title=Fourth Discussion Draft Rationale | accessdate=4 June 2007}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Others, notably some high-profile developers of the [[Linux kernel]], commented to the mass media and made public statements about their objections to parts of discussion drafts 1 and 2.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url=http://lwn.net/Articles/200422/ | title=Kernel developers' position on GPLv3 | publisher=LWN.net | accessdate= 4 June 2007}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Terms and conditions==
The terms and conditions of the GPL must be made available to anybody receiving a copy of the work that has a GPL applied to it (&quot;the licensee&quot;). Any licensee who adheres to the terms and conditions is given permission to modify the work, as well as to copy and redistribute the work or any derivative version. The licensee is allowed to charge a fee for this service, or do this free of charge. This latter point distinguishes the GPL from software licenses that prohibit commercial redistribution. The FSF argues that free software should not place restrictions on commercial use,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.gnu.org/philosophy/selling.html|title=Selling Free Software|publisher=Free Software Foundation}}&lt;/ref&gt; and the GPL explicitly states that GPL works may be sold at any price.

The GPL additionally states that a distributor may not impose &quot;further restrictions on the rights granted by the GPL&quot;. This forbids activities such as distributing of the software under a non-disclosure agreement or contract. Distributors under the GPL also grant a license for any of their patents practiced by the software, to practice those patents in GPL software.

The fourth section for version 2 of the license and the seventh section of version 3 require that programs distributed as pre-compiled binaries are accompanied by a copy of the source code, a written offer to distribute the source code via the same mechanism as the pre-compiled binary, or the written offer to obtain the source code that you got when you received the pre-compiled binary under the GPL. The second section of version 2 and the fifth section of version 3 also require giving &quot;all recipients a copy of this License along with the Program&quot;. Version 3 of the license allows making the source code available in additional ways in fulfillment of the seventh section. These include downloading source code from an adjacent network server or by peer-to-peer transmission, provided that is how the compiled code was available and there are &quot;clear directions&quot; on where to find the source code.

===Copyleft===
{{Main|Copyleft}}
The distribution rights granted by the GPL for modified versions of the work are not unconditional. When someone distributes a GPL'd work plus his/her own modifications, the requirements for distributing the whole work cannot be any greater than the requirements that are in the GPL.

This requirement is known as copyleft. It earns its legal power from the use of [[copyright]] on software programs. Because a GPL work is copyrighted, a licensee has no right to redistribute it, not even in modified form (barring [[fair use]]), except under the terms of the license. One is only required to adhere to the terms of the GPL if one wishes to exercise rights normally restricted by copyright law, such as redistribution. Conversely, if one distributes copies of the work without abiding by the terms of the GPL (for instance, by keeping the source code secret), he or she can be [[lawsuit|sued]] by the original author under copyright law.

Copyleft thus uses copyright law to accomplish the opposite of its usual purpose: instead of imposing restrictions, it grants rights to other people, in a way that ensures the rights cannot subsequently be taken away. It also ensures that unlimited redistribution rights are not granted, should any legal flaw be found in the copyleft statement.{{Citation needed|date=September 2011}}

Many distributors of GPL'ed programs bundle the source code with the [[executable]]s. An alternative method of satisfying the copyleft is to provide a written offer to provide the source code on a physical medium (such as a CD) upon request. In practice, many GPL'ed programs are distributed over the [[Internet]], and the source code is made available over [[File Transfer Protocol|FTP]] or [[Hypertext Transfer Protocol|HTTP]]. For Internet distribution, this complies with the license.

Copyleft applies only when a person seeks to redistribute the program. One is allowed to make private modified versions, without any obligation to divulge the modifications as long as the modified software is not distributed to anyone else. Note that the copyleft applies only to the software and not to its output (unless that output is itself a derivative work of the program&lt;ref&gt;A counter example is the GPL'ed [[GNU Bison]]: the parsers it outputs ''do'' contain parts of itself and are therefore derivatives which would fall under the GPL, if it were not for a special exception granted by GNU Bison: {{cite web |title=Conditions for Using Bison |url=http://www.gnu.org/software/bison/manual/html_node/Conditions.html |accessdate=11 December 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt;). For example, a public web portal running a modified derivative of a GPL'ed [[content management system]] is not required to distribute its changes to the underlying software because its output is not a derivative.

==Licensing and contractual issues==
The GPL was designed as a [[license]], rather than a [[contract]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.gnu.org/philosophy/no-ip-ethos.html |title=Essay by Stallman explaining why a license is more suitable than a contract }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://fsfeurope.org/projects/gplv3/barcelona-moglen-transcript.en.html#q7-a-contract |title=Eben Moglen explaining why the GPL is a license and why it matters}}&lt;/ref&gt; In some [[Common Law]] jurisdictions, the legal distinction between a license and a contract is an important one: contracts are enforceable by [[contract law]], whereas licenses are enforced under [[copyright law]]. However, this distinction is not useful in the many jurisdictions where there are no differences between contracts and licenses, such as [[Civil law (legal system)|Civil Law]] systems.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | last = Guadamuz-Gonzalez | first = Andres | title = Viral contracts or unenforceable documents? Contractual validity of copyleft licenses | journal = European Intellectual Property Review | volume = 26 | issue = 8 | pages = 331–339 | year = 2004 | url = http://papers.ssrn.com/sol3/papers.cfm?abstract_id=569101}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Those who do not accept the GPL's terms and conditions do not have permission, under copyright law, to copy or distribute GPL licensed software or derivative works. However, if they do not redistribute the GPL'd program, they may still use the software within their organization however they like, and works (including programs) constructed by the use of the program are not required to be covered by this license.&lt;!-- including e.g. the right to use modified web servers on a public site without publishing source (in GPLv3 this can be restricted by a special clause) --&gt;

[[Allison Randal]] argued that the GPLv3 as a license is unnecessarily confusing for lay readers, and could be simplified while retaining the same conditions and legal force.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://radar.oreilly.com/archives/2007/05/gplv3_clarity_a.html |author=Allison Randal |title=GPLv3, Clarity and Simplicity }}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Copyright holders==
The text of the GPL is itself [[copyright]]ed, and the copyright is held by the Free Software Foundation. However, the FSF does not hold the copyright for a work released under the GPL, unless an author explicitly [[Copyright assignment|assigns copyrights]] to the FSF (which seldom happens except for programs that are part of the GNU project). Only the individual copyright holders have the authority to sue when a license violation takes place.

The FSF permits people to create new licenses based on the GPL, as long as the derived licenses do not use the GPL preamble without permission. This is discouraged, however, since such a license might be incompatible with the GPL.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.fsf.org/licensing/licenses/gpl-faq.html#ModifyGPL |title=GPL FAQ: Can I modify the GPL and make a modified license? }}&lt;/ref&gt; and causes a perceived [[license proliferation]].

Other licenses created by the GNU project include the [[GNU Lesser General Public License]] and the [[GNU Free Documentation License]].

==Linking and derived works==
===Libraries===
According to the [[Free Software Foundation|FSF]], &quot;The GPL does not require you to release your modified version, or any part of it. You are free to make modifications and use them privately, without ever releasing them.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.gnu.org/licenses/gpl-faq.html#GPLRequireSourcePostedPublic |title=GPL FAQ: Does the GPL require that source code of modified versions be posted to the public?}}&lt;/ref&gt; However if one releases a GPL-licensed entity to the public, there is an issue regarding linking: namely, if a proprietary program uses a GPL library, is the proprietary program in violation of the GPL?

This key dispute is whether or not non-GPL software can legally [[static linking|statically link]] or [[dynamic linking|dynamically link]] to GPL libraries. Different opinions exist on this issue. The GPL is clear in requiring that all [[derivative work]]s of code under the GPL must themselves be under the GPL. Ambiguity arises with regards to using GPL libraries, and bundling GPL software into a larger package (perhaps mixed into a binary via [[static linking]]). This is ultimately a question not of the GPL ''per se'', but of how copyright law defines [[derivative works]]. The following points of view exist:

====Point of view: dynamic and static linking violate GPL====
The [[Free Software Foundation]] (which holds the copyright of several notable GPL-licensed software products and of the license text itself) asserts that an executable which uses a dynamically linked library is indeed a derivative work. This does not however apply to separate programs communicating with one another.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url=http://www.gnu.org/licenses/gpl-faq.html | title=Frequently Asked Questions about the GNU Licenses - GNU Project - Free Software Foundation (FSF) | publisher=FSF | accessdate=15 March 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Free Software Foundation]] also created [[LGPL]] which is nearly identical to GPL, but with additional permission to allow linking for the purposes of &quot;using the library&quot;.

[[Richard Stallman]] and the FSF specifically encourage library-writers to license under the GPL so that proprietary programs cannot use the libraries, in an effort to protect the free-software world by giving it more tools than the proprietary world.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url=http://www.gnu.org/philosophy/why-not-lgpl.html | title=Why you shouldn't use the Lesser GPL for your next library – GNU Project – Free Software Foundation (FSF) | publisher=Gnu.org | accessdate=15 January 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===== Plug-ins =====

FSF differentiate on how the plug-in is being invoked. If the Plug-in is invoked through dynamic linkage and it performs function calls to the GPL program then it's most likely a derivative work.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url=http://www.gnu.org/licenses/gpl-faq.html#GPLPluginsInNF | title=Frequently Asked Questions about the GNU Licenses – GNU Project – Free Software Foundation (FSF) | publisher=Gnu.org | accessdate=15 January 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

====Point of view: static linking violates GPL but unclear as of dynamic linking====
Some people believe that while [[static linking]] produces derivative works, it is not clear whether an executable that dynamically links to a GPL code should be considered a derivative work (see [[Weak copyleft|Weak Copyleft]]). Linux author [[Linus Torvalds]] agrees that dynamic linking can create derived works but disagrees over the circumstances.&lt;ref&gt;Linus Torvalds, [http://lkml.org/lkml/2006/12/17/79 GPL only modules], ''linux-kernel'' mailing list (17 December 2006).&lt;/ref&gt;

A [[Novell]] lawyer has written that dynamic linking not being derivative &quot;makes sense&quot; but is not &quot;clear-cut&quot;, and that evidence for good-intentioned dynamic linking can be seen by the existence of proprietary Linux kernel drivers.&lt;ref&gt;Matt Asay, [http://www.novell.com/coolsolutions/feature/1532.html The GPL: Understanding the License that Governs Linux], ''Novell Cool Solutions Feature'' (16 Jan. 2004).&lt;/ref&gt;

In ''[[Galoob v. Nintendo]]'' the United States [[Ninth Circuit Court of Appeals]] defined a derivative work as having &quot;'form' or permanence&quot; and noted that &quot;the infringing work must incorporate a portion of the copyrighted work in some form&quot;,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite court |litigants=Lewis Galoob Toys, Inc. v. Nintendo of America, Inc. |vol=964 |reporter=F.2d |opinion=965 |pinpoint=¶10 |court=9th Cir. |date=21 May 1992 |url=http://law.justia.com/cases/federal/appellate-courts/F2/964/965/341457/|quote=}}&lt;/ref&gt; but there have been no clear court decisions to resolve this particular conflict.

====Point of view: linking is irrelevant====
According to an article in the [[Linux Journal]], [[Lawrence Rosen]] ([[intellectual property|IP law]] specialist, and [[Open Source Initiative|OSI]] general counsel) argues that the method of linking is mostly irrelevant to the question about whether a piece of software is a [[derivative work]]; more important is the question about whether the software was intended to interface with client software and/or libraries.&lt;ref name=Rosen&gt;Lawrence Rosen, [http://www.linuxjournal.com/article/6366], ''Linux Journal'' (1 January 2003).&lt;/ref&gt;
He states, &quot;The primary indication of whether a new program is a derivative work is whether the source code of the original program was used [in a copy-paste sense], modified, translated or otherwise changed in any way to create the new program. If not, then I would argue that it is not a derivative work,&quot;&lt;ref name=Rosen /&gt; and lists numerous other points regarding intent, bundling, and linkage mechanism.
He further argues on his firm's website&lt;ref&gt;Lawrence Rosen, [http://www.rosenlaw.com/lj19.htm Derivative Works], ''rosenlaw.com'' (25 May 2004)&lt;/ref&gt; that such &quot;market-based&quot; factors are more important than the linking technique.

There is also the specific issue of whether a [[Plug-in (computing)|plugin]] or [[module]] (such as the [[NVidia]] or [[ATI]] [[graphics card]] [[kernel module]]s) must also be GPL, if it could reasonably be considered its own work. This point of view suggests that reasonably-separate plugins, or plugins for software designed to use plugins, could be licensed under an arbitrary license if the work is GPLv2. Of particular interest is the GPLv2 paragraph:

{{quote|
You may modify your copy or copies of the Program or any portion of it, thus forming a work based on the Program, and copy and distribute such modifications or work under the terms of Section 1 above, provided that you also meet all of these conditions:

...

b) You must cause any work that you distribute or publish, that in whole or in part contains or is derived from the Program or any part thereof, to be licensed as a whole at no charge to all third parties under the terms of this License.

...

These requirements apply to the modified work as a whole. If identifiable sections of that work are not derived from the Program, and can be reasonably considered independent and separate works in themselves, then this License, and its terms, do not apply to those sections when you distribute them as separate works. But when you distribute the same sections as part of a whole which is a work based on the Program, the distribution of the whole must be on the terms of this License, whose permissions for other licensees extend to the entire whole, and thus to each and every part regardless of who wrote it.
}}

It should be noted that the GPLv3 has a different clause:
{{quote|
You may convey a work based on the Program, or the modifications to produce it from the Program, in the form of source code under the terms of section 4, provided that you also meet all of these conditions:
c) You must license the entire work, as a whole, under this License to anyone who comes into possession of a copy. This License will therefore apply, along with any applicable section 7 additional terms, to the whole of the work, and all its parts, regardless of how they are packaged. This License gives no permission to license the work in any other way, but it does not invalidate such permission if you have separately received it.

...

A compilation of a covered work with other separate and independent works, which are not by their nature extensions of the covered work, and which are not combined with it such as to form a larger program, in or on a volume of a storage or distribution medium, is called an “aggregate” if the compilation and its resulting copyright are not used to limit the access or legal rights of the compilation's users beyond what the individual works permit. Inclusion of a covered work in an aggregate does not cause this License to apply to the other parts of the aggregate.
}}

As a case study, some supposedly proprietary [[plugins]] and [[theme (computing)|theme]]s/[[skin (computing)|skin]]s for GPLv2 [[Content management system|CMS]] software such as [[Drupal]] and [[WordPress]] have come under fire, with both sides of the argument taken.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url=http://www.webmaster-source.com/2009/01/29/why-theyre-wrong-wordpress-plugins-shouldnt-have-to-be-gpl/ | title=Why They’re Wrong: WordPress Plugins Shouldn’t Have to be GPL | publisher=Webmaster-source.com | date=29 January 2009 | accessdate=15 January 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url=http://drupal.org/licensing/faq#q7 | title=Licensing FAQ | publisher=Drupal.org | accessdate=15 January 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Communicating and bundling with non-GPL programs===
The mere act of communicating with other programs does not, by itself, require all software to be GPL; nor does distributing GPL software with non-GPL software. However, minor conditions must be followed that ensures the rights of GPL software is not restricted. The following is a quote from the [[gnu.org]] GPL [[FAQ]], which describes to what extent software is allowed communicate with and be-bundled-with GPL programs:

{{quote|
'''What is the difference between an “aggregate” and other kinds of “modified versions”?''

An “aggregate” consists of a number of separate programs, distributed together on the same CD-ROM or other media. The GPL permits you to create and distribute an aggregate, even when the licenses of the other software are non-free or GPL-incompatible. The only condition is that you cannot release the aggregate under a license that prohibits users from exercising rights that each program's individual license would grant them.

Where's the line between two separate programs, and one program with two parts? This is a legal question, which ultimately judges will decide. We believe that a proper criterion depends both on the mechanism of communication (exec, pipes, rpc, function calls within a shared address space, etc.) and the semantics of the communication (what kinds of information are interchanged).

If the modules are included in the same executable file, they are definitely combined in one program. If modules are designed to run linked together in a shared address space, that almost surely means combining them into one program.

By contrast, pipes, sockets and command-line arguments are communication mechanisms normally used between two separate programs. So when they are used for communication, the modules normally are separate programs. But if the semantics of the communication are intimate enough, exchanging complex internal data structures, that too could be a basis to consider the two parts as combined into a larger program.
}}

The FSF thus draws the line between &quot;library&quot; and &quot;other program&quot; via 1) &quot;complexity&quot; and &quot;intimacy&quot; of information exchange, and 2) mechanism (rather than semantics), but resigns that the question is not clear-cut and that in complex situations, case law will need to decide.

==The GPL in court==
In 2002, [[MySQL AB]] sued Progress NuSphere for copyright and trademark infringement in [[U.S. District Court for the District of Massachusetts|United States district court]]. NuSphere had allegedly violated MySQL's copyright by linking MySQL's GPL'ed code with NuSphere Gemini table without being in compliance with the license. After a preliminary hearing before Judge Patti Saris on 27 February 2002, the parties entered settlement talks and eventually settled.&lt;ref&gt;See ''Progress Software Corporation v. MySQL AB'', 195 F. Supp. 2d 328 (D. Mass. 2002), on defendant's motion for preliminary injunction.&lt;/ref&gt; After the hearing, FSF commented that &quot;Judge Saris made clear that she sees the GNU GPL to be an enforceable and binding license.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url=http://www.gnu.org/press/2002-03-01-pi-MySQL.html | title=Judge Saris defers GNU GPL Questions for Trial in MySQL vs. Progress Software | publisher=gnu.org | accessdate=24 March 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In August 2003, the [[SCO Group]] stated that they believed the GPL to have no legal validity, and that they intended to take up lawsuits over sections of code supposedly copied from SCO Unix into the [[Linux kernel]]. This was a problematic stand for them, as they had distributed GNU/Linux and other GPL'ed code in their [[Caldera OpenLinux]] distribution, and there is little evidence that they had any legal right to do so except under the terms of the GPL. For more information, see [[SCO-Linux controversies]] and [[SCO v. IBM]].

In April 2004, the [[netfilter/iptables]] project was granted a preliminary [[injunction]] against Sitecom Germany by [[Munich]] District Court after Sitecom refused to desist from distributing Netfilter's GPL'ed software in violation of the terms of the GPL. On July 2004, the German court confirmed this injunction as a final ruling against Sitecom.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.groklaw.net/article.php?story=20040725150736471 Harald Welte vs. Sitecom, final order, translated from German by Jens Maurer]&lt;/ref&gt; The court's justification was that:

:Defendant has infringed on the copyright of plaintiff by offering the software 'netfilter/iptables' for download and by advertising its distribution, without adhering to the license conditions of the GPL. Said actions would only be permissible if defendant had a license grant... This is independent of the questions whether the licensing conditions of the GPL have been effectively agreed upon between plaintiff and defendant or not. If the GPL were not agreed upon by the parties, defendant would notwithstanding lack the necessary rights to copy, distribute, and make the software 'netfilter/iptables' publicly available.

[[Harald Welte]] was represented by [[ifrOSS]] co-founder Till Jaeger. This exactly mirrored the predictions given previously by the FSF's [[Eben Moglen]]. This ruling was important because it was the first time that a court had confirmed that violating terms of the GPL could effect copyright violation.

In May 2005, Daniel Wallace [[Wallace v. International Business Machines Corp. et al.|filed suit]] against the Free Software Foundation in the [[U.S. District Court for the Southern District of Indiana|Southern District of Indiana]], contending that the GPL is an illegal attempt to fix prices (at zero). The suit was dismissed in March 2006, on the grounds that Wallace had failed to state a valid anti-trust claim; the court noted that &quot;the GPL encourages, rather than discourages, free competition and the distribution of computer operating systems, the benefits of which directly pass to consumers&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;groklawwallacevsfsfdismiss&quot;&gt;[http://www.groklaw.net/pdf/WallaceFSFGrantingDismiss.pdf Dismissal] of Wallace v. FSF. From [http://www.groklaw.net/article.php?story=20060320201540127 this article] on Groklaw.&lt;/ref&gt; Wallace was denied the possibility of further amending his complaint, and was ordered to pay the FSF's legal expenses.

On 8 September 2005, the Seoul Central District Court ruled that the GPL was not material to a case dealing with [[trade secret]]s derived from GPL-licensed work.&lt;ref&gt;[http://web.archive.org/web/20071018211119/http://korea.gnu.org/gv/sentence.html Seoul Central District Court ruling (?) (in Korean)]&lt;/ref&gt; Defendants argued that since it is impossible to maintain trade secrets while being compliant with GPL and distributing the work, they are not in breach of trade secrets. This argument was considered without ground.

On 6 September 2006, the [[gpl-violations.org]] project prevailed in court litigation against [[D-Link]] Germany GmbH regarding D-Link's copyright infringing use of parts of the [[Linux Kernel]] in [[Network-attached storage|storage]] devices they distributed.&lt;ref&gt;[http://gpl-violations.org/news/20060922-dlink-judgement_frankfurt.html gpl-violations.org project prevails in court case on GPL violation by D-Link]&lt;/ref&gt; The judgment provided legal precedent that the GPL is valid, legally binding, and stands in German court.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.jbb.de/urteil_lg_muenchen_gpl.pdf D-Link Judgement] {{de icon}} {{Dead link|date=August 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In late 2007, the [[BusyBox]] developers and the [[Software Freedom Law Center]] embarked upon a program to gain GPL compliance from distributors of BusyBox in [[embedded system]]s, suing those who would not comply. These were claimed to be the first US uses of courts for enforcement of GPL obligations. ''See'' [[BusyBox#GPL lawsuits|BusyBox GPL lawsuits]].

On 11 December 2008, the Free Software Foundation [[Free Software Foundation v. Cisco Systems|sued Cisco Systems, Inc.]] for copyright violations by its Linksys division, of the FSF's GPL-licensed [[coreutils]], [[readline]], [[Parted]], [[Wget]], [[GNU Compiler Collection]], [[binutils]], and [[GNU Debugger]] software packages, which Linksys distributes in the GNU/Linux firmware of its popular WRT54G wireless routers, as well as numerous other devices including DSL and Cable modems, Network Attached Storage devices, Voice-Over-IP gateways, Virtual Private Network devices and a home theater/media player device.&lt;ref name=&quot;FSF-Cisco&quot;&gt;{{cite press release |title=Free Software Foundation Files Suit Against Cisco For GPL Violations|publisher=Free Software Foundation |date=11 December 2008 |url=https://www.fsf.org/news/2008-12-cisco-suit |accessdate=22 August 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

After six years of repeated complaints to Cisco by the FSF, claims by Cisco that they would correct, or were correcting, their compliance problems (not providing complete copies of all source code and their modifications), of repeated new violations being discovered and reported with more products, and lots of talk but little action by Linksys (a process described on the FSF blog as a &quot;five-years-running game of Whack-a-Mole&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;FSF-Cisco&quot;/&gt;) the FSF finally took them to court.

Cisco settled the case six months later by agreeing &quot;to appoint a Free Software Director for Linksys&quot; to ensure compliance, &quot;to notify previous recipients of Linksys products containing FSF programs of their rights under the GPL,&quot; to make source code of FSF programs freely available on its website, and to make a monetary contribution to the FSF.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite press release |url= https://www.fsf.org/news/2009-05-cisco-settlement.html |title=FSF Settles Suit Against Cisco |publisher=Free Software Foundation |date=20 May 2009 |accessdate=22 August 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Compatibility and multi-licensing==
[[Image:Quick-guide-gplv3-compatibility.svg|350px|thumb|Quick Guide of license compatibility with GPL]]

Code licensed under several other licenses can be combined with a program under the GPL without conflict, as long as the combination of restrictions on the work as a whole does not put any additional restrictions beyond what GPL allows.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.gnu.org/licenses/gpl.html |title=The GNU General Public License v3.0 - GNU Project - Free Software Foundation (FSF) |publisher=fsf.org |accessdate=24 March 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; In addition to the regular terms of the GPL, there are additional restrictions and permissions one can apply:

# if you want to combine code licensed under different versions of GPL, then this is allowed if the code with the older GPL version includes an &quot;any later version&quot; statement.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web| url=http://www.gnu.org/licenses/gpl-faq.html#v2v3Compatibility| title=Frequently Asked Questions about the GNU Licenses – Is GPLv3 compatible with GPLv2?| publisher=The official site| accessdate=13 April 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;
# Code licensed under [[LGPL]] can be linked with any other code no matter what license that code has.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.gnu.org/licenses/old-licenses/lgpl-2.1.html#SEC2 |title=GNU Lesser General Public License v2.1 - GNU Project - Free Software Foundation (FSF) |publisher=fsf.org |accessdate=26 April 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; Code licensed under LGPLv2 without the &quot;any later version&quot; statement can be relicensed if the whole combined work is licensed to GPLv2 or GPLv3.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web| url=http://www.gnu.org/licenses/gpl-faq.html#AllCompatibility| title=Frequently Asked Questions about the GNU Licenses – How are the various GNU licenses compatible with each other?| publisher=The official site| accessdate=13 April 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

FSF maintains a list of GPL-[[License compatibility|compatible]] free software licenses&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.gnu.org/licenses/gpl-faq.html#WhatIsCompatible |title=Frequently Asked Questions about the GNU Licenses – What does it mean to say that two licenses are &quot;compatible&quot;? |publisher=FSF |accessdate=14 April 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.gnu.org/licenses/gpl-faq.html#WhatDoesCompatMean |title=Frequently Asked Questions about the GNU Licenses – What does it mean to say a license is &quot;compatible with the GPL?&quot; |publisher=FSF |accessdate=14 April 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.gnu.org/licenses/license-list.html#GPLCompatibleLicenses |title=Various Licenses and Comments about Them – GPL-Compatible Free Software Licenses |publisher=FSF |accessdate=14 April 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; with many of the most common free software licenses, such as the original [[MIT License|MIT/X license]], the [[BSD license]] (in its current 3-clause form) and the [[Artistic License]] 2.0.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.blackducksoftware.com/oss/licenses/ |title=Black Duck Open Source Resource Center |publisher=blackducksoftware.com |accessdate=26 April 2011 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[David A. Wheeler]] has advocated that free/open source software developers use only GPL-compatible licenses, because doing otherwise makes it difficult for others to participate and contribute code.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.dwheeler.com/essays/gpl-compatible.html |title=Make Your Open Source Software GPL-Compatible. Or Else. |publisher=David A. Wheeler |accessdate=26 April 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; As a specific example of license incompatibility, [[Sun Microsystems]]' [[ZFS]] cannot be included in the GPL-licensed Linux kernel, because it is licensed under the GPL-incompatible [[CDDL]]. Furthermore, ZFS is protected by patents, so distributing an independently developed GPL-ed implementation would still require Oracle's permission.&lt;ref&gt;[http://kerneltrap.org/node/8066 Linux: ZFS, Licenses and Patents | KernelTrap]&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Multi-licensing ===
{{Main|Multi-licensing}}
A number of businesses use multi-licensing to distribute a GPL version and sell a [[proprietary software|proprietary]] license to companies wishing to combine the package with proprietary code, using dynamic linking or not. Examples of such companies include [[MySQL AB]], [[Digia PLC]] ([[Qt (framework)|Qt framework]], before 2011 from [[Nokia]]), [[Red Hat]] ([[Cygwin]]) and Riverbank Computing ([[PyQt]]). Other companies, like the [[Mozilla Foundation]] (products include [[Mozilla Application Suite]], [[Mozilla Thunderbird]] and [[Mozilla Firefox]]), use multi-licensing to distribute versions under the GPL and some other open-source licenses.

==Adoption==
The Open Source License Resource Center maintained by [[Black Duck Software]] shows that GPL is the license used in about 60% of all software packages released under a [[free software license|free software]] / open source license.&lt;ref name=widelyused&gt;{{cite web|url=http://osrc.blackducksoftware.com/data/licenses/index.php |title=Open Source License Data |publisher=Blackducksoftware.com |date= |accessdate=21 November 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Use for text and other media==
It is possible to use the GPL for text documents instead of computer programs, or more generally for all kinds of media, if it is clear what constitutes the source code (defined as &quot;the preferred form of the work for making changes in it&quot;).&lt;ref&gt;Free Software Foundation: [http://www.gnu.org/licenses/gpl-faq.html#GPLOtherThanSoftware Frequently Asked Questions about the GNU Licenses: Can I use the GPL for something other than software?]. Retrieved 20 June 2009.&lt;/ref&gt; For manuals and textbooks, though, the FSF recommends to use the [[GNU Free Documentation License]] (GFDL) instead, which it created for this purpose.&lt;ref&gt;GNU project: [http://www.gnu.org/licenses/gpl-faq.html#WhyNotGPLForManuals Frequently Asked Questions about the GNU Licenses: Why don't you use the GPL for manuals?] . Retrieved 20 June 2009.&lt;/ref&gt; Nevertheless, the [[Debian]] developers recommended (in a resolution adopted in 2006) to license documentation for their project under the GPL, because of the incompatibility of the GFDL with the GPL (text licensed under the GFDL cannot be incorporated into GPL software).&lt;ref&gt;Debian Project: [http://www.debian.org/vote/2006/vote_001.en.html#amendmenttexta Resolution: Why the GNU Free Documentation License is not suitable for Debian]. Voted February–March 2006. . Retrieved 20 June 2009.&lt;/ref&gt; Also, the [[FLOSS Manuals]] foundation, an organization devoted to creating manuals for free software, decided to eschew the GFDL in favor of the GPL for its texts in 2007.&lt;ref&gt;FLOSS Manuals foundation: [http://en.flossmanuals.net/bin/view/Blog/LicenseChange License Change] 6 June 2007. . Retrieved 20 June 2009.&lt;/ref&gt;

If the GPL is used for fonts, any documents or images made with such fonts might also have to be distributed under the terms of the GPL. This is not the case in countries like the US and Canada where copyright law is inapplicable to the appearance of fonts, though program code inside a font file may still be covered which can complicate font embedding (since the document could be considered 'linked' to the font). FSF provides an exception for cases where this is not desired.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.fsf.org/blogs/licensing/20050425novalis |title=Font Licensing}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.gnu.org/licenses/gpl-faq.html#FontException |title=How does the GPL apply to fonts?}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Criticism==
===Microsoft===
In 2001, [[Microsoft]] CEO [[Steve Ballmer]] referred to [[Linux]] as &quot;a cancer that attaches itself in an intellectual property sense to everything it touches&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news | first=Dave | last=Newbart | title=Microsoft CEO takes launch break with the Sun-Times | date=1 June 2001 | publisher=[[Chicago Sun-Times]] | url=http://suntimes.com/output/tech/cst-fin-micro01.html | archiveurl=http://web.archive.org/web/20010615205548/http://suntimes.com/output/tech/cst-fin-micro01.html | archivedate=15 June 2001}}(Internet archive link)&lt;/ref&gt; Microsoft has released [[Microsoft Windows Services for UNIX]] which contains GPL-licensed code.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.dwheeler.com/frozen/microsoft-interix-gpl.txt text of GPL v1 with reference to source code download site at microsoft.com ]&lt;/ref&gt; In response to Microsoft's attacks on the GPL, several prominent Free Software developers and advocates released a joint statement supporting the license.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.perens.com/Articles/StandTogether.html Free Software Leaders Stand Together]&lt;/ref&gt; In July 2009, Microsoft itself released a body of around 20,000 lines of Linux driver code under the GPL.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news | first=Gavin | last=Clarke | title=Microsoft embraces Linux cancer to sell Windows servers | date=20 July 2009 | publisher=The Register | url=http://www.theregister.co.uk/2009/07/20/microsoft_windows_drivers_linux/}}&lt;/ref&gt; The [[Hyper-V]] code that is part of the submitted code used open-source components licensed under the GPL and was originally statically linked to proprietary binary parts, the latter being inadmissible in GPL-licensed software.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news | first=Gavin | last=Clarke | title=Microsoft opened Linux-driver code after 'violating' GPL | date=23 July 2009| publisher=The Register | url=http://www.theregister.co.uk/2009/07/23/microsoft_hyperv_gpl_violation/}}&lt;/ref&gt;

====&quot;Viral&quot; Nature====
The GPL has been described as being [[Viral license|&quot;viral&quot;]] by Craig Mundie, Microsoft Senior Vice President&lt;ref&gt;&quot;[http://www.microsoft.com/presspass/exec/craig/05-03sharedsource.mspx Speech Transcript – Craig Mundie, The New York University Stern School of Business]&quot;, ''Prepared Text of Remarks by [[Craig Mundie]]'', Microsoft Senior Vice President, The Commercial Software Model The New York University Stern School of Business 3 May 2001&lt;/ref&gt; because the GPL only allows conveyance of whole programs, which means that programmers are not allowed to convey programs that [[GPL linking exception|link]] to libraries having GPL-incompatible licenses. The so-called &quot;viral&quot; effect of this is that under such circumstances disparately licensed software cannot be combined unless one of the licenses is changed. Although theoretically either license could be changed, in the &quot;viral&quot; scenario the GPL cannot be practically changed (because the software may have so many contributors, some of whom will likely refuse), whereas the license of the other software ''can'' be practically changed.

In the views of Richard Stallman, the metaphor of a &quot;virus&quot; is wrong and an extremely unfriendly thing to say. Software under the GPL never &quot;attacks&quot; and &quot;infects&quot; other software. Rather, software under the GPL is like a [[Chlorophytum comosum|spider plant]]: If one takes a piece of it and puts it somewhere else, it grows there too.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | last=Poynder | first=Richard | title=The Basement Interviews: Freeing the Code | date=21 March 2006 | accessdate=5 February 2010 | url=http://www.archive.org/stream/The_Basement_Interviews/Richard_Stallman_Interview_djvu.txt }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book | last=Chopra | first=Samir | last2=Dexter | first2=Scott | title=Decoding liberation: the promise of free and open source software | date=14 August 2007 | publisher=Routledge | isbn=0415978939 | page=56 | url=http://books.google.com/?id=c7ppFih2mSwC&amp;lpg=PT74 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book | last=Williams | first=Sam | title=Free as in Freedom: Richard Stallman's Crusade for Free Software | date=March 2002 | publisher=O'Reilly Media | url=http://oreilly.com/openbook/freedom/ch02.html | isbn=0596002874 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Barrier to commercialization===
The [[FreeBSD]] project has stated that &quot;a less publicized and unintended use of the GPL is that it is very favorable to large companies that want to undercut software companies. In other words, the GPL is well suited for use as a marketing weapon, potentially reducing overall economic benefit and contributing to monopolistic behavior&quot; and that the GPL can &quot;present a real problem for those wishing to commercialize and profit from software&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.freebsd.org/doc/en_US.ISO8859-1/articles/bsdl-gpl/article.html#GPL-ADVANTAGES GPL Advantages and Disadvantages], FreeBSD: doc/en_US.ISO8859-1/articles/bsdl-gpl/article.sgml,v 1.5 2006/10/16 12:35:23 keramida Exp&lt;/ref&gt; [[Poul-Henning Kamp]], author of a [[beerware]] license, considers GPL &quot;a joke&quot; because of vague statements he perceives exist in the license.&lt;ref&gt;[http://people.freebsd.org/~phk/ Poul-Henning Kamp - Beerware, am I really serious?]&lt;/ref&gt;

==See also==
{{multicol}}
* [[Free software]]
* [[GNU Lesser General Public License]] (LGPL)
* [[Affero General Public License]] (AGPL)
* [[BSD license]]
{{multicol-break}}
* [[Permissive and copyleft licenses]]
* [[Dual-licensing]]
* [[European Union Public Licence]] (EUPL)
* [[Proprietary software]]
{{multicol-break}}
* [[List of software licenses]]
* [[Business models for open source software]]
* [[Anti-copyright]]
* [[GPL font exception]]
{{multicol-break}}
{{Portal|Free software}}
{{multicol-end}}

==References==
{{Reflist|2}}

==External links==
{{Wikibooks|FOSS Licensing}}
* [http://www.gnu.org/licenses/old-licenses/gpl-1.0.txt GNU General Public License v1.0] – This version is [[deprecation|deprecated]] by the FSF.
* [http://www.gnu.org/licenses/old-licenses/gpl-2.0.txt GNU General Public License v2.0] – This version is [[deprecation|deprecated]] by the FSF but is still used by many software projects, including Linux and GNU packages
* [http://www.gnu.org/licenses/gpl-3.0.txt GNU General Public License v3.0]
* [http://www.softwarefreedom.org/resources/2008/compliance-guide.html A Practical Guide to GPL Compliance] (Covers GPLv2 and v3) – from the Software Freedom Law Center
* [http://www.sapnakumar.org/EnfGPL.pdf A paper on enforcing the GPL]
* [http://www.gnu.org/licenses/gpl-faq.html Frequently Asked Questions about the GPL]
* [http://www.dwheeler.com/blog/2006/09/01/#gpl-bsd GPL, BSD, and NetBSD – why the GPL rocketed Linux to success] by David A. Wheeler
* [http://www.rattlesnake.com/software-law/GNU-GPL-and-Commentaries.html GNU General Public License and Commentaries] – Edited by [[Robert Chassell]].
* [http://www.gnu.org/copyleft/lesser.html GNU Lesser General Public License v2.1]
* [http://www.free-soft.org/gpl_history/ History of the GPL]
* [http://fsfe.org/transcripts#licenses List of presentation transcripts about the GPL and free software licenses]
* [http://www.dwheeler.com/essays/gpl-compatible.html Make Your Open Source Software GPL-Compatible. Or Else.] (David A. Wheeler, 7 April 2004)&amp;nbsp;— why a GPL-compatible license is important to the health of a project
* [http://www.free-soft.org/gpl_history/emacs_gpl.html The Emacs General Public License], a February 1988 version, a direct predecessor of the GNU GPL
* [http://www.softpanorama.org/Copyright/License_classification/index.shtml The Labyrinth of Software Freedom], (BSD vs GPL and social aspects of free licensing debate), by Dr. Nikolai Bezroukov
* [http://computemagazine.com/google-gives-oracle-a-tutorial-on-api-copyright-law/ Google Gives Oracle a Tutorial on API Copyright Law]

{{GNU}}
{{FOSS}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Gnu General Public License}}
[[Category:Computer law]]
[[Category:Free content licenses]]
[[Category:Open content licenses]]
[[Category:Free software licenses]]
[[Category:GNU Project]]
[[Category:Open source licenses]]
[[Category:Copyleft]]

[[af:GNU Algemene Publieke Lisensie]]
[[ar:رخصة جنو العمومية]]
[[ast:GNU General Public License]]
[[bg:GNU General Public License]]
[[bs:GNU General Public License]]
[[ca:GNU General Public License]]
[[cs:GNU General Public License]]
[[cy:Trwydded Gyhoeddus Gyffredinol GNU]]
[[da:GNU General Public License]]
[[de:GNU General Public License]]
[[et:GNU GPL]]
[[el:Γενική Άδεια Δημόσιας Χρήσης GNU]]
[[es:GNU General Public License]]
[[eo:Ĝenerala Publika Permesilo de GNU]]
[[eu:GNU General Public License]]
[[fa:اجازه‌نامه عمومی همگانی گنو]]
[[fr:Licence publique générale GNU]]
[[ga:Ceadúnas Ginearálta Poiblí GNU]]
[[gl:GNU General Public License]]
[[ko:GNU 일반 공중 사용 허가서]]
[[hr:GNU General Public License]]
[[ilo:GPL]]
[[id:Lisensi Publik Umum GNU]]
[[it:GNU General Public License]]
[[he:הרישיון הציבורי הכללי של גנו]]
[[ka:GNU General Public License]]
[[lv:GNU Vispārējā publiskā licence]]
[[lt:GNU GPL]]
[[lmo:GPL]]
[[hu:GNU General Public License]]
[[mk:ГНУ-ова општа јавна лиценца]]
[[ml:ഗ്നൂ സാർവ്വജനിക അനുവാദപത്രം]]
[[mr:ग्नू सार्वजनिक परवाना]]
[[ms:Lesen Awam Am GNU]]
[[mn:GNU GPL]]
[[nl:GNU General Public License]]
[[ja:GNU General Public License]]
[[no:GNU General Public License]]
[[nn:GNU General Public License]]
[[mhr:GNU General Public License]]
[[pl:GNU General Public License]]
[[pt:GNU General Public License]]
[[ro:Licența Publică Generală GNU]]
[[ru:GNU General Public License]]
[[sc:Lissentzia GPL]]
[[simple:GNU General Public License]]
[[sk:GNU General Public License]]
[[sl:GNU General Public License]]
[[szl:GNU General Public License]]
[[sr:ГНУ-ова општа јавна лиценца]]
[[sh:GNU opća javna licenca]]
[[fi:GNU General Public License]]
[[sv:GNU General Public License]]
[[tl:GNU General Public License]]
[[ta:குனூ பொதுமக்கள் உரிமம்]]
[[th:สัญญาอนุญาตสาธารณะทั่วไปของกนู]]
[[tr:GNU Genel Kamu Lisansı]]
[[uk:GNU General Public License]]
[[vi:Giấy phép Công cộng GNU]]
[[zh:GNU通用公共许可证]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
