<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="18989739" ns="0" title="List of accidents and incidents involving military aircraft (2000–present)"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{TOC right}}

This is a '''list of''' notable '''accidents and incidents involving military aircraft''' grouped by the year in which the accident or incident occurred.  For more exhaustive lists, see the [http://www.baaa-acro.com Aircraft Crash Record Office] or the [http://aviation-safety.net Air Safety Network]. Combat losses are not included except for a very few cases denoted by singular circumstances.

{{inc-transport|date=August 2008}}
==Aircraft terminology==
Information on aircraft gives the type, and if available, the serial number of the operator in italics, the constructors number, also known as the manufacturer's serial number (c/n), exterior codes in apostrophes, nicknames (if any) in quotation marks, flight callsign in italics, and operating units.

==2000==
*8 April - A [[Bell-Boeing V-22 Osprey|Bell-Boeing MV-22B Osprey]] [[tiltrotor]] prototype, BuNo ''165436'', coded 'MX-04', of [[HMX-1]], rolls over and crashes during a rapid descent to land at [[Marana Northwest Regional Airport]], [[Marana, Arizona]], United States, killing all 19 [[United States Marine Corps|US Marines]] on board. Cause of crash was pilot losing control due to high vertical rate of descent causing vortex ring state. MV-22B, BuNo ''165433'', (which was also taking part in the exercise) landed heavily when the resulting explosion blew out its ground cushion. It was struck off charge on 16 July 2001.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.targetlock.org.uk/osprey/development.html&lt;/ref&gt;
*19 April - A [[Rwandan Air Force]] [[Antonov An-8]], ''TL-ACM'', chartered from [[Central African Airlines]], crashes near [[Pepa, Democratic Republic of the Congo]] after engine failure caused by a suspected [[bird strike]]. All 24 on board were killed. A Rwanda army major, two captains, two lieutenants, and some soldiers were killed along with the 4 Russian crewmembers on take-off from [[Pepa airport|Pepa]]. The soldiers were returning on home leave, while others were planning to attend the president's swearing-in ceremony. Other sources report a death toll of around 57 and suggest the Antonov might have been imported into Rwanda illegally.&lt;ref&gt;[http://aviation-safety.net/database/record.php?id=20000419-1 ASN Aircraft accident Antonov 8 TL-ACM Pepa&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Stamford, Lincs., UK: Air Forces Monthly, compiled by Dave Allport, June 2000, Number 147, page 77.&lt;/ref&gt;
*25 August - [[Royal Air Force|RAF]] [[BAE Hawk|BAE Hawk T1]], ''XX266'', of the [[Red Arrows]] demonstration team suffers birdstrike while returning to [[Exeter]] from a display at [[Dartmouth, Devon]], ~17 miles (27&amp;nbsp;km.) SW of Exeter, punching large hole in starboard wing. Aircraft made safe landing at [[Exeter International Airport|Exeter Airport]].&lt;ref&gt;Stamford, Lincs., UK: Air Forces Monthly, compiled by Dave Allport, October 2000, Number 151, page 74.&lt;/ref&gt;
*28 September - A U.S. Navy [[T-34 Mentor|T-34C Turbo Mentor]] of [[Training Squadron 10|VT-10]] crashes in a hayfield in [[Baldwin County, Alabama|Baldwin County]] near [[Silverhill, Alabama]], killing both crew. Navy flight instructor, Lt. James S. McComber, 31, of [[Apple Valley, Minnesota]], and his student pilot, Air Force 2nd Lt. Alex Velkov, 23, of [[Mountain View, California]], an Air Force navigator, were flying out of [[NAS Whiting Field]] when the afternoon accident occurred. &quot;The plane looked like it was in trouble,&quot; said witness Danny Brand, who was questioned by investigators. &quot;(The plane) began rolling to the right, tried to fire up the engine and then corkscrewed straight down to the ground.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Norman, Brett, staff writer, &quot;''Few details in training accident that killed instructor, student''&quot;, Pensacola News-Journal, Pensacola, Florida, Friday 29 September 2000.&lt;/ref&gt;
*25 October - A [[Russian Air Force]] [[Ilyushin Il-18]] crashes near [[Batumi]], [[Georgia (country)|Georgia]] killing all 86 people on board.
*1 November - [[Hellenic Air Force]] [[LTV A-7 Corsair II|LTV A-7H Corsair II]], ''159666'', of the 345th Mira, crashes near [[Cape Tainaros]], [[Crete]], Greece, pilot survives.
*11 December - The 18th [[Bell-Boeing V-22 Osprey|Bell-Boeing MV-22B Osprey]], BuNo ''165440'', of [[VMMT-204]], with only 157.7 flight hours, crashes in a remote wooded area ~10 miles from [[MCAS New River]], [[Jacksonville, North Carolina]], USA, after a leak in a chafed hydraulic line causes an engine to fail and a glitch in the flight control software prevents the pilots from maintaining control of the aircraft; all 4 crew members are killed.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.targetlock.org.uk/osprey/development.html&lt;/ref&gt;

==2001==
*16 February - A [[Royal New Zealand Air Force]] [[Douglas A-4 Skyhawk|Douglas A-4K Skyhawk]], ''NZ6211'', from [[No. 2 Squadron RNZAF]] crashes near {{HMAS|Albatross|air station|6}} in [[New South Wales]] while practicing maneuvers for an upcoming air show, killing the aircraft's pilot.&lt;ref name=&quot;TVNZ_29845&quot;&gt;{{cite news |url=http://tvnz.co.nz/view/page/423466/29845 |title=NZ air force pilot killed |date=16 February 2001 |work=[[Television New Zealand]] |accessdate=14 October 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Allport, Dave, &quot;''Attrition''&quot;, Air Forces Monthly, Stamfords, Lincs., UK, Number 157, April 2001, page 93.&lt;/ref&gt;
*3 March - A [[United States National Guard]] [[Short C-23 Sherpa|Short C-23B+ Sherpa]] ([[Shorts 360]]), ''93-1336'', of [[Florida Army National Guard]] Det. 1 H/171st AVN, based at [[Lakeland Linder Regional Airport]], crashes during heavy rainstorm around 1100 hrs. in [[Unadilla, Georgia|Unadilla]], [[Georgia (U.S. state)|Georgia]] in the United States. All 21 people on board are killed. Aircraft was en route from [[Hurlburt Field]], [[Florida]] to [[NAS Oceana]], [[Virginia]] with Virginia Beach-based [[RED HORSE]] detachment on board who had been training at Hurlburt.&lt;ref&gt;Stamford, Lincs., UK: Air Forces Monthly, compiled by Dave Allport, May 2001, Number 158, page 77.&lt;/ref&gt;
*1 April - '''[[Hainan Island incident]]'''- An American [[Lockheed EP-3|Lockheed EP-3E]] Aries II surveillance plane, BuNo ''156511'', coded 'PR-32', of [[VQ-1]], collided with a Chinese [[Shenyang J-8|Shenyang J-8IID]] fighter jet, reported as ''81192'', and was forced to make an emergency landing at [[Lingshui Li Autonomous County|Lingshui]] air base on [[Hainan]] Island, China. The U.S. crew was detained for 10 days; the Chinese fighter pilot, Wang Wei, was reported missing and presumed dead. The Chinese refused to let the Orion be flown out, so it was dismantled and transported on chartered [[Antonov An-124|Antonov An-124-100]] of Polyot.&lt;ref&gt;Stamford, Lincs., UK: Air Forces Monthly, May 2001, Number 158, page 4.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Stamford, Lincs., UK: Air Forces Monthly, June 2001, Number 159, page 79&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Dawes, Alan, &quot;Spies in the Sky!&quot;, ''Air International'', September 2001, Volume 61, Number 3, page 175.&lt;/ref&gt;
*4 April - A [[Sudan Air Force]] [[Antonov An-24]] '''[[2001 Sudanese Air Force Antonov AN-24 crash|crashes]]''' during a sandstorm in Adar Yeil, [[Sudan]]. Of the 30 people on board, 14 were killed; among them, Sudan's deputy defense minister as well as other high-ranking officers.
*12 April - ''Magyar Légierō'', [[Hungarian Air Force]] [[Mil Mi-24|Mil Mi-24D]], ''579'', collides with [[Mil Mi-24|Mil Mi-24V]], ''715'', while performing low-level formation flight over the range near [[Gyulafirátót]], killing both crews.&lt;ref&gt;Polderman, Robin, &quot;Looking West: Hungarian Air Force&quot;, ''Air International'', Stamford, Lincs., UK, January 2005, Volume 68, Number 1, page 55.&lt;/ref&gt;
*16 May - A [[Turkish Air Force]] [[CASA CN-235|CASA CN-235M-100]] crashes into a field in [[Malatya]], [[Turkey]] killing all 34 on board.&lt;ref&gt;[http://aviation-safety.net/database/record.php?id=20010516-0 ASN Aircraft accident IPTN/CASA CN-235M-100 086 Malatya&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;
*29 May - Three crew are killed when a [[Republic of Korea]] Army [[CH-47 Chinook|CH-47D Chinook]], of the 301st Aviation Regiment, [[Icheon]],&lt;ref&gt;Gunner, Jerry, &quot;Keeping Ahead of the Neighbors&quot;, Air Forces Monthly, No. 271, November 2010, page 94&lt;/ref&gt; crashes in [[Seoul, South Korea]] while installing a torch-shaped sculpture on the [[Han River (Korea)|Han River]] [[Olympic Bridge]], built to commemorate the 1988 Olympic Games. The Chinook had just lowered the flame-shaped statuary onto the bridge central tower when its rotors hit the sculpture and then the tower. The front rotor clipped the top of the sculpture and separated from the helicopter which then fell onto the span, breaking in two, with the rear bursting into flame on the bridge and the forward half falling into the river. No other casualties were reported. The bridge had been closed during the installation work. The dead were identified as pilot Chun Hong-yop, co-pilot Nam In-ho and Sgt. 1st Class Kim Woo-soo. Army scuba divers were working to recover the wreckage.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news| url=http://www.time.com/time/potw/20010601/5.html | work=Time | deadurl=yes}} {{Dead link|date=September 2011|bot=RjwilmsiBot}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;http://english1.people.com.cn/english/200105/30/eng20010530_71388.html&lt;/ref&gt; Footage of this crash is widely available on the web.
*29 May - A US Navy [[FA-18 Hornet|FA-18C Hornet]] from [[VFA-106]] crashed near [[Fort Pierce, Florida]], during a ferry flight from [[NAS Oceana]], Virginia, to [[NAS Key West]], Florida. Pilot was killed.
*17 July - At ~0700 hrs., pilot Maj. Aaron George of the [[416th Flight Test Squadron]] at [[Edwards Air Force Base]], California, and Judson Brohmer of [[Tehachapi, California]], an aerial photographer under contract to the [[Air Force Flight Test Center]], are killed in the crash of an Edwards based [[F-16 Fighting Falcon|F-16B Block 5 Fighting Falcon]], ''78-0100'',&lt;ref&gt;http://www.f-16.net/aircraft-database/F-16/mishaps-and-accidents/year/2001/&lt;/ref&gt; while on a test sortie to chase and film the launch of the [[Miniature Air-Launch Decoy]] (MALD) from a second F-16, also from the 416th Flight Test Squadron.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.f-117a.com/brohmer.html&lt;/ref&gt;
*1 December - A [[Armed Forces of the Russian Federation|Russian military]] [[Ilyushin Il-76]] catches fire and crashes near [[Novaya Inya, Russia]] killing all 18 on board.

==2002==
*17 February - A USMC [[F/A-18 Hornet|F/A-18D Hornet]] from [[VMFA-533]] crash lands at [[Twentynine Palms, California]]. Both aircrew eject but the [[Weapon Systems Officer|WSO]] later dies from injuries in hospital.
*21 February - A [[Russian Navy]] [[Antonov An-26]], 07 Red, crashes one mile (1.5&amp;nbsp;km.) short of runway at [[Lakhta air base|Lakhta Airfield]], near [[Archangelsk]], northern Russia, during an emergency landing. Of the 20 people on board, 17 were killed.&lt;ref&gt;Stamford, Lincs., UK: Air Forces Monthly, compiled by Dave Allport, April 2002, Number 169, page 75.&lt;/ref&gt;
*2 March - A [[F-14 Tomcat|Grumman F-14B-145-GR Tomcat]], BuNo ''162923'', of [[VF-143]], 'AG', from the carrier [[USS John F. Kennedy (CV-67)|USS ''John F. Kennedy'']] crashes into the Mediterranean near the Greek island of [[Crete]], killing its pilot.&lt;ref name=&quot;ReferenceA&quot;&gt;Eisman, Dale, staff writer, &quot;''Oceana-Based F-14 Crashes in Sea; Crew of 2 Rescued''&quot;, The Virginian-Pilot, Norfolk, Virginia, Saturday 9 March 2002&lt;/ref&gt; Aircraft was launching from the carrier when the nose gear disintegrated - both crew eject but the pilot was outside the envelope and was killed.
*8 March -  A [[F-14 Tomcat|Grumman F-14A Tomcat]], BuNo ''158618'', of [[VF-211]], based at [[NAS Oceana]], [[Virginia Beach, Virginia]] crashes into the [[Arabian Sea]] after a failed attempt to land on the carrier [[USS John C. Stennis|USS ''John C. Stennis'']].  The Navy said both crew members were pulled from the water by a rescue helicopter shortly after the accident. Neither appeared to be seriously injured.&lt;ref name=&quot;ReferenceA&quot;/&gt;
*9 March - A [[Portuguese Air Force]] [[F-16 Fighting Falcon|General Dynamics F-16]] crashes in [[Monte Real Air Base|Monte Real, Portugal]], while practicing aerobatic maneuvers, killing the pilot.
*2 April - A [[United States Navy]] [[MH-53E|Sikorsky MH-53E Sea Dragon]] of [[HM-14]] BuNo ''163051'' crashed on the runway at [[Bahrain International Airport]].  All 18 men and woman on board survived with only a few cases of minor injuries.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.joebaugher.com/navy_serials/thirdseries22.html&lt;/ref&gt;
*20 April - During the [[NAS Point Mugu]] air show ([[Point Mugu]], [[California]]), the pilot and radar intercept officer are killed when their United States Navy [[F-4 Phantom II|McDonnell-Douglas QF-4S+ Phantom II]], BuNo ''155749'',  stalls and crashes after pulling away from a diamond formation. Both eject but chutes do not have time to deploy. The Navy report states in part: &quot;The cause of this tragic accident was the failure of the pilot to manage the energy state of the aircraft, and then to recognize a departure from controlled flight at low altitude, and apply the NATOPS recovery techniques.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web| last = | first = | authorlink =| coauthors =| title =QF-4S+ Crash at Pt Mugu - April 20, 2002 | work =| publisher =Goleta Air and Space Museum. | date = | url =http://www.air-and-space.com/20020420%20Pt%20Mugu%20QF-4J%20Crash.htm | doi =| accessdate =June 27, 2008 }}&lt;/ref&gt; This Phantom II was credited with a [[MiG-17]] kill 10 May 1972 with [[VF-96]].&lt;ref&gt;http://home.att.net/~jbaugher/thirdseries19.html&lt;/ref&gt;
*30 April - An [[F-15 Eagle|F-15C Eagle]] of the [[46th Test Wing]], based at [[Eglin Air Force Base]], Florida, crashes in the [[Gulf of Mexico]] ~{{convert|60|mi|km}} S of [[Panama City, Florida]], killing the test pilot. An Accident Investigation Board determines that the crash was caused by the structural failure of the honeycomb material supporting the leading edge of the port vertical stabilizer during a high-speed test dive. A section of the leading edge, approximately 6 X {{convert|3|ft|m}}, broke away.&lt;ref&gt;Books, Kenneth, &quot;''Mid-air collision kills pilot''&quot;, Eglin Flyer, Bayou Enterprises, Inc., Niceville, Florida, Friday, 22 February 2008, page 9.&lt;/ref&gt;
*3 May - An [[Indian Air Force]] [[Mikoyan-Gurevich MiG-21]] pilot ejects after takeoff, with the aircraft crashing into a [[Jalandhar]] bank building, killing eight on the ground (see [[2002 Jalandhar India MiG-21 crash]]).
*12 May - The [[hangar]] housing [[Buran (spacecraft)|''Buran'']] OK-1K1 in [[Kazakhstan]] collapses, due to poor maintenance. The collapse kills eight workers and destroys the orbiter as well as a [[mock-up]] of an Energia carrier rocket.&lt;ref&gt;{{ cite news | publisher=[[BBC]] | title=Russia's space dreams abandoned | url=http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/sci/tech/1985631.stm | work=[[bbc.co.uk]] | accessdate=2007-11-14 | date=2002-05-13 | last=Whitehouse | first=David }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.buran.ru/images/jpg/bbur89.jpg Buran.ru: ''Photo of collapsed hangar'']&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.buran.ru/images/jpg/bbur90.jpg Buran.ru: ''Remains of Buran photo with right front windscreen still visible under the debris'']&lt;/ref&gt;
*2 June - An [[Angolan Armed Forces]] [[Mil Mi-17]] helicopter crashes in poor weather killing 20 of the 25 on board. Among those on board were top military officials that were going to attend a disarmament ceremony by [[National Union for Total Independence of Angola|UNITA]] rebels.
*5 July - U.S. Navy [[H-3 Sea King|UH-3H Sea King]], ''Desert Duck 744'', operated by [[HC-2|HC-2, Detachment 2]], based out of [[Bahrain]], suffers tail rotor failure while landing aboard the [[USS Cushing (DD-985)|USS ''Cushing'']], spins out of control, goes over starboard side. Seven on board get out safely.
*27 July - A [[Ukrainian Air Force]] [[Sukhoi Su-27|Sukhoi Su-27UB]] '''[[Sknyliv (Ukraine) airshow disaster|crashes]]''' during the Lviv airshow killing 85 spectators, 5 of them children. 199 were injured. Pilots managed to eject, but the plane crashed on spectators watching the airshow from the ground. The plane lacked the altitude to escape the crash, and it hit the tribune and fell on the ground. As stated by Ukrainian Defense Ministry, the crash was caused because of engine failure. Pilots, unit commanders later jailed.
*19 August - A [[Russian Air Force]] [[Mil Mi-26]] helicopter is [[Khankala attack|shot down]] by [[Chechnya|Chechen]] rebels using a portable [[Surface-to-air missile|SAM]], probably an [[Igla]], in Khankala, Russia. Of the 152 on board, 118 are killed.&lt;ref&gt;Stamford, Lincs., UK: Air Forces Monthly, compiled by Dave Allport, November 2002, Number 176, page 75.&lt;/ref&gt;
*3 October - [[United States Navy]] [[F-14 Tomcat|Grumman F-14A Tomcat]], BuNo ''162594'', coded ''AD 136'', of [[VF-101]], suffers dual compressor stalls, both engines shut down, during routine training flight, crashing in the [[Gulf of Mexico]] on mission out of [[NAS Key West]], [[Florida]]. Pilot and instructor eject safely at {{convert|5000|ft|m}} and are rescued with only minor injuries by a [[SH-3 Sea King|UH-3 Sea King]] helicopter. On 5 May 2006, one of this Tomcat's tailfins is discovered on isolated beach W of [[Cork (city)|Cork, Ireland]], having floated 4,900 miles (7,900&amp;nbsp;km.) across the Atlantic. This was the sixteenth and last Tomcat lost by VF-101 during 30 years of operation.&lt;ref&gt;Stamford, Lincs., UK: FlyPast, Holmes, Tony, &quot;''A Tomcat's Tail''&quot;, March 2007, Number 308, pages 72-75.&lt;/ref&gt;
*18 October - Two [[F/A-18 Hornet|F/A-18F Hornet]]s collide during [[Air Combat Maneuvering]] off the Southern California coast and crash into Pacific 80&amp;nbsp;mi SW of [[Monterey, California]]. All four crew (two Pilots and two WSOs) are KWF.
*3 November - An [[F/A-18 Hornet|FA-18C Hornet]] from [[VFA-34]] failed to return to [[USS George Washington (CVN 73)|USS ''George Washington'']] from a night at sea bombing mission and crashed into [[Adriatic Sea]]. Pilot was killed.

==2003==
*17 January - A USMC [[F/A-18 Hornet|F/A-18D Hornet]] crashes into the [[Pacific Ocean]] off of [[MCAS Miramar]], California, due to a material failure during a [[functional check flight]] with one engine shut down.  Both crew eject safely and are recovered.
*1 February - The [[Space Shuttle Columbia|Space Shuttle ''Columbia'']], ''OV-102'', is lost as it reenters after a two-week mission, [[STS-107]]. Damage to the shuttle's [[Space shuttle thermal protection system|thermal protection system (TPS)]] leads to structural failure in the shuttle's left wing and, ultimately, the spacecraft breaking apart as it decelerated over [[Texas]]. Investigations after the tragedy reveal the damage to the reinforced carbon-carbon leading edge wing panel had resulted from a piece of insulation foam breaking away from the external tank during the launch and hitting shuttle's wing. [[Rick D. Husband]], [[William McCool]], [[Michael P. Anderson]], [[David M. Brown]], [[Kalpana Chawla]], [[Laurel B. Clark]], and [[Ilan Ramon]] were killed. See [[Space Shuttle Columbia disaster]].
*19 February - [[2003 Iran Ilyushin Il-76 crash]]; an [[Islamic Revolutionary Guards Corps]] [[Ilyushin Il-76|Ilyushin Il-76MD]], ''15-2280'', c/n 0063471155,&lt;ref&gt;http://aviation-safety.net/database/record.php?id=20030219-0&lt;/ref&gt; formerly registered ''YI-AND'', crashes into a mountain in poor weather near Shahdad, [[Iran]]. All 18 crew and 284 passengers on board were killed.
*20 February - A [[Pakistan Air Force]] [[Fokker F-27|Fokker F-27-200]], ''10254'', of 12 Squadron, crashes near [[Kohat]], Pakistan when it strikes a ridge at the {{convert|3000|ft|m|adj=on}} level (915 m) AMSL, obscured by clouds. All 17 people on board died, including [[Air Chief Marshal]] [[Mushaf Ali Mir]]. PAF spokespersons said on 22 May that pilot error was to blame.&lt;ref name=autogenerated1&gt;Stamford, Lincs., UK: Air Forces Monthly, compiled by Dave Allport, July 2003, Number 184, page 76.&lt;/ref&gt;
*27 February - A [[Canadian Forces Air Command]] CH-124B [[H-3 Sea King]] helicopter, ''12401'', of 12 Wing, crashes on the deck of [[HMCS Iroquois (DDH 280)|HMCS ''Iroquois'']] in the [[Persian Gulf]]. No one was killed, but the ship's mission in the Gulf was postponed.&lt;ref name=autogenerated1 /&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Stamford, Lincs., UK: Air Forces Monthly, compiled by Dave Allport, October 2003, Number 187, pages 73-74.&lt;/ref&gt;
*22 March - During the [[2003 invasion of Iraq]], two [[Royal Navy]] [[Westland Sea King|Westland Sea King ASaC7]]  [[AEW]] helicopters, ''[[United Kingdom military aircraft serials|XV650]]'', 'CU-182', and ''XV704'', 'R-186', collide in mid-air five miles (8&amp;nbsp;km) from their aircraft carrier [[HMS Ark Royal (R07)|HMS ''Ark Royal'']] while one had been leaving on a mission as the other returned from the same operation. One American exchange pilot on board, a former E-2C Hawkeye pilot formerly from Carrier Airborne Early Warning Squadron One One Five, was killed. [http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/uk_news/2875009.stm]&lt;ref name=autogenerated1 /&gt;
[[File:Crash.arp.600pix.jpg|thumb|right|Captain Chris Stricklin ejects from his F-16 at an air show in September 2003.]]
*26 June - The [[NASA]] [[NASA Pathfinder|Helios Prototype]] breaks up and falls into the [[Pacific Ocean]] about ten miles (16&amp;nbsp;km) W of the Hawaiian Island [[Kauai]] during a remotely piloted systems checkout flight in preparation for an endurance test scheduled for the following month.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.sciencedaily.com/releases/2003/06/030630111917.htm &quot;Helios Prototype Solar Aircraft Lost In Flight Mishap&quot;, ''Science Daily'', July 1, 2003, accessed September 8, 2003]&lt;/ref&gt; Cause was flight through wind shear on a day when the conditions had been pronounced &quot;marginal&quot;.
*18 August - A [[Polish Air Force|Polish]] [[Su-22|Su-22M-4K]], of 8 ELT, flying at 3000 meter (10,000&amp;nbsp;ft) altitude, during antiaircraft artillery exercises, is shot down at 1600 hrs. within the confines of the Wicko Morskie range, near [[Ustka]] by [[2K12 Kub]] missile. Another account ascribes the downing merely to a &quot;technical malfunction&quot;. The pilot, Lt. Col. [[Andrzej Andrzejewski]], safely ejected and alighted in [[Baltic Sea]] 21&amp;nbsp;km (11 [[Nautical mile|nmi]]) from the coast, and - after one-and-half hour spent in water - picked up by [[Mil Mi-14|Mi-14]]PS [[Search and rescue|SAR]] helicopter from [[Siemirowice Air Base]].&lt;ref&gt;Stamford, Lincs., UK: Air Forces Monthly, compiled by Dave Allport, October 2003, Number 187, page 72.&lt;/ref&gt; Andrzejewski will subsequently perish in 23 January 2008, [[CASA C-295]] crash.
*11 September - While landing aboard [[USS George Washington (CVN-73)|USS ''George Washington'']], operating off the Virginia Capes, an [[F/A-18 Hornet|F/A-18D-32-MC Hornet (Lot 13)]], BuNo ''164198'', c/n 961/DO63, &lt;ref&gt;http://www.joebaugher.com/navy_serials/thirdseries23.html&lt;/ref&gt;, 'AD 432', of [[VFA-106]], &lt;ref&gt;http://www.ejection-history.org.uk/aircraft_by_type/f_18_hornet.htm&lt;/ref&gt; goes off the [[Flight deck#Angled flight deck|angle]] at ~1600 hrs. when the arresting cable parts, pilot ejects and is recovered. The broken [[Arresting gear|cable]], whipping back across the deck, injures eleven deck crew, the most serious of which are airlifted to shore medical facilities. &lt;ref&gt;http://www.itnsource.com/shotlist//RTV/2003/09/11/309110047/?s=storyabout&lt;/ref&gt; Footage: http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=7OxMox2Kdxs&amp;feature=related
*14 September - Opposing Solo Pilot, Capt. Chris R. Stricklin, in [[U.S. Air Force Thunderbirds|Thunderbirds]] Number 6, an [[F-16 Fighting Falcon|F-16C Block 32J Fighting Falcon]], ''87-0327'',&lt;ref&gt;http://www.f-16.net/aircraft-database/F-16/mishaps-and-accidents/year/2003/16/&lt;/ref&gt; misjudges his altitude before beginning a Split-S takeoff maneuver at [[Mountain Home AFB]], Idaho, ejects in [[ACES II]] seat 8/10ths of a second before the aircraft impacts the runway.
*18 September - A [[Tupolev Tu-160|Tupolev Tu-160 &quot;Blackjack&quot;]], bort number '01', of the 121st regiment, 22 heavy bombers division, on a proving flight out of [[Engels Air Base]] after the replacement of one of its four engines, crashes near [[Stepnoye]] settlement, Sovetskoye, [[Saratov]] oblast, killing the four crew. There were no armaments aboard. Just before the crash the crew reported an engine fire to ground control, after which contact with the pilots was lost. The wreckage of the bomber was found 35&amp;nbsp;km from its base. No injuries on the ground. The main staff of the air force identified the dead as crew commander, Lt. Col. Yuriy Deyneko, co-pilot Maj. Oleg Fedusenko [the Russian TV channel gave this name as Fedunenko in its 1000 GMT newscast], and the navigators as Maj. Grigoriy Kolchin and Maj. Sergey Sukhorukov. This was the first Blackjack loss in 17 years of operations.&lt;ref&gt;BBC Monitoring Former Soviet Union Publication date: 18-09-2003&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;http://www.globalsecurity.org/wmd/world/russia/tu-160.htm&lt;/ref&gt;
*15 November - Two [[United States Army]] [[UH-60 Black Hawk]] helicopters collide near [[Mosul]], [[Iraq]]. Twenty-two soldiers were on both aircraft and 17 were killed.
*29 November - An [[Air Force of the Democratic Republic of the Congo]] [[Antonov An-26]], 9T-TAD, blows out a tire during landing in [[Boende]], Democratic Republic of the Congo and overruns the runway and crashes into a market square. Of the 24 people on board, 20 are killed and 13 people on the ground die.&lt;ref&gt;Stamford, Lincs., UK: Air Forces Monthly, compiled by Dave Allport, February 2004, Number 191, page 74.&lt;/ref&gt;

==2004==
*26 February - [[Republic of Macedonia|Macedonia]] Government [[Beechcraft Super King Air|Beechcraft 200 Super King Air]], ''Z3-BAB'', c/n BB-652,  crashes into mountains while attempting to land in poor weather at [[Mostar International Airport]], Bosnia - Herzegovina . All 9 aboard killed including Macedonian President [[Boris Trajkovski]]. Pilot error. The two-man crew misinterpreted crucial flight data in stormy weather.&lt;ref&gt;http://aviation-safety.net/wikibase/wiki.php?id=17014&lt;/ref&gt;
*23 March - First prototype [[Boeing X-50|Boeing X-50A Dragonfly]] Canard Rotor/Wing crashes at the [[United States Army]] [[Yuma Proving Ground]], [[Yuma, Arizona]], during its third hover test flight. It had made its first flight on 4 December 2003.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;Airscene&quot;, AIR International, Stamford, Lincs., UK, May 2004, Volume 66, Number 5, page 11.&lt;/ref&gt;
*24 March - [[U.S. Navy]] [[F/A-18 Hornet|F/A-18C Hornet]], of [[VFA-82]], crashes into the [[Atlantic Ocean]] near [[Tybee Island, Georgia]]. Pilot ejects safely and is rescued.
*21 June - [[F-14 Tomcat|F-14A Tomcat]] of the [[Islamic Republic of Iran Air Force]], flown by Capt. Darioush Yavari and Col. Ali Abou Ataa, crashes on approach to [[Shahid Baba'ie Air Base]] when Yavari, an experienced [[Northrop F-5|F-5]] pilot qualifying on the F-14, misjudges his sink rate during a no-flaps landing, [[undercarriage]] strikes runway with enough force to flip the Tomcat onto its back, killing both crew. Cause is found to be premature rush to put pilot in the cockpit without completing simulator course. Commanding officer of TFB.8, Gen. Ahmad Mieghani (himself a former F-5 pilot) resigns, but investigative commission reinstates him, recognizing the true source of the problem.&lt;ref&gt;Cooper, Tom and Bishop, Farzad, &quot;''The nine lives of the Cat: Iran's Tomcats at War''&quot;, International Air Power Review, Volume 23, AIRtime Publishing Inc., Westport, Connecticut, 2007, ISBN 1-880588-99-4, page 126.&lt;/ref&gt;
*21 July - Two [[United States Marine Corps]] [[F/A-18 Hornet]]s of [[VMFA-134]], [[3rd Marine Air Wing]], based at [[MCAS Miramar]], [[California]], suffer mid-air collision over the [[Columbia River]], {{convert|120|mi|km}} E of [[Portland, Oregon]], shortly after 1430 hrs., killing Marine Reservists Maj. Gary R. Fullerton, 36, of [[Spartanburg, South Carolina]], and Capt. Jeffrey L. Ross, 36, of [[Old Hickory, Tennessee]] in F/A-18B, BuNo ''162870'', 'MF-00',&lt;ref name=&quot;Allport, Dave 2005, page 76&quot;&gt;Allport, Dave, &quot;''Accident Report Updates''&quot;, Air Forces Monthly, Stamford, Lincs., UK, November 2005, Issue 212, page 76.&lt;/ref&gt; coming down in the river. Maj. Craig Barden, 38, ejects from F/A-18A, BuNo 163097, 'MF-04',&lt;ref name=&quot;Allport, Dave 2005, page 76&quot;/&gt; landing nearby on a hillside W of [[Arlington, Oregon]], and is taken to Mid-Columbia Medical Center in [[The Dalles]], suffering minor injuries.&lt;ref&gt;Los Angeles, California, &quot;''Marines Killed in Midair Jet Collision Identified''&quot;, Los Angeles Times, July 25, 2005, page B-5.&lt;/ref&gt; All three crew eject but only two parachutes open. The  fighters were on their way to the Boardman Air Force Range, where the Oregon Air National Guard trains, when they collided, said one spokesman. Another spokesman told the Associated Press that the planes were on a low-altitude training exercise.&lt;ref&gt;Green, Kristen, and Steele, Jeanette, &quot;''Reservists on training mission; one injured''&quot;, July 22, 2004, The San Diego Union-Tribune, San Diego, California.&lt;/ref&gt;
*24 August - A [[Venezuelan Air Force]] [[Shorts 360]] crashes near [[Maracay]], [[Venezuela]], killing all 25 on board.
*9 September - A low-flying [[British Army]] [[Westland Lynx|Lynx AH Mk.9]] helicopter, ''ZE382'', of [[661 Squadron]], [[1st Regiment, Army Air Corps]] (until March 1957, [[No. 661 Squadron RAF]]), is [[AH.9 Lynx crash (September 2004)|caught in high-voltage electric wires]] during an Anglo-Czech joint military training exercise near the village [[Kuroslepy]] (near [[Brno]]). All six persons on board died.&lt;ref&gt;Stamford, Lincs., UK: Air Forces Monthly, compiled by Dave Allport, March 2005, Number 204, page 74.&lt;/ref&gt;
*11 September - A [[Hellenic Army]] [[CH-47|CH-47SD Chinook]], ''EZ-916'', of 4 TEAS, ditches into the [[Aegean Sea]] off [[Mount Athos]], Greece around 1056 hrs. killing all 17 on board. Among those killed was [[Patriarch Peter VII of Alexandria]].&lt;ref&gt;Stamford, Lincs., UK: Air Forces Monthly, compiled by Dave Allport, November 2004, Number 200, page 86.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Stamford, Lincs., UK: Air Forces Monthly, compiled by Dave Allport, December 2004, Number 201, page 74.&lt;/ref&gt;
*14 September - An [[F/A-18 Hornet|F/A-18C Hornet]] of [[VMFA-212]] crashes at [[Manbulloo Station]] about 10 M SW of [[RAAF Tindal]], Australia, during a day approach to landing. The pilot ejects and is injured.
*9 November - A [[U.S. Navy]] [[F/A-18 Hornet|F/A-18C Hornet]] crashes 15 miles E of [[Nellis AFB]], Nevada, after in flight fire and becoming uncontrollable shortly after takeoff. Pilot ejects safely.
*26 November - [[United States Marine Corps|USMC]] [[V-22 Osprey|MV-22B Osprey]], BuNo ''165838'', loses a 20 x 4 inch piece of a prop-rotor blade during test flight in [[Nova Scotia]], Canada, but is able to make safe precautionary landing at [[CFB Shearwater]] despite severe airframe vibration.&lt;ref&gt;Stamford, Lincs., UK: Air Forces Monthly, compiled by Dave Allport, April 2005, Number 205, page 73.&lt;/ref&gt; The blade failed after apparently being hit by ice which broke off from another part of the aircraft.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.targetlock.org.uk/osprey/development.html&lt;/ref&gt;
*29 November - A [[U.S. Army]] [[UH-60 Black Hawk|UH-60L Black Hawk]], crashes shortly after taking off from [[Fort Hood, Texas]], when it strikes guy-wires supporting the television antenna of [[KSWO-TV]], near [[Waco, Texas]], killing all seven soldiers aboard. Conditions were foggy and the warning lights on the tower were not lit, in violation of both [[Federal Communications Commission]] (FCC) and [[Federal Aviation Authority]] (FAA) regulations. Victims included Brigadier General Charles B. Allen of Lawton, Oklahoma; Specialist Richard L. Brown of Stonewall, Louisiana; Chief Warrant Officer Todd T. Christmas of Wagon Mound, New Mexico; Chief Warrant Officer Doug Clapp of Greensboro, North Carolina; Chief Warrant Officer Mark W. Evans of Killeen, Texas; Chief Warrant Officer David H. Garner of Mason City, Iowa; and Colonel James M. Moore of Peabody, Massachusetts.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.helicoptercrashes.com/heliopter-news/black-hawk-helicopter-crash-lawsuit-09212006&lt;/ref&gt;
*2 December - The pilot of a [[Blue Angels]] [[F/A-18]], BuNo ''161956'', ejects approximately one mile off [[Perdido Key]], [[Florida]], after reporting mechanical problems and loss of power.  Lt. Ted Steelman suffered minor injuries and fully recovered.
*10 December - Two Canadian Forces [[CT-114 Tutor]]s of 431 [[Snowbirds]] Air Demonstration Team, ''114064'' and ''114173'', flying as opposing solo '8' and '9' (unclear which was which), collide at the top of a loop during practice over [[RCAF Station Mossbank|Mossbank Airfield]], an abandoned [[World War II]] aerodrome. Captain Miles Selby, pilot of '8' was killed instantly, but Captain Chuck Mallet was thrown clear of the wreckage of '9', released his lap belt and pulled his chute release, landing with minor injuries.&lt;ref&gt;Stamford, Lincs., UK: Air Forces Monthly, compiled by Dave Allport, April 2005, Number 205, page 72.&lt;/ref&gt;
*20 December - An [[F-22 Raptor]] crashes on takeoff at [[Nellis Air Force Base]], [[Nevada]], prompting the U.S. Air Force to ground most of its other F-22s. The pilot ejected safely from the Lockheed Martin-built jet, which smashed into the runway it was trying to leave at about 1545 hrs. local time.

==2005==
*18 January - A [[United States Air Force]] [[Cessna T-37 Tweet|Cessna T-37B]], ''66-8003'', ''Cider 21'', of the [[89th Flying Training Squadron]], [[80th Flying Training Wing]] collides in midair with a civilian [[Air Tractor AT-501|Air Tractor AT-502B]], registration number ''N8526M'', during a training flight over an unpopulated area near [[Hollister, Oklahoma]], USA; both aircraft spiral out of control, 2 aircrew in T-37 eject, 1 suffers minor injuries, pilot and sole occupant of ''N8526M'' is killed. The crash is attributed to the failure of both pilots to watch for conflicting air traffic during [[Visual flight rules|VFR]] flight, a rare example of a [[midair collision]] in daylight VFR conditions during cruise flight in uncongested airspace distant from an airport.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.ntsb.gov/ntsb/brief.asp?ev_id=20050126X00109&amp;key=2|title=NTSB Report CHI05FA055B|publisher=National Transportation Safety Board|accessdate=2010-08-02}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://usaf.aib.law.af.mil/T-37B_14Jan05.pdf|title=Executive Summary- Aircraft Accident Investigation- T-37B S/N 66-8003 &amp; AT-502B, N8526M|publisher=United States Air Force|accessdate=2010-08-02}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*26 January - A [[United States Marine Corps]] [[CH-53E Super Stallion]] helicopter ferrying troops crashes during a sandstorm near [[Ar Rutba]], [[Iraq]] killing all 31 on board.
*29 January - An [[F/A-18 Hornet|F/A-18F Hornet]] crashes into ocean while landing on [[USS Kitty Hawk (CV 63)|USS ''Kitty Hawk'' (CV 63)]]. The No. 3 arresting wire snapped, resulting in the plane plunging into the [[Pacific Ocean]] 100 miles SE of [[Yokosuka, Japan]], hitting an [[Sikorsky SH-60 Seahawk|SH-60F]] and an [[EA-6B Prowler]] en route to the water. Crew LTJG Jon Vanbragt, LCDR Markus Gudmundsson ejected safely.
*31 January - A [[Colombia]]n government [[UH-60 Black Hawk]] helicopter on an anti-narcotics mission crashes in heavy fog near Manguipayan, Colombia killing all 20 on board.
*31 March - An [[Lockheed MC-130|MC-130H Combat Talon II]], USAF ''87-0127'', c/n 5118, ''Wrath 11'', of the [[7th Special Operations Squadron]], [[352d Special Operations Group]], [[RAF Mildenhall]], departs Tirana-Rinas Airport, Albania, for a night training mission to work on terrain-following and avoidance skills, airdrops and landing using night-vision goggles. The aircraft was flying {{convert|300|ft|m}} above the mountainous terrain when it was approaching a ridge. The airplane was not able to clear the ridge and stalled as the crew attempted to climb away. The aircraft struck the ridge, destroying the aircraft and killing all nine crew members on board.
*2 April - [[Royal Australian Navy]] [[Westland Sea King|Westland Sea King Mk50a]], ''N16-100'', '(9)02', helicopter ''[[2005 Nias Island WS-61 Sea King crash|Shark 02]]'' of [[817 Squadron RAN]] crashes on the [[Indonesia]]n island of [[Nias]] while providing humanitarian support following the [[2005 Sumatra earthquake]], killing 9 [[Australian Defence Force]] personnel on board.&lt;ref&gt;Stamford, Lincs., UK: Air Forces Monthly, compiled by Dave Allport, October 2005, Number 210, page 75.&lt;/ref&gt;
*18 April - A [[United States Air Force]]  [[F-16C Fighting Falcon|F-16D]] crashed next to the Ashley River near Charleston, South Carolina. The two crew members ejected safely. Both the main power and backup power failed moments before the crash, the pilot said.
*18 July - An [[F/A-18 Hornet|F/A-18E Hornet]] and an [[F/A-18 Hornet|F/A-18F Hornet]] from [[NAS Lemoore]], California, collide over the [[China Lake]], California, weapons testing ground.  The pilot of the E is KWF, while the two crew of F eject with injuries.
*15 August - A [[US Navy]] [[C-2 Greyhound|C-2A Greyhound]] makes successful [[belly landing]] at [[Naval Air Station Norfolk]], Virginia after undercarriage refuses to extend. Aircraft had departed Norfolk for [[NAS Pensacola]], Florida, when problems were detected. Aircraft circled for two hours to burn fuel before making successful landing. None of 25 on board were injured.
*5 September - [[Sukhoi Su-33]] landing on the [[Russian aircraft carrier Admiral Kuznetsov|Russian aircraft carrier ''Admiral Kuznetsov'']] at 1627 hrs. gets the trap, but arresting wire breaks and the fighter goes off the deck into the North Atlantic, pilot Sub Colonel Yuri Korneev ejecting immediately. Jet sinks in ~1,000 metres of water, pilot deploys raft from his survival pack and is rescued by a [[Kamov Ka-27|Ka-27P]] rescue helicopter and brought on board in a &quot;normal condition.&quot; According to a source in Naval Headquarters, &quot;it is possible that the pilot also made a mistake during the incident. The jet pilot, according to instructions, should have revved the engine after the cable broke and performed an emergency takeoff. However, the fault of the pilot can be determined only after analysis from the Su-33’s black box,&quot; reported ''[[Kommersant]]''. Capt. Of First Rank Igor Dygalo, head of the press center of the Main Staff of the Navy, said that the black box released as it was designed and surfaced after the plane sank. This was the first loss of the type during a &quot;sea flight.&quot; &lt;ref&gt;http://www.kommersant.com/p606360/r_1/Su-33_Landed_in_the_Bottom/&lt;/ref&gt;
*15 September - Russian Air Force [[Su-27]] ''Flanker'' of the 6th Air Force, 177th Fighter Regiment, during a flight between [[St. Petersburg]] and [[Kaliningrad]], for unknown reasons veers off its course while travelling over neutral waters of the Baltic Sea, enters Lithuanian airspace and crashes in [[Jurbarkas]] region, [[Lithuania]]. No one is harmed during the incident, and pilot Maj. Velery Troyanov ejects safely.&lt;ref&gt;Stamford, Lincs., UK: Air Forces Monthly, November 2005, Number 212, page 4.&lt;/ref&gt;
*6 December - An [[Islamic Republic of Iran Air Force]] [[C-130|C-130E Hercules]], ''5-8519'', c/n 4399, '''[[Iranian Air Force C-130 crash in Tehran|crashes]]''' into an apartment building in [[Tehran]], [[Iran]]. Ninety-four people on board were killed as well as 14 in the building.&lt;ref&gt;[[Lars Olausson|Olausson, Lars]], ''Lockheed Hercules Production List - 1954-2009'' - 26th ed., Såtenäs, Sweden, April 2008. Self-published. No [[ISBN]], page 75&lt;/ref&gt;

==2006==
*3 January - An [[United States Army]] [[Sikorsky Aircraft|Sikorsky]] [[UH-60 Black Hawk]] [[Helicopter]] crashes near [[Tal Afar]], [[Ninawa Governorate]], [[Iraq]].  The aircraft, part of a two-Black Hawk helicopter team, was travelling between military bases when the accident occurred resulting in 12 fatalities.&lt;ref&gt;http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/world/middle_east/4592622.stm  BBC News Channel Iraq US helicopter crash kills 12&lt;/ref&gt;
*10 January - A  US Navy [[T-39 Sabreliner]] of [[VT-86]], en route from [[Chattanooga, Tennessee]] to [[NAS Pensacola]], Florida, on a low-level navigation training mission fails to arrive at ~1500 hrs. as expected. The wreckage is found late 11 January near [[LaFayette, Georgia]]. All four personnel on board were killed, a Navy instructor, a Navy student, an Air Force student and a civilian contract pilot, said Navy Lt. j.g. Sean Robertson, a public affairs officer. Their identities were not immediately released.&lt;ref&gt;Associated Press, &quot;''Navy Training Jet Found with no survivors. Prayers for the families....''&quot;, Thursday 12 January 2006.&lt;/ref&gt;
*19 January - A [[Slovak Air Force]] [[Antonov An-24]] carrying peacekeepers from [[Kosovo]] '''[[2006 Slovak Air Force Antonov An-24 crash|crashes]]''' near [[Telkibánya]], Hungary. Of the 43 people on board, only one survived.
*3 April - [[United States Air Force|USAF]] [[C-5 Galaxy|C-5B Galaxy]], ''84-0059'', of [[436th Airlift Wing]]/[[512th Airlift Wing|512th Airlift Wing AF Reserve]], crashes in field one mile (1.6&amp;nbsp;km) short of runway during landing approach to [[Dover AFB]], [[Delaware]]. All 17 on board survive, although three are seriously injured.  Cause was found to be aircrew error as the pilots and flight engineers did not properly configure, maneuver and power the aircraft during approach and landing.&lt;ref&gt;Stamford, Lincs., UK: Air Forces Monthly, compiled by Dave Allport, August 2006, Number 221, page 74.&lt;/ref&gt;
*5 May - During the Children's Day flight exhibition ([[Suwon|Suwon Air Base]], [[South Korea]]), Capt. Kim Do-hyun of the [[Republic of Korea Air Force]]'s [[Black Eagle team|Black Eagles]] display team is killed when he loses control of his [[A-37 Dragonfly|A-37B Dragonfly]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web| last =  Mitchell| first = Terence
| authorlink =| coauthors =| title = Pilot Deaths Put F-15 Deal in Doubt - Korea stunned by deaths of 3 pilots in less than a month | work =| publisher =Ohmynews| date = 2006-06-10| url = http://english.ohmynews.com/ArticleView/article_view.asp?menu=A11100&amp;no=297645&amp;rel_no=1&amp;back_url=| format = 
| doi = | accessdate =July 6, 2008 }}&lt;/ref&gt;
*23 May - A [[Greek Air Force|Greek]] [[F-16C Fighting Falcon|F-16C Block 52 Fighting Falcon]], ''514'', of 343 Mira, and [[Turkish Air Force|Turkish]] [[F-16C Fighting Falcon]], ''93-0684'', of 192 Filo, collide over the [[Aegean Sea]] as the Greek pilot attempts to intercept the Turkish, after an alleged airspace violation. The Greek pilot, Flight Lieutenant Konstantinos Iliakis, is presumed dead, but the Turkish pilot, 1st Lieutenant Halil Ibrahim Ozdemir, is rescued.&lt;ref&gt;Stamford, Lincs., UK: Air Forces Monthly, compiled by Dave Allport, August 2006, Number 221, page 75.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;http://www.f-16.net/aircraft-database/F-16/mishaps-and-accidents/year/2006/&lt;/ref&gt;
*3 June - A [[People's Liberation Army Air Force]] converted [[KJ 200]] (converted from [[Shaanxi Y-8]]), ''Y-8F-600'', [[Airborne Early Warning and Control|AWACS]] '''[[2006 People's Liberation Army Air Force KJ-200 crash|crashes]]''' in [[Guangde County]] in the People's Republic of China.  All 40 people on board died.&lt;ref&gt;Stamford, Lincs., UK: Air Forces Monthly, compiled by Dave Allport, August 2006, Number 221, page 76.&lt;/ref&gt;
*26 June - [[U.S. Navy]] [[VFA-122]] squadron pilot Brian R. Deforge, 25, dies when his [[F/A-18 Hornet]] collides with another over [[Fort Hunter Liggett]], N of [[San Luis Obispo, California]].  The other pilot successfully ejects and survives.&lt;ref&gt;Griswold, Lewis, and Eddie Jimenez, &quot;Two Navy Officers Killed In NAS Lemoore Jet Crash&quot;, ''[[Fresno Bee]]'', 6 April 2011.&lt;/ref&gt;
*13 July - A [[Royal Air Force]] [[BAE Harrier II|BAE Harrier II GR.9]] crashes after the pilot ejects near [[Kidlington]] in [[Oxfordshire]] in the United Kingdom.
*2 September - A [[Royal Air Force]] [[Hawker-Siddeley Nimrod|Hawker-Siddeley Nimrod MR.2]] [[NATO]] reconnaissance plane, ''XV230'', '''[[Royal Air Force Nimrod crash in Afghanistan|crashes]]''' near [[Kandahar]], [[Afghanistan]] after a fire and explosion caused by a fuel leak. All 14 crew on board are killed.
*14 September - A [[US Air Force]] [[F-16 Fighting Falcon|F-16CJ/D Block 50B Fighting Falcon]], ''91-0337'', of the [[22d Fighter Squadron]], [[52d Fighter Wing]], based out of [[Spangdahlem Air Base]], Germany, crashes in the nearby village of [[Oberkail]] after a landing gear failure prevents it from making a controlled landing. The pilot, 1st Lt. Trevor Merrell, ejects safely after aiming his aircraft towards a vacant cow pasture, where it crashes causing no injuries.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.stripes.com/article.asp?section=104&amp;article=40055&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;http://www.f-16.net/aircraft-database/F-16/mishaps-and-accidents/year/2006/16/&lt;/ref&gt;
*17 September - In the [[2006 Nigerian Air Force Dornier 228 crash]], fifteen are killed, including many senior officers.
*29 November - Two members of the [[Australian Army]] are killed and seven are injured when a [[Sikorsky S-70|S-70A-9 Black Hawk]] helicopter, ''A25-221'', of 171 Aviation Squadron,  hits the deck of {{HMAS|Kanimbla|L 51|6}} and crashes off [[Fiji]].
*16 December - A [[Mexican Air Force]] [[Antonov An-32|Antonov An-32B]], ''3103'', of 3 Grupo Aero/EATP 301,  crashes into the sea off the coast of Mexico, near [[Acapulco]]. The four crew members on board are killed.
*18 December - The [[Lockheed Martin Polecat]] [[UAV]] aircraft crashes due to an &quot;irreversible unintentional failure in the flight termination ground equipment, which caused the aircraft's automatic fail-safe flight termination mode to activate,&quot; cited by Lockheed Martin.

==2007==
*24 January - [[Ecuador]]ian Defence Minister [[Guadalupe Larriva]], her 17-year-old daughter and five army officers are killed when two [[Aérospatiale]] [[SA.342|SA.342L Gazelle]] military helicopters, ''EE-343'' and ''EE-360'', of Grupo Aéreo 43, collide near [[Manta Air Base]] at 2019 hrs. during night training.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |url=http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/world/americas/6297093.stm|title=Crash kills Ecuador defence chief|date=2007-01-25 | publisher=[[BBC News]]| accessdate = 2007-01-26}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Stamford, Lincs., UK: Air Forces Monthly, compiled by Dave Allport, March 2007, Number 228, pages 78.&lt;/ref&gt;
*2 February - A [[HAL Dhruv]] helicopter, part of the Saarang Helicopter Aerobatics team loses altitude and crashes while practicing for the Aero India-2007 at the Yelahanka Air Base near [[Bangalore]], India. The pilot is severely injured, and the co-pilot is killed. The Saarang team continue their planned performance for the airshow.
*18 February - A [[United States Army]] [[MH-47|MH-47E Chinook]], ''92-00472'', of 2-[[160th Special Operations Aviation Regiment]], crashes in southeastern [[Afghanistan]] due to a sudden, unexplained loss of power and control killing eight and wounding 14.
*12 April - An unarmed [[Panavia Tornado|Tornado ECR]] of the [[Luftwaffe|German Air Force]] crashes in a rock face {{coord|46.550328|N|7.923805|E|type:landmark_region:CH-BE|name=Crash site near Lauterbrunnen}} near [[Lauterbrunnen]], Switzerland, killing the pilot. The weapons system officer ejects and is rescued severely injured from the rock face by a local helicopter rescue team. The crash occurs minutes after refueling in [[Emmen, Switzerland|Emmen]] during an authorized navigation training in the [[Swiss Alps]] while returning to Germany from a long-distance flight to [[Corsica]], France.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.luftwaffe.de/portal/a/luftwaffe/kcxml/04_Sj9SPykssy0xPLMnMz0vM0Y_QjzKLN483dDLyBMmB2CZhxvqREIY5TCzAECIEVheUkqrv65Gfm6rvrR-gX5AbGlHu6KgIAL6ZKJE!/delta/base64xml/L2dJQSEvUUt3QS80SVVFLzZfN18xQjJJ?yw_contentURL=%2F01DB060000000001%2FW2727L2U978INFODE%2Fcontent.jsp|title=Jagdbomber der Luftwaffe in der Schweiz abgestürzt|date=2007-04-12 | publisher=[[German Air Force]]| accessdate = 2007-05-03}} (in German)&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.blick.ch/news/schweiz/artikel60285|title=Kampfjet abgestürzt!|date=2007-04-12 | publisher=[[Blick]]| accessdate = 2007-05-03}} (in German, map source)&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.bloomberg.com/apps/news?pid=20601100&amp;sid=a3wDghGT34cE&amp;refer=germany|title=German Military Jet Crashes in Switzerland; One Dead|date=2007-04-12 | publisher=[[Bloomberg L.P.|Bloomberg]]| accessdate = 2007-05-03}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*21 April - A [[United States Navy]] [[Blue Angels]] [[F/A-18 Hornet]], BuNo ''162437'', '''[[2007 Blue Angels South Carolina crash|crashes]]''' into a residential neighborhood while performing at an airshow in [[Beaufort, South Carolina]], in the United States, killing the pilot. Military investigators blame pilot for his fatal crash. A report obtained by The Associated Press said that Lieutenant Commander Kevin Davis got disoriented and crashed after not properly tensing his abdominal muscles to counter the gravitational forces of a high-speed turn.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.wkrg.com/local/article/blue_angels_crash_blamed_on_pilot/9111/ Blue Angels Crash Blamed on Pilot - Blue Angels Lieutenant Commander Kevin Davis Pilot Error Kevin Davis&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;
*27 April - A [[Armed Forces of the Russian Federation|Russian military]] [[Mil Mi-8]] transport helicopter '''[[2007 Russian military Mil Mi-8 crash|crashes]]''' near [[Shatoy]], [[Chechnya]] in Russia. The incident occurred during the [[Battle of Shatoy (2007)|Battle of Shatoy]] and killed the crew and 17 [[spetsnaz]] (Russian special forces) soldiers on board.
*1 May - A [[Dassault Mirage III]] of the [[Fuerza Aérea Argentina]] ([[Argentine Air Force]]) crashes at 1110 hrs. at [[Morón Airport and Air Base|Morón Air Base]] after making a low pass during a &quot;baptism of fire&quot; day celebration, observing the opening of combat in the 1982 Falklands/Malvinas War. The pilot, Lt. Marcos Peretti, apparently encountered a fogbank after making the pass. He did not eject after steering the aircraft away from populated areas and was killed. Defence Minister Nilda Garré who presided over the main celebration ordered all Mirage aircraft grounded until a full investigation into the accident is completed &quot;The causes of the accident are under investigation&quot;, said minister Garré adding that &quot;Mirages are grounded until we determine how the accident happened; the pilot was in contact until a minute before the accident&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;http://en.mercopress.com/2007/05/01/malvinas-mirage-iii-crashes-during-baptism-of-fire-celebration&lt;/ref&gt;
*6 May - A [[French Air Force]] [[de Havilland Canada DHC-6 Twin Otter]] transporting [[Multinational Force and Observers]] crashes into a truck while making an emergency landing near El-Thamad, [[Egypt]] killing all nine people on board.
*11 May - A [[Republic of China Air Force]] [[Northrop F-5]] '''[[2007 Hukou F-5F crash|crashes]]''' in [[Hukou, Hsinchu|Hukou]], [[Republic of China|Taiwan]], killing five people.
*24 May - A [[Air Force of Peru|Peruvian Air Force]] [[de Havilland Canada DHC-6 Twin Otter|de Havilland Canada DHC-6-300]], ''FAP-303'', c/n 483, crashes in dense jungle after taking off from Pampa Hermosa, [[Peru]]. Of the 20 people on board, 13 were killed.&lt;ref&gt;[http://aviation-safety.net/database/record.php?id=20070524-0 ASN Aircraft accident de Havilland Canada DHC-6 Twin Otter 300 FAP-303 Pampa Hermosa&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;
*13 June - A [[Mongolian People's Army|Mongolian military]] [[Mil Mi-8]] helicopter crashes in [[Selenge Province]], [[Mongolia]] while en route to a forest fire killing 15 of the 22 people on board.
*30 July - FA-18C from VFA-195 crashed after the pilot inadvertently ejected while on emergency night approach to [[USS Kitty Hawk (CV-63)|USS ''Kitty Hawk'' (CV 63)]]. The aircraft continued to fly for nearly 20 minutes before crashing into the sea 400 miles SE of Guam. The pilot was safely recovered.
*8 August - An [[Royal Air Force|RAF]] [[Aérospatiale Puma|Puma HC.1]], ''ZA934'', 'BZ', of 33 Squadron, crashes in a wooded area of [[Hudswell Grange]], W of [[Catterick Garrison]], [[North Yorkshire]], UK. Two RAF crew, pilot and aircraft commander Flt. Lt. David Oxer Hanson Sale, and crewman Sgt. Phillip Anthony &quot;Taff&quot; Burfoot died in the crash, while Army Pvt. Sean Tait, [[Royal Regiment of Scotland]], died two days later in hospital. Nine others injured but survive.
*15 August - Lts. Ryan Betton, Cameron Hall and Jerry Smith were killed when their [[E-2C Hawkeye]] from Carrier Airborne Early Warning Squadron 120, based at the [[Naval Station Norfolk]], Virginia, crashed in the Atlantic Ocean off [[North Carolina]] at ~2300 hrs. An investigation was unable to determine the cause of the crash, according to a copy of the Judge Advocate General final report — known as a JAGMAN — obtained by Navy Times. The plane catapulted off the deck of the carrier [[USS Harry S. Truman (CVN-75)|USS ''Harry S. Truman'']] and crashed into the water moments later. The carrier never received any emergency radio transmissions or acknowledgment by the mishap crew, according to the report.&lt;ref name=&quot;Tilghman, Andrew 2010&quot;&gt;Tilghman, Andrew, Staff writer, &quot;''Leak reportedly led to Hawkeye crash''&quot;, Navy News, Wednesday 31 March 2010.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;navytimes.com&quot;&gt;http://www.navytimes.com/news/2010/03/navy_hawkeye_crash_033110w/&lt;/ref&gt;
*30 August - [[B-52 Stratofortress|Boeing B-52H Stratofortress]], [[2007 United States Air Force nuclear weapons incident|accidentally loaded]] with six [[W80 (nuclear warhead)|W80]]-1 nuclear-armed [[AGM-129]] advanced [[cruise missile]]s flies from [[Minot Air Force Base]], [[North Dakota]], to [[Barksdale AFB]] in [[Louisiana]], where the unguarded aircraft sits on the tarmac for 10 hours undetected. Officers responsible for the security lapse at Minot are disciplined.
*7 September - A [[Sikorsky Aircraft|Sikorsky]] [[MH-53 Pave Low|MH-53M Pave Low IV]], ''69-05794'', of the [[20th Special Operations Squadron]], [[Hurlburt Field]], crashes near [[Duke Field]], Eglin Auxiliary Field 3, just before midnight when it suffers tail rotor gear box failure while in a hover.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.foia.af.mil/shared/media/document/AFD-090731-041.pdf&lt;/ref&gt; The helicopter was practicing a rescue extraction near a landing zone surrounded by trees more than {{convert|90|ft|m}} tall and had just been brought into a hover at {{convert|150|ft|m}} and was beginning to lower the rescue apparatus when the aircrew felt a shudder. Aircraft commander Lt. Col. Eugene Becker realizes that the tail rotor gears are failing, takes control of the aircraft and prepares to land. Once out of hover, it takes about 45 seconds to return to the LZ, and due to the confined space, Becker drops the chopper vertically but the shuddering worsens. &quot;We knew something was very, very wrong&quot;, stated Becker. &quot;all of the gear boxes were surging up and down and making quite a bit of racket.&quot; When the MH-53 is {{convert|20|ft|m}} above the ground Becker pushes what is left of the rotor's power to the maximum in order to cushion the landing. As soon as the Pave Low hits the ground, the tail rotor fails and the chopper starts spinning and rolls to port, but the sponson fuel tanks keep it from rolling over. Of the seven crew, only two are injured: Col. William Nelson, a flight surgeon from the Air Force Special Operations Command Surgeon General's Office, receives a head injury but walks away from the accident; MH-53 aerial gunner A1C Bradley Jordan suffers a leg fracture. Both men are released from hospital the following day. Lt. Col. Becker is awarded the Koren Kolligian Jr. trophy, one of the Air Force's top safety awards, in July 2008. According to the award nomination, a landing any more forceful could have been fatal to the crew.&lt;ref&gt;Moore, Mona, &quot;''Pilot of crash MH-53 receives safety award''&quot;, The Eglin Dispatch, Northwest Florida Daily News, Fort Walton Beach, Florida, Friday, 18 July 2008, Volume 2, Number 29, page 9.&lt;/ref&gt;
*7 November - An [[Romanian Air Force]] [[IAR 330|IAR-330 Puma SOCAT]] '''[[2007 Romanian Air Force IAR-330 SOCAT crash|crashes]]''' in [[Argeş County]], [[Romania]], killing all three crew members on board.
*6 December - a [[French Air Force]] twin-seat [[Dassault Rafale|Rafale]] aircraft with a single occupant, on a training flight from the Saint-Dizier base, crashes in an uninhabited part of the Neuvic parish in the Corrèze area, with the loss of its pilot.

==2008==
*6 January - An [[F/A-18 Hornet|F/A-18E Hornet]] has a mid air collision with an [[F/A-18 Hornet|F/A-18F Hornet]] over the North [[Persian Gulf]] during routine ops from the [[USS Harry S Truman (CVN-75)|USS ''Harry S Truman'']].  The pilot ejects and is recovered.
*12 January - A [[Republic of Macedonia|Macedonian]] [[Mil Mi-17]] transport helicopter [[2008 Macedonian Armed Forces Mil Mi-17 crash|'''crashes''']], ''VAM-304'', near [[Skopje]], [[Republic of Macedonia]], killing all 11 soldiers on board.&lt;ref&gt;Allport, Dave, &quot;''Damning Mi-17 Crash Report''&quot;, Air Forces Monthly, Stamford, Lincs, UK, Number 252, March 2009, page 72.&lt;/ref&gt;
*15 January - An [[F-16 Fighting Falcon|F-16C Block 30J Fighting Falcon]], ''87-0347'', of the [[482nd Fighter Wing]], [[Air Force Reserve Command]], based at [[Homestead Air Reserve Base]], Florida, crashes in the [[Gulf of Mexico]] near [[Key West]] at ~1930 hrs. during a training mission. The pilot, Major Peter S. Smith, ejects and is recovered by a [[U. S. Navy]] helicopter, transported to a local hospital for examination, and released. A board of officers is appointed to investigate the accident.&lt;ref&gt;Niceville, Florida, &quot;''F-16 crashes; pilot okay''&quot;, Eglin Flyer, Bayou Enterprises, Inc., Friday, 18 February 2008, page 1.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;f-16.net&quot;&gt;http://www.f-16.net/aircraft-database/F-16/mishaps-and-accidents/year/2008/&lt;/ref&gt;
*22 January - A [[Pakistan Air Force]] [[Cessna T-37 Tweet]] trainer faced mechanical failure while in first solo flight of [[Pilot Officer]] [[Raja Jahanzeb]] flying over [[Topi,_Khyber_Pakhtunkhwa|Topi]], [[Pakistan]]. Declining ejection orders to prevent loss of life on the ground he chose to crash land the plane on a campus road of [[GIK Institute]] merely avoiding faculty buildings and blew up into pieces on crashing. The crash killed the pilot and a gardener. [[Raja Jahanzeb]] was posthumously awarded [[Awards_and_decorations_of_the_Pakistan_Armed_Forces|Tamgha-e-Basalat]] (Medal of Good Conduct).&lt;ref&gt;http://jang.com.pk/thenews/feb2008-weekly/us-29-02-2008/p15.htm&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;http://www.ejection-history.org.uk/project/year_pages/2008_Losses.htm&lt;/ref&gt;
*23 January - A Polish military airplane [[EADS CASA C-295]], '019', c/n S-043, crashed in forested area near Polish city [[Miroslawiec]] killing all 20 people aboard - 16 [[Polish Air Force]] officers (incl. one [[General Officer|general]], Gen. [[Andrzej Andrzejewski]], who survived an ejection from a [[Su-22|Su-22M-4K]] on 18 August 2003, and six [[Colonel (United States)|colonel]]s) and 4 crew.&lt;ref&gt;[http://aviation-safety.net/database/record.php?id=20080123-0 ASN Aircraft accident Casa C-295M 019 Miroslawiec AB&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;
*28 January - A [[Portuguese Air Force]] [[F-16 Fighting Falcon|F-16B Block 20 MLU Fighting Falcon]], ''83-1171'', crashes in [[Monte Real Air Base|Monte Real, Portugal]] while performing a test run after going through extensive maintenance. The pilot, Lt. Col. João 'Skipper' Pereira, safely ejects.&lt;ref name=&quot;f-16.net&quot;/&gt;
*1 February - An [[United States Air Force]] [[McDonnell Douglas]] [[F-15 Eagle]] from the [[199th Fighter Squadron]], [[154th Wing]] of the [[Hawaii Air National Guard]] flying on a routine training flight crashes into the Pacific Ocean near [[Oahu]], Hawaii.  After losing control at low altitude simulating air-to-air combat the pilot ejected about {{convert|60|mi|km}} south of the Honolulu International Airport and was rescued by an [[United States Coast Guard]] helicopter.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.airforcetimes.com/news/2008/02/ap_f15crash_080202/&lt;/ref&gt;
*13 February - A [[United States Marine Corps|USMC]] [[AV-8B Harrier II]] from [[VMA-542]] crashes at the Open Ground Farms in [[Carteret County, North Carolina]] after pilot Capt Ian E. Stephenson fails to readjust his engine nozzles from the hover-stop position, making the plane incapable of staying in the air. He is able to safely eject.&lt;ref name=&quot;DN&quot;&gt;{{cite web
  | last =
  | first =
  | authorlink =
  | coauthors =
  | title =Pilot Error Blamed in 2008 Harrier Crash
  | work =
  | publisher =The Daily News, Jacksonville, N.C.
  | date =2009-04-09
  | url =http://www.military.com/news/article/April-2009/pilot-error-blamed-in-2008-harrier-crash.html?col=1186032310810
  | format =
  | doi =
  | accessdate = 2009-04-09}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*20 February - Two [[F-15 Eagle|F-15C Eagle]]s of the [[58th Fighter Squadron]], [[33d Fighter Wing]], [[Eglin AFB]], Florida, collide over the [[Gulf of Mexico]] ~{{convert|50|mi|km}} S of [[Tyndall AFB]], Florida, killing 1st Lt. Ali Jivanjee.  Capt. Tucker Hamilton ejected from the other fighter and survived. Airframes involved were F-15C-26-MC, ''79-0075'', c/n 0624/C144, and F-15C-32-MC, ''81-0043'', c/n 0793/C226. Both pilots ejected and one was rescued from the Gulf by the fishing boat ''Niña'', owned by Bart Niquet of [[Lynn Haven, Florida]], which was guided to the pilot by an [[HC-144 Ocean Sentry|HC-144A Ocean Sentry]] aircraft. A 1st SOW [[AC-130|AC-130H]] and an [[MV-22 Osprey]] were also diverted to the scene to help search as were five [[Coast Guard]] aircraft and two vessels. An [[HH-60 Jayhawk]] from Coast Guard Aviation Training Center Mobile lifted the pilot from the fishing boat and evacuated him to the Eglin Hospital. The second pilot was rescued from the Gulf by an [[HH-60 Jayhawk]] from [[CGAS Clearwater]] and also taken to the Eglin Hospital. One pilot subsequently died several hours later from his injuries.&lt;ref&gt;Books, Kenneth, &quot;''Mid-air collision kills pilot''&quot;, Eglin Flyer, Bayou Enterprises, Inc., Niceville, Florida, Friday, 22 February 2008, pages 1, 9.&lt;/ref&gt;  An accident investigation released 25 August 2008 found that the accident was the result of pilot error and not mechanical failure. Both pilots failed to clear their flight paths and anticipate their impending high-aspect, midair impact, according to Brig. Gen. Joseph Reynes, Jr., Air Combat Command's inspector general who led the investigation.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;Pilot Error Blamed&quot;, Air Force Magazine, November 2008, Volume 91, Number 11, page 20.&lt;/ref&gt; This was the first crash involving an Eglin F-15 since a fatal crash on 30 April 2002.
*23 February - A [[B-2 Spirit|B-2A Spirit]], ''89-0127'', 'WM', &quot;Spirit of Kansas&quot;, of the [[393rd Bomb Squadron]], [[509th Bomb Wing]], [[Whiteman AFB]], [[Missouri]], crashed shortly after takeoff from [[Andersen Air Force Base]] in [[Guam]].  Both pilots ejected from the plane before it crashed, the aircraft was destroyed. Moisture in flight sensors caused steep pitch-up and stall to port. See: [[Andersen Air Force Base B-2 crash]].
*3 March - An [[Iraqi Air Force]] [[Mil Moscow Helicopter Plant|Mil]] [[Mi-17]] helicopter crashes in a dust storm near [[Bayji, Iraq]], killing seven members of the IAF, as well as SSgt. Christopher S. Frost, 24, of Waukesha, Wisconsin, a USAF public affairs specialist who deployed to the Multinational Security Transition Command-Iraq from the 377th Air Base Wing at Kirtland AFB, New Mexico.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;Airman Killed in Helicopter Crash&quot;, Air Force Magazine, May 2008, Volume 91, Number 5, page 18.&lt;/ref&gt;
*7 March - Failure of a brake metering valve causes a [[B-1 Lancer|B-1B Lancer]] bomber of the 28th Bomb Wing to roll forward into two rescue vehicles after engine shutdown at [[Andersen AFB]], Guam, Air Combat Command said 3 September 2008. Damage to the B-1B and the two vehicles totaled $5.8 million.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;News Notes&quot;, Air Force Magazine, November 2008, Volume 91, Number 11, page 26.&lt;/ref&gt; The &quot;Bone&quot; had stopped over at Andersen while transiting home to [[Ellsworth AFB]], South Dakota from the Singapore Air Show and had taken off for home but returned after the crew declared an in-flight emergency. The aircraft stopped at designated spot off the runway to be met by emergency apparatus, but rolled into the vehicles unexpectedly.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;B-1B Accident on Guam&quot;, Air Force Magazine, May 2008, Volume 91, Number 5, page 24.&lt;/ref&gt;
*14 March - An [[F-16 Fighting Falcon|F-16C Block 25D Fighting Falcon]], ''84-1273'',&lt;ref name=&quot;f-16.net&quot;/&gt;  flown by pilot 2nd Lt. David J. Mitchell, 26, of Amherst, Ohio, crashes during training mission in a remote area three miles (5&amp;nbsp;km) S of [[Alamo Lake, Arizona]]. His body is located in a ravine near the aircraft wreckage. Mitchell, of the [[Ohio Air National Guard]]'s [[180th Fighter Wing]] at [[Toledo Express Airport]], [[Swanton, Ohio]], was assigned to the [[62d Fighter Squadron]] at [[Luke AFB]], Arizona since November 2007 as a student pilot. He had 237 total flying hours, ~26 in the F-16.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;F-16 Crash Claims Pilot&quot;, Air Force Magazine, May 2008, Volume 91, Number 5, page 18.&lt;/ref&gt;
*4 April - A [[USAF]] [[B-1 Lancer|B-1B Lancer]], ''86-0116'', of the [[28th Bomb Wing]], suffers hydraulic failure while taxiing after landing at [[Al Udeid Air Base]], [[Qatar]], veering off runway and catching fire. Four crew evacuate safely but airframe is burnt out after bomb load explodes.&lt;ref&gt;Allport, Dave, &quot;''Attrition''&quot;, Air Forces Monthly, Stamford, Lincs, UK, Number 243, June 2008, page 94.&lt;/ref&gt;
*21 May - A [[Serbian Air Force]] single-seat [[J-22 Orao]] ground attack aircraft flown by [[Major]] Tomas Janik crashed near the village of [[Baranda]]. The aircraft that crashed was wearing serial ''25114'' and was operational with the 241 Fighter-Bomber Aviation Squadron, of [[98th Air Base]] [[Kraljevo-Lađevci Airport|Lađevci]]. The flight went well until 1130 hours local time when pilot Major Janik experienced problems with his plane and was forced to eject. The aircraft went down in the vicinity of the village [[Baranda]] and was completely destroyed.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.airserbia.com/news/42/Serbian-jetfighter-and-helicopter-crashed-within-days]&lt;/ref&gt;
*13 June - Two [[United States Navy]] jets collided over the [[NAS Fallon]], [[Nevada]] high desert training range, killing a pilot of the [[F/A-18 Hornet|F/A-18C Hornet]], based at [[NAS Oceana]], [[Virginia]]. Two crew aboard the [[F-5 Tiger]] ejected safely and were rescued.
*8 July - Three Airmen of the 319th Special Operations Squadron, 1st Special Operations Wing, avoid serious injury when the leased [[Pilatus PC-12]] they are training in crashes at the end of the runway at [[Hurlburt Field]], Florida, Eglin Auxiliary Field 9, at ~2330 hrs. as they attempt a landing. The initial investigation finds that the turboprop encountered [[wake turbulence]] from another aircraft that had landed shortly before the accident. As a precaution, the three crew were taken to the Eglin hospital and released the same afternoon. Hurlburt leases the PC-12 to train Airmen for the U-28A, the Air Force's version of the single-engine utility aircraft, used in combat for intra-theatre support for the special operations forces.&lt;ref&gt;Moore, Mona, &quot;''Small plane crashes on Hurlburt runway''&quot;, The Eglin Dispatch, Northwest Florida Daily News, Fort Walton Beach, Florida, Friday, 11 July 2008, Volume 2, Number 28, page 6.&lt;/ref&gt;
*21 July - A [[U.S. Air Force]] [[B-52 Stratofortress|B-52H-155-BW Stratofortress]], ''60-0053'', c/n 464-418, &quot;Louisiana Fire&quot;, crashed into the Pacific Ocean approximately 25 nautical miles (46&amp;nbsp;km) northwest of [[Apra Harbor]], [[Guam]],&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.wnbc.com/news/16939030/detail.html?rss=ny&amp;psp=nationalnews www.wnbc.com: ''B-52 Bomber Crashes Off Guam'' (21.7.2008)]&lt;/ref&gt; after taking off from [[Andersen Air Force Base]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.kuam.com/news/29067.aspx KUAM News: Search continues for those aboard crashed B-52]&lt;/ref&gt; The aircraft was about to participate in a flyover for the [[Liberation Day]] parade in [[Hagåtña]] when it crashed  at 9:45 AM [[Chamorro Time Zone|ChST]] (2345 [[UTC]]), 15 minutes before the parade was scheduled to start.  There were no survivors.
*30 July - A [[U.S. Air Force]] [[F-15 Eagle|F-15D Eagle]], ''85-0131'', crashed on the [[Nevada Test and Training Range]] ~{{convert|50|mi|km}} E of [[Goldfield, Nevada]], at ~1130 hrs. The F-15D, of the [[65th Aggressor Squadron]], [[57th Aggressor Training Group]], [[Nellis Air Force Base]], was participating in a combat training mission as part of Exercise Red Flag 08-03. Air Force officials identified the pilot who died as Lt. Col. Thomas A. Bouley, commander of the 65th AS at Nellis. A United Kingdom [[Royal Air Force]] Tornado F.3 pilot assigned to the USAF's 64th AGRS&lt;ref&gt;&quot;F-15 Crash Kills Pilot&quot;, Air Force Magazine, October 2008, Volume 91, Number 10, page 16.&lt;/ref&gt;  was with him and was taken to Mike O'Callaghan Federal Hospital at Nellis. The pilot arrived ~1330 hrs. Wednesday, the Air Force said. The pilot was in stable condition and under observation. The Royal Air Force pilot's name was withheld while the investigation into the crash continues.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.lasvegassun.com/news/2008/jul/30/f-15-crashes-in-nevada-desert-during-training/&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.lasvegassun.com/news/2008/jul/31/air-force-identifies-pilot-killed-in-plane-crash/ Air Force identifies pilot killed in plane crash - Las Vegas Sun&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;
*24 September - A [[Serbian Air Force]] [[G-4 Super Galeb]] basic trainer/light attack jet aircraft with serial number ''23736'' flown by [[Lt. Colonel]] Ištvan Kanas crashed at [[Batajnica Air Base]]. Ištvan Kanas (aged 43), pilot of Flight Test Section (Sektor za letna ispitivanja - SLI) unfortunately did not survive the crash. Kanas was a top Serbian test pilot and member of the private aerobatics team and former member of [[Leteće Zvezde]] aerobatics team, officials say he was practicing for an upcoming Belgrade 2008 airshow. He was a father of two.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.mod.gov.rs/novi.php?action=fullnews&amp;id=649&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;http://www.b92.net/eng/news/society-article.php?yyyy=2008&amp;mm=09&amp;dd=24&amp;nav_id=53717&lt;/ref&gt; This is the second G-4 Super Galeb ever to crash with tragic consequences after 21 years.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.b92.net/info/vesti/index.php?yyyy=2008&amp;mm=09&amp;dd=24&amp;nav_id=320295]&lt;/ref&gt;
*17 October - The [[Russian Air Force]] grounds all its [[MiG-29]]s following a crash in [[Siberia]] on this date.&lt;ref&gt;. [http://en.rian.ru/russia/20081017/117800830.html &quot;Russia suspends MiG-29 fighter flights over Siberia crash.&quot;] ''[[RIA Novosti]]'', 17 October 2008. Retrieved: 28 March 2009.&lt;/ref&gt; The fighter came down {{convert|60|km|mi|sp=us}} from the Domna airfield during a regular training flight. The pilot ejected safely.&lt;ref&gt;http://en.rian.ru/russia/20090204/119984853.html&lt;/ref&gt;
*5 December - A [[MiG-29]] crash at [[Chita, Zabaykalsky Krai|Chita]] in the district of [[Zabaykalsky Krai]], [[Siberia]] at 0612 hrs. Moscow time, kills the pilot.
*8 December - A [[2008 San Diego F-18 crash|USMC F/A-18D-30-MC Hornet (Lot 12), BuNo ''164017'', crashed into a neighborhood]], University City, coming down two miles (3&amp;nbsp;km) west of [[MCAS Miramar]], [[California]], just after the Marine pilot, Lieutenant Dan Neubauer, from [[VMFAT-101]],&lt;ref name=&quot;MarinesTV&quot;&gt;[http://www.marines.mil/news/Pages/marinestv.aspx/?fr_story=a2d343f26a41ace3fb015dd38bf91da82a87136e F-18 crashes in California] by the [[United States Marine Corps]]&lt;/ref&gt; ejected. Four fatalities on the ground. The Hornet was being flown from the [[USS Abraham Lincoln (CVN-72)|USS ''Abraham Lincoln'']].&lt;ref&gt;Hersham, Surrey, UK, &quot;''Recent Casualties''&quot;, Combat Aircraft, Ian Allen Publishing, February–March 2009, Volume 10, Number 1, page 20.&lt;/ref&gt; The commander of the fighter squadron involved in the crash, its top maintenance officer and two others have been relieved of duty as a result of the crash investigation. The pilot has been grounded pending a further review, Maj. Gen. Randolph Alles announced in March 2009.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news| url=http://www.cnn.com/2009/US/03/03/plane.crash/index.html | work=CNN | title=Marines sack 4 over deadly California plane crash - CNN.com | date=3 March 2009 | accessdate=8 May 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==2009==
*12 January - An [[UH-60 Blackhawk]] of the [[Texas Army National Guard]] crashes on the campus at [[Texas A&amp;M University]] just after take-off, killing 2nd Lt. Zachary Cook, 2008 Texas A&amp;M graduate, member of the Texas A&amp;M ROTC, and Aggie Corps of Cadets and injuring four other Army personnel. The helicopter was participating in the Rudder's Rangers Annual Winter Field Training.
[[File:C-17A 06-0002 No-wheels Landing Bagram Afghanistan lg.jpg|thumb|right|C-17A Globemaster III, ''06-0002'', &quot;Spirit of the Air Force&quot;, on Bagram Air Base runway after inadvertent night belly-landing in January 2009.]]
*15 January - An [[Afghan National Army Air Corps]] [[Mil Moscow Helicopter Plant|Mil]] [[Mil Mi-17|Mi-17]] ''Hip'' [[Helicopter]] crashes in [[Herat Province]] in western [[Afghanistan]].  The incident occurred in bad weather and travelling at low-altitude in a mountainous region resulting in 13 fatalities including the Afghan General Fazaludin Sayar.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.voanews.com/english/archive/2009-01/2009-01-15-voa28.cfm?CFID=292977602&amp;CFTOKEN=57371137&amp;jsessionid=84305ed506a5440fb2ff4850727467414291 Afghan General Killed in Helicopter Crash&lt;/ref&gt;
*17 January - A [[French Army]] [[Eurocopter]] [[Eurocopter AS 532|AS 532 Cougar]] [[Helicopter]] crashes into the [[Atlantic Ocean]] of the coast of [[Gabon]].  The helicopter on a routine exercise was flying from the [[amphibious assault ship]] the [[Foudre (L 9011)|FS ''Foudre'']] and the accident occurred shortly after take-off resulting in 2 injured and 8 fatalities from the [[13th Parachute Dragoon Regiment|13e Régiment de Dragons Parachutistes]] and the [[French Army Light Aviation|Aviation Légère de l'Armée de Terre]].&lt;ref&gt;http://infos.fncv.com/post/2009/01/18/Gabon-:-Crash-dun-helicoptere-Cougar-au-moins-2-militaires-OPEX-morts            Gabon : Crash d'un hélicoptère Cougar, au moins 7 militaires OPEX morts&lt;/ref&gt;
*20 January - Two [[Spanish Air Force]] [[Dassault Mirage F1]] on a training flight, collide in midair. The three pilots were found dead in the debris of the airplanes.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.typicallyspanish.com/news/publish/article_19701.shtml&lt;/ref&gt;
*21 January - An [[Indian Air Force]] [[Hindustan Aeronautics Limited|HAL]] [[HAL Kiran|HJT-16 Kiran Mk.2]] [[Trainer aircraft|military trainer aircraft]] from the No. 52 Squadron [[Surya Kiran]] (''Sun Rays'') Aerobatics display team based at the [[Bidar]] Air Force Station in [[Karnataka]], India crashed into a field during a routine training exercise killing the pilot.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.thaindian.com/newsportal/india-news/iafs-surya-kiran-pilot-killed-in-air-crash-in-karnataka_100145460.html Surya Kiran Aerobatics display team crash Jan 2009&lt;/ref&gt;
*26 January - A [[United States Army]] routine night exercise involving two [[Bell Helicopter|Bell]] [[OH-58 Kiowa]] [[Helicopter]] from the [[6th Cavalry Regiment (United States)|6th Cavalry Regiment]] based at [[Fort Drum]], [[New York]] collide in mid-air.  The accident occurred near the city of [[Kirkuk]] Northern [[Iraq]] resulting in 4 crew fatalities.&lt;ref&gt;http://edition.cnn.com/2009/WORLD/meast/01/26/iraq.deaths/index.html CNN.Com/World Four U.S. soldiers killed in Iraq crash&lt;/ref&gt;
*30 January - The pilots of a [[C-17A Globemaster III|C-17A Globemaster III Lot VIII]], ''06-0002'', c/n P-34, &quot;Spirit of the Air Force&quot;, of the [[16th Airlift Squadron]], [[437th Airlift Wing]], [[Charleston AFB]], South Carolina, distracted by a series of minor problems, neglect to lower the landing gear and belly the transport in at [[Bagram Air Base]], Afghanistan after dark. None of the six crew aboard are injured, but damages of $19 million are sustained by the airframe. Pilots are grounded pending a command review of the accident, an [[Air Mobility Command]] spokesman said. The automated [[ground proximity warning system]] was apparently accidentally turned off.&lt;ref&gt;Army Times, Military Times Media Group, Springfield, Virginia, 25 May 2009, page 28.&lt;/ref&gt; This is the first belly-landing of a C-17 in sixteen years of operation.
*9 February - A leased [[Pilatus UC-28]]A, ''06-0692'', with three personnel of the [[319th Special Operations Squadron]],  [[1st Special Operations Wing]] on board,  based at [[Hurlburt Field]], Florida, makes a gear-up landing at [[Craig Field (Alabama)]] at [[Selma, Alabama]] (formerly [[Craig Air Force Base]]), whilst  performing simulated engine failure approach, breaking off nosewheel and causing severe damage to nosewheel strut assembly, propeller and main undercarriage doors.  A board of officers will investigate the 1415 hrs. incident in which there were no injuries.&lt;ref&gt;Moore, Mona, &quot;Hurlburt aircraft makes hard landing&quot;, ''Northwest Florida Daily News'', Fort Walton Beach, Florida, Tuesday 10 February 2009, Volume 63, Number 11, page B2.&lt;/ref&gt; This accident has been classified as a Class A accident, indicating that fairly substantial damage was incurred.&lt;ref&gt;Allport, Dave, &quot;''Accident Report Updates''&quot;, Air Forces Monthly, Stamford, Lincs, UK, Number 255, June 2009, page 87.&lt;/ref&gt; Aircraft repaired and reported flying again by 29 April 2009.&lt;ref&gt;http://home.att.net/~jbaugher/2006.html&lt;/ref&gt;
*9 February - A [[Royal Air Force]] [[BAE Systems]] [[Harrier Jump Jet|Harrier T10]] (''ZH656'') on a routine training exercise from No. [[No. 20 Squadron RAF|20 Squadron (R)]] [[Operational conversion unit]] based at [[RAF Wittering]] crashes on the runway at [[RAF Akrotiri|Royal Air Force Station Akrotiri]], [[Cyprus]].  The 2 crew ejected safely from the aircraft which was damaged in a fire.&lt;ref&gt;http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/uk/7879658.stm BBC News UK.com UK personnel hurt in Cyprus crash&lt;/ref&gt;
*11 February - Two [[Grob G 115#Grob_Tutor|Grob Tutor]] aircraft collided above [[Porthcawl]], [[South Wales]] killing four people. The aircraft took off from [[RAF St Athan]] shortly before. Among the dead were two female teenage cousins and two instructor pilots.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news| url=http://www.timesonline.co.uk/tol/news/uk/article5716831.ece | work=The Times | location=London | title=Teenage cousins in midair crash were taking RAF taster flight | date=13 February 2009 | accessdate=8 May 2010 | first=Simon | last=de Bruxelles}}&lt;/ref&gt; See [[Porthcawl Mid-Air Collision]].
*18 February - A [[Colombian Air Force|Fuerza Aérea Colombiana]] [[Douglas Aircraft Company]] [[AC-47 Spooky]] intelligence-gathering plane of the Escuadrón de Combate Táctico 113 ''Avion Fantasma'' (ghost planes) crashed near the Comando Aéreo de Combate No 1  Airbase at [[Puerto Salgar]], [[Cundinamarca Department|Cundinamarca]], [[Colombia]].  The aircraft was on a training flight resulting in 5 crew fatalities.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.abs-cbnnews.com/world/02/18/09/colombian-military-plane-crash-kills-five-official ABS News.com Colombian military plane crash kills five&lt;/ref&gt;
*27 February - A [[Polish Army]] [[Mil Moscow Helicopter Plant|Mil]] [[Mil Mi-24|Mi-24]] ''Hind'' [[Helicopter]] crashes in bad weather into a forest near [[Toruń]], [[Kuyavian-Pomeranian Voivodeship|Kuyavian-Pomeranian Province]], Poland.  The aircraft from the 49 Regiment combat helicopters [[Pruszcz Gdański]] was on a night training flight for service in [[Afghanistan]] resulting in 2 crew injured and 1 fatality.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.tvn24.pl/0,10205,1593986,,,zawinil-czlowiek-lub-pogoda,raport_wiadomosc.html TVN24.pl Zawinił człowiek lub pogoda KATASTROFA MI-24&lt;/ref&gt;
*19 March - A small [[Beechcraft]] military plane [[2009 Quito B200 King Air crash|crashes]] into an apartment building in [[Quito]], [[Ecuador]], killing five on board and two on the ground.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news| url=http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/americas/7954173.stm | work=BBC News | title=Ecuador plane crash kills seven | date=20 March 2009 | accessdate=8 May 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news| url=http://www.cnn.com/2009/WORLD/americas/03/19/ecuador.plane/index.html | work=CNN | title=Ecuador: Seven die from Quito plane crash - CNN.com | date=20 March 2009 | accessdate=8 May 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*23 March - A [[Bundeswehr]] [[Luftwaffe]] [[Panavia Tornado]] PA-200, ''45+37'', from ''[[Jagdbombergeschwader 33]]''  crashes on the runway at [[Büchel]] Air Force Base, [[Rhineland-Palatinate]], Germany. The aircraft, on a routine night training exercise, suffers extensive damage during the incident which occurs in high winds and rain, the two crew ejecting safely.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.n-tv.de/panorama/Tornado-in-Buechel-verunglueckt-article63202.html N-tv.de Überschlag bei Landeanflug Tornado in Büchel verunglückt&lt;/ref&gt;
*25 March - An [[USAF]] [[F-22 Raptor|F-22A Block 10 Raptor]], ''91-4008'', ''Raptor 07'', of the [[411th Flight Test Squadron]], [[412th Test Wing]], crashes in the marshy flat land 6 miles N of [[Harper Lake|Harper Dry Lake]] near [[Edwards Air Force Base]], California, during a weapons integration flight test mission.&lt;ref&gt;United States Air Force Aircraft Accident Investigation Board Report, Major General David W. Eidsaune, President, 15 July 2009, Executive Summary, page i.&lt;/ref&gt;  The single-seater goes down about 1000 hrs. (1300 hrs. ET) for unknown reasons, the officials said. The fighter was on a test mission when it crashed about {{convert|35|mi|km}} NE of Edwards AFB, where it was stationed, the Air Force said in a news release.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news| url=http://cnnwire.blogs.cnn.com/2009/03/25/air-force-jet-crashes-in-california/ | work=CNN | title=Air Force jet crashes in California | accessdate=8 May 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; KWF was [[David P. Cooley|David Cooley]], 49, a 21-year Air Force veteran who joined [[Lockheed Martin Corp.]], the plane's principal contractor, in 2003. Cooley, of Palmdale, was pronounced dead at Victor Valley Community Hospital in [[Victorville, California]].&lt;ref&gt;Los Angeles Times, 26 March 2009, page 24.&lt;/ref&gt; An Air Force investigation finds that the accident occurred after the pilot lost consciousness in a high-gravity maneuver. The reports stated that during the third test of the mission the pilot appeared to have been subjected to increased physiological stress and his lack of awareness delayed a recovery maneuver.&lt;ref&gt;Fort Walton Beach, Florida, &quot;Air Force cites 'human factors' in crash&quot;, ''Northwest Florida Daily News'', Wednesday, 5 August 2009, Volume 63, Number 187, page A2.&lt;/ref&gt; At 7,486 ft MSL, the pilot initiated ejection outside of the seat design envelope and immediately sustained fatal injuries.&lt;ref&gt;United States Air Force Aircraft Accident Investigation Board Report, Major General David W. Eidsaune, President, 15 July 2009, Executive Summary, page i.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;http://www.airforce-magazine.com/SiteCollectionDocuments/Reports/2009/July%202009/Day31/F-22_AIB_073109.pdf&lt;/ref&gt;
*31 March - A [[Polish Air Force]] [[PZL M28]] (Antonov An-28TD Bryza 1TD) crashes into trees on final approach to an airfield near [[Gdynia]], Poland. The aircraft was a routine training flight simulating landing on one engine resulting to 4 crew fatalities.&lt;ref&gt;http://blog.taragana.com/n/polish-military-plane-crash-tied-to-budget-cuts-24346/ Polish Airforce An-28 crash&lt;/ref&gt;
*2 April 2009 - A [[Spanish Air Force]] [[F/A-18 Hornet]] crashes in northern Spain. Pilot ejects safely.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.velozia.com/?p=1224&lt;/ref&gt;
*6 April 2009 - An [[Indonesian Air Force]] [[Fokker F27]] crashed in [[Bandung]], [[Indonesia]] killing all 24 occupants on board. The cause of the incident was said to be heavy rain.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.flightglobal.com/blogs/asian-skies/2009/04/video-indonesian-military-fokk.html&lt;/ref&gt; The plane reportedly crashed into a hangar during its landing procedure and killed all on board. The casualties include: 6 crew, an instructor and 17 special forces trainee personnel.
*7 April - A [[Philippine Air Force]] [[Bell Helicopter|Bell]] [[Bell 412|412]] [[helicopter]] crashes in bad weather in a heavily forested area at [[Mount Mangingihe]], Sitio Tawangan, [[Kabayan, Benguet]], [[Philippines]].  The helicopter was travelling from [[Loakan Airport]] to [[Ifugao]] in the [[Cordillera Administrative Region]] in [[Luzon]] when it crashed killing the 3 crew and 5 government officials.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.gmanews.tv/story/156160/Chopper-wreckage-5-bodies-found-on-Ifugao-mountain GMA news - Chopper wreckage, 7 bodies found in Kabayan, Benguet&lt;/ref&gt;
*10 April - A Kenyan Airforce [[Harbin Y-12]] crashes into a hillside on approaching an airstrip near [[Marsabit]], Eastern Province, [[Kenya]] killing 14 personnel.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.redorbit.com/news/international/464854/kenyan_military_plane_crash_kills_14/&lt;/ref&gt;
*14 April - A [[Turkish Air Force]] [[Lockheed Martin]] [[F-16 Fighting Falcon]] [[F-16 Fighting Falcon variants#F-16C.2FD|C]] from the 9th Air Wing flying from [[Balıkesir Airport]] on a routine night exercise crashes near the village of Muradiye Sarnıç, [[Balıkesir Province]], [[Turkey]] killing the pilot.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.cnnturk.com/2009/turkiye/04/14/bursada.askeri.ucak.dustu.1.sehit/522429.0/index.html CNN.com Turkey - Bursa'nın Mustafakemalpaşa ilçesi yakınlarında eğitim uçuşu yapan F-16 tipi savaş uçağı dün akşam düştü. Enkaz uzun aramalar sonucu bulunurken&lt;/ref&gt;
*26 April - The third flying prototype of the [[Sukhoi]] [[Su-35]], ''04'' (?), is destroyed during a high-speed taxi test just before its first flight at [[Komsomolsk-na-Amur]]/[[Dzemgi Airfield]]. Aircraft apparently ran off end of runway, hits obstacle, burns, destroying it. Test pilot Eugene Frolov ejects safely and is unhurt. This was actually the fourth prototype, but ''03'' is purely for ground testing.&lt;ref&gt;Editors, &quot;''Third Su-35 Destroyed Just Before First Flight''&quot;, News - Russia &amp; CIS, Air Forces Monthly, Stamford, Lincs, UK, Number 255, June 2009, page 22.&lt;/ref&gt;
*30 April - An [[Indian Air Force]] [[Su-30MKI]] crashes in the Pokhran region of Rajasthan after it took off from Pune during its routine sortie, killing one of its two pilots. This was the first crash of the Su-30MKI since its induction in the IAF.
*3 May - A [[Venezuelan Army|Fuerzas Terrestres Venezuela]] [[Mil Mi-17|Mil Mi-17 Hip ]] helicopter crashes on a border patrol with [[Colombia]] with 18 fatalities including the Venezuelan General Domingo Faneite.  The accident occurred near the town of El Alto de Rubio, in Táchira state, [[Venezuela]].&lt;ref&gt;http://www.nacion.com/ln_ee/2009/mayo/04/mundo1953205.html&lt;/ref&gt;
* 4 May - A [[Russian Navy]] [[Kamov]] [[Kamov Ka-27|Ka-27]] (''Helix'') [[Helicopter]] landing on the [[Baltic Fleet]] Frigate Yaroslav Mudryi, the main-rotor made contact with the ship superstructure, crashed on the deck and then rolled over the side into the sea.  The 5 crew from the Kamov helicopter were successfully rescued from the sea.&lt;ref&gt;http://army.lv/ru//ka-27/830/18552 Противолодочный вертолет Ка-27 Балтфлота потерпел аварию над Балтийским морем и затонул&lt;/ref&gt;
*5 May - A United States Marine Corps [[AH-1 SuperCobra|AH-1W SuperCobra]] belonging to [[HMM-166]], based at [[MCAS Miramar]], California, crashes at 1154 hrs. PST into the [[Cleveland National Forest]], California, killing both pilots.&lt;ref name=&quot;&quot;&gt;{{cite web| title =Super Cobra crashes in National Forest  | work =| publisher =United States Marine Corps| date =2009-05-06| url =http://www.marines.mil/units/hqmc/Pages/SuperCobracrashesinNationalForest.aspx  | accessdate = 2009-05-07}} {{Dead link|date=October 2010|bot=H3llBot}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*12 May - A [[South African Air Force]] [[Agusta]] [[AgustaWestland AW109|AW109E]], [[helicopter]], ''4022'', crashes at the Woodstock Dam, near [[Bergville, KwaZulu-Natal]], South Africa.  The aircraft from No. [[17 Squadron SAAF]] was travelling from [[Durban International Airport]] to  a satellite base of the [[87 Helicopter Flying School SAAF]] at Dragon's Peak, [[Drakensberg]] for a week long training exercise. Flying with two another aircraft at low level and at high speed over the surface of the Dam, the helicopter stuck the water and crashed, then sinking into the lake killing the 3 crew.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.iol.co.za/index.php?set_id=1&amp;click_id=181&amp;art_id=vn20090514060809349C903997 three South African Air Force (SAAF) members who drowned when their helicopter crashed into the Woodstock Dam near Bergvill&lt;/ref&gt;
*14 May - A [[Royal Air Force]] [[BAE Systems]] [[BAE Harrier II|Harrier GR9]] (''ZG478/68'') from [[No. 1 Squadron RAF|No. 1 Squadron]] based at [[RAF Cottesmore]] makes a heavy landing at [[Kandahar International Airport]], [[Afghanistan]] due to an engine failure forcing the pilot to successfully eject from the aircraft.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.thesun.co.uk/sol/homepage/news/campaigns/our_boys/article2428922.ece  The Sun - Pilot survives Jump Jet crash&lt;/ref&gt;
*15 May - An [[Indian Air Force]] [[Mikoyan|Mikoyan-Gurevich]] [[Mikoyan-Gurevich MiG-27|MiG-27]] ''Flogger''  crashed shortly after take-off and the pilot successfully ejected from the aircraft.  The accident occurred near the Konkani village, [[Jodhpur]], India and resulted in injuries to 7 local villagers.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.expressindia.com/latest-news/MIG27-fighter-aircraft-crashes-near-Jodhpur-7-injured/459926/ Indian Airforce MIG-27 Crash&lt;/ref&gt;
*15 May - A [[Colombian Air Force|Fuerza Aérea Colombiana]] [[Dassault Aviation]] [[Dassault Mirage 5|Mirage 5COAM]] (''FAC-3031'') on a routine training flight from the Comando Aéreo de Combate No. 1, crashed shortly after take-off from the Palanquero airbase, [[Puerto Salgar]], [[Cundinamarca Department]], [[Colombia]].  The aircraft from the Escuadrón de Combate 112 suffered a technical fault causing a fire which forced the pilot to successfully eject from the plane without injury.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.terra.com.co/noticias/articulo/html/acu21604-piloto-de-la-fac-sale-ileso-tras-incendiarse-su-mirage.htm Terra Columbia - Piloto de la FAC sale ileso tras incendiarse su Mirage&lt;/ref&gt;
*19 May - An [[United States Navy]] [[Sikorsky Aircraft|Sikorsky]] [[SH-60 Seahawk|HH-60H Seahawk]] crashes into the Pacific Ocean {{convert|16|mi|km}} SW of [[San Diego]], California.  The aircraft was on a routine training flight and returning to the aircraft carrier [[USS Nimitz CVN-68|USS ''Nimitz'']] when the accident occurred off of [[Point Loma, California]], leaving 3 crew dead and 2 crew members missing.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.oregonlive.com/news/index.ssf/2009/05/navy_seal_from_oregon_killed_i.html Oregonlive.com Helicopter crash off San Diego&lt;/ref&gt;
*20 May - The [[2009 Indonesia C-130H Hercules crash]] was an aircraft accident in [[Indonesia]] on May 20, 2009. The [[Indonesian Air Force]] [[C-130 Hercules]] [[airplane]] was carrying 112 people (98 passengers and 14 crew) and crashed at about 6:30 local time (23:30 UTC), while flying from [[Jakarta]] to eastern [[Java]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |first=Mark |last=McDonald |url=http://www.nytimes.com/2009/05/21/world/asia/21crash.html?ref=world |title=Crash in Indonesia Kills Dozens |work=[[The New York Times]] |date=2009-05-20 |accessdate=2009-05-20}}&lt;/ref&gt; The crash resulted in at least 98 deaths, 5 of which occurred on impact when the plane ploughed through a neighborhood, striking at least four houses before skidding into a paddy, in the village of [[Geplak, Indonesia|Geplak]]. Two people on the ground were killed.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |url=http://www.reuters.com/article/worldNews/idUSTRE54J0WC20090520 |title=Indonesia says 98 killed in military plane crash |agency=[[Reuters]] |date=2009-05-20 |accessdate=2009-05-20}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |url=http://www.google.com/hostednews/afp/article/ALeqM5hAnPYoLnTzGUR60QGuihFEvKywzA |title=Indonesia plane crash kills 78: air force |publisher=[[Google News]] |agency=[[Agence France-Presse]] |date=2009-05-20 |accessdate=2009-05-20}}&lt;/ref&gt; At least 70 others had been taken to a local hospital.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |url=http://www.google.com/hostednews/afp/article/ALeqM5gvml94l0WjZTylmjvz52UeXPhWBg |title=Indonesia military plane crashes, 57 reported dead |publisher=[[Google News]] |agency=[[Agence France-Presse]] |date=2009-05-20 |accessdate=2009-05-20}}&lt;/ref&gt; Authorities believe that there is still 1 missing body.
*21 May - An Air Force test pilot student is killed when his [[T-38 Talon|T-38A Talon]] jet trainer crashes N of [[Edwards Air Force Base]], California, ~ nine miles N of the base, near [[California City]].&lt;ref&gt;http://www.edwards.af.mil/news/story.asp?id=123150653&lt;/ref&gt;
*26 May - A [[Brazilian Air Force|Força Aérea Brasileira]] [[Embraer]] [[Embraer EMB 110 Bandeirante|EMB 110 Bandeirante C-95]] (''FAB 2332'') a twin-engined [[turboprop]] transport made a heavy landing at [[Afonsos Air Force Base|Base Aérea do Campo dos Afonsos]], [[Rio de Janeiro]], [[Brazil]].  The accident occurred when the landing gear failed to operate.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.fab.mil.br/portal/capa/index.php?mostra=3060 - Acidente com aeronave C-95C no Rio de Janeiro&lt;/ref&gt;
*28 May - A [[Nigerian Air Force]] [[Van's Aircraft RV-6|RV-6A Air Beetle]] crashed near Kaduna, Nigeria on a training flight, both occupants killed.&lt;ref name=&quot;Scramble362&quot; /&gt;
*2 June - A [[Royal Jordanian Air Force]] [[Slingsby T-67 Firefly]] while on a routine training flight being flown by a cadet pilot and instructor, crashes near the [[Qualifying Industrial Zones in Jordan|Al-Hassan Industrial Estate]], [[Irbid]], [[Jordan]].  The aircraft  due to a technical fault was unable to recover from a spin leaving 1 crew dead and 1 injured.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.factjo.com/fullNews.aspx?id=8831 تحطمت طائرة تدريب تابعة لسلاح الجو الملكي الأردني في منطقة البويضة القريبة من مدينة الحسن الصناعية صباح&lt;/ref&gt;
*4 June - A [[Hellenic Air Force]] [[Lockheed Martin]] [[F-16 Fighting Falcon variants#F-16C.2FD|F-16C Block 50S Fighting Falcon]], ''93-1059'', '059',&lt;ref name=&quot;ReferenceB&quot;&gt;http://www.f-16.net/aircraft-database/F-16/mishaps-and-accidents/year/2009/&lt;/ref&gt; of the 347 Fighter Squadron based at Nea Anchialos Airforce Base crashes near the village of [[Michalitsi, Ioannina|Michalitsi]] part of the Tzoumerka National Park, [[Ioannina]], Greece.  The aircraft flying with another F-16 from the 111th Combat Wing suffered a bird strike and engine failure forced the pilot to successfully eject.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.newsblog.gr/?p=15171#more-15171 Ένας αετός χτύπησε στο ρύγχος του F16 – Φωτoγραφίες από την περιοχή&lt;/ref&gt;
*8 June - An [[Indonesian Army]] locally-built [[MBB Bo 105]] crashes while flying in bad weather near to [[Situhaing]] village on [[West Java]], killing all five occupants.&lt;ref name=&quot;Scramble362&quot;&gt;{{cite journal | title= Dustpan &amp; Brush | journal= [[Scramble (magazine)|Scramble]] | issue= 362 |month=July |year=2009 | publisher=Dutch Aviation Society  | pages= 67–73}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*9 June - An [[Indian Air Force]] [[Antonov]] [[An-32]] ''Cline'' transport aircraft crashes near a village in West Siang district of [[Arunachal Pradesh]] killing 13 defence personnel. The aircraft crashed over the Rinchi Hill above Heyo village, about 30&amp;nbsp;km from Mechuka advance landing ground in the district located about 60&amp;nbsp;km from the Indo-Chinese Line of Actual Control. Among the seven IAF men and six Army personnel on board the ill-fated aircraft were two wing commanders, two squadron leaders and a flight lieutenant.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.ptinews.com/pti%5Cptisite.nsf/0/561DA65347083994652575D10051F8C8?OpenDocument&lt;/ref&gt;
*9 June - A [[Vietnamese People's Air Force]] [[Sukhoi]] [[Sukhoi Su-17|Su-22M3/4]] ''Fitter J/K'' crashes into a cornfield near Chieng Bay Hill, [[Thanh Hóa Province]], [[Vietnam]] killing the pilot.  The aircraft from the 923rd Fighter Regiment was on a routine training flight and suffered mechanical failure.&lt;ref&gt;http://cazasyhelicopteros.blogspot.com/2009/06/avion-militar-se-estrella-en-vietnam.html Un avión militar Su-22 perteneciente al regimiento 923 de la Fuerza Aérea de Vietnam&lt;/ref&gt;
*12 June - An [[Indonesian Air Force]] locally-built [[Aérospatiale Puma|SA 330J Puma]] crashed at [[Bogor, West Java]] during a test flight following maintenance of the helicopter, all four occupants killed.&lt;ref name=&quot;Scramble362&quot; /&gt;
*14 June - A Royal Air Force Grob Tutor collided with a glider near [[Abingdon, Oxfordshire]], England, killing a reservist pilot and a cadet. The glider pilot parachuted to safety.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.guardian.co.uk/uk/2009/jun/14/air-crash-drayton-oxfordshire Guardian UK news]&lt;/ref&gt;
*16 June - Two [[Spanish Air Force]] [[F/A-18 Hornet]]s collide in midair near the [[Canary Islands]], Spain. Both pilots eject safely.&lt;ref&gt;http://momento24.com/en/2009/06/16/two-spanish-f-18-jets-crashed-near-the-canary-islands/&lt;/ref&gt;
*17 June - A [[Russian Air Force]] [[Sukhoi]] [[Sukhoi Su-24|Su-24MR]] ''Fencer'' crashes on landing at the [[Monchegorsk (air base)|Monchegorsk Airforce Base]], [[Murmansk Oblast]], Russia.  The aircraft from the 98th Separate Reconnaissance Aviation Regiment suffered a heavy landing forcing the 2 crew to eject safely.&lt;ref name=&quot;aviaport.ru&quot;&gt;http://www.aviaport.ru/digest/2009/06/22/175372.html aviaport.ru За неделю в России разбились два самолета Су-24&lt;/ref&gt;
*18 June - An [[Indian Air Force]] [[Mikoyan|Mikoyan-Gurevich]] [[Mikoyan-Gurevich MiG-21|MiG-21]] ''Bison'' from the Chabua Air Force Station, [[Assam]], India crashes due to a technical fault while on a routine training flight, the pilot successfully ejecting from the aircraft.&lt;ref&gt;http://news.oneindia.in/2009/06/18/mig-21-crashes-in-assam-pilot-safe.html Indian Airforce MIG-21 crash June 2009&lt;/ref&gt;
*19 June - A [[Russian Air Force]] [[Sukhoi]] [[Sukhoi Su-24|Su-24MR]] ''Fencer'' crashes near the village of Kostino-Bystrianská,  [[Rostov-on-Don]], [[Rostov Oblast]], Russia.  The aircraft from the 1st Composite Air Division, [[North Caucasus Military District]] suffered a mechanical fault forcing the 2 crew to eject safely after several aborted landings. The Russian Airforce fleet of Sukhoi Su-24 was grounded for technical inspection after 2 accidents in a week.&lt;ref name=&quot;aviaport.ru&quot;/&gt;
*22 June - An [[United States Army]] [[Bell 206|Bell TH-67 Creek]] crashed near Hartfield, Alabama on a training mission, one of the two occupants killed.&lt;ref name=&quot;Scramble362&quot; /&gt;
*22 June - An [[United States Air Force]] Lockheed Martin [[F-16 Fighting Falcon|F-16CM Fighting Falcon]], ''89-2108'', from the [[421st Fighter Squadron]], [[388th Fighter Wing]], based at [[Hill Air Force Base]], [[Ogden, Utah|Ogden]], [[Utah]] crashes on a night training flight on the [[Utah Test and Training Range]].  The pilot, Capt. George B. Houghton, dies in the crash which occurred {{convert|35|mi|km}} S of [[Wendover, Utah]].&lt;ref&gt;http://blog.taragana.com/n/military-identifies-pilot-killed-in-f-16-crash-in-utah-91202/&lt;/ref&gt;
*2 July - A Royal Air Force [[Panavia Tornado]] F3 crashes near the ''Rest and Be Thankful'' beauty spot in Glen Kinglass,  [[Arrochar]], [[Scotland]].  The aircraft was on a routine training flight from No. [[No. 43 Squadron RAF|43 Squadron]] [[RAF Leuchars]] in [[Fife]] resulting in 2 crew killed in the accident. The crew were pilot Kenneth Thompson and weapons systems officer Nigel Morton.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news| url=http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/scotland/glasgow_and_west/8131858.stm | work=BBC News | title=Crashed jet fighter airmen named | date=3 July 2009 | accessdate=8 May 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*3 July - A [[Argentine Air Force|Fuerza Aérea Argentina]] [[Dassault Aviation]] [[Dassault Mirage III|Mirage III]] from Grupo 6 de Caza based at [[Tandil Airport]], [[Buenos Aires Province]], [[Argentina]] crashed into open countryside near Benito Juárez and the pilot successfully ejected from the aircraft.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.lavozdelpueblo.com.ar/interior.php?ar_id=40668 La Voz del Pueblo - Cayó un avión Mirage III en Benito Juárez, pero el piloto logró eyectarse y resultó ileso&lt;/ref&gt;
*3 July - A Pakistan Army Mil Mi-17 helicopter [[2009 Pakistan Army Mil Mi-17 crash|crashed]] at Chapar Feroze Khel near [[Peshawar]], Pakistan due to a technical fault resulting in 26 fatalities.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.google.com/hostednews/afp/article/ALeqM5iQVHpnimnLoea_F_MzBzXUbWaYtA&lt;/ref&gt;
*3 July - A [[Belgian Air Component]] [[Piper Aircraft]] [[Piper PA-18|L21B Super Cub]] crashes on take-off at [[Goetsenhoven Military Airfield]], [[Flanders]], Belgium killing the 2 crew.  The aircraft which was used as a gilder-tug collided with a nearby hangar, crashing into a field and caught fire.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.gva.be/nieuws/binnenland/aid845116/vliegtuigje-crasht-in-tienen.aspx GVA.be news - In Goetsenhoven, een deelgemeente van Tienen, is vrijdagmorgen een vliegtuigje van de luchtkadetten neergestort.&lt;/ref&gt;
*7 July - A Serbian Air Force [[MiG-29]] crashes while performing aerobatic maneouvres in preparation for an upcoming airshow, killing the pilot Lt. Col. Rade Randjelovic and a soldier on the ground while injuring another.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.upi.com/Top_News/2009/07/07/Serbian-MiG-29-jet-crashes-kills-pilot/UPI-12181246977583&lt;/ref&gt;
*15 July - A [[Republic of China Air Force]] [[Northrop Corporation|Northrop]] [[Northrop F-5|F-5 F]] (''5410'') from the 7th Tactical Fighter Group based at [[Ching Chuan Kang Air Base]] crashes on a routine training flight of the coast of [[Penghu]], [[Taiwan]] killing the 2 crew.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.chinapost.com.tw/taiwan/national/national-news/2009/07/16/216437/Air-force.htm The China Post - The R.O.C. Air Force has grounded all of its F-5F jet fighters after one of the twin-seat planes crashed into the sea off the outlying island of Penghu&lt;/ref&gt;
*16 July - A [[Pakistan Air Force]] [[Lockheed Martin]] [[F-16 Fighting Falcon variants#F-16A.2FB|F-16A Block 15AQ OCU Fighting Falcon]], ''92729'', ex-''92-0405'', on a routine night training exercise from No. 9 Squadron from [[Mushaf Airbase]] crashes 105&amp;nbsp;km south-west of [[Sargodha]], Pakistan resulting in the death of the pilot, Squadron Leader Saud Ghulam Nabi.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.nation.com.pk/pakistan-news-newspaper-daily-english-online/Politics/17-Jul-2009/PAF-F16-crashes-in-Khoshab The Nation Online - PAF F-16 crashes in Khoshab&lt;/ref&gt; Another source gives the accident date as 17 July.&lt;ref name=&quot;ReferenceB&quot;/&gt;
*17 July - A [[Venezuelan Air Force|Fuerza Aérea Venezolana]] [[Cessna]] [[Cessna 206|T206H]] (''FAV-2807'') flying from [[Puerto Ayacucho]] to [[La Esmeralda]], [[Amazonas (Venezuelan state)|Estado Amazonas]], [[Venezuela]] crashes into the hillside of El Duida, {{convert|20|mi|km}} from its destination at La Esmeralda airport killing the 3 crew.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.noticias24.com/actualidad/noticia/67598/desaparece-avioneta-en-el-estado-amazonas-video/ Noticias24.com - Desaparecen tres avionetas tipo Cessna en territorio nacional&lt;/ref&gt;
*18 July - An [[United States Air Force]] [[McDonnell Douglas]] [[F-15E Strike Eagle]] from the [[336th Fighter Squadron]], based at [[Seymour Johnson AFB]], North Carolina, flying in support of [[International Security Assistance Force|ISAF]] coalition operations, crashes in eastern Afghanistan.  The two aircrew, Capt. Thomas J. Gramith and Capt. Mark R. McDowell both die in the incident.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.air-attack.com/news/article/3786/F-15E-crew-perishes-in-Afghanistan-crash.html&lt;/ref&gt;
*19 July - A [[People's Liberation Army Air Force|Chinese Air Force]] [[Xian JH-7]] (FBC-1 Flying Leopard) crashes near the Taonan tactical training base in Jilin province while on a joint counter-terrorism exercises with Russia resulting in the death of 2 crew.&lt;ref&gt;http://qip.com/russia-china-drill-continues-despite-aircraft-crash-that-kills-2/&lt;/ref&gt;
*20 July - A [[Royal Air Force]] [[Panavia Tornado]] G4 operating with RAF No. [[No. 1 Squadron RAF|1 Squadron]] crashes on take-off at Kandahār International Airport in Afghanistan and the two crew members successfully eject from the aircraft.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.flightglobal.com/articles/2009/07/20/329851/raf-tornado-crash-follows-f-15e-mi-8-losses-in-afghanistan.html&lt;/ref&gt;
*20 July -  A [[Chilean Air Force]] [[Extra 300L]] aerobatic aircraft cashed 15&amp;nbsp;km south of Santiago, Chile, pilot seriously injured.&lt;ref name=&quot;Scramble364-74&quot;&gt;Scramble Issue 364 page 74.&lt;/ref&gt;
* 20 July - An [[IAI Kfir]] jet fighter crashes near the city of [[Cartagena, Colombia]]. The Israeli pilots operating the plane were unharmed in the incident, but the jet itself was destroyed. Israel Aerospace Industries said in a statement that the plane was flying a refresher flight, and that the aircraft did not come to a stop on the landing strip, landing outside it. The director of the Israel Aerospace Industries announced that an investigation into the incident had already begun and that a panel to probe the crash had been appointed.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.haaretz.com/hasen/spages/1102019.html Ha'aretz.com]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.ynetnews.com/articles/0,7340,L-3749978,00.html ynetnews]&lt;/ref&gt;
*21 July -  A [[United States Navy]] [[HH-60 Pave Hawk|Sikorsky HH-60H]] ''163790'' crashed on a training flight at [[Fort Pickett]], [[Blackstone, Virginia]], United States; minor injuries only.&lt;ref name=&quot;Scramble364-74&quot; /&gt;
*23 July - A [[Turkish Air Force]] [[F-4 Phantom II|McDonnell Douglas F-4 Phantom II]] crashes on take-off after from the [[Erhaç Air Base]] in [[Malatya]], [[Turkey]] due to a technical fault caused by drop-tank falling from the aircraft.  The two crew members successfully eject from the aircraft and were hospitalized after the incident.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.hurriyetdailynews.com/n.php?n=two-pilots-survive-military-plane-crash-in-turkey-2009-07-23&lt;/ref&gt;
*23 July - An [[Military of Uzbekistan|Uzbekistan Air Force]] [[Mil Moscow Helicopter Plant|Mil]] [[Mil Mi-24|Mi-24]] ''Hind'' [[Helicopter]] on a routine training exercise crashes near the airport of [[Chirchiq]], [[Tashkent Province]], [[Uzbekistan]] killing the 2 crew.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.zakon.kz/143898-pod-tashkentom-razbilsja-vertolet-vvs.html Zakon.kz - Под Ташкентом разбился вертолет ВВС Узбекистана&lt;/ref&gt;
*31 July - An [[Indian Air Force]] [[HAL HPT-32 Deepak]] a prop-driven primary military trainer crashes in the Medak district of the [[Andhra Pradesh]] state killing the 2 crew.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.nation.com.pk/pakistan-news-newspaper-daily-english-online/Politics/01-Aug-2009/2-pilots-die-in-Indian-military-plane-crash&lt;/ref&gt;
*5 August - A [[Pakistan Air Force]] [[Chengdu J-7|Chengdu FT-7]] crashes near [[Attock]], northwest Pakistan, killing the pilot.&lt;ref name=&quot;Scramble364-76&quot;&gt;Scramble Issue 364 page 76.&lt;/ref&gt;
*6 August - A [[Swedish Air Force]] [[Saab]] [[JAS 39 Gripen|JAS 39 Gripen C]] from [[F 17 Kallinge]] Blekinge Air Force Wing suffered a heavy landing at [[Ronneby Airport]], Sweden caused by the failure of the under-carriage to operate after a fire alarm was trigged and the pilot was uninjured in the incident.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.mil.se/sv/Forband-och-formagor/Forband/Blekinge-flygflottilj-F-17/Nyheter/JAS-plan-i-olycka/ JAS 39-plan i olycka - En JAS 39C buklandade kort efter 14.00 på flygflottiljen F 17 i Ronneby&lt;/ref&gt;
*16 August - Two [[Russian Knights]] air display [[Su-27]] jets '''[[2009 Russia Sukhoi Su-27 mid-air collision|collided]]''' whilst training, killing one pilot, Igor Tkachenko, and injuring several civilians on the ground. The accident occurred near [[Zhukovsky Airfield]], outside of Moscow.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news| url=http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/world/europe/8204072.stm | work=BBC News | title=Pilot dies as Russia jets collide | date=17 August 2009 | accessdate=8 May 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*16 August - An [[Islamic Republic of Iran Air Force]] [[Bell 214]] crashed on a training flight near Karaj, Iran, four killed.&lt;ref name=&quot;Scramble364-77&quot;&gt;Scramble Issue 364 page 77.&lt;/ref&gt;
*19 August - An [[United States Army]] [[UH-60 Black Hawk|Sikorsky UH-60 Black Hawk]] from [[Fort Campbell]], [[Kentucky]] the home base of the [[101st Airborne Division (United States)|101st Airborne]] crashes while on a training exercise being carried-out by the [[160th Special Operations Aviation Regiment (United States)|160th Special Operations Aviation Regiment (Airborne)]].  The accident occurred 400&amp;nbsp;ft below the summit of the 14,421 feet high (4,268 m) [[Mount Massive]] in the [[Sawatch Range]], [[Colorado]] leaving 2 crew dead, 1 injured and 1 crew member missing.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.turkishweekly.net/news/87254/-2-dead-in-military-chopper-crash-on-colorado-mountain-update-.html&lt;/ref&gt;
*21 August - An [[Indian Navy]] [[BAE Sea Harrier]] crashes shortly after take-off from [[Dabolim Airport]] near [[Goa]], India.  The aircraft on a routine flight crashed in to the [[Arabian Sea]] of the coast of Goa killing the pilot [[Lieutenant Commander|Lt. Cdr.]] Saurav Saxena.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.hindustantimes.com/homepage/goa/Pilot-killed-in-Indian-Navy-Sea-Harrier-crash/446891/H1-Article1-445549.aspx&lt;/ref&gt;
*27 August - A [[Hellenic Air Force]] [[PZL-Mielec M-18 Dromader]] fire-fighting aircraft from the 359 Public Services Air Support Unit based at [[Andravida AB|Andravida Airforce Base]] crashes after hitting high-voltage cables.  The accident occurred while fighting a forest fire in the village of Katseli near [[Argostoli]], [[Kefalonia]], Greece resulting in the death of the pilot.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.macedoniaontheweb.eu/content/view/1164/44/lang,en/ Macedonia On The Web - Συντριβή πυροσβεστικού PZL M-18B της ΠΑ στην Κεφαλονιά, νεκρός ο πιλότος&lt;/ref&gt;
[[Image:E-3NellisPhotoa.jpg|right|thumb|250px|Fire damaged USAF E-3C, ''83-0008'', on Nellis AFB, Nevada, ramp.]]
*28 August - An [[United States Air Force]] [[Boeing]] [[E-3 Sentry|E-3C Sentry]], ''83-0008'', [[Airborne Early Warning and Control|(AEW&amp;C)]] while returning from the Red Flag Exercise 09-5 with the [[552d Air Control Wing]] from [[Tinker Air Force Base]], [[Oklahoma]] makes a landing at [[Nellis Air Force Base]].  Due to a fire the aircraft was damaged and the crew of 32 were safely evacuated and the fire extinguished by Nellis AFB emergency response crew.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.lasvegassun.com/news/2009/aug/29/air-force-plane-damaged-while-landing-nellis/&lt;/ref&gt;
*30 August - A [[Belarusian Air Force]] [[Sukhoi]] [[Su-27]] Flanker was lost during [[Radom Air Show|Radom Airshow 2009]], Poland. The plane crashed near the [[Małęczyn]] village, outside the military air base the event took place on. No civilian was injured. There was no damage reported on the ground. The crew of two did not eject and were found dead by the rescue teams.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=ZOT4Q8wvat8 YouTube video with aircraft taxing, taking off, performing maneuvers and finally crashing]&lt;/ref&gt;
*6 September - A [[Lockheed Corporation|Lockheed]] [[T-33 Shooting Star]] Silver Star Mk 3 (''G-TBRD'') crashed shortly after take-off at Duxford Aerodrome, [[Duxford]], [[Cambridgeshire]], UK.  The facility is part of the [[Imperial War Museum Duxford]] and the privately owned T-33 Shooting Star in [[Royal Canadian Air Force]] livery (''RCAF - 261'') suffered a stall after rotation, clipping trees and crashing {{convert|1|mi|km|adj=on}} from the runway.  The aircraft caught fire and was destroyed in the accident, the 2 crew escaped with minor injuries.&lt;ref&gt;http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/england/cambridgeshire/5320788.stm BBC News Channel - Aircraft crash at historic museum&lt;/ref&gt;
*7 September - An [[Indonesian Air Force]] [[Government Aircraft Factories]] [[GAF Nomad|Nomad P837]] on a routine flight crashes  near a local village of Sekatak Matadau, Bulungan district  in [[East Kalimantan]] killing 4 of the 9 passengers and crew.&lt;ref&gt;http://article.wn.com/view/2009/09/07/Indonesian_military_plane_crashes_with_9_aboard_2/&lt;/ref&gt;
*10 September - A [[Spanish Air Force]] [[Dassault Mirage F1]] crashes in the [[Cazorla]] Natural Park, near [[Jaén, Spain]], while in a training flight. The pilot ejected and suffered minor injuries.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.typicallyspanish.com/news/publish/article_23022.shtml&lt;/ref&gt;
*10 September - An [[Mexican Navy|Armada de México]] [[Bell Helicopter|Bell]] [[OH-58 Kiowa|406]] [[Helicopter]] on a routine patrol crashes near the 27 kilometre post on the [[Perote, Veracruz|Perote]]-Los Humeros Highway, [[Veracruz|Veracruz State]], Mexico, resulting in 2 crew injured and 3 fatalities.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.eldictamen.org/ver_nota.php?noticia=15923&amp;seccion=Nacionales&amp;fecha=2009-09-11  El Dictamen Online - Se Estrella Helicóptero de la armada&lt;/ref&gt;
*12 September - An [[Indian Air Force]] [[Mikoyan|Mikoyan-Gurevich]] [[Mikoyan-Gurevich MiG-21|MiG-21]] ''Bison'' from the Bhatinda Airforce Station, Punjab, India crashed due to a technical fault near the village of Muktsar-Bhatinda in the [[Punjab (Pakistan)|Punjab Provence]], Pakistan killing the pilot.&lt;ref&gt;http://news.yahoo.com/s/afp/20090912/wl_sthasia_afp/pakistanmilitaryaircrash&lt;/ref&gt;
*13 September - An [[Israeli Air Force]] [[Lockheed Martin]] [[F-16 Fighting Falcon]] [[F-16 Fighting Falcon variants#F-16A.2FB|F-16A Block 10A Fighting Falcon]] ''140'', ex-''78-0337'', from the [[Nevatim Israeli Air Force Base]], [[Beersheba]], [[Israel]] crashes near the P'nei Chever settlement in the [[Mount Hebron|Southern Hebron Hills]] at 1345 hrs. killing the pilot.&lt;ref name=&quot;ReferenceB&quot;/&gt;  The incident occurred during military training including a simulated dogfight with another aircraft. During a sharp turn, the pilot Captain [[Assaf Ramon]] the only son [[Colonel]] [[Ilan Ramon]] who died in the [[Space Shuttle Columbia]] disaster in 2003, suffered either loss of consciousness or mechanical failure leading to the crash.&lt;ref&gt;http://fr.jpost.com/servlet/Satellite?cid=1251804563180&amp;pagename=JPost/JPArticle/ShowFull&lt;/ref&gt;
*17 September - An [[Indonesian Air Force]] [[FFA AS-202 Bravo]] on a routine training flight crashes into a rice field in Sragen, Central Java killing the pilot.&lt;ref&gt;http://thejakartaglobe.com/home/indonesian-airforce-plane-crashes-in-central-java-killing-one/330396&lt;/ref&gt;
*19 September - An [[United States Army]] [[Sikorsky Aircraft|Sikorsky]] [[UH-60 Black Hawk]] crashed at [[Joint Base Balad]], (formerly Al-Bakr Air Base), [[Balad, Iraq|Balad]], [[Iraq]].  The accident occurred during a storm including high winds and a sandstorm resulting in 12 crew injured and 1 fatality.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.armytimes.com/news/2009/09/ap_army_black_hawk_crash_092109/ Army Times Blackhawk Crash Iraq Sep 2009&lt;/ref&gt;
*22 September - An [[Islamic Republic of Iran Air Force|Iranian Air Force]] [[Ilyushin Il-76|Ilyushin Il-76MD]] [[Airborne early warning and control|AWACS]] equipped aircraft [[2009 Iranian Air Force mid-air collision|collided]] with another Iranian Airforce [[Northrop F-5|Northrop F-5E Tiger II]] during a military parade near [[Varamin]], [[Iran]] resulting in 7 fatalities.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.ngrguardiannews.com/world/article02//indexn2_html?pdate=230909&amp;ptitle=Plane%20crash%20mars%20Iran's%20military%20parade Ilyushin Crash Iran Airshow Sep 2009&lt;/ref&gt;
*24 September - A [[French Navy]] [[Aviation navale]] test flight involving two [[Dassault Rafale]] aircraft flying back to the Aircraft Carrier [[French aircraft carrier Charles de Gaulle (R91)|''Charles de Gaulle'' (R91)]] collide in mid-air.  The incident occurred in the Mediterranean of the coast of [[Perpignan]], [[Pyrénées-Orientales]], France and one pilot was rescued after ejecting from the aircraft the second pilot listed as missing.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.france24.com/en/20090925-rafale-jet-crash-likely-caused-mid-air-collision-french-military-mediterranean-pilot France24.com French Navy Dassault Rafale collision Eastern Med Sep 2009&lt;/ref&gt;
*28 September - A [[Japan Maritime Self-Defense Force]] (JMSDF) [[Nihon Aircraft Manufacturing Corporation|NAMC]] [[NAMC YS-11|YS-11]] a twin-engined [[turboprop]] transport crashed while landing at JMSDF [[Ozuki Air Field]] in [[Shimonoseki, Yamaguchi|Shimonoseki]], [[Yamaguchi Prefecture]], Japan.  The landing in light rain, the aircraft suffered an overshoot of the runway and crashed through the airfield perimeter fence, crossing a service road and plunged nose-first into a rice field. The 11 JMSDF crew members of the aircraft were uninjured and the NAMC YS-11 aircraft suffered bent propellers.
*2 October - A [[Yemeni Air Force]] [[Mikoyan|Mikoyan-Gurevich]] [[Mikoyan-Gurevich MiG-21|MiG-21]] ''Fishbed'' crashes during a low-flying exercise due to mechanical failure.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.saudigazette.com.sa/index.cfm?method=home.regcon&amp;contentID=2009100350561 Saudi Gazette Yemeni Mig Crash&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;http://derstandard.at/fs/1254310474474/Kampfflugzeug-abgestuerzt  Kampfflugzeug abgestürzt&lt;/ref&gt;
*2 October - A [[Mexican Air Force|Fuerza Aérea Mexicana]] [[Cessna]] [[Cessna 182|182S Skylane]] (''FAM-5498'') crashes near San José Querendaro, [[Michoacán]], Mexico.  The aircraft on a reconnaissance flight from [[Morelia]] Airport crashed in the mountains of Michoacán with 3 crew fatalities.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.sedena.gob.mx/index.php?id_art=2570 Secretaría de la Defensa Nacional - SE DESPLOMA AERONAVE DE LA FUERZA AÉREA MEXICANA EN EL ESTADO DE MICHOACÁN&lt;/ref&gt;
*3 October - A [[Military of Bolivia|Fuerza Aérea Boliviano]] [[Aérospatiale]] [[Aérospatiale Lama|SA 315B Lama]] [[Helicopter]] (''FAB-730'') from the Escuadrón 511 crashes into a building wall on the [[Pampa]] near the city of [[Cochabamba]], [[Bolivia]] leaving 4 crew dead, 1 crew member injured and 1 civilian on the ground injured.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.elmundo.com.bo/Secundarianew.asp?edicion=29/06/2007&amp;Tipo=Policial&amp;Cod=5799 El Mundo.com Cuatro militares mueren al estrellarse helicóptero de la FAB&lt;/ref&gt;
*7 October - A [[Libyan Air Force]] [[Mikoyan|Mikoyan-Gurevich]] [[Mikoyan-Gurevich MiG-23|MiG-23]] ''Flogger'' crashes while taking part during an airshow for the Third Libyan Aviation Exhibition, LAVEX 2009 held at [[Mitiga International Airport]], [[Tripoli]], [[Libya]].  The aircraft travelling at low-level hit a one-storey house in the suburb of Souq Al-Jumaa in Tripoli killing the 2 crew and injuring two civilians.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.tripolipost.com/articledetail.asp?c=1&amp;i=3654# The Tripoli Post - Mig-23 Fighter Jet Crashes in Tripoli Suburb, Two Pilots Killed&lt;/ref&gt;
*9 October - A [[Uruguayan Air Force|Fuerza Aérea Uruguaya]] [[EADS CASA]] [[CASA C-212 Aviocar|C-212-200 Aviocar]] (''FAU-531/UN-146'')  a twin-engined [[turboprop]] transport aircraft, on a reconnaissance flight  crashes near [[Fonds-Verrettes]], [[Ouest Department]], [[Haiti]].  The aircraft taking part in the [[United Nations Stabilization Mission in Haiti]] crashed into a mountainside near the remote village of Pays-Pourri killing the 11 crew.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.fau.com.uy/fallecidos_fau531.html Accidente aéreo en la Fuerza Aérea Uruguaya&lt;/ref&gt;
*12 October - An [[Irish Air Corps]] [[Pilatus Aircraft|Pilatus]] [[Pilatus PC-9|PC-9 M]] flying in poor weather conditions crashes at Crumlin East near [[Cornamona]] in [[County Galway]], [[Republic of Ireland]] killing the flying instructor and cadet pilot.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.rte.ie/news/2009/1012/cornamona.html RTÉ News - Two feared dead after Air Corps crash&lt;/ref&gt;
*15 October - An [[United States Air Force]] [[Lockheed Martin]] [[F-16 Fighting Falcon|F-16C Block 50D Fighting Falcon]], ''91-0365'', is lost while flying on a routine night flying exercise from the [[77th Fighter Squadron]], [[20th Fighter Wing]], based at the [[Shaw Air Force Base]], [[Sumter, South Carolina]] when it collides mid-air with F-16C Block 50D Fighting Falcon, ''91-0364''.&lt;ref name=&quot;ReferenceB&quot;/&gt;   The two aircraft from the 20th Fighter Wing were training with night vision equipment and practising combat tactics when the accident occurred {{convert|40|mi|km}} east of [[Folly Beach, South Carolina]] at ~2030 hrs.  The [[United States Coast Guard]] commenced a search for a missing aircraft in the [[North Atlantic]] of the coast of South Carolina while the second aircraft, piloted by Capt. Lee Bryant, despite damage was able to land at [[Charleston Air Force Base]].&lt;ref&gt;http://www.wtoctv.com/Global/story.asp?S=11324477 WTOC TV Savannah Georgia - Debris found during search for missing F-16 pilot&lt;/ref&gt; on 16 October, Coast Guard searchers found crash debris in the Atlantic Ocean believed to belong to the missing F-16. &quot;The Coast Guard has found some debris in the ocean that is apparently from our missing F-16&quot;, said Robert Sexton, the Shaw Air Force Base Public Affairs chief in Sumter, South Carolina The other pilot, Capt. Nicholas Giglio, is missing. &quot;They have not yet found any sign of the pilot and the search continues&quot;, Mr. Sexton said. No one witnessed what happened to Captain Giglio after the collision.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.af.mil/news/story.asp?id=123173189&lt;/ref&gt;
*17 October - An [[United States Marine Corps]] [[McDonnell Douglas]] [[F/A-18 Hornet]] [[F/A-18 Hornet#Specifications_.28F.2FA-18C.2FD.29|D]] (''164729'') from the Marine All Weather Fighter Attack Squadron No. 224 [[VMFA(AW)-224]] based at the [[Marine Corps Air Station Beaufort]], [[Beaufort, South Carolina]]  experiences a heavy landing at [[Jacksonville International Airport]], [[Duval County, Florida]].  The aircraft with two other Marine F/A-18 Hornet aircraft were landing at Jacksonville Airport in preparation for a flyover at the nearby [[National Football League|NFL]] [[Jacksonville Jaguars]] game when the aircraft experiences an airborne technical fault and the port landing-gear collapses causing the aircraft to land only on the nose-wheel, starboard undercarriage and the exposed port-side external fuel-tank.   The F/A-18 Hornet skidded down the runway with most damage occurring to the grounded external fuel-tank and the 2 Marine crew were uninjured.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.miamiherald.com/news/florida/AP/story/1288592.html Miami Herald - 2 pilots OK after fighter jet's rocky landing&lt;/ref&gt;
*22 October - An [[United States Army]] [[Sikorsky Aircraft|Sikorsky]] [[UH-60 Black Hawk]] [[Helicopter]] while on a routine training exercise crashes onto the deck of the [[USNS Arctic (T-AOE-8)|USNS Arctic]] off the coast of [[Fort Story]], [[Virginia Beach]], [[Virginia]].  The Black Hawk helicopter from the [[160th Special Operations Aviation Regiment (United States)|160th Special Operations Aviation Regiment (Airborne)]] was on a joint exercise with the [[United States Navy SEALs]] and was practising fast maritime interdiction by [[Abseiling|rappelling]] by rope to the ships deck when the accident occurred killing 1 crew and injuring a further 8 service personnel.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.nypost.com/p/news/national/dead_hurt_in_helicopter_crash_on_2xntrqrdzAh43tYU6d591K New York Post - 1 dead, 8 hurt in helicopter crash on Navy ship&lt;/ref&gt;
*23 October - An [[Indian Air Force]] [[Mikoyan|Mikoyan-Gurevich]] [[Mikoyan-Gurevich MiG-27|MiG-27]] ''Flogger D/J'' flying from the [[Hasimara]] Air Force Base, [[Eastern Air Command, Indian Air Force|Eastern Air Command]] crashes near [[New Jalpaiguri]], [[West Bengal]], India.  The aircraft on a routine training exercise suffers a technical fault and an on-board engine fire shortly after take-off.  After a successful ejection the pilot parachutes into a nearby tea estate and the aircraft crashes into a nearby river bank injuring two children.&lt;ref&gt;http://24dunia.com/english-news/topheadlines-news/showgroup/4257922.html Hindustan Times - MiG-27 crash: Pilot survives, children suffer burns&lt;/ref&gt;
*29 October - A [[Brazilian Air Force|Força Aérea Brasileira]] [[Cessna]] [[Cessna 208|208]] C-98/U-27 Caravan 1 '' FAB-2725'' flying from [[Cruzeiro do Sul, Acre]] to [[Tabatinga]] crash lands in the [[Ituí River]] a small tributary of the Rio Javari, [[Amazonas (Brazilian state)|Amazonas]] State.   The twin-engined turboprop aircraft of the 7º Esquadrão de Transporte Aéreo from Base Aérea de Manaus was transporting officials from Brazilian Ministry of Health participating in a vaccination programme when the aircraft crashed landed between the Amazonian villages of Aurelius and New River. The aircraft was later found by indigenous villagers of the region discovering 9 survivors and 2 dead crew.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.fab.mil.br/portal/capa/index.php?datan=31/10/2009&amp;page=mostra_notimpol FAB Os nove sobreviventes de acidente com avião da FAB foram levados para hospital no Acre&lt;/ref&gt;
*30 October - An [[United States Coast Guard]] [[Lockheed C-130 Hercules]] from USCG Air Station Sacramento, CA collided with an [[United States Marine Corps]] [[Bell AH-1 SuperCobra]] Attack Helicopter {{convert|15|mi|km}} off of the coast of Southern California, killing all seven Coast aircrew and both Marine aircrew.
*6 November - A [[Russian Naval Aviation]] [[Tupolev]] [[Tupolev Tu-142|Tu-142 M3]] ''Bear F/J'' from the 310th Independent Long Range Anti-Submarine Aviation Regiment based at [[Kamenny Ruchey]] Airbase crashes 15–20&amp;nbsp;km from the coast of Cape Datta north of  [[Sovetskaya Gavan]].  The Naval aircraft on a routine training exercise crashes into the sea in the [[Strait of Tartary|Tatar Straight]] near the island of [[Sakhalin]] with the loss of all 11 crew.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.newsru.com/russia/07nov2009/tu.html News Russia.com Татарском проливе ищут экипаж упавшего Ту-142&lt;/ref&gt;
*24 November - An Italian Air Force transport plane [[C-130J]] engaged in a training mission crashed nearby train tracks bordering the Pisa airport, while climbing and performing a left turn immediately after take-off. The aircraft immediately burst into flames, killing its five-member crew.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news| url=http://beta.thehindu.com/news/international/article53807.ece | location=Chennai, India | work=The Hindu | title=Italian military plane crashes, 5 dead | date=24 November 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*27 November - A [[Sri Lanka Air Force]] [[Mil Moscow Helicopter Plant|Mil]] [[Mil Mi-24|Mi-24]] ''Hind'' [[Helicopter]] (CH635, c/n 3532431622597) engaged on a training mission, crashed 5&amp;nbsp;km north of Buttala(310&amp;nbsp;km south-east of Colombo) at approximately 1330 HRS due to technical failure. Prior to the crash the pilot have reported a power generator failure to the tail rotor. Pilot, Co-Pilot and 2 door gunners have died from this incident.&lt;ref&gt;http://news.armoks.com/air-force-helicopter-crashes-in-sri-lanka/28598/&lt;/ref&gt;
*30 November - An [[Indian Air Force]] [[Su-30MKI]] crashes near Jethagaon in Jaisalmer of Rajasthan after it took off from Jodhpur, crash happened while returning from a regular training mission, both pilots are safe.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.indianexpress.com/news/HAL-made-Sukhoi-crashes/548279&lt;/ref&gt;
*8 December - A [[Japan Maritime Self-Defense Force]] [[Sikorsky Aircraft|Sikorsky]] [[SH-60 Seahawk|HH-60H Seahawk]] [[Helicopter]] crashed and sank off the coast of Nagasaki. Two crewmembers were killed, while a third was rescued.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.japantoday.com/category/national/view/2-bodies-found-after-
msdf-helicopter-crash&lt;/ref&gt;
*16 December - [[Pakistan Air Force]] [[Dassault Mirage III]] fighter aircraft crashed during a training mission due to a technical fault. The pilot managed to eject safely, landing in the Durrab Lake, (Kallar Kahar) and was rescued by a boat.
*23 December - [[Thai Air Force]] [[Northrop F-5]]E (211 Sq. coded 21118/91681) fighter aircraft crashed in Thailand. Pilot Chatchawan Rassamee died.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.nzz.ch/nachrichten/panorama/thailand_kampfflugzeug_1.4328124.html&lt;/ref&gt;

==2010==
* 13 January - A [[Yemeni Air Force]] [[Aero L-39 Albatros]] training aircraft crashed in the area of Salah al-Din, west of the port city of Aden due to a technical problem. Pilot survived.&lt;ref&gt;http://news.ninemsn.com.au/article.aspx?id=999436&lt;/ref&gt;
* 14 January - A [[Russian Air Force]] [[Sukhoi Su-27]] crashes near Komsomolsk on Amur. Pilot killed.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.newsru.com/russia/16jan2010/kray.html&lt;/ref&gt;
* 14 January - A [[Royal New Zealand Air Force]] CT4 Airtrainer  crashes near Ohakea, New Zealand while performing routine aerobatic training. Pilot, Sqn Ldr Nick Cree, killed.&lt;ref name=&quot;TVNZ_3330170&quot;&gt;{{cite news |url=http://tvnz.co.nz/national-news/pilot-killed-in-air-force-crash-named-3330170 |title=Pilot killed in Air Force crash named |date=14 January 2010 |work=[[Television New Zealand]] |agency=[[Newstalk ZB]]/ [[NZPA]] |accessdate=14 October 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* 21 January - A [[Sociedad de Salvamento y Seguridad Marítima]] [[AgustaWestland AW139]] helicopter fell into the sea off Almería. Three people are missing.&lt;ref name=&quot;Stuff.co.nz_3259311&quot;&gt;{{cite news |url=http://www.stuff.co.nz/world/3259311/NZ-pilots-body-found-after-helicopter-crash |title=NZ pilot's body found after helicopter crash |date=25 January 2010 |work=[[Stuff.co.nz]] |accessdate=14 October 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* 22 January - A [[Myanmar Air Force]] [[Chengdu J-7|F-7]] fighter  crashed  while attempting to land at Yangon airport, killing its pilot.&lt;ref&gt;http://theasiandefence.blogspot.com/2010/01/myanmar-air-force-f-7-jet-crashes.html&lt;/ref&gt;
* 23 January - A [[United States Navy]] T-34C Turbomentor, an upgraded version of the [[T-34 Mentor]], crash-landed in [[Lake Pontchartrain]] near [[New Orleans]]. One pilot was rescued and the other was missing.&lt;ref&gt;[http://forums.liveleak.com/showthread.php?p=779173 US Navy T-34 crash. One pilot found, one missing]&lt;/ref&gt; The plane, on a routine nighttime instrument training mission, crashed about 1845 hrs. and was {{convert|1|nmi|km|adj=on}} north of [[Lakefront Airport]] in New Orleans on an apparent approach to land. [[Coast Guard]] teams rescued the student pilot about 9 p.m. with mild hypothermia and moderate injuries from the 57 degree water. The pilot, Lt. Clinton Wermers, 33, from [[Mitchell, South Dakota]], was presumed dead. He had been assigned to [[Naval Air Station Whiting Field]] since March 2007.&lt;ref&gt;Florida Freedom Newspapers, &quot;Whiting Field pilot presumed dead in Louisiana crash&quot;, Northwest Florida Daily News, Fort Walton Beach, Florida, 26 January 2010, p. A1.&lt;/ref&gt; A memorial service was held for Lt. Wermers on 1 February at Whiting Field.&lt;ref&gt;Florida Freedom Newspapers, &quot;Mourners honor fallen serviceman&quot;, Northwest Florida Daily News, Fort Walton Beach, Florida, 2 February 2010, p. A3&lt;/ref&gt;
* 24 January - A [[Finnish Air Force]] [[F-18]] Hornet crashed in the south of the country. The fighter crashed in Juuapajoki, north of the southern city of Tampere at about 11:50 local time. The two pilots, who were on a routine training flight, ejected safely and were uninjured.&lt;ref&gt;http://english.people.com.cn/90001/90777/90853/6875773.html&lt;/ref&gt;
* 26 January - A [[Nigerian Navy]] [[AgustaWestland AW109|AgustaWestland AW109E]] helicopter crashed in south Nigeria. The accident happened at about 01:30 p.m. (1330 GMT) when the helicopter was returning from a routine patrol of Port-Harcourt area in the Niger-Delta region. Four people were killed.&lt;ref&gt;http://english.people.com.cn/90001/90777/90855/6879952.html&lt;/ref&gt;
* 3 February - [[Sikorsky UH-60 Black Hawk]] [[United States Army]]-helicopter crashed in Germany about 1800 hrs. local time northeast of Mannheim, killing three people on board.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.upi.com/Top_News/US/2010/02/03/US-Army-copter-crashes-in-Germany-3-die/UPI-76081265245951/&lt;/ref&gt;
* 5 February - [[UH-1_Iroquois_variants#UH-1H|UH-1H Iroquois]] [[Brazilian Air Force]] helicopter crashed in Campo Grande.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.campogrande.news.com.br/canais/view/?canal=8&amp;id=281518&lt;/ref&gt;
* 9 February - [[Bell AH-1 Cobra]] [[Pakistan Air Force]] gunship helicopter has crashed in the Teera Valley in Pakistan's Khyber tribal area near the Afghanistan's border. Both helicopter's pilot and gunner lost their lives in the incident.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.defence.pk/forums/land-forces/46845-pakistani-armys-cobra-gunship-helicopter-crashed-teera-valley.html&lt;/ref&gt;
* 10 February - [[Eurocopter AS350]] [[Brazilian Army]]-helicopter crashed while training tactical piloting maneuvering at Sao Pedro da Aldeia naval base, about {{convert|130|km|mi|sp=us}} far Rio de Janeiro city.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.vnews.com.br/noticia.php?id=65849&amp;/?utm_source=google&amp;utm_medium=medium&amp;utm_campaign=VNews_C_Texto&lt;/ref&gt;
* 11 February - An [[Italian Air Force]] [[General Dynamics F-16 Fighting Falcon|F-16A]] ADF Fighting Falcon  from 5th Fighter Wing crashed into the Adriatic Sea {{convert|3|nmi|km}} from the coast  near Ravenna at 1530 hrs. when he was training with another aircraft of the same unit. Pilot survived.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.aeronautica.difesa.it/News/Pagine/F16cadutoinmare.aspx&lt;/ref&gt;
* 14 February - A [[Yemeni Air Force]] [[Mil Mi-17]] [[Helicopter]] crashes in the Kahlan district, east of the provincial capital Saada. Crash was the result of a technical fault. The helicopter's four-man crew and the seven wounded soldiers they were evacuating all died, as did two soldiers in a military vehicle which the aircraft crashed into.&lt;ref&gt;http://business.maktoob.com/20090000435614/Death_toll_in_Yemen_chopper_crash_rises_to_13/Article.htm&lt;/ref&gt;
* 16 February - An [[Indian Air Force]] [[Mikoyan-Gurevich MiG-27]] fighter went down near Siliguri in West Bengal  killing the pilot, a squadron leader.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news| url=http://timesofindia.indiatimes.com/india/Pilot-killed-in-MiG-27-crash-/articleshow/5581367.cms | work=The Times Of India | title=Pilot killed in MiG-27 crash | date=17 February 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* 18 February - [[Sikorsky SH-60 Seahawk|Sikorsky MH-60S Seahawk]] [[United States Navy]]-helicopter crashed in West Virginia outside of Lewisburg. Passengers and crew sustained unspecified injuries, none of which are life-threatening.&lt;ref&gt;http://wowktv.com/story.cfm?func=viewstory&amp;storyid=75427&lt;/ref&gt;
* 18 February - An [[Indian Air Force]] [[Mikoyan-Gurevich MiG-21]] fighter jet (8th Squadron, 20th Wing) crashed soon after take-off from Bagdora in West Bengal  but the pilot ejected to safety.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news| url=http://timesofindia.indiatimes.com/india/IAF-MiG-21-crashes-in-West-Bengal-pilot-safe-/articleshow/5593107.cms | work=The Times Of India | title=IAF MiG-21 crashes in West Bengal, pilot safe | date=19 February 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* 21 February - [[United States Army]] [[Bell OH-58 Kiowa]] helicopter made a &quot;hard landing&quot; in northern Iraq killing the two pilots on board.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news| url=http://timesofindia.indiatimes.com/world/middle-east/US-military-2-US-helicopter-pilots-killed-in-Iraq-/articleshow/5601047.cms | work=The Times Of India | title=US military: 2 US helicopter pilots killed in Iraq | deadurl=yes}} {{Dead link|date=April 2011|bot=RjwilmsiBot}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* 24 February - A [[Mexican Air Force|Fuerza Aérea Mexicana]] [[Cessna 182|Cessna 182S Skylane]] crashed during take off near San Diego de Alcalá, Chihuahua, 3 injured, 2 fatalities.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.segundoasegundo.com/html/43027_0_1_0_C.html&lt;/ref&gt;
* 24 February - A [[Philippine Air Force]] [[North American OV-10 Bronco]] crashed during training at 1455 hrs. Two Philippine Air Force pilots were killed.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.tribune.net.ph/headlines/20100225hed2.html&lt;/ref&gt;
* 25 February - An [[United States Air Force]] [[General Dynamics F-16 Fighting Falcon|F-16C Fighting Falcon]] crashed during landing at Osan Air Base, South Korea.22-year-old plane became uncontrollable and the pilot bailed out. The jet was heavily damaged and crashed within Osan's boundaries.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.airforcetimes.com/news/2010/02/airforce_f16_crash_osan_022610w/&lt;/ref&gt;
* 2 March - An [[Republic of Korea Air Force]] Northrop [[F-5E]] and Northrop [[Northrop F-5|F-5]]F crashed into Mount Hwangbyeong, about {{convert|20|km|mi|sp=us}} west of the city of Gangneung, Gangwon. The pilot of the F-5E and the two pilots of the F-5F were killed.&lt;ref&gt;http://joongangdaily.joins.com/article/view.asp?aid=2917313&lt;/ref&gt;
* 3 March - An [[Indian Navy]] [[HAL Kiran]] crashed into building in Hyderabad during the air show/exhibition &quot;India Aviation 2010&quot;.Both pilots and a civilian on the ground were killed. Also at least 5 other civilians received injuries.&lt;ref&gt;Both pilots and a civilian on the ground were killed. Also at least 5 other civilians received injuries.&lt;/ref&gt;
* 3 March - A [[Azerbaijan Air Force]] [[Sukhoi Su-25]] close air support aircraft crashed in the Shamkir district in northwest Azerbaijan at ~1700 hrs. local time, killing the pilot.&lt;ref&gt;http://en.rian.ru/exsoviet/20100303/158080923.html&lt;/ref&gt;
* 3 March - An [[Republic of Korea Army]] [[MD Helicopters MD 500]]  helicopter  crashed 20&amp;nbsp;km east of the capital Seoul, at ~2014 hrs. Helicopter hit a greenhouse in a rice paddy in Namyangju. The two crew members were rushed to a hospital but were later confirmed dead.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.hindustantimes.com/world-news/restofasia/SKorean-military-chopper-crashes-2-pilots-killed/Article1-514888.aspx&lt;/ref&gt;
* 3 March - A [[Coast Guard]] MH-60T, an upgraded [[Sikorsky HH-60 Jayhawk]] helicopter crashed in the remote Utah mountains. It was one of two traveling through the area en route to its home base in [[Elizabeth City, North Carolina]], after performing security duty at the [[Vancouver]] [[Winter Olympic Games]]. The helicopters made a refueling stop in [[Salt Lake City]] and were headed to [[Leadville, Colorado]], when the crash occurred about {{convert|50|mi|km}} east of Salt Lake City. Three crewmen were airlifted to local hospitals and two others sustained minor injuries.&lt;ref&gt;Associated Press, &quot;Coast Guard helicopter crashes in mountains&quot;, Northwest Florida Daily News, Fort Walton Beach, Florida, Thursday, 4 March 2010, p. A2.&lt;/ref&gt;
* 10 March - A [[Brazilian Army]] [[Eurocopter Fennec]] helicopter crashed During a night training flight during Operation Caburé. All four crew members died.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.cidadebranca.com.br/contents.php?CID=78935&lt;/ref&gt;
* 10 March - A [[United States Marine Corps]] [[F/A-18D Hornet]], BuNo ''164694'', 'WK-01', from [[VMFA(AW)-224]] crashed into the Atlantic Ocean, app. {{convert|35|mi|km}} east of St. Helena Sound, South Carolina, after a double engine failure and a fire. Both pilots ejected and were floating in an inflatable life raft for about one hour before they were rescued by a USCG helicopter.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.google.com/hostednews/ap/article/ALeqM5h8Ycl2CSWZMDDu_jgIJhD4hWm-8QD9ECG7GO0&lt;/ref&gt;
* 11 March - A [[Mil Mi-8]] helicopter Kazakhstan  The Ministry of Emergency Situations crashed for unknown reasons during rescue flight in blizzard.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.velozia.com/?p=2959&lt;/ref&gt;
* 15 March - Two [[United States Navy]] [[F/A-18E Super Hornet]]s from [[VFA-122]] collided in mid-air at 2200 hrs., sending one crashing to the Nevada desert. One pilot ejected safely before his aircraft crashed near [[Naval Air Station Fallon]] and a second pilot landed the single-seat jet safely at Fallon.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.navytimes.com/news/2010/03/navy_hornet_crash_31610/&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Griswold, Lewis, and Eddie Jimenez, &quot;Two Navy Officers Killed In NAS Lemoore Jet Crash&quot;, ''[[Fresno Bee]]'', 6 April 2011.&lt;/ref&gt;
* 19 March - A [[Turkish Army]] [[TAI/AgustaWestland T-129]] (registration CSX81723) helicopter prototype lost its tail rotor at {{convert|15000|ft|m|abbr=on}}. height at 16:30. Two people on board survived.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.vcoazzurranews.info/index.php?option=com_content&amp;task=view&amp;id=17163&amp;Itemid=215&lt;/ref&gt;
* 23 March - A [[Turkish Army]] [[Sikorsky UH-60 Black Hawk]] came down on the outskirts of Wardak town in Afghanistan  at around 10:30. The crash happened as two Turkish helicopters were attempting to land at a Turkish-run Provincial Reconstruction Team.&lt;ref&gt;http://es.quote.com/news/story.action?id=RTT003230714000504&lt;/ref&gt;
* 23 March - A [[Royal Air Force]] [[BAE Hawk]]. Two members of the [[Red Arrows]] aerobatic team were involved in a midair collision in airshow at Heraklion Crete. Pilot of one ejected and received moderate injuries. Aircraft crashed on the airfield and was destroyed. The second aircraft landed safely in Heraklion Airport.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news| url=http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/uk_news/england/lincolnshire/8583263.stm | work=BBC News | title=Red Arrows in mid-air collision | date=23 March 2010 | accessdate=8 May 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* 25 March - A [[Royal Malaysian Air Force]] [[Pilatus PC-7]].Crashed during airshow near local university campus. Pilot bailed at low altitude but was killed.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.thestar.com.my/news/story.asp?file=/2010/3/26/nation/5935143&amp;sec=nation=nation&lt;/ref&gt;
* 25 March - A [[Chilean Army]] [[MD_Helicopters_MD_500#MD_530F|MD Helicopters 530F]] The helicopter was on a mission in the region that was badly damaged by the last earthquake. The helicopter suffered an engine failure shortly after takeoff after disembarking a passenger and crashed. All 4 crew member were taken to the hospital, three of them with serious injuries.&lt;ref&gt;http://latercera.com/contenido/680_236903_9.shtml&lt;/ref&gt;
* 29 March - [[Sikorsky UH-60 Black Hawk]] [[United States Army]]-helicopter crashed in Forward Operating Base Atgar in the Zabul province of Afghanistan.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.velozia.com/?p=3195&amp;utm_source=feedburner&amp;utm_medium=feed&amp;utm_campaign=Feed%3A+VeloziaAir+%28Velozia+Air%29&amp;utm_content=Google+Reader&lt;/ref&gt;
* 31 March - [[Grumman E-2 Hawkeye]] [[United States Navy]] craft from Carrier Airborne Early Warning Squadron 121 crashed at approximately 1400 hrs. local time in Arabian Sea. It was returning to its ship, the [[USS Eisenhower|USS ''Eisenhower'']], after conducting operations in support of Operation Enduring Freedom when it experienced mechanical malfunctions and the crew performed a controlled bailout.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news| url=http://www.foxnews.com/us/2010/03/31/navy-plane-crashes-north-arabian-sea-missing/?utm_source=feedburner&amp;utm_medium=feed&amp;utm_campaign=Feed%3A+foxnews%2Fus+%28Text+-+US%29 | work=Fox News | title=U.S. Navy Plane Crashes in North Arabian Sea, One Missing | date=31 March 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;  The pilot was killed. Navy 5th Fleet officials declined to speculate on the cause of the crash, but the Naval Safety Center’s Web site listed it as “an engine oil leak.”&lt;ref name=&quot;Tilghman, Andrew 2010&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;navytimes.com&quot;/&gt;
* 2 April - [[Embraer EMB 312 Tucano]] [[Brazilian Air Force]] aircraft from the Brazilian Air Force &quot;Smoke Squadron&quot; crashed during an airshow at the Aeroporto Federal de Lages. The pilot, aged 33, died in the crash.&lt;ref&gt;http://aviation-safety.net/wikibase/wiki.php?id=73764&lt;/ref&gt;
* 8 April - [[MFI-17 Mushshak]] [[Pakistan Army]] crashed in an open field, Nelavia area, near Peshawar's suburbs of Tagman.&lt;ref&gt;http://thenews.jang.com.pk/updates.asp?id=102413&lt;/ref&gt;
* 8 April - [[Dassault Mirage F1]] [[French Air Force]] The aircraft was conducting the basic training of Rheims when it crashed about 1140 hrs. in a field near a highway, four miles (6&amp;nbsp;km) from the base of Orléans.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.lepoint.fr/actualites-societe/2010-04-08/un-mirage-f1-s-ecrase-pres-d-orleans-sans-faire-de-victime/920/0/442297&lt;/ref&gt;
* 9 April - [[V-22 Osprey|CV-22 Osprey]] [[United States Air Force]], the first combat loss of an Osprey, went down near [[Qalat, Zabul Province]], killing 4.&lt;ref name=&quot;cnncrashaf&quot;&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.cnn.com/2010/WORLD/asiapcf/04/09/afghanistan.chopper.down/index.html?iref=topnews|title=ISAF: 4 killed in U.S. aircraft crash in Afghanistan|date=April 9, 2010 |work=CNN Wire Staff|publisher=[[CNN]]|accessdate=9 April 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* 10 April - Polish military [[Very Important Person|VIP]] transport [[Tupolev Tu-154|Tupolev Tu-154M]] aircraft, ''101'', from the 36th Special Air Transport Regiment [[2010 Polish Air Force Tu-154 crash|hit trees as it approached Smolensk's airport]] in thick fog killing Polish President [[Lech Kaczyński]], Poland's army chief, central bank governor, MPs and leading historians were among more than 80 passengers.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news| url=http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/world/europe/8612825.stm | work=BBC News | title=Polish leader dies in plane crash | date=10 April 2010 | accessdate=8 May 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* 12 April - [[United States Navy]] [[Rockwell Sabreliner]] crashed [[Morganton, Georgia|Morganton]] killing all four crew on board.&lt;ref&gt;http://aviation-safety.net/database/record.php?id=20100412-0&lt;/ref&gt;
* 13 April - [[Dassault/Dornier Alpha Jet]] [[French Air Force]] E122/F-TERD of Patrouille de France crashed near Plan de Dieu Airport (LF51), Vaucluse area. The pilot ejected and escaped with minor injuries.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.france-info.com/france-regions-2010-04-13-un-avion-de-la-patrouille-de-france-s-ecrase-dans-le-vaucluse-le-429334-9-13.html&lt;/ref&gt;
* 15 April - [[South Korean Navy]] [[Westland Lynx]] helicopter was on a routine patrol mission when it crashed in sea near Chuja Island 14.5&amp;nbsp;km southeast of Jindo, South Jeolla Province. One occupants was killed and three others are missing.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.straitstimes.com/BreakingNews/Asia/Story/STIStory_515267.html&lt;/ref&gt;
* 16 April- [[Spanish Air Force]] [[Bell 212]] crashed in [[Haiti]] near the border with the [[Dominican Republic]] killing all 4 crew on board.[http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/world/americas/8626593.stm]
* 17 April - [[Sikorsky UH-60 Black Hawk]] [[United States Army]]-helicopter crashed in Al-Mahzam area, about {{convert|12|mi|km}} north of Tikrit ,Iraq. One soldier killed.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.military.com/news/article/soldier-killed-in-iraq-black-hawk-crash.html&lt;/ref&gt;
* 20 April-  While performing maneuvers, a [[Vertical de Aviación]] [[Bell 222]]UT helicopter, registered ''HK-3262'', and a [[Fuerza Aérea de Colombia]] (Colombian Air Force) [[MD Helicopters/Hughes 500/530]] crashed on a military garrison near [[Chaparral, Tolima]], Colombia.&lt;ref&gt;http://airflightdisaster.com/?p=9445&lt;/ref&gt;
* 20 April - [[HH-65 Dolphin]] US [[Coast Guard]] crashed into the {{convert|50|ft|m|adj=on}}-deep water in [[Lake Huron]], and sank nine miles (14&amp;nbsp;km) north of [[Port Huron]], Michigan.&lt;ref&gt;http://m.freep.com/news.jsp?key=637744&amp;rc=lo&lt;/ref&gt;
* 21 April - Two [[Mikoyan MiG-29]] [[Belarusian Air Force]] fighter jets collided during a training flight. There were no casualties as one MiG-29 landed safely, while the pilot in the second plane ejected before it crashed.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.etaiwannews.com/etn/news_content.php?id=1234228&amp;lang=eng_news&amp;cate_img=1037.jpg&amp;cate_rss=General&lt;/ref&gt;
* 25 April - A [[Royal New Zealand Air Force]] [[UH-1_Iroquois_variants#UH-1H|UH-1H Iroquois]] crashed in heavy fog about 40&amp;nbsp;km north east of Wellington.  Three persons were killed and a fourth seriously injured.&lt;ref name=&quot;Stuff.co.nz_3620651&quot;&gt;{{cite news |url=http://www.stuff.co.nz/the-press/news/3620651/Airforce-chopper-crashes-near-Wellington |title=Anzac air crash kills three |date=25 April 2010 |work=[[The Press]] |accessdate=14 October 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* 2 May [[Boeing AH-64 Apache]] [[United States Army]] helicopter carrying two soldiers of the 116th Aviation Group, was participating in a routine drill when it crashed on a ramp while taxiing at [[McEntire Joint National Guard Base]], South Carolina, shortly before 1400 hrs. Both crew were taken to hospital. Pilot 1st Lt. Jonathan Shively, Jr, 33, of [[Jamestown, South Carolina|Jamestown]], died of injuries, but second pilot, Chief Warrant Officer Roger Carpenter, 46, of [[Spartanburg, South Carolina|Spartanburg]], was in stable condition.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.upi.com/Top_News/US/2010/05/03/Military-helicopter-crash-probed-in-SC/UPI-86271272924852/&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;http://www.thestate.com/2010/05/02/1270184/mcentire-pilot-dies-in-copter.html&lt;/ref&gt;
* 10 May [[Sikorsky UH-60 Black Hawk]] [[United States Army]] helicopter made a controlled landing after being hit by enemy fire in Helmand Province . All crewmembers were safely returned to base. Helicopter was intentionally destroyed by international forces.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.isaf.nato.int/en/article/isaf-releases/coalition-helicopter-downed-in-helmand-crew-safe.htm&lt;/ref&gt;
* 10 May [[Fairchild A-10 Thunderbolt II]] from 23rd Wing 75th Fighter Squadron s/n 79-0141 [[US Air Force]] crashed during take off at Moody Air Force Base, Georgia.  Pilot ejected safely.&lt;ref&gt;http://aviation-safety.net/wikibase/wiki.php?id=74272&lt;/ref&gt;
* 11 May [[Dassault Mirage 2000]] [[French Air Force]] crashed in a forest of Bougue close to Villeneuve-de-Marsan (Landes, Aquitaine), 6&amp;nbsp;km east of Mont de Marsan AB (LFBM) ,after technical problems. The pilot ejected safely and only received minor injuries.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.lindependant.com/articles/2010-05-11/un-mirage-s-ecrase-pres-de-mont-de-marsan-le-pilote-sain-et-sauf-178970.php&lt;/ref&gt;
* 12 May - After taking off from the base at [[Rimini]] an [[Italian Air Force]] [[MD Helicopters MD 500|NH 500]] helicopter of 15º Stormo (83º Centro CSAR) flew about fifty feet above the ground when the engine suddenly quit.  The helicopter [[autorotate]]d to impact and both occupants escaped unhurt.&lt;ref&gt;http://translate.google.com/translate?js=y&amp;prev=_t&amp;hl=en&amp;ie=UTF-8&amp;layout=1&amp;eotf=1&amp;u=http://www.corriereadriatico.it/articolo.php%3Fid%3D101599&amp;sl=it&amp;tl=en&lt;/ref&gt;
* 21 May - A [[U.S. Navy]] [[Lockheed P-3 Orion]]  accidentally released a sonobuoy shortly after departure from [[NAS Jacksonville]], Florida, which fell {{convert|500|ft|m}} and crashed through the roof of a home in [[Mandarin, Florida]], coming to rest in a bedroom next to a bed. Resident Marwan Saman said his daughter had just gotten out of that bed about a half hour earlier. The Navy sent an explosives demolition team to retrieve the {{convert|3|ft|m|adj=on}}-long, 40-pound cylinder. No injuries were reported, and the Navy was making arrangements to pay for the damage. A malfunctioning launch tube was theorized for the drop.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.nwfdailynews.com/news/navy-29329-bouy-drops.html&lt;/ref&gt;
* 7 July - A [[United States Coast Guard]] MH-60J crashed off of [[La Push, Washington]] apparently after clipping power lines.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news| url=http://seattletimes.nwsource.com/html/localnews/2012301842_coptercrash08m.html | work=The Seattle Times | title=3 dead in Coast Guard copter crash off La Push | date=7 July 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* 19 July - [[Philippine Air Force]] [[SIAI S-211]] ''09005'' crashed during a training flight in the Philippines, crew ejected OK.&lt;ref name=&quot;scramble375-76&quot;&gt;Scramble #375 p. 76&lt;/ref&gt;
* 23 July - A [[Canadian Forces]] [[CF-18 Hornet]], ''188738'', of [[419 Moose Squadron]], based at [[Cold Lake (Alberta)|Cold Lake]], crashed at [[Lethbridge County Airport]] during a low-speed, low-altitude practice run for the [[Alberta International Airshow]], the pilot Capt. Brian Bews, 36, ejected in a [[Martin-Baker]] seat seconds before the fighter fell off on its starboard wing and impacted on the airfield. He suffered a compression fracture in three vertebrae but is expected to fully recover.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news| url=http://www.cbc.ca/canada/edmonton/story/2010/07/26/lethbridge-cf18-crash-bews-pilot-statement-alberta.html | work=CBC News | title=CF-18 crash pilot applauds ejection seat | date=26 July 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;http://www.calgaryherald.com/business/energy-resources/crashes+burns+Lethbridge+airport/3315226/story.html&lt;/ref&gt;
* 26 July - An [[Israeli Air Force|Israeli Air Force (IAF)]] [[Sikorsky Aircraft|Sikorsky]] [[CH-53 Sea Stallion]] helicopter crashed during a joint Israeli-Romanian aviation exercise in the [[Carpathian Mountains]] in northern [[Romania]], killing six IAF officers and one [[Romanian Air Force]] officer.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title=Netanyahu: Romania helicopter crash is an immense tragedy|url=http://www.haaretz.com/news/diplomacy-defense/netanyahu-romania-helicopter-crash-is-an-immense-tragedy-1.304236?localLinksEnabled=false|author=Anshel Pfeffer, Haaretz Service and News Agencies|date=July 26, 2010|work=Haaretz|accessdate=4 August 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* 28 July A [[United States Air Force]] [[Boeing C-17 Globemaster III|Boeing C-17A Globemaster III]], ''00-0173'', ''Spirit of the Aleutians'', on a training mission crashed at ~1814 hrs. into a wooded area on [[Elmendorf Air Force Base]] in [[Anchorage, Alaska]] killing 3 members of the [[Alaska Air National Guard]] and 1 member of the [[US Air Force]]. The cause of the accident is under investigation.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news | title=Four Dead in Alaska Air Force Base Crash | accessdate=2010-07-29 | publisher=cbsnews.com | url =http://www.cbsnews.com/stories/2010/07/29/national/main6723212.shtml?tag=stack | date=29 July 2010 | deadurl=yes}} {{Dead link|date=December 2011|bot=RjwilmsiBot}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news | title=Four confirmed dead in Elmendorf plane crash | accessdate=2010-07-29 | publisher=Anchorage Daily News adn.com | url =http://www.adn.com/2010/07/28/1385727/cargo-plane-reported-down-on-base.html}}&lt;/ref&gt; This is apparently the first C-17 accident to result in the loss of life.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.adn.com/2010/07/28/1385727/cargo-plane-reported-down-on-base.html&lt;/ref&gt; The crash damaged tracks of the [[Alaska Railroad]], which temporarily suspended operations in the area of the accident.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.adn.com/2010/07/29/1387215/fatal-c-17-crash-also-damaged.html&lt;/ref&gt;
* 28 July - An [[Iraqi Air Force]] Mil Mi-17 crashed in a sandstorm south-west of Baghdad, five killed.&lt;ref name=&quot;scramble375-79&quot; /&gt;
* 30 July - A Hellenic Army Boeing AH-64DHA Longbow on a test flight crashed at Megara Air Force Base, Greece, two killed.&lt;ref name=&quot;scramble375-79&quot;&gt;Scramble #375 p. 79&lt;/ref&gt;
* 24 August - A [[Spanish Air Force]] [[Eurofighter]] fighter  crashed  while attempting to take off at Moron Air Base, a Lieutenant Colonel of the Royal Saudi Air Force were killed while a Spanish Air Force Commander bail out exitously.
* 10 November - An [[Indian Air Force]] [[Mikoyan-Gurevich MiG-27]] fighter went down near [[Jodhpur]] in [[Rajasthan]] shortly after take off for a routine sortie, but the pilot bailed out safely.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | title = MiG-27 crashes near Jodhpur, pilot safe |publisher = Ibnlive.in.com | url = http://ibnlive.in.com/news/mig27-crashes-near-jodhpur-pilot-safe/134747-3.html?from=tn| accessdate = Nov 10, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*16 November - A USAF [[F-22A Raptor]], ''06-4125'', of the [[525th Fighter Squadron]], 3d Wing, crashes in [[Alaska]] near [[Susitna Lodge]], killing pilot Capt. Jeffrey Haney, from [[Clarklake, Michigan]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Allport, Dave 2011, page 93&quot;&gt;Allport, Dave, &quot;''Accident Report''&quot;, Air Forces Monthly, Stamford, Lincs., UK, February 2011, Number 274, page 93.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;http://www.f-22raptor.com/news_view.php?nid=423&lt;/ref&gt;
*20 November - Two people were taken to Pensacola Naval Hospital for evaluation after landing an Air Force [[T-6 Texan II]] with the landing gear up. The names of the two crew members were not released after the 1300 hrs. incident, [[Pensacola Naval Air Station]] Public Affairs Officer Harry White said. Both people safely exited the plane, which landed at [[Forrest Sherman Field]] at the air station, White said. The aircraft and crew are assigned to the U.S. Air Force's 455th Flying Training Squadron at NAS Pensacola. The incident is being investigated by a board of officers, a NAS Pensacola news release said.&lt;ref&gt;Pensacola, Florida, &quot;''Two land Air Force plane with landing gear up, taken to hospital''&quot;, Pensacola News-Journal, 20 November 2010.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Allport, Dave, &quot;''Accident Report''&quot;, Air Forces Monthly, February 2011, Number 274, page 93.&lt;/ref&gt;
*2 December - US Navy [[F/A-18C Hornet]], BuNo ''165184'', 'AD-351', suffers port [[undercarriage]] collapse on landing at [[NAF El Centro]], California, at 1615 hrs., and departs runway. The pilot ejects safely.&lt;ref name=&quot;Allport, Dave 2011, page 93&quot;/&gt;

==2011==
* 20 January - [[Ecuadorian Air Force]] [[De Havilland Canada DHC-6 Twin Otter]] ''FAE449'' crashed near Tena, Ecuador, all six on board killed.&lt;ref name=&quot;scramble381-67&quot;&gt;Scramble #381 p. 67&lt;/ref&gt;
* 2 February - An [[Indian Army]] Cheetah helicopter crashed at Nashik, western India, both crew killed.&lt;ref name=&quot;scramble382-66&quot;&gt;Scramble #382 p. 66&lt;/ref&gt;
* 8 February - A [[Royal Jordanian Air Force]] [[General Dynamics F-16|F-16AM]] crashed in central Jordan, pilot killed.&lt;ref name=&quot;scramble382-67&quot;&gt;Scramble #382 p. 67&lt;/ref&gt;
* 14 February - Two [[Royal Thai Air Force]] [[General Dynamics F-16]]s collide over north east Thailand, aircraft destroyed but both pilots ejected safely.&lt;ref name=&quot;scramble382-68&quot;&gt;Scramble #382 p. 68&lt;/ref&gt;
* 29 March - A US Marine [[Sikorsky CH-53 Sea Stallion]] crashed in [[Kaneohe Bay]], killing one and injuring three crewmembers.&lt;ref&gt;[[Associated Press]], &quot;[http://www.navytimes.com/news/2011/04/ap-marine-investigators-raising-crashed-sea-stallion-helo-040611/ Investigators raising crashed Sea Stallion]&quot;, ''[[Military Times]]'', 6 April 2011.&lt;/ref&gt;
*30 March - Ten sailors are injured when an engine of an [[F/A-18C Hornet]] of [[VMFAT-101]] based at [[MCAS Miramar]], California,&lt;ref&gt;http://www.startribune.com/nation/118962469.html&lt;/ref&gt; suffers a catastrophic failure while preparing for launch at 1450 hrs. during routine training exercises from the [[USS John C. Stennis|USS ''John C. Stennis'']], ~100 miles off the California coast. Five of the injured are taken by helicopter to the shore, four to the Naval Medical Center, [[San Diego]], and one to Scripps Institute at [[La Jolla]], California, said U.S. Navy Cmdr. Pauline Storum. None of the injuries were considered life threatening but the fighter sustained over $1 million damage. The ensuing fire was quickly extinguished and the carrier itself was not damaged.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.king5.com/home/Sailors-injured-after-explosion-on-USS-John-C-Stennis-118965909.html&lt;/ref&gt;
* 1 April - An [[A-10 Thunderbolt]] from [[Spangdahlem Air Base]] crashed near [[Laufeld]], Germany.  The pilot, Lieutenant Colonel Scott Hurrelbrink, ejected and was not seriously injured.&lt;ref&gt;Kloeckner, Marcus, &quot;[http://www.stripes.com/news/farmer-recalls-thunderbolt-ii-crash-pilot-s-concern-1.140008 Farmer recalls Thunderbolt II crash, pilot's concern]&quot;, ''[[Stars and Stripes (newspaper)|Stars and Stripes]]'', 4 April 2011, retrieved 6 April 2011.&lt;/ref&gt;
* 6 April -  An [[VFA-122]] [[F/A-18E/F Super Hornet]] from [[Naval Air Station Lemoore]] crashed just outside the base, killing its two crewmembers.&lt;ref&gt;Guentes, Gidget, &quot;[http://www.navytimes.com/news/2011/04/navy-lemoore-2-killed-in-hornet-crash-040611w/ 2 dead as F/A-18 goes down near Lemoore]&quot;, ''[[Military Times]]'', 6 April 2011.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Griswold, Lewis, and Eddie Jimenez, &quot;Two Navy Officers Killed In NAS Lemoore Jet Crash&quot;, ''[[Fresno Bee]]'', 6 April 2011.&lt;/ref&gt;
*1 May - A two [[MH-60]] helicopter raid mounted from Afghanistan from [[Ghazi Airbase]]&lt;ref name=&quot;nationaljournal.com&quot;&gt;{{cite news|url=http://nationaljournal.com/whitehouse/the-secret-team-that-killed-bin-laden-20110502}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.newsmax.com/KenTimmerman/osamabinladen-seals-specialforces-pakistan/2011/05/02/id/394830|title=SEALs Sent to Kill bin Laden}}&lt;/ref&gt; with 20-25 [[United States Navy SEALS]] on a [[Pakistan|Pakistani]] compound to capture or kill [[Osama bin Laden]] results in the death of the [[Al Quaeda]] leader. One helicopter, suffering mechanical failure after a hard landing when it reportedly struck the compound wall, is destroyed by the special operations force, with the team members departing on two [[CH-47 Chinook]]s&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news| url=http://www.reuters.com/article/2011/05/03/us-binladen-helicopter-idUSTRE7427G420110503 | work=Reuters | title=Helicopter loss in bin Laden raid highlights risks | date=3 May 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; with bin Laden's remains.&lt;ref&gt;http://blogs.abcnews.com/politicalpunch/2011/05/obama-gives-order-bin-laden-is-killed-white-house-time-line.html&lt;/ref&gt; Both MH-60s were of the [[160th Special Operations Aviation Regiment]].&lt;ref name=&quot;blogs.abcnews.com&quot;&gt;{{cite news|url=http://blogs.abcnews.com/politicalpunch/2011/05/some-white-knuckle-moments-for-elite-navy-seals-team.html}}&lt;/ref&gt; Subsequent reports state that the [[Sikorsky H-60 Blackhawk|Blackhawk]] helicopter destroyed was a previously unconfirmed, but rumored, [[Stealth technology|stealth]] modification of the design.&lt;ref&gt;Ross, Brian, Schwartz, Rhonda, Ferran, Lee, and Patel, Avni, &quot;Top Secret Stealth Helicopter Program Revealed in Osama Bin Laden Raid: Experts&quot;, ABC World News, 4 May 2011.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;http://abcnews.go.com/Blotter/top-secret-stealth-helicopter-program-revealed-osama-bin/story?id=13530693&lt;/ref&gt;
*13 June - The second test launch of the [[Boeing X-51|Boeing X-51 Waverider]] ends in failure off the Southern California coast when the vehicle fails to separate from its booster rocket after an air launch from an [[Edwards AFB]], California-based [[B-52 Stratofortress]]. Following the drop, the X-51 fell for about four seconds before its booster successfully ignited. The vehicle fell into the Pacific Ocean after the booster did not separate as intended. &lt;ref&gt;Associated Press, &quot;2nd test flight of X-51 aircraft ends in crash,&quot; ''Air Force Times'', Saturday 18 June 2011.&lt;/ref&gt;
*19 July - A [[Royal Thai Army]] [[Sikorsky UH-60 Black Hawk]] helicopter crashed killing 9. The chopper had been sent out to recover five bodies of victims of another helicopter, a [[Bell UH-1 Iroquois]], that had crashed two days before while looking for illegal loggers over the [[Tenasserim Hills]] in the area between Myanmar and Thailand near [[Phetchaburi]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://seattletimes.nwsource.com/html/nationworld/2015692605_apasthailandhelicoptercrash.html?syndication=rss The Seattle Times]&lt;/ref&gt; A third helicopter, a [[Bell 212]], also crashed in the same area on Sunday 25th July a few miles further east close to the Kaeng Krachan reservoir killing three.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.bangkokpost.com/news/security/248732/copter-crashes-explained Bangkok Post - Helicopter crashes 'explained']&lt;/ref&gt; Superstitious people blame the three consecutive crashes on the fact that the densely forested mountains of the Tenasserim Range have strong [[tutelary deity|guardian spirits]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.bangkokpost.com/news/security/248615/superstitions-haunt-forest Bangkok Post - Superstitions haunt forest]&lt;/ref&gt;
*28 July - A [[F-16 Fighting Falcon|General Dynamics F-16C Block 30H Fighting Falcon]], ''87-296'', c/n 5C-557, of the [[187th Fighter Wing]], [[Alabama Air National Guard]], out of [[Montgomery Air National Guard Base]], overruns runway at the [[Experimental Aircraft Association|EAA]] [[EAA AirVenture Oshkosh|AirVenture Oshkosh]] air show at [[Wittman Regional Airport]], [[Oshkosh, Wisconsin]], nose gear collapses, nose radome breaks, airframe skids to a stop. Pilot uninjured. &lt;ref&gt;http://abclocal.go.com/wls/story?section=news/local/wisconsin&amp;id=8277786&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;http://www.fox6now.com/news/witi-20110728-eaa-f16-incident,0,628759.photogallery&lt;/ref&gt;
*20 August - A [[BAE Hawk]] of the RAF's [[Red Arrows]] aerobatic team crashed during a public display at [[Bournemouth Air Festival]], killing the pilot.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/uk-england-14602900|title=Red Arrows pilot dies in Bournemouth Air Festival crash|date=20 August 2011|accessdate=20 August 2011|publisher=BBC|work=BBC News Online}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*2 September - A [[CASA C-212 Aviocar]] of the [[Chilean Air Force]] [[2011 Chilean Air Force CASA 212 crash|crashed into the sea]] off [[Robinson Crusoe Island]]. All 21 people on board were killed.

==See also==
*[[List of accidents and incidents involving military aircraft]]
*[[List of aircraft accidents at Eglin Air Force Base]]
*[[List of C-130 Hercules crashes]]

==References==
{{reflist|2}}

==External links==
* [http://www.aviationweek.com/aw/defense/?channel=defense AVIATION WEEK]
* [http://www.planecrashinfo.com/ PlaneCrashInfo.com]

{{Lists of aviation accidents and incidents}}
{{Aviation lists}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Accidents And Incidents Involving Military Aircraft (2000–Present)}}
[[Category:Aviation accidents and incidents by year|2000 military]]
[[Category:Lists of aviation accidents and incidents|Military 2000]]

[[es:Anexo:Accidentes e incidentes notables en la aviación militar]]
[[ja:航空事故の一覧 (2000年以降)]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
