<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="1899972" ns="0" title="Nuclear sharing"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">[[Image:nwfz.svg|thumb|500px|
{{legend0|#0000FF|[[Nuclear-Weapon-Free Zone]]s}}
{{legend0|#FF0000|[[Nuclear weapons states]]}}
{{legend0|#FF8800|Nuclear sharing}}
{{legend0|#dddd00|Neither, but [[Nuclear Non-Proliferation Treaty|NPT]]}}
]]
'''Nuclear sharing''' is a concept in [[NATO]]'s policy of nuclear [[Deterrence theory|deterrence]], which involves member countries without [[nuclear weapon]]s of their own in the planning for the use of nuclear weapons by NATO, and in particular provides for the [[armed forces]] of these countries to be involved in  delivering these weapons in the event of their use.

As part of nuclear sharing, the participating countries carry out consultations and take common decisions on nuclear weapons policy, maintain technical equipment required for the use of nuclear weapons (including warplanes capable of delivering them), and store nuclear weapons on their territory.

Of the three nuclear powers in NATO ([[France]], the [[United Kingdom]] and the [[United States]]), only the United States has provided weapons for nuclear sharing. {{As of|2009|11}}, [[Belgium]], [[Germany and weapons of mass destruction|Germany]], [[Italy]], the [[Netherlands and weapons of mass destruction|Netherlands]] and [[Turkey]] are still hosting U.S. nuclear weapons as part of NATO's nuclear sharing policy.&lt;ref name=RUSI-2010&gt;{{Citation|url=http://www.rusi.org/publications/occasionalpapers/ref:O4B991ABDC4148/|title=NATO’s Tactical Nuclear Dilemma|author=Malcolm Chalmers and Simon Lunn|date=March 2010|publisher=[[Royal United Services Institute]]|accessdate=2010-03-16|postscript=.}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.spiegel.de/international/germany/0,1518,618550,00.html Der Spiegel: ''Foreign Minister Wants US Nukes out of Germany'' (2009-04-10)]&lt;/ref&gt; [[Canada and weapons of mass destruction|Canada]] hosted weapons until 1984,&lt;ref name=canada-nw&gt;{{citation|url=http://books.google.com/?id=5-R7EJ0r680C|title=Canadian Nuclear Weapons: The Untold Story of Canada's Cold War Arsenal|author=John Clearwater|year=1998|publisher=Dundurn Press Ltd|isbn=1550022997|accessdate=2008-11-10}}&lt;/ref&gt; and [[Greece]] until 2001.&lt;ref name=RUSI-2010 /&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{citation|page=26|url=http://www.nrdc.org/nuclear/euro/euro.pdf|title=U.S. Nuclear Weapons in Europe|author=[[Hans M. Kristensen]]|date=February 2005|publisher=[[Natural Resources Defense Council]]|accessdate=2009-04-02}}&lt;/ref&gt; The [[Nuclear weapons and the United Kingdom|United Kingdom]] also received U.S. tactical nuclear weapons such as [[nuclear artillery]] and [[MGM-52 Lance|Lance missile]]s until 1992, despite the [[UK]] being a nuclear weapons state in its own right; these were mainly deployed in [[Germany]].

In [[Peace|peace time]], the nuclear weapons stored in non-nuclear countries are guarded by [[United States Army|U.S. soldiers]]; the codes required for detonating them are under American control. In case of war, the weapons are to be mounted on the participating countries' warplanes. The weapons are under custody and control of [[United States Air Force|USAF]] Munitions Support Squadrons co-located on NATO main operating bases who work together with the host nation forces.&lt;ref name=RUSI-2010 /&gt;

[[Image:703MUNSS061108.jpg|thumb|right|A U.S. nuclear weapon storage system at [[Volkel Air Base]] to store weapons for delivery by Royal Netherlands Air Force F-16s]]
{{As of|2005}}, 180 tactical [[B61 nuclear bomb]]s of the 480 U.S. nuclear weapons believed to be deployed in [[Europe]] fall under the nuclear sharing arrangement.&lt;ref&gt;{{citation|url=http://www.nrdc.org/nuclear/euro/euro.pdf|title=U.S. Nuclear Weapons in Europe|author=[[Hans M. Kristensen]]|date=February 2005|publisher=Natural Resources Defense Council|accessdate=2009-04-02}}&lt;/ref&gt; The weapons are stored within a vault in [[Hardened Aircraft Shelter]]s, using the [[USAF]] [[WS3 Weapon Storage and Security System]]. The delivery warplanes used are [[F-16]]s and [[Panavia Tornado]]s.

Historically, the shared nuclear weapon delivery systems were not restricted to bombs. Greece used [[Nike-Hercules Missile]]s as well as [[A-7 Corsair II]] attack aircraft. Canada had [[Bomarc]] nuclear-armed anti-aircraft missiles, [[Honest John]] surface-to-surface missiles and the [[AIR-2 Genie]] nuclear-armed air-to-air rocket, as well as tactical nuclear bombs for the [[CF-104]] fighter.&lt;ref name=canada-nw /&gt;

After the [[Soviet Union]] collapsed, the nuclear weapon types shared within NATO were reduced to tactical nuclear bombs deployed by Dual-Capable Aircraft (DCA).&lt;ref name=RUSI-2010 /&gt;

The only German nuclear base is located in [[Büchel]], near the border to Luxembourg. The base has 11 [[Protective Aircraft Shelter]]s (PAS) equipped with WS3 Vaults for storage of nuclear weapons (maximum capacity of 44). There are 20 B61 nuclear bombs stored on the base for delivery by German PA-200 [[Tornado IDS]] bombers of the JaBoG 33 squadron. By 2015 Germany's Tornado IDS aircraft are due to be retired, and it is unclear what nuclear sharing role, if any, Germany will then retain.&lt;ref name=RUSI-2010 /&gt;
__NOTOC__
==Nuclear Non-Proliferation Treaty considerations==
Both the [[Non-Aligned Movement]] and critics inside NATO believe that NATO's nuclear sharing violates Articles I and II of the [[Nuclear Non-Proliferation Treaty]] (NPT), which prohibit the transfer and acceptance, respectively, of direct or indirect control over nuclear weapons.

The US insists that its forces control the weapons, and that no transfer of the nuclear bombs or control over them is intended &quot;unless and until a decision were made to go to war, at which the [[Nuclear Non-Proliferation Treaty|NPT]] treaty would no longer be controlling&quot;, so there is no breach of the NPT.&lt;ref name=Donnelly&gt;{{citation|url=http://www.opanal.org/Articles/cancun/can-Donnelly.htm|title=The Nuclear Weapons Non-Proliferation Articles I, II and VI of the Treaty on the Non-Proliferation of Nuclear Weapons|author=Brian Donnelly, [[Foreign and Commonwealth Office]]|publisher=Agency for the Prohibition of Nuclear Weapons in Latin America and the Caribbean|accessdate=2009-08-07}}&lt;/ref&gt; However, the pilots and other staff of the &quot;non-nuclear&quot; NATO countries practice handling and delivering the US nuclear bombs, and non-US warplanes have been adapted to deliver US nuclear bombs which involved the transfer of some technical nuclear weapons information.  Even if the US argument is considered legally correct, some{{Who|date=May 2009}} argue such peacetime operations appear to contravene both the objective and the spirit of the NPT. Essentially, all preparations for waging nuclear war have already been made by supposedly non-nuclear weapon states.

At the time the NPT was being negotiated, the NATO nuclear sharing agreements were secret. These agreements were disclosed to some of the states, including the [[Soviet Union]], negotiating the treaty along with the NATO arguments for not treating them as proliferation. Most of the states that signed the NPT in 1968 would not have known about these agreements and interpretations at that time.&lt;ref name=BASIC-20090423&gt;{{citation|url=http://www.basicint.org/sites/default/files/gtz13.pdf|url2=http://www.basicint.org/node/320|title=NATO nuclear burden sharing and NPT obligations|date=23 April 2009|author=Laura Spagnuolo|publisher=[[British American Security Information Council]]|accessdate=2009-08-07}} &lt;/ref&gt;

==See also==
*[[1958 US-UK Mutual Defence Agreement]]
*[[United States military deployments]] around the world

==References==
{{Reflist}}

==External links==
*[http://www.nrdc.org/nuclear/euro/euro.pdf U.S. Nuclear Weapons in Europe], Hans M. Kristensen, [[Natural Resources Defense Council]], February 2005
*[http://www.basicint.org/nuclear/NATO/PENNnote-nuclearsharing-1997.htm NATO Nuclear Sharing and the NPT - Questions to be Answered], joint PENN/BASIC-BITS-CESD-ASPR Research Note 97.3, June 1997
*[http://www.basicint.org/pubs/Research/2000nuclearsharing1.htm Questions of Command and Control: NATO, Nuclear Sharing and the NPT], PENN Research Report 2000.1, Martin Butcher et al., 2000
*[http://www.ieer.org/sdafiles/vol_9/9-3/nato.html Nuclear Sharing in NATO: Is it Legal?], Otfried Nassauer, [[Institute for Energy and Environmental Research]], May 2001
*[http://www.nyu.edu/globalbeat/nuclear/PENN0300.html Questions of Command and Control: NATO, Nuclear Sharing and the NPT], [[Project on European Nuclear Non-Proliferation]], March 2000
*[http://web.archive.org/web/20040518210119/http://www.ased.org/artman/publish/article_64.shtml NATO Nuclear Power Sharing and the NPT], Denise Groves, [[Berlin Information-center for Transatlantic Security]], 6 August 2000
*[http://www.nato.int/issues/nuclear/position.htm NATO's Positions Regarding Nuclear Non-Proliferation, Arms Control and Disarmament and Related Issues], [[NATO]], June 2005
*[http://www.globalsecurity.org/wmd/agency/usafe-munss.htm United States Air Forces in Europe - Munitions Support Squadron], [[GlobalSecurity.org]]
*[http://www.un.org/events/npt2005/statements/npt02malaysia.pdf Statement on behalf of the non-aligned state parties to the Treaty on the Non-Proliferation of Nuclear Weapons], 2 May 2005
*[http://www.basicint.org/pubs/Notes/1998criticismnato.htm Opposition to Nuclear Sharing Leads to Proposed Senate Amendment on NATO Expansion], [[British American Security Information Council]], May 1998
*[http://www.acronym.org.uk/uk/nato.htm NPT à la Carte? NATO and Nuclear Non-Proliferation], Nicola Butler, [[Acronym Institute]], 2005
*[http://books.google.co.uk/books?id=2pEQpx8CB7oC A Constructed Peace: The Making of the European Settlement, 1945-1963] (Chapter 5: Eisenhower and Nuclear Sharing), Marc Trachtenberg, 1999, Princeton University Press, ISBN 0691002738
*[http://www.rand.org/pubs/monograph_reports/MR190/ Commitment to purpose : how alliance partnership won the cold war], Richard L. Kugler, [[RAND]], MC-190-RC/FF, 1993, ISBN 0-8330-1385-8

{{Use dmy dates|date=September 2010}}
{{DEFAULTSORT:Nuclear Sharing}}

[[Category:Nuclear weapons policy]]
[[Category:NATO]]

[[ar:خطة المشاركة النووية]]
[[de:Nukleare Teilhabe]]
[[es:Compartición nuclear]]
[[it:Condivisione nucleare]]
[[ja:ニュークリア・シェアリング]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
