<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><redirects><r from="Compositing effects" to="Compositing window manager" /></redirects><pages><page pageid="4029009" ns="0" title="Compositing window manager"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">[[File:Cube Effect - Compiz.png|thumb|[[Compiz]] showing the desktop cube effect in [[Ubuntu (operating system)|Ubuntu]].]]

A '''compositing window manager''' is a type of [[window manager]]. A window manager is software that draws a [[graphical user interface]] on a [[computer display]] – it positions windows, draws additional elements on windows (such as [[border]]s and [[title bar]]s), and controls how windows interact with each other, and with the rest of the [[desktop environment]]. Within the [[Microsoft Windows]] environment, for example, earlier (pre-Windows 2000){{when|date=March 2011}} window managers made each individual program responsible for [[Rendering (computer graphics)|rendering]] its own window directly to display memory. A compositing window manager, however, combines the [[data buffer|buffers]] of each window into a unified [[framebuffer]] representing the entire screen.&lt;ref name=&quot;microsoft1&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url= http://msdn2.microsoft.com/en-us/library/aa969540(VS.85).aspx |title= Desktop Window Manager |publisher= Msdn2.microsoft.com |date= |accessdate= 2008-11-21 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;arstechnica1&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url= http://arstechnica.com/reviews/os/macosx-10-4.ars/13 |title= Mac OS X 10.4 Tiger: Page 13 |publisher=  Arstechnica.com |date= |accessdate=2008-11-21 }}
&lt;/ref&gt;

Compositing window managers may perform additional processing on buffered windows, applying [[2D computer graphics|2D]] and [[3D computer graphics|3D]] animated effects such as [[alpha compositing]], [[Dissolve (filmmaking)|fading]], [[Image scaling|scaling]], [[Rotation (mathematics)|rotation]], [[Multi-monitor#Clone mode|duplication]], bending and contortion, shuffling, [[Gaussian blur|blurring]], redirecting applications, and [[Translation (geometry)|translating]] windows into one of a number of [[Display device|displays]] and [[virtual desktop]]s. Computer graphics technology allows for visual effects to be rendered in real time such as [[drop shadow]]s, live previews, and complex animation.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url= http://compiz.org/ |title= Compiz.org :: Home/Start – Compiz |publisher= Compiz.org |date= |accessdate= 2008-11-21 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url= https://blueprints.launchpad.net/ubuntu/+spec/composite-by-default |title= Blueprint: “Compositing window management (compiz/beryl)” |publisher= Blueprints.launchpad.net |date= |accessdate= 2008-11-21 }}&lt;/ref&gt;
Since, technically, the screen is [[Double buffering|double buffered]], it does not [[Flicker (screen)|flicker]] during updates.

The most commonly used compositing window managers include:
* [[Microsoft Windows]]—the [[Desktop Window Manager]]
* [[Mac OS X]]—the [[Quartz Compositor]]
* [[GNU/Linux]], [[FreeBSD]] and [[OpenSolaris]]—[[Compiz]], [[KWin]], and [[Mutter (window manager)|Mutter]].

== Comparison with stacking window managers ==
The [[window manager]] sends each window a [[Message passing|message]] to repaint itself whenever appropriate (such as when it is resized, or when another window passes in front of it). With a stacking manager, the repainting process can become corrupted when a program that is slow, unresponsive or [[Software bug|buggy]] does not respond to messages in a timely manner.&lt;ref name=&quot;internet-explorer-redraw&quot;&gt;{{cite web | url=http://support.microsoft.com/kb/246113 | title=Multiple Internet Explorer Instances Do Not Redraw Screen Correctly | date=2003-10-09 | publisher=Microsoft | accessdate=2010-12-17}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;epson-drivers&quot;&gt;{{cite web | url=http://www.neuratron.com/faq.htm#Why_do_PhotoScore_for_Mac_windows_not_redraw_properly_after_scanning_with_Epson_scanners_ | title=PHOTOSCORE SUPPORT FAQ | accessdate=2010-12-17}}&lt;/ref&gt; A malicious program can  cause the system to become unstable by simply neglecting to repaint its window. One or more of the following conditions may result:

* a [[Clipping (computer graphics)|clipped]] window does not repaint uncovered regions, resulting in either blank spaces or a &quot;trail&quot; left behind from another window
* portions of windows (such as decorative drop shadows) are left behind and not properly painted over
* the mouse pointer is corrupted&lt;ref name=&quot;mouse-pointer-corruption&quot;&gt;{{cite web | url=http://ubuntuforums.org/archive/index.php/t-227902.html | date=2006-08-02 | title=Mouser cursor corruption on xinerama | publisher=Canonical Ltd. | accessdate=2010-12-17}}&lt;/ref&gt;{{Verify credibility|failed=y|date=March 2011}}
* screen updates become unbearably slow&lt;ref name=&quot;nvidia-slowdown&quot;&gt;{{cite web | url=http://www.tomshardware.co.uk/forum/140227-35-screen-redraw-slow-nvidia-nforce-system-device-driver | title=Archived from groups: microsoft.public.windowsxp.video | date=2004-07-18 | publisher=Bestofmedia Group | accessdate=2010-12-17}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* the entire screen freezes until the program either responds or is terminated&lt;ref name=&quot;swing-freeze&quot;&gt;{{cite web | url=http://forums.java.net/node/655980 | title=Mustang: Swing apps freeze then painting corrupt | date=2006-05-01 | publisher=Oracle | accessdate=2010-12-17 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

With a compositing manager, if a window stops repainting itself when requested by the window manager, its last repaint will remain displayed and the window might be dimmed. Often the title changes to reflect the status of the window as unresponsive. A program may prevent its window from being moved or unmapped, but generally will not cause repainting problems. Newer operating systems with stringent hardware requirements, such as [[Windows 7]], are less tolerant of bugs arising from faulty [[performance tuning]], and will terminate buggy programs as a preventive measure.

== History ==
One of the first systems with a compositing windowing system was the Commodore [[Amiga]]. Applications could first request a region of memory outside the current display region for use as bitmap. The Amiga windowing system would then use a series of  [[bit blit]]s using the system's hardware [[blitter]] to build a composite of these applications' bitmaps, along with buttons and sliders, in display memory, without requiring these applications to redraw any of their bitmaps.
[[File:Gnome-2.20-screenshot.png|thumb|[[Metacity]] window manager, part of [[GNOME]].]]
Windows 2000 was the first version of Windows with native support for [[alpha blending]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.codeguru.com/cpp/frameworks/advancedui/windowingtechniquesandclasses/article.php/c3213/ |title=Alpha Blending (Transparent) Windows |publisher=CodeGuru}}&lt;/ref&gt; Microsoft mentioned plans to develop a 3D-accelerated window manager in a project code-named &quot;Windows 2010&quot; before the release of Windows XP. The &quot;glass&quot; and blur effects in Windows Aero were introduced well into the Longhorn development cycle.

On March 24, 2001, [[Mac OS X v10.0]] became the first mainstream operating system to feature software-based 3D compositing and effects, provided by its [[Quartz (graphics layer)|Quartz]] component. With the release of [[Mac OS X v10.2]] and [[Quartz Extreme]], the job of compositing could be moved to dedicated graphics hardware.&lt;ref name=&quot;arstechnica1&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.kernelthread.com/mac/osx/history.html |title=A Brief History of Mac OS X |publisher=Kernelthread.com |date= |accessdate=2008-11-21}}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Sun Microsystems]] developed an ambitious 3D graphics system to layer on top of its [[Swing (Java)|Swing]] toolkit, which was called Project Looking Glass. It was first demonstrated at the 2003 [[OpenSource World|LinuxWorld Expo]]. Although Apple threatened to sue Sun for breach of [[intellectual property]] rights, some of the functionality in Looking Glass has been implemented in other window managers. A few years into its development, it was discontinued by Sun, whose primary business was selling [[Enterprise software|enterprise]] mainframes.

The Desktop Window Manager in [[Windows Vista|Project Longhorn]] was first presented to the 2003 [[Windows Hardware Engineering Conference]] demonstrating wobbly windows.&lt;ref name=&quot;extremetech&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.extremetech.com/article2/0,1697,1154262,00.asp |title=Microsoft's Longhorn 3D UI– More Info Emerges |publisher=ExtremeTech}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Development of Windows Vista|Severe delays in the development of Longhorn]] caused [[Microsoft]] not to debut its 3D compositing window manager until the release of [[Windows Vista]] in January 2007.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.computerhope.com/history/windows.htm |title=Microsoft Windows History |publisher=Computerhope.com |date= |accessdate=2008-11-21}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Compositing under the [[X Window System]] required some redesign, which took place incrementally.&lt;ref name=&quot;keithp1&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://keithp.com/~keithp/talks/xarch_ols2004/xarch-ols2004-html/ |title=The (Re)Architecture of the X Window System |publisher=Keithp.com |date= |accessdate=2008-11-21}}&lt;/ref&gt; Metacity 2.8.4 was released in August 2004.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://pkgsrc.se/wm/metacity/commit |title=pkgsrc.se &amp;#124; The NetBSD package collection |publisher=Pkgsrc.se |date= |accessdate=2008-11-21}}&lt;/ref&gt; However, the first widely publicized compositing window manager for [[X-Windows|X]] was [[Xfwm]], released in January 2005.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://foo-projects.org/pipermail/xfce/2005-January/012311.html |title=Xfce 4.2.0 released! |publisher=foo-projects.org |date=2005-01-16 |accessdate=2009-02-25}}&lt;/ref&gt; On 2005-01-26, Compiz was released, introducing fully accelerated 3D compositing to the Linux platform.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://hideseek.sourceforge.net/history.html |title=Version History – Preferences Hide and Seek |publisher=Hideseek.sourceforge.net |date= |accessdate=2008-11-21}}&lt;/ref&gt; KDE's KWin also supports compositing.

== 2D compositing ==

The [[Window (computing)|window]] was originally designed as a 2D [[Planar (computer graphics)|planar]] element, which presents challenges when designing a manager to handle three dimensions, or when attempting to create 3D-style visual effects. Metacity, for example, draws windows one at a time, so that hidden components are actively rendered. Even with similar capabilities as their 3D counterparts, the output from 2D compositing window managers has no depth, meaning that windows still exist in a plane. Quasi-3D effects, such as the [[dimple]]d buttons on [[Mac OS Classic]] or the [[bevel]]s and shading on [[Windows 2000]], are usually less realistic than true z-axis rendering techniques such as [[diffuse reflection]].

== 3D compositing ==
Modern compositing window managers, including Desktop Window Manager, Quartz Compositor and Compiz use 3D acceleration. Most communicate with graphics hardware via [[Application programming interface|programming interfaces]] such as [[OpenGL]] or [[Direct3D]].

The earliest widespread implementations using this technique were released for the Mac in Mac OS X 10.2, and for Linux in a [[Luminocity]] prototype. Currently, window managers using OpenGL include Compiz, KWin, and the Quartz Compositor, while Desktop Window Manager currently uses DirectX 9. OpenGL is still not fully supported in hardware, so performance of OpenGL-based compositing should continue to improve as hardware improves.

=== Microsoft Windows ===
While the window manager in Windows 2000 does perform compositing, it does not perform transformations such as a per-pixel alpha. Few commercial applications took advantage of alpha blending; [[freeware]] programs were among the first to experiment with it, albeit through optional settings.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.elgorithms.com/downloads/chaoscrystal.php |title=Example alpha transparency utility}}
&lt;/ref&gt;

Windows Vista and Windows 7 allow the user to disable Desktop Window Manager by selecting the Windows Basic appearance settings. In addition, it is automatically disabled by Windows in order to perform [[hardware overlay]] through the [[DirectShow#Video rendering filters|Overlay Mixer Filter]].

=== Linux ===
Stacking window managers running on [[X.Org Server|X server]] required a [[chroma keying]] or [[green screening]] [[X video extension|extension]]. Compositing was introduced by way of the [[composite (graphics)|&quot;Composite&quot; extension]]. Compositing managers use hardware acceleration through this extension, if available.

{{See|AIGLX}}
[[File:Compiz-ShiftSwitcher.png|thumb|[[Ubuntu (operating system)|Ubuntu]] 8.04 Hardy Heron running Compiz's Shift Switcher in Flip mode.]]
Under Linux and UNIX, the ability to do full 3D-accelerated compositing required fundamental changes to [[X11]] in order to use hardware acceleration. Originally, a number of modified X11 implementations designed around [[OpenGL]] began to appear, including [[Xgl]]. The introduction of [[AIGLX]] would eliminate the need to use Xgl, and allow window managers to do 3D accelerated compositing on a standard X server, while still allowing for [[Direct Rendering Infrastructure|direct rendering]]. Currently [[NVIDIA]], [[Intel]] and [[ATI]] cards support AIGLX.

Compiz introduced a cube effect, which allows the user to see up to 6 virtual desktops at once. Each desktop is converted into a surface texture of the cube, which can be rotated at will. Compiz displays a wide array of 2D and 3D effects and has relatively low hardware requirements.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://forum.compiz-fusion.org/viewtopic.php?t=6623|title=Installing/running Compiz on GeForce2 MX/MX 400}}&lt;/ref&gt; Compiz is included in [[Ubuntu (operating system)|Ubuntu]] Linux, and is enabled automatically when supported hardware and drivers are available.

[[Mutter (window manager)|Mutter]] (Metacity + [[Clutter (toolkit)|Clutter]]) has replaced Metacity as the default window manager for [[Gnome]]. It will be featured in the [[GNOME Shell]] component of Gnome 3.0. It uses the display engine Clutter, which has been ported to all major operating systems, [[netbooks]] and [[smartphones]].

Since version 4, KDE's window manager [[KWin]] has compositing capabilities. KWin features much of the same functionality also present in Compiz.

=== Java ===
{{Main|Project Looking Glass}}
Project Looking Glass was a window manager combining 3D rendering and the cross-platform [[Java (programming language)|Java]] programming language. It is now inactive and released under the [[GNU Public License]]. The [[Granular Linux]] [[live CD|live CD distribution]] includes Looking Glass as an optional window manager.

In the aftermath of it being discontinued, some of its features, such as cover switching and thumbnail live previews, have found their way onto other window managers. Its more unique features included window tilting, two-sided window frames and [[parallax scroll]]ing backgrounds.

=== AmigaOS 4 and MorphOS ===
[[File:AmigaOS4.1b.png|thumb|none|Alpha blending in Amiga OS 4.1]]
While they are able to run on 3D-capable hardware, AmigaOS and MorphOS are designed to run on old [[Legacy system|legacy]] Amiga computers, starting with the [[Amiga 1200]]. As such, their window managers have mostly planar rendering capabilities that include composite layering, alpha blending, gradients, high resolution and multiple desktops (&quot;screens&quot;) that can partially clip one another.

== Usability and eye candy ==
The compositing approach makes it easier to implement a number of features that make the user interface more accessible, simpler to use or with [[eye candy]] elements.

=== Magnifiers ===
[[File:Magnifier - Compiz.png|thumb|none|The magnification effect in Compiz (click image to view in scale).]]

[[Vector graphics]], such as [[True type|true-type]] fonts and 3D-accelerated elements, can be expanded without degradation (usually due to [[aliasing]]). A [[screen magnifier]] enlarges an area of the screen, making portions of text easier to read – whether to prevent [[eye strain]], for the [[visually impaired]], or simply at a distance. [[Zoom]] effects such as the [[fish eye]] magnifier and zoom desktop effects provide this functionality.

=== Live preview ===
&lt;!-- Deleted image removed: [[File:Live Preview - Compiz.png|thumb|none|Live preview in Compiz.]] --&gt;
A preview of a window can be displayed in a pop-up [[thumbnail]] when the user [[hover]]s its associated [[taskbar]] button. This allows the user to identify and manage several concurrently running programs.

=== Window switching ===
[[File:Xgl window switching.png|thumb|none|Basic window switching in Xgl.]]
Windows with similar names and icons tend to cause confusion, especially when their title bars overlap; the position of every such window on the taskbar has to be memorized. When there are many open windows in this manner, the user often has to resort to trial and error—clicking each taskbar button one-by-one—before proceeding. Window switching allows one to quickly preview several windows at once by temporary rearranging them against a decorative background. After a selection is made, the windows are then restored to their original arrangement.

Selection begins when the user either enters a [[Keyboard shortcut|hotkey combination]], moves the mouse pointer to a [[Screen hotspot|hotspot on the screen]], or, in some situations, uses the mouse's [[scroll wheel]]. Items are navigated using the keyboard or mouse. An item is selected by either releasing the hotkey, hitting the Enter key or clicking on it with the mouse.

==== Flip switching ====
[[File:Compiz-fusion-switcher-flip.jpg|thumb|none|Flip switching in Compiz.]]
The flip switcher is an enhancement to the [[Alt-Tab]] switching feature. Running windows are arranged into a stack – similar to a flip-style selector in a 1950s [[jukebox]], or a [[Rolodex]]. In some systems, the user can press Alt-Shift-Tab to navigate backwards. Visual transitions are applied to each item while navigating.

Common implementations of flip switching include [[Flip 3D]] in Windows and [[Shift Switcher]] in Compiz.

==== Cover switching ====
{{multiple image
| align     = center
| width1     = 220
| footer    = Examples of cover switching
| image1    = Kwin Cover Switch.png
| alt1      = Screenshot showing Cover Switch in KWin.
| caption1  = Cover Switch in KWin.
| width2     = 281
| image2    =
| alt2      = Screenshot of showing Cover Flow in iTunes.
| caption2  = [[Cover Flow]] in iTunes,
}}
Cover switching is like flip switching with a few, mostly visual, differences. Instead of one stack with the selection at the top, two symmetrical stacks are shown with the current selection front and center (similar to the window tilting feature in Looking Glass).

[[Cover Flow]] is an implementation of cover switching in Mac OS X. More recent versions use blurring to de-emphasize non-selected items. Cover Flow has also been implemented in other software published by [[Apple, Inc.|Apple]] such as [[iTunes]].

This is also referred to as &quot;flick-book view.&quot;

==== Ring switching ====
[[File:Cf-ring-switcher.png|thumb|none|Ring switching in Compiz Fusion.]]
Ring switching is like flip switching, except the windows move in a circle, with the current selection in front, usually at the bottom. Most compositing window managers include this feature [[out of the box]], and [[Third-party software component|third-party applications]], such as [http://desk3d.sourceforge.net/ 3d-desktop], are also available.

==== Grouping ====
The user can group windows together, such that only one window at a time is visible in each group. In Compiz, the window frame is flipped to indicate when the active window in its group has been changed.

==== Exposé ====
{{Main|Exposé (Mac OS X)}}
Mac OS X displays a preview of every window on the screen by tiling them. Other systems with similar functionality (Microsoft Windows, Compiz, KWin, third-party applications) are referred to as [[Exposé clone]]s. The hotkey to activate Exposé is not Alt-Tab, but rather F3.

==== Mission Control ====
[[Mac OS X 10.7]] combines several other compositing features developed by Apple—such as Exposé, [[Dashboard (Mac OS)|Dashboard]], and [[Spaces (software)|Spaces]]—into a larger program called [[Mission Control (Mac OS X)|Mission Control]].

=== Widget engines ===
{{Main|Software widget}}
On Mac OS, &quot;widgets&quot; (single-purpose [[applet]]s) such as a clock, note pad, and calculator can appear by pressing a [[hotkey]]. Widget engines speed work by keeping commonly used widgets accessible while unobtrusive. They are handled by the Dashboard program in Mac OS.

Compiz starts with a blank Widget Layer, allowing the user to add applications by clicking on them. A variety of widgets are supported, including [[Screenlets]], [[gDesklets]] and [[SuperKaramba]].&lt;ref name=&quot;compiz-widget&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url=http://wiki.compiz.org/Plugins/Widget |title=Plugins/Widget - Compiz Wiki |publisher=Compiz |accessdate=2010-12-26 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

Windows Vista provides [[Microsoft Gadgets|gadgets]] that the user can place on the [[Windows Sidebar]] (Sidebar gadgets), a [[Windows Live]] [[start page]] (Web gadgets), or an external display, such as the user's mobile phone ([[Windows SideShow|SideShow gadgets]]). The Windows Sidebar was a visible partition in Windows Vista, and was eliminated in Windows 7, along with Sidebar gadgets which were changed to [[Windows Desktop Gadgets|Desktop Gadgets]].

=== Transitions and other effects ===
Before compositing window managers were developed, windows would instantly jump in and out of view, which is incongruent with the interface metaphor (and with a physical [[office]] setting). The sudden appearance and disappearance of [[GUI]] elements may seem confusing or even chaotic to inexperienced users.{{Citation needed|date=February 2009}} Visual transitions provide context and help distinguish the causal relationships of GUI elements. Instead of just disappearing, a window may fade away, or visibly shrink to the taskbar. A pull-down menu that has been clicked may smoothly radiate outward from the menu bar, making it easier to determine its origin and purpose.

Gradual and natural transitions may be{{Or|date=November 2009}} especially helpful for elderly or visually impaired users who notice changes to the screen more slowly and with less clarity. For example, an inexperienced user may impulsively click on a menu that was activated by accident, causing him or her to lose work. The short delay necessary to display a visual transition may give the user enough time to make a conscious decision, and avoid such mistakes.

=== User Interface Façades ===
[[Metisse]] implements user interface façades, a system that provides users with simple ways to adapt, reconfigure, and re-combine existing [[Direct manipulation interface|graphical interfaces]], through the use of [[Direct manipulation interface|direct manipulation techniques]].&lt;ref name=&quot;metisse-facades&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url=http://insitu.lri.fr/metisse/facades/|title=Metisse: User Interface Façades |publisher=Metisse |accessdate=2011-08-03 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

== List of compositing window managers ==
* [http://web.archive.org/web/20040206010042/www.3dwm.org/html/about_introduction.php 3Dwm], a three-dimensional workspace manager&lt;ref&gt;{{Citation | title = 3Dwm - About | date = 2004-01-23 | url = http://www.3dwm.org/html/about_introduction.php | accessdate = 2010-02-04 | archiveurl = http://web.archive.org/web/20040206010042/http://www.3dwm.org/html/about_introduction.php | archivedate = 2004-02-06}}&lt;/ref&gt; and general-purpose platform for 3D user interfaces.&lt;ref&gt;{{Citation | title = 3Dwm - About - FAQ - About the Project | date = 2003-12-03 | url = http://www.3dwm.org/faq/index.php#category-About%20the%20Project | accessdate = 2010-02-04 | archiveurl = http://web.archive.org/web/20040224050932/http://www.3dwm.org/faq/index.php#category-About%20the%20Project | archivedate = 2004-02-24}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Citation | title = 3D window manager | url = http://w3.msi.vxu.se/~cha/VR_forskning/3dwm.html | accessdate = 2010-12-16}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Citation | last = Yeargin | first = Ray | title = 3DWM: A screenshot look at the 3D desktop | date = 2005-03-31  | url = http://librenix.com/?inode=1237 | accessdate = 2010-12-16}}&lt;/ref&gt; As of June 2006 this project is inactive.
* Desktop Window Manager and the [[Windows Aero]] theme on Windows
* Quartz Compositor on Mac OS X
* [[Compiz]]
* [[KWin]] (since version 3.3)
* [[Mutter (window manager)|Mutter]]
* [[Xfce]]'s Xfwm (since version 4.2)
* [http://www.freedesktop.org/wiki/Software/xapps xcompmgr]—a minimal alternative to Compiz
* [http://github.com/jeffdameth/ecomorph Ecomorph]—a combination of [http://github.com/jeffdameth/ecomp ecomp] (a hack of Compiz made to work with [[Enlightenment (window manager)|Enlightenment]]) and the ecomorph module for Enlightenment.
* [http://cairo-compmgr.tuxfamily.org/ Cairo Compmgr] (Cairo Composite Manager)—a compositing add-on for existing window managers. It uses [[Cairo (graphics)|Cairo]], a vector graphics library also used in [[GTK+]].
* MCompositor—used on MeeGo handsets.
* [[Metisse|Metisee window system]]

== Operating systems with compositing window managers ==
* Windows Vista, Windows 7, [[Windows Server 2008]] (installable as an optional component)
* Mac OS X 10.0 and later
* GNU/Linux (with [[X.Org Server|XOrg]]/[[AIGLX]] or [[Xgl]])
* FreeBSD
* OpenSolaris
* AmigaOS 4
* [[MorphOS]] 2.0 and later

== See also ==
* [[Window manager]]
* [[Tiling window manager]]
* [[Stacking window manager]]
* [[Re-parenting window manager]]
* [[Zooming user interface]]
* [[Computer graphics]]

== References ==
{{Reflist}}

== External links ==
* {{YouTube|E4Fbk52Mk1w|Various effects in Compiz}}
* {{YouTube|xC5uEe5OzNQ|Comparison between Windows Aero and Compiz}}
* {{YouTube|12-RqR1Vuo0|Mac OS X and the Quartz Compositor}}
* {{YouTube|IApYWE5W28k|Drop shadows and transparency in xcompmgr}}
* {{YouTube|rvYSZ6zPoac|Desktop switching using 3d-desktop}}
* {{YouTube|U9R5kEy_nJ4|Desktop switching using the cube effect}}
* {{YouTube|ISEvGmTQySo|Official demonstration video for Project Looking Glass}}
* {{YouTube|zcPIEMvyPy4|Background and windowing effects in Looking Glass}}

{{Window managers}}
{{XWinSys}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Compositing Window Manager}}
[[Category:Compositing window managers| ]]
[[Category:Graphical user interfaces]]
[[Category:X window managers|*]]

[[de:Composition-Manager]]
[[es:Gestor de composición de ventanas]]
[[it:Compositing window manager]]
[[pl:Menedżer kompozycji]]
[[sv:Kompositionshanterare]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
