<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="190465" ns="0" title="Gonzaga University"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Infobox university|
  name           = Gonzaga University |
  logo           = [[File:Gonzaga University Logo.svg|160px]] |
  motto          = ''[[Ad Majorem Dei Gloriam]]''&lt;br&gt;(''For the greater glory of God'')|
  established    = 1887 |
  type           = [[Private school|Private]] |
  affiliation    = [[Roman Catholic Church|Roman Catholic]] ([[Jesuit]])|
  president      = Dr. [[Thayne McCulloh]] |
  city           = [[Spokane, Washington|Spokane]] |
  state          = [[Washington (U.S. state)|Washington]] |
  country        = United States |
  undergrad      = 4,729 |
  postgrad       = 2,908 |
  postgrad_label = graduate |
  faculty        = 364  |
  free_label     = Tuition and fees|
  free           = $27,820
  campus         = Urban, 108 acres (437,000 m²)|
  free_label     = Conference |
  free           = [[West Coast Conference]] |
  mascot         = Spike the Bulldog |
  colors         = Blue and White {{color box|blue}}{{color box|#FFFFFF}}|
  nickname       = [[Gonzaga Bulldogs|Bulldogs, Zags]]|
  website       = [http://www.gonzaga.edu/ www.gonzaga.edu] |
  image          = [[File:Gonzaga U Seal.png|180px]]
}}
'''Gonzaga University''' is a private Roman Catholic university located in [[Spokane, Washington]], United States. Founded in 1887 by the [[Society of Jesus]], it is one of 28 member institutions of the [[Association of Jesuit Colleges and Universities]] and is named after the young Jesuit saint, [[Aloysius Gonzaga]]. The campus houses 105 buildings across 131 acres (437,000&amp;nbsp;m²) of [[grassland]] along the [[Spokane River]], in a residential setting half a mile (800 m) from downtown Spokane. The university was founded by [[Joseph Cataldo|Father Joseph Cataldo, SJ]], an Italian-born priest and missionary who wished to create a Catholic school in the [[Pacific Northwest]] for local [[Native Americans in the United States|Native Americans]].&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web| title = History of Gonzaga University| publisher = Gonzaga University | url = http://www.gonzaga.edu/About/Mission/Mission-Statement/History.asp| accessdate = 2009-01-30}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Curriculum==
[[Image:Gonzaga University Entrance.jpg|thumb|220px|left|The main entrance to College Hall]]
Gonzaga's liberal arts tradition lies in its core curriculum, which integrates philosophy, religious studies, mathematics, literature, natural and social sciences, and extensive writing in each major discipline. Gonzaga offers studies in 92 fields and 26 graduate programs. In addition, Gonzaga offers programs in preparation for professional schools in business, education, engineering, dentistry, divinity/theology, law, medicine, nursing and veterinary medicine. Gonzaga also sponsors an [[United States Army|Army]] [[Reserve Officers' Training Corps|ROTC]] program which prepares students to become commissioned [[Officer (armed forces)|officers]] upon graduation. Additionally, Gonzaga University partners with [[Bishop White Seminary]], located next to the campus, to prepare Catholic [[Seminarians]] for the priesthood.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web| last = Skylstad| first = William S.| title = The Bishop 333Writes| publisher = The Catholic Diocese of Spokane| date = 2004-01-15| url = http://www.dioceseofspokane.org/BW_2004/bw011504.htm| accessdate = 2009-01-30}} {{Dead link|date=September 2010|bot=H3llBot}}&lt;/ref&gt; Students may study abroad at Gonzaga's campus in [[Florence, Italy]], or at other programs in [[Australia]], [[Benin]], [[British West Indies]], [[China]], [[Costa Rica]], England, France, [[Japan]], [[Kenya]], [[Mexico]], Spain and [[Zambia]].&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web| title = Study Abroad| publisher = Gonzaga University | url = http://www.gonzaga.edu/Academics/Undergraduate/StudyAbroad/default.asp| accessdate = 2009-01-30}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Law School===
{{Main|Gonzaga University School of Law}}

[[Gonzaga University School of Law]], established in 1912, is one of three law schools in Washington.  According to [[U.S. News &amp; World Report]], GU Law currently ranks in the top 100 law schools in the U.S.[http://grad-schools.usnews.rankingsandreviews.com/best-graduate-schools/top-law-schools/items/03165]  The law school has produced prominent alumni, including three of the nine current [[Washington Supreme Court]] justices, both [[U.S. Attorney]]s for Washington's two [[United States district court|federal district courts]], and the [[Governor of Washington]] [[Christine Gregoire]] (all as of 2009).

===Visiting Writers Series===
Gonzaga University’s Annual Reading Series is sponsored by the Department of English, the College of Arts and Sciences, the Academic Vice President, the Office of Intercultural Relations, the Gonzaga Student Body Association, the Faculty Speakers Committee and through a grant from Humanities Washington.
In past years, writers and artists who have visited campus for the Reading Series have included Denis Johnson, Sharon Olds, Sherman Alexie, Beth Cooley,  Tod Marshall, Uwen Akpan, [[Alexandra Fuller]], Joy Harjo, Dan Butterworth and [[Robert Hass]].
This year (2010–2011), Gonzaga University is pleased to welcome Sam Green &lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web| title = Fantasticfiction| publisher = Fantisticfiction | url = http://www.fantasticfiction.co.uk/g/sam-green/| accessdate = 2010-09-08}}&lt;/ref&gt;(October 6), [[Jimmy Santiago Baca]] (October 26), [[Naomi Shihab Nye]] (November 16), [[Rick Moody]] (March 2), and Keya Mitra &lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web| title = Writers in the Schools| publisher = WITS | url = http://www.witshouston.org/wits-writers| accessdate = 2010-09-08}}&lt;/ref&gt;(date TBA). All events begin at 7:30 in the Cataldo Globe Room on Gonzaga's campus and are free and open to the public.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web| title = Reading Series| publisher = Gonzaga University | url = http://www.gonzaga.edu/Academics/Colleges-and-Schools/College-of-Arts-and-Sciences/English/readingseries/default.asp| accessdate = 2010-09-08}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Timothy J. O'Leary, S.J. Lecture Series===
The Timothy O'Leary, S.J. Lecture Series is an annual event sponsored by Gonzaga University science department which endeavors to bring prestigious scientific speakers to the university. This event was named after father Timothy O’Leary, S.J. a former student and professor of chemistry at Gonzaga. This event has run continuously since 1992 and includes two presentations – one for the general public and one for science majors the following day.

===Libraries On Campus===
[[Foley Center Library]] is the main graduate and undergraduate library for Gonzaga University.
Chastek Law Library primarily serves Gonzaga University School of Law.

===Center for Global Engagement===
The center for Global engagement is a new program at Gonzaga. Since the university has an extensive international presence it provides many programs in which the students can get involved with the international community. Some aspects of the Center for Global Engagement are MA/TESL, The Peace Corps, and the study abroad programs.

'''English as a Second Language'''
In the ESL program, students are required to take a placement test that determines the difficulty of the class that they will be enrolled in. Classes are required to meet five days a week and they teach reading, writing, vocabulary, speaking and English development. The ESL Program at Gonzaga seeks to provide international students with the resources and opportunities to get a first rate education, as well as graduate from Gonzaga with a competency in the English language.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web| title = Gonzaga University English Language Center| publisher = Gonzaga University | url = http://www.gonzaga.edu/Academics/Libraries/Foley-Library/Departments/Instruction/PermaLinks/ESL.pdf| accessdate = 2010-09-20}}&lt;/ref&gt;

'''The Peace Corps (PCMI MA/TESL)'''
The Peace Corps program consists of the masters program for graduate students and the MA/TESL and Peace Corps MI. The program is four semesters long including summer, as well as twenty-seven months of Peace Corps service. Applicants must have a competency in a language other than English. Since this is a graduate program, applicants are required to have a baccalaureate degree from an accredited institution with an average cumulative GPA of 3.0. This is a joint program with the Peace Corps in which students get the opportunity to teach English as a Second Language, as well as studies in culture and language.  Students in the Peace Corps will also complete a degree within their time in the Peace Corps.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web| title = Gonzaga University MA/TESL &amp; Peace Corps MI| publisher = Gonzaga University | url = http://www.gonzaga.edu/Academics/Libraries/Foley-Library/Departments/Instruction/PermaLinks/Overview.pdf| accessdate = 2010-09-20}}&lt;/ref&gt;

'''Study Abroad'''
Gonzaga has numerous study abroad locations all over the world including; Australia, Benin, China, Costa Rica, Ecuador, El Salvador, England, France, Ireland, Japan, Mexico, The Netherlands, Scotland, Spain, Taiwan, Turks, Zambia and the Gonzaga campus in Florence, Italy.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web| title = Study Abroad
| publisher = Gonzaga University| url = http://www.gonzaga.edu/academics/undergraduate/studyabroad/default.asp| accessdate = 2010-09-20}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web| title = Center for Global Engagement
| publisher = Gonzaga University| url = http://www.gonzaga.edu/Academics/International-Students/default.asp| accessdate = 2010-09-15}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Statistics==
The 2009–10 operating budget is $206.6 million, with an annual payroll of $71.9 million. Average class size is 23, and there are 364 employed faculty, and 11:1 Student/Faculty ratio. There are 38 Jesuits on campus, 24 employed by the University. There are 648 non-faculty employees. Overall, enrollment in 2009–10 was 7,682 (4,729 undergraduate) students.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web| title = Facts and Figures| publisher = Gonzaga University | url = http://www.gonzaga.edu/About/Facts-and-Figures.asp| accessdate = 2009-01-30}}&lt;/ref&gt; The university ranks third in the [[U.S. News &amp; World Report]] rankings for Universities-Master's in the West.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news| title = Best Colleges| publisher = ''U.S. News &amp; World Report''| date = | url = http://colleges.usnews.rankingsandreviews.com/college/items/3778| accessdate = 2009-01-30}}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Image:LakeArthur.JPG|thumb|180px|right|Lake Arthur in the Fall with the Law School visible in the background]]

==Debate==
For over 100 years Gonzaga University has sponsored a competitive program in [[Inter-Collegiate policy debate|collegiate policy debate]]. Their debate squad typically has 10–14 debaters who compete in policy debate  through the national and regional NDT/CEDA  circuits. Gonzaga’s debate season runs from September to April during which they participate in 12–15&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news| title = ''There’s no debate here: Frappier loves it''| publisher = Gonzaga University SPIRIT| url = http://www.gonzaga.edu/Campus-Resources/Offices-and-Services-A-Z/MarketingandCommunications/pdf/Spirit/2004FebSpirit.pdf| accessdate = 2010-09-07}}&lt;/ref&gt; tournaments a year. Their schedule regularly includes Kentucky, Wake Forest, Harvard, USC, Northwestern, Cal,  CEDA Nationals and the NDT.  The team has four full-time coaches, led by Glen Frappier. Notable alumni of the program include former Speaker of the House Tom Foley and the former President of Gonzaga, Father Robert Spitzer, S.J.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web| title = Gonzaga Debate Program
| publisher = Gonzaga Debate Institute| url = http://www.gonzagadebate.com/index.htm| accessdate = 2010-09-07}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Mock Trial==
Gonzaga University [[Mock Trial]] is a highly competitive political law club.  Mock Trial members are usually undergraduate students, majoring in many different areas of subject, who are looking to experience the American Judicial System.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web| title = Princeton Review| publisher = The Princeton Review| url = http://www.princetonreview.com/GonzagaUniversity.aspx| accessdate = 2010-09-13}}&lt;/ref&gt; Students in this club are given a case and they “mock” a courtroom situation, pretending to be attorneys and witnesses. This club competes with over 600 other universities and institutions nationally and has attended a National Tournament 13 times consecutively. In order to become a member, students must go through a rigorous try-out process where they are chosen to be on different teams. On average, there are 21–24 students who participate in Mock Trial each year.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web| title = Mock Trial Political Law Clubs| publisher = Gonzaga University| url = https://gonzaga-community.symplicity.com/index.php?s=student_group&amp;tab=profile&amp;mode=form&amp;id=5829b3147f78a8b660d302ab47d61a57&amp;au=&amp;ck=| accessdate = 2010-09-13}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Campus Art==
Gonzaga University is host to many unique historical pieces of artwork. For example, a wide range of statues located around campus gives visitors and students alike a taste of the Gonzaga culture. Statues of St. Ignatius, [http://www.gonzaga.edu/Academics/Libraries/Foley-Library/Departments/Instruction/PermaLinks/St_Joseph.jpg St. Joseph], [http://www.gonzaga.edu/Academics/Libraries/Foley-Library/Departments/Instruction/PermaLinks/Bing_Crosby.jpg Bing Crosby] and [http://www.gonzaga.edu/Academics/Libraries/Foley-Library/Departments/Instruction/PermaLinks/St_Aloysius_statue.jpg St. Aloysius] are among the most notable religious landmarks on campus. Some lesser-known statues include [http://www.gonzaga.edu/Academics/Libraries/Foley-Library/Departments/Instruction/PermaLinks/Fr_Dussalt.jpg Father Dussault] and the [http://www.gonzaga.edu/Academics/Libraries/Foley-Library/Departments/Instruction/PermaLinks/Hand.jpg pierced hand of Christ]. With a plethora of statues, Gonzaga truly embraces both artistic and religious values.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web| title = Major Campus Landmarks| publisher = Gonzaga University| url = http://www.gonzaga.edu/Academics/Libraries/Foley-Library/Departments/Instruction/PermaLinks/MapOfLandmarks.pdf| accessdate = 2010-09-09}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Jundt Fall Exhibit===
Gonzaga University offers the invitational exhibit, “Drawn the Wall,” every three years in the Jundt Art Museum, located on the university’s main campus.  This exhibit features five well-known Inland Northwest artists all of whom present an original work on 11 ½-by-8-foot moveable museum wall. Each artist spends two weeks at the museum, during which time they create an original piece of art according to a common theme. For example, artists selected to participate in 2010’s “Drawn to the IV” were asked to find workable solutions to large scale drawings and to the constraints of working in a “common” environment. In a unique fashion, the drawings present in the exhibit are removed and painted over when the exhibit ends, and the walls upon which the drawings once resided are return to their normal use as gallery partitions.  ”Drawn to the Wall IV” features the distinct talents of Michael Horswill,&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web| title = Art Spirit| publisher = Art Spirit Website| url = http://www.theartspiritgallery.com/html/ArtistBio.asp?artnum=13| accessdate = 2010-09-08}}&lt;/ref&gt; Louise Kodis,&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web| title = Spokanearts.org
| publisher = City of Spokane| url = http://www.spokanearts.org/airportart.aspx| accessdate = 2010-09-08}}&lt;/ref&gt; Ken Spiering,&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web| title = Kenneth James Spiering
| publisher = Spokane Falls Community College| url = http://faculty.spokanefalls.edu/art/resu/spear.html| accessdate = 2010-09-08}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web| title = Artist's Statement
| author = Ken Spiering | publisher = Spokane Falls Community College | url = http://faculty.spokanefalls.edu/art/statm/spier_st.html| accessdate = 2010-09-08}}&lt;/ref&gt; Carolyn Stephens, and Gordon Wilson.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web| title = Faculty Whitworth University
| publisher = Whitworth University| url = http://www.whitworth.edu/academic/Department/Art/DepartmentSpotlight/WilsonAward.htm| accessdate = 2010-09-08}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web| title = ‘Drawn to the Wall IV’ Opens at Jundt Art Museum Sept. 7| publisher = Gonzaga News Release| url = http://news.gonzaga.edu/archives/3937| accessdate = 2010-09-08}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web| title = Jundt Galleries| publisher = Gonzaga Website| url = http://www.gonzaga.edu/Campus-Resources/Museums-and-Libraries/Jundt-Art-Museum/Jundt-Galleries.asp| accessdate = 2010-09-08}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Athletics==
{{Main|Gonzaga Bulldogs}}
{{See also|Gonzaga Bulldogs men's basketball}}
[[File:GU Bulldogs Logo.svg|120px|left]]

Gonzaga University, whose official mascot is the Bulldog and whose players are nicknamed the ''Zags,'' is part of the [[National Collegiate Athletic Association|NCAA]] Division I [[West Coast Conference]]. Its [[Gonzaga Bulldogs men's basketball|men's basketball team]], which did not make its first appearance in the [[NCAA Men's Division I Basketball Championship|NCAA tournament]] until [[1995 NCAA Men's Division I Basketball Tournament|1995]] (more than a decade after NBA Hall of Fame player and Gonzaga alum [[John Stockton]] graduated), has become nationally prominent since making the regional finals of the NCAA tournament (&quot;Elite Eight&quot;) in [[1999 NCAA Men's Division I Basketball Tournament|1999]], re-appearing in the tournament every year since.

Gonzaga University [[basketball]] games are held in the [[McCarthey Athletic Center]], in which the men's basketball team has won over 90 percent of its games. The men's team often plays high-profile non-conference games at the [[Spokane Veterans Memorial Arena]] near downtown Spokane, in addition to the annual Comcast Battle in Seattle game held at [[KeyArena]] in Seattle.

Three of Gonzaga's most recent notable athletes are basketball players—former [[center (basketball)|center]] [[Ronny Turiaf]] (now playing for the [[New York Knicks]]); third overall [[2006 NBA Draft]] pick and [[Red Star Belgrade]] [[Adam Morrison]] (who was selected by the [[Charlotte Bobcats]]), regarded for his likeness to Hall of Famer [[Larry Bird]]; and [[Courtney Vandersloot]], 2011 winner of the [[Nancy Lieberman Award]] as the leading Division I women's [[point guard]] and women's [[Frances Pomeroy Naismith Award]] as the top Division I player no taller than 5'8&quot; (1.73 m), selected third overall by the [[Chicago Sky]] in the [[2011 WNBA Draft]]. Men's head coach [[Mark Few]] was the [[West Coast Conference]] coach of the year from [[2001 in sports|2001]] to [[2006 in sports|2006]], and again in [[2008 in sports|2008]]. Few became the [[head coach]] in the summer of [[1999 in sports|1999]], following the departure of [[Dan Monson]] to [[Minnesota Golden Gophers men's basketball|Minnesota]]. Women's head coach [[Kelly Graves]], a six-time WCC coach of the year, has led the Zags to seven consecutive WCC regular-season titles and four WCC tournament titles. The 2010–11 women's team, a #11 seed in [[2011 NCAA Women's Division I Basketball Tournament|that year's NCAA Tournament]], became the lowest seed ever to advance to a regional final in the history of the women's tournament.

Like some other smaller colleges, Gonzaga's [[American football|football]] program ended in the Fall of 1941, just before the U.S. entry into [[World War II]], but not before producing two [[Pro Football Hall of Fame]]rs: [[Tony Canadeo]] '41 of the [[Green Bay Packers]], and [[Ray Flaherty]] '26, head coach of the [[Washington Redskins]]. In addition, Flaherty recruited former Bulldog football stars, [[Ed Justice]], [[George Karamatic|George &quot;Automatic&quot; Karamatic]] and [[Max Krause]] to play in the Redskin backfield. Gonzaga football ended due to declining enrollment of young male athletes{{Citation needed|date=January 2008}}. Efforts to restart the program in 1946 were unsuccessful, and the football stadium was razed in 1949.

Gonzaga University also has an [[Army ROTC]] [[Ranger Challenge]] team, which has won 15 championships in the last 16 years, and is a multiple winner of the Douglas MacArthur Award, given annually to the best Army ROTC program in the Western United States.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web| title = Bulldogs Making Headlines| publisher = Gonzaga University | url = http://www.gonzaga.edu/Academics/Undergraduate/Special-Programs/Military-Science/default1.asp| accessdate = 2009-01-30}}&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web| title = Ranger Challenge| publisher = Gonzaga University | url = http://www.gonzaga.edu/Academics/Undergraduate/Special-Programs/Military-Science/Extracurricular-Activities/| accessdate = 2009-01-30}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Women's Basketball===
{{Merge to|Gonzaga Bulldogs|date=September 2010}}
While men’s basketball at Gonzaga is huge, there are several other varsity athletics programs. The Ladies basketball season of 2010 was incredibly successful.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web| title = ESPN Women's Basketball Schedule| publisher = ESPN | url = http://sports.espn.go.com/ncw/teams/schedule?teamId=2250| accessdate = 2010-09-09}}&lt;/ref&gt; They not only made it to the NCAA tournament but advanced to the sweet sixteen before getting knocked out by Xavier&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web| title = Gonzaga Falls to Xavier; Ends Historic Season | publisher = Gonzaga | url = http://www.gozags.com/sports/w-baskbl/recaps/032810aaa.html| accessdate = 2010-09-09}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Women's Golf===
{{Merge to|Gonzaga Bulldogs|date=September 2010}}
Though not know very well, Women’s Golf at Gonzaga has made an impact. Rachel Sibbitt was named All WCC Women’s Golf Team.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web| title = Rachel Sibbitt Named To All-WCC Women's Golf Team | publisher = Gozags.com | url = http://www.gozags.com/sports/w-golf/spec-rel/041609aab.html| accessdate = 2010-09-16}}&lt;/ref&gt;  The team is small, made of only eight players for the 2010 season, but has won many awards.  These eight players are made up of two seniors, two juniors, two sophomores, and two freshmen.  Brad Rickel, is now in his fourth year of coaching at Gonzaga University.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web| title = Spring season coaches ready to hopscotch past winter | publisher = Gonzaga | url = http://www.gonzaga.edu/Campus-Resources/Offices-and-Services-A-Z/MarketingandCommunications/Publications/GQ/winter10/Bulldog-Bites.asp| accessdate = 2010-09-16}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web| title = Fallgren Ties For Second To Help Women's Golf Take Third| publisher = Gozags.com | url = http://www.gozags.com/sports/w-golf/recaps/091410aab.html| accessdate = 2010-09-16}}&lt;/ref&gt; Unlike most NCAA Division 1 sports, Gonzaga Women play golf year round. They are known for their die hard spirit and go get’em attitude.

===Intramurals===
Gonzaga University offers a multitude of intramural and club sports for each season, open to all students, and over 72% of the student population participates. Through [[intramural sports]], students compete against fellow students.  Gonzaga offers various levels ranging from A to D, with D being the lowest level. In the fall Gonzaga offers golf, soccer, flag football, volleyball, dodge ball, 3-on-3 basketball, badminton and various tournaments.  In the winter soccer, frisbee, volleyball, pickle ball, bench press competition, and handball tournaments  are offered. During the spring softball, spring triathlon, and home run derbies  are offered.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web| title = Intramurals| publisher = Gonzaga University | url = http://www.gonzaga.edu/athletics/intramurals/default.asp| accessdate = 2010-09-07}}&lt;/ref&gt; For a complete list of sports and times visit the official Gonzaga University website.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web| title = Schedules| publisher = Gonzaga University | url = http://www.gonzaga.edu/athletics/intramurals/FacilitySchedules/default.asp| accessdate = 2010-09-07}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===McCarthey Athletic Center===
{{Main|McCarthey Athletic Center}}
McCarthey Athletic Center is home to Gonzaga’s men’s and women’s basketball teams. The basketball teams had competed for 35 years in the Charlotte Y. Martin Centre.  After nearly $25 million dollars spent on construction, the McCarthy Athletic Center opened in November 2004.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web| title = GONZAGA Athletic Facilities| publisher = Gonzaga University| url = http://www.gozags.com/facilities/gonz-facilities.html| accessdate = 2010-09-14}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web| title = McCarthy Athletic Center will open Saturday| publisher = ESPN Men's Basketball| url = http://sports.espn.go.com/ncb/news/story?id=1906949| accessdate = 2010-09-14}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Student Services==
===Unity Multicultural Education Center===

The Unity Multicultural Education Center (UMEC) is an organization at Gonzaga University that promotes a more inclusive community based on trust, honor, and respect by promoting fair, equitable, and just treatment of all cultures and all members of the Gonzaga community via educational programming and presentations, activities and events. UMEC offers three key programs that help students with a multicultural background transition into the Gonzaga community: Summer BRIDGE, LEADS, and Multi-Cultural HONOR SOCIETY. UMEC also houses the Lesbian, Gay, Bisexual, and Transgender Resource Center [[LGBT]].&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web| title = Unity Multicultural Education Center (UMEC)| publisher = Gonzaga University| url = http://www.gonzaga.edu/Student-Life/UMEC/default.asp| accessdate = 2010-09-08}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Gonzaga's Health Center===
Gonzaga University offers an on-campus physician’s office staffed with a MD, a nurse practitioner, and registered nurses at the Health Center. The focus of the health center is to provide health education and medical care so that students can quickly return to their academic life. They promote personal responsibility for wellness and all health concerns are confidential. Services available include treatment of minor illnesses and injury, wellness information, health counseling, and minor surgical procedures.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web| title = Health Center| publisher = Gonzaga University| url = http://www.gonzaga.edu/Student-Life/Support-for-Students/Wellness/Health-Center/default.asp| accessdate = 2010-09-08}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web| title = Gonzaga Universtiy Health Center| publisher = Gonzaga University| url = http://www.gonzaga.edu/Academics/Libraries/Foley-Library/Departments/Instruction/PermaLinks/HealthCenter.pdf| accessdate = 2010-09-09}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Student Wellness Center===

The goal of the Student Wellness Center is to promote the health and wellbeing of students and reduce risks specifically towards alcohol and other drugs.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web| title = Student Wellness Resource Center| publisher = Gonzaga University| url = http://www.gonzaga.edu/Student-Life/Support-for-Students/Wellness/SWRC/default.asp| accessdate = 2010-10-03}}&lt;/ref&gt;  The center provides many resources that include:

'''BASICS'''
'''B'''rief '''A'''lcohol '''S'''creening and '''I'''ntervention for '''C'''ollege '''S'''tudents  (BASICS) is designed for students who drink alcohol heavily or have experienced the negative consequences of alcohol-related problems.  This is an evidence-based model program that has demonstrated a reduction in drinking in college students who drink heavily. BASICS is designed to help students make less risky decisions about their use of alcohol. This program encourages protective behaviors, and involves discussion of accidents, violence, sexual assault, sleep loss, and poor academic performance.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web| title = Student Wellness Resource Center BASICS| publisher = Gonzaga University| url = http://www.gonzaga.edu/Student-Life/Support-for-Students/Wellness/SWRC/basics1/default.asp| accessdate = 2010-10-03}}&lt;/ref&gt;

'''Green Dot'''
A program advancing visible, active intolerance of violence.

'''The PAD: Programs After Dark'''
The PAD’s mission is to provide a safe and fun environment for alternative late-night entertainment for Gonzaga students.  Four students are employed by the Student Wellness Resource Center to plan and host these events. The PAD, with support from many other GU organizations and clubs, typically holds three or four large events and four or five smaller events per semester.  Many of these events are collaborative projects with the Resident Assistants and many student clubs.  The majority of these programs operate after dark on Thursday, Friday or Saturday nights.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web| title = Student Wellness Resource Center The PAD| publisher = Gonzaga University| url = http://www.gonzaga.edu/Student-Life/Support-for-Students/Wellness/SWRC/StudentGroups/ThePAD/default.asp| accessdate = 2010-10-03}}&lt;/ref&gt;

'''Men's Violence Prevention'''
The Men's Violence Prevention Group is the first group on campus dealing solely with Men's Violence Prevention, which we believe is essential to successfully fighting the destructive force of violence against women.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web| title = Student Wellness Resource Center MVP| publisher = Gonzaga University| url = http://www.gonzaga.edu/Student-Life/Support-for-Students/Wellness/SWRC/StudentGroups/MVP/default.asp| accessdate = 2010-10-03}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Disability Resources, Education &amp; Access Management===
Gonzaga University offers an organization called Disability Resources, Education and Access Management (DREAM). They are dedicated to facilitating and co-creating a welcoming and equal opportunity environment for persons with disabilities.  It determines appropriate accommodations for enrollment, classroom accommodations, alternative media, adaptive technology, alternative testing, and student life.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web| title = DREAM| publisher = Gonzaga University| url = http://www.gonzaga.edu/Campus-Resources/Offices-and-Services-A-Z/Disability-Resources-Education-and-Access-Management/default.asp| accessdate = 2010-09-08}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web| title = Students Disability Resources, Education and Access Management| publisher = DREAM| url = http://www.gonzaga.edu/Academics/Libraries/Foley-Library/Departments/Instruction/PermaLinks/DREAM.pdf| accessdate = 2010-09-09}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===University Ministry===
University Ministry's mission is to support the faith development of all students, regardless of religious affiliation and tradition.  In particular, they provide resources for spiritual growth and fellowship through retreats, service projects, liturgies, music ministry, Christian Life Communities (CLCs), Theology on Tap, spiritual direction and residence hall programs.  These activities offer students a more mature understanding of Gonzaga's Jesuit and Catholic identity as well as a deeper respect for other religious traditions.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web| title = University Ministry| publisher = Gonzaga University| url = http://www.gonzaga.edu/About/Mission/University-Ministry/default.asp| accessdate = 2010-09-20}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Student Organizations==
===Gonzaga Student Body Association (GSBA)===

Gonzaga Student Body Association, is in charge of the clubs and activities on campus.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web| title = GSBA| publisher = Gonzaga University| url = http://www.gonzaga.edu/Student-Life/Get-Involved/GSBA.asp| accessdate = 2010-09-16}}&lt;/ref&gt;  Elections for offices such as President, Vice President, and Senator take place annually during the fall. The elected officers meet weekly and create legislation to better serve the Gonzaga community. This group of students vote and decide on new club proposals and act as visible representatives of their class.  GAB (the Gonzaga Activities Board) is a branch of GSBA that organizes special events outside of the classroom and their mission is to help support the Jesuit philosophy of developing the total self. They coordinate activities such as lectures, weekly music events, and Welcome Week. This October 2010, GAB is bringing R&amp;B artist Jay Sean to perform at Gonzaga.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web| title = Gonzaga Activities Board| publisher = Gonzaga University| url = http://www.gonzaga.edu/Student-Life/Get-Involved/GAB.asp | accessdate = 2010-09-16}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web| title = Gonzaga Student Activities Board | publisher = Gonzaga University| url = http://barney.gonzaga.edu/~gsba-technology/ | accessdate = 2010-09-16}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Knights and Setons===
The Knights and Setons are Gonzaga’s sophomore service clubs that are made up of 60 sophomores (30 men make up the Knights, and 30 women make up the Setons). Every year, the Knights and Setons raise money for a charity of their choice, their most successful fund raiser being the charity ball held every fall. They do charity work all over the university and are involved in events such as New Student Orientation and Graduation.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web| title = Knights, Setons Have a Ball Supporting Charity| publisher = Gonzaga University| url = http://www.gonzaga.edu/news-and-events/newsdetail.asp?EventID=4369&amp;DepartmentID=| accessdate = 2010-09-14}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web| title = Gonzaga University Orientation 2010| publisher = Gonzaga University| url = http://www.gonzaga.edu/Student-Life/New-Student-Information/New-Student-Orientation/TransferStudentNewsletter_6-18-10.pdf| accessdate = 2010-09-14}}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Image:Gonzaga University 360.jpg|thumb|800px|center|360° panorama on the campus of Gonzaga University as seen on an August evening]]

[[Image:Gonzaga bulletin newspapers (cropped).JPG|100px|right|thumbnail|A selection of Bulletins, Fall 2002 to Fall 2006]]

==Student Publications==
===''The Gonzaga Bulletin''===

''The Gonzaga Bulletin'' is the official, weekly student newspaper of Gonzaga University. The newspaper is staffed largely by students of the journalism and broadcasting department of the university's communication arts department and managed by a faculty adviser and an advisory board which reports to the university president.

During the 1990s, the paper was recognized for its independence and excellence by the [[Society of Professional Journalists]], winning Best Paper in the Inland Northwest Awards twice.

''The Gonzaga Bulletin'' is designed on the 4th floor of Gonzaga's College Hall. It is printed off-site in Spokane and transported to campus for distribution.

===''Spires''===
''Spires'' is Gonzaga's official yearbook. It details the academic year through pictures and articles. The yearbook is distributed at the beginning of each year and is free to all students. To ensure you are featured in the yearbook, get you picture taken during opening weekend or Fall Family weekend.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web| title = Spires| publisher = Gonzaga Website| url = http://www.gonzaga.edu/Student-Life/Get-Involved/Student-Media/Spires/default.asp| accessdate = 2010-09-08}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===''Charter''===
''Charter'' is Gonzaga's journal of scholarship and opinion. Each semester, a theme is chosen (i.e. : globalization) and students, staff, and faculty submit non-fiction regarding the theme.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web| title = Charter| publisher = Gonzaga Website| url = http://www.gonzaga.edu/Student-Life/Get-Involved/Student-Media/Charter/default.asp| accessdate = 2010-09-08}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===''Reflection''===
''Reflection'' has been published since 1960 in various forms. From its inception, Reflection has been a medium of expression and creativity for Gonzaga students, faculty, staff, and alumni. Poetry and fiction, along with other types of literature have always been the main stay of the journal. Art was not initially included in the journal, first appearing around 1967. Currently, Reflection publishes poetry, short fiction, creative non-fiction, paintings, prints, drawings, digital artwork, photographs, and ceramics in color and grayscale.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web| title = Reflection| publisher = Gonzaga Website| url = http://www.gonzaga.edu/Student-Life/Get-Involved/Student-Media/Reflection/default.asp| accessdate = 2010-09-08}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===''One World''===
''One World'' is a social justice themed journal. Students can submit their articles regarding justice issues in the local, national, or world community.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web| title = One World| publisher = Gonzaga Website| url = http://www.gonzaga.edu/Student-Life/Get-Involved/Student-Media/oneworld/default.asp| accessdate = 2010-09-08}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===''Culture Shock''===
''Culture Shock'' is Gonzaga's newest publication. A collection of essays, poems, and narratives; Culture Shock brings to light the experiences of adjusting (and not adjusting) to the cultural climate of Gonzaga University.
Published once a year, Culture Shock is always looking for submissions from students around campus that encompass a diverse mosaic of creative, thought-provoking, and inspiring material.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web| title = Culture Shock| publisher = Gonzaga Website| url = http://www.gonzaga.edu/Student-Life/Get-Involved/Student-Media/cultureshock/default.asp| accessdate = 2010-09-08}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Campus photos==
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;gallery&gt;&lt;center&gt;
Image:Gonzaga University Library.jpg|Foley Center Library at GU
Image:St Aloysius at GU.jpg|St. Aloysius Church
Image:St. Al's from JFM.JPG|St. Aloysius Church
Image:Gonzaga Fine Art Center and Museum.JPG|Jundt Art Center &amp; Museum
Image:Crosby Student Center.JPG|Crosby Student Center
Image:GU Law School.jpg|GU Law School
Image:Gonzaga University Academic Hall.jpg|Historic College Hall
&lt;/gallery&gt;

==Notable alumni==
[[Image:Bing Crosby in Road to Singapore trailer.jpg|thumb|upright|right]]
[[Image:Tom foley.jpg|thumb|upright|right|Tom Foley; 57th Speaker of the United States House of Representatives]]
[[Image:John Stockton 2002.jpg|thumb|upright|right|John Stockton; [[Basketball Hall of Fame]] inductee]]
* [[Joe Albi]] – attorney and civic leader in Spokane
* [[Sherman Alexie]] – writer
* [[Barats and Bereta]] – comedy team composed of Luke Barats and Joe Bereta
* [[Jason Bay]] – baseball player, American League All-Star - [[New York Mets]]
* [[Frank Burgess|Franklin D. Burgess]] – All American basketball player. [[United States District Court for the Western District of Washington|U.S. district judge]]; graduate of both the undergraduate college and law school
* [[Tony Canadeo]] – football player, [[Green Bay Packers]]
* The [[Chad Mitchell Trio]] – folk group famous in the 1960s, met at Gonzaga
* [[Brian Ching]] – soccer player, [[Houston Dynamo]]
* [[Bing Crosby]] – singer, actor
* [[Dan Cummins]] – Stand-up comic
* [[Tom Foley]] – former [[Speaker of the United States House of Representatives]]
* [[Richie Frahm]] – basketball player, [[Seattle SuperSonics]] and [[Portland Trail Blazers]]
* [[Christine Gregoire]] – Washington governor and the state's first female state attorney general
* [[Max Krause]] – football player, [[New York Giants]] and [[Washington Redskins]]
* [[Chad Little]] – [[NASCAR]] driver
* [[Frank McCool]] – hockey player, [[National Hockey League|NHL]] [[Calder Memorial Trophy|Rookie of the Year]]
* [[Adam Morrison]] – basketball player, [[Los Angeles Lakers]], [[Washington Wizards]]
* [[John Navone]] – Noted Jesuit author and theologian
* [[Carl Pohlad]] - Owner of the Minnesota Twins 
* [[Gary Polonsky]] – founding President and Vice-Chancellor of the [[University of Ontario Institute of Technology]]
* [[Robert Spitzer, SJ]] – Jesuit priest, philosopher, educator and author
* [[John Stockton]] – Hall of Fame basketball player, [[Utah Jazz]]
* [[Ronny Turiaf]] – basketball player, [[New York Knicks]]
* [[Courtney Vandersloot]] – Basketball player with the [[Women's National Basketball Association|WNBA]]'s [[Chicago Sky]]; first Division I player (male or female) with 2,000 points and 1,000 assists in a career
* [[Kevin Waters]] – Jesuit priest, composer, educator
* [[Ben Ysursa]] – Idaho, Secretary of State

==Notes and references==
{{Reflist}}

==External links==
* {{Official website|http://www.gonzaga.edu}}
* [http://gozags.collegesports.com Official Athletics website]
* [http://crosby.gonzaga.edu Crosby Student Center]

{{West Coast Conference}}
{{Association of Jesuit Colleges and Universities}}
{{Private colleges and universities in Washington (state)}}

{{Coord|47.66721|N|117.40235|W|source:placeopedia|display=title}}

[[Category:Educational institutions established in 1887]]
[[Category:Gonzaga University| ]]
[[Category:Jesuit universities and colleges in the United States]]
[[Category:Roman Catholic universities and colleges in the United States]]
[[Category:National Association of Independent Colleges and Universities members]]
[[Category:Universities and colleges accredited by the Northwest Commission on Colleges and Universities]]

[[de:Gonzaga University]]
[[es:Universidad Gonzaga]]
[[fr:Université Gonzaga]]
[[it:Università Gonzaga]]
[[no:Gonzaga University]]
[[ar:جامعة قونزاقا]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
