<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="1907834" ns="0" title="Vodafone New Zealand"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Use dmy dates|date=July 2011}}
{{Infobox Company
| company_name     = Vodafone Plc
| logo             = [[File:Vodafone logo.svg|200px|Vodafone Logo]]
| company_type     = [[Public company|Public]]
| foundation       = 1998
| company_slogan   = &lt;!-- unknown ??? --&gt;
| location         =  [[Auckland]], [[New Zealand]]
| key_people       = 
| revenue          = 
| operating_income = 
| net_income       = 
| parent           = [[Vodafone]]
| num_employees    = 1300
| industry         = [[Mobile phone|Mobile]] [[telecommunications]]
| products         = GSM and UMTS (3G) mobile networks and retail
| homepage         = {{URL|http://www.vodafone.co.nz/}}
}}

'''Vodafone New Zealand''' is a [[United Kingdom|British]] owned telecommunications company, a subsidiary of [[Vodafone]] Plc operating in New Zealand.  It is [[New Zealand]]'s largest [[mobile phone]] operator, based in Auckland, New Zealand and was formed in 1998, after [[Vodafone]] purchased [[BellSouth]]'s New Zealand operations. The company employs 1,300 people and has operations in Auckland, [[Wellington]] and [[Christchurch]] and has an extensive [[dealer (franchising)]] network across the country. 

The company has invested millions of dollars in their [[3G]] network, but continues to maintain its 2G network improving capacity in congested urban areas. In October 2006, Vodafone bought [[IHUG|ihug]], New Zealands third largest [[Internet service provider]] and now provides [[Internet]] service under the Vodafone New Zealand brand name.

== Market share==
At the time of purchase in November 1998, BellSouth had 138,000 customers. As of 8 November 2006, the company had about 2.1 million customers and a market share of 55% [http://www.vodafone.co.nz/aboutus/12.1.1_facts_figures.jsp?item=facts]. The company's main rival is [[Telecom New Zealand]], New Zealand's second largest [[telecommunications]] company, behind Vodafone. Telecom had the advantage that they had a 6-year head-start on BellSouth, however this advantage has slipped away in recent years.

After Vodafone took over Bellsouth, they expanded their coverage of the network to compete better with Telecom. Vodafone has constantly increased its market share and now surpasses Telecom in mobile customers. However, despite having a seemingly huge customer base, the number of active customers is lower due to abandoned [[Prepaid mobile phone|Prepaid]] accounts left by tourists.

== Coverage ==
Vodafone operates a [[GSM]] (2G) mobile phone network at 900&amp;nbsp;MHz and 1800&amp;nbsp;MHz and a [[UMTS]] (3G) network at 900&amp;nbsp;MHz and 2100&amp;nbsp;MHz. They state that the network provides service in &quot;around 97% of where New Zealanders live, work and play&quot;.[https://www.vodafone.co.nz/coverage/maps.jsp?hd=foryou].

=== GSM Coverage ===
Vodafone operates a nationwide GSM service via the 900&amp;nbsp;MHz band, but in certain areas with high demand there are additional GSM services operating in the 1800&amp;nbsp;MHz band, usually from existing 900&amp;nbsp;MHz cell sites, to provide more capacity. Areas with dual-band (i.e. both 900&amp;nbsp;MHz and 1800&amp;nbsp;MHz service) includes most major business districts and large shopping malls. In recent years Vodafone have also established some cell sites that only provide 1800&amp;nbsp;MHz service where it is difficult to release spectrum for more 900&amp;nbsp;MHz cell sites. Most phones sold since the mid-1990s support both bands.

[[2degrees]], a recent entrant to the mobile telecommunications industry, provide GSM service alongside Vodafone in both the 900&amp;nbsp;MHz and 1800&amp;nbsp;MHz bands. 2degrees also has a roaming agreement with Vodafone allowing 2degrees customers to access Vodafone's GSM network in areas where 2degrees does not have their own mobile coverage. There is currently no such agreement in the reverse direction, even though there are certain areas where 2degrees has service which Vodafone does not currently serve.

=== UMTS Coverage ===
In the main centres Vodafone operates UMTS (3G) service via the 2100&amp;nbsp;MHz band. UMTS service is often provided from the same cell site as 900&amp;nbsp;MHz and/or 1800&amp;nbsp;MHz GSM services. Unfortunately, most of the existing 900&amp;nbsp;MHz sites were built in the 1990s when it was not expected that a 2100&amp;nbsp;MHz network would have to be built. Hence the existing 900&amp;nbsp;MHz network was not at all optimised for 2100&amp;nbsp;MHz service. Due to the fact 900&amp;nbsp;MHz and 1800&amp;nbsp;MHz signals travel farther than 2100&amp;nbsp;MHz signals, there were many areas beyond 2100&amp;nbsp;MHz coverage where UMTS phones would have to hand down to 900&amp;nbsp;MHz or 1800&amp;nbsp;MHz GSM service. In recent years Vodafone has established many individual 2100&amp;nbsp;MHz UMTS sites to enhance 3G coverage.

In rural areas, however, Vodafone has installed 900&amp;nbsp;MHz UMTS (3G) service alongside their existing 900&amp;nbsp;MHz GSM (2G) service. In theory 900&amp;nbsp;MHz UMTS service should have roughly the same coverage area as 900&amp;nbsp;MHz GSM service—so instances of UMTS service being handed down to GSM should occur far less often in rural areas due to the similar coverage footprint of the two services. However many older UMTS phones only support 2100&amp;nbsp;MHz service so these phones will hand down to 900&amp;nbsp;MHz GSM even though there is UMTS service available at 900&amp;nbsp;MHz.

== Phone numbers ==
In New Zealand all mobile phone numbers start with 02. Vodafone is allocated the 021 prefix with other networks being allocated other prefixes &amp;mdash; such as 022 to 2degrees, and 027 to Telecom. However [[Local number portability|Number portability]] was introduced to the New Zealand market on 2 April 2007 which now means that customers can bring, for example, their 021 prefixed number to Telecom. Within New Zealand, the network is sometimes referred to in speech by its prefix—i.e. 'Are you 021?' instead of 'Are you with Vodafone?'.

=== 029 Prefix ===
Vodafone used to operate the 029 prefix on behalf of [[TelstraClear]], in addition to their own 021 prefix. TelstraClear customers, mostly corporates, used to be able to get mobile numbers under this prefix. These customers, however, would be billed by TelstraClear instead of being billed directly by Vodafone. In 2007 this agreement lapsed, and in 2008 some of these customers were transitioned to [[Telecom New Zealand]] who serviced these initially by [[CDMA2000]] technology.  Those [[TelstraClear]] 029 customers not transitioned to Telecom New Zealand remained with Vodafone.

=== Comparison with Telecom 027 Prefix ===
Telecom New Zealand, Vodafone's main rival, has fixed 10-digit numbers under their 0272-0278 prefix, which means they have approximately 7 million possible numbers. Telecom originally had mixed 9-digits and 10-digits number using the older 025 prefix, following the same idea Vodafone is currently using. Telecom later introduced the 027 prefix with fixed 10-digits to simplify the numbering system when they introduced their CDMA network. They have now phased out the older 025 prefix since the prefix was attached to their now redundant [[Advanced Mobile Phone System|AMPS]] and [[Digital AMPS|TDMA]] network.

== 3G services ==
On Wednesday 10 August 2005 Vodafone introduced a brand new [[3G]] network, using the [[UMTS]] technology now becoming widespread in Europe. Using this standard, Vodafone now offers [[video telephony|Video Calling]], music downloads, SKY mobile TV, as well as other services from its [[Vodafone live!]] portal.

Vodafone is currently testing a new [[HSPA+]] network with selected clients, to add to its existing UMTS network. HSPA+ is capable of a theoretical maximum 56 Mbit/s download speed and 22 Mbit/s upload speed.

== Plan Pricing Criticism ==
Vodafone New Zealand has been heavily criticised&lt;ref name=&quot;NZ_Herald_10520536&quot;&gt;{{cite news |url=http://www.nzherald.co.nz/nz/news/article.cfm?c_id=1&amp;objectid=10520536 |title=Your Views: What do you think of Vodafone's iPhone pricing plan? |date=8 July 2008 |work=[[The New Zealand Herald]] |accessdate=30 November 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;3News_62352&quot;&gt;{{cite news |url=http://www.3news.co.nz/Video/CampbellLive/tabid/367/articleID/62352/cat/84/Default.aspx |title=Vodafone talks to Campbell Live about the iPhone price - Video |date=8 July 2008 |work=[[3 News]] |accessdate=30 November 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; following the announcement of their [[iPhone]] plans, which were revealed to be among the most expensive in the world.&lt;ref name=&quot;NZ_Herald_10520525&quot;&gt;{{cite news |url=http://www.nzherald.co.nz/technology/news/article.cfm?c_id=5&amp;objectid=10520525 |title=iPhone 3G pricing announced |author=Greenop, Matt |date=8 July 2008 |work=[[The New Zealand Herald]] |accessdate=30 November 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;NZ_Herald_10520590&quot;&gt;{{cite news |url=http://www.nzherald.co.nz/wired/news/article.cfm?c_id=1501834&amp;objectid=10520590 |title=Vodafone defends against iPhone fury |author=Greenop, Matt |date=8 July 2008 |work=[[The New Zealand Herald]] |accessdate=30 November 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The iPhone 3G was launched in the [[USA]] on 11 July 2008 for a suggested retail price of $US199 for the 8GB model. In order to receive the device for the &quot;$199 worldwide&quot; promised by [[Apple Inc|Apple]], New Zealand users would have to sign up for a 24-month contract at $250 a month.&lt;ref name=&quot;costly-catch&quot;&gt;{{cite news |url=http://www.nzherald.co.nz/telecommunications/news/article.cfm?c_id=93&amp;objectid=10520666 |title='Cheap' iPhone has costly catch |author=Eriksen, Alanah |date=9 July 2008 |work=[[The New Zealand Herald]] |accessdate=30 November 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Stuff.co.nz_522646&quot;&gt;{{cite news |url=http://www.stuff.co.nz/technology/522646 |title=NZ iPhone prices disappoint fans |date=8 July 2008 |agency=with [[NZPA]] |work=[[Stuff.co.nz]] |accessdate=30 November 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; Disappointed fans also planned protests outside Vodafone stores in response to the iPhone plans and pricing.&lt;ref name=&quot;costly-catch&quot; /&gt;

== See also==

* [[ihug]]
* [[Vodafone]]
* [[Vodafone Australia]]
* [[TelstraClear]]
* [[Telecom New Zealand]]
* [[2degrees]]

==References==
{{reflist}}

== External links ==
*[http://www.vodafone.co.nz/ Vodafone New Zealand's homepage]
*[http://www.ihug.co.nz/ ihug's homepage]
*[http://www.vodafone.com/ Vodafone's parent]

{{Vodafone}}

[[Category:Vodafone]]
[[Category:Companies established in 1998]]
[[Category:Mobile phone companies of New Zealand]]
[[Category:Companies based in Auckland]]

[[ja:ボーダフォン・ニュージーランド]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
