<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="1930" ns="0" title="Arkansas"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{About|the U.S. state of Arkansas|the river|Arkansas River|other uses}}
{{pp-move-indef}}
{{stack begin}}
{{Infobox U.S. state
| Name = Arkansas
| Fullname = State of Arkansas
| Flag = Flag of Arkansas.svg
| Flaglink = [[Flag of Arkansas|Flag]]
| Seal = Seal of Arkansas.svg
| Map = Arkansas in United States.svg
| Nickname = The Natural State (current)&lt;br/&gt; The Land of Opportunity (former)
| Motto = [[Regnat populus]] ([[Latin]])
| MottoEnglish = The People Rule
| Former = Arkansas Territory
| Capital = [[Little Rock, Arkansas|Little Rock]]
| OfficialLang = [[English language|English]]
| Demonym = [[Adjectivals and demonyms for U.S. states|Arkansan; Arkansawyer;Arkansawian]]&lt;ref name=&quot;Encarta Encyclopedia&quot;&gt;{{cite encyclopedia |date=18 May 2010 |url=http://encarta.msn.com/dictionary_1861695659_1861695659/prevpage.html|title=Arkansawyer definition}}&lt;/ref&gt;
| LargestCity = capital
| LargestMetro = [[Little Rock metropolitan area|Little Rock Metropolitan Area]]
| Governor = [[Mike Beebe]] ([[Democratic Party (United States)|D]])
| Lieutenant Governor = [[Mark Darr]] (R)
| Legislature = [[Arkansas General Assembly|General Assembly]]
| Upperhouse = [[Arkansas Senate|Senate]]
| Lowerhouse = [[Arkansas House of Representatives|House of Representatives]]
| Senators = [[Mark Pryor]] (D)&lt;br/&gt;[[John Boozman]] (R)
|Representative= 3 Republicans, 1 Democrat
| PostalAbbreviation = AR
| TradAbbreviation = Ark.
| AreaRank = 29th
| TotalArea = 137,733
| TotalAreaUS = 53,179
| LandArea = 134,856
| LandAreaUS = 52,068
| WaterArea = 2876
| WaterAreaUS = 1,110
| PCWater = 2.09
| PopRank = 32nd
| 2000Pop (old) = 2,673,400
| 2010Pop = 2,915,918 (2010 Census) &lt;ref&gt;http://www.census.gov/prod/cen2010/briefs/c2010br-01.pdf&lt;/ref&gt; &lt;br/&gt; 2,673,400 (2000)
| Median Income = $24,375 (50th)
| DensityRank = 34th
| 2010Density = 18.34
| 2010DensityUS = 55.03
| AdmittanceOrder = 25th
| AdmittanceDate = June 15, 1836
| TimeZone = [[Central Standard Time Zone|Central]]: [[Coordinated Universal Time|UTC]]-6/[[Daylight saving time|DST]]-5
| Latitude = 33° 00′ N to 36° 30′ N
| Longitude = 89° 39′ W to 94° 37′ W
| Width = 385
| WidthUS = 239
| Length = 420
| LengthUS = 261
| HighestPoint = [[Magazine Mountain]]&lt;ref&gt;{{cite ngs|id=FG1888|designation=Mag|accessdate=October 20, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=USGS&gt;{{cite web|url=http://egsc.usgs.gov/isb/pubs/booklets/elvadist/elvadist.html|title=Elevations and Distances in the United States|publisher=[[United States Geological Survey]]|date=2001|accessdate=October 21, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=NAVD88&gt;Elevation adjusted to [[North American Vertical Datum of 1988]].&lt;/ref&gt;
| HighestElev = 839
| HighestElevUS = 2,753
| MeanElev = 200
| MeanElevUS = 650
| LowestPoint = [[Ouachita River]] at {{nobreak|[[Louisiana]] border}}&lt;ref name=USGS/&gt;&lt;ref name=NAVD88/&gt;
| LowestElev = 17
| LowestElevUS = 55
| ISOCode = US-AR
| TradAbbrev = Ark
| Website = www.arkansas.gov
}}
{{Infobox U.S. state symbols
| Boxwidth = 25em
| Flag = Flag of Arkansas.svg
| Name = Arkansas
| Bird = [[Northern Mockingbird|Mockingbird]]
| Butterfly = [[Diana Fritillary]]
| Flower = [[Apple|Apple blossom]]
| Insect = [[Western honey bee|European honey bee]]
| Mammal = [[White-tailed deer]]
| Tree = [[Loblolly Pine]]
| Beverage = [[Milk]]
| Dance = [[Square Dance]]
| Food = [[Tomato|South Arkansas Vine Ripe Pink Tomato]]
| Gemstone = [[Diamond]]
| Instrument = [[Fiddle]]
| Mineral = [[Quartz]]
| StateRock = [[Bauxite]]
| Soil = [[Stuttgart (soil)|Stuttgart]]
| Song = ''[[Arkansas (song)]]'',&lt;br/&gt;''[[Arkansas (You Run Deep In Me)]]'',&lt;br/&gt;''[[Oh, Arkansas]]'',&lt;br/&gt;''[[The Arkansas Traveler (song)|The Arkansas Traveler]]''
| Tartan = [[:File:Arkansas Traveler Tartan.png|Arkansas Traveler Tartan]]
| Route Marker = Arkansas 201.svg
| Quarter = 2003 AR Proof.png
| QuarterReleaseDate = 2003
}}
{{stack end}}

'''Arkansas''' ({{IPAc-en|audio=en-us-Arkansas.ogg|ˈ|ɑr|k|ən|s|ɔː}} {{respell|AR|kən-saw}})&lt;ref&gt;Jones, Daniel. (1997) ''English Pronouncing Dictionary'', 15th ed. Cambridge University Press. ISBN 0-521-45272-4&lt;/ref&gt; is a [[U.S. state|state]] located in the [[Southern United States|southern region]] of the [[United States]]. Its name is an [[Algonquian languages|Algonquian]] name of the [[Quapaw]] [[Native Americans in the United States|Indians]]. Arkansas shares borders with six states (clockwise: N:[[Missouri]]; E: [[Tennessee]], [[Mississippi]]; S: [[Louisiana]]; SW: [[Texas]]; W: [[Oklahoma]]), and its eastern border is largely defined by the [[Mississippi River]]. Its diverse geography ranges from the mountainous regions of the [[The Ozarks|Ozarks]] and the [[Ouachita Mountains]], which make up the [[U.S. Interior Highlands]], to the eastern lowlands along the Mississippi River. The capital and most populous city is [[Little Rock, Arkansas|Little Rock]], located in the central portion of the state.

==Toponym==
The name &quot;Arkansas&quot; derives from the same root as the name for the [[State of Kansas]]. The [[Kaw (tribe)|Kansa]] tribe of [[Indigenous peoples of the Americas|Native Americans]] are closely associated with the [[Sioux]] tribes of the [[Great Plains]]. The word &quot;Arkansas&quot; itself is a [[French language|French]] pronunciation (&quot;Arcansas&quot;) of a [[Quapaw]] (a related &quot;Kaw&quot; tribe) word &quot;akakaze&quot; meaning &quot;land of downriver people&quot; or the [[Sioux language|Sioux]] word &quot;Akakaze&quot; meaning &quot;people of the south wind&quot;. The pronunciation of Arkansas was made official by an act of the state legislature in 1881, after a dispute between the two U.S. Senators from Arkansas. One wanted to pronounce the name {{IPAc-en|ɑr|ˈ|k|æ|n|z|ə|s}} {{respell|ar|KAN|zəs}} and the other wanted {{IPAc-en|ˈ|ɑr|k|ən|s|ɔː}} {{respell|AR|kən-saw}}.&lt;ref name=&quot;Arkansas&quot;&gt;The name Arkansas has been pronounced and spelled in a variety of fashions. The region was organized as the [[Territory of Arkansaw]] on July 4, 1819, but the territory was admitted to the [[United States|Union]] as the [[State of Arkansas]] on June 15, 1836. The name was historically {{IPAc-en|ˈ|ɑr|k|ən|s|ɔː}}, {{IPAc-en|ɑr|ˈ|k|æ|n|z|ə|s}}, and several other variants. In 1881, the [[Arkansas General Assembly]] passed the following concurrent resolution, now Arkansas Code 1-4-105 ([http://www.arkleg.state.ar.us/assembly/ArkansasCode/0/1-4-105.htm official text]):
&lt;blockquote&gt;Whereas, confusion of practice has arisen in the pronunciation of the name of our state and it is deemed important that the true pronunciation sould be determined for use in oral official proceedings.&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;And, whereas, the matter has been thoroughly investigated by the State Historical Society and the Eclectic Society of Little Rock, which have agreed upon the correct pronunciation as derived from history, and the early usage of the American immigrants.&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;Be it therefore resolved by both houses of the General Assembly, that the only true pronunciation of the name of the state, in the opinion of this body, is that received by the French from the native Indians and committed to writing in the French word representing the sound. It should be pronounced in three (3) syllables, with the final &quot;s&quot; silent, the &quot;a&quot; in each syllable with the Italian sound, and the accent on the first and last syllables. The pronunciation with the accent on the second syllable with the sound of &quot;a&quot; in &quot;man&quot; and the sounding of the terminal &quot;s&quot; is an innovation to be discouraged.&lt;/blockquote&gt;
Citizens of the [[State of Kansas]] often pronounce the [[Arkansas River]] as {{IPAc-en|ɑr|ˈ|k|æ|n|z|ə|s|_|ˈ|r|ɪ|v|ər}}, in a manner similar to the common pronunciation of the name of their state.&lt;/ref&gt;

In 2007, the state legislature officially declared the possessive form of the state's name to be ''Arkansas's''.&lt;ref&gt;Gambrell, John. [http://www2.arkansasonline.com/news/2007/mar/13/senate-gives-support-possessive-form-arkansas/ &quot;Senate gives support to possessive form of Arkansas.&quot;] ''[[Arkansas Democrat Gazette]]'', March 13, 2007.&lt;/ref&gt;

==Geography==
{{See also|List of Arkansas counties|List of cities in Arkansas|List of Arkansas townships|List of Arkansas native plants}}
[[File:Petit Jean State Park view.jpg|thumb|left|250px|View from the summit of Petit Jean Mountain, nestled in the [[Arkansas River|Arkansas River Valley]], from Mather Lodge in [[Petit Jean State Park]].]]
The [[Mississippi River]] forms most of Arkansas's eastern border, except in [[Clay County, Arkansas|Clay]] and [[Greene County, Arkansas|Greene]] counties where the [[St. Francis River]] forms the western boundary of the [[Missouri Bootheel]], and in dozens of places where the current channel of the Mississippi has meandered from where it had last been legally specified.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.encyclopediaofarkansas.net/encyclopedia/entry-detail.aspx?entryID=2546 Arkansas State Boundaries] from the [http://www.encyclopediaofarkansas.net/ Encyclopedia of Arkansas]&lt;/ref&gt; Arkansas shares its southern border with [[Louisiana]], its northern border with [[Missouri]], its eastern border with [[Tennessee]] and [[Mississippi]], and its western border with [[Texas]] and [[Oklahoma]].

Arkansas is a land of lakes and rivers, thick forests and fertile soil. The [[Arkansas Delta]] is a flat landscape of [[River delta|rich alluvial soils formed by repeated flooding]] of the adjacent Mississippi. Farther away from the river, in the southeast portion of the state, the Grand Prairie consists of a more undulating landscape. Both are fertile agricultural areas.

The Delta region is bisected by an unusual geological formation known as [[Crowley's Ridge]]. A narrow band of rolling hills, Crowley's Ridge rises from 250 to {{convert|500|ft|m}} above the surrounding alluvial plain and underlies many of the major towns of eastern Arkansas.

Northwest Arkansas is part of the [[Ozark Plateau]] including the [[Ozark Mountains]], to the south are the [[Ouachita Mountains]], and these regions are divided by the [[Arkansas River]]; the southern and eastern parts of Arkansas are called the Lowlands. These mountain ranges are part of the [[U.S. Interior Highlands]] region, the only major mountainous region between the [[Rocky Mountains]] and the [[Appalachian Mountains]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.srs.fs.usda.gov/4106/about/HotSpringsOffice.htm |title=Managing Upland Forests of the Midsouth|publisher=United States Forestry Service |accessdate=2007-10-13}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://tapestry.usgs.gov/physiogr/physio.html|title=A Tapestry of Time and Terrain: The Union of Two Maps – Geology and Topography|publisher=United States Geological Survey |accessdate=2007-10-13}}&lt;/ref&gt; The highest point in the state is [[Mount Magazine]] in the [[Ouachita Mountains]]; it rises to {{convert|2753|ft|m}} above sea level.

[[File:BuffaloRiver.jpg|right|thumb|[[Buffalo National River]], one of many attractions that give the state's nickname ''The Natural State''.]]

Arkansas is home to many [[List of caves in Arkansas|caves]], such as [[Blanchard Springs Caverns]].
More than 43,000 Native American living, hunting and tool making sites, many of them Pre-Columbian burial mounds and rock shelters, have been catalogued by the State Archeologist. Arkansas is currently the only U.S. state in which [[diamond]]s are mined—although by members of the public with primitive digging tools for a small daily fee, not by commercial interests.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.craterofdiamondsstatepark.com/history/ |title=Crater of Diamonds: History of diamonds, diamond mining in Arkansas |publisher=Craterofdiamondsstatepark.com |date= |accessdate=2010-07-30}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://geology.com/gemstones/united-states-diamond-production.shtml |title=US Diamond Mines – Diamond Mining in the United States |publisher=Geology.com |date= |accessdate=2010-07-30}}&lt;/ref&gt; (near [[Murfreesboro, Arkansas|Murfreesboro]]).

Arkansas is home to many areas protected by the [[National Park System]]. These include:&lt;ref name=&quot;ArkNPS&quot;&gt;{{cite web |title=Arkansas |publisher=National Park Service |accessdate=2008-07-15 |url=http://www.nps.gov/state/ar}}&lt;/ref&gt;

*[[Arkansas Post National Memorial]] at [[Gillett, Arkansas|Gillett]]
*[[Buffalo National River]]
*[[Fort Smith National Historic Site]]
*[[Hot Springs National Park]]
*[[Little Rock Central High School National Historic Site]]
*[[Pea Ridge National Military Park]]
*[[President William Jefferson Clinton Birthplace Home National Historic Site]]

The [[Trail of Tears]] National Historic Trail also runs through Arkansas.&lt;ref name=&quot;ArkNPS&quot;/&gt;

Arkansas is home to a dozen Wilderness Areas totaling around {{convert|150000|acre|km2}}. These areas are set aside for outdoor recreation and are open to hunting, fishing, hiking, and primitive camping. No mechanized vehicles are allowed in these areas, some of which are rarely visited and can provide a good experience of feeling as if you are the only person to have ever stepped foot there.

===Climate===
Arkansas generally has a [[humid subtropical climate]], which borders on [[humid continental climate|humid continental]] in some northern highland areas. While not bordering the [[Gulf of Mexico]], Arkansas is still close enough to this warm, large body of water for it to influence the weather in the state. Generally, Arkansas has hot, humid summers and cold, slightly drier winters. In [[Little Rock, Arkansas|Little Rock]], the daily high temperatures average around {{convert|93|°F|°C|abbr=on}} with lows around {{convert|73|°F|°C|abbr=on}} in the month of July. In January highs average around {{convert|51|°F|°C|abbr=on}} and lows around {{convert|32|°F|°C|abbr=on}}. In [[Siloam Springs, Arkansas|Siloam Springs]] in the northwest part of the state, the average high and low temperatures in July are {{convert|89|°F|°C|abbr=on}} and {{convert|67|°F|°C|abbr=on}} and in January the average high and lows are {{convert|44|°F|°C|abbr=on}} and {{convert|23|°F|°C|abbr=on}}. Annual precipitation throughout the state averages between about {{convert|40|and|60|in|mm}}; somewhat wetter in the south and drier in the northern part of the state.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.ocs.orst.edu/pub/maps/Precipitation/Total/States/AR/ar.gif Average Annual Precipitation – Arkansas]. Spatial Climate Analysis Service, [[Oregon State University]]. Published 2000. Last Retrieved 2007-10-26.&lt;/ref&gt; Snowfall is common, more so in the north half of the state, which usually gets several snowfalls each winter. This is not only due to its closer proximity to the plains states, but also to the higher elevations found throughout the Ozark and Ouachita mountains. The half of the state south of Little Rock gets less snow, and is more apt to see ice storms, however, sleet and freezing rain are expected throughout the state during the winter months, and can significantly impact travel and day to day life. Arkansas' all time record high is {{convert|120|F|C}} at [[Ozark, Arkansas|Ozark]] on August 10, 1936; the all time record low is {{convert|-29|F|C}} at [[Pond, Arkansas|Pond]] on February 13, 1905.

Arkansas is known for extreme weather. A typical year will see thunderstorms, tornadoes, hail, snow and ice storms. Between both the [[Great Plains]] and the [[Gulf Coast of the United States|Gulf States]], Arkansas receives around 60 days of thunderstorms. A few of the most destructive tornadoes in U.S. history have struck the state. While being sufficiently away from the coast to be safe from a direct hit from a hurricane, Arkansas can often get the remnants of a [[tropical cyclone|tropical system]] which dumps tremendous amounts of rain in a short time and often spawns smaller tornadoes.

==History==&lt;!--Linked from [[List of capitals in the United States]] --&gt;
[[File:Flatsidewildernesssunset1a.jpg|thumb|right|250px|Flatside Wilderness Area, Ouachita Mountains, Arkansas]]
{{Main|History of Arkansas}}
The first European to reach Arkansas was the [[Spain|Spanish]] explorer [[Hernando de Soto (explorer)|Hernando de Soto]], a veteran of Pizarro's conquest of Peru who died near Lake Village on the Mississippi River in 1542 after almost a year traversing the southern part of the state in search of gold and a passage to China. Arkansas is one of several [[U.S. states]] formed from the territory purchased from [[Napoleon Bonaparte]] in the [[Louisiana Purchase]]. The early Spanish or French explorers of the state gave it its name, which is probably a phonetic spelling of the [[Illinois language|Illinois]] tribe's name for the [[Quapaw]] people, who lived downriver from them.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://listserv.linguistlist.org/cgi-bin/wa?A2=ind0302b&amp;L=ads-l&amp;P=7800 |title=Linguist list 14.4 |publisher=Listserv.linguistlist.org |date=2003-02-11 |accessdate=2010-07-30}}&lt;/ref&gt; Other [[Native Americans in the United States|Native American]] tribes who lived in Arkansas before moving west were the Quapaw, [[Caddo]], and [[Osage Nation|Osage]] nations. In their forced move westward (under U.S. [[Indian removal]] policies), the [[Five Civilized Tribes]] inhabited Arkansas during its territorial period.

The [[Territory of Arkansas]]&lt;ref name=&quot;Arkansas&quot;/&gt; was organized on July 4, 1819. On June 15, 1836, the State of Arkansas was admitted to the [[United States|Union]] as the 25th [[U.S. state|state]] and the 13th [[slave state]]. Planters settled in the Delta to cultivate cotton; this was the area of the state where most enslaved African Americans were held. Other areas had more subsistence farmers and mixed farming.

Arkansas played a key role in aiding Texas in its war for independence from Mexico; it sent troops and materials to Texas to help fight the war. The proximity of the city of [[Washington, Arkansas|Washington]] to the Texas border involved the town in the [[Texas Revolution]] of 1835–36. Some evidence suggests [[Sam Houston]] and his compatriots planned the revolt in a tavern at Washington in 1834.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.arkansasmediaroom.com/news-releases/listings/display.asp?id=165 |title=Old Washington State Park Conserves Town's Heyday |first=Jim |last=Taylor}}&lt;/ref&gt; When the fighting began, a stream of volunteers from Arkansas and the southeastern states flowed through the town toward the Texas battle fields.

When the [[Mexican-American War]] began in 1846, Washington became a rendezvous for volunteer troops. Governor Thomas S. Drew issued a proclamation calling on the state to furnish one regiment of cavalry and one battalion of infantry to join the United States Army. Ten companies of men assembled here, where they were formed into the first Regiment of Arkansas Cavalry.

The state developed a cotton culture in the east in lands of the Mississippi Delta. This was where enslaved labor was used most extensively, as planters brought with them or imported slaves from the Upper South. On the eve of the Civil War in 1860, enslaved African Americans numbered 111,115 people, just over 25% of the state's population.&lt;ref&gt;[http://fisher.lib.virginia.edu/collections/stats/histcensus/php/state.php Historical Census Browser, 1860 US Census, University of Virginia]. Retrieved March 21, 2008.&lt;/ref&gt;

Arkansas refused to join the [[Confederate States of America]] until after [[United States President]] [[Abraham Lincoln]] called for troops to respond to the Confederate attack upon [[Battle of Fort Sumter|Fort Sumter]], [[South Carolina]]. The State of Arkansas declared its secession from the [[United States|Union]] on May 6, 1861. While not often cited in historical accounts, the state was the scene of numerous small-scale battles during the [[American Civil War]]. Arkansans of note who contributed to the Civil War included Confederate Major General [[Patrick Cleburne]]. Considered by many to be one of the most brilliant Confederate division commanders of the war, Cleburne was often referred to as &quot;The Stonewall of the West.&quot; Also of note was Major General [[Thomas C. Hindman]]. A former United States Representative, Hindman commanded Confederate forces at the [[Battle of Cane Hill]] and [[Battle of Prairie Grove]].

Under the [[Reconstruction era of the United States#Military reconstruction|Military Reconstruction Act]], Congress restored Arkansas to the Union in June 1868. The Reconstruction legislature established universal male suffrage while disenfranchising former Confederates (mostly Democrats), a public education system, and other general issues to improve the state and help more of the population. The state came under almost exclusive control of [[Radical Republicans]], (those who emigrated from the North being derided as &quot;[[carpetbaggers]]&quot; by ex-Confederates based on allegations of corruption), led by newly elected Governor [[Powell Clayton]], marking a time of great upheaval and racial violence in the state between state militia and the [[Ku Klux Klan]].

In 1874, the [[Brooks-Baxter War]], a political struggle between factions of the [[United States Republican Party|Republican Party]] shook Little Rock and the state governorship. It was settled only when President [[Ulysses S. Grant]] ordered [[Joseph Brooks (politician)|Joseph Brooks]] to disperse his militant supporters.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.encyclopediaofarkansas.net/encyclopedia/entry-detail.aspx?entryID=2276 |title=Brooks-Baxter War – Encyclopedia of Arkansas |accessdate=2007-08-24}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Following the Brooks-Baxter War, a new state constitution was ratified re-enfranchising former Confederates.

In 1881, the Arkansas state legislature enacted a bill that adopted an official pronunciation of the state's name, to combat a controversy then simmering. (See Law and Government below.)

After Reconstruction, the state began to receive more immigrants and migrants. [[Chinese people|Chinese]], [[Italians|Italian]], and [[Syrian]] men were recruited for farm labor in the developing Delta region. None of these nationalities stayed long at farm labor; the Chinese especially quickly became small merchants in towns around the Delta. Some early 20th century immigration included people from eastern Europe. Together, these immigrants made the Delta more diverse than the rest of the state. In the same years, some black migrants moved into the area because of opportunities to develop the bottomlands and own their own property. Many Chinese became such successful merchants in small towns that they were able to educate their children at college.&lt;ref&gt;William D. Baker, ''Minority Settlement in the Mississippi River Counties of the Arkansas Delta, 1870–1930'', Arkansas Preservation Commission [http://www.arkansaspreservation.org/pdf/publications/Minority_Settlement.pdf], accessed 14 May 2008&lt;/ref&gt;

Construction of railroads enabled more farmers to get their products to market. It also brought new development into different parts of the state, including the Ozarks, where some areas were developed as resorts. In a few years at the end of the 19th century, for instance, [[Eureka Springs]] in [[Carroll County, Arkansas|Carroll County]] grew to 10,000 people, rapidly becoming a tourist destination and the fourth largest city of the state. It featured newly constructed, elegant resort hotels and spas planned around its natural springs, considered to have healthful properties. The town's attractions included horse racing and other entertainment. It appealed to a wide variety of classes, becoming almost as popular as [[Hot Springs, Arkansas|Hot Springs]].

In the late 1880s, the worsening agricultural depression catalyzed Populist and third party movements, leading to interracial coalitions. Struggling to stay in power, in the 1890s the Democrats in Arkansas followed other Southern states in passing legislation and constitutional amendments that disfranchised blacks and poor whites. Democrats wanted to prevent their alliance. In 1891 state legislators passed a requirement for a [[literacy test]], knowing that many blacks and whites would be excluded, at a time when more than 25% of the population could neither read nor write. In 1892 they amended the state constitution to include a [[poll tax]] and more complex residency requirements, both of which adversely affected poor people and sharecroppers, and forced them from electoral rolls.

By 1900 the Democratic Party expanded use of the [[white primary]] in county and state elections, further denying blacks a part in the political process. Only in the primary was there any competition among candidates, as Democrats held all the power. The state was a Democratic one-party state for decades, until after the [[Civil Rights Act of 1964]] and [[Voting Rights Act of 1965]] were passed.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.oldstatehouse.com/educational_programs/classroom/arkansas_news/detail.asp?id=800&amp;issue_id=36&amp;page=3
&quot;White Primary&quot; System Bars Blacks from Politics – 1900&quot;, ''The Arkansas News'', Old State House, Spring 1987, p.3. Retrieved March 22, 2008.&lt;/ref&gt;

Between 1905 and 1911, Arkansas began to receive a small migration of [[Germans|German]], [[Slovaks|Slovak]], and [[Irish people|Irish]] immigrants. The German and Slovak peoples settled in the eastern part of the state known as the [[Prairie]], and the Irish founded small communities in the southeast part of the state. The Germans were mostly Catholic and the Slovaks were Lutheran. The Irish were mostly [[Protestant]] from [[Ulster]].

After the [[Supreme Court of the United States|Supreme Court]]'s decision in [[Brown v. Board of Education|''Brown ''v.'' Board of Education of Topeka, Kansas'']] in 1954, the [[Little Rock Nine]] brought Arkansas to national attention when the Federal government intervened to protect African-American students trying to integrate a high school in the Arkansas capital. Governor [[Orval Faubus]] ordered the [[Arkansas National Guard]] to aid segregationists in preventing nine African-American students from enrolling at Little Rock's Central High School. After attempting three times to contact Faubus, President [[Dwight D. Eisenhower]] sent 1000 troops from the active-duty 101st Airborne Division to escort and protect the African-American students as they entered school on September 25, 1957. In defiance of federal court orders to integrate, the governor and city of Little Rock decided to close the high schools for the remainder of the school year. By the fall of 1959, the Little Rock high schools were completely integrated.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.encyclopediaofarkansas.net/encyclopedia/entry-detail.aspx?search=1&amp;entryID=723 |title=Little Rock Nine – Encyclopedia of Arkansas |accessdate=2007-08-24}}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Bill Clinton]], the 42nd [[President of the United States]], was born in [[Hope, Arkansas]]. Before his presidency, Clinton served as the 40th and 42nd [[Governor of Arkansas]], a total of nearly 12 years.

==Demographics==
{{US Census population
| 1810 = 1062
| 1820 = 14273
| 1830 = 30388
| 1840 = 97574
| 1850 = 209897
| 1860 = 435450
| 1870 = 484471
| 1880 = 802525
| 1890 = 1128211
| 1900 = 1311564
| 1910 = 1574449
| 1920 = 1752204
| 1930 = 1854482
| 1940 = 1949387
| 1950 = 1909511
| 1960 = 1786272
| 1970 = 1923295
| 1980 = 2286435
| 1990 = 2350725
| 2000 = 2673400
| 2010 = 2915918
| footnote = Sources: 1910-2010&lt;ref&gt;http://2010.census.gov/2010census/data/apportionment-pop-text.php&lt;/ref&gt;
}}
As of 2006, Arkansas has an estimated population of 2,810,872,&lt;ref name=&quot;stateest&quot;&gt;{{cite web |date=June 21, 2006 |url=http://www.census.gov/popest/states/tables/NST-EST2005-01.csv |title=Annual Estimates of the Population for the United States and States, and for Puerto Rico: April 1, 2000 to July 1, 2005|format=[[Comma-separated values|CSV]] |work=2005 Population Estimates |publisher=U.S. Census Bureau, Population Division   |accessdate=November 15, 2006}}&lt;/ref&gt; which is an increase of 29,154, or 1.1%, from the prior year and an increase of 105,756, or 4.0%, since the year 2000. This includes a natural increase since the last census of 52,214 people (that is 198,800 births minus 146,586 deaths) and an increase due to net migration of 57,611 people into the state. Immigration from outside the United States resulted in a net increase of 21,947 people, and migration within the country produced a net increase of 35,664 people. It is estimated that about 48.8% is male, and 51.2% is female. From 2000 through 2006 Arkansas has had a population growth of 5.1% or 137,472.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://quickfacts.census.gov/qfd/states/05000.html|title=Arkansas QuickFacts from the US Census Bureau}}&lt;/ref&gt; The population density of the state is 51.3 people per square mile.

According to the [[2010 U.S. Census]], Arkansas had a population of 2,915,918. In terms of race and ethnicity, the state was 77.0% White, 15.4% Black or African American, 0.8% American Indian and Alaska Native, 1.2% Asian, 0.2% Native Hawaiian and Other Pacific Islander, 3.4% from Some Other Race, and 2.0% from Two or More Races. Hispanics or Latinos of any race made up 6.4% of the population.&lt;ref&gt;http://factfinder2.census.gov/faces/tableservices/jsf/pages/productview.xhtml?pid=DEC_10_PL_QTPL&amp;prodType=table&lt;/ref&gt;

According to the 2006–2008 [[American Community Survey]],&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|author=American FactFinder, United States Census Bureau |url=http://factfinder.census.gov/servlet/ADPTable?_bm=y&amp;-geo_id=04000US05&amp;-qr_name=ACS_2008_3YR_G00_DP3YR2&amp;-ds_name=ACS_2008_3YR_G00_&amp;-_lang=en&amp;-_sse=on |title=Arkansas – Selected Social Characteristics in the United States: 2006–2008 |publisher=Factfinder.census.gov |date= |accessdate=2010-07-30}}&lt;/ref&gt; the ten largest ancestry groups in the state [[African American]] (15.5%), [[Irish American|Irish]] (13.6%), [[German American|German]] (12.5%), [[People of the United States|American]] (11.1%), [[English American|English]] (10.3%), [[French American|French]] (2.4%), [[Scotch-Irish American|Scotch-Irish]] (2.1%), [[Dutch American|Dutch]] (1.9%), [[Scottish American|Scottish]] (1.9%) and [[Italian American|Italian]] (1.7%).

European Americans have a strong presence in the northwestern [[Ozarks]] and the central part of the state. African Americans live mainly in the southern and eastern parts of the state. Arkansans of Irish, English and German ancestry are mostly found in the far northwestern Ozarks near the Missouri border. Ancestors of the Irish in the Ozarks were chiefly [[Ulster Scots people|Scotch-Irish]], Protestants from [[Northern Ireland]], the [[Scotland|Scottish]] lowlands and northern England part of the largest group of immigrants from [[Kingdom of Great Britain|Great Britain]] and [[Kingdom of Ireland|Ireland]] before the American Revolution. [[English American|English]] and [[Scotch-Irish American|Scotch-Irish]] immigrants settled throughout the backcountry of the South and in the more mountainous areas. Americans of [[English American|English]] stock are found throughout the state.&lt;ref&gt;David Hackett Fischer, ''Albion's Seed: Four British Folkways in America'', New York: Oxford University Press, 1989, pp.633–639&lt;/ref&gt;

According to the 2006–2008 American Community Survey, 93.8% of Arkansas' population (over the age of five) spoke only [[English language|English]] at home. About 4.5% of the state's population spoke [[Spanish language|Spanish]] at home. About 0.7% of the state's population spoke any other [[Indo-European languages|Indo-European language]]. About 0.8% of the state's population spoke an [[Languages of Asia|Asian language]], and 0.2% spoke other languages.

In 2006, Arkansas has a larger percentage of tobacco smokers than the national average, with 24.0% of adults smoking.&lt;ref&gt;[http://apps.nccd.cdc.gov/StateSystem/stateSystem.aspx?selectedTopic=100&amp;selectedMeasure=1000&amp;dir=epi_report&amp;ucName=UCSummary&amp;year=2006&amp;excel=htmlTable&amp;submitBk=y CDC's State System – State Comparison Report Cigarette Use (Adults) – BRFSS] for 2006, lists the state as having 23.7% smokers. The national average is 20.8% according to [http://www.cdc.gov/mmwr/preview/mmwrhtml/mm5644a2.htm Cigarette Smoking Among Adults --- United States, 2006] article in the CDC's Morbidity and Mortality Weekly Report.&lt;/ref&gt;

===Religion===
Arkansas, like most other Southern states, is part of the [[Bible Belt]] and is predominantly Protestant. The religious affiliations of the people are as follows:&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.gc.cuny.edu/faculty/research_briefs/aris/key_findings.htm |title=American Religious Identification Survey, 2001 |publisher=Gc.cuny.edu |date= |accessdate=2010-07-30}}&lt;/ref&gt;
[[File:Arkansas population map.png|thumb|right|250px|Arkansas Population Density Map]]
*[[Christianity|Christian]]: 86.0%
**[[Protestant]]: 78.0%
***[[Baptist]]: 39.0%
***[[Methodist]]: 9.0%
***[[Pentecostal]]: 6.0%
***[[Churches of Christ|Church of Christ]]: 6.0%
***[[Assemblies of God USA|Assemblies of God]]: 3.0%
***Other Protestant: 15.0%
**[[Roman Catholicism in the United States|Roman Catholic]]: 7.0%
**[[Eastern Orthodox Church|Eastern Orthodox]]: &lt;1.0%
**Other Christian: &lt;1.0%
*Non-religious: 14.0%
*Other religions: &lt;1.0%
*[[Judaism|Jewish]]: &lt;1.0%
*[[Islam|Muslim]]: &lt;1.0%
The largest denominations by number of adherents in 2000 were the [[Southern Baptist Convention]] with 665,307; the [[United Methodist Church]] with 179,383; the [[Roman Catholic Church]] with 115,967; and the [[American Baptist Association]] with 115,916.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.thearda.com/mapsReports/reports/state/05_2000.asp |title=The Association of Religion Data Archives &amp;#124; Maps &amp; Reports |publisher=Thearda.com |date= |accessdate=2010-07-30}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Economy==
{{See also|List of Arkansas companies}}
[[File:2003 AR Proof.png|thumb|left|150px|The quarter for Arkansas, released October 20, 2003]]
&lt;!--Deleted image removed: [[File:Littlerockskyline.jpg|thumb|right|[[Little Rock]] city center.]]--&gt;

The state's gross domestic product for 2010 was $103 billion.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=GDP by State|url=http://greyhill.com/gdp-by-state|publisher=Greyhill Advisors|accessdate=23 September 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; Its per capita household median income (in current dollars) for 2004 was $35,295, according to the U.S. Census Bureau.&lt;ref&gt;[http://quickfacts.census.gov/qfd/states/05000.html Arkansas QuickFacts] from the US Census Bureau&lt;/ref&gt; The state's agriculture outputs are poultry and eggs, soybeans, sorghum, cattle, cotton, rice, hogs, and milk. Its industrial outputs are food processing, electric equipment, fabricated metal products, machinery, paper products, bromine, and vanadium.

As of August 2011, the state's unemployment rate is 8.3%.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Local Area Unemployment Statistics|url=http://www.bls.gov/web/laus/laumstch.htm|publisher=BLS|accessdate=23 September 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; 

Several global companies are headquartered in the northwest corner of Arkansas, including [[Wal-Mart]] (the world's largest public corporation by revenue in 2007),&lt;ref name=&quot;2007-Fortune-Global-500&quot;&gt;Staff Writer. &quot;[http://money.cnn.com/magazines/fortune/global500/2007/ Fortune Global 500].&quot; ''[[CNN]]/[[Fortune (magazine)|Fortune]].'' 2007. Retrieved on November 8, 2007.&lt;/ref&gt; [[J.B. Hunt]] and [[Tyson Foods]]. This area of the state has experienced an economic boom since the 1970s as a result.

In recent years, [[automobile]] parts manufacturers have opened factories in eastern Arkansas to support auto plants in other states.

Tourism is also very important to the Arkansas economy; the official state nickname &quot;The Natural State&quot; was originally created (as &quot;Arkansas Is A Natural&quot;) for state tourism advertising in the 1970s, and is still regularly used to this day.

According to Forbes.com&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.forbes.com/2007/07/10/washington-virginia-utah-biz-cz_kb_0711bizstates-table.html |title=Table: The Best States For Business |publisher=Forbes.com |date= July 11, 2007|accessdate=2010-07-30}}&lt;/ref&gt; Arkansas currently ranks 21st for The Best States for Business, 9th for Business Cost, 40th for Labor, 22nd for Regulatory Environment, 17th for Economic Climate, 9th for Growth Prospects, 34th in Gross Domestic Product, and positive economic change of 3.8% or ranked 22nd.

===Largest employers===
According to the [[Arkansas Economic Development Commission]], the following are the largest employers in Arkansas by number of in-state employees as of 2010:&lt;ref name=&quot;AEDC&quot;&gt;&quot;[http://www.arkansasedc.com/media/118399/arkansas%27%20largest%20employers.pdf Arkansas’ Largest Employers -- 2010]&quot; (August 2010). Arkansas Economic Development Commission, Research Division.&lt;/ref&gt;

{| class=&quot;wikitable&quot;
|-
! Rank
! Company
|-
| 1
| [[State of Arkansas]]
|-
| 2
| [[Wal-Mart Stores, Inc.]]
|-
| 3
| [[Federal government of the United States|Federal government]]
|-
| 4
| [[Tyson Foods|Tyson Foods, Inc.]]
|-
| 5
| [[Baptist Health]]
|-
| 6
| [[Acxiom Corporation]]
|-
| 7
| [[Arkansas Children's Hospital]]
|-
| 8
| [[J.B. Hunt Transport Services, Inc.]]
|-
| 9
| [[Sisters of Mercy Health System]]
|-
| 10
| [[The Kroger Company]]
|-
| 11
| [[Arvest Bank Group, Inc.]]
|-
| 12
| [[Community Health Systems, Inc.]]
|-
| 13
| [[Simmons Foods, Inc.]]
|-
| 14
| [[USA Truck, Inc.]]
|-
| 15
| [[Georgia-Pacific Corporation]]
|-
| 16
| [[Lowe's Companies, Inc.]]
|-
| 17
| [[St. Vincent Infirmary Medical Center]]
|-
| 18
| [[FedEx Corporation]]
|-
| 19
| [[Entergy Corporation]]
|-
| 20
| [[Verizon Communications, Inc.]] ([[Cellco Partnership]])
|-
| 21
| [[Union Pacific Railroad Company]]
|-
| 22
| [[Dillard's|Dillard's, Inc.]]
|-
| 23
| [[PAM Transportation Services, Inc.]]
|-
| 24
| [[Pilgrim’s Pride Corporation]]
|-
| 25
| [[AT&amp;T]]
|-
| 26
| [[Baldor Electric Company]]
|-
| 27
| [[United Parcel Service]]
|-
| 28
| [[St. Bernard's Medical Center]]
|-
| 29
| [[Dollar General|Dollar General Corporation]]
|-
| 30
| [[Arkansas Blue Cross &amp; Blue Shield]]
|-
| 31
| [[Whirlpool Corporation]]
|-
| 32
| [[George's, Inc.]]
|-
| 33
| [[Husqvarna Home Products]]
|-
| 34
| [[Sparks Health System]]
|-
| 35
| [[Dassault Aviation Group]]
|-
| 36
| [[OK Industries, Inc.]]
|-
| 37
| [[Jefferson Regional Medical Center]]
|-
| 38
| [[Harps Food Stores, Inc.]]
|-
| 39
| [[Walgreen Company]] 
|-
| 40
| [[University of Central Arkansas]]
|-
| 41
| [[Cooper Tire &amp; Rubber Company]]
|-
| 42
| [[Washington Regional Medical Center]]
|-
| 43
| [[JC Penney Company, Inc.]]
|-
| 44
| [[Nucor Corporation]]
|-
| 45
| [[The Heritage Company]]
|-
| 46 
| [[ConAgra Foods, Inc.]] 
|-
| 47
| [[Riceland Foods, Inc.]]
|-
| 48
| [[Home Depot, Inc.]]
|-
| 49
| [[McKee Foods Corporation]]
|-
| 50
| [[American Greetings Corporation]]
|}

The [[University of Arkansas for Medical Sciences]], including the [[UAMS Medical Center]], is included in the State of Arkansas' numbers, and would rank in the top ten if listed separately.&lt;ref name=&quot;AEDC&quot;/&gt;

===Aquaculture===

The state also ranks third in terms of [[channel catfish]] [[aquaculture]], with about {{convert|19200|acre|km2}} under catfish farming in 2010. The peak of catfish farming in the state was in the year 2002, when {{convert|38000|acre|km2}} were under farming.  In 2007, the state’s catfish producers generated sales of $71.5 million – 16 percent of the total U.S. market.&lt;ref&gt;[http://usda.mannlib.cornell.edu/usda/nass/CatfProd//2000s/2002/CatfProd-02-07-2002.pdf] from USDA NASS&lt;/ref&gt; Arkansas was the first state to develop commercial catfish farms in the late 1950s. The number of catfish farms in the state grew through the 1990s as farmers entered the catfish business as a way to provide additional income during a time of low prices for cotton and soybeans. Banks loaned money to support what they saw as a stable source of revenue.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.arfb.com/news_information/ark_agri/2008v5i2/catfish.aspx] Arkansas Farm Bureau Federation&lt;/ref&gt;

===Taxation===
[[File:Map of Arkansas.png|215px|thumb|right|A map of Arkansas with county boundaries drawn]]
Arkansas imposes a [[state income tax]] with six brackets, ranging from 1.0% to 7.0%. The first $9,000 of military pay of enlisted personnel is exempt from Arkansas tax; officers do not have to pay state income tax on the first $6,000 of their military pay. Retirees pay no tax on [[Social Security (United States)|Social Security]], or on the first $6,000 in gain on their pensions along with recovery of [[cost basis]]. Residents of [[Texarkana, Arkansas]] are exempt from Arkansas income tax; wages and business income earned there by residents of [[Texarkana, Texas]] are also exempt. Arkansas's gross receipts ([[sales tax|sales]]) tax and compensating ([[use tax|use]]) tax rate is currently 6%. The state has also mandated that various services be subject to sales tax collection. They include wrecker and towing services; dry cleaning and laundry; body piercing, tattooing and electrolysis; pest control; security and alarm monitoring; self-storage facilities; boat storage and docking; and pet grooming and kennel services.

Along with the state sales tax, there are more than 300 [[Tax|local taxes]] in Arkansas. Cities and counties have the authority to enact additional local sales and use taxes if they are passed by the voters in their area. These local taxes have a ceiling or cap; they cannot exceed $25 for each 1% of tax assessed. These additional taxes are collected by the state, which distributes the money back to the local jurisdictions monthly. Low-income taxpayers with a total annual household income of less than $12,000 are permitted a sales [[tax exemption]] for [[electricity]] usage.

Sales of [[alcoholic beverage]]s account for added taxes. A 10% supplemental mixed drink tax is imposed on the sale of alcoholic beverages (excluding [[beer]]) at [[restaurant]]s. A 4% tax is due on the sale of all [[mixed drink]]s (except beer and [[wine]]) sold for &quot;on-premises&quot; consumption. A 3% tax is due on beer sold for off-premises consumption.

[[Property tax]]es are assessed on real and personal property; only 20% of the value is used as the tax base.

==Transportation==
[[File:AR highways.png|right|thumb|200px|Arkansas depicting interstate and other major highways in 2009.]]
{{Main|Transportation of Arkansas}}
The [[List of Interstate Highways in Arkansas|Interstate Highway system in Arkansas]] includes

*[[Image:I-30 (AR).svg|23px]] [[Interstate 30]]
*[[Image:I-40 (AR).svg|23px]] [[Interstate 40]]
*[[Image:I-55 (AR).svg|23px]] [[Interstate 55]]
*[[Image:I-430 (AR).svg|27px]] [[Interstate 430]] Connector Route
*[[Image:I-440 (AR).svg|27px]] [[Interstate 440]] Connector Route
*[[Image:I-530 (AR).svg|27px]] [[Interstate 530]]
*[[Image:I-540 (AR).svg|27px]] [[Interstate 540]]
*[[Image:I-630 (AR).svg|27px]] [[Interstate 630]] Connector Route

Also Additional Future Interstate Highways in Arkansas under construction such as:

*[[Image:I-49 (AR).svg|23px]] [[Interstate 49]]
*[[Image:I-69 (AR).svg|23px]] [[Interstate 69]]
*[[Image:I-555 (AR).svg|27px]] [[Interstate 555]]





There are 20 [[List of U.S. Routes in Arkansas|U.S. Routes in Arkansas]], and over 200 [[List of Arkansas state highways|Arkansas state highways]].

There are four airports with commercial service: [[Little Rock National Airport]],
[[Northwest Arkansas Regional Airport]],
[[Fort Smith Regional Airport]], and
[[Texarkana Regional Airport]], with [[List of airports in Arkansas|dozens of smaller airports in the state]].  The [[Texas Eagle]], an Amtrak passenger train, serves five stations in the state:  [[Walnut Ridge (Amtrak station)|Walnut Ridge]],
[[Little Rock (Amtrak station)|Little Rock]],
[[Malvern (Amtrak station)|Malvern]],
[[Arkadelphia (Amtrak station)|Arkadelphia]], and
[[Texarkana (Amtrak station)|Texarkana]]. [[List of Arkansas railroads|About two dozen railroads]] carry freight in the state. Public transit and community transport services for the elderly or those with developmental disabilities are provided by agencies such as the [[Central Arkansas Transit Authority]] and the [[Ozark Regional Transit]], organizations that are part of the [[Arkansas Transit Association]].

==Law and government==
The current [[Governor of Arkansas]] is [[Mike Beebe]], a [[Democratic Party (United States)|Democrat]], who was elected on November 7, 2006.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://archive.stateline.org/weekly/Stateline.org-Weekly-Original-Content-2006-11-06.pdf |title=Winners in '06 Governors races |format=PDF |date= |accessdate=2010-07-30}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://dwe.arkansas.gov/GenIfo/administration.html |title=Arkansas.gov Administration page for Governor |publisher=Dwe.arkansas.gov |date=2007-03-16 |accessdate=2010-07-30}}&lt;/ref&gt;

One of Arkansas's U.S. Senators is Democrat [[Mark Pryor]], and the other one is Republican [[John Boozman]]. The state has four seats in [[United States House of Representatives|U.S. House of Representatives]]. One seat is held by Democrats: [[Mike Ross (politician)|Mike Ross]] ([http://nationalatlas.gov/printable/images/preview/congdist/ar04_109.gif map]), and three are held by Republicans: [[Rick Crawford (politician)]], ([http://nationalatlas.gov/printable/images/preview/congdist/ar01_109.gif map]), [[Tim Griffin]]([http://nationalatlas.gov/printable/images/preview/congdist/ar02_109.gif map]), and [[Steve Womack]]([http://nationalatlas.gov/printable/images/preview/congdist/ar03_109.gif map]).

{| class=&quot;wikitable&quot; style=&quot;float:right; font-size:92%;&quot;
|+ '''Presidential elections results'''
|- style=&quot;background:lightgrey;&quot;
! Year
! [[Republican Party (United States)|Republican]]
! [[Democratic Party (United States)|Democratic]]
|-
| style=&quot;text-align:center; background:#fff3f3;&quot;|[[U.S. presidential election, 2008|2008]]
| style=&quot;text-align:center; background:#fff3f3;&quot;|'''58.72%''' ''638,017
| style=&quot;text-align:center; background:#f0f0ff;&quot;|38.86% ''422,310
|-
| style=&quot;text-align:center; background:#fff3f3;&quot;|[[U.S. presidential election, 2004|2004]]
| style=&quot;text-align:center; background:#fff3f3;&quot;|'''54.31%''' ''572,898
| style=&quot;text-align:center; background:#f0f0ff;&quot;|44.55% ''469,953
|-
| style=&quot;text-align:center; background:#fff3f3;&quot;|[[U.S. presidential election, 2000|2000]]
| style=&quot;text-align:center; background:#fff3f3;&quot;|'''51.31%''' ''472,940
| style=&quot;text-align:center; background:#f0f0ff;&quot;|45.86% ''422,768
|-
| style=&quot;text-align:center; background:#f0f0ff;&quot;|[[U.S. presidential election, 1996|1996]]
| style=&quot;text-align:center; background:#fff3f3;&quot;|36.80% ''325,416
| style=&quot;text-align:center; background:#f0f0ff;&quot;|'''53.74%''' ''475,171
|-
| style=&quot;text-align:center; background:#f0f0ff;&quot;|[[U.S. presidential election, 1992|1992]]
| style=&quot;text-align:center; background:#fff3f3;&quot;|35.48% ''337,324
| style=&quot;text-align:center; background:#f0f0ff;&quot;|'''53.21%''' '' ''505,823
|-
| style=&quot;text-align:center; background:#fff3f3;&quot;|[[U.S. presidential election, 1988|1988]]
| style=&quot;text-align:center; background:#fff3f3;&quot;|'''56.37%''' ''466,578
| style=&quot;text-align:center; background:#f0f0ff;&quot;|42.19% ''349,237
|-
| style=&quot;text-align:center; background:#fff3f3;&quot;|[[U.S. presidential election, 1984|1984]]
| style=&quot;text-align:center; background:#fff3f3;&quot;|'''60.47%''' ''534,774
| style=&quot;text-align:center; background:#f0f0ff;&quot;|38.29% ''338,646
|-
| style=&quot;text-align:center; background:#fff3f3;&quot;|[[U.S. presidential election, 1980|1980]]
| style=&quot;text-align:center; background:#fff3f3;&quot;|'''48.13%''' ''403,164
| style=&quot;text-align:center; background:#f0f0ff;&quot;|47.52% ''398,041
|-
| style=&quot;text-align:center; background:#f0f0ff;&quot;|[[U.S. presidential election, 1976|1976]]
| style=&quot;text-align:center; background:#fff3f3;&quot;|34.93% ''268,753
| style=&quot;text-align:center; background:#f0f0ff;&quot;|'''64.94%''' ''499,614
|-
| style=&quot;text-align:center; background:#fff3f3;&quot;|[[U.S. presidential election, 1972|1972]]
| style=&quot;text-align:center; background:#fff3f3;&quot;|'''68.82%''' ''445,751
| style=&quot;text-align:center; background:#f0f0ff;&quot;|30.71% ''198,899
|-
| style=&quot;text-align:center; background:lightgrey;&quot;|[[U.S. presidential election, 1968|1968]]*
| style=&quot;text-align:center; background:#fff3f3;&quot;|31.01% ''189,062
| style=&quot;text-align:center; background:#f0f0ff;&quot;|30.33% ''184,901
|-
| style=&quot;text-align:center; background:#f0f0ff;&quot;|[[U.S. presidential election, 1964|1964]]
| style=&quot;text-align:center; background:#fff3f3;&quot;|43.41% ''243,264
| style=&quot;text-align:center; background:#f0f0ff;&quot;|'''56.06%''' ''314,197
|-
| style=&quot;text-align:center; background:#f0f0ff;&quot;|[[U.S. presidential election, 1960|1960]]
| style=&quot;text-align:center; background:#fff3f3;&quot;|43.06% ''184,508
| style=&quot;text-align:center; background:#f0f0ff;&quot;|'''50.19%''' ''215,049
|-
| colspan=&quot;3&quot; style=&quot;text-align:center; background:lightgrey;&quot;|*State won by [[George Wallace]]&lt;br/&gt;of the [[American Independent Party]],&lt;br/&gt;at 38.65%, or 235,627 votes
|}

The Democratic Party holds [[majority]] status in the [[Arkansas General Assembly]]. A majority of local and statewide offices are also held by Democrats. This is rare in the modern [[Southern United States|South]], where a majority of statewide offices are held by Republicans. Arkansas had the distinction in 1992 of being the only state in the country to give the majority of its vote to a single candidate in the presidential election—native son [[Bill Clinton]]—while every other state's electoral votes were won by pluralities of the vote among the three candidates. Arkansas has become more reliably Republican in presidential elections in recent years. The state voted for [[John McCain]] in 2008 by a margin of 20 percentage points, making it one of the few states in the country to vote more Republican than it had in 2004. (The others were Louisiana, Tennessee, Oklahoma and West Virginia.)&lt;ref&gt;http://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/5/54/Election-state-04-08.png&lt;/ref&gt; Obama's relatively poor showing in Arkansas was likely due to a lack of enthusiasm from state Democrats following former Arkansas First Lady [[Hillary Clinton]]'s failure to win the nomination{{Citation needed|date=July 2011}}, and his relatively poor performance among rural white voters. However, the Democratic presence remains strong on the state level; in 2006, Democrats were elected to all statewide offices by the voters in a Democratic sweep that included the [[Democratic Party of Arkansas]] regaining the governorship, and in 2008, freshman Senator Mark Pryor was re-elected with nearly 80% of the vote against Green candidate [[Rebekah Kennedy]] with no Republican opposition.{{Citation needed|old data?|date=July 2011}}

Most Republican strength lies mainly in the northwestern part of the state, particularly [[Fort Smith, Arkansas|Fort Smith]] and [[Bentonville, Arkansas|Bentonville]], as well as North Central Arkansas around the [[Mountain Home, Arkansas|Mountain Home]] area. In the latter area, Republicans have been known to get 90 percent or more of the vote. The rest of the state is more Democratic. Arkansas has only elected two Republicans to the U.S. Senate since [[Reconstruction era of the United States|Reconstruction]], [[Tim Hutchinson]], who was defeated after one term by [[Mark Pryor]] and [[John Boozman]], who defeated incumbent [[Blanche Lincoln]]. The General Assembly has not been controlled by the Republican Party since Reconstruction and is the fourth most heavily Democratic Legislature in the country, after [[Massachusetts General Court|Massachusetts]], [[Hawaii State Legislature|Hawaii]], and [[Connecticut General Assembly|Connecticut]]. Arkansas was one of just three states among the states of the former [[Confederate States of America|Confederacy]] that sent two Democrats to the U.S. Senate (the others being [[Florida]] and [[Virginia]]) during the first decade of the 21st century.

Although Democrats have an overwhelming majority of registered voters, Arkansas Democrats tend to be slightly more conservative than their national counterparts, particularly outside Little Rock. Arkansas' Democratic congressman is a member of the [[Blue Dog Coalition]], which tends to be more pro-business, pro-military, and socially conservative than the center-left Democratic mainstream. Reflecting the state's large evangelical population, the state has a strong social conservative bent. Under the [[Arkansas Constitution]] Arkansas is a [[right to work state]], its voters passed a ban on [[same-sex marriage]] with 75% voting yes, and the state is one of a handful with legislation on its books banning [[abortion]] in the event ''[[Roe v. Wade]]'' is ever overturned.

In Arkansas, the lieutenant governor is elected separately from the governor and thus can be from a different political party.

Each officer's term is four years long. Office holders are [[term-limited]] to two full terms plus any partial terms before the first full term. Arkansas governors served two-year terms until a referendum lengthened the term to four years, effective with the 1986 general election. Statewide elections are held two years after presidential elections.

Some of Arkansas's [[county (United States)|counties]] have two [[county seat]]s, as opposed to the usual one seat. The arrangement dates back to when travel was extremely difficult in the state. The seats are usually on opposite sides of the county. Though travel is no longer the difficulty it once was, there are few efforts to eliminate the two seat arrangement where it exists, since the county seat is a source of pride (and jobs) to the city involved.

Arkansas is the only state to specify the pronunciation of its name by law (AR-kan-saw).&lt;ref name=&quot;Arkansas&quot;/&gt;

Article 19 (Miscellaneous Provisions), Item 1 in the [[Arkansas Constitution]] is entitled &quot;Atheists disqualified from holding office or testifying as witness,&quot; and states that &quot;No person who denies the being of a God shall hold any office in the civil departments of this State, nor be competent to testify as a witness in any Court.&quot; However, in 1961, the [[United States Supreme Court]] in ''[[Torcaso v. Watkins]]'' (1961), held that a similar requirement in [[Maryland]] was unenforceable because violated the [[First Amendment to the United States Constitution|First]] and [[Fourteenth Amendment to the United States Constitution|Fourteenth]] Amendments to the US Constitution. The latter amendment, per current precedent, makes the [[United States Bill of Rights|federal Bill of Rights]] binding on the states. As a result, this provision has not been known to have been enforced in modern times, and it is understood that it would be struck down if challenged in court.
{{See also|List of Arkansas Governors|Political party strength in Arkansas}}

==Metropolitan areas==
The [[Little Rock-North Little Rock-Pine Bluff Combined Statistical Area]] had 877,091 people in the 2010 census. It is the largest in Arkansas.

The [[Fayetteville-Springdale-Rogers metropolitan area]] is increasingly important to the state and its economy. The US Census showed the population of the MSA to be 463,204 in 2010 (up from 347,045 in 2000), making it one of the fastest growing areas in the nation.

See also [[Arkansas Metropolitan Areas]].

'''Cities with 10,000 or More Residents as of 2010'''

{| class=&quot;wikitable&quot;
|-
! Rank
! City
! 2010 Pop.
! Region
|-
| 1. || [[Little Rock, Arkansas]]    || 193,524 || Central
|-
| 2. || [[Fort Smith, Arkansas]]     || 86,209  || Northwest
|-
| 3. || [[Fayetteville, Arkansas]]    || 73,580  || Northwest
|-
| 4. || [[Springdale, Arkansas]]     || 69,797  || Northwest
|-
| 5. || [[Jonesboro, Arkansas]]     || 67,263  || Northeast
|-
| 6. || [[North Little Rock, Arkansas]] || 62,304  || Central
|-
| 7. || [[Conway, Arkansas]]       || 58,908  || Central
|-
| 8. || [[Rogers, Arkansas]]       || 55,964  || Northwest
|-
| 9. || [[Pine Bluff, Arkansas]]     || 49,083  || Southeast
|-
| 10. || [[Bentonville, Arkansas]]    || 35,301  || Northwest
|-
| 11. || [[Hot Springs, Arkansas]]    || 35,193  || Southwest
|-
| 12. || [[Texarkana, Arkansas]]       || 30,681  || Southwest
|-
| 13. || [[Benton, Arkansas]]     || 29,919  || Central
|-
| 14. || [[Sherwood, Arkansas]]      || 29,523  || Central
|-
| 15. || [[Jacksonville, Arkansas]]    || 28,364  || Central
|-
| 16. || [[Russellville, Arkansas]]    || 27,920  || Northwest
|-
| 17. || [[Bella Vista, Arkansas]]    || 26,461  || Northwest
|-
| 18. || [[West Memphis, Arkansas]]    || 26,245  || Northeast
|-
| 19. || [[Paragould, Arkansas]]     || 26,113  || Northeast
|-
| 20. || [[Cabot, Arkansas]]       || 23,776  || Central
|-
| 21. || [[Searcy, Arkansas]]       || 22,858  || Central
|-
| 22. || [[Van Buren, Arkansas]]     || 22,791  || Northwest
|-
| 23. || [[El Dorado, Arkansas]]     || 18,884  || Southwest
|-
| 24. || [[Maumelle, Arkansas]]      || 17,163  || Central
|-
| 25. || [[Bryant, Arkansas]]       || 16,688  || Central
|-
| 26. || [[Blytheville, Arkansas]]    || 15,620  || Northeast
|-
| 27. || [[Forrest City, Arkansas]]    || 15,371  || Northeast
|-
| 28. || [[Siloam Springs, Arkansas]]   || 15,039  || Northwest
|-
| 29. || [[Harrison, Arkansas]]      || 12,943  || Northwest
|-
| 30. || [[Mountain Home, Arkansas]]   || 12,448  || Northwest
|-
| 31. || [[Marion, Arkansas]]       || 12,345  || Northeast
|-
| 32. || [[Helena-West Helena, Arkansas]] || 12,282  || Northeast
|-
| 33. || [[Camden, Arkansas]]       || 12,183  || Southwest
|-
| 34. || [[Magnolia, Arkansas]]      || 11,577  || Southwest
|-
| 35. || [[Arkadelphia, Arkansas]]    || 10,714  || Southwest
|-
| 36. || [[Malvern, Arkansas]]      || 10,318  || Southwest
|-
| 37. || [[Batesville, Arkansas]]     || 10,248  || Northeast
|-
| 38. || [[Hope, Arkansas]]        || 10,095  || Southwest
|}
These population numbers are according to the 2010 US Census.

==Cities and towns==
[[File:Littlerock.JPG|thumb|'''Little Rock''' is Arkansas' capital and most populous city]]
[[File:GarrisonFSM.jpg|thumb|'''Fort Smith''']]
[[File:Fay1.jpg|thumb|'''Fayetteville''']]
[[File:Downtown Camden, AR IMG 2234.JPG|thumb|'''Camden''']]
[[File:Downtown Magnolia, AR IMG 2313.JPG|thumb|'''Magnolia''']]
Names in '''bold''' have populations greater than 20,000.
{|
|-
| valign = top |
*[[Alma, Arkansas|Alma]]
*[[Alpena, Arkansas|Alpena]]
*[[Arkadelphia, Arkansas|Arkadelphia]]
*[[Avoca, Arkansas|Avoca]]
*[[Batesville, Arkansas|Batesville]]
*[[Bay, Arkansas|Bay]]
*[[Beech Grove, Arkansas|Beech Grove]]
*[[Beebe, Arkansas|Beebe]]
*[[Bella Vista, Arkansas|Bella Vista]]
*[[Bellefonte, Arkansas|Bellefonte]]
*'''[[Benton, Arkansas|Benton]]'''
*'''[[Bentonville, Arkansas|Bentonville]]'''
*[[Bergman, Arkansas|Bergman]]
*[[Berryville, Arkansas|Berryville]]
*[[Biggers, Arkansas|Biggers]]
*[[Black Oak, Arkansas|Black Oak]]
*[[Black Rock, Arkansas|Black Rock]]
*[[Blytheville, Arkansas|Blytheville]]
*[[Bono, Arkansas|Bono]]
*[[Booneville, Arkansas|Booneville]]
*[[Bryant, Arkansas|Bryant]]
*[[Brookland, Arkansas|Brookland]]
*'''[[Cabot, Arkansas|Cabot]]'''
*[[Camden, Arkansas|Camden]]
*[[Caraway, Arkansas|Caraway]]
*[[Cash, Arkansas|Cash]]
*'''[[Conway, Arkansas|Conway]]'''
*[[Clinton, Arkansas|Clinton]]
*[[College City, Arkansas|College City]]
*[[Corning, Arkansas|Corning]]
*[[Cotter, Arkansas|Cotter]]
*[[Crossett, Arkansas|Crossett]]
*[[Delaplaine, Arkansas|Delaplaine]]
*[[Dell, Arkansas|Dell]]
*[[DeQueen, Arkansas|DeQueen]]
*[[De Witt, Arkansas|De Witt]]
*[[Diamond City, Arkansas|Diamond City]]
*[[Earle, Arkansas|Earle]]
*'''[[El Dorado, Arkansas|El Dorado]]'''
*[[Egypt, Arkansas|Egypt]]
*[[Eureka Springs, Arkansas|Eureka Springs]]
*[[Everton, Arkansas|Everton]]
*'''[[Fayetteville, Arkansas|Fayetteville]]'''
*[[Forrest City, Arkansas|Forrest City]]
*'''[[Fort Smith, Arkansas|Fort Smith]]'''
*[[Flippin, Arkansas|Flippin]]
*[[Gassville, Arkansas|Gassville]]
*[[Greenwood, Arkansas|Greenwood]]
*[[Grubbs, Arkansas|Grubbs]]
*[[Gurdon, Arkansas|Gurdon]]
| valign = top |
*[[Harrison, Arkansas|Harrison]]
*[[Horatio, Arkansas|Horatio]]
*[[Helena-West Helena, Arkansas|Helena-West Helena]]
*[[Hope, Arkansas|Hope]]
*'''[[Hot Springs, Arkansas|Hot Springs]]'''
*[[Hoxie, Arkansas|Hoxie]]
*[[Imboden, Arkansas|Imboden]]
*[[Jasper, Arkansas|Jasper]]
*'''[[Jacksonville, Arkansas|Jacksonville]]'''
*'''[[Jonesboro, Arkansas|Jonesboro]]'''
*[[Lafe, Arkansas|Lafe]]
*[[Lake City, Arkansas|Lake City]]
*[[Lake Village, Arkansas|Lake Village]]
*[[Leachville, Arkansas|Leachville]]
*[[Lead Hill, Arkansas|Lead Hill]]
*'''[[Little Rock, Arkansas|Little Rock]]'''
*[[Lonoke, Arkansas|Lonoke]]
*[[Lockesburg, Arkansas|Lockesburg]]
*[[Magnolia, Arkansas|Magnolia]]
*[[Malvern, Arkansas|Malvern]]
*[[Marion, Arkansas|Marion]]
*[[Marked Tree, Arkansas|Marked Tree]]
*[[Maumelle, Arkansas|Maumelle]]
*[[Mena, Arkansas|Mena]]
*[[Midway, Arkansas|Midway]]
*[[Monticello, Arkansas|Monticello]]
*[[Morrilton, Arkansas|Morrilton]]
*[[Monette, Arkansas|Monette]]
*[[Mountain Home, Arkansas|Mountain Home]]
*[[Mountain View, Arkansas|Mountain View]]
*[[Natural Steps, Arkansas|Natural Steps]]
*[[Newport, Arkansas|Newport]]
*'''[[North Little Rock, Arkansas|North Little Rock]]'''
*[[Omaha, Arkansas|Omaha]]
*[[Osceola, Arkansas|Osceola]]
*[[Otwell, Arkansas|Otwell]]
*'''[[Paragould, Arkansas|Paragould]]'''
*[[Parkin, Arkansas|Parkin]]
*'''[[Pine Bluff, Arkansas|Pine Bluff]]'''
*[[Pleasant Hill, Arkansas|Pleasant Hill]]
*[[Pocahontas, Arkansas|Pocahontas]]
*[[Pyatt, Arkansas|Pyatt]]
*[[Ravenden, Arkansas|Ravenden]]
*[[Ravenden Springs, Arkansas|Ravenden Springs]]
*[[Rea Valley, Arkansas|Rea Valley]]
*'''[[Rogers, Arkansas|Rogers]]'''
*'''[[Russellville, Arkansas|Russellville]]'''
*'''[[Searcy, Arkansas|Searcy]]'''
*'''[[Sherwood, Arkansas|Sherwood]]'''
*[[Sheridan, Arkansas|Sheridan]]
| valign = top |
*[[Siloam Springs, Arkansas|Siloam Springs]]
*[[Smackover, Arkansas|Smackover]]
*'''[[Springdale, Arkansas|Springdale]]'''
*[[South Lead Hill, Arkansas|South Lead Hill]]
*[[Stuttgart, Arkansas|Stuttgart]]
*[[Summit, Arkansas|Summit]]
*[[Swifton, Arkansas|Swifton]]
*'''[[Texarkana, Arkansas|Texarkana]]'''
*[[Trumann, Arkansas|Trumann]]
*[[Tuckerman, Arkansas|Tuckerman]]
*[[Valley Springs, Arkansas|Valley Springs]]
*'''[[Van Buren, Arkansas|Van Buren]]'''
*[[Waldron, Arkansas|Waldron]]
*[[Walnut Ridge, Arkansas|Walnut Ridge]]
*[[Warren, Arkansas|Warren]]
*'''[[West Memphis, Arkansas|West Memphis]]'''
*[[Weiner, Arkansas|Weiner]]
*[[Western Grove, Arkansas|Western Grove]]
*[[Wynne, Arkansas|Wynne]]
*[[Yardelle, Arkansas|Yardelle]]
*[[Yellville, Arkansas|Yellville]]
*[[Zinc, Arkansas|Zinc]]
|}

==Education==
===Public school districts===
*[[List of school districts in Arkansas]]

===Centers of research===
*[[National Center for Toxicological Research]]
*[[University of Arkansas Division of Agriculture]]

===Colleges and universities===
[[File:Astate.jpg|thumb|right|[[Arkansas State University]], Jonesboro.]]
*[[Arkansas Baptist College]]
*[[Arkansas State University System]]
**[[Arkansas State University|Arkansas State University – Jonesboro]]
**[[Arkansas State University Beebe]]
**[[Arkansas State University - Mountain Home]]
*[[Arkansas Tech University]]
*[[Central Baptist College]]
*[[Harding University]]
*[[Henderson State University]]
*[[Hendrix College]]
*[[John Brown University]]
*[[Lyon College]]
*[[Ouachita Baptist University]]
*[[Ozarka College]]
*[[Philander Smith College]]
*[[Southern Arkansas University]]
[[File:UAMS 2.jpg|frame|[[University of Arkansas for Medical Sciences|UAMS]] is the flagship health education institution of the state.]]
*[[University of Arkansas System]]
**[[University of Arkansas at Fayetteville]]
**[[University of Arkansas at Fort Smith]]
**[[University of Arkansas at Little Rock]]
**[[University of Arkansas for Medical Sciences]]
**[[University of Arkansas at Monticello]]
**[[University of Arkansas at Pine Bluff]]
**[[University of Arkansas Community College at Batesville]]
**[[University of Arkansas Community College at Morrilton]]
*[[University of Central Arkansas]]
*[[University of the Ozarks]]
*[[Williams Baptist College]]

==Notable residents==
{{div col|4}}
* [[Joey Lauren Adams]]
* [[Homer M. Adkins]]
* [[William Vollie Alexander, Jr.|Bill Alexander]]
* [[Dale Alford]]
* [[Kris Allen]]
* [[Maya Angelou]]
* [[Beryl Anthony]]
* [[Morris Arnold]]
* [[Harry Ashmore]]
* [[Wayne H. Babbitt]]
* [[Gilbert Baker (Arkansas politician)|Gilbert Baker]]
* [[Daisy Bates (civil rights activist)|Daisy Bates]]
* [[Bruce Bennett (Arkansas politician)|Bruce Bennett]]
* [[Robert Marion Berry]]
* [[Edwin R. Bethune]]
* [[Len Blaylock]]
* [[Brian Bohrer]]
* [[Fay Boozman]]
* [[John Boozman]]
* [[Vickey Boozman]]
* [[Henry M. Britt]]
* [[Maurice L. Britt]]
* [[Lou Brock]]
* [[Frank Broyles]]
* [[Dee Brown (writer)|Dee Brown]]
* [[Helen Gurley Brown]]
* [[Paul &quot;Bear&quot; Bryant]]
* [[Dale Bumpers]]
* [[Preston Bynum]]
* [[Glen Campbell]]
* [[Hattie Caraway]]
* [[Johnny Cash]]
* [[Francis Cherry]]
* [[Norris Church]] (Barbara Jean Davis)
* [[Wesley Clark]]
* [[Jerry Climer]]
* [[Bill Clinton]]
* [[Chelsea Clinton]]
* [[L. L. Clover]]
* [[Ken Coon]]
* [[James Cotten]]
* [[Maud Crawford]]
* [[Fulham Davies]]
* [[Lynn A. Davis]]
* [[Dizzy Dean|&quot;Dizzy&quot; Dean]]
* [[Gauge (person)|Elizabeth R. Deans]]
* [[Bill Dickey]]
* [[Jay Dickey]]
* [[Beth Ditto]]
* [[David O. Dodd]]
* [[Jimmy Driftwood]]
* [[Duggar family]]
* [[Jimmy Dykes]]
* [[Orval Faubus]]
* [[Derek Fisher]]
* [[John Gould Fletcher]]
* [[Connie Franklin murder case|Connie Franklin]]
* [[Woody Freeman]]
* [[J. William Fulbright]]
* [[Augustus Garland]]
* [[Tyson Gay]]
* [[David Delano Glover]]
* [[Robert W. Glover]]
* [[Leon Griffith]]
* [[John Grisham]]
* [[E. Lynn Harris]]
* [[John Paul Hammerschmidt]]
* [[Ronnie Hawkins]]
* [[Brooks Hays]]
* [[Levon Helm]]
* [[Ernest Hemingway]]
* [[Kim Hendren]]
* [[Peyton Hillis]]
* [[Harlan Holleman]]
* [[Mike Huckabee]]
* [[Johnnie Bryan Hunt]]
* [[Torii Hunter]]
* [[Asa Hutchinson]]
* [[Tim Hutchinson]]
* [[Joe Jackson (manager)|Joe Jackson]]
* [[Keith Jackson (tight end)|Keith Jackson]]
* [[Travis Jackson]]
* [[James D. Johnson|James Douglas &quot;Justice Jim&quot; Johnson]]
* [[Joe Johnson (basketball)|Joe Johnson]]
* [[John H. Johnson]]
* [[Virginia Johnson (Arkansas)|Virginia Morris Johnson]]
* [[Jerry Jones]]
* [[Scott Joplin]]
* [[Jim Keet]]
* [[George Kell]]
* [[Larry Lacewell]]
* [[Alan Ladd]]
* [[Benjamin T. Laney]]
* [[Marjorie Lawrence]]
* [[Amy Lee]]
* [[Cliff Lee]]
* [[Blanche Lambert Lincoln]]
* [[Jim Lindsey]]
* [[Sonny Liston]]
* [[Lynn Lowe|A. Lynn Lowe]]
* [[Josh Lucas]]
* [[Douglas MacArthur]]
* [[Charlotte Mailliard]]
* [[Mark Martin (racecar driver)|Mark Martin]]
* [[John L. McClellan]]
* [[Hayes McClerkin]]
* [[James S. McDonnell]]
* [[Jim McDougal|James McDougall]]
* [[Darren McFadden]]
* [[Sid McMath]]
* [[Ada Mills]]
* [[Wilbur Mills]]
* [[Martha Beall Mitchell]]
* [[Ben Moody]]
* [[Justin Moore (singer)|Justin Moore]]
* [[Jonathan Moreira]]
* [[Joe Nichols]]
* [[Sheffield Nelson]]
* [[Robert Palmer (writer)|Robert Palmer]]
* [[Bobby Petrino]]
* [[Judy Petty Wolf]]
* [[Albert Pike]]
* [[Scottie Pippen]]
* [[Odell Pollard]]
* [[Charles Portis]]
* [[Dick Powell]]
* [[A. T. Powers]]
* [[David H. Pryor]]
* [[Mark Pryor]]
* [[Joe Purcell]]
* [[Pratt Remmel]]
* [[Willis Ricketts]]
* [[Thomas Robb]]
* [[Brooks Robinson]]
* [[Joseph T. Robinson]]
* [[Tommy F. Robinson]]
* [[Winthrop Rockefeller]]
* [[Winthrop Paul Rockefeller]]
* [[Mike Ross (politician)|Mike Ross]]
* [[Monroe Schwarzlose]]
* [[Shaffer Smith]]
* [[John W. Snyder]]
* [[Jefferson W. Speck]]
* [[Sir Henry Morton Stanley]]
* [[Mary Steenburgen]]
* [[Edward Durell Stone]]
* [[Pat Summerall]]
* [[Barry Switzer]]
* [[Jermain Taylor]]
* [[Jerry Thomasson]]
* [[Billy Bob Thornton]]
* [[Leona Troxell]]
* [[Jim Guy Tucker]]
* [[Don Tyson]]
* [[C. Vann Woodward]]
* [[Arky Vaughan]]
* [[Ehron VonAllen]]
* [[Sam Walton]]
* [[Joseph H. Weston]]
* [[Frank D. White]]
* [[Travis Wood]]
* [[Archibald Yell]]
{{div col end}}

==See also==
{{satop|Geography|North America|Northern America|United States|Arkansas}}
*[[National Register of Historic Places listings in Arkansas|List of National Register of Historic Places in Arkansas]]
*[[List of people from Arkansas]]
*[[List of places in Arkansas]]
*[[U.S. state]]
{{clear}}

==References==
{{reflist|2}}

==Further reading==
{{Refbegin}}
*Blair, Diane D. &amp; Jay Barth ''Arkansas Politics &amp; Government: Do the People Rule?'' (2005)
*Deblack, Thomas A. ''With Fire and Sword: Arkansas, 1861–1874'' (2003)
*Donovan, Timothy P. and Willard B. Gatewood Jr., eds. ''The Governors of Arkansas'' (1981)
*Dougan, Michael B. ''Confederate Arkansas'' (1982),
*Duvall, Leland. ed., ''Arkansas: Colony and State'' (1973)
*Fletcher, John Gould. ''Arkansas'' (1947)
*[http://books.google.com/books?ie=UTF-8&amp;vid=LCCN04001664&amp;id=dvMZ_YNpYrYC&amp;pg=PP16&amp;lpg=PP16&amp;dq=peter+joseph+hamilton+reconstruction+period Hamilton, Peter Joseph. ''The Reconstruction Period''] (1906), full length history of era; [[Dunning School]] approach; 570 pp; ch 13 on Arkansas
*Hanson, Gerald T. and Carl H. Moneyhon. ''Historical Atlas of Arkansas'' (1992)
*Key, V. O. ''Southern Politics'' (1949)
*Kirk, John A., ''Redefining the Color Line: Black Activism in Little Rock, Arkansas, 1940–1970'' (2002).
*McMath, Sidney S. ''Promises Kept'' (2003)
*Moore, Waddy W. ed., ''Arkansas in the Gilded Age, 1874–1900'' (1976).
*Peirce, Neal R. ''The Deep South States of America: People, Politics, and Power in the Seven Deep South States'' (1974)\
*Thompson, Brock. ''The Un-Natural State: Arkansas and the Queer South'' (2010)
*Thompson, George H. ''Arkansas and Reconstruction'' (1976)
*Whayne, Jeannie M. et al. ''Arkansas: A Narrative History '' (2002)
*Whayne, Jeannie M. ''Arkansas Biography: A Collection of Notable Lives'' (2000)
*White, Lonnie J. ''Politics on the Southwestern Frontier: Arkansas Territory, 1819–1836'' (1964)
*Williams, C. Fred. ed. ''A Documentary History Of Arkansas'' (2005)
*WPA., ''Arkansas: A Guide to the State'' (1941)
{{Refend}}

==External links==
{{Sister project links|Arkansas}}
{{osmrelation|161646}}
*[http://www.arkansas.gov Official State website]
*[http://www.arkleg.state.ar.us/data/ar_code.asp Arkansas State Code (the state statutes of Arkansas)]
*[http://wikis.ala.org/godort/index.php/Arkansas Arkansas State Databases] – Annotated list of searchable databases produced by Arkansas state agencies and compiled by the Government Documents Roundtable of the American Library Association.
*[http://www.ers.usda.gov/statefacts/ar.htm Arkansas State Facts]
*[http://www.arkansas.com Official State tourism website]
*[http://www.encyclopediaofarkansas.net/ The Encyclopedia of Arkansas History &amp; Culture]
*[http://tonto.eia.doe.gov/state/state_energy_profiles.cfm?sid=AR Energy &amp; Environmental Data for Arkansas]
*[http://quickfacts.census.gov/qfd/states/05000.html U.S. Census Bureau]
* [http://www2.census.gov/census_2000/datasets/demographic_profile/Arkansas/2kh05.pdf 2000 Census of Population and Housing for Arkansas], [[U.S. Census Bureau]]
*[http://www.usgs.gov/state/state.asp?State=AR USGS real-time, geographic, and other scientific resources of Arkansas]
*{{Ballotpedia|Arkansas|Arkansas}}
*{{Judgepedia|Arkansas|Arkansas}}
*{{Sunshine|Arkansas|Arkansas}}
*{{dmoz|Regional/North_America/United_States/Arkansas}}

{{-}}
{{Geographic location
|Centre    = Arkansas
|North     = [[Missouri]]
|Northeast = [[Tennessee]]
|East      = [[Mississippi]]
|Southeast =
|South     = [[Louisiana]]
|Southwest = [[Texas]]
|West      = [[Oklahoma]]
|Northwest =
}}

{{Template group
| list =
{{Arkansas|expanded}}
{{United States}}
{{Confederate States of America}}

{{succession
| preceded = [[Missouri]]
| office = [[List of U.S. states by date of statehood]]
| years = Admitted on June 15, 1836 (25th)
| succeeded = [[Michigan]]
}}
}}

{{Coord|34.8|N|92.2|W|region:US-AR_type:adm1st_scale:3000000|display=title}}
{{United States topics}}

[[Category:Arkansas| ]]
[[Category:States of the United States]]
[[Category:States of the Confederate States of America]]
[[Category:States and territories established in 1836]]
[[Category:States of the Southern United States]]

[[af:Arkansas]]
[[ang:Arkansas]]
[[ar:أركنساس]]
[[an:Arkansas]]
[[arc:ܐܪܟܢܣܐܣ]]
[[frp:Arkansas]]
[[ast:Arkansas]]
[[gn:Arkansas]]
[[az:Arkanzas]]
[[bn:আর্কান্‌স]]
[[zh-min-nan:Arkansas]]
[[be:Штат Арканзас]]
[[be-x-old:Арканзас]]
[[bcl:Arkansas]]
[[bi:Arkansas]]
[[bo:ཨར་ཁན་སཱ་སི།]]
[[bs:Arkansas]]
[[br:Arkansas]]
[[bg:Арканзас]]
[[ca:Arkansas]]
[[cv:Арканзас]]
[[cs:Arkansas]]
[[co:Arkansas]]
[[cy:Arkansas]]
[[da:Arkansas]]
[[de:Arkansas]]
[[nv:Áákinsoo Hahoodzo]]
[[et:Arkansas]]
[[el:Αρκάνσας]]
[[es:Arkansas]]
[[eo:Arkansaso]]
[[eu:Arkansas]]
[[fa:آرکانزاس]]
[[hif:Arkansas]]
[[fo:Arkansas]]
[[fr:Arkansas]]
[[fy:Arkansas]]
[[ga:Arkansas]]
[[gv:Arkansas]]
[[gag:Arkansas]]
[[gd:Arkansas]]
[[gl:Arcansas]]
[[gu:અરકાનસાસ]]
[[hak:Â-khén-set]]
[[xal:Әркәнзә]]
[[ko:아칸소 주]]
[[haw:‘Akanaka]]
[[hy:Արկանզաս (նահանգ)]]
[[hi:अरकांसास]]
[[hr:Arkansas]]
[[io:Arkansas]]
[[ig:Arkinsọ]]
[[bpy:আরকান্‌সাস]]
[[id:Arkansas]]
[[ia:Arkansas]]
[[ie:Arkansas]]
[[ik:Arkansas]]
[[os:Арканзас]]
[[is:Arkansas]]
[[it:Arkansas]]
[[he:ארקנסו]]
[[jv:Arkansas]]
[[kn:ಅರ್ಕಾನ್ಸಾಸ್]]
[[pam:Arkansas]]
[[ka:არკანზასი]]
[[kw:Arkansas]]
[[sw:Arkansas]]
[[ht:Akennsas (eta)]]
[[ku:Arkansas]]
[[lad:Arkansas]]
[[la:Arcansia]]
[[lv:Ārkanzasa]]
[[lb:Arkansas]]
[[lt:Arkanzasas]]
[[lij:Arkansas]]
[[li:Arkansas]]
[[lmo:Arkansas]]
[[hu:Arkansas]]
[[mk:Арканзас]]
[[mg:Arkansas]]
[[ml:അർക്കൻസാസ്]]
[[mi:Arkansas]]
[[mr:आर्कान्सा]]
[[arz:اركنساس]]
[[ms:Arkansas]]
[[mn:Арканзас]]
[[nah:Arkansas]]
[[mrj:Арканзас]]
[[nl:Arkansas (staat)]]
[[nds-nl:Arkansas (stoat)]]
[[ja:アーカンソー州]]
[[frr:Arkansas]]
[[no:Arkansas]]
[[nn:Arkansas]]
[[oc:Arkansas]]
[[uz:Arkanzas]]
[[pnb:آرکانساس]]
[[pap:Arkansas]]
[[pms:Arkansas]]
[[nds:Arkansas]]
[[pl:Arkansas]]
[[pt:Arkansas]]
[[ro:Arkansas]]
[[rm:Arkansas]]
[[qu:Arkansas suyu]]
[[ru:Арканзас]]
[[sah:Арканзас]]
[[sa:अर्कान्स]]
[[sq:Arkansas]]
[[scn:Arkansas]]
[[simple:Arkansas]]
[[sk:Arkansas]]
[[sl:Arkansas]]
[[szl:Arkansas]]
[[ckb:ئارکانساس]]
[[sr:Арканзас]]
[[sh:Arkansas]]
[[fi:Arkansas]]
[[sv:Arkansas]]
[[tl:Arkansas]]
[[ta:ஆர்கன்சா]]
[[tt:Арканзас]]
[[te:ఆర్కాన్సా]]
[[th:รัฐอาร์คันซอ]]
[[tr:Arkansas]]
[[uk:Арканзас]]
[[ur:آرکنساس]]
[[ug:Arkanzas Shtati]]
[[vi:Arkansas]]
[[vo:Arkansas]]
[[war:Arkansas]]
[[yi:ארקענסא]]
[[yo:Arkansas]]
[[zh-yue:阿肯色州]]
[[diq:Arkansas]]
[[bat-smg:Arkanzasos]]
[[zh:阿肯色州]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
