<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="193303" ns="0" title="Ira Hayes"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Infobox military person
|name= Ira Hamilton Hayes
|birth_date= {{Birth date|1923|01|12}}
|death_date= {{death date and age|1955|01|24|1923|01|23}}
|birth_place= [[Sacaton, Arizona]], United States
|death_place= Sacaton, Arizona, United States
|placeofburial= [[Arlington National Cemetery]], Section 34
|placeofburial_label= Place of burial
|image= [[File:Ira Hayes.jpg|150px]]
|nickname= Chief Falling Cloud
|allegiance={{flagicon|United States}} [[United States|United States of America]]
|branch=[[File:Marine corps flag.svg|25px]] [[United States Marine Corps]]
|serviceyears= 1942-1945
|rank= [[Corporal#United States|Corporal]]
|unit=[[Paramarines|3rd Parachute Battalion]]&lt;br/&gt;[[2nd Battalion, 28th Marines]]&lt;br/&gt;1st Headquarters Battalion, [[Headquarters Marine Corps|HQMC]]
|battles= [[World War II]]
*[[Battle of Vella Gulf]]
*[[Bougainville campaign (1944-45)|Bougainville Campaign]]
*[[Battle of Iwo Jima]]
}}
&lt;div class=&quot;floatright&quot;&gt;
{|
|- valign=&quot;top&quot;
|}
&lt;/div&gt;
'''Ira Hamilton Hayes''' (January 12, 1923 – January 24, 1955) was a [[Pima]] [[Indigenous peoples of the Americas|Native American]] and an [[United States|American]] [[United States Marine Corps|Marine]] who was one of the six men immortalized in the iconic photograph of the [[Raising the Flag on Iwo Jima|flag raising on Iwo Jima]] during [[World War II]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |url = http://www.irishtimes.com/newspaper/opinion/2006/0901/1156791312212.html |title = An Irishman's Diary |last = Ó'Riain |first = Seán |publisher = The Irish Times |date = 2006-09-01}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url = http://hqinet001.hqmc.usmc.mil/HD/Historical/Whos_Who/Hayes_IH.htm |title = Corporal Ira Hamilton Hayes, USMCR |work=Who's Who in Marine Corps History|publisher = History Division, United States Marine Corps |accessdate = 2006-09-01}}&lt;/ref&gt; Hayes was an enrolled member of the [[Gila River Indian Community]] in [[Sacaton, Arizona]], and enlisted in the [[Marine Forces Reserve]] on August 24, 1942. He trained as a [[Paramarine]] and saw action in the [[Pacific War|Pacific Theatre]] of World War II. On February 19, 1945, Hayes participated in the landing at [[Iwo Jima]] and fought in the subsequent [[Battle of Iwo Jima|battle for the island]]. On February 23, Hayes, together with fellow Marines [[Rene Gagnon]], [[Harlon Block]], [[Franklin Sousley]], and [[Mike Strank]], and Navy Corpsman [[John Bradley (Navy)|John Bradley]], raised the American flag over [[Mount Suribachi]], an event photographed by [[Joe Rosenthal]].

As a result of Rosenthal's photograph, Hayes and the others became national heroes in the United States. He was instrumental in confirming the identity of one of his fellow Marines in the photograph, Harlon Block. Hayes was never comfortable with his new-found fame, however, and after his honorable discharge from the Marine Corps he descended into alcoholism. He died of exposure and alcohol poisoning on January 24, 1955 after a night of drinking, and was buried with full military honors at [[Arlington National Cemetery]].

Hayes was often commemorated in art and film, both before and after his death. He is depicted in the [[Marine Corps War Memorial]] at Arlington National Cemetery, based on the famous photograph, and he portrayed himself in the 1949 film ''[[Sands of Iwo Jima]]''. His tragic story was the subject of the 1961 film ''[[The Outsider (1961 film)|The Outsider]]'', and inspired [[Peter La Farge]]'s song &quot;[[The Ballad of Ira Hayes]]&quot;. He was also depicted in the 2006 film ''[[Flags of Our Fathers]]''.

==Early life==
Hayes was born in [[Sacaton, Arizona]], a town located in the [[Gila River Indian Community]] in [[Pinal County, Arizona|Pinal County]], the first of six children to Nancy Hamilton (1901–1972) and Joseph Hayes (1887–1978).&lt;ref name= &quot;Bradley-Powers p. 38&quot;&gt;{{harvnb|Bradley|Powers|2006|p=38}}&lt;/ref&gt;  The Hayes children were: Ira (1923–1955), Harold (1924–1925), Arlene (1926–1929), Leonard (1927–1952), Vernon (1929–1958), and Kenneth (born 1931).&lt;ref name= &quot;Bradley-Powers p. 38&quot;/&gt;

Joseph Hayes was a [[World War I]] veteran who supported his family by [[subsistence agriculture|subsistence farming]] and cotton harvesting.&lt;ref name= &quot;Bradley-Powers p. 39&quot;&gt;{{harvnb|Bradley|Powers|2006|p=39}}&lt;/ref&gt; Nancy Hayes was a devout [[Presbyterianism|Presbyterian]] and a [[Sunday school]] teacher at the [[Assemblies of God]] church in Sacaton.&lt;ref name= &quot;Bradley-Powers p. 39&quot;/&gt; 

As a child, Hayes was remembered as being shy and sensitive by his family and friends. Sara Bernal, his first cousin, stated, &quot;[Joseph Hayes] was a very quiet man, he would go days without saying anything unless you spoke to him first. The other Hayes children would play and tease me, but not Ira. He was quiet, and somewhat distant. Ira didn't speak unless spoken to. He was just like his father.&quot;&lt;ref name= &quot;Bradley-Powers pp. 39-41&quot;&gt;{{harvnb|Bradley|Powers|2006|pp=39–41}}&lt;/ref&gt; His boyhood friend Dana Norris stated, &quot;Even though I'm from the same culture, I could never get under his skin. Ira had the characteristic of not wanting to talk. But we Pimas are not prone to tooting our own horns. Ira was a quiet guy, such a quiet guy.&quot;&lt;ref name= &quot;Bradley-Powers pp. 39-41&quot;/&gt; Despite this, Hayes was a precocious child who displayed an impressive grasp of the [[English language]], a language many Pimas did not know how to speak.&lt;ref name= &quot;Bradley-Powers p. 39&quot;/&gt; He was also a voracious reader, learning how to read and write by age four.&lt;ref name= &quot;Bradley-Powers p. 39&quot;/&gt;
[[File:Pfc. Ira H. Hayes, a Pima, at age 19, ready to jump, Marine Corps Paratroop School, 1943 - NARA - 519164.tif|thumb|Pfc. Ira H. Hayes, a Pima, at age 19, ready to jump, Marine Corps Paratroop School, 1943]]
In 1932, the family settled in [[Bapchule, Arizona]], located approximately 12 miles northwest of Sacaton.&lt;ref name= &quot;Bradley-Powers p. 39&quot;/&gt; The Hayes children attended grade school in Sacaton and high school at the Phoenix Indian School in [[Phoenix, Arizona]]. Esther Monahan, one of his classmates, stated, &quot;Ira wasn't like the other guys. He was shy and never talked to us girls. He was so much more shy than the other Pima boys. The girls would chase him and try to hug him and kiss him, like we did with all the boys. We'd catch the other boys, who enjoyed it. But not Ira. Ira would just run away.&quot;&lt;ref name= &quot;Bradley-Powers p. 41&quot;&gt;{{harvnb|Bradley|Powers|2006|p=41}}&lt;/ref&gt; After the [[attack on Pearl Harbor]] in [[Hawaii]], Ira confided to his classmate Eleanor Pasquale that he was determined on serving in the [[United States Marine Corps]].&lt;ref name= &quot;Bradley-Powers p. 41&quot;/&gt; Pasquale stated, &quot;Every morning in school, [the students] would get a report on [[World War II]]. We would sing the anthems of the [[United States Army|Army]], Marines, and the [[United States Navy|Navy]].&quot;&lt;ref name= &quot;Bradley-Powers pp. 41-42&quot;&gt;{{harvnb|Bradley|Powers|2006|pp=41–42}}&lt;/ref&gt; In June 1942, Hayes graduated at the Phoenix Indian School and returned to the reservation. 

On August 24, 1942, Hayes enlisted in the [[Marine Forces Reserve]] at age nineteen.&lt;ref name= &quot;Bradley-Powers p. 42&quot;&gt;{{harvnb|Bradley|Powers|2006|p=42}}&lt;/ref&gt;

After he completed [[recruit training]] at [[Marine Corps Recruit Depot San Diego]], [[California]], Hayes trained as a [[paratrooper]] at [[Marine Corps Base San Diego]] and had a codename of ''Chief Falling Cloud''. On December 2, 1942, he joined Company B, 3rd Parachute Battalion, Divisional Special Troops, [[U.S. 3rd Marine Division]], at [[Camp Elliott]], [[California]]. On March 14, 1943, Hayes sailed for [[New Caledonia]] with the 3rd Parachute Battalion. Hayes first saw combat in the [[Bougainville Campaign]]. 

The Marine Corps parachute units were disbanded in February, and Hayes was transferred to Company E, [[2nd Battalion, 28th Marines]], [[U.S. 5th Marine Division]] at [[Camp Pendleton]], [[California]]. In September 1944, Hayes sailed to [[Hawaii]] for further training.

===Battle of Iwo Jima===
[[File:Raising the Flag outline.png|thumb|Hayes is pictured to the far left]]

On February 19, 1945, Hayes took part in the landing on [[Battle of Iwo Jima|Iwo Jima]]. He participated in the battle for the island and was among the group of Marines that took [[Mount Suribachi]] five days later on February 23, 1945.

The [[Raising the Flag on Iwo Jima|raising of the second American flag on Suribachi]] by five Marines: Ira Hayes, [[Rene Gagnon]], [[Harlon Block]], [[Franklin Sousley]], and [[Mike Strank]], and a Navy Corpsman, [[John Bradley (Navy)|John Bradley]], was immortalized by photographer [[Joe Rosenthal]] and became an icon of the war. Overnight, Hayes became a national hero, along with the two other survivors in the famous photograph, Rene Gagnon and John Bradley.

When Iwo Jima was secured by U.S. forces, Hayes was ordered to [[Washington, D.C.]] Together with the Navy Pharmacist's Mate John Bradley and Marine Private First Class Rene Gagnon, he was assigned to temporary duty with the Finance Division, U.S. Treasury Department, for appearances in connection with the Seventh [[War Bond]] Drive.

===Rank and military awards===
* Corporal 
* Navy-Marine Commendation Medal with Combat &quot;V&quot; Device
* Combat Action Ribbon
*[[Presidential Unit Citation]] (Ribbon only) with One 5/16&quot; Silver Star
*[[American Campaign Medal]]
*[[Asiatic-Pacific Campaign Medal]] with Four Bronze 3/16&quot; Stars (for Vella Lavella, Bougainville, Consolidation of the Northern Solomons, and Iwo Jima)
*[[World War II Victory Medal]]
*[[USMC Occupation of Japan Medal]]
*[[Parachutist Badge]]
*[[Rifle Sharpshooter Badge]]

===Post World War II===
[[File:Hayes in LA.jpg|thumb|'''Ira Hayes''' (left) with Los Angeles mayor [[Fletcher Bowron]] (1947)]]
After the war, Hayes attempted to lead a normal civilian life. &quot;I kept getting hundreds of letters. And people would drive through the reservation, walk up to me and ask, 'Are you the Indian who raised the flag on Iwo Jima?'&quot;&lt;ref name=Viola&gt;{{cite book
|last=Viola
|first=Herman J.
|title=Warriors in Uniform: The Legacy of American Indian Heroism
|url=http://books.google.com/?id=JYXMqa1MYNsC&amp;pg=PA93&amp;dq=%22Are+you+the+Indian+who+raised+the+flag+on+Iwo+Jima%22&amp;q=%22Are%20you%20the%20Indian%20who%20raised%20the%20flag%20on%20Iwo%20Jima%22
|date=November 18, 2008
|work=[[National Geographic (magazine)|National Geographic]]
|isbn=978-1426203619
|pages=93–94
|chapter=Fighting the Metal Hats: World War II
|author2=Campbell, Ben Nighthorse
}}
&lt;/ref&gt; Although he rarely spoke about the flag raising, he spoke about his service in the Marine Corps with great pride.

After returning home from the war, Hayes remained troubled that one of his friends, [[Harlon Block]], one of the flag raisers who was [[killed in action]] days after, was mistaken for another man, [[Hank Hansen]]. Hayes later hitchhiked 1,300 miles from the Gila River Indian Community to Edward Frederick Block, Sr.'s farm in [[Weslaco, Texas]] in order to reveal the truth to Block's family. He was instrumental in having the controversy resolved, to the delight and gratitude of the Block family.

Ira Hayes appeared in the 1949 [[John Wayne]] film, ''[[Sands of Iwo Jima]]'', along with fellow flag raisers [[John Bradley (Navy)|John Bradley]] and [[Rene Gagnon]]. All three men played themselves in the film. Wayne hands the flag to be raised to the three men. (The actual flag that was raised on Mount Suribachi is used in the film.)

After the war, Hayes accumulated a record of 52 arrests for public [[drunkenness]].&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news
 | last =
 | first =
 | title = Then There Were Two
 | newspaper = Time
 | pages =
 | date = February 7, 1955
 | url = http://www.time.com/time/magazine/article/0,9171,823714,00.html
 | publisher =[[Time (magazine)]]
 | postscript =&lt;!--None--&gt;}}
&lt;/ref&gt; Referring to his [[alcoholism]], he once said: &quot;I was sick. I guess I was about to crack up thinking about all my good buddies. They were better men than me and they're not coming back. Much less back to the [[White House]], like me.&quot;&lt;ref name=Viola/&gt;

In 1954, after a ceremony where he was lauded by [[President of the United States|President]] [[Dwight D. Eisenhower]] as a hero, a reporter approached Hayes and asked him, &quot;How do you like the pomp and circumstance?&quot; Hayes hung his head and said, &quot;I don't.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;
{{cite book
|last=Jeffers
|first=Harry Paul
|title=The 100 Greatest Heroes
|url=http://books.google.com/?id=VO34DY1TRM0C&amp;pg=PA135&amp;dq=ira+hayes+eisenhower&amp;q=ira%20hayes%20eisenhower
|date=April 1, 2003
|publisher=[[Citadel Press]]
|isbn=978-0806524764
|page=135
|chapter=Ira Hayes
}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Hayes' disquiet about his unwanted fame and his subsequent post-war problems were first recounted in detail by the author [[William Bradford Huie]] in ''The Outsider'', published in 1959 as part of his collection ''Wolf Whistle and Other Stories''. ''[[The Outsider (1961 film)|The Outsider]]'' was filmed in 1961, directed by former World War II veteran turned film director [[Delbert Mann]] and starring [[Tony Curtis]].&lt;ref name=imdbout&gt;{{imdb title | id=55270 | title=The Outsider}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The 2006 film ''[[Flags of Our Fathers (film)|Flags of Our Fathers]]'', directed by [[Clint Eastwood]], suggests that Hayes suffered from [[posttraumatic stress disorder]].

===Death===
[[File:Ira Hayes Tombstone.jpg|thumb|left|225px|Ira Hayes' tombstone.]]
On the morning of January 24, 1955, Hayes was found dead, lying in his own blood and vomit, near an abandoned adobe hut in Sacaton, Arizona. He had been drinking and playing cards at a bar on the reservation with his friends and brothers Vernon and Kenneth. An altercation ensued between Hayes and a Pima named Henry Setoyant, and all left except Hayes and Setoyant. 

The Pinal County coroner concluded that Hayes' death was caused by [[hypothermia|exposure]] and [[alcohol poisoning]]. However, his brother Kenneth still believes that the death resulted from the altercation with Setoyant. The Gila River Police Department did not conduct an investigation into Hayes' death and Setoyant denied any allegations of fighting with Hayes.&lt;ref name= &quot;Bradley-Powers p. 503&quot;&gt;{{harvnb|Bradley|Powers|2006|p=503}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In the 1961 film of his life, (starring [[Tony Curtis]])  ''The Outsider'', his death is dramatized for the screen. He is shown freezing to death on an Arizona mountain top, after a night of drinking.

Hayes is buried in Section 34, Grave 479A at [[Arlington National Cemetery]]. At the funeral, fellow flag-raiser [[Rene Gagnon]] said of him: &quot;Let's say he had a little dream in his heart that someday the Indian would be like the white man &amp;mdash; be able to walk all over the United States.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Chavers
|first=Dean
|title=Modern American Indian Leaders: Their Lives and Their Work
|url=http://books.google.com/?id=p1t0AAAAMAAJ&amp;pg=PA243&amp;dq=Let's+say+he+had+a+little+dream+in+his+heart+that+someday+the+Indian+would+be+like+the+white+man
|volume=1
|year=2007
|publisher=[[Edwin Mellen Press]]
|isbn=978-0773455559
|page=243}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Commemoration==
On November 10, 1993, the [[United States Marine Corps]] held a ceremony at the Iwo Jima Memorial commemorating the anniversary of the Corps. Of Ira Hayes, [[Commandant of the Marine Corps|USMC Commandant]] General [[Carl Mundy]] said:

{{bquote|One of the pairs of hands that you see outstretched to raise our national flag on the battle-scarred crest of Mount Suribachi so many years ago, are those of a Native American ... Ira Hayes ... a Marine not of the ethnic majority of our population.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Were Ira Hayes here today ... I would tell him that although my words on another occasion have given the impression that I believe some Marines ... because of their color ... are not as capable as other Marines ... that those were not the thoughts of my mind ... and that they are not the thoughts of my heart.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I would tell Ira Hayes that our Corps is what we are because we are of the people of America ... the people of the broad, strong, ethnic fabric that is our nation. And last, I would tell him that in the future, that fabric will broaden and strengthen in every category to make our Corps even stronger ... even of greater utility to our nation. That's a commitment of this commandant ... And that's a personal commitment of this Marine.}}

==Portrayal in music, film and literature==
*Hayes' story was immortalized in a song, &quot;[[The Ballad of Ira Hayes]]&quot;, by [[Peter LaFarge]]. [[Johnny Cash]], [[Kris Kristofferson]], [[Smiley Bates]], [[Pete Seeger]], [[Bob Dylan]], [[Kinky Friedman]], [[Tom Russell]], [[Hazel Dickens]], [[Patrick Sky]], and [[Townes Van Zandt]] each [[Cover version|covered]] the song. In 1964, Cash took the song to number 3 on the [[Billboard chart|Billboard]] [[country music]] chart.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|url=http://books.google.com/?id=N7Tk0O2naR0C|title=Cash: The Autobiography |last=Cash|first=Johnny |year=1977|publisher=Harper Collins|accessdate=7 May 2010|isbn=9780060727536}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*Ira Hayes appeared as himself in the 1949 [[John Wayne]] film, ''[[Sands of Iwo Jima]]''.
*In the 1960 telefilm ''[[The American (1960 film)|The American]]'', he was played by Marine veteran [[Lee Marvin]].
*[[Tony Curtis]] played Hayes in the 1961 film ''[[The Outsider (1961 film)|The Outsider]]''.&lt;ref name=imdbout/&gt;
*Hayes was portrayed by [[Adam Beach]] in the 2006 movie ''[[Flags of Our Fathers (film)|Flags of Our Fathers]]'', directed by [[Clint Eastwood]]. The movie was based on the 2000 bestselling [[Flags of Our Fathers|book of the same name]] by [[James Bradley (author)|James Bradley]] and [[Ron Powers]].
*The poet [[Ai (poet)|Ai]] dedicates her poem &quot;I Can't Get Started&quot; to Hayes.
*Ira Hayes is mentioned in the poem &quot;Petroglyphs of Serena&quot; by [[Adrian C. Louis]].
*Ira Hayes was also mentioned briefly in the book &quot;The Code Talker&quot; by [[Joseph Bruchac]].

==Monuments, memorials, and namings==
* Marine Corps War Memorial (rear Marine flag raising figure), Arlington, VA
* Hayes Peak, the northernmost mountain in the [[Sierra Estrella]], Phoenix, AZ
* Ira Hayes Park (statue), Sacaton, Arizona
* Marine Corps League, Ira Hayes Detachment 2, Phoenix, AZ
* American Legion, Ira Hayes Post 84, Sacaton, AZ

==See also==
{{Portal box|Biography|World War II|United States Marine Corps}}
*[[Native Americans and World War II]]
*[[PTSD]]
*[[Raising the Flag on Iwo Jima]]
*[[Shadow of Suribachi: Raising The Flags on Iwo Jima]]
*[[Survivor guilt]]

==Bibliography==
;Notes
{{reflist|2}}
;References
*{{cite book |ref=harv|last=Bradley|first=James | authorlink = James Bradley (author)|last2=Powers|first2=Ron | title = Flags of Our Fathers|edition=2006|year=2006| publisher = [[Bantam Books]]| isbn= 9780553589085 }} &lt;small&gt;- Total pages: 576 &lt;/small&gt;
*''[http://www.leeandlow.com/books/irahayes.html Quiet Hero: The Ira Hayes Story]'' written and illustrated by S. D. Nelson, ([http://www.leeandlow.com Lee &amp; Low Books], 2006) ISBN 978-1-58430-263-6.
*''The Outsider and Other Stories'', by [[William Bradford Huie]], Panther Books, GB 1961, originally published in the USA 1959, by Signet as ''Wolf Whistle and Other Stories''

==External links==
{{Commons category|Ira H. Hayes|Ira Hayes}}
*[http://www.gric.nsn.us/newdirection/ Gila River Indian Community official website]
*[http://music.yahoo.com/ar-254822-bio--Peter-LaFarge Peter LaFarge Biography]
*[http://www.iwojima.com/raising/raisingc.htm The Flag Raisers] on Iwojima.com
*{{imdb title | id=55270 | title=The Outsider}}
*[http://www.imdb.com/title/tt0418689/ Flags of Our Fathers] - Movie

{{Persondata
|NAME= Hayes, Ira
|ALTERNATIVE NAMES=
|SHORT DESCRIPTION= United States Marine
|DATE OF BIRTH= January 12, 1923
|PLACE OF BIRTH= [[Gila River Indian Community|Gila River Indian Reservation]]
|DATE OF DEATH= January 24, 1955
|PLACE OF DEATH= [[Gila River Indian Community|Gila River Indian Reservation]]
}}
{{DEFAULTSORT:Hayes, Ira}}
[[Category:1923 births]]
[[Category:1955 deaths]]
[[Category:People from Phoenix, Arizona]]
[[Category:Alcohol-related deaths in Arizona]]
[[Category:American military personnel of World War II]]
[[Category:Battle of Iwo Jima]]
[[Category:Burials at Arlington National Cemetery]]
[[Category:Native American United States military personnel]]
[[Category:United States Marines]]

[[ca:Ira Hayes]]
[[de:Ira Hayes]]
[[es:Ira Hayes]]
[[fr:Ira Hayes]]
[[it:Ira Hayes]]
[[nl:Ira Hayes]]
[[ja:アイラ・ヘイズ]]
[[pl:Ira Hayes]]
[[ru:Хейз, Айра]]
[[sv:Ira Hayes]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
