<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="1935334" ns="0" title="History of the Jews in Egypt"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Jews and Judaism sidebar}}
Egyptian Jews constitute both one of the oldest and youngest [[Jew]]ish communities in the world. While no exact census exists, the Jewish population of [[Egypt]] was estimated at fewer than a hundred in 2004,&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.jewishvirtuallibrary.org/jsource/anti-semitism/egjews.html Jewish Virtual Library]&lt;/ref&gt; down from between 75,000 and 80,000 in 1922.&lt;ref&gt;The 1947 census gives 65,639, possibly too low. See [[Joel Beinin]], ''The Dispersion of Egyptian Jewry: Culture, Politics, and the Formation of a Modern Diaspora''Introd.&lt;/ref&gt; The historic core of the indigenous community consisted mainly of Arabic-speaking [[Rabbanites]] and [[Karaites]]. After their expulsion from Spain, more [[Sephardi]] and [[Karaite]] Jews began to emigrate to Egypt, and their numbers increased significantly with the growth of trading prospects after the opening of the [[Suez Canal]], to constitute the commercial and cultural elite of the modern community. The [[Ashkenazi Jews|Ashkenazi]] community, mainly confined to Cairo's Darb al-Barabira quarter, began to arrive in the aftermath of the waves of [[pogrom]]s that hit Europe in the latter part of the 19th century.

==Ancient times==
In the [[Elephantine]] papyri, caches of legal documents and letters written in [[Aramaic]] amply document the lives of a community of Jewish soldiers stationed in there as part of a frontier garrison in Egypt for the [[Achaemenid Empire]].&lt;ref name=&quot;ancientsudan.org&quot;&gt;[http://www.ancientsudan.org/articles_jewish_elephantine.html Ibrahim M. Omer, &quot;Briefly Investigating the Origin of the Ancient Jewish Community at Elephantine: A Review.&quot;]&lt;/ref&gt; Established at Elephantine in about 650 BC during [[Manasseh of Judah|Manasseh]]'s reign, these soldiers assisted [[Pharaoh]] [[Psammetichus I]] in his [[Nubia]]n campaign. Their religious system shows strong traces of [[Babylonian]] [[polytheism]], something which suggests to certain scholars that the community was of mixed Judaeo-[[Samaritan]] origins,&lt;ref&gt;[[A. van Hoonacker]], ''Une Communité Judéo-Araméenne à Éléphantine, en Egypte, aux vi et v siècles avant J.-C,'' London 1915 cited, [[Arnold Toynbee]], ''A Study of History,'' vol.5, (1939) 1964 p125 n.1&lt;/ref&gt; and they maintained their own temple, functioning alongside that of the local deity [[Chnum]]. The documents cover the period 495 to 399 BC.

The [[Hebrew Bible]] also records that a large number of Jews took refuge in Egypt after the destruction of the [[Kingdom of Judah]] in 597 BC, and the subsequent assassination of the Jewish governor, [[Gedaliah]]. ({{bibleverse|2|Kings|25:22-24|HE}}, {{bibleverse||Jeremiah|40:6-8|HE}}) On hearing of the appointment, the Jews that had fled to [[Moab]], [[Ammon]], [[Edom]] and in other countries returned to Judah. ({{bibleverse||Jeremiah|40:11-12|HE}}) However, before long Gedaliah was assassinated, and the population that was left in the land and those that had returned ran away to Egypt for safety. ({{bibleverse|2|Kings|25:26|HE}}, {{bibleverse||Jeremiah|43:5-7|HE}}) The numbers that made their way to Egypt is subject to debate. In Egypt, they settled in [[Migdol]], [[Tahpanhes]], [[Noph]], and [[Pathros]]. ({{bibleverse||Jeremiah|44:1|HE}})

Although the [[Book of Exodus]] describes a period of Hebrew servitude in ancient Egypt, more than a century of archaeological research has discovered nothing which could support its narrative elements— the four centuries sojourn in Egypt, the escape of well over a million Israelites from the Delta, or the three months journey through the wilderness to Sinai.&lt;ref&gt;James Weinstein, &quot;Exodus and the Archaeological Reality&quot;, in ''Exodus: The Egyptian Evidence'', ed. Ernest S. Frerichs and Leonard H. Lesko (Eisenbrauns, 1997), p.87&lt;/ref&gt; 
The Egyptian records themselves have no mention of anything recorded in Exodus, the wilderness of the southern Sinai peninsula shows no traces of a mass-migration such as Exodus describes, and virtually all the place-names mentioned, including [[Land of Goshen|Goshen]] (the area within Egypt where the Israelites supposedly lived), the store-cities of [[Pithom]] and [[Avaris|Rameses]], the site of the crossing of the Red Sea (or, more commonly among modern Biblical scholars, the Sea of Reeds), and even Mt Sinai itself, have resisted identification.&lt;ref&gt;John Van Seters, &quot;The Geography of the Exodus&quot;, in ''The Land I Will Show You: Essays on the History and Archaeology of the Ancient Near East in Honour of J. Maxwell Miller'', ed. J. Andrew Dearman and M. Patrick Graham (JSOT 343, Sheffield Academic Press, 2001), pp. 255-76&lt;/ref&gt; Scholars who hold the Exodus to represent historical truth concede that the most the evidence can suggest is plausibility.&lt;ref&gt;James K. Hoffmeier, ''Israel in Egypt: The Evidence for the Authenticity of the Exodus Tradition'', (OUP, 1999)&lt;/ref&gt;

==Ptolemaic and Roman (400 BC to 641 AD)==
{{See also|Leontopolis|Alabarch|Philo|Elephantine}}

Further waves of Jewish immigrants settled in Egypt during the [[Ptolemaic dynasty|Ptolemaic]] era, especially around [[Alexandria]]. Thus, their history in this period centers almost completely on Alexandria, though daughter communities rose up in places like the present Kafr ed-Dawar, and Jews served in the administration as custodians of the river.&lt;ref&gt;Aryeh Kasher ''The Jews in Hellenistic and Roman Egypt: The Struggle for Equal Rights,'' Mohr Siebeck, 1985 pp.107-8&lt;/ref&gt; As early as the third century B.C. one can speak of a widespread [[diaspora]] of Jews in many Egyptian towns and cities. In [[Josephus]]'s history, it is claimed that, after the first [[Ptolemy I Soter|Ptolemy]] took [[Judea]], he led  some 120,000 Jewish captives to Egypt from the areas of Judea, [[Jerusalem]], [[Samaria]], and [[Mount Gerizim]]. With them, many other Jews, attracted by the fertile soil and Ptolemy's liberality, emigrated there of their own accord. An inscription recording a Jewish dedication of a synagogue to Ptolemy and [[Berenice]] was discovered in the 19th century near Alexandria.&lt;ref&gt;[[John Pentland Mahaffy|Sir John Pentland Mahaffy]] 
''The History of Egypt under the Ptolemaic Dynasty'', New York 1899 p. 192.&lt;/ref&gt;
Josephus also claims that, soon after, these 120,000 captives were freed of their bondage by [[Philadelphus]].&lt;ref&gt;[[Josephus]], ''Antiquities of the Jews,'' in ''The Works of Josephus, Complete and Unabridged'', New Updated Edition (Translated by William Whiston, A.M.; Peabody Massachusetts:Hendrickson Publishers, 1987; Fifth Printing:Jan.1991 Bk. 12, chapters. 1, 2, pp. 308-309 (Bk. 12: verses 7, 9, 11)&lt;/ref&gt;  

The history of the Alexandrian Jews dates from the foundation of the city by [[Alexander the Great]], 332 B.C., at which they were present. They were numerous from the very outset, forming a notable portion of the city's population under Alexander's successors. The Ptolemies assigned them a separate section, two of the five districts of the city, to enable them to keep their laws pure of indigenous cultic influences. The Alexandrian Jews enjoyed a greater degree of political independence than elsewhere. While the Jews elsewhere throughout the later [[Roman Empire]] formed private societies for religious purposes, or else became a corporation of foreigners like the Egyptian and [[Phoenicia]]n merchants in the large commercial centers, those of Alexandria constituted an independent political community, side by side with that of the indigenous population. 

For the Roman period there is evidence that at [[Oxyrynchus]] (modern ''Behneseh''), on the east side of the Nile, there was a Jewish community of some importance. It even had a Jews' street. Many of the Jews there must have become Christians, though they retained their Biblical names (e.g., &quot;David&quot; and &quot;Elisabeth,&quot; occurring in a litigation concerning an inheritance). There is even found a certain Jacob, son of Achilles (c. 300 AD), as beadle of an Egyptian temple.

The Jewish community of Alexandria was virtually wiped out by [[Trajan]]'s army during the [[Kitos War|Jewish revolt]] of 115-117 CE (which destroyed pagan temples), and Josephus&lt;ref&gt;''The Jewish War'' Book 2.495ff.&lt;/ref&gt; puts the figure for those slaughtered in the vast [[pogrom]] at 50,000.

==Arab rule (641 to 1250)==
The Arab invasion of Egypt at first found support not only from Copts, and other Christians, but from Jews as well, all disgruntled by the corrupt administration of the [[Patriarch]] Cyrus of Alexander, notorious for his [[Monothelitism|Monotheletic]] proselytizing.&lt;ref&gt;[[Steven Runciman]], ''A History of the Crusades'' 1951 vol.1 pp.18-19&lt;/ref&gt; In addition to the Jews settled there from early times, some must have come from the [[Arabian Peninsula]]. The letter sent by [[Muhammad]] to the Jewish ''Banu Janba'' in [[630]]&lt;ref&gt;Julius Wellhausen, ''Skizzen und Vorarbeiten IV = Medina vor dem Islam'', Berlin 1889.p.119&lt;/ref&gt;  is said by Al-Baladhuri to have been seen in Egypt. A copy, written in Hebrew characters, has been found in the [[Cairo Geniza]]. 

The Jews had no reason to feel kindly toward the former masters of Egypt. In 629 the Emperor [[Heraclius|Heraclius I]] had driven the Jews from Jerusalem this was followed by a massacre of Jews throughout the empire—in Egypt, aided by the Copts, who had old scores to settle with the Jews, dating from the Persian conquest of Amida at the time of Emperor [[Anastasius I (emperor)|Anastasius I]] (502) and of Alexandria by the Persian general [[Shahin]] (617), when the Jews assisted the conquerors in fighting against the Christians.{{Citation needed|date=March 2009}} The ''Treaty of Alexandria'' (Nov. 8, 641), which sealed the Arab conquest of Egypt, expressly stipulates that the Jews are to be allowed to remain in that city; and at the time of the capture of that city, [['Amr ibn al-'As]], in his letter to the caliph, relates that he found there 40,000 Jews.&lt;sup&gt;[needs citation]&lt;/sup&gt;

Of the fortunes of the Jews in Egypt under the [[Umayyad Caliphate|Umayyad]] and [[Abbasid Caliphate]]s (641-868), little is known. Under the [[Tulunids]] (863-905), the Karaite community enjoyed robust growth.

===Rule of the Fatimid Caliphs (969 to 1169)===
The rule of the [[Fatimid Caliphate]] was in general favorable for the Jews, except the latter portion of al-Ḥakim bi-Amr Allah's reign. The foundation of Talmudic schools in Egypt is usually placed at this period. One of the Jews who rose to high position in that society was Ya‘qub Ibn Killis.

The caliph al-Ḥakim (996-1020) vigorously applied the [[Pact of Umar II|Pact of Umar]], and compelled the Jews to wear bells and to carry in public the wooden image of a calf. A street in the city, al-Jawdariyyah, was inhabited by Jews. Al-Ḥakim, hearing that they were accustomed to mock him in verses, had the whole quarter burned down.

By the beginning of the twelfth century a Jew, Abu al-Munajja ibn Sha'yah, was at the head of the Department of Agriculture. He is especially known as the constructor of a Nile sluice (1112), which was called after him &quot;Baḥr Abi al-Munajja&quot;. He fell into disfavor because of the heavy expenses connected with the work, and was incarcerated in Alexandria, but was soon able to free himself. A document concerning a transaction of his with a banker has been preserved. Under the [[vizier]] [[Al-Afdal Shahanshah|Al-Malik al-Afḍal]] (1137) there was a Jewish master of finances, whose name, however, is unknown. His enemies succeeded in procuring his downfall, and he lost all his property. He was succeeded by a brother of the Christian patriarch, who tried to drive the Jews out of the kingdom. Four leading Jews worked and conspired against the Christian, with what result is not known. There has been preserved a letter from this ex-minister to the Jews of Constantinople, begging for aid in a remarkably intricate poetical style (''J. Q. R.'' ix. 29, x. 430; ''Z. D. M. G.'' li. 444). One of the physicians of the caliph Al-Ḥafiẓ (1131–49) was a Jew, Abu Manṣur ([[Wüstenfeld]], p.&amp;nbsp;306). Abu al-Faḍa'il ibn al-Nakid (died 1189) was a celebrated oculist.

In this century a little more light is thrown upon the communities in Egypt through the reports of certain Jewish scholars and travelers who visited the country. [[Judah Halevi]] was in Alexandria in 1141, and dedicated some beautiful verses to his fellow resident and friend Aaron Ben-Zion ibn Alamani and his five sons. At [[Damietta]] Halevi met his friend, the Spaniard Abu Sa'id ibn Ḥalfon ha-Levi. About 1160 [[Benjamin of Tudela]] was in Egypt; he gives a general account of the Jewish communities which he found there. At Cairo there were 2,000 Jews; at Alexandria 3,000, whose head was the French-born R. Phineas b. Meshullam; in the [[Faiyum]] there were 20 families; at Damietta 200; at [[Bilbeis]], east of the Nile, 300 persons; and at Damira 700.

===From Saladin and Maimonides (1169 to 1250)===
[[Saladin]]'s war with the Crusaders (1169–93) does not seem to have affected the Jews in his kingdom. A Karaite doctor, Abu al-Bayyan al-Mudawwar (d. 1184), who had been physician to the last Fatimid, treated Saladin also.&lt;ref&gt;B.A. § 153&lt;/ref&gt; Abu al-Ma'ali, brother-in-law of Maimonides, was likewise in his service.&lt;ref&gt;B.A. ibid. § 155)&lt;/ref&gt; In 1166 [[Maimonides]] went to Egypt and settled in [[Fostat]], where he gained much renown as a physician, practising in the family of Saladin and in that of his vizier al-Qadi al-Fadil|Ḳaḍi al-Faḍil al-Baisami, and Saladin's successors. The title ''Ra'is al-Umma'' or ''al-Millah'' (Head of the Nation or of the Faith), was bestowed upon him. In Fostat, he wrote his ''[[Mishneh Torah]]'' (1180) and ''[[The Guide for the Perplexed]],'' both of which evoked opposition from Jewish scholars. From this place he sent many letters and [[responsa]]; and in 1173 he forwarded a request to the North-African communities for help to secure the release of a number of captives. The original of the last document has been preserved.&lt;ref&gt;M. xliv. 8&lt;/ref&gt; He caused the Karaites to be removed from the court.&lt;ref&gt;''J. Q. R.'' xiii. 104&lt;/ref&gt;

==Mamelukes (1250 to 1517)==
Under the [[Bahri dynasty|Baḥri]] [[Mamelukes]] (1250–1390) the Jews led a comparatively quiet existence; though they had at times to contribute heavily toward the maintenance of the vast military equipment, and were harassed by the cadis and ulemas of these strict Moslems. [[Al-Maqrizi]] relates that the first great Mameluke, Sultan [[Baibars]] (Al-Malik al-Thahir, 1260–77), doubled the tribute paid by the &quot;ahl al-dhimmah.&quot; At one time he had resolved to burn all the Jews, a ditch having been dug for that purpose; but at the last moment he repented, and instead exacted a heavy tribute, during the collection of which many perished.

An account is given in Sambari (135, 22) of the strictness with which the provisions of the Pact of Omar were carried out. The sultan had just returned from a victorious campaign against the [[Mongols]] in Syria (1305). A fanatical convert from Judaism, Sa'id ibn Ḥasan of Alexandria, was incensed at the arrogance of the non-Moslem population, particularly at the open manner in which services were conducted in churches and synagogues. He tried to form a synod of ten rabbis, ten priests, and the ulemas. Failing in this, he endeavored to have the churches and synagogues closed. Some of the churches were demolished by Alexandrian mobs; but most of the synagogues were allowed to stand, as it was shown that they had existed at the time of Omar, and were by the pact exempted from interference. Sambari (137, 20) says that a new pact was made at the instance of letters from a Moorish king of Barcelona (1309), and the synagogues were reopened; but this probably refers only to the reissuing of the Pact of Omar. There are extant several notable [[fatwā]]s (responsa) of Moslem doctors touching this subject; e.g., those of Aḥmad ibn 'Abd al-Ḥaḳḳ, who speaks especially of the synagogues at Cairo, which on the outside appeared like ordinary dwelling-houses—a fact which had occasioned other legal writers to permit their presence. According to Taki al-Din ibn Taimiyyah (b. 1263), the synagogues and churches in Cairo had once before been closed. This fanatical Moslem fills his [[fatwā]]s with invectives against the Jews, holding that all their religious edifices ought to be destroyed, since they had been constructed during a period when Cairo was in the hands of heterodox Moslems, [[Ismaili]]ans, [[Karmatians]], and [[Nusairi]]s (R. E. J. xxx. 1, xxxi. 212; Z. D. M. G. liii. 51). The synagogues were, however, allowed to stand (Weil, l.c. iv. 270). Under the same sultan (1324) the Jews were accused of incendiarism at [[Fostat]] and Cairo; they had to exculpate themselves by a payment of 50,000 gold pieces.

Under the [[Burji dynasty|Burji]] Mamelukes the [[Franks]] again attacked Alexandria (1416), and the laws against the Jews were once more strictly enforced by Sheik al-Mu'ayyid (1412–21); by Ashraf Bars Bey (1422–38), because of a plague which decimated the population in 1438; by Al-Ẓahir Jaḳmaḳ (1438–53); and by Ḳa'iṭ-Bey (1468–95). The lastnamed is referred to by Obadiah of Bertinoro (O. p.&amp;nbsp;53). The Jews of Cairo were compelled to pay 75,000 gold pieces.

==Turkish rule (1517 to 1922)==
On January 22, 1517, the [[Ottoman Turks|Turkish]] sultan, [[Selim I]], defeated [[Tuman Bey]], the last of the Mamelukes. He made radical changes in the affairs of the Jews, abolishing the office of nagid, making each community independent, and placing David ibn Abi Zimra, at the head of that of Cairo. He also appointed Abraham de Castro to be master of the mint. It was during the reign of Salim's successor, [[Suleiman II]], that Aḥmad Pasha, Viceroy of Egypt, revenged himself upon the Jews because De Castro had revealed (1524) to the sultan his designs for independence (see Aḥmad Pasha; Abraham de Castro). The &quot;Cairo Purim,&quot; in commemoration of their escape, is still celebrated on Adar 28.

Toward the end of the sixteenth century Talmudic studies in Egypt were greatly fostered by Bezaleel Ashkenazi, author of the &quot;Shiṭṭah Meḳubbeẓet.&quot; Among his pupils were [[Isaac Luria]], who as a young man had gone to Egypt to visit a rich uncle, the tax-farmer Mordecai Francis (Azulai, &quot;Shem ha-Gedolim,&quot; No. 332); and Abraham Monson (1594). Ishmael Kohen Tanuji finished his &quot;Sefer ha-Zikkaron&quot; in Egypt in 1543. Joseph ben Moses di Trani was in Egypt for a time (Frumkin, l.c. p.&amp;nbsp;69), as well as Ḥayyim Vital Aaron ibn Ḥayyim, the Biblical and Talmudical commentator (1609; Frumkin, l.c. pp.&amp;nbsp;71, 72). Of Isaac Luria's pupils, a Joseph Ṭabul is mentioned, whose son Jacob, a prominent man, was put to death by the authorities.

According to Manasseh b. Israel (1656), &quot;The viceroy of Egypt has always at his side a Jew with the title 'zaraf bashi,' or 'treasurer,' who gathers the taxes of the land. At present Abraham Alkula holds the position.&quot; He was succeeded by Raphael Joseph Tshelebi, the rich friend and protector of [[Shabbatai Zevi]]. Shabbetai was twice in Cairo, the second time in 1660. It was there that he married the ill-famed Sarah, who had been brought from Leghorn. The Shabbethaian movement naturally created a great stir in Egypt. It was in Cairo that Miguel (Abraham) Cardoso, the Shabbethaian prophet and physician, settled (1703), becoming physician to the pasha Kara Mohammed. In 1641 Samuel b. David, the Karaite, visited Egypt. The account of his journey (G. i. 1) supplies special information in regard to his fellow sectaries. He describes three synagogues of the Rabbinites at Alexandria, and two at Rashid (G. i. 4). A second Karaite, Moses b. Elijah ha-Levi, has left a similar account of the year 1654; but it contains only a few points of special interest to the Karaites (ib).

Sambari mentions a severe trial which came upon the Jews, due to a certain &quot;ḳadi al-'asakir&quot; (=&quot;generalissimo,&quot; not a proper name) sent from Constantinople to Egypt, who robbed and oppressed them, and whose death was in a certain measure occasioned by the graveyard invocation of one Moses of Damwah. This may have occurred in the seventeenth century (S. 120, 21). [[David Conforte]] was dayyan in Egypt in 1671. [[Blood libels]] occurred at Alexandria in 1844, in 1881, and in Jan., 1902. In consequence of the [[Damascus Affair]], [[Moses Montefiore]], [[Isaac Moïse Crémieux|Crémieux]], and [[Salomon Munk]] visited Egypt in 1840; and the last two did much to raise the intellectual status of their Egyptian brethren by the founding, in connection with Rabbi Moses Joseph Algazi, of schools in Cairo. At the turn of the century, a Jewish observer noted with 'true satisfaction that a great spirit of tolerance sustains the majority of our fellow Jews in Egypt, and it would be difficult to find a more liberal population or one more respectful of all religious beliefs.’&lt;ref&gt;Aron Rodrigue, ''Jews and Muslims: Images of Sephardi and Eastern Jewries in Modern Times'', University of Washington Press, 2003 p.163, quoting a document by S.Somekh  of 1895&lt;/ref&gt;

According to the official census published in 1898 (i., xviii.), there were in Egypt 25,200 Jews in a total population of 9,734,405.

==Modern times (since 1919)==
[[File:Demonstration in Egypt in 1919 (Crescent, the Cross and Star of David).jpg|thumb|[[Egyptian Revolution of 1919|Demonstration in Egypt in 1919]] holding the Egyptian flag with Crescent, the Cross and Star of David on it.]]
During British rule, and under [[Fuad I of Egypt|King Fuad I]], Egypt was friendly towards its Jewish population, though Egyptian nationality was denied to 90 % of Egyptian Jews regardless of how many generations they resided in the country.  Jews played important roles in the economy, and their population climbed to nearly 80,000 as Jewish refugees settled there in response to increasing persecution in Europe. A sharp distinction had long existed between the respective Karaite and Rabbanite communities, among whom traditionally intermarriage was forbidden. They dwelt in Cairo in two contiguous areas, the former in the ''harat al-yahud al-qara’in'' , and the latter in the adjacent ''harat al-yahud'' quarter. Notwithstanding the division, they often worked together and the younger educated generation pressed for improving relations between the two.&lt;ref name=&quot;Joel_Beinin&quot;&gt;Joel Beinin, ''The Dispersion of Egyptian Jewry: Culture, Politics, and the Formation of a Modern Diaspora,''&lt;/ref&gt;

Individual Jews played an important role in Egyptian [[nationalism]]. René Qattawi, leader of the Cairo Sephardi community, endorsed the creation in 1935 of the Association of Egyptian Jewish Youth, with its slogan: 'Egypt is our homeland, Arabic is our language.' Qattawi strongly opposed political [[Zionism]] and wrote a note on 'The Jewish Question' to the [[World Jewish Congress]] in [[1943]] in which he argued that Palestine would be unable to absorb Europe's Jewish refugees.&lt;ref name=&quot;Joel_Beinin&quot;/&gt; Nevertheless, various wings of the Zionist movement had representatives in Egypt. Karaite Jewish scholar [[Murad Beh Farag]] (1866–1956) was both an Egyptian nationalist and a passionate Zionist. His poem, 'My Homeland Egypt, Place of my Birth', expresses loyalty to Egypt, while his book, ''al-Qudsiyyat'' (Jerusalemica, 1923), defends the right of the Jews to a State.&lt;ref&gt;Mourad El-Kodsi, ''The Karaite Jews of Egypt'', 1882–1986, Lyons, NY: Wilprint, 1987.&lt;/ref&gt; ''al-Qudsiyyat''  is perhaps the most eloquent defense of Zionism in the Arabic language. Farag was also one of the coauthors of Egypt's first Constitution in 1923.

Another famous Egyptian Jew of this period was [[Yaqub Sanu]], who became a patriotic Egyptian nationalist advocating the removal of the British. He edited the nationalist publication [[Abu Naddara 'Azra]] from exile. This was one of the first magazines written in [[Egyptian Arabic]], and mostly consisted of [[satire]], poking fun at the British as well as the Monarchy which was a puppet of the British. Another was [[Henri Curiel]], who founded 'The Egyptian Movement for National Liberation' in 1943, an organization that was to form the core of the Egyptian Communist party.&lt;ref name=&quot;Joel_Beinin&quot;/&gt; Curiel was to play an important role in establishing early informal contacts between the PLO and Israel.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.counterpunch.org/avnery03242008.html [[Uri Avnery]], 'Two Americas,' [[CounterPunch]] 24 March 2009]&lt;/ref&gt;

In 1937, the government annulled the Capitulations that gave foreign nationals a virtual status of exterritoriality the minorities groups were mainly from Syrian, Greece, Italy, Armenia (this also affected some Jews who were nationals of other countries). The immunities from taxation  to foreign nationals ''[[mutamassir]]'' (minority groups) trading within Egypt had given them highly favourably trading advantages.&lt;ref&gt;Gudrun Krämer (1989) The Jews in modern Egypt, 1914-1952 I.B.Tauris, ISBN 1850431000 p 8&lt;/ref&gt;

The impact of the well-publicized Arab-Jewish clash in Palestine from 1936 to 1939, together with the rise of Nazi Germany, also began to affect the Jewish relations with Egyptian society, despite the fact that the number of active Zionists in their ranks was small.&lt;ref&gt;Joel Beinin, op.cit. Introduction&lt;/ref&gt; The rise of local militant nationalistic societies like ''Young Egypt'' and the ''Society of Muslim Brothers'', who were sympathetic to the various models evinced by the Axis Powers in Europe, and organized themselves along similar lines, were also increasingly antagonistic to Jews.

Egyptian Banks were a common destination for European Jews transferring money from central Europe and a for those Jews escaping the Fascist regimes.&lt;ref&gt;Gudrun Krämer (1989) The Jews in modern Egypt, 1914-1952 I.B.Tauris, ISBN 1850431000 p 158&lt;/ref&gt;
 
By the 1940s, the situation worsened. Sporadic [[pogroms]] took place in 1942 onwards. In 1945, the [[1945 Cairo pogrom|Jewish quarter of Cairo was severely damaged]]. As the [[Partition of Palestine]] and the founding of Israel drew closer, hostility strengthened, fed also by press attacks on all foreigners accompanying the rising ethnocentric nationalism of the age. In 1947, the Company Laws set quotas for employing Egyptian nationals in incorporated firms, requiring that 75% of salaried employees, and 90% of all workers be Egyptian. As Jews were denied citizenship as a rule, this constrained Jewish and foreign owned entrepreneurs to reduce recruitment for employment positions from their own ranks. The law also required that just over half of the paid-up capital of joint stock companies be Egyptian.

===1948===
[[File:Egyptian Alexandria Jewish girls during BatMitzva.jpg|thumb|right|290px|Egyptian [[Alexandria]] Jewish girls during [[Bar and Bat Mitzvah|Bat Mitzva]].]]
[[File:Egyptian Alexandria Jews. Choir of Rabbin Moshe Cohen in Samuel Menashe synagogue. Alexandria.jpg|thumb|right|290px|Egyptian Alexandria Jewish choir of Rabbin Moshe Cohen at Samuel Menashe synagogue. Alexandria.]]
After the foundation of Israel in 1948, difficulties multiplied for Egyptian Jews. That year, bombings of Jewish areas killed 70 Jews and wounded nearly 200, while riots claimed many more lives.&lt;ref&gt;Mangoubi, Rami, &quot;A Jewish Refugee Answers Youssef Ibrahim&quot;, ''Middle East Times'', October 30, 2004.&lt;/ref&gt; During the Arab-Israeli war, the famous Cicurel department store near Cairo's Opera Square was firebombed. The government helped with funds to rebuild it, but it was again burnt down in 1952, and eventually passed into Egyptian control.

The [[Lavon Affair]] of 1954, in which an Israeli sabotage operation designed to discredit [[Gamal Abdel Nasser]] and perhaps also to derail secret negotiations with Egypt proposed by [[Moshe Sharett]], blew up Western targets (without causing deaths), led to deeper distrust of Jews, from whose community key agents in the operation had been recruited. In his summing up statement Fu’ad al-Digwi, the prosecutor at their trial,  repeated the official government stance:

&lt;blockquote&gt;'The Jews of Egypt are living among us and are sons of Egypt. Egypt makes no difference between its sons whether Moslems, Christians, or Jews. These defendants happen to be Jews who reside in Egypt, but we are trying them because they committed crimes against Egypt, although they are Egypt's sons.'&lt;ref name=&quot;Joel_Beinin&quot;/&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

Though not one person was killed in the Lavon affair, two members of the ring, Dr. Moussa Marzouk and Shmuel Azzar, received a death sentence.  By contrast, six members from Dr. Marzouk's extended family were killed in the 1948 massacres, and yet no one was arrested.{{Citation needed|date=May 2010}}  In 1953, a cousin of Dr. Marzouk, Kamal Massuda, was killed in cold blood, and the authorities did not make arrests.{{Citation needed|date=May 2010}}   Other members of the sabotage rings had families who lost their livelihood after the notorious 1947 Company Law was implemented.  

In the immediate aftermath of trilateral invasion during the [[Suez Crisis]] of [[1956]], on November 23 by Britain France and Israel, a proclamation was issued stating that 'all Jews are Zionists and enemies of the state', and it promised that they would be soon expelled. Some 25,000 Jews, almost half of the Jewish community left, mainly for Europe, the United States and South America, and Israel, after being forced to sign declarations that they were leaving voluntarily, and agreed with the confiscation of their assets. Some 1,000 more Jews were imprisoned. Similar measures were enacted against British and French nationals in retaliation for the invasion. In Joel Beinin's summary: &quot;Between 1919 and 1956, the entire Egyptian Jewish community, like the Cicurel firm, was transformed from a national asset into a [[fifth column]].&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;Joel_Beinin&quot;/&gt;

After the 1967 war, more confiscations took place. Rami Mangoubi, who lived in Cairo at the time, states that nearly all Egyptian Jewish men between the ages of 17 and 60 were either thrown out of the country immediately, or taken to the detention centres of Abou Za'abal and Tura, where they were incarcerated and tortured for more than three years.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.jpost.com/Home/Article.aspx?id=63211 |last=Mangoubi |first=Rami |title=My Longest 10 Minutes |publisher=''The Jerusalem Post'' |date=May 31, 2007 |accessdate=May 8, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; The eventual result was the almost complete disappearance of the Jewish community in Egypt; less than a hundred or so remain today.  Most Egyptian Jews fled to Israel (35,000), Brazil (15,000), France (10,000), the US (9,000) and Argentina (9,000).{{Citation needed|date=November 2007}}  Today, anti-Jewish feelings run high in Egypt, and is common in the media. The last Jewish wedding in Egypt took place in 1984.

==Works by Egyptian Jews on their communities==
*Ronit Matalon, ''Zeh ‘im ha-panim eleynu'' ('The one facing us') (novel of life in an Egyptian Jewish family)
*Yahudiya Misriya (pseudonym of Giselle Littman, [[Bat Ye'or]]), ''Les juifs en Egypte: Aperçu sur 3000 ans d'histoire,'' Geneva: Editions de l'Avenir, 1971 (In the Hebrew trans.''Yehudei mitzrayim'', 1974, the authoress is called Bat-Ye’or).
*[[Lucette Lagnado]], &quot;The Man in the White Sharkskin Suit&quot; (an autobiography of a Jewish family during their years in Egypt and after they emigrated to the United States)
* Mangoubi, Rami, &quot;My Longest 10 Minutes&quot;, The Jerusalem Post Magazine, May 31, 2007.  A Cairo Jewish boyhood during and after the Six Day War.
* &quot;Out of Egypt&quot; by Andre Aciman, Picador, 1994
* &quot;Growing Up Under Pharaoh&quot;, by Maurice M. Mizrahi, 2004, http://www.hsje.org/growing_up_under_pharaoh.htm

==See also==

===Ancient history===
*[[Elephantine papyri]]
*[[Jewish temple at Elephantine]]
*[[Judaism and ancient Egyptian religion]]
*[[Land of Onias]]
*[[Philo]]

===Modern history===
*[[History of the Jews under Muslim rule]]
*[[Suez Crisis]]
*[[Israel-Egypt Peace Treaty]]
*[[Jewish exodus from Arab lands]]

===Institutions===

*[[Ben Ezra Synagogue]] (Cairo)
*[[Eliyahu Hanavi Synagogue (Alexandria)]]
*[[Chaar Hachamaim Synagogue (Cairo)]]
*[[Cairo Geniza]]
*[[List of synagogues in Egypt]]
*Tomb of Rabbi [[Yaakov Abuhatzeira]] ([[Damanhur]])

==References==
{{reflist}}
*{{JewishEncyclopedia}}
*''The Works of Josephus, Complete and Unabridged'', New Updated Edition (Translated by William Whiston, A.M.) Peabody Massachusetts:Hendrickson Publishers, 1987 (Fifth Printing:Jan.1991): ''Antiquities of the Jews'', Book 12, chapters 1 and 2, pp.&amp;nbsp;308–9
*Gudrun Krämer, ''The Jews in Modern Egypt, 1914–1952,'' Seattle: University of Washington Press, 1989
*Mourad El-Kodsi, ''The Karaite Jews of Egypt, 1882–1986,'' Lyons, NY: Wilprint, 1987.

==External links==
* [http://www.bassatine.net Bassatine News: The only Jewish newsletter reporting directly from Egypt]
* [http://www.jewishvirtuallibrary.org/jsource/anti-semitism/egjews.html Jewish Virtual Library]
* [http://www.hsje.org/homepage.htm Historical Society of Jews from Egypt]
* [http://www.metimes.com/storyview.php?StoryID=20041030-025149-4018r A Jewish Refugee Answers... Middle East Times, October 30, 2004.]
* [http://www.iajegypt.org/index.shtml The International Association of Jews from Egypt]
* [http://www.jta.org/page_view_story.asp?intarticleid=17413&amp;intcategoryid=1 Jews expelled from Egypt left behind a piece of their hearts]
* [http://www.ancientsudan.org/articles_jewish_elephantine.html Briefly Investigating the Origin of the Ancient Jewish Community at Elephantine: A Review ]
* [http://www.jstandard.com/articles/2059/1/Egyptian-Jews-look-back-with-anger%2C-love Egyptian Jews look back with anger, love]
* [http://www.guernicamag.com/features/240/the_last_jews_of_cairo/ Guernica Magazine (guernica.com) on the last Jews of Cairo]
*[[Joel Beinin|Beinin, Joel]]: [http://ark.cdlib.org/ark:/13030/ft2290045n/ ''The Dispersion Of Egyptian Jewry Culture, Politics, And The Formation Of A Modern Diaspora''] Berkeley:   University of California Press,   c1998.   Amer Univ in Cairo Pr, 2005, ISBN 9774248902
* [http://www.jimena.org/ Jews Indigenous to the Middle East and North Africa ]
* [http://www.abc.net.au/rn/latenightlive/stories/2007/2101814.htm A Family's Exodus from Cairo to the New World. Lucette Lagnado remembers her childhood]
* [http://www.tabletmag.com/life-and-religion/58487/out-of-egypt/ Out of Egypt]
{{Africa topic|History of the Jews in}}
{{Ancient Near East}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:History Of The Jews In Egypt}}
[[Category:Jewish Egyptian history| ]]

[[ar:يهود مصر]]
[[fr:Histoire des Juifs en Égypte]]
[[he:יהדות מצרים]]
[[arz:يهود مصر]]
[[pl:Historia Żydów w Egipcie]]
[[ru:История евреев в Египте]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
