<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="1935496" ns="0" title="Film poster"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">A '''movie poster''' is a [[poster]] used to advertise a [[film]]. Studios often print several posters that vary in size and content for various domestic and international markets. They  normally contain an image with text.  Today's posters often feature photographs of the main actors.  Prior to the 1990s, illustrations instead of photos were far more common.  The text on movie posters usually contains the film title in large lettering and often the names of the main actors. It may also include a [[tag line]], the name of the director, names of characters, the release date, etc.  

Movie posters are displayed inside and on the outside of [[movie theater]]s, and elsewhere on the street or in shops. The same images appear in the film exhibitor's [[pressbook]] and may also be used on websites, DVD (and historically VHS) packaging, flyers, advertisements in newspapers and magazines, etc.

Movie posters have been used since the earliest public exhibitions of film. They began as outside placards listing the programme of (short) films to be shown inside the hall or movie theater. By the early 1900s, they began to feature [[illustration]]s of a scene from each individual film or an array of overlaid images from several scenes. Other movie posters have used artistic interpretations of a scene or even the theme of the film, represented in a wide variety of artistic styles.

==History==
[[File:Rudolph Valentino movie poster bullfight.jpeg|thumb|right|250px|[[Rudolph Valentino]] in ''Blood and Sand'', 1922]]
Originally, movie posters were produced for the exclusive use by the theatres exhibiting the film the poster was created for, and the copies of the posters were required to be returned to the distributor after the film left the theatre. In the [[United States]], movie posters were usually returned to a nation-wide operation called the [[National Screen Service]] (NSS) which printed and distributed most of the film posters for the studios between 1940 and 1984. As an economy measure, the NSS regularly recycled posters that were returned, sending them back out to be used again at another theatre. During this time, a film could stay in circulation for several years, and so many old movie posters were badly worn before being retired into storage at an NSS warehouse (most often, they were thrown away when they were no longer needed or had become too worn to be used again). Those posters which were not returned were often thrown away by the theatre owner, but some movie posters found their way into the hands of collectors.{{Citation needed|date=May 2011}}

Beginning in the 1980s, the American [[film studio]]s began taking over direct production and distribution of their posters from the National Screen Service and the process of making and distributing movie posters became decentralised in that country. {{Citation needed|date=May 2011}}

==Collecting==
The collecting of [[movie memorabilia]] began with such things as scrap-books, autographs, photographs, and industry magazines, but quickly expanded in the post-[[World War II]] era. Collectors began seeking out original advertising material, and the classic &quot;[[one sheet]]&quot; movie poster became the pinnacle object to own for any given film. Other material, such as lobby cards, other-sized posters, international posters, personality posters, and glass slides also began to become highly sought after.  Today, the field of movie memorabilia collecting has grown into an internationally recognised community of increasingly serious and financially secure collectors, making it one of the fastest areas of speculation for investment.{{Citation needed|date=January 2007}}
[[Image:Vintage Potemkin.jpg|thumb|155px|&lt;center&gt;''[[The Battleship Potemkin]]'', 1925&lt;/center&gt;]]

After the National Screen Service ceased most of its movie poster printing and distribution operations in 1985, some of the posters which they had stored in warehouses around the United States ended up in the hands of private collectors and movie poster dealers. Today there is a thriving collectibles market in movie posters.  Some have become very valuable among collectors, with a few rare examples being auctioned for US$500,000 or more. The record price for a poster was set on November 15, 2005 when US$690,000 was paid for a poster of [[Fritz Lang]]'s 1927 film ''[[Metropolis (film)|Metropolis]]'' from the Reel Poster Gallery in London.&lt;ref name=&quot;metropolis&quot;&gt;{{cite news|url=http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/entertainment/4438948.stm |title=Lang movie poster fetches record |publisher=BBC News |date=2005-11-15 |accessdate=2009-01-11}}&lt;/ref&gt; Other early horror and science fiction posters are known to bring tremendous prices as well, with an example from [[The Mummy (1932 film)|The Mummy]] realizing $452,000 in a 1997 [[Sotheby's]] auction,&lt;ref name=metropolis /&gt; and posters from both [[The Black Cat (1934 film)|The Black Cat]] and [[Bride of Frankenstein]] selling for $334,600 in various [[Heritage Auctions|Heritage]] Auctions.&lt;ref&gt;[http://movieposters.ha.com/common/search_results.php?ic=homepage_search&amp;Nty=1&amp;N=54+790+231]&lt;/ref&gt; The 1931 [[Frankenstein (1931 film)|Frankenstein]] 6-sheet poster, of which only 1 copy is known to exist, is considered to be the most valuable movie poster in the world.{{Citation needed|date=July 2008}}.

As a result of market demand, some of the more popular older movie posters have been reproduced either under license or illegally.  Although the artwork on reproductions is the same as originals, reproductions can often be distinguished by size, printing quality, and paper type.  Several websites on the Internet offer &quot;authentication&quot; tests to distinguish originals from reproductions.

Original movie posters distributed to theaters and other poster venues (such as bus stops) by the movie studios are never sold directly to the public. However, most modern movie posters are produced in large quantities and normally become available for purchase by collectors indirectly through various secondary markets such as Ebay. Accordingly, most modern posters are not rare. However, some recent posters, such as the recalled Pulp Fiction &quot;Lucky Strikes&quot; United States one sheet poster, are quite rare and valuable.

==Types of movie posters==
===Lobby cards===
[[Image:Birth of a Nation Poster - Seattle.jpg|left|thumb|155px|Window card for the 1915 film, ''[[Birth of a Nation]]'']]
[[Image:MaryPickford4.jpg|thumb|155px|A lobby card of a 1921 [[Mary Pickford]] film.]]
Lobby cards are like posters but smaller, usually {{convert|11|×|14|in|cm|abbr=on}}, also {{convert|8|×|10|in|cm|abbr=on}} before 1930. Lobby cards are collected and their value depends on their age, quality and popularity.  Typically issued in sets of eight, each featuring a different scene from the film. In unusual circumstances, some releases were promoted with larger (12 cards) or smaller sets (6 cards). &quot;The Running Man&quot; set, for example had only six (6) cards, whereas the earlier classic &quot;The Italian Job&quot; set spanned twelve photographs. Films released by major production companies experiencing financial difficulties sometimes had no accompanying &quot;lobby set&quot; at all. Perhaps one of the most notable examples of this scenario would be Michael Mann's cult classic ''[[Manhunter (film)|Manhunter]]'' (1986), for which no USA lobby card set was ever printed. Notably, there was also no 10&quot; x 8&quot; colour set of cards for John Carpenter's cult horror classic ''[[Halloween (1978 film)|Halloween]]'' (1978)

In the United Kingdom, sets of lobby cards are more typically referred to as &quot;Front Of House&quot; cards. However, this can sometimes also refer to black and white press photographs—in addition to the more typical 8 × 10&amp;nbsp;inch lobby card style promotional devices.

The Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library at Yale University holds a collection of lobby cards from silent western films that date between 1910 and 1930.&lt;ref&gt;[http://beinecke.library.yale.edu/digitallibrary/lobbycards.html The Western Silent Films Lobby Cards Collection, 1910-1930.] Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library at Yale University. Retrieved on 2009-07-08.&lt;/ref&gt;

===Teaser poster===
A '''teaser poster''' or '''advance poster''' is an early promotional movie poster, containing a basic image or design without revealing too much information such as the plot, theme, and characters.  The purpose is to incite awareness and generate [[Promotion (marketing)|hype]] for the film.  A [[tagline]] may be included. There are some instances when teaser posters are issued long in advance before the film goes into production, although they are issued during the film development.

===Character posters===
&lt;!--  Commented out because image was deleted: [[Image:TMNT Character poster.jpg|thumb|150px|right|[[TMNT (film)|TMNT]] character poster]] --&gt;
For a film  with an [[ensemble cast]] there may be a set of '''character posters''', each featuring an individual character from the film. Usually it contains the name of the actor/actress, with or without the name of the character played. It may also include a tagline that reflects the quality of the character.

===Motion posters===
The most recent type of poster in which the poster is animated.

===Remix posters===
A poster that has been altered or &quot;remixed&quot; to change the intent of the original movie poster.  A remixed poster often contains a political or comedic message, using the credibility of the movie poster format to deliver the message of whoever is creating the remixed poster.

==Film poster sizes==
[[Image:Seven Samurai poster.jpg|thumb|155px|&lt;center&gt;''[[Seven Samurai]]'' (1954)&lt;/center&gt;]]
Movie posters come in different sizes and styles depending on the country. The most common are listed below.&lt;ref name=&quot;Poster Sizes&quot;&gt;[http://www.mpag.co.uk/posterglossary.htm Movie Poster Art Gallery - Glossary Sizes] Accessed 06/Dec/2007&lt;/ref&gt;

===United States===

Note: In the United States motion pictures are normally referenced as &quot;movies.&quot; The word &quot;film&quot; is far less common and generally used only to refer to an &quot;art house&quot; or foreign production.  Accordingly, in the United States, and most English-speaking countries, promotional posters are almost always referenced as &quot;movie posters&quot; rather than &quot;film posters.&quot;

* [[One sheet (film)|One sheet]], 27&amp;nbsp;inches by 40&amp;nbsp;inches (686x1020mm), portrait format
* Bus stop, 40&amp;nbsp;inches by 60&amp;nbsp;inches (1016mm x 1524mm), portrait format

The following sizes were in common use in the United States prior to the mid-1980s, but have since been phased out of production:{{Citation needed|date=July 2008}}

* One sheet, 27&amp;nbsp;inches by 41&amp;nbsp;inches (686x1040mm), portrait format (this size is one inch longer than the modern One sheet)
* Display (aka Half-sheet), 22&amp;nbsp;inches by 28&amp;nbsp;inches (559x711mm), landscape format
* Insert, size 14&amp;nbsp;inches by 36&amp;nbsp;inches (356x914mm), portrait format
* Window Card, 14&amp;nbsp;inches by 22&amp;nbsp;inches (356x559mm), portrait format; typically has blank space at top to accommodate promotional text for local theatre
* Two sheet, 41&amp;nbsp;inches by 54&amp;nbsp;inches (1040x1370mm), either landscape format or portrait format
* Three sheet, 41&amp;nbsp;inches by 81&amp;nbsp;inches (1040x2060mm), portrait format; usually assembled from two separate pieces
* 30x40, 30&amp;nbsp;inches by 40&amp;nbsp;inches (762x1016mm), portrait format&lt;ref name=&quot;MovieArt.net&quot;&gt;[http://movieart.net/articles-and-resources/collecting-posters/collecting-basics-part-two/ MovieArt.net]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;AllMovieReplicas.com&quot;&gt;[http://www.allmoviereplicas.com/Movie_Poster_Description-sp-122.html AllMovieReplicas.com]&lt;/ref&gt;
* 40x60, 40&amp;nbsp;inches by 60&amp;nbsp;inches (1016x1524mm), portrait format&lt;ref name=&quot;MovieArt.net&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;AllMovieReplicas.com&quot;/&gt;
* Six sheet, 81&amp;nbsp;inches by 81&amp;nbsp;inches (2060x2060mm), a square format; usually assembled from four separate pieces
* Twenty four sheet, 246&amp;nbsp;inches by 108&amp;nbsp;inches (6250x2740mm), landscape format often called a billboard

===United Kingdom===
* Quad, size 30&amp;nbsp;inches by 40&amp;nbsp;inches (762x1020mm), landscape format
* Double crown, size 20&amp;nbsp;inches by 30&amp;nbsp;inches (508x762mm), portrait format
* One-sheet, size 27&amp;nbsp;inches by 40&amp;nbsp;inches (686x1020mm), portrait format
* Three sheet, size 40&amp;nbsp;inches by 81&amp;nbsp;inches (1020x2060mm), portrait format

===Australia===
* [[Daybill]], size 13&amp;nbsp;inches by 30&amp;nbsp;inches (330x762mm), portrait format (before the 1960s, Daybills were 36&amp;nbsp;inches long)
* [[One sheet]], size 27&amp;nbsp;inches by 40&amp;nbsp;inches (686x1040mm), portrait format

==Billing block==
{{main|Billing (filmmaking)}}
The [[credits]] for the film that appear in condensed type on contemporary film posters and other advertising copy are referred to as the [[billing block]].

==Notable movie poster artists==
[[File:Attackofthe50ftwoman.jpg|thumb|''[[Attack of the 50 Foot Woman]],'' an iconic poster by [[Reynold Brown]].]]
Normally, the artist is not identified on the film poster and, in many cases, the artist is anonymous.  However, several artists have become well-known because of their outstanding illustrations on movie posters, including the following. Indeed, some artists, such as Drew Struzan, often sign their poster artwork and the signature is included on distributed posters.

;[[John Alvin]]
:Examples: ''[[Blade Runner]]'', ''[[The Lion King]]'', ''[[E.T. the Extra-Terrestrial]]''

;[[Richard Amsel]]
:Examples: ''[[Raiders of the Lost Ark]]'', ''[[The Sting]]''

;[[Saul Bass]]
:Examples: ''[[Vertigo (film)|Vertigo]]'', ''[[The Shining (film)|The Shining]]''

;[[Reynold Brown]][http://arglebarglin.blogspot.com/2006/07/reynold-brown-at-work.html]
:Examples: ''[[Attack of the 50 Foot Woman]]'', ''[[Creature from the Black Lagoon]]'', ''[[The Incredible Shrinking Man]]'', ''[[The Time Machine (1960 film)|The Time Machine]]''[http://www.americanartarchives.com/brown,reynold.htm]

;[[Tom Chantrell]]
:Examples: ''[[Von Ryan's Express]]'', ''[[Zulu Dawn]]'', ''[[The Land That Time Forgot (1975 film)|The Land That Time Forgot]]''

;[[Jack Davis (cartoonist)|Jack Davis]]
:Examples: ''[[It's a Mad, Mad, Mad, Mad World]]'', ''[[Viva Max!]]'', ''[[Kelly's Heroes]]''

;[[Frank Frazetta]]
:Examples: ''[[What's New Pussycat?]]''

;[[Bill Gold]]
:Examples: ''[[Casablanca (film)|Casablanca]], [[A Clockwork Orange (film)|A Clockwork Orange]]'', ''[[For Your Eyes Only (film)|For Your Eyes Only]]''

;[[Mitchell Hooks]]
:Examples: ''[[Dr. No (film)|Dr. No]]'', ''[[The Sand Pebbles (film)|The Sand Pebbles]]'', ''[[El Dorado (1966 film)|El Dorado]]''.

;[[The Brothers Hildebrandt]]
:Examples: ''[[Star Wars Episode IV: A New Hope]]'' (&quot;Style B&quot; re-release),&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://posterwire.com/archives/2006/06/13/tim-hildebrandt/ |title=Tim Hildebrandt |publisher=Posterwire.com |date=June 13, 2006 |accessdate=2009-03-16}}&lt;/ref&gt; ''[[Barbarella (film)|Barbarella]]'' (1979 re-release)

;[[Tom Jung]]
:Examples: ''[[Star Wars Episode IV: A New Hope|Star Wars (Style A)]]'', ''[[Tom Jung| The Empire Strikes Back (Style B)]]'',''[[Papillon (film)|Papillon]]'',''[[The Lord of the Rings (1978 film)|The Lord of the Rings]]'',''[[Tom Jung|Gone With The Wind (re-release)]]

;[[Mort Künstler]]
:Examples: ''[[The Taking of Pelham One Two Three (1974 film)|The Taking of Pelham One Two Three]]'', ''[[The Hindenburg (film)|The Hindenburg]]''

;[[Frank McCarthy (artist)|Frank McCarthy]]&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.americanartarchives.com/mccarthy,f.htm |title=Frank McCarthy |publisher=American Art Archives |date= |accessdate=2009-01-11}}&lt;/ref&gt;
:Examples: ''[[The Ten Commandments (1956 film)|The Ten Commandments]]'', ''[[The Train (1964 film)|The Train]]'', ''[[The Dirty Dozen]]'', ''[[On Her Majesty's Secret Service (film)|On Her Majesty's Secret Service]]''

;[[Robert McGinnis]]&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.americanartarchives.com/mcginnis.htm |title=Robert McGinnis |publisher=American Art Archives |date= |accessdate=2009-01-11}}&lt;/ref&gt;
:Examples: ''[[Casino Royale (1967 film)|Casino Royale]]'', ''[[Breakfast at Tiffany's (film)|Breakfast at Tiffany's]]''

;[[Bob Peak]]
:Examples: ''[[Our Man Flint]]'', ''[[Camelot (film)|Camelot]]'', ''[[Apocalypse Now]]'', ''[[The Spy Who Loved Me (film)|The Spy Who Loved Me]]''

;[[John Solie]]
:Examples: ''[[Shaft's Big Score]]'', ''[[Capone (film)|Capone]]''&lt;ref&gt;http://www.johnsolie.com/?dir_cat=29061&lt;/ref&gt;

;[[Stenberg brothers|Vladimir and Georgii Stenberg]]
:Examples: ''[[Man with a Movie Camera]]''

;[[Drew Struzan]]
:Examples: ''[[Star Wars]]'', ''[[E.T: The Extra-Terrestrial]]'', ''[[Indiana Jones (franchise)|Indiana Jones]]'', ''[[Back to the Future]]'', ''[[The Thing (1982 film)|The Thing]]'', ''[[Jurassic Park (film)|Jurassic Park]]'', ''[[Harry Potter and the Sorcerer's Stone (film)|Harry Potter and the Sorcerer's Stone]]''

;[[Howard Terpning]]
:Examples: ''[[The Guns of Navarone (film)|The Guns of Navarone]]'', ''[[Cleopatra (1963 film)|Cleopatra]]'', ''[[The Sound of Music (film)|The Sound of Music]]''

==European movie poster artists==
* France
** [[Boris Grinsson]]
** [[Jean Mascii]]
** [[Yves Thos]]

* Italy
** [[Anselmo Ballester]]
** [[Alfredo Capitani]]
** [[Renato Casaro]]
** [[Averado Ciriello]]
** [[Renato Fratini]]
** [[Luigi Martinati]]

* Spain
** [[Macario Gomez]]

==Awards==
The annual [[Key Art Awards]], sponsored by ''[[The Hollywood Reporter]]'', include awards for best movie poster in the categories of comedy, drama, action adventure, teaser, and international film. The ''Hollywood Reporter'' defines the term &quot;key art&quot; as &quot;the singular, iconographic image that is the foundation upon which a movie's marketing campaign is built.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite press release|url=http://www.moviecitynews.com/Notepad/2003/030623_pr.html |title=Key Art Awards press release |publisher=Movie City News |date=2003-06-23 |accessdate=2009-01-11}}&lt;/ref&gt; In 2006, the original poster for ''[[The Silence of the Lambs (film)|The Silence of the Lambs]]'' was named best film poster &quot;of the past 35 years&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.hollywoodreporter.com/hr/search/article_display.jsp?vnu_content_id=1002690024 'Sin City' place to be at Key Art Awards] Hollywood Reporter. Retrieved 2007-10-07&lt;/ref&gt;

==References==
{{reflist}}

==External links==
&lt;!--========================({{No More Links}})============================
    | PLEASE BE CAUTIOUS IN ADDING MORE LINKS TO THIS ARTICLE. WIKIPEDIA  |
    | IS NOT A COLLECTION OF LINKS NOR SHOULD IT BE USED FOR ADVERTISING. |
    |                                                                     |
    |           Excessive or inappropriate links WILL BE DELETED.         |
    | See [[Wikipedia:External links]] &amp; [[Wikipedia:Spam]] for details.  |
    |                                                                     |
    | If there are already plentiful links, please propose additions or   |
    | replacements on this article's discussion page, or submit your link |
    | to the relevant category at the Open Directory Project (dmoz.org)   |
    | and link back to that category using the {{dmoz}} template.         |
    =======================({{No More Links}})=============================--&gt;

{{commons category|Movie posters}}
* [http://www.allposterforum.com AllPosterForum.com: Forum for movie poster collectors (founded 2009)]
* [http://www.filmfan.com Filmfan.com: The Internet's first movie poster forum (founded 1995)]
* [http://www.impawards.com IMPAwards.com: Movie poster images,  and annual awards]
* [http://www.moviepostercollectors.com MoviePosterCollectors.com: Reference, authentication, and showcase website]
* [http://www.movieposterforum.com MoviePosterForum.com: Discussion and Authentication (founded 2005)]
* [http://www.movieposterdb.com MPDB.com: Movie poster database and images]
* [http://www.mposter.com: MPoster.com: Movie poster images]
* [http://www.stylec.yuku.com Not Strictly For General Exhibition: Discussion forum (founded 2005)]
* [http://beinecke.library.yale.edu/digitallibrary/lobbycards.html Yale Beinecke Library Western Silent Films Lobby Cards Collection, 1912-1930]



[[Category:Film advertising material]]
[[Category:Posters]]
[[Category:Film and video terminology]]

[[ar:أفيش]]
[[de:Filmplakat]]
[[es:Cartel de cine]]
[[it:Locandina]]
[[mk: Филмски плакат]]
[[nl:Filmposter]]
[[ja:映画ポスター]]
[[sr:Филмски постер]]
[[fi:Elokuvajuliste]]
[[sv:Filmaffisch]]
[[tr:Film afişi]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
