<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="194056" ns="0" title="Rollie Fingers"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Infobox MLB player
|name=Rollie Fingers
|image= Rolliefingers.JPG
|width=260
|caption= 
|position=[[Pitcher]]
|bats=Right
|throws=Right
|birth_date={{birth date and age|1946|8|25}}
|birth_place=[[Steubenville, Ohio]]
|debutdate=September 15
|debutyear=1968
|debutteam=Oakland Athletics
|finaldate=September 17
|finalyear=1985
|finalteam=Milwaukee Brewers
|stat1label=[[Games pitched]]
|stat1value=944
|stat2label=[[Win–loss record (pitching)|Win–Loss record]]
|stat2value=114–118
|stat3label=[[Earned run average]]
|stat3value=2.90
|stat4label=[[Strikeout]]s
|stat4value=1,299
|stat5label=[[Save (baseball)|Saves]]
|stat5value=341
|teams=&lt;nowiki&gt;&lt;/nowiki&gt;
* [[Oakland Athletics]] ({{by|1968}}–{{by|1976}})
* [[San Diego Padres]] ({{by|1977}}–{{by|1980}})
* [[Milwaukee Brewers]] ({{by|1981}}–{{by|1985}})
|highlights=&lt;nowiki&gt;&lt;/nowiki&gt;
* 7× [[Major League Baseball All-Star Game|All-Star]] selection ([[1973 Major League Baseball All-Star Game|1973]], [[1974 Major League Baseball All-Star Game|1974]], [[1975 Major League Baseball All-Star Game|1975]], [[1976 Major League Baseball All-Star Game|1976]], [[1978 Major League Baseball All-Star Game|1978]], [[1981 Major League Baseball All-Star Game|1981]], [[1982 Major League Baseball All-Star Game|1982]])
* 3× [[World Series]] champion ({{wsy|1972}}, {{wsy|1973}}, {{wsy|1974}})
* 1981 [[Major League Baseball Most Valuable Player Award|AL MVP]]
* 1981 [[Cy Young Award|AL Cy Young Award]]
* 1974 [[World Series Most Valuable Player Award|World Series MVP]]
* 3× [[Rolaids Relief Man Award|NL Rolaids Relief Man of the Year]] (1977, 1978, 1980)
* 1981 [[Rolaids Relief Man Award|AL Rolaids Relief Man of the Year]]
* [[Oakland Athletics#Retired numbers|Oakland Athletics #34]] retired
* [[Milwaukee Brewers#Retired numbers|Milwaukee Brewers #34]] retired
|hofdate={{by|1992}}
|hofvote=81.16%
}}
'''Roland Glen Fingers''' (born August 25, 1946) is a former [[Major League Baseball]] [[relief pitcher]]. During his 18-year baseball career, he pitched for the [[Oakland Athletics]] (1968&amp;ndash;76), [[San Diego Padres]] (1977&amp;ndash;80) and [[Milwaukee Brewers]] (1981&amp;ndash;85). He became only the second reliever to be elected to the [[National Baseball Hall of Fame]] in 1992. Fingers is also one of only a few MLB players to have his number retired by more than one club (Oakland Athletics and Milwaukee Brewers).

==Early life and minor league career==
Fingers was born in [[Steubenville, Ohio]] to George Michael Fingers and Edna Pearl (née Stafford) Fingers.&lt;ref name=PorterDL-2000-p470-471&gt;{{cite book |author=Porter, David L. |year=2000 |title=Biographical Dictionary of American Sports: A-F |publisher=Greenwood Publishing Group |pages=470–471 |isbn=978-0313311741 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |year=1986 |title=The Celebrity Who's Who |publisher=World Almanac |pages=118 |isbn=978-0345339904 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

His father (who had also played minor league baseball for the [[St. Louis Cardinals]] and roomed with [[Stan Musial]]), worked in a Steubenville steel mill.  George Fingers came home from work fed-up one day, said &quot;That's it, we're moving to California,&quot; and sold the house for [[United States dollar|$]]1500 and bought a car and took the family to [[Cucamonga, California|Cucamonga]].  They couldn't afford hotels so they slept in sleeping bags beside the highway.  After getting to California George Fingers had to eventually go back to work in another steel mill.&lt;ref name=TTMS-August-2010&gt;{{cite video |people=Fingers, Rollie; Tim McCarver |date=August 2010 |title=The Tim McCarver Show |publisher=JMJ Films Production |location=New York City }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=RosenbloomS-CT-2006&gt;{{cite news |author=Rosenbloom, Steve |date=September 14, 2006 |title=Rollie Fingers: Our Guy gets a handle on Hall of Famer known for his mustache -- and a deadly sinking fastball |newspaper=[[Chicago Tribune]] |page=Sports: 10 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

Fingers attended [[Upland High School]] in the city of [[Upland, California]], and then one semester at [[Chaffey College|Chaffey Junior College]].&lt;ref name=Reidenbaugh-and-Hoppel&gt;{{cite book |author=Reidenbaugh, Lowell; and Joe Hoppel |year=1988 |title=Baseball's Hall of Fame: Cooperstown, Where the Legends Live Forever |publisher=Random House Value Publishing |pages=89 |isbn=978-0517669860 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

The [[Los Angeles Dodgers]] offered Fingers a signing bonus of $20,000, but because they had a solid pitching staff, that included [[Sandy Koufax]] and [[Don Drysdale]], were already winning pennants, and their farm system appeared to be full of talented players, he felt he would not make it the major leagues for years.  He turned them down and signed for less money, $13,000 signing bonus, with the Kansas City Athletics, on Christmas Eve 1964.&lt;ref name=TTMS-August-2010 /&gt;&lt;ref name=RosenbloomS-CT-2006 /&gt;&lt;ref name=Reidenbaugh-and-Hoppel /&gt;  At first the A's didn't know whether to make him a pitcher or outfielder, but after deciding on pitcher, he was sent to Leesburg, Florida (Florida Southern League) for the 1965 season, then Modesto, California (California Athletic League) in 1966, and finally to Birmingham, Alabama (Southern League) for two seasons, 1967 and 1968.&lt;ref name=PorterDL-2000-p470-471 /&gt;  

Just nine days after he got married to his high school sweetheart and the Upland High School team statistician (Jill), on minor league opening day 1967 in Birmingham, Alabama (with the Birmingham A's), a ball hit Fingers in the face, breaking his cheekbone, jaw, and knocking out some teeth.  His jaw was wired shut for five weeks and when he returned he jumped every time the ball was hit; it took him about half the remaining season to get used to being on the mound again.&lt;ref name=TTMS-August-2010 /&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |author=Rosengren, John |year=2008 |title=Hammerin' Hank, George Almighty and the Say Hey Kid: The Year That Changed Baseball Forever |publisher=Sourcebooks |pages=38–39 |isbn=978-1402209567 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |author=Barra, Allen |year=2010 |title=Rickwood Field: A Century in America's Oldest Ballpark |publisher=W. W. Norton &amp; Company |pages=191 |isbn=978-0393069334 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |author=Watkins, Clarence |year=2010 |title=Baseball in Birmingham |publisher=Arcadia Publishing |pages=89 |isbn=978-0738566863 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Fingers and modern relief pitching==
Fingers was a starter throughout his minor league career.&lt;ref name=&quot;FlahertyT-TMJ-1990-12-20&quot;&gt;Flaherty, Tom (December 20, 1990). - &quot;What a relief for Fingers Manager's decision launched career that may land him in Hall of Fame&quot;. - ''[[The Milwaukee Journal]]''.&lt;/ref&gt;  He had started 19 games in 1970.&lt;ref name=&quot;FingersR-B-R&quot;&gt;[http://www.baseball-reference.com/players/f/fingero01.shtml Rollie Fingers]. - Baseball-Reference.com.&lt;/ref&gt;  But a May 15, 1971 start against the Royals in Kansas City would be his last in regular rotation (he gave up one run on four hits in five full innings; final score Royals 5 - A's 4).&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.baseball-reference.com/boxes/KCA/KCA197105150.shtml Athletics @ Royals - Saturday, May 15, 1971]. - Baseball-Reference.com.&lt;/ref&gt;  He came in on May 21, 1971 in the first inning, after [[Blue Moon Odom]] gave up three runs and three walks facing eight batters, against the Minnesota Twins in Oakland, and pitch 5-1/3 allowing three hits and two runs (Twins 10 - Oakland 1).&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.baseball-reference.com/boxes/OAK/OAK197105210.shtml Twins @ Athletics - Friday, May 21, 1971]. - Baseball-Reference.com.&lt;/ref&gt;  After that his earliest entrance to a game was in the sixth inning, and only three times. Mainly he came in the seventh, eighth, or ninth (he came in once in the eleventh and once in the twelfth).&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.baseball-reference.com/players/gl.cgi?n1=fingero01&amp;t=p&amp;year=1971 Rollie Ringers 1971 Pitching Gamelog]. - Baseball-Reference.com.&lt;/ref&gt;

By the end of May 1971 his manager with the Athletics, [[Dick Williams]], had made up his mind that Fingers would be the late inning closer.&lt;ref name=&quot;FlahertyT-TMJ-1990-12-20&quot; /&gt;  The following season, 1972, Fingers entered the game in the fifth four times, otherwise it was the sixth or later.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.baseball-reference.com/players/gl.cgi?n1=fingero01&amp;t=p&amp;year=1972 Rollie Ringers 1972 Pitching Gamelog]. - Baseball-Reference.com.&lt;/ref&gt;  He did start two games in 1973 (April 21 versus the California Angels at Oakland and May 7 against the Orioles at Baltimore;  His May 7, 1973 start was the last of his career), other than that he came in to the game no earlier than the sixth on three more occasions.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.baseball-reference.com/players/gl.cgi?n1=fingero01&amp;t=p&amp;year=1973 Rollie Ringers 1973 Pitching Gamelog]. - Baseball-Reference.com.&lt;/ref&gt;  After that he rarely entered a game before the seventh inning for the rest of his career.&lt;ref&gt;Rollie Ringers 1974–1985 Pitching Gamelogs. - Baseball-Reference.com.&lt;/ref&gt;

When Fingers reached the major leagues, the role of [[relief pitcher]]s was limited, as [[starting pitcher]]s rarely left games while holding a lead; but as team offense increased following the 1968 season, and especially with the [[American League|American League's]] introduction of the [[designated hitter]] in 1973, managers became more willing to replace starters in the late innings with a lead in order to forestall any late rallies by opponents. Through the 1960s, both leagues' annual [[save (sport)|saves]] leaders tended toward totals of 20&amp;ndash;25 saves; few pitchers remained in the role more than two or three years, with significant exceptions such as [[Roy Face]] and [[knuckleball]]er [[Hoyt Wilhelm]]. But in the 1970s, in an era allowing for greater opportunities for [[closer (baseball)|closers]] than had previously been available, Fingers' excellence in relief allowed him to gradually increase his annual saves totals past 30. In 1980 he broke Wilhelm's record of 227 saves, and eventually finished with 341, a record that stood until [[Jeff Reardon]] passed it in 1992.

Fingers is regarded as a pioneer of modern relief pitching, essentially defining the role of the closer for years to come. As had generally been true in baseball through the 1960s, Fingers was originally moved to the bullpen&amp;mdash;and eventually to his role as a closer&amp;mdash;due to struggles with starting. Before Fingers' time, a former starter's renewed success in the bullpen would have led back to a spot in the starting rotation; but since the successes of not only Fingers but also contemporaries such as [[Sparky Lyle]] and [[Goose Gossage]], it has been widely accepted that an excellent pitcher might actually provide a greater benefit to his team as a closer than as a third or fourth starter. (Gossage, for example, was moved to the starting rotation after a first few seasons in relief&amp;mdash;and he got clobbered despite pitching 17 complete games and was then moved back to the bullpen to stay.) As a result, later teams have been more willing to move successful starters&amp;mdash;notably [[Dennis Eckersley]], [[Dave Righetti]], and [[John Smoltz]]&amp;mdash;to the ''permanent'' role of closer, with no plans to bring them back to the rotation (although Smoltz bucked that trend by successfully returning to the rotation in [[2005 in baseball|2005]]). In 2006, [[Bruce Sutter]] became the first pitcher in baseball history elected to the Hall of Fame who never started a game in his major league career.

==Moustache==
In addition to his pitching ability, he was noted for his waxed [[handlebar moustache]] which he originally grew to get a [[USD|$]]300 bonus from Athletics owner [[Charles O. Finley]].

On the first day of [[spring training]] for the 1972 season, [[Reggie Jackson]] showed up with a beard.  In protest, Fingers and a few other players started going without shaving to force Jackson to shave off his beard, in the belief that management would also want Jackson to shave.  Instead, Finley, ever the showman who would do anything to sell tickets, then offered prize-money to the player who could best grow and maintain their facial hair until [[Opening Day]] (April 15 versus Minnesota).  Fingers went all out for the monetary incentive offered by Finley and patterned his moustache after the images of the players of the late 19th century.&lt;ref name=&quot;ArmoldE-YDR-2007-01-25&quot;&gt;Armold, Elijah (January 25, 2007). - &quot;A Man and His Famous Moustache: Hall of Fame reliever Rollie Fingers and his facial hair visited York Area Sports Night&quot;. - ''[[York Daily Record]]''.&lt;/ref&gt;  Taking it even further, Finley came up with &quot;Moustache Day&quot; at the ballpark, where any fan with a moustache could get in free.&lt;ref&gt;Conklin, Mike (August 22, 2003). -  Chin music - The art and science of pitchers' facial hair&quot;. - ''[[Chicago Tribune]]''.&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Catfish Hunter]] and [[Ken Holtzman]] also went for the bonus, but Fingers with his [[Snidely Whiplash]] took the prize.&lt;ref&gt;P-I News Services (February 10, 1986). - &quot;Horner Gives Bone Marrow-To Brother&quot;. - ''[[Seattle Post-Intelligencer]]''.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Slocum, Bob (February 10, 1987). - &quot;Are These Two Veterans Washed Up? Fingers: 'I feel real healthy'&quot;. - [[The San Diego Union-Tribune|''Evening Tribune'']].&lt;/ref&gt;  He would say later: &quot;Most of us would have grown one anywhere on our bodies for $300&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;Dickey, Glenn (September 16, 1986). - &quot;49ers Shopping For QB - How About Young?&quot;. - ''[[San Francisco Chronicle]]''.&lt;/ref&gt;  The players would become known as the &quot;Moustache Gang&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;Peters, Nick (October 14, 1990). - &quot;They've Met Before - In 1971, The A's Moustache Gang Met Cincinnati's Big Red Machine&quot;. - ''[[The Sacramento Bee]]''.&lt;/ref&gt;

Although most former A's players shaved their handlebar moustaches off after the team traded most of their players in 1975–76, Fingers maintained his after signing with the [[San Diego Padres]] as a free agent in 1977, and still has the moustache today.

At the end of his career, after being released by the [[Milwaukee Brewers]] the previous season, he was offered a contract by [[Pete Rose]] to play for the [[Cincinnati Reds]] for {{by|1986}}, but owner [[Marge Schott]] had a &quot;clean cut&quot; policy for her players (mandating that all players must be clean shaven).  Fingers's reply to Reds [[General manager (baseball)|general manager]] [[Bill Bergesch]] was: &quot;Well, you tell Marge Schott to shave her Saint Bernard, and I'll shave my moustache&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;ArmoldE-YDR-2007-01-25&quot; /&gt;

==Awards==
{{MLBBioRet
|Image  = OaklandRetired34.PNG
|Name   = Rollie Fingers
|Number = 34
|Team   = Oakland Athletics
|Year   = 1993
|}}
{{MLBBioRet
|Image  = Milret34.PNG
|Name   = Rollie Fingers
|Number = 34
|Team   = Milwaukee Brewers
|Year   = 1992
|}}

Fingers won both the [[American League]] [[Major League Baseball Most Valuable Player Award|MVP]] and [[Cy Young Award]] in 1981 while with Milwaukee.  In 1974 he was given the [[World Series MVP Award]] while with Oakland, earning two saves and one win. Rollie Fingers was on the Oakland A's team that accomplished the first modern-day &quot;three-peat,&quot; winning the World Series in '72, '73 and '74.  Fingers won the [[Rolaids Relief Man Award|Rolaids Relief Man of the Year Award]] in 1977, 1978, and 1980 with the Padres and in 1981 with the Brewers. He saved 29 games for the 1982 Brewers, but he pitched most of the season in pain and was forced to miss the Brewers' first (and to date, only) trip to the World Series&amp;mdash;where they were beaten in seven games by the Cardinals&amp;mdash;and any prospect of a showdown or two with Bruce Sutter, who proved vital to the Cardinals' winning effort.

In 1992 he was inducted into the [[Baseball Hall of Fame]], joining Wilhelm to become only the second reliever inducted (Eckersley, Sutter, and Gossage have since followed).  In 1999, he ranked Number 96 on [[The Sporting News list of Baseball's Greatest Players]], and was nominated as a finalist for the [[Major League Baseball]] All-Century Team. Fingers later pitched a season in the short-lived Senior Professional Baseball League.

Fingers is one of only eight players who have [[List of Major League Baseball retired numbers#Major League players and managers with numbers retired from multiple teams|had their numbers retired from more than one team]].

In 2000, Fingers was also inducted by the [[San Diego Hall of Champions]] into the honoring San Diego's finest athletes both on and off the playing surface.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.sdhoc.com/awards/hall-of-fame/baseball/rollie-fingers/ Rollie Fingers]. - [[San Diego Hall of Champions]].&lt;/ref&gt;

==Income tax controversy==
''[[Sports Illustrated]]'' reported on January 2, 2007 that Fingers owed the State of Wisconsin (in 2007) more than $1.4 million in income taxes dating back to his time with the Brewers (including $1.1 million in interest) and was at the time the seventh biggest tax delinquent in the state.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://sports.espn.go.com/mlb/news/story?id=2732444|title=Hall of Famer Fingers disputes tax delinquency |publisher=ESPN.com |accessdate=8 April 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;  Fingers disputed the claim, saying he was shocked when he learned of it in 2005 and that taxes were properly withheld from his Brewers paychecks.

On August 15, 2007, the Associated Press reported that Fingers' name had been removed from Wisconsin's delinquent tax list the previous month.  &quot;That's all been taken care of,&quot; he told the AP.  &quot;I've had more people try to tell me, 'You know, you owe 1.4 million dollars.'  I said, 'No, I don't.'  We got all that squared away.  I had to go all the way back to 1981 on my income taxes.  That's all been taken care of, and I did pay my taxes back then, so there's no problem.  The [[Wisconsin Department of Revenue|revenue department]]'s happy with me right now, so it's all been resolved.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.sportingnews.com/mlb/article/2007-08-14/fingers-says-wisconsin-tax-issues-resolved|title=Fingers says Wisconsin tax issues resolved |publisher=''The Sporting News'' |accessdate=8 April 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==In media==
[[File:Rollie Fingers All Star Parade 2008.jpg|thumb|right|upright|Fingers at the 2008 All-Star Game Red Carpet Parade.]]

===Books===
On April 1, 2009 Rollie Fingers and co-author Christopher &quot;Yellowstone&quot; Ritter released:

*''[[Rollie's Follies]]: A Hall of Fame Revue of Baseball Lists and Lore, Stats and Stories''
: - Cincinnati, Ohio: Clerisy Press. - ISBN 978-1-57860-335-0.

The work is a non-fiction baseball book that combines elements of humor, anecdotal storytelling, odd lists and historical trivia.&lt;ref&gt;Fingers, Rollie; and Christopher &quot;Yellowstone&quot; Ritter (2009). - ''Rollie's Follies: A Hall of Fame Revue of Baseball Lists and Lore, Stats and Stories''. - Cincinnati, Ohio: Clerisy Press. - ISBN 978-1-57860-335-0.&lt;/ref&gt; 

The first book inspired a sequel, released March 16, 2010 by Fingers and Ritter:&lt;ref&gt;Fingers, Rollie; and Christopher &quot;Yellowstone&quot; Ritter (2010). - ''The Rollie Fingers Baseball Bible: Lists and Lore, Stories and Stats''. - Cincinnati, Ohio: Clerisy Press. - ISBN 978-1-57860-342-8.&lt;/ref&gt;

*''[[The Rollie Fingers Baseball Bible]]: Lists and Lore, Stories and Stats''
: - Cincinnati, Ohio: Clerisy Press. - ISBN 978-1-57860-342-8.

===Television appearances===
Rollie Fingers and 4 other members of his family appeared on a 1983 episode of the [[game show]] ''[[Family Feud]]''.  After the opening theme, to honor Fingers, host [[Richard Dawson]] led the crowd in a chorus of &quot;[[Take Me Out to the Ball Game]]&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;Richmond, Peter (March 3, 1983). - &quot;Brewers Crossing Fingers&quot;. - ''[[The Miami Herald]]''.&lt;/ref&gt;  Fingers also appeared in a commercial for [[Pepsi Max]], playing himself in a spoof on the movie [[Field of Dreams]].

===Radio===
In 1994/1995 a comedy segment entitled &quot;Rollie TV&quot;, concerning a fictitious cable television channel devoted solely to the life of Rollie Fingers and helmed by a Rollie Fingers obsessed host named Greg Shuttlecock, aired once a week on The [[Steve Dahl]] Radio Show on [[WMVP]] AM1000 in [[Chicago]]. The idea and segment were created &amp; performed by Jeffery C. Johnson and Jim Toth. A &quot;Rollie TV&quot; skit had originally aired in 1993 on Toth &amp; Johnson's Chicago cable TV show &quot;Color TV&quot; and was then adapted in to segments for radio.

==See also==
* [[Bay Area Sports Hall of Fame]]
* [[List of Major League Baseball saves champions]]
* [[List of Major League Baseball all-time saves leaders]]
* [[List of Major League Baseball leaders in career wins]]
* [[Games finished]]

==References==
{{reflist}}

==External links==
{{Commons category}}
*[http://www.rfingers34.com/ Rollie Fingers Official Website]
*[http://www.rolliesbaseballfollies.com/ Rollie's Baseball Follies]
*{{bbhof|fingers-rollie}}
*{{baseballstats |mlb= |espn= |br=f/fingero01 |fangraphs=1004051 |cube=rollie-fingers}}
{| class=&quot;toccolours collapsible collapsed&quot; width=70% align=&quot;center&quot;
|-
! style=&quot;background:#ccccff&quot;| Accomplishments
|-
|
{{s-start}}
{{succession box | before = [[Reggie Jackson]] | title = [[World Series MVP Award|World Series MVP]]| years = [[1974 World Series|1974]] | after = [[Pete Rose]]}}
{{Succession box|title=[[List of Major League Baseball no-hitters|No-hit game]] |before=[[Ed Halicki]]| years= September 28, {{by|1975}} &lt;br&gt; (with [[Vida Blue|Blue]], [[Glenn Abbott|Abbott]] &amp; [[Paul Lindblad|Lindblad]])|after=[[Larry Dierker]]}}
{{succession box
| title  = [[List of Major League Baseball saves champions|National League Saves Champion]]
| years  = 1977–1978
| before = [[Rawly Eastwick]]
| after  = [[Bruce Sutter]]
}}
{{succession box
| title  = [[List of Major League Baseball saves champions|American League Saves Champion]]
| years  = 1981
| before = [[Goose Gossage]] &amp; [[Dan Quisenberry]]
| after  = [[Dan Quisenberry]]
}}
{{succession box | before = [[George Brett (baseball)|George Brett]] | title = [[MLB Most Valuable Player Award|American League Most Valuable Player]]| years = 1981 | after = [[Robin Yount]]}}
{{succession box | before = [[Steve Stone (baseball player)|Steve Stone]] | title = [[Cy Young Award|American League Cy Young Award]]| years = 1981 | after = [[Pete Vuckovich]]}}
{{s-end}}
|}

{{Oakland Athletics}}
{{1972 Oakland Athletics}}
{{1973 Oakland Athletics}}
{{1974 Oakland Athletics}}
{{AL Cy Young}}
{{AL MVPs}}
{{World Series MVPs}}
{{NL Relief Man Award Winners}}
{{AL Relief Man Award Winners}}
{{300 saves club}}
{{Athletics Retired Numbers}}
{{Brewers Retired Numbers}}
{{Milwaukee Brewers}}
{{1992 Baseball HOF}}
{{Pitchers in the Baseball Hall of Fame}}

{{Persondata &lt;!-- Metadata: see [[Wikipedia:Persondata]]. --&gt;
| NAME              =Fingers, Rollie
| ALTERNATIVE NAMES =
| SHORT DESCRIPTION =
| DATE OF BIRTH     =August 25, 1946
| PLACE OF BIRTH    =Steubenville, Ohio
| DATE OF DEATH     =
| PLACE OF DEATH    =
}}
{{DEFAULTSORT:Fingers, Rollie}}
[[Category:1946 births]]
[[Category:Living people]]
[[Category:National Baseball Hall of Fame inductees]]
[[Category:Cy Young Award winners]]
[[Category:300 saves club]]
[[Category:American League All-Stars]]
[[Category:National League All-Stars]]
[[Category:American League saves champions]]
[[Category:National League saves champions]]
[[Category:Milwaukee Brewers players]]
[[Category:Oakland Athletics players]]
[[Category:San Diego Padres players]]
[[Category:Major League Baseball pitchers]]
[[Category:Baseball players from Ohio]]
[[Category:People from Jefferson County, Ohio]]
[[Category:Major League Baseball players with retired numbers]]
[[Category:Leesburg A's players]]
[[Category:Modesto Reds players]]
[[Category:Birmingham A's players]]

[[de:Rollie Fingers]]
[[es:Rollie Fingers]]
[[fr:Rollie Fingers]]
[[ja:ローリー・フィンガーズ]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
