<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><redirects><r from="Brasero software" to="Brasero (software)" /></redirects><pages><page pageid="11661642" ns="0" title="Brasero (software)"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Infobox software
| name                   = Brasero
| logo                   = [[Image:Logo Brasero.svg|75px]]
| screenshot             = [[File:Brasero3-2-0.png|250px]]
| caption                = Brasero 3.2.0
| developer              = Philippe Rouquier &amp; Luis Medinas
| latest_release_version = 3.2.0&lt;ref&gt;http://ftp.gnome.org/pub/GNOME/sources/brasero/&lt;/ref&gt;
| latest_release_date    = {{release date and age|2011|9|27}}
| latest_preview_version = 2.91.4
| latest_preview_date    = {{release date and age|2010|12|23}}
| programming_language   = [[C (Programming Language)]]
| operating_system       = [[Unix-like]]
| genre                  = [[Optical disc]] operations
| license                = [[GNU General Public License]]
| website                = {{URL|http://www.gnome.org/projects/brasero}}
}}

'''Brasero''' is a [[free software|free]] [[optical disc|disc]]-[[optical disc authoring|burning]] program for [[Unix-like]] [[operating system|systems]], which serves as a graphical [[front-end and back-end|front-end]] (using [[GTK+]]) to [[cdrtools]], [[dvd+rw-tools|growisofs]], and (optionally) libburn.&lt;ref name=&quot;FSMApr07&quot;&gt;{{cite web| url=http://www.freesoftwaremagazine.com/articles/burning_cds_in_gnome | title= Free Software Magazine Review |accessdate= 2007-06-13}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web| url=http://gnomefiles.org/app.php/Brasero | title= GnomeFiles.org |accessdate=2007-06-13}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;BraseroHomePage&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url = http://projects.gnome.org/brasero/|title = Brasero|accessdate = 2009-03-29|last = [[GNOME|The GNOME Project]]|authorlink = |year = 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Brasero is the default CD/DVD application in the [[GNOME]] desktop.&lt;ref name=&quot;Paul20Mar09&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url = http://arstechnica.com/open-source/reviews/2009/03/hands-on-gnome-226-brings-incremental-improvement.ars|title = Hands-on: GNOME 2.26 brings incremental improvements|accessdate = 2009-03-29|last = Paul|first = Ryan|authorlink = |year = 2009|month = March}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Licensed under the terms of the [[GNU General Public License]], Brasero is [[free software]].&lt;ref name=&quot;BraseroHomePage&quot; /&gt;

==History==
Brasero was developed by Philippe Rouquier &amp; Luis Medinas. The project was originally named Bonfire, but was renamed after the Spanish word ''[[Brasero (heater)|brasero]]'' for a small heater used to provide warmth for people sitting at a table.&lt;ref name=&quot;FSMApr07&quot; /&gt;

Early releases of the application were well received. In a review in April 2007 published in [[Free Software Magazine]] Robin Monks concluded:

{{quote|Brasero is a much simpler disk burning solution, and has a nicer user experience over GnomeBaker. I would recommend this for those who don’t want to think much about their disk burner, and just want it to work.&lt;ref name=&quot;FSMApr07&quot; /&gt; }}

After further development and the inclusion of Brasero 0.7.1 in [[Ubuntu (operating system)|Ubuntu]] 8.04 ''Hardy Heron'' in April 2008 the application received further press reviews. In May 2008 Ryan Paul of [[Ars Technica]] said:

{{quote|Brasero's start screen is very intuitive and user-friendly, but the default configuration for the project interface feels a bit cluttered because it includes a bulky file browsing widget. Users can add files to a project by selecting them in the built-in file browsing component or by dragging and dropping them from the regular file manager. A bar at the bottom will show how much space the selected files use relative to the total capacity of the disc.

Brasero is similar to KDE's K3B burning program, but lacks a few of K3B's really advanced features like automatic video encoding support for DVDs and VCDs. Despite a few omissions like that, Brasero is very complete and is far more useful than the simplistic CD/DVD Creator that is built into the GNOME file manager. I burned several data CDs and DVDs with Brasero to test its reliability. The program crashed once while I was adding files, but never had any problems at all while burning.&lt;ref name=&quot;Paul07May08&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url = http://arstechnica.com/software/news/2008/05/hardy-heron-review.ars/2|title = The heron has landed: a review of Ubuntu 8.04|accessdate = 2009-03-29|last = Paul|first = Ryan|authorlink = |year = 2008|month = May}}&lt;/ref&gt; }}

Brasero was later integrated into GNOME and the version numbers were aligned with GNOME desktop version numbering. Ars Technica reviewed Brasero 2.26, then the newest version, in March 2009, saying:

{{quote|[Brasero has] improved a bit since [2008] and has added support for video and several other features. The project user interface, however, seems to have worsened. They have gotten rid of the useful disc capacity meter at the bottom and replaced it with a size indicator element that is displayed next to each item in the file list.

They have also added a file filtering mechanism of some kind at the bottom of the window. It isn't entirely clear to me what purpose it is supposed to serve, but it seems like unnecessary clutter. I also strongly dislike the superfluous file preview feature which wastes a lot of screen space in order to display a playable video thumbnail. The preview feature is fortunately easy to disable.

The whole programs feels uncharacteristically clunky by GNOME standards, but it's a lot more functional than the stale and unambitious CD burning component that was included in previous versions of GNOME. I think that Brasero is the right way forward in the long term, but the user interface really doesn't please me.

My biggest complaint with the old Nautilus CD burner is that it didn't give you clear visual hints about how much space you have left when you are putting in files to burn. The fact that Brasero dropped that feature is a bit of a disappointment. It seems like the task of building a good disc burning UI with GTK+ is not trivial and it's something that I suspect will take a skilled designer rather than a developer.

Despite the problems with Brasero's interface, it's really a very capable program with a rich feature set, which leaves me hopeful that it will be able to really shine someday.&lt;ref name=&quot;Paul20Mar09&quot; /&gt; }}

== Features ==
===Data===
Brasero supports both CD and DVD formats. It allows for editing of the disc contents and can remove, move and rename files that are located inside [[folders]]. It can also burn data CD/DVDs [[On_the_fly#Computer_usage|on the fly]].&lt;ref name=&quot;BraseroHomePage&quot; /&gt;

The application allows automatic filtering for unwanted files, including [[hidden files]], broken and [[recursive]] [[Symbolic link|symlinks]] and files not conforming to the [[Joliet (file system)|Joliet CD standard]]. Brasero supports [[multisession]]s, the Joliet extension and can create an [[Disk image|image]] of the user's [[hard drive]].&lt;ref name=&quot;BraseroHomePage&quot; /&gt;

===Audio===
When creating audio CDs Brasero writes [[CD-TEXT]] information automatically found, using [[GStreamer]]. It also supports the editing of CD-TEXT information and can burn audio CDs on the fly. It can use all audio file formats handled by GStreamer local installation, including [[Ogg]], [[Free Lossless Audio Codec|FLAC]] and [[MP3]]. Brasero can also search for audio files that are inside dropped [[Directory (file systems)|folders]].&lt;ref name=&quot;BraseroHomePage&quot; /&gt;

===Copying===
Brasero is capable of copying a CD/DVD to the user's hard drive in [[iso image|iso]] format and can copy DVDs and CDs on the fly. It supports single-session data DVDs and any type of CD.&lt;ref name=&quot;BraseroHomePage&quot; /&gt; 

No information is available about its behaviour with dual layer discs, nor with respect to copy-protected disks.{{Citation needed|date=May 2011}}

===Other features===
Brasero can also erase CD/DVDs, save and load ongoing projects and can burn CD and DVD images and cue files.&lt;ref name=&quot;BraseroHomePage&quot; /&gt;

It includes a song, image and video previewer and full device detection through the [[HAL (software)|HAL (Hardware Abstraction Layer)]]. When operating on a [[Linux kernel]] newer than 2.6.13 it provides [[inotify|file change notification]].&lt;ref name=&quot;BraseroHomePage&quot; /&gt;

When used with GDL, Brasero has a customizable [[graphical user interface|user interface]].&lt;ref name=&quot;BraseroHomePage&quot; /&gt;

The application supports [[drag and drop]] as well as [[cut and paste]] from the [[Nautilus (file manager)|Nautilus (GNOME file manager)]] and also other applications. It can use files from a network when the protocol is handled via gnome-vfs. It can search for files using [[Beagle (software)|Beagle]], allowing a search that is based on keywords or on file type. Brasero can also display a [[playlist]] and its contents. Playlists are automatically searched using Beagle.&lt;ref name=&quot;BraseroHomePage&quot; /&gt;

== See also ==
{{Portal|Free software}}
* [[List of optical disc authoring software]]
* [[k3b]]

==References==
{{Reflist}}

==External links==
* [http://www.gnome.org/projects/brasero/index.html Official website]

{{Optical disc image software}}

[[Category:Free CD writing software]]
[[Category:GTK+]]
[[Category:Optical disc authoring software]]
[[Category:Linux CD/DVD writing software]]

[[ast:Brasero (software)]]
[[br:Brasero (urzhiataerezh)]]
[[ca:Brasero]]
[[de:Brasero (Brennprogramm)]]
[[es:Brasero (software)]]
[[eu:Brasero]]
[[fr:Brasero (logiciel)]]
[[id:Brasero Disk Burner]]
[[it:Brasero]]
[[ml:ബ്രസേരോ (സോഫ്റ്റ്‌വെയർ)]]
[[nl:Brasero]]
[[ja:Brasero]]
[[pl:Brasero]]
[[ru:Brasero]]
[[sk:Brasero]]
[[sv:Brasero]]
[[uk:Brasero]]
[[zh:Brasero]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
