<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="19448" ns="0" title="Marilyn Manson (band)"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Infobox musical artist
|name = Marilyn Manson
|image = Marilyn Manson (Florence).jpg
|caption = Marilyn Manson performing live in Florence in 2007.
|image_size = 250
|landscape = Yes
|background = group_or_band
|genre = [[Industrial metal]], [[alternative metal]], [[glam rock]], [[Heavy metal music|heavy metal]]&lt;ref name=&quot;AllMusic&quot;&gt;{{cite web|last=Ankeny |first=Jason |url=http://www.allmusic.com/artist/marilyn-manson-p45021 |title=Marilyn Manson |publisher=AllMusic |date= |accessdate=2011-09-14}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;!--DO NOT CHANGE OR ADD GENRES WITHOUT DISCUSSING FIRST.--&gt;
|origin = [[Fort Lauderdale, Florida|Fort Lauderdale]], [[Florida]], {{nowrap|[[United States]]}}
|years_active = 1989–present
|label = [[Cooking Vinyl]],&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last=Paine |first=Andre |url=http://abcnews.go.com /Entertainment/wireStory?id=12084149 |title=Marilyn Manson: Antichrist Indie Star |publisher=ABCNews |date=2010-11-08 |accessdate=2010-11-08}} {{dead link|date=April 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last= |first= |url=http://www.roadrunnerrecords.com/blabbermouth.net/news.aspx?mode=Article&amp;newsitemID=149002 |title=MARILYN MANSON Signs With COOKING VINYL RECORDS |publisher=Blabbermouth.net |date=2010-11-07 |accessdate=2010-11-08}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Nothing Records|Nothing]], [[Interscope Records|Interscope]]
|associated_acts = [[Nine Inch Nails]], [[Goon Moon]], [[Jack Off Jill]], [[Rob Zombie]], [[Amboog-a-Lard]], [[Godhead (band)|gODHEAD]], [[Loser (band)|Loser]], [[Satan on Fire]]
|website = {{URL|http://www.marilynmanson.com/}}
|current_members = [[Marilyn Manson]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Jeordie White|Twiggy Ramirez]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Fred Sablan]]&lt;br&gt;
|past_members = [[Chris Vrenna]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Ginger Fish]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Andy Gerold]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Wes Borland]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Rob Holliday]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Tim Skold]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Madonna Wayne Gacy]]&lt;br /&gt;[[John 5 (guitarist)|John 5]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Zim Zum]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Daisy Berkowitz]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Sara Lee Lucas]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Gidget Gein]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Olivia Newton Bundy]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Zsa Zsa Speck]]
}}

'''Marilyn Manson''' is an American [[Heavy metal music|metal]] band from [[Fort Lauderdale, Florida]]. Formed in 1989 by [[Marilyn Manson|Brian Warner]] and [[Scott Putesky]], the group was originally named '''Marilyn Manson &amp; the Spooky Kids''' with their uniquely theatrical performances gathering a local cult following in the early '90s. This attention subsequently developed into a worldwide fanbase. The band's lineup has changed between many of their album releases. The current members of Marilyn Manson are the [[Marilyn Manson|eponymous lead singer]], guitarist [[Twiggy Ramirez]] (who previously played bass) and bassist [[Fred Sablan]].

The name of each band member was originally created by combining the first name of an [[Secular icon|iconic]] female [[sex symbol]] and the last name of an iconic serial killer ([[Marilyn Monroe]] and [[Charles Manson]]), doing so to demonstrate the odd dichotomy of American society as a critical and, simultaneously, laudatory appraisal of the US and its peculiar [[American culture|culture]].&lt;ref name=&quot;longhard&quot;&gt;{{cite book |title=The Long Hard Road out of Hell |last=Manson |first=Marilyn |publisher=HarperCollins |year=1998|isbn=978-0-06-098746-6|pages=85–87}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;imdb&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.imdb.com/name/nm0001504/bio|title=Biography for Marilyn Manson|accessdate=2008-01-12|work=[[Internet Movie Database]]}}&lt;/ref&gt; The members of the band dress in outlandish makeup and costumes, and have engaged in intentionally [[shock value|shocking]] behavior both onstage and off. Their lyrics often receive criticism for their anti-religious sentiment and their references to sex, violence and drugs. Marilyn Manson's music and performances have frequently been called offensive and [[obscenity|obscene]], and, on several occasions, protests and petitions have led to the group being banned from performing.

As this controversy began to wane, so did the band's mainstream popularity. Despite this, the band has a fairly massive underground fanbase. Marilyn Manson has garnered much success: four of the band's albums have been multi-platinum, and 2 more have been gold, and the band has seen five of its releases debut in the top ten,&lt;ref name=&quot;EatDrink_Billboard&quot;&gt;{{cite web| title=Billboard 200: Week of June 23, 2007| url=http://www.billboard.com/news/marilyn-manson-posts-grotesque-at-no-1-1892893.story#/charts/billboard-200?chartDate=2007-06-23| work=[[Billboard (magazine)|''Billboard'']]| date=2007-06-23| accessdate=2010-08-30}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;HighEnd_Billboard&quot;&gt;{{cite web| title=Eminem Stays Atop Billboard 200; Grizzly Bear, Manson Debut Top 10| url=http://www.billboard.com/bbcom/news/eminem-stays-atop-billboard-200-grizzly-1003979230.story#/bbcom/news/eminem-stays-atop-billboard-200-grizzly-1003979230.story| last=Caulfield| first=Keith| work=[[Billboard (magazine)|''Billboard'']]| date=2009-06-03| accessdate=2010-08-30}}&lt;/ref&gt; including two number-one albums. [[VH1]] has ranked Marilyn Manson as the seventy-eighth best rock band on their ''100 Great Artists of Hard Rock''.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.rockonthenet.com/archive/2000/vh1hardrock.htm |title=Rock On The Net: VH1: 100 Greatest Hard Rock Artists}}&lt;/ref&gt; Aggregate site AcclaimedMusic.net lists Marilyn Manson number 723 in their artist rank for greatest of all time.&lt;ref name=&quot;acclaimedmusic.net&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://acclaimedmusic.net/Current/Marilyn%20Manson.htm |title=Marilyn Manson Artist Rank |publisher=Acclaimedmusic.net |accessdate=2011-03-06}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Marilyn Manson has sold over 50 million albums worldwide as of May 2009.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://cookingvinyl.com/artists/marilyn-manson/ |title=Cooking Vinyl artist page: Marilyn Manson |publisher=[[Cooking Vinyl Records]] |date=2010-11-08 |accessdate=2010-11-08}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Band history==
===The Spooky Kids (1989–1992)===
[[File:SpookyKidsFlyer.jpg|thumb|right|A 1992 flyer for a Marilyn Manson &amp; The Spooky Kids show, with artwork by Marilyn Manson. It parodies [[Baphomet]].]]

In 1989, Brian Warner was a college student working toward a [[journalism]] degree, and gaining experience in the field by writing music articles for a South Florida lifestyle magazine, ''[[25th Parallel (magazine)|25th Parallel]]''. It was in this capacity that he was able to meet several of the musicians to whom his own band would later be compared, including [[My Life With the Thrill Kill Kult]] and [[Trent Reznor]] of [[Nine Inch Nails]]{{Citation needed|date=July 2011}}. He met [[Scott Putesky]] shortly afterward and, after showing him some lyrics and poems he had written, proposed that they form a band together. Warner, guitarist Putesky, and bassist Brian Tutunick recorded their first demo tape as Marilyn Manson &amp; the Spooky Kids in 1990, taking on the stage names of [[Marilyn Manson]], [[Daisy Berkowitz]] and [[Olivia Newton Bundy]], respectively. They were soon joined by Stephen Bier, who called himself [[Madonna Wayne Gacy]]; Bundy was replaced by [[Gidget Gein]], born Brad Stewart. In 1991, drummer Fred Streithorst joined the band, with the stage name [[Sara Lee Lucas]].

The stage names used by each member were representative of a concept the band considered central: the [[dichotomy]] of [[good and evil]], and the existence of both, together, in every whole. &quot;[[Marilyn Monroe]] had a dark side&quot;, explained Manson in his autobiography, &quot;just as [[Charles Manson]] has a good, intelligent side&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;autogenerated2&quot;&gt;{{cite book |title=''[[The Long Hard Road out of Hell]]'' |last=Manson |first=Marilyn |authorlink= |coauthors=[[Neil Strauss]] |year=1998 |publisher=[[HarperCollins]] |location= |isbn=978-0-06-098746-6 |page= |pages= |url= |accessdate=}}&lt;/ref&gt; Images of both Monroe and Manson, as well as of others equally famous and notorious, were common in the band's early promotional materials.

&lt;div style=&quot;float: left;&quot;&gt;
{{listen
|pos=left
| filename = Marilyn Manson &amp; the Spooky Kids - Choklit Factory.ogg
| title = &quot;Choklit Factory&quot;
| description = Demo version, as it appeared on ''After School Special''
| format = [[Ogg]]
}}
&lt;/div&gt;
The Spooky Kids' popularity in the area grew quickly, largely because of radio DJ Scott David of WYNX-FM, an early fan who eagerly played songs from the band's demo tapes on the air; and because of [[Marilyn Manson independent touring|the band's highly visual concerts]], which drew from [[performance art]] and used many [[shock value|shock]] techniques. It was not uncommon to see onstage &quot;naked women nailed to a cross, a child in a cage, or bloody animal body parts&quot;;&lt;ref name=&quot;MiamiNewTimes&quot;&gt;{{cite news |title=Manson Family Values |first=Baker |last=Greg |url=http://www.miaminewtimes.com/issues/1994-07-20/music/music3.html |format=[[Tabloid (newspaper format)|Tabloid]] |agency=[[Village Voice Media]], Inc. |newspaper=''[[Miami New Times]]'' |publisher=Adam Simon |date=1994-07-20 |page= |pages= |accessdate=2006-09-09}}&lt;/ref&gt; Manson, Berkowitz, and Gein variously performed in [[Cross-dressing|women's clothing]] or bizarre costumes; and, for lack of a professional [[pyrotechnics|pyrotechnician]], they would occasionally set their own stage props on fire. The band would dramatically contrast these grotesque theatrics with elements drawn from the culture of the members' youth in the 1970s and 1980s: characters from that era's children's television made regular, often somewhat altered, appearances on Marilyn Manson flyers and newsletters, and were frequently [[Sampling (music)|sampled]] in the music. They continued to perform and release cassettes—shortening their name to Marilyn Manson in 1992—until the summer of 1993, when the band drew the attention of [[Trent Reznor]], who at the time had just founded his own record label, [[Nothing Records]]{{Citation needed|date=July 2011}}.

===Nothing Records and ''Portrait of an American Family'' (1993–1995)===


Reznor offered Marilyn Manson a contract with his new label and the opportunity to support [[Nine Inch Nails]] on their upcoming headlining tour. The band accepted both offers, and recording sessions for its national debut, ''[[Portrait of an American Family]]'', began in July 1993. Working with producer [[Roli Mosimann]] at [[Criteria Studios]] in [[Miami, Florida]], the band recorded a selection of new songs along with material from their Spooky Kids repertoire and, by the end of Autumn 1993, had completed the first version of their debut, titled ''The Manson Family Album''. However, it was not well-received. The abrasive sonic &quot;rawness&quot; that Mosimann's production had brought to such groups as [[Swans (band)|Swans]] had failed to materialize on ''The Manson Family Album''; Reznor and all the band's members found it flat and lifeless, and poorly representative of Marilyn Manson's dynamic performances. &quot;I thought, 'This really sucks', Manson explained, &quot;so I played it for Trent, and he thought it sucked&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;MiamiNewTimes&quot;/&gt; At the same time, the band was having difficulties with bassist [[Gidget Gein]], who had begun to lose control of his addiction to [[heroin]]. While reworking the album the band played two shows in South Florida under the name Mrs. Scabtree. Not much is known about the complete lineup, except that Manson performed on the drums, Gacy on keyboard, Berkowitz on guitar, and [[Jeordie White]] of Miami [[thrash metal|thrash]] band [[Amboog-a-Lard]] and [[Jessicka]] of [[Jack Off Jill]] sharing vocal duties. Four other local musicians, bassists Mark Dubin of Sister Venus and Patrick Joyce from The Itch, guitarist Miles Hie, and violinist Mary Karlzen, were also involved.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |title=Program Notes 48 - Page 1 - News - Miami - Miami New Times |first=Baker |last=Greg |url=http://www.miaminewtimes.com/1993-03-16/news/program-notes-48 |format=[[Tabloid (newspaper format)|Tabloid]] |agency=[[Village Voice Media]], Inc. |newspaper=''[[Miami New Times]]'' |publisher=Adam Simon |date=1993-03-16 |page= |pages= |accessdate=2011-05-31}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |title=Program Notes - Page 2 - News - Miami - Miami New Times |first=Baker |last=Greg |url=http://www.miaminewtimes.com/1994-02-09/news/program-notes/2 |format=[[Tabloid (newspaper format)|Tabloid]] |agency=[[Village Voice Media]], Inc. |newspaper=''[[Miami New Times]]'' |publisher=Adam Simon |date=1994-02-09 |page= |pages= |accessdate=2011-05-31}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;div style=&quot;float: right;&quot;&gt;
{{listen
|pos=left
| filename = Marilyn Manson - Cake And Sodomy.ogg
| title = &quot;Cake and Sodomy&quot;
| description = Album version, as it appeared on ''Portrait of an American Family''
| format = [[Ogg]]
}}
&lt;/div&gt;
In October 1993, Reznor agreed to rework the production on Marilyn Manson's album, taking them and their tapes to The Record Plant in Los Angeles. Gein, who had been hospitalized after an overdose, was not invited. After seven weeks of mixing, remixing, and rerecording, the album — now titled ''Portrait of an American Family'' — was ready to be presented to [[Interscope Records]]. Even as the first single &quot;[[Get Your Gunn]]&quot; was beginning to receive radio airplay, Gein received a letter declaring his services &quot;no longer needed&quot; by the band after he overdosed on heroin for the fourth time; he was replaced by White, of Amboog-a-Lard,&lt;ref name=&quot;MTV.com&quot;&gt;{{cite web|last=Kaufman |first=Gil |url=http://www.mtv.com/news/articles/1596907/20081013/marilyn_manson.jhtml |title=Former Marilyn Manson Bassist Gidget Gein Dead At 39 |publisher=MTV News |date=2008-10-13 |accessdate=2009-03-02}}&lt;/ref&gt; and undertook the alias Twiggy Ramirez. In December 1993, Ramirez first performed as the band's new bass player on a week's worth of headline dates through Florida with Jack Off Jill opening. While playing Club 5 in [[Jacksonville, Florida]] Manson was accused by the town's [[Christian Coalition of America|Christian Coalition]] of violating the town's adult entertainment codes. Jack Off Jill singer Jessicka was accused of solicitation and offering to engage in lewdness. Both singers were arrested and charged with misdemeanors.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |title=Program Notes 48 - Page 3 - News - Miami - Miami New Times |first=Baker |last=Greg |url=http://www.miaminewtimes.com/1995-01-05/news/program-notes-3 |format=[[Tabloid (newspaper format)|Tabloid]] |agency=[[Village Voice Media]], Inc. |newspaper=''[[Miami New Times]]'' |publisher=Adam Simon |date=1995-01-05 |page= |pages= |accessdate=2011-05-31}}&lt;/ref&gt; On the first date of a fourteen-week national tour opening for Nine Inch Nails, Ramirez made his national touring debut. It was during this tour that Manson had occasion to meet with [[Church of Satan]] founder Dr. [[Anton LaVey]]. After a cordial meeting, LaVey honored Manson with the title of &quot;[[Reverend]]&quot; — meaning, in the Church of Satan, a person who is revered by the church, and not necessarily one who dedicates his life to preaching the religion to others, as with a [[priest]] or [[minister of religion|minister]]. Manson would use this title in album liner notes, citing himself as &quot;Reverend Marilyn Manson.&quot;

In March 1995, the band began its first national headlining tour, a two-month outing with [[Monster Voodoo Machine]] as support; this would be drummer Sara Lee Lucas' last tour with the band. Tension between Lucas and Manson had apparently grown as the tour wore on and, on the next-to-last night of the tour, Manson secretly decided to end the show with a flourish: during a performance of the then-current single, &quot;[[Lunchbox (single)|Lunchbox]]&quot;, he doused Lucas' drum kit in lighter fluid and set it ablaze — with Lucas still attempting to play on behind it. (Manson apparently forgot that the band had one more date to play.) Lucas quit the band after the final gig the next night. Less than two weeks later his replacement, [[Ginger Fish|Kenneth Wilson]], better known by his stage name Ginger Fish, joined the group. Marilyn Manson was touring again, this time on a bill with [[Danzig (band)|Danzig]] and [[Korn]].

====''Smells Like Children''====
[[File:Nights of Nothing MM.jpg|thumb|right|Marilyn Manson performing at [[Nothing Records]]' &quot;A Night of Nothing&quot; industry showcase.]]
&lt;div style=&quot;float: left;&quot;&gt;
{{listen
|pos=left
| filename = Marilyn Manson - Diary of a Dope Fiend.ogg
| title = &quot;Diary of a Dope Fiend&quot;
| description = Album version, as it appeared on ''Smells Like Children''
| format = [[Ogg]]
}}
&lt;/div&gt;
That tour ended in summer 1995, after which the band relocated to the new home of Nothing Studios in [[New Orleans, Louisiana]] to begin work on the third single from ''Portrait of an American Family'', &quot;[[Dope Hat]]&quot;. Accompanied by a [[music video]] which featured Manson in the role of [[Willy Wonka]] in a shock-horror version of ''[[Willy Wonka &amp; the Chocolate Factory]]'', the proposed single for &quot;Dope Hat&quot; eventually developed into an hour-long remix EP, ''[[Smells Like Children]]''. The album's fifteen tracks of covers, remixes, and bizarre sonic experiments also included the band's version of the [[Eurythmics]]' &quot;[[Sweet Dreams (Are Made of This) (Marilyn Manson song)|Sweet Dreams (Are Made of This)]]&quot;, which would prove to be Marilyn Manson's first legitimate hit: the video was placed in heavy rotation on MTV (in stark contrast with the &quot;Dope Hat&quot; video, which MTV had banished to late-night airplay only a few months before) and the mainstream music press was suddenly clamoring to cover the group. It was also around this time that the group began to experiment with [[Gothic Fashion|goth makeup]], and more bizarre outfits.

A five-month headlining tour followed, from September through February, during which the band began to debut new material like &quot;Irresponsible Hate Anthem&quot;, &quot;Minute of Decay&quot;, and &quot;Smells Like Children&quot;. Rumors of a new album circulated widely during this time, and were confirmed when the band returned to Nothing's New Orleans studio in early 1996 to perform what Manson termed &quot;a musical ritual designed to bring about the Apocalypse&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://groups.google.com/group/alt.music.marilyn-manson/msg/d16ff30c756d7341 |title=''The Antichrist Superstar Story'' (Quoted from 1997 Marilyn Manson press kit) |publisher=alt.music.net (archived at [[Google Groups]] |date=1997-02-24 |accessdate=2011-05-31}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===''Antichrist Superstar'' (1996–1997)===
[[File:Antichrist Live.jpg|thumb|left|Twiggy Ramirez live in Argentina, November 24, 1996, during the highly controversial &quot;Dead to the World Tour&quot;.]]
Marilyn Manson's second full-length studio album, ''[[Antichrist Superstar]]'', was released on October 8, 1996. The [[rock opera]] [[concept album]] was recorded at Nothing Studios with Trent Reznor himself acting as executive producer; the process of making the album was reportedly a long and difficult one, highlighted by experiments allegedly involving [[sleep deprivation]] and near-constant drug use in an effort to create an environment suited to the album's moody and occasionally violent content. During this time, antagonism between band members was high, which caused the departure of guitarist and founding member [[Daisy Berkowitz]]. With Berkowitz out of the band, [[Twiggy Ramirez]] performed lead guitar for much of the recording of ''Antichrist Superstar'', and the group placed an ad seeking a new guitarist for its upcoming tour; Timothy Linton, auditioned for and was given the position. Breaking with the six-year tradition of icon / killer naming structures, the newest member was dubbed [[Zim Zum]] – a name derived from [[Kabbalah]],&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.nachtkabarett.com/AlchemyAndKabbalah#zimzum |title=''Alchemy &amp; Kabbalah: Zim Zim'' |publisher=The Nachtkabarett}}&lt;/ref&gt; one of the major sources of inspiration for the album.

The album's first single, &quot;[[The Beautiful People (Marilyn Manson song)|The Beautiful People]]&quot;, made a fairly major impact on the alternative rock charts, and created enough anticipation for ''Antichrist Superstar'' that the album debuted at number three on the album charts.&lt;ref name=&quot;satanhelper&quot;&gt;{{cite news|last=Thigpen |first=David |url=http://www.time.com/time/magazine/article/0,9171,985963-1,00.html |title=Music: Satan's Little Helpers |publisher=[[Time (magazine)|''TIME'' Magazine]] |date=1997-02-24 |accessdate=2010-12-09}}&lt;/ref&gt; The [[Marilyn Manson|band's frontman]] was featured on the cover of ''[[Rolling Stone]]'' magazine who also awarded the band their ''Best New Artist'' accolade for [[1996 in music|1996]].&lt;ref name=&quot;satanhelper&quot;/&gt; The year-and-a-half long &quot;[[Dead to the World Tour]]&quot; in support of the album followed; it was the band's longest and widest yet, and included Marilyn Manson's live debut in [[Alaska]], [[Hawaii]], the [[United Kingdom]], continental [[Europe]], [[South America]], [[Asia]] and [[Australia]] as their fame spread to all corners of the world. In the United States, however, the band was receiving more attention than ever before, and not all of it was positive.

&lt;div style=&quot;float: right;&quot;&gt;
{{listen
|pos=left
| filename = Marilyn Manson - 1996.ogg
| title = &quot;1996&quot;
| description = Album version, as it appeared on ''Antichrist Superstar''
| format = [[Ogg]]
| filename2 = Marilyn Manson - The Reflecting God.ogg
| title2 = &quot;The Reflecting God&quot;
| description2 = Album version, as it appeared on ''Antichrist Superstar''
| format2 = [[Ogg]]
}}
&lt;/div&gt;
As the tour was getting underway, the band found itself the target of congressional hearings, led by Senator [[Joseph Lieberman]], to determine the effects, if any, of violent lyrics on young listeners. Lieberman would later go on to refer to Marilyn Manson as &quot;perhaps the sickest group ever promoted by a mainstream record company&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;Strauss&quot;&gt;{{cite news|last=Strauss |first=Neil |url=http://www.nytimes.com/1997/05/17/arts/a-bogey-band-to-scare-parents-with.html |title=A Bogey Band to Scare Parents With |publisher=''[[The New York Times]]'' |date=1997-05-17 |accessdate=2009-12-30}}&lt;/ref&gt; In addition, nearly every performance on the tour was picketed by religious organizations, pleading with fans to not see the musician who once said &quot;I think every time people listen to this new album maybe God will be destroyed in their brainwashed minds.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |last1=Semel |first1=Paul |date=1996-10 |title=Where The Wild Things Are |journal=[[huH]] |volume= |issue=26 |pages=32‐38 |publisher=[[Ray Gun Publishing, Inc]] |doi= |url= |accessdate=}}&lt;/ref&gt;

On November 10, 1997, the band released a remix/live EP, ''[[Remix &amp; Repent]]'', featuring new versions of ''Antichrist Superstar'''s four singles, &quot;The Beautiful People&quot;, &quot;Tourniquet&quot;, &quot;Antichrist Superstar&quot;, and &quot;Man that You Fear&quot;, alongside songs recorded live on the U.S. leg of the Dead to the World Tour. Two unreleased songs from the ''Antichrist Superstar'' recording sessions were contributed to film soundtracks: &quot;Apple of Sodom&quot; to [[David Lynch]]'s ''[[Lost Highway (film)|Lost Highway]]'', and &quot;The Suck for Your Solution&quot; to the [[Howard Stern]] biopic ''[[Private Parts (1997 film)|Private Parts]]''. As the year ended, Manson made the announcement of the upcoming publication of his first book, the autobiographical ''[[The Long Hard Road out of Hell]]''; the book was released in February 1998, along with another live document of the world tour, a home video entitled ''[[Dead to the World]]''. It also came to light around this time that ''Antichrist Superstar'' would be the first installment in a [[concept album]] trilogy and that the release of the follow-up was, according to the band, also imminent, accompanied by early rumors of the involvement of [[Billy Corgan]] and [[The Dust Brothers]] with the as-yet-untitled album.

===''Mechanical Animals'' (1998–1999)===
[[File:omegasinginscomawhite.jpg|thumb|right|250px|Marilyn Manson singing &quot;The Speed of Pain&quot; live.]]
On September 15, 1998, Marilyn Manson released the second part of that triptych, ''[[Mechanical Animals]]'', an album strongly influenced by [[David Bowie]]. Interscope's promotion of the album was massive, including an enormous billboard of singer Manson as an androgynous [[extraterrestrial life|extraterrestrial]] over [[Times Square]], and repeated appearances on MTV and other networks to promote the album and the single &quot;[[The Dope Show]]&quot;; propelled by the success of ''Antichrist Superstar'' and by this press push, the album debuted at number one on the Billboard 200 Albums chart. The band had recast itself in a new image for this album; setting aside the bleak darkness of the previous record for a more concealed morbidity.

&lt;div style=&quot;float: left;&quot;&gt;
{{listen
|pos=left
| filename = The Last Day On Earth.ogg
| title = &quot;The Last Day on Earth&quot;
| description = Album version, as it appeared on ''Mechanical Animals''
| format = [[Ogg]]
}}
&lt;/div&gt;Marilyn Manson was now a [[glam rock]] band, borrowing its visual presentation largely from Bowie, and from [[Roxy Music]] and its contemporaries. By this time, the band had permanently relocated to Los Angeles, and Zim Zum had been replaced by glam-influenced guitarist [[John Lowery]], who joined the band as John 5. After a brief promotional tour, the band set out on the &quot;[[Beautiful Monsters Tour]]&quot; with [[Hole (band)|Hole]] and [[Monster Magnet]] as support. The tour, however, would be a problematic one: on March 1, 1999, the three bands played the first show in [[Spokane, Washington]]; by March 14, Hole had left the tour and Manson had broken his ankle, forcing postponements of some shows. The tour was then renamed the &quot;[[Rock Is Dead Tour]]&quot; and both [[Jack Off Jill]] and [[Nashville Pussy]] were asked to take select remaining opening slots on tour.&lt;ref name=&quot;autogenerated1&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.mtv.com/news/articles/1430051/19990322/hole.jhtml |title=Manson Resumes Tour Without Hole, Taps Nashville Pussy And Jack Off Jill For Upcoming Dates |publisher=MTV News |date=1999-03-22 |accessdate=2007-06-18}}&lt;/ref&gt;

====Columbine shootings====
Less than three weeks after the tour resumed, two students (Eric Harris and Dylan Klebold) at [[Columbine High School]] in [[Littleton, Colorado]] killed thirteen people, and then took their own lives; early media reports declared them fans of &quot;violent&quot; music and video games. Substantial attention was directed at Manson, however it was later confirmed that Harris and Klebold were not fans of the group.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |title=Marilyn Manson Concert Canceled |first=Glasgow |last=Greg |url=http://www.thedailycamera.com/shooting/23manson.html |format=[[Broadsheet]] |agency=[[MediaNews Group]] |newspaper=''[[Camera (newspaper)|The Daily Camera]]'' |publisher=Albert J. Manzi |date=1999-04-23 |page= |pages= |accessdate=2011-05-31}}&lt;/ref&gt; On April 28, out of respect for the victims, Marilyn Manson canceled the remaining dates of the Rock Is Dead tour, and would not reappear in Denver until the 2001 [[Ozzfest]]. Manson's song [[The Nobodies (song)|The Nobodies]] was directly inspired by the shootings.

===''Holy Wood'' (2000–2002)===
[[File:Holy25.jpg|thumb|right|Marilyn Manson performing &quot;Antichrist Superstar&quot; during the &quot;Guns, God and Government Tour&quot;.]]
The rest of 1999 and much of 2000 was a period of relative silence for Marilyn Manson. The band spent over a year quietly writing and recording in a studio in [[Death Valley]], with only the single [[Astonishing Panorama of the Endtimes]] — an outtake from ''Antichrist Superstar''&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last=Manson |first=Marilyn |url=http://www.nineinchnails.net/news/jun99.html |archiveurl=http://web.archive.org/web/20000816030605/http://www.nineinchnails.net/news/jun99.html |archivedate=2000-08-16 |title=Astonishing Panorama |publisher=Seems Like Salvation News |date=1999-06-09 |accessdate=2011-05-31}}&lt;/ref&gt; — appearing during that time. On November 14, 2000, ''[[Holy Wood (In the Shadow of the Valley of Death)]]'' was released. Returning to the darker, more abrasive sound of ''Antichrist Superstar'', much of the album's content was written in response to the Columbine massacre.

Described by the band as the third part of the trilogy begun with ''Antichrist Superstar'' and continued in ''Mechanical Animals'', its overarching theme is an exploration of the relationship between death and fame in American culture, and its lyrics and artwork contain many references to [[John F. Kennedy]] and [[Lee Harvey Oswald]], [[John Lennon]] and [[Mark David Chapman]], and even [[Abraham Lincoln]] and [[John Wilkes Booth]]. The international &quot;[[Guns, God and Government Tour]]&quot; expanded upon the exploration of America's fascination with violence, and with the tour's logo — a rifle and handguns arranged to resemble the [[Christian cross]] — Manson made no attempt to conceal what he saw as the source of that fascination.

The band also revealed that within Marilyn Manson's massive concept album trilogy,&lt;ref name=&quot;Goldyn 2&quot;&gt;{{cite web|last=Goldyn |first=A.R. |url=http://www.alternet.org/media/11052?page=2 |title=Guns, God and Government: Interview with Marilyn Manson (page 2) |publisher=Omaha Reader (latterly by AlterNet.org) |date=2001-06-19 |accessdate=2010-08-22}}&lt;/ref&gt; ''Holy Wood'' serves as prequel to ''[[Mechanical Animals]]'' and ''[[Antichrist Superstar]]'' despite the latter two preceding ''Holy Wood'' in release date.&lt;ref name=&quot;Goldyn 3&quot;&gt;{{cite web|last=Goldyn |first=A.R. |url=http://www.alternet.org/media/11052?page=3 |title=Guns, God and Government: Interview with Marilyn Manson (page 3) |publisher=Omaha Reader (latterly by AlterNet.org) |date=2001-06-19 |accessdate=2010-08-22}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Quelland&quot;&gt;{{cite web|last=Quelland |first=Sarah |url=http://www.metroactive.com/papers/metro/12.14.00/cover/manson-0050.html |title=Into the Mind of Marilyn |publisher=Metroactive Music |date=2000-12-14 |accessdate=2010-08-10}}&lt;/ref&gt; Each of the three albums contain its own storyline distinct from one other but also linked together abstractly in a fourth larger over-arching storyline encompassing all three.&lt;ref name=&quot;Quelland&quot;/&gt; Manson has offered this much in the way of an interpretation,

{{cquote|[''Holy Wood'' is about] wanting to fit into a world that didn't want me, and fighting really hard to get there. [The album's deepest elements] are idealism and the desire to start a revolution. If you begin with ''Holy Wood'', then ''Mechanical Animals'' really talks about how that revolution gets taken away from you and turned into a product, and then ''Antichrist Superstar'' is where you're given a choice to decide if you're going to be controlled by the power that you created or if you want to destroy yourself and then start over. It just becomes a cycle.|4=[[Marilyn Manson]] |5=Guns, God and Government: Interview with Marilyn Manson&lt;ref name=&quot;Goldyn 3&quot;/&gt;}}

&lt;div style=&quot;float: left;&quot;&gt;
{{listen
|pos=left
| filename = Marilyn Manson - Target Audience (Narcissus Narcosis).ogg
| title = &quot;Target Audience (Narcissus Narcosis)&quot;
| description = Album version, as it appeared on ''Holy Wood (In the Shadow of the Valley of Death)''
| format = [[Ogg]]
}}
&lt;/div&gt;
On May 16, 2001, Manson announced on the band website that he planned to quote the [[Bible]] at his next concert, to &quot;balance out&quot; his violent lyrics, &quot;so we can examine the virtues of wonderful Christian stories of disease, murder, adultery, suicide and child sacrifice. Now that seems like entertainment to me&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;coloradoantimanson&quot;&gt;{{cite web|last=D'Angelo |first=Joe |url=http://www.mtv.com/news/articles/1443825/20010517/marilyn_manson.jhtml |title=Colorado Governor, Congressman Support Anti-Manson Group |publisher=MTV News |date=2001-05-21 |accessdate=2010-11-17}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.nme.com/news/marilyn-manson/7743 |title=Manson To Lead Bible Studies Class |publisher=''NME'' |date=2001-05-13 |accessdate=2011-03-31}}&lt;/ref&gt; On June 21, 2001, Manson did indeed read from the Bible onstage in [[Denver, Colorado]], presenting such passages as [[Leviticus]] 20:9 (&quot;For every one that curseth his father or his mother shall surely be put to death&quot;) and [[Psalms|Psalm]] 137:9 (&quot;Happy shall he be, that taketh and dasheth thy little ones against the stones&quot;).

This tour was documented in a DVD release of the same name, released October 29, 2002 and described by Manson as &quot;This will help you see what it's like to be nailed to this wrecking ball&quot; on the DVD packaging.&lt;ref name=&quot;AmazonGGGDVD&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.amazon.com/Marilyn-Manson-Guns-Government-World/dp/B00005U2JL/ref=sr_1_1?ie=UTF8&amp;qid=1301296337&amp;sr=8-1 |title=Marilyn Manson - Guns, God and Government World Tour (2001)|publisher=[[Amazon.com]]|accessdate=2011-03-28}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;MTVGGGDVD&quot;&gt;{{cite web |last=LeVasseur |first=Andrea |url=http://www.mtv.com/movies/movie/217688/moviemain.jhtml |title=Marilyn Manson: Guns, God and Government World Tour |publisher=MTV |accessdate=2011-03-28}}&lt;/ref&gt; In addition to a compilation style concert from the tour [songs from multiple individual shows edited to appear as single performance], the DVD includes a short thirty minute film titled &quot;Death Parade&quot; in the style of an All Access Pass for the tour.&lt;ref name=&quot;MTVGGGDVD&quot;/&gt;

Seven years later it was followed by ''Guns, God and Government – Live in L.A.'' Released in [[Blu-ray]] on November 17, 2009, it depicts the sixteen song set of the [[Los Angeles]] performance in its entirety.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.amazon.com/Marilyn-Manson-Government-L-Blu-ray/dp/B002OOG6YY/ref=sr_1_3?ie=UTF8&amp;qid=1301296337&amp;sr=8-3 |title=Marilyn Manson: Guns, God and Government - Live in L.A. &lt;nowiki&gt;[&lt;/nowiki&gt;Blu-ray&lt;nowiki&gt;]&lt;/nowiki&gt; (2009)|publisher=[[Amazon.com]]|accessdate=2011-03-28}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |last=Seibert |first=Perry |url=http://www.mtv.com/movies/movie/437258/moviemain.jhtml |title=Marilyn Manson: Guns, God and Government - Live in L.A. |publisher=MTV |accessdate=2011-03-28}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===''The Golden Age of Grotesque'' (2003–2005)===
[[File:Mm ozzfest 2003.jpg|thumb|left|225px|Marilyn Manson performing at [[Ozzfest]] in 2003.]]
With the &quot;[[triptych]]&quot; of the previous three albums now complete, Marilyn Manson was free to begin a fresh project. In 2002, [[Jonathan Davis]] of [[Korn]] invited Marilyn Manson into a studio to record vocals on a track he wrote entitled &quot;Redeemer&quot;. The song, produced by both Jon and Richard Gibbs, was then released on the [[Queen of the Damned (film)|Queen of the Damned]] soundtrack. After finding inspiration in the decadent [[Swing (genre)|Swing]] era of the 1920s, the band recorded ''[[The Golden Age of Grotesque]]'' that year and the album was released on May 13, 2003.

&lt;div style=&quot;float: right;&quot;&gt;
{{listen
|pos=left
 | filename = Marilyn Manson - The Golden Age of Grotesque.ogg
 | title = &quot;The Golden Age of Grotesque&quot;
 | description = Album version, as it appeared on ''The Golden Age of Grotesque''
 | format = [[Ogg]]
}}
&lt;/div&gt;
Eschewing the lyrical depth and volume of symbolism and hidden meaning of ''Holy Wood'', the new album was relatively straightforward; in an extended metaphor, Manson compares his own often-criticized music to the ''[[degenerate art|entartete Kunst]]'' banned by the [[Nazi Germany|Nazi]] regime. New member [[Tim Skold]], replacing Twiggy Ramirez, added a new dimension to the band's sound; he brought with him from [[KMFDM]] that band's use of heavy [[industrial rock|industrial]] beats—''The Golden Age of Grotesque'' was frequently impugned{{By whom|date=April 2010}} as derivative of KMFDM and lacking the originality that Marilyn Manson had become known for.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last=Erlewine |first=Stephen Thomas |url=http://www.allmusic.com/album/the-golden-age-of-grotesque-r638438/review |title=The Golden Age of Grotesque review |publisher=[[allmusic]] |accessdate=2011-05-31}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last=Chambers |first=Catherine |url=http://www.bbc.co.uk/music/reviews/m6n8 |title=The Golden Age Of Grotesque Review |publisher=BBC Music |date=2003-05-29 |accessdate=2010-11-08}}&lt;/ref&gt; The album debuted at #1 on the album charts, selling over 118,000 copies in the US its first week of release.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.billboard.com/#/album/marilyn-manson/the-golden-age-of-grotesque/580008 |title=Billboard 200 and Canadian Albums charting |publisher=[[Billboard (magazine)|''Billboard'']] |accessdate=2010-11-08}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Another world tour, the &quot;Grotesk Burlesk Tour&quot;, followed, which furthered the album's [[Weimar Republic]]-inspired theme by adding elements of German ''[[cabaret|Kabarett]]'' to the group's performances. Elaborate artwork by [[Gottfried Helnwein]] appeared in the band's stage dressing, and the members began appearing both on-stage and off- in designer suits and with fashion superstars.

====''Lest We Forget: The Best Of''====
[[File:Marilyn Manson 2004.jpg|thumb|right|Marilyn Manson performing on the &quot;Against All Gods Tour&quot; in 2004.]]
''[[Lest We Forget: The Best Of]]'' was released on September 28, 2004. It was referred to by the singer as his &quot;farewell&quot; album.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.vh1.com/news/articles/1491296/20040922/marilyn_manson.jhtml?_requestid=266882 |title=Marylin Manson Calls Lest We Forget 'A Farewell Compilation' |publisher=Vh1.com |date=2004-09-22 |accessdate=2011-09-14}}&lt;/ref&gt; It was supported by a series of &quot;greatest hits&quot; performances, the &quot;[[Against All Gods Tour]]&quot;. After the release of the single &quot;[[Personal Jesus#Marilyn Manson cover|Personal Jesus]]&quot;, the band made a number of promotional appearances including a performance on ''[[Mad TV|MADtv]]'';&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://vodpod.com/watch/4343902-marilyn-manson-personal-jesus-mad-tv-live-performance |title=Marilyn Manson Personal Jesus MAD TV Live Performance Video |publisher=Vodpod.com |date= |accessdate=2011-09-14}}&lt;/ref&gt; at one of these, the Comet awards show in [[Germany]], drummer [[Ginger Fish]] fell from his drum riser, fracturing his [[human skull|skull]] and wrist.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.billboard.com/news/manson-s-drummer-injured-in-fall-1000642520.story#/news/manson-s-drummer-injured-in-fall-1000642520.story |title=Manson's Drummer Injured In Fall |publisher=Billboard.com |date= |accessdate=2011-09-14}}&lt;/ref&gt; Former Nine Inch Nails drummer [[Chris Vrenna]] replaced him; after recovering from the accident Fish had been recording and performing with a new band, [[Martyr Plot]], before rejoining Marilyn Manson.

&lt;div style=&quot;float: left;&quot;&gt;
{{listen
|pos=left
 | filename = Marilyn Manson - Personal Jesus.ogg
 | title = &quot;Personal Jesus&quot;
 | description = Album version, as it appeared on ''Lest We Forget: The Best Of''
 | format = [[Ogg]]
}}
&lt;/div&gt;
[[John Lowery|John 5]] had also been replaced; [[Mark Chaussee]] of [[Fight (band)|Fight]] took over lead guitar on the &quot;Against All Gods Tour&quot;, and was subsequently replaced in the studio by Tim Skold. Though John 5 denied any hostility towards Marilyn Manson following the announcement of his departure, at the band's appearance on the [[Rock am Ring]] music festival in 2003 an incident took place between John 5 and Marilyn Manson where Manson kicked and then shoved the guitarist. John 5 responded with anger, throwing off his guitar mid-song and raising his fists to Manson as if to fight with him, before resuming the song without any further incident. ''Lest We Forget'' was certified [[gold record|Gold]] in 2005.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.roadrunnerrecords.com/blabbermouth.net/news.aspx?mode=Article&amp;newsitemID=44134 |title=MARILYN MANSON: 'Lest We Forget' Certified Gold – November 12, 2005 |publisher=Roadrunnerrecords.com |date= |accessdate=2011-09-14}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===''Eat Me, Drink Me'' (2006–2008)===
[[File:Marilyn Manson Live In Florence.jpg|thumb|right|250px|Marilyn Manson performing live in Florence, Italy during the &quot;Rape of the World Tour&quot;.]]
Beginning in January 2006, and continuing for some months, Marilyn Manson's official website was updated several times, adding new artwork and music, and making obtuse references to The Celebritarian Corporation, an art movement led by the frontman. Merchandise has since become available featuring logos such as the &quot;double cross&quot; (a variation on the [[Cross of Lorraine]]), as well as the slogans &quot;we will sell our shadow to those who stand within it&quot; and &quot;do not seek death; seek destruction&quot;.

Marilyn Manson's sixth studio album, [[Eat Me, Drink Me]], was released on June 5, 2007, debuting at number 8 in the United States with more than 88,000 copies sold.&lt;ref name=&quot;EatDrink_Billboard&quot; /&gt; Released more than four years after ''[[The Golden Age of Grotesque]]'', ''Eat Me, Drink Me'' marked another change in musical styles that the band has become famous for. One remarkable note of the album is that it was written entirely by Manson and Skold in a rented home studio. The album is also the first major label Manson album without [[Madonna Wayne Gacy]] (Pogo) as a listed member, making lead singer [[Marilyn Manson]] the only original member since ''[[Portrait of an American Family]]''. [[Chris Vrenna]], who temporarily replaced [[Ginger Fish]] on drums during the Against All Gods Tour, replaced Pogo to become the band's full-time keyboardist. Marilyn Manson co-headlined a tour with [[Slayer]] in order to promote the album with [[Bleeding Through]] as the opening act and [[Deadly Apples]] on select dates.

&lt;div style=&quot;float: left;&quot;&gt;
{{listen
|pos=left
| filename = Marilyn Manson - If I Was Your Vampire.ogg
| title = &quot;If I Was Your Vampire&quot;
| description = Album version, as it appeared on ''Eat Me, Drink Me''
| format = [[Ogg]]
}}
&lt;/div&gt;
Rumors also circulated for some time that Marilyn Manson wrote the song &quot;Mutilation Is the Most Sincere Form of Flattery&quot; as an attack on the band [[My Chemical Romance]]. He later denied this, stating that it was aimed at people in general who sought to imitate him. In another interview Manson stated that &quot;I'm embarrassed to be me because these people are doing a really sad, pitiful, shallow version of what I've done&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Marilyn Manson slams My Chemical Romance 'sad and pitiful'|author=|publisher=NME.com|date=2007-06-05|url=http://www.nme.com/news/marilyn-manson/28753|accessdate=2008-01-27}}&lt;/ref&gt; In response to this, [[Gerard Way]], the lead singer of [[My Chemical Romance]] claimed nothing Manson could say would bring the band down. On January 9, 2008 Marilyn Manson posted a bulletin on [[MySpace]] confirming that former bassist [[Jeordie White|Twiggy Ramirez]] had rejoined the band, resulting in the exit of [[Tim Skold]]. Skold and Manson had apparently began writing new material before the personnel change. Future collaborations with Skold were not ruled out.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.marilynmanson.com/news/index.html Marilyn Manson | The Official Web Site] {{dead link|date=April 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.rollingstone.com/rockdaily/index.php/2008/01/18/marilyn-manson-bringing-twiggy-songs-satan-one-giant-evil-cocktail-on-tour/ Rolling Stone : Marilyn Manson Bringing Twiggy Songs, Satan, “One Giant Evil Cocktail” On Tour] {{dead link|date=April 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.rollingstone.com/rockdaily/index.php/2008/01/11/marilyn-manson-says-led-zeppelin-is-responsible-reunion-with-twiggy/ Rolling Stone : Marilyn Manson Says Led Zeppelin Is Responsible For Reunion With Twiggy] {{dead link|date=April 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===The return of Twiggy Ramirez and ''The High End of Low'' (2008–2009)===
[[File:Marilyn Manson f10300967.jpg|thumb|left|Marilyn Manson performing at Eurockéennes in 2009.]]
The band's seventh full-length studio album began recording sessions following the conclusion of their &quot;[[Rape of the World Tour]]&quot; on March 2, 2008.{{Citation needed|date=October 2009}} On November 29, 2007, Marilyn Manson fansite &quot;The Hierophant&quot; reported that the frontman planned to start writing songs for the new record on January or February (2008).{{Citation needed|date=October 2009}} The actual recording took place at Manson's [[Hollywood Hills]] home between November 2008 and January 5, 2009. The last song, called &quot;15&quot;, was completed on the evening of Manson's Jan 5 birthday—hence the name.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://suicidegirls.com/interviews/Marilyn%20Manson%3A%20The%20High%20End%20of%20Low/|title=Marilyn Manson: The High End of Low|publisher=[[SuicideGirls.com]]|date=2009-06-10|accessdate=2009-06-10}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Manson said, &quot;after my greatest hits album (''[[Lest We Forget: The Best Of]]'') came out I took a long break from music because it was a period where I was not sure who I wanted to be. I left music for a while but that's not an error I want to repeat in the future.&quot; He mentioned [[Kerry King]], [[James Iha]] former guitarist of [[The Smashing Pumpkins]], and [[Nick Zinner]] of the [[Yeah Yeah Yeahs]] as likely contributors.&lt;ref name=&quot;Manson: New album is very violent&quot;&gt;Kerrang! Magazine [http://www2.kerrang.com/2008/05/manson_new_album_is_very_viole.html Manson: &quot;New album is very violent&quot;], Kerrang! Magazine, May 23, 2008&lt;/ref&gt; During an exclusive interview titled ''Everyone Will Suffer Now'' at the now-defunct fansite MansonUSA on January 11, 2008, Manson shared, &quot;I just feel like there is a big change happening now. It's going to be the one. ''Eat Me, Drink Me'' is opening the window and this is going to be the Hurricane Katrina.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web| title=Everyone Will Suffer Now (archived by MansonWiki.com)| url=http://www.mansonwiki.com/wiki/Interview:Everyone_Will_Suffer_Now| publisher=MansonUSA (now defunct)| date=2008-01-12| accessdate=2010-11-01}}&lt;/ref&gt; Since parting company with Skold and reuniting with Ramirez, the band had occupied themselves with work on the album to achieve their target of a February 2009 release. It was soon followed by the announcement of new tour dates. In an interview with Steppin' Out, Manson described the then-nascent record as, &quot;very ruthless, very heavy, and very violent&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;Manson: New album is very violent&quot;/&gt;

On August 14, 2008, Manson announced at a public interview in [[Seoul, Korea]] that former [[Limp Bizkit]] guitarist and current [[Black Light Burns]] frontman [[Wes Borland]] had joined the lineup, replacing Rob Holliday on guitars. The band attended the ETP Festival and were wrapping up production on the new album. However, Borland left a few months later to reunite with Limp Bizkit for the third time. Borland told UK's [[Kerrang]] Magazine that he quit after seeing none of the nine songs he wrote for the record make the final cut, and was extremely dissatisfied at the thought of being just a hired gun.&lt;ref name=&quot;FMQB: QuickHits 8-15-08&quot;&gt;
{{cite web| title= FMQB: QuickHits 8-15-08| url= http://www.fmqb.com/article.asp?id=842530&amp;spid=1314| accessdate = 2008-08-16}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;div style=&quot;float: right;&quot;&gt;
{{listen
|pos=left
| filename = Marilyn Manson - Blank And White.ogg
| title = &quot;Blank and White&quot;
| description = Album version, as it appeared on ''The High End of Low''
| format = [[Ogg]]
| filename2 = Marilyn Manson - Into The Fire.ogg
| title2 = &quot;Into the Fire&quot;
| description2 = Album version, as it appeared on ''The High End of Low''
| format2 = [[Ogg]]
}}
&lt;/div&gt;
On October 5, the band played a special show at the annual Hot Topic managers meeting. The show took place at the [[Los Angeles International Airport]]'s [[Marriott Hotels &amp; Resorts|Marriott Hotel]]. During an after party for the 2008 [[Scream Awards]], Manson was overheard comparing the new album to ''Antichrist Superstar'' and stating the album was &quot;pretty much finished.&quot; He expected a new song to be released before the end of the year and expressed desire to release the record by Valentine's Day.{{Citation needed|date=October 2009}} In an interview on the February 2009 issue of ''Revolver Magazine'', he revealed the title of two songs, namely, &quot;I Wanna Kill You Like They Do in the Movies&quot; and &quot;Armagoddamnmotherfuckinggeddon&quot;. The album's producer [[Sean Beavan]], later posted a Myspace blog revealing two more song titles, &quot;15&quot; and &quot;Four Rusted Horses&quot;. Manson told ''Revolver'' &quot;I've got my fire back,&quot; and the record &quot;really wipes the floor with everything we've done before.&quot;{{Citation needed|date=October 2009}}

A statement was released by Manson on Christmas Eve in order to dispel rumors that had been circulating regarding his relationship with Evan Rachel Wood and a speculated collaboration with rapper [[Ne-Yo]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.vh1.com/news/articles/1600647/20081203/index.jhtml|title=Marilyn Manson Is Not Working With Ne-Yo, Spokesperson Insists|publisher=[[VH1]]|date=2008-12-03|accessdate=2011-05-24}}&lt;/ref&gt; On January 12, a new song title was divulged by [[Rudy Coby]], a collaborator and friend of the frontman. The song is called &quot;Devour&quot; and was said to be the album's first track.

Marilyn Manson joined Slayer as headliners for the [[Rockstar (drink)|Rockstar Energy]] [[Mayhem Festival]] tour in 2009. The press release for the tour stated that &quot;Manson is currently in the studio working on his seventh studio album scheduled for release May 18th on Interscope Records.&quot; On February 2, ''Rolling Stone'' confirmed the album had been officially titled ''[[The High End of Low]]''.

On March 18, 2009, Kerrang! reported that the album contained a total of 15 tracks and that the final song is called &quot;15&quot;. They also revealed another new song entitled &quot;We're from America&quot;. Manson opined on the latter song, &quot;I think a lot of people will hear the track and initially think it's just political, but it's not just that, it's also me describing a lot of fucked-up scenarios that I'm going through in my personal life. Someone asked me, 'Why are you so fucked up?', 'Well, I am from America.' I hate the fact that so many people have fucked the country up, and so many people fucked up my personal life and I allowed it to happen. So in a way, I feel like America as a whole feels, but in no way does that make me a tree-hugging patriotic freedom rocker.&quot; The track was released exclusively on the band's official website as a free download on March 27, 2009. On April 7, it became available for purchase as a digital single.

The album's official first single, &quot;[[Arma-Goddamn-Motherfuckin-Geddon]],&quot; arrived in radio stations on April 21. It peaked at number 37 on the ''Billboard'' Mainstream Rock Chart.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web| title=Arma-Goddamn-Motherfuckin-Geddon release and ''Billboard'' charting | url=http://news.prnewswire.com/DisplayReleaseContent.aspx?ACCT=104&amp;STORY=/www/story/03-23-2009/0004992609&amp;EDATE= | publisher=PRNewswire | date=2009-03-23| accessdate=2011-05-31}}&lt;/ref&gt; On April 16, 2009, marilynmanson.com was updated with a new splash page featuring the projected album artwork as well as the track listing for ''The High End of Low''. The record was released on May 26, 2009. It debuted at number 4 on the [[Billboard 200|''Billboard'' 200]] with 49,000 copies sold.&lt;ref name=&quot;HighEnd_Billboard&quot; /&gt; Despite reaching a higher charting position than Manson's prior studio effort ''Eat Me, Drink Me'', which debuted at number 8,&lt;ref name=&quot;EatDrink_Billboard&quot; /&gt; it arrived with the lowest opening week sum of any of Manson's albums since ''The Last Tour on Earth'' opened with sales of 26,000 units in 1999.

After much fan speculation and no official announcement, [[Andy Gerold]] joined Marilyn Manson in the capacity of live bassist for &quot;[[The High End of Low Tour]]&quot; after former bassist Twiggy Ramirez switched to lead guitar duties. Gerold played his first show with the band on June 3, 2009, in Brno, Czech Republic. As of 2011, Gerold is still the youngest musician to play in the band, preceding former drummer Sara Lee Lucas by nearly seven years. During the summer of 2009, the band co-headlined the [[Mayhem Festival 2009|2009 Mayhem Festival]] with [[Slayer]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.metalinjection.net/tour-dates/slayer-marilyn-manson-to-headline-mayhem-fest-2009-full-lineup-and-itinerary |title=SLAYER &amp; MARILYN MANSON to headline Mayhem Fest 2009 – Full Lineup and Itinerary |publisher=Metalinjection.net |date=2009-01-27 |accessdate=2011-09-14}}&lt;/ref&gt; Later in October 2009, the band headlined the internationally advertised [[visual kei]] event, V-Rock Music festival.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://search.japantimes.co.jp/cgi-bin/fm20091023a1.html |title=Versailles get dolled up for visual-kei fest &amp;#124; The Japan Times Online |publisher=Search.japantimes.co.jp |date=2009-10-23 |accessdate=2011-09-14}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Cooking Vinyl and ''Born Villain'' (2009–present)===
{{main|Born Villain}}
[[File:Marilyn Manson eight studio album logo.png|right|thumb|130px|Unveiled on May 22, 2011, the new [[CMYK color model|CMYK-styled]] logo is used by the band to signify the eighth studio album and their new era.&lt;ref name=&quot;NMEeighthstudioalbumonlinepreview&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;rapeture&quot;/&gt;]]
The eighth studio album by Marilyn Manson entered the writing phase during &quot;The High End of Low Tour&quot; in 2009.&lt;ref name=&quot;FirstMention&quot;&gt;{{cite web|last=Gill |first=James |url=http://www.metalhammer.co.uk/news/exclusive-marilyn-manson-i%E2%80%99m-back-with-evan-rachel-wood/ |title=Marilyn Manson: &quot;I'm Back With Evan Rachel Wood&quot; |work=[[Metal Hammer]] |publisher=[[Future Publishing]] |date=2009-03-12 |accessdate=2011-01-28}}&lt;/ref&gt; Bassist Twiggy projected a release date of 2011 through [[Cooking Vinyl|Cooking Vinyl Records]] and Marilyn Manson's own label Hell, etc.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.smnnews.com/2010/11/09/new-marilyn-manson-album-out-in-2011/|title=New Marilyn Manson Album Out in 2011 |work=SMNNews |date=2010-11-09|accessdate=2011-01-28}}&lt;/ref&gt; It is the band's first album since allowing their contract with Interscope Records to expire back in late 2009. Marilyn Manson attested that the lyrical content of the album will be &quot;more romantic&quot; yet &quot;self-abusive,&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;FirstMention&quot;/&gt; and described the sonic elements of the record as &quot;suicide death metal.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;RevolverTV&quot;&gt;{{cite web|last=Peterson |first=Marta |url=http://www.providermodule.com/media/index.php?v=i/2010/revolvertv |title=Marilyn Manson at Revolver Golden Gods Awards Interview |work=Revolver ''TV'' |publisher=[[Future US]] |date=2010-08-04 |accessdate=2011-01-28}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The prospect of an eighth studio album by the band was first confirmed by the frontman himself during an interview with Metal Hammer on December 3, 2009.&lt;ref name=&quot;FirstMention&quot;/&gt; He elaborated, &quot;We've just been released from our record contract with Interscope so I think a lot of the creative control on which my hands were tied on a lot of choices—the music videos—things like that. And the first example is [[The High End of Low#&quot;Running to the Edge of the World&quot;|the newest video]], they clearly wouldn't have allowed me to make that video. So we started writing new songs on the road—a bit like &lt;nowiki&gt;[&lt;/nowiki&gt;[[David Bowie]]'s album] ''[[Aladdin Sane]]''—I think people can expect a new record a lot sooner than we [expected].&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;FirstMention&quot;/&gt; According to Chris Vrenna, by January 2010, the band was already &quot;talking and coming up with concepts&quot; for the album.&lt;ref name=&quot;VrennaVF&quot;&gt;{{cite web|last=Shlosman |first=Rafi |url=http://vampirefreaks.com/content/comment.php?entry=447&amp;amp;amp;t=Interview+with+Chris+Vrenna |title=Interview with Chris Vrenna (NIN / Marilyn Manson) |work=''[[Vampirefreaks.com]]'' |date=2010-01-12 |accessdate=2011-01-28}}&lt;/ref&gt; On January 24, 2010, Manson confirmed on the band's official MySpace profile that &quot;the new album is officially in motion.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last=Manson |first=Marilyn |url={{WebCite|url=http://www.webcitation.org/5k0k4zdCq|date =2009-09-23}} |title=Marilyn Manson on MySpace Music |work=Myspace Music |publisher=[[News Corporation]] |date=2009-09-23 |accessdate=2011-01-28}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In April 2010, during his appearance at the ''[[Revolver (magazine)|Revolver]]'' Golden Gods Awards, Manson divulged that the band had recorded 13 songs, one of which failed to appear in a television series about vampires.&lt;ref name=&quot;RevolverTV&quot;/&gt; He referred to the album as &quot;very death metal&quot; and voiced interest in releasing the album differently than previous Marilyn Manson records.&lt;ref name=&quot;RevolverTV&quot;/&gt; He also indicated his friendship with [[Slayer]] as a vague influence on the record.&lt;ref name=&quot;RevolverTV&quot;/&gt; During an interview with ''[[Full Metal Jackie]]'', he stated that the album was halfway finished.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.youtube.com/v/RfsXHwv2SfQ?fs |title=Revolver Golden Gods Marilyn Manson Interview |date= |accessdate=2011-09-14}}&lt;/ref&gt;

On May 7, 2010, both entertainer Rudy Coby and The Nachtkabarett's Nick Kushner were previewed material from the album, the latter described it on Facebook as &quot;fuckin' hardcore.&quot; Elaborating on the band's musical direction, Manson commented on Twiggy being influenced by his touring experiences in 2009, particularly during the [[Rockstar (drink)|Rockstar]] [[Mayhem Festival]]. Manson's father, Hugh Warner, described the album,

{{cquote|It will make a vagina wet. What can you say after that? If the vagina's wet, all things are good. That's what he [Manson] told me when I was listening to it. It's very hard, very heavy, very good. Everyone should be extremely excited and happy.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last=Aaron &amp; Jen |url=http://www.mansonwiki.com/wiki/Interview:2010/08/15_The_Apple_Does_Not_Fall_Far...(Interview_with_Hugh_Warner) |title=The Apple Does Not Fall Far...(Interview with Hugh Warner) |work=MansonWiki |date=2010-08-15 |accessdate=2011-01-28}}&lt;/ref&gt;}}

During an interview with Eric Blair on November 3, 2010, bassist Twiggy Ramirez indicated that the new album was &quot;almost done. It'll probably be out next year. [...] It's our best record yet, I think. I mean, everyone always says that, but I think this is our best work so far... It's kind of like a little more of a [[punk rock]] ''[[Mechanical Animals]]'' without sounding too pretentious.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last=Blair |first=Eric |url=http://www.roadrunnerrecords.com/blabbermouth.net/news.aspx?mode=Article&amp;newsitemID=148750 |title=Marilyn Manson Bassist Says Upcoming Album Is 'Our Best Record Yet' |work=''[[Blabbermouth.net]]'' |publisher=Borivoj Krgin |date=2010-11-03 |accessdate=2011-01-28}}&lt;/ref&gt;

For much of the early half of 2011, Marilyn Manson removed himself from the public spotlight and ceased almost all communication with his fans or the outside world.&lt;ref name=&quot;MMinTempatKuVid&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.kerrang.com/blog/2011/03/marilyn_manson_stars_in_my_che.html |title=Marilyn Manson stars in My Chemical Romance-esque pop video |work=Kerrang! |publisher=Bauer Media Group |date=2011-03-18 |accessdate=2011-06-04}}&lt;/ref&gt; On February 24, 2011, the band's longtime drummer [[Ginger Fish]] announced his resignation from the group, prompting a search for a replacement.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.twitlonger.com/show/8vrp3u |title=Ginger Fish Announces Resignation |work=''Twitlonger.com'' |date=2011-02-24 |accessdate=2011-02-24}}&lt;/ref&gt; Meanwhile, on March 18, 2011, Marilyn Manson took a short break from his self-imposed sequestration by appearing in the music video for the song &quot;Tempat Ku&quot; by Brunei pop outfit [[D'Hask]].&lt;ref name=&quot;MMinTempatKuVid&quot;/&gt; On March 23, 2011, he uploaded new pictures onto the band's [[Facebook]] page, in a different style of previous photos.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.facebook.com/album.php?id=93211205814&amp;aid=138917#!/photo.php?fbid=10150173993640815&amp;set=a.146185015814.138917.93211205814&amp;theater Wall Photos | Facebook]—Manson's Facebook reveals new photos of the new era. Access date: March 23, 2011.&lt;/ref&gt; The new style suggested the 'new era' of Marilyn Manson had begun, further generating anticipation for the upcoming release.

On May 22, 2011, the band's website underwent a complete overhaul. A short 26 second snippet of a new song, tentatively titled, &quot;I am among no one (excerpt from an undisclosed song with an unreleased title)&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;NMEeighthstudioalbumonlinepreview&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.nme.com/news/marilyn-manson/56835 |title=Marilyn Manson previews eighth studio album online |work=NME |publisher=IPC Media |date=2011-05-23 |accessdate=2011-06-11}}&lt;/ref&gt; was uploaded to the redesigned main page along with a new logo to signify their eight studio album and the new era. The logo consisted of the letter M repeated four times in a spiral pattern, each with one long tail. At the end of the long tail is the Chinese [[Ba gua|trigram]] ☲ (離 lí) of the [[I Ching]]. Read lengthwise or up-and-down, it formed [[Hexagram 30]], &quot;Radiance,&quot; also called &quot;the clinging&quot; and &quot;the net&quot;. The origin of the character is rooted in symbols of long-tailed birds such as the [[peacock]] or the legendary [[phoenix (mythology)|phoenix]]. The [[CMYK color model|CMYK coloring]] was also notable with regard to an [[acrostic]] formed by Manson, in a journal entry that accompanied the site changes, which spelled out the words &quot;Christianity Manufactures Yesterdays Killers&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;NMEeighthstudioalbumonlinepreview&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;rapeture&quot;&gt;{{cite web|last=Manson |first=Marilyn |url=http://marilynmanson.com/2011/rapeture/ |title=Rapeture |work=''[[Marilynmanson.com]]'' |publisher=[[Marilyn Manson]] |date=2011-05-22 |accessdate=2011-05-23}}&lt;/ref&gt;

On June 3, 2011 the Brazilian edition of the Portuguese [[broadsheet]] newspaper [[Destak]] confirmed that agents for the band had finalized negotiations for the group to tour in Brazil and other South American countries as part of the [[SWU Music &amp; Arts|SWU Music &amp; Arts Festival]] beginning on the second week of November 2011.&lt;ref name=&quot;SWU2011Destak1&quot;&gt;{{cite web|last=Flesch |first=José Norberto |url=http://www.destakjornal.com.br/readContent.aspx?id=17,98997 |title=Marilyn Manson comes to Brazil in November |work=[[Destak]] |publisher=[[Cofina]] |date=2011-06-03 |accessdate=2011-06-08}}&lt;/ref&gt; The Brazilian music festival also saw a change in venue for 2011.&lt;ref name=&quot;SWU2011Destak1&quot;/&gt; While organizers have yet to finalize details, it was speculated that the event may be held at the [[São Paulo (state)|São Paulo]] municipality of [[Paulínia]].&lt;ref name=&quot;SWU2011Destak1&quot;/&gt; Manson appeared live via the [[Ustream.tv|Ustream]] broadcast of ''[[Charles Fleischer|Fleischer's Universe]]'' on June 21, 2011, where he announced that the new album title will be revealed within a week. He also divulged the following lyrics, &quot;The center of the universe cannot exist if there are no edges&quot;, of a yet to be released song.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite interview |last=Manson |first=Marilyn |subjectlink=Marilyn Manson |interviewer=[[Charles Fleischer]] |title=Marilyn Manson interview on Fleischer's Universe |callsign =[[Ustream.tv]] |publisher=John Ham |city=Los Angeles |date=2011-06-21}}&lt;/ref&gt; The album title was not, in fact, revealed within a week, but was announced on September 1 as ''Born Villain'' via Twitter.

After being impressed by his directorial work on one of [[Kid Cudi]]'s music videos, Marilyn Manson employed the actor [[Shia LaBeouf]] to work on the album artwork as well as create a &quot;making-of&quot; video documenting the album's recording and production.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web| title = Marilyn Manson recruits Shia LaBeouf to document new album| work = Kerrang! | publisher = Bauer Media Group| url = http://www.kerrang.com/blog/2011/07/marilyn_manson_recruits_shia_l.html|date=2011-07-01 | accessdate = 2011-07-01}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web| last = Barshad| first = Amos| title = Shia LaBeouf Told Regis and Kelly He's Working With Marilyn Manson| work = Vulture | publisher= [[New York (magazine)|''New York'' magazine]]| date = 2011-07-01| url = http://nymag.com/daily/entertainment/2011/07/shia_labeouf_told_regis_and_ke.html| accessdate = 2011-07-01}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title =Transformers star Shia LaBeouf set to shoot new Marilyn Manson documentary| work =NME | publisher=IPC Media | date = 2011-07-01 | url = http://www.nme.com/news/marilyn-manson/57704| accessdate = 2011-07-02}}&lt;/ref&gt;

On November 22, 2011, it was announced that Chris Vrenna had officially left the band after contributing to the writing and production of ''Born Villain''. &lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title =Chris Vrenna Leaves Marilyn Manson to Focus on New Projects | work = Type 3 Media | publisher=Type 3 Media | date = 2011-23-11 | url = http://type3media.com/2011/11/23/chris-vrenna-leaves-marilyn-manson-to-focus-on-new-projects/}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Marilyn Manson (Brian Warner)==
{{main|Marilyn Manson}}
Marilyn Manson (born Brian Hugh Warner; January 5, 1969) is an American musician and artist known for his controversial stage persona and image as the frontman of the band. His stage name was formed from the names of actress [[Marilyn Monroe]] and convicted murderer [[Charles Manson]]. His long legacy as being depicted in the media as a bad influence on children and society, along with his seemingly outrageous styles for which he models, and the controversy surrounding his lyrics all have led to his more pronounced public appeal. Manson's frequent clashes with political and religious figures, along with his actions and performances make him iconic to the band.

==Controversy==
In December 1996, a press conference was called by [[William J. Bennett]], Senator [[Joseph Lieberman]], and activist [[C. Delores Tucker|C. DeLores Tucker]], aimed at [[Music Corporation of America|MCA]], the owner of Interscope Records. Calling several albums released by the label — including ''[[Antichrist Superstar]]'' — &quot;profane&quot;, &quot;violent&quot;, &quot;filth&quot;, and &quot;crap&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |last=Phillips |first=Chuck |url=http://www.latimes.com/news/local/la-me-mcaphilips10dec1096,0,7510275.story |title=Critics expected to take on MCA for explicit rap lyrics |publisher=''[[Los Angeles Times]]'' |date=1996-12-10 |accessdate=2011-05-10}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;blame&quot;&gt;[http://groups.google.com/group/alt.music.marilyn-manson/msg/5f8b2fa591032024 Manson the blame of suicide 11/6/97] while apparently listening to The Reflecting God&lt;/ref&gt; the group questioned MCA president [[Edgar Bronfman, Jr.]]'s ability to head the label competently while profiting from such material. That November 6, U.S. Senate Subcommittee on Oversight of Government Management and Restructuring held a public hearing on the effect of violent rock and rap lyrics on youths. Supporters of the band claim it was merely another salvo in Senator Lieberman's declared war on the band. The hearing, chaired by Representative [[Sam Brownback]], featured the testimony of Lieberman and Tucker, and of Raymond Kuntz, of [[Burlington, North Dakota]], who blamed his son's [[suicide]] on ''Antichrist Superstar'', which Lieberman denounced as &quot;vile, hateful, [[Nihilism|nihilistic]] and damaging.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;blame&quot;/&gt;

In addition, the band's performances have come under fire — the Dead to the World Tour, in particular, was followed by protesters at nearly every North American venue it visited. The band's March 10, 1997 performance in [[Columbia, South Carolina]] was canceled &quot;in response to growing public pressure by religious, civic and political leaders who criticized the group's image&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;Paula O' Keefe, &quot;The History of Marilyn Manson, 1997 Update Part 1 of 2&quot;, at [http://www.spookhouse.net/97update.html Spookhouse.net]. Retrieved September 9, 2006.&lt;/ref&gt; The owner of [[Calgary]]'s Max Bell Centre had Marilyn Manson's July 25 show canceled, citing &quot;immorality&quot; and the band's &quot;use of animals on stage.&quot; Another concert in [[Portland, Oregon|Portland]] was canceled a few days later due to Manson's reputation, and the venue's inability to get insurance for the show.&lt;ref&gt;Paula O' Keefe, &quot;The History of Marilyn Manson, 1997 Update Part 2 of 2&quot;, at [http://www.spookhouse.net/update2.html Spookhouse.net]. Retrieved September 9, 2006.&lt;/ref&gt;

The New Jersey date of Ozzfest '97, to be held at [[Giants Stadium]], was canceled by the New Jersey Sports and Exhibition Authority, who cited Marilyn Manson's performance as its reason; the event was only held after [[Ozzy Osbourne]] himself successfully sued the state, which compelled the authorities to allow the concert. Legislation was introduced and passed in South Carolina and Utah allowing state-operated venues to ban groups like Marilyn Manson from performing and, in at least one instance, in Florida, local schools have gone so far as to threaten [[expulsion (academia)|expulsion]] for students in attendance of Marilyn Manson concerts.&lt;ref name=&quot;Strauss&quot;/&gt;

===School shootings===
{{Quote box|quote=&quot;I couldn't care less about [[Eric Harris and Dylan Klebold|those kids']] reasoning. What reason do we have to go to war? It's all the same. Killing somebody can't be justified by having a reason. I think it says a lot about the [news] media that those two kids were on the cover of [[Time (magazine)|''Time'' magazine]] twice because I'm sure that's everything they wanted. They wanted fame. America sold them the idea that an obituary is just another headline.&quot; |source=—Marilyn Manson on the Columbine massacre.&lt;ref name=&quot;NME Marilyn Manson Goes Ape&quot;&gt;{{cite journal |last1=Kessler |first1=Ted |last2= |first2= |date=2000-09-09 |title=Marilyn Manson Goes Ape |journal=[[NME]] |volume= |issue= |pages=28–31 |publisher=[[IPC Media]] |doi= |url= |accessdate=2011-04-30}}&lt;/ref&gt; |salign=center |width=25% |align=right |style=padding:8px;}}Following the [[Columbine High School massacre]], there were accusations that killers [[Eric Harris and Dylan Klebold]] were influenced by Marilyn Manson's music. When later evidence was presented that neither Harris nor Klebold were fans of the band, many were led to criticize the media for using the band as a scapegoat instead of analyzing the underlying societal problems surrounding the incident.&lt;ref&gt;Cullen, Dave. [http://www.salon.com/news/feature/1999/09/23/columbine/index.html Inside the Columbine High investigation]. ''Salon News'', September 23, 1999.&lt;/ref&gt; In the controversial documentary ''[[Bowling for Columbine]]'', [[Michael Moore]] interviewed Manson about the tragedy. When asked what he would say to the victims, Manson replied &quot;I wouldn't say a single word to them; I would listen to what they have to say, and that's what no one did&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;Marilyn Manson in [http://www.imdb.com/title/tt0310793/quotes ''Bowling for Columbine'']&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.bowlingforcolumbine.com/media/clips/windowsmedia.php?Clip=manson1021LG |title=Marilyn Manson Interview on Bowling for Columbine |publisher=[http://www.bowlingforcolumbine.com/index.php Bowling for Columbine Official Website] |date=2002-10-11 |accessdate=2010-11-15}}&lt;/ref&gt; Manson also submitted an op-ed piece to ''[[Rolling Stone]]'' magazine [June 24, 1999] titled &quot;[http://www.antilife.org/files/marilyn.html Columbine: Whose Fault Is It?]&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;RS Columbine: Whose Fault Is It?&quot;&gt;{{cite journal |author= Marilyn Manson |title= Columbine: Whose Fault Is It? |type=op-ed essay |edition= |issue=815 |series= |volume= |date=1999-05-28 |journal=[[Rolling Stone]] |publisher=Wenner Media LLC}}&lt;/ref&gt; which detailed his opinion on violence as an inherent cultural presence as well as discussing the shootings and his status as an easy target for blame in incidents of this kind. He also said that he expresses condolences to the victim's families. Rapper [[Eminem]] criticized the controversy in his song &quot;[[The Way I Am (Eminem song)|The Way I Am]]&quot;, which contains the line, &quot;When a dude's gettin' bullied and shoots up his school/And they blame it on Marilyn, and the heroin/Where were the parents at?&quot;. Marilyn Manson made a cameo in the video for the song, and even contributed vocals to a guitar-heavy remix.

The controversy connecting Marilyn Manson and American [[school shootings]] continued on October 10, 2007 when 14-year-old [[Asa Coon]] opened gunfire on his high school in Cleveland, Ohio. [[SuccessTech Academy]] went to lock-down status around 1:15pm, when Coon shot four people; including two students, and two teachers, before turning the gun on himself. Police reports, and student interviews claim that Coon was wearing a Marilyn Manson t-shirt during the rampage. On several occasions, Coon told students and teachers that he did not believe in, nor respect God; instead worshipped the band's vocalist, Brian Warner. Coon was known for violent behavior, and stood out among the student body for his appearance—which included black boots, a black trench coat, black nail polish, and rock t-shirts.&lt;ref&gt;[http://news.yahoo.com/s/ap/20071011/ap_on_re_us/school_shooting School Shooting]{{dead link|date=September 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Musical style==
Marilyn Manson has come to be known for altering both its image and its musical trappings frequently; the group's sound incorporating, at various stages, elements of spoken-word poetry, glam rock, and — more recently — [[vaudeville]] and [[American burlesque|burlesque]]. Genres ascribed to the band over its career include [[alternative metal]],&lt;ref name=&quot;allmusic1&quot;&gt;[{{Allmusic|class=artist|id=p45021|pure_url=yes}} Manson at allmusic]&lt;/ref&gt; [[alternative rock]],&lt;ref name=&quot;allmusic2&quot;&gt;[{{Allmusic|class=album|id=r374601|pure_url=yes}} Mechanical Animals review at allmusic]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;IGN&quot;&gt;{{cite web|author=Ed Thompson |url=http://uk.music.ign.com/articles/794/794055p1.html |title=Eat Me Drink Me review at IGN Music |publisher=Uk.music.ign.com |date=2007-06-04 |accessdate=2011-09-14}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[hard rock]],&lt;ref name=&quot;RollingStone&quot;&gt;[http://www.rollingstone.com/artists/marilynmanson/biography Manson at Rolling Stone] {{dead link|date=April 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Musicmight&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://musicmight.com/artist/united+states/florida/fort+lauderdale/marilyn+manson |title=Manson at Musicmight |publisher=Musicmight.com |date= |accessdate=2011-09-14}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[heavy metal music|heavy metal]],&lt;ref name=&quot;allmusic1&quot; /&gt; [[industrial metal]],&lt;ref name=&quot;allmusic1&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;RollingStone&quot; /&gt; [[industrial rock]]&lt;ref name=&quot;RollingStone&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;NME&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.nme.com/artists/marilyn-manson |title=Marilyn Manson at NME |publisher=Nme.com |date= |accessdate=2011-09-14}}&lt;/ref&gt; and [[shock rock]].&lt;ref name=&quot;allmusic1&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;IGN&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Musicmight&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Essi Berelian, ''The Rough Guide to Heavy Metal'', 2005, p. 215&lt;/ref&gt; Lead singer Manson was fond of [[Alice Cooper]], [[David Bowie]], [[The Doors]], [[Black Sabbath]] and [[Kiss (band)|Kiss]] as a young music fan.&lt;ref name=&quot;longhard&quot;/&gt; Then later fond of [[The Cure]] and [[Bauhaus (band)|Bauhaus]] (''[[Eat Me, Drink Me]]'' period).

===Influences===
Initially, after being introduced to [[Big Black]]'s album ''[[Songs About Fucking]]'' by a fellow Miami clubgoer, who would become his keyboard player, [[Madonna Wayne Gacy]], Manson had the desire to form a rock band that used a [[drum machine]] — an uncommon technique outside of dance music at the time.&lt;ref name=&quot;longhard&quot;/&gt; The earliest incarnations of Marilyn Manson used this setup, and produced experimental, drum-heavy compositions similar to [[Steve Albini]]'s work with Big Black; later, with the addition of a live drummer, the band's composing process, recording techniques, and live performances were by necessity altered. Guitarist [[Daisy Berkowitz]] and bassist [[Gidget Gein]], who came from [[punk rock]] backgrounds, brought the musicianship and songwriting style of the [[Jim Carroll]] Band (whose &quot;People Who Died&quot; was an early favorite [[cover song|cover]] for Marilyn Manson) and the showmanship of [[The New York Dolls]] to the mixture. The result was something that [[Nothing Records]] would initially compare to [[Jane's Addiction]],{{Citation needed|date=October 2009}} but which, after the band spent some time at Nothing, would also gather sonic elements from other bands on that label's roster, like [[Nine Inch Nails]] and [[Kevin McMahon (musician)|Prick]].

Marilyn Manson was also influenced by his mentor who raised his notoriety in the industrial scene, Nine Inch Nails' Trent Reznor. Reznor started Manson on his record label, Nothing Records, as well as allowing him a spot in his touring entourage.

Evidently, Manson is heavily influenced by the [[shock rock]] stylings of such artists as [[Arthur Brown (musician)|Arthur Brown]], [[Mötley Crüe]], [[Alice Cooper]], [[Kiss (band)|Kiss]] and some of [[Iggy Pop]]; however, late influences have come from the glam rock of [[David Bowie]] (who Manson claims is his biggest influence), whose [[chameleon]]-like ability to shift from one style to another, replete with a new look and musical philosophy, was a characteristic which would also be frequently ascribed to Marilyn Manson by the music press.&lt;ref&gt;Ankeny, Jason. ''Marilyn Manson''. [{{Allmusic|class=artist|id=p45021|pure_url=yes}} Allmusic]. Retrieved December 1, 2005.&lt;/ref&gt; Such an influence is exemplified in the similarities between the music videos of Bowie's &quot;[[The Heart's Filthy Lesson]]&quot; and many of Manson's videos, such as &quot;[[Sweet Dreams (Are Made of This)]]&quot;. (Floria Sigismondi has directed music videos for both Bowie (Little Wonder) and Manson (The Beautiful People and Tourniquet)) The [[hard rock]] background of John 5 amplified this aspect of the band's sound in live performance; Tim Skold, a former guitarist, bassist, and vocalist in [[Shotgun Messiah]], later blended in that band's mixture of industrial drums and guitars. Both Manson and Twiggy Ramirez have mentioned the influence of [[Queen (band)|Queen]] on their more melodic work, particularly on ''[[Mechanical Animals]]'' and ''[[Eat Me, Drink Me]]'', the latter of which Twiggy did not work on.

===Composition and songwriting===
{{Section OR|date=July 2009}}
All of the band's lyrics are written by the lead singer, [[Marilyn Manson]], whose songwriting style varies between the band's albums. He uses sharp and inventive [[word play]] often making use of [[pun]]s and [[double entendre]]s in his writing — for instance, a song on the ''[[Holy Wood (In the Shadow of the Valley of Death)|Holy Wood]]'' album, which references the shootings at [[Columbine High School]], is titled &quot;Target Audience&quot;; the album also makes frequent allusions to [[assassination]], and the song &quot;The Fall of Adam&quot; refers to &quot;[[Abraham Lincoln]] [[Lincoln Town Car|Town Cars]]&quot;. These witticisms often take the form of [[neologism]]s, delivered several at a time in rapid-fire fashion. Concerning Manson's vocal melodies, the lyrics are usually delivered in a spoken, shouting, or melody driven fashion, the latter usually being reserved for the chorus sections.

The instrumental component is primarily composed by the other permanent band members, who at present are Twiggy Ramirez on studio &amp; live bass and occasional studio guitars; and Ginger Fish, on live drums. Until his departure from the band, [[Twiggy Ramirez]] was a chief contributor to the compositions, with receiving &quot;music by&quot; credits on every Marilyn Manson album prior to ''[[The Golden Age of Grotesque]]'', with the exception of ''[[Portrait of an American Family]]'', with [[Daisy Berkowitz]] and [[Gidget Gein]] sharing songwriting credits. According to the albums' credits, every permanent member of the band has had input, at some point, in its songwriting process.

During the first part of their major label career (1994–2004), Marilyn Manson often recorded [[cover version]]s of songs by other artists.
All of the officially-released covers the band have recorded are:

{| class=&quot;wikitable&quot;
|-
!width=&quot;35&quot;|Year
!Title
!Released on
!Original artist
|-
|rowspan=&quot;4&quot;|1995
| &quot;[[Down in the Park]]&quot;
| ''[[Lunchbox (song)|Lunchbox]]'' (EP)
| [[Gary Numan]]
|-
| &quot;[[Sweet Dreams (Are Made of This) (Marilyn Manson song)|Sweet Dreams (Are Made of This)]]&quot;
| ''[[Smells Like Children]]'' (EP)
| [[Eurythmics]]
|-
| &quot;[[I Put a Spell on You]]&quot;
| ''Smells Like Children''
| [[Screamin' Jay Hawkins]]
|-
| &quot;[[Rock N Roll Nigger|Rock 'n' Roll Nigger]]&quot;
| ''Smells Like Children''
| [[Patti Smith]]
|-
||1998
| &quot;[[Golden Years (song)|Golden Years]]&quot;
| ''[[Dead Man on Campus (film)|Dead Man on Campus]]'' ([[Soundtrack|OST]])
| [[David Bowie]]
|-
|rowspan=&quot;3&quot;|1999
| &quot;[[Highway to Hell (song)|Highway to Hell]]&quot;
| ''[[Detroit Rock City (film)#Soundtrack|Detroit Rock City]]'' (OST)
| [[AC/DC]]
|-
| &quot;Get My Rocks Off&quot;
| ''[[The Last Tour on Earth]]''
| [[Dr. Hook &amp; The Medicine Show|Doctor Hook]]
|-
| &quot;[[A Rose and a Baby Ruth]]&quot;
| ''The Last Tour on Earth''
| [[George Hamilton IV]]
|-
|rowspan=&quot;3&quot;|2000
| &quot;[[Working Class Hero]]&quot;
| [[Disposable Teens]] (single)
| [[John Lennon]]
|-
| &quot;[[Five to One]]&quot;
| Disposable Teens
| [[The Doors]]
|-
| &quot;[[Suicide Is Painless]]&quot;
| ''[[Book of Shadows: Blair Witch 2#Soundtrack|Book of Shadows: Blair Witch 2]]'' (OST)
| [[Theme song|Theme From]] ''[[M*A*S*H]]''
|-
| 2001
| &quot;[[Tainted Love#Marilyn Manson cover|Tainted Love]]&quot;
| ''[[Not Another Teen Movie Soundtrack|Not Another Teen Movie]]'' (OST)
| [[Gloria Jones]]
|-
|rowspan=&quot;2&quot;|2003
| &quot;[[The KKK Took My Baby Away]]&quot;
| ''[[We're a Happy Family: A Tribute to Ramones|We're A Happy Family: A Tribute to]]''
| [[The Ramones]]
|-
| &quot;Mind of a Lunatic&quot;
| [[This Is the New Shit]] (single)
| [[Geto Boys|The Geto Boys]]
|-
| 2004
| &quot;[[Personal Jesus#Marilyn Manson cover|Personal Jesus]]&quot;
| ''[[Lest We Forget: The Best Of]]''
| [[Depeche Mode]]
|-
| 2006
| &quot;[[This Is Halloween]]&quot;
| ''[[The Nightmare Before Christmas (soundtrack)|The Nightmare Before Christmas]]'' (OST)
| [[Danny Elfman]]
|}

==Band members==
{{Main|Marilyn Manson band members}}
Many members have contributed performances (either live or in-studio) on instruments other than their primary ones. For instance, Ramirez has played guitar on several records while his live instrument is bass (though has recently switched to live guitar), Madonna Wayne Gacy (&quot;Pogo&quot;) has played [[Keyboard instrument|Keyboards]], [[theremin]] and [[calliope (music)|calliope]], Manson has played [[pan flute]], [[harpsichord]], [[Keyboard instrument|keyboards]], and [[guitar]], and Berkowitz has been credited with bass guitar and [[drum machine]]s. Chris Vrenna filled in on drums for Ginger Fish when he was injured, and later replaced Pogo on keyboards, however, following the departure of Ginger Fish, Vrenna may become the permanent drummer.

{{col-begin}}
{{Col-2}}
;Current
* [[Marilyn Manson]] – lead vocals (since 1989)
* [[Twiggy Ramirez]] – guitars (since 2009), bass guitar (1993–2002, 2008)
* [[Fred Sablan]] – bass guitar (since 2010) &lt;ref name=&quot;Manson_Facebook&quot;&gt;{{cite web| title=Official Marilyn Manson facebook| url=http://www.facebook.com/MarilynManson| publisher=[[Marilyn Manson]]| date=2010-07-25| accessdate=2010-11-01}}&lt;/ref&gt;
{{Col-2}}
;Former&lt;!--DO NOT REMOVE THE FOLLOWING BAND MEMBERS WITHOUT A RATIONALE.--&gt;
* [[Zsa Zsa Speck]] – keyboards (1989)
* [[Olivia Newton Bundy]] – bass (1989)
* [[Gidget Gein]] – bass (1989/1990–1994)
* [[Sara Lee Lucas]] – drums, percussion (1991–1995)
* [[Scott Putesky|Daisy Berkowitz]] – guitars (1989–1996)
* [[Zim Zum]] – guitars (1996–1998)
* [[John 5 (guitarist)|John 5]] – guitars (1998–2004)
* [[Madonna Wayne Gacy]] – keyboards, percussion (1989–2007)
* [[Tim Sköld]] – guitars (2006–2008), bass (2002–2005)
* [[Ginger Fish]] – drums, percussion (1995–2011)
* [[Chris Vrenna]] – drums, percussion (2004-2005), keyboards, percussion (2007–2011)

;Touring
* [[Mark Chaussee]] – guitars (2004–2005)
* [[Chris Vrenna]] – drums (2004–2005)
* [[Rob Holliday]] – bass (2007), guitars (2008)
* [[Wes Borland]] – guitars (2008)
* [[Andy Gerold]] – bass (2009)
{{col-end}}

==Discography==
{{Main|Marilyn Manson discography}}

* ''[[Portrait of an American Family]]'' (1994)
* ''[[Antichrist Superstar]]'' (1996)
* ''[[Mechanical Animals]]'' (1998)
* ''[[Holy Wood (In the Shadow of the Valley of Death)]]'' (2000)
* ''[[The Golden Age of Grotesque]]'' (2003)
* ''[[Eat Me, Drink Me]]'' (2007)
* ''[[The High End of Low]]'' (2009)
* ''[[Born Villain]]'' (2012)

==Awards==
&lt;!-- ATTENTION: If you wish to delete this section, the reason must not be that you despise the Grammy Awards or that you think no one takes them seriously. Regardless of whether that is true, this content is still notable enough to be on Wikipedia. See: [[Wikipedia: Notability]]--&gt;
Marilyn Manson has been nominated for three [[Grammy Award]]s.

* &quot;[[The Dope Show]]&quot;&amp;nbsp;– [[Grammy Award for Best Hard Rock Performance|Best Hard Rock Performance]], 1999
* &quot;[[Astonishing Panorama of the Endtimes]]&quot;&amp;nbsp;– [[Grammy Award for Best Metal Performance|Best Metal Performance]], 2001
* &quot;[[Mobscene|mOBSCENE]]&quot;&amp;nbsp;– [[Grammy Award for Best Metal Performance|Best Metal Performance]], 2004

On August 29, 2000, the band was inducted by ''[[Kerrang!]]'' into their Hall of Fame at the 2000 [[Kerrang! Awards]]. The band's frontman was on hand to receive the award from [[Swedish people|Swedish-born]] actress [[Britt Ekland]]. As a result of a [[food fight]] that erupted between guests like [[Iron Maiden]], [[Foo Fighters]], and [[Motorhead]], the presenter slipped on piece of watermelon and broke her ankle and wrist. Still, she presented the award to [[Marilyn Manson]] while sitting in a chair.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.vh1.com/news/articles/1436862/20000830/index.jhtml |title=Marilyn Manson's Big Day Out |work=[[VH1]] |publisher=MTV Networks (Viacom) |date=2000-08-30 |accessdate=2011-04-05}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==References==
{{reflist|colwidth=30em}}

===Literature===
* &lt;cite id=refScaruffi2003&gt;{{Cite book | last=Scaruffi |first=Piero |title=A History of Rock Music:1951-2000 |publisher=¡Universe, Inc. |year=2003 |isbn=978-0-595-29565-4}}

==External links==
{{Commons category|Marilyn Manson}}
* {{Official website|www.marilynmanson.com}}
* [http://www.spookykids.net Marilyn Manson &amp; the Spooky Kids website]

{{Marilyn Manson}}
{{Nine Inch Nails}}
{{Nothing Records}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Manson, Marilyn}}
[[Category:Marilyn Manson|*]]
[[Category:American rock music groups]]
[[Category:American alternative metal musical groups]]
[[Category:Industrial metal musical groups]]
[[Category:Heavy metal musical groups from Florida]]
[[Category:Interscope Records artists]]
[[Category:Nothing Records artists]]
[[Category:Musical groups from Fort Lauderdale, Florida]]
[[Category:Musical groups established in 1989]]
[[Category:Musical quartets]]
[[Category:Musical quintets]]
[[Category:Kerrang! Awards winners]]
[[Category:Obscenity controversies]]

{{Link GA|eo}}
{{Link GA|sv}}
[[bn:মারিলিয়্যান ম্যানসন]]
[[bs:Marilyn Manson (grupa)]]
[[cs:Marilyn Manson]]
[[da:Marilyn Manson (band)]]
[[de:Marilyn Manson]]
[[et:Marilyn Manson]]
[[es:Marilyn Manson (banda)]]
[[eo:Marilyn Manson (muzika grupo)]]
[[eu:Marilyn Manson]]
[[fa:مریلین منسون (گروه موسیقی)]]
[[fr:Marilyn Manson (groupe)]]
[[hr:Marilyn Manson]]
[[id:Marilyn Manson (band)]]
[[it:Marilyn Manson (gruppo musicale)]]
[[he:מרילין מנסון (להקה)]]
[[lv:Marilyn Manson (grupa)]]
[[lt:Marilyn Manson (grupė)]]
[[hu:Marilyn Manson (együttes)]]
[[nl:Marilyn Manson (band)]]
[[ja:マリリン・マンソン (バンド)]]
[[no:Marilyn Manson (band)]]
[[uz:Marilyn Manson (guruh)]]
[[pl:Marilyn Manson (grupa muzyczna)]]
[[pt:Marilyn Manson (banda)]]
[[ro:Marilyn Manson (formaţie)]]
[[ru:Marilyn Manson]]
[[sk:Marilyn Manson (skupina)]]
[[sl:Marilyn Manson (skupina)]]
[[sr:Merilin Menson (grupa)]]
[[fi:Marilyn Manson]]
[[sv:Marilyn Manson (musikgrupp)]]
[[tr:Marilyn Manson (müzik grubu)]]
[[uk:Marilyn Manson]]
[[zh:瑪麗蓮·曼森 (樂隊)]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
