<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="19596391" ns="0" title="Aníbal Cavaco Silva"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{pp-move-vandalism|small=yes}}
{{BLP sources|date=January 2011}}
{{Portuguese name|Cavaco|Silva}}
{{Infobox Officeholder
|honorific-prefix = &lt;small&gt;[[Excellency|His Excellency]]&lt;/small&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
|name             = Aníbal Cavaco Silva
|honorific-suffix = &lt;br /&gt;&lt;small&gt;[[Order of Christ (Portugal)|GCC]]&lt;/small&gt;
|image            = Cavaco Silva 2007.jpg
|office           = 19th [[President of Portugal]]&lt;br&gt;&lt;small&gt;6th since [[Carnation revolution]]&lt;/small&gt;
|primeminister    = [[José Sócrates]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Pedro Passos Coelho]]
|term_start       = 9 March 2006
|term_end         =
|predecessor      = [[Jorge Sampaio]]
|successor        =
|office2          = [[Prime Minister of Portugal]]
|president2       = [[António Ramalho Eanes]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Mário Soares]]
|term_start2      = 6 November 1985
|term_end2        = 28 October 1995
|predecessor2     = [[Mário Soares]]
|successor2       = [[António Guterres]]
|office3          = Minister of Finance
|primeminister3   = [[Francisco de Sá Carneiro]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Diogo de Freitas do Amaral]] &lt;small&gt;(Acting)&lt;/small&gt;
|term_start3      = 10 January 1980
|term_end3        = 12 January 1981
|predecessor3     = [[António Sousa Franco]]
|successor3       = [[João Morais Leitão]]
|office4          = Member of Parliament
|term_start4      = 13 November 1980
|term_end4        = 30 May 1983
|term_start5      = 4 November 1985
|term_end5        = 26 October 1995
|constituency5    = [[Lisbon district|Lisbon]]
|birth_date       = {{birth date and age|1939|7|15|df=y}}
|birth_place      = [[Boliqueime]], [[Estado Novo (Portugal)|Portugal]]
|death_date       =
|death_place      =
|party            = [[Social Democratic Party (Portugal)|Social Democratic Party]]
|spouse           = Maria Alves da Silva
|children         = Patrícia&lt;br /&gt;Bruno
|residence        = [[Belém Palace]]
|alma_mater       = [[Technical University of Lisbon]]&lt;br /&gt;[[University of York]]
|profession       = [[Economist]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Lecturer]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Financial adviser]]
|religion         = [[Catholic Church|Roman Catholicism]]
|signature        = Signature Aníbal Cavaco Silva-edit.svg
|website          = [http://www.presidenciarepublica.pt Official website]
}}
'''Aníbal António Cavaco Silva''', [[Order of Christ (Portugal)|GCC]] ({{IPA-pt|ɐˈniβɐɫ kɐˈvaku ˈsiɫvɐ}}; born 15 July 1939), is the President of [[Portugal]]. He won the [[Portuguese presidential election, 2006|Portuguese presidential election]] on 22 January 2006 and was [[Portuguese presidential election, 2011|re-elected]] on 23 January 2011, for a second five-year term. Cavaco Silva was sworn in on 9 March 2006.

He was previously [[List of Prime Ministers of Portugal|Prime Minister]] of [[Portugal]] from 6 November 1985 to 28 October 1995. His tenure of ten years was the longest of any Prime Minister since [[António de Oliveira Salazar|Salazar]], and he was the first Portuguese Prime Minister to have won an absolute parliamentary majority under the current constitutional system (which was established after the country's redemocratization following the [[Carnation Revolution]]).

==Early life and career==
He was born in [[Boliqueime]], [[Loulé]], [[Algarve]], the son of Teodoro Gonçalves Silva ([[Loulé]], [[Boliqueime]], Maritenda, 30 August 1912 - 30 September 2007) and wife (m. Loulé, Boliqueime, 4 March 1935) Maria do Nascimento Cavaco (b. [[Loulé]], [[Boliqueime]], Maritenda, 27 December 1912), Aníbal António Cavaco Silva was an undistinguished student at school. As a 13-year-old, he flunked at the 3rd grade of the Commercial School, and his grandfather put him working on the farm as a punishment.&lt;ref&gt;{{pt icon}} [http://diario.iol.pt/noticia.html?id=637824&amp;div_id=4071 Perfil de Cavaco Silva], [[iol.pt]]&lt;/ref&gt; After returning to school, Cavaco went on to become an accomplished student. Cavaco Silva then went to [[Lisbon]] enrolling at the ''Instituto Superior de Ciências Económicas e Financeiras de Lisboa (ISCEF)'' of the [[Technical University of Lisbon]] (UTL) (currently the ''Instituto Superior de Economia e Gestão (ISEG)'' of the Technical University of Lisbon), and obtained in 1963, with distinction, a degree in [[economics]] and [[finance]] (he scored a mark of 16 out of 20). While studying in Lisbon, Cavaco Silva was an athlete of [[Centro Desportivo Universitário de Lisboa|CDUL]] [[athletics (sport)|athletics]] department from 1958 to 1963.&lt;ref&gt;{{pt icon}} [http://www.record.xl.pt/interior.aspx?content_id=258860 Ás nas barreiras], [[Record (Portuguese newspaper)|Record]]&lt;/ref&gt; In 1964 he married Maria Alves da Silva, a lecturer in [[Germanic philology|Germanic]] [[philology]] at the [[University of Lisbon]], with whom he has two children (Bruno and Patrícia Maria), and took compulsory military service in the then Portuguese [[Overseas Province of Mozambique]], as an official of military administration in [[Maputo|Lourenço Marques]] (now the city of Maputo). His teaching career began in 1966 as assistant to ISCEF, but two years later Cavaco Silva went to the [[University of York]], in the [[United Kingdom]], where, in 1973, he was awarded a [[doctorate]] in [[economics]]. His thesis at York was a defense of (then popular) [[Keynesian economics]]&lt;ref&gt;[http://puraeconomia.blogspot.com/2004/11/o-esquizofrnico-livro-do-professor.html O esquizofrénico livro do Professor Cavaco Silva, Pura Economia]&lt;/ref&gt; (Neo-Keynesianism would influence his thought as Prime Minister later and he still self-identifies as a Neo-Keynesian). Returning to Portugal, he took up a post as assistant professor in ISCEF (1974), professor at the [[Catholic University of Portugal]] (1975), extraordinary professor at the [[New University of Lisbon]] (1979) and finally director of the Office of Studies of the [[Bank of Portugal]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://noticias.uol.com.br/ultnot/lusa/2006/01/22/ult611u70070.jhtm Cavaco Silva - Perfil], source [[Agência Lusa]]; website [[UOL]] (January 2006)&lt;/ref&gt;

He only became active in politics after the [[Carnation Revolution]] of 25 April 1974, later that year joining the then PPD, a political party headed by [[Francisco Sá Carneiro]]. Cavaco Silva, was appointed Minister of Finance by [[List of Prime Ministers of Portugal|Prime Minister]] Francisco Sá Carneiro in 1980. He gained a reputation as an economic liberal, gradually dismantling regulations inhibiting free enterprise. He refused to serve in the [[Center Bloc]] coalition of [[Socialist Party (Portugal)|Socialists]] and [[Social Democratic Party (Portugal)|Social Democrats]] (PSD) that governed from 1983 to 1985, and his election to the leadership of the PSD on 2 June 1985, portended the end of the coalition.

Professor Cavaco Silva has published several academic works in economics, including in subfields like [[monetary policy]] and [[monetary union]]s.

==Decade in power: 1985–1995==
The [[Portuguese legislative election, 1985|election that followed]] was complicated by the arrival of a new political party, the [[Democratic Renovator Party (Portugal)|Democratic Renovator Party]] (PRD) formed by the supporters of the [[List of Presidents of Portugal|President]], [[António Ramalho Eanes]]. In the 250-member [[Assembly of the Republic]], the nation's legislature, the PRD won 45 seats - at the expense of every party except Cavaco Silva's PSD.  Despite winning less than 30 percent of the vote and 88 seats, the PSD was the only traditional political party not to suffer substantial losses; its 88 seats, in fact, represented a gain of 13 over the previous election. Cavaco Silva became Prime Minister on 6 November 1985.

Tax cuts and economic deregulation and the arrival of EU funds spurred several years of uninterrupted economic growth, which increased Cavaco Silva's popularity. He was hampered, however, by heading a minority government. On most issues, his Social Democrats could rely on the 22 votes of the [[Democratic and Social Centre – People´s Party|Social and Democratic Center Party]] (CDS), but the two parties' combined 110 votes fell 16 short of a parliamentary majority.  The [[Socialist Party (Portugal)|Socialists]] and [[Portuguese Communist Party|Communists]] held 57 and 38 seats respectively; Cavaco Silva could govern if the 45 members of the PRD, who held the balance of power, abstained, as they frequently did. In 1987, however, the PRD withdrew its tacit support, and a parliamentary vote of no confidence forced President [[Mário Soares]] to call [[Portuguese legislative election, 1987|an early election]].

The results of the election stunned even the most optimistic of Cavaco Silva's supporters. His Social Democrat party captured 50.2 percent of the popular vote and 148 of the 250 seats in the Assembly of the Republic. Far behind were the Socialists, with only 60 seats, and the Communists, with 31. The CDS and the PRD were virtually wiped out, left with only 4 and 7 seats, respectively.  This was the first time since the 1974 revolution that a single party had won an outright majority in the national parliament.

The [[Portuguese legislative election, 1991|1991 election]] was another triumph for Cavaco Silva; it yielded a majority even larger (50.6 percent) than the one of four years earlier. However, the 1993 European economic crisis, sparking a high unemployment rate, and the country's mistrust of [[Cavaco Silva's Cabinets (1985-95)|long-spanning governments]], eroded his popularity. He decided not to contest the [[Portuguese legislative election, 1995|1995 election]], and the PSD, lacking a leader of his stature, lost 48 seats and the election.

==Out of office: 1995–2006==
Cavaco Silva contested the 1996 [[Portuguese presidential election, 1996|presidential election]], but was defeated by the Mayor of [[Lisbon]], [[Jorge Sampaio]], the Socialist candidate. Retiring from politics, he served for several years as an advisor to the board of the [[Banco de Portugal]] (Bank of Portugal), but retired from this position in 2004. He then became a full professor at the School of Economics and Management of the [[Catholic University of Portugal]], where he taught the undergraduate and MBA programs.

He declined to support [[Pedro Santana Lopes]], whom he branded as a mediocre politician, in the [[Portuguese legislative election, 2005|2005 parliamentary election]], despite pressure from within his party.

He is a member of the [[Club of Madrid]]&lt;ref&gt;{{en}}[http://www.clubmadrid.org The Club of Madrid is an independent organization dedicated to strengthening democracy around the world by drawing on the unique experience and resources of its Members – 66 democratic former heads of state and government]&lt;/ref&gt; and an honorary member of [http://www.raoulwallenberg.net The International Raoul Wallenberg Foundation].

==Presidential candidacy and term==
[[File:Cavaco Silva and Barack Obama.JPG|thumb|300px|left|Cavaco Silva escorts US President Barack Obama from Belem National Palace after meeting, Nov 19, 2010]]
On 20 October 2005, Cavaco Silva announced his candidacy in the election, 2006.He was elected president on 22 January 2006 with 50.6% of votes cast, avoiding a run-off. He is the first elected [[centre-right]] president in Portugal since 1974.  He is also the second former Prime Minister to be elected president, following in the footsteps of [[Mário Soares]].

He was sworn-in on 9 March 2006. He is also the Head of the [[Portuguese Council of State]].

Cavaco Silva's term was initially marked by a mutual understanding with the government led by Socialist [[José Sócrates]], which he referred to as &quot;strategic co-operation&quot;. He also avidly encouraged the suppression of partisan differences between the political parties in parliament, as a means of working towards the greater national good, despite the absolute majority held by the Socialist Party. This has led to several controversies, with some branding Cavaco Silva, a practising Roman Catholic and a self-described believer in [[Fátima]] [[Fátima#Marian apparitions|apparitions]], as a traitor to the center-right and to some of his own personal beliefs. Nevertheless, this seems to have been a misconception with respect to his presidency. He has, in effect, resorted to his veto power more than Mário Soares, who as a President was largely seen as too conflicting with the Government, in the latter's first term.

The most controversial moment of his presidency was when the Assembly of the Republic passed a bill for the holding of a pre-legislative referendum on the legalization of abortion in Portugal without any restrictions in the 10 first weeks of pregnancy. After the parliamentary approval of the bill summoning the referendum, Cavaco Silva referred the matter to the Portuguese Constitutional Court, which declared both the proposed legalization and the referendum constitutional by a narrow 7-6 margin. Cavaco Silva, who could still have vetoed the referendum bill, decided to sign it into law despite pressure from some pro-life sectors, and thus allowed the referendum. The majority of the Portuguese electorate abstained from the referendum, but the vote for legalization prevailed among those who chose to cast their ballot.

==Family==
He married at the Church of the [[Monastery of São Vicente de Fora]], São Vicente de Fora, Lisbon, on 20 October 1964 Maria Alves da Silva (b. [[Silves Municipality, Portugal|Silves]], [[São Bartolomeu de Messines]], 31 October 1938), daughter of Francisco dos Santos Silva and wife Adelina de Jesus Pincho, with whom he has had two children:&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.geneall.net/P/per_page.php?id=277263 Aníbal António Cavaco Silva], GeneAll.net&lt;/ref&gt;
* Bruno Alves Cavaco Silva, married to Perpétua da Conceição Gomes Anacleto, and has one son:
** João Vicente Anacleto Cavaco Silva (b. Lisbon, 13 January 2009)
* Patrícia Maria Alves Cavaco Silva, married to Luís Manuel de Sá Montez, and has four children:
** Mariana Cavaco Silva de Sá Montez (b. 1996)
** Afonso Cavaco Silva de Sá Montez (b. 1998)
** António Luís Cavaco Silva de Sá Montez (b. 2001)
** João Maria Cavaco Silva de Sá Montez (b. 2004)

==State visits==
{{See also|List of state visits made by President Cavaco Silva of Portugal}}

[[File:CavacoSilva Presidential Trips.PNG|thumb|right|Foreign trips of Cavaco Silva.]]

==={{flag|Spain}} (25 September to 28 September 2006)===
President Cavaco Silva was invited to visit [[Spain]] by [[Juan Carlos of Spain|King Juan Carlos]] in March, through [[Felipe, Prince of Asturias|Prince Felipe]]. His visit was overshadowed by the announcement of [[Letizia, Princess of Asturias|Princess Letizia]]'s pregnancy.

==={{flag|India}} (11 January to 17 January 2007)===
During this visit, President Cavaco Silva received an honorary degree by the [[Goa University]] on 14 January.

==={{flag|United States}} (19 June, 23 June 2007)===
During this visit, President Cavaco Silva plans to open an exhibition concerning Portugal's role in the discovery and convergence of diverse cultures, and to contact some Portuguese communities on the [[East Coast of the United States|North American Eastern Seaboard]], including the city of [[Fall River, Massachusetts]] whose Portuguese-descended population (43.9 percent at the 2000 [[census]]) is the highest of any municipality in the United States. Fall River features a replica of &quot;The Gates of the City of Ponta Delgada&quot; or &quot;Portas da Cidade&quot; in [[Portuguese language|Portuguese]].

==Personal quotes==
* Àqueles que querem atrasar o desenvolvimento do país, àqueles que nada fizeram no passado, quando tiveram a oportunidade de fazer pelo desenvolvimento do país, digo apenas: deixem-nos trabalhar, deixem-nos trabalhar! (''To those who want to delay the development of the country, to those who nothing did in the past, when they had the opportunity of doing for the development of the country, I say only: let us work, let us work!'') (in a public speech)
* ''Quando eu faço uma decisão, eu nunca me engano, e raramente tenho dúvidas.'' (''When I make a decision, I never am wrong, and I seldom have doubts.'') (in an interview to ''[[Expresso (Portuguese newspaper)|Expresso]]'')
* ''It's wait for them to die.'' (concerning the excess of civil servants)
* ''Duas pessoas em boa fé com a mesma informação técnica obrigatoriamente devem concordar.'' (''Two people in good faith with the same technical information obligatorily must agree.'')

==Electoral results==
===1996 Portuguese presidential election===
{{Election table|Portuguese presidential election, 1996}}'''Summary of the 14 January 1996 [[Portugal|Portuguese]] [[President of Portugal|presidential]] [[Elections in Portugal|election results]]
|-
!  style=&quot;background:#e9e9e9; text-align:left;&quot; colspan=&quot;2&quot; rowspan=&quot;2&quot;|Candidates
!  style=&quot;background:#e9e9e9; text-align:left;&quot; rowspan=&quot;2&quot;|Supporting parties
!  style=&quot;background:#e9e9e9; text-align:right;&quot; colspan=&quot;2&quot;|First round
|-
!  style=&quot;background:#e9e9e9; text-align:right;&quot;|Votes
!  style=&quot;background:#e9e9e9; text-align:right;&quot;|%
|-
|  style=&quot;background:#f6f; width:9px; text-align:center;&quot;|
|align=left|[[Jorge Sampaio]]
|align=left|[[Socialist Party (Portugal)|Socialist Party]]
| style=&quot;text-align:right;&quot;|3,035,056
| style=&quot;text-align:right;&quot;|53.91
|-
|  style=&quot;background:#f90; width:9px; text-align:center;&quot;|
|align=left|Aníbal Cavaco Silva
|align=left|[[Social Democratic Party (Portugal)|Social Democratic Party]], [[People's Party (Portugal)|People's Party]]
| style=&quot;text-align:right;&quot;|2,595,131
| style=&quot;text-align:right;&quot;|46.09
|-
|  style=&quot;background:red; width:9px; text-align:center;&quot;|
|align=left|[[Jerónimo de Sousa]]
|align=left|[[Portuguese Communist Party]], [[Ecologist Party &quot;The Greens&quot;]]
| colspan=&quot;2&quot; style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;|''left the race''
|-
|  style=&quot;background:#e2062c; width:9px; text-align:center;&quot;|
|align=left|[[Alberto Matos]]
|align=left|[[People's Democratic Union (Portugal)|People's Democratic Union]]
| colspan=&quot;2&quot; style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;|''left the race''
|- style=&quot;background:#e9e9e9;&quot;
| colspan=&quot;3&quot;  style=&quot;text-align:left; &quot;|'''Total valid'''
|  style=&quot;text-align:right; width:65px; &quot;|'''5,630,187'''
|  style=&quot;text-align:right; width:40px; &quot;|'''100.00'''
|- style=&quot;text-align:right;&quot;
| colspan=&quot;3&quot;|Blank ballots
|  style=&quot;width:65px; &quot;|69,328
|  style=&quot;width:40px; &quot;|1.20
|- style=&quot;text-align:right;&quot;
| colspan=&quot;3&quot;|Invalid ballots
|  style=&quot;width:65px; &quot;|63,463
|  style=&quot;width:40px; &quot;|1.10
|- style=&quot;background:#e9e9e9;&quot;
| colspan=&quot;3&quot;  style=&quot;text-align:left; &quot;|'''Total''' (turnout 66.29%)
|  style=&quot;text-align:right; width:65px; &quot;|'''5,762,978 '''
|  style=&quot;text-align:right; width:40px; &quot;|
|-
| colspan=&quot;5&quot; style=&quot;text-align:left;&quot;|Source: [http://eleicoes.cne.pt/cne2005/sel_eleicoes.cfm?m=raster#assemb Comissão Nacional de Eleições]
|}

===2006 Portuguese presidential election===
{{Election table|Portuguese presidential election, 2006}}'''Summary of the 22 January 2006 [[Portugal|Portuguese]] [[President of Portugal|presidential]] [[Elections in Portugal|election results]]
|-
!  style=&quot;background:#e9e9e9; text-align:left;&quot; colspan=&quot;2&quot; rowspan=&quot;2&quot;|Candidates
!  style=&quot;background:#e9e9e9; text-align:left;&quot; rowspan=&quot;2&quot;|Supporting parties
!  style=&quot;background:#e9e9e9; text-align:right;&quot; colspan=&quot;2&quot;|First round
|-
!  style=&quot;background:#e9e9e9; text-align:right;&quot;|Votes
!  style=&quot;background:#e9e9e9; text-align:right;&quot;|%
|-
|  style=&quot;background:#f90; width:9px; text-align:center;&quot;|
|align=left|Aníbal Cavaco Silva
|align=left|[[Social Democratic Party (Portugal)|Social Democratic Party]], [[People's Party (Portugal)|People's Party]]
| style=&quot;text-align:right;&quot;|2,773,431
| style=&quot;text-align:right;&quot;|50.54
|-
|  style=&quot;background:gray; width:8px; text-align:center;&quot;|
|align=left|[[Manuel Alegre]]
|align=left|[[Independent (politician)|Independent]]
| style=&quot;text-align:right;&quot;|1,138,297
| style=&quot;text-align:right;&quot;|20.74
|-
|  style=&quot;background:#f6f; width:8px; text-align:center;&quot;|
|align=left|[[Mário Soares]]
|align=left|[[Socialist Party (Portugal)|Socialist Party]]
| style=&quot;text-align:right;&quot;|785,355
| style=&quot;text-align:right;&quot;|14.31
|-
|  style=&quot;background:red; width:8px; text-align:center;&quot;|
|align=left|[[Jerónimo de Sousa]]
|align=left|[[Portuguese Communist Party]], [[Ecologist Party &quot;The Greens&quot;]]
| style=&quot;text-align:right;&quot;|474,083
| style=&quot;text-align:right;&quot;|8.64
|-
|  style=&quot;background:darkRed; width:8px; text-align:center;&quot;|
|align=left|[[Francisco Louçã]]
|align=left|[[Left Bloc]]
| style=&quot;text-align:right;&quot;|292,198
| style=&quot;text-align:right;&quot;|5.32
|-
|  style=&quot;background:#c00; width:8px; text-align:center;&quot;|
|align=left|[[António Garcia Pereira]]
|align=left|[[PCTP/MRPP]]
| style=&quot;text-align:right;&quot;|23,983
| style=&quot;text-align:right;&quot;|0.44
|- style=&quot;background:#e9e9e9;&quot;
| colspan=&quot;3&quot;  style=&quot;text-align:left; &quot;|'''Total valid'''
|  style=&quot;text-align:right; width:65px; &quot;|'''5,487,347'''
|  style=&quot;text-align:right; width:40px; &quot;|'''100.00'''
|- style=&quot;text-align:right;&quot;
| colspan=&quot;3&quot;|Blank ballots
|  style=&quot;width:65px; &quot;|59,636
|  style=&quot;width:40px; &quot;|1.07
|- style=&quot;text-align:right;&quot;
| colspan=&quot;3&quot;|Invalid ballots
|  style=&quot;width:65px; &quot;|43,149
|  style=&quot;width:40px; &quot;|0.77
|- style=&quot;background:#e9e9e9;&quot;
| colspan=&quot;3&quot;  style=&quot;text-align:left; &quot;|'''Total''' (turnout 61.53%)
|  style=&quot;text-align:right; width:65px; &quot;|'''5,590,132 '''
|  style=&quot;text-align:right; width:40px; &quot;|
|-
| colspan=&quot;5&quot; style=&quot;text-align:left;&quot;|Source: [http://eleicoes.cne.pt/vector/index.cfm?dia=22&amp;mes=01&amp;ano=2006&amp;eleicao=pr Comissão Nacional de Eleições]
|}

===2011 Portuguese presidential election===
{{Election table|Portuguese presidential election, 2011}}'''Summary of the 23 January 2011 [[Portugal|Portuguese]] [[President of Portugal|presidential]] [[Elections in Portugal|election results]]
|-
!  style=&quot;background:#e9e9e9; text-align:left;&quot; colspan=&quot;2&quot; rowspan=&quot;2&quot;|Candidates
!  style=&quot;background:#e9e9e9; text-align:left;&quot; rowspan=&quot;2&quot;|Supporting parties
!  style=&quot;background:#e9e9e9; text-align:right;&quot; colspan=&quot;2&quot;|First round
|-
!  style=&quot;background:#e9e9e9; text-align:right;&quot;|Votes
!  style=&quot;background:#e9e9e9; text-align:right;&quot;|%
|-
|  style=&quot;background:#f90; width:9px; text-align:center;&quot;|
|align=left|Aníbal Cavaco Silva
|align=left|[[Social Democratic Party (Portugal)|Social Democratic Party]], [[People's Party (Portugal)|People's Party]], [[Hope for Portugal Movement]]
| style=&quot;text-align:right;&quot;|2,231,956
| style=&quot;text-align:right;&quot;|52.95
|-
|  style=&quot;background:#f6f; width:8px; text-align:center;&quot;|
|align=left|[[Manuel Alegre]]
|align=left|[[Socialist Party (Portugal)|Socialist Party]], [[Left Bloc]], [[Democratic Party of the Atlantic]], [[Portuguese Workers' Communist Party|PCTP/MRPP]]
| style=&quot;text-align:right;&quot;|831,838
| style=&quot;text-align:right;&quot;|19.74
|-
|  style=&quot;background:gray; width:8px; text-align:center;&quot;|
|align=left|[[Fernando Nobre]]
|align=left|[[Independent (politician)|Independent]]
| style=&quot;text-align:right;&quot;|593,021
| style=&quot;text-align:right;&quot;|14.07
|-
|  style=&quot;background:red; width:8px; text-align:center;&quot;|
|align=left|[[Francisco Lopes]]
|align=left|[[Portuguese Communist Party]], [[Ecologist Party &quot;The Greens&quot;]]
| style=&quot;text-align:right;&quot;|301,017
| style=&quot;text-align:right;&quot;|7.14
|-
|  style=&quot;background:#1f468b; width:8px; text-align:center;&quot;|
|align=left|[[José Manuel Coelho]]
|align=left|[[New Democracy Party (Portugal)|New Democracy Party]]
| style=&quot;text-align:right;&quot;|189,918
| style=&quot;text-align:right;&quot;|4.51
|-
|  style=&quot;background:gray; width:8px; text-align:center;&quot;|
|align=left|[[Defensor Moura]]
|align=left|[[Independent (politician)|Independent]]
| style=&quot;text-align:right;&quot;|67,110
| style=&quot;text-align:right;&quot;|1.59
|- style=&quot;background:#e9e9e9;&quot;
| colspan=&quot;3&quot;  style=&quot;text-align:left; &quot;|'''Total valid'''
|  style=&quot;text-align:right; width:65px; &quot;|'''4,214,860'''
|  style=&quot;text-align:right; width:40px; &quot;|'''100.00'''
|- style=&quot;text-align:right;&quot;
| colspan=&quot;3&quot;|Blank ballots
|  style=&quot;width:65px; &quot;|192,127
|  style=&quot;width:40px; &quot;|4.28
|- style=&quot;text-align:right;&quot;
| colspan=&quot;3&quot;|Invalid ballots
|  style=&quot;width:65px; &quot;|85,466
|  style=&quot;width:40px; &quot;|1.90
|- style=&quot;background:#e9e9e9;&quot;
| colspan=&quot;3&quot;  style=&quot;text-align:left; &quot;|'''Total''' (turnout 46.52%)
|  style=&quot;text-align:right; width:65px; &quot;|'''4,492,453 '''
|  style=&quot;text-align:right; width:40px; &quot;|
|-
| colspan=&quot;5&quot; style=&quot;text-align:left;&quot;|Source: [http://eleicoes.cne.pt/vector/detalhe.cfm?eleicao=pr&amp;dia=23&amp;mes=01&amp;ano=2011&amp;codreg=0&amp;local=0 Comissão Nacional de Eleições]
|}
{{Clear}}

==Bibliography==
* ''Cavaco Silva, Autobiografia Política'', in 2 Vols.

==References==
{{reflist}}

{{s-start}}
{{s-par}}
{{s-bef|rows=2|before=Title jointly held}}
{{s-ttl|title=Member of Parliament for [[Lisbon district|Lisbon]]|years=1980–1983}}
{{s-aft|rows=2|after=Title jointly held}}
|-
{{s-ttl|title=Member of Parliament for [[Lisbon district|Lisbon]]|years=1985–1995}}
|-
{{s-ppo}}
{{s-bef|before=[[Carlos Mota Pinto]]}}
{{s-ttl|title=President [[Social Democratic Party (Portugal)|Social Democratic Party]]|years=1985–1995}}
{{s-aft|after=[[Fernando Nogueira]]}}
|-
{{s-off}}
{{s-bef|before=[[Ruud Lubbers]]}}
{{s-ttl|title=[[President of the European Council]]|years=1992}}
{{s-aft|after=[[John Major]]}}
|-
{{s-bef|before=[[Mário Soares]]}}
{{s-ttl|title=[[Prime Minister of Portugal]]|years=1985–1995}}
{{s-aft|after=[[António Guterres]]}}
|-
{{s-bef|before=[[Jorge Sampaio]]}}
{{s-ttl|title=[[President of Portugal]]|years=2006–present}}
{{s-inc}}
{{s-end}}

{{Presidents of Portugal}}
{{Prime Ministers of Portugal}}
{{Presidents of the European Council}}
{{Heads of state of the European Union Member states}}


{{Persondata &lt;!-- Metadata: see [[Wikipedia:Persondata]]. --&gt; 
|NAME=Cavaco Silva, Aníbal
|ALTERNATIVE NAMES=Cavaco Silva, Aníbal António (full name)
|SHORT DESCRIPTION=[[President of Portugal]]
|DATE OF BIRTH=15 July 1939
|PLACE OF BIRTH=[[Boliqueime]], [[Loulé]], [[Algarve]], [[Portugal]]
|DATE OF DEATH=
|PLACE OF DEATH=
}}
{{DEFAULTSORT:Cavaco Silva, Anibal}}
[[Category:1939 births]]
[[Category:Alumni of the University of York]]
[[Category:Current national leaders]]
[[Category:Knights Grand Cross of the Order of St. Olav]]
[[[Category:Grand Crosses of the Order of Christ (Portugal)‎]]
[[Category:Living people]]
[[Category:Members of the Assembly of the Republic (Portugal)]]
[[Category:People from Faro District]]
[[Category:Portuguese economists]]
[[Category:Portuguese Roman Catholics]]
[[Category:Presidents of Portugal]]
[[Category:Prime Ministers of Portugal]]
[[Category:Recipients of the Collar of the Order of the Cross of Terra Mariana]]
[[Category:Social Democratic Party (Portugal) politicians]]
[[Category:Technical University of Lisbon alumni]]

[[ar:انيبال كافاكو سيلفا]]
[[an:Aníbal Cavaco Silva]]
[[be:Анібал Каваку Сілва]]
[[bg:Анибал Каваку Силва]]
[[br:Aníbal Cavaco Silva]]
[[ca:Aníbal Cavaco Silva]]
[[cs:Aníbal Cavaco Silva]]
[[da:Aníbal Cavaco Silva]]
[[de:Aníbal Cavaco Silva]]
[[et:Aníbal Cavaco Silva]]
[[el:Ανίμπαλ Καβάκο Σίλβα]]
[[es:Aníbal Cavaco Silva]]
[[eo:Aníbal Cavaco Silva]]
[[fr:Aníbal Cavaco Silva]]
[[gl:Aníbal Cavaco Silva]]
[[ko:아니발 카바쿠 실바]]
[[io:Aníbal Cavaco Silva]]
[[id:Aníbal Cavaco Silva]]
[[is:Cavaco Silva]]
[[it:Aníbal Cavaco Silva]]
[[he:אניבל קבאקו סילבה]]
[[ka:ანიბალ კავაკუ სილვა]]
[[la:Hannibal Cavaco Silva]]
[[lb:Aníbal Cavaco Silva]]
[[my:ကဗာကို၊ စီလဗာ၊ အန်နီဗယ်]]
[[nl:Aníbal Cavaco Silva]]
[[ja:アニーバル・カヴァコ・シルヴァ]]
[[no:Aníbal Cavaco Silva]]
[[nn:Aníbal Cavaco Silva]]
[[oc:Aníbal Cavaco Silva]]
[[pl:Aníbal Cavaco Silva]]
[[pt:Aníbal Cavaco Silva]]
[[ty:Aníbal Cavaco Silva]]
[[ro:Aníbal Cavaco Silva]]
[[rm:Aníbal Cavaco Silva]]
[[ru:Каваку Силва, Анибал]]
[[sl:Aníbal Cavaco Silva]]
[[sr:Анибал Кавахо Силва]]
[[fi:Aníbal Cavaco Silva]]
[[sv:Aníbal Cavaco Silva]]
[[tr:Aníbal Cavaco Silva]]
[[uk:Анібал Каваку Сілва]]
[[vi:Aníbal Cavaco Silva]]
[[vo:Aníbal Cavaco Silva]]
[[war:Aníbal Cavaco Silva]]
[[yo:Aníbal Cavaco Silva]]
[[zh:阿尼巴尔·卡瓦科·席尔瓦]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
