<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="19597351" ns="0" title="Wilson the Wonder Athlete"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Infobox comics character &lt;!--Wikipedia:WikiProject Comics--&gt;
| character_name = William Wilson
| image          =  
| imagesize      = &lt;!-- default 250 --&gt;
| caption        = Wilson paperback.
| publisher      = [[D. C. Thomson &amp; Co.]]
| debut          = ''[[The Wizard (comic)|The Wizard]]'' #1029 (24 July 1943)
| creators       = [[Gilbert Lawford Dalton]]
| alter_ego      = Wilson the Wonder Athlete
| full_name      = 
| species        = &lt;!-- optional --&gt;
| homeworld      = &lt;!-- optional --&gt;
| alliances      = &lt;!-- optional --&gt;
| partners       = &lt;!-- optional --&gt;
| supports       = &lt;!-- optional --&gt;
| aliases        = &lt;!-- optional --&gt;
| powers         = 
| cat            = 
| subcat         = DC Thomson Comics
| hero           = 
| villain        = 
| sortkey        = Wilson the Wonder Athlete
}}
'''Wilson the Wonder Athlete''' or '''William Wilson''' is a fictional character whose adventures were initially published in the British illustrated story paper ''[[The Wizard (comic)|The Wizard]]'' published by [[D. C. Thomson &amp; Co.]]

==Publication history==
The character first appeared in issue 1029 ''Wizard'' (24 July 1943) in a story titled &quot;The Truth About Wilson&quot;. The first adventure introduced Wilson as a supreme athlete, who joins a race from out of the crowd and manages to record a [[three-minute mile]].&lt;ref name=&quot;GBC&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;LWLO&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Benny Green recalled in ''[[The Spectator]]'' on 26 December 1970, [http://books.google.com/books?id=A20HAQAAIAAJ&amp;q=%22In+one+episode+he+takes+a+giant+leap+and+breaks+the+world+long+jump+record+while+in+the+act+of+running+a+three-minute+mile%22&amp;dq=%22In+one+episode+he+takes+a+giant+leap+and+breaks+the+world+long+jump+record+while+in+the+act+of+running+a+three-minute+mile%22&amp;hl=en&amp;ei=rE1HTLTKNc_9nQfcl5W8BA&amp;sa=X&amp;oi=book_result&amp;ct=result&amp;resnum=1&amp;ved=0CCUQ6AEwAA p. 840] that Wilson's exploits were so extraordinary, they inspired a game of topping each other with increasingly absurd 'Wilsonisms': &quot;In one episode he takes a giant leap and breaks the world long jump record while in the act of running a three-minute mile...His most tangible legacy is a parlour game still played occasionally by grown men of my own vintage who ought to know better. The game is called 'Wilsonisms' and its aim is to arrive at the ultimate absurdity in physical achievement.

1st player: Wilson climbed Mount Everest.
2nd player: At night.
3rd player: Barefoot.
4th player: Without oxygen.
1st player: With a twelve-stone man on his back.
2nd player: In fifteen minutes.
3rd player: Backwards.
4th player: With a tray of drinks in each hand.&quot; - quoted on [http://www.reocities.com/jjnevins/pulpsw.html Jess Nevins' Pulp and Adventure Heroes site], now on Reocities.&lt;/ref&gt; The character's adventures were written by [[Gilbert Lawford Dalton]] using the pen name W S K Webb, and a book, ''The Truth About Wilson'' collected a number of the text stories in the 1960s.&lt;ref name=&quot;LWLO&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;FB&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://bishsbeat.blogspot.com/2008/08/forgotten-books-truth-about-wilson.html|title=Forgotten Books: The Truth About Wilson!|last=Bishop|first=Paul|date=August 15, 2008|publisher=Self published|accessdate=2008-10-03}} [http://www.webcitation.org/5bIpeq2KD Archived] on 2008-10-03.&lt;/ref&gt;  Thought by [[Paul Gravett]] to be the prototype of the &quot;astonishing sporting prodigies&quot; who became popular in British comics, (cf. [[Alf Tupper]], [[Roy of the Rovers]]), Gravett describes him as an &quot;unassuming totally dedicated loner, [wanting] no glory or publicity&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;GBC&quot;&gt;{{cite book|last=Gravett|first=Paul|coauthors=Peter Stanbury|title=Great British Comics|publisher=Aurum|year=2006|isbn=1845131703}}&lt;/ref&gt;  Although his stories were initially told in prose, a move to the comic papers ''[[Hornet (comic)|The Hornet]]'' and  ''[[Hotspur (comic)|Hotspur]]'' saw the character depicted in comic strip form.&lt;ref name=&quot;GBC&quot; /&gt;  The character was later revived for D.C. Thomson's ''[[Spike (comic)|Spike]]'' comic of 1984 to 1985, initially within a comic strip with art by Neville Wilson.  Referred to as '''The Man in Black''', the character was revealed to be Wilson in the course of the story, with reprints of the older material published within the comic as Wilson's diaries.&lt;ref name=&quot;FB&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref&gt;''Spike'', DC Thomson, (weekly) 22nd January 1983 to 28th April 1984&lt;/ref&gt;

==Fictional character biography==
William Wilson was born in the village of Stayling in Yorkshire and claimed to be born on 1 November 1795. However a document dated 11 March 1774 listed him as &quot;clerk to the manor&quot;. He was sufficiently old that when writing, he used an &quot;f&quot; instead of an &quot;s&quot;. His farmer father died in middle age, leaving Wilson £5,000. He studied medicine and biology in a number of countries around the world and determined not to die early as so many he knew had, he worked out a health and fitness regime and learned how to slow his heart right down, using a formula created by people who could live to over 200. He developed his will power and hardened his body by whole winters spent in the open. Squadron leader W. Wilson D.S.O., D.F.C. and bar, who had 25 victories to his name, was shot down during the Second World War and was officially listed as missing. 

The character is depicted within stories as performing a number of improbable events. Wilson was seen in one strip becoming the first man to climb [[Everest]], and another saw him captaining an England [[cricket]] team to [[The Ashes]] in Australia.&lt;ref name=&quot;WWCS&quot;&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.telegraph.co.uk/sport/othersports/2353289/Wizard-Wilson-still-casts-spell.html|title=Wizard Wilson still casts spell|last=Gallagher|first=Brendan|date=5 January 2005|publisher=The Telegraph|accessdate=2008-10-03}} [http://www.webcitation.org/5bInSk0id Archived] 2008-10-03.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;JS&quot;&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.telegraph.co.uk/sport/othersports/2393471/Just-spiffing!.html|title=Just spiffing!|last=Gallagher|first=Brendan|date=27 December 2004|publisher=The Telegraph|accessdate=2008-10-03}}[http://www.webcitation.org/5bIo0VfPh Archived] 2008-10-03.&lt;/ref&gt; Depicted as being born in 1795, he is given the secret of eternal life by a hermit.&lt;ref name=&quot;GBC&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;BRCS&quot;&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.independent.co.uk/sport/general/the-blaydon-racers-shun-chemistry-set-725851.html|title=The Blaydon Racers Shun Chemistry Set|last=Turnbull|first=Simon|date=20 February 2000|publisher=The Independent|accessdate=2008-10-03}} [http://www.webcitation.org/5bIqdiqBI Archived] on 2008-10-03.&lt;/ref&gt; Originally hailing from Yorkshire, and living in a cave on a diet of nuts and berries, Wilson exemplified British grit and the stiff upper lip.&lt;ref name=&quot;GBC&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;LWLO&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;JS&quot; /&gt;  According to ''[[The Guardian]]'' he &quot;was hailed as a welcome wartime morale booster&quot;, while ''[[The Daily Telegraph|The Telegraph]]'' remembers him as a &quot;focused and intense individual&amp;nbsp;... [with no] recorded instance of him smiling or cracking a joke.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;JS&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;CHAW&quot;&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.guardian.co.uk/uk/2004/sep/12/arts.artsnews|title=Crumbs! Comic heroes storm art world|last=Thorpe|first=Vanessa|date=September 12, 2004|publisher=The Guardian|accessdate=2008-10-03}} [http://www.webcitation.org/5bIn826n6 Archived] 2008-10-03.&lt;/ref&gt; In 2004 artist John Reynolds acquired the licence to reproduce images of Wilson as large [[screen printing|screen-print]] canvases.&lt;ref name=&quot;CHAW&quot; /&gt; Former ''Guinness Book of Records'' deputy editor and athletics statistician, Ian Smith, cites the character as an inspiration, and he inspired many British athletes in their careers as well as Belgian cyclist [[Eddy Merckx]].&lt;ref name=&quot;GBC&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;LWLO&quot;&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.telegraph.co.uk/sport/othersports/athletics/2394961/Philip-on-Saturday-Legend-of-Wizard%27s-Wilson-lives-on.html|title=Philip on Saturday: Legend of Wizard's Wilson lives on|date=24 January 2003|publisher=The Telegraph|accessdate=2008-10-03}} [http://www.webcitation.org/5bIpJ1gOO Archived] 2008-10-03.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Bryant, John. &quot;Phenomenal pen that rewrote the record books&quot;, ''The Times'' (London), Jan 14 1999, p. 44.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;
Turnbull, Simon. &quot;Leftfield: Cortisone in the act of doing a bit of bird&quot;, ''The Independent on Sunday'' (London), Feb 27 2000, p. 18.&lt;/ref&gt; The character is still used in newspaper reports on sport as a cultural reference point.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.guardian.co.uk/sport/2007/mar/15/sixnations2007.sixnations2|title=Geraghty has the x factor England need|last=Kitson|first=Robert|date=March 15, 2007|publisher=The Guardian|accessdate=2008-10-03}} &quot;As eye-catching debuts go, Geraghty's extravagant bow against France made even Wilson of the Wizard look pedestrian.&quot; [http://www.webcitation.org/5bIqw0xaM Archived] on 2008-10-03.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.independent.co.uk/sport/cricket/selectors-fail-their-first-big-test-with-peculiar-pick-of-pattinson-872330.html|title=
Selectors fail their first big test with peculiar pick of Pattinson|last=Brenkley|first=Stephen|date=20 July 2008|publisher=The Independent|accessdate=2008-10-03}} &quot;Only if Geoff Miller, the chairman of selectors, and his panel had summoned some recluse from a solitary eyrie on the Yorkshire moors where he had spent years honing his action so one day he could come to England's rescue at the 11th hour (Wilson of the Wizard, say) could they have sprung a greater surprise.&quot; [http://www.webcitation.org/5bIr3weU9 Archived] on 2008-10-03.&lt;/ref&gt;

==References==
{{Reflist|2}}

==Further reading==
*Gallagher, Brendan. ''Sporting Supermen: Wilson of the Wizard, &quot;Tough of the Track&quot; and Roy of the Rovers: The Life and Times of the Comic-Book Heroes'' ISBN 1845131657

==External links==
* [http://www.26pigs.com/wizard/index.html Fan site with reader memories of the strip and comic]

{{D. C. Thomson Comics}}

[[Category:Fictional track and field athletes]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
