<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="19600202" ns="0" title="List of Hannah Montana main characters"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">[[File:Hannah Montana cast 2.JPG|right|thumb|Promotional photo of the ''Hannah Montana'' main characters from season one to three. From Left to right are [[#Rico Suave|Rico Suave]] (Moises Arias), [[#Jackson Stewart|Jackson Stewart]] (Jason Earles), [[Robby Stewart]] (Billy Ray Cyrus), [[Miley Stewart|Miley Stewart as Hannah Montana]] (Miley Cyrus), [[#Oliver Oken|Oliver Oken]] (Mitchell Musso) and [[#Lilly Truscott|Lilly Truscott]] (Emily Osment)]]

This '''list of ''Hannah Montana'' main characters''' includes [[Character (arts)|fictional characters]] from the [[Disney Channel]] series ''[[Hannah Montana]]''  portrayed by the main cast. Characters are listed by order of appearance.

==Miley Stewart==
{{main|Miley Stewart}}
'''Miley Ray Stewart''' ([[Miley Cyrus]]) is the  teen [[Protagonist|main character]] of ''Hannah Montana''. As her alter ego, '''Hannah Montana''', she secretly lives a double life as a famous [[Celebrity|pop star]]. Her best friends are Lilly and Oliver. She tries to keep the fact that she is Hannah Montana a secret but has told several people during the duration of the series, such as Lilly, Oliver, Siena, Jake, and Jesse. She is known to say &quot;Sweet niblets!&quot; &quot; ya think&quot; and &quot;Say what?&quot; as her catch phrases. She finally reveals to the world that she is Hannah Montana in the episode ''[[I'll Always Remember You]]''.

==Robby Stewart==
{{main|Robby Stewart}}
'''Robby Ray Stewart''' ([[Billy Ray Cyrus]]) is the single father of Jackson and Miley Stewart. He is also Hannah's manager, producer, and songwriter.
His catchphrases are &quot;Sweet niblets&quot; and &quot;Wee-doggies&quot;.

==Jackson Stewart==
{{Infobox character
| name             = Jackson Stewart
| series           = Hannah Montana
| image            = 
| caption          = 
| first            = ''&quot;[[Lilly, Do You Want to Know a Secret?]]&quot;''
| last             = ''&quot;[[Wherever I Go]]&quot;''
| cause            = 
| creator          = [[Michael Poryes]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Richard Correll]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Barry O'Brien]]
| portrayer        = [[Jason Earles]]&lt;br /&gt;Ryan Adkisson (young)&lt;ref&gt;&quot;I Am Hannah, Hear Me Croak&quot;&lt;/ref&gt;
| nickname         = 
| gender           = Male
| occupation       = Student (10th grader in Season 1) (11th grader in Season 2) (12th grader in early Season 3)                   (College student in Season 4) Attendant at Rico's Surf Shop
                     Video game tester.
| title            = 
| family           = [[Robby Stewart]] (father)&lt;br /&gt;[[List_of_Hannah_Montana_characters#Susan_Stewart|Susan Stewart]] (mother)&lt;br /&gt;[[Miley Stewart]] (sister)
| significantother = [[List of Hannah Montana characters#Siena|Siena]] (girlfriend)
| relatives        = 
| religion         = &lt;!-- never mentioned in show --&gt;
| nationality      = 

}}
'''Jackson Rod Stewart''' ([[Jason Earles]]) is the older teenage brother of [[Miley Stewart]] and son of [[Robby Stewart]]. He is known for his goofy, lazy and disgusting habits. Jackson is a very regular character in ''Hannah Montana''. In the episode &quot;[[Hannah Montana (season 3)#ep72|He Could Be the One]]&quot;, Jackson does not take part in the actual story, but appears as a [[Third-person omniscient narrative|third-person omniscient narrator]], although even in this role he appears in character. Jackson also has a central role in the feature film ''[[Hannah Montana: The Movie]]''. Despite portraying a teen, Jason Earles was in his late twenties when he started the show.

===Background===
Like the rest of his family, Jackson is from Tennessee. He moved to [[Malibu, California]] with his father Robby and sister Miley after the death of his mother. In an off-handed remark in &quot;Song Sung Bad,&quot; Jackson implausibly suggests the reason for this move involved an embarrassing incident with a Tennessean girlfriend. When Jackson first attended school in California he was made fun of because of his [[Southern American English|accent]], cowboy hat, boots, and large belt buckle with shining bright lights which he wore to school.

===Personality===
Jackson is laid back, casual and often lazy.  He is also very foolish.  He leaves his room very untidy. Jackson is a mediocre high school student, and has a rough time starting college in the third season. He is known for how disgustingly he lives. Jackson is often seen barefoot or wearing flip-flops. It is also revealed in the episode &quot;Schooly Bully&quot; that Jackson's bare feet are ticklish.


He is constantly looking for ways to earn money, generally for the purpose of impressing girls.  He is often asking his dad to supplement his income or to increase his allowance. In &quot;Debt It Be&quot; Jackson recalls selling Miley's used tissues on the internet for $37.95. In &quot;Achy Jakey Heart&quot; he teams up with Oliver and opens a cheese jerky stand. In the pilot episode Jackson gets paid to model Miley's Hannah clothes for Farmane. He also holds the world record for the longest amount of time hopping on a [[pogo stick]], a feat which earned him $5,000.&quot;[[Me and Mr. Jonas and Mr. Jonas and Mr. Jonas]]&quot; After initially failing to enter college, Jackson says that his plans for the future include collecting an inheritance from Robby and writing a tell-all book about Miley. After experiencing a [[flashforward]] in which he is an old man and still working at Rico's, Jackson's college ambition is reenergized.

In the episode &quot;Judge Me Tender&quot;, he gets a traffic ticket and Robby Ray makes him pay for the ticket and he states he is not working at Rico's anymore so he has to clean up their, upstairs attic.

In &quot;[[Miley Get Your Gum]]&quot; Jackson saves up enough money to buy a used car and is very proud of it, until his friend Cooper tells him it's a &quot;[[Girl car]].&quot; Although his dad, Robby Ray, makes changes, such as changing the horn and adding a loud stereo, after Robby Ray is unable to sell it back to the original owner.  Jackson eventually paints it blue.

Jackson plays [[volleyball]] on his school team. He enjoys playing basketball until learning his father only lets him win so he will feel happy. He learns [[ping-pong]] well enough to beat his father. He is a big fan of both the &quot;[[Los Angeles Dodgers]]&quot; and the &quot;[[Los Angeles Lakers]].&quot; &quot;[[Grandmas Don't Let Your Babies Grow Up to Play Favorites]]&quot; He enjoys videogames, yet his portable system appears to be an original Nintendo Game Boy from the 1980s. 

Unlike his father and sister, Jackson seems to have no musical talent. Even his own mother admitted that he sings like &quot;a regular [[Tone deafness|tone deaf]] walrus.&quot; During one of Miley's nightmares he becomes a rock-star sensation named Bucky Kentucky.''[[Hannah Montana]]' episode ''[[I Am Hannah, Hear Me Croak]].''

Jackson's main talent seems to be for acting. In &quot;Debt It Be&quot; he plays an old woman at a rest home, in &quot;You Give Lunch a Bad Name&quot; he plays a pot-bellied health inspector, and in &quot;Knock Knock Knockin' on Jackson's Head&quot; he gives a believable performance of having suffered [[amnesia]]. He is also good at impersonations, such as [[Elvis Presley]], [[Ozzy Osbourne]], the &quot;[[Vito Corleone|Godfather]]&quot;, and [[Arnold Schwarzenegger]]. He also imitates his father in &quot;You Give Lunch a Bad Name&quot; and his sister in &quot;You Gotta Not Fight for Your Right to Party.&quot; Perhaps as a consequence of his acting skills, Jackson is also good at dodging direct questions and using [[weasel word]]s. In &quot;Welcome to the Bungle,&quot; Jackson coaches Miley on his techniques before she appears on a talk show to which Miley responds he could have a future as a lawyer. He now goes to college, which he often brags about.

===Relationship with Miley===
Jackson and Miley constantly bicker and compete for their father's approval. Miley often finds Jackson's antics disgusting and Jackson thinks Miley is too full of herself sometimes. Yet on a deeper level, both Miley and Jackson privately express love and appreciation for each other. On several occasions Jackson even goes to great lengths to help Miley when she gets herself in serious trouble. 

Despite being the first born, and therefore having high expectations from Robby, Jackson constantly lives under Miley's shadow. Unlike Robby, Lilly and Oliver, Jackson does not attend Hannah events in disguise. This is at first because he exploits his connection with Hannah to impress his dates.&lt;ref&gt;The opposite of this plays out in &quot;When You Wish You Were the Star.&quot; Jackson gets tired of people pretending to be his friends just to get close to Hannah and moves out of the house and becomes a hermit. This takes place in a parallel universe in which Miley is Hannah all the time.&lt;/ref&gt; Later, in &quot;My Boyfriend's Jackson and There's Gonna Be Trouble&quot; a [[paparazzi|paparazzo]] follows Miley and Jackson home from a concert and reports that they are dating. After this incident, Jackson publicly declares his love for Hannah is &quot;like a sister,&quot; but still keeps her secret. In &quot;We Are Family: Now Get Me Some Water!&quot; he openly works as Hannah's &quot;assistant.&quot; He also sometimes works as her [[chauffeur]].&lt;ref&gt;&quot;She's a Supersneak&quot; and &quot;Bye Bye Ball&quot;&lt;/ref&gt;

While working as Hannah's chauffeur, Jackson is sometimes forced to miss his own activities. He reveals in &quot;Bad Moose Rising&quot; that he really does not mind driving her, as long as she shows appreciation. After Miley gets her license in the third season this is no longer an issue.

===Dating===
Throughout seasons 1–3, Jackson leads a frustrating dating life. However, his longest relationship so far is his current girlfriend [[List of Hannah Montana characters#Siena|Siena]] ([[Tammin Sursok]]) on the 4th season ''[[Hannah Montana (season 4)|Hannah Montana Forever]]''.
* In &quot;Lilly, Do You Want to Know a Secret?&quot; Jackson takes an unnamed girl to Hannah's concert in Los Angeles. He uses his connection with Hannah to impress her, giving her a roll of Hannah's toilet paper as a souvenir.
* In &quot;It's My Party and I'll Lie If I Want To&quot; Jackson tries to date Nina ([[Alison Brie]]), a terribly incompetent hairdresser. He later discovers she was part of one of Rico's plots.
* In &quot;I Can't Make You Love Hannah If You Don't&quot; Jackson dates Olivia (Rae'Ven Larrymore Kelly), his friend Cooper's sister. She is very flirtatious and dishonest. She sends Jackson mixed signals and tells Cooper she does not like Jackson.
* In &quot;Get Down Study-udy-udy&quot; Jackson mentors Becky ([[Tiffany Thornton]]), a girl he is attracted to but finds to be an airhead. She is called &quot;Brainless Becky&quot; by Thor, but &quot;Brainless, ''Bodacious'' Becky&quot; by Jackson. Thor mixes her up with two other Beckies – &quot;Bucktooth Becky&quot; and &quot;Becky with the Bad Breath.&quot; Becky is unique among Jackson's love interests in that she gives him a second chance in &quot;Yet Another Side of Me.&quot;
* In &quot;Take This Job and Love It,&quot; Jackson tries to date Julie by telling her that he is a professional [[motocross]] racer.
* In &quot;You're So Vain You Probably Think This Zit Is About You&quot; Jackson goes on a date with Melissa ([[Aimee Teegarden]]). She calls it the worst date of her life after the car ran out of gas and Jackson made her get out and push.
* In &quot;I Am Hannah, Hear Me Croak&quot; Jackson takes Jenny ([[Unseen character|unseen]]) to a Hannah concert.
* In &quot;Achy Jakey Heart, Part 1&quot; Jackson flirts with Natasha ([[Tiya Sircar]]) who turns out to be a [[Plant (person)|plant]] by Rico.
* In &quot;You Gotta Not Fight for Your Right to Party&quot; Jackson sets up a date with a girl named Sienna Grace ([[Unseen character|unseen]]) to a [[Panic! at the Disco]] concert, but he gets grounded.
* In &quot;Song Sung Bad&quot; Jackson unwillingly enters a relationship with Miley's classmate Sarah ([[Morgan York]]), although they are never seen actually dating. She misunderstands Jackson's comments when he suggests Rico is interested in her. Jackson has a difficult time breaking up with Sarah, and she finally leaves by saying &quot;It's clear you aren't emotionally ready for me... that's why I'll wait.&quot;. Sarah is still seen harassing Jackson in &quot;Would I Lie To You Lilly?&quot; and even costs him a date.
* In &quot;Everybody Was Best Friend Fighting&quot; Jackson sets up a date with Stephanie (Najla Bashira). Right before they are about to leave, Stephanie sees Jackson harassing a boy who he thought was part of Rico's plot. She gets offended and leaves.
* In &quot;Uptight (Oliver's Alright)&quot; Jackson dated and was tutored by a girl named Allison (Katerina Graham). She must have been effective as Jackson grades rose higher, much to Robby Ray's surprise. When she grew bored of Jackson, Robby Ray schemed to keep them together. She later began dating Jackson again in &quot;Jake...Another Piece of My Heart&quot;, but claimed no memory of their past history. Their reunion was spoiled by the arrival of Camp Rico's campers. Later she admitted liking Jackson's way with kids, but fled the Stewart residence when Jackson sneezed in her face.
* In &quot;He Ain’t A Hottie, He’s My Brother&quot;, Miley has a dream that Lilly almost kisses Jackson. When she tells Lilly about it she admits that she has a crush on him. Lilly asks Miley to talk to Jackson and he admits that he likes her too. To keep both of them apart, Miley tells them both that they are not interested in each other but on the Mack and Mickey Show, Miley realizes that it was wrong to lie and tells them both the truth. Lilly and Jackson make up but then Miley wakes up and realizes the whole thing was a dream.
{{clear}}

==Lilly Truscott==
{{Infobox character
| name             = Lilly Truscott
| series           = Hannah Montana
| image            =  
| caption          = 
| first            = &quot;[[Lilly, Do You Want to Know a Secret?]]&quot;
| last             = &quot;[[Wherever I Go]]&quot;
| cause            = 
| creator          = [[Michael Poryes]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Richard Correll]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Barry O'Brien]]
| portrayer        = [[Emily Osment]]&lt;br /&gt;Cubbie Kile&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.imdb.com/title/tt1268620/ Hannah Montana (TV series 2006– )], imdb.com&lt;/ref&gt; (young)
| nickname         = Lilly-pop (by Oliver)
| alias            = Lola LaFonda&lt;ref name=&quot;Gum&quot;&gt;{{cite episode|title=Miley Get Your Gum|episodelink=List of Hannah Montana episodes (Season 1)|series=Hannah Montana|serieslink=Hannah Montana|airdate=March 31, 2006|season=1|number=2}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Lola Luftnagle&lt;ref&gt;{{cite episode|title=It's My Party and I'll Lie if I Want To|episodelink=List of Hannah Montana episodes (Season 1)|series=Hannah Montana|serieslink=Hannah Montana|airdate=April 21, 2006|season=1|number=5}}&lt;/ref&gt;
| gender           = Female
| occupation       = Student
| title            = 
| family           = Kenneth Truscott (father)&lt;br /&gt;Heather Truscott (mother)&lt;ref name=&quot;Mom&quot;&gt;{{cite episode|title=Lilly's Mom Has Got it Goin' On|episodelink=List of Hannah Montana episodes (Season 2)|series=Hannah Montana|serieslink=Hannah Montana|airdate=November 10, 2007|season=2|number=19}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Unnamed brother&lt;ref name=&quot;Gum&quot;/&gt;
| lbl21            = Pet
| data21           = Thor (dog)&lt;ref name=&quot;Gum&quot;/&gt;, Mr. Squeakers (hamster)
| significantother = [[#Oliver Oken|Oliver Oken]] (season 3)
| relatives        = 
| religion         = &lt;!-- never mentioned in show --&gt;
| nationality      = American
}}

'''Lillian &quot;Lilly&quot; Truscott'''&lt;ref&gt;Lillian Truscott spoken by Mamaw in &quot;You Give Lunch a Bad Name&quot; (closed captions confirm)&lt;/ref&gt; ([[Emily Osment]]) is the best friend of Miley Stewart and girlfriend to Oliver Oken. Under the [[Pseudonym|alias]] '''Lola Luftnagle''', she is also close friends with Hannah Montana and part of her entourage. Lilly/Lola has a huge crush on [[Orlando Bloom]] in the episode &quot;The Test Of My Love&quot;, and tells Miley that she will see &quot;the Lilly Bloom&quot; when Orlando finally meets her. She also plays a central role in the film ''[[Hannah Montana: The Movie]]''.

===Development===
The character was originally named Lilly Romero and then changed to Lilly Truscott. Miley Cyrus first auditioned for the role but was cast as the main character instead.&lt;ref&gt;''Hannah Montana'' DVD ''Livin' the Rock Star Life'' special feature &quot;Miley's Audition Tapes.&quot;&lt;/ref&gt; Emily Osment auditioned for the role after Cyrus was cast.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite interview|subject=Emily Osment|subjectlink=Emily Osment|interviewer=[[Whoopi Goldberg]], [[Joy Behar]], [[Sherri Shepherd]], and [[Elisabeth Hasselbeck]]|program=[[The View (U.S. TV series)|The View]]|date=February 18, 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Background===
Lilly was born in and grew up in [[California]] and was childhood friends with Oliver. She met Oliver in kindergarten and has been best friends with him ever since. In Judge Me Tender, she describes him as a dead beat when she first met him. She recently lived with her mother Heather Truscott ([[Heather Locklear]]) in [[Malibu, California|Malibu]]. Heather appears in one episode, &quot;Lilly's Mom Has Got It Goin' On,&quot; where she briefly dates Miley's father [[Robby Stewart|Robby]]. Lilly's parents are divorced, and her father is an accountant.&lt;ref name=&quot;Road&quot;&gt;{{cite episode|title=On the Road Again?|episodelink=List of Hannah Montana episodes (Season 1)|series=Hannah Montana|serieslink=Hannah Montana|airdate=July 28, 2006|season=1|number=12}}&lt;/ref&gt; In season one Lilly claims to have a brother but this is contradicted by her in season three. In &quot;[[List of Hannah Montana episodes (Season 1)|Miley Get Your Gum]],&quot; Lilly refers to her brother's pet hamster. However, in the episode &quot;Cheat it&quot; Lilly says &quot;Sometimes I wish I had a brother, then I come over here. All better!&quot; In the season 3 episode &quot;[[List of Hannah Montana episodes (Season 3)|The Wheel Near My Bed (Keeps on Turnin')]],&quot; she moves in with the Stewart's house when her mother gets a job in Atlanta. But after she hears that Miley does not like her staying with them, she goes to stay at her dad Kenneth's ([[Jon Cryer]]) apartment only to find it even worse than the Stewart's house. Once Lilly and Miley make up, Lilly goes back to staying at the Stewart's house.

Lilly and Miley have been best friends since about the 6th grade.&lt;ref&gt;In &quot;Lilly's Mom Has Got It Goin' On&quot; Miley talks about her and Lilly's custom of celebrating their friendship's &quot;weekiversary.&quot; Miley mentions missing their 200th weekiversary, which is almost four years. This episode takes place during their 9th grade year.&lt;/ref&gt; She discovers Miley's secret in the pilot episode, &quot;[[Lilly, Do You Want to Know a Secret?]]&quot; when she sneaks into Hannah's dressing room after a concert and she sees the lucky bracelet that she had given Miley earlier in the episode. Although Lilly is dating Oliver, she looks at other guys. In &quot;Once, Twice, Three Times Afraidy&quot;, she gazed at Tim, an old friend from camp, causing Oliver to point to the menu on the side, showing his muscles. Also in &quot;He Could Be The One&quot;, she gave advice to Miley stating &quot;whatever choice you make, it's gonna be okay... let's face it, they're both gorgeous!&quot;, making Oliver mad. Other than that, she stays faithful to him.

===Personality===
Lilly is a huge fan of Hannah Montana even before she learns Miley's secret. She is extremely extroverted, excitable, clumsy, and impulsive. She is also very athletic, and loves skateboarding, surfing, hockey, and cheerleading. Lilly does cartwheels whenever she is excited about something such as getting asked to be someone's girlfriend in &quot;My Best Friend's Boyfriend&quot; and getting to go to Washington D.C. in &quot;Would I Lie To You, Lilly?&quot;. In &quot;Joannie B. Goode&quot;, she says she takes piano lessons on Wednesday.

Lilly and Miley have an especially close friendship. Although they often have fights and disagreements, they always manage to restore their friendship, making it all the more stronger. Episodes which significantly deal with their relationship include &quot;Lilly, Do You Want to Know a Secret?,&quot; &quot;Would I Lie To You, Lilly?,&quot; &quot;You're So Vain, You Probably Think This Zit is About You,&quot; and &quot;Cuffs Will Keep Us Together.&quot;

Lilly is [[Tone deafness|tone deaf]] as heard in the episode &quot;Song Sung Bad.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Lilly sings along with other people in &quot;Get Down Study-udy-udy&quot; and &quot;I Am Hannah, Hear Me Croak&quot; without sounding tone deaf.&lt;/ref&gt; Miley Stewart (without telling Lilly) [[remix]]es her rendition of &quot;[[One in a Million (Sandy Mölling song)|One in a Million]]&quot; to make her voice sound on key. Lilly, believing that she is a great singer, challenges classmate Amber Addison to a singing competition in front of their whole class. Lilly proudly declares to be singing &quot;[[I Got Nerve]]&quot; to which Robby replies, &quot;You sure do.&quot;. Lilly is also not very good at doing an impression of Miley as shown in the episodes &quot;You Gotta Not Fight for Your Right to Party&quot; and &quot;Miley Hurt the Feelings of the Radio Star&quot;, Lilly does a unconvincing and very poor impression of Miley, while pretending to be her when Robbie tries to have a talk with Miley (who snuck out of the house with Jackson after being grounded) in the former, and while substituting for Miley when she is late coming to do her radio show with Oliver in the latter.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;You Gotta Not Fight for Your Right to Party&quot; and &quot;Miley Hurt the Feelings of the Radio Star&quot;&lt;/ref&gt;

Despite being somewhat of a [[tomboy]], Lilly is also seen to be very concerned about her appearance. She refuses to enter a skating competition after her dog eats her [[Contact lens|contacts]] and does not want to be seen with her [[horn-rimmed glasses]]. (She is virtually blind without her glasses.) Sometimes she is more excited about wearing cute outfits than of solving problems. She is currently in the series dating Oliver.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;Mascot Love&quot; and &quot;Good Golly Miss Dolly&quot;&lt;/ref&gt;

Lilly is seen in the first season as a tomboy and wears a lot of hats but not so much during Season 2 and 3. In Season 2, Lilly starts wearing wristbands in all colors and also in Season 3. In Season 3, Lilly is seen in a lot of episodes to be wearing a gold heart necklace.

In 'You Gotta Lose That Job', Lilly mentions that she would like to be teacher and that she would be supportive, fun but no talking back (that is unacceptable, Lilly says). She has an ongoing crush on [[Orlando Bloom]] regardless of her many crushes and boyfriends. She says that any movie scenes where he is shirtless is where she runs the movie in slow-motion.

===Lola Luftnagle===
In order to help Miley keep her secret, Lilly attends all Hannah Montana events wearing a disguise and posing as Hannah's companion and assistant &quot;Lola Luftnagle.&quot;  Lilly first comes up with the name &quot;Lola LaFonda&quot; for her alter ego in the episode &quot;[[List of Hannah Montana episodes (Season 1)|Miley Get Your Gum]]&quot;, but she would later settle on Luftnagle in &quot;[[List of Hannah Montana episodes (Season 1)|It's My Party And I'll Lie If I Want To]]&quot; and that name is used in all subsequent episodes. Lilly claims that Lola is the &quot;daughter of oil baron Rudolph Luftnagle, [and] sister of [[socialite]]s Bunny and Kiki Luftnagle.&quot;

Unlike Lilly, who wears a lot of hoodies/jackets, sneakers/sandals and sporty pants, Lola wears very tight clothes that have loud colors. Emily Osment once said in a backstage interview that Lola has some very tight pants that are impossible to sit in. Lola wears a lot of jewellery like rings, necklaces, huge earrings and bangles. Lola usually wears a short, brightly colored, wig but in Season 3 the wig is a little bit longer than the wigs used in Season 1 and 2. In most episodes Lola wears a differently colored wig, from white to red to purple to pink to blue (in one episode Traci Van Horne refers to Lola as a &quot;bitter [[anime]] character&quot;). Emily Osment has said that she has around 80 wigs for Lola, and that her personal favorites are the purple and white wigs.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite interview|subject=Emily Osment|subjectlink=Emily Osment|title=Emily Osment: Wigs, wigs, wigs|url=http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=NfC7DxfVpww|format=video|program=[[WPIX|CW11]]|city=[[New York City]]|date=December 20, 2007}}&lt;/ref&gt; Lola is not dating Mike as said in &quot;He Could Be The One&quot;. Instead she is dating Justin Timberlake, according to an internet rumour she has 'no idea' who started it. Emily Osment said in a backstage interview that she is more like Lola than Lilly and that she loves Lola’s clothes and just wants to keep them.{{citation needed|date=October 2010}} Ashleigh and Molly Luftnagle, Ashleigh played by [[Emily Osment]] and Molly played by [[Miley Cyrus]], are not any relation to Lola. Lola did not appear in [[Hannah Montana: The Movie.]]

===Relationships===
Lilly experiences a few short-lived dating relationships  and only one serious one. She dates actor Jake Ryan ([[Cody Linley]]) at a 70s dance until Miley jealously breaks them up, and her schoolmate Lucas ([[Sterling Knight]]) until Miley discovers he is a cheater.

Miley also has a dream in which Lilly starts dating [[#Jackson Stewart|Jackson]], and must learn to accept her friend for who she is. When Miley wakes up, she believes the dream was real and is pleasantly surprised when Lilly reacts with disgust.

In &quot;[[List of Hannah Montana episodes (Season 2)|You Are So Sue-able to Me]],&quot; Lilly has a crush on her schoolmate Matt Marshall, but it is never revealed if they actually dated. After Matt asks Lilly to a dance, Miley tries to get Lilly to change her tomboy image so that Matt will find her more attractive. However, Matt gets turned off by Lilly's new look and stands her up. (Lilly and Matt reconcile at the end of the episode after Miley was found [[Public liability|liable]] for Lilly's suffering in the Teen Court.) Lilly's celebrity crush is [[Orlando Bloom]]. Bloom is a recurring [[Unseen character|off-screen character]] in the show whom Lilly sometimes harasses at parties as Lola. She also has a crush on Justin Timberlake and supposedly spread a rumor that he's dating Lola.

In the season 3 episode &quot;[[Hannah Montana (season 3)#ep78|Uptight (Oliver's Alright)]]&quot;, it is mentioned that Lilly had a crush on her French teacher during 7th grade. She wore a [[beret]] to school and said &quot;Oui, Oui&quot; so much that people started calling her &quot;Tinkles Truscott&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite episode|title=Uptight (Oliver's Alright|episodelink=Hannah Montana (season 3)#ep78|series=Hannah Montana|serieslink=Hannah Montana|network=[[Disney Channel]]|airdate=September 20, 2009|season=3|number=23|minutes=03:39}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Lilly starts her most significant and successful relationship when she started dating [[Oliver Oken]] in season 3 of the series. Their friendship started in preschool when Lilly held his hand in order to share his [[crayon]]s. Said Lilly, &quot;He had the 64-Pack with the sharpener!&quot; For years the two were best friends, but after a beach party, they decide to date each other (while Miley was away shooting her feature film ''Indiana Joannie'') and we (and Miley) find out in &quot;[[List of Hannah Montana episodes (Season 3)|What I Don't Like About You]].&quot;  However, after an argument over their favorite bands, ([[Radiohead]] and [[Coldplay]]) they broke up. Miley made a mini-Indiana Joannie movie and they made up and resumed dating. They attended prom together in [[List of Hannah Montana episodes (Season 3)|Promma Mia]]. In [[List of Hannah Montana episodes (Season 3)|&quot;He Could Be The One]],&quot; Lilly says she loves Oliver. Their names for each other are &quot;Olly-pop&quot; and &quot;Lilly-pop.&quot; In &quot;I Honestly Love You (No Not You)&quot; Lilly tells Miley that Oliver calls her &quot;Lilly-pop&quot; because she had a pimple.

In [[List of Hannah Montana episodes (Season 3)|I Honestly Love You (No Not You)]] a love triangle appears when Miley (while alseep in the hospital because of a broken ankle), overhears Oliver say &quot;I love you&quot; while talking to Miley. This leads to Miley believing that Oliver was in love with her while dating Lilly. Miley thinks that all she has to do is wait till Lilly moves onto someone else and that Oliver will change his mind. But when Lilly announces that she loves Oliver, Miley tells her the truth. Miley and Lilly then hatch a plan to get Oliver back only to find out that Oliver was in fact, practicing saying &quot;I love you&quot; so he could say it to Lilly. In the end of the episode, Lilly and Oliver both say that they love each other.

However, in &quot;He Could Be The One,&quot; Lilly tells Oliver that while Lilly may be dating Oliver, Lola is dating Justin Timberlake according to an online rumor &quot;she doesn't know who started.&quot;

In &quot;B-B-B-Bad To The Chrome,&quot; Lilly and Oliver celebrated their 100th day relationship anniversary which Oliver forgets at first and Lilly was upset. They make-up again after Rico helped them get back together by writing a fake poem and send it to Lilly but signed as &quot;Oliver Oken.&quot;

In the episode &quot;Judge Me Tender&quot;, Oliver’s singing career takes off, but all the attention he receives causes him to neglect Lilly. As a result, Lilly asks Miley to boot him off the show which results in them breaking up. However, Miley lets Oliver succeed to the semi-finals. Afterward, Miley manages to talk some sense into Oliver, causing him to make up with Lilly.

==Oliver Oken==
{{Infobox character
| name             = Oliver Oken
| series           = Hannah Montana
| image            = 
| caption          = 
| first            = ''&quot;[[Lilly, Do You Want to Know a Secret?]]&quot;''
| last             = ''&quot;[[Wherever I Go]]&quot;''
| cause            =  
| creator          = [[Michael Poryes]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Richard Correll]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Barry O'Brien]]
| portrayer        = [[Mitchel Musso]]
| nickname         = Smoken' Oken&lt;br /&gt;Locker Man&lt;br /&gt;Locker Doctor&lt;br /&gt;Ollikens (by Sarah)&lt;br /&gt;Ollie-pop (by Lilly)
| alias            = Mike Standley III&lt;!-- Yes it is actually spelled Standley with a D, this is not a mistake - see following cite for proof --&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Standley&quot;/&gt;
| gender           = Male
| occupation       = Student&lt;br /&gt;Attendant at Rico's Surf Shop&lt;br /&gt;Singer
| title            = 
| family           = Nancy Oken (mother)&lt;br /&gt;Unnamed younger brother
| significantother = [[#Lilly Truscott|Lilly Truscott]] (season 3-4)
| relatives        = Aunt Harriet (seen in Miley Get Your Gum)&lt;br /&gt;unnamed uncle
| religion         = &lt;!-- never mentioned in show --&gt;
| nationality      = American
}}
'''Oliver Oscar Oken''' ([[Mitchel Musso]]) is the male best friend to Miley Stewart and Lilly Truscott . He later begins to date Lilly. He uses the [[Pseudonym|alias]] '''Mike Standley III''' while attending events with Hannah Montana in order to keep Miley's secret. Sometimes Oliver makes fun of Miley along with Lilly. A [[running gag]] is that Miley, Lilly, or both hit him.

===Background===
Oliver was born July 3, 1992 and grew up in California and was childhood friends and Kindergarten friends with Lilly. In Judge Me Tender, Lilly describes him as a dead beat when she first met him. He met Miley in the 6th grade and has been her closest guy friend ever since. However, before he met her, he had spread a rumour that she ate possum. He lives with his mother Nancy Oken who works as a [[police officer]], his overprotective father,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite episode|title=You Never Give Me My Money|episodelink=List of Hannah Montana episodes (Season 3)#ep59|series=Hannah Montana|serieslink=Hannah Montana|airdate=08-11-23|season=1|number=59}}&lt;/ref&gt; and a little brother. Oliver also has type 1 diabetes.

Oliver is Jewish, as revealed in a few episodes. He says his family follows Kosher, and says his mom goes ''Mashugana'', &quot;crazy&quot; in Hebrew so it is revealed Oliver is of the [[Jewish faith]].

In the first two episodes, Oliver is an overly enthusiastic Hannah Montana fan, saying &quot;Hannah Montana is a ''goddess''! I worship at her feet!&quot; He has a record of stalking her and even dreams of one day marrying her. Miley mercifully reveals her secret to Oliver in the second episode. Since he has never had any romantic feelings for Miley, Oliver is freed from his Hannah obsession, but remains close personal friends with Miley.

He makes a brief appearance in ''[[Hannah Montana: The Movie]]'' at Lilly's sweet 16th birthday party and in the credits doing the Hoedown Throwdown. He and Rico are the only main characters from the series to have small roles in the film. Oliver has a small role in the film because Mitchel Musso was working on his music career during the filming.{{Citation needed|date=July 2010}}

===Personality===
Oliver is very friendly, outgoing, flirtatious,
sometimes over confident and funny. Aside from being bullied a few times, Oliver is well liked by most people. He generally avoids Miley and Lilly's ongoing feud with Amber and Ashley and Jackson's confrontations with Rico. At school he earns the nickname &quot;Locker Man&quot; for his ability to effortlessly open his classmates jammed lockers. He commonly serves as the [[Disc jockey|DJ]] at school events.&lt;ref&gt;Oliver once publicly gives out his phone number as [[555 (telephone number)|555]]-0121 and then again as 555-0127 on the PA system. This is possibly an error on Musso's part, as ones sometimes look like sevens.&lt;/ref&gt; His [[catchphrase]] is &quot;Freaky freaky fresh&quot;, which often annoys Miley.

Oliver shares Lilly's interests in skating, surfing, and hockey. He likes rapping and is a fan of [[Coldplay]]. In the episode &quot;You Gotta Lose This Job,&quot; Oliver is heard to be a good singer, although he earlier sang terribly at the end of &quot;Song Sung Bad.&quot; Early in the series, he has a deep fear of gum (Miley Get Your Gum), appearing in front of people, and losing what he claims to be his only chest hair. In later episodes such as &quot;You Gotta Lose This Job&quot; and &quot;Judge Me Tender,&quot; he performs very well on stage and in the latter episode he is also seen chewing gum. It is revealed that Oliver is a [[Diabetes mellitus|diabetic]] in the episode &quot;No Sugar Sugar.&quot; This episode was cancelled, rewritten and aired in September 2009 under the title &quot;Uptight, Oliver's Alright.&quot;

Oliver is somewhat connected with his feminine side, possibly as a result of having two girls for best friends. He reads his mother's &quot;chick magazines,&quot; watches soap operas with his grandmother, and lets Miley give him a [[manicure]] in the episode &quot;Cuffs Will Keep Us Together.&quot; Oliver once bemoans this fact by stating &quot;I so need more guy friends.&quot; However, Oliver often shows himself to be a good and loyal friend to Miley and Lilly, and they both value his friendship. Oliver describes Miley as being his closest girl bud, alongside Lilly.

In the episode &quot;Judge Me Tender&quot;, Oliver's singing career takes off when he participates in America's Top Talent. He manages to succeed to the semi-finals. 

In &quot;Miley says Goodbye (Part 2)&quot; Oliver gets an offer to support a band and goes off for a six month tour. Because of this he only has a recurring role in season 4 and is not credited as part of the main cast. [[Mitchel Musso]] was working on his music career and filming ''[[Pair of Kings]]'' during the filming of season 4 and wasn't able to be a part of all of the episodes.

===Mike Standley III===
In the episode &quot;Everybody Was Best-Friend Fighting,&quot; Oliver creates a disguise to attend Hannah events without blowing Miley's secret, similar to how Lilly created Lola Luftnagle. Lilly helps Oliver come up with the disguise which consists of a fake [[goatee]], [[Ray-Ban Aviator|aviator]] sunglasses, an upside-down visor, white and blue shorts and a zip-up [[hoodie]] since he only had a vampire costume as a disguise so Lilly helped him. When asked for his name, Oliver thinks of the name &quot;Mike Standley III&quot;, being inspired by a nearby [[Microphone stand|mic stand]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Standley&quot;&gt;{{cite web|last=Musso|first=Mitchel|title=Mitchel's Official Blog|publisher=Mitchel Musso Online|date=September 18, 2007|url=http://mitchels-blog.blogspot.com/2007/09/mike-standley-third.html|quote=&quot;Mike Standley the Third is in the House this week.&quot;&lt;!--This is a direct written quote from Mitchel Musso who read the script.--&gt;|accessdate=2007-09-18}}&lt;/ref&gt; Mike is not dating Lola, as said in &quot;He Could Be the One&quot;.

===Relationships===
Oliver has several dating relationships, but only two of them have been successful. He first dates Becca Weller whom Miley sets him up with after Becca confesses her feelings for Oliver to Hannah Montana in an email. (Becca was unaware that Hannah knew Oliver.) It is unknown how Oliver and Becca break up, but she only appears in one episode. Oliver later dates his classmate Sarah ([[Morgan York]]) with whom he is assigned a school project in which they must raise an imaginary child (a sack of flour). They break up after the project is due when they discover they have nothing in common, except their love for their imaginary flour child.

So far, Oliver's second longest relationship has been with Joannie Palumbo ([[Hayley Chase]]), whom he starts dating in &quot;Joannie B. Goode.&quot; Miley and Lilly at first have a lot of animosity towards Joannie, but eventually Lilly becomes good friends with her and Miley accepts their relationship. Oliver and Joannie's relationship lasts for 11 more episodes until their amicable break up in &quot;Papa's Got a Brand New Friend.&quot;

Oliver's most significant relationship and longest is with [[Lilly Truscott]] when they started dating in season 3 of the series. In [[pre-school]], Lilly held Oliver's hand for his crayons, with the reasoning, &quot;He had the 64-pack with the sharpener!&quot; For years, the two were best friends, but after a beach party they decided to start dating and we first see this in &quot;[[List of Hannah Montana episodes (Season 3)|What I Don't Like About You]]&quot; while Miley was away shooting her feature film ''Indiana Joannie.'' However after an argument over their favourite bands ([[Radiohead]] and [[Coldplay]]) they broke up but Miley, made a mini-Indiana Joannie movie and they made up and resumed dating. They attended prom together in [[List of Hannah Montana episodes (Season 3)|Promma Mia]]. The circumstances of their first date are under dispute by both Lilly and Oliver. 

In [[List of Hannah Montana episodes (Season 3)|He Could Be The One]], Lilly says that she loves Oliver. Their names for each other are Ollie-pop and Lilly-pop.

In [[List of Hannah Montana episodes (Season 3)|I Honestly Love You (No Not You)]] a love triangle appears when Miley (while asleep in the hospital because of a broken ankle), overhears Oliver say &quot;I love you&quot; while talking to Miley. This leads to Miley believing that Oliver was in love with her while dating Lilly. Miley thinks that all she has to do is wait till Lilly moves onto someone else and that Oliver will change his mind. But when Lilly announces that she loves Oliver, Miley tells her the truth. Miley and Lilly then hatch a plan to get Oliver back only to find out that Oliver was in fact, practicing saying &quot;I love you&quot; so he could say it to Lilly. In the end of episode Lilly and Oliver both say that they love each other. It is also mentioned in this episode that Lilly is the only girl he has ever loved.

In &quot;B-B-B-Bad To The Chrome,&quot; Lilly and Oliver celebrated their 100th day relationship anniversary which Oliver forgets at first and Lilly was upset. They make-up again after Rico helped them get back together by writing a fake poem and send it to Lilly but signed as &quot;Oliver Oken&quot;. It is also revealed in this episode that whenever he and Lilly are not together, he gets in a bad mood.

In the episode &quot;Judge Me Tender,&quot; Oliver’s singing career takes off, but all the attention he receives causes him to neglect Lilly. As a result, Lilly asks Miley to boot him off the show which results in them breaking up. However, Miley lets Oliver succeed to the semi-finals. Afterward, Miley manages to talk some sense into Oliver, causing him to make up with Lilly.

In &quot;Got to Get Her out of My House&quot;, Oliver and Lilly try and buy a car together.  Also in the same episode, Rico insults Lilly and makes Oliver very angry to the point he tries to beat him up, much to Rico's delight.

The final episode they say I love you to each other again and kiss, before Lilly decides to leave for France.

Oliver's celebrity crushes include [[Hannah Montana (character)|Hannah Montana]] (until he finds out that Miley is Hannah), [[Mandy Moore]], [[Jessica Simpson]] and [[Taylor Swift]].

===Episodes===
Episodes which significantly deal with Oliver's character development include &quot;Miley Get Your Gum,&quot; &quot;Everybody Was Best-Friend Fighting,&quot; &quot;Uptight (Oliver's Alright)&quot;(Previously titled &quot;No Sugar Sugar&quot;), &quot;Judge Me Tender&quot; and &quot;You Gotta Lose That Job.&quot; As a series regular, he was absent from twelve episodes and only appeared for 2 episodes in Season 4:
*&quot;You Are So Sue-Able to Me&quot;
*&quot;Take This Job and Love It!&quot;
*&quot;I Want You to Want Me...To Go to Florida&quot;
*&quot;Me and Mr. Jonas and Mr. Jonas and Mr. Jonas&quot;
*&quot;Don't Stop Til You Get the Phone&quot;
*&quot;Test of My Love&quot;
*&quot;Cheat It!&quot;
*&quot;Knock Knock Knockin' on Jackson's Head&quot;
*&quot;Jake... Another Little Piece of my Heart
*&quot;Can't Get Home to You Girl&quot;
*&quot;Come Fail Away&quot;
*&quot;For (give) A Little Bit

==Rico Suave==
{{Infobox character
| name             = Rico Suave, Jr.
| series           = Hannah Montana
| image            =  
| caption          = 
| first            = ''&quot;[[List of Hannah Montana episodes#ep5|It's My Party and I'll Lie if I Want To]]&quot;''
| last             = ''&quot;[[Wherever I Go]]&quot;''
| cause            = 
| creator          = [[Michael Poryes]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Richard Correll]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Barry O'Brien]]
| portrayer        = [[Moises Arias]]
| nickname         = Shortstop, Squirt
| gender           = Male
| occupation       = Student&lt;br /&gt;Manager of Rico's Surf Shop&lt;br /&gt;Owner of Senor Steam&lt;br /&gt;landlord
| title            = 
| family           = Rico Suave, Sr. (father)&lt;br /&gt;unnamed mother&lt;br /&gt;Mateo (brother)&lt;br /&gt;unnamed sister 
| significantother = 
| relatives        = Teresa (cousin)&lt;br /&gt;Angus (cousin)
| religion         = &lt;!-- never mentioned in show --&gt;
| nationality      = American 
}}
'''Rico Suave'''&lt;ref&gt;The name Rico is [[Spanish language|Spanish]] for &quot;rich.&quot;&lt;/ref&gt; ([[Moises Arias]]) is the young manager of &quot;Rico's Surf Shop,&quot; a [[concession stand]] located on the beach near the Stewarts' home. He most commonly interacts with Jackson, his employee, despite the fact that Rico is several years younger. In the second season he also attends school with Miley, Lilly, and Oliver. Rico is the main antagonist in the series. 

Rico's first appearance is in [[List of Hannah Montana episodes#ep5|&quot;It's My Party and I'll Lie if I Want To&quot;]], the fifth episode of ''Hannah Montana''. He makes a total of five appearance in that season as a [[recurring character]]. His popularity led to his becoming a main character beginning with season two. All together, Rico has appeared in 58 episodes. He also makes a brief appearance in the film ''[[Hannah Montana: The Movie]]''. Although Rico does not know Miley's secret, he appears partly out of character in the episode [[Hannah Montana (season 3)#ep73|&quot;He Could Be the One&quot;]] as an [[Third-person omniscient narrative|omniscient narrator]] who is aware of the secret. In this role Rico acts apart from the story. In the episode &quot;[[Get Down Study-udy-udy]]&quot;, Rico had almost discovered Miley's secret according to the steps, the song used in the &quot;Bone Dance&quot; created by Miley and her voice. When Miley reveals herself on television as Hannah, Rico is shocked and horrified that he couldn't see the obvious, unable to talk to anyone afterward.

===Background===
Rico comes from a very wealthy [[Hispanic and Latino Americans|Latino]] family. His billionaire parents are often mentioned but [[Unseen character|never seen]]. He has a sister, a brother named Mateo (Mateo Arias), a cousin named Teresa, and an [[Australia]]n/[[Mexico|Mexican]] cousin nicknamed &quot;Angus&quot; who's real name is '''A'''lejandro '''N'''uñez '''G'''onzales '''U'''berto '''S'''ifuentes (Moises Arias).

===Personality===
Rico is manipulative, arrogant, and spoiled, even described as &quot;evil&quot; by some characters. His self-centeredness leads him to constantly look for ways to increase his revenue, even at the expense of taking if from others. (He sees everyone else as a direct competitor and becomes extremely jealous whenever someone makes money.) His [[catchphrase]]s include his greeting, &quot;Hey-O!&quot;, and a diabolical laugh, &quot;Mwah-ha-ha!&quot;, which he does frequently.

Rico is very gifted academically. He skips a couple of grades in school and is in the same grade as Miley, Lilly, and Oliver, even though he is two years younger. Studying is easy for him because he has a [[Eidetic memory|photographic memory]]. He is especially good at biology and mathematics, once finishing a biology mid-term exam in less than one second, with still enough time to recheck all of his answers.

It is revealed that Rico sometimes suffers from personal insecurities from his big ears and buck teeth. Perhaps as a result of a [[Napoleon complex]], Rico uses his money and influence to put other people down. He also tends to pursue relationships with girls much older than himself in order to increase his social standing. He bribes both Miley and Lilly in this way. He often blackmails them both to be his girlfriend. In 'Knock Knocking on Jackson's Head', Lilly has to pretend to be Rico's girlfriend (so he can impress his cousin Angus), in return for tutoring in math from Rico. In 'Me and Rico Down By The Schoolyard', Miley gets blackmailed in being Rico's girlfriend because she thought he knew her Hannah secret but it turned out to be attachment to her teddy bear.

In the episode &quot;Cheat It,&quot; Rico runs a [[sauna]] company called &quot;Señor Steam&quot; which Robby patronizes.

Episodes that especially deal with Rico's character development include &quot;Me and Rico Down By the Schoolyard&quot;, &quot;Get Down, Study-udy-udy&quot; and &quot;Joannie B. Goode&quot;.

===Relationship with Jackson===
Jackson and Rico have a [[frenemy]] relationship. Rico often comes up with ways of making Jackson miserable or getting him in trouble. He is an unforgiving employer and sometimes fires Jackson, only to re-hire him later. Rico is usually successful in his practical jokes on Jackson because of his virtually unlimited financial resources. On a few rare occasions Jackson gets the last laugh with Rico, as seen in &quot;Hannah In The Streets With Diamonds.&quot; (Rico called Jackson and his father 'country dumpkins', and Jackson got angry.) In &quot;Once, Twice, Three Times Afraidy&quot; he tells Jackson that he is the closest thing to a best friend he has.  In &quot;Wherever I Go&quot;, Rico fires Jackson to force him to get a real job.  After he fails, Rico gets him a real job as a video game tester saying (though it was hard for him) that Jackson is his best friend which Jackson reciprocates. When Miley reveals herself to be Hannah, Jackson at first gloats over Rico not knowing the secret but takes pity on him and cheers him up by having a choir sing of all the other people who didn't figure it out.

===Relationship with Oliver===
The relationship Oliver and Rico have is practically the same as Jackson and Rico. Rico sometimes looks to Oliver as an older brother, but also as a target. He usually sees Oliver's complications and uses them against him, such as in &quot;Don't Go Breaking My Tooth&quot;. He also takes heed in making fun and manipulating Jackson and Oliver, such as in &quot;That's What Friends Are For?.&quot; When it comes to business matters, such as making a commercial for Rico's, he turns to Oliver. He also thinks of Oliver as a much more efficient employee than Jackson, as he once got a job and Rico said he was perfect. Oliver is also seen working at Rico's again in season 3 in the episode &quot;B-B-B-Bad To The Chrome&quot; as well as in season 1 in the episode &quot;We Are Family – Now Get Me Some Water&quot;.

==References==
{{reflist|30em}}

{{Hannah Montana}}

[[Category:Hannah Montana characters| ]]
[[Category:Lists of Disney characters|Hanna Montana]]

[[ko:한나 몬타나의 주요 등장인물 목록]]
[[nn:Lilly Truscott]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
