<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="1960395" ns="0" title="RBD"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{About|the [[Mexican pop]] group}}
{{Infobox musical artist
|name = RBD
|image = Rebelde1.jpg
|image_size =
|caption = (Top – Bottom, L-R) Dulce, Anahi, Maite, Christopher, Christian and Alfonso in Brazil.
|background = group_or_band
|origin = Mexico
|genre = [[Latin pop]] / [[Mexican pop]]&lt;br&gt;[[Pop/rock]]
|years_active = 	2004–2009
|label = [[EMI]]/[[Capitol Records|Capitol]]
|website = [http://www.grupo-rbd.com/ Official website]
|Currernt_members =  &lt;small&gt;(in alphabetical order)&lt;br&gt;&lt;/small&gt;[[Alfonso Herrera]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Anahí]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Omar Fercho Villa]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Christopher Uckermann]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Dulce María]] &lt;br /&gt; [[Maite Perroni]]
|past_members =  &lt;small&gt;(in alphabetical order)&lt;br&gt;&lt;/small&gt;[[Alfonso Herrera]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Anahí]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Christian Chávez]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Christopher Uckermann]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Dulce María]] &lt;br /&gt; [[Maite Perroni]]

}}

'''RBD''' was a two-time Latin-Grammy nominated [[Mexican pop]] group that gained popularity from [[Televisa|Televisa's]] teen drama series ''[[Rebelde]]''. RBD sold over 17&amp;nbsp;million digital downloads&lt;ref&gt;http://www.emimusic.es/artistas/noticias/1138/1318&lt;/ref&gt; and over 20&amp;nbsp;million albums worldwide in four years since their formation, according to [[EMI]].&lt;ref&gt;http://music.moldova.org/artist/rbd-338-0-eng.html&lt;/ref&gt; The band was officially formed on October 4, 2004, and announced their separation on August 15, 2008.

==Members==
{| class=&quot;wikitable&quot;
|-
!Name
!Date (age)
!Birth
|-
|[[Anahí|Anahí Giovanna Puente Portilla]]
|May 14, 1983
|[[Mexico City]]
|-
|[[Alfonso Herrera|Alfonso Herrera Rodríguez]]
|August 28, 1983
|[[Mexico City]]
|-
|[[Dulce María|Dulce María Espinoza Saviñón]]
|December 6, 1985
|[[Mexico City]]
|-
|[[Christopher Uckermann|Christopher Alexander Luís Casillas Von Uckermann]]
|October 21, 1986
|[[Mexico City]]
|-
|[[Maite Perroni|Maite Perroni Beorlegui]]
|March 9, 1983
|[[Mexico City]]
|-
|[[Christian Chávez|José Christian Chávez Garza]]
|August 7, 1983
|[[Reynosa, Tamaulipas]]
|}

==Biography==
===2004–2005: ''Rebelde''===
{{listen
 | filename     = RBD - Rebelde.ogg
 | title        = &quot;Rebelde&quot; (2004)
 | description  = RBD's lead single from their first album ''Rebelde''.
 | format       = [[Ogg]]
}}
Their first album [[Rebelde (album)|Rebelde]], was released on November 30, 2004 by EMI. The main writers and producers for the project were Carlos Lara (aka D.J. Kafka) and Max di Carlo. The first three singles (&quot;[[Rebelde (song)|Rebelde]]&quot;, &quot;[[Solo quédate en silencio|Sólo Quédate En Silencio]]&quot; and &quot;[[Sálvame]]&quot;) were all number one hits in Mexico, with the fourth single, &quot;[[Un poco de tu amor|Un Poco De Tu Amor]]&quot; reaching number two.

Rebelde sold well in the United States, reaching #95 on the Billboard 200 and reaching number two on the Latin Albums chart. In July 2005 a live CD/DVD, [[Tour Generación RBD En Vivo]] was released documenting their tour around Mexico (45 sold-out concerts across the country, including sixteen in Mexico City alone). 

===2005–2006: ''Nuestro Amor''===
They released their second studio album, [[Nuestro Amor]] in 2005. This album set new record sales in Mexico, selling 127,000 copies on its release day, and 160,000 copies within its first week. In the U.S., the album topped the Latin Albums Chart for 3 weeks and peaked at #88 on the Billboard 200. The first four singles reached number one in Mexico. In the United States &quot;[[Nuestro amor|Nuestro Amor]]&quot;, &quot;[[Aún hay algo|Aún Hay Algo]]&quot; and &quot;[[Este corazón|Este Corazón]]&quot; charted on the Hot Latin chart at #6, #24 and #10 respectively.

With the success of [[Rebelde]], the group used the hiatus between the first and second season to release Nuestro Amor, which included twelve brand-new songs plus &quot;Una Canción&quot; (a live recording), and &quot;Liso, Sensual&quot; (a studio version of the song previously performed on their last tour).

2006 also brought RBD a nomination for the [[Latin Grammy Awards]] in the category &quot;Best Pop Album by a Group or Duo&quot; for Nuestro Amor. They performed a new version of &quot;Tras de Mí&quot; at the ceremony.

;Rebelde (versão Brasil) e Nosso Amor Rebelde
In November 2005 a Portuguese language version of their debut album was released under the title [[Rebelde (Edição Brasil)|Brazilian Edition]].

In early 2006, RBD went on tour around the U.S. for the first time. The tour was recorded and released as a CD/DVD in April under the title [[Live In Hollywood (RBD album)|Live In Hollywood]]. It peaked at number 6 on the Latin Albums Chart.

In May 2006, they released a Portuguese version of Nuestro Amor, entitled [[Nosso Amor Rebelde|Brazilian Edition]], intended for the Brazilian market. Nosso Amor Rebelde is their second album in Portuguese. Released only in Brazil, the album contains Portuguese versions of 11 songs from Nuestro Amor.

===2006–2007: ''Celestial'', ''Celestial (versão Brasil)'' and ''Rebels''===
In November 2006, they released their third studio album ''[[Celestial (RBD album)|Celestial]]'' produced and directed by Carlos Lara which debuted at number 15 in the [[Billboard 200|''Billboard'' 200]], marking first-week sales of over 137,000 copies in the U.S.
{{listen
 | filename     = RBD - Ser o Parecer.ogg
 | title        = &quot;Ser o Parecer&quot; (2006)
 | description  = RBD's second major hit single worldwide.
 | format       = [[Ogg]]
}}
.
The album however did not have a full week of album sales, due to its Friday release. Despite this, it became their first album to peak or chart within the top 20 of the Billboard 200.&lt;ref&gt;[http://billboard.com/bbcom/news/article_display.jsp?vnu_content_id=1003465594 First (and only) debut within top 20]&lt;/ref&gt;

Celestial is the 3rd album in Spanish of the Mexican group RBD, and also the first to be launched simultaneously in all the countries in which the group is known. Three singles were released: &quot;[[Ser o Parecer]]&quot;, &quot;[[Celestial (song)|Celestial]]&quot; and &quot;[[Bésame Sin Miedo]]&quot;

One month later, in December 2006 a Portuguese language edition of the album was released for the Brazilian market called ''[[Celestial (Versão Brasil)]]''.This 3rd album in Portuguese was the first to be recorded in Brazil.

From their tour of Brazil, RBD released a DVD entitled ''[[Live in Rio (RBD DVD)|Live in Rio]]''. They were also honored for selling over 2.5&amp;nbsp;million copies of their albums and DVDs in Brazil. Meanwhile, in Spain, ''Rebelde'' spent 5 weeks on the top of the charts going 3× Platinum for sales over 240,000, ''[[Nuestro Amor]]'' sold enough to be certified 2× Platinum, while ''[[Celestial (RBD album)|Celestial]]'', has been certified Platinum.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.los40.com/actualidad/listas/afyve.html]&lt;/ref&gt;

On March 2, 2007, Christian Chavez revealed that he is homosexual after pictures of him getting married to another man in Canada surfaced on the Internet. In a letter on the group's website, he asked fans for understanding and acceptance.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.grupo-rbd.com/static/ChristianChavezEN.htm Christian reveils sexuality]&lt;/ref&gt; After this the group worked two side-projects; ''Sálvame'', an organization that helps homeless youth get an education and shelter, and ''[[RBD: La Familia]]'', their new sitcom.
RBD was also nominated four times in three categories for the 2007 [[Billboard Latin Music Awards]].

In December 2006, they released their first English album, ''[[Rebels (album)|Rebels]]'' which debuted at number 40 on the Billboard 200 album chart with first-week sales of 94,000 copies.
{{listen
 | filename    = RBD - Tu Amor.ogg
 | title       = &quot;Tu Amor&quot; (2006)
 | description = RBD's lead English single.
 | format      = [[Ogg]]
}}

They were nominated twice in the category for &quot;Latin Pop Album of the Year By a Duo or Group&quot;, with ''Celestial'' and ''Live in Hollywood'', which were both released in 2006. They also received a nomination for &quot;Top Latin Albums Artist of the Year&quot; and &quot;Latin Tour of the Year&quot; for Tour Generación 2006.&lt;ref name=&quot;2007 BLMA nominations&quot;&gt;[http://artists.letssingit.com/artist-84gtp/news/213726 2007 Billboard Latin Music Awards nominations]&lt;/ref&gt; The show was held on April 26 in Miami. They won in all categories they were nominated in; ''Celestial'' was the one for which they won the &quot;Latin Pop Album of the Year By a Duo or Group&quot; award.&lt;ref name=&quot;2007 BLMA winner&quot;&gt;[http://www.billboard.com/bbcom/awards/index.jsp Billboard Latin Music Awards winners]&lt;/ref&gt;  The group also prepared their 2007 world tour called ''Tour Celestial 2007'', starting in [[Ecuador]] on April 20. They were invited by [[Donald Trump]] to perform 3 songs at the [[Miss Universe 2007|2007 Miss Universe]] final in Mexico City, on May 28, 2007. The group performed a medley of &quot;[[Wanna Play]]&quot;, &quot;Cariño Mio&quot; and &quot;Money Money&quot; in the event. In June 2007, RBD recorded the video for &quot;[[Bésame sin miedo|Bésame Sin Miedo]]&quot; in [[Transylvania]], while touring in [[Romania]], where ''Celestial'' was also released. It was the same year they were chosen to headline, along with [[The Black Eyed Peas]], a series of [[Pepsi]] commercials to air on South America and Spanish-speaking countries. On July 19, 2007, RBD performed their single &quot;Bésame Sin Miedo&quot; at Premios Juventud 2007, and also won 7 awards that night, including &quot;Voice of the Moment&quot; and &quot;Favorite Concert&quot;. They had won a total of 24 Premios Juventud awards by then. RBD broke the record for most albums in the top 20 in Brazil, being with three different albums in the top 20 for the week ending January 20, 2007. The group has become such a phenomenon they have been nominated as best international song of &quot;[[Tu Amor]]&quot; in France proving their huge success. In a recent interview with Christopher in Mexico he stated that it has always been an honor to be compared to Menudo and Timbiriche but mentioned that RBD over passed those 2 groups accomplishing a lot more in only 5 years, being the only Mexican group ever to expand throughout the world.(RBD: World Wide Phenomenon)

===2007–08: ''Empezar Desde Cero''===
[[File:RBD 2008-2.jpg|200px|thumb|RBD live in 2008.]]

The first worldwide &quot;RBD Day&quot; was held on October 4, 2007. RBD celebrated the day with many fans in Houston, Texas, and during their press conference they confirmed that their fourth Spanish studio album would be titled [[Empezar Desde Cero]], produced again by Carlos Lara and Armando Avila. The first single from Empezar Desde Cero, [[Inalcanzable (song)|Inalcanzable]], debuted on October 2007 and peaked at #2 in Mexican charts. Empezar Desde Cero was released November 20, debuting on #1 on the Billboard Latin Charts, and peaking at the top 5 in a variety of countries such as Brazil (being their first album not to top the charts in that country, peaking at #3) and Mexico. As of November 2008, [[Empezar Desde Cero]] had sold over 1&amp;nbsp;million copies worldwide. It was also voted by Billboard Readers as the third best album released in 2007.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.billboard.com/bbcom/yearend/2007/readers/index.html &quot;2007 Billboard Readers Choice&quot;]. ''Billboard''. Retrieved April 23, 2008.&lt;/ref&gt;

Meanwhile, in April 2008, RBD performed a concert for Brazil's capitol city, [[Brasilia]]'s 48th Birthday Celebration Party. The free concert was held at the city's main park and had an audience of over 500,000 fans.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www2.esmas.com/rbd/noticias/000564/rbd-brasil-concierto-gratuito &quot;RBD se presenta ante casi 500 mil admiradores en Brasil&quot;]. ''Esmas''. Retrieved April 21, 2008.&lt;/ref&gt; Still on April, RBD was stated to be the first artist ever in the history of Slovenia charts to have 6 different albums in the Top 10 at the same weekend.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www2.esmas.com/rbd/noticias/000589/rbd-impone-record-eslovenia &quot;RBD impone récord en Eslovenia&quot;]. ''Esmas''. Retrieved April 23, 2008.&lt;/ref&gt;

On August, 2008, the 2008 [[Latin Grammy]] nominations were announced, with RBD being nominated for Best Pop Album with [[Empezar Desde Cero]]

===2008–09: ''Best Of RBD'' and ''Para Olvidarte De Mi''===
On August 14, 2008, RBD announced through a press release that they would disband in 2009.&lt;ref name=&quot;Comunicado de RBD&quot;&gt;[http://www2.esmas.com/rbd/fotos/comunicado-rbd/9543 Comunicado official] Retrieved August 12, 2009.&lt;/ref&gt;  The group's manager, Pedro Damian, explained that, although there weren't any fights among the members, it was decided to be the best that they should disband, for the members were already planning different solo activities.

Alfonso and Maite were occupied with their television projects (Maite as the protagonist of ''[[Cuidado con el ángel]]'' and Alfonso with TV Series ''Terminales'').  Christian was in the middle of a tour with the musical ''[[Avenue Q]]'''s Mexican stage production.  Anahí managed her own clothing store in Mexico City and began an organization to help those with eating disorders. Dulce was involved with the shooting of a movie and a variety of projects, such as dubbing a cartoon character in a Mexican motion picture, while Christopher said he planned to build a career as a drummer and musical producer.

On November 25, RBD released ''[[Best Of RBD]]'' (in Brazil: ''Hits Em Português''; in U.S.: ''Greatest Hits''), a CD/DVD featuring their singles and a DVD with music videos, as part of their goodbye.&lt;ref name=&quot;Emi Music Mexico anuncia el nuevo de RBD&quot;&gt;{{Dead link|url=http://www.emimusic.com.mx/portal/hgxpp001.aspx?2,1,135,O,S,0,PAG;CONC;2;71;D;1801440;1;PAG;,|date=August 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt;  A Portuguese version of the album was also released.{{Citation needed|date=April 2009}}

[[Para Olvidarte De Mí]] was the last RBD album to be released.  It was released March 10, 2009.{{Citation needed|date=August 2011}}
The album is preceded by the first single &quot;Para Olvidarte De Mí&quot;. Though the album had no other form of promotion, since the group had already split up, to date, the album has sold 150,000 copies worldwide.

;Tournée do Adeus
On December 2, the live concert DVD, [[Tournée do Adeus]], was released, containing the group's last show in Brazil. The DVD was recorded in [[Sao Paulo]].

==Discography==
{{Main|RBD discography}}

===Spanish Albums===
*2004: ''[[Rebelde (album)|Rebelde]]''
*2005: ''[[Nuestro Amor]]''
*2006: ''[[Celestial (RBD album)|Celestial]]''
*2007: ''[[Empezar Desde Cero]]''
*2009: ''[[Para Olvidarte De Mí]]''

===Bilingual Albums===
*2005: ''[[Rebelde (Edição Brasil)|Rebelde]]
*2006: ''[[Nosso Amor Rebelde]]''
*2006: ''[[Celestial (Edição Brasil)|Celestial]]
*2006: ''[[Rebels (album)|Rebels]]''

===Live Albums===
*2005: ''[[Tour Generación RBD En Vivo]]''
*2006: ''[[Live in Hollywood (RBD album)|Live in Hollywood]]''
*2007: ''[[Hecho En España]]''

===Compilations===
*2008: ''RBD: Greatest Hits'' &lt;small&gt;(Only Mexico)&lt;/small&gt;
*2008: ''Hits Em Português'' &lt;small&gt;(Only Brazil)&lt;/small&gt;
*2008: ''Greatest Hits RBD'' &lt;small&gt;(Only E.U.A)&lt;/small&gt;

===Special Edition===
* 2006: ''Rebelde Edición Diamante'' – &lt;small&gt;(Incluye: Tracks en portugués, fotos exclusivas, juegos, wall papers y mucho más!!!)&lt;/small&gt;
* 2006: ''Tour Generación RBD En Vivo Edición Diamante'' – &lt;small&gt;(Incluye: Tracks en portugués, fotos exclusivas, juegos, wall papers y mucho más!!!)&lt;/small&gt;
* 2006: ''Nuestro Amor Edición Diamante'' – &lt;small&gt;(Incluye: Tracks en portugués, fotos exclusivas, juegos, wall papers y mucho más!!!)&lt;/small&gt;
*2007: ''[[Celestial (RBD album)#Celestial Fan Edition|Celestial Fan Edition]]'' – &lt;small&gt;CD/DVD&lt;/small&gt;
*2007: ''[[Rebels (album)|Rebels: We Are RBD]]'' – &lt;small&gt;Japanese Deluxe Edition CD/DVD&lt;/small&gt;
*2008: ''[[Empezar Desde Cero#Fan Edition|Empezar Desde Cero Fan Edition]]''

===Live DVDs===
*2005: ''[[Tour Generación RBD En Vivo]]''
*2006: ''[[Live in Hollywood (DVD)|Live In Hollywood]]''
*2007: ''[[Live in Rio (RBD DVD)|Live In Rio]]''
*2007: ''[[Hecho En España]]''
*2009: ''[[Live in Brasília|Live In Brasília]]''
*2009: ''[[Tournée do Adeus]]''

===Series===
2007: [[RBD: La Familia]]

==Tours==
===2005: ''Tour Generación RBD''===
Tour Generación RBD was RBD's first national tour. It spawned 80 sold out dates in Mexico, they visited Monterrey three times gathering over 150,000 fans. The tour was certified by OCESA as the fourth most rapidly sold tour in Mexico, behind [[The Cure]]'s 2004 Sing to the Deadly Mouse Trap Tour (#1), [[Britney Spears]]' 2002 [[Dream Within a Dream Tour]] (#2), and [[Backstreet Boys]] 2001 Black &amp; Blue Tour (#3). The tour started on May 13, 2005 in Toluca, Mexico, and ended on December 18, 2005 in Lima, Peru. The band first international concerts took place in Colombia with much success, they performed first in Medellin in front a crowd of 30,000, later in Cali in front of more than 50,000 being the group's highest attendance concert in Colombia and later in Bogota.

===2006 ''Tour Generación World 2006''===
The Tour Generación World 2006 began in the United States in March 2006, at the Los Angeles Memorial Coliseum with a crowd of more than 68,000 fans – a record-breaking act for a Latin group and a sure sign of their widespread success. 694,655 tickets were sold in 2006 accounting for North American Shows worth a total of $23,600,000  world wide tickets sells reached 749,485 they came in as the 14th top selling act of 2006 worldwide.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.pollstarpro.com/specialfeatures2006/Year%20End%20Top%20100.pdf RBD Shows]&lt;/ref&gt;
;''RBD Tour Brasil 2006''
RBD did a stadium tour through Brazil. They were the first Mexican pop group to perform in big venues such as [[Estádio do Maracanã|Maracanã]] and [[Morumbi]] which are usually used by global popstars, such as [[Madonna (entertainer)|Madonna]], [[U2]] and [[The Rolling Stones]].

===2007: ''Tour Celestial 2007''===
''[[Tour Celestial|Tour Celestial 2007]]'' is RBD's third tour where they performed in America and Europe and  South and Central America. On June 22, 2007 RBD filmed their concert in [[Madrid, Spain]](40.000+ attended the concert) for a DVD called ''[[Hecho en España (DVD)|Tour Celestial 2007: Hecho en España]]''.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.esmas.com/rbd/noticias/639662.html Noticias&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;
In early October, it was confirmed by Roptus.com that the rest of the tour would be postponed until further notice. The reason the website gave for these actions was that RBD wants to give their audience a much well deserved show by performing some songs off their new album, ''[[Empezar desde Cero]]'', which was released on November 20, 2007. RBD Grossed $5,400,000 alone on North American dates only and a combined total of 293,742 Tickets WorldWide.

===2008: ''Empezar Desde Cero World Tour 2008''===
The ''[[Empezar Desde Cero Tour 2008|Empezar Desde Cero Tour]]'' began in Hildalgo, Texas on February 2008, at the Dodge Arena. In late 2007, their Celestial Tour 2007 in U.S.A was re-scheduled until February 2008 and became part of their new tour, ''[[Empezar Desde Cero Tour 2008|Empezar Desde Cero Tour]]''. La Nueva Banda [[Timbiriche]] was their opening act in the U.S.A. The tour is taking place in the U.S.A, Mexico, Chile, Argentina, Paraguay, Brazil, Spain, Slovenia, [[Serbia]], [[Dominican Republic]], Romania, and many other countries in South America, and Europe. RBD performed in Brazil for over 500,000 people, breaking the [[Rolling Stones]]'s record. In September, they did a series of concerts in Slovenia, the first concert was sold out in only 30 minutes breaking records. Poll Star released the top 100 selling concerts for the mid year 2008
RBD came in number 49 with 166,839 Tickets sold from 1/1/08 to 6/30/08.. Third Quarter sales from Pollsatr ranked RBD at nuber 48 out of 100 with  301,015 tickets sold from 1/1/08 to 9/30/08. PollStar Year end sales from 1/01/08 to 12/31/08 showed RBD with a total of 367,346 tickets sold for 2008. RBD pulled in 4.4&amp;nbsp;million dollars worth of ticket sales in from there North American dates.

===2008–09: ''Gira Del Adiós''===
The [[Gira Del Adios World Tour|Gira Del Adiós]] was a world tour by Mexican group RBD. The tour was set to visit South America, North America and Europe and it started on November 1, 2008. The tour  ended on December 21, 2009.

On August 14, 2008 the group RBD announced its last tour, named [[Gira Del Adios World Tour|Gira Del Adiós]] or [[Gira Del Adios World Tour|Tour Del Adiós]].

The tour itinerary included about 20 cities in countries such as Argentina, Colombia, Venezuela, Ecuador, Paraguay and Chile, and Brazil.

In the month of November 2008 the group began the tour in the following cities: [[La Paz]] (Bolivia), [[Buenos Aires]], [[Córdoba, Argentina|Córdoba]] and [[Rosario]] (Argentina).

In December, RBD concerts were held in the cities of: Los Angeles (United States), [[Guayaquil]] ([[Ecuador]]), [[Quito]] ([[Ecuador]]), [[Lima]] ([[Peru]]), [[Santiago, Chile|Santiago]] ([[Chile]]), [[Ljubljana]] ([[Slovenia]]), [[Belgrade]] ([[Serbia]]), [[Madrid]] (Spain).

The last presentation of &quot;[[Gira Del Adios World Tour|Gira Del Adiós]]&quot; occurred on December 21 in [[Madrid]], as well as the final farewell of the phenomenon, RBD .

;''Turnê Do Adeus''.
In Brazil, the tour was called &quot;[[Gira Del Adios World Tour|Turnê Do Adeus]]&quot;. The first five presentations in the country were held soon after the presentations in Argentina.

As in [[Fortaleza]], [[Porto Alegre]], [[Rio de Janeiro]] with 30 000 persons and more than 25 000 in [[São Paulo]] (Where was the last recorded live DVD of the group, entitled ''&quot;[[Tournée do Adeus]].&quot;'') and [[Brasília]].

==Fundación Sálvame==
After the accident in Brazil in February 2006, the Mexican group RBD launched &quot;Fundación Sálvame&quot; (the &quot;Save Me Foundation&quot;, named after one of their songs) to help street children. It began operations on May 1, 2006, with the aim of helping street children, and among the first activities planned is a free concert in Brazil. The foundation serves Mexico, Brazil and Spain.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.surnoticias.com/modules.php?name=News&amp;file=article&amp;sid=2636 RBD crea fundación ''Salvame''] Retrieved August 12, 2009&lt;/ref&gt;

==Awards and nominations==
{{Main|RBD awards and nominations}}

==References==
{{Reflist|3}}

==External links==
{{commons}}
* [http://www.grupo-rbd.com Official Website]

{{RBD discography}}
{{Use mdy dates|date=September 2010}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Rbd}}
[[Category:RBD]]
[[Category:Musical groups established in 2004]]
[[Category:Musical groups disestablished in 2009]]
[[Category:Capitol Records artists]]
[[Category:Mexican pop music groups]]
[[Category:Mexican musical groups]]
[[Category:Mexico City musical groups]]
[[Category:Mexican dance musicians]]

[[bs:RBD]]
[[bg:RBD]]
[[ca:RBD]]
[[cs:RBD]]
[[de:RBD (Band)]]
[[et:RBD]]
[[el:RBD]]
[[es:RBD]]
[[fr:RBD]]
[[hr:RBD]]
[[it:RBD (gruppo musicale)]]
[[he:RBD]]
[[la:RBD]]
[[lt:RBD]]
[[nl:RBD]]
[[ja:RBD]]
[[no:RBD]]
[[pl:RBD]]
[[pt:RBD]]
[[ro:RBD]]
[[qu:RBD]]
[[ru:RBD]]
[[sk:RBD (skupina)]]
[[sl:RBD]]
[[sr:RBD]]
[[sh:RBD]]
[[fi:RBD]]
[[sv:RBD]]
[[uk:RBD]]
[[zh:RBD]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
