<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="19730091" ns="0" title="All Across the Havens"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Infobox Song &lt;!-- See Wikipedia:WikiProject_Songs --&gt; |
| Name        = All Across the Havens
| Type        = [[Song]] 
| Artist      = [[Elton John]]
| Album       = [[Empty Sky]] (1995 reissue)
| Cover       =  
| track_no    = 11
| Released    = January 17, 1969
| Recorded    = DJM Studios, December [[1968 in music|1968]]
| Genre       = [[Pop music|Pop]], [[Rock music|Rock]]
| Length      = 2:52
| Label       = [[DJM Records]]
| Writer      = Elton John, [[Bernie Taupin]]
| Producer    = Steve Brown
| prev           = &quot;[[Lady Samantha]]&quot;
| prev_no        = 10
| next           = &quot;[[It's Me That You Need]]&quot;
| next_no        = 12
}}
'''All Across the Havens''' is a song by [[Elton John]] with lyrics by [[Bernie Taupin]]. It was originally the b-side of his second single &quot;[[Lady Samantha]]&quot; and appeared as a bonus-track of the 1995 reissue of his first album &quot;[[Empty Sky]]&quot;.

==Musical structure==
It opens with an acoustic guitar, but when the main verse kicks in the country-feel goes off. The drums are echoed and the song is led by a [[hammond organ]]. It is also a very slow song, and as many of John's other songs at the time, it could be written in style of a [[hymn]]. It is relatively short for a John song, but not for a single b-side.

==Lyrical meaning==
This was written as early as 1967 or 1968. It clearly bares the feel of Taupin's religious childhood, using crosses hanging from people, etc. The song mentions walking across the havens to the waterfall, separating the waters and going on to a road that leads to what could be heaven. It is a very cryptic lyric in style with other of Taupin's earliest compositions.

==Performances==
It appeared on several radio shows in 1968. Released as the b-side to a single that didn't even hit the charts the song was very unpopular and not known at all. Today it is still relatively unknown, not being performed anywhere else.

==Personnel==
*Elton John - [[hammond organ]], [[grand piano]], vocals
*[[Caleb Quaye]] - [[Acoustic guitar|guitar]]
*Tony Murray - [[Bass guitar|bass]]
*Roger Pope - [[Drum kit|drums]]

[[Category:1969 songs]]
[[Category:Elton John songs]]
[[Category:Songs with lyrics by Bernie Taupin]]
[[Category:Songs with music by Elton John]]

[[it:All Across the Havens]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
