<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="198155" ns="0" title="Wackenhut"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{for|the prison company formerly known as Wackenhut Corrections Corporation|GEO Group}}
{{Multiple issues|refimprove=April 2010
|original research=March 2009
|synthesis=March 2009
}}
{{Infobox Company
| company_name    = G4S Secure Solutions (USA)
| company_logo    = [[Image:G4S.svg|150px]]
| company_type    = [[Subsidiary]]
| parent          = [[G4S]]
| foundation      = [[1954]], [[Coral Gables, Florida]]
| key_people      = [[George Wackenhut]] &lt;small&gt;([[Entrepreneur|Founder]])&lt;/small&gt;
| location        = [[Jupiter, Florida]], [[United States]]
| industry        = [[Security]]|
| homepage        = [http://www.g4s.com/us www.g4s.com/us]
}}

'''G4S Secure Solutions (USA)''' is a [[private security company]].  It was founded as The Wackenhut Corporation in 1954, in [[Coral Gables, Florida]], by [[George Wackenhut]] and three partners (all former [[FBI]] agents). 

In 2002 the company was acquired for $570 million by [[Denmark|Danish]] corporation [[Group 4 Falck]] (itself then merged to form [[United Kingdom|British]] company [[G4S]] in 2004).&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
|url =http://articles.sun-sentinel.com/2002-03-09/business/0203081071_1_falck-george-wackenhut-security-firm
|title =Danish Firm Agrees To Buy Wackenhut: $570m Deal Ends S. Florida Family's Control
|date =2002-03-09
|accessdate =2010-04-20
|publisher =Sun Sentinel
}}&lt;/ref&gt; In 2010, G4S Wackenhut changed its name to G4S Secure Solutions (USA) to reflect the new business model.&lt;ref name=&quot;Chunovic&quot;&gt;{{cite web
|url =http://www.gsnmagazine.com/article/20448/g4s_wackenhut_rebrands_g4s
|title =G4S Wackenhut rebrands as G4S
|last =Chunovic
|first =Louis
|date =2010-04-07
|accessdate =2010-04-19
|publisher =Government Security News
}}&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;ref name=&quot;Government Security News&quot;&gt;{{cite web
|url =http://www.gsnmagazine.com/videos/20082/g4s_wackenhut
|title =G4S Wackenhut President Drew Levine Explains Rebrand and Company Strategy
|date =2010-01-18
|accessdate =2010-04-19
|publisher =Government Security News
}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The [[G4S]] Americas Region headquarters is in [[Jupiter, Florida]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.g4s.us/en-us/Site%20Tools/Contact%20us/ Contact Us].&quot; Wackenhut. Retrieved on July 6, 2010.&lt;/ref&gt; &lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
|url =http://www.palmbeachpost.com/money/wackenhut-planning-new-corporate-headquarters-in-jupiter-18327.html
|title =Wackenhut planning new corporate headquarters in Jupiter
|date =2009-10-15
|accessdate =2010-04-19
|publisher =Palm Beach Post
}}&lt;/ref&gt;



==Background==

After early struggles (including a fistfight between George Wackenhut and one of his partners),  Wackenhut took sole control of his company in 1958 then, naming it after himself. Working throughout the day in his office, he sometimes continued nightly as a [[security guard]]. By 1964, he had contracts to guard the [[Kennedy Space Center]] and the [[United States Atomic Energy Commission|U.S. Atomic Energy Commission]]'s [[nuclear test site]] in [[Nevada]]. The following year, he took his company [[initial public offering|public]].

In the mid-60s, Florida Governor [[Claude Kirk]] commissioned the Wackenhut Corporation to help fight a &quot;war on organized crime&quot;, awarding the company a $500,000 contract.  The commission lasted about a year but led to more than 80 criminal indictments, including many for local politicians and government employees.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal
|author=Fisk, Kiesling, Herbert Kiesling, and Thomas Muller
|year=1978
|pages=34
|title=Private Provision of Public Services: An Overview
|publisher=Urban Institute
}}&lt;/ref&gt; Following the murder of a British tourist at a rest stop in 1993, Florida contracted with Wackenhut to provide security at all state rest stops.

==Security Services | Security Company ==

Services by security companies typically include: permanent guarding service, security officers, manned security, disaster response, emergency services, control room monitoring, armed security, unarmed security, special event security, security patrols, reception/concierge service, access control, emergency medical technicians (EMT) service, ambassador service.

Like other security companies, G4S targets sectors: Energy, Utilities, and Chemical/Petrochemical, Financial Institutions, Government, Hospitals and Healthcare Facilities, Major Corporates, Industrials &amp; Construction,  Ports and Airports, Residential Communities, Retail and Commercial Real Estate, Transit Systems

Clients include: GSK&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
|url =http://www.ft.com/cms/s/0/0cfbec10-3ab7-11df-b6d5-00144feabdc0,s01=1.html
|title =G4S wins £85m multinational security contract
|date =2010-03-29
|accessdate =2010-04-19
|publisher =The Financial Times
}}&lt;/ref&gt; and U.S. Customs and Border Protection&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
|url =http://www.cbp.gov/xp/cgov/newsroom/news_releases/archives/2007_news_releases/102007/10042007_2.xml
|title =CBP Renews Southwest Border Transportation Contract
|date =2007-10-04
|accessdate =2010-04-19
|publisher =CBP.gov
}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==G4S Acquisitions in the U.S.==

AMAG Technology, Touchcom Inc., Adesta, and Nuclear Security Services Corp. (NSSC)&lt;ref name=&quot;Chunovic&quot;/&gt;

==Wackenhut Corrections Becomes GEO Group (2003)==

Having expanded into providing [[food service]]s for U.S. [[prisons]] in the 1960s, Wackenhut in 1984 launched a subsidiary  to design and manage [[Prison|jail]]s and [[detention center]]s for the burgeoning [[private prison]] market. Wackenhut then became the nation's second largest for-profit prison operator.

In April 1999, the state of Louisiana took over the running of Wackenhut's 15-month-old [[juvenile prison]] after the [[U.S. Justice Department]] accused Wackenhut of subjecting its young inmates to &quot;excessive abuse and neglect.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;DOJ&quot;&gt;{{cite web
|url=http://www.justice.gov/crt/split/documents/la_summa.php
|title=RESPONSE OF THE UNITED STATES TO THE COURT'S ORDER OF NOVEMBER 6, 1998
|author=DOJ
|date=1998-11-06
|accessdate=2010-04-02
}}&lt;/ref&gt; U.S. journalist [[Gregory Palast]] commented on the case: &quot;New Mexico's privately operated prisons are filled with America's impoverished, violent outcasts — and those are the guards.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;palast&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.corpwatch.org/article.php?id=868 |title=Wackenhut's Free Market in Human Misery |author=Greg Palast |date=1999-09-26 |accessdate=2009-03-10}}&lt;/ref&gt; He catalogued lax [[background check]]s before hiring guards, which led to several alleged cases of guards physically and sexually abusing inmates. In the U.S., Wackenhut has appeared in the [[United States federal courts|federal courts]] 62 times since 1999, largely resulting from prisoners' claims of [[human rights]] abuses.&lt;ref name=&quot;palast&quot;/&gt; The company has been accused of trying to maximise profits in its private prisons at the expense of [[drug rehabilitation]], counselling and literacy programs. In 1995 Wackenhut was investigated for diverting $700,000 intended for drug treatment programs at a Texas prison.

The [[GEO Group]], Inc. now runs former Wackenhut facilities in 14 states, as well as in [[South Africa]] and Australia.  Some facilities, such as the Wackenhut Corrections Centers in New York, retain the Wackenhut name despite no longer having any open connection with the company.

In 2003, GEO Group changed from a corporate subsidy (WCC) into a fully independent company from Wackenhut.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
|url =http://www.thegeogroupinc.com/history.asp
|title =Officially changes name to The GEO Group, Inc.
|date =2003-01-04
|accessdate =2010-04-19
|publisher =GEO Group
}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Nuclear Services at Peach Bottom (2008)==

The Wackenhut Corporation provided armed security services for many nuclear power plants. In September 2007, former employee [[Kerry Beal and Paul A. Kennedy]] videotaped fellow security guards at the [[Peach Bottom Nuclear Generating Station]] sleeping while on duty. Beal had previously tried to notify supervisors at Wackenhut and the US [[Nuclear Regulatory Commission]]. Wackenhut was fired from its role guarding Peach Bottom and nine other nuclear plants.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
|url =http://www.washingtonpost.com/wp-dyn/content/article/2008/01/03/AR2008010304442.html?sub=AR
|title =Video of Sleeping Guards Shakes Nuclear Industry
|last =Mufson
|first =Steven
|date =2008-01-04
|accessdate =2008-12-19
|publisher =Washington Post
|pages =A01
}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Murder of Janet Chandler (1979)==
	 
In 1979, hotel clerk and [[Hope College]] senior [[Janet Chandler]] was found dead in a snowbank along [[Interstate 196]] near [[Holland, Michigan]]. She had been raped. Initially treated as a robbery, the case remained [[cold case (criminology)|unsolved]] until a group of Hope students produced a documentary that uncovered a sex and drugs party atmosphere at the hotel, which had been occupied by dozens of Wackenhut security guards (assigned to protect the facilities of local manufacturer Chemtron during a bitter strike). The documentary prompted a reopening of the case, and arrests of six security guards and a hotel supervisor who was Chandler's roommate. In November 2007, two individuals plead guilty to charges, and the remaining four then-guards were additionally found guilty of her murder.[http://www.cbsnews.com/stories/2007/11/02/national/main3446980.shtml]

==Rumors About Wackenhut and the CIA==

Frequent rumors that his company was in the employ of the [[Central Intelligence Agency]], particularly in the 1960s, were never substantiated, but Wackenhut, who was obsessive about high-tech security gadgets in his private life, did not discourage the suggestion. In 1991, a [[U.S. House of Representatives]] committee investigated charges that a Wackenhut executive, working for a [[consortium]] of oil companies, illegally spied on a [[whistleblower]], former independent oil executive [[Chuck Hamel]], exposing environmental damage caused by the [[Exxon Valdez oil spill]].&lt;ref name=&quot;O'Don&quot;&gt;{{cite web
|url=http://www.xs4all.nl/~evel/n5m/sheilatxt.html
|title=Violence against campaigners
|last=O'Donnell
|first=Sheila
|publisher=N5M Conference
|date=March 1999
|accessdate=2008-12-11
|pages=
}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Prop1&quot;&gt;{{cite web
|url=http://www.prop1.org/legal/prisons/9111wack.htm
|title=Wackenhut Oversight Hearings
|last=House Interior and Insular Affairs Committee
|first=
|publisher=Proposition 1
|date=November 4, 1991
|accessdate=2010-12-18
|pages=
}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Wackenhut and Miami-Dade==

A dispute between Wackenhut and Miami-Dade Transit arose from allegations made by a former employee, who claimed that G4S Wackenhut over-billed Miami-Dade County for work not performed. As a result of the allegations of that lawsuit, the County ordered an audit of the contract in 2005. That audit was completed in 2009 and came up with an amount of estimated overbillings. In response, G4S Wackenhut filed a lawsuit in federal court alleging, among other things, that the audit’s findings were erroneous.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
|url =http://www.miaminewtimes.com/2009-05-07/news/wackenhut-stands-up-to-miami-dade/
|title =Wackenhut Stands up to Miami-Dade: Security firm denies ripping off the county and fires back with a $20 million lawsuit.
|date =2010-05-07
|accessdate =2010-04-20
|publisher =Miami New Times
}}&lt;/ref&gt;
In February 2010 the issue was resolved. Miami-Dade County commissioners approved a $7.5 million settlement agreement with Wackenhut Corp. to resolve the dispute. As part of the deal, Wackenhut can bid on future contracts and the county won’t use this case against it when considering Wackenhut’s bids.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
|url =http://southflorida.bizjournals.com/southflorida/stories/2010/02/15/daily47.html
|title =Wackenhut, Miami-Dade settle legal battle
|date =2010-02-18
|accessdate =2010-04-20
|publisher =South Florida Business Journal
}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Google==

G4S Wackenhut staff can be seen working for Google in a video produced by Google and distributed by the Official Google Enterprise Blog.
[http://www.youtube.com/watch?feature=player_embedded&amp;v=1SCZzgfdTBo]

==See also==

*[[G4S]]
*[[G4S Technology]]
*[[Private security companies]]
*[[Wackenhut Services, Inc.|WSI]]&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.stability-operations.org/index.php &quot;Current Members: WSI&quot;], [[International Peace Operations Association|International Stability Operations Association]] webpage. Retrieved 2011-08-05.&lt;/ref&gt;
*[[GEO Group]]
*[[Correctional Services Corporation]]
*[[Private prison]]

==References==

&lt;references/&gt;

==Further reading==
* [http://www.gsnmagazine.com/article/20448/g4s_wackenhut_rebrands_g4s G4S Wackenhut rebrands as G4S]
* [http://www.gsnmagazine.com/article/19793/g4s_wackenhut_pursues_bold_new_business_strategy G4S Wackenhut pursues a bold new business strategy]
* Minahan, John. The Quiet American: A Biography of George R. Wackenhut. International Publishing Group (September 1994) ISBN 0-9639395-0-5
* Palast, Greg (2002). ''[[The Best Democracy Money Can Buy|The Best Democracy Money Can Buy: The Truth About Corporate Cons, Globalization and High-Finance Fraudsters]].'' Pluto Press. ISBN 0-7453-1846-0.
* [http://www.blogofdeath.com/archives/001280.html Obituary of George Wackenhut from Blog of Death]
* [http://www.washingtonpost.com/wp-dyn/articles/A54899-2005Jan6.html Obituary of George Wackenhut from the Washington Post]
* [http://www.greenleft.org.au/back/2001/450/450p15.htm Wackenhut: Prisons, profits and golf umbrellas]
* [http://www.washingtonpost.com/wp-dyn/content/article/2008/01/03/AR2008010304442.html?sub=AR Video of Sleeping Guards Shakes Nuclear Industry]
* [http://www.securitydirectornews.com/?p=article&amp;id=sd200906rKDALW Wackenhut security officer dies 'heroically' at Holocaust Museum]
* [http://islamabad.usembassy.gov/pr-10041301.html U.S. Mission acknowledges the heroic actions of G4S Wackenhut personnel in Pakistan]
* [http://www.palmbeachpost.com/money/wackenhut-planning-new-corporate-headquarters-in-jupiter-18327.html Wackenhut planning new corporate headquarters in Jupiter]
* [http://www.gsnmagazine.com/videos/20082/g4s_wackenhut G4S Wackenhut President Drew Levine Interviewed By Government Security News]
* [http://www.ft.com/cms/s/0/f321ae84-3ac9-11df-b6d5-00144feabdc0.html G4S wins £85m multinational security contract]

==External links==
{{Portalbox|Miami|Companies}}
* [http://www.g4s.com/us Official website]
* [http://www.g4s.com Parent official website]

[[Category:Companies based in Florida]]
[[Category:Security companies]]
[[Category:Companies established in 1954]]

[[es: Wackenhut]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
