<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="1981296" ns="0" title="Kiwi FM"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Use dmy dates|date=September 2011}}
{{Unreferenced|date=October 2007}}
{{Infobox Radio Station 
| image     = [[File:KiwiFM.PNG]]
| name      = Kiwi FM 
| airdate   = [[2005 in radio|2005]]
| area      = 3 Markets in [[New Zealand]]
| frequency = 102.2 Akl, 102.1 Wltn, 102.5 Chc
| format    = [[New Zealand Music]] 
| owner     = [[MediaWorks New Zealand]] 
| slogan    = &quot;New Zealand's Global Radio Station&quot;
| webcast   = [http://streaming.mediaworks.co.nz/kiwifmakl Dialup]&lt;br&gt;[http://streaming.mediaworks.co.nz/kiwifmakl_high Broadband]
|}}
'''Kiwi FM''' is a [[New Zealand]] Radio Network playing 100 percent New Zealand music both nationally and to the world via its 24/7 live stream. The network was designed specifically to showcase the best New Zealand music across the broadest range of genres, enabling greater access to an international market for local, contemporary artists. The station broadcasts in [[Auckland]], Wellington and Christchurch on FM frequencies, nationwide on SkyTV Channel 500, and globally through its [http://www.kiwifm.co.nz internet stream]. Kiwi FM is operated by Kiwi Radio Ltd, a non-profit subsidiary of [[MediaWorks New Zealand]]. 

== History ==
The station Kiwi FM was launched on Waitangi Day, 6 February 2005 and was opened with a speech by Prime Minister Helen Clark. It was made to replace a much loved brand 'channel Z' which had failed to deliver on its ratings. 

The initial station ran for around a year and was rebranded in July 2006 when legendary New Zealand music journalist Karyn Hay stepped in as General Manager with Andrew Fagan as music director.
On 1 May 2006, the New Zealand Government granted Kiwi FM access to new FM frequencies, under an agreement that kept the 100 percent Kiwi music station on the airwaves. Broadcasting Minister Steve Maharey said the station had been granted the use of three FM frequencies for an initial period of one year, during which time it would work towards becoming a not-for-profit organisation. As part of the agreement to use the frequencies, the station's brief will be to significantly expand its content to include a greater range of New Zealand Music. 

Kiwi FM was relaunched under one of the most innovative broadcasting models in New Zealand history - ostensibly a partnership between Government Ministries of Broadcasting and Economic Development, and listed media company [[Canwest]] [[Mediaworks]]. The new network was designed and implemented in less than three months, launching on 17 July 2006 with a number of respected staff members - including [[Opshop]] frontman Jason Kerrison, The Twitch lead vocalist Fleur Jack, former Student radio breakfast hosts Wallace Chapman and Glenn 'Wammo' Williams, actress Danielle Cormack, [[Blindspott]] frontman Damian Alexander, The Bads' vocalist Dianne Swann, and former Mockers and Lig frontman (And Kiwi FM Music Director) Andrew Fagan - all under the guidance of network GM Karyn Hay.

Currently (August 2011) the station is run by three people, Sam Collins as operations manager, Glenn 'Wammo' Williams as the breakfast host and Auckland musician Fleur Jack.
The best way to find out about Kiwi Fm promotions is on the website www.kiwifm.co.nz

== Future ==
Kiwi FM aims to be key figure in furthering New Zealand's international music success. The network has attracted a local and international audience with its playlist. There are more than a dozen specialist shows, concentrating on genres that reach large audiences globally,{{Fact|date=December 2008}} but have found limited success at home. 

Kiwi FM continues to utilise new digital media to archive and catalogue shows of importance to international audiences and has recently been seconded to produce NZ-specific shows for internationally syndicated radio show Passport Approved.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.passportapproved.com/about.php Passport Approved works with DJs and radio stations from around the world, including Kiwi FM]&lt;/ref&gt;

Kiwi FM's weekly top 10 has led to more airplay for many New Zealand bands and musicians, and its focus on independent labels has allowed the network to enjoy the support of New Zealand's independent music scene.

==Ratings==
One year after launching Kiwi FM reported to have around 43,000 listeners across all markets [http://www.radioscope.net.nz/index.php?option=com_content&amp;task=view&amp;id=27&amp;Itemid=39 ] in the April 2006 Research International Survey. Kiwi FM did not participate in the October 2006 survey and the April 2007 survey was cancelled. In the April 2008 survey Kiwi had 20,000 listeners and 0.1% of the market share. [http://www.radioscope.net.nz/index.php?option=com_content&amp;task=view&amp;id=1121&amp;Itemid=39]

==Other Kiwi FM==
In 1988 in the [[Waikato]] and [[Bay of Plenty]] a local station called [[898 FM]] was renamed to Kiwi FM broadcasting on 89.8 FM. The Kiwi FM station played Hit Music similar to [[Magic 91FM]] in Auckland and [[ZM (New Zealand)|ZM]]. In 1993 Kiwi FM was rebranded as The Breeze but this station was completely separate to the current The Breeze station both in the Waikato and even the original The Breeze station in Wellington, a similar station was launched in Auckland replacing Magic 91FM. In 1997 this frequency was taken over by [[The Radio Network]] and used to launch [[ZM (New Zealand)|ZM]] into the Waikato and Bay of Plenty.

In [[Te Puke]] a local station called [[92.9 KIWI]] operates, this station is independently owned and operated and has been on air longer than the Kiwi FM network stations.

== Frequencies ==
* Auckland - 102.2FM
* Wellington - 102.1FM
* Christchurch 102.5FM
* www.kiwifm.co.nz

==References==
{{reflist|2}}

==External links==
* [http://www.kiwifm.co.nz/ Kiwi FM Official Website]
* [http://www.mediaworks.co.nz/Default.aspx?tabid=98 RadioWorks Information Site About Kiwi FM]
* [http://www.sealion.co.nz/index.php Kiwi Sealion-Information Site About Kiwi Music]
* &quot;Job loss&quot;- information from NZMUSICIAN Magazine;Article-Out on the street.October November 2008 (see also at [http://www.nzmusician.co.nz]

{{MediaWorks (New Zealand)}}
{{New Zealand radio networks}}

{{coord missing|New Zealand}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Kiwi Fm}}
[[Category:Radio stations in New Zealand]]
[[Category:New Zealand radio networks]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
