<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="1982458" ns="0" title="Linux on Power"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Technical|date=April 2009}}
'''Linux on Power''' is the combination of any [[Linux]]-based [[operating system]] running on [[Power Architecture]] technology, a [[microprocessor]] architecture.

==Introduction==
Power Architecture is one of the many architectures the [[Linux kernel]] has been compiled to run on allowing computers such as [[PowerPC]]-based [[Power Macintosh]] computers originally designed to run [[Mac OS]] to use [[Linux|GNU/Linux]] distributions such as [[Debian]].

[[IBM]] supports Linux on Power with its line of Power servers, which has gone through an evolution of names; ''e''Server [[IBM System p|p5]] series, [[RS/6000]], P Series, System P, and as of April 2008, IBM Power Systems. Linux releases that run on this type of hardware are a [[ppc64]] Linux port compiled to run on [[IBM]] [[IBM POWER|POWER]] based servers.

Since the release of ''e''Server p5 series and the Linux 2.6 kernel, many Linux distributions can take advantage of POWER hardware features such as [[LPAR|logical partitioning]], [[Micro-Partitioning]] and [[Run-Time Abstraction Services|RTAS]]. IBM at one time offered an entry/midrange line of servers called [[IBM OpenPower|OpenPower]] which only run Linux, as opposed to other POWER-based servers that can also run the [[IBM AIX|AIX operating system]].

==Virtualization on Power6 and OpenPower==
[[POWER6]] based IBM systems have built in [[Full virtualization|virtualization]] capabilities derived from [[Mainframe computer|mainframe]] technology. On System P, this virtualization package is referred to as PowerVM. There is an additional layer between hardware and operating systems which is called the [[hypervisor]]. IBM Power6 systems support up to 256 logical partitions on one machine, with a maximum of 10 per processor. These micropartitions can run in a shared processor pool and utilize automatic [[load balancing (computing)|load balancing]].

The hypervisor also allows the assignment of virtual I/O and network adapters to logical partitions.

*The hypervisor acts as a virtual switch for internal network connectivity. This allows for network communication between the LPARs to be direct (memory to memory) and not have to leave the physical machine. A dedicated virtual I/O server (VIO) partition (running a [[Linux]] or [[IBM AIX|AIX]]-based system) can act as a network bridge between the internal VLAN, on which the VIO server is connected, to a physical external network.
*[[SCSI]] virtualization is implemented via virtual SCSI device assignment from the VIO to the client [[LPAR]]. The VIO server has the physical storage; parts of that storage (whole disks, logical volumes or partitions) are shared to the clients through a VSCSI server to VSCSI client relationship.

Any [[SUSE Linux distributions]] or [[Debian]] installation with real resources assigned can be used as a virtual I/O server. There are only two kernel modules, ibmvscsis and ibmveth, that need to be loaded to provide this functionality. Both modules are licensed under the [[GNU General Public License|GPL]] and part of the distribution kernel.

For dynamic LPAR changes on the fly (for example, adding CPU or memory, or removing a PCI adapter), some [http://www14.software.ibm.com/webapp/set2/sas/f/lopdiags lopdiags additional packages] are needed for RSCT (Reliable Scalable Cluster Technology) communication with the HMC (Hardware Management Console). Those packages are provided from IBM in [[RPM Package Manager|RPM]] format but not in source code. After installing these packages, dynamic reconfiguration of CPU and hotpluggable PCI adapters can be done without rebooting the operating system. Reducing the memory amount assigned to the logical partition still requires reboot of the target LPAR.

==Pricing and costs==
The two largest commercial Linux vendors, [[Red Hat]] and [[Novell]], offer licensing and support based on a &quot;per physical machine&quot; system for System P servers. Cost is not based on number of processors installed, which is different from pricing on IBM's [[IBM System z9|System Z]] servers, where licensing and support is based on the number of [[Integrated Facility for Linux|IFL]]s.  Purchasing higher model numbered servers, such as a p570 or p590, allows for a smaller monetary investment but yet leaves room for more physical expansion if capacity exceeds the original investment. Each LPAR on a System P machine can be as small as 0.1 processors. This allows the total number of LPARs on a physical machine to go as high as 10 times the number of physical processors. A higher number of logical servers reduces the &quot;per-server&quot; cost.

==Systems==
{{out of date|section|date=April 2009}}
Systems running Linux on [[Power Architecture]] are:
*[[IBM Power Systems|IBM POWER Systems]]
*JS43, JS23, JS20, JS21, QS20, QS21, QS22 [[Blade server|Blade]] Center
*[[IBM OpenPower|OpenPower]]
*[[Cell (microprocessor)|Cell]] blade server from [[Mercury Computer Systems]]
*[[PlayStation 3]]

==Linux distributions==
===Officially supported distributions===
*For IBM System p and i – [[SUSE Linux distributions|SUSE]] SLES8, SLES9, SLES10 and SLES11{{Citation needed|date=September 2007}}
*For IBM System p and i –  [[Red Hat]] EL AS 3, 4 and 5{{Citation needed|date=September 2007}}

===Working distributions===
*[[CRUX#CRUX PPC|CRUX PPC]]
*[[Debian]]
*[[Fedora (operating system)|Fedora Core]]
*[[Gentoo Linux|Gentoo]]
*[[openSUSE]]
*[[Ubuntu (operating system)|Ubuntu]]

==See also==
*[[Linux on zSeries]]
*[[Linux on the PlayStation 3]]

==External links==
* [https://www.ibm.com/developerworks/mydeveloperworks/groups/service/html/communityview?communityUuid=fe313521-2e95-46f2-817d-44a4f27eba32 IBM developerWorks &quot;Think Power Linux&quot; Community site ]

[[Category:Linux]]
[[Category:Power Architecture]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
