<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="1988447" ns="0" title="Free Patriotic Movement"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{refimprove|date=November 2011}}
{{Infobox political party
| colorcode        = orange
| party_name       = Free Patriotic Movement
| native_name      = التيار الوطني الحر
| party_logo       = [[File:Mpllibano.png|200px|centre|]]
| leader           = [[Michel Aoun]]
| foundation       = Founded in 2003, officially declared in 2005
| ideology         = [[Centrism]]
| position         = [[Centre]]
| country          = Lebanon
| religion         = [[Secular]]
| headquarters     = {{flagicon|Lebanon}} Rabieh&amp;nbsp;— Beirut, [[Lebanon]]
| youth_wing       = FPM Youth and Students Commitee
|  
|seats1_title      = [[Parliament of Lebanon]]
|seats1            = {{Infobox political party/seats|19|128|hex=#ffa500}}
|seats2_title      = [[Lebanese government of June 2011|Cabinet of Lebanon]]
|seats2            = {{Infobox political party/seats|7|30|hex=#ffa500}}
| website          = http://www.tayyar.org
}}

The '''Free Patriotic Movement''' (FPM) ([[Arabic language|Arabic]]: التيار الوطني الحر, ''Al-Tayyar Al-Watani Al-Hur''), also known as the &quot;Aounist Movement&quot; (Arabic: التيار العوني, ''Tayyar Al-Aouni''), is a [[Lebanon|Lebanese]] [[List of political parties in Lebanon|political party]], led by [[Michel Aoun]] and allied with Hezbollah,  The movement was officially declared a political party on September 18, 2005

Though most of the party's support comes from Lebanon's [[Christian]] community, it also enjoys minor support from some [[Shia Muslims]]. The FPM party advocates secularism and the right to vote for Lebanese abroad. It is one of the allies of [[Hezbollah]].

==Aoun return from Exile==
For many years, while Aoun was [[exile]]d in [[Paris]], he led the FPM from abroad.  He returned to Lebanon on May 7, 2005 after the [[Cedar Revolution]] forced the withdrawal of the Syrian forces, and then contested the [[Elections in Lebanon|legislative elections]] held in late May in early June although it placed him on the head of the largest Christian group of deputies.

Aoun also contested the [[Cedar Revolution]] which itself gave him the opportunity to come back to [[Lebanon]].

==2005 Elections and rise of the FPM==

At the time of the 2005 elections, the FPM came up with a detailed political program which contained economic and political reform plans and gained the support of many Lebanese Christians.

The FPM won 21 seats in the parliament, and formed the second biggest bloc in the Lebanese Parliament.

==Memorandum of Understanding between the FPM and Hezbollah==
In 2006, the FPM signed a memorandum of understanding with Hezbollah organizing their relation and discussing Hezbollah's disarmament, given some conditions. The second and third conditions for disarmament were the return of Lebanese prisoners from Israeli jails and the elaboration of a defense strategy to protect Lebanon from the Israeli threat.  The agreement also discussed the importance of having normal diplomatic relations with [[Syria]] and the request for information about the Lebanese political prisoners in [[Syria]] and the return of all political prisoners and diaspora in [[Israel]].

==2006 Lebanese Anti-Government Protest==
{{main|2006 Lebanese Anti-Government Protest}}
On December 1, 2006, Free Patriotic Movement leader Michel Aoun declared to a crowd of protesters that the current government of Lebanon was unconstitutional, claiming that the government  had &quot;made corruption a daily affair&quot; and called for the resignation on the government.&lt;ref&gt;[http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/middle_east/6197992.stm Huge Beirut rally demands change], [[BBC]], 1 December 2006&lt;/ref&gt; Hundred of thousands of supporters of this party, [[Amal Movement]], and [[Hezbollah]], according to the Internal Security Forces (ISF), gathered at Downtown Beirut trying to force [[Fouad Siniora]] to abdicate.

==2008 Government formation==
On July 11, 2008, FPM members, [[Issam Abu Jamra]] as Deputy-Prime Minister, [[Gebran Bassil]] as Minister of Telecommunications, and [[Mario Aoun]] as Minister of Social Affairs were elected into government. It is the Movement's first participation in any Lebanese Government.

==2009 Elections==
{{Main|Lebanese general election, 2009}}

Despite the strong media and political war against the Free Patriotic Movement, the results of the [[Lebanese general election, 2009|2009 Elections]] granted the FPM 27 parliamentary seats. These results showed dis-improvement within the Christian votes, but despite this the FPM's bloc is the second largest in the Lebanese parliament. Based on statistics,FPM has lost about 25% of his popularity within the Christian vote in order to spread throughout the country at various ethnic groups of the Lebanese people
. He know only represents around 53% of Christians. The FPM gained 7 more seats then the [[Lebanese general election, 2005|2005 elections]], earning at least triple the number of deputies of any other Christian-based bloc in the parliament due to geographical distribution. The total seats won were 57 out of 128, which led to a defeat for the FPM.

==2009 Government formation==
In November 2009, the Free Patriotic Movement nominated five ministers to join the first government headed by [[Saad Hariri]].  The five ministers included:

*[[Gebran Bassil]] as Minister of Power
*[[Charbel Nahas]] as Minister of Telecommunications
*[[Youssef Saade]] as Minister of State
*[[Abraham Dadayan]] as Minister of Industry
*[[Fadi Aboud]] as Minister of Tourism

==OTV==
{{main|OTV (Lebanon)}}
The Free Patriotic Movement launched its own broadcasting channel (OTV) on the 20th of July 2007, and their own radio station called Sawt Al Mada (voice of scope in English)  on June 1, 2009.

==2011 Government formation==
In June 2011, the [[Change and Reform bloc]] led by Aoun nominated eleven ministers to join the second government headed by [[Najib Mikati]], gaining more than double the share they had in the former government
The eleven ministers are:

'''Ministers with Portfolios:'''
*[[Shakib Kortbawi]] as Minister of Justice
*[[Fayez Ghosn]] as Minister of Defense
*[[Gebran Bassil]] as Minister of Energy
*[[Nicolas Sehnaoui]] as Minister of [[Telecommunications]]
*[[Vrej Sabounjian]] as Minister of [[Industry]]
*[[Fadi Aboud]] as Minister of [[Tourism]]
*[[Charbel Nahas]] as Minister of [[Labour relations|Labour]]
*[[Gaby Layoun]] as Minister of Culture

*[[Marwan Charbel]] as Minister of Interior and Municipalities (merge power between Aoun and [[Michel Suleiman]])

'''Ministers without Portfolios:'''
*[[Salim Karam]]
*[[Panos Manjian]]
*[[Marwan Kheiredine]]

==Notes==
{{reflist|2}}

==External links==
* [http://www.tayyar.org/ Free Patriotic Movement - official website]
* [http://forum.tayyar.org/  Free Patriotic Movement Message Boards (Official Forum)]
* [http://www.flf-tayyar.de/ FLF in Germany: Freiheitlichen Libanesischen Freundeskreis e.V.] German version of the FPM website.
* [http://rplfrance.org/ CPL en France : Rassemblement pour le Liban]
* [http://mplbelgique.org/ CPL en Belgique : Mouvement pour le Liban]
* [http://www.tayyar.org/elections/political_program_fr/data/downloads/programanglica.pdf FPM political platform (in English)]
* [http://www.mideastmonitor.org/issues/0602/0602_3.htm Memorandum of Joint Understanding between Hezbollah and the Free Patriotic Movement]
* [http://www.voltairenet.org/article163915.html Charter of the Free Patriotic Movement Party]

{{Lebanese political parties}}


[[Category:Political parties in Lebanon]]
[[Category:Political parties established in 2003]]

[[ar:التيار الوطني الحر]]
[[de:Freie Patriotische Bewegung]]
[[es:Movimiento Patriótico Libre]]
[[fr:Courant patriotique libre]]
[[he:הזרם הפטריוטי החופשי]]
[[pl:Wolny Ruch Patriotyczny]]
[[uk:Вільна національна течія Лівану]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
