<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="199106" ns="0" title="USS Abraham Lincoln (CVN-72)"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Other ships|USS Abraham Lincoln}}
{{Lead too short|date=September 2008}}
{{refimprove|date=July 2011}}
{|{{Infobox ship begin}}
{{Infobox ship image
|Ship image=[[Image:USS Abraham Lincoln(CVN 72).jpg|300px|USS Abraham Lincoln, supporting Operation Southern Watch, 28 November 2002]]
|Ship caption=USS ''Abraham Lincoln'' underway, with support aircraft overhead, in the Western Pacific Ocean, 8 May 2006
}}
{{Infobox ship career
|Hide header=
|Ship country=United States
|Ship flag={{USN flag}}
|Ship name=USS ''Abraham Lincoln''
|Ship namesake=[[Abraham Lincoln]]
|Ship owner=
|Ship operator=
|Ship registry=
|Ship route=
|Ship ordered=27 December 1982
|Ship awarded=
|Ship builder=[[Newport News Shipbuilding]] Co.
|Ship original cost=
|Ship yard number=
|Ship way number=
|Ship laid down=3 November 1984
|Ship launched=13 February 1988
|Ship sponsor=
|Ship christened=13 February 1988
|Ship completed=
|Ship acquired=
|Ship commissioned=11 November 1989
|Ship recommissioned=
|Ship decommissioned=
|Ship maiden voyage=
|Ship in service=
|Ship out of service=
|Ship renamed=
|Ship reclassified=
|Ship refit=
|Ship struck=
|Ship reinstated=
|Ship homeport=[[Naval Station Everett|NS Everett]], [[Washington (U.S. state)|Washington]]
|Ship identification=
|Ship motto=''Shall not Perish''
|Ship nickname=''Abe''
|Ship honors=
|Ship captured=
|Ship fate=
|Ship status={{Ship in active service}}
|Ship notes=
|Ship badge=[[Image:Cvn72 badge.jpg|100px]]
}}
{{Infobox ship characteristics
|Hide header=
|Header caption=
|Ship class={{Sclass|Nimitz|aircraft carrier}}
|Ship type=
|Ship tonnage=
|Ship displacement= {{convert|100000|LT|ST}}&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|title=The Naval Institute guide to the ships and aircraft of the U.S. fleet |last=Polmar |first=Norman |authorlink= |coauthors= |year=2004 |publisher=[[Naval Institute Press]] |location= |isbn=978-1591146858 |page=112 |pages= |url=http://books.google.co.uk/books?id=8MwyTX-iA2wC&amp;pg=PA112&amp;dq=nimitz+class+displacement&amp;hl=en&amp;ei=7DD0S-W8BYSdlgeRrNDuDA&amp;sa=X&amp;oi=book_result&amp;ct=result&amp;resnum=2&amp;ved=0CC4Q6AEwAQ#v=onepage&amp;q=nimitz%20class%20displacement&amp;f=false |accessdate=}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|Ship tons burthen=
|Ship length={{Nimitz class aircraft carrier length}}
|Ship beam={{Nimitz class aircraft carrier beam}}
|Ship height=
|Ship draft={{Nimitz class aircraft carrier draught}}
|Ship depth=
|Ship hold depth=
|Ship decks=
|Ship deck clearance=
|Ship ramps=
|Ship ice class=
|Ship power=
|Ship propulsion={{Nimitz class aircraft carrier propulsion}}
|Ship sail plan=
|Ship speed={{Nimitz class aircraft carrier speed}}
|Ship range={{Nuclear ship range}}
|Ship endurance=
|Ship test depth=
|Ship boats=
|Ship capacity=
|Ship troops=
|Ship complement={{Nimitz class aircraft carrier complement}}
|Ship crew=
|Ship time to activate=
|Ship sensors={{Nimitz class aircraft carrier sensors I}}
|Ship EW={{Nimitz class aircraft carrier EW}}
|Ship armament={{Nimitz class aircraft carrier armament III}}
|Ship armor={{Nimitz class aircraft carrier armour}}
|Ship aircraft={{Nimitz class aircraft carrier aircraft}}
|Ship aircraft facilities=
|Ship notes=
}}
|}

'''USS ''Abraham Lincoln'' (CVN-72)''', is the fifth [[Nimitz class aircraft carrier|''Nimitz''-class supercarrier]] in the [[United States Navy]]. She is the second Navy ship named after former president [[Abraham Lincoln]]. Her home port is [[Naval Station Everett|Everett, Washington]].

==Ship history==
===Construction===
''Lincoln'''s contract was awarded to [[Northrop Grumman Newport News|Newport News Shipbuilding]] on 27 December 1982; her keel was laid 3 November 1984 at [[Newport News, Virginia]].  The ship was [[ship naming and launching|launched]] on 13 February 1988 and [[ship commissioning|commissioned]] on 11 November 1989. She cost $4.5&amp;nbsp;billion in 2007 dollars.

===1990 to 1999===
''Abraham Lincoln'' was transferred to the Pacific in September 1990 performing [[Gringo-Gaucho]] with the [[Argentine Naval Aviation]] during her transit. Her maiden [[Pacific Ocean|Western Pacific]] deployment came unexpectedly on 28 May 1991 in response to [[Gulf_War#Operation_Desert_Shield|Operation Desert Shield]]/[[Operation Desert Storm|Desert Storm]].

While heading towards the Indian Ocean, the ship was diverted to support evacuation operations after [[Mount Pinatubo]] erupted on [[Luzon]] Island in the Philippines.  In support of [[Operation Fiery Vigil]], ''Lincoln'' led a 23-ship armada that moved over 45,000 people from the [[Subic Bay Naval Station]] to the port of [[Cebu City|Cebu]] in the [[Visayas]].  It was the largest peacetime evacuation of active military personnel and their families in history.

After Fiery Vigil, ''Lincoln'' steamed toward the [[Persian Gulf]], to run reconnaissance and [[combat air patrol]]s in [[Iraq]] and [[Kuwait]], assisting allied and US troops involved with Desert Storm.

In early 1992, the ship was at [[Naval Air Station Alameda]] on Ship's Restricted Availability (SRA) for minor maintenance and refitting.

From June 1993 ''Lincoln'' was the flagship of Commander, Carrier Group Three.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.history.navy.mil/danfs/a2/abraham_lincoln.htm History.navy.mil]&lt;/ref&gt; In October 1993, the carrier was ordered to the coast of [[Somalia]] to assist UN humanitarian operations.  For four weeks, ''Abraham Lincoln'' flew air patrols over [[Mogadishu]] in support of [[Operation Restore Hope]].

''Abraham Lincoln'' was to be the first carrier to integrate female aviators into the crew after the Combat Exclusion Laws were lifted on 28 April 1993. The ship left [[Naval Station San Diego|San Diego]] on 24 October 1994, to begin refresher training. The next day, Lieutenant [[Kara Spears Hultgreen]], first female [[F-14 Tomcat]] pilot, died when her plane crashed into the sea on final approach due to a combination of engine malfunction and pilot error.

''Abraham Lincoln'''s third deployment began in April 1995 when ''Lincoln'' was sent to the [[Persian Gulf]], where the ship assisted in [[Southern Watch]] and in [[Operation Vigilant Sentinel]].{{Citation needed|date=April 2009}}  During an underway replenishment, the ''Lincoln'' was run into by USS Sacramento when the Sacramento had steering difficulties due to a split rudder, crushing the port side of the [[USS Sacramento (AOE-1)|USS ''Sacramento'']], crushing the M-frames, partially crushing a female crew berthing area, and punching a large hole in the ''Sacramento''’s superstructure. (TACAN room)  The ''Lincoln'' was able to continue on with her mission while the ''Sacramento'' had to dock at Jebel Ali, U.A.E. for several weeks for repair.

Later that year, [[Lighthouse and naval vessel urban legend|a supposed transcript of an exchange]] between the ''Abraham Lincoln'' and a Canadian lighthouse was widely disseminated on the Internet. The Navy has officially denied it occurred,&lt;ref name=&quot;USN denial&quot;&gt;{{cite web|title=The Lighthouse Joke|author=[[United States Navy]]|url=http://www.navy.mil/navydata/navy_legacy_hr.asp?id=174|date=September 2, 2009|accessdate=September 17, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;  but it continues to circulate.&lt;ref name=&quot;Snopes lighthouse page&quot;&gt;{{cite web|last=Mikkelson|first=Barbara|authorlink=Barbara Mikkelson|title=The Obstinate Lighthouse|url=http://www.snopes.com/military/lighthouse.asp|publisher=[[Snopes.com]]|date=March 18, 2008|accessdate=September 17, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;
====Operation Infinite Reach====
''Abraham Lincoln'' began a fourth deployment in June 1998.  Once again, the ship headed for the Persian Gulf in support of operation Southern Watch.  During this deployment, the [[Carrier Strike Group Nine|USS Abraham Lincoln Battle Group]] launched [[Tomahawk cruise missiles]] against two sites. First was a [[Al-Shifa pharmaceutical factory|Sudanese Pharmecutical company]] suspected of assisting [[Osama Bin Laden]] in making chemical weapons.  The second was Bin Laden's  terrorist training camps in Afghanistan.  These Strikes were ordered by President Clinton 13 days after terrorists [[1998 United States embassy bombings|bombed the U.S. embassies in Kenya and Tanzania]] and was codenamed [[Operation Infinite Reach]].&lt;ref&gt;http://www.globalsecurity.org/military/systems/munitions/bgm-109-operation.htm&lt;/ref&gt; The USS Abraham Lincoln  was awarded the [[Armed Forces Expeditionary Medal]], and the [[Carrier Strike Group Nine|USS Abraham Lincoln Battle Group]] the [[Meritorious Unit Commendation]] ribbon for its participation. &lt;ref&gt; http://www.usscoralsea.net/docs/opnavnote1650.pdf &lt;/ref&gt;

===2000s===
The carrier's fifth deployment commenced in August 2000 when ''Abraham Lincoln'' again traveled to the Persian Gulf in support of Southern Watch.  On this deployment, the carrier, air wing and battle group ships earned the Navy [[Meritorious Unit Commendation]]. Additionally the ship earned the prestigious Arleigh Burke Award as the most improved command in the [[United States Pacific Fleet|Pacific Fleet]].

''Abraham Lincoln'' was in port on 11 September 2001.  She was put to sea on 20 July 2002 to support [[War in Afghanistan (2001-present)|Operation Enduring Freedom]].  She took up station once more in support of [[Operation Southern Watch]] before taking a port visit to [[Perth, Western Australia]].  It was during this time that the ''Lincoln'' was ordered to the [[Persian Gulf]] to take part in [[2003 invasion of Iraq|Operation Iraqi Freedom]]. This forced the Navy to extend ''Lincoln'''s stay from 20 January 2003 to 6 May 2003.  The news of this extension was delivered to the ship's crew on New Years morning by the then Battlegroup Commander, RADM Kelly, with the phrase, &quot;We don't need to be home holding our loved ones, we need to be here holding the line. Get over it!&quot;  The term &quot;Get over it&quot; became the running joke aboard ship, which eventually led to a deployment patch made aboard that read &quot;Westpac 2003 CVN-72 CVW-14 GET OVER IT&quot; with an image intended to depict an admiral kicking a sailor in the groin.&lt;ref&gt;  [http://www.av8rstuff.com/gifs/cvn72getoverit.JPG AV8rstuff.com]&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Image:USS Abraham Lincoln (CVN-72) Mission Accomplished.jpg|thumb|left|The USS ''Abraham Lincoln'' returning to port carrying its Mission Accomplished banner, 2 May 2003.]]
''Abraham Lincoln'' and the carrier battle group and airwing helped deliver the opening salvos and air strikes in [[Operation Iraqi Freedom]]. During her deployment, some 16,500 sorties were flown and 1.6&amp;nbsp;million pounds of ordnance used. Sea Control Squadron 35 (VS-35), the &quot;Blue Wolves&quot;, was instrumental in delivering over 1&amp;nbsp;million pounds of fuel to these strike aircraft, one of the largest aerial refueling undertakings by a carrier aviation squadron in history.  The carrier returned home in May 2003, in the process receiving a visit from President [[George W. Bush]] before officially ending ''Lincoln'''s deployment by docking at San Diego before returning to homeport in Everett, WA. Bush stated at the time that this was the end to [[2003 invasion of Iraq|major combat operations]] in [[Iraq]]. While this statement did coincide with an end to the conventional phase of the war, Bush's assertion—and the sign itself—became controversial after [[guerrilla]] warfare in Iraq increased during the [[Iraqi insurgency]]. The vast majority of casualties, both military and civilian, have occurred since the speech.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.globalsecurity.org/military/ops/iraq_casualties.htm Globalsecurity.org]&lt;/ref&gt; The [[White House]] said their services constructed the banner.  As explained by Cmdr. Conrad Chun, a Navy spokesman, &quot;The banner was a Navy idea, the ship's idea.  The idea popped up in one of the meetings aboard the ship preparing for its homecoming and thought it would be good to have a banner, '[[Mission Accomplished]].' The sailors then asked if the White House could get the sign made. ... The banner signified the successful completion of the ship's deployment,&quot; Cmdr. Chun continued noting that the Abraham Lincoln was deployed 290 days, longer than any other nuclear-powered aircraft carrier in history.

On 1 October 2004, the carrier's controlling formation was redesignated from Cruiser-Destroyer Group Three to [[Carrier Strike Group Nine]]. ''Abraham Lincoln'' departed for her next voyage on 15 October 2004.  The carrier was on a port call in Hong Kong when a the 9.0-magnitude [[2004 Indian Ocean earthquake]] struck southern Asia on 26 December 2004. To help with the international relief effort and assist with search and rescue efforts already underway, the ''Lincoln'' deployed to the hard hit western coast of [[Sumatra]] to provide humanitarian assistance. The deployment was designated [[Operation Unified Assistance]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.globalsecurity.org/military/ops/unified-assistance.htm Globalsecurity.org]&lt;/ref&gt;

In mid-January 2005 the carrier left [[Indonesia]]n waters after the Indonesian government refused to allow fighter pilots assigned to ''Lincoln'' to conduct air patrols and training flights.  By law, US carrier-based pilots must practice at least once every two to three weeks to remain &quot;fit,&quot; otherwise they are grounded. Despite the move into international waters, ''Lincoln'' continued to provide support to the region until 4 February. During the carrier's 33 days on station, she and her battle group, [[Carrier Strike Group Nine]] delivered 5.7&amp;nbsp;million pounds of relief supplies. The 17 [[helicopter]]s assigned to HSL-47 Saberhawks and HS-2 &quot;Golden Falcons&quot;, attached to CVW-2 flew 1,747 relief missions along the western coast of Sumatra. The carrier's departure coincided with the arrival of the hospital ship [[USNS Mercy (T-AH-19)|''Mercy'']].

[[File:US Navy 060505-N-9079D-025 Air Traffic Controller 3rd Class David McKeehe works approach controller in Carrier Air Traffic Control Center (CATTC).jpg|thumb|left|An Air Traffic Controller works approach controller in Carrier Air Traffic Control Center (CATTC) aboard the [[Nimitz class aircraft carrier|''Nimitz'' class]] aircraft carrier USS ''Abraham Lincoln''.]]

On 18 December 2006, the USS ''Abraham Lincoln'' left dry dock at the shipyard ahead of schedule and under budget. The Puget Sound Naval Shipyard and Intermediate Maintenance Facility (PSNS &amp; IMF) completed ship tank maintenance in less than half the scheduled time.  In 89 days, 18 tanks were completed.  The Tank Value Stream Team achieved this partnering with Ship’s Force and the Lincoln Project Team.  While in dry dock, the whole ship was painted by the crew at nights and on weekends rather than waiting for contractors to do the job.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.news.navy.mil/search/display.asp?story_id=28368 Deck Department Gives Abe “That New Ship Look”&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;

The refit was completed 26 March 2007, when Rear Adm. Scott Van Buskirk assumed command of Carrier Strike Group Nine (CSG 9) from Rear Adm. Bill Goodwin.

[[Image:2004 Indian Ocean Earthquake relief3.jpg|thumb|Helicopters depart from the ''Abraham Lincoln'' en route to [[Aceh]], [[Sumatra]], supporting humanitarian airlifts to tsunami-stricken coastal regions in early 2005.]]

===2010s===
On January 13, 2010, the carrier completed upgrades and repair that cost $250&amp;nbsp;million at [[Puget Sound Naval Shipyard]].  The carrier was to be assigned to [[Carrier Strike Group Nine]].
On February 03, 2011, The ship was awarded the [[Battle Effectiveness Award]] for its high standards of excellence and combat readiness.&lt;ref&gt;Bacon, Lance M., &quot;[http://militarytimes.com/news/2010/01/navy_lincolndone_011410w/ Lincoln leaves yard after $250M in upgrades]&quot;, ''[[Military Times]]'', 14 January 2010.&lt;/ref&gt;

On 9 December 2010, the U.S. Navy officially  announced that [[Naval Station Everett]], Washington, was the new homeport for the {{USS|Nimitz|CVN-68}}, replacing ''Abraham Lincoln'', which would be undergoing its scheduled [[Refueling and Complex Overhaul]] (RCOH) at the [[Northrop Grumman Shipbuilding Newport News|Northrop Grumman Shipbuilding-Newport News shipyard]] in Virginia which is slated to begin in 2013.&lt;ref name=Wertheim&gt;{{cite journal |last= Wertheim |first= Eric |authorlink= Eric Wertheim |year= 2011 |month= February |title= Combat Fleets |journal= [[U.S. Naval Institute|U.S. Naval Institute Proceedings]] |volume= 137 |issue= 2 |pages= 92 |id= 0041-798X |url= http://www.usni.org/magazines/proceedings/2011-02/combat-fleets |accessdate=2011-03-14 |quote= Registration required.}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | title= Navy Announces USS ''Nimitz'' Homeport Change to Everett, Wash. | url= http://www.navy.mil/search/display.asp?story_id=57665 | work= NNS101209-21 | publisher= [[U.S. Department of Defense]] | date= December 9, 2010 | accessdate=2010-12-11}}&lt;/ref&gt;  

On 1 March 2011, the news media reported that the U.S. Navy had awarded Northrop Grumman Shipbuilding-Newport News a $206.7 million USD option under a previously awarded contract to plan ''Abraham Lincoln''{{'}}s [[Refueling_and_Overhaul|RCOH]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | author= Robert McCabe | title= Northrop Grumman gets $206.7M option on carrier work | url= http://hamptonroads.com/2011/02/northrop-grumman-gets-2067m-option-carrier-work | work= Business - Defense and Shipyards  | publisher= ''[[The Virginian-Pilot]]'' | date= March 1, 2011 | accessdate=2011-03-07}}&lt;/ref&gt;   The planning contract covered the design, documentation, engineering, advanced material procurement, inspections, fabrication, and support work for ''Lincoln''{{'}}s RCOH, with more than 1,000 employees supporting this planning phase.  Additional funding for the RCOH was pending the passage of the [[U.S. Department of Defense]]'s Fiscal Year 2011 budget appropriations by the [[U.S. Congress]].  Upon authorization, the ''Lincoln''{{'}}s RCOH was anticipated to begin in 2013, and it is scheduled to take between three and four years to complete at an estimated overall cost of $3 billion USD.&lt;ref name=Wertheim&gt;{{cite journal |last= Wertheim |first= Eric |authorlink= Eric Wertheim |year= 2011 |month= February |title= Combat Fleets |journal= [[U.S. Naval Institute|U.S. Naval Institute Proceedings]] |volume= 137 |issue= 2 |pages= 92 |id= 0041-798X |url= http://www.usni.org/magazines/proceedings/2011-02/combat-fleets |accessdate=2011-03-14 |quote= Registration required.}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | author= Peter Frost | title= Shipyard gets $206.7M to overhaul ''Lincoln'' | url= http://articles.dailypress.com/2011-03-01/business/dp-nws-lincoln-carrier-20110301_1_workers-between-major-construction-refueling-and-complex-overhauls-midlife-maintenance | publisher= ''[[Daily Press (Virginia)|Daily Press]]'' | date= March 1, 2011 | accessdate=2011-03-07}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In addition to the refueling of its two [[A4W reactor|A4W nuclear reactors]], ''Abraham Lincoln''{{'}}s upcoming RCOH will include the installation of the newly developed Advanced Arresting Gear (AAG) system.  Developed by [[General Atomics]], the AAG system will replace the ''Lincoln''{{'}}s current Mark-7 arresting gear’s hydraulic machinery with an electric motor-based system. The new system offers greater operational flexibility, reliability, and safety with reduced manning and maintenance costs.   The AAG system is standard equipment for the upcoming [[Gerald R. Ford class aircraft carrier|''Ford''-class supercarriers]].  ''Abraham Lincoln'' is the first [[Nimitz class aircraft carrier|''Nimitz''-class supercarrier]] to have the AAG system retro-fitted with other ''Nimitz''-class carriers also to be so retro-fitted during their upcoming RCOH yard period.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|last= Jacobs |first= Jan C. |year= 2011 |month= May |title= U.S. Naval Aviation and Weapons Development in Review |journal= [[United States Naval Institute|Naval Institute Processings]] |volume= 137 |issue= 5 |pages= 83 |id= ISSN 0041-798X |url= http://www.usni.org/magazines/proceedings/2011-05/us-naval-aviation-and-weapons-development-review |accessdate= 2011-05-09|quote=Registration required.}}&lt;/ref&gt;

On 1 August 2011, the U.S. Navy announced that the ''Abraham Lincoln'' will shift its homeport from Everett, Washington, to [[Newport News, Virginia]], for its Refueling and Complex Overhaul in August 2012.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | author= | title= Change in Permanent Duty Station for Carrier Strike Group Nine | url= http://doni.daps.dla.mil/Directives/05000%20General%20Management%20Security%20and%20Safety%20Services/05-400%20Organization%20and%20Functional%20Support%20Services/5400.8546.pdf | work= OPNAV NOTICE 5400 Ser DNS-33/llU228546 | publisher= [[Chief of Naval Operations|Office of the Chief of Naval Operations]] - [[U.S. Department of the Navy]] | date= 01 August 2011 | accessdate=2011-09-09}}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:USSAbrahamLincolnByPhilKonstantin.jpg|thumb|USS Abraham Lincoln in San Diego Bay, 2011]]

== See also ==
{{Portal box|United States Navy|Military of the United States}}
{{Wikipedia-Books|Nimitz class aircraft carriers}}
* [[2003 Mission Accomplished Speech]]
* [[List of aircraft carriers]]
* [[List of aircraft carriers of the United States Navy]]
* [[Modern US Navy carrier air operations]]

==References==
{{More footnotes|date=September 2008}}
{{Reflist}}

==Sources==
*{{DANFS|http://www.history.navy.mil/danfs/a2/abraham_lincoln.htm}}

==External links==
{{Commons and category|USS Abraham Lincoln (CVN-72)|USS Abraham Lincoln (CVN-72)}}
* [http://www.maritimequest.com/warship_directory/us_navy_pages/aircraft_carriers/uss_abraham_lincoln_cvn_72_page_1.htm Maritimequest USS Abraham Lincoln CVN-72 pages]
* [http://www.lincoln.navy.mil/ Official USS ''Abraham Lincoln'' website]
* Story Archive - U.S. Navy, [http://www.navy.mil/local/story_archive.asp?id=96 USS ''Abraham Lincoln'' (CVN-72)]
* [http://www.uscarriers.net/cvn72history.htm USS Abraham Lincoln history at U.S. Carriers]
* USS ''Abraham Lincoln'' (CVN-72) command histories – [[Naval History &amp; Heritage Command]]
&lt;div class=&quot;horizontal&quot;&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;[http://www.history.navy.mil/shiphist/a/cvn-72/1989a.pdf 1989]&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;[http://www.history.navy.mil/shiphist/a/cvn-72/1990a.pdf 1990]&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;[http://www.history.navy.mil/shiphist/a/cvn-72/1991a.pdf 1991]&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;[http://www.history.navy.mil/shiphist/a/cvn-72/1992a.pdf 1992]&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;[http://www.history.navy.mil/shiphist/a/cvn-72/1993a.pdf 1993]&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;[http://www.history.navy.mil/shiphist/a/cvn-72/1994a.pdf 1994]&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;[http://www.history.navy.mil/shiphist/a/cvn-72/1995a.pdf 1995]&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;[http://www.history.navy.mil/shiphist/a/cvn-72/1996a.pdf 1996]&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;[http://www.history.navy.mil/shiphist/a/cvn-72/1997a.pdf 1997]&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;[http://www.history.navy.mil/shiphist/a/cvn-72/1998a.pdf 1998]&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;[http://www.history.navy.mil/shiphist/a/cvn-72/1999a.pdf 1999]&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;[http://www.history.navy.mil/shiphist/a/cvn-72/2001a.pdf 2001]&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;[http://www.history.navy.mil/shiphist/a/cvn-72/2002a.pdf 2002]&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;[http://www.history.navy.mil/shiphist/a/cvn-72/2003a.pdf 2003]&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;[http://www.history.navy.mil/shiphist/a/cvn-72/2004a.pdf 2004]&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;!-- non-breaking space to keep AWB drones from altering the space before the navbox--&gt;

{{Nimitz class aircraft carrier}}
{{Use dmy dates|date=August 2010}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Abraham Lincoln (Cvn-72)}}
[[Category:Nimitz class aircraft carriers]]
[[Category:Ships built in Virginia]]
[[Category:1988 ships]]
[[Category:Cold War aircraft carriers of the United States]]
[[Category:Active aircraft carriers of the United States]]
[[Category:United States Navy Illinois-related ships]]
[[Category:United States Navy Kentucky-related ships]]

[[de:USS Abraham Lincoln (CVN-72)]]
[[es:USS Abraham Lincoln (CVN-72)]]
[[fa:ناو هواپیمابر آبراهام لینکلن]]
[[fr:USS Abraham Lincoln (CVN-72)]]
[[it:USS Abraham Lincoln (CVN-72)]]
[[lt:USS Abraham Lincoln (CVN-72)]]
[[hu:USS Abraham Lincoln (CVN–72)]]
[[nl:USS Abraham Lincoln (CVN-72)]]
[[ja:エイブラハム・リンカーン (空母)]]
[[no:USS «Abraham Lincoln» (CVN-72)]]
[[nn:USS «Abraham Lincoln» (CVN-72)]]
[[pl:USS Abraham Lincoln (CVN-72)]]
[[pt:USS Abraham Lincoln (CVN-72)]]
[[ru:USS Abraham Lincoln (CVN-72)]]
[[sl:USS Abraham Lincoln (CVN-72)]]
[[sr:Носач авиона Абрахам Линколн (CVN-72)]]
[[fi:USS Abraham Lincoln (CVN-72)]]
[[zh:亞伯拉罕·林肯號航空母艦]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
