<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="200269" ns="0" title="Annie Besant"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Hatnote|&quot;Besant&quot; redirects here. For Walter Besant see [[Walter Besant]]. For the coin, see [[Bezant]].}}
{{Multiple issues
| external links = August 2009
| refimprove     = September 2007
| tone           = August 2009}}
{{Infobox person
| name        = Annie Besant
| image       = Annie Besant.png
| caption     = Annie Besant in the 1880s
| birth_date  = {{birth date|df=yes|1847|10|1}}
| birth_place = [[Clapham]], [[London]], [[United Kingdom of Great Britain and Ireland]]
| death_date  = {{death date and age|df=yes|1933|9|20|1847|10|1}}
| death_place = [[Adyar (Tamil Nadu)|Adyar]], [[Madras Presidency]], [[British India|India]]
| other_names = 
| spouse      = Frank Besant
| children    = Arthur, Mabel
| known_for   = [[Theosophist]], [[women's rights]] [[activist]], [[writer]] and [[orator]]
}} 

'''Annie Besant''' ({{IPAc-en|ˈ|b|ɛ|s|ə|n|t}}; ''née'' '''Wood''', 1 October 1847 – 20 September 1933)&lt;!--Per MOS, full dates in infobox need not be repeated in lede--&gt; was a prominent British [[Theosophy|Theosophist]], [[women's rights]] [[activist]], [[writer]] and [[orator]] and supporter of [[Ireland|Irish]] and [[India]]n self rule.

She was married at 19 to Frank Besant but separated from him over religious differences. She then became a prominent speaker for the [[National Secular Society]] (NCS) and writer and a close friend of [[Charles Bradlaugh]]. In 1877 they were prosecuted for publishing a book by birth control campaigner [[Charles Knowlton]]. The scandal made them famous and Bradlaugh was elected [[Member of Parliament]] for Northampton in 1880.

She became involved with Union organisers including the [[Bloody Sunday (1887)|Bloody Sunday]] demonstration and the [[London matchgirls strike of 1888]] and was a leading speaker for the [[Fabian Society]] and the [[Marxist]] [[Social Democratic Federation]] (SDF). She was elected to the [[London School Board]] for [[Tower Hamlets]], topping the poll even though few women were qualified to vote at that time.

In 1890 Besant met [[Helena Blavatsky]] and over the next few years her interest in [[Theosophy]] grew while her interest in secular matters waned. She became a member of the Society and a highly successful lecturer in Theosophy. As part of her Theosophy-related work, she travelled to India where in 1898 she helped establish the [[Central Hindu College]], and in 1902 she formed the International Order of Co-Freemasonry in England. Over the next few years she established lodges in many parts of the [[British Empire]]. In 1907 she became President of the [[Theosophical Society]].

She also became involved in politics in India, joining the [[Indian National Congress]]. When [[World War I]] broke out in 1914 she helped launch the [[Indian Home Rule Movement|Home Rule League]] to campaign for democracy in India and dominion status within the Empire. This led to her election as president of the India National Congress in late 1917. After the war she continued to campaign for Indian independence and for the causes of Theosophy until her death in 1933.

==Early life==
[[File:Sibsey church tower.JPG|left|thumb|200px|St. Margaret's church, Sibsey, where Frank Besant was vicar, 1871–1917]]
Annie Wood was born in 1844 in London into a middle-class family of [[Ireland|Irish]] origin. She was proud of her heritage and supported the cause of Irish self-rule throughout her adult life. Her father died when she was five years old, leaving the family almost penniless. Her mother supported the family by running a boarding house for boys at [[Harrow School]]. However, she was unable to support Annie and persuaded her friend Ellen Marryat to care for her. Marryat made sure that Besant had a good education.  She was given a strong sense of duty to society and an equally strong sense of what independent women could achieve.  As a young woman, she was also able to travel widely in Europe. There she acquired a taste for [[Roman Catholic]] colour and ceremony that never left her.

In 1867, at age nineteen she married 26-year-old [[clergyman]] Frank Besant, younger brother of [[Walter Besant]]. He was an evangelical [[Anglican]] who seemed to share many of her concerns. On the eve of marriage, she had become more politicised through a visit to friends in Manchester, who brought her into contact with both English radicals and the [[Manchester Martyrs]] of the Irish Republican [[Fenian Brotherhood]],&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.gutenberg.org/dirs/1/2/0/8/12085/12085-h/12085-h.htm#CHIV Annie Besant: An Autobiography, London, 1885, chapter 4.]&lt;/ref&gt; as well as with the conditions of the urban poor.
[[File:Annie Besant 1.jpg|thumb|Annie Besant]]
[[File:Sibsey Besant grave.JPG|right|thumb|200px|Grave of Frank Besant at Sibsey, where he remained vicar until his death]]
Soon Frank became vicar of [[Sibsey]] in [[Lincolnshire]]. Annie moved to Sibsey with her husband, and within a few years they had two children, Arthur and Mabel; however the marriage was a disaster. The first conflict came over money and Annie's independence. Annie wrote short stories, books for children, and articles. As married women did not have the legal right to own property, Frank was able to take all the money she earned. Politics further divided the couple. Annie began to support farm workers who were fighting to unionise and to win better conditions. Frank was a [[Tory]] and sided with the landlords and farmers. The tension came to a head when Annie refused to attend [[Eucharist|Communion]]. In 1873 she left him and returned to London. They were legally separated and Annie took her daughter with her.

Besant began to question her own faith. She turned to leading churchmen for advice, going to see [[Edward Bouverie Pusey]], leader of the Catholic wing of the [[Church of England]]. When she asked him to recommend books that would answer her questions, he told her she had read too many already.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.gutenberg.org/dirs/1/2/0/8/12085/12085-h/12085-h.htm#CHV Annie Besant: An Autobiography, London, 1885, chapter 5.]&lt;/ref&gt; Besant returned to Frank to make a last unsuccessful effort to repair the marriage. She finally left for [[London]].

==Birkbeck==
For a time she undertook part-time study at the [[Birkbeck, University of London|Birkbeck Literary and Scientific Institution]], where her religious and political activities caused alarm. At one point the Institution's governors sought to withhold the publication of her exam results.&lt;ref name=&quot;BBK&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.bbk.ac.uk/bbk/history/ |title=The History of Birkbeck |work=Birkbeck, University of London |accessdate=2006-11-26 |archiveurl = http://web.archive.org/web/20061006035925/http://www.bbk.ac.uk/bbk/history/ |archivedate = 2006-10-06}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Reformer and secularist==
[[File:Annie Besant - portrait.jpg|thumb|right|Annie Besant - 1880s]]
She fought for the causes she thought were right, starting with [[freedom of thought]], women's rights, [[secularism]] (she was a leading member of the [[National Secular Society]] alongside [[Charles Bradlaugh]]), [[birth control]], [[Fabian socialism]] and [[workers' rights]].

Divorce was unthinkable for Frank, and was not really within the reach of even [[middle-class]] people. Annie was to remain Mrs Besant for the rest of her life. At first, she was able to keep contact with both children and to have Mabel live with her; she also got a small allowance from her husband.

Once free of Frank Besant and exposed to new currents of thought, she began to question not only her long-held religious beliefs but also the whole of conventional thinking. She began to write attacks on the churches and the way they controlled people's lives. In particular she attacked the status of the [[Church of England]] as a state-sponsored faith.

Soon she was earning a small weekly wage by writing a column for the ''National Reformer'', the newspaper of the NCS. The NCS stood for a secular state and an end to the special status of Christianity, and allowed her to act as one of its public speakers. Public lectures were very popular entertainment in [[Victorian Era|Victorian]] times. Besant was a brilliant speaker, and was soon in great demand. Using the railway, she criss-crossed the country, speaking on all of the most important issues of the day, always demanding improvement, reform and freedom.

For many years Besant was a friend of the Society's leader, [[Charles Bradlaugh]]. It seems that they were never lovers, but their friendship was very close. Bradlaugh, a former seaman, had long been separated from his wife; Besant lived with him and his daughters, and they worked together on many issues. He was an [[atheist]] and a republican; he was also trying to get elected as [[House of Commons of the United Kingdom|Member of Parliament]] (MP) for [[Northampton]].

Besant and Bradlaugh became household names in 1877 when they published a book by the American birth-control campaigner [[Charles Knowlton]]. It claimed that [[working-class]] families could never be happy until they were able to decide how many children they wanted. It suggested ways to limit the size of their families. The Knowlton book was highly controversial, and was vigorously opposed by the Church. Besant and Bradlaugh proclaimed in the National Reformer:

&lt;blockquote&gt;We intend to publish nothing we do not think we can morally defend. All that we publish we shall defend.&lt;/blockquote&gt;

The pair were arrested and put on trial for publishing the Knowlton book. They were found guilty, but released pending appeal. As well as great opposition, Besant and Bradlaugh also received a great deal of support in the Liberal press. Arguments raged back and forth in the letters and comment columns as well as in the courtroom. Besant was instrumental in founding the [[Malthusian League]] during the trial, which would go on to advocate for the abolition of penalties for the promotion of contraception.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |jstor=2173367 |title=The Malthusian League and Resistance to Birth Control Propaganda in Late Victorian Britain |journal=Population Studies |author=F. D'arcy |date=Vol. 31, No. 3, Nov., 1977 }}&lt;/ref&gt; For a time, it looked as though they would be sent to prison. The case was thrown out finally only on a technical point, the charges not having been properly drawn up.

The scandal cost Besant custody of her children. Her husband was able to persuade the court that she was unfit to look after them, and they were handed over to him permanently.

Bradlaugh's political prospects were not damaged by the Knowlton scandal and he got elected to Parliament in 1881. Because of his atheism, he refused to swear the oath of loyalty. Although many Christians were shocked by Bradlaugh, others (like the Liberal leader [[William Ewart Gladstone|Gladstone]]) spoke up for freedom of belief. It took more than six years before the whole issue was sorted out (in Bradlaugh's favor) after a series of by-elections and court appearances.

Meanwhile Besant built close contacts with the [[Devolution#Irish home rule|Irish Home Rulers]] and supported them in her newspaper columns during what are considered crucial years, when the Irish nationalists were forming an alliance with Liberals and Radicals. Besant met the leaders of the Irish home rule movement. In particular, she got to know [[Michael Davitt]], who wanted to mobilise the Irish peasantry through a Land War, a direct struggle against the landowners. She spoke and wrote in favour of Davitt and his Land League many times over the coming decades.

However, Bradlaugh's parliamentary work gradually alienated Besant. Women had no part in parliamentary politics. Besant was searching for a real political outlet, where her skills as a speaker, writer and organiser could do some real good.

==Political activism==
For Besant, politics, friendship and love were always closely intertwined. Her decision in favour of Socialism came about through a close relationship with , a struggling young Irish author living in London, and a leading light of the  Annie was impressed by his work and grew very close to him too in the early 1880s. It was Besant who made the first move, by inviting Shaw to live with her. This he refused, but it was Shaw who sponsored Besant to join the Fabian Society. In its early days, the Society was a gathering of people exploring spiritual, rather than political, alternatives to the capitalist system.{{citation needed|date=July 2011}}
Besant began to write for the Fabians. This new commitment – and her relationship with Shaw – deepened the split between Besant and Bradlaugh, who was an individualist and opposed to Socialism of any sort. While he defended free speech at any cost, he was very cautious about encouraging working-class militancy.{{citation needed|date=July 2011}}in India

Unemployment was a central issue of the time, and in 1887 some of the London unemployed started to hold protests in [[Trafalgar Square]]. Besant agreed to appear as a speaker at a meeting on 13 November. The police tried to stop the assembly, fighting broke out, and troops were called. Many were hurt, one man died, and hundreds were arrested; Besant offered herself for arrest, an offer disregarded by the police.{{Citation needed|date=July 2011}}

The events created a great sensation, and became known as [[Bloody Sunday (1887)|Bloody Sunday]]. Besant was widely blamed – or credited – for it.{{Citation needed|date=July 2011}} She threw herself into organising legal aid for the jailed workers and support for their families. Bradlaugh finally broke with her because he felt she should have asked his advice before going ahead with the meeting.

Another activity in this period was her involvement in the [[London matchgirls strike of 1888]]. She was drawn into this battle of the &quot;New Unionism&quot; by a young socialist, [[Herbert Burrows]]. He had made contact with workers at [[Bryant and May]]'s match factory in [[Bow, London]], who were mainly young women and were very poorly paid. They were also prey to industrial illnesses, like the bone-rotting [[Phossy jaw]], which was caused by the chemicals used in match manufacture.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.mernick.org.uk/thhol/thelink.html &quot;White slavery in London&quot;] The Link, Issue no. 21 (via Tower Hamlets' Local History Library and Archives)&lt;/ref&gt; Some of the match workers asked for help from Burrows and Besant in setting up a union.

Besant met the women and set up a committee, which led the women into a strike for better pay and conditions, an action that won public support. Besant led demonstrations by &quot;match-girls&quot;, who were cheered in the streets, and prominent churchmen wrote in their support. In just over a week they forced the firm to improve pay and conditions. Besant then helped them to set up a proper union and a social centre.

At the time, the matchstick industry was a very powerful lobby, since electric light was not yet widely available, and matches were an essential commodity; in 1872, lobbyists from the match industry had persuaded the British government to change its planned tax policy. Besant's campaign was the first time anyone had successfully challenged the match manufacturers on a major issue, and was seen as a landmark victory of the early years of British Socialism.

During 1884, Besant had developed a very close friendship with [[Edward Aveling]], a young socialist teacher who lived in her house for a time. Aveling was a scholarly figure and it was he who first translated the important works of Marx into English. He eventually went to live with [[Eleanor Marx]], daughter of [[Karl Marx]]. Aveling was a great influence on Besant's thinking and she supported his work, yet she moved towards the rival Fabians at that time. Aveling and Eleanor Marx had joined the Marxist SDF and then the [[Socialist League (UK, 1885)|Socialist League]], a small Marxist splinter group which formed around the artist [[William Morris]].

It seems that Morris played a large part in converting Besant to Marxism, but it was to the SDF, not his Socialist League, that she turned in 1888. She remained a member for a number of years and became one of its best speakers. She was still a member of the Fabian Society; neither she nor anyone else seemed to think the two movements incompatible at the time.

Soon after joining the Marxists, Besant stood for election to the [[London School Board]]. Women at that time were not able to take part in parliamentary politics, but had been brought into the local electorate in 1881.

Besant drove about with a red ribbon in her hair, speaking at meetings. &quot;No more hungry children,&quot; her manifesto proclaimed. She combined her socialist principles with feminism:
&quot;I ask the electors to vote for me, and the non-electors to work for me because women are wanted on the Board and there are too few women candidates.&quot; Besant came out on top of the poll in [[Tower Hamlets (UK Parliament constituency)|Tower Hamlets]], with over 15,000 votes. She wrote in the National Reformer: &quot;Ten years ago, under a cruel law, Christian bigotry robbed me of my little child. Now the care of the 763,680 children of London is placed partly in my hands.&quot;

Besant was also involved in the [[London Dock Strike (1889)]], in which the dockers, who were employed by the day, were led by [[Ben Tillett]] in a struggle for the &quot;Dockers' Tanner&quot;. Besant helped Tillett draw up the union's rules and played an important part in the meetings and agitation which built up the organisation. She spoke for the dockers at public meetings and on street corners. Like the match-girls, the dockers won public support for their struggle, and the strike was won.

==Theosophy==
Besant was a prolific writer and a powerful orator. In 1889, she was asked to write a review for the ''Pall Mall Gazette'' &lt;ref&gt;Lutyens, ''Krishnamurti: The Years of Awakening'', Avon/Discus. 1983. p 13&lt;/ref&gt; on ''[[The Secret Doctrine]]'', a book by [[H.P. Blavatsky]].  After reading it, she sought an interview with its author, meeting Blavatsky in Paris. In this way she was converted to Theosophy. Besant's intellectual journey had always involved a spiritual dimension, a quest for transformation of the whole person. As her interest in Theosophy deepened, she allowed her membership of the Fabian Society to lapse (1890) and broke her links with the [[Marxists]]. When Blavatsky died in 1891, Besant was left as one of the leading figures in Theosophy and in 1893 she represented it at the [[World's Columbian Exposition|Chicago World Fair]].

In 1893, soon after becoming a member of the [[Theosophical Society]] she went to India for the first time. After a [[Theosophical Society#Schisms|dispute]] the American section split away into an independent organization. The original Society, then led by [[Henry Steel Olcott]] and Besant, is today based in [[Chennai]], India, and is known as the [[Theosophical Society Adyar]]. Following the split Besant devoted much of her energy not only to the Society, but also to India's freedom and progress. [[Besant Nagar]], a neighborhood near the Theosophical Society in Chennai, is named in her honor.

===Co-freemasonry===
[[File:Annie Besant in 1897.JPG|thumb|right|200px|Annie Besant in 1897]] She pursued freemasonry with equal vigour when it was mentioned to her that there was a masonry that &quot;accepted women as well as men&quot;. She saw freemasonry, in particular [[Co-Freemasonry|co-freemasonry]], as an extension of her interest in the rights of women and the greater brotherhood of man and saw co-freemasonry as a &quot;movement which practised true brotherhood, in which women and men worked side by side for the perfecting of humanity. She immediately wanted to be admitted to this organisation&quot;, known now as The International Order of Co-Freemasonry, Le Droit Humain.

The link was made in 1902 by the Theosophist Francesca Arundale, who accompanied Besant to Paris, along with six friends. &quot;They were all initiated, passed and raised into the first three degrees and Annie returned to England, bearing a Charter and founded there the first Lodge of International Mixed Masonry, Le Droit Humain.&quot;  Besant eventually became the Order's Most Puissant Grand Commander, and was a major influence in the international growth of the Order.&lt;ref&gt;The International Bulletin, 20 September 1933, The International Order of Co-Freemasonry, Le Droit Humain. &quot;In a very short time, Sister Besant founded new lodges: three in London, three in the south of England, three in the North and North-West; she even organised one in Scotland. Travelling in 1904 with her sisters and brothers she met in Holland, other brethren of a male obedience, who, being interested, collaborated in the further expansion of Le Droit Humain. Annie continued to work with such ardour that soon new lodges were formed Great Britain, South America, Canada, India, Ceylon, Australia and New Zealand. The lodges in all these countries were united under the name of the British Federation.&quot;&lt;/ref&gt;

===President of Theosophical Society===
[[File:Olcott Besant Leadbeater.jpg|thumb|right|250px|Annie Besant with [[Henry Olcott]] (left)  and [[Charles Webster Leadbeater|Charles Leadbeater]] (right) in [[Adyar (Chennai)|Adyar]] in  December 1905]]
Besant met fellow Theosophist [[Charles Webster Leadbeater]] in London in April 1894. They became close co-workers in the Theosophical Movement and would remain so for the rest of their lives. Leadbeater claimed [[clairvoyance]] and reputedly helped Besant become clairvoyant herself in the following year. In a letter dated 25 August 1895 to Francisca Arundale, Leadbeater narrates how Besant became clairvoyant.&lt;ref&gt;This letter is now on-line and can be read by clicking [http://www.tphta.ws/TPH_BCFU.HTM here]&lt;/ref&gt;  Together they clairvoyantly investigated the universe, matter, thought-forms, and the history of mankind, and co-authored several books.

In 1906 Leadbeater became the centre of controversy when it emerged that he had advised the practice of masturbation to some boys under his care and spiritual instruction. Leadbeater stated he had encouraged the practice in order to keep the boys celibate, which was considered a prerequisite for advancement on the spiritual path.&lt;ref&gt;[http://leadbeater.org/tillettcwlchap10.htm Charles Webster Leadbeater 1854-1934: A Biographical Study, by Gregory John Tillett, 2008].&lt;/ref&gt; Due to the controversy, he offered to resign from the Theosophical Society in 1906, which was accepted. The next year Besant became President of the Society and in 1908, with her express support, Leadbeater was readmitted to the Society. Leadbeater went on to face accusations of improper relations with boys, but none of the accusations were ever proven and Besant never deserted him.&lt;ref&gt;Besant, Annie (2 June 1913). &quot;Naranian v. Besant&quot;. [Letters to the Editor]. ''[[The Times]]'' (London). p. 7. {{ISSN|0140-0460}}.&lt;/ref&gt;

Until Besant's presidency, the society had as one of its foci [[Theravada]] [[Buddhism]] and the island of [[Sri Lanka]], where Henry Olcott did the majority of his useful work.&lt;ref&gt;Blavatsky and Olcott had become Buddhists in Sri Lanka, and promoted Buddhist revival on the subcontinent. See also: [[Maha Bodhi Society]].&lt;/ref&gt; Under Besant's leadership there was more stress on the teachings of &quot;The Aryavarta&quot;, as she called central India, as well as on esoteric Christianity.{{Citation needed|date=July 2011}}

Besant set up a new school for boys, the [[Central Hindu College]] (CHC) at [[Benares]] which was formed on underlying Theosophical principles, and which counted many prominent Theosophists in its staff and faculty. Its aim was to build a new leadership for India. The students spent 90 minutes a day in prayer and studied religious texts, but they also studied modern science. It took 3 years to raise the money for the CHC, most of which came from Indian princes.{{Citation needed|date=June 2011}} In April 1911, Besant met Pandit [[Madan Mohan Malaviya]] and they decided to unite their forces and work for a common Hindu University at Varanasi. Besant and fellow trustees of the Central Hindu College also agreed to Government of India's precondition that the college should become a part of the new University. The [[Banaras Hindu University]] started functioning from 1 October 1917 with the Central Hindu College as its first constituent college.

Blavatsky had stated in 1889 that the main purpose of establishing the Society was to prepare humanity for the future reception of a &quot;torch-bearer of Truth&quot;, an emissary of a hidden [[Spiritual Hierarchy]] that according to Theosophists guides the evolution of Humankind.&lt;ref&gt;[[Helena Blavatsky|Blavatsky, H. P.]] (1889). ''[[The Key to Theosophy]]''. London: The Theosophical Publishing Company. pp. 306-307.&lt;/ref&gt; This was repeated by Besant as early as 1896; Besant came to believe in the imminent appearance of the &quot;emissary&quot;, who was identified by Theosophists as the so-called ''[[World Teacher]]''.&lt;ref&gt;Lutyens, p. 12.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Wessinger, Catherine Lowman (1988). ''Annie Besant and Progressive Messianism, 1847-1933''. [[Lewiston, New York]]: [[Edwin Mellen Press]]. ISBN 978-0-88946-523-7.&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:Music of Gounod - Annie Besant Thought Form - Project Gutenberg eText 16269.jpg|thumbnail|right|Thought-form of the music of [[Charles Gounod]], according to Besant and C.W. Leadbeater in ''Thought-Forms '' (1901)]]

===The World Teacher Project===
In 1909, soon after Besant's assumption of the presidency, Leadbeater &quot;discovered&quot; fourteen-year-old [[Jiddu Krishnamurti]] (1895–1986), a South Indian boy who had been living next to the headquarters of the Theosophical Society at [[Adyar (Chennai)|Adyar]], and declared him the probable &quot;vehicle&quot; for the expected [[Maitreya (Theosophy)|World Teacher]].&lt;ref&gt;[[Mary Lutyens|Lutyens, Mary]] (1975). ''[[Krishnamurti: The Years of Awakening]]''. NewYork: [[Farrar Straus and Giroux]]. Hardcover. pp. 20-21. ISBN 0374182221.&lt;/ref&gt; The &quot;discovery&quot; and its objective received widespread publicity and attracted worldwide following, mainly among Theosophists. It also started years of upheaval, and contributed to splits in the Theosophical Society and doctrinal schisms in Theosophy. Following the discovery, Jiddu Krishnamurti and his younger brother Nityananda (&quot;Nitya&quot;) were placed under the care of Theosophists and Krishnamurti was extensively groomed for his future mission as the new vehicle for the &quot;World Teacher&quot;. Besant soon became the boys' [[legal guardianship|legal guardian]] with the consent of their father, who was very poor and could not take care of them. However, his father later changed his mind and began a legal battle to regain the guardianship, against the will of the boys.&lt;ref&gt;Lutyens ch. 7.&lt;/ref&gt; Early in their relationship, Krishnamurti and Besant had developed a very close bond and he considered her a surrogate mother – a role she happily accepted. (His biological mother had died when he was ten years old).&lt;ref&gt;Lutyens p. 5. Also in p. 31, Krishnamurti's letter to Besant dated December 24, 1909, and in p. 62, letter dated January 5, 1913.&lt;/ref&gt;

In 1929, twenty years after his &quot;discovery&quot;, Krishnamurti, who had grown disenchanted with the ''World Teacher Project'', repudiated the role that many Theosophists expected him to fulfil. He dissolved the [[Order of the Star in the East]], an organization founded to assist the World Teacher in his mission, and eventually left the [[Theosophical Society]] and Theosophy at large.&lt;ref&gt;Lutyens pp. 276–278, 285.&lt;/ref&gt; He spent the rest of his life travelling the world as an unaffiliated speaker, becoming in the process widely known as an original, independent thinker on philosophical, psychological, and spiritual subjects. His love for Besant never waned, as also was the case with Besant's feelings towards him;&lt;ref&gt;[[Mary Lutyens|Lutyens, Mary]] (2003). ''The Life and Death of Krishnamurti''. [[Bramdean]]: [http://www.kfoundation.org.uk/acatalog/ Krishnamurti Foundation Trust]. p. 81. ISBN 0-900506-22-9.&lt;/ref&gt; concerned for his wellbeing after he declared his independence, she had purchased {{convert|6|acre|m2}} of land near the Theosophical Society estate which later became the headquarters of the [[Jiddu Krishnamurti#External_links|''Krishnamurti Foundation India'']].

==The Home Rule movement==
Along with her Theosophical activities, Besant continued to actively participate in  political matters. She had joined the [[Indian National Congress]]. As the name suggested, this was originally a debating body, which met each year to consider resolutions on political issues. Mostly it demanded more of a say for middle-class Indians in British Indian government. It had not yet developed into a permanent mass movement with local organisation. About this time her co-worker Leadbeater moved to [[Sydney]], Australia.

In 1914 [[World War I]] broke out, and Britain asked the support of its Empire in the fight against [[Germany]]. Echoing an Irish nationalist slogan, Besant declared, &quot;England's need is India's opportunity&quot;. As editor of the ''New India'' newspaper, she attacked the [[British Raj|colonial government]] of India and called for clear and decisive moves towards self-rule. As with Ireland, the government refused to discuss any changes while the war lasted.

[[File:Annie Besant.001.jpg|right|210px|thumb|Annie Besant in [[Sydney, Australia]], 1922]]
In 1916 Besant launched the [[Home Rule Movement|Home Rule League]] along with the Indian [[Lokmanya Tilak]], once again modeling demands for India on Irish nationalist practices. This was the first political party in India to have regime change as its main goal. Unlike the Congress itself, the League worked all year round. It built a structure of local branches, enabling it to mobilise demonstrations, public meetings and agitations. In June 1917 Besant was arrested and interned at a [[hill station]], where she defiantly flew a red and green flag. The Congress and the [[All-India Muslim League|Muslim League]] together threatened to launch protests if she were not set free; Besant's arrest had created a focus for protest.

The government was forced to give way and to make vague but significant concessions. It was announced that the ultimate aim of British rule was Indian self-government, and moves in that direction were promised. Besant was freed in September 1917 to great welcome from crowds all over India and in December she took over as President of the Indian National Congress for a year.

After the war, a new leadership emerged around [[Mohandas K. Gandhi]] - one of those who had written to demand Besant's release. He was a lawyer who had returned from leading Asians in a peaceful struggle against racism in [[South Africa]]. [[Jawaharlal Nehru]], Gandhi's closest collaborator, had been educated by a Theosophist tutor.

The new leadership was committed to action that was both militant and nonviolent, but there were differences between them and Besant. Despite her past, she was not happy with their socialist leanings. Until the end of her life, however, she continued to campaign for India's independence, not only in India but also on speaking tours of Britain. In her own version of Indian dress, she remained a striking presence on speakers' platforms. She produced a torrent of letters and articles demanding independence.

==Later years==
Besant tried as a person, Theosophist, and President of the Theosophical Society, to accommodate Krishnamurti's views into her life, without success; she vowed to personally follow him in his new direction although she apparently had trouble understanding both his motives and his new message.&lt;ref&gt;Lutyens pp. 236, 278-280.&lt;/ref&gt; The two remained friends until the end of her life.  Besant died in 1933 and was survived by her daughter, [[Mabel Besant-Scott|Mabel]]. After her death, colleagues J. Krishnamurti, [[Aldous Huxley]], Dr. Guido Ferrando, and [[Rosalind Rajagopal]], built Happy Valley School, now renamed [[Besant Hill School]] in her honour.

==Descendants==
The subsequent family history became fragmented. A number of Besant's descendants have been traced in detail from her son [[Arthur Digby]]'s side. One of Arthur Digby's daughters was Sylvia Besant, who married [[Commander]] [[Clem Lewis (Commander)|Clem Lewis]] in the 1920s. They had a daughter, Kathleen Mary, born in 1934, who was given away for [[adoption]] within three weeks of the birth and had the new name of [[Lavinia Pollock]]. Lavinia married Frank Castle in 1953 and raised a family of five Besant's great-great grandchildren – James, Richard, David, Fiona and [[Andrew Castle]] – the last and youngest sibling being a former British professional tennis player and now television presenter and personality.

==Selected works==
* ''The Political Status of Women'' (1874)
* ''My Path to Atheism'' (1877)
* ''The Law Of Population'' (1877)
* ''Marriage, As It Was, As It Is, And As It Should Be: A Plea For Reform'' (1878)
* ''Autobiographical Sketches'' (1885)
* ''Why I became a Theosophist'' (1889)
* ''The Devachanic Plane''. Theosophical Publishing House, London, ca 1895.
* ''[[The Ancient Wisdom]]'' (1898)
* ''[[Thought Forms]]'' (1901)
* ''Bhagavad Gita'' (translation) (1905)
* ''[[Study in Consciousness]] - A contribution to the science of psychology.'' Theosophical Publishing House, Madras, ca 1907.
* ''Introduction to Yoga'' (1908)
* ''Australian Lectures ''(1908)
* ''Man and his bodies''. Theosophical Publishing House, London, 1911.
* ''Man's life in this and other worlds.'' Theosophical Publishing House, Adyar, 1913.
* [[Occult Chemistry (book)|''Occult Chemistry'']] (With [[Charles Webster Leadbeater]])
* ''Initiation: The Perfecting of Man (1923)
* ''The Doctrine of the Heart'' (1920)
* ''Esoteric Christianity''.
* ''The Future of Indian Politics'' (booklet), Theosophical Publishing House, Adyar, 1922
* ''The Life and Teaching of Muhammad'', Madras, 1932
* ''Memory and Its Nature'', Theosophical Publishing House, Madras, ca 1935. (With [[Helena Blavatsky]]).

== Further reading ==
* Chandrasekhar, S. &quot;A Dirty, Filthy Book&quot;: The Writing of Charles Knowlton and Annie Besant on Reproductive Physiology and Birth Control and an Account of the Bradlaugh-Besant Trial. University of California Berkeley 1981
* Grover, Verinder and Ranjana Arora (eds.) ''Annie Besant: Great Women of Modern India – 1''  : Published by Deep of Deep Publications, New Delhi, India, 1993
* Kumar, Raj  Rameshwari Devi and Romila Pruthi. ''Annie Besant: Founder of Home Rule Movement'', Pointer Publishers, 2003 ISBN 81-7132-321-9
* Manvell, Roger. The trial of Annie Besant and Charles Bradlaugh. Elek, London 1976
* Nethercot, Arthur H. ''The first five lives of Annie Besant'' Hart-Davis: London, 1961
* Nethercot, Arthur H. ''The last four lives of Annie Besant'' Hart-Davis: London (also University of Chicago Press 1963) ISBN 0-226-57317-6
* Taylor, Anne. ''Annie Besant: A Biography'', Oxford University Press, 1991 (also US edition 1992) ISBN 0-19-211796-3

==See also==
*[[Theosophical Society]]
*[[History of feminism]]

==References==
&lt;!--See [[Wikipedia:Footnotes]] for an explanation of how to generate footnotes using the &lt;ref(erences/)&gt; tags--&gt;
{{Reflist}}

==External links==
{{Sister project links|Annie Besant|s=Annie Wood Besant|author=yes}}
*{{gutenberg author|id=Annie_Wood_Besant|name=Annie Wood Besant}}
*[http://www.csuchico.edu/phil/sdobra_mat/besantpaper.html Annie Wood Besant: Orator, Activist, Mystic, Rhetorician] By Susan Dobra
*[http://www.spartacus.schoolnet.co.uk/Wbesant.htm Biography]
*[http://www.bbc.co.uk/history/historic_figures/besant_annie.shtml Biography (BBC)]
*[http://www.alpheus.org/html/articles/theosophy/bevir3.html Annie Besant's Quest for Truth: Christianity, Secularism, and New Age Thought]
*[http://www.kheper.net/topics/Theosophy/Besant.html Biography and links]
*[http://www.indianpost.com/viewstamp.php/Print%20Size/3.3%20x%202.9/MRS%20ANNIE%20BESANT Annie Besant Memorial from the Indian Post]
*[http://www.ts-adyar.org/history.html History of Theosophical Society Adyar and Besant]
*[http://dlxs2.library.cornell.edu/cgi/t/text/text-idx?c=cdl;idno=cdl364 Thought power, its control and culture] Cornell
University Library Historical Monographs Collection.
*[http://www.kamat.com/kalranga/women/besant.htm Annie Besant] by [http://www.kamat.com/jyotsna/ Jyotsna Kamat]
{{Indian National Congress Presidents}}
{{Indian independence movement}}
{{ModernDharmicWriters}}

&lt;!-- Metadata: see [[Wikipedia:Persondata]] --&gt;
{{Persondata
| NAME              = Besant, Annie
| ALTERNATIVE NAMES = 
| SHORT DESCRIPTION = Theosophist, British social reformer
| DATE OF BIRTH     = 1 October 1847
| PLACE OF BIRTH    = Clapham, London
| DATE OF DEATH     = 20 September 1933
| PLACE OF DEATH    = Adyar, India
}}
{{DEFAULTSORT:Besant, Annie}}
[[Category:1847 births]]
[[Category:1933 deaths]]
[[Category:People from Clapham]]
[[Category:English Theosophists]]
[[Category:Esoteric Christianity]]
[[Category:British birth control activists]]
[[Category:English occult writers]]
[[Category:English non-fiction writers]]
[[Category:English spiritual writers]]
[[Category:English activists]]
[[Category:English socialists]]
[[Category:Presidents of the Indian National Congress]]
[[Category:English suffragists]]
[[Category:Feminist artists]]
[[Category:History of Chennai]]
[[Category:English women writers]]
[[Category:Dharmic writers]]
[[Category:Alumni of Birkbeck, University of London]]
[[Category:English vegetarians]]
[[Category:Former Anglicans]]
[[Category:Former atheists and agnostics]]
[[Category:Feminism and spirituality]]
[[Category:Scouting and Guiding in India]]
[[Category:Recipients of the Silver Wolf Award]]
[[Category:Members of the Fabian Society]]
[[Category:Women of the Victorian era]]
[[Category:People of the Edwardian era]]
[[Category:Members of the London School Board]]
[[Category:Victorian women writers]]
[[Category:Banaras Hindu University people]]

[[ar:آني بيزنت]]
[[ca:Annie Besant]]
[[de:Annie Besant]]
[[et:Annie Besant]]
[[es:Annie Besant]]
[[fr:Annie Besant]]
[[hi:एनी बेसेन्ट]]
[[it:Annie Besant]]
[[kn:ಅನ್ನಿ ಬೆಸೆಂಟ್]]
[[la:Anna Besant]]
[[ml:ആനി ബസന്റ്]]
[[mr:अॅनी बेझंट]]
[[nl:Annie Besant]]
[[ja:アニー・ベサント]]
[[no:Annie Besant]]
[[pl:Annie Besant]]
[[pt:Annie Wood Besant]]
[[ru:Безант, Анни]]
[[simple:Annie Besant]]
[[sk:Annie Besantová]]
[[fi:Annie Besant]]
[[sv:Annie Besant]]
[[ta:அன்னி பெசண்ட்]]
[[te:అనీ బిసెంట్]]
[[ur:مسز اینی بسنٹ]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
