<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="2003927" ns="0" title="Fondant"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Refimprove|date=November 2009}}
{{distinguish|fondue}}
[[File:Cakeinwhitesatin-1.jpg|thumb|Wedding cake covered and decorated with fondant]]
[[File:Cake with rose 2.jpg|thumb|right|Cake covered with chocolate rolled fondant]]

'''Fondant''' (UK: /'fɒndənt/, US: /'fɑndənt/ or /'fɑndɑnt/, from the French: /fɔ̃.dɑ̃/) is one of several kinds of [[Icing (food)|icing]]-like substance used to decorate or sculpt pastries. The word, in French, means &quot;melting&quot;, coming from the same root as &quot;[[foundry]]&quot; in English.

==Types==

'''Poured fondant''' is a cream [[confection]] used as a filling or coating for [[cakes]], [[pastries]], and [[candies]] or [[sweets]]. In its simplest form, it is [[sugar]] and [[water]] cooked to the [[Candy#Manufacture|soft-ball stage]], cooled slightly, and stirred or beaten until it is an opaque mass of creamy consistency. Sometimes lemon is added to the mixture, mainly for taste. Other flavorings are used as well, as are various colorings. For example, the main filling of a [[Cadbury Creme Egg]] is poured fondant.
'''Rolled fondant''' or '''fondant icing''', which is not the same material as poured fondant, is commonly used to [[cake decorating|decorate wedding cakes]]. It includes gelatin (or [[agar]] in vegetarian recipes) and food-grade [[glycerine]], which keep the sugar pliable and creates a dough-like consistency. It can also be made using powdered sugar and melted marshmallows.  Rolled fondant is rolled out like a pie crust and used to cover the cake.

==Chemistry==
Poured fondant is formed by [[supersaturation|supersaturating]] water with [[sucrose]].  More than twice the sugar will dissolve in water at the boiling point than at room temperature. After the sucrose is dissolved, the solution is left to cool and the sugar will remain dissolved in the supersaturated solution until [[nucleation]] occurs. While the solution is supersaturated, if a [[seed crystal]] (undissolved sucrose) falls into the mix, or if the solution is agitated, the dissolved sucrose crystallizes to form large, crunchy crystals (which is how [[rock candy]] is made). However, if the solution is allowed to cool and then stirred vigorously, it forms many tiny crystals and results in a smooth texture.

==In popular culture==
[[Image:Fondant.JPG|thumb|A fondant-covered cake depicting a sewing kit]]
Fondant is popular on many cake-related [[reality television]] shows in the US, including shows such as ''[[Ace of Cakes]]'', ''[[Ultimate Cake Off]]'', ''[[Cake Boss]]'', and ''[[The Next Great Baker]]'',  all which often showcase decorators creatively decorating complex cake structures with fondant and other types of frosting and icing.

With the increased popularity of such reality shows, fondant has become a more popular way to decorate cakes.{{Citation needed|date=August 2010}}  It is also seen as much easier to use, as well as to be creative with, than the butter cream icing traditionally used to decorate cakes.{{Citation needed|date=August 2010}}  There are several different brands of fondant, and they can be found in major retailers as well as in specialty cake stores; cake stores are known to have a better quality fondant than retail or craft stores.{{Citation needed|date=July 2011}} Alternatively, numerous recipes for making homemade fondant are available.

==References==
{{Reflist}}

==External links==
{{Commons category|Fondant}}
*[http://www.cakedecoratingclasses.org/cake-decorating-tips/cake-decorating-tips-fondant/ Cake Decorating Tips: An Introduction to Fondant]
*[http://www.venuscakes.com/blog/making-a-fondant-rose/2706/ Step by step instructions on making a fondant rose by Venus Cakes]
*[http://www.wikihow.com/Make-Fondant How to make fondant]
*[http://www.cakejournal.com/archives/how-to-make-poured-fondant-icing]

[[Category:Confectionery]]
[[Category:French words and phrases]]
[[Category:Doughs]]

[[da:Fondant]]
[[de:Fondant]]
[[es:Fondant]]
[[fr:Fondant (pâtisserie)]]
[[he:בצק סוכר]]
[[io:Konfekto]]
[[nl:Glazuur (gebak)]]
[[pl:Lukier]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
