<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="2006" ns="0" title="Auschwitz concentration camp"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Hatnote|&quot;Auschwitz&quot; and &quot;Auschwitz-Birkenau&quot; redirect here. For the town, see [[Oświęcim]]. Distinguish from [[Austerlitz]]. Or see [[Auschwitz (disambiguation)]]}}
{{pp-semi-indef}}
{{Infobox concentration camp
| name         = Auschwitz
| image = Birkenau gate.JPG
| image size   =
| caption      = The main entrance to [[extermination camp]] Auschwitz-Birkenau
| alt          =
| location map = Poland
| map alt      =
| map caption  = Location of Auschwitz in contemporary Poland
| latd = 50| latm = 02| lats = 09| latNS = N
| longd= 19| longm= 10| longs= 42| longEW= E
| coordinates type    = region:PL-MA_type:landmark
| coordinates display = inline,title
| other names  = Birkenau
| known for    =
| location     = [[Oświęcim]], [[Polish areas annexed by Nazi Germany]]
| built by     =
| operated by  = the German ''[[Schutzstaffel]]'' (SS), the [[NKVD]] (after WWII)
| original use = Army barracks
| construction =
| in operation = May 1940 – January 1945
| gas chambers =
| prisoner type= mainly Jews, Poles, Roma, Soviet soldiers
| inmates      =
| killed       = 1.1&amp;nbsp;million (estimated)
| liberated by = [[Soviet Union]], January 27, 1945
| notable inmates = [[Viktor Frankl]], [[Primo Levi]], [[Witold Pilecki]], [[Rudolf Vrba]], [[Elie Wiesel]], [[Maximillian Kolbe]]
| notable books   = ''[[If This is a Man]]'', ''[[Night (book)|Night]]'', ''[[Man's Search for Meaning]]''
| website      = [http://en.auschwitz.org.pl/m/ Auschwitz-Birkenau State Museum]
| box width    =
| color        =
}}

'''Concentration camp Auschwitz''' ({{lang-de|Konzentrationslager Auschwitz}} {{IPA-de|ˈaʊʃvɪts||De-Konzentrationslager_Auschwitz.ogg}}) was a network of Nazi [[Nazi concentration camps|concentration]] and [[extermination camp]]s built and operated by the [[Third Reich]] in [[Polish areas annexed by Nazi Germany]] during [[World War II]]. It was the largest of the German concentration camps, consisting of Auschwitz I (the ''Stammlager'' or base camp); Auschwitz II–Birkenau (the ''Vernichtungslager'' or [[extermination camp]]); [[Monowitz concentration camp|Auschwitz III–Monowitz]], also known as Buna–Monowitz (a labor camp); and 45 satellite camps.&lt;ref name=&quot;krakowski&quot;/&gt;

Auschwitz had for a long time been a German name for [[Oświęcim]], the town by and around which the camps were located; the name &quot;Auschwitz&quot; was made the official name again by the Germans after they [[Invasion of Poland (1939)|invaded Poland]] in September 1939. Birkenau, the German translation of ''[[Brzezinka]]'' (= &quot;birch tree&quot;), referred originally to a small Polish village that was destroyed by the Germans to make way for the camp.

Auschwitz II–Birkenau was designated by the ''[[Reichsführer-SS]]'' [[Heinrich Himmler]], Germany's Minister of the Interior, as the place of the &quot;[[Final Solution|final solution of the Jewish question in Europe]]&quot;. From early 1942 until late 1944, transport trains delivered Jews to the camp's gas chambers from all over [[Occupied Europe|Nazi-occupied Europe]].&lt;ref name=&quot;gutman&quot;/&gt; The camp's first commandant, [[Rudolf Höss]], testified after the war at the [[Nuremberg Trials]] that up to three million people had died there (2.5&amp;nbsp;million gassed, and 500,000 from disease and starvation),&lt;ref name=&quot;International Military Tribunal 1946, Page 251&quot;/&gt; a figure since revised to 1.1&amp;nbsp;million, around 90 percent of them Jews.&lt;ref name=&quot;auschwitz.org1&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;piper&quot;/&gt; Others deported to Auschwitz included 150,000 [[Poles]], 23,000 [[Roma (Romani subgroup)|Roma]] and [[Sinti]], 15,000 [[Nazi crimes against Soviet POWs|Soviet prisoners of war]], some 400 [[Jehovah's Witnesses]] and tens of thousands of people of diverse nationalities.&lt;ref name=&quot;dccam&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;auschwitz&quot;/&gt; Those not killed in the gas chambers died of starvation, forced labor, [[infectious disease]], individual executions, and medical experiments.&lt;ref name=&quot;piper1&quot;/&gt;

On January 27, 1945, Auschwitz was liberated by [[Red Army|Soviet troops]], a day commemorated around the world as [[International Holocaust Remembrance Day]]. In 1947, Poland founded a museum on the site of Auschwitz I and II, which by 2010 had seen 29 million visitors—1,300,000 annually—pass through the iron gates crowned with the infamous motto, ''[[Arbeit macht frei]]'' (&quot;work makes free&quot;).&lt;ref name=&quot;International Military Tribunal 1946, Page 251&quot;/&gt;

==Camps==
===Main camps===
[[File:Auschwitz 1944.jpg|thumb|Surveillance photo showing location of three main camps]]
[[File:Map auschwitz deportation 4499-Cut.jpg|thumb|left|Map showing the originating locations in Europe for deportations to Auschwitz concentration camp]]
Located approximately 50&amp;nbsp;km west of [[Kraków]], the Auschwitz complex of camps encompassed a large industrial area rich in natural resources. There were 48 camps in all. The three main camps were Auschwitz I, Auschwitz II-Birkenau, and a work camp called Auschwitz III-Monowitz, or the Buna. Auschwitz I served as the administrative center, and was the site of the deaths of roughly 70,000 people, mostly ethnic Poles and Soviet prisoners of war. Auschwitz II was an extermination camp or ''Vernichtungslager'', the site of the deaths of at least 960,000 Jews, 75,000 Poles, and some 19,000 [[Romani people|Roma]]. Auschwitz III-Monowitz served as a labor camp for the Buna-Werke factory of the [[IG Farben]] concern. The ''[[SS-Totenkopfverbände]]'' (SS-TV) was the SS organization responsible for administering the Nazi concentration camps for the Third Reich. The SS-TV was an independent unit within the [[Schutzstaffel|SS]] with its own ranks and command structure.
''[[Obersturmbannführer]]'' [[Rudolf Höss]] was overall commandant of the Auschwitz complex from May 1940 – November 1943; ''Obersturmbannführer'' [[Arthur Liebehenschel]] from November 1943 – May 1944; and ''[[Sturmbannführer]]'' [[Richard Baer]] from May 1944 – January 1945.

[[Yisrael Gutman]] writes that it was in the concentration camps that [[Adolf Hitler|Hitler]]'s concept of absolute power came to fruition. [[Primo Levi]], who described his year in Auschwitz in ''[[If This Is a Man]]'', wrote:

{{quotation|[N]ever has there existed a state that was really &quot;totalitarian.&quot; ... Never has some form of reaction, a corrective of the total tyranny, been lacking, not even in the Third Reich or Stalin's Soviet Union: in both cases, public opinion, the magistrature, the foreign press, the churches, the feeling for justice and humanity that ten or twenty years of tyranny were not enough to eradicate, have to a greater or lesser extent acted as a brake. Only in the ''Lager'' [camp] was the restraint from below non-existent, and the power of these small [[satrap]]s absolute.&lt;ref name=&quot;quoted&quot;/&gt;}}

===Auschwitz I===
[[File:Auschwitz I Entrance.jpg|thumb|upright|Auschwitz I entrance]]
[[File:Map Auschwitz 1 1940.jpg|thumb|Map of Auschwitz I, shows Polish Tobacco Monopoly building; 1940]]
Auschwitz I was the original camp, serving as the administrative center for the whole complex. The site for the camp (16 one-story buildings) had earlier served as Polish army artillery barracks. It was first suggested as a site for a concentration camp for Polish prisoners by ''[[SS-Oberfuhrer]]'' [[Arpad Wigand]], an aide to [[Higher SS and Police Leader]] for [[Silesia]], [[Erich von dem Bach-Zelewski]]. Bach-Zelewski had been searching for a site to house prisoners in the Silesia region as the local prisons were filled to capacity. [[Richard Glucks]], head of the [[Concentration Camps Inspectorate]], sent former [[Sachsenhausen concentration camp]] commandant, Walter Eisfeld, to inspect the site. Glucks informed ''SS- Reichsfuhrer'' [[Heinrich Himmler]] that a camp would be built on the site on February 21, 1940.&lt;ref name=&quot;rees&quot;/&gt; [[Rudolf Höss]] would oversee the development of the camp and serve as the first commandant, ''SS-Obersturmführer'' [[Josef Kramer]] was appointed Höss's deputy.&lt;ref name=&quot;Gutman 1994, pp. 10, 16&quot;/&gt;

Local residents were evicted, including 1,200 people who lived in shacks around the barracks, creating an empty area of 40&amp;nbsp;km&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt;, which the Germans called the &quot;interest area of the camp&quot;. 300 Jewish residents of [[Oświęcim]] were brought in to lay foundations. From 1940 to 1941 17,000 Polish and Jewish residents of the western districts of [[Oświęcim]] town, from places adjacent to [[Auschwitz Concentration Camp]], were expelled. Germans ordered also expulsions from the villages of [[Broszkowice]], [[Babice, Oświęcim County|Babice]], [[Brzezinka]], [[Rajsko, Oświęcim County|Rajsko]], [[Pławy]], [[Harmęże]], [[Bór, Lesser Poland Voivodeship|Bór]], and Budy.&lt;ref name=&quot;oswiecim&quot;/&gt; [[Expulsion of Poles by Germany|The expulsion of Polish civilians]] was a step towards establishing the Camp Interest Zone, which was set up to isolate the camp from the outside world and to carry out business activity to meet the needs of the [[Schutzstaffel|SS]]. German and ''[[Volksdeutsche]]'' settlers moved into some buildings whose Jewish population had been deported to the ghetto.
{{main|First mass transport to Auschwitz concentration camp}}
The first prisoners (30 German criminal prisoners from the [[Sachsenhausen concentration camp|Sachsenhausen]] camp) arrived in May 1940, intended to act as functionaries within the prison system. [[First mass transport to Auschwitz concentration camp|The first transport of 728 Polish prisoners which included 20 Jews]] arrived on June 14, 1940 from the prison in [[Tarnów]], Poland. They were interned in the former building of the Polish Tobacco Monopoly adjacent to the site, until the camp was ready. The inmate population grew quickly, as the camp absorbed Poland's intelligentsia and dissidents, including the [[Polish resistance movement in World War II|Polish underground resistance]]. By March 1941, 10,900 were imprisoned there, most of them Poles.&lt;ref name=&quot;Gutman 1994, pp. 10, 16&quot;/&gt;

The SS selected some prisoners, often German criminals, as specially privileged supervisors of the other inmates (so-called [[Kapo (concentration camp)|''kapos'']]). Although involved in numerous atrocities, only two Kapos were ever prosecuted for their individual behavior; many were deemed to have had little choice but to act as they did.&lt;ref name=&quot;wittmann&quot;/&gt; The various classes of prisoners were distinguishable by special marks on their clothes; Jews and Soviet prisoners of war were generally treated the worst. All inmates had to work in the associated arms factories, except on Sundays, which were reserved for cleaning and showering. The harsh work requirements, combined with poor nutrition and hygiene, led to high death rates among the prisoners.

Block 11 of Auschwitz was the &quot;prison within the prison&quot;, where violators of the numerous rules were punished. Some prisoners were made to spend the nights in &quot;[[standing cell]]s&quot;. These cells were about {{convert|1.5|m2|sqft|abbr=on}}, and four men would be placed in them; they could do nothing but stand, and were forced during the day to work with the other prisoners. In the basement were located the &quot;starvation cells&quot;; prisoners incarcerated here were given neither food nor water until they were dead.&lt;ref name=&quot;Maximilian Kolbe&quot;/&gt;
[[File:Auschwitz I death block 11 04.jpg|thumb|left|Block 11]]
In the basement were the &quot;dark cells&quot;; these cells had only a very tiny window, and a solid door. Prisoners placed in these cells would gradually suffocate as they used up all of the oxygen in the cell; sometimes the [[SS]] would light a candle in the cell to use up the oxygen more quickly. Many were subjected to hanging with their hands behind their backs for hours, even days, thus dislocating their shoulder joints.&lt;ref name=&quot;rees2&quot;/&gt;

On September 3, 1941, deputy camp commandant SS-''[[Hauptsturmführer]]'' [[Karl Fritzsch|Fritzsch]] experimented on 600 Russian POWs and 250 Polish inmates by gathering them in the basement of Block 11 and gassing them with [[Zyklon B]], a highly lethal [[cyanide]]-based [[pesticide]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Fritsch&quot;/&gt; This paved the way for the use of Zyklon B as an instrument for extermination at Auschwitz, and a gas chamber and crematorium were constructed by converting a bunker. This gas chamber operated from 1941 to 1942, during which time some 60,000 people were killed therein; it was then converted into an air-raid shelter for the use of the SS. This gas chamber still exists, together with the associated crematorium, which was reconstructed after the war using the original components, which remained on-site.&lt;ref&gt;Dwork and van Pelt 1997, p. 364.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Reeves 2009, p. 56.&lt;/ref&gt;
{{clear}}

===Auschwitz II-Birkenau===&lt;!-- This section is linked from [[Treblinka extermination camp]] --&gt;
[[File:Auschwitz-birkenau-main track.jpg|thumb|Auschwitz II-Birkenau]]
Construction on Auschwitz II-Birkenau, the extermination camp, began in October 1941 to ease congestion at the main camp. It was larger than Auschwitz I, and more people passed through its gates than through Auschwitz I. It was designed to hold several categories of prisoners, and to function as an extermination camp in the context of [[Heinrich Himmler]]'s preparations for the [[Final Solution of the Jewish Question]], the extermination of the Jews.&lt;ref name=&quot;Gutman16&quot;/&gt; The first gas chamber at Birkenau was &quot;The Little Red House,&quot; a brick cottage converted into a gassing facility by tearing out the inside and bricking up the walls. It was operational by March 1942. A second brick cottage, &quot;The Little White House,&quot; was similarly converted some weeks later.&lt;ref name=&quot;rees3&quot;/&gt;

The Nazis had committed themselves to the final solution no later than January 1942, the date of the [[Wannsee Conference]]. In his Nuremberg testimony on April 15, 1946, [[Rudolf Höss]], the commandant of Auschwitz, testified that Heinrich Himmler personally ordered him to prepare Auschwitz for that purpose:

{{quotation|In the summer of 1941 I was summoned to Berlin to Reichsführer-SS Himmler to receive personal orders. He told me something to the effect—I do not remember the exact words—that the Fuehrer had given the order for a final solution of the Jewish question. We, the SS, must carry out that order. If it is not carried out now then the Jews will later on destroy the German people. He had chosen Auschwitz on account of its easy access by rail and also because the extensive site offered space for measures ensuring isolation.&lt;ref name=&quot;umkc&quot;/&gt;}}
[[File:Birkenau25August1944.jpg|right|thumb|Picture of Birkenau taken by an American surveillance plane, August 25, 1944]]
British historian [[Laurence Rees]] writes, that Höss may have misremembered the year Himmler said this. Himmler did indeed visit Höss in the summer of 1941, but there is no evidence that the final solution had been planned at this stage. Rees writes that the meeting predates the killings of Jewish men by the ''Einsatzgruppen'' in the East and the expansion of the killings in July 1941. It also predates the [[Wannsee Conference]]. Rees speculates that the conversation with Himmler was most likely in the summer of 1942.&lt;ref name=&quot;Rees53&quot;/&gt; The first gassings, using an industrial gas derived from [[prussic acid]] and known by the brand name [[Zyklon-B]], were carried out at Auschwitz in September 1941.&lt;ref name=&quot;yadvashem&quot;/&gt;

In early 1943, the Nazis decided to increase greatly the gassing capacity of Birkenau. Crematorium II, originally designed as a mortuary, with morgues in the basement and ground-level furnaces, was converted into a killing factory by placing a gas-tight door on the morgues and adding vents for [[Zyklon B]] and ventilation equipment to remove the gas.&lt;ref name=&quot;holocaust-history&quot;/&gt; It went into operation in March. Crematorium III was built using the same design. Crematoria IV and V, designed from the start as gassing centers, were also constructed that spring. By June 1943 all four crematoria were operational. Most of the victims were killed during the period afterwards.&lt;ref name=&quot;rees4&quot;/&gt;

The camp was staffed partly by prisoners, some of whom were selected to be ''kapos'' (orderlies, most of whom were convicts) and ''[[sonderkommando]]s'' (workers at the crematoria). The ''kapos'' were responsible for keeping order in the barrack huts; the ''sonderkommandos'' prepared new arrivals for gassing (ordering them to remove their clothing and surrender their personal possessions) and transferred corpses from the gas chambers to the furnaces, having first pulled out any gold that the victims might have had in their teeth. Members of these groups were killed periodically. The ''kapos'' and ''sonderkommandos'' were supervised by members of the SS; altogether 6,000 SS members worked at Auschwitz.

Command of the women's camp, which was separated from the men's area by the incoming railway line, was held in turn by [[Johanna Langefeld]], [[Maria Mandel]], and [[Elisabeth Volkenrath]].

====The Gypsy camp====
[[File:Romani Kids ww2.jpg|thumb|300px|''Zigeunermischlinge'' (&quot;Gypsy half-breeds&quot;) used in an [[Anthropology|anthropological]] study by German psychologist [[Eva Justin]]. They were sent to the &quot;Gypsy camp&quot; and murdered when the camp was liquidated]]
On December 1942, Heinrich Himmler issued an order to send all [[Sinti]] and [[Romani people|Roma]] (gypsies) to concentration camps with Auschwitz being one of the main camps; they had been previously sent to internment camps and ghettos such as the [[Lodz ghetto]], to which 5,000 ''Ungrika'' (Hungarian) Roma from [[Burgenland]], Austria were sent.&lt;ref&gt;Lucjan Dobroszycki: The Chronicle of the Lodz Ghetto, 1941-1944, p.82, Yale University Press (1987) ISBN 0300039247&lt;/ref&gt;  A separate camp for the Roma was set up at Auschwitz II-Birkenau known as the ''Zigeunerfamilienlager'' (&quot;Gypsy Family Camp&quot;). The first transport of German Gypsies arrived on February 26, 1943,and housed in Section B-IIe of Asuchwitz II. The &quot;Gypsy Family Camp&quot;, which was still under construction at the time was to become a separate subcamp within Auschwitz II. The camp would eventually contain 32 residential and 6 sanitation barracks and house a total of 20,967 Romani men, women, and children. This does not include a transport of approximately 1,700 Polish Sinti and Roma men, women, and children mentioned which arrived from [[Białystok]] on March 23, 1943. Some of the people on the transport had [[typhus]]; to avoid an outbreak in the camp they were all murdered in the gas chamber.

Amongst the victims who were killed after being shipped to the &quot;Gypsy camp&quot; was 9-year-old Dutch girl [[Settela Steinbach|Anna Maria Steinbach]] (Settela) who appears in an iconic haunting still image from a film peering out from a transport train that would take her from the [[Westerbork concentration camp|Westerbork detention camp]] in the [[Netherlands]] to her eventual death in the gas chambers at Auschwitz. Steinbach was believed to be Jewish until research uncovered her Sinti heritage in 1994.&lt;ref&gt;Simone Gigliotti: The Train Journey: Transit, Captivity, and Witnessing in the Holocaust, p. 13; Berghahn Books (2010) 
ISBN 1845457854&lt;/ref&gt;

German psychologist [[Eva Justin]] did a pseudo-scientific study for her doctoral dissertation, titled &quot;Lebensschicksale artfremd erzogener Zigeunerkinder und ihrer Nachkommen&quot; (English: the life history of alien-raised Gypsy children and their descendants). The basis of the study was to ascertain the prevalence of &quot;Gypsy traits&quot; in &quot;''Zigeunermischlinge''&quot;, (Gypsy half-breed) half-Romani children, many half-German, were taken from their parents and raised in orphanages and foster homes without any contact with Romani culture.&lt;ref&gt;Nicholas Stargardt: Witnesses of war: children's lives under the Nazis, p.ii; (2005)ISBN 1400040884&lt;/ref&gt;

Of the 41 children in the study at St. Josefspflege orphanage in [[Mulfingen]], [[Germany]], 39 of them (20 boys and 19 girls) were shipped to Auschwitz on May 6, 1944. Of the 39 children, two survived Auschwitz; all the others were killed, most during the final liquidation of the camp on the night of August 2–3, 1944.&lt;ref&gt;Fredrik Barth: One discipline, four ways: British, German, French, and American anthropology, p. 122, University Of Chicago Press;(2005) ISBN 0226038297&lt;/ref&gt; 

During the final liquidation of the Gypsy camp, the remaining 2,897 Romani in the camp were sent to the gas chambers.&lt;ref&gt;Toby F. Sonneman: Shared sorrows: a gypsy family remembers the Holocaust pp.73-74, University Of Hertfordshire Press (2002) ISBN 1902806107&lt;/ref&gt; The murder of the Romani people by the Nazis during World War II is known in the [[Romani language]] as the ''&quot;[[Porajmos|The Porajmos]]&quot;'' (&quot;The Devouring&quot;).&lt;ref&gt;Levon Chorbajian, George Shirinian: Studies in comparative genocide, p. 223&lt;/ref&gt;

===Auschwitz III===
{{Main|Monowitz concentration camp}}
[[File:Buna Werke.png|thumb|[[Buna-Werke]], [[Monowitz]] and subcamps]]
'''Monowitz''' (also called '''Monowitz-Buna''' or '''Auschwitz III'''), initially established as a subcamp of Auschwitz concentration camp, Monowitz became one of the three main camps in the Auschwitz concentration camp system, with an additional 45 subcamps in the surrounding area. It was named after the town of Monowice (German, Monowitz) upon which it was built which was located in the annexed portion of [[Poland]]. The camp was established in October 1942 by the SS at the behest of [[I.G. Farben]] executives to provide slave labor for their Buna-Werke (Buna Works) industrial complex. The name ''Buna'' was derived from the [[butadiene]]-based synthetic rubber and the chemical symbol for sodium Na utilized in the process of synthetic rubber production developed in Germany. Various other German industrial enterprises built factories with their own subcamps, such as [[Siemens-Schuckert]]'s [[Bobrek concentration camp|Bobrek]] subcamp, close to Monowitz in order to profit from the use of slave labor. The German armaments manufacturer [[Krupp]] headed by SS member [[Alfried Krupp]] also built their own manufacturing facilities near Monowitz.&lt;ref name=&quot;contributions&quot;/&gt;

Monowitz was built as an ''[[arbeitslager]]'' (workcamp), it also contained a &quot;ArbeitsausbildungLager&quot; (Labor Education Camp)&quot; for non-Jewish prisoners perceived not up to par with German work standards. It held approximately 12,000 prisoners, the great majority of whom were Jewish, but also carried non-Jewish criminals and political prisoners. Monowitz prisoners were leased out by the SS to [[IG Farben]] to labor at the Buna-Werke, a collection of chemical factories including those used to manufacture ''Buna''  ([[synthetic rubber]]) and [[synthetic oil]]. The SS charged IG Farben three Reichsmarks (RM) per hour for unskilled workers, RM4 per hour for skilled workers and RM1½ for children. [[Elie Weisel]] author of the Pulitzer Prize winning book ''[[Night (book)|Night]]'' was a teenage inmate at Monowitz along with his father. The life expectancy of Jewish workers at Buna Werke was three to four months, for those working in the outlying mines, only one month. Those deemed unfit for work were gassed at Birkenau or sent &quot;to Birkenau&quot; (''nach Birkenau''), according to a euphemism used in I.G. Farben record books.&lt;ref name=&quot;gutman5&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;publisher&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;psychology&quot;/&gt;

[[Fritz Löhner-Beda]] (prisoner number 68561) was a popular song lyricist who was murdered in Monowitz-Buna at the behest of an I.G. Farben executive, as his friend Raymond van den Straaten testified at the Nuremberg trial of 24 I.G. Farben executives:
{{quotation|''One day, two Buna inmates, Dr. Raymond van den Straaten and Dr. Fritz Löhner-Beda, were going about their work when a party of visiting I.G. Farben dignitaries passed by. One of the directors pointed to Dr. Löhner-Beda and said to his SS companion, ‘This Jewish swine could work a little faster.’ Another director then chanced the remark, ‘If they can’t work, let them perish in the gas chamber.’ After the inspection was over, Dr. Löhner-Beda was pulled out of the work party and was beaten and kicked until, a dying man, he was left in the arms of his inmate friend, to end his life in I.G. Auschwitz.''”&lt;ref name=&quot;schwarberg&quot;/&gt;}}

===Subcamps===
{{See|List of subcamps of Auschwitz}}
[[File:USHMM95273 -Siemens factory in KZ Bobrek.jpg|thumb|left|Prisoners building airplane parts at [[Siemens-Schuckert]] factory at Bobrek sub-camp]]
There were 45 smaller satellite camps, some of them tens of kilometers from the main camps, with prisoner populations ranging from several dozen to several thousand.&lt;ref name=&quot;Gutman17&quot;/&gt; The largest were built at [[Trzebinia]], [[Blechhammer]] and Althammer. Women's subcamps were constructed at Budy, [[Pławy]], [[Zabrze]], [[Gliwice|Gleiwitz]] I, II, III, [[Rajsko, Oświęcim County|Rajsko]], and Lichtenwerden (now Světlá). The satellite camps were named ''Aussenlager'' (external camp), ''Nebenlager'' (extension or subcamp), and ''Arbeitslager'' (labor camp).&lt;ref name=&quot;Gutman17&quot;/&gt;

Danuta Czech of the [[Auschwitz-Birkenau State Museum]] writes that most of the satellite camps were pressed into service on behalf of German industry. Inmates of 28 of them worked for the German armaments industry. Nine camps were set up near foundries and other metal works, six near coal mines, six supplied prisoners to work in chemical plants, and three to light industry. One was built next to a plant making construction materials and another near a food processing plant. Apart from the weapons and construction industries, prisoners were also made to work in forestry and farming.&lt;ref name=&quot;danuta&quot;/&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
{{clear}}

==Command and control==
{{Main|SS command of Auschwitz concentration camp}}
[[File:Auschwitz-Richard Baer Karl Hocker Enno Lolling.jpg|thumb|300px|SS-[[Standartenführer]] Dr. [[Enno Lolling]], the director of the Office for Sanitation and Hygiene in the Inspectorate of Concentration Camps looks over a document with SS-[[Sturmbannführer]] [[Richard Baer]], commandant of Auschwitz, and his [[adjutant]] SS-[[Obersturmführer]] [[Karl-Friedrich Höcker]] (left to right)]]
Due to its large size and key role in the Nazi genocide program, the Auschwitz Concentration Camp encompassed personnel from several different branches of the SS, some of which held overlapping and shared areas of responsibility. In all, there were over 7000 members of the SS [[SS personnel assigned to Auschwitz|assigned to Auschwitz]] during the entirety of the camp's existence.

The overall command authority for the entire camp was the SS-Economics Main Office, known as the ''[[SS-Wirtschafts-Verwaltungshauptamt]]'' or SS-WVHA. Within the WVHA, it was Department D (the [[Concentration Camps Inspectorate]]) which commanded directly the activities at Auschwitz.

The command personnel of Auschwitz, who lived on site and ran the camp complex, were all members of the ''[[SS-Totenkopfverbande]]'', or the SS-TV. Due to a 1941 personnel directive from the ''[[SS Personalhauptamt]]'', members of the SS-TV were also considered full members of the ''[[Waffen-SS]]''. Such personnel were further authorized to display the Death's Head Collar Patch, indicating full membership in both the SS-TV and Waffen-SS.

The ''[[Gestapo]]'' also maintained a large office at Auschwitz, staffed by uniformed Gestapo officers and personnel. Auschwitz also maintained a medical corps, led by [[Eduard Wirths]], whose doctors and medical personnel were from various backgrounds in the SS. The infamous [[Joseph Mengele]], for example, was a combat field doctor in the Waffen-SS before transferring to Auschwitz after being wounded in combat.

Internal camp order was under the authority of another SS group, answering directly to the Camp Commander through officers known by the title ''[[Lagerführer]]''. Each of the three main camps at Auschwitz was assigned a ''Lagerführer'' to which answered several SS-non-commissioned officers known as ''[[Rapportführer]]s''. The ''Rapportführer'' commanded several ''[[Blockführer]]'' who oversaw order within individual prisoner barracks. Assisting the SS with this task was a large collection of Kapos, who were trustee prisoners. SS personnel assigned to the gas chambers were technically under the same chain of command as other internal camp SS personnel, but in practice were segregated and worked and lived locally on site at the crematorium. In all, there were usually four SS personnel per gas chamber, led by a non-commissioned officer, who oversaw around one hundred Jewish prisoners (known as the ''Sonderkommando'') forced to assist in the extermination process. The actual delivery of the gas to the victims was always handled by the SS, this was accomplished by a special SS unit known as the &quot;Hygiene Division&quot; which would drive [[Zyklon B]] to the crematorium in an ambulance and then empty the canister into the gas chamber. The Hygiene Division was under the control of the Auschwitz Medical Corps, with the Zyklon B ordered and delivered through the camp supply system.&lt;ref name=&quot;eyewitness&quot;/&gt;

External camp security was under the authority of an SS unit known as the &quot;Guard Battalion&quot;, or ''Wachbattalion''. These guards manned watchtowers and patrolled the perimeter fences of the camp. During an emergency, such as a prisoner uprising, the Guard Battalion could be deployed within the camp as the need arose; a scene in the film ''[[The Grey Zone]]'' depicts the Guard Battalion entering and machine gunning a crematorium after the Jewish Sonderkommando rose up against the normal contingent of SS guards.

Various administrative and supply SS personnel were also assigned to Auschwitz, usually &quot;out of the way&quot; of the more horrific activities of the camp, based out of command administrative offices in the main camp of Auschwitz I. [[Oskar Gröning]] is one such well known Auschwitz clerk, who has appeared on several documentaries speaking about life in Auschwitz for the SS, and how living in the camp was in fact an enjoyable experience.&lt;ref name=&quot;auschwitz6&quot;/&gt;  Auschwitz also maintained a [[motor pool]] as well as an arsenal from which all the SS personnel would draw weapons and ammunition, although several of the SS were known to purchase their own handguns and pistols.

In addition to the command and control proper of Auschwitz Concentration Camp, the camp further frequently received orders and directives from other organs of the SS and the Nazi state. The camp itself was located in the Nazi Region of [[Upper Silesia]] and therefore under the geographical control of the corresponding ''[[Gauleiter]]'' (prior to 1942, the camp had been under geographical jurisdiction of the [[General Government]]). Furthermore, the camp fell under the subordinate command of the [[SS and Police Leader]] of the region and was often issued orders from the ''[[SS-Reichssicherheitshauptamt]]'' or RSHA, which was a key SS organization involved in the genocide program. ''Reichsführer-SS'' [[Heinrich Himmler]] was known to issue orders to the camp commander, bypassing all other chains of command, in response to his own directives. Himmler would also occasionally receive broad instructions from [[Adolf Hitler]] or [[Hermann Göring]], which he would interprete as he saw fit and transmit to the Auschwitz Camp Commander.

==Selection process and genocide==
{{multiple image
 | align     = right
 | direction = horizontal
 | image1    = Selection Birkenau ramp.jpg
 | width1    = 255
 | caption1  = [[Hungarian Jew]]s on the ''Judenrampe'' (Jewish ramp) after disembarking from the [[Holocaust train|transport trains]], to be sent '''''rechts!''''' – to the right – meant labor; '''''links!''''' – to the left – the [[gas chamber]]s. Photo from the [[Auschwitz Album]] (May 1944)
 | image2    = Bundesarchiv Bild 183-N0827-318, KZ Auschwitz, Ankunft ungarischer Juden.jpg
 | width2    = 255
 | caption2  = Hungarian Jewish mothers, children, elderly and infirm sent to the left after 'selection&quot; They will be murdered in the gas chamber soon after (May 1944)&lt;ref name=&quot;financing&quot;/&gt;}}

By July 1942, the SS were conducting the infamous &quot;selections,&quot; in which incoming Jews were divided into those deemed able to work, who were sent to the right and admitted into the camp, and those who were sent to the left and immediately gassed.&lt;ref name=&quot;rees7&quot;/&gt; Prisoners were transported from all over German-occupied Europe by rail, arriving in daily convoys. The SS forced an orchestra to play as new inmates walked towards their &quot;selection&quot; and possible extermination; the musicians had the highest suicide rate of anyone in the camps, besides ''[[Sonderkommandos]]''.&lt;ref name=&quot;compositions&quot;/&gt; The group selected to die, about three-quarters of the total, included almost all children, women with children, all the elderly, and all those who appeared on brief and superficial inspection by an SS doctor not to be completely fit. Auschwitz II-Birkenau claimed more victims than any other German extermination camp, despite coming into use after all the others.
[[File:Güterwagen Oppeln der DR (heute im Besitz der Freunde der historischen Hafenbahn e.V.).jpg|thumb|left|upright|A [[Deutsche Reichsbahn]] &quot;Güterwagen&quot; (goods wagon), one of the types used for deportations]]
SS officers told the victims they were to take a shower and undergo delousing. The victims would undress in an outer chamber and walk into the gas chamber, which was disguised as a shower facility, complete with dummy shower heads. After the doors were shut, SS men would dump in the cyanide pellets via holes in the roof or windows on the side. In Auschwitz II-Birkenau, more than 20,000 people could be gassed and cremated each day. The Nazis used a [[cyanide]] gas produced from Zyklon B pellets, manufactured by two companies who had acquired licensing rights to the patent held by [[IG Farben]].&lt;!--The following needs a source: The two companies were [[Tesch &amp; Stabenow]], of Hamburg, who supplied two tons of the crystals each month, and [[Degesch]], of [[Dessau]], who produced three-quarters of a ton. The bills of lading were produced at Nuremberg.--&gt;  Despite the thick concrete walls of the gas chambers, screaming and moaning from within could be heard outside for 15 to 20 minutes. In one failed attempt to muffle the noise, two motorcycle engines were revved up to full throttle nearby, but the sound of yelling could be heard over the engines.&lt;ref name=&quot;ReferenceA&quot;/&gt;

''Sonderkommandos'' removed gold teeth from the corpses of gas chamber victims; the gold was melted down and collected by the SS. The belongings of the arrivals were seized by the SS and sorted in an area of the camp called &quot;Canada,&quot; so-called because Canada was seen as a land of plenty. Many of the SS at the camp enriched themselves by pilfering the confiscated property.&lt;ref name=&quot;rees8&quot;/&gt;

The gas chambers worked to their fullest capacity from April–July 1944, during the [[History of the Jews in Hungary#Occupation and deportation|massacre of Hungary's Jews]]. Hungary was an ally of Germany during the war, but it had resisted turning over its Jews to the Germans until Germany invaded in March 1944. From April until July 9, 1944, 475,000 Hungarian Jews, half of the pre-war population, were deported to Auschwitz, at a rate of 12,000 a day for a considerable part of that period.&lt;ref name=&quot;autogenerated&quot;/&gt; The incoming volume was so great that the SS resorted to burning corpses in open-air pits as well as in the crematoria.&lt;ref name=&quot;dwork&quot;/&gt;

{| class=&quot;wikitable&quot; style=&quot;text-align:left; margin-left:1em; float:center&quot;
|bgcolor=&quot;B0CCE5&quot; colspan=&quot;5&quot;|&lt;div align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;Speech given to condemned Jews by ''Obersturmführer'' [[Franz Hössler]] &lt;/div&gt;
|-
|bgcolor=&quot;FBF4CE&quot; colspan=&quot;5&quot;|[[File:Franz Hoessler.jpeg|thumb|right|140px|[[Franz Hoessler]]]]
Speech ([[paraphrased]]) given by ''Obersturmführer'' [[Franz Hössler]] to a group of Greek Jews in the undressing room just prior to being killed in the gas chamber:&lt;ref name=&quot;klarsfeld&quot;/&gt;

&quot;On behalf of the camp administration I bid you welcome. This is not a holiday resort but a labor camp. Just as our soldiers risk their lives at the front to gain victory for the Third Reich, you will have to work here for the welfare of a new Europe. How you tackle this task is entirely up to you. The chance is there for every one of you. We shall look after your health, and we shall also offer you well-paid work. After the war we shall assess everyone according to his merits and treat him accordingly.&quot;

&quot;Now, would you please all get undressed. Hang your clothes on the hooks we have provided and please remember your number [of the hook]. When you've had your bath there will be a bowl of soup and coffee or tea for all. Oh yes, before I forget, after your bath, please have ready your certificates, diplomas, school reports and any other documents so that we can employ everybody according to his or her training and ability.&quot;

&quot;Would diabetics who are not allowed sugar report to staff on duty after their baths&quot;.
|}

===Life in the camps===
The prisoners' day began at 4:30&amp;nbsp;am with &quot;reveille&quot; or roll call, with 30 minutes allowed for morning ablutions. After roll call, the ''Kommando'', or work details, would walk to their place of work, five abreast, wearing striped camp fatigues, no underwear, and wooden shoes without socks, most of the time ill-fitting, which caused great pain. A prisoner's orchestra (such as the [[Women's Orchestra of Auschwitz]]) was forced to play grotesquely cheerful music as the workers marched through the gates in step.&lt;ref name=&quot;confronting&quot;/&gt; [[Kapo (concentration camp)|''Kapos'']]—prisoners who had been promoted to foremen—were responsible for the prisoners' behavior while they worked, as was an SS escort. The working day lasted 12 hours during the summer, and a little less in the winter. No rest periods were allowed. One prisoner would be assigned to the latrines to measure the time the workers took to empty their bladders and bowels.&lt;ref name=&quot;gutman9&quot;/&gt;

After work, there was a mandatory evening roll call. If a prisoner was missing, the others had to remain standing in place until he was either found or the reason for his absence discovered, even if it took hours, regardless of the weather conditions. After roll call, there were individual and collective punishments, depending on what had happened during the day, and after these, the prisoners were allowed to retire to their blocks for the night to receive their bread rations and water. Curfew was two or three hours later, the prisoners sleeping in long rows of wooden bunks, lying in and on their clothes and shoes to prevent them from being stolen.&lt;ref name=&quot;gutman10&quot;/&gt;

===Medical experiments===
{{Main|Nazi human experimentation}}
[[File:Auschwitz Mengele Block 10.jpg|thumb|left|Block 10, the medical experimentation block]]
German doctors performed a wide variety of experiments on prisoners at Auschwitz. SS doctors tested the efficacy of [[X-rays]] as a [[forced sterilization|sterilization]] device by administering large doses to female prisoners. Prof. Dr. [[Carl Clauberg]] injected chemicals into women's [[uteruses]] in an effort to glue them shut. [[Bayer]], then a subsidiary of [[IG Farben]], bought prisoners to use as [[Human subject research|guinea pigs]] for testing new drugs.&lt;ref name=&quot;rees11&quot;/&gt;

The most infamous doctor at Auschwitz was [[Josef Mengele]], known as the &quot;Angel of Death&quot;. Particularly interested in research on [[identical twins]], Mengele performed cruel experiments on them, such as inducing diseases in one twin and killing the other when the first died to perform comparative [[autopsies]]. He also took a special interest in dwarfs, and he deliberately induced [[gangrene]] in twins, dwarfs and other prisoners to study the effects.&lt;ref name=&quot;rees12&quot;/&gt;

Mengele, at the behest of fellow Nazi physician [[Kurt Heissmeyer]], was responsible for picking the twenty Jewish children to be used in Heissmeyers' pseudoscientific&lt;ref name=&quot;bullenhuser&quot;/&gt; medical experiments at the [[Neuengamme concentration camp]]. These children, at the conclusion of the experiments, were infamously hanged from wall hooks in the basement of the [[Bullenhuser Damm]] school in Hamburg.
{{clear}}

===Jewish skeleton collection===
{{Main|Jewish skeleton collection}}
[[File:Menachem taffel.jpg|thumb|260px|The [[cadaver]] of Berlin dairy merchant Menachem Taffel. Deported to Auschwitz in March 1943 along with his wife and child who were gassed upon arrival. He was chosen to be an anatomical specimen, shipped to [[Natzweiler-Struthof]] and murdered in the gas chamber in August 1943]]
The Jewish skeleton collection was obtained from among a pool of 115 Jewish inmates at Auschwitz, chosen for their perceived stereotypical racial characteristics. [[Rudolf Brandt]] and [[Wolfram Sievers]], general manager of the [[Ahnenerbe]], were responsible for collecting the skeletons for the collection of the Anatomy Institute at the [[Reichsuniversität Straßburg|Reich University of Strasbourg]] in the [[Alsace]] region of [[Occupied France]]. Due to a [[typhus]] epidemic, the candidates chosen for the skeleton collection were [[quarantine]]d in order to prevent them from becoming ill and ruining their value as anatomical specimens; from a letter written by Sievers in June 1943: &quot;Altogether 115 persons were worked on, 79 were Jews, 30 were Jewesses, 2 were Poles, and 4 were Asiatics. At the present time these prisoners are segregated by sex and are under quarantine in the two hospital buildings of Auschwitz.&quot;

The collection was sanctioned by Heinrich Himmler and under the direction of [[August Hirt]].

Ultimately 87 of the inmates were shipped to [[Natzweiler-Struthof]]. The deaths of 86 of these inmates was, in the words of Hirt, &quot;induced&quot; at a jury rigged gassing facility over the course of a few days in August 1943. One of the victims was shot by the SS when he fought entering the gas chamber. The corpses; 57 men and 29 women were sent to Strasbourg. [[Josef Kramer]] who would become the last commandant of [[Bergen Belsen]] personally carried out the gassing of 80 of the victims. In 1944 with the approach of the allies, there was concern over the possibility of the corpses being discovered, at this point they had still not been defleshed. The first part of the process for this &quot;collection&quot; was to make anatomical casts of the bodies prior to reducing them to skeletons. In September, 1944 Sievers telegrammed Brandt: &quot;The collection can be defleshed and rendered unrecognizable. This, however, would mean that the whole work had been done for nothing – at least in part – and that this singular collection would be lost to science, since it would be impossible to make plaster casts afterwards.&quot;

Brandt and Sievers would be indicted, tried and convicted in the Doctor's Trial in Nuremberg. Hirt committed suicide in [[Bizau|Schonenbach]], Austria, on June 2, 1945 with a gunshot to the head.&lt;ref name=&quot;publications&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;international&quot;/&gt;
The names and biographical information of the murder victims were published in the book ''Die Namen der Nummern'' (The Names of the Numbers) by German historian Dr. Hans-Joachim Lang.&lt;ref name=&quot;gebundene&quot;/&gt;

==Escapes, resistance, and the Allies' knowledge of the camps==
{{See|Auschwitz bombing debate|Witold Pilecki|Rudolf Vrba}}
[[File:Pilecki ausch f.jpg|thumb|[[Witold Pilecki]], the only known person to volunteer to be imprisoned at Auschwitz concentration camp (1941)]]
Information regarding Auschwitz was available to the Allies during the years 1940–43 by the accurate and frequent reports of Polish Army Captain [[Witold Pilecki]]. Pilecki was the only known person to volunteer to be imprisoned at Auschwitz concentration camp, spending 945 days there, not only actively gathering evidence of genocide and supplying it to the British in London by [[Polish resistance movement in World War II|Polish resistance movement]] organization [[Home Army]] but also organizing resistance structures at the camp known as ZOW, [[Związek Organizacji Wojskowej]].&lt;ref name=&quot;ipn&quot;/&gt; His first report was smuggled to the outside world in November 1940, through an inmate who was released from the camp.&lt;ref name=&quot;publishers&quot;/&gt; He eventually escaped on April 27, 1943, but his personal report of mass killings was dismissed as exaggeration by the Allies, as were his previous ones.&lt;ref name=ac/&gt;

The attitude of the Allies changed with receipt of the very detailed [[Vrba-Wetzler report]], compiled by two Jewish prisoners, [[Rudolf Vrba]] and [[Alfréd Wetzler]], who escaped on April 7, 1944, and which finally convinced Allied leaders of the truth about Auschwitz. Details from the Vrba-Wetzler report were broadcast on June 15, 1944 by the BBC, and on June 20 by ''The New York Times'', causing the Allies to put pressure on the Hungarian government to stop the mass deportation of Jews to the camp.&lt;ref name=&quot;karny&quot;/&gt;

Starting with a plea from the Slovakian rabbi [[Chaim Michael Dov Weissmandl|Weissmandl]] in May 1944, there was a growing campaign to persuade the Allies to bomb Auschwitz or the railway lines leading to it. At one point [[Winston Churchill]] ordered that such a plan be prepared, but he was told that bombing the camp would most likely kill prisoners without disrupting the killing operation, and that bombing the railway lines was not technically feasible. The debate over what could have been done, or what should have been attempted even if success was unlikely, has continued ever since.
{{-}}

===Underground media===
Inmates were able to distribute information from the camp without escaping themselves. The ''Auschwitzer Echo'' was an [[Polish underground press|underground newspaper]] published by inmates and distributed as well to the resistance movement in [[Kraków]].&lt;ref name=&quot;widerstandsgruppen&quot;/&gt; Writers included the [[Communist Party of Germany|Communist Party]] member Bruno Baum. A [[shortwave]] transmitter hidden in Block 11 sent information directly to the [[Polish government-in-exile]] in London.&lt;ref name=&quot;rubeigh&quot;/&gt;
These reports were the first revelation about the [[Holocaust]] and were the principal source of intelligence on Auschwitz for the Western Allies. Nonetheless, those reports were for a long time discarded as &quot;too extreme&quot; by the Allies.&lt;ref name=&quot;DE&quot;/&gt;

===Birkenau revolt===
[[File:Auschwitz Birkenau Krematorium IV - 05.jpg|thumb|Ruins of Crematorium IV, blown up in the revolt]]
By 1943, resistance organizations had developed in the camp. These organizations helped a few prisoners escape; these escapees took with them news of exterminations, such as the killing of hundreds of thousands of Jews transported from Hungary between May and July 1944. On October 7, 1944, the Jewish ''[[Sonderkommando]]s'' (those inmates kept separate from the main [[Internment|camp]] and put to work in the gas chambers and crematoria) of Birkenau Kommando III staged an uprising. They attacked the [[SS]] with makeshift weapons: stones, axes, hammers, other work tools and homemade [[grenade]]s. They caught the SS guards by surprise, overpowered them and blew up the Crematorium IV, using [[explosives]] smuggled in from a weapons factory by female inmates. At this stage they were joined by the Birkenau Kommando I of the Crematorium II, which also overpowered their guards and broke out of the [[Compound (enclosure)|compound]]. Hundreds of prisoners escaped, but were all soon captured and, along with an additional group who participated in the [[revolt]], executed.&lt;ref name=&quot;rees13&quot;/&gt;

There were also plans for a general uprising in [[Auschwitz]], coordinated with an [[Allies of World War II|Allied]] [[airstrike|air raid]] and a Polish resistance ([[Armia Krajowa]], Home Army) attack from the outside.&lt;ref name=&quot;ac&quot;/&gt; That plan was authored by Polish resistance fighter, [[Witold Pilecki]], who organized in Auschwitz an underground Union of Military Organization – ([[Związek Organizacji Wojskowej]], ZOW). Pilecki and ZOW hoped that the Allies would drop arms or troops into the camp (most likely the [[Polish 1st Independent Parachute Brigade]], based in Britain), and that the Home Army would organize an assault on the camp from outside. By 1943, however, he realized that the Allies had no such plans. Meanwhile, the Gestapo redoubled its efforts to ferret out ZOW members, succeeding in killing many of them. Pilecki decided to break out of the camp, with the hope of personally convincing Home Army leaders that a rescue attempt was a valid option. He escaped on the night of April 26 – 27, 1943, but his plan was not accepted by the Home Army as the Allies considered his reports about the Holocaust exaggerated.&lt;ref name=&quot;ac&quot; /&gt;

===Individual escape attempts===
[[File:Mala zimetbaum.jpg|thumb|right|Twenty-two year old [[Mala Zimetbaum]], proficient in five languages, briefly escaped Auschwitz with boyfriend Edek Galinski]]
At least 802 prisoners attempted to escape from the Auschwitz camps during the years of their operation, of which 144 were successful. The fates of 331 of the escapees are still unknown.&lt;ref name=&quot;auschwitz14&quot;/&gt; A common punishment for escape attempts was death by starvation; the families of successful escapees were sometimes arrested and interned in Auschwitz and prominently displayed to deter others. If someone did manage to escape, the SS would pick 10 people at random from the prisoner's block and starve them to death.&lt;ref name=&quot;rees15&quot;/&gt;

The most spectacular escape from Auschwitz took place on June 20, 1942, when Ukrainian Eugeniusz Bendera and three Poles, [[Kazimierz Piechowski]], Stanisław Gustaw Jaster and Józef Lempart made a daring escape.&lt;ref name=&quot;piechowski&quot;/&gt; The escapees were dressed as members of the ''[[SS-Totenkopfverbände]]'', fully armed and in an SS staff car. They drove out the main gate in a stolen automobile, a [[Steyr automobile|Steyr]] 220 belonging to [[Rudolf Höss]]. Jaster carried with him a report about conditions in the camp, written by [[Witold Pilecki]]. The Germans never recaptured any of them.&lt;ref name=&quot;Auschwitz.org.pl&quot;/&gt;

In 1943, the &quot;''Kampfgruppe Auschwitz''&quot; was organised with the aim to send out as much information about what was happening in Auschwitz as possible. They buried notes in the ground in the hope a liberator would find them and smuggled out photos of the crematoria and gas chambers.&lt;ref name=&quot;holocaust&quot;/&gt;

June 24, 1944, [[Mala Zimetbaum]] escaped with her Polish boyfriend, Edek Galinski. They also wanted to smuggle out deportation lists Zimetbaum had been able to copy due to her translator job in the office of the &quot;''Lagerleitung''&quot;. They both were arrested on July 6 near the Slovakian frontier and sentenced to be executed on September 15, 1944 in Birkenau; Galinski managed to kill himself before being executed, while Zimetbaum, having failed to commit suicide, died finally after being tortured by the SS.&lt;ref name=&quot;paperbacks&quot;/&gt;
{{clear}}

==Evacuation, death marches, and liberation==
{{See|Death marches (Holocaust)}}
{{multiple image
 | align     = right
 | direction = horizontal
 | image1    = Dachau death march.jpg
 | width1    = 200
 | caption1  = A [[Death marches (Holocaust)|Death march]] in the final days of the war
 | image2    = Auschwitz Liberated January 1945.jpg
 | width2    = 190
 | caption2  = Survivors at the camp liberated by the Red Army in January 1945}}
The last selection took place on October 30, 1944. The next month, Heinrich Himmler ordered the crematoria destroyed before the [[Red Army]] reached the camp. The gas chambers of Birkenau were blown up by the SS in January 1945 in an attempt to hide the German crimes from the advancing Soviet troops.&lt;ref name=&quot;Auschwitz: The Nazis &amp; the Final Solutiuon&quot;/&gt; The SS command sent orders on January 17, 1945 calling for the execution of all prisoners remaining in the camp, but in the chaos of the Nazi retreat the order was never carried out. On January 17, 1945, Nazi personnel started to evacuate the facility. Nearly 60,000 prisoners were forced on a [[Death marches (Holocaust)|death march]] toward a camp in [[Wodzisław Śląski]] (German: ''[[Loslau]]''). Those too weak or sick to walk were left behind. These remaining 7,500 prisoners were liberated by the [[322nd Rifle Division (Soviet Union)|322nd Rifle Division]] of the [[Red Army]] on January 27, 1945. Approximately 20,000 Auschwitz prisoners made it to [[Bergen-Belsen concentration camp]] in Germany, where they were liberated by the British in April 1945.&lt;ref name=&quot;rees16&quot;/&gt; Among the artifacts of automated murder found by the Russians were 348,820 men's suits and 836,255 women's garments.

==Death toll==
[[File:Bundesarchiv Bild 183-74237-004, KZ Auschwitz-Birkenau, alte Frau und Kinder.jpg|right|thumb|280px|[[Hungarian Jews|Hungarian Jewish]] children and an elderly woman on the way to the [[gas chamber]]s of Auschwitz-Birkenau (1944), many children and elderly were murdered immediately after arrival and were never registered&lt;ref name=&quot;encyclopedia&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;auschwitz17&quot;/&gt;]]
The exact number of victims at Auschwitz is impossible to fix with certainty. Since the Nazis destroyed a number of records, immediate efforts to count the dead depended on the testimony of witnesses and the defendants on trial at [[Nuremberg Trials|Nuremberg]]. While under interrogation [[Rudolf Höss]], commandant of Auschwitz concentration camp from 1940 to 1943, said that [[Adolf Eichmann]] told him that two and a half million Jews had been killed in gas chambers and about half a million had died &quot;naturally&quot;. Later he wrote &quot;I regard two and a half million far too high. Even Auschwitz had limits to its destructive possibilities&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;commandant&quot;/&gt;

Communist Polish and Soviet authorities maintained a figure &quot;between 2.5 and 4 million&quot;,&lt;ref name=&quot;harmon-drobnicki&quot;/&gt; and the Auschwitz State Museum itself displayed a figure of 4 million killed, but &quot;[f]ew (if any) historians ever believed the Museum's four million figure&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;AuschwitzGambit&quot;/&gt; [[Raul Hilberg]]'s 1961 work ''[[The Destruction of the European Jews]]'' estimated the number killed at 1,000,000, and [[Gerald Reitlinger]]'s 1968 book ''The Final Solution'' described the Soviet figures as &quot;ridiculous&quot;, and estimated the number killed at &quot;800,000 to 900,000&quot;.&lt;ref name=AuschwitzGambit/&gt;

In 1983, French scholar George Wellers was one of the first to use German data on deportations to estimate the number killed at Auschwitz, arriving at 1.613&amp;nbsp;million dead, including 1.44&amp;nbsp;million Jews and 146,000 Catholic Poles.&lt;ref name=&quot;determination&quot;/&gt; A larger study started later by [[Franciszek Piper]] used timetables of train arrivals combined with deportation records to calculate 960,000 Jewish deaths and 140,000–150,000 ethnic Polish victims, along with 23,000 [[Romani people|Roma]] and [[Sinti]],&lt;ref name=&quot;Piper 1994, pp. 68-72&quot;/&gt; a figure that has met with significant agreement from other scholars.&lt;ref name=&quot;kavanaugh&quot;/&gt;

After the collapse of the Communist government in 1989, the plaque at Auschwitz State Museum was removed and the official death toll given as 1.1&amp;nbsp;million. [[Holocaust denial|Holocaust deniers]] have attempted to use this change as propaganda, in the words of the [[Nizkor Project]]: {{quote|Deniers often use the 'Four Million Variant' as a stepping stone to leap from an apparent contradiction to the idea that the Holocaust was a hoax, again perpetrated by a conspiracy. They hope to discredit historians by making them seem inconsistent. If they can't keep their numbers straight, their reasoning goes, how can we say that their evidence for the Holocaust is credible? One must wonder which historians they speak of, as most have been remarkably consistent in their estimates of a million or so dead... Few (if any) historians ever believed the Museum's four million figure, having arrived at their own estimates independently. The museum's inflated figures were never part of the estimated five to six million Jews killed in the Holocaust, so there is no need to revise this figure.&lt;ref name=AuschwitzGambit/&gt;}}

==Timeline of Auschwitz==
The timeline of events at the Auschwitz concentration camp began in January 1940 when the location was first visited by [[Arpad Wigand]] an aid to the Higher SS and Police Leader for [[Silesia]] [[Erich von dem Bach-Zelewski]]. The original intent of the camp was to intern Polish political prisoners. The original uses of the camp were added to and the capacity expanded over the course of the next four years, which reflected the political and economic decisions of the Third Reich, including the implementation of the [[Final Solution]].
{| class=&quot;wikitable collapsible collapsed&quot;  style=&quot;margin:auto; margin:1em; margin-top:0; margin:auto;&quot;
|-
! style=&quot;background:brown;color:white;&quot; colspan=&quot;2&quot;|&lt;span style=&quot;padding:0 2em;&quot;&gt;Timeline of Auschwitz&lt;/span&gt;
|-
| '''February 21, 1940'''|| || In January [[Arpad Wigand]] aide to Höhere SS- und Polizeiführer for [[Silesia]] [[Erich von dem Bach-Zelewski]] suggests the Polish military barracks at [[Oświęcim]] as a site for a concentration camp for Polish prisoners. Inspector of concentration camps [[Richard Glücks]] sends Sachenhausen commandant Walter Eisfeld to inspect the site. On Feb. 21 Glücks informs Reichsfuhrer SS [[Heinrich Himmler]] that the site will be developed into a concentration camp.&lt;ref name=&quot;auschwitz18&quot;/&gt;
|-
|'''May 20, 1940''' || [[File:Auschwitz I Block 11.jpg|120px]]
|| The first prisoners, 30 German career criminals from [[Sachsenhausen concentration camp|Sachsenhausen]], arrive. Most will be made kapos, prisoner no. 1 is a German of Polish descent Bruno Brodniewicz. Among this group is Kurt Pachala from Breslau (prisoner no. 24) who was tortured and then sent to a &quot;standing cell&quot; in the basement of Block 11 where he died of thirst and hunger on Jan. 14, 1943 as punishment for the June 20, 1942 escape of four prisoners.&lt;ref name=&quot;university&quot;/&gt;
&lt;ref name=&quot;franciszek&quot;&gt;Auschwitz, 1940–1945: Mass murder By Wacław Długoborski, Franciszek Piper&lt;/ref&gt;
|-
| '''June 14, 1940'''|| [[File:Pmt 1.jpg|120px]] || [[First mass transport to Auschwitz concentration camp|First mass transport]], consisting of 728 Polish political prisoners from [[Tarnów|Tarnow]]. They are held in the building which housed the Polish Tobacco Monopoly, until the camp is ready. Among the prisoners is [[Mala Zimetbaum#Failed escape from Auschwitz-Birkenau|Edward Galinski]] who would later make an escape with his girlfriend.&lt;ref name=&quot;publishers19&quot;/&gt;
|-
| '''March 1, 1941'''  || [[File:Bundesarchiv Bild 146-2007-0050, IG-Farbenwerke Auschwitz.jpg|120px]]&lt;!-- Deleted image removed: [[File:MaxFaustMonowitz.jpg|120px]] --&gt;|| Reichsführer SS and Chief of German Police [[Heinrich Himmler]] inspects the camp. Because nearby factories use prisoners for forced labor, Himmler is concerned about the camp's capacity. On this visit, he orders both the expansion of Auschwitz I camp facilities to hold 30,000 prisoners and the building of a camp near Birkenau for an expected influx of 100,000 Soviet prisoners of war. Himmler also orders that the camp supply 10,000 prisoners for forced labor to construct an [[IG Farben]] factory complex at [[Dwory]], about a mile away. Himmler made additional visits to Auschwitz in 1942, when he witnessed the killing of prisoners in the gas chambers.
|-
|'''September 3, 1941'''  || [[File:Zyklon B.jpg|120px]]&lt;br /&gt;|| The first gassings of prisoners occur in Auschwitz I. The SS tests Zyklon B gas by killing 600 Soviet prisoners of war and 250 other ill or weak prisoners. Testing takes place in a makeshift gas chamber in the cellar of Block 11 in Auschwitz I. The success of these experiments leads to the adoption of Zyklon B as the killing agent for Auschwitz II-Birkenau.
|-
| '''January 25, 1942'''  || [[File:Glucks.jpg|120px]] || Himmler informs [[Richard Glücks]], the Inspector of Concentration Camps, that 100,000 Jewish men and 50,000 Jewish women are to be deported from Germany to Auschwitz as forced laborers.
|-
| '''February 15, 1942'''  || [[File:Auschwitz survivor displays tattoo detail.jpg|120px]]&lt;br /&gt;|| The first transport of Jews from [[Bytom]] (Beuthen) in German-annexed [[Upper Silesia]] arrives in Auschwitz I. The SS camp authorities kill all those on the transport immediately upon arrival with Zyklon B gas. German SS and police authorities deport around 175,000 Jews to Auschwitz in 1942.
|-
| '''{{Dts|1942|April|29}}'''|| || First transport of Slovakian Jews arrives.&lt;ref name=&quot;ReferenceA&quot;/&gt;
|-
|'''June 20, 1942'''  || [[File:MHV Steyr 220 1937 01.jpg|120px]]&lt;br /&gt;
||Polish political prisoner [[Kazimierz Piechowski]] (prisoner 918), and three other prisoners, Stanisław Gustaw Jaster, Józef Lempart, and Eugeniusz Bendera, escaped from Auschwitz I. They dressed as members of the [[SS-Totenkopfverbände]], fully armed. They stole an SS staff car, a [[Steyr automobile|Steyr]] 220 belonging to [[Rudolf Höss]], from the motor pool and drove out the main gate. The escape was facilitated by Piechowski's fluent command of German. As they drove toward the gate he told the guards to hurry up and open it. None of the four were recaptured.&lt;ref name=&quot;auschwitz20&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;auschwitz21&quot;/&gt;
|-
| '''{{Dts|1942|August|4}}''' || [[File:Breendonk071.jpg|120px]] || First transport of Jews from Belgium are deported to Auschwitz. Due to rescue efforts by resistance groups in Belgium, approximately 25,000 of the country's 57,000 registered Jews find hiding within the country and survive the war.&lt;ref name=&quot;extermination&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;comparative&quot;/&gt;
|-
| '''January 1, 1943 – March 31, 1943'''|| || German SS and police authorities deport approximately 105,000 Jews to Auschwitz
|-
| '''January 29, 1943'''  || [[File:Bundesarchiv R 165 Bild-244-52, Asperg, Deportation von Sinti und Roma.jpg|120px]]&lt;br /&gt;|| The [[SS-Reichssicherheitshauptamt|Reich Central Office for Security]] orders all designated Roma residing in Germany, Austria, and the Protectorate of Bohemia and Moravia to be deported to Auschwitz.
|-
| '''February 26, 1943'''||  || The first transport of [[Roma (Romani subgroup)|Roma]] from Germany arrives. The SS authorities house them in Section B-IIe of Auschwitz-Birkenau, which becomes known as the &quot;Zigeunerlager or the Roma family camp.&quot; By the end of 1943 more than 18,000 Roma were incarcerated there, and 23,000 deported to other parts of the camp complex.
|-
|'''March 13, 1943'''  || [[File:Krakow Ghetto 06694.jpg|120px]]&lt;br /&gt;|| Out of a transport of 2,000 Jews from the [[Kraków Ghetto]], 1,492 are gassed in the basement gas chamber of Crematorium II at Birkenau in the evening. This operation tests the gas chamber's ventilation and air extraction equipment installed by J.A. Topf engineer Heinrich Messing, who declared it operational earlier that day.&lt;ref name=&quot;Gutman232&quot;/&gt;
|-
| '''March 22, 1943'''||  || Crematorium IV is ready for use.&lt;ref name=&quot;Gutman234&quot;/&gt;
|-
| '''March 31, 1943'''  || [[File:Auschwitz Birkenau Krematorium II 04 Plan.jpg|120px]]&lt;br /&gt;
|| Crematorium II is handed over to the Auschwitz authorities.&lt;ref name=Gutman232/&gt; Holocaust scholar [[Robert Jan van Pelt]] comments that more people lost their lives in this room than in any other room on Earth: 500,000 people.&lt;ref name=&quot;morris&quot;/&gt;
|-
|'''April 4, 1943'''||  || Crematorium V is ready for use.&lt;ref name=Gutman234/&gt;
|-
|'''April 22, 1943'''  || [[File:Livshitz.jpg|120px]]&lt;br /&gt;||[[Twentieth convoy|Transport 20]] from the transit camp in [[Mechelen]], Belgium arrives in Auschwitz. A Jewish doctor Youra Livschitz and his two non-Jewish high school friends Robert Maistriau and Jean Franklemon managed to stop the train on the tracks with only a lantern and a handgun when it rounded a curve in [[Boortmeerbeek]], Belgium and open the doors on some of the rail cars. Some prisoners managed to escape then, over 200 more jumped from the train en route.&lt;ref name=&quot;twentieth&quot;/&gt;
|-
|'''April 26–27, 1943'''|| [[File:Proces Pileckiego 1948-2jpg.jpg|120px]] || [[Witold Pilecki]] escapes during the night. He would later take part in the [[Warsaw Uprising]], get captured and spend the remainder of the war in P.O.W. camps.
|-
|'''May 30, 1943'''  || [[File:WP Josef Mengele 1956.jpg|120px]] ||[[Josef Mengele]] arrives at Auschwitz. He often took part in &quot;selections&quot; of incoming prisoners on the ramp at Birkenau. During his time at Aushwitz he engaged in pseudoscientific experiments on camp inmates. He had a special fascination with [[twins]]. Mengele was known as &quot;the Angel of Death&quot;. He escaped to South America after the war and was never brought to justice.&lt;ref name=&quot;auschwitz22&quot;/&gt;
|-
| '''June 24, 1943'''  || [[File:Entrance to Crematorium III in Auschwitz II (Birkenau).jpg|120px]]&lt;br /&gt;|| Crematorium III is ready for use.&lt;ref name=&quot;Gutman236&quot;/&gt;
|-
|'''July 19, 1943''' || [[File:Auschwitz I Stammlager 2001 07.jpg|120px]]&lt;br /&gt;||Largest mass hanging at Aushwitz, public gallows constructed of train rails and railroad ties, specifically constructed to simultaneously hang 12 Polish prisoners, part of the Survey Kommando, for helping three prisoners escape. Two of the hanged are Boguslaw Ohrt: [no. 367] and Janusz Pogonowskino [no.253]&lt;ref name=&quot;auschwitz23&quot;/&gt;
|-
|'''February 21, 1944'''||  || [[Primo Levi]] arrives in the camp from Italy.
|-
|'''April 7, 1944'''|| [[File:AuschwitzProtocolsmap.jpg|120px]] || Two Jewish prisoners, [[Rudolf Vrba]] and [[Alfréd Wetzler]], escape and pass a 32-page report of what is happening in the camp to Jewish officials in Slovakia. Their information becomes known as the [[Vrba-Wetzler report]].
|-
| '''May 2, 1944''' || [[File:Bundesarchiv Bild 101I-680-8285A-08, Budapest, Festnahme von Juden.jpg|120px]]&lt;br /&gt;|| The first two transports of Hungarian Jews arrive in Auschwitz. Throughout May and June 1944, Hungarian Jews are deported to the camp at a rate of 12,000 a day.
|-
|'''May 16, 1944'''  || [[File:Buchenwald Slave Laborers Liberation.jpg|120px]]&lt;br /&gt;|| [[Elie Wiesel]] arrives with his family on or around this date. His mother and youngest sister are immediately sent to be gassed.
|-
|'''May 22, 1944'''  || || Romani-Sinti, deported from the Netherlands arrive in Auschwitz-Birkenau. [[Settela Steinbach]] an eleven year old Sinti girl is caught on film peering out from the transport on May 19, by Jewish prisoner Rudolf Breslauer, who was ordered to film the deportation by the commandant of the [[Westerbork]] transit camp. Settela would die in the gas chamber.
|-
|'''June 6, 1944'''||  || The Allies land in Normandy, France to begin the [[Operation Overlord|liberation of Western Europe]].
|-
|'''June 15 and 20, 1944'''||  || The first reports regarded as credible that describe the mass murder taking place in the camp are published by the BBC and ''The New York Times'' respectively, based on the Vrba-Wetzler report
|-
|'''June 24, 1944'''  || ||Polish born Jewish girl [[Mala Zimetbaum]] (prison no.19880) and her Polish boyfriend Edward &quot;Edek&quot; Galinski (prison no. 518) escape from Birkenau. Galinski, one of the first deportees to Auschwitz, was wearing an SS uniform provided to him by SS-Rottenfuehrer Edward Lubusch, an ethnic German raised in Poland. They were caught on July 6, 1944 and returned to Auschwitz. They were imprisoned in separate cells in Block 11; both were sentenced to death. On September 15, 1944, Galinski was hung. Mala slit her wrists with a razor blade interrupting her execution. She was, according to various accounts taken to the crematorium to be burned alive. It's not known whether that occurred or she was shot in the crematorium.&lt;ref name=&quot;36publisher&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;34publisher&quot;/&gt;
|-
| '''July 7, 1944''' || [[File:Laszlo - Miklós Horthy.jpg|120px]]&lt;br /&gt;|| In response to the publication of the [[Vrba-Wetzler Report]], governments around the world put pressure on Regent [[Miklós Horthy]] of Hungary to halt the deportation of Hungarian Jews to Auschwitz, which he does on July, 7 1944
|-
| '''August 2–3, 1944''' || [[File:Romani Kids ww2.jpg|120px]]&lt;br /&gt;||The Zigeunerlager family is liquidated during the night; 2,897 men women and children perish in the gas chamber, 1,400 surviving men and women are transferred to Buchenwald and Ravensbruck for slave labor. An estimated 20,000 Roma were killed there in Aushwitz. Among the murdered are Romani [[mischlinge]], used by Nazi race scientist [[Eva Justin]] in her pseudoscientific race research.
|-
|'''August 12–13, 1944''' || [[File:Warsaw Uprising by Chrzanowski - Henio Roma - 14828.jpg|120px]]&lt;br /&gt;
 || Almost 6,000 residents of Warsaw are transported to Auschwitz in response to the [[Warsaw Uprising]] (approximately twice as many females as males, including over a thousand children).
|-
| '''September 3, 1944''' || || [[Anne Frank]] is transported to Auschwitz along with her mother Edith and sister Margot; on October 28, 1944 Anne and Margot were chosen in a selection to be transferred to [[Bergen-Belsen concentration camp|Bergen-Belsen]]. Edith was left behind where it was reported she died of starvation. Anne and Margot would both die in March 1945 in the [[typhus]] epidemic at Bergen-Belsen only weeks before the camp's liberation by the British on April 15, 1945.&lt;ref name=&quot;biography&quot;/&gt;
|-
|'''September 4, 1944'''|| || A transport of 3,087 predominantly Polish men, women, and children from Warsaw arrive in Auschwitz in retribution for Warsaw uprising
|-
|'''September 13 and 17, 1944'''|| || Another 4,000 predominantly Polish men and boys from Warsaw arrive in Auschwitz as retribution for the uprising.
|-
| '''October 7, 1944''' || [[File:Four4ruine.jpg|120px]]&lt;br /&gt;|| Members of the Jewish prisoner &quot;special detachment&quot; (''Sonderkommando'') that was forced to remove bodies from the gas chambers and operate the crematoria stage an uprising. They successfully blow up Crematorium IV and kill several guards. Women prisoners had smuggled gunpowder out of nearby factories to members of the ''Sonderkommando''. The SS quickly suppresses the revolt and kills all the ''Sonderkommando'' members.
|-
|'''October 30, 1944''' || [[File:Arbeitmachtfrei 01.jpg|120px]]&lt;br /&gt;|| The last selections take place on the Jewish ramp at Birkenau; 1,689 people from a transport from [[Theresienstadt concentration camp]] are sent to the gas chambers. After this, only individuals are gassed after selection within the camp. The last 13 people to be killed this way were women, gassed or shot in crematorium II on November 25.&lt;ref name=&quot;Gutman563&quot;/&gt;
|-
| '''November 25, 1944''' || &lt;!-- Deleted image removed: [[File:Kanada Auschwitz.jpg|120px]] --&gt;|| As Soviet forces approach, SS chief Heinrich Himmler orders the destruction of the Auschwitz-Birkenau gas chambers and crematoria. During this attempt to destroy the evidence of mass killings, prisoners are forced to dismantle and dynamite the structures.
|-
|'''November 27, 1944''' || [[File:Sergio de Desimone.jpg|120px]]&lt;br /&gt;||Twenty Jewish children, 10 boys and 10 girls ages 5–12, are selected from Block 10, by Josef Mengele at the behest of [[Kurt Heissmeyer]]. The children are sent to [[Neuengamme concentration camp]]. There they are infected with tuberculosis and subjected to medical experimentation. They are ultimately murdered by being hanged in the basement of the [[Bullenhuser Damm]] school in [[Hamburg]].&lt;ref name=&quot;bullenhuser24&quot;/&gt;
|-
| '''January 12, 1945''' || [[File:Soviets liberating lodz.jpg|120px]]&lt;br /&gt;|| The Red Army launches the [[Vistula-Oder Offensive]]; Soviet troops liberate [[Lodz]] on January 17, only 877 Jews remain in the ghetto out of a high of 163,177 people in 1941; [[Warsaw]] and [[Kraków]] are both liberated on January, 19. The advance heads toward Oświęcim.
|-
| '''January 18–27, 1945''' || || As Soviet units approach the camp, the SS evacuates prisoners to the west. Tens of thousands, mostly Jews, are forced to [[Death marches (Holocaust)|march]] to the cities of [[Wodzisław|Loslau]] and [[Gliwice|Gleiwitz]] in [[Upper Silesia]]. During the march, SS guards shoot anyone who cannot continue. In Loslau and Gleiwitz, the prisoners are placed on unheated freight trains and deported to concentration camps in Germany, particularly to [[Flossenburg]], [[Sachsenhausen concentration camp|Sachsenhausen]], [[Gross-Rosen]], [[Buchenwald]], and [[Dachau concentration camp|Dachau]], and to [[Mauthausen-Gusen concentration camp|Mauthausen]] in Austria. Nearly 60,000 prisoners are forced on death marches from the Auschwitz camp system. As many as 15,000 die. Thousands more are killed in the days before the evacuation.
|-
| '''January 27, 1945''' || [[File:Children in the Holocaust concentration camp liberated by Red Army.jpg|120px]]&lt;br /&gt;|| Soviet troops enter the Auschwitz camp complex and liberate 7,000 prisoners, including children.
|-
|'''March 11, 1946'''||  [[File:Hoess4.jpg|120px]] || British troops capture the camp's first commandant, [[Rudolf Höss]], who is living as a farmer called Franz Lang.
|-
|'''April 16, 1947''' || [[File:Hoess7.jpg|120px]]|| Poland sentences Rudolf Höss to death on April 2, 1947 and he is hanged on April 16.
|}

==After the war==
{{main|Auschwitz Trial}}
[[File:Auschwitz-Birkenau abgebrannte Barracken.jpg|thumb|left|260px|Ruins of inmates' barracks at Birkenau]]
After the war, parts of Auschwitz 1 and/or its guards' quarters served first as a hospital for sick liberated prisoners.&lt;ref name=&quot;Auschwitz.org.pl25&quot;/&gt; Until 1947 some of the facilities were used as an [[NKVD]] and [[Ministry of Public Security of Poland|MBP]] prison camp. The ''Buna–Werke'' were taken over by the Polish government and became the foundation for the region's chemical industry. At Auschwitz 1 the Gestapo building was demolished and on its site was built a [[gallows]] on which [[Standartenführer]] SS [[Rudolf Höss]] was hanged on April 17, 1947 for numerous war crimes.&lt;ref name=&quot;isurvived&quot;/&gt; On November 24, 1947, the [[Auschwitz trial]] began in [[Kraków]], when the Poland's [[Supreme National Tribunal]] tried 41 former staff of the Auschwitz concentration camps complex. The trials ended on December 22, 1947, with 23 death sentences issued, as well as 16 imprisonments ranging from life sentence to 3 years.

After liberation, local Polish farming population returning to the area searched the ruins of Birkenau thoroughly for re-usable fallen bricks, so they could rebuild farm buildings for shelter needed for the next winter. That explains the &quot;missing rubble&quot; argument brought up by [[Holocaust denial|Holocaust deniers]].

Today, at Birkenau the entrance building and some of the southern brick-built barracks survive; but of the almost 300 wooden barracks, only 19 have been reconstructed from authentic materials: 18 near the entrance building and one, on its own, farther away. All that survives of the others are chimneys, remnants of a largely ineffective means of heating. Many of these wooden buildings were constructed from prefabricated sections made by a company that intended them to be used as stables; inside, numerous metal rings for the tethering of horses can still be seen.
{{clear}}

===Creation of the museum===
{{Main|Auschwitz-Birkenau State Museum}}
[[File:AuschwitzGallows2006.JPG|upright|thumb|[[Gallows]] in Auschwitz I where [[Rudolf Höss]] was executed on April 16, 1947]]
The Polish government decided to restore Auschwitz I and turn it into a museum honouring the victims of [[Nazism]]; Auschwitz II, where buildings (many of which were prefabricated wood structures) were prone to decay, was preserved but not restored. Today, the Auschwitz I museum site combines elements from several periods into a single complex: for example the gas chamber at Auschwitz I (which had been converted into an air-raid shelter for the [[Schutzstaffel|SS]]) was restored and the fence was moved (because of building work being done after the war but before the museum was established). However, in most cases the departure from the historical truth is minor, and is clearly labelled. The museum contains many men's, women's and children's shoes taken from their victims; also suitcases, which the deportees were encouraged to bring with them, and many household utensils. One display case, some {{convert|30|m|ft}} long, is wholly filled with human hair which the Nazis gathered from people before they were sent to labor or before and after they were killed.

Auschwitz II and the remains of the gas chambers there are open to the public. The camp is on the list of [[UNESCO]] [[World Heritage Sites]]. The ashes of the victims were scattered between the huts, and the entire area is regarded as a grave site. Most of the buildings of Auschwitz I are still standing. The public entrance area is outside the [[perimeter fence]] in what was the camp admission building, where new prisoners were registered and given their uniforms. At the far end of Birkenau are memorial [[Commemorative plaque|plaques]] in many languages, including [[Romani language|Romani]].

The museum has allowed scenes for three films to be filmed on the site: ''[[Passenger (1963 film)|Pasażerka]]'' (1963) by Polish director [[Andrzej Munk]], ''[[Landscape After the Battle]]'' (1970) by Polish director [[Andrzej Wajda]], and a television miniseries ''[[War and Remembrance]]'' (1978). Permission was denied to [[Steven Spielberg]] to film scenes for ''[[Schindler's List]]'' (1993). A &quot;mirror&quot; camp was constructed outside the infamous archway for the scene where the train arrives carrying the women who were saved by [[Oskar Schindler]].

===&quot;Arbeit macht frei&quot; sign theft===
&lt;!-- Keep all the information on this theft here and avoid content forking. --&gt;
[[File:Auschwitz entrance.JPG|thumb|''[[Arbeit macht frei]]'' sign, Auschwitz I]]
&lt;!--{{see|Auschwitz-Birkenau State Museum#&quot;Arbeit macht frei&quot; sign theft|Arbeit macht frei#Sign theft at Auschwitz}}--&gt;
The {{convert|5|m|ft|adj=on}}, {{convert|41|kg|lb|adj=on}} wrought-iron &quot;[[Arbeit macht frei]]&quot; sign over the entrance to Auschwitz I was stolen in the early morning of December 18, 2009. The thieves unscrewed the sign at one end and broke it off its mountings at the other end, then carried the sign 300 metres to a hole in the concrete wall, where they cut four metal bars blocking the opening. After the theft, authorities replaced the stolen sign with a replica, which was originally made to replace the original sign while it was being restored some years earlier.&lt;ref name=&quot;Auschwitz death camp sign stolen&quot;/&gt; Shortly afterward, border control security was increased, and random police checks occurred.&lt;ref name=&quot;guardian&quot;/&gt;

Police found the sign, cut into three parts, in northern Poland two days later in the home of one of five men who were arrested. An unnamed overseas buyer is believed to have been involved.&lt;ref name=&quot;nytimes&quot;/&gt; Polish police said that the five were common thieves, not [[neo-Nazi]]s.&lt;ref name=&quot;yahoo&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;bbc&quot;/&gt; The original sign was welded back together on site and will probably form part of a new exhibition.&lt;ref name=&quot;Auschwitz museum unveils restored stolen sign&quot;/&gt;  An improved security system will be put in place.&lt;ref name=&quot;sltrib&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Gera&quot;/&gt;

The sign was made by Polish workers on Nazi orders after the Auschwitz barracks were converted into a [[labor camp]] to house captured Polish resistance fighters in 1940.&lt;ref name=&quot;Telegraph.co.uk&quot;/&gt;

The ''[[Aftonbladet]]'' newspaper reported that the sign had been stolen by Polish thieves paid by and working on behalf of a [[Swedish people|Swedish]] right-wing extremist group hoping to use proceeds from the proposed sale of the sign to a collector of Nazi memorabilia, to finance a series of terror attacks aimed at influencing voters in upcoming Swedish parliamentary elections.&lt;ref name=&quot;Politicsdaily.com&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;DigitalJournal.com&quot;/&gt; The theft was organised by the Swedish former Nazi, Anders Högström.&lt;ref name=&quot;Aftonbladet.se&quot;/&gt;

On March 18, 2010, a Polish court sentenced three men to prison for stealing the sign. They [[Plead guilty|pleaded guilty]]. The sentences were from 18 months to 30 months. They were fined £2,300 each.&lt;ref name=&quot;telegraph&quot;/&gt; Two of them were granted compassionate leave, but in April the three did not report to the prison to serve their sentences, and police were trying to find them.&lt;ref name=&quot;associated&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Auschwitz Thieves Fail to Report to Jail&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Men jailed for stealing Auschwitz camp sign failed to return after compassionate leave&quot;/&gt;

It has been announced that the sign will not be returned to its old location, but rather will only be shown in an enclosed room of the museum.&lt;ref name=&quot;nytimes26&quot;/&gt;

==Gallery==
&lt;div style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;&gt;
&lt;gallery&gt;
File:Auschwitz-2.jpg|Auschwitz I in winter
File:Aushwitz I gas chamber memorial.jpg|Interior of the gas chamber of Auschwitz I
File:Aushwitz I crematoria memorial.jpg|Interior of the crematorium of Auschwitz I. This facility was much smaller than those of Auschwitz II.
File:Auschwitz Resistance 282 cropped.JPG|Surreptitious photo taken by a member of the [[Sonderkommando]], women undressed and sent to gas chamber
File:BirkenauPrisonerBuildings.jpg|Auschwitz II-Birkenau in 2009
File:BirkenauChimneys.jpg|Auschwitz II-Birkenau ruins in 2009
File:Rudolf Höß.jpg|[[Rudolf Höss]] (1900–1947), the first commandant of Auschwitz
File:Josef Kramer.JPG|[[Josef Kramer]] (1906–1945), Höss's first deputy
File:Auschwitz - Blok Smierci and The Execution Wall Sk06 C P.jpg|Block 11, execution wall seen in courtyard, through archway
File:AuschwitzExecutionWall2006.jpg|Execution wall in Auschwitz I, between blocks 10 and 11
File:Bundesarchiv Bild 183-R69919, KZ Auschwitz, Brillen.jpg|Eyeglasses of victims
File:Auschwitz I material proofs of crimes 10.jpg|Exhibit of shoes from the victims of Auschwitz
File:AuI krematorium.jpg|Gas chamber in Auschwitz I
File:May 1944 - Jews from Carpathian Ruthenia arrive at Auschwitz-Birkenau.jpg|Jews from [[Carpathian Ruthenia]] arriving at Auschwitz-Birkenau
File:Auschwitz.Birkenau.QuarantaineBarrack.jpg|[[Bunk bed]]s in Auschwitz II. There were as many as four inmates per bunk. There could be as many as a thousand inmates per barrack.
File:Elisabeth Klein.jpg|Elisabeth Klein; one of the 86 victims in the &quot;[[Jewish skeleton collection]]&quot;
File:Birkenau tower.JPG|Entrance to Birkenau, 2006. Guard tower, two information boards seen on the left.
File:Oeremony Of Israel Defense Forces In Auschwitz.JPG|[[Israeli Defense Forces]] ceremony near the entrance of Auschwitz
&lt;/gallery&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

==See also==
{{Commons category|Auschwitz-Birkenau concentration camp}}
* [[Auschwitz Album]] – a collection of pictures taken at Auschwitz during its operation.
* [[Auschwitz Trial]]
* [[Central Labour Camp Jaworzno]] Arbeitslager Neu-Dachs (Jaworzno)
* [[Frankfurt Auschwitz Trials]]
* [[Höcker Album]]
* [[International Auschwitz Committee]]
* [[Kaiser Wilhelm Institute of Anthropology, Human Heredity, and Eugenics]]
* [[List of Nazi concentration camps]]
* [[List of victims and survivors of Auschwitz]]
* [[Oświęcim synagogue]]
* [[Przyszowice massacre]]
* [[Research Materials: Max Planck Society Archive]]
* [[Shark Island, German South West Africa]]
* [[SS command of Auschwitz concentration camp]]
* [[Survivor syndrome]]

==Notes==
{{reflist|colwidth=30em|refs=

&lt;ref name=&quot;34publisher&quot;&gt;Rena's Promise By Rena Kornreich Gelissen, Heather Dune Macadam pages 230-34Publisher: Beacon Press (October 30, 1996) ISBN 0-8070-7071-8 ISBN 978-0-8070-7071-0&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;36publisher&quot;&gt;Testimony from the Nazi camps: French women's voices By Margaret-Anne Hutton pages 34-36Publisher: Routledge; 1 edition (December 29, 2004) ISBN- 0415349338 ISBN 978-0-415-34933-8&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Aftonbladet.se&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.aftonbladet.se/nyheter/article6760745.ab |title=Aftonbladet.se |publisher=Aftonbladet.se |date=March 11, 2010 |accessdate=August 23, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Auschwitz Thieves Fail to Report to Jail&quot;&gt;{{cite news|last=Associated |first=The |url=http://www.nytimes.com/2010/04/22/world/europe/22poland.html |title=Auschwitz Thieves Fail to Report to Jail |work=The New York Times  |date=April 21, 2010 |accessdate=May 18, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Auschwitz death camp sign stolen&quot;&gt;{{cite news |url=http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/world/europe/8419948.stm |title=Auschwitz death camp sign stolen |publisher=BBC News  |date=December 18, 2009 |accessdate=December 18, 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Auschwitz museum unveils restored stolen sign&quot;&gt;{{cite news  | last = Easton  | first = Adam  | title = Auschwitz museum unveils restored stolen sign  | url=http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/world-europe-13444744  | date = May 18, 2011  |publisher=BBC News   | accessdate =May 19, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Auschwitz.org.pl&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://en.auschwitz.org.pl/m/index.php?option=com_content&amp;task=view&amp;id=578&amp;Itemid=8 |title=Auschwitz.org.pl |publisher=En.auschwitz.org.pl |date=January 13, 2009 |accessdate=August 23, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Auschwitz.org.pl25&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://en.auschwitz.org.pl/m/index.php?option=com_content&amp;task=view&amp;id=227&amp;Itemid=13&amp;limit=1&amp;limitstart=1 |title=Auschwitz.org.pl |publisher=En.auschwitz.org.pl |accessdate=August 23, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Auschwitz: The Nazis &amp; the Final Solutiuon&quot;&gt;{{cite book|last=Rees|first=Laurence|title=Auschwitz: The Nazis &amp; the Final Solutiuon|year=2005|publisher=Random House|isbn=9780563522966|page=326}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;AuschwitzGambit&quot;&gt;[[Nizkor Project|Nizkor]], [http://www.nizkor.org/features/techniques-of-denial/four-million-02.html The Auschwitz Gambit: The Four Million Variant]&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;DE&quot;&gt;[[Norman Davies]], ''Europe: A History'', Oxford University Press, 1996, ISBN 0198201710., [http://books.google.com/books?id=jrVW9W9eiYMC&amp;pg=PA1023&amp;dq=Witold+Pilecki+Auschwitz&amp;as_brr=3 Google Print, p. 1023]&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;DigitalJournal.com&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.digitaljournal.com/article/284804 |title=DigitalJournal.com |publisher=DigitalJournal.com |accessdate=August 23, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Fritsch&quot;&gt;{{en icon}} [http://en.auschwitz.org.pl/h/index.php?option=com_content&amp;task=view&amp;id=29&amp;Itemid=32&amp;limit=1&amp;limitstart=2 Muzeum Auschwitz-Birkenau w Oświęcimiu]&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Gera&quot;&gt;{{cite news |last=Gera |first=Vanessa |url=http://www.sltrib.com/ci_14044451 |title=Damaged Auschwitz sign to go back up at main gate |agency=[[The Associated Press]] |publisher=[[The Salt Lake Tribune]] |date=December 21, 2009 |accessdate=December 23, 2009}}{{Dead link|date=August 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Gutman 1994, pp. 10, 16&quot;&gt;Gutman 1994, pp. 10, 16.&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Gutman16&quot;&gt;Gutman 1994, p. 16.&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Gutman17&quot;&gt;Gutman 1994, p. 17.&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Gutman232&quot;&gt;Pressac, Jean-Claude and Van Pelt, Robert-Jan &quot;The Machinery of Mass Murder at Auschwitz&quot; in Gutman, Yisrael &amp; Berenbaum, Michael. ''Anatomy of the Auschwitz Death Camp'', Indiana University Press, 1994; this edition 1998, p. 232.&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Gutman234&quot;&gt;Pressac, Jean-Claude and Van Pelt, Robert-Jan &quot;The Machinery of Mass Murder at Auschwitz&quot; in Gutman, Yisrael &amp; Berenbaum, Michael. ''Anatomy of the Auschwitz Death Camp'', Indiana University Press, 1994; this edition 1998, p. 234.&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Gutman236&quot;&gt;Pressac, Jean-Claude and Van Pelt, Robert-Jan &quot;The Machinery of Mass Murder at Auschwitz&quot; in Gutman, Yisrael &amp; Berenbaum, Michael. ''Anatomy of the Auschwitz Death Camp'', Indiana University Press, 1994; this edition 1998, p. 236.&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Gutman563&quot;&gt;Karny, Miroslav. &quot;The Vrba and Wetzler Report&quot; in Gutman, Yisrael &amp; Berenbaum, Michael. ''Anatomy of the Auschwitz Death Camp'', Indiana University Press, 1994; this edition 1998, pp. 563–564.&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;International Military Tribunal 1946, Page 251&quot;&gt;Trials of the Major War Criminals Before the International Military Tribunal, Nuremberg November 14, 1945 – October 1, 1946, Volume 1, Page 251&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Maximilian Kolbe&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.jewishvirtuallibrary.org/jsource/biography/Kolbe.html |title=Maximilian Kolbe |publisher=Jewishvirtuallibrary.org |accessdate=August 23, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Men jailed for stealing Auschwitz camp sign failed to return after compassionate leave&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.mirror.co.uk/news/top-stories/2010/04/22/auschwitz-thieves-flee-115875-22203083/ |title=Men jailed for stealing Auschwitz camp sign failed to return after compassionate leave |work=Daily Mirror |location=UK |accessdate=May 18, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Piper 1994, pp. 68-72&quot;&gt;Piper 1994, pp. 68–72.&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Politicsdaily.com&quot;&gt;{{cite web|last=Fish |first=Sandra |url=http://www.politicsdaily.com/2010/01/01/auschwitz-sign-theft-linked-to-far-right-terrorist-plot/ |title=Politicsdaily.com |publisher=Politicsdaily.com |accessdate=August 23, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Rees53&quot;&gt;[[Gustave Gilbert]] witness statement cited in Dwork and Van Pelt 2002, p. 278, cited in Rees 2005, p. 53.&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;ReferenceA&quot;&gt;BBC History of World War II. Auschwitz; Inside the Nazi State. Part 2, Orders and Initiatives.&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Telegraph.co.uk&quot;&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.telegraph.co.uk/news/worldnews/europe/poland/6854075/Auschwitz-sign-found-in-three-pieces.html |title=Telegraph.co.uk |work=The Daily Telegraph |location=UK |date=December 21, 2009 |accessdate=August 23, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;ac&quot;&gt;Adam Cyra, Ochotnik do Auschwitz – Witold Pilecki 1901–1948, Oświęcim 2000. ISBN 83-912000-3-5&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;associated&quot;&gt;{{cite web|last=Associated |first=The |url=http://www.haaretz.com/jewish-world/news/auschwitz-sign-thieves-fail-to-show-up-for-prison-terms-1.284630 |title=Auschwitz sign thieves fail to show up for prison terms – Haaretz Daily Newspaper &amp;#124; Israel News |work=Haaretz |location=Israel |accessdate=May 18, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;auschwitz&quot;&gt;[http://en.auschwitz.org.pl/m/index.php?option=com_content&amp;task=view&amp;id=370&amp;Itemid=8 Auschwitz-Birkenau:Imprisoned for Their Faith: Jehovah’s Witnesses in Auschwitz]&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;auschwitz.org1&quot;&gt;[http://en.auschwitz.org.pl/h/index.php?option=com_content&amp;task=view&amp;id=29&amp;Itemid=32&amp;limit=1&amp;limitstart=6 Dr. Franciszek Piper, &quot;Auschwitz and Shoah. The number of victims.&quot;] [[Auschwitz-Birkenau State Museum]].&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;auschwitz14&quot;&gt;{{en icon}} [http://en.auschwitz.org.pl/m/index.php?option=com_content&amp;task=view&amp;id=458&amp;Itemid=8 Państwowe Muzeum Auschwitz-Birkenau w Oświęcimiu]&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;auschwitz17&quot;&gt;Adam Bujak, Teresa Świebocka, Henryk Świebocki: Auschwitz: the residence of death p.1938 Auschwitz-Birkenau State Museum, 2003&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;auschwitz18&quot;&gt;Auschwitz by Debórah Dwork , Robert Jan van Pelt. page 166 Publisher: [[W. W. Norton &amp; Company]] (April 17, 2002) ISBN 0-393-32291-2 ISBN 978-0-393-32291-0&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;auschwitz20&quot;&gt;Auschwitz chronicle 1939–1945 By Danuta Czech Publisher: I B Tauris &amp; Co Ltd (November 1990) ISBN 1-85043-291-0 ISBN 978-1-85043-291-3&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;auschwitz21&quot;&gt;[http://en.auschwitz.org.pl/m/index.php?option=com_content&amp;task=view&amp;id=578&amp;Itemid=8 Auschwitz-Birkenau Memorial and Museum: The Film about the Amazing Escape from Auschwitz]&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;auschwitz22&quot;&gt;Children of the Flames; Dr. Josef Mengele and the Untold Story of the Twins of Auschwitz by Lucette Matalon and Sheila Cohen Dekel Publisher: Penguin (Non-Classics) (May 1, 1992) ISBN 0-14-016931-8 ISBN 978-0140169317&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;auschwitz23&quot;&gt;From the history of KL-Auschwitz, Volume 1 – Page 73 Kazimierz Smoleń – History – 1967&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;auschwitz6&quot;&gt;&quot;Auschwitz: Inside the Nazi State&quot;, PBS (2004–2005)&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;autogenerated&quot;&gt;Kárný 1994, p. 556.&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;bbc&quot;&gt;[http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/europe/8423827.stm Police in Poland find sign stolen from Auschwitz gate], BBC News, December 21, 2009.&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;biography&quot;&gt;Müller, Melissa. Anne Frank: The Biography Macmillan, 1998. ISBN 0-8050-5996-2 pp. 119–120&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;bullenhuser&quot;&gt;For &quot;pseudo-scientific&quot;, see: * Kater, Michael H. ''Doctors Under Hitler'', [[University of North Carolina Press]], 2000, ISBN 9780807848586, pp. 124–125. * [[Richard C. Lukas|Lukas, Richard C.]] ''Did the Children Cry?: Hitler's War Against Jewish and Polish Children, 1939–1945'', [[Hippocrene Books]], 1994, ISBN 9780781802420, pp. 88–89. * Schwarberg, Günther. ''The Murders at Bullenhuser Damm'', [[Indiana University Press]], 1984, ISBN 9780253154811, p. 117.&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;bullenhuser24&quot;&gt;The Murders at Bullenhuser Damm: The SS Doctor and the Children [[Günther Schwarberg]] Publisher: Indiana University Press; First Edition edition (April 1984) ISBN 0-253-15481-2 ISBN 978-0-253-15481-1&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;commandant&quot;&gt;''Commandant of Auschwitz: Rudolf Höß''. Appendix one, pp. 193–194. ISBN 1-84212-024-7&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;comparative&quot;&gt;Griffioen and Zeller, &quot;A Comparative Analysis of the Persecution of the Jews in the Netherlands and Belgium during the Second World War,&quot; p. 21.&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;compositions&quot;&gt;Gilbert, S. ''Music in the Holocaust: Confronting Life in the Nazi Ghettos and Camps''. Oxford: Oxford University Press, 2005. The compositions were written by musicians in the camps and included &quot;Arbeitslager-March&quot; (Work camp march) and &quot;[[Arbeit macht frei]]&quot;.&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;confronting&quot;&gt;Gilbert, S. ''Music in the Holocaust: Confronting Life in the Nazi Ghettos and Camps''. Oxford: Oxford University Press, 2005. p. 184&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;contributions&quot;&gt;Synthetic Rubber: A Project That Had to Succeed (Contributions in Economics and Economic History) by Vernon Herbert &amp; Attilio Bisio.Publisher: Greenwood Press (December 11, 1985) Language: English ISBN 0313246343 ISBN 978-0313246340&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;danuta&quot;&gt;Danuta Czech in Gutman 1994, p. 18.&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;dccam&quot;&gt;Swiebocka, Teresa. [http://www.dccam.org/Projects/Affinity/SIF/DATA/2000/page1126.html Report from Workshop 1 on Remembrance and Representation: Presentation by Teresa Swiebocka], Stockholm International Forum on the Holocaust, 2000. Retrieved December 22, 2009.&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;determination&quot;&gt;Wellers, Georges. Essai de determination du nombre de morts au camp d'Auschwitz (attempt to determine the number of dead at the Auschwitz camp), ''Le Monde Juif'', Oct–Dec 1983, pp. 127–159.&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;dwork&quot;&gt;Dwork and van Pelt 1997, pp. 337–343.&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;encyclopedia&quot;&gt;Desmond Tutu, Simon Wiesenthal, Israel W. Charny: Encyclopedia of genocide p.300&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;extermination&quot;&gt;[[Saul Friedländer|Friedländer, Saul]]. [[The Years of Extermination: Nazi Germany and the Jews, 1939-1945]] (2007). Pp. 422–423.&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;eyewitness&quot;&gt;&quot;Auschwitz: A Doctor's Eyewitness Account&quot; (Dr. [[Miklos Nyiszli]])&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;financing&quot;&gt;Gabor Kadar and Zoltan Vagi: Self-Financing Genocide: The Gold Train – The Becher Case – The Wealth of Jews p.125, Hungary; Central European Univ Pr; ISBN 9639241539 (Sep 2004)&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;gebundene&quot;&gt;Die Namen der Nummern (Gebundene Ausgabe) von Hans-Joachim Lang (Autor)Publisher: Hoffmann + Campe Vlg GmbH (August 31, 2004) ISBN 3-455-09464-3 ISBN 978-3-455-09464-0&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;guardian&quot;&gt;Connolly, Kate. [http://www.guardian.co.uk/world/2009/dec/18/auschwitz-arbeit-macht-frei-sign Poland declares state of emergency after 'Arbeit Macht Frei' stolen from Auschwitz], ''[[The Guardian]]'', December 18, 2009.&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;gutman&quot;&gt;Gutman 1992, p. 6.&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;gutman10&quot;&gt;Gutman 1994, p. 21.&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;gutman5&quot;&gt;Anatomy of the Auschwitz death camp By Yisrael Gutman, Michael Berenbaum Publisher: Indiana University Press (April 1, 1998) Language: English ISBN 025320884X ISBN 978-0253208842&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;gutman9&quot;&gt;Gutman 1994, pp. 20–21.&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;harmon-drobnicki&quot;&gt;Brian Harmon, John Drobnicki, [http://nizkor.org/features/techniques-of-denial/appendix-2-01.html Historical sources and the Auschwitz death toll estimates], [http://nizkor.org/ ''The Nizkor Project'']&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;holocaust&quot;&gt;Daring to Resist: Jewish Defiance in the Holocaust Publisher: Museum of Jewish Heritage – A Living Memorial to the Holocaust (April 1, 2007) ISBN 0-9716859-2-4 ISBN 978-0-9716859-2-5&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;holocaust-history&quot;&gt;Pressac: Auschwitz: Technique and Operation of the Gas Chambers [http://www.holocaust-history.org/auschwitz/pressac/technique-and-operation/pressac0100.shtml Holocaust-History.org] p. 100 reports that the timesheets of a civilian worker from the company building the crematorium furnaces prove that the installed ventilation system for removing the hydrocyan acid gas from Zyklon B application in the morgues worked well.&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;international&quot;&gt;Substantive and Procedural Aspects of International Criminal Law : The Experience of International and National Courts: Materials by Gabrielle Kirk McDonald Publisher: Springer; 1 edition (March 1, 2000) ISBN 90-411-1134-4 ISBN 9789041111340&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;ipn&quot;&gt;Garlinski 1975; [http://www.pilecki.ipn.gov.pl/portal/rp/867/7081/Rotmistrz_Witold_Pilecki.html IPN.gov.pl]&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;isurvived&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://isurvived.org/Lustig_Oliver-CCDictionary/CCD-05_FG.html#B5 |title=Concentration Camp Dictionary &quot;F-G&quot;]|author=Oliver Lustig |publisher=Isurvived.org |accessdate=August 23, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;karny&quot;&gt;Karny 1994, p. 556.&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;kavanaugh&quot;&gt;Cesarani and Kavanaugh 2004, p. 357.&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;klarsfeld&quot;&gt;[[Peter Hellman]], [[Lili Meier]], [[Beate Klarsfeld]]. ''The Auschwitz Album'', p. 166. Random House, Inc. New York, NY, 1981. ISBN 394-51932-9.&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;krakowski&quot;&gt;Krakowski 1994, p. 50.&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;morris&quot;&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.errolmorris.com/film/mrd_transcript.html|title=Mr. Death: Transcript|first=Errol|last=Morris|accessdate=May 15, 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;nytimes&quot;&gt;[http://www.nytimes.com/2009/12/23/world/europe/23briefs-Polandbf.html Poland: Foreigner Is Suspected in Theft of Auschwitz Sign], Associated Press, December 22, 2009.&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;nytimes26&quot;&gt;{{cite news| url=http://www.nytimes.com/2011/06/03/world/europe/03briefs-Poland.html | work=The New York Times | title=Poland: Auschwitz Sign to Hang Indoors | date=June 2, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;oswiecim&quot;&gt;[http://www.um.oswiecim.pl/rocznica/index.php?Itemid=99&amp;id=55&amp;option=com_content&amp;task=view Article about expulsions from Oświęcim in Polish]&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;paperbacks&quot;&gt;The Holocaust: a history of the Jews of Europe during the Second World War By Martin Gilbert Pages 683–697; Publisher: Holt Paperbacks (May 15, 1987) ISBN 0-8050-0348-7 ISBN 978-0-8050-0348-2&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;piechowski&quot;&gt;&quot;Byłem Numerem: swiadectwa Z Auschwitz&quot; by Kazimierz Piechowski, Eugenia Bozena Kodecka-Kaczynska, Michal Ziokowski, Hardcover, Wydawn. Siostr Loretanek, ISBN 83-7257-122-8&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;piper&quot;&gt;Piper 1994, pp. 68–70.&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;piper1&quot;&gt;Piper 1994, p. 62.&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;psychology&quot;&gt;The Nazi Doctors: Medical Killing and the Psychology of Genocide by Robert Jay Lifton Publisher: Basic Books (August 2000) Language: English ISBN 0465049052 ISBN 978-0465049059&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;publications&quot;&gt;Doctors from Hell: the Horrific Account of Nazi Experiments on Humans. By Vivien Spitz Publisher: Sentient Publications (May 25, 2005) ISBN 1-59181-032-9 ISBN 978-1-59181-032-2 Pages 232–234&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;publisher&quot;&gt;Night by Elie Weisel Publisher: Bantam (March 1, 1982) Language: English ISBN 0553272535 ISBN 978-0553272536&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;publishers&quot;&gt;Lewis, Jon E. (1999), ''The Mammoth Book of True War Stories, Carroll &amp; Graf Publishers'', ISBN 0-7867-0629-5. p. 391.&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;publishers19&quot;&gt;Last Traces: The Lost Art of Auschwitz by Joseph Czarnecki Publisher: [[Macmillan Publishers]] ISBN 0-689-12022-2 ISBN 978-0-689-12022-0&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;quoted&quot;&gt;[[Primo Levi]] quoted in Gutman 1994, p. 5.&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;rees&quot;&gt;Rees 2009, BBC.&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;rees11&quot;&gt;Rees 2005, pp. 178–179.&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;rees12&quot;&gt;Rees 2005, pp. 180–182.&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;rees13&quot;&gt;Rees 2005, pp. 256–257.&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;rees15&quot;&gt;Rees 2005, pp. 141.&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;rees16&quot;&gt;Rees 2005, pp. 260–265.&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;rees2&quot;&gt;Rees 2005, p. 26.&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;rees3&quot;&gt;Rees 2005, pp. 96–97, 101.&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;rees4&quot;&gt;Rees 2005, pp. 168–169.&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;rees7&quot;&gt;Rees 2005, p. 100.&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;rees8&quot;&gt;Rees 2005, pp. 172–175.&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;rubeigh&quot;&gt;Rubeigh James Minney. ''I shall fear no evil: the story of Dr. Alina Brewda''. Kimber, 1966. p. 152.&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;schwarberg&quot;&gt;Dein ist mein ganzes Herz (Fritz Löhner-Beda) by [[Günther Schwarberg]] (2000) ISBN 3882437154&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;sltrib&quot;&gt;[http://www.sltrib.com/ci_14044451?source=rss SLtrib.com]{{Dead link|date=August 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;telegraph&quot;&gt;''[[Daily Telegraph]]'', page 20, issue of Friday March 19, 2010.&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;twentieth&quot;&gt;The Twentieth Train: The True Story of the Ambush of the Death Train to Auschwitz by Marion Schreiber Publisher: Grove Press (February 5, 2004) ISBN 0-8021-1766-X ISBN 978-0-8021-1766-3&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;umkc&quot;&gt;[http://www.law.umkc.edu/faculty/projects/ftrials/nuremberg/hoesstest.html Testimony of Rudolf Hoess, Commandant of Auschwitz], University of Missouri-Kansas City School of Law; [http://www1.yadvashem.org/odot_pdf/microsoft%20word%20-%206418.pdf Hoess, Rudolf (1900–1947), camp commandant of Auschwitz], Yad Vashem. Retrieved December 22, 2009.&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;unesco&quot;&gt;[http://whc.unesco.org/en/list/31 Auschwitz Birkenau, German Nazi Concentration and Extermination Camp (1940–1945).] [[UNESCO]] World Heritage List.&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;university&quot;&gt;Beyond Justice: The Auschwitz Trial by Rebecca Wittmann Publisher: Harvard University Press (May 30, 2005) ISBN 0-674-01694-7 ISBN 978-0-674-01694-1&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;widerstandsgruppen&quot;&gt;[[Heinz Galinski]], &quot;Jüdische Widerstandsgruppen&quot;. ''Unser Appell'' (journal of the [[Union of Persecutees of the Nazi Regime]]), no. 3/4 (September 10, 1947)&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;wittmann&quot;&gt;Wittmann 2003.&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;yadvashem&quot;&gt;[http://www1.yadvashem.org/about_holocaust/chronology/1939-1941/1941/chronology_1941_27.html September 3: First experimental gassings at Auschwitz], Yad Vashem.&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;yahoo&quot;&gt;[http://uk.news.yahoo.com/22/20091221/tts-uk-poland-auschwitz-ca02f96.html News.Yahoo.com]{{Dead link|date=August 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;
}}

==References==
{{Refbegin|2}}
* Cesarani, David and Kavanaugh, Sarah (2004). ''Holocaust: Critical Concepts in Historical Studies''. [[Routledge]]. ISBN 0-415-27512-1, 9780415275125
* Czech, Danuta (ed.) (1989). ''Kalendarium der Ereignisse im Konzentrationslager Auschwitz-Birkenau 1939–1945'', Reinbek bei Hamburg.
* [[Lucy Dawidowicz|Dawidowicz, Lucy]] (1979). ''The War Against the Jews''. New York: Bantam Books.
* [[Debórah Dwork|Dwork, Deborah]] and Robert Jan van Pelt. ''Auschwitz: 1270 to the Present''. 1997, Norton Paperback edition, ISBN 0-393-31684-X
* Garlinski, Josef (1975). ''Fighting Auschwitz: the Resistance Movement in the Concentration Camp''. Fawcett. ISBN 0-449-22599-2
* [[Yisrael Gutman|Gutman, Yisrael]] and [[Michael Berenbaum|Berenbaum, Michael]] (eds.) (1998).  ''Anatomy of the Auschwitz Death Camp''. [[Indiana University Press]]; first published 1994.
* [[Raul Hilberg|Hilberg, Raul]] (1961). ''The Destruction of the European Jews''. Chicago: Quadrangle Books.
* [[Primo Levi|Levi, Primo]] (1947). ''[[If This Is a Man]]''. First published in Italy in 1947, first translated into English 1958.
* [[Miroslav Kárný|Kárný, Miroslav]] (1994). &quot;The Vrba and Wetzler report,&quot; in Gutman and Berenbaum, 1998.
* Krakowski, Shmuel (1994). &quot;The Satellite Camps&quot; in Gutman and Berenbaum, 1998.
* [[Franciszek Piper|Piper, Franciszek]] (1994). &quot;The Number of Victims&quot; in Gutman and Berenbaum, 1998.
* [[Laurence Rees|Rees, Laurence]] (2005). ''Auschwitz: A New History''. Public Affairs, 2005. ISBN 1-58648-303-X
* Rees, Laurence (2009). [http://www.bbc.co.uk/history/worldwars/genocide/hoss_commandant_auschwitz_01.shtml Rudolf Höss – Commandant of Auschwitz], BBC, November 5, 2009.
* {{cite book|last=Rees|first=Laurence|title=Auschwitz: The Nazis &amp; the Final Solutiuon|year=2005|publisher=Random House|isbn=9780563522966}}
* {{Cite book|last=Reeves |first=Keir |title=Places of Pain and Shame: Dealing with 'Difficult Heritage'  |year=2009 |publisher=Taylor &amp; Francis US |isbn=978-0-415-45449-0 |url=http://books.google.com/books?id=ErJQ_OgrYpMC&amp;pg=PA56 |accessdate=23 November 2011 }}
* Wittmann, Rebecca Elizabeth. &quot;Indicting Auschwitz? The Paradox of the Frankfurt Auschwitz Trial,&quot; ''German History'', volume 21, issue 4, [[Oxford University Press]], October 2003, doi 10.1191/0266355403gh294oa
{{Refend}}

==Further reading==
{{Refbegin|2}}
* [http://en.auschwitz.org.pl/m/ Memorial and museum website]
* Boyne, John (2006). ''The Boy in the Striped Pyjamas'' Great Britain: David Fickling Books, 2006 ISBN 0-385-75106-0
* [[Borowski, Tadeusz]] (1976). ''[[This Way for the Gas, Ladies and Gentlemen]] (Penguin Classics)'' trans. from the Polish by Barbara Vedder. Penguin Books, 1976 ISBN 0-14-018624-7
* Cyra, Adam (2000). ''Ochotnik do Auschwitz – Witold Pilecki 1901–1948'', Oświęcim 2000. ISBN 83-912000-3-5
* Dlugoborski, Waclaw, and Franciszek Piper (eds.) (2000). ''Auschwitz, 1940–1945: Central Issues in the History of the Camp'' Five Vols. Oświęcim: Auschwitz-Birkenau State Museum. ISBN 83-85047-87-5
* [[Gilbert, Martin]] (1981). ''Auschwitz and the Allies'' New York: Holt, Rinehart and Winston, 1981 Photographs, maps. ISBN 0-03-057058-1
* Muller, Filip ''Eyewitness Auschwitz: Three Years in the Gas Chambers'' Ivan R Dee Inc, 1999 ISBN 1-56663-271-4
* Nyisli, Miklos ''Auschwitz: A Doctor's Eye-witness Account'' Mayflower, 1977 ASIN B000QIZILC
* van Pelt, Robert Jan. ''The Case for Auschwitz: Evidence from the Irving Trial''. Indiana University Press, 2002. ISBN 0-253-34016-0
* [http://www.druhasvetovavalka.cz/galerie.php?g=2_brezinka Druhasvetovavalka.cz], – Pages show pictures and videos of the day taken at places connected with World War II
* [http://www.auschwitz.org.pl/ Auschwitz-Birkenau Memorial and Museum] {{en icon}}, {{ge icon}}, {{pl icon}} – Official website
* [http://www.remember.org/auschwitz/ A Virtual Tour of Auschwitz/Birkenau] Annotated images of the camp (accessed February 14, 2008)
* [http://remember.org/camps/birkenau/index.html Interactive image map of Birkenau]
* [http://www.ajcf.org/ Auschwitz Jewish Center] situated in the town of Oświęcim
* {{pl icon}} [http://www.auschwitz-oswiecim.pl/ Auschwitz-Birkenau and city Oswiecim]
* [http://isurvived.org/AUSCHWITZ_TheCamp.html Data and summary facts]
* [http://video.google.com/videoplay?docid=5156918753541068347&amp;q=auschwitz&amp;hl=en Video footage from a 2003 visit to Auschwitz-Birkenau]
* [http://isurvived.org/Lustig_AuschwitzAlbum.html Selected Photos from the Auschwitz Album with commentary by Oliver Lustig]
* [http://www.ushmm.org/museum/exhibit/focus/auschwitz Liberation of Auschwitz – 60th Anniversary] United States Holocaust Memorial Museum
* [http://www.ushmm.org/wlc/en/index.php?ModuleId=10005189 Holocaust Encyclopedia – Auschwitz] United States Holocaust Memorial Museum
* [http://www.remember.org/ Cybrary of the Holocaust] Holocaust education site
* [http://www.annaheilman.net/index.html Anna Heilman] Anna Heilman is the last living survivor of the plot to blow up Crematorium IV at Auschwitz-Birkenau. Her Holocaust experiences are discussed in her novel ''Never Far Away: The Auschwitz Chronicle of Anna Heilman''
* [http://www.auschwitz-birkenau.org/ Auschwitz-Birkenau 2005] Photographs and commentary marking the 60th anniversary of the camp's liberation
* [http://www.remember.org/camps/ Photos From Auschwitz and Birkenau] Detailed Photos From Auschwitz and Birkenau by Alan Jacobs
* [http://www.remember.org/auschwitz/ Virtual Reality panoramas of Auschwitz and Birkenau] Interactive Virtual Reality panoramas of Auschwitz and Birkenau
* [http://remember.org/then-and-now/ Auschwitz, Then and Now Photo/Art Exhibit] Paintings by survivor Jan Komski – click and see an actual photo taken in the same place depicted in the painting
* [http://www.bbc.co.uk/history/worldwars/genocide/ Auschwitz: The Nazis and the 'Final Solution'], BBC.
* [http://www.wiesenthal.com/ The Simon Wiesenthal Center]
* [http://maps.google.com/maps?f=q&amp;hl=en&amp;q=50%C2%B0+1%27+26%22,+19%C2%B0+12%27+18%22&amp;ll=50.023889,19.205&amp;spn=0.026138,0.086517&amp;t=k Auschwitz] and [http://maps.google.com/maps?f=q&amp;hl=en&amp;q=50%C2%B0+2%27+20%22,+19%C2%B0+10%27+30%22&amp;ll=50.038895,19.175005&amp;spn=0.02613,0.086517&amp;t=k Birkenau] at Google Maps
* [http://archives.cbc.ca/IDD-1-71-1579/conflict_war/echoes_of_auschwitz/ CBC Digital Archives – Life after Auschwitz]
{{Refend}}

==External links==
* [http://www.pbs.org/wnet/secrets/episodes/escape-from-auschwitz/8/ Escape From Auschwitz]
* [http://en.auschwitz.org.pl/m/ Auschwitz Memorial]
* [http://www1.yadvashem.org/exhibitions/album_auschwitz/index.html?WT.mc_id=wiki The Auschwitz Album] – Online exhibition from Yad Vashem
* [http://www1.yadvashem.org/yv/en/exhibitions/auschwitz_architecture/index.asp?WT.mc_id=wiki The Auschwitz-Birkenau Blueprints- Architecture of Murder] – Online exhibition from Yad Vashem
{{World Heritage Sites in Poland}}
{{Holocaust Poland}}
{{The Holocaust (end)}}
{{Use mdy dates|date=July 2011}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Auschwitz Concentration Camp}}
[[Category:Auschwitz concentration camp| ]]
[[Category:World War II sites]]
[[Category:1940 establishments]]
[[Category:Human rights abuses]]

{{Link FA|he}}
[[ar:معسكر أوشفيتز بيركينو]]
[[az:Auşvits]]
[[be:Асвенцым]]
[[be-x-old:Асьвенцім]]
[[bs:Koncentracioni logor Auschwitz]]
[[br:Auschwitz-Birkenau]]
[[bg:Аушвиц (концлагер)]]
[[ca:Auschwitz]]
[[ceb:Auschwitz-Birkenau]]
[[cs:Auschwitz-Birkenau]]
[[cy:Auschwitz]]
[[da:Auschwitz]]
[[de:KZ Auschwitz-Birkenau]]
[[et:Oświęcimi koonduslaager]]
[[el:Στρατόπεδο συγκέντρωσης Άουσβιτς]]
[[es:Auschwitz]]
[[eo:Aŭŝvico (koncentreja komplekso)]]
[[eu:Auschwitz]]
[[fa:اردوگاه آشویتس]]
[[fr:Auschwitz]]
[[fy:Auschwitz]]
[[fur:Auschwitz]]
[[gl:Auschwitz-Birkenau]]
[[ko:아우슈비츠 강제 수용소]]
[[hr:Auschwitz]]
[[id:Kamp konsentrasi Auschwitz]]
[[is:Auschwitz]]
[[it:Campo di concentramento di Auschwitz]]
[[he:אושוויץ]]
[[ka:ოსვენციმის საკონცენტრაციო ბანაკი]]
[[lad:Auschwitz]]
[[lv:Aušvicas koncentrācijas nometne]]
[[lt:Aušvico koncentracijos stovykla]]
[[lmo:Auschwitz (KZ)]]
[[hu:Auschwitzi koncentrációs tábor]]
[[mk:Аушвиц]]
[[ml:ഓഷ്‌വ്വിറ്റ്സ് തടങ്കൽപ്പാളയം]]
[[mr:ऑश्विझ छळछावणी]]
[[ms:Kem tumpuan Auschwitz]]
[[nl:Auschwitz (concentratiekamp)]]
[[ja:アウシュヴィッツ＝ビルケナウ強制収容所]]
[[no:Auschwitz]]
[[nn:Auschwitz]]
[[pl:Auschwitz-Birkenau]]
[[pt:Auschwitz-Birkenau]]
[[ksh:Konzentratiunslajer Auschwitz-Birkenau]]
[[ro:Lagărul de exterminare Auschwitz]]
[[ru:Освенцим]]
[[sc:Campu de cuncentramentu de Auschwitz]]
[[sq:Kampi Auschwitz-Birkenau]]
[[simple:Auschwitz concentration camp]]
[[sk:Koncentračný tábor Auschwitz-Birkenau]]
[[sl:Koncentracijsko taborišče Auschwitz]]
[[sr:Логор Аушвиц]]
[[fi:Auschwitz]]
[[sv:Auschwitz]]
[[ta:அவுஷ்விட்ஸ் வதை முகாம்]]
[[th:ค่ายกักกันเอาชวิทซ์]]
[[tr:Auschwitz-Birkenau]]
[[uk:Аушвіц—Біркенау]]
[[vi:Trại tập trung Auschwitz]]
[[yi:אוישוויץ]]
[[zh-yue:奧斯威辛集中營]]
[[zh:奥斯威辛集中营]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
