<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="20086925" ns="0" title="Greg Heffley"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{notability|date=December 2011}}
{{Infobox character
| colour      = #FFFFB
| colour text = 
| name        = Greg &quot;Gregory&quot; Heffley
| series      = [[Diary of a Wimpy Kid (series)|Diary of a Wimpy Kid]]
| image       = [[Image:Wimpy kid.jpg]]
| caption     = 
| first       = [[Diary of a Wimpy Kid]]
| last        = 
| cause       = 
| creator     = [[Jeff Kinney (writer)|Jeff Kinney]]
| portrayer   = [[Zachary Gordon]]
| episode     = 
| nickname    = Greg
| alias       = Wimpy Kid
| species     = [[Human]]
| gender      = [[Male]]
| age         = 11 (as of 2006) ([[Diary of a Wimpy Kid|Book 1]]), 12 ([[Diary of a Wimpy Kid: Rodrick Rules|Book 2]], and [[Diary of a Wimpy Kid: The Last Straw|Book 3]], and part of [[Diary of a Wimpy Kid: Dog Days|Book 4]]), 13 (Book 4, [[Diary of a Wimpy Kid: The Ugly Truth|Book 5]], and [[Diary of a Wimpy Kid: Cabin Fever|Book 6]]) 
| born        = June 15, 1995 (Novel Series), February 23 ([[Funbrain]] Version))&lt;ref name=&quot;gregbirthday&quot;&gt;{{cite web|title=Diary of a Wimpy Kid|url=http://www.funbrain.com/journal/Journal.html?ThisJournalDay=170&amp;ThisPage=1|work=Funbrain|publisher=Family Education Network|accessdate=5 March 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;
| death       = 
| specialty   =
| occupation  = Student 
| title       = 
| callsign    = 
| family      = Susan Heffley (Mom), Frank Heffley (Dad), Rodrick (older brother), Manny (younger brother)
| spouse      = 
| significantother = 
| children    = 
| relatives   = 
| residence   = 12 Surrey Street (as of the Do-It-Yourself Book)
| religion    = 
| nationality = 
| imdb_id     = 
}}

'''Gregory &quot;Greg&quot; Heffley''' is the main [[protagonist]] of the [[realistic fiction]] book series ''[[Diary of a Wimpy Kid (series)|Diary of a Wimpy Kid]]'' created by American cartoonist [[Jeff Kinney (writer)|Jeff Kinney]]. Greg has appeared in [[Diary of a Wimpy Kid]],&lt;ref name=&quot;first book&quot;&gt;{{cite book
|last= Kinney
|first= Jeff
|title= [[Diary of a Wimpy Kid]]
|series= [[Diary of a Wimpy Kid (series)|''Diary of a Wimpy Kid'']]
|publisher= [[Amulet Books]]
|year= 2007
|isbn= 0-8109-9313-9}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Diary of a Wimpy Kid: Rodrick Rules|Rodrick Rules]],&lt;ref name=&quot;second book&quot;&gt;{{cite book
|last=Kenny
|first=Jeff
|title= [[Diary of a Wimpy Kid: Rodrick Rules]]
|series=[[Diary of a Wimpy Kid (series)|Diary of a Wimpy Kid]]
|year=2008
|isbn=
}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Diary of a Wimpy Kid: The Last Straw|The Last Straw]],.&lt;ref name=&quot;amulet&quot;&gt;{{cite book |last=Kinney |first=Jeff |authorlink=Jeff Kinney (writer) |title=Diary of a Wimpy Kid: The Last Straw |year=2009 |origmonth=January |accessdate=August 1, 2008 |series=[[Diary of a Wimpy Kid (series)]] |publisher=[[Amulet Books]] }}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Diary of a Wimpy Kid: Dog Days|Dog Days]],.&lt;ref name=&quot;dogdays&quot;&gt;{{cite book|last=Kinney|first=Jeff|title=Diary of a Wimpy Kid: Dog Days|year=2009|publisher=Abrams Books|pages=217}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Diary of a Wimpy Kid: The Ugly Truth|The Ugly Truth]],&lt;ref name=&quot;fifth book&quot;&gt;{{cite book
|last= Kenny
|first=Jeff
|title= [[Diary of a Wimpy Kid: The Ugly Truth]]
|series= [[Diary of a Wimpy Kid (series)|Diary of a Wimpy Kid]]
|year= 2010
|isbn=
}}&lt;/ref&gt; and [[Diary of a Wimpy Kid: Cabin Fever|Cabin Fever]]. He has also appeared in all of the spin offs, [[Diary of a Wimpy Kid: Do-It-Yourself Book]], and [[The Wimpy Kid Movie Diary]], along with the expansions ''The Wimpy Kid Do-It-Yourself'' and ''The Wimpy Kid Movie Diary 2: Rodrick Rules''

==Personality==
===Actions in the Diary of a Wimpy Kid series===
Unlike his brother, Rodrick,  Greg has been shown to show remorse for his actions and enjoys sleeping.  He explains that he is good at nothing except video games, which he spends most of his time playing. He grows an interest of drawing [[Comic strip|comics]] for the school newspaper before he quits when Mr. Ira, a teacher at his school who edits the comics, ruins it by trying to use it as an ad for the school's library. Greg comes up with many different ideas and sub-jobs, including becoming a safety patroller in school. He also has a crush on Holly Hills until the end of ''[[Diary of a Wimpy Kid: The Last Straw|The Last Straw]]'', where he decides it wouldn't work out because she mistakens him for Fregley.  He began to have a crush on a new girl that moved to his street, called Trista, but it seems like she didn't have any interest in him.  Greg later began to impress Heather Hills when she became a life guard at the town pool, but that didn't work either. It is presumed that Greg's family believes in the Catholic Christian faith because they attend church and in the visual novel Greg goes to confession. Greg often tries avoiding certain events (such as being in a school play) or to achieve a goal (such as impressing a crush), but almost all of Greg's schemes fail and sometimes leads to serious, frustrating, and always unfair outcomes. 

He is shown to be quite paranoid in numerous occasions, usually over petty reasons. For example, he believes he will be arrested for returning to a library where he has forgotten to return a book years ago. In &quot;Cabin Fever&quot;, he is afraid that he may not graduate due to being unable to skip in the first grade.

He is shown on a few occasions to be a hypocrite, usually directed towards his thoughts of his friendship with Rowley. In &quot;The Ugly Truth&quot;, he believes that a friendship will only work if one friend is a lackey to the other, which he believed wasn't the case with him and Rowley (thinking they were equals), when in reality Greg constantly abused Rowley for selfish reasons, which was one of the reasons they were no longer friends in that book. In the same book, Greg becomes angry at Rowley's choice of going to a party without him just because Greg couldn't go, causing Greg to angrily state that he's glad he's not friends with him anymore to Rowley's &quot;selfish choice&quot;, when in reality Greg abused him constantly for selfish reasons.

One of the main points of the series is that rarely does anything good ever really happen to Greg, at least in the short-term. He is often seen in embarrassing, unfair, and overall unpleasant and difficult situations. This stems from both his selfish and lazy personality and the fact that he does not get along with his family, Rowley or peers at school, and sometimes because of simply bad luck, which usually trumps over any good luck he's had in the series.

As the series progresses, Greg is fit enough to do push-ups, sit-ups and even climb up trees. He also reads books and newspapers more actively. It is noted that Greg has a talent for comics and loves illustrating and writing them, even known for starting the successful comic, ''Zoo-Wee Mama!'', but his comic was under Rowley's name when they were enemies.

==Relationships with other characters in Diary of a Wimpy Kid==
===Rodrick===
Rodrick is greg's older brother. Rodrick is in elementry school, and he is at least 16 years old, due to the fact that he can drive and that Greg said Rodrick was sick for his sophomore yearbook pictures. In the second book, Rodrick has more parts in the story, including his band called Löded Diper (according to Greg is really spelled Loaded Diaper), in which he plays the drums. He often argues with Greg. He was grounded along with Greg after their parents discovered Rodrick's party, blaming Greg for thinking that he helped Rodrick, when Greg was in fact, locked in the basement all night. Rodrick once locked Greg out of a hotel room when Greg was in his underwear (he calls them &quot;tighty whities&quot;) in ''[[The Last Straw]]''. It has also been shown that Rodrick greatly conceals his pranks on Greg, causing their parents to think Greg is crazy.

===Rowley===
Rowley is Greg's overall best buddy. They met each other when Rowley moved into Greg's neighborhood. They go to the same school and walk there together, and they share 4 classes.
Rowley has a number of peculiar characteristics which mostly embarrass Greg but sometimes interest him.    

What Greg resents the most of Rowley is his lack of macho and with rather strange interests, such as   a &quot;Sweet Secrets&quot; diary, an interest in the band singer Joshie (who Greg thinks might be for six-year old girls, although Rowley thought he was just jealous), sensitivity, love for the comic &quot;Li'l Cutie&quot; (which Greg hates), bumper boats, and kiddie birthday parties, Rowley's not exactly the picture of manliness. In [[Diary of a Wimpy Kid (film)|the movie]], Greg was talking Rowley into burning a shirt of him and his mom on it that said &quot;Me and my Mommy&quot;.    

Greg and Rowley have a complex relationship. They are both great friends, but Greg has a habit of treating Rowley poorly and often takes advantage of him for his own selfish desires. Rowley starts out as a pushover in the beginning of the series, being treated poorly by Greg and often following his schemes, but this trait seems to fade away as in the fourth book, as Rowley is starting to lose patience with Greg.

Rowley's dad does not like Greg and uses him as an example of a &quot;bad influence&quot;. Although Rowley has been described as &quot;unpopular&quot; by Greg (thinking that he is about the 150th most popular kid in the school), girls seem to like him because he is cute (in a little kid way) and his family is always taking expensive vacations, like going to [[Europe]], [[South America]] and [[Australia]] (as mentioned in the beginning of ''Rodrick Rules'') and renting a log cabin on their trip to the beach late in ''Dog Days''.

Rowley and Greg begin to slowly drift apart in ''Dog Days'', after several fights and conflicts, which implies that Greg will no longer maintain friendship with Rowley. However, they did make up at the end of [[Diary of a Wimpy Kid: The Ugly Truth]].

==Allusions from other works==
Greg Heffley appears on [[Poptropica]]'s 18th island, Wimpy Wonderland, revolving around the ''Wimpy Kid'' series&lt;ref&gt;http://www.poptropica.com/island-tour/wimpy-wonderland-island.html&lt;/ref&gt;

==Film==
In 2010, [[Diary of a Wimpy Kid]], was made into a film, released in March 19, and Greg was portrayed by [[Zachary Gordon]].

==Reception==
As for the [[Diary of a Wimpy Kid (film)|2010 film]], [[Rotten Tomatoes]] has said that Greg is an &quot;unlikable [[protagonist]]&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |title = Diary of a Wimpy Kid (2010) |url = http://www.rottentomatoes.com/m/diary_of_a_wimpy_kid/ |work = [[Rotten Tomatoes]] |publisher = [[Flixster]] |accessdate = August 29, 2010 }}&lt;/ref&gt; Pomeranz disliked the character of Greg Heffley, saying &quot;I really thought he was unpleasant. I did not want to spend time with him. I couldn't wait for the end of this film.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite episode |title = 29 September 2010 |series = At the Movies |serieslink = At the Movies (Australian TV series) |credits = [[David Stratton]], [[Margaret Pomeranz]] |network = [[Australian Broadcasting Corporation]] |airdate = September 29, 2010 |seriesno = |number = |transcript = 29 September 2010|transcripturl = http://www.abc.net.au/atthemovies/txt/s3005044.htm}}&lt;/ref&gt;  Greg also appeared as a balloon in the 2010 and 2011 [[Macy's]] Thanksgiving Day Parade.

==References==
{{reflist}}

{{Diary of a Wimpy Kid}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Heffley, Greg}}
[[Category:Diary of a Wimpy Kid]]
[[Category:Child characters in literature]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
