<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><redirects><r from="Moundsville State Penitentiary" to="West Virginia State Penitentiary" /></redirects><pages><page pageid="7715554" ns="0" title="West Virginia State Penitentiary"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Infobox building
| name       = West Virginia State Penitentiary
| native_name= 
| former_names        = 
| image               = West_Virginia_State_Penitentiary.jpg
| caption             = The penitentiary in 2006
| map_type            = 
| building_type       = Prison
| architectural_style = [[Gothic architecture]]
| structural_system   = 
| cost                = $363,061
| location            = [[Moundsville, West Virginia]]
| address             = 818 Jefferson Avenue
| client              = 
| owner               = 
| current_tenants     = Moundsville Economic Development Council
| landlord            = 
| coordinates         = {{coord|39.91649|-80.742368|type:edu|display=inline,title}}
| start_date          = 1867
| completion_date     = 1876
| inauguration_date   = 
| demolition_date     = 
| destruction_date    = 
| height              = 
| diameter            = 
| other_dimensions    = 
| floor_count         = 
| floor_area          = 
| main_contractor     = 
| architect           = 
| structural_engineer = 
| services_engineer   = 
| civil_engineer      = 
| other_designers     = 
| quantity_surveyor   = 
| awards              = 
| references          = 
}}

The '''West Virginia State Penitentiary''' is a retired, [[Gothic architecture|gothic]] style prison located in [[Moundsville, West Virginia]]. It operated from 1876 to 1995. Currently, the site is maintained as a tourist attraction and training facility.&lt;ref name=&quot;Official&quot;&gt;{{cite news | title=Former West Virginia Penitentiary (Official Site)| url=http://www.wvpentours.com | accessdate=6 November 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Design==
The West Virginia State Penitentiary's design is similar to the facility at [[Joliet Prison|Joliet]] with its castellated Gothic, stone structure, complete with turrets and battlements, except only half the size.&lt;ref name=&quot;Official&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;LandPurchase&quot;&gt;{{cite news | title=Abandoned - West Virginia Pentitentiary| url=http://www.abandonedonline.net/index.php?catid=320 | accessdate=6 November 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt; Unfortunately, the original architectural designs have been lost.&lt;ref name=&quot;Official&quot;/&gt; The dimensions of the parallelogram-shaped prison yard are 82½ feet in length, by 352½ feet in width.&lt;ref name=&quot;Official&quot;/&gt; The stone walls are {{convert|5|ft|m}} thick at the base, tapering to 2½ feet at the top, with foundations {{convert|5|ft|m}} deep.&lt;ref name=&quot;Official&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;LandPurchase&quot;/&gt; The center tower section is {{convert|682|ft|m}} long.&lt;ref name=&quot;Official&quot;/&gt; It lies at the western side of the complex along Jefferson Avenue and is considered the front, as this is where the main entrance is located.&lt;ref name=&quot;Official&quot;/&gt; The walls here are {{convert|24|ft|m}} high and {{convert|6|ft|m}} wide at the base, tapering to {{convert|18|in|mm}} towards the top.&lt;ref name=&quot;Official&quot;/&gt;

==History==
===Founding===
In 1863, [[West Virginia]] seceded from [[Virginia]] at the height of the [[American Civil War]]. Consequently, the new state had a shortage of various public institutions, including prisons.The Wagon Gate was the only building at this site, during the Civil War From 1863 to 1866, [[List of Governors of West Virginia|Governor]] [[Arthur I. Boreman]] lobbied the [[West Virginia Legislature]] for a state penitentiary but was repeatedly denied.&lt;ref name=&quot;LandPurchase&quot;/&gt; The Legislature at first tried to direct him to send the prisoners to other institutions out of the state, and then they directed him to use existing county jails, which turned out to be inadequate.&lt;ref name=&quot;LandPurchase&quot;/&gt; After nine inmates escaped in 1865, the local press took up the cause, and the Legislature took action.&lt;ref name=&quot;LandPurchase&quot;/&gt;  On 7 February 1866, the state legislature approved the purchase of land in Moundsville for the purpose of constructing a state prison.&lt;ref name=&quot;LandPurchase&quot;/&gt;  Ten acres were purchased just outside of the then city limits of Moundsville for $3000.&lt;ref name=&quot;LandPurchase&quot;/&gt;  Moundsville proved an attractive site, as it is approximately twelve miles south of [[Wheeling, West Virginia]], which at that time was the state capital.&lt;ref name=&quot;Official&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;LandPurchase&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;TCGA&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.travelchannel.com/TV_Shows/Ghost_Adventures/ci.Moundsville_State_Penitentiary.show?vgnextfmt=show |title=Moundsville State Penitentiary |accessdate=31 October 2008 |work=travelchannel.com |publisher=The Travel Channel, L.L.C. }}&lt;/ref&gt;

The state built a temporary wooden prison nearby that summer. This gave prison officials time to assess what prison design should be used.  Northern Illinois Penitentiary at Joliet proved to be an attractive design. Its Gothic Revival architecture &quot;exhibit[ed], as much as possible, great strength and convey[ed] to the mind a cheerless blank indicative of the misery which awaits the unhappy being who enters within its walls.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;LandPurchase&quot;/&gt;

The first building constructed on the site was the North Wagon Gate.&lt;ref name=&quot;Official&quot;/&gt; It was made with hand-cut [[sandstone]], which was quarried from a local site.&lt;ref name=&quot;Official&quot;/&gt;  The state used prison labor during the construction process, and work continued on this first phase until 1876.&lt;ref name=&quot;Official&quot;/&gt;  When completed, the total cost was of $363,061.&lt;ref name=&quot;Official&quot;/&gt; In addition to the North Wagon Gate, there was now north and south cellblock areas (both measuring 300&amp;nbsp;ft. by 52&amp;nbsp;ft.&lt;ref name=&quot;LandPurchase&quot;/&gt;).&lt;ref name=&quot;Official&quot;/&gt; South Hall had 224 cells (7&amp;nbsp;ft. by 4&amp;nbsp;ft.), and North Hall had a kitchen, dining area, hospital, and chapel.&lt;ref name=&quot;LandPurchase&quot;/&gt; A 4-story tower connecting the two was the administration building (measuring 75&amp;nbsp;ft. by 75&amp;nbsp;ft.&lt;ref name=&quot;LandPurchase&quot;/&gt;).&lt;ref name=&quot;Official&quot;/&gt;  It included space for female inmates and personal living quarters for the warden and his family.&lt;ref name=&quot;Official&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;LandPurchase&quot;/&gt;  The facility officially opened in this year, and it had a prison population of 251 male inmates, including some who had helped construct the very prison that now held them.&lt;ref name=&quot;Official&quot;/&gt; After this phase, work began on prison workshops and other secondary facilities.&lt;ref name=&quot;LandPurchase&quot;/&gt;

===Operation===
In addition to construction, the inmates had other jobs to do in support of the prison. In the early 1900s some industries within the prison walls included a [[Carpenter|carpentry]] shop, a [[paint]] shop, a [[wagon]] shop, a [[quarry|stone yard]], a [[brickyard]], a [[blacksmith]], a [[tailor]], a [[baker]]y, and a [[hospital]]. At the same time, revenue from the prison farm and inmate labor helped the prison financially. It was virtually self-sufficient. A prison [[coal]] [[Mining|mine]] located a mile away opened in 1921. This mine helped serve some of the prison's energy needs and saved the state an estimated $14,000 a year. Some inmates were allowed to stay at the mine's camp under the supervision of a mine foreman, who was not a prison employee.&lt;ref name=&quot;Official&quot;/&gt;

Conditions at the prison during the turn of the 20th century were good, according to a warden's report, which stated that, &quot;both the quantity and the quality of all the purchases of material, food and clothing have been very gradually, but steadily, improved, while the discipline has become more nearly perfect and the exaction of labor less stringent.&quot; Education was a priority for the inmates during this time. They regularly attended class. Construction on a school and library was completed in 1900 to help reform and educate inmates.&lt;ref name=&quot;Official&quot;/&gt;
[[File:moundsvilleconfine.jpg|thumb|left|Cells where the prison's worst inmates were kept.]]
However, the conditions at the prison worsened through the years, as the facility would be ranked on the [[United States Department of Justice|United States Department of Justice's]] ''Top Ten Most Violent Correctional Facilities'' list.&lt;ref name=&quot;TCGA&quot;/&gt; One of the more infamous locations in the prison, with instances of gambling, fighting,and raping, was a recreation room known as &quot;The Sugar Shack&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;TCGA&quot;/&gt; 

A notable inmate in the early 20th Century was [[Eugene V. Debs]], who served time here from April 13 to June 14, 1919 (at which time he was transferred to an [[Atlanta]] prison) for violating the [[Espionage Act of 1917]]. 

In 1929, the state decided to double the size of the penitentiary because overcrowding was a problem. The 5 x {{convert|7|ft|m|sing=on}} cells were too small to hold three prisoners at a time, but until the expansion there was no other option. Two prisoners would sleep in the bunks with the third sleeping on a mattress on the floor.&lt;ref name=&quot;TCGA&quot;/&gt; The state utilized prison labor once again and completed this phase of construction in 1959. The construction had been delayed by a [[steel]] shortage during [[World War II]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Official&quot;/&gt;

In total, thirty-six homicides took place in the prison.&lt;ref name=&quot;TCGA&quot;/&gt; One of the more notable ones is the butchering of R.D. Wall, inmate number 44670. On October 8, 1929, after &quot;[[Informant#Criminal_informers|snitching]]&quot; on his fellow inmates, he was attacked by three prisoners with dull [[Shiv (weapon)|shivs]] while heading to the boiler room.&lt;ref name=&quot;TCGA&quot;/&gt;

In 1983, [[Charles Manson]] requested to be transferred to this prison to be nearer to his family. His request was denied.&lt;ref name=&quot;AfterLife&quot;&gt;{{cite news |title=Afterlife Sentence| url=http://www.newsobserver.com/105/story/544546-p2.html |accessdate=6 July 2009}}{{Dead link|date=October 2010|bot=H3llBot}}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== 1979 prison break ===
On Wednesday, November 7, 1979, fifteen prisoners escaped from the prison. One of the escapees was Ronald Turney Williams, serving time for murdering Sergeant David Lilly of the [[Beckley, West Virginia|Beckley]] Police Department on May 12, 1975. He managed to steal a prison guard's service weapon in the escape, and upon reaching the streets of Moundsville, encountered twenty-three-year-old off-duty West Virginia State Trooper Philip S. Kesner, who was driving past the prison with his wife.&lt;ref name=Lilly&gt;{{cite news |first=Michelle |last=James |title=Beckley Fallen Heroes Fund: David Lilly |url=http://www.register-herald.com/features/local_story_146221349.html |work=register-herald.com |publisher=The Register-Herald |date=26 May 2007 |accessdate=6 July 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=TrooperMemorial&gt;{{cite web |title=Trooper Philip S. Kesner, West Virginia State Police |url=http://www.odmp.org/officer/7504-trooper-philip-s.-kesner |work=www.odmp.org |publisher=The Officer Down Memorial Page, Inc. |accessdate=30 June 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=Arizona&gt;{{cite web |title=Ronald Turney Williams |url=http://www.azcentral.com/specials/special32/articles/0903RWilliams-ON.html |date=4 September 2003 |work=azcentral.com |publisher=Arizona Central |accessdate=6 July 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=Rome&gt;{{cite news |author=Associated Press |title=Fugitive injured in shootout |url=http://news.google.com/newspapers?id=sPsGAAAAIBAJ&amp;sjid=4TQDAAAAIBAJ&amp;pg=6277,996870&amp;dq=philip+kesner |work=Google News |publisher=Rome News Tribune |date=9 June 1981 |accessdate=6 July 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Trooper Kesner saw the escapees and attempted to take action against them.  The prisoners pulled him from his car and Williams shot him. Trooper Kesner returned fire at the fleeing suspects despite being mortally wounded.&lt;ref name=TrooperMemorial/&gt;

Williams remained at large for eighteen months, sending taunting notes to authorities and making the [[Federal Bureau of Investigation|FBI's]] [[FBI Ten Most Wanted Fugitives|Ten Most Wanted List]]. During that time, he murdered John Bunchek in [[Scottsdale, Arizona]] during a robbery and was connected to crimes in [[Colorado]] and [[Pennsylvania]]. After a shootout with federal agents at the George Washington Hotel in New York City in 1981, he was apprehended and returned to West Virginia to complete several life sentences. Arizona had sought his extradition for his execution, but as of {{date}} he remains in West Virginia custody.&lt;ref name=TrooperMemorial/&gt;&lt;ref name=Arizona/&gt;&lt;ref name=Rome/&gt;&lt;ref name=Extradition&gt;{{cite news |first=William |last=Rawson |title=Transfer of convicted murderer sought |url=http://news.google.com/newspapers?nid=932&amp;dat=19950725&amp;id=pHcNAAAAIBAJ&amp;sjid=i1MDAAAAIBAJ&amp;pg=5313,4077123 |work=Google News |publisher=Kingman Daily Miner |date=25 July 1995 |accessdate=6 July 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=ArizonaDOC&gt;{{cite web |title=Information for Inmate 049942 WILLIAMS |url=http://www.azcorrections.gov/inmate_datasearch/results.aspx?InmateNumber=049942&amp;LastName=WILLIAMS&amp;FNMI=R&amp;SearchType=SearchInet |work=azcorrections.gov |publisher=Arizona Department of Corrections |accessdate=6 July 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=WVDOC&gt;{{cite web |title=Offender Search |url=http://www.wvdoc.com/wvdoc/OffenderSearch/tabid/117/Default.aspx |work=wvdoc.com |publisher=West Virginia Department of Corrections |accessdate=6 July 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt;

At the time, Marshall County Sheriff Robert Lightner was very critical over the poor police communications during the break. The sheriff's office and local police did not learn about the escape from the state police. They first heard of it over the police scanner. &quot;It was a good twenty minutes before we knew about the escape. If somebody had notified us, there's a good chance that the sheriff's department and the Moundsville police could have been on the scene while all the prisoners were still on the block.&quot; He was also critical of the four-state manhunt that followed, when convicted murderers David Morgan and Ronald T. Williams, along with convicted rapist Harold Gowers Jr., remained at large. &quot;Communications have been very poor. I think they should keep the local law enforcement officers more informed I have no idea what they're doing, what they've found.&quot;&lt;ref name=PPG&gt;{{cite news |first=Jeff |last=Samuels |title=Troopers Criticized In Breakout |url=http://news.google.com/newspapers?nid=1129&amp;dat=19791114&amp;id=GgQOAAAAIBAJ&amp;sjid=-m0DAAAAIBAJ&amp;pg=5579,2323087 |work=Google News |publisher=Pittsburgh Post-Gazette |date=14 November 1979 |accessdate=6 July 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== 1986 riot ===
January 1, 1986 was not only the beginning of a new year, but also the date of one of the most infamous riots in recent history.  The West Virginia Penitentiary was then undergoing many changes and problems.  Security had become extremely loose in all areas. Since it was a &quot;cons&quot; prison, most of the locks on the cells had been picked and inmates roamed the halls freely.  Bad plumbing and insects caused rapid spreading of various diseases.  The prison was now holding more than 2,000 men and crowding became an issue once again.  Another major contribution to the riot's cause was the fact that it was a holiday.  Many of the guards had called off work, which fueled the prisoners to conduct their plan on this specific day.  

At around 5:30 pm, twenty inmates, known as a group called the Avengers, stormed the mess hall as Captain Glassock was on duty. &quot;Within seconds, he (Captain Glassock), five other guards, and a food service worker were tackled and slammed to the floor. Inmates put knives to their throats and handcuffed them with their own handcuffs.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;SoS&quot;&gt;{{cite book | last = Useem | first = Bert | coauthors = Peter Kimball | title = States of Siege: U.S. Prison Riots, 1971-1986 | publisher = Oxford University Press, Incorporated | year = 1991 | location = Cary, NC, USA | pages = 179–181}}&lt;/ref&gt; Even though several hostages were taken throughout the day, none of them were seriously injured. However, over the course of the two-day upheaval, three inmates were slaughtered for an assortment of reasons.  &quot;The inmates who initiated the riot were not prepared to take charge of it. Danny Lehman, the Avengers' president, was quickly agreed upon as best suited for the task of negotiating with authorities and presenting the demands to the media.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;SoS&quot;/&gt; Yet, Lehman was not a part of the twenty men who began the riot. Governor [[Arch A. Moore, Jr.]] was sent to the penitentiary to converse with the inmates.  This meeting set up a new list of rules and standards on which the prison would build.  National and local news covered the story, as well as the inmates meeting with Governor Moore.

===Decommissioning===
Towards the end of its life as a prison, the facility was marked with many instances of riots and escapes.&lt;ref name=&quot;TCGA&quot;/&gt; In the 1960s, the prison reached a peak population of about 2,000 inmates.&lt;ref name=&quot;TCGA&quot;/&gt; With the building of more prisons, that number declined to 600 - 700 inmates by 1995.&lt;ref name=&quot;TCGA&quot;/&gt; The fate of the prison was sealed in a 1986 ruling by the [[Supreme Court of Appeals of West Virginia|West Virginia Supreme Court]] which stated that the 5 x {{convert|7|ft|m|sing=on}} cells were cruel and unusual punishment.&lt;ref name=&quot;LandPurchase&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;TCGA&quot;/&gt; Within nine years, the West Virginia State Penitentiary was closed as a prison.&lt;ref name=&quot;LandPurchase&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;TCGA&quot;/&gt;  Most of the inmates were transferred to the [[Mt. Olive Correctional Complex]] in [[Fayette County, West Virginia]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Official&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;LandPurchase&quot;/&gt;  A smaller correctional facility was built a mile away in Moundsville to serve as a regional jail.&lt;ref name=&quot;Official&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;LandPurchase&quot;/&gt;

===Executions===
[[File:moundsvilleoldsparky.jpg|thumb|left|The original Old Sparky on display]]
From 1899 to 1959, ninety-four men were [[Capital punishment|executed]]. [[Hanging]] was the method of execution until 1949 with eighty-five men meeting that fate. The public could attend hangings until  June 19, 1931. On that date, Frank Hyer was executed for murdering his wife. However, when the trap door beneath him was opened and his full weight was put onto the noose, he was instantly decapitated. Following this event, attendance at hangings was by invitation only.&lt;ref name=&quot;AfterLife&quot;/&gt; The last man to face execution by hanging, Bud Peterson from [[Logan County, West Virginia|Logan County]], lies in the prison's cemetery, as his family refused to claim his body.&lt;ref name=&quot;TCGA&quot;/&gt;  Beginning in 1951, electrocution became the means of execution.  Ironically, the [[Old Sparky|electric chair]], nicknamed &quot;Old Sparky&quot;, used by the prison was originally built by an inmate there, Paul Glenn.&lt;ref name=&quot;TCGA&quot;/&gt; Nine men died in the chair until the state outlawed execution entirely in 1965.&lt;ref name=&quot;TCGA&quot;/&gt; The original chair is on display in the facility and is a part of the official tour.&lt;ref name=&quot;Official&quot;/&gt;

==Training==
After the prison closed its doors as a state institution, the Moundsville Economic Development Council obtained a 25-year lease on the complex. The facility is used for training law enforcement and corrections practitioners with regular mock-riot drills.&lt;ref name=&quot;MockRiot&quot;&gt;{{cite news |title=The Mock Prison Riot |url=http://mockprisonriot.org/MPR/INDEX.ASPX |accessdate=17 March 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; To assist teams in the planning and execution of scenarios the West Virginia High Technology Consortium Foundation commissioned ''The 3D Model of the West Virginia Penitentiary'', an interactive 3D model of the penitentiary, and made the software available to the public prior to the 2009 Mock Prison Riot.&lt;ref name=&quot;3DPenitentiary&quot;&gt;{{cite news |title=The 3D Model of The West Virginia Penitentiary |url=http://mockprisonriot.org/MPR/CUSTOMCONTENT/PUBLICVIEW.ASPX?id=49&amp;moduleid=17 |accessdate=1 April 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; Some previous training programs for law enforcement officials that took place here, such as the ''National Corrections and Law Enforcement Training and Technology Center'', are now discontinued.&lt;ref name=&quot;TrainingClosed&quot;&gt;{{cite news |title=National Corrections and Law Enforcement Training and Technology Center Closing in Moundsville |url=http://www.statejournal.com/story.cfm?func=viewstory&amp;storyid=44227 |accessdate=6 November 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Tourism==
Tours are available for tourists wishing to see the prison.&lt;ref name=&quot;Official&quot;/&gt; The Elizabethtown Festival is held every May to celebrate and remember historic Moundsville. A [[haunted attraction]] called the &quot;Dungeon of Horrors&quot; is also set up for the [[Halloween]] season. Paranormal groups and enthusiast travel guides consider Moundsville Prison to be one of the most [[list of reportedly haunted locations|haunted]] prisons in the United States, with [[Ghost story|ghost stories]] originating as early as the 1930s. Legends include the prison occupying the site of a Native American burial ground. Reports include former guards seeing phantom inmates and a &quot;[[shadow people|shadow man]]&quot; wandering the premises, as well as unexplained noises, voices, and [[cold spot]]s.&lt;ref name=&quot;haunted&quot;&gt;{{cite news | title=The Haunted Prison in Moundsville, West Virginia| url=http://www.haunted-places-to-go.com/haunted-prison-2.html | accessdate=1 January 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==In popular culture==
The prison has appeared in various books, movies, and television shows.  Moundsville native [[Davis Grubb]] set his 1953 novel ''[[The Night of the Hunter (novel)|The Night of the Hunter]]'' in Moundsville with the prison having a notable role. This novel was adapted into a film by [[Charles Laughton]] and [[James Agee]]. The film ''[[The Night of the Hunter (film)|The Night of the Hunter]]'' starred [[Robert Mitchum]] and [[Shelley Winters]].  Davis Grubb also set his novel ''Fools' Parade'' (also known as ''Dynamite Man from Glory Jail'') in Moundsville with the penitentiary serving a notable role here too. The novel was adapted into the 1971 film, ''[[Fools' Parade (film)|Fools' Parade]]'', starring [[James Stewart (actor)|James Stewart]], [[Kurt Russell]], and [[George Kennedy]].

[[MTV]] debuted a show in 2000 named ''[[MTV's Fear|Fear]]''. This show allowed six college students to experience the so-called &quot;haunted prison&quot; for themselves. The first episode had a small number of young adults spending the night in the penitentiary, attempting to document any paranormal activities. The [[Syfy]]'s show ''[[Ghost Hunters]]'' also visited the location in episode 303, which originally aired on October 25, 2006. [[ABC Family]]’s ''[[Scariest Places on Earth]]'' featured the Penitentiary on October 29, 2006. The prison was also featured in 2008 on the [[Travel Channel]]'s ''[[Ghost Adventures]].'' The team of the  [[A&amp;E Network|A&amp;E]] television show ''[[Paranormal State]]'' also visited the prison. Additionally, the prison was investigated by [[Everyday Paranormal]] and featured on their Discovery Channel show ''[[Ghost Lab]]'' on November 20, 2010.

The West Virginia Penitentiary is also the setting for two ''[[Left 4 Dead]]'' video game campaigns titled ''Moundsville Slammer''. The campaign's original incarnation has garnered over 10,000 downloads.&lt;ref name=&quot;MoundsvilleSlammer&quot;&gt;{{cite news |title=Moundsville Slammer |url=http://www.l4dmaps.com/details.php?file=4085 |accessdate=22 October 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; while the 2.0 release has received 8,234 downloads as of this writing.&lt;ref name=&quot;MoundsvilleSlammer2&quot;&gt;{{cite news |title=Moundsville Slammer 2.0 |url=http://www.l4dmaps.com/details.php?file=5224 |accessdate=22 October 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; The campaign data was developed using [[LIDAR]] laser range finding techniques&lt;ref name=&quot;MoundsvilleSlammerLIDAR&quot;&gt;{{cite news |title=How we made it |url=http://games.valador.com/?p=4 |accessdate=17 May 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The West Virginia Penitentiary will serve as the fictitious Statesville Penitentiary in Cync Entertainment's upcoming thriller, &quot;Hidden.&quot; Production on &quot;Hidden,&quot; scheduled for early 2011, will mark the 40-year anniversary of the prison appearing in a motion picture. The facility was last seen on film in &quot;[[Fools' Parade]].&quot;

==See also==
*[[List of Registered Historic Places in West Virginia]]

==External links==
*{{official website|http://www.wvpentours.com Former West Virginia Penitentiary}}
*[http://www.hauntedplacesinamerica.com/2009/12/the-haunting-of-the-west-virginia-state-penitentiary/ West Virginia State Penitentiary Hauntings]
*[http://www.cyncentertainment.com/ Cync Entertainment]
*[http://www.hauntedhamilton.com/54_article_westvirginiapenitentiary_1.html Haunted Hamilton's article on the History and Ghosts of West Virginia Penitentiary]

==References==
&lt;!--See http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Wikipedia:Footnotes for an explanation of how to generate footnotes using the &lt;ref&gt; and &lt;/ref&gt; tags and the tag below --&gt; 
{{reflist|2}}

{{Northern Panhandle of West Virginia}}
{{National Register of Historic Places in West Virginia}}

[[Category:1876 establishments in the United States]]
[[Category:1995 disestablishments]]
[[Category:Defunct prisons in West Virginia]]
[[Category:History of West Virginia]]
[[Category:Landmarks in West Virginia]]
[[Category:Museums in Marshall County, West Virginia]]
[[Category:Prison museums in the United States]]
[[Category:Government buildings on the National Register of Historic Places in West Virginia]]
[[Category:History museums in West Virginia]]
[[Category:Gothic Revival architecture in West Virginia]]
[[Category:Reportedly haunted locations in the United States]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
