<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="20124029" ns="0" title="That Guy with the Glasses"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{fancruft|date=November 2010}}
{{Infobox website
|name            = That Guy with the Glasses
|logo            = 
|logocaption     = 
|screenshot      = 
|collapsible     = 
|collapsetext    = 
|caption         = 
|url             = {{URL|http://www.thatguywiththeglasses.com}}
|slogan          = 
|commercial      = Yes
|type            = [[Review|Reviews]], [[Comedy]], [[Satire]]
|registration    = 
|language        = [[English language|English]]
|content license = 
|owner           = [[Channel Awesome]]
|author          = Michael Michaud&lt;br&gt;Doug Walker&lt;br&gt;Michael Ellis
|launch date     = April 4, 2008
|alexa           = 
|revenue         = 
|current status  = 
|footnotes       = 
}}

'''''That Guy with the Glasses''''' is a website that mostly showcases satirical reviews of [[movies]] and [[video games]]. It primarily stars [[Chicago]] native '''Douglas Darien &quot;Doug&quot; Walker''' (born November 17, 1981)&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.imdb.com/name/nm3766090/ Doug Walker] on [[Internet Movie Database|imdb.com]]&lt;/ref&gt;  as &quot;That Guy with the Glasses&quot;. The founder and administrator of the site is Michael Michaud, CEO of the parent company [[Channel Awesome]]. The site was launched in April 2008 after the original videos were removed from [[YouTube]] following complaints of copyright infringement.

The website is home to several episodic series, starring Douglas Walker [[List of Channel Awesome shows#Team TGWTG|and others]]. The main Walker series are ''5 Second Movies'' (hyper-edited feature films), ''[[The Nostalgia Critic]]'' (reviews of 1980-90s films and television), ''Ask That Guy with the Glasses'' (comedy question and answer show) and ''Bum Reviews'' (plot summaries of current feature films). Other videos and written articles are hosted on the site, including some minor series and sketches starring Walker. Videos are now hosted by [[blip.tv]] after problems with earlier provider [[Revver]].&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.streamingmedia.com/article.asp?id=11141|title=Revver Non-Payments Have Video Makers Crying Foul|accessdate=2009-04-14|first=Troy |last=Dreier |publisher=''StreamingMedia''}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==History==
Doug Walker's first appearance on the web was on the video website [[YouTube]], in which he created satirical video reviews of films and other media entertainment of the past and present. The series drew complaints from major studios like [[20th Century Fox]] and [[Lionsgate]] over alleged copyright infringement.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|url=http://www.guardian.co.uk/film/filmblog/2007/nov/19/thefivesecondmoviesandwhyyoushouldwatchthem|title=The five-second movies and why you should watch them|accessdate=2008-12-09|first=Anna |last=Pickard |publisher=''[[The Guardian]]'' | location=London | date=November 19, 2007}}&lt;/ref&gt; This led to his video content being taken off the website. Walker attempted to re-upload his content by assigning each video a new, separate channel so that if one were deleted, the others would be left intact. However, due to continuing issues with YouTube, Walker decided to leave the website altogether and create the website ''That Guy with the Glasses'' with Internet webmaster Mike Michaud. Michaud had created the sites' parent company, [[Channel Awesome]], after he and two others were laid off from [[Circuit City (1949–2009 company)|Circuit City]] in 2007. Michaud has stated, &quot;If we didn't lose our jobs, [the business] wouldn't have happened anytime soon.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;suntimes&quot;&gt;{{Cite news|first=Brad |last=Spirrison |authorlink= |title=Entertainers don't need TV break to hit it big |url=http://www.suntimes.com/business/spirrison/1653029,CST-FIN-spirr06.article |work=[[Chicago Sun-Times]] |date=July 6, 2009 |accessdate=9 July 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;tribune060709&quot;&gt;{{Cite news|first=Ann |last=Meyer |authorlink= |title=Growing breed of accidental entrepreneur has recession to thank for business creation |url=http://www.chicagotribune.com/business/columnists/chi-mon-minding-accidental-0706-jul06,0,1814450.column |work=[[Chicago Tribune]] |date=July 6, 2009 |accessdate=10 July 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;entrepreneur&quot;&gt;{{Cite journal|last=Daley|first=Jason|date=December 2009|title=The Entrepreneur Economy|journal=[[Entrepreneur (magazine)|Entrepreneur]]|url=http://www.entrepreneur.com/magazine/entrepreneur/2009/december/204086.html}} Please note that Mike Ellis and Mike Michaud have been mislabeled in the article.&lt;/ref&gt;

The site was re-launched in April 2008, and all of Walker's future videos would only be posted there. The site later expanded to feature content from various other contributors. In December 2008, Walker appeared in a commercial for the [[Public Broadcasting Service|PBS]] documentary ''Make 'Em Laugh: The Funny Business of America'', performing a series of brief imitations of famous comedians, from [[Charlie Chaplin]] to [[Stephen Colbert]].&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://thatguywiththeglasses.com/videolinks/thatguywiththeglasses/specials/4766-lost-in-dc-pbs-commercial-documentary |title=Lost in DC: PBS Commercial Documentary |date=February 18, 2009 |accessdate=2009-01-27|work=That Guy with the Glasses}}&lt;/ref&gt; In 2009, Doug and Rob Walker and Brian Heinz produced an iRiff of ''[[The Lion King]]'' for [[RiffTrax]]. In March 2009, the iRiff was chosen as the winner of the website's RiffTrax Presents contest. The performers received $1,000 and, with instruction from [[Michael J. Nelson]], [[Kevin Murphy (actor)|Kevin Murphy]] and [[Bill Corbett]], recorded a commentary for the film ''[[Batman Forever]]''.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.rifftrax.com/iriffs-contest-winner |title=We have a Winner! |accessdate=2009-03-19 |publisher=RiffTrax}}&lt;/ref&gt;

''The Nostalgia Critic'' show averages 100,000 to 300,000 viewers per week, and the site as a whole receives 1 million page views per month.&lt;ref name=&quot;suntimes&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;tribune060709&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|first=Jefferson |last=Graham |authorlink=Jefferson Graham |title=Blip.tv gives videomakers a chance to be a star |url=http://www.usatoday.com/tech/products/2009-02-10-blip-tv-videomakers_N.htm |work=[[USA Today]] |publisher=Gannett Company |date=February 13, 2009 |accessdate=May 12, 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt; This is expected to increase following content-provider Blip.tv's deal with YouTube in July 2009.&lt;ref name=&quot;adage&quot;&gt;{{Cite news|first=Mke |last=Learmonth |authorlink= |title=Blip.tv Brings Programs to YouTube, Ads to 'Channel Awesome' |url=http://adage.com/digital/article?article_id=138164 |work=[[Advertising Age]] |date=July 28, 2009 |accessdate=July 30, 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt; As of July 2009, the site earns more than $10,000 per month in advertising revenue and has received more than $11,000 in online donations, with the company expecting to earn $150,000 by the end of the year. In the third quarter of the 2009 [[Fiscal year]], Walker's shows earned $53,000, including $32,000 from the Nostalgia Critic alone. This revenue was generated by [[run of network]] from Puma and [[Starburst (confectionery)|Starburst]].&lt;ref name=&quot;suntimes&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;tribune060709&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;entrepreneur&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;adage&quot; /&gt; The success of his shows has allowed Walker to make a living performing and to quit his previous job as an illustrator, as well as pay the salary of co-founder/[[Chief operating officer|COO]] Mike Ellis.&lt;ref name=&quot;suntimes&quot; /&gt;

Channel Awesome has plans to build on the success of ''That Guy with the Glasses'' with a network of new websites including ''Bar Fiesta'' (covering Chicago entertainment and nightlife), ''Blistered Thumbs'' (a spin off incorporating the current site's video game content) and ''InkedReality'' (anime, manga, and comic books). Michaud told the [[Chicago Sun-Times]] that he has 300 new show ideas in the works, intends to discover more performers like Walker, and has plans to increase revenue through sponsorships and merchandising.&lt;ref name=&quot;suntimes&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;entrepreneur&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|title=Status of the Site 6/5/09|url=http://thatguywiththeglasses.com/site-news/general-updates/7914-sots60509 |date=June 5, 2009 |work=That Guy With The Glasses |accessdate=July 9, 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt;
==Events==
===First Anniversary: That Guy With The Glasses Team Brawl===
On May 10, 2009, The Nostalgia Critic and the [[Angry Video Game Nerd]] starred in &quot;TGWTG Team Brawl&quot;, which was filmed in Chicago, IL, and celebrated That Guy With the Glasses' one-year anniversary. Various personalities from both the Critic and Nerd's sites participated in a battle between the &quot;Reviewers&quot;, led by the Critic, and &quot;Gamers&quot;, led by the Nerd. &quot;The Final Brawl&quot; was created not only as a major cross-over video, but as a meet up for the contributors. One notable crossover video was a joint review with the Nostalgia Critic and Angry Video Game Nerd who reviewed a documentary about the ''[[Teenage Mutant Ninja Turtles]]''&lt;nowiki&gt;'&lt;/nowiki&gt; &quot;[[Teenage Mutant Ninja Turtles#Concert tour|Coming Out of their Shells]]&quot; concert.

===TGWTG Charity Donation Drive===
On December 5, 2009, Doug and Rob Walker, Noah Antwiler, Joe Vargas, Ed Glaser, Brian Heinz, Bhargav Dronamraju, Bennett White, and Victoria Turner hosted a live charity drive to raise money for the Ronald McDonald house charity. The drive was hosted on [[UStream]], accepting donations through [[PayPal]] and offering incentives on the site such as premium memberships on the site, along with a phone call from Doug and company for any donations over $300. The drive started at 7:00 CST, and had raised over $20,000 by midnight. The drive ran for over 7 hours and ended with a grand total of $26,400. The second donation drive was held on December 5, 2010, ending with a grand total of $50,025.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://thatguywiththeglasses.com/site-news/general-updates/28877-charity-drive-2010-aftermath |title=Charity Drive 2010 Aftermath |work=That Guy with the Glasses |last=Michaud |first=Mike |date=2010-12-06}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Second Anniversary: Kickassia===
A special marking the second anniversary of the site was filmed in the [[Republic of Molossia]], [[Nevada]] on April 9 through April 11, 2010. In addition to the site contributors, the video also features Molossia's President Kevin Baugh and his family playing parodies of themselves. The plot involves the site members invading Molossia, under the leadership of the Nostalgia Critic, renaming the [[micronation]] ''Kickassia'', before infighting caused by the previous ruler leads to the collapse of the new state and restoration of the previous government.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|title=Invasion! |date=12 April 2010|url=http://www.molossia.org/article202.html |work=Khamsin Molossia News |publisher=Molossia.org |accessdate=15 May 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; A DVD of the special was released in October 2010.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://thatguywiththeglasses.com/videolinks/thatguywiththeglasses/specials/28214-kickassia-the-dvd|title=Kickassia the DVD!  |work=That Guy with the Glasses |date=2010-10-17}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Third Anniversary: Suburban Knights===
The third year anniversary special of the site, entitled ''Suburban Knights'', aired in seven parts from June 27th to July 2nd in 2011. The plot involves the reviewers going after &quot;Malachite's Hand&quot;&lt;ref&gt;[http://thatguywiththeglasses.com/videolinks/thatguywiththeglasses/specials/31491-suburban-knights-part-1]&lt;/ref&gt;, a magic gauntlet hidden in suburban [[Illinois]] while dressed as famous characters from fantasy films and video games, including The Nostalgia Critic dressed as [[Link (The Legend of Zelda)|Link]] from ''[[The Legend of Zelda]]'', Spoony as [[Gandalf]], Linkara as [[King Arthur]], Todd in the Shadows as the Dread Pirate Roberts, and the Cinema Snob as [[Indiana Jones]] (when told that Indiana Jones was not a fantasy film he retorted that &quot;if [[Nuke the fridge|surviving a nuclear blast in a fridge]] isn't fantasy, I don't know what is&quot;). While they are on their quest, they are opposed by a force of guardians who protect the gauntlet from the unworthy, and are pursued by Malachite, an ancient sorcerer who seeks the gauntlet to restore his powers and destroy the world of technology forever. Part 5 of the special marked the return of former TGWTG member That Dude in the Suede.&lt;ref&gt;[http://thatguywiththeglasses.com/videolinks/thatguywiththeglasses/specials/31222-the-third-year-anniversary-teaser Third Year Anniversary Teaser]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://thatguywiththeglasses.com/videolinks/thatguywiththeglasses/specials/31413-suburban-knights-full-trailer Suburban Knights Full Trailer]&lt;/ref&gt; Malachite overpowers the reviewers with his magic, and briefly reclaims the gauntlet (which had been refashioned into a Nintendo [[Power Glove]]) but is defeated by Ma-Ti through the power of heart. Ma-Ti is destroyed along with Malachite and the reviewers hold a funeral for Ma-Ti that is nearly identical to that of [[Spock]] in ''[[Star Trek II: The Wrath of Khan]]''.

==Major series==
===5 Second Movies===
Walker is a figure in the &quot;hyperediting&quot; trend.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|url=http://technology.timesonline.co.uk/tol/news/tech_and_web/article3831656.ece|title=Times Online - Microtrends: Hyperediting|first=Tom |last=Whitwell |work=[[The Times|Times Online]] |accessdate=2008-12-09 | location=London | date=May 3, 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt; Currently, ''5 Second Movies'' has had a total of 131 episodes. After the 101st episode, Walker said he will only make them if he thinks of a very funny idea, because he has almost run out of ideas and he does not want to run the series into the ground and grow stale.&lt;ref name=&quot;TGH interview&quot;&gt;[http://thatguywiththeglasses.com/site-news/interview/540-interview-with-handsome-tom-at-tgh Interview between Handsome Tom of The Game Heroes and That Guy with the Glasses]&lt;/ref&gt; The link on the front page was removed during the site's January 2010 renovation. After his videos were taken down from YouTube, Walker made a video that parodied [[Chris Crocker (Internet celebrity)|Chris Crocker]]'s &quot;Leave Britney Alone!&quot; video, entitled &quot;Leave 5 Second Movies Alone!&quot; Today, 5 Second Movies is something of an internet phenomenon with several fan-made videos on YouTube. On TGWTG, Doug finished the series and several other contributors have made their versions and have made spin offs such as '''Comics in 5 Panels''' and '''5 Second Video Games'''.

===Nostalgia Critic===
{{main|The Nostalgia Critic}}
[[File:Nostalgia Critic.jpg|thumb|250px|right|The [[Nostalgia Critic]], Doug Walker.]]
The Nostalgia Critic is the most popular video series created by Walker, in which he plays the titular reviewer. The show is written by Doug and Rob Walker (born May 6, 1979)&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.imdb.com/name/nm3597657/ Rob Walker] on [[Internet Movie Database|imdb.com]]&lt;/ref&gt;  . The series was initially launched on [[YouTube]] before moving to this site. It is the flagship show for Channel Awesome, which has since built on it with additional content, additional websites and the spin-off show ''The Nostalgia Chick''.

The show involves the Nostalgia Critic, often referred to as simply the Critic, reviewing nostalgic media, being mostly negative. This mostly concerns movies and television series from the 1980s to 1990s, but he has made exceptions for movies that came out after 2000. These include ''[[The Room (film)|The Room]]'', ''[[Titanic: The Legend Goes On]]'', ''[[Battlefield Earth (film)|Battlefield Earth]]'', ''[[Dungeons &amp; Dragons (film)|Dungeons &amp; Dragons]]'', ''[[TMNT (film)|TMNT]]'', ''[[Cloverfield]]'' and ''[[Alone in the Dark (2005 film)|Alone In The Dark]]''. Not all reviews are negative, such as those of ''[[Double Dare (1986 game show)|Double Dare]]'', ''[[Sonic the Hedgehog (TV series)|Sonic The Hedgehog]]'' (The SatAM version), [[X-Men (TV series)]], [[DuckTales]], [[Teenage Mutant Ninja Turtles]]'',  ''[[Commando (film)|Commando]]'', ''[[Hook (film)|Hook]]'', ''[[Gargoyles (TV series)|Gargoyles]]'', [[Superman: The Animated Series]], ''[[Follow That Bird]]'' and ''[[Animaniacs]]''.

The series and character gained increased fame from a fictional feud between the Critic and fellow web revewier-comedian [[The Angry Video Game Nerd]] (played by James Rolfe). This began with the Critic launching a satirical attack in an early episode. The feud took place over many episodes in 2008-09.

Walker featured a &quot;Let's Play&quot; video, with him narrating his playing of [[Bart's Nightmare]], which was a significant change in style of his usual reviews. The video has become infamous among fans, which the Nostalgia Critic acknowledged on his subsequent review as being the most unfunny review he has ever done. Other fans defended Walker for the video, but Walker explained that he also didn't like the way it turned out, so the apology made in the following video was just as much him making fun of himself.

===Ask That Guy with the Glasses===
The series ''Ask That Guy with the Glasses'' involves Walker, wearing a blue robe, red ascot and carrying a pipe and drink, answering questions. The narrator reads each question and Walker responds with a comedic answer, sometimes commenting on the person who asked it, although he has a strong dislike of being asked &quot;Can I borrow a cup of sugar?&quot;. &quot;That Guy&quot; is portrayed as an [[upper-class]], [[perverted]] and disturbed person.

===Atop the Fourth Wall===
This series, hosted by Lewis Lovhaug (born August 19, 1987)&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.imdb.com/name/nm3809533/ Lewis Lovhaug] on [[Internet Movie Database|imdb.com]]&lt;/ref&gt;  as &quot;Linkara&quot;, involves him reviewing bad [[comic book]]s. This was initially started a textbased review blog until Lovhaug created a video for an &quot;Ask That Guy with the Glasses&quot; contest, followed by ''Atop the Fourth Wall'' premiering on November 29, 2008. In addition, Lovhaug hosts a video series detailing the history of the ''[[Power Rangers]]'' series. Unlike other review series, Lovhaug has a running storyline on his show, and rarely swears in his videos.

===Bum Reviews with Chester A. Bum===
The series ''Bum Reviews with Chester A. Bum'' features Walker reviewing films in the character Chester Alfred Bum (often referred to as 'the Bum'). The character was created by Walker to review current and new film releases. The character is portrayed as a hyperactive, drug-addicted tramp and cinemagoer who appears with an orange and black woolly hat over a long, dark wig. He was created after the Nostalgia Critic's review of ''[[Cloverfield]]''. Walker loved his impersonation of Hud from the film so much, that he gave Chester it,&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://thatguywiththeglasses.com/site-news/interview/2503-columbia-college-qaa|title= Columbia College, IL Q&amp;A Session|accessdate=2009-01-20|work=That Guy With The Glasses}}&lt;/ref&gt; though the origins of the character came from Doug's review of ''[[Transformers (film)|Transformers]]''. His first review was released in early May 2008 on the movie ''[[Speed Racer (film)|Speed Racer]]''. He typically begins an episode by exclaiming that the movie he's reviewing is &quot;the greatest movie I've ever seen in my life,&quot; and ends the review with his final verdict and a plea for some change in his Styrofoam cup. Walker's actual opinion of the film is presented in the end credits for most of the episodes. However, starting with ''[[Thor (film)|Thor]]'', Walker now makes separate videos next to his Bum reviews and gives his opinion on the film he reviews.

===Nostalgia Chick===
[[File:Nostalgia Chick Dark Nella Saga Trailer.ogv|300px|thumb|thumbtime=17|right|alt=Video in Ogg Theora file format.|Trailer for &quot;The Dark Nella Saga&quot; arc of episodes from the ''Nostalgia Chick'' series.  This trailer is an example of the style of videos with some plot elements accompanying the reviews.]]
The idea of a &quot;Nostalgia Chick&quot; to complement the existing &quot;Nostalgia Critic&quot; (Douglas Walker) was announced on the ''That Guy with the Glasses'' website in &quot;[[List of The Nostalgia Critic episodes#ep30|The Search for the Nostalgia Chick]]&quot; (August 10, 2008). The idea was for a female host to review female-targeted nostalgic films and television.&lt;ref name=&quot;manhour&quot;&gt;{{cite web &lt;!--|url=http://www.themanhour.net/--&gt;|title=The Man Hour|last1=Jenkins|first1=Mike|last2=Bacio|first2=Jose|date=June 19, 2009|work=Man Hour Goes Nostalgic|accessdate=24 December 2009}} ([http://itunes.apple.com/us/podcast/the-man-hour-blog-talk-radio/id297194268 itunes])&lt;/ref&gt; The contest ended in a three-way tie between Lindsay Ellis (who reviewed [[Pocahontas (1995 film)|Disney's ''Pocahontas'']]), Krissy Diggs (who reviewed ''[[Sailor Moon]]''), and Kaylyn Dicksion (who reviewed ''[[The Last Unicorn]]''). The competition was won by Lindsay Ellis (born 1984)&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.imdb.com/name/nm3805989/ Lindsay Ellis] on [[Internet Movie Database|imdb.com]]&lt;/ref&gt; , then using the name &quot;The Dudette&quot;, as announced on the site in &quot;[[List of The Nostalgia Critic episodes#ep36|Nostalgia Chick Winner!]]&quot; (September 15, 2008).&lt;ref name=&quot;manhour&quot; /&gt; During the competition, Ellis actually believed that the winner would be Krissy Diggs.&lt;ref name=&quot;manhour&quot; /&gt; The runners-up were rewarded by adding them to the site as contributors: Krissy Diggs (born February 22, 1988)&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.imdb.com/name/nm3884565/ Krissy Diggs] on [[Internet Movie Database|imdb.com]]&lt;/ref&gt; under the name ''That Chick with the Goggles'' and Kaylyn Dicksion (born January 27, 1986)&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.imdb.com/name/nm3889718/ Kaylyn Dicksion] on [[Internet Movie Database|imdb.com]]&lt;/ref&gt; under the name '' MarzGurl''.

The costume of the Nostalgia Chick initially included a pair of glasses and a bow tie worn as a choker. Ellis wore the glasses to disguise the tired appearance of her eyes in her submission. They were never real and their appearances diminished due to losing them. The glasses were eventually stolen from Ellis' car in Brooklyn and no longer appear in the show.&lt;ref name=&quot;manhour&quot; /&gt; The bow tie was left over from Ellis' appearance in a production of ''[[Cabaret (musical)|Cabaret]]'' while studying at [[New York University]] (she played the [[accordion]]).&lt;ref name=&quot;manhour&quot; /&gt; Early episodes include the closing catchphrase &quot;I remember it because the dudes don't&quot; (based on the Nostalgia Critic's &quot;I remember it so you don't have to&quot;). Ellis eventually dropped this as it seemed anti-feminist; it gave the impression that the subject was being reviewed by a woman because it was not important enough to be reviewed by a man. After requesting submissions for a new catchphrase, Ellis decided against using any catchphrase in her work.&lt;ref name=&quot;manhour&quot; /&gt; Early reviews initially mirrored Walker's linear playthrough, noting memorable or infamous scenes with humorous commentary, but beginning with a video entitled &quot;The Smurfette Principle&quot; noting her status as the Critic's female counterpart, she started a more broad analytical style of review, discussing the movies more as a whole than from beginning to end.&lt;ref&gt;http://thatguywiththeglasses.com/videolinks/thedudette/nostalgia-chick/16616-the-smurfette-principle&lt;/ref&gt;

Some later episodes have been delayed by Ellis' enrollment in a master's degree program at the [[University of Southern California]] and her subsequent traveling between New York and Los Angeles.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://wegotclass.wordpress.com/2009/08/07/big-damn-public-statement/|title=Big damn public statement|last=Ellis|first=Lindsay|date=August 7, 2009|work=Lindsay Goes to Hollywood|accessdate=24 December 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt; At the time of the competition for a Nostalgia Chick, Ellis was unemployed and had not received confirmation of a place at USC. She has stated that, due to the work load, she would not have entered the competition if she had known she would be going to USC.&lt;ref name=&quot;manhour&quot; /&gt;

Ellis comes from [[Tennessee]] and moved to [[New York City|New York]] when she was 18. She now lives in [[Los Angeles, California|Los Angeles]] (during term time) and New York.&lt;ref name=&quot;manhour&quot; /&gt; Despite the subject and tone of the series, Ellis has stated that she likes some of the films, such as ''[[Labyrinth (film)|Labyrinth]]'', although she honestly does not like Disney's ''[[Pocahontas (1995 film)|Pocahontas]]'', the subject of her initial submission.&lt;ref name=&quot;manhour&quot; /&gt;

===The Spoony Experiment===
{{main|The Spoony Experiment}}
The Spoony Experiment (TSE) is series starring by Noah Antwiler (born December 27, 1980)&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.imdb.com/name/nm3872444/ Noah Antwiler] on [[Internet Movie Database|imdb.com]]&lt;/ref&gt; as &quot;The Spoony One&quot; or &quot;Spoony&quot;. The series is hosted on both its own site of the same name, and ''That Guy with the Glasses''. The primary format of the series is humorous reviews of video games and movies. From 2010, it has also incorporated some games journalism at trade shows such as the [[Electronic Entertainment Expo]]. The mascot of the series is &quot;Burton the Robot&quot;, a robot puppet made by Antwiler.

==Awards==
On January 6, 2011, Doug was awarded Entrepreneur of the Year in Las Vegas at the 4th Annual Mashable Awards, Mashable Awards 2010.&lt;ref name=&quot;Mashable&quot;&gt;{{Cite web|title=Mashable|url=http://mashable.com/2011/01/07/mashable-awards-2010-announcing-the-winners/?utm_source=twitterfeed&amp;utm_medium=twitter&amp;utm_campaign=Feed:+Mashable+(Mashable)&amp;utm_content=Twitter |date=January 6, 2009 |work=Mashable |accessdate=January 7, 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Revver issues==
After contracting with Live Universe, [[Revver]]'s earnings from July 2008 onwards were still &quot;pending&quot;, meaning that Revver had delayed payments to unspecified date. On December 9, 2008, Revver sent a message to all its users saying that earnings from June were transferred, and the other earnings would be transferred as soon as possible. However, many people still have yet to receive these payments.

Several of their most popular content providers, including [[ScrewAttack]] and That Guy with the Glasses, have also publicly posted complaints of Revver owing them vast amounts of money on their websites and began moving their content over to [[blip.tv]].&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.thatguywiththeglasses.com/site-news/general-updates/2483-revver-be-dead |title=Revver be Dead |work=That Guy With The Glasses|date=2008-11-14 |accessdate=2008-11-14}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==See also==
*''[[The Nostalgia Critic]]''
*[[List of Channel Awesome shows]]

==References==
{{Reflist|2}}

==External links==
{{Wikiquote|The Nostalgia Critic|lb1=TGWTG}}
*[http://www.thatguywiththeglasses.com/ ThatGuyWithTheGlasses.com]
*{{IMDb title|1635327|The Nostalgia Critic}}
*{{IMDb title|1566050|5 Second Movies}}

{{Channel Awesome}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:That Guy With The Glasses}}
[[Category:American websites]]
[[Category:Review websites]]
[[Category:Web series]]
[[Category:American Internet personalities]]
[[Category:YouTube videos]]
[[Category:Internet memes]]
[[Category:Web humor]]
[[Category:Internet culture]]
[[Category:Internet television channels]]
[[Category:Black comedy]]

[[de:That Guy with the Glasses]]
[[es:That Guy With The Glasses]]
[[nl:That Guy with the Glasses]]
[[sv:That Guy with the Glasses]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
