<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="2013448" ns="0" title="Scrubber"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{about|the pollution control device}}
'''Scrubber''' systems are a diverse group of [[air pollution]] control devices that can be used to remove some [[particulate]]s and/or gases from industrial exhaust streams. Traditionally, the term &quot;scrubber&quot; has referred to pollution control devices that use liquid to wash unwanted pollutants from a gas stream. Recently, the term is also used to describe systems that inject a dry reagent or [[slurry]] into a dirty exhaust stream to &quot;wash out&quot; [[acid gas]]es. Scrubbers are one of the primary devices that control gaseous emissions, especially acid gases. Scrubbers can also be used for heat recovery from hot gases by [[flue gas condensation]].&lt;ref name=gmab_condensation&gt;[http://www.gmab.se/eng_rokgaskondensering.htm On Flue gas Condensation] by Götaverken Miljö AB&lt;/ref&gt;

There are several methods to remove toxic or corrosive compounds from exhaust gas and neutralize it.

== Combustion ==
[[Combustion]] is sometimes the cause for harmful exhaust gas, but, in many cases, combustion may also be used for exhaust gas cleaning if the temperature is high enough and enough oxygen is available&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.crystec.com/ksiburne.htm |title=Burn and wet scrubber for process exhaust gas cleaning}}&lt;/ref&gt;.

=== Wet scrubbing ===
The exhaust gases of combustion may contain substances considered harmful to the environment, and the scrubber may remove or neutralize those substances.
A [[wet scrubber]] is used to clean [[air]], [[flue gas]] or other [[gas]]es of various [[pollutant]]s and [[dust]] particles. Wet scrubbing works via the contact of target compounds or particulate matter with the scrubbing solution. Solutions  may simply be [[water]] (for dust) or solutions of reagents that specifically target certain compounds.

Process exhaust gas can also contain water soluble toxic and/or corrosive gases like [[hydrogen chloride]] HCl or [[ammonia]] NH&lt;sub&gt;3&lt;/sub&gt;. These can be removed very well by a wet scrubber&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.crystec.com/ksiwete.htm |title=Wet scrubber for process exhaust gas cleaning}}&lt;/ref&gt;.

Removal efficiency of pollutants is improved by increasing residence time in the scrubber or by the increase of surface area of the scrubber solution by the use of a [[spray nozzle]], [[Packed bed|packed towers]] or an [[aspirator]]. [[Wet scrubber]]s may increase the proportion of water in the gas, resulting in a visible stack plume, if the gas is sent to a stack.

===Dry scrubbing===&lt;!-- This section is linked from [[Air pollution]] --&gt;
A [[dry scrubber|dry]] or [[dry scrubber|semi-dry scrubbing system]], unlike the [[wet scrubber]], does not saturate the flue gas stream that is being treated with moisture. In some cases no moisture is added; while in other only the amount of moisture that can be evaporated in the flue gas without condensing is added. Therefore, dry scrubbers do generally not have a stack steam plume or [[wastewater]] handling/disposal requirements. Dry scrubbing systems are used to remove [[acid gas]]es (such as [[Sulfur dioxide|SO&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;]] and [[Hydrogen chloride|HCl]]) primarily from [[combustion]] sources. 

There are a number of dry type scrubbing system designs. However, all consist of two main sections or devices:  a device to introduce the [[acid gas]] [[sorbent]] material into the gas stream and a particulate matter control device to remove reaction products, excess sorbent material as well as any particulate matter already in the [[flue gas]]. 

Dry scrubbing systems can be categorized as [[dry sorbent injection|dry sorbent injectors (DSIs)]] or as [[spray dryer|spray dryer absorbers (SDAs)]]. Spray dryer absorbers are also called semi-dry scrubbers or spray dryers.

Dry scrubbing systems are often used for the removal of odorous and corrosive gases from [[industrial wastewater treatment|wastewater treatment plant]] operations.  The medium used is typically an [[activated alumina]] compound impregnated with materials to handle specific gases such as [[hydrogen sulfide]].  Media used can be mixed together to offer a wide range of removal for other odorous compounds such as [[methyl mercaptan]]s, [[aldehyde]]s, [[volatile organic compound]]s, [[dimethyl sulfide]], and [[dimethyl disulfide]].

'''Dry sorbent injection''' involves the addition of an [[alkaline]] material (usually [[hydrated lime]] or [[soda ash]]) into the gas stream to react with the [[acid gas]]es. The sorbent can be injected directly into several different locations:  the combustion process, the [[flue gas]] duct (ahead of the particulate control device), or an open reaction chamber (if one exists). The acid gases react with the alkaline [[sorbent]]s to form solid [[salt]]s which are removed in the particulate control device. These simple systems can achieve only limited acid gas (SO&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt; and HCl) removal efficiencies. Higher collection efficiencies can be achieved by increasing the flue gas [[humidity]] (i.e., cooling using water spray). These devices have been used on [[medical waste]] incinerators and a few [[municipal waste]] combustors.

In '''spray dryer absorbers''', the [[flue gas]]es are introduced into an absorbing tower (dryer) where the gases are contacted with a finely atomized alkaline [[slurry]]. Acid gases are absorbed by the slurry mixture and react to form solid [[salt]]s which are removed by the particulate control device. The heat of the flue gas is used to evaporate all the water droplets, leaving a non-saturated flue gas to exit the [[absorption (chemistry)|absorber]] tower. Spray dryers are capable of achieving high (80+%) acid gas removal efficiencies. These devices have been used on industrial and utility [[boiler]]s and [[municipal waste]] [[incinerator]]s.

=== Absorber ===
Many chemicals can be removed from exhaust gas also by using absorber material. The flue gas is passed through a cartridge, filled with one or several absorber materials, adapted to the chemical properties of the components that should be removed from the exhaust gas&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.crystec.com/ksicate.htm |title=Absorption scrubber for exhaust gas cleaning}}&lt;/ref&gt;. This type of scrubber is sometimes also called dry scrubber. The absorber material has to be replaced after its surface is saturated.

=== Mercury removal ===
[[mercury (element)|Mercury]] is a highly toxic element commonly found in [[coal]] and municipal waste. [[Wet scrubber]]s are only effective for removal of soluble mercury species, such as oxidized mercury, Hg&lt;sup&gt;2+&lt;/sup&gt;.  Mercury vapor in its elemental form, Hg&lt;sup&gt;0&lt;/sup&gt;, is insoluble in the scrubber slurry and not removed. Therefore, additional process of Hg&lt;sup&gt;0&lt;/sup&gt; conversion is required to complete mercury capture. Usually addition of the halogens to the flue gas are used for this purpose. The type of coal burned as well as the presence of a [[selective catalytic reduction]] unit both affect the ratio of elemental to oxidized mercury in the flue gas and thus the degree to which the mercury is removed.

== Heat recovery ==
Wet scrubbers can be used for heat recovery from hot gases by [[flue gas condensation]]&lt;ref name=&quot;gmab_condensation&quot;/&gt;. In this mode, termed a condensing scrubber, water from the scrubber drain is circulated through a cooler to the nozzles at the top of the scrubber. The hot gas enters the scrubber at the bottom. If the gas temperature is above the water [[dew point]], it is initially cooled by [[evaporation]] of water drops. Further cooling cause [[water vapor]]s to [[condensation|condense]], adding to the amount of circulating water.

The condensation of water release significant amounts of low temperature heat (more than {{convert|2|GJ}} per ton of water), that can be recovered by the cooler for e.g. [[district heating]] purposes.

Excess condensed water must continuously be removed from the circulating water.

The gas leaves the scrubber at its [[dew point]], so even though significant amounts of water may have been removed from the cooled gas, it is likely to leave a visible stack plume of water vapor.

== Scrubber waste products ==
One side effect of scrubbing is that the process only moves the unwanted substance from the exhaust gases into a liquid solution, solid paste or powder form. This must be disposed of safely, if it can not be reused.

For example, mercury removal results in a waste product that either needs further processing to extract the raw mercury, or must be buried in a special hazardous wastes [[landfill]] that prevents the mercury from seeping out into the environment.

As an example of reuse, limestone-based scrubbers in coal fired [[power plants]] can produce a synthetic [[gypsum]] of sufficient quality that can be used to manufacture [[drywall]] and other industrial products.&lt;ref&gt;[http://antoine.frostburg.edu/chem/senese/101/inorganic/faq/waste-so2-to-wallboard.shtml How Sulfuric (SO&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;) waste is chemically removed from emissions] at General Chemistry Online&lt;/ref&gt;

== Bacteria spread ==
Poorly maintained scrubbers have the potential to spread disease-causing bacteria.  The problem is a result of inadequate cleaning.  For example, the cause of a 2005 outbreak of [[Legionnaires' disease]] in [[Norway]] was just a few infected scrubbers.  The outbreak caused 10 deaths and more than 50 cases of infection.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.eurosurveillance.org/ViewArticle.aspx?PublicationType=W&amp;Volume=10&amp;Issue=23&amp;OrderNumber=1 Update: Outbreak of legionnaires’ disease in Norway traced to air scrubber]&lt;/ref&gt;

== See also ==
* [[Wet scrubber]]
** [[Baffle spray scrubber]]
** [[Ejector venturi scrubber]]
** [[Liquid-to-gas ratio]]
** [[Mechanically aided scrubber]]
** [[Spray tower]]
** [[Spray nozzle]]
** [[Stripping (chemistry)]]
** [[Venturi scrubber]]
** [[Air Turbo-Impactor]]
* [[Flue gas desulfurization]]
* [[Flue gas condensation]]
* [[Oil desulfurization]]
* [[Electrostatic precipitator]]
* [[BS4994]] Chemical Process Plant Equipments in FRP

==References==
{{reflist}}

[[Category:Scrubbers| ]]
[[Category:Pollution control technologies]]
[[Category:Air pollution control systems]]
[[Category:Acid gas control]]
[[Category:Industrial processes]]

[[da:Røggasrensning]]
[[de:Gaswäscher]]
[[fr:Absorbeur-neutralisateur]]
[[it:Scrubber]]
[[nl:Gaswasser]]
[[no:Skrubber]]
[[ru:Скруббер]]
[[sv:Skrubber]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
