<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="201993" ns="0" title="Amr Moussa"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Infobox Officeholder
|name           = Amr Moussa&lt;br&gt;&lt;small&gt;عمرو موسى‎&lt;/small&gt;
|image          = Amr Moussa at the 37th G8 Summit in Deauville 054.jpg
|office         = Secretary-General of the [[Arab League]]
|deputy         = 
|term_start     = 1 June 2001
|term_end       = 1 June 2011
|predecessor    = [[Ahmed Asmat Abdel-Meguid]]
|successor      = [[Nabil el-Araby]] 
|office2        = [[Minister of Foreign Affairs (Egypt)|Minister of Foreign Affairs]]
|primeminister2 = [[Atef Sedki]]&lt;br&gt;[[Kamal Ganzouri]]&lt;br&gt;[[Atef Ebeid]]
|predecessor2   = [[Ahmed Asmat Abdel-Meguid]]
|successor2     = [[Ahmad Maher (diplomat)|Ahmed Maher]]
|term_start2    = 20 May 1991
|term_end2      = 15 May 2001
|office3        = [[List of current Permanent Representatives to the United Nations|Egyptian Ambassaor to the United Nations]]
|president3     = [[Hosni Mubarak]]
|term_start3    = 1 January 1990
|term_end3      = 20 May 1991
|predecessor3   = [[Ahmed Aboul Gheit]]
|successor3     = [[Nabil el-Araby]]
|birth_date     = {{birth date and age|1936|10|3|df=y}} 
|birth_place    = [[Cairo]], [[Kingdom of Egypt|Egypt]]
|death_date     = 
|death_place    = 
|party          = [[Independent (politician)|Independent]]
|alma_mater     = [[Cairo University]]
|profession     = [[Diplomat]]
|religion       = [[Sunni Islam]]
}}
'''Amr Mohammed Moussa''' ({{lang-ar|عمرو محمد موسى}}, {{IPA-arz|ˈʕɑmɾe mæˈħæmːæd ˈmuːsæ|IPA}}; born 3 October 1936) is an [[Egypt]]ian [[politician]] and [[diplomat]] who was the Secretary-General of the [[Arab League]], a 22-member forum representing [[Arab World|Arab states]], from 1 June 2001 until 1 June 2011. He is a candidate in [[Egyptian presidential election, 2011|the 2011 Egyptian presidential election]].

==Early life==
He was born on 3 October 1936 in [[Cairo]], [[Egypt]]. He finished his education after earning a degree in [[law]] from [[Cairo University]] in 1957.

==Diplomatic career==
Moussa then began his [[Diplomacy|diplomatic career]]. Between 1958 and 1972 he worked in several Egyptian missions including Egypt’s Embassy in [[Switzerland]] and the Egyptian mission to the [[United Nations]]. From 1974 to 1977 he was an advisor to the Minister for Foreign Affairs of Egypt.  From 1977 to 1981 and again from 1983 to 1990, he was the Director of the Department of International Organizations at the Ministry of Foreign Affairs of Egypt.  From 1981 to 1983, Moussa was the Deputy Permanent Representative to the [[United Nations]] in New York, then from 1983 to 1986 Ambassador to [[India]]. In 1990, he was promoted Permanent Representative of Egypt to the [[United Nations]].

====Appointment as foreign minister====
He was named [[Minister of Foreign Affairs (Egypt)|Minister of Foreign Affairs]] by [[Prime Minister of Egypt|Prime Minister]] [[Atef Sedki]] on 20 May 1991. He was minister until 15 May 2001 when he was elected as Secretary General of [[Arab League]].

====Secretary-General of the Arab League====
On 15 May 2001, Moussa was selected as Secretary General of the [[League of Arab States]] and took office on 1 June 2001. Critics of the Egyptian president [[Hosni Mubarak]] allege that Moussa's appointment to the Office of Secretary-General of the Arab League was motivated by Mubarak's desire to remove him from the public spotlight.

On 2003,  he became a member of the United Nations High Level Panel on Threats, Challenges and Change for International Peace and Security

On 2009, he signed a memorandum of understanding with the [[Holy See]] and met with Pope [[Benedict XVI]] in order to strengthen joint projects and to promote peace and dialogue on a cultural and political level.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.catholicnews.com/data/stories/cns/0901836.htm |title=Vatican, Arab League sign new agreement to promote peace, dialogue |publisher=Catholic News |date=2009-04-23 |first=Cindy |last=Wooden |accessdate=2011-02-02}}&lt;/ref&gt;

On 13 June 2010, Moussa visited [[Gaza]] in a move to pressure Israel to lift its economic blockade over Hamas-ruled Gaza.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|author=Tim Franks |url=http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/world/middle_east/10303301.stm |title=Arab League chief Amr Moussa in first visit to Gaza |publisher=BBC News |date=2010-06-13 |accessdate=2011-02-02}}&lt;/ref&gt; The visit by Moussa was the first by an official of the Arab League since the election of Hamas in 2007. Immediately after the [[Gaza flotilla raid]], Moussa said the Arab League would go to the [[UN Security Council]] to demand the blockade be lifted. On 15 May 2011, [[Nabil el-Araby]] elected as Secretary General of Arab League and succeed Moussa in June 1, 2011.

[[Image:Dmitry Medvedev in Egypt 23 June 2009-16.jpg|thumb|right|Moussa with [[President of Russia]] [[Dmitry Medvedev]] in Cairo on 23 June 2009]]

===Foreign relations===
Moussa has been heavily involved with Egypt's foreign policy since 1958.  He has been Egypt's Ambassador to the United Nations, India, and Switzerland for a total of 21 years. Moussa was among the many Arab and international diplomats who tried to resolve the [[Lebanon War]] (1975-1990), and for this he is criticized for taking a strong anti-Christian position. After serving as Egypt's Foreign Minister from 1991 to 2001, he served as the Secretary General of the Arab League.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|last=United|first=Nations|title=Biography of Amre Mahmoud Moussa|url=http://www.un.org/News/dh/hlpanel/amre-moussa-bio.pdf|newspaper=United Nations|date=March 4, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; Moussa has been an extremely popular political figure in Egypt due to his criticism of Israeli policies towards Gaza and the West Bank.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title=Profile: Amre Moussa|url=http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/middle_east/1766776.stm|newspaper=British Broadcasting Company|date=January 23, 2002}}&lt;/ref&gt; At the Forum for New Diplomacy in February 2010, Moussa gave a speech in which he criticized the U.S. government's double standard supporting Israel's nuclear weapons policy but not allowing Iran to pursue nuclear energy.  He also criticized Western countries, including the U.S. for not recognizing the results of the 2006 Palestinian elections that brought Hamas into power.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|last=Seale|first=Patrick|title=An Arab Voice|url=http://www.nytimes.com/2010/02/06/opinion/06iht-edseale.html?pagewanted=1&amp;_r=1&amp;ref=amrmoussa|newspaper=The New York Times|date=February 5, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;  Like El-Baradei and the Muslim Brotherhood, he supports opening the Gaza Strip/Egypt border (Seale, 2010).  His criticisms have made Moussa extremely popular.  Many political commentators said the Mubarak sent him to work for the Arab League in 2001 so as not to compete as a presidential candidate in the 2005 Presidential elections because of his popularity.  Amr Moussa announced that he would be running as a presidential candidate on March 1, 2011.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|last=Badawi|first=Rania|title=Moussa To Run For President, Will Announce Election Platform Soon|url=http://www.almasryalyoum.com/en/node/335453|newspaper=Al-Masry Al-Youm|date=March 1, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Possible presidential candidacies ==
====2005 presidential election====
{{Main|Egyptian presidential election, 2005}}
In 2004 an online community gathered tens of thousands of signatures petitioning for Moussa to run in the 2005 elections, but there was no response. In a ''Doha Debate'' Forum televised by the BBC in 2006,&lt;ref&gt;http://www.thedohadebates.com/output/page13.asp&lt;/ref&gt; Moussa was asked about his Presidential hopes. Moussa merely replied that he hoped to continue the recent run of successes that have occurred under his leadership at the Arab League until the end of his term.

====2011 presidential election====
{{Main|Egyptian presidential election, 2011}}
When asked about rumours that he might run for Presidency in 2011, Moussa did not deny his intention to run for office or rule it out, leaving the door open to speculations. He argued that &quot;It's the right of every citizen that has the capacity and efficiency to aspire to any political office that would allow him to contribute to the service of his nation&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;Amr Moussa opened the way for speculation about his candidacy for the presidency of Egypt&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://arabic.cnn.com/2009/middle_east/10/20/Amro.Mousa/ |title=Amr Moussa opened the way for speculation about his candidacy for the presidency of Egypt |publisher=CNN Arabic |date=2009-10-20 |accessdate=2011-02-02}}&lt;/ref&gt; He further stated to the press that the qualities required to be the President of [[Egypt]] also apply to [[Gamal Mubarak]], son of the [[Egypt]]ian President [[Hosni Mubarak]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Amr Moussa did not rule out running for the presidency of Egypt&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://ara.reuters.com/article/topNews/idARACAE59I1E020091020 |title=Amr Moussa did not rule out running for the presidency of Egypt |publisher=Reuters Arabia |date=2009-10-20 |accessdate=2011-02-02}}&lt;/ref&gt; He also expressed appreciation &quot;for the confidence expressed by many people when they talk about his candidacy for the presidency and that the message reached him.&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;Amr Mousa to (Al-Shorouk): Every qualified citizen has the right to aspire to serve the country and become the president&quot;&gt;[http://www.shorouknews.com/ContentData.aspx?id=143426 Amr Mousa to (Al-Shorouk): Every qualified citizen has the right to aspire to serve the country and become the president].&lt;/ref&gt;

Moussa held talks with [[Mohamed Elbaradei]] after his return to Egypt. Many{{who|date=January 2011}} speculate that this meeting was held to discuss Constitutional reforms that will allow transparency in the election process as well as lifting restrictions on independent candidates. On January, 26, 2011 at the Annual [[Horasis]] meeting in [[Zurich]], Moussa shared strong views on the need for economic and political reforms in Egypt, and made it clear that he was considering a run. &lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.horasis.org/Horasis%20Annual%20Meeting%202011%20-%20Report%20.pdf|retrieve date=30th November, 2011|author=Frank-Jurgen Richter}}&lt;/ref&gt;
On February 1, 2011, following the announcement by President Hosni Mubarak that he would not stand in the upcoming Presidential elections, Moussa told CNN that he would seriously think about standing himself as a candidate in the next few weeks.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last=Weaver |first=Matthew |url=http://www.guardian.co.uk/news/blog/2011/feb/01/egypt-protests-live-updates |title=Egypt protests |publisher=Guardian |date=2011-02-01 |accessdate=2011-02-02}}&lt;/ref&gt; On the February 8 broadcast of [[Al Jazeera]] English's Empire, well-connected American journalist [[Seymour Hersh]] stated that Moussa was considered America's favored &quot;Plan B&quot; should Mubarak resign, &quot;whether he knows it or not.&quot; &lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last=Hersh |first=Seymour |url=http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=gDp8TnY3IsA |title=Empire |publisher=Al Jazeera |date=2011-02-08 |accessdate=2011-02-08}}&lt;/ref&gt;  On February 11, 2011 Al Jazeera English Online read from a Reuters report that stated Moussa was resigning from his position with the Arab League; on the day that President Mubarak resigned from the Egyptian presidency this furthered rumours he might make a strong bid for president when elections are announced in Egypt. On February 12, 2011 the Egyptian daily newspaper ''Alwafd'' reported that a group of Egyptian youth met with Moussa to discuss a possible nomination for the Egyptian presidential election. Moussa reportedly agreed to the nomination, but stated that  he would await the currently proposed constitutional reforms in Egypt.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.alwafd.org/index.php?option=com_content&amp;view=article&amp;id=15975:ثوار-يلتقون-موسى-وزويل-لبحث-مرشح-الرئاسة&amp;catid=98:محلية&amp;Itemid=92&lt;/ref&gt;

A poll conducted during the 2011 protests asking &quot;who do you think should be the next President of Egypt?&quot; showed Moussa in the lead, with 26% of respondents naming him.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.scribd.com/Egypt-Poll/d/48662607 &quot;Phone Survey of Cairo and Alexandria&quot;, Scribd Middle East Polls]&lt;/ref&gt;


[[File:Amre Moussa at the 2011 Horasis Annual Meeting.jpg|thumb|Amr Moussa a the 2011 Annual Horasis Meeting, &quot;The Arab world must reform&quot;]]

== Criticisms ==
[[Image:Amr Moussa.jpg|thumb|left|Moussa speaks to journalists at the [[World Economic Forum]], [[Davos]], [[Switzerland]], 2007]]
Although credited with shaking up the Arab League’s bureaucracy,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|first=Michael |last=Moran |url=http://www.cfr.org/publication/9061/arab_league_and_iraq.html |title=The Arab League and Iraq |publisher=Council on Foreign Relations |date=2005-10-20 |accessdate=2011-02-02}}&lt;/ref&gt; Moussa has been criticized by former and current staff members of the Arab League for his management of the organization. In his book, ''The League of the Arab States: what’s left of it'', former Arab League and Syrian diplomat [[Kawkab Najib El-Rayess]] accused Moussa of favoritism and promoting his loyalists into the high ranks of the Arab League at the expense of the more-qualified diplomats.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.almasryalyoum.com/en/news/egypt’s-opposition-divided-over-counter-attack-strategy Egypt’s opposition divided over counter-attack strategy]&lt;/ref&gt;

==Awards==
*2001 [[Grand Cordon of the Nile]], Egypt
*2001 [[The Two Niles]], First Class, Sudan

{{clear}}

==References==
{{reflist|2}}

==External links==
{{Commons category|Amr Moussa}}
*[http://www.arableagueonline.org/las/arabic/categoryList.jsp?level_id=941 Secretary-General] at [[League of Arab States]] (Arabic)
*{{C-SPAN|amrmoussa}}
*{{Charlie Rose view|845}}
*{{IMDb|1969640}}
*{{Aljazeeratopic|person/amr-moussa}}
*{{NYTtopic|people/m/amr_moussa}}
* [http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/middle_east/1766776.stm Profile: Amr Moussa] at ''[[BBC News]]'', 23 January 2002
*{{Worldcat id|np-moussa,%20amre}}
*{{Nndb|591/000045456}}
;Articles
*[http://www.medea.be/index.html?page=2&amp;lang=fr&amp;doc=136 Profile] at ''Medea'', April 2010 (French)
*[http://www.washingtonpost.com/wp-dyn/content/article/2011/02/14/AR2011021406948.html Arab League leader says nations shouldn't fear revolts], Leila Fadel, ''[[The Washington Post]]'', February 15, 2011
*[http://www.latimes.com/news/nationworld/world/la-fg-egypt-moussa-20110217,0,6359426.story Diplomat seen as a solid leader, but too old to be Egypt's president], Timothy M. Phelps, ''[[Los Angeles Times]]'', February 17, 2011
*[http://english.ahram.org.eg/NewsContent/1/64/7332/Egypt/Politics-/Amr-Moussa-launches-presidential-campaign.aspx Amr Moussa launches presidential campaign], Dina Ezzat, ''[[Ahram Online]]'', 9 March 2011
*[http://www.almasryalyoum.com/en/node/346447 Moussa sharply criticized during first campaign trail speech], staff, ''[[Al-Masry Al-Youm]]'', 9 March 2011
*[http://www.guardian.co.uk/world/2011/mar/21/amr-moussa-secretary-general-arab-league?intcmp=239 Amr Moussa, secretary general of the Arab League], Jason Burke, ''[[The Guardian]]'', 21 March 2011, profile

{{s-start}}
{{s-dip}}
{{s-bef|before=[[Ahmed Aboul Gheit]]}}
{{s-ttl|title=[[List of current Permanent Representatives to the United Nations|Egyptian Ambassaor to the United Nations]]|years=1990–1991}}
{{s-aft|rows=2|after=[[Nabil el-Araby]]}}
|-
{{s-bef|before=[[Ahmed Asmat Abdel-Meguid]]}}
{{s-ttl|title=Secretary-General of the [[Arab League]]|years=2001–2011}}
|-
{{s-off}}
{{s-bef|before=[[Ahmed Asmat Abdel-Meguid]]}}
{{s-ttl|title=[[Minister of Foreign Affairs (Egypt)|Minister of Foreign Affairs]]|years=1991–2001}}
{{s-aft|after=[[Ahmad Maher (diplomat)|Ahmed Maher]]}}
{{s-end}}

{{Secretaries-General of the Arab League}}

{{Persondata &lt;!-- Metadata: see [[Wikipedia:Persondata]]. --&gt;
| NAME              = Moussa, Amre
| ALTERNATIVE NAMES =
| SHORT DESCRIPTION =
| DATE OF BIRTH     = 1936-10-03
| PLACE OF BIRTH    = [[Cairo]], [[Egypt]]
| DATE OF DEATH     =
| PLACE OF DEATH    =
}}
{{DEFAULTSORT:Moussa, Amre}}

[[Category:1936 births]]
[[Category:Cairo University alumni]]
[[Category:Egyptian diplomats]]
[[Category:Foreign Ministers of Egypt]]
[[Category:Living people]]
[[Category:People of the 2011 Egyptian revolution]]
[[Category:Permanent Representatives of Egypt to the United Nations]]
[[Category:Secretaries General of the Arab League]]

[[ar:عمرو موسى]]
[[az:Əmr Musa]]
[[bg:Амр Муса]]
[[ca:Amr Moussa]]
[[cs:Amr Músa]]
[[de:Amr Musa]]
[[es:Amr Musa]]
[[fa:عمرو موسی]]
[[fr:Amr Moussa]]
[[id:Amr Moussa]]
[[it:ʿAmr Mūsā]]
[[he:עמר מוסא]]
[[ka:ამრ მუსა]]
[[arz:عمرو موسى]]
[[nl:Amr Moussa]]
[[ja:アムル・ムーサ]]
[[no:Amre Moussa]]
[[pl:Amr Musa]]
[[pt:Amr Moussa]]
[[ru:Муса, Амр]]
[[fi:Amr Musa]]
[[sv:Amr Musa]]
[[tr:Amr Musa]]
[[uk:Амр Муса]]
[[zh:阿穆尔·穆萨]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
