<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="2032075" ns="0" title="The Catherine Tate Show"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Infobox television |
 | show_name           = The Catherine Tate Show 
 | image               = [[Image:The Catherine Tate Show.jpg|230px]]
 | caption             = ''The Catherine Tate Show'' logo
 | format              = [[Sketch comedy]] / [[Sitcom]]
 | camera_setup        = [[Multiple-camera setup|Multiple-camera]]
 | runtime             = 30 minutes, 50 minutes (Christmas special)
 | creator             = [[Catherine Tate]]&lt;br&gt;[[Derren Litten]]
 | executive_producer  = [[Geoffrey Perkins]]
 | starring            = [[Catherine Tate]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Niky Wardley]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Mathew Horne]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Angela McHale]]
 | country             = United Kingdom
 | network             = [[BBC Two]], [[BBC One]]
 | picture_format      = [[576i]] ([[16:9]] [[SDTV]])
 | num_series          = 3
 | num_specials        = 1
 | first_aired         = '''Original series''':&lt;br&gt;16 February 2004
 | last_aired          = &lt;br&gt;25 December 2007&lt;br&gt;'''[[Nan's Christmas Carol]]''':&lt;br&gt; 25 December 2009
 | num_episodes        = 22 &lt;small&gt;(as of 25 December 2009)&lt;/small&gt;
 | related             = Nan's Christmas Carol &lt;small&gt;(2009)&lt;/small&gt; 
 | status              = Ended
 | website              =http://www.bbc.co.uk/comedy/guide/articles/c/catherinetateshow_999040216.shtml
 |}}
'''''The Catherine Tate Show''''' is a British television [[sketch comedy]] written by [[Catherine Tate]] and [[Aschlin Ditta]]. Tate also stars in all but one of the show's sketches, which feature a wide range of [[The Catherine Tate Show characters|characters]]. ''The Catherine Tate Show'' airs on [[BBC Two]] and is shown worldwide through the [[BBC]]. Collectively, the show has been nominated for six [[BAFTA TV Awards|BAFTA Awards]], two [[British Comedy Awards]] and an [[Emmy Award]], and it has won two [[Royal Television Society|Royal Television Society Award]]s, two British Comedy Awards and a [[National Television Awards|National Television Award]] since its debut in 2004.

==History==
The first series of the show, which consisted of six episodes, aired from 16 February to 22 March 2004. A [[DVD]] of this series was released in August 2005. 

A second series aired from 21 July to 25 August 2005, and a 40-minute Christmas special was aired on 20 December 2005. For this series a new theme tune was introduced. A DVD of series two was released in October 2006. 

The third series aired from 14 October to 25 November 2006. There had been speculation that this would be the final series. However, Tate explained in an interview on ''[[This Morning (TV series)|This Morning]]'' that she had never said this and would like to at least do specials in the future.

Tate filmed a Christmas special which aired on 25 December 2007, with viewing figures of 6.4 million.&lt;ref name=&quot;backintime&quot;&gt;&quot;[http://www.mailonsunday.co.uk/pages/live/articles/showbiz/showbiznews.html?in_article_id=466688&amp;in_page_id=1773 Catherine Tate takes foul-mouthed Nan back in time]&quot;. ''[[The Mail on Sunday]]''. Retrieved 9 July 2007.&lt;/ref&gt; Tate has announced that there will be no more series after the special.&lt;ref name=&quot;late&quot;&gt;&quot;[http://www.mirror.co.uk/showbiz/tv/tvland/2007/11/26/cath-s-late-tate-show-89520-20162890/ Cath's late Tate show]&quot;. ''[[Daily Mirror]]''. Retrieved 26 November 2007.&lt;/ref&gt; However, a Christmas special was shown on 25 December 2009.

==Main characters==
{{main|The Catherine Tate Show characters}}

This is only a list and small description of the most popular or well-known characters.

*'''[[Joannie Taylor|Joannie 'Nan' Taylor]]''' is a [[Profanity|foul-mouthed]] grandmother who constantly swears at and criticises other people, especially when they are not present, including her grandson. She often uses the phrases &quot;What a fuckin' liberty!&quot; and &quot;What a load of 'orse shit!&quot;.
*'''[[The Catherine Tate Show characters#Paul and Sam|Paul and Sam]]''' are a Thames Estuary/Essex couple played by Tate and Former Eastenders actor [[Lee_Ross_(actor)|Lee Ross]],Sam comes home from work with 'amazing' tales of her mundane life at work and Paul hangs on every word getting as excited as she does over the trivial things that they blow out of all proportion.Their catchphrases included 'What am I like,What are you like' and 'I dunno'. In the third series Sam and Paul only appeared in the last episode due to Lee Ross's work on Eastenders as Owen.
*'''[[Lauren Cooper]]''' is an [[argumentative]] and [[Laziness|lazy]] teenage girl who gets out of awkward situations by repeating her catchphrase, &quot;Am I bovered?&quot; or &quot;Look at my face, is my face bovvered? Face? Bovvered?&quot; In 2006, this catchphrase was named [[Word of the Year]]&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
|url=http://www.guardian.co.uk/news/blog/2006/oct/12/bovveredwinsw1
|title='Bovvered' wins Word of the Year award |date = 12 October 2006 |publisher=[[The Guardian]]
|accessdate=2009-03-12 |last=Philips |first=Sarah }}&lt;/ref&gt; and entered the [[Oxford English Dictionary]]. A spokesperson for the OED commented {{cquote|Am I bovvered?' and its follow-up, 'Does my face looked bovvered?' had already come to be seen as the perfect expression of a generation of teenagers and their speaking style.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;&quot;[http://blogs.guardian.co.uk/news/archives/2006/10/12/bovvered_wins_word_of_the_year_award.html 'Bovvered' wins Word of the Year award]&quot;. ''[[The Guardian]]''. Retrieved 1 October 2007&lt;/ref&gt;}}
*'''[[The Catherine Tate Show characters#Kate and Ellen|Kate and Ellen]]''' are two office workers who sit next to each other. While Ellen (played by [[Ella Kenion]]) is usually keen to get on with her work, she is frequently disturbed by Kate (Tate), who asks her to guess answers to questions and when she answers wrongly she gets mad - however it is common that she will then get it right and Tate will just say &quot;...Yeah&quot; and get back to her work.
*'''[[The Catherine Tate Show characters#The Aga Saga Woman|The Aga Saga Woman]]''' is an [[upper middle class]] English woman who goes into a state of shock in various, seemingly harmless situations when confronted with people, places, or products, which are lower than her own [[Social Class]].
*'''[[The Catherine Tate Show characters#Derek Faye|Derek Faye]]''' is a man who shows several signs of being [[homosexual|gay]] but seems to be in denial about his sexuality and becomes extremely offended and defensive when people assume he is gay, often exclaiming, &quot;How very dare you!&quot; or &quot;What? Gay, dear? Who, dear? Me dear? No, dear&quot;.
*'''[[The Catherine Tate Show characters#Janice and Ray|Janice and Ray]]''' are a couple from [[Beverley]], [[East Riding of Yorkshire]] who express their disgust at the various signs of multi-culturalism in their very British circle. Sources of outrage include restaurant meals, due to their perception of over-pricing or the exotic nature of the food such as grapes in a [[Brie (cheese)|brie]] cheese sandwich. They perceive global foods as adulterated British fare and view such culinary transgressions as personal affronts - finally responding with their catchphrase &quot;The dirty bastards!&quot;
*'''[[The Catherine Tate Show characters#Geordie Georgie|Geordie Georgie]]''' is a frequent petitioner, always trying to get her co-worker, Martin, to sponsor &quot;me and some of the girls&quot; in her latest charitable endeavour. With facts such as &quot;Every 38 minutes ...&quot; she follows her statements up with &quot;If you don't believe me then log on to the website double-you, double-you, double-you, dot...&quot;
*'''[[The Catherine Tate Show characters#Ally|Ally]]''' is a tactless woman with good intentions who unfortunately is a perfect example of someone with foot-in-mouth syndrome. Unwittingly she offends all that she comes into contact with at parties, and then in an attempt to dig herself out of the ditch she has created, only worsens the situation.
*'''[[The Catherine Tate Show characters#Bernie|Bernie]]''' is a vulgar nurse with an infectious snort, who works at a hospital who is never shy from both saying it how it is, and from airing her personal problems or feelings with everyone and anyone, particularly the male doctors.

==Series one (2004)==
The first series of the show, which consisted of six episodes, aired from 16 February to 22 March 2004. The programme's theme tune for the first series was &quot;In These Shoes?&quot; by [[Kirsty MacColl]]. 

In the months preceding the launch of the second series, BBC Two aired three &quot;best of&quot; episodes, featuring a variety of the funniest clips from the six episodes of series one, including Lauren Cooper the teenager and the Joannie Taylor the foul-mouthed grandmother. Meanwhile, repeats of all six episodes of the first series aired on UKTV G2 (now [[Dave (TV channel)|Dave]]). Tate also appeared in a comedy sketch with boy band McFly (see charity sketches for details).

In 2004, Catherine Tate won a [[British Comedy Award]] for &quot;Best Comedy Newcomer&quot; for her work on the first series of ''The Catherine Tate Show''.

==Series two (2005)==
The second series aired from 21 July to 25 August 2005. Following Tate's [[Comic Relief (charity)|Comic Relief]] appearance with [[McFly]], and speculation of her non-existent feud with [[David Schwimmer]],&lt;ref&gt;&quot;[http://www.digitalspy.co.uk/showbiz/a22111/catherine-tate-denies-schwimmer-feud.html Catherine Tate denies Schwimmer feud]&quot;. ''[[Digital Spy]]''. Retrieved 15 August 2007.&lt;/ref&gt; it received slightly more publicity than series one in the run-up to the first episode. BBC Two also promoted the series by running trailers showing Lauren arguing with a furry dog in the shape of the channel's [[logo]]. 

This series was far more successful with viewing figures than the first, securing ratings of 2.89 to 3.92 million, with the final episode receiving higher viewing figures than the episode of ''[[Extras (TV series)|Extras]]'' which aired beforehand.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;[http://www.barb.co.uk/viewingsummary/weekreports.cfm?report=weeklyterrestrial&amp;RequestTimeout=500 Weekly Viewing Summary. Scroll from 24/07/05 - 28/08/05]&quot;. ''[[BARB]]''. Retrieved 21 January 2007.&lt;/ref&gt; Celebrities such as [[Peter Kay]] and [[Jill Halfpenny]] made guest appearances in series two. The series also had new theme music composed by [[Howard Goodall]]. For the opening, various characters are in an open field. The camera closes in on Lauren Cooper, zooms into her eye, then zooms out of Sheila Carter's eye. The camera pans to the right, where Bernie enters. The camera zooms into her eye, then zooms out of Nan's eye, where she is seen laughing. The end of the sequence shows the main title ''The Catherine Tate Show''. The zooming is the same for both series two and three although Shelia Carter does not appear in series three (in the 2007 Christmas Special, Sheila is replaced by Geordie Georgie). 

The second series began airing in Australia on 4 April 2007 on [[Australian Broadcasting Corporation|ABC TV]].&lt;ref&gt;&quot;[http://abc.net.au/tv/guide/netw/200704/programs/ZY8674A001D4042007T213500.htm The Catherine Tate Show]&quot;. ''[[ABC (TV station)|ABC]]''. Retrieved 10 April 2007.&lt;/ref&gt; Prior to this the BBC-owned Australian cable channel [[UK.TV]] had aired the complete series starting in 2004. The re-runs of the series were shown starting from 6 May 2007.

In November 2005, Tate was a guest at the 77th ''[[Royal Variety Performance]]'', and appeared in the guise of teenager Lauren Cooper, accompanied by Lauren's friends, Ryan and Liese. After Lauren embarrassed herself in front of the audience, Ryan pointed out that the [[Elizabeth II of the United Kingdom|Queen]] was laughing at her. Looking up at the Royal Box, she asked &quot;Are you disrespecting me?&quot; and mimicked the Queen's accent, asking, &quot;Is one bovvered? Is one's face bovvered?&quot;, before adding, &quot;Who is looking after the [[Welsh Corgi|corgi]]s?&quot;&lt;ref&gt;&quot;[http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/wales/4454382.stm Tate asks if Queen is 'bovvered']&quot;. ''[[BBC News]]''. Retrieved 28 December 2006.&lt;/ref&gt; The Queen was seen laughing at this joke, and [[Prince Philip, Duke of Edinburgh|Prince Phillip]] also appeared to take this in good humour. There were, however, reports that the Prince was extremely unimpressed by the performance and complained to the show's executive producer.&lt;ref name=&quot;shystar&quot;&gt;&quot;[http://news.independent.co.uk/people/profiles/article2097803.ece Catherine Tate: The shy star]&quot;. ''[[The Independent]]''. Retrieved 10 August 2007.&lt;/ref&gt; She also appeared as Lauren in a special sketch for the BBC's annual [[Children in Need]] telethon. The segment was a crossover with ''[[EastEnders]]'' (see [[The_Catherine_Tate_Show#Charity_sketches_2|charity sketches]] for details).

&lt;!-- Deleted image removed: [[Image:Tate book.jpg|thumbnail|230px|Front cover of The Catherine Tate show script book.]] --&gt;
A Christmas show was aired on 20 December 2005. It featured appearances from celebrity guests [[Richard Park (Media consultant)|Richard Park]], [[Charlotte Church]]&lt;ref name=&quot;shystar&quot;/&gt; and [[Chas &amp; Dave]]. During the show, Paul and Sam's two children were seen for the first time. They physically resembled, and had identical characteristics to their parents. The characters of Margaret and the enigmatic detective, who did not appear in series two, made appearances in the Christmas special. According to [[BARB]]'s official viewing figures, over 5.66 million viewers watched the show, making it the most-watched programme at the time and the most watched programme on BBC Two the week it was aired.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;[http://www.barb.co.uk/viewingsummary/weekreports.cfm?report=weeklyterrestrial&amp;RequestTimeout=500 Weekly Viewing Summary. Scroll to 25/12/05]&quot;. ''[[BARB]]''. Retrieved 21 January 2007.&lt;/ref&gt; The show was also nominated for the People's Choice Award at the [[British Comedy Awards]] in 2005, but did not win after it was announced that the show had received less votes than ''[[Ant and Dec's Saturday Night Takeaway]]''.&lt;ref name=&quot;rigged&quot;&gt;&quot;[http://www.dailymail.co.uk/pages/live/articles/news/news.html?in_article_id=564778&amp;in_page_id=1770 ITV rigged comedy award phone vote because Robbie Williams wanted Ant and Dec to win]&quot;. ''[[The Daily Mail]]'', 8 May 2008. Retrieved 8 May 2008.&lt;/ref&gt; In an investigation, it was revealed in May 2008 that ''The Catherine Tate Show'' was the true winner of the British Comedy Award, and that Ant and Dec were wrongly awarded; Tate had actually received more votes from the public.&lt;ref name=&quot;rigged&quot;/&gt; A report by independent law firm, [[Olswang]], said &quot;[[Robbie Williams]] was invited to present an award. It was understood that he would be happy [to do so] if the recipients were [[Anthony McPartlin]] and [[Declan Donnelly]]. In order to ensure his attendance, this assurance was given&quot;; however, it is not known if Williams' comments led to the wrong announcement.&lt;ref name=&quot;deception&quot;&gt;&quot;[http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/entertainment/7390193.stm ITV admits comedy award deception]&quot;. [[BBC News]], 8 May 2008. Retrieved 8 May 2008.&lt;/ref&gt; It was also exposed that the second half of the ceremony was not broadcast live but with a delay of half-an-hour, yet viewers were still encouraged to vote for the People's Choice Award, even though the votes had been counted and the trophy presented half-an-hour before.&lt;ref name=&quot;deception&quot;/&gt;  

The second series started airing on [[Dave (TV channel)|UKTV G2]] in January 2006. Series one continued on UKTV Gold. The second series was also being screened on [[BBC America]], and repeated on BBC Two, from June 2006. Following the success of series two, Tate launched a range of merchandise based on characters from the show in 2006. In September 2006 ''The Catherine Tate Show'' official calendar 2007 was released. Also, on 2 October 2006 a book was released of the scripts of both series one and two, called ''Am I Bovvered The Catherine Tate Show Scripts''. 

On 13 December 2006, Tate won another British Comedy Award for &quot;Best TV Comedy Actress&quot; for her work in the second series of ''The Catherine Tate Show''.

==Series three (2006)==
The third and final series started on 26 October 2006 and ran until 25 November 2006. Prior to the launch of the series, it had been reported that [[BBC One]] controller [[Peter Fincham]] hoped to lure Tate to the channel; however, she decided to stay with BBC Two, where she would not be as pressured to secure higher ratings.

The series gained strong viewing figures for [[BBC Two]], ranging from 4.00 to 4.92 million, becoming the top show on BBC Two each week.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;[http://www.barb.co.uk/viewingsummary/weekreports.cfm?report=weeklyterrestrial&amp;RequestTimeout=500 Weekly Viewing Summary. Scroll from 29/10/06 - 03/12/06]&quot;. ''[[BARB]]''. Retrieved 21 January 2007.&lt;/ref&gt; There were many more guest appearances in the third series which included [[Paul O'Grady]] being featured in a sketch with Joannie &quot;Nan&quot; Taylor when she appeared on ''[[The Paul O'Grady Show]]''.

On 19 February 2007, Tate appeared again on ''This Morning'' and stated that a forty-minute Comic Relief special had been made, which aired on 16 March 2007. Several sketches were interspersed throughout the Comic Relief programme, with guests such as the prime minister at the time, [[Tony Blair]] (see charity sketches for details). [[Kim Cattrall]] has also expressed an interest in appearing on an episode of the show. Cattrall commented that she is a &quot;huge fan&quot; and would like to be given a role.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;[http://www.digitalspy.co.uk/showbiz/a74269/kim-cattrall-wants-catherine-tate-role.html Kim Cattrall wants Catherine Tate role]&quot;. ''[[Digital Spy]]''. Retrieved 9 September 2007.&lt;/ref&gt;

Tate has revealed that she is considering taking the characters from the show on the road for a UK stage tour.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;[http://www.itv.com/news/entertainment_5c9e2d427ce3c12ca81af1d9732408f0.html Catherine Tate to go on tour?]&quot;. ''[[ITV News]]''. Retrieved 4 July 2007.&lt;/ref&gt; Series Three was released on DVD on 12 November 2007. On 31 October 2007 ''The Catherine Tate Show'' won the [[National Television Awards|National Television Award]] for most popular comedy as voted for by the public.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;[http://www.guardian.co.uk/media/2007/nov/01/television National Television Awards 2007]&quot;. ''[[The Guardian]]''. Retrieved 1 November 2007.&lt;/ref&gt;

A new Christmas special episode aired on 25 December 2007 on [[BBC One]],&lt;ref name=&quot;comedy&quot;&gt;&quot;[http://www.telegraph.co.uk/arts/main.jhtml?xml=/arts/2007/12/05/btcomedy105.xml Comedy in December]&quot;. ''[[The Daily Telegraph|The Telegraph]]''. Retrieved 11 December 2007.&lt;/ref&gt; in which [[pop star]] [[George Michael]] made a guest appearance. He was featured in several scenes with Irish nurse, Bernie, including one kissing scene.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;[http://www.thesun.co.uk/article/0,,2001320029-2007360270,00.html George says don't kiss me, Tate]&quot;. ''[[The Sun (newspaper)|The Sun]]''. Retrieved 12 August 2007.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;&quot;[http://www.dailymail.co.uk/pages/live/articles/showbiz/showbiznews.html?in_article_id=501022&amp;in_page_id=1773 Catherine Tate attempts to bed George Michael - but it's all for her Christmas special]&quot;. ''[[Daily Mail]]''. Retrieved 10 December 2007.&lt;/ref&gt; The character of [[Lauren Cooper|Lauren]] was killed in a [[kayak]]ing accident during the episode.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;[http://www.thesun.co.uk/sol/homepage/showbiz/tv/article562980.ece But, am I bovv-oar-ed??]&quot;. ''[[The Sun (newspaper)|The Sun]]''. Retrieved 11 December 2007.&lt;/ref&gt; Rumours had emerged about this story line in July 2007.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;[http://entertainment.aol.co.uk/bovvered-lauren-to-be-killed-off/article/20070718055509990003 Bovvered Lauren 'to be killed off']&quot;. ''[[AOL]]''. Retrieved 18 July 2007.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;&quot;[http://www.digitalspy.co.uk/tv/a66512/catherine-tate-to-kill-off-character.html Catherine Tate to kill off character?]&quot;. ''[[Digital Spy]]''. Retrieved 20 July 2007.&lt;/ref&gt; [[Kathy Burke]] and [[Tamzin Outhwaite]] also guest starred,&lt;ref name=&quot;comedy&quot;/&gt; and the special averaged with 6.4 million viewers.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;[http://www.dailymail.co.uk/pages/live/articles/showbiz/showbiznews.html?in_article_id=504572&amp;in_page_id=1773&amp;ito=1490 EastEnders and Doctor Who help the BBC exterminate ITV in the Christmas Day ratings battle]&quot;. ''[[The Daily Mail]]''. Retrieved 26 December 2007.&lt;/ref&gt; The episode was subject to criticism when some viewers complained about the amount of [[Profanity|swearing]], and accused Tate of bigotry over the depiction of a family from [[Northern Ireland]] as terrorists, whose Christmas presents included a [[Balaclava (clothing)|balaclava]] and a pair of [[Brass knuckles|knuckle dusters]], in reference to [[The Troubles]].&lt;ref name=&quot;investigate&quot;&gt;&quot;[http://www.telegraph.co.uk/news/main.jhtml?xml=/news/2007/12/28/nbbc128.xml Ofcom to investigate Catherine Tate 'bigotry']&quot;. ''[[The Daily Telegraph]]''. Retrieved 4 January 2008.&lt;/ref&gt; A statement was issued from the BBC that read &quot;Catherine Tate creates characters who are so over the top as to be almost cartoon-like and this is where her genius lies. Her comedy is never meant to offend any viewer and is always based on satire and grotesque exaggeration.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;investigate&quot;/&gt; After the complaints were made, an [[Ofcom]] report later concluded that the show was not offensive and did not violate broadcasting regulations.&lt;ref&gt;O'Shea, Katherine. &quot;[http://www.telegraph.co.uk/arts/main.jhtml?xml=/arts/2008/04/14/bvtate114.xml BBC cleared over 'offensive' Catherine Tate]&quot;. ''[[The Daily Telegraph]]'', 14 April 2008. Retrieved 8 May 2008.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;&quot;[http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/entertainment/7346479.stm Tate festive show 'not offensive']&quot;. [[BBC News]], 14 April 2008. Retrieved 8 May 2008.&lt;/ref&gt; An extract from the Ofcom report read &quot;Overall this episode was typical of the Catherine Tate Show and would not have gone beyond the expectations of its usual audience. For those not familiar with the show, the information given at the start was adequate.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Plunkett, John.&quot; [http://www.guardian.co.uk/media/2008/apr/14/ofcom.television?gusrc=rss&amp;feed=media Ofcom not bovvered by Tate swearing]&quot;. ''[[The Guardian]]'', 14 April 2008. Retrieved 8 May 2008.&lt;/ref&gt; 

During Tate's appearance on ''[[The Paul O'Grady Show]]'' on 24 September 2007, Tate did not make a reference to the speculation of there being any more series, but she did state that she may just continue her work on ''The Catherine Tate Show'' through one-off specials. It has since been announced by Tate that she does not plan any more series after the Christmas special.&lt;ref name=&quot;late&quot;/&gt; She commented: &quot;It's hard to keep coming up with ideas. And I'd like to stay in people's good graces, rather than, 'Oh no, she's not doing another series of that, is she?'&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;late&quot;/&gt; Tate also left to concentrate on other projects such as her role as [[Donna Noble]], in series four of ''[[Doctor Who]]''.&lt;ref name=&quot;bbc&quot;&gt;&quot;[http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/entertainment/6267680.stm Tate to be Doctor's companion]&quot;. ''[[BBC News]]''. Retrieved 4 July 2007.&lt;/ref&gt;

The BBC confirmed that a new Christmas special will be broadcast in December 2009, titled ''[[Nan's Christmas Carol]]'', featuring Tate's Nan character as Scrooge. The special guest stars [[Mathew Horne]] (reprising his role as Nan's grandson Jamie) and [[Ben Miller]], [[David Tennant]] and [[Roger Lloyd Pack]] as ghosts. [[Niky Wardley]] who played many various characters mainly Lisa Jackson, also returned as Joannie Taylor's mother.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.bbc.co.uk/pressoffice/proginfo/tv/2009/wk51/bbc_one.shtml#bbc_one_catherine_tate&lt;/ref&gt; Despite this special, shown on 25 December 2009, Tate has reiterated that she has no plans for the show to make a full return.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |author=Daniel Kilkelly | url=http://www.digitalspy.co.uk/tv/news/a192696/tate-unsure-over-sketch-show-future.html | title=Tate unsure over sketch show future |work=[[Digital Spy]] |date=2009-12-24 | accessdate=2009-12-24}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Charity sketches==
Tate made an appearance during the BBC's [[Comic Relief (charity)|Comic Relief]] [[telethon]] in March 2005, in the guise of [[Lauren Cooper]]. In a section of the show which features fans of [[McFly (band)|McFly]] asking questions to the group, Lauren decides to ask, &quot;Why are you so rubbish?&quot; When told by [[Simon Amstell]], who is hosting the segment, that only positive questions are allowed, Lauren uses a variety of her [[catchphrase]]s, including &quot;Am I bovvered?&quot; and &quot;Are you calling me stupid?&quot; Lauren is then &quot;ordered&quot; to ask a more positive question to the group, and confuses them with [[Busted (band)|Busted]], asking &quot;Are you gutted that [[Charlie Simpson|Charlie]] left?&quot; When told to leave the set, on her way out she asks [[Danny Jones]] from McFly to sign her knee, walking away promptly saying &quot;You can't even spell.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;guardianprofile&quot;&gt;&quot;[http://arts.guardian.co.uk/features/story/0,,1673257,00.html The Guardian profile: Catherine Tate]&quot;. ''[[The Guardian]]''. Retrieved 18 July 2007.&lt;/ref&gt; 

In November 2005, Tate appeared as Lauren in a special sketch for the BBC's annual [[Children in Need]] telethon. The segment is posed as a crossover with ''[[EastEnders]]'', featuring [[Barbara Windsor]] as [[Peggy Mitchell]], [[Kacey Ainsworth]] as [[Little Mo Mitchell|Little Mo]] and [[Lacey Turner]] as [[Stacey Slater]]. The sketch sees Lauren arrive in [[Walford]] in search of [[revenge]] on Stacey, who has apparently stolen her boyfriend. When she makes an appearance in the [[The Queen Victoria|Queen Vic]], Peggy finds herself getting increasingly frustrated with Lauren, who asks, &quot;Are you a [[Cockney]]? Are you a Cockney sparrow?&quot; (pronounced 'Cock-er-ney') and &quot;Do you know [[Chas &amp; Dave]]? Are you their mum?&quot; repeatedly. Peggy also unintentionally uses some of Lauren's catchphrases, such as &quot;Are you disrespecting my family?&quot; and &quot;Are you calling me a [[pikey]]?&quot; Lauren eventually leaves the pub after mixing some famous lines from the soap, including &quot;Hello princess&quot; and &quot;Rickaay!&quot; with her usual catchphrase, &quot;Bovvered?&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;[http://news.bbc.co.uk/nolavconsole/ukfs_news/hi/newsid_4450000/newsid_4452400/bb_rm_4452426.stm Catherine Tate appears in Walford]&quot;. ''[[BBC News]]''. Retrieved 18 February 2007.&lt;/ref&gt;

In the BBC's [[Sport Relief]], Tate created a sketch as &quot;Nan&quot;, commenting on the 1966 world cup win and the comments of [[Kenneth Wolstenholme]]. The sketch involves &quot;Nan&quot; and her grandson watching a [[David Beckham]] football game, where she expresses her disgust at the objective of football by exclaiming &quot;What a load of old shit!&quot;.{{Citation needed|date=January 2009}}

On 16 March 2007, Catherine Tate appeared on [[Comic Relief (charity)|Comic Relief]] as many of her well-known characters from the show. The sketches were interspersed throughout the Comic Relief programme. Guests in sketches include [[David Tennant]] (who acts as Lauren Cooper's teacher and actually turns out to be the real [[Doctor (Doctor Who)|Doctor]]), and [[Daniel Craig]] as another one of Elaine Figgis's boyfriends whom she has met through the internet. During his time as prime minister, [[Tony Blair]] made a [[cameo appearance]] in a sketch which features Lauren Cooper on work experience at [[10 Downing Street]]. Upon Lauren attempting to tell Blair who the most famous person she has met is, he asks ''her'' if he is &quot;bovvered&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;[http://www.telegraph.co.uk/news/main.jhtml?xml=/news/2007/03/22/ntate121.xml Catherine Tate hails Blair's comic skills]&quot;. ''[[The Daily Telegraph]]''. Retrieved 4 June 2007.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;&quot;[http://www.thisislondon.co.uk/showbiz/article-23390027-details/Blair+He+is+a+real+joker%2C+says+Lauren/article.do Blair? He is a real joker, says Lauren]&quot;. ''[[London Evening Standard]]''. Retrieved 28 July 2007.&lt;/ref&gt; [[The Catherine Tate Show characters#Geordie Georgie|Geordie Georgie]] made an appearance with [[Lenny Henry]] when he does his own fund raising for Comic Relief, and Joannie Taylor also appeared on game show ''[[Deal or No Deal (UK game show)|Deal or No Deal]]'' hosted by [[Noel Edmonds]].&lt;ref name=&quot;record&quot;&gt;&quot;[http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/entertainment/6470511.stm Catherine Tate DVD 'sets record']&quot;. ''[[BBC News]]''. Retrieved 4 June 2007.&lt;/ref&gt; The DVD of the sketches was available exclusively to [[Amazon (website)|Amazon]] and became the most pre-ordered DVD the site has ever seen.&lt;ref name=&quot;record&quot;/&gt;

In 13 March 2009, Nan appeared on the 2009 [[Comic Relief]]. She was receiving a cheque for her Community Centre from [[Fern Britton]] and [[Alan Carr]]. She was then disgusted that she only got £1000.

{| class=&quot;wikitable&quot; width=100% style=&quot;margin-right: 0;&quot;
! Year
! Event
! Character
! Guest Star(s)
|-
|rowspan=&quot;2&quot;|2005
|Comic Relief
|[[Lauren Cooper]]
|[[McFly (band)|McFly]], [[Simon Amstell]]
|-
|Children in Need
|[[Lauren Cooper]]
|[[Barbara Windsor]], [[Lacey Turner]], [[Kacey Ainsworth]]
|-
|2006
|Sports Relief
|[[Joannie Taylor]]
|[[David Beckham]]
|-
|rowspan=&quot;6&quot;|2007
|rowspan=&quot;6&quot;|Comic Relief
|Lauren Cooper
|[[David Tennant]]
|-
|[[The Catherine Tate Show characters#Bernie|Bernie]]
|[[George Michael]]
|-
|[[The Catherine Tate Show characters#Elaine Figgis|Elaine Figgis]]
|[[Daniel Craig]]
|-
|Lauren Cooper
|[[Tony Blair]]
|-
|[[The Catherine Tate Show characters#Geordie Georgie|Geordie Georgie]]
|[[Lenny Henry]]
|-
|Joannie Taylor
|[[Noel Edmonds]]
|-
|2009
|Comic Relief
|Joannie Taylor
|[[Fern Britton]], [[Alan Carr]]
|-
|2010
|[[Channel 4's Comedy Gala]]
|Joannie Taylor
|
|-
|}

==Awards==
===Won===
*2004: [[Banff Rockie Award]] &amp;mdash; Best Comedy
*2004: [[British Comedy Award]] &amp;mdash; Best TV Comedy Newcomer
*2006: British Comedy Award &amp;mdash; Best TV Comedy Actress
*2006: [[Royal Television Society|RTS Television Award]] &amp;mdash; Best Comedy Performance
*2006: RTS Television Award &amp;mdash; Best Entertainment
*2007: [[National Television Awards|National Television Award]] &amp;mdash; Most Popular Comedy Programme

===Nominated===
*2004: British Comedy Award &amp;mdash; Best TV Comedy Actress
*2004: RTS Television Award &amp;mdash; Best Make Up Design in Entertainment and Non-Drama Productions
*2005: [[BAFTA TV Award]] &amp;mdash; Best New Writer
*2005: BAFTA TV Award &amp;mdash; Comedy Programme or Series Award
*2005: British Comedy Award &amp;mdash; Best TV Comedy Actress
*2005: British Comedy Award &amp;mdash; People's Choice Award (Polled most votes but award not received)
*2005: [[Emmy]] &amp;mdash; Best Performance by an Actress
*2006: BAFTA TV Award &amp;mdash; Best Comedy Performance
*2006: BAFTA TV Award &amp;mdash; Best Comedy Programme or Series &quot;production team&quot;
*2006: National Television Award &amp;mdash; Most Popular Comedy Programme
*2007: BAFTA TV Award &amp;mdash; Best Comedy Programme
*2007: BAFTA TV Award &amp;mdash; Best Make Up &amp; Hair Design

==Guest stars==
===Series two===
*[[Brian Murphy (actor)|Brian Murphy]] - with Irene and Vern
*[[Geraldine McNulty]] - with Paul and Sam
*[[Jill Halfpenny]] - with The Aga Saga Woman
*[[Michael Brandon]] - with Boob Job Babe
&lt;!-- Deleted image removed: [[Image:Bonnie Derek.jpg|thumb|215pix|Bonnie Langford with Derek Faye (middle) and Leonard Mincing]] --&gt;
*[[Paul Whitehouse]] - with Paul and Sam
*[[Peter Kay]] - with Joannie &quot;Nan&quot; Taylor
*[[Roger Allam]] - with Bernie
*[[Siobhan Redmond]] - with Gingers For Justice
*[[Una Stubbs]] - with Trudy and Ivan

===Series three===
*[[Bonnie Langford]] - with Derek Faye
*[[Jools Holland]] - with Helen Marsh
*[[Rhona Martin]] - with Helen Marsh
*[[Leslie Phillips]] - with Joannie &quot;Nan&quot; Taylor
*[[Natalie Cassidy]] - with Lauren Cooper
*[[Nick sidi|Nick Sidi]] - with Derek Faye
*[[Patsy Palmer]] - with Gingers For Justice
*[[Paul O'Grady]] - with Joannie &quot;Nan&quot; Taylor
*[[Sheila Hancock]] - with Joannie &quot;Nan&quot; Taylor
*[[Siobhan Redmond]] - with Gingers For Justice
*[[Tom Ellis (actor)|Tom Ellis]] - with Ma Willow
*[[Una Stubbs]] - with Ma Willow
*[[Dominic West]] - with Frankie Howerd impressionist

===Christmas specials===
*[[Charlotte Church]] - with Joannie &quot;Nan&quot; Taylor
*[[Chas &amp; Dave]] - with Joannie &quot;Nan&quot; Taylor
*[[David Tennant]] - with Joannie &quot;Nan&quot; Taylor
*[[George Michael]] - with Bernie
*[[Kathy Burke]] - with Joannie &quot;Nan&quot; Taylor
*[[Philip Glenister]] - with Ma Willow
*[[Richard Park (broadcaster)|Richard Park]] - with Lauren Cooper
*[[Tamzin Outhwaite]] - with Paul and Sam
*[[Colin Morgan]] - with the O'Leary family

===Charity sketches===
*[[Daniel Craig]] - with Elaine Figgis
*[[David Tennant]] - with Lauren Cooper
*[[Lenny Henry]] - with Geordie Georgie
*[[Kacey Ainsworth]] - with Lauren Cooper
*[[McFly (band)|McFly]] - with Lauren Cooper
*[[Noel Edmonds]] - with Joannie &quot;Nan&quot; Taylor
*[[Barbara Windsor]] - with Lauren Cooper
*[[Simon Amstell]] - with Lauren Cooper
*[[Lacey Turner]] - with Lauren Cooper
*[[Tony Blair]] - with Lauren Cooper
*[[Alan Carr]] and [[Fern Britton]] - with Joannie &quot;Nan&quot; Taylor

==DVD releases==
All three series and the Christmas specials of ''The Catherine Tate Show'' have been released on DVD.  In the UK and Australia all three series have been separately released, with the first Christmas special (2005) being part of series two, a series one &amp; two boxset was released, and a complete series boxset was released.  The Australian version of the complete boxset includes the second Christmas special (2007), but, the UK version doesn't, it is released as a separate edition.  The third Christmas special ''Nan's Christmas Carol'' (2009) has been released in the UK.

In the United States, Series one and two have only been released separately, and the first Christmas special is released as a separate edition. 

{| class=&quot;wikitable&quot; width=&quot;100%&quot; style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;
|-
!rowspan=&quot;2&quot; colspan=&quot;2&quot;|DVD title
!rowspan=&quot;2&quot;|Disc #
!rowspan=&quot;2&quot;|Year
!rowspan=&quot;2&quot;|Ep. #
!colspan=&quot;3&quot;|DVD release
|-
!Region 1
!Region 2
!Region 4
|-
|bgcolor=&quot;ffffff&quot;|
|''Complete Series 1''
|1
|2004
|6
|25 September 2007
|22 August 2005
|5 November 2007
|-
|bgcolor=&quot;A020F0&quot;|
|''Complete Series 2''
|1
|2005
|7
|25 March 2008
|30 October 2006
|5 April 2007
|-
|bgcolor=&quot;A76BCF&quot;|
|''Complete Series 3''
|1
|2006
|6
|TBA
|12 November 2007 
|30 June 2008
|-
|bgcolor=&quot;000000&quot;|
|''[[Christmas]] Special 1''
|1
|2005
|1
|28 October 2008
|On Series 2 DVD
|On Series 2 DVD
|-
|bgcolor=&quot;008000&quot;|
|''[[Christmas]] Special 2''
|1
|2007
|1
|TBA
|26 December 2007
|On Series 3 DVD
|-
|bgcolor=&quot;FF0000&quot;|
|''[[Comic Relief]] Special''
|1
|2007
|1
|TBA
|23 April 2007 &lt;ref&gt;[[Amazon.com|Amazon.co.uk]] Exclusive&lt;/ref&gt;
|TBA
|-
|bgcolor=&quot;FFC0CB&quot;|
|''Complete Series 1&amp;2''
|2
|2004 - 2005
|13
|TBA
|30 October 2006
|6 September 2007
|-
|bgcolor=&quot;E75480&quot;|
|''Complete Series 1-3''
|3
|2004 - 2006
|19
|TBA
|12 November 2007
|2 April 2009
|-
|bgcolor=&quot;B0C4DE&quot;|
|''Nan's Christmas Carol''
|1
|2009
|1
|TBA
|29 November 2010
|TBA
|}

==See also==
*[[The Catherine Tate Show characters]]
*''[[Nan's Christmas Carol]]''

==References==
{{Reflist|2}}

==External links==
{{Wikiquote}}
*{{tv.com|24747}}
*{{IMDb title|0441051}}
*{{British Comedy Guide|tv|the_catherine_tate_show}}
*[http://www.catherinetateshow.co.uk Catherinetateshow.co.uk &amp;mdash; Fansite]
*[http://www.catherinetate.co.uk Catherinetate.co.uk &amp;mdash; Fansite]

{{DEFAULTSORT:Catherine Tate Show}}
[[Category:2004 British television programme debuts]]
[[Category:2007 British television programme endings]]
[[Category:2009 British television programme endings]]
[[Category:2000s British television series]]
[[Category:BBC television comedy]]
[[Category:British LGBT-related television programmes]]
[[Category:British television sketch shows]]
[[Category:English-language television series]]

[[cy:The Catherine Tate Show]]
[[de:The Catherine Tate Show]]
[[it:The Catherine Tate Show]]
[[nl:The Catherine Tate Show]]
[[ru:Шоу Кэтрин Тейт]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
