<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="20352655" ns="0" title="Development of Windows 7"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Windows 7}}
'''Development of [[Windows 7]]''' began when [[Windows Vista]] was released. Milestone 1, Milestone 2, and Milestone 3 were sent to Microsoft's partners in 2008. In October 2008, Microsoft gave build 6801 to PDC attendees and a public beta was released in January 2009.

The release candidate was available from April 30, 2009 for MSDN and Technet subscribers, and was released to the public on May 5, 2009. The final build of Windows 7 was released to manufacturing on July 22, 2009;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://arstechnica.com/microsoft/news/2009/07/microsoft-windows-7-is-done-on-its-way-to-manufacturers.ars |title=Microsoft: Windows 7 is done, on its way to manufacturers |last=Protalinski |first=Emil |date=2009-07-22 |publisher=Ars Technica |accessdate=2009-07-22}}&lt;/ref&gt; Technet and MSDN subscribers were able to download it on August 6. On October 22, the operating system was made generally available for public purchase.

==History==
In 2000, Microsoft was planning to follow up [[Windows XP]], and its server counterpart, [[Windows Server 2003]] (both codenamed ''Whistler''), with a major new release of Windows, [[Microsoft code names|codenamed]] ''Blackcomb'' (both codenames refer to the [[Whistler-Blackcomb]] resort). This new version was, at that time, scheduled for a 2005 release.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.wininsider.com/news/?226 Microsoft pushes back Blackcomb to 2005]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://news.cnet.com/2100-1001-966174.html .Net Server: Three delays a charm?]&lt;/ref&gt;

Major features were planned for Blackcomb, including an emphasis on searching and querying data, and an advanced storage system named [[WinFS]] to enable such scenarios. In this context, a feature mentioned by Microsoft co-founder Bill Gates for Blackcomb was &quot;a pervasive typing line that will recognize the sentence that [the user is] typing in.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.microsoft.com/presspass/exec/billg/speeches/2000/07-12pdc.aspx |title = Professional Developers Conference Remarks |last=Gates |first=Bill |authorlink=Bill Gates |publisher=[[Microsoft|microsoft.com]] |date = 2000-07-12 |accessdate=2008-03-05}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Later, Blackcomb was delayed, and an interim, minor release, codenamed &quot;Longhorn&quot; (named for the Longhorn Tavern between the resorts), was announced for a 2003 release.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url= http://www.theregister.co.uk/2001/10/24/gates_confirms_windows_longhorn |title=Gates confirms Windows Longhorn for 2003 |last=Lettice |first=John |date=2001-10-24 |publisher=The Register |accessdate=2008-03-05}}&lt;/ref&gt; By the middle of 2003, however, Longhorn had acquired some of the features originally intended for Blackcomb, including [[WinFS]], the [[Desktop Window Manager]], and new versions of system components built on the [[.NET Framework]]. After the 2003 &quot;Summer of Worms&quot;, where three major viruses − [[Blaster (computer worm)|Blaster]], [[Sobig (computer worm)|Sobig]], and [[Welchia]] − exploited flaws in Windows operating systems within a short time period, Microsoft changed its development priorities, putting some of Longhorn's major development work on hold in order to develop new service packs for Windows XP and [[Windows Server 2003]]. [[Development of Windows Vista|Development of Longhorn]] was also &quot;reset&quot; in September 2004.

===Naming===
As major feature work on Windows Vista wound down in early 2006, Blackcomb was renamed ''Vienna''.&lt;ref name=thurrottfaq&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.winsupersite.com/faq/windows_7.asp |title=Windows &quot;7&quot; FAQ |last=Thurrott |first=Paul |authorlink=Paul Thurrott |publisher=Paul Thurrott's SuperSite for Windows |date=14 February 2007 |accessdate=2008-01-05}}&lt;/ref&gt; However, following the release of [[Windows Vista]], it was confirmed by [[Microsoft]] on July 20, 2007 that &quot;the internal name for the next version of the Windows Client OS&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;zdnet592&quot;&gt;{{cite news | first=Mary J |last=Foley |title=Windows Seven: Think 2010 |date=2007-07-20 |publisher=[[ZDNet]] | url=http://blogs.zdnet.com/microsoft/?p=592 |accessdate = 2007-09-19}}&lt;/ref&gt; was ''Windows 7'', a name that had been reported by some sources months before.&lt;ref name=&quot;thurrottfaq&quot; /&gt; On October 13, 2008, it was announced that ''Windows 7'' would also be the official name of the operating system.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news | first=Ina | last=Fried | title=Microsoft makes Windows 7 name final | date=2008-10-13 | publisher=[[CNET]] | url=http://news.cnet.com/8301-13860_3-10064971-56.html | accessdate=2008-10-13}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;CBC14Oct08&quot;&gt;{{cite news|url = http://www.cbc.ca/technology/story/2008/10/14/tech-windows.html|title = For Microsoft's Windows, 7th time's a charm|accessdate = 2008-10-27|last = [[Canadian Broadcasting Corporation]]|authorlink = |year = 2008|month = October | work=CBC News}}&lt;/ref&gt; Mike Nash, Microsoft's vice-president of Windows product management said:

{{blockquote| The decision to use the name Windows 7 is about simplicity. Simply put, this is the seventh release of Windows, so therefore Windows 7 just makes sense.

Coming up with an all-new 'aspirational' name does not do justice to what we are trying to achieve, which is to stay firmly rooted in our aspirations for Windows Vista, while evolving and refining the substantial investments in platform technology in Windows Vista into the next generation of Windows.&lt;ref name=&quot;CBC14Oct08&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
|url = http://www.pcpro.co.uk/news/230106/windows-7-to-be-called-windows-7.html
|title = Windows 7 to be called... Windows 7 
|date = 14 October 2008
|accessdate = 2008-10-17
|last = Collins
|first = Barry
|publisher = [[PC Pro]]
}}&lt;/ref&gt; }}

Numbering this version of Windows as &quot;7&quot; has confused many users, so on October 14, 2008, Nash clarified his earlier remarks, saying:&lt;ref name=&quot;Protalinski&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url = http://arstechnica.com/journals/microsoft.ars/2008/10/15/final-release-of-windows-7-to-have-kernel-version-6-1|title = Final release of Windows 7 to have kernel version 6.1|accessdate = 2008-11-24|last = Protalinski |first = Emil|authorlink = |year = 2008|month = October}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Nash14Oct08&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url = http://windowsteamblog.com/blogs/windowsvista/archive/2008/10/14/why-7.aspx|title = Windows Vista Team Blog - Why 7?|accessdate = 2008-11-24|last = Nash|first = Mike.|authorlink = |year = 2008|month = October}}&lt;/ref&gt;

{{blockquote|The very first release of Windows was Windows 1.0, the second was Windows 2.0, the third Windows 3.0. Here's where things get a little more complicated. Following Windows 3.0 was Windows NT which was code versioned as Windows 3.1. Then came Windows 95, which was code versioned as Windows 4.0. Then, Windows 98, 98 SE and Windows Millennium each shipped as 4.0.1998, 4.10.2222, and 4.90.3000, respectively. So we're counting all 9x versions as being 4.0. Windows 2000 code was 5.0 and then we shipped Windows XP as 5.1, even though it was a major release we didn't want to change code version numbers to maximize application compatibility. That brings us to Windows Vista, which is 6.0. So we see Windows 7 as our next logical significant release and 7th in the family of Windows releases...There's been some fodder about whether using 6.1 in the code is an indicator of the relevance of Windows 7.  It is not. Windows 7 is a significant and evolutionary advancement of the client operating system.  It is in every way a major effort in design, engineering and innovation.  The only thing to read into the code versioning is that we are absolutely committed to making sure application compatibility is optimized for our customers.&lt;ref name=&quot;Nash14Oct08&quot; /&gt; }}

==Focus==

Microsoft's Ben Fathi stated on 9 February 2007 that the focus of the operating system was still being worked out, and he could only hint at some possibilities:&lt;ref name=&quot;Vista2009&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.infoworld.com/article/07/02/09/HNvistafollowup_1.html|title=Microsoft: Vista follow-up likely in 2009|author=Robert McMillan, IDG News Service|date=9 February 2007}}&lt;/ref&gt;
{{blockquote|We're going to look at a fundamental piece of enabling technology. Maybe it's [[hypervisor]]s. I don't know what it is [...] Maybe it's a new [[user interface]] [[paradigm]] for consumers.|Ben Fathi, Windows Core Operating System Division Vice President}}

[[Bill Gates]], in an interview with [[Newsweek]], suggested that the next version of Windows would &quot;be more user-centric.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;gates&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.msnbc.msn.com/id/16934083/site/newsweek/page/4/print/1/displaymode/1098/|title=Bill Gates on Vista and Apple's 'Lying' Ads|author=Steven Levy|date= 3 February 2007}}&lt;/ref&gt; When asked to clarify what he meant, Gates said: 
{{blockquote|That means that right now when you move from one [[Personal computer|PC]] to another, you've got to install apps on each one, do upgrades on each one. Moving information between them is very painful. We can use [[Windows Live|Live Services]] to know what you're interested in. So even if you drop by a [public] kiosk or somebody else's PC, we can bring down your home page, your files, your fonts, your favorites and those things. So that's kind of the user-centric thing that Live Services can enable. [Also,] in Vista, things got a lot better with [digital] ink and speech, but by the next release there will be a much bigger bet. Students won't need textbooks; they can just use these [[tablet computer|tablet devices]]. [[Parallel computing]] is pretty important for the next release. We'll make it so that a lot of the high-level graphics will be just built into the operating system. So we've got a pretty good outline.}}

Gates later said that Windows 7 will also focus on performance improvements:&lt;ref name=&quot;gates2&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.microsoft.com/presspass/exec/billg/speeches/2008/05-07japanwdlc.mspx|title=Bill Gates: Japan—Windows Digital Lifestyle Consortium|author=Bill Gates|date=12 May 2007}}&lt;/ref&gt;
{{blockquote|We're hard at work, I would say, on the next version, which we call Windows 7. I'm very excited about the work being done there. The ability to be lower power, take less memory, be more efficient, and have lots more connections up to the mobile phone, so those scenarios connect up well to make it a great platform for the best gaming that can be done, to connect up to the thing being done out on the Internet, so that, for example, if you have two personal computers, that your files automatically are synchronized between them, and so you don't have a lot of work to move that data back and forth.}}

Senior Vice President Bill Veghte stated that Windows 7 will not have the kind of compatibility issues with Vista that Vista has with previous versions:&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://news.softpedia.com/news/Windows-7-Will-Not-Inherent-the-Incompatibility-Issues-of-Vista-88625.shtml|title=Windows 7 Will Not Inherit the Incompatibility Issues of Vista|author=Marius Oiaga|date=24 June 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt;
{{blockquote|You've let us know you don't want to face the kinds of incompatibility challenges with the next version of Windows you might have experienced early with Windows Vista. As a result, our approach with Windows 7 is to build off the same core architecture as Windows Vista so the investments you and our partners have made in Windows Vista will continue to pay off with Windows 7. Our goal is to ensure the migration process from Windows Vista to Windows 7 is straightforward.}}

Speaking about Windows 7 on 16 October 2008, Microsoft CEO [[Steve Ballmer]] confirmed compatibility between Vista and Windows 7:&lt;ref name=&quot;DignanOctober2008&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url = http://blogs.zdnet.com/BTL/?p=10464|title = Ballmer: It's ok to wait until Windows 7; Yahoo still 'makes sense'; Google Apps 'primitive'|accessdate = 2008-10-17|last = Dignan|first = Larry|authorlink = |year = 2008|month = October}}&lt;/ref&gt;

{{blockquote| Our next release of Windows will be compatible with Vista. The key is let's get on with it. We'll be ready when you want to deploy Windows 7.&lt;ref name=&quot;DignanOctober2008&quot; /&gt; }}

Ballmer also confirmed the relationship between Vista and Windows 7, indicating that Windows 7 will be an improved version of Vista.&lt;ref name=&quot;DignanOctober2008&quot; /&gt;

==Builds==
===Milestones===

====Milestone 1====

Windows 7 Milestone 1 Build 6519 is still very similar to Windows Vista, with only a few changes. For example, [[Windows Sidebar]] has been replaced with standalone gadgets. The first known [[Software build|build]] of Windows 7 was identified as a &quot;Milestone 1 (M1) code drop&quot; according to TG Daily with a version number of 6.1.6519.1. It was sent to key Microsoft partners by January 2008 in both [[x86]] and [[x86-64]] versions.&lt;ref name=&quot;tgdailym1&quot;&gt;{{cite web|first=Wolfgang|last=Gruener|url=http://www.tgdaily.com/content/view/35641/118/|title=TG Daily - Windows Vista successor scheduled for a H2 2009 release?|publisher=TG Daily|date=2008-01-16|accessdate=2008-01-17}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.techradar.com/news/software/operating-systems/windows-7-set-for-late-2009-release-201142|title=Windows 7 set for late 2009 release|author=Dan Graham|date=2008-01-18|accessdate=2008-01-18}}&lt;/ref&gt; Build 6519 was the first build to have textures of a different taskbar, although nobody knew until recently how to enable the new taskbar.&lt;ref&gt;[http://withinwindows.com/img/6519_superbar.png ]{{dead link|date=June 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; Though not yet commented on by [[Microsoft]], reviews and screenshots have been published by various sources.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.tgdaily.com/content/view/35814/140/|title=More Windows 7 screenshots surfacing|accessdate=2008-01-28}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.thinknext.net/archives/2150 ThinkNext.net: Screenshots from a blogger with Windows 7 M1]&lt;/ref&gt; The M1 code drop installation comes as either a standalone install or one which requires Windows Vista with [[Windows Vista Service Pack 1|Service Pack 1]], and creates a dual-boot system.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.tgdaily.com/content/view/35936/140/ TG Daily: Windows 7 M1: Nothing to get excited about]&lt;/ref&gt; It had the ability to visually pin and unpin items from the Start Menu.

On 20 April 2008, screenshots and videos of a second build of M1 were leaked with a version number of 6.1.6574.1. This build included changes to Windows Explorer as well as a new Windows Health Center.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://news.softpedia.com/news/Leaked-Details-of-Windows-7-M1-March-2008-Edition-Version-6-1-Build-6574-1-83964.shtml|title=Leaked Details of Windows 7 M1 March 2008 Edition Version 6.1 Build 6574.1|accessdate=2008-04-24}}&lt;/ref&gt;

====Milestone 2====

According to the TG Daily article of 16 January 2008, the Milestone 2 (M2) code drop was at that time scheduled for April or May 2008.&lt;ref name=&quot;tgdailym1&quot;/&gt; A Milestone 2 build was demonstrated at the D6 conference&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.engadget.com/2008/05/27/live-from-d-gates-and-ballmer-debut-windows-7/|title=Gates and Ballmer debut Windows 7|date=2008-05-27|accessdate=2008-05-31|publisher=engadget}}&lt;/ref&gt; with a build number of 6.1.6589.1.winmain_win7m2.080420-1634. The build had a different taskbar than found in Windows Vista, with, among other features, sections divided into different colors. The host declined to comment on it, stating &quot;I'm not supposed to talk about it now today&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.istartedsomething.com/20080529/evolution-of-taskbar-windows-7/|accessdate=2008-06-27|title=Evolution of the taskbar in Windows 7 - &quot;Superbar&quot;}}&lt;/ref&gt; The taskbar in Milestone 2 showed the total number of combined windows like Windows XP and Windows Vista, a feature which was removed in the final version of Windows 7.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.withinwindows.com/2009/07/29/the-unseen-evolution-of-the-windows-7-taskbar/ The unseen evolution of the Windows 7 Taskbar]&lt;/ref&gt;

====Milestone 3====

According to [[Paul Thurrott]], Milestone 3 (build 6780) was shipped to Microsoft employees and close partners in the week of 7 September 2008. Described as visually and functionally similar to Windows Vista by Mary Jo Foley of ZDNet&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://blogs.zdnet.com/microsoft/?p=1590 |title=Windows 7 hits Milestone 3|publisher=ZDNet.com}}&lt;/ref&gt; and Stephen Chapman of UX Evangelist,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://uxevangelist.blogspot.com/2008/09/windows-7-paint-and-wordpad-new-ui-new.html |title=Windows 7 Paint and WordPad: New UI, New Functionality}}&lt;/ref&gt; some bundled applications in Milestone 3 now use a [[Ribbon (computing)|ribbon interface]] similar to that of [[Office 2007]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://windowsitpro.com/windowspaulthurrott/article/articleid/100295/ahead-of-pdc-microsoft-begins-internal-test-of-windows-7.html|title=Ahead of PDC, Microsoft Begins Internal Test of Windows 7|date=2008-09-14|accessdate=2008-09-15|publisher=Paul Thurrott}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Many applications that had been integrated into previous versions of Windows have been removed, including Calendar, Contacts, Mail, Meeting Space, Movie Maker, and Photo Gallery and are available as downloads in the [[Windows Live]] Wave 3 beta release.&lt;ref name=&quot;thinknext.net&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.thinknext.net/archives/2268 |title=Windows 7 M3 Build 6780 Pictures and Video|publisher=Thinknext.net}}&lt;/ref&gt; WinFuture.de later leaked 192 images of Windows 7 build 6780.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://winfuture.de/screenshots/Windows-7-Meilenstein-3-Build-6.1.6780-3500-1.html |title=Windows 7 Meilenstein 3 Build 6.1.6780 Screenshots and Photos|publisher=WinFuture.de}}&lt;/ref&gt; Windows 7 build 6780 Enterprise Edition has since been leaked to the public.

===Pre-Beta===

&lt;!--Build 6801 does contain the string winmain_win7m3, and is therefore milestone 3! --&gt;
On 8 October 2008, screenshots of Windows 7 build 6801 were leaked.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://winfuture.de/screenshots/Windows-7-Meilenstein-3-Build-6.1.6801-3540-1.html |title=Windows 7 Meilenstein 3 Build 6.1.6801 Screenshots and Photos|publisher=WinFuture.de}}&lt;/ref&gt; On 28 October 2008, Microsoft distributed Pre-Beta build 6801 (also known as the PDC build) x86 and x64 to attendees at its [[Professional Developers Conference]] (PDC).&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.ditii.com/2008/10/29/windows-7-media-center-features-in-pdc-build-6801-of-windows-7/|title=Windows 7 Media Center Features in PDC Build 6801 of Windows 7|date=2008-10-29|accessdate=2008-11-07|publisher=D' Technology Weblog}}&lt;/ref&gt; It has since been leaked to bittorrent networks.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.idm.net.au/story.asp?id=16324|title=Windows 7 Pre-Beta Hits Bittorrent|date=2008-11-04|accessdate=2008-11-04}} {{Dead link|date=October 2010|bot=H3llBot}}&lt;/ref&gt; It features an enhanced taskbar similar to the one in build 6933 although it is disabled by default. An unofficial patch has been released to enable the new taskbar and other hidden features in build 6801.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.withinwindows.com/2008/12/09/blue-badge-rev-3-adds-registry-override-bits-aero-peek-enabled/|title=Blue Badge rev. 3 adds registry override bits, &quot;Aero Peek&quot; enabled|date=2008-10-28|accessdate=2008-10-28|publisher=withinwindows}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.doeswhat.com/tutorialwhat/unlocking-special-features-and-taskbar-removing-30-day-trial-and-watermark-on-windows-7-build-6801/|title=Unlocking special features and taskbar, removing 30 day trial and watermark on Windows 7 (build 6801)|date=2008-11-06|accessdate=2008-11-06|publisher=DoesWhat (Tutorial What)}}&lt;/ref&gt; The glass window borders in Windows 7 build 6801 have a different blending style, making the colors behind them more saturated. This was removed in build 7000. Also, other features that were present in build 6801 have been removed in later builds like Accelerators, RSS-feed wallpapers and Pen and Touch panning.
&lt;!--Build 6933 and above does not contain the string winmain_win7m3, and is therefore not milestone 3.--&gt;
Microsoft also demonstrated build 6933.winmain.081020-1842 during the PDC, but did not give it to attendees.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://neowin.net/news/live/08/10/28/introducing-the-windows-7-ui|title=Introducing the Windows 7 UI|date=2008-10-28|accessdate=2008-10-28|publisher=Tom Warren}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;!--According to http://www.winsupersite.com/win7/win7_m3_screens.asp there are two new builds: the one distributed at PDC (build 6801) and one that was only demonstrated (build 6933). Be sure not to get these confused when writing and adding references.--&gt; On 14 November 2008, screenshots of Windows 7 build 6936 were leaked by Winfuture.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://winfuture.de/screenshots/Windows-7-Build-6.1.6936-3640-1.html |title=Windows 7 Meilenstein Build 6.1.6936 Screenshots and Photos|publisher=WinFuture.de}}&lt;/ref&gt; On 20 November 2008, Microsoft posted screenshots of build 6948 on the Engineering Windows 7 blog.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://blogs.msdn.com/e7/archive/2008/11/20/happy-anniversary-windows-on-the-evolution-of-the-taskbar.aspx|title=Engineering Windows 7: The Windows 7 Taskbar|date=2008-11-20|2008-11-22|publisher=Microsoft|author=Chaitanya}}&lt;/ref&gt; In early December, WinFuture.de leaked screenshots of build 6956, which demonstrated a new bootscreen (since build 6954) and several improvements.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://winfuture.de/screenshots/Windows-7-Build-6.1.6956-3664-1.html|title=Windows 7 Meilenstein Build 6.1.6956 Screenshots and Photos|publisher=WinFuture.de}}&lt;/ref&gt; At WinHEC in China, screenshots of build 6951 were leaked and an attendee leaked Windows 7 build 6956 x86.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://windows7center.com/windows-7-news/windows-7-build-6956-leaked-by-attendee-at-winhec-china/#more-955|title=Windows 7 Build 6956 leaked by an attendee at WinHEC China|publisher=Windows7Center.com}}&lt;/ref&gt; Paul Thurrott has posted several screenshots on his website of another build from the 69xx range.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.winsupersite.com/win7/win7_m3_69xx.asp|title=Windows 7 Build 69xx Screenshots|publisher=WinSuperSite.com}}&lt;/ref&gt; On December 10, 2008, Windows 7 build 6936 x64 leaked to the Internet.

===Beta===

[[Image:Windows 7 Beta.png|thumb|right|Windows 7 Beta]]

On December 23, 2008, screenshots of the Windows 7 beta (build 7000) were leaked.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://winfuture.de/screenshots/Windows-7-Build-6.1.7000-Beta-1-%28Englisch%29-3699-1.html|title= Windows 7 Build 6.1.7000 Beta 1 (English)|publisher=Winfuture.de}}&lt;/ref&gt; On December 27, the x86 version of Windows 7 Beta build 7000 leaked and quickly spread to torrent sites, and many FTPs. On 5 January 2009, the 64-bit version of the Windows 7 Beta (build 7000) was leaked onto the web.

The Windows 7 Beta was released on January 7, 2009 to TechNet and MSDN subscribers.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://windowsteamblog.com/blogs/windows7/archive/2009/01/07/information-on-downloading-and-installing-windows-7-beta.aspx|title=Windows 7 Team Blog Information on Downloading and Installing Windows 7 Beta|first=2009-01-07|accessdate=2009-01-08}}&lt;/ref&gt; On January 10, after a short delay due to overwhelming demand, both 32 and 64-bit versions of the Beta were made available to the public until the 10th of February. The build number is 7000.winmain_win7beta.081212-1400.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.computerworld.com/action/article.do?command=viewArticleBasic&amp;articleId=9126739|title=Microsoft Extends Windows 7 Beta Availability}}&lt;/ref&gt; Existing installations of the beta continued to operate until August 1, 2009 with bi-hourly shutdowns beginning July 1.

===Pre-Release Candidate===

On February 8, 2009, build 7022 x86 of Windows 7 was leaked to file sharing sites on the Internet by a Microsoft Ukraine employee.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.neowin.net/news/main/09/02/08/windows-7-build-7022-leaks|title=Windows 7 build 7022 leaks|publisher=Neowin|author=Tom Warren}}&lt;/ref&gt; On March 1, 2009, build 7022 x64 was leaked. Reviewers have noted that [[Internet Explorer 8]] had been updated to RC1, a few new icons, new animation effects for Windows Desktop Gadgets with new icons and changes to Paint and a faster setup process. The build was completed on January 15, 2009.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://arstechnica.com/microsoft/news/2009/02/whats-new-in-the-leaked-windows-7-build-7022.ars|title=What's new in the leaked Windows 7 build 7022|publisher=Ars Technica|author=Emil Protalinski}}&lt;/ref&gt;

A 64-bit build 7048 was leaked on March 2, 2009&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://windows7center.com/windows-7-news/windows-7-build-7048-x64-download-leaked/ | title = Windows 7 Build 7048 x64 Download Leaked&amp;nbsp;- Windows 7 Center}}&lt;/ref&gt; and the 32-bit build 7048 was leaked on March 6. One notable change of this build was that users now had the ability to turn off functionality of various Windows features, like Internet Explorer, Windows Search, and Windows Media Player via the Control Panel. Ars Technica did a roundup of some of the visual UI changes between build 7000 and 7048 &lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://arstechnica.com/microsoft/news/2009/03/side-by-side-changes-from-windows-7-beta-to-build-7048.ars/|title=Side by side: UI changes from Windows 7 beta to build 7048|publisher=Ars Technica|author=Emil Protalinski}}&lt;/ref&gt; and ZDNet managed to do some performance tests showing build 7048 was superior to build 7000.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://blogs.zdnet.com/hardware/?p=3789|title=Windows 7 build 7048 vs. Windows 7 beta 1 vs. Vista vs. XP performance shootout - which is best?|publisher=ZDNet|author=Adrian Kingsley-Hughes}}&lt;/ref&gt;

On February 26, 2009, Microsoft announced 36 major user-visible changes to Windows 7 since the Beta.&lt;ref name=&quot;RCchanges&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://blogs.msdn.com/e7/archive/2009/02/26/some-changes-since-beta.aspx|title=Some Changes Since Beta for RC|author=Engineering Windows 7}}&lt;/ref&gt; On March 6, 2009, Microsoft announced that users would have the ability to turn off even more features than in Windows Vista. Some programs users would be able to turn off included [[Windows Media Player]], [[Windows Media Center]], Internet Explorer 8, [[Windows Search]], and the Windows Gadget Platform.&lt;ref name=&quot;Engineering Windows 7&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://blogs.msdn.com/e7/archive/2009/03/06/beta-to-rc-changes-turning-windows-features-on-or-off.aspx|title=Beta to RC Changes - Turning Windows Features On or Off}}&lt;/ref&gt;

On March 11, 2009, build 7057 x86 was leaked and on March 13, 2009, the x64 version was leaked. Build 7057 was compiled on March 5, 2009.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://arstechnica.com/microsoft/news/2009/03/side-by-side-ui-changes-from-windows-7-beta-to-build-7057.ars|title=Side by side: UI changes from Windows 7 beta to build 7057|publisher=Ars Technica|author=Emil Protalinski}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Build 7068 was compiled on March 21, 2009, and was available to select Microsoft Connect testers.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://windows7center.com/windows-7-news/windows-7-build-7068-released-on-connect-today/|title=Windows 7 Build 7068 spotted on Connect today|publisher=Windows 7 Center}}&lt;/ref&gt; On March 27, 2009, build 7068 x86 was leaked and on March 28, 2009, the x64 version was leaked. Cnet journalist Rory Gee noted  on a significant decrease of system resources to use build 7068. 

On April 7, 2009, the 32-bit version of build 7077, an RC escrow build,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.neowin.net/news/main/09/04/08/windows-7-build-7077-leaks|title=Windows 7 build 7077 leaks|publisher=Neowin|author=Tom Warren}}&lt;/ref&gt; was leaked.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://arstechnica.com/microsoft/news/2009/04/first-screenshots-of-build-windows-7-build-7077-leak.ars|title=First screenshots of build Windows 7 build 7077 leak|publisher=Ars Technica|author=Emil Protalinski}}&lt;/ref&gt; and the x64 version was leaked two days later, on April 9, 2009.

===Release Candidate===
[[File:Windows 7 RC.png|thumb|right|Windows 7 Release Candidate]]
The Windows Team Blog announced on April 24, 2009 that the Release Candidate would be available to MSDN and TechNet subscribers on April 30 and to the public on May 5. The release candidate was also reportedly given to OEM partners and TAP gold testers. 

The Release Candidate, build 7100.0.winmain_win7rc.090421-1700 was leaked to popular file sharing networks in both x86 and x64 editions on April 24, 2009. 

On Thursday, August 20, 2009, the Windows 7 Release Candidate download was removed from Microsoft's website. Product keys for the Release Candidate were available until October 21, 2009.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.microsoft.com/windows/windows-7/get/download.aspx|title=Windows 7 Release Candidate (RC) Download Is No Longer Available|publisher=Microsoft|author=Microsoft}}&lt;/ref&gt;

On March 1, 2010, computers running Windows 7 Release Candidate started shutting down bihourly, and on June 1 the release candidate expired.

On May 26, an update with 31 languages was available to download through Windows Update.

===Pre-Release to manufacturing===
On April 12, 2009, build 7106 leaked in both x86 and x64 in the Chinese language. On April 13, Language Packs for 7106 x86 and x64 for the English language were leaked.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://windows7center.com/news/windows-7-build-7106-x86-english-leaks-kinda/|title=Windows 7 Build 7106 x86 English Leaks (kinda)|publisher=Windows 7 Center}}&lt;/ref&gt; Build 7106 was compiled before build 7077 from the RC branch.

Build 7127.0.winmain.090507-1820, built on May 7, 2009, is available to selected Microsoft Connect testers.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://news.softpedia.com/news/Windows-7-Build-7127-Is-Live-111552.shtml|title=Windows 7 Build 7127 Is Live - Forget about 7100 - Softpedia|date=2009-05-13|accessdate=2009-05-14|publisher=Softpedia|author=Marius Oiaga}}&lt;/ref&gt;  The 32-bit and 64-bit versions of this build were also leaked to torrent sites on May 14, 2009.

Build 7137.0.winmain.090521-1745, built on May 21, 2009, leaked on May 28 in both x86 and x64 versions.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.neowin.net/news/main/09/05/28/windows-7-build-7137-leaked |title=Windows 7 build 7137 leaked |publisher=Neowin.net |date=2009-05-28 |accessdate=2011-06-15}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Build 7201, built on June 1, 2009, leaked on June 3 in both x86 and x64 versions.

Build 7229.0.winmain.090604-1901, built on June 4, 2009, leaked on June 11 in both x86 and x64 versions. Language packs for the build are also available on torrent sites.

Build 7231.0.winmain.090608-1900, built on June 8, 2009, leaked on June 11 in x86 VHD format.

Build 7232.0.winmain.090610-1900, built on June 10, 2009, leaked on June 14 in x64 VHD format. Unlike previously leaked builds, this build has a [http://www.winsupersite.com/images/win7/win7_7232_02.jpg new wallpaper] that replaces the &lt;!-- &quot;betta&quot; is not a spelling error --&gt;[[betta]] fish wallpaper, which was the default wallpaper in the Beta and Release Candidate.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://news.softpedia.com/news/Windows-7-Build-7232-Close-to-RTM-Escrow-114232.shtml |title=Windows 7 Build 7232 Close to RTM Escrow - Softpedia |publisher=News.softpedia.com |date=2009-06-15 |accessdate=2011-06-15}}&lt;/ref&gt; 

Build 7260.0.win7_rtm.090612-2110, built on June 12, 2009, leaked on June 17 in x86 VHD format.

Build 7264.0.win7_rtm.090622-1900, built on June 22, 2009, leaked on June 30, 2009 in both x86 and x64 versions. Language packs for the build are also available on torrent sites.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://news.softpedia.com/news/Windows-7-Build-7264-Leaked-and-Available-for-Download-115499.shtml |title=Windows 7 Build 7264 Leaked and Available for Download - Softpedia |publisher=News.softpedia.com |date= |accessdate=2011-06-15}}&lt;/ref&gt;

====Build 7600.16384====
Build 7600.16384.win7_rtm.090710-1945, built on July 10, 2009, leaked on July 12, 2009 in both x86 and x64 versions;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://news.softpedia.com/news/Windows-7-RTM-Build-7600-Leaked-and-Available-for-Download-116499.shtml |title=Windows 7 RTM Build 7600 Leaked and Available for Download - Softpedia |publisher=News.softpedia.com |date= |accessdate=2011-06-15}}&lt;/ref&gt; a Chinese individual uploaded an [[OEM]] copy of Windows 7 Ultimate build 7600, reportedly given to [[Lenovo]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url = http://www.mydigitallife.info/2009/07/13/download-windows-7-rtm-build-7600-16384-x64-64-bit-iso-images | title = Download Windows 7 RTM Build 7600.16384 x64 (64-bit) ISO Images | author = My Digital Life}}&lt;/ref&gt; The disc image contained the crucial boot.wim file given to PC manufacturers to pre-activate PCs at the factory. The file contains both the OEM activation certificate and the product key.

In a recent blog post, however, Genuine Windows director Alex Kochis stated that the product key is indeed valid but will only activate PCs from the original manufacturer it has been given to.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url = http://blogs.msdn.com/wga/archive/2009/07/30/windows-7-oem-product-key-leak.aspx | title = Windows 7 OEM Product Key Leak | author = Alex Kochis}}&lt;/ref&gt; Kochis went on to say that anti-piracy technologies built into the operating system would detect copies activated with the leaked OEM certificate and product key as non-genuine and would notify the customer that they are running a possibly counterfeit copy of Windows.

It has already been proven however, that the product key and certificate are able to activate Windows 7 build 7600 on many different PC brands.&lt;ref name=&quot;OEMLeak&quot;&gt;{{cite web| url = http://scforum.info/index.php/topic,3057.msg6900.html | title = Windows 7 Ultimate hacked with OEM master key (boot.wim, .xrm-ms, OEM-SLP key) | author = Samker}}&lt;/ref&gt; It is not clear however, if copies of Windows installed this way will pass Microsoft's Genuine Advantage check if the product key is blacklisted. If so, OEMs will be forced to recollect PCs manufactured, installed and activated with the key and install different keys.

[[File:Windows 7.png|thumb|right|Windows 7 build 7600&lt;!--I, Josh the Nerd, am pretty sure this is 7600.16384, not 7600.16385, which is RTM, because 7600.16385 apparently leaked on July 16, but the screenshot was uploaded on July 14. Therefore, it should not say that it is 7600.16385 or RTM.--&gt;]]&lt;!--Please move the image and update the caption rather than just removing the image next time.--&gt;

===Release to manufacturing===
The final RTM build of Windows 7 has a build string of 7600.16385.win7_rtm.090713-1255, built on July 13, 2009.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url = http://www.neowin.net/news/main/09/07/22/microsoft-announces-windows-7-rtm-at-mgx | title = Microsoft announces Windows 7 RTM, MGX details | author = Tom Warren }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url = http://windowsteamblog.com/blogs/windows7/archive/2009/07/22/windows-7-has-been-released-to-manufacturing.aspx | title = Windows 7 Has Been Released to Manufacturing | author = Brandon LeBlanc}}&lt;/ref&gt; It leaked in both x86 and x64 versions. On July 24, 2009 Microsoft released Windows 7 to OEMs (original equipment manufacturers and system builders) online, followed by MSDN and TechNet Subscribers via download and Microsoft Connect on August 6, 2009. Since the next day, August 7, 2009, companies which bought Software Assurance have been able to download Windows 7 RTM.

Since August 16, 2009, Windows 7 is available to Microsoft Certified and Gold Certified Partners, followed by Microsoft Action Pack subscribers on August 23. Microsoft has also announced that companies which have a  contract with Software Assurance may acquire Windows 7 when it became available for volume licensing on September 1, 2009. Windows 7 was released to consumers on October 22, 2009.

Language Packs for Windows 7 RTM are available via Windows Update since August 25, 2009.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url = http://windowsteamblog.com/blogs/springboard/archive/2009/08/25/windows-7-language-packs-available.aspx | title = Windows 7 Language Packs Available | author = Stephen L Rose}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Service Packs==
&lt;!--ATTENTION: Please do not remove the Pre-Service Pack 1 section. It is not too early to write about these builds which are in existence. See the discussion page.--&gt;

===Pre-Beta Service Pack 1===
Build 7138.0.winmain_sp.090523-2200, built on May 23, 2009, is the first known Service Pack 1 build. This build belongs to the winmain_sp branch, which incorporates preliminary changes as a Service Pack 1 build.

Build 7227.0.winmain_sp.090602-2110, built on June 2, 2009, was leaked on June 9 in x86 VHD formats.

Build 7230.0.winmain_sp.090607-2000, built on June 7, 2009, is the last known Service Pack 1 build prior to the RTM release.

Build 7601.16485.winmain_sp.100114-1500, built on January 14, 2010, is the final Service Pack 1 build in the winmain_sp branch.

Build 7601.16518.100302-1530, built on March 2, 2010, is the pre-beta build for Service Pack 1.

===Service Pack 1 Beta===
Build 7601.16562.100603-1800, built on June 3, 2010, is the Beta release for Service Pack 1.

Build 7601.17077.100813-0322, v.693, built on August 13, 2010, is the Beta refresh release for Service Pack 1 and the new internet browser made by [[Microsoft]] is [[Internet Explorer 9]] .

===Service Pack 1 Release Candidate===
Build 7601.17105.100929-1730, built on September 29, 2010, is the RC release for Service Pack 1.

===Service Pack 1 Pre-RTM===
Build 7601.17125.101210-1930, v.741; compiled on December 10, 2010 was leaked on December 28, 2010.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://news.softpedia.com/news/Windows-7-SP1-pre-RTM-Build-7601-171257-Leaked-and-Available-for-Download-175000.shtml |title=Windows 7 SP1 pre-RTM Build 7601.171257 Leaked and Available for Download - Softpedia |publisher=News.softpedia.com |date= |accessdate=2011-06-15}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Service Pack 1 RTM===
On February 9, 2011, Microsoft officially released the final release (RTM) of Windows 7 and Windows Server 2008 R2 Service Pack 1 (SP1) to OEM partners. As of February 16th Windows 7 and Windows Server 2008 R2 SP1 have been available for MSDN and TechNet Subscribers as well as Volume License customers. As of February 22nd, Windows 7 and Windows Server 2008 R2 SP1 has been generally available for download via the Microsoft Download Center and available on Windows Update. It has a version number of &quot;6.1.7601.17514.101119-1850&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://windowsteamblog.com/windows/b/bloggingwindows/archive/2011/02/09/announcing-availability-of-windows-7-and-windows-server-2008-r2-sp1.aspx |title=Announcing Availability of Windows 7 and Windows Server 2008 R2 SP1 |publisher=Windowsteamblog.com |date= |accessdate=2011-06-15}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==See also==

* [[Development of Windows 98]]
* [[Development of Windows XP]]
* [[Development of Windows Vista]]
* [[History of Microsoft Windows]]

==References==

{{reflist|2}}

==External links==
* [http://www.microsoft.com/windows/windows-7/ Windows 7 official website]
* [http://social.technet.microsoft.com/Forums/en-US/category/w7itpro/ Windows 7 Beta Forums on Microsoft TechNet]
* [http://technet.microsoft.com/en-us/windows/dd361745.aspx?ITPID=tnforum/ Springboard Series for Windows 7 on Microsoft TechNet]

{{Microsoft Windows family}}

[[bg:Разработване на Windows 7]]
[[es:Anexo:Desarrollo de Windows 7]]
[[pl:Rozwój Windows 7]]
[[pt:Desenvolvimento do Windows 7]]
[[ru:Разработка Windows 7]]
[[zh:Windows 7开发历史]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
