<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="2040038" ns="0" title="Ori (Stargate)"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{redirect|Orisi|the Italian wine grape that is also known as Orisi bianca|Vespaiola}}
The '''Ori''' ({{IPAc-en|icon|ˈ|ɒr|aɪ}})&lt;ref name=decisions /&gt; are [[fictional character]]s in the [[science fiction]] [[television series]], ''[[Stargate SG-1]]''. They are a group of &quot;[[Ascension (Stargate)|ascended]]&quot; beings who use their advanced technology and knowledge of the universe to attempt to trick non-ascended humans into worshipping them as gods.

They first appeared in the ninth season of ''Stargate SG-1'', replacing the [[Goa'uld]] as the show's primary antagonists. While the Goa'uld relied on stolen technology from other civilizations to pose as gods, the Ori also have [[paranormal]] abilities in addition to very advanced technology. As Ascended beings, they live on a higher plane of existence with great power and knowledge and are as close to being &quot;gods&quot; as any non-deific being can be.&lt;ref name=&quot;Origin&quot;&gt;&quot;[[Origin (Stargate SG-1)|Origin]]&quot; (''[[Stargate SG-1]]'')&lt;/ref&gt;
The Ori fabricated a religion called Origin, which they use in an attempt to control non-ascended beings. The Ori also attempt to destroy any planets and civilizations that reject Origin. A central theme in the show is that power does not make someone a god nor entitle them to be worshipped; rather, the way they use great power is the measure of how they should be honored.

==Concept and creation==
===Genesis===
Since the eighth season of ''Stargate SG-1'' was intended to be the last, the producers finished it with the defeat of the [[Goa'uld]] and [[Replicator (Stargate)|Replicator]]s. When the [[Sci Fi Channel (United States)|Sci Fi Channel]] renewed the series, however, the producers had grown creatively tired of writing endings. Having had good experiences with the first season of ''[[Stargate Atlantis]]'', the producers hence decided to revamp the series in more fronts than just adding new characters by introducing new villains and new missions. Thus they considered the beginning of Season 9 as the pilot of a new show.&lt;ref name=tvzones64_24&gt;{{Cite news |last=Eramo |first=Steven |author-link= | title=Stargate SG-1 Season 9 preview - Nine Lives |newspaper=[[TV Zone]] |issue=Special #64 |pages=24&amp;ndash;30; 44&amp;ndash;48 56&amp;ndash;60 |date=July 2005 |postscript=&lt;!--None--&gt;}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Season Nine was about wiping the slate clean and resetting the story to where ''Stargate SG-1'' was in its first season.&lt;ref name=directing /&gt; The reason was that the SG-1 team was now winning every time, having already defeated the main enemies the previous season.&lt;ref name=directing /&gt; Since ''SG-1'' had always been grounded in Earth mythology, the producers chose the [[King Arthur]]  mythology for the new season as that had not been done before. Merlin as a famous magical figure was made an Ancient, leading to the Ancients' enemies named the Ori.&lt;ref name=tvzones64_24 /&gt; The Ori are thus &quot;a natural extension of where the Ancient mythology had gone.&quot;&lt;ref name=mythmaker /&gt; Up until that point, the story of the Ancients had been kept at arm's length because the show was not about the aliens but &quot;human beings going out into this unexplored, fantastical universe.&quot;&lt;ref name=mythmaker /&gt; The producers also acknowledged that a premature full revelation of the Ancients would have caused their story to be less interesting.&lt;ref name=mythmaker /&gt;

Producer [[Brad Wright]] believed the Ori are still within the overriding theme of Stargate, as they are &quot;aliens playing gods&quot; and &quot;false gods&quot; and the relationship between aliens as gods and ordinary human folk.&lt;ref name=decisions&gt;{{cite web |last=Sumner |first=Darren |url=http://www.gateworld.net/interviews/executive_decisions_part_1.shtml |title=Executive Decisions &amp;ndash; GateWorld talks with Brad Wright and Robert C. Cooper |publisher=gateworld.net |month=July | year=2005 |accessdate=2008-03-05}}&lt;/ref&gt; The introduction of the Ori was to prepare the viewer for their invasion and overtaking that would take place later.&lt;ref name=directing /&gt; The Ori also served as a challenge for the new heroes in the SG-1 team (Mitchell, Landry, Vala).&lt;ref name=directing /&gt; The writers believed that new bad guys and new obstacles for the characters to overcome would make for a more interesting story.&lt;ref name=directing /&gt;

The name &quot;Ori&quot; comes from the word &quot;Origin&quot;, as in the origin of the Ancients.&lt;ref name=decisions /&gt; When Cooper looked at the root of &quot;origin&quot;, he retcon-invented the word &quot;Origin&quot; as the name of the Ori religion.&lt;ref name=decisions /&gt; Cooper said it was an interesting idea for him to address the philosophical arguments with various religious people, seeing the whole challenge as &quot;how do you prove whose God exists or whether God exists at all?&quot;&lt;ref name=newdirections /&gt; Instead of the Goa'uld, who were proved quickly to not be gods by killing them and figuring out their technology, it would be hard to present the same argument to the Ori followers because the Ori were essentially ascended gods.&lt;ref name=newdirections /&gt; Even if their gods were dead, it would not make much difference for them, as their followers would continue to believe; without the &quot;magic powers&quot; of the Ori, their followers and the [[#Priors|Priors]] (the Ori's missionaries) could still use the technology and their ships.&lt;ref name=newdirections /&gt; Cooper said that &quot;it's not necessarily wrong to believe in something ... what's wrong is to murder somebody because they don't believe the way you do.&quot;&lt;ref name=newdirections /&gt; Although Cooper was reluctant to get too serious about the meaning behind the Ori as ''Stargate'' should &quot;first and foremost [...] entertain people&quot;,&lt;ref name=mythmaker /&gt; he considered it representative of television and the media,&lt;ref name=newdirections /&gt; &quot;mak[ing] people believe whatever the people in charge of that magic box &amp;ndash; whatever they want you to believe they can pretty much convince you, or convince the vast majority of people.&quot;&lt;ref name=newdirections /&gt; For Cooper, &quot;the followers of the Ori were the interesting part&quot;, and he &quot;wanted to do a story that was in some way reflective of the differences between people's beliefs that we see around us in our society, and how conflicts arise as a result of that.&quot;&lt;ref name=mythmaker&gt;{{cite web |last=Sumner |first=Darren |url=http://www.gateworld.net/interviews/myth_maker_part_1.shtml |title=Myth Maker, Part One &amp;ndash; GateWorld talks with Robert C. Cooper |publisher=gateworld.net |month=April | year=2008 |accessdate=2008-04-08}}&lt;/ref&gt; Cooper was particularly interested in the interaction between Ori followers and other normal human beings, the resulting &quot;mysterious aspect and quality to religious belief and the passion that it invokes.&quot; The producers therefore put the Ori in the story background, similar to the way there was very little direct interaction between the actual deities of the religion and mankind in real life.&lt;ref name=mythmaker /&gt;

Cooper was concerned that the distinction between the Ori and the Ori's followers was often overlooked, and that the SG-1 team dealt with the followers, not the ascended gods.&lt;ref name=newdirections /&gt; If, as {{sgcite|The Shroud}} suggested, the Ori were actually destroyed by the Merlin's Ancient weapon, the real issue for the SG-1 teams became the followers.&lt;ref name=newdirections /&gt; Brad Wright pointed to power corruption, and the catch of the Ori killing unbelievers.&lt;ref name=decisions /&gt;

===Story ideas===
In the original pitch for {{sgcite|Beachhead}}, Brad Wright had intended to let Ori build the Supergate and come through. It was then decided among the writers to only let the threat of the Ori come through the Priors, and wait for the Ori arrival until the end of the season.&lt;ref name=ontarget /&gt;

The last ten minutes of &quot;Camelot&quot; should serve as a &quot;great, ominous harbinger of the foe&quot; SG-1 is up against.&lt;ref name=directing /&gt; In Season 10, the Ori  sweep through the [[Milky Way galaxy]], forcing SG-1 to start from scratch again to find technology, resources, and allies to fight against them.&lt;ref name=directing /&gt;

If ''Stargate SG-1'' had gone on, the producers would have considered the search for the Ark (of ''[[Stargate: The Ark of Truth]]'') as the overriding story for an eleventh season, similar to the Sangraal in seasons nine and ten. The producers did not explore more detailed ideas after the show's cancellation.&lt;ref name=mythmaker /&gt;

===Design===
Art director James Robbins developed the design of the Ori and the Priors from scratch. At the beginning he knew a basic description of them and their powers, and that they would carry a staff weapon. The art department first looked at Japanese and Samurai from a costuming point of view. Inspired by remote jungle tribes for the mystical aspects, Robbins came up with the idea of [[scarification]] for the Priors and the Doci. The Priors have scarifications on the chin and the cheek, while the Doci also have them on their forehead. Scarification would therefore be a symbol of high establishment. Originally, it was also considered to have scarification on the hands, and to have the Priors have finger extensions, but this became too impracticable.&lt;ref name=tvzones64_24 /&gt; When the Prime Jaffa [[Gerak]] became a Prior in {{sgcite|The Fourth Horseman}}, his golden Jaffa tattoo on his forehead was replaced with a Prior scarification, and his makeup was made to look like the gold had melted and become part of his Prior scarification.&lt;ref name=tvzones67_6 /&gt;

Each Prior was given his own unique symbol, which he would wear on his wardrobe and also on his staff weapon. The art department built each staff to have a little orb encased in natural wood, and the orbs start to glow when the actor pushes a little button on the handle.&lt;ref name=tvzones64_24 /&gt;

===Music===
Composer Joel Goldsmith's inspiration for the Ori themes were the &quot;certain parallels to what's happening today, in modern day&quot;. He admits that the music of the Ori was intentionally given a gothic, Gregorian and Christian feel. He tried to meld a few different styles.&lt;ref name=joel&gt;{{cite web |last=Read |first=David |url=http://www.gateworld.net/interviews/gate_harmonics_part_1_of_2.shtml |title=Gate Harmonics &amp;ndash; GateWorld talks with Joel Goldsmith |publisher=gateworld.net |month=November | year=2006 |accessdate=2008-03-05}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Mythology of the Ori and the Ancients==

The Ori backstory is elaborate and is explained over Season 9 and 10 and the film ''[[Stargate: The Ark of Truth]]''. Robert C. Cooper considered the backstory &quot;pretty complicated&quot; but felt the show gave the answers to the audience members who wanted to delve deeper.&lt;ref name=mythmaker2 /&gt;

Part of this story returns to the Ancients, whose backstory began in the Season 1 episode {{sgcite|The Torment of Tantalus}}. Early in Season 9, Brad Wright explained that the Ori are the original Ancients, who would disagree with the Alterans (later to relocate and be known as the Ancients of the [[Milky Way]] [[galaxy]]) that they shouldn't interfere because interference would mean playing god, which these beings hadn't quite achieved.&lt;ref name=decisions /&gt;

The Ori and the Alterans&lt;ref name=newdirections /&gt; were one race millions of years ago and lived in a single society on an evolutionary path to ascension.&lt;ref name=&quot;The Fourth Horseman&quot; /&gt; ''The Ark of Truth'' shows flashbacks to human Ancients coexisting with the people who eventually became the Ori. However, a philosophical division emerged. The Ori grew more and more fervent in their religious belief, while the Alterans adopted a more scientific/rational outlook to become a more progressive society.&lt;ref name=newdirections /&gt; The Ancients were well known for their fierce belief in [[free will]]&lt;ref name=&quot;Threads&quot;&gt;&quot;[[Threads (Stargate SG-1)|Threads]]&quot; (''[[Stargate SG-1]]'')&lt;/ref&gt; and had a code to be &quot;fairly non-violent&quot;.&lt;ref name=newdirections /&gt; As such, they do not interfere on lower planes of existence at all, not even to save their own kind from being exterminated by the Ori,&lt;ref name=&quot;The Pegasus Project&quot;&gt;&quot;[[The Pegasus Project (Stargate SG-1)|The Pegasus Project]]&quot; (''[[Stargate SG-1]]'')&lt;/ref&gt; or to prevent all life in the Milky Way galaxy from being exterminated by Anubis.&lt;ref name=Threads /&gt; In contrast, the Ori constantly interfere. For example, Origin states that failure to share the secrets of the universe to those on the lower planes of existence is an evil act and that anyone not following it must be eliminated; by this definition, every ascended Ancient was evil and must be destroyed. They also have no rules against taking direct control of living beings or completely changing them to behave as they desire.&lt;ref name=&quot;Origin&quot; /&gt; With the Ori outnumbering the Alterans,&lt;ref name=newdirections /&gt; their viewpoints ultimately diverged so much that the two groups split apart and began to actively oppose each other, with the Ori attempting to kill the Alterans.&lt;ref name=mythmaker2&gt;{{cite web |last=Sumner |first=Darren |url=http://www.gateworld.net/interviews/myth_maker_part_2.shtml |title=Myth Maker, Part Two &amp;ndash; GateWorld talks with Robert C. Cooper |publisher=gateworld.net |month=April | year=2008 |accessdate=2008-04-14}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Their fundamentally different beliefs in regards to science led the Alterans to hide their level of scientific belief so that they would not get into a conflict. Eventually, the Ancients decided to build a space ship and leave rather than to use their technology, like the Ark of Truth, to defeat the Ori.&lt;ref name=mythmaker2 /&gt; Though they had the ability to stop the Ori, they thought it to be philosophically and morally wrong.&lt;ref name=newdirections /&gt; The film thus addresses the non-interference policy of the Ancients under the Ori threat, and how they act since SG-1 did them a big favor by killing the Ori.&lt;ref name=newdirections /&gt;

After much time, believed by [[Daniel Jackson (Stargate)|Daniel Jackson]] to be thousands of years, the Alterans discovered the [[Milky Way]], where they eventually built their empire. However, even after the Ori had forced the Alterans to leave their galaxy, the two factions remained bitter enemies. Eventually, the Alterans were afflicted with a terrible plague that wiped out most of their civilization.&lt;ref name=&quot;Window of Opportunity&quot;&gt;&quot;[[Window of Opportunity (Stargate SG-1)|Window of Opportunity]]&quot; (''[[Stargate SG-1]]'')&lt;/ref&gt; It would later be discovered that what was known of this plague is very similar to the disease used by Ori [[Prior (Stargate)|Priors]] against non-believers, which had led Daniel Jackson to speculate that the pre-Ascended Ori might have been responsible for this plague.&lt;ref name=&quot;The Powers That Be&quot;&gt;&quot;[[The Powers That Be (Stargate SG-1)|The Powers That Be]]&quot; (''[[Stargate SG-1]]'')&lt;/ref&gt;

After millions of years, both the Alterans and the Ori learned how to ascend and evolved,&lt;ref name=mythmaker2 /&gt; forming two groups that continued to oppose each other, even at the higher planes of existence. According to the Orici Adria, the Ori-Ancient war on the Ascended plane is due to the Ancients' intolerance for those who do not comply with their rules about non-interference.&lt;ref name=&quot;The Shroud&quot;&gt;&quot;[[The Shroud (Stargate SG-1)|The Shroud]]&quot; (''[[Stargate SG-1]]'')&lt;/ref&gt; According to Orlin, a de-ascended Ancient, the conflict arises from the Ori's ultimate wish to destroy the Ancients once and for all as they seek to eliminate all who oppose them.&lt;ref name=&quot;The Fourth Horseman&quot;&gt;&quot;[[The Fourth Horseman (Stargate SG-1)|The Fourth Horseman]]&quot; (''[[Stargate SG-1]]'')
* '''Orlin:''' &quot;He just told you why the Ori are on their way to this Galaxy... they're coming to destroy the Ancients.&quot;
* '''Orlin:''' &quot;A long time ago the Ori and the Alterans were one society...human on an evolutionary path to ascension... but a philosophical division grew...the Ori grew more and more fervent in their religious belief. The Alterrans, for lack of a better way of putting it, believed in science... The Ori tried to wipe them out.&quot; '''/ Daniel:''' &quot;So instead of going to war, the Alterans built a ship, left their galaxy and came here. We know that both the Alterrans and the Ori eventually ascended and that the Ori passed on their religion called Origin to the next evolution of humans they created.&quot; '''/ Orlin:''' &quot;Yes, but the central promise of the religion... everything the Origins follow... devote themselves to... is a lie.&quot;
* '''Carter:''' &quot;Are you saying there's a real physical transfer of energy to the Ori that occurs simply through a human being's belief in them?&quot; '''/ Orlin:''' &quot;[...] for it to have a measurable effect, it requires massive numbers of humans relinquishing their will... nevertheless it is one of the main reasons the Ancients have so strongly believed in strict non interference in the lower planes. [...] The Ori empower themselves by sapping the life force of those willing to surrender themselves to them.&quot;&lt;/ref&gt;

When the Ori ascended they re-created humanity (the second generation of humans) to worship them in the Ori galaxy, and gave their followers the knowledge and technology to essentially enslave others and to force them to believe as the Ori desired.&lt;ref name=mythmaker2 /&gt; The Ancients also created a new evolution of humans (i.e. current human culture) in the Milky Way and shielded them, preventing the Ori from finding out about them and enslaving the people to Origin as they had in their own galaxy. They do not view this action as a violation of their non-interference policies as the Ori are at a level equal to themselves. However, as the Ancients will not interfere in the lower planes of existence, the Ori are allowed to send their human followers to the Milky Way in order to convert it, and anyone who wishes to worship the Ori will not be prevented from doing so.&lt;ref name=&quot;Origin&quot; /&gt;

According to Orlin, ascended beings can be empowered by massive numbers of humans worshipping them. The Ori have fabricated an entire religion, named Origin, based on the false promise of [[ascension (Stargate)|ascension]] to drain power from their followers. The Ancients firmly resent using their powers this way, and therefore refrain from interfering in the lower planes of existence because manipulating and aligning lower life forms could result in exactly this type of abusive corruption.&lt;ref name=&quot;The Fourth Horseman&quot; /&gt; According to the Ancient [[Moros (Stargate)|Myrddin]], the Ori had the best intentions when they first began,&lt;ref name=&quot;The Quest&quot;&gt;&quot;[[The Quest (Stargate SG-1)|The Quest]]&quot; (''[[Stargate SG-1]]'')&lt;/ref&gt; but as evidenced on numerous occasions throughout history, power corrupts, and absolute power corrupts absolutely. The Ori were, for all intents and purposes, omnipotent and liked it. Even after they were presumably destroyed, their followers and Priors continued to use their powers and name to oppress and enslave thousands of people.

==Characteristics==
{{wikiquote|Stargate_SG-1/Ori|Ori}}
{{see also|Ori technology in Stargate}}
The Ori impose a religion called '''Origin''' on sentient beings, promising a guide towards enlightenment that is also known in the series as [[Ascension (Stargate)|Ascension]].&lt;ref name=tvzones67_6&gt;{{Cite news |last=Eramo |first=Steven |author-link= | title=SG-1 Season Nine Part 2 - Alien Siege |newspaper=[[TV Zone]] |issue=Special #67 |pages=6&amp;ndash;18 |date=December 2005 |postscript=&lt;!--None--&gt;}}&lt;/ref&gt; The faith comes with a holy book called '''The Book of Origin''', and the Priors spread the Word of Origin. ''The Book of Origin'' contains tales of how the followers of the Ori returned to the path to enlightenment, and thus achieved Ascension, although some skeptics consider these merely &quot;fables meant to fill a soul bereft of hope with purpose&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;The Fourth Horseman&quot; /&gt; Several lines from the ''Book of Origin'', or otherwise repeated mantras, are heard on the show. These include variations of &quot;Hallowed are the Ori&quot;. The central icon of this religion is fire, something that gives off light and warmth.&lt;ref name=&quot;Origin&quot;/&gt; The fact that on Earth this icon has some evil or [[Satan]]ic associations in many modern religions prompted Daniel to posit that the Ancients had influenced this negative connotation in order to identify the threat the Ori pose. Among the populations of natives in the Ori home galaxy are groups of heretics who believe they are being suppressed, and seek to discover forbidden historical knowledge to show others that the Ori, despite their power, are not gods.

Ori military tactics varied during the initial incursions into the Milky Way galaxy and the full scale invasion that was later achieved through the Supergate. The initial incursions were achieved through lone Priors who were sent to worlds in the Milky Way galaxy, preaching to the populace and distributing copies of the Book of Origin. When the people failed to comply, more drastic measures were taken, eventually to the point of destroying the population. The show features powerful Ori weapons in {{sgcite|Ethon}}, ships in {{sgcite|Camelot}}, control chairs like that in {{sgcite|Counterstrike}} and [[Supergate (Stargate)|Supergates]] in {{sgcite|Beachhead}}. The Ori can be killed by [[Ancient characters in Stargate#Moros/Merlin/Myrddin|Merlin's]] Sangraal weapon, which nullifies ascended beings.&lt;ref name=&quot;The Quest&quot;/&gt; As seen in ''The Ark of Truth'', there is also an Ark that Cooper considered &quot;a truly fascinating centerpiece&quot; and &quot;mass brain-washing device&quot; to convince people of the truth.&lt;ref name=newdirections /&gt; Comparing the Ark to television as it is &quot;a box that light comes out of, and you believe what it says&quot;, Cooper left it open whether the choice to do it without guns was ultimately the better method.&lt;ref name=mythmaker2 /&gt;

==Characters==
===Doci===
[[Image:Doci and Prior.jpg|thumb|right|The Doci (middle) amidst two Priors in the episode {{sgcite|Origin}}]]

The '''Doci''' (Latin ''docere'', &quot;to teach&quot;), played by [[Julian Sands]], represents the Ori in their home galaxy and leads the Priors.&lt;ref name=directing&gt;{{cite web |author=Sumner, Darren and Read, David |url=http://www.gateworld.net/interviews/directing_the_future.shtml |title=Directing The Future &amp;ndash; GateWorld talks with Robert C. Cooper |publisher=gateworld.net |month=April | year=2006 |accessdate=2008-03-05}}&lt;/ref&gt; He appears in &quot;[[Origin (Stargate SG-1)|Origin]]&quot;, &quot;[[The Fourth Horseman (Stargate SG-1)|The Fourth Horseman, Part 1]]&quot; and ''[[Stargate: The Ark of Truth]]''. The Doci is essentially a chief Prior who acts as a mediator or mouthpiece for the Ori. The Doci has brown hair and colored eyes, pale skin and facial markings of a Prior. The Doci was introduced in {{sgcite|Origin}}, where he was shown to reside in the city of Celestis, with his chambers next to the Ori's ''Flames of Enlightenment''. In one instance, the Ori possessed the Doci to speak to Daniel.&lt;ref name=&quot;Origin&quot;/&gt; Had Julian Sands not been able to come back as the Doci for the direct-to-DVD film ''The Ark of Truth'', the producers had planned to hire another actor as a different Doci in charge in Celestis.&lt;ref name=newdirections&gt;{{cite web |author=Sumner, Darren and Read, David |url=http://www.gateworld.net/interviews/new_directions_part_1.shtml |title=New Directions &amp;ndash; GateWorld talks with Robert C. Cooper |publisher=gateworld.net |month=June | year=2007 |accessdate=2008-03-05}}&lt;/ref&gt; Although Sands' availability eventually was a hindrance in ''The Ark of Truth'', the producers felt it was better to include the Doci than to forgo the character.&lt;ref name=mythmaker2 /&gt;

===Priors===

The Ori are served by so-called '''Priors''', highly evolved human beings &lt;ref name=&quot;Origin&quot;/&gt; who act as missionaries of the Ori&lt;ref name=directing /&gt; by traveling to different planets to spread the religion of Origin.&lt;ref name=tvzones67_6 /&gt; As the Ori are incapable of directly affecting the material universe in the Milky Way Galaxy due to the protection of the [[ascension (Stargate)|ascended]] [[Ancient (Stargate)|Ancients]],&lt;ref name=&quot;Origin&quot;/&gt; they send the Priors as their representatives.&lt;ref name=tvzones64_24 /&gt; Cooper said the Priors have &quot;these incredible, superhuman powers&quot;,&lt;ref name=newdirections /&gt; which allows them to perform deeds which they convince people are [[miracle]]s,&lt;ref name=&quot;Origin&quot;/&gt; attack enemies,&lt;ref name=&quot;Origin&quot;/&gt; and resurrect the dead.&lt;ref name=&quot;The Powers That Be&quot;/&gt; They also unleash plagues as punishment for not following the Ori.&lt;ref name=tvzones67_6 /&gt; The Priors believe fervently in their mission, and essentially offer a real religion with big promises.&lt;ref name=tvzones64_24 /&gt; Priors have been encountered on various worlds, trying to convert the local population and fight anyone who tried to stop them, including the [[Tau'ri]] and the [[Jaffa (Stargate)|Jaffa]].

As shown in the series, priors are normal humans whom the Ori transform into an evolved state of human to serve as missionaries as a reward for loyalty and devoted service. This process drastically alters their appearance: [[albino]] skin and hair, a tracery of raised lines on the chin and cheeks, and indentation of the [[human skull|skull]] just above and behind the eyes. Their eyes appear as a misty gray pupil without an iris. In {{sgcite|The Fourth Horseman}} and [[Stargate: The Ark of Truth|The Ark of Truth]], SG-1 was able to temporarily disable a Prior's abilities by using ultrasonic sounds to deny Priors access to the advanced areas of their brains.

* '''Damaris''' (played by [[William B. Davis]]) A Prior who makes contact with the [[Mythology of Stargate#Jaffa|Sodan]] in &quot;[[Babylon (Stargate SG-1)|Babylon]]&quot;. SG-1 challenges him in &quot;[[The Fourth Horseman (Stargate SG-1)|The Fourth Horseman]]&quot;, where Damaris is killed in self-defense.
* '''[[Daniel Jackson (Stargate)|Daniel Jackson]]''' (played by [[Michael Shanks]]) Is turned into a Prior by Adria in {{sgcite|The Shroud}}, as part of her plan to convert the [[Tau'ri]] to the path of Origin.  However, because Merlin had previously downloaded his memories into him, Daniel is able to maintain his own personality and, after exploiting his Prior powers to finish constructing and activating the [[Sangraal (Stargate SG-1)|Sangraal]], reverts to his normal form.
* '''[[Gerak]]''' (played by [[Louis Gossett, Jr.]]) A [[Jaffa (Stargate)|Jaffa]] introduced in {{sgcite|Origin}} who, after becoming interested in the promised path of ascension, turns into a Prior in {{sgcite|The Fourth Horseman}} and dies in the same episode after turning against Origin.  Daniel Jackson speculated that the Ori had included a kill switch when they transformed him into a Prior, to prevent disloyalty.
* '''Prior #1''' (played by [[Mark Houghton (Canadian actor)|Mark Houghton]]) Visits the village of Ver Eger and revives Vala after her Trial of Fire in {{sgcite|Avalon}}. He then brings Vala and Daniel to the [[Doci]] in the city of Celestis and back to the village to find more heretics in {{sgcite|Origin}}.
* '''Prior #2''' (played by [[Larry Cedar]]) The first Prior to be sent to the Milky Way after the Ori learned of the existence of humans in this galaxy. [[Cameron Mitchell (Stargate)|Cameron Mitchell]] brings him to [[Stargate Command]] in {{sgcite|Origin}}, where the prior eventually bursts into flames after learning that he would never again leave the planet.
* '''Prior #3''' (played by [[Greg Anderson (actor)|Greg Anderson]]) The governor of the village of Ver Eger, introduced in {{sgcite|Avalon}} when Daniel and Vala first came to the village. As a reward for doing his duties and putting Vala through a Trial by Fire, he is transformed into a Prior in {{sgcite|Origin}}. He is later sent to the Milky Way and makes appearances in {{sgcite|The Powers That Be}} unleashing a plague in a defiant village, in {{sgcite|The Fourth Horseman}} turning Gerak into a Prior, and in {{sgcite|Line in the Sand}} ordering the destruction of a village by spaceship. He also appeared in ''[[Stargate: The Ark of Truth]]'', in which he was killed.
* '''Prior #4''' (played by [[Ian Butcher]]) Tries to convert the people of Kallana in {{sgcite|Beachhead}} and later transforms the planet into a [[micro black hole]] to power a [[Supergate]].
* '''Prior #5''' (played by [[Morris Chapdelaine]]) Visits the [[Mythology of Stargate#Jaffa|Sodan]] homeworld in {{sgcite|Arthur's Mantle}} and causes Volnek to turn on his fellow Jaffa and kill them.
* '''Prior #6''' (played by [[Doug Abrahams]]) A Prior introduced in {{sgcite|Crusade}}, who visits Ver Isca and cures Tomin of his limp, also informing him that he was unable to father children. Prior #6 is on board one of the [[Ori battlecruiser]]s invading the Milky Way in {{sgcite|Camelot}} and is present during [[Adria (Stargate)|Adria]]'s birth in {{sgcite|Flesh and Blood}}, informing her parents of her divine purpose. He also appears in {{sgcite|The Quest}}, accompanying Adria in the search of the [[Ancient technology in Stargate#Holy Grail|Sangraal]]. He made an appearance in ''[[Stargate: The Ark of Truth]]''.
* '''Prior #7''' (played by [[Peter Nicholas Smyth]]) Accompanies [[Adria (Stargate)|Adria]] in {{sgcite|Counterstrike}} and is killed in an attack by the [[Jaffa (Stargate)|Jaffa]] with the [[Dakara Superweapon]].

===&lt;span id=&quot;Tomin&quot; /&gt;&lt;span id=&quot;Ori warriors&quot; /&gt;Tomin and the Ori warriors===
[[Image:Tomin.jpg|thumb|Tomin and some Ori warriors in ''[[Stargate: The Ark of Truth]]'']]

The '''Ori warriors''' are conscripted men, who were trained to fight non-believers as foot soldiers and take over the Milky Way. They are plated in metallic [[armor]] and are armed with powerful [[Staff Weapon#Ori Staff Weapon|staff weapon]]s. They are men who are actually doing the fighting.&lt;ref name=directing /&gt; They were introduced in &quot;Crusade&quot; and were first shown in combat in Season 10.&lt;ref name=directing /&gt; Cooper wrote &quot;Crusade&quot; with the intention to show that the Ori warriors are not two-dimensional, even though their strength of belief and single-mindedness makes them fight for what they want to fight for.&lt;ref name=directing /&gt; According to Cooper, the Ori warriors are a fictional mirror of the events in the real world, but he wanted people to try and understand &quot;why people want to go to war with us, or blow up our buildings, or our airplanes&quot;.&lt;ref name=directing /&gt; Cooper also wanted to show that &quot;there's really no winner to the argument&quot; when it comes to &quot;religion and belief, and gods&quot;; according to Cooper, there is a line when a society takes up arms instead of finding a more civilized way of dialogue.&lt;ref name=directing /&gt;

[[Tim Guinee]] played '''Tomin''', a devout Ori follower of the village of Ver Isca, who becomes an Ori commander in Season 10. He appears in {{sgcite|Crusade}}, {{sgcite|Flesh and Blood}}, {{sgcite|Line in the Sand}}, and ''[[Stargate: The Ark of Truth]]''. Tomin is intended as a representation of the Ori warriors,&lt;ref name=directing /&gt; and Cooper described Guinee as a &quot;fabulous actor who instantly creates that humanity and empathy ... while he's mass-murdering people&quot;&lt;ref name=mythmaker /&gt; Tomin is introduced in flashbacks in {{sgcite|Crusade}}, having found Vala after she was transported to the Ori home galaxy. Tomin had been crippled since childhood, and was therefore looked down on by his fellow villagers. Tomin married Vala and accepted her pregnancy as his child, not knowing that it was a [[Virgin birth of Jesus|miraculous conception]] set by the Ori. A little later, a Prior visited the village and cured Tomin of his limp, allowing him to become a warrior for the Ori. The prior also told Tomin the truth about the child as &quot;the will of the Ori&quot;, who would later be the [[Orici]]. Tomin is later able to forgive Vala.&lt;ref name=&quot;Crusade&quot;&gt;&quot;[[Crusade (Stargate SG-1)|Crusade]]&quot; (''[[Stargate SG-1]]'')&lt;/ref&gt; Tomin and Vala depart aboard the first wave of Ori vessels entering the Milky Way,&lt;ref name=&quot;Camelot&quot;&gt;&quot;[[Camelot (Stargate SG-1)|Camelot]]&quot; (''[[Stargate SG-1]]'')&lt;/ref&gt; and they go separate ways in {{sgcite|Flesh and Blood}}.&lt;ref name=&quot;Flesh and Blood&quot;&gt;{{cite episode| episodelink=Flesh and Blood (Stargate SG-1)| title=Flesh and Blood| series=[[Stargate SG-1]]}}&lt;/ref&gt; Tomin rises to the rank of commander within the Ori warrior armies, and he and Vala meet again in {{sgcite|Line in the Sand}}. Because a Prior twists the words of the Book of Origin, Tomin begins to doubt the Priors and their interpretations of Origin's teachings, and helps Vala escape.&lt;ref name=&quot;Line in the Sand&quot;&gt;&quot;[[Line in the Sand (Stargate SG-1)|Line in the Sand]]&quot; (''[[Stargate SG-1]]'')&lt;/ref&gt; Tomin plays an important role in the film ''[[Stargate: The Ark of Truth]]'', in which, after seeing a Prior's death with his own eyes, he learns the truth about the Ori.

===&lt;span id=&quot;Adria&quot; /&gt;&lt;span id=&quot;Orici&quot; /&gt;Adria the Orici===
In Season 10, the primary antagonist switched from the Priors and the Doci to the '''Orici''', also known by the name '''Adria'''.&lt;ref name=directing /&gt; The story presents her as a genetically advanced human infused with Ori knowledge, created to circumvent the Ancients' rules that the Ori cannot directly use their powers to conquer the [[Milky Way galaxy]].&lt;ref name=ontarget&gt;{{cite web |last=Sumner |first=Darren |url=http://www.gateworld.net/interviews/wright_on_target.shtml |title=Wright On Target &amp;ndash; GateWorld talks with Brad Wright |publisher=gateworld.net |month=July | year=2006 |accessdate=2008-03-05}}&lt;/ref&gt; Adria is one step higher than the Doci, but equal in terms of her role in the Milky Way galaxy, which is to lead the armies of the Ori in the Milky Way galaxy,&lt;ref name=directing /&gt; converting the galaxy to Origin in the process. Adria possesses several Prior-like superhuman abilities, and leads the armies of the Ori until her [[Ascension (Stargate)|Ascension]] in the penultimate episode of ''Stargate SG-1''. From a creative standpoint, Adria's character was created to give [[Vala Mal Doran]] a story and personality arc as a member of the [[SG-1]] team.&lt;ref name=mythmaker /&gt;

Adria's story begins shortly after the events of &quot;Beachhead&quot;, when Vala is impregnated by the Ori in the Ori home galaxy.&lt;ref name=&quot;Crusade&quot;&gt;{{cite episode| episodelink=Crusade (Stargate SG-1)| title=Crusade| series=[[Stargate SG-1]]}}&lt;/ref&gt; Vala eventually returns to the Milky Way aboard one of the [[Ori battlecruiser]]s invading the Milky Way galaxy. In &quot;Flesh and Blood&quot;, Vala gives birth to a baby girl, the Orici. Within hours of being born, the child reaches the apparent age of four and heals her mother's pain, knowing that Vala is not a believer in Origin. By the child's apparent age of seven, Vala gives her the name Adria, after her &quot;witch of a woman&quot; stepmother. Vala escapes when Adria is at the apparent age of twelve.&lt;ref name=&quot;Flesh and Blood&quot; /&gt; Adria only starts to have an impact in the second quarter of the season, when she has grown &quot;into a beautiful but deadly young woman&quot;.&lt;ref name=directing /&gt;&lt;ref name=tvzones74_48&gt;{{Cite news |last=Eramo |first=Steven |author-link= | title=Actress Morena Baccarin &amp;ndash; Child's Play |newspaper=[[TV Zone]] |issue=Special #74 |pages=48&amp;ndash;49 |date=January 2007 |postscript=&lt;!--None--&gt;}}&lt;/ref&gt;

When Vala, who has joined the [[SG-1]] team, meets adult Adria in &quot;Counterstrike&quot;, Adria foreshadows her plans with [[Daniel Jackson (Stargate)|Daniel]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Counterstrike&quot;&gt;{{cite episode| episodelink=Counterstrike (Stargate SG-1)| title=Counterstrike| series=[[Stargate SG-1]]}}&lt;/ref&gt; In &quot;The Quest&quot;, Adria tricks SG-1 into obtaining the [[Sangraal (Stargate)|Sangraal]] for her. Adria captures Daniel before he can complete the device.&lt;ref name=&quot;The Quest&quot;&gt;{{cite episode| episodelink=The Quest (Stargate SG-1)| title=The Quest| series=[[Stargate SG-1]]}}&lt;/ref&gt; Hoping to convert both [[Earth]] and Vala, Adria attempts to convert Daniel to the path of [[Origin (Stargate SG-1)|Origin]] and makes him a Prior. In &quot;The Shroud&quot;, however, Daniel betrays her and uses the weapon on the Ori galaxy.&lt;ref name=&quot;The Shroud&quot; /&gt; In &quot;Dominion&quot;, Adria is briefly implanted with a cloned [[Ba'al (Stargate)|Ba'al]] symbiote. Although the symbiote is removed, the procedure almost kills Adria and she ascends.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;[[Dominion (Stargate SG-1)|Dominion]]&quot;&lt;/ref&gt; Being the only surviving Ori power after the events of &quot;The Shroud&quot;, Adria alone controls the power generated by the followers of Origin, and continues the Ori's assault on the Milky Way in ''Stargate: The Ark of Truth''. After an Ancient device known as the [[Ancient technology in Stargate#The_Ark_of_Truth|Ark of Truth]] affects her galaxy's believers, Adria is last seen in ''[[Stargate: The Ark of Truth]]'' in a battle with the Ancient [[Morgan le Fay (Stargate)|Morgan le Fay]], which in Cooper's view started as a fight in the human realm of existence and continues on the [[Ascension (Stargate)|ascended]] level similar to what happened with [[Anubis (Stargate)|Anubis]] and [[Oma Desala]] in {{sgcite|Threads}}. Adria is thus &quot;eternally distracted from being able to continue her evil ways&quot;.&lt;ref name=mythmaker2 /&gt;

Young Adria was played by three child actresses &amp;ndash; Adria at age four was played by [[Robert C. Cooper]]'s daughter Emma, who replaced the originally cast child who suffered from stage fright.&lt;ref name=ac1001&gt;Audio commentary for &quot;Flesh and Blood&quot;&lt;/ref&gt; Adria at age seven was played by [[Jodelle Ferland]], and at age twelve by [[Brenna O'Brien]]. [[Morena Baccarin]] was offered the role of adult Adria in a phone call by the producers, who were ''[[Firefly (TV series)|Firefly]]'' fans. The orange contact lenses that the actress had to wear made her feel nearly blind and irritated her eyes, so the lenses were dropped during the shooting of &quot;The Quest&quot;. Baccarin enjoyed &quot;the whole experience [...] incredible&quot; as she got to play a character she could learn from. In her words, &quot;Adria was a complex character and I loved trying to make her sweet as well as totally bad.&quot;&lt;ref name=tvzones74_48 /&gt;&lt;ref name=ac1011&gt;Audio commentary for &quot;The Quest&quot;, Part 1&lt;/ref&gt; Brad Wright called Adria &quot;an interesting character because she's the Ori cheating&quot;,&lt;ref name=ontarget /&gt; and compared her to the Ori equivalent of a [[Harcesis]].&lt;ref name=ontarget /&gt; Cooper considered Adria becoming host to a Goa'uld &quot;the marriage of the old villains and the new villains&quot; and compared it to the episode {{sgcite|Enemies}}, the first where both the Replicators and the Goa'uld first appeared together.&lt;ref name=newdirections /&gt; Morena Baccarin was only available for one day during the filming of ''Stargate: The Ark of Truth'', worth six pages of script. Cooper had written more scenes between her,  Julian Sands (&quot;Doci&quot;) and the SG-1 team, but the only other option to what ended up in the film was to cut the character.&lt;ref name=mythmaker /&gt;

===Anti-Ori underground===

In the second episode of season 9, it is shown that not all Humans in the Ori Home Galaxy believe their gods to be benevolent as is seen in the case of the '''Anti-Ori Underground'''. This group of humans live a dangerous life in hiding from purges and the fanatical followers. Their purpose is simply to collect enough evidence to prove to their brethren that the claims of the Ori are false. Despite this, they do believe that the Ori are very powerful; it is only their intentions they doubt. Even though the group lives in the shadows of Ori society, they have collected a number of artifacts that they have kept hidden, since such pieces of technology contradict the book of Origin and thus would be destroyed if discovered. The group also has a number of followers in high positions even within the City of the Gods. All known members of  this movement &amp;ndash; '''Harrid''' (played by [[Stephen Park]]), '''Sallis''' ([[April Amber Telek]]), '''Fannis''' ([[Paul Moniz de Sa]]), '''Seevis''' ([[Michael Ironside]]), and '''Denya''' ([[Daniella Evangelista]]) &amp;ndash; die shortly after their introduction.  Another member is introduced in Stargate: The Ark of Truth: '''Hertis''' ([[Chris Gauthier]]).  Tomin somehow finds him and takes him to meet with Daniel and Vala in order to find the location of Ortus Malum where the team believes the Ark of Truth to be.  He is somewhat suspicious of Daniel and Vala as they are unaware that the fires of Celestis are out (an indication that the Ori are dead) which should have spread very far.  Apparently Tomin told him they were from far away but just not ''how'' far (another galaxy).  In order to give him proof of their story, Daniel, Vala and Tomin take him to the ''Odyssey'' which is in orbit which is proof enough for him.  He tells them what is believed to be the location: a mountain high above the Plains of Celestis on another planet.  Presumably he is then returned to his home planet as he is not seen again.

==Reception==
In reviewing the first part of Season 9, Steven Graves of ''[[TV Zone]]'' was concerned that &quot;mining Arthurian mythology for season 9 may prove to be a mistake for ''Stargate''&quot;, comparing scenes of {{sgcite|Avalon}} to &quot;a god-awful Merri Olde England pastiche straight out of ''[[Monty Python and the Holy Grail]]'', complete with unwashed peons, an overbearing church and witchburning.&quot;&lt;ref name=tvzones67_20&gt;{{Cite news |last=Graves |first=Steven |author-link= | title=Season Nine episodes 1&amp;ndash;10 Reviews |newspaper=[[TV Zone]] |issue=Special #67 |pages=20&amp;ndash;22 |date=December 2005 |postscript=&lt;!--None--&gt;}}&lt;/ref&gt; He however commented about {{sgcite|Origin}} that &quot;''Stargate SG-1'' seems to be establishing an interesting set of themes this season, providing a timely commentary on religious evangelism and intolerance with its new villains, the Ori.&quot;&lt;ref name=tvzones67_20 /&gt; By {{sgcite|The Powers That Be}}, Graves was sure that &quot;the Ori are a force to be reckoned with.&quot;&lt;ref name=tvzones67_20 /&gt; Regarding {{sgcite|The Fourth Horseman}}, he thought it was &quot;doubly nice&quot; to see an ''SG-1'' story where the apocalyptic events have an effect on contemporary Earth instead of on alien planets.&lt;ref name=tvzones67_20 /&gt;
{{Expand section|date=June 2008}}

==References==
{{Reflist|2}}

==External links==
* [[wikia:Stargate:Ori|Ori]] at [[wikia]]
* [http://www.gateworld.net/omnipedia/races/links/ori.shtml &quot;Ori&quot;] at [[GateWorld]] Omnipedia

{{Stargate}}
{{Use dmy dates|date=January 2011}}

[[Category:Fictional deities]]
[[Category:Stargate races]]
[[Category:Fictional religions]]
[[Category:Fictional emperors and empresses]]

[[ar:اوراي]]
[[bs:Ori]]
[[ca:Ori]]
[[cs:Oriové]]
[[es:Ori]]
[[fr:Ori]]
[[hr:Ori]]
[[it:Ori (Stargate)]]
[[hu:Ori]]
[[nl:Ori (Stargate)]]
[[pl:Ori (Gwiezdne wrota)]]
[[ro:Ori (Stargate)]]
[[ru:Орай (Звёздные врата)]]
[[sk:Ori]]
[[sh:Ori (Stargate)]]
[[tr:Ori (Yıldız Geçidi)]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
