<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="20405839" ns="0" title="Amazon Payments"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Advert|date=December 2009}}
{{Infobox Dotcom company 
 | company_name = Amazon Payments
 | company_type = Subsidiary of [[Amazon.com]]
 | genre =
 | foundation = 
 | founder =
 | location_city =
 | location_country =
 | url = [http://payments.amazon.com/ payments.amazon.com]
 | location = [[Seattle, Washington]] [[USA]]
 | parent = [[Amazon.com]]
 | language = [[English language|English]]
 | commercial = Yes
 | registration = Free
 | current_status = active
}}

'''Amazon Payments, Inc.''' is a wholly owned [[subsidiary]] of [[Amazon.com]] &lt;ref name=launch&gt;{{cite web |url=http://payments.amazon.com |title=Amazon Payments Website|publisher=Amazon Payments|date=2009-07-22}}&lt;/ref&gt; that provides a means to process transactions online. Launched in 2006, Amazon Payments uses the consumer base of Amazon.com and focuses on giving users the same checkout experience available on Amazon.com. 

Amazon Payments has several products for consumers, businesses, and developers.

==Consumers==
===Online purchases===
Amazon Payments is a way for customers to purchase goods and services at websites across the internet using the payment methods in their Amazon.com accounts, such as their Visa or MasterCard. (Currently Amazon.com and Amazon Payments will not accept payment methods such as PayPal or Google Checkout.) At participating vendors, which include [[Patagonia (clothing)|Patagonia]] and [[Jockey International, Inc.|Jockey]], users can check out using their Amazon account information without needing to re-enter credit card numbers or shipping addresses. Users can also check out with Amazon's [[One click|1 Click]].

===Other consumer products ===
* Amazon TextBuyIt is an [[SMS]]-based service which allows users to find items, check prices, or purchase items simply by sending a text message to &quot;262966{{Clarify|The number doesn't include an international calling prefix, so it is unclear in which country the SIM card has to be issued for the number to work.|date=July 2010}}&quot; (AMAZON). Users can also text searches to &quot;262966&quot; and receive search results and prices quickly.

* Amazon WebPay is a free service to send or receive money using an e-mail address or mobile telephone number. 

*Amazon TextPayMe is a service similar to WebPay, except users can use SMS messages to complete the transaction. The premise behind the service was to allow users to pay each other instantly and securely, without having to carry change or remember IOUs.

==Businesses==
===Checkout by Amazon===
Checkout by Amazon (CBA) is an e-commerce solution that allows web merchants to accept Amazon account information and use Amazon for payment processing. CBA can manage several aspects of the transaction including order processing, promotional discounts, shipping rates, sales tax calculation, and up-selling. Depending upon the needs of the merchant, CBA can be integrated into the merchant's systems with manual processing (through Seller Central) or through SOAP APIs or downloadable CSV files. CBA also claims to reduce [[bad debt]] because of Amazon's fraud detection capabilities.

===Amazon Simple Pay===
Amazon Simple Pay (ASP) is a set of payment-only products that allows web merchants to accept Amazon account information and use Amazon for payment-only processing. ASP differs from CBA in that ASP does not handle additional capabilities associated with order processing such as promotions, tax &amp; shipping, and so on.

===Amazon PayPhrase===
Amazon PayPhrase is a recent (November 2009) addition to Amazon Payments which allows customers to check out by typing their PayPhrase and their PIN without having to enter any shipping or credit card information.  As of now, this is accepted at Amazon.com as well as at certain retailers, including Buy.com and J&amp;R Music and Computers.  PayPhrase's claim of being additionally secure is controversial.&lt;ref&gt;{{citeweb|
url=http://www.technologyreview.com/web/23845/?a=f
|title=Can Amazon's PayPhrase Combine Convenience with Security?
|author=Robert Lemos
|date=2009-11-03
|accessdate=2010-05-10
|publisher=Technology Review}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Developers==
===Flexible Payments Service===
{{Main|Amazon Flexible Payments Service}}
Flexible Payments Service (FPS), part of [[Amazon Web Services]], enables developers to use Amazon's scalable payment infrastructure to accept payments using the customer's Amazon account information. FPS includes several lightweight [[api|APIs]] that are designed to enable developers to get up and running quickly and easily.

==References==
{{Reflist}}

==See also==
*[[PayPal]]
*[[Google Checkout]]
*[[Bitcoin]]
*[[Dwolla]]

==External links==
*[http://payments.amazon.com/ Official website]
*[http://www.techcrunch.com/2006/02/15/everyone-send-me-5/ Everyone Send Me $5] [[TechCrunch]], February 15, 2006.

{{Amazon}}

[[Category:Amazon.com|Payments]]
[[Category:Banking technology]]
[[Category:Electronic currencies]]
[[Category:Mobile payments]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
