<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="20412121" ns="0" title="Depictions of Muhammad"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{pp-semi-indef}}
{{pp-move-indef}}
{{Muhammad}}
{{disputed-section|date=November 2011}}
The permissibility of '''depictions of [[Muhammad]]''', the founder of [[Islam]], has long been a concern in the [[history of Islam]]. Oral and written descriptions are readily accepted by all traditions of [[Islam]], but there is disagreement about visual depictions.&lt;ref name=best&gt;{{cite web
|url=http://links.jstor.org/sici?sici=0951-0788%28191906%2934%3A195%3C249%3AAIPOMA%3E2.0.CO%3B2-6
| title = An Indian Picture of Muhammad and His Companions
| accessdate = 2007-05-01
| author = T. W. Arnold
| month = June
| year = 1919
| publisher = The Burlington Magazine for Connoisseurs, Vol. 34, No. 195.
| pages = 249–252
}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=a&gt;{{cite book |author=Jonathan Bloom &amp; Sheila Blair |title=Islamic Arts |publisher=London: Phaidon |year=1997 |pages=202}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The [[Quran]] does not explicitly forbid images of Muhammad, but there are a few [[hadith]] (supplemental teachings) which have explicitly prohibited Muslims from creating visual depictions of figures. Most [[Sunni]] Muslims believe that visual depictions of all the [[prophets of Islam]] should be prohibited{{Citation needed|date=August 2011}} and are particularly averse to visual representations of Muhammad.&lt;ref name=BergenMuhammad&gt;[http://www.webcitation.org/63BsneOUJ Devotion in pictures: Muslim popular iconography – The prophet Muhammad], [[University of Bergen]]&lt;/ref&gt; The key concern is that the use of images can encourage [[idolatry]].{{Citation needed|date=November 2011}} In [[Shia]] Islam, however, images of Muhammad are quite common nowadays, even though Shia scholars historically were against such depictions.&lt;ref name=BergenMuhammad/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[[Thomas Walker Arnold]] says that
:''&quot;It was not merely Sunni schools of law but Shia jurists also who fulminated against this figured art. Because the Persians are Shiites, many Europeans writers have assumed that the Shia sect had not the same objection to representing living being as the rival set of the Sunni; but such an opinion ignores the fact that Shiisum did not become the state church in Persia until the rise of the Safivid dynasty at the beginning of the 16th century.&quot;''&lt;/ref&gt; Still, many Muslims who take a stricter view of the supplemental traditions, will sometimes challenge any depiction of Muhammad, including those created and published by non-Muslims.&lt;ref name=facts&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.religionfacts.com/islam/things/depictions-of-muhammad-in-islamic-art.htm|accessdate=2007-07-06|title=Islamic Figurative Art and Depictions of Muhammad|publisher=religionfacts.com}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The question of whether images in [[Islamic art]], including those depicting the Prophet, can be considered as [[religious art]] remains a matter of contention between scholars.&lt;ref&gt;Gruber (2010), p.27&lt;/ref&gt; They appear in illustrated books that are normally works of history or poetry, including those with religious subjects; the Qu'ran is never illustrated: &quot;context and intent are essential to understanding Islamic pictorial art. The Muslim artists creating images of Muhammad, and the public who beheld them, understood that the images were not objects of worship. Nor were the objects so decorated used as part of religious worship&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;Cosman, Pelner and Jones, Linda Gale. ''Handbook to life in the medieval world'', p. 623, Infobase Publishing, ISBN 0816048878, 9780816048878&lt;/ref&gt;  However, scholars concede that such images have &quot;a spiritual element&quot;, and were also sometimes used in informal religious devotions celebrating the day of the [[Mi'raj]].&lt;ref&gt;Gruber (2010), p.27 (quote) and 43&lt;/ref&gt; Most visual depictions only show Muhammad with his face veiled, or symbolically represent him as a flame; other images, notably from before about 1500, show him fully.&lt;ref&gt;Gruber (2005), pp. 239, 247–253&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;January2009&quot;&gt;{{cite book|author=Brendan January|title=The Arab Conquests of the Middle East|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=K9XGWkkFy0sC&amp;pg=PA34|accessdate=14 November 2011|date=1 February 2009|publisher=Twenty-First Century Books|isbn=978-0-8225-8744-6|page=34}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Safi2010&quot;&gt;{{cite book|author=Omid Safi|title=Memories of Muhammad: Why the Prophet Matters|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=s63i21E9dr8C&amp;pg=PA171|accessdate=14 November 2011|date=2 November 2010|publisher=HarperCollins|isbn=978-0-06-123135-3|page=171}}&lt;/ref&gt; However, depictions of Muhammad were rare, never numerous in any community or era throughout Islamic history,&lt;ref name=&quot;Arnold&quot;&gt;{{Cite book| publisher = Gorgias Press LLC| isbn = 9781931956918| last = Arnold| first = Thomas W.| title = Painting in Islam, a Study of the Place of Pictorial Art in Muslim Culture| date = First published 1928, reprint 2002-11| pages=91–9}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Plas1987&quot;&gt;{{cite book|author=Dirk van der Plas|title=Effigies dei: essays on the history of religions|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=ops3AAAAIAAJ&amp;pg=PA124|accessdate=14 November 2011|year=1987|publisher=BRILL|isbn=978-90-04-08655-5|page=124}}&lt;/ref&gt; appearing almost entirely in the private medium of Persian and other [[Persian miniature|miniature]] book illustration.&lt;ref name=&quot;Ernst2004&quot;&gt;{{cite book|last1=Ernst|first1=Carl W.|authorlink1Carl W. Ernst|title=Following Muhammad: Rethinking Islam in the Contemporary World|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=DOWn22EkJsQC&amp;pg=PA78|accessdate=14 November 2011|date=August 2004|publisher=UNC Press Books|isbn=978-0-8078-5577-5|pages=78–79}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.webcitation.org/63Bu5f5N0 Devotion in pictures: Muslim popular iconography – Introduction to the exhibition], [[University of Bergen]]&lt;/ref&gt; The key medium of public religious art in Islam was and is [[calligraphy]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Plas1987&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Ernst2004&quot; /&gt;

==Background==
{{main|Aniconism in Islam}}
Some major religions have experienced times during their history when [[aniconism|images of their religious figures were forbidden]]. In Judaism, one of the [[Ten Commandments]] forbade &quot;graven images&quot;.  In [[Byzantine]] Christianity during the period of [[byzantine iconoclasm|Iconoclasm]] in the 8th century, and again during the 9th century, visual representations of sacred figures were forbidden, and only the [[Christian cross|Cross]] could be depicted in churches. Even in modern times, different groups of Protestant Christians have had disputes about the appropriateness of having religious [[icons]] of saints. The concern generally boils down to the concept of whether or not the image is becoming more important than what is being represented.&lt;ref name=Halicks&gt;{{cite news|title=Images of Muhammad: Three ways to see a cartoon|author=Richard Halicks|date=2006-02-12|work=[[Atlanta Journal-Constitution]]}}&lt;/ref&gt; In Islam, although nothing in the [[Qur'an]] explicitly bans images, some supplemental [[hadith]] explicitly ban the drawing of images of any living creature; other hadith tolerate images, but never encourage them. Hence, most Muslims avoid visual depictions of Muhammad or [[Prophets of Islam|any other prophet]] such as [[Moses]] or [[Abraham]].&lt;ref name=best/&gt;&lt;ref name=USSC&gt;{{cite web|url={{SCOTUS URL|about/north&amp;southwalls.pdf}} |format=pdf|title=Courtroom Friezes: North and South Walls|author=Office of the Curator|date=2003-05-08|accessdate=2007-07-08|work=Information Sheet, Supreme Court of the United States}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=explaining&gt;{{cite news|title=Explaining the outrage|date=2006-02-08|work=[[Chicago Tribune]]}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Depiction by Muslims==
===Verbal descriptions===
[[File:Hilye-i serif 2.jpg|thumb|''[[hilya|Hilye]]'' by [[Hâfiz Osman]] (1642–1698)]]
In one of the earliest sources, [[Ibn Sa'd]]'s ''Kitab al-Tabaqat al-Kabir'', there are numerous verbal descriptions of Muhammad. One description sourced to [[Ali ibn Abi Talib]] is as follows:

: ''The Apostle of Allah, may Allah bless him, is neither too short nor too tall. His hair are neither curly nor straight, but a mixture of the two. He is a man of black hair and large skull. His complexion has a tinge of redness. His shoulder bones are broad and his palms and feet are fleshy. He has long ''al-masrubah'' which means hair growing from neck to navel. He is of long eye-lashes, close eyebrows, smooth and shining fore-head and long space between two shoulders. When he walks he walks inclining as if coming down from a height. I never saw a man like him before him or after him.''&lt;ref&gt;Ibn Sa'd – ''Kitabh al-Tabaqat al-Kabir'', as translated by S. Moinul and H.K. Ghazanfar, Kitab Bhavan, New Delhi, n.d.&lt;/ref&gt;

Athar Husain gives a non-pictorial description of his appearance, dress, etc. in &quot;The Message of Mohammad&quot;. According to Husain, Muhammad was a little taller than average, sturdily built, and muscular. His fingers were long. His hair, which was long, had waves, and he had a thick beard, which had seventeen gray hairs at the time of his death. He had good teeth and spare cheeks, and brownish-black eyes. His complexion was fair and he was very handsome. He walked fast with firm gait. He always kept himself busy with something, did not speak unnecessarily, always spoke to the point and without verbosity, and did not behave in an emotional way. He usually wore a shirt, trousers, a sheet thrown round the shoulders, and a turban, all spotlessly clean, rarely wearing the fine clothes that had been presented to him. He wanted others to wear simple, but always clean, clothes.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.usc.edu/dept/MSA/fundamentals/prophet/prophetdescription.html|title=USC-MSA Compendium of Muslim Texts|accessdate =2006-03-10}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The Arabic term for a written description of Muhammad is a ''[[hilya]]'' (Turkish: ''hilye'', pl. ''hilyeler''), and in the Ottoman period such texts may be surrounded by an elaborate frame of [[Ottoman illumination|illuminated decoration]], either in books or, more often, [[muraqqa]]s or albums, or sometimes placed in wooden frames so that they can hang on a wall.&lt;ref&gt;Gruber (2005), p.231-232&lt;/ref&gt;   The elaborated form of the calligraphic tradition was founded in the 17th century by the Ottoman calligrapher [[Hâfiz Osman]]. While containing a concrete and artistically appealing description of Muhammad's appearance, they complied with the strictures against figurative depictions of the Prophet, leaving his appearance to the viewer's imagination.&lt;ref name=&quot;Peters2010&quot;&gt;{{cite book|author=F. E. Peters|title=Jesus and Muhammad: Parallel Tracks, Parallel Lives|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=olEi-1LZYYQC&amp;pg=PA160|accessdate=5 November 2011|date=10 November 2010|publisher=Oxford University Press|isbn=978-0-19-974746-7|pages=160–161}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Brockopp2010&quot;&gt;{{cite book|author=Jonathan E. Brockopp|title=The Cambridge companion to Muḥammad|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=o58K2t344YQC&amp;pg=PA130|accessdate=6 November 2011|date=30 April 2010|publisher=Cambridge University Press|isbn=978-0-521-71372-6|page=130}}&lt;/ref&gt;  The Ottoman ''hilye'' format customarily starts with a [[basmala]], shown on top, and is separated in the middle by {{cite quran|21|107|style=ref}}: &quot;And We have not sent you but as a mercy to the worlds&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;Brockopp2010&quot; /&gt; The four circles often contain the names of the [[Rashidun|Rightly-guided Caliphs]], [[Abu Bakr]], [[Umar]], [[Uthman]], and [[Ali]], each followed by &quot;radhi Allahu anhu&quot; (&quot;may God be pleased with him&quot;).   


&lt;div align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
&lt;gallery&gt;
Image:Hilye-i serif 1.jpg|''Hilye'' by Hâfiz Osman
Image:Hilye-i serif 3.png|''Hilye'' by Hâfiz Osman
Image:Hilye-i serif 5.jpg|''Hilye'' by Hâfiz Osman
Image:Hilye-i serif 4.jpg|''Hilye'' by Kazasker Mustafa İzzet Efendi (1801–1876)
Image:Hilye-i Serif 6.jpg|''Hilye'' by Kazasker Mustafa İzzet Efendi
&lt;/gallery&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

===Calligraphic representations===
The most common visual representation of the Prophet in Islamic art, especially in Arabic-speaking areas, is by a calligraphic representation of his name, a sort of [[monogram]] in roughly circular form, often given a decorated frame. Such inscriptions are normally in Arabic, and may rearrange or repeat forms, or add a blessing or honorific, or for example the word &quot;messenger&quot; or a contraction of it.  The range of ways of representing Muhammad's name is considerable, including [[ambigram]]s.

The more elaborate versions relate to other Islamic traditions of special forms of calligraphy such as those writing the [[Names of God in Islam|names of God]], and the secular [[tughra]] or elaborate monogram of Ottoman rulers.


&lt;div align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
&lt;gallery&gt;
Image:Edirne 7331 Nevit.JPG|Calligraphic representation of the Prophet's name, painted on the wall of a [[mosque]] in [[Edirne]] in Turkey
Image:Muhammad Salat.PNG|Muhammad's name in [[Thuluth]], Arabic calligraphic script; the smaller writing in the top left means &quot;Peace be upon him&quot;
Image:Ambigram_-_Muhammad_and_Ali2.svg|Ambigram – Muhammad (محمد) upside down is read as Ali (علي), and vice versa]]
&lt;/gallery&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

===Figurative visual depictions===
{{disputed-section|date=November 2011}}
{{Commons category|Muslim depictions of Muhammad}}
[[Image:Siyer-i Nebi 158b.jpg|thumb|right|200px|Muhammad, shown with a veiled face and halo, at [[Mount Hira]] (16th century Ottoman illustration of the [[Siyer-i Nebi]])]]

Throughout Islamic history, depictions of Muhammad in Islamic art were rare.&lt;ref name=&quot;Arnold&quot; /&gt; According to Christiane Gruber, there exists a &quot;notable corpus of images of Muhammad produced, mostly in the form of manuscript illustrations, in various regions of the Islamic world from the thirteenth century through modern times&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;Gruber (2005), p. 240-241&lt;/ref&gt; Depictions of Muhammad date back to the start of the tradition of [[Persian miniature]]s as illustrations in books. The illustrated book from the [[Persianate]] world (''[[Warka and Gulshah]]'', [[Topkapi Palace]] Library H. 841, attributed to [[Konya]] 1200-1250) contains the two earliest known Islamic depictions of the Prophet.&lt;ref&gt;Grabar, p. 19; Gruber (2005), p. 235 (from where the date range), Blair, Sheila S., ''The Development of the Illustrated Book in Iran'', ''Muqarnas'', Vol. 10, Essays in Honor of Oleg Grabar (1993), p. 266, BRILL, [http://www.jstor.org/stable/1523191 JSTOR] says &quot;c. 1250&quot;&lt;/ref&gt; This book dates to before or just around the time of the [[Mongol invasion]] of [[Anatolia]] in the 1240s, and before the campaigns against Persia and Iraq of the 1250s, which destroyed great numbers of books in libraries. 

Gruber traces a development from &quot;veristic&quot; images showing the whole body and face, in the 13th to 15th centuries, to more &quot;abstract&quot; representations in the 16th to 19th centuries, the latter including the representation of the Prophet by a special type of [[calligraphic]] reresentation, with the older types also remaining in use.&lt;ref&gt;Gruber (2005), 229, and throughout&lt;/ref&gt;  An intermediate type, first found from about 1400, is the &quot;inscribed portrait&quot; where the face of Muhammad is blank, with &quot;Ya Muhammad&quot; (&quot;O Muhammad&quot;) or a similar phrase written in the space instead; these may be related to [[Sufi]] thought.  In some cases the inscription appears to have been a underpainting that would later be covered by a face or veil, so a pious act by the painter, for his eyes alone, but in others it was intended to be seen.&lt;ref&gt;Gruber (2005), p. 240-241&lt;/ref&gt; According to Gruber, a good number of these paintings, however, underwent later [[iconoclasm|iconoclastic]] mutilations, in which the facial features of the Prophet were scratched or smeared&quot; as Muslim views on the acceptability of veristic images changed.&lt;ref&gt;Gruber (2005), 229&lt;/ref&gt; 

A number of extant Persian manuscripts representing Muhammad date from the [[Ilkhanid]] period under the new [[Mongol]] rulers, including a ''[[Marzubannama]]'' dating to 1299. The Ilkhanid [[MS Arab 161]] of 1307/8 contains 25 illustrations found in an illustrated version of [[Al-Biruni]]'s ''[[The Remaining Signs of Past Centuries]]'', of which five include depictions Muhammad, including the two concluding images, the largest and most accomplished in the manuscript, which emphasize the relation of Muhammad and [[`Ali]] according to [[Shi`ite]] doctrine.&lt;ref&gt;Gruber (2010), pp.27-28&lt;/ref&gt; According to Christiane Gruber, other works use images to promote [[Sunni]] Islam, such as a set of Mi'raj illustrations (MS H 2154) in the early 14th century,&lt;ref&gt;Gruber (2010), quote p. 43; generally pp.29-45&lt;/ref&gt; although other historians have dated the same illustrations to the [[Jalayrid]] period of Shia rulers.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book| publisher = Tauris Academic Studies| isbn = 184511499X| last = Gruber| first = Christiane| title = The Ilkhanid Book of Ascension| date = 2010-03-15| page=25}}&lt;/ref&gt;   
[[File:Muhammad_destroying_idols_-_L'Histoire_Merveilleuse_en_Vers_de_Mahomet_BNF.jpg|thumb|left|The destruction of idols at the [[Kaaba]]. [[Muhammad]] (top left and mounted at right){{fact|date=November 2011}} is represented as a flaming [[aureole]]. From ''Hamla-i haydarî'' (&quot;Haydar's Battle&quot;), [[Kashmir]], 1808.]]

Depictions of Muhammad are also found in Persian manuscripts in the following [[Timurid dynasty|Timurid]] and [[Safavid dynasty|Safavid]] dynasties, and Turkish [[Ottoman Empire|Ottoman]] art in the 14th to 17th centuries, and beyond. Perhaps the most elaborate cycle of illustrations of Muhammad's life is the late 16th century copy of the 14th century biography ''[[Siyer-i Nebi]]'' commissioned by the Ottoman sultan [[Murat III]] for his son, the future [[Mehmed III]], containing over 800 illustrations.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book| publisher = Hürriyet Vakfı Yayınları| last = Tanındı| first = Zeren| title = Siyer-i nebî: İslam tasvir sanatında Hz. Muhammedʹin hayatı| date = 1984}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Probably the commonest narrative scene represented is the [[Mi'raj]]; according to Gruber, &quot;There exist countless single-page paintings of the meʿrāj included in the beginnings of Persian and Turkish romances and epic stories produced from the beginning of the 15th century to the 20th century&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;Gruber (Iranica)&lt;/ref&gt;  These images were also used in celebrations of the anniversary of the Mi'raj on 27 [[Rajab]], when the accounts were recited aloud to male groups: &quot;Didactic and engaging, oral stories of the ascension seem to have had the religious goal of inducing attitudes of praise among their audiences&quot;.  Such practices are most easily documented in the 18th and 19th centuries, but manuscripts from much earlier appear to have fulfilled the same function.&lt;ref&gt;Gruber (2010), p.43&lt;/ref&gt;  Otherwise a large number of different scenes may be represented at times, from the Prophet's birth to the end of his life, and his existence in Paradise.&lt;ref&gt;The birth is rare, but appears in an early manuscript in Edinburgh&lt;/ref&gt;

In the earliest depictions Muhammad may be shown with or without a [[halo (religious iconography)|halo]], the earliest halos being round in the style of Christian art,&lt;ref&gt;Arnold, 95&lt;/ref&gt;, but before long a flaming halo or [[aureole]] in the [[Buddhist]] or Chinese tradition becomes more common than the circular form found in the West, when a halo is used.  A halo or flame may surround only his head, but often his whole body, and in some images the body itself cannot be seen for the halo.  This &quot;luminous&quot; form of representation avoided the issues caused by &quot;veristic&quot; images, and could be taken to convey qualities of the Prophet's person described in texts.&lt;ref&gt;Gruber, 230, 236&lt;/ref&gt;  If the body is visible, the face may be covered with a veil (see gallery for examples of both types). This form of representation, which began at the start of the [[Safavid]] period in Persia,&lt;ref&gt;Brend, Barbara. ''Islamic Art'', p. 161, British Museum Press.&lt;/ref&gt; was done out of reverence and respect.&lt;ref name=&quot;Arnold&quot;/&gt; Other [[prophets of Islam]], and the Prophet's wives and relations, may be treated in similar ways if they also appear.

[[Thomas Walker Arnold|T. W. Arnold]] (1864-1930), an early historian of Islamic art, stated that &quot;Islam has never welcomed painting as a handmaid of religion as both Buddhism and Christianity have done. Mosques have never been decorated with religious pictures, nor has a pictorial art been employed for the instruction of the heathen or for the edification of the faithful.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;Arnold&quot; /&gt; Comparing Islam to Christianity, he also writes: &quot;Accordingly, there has never been any historical tradition in the religious painting of Islam – no artistic development in the representation of accepted types – no schools of painters of religious subjects; least of all has there been any guidance on the part of leaders of religious thought corresponding to that of ecclesiastical authorities in the Christian Church.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;Arnold&quot; /&gt;

Images of the Prophet remain controversial to the present day, and are not considered acceptable in many countries in the Middle East.  For example in 1963 an account by a Turkish author of a [[Hajj]] pilgrimage to [[Mecca]] was banned in [[Pakistan]] because it contained reproductions of miniatures showing the Prophet unveiled.&lt;ref&gt;Schimmel, Annemarie, ''Deciphering the signs of God: a phenomenological approach to Islam'', p.45, n. 86, SUNY Press, 1994, ISBN 0791419827, 9780791419823&lt;/ref&gt;  However in Iran depictions have considerable acceptance to the present day, and may be found in the modern forms of the poster and [[postcard]].&lt;ref&gt;Gruber (2010), p.253, illustrates a postcard bought in 2001.&lt;/ref&gt;


&lt;div align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
&lt;gallery&gt;
Image:Investiture of Ali Edinburgh codex.jpg| The Investiture of [[Ali]] at [[Ghadir Khumm]], [[MS Arab 161]], fol. 162r, AD 1309/8 [[Ilkhanid]] manuscript illustration.
Image:Muammad-as-youth-meeting-monk-bahira-compendium-persia-1315-edin-550.jpg|Muhammad meets the monk [[Bahira]]. From [[Jami Al-Tawarikh]] (&quot;The Universal History&quot; written by [[Rashid-al-Din Hamadani|Rashid Al-Din]]), a manuscript in the Library of the [[University of Edinburgh]]; illustrated in [[Tabriz]], [[Muzaffarids|Muzaffarid]] period, [[Circa|c.]] 1315.
Image:Mohammed_kaaba_1315.jpg|Miniature of Muhammad re-dedicating the [[Black Stone]] at the [[Kaaba]]. From [[Jami Al-Tawarikh]], c. 1315
Image:Muhammad-Majmac-al-tawarikh-1.jpg|Muhammad's Call to Prophecy and the First Revelation; in the [[Majmac al-tawarikh]] (Compendium of Histories), ca. 1425; [[Timurid dynasty|Timurid]], [[Herat]], [[Afghanistan]]
Image:Muhammad-Majmac-al-tawarikh-2.jpg|''Journey of the Prophet Muhammad'' in the Majmac al-tawarikh (Compendium of Histories), ca. 1425; Timurid. Herat, Afghanistan.

&lt;!--Image:MuhammadBirth.jpg |Birth of Muhammad (16th century Ottoman illustration of the [[Siyer-i Nebi]])--&gt;
Image:Siyer-i_Nebi_151b.jpg|&quot;Muhammad at the Ka'ba&quot; from [[Siyer-i Nebi]], a 16th-century [[Ottoman Empire|Ottoman]] manuscript, probably by [[Nakkaş Osman]].&lt;ref&gt;http://www.ee.bilkent.edu.tr/~history/ottoman33.html&lt;/ref&gt; Muhammad is shown with veiled face.
&lt;!--Image:Muhammad advancing on Mecca.jpg |Muhammad advancing on Mecca, with the angels [[Gabriel]], [[Michael (archangel)|Michael]], [[Israfil]] and [[Azrail]] (16th century Ottoman illustration of the [[Siyer-i Nebi]])--&gt;
Image:Medieval Persian manuscript Muhammad leads Abraham Moses Jesus.jpg|Muhammad leads [[Abraham]], [[Moses]], [[Jesus]] and others in prayer. Persian miniature
Image:Miraj_by_Sultan_Muhammad.jpg|A 16th century [[Persia]]n miniature painting with a veiled Muhammad's ascent into the Heavens, a journey known as the [[Miraj]].
Image:Maome.jpg |Muhammad delivering [[The Farewell Sermon]], 17th century Ottoman copy of an early 14th century Persian image.&lt;ref&gt;From an illustrated version of Al-Biruni's 11th c. ''[[Vestiges of the Past]]'' (Bibliothèque Nationale, Paris, Arabe 1489 fol. 5v. (Bibliothèque Nationale on-line catalog [http://mandragore.bnf.fr/jsp/rechercheExperte.jsp''Mandragore'']&lt;/ref&gt;
Image:Banu Qurayza.png|Detail showing the Prophet, Ali, and the Companions at the Massacre of the Prisoners of the Jewish Tribe of Beni Qurayzah, 19th century text by Muhammad Rafi Bazil.  Both Muhammad (upper right) and Ali (center) are depicted as columns of flame rather than illustrated directly.
&lt;!--Image:MuhammadBirth.jpg |Birth of Muhammad (16th century Ottoman illustration of the [[Siyer-i Nebi]])--&gt;
File:Mohammed receiving the submission of the Banu Nadir.jpg|Mohammad (riding the horse) receiving the submission of the [[Banu Nadir]].
Image:Mohammed´s Paradise.jpg|&quot;Mohammed's Paradise,&quot; Persian miniature from ''The History of Mohammed'', [[BnF]], Paris.
&lt;/gallery&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

===Cinema===
{{main|List of films about Muhammad}}
Very few films have depicted Muhammad.  The only modern one to do so was the 1976 ''The Message'', also known as ''[[Mohammad, Messenger of God]]''. The movie focused on other persons and never directly showed Muhammad, or most members of his family.  When Muhammad was essential to a scene, the camera would show events from his point of view.&lt;ref name=Message&gt;{{cite web|url=http://taylorandfrancis.metapress.com/index/L7M5247402032139.pdf|title=The image of Muhammad in The Message, the first and only feature film about the Prophet of Islam|format=pdf|author=Freek L. Bakker|month=January | year=2006|publisher=Routledge, &quot;Islam and Christian-Muslim Relations&quot;, Vol. 17, No.1|accessdate=2007-07-06}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Two well-known [[fatwa]]s from [[Al-Azhar]] University and Shiite Council of Lebanon were issued about ''The Message''.
:&quot;''It is certainly probable that this is not the result of the creativity of the filmmakers but of the rules announced by the Islamic scholars of the Azhar and the Shiite Council of Lebanon, who prohibited any representation of Muhammad's wives as well as of the Prophet himself.&quot;''&lt;ref name=Message/&gt;

A more severe case occurred in Egypt in 1926, around the anticipated production of a film about the grandeur of the early days of Islam. Upon learning of this plan, the Islamic [[Al-Azhar University]] in Cairo alerted Egyptian public opinion, and published a juridical decision ([[fatwa]]), stipulating that Islam categorically forbids the representation of Muhammad and his companions on the screen. [[King Fuad I of Egypt|King Fauad]] sent a severe warning to actor [[Youssef Wahbi]], threatening to exile him and strip him of his Egyptian nationality.&lt;ref name=fatwa_important&gt;{{cite book|author=Alessandra. Raengo &amp; Robert Stam |title = A Companion To Literature And Film |publisher = Blackwell Publishing |year = 2004|isbn=063123053X |pages=31}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Other contemporary [[Shi'a]] scholars, outside Shi'a majority [[Iran]], have taken a relaxed attitude towards pictures of Muhammad and his household, the [[Ahlul Bayt]]. A fatwa given by [[Ali al-Sistani]], the [[Shi'a]] [[marja]] of Iraq, states that it is permissible to depict Muhammad, even in television or movies, if done with respect.&lt;ref name=sistani&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.sistani.org/html/eng/menu/4/?lang=eng&amp;view=d&amp;code=234&amp;page=1|title=Istifta|accessdate=2006-03-10}}&lt;/ref&gt; A devotional cartoon called ''Muhammad: The Last Prophet'' was released in 2004.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.finemediagroup.com/user/finemedia/press.cfm|title=Fine Media Group|accessdate=2006-03-11}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Depiction by non-Muslims==
{{Commons category|Western depictions of Muhammad}}
Muhammad figures frequently in depictions of influential people in world history. Such depictions tend to be favourable or neutral in intent; one example can be found at the [[United_States_Supreme_Court_building#Sculptural_program|United States Supreme Court building]] in [[Washington, D.C.]]. A frieze including major historical lawgivers places Muhammad alongside [[Hammurabi]], [[Moses]], [[Confucius]], and others. Because of a 1997 controversy surrounding the frieze, tourist materials have been edited so they call the depiction &quot;a well-intentioned attempt by the sculptor to honor Muhammad&quot; that &quot;bears no resemblance to Muhammad.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.dailyrepublican.com/sup_crt_frieze.html|title=The Daily Republican: Supreme Court Frieze|accessdate=2006-03-13}}&lt;/ref&gt; In 1955, a statue of Muhammad was removed from a courthouse in New York City after the ambassadors of [[Indonesia]], Pakistan, and [[Egypt]] requested its removal.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.yourmailinglistprovider.com/pubarchive_show_message.php?montrealmuslimnews+7289|accessdate=2006-03-10|first=2006-02-12|title=Archive &quot;Montreal News Network&quot;: Images of Muhammad, Gone for Good}} {{Dead link|date=October 2010|bot=H3llBot}}&lt;/ref&gt;

There have also been numerous book illustrations showing Muhammad.

[[Dante]], in ''[[The Divine Comedy#Inferno|The Divine Comedy: Inferno]]'', placed Muhammad in Hell, with his entrails hanging out (Canto 28):

:No barrel, not even one where the hoops and staves go every which way, was ever split open like one frayed Sinner I saw, ripped from chin to where we fart&lt;!-- this is the actual quotation; do not remove--&gt; below.
:His guts hung between his legs and displayed His vital organs, including that wretched sack Which converts to shit&lt;!-- this is the actual quotation; do not remove --&gt; whatever gets conveyed down the gullet.
:As I stared at him he looked back And with his hands pulled his chest open, Saying, ''&quot;See how I split open the crack in myself! See how twisted and broken Mohammed is! Before me walks [[Ali]], his face Cleft from chin to crown, grief–stricken.&quot;''&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|author=Seth Zimmerman|title=The Inferno of Dante Alighieri |page=191 |url=http://books.google.com/books?id=r3hWDEjN7JcC&amp;pg=PA191#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false |year=2003 |publisher=iUniverse |isbn=0-595-28090-0}}&lt;/ref&gt;

This scene is frequently shown in illustrations of the ''[[The Divine Comedy|Divina Commedia]]''. For example it is represented in a 15th century [[fresco]] in [[Bologna, Italy]], in the [[Church of San Petronio]],&lt;ref name=fresco&gt;{{cite web|url=http://arts.guardian.co.uk/news/story/0,11711,742914,00.html|title=Al-Qaida plot to blow up Bologna church fresco|date=2002-06-24|work=[[The Guardian]]|author=Philip Willan}}&lt;/ref&gt; and artwork by [[Salvador Dalí]], [[Auguste Rodin]], [[William Blake]], and [[Gustave Doré]].&lt;ref name=Chronicle&gt;{{cite web|url=http://sfgate.com/cgi-bin/article.cgi?file=/c/a/2006/02/11/MNGRCH6UQK1.DTL|title=What's behind Muslim cartoon outrage|date=2006-02-11|work=[[San Francisco Chronicle]]|author=Ayesha Akram}}&lt;/ref&gt;


&lt;div align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
&lt;gallery&gt;
Image:Mahomet.jpg|Portrait of Muhammad as a generic &quot;Easterner&quot;, from the ''PANSEBEIA, or A View of all Religions in the World'' by [[Alexander Ross (writer)|Alexander Ross]] (1683).
Image:Lifeofmahomet.jpg|An engraving of [[Muhammad]] in ''The Life of Mahomet'' (1719).
Image:Muhammad_blake.jpg|[[William Blake]], Muhammad pulling his chest open in an illustration to [[Dante]]'s ''[[The Divine Comedy|Inferno]]'' (1827).
Image:Scotusnfrieze.jpeg|Muhammad as depicted by sculptor [[Adolph Weinman]] on the [[United States Supreme Court building|U.S. Supreme Court building]] in [[Washington, DC]] carrying a sword and the [[Quran]].
Image:Mohameddemons2.jpg|Renaissance [[fresco]] illustrating the negative view of Islam held by Europeans. Muhammad is depicted being tortured in Hell.
Image:La.Vie.de.Mahomet.jpg|This illustration is taken from La vie de Mahomet, by M. Prideaux, published in 1699. It shows Muhammad holding a sword and a crescent while trampling on a globe, a cross, and the Ten Commandments.
Image:Mohammed2.jpg|''Muhammed and the [[Bahira|Monk Sergius]]'' (Bahira). This 1508 [[engraving]] by the Dutch artist [[Lucas van Leyden]] shows [[Bahira#Later_legend|a legend that circulated in Europe]].
&lt;/gallery&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

==Recent controversies==
The start of the 21st century has been marked by controversies over depictions of Muhammad, not only for recent caricatures or cartoons, but also regarding the display of historical artwork.  In 2002, Italian police reported that they had disrupted a terrorist plot to destroy a church in [[Bologna]], which contains a 15th century [[fresco]] depicting an image of Muhammad.&lt;ref name=fresco/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0CE2D9163CF931A1575BC0A9649C8B63|title=Italy frees Fresco Suspects|date=2002-08-22|work=[[New York Times]]}}&lt;/ref&gt;  In 2005, worldwide media attention focused on the [[Jyllands-Posten Muhammad cartoons controversy|controversy surrounding a dozen editorial cartoons published in the ''Jyllands-Posten'']].

===Cartoons===
[[Image:Jyllands-Posten-pg3-article-in-Sept-30-2005-edition-of-KulturWeekend-entitled-Muhammeds-ansigt.png|thumb|200px|[[Jyllands-Posten Muhammad cartoons controversy|Controversial cartoons of Muhammad]], first published in ''[[Jyllands-Posten]]'' in September 2005.]]

{{see|Jyllands-Posten Muhammad cartoons controversy}}

In 2005, a Danish newspaper published a set of [[editorial cartoons]], many of which depicted Muhammad. In late 2005 and early 2006, Danish Muslim organizations ignited a [[Jyllands-Posten Muhammad cartoons controversy|controversy]] through public protests and by spreading knowledge of the publication of the cartoons.&lt;ref name=Halicks/&gt; According to John Woods, Islamic history professor at the University of Chicago, it was not simply the depiction of Muhammad that was offensive, but the implication that Muhammad was somehow a supporter of terrorism.&lt;ref name=explaining/&gt; On 12 February 2008 the Danish police arrested three men alleged to be involved in a plot to  assassinate [[Kurt Westergaard]], one of the cartoonists.&lt;ref&gt;Staff. [http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/world/europe/7240481.stm Danish cartoons 'plotters' held] [[BBC]], 12 February 2008&lt;/ref&gt;

In 2005, an episode of ''[[30 Days (TV series)|30 Days]]'' with [[Morgan Spurlock]], titled &quot;Muslims and America,&quot; depicted Muhammad twice, in a cartoon explaining the origins of the Islamic faith. There was no outcry over this.{{Citation needed|date=May 2010}} In 2006, the controversial American [[animated]] television comedy program ''[[South Park]]'', which had previously depicted Muhammad as a [[superhero]] character in the July 4, 2001 episode &quot;[[Super Best Friends]]&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite episode | title = Super Best Friends | episodelink = Super Best Friends | series = South Park | serieslink = South Park | airdate = 2001-07-04 | season = 5 | number = 68}}&lt;/ref&gt; and has depicted Muhammad in the opening sequence since that episode,&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.tvsquad.com/2006/04/15/south-parks-been-showing-muhammad-all-season/ Ryan j Budke. &quot;South Park's been showing Muhammad all season!&quot; TVSquad.com; April 15, 2006]&lt;/ref&gt; attempted to satirize the Danish newspaper incident. In the episode &quot;[[Cartoon Wars Part II]]&quot;, they intended to show Muhammad handing a salmon helmet to [[Peter Griffin]], a character in the [[Fox Broadcasting Company|Fox]] animated television show ''[[Family Guy]]''. However, [[Comedy Central]], the [[parent company]] of ''South Park'', rejected the scene, citing concerns of violent protests in the [[Islamic world]]. The creators of ''South Park'' reacted by instead satirizing Comedy Central's [[double standard]] for broadcast acceptability by including a segment in which [[President of the United States|American president]] [[George W. Bush]] and [[Jesus]] defecate on the [[flag of the United States]].

[[Image:South park muhammad.jpg|thumb|210 px|left|Muhammad appeared in the 2001 ''[[South Park]]'' episode &quot;[[Super Best Friends]]&quot;. The prophet's image was later removed from the 2006 episode &quot;[[Cartoon Wars Part II|Cartoon Wars]]&quot; and the 2010 episodes &quot;[[200 (South Park)|200]]&quot; and &quot;[[201 (South Park)|201]]&quot; due to controversies regarding Muhammad cartoons in European newspapers.]]
The [[Lars Vilks Muhammad drawings controversy]] began in July 2007 with a series of drawings by [[Sweden|Swedish]] artist [[Lars Vilks]] which depicted Muhammad as a [[roundabout dog]]. Several art galleries in Sweden declined to show the drawings, citing security concerns and fear of violence. The controversy gained international attention after the [[Örebro]]-based regional newspaper ''[[Nerikes Allehanda]]'' published one of the drawings on August 18 to illustrate an [[editorial]] on [[self-censorship]] and [[freedom of religion]].&lt;ref name=na&gt;{{cite news |first=Lars |last=Ströman |title=Rätten att förlöjliga en religion |url=http://www.na.se/artikel.asp?intId=1209627 |publisher=[[Nerikes Allehanda]] |language=Swedish |date=2007-08-18 |accessdate=2007-08-31 |archiveurl = http://web.archive.org/web/20070906190721/http://www.na.se/artikel.asp?intId=1209627 &lt;!-- Bot retrieved archive --&gt; |archivedate = 2007-09-06}}&lt;br/&gt;English translation: {{cite news |first=Lars |last=Ströman |title=The right to ridicule a religion |url=http://www.na.se/artikel.asp?intId=1209676 |publisher=[[Nerikes Allehanda]] |date=2007-08-28 |accessdate=2007-08-31 |archiveurl = http://web.archive.org/web/20070830163657/http://www.na.se/artikel.asp?intId=1209676 &lt;!-- Bot retrieved archive --&gt; |archivedate = 2007-08-30}}&lt;/ref&gt; While several other leading Swedish newspapers had published the drawings already, this particular publication led to protests from [[Islam in Sweden|Muslims in Sweden]] as well as official condemnations from several foreign governments including [[Iran]],&lt;ref name=iran&gt;{{cite news |title=Iran protests over Swedish Muhammad cartoon |url=http://www.thelocal.se/8305/20070827/ |publisher=[[Agence France-Presse]] |date=2007-08-27 |accessdate=2007-08-27}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Pakistan]],&lt;ref name=pakistan&gt;{{cite press release |title=PAKISTAN CONDEMNS THE PUBLICATION OF OFFENSIVE SKETCH IN SWEDEN |publisher=[[Pakistan Ministry of Foreign Affairs]] |date=2007-08-30 |url=http://www.mofa.gov.pk/Press_Releases/2007/Aug/PR_234_07.htm |accessdate=2007-08-31}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Afghanistan]],&lt;ref name=afghanistan&gt;{{cite news |first=Sayed |last=Salahuddin |title=Indignant Afghanistan slams Prophet Mohammad sketch |url=http://in.reuters.com/article/SouthAsiaNews/idINIndia-29281220070901 |publisher=[[Reuters]] |date=2007-09-01 |accessdate=2007-09-09}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Egypt]]&lt;ref name=egypt&gt;{{cite news |first=Gwladys |last=Fouché |title=Egypt wades into Swedish cartoons row |url=http://media.guardian.co.uk/presspublishing/story/0,,2161595,00.html |publisher=[[The Guardian]] |date=2007-09-03 |accessdate=2007-09-09}}&lt;/ref&gt; and [[Jordan]],&lt;ref name=jordan&gt;{{cite news |title=Jordan condemns new Swedish Mohammed cartoon |url=http://news.yahoo.com/s/afp/20070903/wl_mideast_afp/jordanswedenislam_070903124623 |publisher=[[Agence France-Presse]] |date=2007-09-03 |accessdate=2007-09-09}} {{Dead link|date=October 2010|bot=H3llBot}}&lt;/ref&gt; as well as by the inter-governmental [[Organisation of the Islamic Conference]] (OIC).&lt;ref name=oic&gt;{{cite press release |title=The Secretary General strongly condemned the publishing of blasphemous caricatures of prophet Muhammad by Swedish artist |publisher=[[Organisation of the Islamic Conference]] |date=2007-08-30 |url=http://www.oic-oci.org/press/English/2007/08/caricatur.htm |accessdate=2007-09-09}}&lt;/ref&gt; The controversy occurred about one and a half years after the [[Jyllands-Posten Muhammad cartoons controversy|''Jyllands-Posten'' Muhammad cartoons controversy]] in Denmark in early 2006.

Another controversy emerged in September 2007 when [[Bangladesh]]i cartoonist [[Arifur Rahman]] was detained on suspicion of showing disrespect to Muhammad.  The interim government confiscated copies of the [[Bengali language|Bengali]]-language ''[[Prothom Alo]]'' in which the drawings appeared. The cartoon consisted of a boy holding a cat conversing with an elderly man.  The man asks the boy his name, and he replies &quot;Babu&quot;. The older man chides him for not mentioning the name of Muhammad before his name. He then points to the cat and asks the boy what it is called, and the boy replies &quot;Muhammad the cat&quot;. The cartoon caused a firestorm in Bangladesh, with militant [[Islamists]] demanding that Rahman be executed for [[blasphemy]]. A group of people [[book burning|torched copies of the paper]] and several Islamic groups protested, saying the drawings ridiculed Mohammad and his companions. They demanded &quot;exemplary punishment&quot; for the paper's editor and the cartoonist. Bangladesh, however, does not have a blasphemy law, although one had been demanded by the same extremist Islamic groups.

===Sooreh Hera===
[[Image:Sooreh hera-021 cropped.jpg|thumb|200px|One of Sooreh Hera's images from 2007]]
In December 2007, controversy erupted in [[the Netherlands]] when Iranian artist Sooreh Hera exhibited photos of two [[homosexuality in Iran|Iranian gay men]] in a series of sexually provocative positions, wearing masks depicting Muhammad and his son-in-law [[Ali]]. The photo series was intended to highlight the hypocrisy the artist saw, of Muslim [[men who have sex with men|married men engaging in sexual relations with other men]]. The [[Gemeentemuseum Den Haag|Hague Municipal Museum]] expressed interest in buying the series, but refused to display it, citing fear that it could &quot;offend certain groups&quot;. Dutch politician [[Geert Wilders]], leader of the [[Partij voor de Vrijheid]] ([[Party for Freedom]]), excoriated the museum's decision, saying it was &quot;based on fear&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;[http://gayswithoutborders.wordpress.com/2007/12/05/allah-o-gay-bar-sooreh-hera-depicts-muhammed-as-homosexual/ &quot;Allah o gay bar&quot;]; gayswithoutborders.com; Retrieved on 2007-12-06&lt;/ref&gt;

===Wikipedia article===
&lt;!-- Deleted image removed: [[Image:Faraz Ahmad.jpeg|thumb|right|150px|A self-uploaded image of Faraz Ahmad, the editor who started the petition]] --&gt;
In 2008, several Muslims protested against the inclusion of Muhammad's depictions in [[Muhammad|Wikipedia's ''Muhammad'' article]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
 | url = http://www.foxnews.com/story/0,2933,328966,00.html
 | title = Muslims Protest Wikipedia Images of Muhammad
 | publisher = [[Fox News]]
 | date = 2008-02-06
 | accessdate = 2008-02-07
}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;NY&quot;&gt;{{cite web
 | url = http://www.nytimes.com/2008/02/05/books/05wiki.html
 | title = Wikipedia Islam Entry Is Criticized
 | author = Noam Cohen
 | publisher = [[New York Times]]
 | date = 2008-02-05
 | accessdate = 2008-02-07
}}&lt;/ref&gt;
An [[online petition]] claims to have collected over 450,000 signatures in three months (December 2007 to February 2008). The petition was started by Faraz Ahmad of [[Daska|Daska, Pakistan]], resident in [[Glasgow]], formerly editing Wikipedia as &quot;Farazilu&quot;.&lt;!--&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.thepetitionsite.com/2/removal-of-the-pic-of-muhammad-from-wikipedia.go petition homepage] (hosted by [[Care2]]). see also&quot;[[Wikipedia:Wikipedia Signpost/2008-02-11/Muhammad image|Petition seeks to remove images of Muhammad]]&quot; ''Wikipedia Signpost'' 11 February 2008.&lt;/ref&gt;--&gt;
The petition specifies opposition to a reproduction of a 17th century Ottoman copy of a 14th century [[Ilkhanate]] manuscript image ([[MS Arabe 1489]]) depicting Muhammad as he prohibited Nasīʾ, a special form of [[intercalary month]]s practiced in Arabia.&lt;ref&gt;MS Arabe 1489. The image used by Wikipedia is hosted on [[Wikimedia Commons]] ([http://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/0/0d/Maome.jpg upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/0/0d/Maome.jpg]). The reproduction originates from the website of the [[Bibliothèque nationale de France]] [http://expositions.bnf.fr/livrarab/pedago/grands/0_01.htm].&lt;/ref&gt;
Jeremy Henzell-Thomas of ''[[The American Muslim]]'' deplored the petition as one of &quot;these mechanical knee-jerk reactions&quot; which, &quot;are gifts to those who seek every opportunity to decry Islam and ridicule Muslims and can only exacerbate a situation in which Muslims and the Western media seem to be locked in an ever-descending spiral of ignorance and mutual loathing&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.theamericanmuslim.org/tam.php/features/articles/wikipedia_and_depictions_of_the_prophet_muhammad_the_latest_inane_distracti/0015659 Wikipedia and Depictions of the Prophet Muhammad: The Latest Inane Distraction], 10 February 2008&lt;/ref&gt;

Wikipedia considered but rejected a compromise that would allow visitors to choose whether to view the page with images.&lt;ref name=&quot;NY&quot;/&gt; The Wikipedia community has not acted upon the petition.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.guardian.co.uk/technology/2008/feb/17/wikipedia.islam?gusrc=rss&amp;feed=worldnews Wikipedia defies 180,000 demands to remove images of the Prophet] ''[[The Guardian]]'' 17 February  2008&lt;/ref&gt; The site's [[Talk:Muhammad/FAQ|answers to frequently asked questions about these images]] state that Wikipedia does not censor itself for the benefit of any one group.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.informationweek.com/news/showArticle.jhtml?articleID=206106192 Wikipedia Refuses To Delete Picture Of Muhammad] ''[[Information Week]]'' 7 February 2008.&lt;/ref&gt;
[[File:Everybody Draw Mohammed Day.jpg|thumb|left|120px|Cartoon, &quot;Everybody Draw Mohammed Day!&quot;]]

===Metropolitan Museum of Art===
The [[Metropolitan Museum of Art]] in January 2010 confirmed to the ''[[New York Post]]'' that it had quietly removed all historic paintings which contained depictions of Muhammad from public exhibition. The Museum quoted objections on the part of conservative Muslims which were &quot;under review.&quot;
The museum's action was criticized as excessive [[political correctness]], also apparent in other recent decision, including the renaming of the &quot;Primitive Art Galleries&quot; to the &quot;Arts of Africa, Oceania and the Americas&quot; and the projected &quot;Islamic Galleries&quot; to &quot;Arab Lands, Turkey, Iran, Central Asia and Later South Asia&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.nypost.com/p/news/local/manhattan/jihad_jitters_at_met_76yj3VNUy4hcRAnhOcPCHP 'Jihad' jitters at Met – Mohammed art gone] by Isabel Vincent, 10 January 2010.&lt;/ref&gt;

===Everybody Draw Mohammed Day===
{{main|Everybody Draw Mohammed Day}}
Everybody Draw Mohammed Day was a protest against those who threatened violence against artists who drew representations of Muhammad. It began as a protest against the action of  [[Comedy Central]] in forbidding the broadcast of the ''[[South Park]]'' episode [[201 (South Park)|&quot;201&quot;]] in response to [[death threat]]s against some of those responsible for the segment. Observance of the day began with a drawing posted on the [[Internet]] on April 20, 2010, accompanied by text suggesting that &quot;everybody&quot; create a drawing representing Muhammad, on May 20, 2010, as a protest against efforts to limit [[freedom of speech]].

==See also==
{{Portal box|Culture|Islam|Middle Ages|Visual arts}}
*[[Qadam Rasul]]
*''[[The Satanic Verses]]'' by [[Salman Rushdie]]

;Controversial depictions
*[[Idomeneo (controversy)|Idomeneo controversy]]
{{-}}




==Notes==
{{reflist|2}}

==References==
*{{Cite book| publisher = Gorgias Press LLC| isbn = 9781931956918| last = Arnold| first = Thomas W.| title = Painting in Islam, a Study of the Place of Pictorial Art in Muslim Culture| date = (First published 1928, reprint 2002-11| pages=91–9}}
*{{cite | author=Ali, Wijdan | url=http://www2.let.uu.nl/Solis/anpt/ejos/pdf4/07Ali.pdf  |format=PDF| title=From the Literal to the Spiritual: The Development of Prophet Muhammad's Portrayal from 13th Century Ilkhanid Miniatures to 17th Century Ottoman Art | periodical=Proceedings of the 11th International Congress of Turkish Art | editor=M. Kiel, N. Landman, and H. Theunissen | volume=7 | issue=1–24 | publisher=Utrecht | location=The Netherlands | date=23–28 August| pages=7 |archiveurl = http://web.archive.org/web/20071201123841/http://www2.let.uu.nl/Solis/anpt/ejos/pdf4/07Ali.pdf |archivedate = 2007-12-01}}
*[[Oleg Grabar|Grabar, Oleg]], ''The Story of Portraits of the Prophet Muhammad'', in ''Studia Islamica'', 2004, p. 19 onwards.
*&quot;Gruber (2005)&quot;, Gruber, Christiane, ''Representations of the Prophet Muhammad in Islamic painting'', in Gulru Necipoglu, Karen Leal eds., [[Muqarnas (journal)|Muqarnas]], Volume 26, 2009, BRILL, ISBN 900417589X, 9789004175891, [http://books.google.co.uk/books?id=Gq6obUbnqsMC&amp;pg=PA247&amp;dq=%22Depiction+of+Muhammad%22+Muqarnas&amp;hl=en&amp;ei=dSCTTaONA8OZ8QOPjs3mAw&amp;sa=X&amp;oi=book_result&amp;ct=result&amp;resnum=1&amp;ved=0CDEQ6AEwAA#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false google books]
*&quot;Gruber (2010)&quot;, Gruber, Christiane J., ''The Prophet's ascension: cross-cultural encounters with the Islamic mi'rāj tales'', Christiane J. Gruber, Frederick Stephen Colby (eds), Indiana University Press, 2010, ISBN 0253353610, 9780253353610, [http://books.google.co.uk/books?id=sjLHirJmvPUC&amp;pg=PA247&amp;dq=gruber+Muhammad&amp;hl=en&amp;ei=v6WuTqbIIM7dsgbmqYHDBA&amp;sa=X&amp;oi=book_result&amp;ct=result&amp;resnum=1&amp;ved=0CC4Q6AEwAA#v=onepage&amp;q=gruber%20Muhammad&amp;f=false google books]
*&quot;Gruber (Iranica)&quot;,  Gruber, Christiane, &quot;MEʿRĀJ ii. Illustrations&quot;, in ''[[Encyclopedia Iranica]]'', 2009, [http://www.iranicaonline.org/articles/meraj-ii-illustrations online]

==External links==
{{Commons category|Depictions of Muhammad}}
*[http://www.hf.uib.no/religion/popularikonografi/devotion04.html Devotion in pictures: Muslim popular iconography], [[University of Bergen]]
*[http://www.sfusd.k12.ca.us/schwww/sch618/Art/Art3.html &quot;Religious&quot; Paintings in Islamic Art]
*[http://zombietime.com/mohammed_image_archive/ Mohammed Image Archive: Depictions of Mohammed Throughout History]
*[http://www.bodley.ox.ac.uk/dept/scwmss/wmss/medieval/jpegs/holkham/misc/48/1500/04800419.jpg Mohammed in Virgil's Inferno 28]
{{Depictions of Muhammad|state=autocollapse}}

[[Category:Depictions of Muhammad| ]]
[[Category:Iconography]]
[[Category:Idolatry]]
[[Category:Censorship in Islam]]

[[de:Bilderverbot im Islam]]
[[fr:Représentation figurée dans les arts de l'Islam]]
[[it:Raffigurazioni di Maometto]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
