<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="20527929" ns="0" title="Graduated response"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">'''Graduated response''', also known as '''three strikes''', is an approach, adopted in several countries, aimed at addressing  online [[copyright infringement]].

In response to copyright infringement using [[peer-to-peer]] software, the [[creative industries]], reliant on copyright, advocate what is known as a &quot;graduated response&quot; which sees consumers disconnected after a number of notification letters warning that they are infringing copyright. The content industry has thought to gain the co-operation of [[internet service providers]] (ISPs), asking them to provide subscriber information for [[IP addresses]] identified by the content industry as engaged in copyright infringement.&lt;ref name=&quot;Klosek&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.mondaq.com/article.asp?articleid=67534|title=United States: Combating Piracy And protecting privacy: A European Perspective |last=Klosek  |first=Jacqueline |date=9 October 2008 |publisher= Mondaq}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Early developments ==
The content industry's proposal for [[internet service providers]] to cut off Internet access to a subscriber who had received three warning letters of alleged copyright infringement was initially known as &quot;three strikes&quot;, based on the baseball rule of &quot;[[English language idioms derived from baseball|three strikes and you're out]]&quot;. Because &quot;three strikes&quot; was understood to refer to physical assault, the approach was later termed &quot;graduated response&quot;. Media attention has focused on attempts to implement such an approach in France (see the [[HADOPI law]]) and the UK (see the [[Digital Economy Act 2010]]), though the approach, or variations of it, has been implemented in a number of other countries, or attempts are made to do so.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web| last = Anderson| first = Nate| title = IFPI: “Three strikes” efforts hit worldwide home run| publisher = Ars Technica| date = 19 August 2008| url = http://arstechnica.com/tech-policy/news/2008/08/ifpi-three-strikes-efforts-hit-worldwide-home-run.ars| accessdate = 26 July 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In a number of European countries early attempts to implement a graduated response have led to court cases to establish under which circumstances an ISP may provide subscriber data to the content industry. In order to pursue those that download copyrighted material the individual committing the infringing must be identified. Internet users are often only identifiable by their Internet Protocol address ([[IP address]]), which distinguishes the virtual location of a particular [[computer]]. Many ISPs allocate a pool of IP addresses as needed, rather than assigning each computer a never-changing static IP address. Using ISP subscriber information the content industry has thought to remedy copyright infringement, assuming that the ISPs are legally responsible for end user activity, and that the end user is responsible for all illegal activity connected to his or hers IP address.&lt;ref name=&quot;Klosek&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://forbrukerportalen.no/Artikler/2008/ISP%20liability_Norwegian%20Consumer%20Council%20warns%20consumers%20not%20to%20sign%20letter%20of%20guilt|title=ISP liability: Norwegian Consumer Council warns consumers not to sign letter of guilt |last=Herseth Kaldestad |first=Oyvind |date=28 February 2008 |publisher= Forbrukerradet}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In 2005 a Dutch court ordered ISPs in the Netherlands to not divulge subscriber information because of the way the Dutch content industry group had collected the [[IP address]]es (Foundation v. [[UPC Netherlands]]). According to Dutch law ISPs can only be ordered to provide personal subscriber data if it is plausible that an unlawful act occurred, and if it is shown beyond a [[reasonable doubt]] that the subscriber information will identify the person who committed the infringing act. In Germany court specifically considered the right to privacy and in March 2008 the [[German Federal Constitutional Court]] ruled that ISPs could only give out IP address subscription information in case of a &quot;serious criminal investigation&quot;. The court furthermore ruled that copyright infringement did not qualify as a serious enough offense. Subsequently, in April 2008, the [[Bundestag]] (German parliament) approved a new law requiring ISPs to divulge the identity of suspected infringers who infringe on a commercial scale. In Spain the Spanish Supreme Court recently ruled that personal data associated with an IP address could only be disclosed in the course of a criminal investigation or for public safety reasons (Productores de Música de España v. Telefónica de España SAU). In Italy courts established that criminally liability does not extend to file sharing copyrighted material, as long as it is not done for commercial gain. Ruling on a case involving a copyright holder employed a third party to collect IP addresses of suspected copyright infringers, the Italian Data Protection Authority ruled in February 2008 that the systematic monitoring [[peer-to-peer]] activities for the purpose of detecting copyright infringers and suing them.&lt;ref name=&quot;Klosek&quot;/&gt;

== Approach ==
The graduated response may vary form country to country, though the [[European Data Protection Supervisor]] has summarised the approach as follows:
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&quot;...copyright holders using automated technical means, possibly provided by third parties, would identify alleged copyright infringement by engaging in monitoring of Internet users’ activities, for example, via the surveillance of forums, blogs or by posing as file sharers in peer-to-peer networks to identify file sharers who allegedly exchange copyright material. After identifying Internet users alleged to be engaged in copyright violation by collecting their Internet Protocol addresses (IP addresses), copyright holders would send the IP addresses of those users to the relevant Internet service provider(s) who would warn the subscriber to whom the IP address belongs about his potential engagement in copyright infringement. Being warned by the ISP a certain number of times would automatically result in the ISP's termination or suspension of the subscriber’s Internet connection.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book| title = Opinion of the European Data Protection Supervisor on the current negotiations by the European Union of an Anti-Counterfeiting Trade Agreement (ACTA)| publisher = [[European Data Protection Supervisor]]| date = 22 February 2010| pages = 3–4| url = http://www.edps.europa.eu/EDPSWEB/webdav/site/mySite/shared/Documents/Consultation/Opinions/2010/10-02-22_ACTA_EN.pdf}}&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

== Supporters ==
It has been promoted by the [[Recording Industry Association of America]] and other national bodies.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.readwriteweb.com/archives/riaa_drops_lawsuits_-_makes_de.php|title=Pirates Rejoice: RIAA Drops Lawsuits, Makes Deal with ISPs|date=2008-12-19|publisher=ReadWriteWeb|accessdate=2009-03-16}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.eff.org/deeplinks/2008/12/riaa-v-people-turns-lawsuits-3-strikes|title=RIAA v. The People Turns from Lawsuits to 3 Strikes|date=2008-12-19|publisher=Electronic Frontier Foundation|accessdate=2009-03-16}}&lt;/ref&gt; Consumers' association ''[[Which?]]'' favours the initiative, calling measures &quot;proportionate&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.which.co.uk/news/2010/04/law-firm-to-quit-chasing-file-sharing-pirates-210736 Law firm to quit chasing file sharing pirates] ''Which?'' 9 April 2010.&lt;/ref&gt;

== Opposition ==
Many [[consumer rights]] groups have argued that the graduated response denies consumers the [[right to a fair trial]] and the [[right to privacy]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://forbrukerportalen.no/Artikler/2008/Norwegian%20Consumer%20Council%20calls%20for%20Internet%20complaint%20board|title=Norwegian Consumer Council calls for Internet complaint board |last=Herseth Kaldestad |first=Oyvind |date=9 September 2008 |publisher= Forbrukerradet}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Klosek&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.mondaq.com/article.asp?articleid=67534|title=United States: Combating Piracy And protecting privacy: A European Perspective |last=Klosek  |first=Jacqueline |date=9 October 2008 |publisher= Mondaq}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Graduated response laws ==
In October 2008 a number of other European countries were considering the implementation of a graduated response to copyright infringement via the internet, including [[France]] and [[United Kingdom|Britain]].

=== France ===
In [[France]] President [[Nicolas Sarkozy]] backed the proposal to implement a graduated response law&lt;ref name=&quot;Klosek&quot;/&gt; and the French government passed a three strikes policy in the [[HADOPI law]]. The law was initially rejected by the [[Constitutional Council of France]] for contravening the [[Constitution of France]] and [[Declaration of the Rights of Man and of the Citizen]].&lt;ref&gt;http://www.conseil-constitutionnel.fr/conseil-constitutionnel/francais/les-decisions/2009/decisions-par-date/2009/2009-580-dc/communique-de-presse.42667.html&lt;/ref&gt;

=== New Zealand ===
[[New Zealand]] was one of the first countries to enact a three strikes policy, but its implementation was delayed for a month pending development of a code of practice and may be deferred indefinitely.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.3news.co.nz/Government-delays-introduction-of-controversial-S92A/tabid/412/articleID/92441/cat/73/Default.aspx|title=Government delays introduction of controversial 'S92A'|date=2009-02-23|publisher=Channel 3 News|accessdate=2009-03-16}}&lt;/ref&gt; It was revealed that the US was instrumental in the implementation of this policy.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.zeropaid.com/news/93326/new-zealands-three-strikes-law-was-pushed-bought-and-paid-for-by-the-us-wikileaks/|title=New Zealands Three Strikes Law was Pushed, Bought and Paid for by the US – Wikileaks|date=2011-5-1}}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== United Kingdom ===
In January 2009 the British government announced its plans to legislate a graduated response system for [[peer-to-peer]] [[copyright infringement]]. In the report entitled ''Digital Britain'' the government includes plans for a mandatory &quot;code&quot; for ISPs to follow, as well as the creation of a government &quot;Rights Agency&quot; to help stakeholders deal with the issue of “civil copyright”. Under the proposed scheme the UK government would legislate a &quot;Code on unlawful file-sharing&quot; that’s ISPs would have to follow and would establish &quot;appeals and standards of evidence&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://arstechnica.com/tech-policy/news/2009/01/digital-britain-will-legislate-graduated-response-for-isps.ars | title=&quot;Digital Britain&quot; to legislate graduated response for ISPs| last=Anderson | first=Nate | date=29 January 2009 | publisher= ArsTechnica}}&lt;/ref&gt; Since late 2009 [[Great Britain]]'s [[Lord Mandelson]] is pushing ahead with plans to impose a graduated response through the [[Digital Economy Bill]]&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news| url=http://www.guardian.co.uk/technology/2009/oct/28/mandelson-date-blocking-filesharers-connections | work=The Guardian | location=London | title=Lord Mandelson sets date for blocking filesharers' internet connections | first=Mark | last=Sweney | date=2009-10-28 | accessdate=2010-05-04}}&lt;/ref&gt;, despite the [[Gowers Review of Intellectual Property|Gower's report]] and [[Digital Britain|Lord Carter's Digital Britain]] report advising against it.{{Citation needed|date=March 2009}} The Act has now been passed into law.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Controversial UK anti-piracy law finally passed|publisher= Telecoms Europe|date=|url=http://www.telecomseurope.net/content/controversial-uk-anti-piracy-law-finally-passed?section=HEADLINE&amp;utm_source=lyris&amp;utm_medium=newsletter&amp;utm_campaign=telecomseurope|accessdate=9 April 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== South Korea ===
[[South Korea]] adopted a graduated response system in July 2009.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.apaaonline.org/pdf/APAA_56th_&amp;_57th_council_meeting/copyright/2-Korea%20Copyright%20Cttee%20Country%20Report%202009.pdf | title=Annual Report 2009 – Korea | last=Asian Patent Attorney's Association | date=18 November 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt; Article 133bis of the Korean Copyright Act allows the Korean Copyright Commission to recommend ISPs to suspend the accounts of repeat file sharing offenders (as adjudged by the Commission) for six months. However, users' email accounts are not to be suspended.

== Graduated response business policy ==
=== Ireland ===
Attempts in [[Ireland]] to implement three strikes for a number of ISPs have resulted in court proceedings, the latest of which concerned data protection issues. See [[Internet censorship in Ireland]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://johnnyryan.wordpress.com/2010/04/24/three-strikes-copyright-and-copytight/ | title=Overview of three strikes measures around the world 2010 | last=IIEA | date=May 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== See also ==
=== Related organizations ===
* [[Directorate-General for Information Society and Media (European Commission)]]
* [[European Round Table of Industrialists]]
* [[World Summit on the Information Society]]
* [[World Intellectual Property Organization]]
* [[World Intellectual Wealth Organisation]]

=== Related topics ===
* [[Anti-Counterfeiting Trade Agreement]]
* [[Copyright]]
* [[Copyright infringement]]
* [[Counterfeit]]
* [[Digital rights]]
* [[Information freedom]]
* [[Secondary liability]]

==References==
{{Reflist|2}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Graduated Response}}
[[Category:Copyright enforcement]]
[[Category:Recording Industry Association of America]]

[[it:Risposta graduale]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
