<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="20598015" ns="0" title="Brachiosaurus"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Other uses}}
{{italictitle}}
{{pp-move-indef}}
{{Automatic taxobox
| name = ''Brachiosaurus''
| fossil_range = [[Late Jurassic]], {{Fossil range|154|153}}
| image = FMNH Brachiosaurus.JPG
| image_width = 250px
| image_caption = Mounted skeleton cast, [[Field Museum of Natural History]]
| display_parents = 3
| taxon = Brachiosaurus altithorax
| parent_authority = [[Elmer S. Riggs|Riggs]], 1903
| authority = Riggs, 1903
}}

'''''Brachiosaurus''''' {{IPA-en|ˌbrækiəˈsɔrəs|}} is a [[genus]] of [[sauropod]] [[dinosaur]] from the [[Jurassic]] [[Morrison Formation]] of [[North America]]. It was first described by [[Elmer S. Riggs]] in 1903 from fossils found in the Grand River Canyon (now [[Colorado River]]) of western [[Colorado]], in the [[United States]]. Riggs named the dinosaur ''Brachiosaurus altithorax'', declaring it &quot;the largest known dinosaur&quot;. ''Brachiosaurus''  had a proportionally long neck, small skull, and large overall size, all of which are typical for sauropods. However, the proportions of ''Brachiosaurus'' are unlike most sauropods. The forelimbs were longer than the hindlimbs, which result in a steeply inclined trunk, making the overall body shape reminiscent of a modern [[giraffe]]. Also, while the tail is a typical long dinosaur tail, it was relatively short for a sauropod.

''Brachiosaurus'' is the namesake genus of the family [[Brachiosauridae]], which includes a handful of other similar sauropods. Much of what is known by laypeople about ''Brachiosaurus'' is in fact based on ''[[Giraffatitan|Giraffatitan brancai]]'', a species of brachiosaurid dinosaur from the [[Tendaguru]] Formation of [[Tanzania]] that was originally described by German paleontologist [[Werner Janensch]] as a species of ''Brachiosaurus''. Recent research shows that the differences between the type species of ''Brachiosaurus'' and the Tendaguru material are significant enough that the African material should be placed in a separate genus. Several other potential species of ''Brachiosaurus'' have been described from [[Africa]] and [[Europe]], but none of them are thought to belong to ''Brachiosaurus'' at this time.

''Brachiosaurus'' is one of the rarer sauropods of the Morrison Formation.  The [[holotype|type specimen]] of ''B. altithorax'' is still the most complete specimen, and only a relative handful of other specimens are thought to belong to the genus. It is regarded as a high [[browsing (predation)|browser]], probably cropping or nipping vegetation as high as possibly {{convert|9|m|ft}} off of the ground. Unlike other sauropods, and its depiction in ''[[Jurassic Park (film)|Jurassic Park]]'', it was unsuited for rearing on its hindlimbs.  It has been used an example of a dinosaur that was most likely [[ectothermic]] due to its large size and the corresponding need for [[forage]], but more recent research finds it to have been [[warm-blooded]].

==Description==
[[Image:Brachiosaurus DB.jpg|thumb|left|Life restoration]] 
Like all sauropod dinosaurs, ''Brachiosaurus'' was a quadrupedal animal with a small skull, a long neck, a large trunk with a high-ellipsoid cross section, a long, muscular tail and slender, columnar limbs.&lt;ref name=upchurch&amp;al2004&gt;Upchurch, P., Barrett, P.M. &amp; Dodson, P. (2004): &quot;Sauropoda.&quot; Pp. 259-322 in Weishampel, D.B., Dodson, P. and Osmolska, H. (eds.): ''The Dinosauria, Second Edition''. University of California Press, Berkeley. ISBN 9780520242098&lt;/ref&gt; The skull had a robust, wide muzzle and thick jaw bones, with spoon–shaped teeth.  As in ''Giraffatitan'', there was an arch of bone over the snout and in front of the eyes that encircled the nasal opening, although this arch was not as large as in its relative.&lt;ref name=foster2007b&gt;Foster, J. (2007). &quot;''Brachiosaurus altithorax''.&quot; ''Jurassic West: The Dinosaurs of the Morrison Formation and Their World''. Indiana University Press. pp. 205–208.&lt;/ref&gt; Large air sacs connected to the lung system were present in the neck and trunk, invading the [[vertebra]]e and ribs, greatly reducing the overall density.&lt;ref name=wedel2003a&gt;Wedel, M.J. (2003). &quot;Vertebral pneumaticity, air sacs, and the physiology of sauropod dinosaurs.&quot; ''Paleobiology'' '''29''':243-255.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=wedel2003b&gt;Wedel, M.J. (2003). &quot;The evolution of vertebral pneumaticity in sauropod dinosaurs.&quot; ''Journal of Vertebrate Paleontology'' '''23''':344-357.&lt;/ref&gt; Unusually for a sauropod, the forelimbs were longer than the hind limbs. The [[humerus]] (upper arm bone) of ''Brachiosaurus'' was relatively lightly built for its size,&lt;ref name=taylor2009&gt;Taylor, M.P. (2009). &quot;[http://www.miketaylor.org.uk/dino/pubs/taylor2009/Taylor2009-brachiosaurus-and-giraffatitan.pdf A re-evaluation of ''Brachiosaurus altithorax'' Riggs 1903 (Dinosauria, Sauropoda) and its generic separation from ''Giraffatitan brancai'' (Janensh 1914)].&quot; ''Journal of Vertebrate Paleontology'', '''29'''(3): 787-806.&lt;/ref&gt; measuring {{convert|2.04|m|ft}} in length in the type specimen.&lt;ref name=riggs1903&gt;Riggs, E.S. (1903). [http://books.google.com/books?id=1PjRAAAAMAAJ&amp;pg=PR6&amp;lpg=PR6&amp;dq=%22Brachiosaurus+altithorax,+the+largest+known+dinosaur%22&amp;source=bl&amp;ots=TKCG6wx3LZ&amp;sig=2NQ81hDw0TrzaGD3b6Qi7WmQSCw&amp;hl=en&amp;ei=qr3oS9BUpfA0wOKo1Qk&amp;sa=X&amp;oi=book_result&amp;ct=result&amp;resnum=3&amp;ved=0CBkQ6AEwAg#v=onepage&amp;q=%22Brachiosaurus%20altithorax%2C%20the%20largest%20known%20dinosaur%22&amp;f=false &quot;''Brachiosaurus altithorax'', the largest known dinosaur.&quot;] ''American Journal of Science'' (series 4) '''15'''(88): 299-306.&lt;/ref&gt; The [[femur]] (thigh bone) of the type specimen was only {{convert|2.03|m|ft}} long.&lt;ref name=riggs1903/&gt; Unlike other sauropods, ''Brachiosaurus'' appears to have been slightly sprawled at the shoulder joint,&lt;ref name=taylor2009/&gt; and the ribcage was unusually deep.&lt;ref name=riggs1903/&gt; This led to the trunk being inclined, with the front much higher than the hips, and the neck exiting the trunk at a steep angle. Overall, this shape resembles a giraffe more than any other living animal.&lt;ref name=paul1988&gt;{{Cite journal|last=Paul |first=G.S. |year=1988 |title=The brachiosaur giants of the Morrison and Tendaguru with a description of a new subgenus, ''Giraffatitan'', and a comparison of the world's largest dinosaurs |journal=Hunteria |volume=2 |issue=3}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Size===
[[Image:Brachiosaurus scale.png|thumb|Size compared to a human]] 
Because &quot;Brachiosaurus&quot; ''brancai'' (''Giraffatitan'') is known from much more complete material than ''B. altithorax'', most size estimates for ''Brachiosaurus'' are actually for the African form. There is an additional element of uncertainty for North American ''Brachiosaurus'' because the most complete skeleton appears to have come from a [[subadult]].&lt;ref name=taylor2009/&gt; Over the years, the mass of ''B. altithorax'' has been estimated as {{convert|35.0|MT|ST}},&lt;ref name=paul1988/&gt; {{convert|43.9|MT|ST}},&lt;ref name=Foster2003&gt;{{Cite book|last=Foster |first=J.R. |title=Paleoecological analysis of the vertebrate fauna of the Morrison Formation (Upper Jurassic), Rocky Mountain region, U.S.A. |year=2003 |series=New Mexico Museum of Natural History and Science Bulletin, '''23''' |publisher=New Mexico Museum of Natural History and Science |location=Albuquerque, New Mexico}}&lt;/ref&gt; and, most recently, {{convert|28.7|MT|ST}}.&lt;ref name=taylor2009/&gt;  In the first and last cases, the authors also provided estimates for ''Giraffatitan'', and found that genus to be somewhat lighter ({{convert|31.5|MT|ST}} for Paul [1988]&lt;ref name=paul1988/&gt; and {{convert|23.3|MT|ST}} for Taylor [2009]&lt;ref name=taylor2009/&gt;).   The length of ''Brachiosaurus'' has been estimated at {{convert|26|m|ft}}.&lt;ref name=holtz2008&gt;Holtz, T.R. Jr. (2008) ''Dinosaurs: The Most Complete, Up-to-Date Encyclopedia for Dinosaur Lovers of All Ages'' [http://www.geol.umd.edu/~tholtz/dinoappendix/DinoappendixSummer2008.pdf Supplementary Information]&lt;/ref&gt;

==Classification==
''Brachiosaurus'' is the namesake genus of [[Brachiosauridae]].&lt;ref name=riggs1904&gt;{{Cite journal|last=Riggs |first=E.S. |year=1904 |title=Structure and relationships of opisthocoelian dinosaurs. Part II. The Brachiosauridae |journal= Geological Series (Field Columbian Museum) |volume=2 |issue=6 |pages=229–247 |url=http://books.google.com/?id=9y2PAAAAMAAJ&amp;pg=PA246-IA49&amp;lpg=PA246-IA49&amp;dq=%22Structure+and+relationships+of+opisthocoelian+dinosaurs%22#v=onepage&amp;q=%22Structure%20and%20relationships%20of%20opisthocoelian%20dinosaurs%22&amp;f=false}}&lt;/ref&gt; Over the years a number of  sauropods have been assigned to Brachiosauridae, such as ''[[Astrodon]]'', ''[[Bothriospondylus]]'', ''[[Dinodocus]]'', ''[[Pelorosaurus]]'', ''[[Pleurocoelus]]'', and ''[[Ultrasaurus]]'',&lt;ref name=lambert1990&gt;{{Cite book|last=Lambert |first=David |coauthors=and the Diagram Group |title=The Dinosaur Data Book |year=1990 |publisher=Avon Books |location=New York |isbn=0-380-75896-3 |chapter=Brachiosaurids |page=142}}&lt;/ref&gt; but most of these are currently regarded as [[nomen dubium|dubious]] or of uncertain placement.&lt;ref name=upchurch&amp;al2004/&gt; A [[cladistics|phylogenetic analysis]] of sauropods published in the description of ''[[Abydosaurus]]'' found that genus to form a [[clade]] with ''Brachiosaurus'' and ''Giraffatitan'' (included in ''Brachiosaurus'').&lt;ref name=chure&amp;al2010&gt;{{Cite journal|last=Chure |first=D. |coauthors=Britt, B.; Whitlock, J. A.; and Wilson, J. A. |year=2010 |title=First complete sauropod dinosaur skull from the Cretaceous of the Americas and the evolution of sauropod dentition |journal=[[Naturwissenschaften]] |volume=97|pmid=20179896 |issue=4 |pages=379–391|pmc=2841758 |url=http://www.springerlink.com/content/lpn30h8tx2231223/fulltext.pdf |doi=10.1007/s00114-010-0650-6 }}&lt;/ref&gt; A more recent analysis focused on possible Asian brachiosaurid material found a clade including ''Abydosaurus'', ''Brachiosaurus'', ''[[Cedarosaurus]]'', ''Giraffatitan'', and ''Paluxysaurus'', but not ''[[Qiaowanlong]]'', the putative Asian brachiosaurid.&lt;ref name=ksepkanorell2010&gt;{{cite journal |last=Ksepka |first=D. T. |coauthors=and Norell, M. A. |year=2010 |title=The illusory evidence for Asian Brachiosauridae: new material of ''Erketu ellisoni'' and a phylogenetic appraisal of basal Titanosauriformes |journal=American Museum Novitates |volume=3700 |pages=1–27 |url=http://digitallibrary.amnh.org/dspace/bitstream/2246/6087/1/N3700.pdf |format=pdf |doi=10.1206/3700.2}}&lt;/ref&gt; Related genera include ''Lusotitan'' and ''[[Sauroposeidon]]''.&lt;ref name=upchurch&amp;al2004/&gt; Brachiosauridae is situated at the base of [[Titanosauriformes]], a group of sauropods that also includes the [[titanosaur]]s.&lt;ref name=ksepkanorell2010/&gt;

According to the revised diagnosis by Taylor ''Brachiosaurus altithorax'' is diagnosed by a plethora of characters, many to be found on the dorsal (back) vertebrae.&lt;ref name=taylor2009/&gt; Among the characters playing it in the family Brachiosauridae are a ratio of humerus to femur length greater or equal to 0.9 (i.e., the upper arm bone is at least nearly as long as the thigh bone), and a very flattened femur shaft (ratio ≥1.85).&lt;ref name=taylor2009/&gt;

==Discovery and history==
[[Image:Brach humerus.jpg|thumb|upright|Elmer S. Riggs’ assistant lying by a ''Brachiosaurus altithorax'' humerus during the excavation in 1900]]
The genus ''Brachiosaurus'', and [[type species]] ''B. altithorax'', are based on a partial [[postcrania]]l skeleton from [[Fruita, Colorado|Fruita]], in the valley of the [[Colorado River]] of western Colorado.&lt;ref name=glut1997&gt;{{Cite book|title=Dinosaurs: The Encyclopedia|last=Glut|first=D.F.|publisher=McFarland &amp; Company|year=1997|isbn=0-89950-917-7|chapter=Brachiosaurus|pages=213–221}}&lt;/ref&gt;  This specimen was collected from rocks of the Brushy Basin Member of the Morrison Formation&lt;ref name=turner&amp;peterson1999&gt;{{Cite book|last=Turner |first=C.E. |coauthors=and Peterson, F. |year=1999 |chapter=Biostratigraphy of dinosaurs in the Upper Jurassic Morrison Formation of the Western Interior, USA |editor=Gillete, David D. (ed.) |title=Vertebrate Paleontology in Utah |publisher=Utah Geological Survey |location=Salt Lake City, Utah |series=Miscellaneous Publication 99-1 |pages=77–114 |isbn=1-55791-634-9 }}&lt;/ref&gt; in [[1900 in paleontology|1900]] by [[Elmer S. Riggs]] and his crew from the Field Columbian Museum (now the [[Field Museum of Natural History]]) of [[Chicago]].&lt;ref name=riggs1903/&gt; It is currently cataloged as [[Field Museum of Natural History|FMNH]]&amp;nbsp;P&amp;nbsp;25107.&lt;ref name=taylor2009/&gt; Riggs and company were working in the area as a result of favorable correspondence between Riggs and S. M. Bradbury, a dentist in nearby [[Grand Junction, Colorado|Grand Junction]].  In 1899 Riggs had sent inquiries to rural locations in the western United States concerning fossil finds, and Bradbury, an amateur collector himself, reported that dinosaur bones had been collected in the area since 1885.&lt;ref name=glut1997/&gt;  It was Riggs' field assistant H. W. Menke who found FMNH&amp;nbsp;P&amp;nbsp;25107,&lt;ref name=riggs1903/&gt; on July 4, 1900.&lt;ref name=chenoweth1987&gt;{{cite book |last= Chenoweth |first=W.L. |year=1987 |chapter=The Riggs Hill and Dinosaur Hill sites, Mesa County, Colorado |pages=97–100 |editor=Averett, W. R. (ed.) |title=Paleontology and geology of the Dinosaur Triangle |publisher=Museum of Western Colorado |location=Grand Junction, Colorado |isbn=9999790410}}&lt;/ref&gt; The locality, Riggs Quarry 13, was found on a small hill later known as Riggs Hill; it is marked by a plaque. Additional ''Brachiosaurus'' fossils are reported on Riggs Hill, but other fossil finds on the hill have been vandalized.&lt;ref name=chenoweth1987/&gt;&lt;ref name=lohman1965&gt;{{cite book |last=Lohman |first=S.W. |year=1965 |title=Geology and artesian water supply of the Grand Junction area, Colorado |publisher=U.S. Geological Survey |location=Reston, Virginia |series=Professional Paper 451 |url=http://pubs.er.usgs.gov/publication/pp451}}&lt;/ref&gt; Riggs published a short report in 1901, noting the unusual length of the humerus compared to the femur and the extreme overall size and the resulting giraffe-like proportions, as well as the lesser development of the tail, but did not publish a name for the new dinosaur.&lt;ref name=riggs1901&gt;{{Cite journal|doi=10.1126/science.13.327.549-a|last=Riggs |first=E.S. |year=1091 |title=The largest known dinosaur |journal=Science |volume=13|issue=327 |pages=549–550|pmid=17801098}}&lt;/ref&gt; The titles of Riggs (1901) and (1903) suggested that the specimen was the largest known dinosaur.&lt;ref name=riggs1903/&gt;&lt;ref name=riggs1901/&gt; Riggs followed his 1903 publication that named ''Brachiosaurus altithorax''&lt;ref name=riggs1903/&gt; with a more detailed description in a [[monograph]] in 1904.&lt;ref name=riggs1904/&gt;
[[Image:Brachiosaurus skull.jpg|thumb|left|upright|The Felch Quarry skull as reconstructed by Carpenter and Tidwell]]
The Fruita skeleton was not the first discovery of ''Brachiosaurus'' bones, although it was the first to be recognized as belonging to a new and distinct animal.  In 1883, a sauropod skull was found near [[Garden Park, Colorado|Garden Park]], Colorado, at Felch Quarry 1, and was sent to [[Othniel Charles Marsh]] (of &quot;[[Bone Wars]]&quot; fame).&lt;ref name=taylor2009/&gt; Marsh incorporated the skull into his skeletal restoration of &quot;Brontosaurus&quot; (now ''[[Apatosaurus]]'').&lt;ref name=taylor2009/&gt;&lt;ref name=marsh1891&gt;{{Cite journal|last=Marsh |first=O.C. |year=1891 |title=Restoration of ''Triceratops'' |journal=American Journal of Science |volume=41 |issue=244 |pages=339–342 |url=http://marsh.dinodb.com/marsh/Marsh%201891%20-%20Restoration%20of%20Triceratops%20%28and%20Brontosaurus%29.pdf |format=pdf}}&lt;/ref&gt; It eventually became part of the collections of the [[National Museum of Natural History]], as USNM&amp;nbsp;5730.&lt;ref name=taylor2009/&gt; In the 1970s, when Jack McIntosh and David Berman were working on the issue of the true skull of ''Apatosaurus'', they reevaluated the Garden Park skull as more similar to ''[[Camarasaurus]]''.&lt;ref name=mcintosh&amp;berman1975&gt;{{Cite journal|last=McIntosh |first=J.S. |coauthors=and Berman, D.S. |year=1975 |title=Description of the palate and lower jaw of the sauropod dinosaur ''Diplodocus'' (Reptilia: Saurischia) with remarks on the nature of the skull of ''Apatosaurus'' |journal=Journal of Paleontology |volume=49 |issue=1 |pages=187–199}}&lt;/ref&gt; It was described and recognized as a ''Brachiosaurus'' skull in 1998 by [[Kenneth Carpenter]] and Virginia Tidwell, intermediate in [[morphology (biology)|form]] between ''Camarasaurus'' and ''Giraffatitan brancai'' (then still considered to be ''B. brancai'').&lt;ref name=carp&amp;tid1998&gt;Carpenter, K. and Tidwell, V. (1998). &quot;Preliminary description of a ''Brachiosaurus'' skull from Felch Quarry 1, Garden Park, Colorado.&quot; Pp. 69–84 in: Carpenter, K., Chure, D. and Kirkland, J. (eds.), ''The Upper Jurassic Morrison Formation: An Interdisciplinary Study''. ''Modern Geology'', '''23''':1-4.&lt;/ref&gt;  Because there are no overlapping parts between this skull and FMNH&amp;nbsp;P&amp;nbsp;25107, it cannot be confidently assigned to a species,&lt;ref name=taylor2009/&gt;&lt;ref name=carp&amp;tid1998/&gt; so it is classified as ''Brachiosaurus'' sp.&lt;ref name=carp&amp;tid1998/&gt;

Additional discoveries of ''Brachiosaurus'' material in North America have been uncommon and consist of a handful of bones. Material has been described from Colorado,&lt;ref name=taylor2009/&gt;&lt;ref name=Jjenson1987&gt;{{Cite journal|last=Jensen |first=J.A. |year=1987 |title=New brachiosaur material from the Late Jurassic of Utah and Colorado |journal=The Great Basin Naturalist |volume=47 |issue=4 |pages=592–608}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=curtice&amp;al1996&gt;Curtice, B., Stadtman, K., and Curtice, L. (1996) &quot;A re-assessment of ''Ultrasauros macintoshi'' (Jensen, 1985).&quot; Pp. 87-95 in M. Morales (ed.), ''The Continental Jurassic: Transactions of the Continental Jurassic Symposium'', Museum of Northern Arizona Bulletin number 60.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=curt&amp;stad2001&gt;{{Cite book|last=Curtice |first=B. |coauthors=and Stadtman, K. |year=2001 |chapter=The demise of ''Dystylosaurus edwini'' and a revision of ''Supersaurus vivianae'' |title=Western Association of Vertebrate Paleontologists and Southwest Paleontological Symposium - Proceedings 2001 |editor=McCord, R.D.; and Boaz, D. (eds.) |series=Mesa Southwest Museum Bulletin |volume=8 |pages=33–40}}&lt;/ref&gt; Oklahoma,&lt;ref name=taylor2009/&gt;&lt;ref name=Bonnan&amp;wedel2004&gt;{{Cite journal|last=Bonnan |first=M.F. |coauthors=and Wedel, M.J. |year=2004 |title=First occurrence of ''Brachiosaurus'' (Dinosauria, Sauropoda) from the Upper Jurassic Morrison Formation of Oklahoma |journal=PaleoBios |volume=24 |issue=2 |pages=12–21}}&lt;/ref&gt; Utah,&lt;ref name=taylor2009/&gt;&lt;ref name=Jjenson1987/&gt; and Wyoming,&lt;ref name=taylor2009/&gt;&lt;ref name=Foster2003/&gt; and undescribed material has been mentioned from several other sites.&lt;ref name=taylor2009/&gt;&lt;ref name=turner&amp;peterson1999/&gt; One of these specimens, a [[scapulocoracoid|shoulder blade]] from [[Dry Mesa Quarry]], Colorado, is one of the specimens at the center of the ''[[Supersaurus]]''/''Ultrasauros'' issue of the 1980s and 1990s.  In 1985, [[James A. Jensen]] described disarticulated sauropod remains from the quarry as belonging to several [[taxon|taxa]], including the new genera ''Supersaurus'' and ''Ultrasaurus'',&lt;ref name=jenson1985&gt;{{Cite journal|last=Jensen |first=J.A. |year=1985 |title=Three new sauropod dinosaurs from the Upper Jurassic of Colorado |journal=The Great Basin Naturalist |volume=45 |issue=4 |pages=697–709}}&lt;/ref&gt; the latter renamed ''Ultrasauros'' shortly thereafter because [[Ultrasaurus|another sauropod]] already had the name.&lt;ref name=olshevsky1991&gt;Olshevsky, G. (1991). &quot;A revision of the parainfraclass Archosauria Cope, 1869, excluding the advanced Crocodylia.&quot; ''Mesozoic Meanderings'' '''2''':1-196&lt;/ref&gt; Later study showed that the &quot;ultrasaur&quot; material mostly belonged to ''Supersaurus'', although the shoulder blade did not.  Because the holotype of ''Ultrasauros'', a back vertebra, was one of the specimens that was actually from ''Supersaurus'', the name ''Ultrasauros'' is a synonym of ''Supersaurus''.  The shoulder blade is now assigned to ''Brachiosaurus'', but the species is uncertain.&lt;ref name=taylor2009/&gt;&lt;ref name=curtice&amp;al1996/&gt; In addition, the Dry Mesa &quot;ultrasaur&quot; was not as large as had been thought; the dimensions of the shoulder's [[coracoid]] bone indicate that the animal was smaller than Riggs' original specimen of ''Brachiosaurus''.&lt;ref name=taylor2009/&gt;

===Etymology===
Riggs derived the genus name from the [[Ancient Greek|Greek]] ''brachion''/βραχιων meaning &quot;arm&quot; and ''sauros''/σαυρος meaning &quot;lizard&quot;, because he realized that the length of the arms was unusual for a sauropod.&lt;ref name=riggs1903/&gt; The species epithet &quot;altithorax&quot; was chosen because of the unusually deep and wide chest cavity, from [[Latin]] ''altus'' meaning &quot;deep&quot; and Greek ''thorax''/θώραξ (Latin ''thorax''), meaning &quot;breastplate, cuirass, corslet&quot;.&lt;ref name=thoraxdict&gt;[http://www.perseus.tufts.edu/hopper/text?doc=Perseus%3Atext%3A1999.04.0057%3Aentry%3Dqw%2Frac θώραξ], Henry George Liddell, Robert Scott, ''A Greek-English Lexicon'', on Perseus Digital Library&lt;/ref&gt;

==Species==
===''Brachiosaurus altithorax''===
[[Image:Altithorax.jpg|thumb|Riggs and H.W. Menke working on ''Brachiosaurus altithorax'' bones]]
FMNH&amp;nbsp;P&amp;nbsp;25107, the [[holotype]] of both the genus ''Brachiosaurus'' and the species ''B. altithorax'', consists of the right humerus (upper arm bone), the right femur (thigh bone), the right [[ilium (bone)|ilium]] (a hip bone), the right coracoid (a shoulder bone), the sacrum (fused vertebrae of the hip), the last seven thoracic (trunk) and two caudal (tail) [[vertebra]]e, and a number of ribs.&lt;ref name=taylor2009/&gt;&lt;ref name=riggs1903/&gt;&lt;ref name=riggs1901/&gt; Riggs described the coracoid as from the left side of the body,&lt;ref name=riggs1903/&gt;&lt;ref name=riggs1904/&gt;&lt;ref name=riggs1901/&gt; but restudy has shown it to be a right coracoid.&lt;ref name=taylor2009/&gt;

===Other assigned species===
*''&quot;B.&quot; atalaiensis'': Originally described by [[Albert-Félix de Lapparent|de Lapparent]] and Zbyszewski,&lt;ref name=lapp&amp;zby1957&gt;de Lapparent,A.F. &amp; Zbyszewski, G. (1957). &quot;Les dinosauriens du Portugal&quot;. ''Mémoire Service géologique Portugal'' '''2''':1–63.&lt;/ref&gt; this material's reference to ''Brachiosaurus'' was doubted by Upchurch, Barret and Dodson,&lt;ref name=upchurch&amp;al2004/&gt; who listed it as an unnamed brachiosaurid, and placed in its own genus ''[[Lusotitan]]'' by Antunes and Mateus.&lt;ref name=antunes&amp;mateus2003&gt;{{Cite journal| last = Antunes| first = M.| coauthors = Mateus, O.| title = Dinosaurs of Portugal| journal = Comptes rendus. Palévol | volume = 2| issue = 1| pages = 77–95| year = 2003| doi = 10.1016/S1631-0683(03)00003-4}}&lt;/ref&gt; De Lapparent and Zbyszewski described a series of remains but did not designate a [[type specimen]].  Antunes and Mateus selected a partial postcranial skeleton ([[Museo Geológico do Instituto Geológico e Mineiro|MIGM]]&amp;nbsp;4978, 4798, 4801–4810, 4938, 4944, 4950, 4952, 4958, 4964–4966, 4981–4982, 4985, 8807, 8793–87934) as a [[lectotype]]; this specimen includes 28 vertebrae, [[chevron (anatomy)|chevrons]], ribs, a possible shoulder blade, humeri, forearm bones, partial left pelvis, lower leg bones, and part of the right ankle.  The low neural spines, the prominent deltopectoral crest of the humerus (a muscle attachment site on the upper arm bone), the elongated humerus (very long and slender), and the long axis of the ilium tilted upward indicate that ''Lusotitan'' is a brachiosaurid.&lt;ref name=antunes&amp;mateus2003/&gt;

*''&quot;B.&quot; brancai'': Janensch based his description on &quot;Skelett S&quot; (skeleton S) from Tendaguru,&lt;ref name=janensch1914&gt;Janensch, W. (1914). &quot;Übersicht über der Wirbeltierfauna der Tendaguru-Schichten nebst einer kurzen Charakterisierung der neu aufgefuhrten Arten von Sauropoden.&quot; ''Archiv fur Biontologie'', '''3''': 81–110.&lt;/ref&gt; but later realized that it comprised two partial individuals: S&amp;nbsp;I and S&amp;nbsp;II.&lt;ref name=janensch1929&gt;Janensch, W. (1929). &quot;Material und Formengehalt der Sauropoden in der Ausbeute der Tendaguru-Expedition.&quot; ''Palaeontographica'' '''(Suppl. 7) 2''':1–34.&lt;/ref&gt; He did not designate them as a syntype series, nor specify a lectotype, and Taylor proposed the larger and more complete S&amp;nbsp;II (MB.R.2181) as the lectotype.&lt;ref name=taylor2009/&gt; It includes, among other bones, several dorsal (trunk) vertebrae, the left scapula, both coracoids, both sternals (breastbones), both humeri, both ulna and radii (lower arm bones), a right hand, a partial left hand, both [[pubis (bone)|pubes]] (a hip bone) and the right femur, tibia and fibula (shank bones). A re-assessment of the relation between the African and American brachiosaur material indicates that a separate generic name is warranted for the Tendaguru material, meaning that it now is considered to belong to ''[[Giraffatitan]]''.&lt;ref name=taylor2009/&gt;&lt;ref name=paul1988/&gt;

*''&quot;B.&quot; fraasi'': erected by Janensch in 1914, but later synonomized with ''&quot;B.&quot; brancai'';&lt;ref name=janensch1929/&gt; this material now belongs to ''Giraffatitan''.&lt;ref name=taylor2009/&gt;

*''[[&quot;Brachiosaurus&quot; nougaredi|&quot;B.&quot; nougaredi]]'': This species is known from fragmentary remains discovered in eastern [[Algeria]], in the [[Sahara Desert]]. The present type material consists of a [[sacrum]] and some of the left [[metacarpus|metacarpals]] and [[phalanx bones|phalanges]].  Found at the discovery site but not collected were partial bones of the left forearm, wrist bones, a right shin bone, and fragments that may have come from [[metatarsus|metatarsals]].&lt;ref name=lapparent1960&gt;de Lapparent, A.F. (1960): &quot;Les dinosauriens du &quot;continental intercalaire&quot; du Sahara central&quot; (&quot;The dinosaurs of the &quot;continental intercalaire&quot; of the central Sahara.&quot;) ''Mémoires de la Société Géologic de France, Nouvelle Série'' '''88A''' vol.39(1-6):1-57. [in French; [http://www.paleoglot.org/files/Lapparent_60.pdf a translated version], by Matthew Carrano (pdf, no figures), is available through the Polyglot Paleontologist]&lt;/ref&gt; de Lapparent, who described and named the material in 1960, reported the discovery locality as being in the [[Late Jurassic]]–age [[Taouratine Series]] (he assigned the rocks this age in part because of the presumed presence of ''Brachiosaurus''),&lt;ref name=lapparent1960/&gt; but more recent review assigns it to the &quot;[[Kem Kem Beds|Continental intercalaire]],&quot; which is considered to be of [[Albian]] age (late [[Early Cretaceous]], significantly younger).&lt;ref name=upchurch&amp;al2004/&gt; This material was found disjointed over an area of several hundred meters.&lt;ref name=lapparent1960/&gt;  Upchurch, Barrett and Dodson (2004) doubted its assignment to ''Brachiosaurus'', and listed it as an unnamed brachiosaurid.&lt;ref name=upchurch&amp;al2004/&gt; The sacrum is of notable size, with a length of {{convert|130|cm|in}} for four vertebrae compared to {{convert|95|cm|in}} for five vertebrae in ''B. altithorax''; other bones are not of unusual size in comparison to ''B. altithorax'' or ''Giraffatitan brancai''.&lt;ref name=lapparent1960/&gt;

===Referred material===
[[Image:Brachiosaurus leg bone.jpg|thumb|Front limb bone (humerus) from Potter Creek, USNM 21903]]
Taylor (2009) lists a number of specimens referred to ''Brachiosaurus''. These include some material, e.g., a humerus from Potter Creek and some Dry Mesa material (the latter partly described as ''[[Ultrasauros]]'' by Jensen), that are either clearly not brachiosaurid in origin, or at least not clearly referable to ''Brachiosaurus''.&lt;ref name=taylor2009/&gt; In contrast, a cervical (neck) vertebra and the skull mentioned above may belong to either ''B. altithorax'' or an as-yet unknown brachiosaurid from North America.&lt;ref name=taylor2009/&gt; The cervical was found near Jensen, Utah, by Jensen,&lt;ref name=&quot;Jjenson1987&quot;/&gt; and – if it belongs to ''Brachiosaurus'' – is one of a handful of neck vertebrae known for American brachiosaurids.&lt;ref name=taylor2009/&gt;  There is no unambiguous material of the skull, neck, [[anatomical terms of location|anterior]] dorsal (forward trunk) region, [[anatomical terms of location|distal]] (lower) limbs or feet.&lt;ref name=taylor2009/&gt;

There was ample material referred to ''&quot;B.&quot; brancai'' in the collections of the [[Museum für Naturkunde]] Berlin, some of which was destroyed during [[World War II]]. Other material was transferred to other institution throughout Germany, some of which was also destroyed. Additional specimens are likely among the material collected by the [[British Museum of Natural History]]'s Tendaguru expedition.&lt;ref name=maier2003&gt;Maier, G. (2003). ''African dinosaurs unearthed. The Tendaguru Expeditions.&quot; Bloomington, IN: Indiana University Press.&lt;/ref&gt; Much or all of this material probably belongs to ''Giraffatitan'', although some may represent a new brachiosaurid.&lt;ref name=SVPOW2009-11-18&gt;Taylor, M. (18 Nov. 2009): CT-scanning the Archbishop. Sauropod Vertebrate Picture of the Week (Blog) post at http://svpow.wordpress.com/2009/11/18/ct-scanning-the-archbishop/.&lt;/ref&gt;

===Separation from ''Giraffatitan''===
When describing the brachiosaurid material from Tendaguru in 1914, Janensch listed a number of differences and commonalities between them and ''B. altithorax''.&lt;ref name=janensch1914/&gt; In three further publications in 1929,&lt;ref name=janensch1929/&gt; 1950
&lt;ref name=janensch1950a&gt;Janensch, W. (1950). &quot;Die Wirbelsäule von ''Brachiosaurus brancai''.&quot; ''Palaeontographica'' '''(Suppl. 7) 3''':27–93.&lt;/ref&gt; and 1961&lt;ref name=janensch1961&gt;Janensch, W. (1961). &quot;Die Gliedmaßen und Gliedmaßengürtel der Sauropoden der Tendaguru-Schichten.&quot; '''Palaeontographica (Suppl. 7) 3''':177–235.&lt;/ref&gt; Janensch compared the two species in more detail, listing 13 putative shared characters.&lt;ref name=taylor2009/&gt; Of these, however, only four appear to be valid, while six pertain to more inclusive groups than Brachiosauridae, and the rest are either difficult to assess or refer to material that is not ''Brachiosaurus''.&lt;ref name=taylor2009/&gt;

In 1988, [[Gregory Paul]] published a new reconstruction of the skeleton of ''&quot;B.&quot; brancai'', highlighting a number of differences in proportion between it and ''B. altithorax''. Chief among them is a difference in the way the trunk vertebrae vary: they are fairly uniform in ''B. altithorax'', but vary widely in the African material. Paul believed that the limb and girdle elements of both species were very similar, and therefore suggested to separate them not at [[genus]], but only at [[subgenus]] level.&lt;ref name=paul1988/&gt;

''Giraffatitan'' was raised to genus level by Olshevsky without comment.&lt;ref name=olshevsky1991/&gt; A detailed study of all material, including the limb and girdle bones, by Michael Taylor in 2009 found that there are significant differences between ''Brachiosaurus altithorax'' and the Tendaguru material in all elements known from both species. Taylor found 26 distinct osteological (bone-based) characters, a larger difference than that between, e.g., ''[[Diplodocus]]'' and ''[[Barosaurus]]'', and therefore argued that the African material should be placed in its own genus, ''Giraffatitan'', as ''G. brancai''.&lt;ref name=taylor2009/&gt; An important difference between the two genera is the overall body shape, with ''Brachiosaurus'' having a 23% longer dorsal (trunk) vertebrate series and a 20 to 25% longer and also taller tail.&lt;ref name=taylor2009/&gt;

==Paleoecology==
With the removal of the East African ''Giraffatitan'', ''Brachiosaurus'' is known only from the [[Morrison Formation]] of western North America.&lt;ref name=taylor2009/&gt;  The Morrison Formation is interpreted as a [[semiarid]] environment with distinct [[wet season|wet]] and [[dry season]]s,&lt;ref name=russell1989&gt;{{Cite book|last=Russell |first=D. A. |authorlink=Dale Russell |title=An Odyssey in Time: Dinosaurs of North America |year=1989 |publisher=NorthWord  Press |location=Minocqua, Wisconsin |isbn=1-55971-038-1 |pages=64–70 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=engelmann&amp;al04&gt;Engelmann, G.F.; Chure, D.J.; and Fiorillo, A.R. (2004). &quot;The implications of a dry climate for the paleoecology of the fauna of the Upper Jurassic Morrison Formation.&quot; ''Sedimentary Geology'' '''167'''(3-4):297-308.&lt;/ref&gt; and flat [[floodplain]]s.&lt;ref name=russell1989/&gt; Vegetation varied from [[gallery forest]]s (river–lining forests in otherwise treeless settings) of [[conifer]]s, [[tree fern]]s, and [[fern]]s, to fern [[savanna]]s with rare ''[[Araucaria]]''-like trees.&lt;ref name=carpenter2006&gt;{{Cite book|last=Carpenter |first=K. |authorlink=Kenneth Carpenter |year=2006  |chapter=Biggest of the big: a critical re-evaluation  of the mega-sauropod  ''Amphicoelias fragillimus'' |editors=Foster, J. R.; and Lucas, S. G. (eds.) |title=Paleontology and Geology of the Upper Jurassic Morrison Formation |series=New Mexico Museum of Natural History and Science Bulletin, '''36'''  |publisher=New Mexico Museum of Natural History and Science |location=Albuquerque, New Mexico |pages=131–138 }}&lt;/ref&gt;  Several other sauropod genera were present in the Morrison Formation, with differing body proportions and feeding adaptations.&lt;ref name=Foster2003/&gt; Among these were ''[[Apatosaurus]]'', ''[[Barosaurus]]'', ''[[Camarasaurus]]'', ''[[Diplodocus]]'', ''[[Haplocanthosaurus]]'', and ''[[Supersaurus]]''.&lt;ref name=Foster2003/&gt;&lt;ref name=Dchure&amp;al2006&gt;{{Cite book|last=Chure |first=D.J. |coauthors=Litwin, R.; Hasiotis, S.T.; Evanoff, E.; and Carpenter, K. |year=2006 |chapter=The fauna and flora of the Morrison Formation: 2006 |editor=Foster, J.R.; and Lucas, S.G. (eds.) |title=Paleontology and Geology of the Upper Jurassic Morrison Formation |series=New Mexico Museum of Natural History and Science Bulletin, '''36''' |publisher=New Mexico Museum of Natural History and Science |location=Albuquerque, New Mexico |pages=233–248}}&lt;/ref&gt; ''Brachiosaurus'' was one of the less abundant Morrison Formation sauropods.  In a survey of over 200 fossil localities, John Foster reported 12 specimens of the genus, comparable to ''Barosaurus'' (13) and ''Haplocanthosaurus'' (12), but far fewer than ''Apatosaurus'' (112), ''Camarasaurus'' (179), and ''Diplodocus'' (98).&lt;ref name=Foster2003/&gt; ''Brachiosaurus'' fossils are found only in the lower-middle part of the expansive Morrison Formation (stratigraphic zones 2-4), dated to about 154-153 million years ago,&lt;ref name=turner1999&gt;Turner, C.E. and Peterson, F., (1999). &quot;Biostratigraphy of dinosaurs in the Upper Jurassic Morrison Formation of the Western Interior, U.S.A.&quot; Pp. 77–114 in Gillette, D.D. (ed.), ''Vertebrate Paleontology in Utah''. Utah Geological Survey Miscellaneous Publication 99-1.&lt;/ref&gt; unlike many other types of sauropod which have been found throughout the formation.&lt;ref name=Foster2003/&gt;

==Paleobiology==
===Neck position===
In contrast to most other sauropods, brachiosaurids had an inclined back, due to their long forelimbs. Therefore, if the neck exited the body in a straight line, it already pointed upwards.&lt;ref name=taylor2009/&gt;&lt;ref name=stevensparrish1999&gt;Stevens, K. A. and Parrish, M. J. (1999). &quot;Neck posture and feeding habits of two Jurassic sauropod dinosaurs.&quot; ''Science'' '''284''':798–800. doi:10.1126/science.284.5415.798&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=stevensparrish2005&gt;Stevens, K. A. and Parrish, M. J. (2005). &quot;Digital reconstructions of sauropod dinosaurs and implications for feeding.&quot; In ''The sauropods: evolution and paleobiology'' (eds. J. A.Wilson &amp; K. Curry-Rogers), pp. 178–200. Berkeley, CA: University of California Press.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=stevensparrish2005b&gt;Stevens, K. A. and Parrish, M. J. (2005). &quot;Neck posture, dentition and feeding strategies in Jurassic sauropod dinosaurs.&quot; In ''Thunder Lizards: The Sauropodomorph dinosaurs&quot; (eds. V. Tidwell &amp; K. Carpenter). Bloomington, IN: Indiana University Press.&lt;/ref&gt; The exact angle is influenced by how the pectoral girdle is reconstructed, that is how the shoulder blades are placed on the ribcage.&lt;ref name=stevensparrish1999/&gt;&lt;ref name=stevensparrish2005/&gt;&lt;ref name=stevensparrish2005b/&gt; The mobility of the neck was reconstructed as quite low by Stevens and Parrish,&lt;ref name=stevensparrish1999/&gt;&lt;ref name=stevensparrish2005/&gt;&lt;ref name=stevensparrish2005b/&gt; while other researchers like Paul and Christian and Dzemski argued for more flexible necks.&lt;ref name=paul1988/&gt;&lt;ref name=dzemskichristian2007&gt;Dzemski, G. and Christian, A. (2007). &quot;Flexibility along the neck of the ostrich (''Struthio camelus'') and consequences for the reconstruction of dinosaurs with extreme neck length.&quot; ''Journal of Morphology'' '''268''':701-714.&lt;/ref&gt;
===Nostril placement===
[[File:Brachiosaurus nostrils placement.PNG|thumb|left|alt=Various Brachiosaurus nostrils placement.|Digital reconstructions showing three of the most likely placements of the fleshy nostrils in ''Brachiosaurus'', '''C''' being currently regarded as the most likely option.&lt;ref name=Naish2009&gt;{{cite web | last = Naish | first = D. |title=Junk in the trunk: why sauropod dinosaurs did not possess trunks |url=http://scienceblogs.com/tetrapodzoology/2009/03/junk_in_the_trunk.php |publisher=ScienceBlogs |date=March 20, 2009 |pages= |isbn= |doi= |accessdate=}}&lt;/ref&gt;]]
The placement of ''Brachiosaurus'' nostrils has been the source of much debate with Witmer (2001)&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal| last = Witmer | first = L.M.|title=Nostril position in dinosaurs and other vertebrates and its significance for nasal function |journal=Science | volume = 293 | issue = 5531 | pages = 850–853 |year=2001 |doi= 10.1126/science.1062681 |accessdate= | url=http://bill.srnr.arizona.edu/classes/182h/vertebrate%20evolution/DinosaurNoses.pdf | pmid=11486085}}&lt;/ref&gt; describing in ''[[Science (journal)|Science]]'' the hypothesized position of the fleshy nostrils in ''Brachiosaurus'' in as many as five possible locations.

There has also been the hypothesis of various sauropods, such as ''Brachiosaurus'', possessing a trunk. The fact that there were no narrow-snouted sauropods (''Brachiosaurus'' included) tends to discredit such a hypothesis. Stronger evidence for the absence of a trunk is found in the teeth wear of ''Brachiosaurus'', which shows the kind of wear that would result from biting and tearing off of plant matter rather than purely grinding, which would be the result of having already ripped the leaves and branches off with its trunk.&lt;ref name=Naish2009 /&gt;

===Feeding ecology===
''Brachiosaurus'' is thought to have been a high [[browsing (predation)|browser]], feeding on foliage well above the ground.  Even if it did not hold its neck near vertical, and instead had a straighter neck, its head height may still have been over {{convert|9|m|ft}} above the ground.&lt;ref name=foster2007b/&gt;&lt;ref name=Foster2003/&gt; It probably fed mostly on foliage above {{convert|5|m|ft}}. This does not preclude the possibility that it also fed lower at times, between {{convert|3|to|5|m|ft}} up.&lt;ref name=foster2007b/&gt; Its diet likely consisted of ginkgoes, conifers, tree ferns, and large cycads, with intake estimated at {{convert|200|to|400|kg|lb}} of plant matter daily.&lt;ref name=foster2007b/&gt; However, more recent studies estimate that ~{{convert|240|kg|lb}} of plant matter would have been sufficient to feed a {{convert|70|MT|ST}} sauropod,&lt;ref name=hummel&amp;al2008&gt;Hummel, J., Gee, C.T., Südekum, K.-H., Sander, P.M., Nogge, G. and Clauss, M. (2008). &quot;In vitro digestibility of fern and gymnosperm foliage: implications for sauropod feeding ecology and diet selection&quot;. ''Proceedings of the Royal Society B'', '''275''':1015-1021. doi:10.1098/rspb.2007.1728&lt;/ref&gt; so ''Brachiosaurus'' may have required only about {{convert|120|kg|lb}} of fodder a day. Brachiosaur feeding involved simple up–and–down jaw motion. The teeth were arranged to shear material as they closed, and were probably used to crop and/or nip vegetation.&lt;ref name=bar&amp;up05&gt;{{Cite book|last=Barrett |first=Paul M. |coauthors=and Upchurch, Paul |year=2005 |chapter=Sauropodomorph diversity through time |title=The Sauropods: Evolution and Paleobiology |editors=Curry Rogers, Kristina A.; and Wilson, Jeffrey A. |pages=125–156 |publisher=University of California |location=Berkeley, CA |isbn=0-520-24623-3}}&lt;/ref&gt;

It has repeatedly been suggested, e.g. in the movie ''[[Jurassic Park (film)|Jurassic Park]]'', that ''Brachiosaurus'' could rear into a bipedal or tripodal (with tail support) pose to feed. However, a detailed physical modelling-based analysis of sauropod rearing capabilities by Heinrich Mallison showed that while many sauropods could rear, the unusual brachiosaurid body shape and limb length ratio made them exceptionally ill suited for rearing. The forward position of the center of mass would have led to problems with stability, and required unreasonably large forces in the hips to obtain an upright posture. ''Brachiosaurus'' would also have gained relatively little from rearing (only 33% more feeding height), compared to other sauropods, for which a bipedal pose may have tripled the feeding height.&lt;ref name=mallisonsaubook2&gt;Mallison, H. (2011). &quot;Rearing Giants – kinetic-dynamic modeling of sauropod bipedal and tripodal poses.&quot; In Klein, N., Remes, K., Gee, C. &amp; Sander M. (eds): ''Biology of the Sauropod Dinosaurs: Understanding the life of giants.'' Life of the Past (series ed. Farlow, J.). Bloomington, IN: Indiana University Press.&lt;/ref&gt;

===Metabolism===
Like all sauropods, ''Brachiosaurus'' was [[warm-blooded|homeothermic]] (maintaining a stable internal temperature) and [[endothermic]] (controlling body temperature through internal means), meaning that it was able to actively control its body temperature, producing the necessary heat through a high [[basal metabolic rate|basic metabolic rate]] of its cells.&lt;ref name=sander&amp;al2010&gt;Sander, P.M., Christian, A., Clauss, M., Fechner, R., Gee, C.T., Griebeler, E.-M., Gunga, H.-C., Hummel, J., Mallison, H., Perry, S.F., Preuschoft, H., Rauhut, O.W.M., Remes, K., Tütken, T., Wings, O. &amp; Witzel, U. (2010). Biology of the sauropod dinosaurs: the evolution of gigantism. ''Biology Reviews'' online first publication, doi:10.1111/j.1469-185X.2010.00137.x http://www3.interscience.wiley.com/cgi-bin/fulltext/123397084/HTMLSTART&lt;/ref&gt; In the past, ''Brachiosaurus'' has been used an example of a dinosaur for which endothermy is unlikely, because of the combination of great size (leading to overheating) and great [[calorie|caloric]] needs to fuel endothermy.&lt;ref name=russell1989b&gt;{{Cite book|last=Russell |first=D. A. |authorlink=Dale Russell |title=An Odyssey in Time: Dinosaurs of North America |year=1989 |publisher=NorthWord  Press |location=Minocqua, Wisconsin |isbn=1-55971-038-1 |page=78 }}&lt;/ref&gt; However, these calculations were based on incorrect assumptions about the available cooling surfaces (the large air sacs were not known), and a grossly inflated body mass. These inaccuracies resulted in overestimation of heat production and underestimation of heat loss.&lt;ref name=sander&amp;al2010/&gt; The large nasal arch has been postulated as an adaptation for cooling the brain, as a surface for evaporative cooling of the blood.&lt;ref name=russell1989b/&gt; Again, when this was proposed, cooling via the air sacs was not known, and thus not taken into account. Furthermore, other similar sized sauropods had no comparable structure. Additionally, in proportion to the entire animal, the nasal arch is very small, and would thus have made only an insignificant contribution to heat loss.

==In culture==
{{See also|Biological issues in Jurassic Park}}
[[Image:Brachiosaurus altithorax airport3.jpg|thumb|upright|Mounted skeleton in O'Hare International Airport]]
The original ''Brachiosaurus'' specimens collected by Elmer Riggs for the [[Field Museum of Natural History]] ([[Chicago]]) were not put on display in the museum until 1994, when a skeletal mount (made up of resin casts rather than actual fossil bones) was constructed inside the museum's main Stanley Field Hall. The mount stood until 1999, when it was moved to the B Concourse of [[United Airlines]]' Terminal One in [[O'Hare International Airport]].&lt;ref name=fmnhpr&gt;{{cite press release |title= Expect Awe-Struck Travelers|url= http://www.fieldmuseum.org/museum_info/press/press_brachiosaurus.htm|publisher= The Field Museum|date= November 26, 1999|accessdate=2009-08-27}}&lt;/ref&gt; At the same time, a second cast (in bronze) of the Field Museum's ''B. altithorax'' was constructed outside the museum.&lt;ref name=fieldcaptions&gt;The Field Museum. &quot;Captions from Selected Historical Photographs (caption number GN89396_52c).&quot; ''The Field Museum Photo Archives''. [http://www.fieldmuseum.org/research_collections/library/library_sites/photo_archives/forms/general_cap.pdf pdf link]. Accessed 2009-Aug-27.&lt;/ref&gt;

''Brachiosaurus'' is one of the best-known dinosaurs amongst both paleontologists and the general public. A [[asteroid belt|main belt]] [[asteroid]], {{mp|1991 GX|7}}, has been named [[&lt;!--no italics here--&gt;9954 Brachiosaurus&lt;!--no italics here--&gt;]] in honor of the genus.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web| title = JPL Small-Body Database Browser: 9954 Brachiosaurus (1991 GX7) | publisher = [[NASA]] | url= http://ssd.jpl.nasa.gov/sbdb.cgi?sstr=9954 | accessdate = 2007-04-28}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Williams&quot;&gt;{{Cite web| author = Williams, G. | title = Minor Planet Names: Alphabetical List |publisher = [[Smithsonian Astrophysical Observatory]] | url= http://www.cfa.harvard.edu/iau/lists/MPNames.html | accessdate = 2007-02-10}}&lt;/ref&gt; The genus has been featured in many films and television programs, most notably the ''[[Jurassic Park (film)|Jurassic Park]]'' and ''[[Walking with Dinosaurs]]'' series. The digital model of ''Brachiosaurus'' used in ''Jurassic Park'' went on to become the starting point for the [[List of Star Wars creatures#Ronto|ronto]] models in the 1997 special edition of the science fiction film ''[[Star Wars Episode IV: A New Hope]]''.&lt;ref name=&quot;ronto&quot;&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.starwars.com/databank/creature/ronto/index.html|title=Ronto|work=Databank|publisher=Star Wars.com|accessdate=2009-01-13}}&lt;/ref&gt;

{{clear}}

==References==
{{Reflist|30em}}

==External links==
{{Wiktionary|Brachiosaurus}}
{{Commons|Brachiosaurus|Brachiosaurus}}
*[http://www.fieldmuseum.org/museum_info/press/press_brachiosaurus.htm Expect awe-struck travelers], from the Field Museum. (O'Hare airport mount)
*[http://dinosaurier-info.de/animals/dinosaurs/pages_b/brachiosaurus.php Dinosaurier-info], fact-sheet with picture (in German)
*Benes, Josef. ''[http://homepage.mac.com/doubtboy/Burian.html Prehistoric Animals and Plants]'': old-fashioned illustration of ''Brachiosaurus'', bottom left.
*[http://www.life-of-science.net/evolution/news/swallowing-food-made-dinosaurs-that-big.html Why was Brachiosaurus that big? Short summary of a peer review paper]
*[http://www.dinodata.org/index.php?option=com_content&amp;task=view&amp;id=9305&amp;Itemid=67 ''Brachiosaurus''] at DinoData
*[http://internt.nhm.ac.uk/jdsml/nature-online/dino-directory//detail.dsml?Genusqtype=starts+with&amp;disp=gall&amp;identifier=brach&amp;sort=Genus&amp;dataHeaderText_EX=dinosaurs+beginning+with+%27B%27&amp;Genus=B&amp;beginIndex=6&amp;listPageURL=nameAZ%2edsml%3fGenusqtype%3dstarts%2bwith%26disp%3dgall%26sort%3dGenus%26Genus%3 dB ''Brachiosaurus'' (Natural History Museum)]

{{Portal|Dinosaurs}}

[[Category:Brachiosaurs]]
[[Category:Dinosaurs of North America]]
[[Category:Jurassic dinosaurs]]
[[Category:Dinosaurs of the Morrison Formation]]

[[be:Брахіязаўр]]
[[bg:Брахиозаври]]
[[br:Brakiosaor]]
[[ca:Braquiosaure]]
[[cs:Brachiosaurus]]
[[da:Brachiosaurus]]
[[de:Brachiosaurus]]
[[es:Brachiosaurus]]
[[eo:Braĥiosaŭro]]
[[fa:برکیوسور]]
[[fr:Brachiosaurus]]
[[gl:Brachiosaurus]]
[[ko:브라키오사우루스]]
[[hr:Brahiosaur]]
[[it:Brachiosaurus altithorax]]
[[he:ברכיוזאורוס]]
[[jv:Brachiosaurus]]
[[kk:Брахиозаврлар]]
[[lt:Brachiozauras]]
[[hu:Brachiosaurus]]
[[ml:ബ്രാക്കിയോസോറസ്‌]]
[[ms:Brachiosaurus]]
[[mn:Брахиозавр]]
[[nl:Brachiosaurus]]
[[ja:ブラキオサウルス]]
[[no:Brachiosaurus]]
[[nn:Brachiosaurus]]
[[pl:Brachiozaur]]
[[pt:Braquiossauro]]
[[ro:Brachiosaurus]]
[[ru:Брахиозавр]]
[[simple:Brachiosaurus]]
[[sk:Brachiosaurus]]
[[sr:Брахиосаур]]
[[sh:Brahiosaur]]
[[fi:Brachiosaurus]]
[[sv:Brachiosaurus]]
[[tl:Brachiosaurus]]
[[th:แบรกคิโอซอรัส]]
[[tr:Brachiosaurus]]
[[uk:Брахіозавр]]
[[vi:Brachiosaurus]]
[[bat-smg:Brakiozaurs]]
[[zh:腕龍]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
