<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><redirects><r from="Egyptian Organisation for Human Rights" to="Egyptian Organization for Human Rights" /></redirects><pages><page pageid="26091185" ns="0" title="Egyptian Organization for Human Rights"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">The '''Egyptian Organization for Human Rights''' ('''EOHR'''), founded in April 1985&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=S58MEk04feMC&amp;pg=PA38&amp;dq=%22+Egyptian+Organization+for+Human+Rights%22+1985&amp;num=100&amp;ei=WnRtS6iFM4fsyASLneStDg&amp;cd=2#v=onepage&amp;q=%22%20Egyptian%20Organization%20for%20Human%20Rights%22%201985&amp;f=false |title=Human Rights in the Arab World ... – Google Books |publisher=Books.google.com |date= |accessdate=March 18, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; and with its headquarters in [[Cairo, Egypt]], is a non-profit [[NGO]] and one of the longest-standing bodies for the defense of [[human rights in Egypt]].&lt;ref name=&quot;autogenerated1&quot;&gt;[http://en.eohr.org Egyptian Organization for Human Rights]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://pqasb.pqarchiver.com/thestar/access/518629641.html?dids=518629641:518629641&amp;FMT=ABS&amp;FMTS=ABS:FT&amp;type=current&amp;date=Apr+21%2C+1993&amp;author=Bob+Hepburn+Toronto+Star&amp;pub=Toronto+Star&amp;desc=Abuses+escalate+in+Egypt&amp;pqatl=google |title=Abuses escalate in Egypt |publisher=Google.com |date= |accessdate=March 18, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.accessmylibrary.com/premium/0286/0286-27472465.html |title=Article: Egypt – Egyptian human rights defender faces years of imprisonment. &amp;#124; AccessMyLibrary – Promoting library advocacy |publisher=Google.com |date=February 17, 2000 |accessdate=March 18, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://docs.newsbank.com/g/GooglePM/APAB/lib00582,0F89C46864B3719E.html |title=NewsLibrary.com – newspaper archive, clipping service – newspapers and other news sources |publisher=Google.com |date=August 5, 2000 |accessdate=March 18, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;  It investigates, monitors, and reports on human rights violations.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=zhHVKKBmZKEC&amp;pg=PA55&amp;dq=%22+Egyptian+Organization+for+Human+Rights%22+1985&amp;num=100&amp;ei=WnRtS6iFM4fsyASLneStDg&amp;cd=11#v=onepage&amp;q=%22%20Egyptian%20Organization%20for%20Human%20Rights%22%201985&amp;f=false |title=Speak truth to power: human rights ... – Google Books |publisher=Books.google.com |date= |accessdate=March 18, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; It is registered with the [[United Nations]] and works with other human rights groups.&lt;ref&gt;http://www1.umn.edu/humanrts/africa/comcases/201-97.html&lt;/ref&gt;

==Overview==
EOHR acts against both governmental and non-governmental human rights violations.  EOHR has a national membership of 2,300, with 17 provincial branches in Egypt.&lt;ref name=&quot;autogenerated1&quot;/&gt;  It says that from the late 1980s through the late 1889s there was a marked increase in torture in Egypt.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=pHp4lsrx92AC&amp;pg=PA59&amp;dq=%22+Egyptian+Organization+for+Human+Rights%22+1985&amp;num=100&amp;ei=WnRtS6iFM4fsyASLneStDg&amp;cd=4#v=onepage&amp;q=%22%20Egyptian%20Organization%20for%20Human%20Rights%22%201985&amp;f=false |title=Dictionary of human rights advocacy ... – Google Books |publisher=Books.google.com |date=January 1, 1997 |accessdate=March 18, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=Rjj48T4zrb8C&amp;pg=PA102&amp;dq=%22+Egyptian+Organization+for+Human+Rights%22+1985&amp;num=100&amp;ei=WnRtS6iFM4fsyASLneStDg&amp;cd=18#v=onepage&amp;q=%22%20Egyptian%20Organization%20for%20Human%20Rights%22%201985&amp;f=false |title=Passion for Islam: Shaping the ... – Google Books |publisher=Books.google.com |date= |accessdate=March 18, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The Egyptian Organization for Human Rights (EOHR) was founded in 1985. She is now considered as one of the oldest and most professional non-governmental organizations (NGOs) in Egypt. His headquarters is in Cairo. She has a national membership of 2,300 and has 17 provincial branches located throughout Egypt. EOHR is a non-profit NGO working within the framework of the principles established in the Universal Declaration of Human Rights and other international human rights instruments regardless of the identity or affiliation of the victim or violator .It acts against both governmental and non-governmental human rights violations.

==EOHR's international status==
EOHR is part of the wider international and Arab human rights movement. It cooperates with the United Nations human rights bodies, as well as with other international and regional human rights organizations .EOHR was registered at the Ministry of Social Affairs in 2003 under registration No. 5220/2003.

EOHR was granted special consultative status with the United Nations Economic and Social Council in 2006. This consultative status enables EOHR to enjoy closer interaction with the United Nations by participating in the activities of the International Council for Human Rights, according to ECOSOC decision 31/1996. This decision aimed to reinforce the principles of the human rights stipulated in the [[Universal Declaration of Human Rights]], the Vienna Declaration and all other international human rights documents. EOHR is also a member of five international organizations: the [[Arab Organization for Human Rights]] (AOHR), the [[World Organisation Against Torture]] (OMCT), [[International Federation for Human Rights]] (IFHR), the [[International Commission of Jurists]] (ICJ), and the [[International Freedom of Expression Exchange]] (IFEX).

==Goals==
# To provide full respect for human rights and the basic freedoms of all Egyptians and non-Egyptians who are in Egypt, according to the Universal Declaration of Human Rights and other international human rights instruments. These include, in particular, the International Covenant on Civil and Political Rights (ICCPR), the International Covenant on Economic, Social and Cultural Rights (ICESCR) and the United Nations Declaration on the Elimination of All Forms of Racial Discrimination. EOHR defends the human rights of all individuals and groups against all forms of violation.
# To reform the Egyptian constitution and legislation to bring them into accordance with international human rights covenants and conventions.
# To promote the rule of law and full respect for an independent judiciary.
# To guarantee the right to participation in public affairs without discrimination due to opinion, religion, gender, race or colour.
# To guarantee freedom of opinion and expression, in addition to artistic and literary invention.
# To guarantee freedom of belief, thought and religion.
# To ensure a fair trial for all defendants before a competent judge regardless of the kind of charge. To grant legal aid to those defendants if possible and necessary.
# To call for the release of those who are detained, or whose freedoms are restricted, due to the peaceful expression of their opinions or because of their beliefs, religion, race, gender or color.
# To provide legal aid to the victims of violations against the freedom of opinion and expression. In addition, to assist prisoners and detainees who are subject to torture or other cruel, inhuman and degrading treatment.
# To ensure that prison regulations and the treatment of prisoners are in conformity with the international Standard Minimum Rules for the Treatment of Prisoners.

==Working methods==
EOHR adopts peaceful methods to promote and defend human rights. It believes that the promotion of human rights is a common goal for the entire world community and it is determined to spare no peaceful effort in its struggle against human rights violations. His mains actions are: 

# Sends fact-finding missions. These include visits to prisons in order to collect testimonies, and to obtain document information about human rights violations.
# Issues urgent appeals, press releases, reports and publications on human rights violations.
# Raises awareness on human rights issues among individuals and groups through publications, conferences, seminars and studies. 
# Contacts Egyptian governmental and non-governmental bodies as well as international, regional and national organizations to seek co-operation, obtain information and take action to increase respect for human rights.

==Organizational structure==
The General Assembly of fee-paying members holds supreme authority in EOHR. A General Assembly meeting is convened once every other year to review and evaluate the organization’s progress and to elect the Board of Trustees. The Board of Trustees is the policy-making body within the EOHR and is led by the Chairman. It is made up of fifteen elected members, and up to four other prominent figures in the field of human rights can be invited by the Board of Trustees to join.

The Executive Board is elected by the Board of Trustees and consists of the Secretary-General, the Treasurer and representatives of the main committees of the organization. The Executive Board, led by the Secretary-General, is responsible for the day-to-day activities of the EOHR and for any decisions made in the interim period between meetings of the Board of Trustees.

EOHR has five substantive and inter-linked departments: the Field Work Unit, the Women’s Legal Aid Project (WLAP), the Research and Publications Desk, the International and Translation Unit and the Refugees’ Legal Aid Project.

;The Field Work Unit
This unit consists of a team of lawyers trained in investigative work. They receive individual allegations of human rights violations and investigate each case’s merits. Much of their work takes place in the field, on the ground, in prisons, in court, in detention centers, in homes, anywhere information can be found. The investigating lawyer writes an official report on each case. Then, depending on the nature and the merits of the case, the case may be removed from consideration or investigated further. Appeals and requests for information may be made to competent authorities and complainants may receive free legal counsel so that they can pursue a formal suit. All services made available to victims of human rights violations are absolutely free of charge.

;The Women’s Legal Aid Project (WLAP)
This unit manages human rights problems dealing with women’s issues. Such problems include marital and family issues and sexual discrimination. WLAP undertakes most of the work supporting campaigns that focus on women’s issues and coordinates an educational and training program aimed at increasing women’s legal literacy in Egypt’s poorer areas.

;The Research and Publications Unit
This unit conducts academic research on human rights issues, analyzes the raw material of human rights abuses supplied by the Field Work Unit and the WLAP. This desk is responsible for producing EOHR’s reports and is our routine link to the Arab media.

;The International and Translation Unit
This unit coordinates EOHR’s partnerships with other human rights organizations throughout the non-Arab world. This desk also coordinates our endless battle to equip us with the financial resources necessary to meet our objectives.
Moreover, it is responsible for translating all EOHR’s literature into English so that it can be shared with the English-speaking world.

;Refuge Legal Aid Project
This project was established in 2001 as a joint project between EOHR and the [[American University in Cairo]]. This unit provides legal aid to those who seek refugee status in Egypt and it works within the framework of the [[United Nations High Commissioner for Refugees]] (UNHCR).

==Campaigns==
* Campaign Against Torture 
* Campaign Against Inhumane Prison Conditions 
* Campaign for the Defense of Freedom of Thought and Belief 
* Campaign to Restore the Rights of Egyptian Prisoners of War 
* Campaign to Cancel the Emergency State in Egypt

==References==
{{Reflist|2}}

==External links==
*[http://en.eohr.org/ EOHR website]
*[http://www.newswatch.in/newspaedia/499 Egyptian Organisation for Human Rights]

{{DEFAULTSORT:Egyptian Organization For Human Rights}}
[[Category:Organizations established in 1985]]
[[Category:Civil rights organizations]]
[[Category:Human rights in Egypt]]
[[Category:Human rights organisations based in Egypt]]
[[Category:Non-governmental organizations based in Egypt]]
[[Category:Organisations based in Cairo]]
[[Category:1985 establishments in Egypt]]


{{humanrights-stub}}</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
