<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="206646" ns="0" title="Zakk Wylde"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{BLP sources|date=February 2008}}
{{Infobox musical artist &lt;!-- See Wikipedia:WikiProject_Musicians --&gt;
|name                = Zakk Wylde
|image               = Wylde flipped.png
|caption             = Wylde in August 2010
|image_size          =
|background          = solo_singer
|birth_name          = Jeffrey Phillip Wielandt
|alias               = Ghode, The Ghost of Rock Past, The Idol
|Born                = {{Birth date and age|1967|1|14}}&lt;br&gt;[[Bayonne, New Jersey|Bayonne]], [[New Jersey]], [[United States|U.S.]]
|death_date                
|instrument          = [[Guitar]], [[Singer|vocals]], [[Bass guitar|bass]], [[banjo]], [[piano]], [[Keyboard instrument|keyboards]], [[mandolin]], [[harmonica]], [[Organ (music)|organ]], [[mellotron]]
|genre               = [[Heavy metal music|Heavy metal]], [[Southern rock|southern metal]], [[groove metal]], [[southern rock]]
|occupation          = [[Musician]], [[songwriter]], [[actor]], [[Record producer|producer]]
|years_active        = 1987–present
|label               = [[Geffen Records|Geffen]], [[Spitfire Records|Spitfire]], [[InsideOut Music]], Artemis, [[Roadrunner Records|Roadrunner]], [[Epic Records|Epic]], [[Sony BMG|Sony]]
|associated_acts     = [[Ozzy Osbourne]], [[Black Label Society]], [[Pride and Glory (band)|Pride &amp; Glory]], [[Steel Dragon]], [[Britny Fox]]
|website             = [http://www.zakkwylde.com zakkwylde.com]
|notable_instruments = [[Gibson Les Paul|Zakk Wylde Signature Les Paul]],&lt;br&gt;[[Gibson Flying V|Zakk Wylde Signature Gibson Flying V]]
}}

'''Zachary Phillip Wylde''' (born January 14, 1967), best known by the stage name '''Zakk Wylde''', is an American musician, songwriter, and occasional actor who is best known as the former [[guitarist]] for [[Ozzy Osbourne]] and founder of the [[heavy metal music|heavy metal]] band [[Black Label Society]]. He was the lead guitarist and vocalist in [[Pride and Glory (band)|Pride &amp; Glory]], who released one self-titled album in 1994 before disbanding. As a solo artist he released ''[[Book of Shadows (album)|Book of Shadows]]'' in 1996.

==Early life==
Wylde was born in [[Bayonne, New Jersey|Bayonne]], [[New Jersey]].

==Music career==
Growing up, Wylde played locally with his first band, &quot;Stone Henge&quot;, then later with local Jersey band Zyris. Years later, he landed the role as lead guitarist and co-writer for Ozzy Osbourne. He sent Ozzy a demo tape in 1987 and was hired to replace [[Jake E. Lee]]. Lee had replaced the deceased [[Randy Rhoads]], Ozzy's principal guitarist in the post-[[Black Sabbath]] period, beginning in late 1979. Rhoads remains Wylde's foremost guitar-playing and stagecraft influence.{{Citation needed|date=October 2011}}

Wylde gravitated toward a particular Les Paul guitar, which has become known as &quot;The Grail&quot;; his infamous bullseye-painted Gibson Les Paul custom. Wylde lost the guitar after it fell from the back of a truck transporting equipment as he was travelling between gigs in Texas. Rewards were offered to anyone that had information about the guitar. Wylde and 'The Grail' were reunited years later when a fan bought it at a Dallas pawn shop and saw the initials &quot;Z.W.&quot; carved into the humbucker pickups backs. He contacted Wylde's former webmaster Randy Canis to arrange its return to Wylde. He was eventually able to barter for it, in exchange for two other Les Pauls.{{Citation needed|date=October 2011}}

Osbourne has maintained a flexible attitude with regard to his backing band, leaving his band members free to leave as they wish, but Wylde has remained largely faithful to Osbourne. Wylde was replaced in Osbourne's band by Joe Holmes from 1995 until his return in 2001.

On January 17, 2006, Zakk Wylde was recognized at the Hollywood Rock Walk of Fame located at 7425 Sunset Boulevard, featuring his handprints and signature, in recognition of his successful career as a musician and his contribution to the music industry. The event was open to the public and many rock celebrities were present, including Ozzy Osbourne.{{Citation needed|date=October 2011}}

After auditions in 2005/2006, Ozzy Osbourne announced Wylde as the official guitarist for his upcoming album, [[Black Rain (Ozzy Osbourne album)|Black Rain]], which was released in 2007. On stage with Osbourne, Wylde has been credited for lending a high level of energy and passion to performances.

Black Label Society's album, Shot To Hell, was released on September 11, 2006 in the UK, and September 12, 2006 in the U.S. through Roadrunner records, with production by Michael Beinhorn (Soundgarden, Ozzy Osbourne, Red Hot Chili Peppers). Black Label Society headlined the second stage at the 2006 Ozzfest, with Wylde playing double duty with Ozzy on certain dates. Ozzy Osbourne's album, Black Rain, was released in May 2007.

Black Label Society released 'The Song Remains Not the Same' on May 10, 2011
on E1.

As reported by Alternative Press, Zakk Wylde will be contributing a guitar solo to Black Veil Brides' upcoming cover of Kiss' &quot;Unholy,&quot; slated to appear on the band's upcoming Rebels EP due out December 2011.

==Personal life==
Wylde lives with his wife, Barbaranne, and his three children: Hayley Rae, Hendrix, and Jesse—who is godson to [[Ozzy Osbourne]]. Wylde was a close friend of [[Dimebag Darrell|Darrell &quot;Dimebag&quot; Abbott]] before the latter was murdered in 2004. As of 2011, he is also in partnership with [[Blair's Sauces and Snacks]] to produce &quot;Berserker&quot; Hot Sauce and several variations thereof.&lt;ref&gt;[http://extremefood.com/shop/home.php?cat=7 Blair's Sauces and Snacks: The Official Home of Blair's Death Sauce and Extreme Food: Hot Sauces: Zakk Wylde&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;

===Health problems===
Wylde's health has come under scrutiny for several years. Wylde was asked by [[Sharon Osbourne]] to attend rehab, but left very early on.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.roadrunnerrecords.com/blabbermouth.net/news.aspx?mode=Article&amp;newsitemID=32924|title=ZAKK WYLDE Denies He Spat Booze In JAMES HETFIELD's Face|publisher=BlabberMouth}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In August 2009, Wylde was hospitalized due to blood clots.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.musicradar.com/news/guitars/zakk-wylde-hospitalized-for-blood-clots-cancels-tour-217850 Zakk Wylde hospitalized for blood clots, cancels tour | MusicRadar.com&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt; He was forced to cancel his tour with [[Mudvayne]] and [[Static-X]] due to an [[embolism]]. He has been sober ever since.{{cn|date=November 2011}}

==Equipment==
He is known for his use of [[Gibson Les Paul Custom]] model guitars with a &quot;bulls-eye&quot; graphic on them, a design he used to deliberately differentiate himself visually from [[Randy Rhoads]] - who was also frequently identified by his white Les Paul Custom. Interestingly, one of Wylde's favorite stage guitars of late is a replica of Rhoads' [[Gibson Flying V|Flying V]]. The &quot;bulls-eye&quot; paint job was originally supposed to look like the spiral from the movie ''[[Vertigo (film)|Vertigo]]'', but when it came back incorrect from the [[luthier]], he liked the result and stuck with it. He was sometimes criticized by viewers and media for taking the idea of the &quot;bulls-eye&quot; from [[Eddie Ojeda]] from [[Twisted Sister]], however, both Eddie and Zakk deny it and suppose it rather to be coincidence.

Wylde's signature Les Pauls include a red flame-maple bulls-eye model, a black and antique-white bulls-eye model, an orange &quot;buzz-saw&quot; model, the pattern on which was inspired by a design on a [[Zippo]] lighter,&lt;ref&gt;http://www.guitarchina.com/news/newspic/20050201_091635_93490.jpg&lt;/ref&gt; and a &quot;camo&quot; bulls-eye model with [[mother of pearl]] [[fretboard|neck]] [[inlay (guitar)|inlays]] and a green camouflage paint scheme. His original bulls-eye Les Paul was purchased from one of the owners of Metaltronics Amplification. Metaltronics was building a one-off live rig for Wylde that was designed around one of the owner's guitars, a creamy white Les Paul Custom with EMG pickups, which would later become known as &quot;The Grail&quot;. Zakk also has a custom Dean Splittail with a mud splatter bulls-eye graphic, as well as a signature Splittail shaped Gibson model called the &quot;ZV&quot;. Another Dean in his collection is a Dime series Razorback with custom Bulls-eye graphics ordered for him specially by [[Dimebag Darrell]] shortly before his death; since receiving the guitar, he has only ever used it on stage to play &quot;In This River,&quot; Zakk's personal tribute to Dimebag.

Practice: Zakk uses Marshall MG Series practice combos ranging in wattage levels from 10-30W during tour/private use especially in hotels and buses. Zakk also has an extensive relationship with Marshall Amplification due to his love for their amplifiers, both solid state and valve powered. 
Live: Zakk exclusively uses Marshall JCM 800's with twin 4 X 12 Cabinets loaded with EVM12L 300W Black Label Speakers.

His usual signal path consists of his guitar &gt; (on stage pedal board) Dunlop Wylde [[Wah-wah pedal|Wah]] &gt; Dunlop [[Rotovibe]] &gt; [[MXR Phase 90|MXR EVH Phase 90]] (*Soon to be replaced by the new MXR Wylde Phase) &gt; MXR Wylde [[Distortion (music)|Overdrive]] &gt; MXR Carbon Copy Delay [[Delay effect| Delay]] &gt; (to a back stage pedal board) &gt;  MXR EVH Flanger &gt; MXR Black Label [[Chorus effect|Chorus]] &gt; split signals, one to each distorted amp into the High Gain input.

==Appearances in media==
{{BLP unsourced section|date=August 2008}}

===Music===
* Wylde has made guest appearances on various albums, such as [[Damageplan]]'s debut album, ''[[New Found Power]]'', as guest vocalist and guitarist on the tracks &quot;Soul Bleed&quot; and &quot;Reborn&quot;.
* He played guitar solos on [[Dope (band)|Dope]]'s single &quot;Addiction&quot; from their newest album, ''No Regrets''.
* He plays a solo on [[Fozzy]]'s 2005 release &quot;All That Remains&quot; on the song, Wanderlust.
* He has also worked on five of [[Derek Sherinian]]'s solo albums: ''[[Inertia (Derek Sherinian album)|Inertia]]'', ''[[Black Utopia]]'', ''[[Mythology (Derek Sherinian album)|Mythology]]'', ''[[Blood of the Snake]]'' and ''[[Molecular Heinosity]]'' alongside [[Yngwie Malmsteen]] and others.
* Wylde was also a judge for the 8th annual [[The Independent Music Awards|Independent Music Awards]]. His contributions helped assist independent artists' careers.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.prlog.org/10244858-bostons-own-debbie-and-friends-among-the-8th-annual-independent-music-awards-vox-populi-winners.html PRLog]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.independentmusicawards.com/ima_new/imajudges2009.asp Independent Music Awards - 8th Annual IMA Judges]&lt;/ref&gt;
* In 2010 he played lead guitar on [[My Darkest Days]] first single &quot;Porn Star Dancing&quot;, along with guest singers [[Chad Kroeger]] and [[Ludacris]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=VdaKwt5cHEk YouTube - ‪Porn Star Dancing (Extended Uncensored)‬‏&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;
* In 1993 Ozzy Osbournes double album [[Live and Loud]] was released. Wylde is the guitarist.
* In 2011 he featured in [[Jamey Jasta]] of [[Hatebreed]]'s new project, &quot;Jasta&quot; in the song &quot;The Fearless must Endure&quot;.
* Wylde was a member of [[Guns N' Roses]] for a short period of time during the making of [[Chinese Democracy]] but left due to commitments to Ozzy Osbourne and Guns N' Roses having no completed songs.

===Live performances===
[[File:Black Label Society (04).jpg|thumb|left|[[Black Label Society]] performing at [[Allen Event Center]] in [[Allen, Texas]] on October 16, 2011]]

* On August 1, 1993, at Great Woods Amphitheatre in Mansfield, MA, Wylde appeared on stage with the [[Allman Brothers]] on lead guitar since [[Dickey Betts]] was unable to make the show, and they needed a guitarist at the last minute. This show is documented on the bootleg &quot;Zakk Goes Wylde&quot;.
* Wylde is a [[New York Yankees]] fan. He performed the National Anthem on the electric guitar during a [[New York Rangers]] game in October 2005. He has also played the anthem at [[Los Angeles Kings]] and [[Los Angeles Dodgers|Dodgers]] games. A video of a Kings performance is included as an extra feature, on the [[DVD]] ''[[Boozed, Broozed, and Broken-Boned]]''.
* On February 1, 2007 Wylde and [[Nick Catanese]] began a tour of acoustic shows at the [[Hard Rock Cafe]] in various cities across [[North America]]. Although Catanese had to leave mid-tour due to unspecified personal reasons, Wylde continued to play shows alone. He performed several songs, on both the acoustic guitar and keyboard. The tour was eventually canceled due to unspecified reasons.
* On April 13, 2011 he was the guitarist for [[James Durbin (singer)|James Durbin]] on [[American Idol]], during Durbin's performance of &quot;[[Heavy Metal (song)|Heavy Metal]]&quot;, by [[Sammy Hagar]].
* On May 14, 2011 he performed the National Anthem at Rockfest in Kansas City, Missouri.

===Film and television===
* On June 5, 2011, he appeared on ''[[Late Night with Jimmy Fallon]]'' and performed with ''[[The Roots]]''
* Wylde's film credits include ''[[Rock Star (2001 film)|Rock Star]]'' (As &quot;Ghode&quot;, [[guitarist]] of the fictitious band [[Steel Dragon]])
* Wylde also appeared on the TV show ''[[Angel (TV Series)|Angel]]'' in the season four episode &quot;[[The Magic Bullet (Angel episode)|The Magic Bullet]]&quot; where he plays acoustic on the song &quot;[[Mandy (song)|Mandy]]&quot; while Angel and Conner sing along.
* Wylde has also appeared as a guest star on the TV show ''[[Aqua Teen Hunger Force]]''. In it, he plays guitar on a track produced by [[Master Shake]] that is supposed to become the next big birthday song, which is called &quot;Spirit Journey Formation Anniversary.&quot; Wylde becomes irate when he finds out that Shake cannot pay him for his input on the project. Later in the show, Wylde is killed when caught between the crossfire of two robotic banjo-playing [[scorpion]]s.
* On September 26, 2003, Wylde appeared on ''[[Jimmy Kimmel Live!]]'' and sat in with the house band. During the course of the night he repeatedly made fun of and threatened to beat up [[Fred Durst]], the front man for [[Limp Bizkit]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=PDReyEP0x4g YouTube - ‪Zakk Wylde Live On Jimmy Kimmel‬‏&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;
* On January 30, 2007, Wylde, alongside [[Black Label Society]], were the musical guests for [[MTV]]'s [[Wrestling Society X]] debut episode. He worked the night as a guest commentator as well.
* On February 2, 2007, Wylde guest hosted on [[Seattle]]'s [[KISW-FM|99.9 KISW]] on the afternoon program ''The Men's Room''.
* On the May 18 edition of ''[[WWE Friday Night SmackDown|WWE Smackdown!]]'', Wylde appeared with [[Ozzy Osbourne]] to perform the song &quot;[[I Don't Wanna Stop]]&quot;, at the [[First Mariner Arena]] in [[Baltimore, Maryland]].
* Wylde performed alongside Osbourne on the 2007 ''[[VH1 Rock Honors]]'' broadcast.
* On October 18, 2009, Zakk Wylde performed the National Anthem on [[Total Nonstop Action Wrestling]]'s biggest PPV, [[Bound for Glory (2009)|Bound for Glory]], before the matches officially started.
* He appears as a guest in ''[[Rush: Beyond the Lighted Stage]]''.
* He appears in the [[Pantera]] episode of ''[[Behind the Music]]''.
* He appears as a music store worker in a scene from the TV show [[Californication (TV series)|Californication]] on Showtime, Season 4 Episode 2.t
* He was on tour with Black Label Society in 2010 on the Ozzfest Tour that also had Ozzy and Mötley Crüe, among many others.
* He performed &quot;Heavy Metal&quot; by Sammy Hagar with James Durbin during season 10 of American Idol.

===Video games===
* Wylde recorded a [[guitar duel]] for the video game ''[[Guitar Hero: World Tour]]''. He also appears as a [[playable character]] performing the songs [[Stillborn (song)|Stillborn]] and, along with Ozzy Osbourne, [[Crazy Train]] and [[Mr. Crowley]].
* Some of Wylde's signature guitars have been for sale to play with throughout the ''[[Guitar Hero]]'' series. These include &quot;The Grail&quot;, &quot;The Camo Grail&quot;, and &quot;The Buzzsaw&quot;.
* Wylde was featured in the first [[Guitar Hero (video game)|Guitar Hero]] with the studio version recording of [[Fire It Up (Black Label Society song)|Fire it Up]].
* He was the guitarist in the remix of &quot;Bring The Noise&quot; called &quot;Bring The Noise 20XX&quot; that appeared in Guitar Hero 5 as a playable track

==Discography==
{{Main|Zakk Wylde discography}}
{{col-begin}}
{{col-2}}
;With Black Label Society
* 1999: ''[[Sonic Brew]]''
* 2000: ''[[Stronger Than Death]]''
* 2001: ''[[Alcohol Fueled Brewtality|Alcohol Fueled Brewtality Live!! +5]]''
* 2002: ''[[1919 Eternal]]''
* 2003: ''[[The Blessed Hellride]]''
* 2004: ''[[Hangover Music Vol. VI]]''
* 2005: ''[[Mafia (Black Label Society album)|Mafia]]''
* 2006: ''[[Shot to Hell]]''
* 2009: ''[[Skullage]]''
* 2010: ''[[Order of the Black]]''
* 2011: ''[[The Song Remains Not The Same]]''
{{col-2}}
;With Ozzy Osbourne
* 1988: ''[[No Rest for the Wicked (Ozzy)|No Rest For The Wicked]]''
* 1990: ''[[Just Say Ozzy]] (live album)''
* 1991: ''[[No More Tears]]''
* 1993: ''[[Live &amp; Loud]] (live album)''
* 1995: ''[[Ozzmosis]]''
* 2001: ''[[Down to Earth (Ozzy Osbourne album)|Down to Earth]]''
* 2002: ''[[Live at Budokan (Ozzy Osbourne album)|Live At Budokan]] (live album)''
* 2007: ''[[Black Rain (Ozzy Osbourne album)|Black Rain]]''
;Pride &amp; Glory
* 1994: ''[[Pride and Glory (album)|Pride &amp; Glory]]''
;Zakk Wylde
* 1996: ''[[Book of Shadows (album)|Book of Shadows]]''
{{col-end}}

==References==
{{Reflist}}

==External links==
{{Commons|Zakk Wylde|Zakk Wylde}}
* [http://www.blacklabelsociety.net Black Label Society official website]
* [http://www.zakkwylde.com/gear.html Zakk Wylde's guitar gear]
* [http://www.bonedo.de/workshop/gitarre-bass/play-alike-35-zakk-wylde-video-workshop-interview/workshop/zwylde-seite-1/index.html Zakk Wylde Video Workshop (Videos in engl.)] Source: Bonedo.de
* [http://www.bonedo.de/feature/allgemein/interviews/video-interview-zakk-wylde/video/index.html Zakk Wylde Interview] Source: Bonedo.de
* [http://www.altpress.com/news/entry/zakk_wylde_to_guest_on_new_black_veil_brides_ep?utm_source=dlvr.it&amp;utm_medium=twitter&amp;utm_campaign=altpress] Source: Alternative Press

{{Black Label Society|state=plain}}
{{Ozzy Osbourne}}
{{Derek Sherinian}}
{{Aqua Teen Hunger Force}}

{{Persondata &lt;!-- Metadata: see [[Wikipedia:Persondata]]. --&gt;
| NAME              =Wylde, Zakk
| ALTERNATIVE NAMES =
| SHORT DESCRIPTION =
| DATE OF BIRTH     =January 14, 1967
| PLACE OF BIRTH    =
| DATE OF DEATH     =
| PLACE OF DEATH    =
}}
{{DEFAULTSORT:Wylde, Zakk}}
[[Category:1967 births]]
[[Category:Living people]]
[[Category:American heavy metal guitarists]]
[[Category:The Ozzy Osbourne Band members]]
[[Category:People from Bayonne, New Jersey]]
[[Category:People from Jackson Township, New Jersey]]
[[Category:American people of Irish descent]]
[[Category:Lead guitarists]]
[[Category:Musicians from New Jersey]]
[[Category:American musicians of Irish descent]]

{{Link GA|fr}}
[[bg:Зак Уайлд]]
[[cs:Zakk Wylde]]
[[da:Zakk Wylde]]
[[de:Zakk Wylde]]
[[et:Zakk Wylde]]
[[es:Zakk Wylde]]
[[fa:زک وایلد]]
[[fr:Zakk Wylde]]
[[it:Zakk Wylde]]
[[hu:Zakk Wylde]]
[[nl:Zakk Wylde]]
[[ja:ザック・ワイルド]]
[[no:Zakk Wylde]]
[[pl:Zakk Wylde]]
[[pt:Zakk Wylde]]
[[ru:Зак Вайлд]]
[[sk:Zakk Wylde]]
[[fi:Zakk Wylde]]
[[sv:Zakk Wylde]]
[[tr:Zakk Wylde]]
[[uk:Закк Уайлд]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
