<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="20742" ns="0" title="Muslim Brotherhood"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{for|The Chinese Islamist organization known as the Muslim Brotherhood|Yihewani}}
{{cleanup|date=June 2011}}

{{Infobox Political party
| party_name = The Muslim Brotherhood
| name_native = ''{{lang|ar|الإخوان المسلمون/المسلمين}}&lt;br /&gt;''{{transl|ar|DIN|al-ʾIḫwān al-Muslimūn/Muslimīn}}''&lt;br /&gt;{{IPA-arz|elʔexˈwæːn elmosleˈmiːn|IPA}}
|party_logo= [[File:Muslim Brotherhood logo.png|150px|Party logo]]
| colorcode = #009900
| leader = [[Mohammed Badie]]
| chairman =
| spokesperson =
| foundation = 1928 &lt;br /&gt; [[Ismailia]], [[Egypt]]
| ideology = [[Islamism]]&lt;br&gt;[[Pan-Islamism]]&lt;br&gt;[[Islamic democracy]]&lt;br&gt;[[Qutbism]]&lt;br&gt;[[Jihad]]&lt;br&gt;[[Anti-Zionism]]&lt;br&gt;[[Anti-Masonry]]
| headquarters =
| international =
|website = [http://www.ikhwanonline.com/ www.ikhwanonline.com]&lt;br /&gt;[http://www.ikhwanweb.com www.ikhwanweb.com]
}}

'''The Society of the Muslim Brothers''' ({{lang-ar|الإخوان}} ''{{transl|ar|DIN|al-ʾIḫwān}}/Ikhwan/el-ekhwan'', {{IPA-arz|elʔexˈwæːn|IPA}}, often simply &quot;The Brotherhood&quot; or &quot;MB&quot;) is the world's oldest&lt;ref&gt;[http://english.aljazeera.net/indepth/2010/11/2010111681527837704.html The Muslim Brotherhood in flux] 21 Nov 2010 [[aljazeera]]&lt;/ref&gt; and one of the largest Islamist parties,&lt;ref name=&quot;ikhwanweb.com&quot;&gt;[http://www.ikhwanweb.com/Home.asp?zPage=Systems&amp;System=PressR&amp;Press=Show&amp;Lang=E&amp;ID=6674 The Moderate Muslim Brotherhood]. Robert S. Leiken &amp; Steven Brooke, ''Foreign Affairs Magazine''&lt;/ref&gt; and is the largest political opposition organization in many Arab states.{{which|date=September 2011}}  It was founded in 1928 in [[Egypt]] by the [[Islamic scholarship|Islamic scholar]] and schoolteacher [[Hassan al-Banna]] and by the late 1940s had an estimated two million members.&lt;ref&gt;Hallett, Robin. Africa Since 1875. Ann Arbor, Michigan: The University of Michigan Press (1974), pg. 138.&lt;/ref&gt; Its ideas had gained its supporters throughout the Arab world and influenced other Islamist groups with its &quot;model of political activism combined with Islamic charity work&quot;.&lt;ref name=BBC_profile/&gt;  Its most famous slogan, used worldwide, is &quot;Islam is the solution.&quot;&lt;ref name=BBC_profile&gt;{{cite news|title=Profile: Egypt's Muslim Brotherhood|url=http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/world-middle-east-12313405|publisher=[[BBC News]] | first=Kim|last=Ghattas|date=2001-2-9}}&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;!--ideology--&gt;

The Brotherhood's stated goal is to instill the [[Qur'an]] and [[Sunnah]] as the &quot;sole reference point for&amp;nbsp;...ordering the life of the Muslim family, individual, community&amp;nbsp;... and state&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.ikhwanweb.com/Home.asp?zPage=Systems&amp;System=PressR&amp;Press=Show&amp;Lang=E&amp;ID=4584|title=Principles of the Muslim Brotherhood}}&lt;/ref&gt; Since its inception in 1928 the movement has officially opposed violent means to achieve its goals.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|date=February 6, 2007 |title=Egyptian Regime Resasserts Its Absolute Disrespect of Law |url=http://www.ikhwanweb.com/Article.asp?ID=2496&amp;SectionID=77}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Ikhwan_History&quot;&gt;{{Cite book|url=http://www.ikhwanweb.com/lib/History_of_the_Muslim_Brotherhood_in_Egypt.doc|title=History of Muslim Brotherhood Movement Homepage}}&lt;/ref&gt;  The MB's non-violent stance has resulted in breakaway groups from the movement, and been criticized by [[al-Qaeda]] for its support for democratic elections rather than armed jihad.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.foreignaffairs.com/articles/62453/robert-s-leiken-and-steven-brooke/the-moderate-muslim-brotherhood The Moderate Muslim Brotherhood] Leiken, Robert S; Brooke, Steven}| Foreign Affairs v.86. 2 (Mar/Apr 2007): 107-121. ] quote: Al Qaeda's Ayman al-Zawahiri sneers at them for &quot;lur[ing] thousands of young Muslim men into lines for elections ... instead of into the lines of jihad.&quot; &lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;!--history--&gt;
The Muslim Brotherhood started off as a religious social organization, preaching Islam, teaching the illiterate, setting up hospitals and even launching commercial enterprises. As it continued to rise in influence, starting in 1936, it began to oppose [[United Kingdom|British]] rule in Egypt.&lt;ref name=brill&gt;{{citation|last=Delanoue|first=G.|contribution=al-Ik̲h̲wānal-Muslimūn| encyclopedia =  Encyclopaedia of Islam|publisher= [[Brill]]}}&lt;/ref&gt; Many Egyptian nationalists accuse the MB of violent killings during this period.&lt;ref name=&quot;Chamieh&quot;&gt;Chamieh, Jebran, Traditionalists, Militants and Liberal in Present Islam, Research and Publishing House, [[1994?]], p. 140.&lt;/ref&gt; After the Arab defeat in the [[First Arab-Israeli war]], the [[Egyptian government]] dissolved the organisation and arrested its members.&lt;ref name=brill/&gt; It supported the [[Egyptian Revolution of 1952]], but after an attempted assassination of Egypt's president it was once again banned and [[Human rights in Egypt|repressed]].&lt;ref name=BBC_history&gt;{{cite news|title=Egypt opposition wary after talks|url=http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/world-middle-east-12313405|publisher=[[BBC News]] | date=2011-02-09}}&lt;/ref&gt; The MB has been suppressed in other countries as well, most notably in Syria in 1982 during the [[Hama massacre]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title=Syria cracks down on 'Islamists'|url=http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/middle_east/4557543.stm|publisher=[[BBC News]] | first=Kim|last=Ghattas|date=2005-05-18}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;!--structure--&gt;
The MB is financed by contributions from its members, who are required to allocate a portion of their income to the movement. Some of these contributions are from members who work in [[Saudi Arabia]] and other [[OPEC|oil-rich countries]].&lt;ref name=&quot;WashingtonPost-Diverse&quot;&gt;[http://www.washingtonpost.com/wp-dyn/articles/A12823-2004Sep10.html In Search Of Friends Among The Foes U.S. Hopes to Work With Diverse Group]&lt;/ref&gt;

==Beliefs==
{{Islamism sidebar}}
The Brotherhood's credo was and is, &quot;God is our objective; the Quran is our constitution, the Prophet is our leader; [[Jihad]] is our way; and death for the sake of God is the highest of our aspirations.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;FAS&quot;&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.fas.org/irp/world/para/mb.htm|title=FAS Intelligence Resource Program}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;MBMHome&quot;&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.ummah.net/ikhwan/|title=Muslim Brotherhood Movement Homepage}}&lt;/ref&gt;  The Brotherhood's English language website describes the &quot;principles of the Muslim Brotherhood&quot; as including firstly the introduction of the Islamic [[Shari`ah]] as &quot;the basis controlling the affairs of state and society;&quot; and secondly work to unify &quot;Islamic countries and states, mainly among the Arab states, and liberating them from foreign [[imperialism]]&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.ikhwanweb.com/Article.asp?ID=813&amp;LevelID=2&amp;SectionID=116|title=The Principles of The Muslim Brotherhood}}&lt;/ref&gt; 

According to a spokesman, the MB believe in reform, [[democracy]], [[freedom of assembly]], [[Freedom of the press|press]], etc. &lt;blockquote&gt;&quot;We believe that the political reform is the true and natural gateway for all other kinds of reform. We have announced our acceptance of democracy that acknowledges political pluralism, the peaceful rotation of power and the fact that the nation is the source of all powers. As we see it, political reform includes the termination of the state of emergency, restoring public freedoms, including the right to establish political parties, whatever their tendencies may be, and the freedom of the press, freedom of criticism and thought, freedom of peaceful demonstrations, freedom of assembly, etc. It also includes the dismantling of all exceptional courts and the annulment of all exceptional laws, establishing  the independence of the judiciary, enabling the judiciary to fully and truly supervise general elections so as to ensure that they authentically express people's will, removing all obstacles that restrict the functioning of civil society organizations, etc.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.ikhwanweb.com/faq.php interview w/Dr. Mohamed El-Sayed Habib]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

Its founder, Hassan Al-Banna, was influenced by Islamic reformers [[Muhammad Abduh]] and [[Rashid Rida]]. In the group's belief, the [[Quran]] and [[Sunnah]] constitute a perfect way of life and social and political organization that [[Islamic concept of God|God]] has set out for man. [[Islamic State|Islamic governments]] must be based on this system and eventually unified in a [[Caliphate]]. The Muslim Brotherhood's goal, as stated by Brotherhood founder [[Hassan al-Banna]] was to reclaim Islam's manifest destiny, an empire, stretching from [[Spain]] to [[Indonesia]].&lt;ref&gt;Davidson, Lawrence (1998) ''Islamic Fundamentalism'' Greenwood Press, Westport, Conn., ISBN 0-313-29978-1 pp. 97–98;&lt;/ref&gt; It preaches that Islam enjoins man to strive for social justice, the eradication of poverty and corruption, and political freedom to the extent allowed by the laws of Islam. The Brotherhood strongly opposes Western [[colonialism]], and helped overthrow the pro-[[Western world|western]] monarchies in Egypt and other Muslim countries during the early 20th century.

On the issue of women and gender the Muslim Brotherhood interprets Islam conservatively. Its founder called for &quot;a campaign against ostentation in dress and loose behavior&quot;, &quot;segregation of male and female students&quot;, a separate curriculum for girls, and &quot;the prohibition of dancing and other such pastimes...&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;Women&quot;&gt;In his tract, &quot;Toward the Light&quot; in ''Five Tracts of Hasan al-Banna'', trans. by Charles Wendell (Berkeley, 1978), ISBN 0-520-09584-7 pp. 126f., al-Banna writes: Following are the principal goals of reform grounded on the spirit of genuine Islam... Treatment of the problem of women in a way which combines the progressive and the protective, in accordance with Islamic teaching, so that this problem&amp;nbsp;– one of the most important social problems&amp;nbsp;– will not be abandoned to the biased pens and deviant notions of those who err in the directions of deficiency and excess... a campaign against ostentation in dress and loose behaviour; the instruction of women in what is proper, with particular strictness as regards female instructors, pupils, physicians, and students, and all those in similar categories... a review of the curricula offered to girls and the necessity of making them distinct from the boys' curricula in many stages of education... segregation of male and female students; private meetings between men and women, unless within the permitted degrees of relationship, to be counted as a crime for which both will be censured... the encouragement of marriage and procreation, by all possible means; promulgation of legislation to protect and give moral support to the family, and to solve the problems of marriage... the closure of morally undesirable ballrooms and dance-halls, and the prohibition of dancing and other such pastimes...&quot;&lt;/ref&gt;

The MB is a movement, not a political party, but members have created political parties in several countries, such as the Islamic Action Front in Jordan and [[Hamas]] in [[Gaza]] and the [[West Bank]] and the newly created [[Freedom and Justice Party (Egypt)|Freedom and Justice Party]] in [[Egypt]]. These parties are staffed by Brotherhood members but kept independent from the MB to some degree, unlike [[Hizb ut-Tahrir]] which is highly centralized.&lt;ref&gt;''The Future of Political Islam,'' Graham E. Fuller, Palgrave MacMillan, (2003), p. 138.&lt;/ref&gt;

The Brotherhood's nonviolent stance has resulted in breakaway groups from the movement, including the [[Al-Gama'a al-Islamiyya]] and [[Al Takfir Wal Hijra]].&lt;ref name=Pbs&gt;[http://www.pbs.org/wgbh/pages/frontline/shows/front/special/sala.html The Salafist Movement], ''[[Frontline (PBS)]]&lt;/ref&gt; [[Osama bin Laden]] similarly criticized the Brotherhood, and accused it of betraying [[jihad]] and the ideals of [[Sayyid Qutb]], an influential Brother member and author of ''[[Ma'alim fi al-Tariq|Milestones]]''.&lt;ref name=&quot;Muslim Brotherhood vs Al Qaeda&quot;&gt;[http://www.ikhwanweb.com/article.php?id=22699 &quot;Muslim Brotherhood vs Al Qaeda&quot;] January 19, 2010&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;MB Chief Criticism&quot;&gt;[http://www.nefafoundation.org/miscellaneous/FeaturedDocs/nefambexecbureaurejectubltape1207.pdf &quot;MB Chief Criticism&quot;] Dec. 30 2007&lt;/ref&gt;

==Organization==
The Transcripts&lt;ref&gt;Zeid al-Noman, [http://www.nefafoundation.org/miscellaneous/HLF/IkhwanAmerica.pdf &quot;Ikhwan in America&quot;], pp. 15–16.&lt;/ref&gt; the following hierarchical Organisation structure can be derived:

*'''The General Organisational Conference''' is the highest body of the [[Ikhwan]]s stemming from the [[Ikhwan]]s bases, every Usra elects one or two deputies according to its number.

*'''The Shura Council''' has the duties of planning, charting general policies and programs that achieve the goal of the Group. Its resolutions are binding to the Group and only the General Organisational Conference can modify or annul them and the Shura Office has also the right to modify or annul resolutions of the Executive Office. It follows the implementation of the Group policies and programs. It directs the Executive Office and it forms dedicated branch committees to assist in that.&lt;ref&gt;[http://books.google.co.in/books?id=heMyqgE_l5QC&amp;pg=PA68&amp;lpg=PA68&amp;dq=ikhwan+shura+council&amp;source=web&amp;ots=tn32fDmdyG&amp;sig=0SoJDcxnSU_IaZwfl-8pHvw3-sk&amp;hl=en&amp;sa=X&amp;oi=book_result&amp;resnum=4&amp;ct=result &quot;The West and Islam&quot;], By Mishal Fahm Sulami&lt;/ref&gt;
*'''Executive Office''' (Guidance Office) with its leader the General Masul (General Guide) and its members, both appointed by the Shura Office, has to follow up and guide the activities of the General Organisation. It submits a periodical report to the Shura Council about its work and of the activity of the domestic bodies and the general organisations. It distributes its duties to its members according to the internal bylaws.
It has the following divisions (not complete):
– Executive leadership
– Organisational office
– Secretariat general
– Education office
– Political office
– Sisters office

The Muslim Brotherhood aimed to build a [[Transnational organization|transnational organisation]], founding groups in [[Lebanon]] (in 1936), [[Syria]] (1937), and [[Transjordan]] (1946). It also recruited among the foreign students in [[Cairo]] where its headquarters became a center and meeting place for representatives from the whole Muslim world.&lt;ref name=Kuntzel/&gt;

In each country there is a Branch committee with a Masul (leader) appointed by the General Executive leadership with essentially the same Branch-divisions as the Executive office has. To the duties of every branch belong fundraising, infiltrating in and overtaking other Muslim organisations for the sake of uniting the Muslims to dedicate them to the general goals of the MB.

==In Egypt==
{{Main|Muslim Brotherhood in Egypt}}

===Founding===
[[Hassan al-Banna]] founded the Muslim Brotherhood in the city of [[Ismailia]] in March 1928 along with six workers of the [[Suez Canal]] Company, as a [[Pan-Islamic]], religious, political, and [[social movement]].   According to al-Banna, contemporary Islam had lost its social dominance, because most Muslims had been corrupted by [[Western world|Western]] influences. [[Sharia]] law based on the [[Qur'an]] and the [[Sunnah]] were seen as laws passed down by God that should be applied to all parts of life, including the organization of the government and the handling of everyday problems.&lt;ref name=Kuntzel&gt;Küntzel, 2002, pp. 17–19.&lt;/ref&gt;

Al-Banna was [[populism|populist]] in his message of protecting workers against the tyranny of foreign and monopolist companies. It founded social institutions such as hospitals, pharmacies, schools, etc. Al-Banna held highly conservative views on issues such as women's rights, opposing equal rights for women.&lt;ref name=&quot;Women&quot;/&gt;

The Brotherhood grew rapidly going from 800 members in 1936, to 200,000 by 1938, 500,000 in 1948.&lt;ref&gt;Hallett, Robin. Africa Since 1875. Ann Arbor, Michigan: The University of Michigan Press (1974), pg. 138.&lt;/ref&gt;

===Post WWII===
In November 1948, following several bombings and assassination attempts, the government arrest 32 leaders of the Brotherhood's &quot;secret apparatus&quot; and banned the Brotherhood.&lt;ref&gt;Chamieh, Jebran, Traditionalists, Militants and Liberal in Present Islam, Research and Publishing House, [1994?],  p.140&lt;/ref&gt;  At this time the Brotherhood was estimated to have 2000 branches and 500,000 members or sympathizers.&lt;ref&gt;Wright, Robin, ''Sacred Rage'' 1985, p.179&lt;/ref&gt;  In succeeding months Egypt's prime minister was assassinated by a Brotherhood member, and following that Al-Banna himself was assassinated in what is thought to be a cycle of retaliation.  In [[1952]] members of the Muslim Brotherhood are accused of taking part in the [[Cairo Fire]] that destroyed some &quot;750 buildings&quot; in downtown Cairo — mainly night clubs, theatres, hotels, and restaurants frequented by British and other foreigners.&lt;ref name=&quot;RebellionWright&quot;&gt;[http://www.newyorker.com/reporting/2008/06/02/080602fa_fact_wright?currentPage=all The Rebellion Within, An Al Qaeda mastermind questions terrorism. by Lawrence Wright.] newyorker.com, June 2, 2008&lt;/ref&gt;

In 1952 Egypt's monarchy was [[Egyptian Revolution of 1952|overthrown]] by nationalist military officers supported by the Brotherhood. However the Brotherhood opposed the secularist constitution of the coup leaders and in 1954 another assassination was attempted against Egypt's prime minister ([[Gamal Abdel Nasser]]), and blamed on the &quot;secret apparatus&quot; of the Brotherhood (this attempt was unsuccessful). The Brotherhood was again banned and this time thousands of its members were imprisoned, many of them held for years in prisons and [[concentration camp]]s, and sometimes tortured. 

Since the 1970s the Egyptian Brotherhood has disavowed violence and sought to participate in Egyptian politics.&lt;ref name=&quot;Crane&quot;&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.cfr.org/publication/9248/|title=Does the Muslim Brotherhood Have Ties to Terrorism|last=Crane|first=Mary|publisher=Council on Foreign Relations}}&lt;/ref&gt;  Imprisoned Brethren were released and the organization was tolerated to varying degrees with periodic arrests and crackdowns until the [[2011 Egyptian revolution|2011 Revolution]].

===Mubarak era===
In the 2005 parliamentary elections, the Brotherhood's candidates, who had to run as independents because of their illegality as a political party, won 88 seats (20% of the total). (The legal opposition won only 14 seats.)  This was despite electoral irregularities, including the arrest of hundreds of Brotherhood members. The Brotherhood became &quot;in effect, the first opposition party of Egypt’s modern era.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;nytimes2007&quot;/&gt;  

Accounts differ over the Brotherhood's record in parliament. Initially there was widespread skepticism inside and outside Egypt towards the MB's commitment to democracy, along with fears of &quot;severe restrictions on its freedom of opinion and belief&quot; in both religious matters, and &quot;social, political, economic and cultural affairs.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;[http://weekly.ahram.org.eg/2005/772/op8.htm Fawzi, Sameh. &quot;Brothers and Others&quot;.] Al-Ahram Weekly 8 December 2005. accessed 6 September 2011&lt;/ref&gt; 

But by 2007 a [[New York Times]] journalist wrote: &quot;While many secular critics fear that the brotherhood harbors a hidden Islamist agenda, so far the organization has posed a democratic political challenge to the regime, not a theological one.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;nytimes2007&quot;&gt;[http://www.nytimes.com/2007/04/29/magazine/29Brotherhood.t.html Traub, James. &quot;Islamic Democrats?&quot;] The New York Times. 29 April 2007. accessed 6 September 2011 &lt;/ref&gt;; and another report praised the MB for an &quot;unmatched record of attendance&quot;, forming a coalition to fight the extension of Egypt's emergency law, and generally attempting to transform &quot;the Egyptian parliament into a real legislative body, as well as an institution that represents citizens and a mechanism that keeps government accountable&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;merip2006&quot;&gt;[http://web.archive.org/web/20061001175005/http://www.merip.org/mer/mer240/shehata_stacher.html &quot;The Brotherhood Goes to Parliament&quot;]. Samer Shehata from [[Georgetown University]] and Joshua Stacher from the [[British University in Egypt]] ''Middle East Report''. Fall 2006. 29 November 2009&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;nytimes2007&quot;/&gt;

However, in December 2006 a campus demonstration by Muslim Brotherhood students in uniforms, demonstrating martial arts drills betrayed &quot;the group's intent to plan for the creation of militia structures, and a return by the group to the era of 'secret cells,'&quot; according to Jameel Theyabi.&lt;ref&gt;[http://english.daralhayat.com/opinion/OPED/12-2006/Article-20061218-95ae9eb8-c0a8-10ed-00b1-7119b3684228/story.html The Brotherhood's Power display] ''Dar Al-Hayat'' (18 December 2006)] &lt;/ref&gt; Another report highlighted the MB's efforts in Parliament to combat what one member called the `current US-led war against Islamic culture and identity`, forcing the Minister of Culture ([[Farouk Hosny]]) to ban the publication of three novels on the ground they promoted blasphemy and unacceptable sexual practices.&lt;ref&gt;Bradley, John R., ''Inside Egypt: The Land of the Pharaohs on the Brink of a Revolution'' by John R. Bradley, Palgrave MacMillan, 2008, p.62&lt;/ref&gt;  In October 2007, the Muslim Brotherhood issued a detailed political platform. Amongst other things it called for a board of Muslim clerics to oversee the government, and limiting the office of the presidency to Muslim men. In the `Issues and Problems` chapter of the platform, it declared that a woman was not suited to be president because the post's religious and military duties `conflict with her nature, social and other humanitarian roles.`   While underlining `equality between men and women in terms of their human dignity,` the document warned against `burdening women with duties against their nature or role in the family.`&lt;ref&gt;Bradley, John R., ''Inside Egypt'', Palgrave MacMillan, (p.65)&lt;/ref&gt;

Since 2005 Muslim Brotherhood members in Egypt have also become a significant movement online,&lt;ref name=&quot;arabmediasociety.com&quot;&gt;http://www.arabmediasociety.com/?article=692&lt;/ref&gt; with some &quot;cyberactivists&quot; critical of the organization.&lt;ref name=&quot;arabmediasociety.com&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;www.arabinsight.org/aiarticles/186.pdf&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news| url=http://www.guardian.co.uk/commentisfree/2007/mar/05/brotherhoodoftheblog | location=London | work=The Guardian | first=Marc | last=Lynch | title=Brotherhood of the blog | date=2007-03-05}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Whether or not the Brotherhood would unconditionally or conditionally dissolve Egypt's 32-year peace treaty with Israel is disputed within the Brotherhood. While the deputy leader of the Brotherhood has said the Brotherhood would seek the dissolution of Egypt's 32-year peace treaty with Israel,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title=Muslim Brotherhood seeks end to Israel treaty|url=http://www.washingtontimes.com/news/2011/feb/3/muslim-brotherhood-seeks-end-to-israel-treaty|publisher=[[The Washington Times]]}}&lt;/ref&gt; a Brotherhood spokesman has said that the Brotherhood would respect the treaty as long as &quot;Israel shows real progress on improving the lot of the Palestinians.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title=Live Blog: Egypt in Crisis, Day 8|url=http://www.cbsnews.com/8301-503543_162-20030175-503543.html|publisher=[[CBS News]] | date=2011-02-01}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The Brotherhood remains the largest opposition group in Egypt, advocating Islamic reform, democratic system and maintaining a vast network of support through Islamic charities working among poor Egyptians.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.irinnews.org/report.asp?ReportID=51850 |title=IRIN Middle East &amp;#124; EGYPT: Social programs bolster appeal of Muslim Brotherhood &amp;#124; Middle East &amp;#124; Egypt &amp;#124; Education Gender Issues Governance Health &amp; Nutrition Human Rights &amp;#124; News Item |publisher=Irinnews.org |date= |accessdate=2010-08-27}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===2011 revolution and after===
Following the [[2011 Egyptian revolution]] and fall of [[Hosni Mubarak]], the group was legalized.&lt;ref name=MBSharia&gt;[http://www.hurriyetdailynews.com/n.php?n=8220shari8217a-law-in-egypt-is-enough-for-us8221-tells-a-muslim-brotherhood-leader-2011-05-23 'Shariah in Egypt is enough for us,' Muslim Brotherhood leader says|23 May 2011]&lt;/ref&gt; The Brotherhood supported the [[Egyptian constitutional referendum, 2011|constitutional referendum]] in March which was also supported by the Egyptian army and opposed by Egyptian liberals.&lt;ref&gt;El Rashidi, Yasmine, &quot;Egypt: The Victorious Islamists&quot;,  ''New York Review of Books'', July 14, 2011&lt;/ref&gt; In 30 April 2011 it launched a new party called the [[Freedom and Justice Party (Egypt)|Freedom and Justice Party]], which reportedly plans to &quot;contest up to half the seats&quot; in the Egyptian parliamentary election scheduled for September 2011.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/world-middle-east-13249434 Egypt: Muslim Brotherhood sets up new party], 30 April 2011&lt;/ref&gt; The party &quot;rejects the candidacy of women or Copts for Egypt's presidency&quot;, but not for cabinet positions.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.ikhwanweb.com/article.php?id=28554 Freedom and Justice Party Open to Copt as Deputy], 2011 May 11&lt;/ref&gt; Some splinter groups have appeared in the wake of the revolution.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.washingtonpost.com/world/egypts-muslim-brotherhood-could-be-unraveling/2011/07/06/gIQAdMZp1H_story.html Egypt’s Muslim Brotherhood could be unraveling], By Leila Fadel,  July 7, 2011&lt;/ref&gt;

===General leaders===
({{lang|ar|المرشد العام لجماعة الإخوان المسلمون}})'''

:* Founder &amp; First G. leader: (1928–1949) [[Hassan al Banna]]
:* 2nd G.L. : (1949–1972) [[Hassan al-Hudaybi]]
:* 3rd G.L. : (1972–1986) [[Umar al-Tilmisani]]
:* 4th G.L. : (1986–1996) [[Muhammad Hamid Abu al-Nasr]]
:* 5th G.L. : (1996–2002) [[Mustafa Mashhur]]
:* 6th G.L. : (2002–2004) [[Ma'mun al-Hudaybi]]
:* 7th G.L. : (2004–2010)  [[Mohammed Mahdi Akef]]
:* 8th G.L. : (16 January 2010 – present) [[Mohammed Badie]] {{Citation needed|date=January 2011}}

==In West Asia==
===Bahrain===
In [[Bahrain]], the Muslim Brotherhood is represented by the [[Al Eslah Society]] and its political wing, the [[Al-Menbar Islamic Society]]. Following parliamentary elections in 2002, [[Al-Menbar Islamic Society|Al Menbar]] became the joint largest party with eight seats in the forty seat [[Chamber of Deputies of Bahrain|Chamber of Deputies]]. Prominent members of Al Menbar include Dr Salah Abdulrahman, Dr [[Salah Al Jowder]], and outspoken MP [[Mohammed Khalid]]. The party has generally backed government sponsored legislation on economic issues, but has sought a clampdown on pop concerts, sorcery and soothsayers. It has strongly opposed the government's accession to the [[International Covenant on Civil and Political Rights]] on the grounds that this w ould give Muslim citizens the right to change religion, when in the party's view they should be &quot;beheaded&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.gulf-daily-news.com/1yr_arc_Articles.asp?Article=136119&amp;Sn=BNEW&amp;IssueID=28339&amp;date=2-22-2006 |title=Gulf Daily News |publisher=Gulf Daily News |date=2009-03-09 |accessdate=2010-08-27}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In March 2009, the Shi'a group [[The Islamic Enlightenment Society]] held its annual conference with the announced aim of diffusing tension between Muslim branches. The society invited national Sunni and Shi'a scholars to participate. Bahraini independent Salafi (Sunni) religious scholars Sheikh [[Salah Al-Jowder]] and Sheikh Rashid Al Muraikhi, and Shi'a clerics Sheikh Isa Qasim and Abdulla Al Ghoraifi spoke about the importance of sectarian cooperation. Additional seminars were held throughout the year.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.state.gov/g/drl/rls/irf/2009/127345.htm International Religious Freedom Report 2009], ''[[U.S. Department of State]]'', October 26, 2009&lt;/ref&gt;

In 2010, the U.S. government sponsored the visit of Al-Jowder, described as a prominent Sunni cleric, to the United States for a three-week interfaith dialogue program in several cities.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.state.gov/g/drl/rls/irf/2010/148815.htm International Religious Freedom Report 2010], ''[[U.S. Department of State]]'', November 17, 2010&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.eurasiareview.com/analysis/bahrain-the-political-structure-reform-and-human-rights-28022011/ Bahrain: The Political Structure, Reform And Human Rights], Kenneth Katzman, ''[[Eurasia Review]]'', February 18, 2011&lt;/ref&gt;

===Syria===
{{Main|History of the Muslim Brotherhood in Syria}}

Muslim Brotherhood in Syria was founded in the 1930s (according to lexicorient.com) or in 1945, a year before independence from France, (according to journalist [[Robin Wright (author)]]).  In the first decade or so of independence it was part of the legal opposition, and in the [[Syrian parliamentary election, 1961|1961 parliamentary elections]] it won ten seats (5.8% of the house). But after the 1963 coup that brought the [[Baath Party]] to power it was banned.&lt;ref&gt;Wright, Robin, ''Dreams and Shadows : the Future of the Middle East'', Penguin Press, 2008, p. 241.&lt;/ref&gt; It played a major role in the mainly [[Sunni]]-based terrorist movement that opposed the [[secularism|secularist]], [[pan-Arabism|pan-Arabist]] [[Baath party]]. This conflict developed into an armed struggle that continued until culminating in the [[Hama massacre|Hama uprising]] of 1982, when the rebellion was crushed by the military.&lt;ref&gt;[http://lexicorient.com/e.o/mus_br_syria.htm Looklex encyclopedia]&lt;/ref&gt;

Membership in the Syrian Brotherhood became a [[capital punishment|capital offence]] in Syria in 1980 (under Emergency Law 49, which was revoked in 2011), but the headquarters of the MB-linked Palestinian group, [[Hamas]], is located in the Syria's capital Damascus, where it is given Syrian government support. This is seen by some as an example of the lack of international centralisation or even coordination of the MB.&lt;ref&gt;Wright, Robin, ''Dreams and Shadows : the Future of the Middle East'', Penguin Press, 2008, p. 248.&lt;/ref&gt;

===Jordan===
The [[Jordan]]ian branch of the Muslim Brotherhood was formed in 1942, and is a strong factor in [[Politics of Jordan|Jordanian politics]]. While most political parties and movements were banned for a long time in Jordan such as [[Hizb ut-Tahrir]], the Brotherhood was exempted and allowed to operate by the [[King of Jordan|Jordanian monarchy]]. The Jordanian Brotherhood has formed its own [[political party]], the [[Islamic Action Front]], which has the largest number of seats of any party in the [[Parliament of Jordan|Jordanian parliament]].&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|author=Tore Kjeilen |url=http://lexicorient.com/e.o/mus_br_jordan.htm |title=Muslim Brotherhood / Jordan - LookLex Encyclopaedia |publisher=Lexicorient.com |date=2000-09-20 |accessdate=2010-08-27}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The Muslim Brotherhood is playing an active role in the unrest in several Arab countries in January 2011. For example, at a rally held outside the Egyptian Embassy in Amman on Saturday, 29 January 2011 with some 100 participants, Hammam Saeed, head of the Muslim Brotherhood of Jordan and a close ally of the Hamas's Damascus-based leader, [[Khaled Meshaal]], said: &quot;Egypt's unrest will spread across the Mideast and Arabs will topple leaders allied with the United States.&quot; However, he did not specifically name Jordanian King [[Abdullah II]].&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|author=Commentator |url=http://timesofindia.indiatimes.com/world/middle-east/Jordans-opposition-Arabs-will-topple-tyrants/articleshow/7385868.cms | title=Jordan's opposition: Arabs will topple tyrants | Times of India|publisher=timesofindia.indiatimes.com |date=2011-01-30 |accessdate=2011-01-30}}&lt;/ref&gt; The Muslim brotherhood is rightfully or wrongfully feared by several commentators in the west, however it is not known how many seats in a democratic government the brotherhood will gain in any of the aforementioned countries.

===Iran===
Although Iran is a predominately Shia Muslim country and the Muslim Brotherhood is Sunni in doctrine, Olga Davidson and Mohammad Mahallati claim the Brotherhood has had influence among Shia in Iran.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.bitterlemons-international.org/previous.php?opt=1&amp;id=30 |title=Middle East Roundtable |publisher=bitterlemons-international.org |date= |accessdate=2010-08-27}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Navab Safavi]], who founded Fadaian Islam,  (also Fedayeen of Islam, or Fadayan-e Islam), an Iranian Islamic organization active in Iran in the 1940s and 1950s, &quot;was highly impressed by the Muslim Brotherhood.&lt;ref&gt;[http://pajamasmedia.com/michaeltotten/2011/02/01/the-iranian-revolution-echoes-in-egypt/ &quot;The Iranian Revolution Echoes in Egypt&quot;], M.J.Toten in Interview with Dr. [[Abbas Milani]]&lt;/ref&gt; From 1945 to 1951 the Fadain assassinated several high level Iranian personalities and officials who they believed to be un-Islamic. They included anti-clerical writer Ahmad Kasravi, Premier Haj-Ali Razm-Ara, former Premier Abdul-Hussein Hazhir, and Education and Culture Minister Ahmad Zangeneh.&lt;ref name=&quot;TSOA-Adler-1985&quot;&gt;''The Spirit of Allah: Khomeini and the Islamic Revolution'' by Amir Taheri, Adler and Adler c1985, pp. 107–109.&lt;/ref&gt;

At that time Navab Safavi was an associate and ally of Ayatollah Khomeini who went on to become a figure in the [[Iranian Revolution]] of 1979.&lt;ref name=&quot;TSOA-Adler-1985&quot;/&gt; Khomeini and other religious figures in Iran worked to establish Islamic unity and downplay Shia-Sunni differences. {{Citation needed|date=March 2007}}

===Iraq===
The [[Iraqi Islamic Party]] was formed in 1960 as the [[Iraq]]i branch of the Brotherhood,&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|author=Alan Godlas |url=http://www.uga.edu/islam/muslim_brotherhood_iraq.html |title=The Muslim Brotherhood in Iraq |publisher=Uga.edu |date=1968-07-17 |accessdate=2010-08-27}}&lt;/ref&gt; but was banned from 1961 during the nationalist rule of [[Abd al-Karim Qasim]]. As government repression hardened under the [[Baath Party]] from February 1963, the group was forced to continue underground. After the [[2003 invasion of Iraq|fall]] of the [[Saddam Hussein]] regime in 2003, the Islamic Party has reemerged as one of the main advocates of the country's Sunni community. The Islamic Party has been sharply critical of the U.S.-led [[military occupation|occupation]] of Iraq, but participates in the political process.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|author=John Pike |url=http://www.globalsecurity.org/military/world/iraq/iip.htm |title=Iraqi Islamic Party |publisher=Globalsecurity.org |date=2010-05-13 |accessdate=2010-08-27}}&lt;/ref&gt; Its leader is Iraqi Vice-President [[Tariq Al-Hashimi]].

Also, in the north of Iraq there are several Islamic movements inspired by or part of the Muslim Brotherhood network. The [[Kurdistan Islamic Union]] (KIU) holds seats in the Kurdish parliament, and is the main political force outside the dominance of the two main [[secularist]] parties, the [[Patriotic Union of Kurdistan|PUK]] and [[Kurdistan Democratic Party of Iraq|KDP]].&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news| url=http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/not_in_website/syndication/monitoring/media_reports/2588623.stm | work=BBC News | title=Profile: Kurdish Islamist movement | date=2003-01-13 | accessdate=2010-04-06}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Palestine===
'Abd al-Rahman al-Banna, the brother of the Muslim Brotherhood founder Hasan al-Banna, went to the [[British Mandate for Palestine]] and established the Muslim Brotherhood there in 1935. [[Mohammad Amin al-Husayni|Al-Hajj Amin al-Husseini]], eventually appointed by the British as Grand Mufti of Jerusalem in hopes of accommodating him, was the leader of the group in Palestine.&lt;ref&gt;http://archive.frontpagemag.com/readArticle.aspx?ARTID=11146&lt;/ref&gt; Another important leader associated with the Muslim Brotherhood in Palestine was 'Izz al-Din al-Qassam, an inspiration to Islamists because he had been the first to lead an armed resistance in the name of Palestine against the British in 1935.&lt;ref&gt;Cohen, 1982, p. 144.&lt;/ref&gt; In 1945, the group established a branch in [[Jerusalem]], and by 1947 twenty-five more branches had sprung up, in towns such as [[Jaffa, Israel|Jaffa]], [[Lod]], [[Haifa]], [[Nablus]], and [[Tulkarm]], which total membership between 12,000 to 20,000.

Brotherhood members fought alongside the Arab armies during the [[1948 Arab-Israeli war]], and, after Israel's creation, the ensuing [[Palestinian refugee]] crisis encouraged more Palestinian Muslims to join the group. After the war, in the West Bank, the group's activity was mainly social and religious, not political, so it had relatively good relations with Jordan, which was in control of the West Bank after 1950. In contrast, the group frequently clashed with the Egyptian regime that controlled the Gaza Strip until 1967.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|jstor=3992661}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In the 1950s and 1960s, the Brotherhood's goal was &quot;the upbringing of an Islamic generation&quot; through the restructuring of society and religious education, rather than Palestine's liberation from Israel, and so it lost popularity to national resistance movements and the presence of [[Hizb ut-Tahrir]].&lt;ref&gt;0253208661&lt;/ref&gt; Eventually, however, the Brotherhood was strengthened by several factors:

#The creation of al-Mujamma' al-Islami, the Islamic Center in 1973 by Shaykh Ahmad Yasin had a centralizing effect that encapsulated all religious organizations.
#The Muslim Brotherhood Society in Jordan and Palestine was created from a merger of the branches in the West Bank and Gaza and Jordan.
#Palestinian disillusion with the liberation front caused them to become more open to alternatives.
#The Islamic Revolution in Iran offered inspiration to Palestinians. The Brotherhood was able to increase its efforts in Palestine and avoid being dismantled like national resistance groups because it did not focus on the occupation.  While national resistance groups were being dismantled, the Brotherhood filled the void.&lt;ref name=hamas&gt;{{citation |title=Hamas: A Historical and Political Background |author=Ziad Abu-Amr |journal=Journal of Palestine Studies |volume=22 |issue=4 |date=Summer, 1993 |pages=5–19 |jstor=2538077}}&lt;/ref&gt;

After the 1967 [[Six Day War]], as Israel's occupation started, Israel may have looked to cultivate political Islam as a counterweight to [[Fatah]], the main secular Palestinian nationalist political organization.&lt;ref name=&quot;online.wsj.com&quot;&gt;[http://online.wsj.com/article/SB123275572295011847.html How Israel Helped to Spawn Hamas, by Andrew Higgins] ''Wall Street Journal'' January 24, 2009&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.guardian.co.uk/world/2009/jan/07/gaza-israel-palestine/print?2 How Israel brought Gaza to the brink of humanitarian catastrophe, by Avi Shlaim] ''Guardian UK'' January 7, 2009&lt;/ref&gt; Between 1967 and 1987, the year Hamas was founded, the number of mosques in Gaza tripled from 200 to 600, and the Muslim Brotherhood named the period between 1975 and 1987 a phase of 'social institution building.'&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.metimes.com/Politics/2009/03 ]{{Dead link|date=August 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; During that time, the Brotherhood established associations, used [[zakat]] (alms giving) for aid to poor Palestinians, promoted schools, provided students with loans, used waqf (religious endowments) to lease property and employ people, and established mosques. Likewise, antagonistic and sometimes violent opposition to [[Fatah]], the [[Palestine Liberation Organization]] and other secular nationalist groups increased dramatically in the streets and on university campuses.&lt;ref name=&quot;online.wsj.com&quot;/&gt;

The Brotherhood's downfall was its failure to fight the Israeli occupation, but the Intifada changed the Brotherhood's position and Hamas was established.&lt;ref name=hamas/&gt; The ''Islamic Resistance Movement'', or [[Hamas]], founded in 1987 in Gaza, is a wing of the Brotherhood,&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.mideastweb.org/hamas.htm |title=Hamas Charter |publisher=Mideastweb.org |date= |accessdate=2010-08-27}}&lt;/ref&gt; formed out of Brotherhood-affiliated charities and social institutions that had gained a strong foothold among the local population. During the [[First Intifada]] (1987–93), Hamas militarized and transformed into one of the strongest Palestinian militant groups.

The [[Hamas takeover of the Gaza Strip]] in 2007 was the first time since the Sudanese coup of 1989 that brought [[Omar al-Bashir]] to power, that a Muslim Brotherhood group ruled a significant geographic territory.&lt;ref name=&quot;Schanzer&quot;&gt;[http://www.currenttrends.org/research/detail/the-talibanization-of-gaza-a-liability-for-the-muslim-brotherhood The Talibanization of Gaza: A Liability for the Muslim Brotherhood]. by Jonathan Schanzer. August 19, 2009. [[Current Trends in Islamist Ideology]] vol. 9&lt;/ref&gt;

===Saudi Arabia===
The Muslim Brotherhood's brand of Islam and Islamic politics differs from the strict [[Salafism|Salafi]] creed, [[Wahhabi]]yya, officially held by the state of [[Saudi Arabia]]. Despite this, the Brotherhood has been tolerated by the Saudi government, and maintains a presence in the country.{{Citation needed|date=October 2009}} Aside from tolerating the Brotherhood organization{{Citation needed|date=October 2009}}, and according to [[Washington Post]] report, Saudi Interior Minister [[Prince Nayef]] has denounced the Brotherhood, saying it is guilty of &quot;betrayal of pledges and ingratitude&quot; and is &quot;the source of all problems in the Islamic world&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;WashingtonPost-Diverse&quot;/&gt;

===Kuwait===
The Muslim Brotherhood in Kuwait is represented in the Kuwaiti parliament by [[Hadas]].&lt;ref&gt;''The Future of Political Islam'', by Graham E. Fuller, Palgrave MacMillan, 2003, p. 39.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.spiegel.de/international/world/0,1518,491925,00.html|title=Charting the Rise of the Muslim Brotherhood}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Yemen===
The Muslim Brotherhood is the political arm of the [[Yemeni Congregation for Reform]], commonly known as Islah. President [[Ali Abdullah Saleh]] accused them of being in league with Al Qaida and stirring up the [[2011 Yemen protests]] against his rule.&lt;ref&gt;www.time.com/time/world/article/0,8599,2095702,00.html&lt;/ref&gt;
===Oman===
Sultan [[Qaboos bin Said al Said]] of [[Oman]] claimed that the [[Muslim Brotherhood]] obtained support from the uneducated people.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news| url=http://www.guardian.co.uk/world/us-embassy-cables-documents/143790 | location=London | work=The Guardian | title=US embassy cables: Oman sultan resists Iranian charm offensive | date=2010-11-28}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Elsewhere in Africa==
===Algeria===
The Muslim Brotherhood reached [[Algeria]] during the later years of the French colonial presence in the country (1830–1962). Sheikh Ahmad Sahnoun led the organization in Algeria between 1953 and 1954 during the French colonialism. Brotherhood members and sympathizers took part in the uprising against France in 1954–1962, but the movement was marginalized during the largely secular FLN one-party rule which was installed at independence in 1962. It remained unofficially active, sometimes protesting the government and calling for increased Islamization and Arabization of the country's politics.

When a multi-party system was introduced in Algeria in the early 1990s, the Muslim Brotherhood formed the [[Movement for the Society of Peace]] (MSP, previously known as Hamas), led by [[Mahfoud Nahnah]] until his death in 2003 (he was succeeded by present party leader [[Boudjerra Soltani]]). The Muslim Brotherhood in Algeria did not join the [[Front islamique du salut]] (FIS), which emerged as the leading Islamist group, winning the 1991 elections and which was banned in 1992 following a military [[coup d'état]], although some Brotherhood sympathizers did. The Brotherhood subsequently also refused to join the violent post-coup uprising by FIS sympathizers and the [[Armed Islamic Groups]] (GIA) against the Algerian state and military which followed, and urged a peaceful resolution to the conflict and a return to democracy. It has thus remained a legal political organization and enjoyed parliamentary and government representation. In 1995, Sheikh Nahnah ran for [[President of Algeria]] finishing second with 25.38% of the popular vote. During the 2000s, the party—led by Nahnah's successor [[Boudjerra Soltani]]—has been a member of a three-party coalition backing President [[Abdelaziz Bouteflika]].

===Sudan===
Until the election of [[Hamas]] in [[Gaza]], [[Sudan]] was the one country were the Brotherhood was most successful in gaining power, its members making up a large part of the government officialdom following the 1989 coup d'état by General [[Omar Hassan al-Bashir]].

Always close to Egyptian politics, Sudan has had a Muslim Brotherhood presence since 1949. In 1945, a delegation from the Muslim Brotherhood in Egypt visited Sudan and held various meetings inside the country advocating and explaining their ideology. Sudan has a long and deep history with the Muslim Brotherhood compared to many other countries. By April 1949, the first branch of the Sudanese Muslim Brotherhood organization emerged. However, simultaneously, many Sudanese students studying in Egypt were introduced to the ideology of the Brotherhood. The Muslim student groups also began organizing in the universities during the 1940s, and the Brotherhood's main support base has remained to be college educated. In order to unite them, in 1954, a conference was held, attended by various representatives from different groups that appeared to have the same ideology. The conference voted to establish a Unified Sudanese Muslim Brotherhood Organization based on the teachings of Imam Hassan Al-banna.

An offshoot of the Sudanese branch of the Muslim Brotherhood, the [[Islamic Charter Front]] grew during the 1960, with Islamic scholar [[Hasan al-Turabi]] becoming its Secretary general in 1964. The Islamic Charter Front (ICM) was renamed several times most recently being called the [[National Islamic Front]] (NIF). Turabi has been the prime architect of the NIF as a modern Islamist party. He worked within the Institutions of the government, which led to a prominent position of his organization in the country. NIF supported women's right to vote and ran women candidates. The Muslim Brotherhood/NIF's main objective in Sudan was to Islamize the society &quot;from above&quot; and to institutionalize the Islamic law throughout the country where they succeeded.

The Brotherhood penetrated into the ruling political organizations, the state army and security personal, the national and regional assemblies of Sudan. They also launched their own mass organizations among the youth and women such as the shabab al-binna, and raidat al-nahda, and launched educational campaigns to Islamize the communities throughout the country. At the same time, they gained control of several newly founded Islamic missionary and relief organizations to spread their ideology. The Brotherhood members took control of the newly established Islamic Banks as directors, administrators, employees and legal advisors, which became a source of power for the Brotherhood.

The Sudanese government has come under considerable criticism for its [[human rights]] policies, links to terrorist groups, and war in southern Sudan and Darfur.
{{See also|Darfur conflict|Second Sudanese Civil War|Human rights in Sudan}}

The conservatism of at least some elements of the Sudanese Muslim Brotherhood was highlighted in an August 3, 2007 [[Al-Jazeera]] television interview of Sudanese Muslim Brotherhood leader Sheikh [[Sadeq Abdallah bin Al-Majed]]. As translated by the Israeli-based [[Middle East Media Research Institute|MEMRI]], Bin Al-Majed told his interviewer that &quot;the West, and the Americans in particular&amp;nbsp;… are behind all the tragedies that are taking place in [[Darfur]]&quot;, as they &quot;realized that it [[Darfur]] is full of treasures&quot;; that &quot;Islam does not permit a non-Muslim to rule over Muslims;&quot; and that he had issued a fatwa prohibiting the vaccination of children, on the grounds that the vaccinations were &quot;a conspiracy of the [[Jew]]s and [[Freemason]]s&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.memri.org/bin/opener_latest.cgi?ID=SD168507|title=Al-Jazeera Interviews – Muslim Brotherhood Leader in Sudan}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Somalia===
Somalia's wing of the Muslim Brotherhood is known by the name Harakat Al-Islah or &quot;Reform Movement&quot;. Nonetheless, the Brotherhood, as mentioned earlier, has inspired many Islamist organizations in Somalia. Muslim Brotherhood ideology reached [[Somalia]] in the early 1960s, but Al-Islah movement was formed in 1978 and slowly grew in the 1980s. Al-Islah has been described as &quot;a generally nonviolent and modernizing Islamic movement that emphasizes the reformation and revival of Islam to meet the challenges of the modern world&quot;, whose &quot;goal is the establishment of an [[Islamic state]]&quot; and which &quot;operates primarily in Mogadishu&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;state2004&quot;&gt;[http://www.state.gov/g/drl/rls/irf/2004/35382.htm International Religious Freedom Report 2004. Somalia]&lt;/ref&gt;

The founders of the Islah Movement are: Sh. Mohamed Ahmed Nur, Dr. [[Ali Sheikh Ahmed]], Dr. Mohamed Yusuf Abdi, Sh. Ahmed Rashid Hanafi, and Sh. Abdullah Ahmed Abdullah. The organization structured itself loosely and was not openly visible on the political scene of Somali society.

They chose to remain a secret movement fearing the repressive regime of [[Siad Barre]] but are considered the first ever opposition to the dictatorship. However, they emerged from secrecy when the regime collapsed in 1991 and started working openly thereafter. Most Somalis were surprised to see the new group they had never heard of, which was in the country since the 1970s in secrecy.

According to the Islah by-law, every five years the organization has to elect its Consultative (Shura) Council which elects the Chairman and the two Vice-chairman. During the last 30 years, four chairmen were elected. These are Sheikh Mohamed Geryare (1978–1990), Dr. Mohamed Ali Ibrahim (1990–1999), Dr. Ali Sheikh Ahmed (1999–2008) and Dr. Ali Bashi Omar Roraye (2008–2013).

Dr. Ali Bashi is a [[medical doctor]], a former university professor and a member of the transitional parliament (2000–2008). During the 1990s, Al-Islah devoted much effort to humanitarian efforts and providing free basic social services.

The leaders of Al-Islah played a key role in the educational network and establishing Mogadishu University. Through their network, they educate more than 120,000 students in the city of Mogadishu. Many other secondary schools such as the University of East Africa in Bosasso, Puntland, are externally funded and administered through organizations affiliated with the Muslim Brotherhood-affiliated Islamic organization Al-Islah.&lt;ref name=&quot;state2004&quot;/&gt;  In Somalia, they are known to be a peaceful organization that does not participate in any factional fighting and rejects the use of violence.

Today the group's membership includes urban professionals and students. According to a Crisis Group Report, Somalia's Islamists, &quot;Al-Islah organization is dominated by a highly educated urban elite whose professional, middle class status and extensive expatriate experiences are alien to most Somalis.&quot;

Although Al-Islah have been criticized by some hardcore Islamists who considered them to be influenced by imperialist western values, Al-Islah speaks of democratic peaceful Somalia. They promote women's rights, human rights, and other ideas, which they argue that these concepts originate from Islamic concepts. Al-Islah is gaining momentum in the Somali societies for their humanitarian work and moderate view of Islam, which is compatible to modernisation and respect of human rights. Currently, Islah initiated to establish political party under the name of Justice and Unity Party which is open for all citizens of Somalia.

===Tunisia===
Like their counterparts elsewhere in the Islamic world in general, the Egyptian Muslim Brotherhood has influenced the Tunisia's Islamists. One of the notable organization that was influenced and inspired by the Brotherhood is [[Ennahda Movement|Ennahda]] (The Revival or Renaissance Party), which is Tunisia's major Islamist political grouping. An Islamist named [[Rashid Ghannouchi]] founded the organization in 1981. While studying in Damascus and Paris, Rashid Ghannouchi embraced the ideology of the Muslim Brotherhood, which he disseminated on his return to Tunisia.

==Other states==
===Russian Federation===
The Muslim Brotherhood is banned in [[Russia]] as a [[terrorist organisation]].&lt;ref name=&quot;FSB list&quot;&gt;{{ru icon}} {{cite web|url=http://nak.fsb.ru/nac/ter_org.htm|title=Единый федеральный список организаций, признанных террористическими Верховным Судом Российской Федерации|publisher=[[Federal Security Service]]|accessdate=2011-04-13}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{ru icon}} {{cite web|url=http://base.consultant.ru/cons/cgi/online.cgi?req=doc;base=EXP;n=257852|title=Постановление ГД ФС РФ от 12.02.2003 N 3624-III ГД &quot;О Заявлении Государственной Думы Федерального Собрания Российской Федерации &quot;О пресечении деятельности террористических организаций на территории Российской Федерации&quot;] // &quot;Собрание законодательства РФ&quot;, 24.02.2003, N 8, ст. 720 ({{lang-ru|Resolution of the State Duma,  12.02.2003 N 3624-III GD &quot;on the Application of the State Duma of the Russian Federation&quot; on the suppression of the activities of terrorist organisations on the territory of the Russian Federation}})|publisher=[[Consultant Plus]]}}&lt;/ref&gt;

As affirmed on 14 February, 2003 by the decision of the [[Supreme Court of Russia]], the Muslim Brotherhood coordinated the creation of an Islamic organisation called ''The Supreme Military Majlis ul-Shura of the United Forces of Caucasian Mujahedeen'' ({{lang-ru|[[:ru:Высший военный маджлисуль шура объединённых сил моджахедов Кавказа|''Высший военный маджлисуль шура объединённых сил моджахедов Кавказа'']])}}, led by [[Ibn Al-Khattab]] and [[Basaev]]; an organisation that committed multiple attacks acts in Russia and was allegedly financed by drug trafficking, counterfeiting of coins and racketeering.&lt;ref name=&quot;RF SC Decision&quot;&gt;{{ru icon}}  {{cite web|url=http://www.religare.ru/2_5347.html |title=Решение ВС РФ о признании террористическими ряда иностранных организаций |publisher=Справочно-информационный интернет-портал RELIGARE (&quot;РЕЛИГИЯ и СМИ&quot;)|accessdate=2011-04-13}}&lt;/ref&gt;

According to the above-mention decision of the Supreme Court:
{{quote|Muslim Brotherhood is an organisation, basing its activities on the ideas of its theorists and leaders [[Hassan al-Banna]] and [[Sayyid Qutb]] with an aim of destruction of non-Islamic governments and the establishment of the worldwide Islamic government by the reconstruction of the &quot;Great Islamic Caliphate&quot;; firstly, in regions with majority of Muslim population, including those in Russia and [[CIS]] countries. The organisation is illegal in some Middle East countries ([[Syria]], [[Jordan]]). The main forms of activities are warlike [[Islamism]] propaganda with intolerance to other religions, recruitment in mosques, armed [[Jihad]] without territorial boundaries.|[[Supreme Court of Russia|The Supreme Court of Russia]]&lt;ref name=&quot;RF SC Decision&quot; /&gt;}}

===United States of America===
The MB's organisations in the USA were started by activists involved with the Muslim Brotherhood and included the [[Muslim Students Association]] in 1963,&lt;ref name=&quot;WashingtonPost-Diverse&quot;/&gt; [[North American Islamic Trust]] in 1971, the [[Islamic Society of North America]] in 1981, the [[American Muslim Council]] in 1990, the [[Muslim American Society]] in 1992 and the [[International Institute of Islamic Thought]] in the 1980s.&lt;ref name=&quot;WashingtonPost-Diverse&quot;/&gt; According to the ''[[Washington Post]]'', Muslim activists say the MSA's members represent &quot;all schools of Islam and political leanings&amp;nbsp;– many are [[moderate]]s, while others express anti-U.S. views or support resistance against Israelis.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;WashingtonPost-Diverse&quot;/&gt;

The [[Holy Land Foundation for Relief and Development#Terrorism charges|Holy Land Foundation trial]] has led to the release, as evidence, of&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.nefafoundation.org/hlfdocs.html |title=United States v. Holy Land Foundation |publisher=The NEFA Foundation |date= |accessdate=2010-08-27}} {{Dead link|date=October 2010|bot=H3llBot}}&lt;/ref&gt; several documents on the Muslim Brotherhood. One of these documents, dated in 1991,  explains that the goal of the Muslim Brotherhood in the U.S. is &quot;settlement,&quot; defined by the brotherhood as a form of jihad aimed at destroying Western civilisation from within and allowing for the victory of Islam over other religions.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;The Muslim Brotherhood in the United States&quot; http://www.currenttrends.org/docLib/20090411_Merley.USBROTHERHOOD.pdf&lt;/ref&gt; In another one of these documents, &quot;Ikhwan in America&quot;, the author alleges that the activities of the Muslim Brotherhood in the US include going to camps to do weapons training (referred to as ''Special work'' by the Muslim Brotherhood),&lt;ref&gt;Zeid al-Noman, [http://www.nefafoundation.org/miscellaneous/HLF/IkhwanAmerica.pdf &quot;Ikhwan in America&quot;], pp. 13, 16.&lt;/ref&gt; as well as engaging in [[counter-espionage]] against US government agencies such as the [[Federal Bureau of Investigation|FBI]] and [[Central Intelligence Agency|CIA]] (referred to as ''Securing the Group'').&lt;ref&gt;Zeid al-Noman, [http://www.nefafoundation.org/miscellaneous/HLF/IkhwanAmerica.pdf &quot;Ikhwan in America&quot;], p. 13.&lt;/ref&gt;

===United Kingdom===
The Muslim Brotherhood has formally been active in the U.K since 1996 and now holds a significant but widely unknown presence within the U.K's Muslim population.

In 1996, the first representative of the MB in Britain, Kamal el-Helbawy, an Egyptian, was able to say that &quot;there are not many members here, but many Muslims in Britain intellectually support the aims of the Muslim Brotherhood.&quot; He added that at that time, the object of the MB in Britain was only to disseminate information on Islam, Islamic issues and movements, and to rectify the distortions and misunderstandings created by &quot;different forces against Islam&quot;.

In September 1999, the MB opened a &quot;global information centre&quot; in London. A press notice published in Muslim News stated that it would &quot;specialize in promoting the perspectives and stances of the Muslim Brotherhood, and [communicate] between Islamic movements and the global mass media.&quot;

One of the notable mosques which has affiliations with the Brotherhood is the [[East London Mosque]].

==Criticisms==
===Motives===
Numerous officials and reporters question the sincerity of the MB's pronouncements. These critics include, but are not limited to:

*According to [[FrontPage Magazine]], a conservative publication, former U.S. [[White House]] counterterrorism chief [[Juan Zarate]] said: &quot;The Muslim Brotherhood is a group that worries us not because it deals with philosophical or ideological ideas but because it defends the use of violence against civilians.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;[http://97.74.65.51/readArticle.aspx?ARTID=3996 Ehrenfeld, Rachel and Lappen, Alyssa A., (16 June 2006) &quot;The Truth about the Muslim Brotherhood&quot; Front Page Magazine, citing Sylvain Besson, La Conquête De L'Occident: Le Projet Secret Des Islamistes, as quoted in Guitta, Olivier, (20 February 2006), &quot;The Cartoon Jihad,&quot; The Weekly Standard]. Retrieved 2007-03-01.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.frontpagemag.com/Articles/ReadArticle.asp?ID=27519 Poole, Patrick, (26 March 2007) &quot;Mainstreaming the Muslim Brotherhood&quot; Front Page Magazine, citing Sylvain Besson, La Conquête De L'Occident: Le Projet Secret Des Islamistes, p. 39)]. Retrieved 2007-04-25.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;/BLOCKQUOTE&gt;
*[[Raymond Ibrahim]], editor of ''The Al Qaeda Reader'', who notes that [[Muhammad]] himself described war as &quot;deceit&quot; and that Muslim Brotherhood disciples, past and present, merely duplicate the &quot;everlasting words of Allah&quot;, as iterated in the Qur'an.&lt;ref&gt;[http://article.nationalreview.com/print/?q=NGIxMmVmZjRjYTEzNGVlYjJjNDBhNTA4ZTQ3OTdhZTY= Raymond Ibrahim on Abu Hamza al-Masri on National Review Online&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.americanthinker.com/2007/11/the_al_qaeda_reader_a_review.html American Thinker: The Al Qaeda Reader: A Review&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;
*[[Miles Axe Copeland, Jr.]] -a prominent U.S. [[Central Intelligence Agency]] (CIA) operative who was one of the founding members of the [[Office of Strategic Services]] (OSS) under [[William Joseph Donovan|William Donovan]]- divulges the confessions of numerous members of the Muslim brotherhood that resulted from the harsh interrogations done against them by Egyptian president [[Gamal Abdel Nasser]], for their alleged involvement in the assassination attempt made against Nasser (an assassination attempt that many believe was staged by Nasser himself&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://gulfnews.com/about-gulf-news/al-nisr-portfolio/weekend-review/articles/revolutionary-leader-1.40238 |title=Revolutionary leader |publisher=gulfnews |date= |accessdate=2010-08-27}}&lt;/ref&gt;), which revealed that the Muslim Brotherhood was merely a &quot;guild&quot; that fulfilled the goals of western interests: &quot;Nor was that all. Sound beatings of the Moslem Brotherhood organizers who had been arrested revealed that the organization had been thoroughly penetrated, at the top, by the British, American, French and Soviet intelligence services, any one of which could either make active use of it or blow it up, whichever best suited its purposes. Important lesson: fanaticism is no insurance against corruption; indeed, the two are highly compatible.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;[[Miles Axe Copeland, Jr.]], &quot;The Game of Nations: The Amorality of Power Politics, New York: Simon &amp; Schuster, 1970&quot;&lt;/ref&gt;
*Former U.S. Middle East peace envoy Dennis Ross, who told ''[[Asharq Alawsat]]'' newspaper that the Muslim Brotherhood is a global, not a local organization, governed by a Shura (Consultative) Council, which rejects cessation of violence in Israel, and supports violence to achieve its political objectives elsewhere too.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://aawsat.com/english/news.asp?section=3&amp;id=8310|title=Lufti, Manal, &quot;The Brotherhood and America Part III,&quot; (14 March 2007) Asharq Alawsat}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*The Interior Minister of Saudi Arabia, Prince Naif Ibn Abdul Aziz has stated that the Muslim Brotherhood organization was the cause of most problems in the Arab world. 'The Brotherhood has done great damage to Saudi Arabia,' he said. Prince Naif accused the foremost Islamist group in the Arab world of harming the interests of Muslims. 'All our problems come from the Muslim Brotherhood. We have given too much support to this group...&quot; &quot;The Muslim Brotherhood has destroyed the Arab world,' he said. 'Whenever they got into difficulty or found their freedom restricted in their own countries, Brotherhood activists found refuge in the Kingdom which protected their lives... But they later turned against the Kingdom...' The Muslim Brotherhood has links to groups across the Arab world, including Jordan's main parliamentary opposition, the 'Islamic Action Front,' and the 'Palestinian resistance movement, 'Hamas.&quot; The Interior Minister's outburst against the Brotherhood came amid mounting criticism in the United States of Saudi Arabia's longstanding support for Islamist groups around the world...&quot;&lt;ref&gt;MEMRI, the Middle East Media Research Institute posted this at their website, [http://www.memri.org/bin/articles.cgi?Area=sd&amp;ID=SP44602] introducing it with the following: &quot;On November 29, 'Ain-Al-Yaqeen, a weekly news magazine published online by the Saudi royal family, released an English translation of an interview with Saudi Minister of Interior Prince Nayef Ibn Abd Al-Aziz; the interview originally appeared in the Kuwaiti newspaper Al Siyasa. The following are excerpts from the translation[1] as it appeared in the Saudi weekly.&quot;&lt;/ref&gt;

===Links to violence===
*Caryle Murphy believes that the organization has had a &quot;secret apparatus&quot; responsible for attacks in Egypt, including the assassination of [[Mahmoud an-Nukrashi Pasha]], the Egyptian Prime Minister in 1948.&lt;ref&gt;''Passion for Islam: Shaping the Modern Middle East: the Egyptian Experience'' by Caryle Murphy, p. 54.&lt;/ref&gt;
*[[Newsweek]] journalists Mark Hosenball and Michael Isikoff reported connections between [[al-Qaeda]] and Brotherhood figures [[Mamoun Darkazanli]] and [[Youssef Nada]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.pbs.org/weta/crossroads/about/show_the_brotherhood.html] &quot;Spreading fundamentalist Islam – but does the Muslim Brotherhood also support terrorism?&quot;&lt;/ref&gt;
*A similar article in the [[Financial Times]] reported financial links between 74-year-old Swiss Muslim convert, and businessman [[Ahmed Huber]], and members of the Muslim Brotherhood, notably [[Youssef Nada]], [[Ali Ghaleb Himmat]]. According to the U.S. government, Al Taqwa &quot;has long acted as financial advisers to al-Qaeda.&quot; He is reported to have &quot;confirmed&quot; having &quot;had contact with associates of Osama bin Laden at an Islamic conference in Beirut&quot;, whom he called &quot;very discreet, well-educated, very intelligent people&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;far-right&quot;&gt;[http://specials.ft.com/theresponse/FT38ZL6ZSTC.html www.ft.com] Far-right has ties with Islamic extreme. By Hugh Williamson and Philipp Jaklin. 8 November 2001&lt;/ref&gt;

===Status of non-Muslims===
*In 1997 Muslim Brotherhood Supreme Guide [[Mustafa Mashhur]] told journalist Khalid Daoud&lt;ref&gt;article printed in ''Al Ahram Weekly'' July 5–9, 1997, quoted in Passion for Islam: Shaping the Modern Middle East: the Egyptian Experience by Caryle Murphy, pp. 241, 330.&lt;/ref&gt; that he thought Egypt's Coptic Christians and Orthodox Jews should pay the long-abandoned [[jizya]] poll tax, levied on non-Muslims in exchange for protection from the state, rationalized by the fact that non-Muslims are exempt from military service while it is compulsory for Muslims. He went on to say, &quot;we do not mind having Christians members in the [[People's Assembly of Egypt|People's Assembly]]...the top officials, especially in the army, should be Muslims since we are a Muslim country...This is necessary because when a Christian country attacks the Muslim country and the army has Christian elements, they can facilitate our defeat by the enemy.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;''Passion for Islam: Shaping the Modern Middle East: the Egyptian Experience,'' by Caryle Murphy, Simon and Schuster, 2002, pp. 241, 330.&lt;/ref&gt;  According to [[The Guardian]] newspaper, the proposal caused an &quot;uproar&quot; among Egypt's six million Coptic Christians and &quot;the movement later backtracked.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.guardian.co.uk/world/2011/feb/08/egypt-muslim-brotherhood-uncovered The Muslim Brotherhood uncovered]| ack Shenker in Cairo and  Brian Whitaker| guardian.co.uk| 8 February 2011 &lt;/ref&gt;

===Response to criticism===
According to authors writing in the Council on Foreign Relations magazine Foreign Affairs:  &quot;At various times in its history, the group has used or supported violence and has been repeatedly banned in Egypt for attempting to overthrow Cairo's secular government. Since the 1970s, however, the Egyptian Brotherhood has disavowed violence and sought to participate in Egyptian politics.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;Crane&quot;&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.cfr.org/publication/9248/|title=Does the Muslim Brotherhood Have Ties to Terrorism|last=Crane|first=Mary|publisher=Council on Foreign Relations}}&lt;/ref&gt; Jeremy Bowen, [[BBC]] [[Middle East]] [[editor]], calls it &quot;conservative and non-violent&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news| url=http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/world-middle-east-12325128 | work=BBC News | title=Egypt unrest: What if Mubarak goes? | date=2011-01-31}}&lt;/ref&gt; The Brotherhood has condemned [[terrorism]] and the [[9/11 attacks]].&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.unc.edu/~kurzman/terror.htm|title=Muslim Brother Hood Condemns 9/11 attack}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.ikhwanweb.com/article.php?ID=14069&amp;LevelID=1&amp;SectionID=71|title=Morsi: 9/11 a global calamity, not only for U.S.}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The Brotherhood itself denounces the &quot;catchy and effective terms and phrases&quot; like &quot;[[fundamentalist]]&quot; and &quot;political Islam&quot; which it claims are used by &quot;Western Media&quot; to pigeonhole the group, and points to its &quot;15 Principles&quot; for an Egyptian National Charter, including &quot;freedom of personal conviction... opinion... forming political parties... public gatherings... free and fair elections...&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.ikhwanweb.com/Article.asp?ID=813&amp;LevelID=2&amp;SectionID=116|title=The Principles of The Muslim Brotherhood}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Similarly, some analysts maintain that whatever the source of modern Jihadi terrorism and the actions and words of some rogue members, the Brotherhood now has little in common with radical Islamists and modern jihadists who often condemn the Brotherhood as too moderate. They also deny the existence of any centralized and secretive global MB leadership.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.foreignaffairs.org/20070301faessay86208/robert-s-leiken-steven-brooke/the-moderate-muslim-brotherhood.html|title=The Moderate Muslim Brotherhood}}&lt;/ref&gt; Some claim that the origins of modern Muslim terrorism are found in [[Wahhabi]] ideology, not that of the Muslim Brotherhood.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.buzzle.com/editorials/4-10-2006-93214.asp|title=The root of terrorism is Wahabism}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.ataturksociety.org/letters/tarhan.html|title=The root of terrorism}}&lt;/ref&gt;

According to anthropologist [[Scott Atran]], the influence of the Muslim Brotherhood even in Egypt has been overstated by Western commentators. He estimates that it can count on only 100,000 militants (out of some 600,000 dues paying members) in a population of more than 80&amp;nbsp;million, and that such support as it does have among Egyptians—an often cited figure is 20 percent to 30 percent—is less a matter of true attachment than an accident of circumstance: secular opposition groups that might have countered it were suppressed for many decades, but in driving the [[Egyptian Revolution of 2011]], a more youthful constellation of secular movements has emerged to threaten the Muslim Brotherhood's dominance of the political opposition.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|url=http://www.nytimes.com/2011/02/03/opinion/03atran.html|title=Egypt's Bumbling Brotherhood | work=The New York Times | first=Scott|last=Atran|date=2011-02-02}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Foreign Relations==
On 29 June 2011, as the Brotherhood's political power became more apparent and solidified following the [[2011 Egyptian revolution]], the [[United States]] announced that it would reopen formal diplomatic channels with the group, with whom it had suspended communication as a result of suspected terrorist activity. The next day, the Brotherhood's leadership announced that they welcomed the diplomatic overture.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.haaretz.com/news/international/egypt-s-muslim-brotherhood-welcomes-idea-of-u-s-contacts-1.370446 Egypt's muslim brotherhood welcomes idea of U.S. contacts], on Haaretz.com&lt;/ref&gt;

==In media==
{{Main|Al-Gama'a}}

==See also==
{{Portalbox|Middle East|Islam|Politics|Egypt}}
* [[Islamism]]
* [[Pacifism in Islam]]
* [[Islamic terrorism]]
{{-}}

==Footnotes==
&lt;!--&lt;nowiki&gt;
See http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Wikipedia:Footnotes for an explanation of how to generate footnotes using the&lt;ref&gt; and &lt;/ref&gt; tags.
&lt;/nowiki&gt;--&gt;
{{Reflist|2}}

==References==
*Abdullahi, Abdurahman (Baadiyow) (October 2008) [http://www.hiiraan.com/oct2008/ISLAH.pdf &quot;The Islah Movement: Islamic moderation in war-torn Somalia&quot;] ''Hiiraan Online'' Mogadishu, Somalia
*{Ankerl, Guy}(2000) ''Coexisting Contemporary Civilizations: Arabo-Muslim, Bharati, Chinese, and Western. INUPRESS, Geneva. ISBN 2-88155-004-5
*{{Cite book|last=Baer |first=Robert| title=[[See No Evil (book)|See No Evil]]: The True Story of a Ground Soldier in the CIA's War on Terrorism| publisher=Three Rivers Press| isbn = 978-1-4000-4684-3 | year=2002}}
*{{Cite book|last=Cohen|first=Amnon|title=Political Parties in the West Bank under the Jordanian Regime, 1949–1967|publisher=Cornell University Press|year= 1982|place=Ithaca, NY|isbn=978-0-8014-1321-6}}
*Cohen, Nick (9 July 2006) [http://observer.guardian.co.uk/comment/story/0,,1816257,00.html &quot;The Foreign Office ought to be serving Britain, not radical Islam&quot;] ''The Observer'' London
*{{Cite book|last=Dreyfuss|first= Robert|title= Devil's Game: How the United States Helped Unleash Fundamentalist Islam|publisher= Owl Books |year=2006|isbn=978-0-8050-7652-3}}
*Mallmann, Klaus-Michael and Martin Cüppers (2006) ''Halbmond und Hakenkreuz: Das 'Dritte Reich', die Araber und Palästina''  Wissenschaftliche Buchgesellschaft, Darmstadt. ISBN 978-3-534-19729-3
*Mayer, Thomas (1982) &quot;The Military Force of Islam: The Society of the Muslim Brethren and the Palestine Question, 1945–1948&quot; ''In'' Kedourie, Elie and Haim, Sylvia G. (1982) ''Zionism and Arabism in Palestine and Israel'' Frank Cass, London, pp.&amp;nbsp;100–117, ISBN 0-7146-3169-8

==External links==
{{External links|date=June 2011}}
{{Wikiquote}}
*[http://www.ikhwanonline.com Ikhwan Online] ''official site'' (Arabic)
*[http://www.ikhwanweb.com Ikhwan Web] ''official site'' (English)
*[http://www.hassanalbanna.com/ Founder of the Muslim Brotherhood] (Arabic)
;Egypt
*[http://english.aljazeera.net/indepth/2011/02/201126101349142168.html Profile: Egypt's Muslim Brotherhood], ''[[Al Jazeera English]]'', February 6, 2011
*[http://www.guardian.co.uk/world/2011/feb/08/egypt-muslim-brotherhood-uncovered The Muslim Brotherhood Uncovered], Jack Shenker and [[Brian Whitaker]], ''[[The Guardian]]'', February 8, 2011
*[http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/world-middle-east-12313405 Profile: Egypt's Muslim Brotherhood], ''[[BBC News]]'', 9 February 2011
*{{cite news | title = Revolution in Cairo: Interview with Shadi Hamid | date = Feb., 2011 | publisher = [[Public Broadcasting Service|PBS]] | url = http://www.pbs.org/wgbh/pages/frontline/revolution-in-cairo/interviews/shadi-hamid.html | work = [[Frontline (U.S. TV series)|Frontline]]}}. Hamid is director of research at the [[Brookings Doha Center|Doha Center]], part of the [[Brookings Institution]].
*[http://www.iss.europa.eu/publications/detail/article/egyptian-democracy-and-the-muslim-brotherhood/ &quot;Egyptian democracy and the Muslim Brotherhood&quot;], [http://www.iss.europa.eu/home/ EU Institute for Security Studies], Report No.10
;Other branches
*[http://www.ikhwansyria.com/ The Syrian Brotherhood's page.] In Arabic.
*[http://www.ikhwanjo.com/ The Jordanian Brotherhood's official page.] In Arabic.
*[http://www.iraqiparty.org/ The Iraqi Islamic Party.] In Arabic.
*[http://www.turabi.com/ Hasan al-Turabi homepage.] In English and Arabic.
*[http://www.kurdiu.org/ Kurdish Islamic Union.] In Kurdish, English and Arabic.
*[http://www.hiiraantv.com/ Somali News World Wide.] In English.

{{2010–2011 Middle East and North Africa protests}}
{{Islamism}}
{{Egyptian political parties}}

[[Category:Islam in Egypt]]
[[Category:History of Islam]]
[[Category:Islamic political parties]]
[[Category:Islamist groups]]
[[Category:Political parties established in 1928]]
[[Category:Politics of Egypt]]
[[Category:Muslim Brotherhood| ]]
[[Category:Russian Federal Security Service designated terrorist organizations]]
[[Category:2011 Egyptian revolution]]

{{Link GA|ar}}
[[ar:الإخوان المسلمون]]
[[az:Müsəlman qardaşlar]]
[[be-x-old:Браты-мусульмане]]
[[bs:Muslimansko bratstvo]]
[[bg:Мюсюлманско братство]]
[[ca:Germans Musulmans]]
[[cs:Muslimské bratrstvo]]
[[da:Det muslimske broderskab]]
[[de:Muslimbrüder]]
[[es:Hermanos Musulmanes]]
[[eo:Islama Frataro]]
[[eu:Anaia Musulmanak]]
[[fa:اخوان‌المسلمین]]
[[fr:Frères musulmans]]
[[hr:Muslimansko bratstvo]]
[[id:Ikhwanul Muslimun]]
[[it:Fratelli musulmani]]
[[he:האחים המוסלמים]]
[[la:Fratres musulmani]]
[[lt:Musulmonų Brolija]]
[[hu:Muszlim Testvériség]]
[[ml:മുസ്‌ലിം ബ്രദർഹുഡ്]]
[[arz:الاخوان المسلمين]]
[[ms:Ikhwanul Muslimun]]
[[nl:Moslimbroederschap]]
[[ja:ムスリム同胞団]]
[[no:Det muslimske brorskapet]]
[[nn:Det muslimske brorskapet]]
[[pnb:اخوان المسلمین]]
[[ps:اخوان المسلمون]]
[[pl:Bracia Muzułmańscy]]
[[pt:Irmandade Muçulmana]]
[[ro:Frăția Musulmană]]
[[ru:Братья-мусульмане]]
[[simple:Muslim Brotherhood]]
[[sr:Муслиманска браћа]]
[[fi:Muslimiveljeskunta]]
[[sv:Muslimska brödraskapet]]
[[th:อิควานมุสลิมีน]]
[[tg:Ихвонул муслимин]]
[[tr:Müslüman Kardeşler]]
[[uk:Брати мусульмани]]
[[ur:اخوان المسلمین]]
[[wa:Frés moslimîs]]
[[yi:מוסלעם ברידערשאפט]]
[[zh-yue:穆斯林兄弟會]]
[[zh:穆斯林兄弟會]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
