<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="20754162" ns="0" title="Bill Johnston with the Australian cricket team in England in 1948"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Infobox cricketer tour biography
|          playername = Bill Johnston
|               image = BillJohnstonPic.jpg
|             country = Australia
|            fullname = William Arras Johnston
|            nickname = Big Bill
|              living = 
|          dayofbirth = 26
|        monthofbirth = 2
|         yearofbirth = 1922
|        placeofbirth = [[Beeac, Victoria]]
|      countryofbirth = Australia
|          dayofdeath = 25
|        monthofdeath = 5
|         yearofdeath = 2007
|        placeofdeath = [[Mosman, New South Wales]]
|      countryofdeath = Australia
|            heightft = 
|          heightinch = 
|             heightm = 
|             batting = Right-hand
|             bowling = [[Left-arm orthodox spin]] or [[medium pace|fast medium]] 
|                role = Specialist bowler
|       international = true
|       testdebutdate = 10 June
|       testdebutyear = 1948
|    testdebutagainst = England
|        lasttestdate = 14 August
|        lasttestyear = 1948
|     lasttestagainst = England
|             columns = 2
|             column1 = [[Test cricket|Tests]]
|            matches1 = 5
|               runs1 = 62
|            bat avg1 = 20.66
|           100s/50s1 = 0/0
|          top score1 = 29
|         deliveries1 = 1856
|            wickets1 = 27
|           bowl avg1 = 23.33
|            fivefor1 = 1
|             tenfor1 = 0
|       best bowling1 = 5/36
|  catches/stumpings1 = 2/0
|             column2 = [[First-class cricket|FC]]
|            matches2 = 21
|               runs2 = 188
|            bat avg2 = 18.80
|           100s/50s2 = 0/0
|          top score2 = 29
|         deliveries2 = 5107
|            wickets2 = 102
|           bowl avg2 = 16.42
|            fivefor2 = 6
|             tenfor2 = 2
|       best bowling2 = 6/18
|  catches/stumpings2 = 9/0
|                date = 29 February
|                year = 2008
|              source = &lt;Ref name=aus/&gt;&lt;Ref name=fc/&gt;
}}

[[Bill Johnston (cricketer)|Bill Johnston]] was a key member of [[Donald Bradman]]'s famous [[Australian cricket team in England in 1948|Australian cricket team, which toured England in 1948]]. The Australians went undefeated in their 34 matches during the English summer; this unprecedented feat by a Test side touring England earned them the sobriquet ''The Invincibles''. 

Johnston was a left-arm bowler who engaged in [[fast bowling]] when the ball was new and conducive to pacemen, before reverting to [[Left-arm orthodox spin|orthodox spin]] when the ball became old. He was Australia's third fast bowler in the Tests, reinforcing the [[cricket ball|new ball]] attack of [[Keith Miller]] and [[Ray Lindwall]], who were regarded as one of the finest pace pairings of all time. Bradman typically used Miller and Lindwall in short bursts against the English batsmen with the new ball. The hosts had agreed to make a new ball available every 55 overs, more frequently than usual. This allowed the Australian pacemen more frequent use of a shiny ball that [[swing bowling|swung]] at high pace. Johnston typically delivered pace after the Lindwall and Miller had first use of the new ball, before resorting to spin later in the innings. In order to keep Lindwall and Miller fresh, Bradman had Johnston deliver the most [[over (cricket)|overs]] by any bowler.

Johnston was the equal-leading [[wicket|wicket-taker]] in the [[Test cricket|Tests]] (27 along with Lindwall) and Australia's most prolific wicket-taker in the [[first-class cricket|first-class]] matches with 102. The latter feat made him the last Australian to take a century of wickets on an Ashes tour. In recognition of his achievements, Johnston was chosen as one of the five [[Wisden Cricketers of the Year]]. ''[[Wisden]]'' said &quot;no Australian made a greater personal contribution to the playing success of the 1948 side&quot;.&lt;Ref name=wisden/&gt;

== Background ==
During the Australian summer of 1947&amp;ndash;48, Johnston played in four of the five Tests against the touring [[Indian cricket team]]. He was a major part in Australia's 4&amp;ndash;0 series win; the second highest wicket-taker with 16 scalps, Johnston had the best [[bowling average]] of 11.37. [[Ray Lindwall]] led the wicket-takers with 18.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title= Test Bowling for Australia India in Australia 1947/48|url=http://www.cricketarchive.com/Archive/Events/AUS/India_in_Australia_1947-48/t_Australia_Bowling.html |accessdate=2008-12-22 |publisher=[[CricketArchive]]}}&lt;/ref&gt; As a result, Johnston was selected for the 1948 tour of England. During the trip, Johnston roomed with [[Doug Ring]] who was a team-mate in the [[Richmond Cricket Club|Richmond]] and Victorian cricket teams. As Ring was a [[leg spin]]ner, he and Johnston were in direct competition for a place in the [[First eleven|playing XI]].&lt;Ref name=haigh/&gt;

== Early tour ==
Australia traditionally fielded its first-choice team in the tour opener, which was customarily against [[Worcestershire County Cricket Club|Worcestershire]]. When Johnston was omitted for the opening match, it appeared he would not be in Bradman's Test plans.&lt;ref name=haigh/&gt; Australia went on to win by an innings, setting the tone for their tour.&lt;Ref name=sched/&gt;

Bradman brought Johnston into the team for the second tour match against [[Leicestershire County Cricket Club|Leicestershire]]. He made 12 runs and was the last man out as Australia ended on 448.&lt;Ref name=leics/&gt; After a lower order collapse of 5/38&lt;ref&gt;This notation means that five wickets were lost while 38 runs were scored.&lt;/ref&gt; against the local [[spin bowling|spin attack]], Johnston came in and put on 37 in [[partnership (cricket)|partnership]] with [[Keith Miller]], allowing his colleague to reach his double century.&lt;ref&gt;Fingleton, p. 50.&lt;/ref&gt; Johnston bowled six wicketless overs for 15 as the hosts fell for 130. Made to [[follow on]], Leicestershire made 147 to lose by an innings. Johnston took his first wicket of the tour, trapping [[Jack Walsh]] [[leg before wicket]] (lbw) to end with 1/42 from 27 overs.&lt;ref name=leics&gt;{{cite web
|url = http://www.cricketarchive.com/Archive/Scorecards/18/18406.html 
|title = Leicestershire v Australians
|publisher = [[CricketArchive]]
|accessdate = 2008-12-18}}&lt;/ref&gt; Johnston played a leading role in Australia's victory in the next match, against [[Yorkshire County Cricket Club|Yorkshire]], on a [[sticky wicket|damp pitch]] favourable to slower bowling.&lt;Ref name=o/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Fingleton, pp. 53&amp;ndash;55.&lt;/ref&gt; In this match, Johnston resorted to bowling [[left arm orthodox spin]]. The hosts elected to bat and he bowled almost unchanged, sending down 26 of the 54.3 overs, 14 of which were [[over (cricket)|maidens]]. He took 4/18 as Yorkshire were bowled out in difficult batting conditions for 71. His wickets included batsmen [[Alec Coxon]] and [[Willie Watson (England cricketer)|Willie Watson]], who went on to become England Test cricketers. The match remained finely balanced after Australia made 101, with Johnston [[not out|unbeaten]] on five. He was again miserly in the second innings, bowling 15.2 overs with seven maidens and taking 6/18. His victims included leading English batsman [[Len Hutton]], and Coxon and Watson for the second time as the hosts were bowled out for 89. Johnston had ended the match with 10/40. After collapsing to 6/31&amp;mdash;effectively seven wickets down as [[Sam Loxton]] was injured and unable to bat&amp;mdash;Australia scraped home by four wickets.&lt;Ref name=york&gt;{{cite web
|url = http://www.cricketarchive.com/Archive/Scorecards/18/18412.html 
|title = Yorkshire v Australians
|publisher = [[CricketArchive]]
|accessdate = 2008-12-18}}&lt;/ref&gt; It was the closest Australia would come to defeat for the whole tour.&lt;ref&gt;Fingleton, pp. 54&amp;ndash;57.&lt;/ref&gt;

The tourists travelled to London to play [[Surrey County Cricket Club|Surrey]] at [[The Oval]], and they amassed 632 after batting first. Johnston bowled without success in the first innings. In the second innings he claimed both [[List of cricket terms#O|openers]] to reduce the hosts to 2/11 after Bradman had forced them to [[follow on]]. He returned later in the innings to remove [[Alec Bedser]] and [[Jim Laker]], ending with 4/40 as Surrey were defeated by an innings.&lt;Ref name=surreyw&gt;{{Cite book
| title = [[Wisden Cricketers' Almanack]]
| edition = 1949
| publisher = [[Wisden]]
| chapter = Australians in England, 1948
| pages = 219&amp;ndash;220
}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;Ref name=surrey&gt;{{cite web
|url = http://www.cricketarchive.com/Archive/Scorecards/18/18422.html 
|title = Surrey v Australians
|publisher = [[CricketArchive]]
|accessdate = 2008-12-18}}&lt;/ref&gt; Johnston was rested for the following match against [[Cambridge University Cricket Club|Cambridge University]], which Australia won by an innings.&lt;Ref name=o/&gt;

Johnston returned as Australia crushed [[Essex County Cricket Club|Essex]] by an innings and 451 runs, their largest winning margin for the summer. After setting a world record for the most number of first-class runs in one day’s play (721),&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book
| title = [[Wisden Cricketers' Almanack]]
| edition = 1949
| publisher = [[Wisden]]
| chapter = Australians in England, 1948
| pages = 221&amp;ndash;222
}}&lt;/ref&gt; of which Johnston contributed nine, Bradman’s men bowled Essex out for 83 and 187 after enforcing the follow on. Johnston managed a match total of only 1/36. This was followed by another innings victory, this time over [[Oxford University Cricket Club|Oxford University]]. After scoring 13 in Australia's 431, Johnston bowled the most overs by an Australian in the match, taking 2/40 and 2/44 across a total of 42 overs.&lt;ref name=ox&gt;{{cite web
|url = http://www.cricketarchive.com/Archive/Scorecards/18/18444.html 
|title = Oxford University v Australians
|publisher = [[CricketArchive]]
|accessdate = 2008-12-18}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Johnston was the left out for the next fixture, which was against the [[Marylebone Cricket Club]] (MCC) at [[Lord's]]. The MCC fielded seven players who would represent England in the Tests,&lt;ref name=sco1/&gt;&lt;ref name=sco2/&gt;&lt;Ref name=sco3/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;sco4&quot;&gt;{{cite web| title = 4th Test England v Australia at Leeds Jul 22-27 1948|url=http://www.cricinfo.com/ci/engine/match/62688.html|publisher= [[Cricinfo]]|accessdate=2007-12-12}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=sco5&gt;{{cite web| title = 5th Test England v Australia at The Oval Aug 14&amp;ndash;18 1948|url=http://www.cricinfo.com/ci/engine/match/62689.html|publisher= [[Cricinfo]]|accessdate=2007-12-12}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;Ref name=mcc/&gt; and were basically a full strength Test team, while Australia fielded their first-choice team, with Johnston omitted. It was a chance for the Australian bowlers to gain a psychological advantage, with [[Len Hutton]], [[Denis Compton]] and [[Bill Edrich]]&amp;mdash;three of England's first four batsmen&amp;mdash;all playing. Australia won by an innings to give an indication of their strength.&lt;Ref name=mcc&gt;{{cite web
|url = http://www.cricketarchive.com/Archive/Scorecards/18/18451.html 
|title = MCC v Australians
|publisher = [[CricketArchive]]
|accessdate = 2008-12-18}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Four county matches remained before the Tests, givng the players more chances to press their claims for selection.&lt;Ref name=sched/&gt; Johnston was recalled for Australia'a first non-victory of the tour, which was against [[Lancashire County Cricket Club|Lancashire]]. After the first day was washed out, Johnston made 24 in a 25-run ninth-wicket partnership with wicket-keeper [[Ron Saggers]], which took Australia from 8/170 to 9/195. The tourists were eventually bowled out for 204.&lt;Ref name=lancs/&gt; During his innings, Johnston swung lustily and hit three [[six (cricket)|sixes]].&lt;ref&gt;Fingleton, p. 76.&lt;/ref&gt; In reply, Lancashire reached 4/144 before Johnston took five of the last six wickets to help dismiss the home side for 182, securing a slender lead for the tourists. Johnston ended with 5/49 from 29 overs, the most by any of the Australians, and was not required to bat in the second innings.&lt;ref name=lancs&gt;{{cite web
|url = http://www.cricketarchive.com/Archive/Scorecards/18/18458.html 
|title = Lancashire v Australians
|publisher = [[CricketArchive]]
|accessdate = 2008-12-18}}&lt;/ref&gt; 

Johnston was rested for the subsequent match against [[Nottinghamshire County Cricket Club|Nottinghamshire]] at [[Trent Bridge]], which was drawn.&lt;Ref name=sched/&gt;&lt;Ref name=o/&gt; He returned against [[Hampshire County Cricket Club|Hampshire]] and played a major role in Australia's eight-wicket win.&lt;Ref name=sched/&gt;&lt;Ref name=o/&gt; The home team were put into bat on a drying pitch by vice-captain [[Lindsay Hassett]]&amp;mdash;Bradman had rested himself for the match. Johnston bowled for almost the whole innings, sending down 38.4 of 85.4 overs. He took wickets at regular intervals to end with 6/74 as Hampshire were bowled out for 195.&lt;Ref name=hants/&gt;&lt;Ref name=hantsw&gt;{{Cite book
| title = [[Wisden Cricketers' Almanack]]
| edition = 1949
| publisher = [[Wisden]]
| chapter = Australians in England, 1948
| pages = 226&amp;ndash;227
}}&lt;/ref&gt; Johnston was unbeaten on two as Australia lost 8/47 and collapsed to 117 all out, trailing by 78 runs. It was the first time tha the tourists had conceded a first innings lead for the season.&lt;Ref name=o/&gt;&lt;ref name=hantsw/&gt; In the second innings, Johnston bowled unchanged at his end for the entire innings, providing steady breakthroughs to end with 5/43 as Hampshire were bowled out for 103. This left Australia a target of 182, and they batted fluently in their second innings to win by eight wickets. Johnston ended with match figures of 11/117.&lt;Ref name=hants&gt;{{cite web
|url = http://www.cricketarchive.com/Archive/Scorecards/18/18473.html 
|title = Hampshire v Australians
|publisher = [[CricketArchive]]
|accessdate = 2008-12-18}}&lt;/ref&gt; He was rested in the innings win over [[Sussex County Cricket Club|Sussex]], in the last fixture before the First Test.&lt;Ref name=sched&gt;{{cite web|title=Matches, Australia tour of England, Apr-Sep 1948 |url=http://www.cricinfo.com/invincibles/engine/series/61329.html |publisher=[[Cricinfo]] |accessdate=2008-07-16}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;Ref name=o&gt;{{cite web|url = http://www.cricketarchive.com/cgi-bin/player_oracle_reveals_results2.cgi?playernumber=794&amp;opponentmatch=exact&amp;playername=John&amp;resulttype=All&amp;matchtype=All&amp;teammatch=exact&amp;startwicket=&amp;homeawaytype=All&amp;opponent=&amp;endwicket=&amp;wicketkeeper=&amp;searchtype=InningsList&amp;endscore=&amp;playermatch=contains&amp;branding=cricketarchive&amp;captain=&amp;endseason=1948&amp;startscore=&amp;team=&amp;startseason=1948
|title = Player Oracle WA Johnston 1948
|publisher = [[CricketArchive]]
|accessdate = 2008-12-18}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== First Test ==
{{main|First Test, 1948 Ashes series}}
Johnston was not in Bradman's planned Test team. However, the Australian skipper changed his mind on the morning of the First Test in [[Trent Bridge]] when rain was forecast. Johnston was played in the hope of exploiting a [[sticky wicket|wet wicket]].&lt;ref name=&quot;haigh&quot;&gt;{{cite news| title=Gentrifying the game| first=Gideon | last=Haigh| authorlink=Gideon Haigh| url=http://www.cricinfo.com/ci/content/story/295893.html |publisher=[[Cricinfo]] |date=2007-05-26| accessdate=2007-06-01}}&lt;/ref&gt; Johnston had taken 10/40 against Yorkshire and 11/117 against Hampshire on similar surfaces.&lt;Ref name=o/&gt;&lt;Ref name=hantsw/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Fingleton, p. 54.&lt;/ref&gt; He showed his credentials by taking a match total of 9/183 from 84 overs to help Australia to grind out a victory by eight wickets.&lt;ref name=&quot;cobit&quot;&gt;{{cite news| title= 'Invincible' bowler Johnston dies at 85 |url=http://www.cricinfo.com/ci/content/story/295739.html |date=2007-05-25| accessdate=2007-06-01| publisher=[[Cricinfo]]}}&lt;/ref&gt; England elected to bat first and after strike bowler [[Ray Lindwall]] broke down on the first day, the burden on Johnston grew.&lt;Ref name=report1/&gt;

England had reached 2/46 when Johnston was brought into the attack for his first over. He bowled [[Bill Edrich]], knocking out the [[stump (cricket)|off stump]] while the batsman was on the front foot. Two balls later, Johnston removed [[Joe Hardstaff junior]] without scoring, caught by Miller [[Fielding (cricket)#Fielding position names and locations|in slips]] after attempting a [[Batting (cricket)#Cut|cut shot]]; the catch was described by ''[[Wisden]]'' as &quot;dazzling&quot;.&lt;Ref name=&quot;sco1&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;report1&quot;/&gt; Miller dived and balanced himself on his spine before catching the ball to leave England at 4/46.&lt;ref name=f86&gt;Fingleton, p. 86.&lt;/ref&gt; Journalist and former Australian Test leg spinner [[Bill O'Reilly (cricketer)|Bill O'Reilly]] said: &quot;Johnston had trimmed and embroidered the efforts of his opening bowlers and had swung the fortunes of the game completely in Australia's favour&quot;.&lt;Ref name=o34&gt;O'Reilly, p. 34.&lt;/ref&gt;

Johnston then knocked over [[Charlie Barnett (cricketer)|Charlie Barnett]]'s stumps as the batsman leaned onto the front foot and inside edged the ball into his stumps for eight;&lt;Ref name=f87/&gt;&lt;ref name=o35&gt;O’Reilly, p. 35.&lt;/ref&gt; this brought [[Godfrey Evans]]&amp;mdash;who was given two lives&amp;mdash;to the crease at 6/60. Evans hit Johnston hard in the air to cover, where the ball went through Bradman for a [[boundary (cricket)|boundary]]. The second catching opportunity went in the same direction before traveling through Bradman's hand and striking him in the abdomen. However, Johnston eventually snared Evans, who hit a ball strongly, but straight to [[Fielding (cricket)#Fielding position names and locations|short leg]] where [[Arthur Morris]] took the catch close in,&lt;Ref name=f87&gt;Fingleton, p. 87.&lt;/ref&gt; as England reached 8/74.&lt;ref name=sco1/&gt; 

However, a rearguard action took England to a total of 165, before Johnston removed [[Alec Bedser]] to end the innings.&lt;ref name=&quot;sco1&quot;/&gt; Johnston finished with 5/36, in a display characterised by his accuracy and variations in pace and swing.&lt;ref name=&quot;sco1&quot;&gt;{{cite web| title = 1st Test England v Australia at Nottingham Jun 10&amp;ndash;15 1948|url=http://www.cricinfo.com/ci/engine/match/62685.html|publisher= [[Cricinfo]]|accessdate=2007-12-12}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;report1&quot;&gt;{{Cite web|title= First Test Match England v Australia |work= [[Wisden Cricketers' Almanack]] |year=1949  |url=http://www.cricinfo.com/wisdenalmanack/content/story/152894.html |accessdate=2008-07-02 |publisher=[[Wisden]]}}&lt;/ref&gt; When Australia batted, Johnston and [[Ernie Toshack]] wagged a last-wicket partnership of 33 runs in only 18 minutes. They played in a free-wheeling manner before Bedser trapped Toshack lbw to end the home team’s innings on 509, leaving the tourists with a 344-run lead and Johnston unbeaten on 17.&lt;Ref name=&quot;sco1&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Arlott, pp. 40&amp;ndash;41.&lt;/ref&gt;

Johnston took the new ball with Miller and delivered 59 overs in the second innings to take 4/147 in Lindwall's absence.&lt;ref name=sco1/&gt; Johnston bowled without success in the first half of the innings;&lt;ref name=sco2/&gt; the closest he came to a wicket on the third afternoon when [[Len Hutton]] and [[Denis Compton]] were putting on a century partnership was when Compton aimed an uppish square drive from Johnston that flew in the air wide of cover point.&lt;Ref name=a41&gt;Arlott, p. 41.&lt;/ref&gt; On the fourth day, England continued to make steady progress and Johnston was unsuccessful although he was able to make the ball move sideways in the morning under cloudy conditions.&lt;Ref name=a45&gt;Arlott, p. 45.&lt;/ref&gt; He was then attacked by Hardstaff, who drove several fours through the off side and forced Bradman to removed Johnston. He returned to remove Barnett and English captain [[Norman Yardley]] late on the fourth day as the hosts’ neared 300.&lt;ref name=sco1/&gt; Barnett was caught by Miller in the slips and Johnston took a return catch to remove the English skipper.&lt;ref name=sco1/&gt; Johnston bowled 30 overs, the most of any bowler for the day, as England reached the penultimate evening on 345/6, a lead of one run.&lt;ref&gt;Arlott, pp. 44, 47.&lt;/ref&gt; The next morning, Johnston removed Evans and bowled [[Jack Young (cricketer)|Jack Young]] to end England's innings at 441 on the final day. Johnston bowled the most overs of any player and was the leading wicket-taker for the match as Australia took a 1&amp;ndash;0 lead&lt;ref name=&quot;sco1&quot;/&gt;&lt;Ref name=report1/&gt;&amp;mdash;the Australian batsmen reached the target of 98 with eight wickets in hand.&lt;Ref name=o/&gt; 

After the First Test, Johnston was the leading wicket-taker as Australia completed an innings victory over [[Northamptonshire County Cricket Club|Northamptonshire]]. He took 3/25 in the first innings, before dismissing the home side's top four batsmen in the second innings to reduce them to 4/108; they were eventually bowled out for 169. Johnston ended with 4/49.&lt;Ref name=northants&gt;{{cite web
|url = http://www.cricketarchive.com/Archive/Scorecards/18/18514.html 
|title = Northamptonshire v Australians
|publisher = [[CricketArchive]]
|accessdate = 2008-12-18}}&lt;/ref&gt; This was followed by a drawn match against Yorkshire, in which Johnston scored an unbeaten 15, before bowling almost unchanged in the home side's first innings. Johnston bowled 41.1 out of 90.1 overs and ended with 3/101, including the wickets of Test players [[Alec Coxon]] and Watson. The match ended in a draw.&lt;Ref name=o/&gt;&lt;Ref name=york2&gt;{{cite web
|url = http://www.cricketarchive.com/Archive/Scorecards/18/18526.html 
|title = Yorkshire v Australians
|publisher = [[CricketArchive]]
|accessdate = 2008-12-18}}&lt;/ref&gt; Johnston bowled three overs for 15 in the second innings; Bradman chose not to push for a win and declared late in the second innings so that his bowlers would not have to exert themselves to any significant extent before the next Test.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book
| title = [[Wisden Cricketers' Almanack]]
| edition = 1949
| publisher = [[Wisden]]
| chapter = Australians in England, 1948
| pages = 233&amp;ndash;234
}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Second Test ==
{{main|Second Test, 1948 Ashes series}}
In the Second Test at [[Lord's]], Australia batted first and Johnston scored his Test career best of 29 in another tail-wagging performance in the first innings. After coming to the crease with the score at 8/275 on the second morning, Johnston added 45 runs with wicket-keeper [[Don Tallon]] before the latter fell to Bedser. He was joined by last man Toshack and they put on 30 before Johnston was stumped&amp;mdash;having overbalanced while leaning onto the front foot and trying to hit a ball for [[six (cricket)|six]]&amp;mdash;from the bowling of [[Doug Wright (cricketer)|Doug Wright]] to end Australia's innings at 350.&lt;Ref name=sco2/&gt;&lt;ref name=o68&gt;O'Reilly, p. 68.&lt;/ref&gt; Both Johnston and Toshack threw the bat at the ball, which often went in vastly different directions compared to where they had aimed their shots.&lt;Ref name=f110/&gt; Both men&amp;mdash;not known for their batting ability&amp;mdash;played without inhibitions, joyfully revelling in their luck.&lt;ref name=a61&gt;Arlott, p. 61.&lt;/ref&gt; One sequence of two overs from Edrich was taken for 28 runs, with many balls being unintentionally spooned over the slips or the covers.&lt;ref name=f110&gt;Fingleton, p. 110.&lt;/ref&gt;

With [[Keith Miller]] injured and playing purely as a batsman,&lt;ref&gt;Perry, p. 239.&lt;/ref&gt; Johnston took the new ball, sharing it with Lindwall. He was unable to take a wicket initially, but the English openers were uncomfortable when he and Lindwall were taking the new ball.&lt;ref name=sco2/&gt;&lt;ref name=o69&gt;O'Reilly, p. 69.&lt;/ref&gt; Following the tea break,&lt;ref name=o71&gt;O'Reilly, p. 71.&lt;/ref&gt; he returned with the second new ball after Compton and Yardley had put on an 87-run partnership to stabilise the middle-order. Johnston took Compton's outside edge and Miller completed the catch in slips. The left armer then claimed Evans, caught by a diving Miller after the Englishman had taken a swing of the bat wide outside off stump; this left the hosts at 7/145.&lt;ref name=sco2/&gt;&lt;ref name=f112&gt;Fingleton, p. 112.&lt;/ref&gt; Johnston ended with 2/43 from 22 overs as England were bowled for at 215 early on the third morning.&lt;ref name=sco2/&gt;&lt;Ref name=report2/&gt; After Australia declared at 7/460 on the fourth afternoon to leave the home side a target of 596, Johnston troubled the English openers with the new ball, but did not take a wicket.

Lindwall and Johnston extracted steep bounce with the new ball, troubling the English batsmen.&lt;ref name=report2/&gt; Fielding in the slips, Lindwall dropped Hutton from Johnston's bowling before the English batsman had scored.&lt;ref name=&quot;report2&quot;/&gt; Johnston usually moved the ball into the right-handed batsmen, but on this occasion the ball went straight on and took the outside of the edge of Hutton's bat.&lt;ref name=o77&gt;O'Reilly, p. 77.&lt;/ref&gt; Hutton had trouble with both Australian pacemen, and played and missed multiple times in the deteriorating light.&lt;ref name=f121&gt;Fingleton, p. 121.&lt;/ref&gt; In a fidgety display, he played loosely outside the off stump and missed four times in one Johnston over,&lt;ref name=o77/&gt; before Lindwall dismissed him.&lt;ref name=sco2/&gt; 

Yardley’s men resumed at 3/106 on the final day.&lt;Ref name=sco2/&gt; On the second ball of the final morning, bowled by Johnston, Compton aimed a square drive, but the delivery was Johnston's variation ball, which went away instead of into the batsman.&lt;ref name=o74&gt;O'Reilly, p. 74.&lt;/ref&gt; The ball flew off the outside edge to a diving Miller, who knocked the ball up before falling on his back and completing the catch as the ball came down.&lt;ref name=f122&gt;Fingleton, p. 122.&lt;/ref&gt; Compton stood his ground and waited for the umpire to confirm whether Miller had caught the ball cleanly, and was duly given out by the unhesitating official.&lt;ref name=o79&gt;O'Reilly, p. 79.&lt;/ref&gt; O'Reilly described Miller's effort as &quot;perhaps the very best slips catch of the whole series and&amp;nbsp;...&amp;nbsp;a real match-winner.&quot;&lt;ref name=o79/&gt; Johnston then removed Bedser for nine to end with 2/62 as Australia won by 409 runs and took a 2&amp;ndash;0 series lead.&lt;ref name=&quot;sco2&quot;&gt;{{cite web| title = 2nd Test England v Australia at Lord's Jun 24&amp;ndash;29 1948|url=http://www.cricinfo.com/ci/engine/match/62686.html|publisher= [[Cricinfo]]|accessdate=2007-12-12}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;Ref name=report2&gt;{{Cite web|title= Second Test Match England v Australia |work= [[Wisden Cricketers' Almanack]] |year=1949  |url=http://www.cricinfo.com/wisdenalmanack/content/story/152895.html |publisher=[[Wisden]] |accessdate=2008-07-02}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;testlist&quot;/&gt;

After 16 days of cricket in 20 days, from the First to the Second Test, Johnston was rested from the next two matches against [[Surrey County Cricket Club|Surrey]] and [[Gloucestershire County Cricket Club|Gloucestershire]], which Australia won by ten wickets and an innings respectively.&lt;Ref name=sched/&gt;&lt;Ref name=o/&gt;

== Third Test ==
{{main|Third Test, 1948 Ashes series}}
Johnston returned for the Third Test at [[Old Trafford (cricket ground)|Old Trafford]], where the home team elected to bat first. In an effective containing performance, Johnston took 3/67 from 45.5 overs in the first innings.&lt;Ref name=sco3/&gt; England had looked assured in the first hour,&lt;ref name=a80&gt;Arlott, p. 80.&lt;/ref&gt; before Johnston&amp;mdash;again taking the new ball with Lindwall&lt;ref name=o87&gt;O'Reilly, p. 87.&lt;/ref&gt;&amp;mdash;bowled [[Cyril Washbrook]] with a [[yorker]] to leave England at 1/22.&lt;Ref name=sco3/&gt;&lt;ref name=o87/&gt; Johnston had been bowling from over the wicket, and his left-arm deliveries had generally been swinging back into the right-handed Washbrook. However, the opening batsman did not detect Johnston’s variation ball, which was released from wide of the crease and angled across more sharply without curling back in.&lt;Ref name=o87/&gt; Washbrook played inside the line of the ball, which hit his stumps.&lt;ref name=o87/&gt; Australia nearly had two wickets in the same over as the new batsman Edrich struggled. He played loosely outside the off stump to the first ball from Johnston but did not get an edge, and on the third delivery, Edrich survived again. Receiving a ball on middle and leg stump, he tried to defend it straight back down the pitch, rather than the conventional stroke to the leg side, and managed to edge the ball past the slips for four.&lt;Ref name=o88&gt;O'Reilly, p. 88.&lt;/ref&gt; Johnston repeatedly hurried Edrich with his pace, forcing the batsman to make many last-moment movements to either hit the ball or withdraw from a shot during the formative stage of his innings.&lt;Ref name=f131&gt;Fingleton, p. 131.&lt;/ref&gt; 

Johnston returned with the second new ball after lunch to remove [[Tom Dollery]] with another yorker, leaving England at 4/97.&lt;ref name=report3/&gt; This dismissal mirrored that of Washbrook’s in that Dollery failed to detect Johnston’s variation ball, and thus played for swing when there was none.&lt;ref name=o92&gt;O'Reilly, p. 92.&lt;/ref&gt; Late in the day, Johnston took the catch as Lindwall removed Evans, who had taken a wild slash to leave England at 7/216.&lt;Ref name=&quot;sco3&quot;/&gt;&lt;Ref name=&quot;report3&quot;/&gt; In the final minutes of play, Johnston extracted an [[List of cricket terms#E|edge]] from Compton on 64, but Tallon dropped the catch.&lt;ref&gt;Fingleton, pp. 133&amp;ndash;134.&lt;/ref&gt; On the second morning, Tallon dropped Compton&amp;mdash;then on 73&amp;mdash;for the third time, off the bowling of Johnston,&lt;ref name=f134&gt;Fingleton, p. 134.&lt;/ref&gt; who eventually ended the England innings on 363 by removing Young. Compton had added a further 81 after being dropped from Johnston's bowling to end unbeaten on 145. Johnston had bowled the most overs of the Australians and been the most [[economy rate|economical]].&lt;ref name=sco3/&gt;

In reply, Australia were in trouble at 7/208 when Johnston came to the crease to join Lindwall, with five more runs needed to avoid the follow on. As [[Sid Barnes]] was unable to bat due to injury, Australia were effectively eight wickets down.&lt;ref name=sco3/&gt; Johnston helped Lindwall advance Australia beyond the follow-on before Bedser removed both.&lt;Ref name=sco3/&gt; Johnston was reprieved in his brief innings when he edged a delivery from [[Dick Pollard]] in the direction of Edrich at first slip, but Evans dived across, trying to catch the ball at full stretch in his right hand. The wicket-keeper could not hold onto the ball, and the resulting deflection further to the right wrong-footed Edrich, who was moving the other way, and it went past him. From second slip, [[Jack Crapp]] dived left behind Edrich but the ball landed a few centimetres beyond his fingers.&lt;ref name=a91/&gt; However, in the next over Bedser, Johnston edged the ball in the same manner and Crapp caught the ball easily.&lt;Ref name=a91&gt;Arlott, p. 91.&lt;/ref&gt; Johnston was out for three as Australia ended with 221 to narrowly avoid the follow on by eight runs.&lt;ref name=sco3/&gt; He was wicketless in the second innings, taking 0/34 as England declared at 3/174 and set Australia 317 for victory on the last day after the fourth day was completely washed out by rain. The match ended in a draw with Australia at 1/92, after many rain interruptions.&lt;ref name=&quot;sco3&quot;&gt;{{cite web| title = 3rd Test England v Australia at Manchester Jul 8&amp;ndash;13 1948|url=http://www.cricinfo.com/ci/engine/match/62687.html|publisher= [[Cricinfo]]|accessdate=2007-12-12}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;report3&quot;&gt;{{Cite web|title= Third Test Match England v Australia |work= [[Wisden Cricketers' Almanack]] |year=1949  |url=http://www.cricinfo.com/wisdenalmanack/content/story/152896.html |accessdate=2008-07-02 |publisher=[[Wisden]]}}&lt;/ref&gt; 

Johnston played in Australia's only match before the Fourth Test, which was against [[Middlesex County Cricket Club|Middlesex]]. He dismissed [[Jack Robertson]], Edrich and [[John Dewes]] to leave the hosts at 4/92 and ended with 3/43 as they were bowled out for 203. In the second innings, he took two early wicket&amp;mdash;including Compton&amp;mdash;to reduce the hosts to 3/27 before ending with 2/28 as Australia bowled Middlesex out for 135. Bradman’s men went on to win by ten wickets.&lt;ref name=sched/&gt;&lt;Ref name=o/&gt;&lt;Ref name=middle&gt;{{cite web
|url = http://www.cricketarchive.com/Archive/Scorecards/18/18593.html 
|title = Middlesex v Australians
|publisher = [[CricketArchive]]
|accessdate = 2008-12-18}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Fourth Test ==
{{main|Fourth Test, 1948 Ashes series}}
In the Fourth Test at [[Headingley Stadium#Headingley Carnegie Cricket Ground|Headingley]], England batted first on a [[cricket pitch|pitch]] regarded as being ideal for strokeplay, and Australia's bowlers had little success on the first day.&lt;Ref name=report4/&gt; Early in the day, Johnston appeared to be having back problems. He had bowled the most overs of any bowler on the tour and his loss would have meant a heavy workload for his remaining colleagues.&lt;ref name=o112&gt;O’Reilly, p. 112.&lt;/ref&gt; His apparent discomfort led onlookers to opine that he should have been given more rest in the county matches.&lt;ref name=o112/&gt; After an opening partnership of 143, England consolidated to reach 1/268 in the last over of the day before Johnston removed Washbrook for 143.&lt;Ref name=sco4/&gt;&lt;Ref name=report4/&gt; Johnston did not taste further success in the first innings and ended with 1/86 from 38 overs as the home team ended on 496, their highest score of the series.&lt;Ref name=sco1/&gt;&lt;Ref name=sco2/&gt;&lt;Ref name=sco3/&gt;&lt;Ref name=sco4/&gt;&lt;Ref name=sco5/&gt;

In reply, Australia were still more than 100 runs behind when Johnston joined Lindwall with the score at 8/355, late on the third day.&lt;Ref name=sco4/&gt; Lindwall hit out, scoring 77 in an innings marked by powerful [[batting (cricket)#Types of batting shots|driving and pulling]],&lt;ref name=&quot;pol14&quot;&gt;Pollard, p. 14.&lt;/ref&gt; dominating the [[partnership (cricket)|stand]] of 48 with Johnston, who made only 13.&lt;ref name=&quot;sco4&quot;/&gt; Johnston accompanied Lindwall for 80 minutes, before the injured [[Ernie Toshack]] survived the last 50 minutes until [[List of cricket terms#S|stumps]], with Johnston [[runner (cricket)|running]] for him. Despite Toshack and Johnston’s lack of familiarity with having and acting as a runner respectively, and the resulting disorders in running between the wickets, Lindwall was able to manipulate the strike so he faced most of the balls.&lt;ref name=o131&gt;O’Reilly, p. 131.&lt;/ref&gt; Johnston able to survive against the English pacemen with relative ease when he was batting, leading O’Reilly to lament the absence of leg spinner [[Doug Wright (cricketer)|Doug Wright]], whose guile and flight was held in high regard by the Australians.&lt;ref name=o129&gt;O’Reilly, p. 129.&lt;/ref&gt; Lindwall was the last man out on the fourth morning with the total on 458, leaving Australia 38 runs in arrears on the first innings.&lt;ref name=&quot;sco4&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=f167&gt;Fingleton, p. 167.&lt;/ref&gt;

Australia lost the services of Toshack after he broke down with a knee injury in the first innings,&lt;ref&gt;Cashman et al., pp. 299&amp;ndash;300.&lt;/ref&gt; increasing the burden on the remaining bowlers as England sought to extend their lead on the fourth day. For the second time in the match, Washbrook and Hutton put on a century opening partnership.&lt;ref name=sco4/&gt; After reaching 50, Washbrook [[Batting (cricket)#Pull and hook|hooked]] a short ball from Johnston and top edged it, but Bradman failed to take the catch.&lt;Ref name=f170&gt;Fingleton, p. 170.&lt;/ref&gt; However, Washbrook soon repeated the shot from the bowling of Johnston with fatal results. The ball again went in the air, and [[Neil Harvey]] quickly ran across the ground and bent over to catch it at feet height while on the run, removing the opener for 65. Fingleton said that Harvey’s effort &quot;was the catch of the season&amp;mdash;or, indeed, would have been had Harvey not turned on several magnificent aerial performances down at [[The Oval]] [in the match against Surrey]&quot;.&lt;ref name=f170/&gt; O’Reilly doubted &quot;whether any other player on either side could have made the distance to get to the ball, let alone make a neat catch of it&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;O’Reilly, pp. 133&amp;ndash;134.&lt;/ref&gt; He further said the &quot;hook was a beauty and the catch was a classic&quot;.&lt;ref name=o134&gt;O'Reilly, p. 134.&lt;/ref&gt; 

England moved to 4/277 when a mini-collapse occurred. Yardley made seven before he was removed by Johnston, caught by a leaping Harvey while attempting a big shot.&lt;Ref name=f172&gt;Fingleton, p. 172.&lt;/ref&gt; Johnston then removed [[Ken Cranston]], caught behind for a [[duck (cricket)|duck]] to leave England at 6/278. When Johnston removed Compton for 66, caught by Miller at cover, the hosts were 7/293 with no recognised batsmen remaining, having lost 4/33.&lt;ref name=&quot;sco4&quot;/&gt; England recovered to reach 8/362 at the close of the fourth day.&lt;ref name=&quot;sco4&quot;/&gt;&lt;Ref name=&quot;report4&quot;&gt;{{Cite web|title= Fourth Test Match England v Australia |work= [[Wisden Cricketers' Almanack]] |year=1949  |url=http://www.cricinfo.com/wisdenalmanack/content/story/152897.html |accessdate=2008-07-02 |publisher=[[Wisden]]}}&lt;/ref&gt; The next day, Yardley [[Declaration and forfeiture|declared]] at 8/365,&lt;ref name=&quot;sco4&quot;/&gt;&lt;Ref name=&quot;report4&quot;/&gt; leaving Johnston with the pick of the bowling figures, 4/95 from 29 overs.&lt;Ref name=&quot;sco4&quot;/&gt; This left the tourists a target of 404 from 345 minutes. Australia went on to break the world record Test run-chase record by scoring 3/404 to take a 3&amp;ndash;0 lead with 15 minutes to spare.&lt;Ref name=report4/&gt;

Johnston went on to play in the match against [[Derbyshire County Cricket Club|Derbyshire]] immediately after the Headingley Test, taking 3/41 and 1/35 as Australia enforced the [[follow on]] and won by an innings.&lt;Ref name=sched/&gt;&lt;ref name=o/&gt; He was rested for the next game against [[Glamorgan County Cricket Club|Glamorgan]], which ended in a rain-affected draw without reaching the second innings.&lt;ref name=sched/&gt; Johnston returned and took 2/41 in the first innings against [[Warwickshire County Cricket Club|Warwickshire]], before taking 4/32 in the second innings, including three of the last five wickets, as the hosts fell from 5/118 to 155 all out. The left armer bowled almost unchanged during the second innings, sending down 39 of the 85.5 overs, including 16 maidens. His wickets included [[New Zealand cricket team |New Zealand]] Test batsman [[Martin Donnelly (cricketer)|Martin Donnelly]] and [[India national cricket team|Indian]] and [[Pakistan national cricket team|Pakistani]] dual international [[Abdul Hafeez Kardar]], as Australia went on to win by nine wickets.&lt;Ref name=warwick&gt;{{cite web
|url = http://www.cricketarchive.com/Archive/Scorecards/18/18634.html 
|title = Warwickshire v Australians
|publisher = [[CricketArchive]]
|accessdate = 2008-12-18}}&lt;/ref&gt; Johnston was then rested from two consecutive matches, against Lancashire and [[Durham County Cricket Club|Durham]], both of which were rain-affected draws.&lt;Ref name=sched/&gt;&lt;Ref name=o/&gt;&lt;Ref name=lancs2&gt;{{cite web
|url = http://www.cricketarchive.com/Archive/Scorecards/18/18639.html 
|title = Lancashire v Australians
|publisher = [[CricketArchive]]
|accessdate = 2008-12-18}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;Ref name=durham&gt;{{cite web
|url = http://www.cricketarchive.com/Archive/Scorecards/18/18654.html 
|title = Durham v Australians
|publisher = [[CricketArchive]]
|accessdate = 2008-12-18}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Fifth Test ==
{{main|Fifth Test, 1948 Ashes series}}

Johnston rounded off his Ashes series with the Fifth Test at [[The Oval]]. English skipper [[Norman Yardley]] elected to bat on a rain-affected pitch, a decision many regarded as surprising. Precipitation in the past week rendered play before midday impossible.&lt;ref name=&quot;f183&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;report5&quot;/&gt; Former Australian Test batsman and leading commentator [[Jack Fingleton]] speculated that the tourists would have bowled if they had won the toss.&lt;Ref name=&quot;f183&quot;&gt;Fingleton, p. 183.&lt;/ref&gt;

The damp conditions meant required a large amount of sawdust to be laid down to help the players keep their grip. Along with the rain, the humid conditions assisted the Australian bowlers, who were able to make the ball bounce at variable heights.&lt;Ref name=&quot;report5&quot;&gt;{{Cite web|title= Fifth Test Match England v Australia |work= [[Wisden Cricketers' Almanack]] |year=1949  |url=http://www.cricinfo.com/wisdenalmanack/content/story/152898.html |accessdate=2008-07-02 |publisher=[[Wisden]]}}&lt;/ref&gt;

After Miller removed [[John Dewes]] with the score at 1/2, Bradman made an early bowling change and introduced Johnston. Edrich joined Hutton and they played cautiously until the former attempted to [[Batting (cricket)#Pull and hook|hook]] a [[bouncer (cricket)|short ball]] from Johnston. He failed to get the ball in the middle of the bat and it looped up and travelled around {{convert|10|m}}. [[Lindsay Hassett]] caught the ball just behind [[Fielding (cricket)#Fielding position names and locations|square leg]], after diving sideways and getting both hands to the ball.&lt;Ref name=&quot;f184&quot;&gt;Fingleton, p. 184.&lt;/ref&gt; This left England at 2/10.&lt;Ref name=&quot;sco5&quot;/&gt; After  the [[List of cricket terms#L|lunch break]], Johnston dismissed debutant [[Allan Watkins]] without scoring after the batsman played across the line to be trapped lbw, leaving England at 6/42.&lt;ref name=&quot;sco5&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;f186&quot;&gt;Fingleton, p. 186.&lt;/ref&gt; Johnston ended with 2/20 from 16 overs as England were skittled for 52. After being unbeaten without scoring in Australia's innings of 389, Johnston was again among the wickets when England's second innings late on the second day.&lt;Ref name=sco5/&gt;

England started their second innings with a deficit of 337 runs and reached 1/54 by the premature end of the second day due to [[List of cricket terms#L|bad light]].&lt;Ref name=&quot;sco5&quot;/&gt; The following morning, they made slow and steady progress as Johnston bowled his finger spin from around the wicket with a well-protected off side.&lt;Ref name=o154&gt;O'Reilly, p. 154.&lt;/ref&gt; The four men in the off side ring had much work to do as Hutton hit the ball there repeatedly.&lt;ref name=a134&gt;Arlott, p. 134.&lt;/ref&gt; The English batsmen progressed and Johnston had one confident appeal for lbw against Compton¸ but there were few scares.&lt;Ref name=o155&gt;O'Reilly, p. 155.&lt;/ref&gt;

They reached 2/125 after lunch, when Compton&amp;mdash;who was on 39&amp;mdash;aimed a hard [[Batting (cricket)#Cut|cut shot]] from Johnston's bowling, which flew off the edge into Lindwall's left hand at [[Fielding (cricket)#Fielding position names and locations|second slip]] for a &quot;freak slip catch&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;sco5&quot;/&gt;&lt;Ref name=&quot;f189&quot;&gt;Fingleton, p. 189.&lt;/ref&gt; This triggered a collapse late in the afternoon, which saw the hosts lose 4/25 to end the third day at 7/178.&lt;ref name=&quot;sco5&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;report5&quot;/&gt; England resumed on the fourth morning with only three wickets in hand, still needing 159 runs to make Bradman’s men bat again. Johnston quickly removed the last three wickets, [[Alec Bedser]], Yardley and [[Eric Hollies]] to seal an Australian victory by an innings and 149 runs. Only ten runs were added in the brief morning session; Hollies fell for a [[duck (cricket}|golden duck]] after skying a ball to Morris, immediately after Yardley became the ninth man to fall.&lt;Ref name=&quot;sco5&quot;/&gt;&lt;Ref name=&quot;report5&quot;/&gt; Johnston ended with 4/40 from 27.3 overs and he was the most economical of the bowlers.&lt;ref name=&quot;sco5&quot;/&gt; Given the time lost to inclement weather on the first day, Australia had won the match in less than three days of playing time.&lt;ref name=&quot;haigh&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;testlist&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://statserver.cricket.org/guru?sdb=player;playerid=794;class=testplayer;filter=basic;team=0;opposition=0;notopposition=0;season=0;homeaway=0;continent=0;country=0;notcountry=0;groundid=0;startdefault=1947-11-28;start=1947-11-28;enddefault=1955-06-17;end=1955-06-17;tourneyid=0;finals=0;daynight=0;toss=0;scheduledovers=0;scheduleddays=0;innings=0;result=0;followon=0;seriesresult=0;captain=0;keeper=0;dnp=0;recent=;viewtype=aro_list;runslow=;runshigh=;batposition=0;dismissal=0;bowposition=0;ballslow=;ballshigh=;bpof=0;overslow=;overshigh=;conclow=;conchigh=;wicketslow=;wicketshigh=;dismissalslow=;dismissalshigh=;caughtlow=;caughthigh=;caughttype=0;stumpedlow=;stumpedhigh=;csearch=;submit=1;.cgifields=viewtype| title=Statsguru &amp;ndash; WA Johnston &amp;ndash; Tests &amp;ndash; Innings by innings list |publisher=[[Cricinfo]] |accessdate=2007-06-01}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;f182&quot;&gt;Fingleton, p. 182.&lt;/ref&gt; Overall, Johnston finished with 27 Test wickets at an [[bowling average|average]] of 23.33,&lt;ref name=&quot;testlist&quot;/&gt; equal to Lindwall but at a higher average.&lt;ref name=&quot;wisden&quot;/&gt;

== Later tour matches ==

Seven matches remained on Bradman's quest to go through a tour of England without defeat.&lt;Ref name=sched/&gt; Australia batted first against [[Kent County Cricket Club|Kent]] and made 361. Johnston then took three wickets with the new ball to help reduce the hosts to 5/16, before ending with 3/10 from six overs. Forced to follow on after being bowled out for 51 in 23 overs, Kent were reduced to 4/37 by three early Lindwall wickets. Johnston ended with 1/28 as the home team capitulated for 124 and lost by an innings.&lt;Ref name=kent&gt;{{cite web
|url = http://www.cricketarchive.com/Archive/Scorecards/18/18674.html 
|title = Kent v Australians
|publisher = [[CricketArchive]]
|accessdate = 2008-12-18}}&lt;/ref&gt; The victory over Kent was followed by a match against the [[Gentlemen of England cricket team|Gentlemen of England]]. Johnston was rested as Australia completed another innings victory.&lt;Ref name=sched/&gt;&lt;Ref name=o/&gt; He returned for the match against [[Somerset County Cricket Club|Somerset]], which resulted in a third consecutive innings win.&lt;ref name=sched/&gt;&lt;Ref name=o/&gt; After Australia had declared at 5/560, Johnston took the opening wicket of [[Harold Gimblett]] before returning to take the last two scalps of the first innings from consecutive balls, bowling his finger spin.&lt;ref name=sw/&gt; He ended with 3/34 as Somerset fell for 115 and were forced to follow on. Johnston bowled the second over of the second innings. As Johnston had taken wickets with his last two balls in the first innings, his first delivery was the [[hat-trick]] ball. Gimblett negotiated the first ball safely, before being trapped lbw for a duck on the next.&lt;ref name=sw&gt;{{Cite book
| title = [[Wisden Cricketers' Almanack]]
| edition = 1949
| publisher = [[Wisden]]
| chapter = Australians in England, 1948
| pages = 256&amp;ndash;257
}}&lt;/ref&gt; Johnston had thus taken three wickets in four balls. He bowled unchanged throughout the innings to end with 5/34 from 17.4 overs as Somerset were bowled out for 71.&lt;Ref name=somerset&gt;{{cite web
|url = http://www.cricketarchive.com/Archive/Scorecards/18/18696.html 
|title = Somerset v Australians
|publisher = [[CricketArchive]]
|accessdate = 2008-12-18}}&lt;/ref&gt; Johnston took the final wicket to fall&amp;mdash;[[Horace Hazell]]&amp;mdash;trapped for a duck, which brought up his 100th first-class wicket for the tour.&lt;ref name=somerset/&gt;

In the match against the [[South of England cricket team|South of England]], Johnston took 1/63&amp;mdash;Edrich being his only wicket&amp;mdash;after Australia declared at 7/522. Bradman’s men dismissed the hosts for 298 and rain ended the match before the second innings could start.&lt;ref name=o/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book
| title = [[Wisden Cricketers' Almanack]]
| edition = 1949
| publisher = [[Wisden]]
| chapter = Australians in England, 1948
| pages = 257&amp;ndash;258
}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Australia's biggest challenge in the post-Test tour matches was against the [[H. D. G. Leveson-Gower|Leveson-Gower's]] XI. During the last tour in 1938, this team was effectively a full-strength England outfit, but this time Bradman insisted that only six current England Test players be allowed to represent the hosts. After his opponents had finalised their players, Bradman named a full-strength team.&lt;ref&gt;Perry, pp. 253&amp;ndash;254.&lt;/ref&gt; In a rain-interrupted match, Johnston bowled Edrich for 15. He ended with 1/20 as the hosts folded for 177. Johnston made an unbeaten 26 in a partnership of 30 with [[Lindsay Hassett]] as Australia replied with 8/489 declared. Time ran out with the Leveson-Gower's XI at 0/75 in the second innings.&lt;Ref name=lg&gt;{{cite web
|url = http://www.cricketarchive.com/Archive/Scorecards/18/18706.html 
|title = H.D.G. Leveson-Gower's XI v Australians
|publisher = [[CricketArchive]]
|accessdate = 2008-12-18}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The tour ended with two non-first-class matches against [[Scotland national cricket team|Scotland]]. In the first, Australia scored 236 before Johnston took 6/15 from 12.5 overs. He took the last four wickets as the home team fell from 6/81 to be all out for 85. Johnston bowled four wicketless overs in the second innings as Australia completed victory without needing to bat for a second time.&lt;Ref name=sched/&gt;&lt;Ref name=o/&gt; In the second match, he signed off on his tour in a low key manner, taking a wicket in each innings to end with a match total of 2/48 as Australia completed another innings triumph.&lt;Ref name=o/&gt;

== Role ==
[[Image:Bill Johnston graph 1948.png|300px|right|thumb|A chart showing Johnston's batting performance during the tour. The runs scored per innings are represented by the bars, with the red bars being Test innings and the pink bars being other first-class innings. The blue line is the average of the five most recent innings and the dots indicate [[not out]]s.&lt;ref name=o/&gt;]] 

Johnston played as a left-arm [[fast bowling|fast bowler]] when the ball was new and conducive to pace bowling, before reverting to [[Left-arm orthodox spin|finger spin]] when it became old and lost its shine. He was Australia's third fast bowler in the Tests, reinforcing the new ball pairing of [[Keith Miller]] and [[Ray Lindwall]], who were regarded as one of the finest pace duos of all time. Bradman typically used Miller and Lindwall in short and sharp new ball bursts against the local batsmen. England had agreed that a new ball would be available every 55 overs, a milestone that usually came more frequently than the old regulation of 200 runs for every ball. This allowed Australia&amp;mdash;who had the superior pace attack&amp;mdash;more frequent use of a shiny ball, which [[swing bowling|swung]] at high pace.&lt;ref&gt;Perry, pp. 222&amp;ndash;223.&lt;/ref&gt; Johnston typically bowled pace after the first-choice pair had finished their new ball spell, before reverting to spin when the ball was worn. He took 27 wickets at 23.33 in the Tests, making him the equal-leading wicket-taker along with Lindwall, who averaged 19.62. The Australian pacemen’s tally was substantially more than the next best, recorded by England's [[Alec Bedser]], who took 18 wickets at 38.22.&lt;Ref name=aus&gt;{{cite web| url=http://stats.cricinfo.com/ci/engine/records/averages/batting_bowling_by_team.html?id=83;team=2;type=series |publisher=[[Cricinfo]] |title=Batting and bowling averages The Ashes, 1948 &amp;ndash; Australia |accessdate=2008-12-10}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;Ref name=eng&gt;{{cite web| url=http://stats.cricinfo.com/ci/engine/records/averages/batting_bowling_by_team.html?id=83;team=1;type=series |publisher=[[Cricinfo]] |title=Batting and bowling averages The Ashes, 1948 &amp;ndash; England |accessdate=2008-12-10}}&lt;/ref&gt; 

In both the Test and county matches during the 1948 tour, Johnston carried the heaviest workload, bowling nearly 200 overs more than any other squad member. He was the leading wicket-taker in all first-class matches with 102 wickets at 16.42,&lt;ref name=&quot;az&quot;/&gt; and the last Australian to take a century of wickets on a tour of England.&lt;ref name=&quot;guard&quot;&gt;{{cite news| title=Obituary:Bill Johnston| first= David |last=Frith |authorlink=David Frith| url=http://www.guardian.co.uk/australia/story/0,,2089626,00.html|date=2007-05-28 |accessdate=2007-05-31| work=[[The Guardian]]}}&lt;/ref&gt; His average was only slightly inferior to that of Lindwall, who took 86 wickets at 15.68.&lt;Ref name=fc&gt;{{cite web| url=http://stats.cricinfo.com/ci/engine/records/averages/batting_bowling.html?class=4;id=1070;type=tour |publisher=[[Cricinfo]] |title=Batting and bowling averages Australia tour of England, Apr-Sep 1948 &amp;ndash; First-class matches|accessdate=2008-12-10}}&lt;/ref&gt; The roles Johnston fulfilled are borne out in his [[economy rate]] and [[strike rate]]. He was more economical than Miller and Lindwall, who took wickets more frequently.&lt;Ref name=aus/&gt;&lt;ref name=fc/&gt;

Johnston's performances prompted Bradman to call him &quot;Australia's greatest left-hand bowler&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;az&quot;/&gt; As a result of his ability to bowl spin and pace, teammate [[Neil Harvey]] thought the team effectively had 13 players, saying &quot;we reckoned Bradman was worth two [batsmen] and Bill Johnston was worth two [bowlers]&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;tribute&quot;/&gt; Harvey rated Johnston the best team man in the squad, and [[Bill Brown (cricketer)|Bill Brown]] praised Johnston's work ethic in bowling for long periods after Lindwall and Miller had been given the best opportunities with the new ball.&lt;ref name=&quot;tribute&quot;&gt;{{cite news|title=Invincibles pay tribute to Johnston| url=http://www.cricinfo.com/ci/content/story/295751.html |date=2007-05-25| accessdate=2007-06-01| publisher=[[Cricinfo]]}}&lt;/ref&gt; Spin bowling teammate [[Ian Johnson (cricketer)|Ian Johnson]] described him as &quot;the finest team man and tourist&quot; in cricket and valued his personality,&lt;ref name=&quot;wisden&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;az&quot;/&gt; while Miller described him as &quot;the most popular man in cricket&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;haigh&quot;/&gt; Johnston sometimes amused his colleagues by demonstrating his double jointedness, wrapping his feet around the back of his neck. He was reputed to have nearly drowned when he attempted this in the communal bath at Lord's.&lt;ref name=&quot;smh&quot;&gt;{{cite news 
| work = [[The Sydney Morning Herald]]
| url = http://www.smh.com.au/news/cricket/invincible-dies-aged-85/2007/05/25/1179601630079.html?s_cid=rss_smh | title = 'Invincible' Bill Johnston dies
| date = 2007-05-25
| accessdate = 2007-05-25
}}&lt;/ref&gt; 

After carrying a heavy workload in the early stages of the tour, Johnston was used more sparingly in the latter stages. As the tour progressed, Johnston improved his control and restrained England's batsmen between the new ball bursts of Lindwall and Miller. Johnston was chosen as one of the five [[Wisden Cricketers of the Year]]. ''[[Wisden]]'' said &quot;no Australian made a greater personal contribution to the playing success of the 1948 side&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;wisden&quot;&gt;{{cite web| title= Wisden 1949 &amp;ndash; William Johnston |url=http://www.cricinfo.com/wisdenalmanack/content/story/154626.html| year= 1949 |accessdate=2007-05-25| publisher=[[Wisden]]}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;az&quot;&gt;Cashman et al., pp. 152&amp;ndash;154.&lt;/ref&gt; Fingleton wrote that Australia had never sent a greater left-hander to England.&lt;ref name=&quot;indep&quot;&gt;{{cite news|title=Obituaries:Bill Johnston| url=http://news.independent.co.uk/people/obituaries/article2584120.ece| work=[[The Independent]] |date=2007-05-25 |accessdate=2007-06-01}}&lt;/ref&gt;

During the tour, Johnston had few opportunities with the bat, invariably batting at either No. 10 and No. 11 alongside Toshack, another [[tail-ender]] with little batting ability.&lt;sup&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#00f&quot;&gt;N-&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;{{Ref label|bat|1|a}} Neither player ever passed 30 in their first-class career,&lt;ref&gt;Cashman et al., pp. 152, 300.&lt;/ref&gt; and they were the only two Australians who failed to pass 50 during the tour.&lt;Ref name=fc/&gt; As Australia's other frontline bowlers were Miller, Lindwall, [[Colin McCool]], [[Ian Johnson (cricketer)|Ian Johnson]] and [[Doug Ring]], all of whom scored [[century (cricket)|centuries]] and more than 20 fifties each during their first-class career,&lt;ref&gt;Cashman et al., pp. 152, 175, 199, 258.&lt;/ref&gt; Toshack and Johnston were rooted at the bottom of the [[batting order (cricket)|batting order]]. As Australia often won by an innings, and declared in the first innings many time due to their batting strength, Johnston only had 18 innings in his 21 first-class fixtures and scored 188 runs at 18.80, the third lowest average and aggregate. He scored 62 runs in the Tests at 20.66, including his highest first-class score of 29 in the Second Test at Lord’s.&lt;Ref name=o/&gt;

== Notes ==
===Statistical note===
&lt;div class=&quot;references-small&quot;&gt;
&lt;span style=&quot;color:#00f;font-variant:small-caps&quot;&gt;n-[1]&lt;/span&gt;
{{note_label|bat|1|a}}
This statement can be verified by consulting all of the scorecards for the matches, as listed here.&lt;Ref name=leics/&gt;&lt;ref name=o/&gt;&lt;ref name=york/&gt;&lt;ref name=surrey/&gt;&lt;ref name=ox/&gt;&lt;ref name=sco1/&gt;&lt;ref name=sco2/&gt;&lt;ref name=sco3/&gt;&lt;ref name=sco4/&gt;&lt;ref name=sco5/&gt;&lt;ref name=mcc/&gt;&lt;ref name=lancs/&gt;&lt;ref name=hants/&gt;&lt;ref name=northants/&gt;&lt;ref name=york2/&gt;&lt;ref name=warwick/&gt;&lt;ref name=lancs2/&gt;&lt;ref name=durham/&gt;&lt;ref name=kent/&gt;&lt;ref name=somerset/&gt;&lt;ref name=lg/&gt;&lt;Ref name=gents&gt;{{cite web
|url = http://www.cricketarchive.com/Archive/Scorecards/18/18684.html 
|title = Gentlemen v Australians
|publisher = [[CricketArchive]]
|accessdate = 2007-12-26}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=surrey2&gt;{{cite web
|url = http://www.cricketarchive.com/Archive/Scorecards/18/18553.html 
|title = Surrey v Australians
|publisher = [[CricketArchive]]
|accessdate = 2008-12-18}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=gloucs&gt;{{cite web
|url = http://www.cricketarchive.com/Archive/Scorecards/18/18558.html 
|title = Gloucestershire v Australians
|publisher = [[CricketArchive]]
|accessdate = 2007-12-26}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;Ref name=middlesex&gt;{{cite web
|url = http://www.cricketarchive.com/Archive/Scorecards/18/18593.html 
|title = Middlesex v Australians
|publisher = [[CricketArchive]]
|accessdate = 2008-12-18}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=derby&gt;{{cite web
|url = http://www.cricketarchive.com/Archive/Scorecards/18/18616.html 
|title = Derbyshire v Australians
|publisher = [[CricketArchive]]
|accessdate = 2008-12-18}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=glam&gt;{{cite web
|url = http://www.cricketarchive.com/Archive/Scorecards/18/18619.html 
|title = Glamorgan v Australians
|publisher = [[CricketArchive]]
|accessdate = 2008-12-18}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;Ref name=soe&gt;{{cite web
|url = http://www.cricketarchive.com/Archive/Scorecards/18/18698.html 
|title = South of England v Australians
|publisher = [[CricketArchive]]
|accessdate = 2008-12-18}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;Ref name=worcs&gt;{{cite web
|url = http://www.cricketarchive.com/Archive/Scorecards/18/18403.html 
|title = Worcestershire v Australians
|publisher = [[CricketArchive]]
|accessdate = 2008-12-18}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;Ref name=scot1&gt;{{cite web
|url = http://www.cricketarchive.com/Archive/Scorecards/18/18707.html 
|title = Scotland v Australians
|publisher = [[CricketArchive]]
|accessdate = 2008-12-18}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;Ref name=scot2&gt;{{cite web
|url = http://www.cricketarchive.com/Archive/Scorecards/18/18709.html 
|title = Scotland v Australians
|publisher = [[CricketArchive]]
|accessdate = 2008-12-18}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=camb&gt;{{cite web
|url = http://www.cricketarchive.com/Archive/Scorecards/18/18423.html 
|title = Cambridge University v Australians
|publisher = [[CricketArchive]]
|accessdate = 2008-12-18}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=essex&gt;{{cite web
|url = http://www.cricketarchive.com/Archive/Scorecards/18/18429.html 
|title = Essex v Australians
|publisher = [[CricketArchive]]
|accessdate = 2007-12-26}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=sussex&gt;{{cite web
|url = http://www.cricketarchive.com/Archive/Scorecards/18/18489.html 
|title = Sussex v Australians
|publisher = [[CricketArchive]]
|accessdate = 2008-12-18}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;Ref name=notts&gt;{{cite web
|url = http://www.cricketarchive.com/Archive/Scorecards/18/18467.html 
|title = Nottinghamshire v Australians
|publisher = [[CricketArchive]]
|accessdate = 2008-12-18}}&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

=== General notes ===
{{Reflist|2}}

== References ==
*{{cite book |last=Arlott |first=John |authorlink=John Arlott |year=1949 |title=Gone to the test match : being primarily an account of the test series of 1948  |publisher=Longmans |location=London}}
*{{cite book | last = Cashman, Richard; Franks, Warwick; [[Jim Maxwell (commentator)|Maxwell, Jim]]; Sainsbury, Erica; Stoddart, Brian; Weaver, Amanda; Webster, Ray | year = 1997 | title = The A&amp;ndash;Z of Australian cricketers| isbn=0-9756746-1-7|location=Melbourne, Victoria |publisher=Oxford University Press}}
*{{cite book| last=Fingleton |first=Jack |authorlink=Jack Fingleton |title=Brightly fades the Don |year=1949 |publisher=Collins |location=London}}
*{{cite book |author=[[Bill O'Reilly (cricketer)|O'Reilly, W. J.]] |year=1949 |title=Cricket conquest: the story of the 1948 test tour |publisher=Werner Laurie |location=London}}
*{{cite book|last=Perry|first=Roland|authorlink=Roland Perry|title=Miller's Luck: the life and loves of Keith Miller, Australia's greatest all-rounder|year=2005|publisher=Random House|location=Milsons Point, New South Wales|isbn=9781741662221}}
*{{cite book|first=Jack |last=Pollard |authorlink=Jack Pollard|year=1990 |publisher=[[Harper Collins]] |title=From Bradman to Border: Australian Cricket 1948&amp;ndash;89 |isbn=0-207-16124-0 &lt;!--0-207-15596-8 The Bradman Years 1918&amp;ndash;1948--&gt; |location=North Ryde, New South Wales}}
{{The Invincibles squad}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Johnston, Bill}}
[[Category:The Invincibles (cricket)]]
{{good article}}</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
