<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="207630" ns="0" title="Dominion War"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Use mdy dates|date=April 2011}}
{{infobox military conflict
|conflict     =Dominion War
|partof       =''[[Star Trek: Deep Space Nine]]''
|image        = [[File:USS Majestic hit.jpg|300px]]
| caption     = 
|date=2373-2375
|place=Primarily the [[Galactic quadrant|Alpha and Gamma Quadrants]]
| coordinates = 
| map_type    = 
| latitude    = 
| longitude   = 
| map_size    = 
| map_caption = 
| map_label   = 
| territory   = 
|result=Conditional Dominion surrender
| status      = 
| combatant1  = '''Federation Alliance'''
* [[United Federation of Planets]]
* [[Klingon Empire]]
* [[Romulan Star Empire]] (2374-2375)
* [[Bajor]] (2374-2375)
* [[Cardassian Union]] (2375)
* [[Section 31]]
* [[Maquis (Star Trek)|Maquis]] (eliminated 2373)
|combatant2='''Neutral'''
* [[Romulan Star Empire]] (2373-2374)
* [[Breen (Star Trek)|Breen]] (2375-2375)
* [[Bajoran]]s (2373-2374)
|combatant3='''Dominion&lt;br&gt;Axis'''
* [[The Dominion (Star Trek)|Dominion]]
* [[Cardassian Union]] (2373-2375)
* [[Breen (Star Trek)|Breen]] Confederacy (2375)
| commander1  = 
| commander2  = 
| commander3  = 
| units1      =
| units2      =
| units3      = 
| strength1   = 
| strength2   = 
| strength3   = 
| casualties1 = 
| casualties2 = 
| casualties3 = 
| notes       = 
| campaignbox =
}}

The '''Dominion War''' is an extended plot concept developed in a number of [[story arc]]s of  ''[[Star Trek: Deep Space Nine]]'', an American science-fiction television series produced by [[Paramount Pictures]].  In the fictional ''[[Star Trek]]'' universe, the Dominion War is a conflict between the forces of the [[Dominion (Star Trek)|Dominion]], [[Cardassian Union]] and, later, the [[Breen (Star Trek)|Breen Confederacy]] against the [[Alpha Quadrant]] alliance of the [[United Federation of Planets]], [[Klingon Empire]] and, later, the [[Romulan Star Empire]].

The primary setting of much of the series is aboard the fictional [[Starfleet]] controlled space station [[Deep Space Nine (space station)|Deep Space Nine]], located above the planet [[Bajor]]. In the series this space station is situated near a [[Bajoran wormhole|wormhole]] which provided instantaneous travel to the [[Gamma Quadrant]], a region on the other side of the galaxy. During season two of Deep Space Nine, the [[Dominion (Star Trek)|Dominion]] is introduced. Over the course of season two and three more information is introduced, until the conflict escalated in season four, particularly in the episodes [[Homefront (Star Trek: Deep Space Nine)|''Homefront'']] and [[Paradise Lost (Star Trek: Deep Space Nine)|''Paradise Lost'']]. The Dominion War arcs present themes that challenge the values of the characters in a manner not attempted in earlier series of ''Star Trek'', and have received a mixed critical response. Developing the plot of the Dominion War also altered the manner in which the series was scripted, shifting the emphasis from an episodic to a serialized narrative format.

==Synopsis==
{{Main|Star Trek: Deep Space Nine}}

In &quot;[[Emissary (Star Trek: Deep Space Nine)|Emissary]]&quot;, the pilot episode, the [[United Federation of Planets]] dispatches [[Benjamin Sisko|Commander Benjamin Sisko]] to take command of the space station [[Deep Space Nine (space station)|Deep Space Nine]].&lt;ref name=Emissary&gt;{{cite episode|title=Emissary|url=http://www.startrek.com/database_article/emissary-part-i|series=Star Trek: Deep Space Nine|serieslink=Star Trek: Deep Space Nine|credits=Writer: [[Michael Piller]]. Story: Michael Piller and [[Rick Berman]]. Creators: Rick Berman and Michael Piller|network=[[UPN]]|airdate=1993-01-03}}&lt;/ref&gt; The station is located near a [[Bajoran Wormhole|stable wormhole]] located in the [[Alpha Quadrant]], which leads to the [[Gamma Quadrant]] of the [[Milky Way|Milky Way Galaxy]], nearly 70,000 light years away. Deep Space Nine is moved from the orbit of the planet [[Bajor]] to the Alpha Quadrant terminus of the wormhole to lay claim. Starships begin to enter the wormhole to explore, colonize and trade. The crews on the ships were unaware that they are entering a region of space controlled by the [[Dominion (Star Trek)|Dominion]], a union of planets ordered by force and intimidation.&lt;ref name=Emissary/&gt;

Deep Space Nine's [[Ferengi]] bartender, [[Quark (Star Trek)|Quark]], makes contact with the [[Vorta]], a Dominion member race. However, he and Sisko are captured by the [[Jem'Hadar]], the soldiers of the Dominion. The Alpha Quadrant group is rescued, but the Federation ship USS ''Odyssey'' is lost in the attempt to return home, and colonies are destroyed as a warning not to re-enter Dominion space. Later, it is revealed that a race of [[shapeshifter]]s, known as &quot;[[Changeling (Star Trek)|Founders]]&quot;, are the rulers of the Dominion, and that [[Odo (Star Trek)|Constable Odo]] is of this species. Members of the [[Cardassia]]n [[Obsidian Order]] and the [[Romulan]] [[Tal Shiar]] intelligence factions plan to eradicate the Founders and their homeworld, but are themselves deceived by a shapeshifter and ambushed.

The Founders initiate a campaign of sabotage and terror against the Alpha Quadrant, which leaves many governments fearful of infiltrators, who are able to assume any physical form. When Earth is attacked, a band of [[Starfleet]] officers illegally attempt to impose [[martial law]] at the heart of the Federation. The [[Klingon Empire]] invades Cardassia in the inaccurate assumption that the Dominion is influencing its government. Later, the Federation suspects the Klingon Chancellor, [[Gowron]], of being a shapeshifter. This turned out to be a ploy by the Dominion so that the Federation would assassinate Gowron and further intensify the rift between the Federation and Klingons due to the Klingon invasion of Cardassia. During the assassination attempt, the Federation realized that Klingon [[General Martok]] was the actual shapeshifter. It would turn out that Martok, Dr. [[Julian Bashir]] and others have been held captive at a prison camp in the Gamma Quadrant while shapeshifters took their place in the Alpha Quadrant. Shortly before their escape, the Dominion succeeds in urging the Cardassians to enter an alliance during the confusion, establishing its presence in the Alpha Quadrant. Realizing the danger, the Federation and Klingons join forces to slow the Dominion build-up, co-operating to plant a minefield across the entrance to the Bajoran Wormhole as a rescued Martok is assigned as a permanent Klingon commander at Deep Space Nine.

Nevertheless, the Dominion begins to advance, and seizes control of Deep Space Nine. After a brief retreat, Sisko executes a successful return to the space station, but the wider conflict continues. More setbacks hinder the Alpha Quadrant alliance as additional races, such as the [[Breen (Star Trek)|Breen]], offer their support to the Dominion. Questionable tactics are adopted in the search for victory, including the dissemination of an [[Biological warfare|engineered virus]] among the Founders by a shadow Federation group called [[Section 31]]. A ruse involving a murder is used to enlist the help of the Romulans against the Dominion, and dissatisfactions lead the Cardassian leader, [[Legate Damar]], to launch a successful resistance movement against his former Dominion comrades. Eventually, the Dominion is forced back to the planet Cardassia Prime where it is cut off from reinforcements. The female shapeshifter in command informs Odo that they would fight to the end in order to prevent any counter-attack by the alliance into the Gamma Quadrant. Odo assures her that the Federation would not do that while the other parties would be too weak to. After linking together, Odo cures the female shapeshifter of the biological disease afflicting her and the other Founders with the antidote he received and the Dominion agrees to surrender.

==Conception==
{{Main|Dominion (Star Trek)}}

In 2002, ''[[Star Trek: Deep Space Nine]]'' producer [[Ira Steven Behr]] stated that unlike some plots, which originated from a single small idea, the creation of the [[Dominion (Star Trek)|Dominion]] villain and [[story arc]] was &quot;very much thought out.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;Birth_and_Beyond&quot;&gt;{{cite video|people=Behr, Wolfe, Piller|title=The Birth of the Dominion and Beyond|date=2003|medium=''Star Trek: Deep Space Nine'' Season Three DVD Special Features|publisher=Paramount Pictures}}&lt;/ref&gt; Behr said that the earliest mention of the Dominion was purposely planted in the comic Season Two [[Ferengi]] episode, &quot;[[Rules of Acquisition (Star Trek: Deep Space Nine)|Rules of Acquisition]]&quot;, to leave the audience with an impression of &quot;how important could it be?&quot; It was decided that the [[Gamma Quadrant]] would need an ambiance that would distinguish it from the Alpha Quadrant. The producers wanted to portray the region as something other than &quot;uncharted space&quot;, and avoid imitating the adventures of ''[[Star Trek: The Next Generation]]'' with another series of plots focusing primarily on themes of exploration.&lt;ref name=&quot;Deep Space Nine Companionp97&quot;&gt;{{cite book|last1=Erdmann|first1=Terry|last2=Block|first2=Paula|title=The Star Trek: Deep Space Nine Companion|publisher=Pocket Books, Simon &amp; Schuster Inc|location=New York City|year=2000|page=97|isbn=1-0671-5010-62}}&lt;/ref&gt; After 18 months of ''Deep Space Nine'' exposition, the producers decided to characterize The Dominion as &quot;anti-[[United Federation of Planets|Federation]]&quot;. Writer and script editor [[Robert Hewitt Wolfe]] has explained that this move also distinguished ''Deep Space Nine'' from its successor series, ''[[Star Trek: Voyager]]'', which stars a [[USS Voyager (Star Trek)|lost Federation ship]] traversing the chaotic and divided [[Delta Quadrant]] of the [[Milky Way]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Birth_and_Beyond&quot;/&gt;

Instead of introducing one alien race, three were introduced simultaneously: the [[Changeling (Star Trek)|Changelings]], the [[Vorta]] and the [[Jem'Hadar]]. These three were intended to represent the front of an ancient civilization coupled together by fear, to contrast with the unity of the Federation enabled by bonds of friendship. Behr, Wolfe, writer [[Peter Allan Fields]] and Jim Crocker attended meetings to develop the concepts of these species and found general inspiration in [[Isaac Asimov]]'s [[Foundation series|''Foundation'' Trilogy]] novels.&lt;ref name=&quot;Deep Space Nine Companionp153&quot;&gt;{{cite book|last1=Erdmann|first1=Terry|last2=Block|first2=Paula|title=The Star Trek: Deep Space Nine Companion|publisher=Pocket Books, Simon &amp; Schuster Inc|location=New York City|year=2000|page=153|isbn=1-0671-5010-62}}&lt;/ref&gt; Executive producer [[Michael Piller]] suggested the idea that the Founders of the Dominion be the race to which [[Odo (Star Trek)|Odo]] belongs, toward the end of Season Two production, and discovered that Behr and Wolfe had also discussed this possibility.&lt;ref name=&quot;Birth_and_Beyond&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Deep Space Nine Companionpp158-159&quot;&gt;{{cite book|last1=Erdmann|first1=Terry|last2=Block|first2=Paula|title=The Star Trek: Deep Space Nine Companion|publisher=Pocket Books, Simon &amp; Schuster Inc|location=New York City|year=2000|pages=158–159|isbn=1-0671-5010-62}}&lt;/ref&gt; This character had been introduced with no knowledge of his true origins. Piller asserts the endeavor to create a new villain was one of the most difficult tasks he undertook in his work on ''Star Trek''.&lt;ref name=&quot;Birth_and_Beyond&quot;/&gt; Wolfe perceives similarities between the fictional Founders and the [[Roman Empire]], in that the species first uses diplomacy, deception and cultural imperialism to achieve their aims before ultimately resorting to coercion.&lt;ref name=&quot;Deep Space Nine Companionp167&quot;&gt;{{cite book|last1=Erdmann|first1=Terry|last2=Block|first2=Paula|title=The Star Trek: Deep Space Nine Companion|publisher=Pocket Books, Simon &amp; Schuster Inc|location=New York City|year=2000|page=167|isbn=1-0671-5010-62}} [[Robert Hewitt Wolfe]]: &quot;[The Founders, like the Roman Empire] would rather take over someplace without firing a shot, but they're going to take over ...&quot;&lt;/ref&gt;

According to writer [[Ronald D. Moore]], co-creator [[Rick Berman]] originally intended the Dominion War to be the focus of three or four episodes, but Behr intended to expand the plotline all along. Moore has stated that Berman sometimes questioned the writing staff about the [[Media violence research|degree of violence]] included in some episodes. Berman also expressed concern about the portrayal of long-term consequences for the main characters, such as the loss of a character's leg in Season Seven. The writers argued in favor of the increased violence, asserting that it was justified in view of the plotlines detailing the progression of the Dominion War.&lt;ref name=&quot;IGN p8&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://movies.ign.com/articles/444/444306p8.html|title=An Interview with Ron Moore|page=8|accessdate=May 8, 2010|date=December 4, 1993|work=IGN}}&lt;/ref&gt; Piller supported the idea that the repercussions of past episodes should continue to be felt, and that characters should &quot;learn that actions have consequences&quot;, even if such consequences were to lead off in directions Piller had not originally imagined when ''Deep Space Nine'' remained in the conceptual stages.&lt;ref name=&quot;boldnew&quot;&gt;[[Michael Piller]]: ''A Bold New Beginning'' Featurette [''Star Trek: Deep Space Nine'' Season One DVD Special Features].&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;TrekWeb Ira Behr p2&quot;/&gt; Moore has stated that the filming of ''Star Trek: Voyager'' occupied more of Berman and Piller's time from ''Deep Space Nine''&lt;nowiki&gt;'&lt;/nowiki&gt;s third season, which allowed Behr to defend his creative decisions more successfully.&lt;ref name=&quot;IGN p7&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://uk.movies.ign.com/articles/444/444306p7.html|title=An Interview with Ron Moore|page=7|accessdate=April 4, 2011|date=December 4, 1993|work=IGN}}&lt;/ref&gt; Following the completion of ''Star Trek: The Next Generation'', the writing staff could dedicate more time to working on scripts for ''Deep Space Nine''. The writers admired the scripting techniques used for ''[[Star Trek: The Original Series]]'': Moore cites the 1967 episode &quot;[[Errand of Mercy]]&quot; as a strong influence on his treatment of the Dominion War.&lt;ref name=&quot;IGN p3&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://movies.ign.com/articles/444/444306p8.html|title=An Interview with Ron Moore|page=3|accessdate=May 8, 2010|date=December 4, 1993|work=IGN}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Development==
The plot of the Dominion War is presented in a succession of shorter [[story arc]]s which span Seasons Two to Seven of ''[[Star Trek: Deep Space Nine]]'' and are linked editorially by the decisions of the producers and writers.

===Season Two: introducing the Dominion===
After conceptual meetings, the writers began to introduce allusions to the [[Dominion (Star Trek)|Dominion]] into episodes of Season Two. The intention was to gradually increase the audience's awareness that there was a large and pervasive [[polity]] at work behind apparently innocuous events in the [[Gamma Quadrant]]. The Dominion and its methods are revealed across three episodes of the season.&lt;ref name=&quot;Deep Space Nine Companionp73&quot;&gt;{{cite book|last1=Erdmann|first1=Terry|last2=Block|first2=Paula|title=The Star Trek: Deep Space Nine Companion|publisher=Pocket Books, Simon &amp; Schuster Inc|location=New York City|year=2000|page=73|isbn=1-0671-5010-62}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&quot;[[Rules of Acquisition (Star Trek: Deep Space Nine)|Rules of Acquisition]]&quot; marks the first mention of the Dominion,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite episode|title=Rules of Acquisition|url=http://www.startrek.com/database_article/rules-of-acquisition|series=Star Trek: Deep Space Nine|serieslink=Star Trek: Deep Space Nine|credits=Writer: [[Ira Steven Behr]]. Story: Hilary Bader. Creators: [[Rick Berman]] and [[Michael Piller]]|network=[[UPN]]|airdate=1993-11-07}}&lt;/ref&gt; when the [[Ferengi]] character [[Quark (Star Trek)|Quark]] hears whispers of a powerful union of civilizations in the Gamma Quadrant with which he may be able to trade. Dialogue that seems inconsequential within the framework of a light-hearted episode was planned to ultimately create major change in the dynamics of ''[[Star Trek: Deep Space Nine]]''.&lt;ref name=&quot;Birth_and_Beyond&quot;/&gt;

As Alpha Quadrant races begin to colonize planets in the Gamma Quadrant and their presence becomes known, disturbing reports indicate that what the Dominion cannot attain through trade is forcibly seized. These reports are justified in &quot;[[Sanctuary (Star Trek: Deep Space Nine)|Sanctuary]]&quot;, when a large fleet of Skrreea ships appears in the Alpha Quadrant, in search of a new homeworld in light of the conquest of their original planet by Dominion forces.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite episode|title=Sanctuary|url=http://www.startrek.com/database_article/sanctuary|series=Star Trek: Deep Space Nine|serieslink=Star Trek: Deep Space Nine|credits=Writer: Frederick Rappaport. Story: Kelley Miles and Gabe Essoe. Creators: [[Rick Berman]] and [[Michael Piller]]|network=[[UPN]]|airdate=1993-11-28}}&lt;/ref&gt; The actions of the Dominion are contrasted with the reactions of the regular characters to the Skrreea refugees. Executive producer [[Michael Piller]] has suggested that the plot evoked real-world debate surrounding [[Proposition 187]], a Californian law concerning the rights of [[Alien (law)|illegal aliens]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Deep Space Nine Companionp106&quot;&gt;{{cite book|last1=Erdmann|first1=Terry|last2=Block|first2=Paula|title=The Star Trek: Deep Space Nine Companion|publisher=Pocket Books, Simon &amp; Schuster Inc|location=New York City|year=2000|page=106|isbn=1-0671-5010-62}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The finale of Season Two, &quot;[[The Jem'Hadar]]&quot;, permitted writer [[Robert Hewitt Wolfe]] to surprise the audience, and challenge their opinions concerning the safety of the [[United Federation of Planets|Federation]] and [[Starfleet]], when the USS ''Odyssey'', a [[Galaxy class starship|''Galaxy''-class starship]] similar to the [[USS Enterprise (NCC-1701-D)|USS ''Enterprise'']] from ''[[Star Trek: The Next Generation]]'', is outfought and destroyed.&lt;ref name=&quot;Birth_and_Beyond&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Deep Space Nine Companionpp154-155&quot;&gt;{{cite book|last1=Erdmann|first1=Terry|last2=Block|first2=Paula|title=The Star Trek: Deep Space Nine Companion|publisher=Pocket Books, Simon &amp; Schuster Inc|location=New York City|year=2000|pages=154–5|isbn=1-0671-5010-62}} [[Robert Hewitt Wolfe]]: &quot;We wanted to show the long-term fans how dangerous these guys were. And it's my belief that if that had been the ''Enterprise'' and not the ''Odyssey'', and [Jean-Luc] Picard rather than Keogh in command, it still wouldn't have survived.&quot;&lt;/ref&gt; The Dominion is revealed to be a ruthless empire, using &quot;[[carrot and stick]]&quot; methods to control others, with three distinct races performing crucial roles.&lt;ref&gt;Interview with [[Robert Hewitt Wolfe]]: ''The Birth of the Dominion and Beyond'' Documentary [''Star Trek: Deep Space Nine'' Season Three DVD Special Features]. Paramount, ASIN: B00008KA5A, June 3, 1993: &quot;The Gamma Quadrant isn't empty, it isn't just a bunch of planets. It's bound together by the Dominion, a very, very tough, very smart, very old civilization, run by the mysterious Founders, who are experts in genetic engineering, and who turn out to be Odo's people, the shapeshifters. They then go and engineer these slave races that do their bidding. Essentially, the two main slave races were the 'carrot' and the 'stick'. The carrot being the Vorta, who would come to your planet and say, 'Hey, you're nice people, here's some M16s and some popcorn, and whatever else you want, baby: alcohol, fire-water? All you have to do is sign this little contract and we'll make you cool.' Then there's the Jem'Hadar. So the Vorta say, 'Oh, you don't want to play ball? Then meet these guys. They're gonna kick your asses.'&quot;&lt;/ref&gt; The Dominion's [[Jem'Hadar]] [[shock troops]] capture [[Benjamin Sisko|Commander Sisko]], Quark and an alien named Eris, who is later identified as a [[double agent]] and one of the [[Vorta]], the Dominion's negotiators and administrators. The Jem'Hadar send a Jem'Hadar representative to [[Deep Space Nine (space station)|Deep Space Nine]] with the message that no further intrusions into Dominion space will be tolerated, and to hand [[Kira Nerys|Major Kira Nerys]] a list of colonies and ships already eliminated for trespassing. The Federation dispatches a rescue team that returns Sisko's group to the station, but while retreating back to the Alpha Quadrant a Jem'Hadar ship launches a [[kamikaze]] run against the ''Odyssey'', resulting in the destruction of both ships.&lt;ref name=&quot;The Jem'Hadar&quot;&gt;{{cite episode|title=The Jem'Hadar|url=http://www.startrek.com/database_article/jemhadar-the|series=Star Trek: Deep Space Nine|serieslink=Star Trek: Deep Space Nine|credits=Story: [[Ira Steven Behr]]. Creators: [[Rick Berman]] and [[Michael Piller]]|network=[[UPN]]|airdate=1994-06-12}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Season Three: introducing the Founders===
With the third season, [[Ronald D. Moore]] and others started to write regularly for ''Star Trek: Deep Space Nine'' following the completion of ''[[Star Trek: The Next Generation]]''.&lt;ref name=&quot;IGN p7&quot;/&gt; [[Robert Hewitt Wolfe]] joined [[Ira Steven Behr]] in scripting episodes developing the [[Dominion (Star Trek)|Dominion]] plotline, beginning with &quot;[[The Search (Star Trek: Deep Space Nine)|The Search]]&quot;. Behr became full executive producer at the midpoint of the season, after the departure of [[Michael Piller]].

In the two-part season opener, &quot;The Search&quot;, [[Benjamin Sisko|Commander Sisko]] returns from [[Starfleet]] Headquarters on Earth with a [[Defiant class starship|''Defiant''-class]] prototype starship, the [[USS Defiant|USS ''Defiant'']].&lt;ref name=&quot;The Search, Part I&quot;/&gt; Executive producer [[Rick Berman]] had to be convinced that the introduction of the ''Defiant'' would not distract the audience from the [[USS Voyager (Star Trek)|main starship]] of the latest ''[[Star Trek]]'' production, ''[[Star Trek: Voyager]]''. The decision was made on the basis that a ship was needed to provide an avenue for stories set off the [[Deep Space Nine (space station)|Deep Space Nine]] space station, and that such a vessel would need the potential to oppose the [[Jem'Hadar]], who had already been portrayed obliterating large ships. Audience research had also suggested that young male viewers were hoping for more action-oriented episodes with greater jeopardy.&lt;ref name=&quot;Deep Space Nine Companionp158&quot;&gt;{{cite book|last1=Erdmann|first1=Terry|last2=Block|first2=Paula|title=The Star Trek: Deep Space Nine Companion|publisher=Pocket Books, Simon &amp; Schuster Inc|location=New York City|year=2000|page=158|isbn=1-0671-5010-62}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Season Three's Dominion stories explore the connection between [[Odo (Star Trek)|Odo]] and his people, and their conflicting attitudes toward &quot;solid&quot; sentient lifeforms. The ''Defiant'' enters the [[Gamma Quadrant]] on a peace mission to locate the [[Changeling (Star Trek)|Founders]] in &quot;The Search&quot;, and it is discovered that the Founders are of the same race as Odo. Despite a burning desire to return to his home, he finds his people's philosophy – that which you can control cannot hurt you – abhorrent, and asks to return to the Alpha Quadrant.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.twiztv.com/scripts/ds9/season3/ds9-302.txt|archiveurl=http://web.archive.org/web/20080502202855/http://www.twiztv.com/scripts/ds9/season3/ds9-302.txt|archivedate= May 2, 2008|title=Script for &quot;The Search, Part II&quot;|publisher=twiztv.com|month=July|year=1994|accessdate=April 23, 2010}} Act 5, Scene 74. Writer: [[Ira Steven Behr]]. Story: [[Robert Hewitt Wolfe]] and Ira Steven Behr. July 18, 1994. Female Changeling: &quot;What you can control can't hurt you.&quot; Odo: &quot;How can you justify the deaths of so many people?&quot; Female Changeling: &quot;The solids have always been a threat to us, that's the only justification we need.&quot;&lt;/ref&gt; The Founders, led by a character identified only as the &quot;[[Female Changeling]]&quot;, acquiesce to Odo's request in the hope that he will ultimately rejoin them.&lt;ref name=&quot;The Search, Part I&quot;&gt;{{cite episode|title=The Search, Part I|url=http://www.startrek.com/database_article/search-part-i|series=Star Trek: Deep Space Nine|serieslink=Star Trek: Deep Space Nine|credits=Writer: [[Ronald D. Moore]]. Story: [[Robert Hewitt Wolfe]] and [[Ira Steven Behr]]. Creators: [[Rick Berman]] and [[Michael Piller]]|network=[[UPN]]|airdate=1994-09-26}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;The Search, Part II&quot;&gt;{{cite episode|title=The Search, Part II|url=http://www.startrek.com/database_article/search-part-ii|series=Star Trek: Deep Space Nine|serieslink=Star Trek: Deep Space Nine|credits=Writer: [[Ira Steven Behr]]. Story: [[Robert Hewitt Wolfe]] and Ira Steven Behr. Creators: [[Rick Berman]] and [[Michael Piller]]|network=[[UPN]]|airdate=1994-10-03}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Another facet to the Dominion was evaluated more closely in Season Three – the Jem'Hadar. In &quot;[[The Abandoned (Star Trek: Deep Space Nine)|The Abandoned]]&quot;, a juvenile Jem'Hadar is found alone and matures under Odo's guidance. The crew of Deep Space Nine witnesses the Jem'Hadar's difficulty in adjusting to a society with rules different to those of his native culture. [[Avery Brooks]], directing this episode, has emphasised the story as a metaphor for African-American adolescents in the 20th century and their struggles with addiction and violence, their integration into American society, and the manner in which their upbringing might contribute to these problems.&lt;ref name=&quot;Deep Space Nine Companionp180a&quot;&gt;{{cite book|last1=Erdmann|first1=Terry|last2=Block|first2=Paula|title=The Star Trek: Deep Space Nine Companion|publisher=Pocket Books, Simon &amp; Schuster Inc|location=New York City|year=2000|page=180a|isbn=1-0671-5010-62}} [[Avery Brooks]]: &quot;For me, it was very much a story about young brown men, and, to some extent, a story about a society that is responsible for the creation of a generation of young men who are feared, who are addicted, who are potential killers ...&quot;&lt;/ref&gt; Brooks ensured that Odo continues to support the maturing Jem'Hadar despite the alien's regression to Dominion custom, as a commentary on how modern society should engage with young people.&lt;ref name=&quot;Deep Space Nine Companionp180b&quot;&gt;{{cite book|last1=Erdmann|first1=Terry|last2=Block|first2=Paula|title=The Star Trek: Deep Space Nine Companion|publisher=Pocket Books, Simon &amp; Schuster Inc|location=New York City|year=2000|page=180|isbn=1-0671-5010-62}} [[Avery Brooks]]: &quot;Odo knows that this is still a child, and for him to give up and just let the boy go – what kind of a statement would we be making? That these people are expendable, that we don't really care about them? Those are the hard questions to answer.&quot;&lt;/ref&gt;

&quot;[[Improbable Cause]]&quot; initiates a two-part adventure concerning the search for the Founders' homeworld which concludes in &quot;[[The Die is Cast (Star Trek: Deep Space Nine)|The Die is Cast]]&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;Improbable Cause&quot;&gt;{{cite episode|title=Improbable Cause|url=http://www.startrek.com/database_article/improbable-cause|series=Star Trek: Deep Space Nine|serieslink=Star Trek: Deep Space Nine|credits=Writer: [[René Echevarria]]. Story: [[Robert Lederman]] and David R. Long. Creators: [[Rick Berman]] and [[Michael Piller]]|network=[[UPN]]|airdate=1995-04-24}}&lt;/ref&gt; Following [[First contact (science fiction)|first contact]] with the Founders, the [[Obsidian Order]] – a covert [[Cardassian]] intelligence force – ally themselves with the [[Tal Shiar]], their [[Romulan]] counterpart, and launch a secret, pre-emptive strike to destroy the Founders' homeworld, hoping that the Founders and the rest of the Dominion will collapse. The Dominion successfully lure the fleets of the Tal Shiar and the Obsidian Order into a trap, eliminating both organizations. The plot establishes an atmosphere of suspicion amongst the Alpha Quadrant powers, initiated by the shapeshifters' abilities to assume other identities, which forms the basis of plots for Season Four.&lt;ref name=&quot;The Die is Cast&quot;&gt;{{cite episode|title=The Die is Cast|url=http://www.startrek.com/database_article/die-is-cast-the|series=Star Trek: Deep Space Nine|serieslink=Star Trek: Deep Space Nine|credits=Writer: [[Ronald D. Moore]]. Creators: [[Rick Berman]] and [[Michael Piller]]|network=[[UPN]]|airdate=1995-05-01}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The Season Three finale turned out to differ significantly from the production staff's conceptual vision. [[Paramount Television|Paramount]] did not favor the idea of a season-end [[cliffhanger]] which would have revealed the presence of shapeshifters on Earth. To continue the theme of paranoia about shapeshifters and the Dominion, &quot;[[The Adversary (Star Trek: Deep Space Nine)|The Adversary]]&quot; was instead scripted to set up a hunt for a Founder aboard the ''Defiant'', incorporating some narrative elements at first intended to commence Season Four, while offering a more self-contained plot and using existing sets to reduce production costs.&lt;ref name=&quot;Deep Space Nine Companionp250&quot;&gt;{{cite book|last1=Erdmann|first1=Terry|last2=Block|first2=Paula|title=The Star Trek: Deep Space Nine Companion|publisher=Pocket Books, Simon &amp; Schuster Inc|location=New York City|year=2000|page=250|isbn=1-0671-5010-62}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Season Four: Founder infiltration and political destabilization===
[[Rick Berman]], [[Robert Hewitt Wolfe]] and [[Ira Steven Behr]] originally expected to open Season Four with the two-part adventure, postponed from the end of Season Three, that ultimately became &quot;[[Homefront (Star Trek: Deep Space Nine)|Homefront]]&quot; and &quot;[[Paradise Lost (Star Trek: Deep Space Nine)|Paradise Lost]]&quot;. [[Paramount Television|Paramount]] determined that the writers needed to come up with a much different opener to satisfy the audience, but without giving specific instructions. The production staff decided to begin a plotline based around suspicions between the Federation and the [[Klingons]], finally leading to conflict between the former allies, which was inspired by a line from the Season Three episode &quot;[[The Die is Cast (Star Trek: Deep Space Nine)|The Die is Cast]]&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;Deep Space Nine Companionpp255-256a&quot;&gt;{{cite book|last1=Erdmann|first1=Terry|last2=Block|first2=Paula|title=The Star Trek: Deep Space Nine Companion|publisher=Pocket Books, Simon &amp; Schuster Inc|location=New York City|year=2000|pages=255–6|isbn=1-0671-5010-62}} [[Ira Steven Behr]]: &quot;A shapeshifter in that episode says something like, 'In the future, all we have to worry about is the Klingons and the Federation, and that won't be for much longer.' I'd said to Ron at the time, 'You know, we could do a whole show about that ...' But the earth didn't move. Nothing shook.&quot;&lt;/ref&gt; With the Klingons set to reappear, Berman suggested the return of a character from ''[[Star Trek: The Next Generation]]'' – the Klingon [[Worf]] – as a permanent officer aboard [[Deep Space Nine (space station)|Deep Space Nine]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Deep Space Nine Companionpp255-256&quot;&gt;{{cite book|last1=Erdmann|first1=Terry|last2=Block|first2=Paula|title=The Star Trek: Deep Space Nine Companion|publisher=Pocket Books, Simon &amp; Schuster Inc|location=New York City|year=2000|pages=255–6|isbn=1-0671-5010-62}} [[Ira Steven Behr]]: &quot;Rick [Berman] said, 'The Klingons – that's the way to go. Everyone loves the Klingons. And if we bring in the Klingons, why don't we bring back Worf?'&quot;&lt;/ref&gt; While both the new plot and character offered interesting possibilities, the producers felt that their vision for ''[[Star Trek: Deep Space Nine]]'' was put off-course for almost one year.&lt;ref name=&quot;Deep Space Nine Companionp256&quot;&gt;{{cite book|last1=Erdmann|first1=Terry|last2=Block|first2=Paula|title=The Star Trek: Deep Space Nine Companion|publisher=Pocket Books, Simon &amp; Schuster Inc|location=New York City|year=2000|page=256|isbn=1-0671-5010-62}} [[Ira Steven Behr]]: &quot;We only recovered our equilibrium in the middle of the fifth season, following another meeting with the studio in which we said, 'How about making the Klingons our friends again? You'll see them as much as you want, but we want to get back to the Dominion.' While I like having brought Worf onto the show ... I think it had a fairly substantial impact ... It took us way off from where we'd intended to go and it was slow going getting back.&quot;&lt;/ref&gt;

Season Four begins with &quot;[[The Way of the Warrior (Star Trek: Deep Space Nine)|The Way of the Warrior]]&quot;, which marks the arrival of Worf. This episode is one of a few in this season to explore themes of suspicion and paranoia, and their effect upon societies and relationships, building up to &quot;Homefront&quot; and &quot;Paradise Lost&quot;. After the events of &quot;The Die is Cast&quot;, fear about the identities of the infiltrator [[Changeling (Star Trek)|shapeshifters]] leads the Klingons to suspect Dominion involvement in the new [[Cardassian]] civilian government. Their refusal to break off an invasion, even after Dominion involvement has been disproved, results in a military confrontation and diplomatic breakdown, and the Klingons attempt to seize Deep Space Nine. This seems to further the Founders' goal of the destabilization of the [[Alpha Quadrant]] as a prelude to their own invasion.&lt;ref name=&quot;The Way of the Warrior&quot;&gt;{{cite episode|title=The Way of the Warrior|url=http://www.startrek.com/database_article/way-of-the-warrior-the-part-i|series=Star Trek: Deep Space Nine|serieslink=Star Trek: Deep Space Nine|credits=Story: [[Ira Steven Behr]] and [[Robert Hewitt Wolfe]]. Creators: [[Rick Berman]] and [[Michael Piller]]|network=[[UPN]]|airdate=1995-10-02}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In &quot;[[Hippocratic Oath (Star Trek: Deep Space Nine)|Hippocratic Oath]]&quot;, the characters of [[Julian Bashir|Dr. Bashir]] and [[Miles O'Brien (Star Trek)|Chief O'Brien]] debate curing a group of [[Jem'Hadar]] soldiers of an addiction in the hope that they will rebel against the Dominion. There is discussion about the identity of the true enemy, the limits of duty, and whether soldiers are responsible for the actions of their leaders.&lt;ref name=&quot;Hippocratic Oath&quot;&gt;{{cite episode|title=Hippocratic Oath|url=http://www.startrek.com/database_article/hippocratic-oath|series=Star Trek: Deep Space Nine|serieslink=Star Trek: Deep Space Nine|credits=Writer: Lisa Klink. Story: Lisa Klink and [[Nicholas J. Corea]]. Creators: [[Rick Berman]] and [[Michael Piller]]|network=[[UPN]]|airdate=1995-10-16}}&lt;/ref&gt; &quot;[[To the Death (Star Trek: Deep Space Nine)|To the Death]]&quot; further investigates the themes of soldier duty and loyalty, and contrasts the opposing rules of discipline that regulate [[Starfleet]] officers and Jem'Hadar troops. In addition, this episode introduced the Vorta representative [[Weyoun]], who would become the most prominent Vorta in the rest of the series.&lt;ref name=&quot;To the Death&quot;&gt;{{cite episode|title=To the Death|url=http://www.startrek.com/database_article/to-the-death|series=Star Trek: Deep Space Nine|serieslink=Star Trek: Deep Space Nine|credits=Story: [[Ira Steven Behr]] and [[Robert Hewitt Wolfe]]. Creators: [[Rick Berman]] and [[Michael Piller]]|network=[[UPN]]|airdate=1996-05-13}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In &quot;Homefront&quot;, the mistrust generated by the shapeshifters continues, with [[Benjamin Sisko|Commander Sisko]] suspecting his own father and recommending a [[state of emergency]] be declared on Earth.&lt;ref name=&quot;Homefront&quot;&gt;{{cite episode|title=Homefront|url=http://www.startrek.com/database_article/homefront|series=Star Trek: Deep Space Nine|serieslink=Star Trek: Deep Space Nine|credits=Story: [[Ira Steven Behr]] and [[Robert Hewitt Wolfe]]. Creators: [[Rick Berman]] and [[Michael Piller]]|network=[[UPN]]|airdate=1996-01-01}}&lt;/ref&gt; In &quot;Paradise Lost&quot;, some Starfleet officers go further and attempt to implement a ''[[coup d'état]]'' against the President of the [[United Federation of Planets|Federation]] after it is revealed that shapeshifters have infiltrated Earth and committed a terrorist attack. This leads to an armed conflict between Starfleet vessels for the first time in a century, according to the [[Timeline of Star Trek|''Star Trek'' in-universe timeline]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Paradise Lost&quot;&gt;{{cite episode|title=Paradise Lost|url=http://www.startrek.com/database_article/paradise-lost|series=Star Trek: Deep Space Nine|serieslink=Star Trek: Deep Space Nine|credits=Story: [[Ira Steven Behr]] and [[Robert Hewitt Wolfe]]. Creators: [[Rick Berman]] and [[Michael Piller]]|network=[[UPN]]|airdate=1996-01-08}}&lt;/ref&gt; Sisko is able to force Admiral Leyton to abandon his efforts to impose [[martial law]] by telling him, &quot;You're fighting the wrong war!&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.twiztv.com/scripts/ds9/season4/ds9-412.txt|archiveurl=http://web.archive.org/web/20050830191727/http://www.twiztv.com/scripts/ds9/season4/ds9-412.txt|archivedate= May 2, 2008|title=Script for &quot;Paradise Lost&quot;|publisher=twiztv.com|month=November|year=1995|accessdate=May 6, 2010}} Act 5, Scene 50. Writers: [[Ira Steven Behr]] and [[Robert Hewitt Wolfe]]. Story: [[Ronald D. Moore]]. Revised November 14, 1995. Leyton: &quot;It's not over! I have enough loyal officers to make a fight of it!&quot; Sisko: &quot;Who will you fight? Starfleet? The Federation? Don't you see, Admiral! You're fighting the wrong war! And as for your loyal officers, Benteen's already abandoned you. And she was closer to you than anyone. You've lost! Don't make anyone else pay for your mistakes.&quot; Leyton: &quot;I hope ... you're not the one making the mistake.&quot;&lt;/ref&gt; Behr's favorite line from the episode is &quot;[[Paradise]] never seemed so well-armed&quot;, highlighting one of many occasions when ''Deep Space Nine'' would point out the practical issues revolving around maintaining the peaceful culture of the Federation, and the moral or immoral choices made to achieve this ideal.&lt;ref name=&quot;Deep Space Nine Companionp303&quot;&gt;{{cite book|last1=Erdmann|first1=Terry|last2=Block|first2=Paula|title=The Star Trek: Deep Space Nine Companion|publisher=Pocket Books, Simon &amp; Schuster Inc|location=New York City|year=2000|page=303|isbn=1-0671-5010-62}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Season Five: build-up to all-out war===
In the fifth season, the [[Dominion (Star Trek)|Dominion]] invasion of the [[Alpha Quadrant]] gathers pace, appearing in episodes such as &quot;[[Apocalypse Rising]]&quot;, &quot;[[In Purgatory's Shadow]]&quot;, &quot;[[By Inferno's Light]]&quot;, and &quot;[[Blaze of Glory (Star Trek: Deep Space Nine)|Blaze of Glory]]&quot;. [[Robert Hewitt Wolfe]] and [[Ira Steven Behr]] were again responsible for the major Season Five episodes concerning the Dominion.&lt;ref name=&quot;In Purgatory's Shadow&quot;&gt;{{cite episode|title=In Purgatory's Shadow|url=http://www.startrek.com/database_article/in-purgatorys-shadow|series=Star Trek: Deep Space Nine|serieslink=Star Trek: Deep Space Nine|credits=Writers: [[Ira Steven Behr]] and [[Robert Hewitt Wolfe]]. Creators: [[Rick Berman]] and [[Michael Piller]]|network=[[UPN]]|airdate=1997-02-10}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;By Inferno's Light&quot;&gt;{{cite episode|title=By Inferno's Light|url=http://www.startrek.com/database_article/by-infernos-light|series=Star Trek: Deep Space Nine|serieslink=Star Trek: Deep Space Nine|credits=Story: [[Ira Steven Behr]] and [[Robert Hewitt Wolfe]]. Creators: [[Rick Berman]] and [[Michael Piller]]|network=[[UPN]]|airdate=1997-02-17}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Blaze of Glory&quot;&gt;{{cite episode|title=Blaze of Glory|url=http://www.startrek.com/database_article/blaze-of-glory|series=Star Trek: Deep Space Nine|serieslink=Star Trek: Deep Space Nine|credits=Story: [[Ira Steven Behr]] and [[Robert Hewitt Wolfe]]. Creators: [[Rick Berman]] and [[Michael Piller]]|network=[[UPN]]|airdate=1997-05-12}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Call to Arms&quot;&gt;{{cite episode|title=Call to Arms|url=http://www.startrek.com/database_article/call-to-arms|series=Star Trek: Deep Space Nine|serieslink=Star Trek: Deep Space Nine|credits=Story: [[Ira Steven Behr]] and [[Robert Hewitt Wolfe]]. Creators: [[Rick Berman]] and [[Michael Piller]]|network=[[UPN]]|airdate=1997-06-16}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In the Season Five opener, &quot;Apocalypse Rising&quot;, [[Odo (Star Trek)|Odo]] discovers that his race are capable of deceiving their own kind as well as &quot;solids&quot; when he is led to believe that Klingon Chancellor [[Gowron]] is a [[Changeling (Star Trek)|Changeling]] instead of the General, [[Martok]]. This plot was planned to shift the focus of ''[[Star Trek: Deep Space Nine]]'' episodes back toward the struggle with the Dominion, which had been postponed in earlier production discussions with [[Paramount Television|Paramount]] in favor of bringing [[Worf]] and a [[Klingon]]-based plotline into the series.&lt;ref name=&quot;Deep Space Nine Companionp359&quot;&gt;{{cite book|last1=Erdmann|first1=Terry|last2=Block|first2=Paula|title=The Star Trek: Deep Space Nine Companion|publisher=Pocket Books, Simon &amp; Schuster Inc|location=New York City|year=2000|page=359|isbn=1-0671-5010-62}} [[Ira Steven Behr]]: &quot;Season Four threw us for a loop, with the whole Klingon thing, and bringing Worf into the show. So the seminal thing about our fifth season opener was that we wanted to get back on the track we'd anticipated being on a year earlier. We were moving back toward making the shapeshifters and the Dominion our enemies. Not the Klingons. I didn't want to have the Klingons as our enemies ... We wanted to let people know that we didn't switch horse in midstream. So &quot;Apocalypse Rising&quot; was an important episode. By having that shapeshifter in there, we were saying, 'Season Four wasn't a mistake. It wasn't the Klingons turning against us. There was a shapeshifter behind it all along.' And that's why we had to do that episode.&quot;&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Apocalypse Rising&quot;&gt;{{cite episode|title=Apocalypse Rising|url=http://www.startrek.com/database_article/apocalypse-rising|series=Star Trek: Deep Space Nine|serieslink=Star Trek: Deep Space Nine|credits=Story: [[Ira Steven Behr]] and [[Robert Hewitt Wolfe]]. Creators: [[Rick Berman]] and [[Michael Piller]]|network=[[UPN]]|airdate=1996-09-30}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In &quot;In Purgatory's Shadow&quot;, it is discovered that [[Julian Bashir|Dr. Bashir]] has been kidnapped, imprisoned for weeks and in the interim replaced by a Changeling. The [[shapeshifter]] double sabotages efforts to close the Wormhole, and attempts to destroy the Bajoran sun, leaving the path open for Dominion fleets to enter the Alpha Quadrant.&lt;ref name=&quot;In Purgatory's Shadow&quot;/&gt; In the following episode, &quot;By Inferno's Light&quot;, the [[Cardassian]]s become a member of the Dominion, and the [[United Federation of Planets|Federation]] and Klingon Empire resolve to cast aside their mutual distrust and unite against the common threat. A garrison of Klingon troops is stationed on [[Deep Space Nine (space station)|Deep Space Nine]], under the command of the real General [[Martok]], rescued from Dominion incarceration with Bashir.&lt;ref name=&quot;By Inferno's Light&quot;/&gt; In &quot;Blaze of Glory&quot;, the characters confront the issue of [[ethnic cleansing]] when the [[Maquis (Star Trek)|Maquis]] – a resistance group of former Federation citizens now living in Cardassian space – are hunted down and ask for the assistance of [[Benjamin Sisko|Sisko]], who used to criticize their methods.&lt;ref name=&quot;Blaze of Glory&quot;/&gt;

The Season Five finale, &quot;[[Call to Arms (Star Trek: Deep Space Nine)|Call to Arms]]&quot;, sets the scene for the commencement of full-scale war between the Dominion and the Federation during the final two seasons of ''Deep Space Nine''. When the Dominion begins to send ships through the Wormhole, the Alpha Quadrant allies build a minefield at its mouth to cut off the supply line. The plot considers whether it is better for the planet [[Bajor]] to stand with their Federation friends or remain neutral in the coming war to protect themselves. Sisko persuades them that [[Neutrality (international relations)|neutrality]] is the favorable course.&lt;ref name=&quot;Call to Arms&quot;/&gt;

===Season Six: the war rages===
Season Six, charting the turmoil of the Dominion War, faces themes of the moral dilemmas of conflict. New plot elements permitted ''[[Star Trek: Deep Space Nine]]'' to examine themes in a manner unlike preceding ''[[Star Trek]]'' productions, as characters are forced to re-evaluate their beliefs. The production staff resolved to start the season with a six-episode arc, the first attempted in the history of the ''Star Trek'' franchise.

[[Rick Berman]] originally pictured that the Dominion War would last for a limited number of episodes before a prompt resolution.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://memory-alpha.org/wiki/A_Time_to_Stand_(episode)|title=Interview with Ronald D. Moore about &quot;A Time to Stand&quot; for Memory Alpha|publisher=memory-alpha.org|accessdate=April 23, 2010}}: &quot;The initial thinking was that we would end Season Five on a cliffhanger with the Federation plunged into war, and then we would come back and do a multi-episode arc, and the war would last that long.&quot;&lt;/ref&gt; Planning the arc, [[Ira Steven Behr]], [[Ronald D. Moore]] and the writers conceived a longer chain of first five, then six connected episodes, stretching from &quot;[[A Time to Stand]]&quot; to &quot;[[Sacrifice of Angels (Star Trek: Deep Space Nine)|Sacrifice of Angels]]&quot;, as themes increased demands for greater narrative development.&lt;ref name=&quot;Deep Space Nine Companionp475-6&quot;&gt;{{cite book|last1=Erdmann|first1=Terry|last2=Block|first2=Paula|title=The Star Trek: Deep Space Nine Companion|publisher=Pocket Books, Simon &amp; Schuster Inc|location=New York City|year=2000|pages=475–6|isbn=1-0671-5010-62}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Deep Space Nine Companionp494&quot;&gt;{{cite book|last1=Erdmann|first1=Terry|last2=Block|first2=Paula|title=The Star Trek: Deep Space Nine Companion|publisher=Pocket Books, Simon &amp; Schuster Inc|location=New York City|year=2000|page=494|isbn=1-0671-5010-62}}&lt;/ref&gt; No writer had previously contributed to a series involving arcs of such length, and Moore, Behr and novice scripting partner, supervising producer [[Hans Beimler (screenwriter)|Hans Beimler]], have all stated that the writing process changed as a result, with more production collaboration and interaction than for earlier seasons of ''Deep Space Nine''.&lt;ref name=&quot;Deep Space Nine Companionp476a&quot;&gt;{{cite book|last1=Erdmann|first1=Terry|last2=Block|first2=Paula|title=The Star Trek: Deep Space Nine Companion|publisher=Pocket Books, Simon &amp; Schuster Inc|location=New York City|year=2000|page=476|isbn=1-0671-5010-62}} [[Ronald D. Moore]]: &quot;We broke the six episodes together, but as everybody went off and worked on writing them, things would start to change or shift. It became a much more interactive process than it ever had been before. Because each detail had a domino effect. We'd had that happen before, to a certain extent, but we'd never done this many episodes with this many continuing storylines as a single piece. We weren't used to the rhythm. It was definitely challenging!&quot;&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Deep Space Nine Companionp486a&quot;&gt;{{cite book|last1=Erdmann|first1=Terry|last2=Block|first2=Paula|title=The Star Trek: Deep Space Nine Companion|publisher=Pocket Books, Simon &amp; Schuster Inc|location=New York City|year=2000|page=486|isbn=1-0671-5010-62}} [[Hans Beimler (screenwriter)|Hans Beimler]]: &quot;It changed the dynamic of the way we work and it changed the kind of involvement that everybody had. Because René Echevarria or Ronald D. Moore would go away to work on an episode, and discover something in the writing process that was going to change everybody else's script. One of them would be coming back all the time saying, 'You know what guys? We need to re-think.' And then we'd call in all the troops and re-think the storyline.&quot;&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Deep Space Nine Companionp486b&quot;&gt;{{cite book|last1=Erdmann|first1=Terry|last2=Block|first2=Paula|title=The Star Trek: Deep Space Nine Companion|publisher=Pocket Books, Simon &amp; Schuster Inc|location=New York City|year=2000|page=486|isbn=1-0671-5010-62}} [[Ira Steven Behr]]: &quot;The guys were coming in saying, 'What are you writing?' 'Are we gonna do this?' 'Where's Kira at right now?' 'What's Odo doing?' There were a lot of phone calls, a lot of running into each other's offices, a lot of 'Should this go before this?' and 'Wait a second – does this track?' The fact is, the show isn't geared to work like that.&quot;&lt;/ref&gt; The potential for serialization that [[Rick Berman]] had perceived from the start of ''Deep Space Nine'' came to fruition as a result of the multiple plotlines accumulating to form the Dominion War.&lt;ref name=&quot;Deep Space Nine Companionp475-6&quot;/&gt;

The return of [[Gul Dukat]] as commander of the Dominion-controlled [[Deep Space Nine (space station)|Deep Space Nine]] enabled the writers to contrast the space station of the audience's imagination to its incarnation as a former [[Cardassian]] mining facility. Former resistance fighter [[Major Kira]] is portrayed re-considering her ethical code as she sets out on the path to collaboration in &quot;[[Rocks and Shoals (Star Trek: Deep Space Nine)|Rocks and Shoals]]&quot;, but the suicide of a [[Bajoran]] monk reminds her of the reality of her situation. Through &quot;Rocks and Shoals&quot;, ''Deep Space Nine'' also revisits themes of the war conduct as [[Benjamin Sisko|Sisko]] considers the morality of ambushing soldiers whom superiors have forsaken, only for events to force his hand.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite episode|title=Rocks and Shoals|url=http://www.startrek.com/database_article/who-mourns-for-morn|series=Star Trek: Deep Space Nine|serieslink=Star Trek: Deep Space Nine|credits=Writer: [[Ronald D. Moore]]. Creators: [[Rick Berman]] and [[Michael Piller]]|network=[[UPN]]|airdate=1997-10-06}}&lt;/ref&gt; In &quot;[[A Time to Stand]]&quot; and &quot;[[Behind the Lines (Star Trek: Deep Space Nine)|Behind the Lines]]&quot;, the character of [[Odo (Star Trek)|Odo]] is torn between the trust placed in him by Kira and the [[Bajoran]]s, and his status as a [[Changeling (Star Trek)|Founder]], when he joins Deep Space Nine's Dominion council and then neglects to help his comrades at a critical moment.

Fortune is reversed again in Season Six as [[Starfleet]] re-captures Deep Space Nine in the closing episodes of the opening arc, &quot;[[Favor the Bold]]&quot; and &quot;Sacrifice of Angels&quot;. The [[USS Defiant|USS ''Defiant'']] stands alone in an attempt to hold back thousands of Dominion ships entering through the Wormhole. An intervention from the [[Wormhole Prophets]], considered gods by the Bajorans, leads characters to ponder questions of faith and destiny.&lt;ref name=&quot;Sacrifice of Angels&quot;&gt;{{cite episode|title=Sacrifice of Angels|url=http://www.startrek.com/database_article/sacrifice-of-angels|series=Star Trek: Deep Space Nine|serieslink=Star Trek: Deep Space Nine|credits=Writers: [[Ira Steven Behr]] and [[Hans Beimler (screenwriter)|Hans Beimler]]. Creators: [[Rick Berman]] and [[Michael Piller]]|network=[[UPN]]|airdate=1997-11-03}}&lt;/ref&gt; Writer [[Hans Beimler (screenwriter)|Hans Beimler]] wished to include mythological allusions, stating, &quot;It's tragic hero stuff. A hero [Sisko] takes on things for others, but doesn't necessarily find any peace himself in the result.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;Deep Space Nine Companionp495&quot;&gt;{{cite book|last1=Erdmann|first1=Terry|last2=Block|first2=Paula|title=The Star Trek: Deep Space Nine Companion|publisher=Pocket Books, Simon &amp; Schuster Inc|location=New York City|year=2000|page=495|isbn=1-0671-5010-62}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Ira Steven Behr]] compares Sisko to the Biblical figure, [[Moses]], who fails to reach the [[Promised Land]], and to the character of Ethan Edwards from the 1956 [[Western (genre)|Western]] film, ''[[The Searchers (film)|The Searchers]]'', who neglects to return to his family once his task is complete.&lt;ref name=&quot;Deep Space Nine Companionp495&quot;/&gt; It was determined that this facet to Sisko's character justified the use of divine intervention to resolve the Dominion threat:&lt;ref name=&quot;Deep Space Nine Companionp495a&quot;&gt;{{cite book|last1=Erdmann|first1=Terry|last2=Block|first2=Paula|title=The Star Trek: Deep Space Nine Companion|publisher=Pocket Books, Simon &amp; Schuster Inc|location=New York City|year=2000|page=495|isbn=1-0671-5010-62}} [[Ira Steven Behr]]: &quot;... They [the Prophets] wouldn't have done this for just anyone. This was the man going out into the wilderness and demanding his god to interfere, to do something, for crying out loud. The corporeal characters had done so much in this episode; surely, they'd earned the help of the gods.&quot;&lt;/ref&gt; the fleet disappears and the Federation regains control of Deep Space Nine. The defeat costs Dukat his mental health, the life of his daughter, [[Tora Ziyal]], and his status as Cardassian leader. Dukat is the first but not the only character in Season Six to face the pain of loss in conflict. Later, in the season six finale [[Tears of the Prophets]], [[Worf]] loses his wife [[Jadzia Dax]] when she is killed by Dukat.

Although themes of death are apparent in ''Deep Space Nine''&lt;nowiki&gt;'&lt;/nowiki&gt;s previous seasons, &quot;[[Far Beyond the Stars]]&quot; details how Sisko copes with the loss of a friend on a deeper psychological level. Experiencing visions of himself confronting racial discrimination against Black Americans in the 1950s, Sisko interprets useful parallels connected to his life on Deep Space Nine.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite episode|title=Far Beyond the Stars|url=http://www.startrek.com/database_article/far-beyond-the-stars|series=Star Trek: Deep Space Nine|serieslink=Star Trek: Deep Space Nine|credits=Writers: [[Ira Steven Behr]] and [[Hans Beimler (screenwriter)|Hans Beimler]]. Story: [[Marc Scott Zicree]]. Creators: [[Rick Berman]] and [[Michael Piller]]|network=[[UPN]]|airdate=1998-11-02}}&lt;/ref&gt; Sisko's response to the death toll of the Dominion War is re-examined in &quot;[[In the Pale Moonlight]]&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;In the Pale Moonlight&quot;/&gt;

Additionally, Season Six introduces [[Section 31]], a secret organization dedicated to preserving the Federation's principles regardless of the cost and legitimacy of its methods. In &quot;[[Inquisition (Star Trek: Deep Space Nine)|Inquisition]]&quot;, the character of [[Julian Bashir|Dr. Bashir]] refuses to join Section 31 and reports its actions, but still ponders its significance: &quot;But what would that say about us? That we're no different than our enemies? That when push comes to shove, we're willing to throw away our principles in order to survive?&quot; Sisko replies, &quot;I wish I had an answer for you.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite episode|title=Inquisition|url=http://www.startrek.com/database_article/inquisition|series=Star Trek: Deep Space Nine|serieslink=Star Trek: Deep Space Nine|credits=Writers: [[Bradley Thompson]] and [[David Weddle]] Creators: [[Rick Berman]] and [[Michael Piller]]|network=[[UPN]]|airdate=1998-04-08}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.twiztv.com/scripts/ds9/season6/ds9-618.txt|archiveurl= http://web.archive.org/web/20080502203321/http://www.twiztv.com/scripts/ds9/season6/ds9-618.txt|archivedate = May 2008|title=Script for &quot;Inquisition&quot;|publisher=twiztv.com|accessdate=May 6, 2010}} Act Five, Scene 43. Writers: [[Bradley Thompson]] and [[David Weddle]]. January 14, 1998. Revised January 29, 1998. Bashir: &quot;I can't believe the Federation condones this kind of activity.&quot; Odo: &quot;Personally, I find it hard to believe they wouldn't. Every other great power has a unit like Section 31. The Romulans have the Tal Shiar, the Cardassians had the Obsidian Order ...&quot; Bashir: &quot;But what does that say about us? When push comes to shove, are we willing to sacrifice our principles in order to survive?&quot; Sisko: &quot;I wish I had an answer for you, Doctor.&quot;&lt;/ref&gt;

&quot;In the Pale Moonlight&quot; considers a similar moral dilemma when the Dominion captures an important Federation planet, [[Betazed]], in a surprise attack. The subjugation of a planet familiar to the audience was used to heighten the sense of danger and the stakes for the characters.&lt;ref name=&quot;Deep Space Nine Companionp557&quot;&gt;{{cite book|last1=Erdmann|first1=Terry|last2=Block|first2=Paula|title=The Star Trek: Deep Space Nine Companion|publisher=Pocket Books, Simon &amp; Schuster Inc|location=New York City|year=2000|page=557|isbn=1-0671-5010-62}} [[Ronald D. Moore]]: &quot;We wanted a moment that would really galvanize Sisko ... so we needed to have a familiar world fall [in the war] ...&quot;&lt;/ref&gt; In this episode, Sisko fuels a conspiracy intended to improve the war situation that ultimately results in the character of [[Elim Garak]] committing murder. In the context of the Dominion War, it is resolved to conceal the truth for the greater good.&lt;ref name=&quot;In the Pale Moonlight&quot;&gt;{{cite episode|title=In the Pale Moonlight|url=http://www.startrek.com/database_article/in-the-pale-moonlight|series=Star Trek: Deep Space Nine|serieslink=Star Trek: Deep Space Nine|credits=Writers: [[Michael Taylor (screenwriter)|Michael Taylor]], [[Peter Allan Fields]] and [[Ronald D. Moore]]. Creators: [[Rick Berman]] and [[Michael Piller]]|network=[[UPN]]|airdate=1998-04-15}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.twiztv.com/scripts/ds9/season7/ds9-724.txt|archiveurl= http://web.archive.org/web/20080502203512/http://www.twiztv.com/scripts/ds9/season7/ds9-724.txt|archivedate= May 2, 2008|title=Script for &quot;In the Pale Moonlight&quot;|publisher=twiztv.com|accessdate=May 6, 2010}} Act Five, Scene 45. Writer: [[Michael Taylor (screenwriter)|Michael Taylor]]. Uncredited contribution: [[Ronald D. Moore]]. Story: [[Peter Allan Fields]]. January 26, 1998. Revised February 11, 1998. Sisko: &quot;So ... I lied. I cheated. I bribed men to cover the crimes of other men. I am an accessory to murder. But the most damning thing of all ... I think I can live with it. And if I had to do it all over again, I would. Garak was right about one thing, a guilty conscience is a small price to pay for the safety of the Alpha Quadrant. So I will learn to live with it. Because I can live with it. I can live with it ...&quot;&lt;/ref&gt; Writer [[Michael Taylor (screenwriter)|Michael Taylor]] has suggested, &quot;It showed how ''Deep Space Nine'' could really stretch the ''Star Trek'' formula. It pushes the boundaries in a realistic way, because the decisions Sisko makes are the kinds of decisions that have to be made in war. They're for the greater good.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;Deep Space Nine Companion&quot;/&gt;

===Season Seven: end of the war===
Season Seven charts further dilemmas of conflict. Following the example of Season Six, the writers considered using an arc to conclude the multiple Dominion War threads in satisfying fashion, deciding that ''[[Star Trek: Deep Space Nine]]'' could not be concluded in one or two episodes alone.&lt;ref&gt;Interview with [[Hans Beimler (screenwriter)|Hans Beimler]], ''[[Star Trek: Deep Space Nine Companion]]'', Pocket Books, 2000: &quot;It showed us the possibilities and the excitement that could be garnered, and in the end, we liked it so much that we decided to do the ten-episode arc at the end of the series.&quot;&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Deep Space Nine Companionp592b&quot;&gt;{{cite book|last1=Erdmann|first1=Terry|last2=Block|first2=Paula|title=The Star Trek: Deep Space Nine Companion|publisher=Pocket Books, Simon &amp; Schuster Inc|location=New York City|year=2000|page=592|isbn=1-0671-5010-62}} [[Rick Berman]]: &quot;So rather than tie up every thread in the few hours, we thought, 'Why not look at the last third of the season as a continuing, building conclusion to the seven-year story?'&quot;&lt;/ref&gt; A ten-episode arc was outlined to end Season Seven, the Dominion War, and all of ''Deep Space Nine'', and more alterations were made as scripting progressed.&lt;ref name=&quot;Deep Space Nine Companionp591-592&quot;&gt;{{cite book|last1=Erdmann|first1=Terry|last2=Block|first2=Paula|title=The Star Trek: Deep Space Nine Companion|publisher=Pocket Books, Simon &amp; Schuster Inc|location=New York City|year=2000|pages=591–2|isbn=1-0671-5010-62}} [[Ira Steven Behr]]: &quot;The show wasn't geared to be what we kept turning it into ... We had to kind of do it and hope it was going to work out ... So we didn't lay it out at the beginning of the year. We planned then as we were doing them. That allowed us to find great stuff, but occasionally it put us into situations where we were saying to each other, 'Well, what do you want to do with —?' 'I dunno, what do you want to do with them?'&quot;&lt;/ref&gt;

Characters face issues of [[genocide]]: in &quot;[[Treachery, Faith, and the Great River (Star Trek: Deep Space Nine)|Treachery, Faith, and the Great River]]&quot;, Constable [[Odo (Star Trek)|Odo]] learns of the engineered virus that the Federation has disseminated among the Founders,&lt;ref name=&quot;Treachery, Faith, and the Great River&quot;&gt;{{cite episode|title=Treachery, Faith, and the Great River|url=http://www.startrek.com/database_article/treachery-faith-and-the-great-river|series=Star Trek: Deep Space Nine|serieslink=Star Trek: Deep Space Nine|credits=Writers: [[David Weddle]] and [[Bradley Thompson]]. Story: Phillip Kim. Creators: [[Rick Berman]] and [[Michael Piller]]|network=[[UPN]]|airdate=1998-11-22}}&lt;/ref&gt; and in &quot;[[When It Rains...]]&quot; that [[Section 31]] has infected him to communicate the disease.&lt;ref name=&quot;When It Rains...&quot;/&gt; While [[Julian Bashir|Dr. Bashir]] supports providing the Founders with a cure, others are unconvinced.

Another opponent reveals itself in the [[Breen (Star Trek)|Breen]]-[[Dominion (Star Trek)|Dominion]] pact enacted in &quot;[['Til Death Do Us Part (Star Trek: Deep Space Nine)|'Til Death Do Us Part]]&quot;. For &quot;[[The Changing Face of Evil]]&quot;, writers [[Ira Steven Behr]] and [[Hans Beimler (screenwriter)|Hans Beimler]] scripted a second strike against the [[United Federation of Planets|Federation]] through a Breen assault on Earth which sees the destruction of the [[USS Defiant|USS ''Defiant'']]. [[Ronald D. Moore]] has stated, &quot;We wanted to kill the ''Defiant'' as a statement on how tough the Breen were. We thought that would rock the characters and the audience.&quot; Behr explains that, &quot;... the ship had become a character that had caught on in people's hearts and minds ... when the ''Defiant'' went down, that hurt.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;Deep Space Nine Companionp689-690&quot;&gt;{{cite book|last1=Erdmann|first1=Terry|last2=Block|first2=Paula|title=The Star Trek: Deep Space Nine Companion|publisher=Pocket Books, Simon &amp; Schuster Inc|location=New York City|year=2000|pages=689–690|isbn=1-0671-5010-62}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Deep Space Nine Companionp693&quot;&gt;{{cite book|last1=Erdmann|first1=Terry|last2=Block|first2=Paula|title=The Star Trek: Deep Space Nine Companion|publisher=Pocket Books, Simon &amp; Schuster Inc|location=New York City|year=2000|page=693|isbn=1-0671-5010-62}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The resurgence in the conflict provided opportunities to introduce problems such as post-conflict [[psychological trauma]] in &quot;[[The Siege of AR-558]]&quot;,&lt;ref name=&quot;The Siege of AR-558&quot;&gt;{{cite episode|title=The Siege of AR-558|url=http://www.startrek.com/database_article/siege-of-ar-558|series=Star Trek: Deep Space Nine|serieslink=Star Trek: Deep Space Nine|credits=Writers: [[Ira Steven Behr]] and [[Hans Beimler (screenwriter)|Hans Beimler]]. Creators: [[Rick Berman]] and [[Michael Piller]]|network=[[UPN]]|airdate=1998-11-18}}&lt;/ref&gt; and injury when the character of [[Nog (Star Trek)|Nog]] undergoes leg [[amputation]] in &quot;[[It's Only a Paper Moon (Star Trek: Deep Space Nine)|It's Only a Paper Moon]]&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;It's Only a Paper Moon&quot;&gt;{{cite episode|title=It's Only a Paper Moon|url=http://www.startrek.com/database_article/its-only-a-paper-moon|series=Star Trek: Deep Space Nine|serieslink=Star Trek: Deep Space Nine|credits=Writer: [[Ronald D. Moore]]. Story: [[David Alan Mack]] and [[John J. Ordover]]. Creators: [[Rick Berman]] and [[Michael Piller]]|network=[[UPN]]|airdate=1998-11-30}}&lt;/ref&gt; Moore has said that the plot of this episode was agreed on after an &quot;extended argument&quot; between Behr and ''Deep Space Nine'' creator [[Rick Berman]], and that such discussions were a common occurrence when war casualties were considered.&lt;ref name=&quot;IGN p8&quot;/&gt; Academic Michele Barrett perceives the allusions made to the traumas of [[World War I]].&lt;ref name=HumanFrontierp66p72/&gt;

The concept of resistance is re-opened in the context of [[Cardassia]] rather than [[Bajor]]. [[Legate Damar]] becomes more and more frustrated with the deadlocked conflict and his situation as a Dominion puppet.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.twiztv.com/scripts/ds9/season7/ds9-724.txt|archiveurl= http://web.archive.org/web/20080502203512/http://www.twiztv.com/scripts/ds9/season7/ds9-724.txt|archivedate= May 2, 2008|title=Script for &quot;The Changing Face of Evil&quot;|publisher=twiztv.com|accessdate=May 6, 2010}} Act Five, Scenes 67-71. Writers: [[Hans Beimler (screenwriter)|Hans Beimler]] and [[Ira Steven Behr]]. February 3, 1999. Revised February 23, 1999. Damar: &quot;Seven million of our brave soldiers have given their lives to fulfill our part of the agreement, and what has the Dominion done in return? Nothing. We've gained no new territories. In fact, our influence throughout the quadrant has diminished. And to make matters worse we are no longer masters in our own home. Travel anywhere on Cardassia and what do you find? Jem'Hadar, Vorta, and now Breen. Instead of the invaders we have become the invaded. Our allies have conquered us without firing a single shot. Well, no longer.&quot;&lt;/ref&gt; As Cardassian military losses mount, and Dominion control of Cardassia deepens, he becomes alcoholic and criticizes the Dominion's power. Damar was originally to be revealed as a [[double agent]] for the Federation, but Moore then suggested the slave revolt of [[Spartacus]] as a model.&lt;ref name=&quot;Deep Space Nine Companionp690&quot;&gt;{{cite book|last1=Erdmann|first1=Terry|last2=Block|first2=Paula|title=The Star Trek: Deep Space Nine Companion|publisher=Pocket Books, Simon &amp; Schuster Inc|location=New York City|year=2000|page=690|isbn=1-0671-5010-62}}&lt;/ref&gt; Damar establishes an underground [[resistance movement]], is branded a rebel and goes into hiding. [[Kira Nerys|Kira]], [[Elim Garak|Garak]] and [[Odo (Star Trek)|Odo]] are sent as &quot;technical advisors&quot; to help him in &quot;When It Rains...&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;When It Rains...&quot;&gt;{{cite episode|title=When It Rains...|url=http://www.startrek.com/database_article/when-it-rains|series=Star Trek: Deep Space Nine|serieslink=Star Trek: Deep Space Nine|credits=Writer: [[René Echevarria]]. Story: [[René Echevarria]] and Spike Steingasser. Creators: [[Rick Berman]] and [[Michael Piller]]|network=[[UPN]]|airdate=1999-05-05}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The relationship between Cardassians and [[Bajoran]]s, former enemies turned allies, is charted in &quot;[[Tacking Into the Wind]]&quot;, in which Damar and Kira's group abandon prejudice and collaborate to seize a Breen weapon.&lt;ref name=&quot;Tacking Into the Wind&quot;&gt;{{cite episode|title=Tacking Into the Wind|url=http://www.startrek.com/database_article/tacking-into-the-wind|series=Star Trek: Deep Space Nine|serieslink=Star Trek: Deep Space Nine|credits=Writer: [[Ronald D. Moore]]. Creators: [[Rick Berman]] and [[Michael Piller]]|network=[[UPN]]|airdate=1999-05-12}}&lt;/ref&gt; Continuing into &quot;[[The Dogs of War (Star Trek: Deep Space Nine)|The Dogs of War]]&quot;, Damar is forced to choose between his Cardassian comrades, stubborn in their beliefs, and the support of Kira and others whom he used to consider enemies.&lt;ref&gt;Interview with [[Ira Steven Behr]], ''[[Star Trek: Deep Space Nine Companion]]'', Pocket Books, 2000: &quot;We needed someone [Gul Rusot] who would highlight Damar's strength, by putting Damar in a position where he'd have to hold this tiger by the tail and keep him in line.&quot;&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;The Dogs of War&quot;&gt;{{cite episode|title=The Dogs of War|url=http://www.startrek.com/database_article/dogs-of-war-the|series=Star Trek: Deep Space Nine|serieslink=Star Trek: Deep Space Nine|credits=Writers: [[René Echevarria]] and [[Ronald D. Moore]]. Story: [[Peter Allan Fields]]. Creators: [[Rick Berman]] and [[Michael Piller]]|network=[[UPN]]|airdate=1999-05-26}}&lt;/ref&gt; As the tide turns against the Dominion, cut off from the [[Gamma Quadrant]] and without technological advantage, a last stand is prepared.&lt;ref name=&quot;The Dogs of War&quot;/&gt; The [[Changeling (Star Trek)|Female Changeling]] orders the destruction of a metropolis to coerce the Cardassians back into line, but instead the Cardassian fleet defects, passing the advantage to the [[Alpha Quadrant]] alliance.&lt;ref name=&quot;What You Leave Behind, Part I&quot;/&gt; Consequently, an attempted extermination results in the deaths of 800&amp;nbsp;million Cardassians in a Dominion bombardment.&lt;ref name=&quot;What You Leave Behind, Part I&quot;&gt;{{cite episode|title=What You Leave Behind, Part I|url=http://www.startrek.com/database_article/what-you-leave-behind-part-i|series=Star Trek: Deep Space Nine|serieslink=Star Trek: Deep Space Nine|credits=Writers: [[Ira Steven Behr]] and [[Hans Beimler (screenwriter)|Hans Beimler]]. Creators: [[Rick Berman]] and [[Michael Piller]]| network=[[UPN]]|airdate=1999-06-02}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Allusions to genocide contrast with ethical discussion concerning the engineered &quot;Founders disease&quot; and a potential cure. In &quot;[[Extreme Measures (Star Trek: Deep Space Nine)|Extreme Measures]]&quot;, the characters of [[Julian Bashir|Dr. Bashir]] and [[Miles O'Brien (Star Trek)|Chief O'Brien]] locate a treatment inside the mind of Section 31 agent [[List of Star Trek: Deep Space Nine characters#Sloan, Luther|Luther Sloan]]. A moral debate ensues on what constitutes genocide. While Bashir supports offering a cure to the Founders, Sisko determines that the disease should be left to continue crippling the powerful opposition. However, in &quot;The Dogs of War&quot;, Odo declares that this amounts to genocide of his species and is handed a treatment by Bashir.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.twiztv.com/scripts/ds9/season7/ds9-724.txt|archiveurl= http://web.archive.org/web/20080502203512/http://www.twiztv.com/scripts/ds9/season7/ds9-724.txt|archivedate= May 2, 2008|title=Script for &quot;The Dogs of War&quot;|publisher=twiztv.com|accessdate=May 6, 2010}} Act 1, Scenes 20-1. Writers: [[René Echevarria]] and [[Ronald D. Moore]]. Story: [[Peter Allan Fields]]. Revised April 9, 1998. Odo: &quot;Don't split hairs with me, doctor. They used me as an instrument to try to commit genocide. We may be at war with the Founders, but that's no excuse.&quot; Bashir: &quot;I completely agree.&quot; Sisko: &quot;I don't condone what Section 31 did, but the Founders started this war, not us. Giving them the cure would only strengthen their hand. And we can't do that – not when there are millions of men and women out there putting their lives on the line every day.&quot; Odo: &quot;Interesting, isn't it? The Federation claims to abhor Section 31's tactics, but when they need their dirty work done they look the other way. It's a tidy little arrangement, wouldn't you say?&quot;&lt;/ref&gt; In return for the Dominion's peaceful surrender, and the arrest of the Female Changeling on charges of [[war crime]]s, the Alpha Quadrant alliance permits Odo to heal the rest of his people.&lt;ref name=&quot;What You Leave Behind, Part II&quot;&gt;{{cite episode|title=What You Leave Behind, Part II|url=http://www.startrek.com/database_article/what-you-leave-behind-part-ii|series=Star Trek: Deep Space Nine|serieslink=Star Trek: Deep Space Nine|credits=Writers: [[Ira Steven Behr]] and [[Hans Beimler (screenwriter)|Hans Beimler]]. Creators: [[Rick Berman]] and [[Michael Piller]]|network=[[UPN]]|airdate=1999-06-02}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The Treaty of Bajor is signed aboard Deep Space Nine in the Season Seven finale, &quot;[[What You Leave Behind (Star Trek: Deep Space Nine)|What You Leave Behind, Part II]]&quot;. The conclusion to the Dominion War arc formed the resolution to ''Deep Space Nine'' as a series, and a moment for the production staff to settle the destinies of the main characters. Berman and Behr agreed with [[Paramount Television|Paramount]] that the final episode of the series should concentrate on human drama rather than the endgame of the Dominion War.&lt;ref name=&quot;Deep Space Nine Companionp592&quot;&gt;{{cite book|last1=Erdmann|first1=Terry|last2=Block|first2=Paula|title=The Star Trek: Deep Space Nine Companion|publisher=Pocket Books, Simon &amp; Schuster Inc|location=New York City|year=2000|page=592|isbn=1-0671-5010-62}} [[Ira Steven Behr]]: &quot;I could see their point. ''Deep Space Nine'' is bigger than just the Dominion War. So we split it. We had a two-hour episode, which allowed us to give the audience the big battle scenes and all that stuff, but then say, 'Hey, this is the final episode, and we have a lot of other stuff to take care of too!' ... I wanted to tie up all the loose ends. I didn't want this show to end like so many TV shows do, with all this open-ended 'Whatever happened to these characters?' I mean, obviously these characters go off and have some kind of life, but in terms of this series, I wanted to bring some closure, it was important to me.&quot;&lt;/ref&gt; Moore opines the production staff succeeded in ensuring the Dominion War acted as a means of deepening [[characterization]].&lt;ref name=&quot;IGN p10&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://movies.ign.com/articles/444/444306p8.html|title=An Interview with Ron Moore|page=10|accessdate=May 8, 2010|date=December 4, 1993|work=IGN}}&lt;/ref&gt; Although further plots would have been scripted had ''Deep Space Nine'' continued into an eighth season, Behr accepted the resolution of the Dominion War at the end of Season Seven.&lt;ref name=&quot;TrekWeb Ira Behr p2&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.trekweb.com/stories.php?aid=40f49602300c0|title=Interview, Part 2: Producer Ira Steven Behr Reflects on the Legacy of ''Deep Space Nine'', by Steve Krutzler|publisher=TrekWeb.com|page=2|accessdate=April 4, 2011|date=July 14, 1994}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Reception==
===Former cast members and production staff===
In a 2007 interview with ''iF'' magazine, [[George Takei]], who played [[Hikaru Sulu]] in ''[[Star Trek: The Original Series]]'' and its [[Star Trek (film series)|films]], described ''[[Star Trek: Deep Space Nine]]'' as representing the &quot;polar opposite&quot; of [[Gene Roddenberry]]'s vision and philosophy of the future.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.ifmagazine.com/feature.asp?article=2478|publisher=iF Magazine|author=Sean Elliot|title=Exclusive: George Takei Thanks Fans for 40 Years of ''Star Trek''|date=November 20, 2007|accessdate=November 20, 2007 |archiveurl = http://web.archive.org/web/20071123012040/http://ifmagazine.com/feature.asp?article=2478|archivedate = November 23, 2007 |accessdate = April 4, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; Writer [[D.C. Fontana]] has stated in an interview that Roddenberry would have admired the later series for its dark themes, referring to Roddenberry's military service record in [[World War II]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Interview – Dorothy Fontana On New Comics, New Novel + Canon, DS9, ENT &amp; New Movie|url=http://trekmovie.com/2007/08/16/dorothy-fontana-on-new-comics-new-novel-canon-ds9-ent-new-movie/|work=August 16, 2007|publisher=TrekMovie.com|accessdate=April 4, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; 

Roddenberry doubted that a series concentrating on themes of aside from [[space exploration]] could endure, and voiced displeasure with initial concepts for ''Deep Space Nine'' presented to him in 1991. [[Rick Berman]] has explained that Roddenberry, although terminally ill, had given him his blessing for its development, but that he had no opportunity to discuss any of the ideas with Roddenberry.&lt;ref name=&quot;Deep Space Nine Companion&quot;&gt;{{cite book|last1=Erdmann|first1=Terry|last2=Block|first2=Paula|title=The Star Trek: Deep Space Nine Companion|publisher=Pocket Books, Simon &amp; Schuster Inc|location=New York City|year=2000|page=3|isbn=1-0671-5010-62}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Critical reception===
[[John J. O'Connor (journalist)|John J. O'Connor]], writing for ''[[The New York Times]]'' in January 1993, noted that pre-release advertisements for ''[[Star Trek: Deep Space Nine]]'' offered &quot;a new ''Star Trek'' era&quot; and added, &quot;Welcome to the Dark Side. The determinedly optimistic [[Gene Roddenberry|Mr. Roddenberry]] was partial to plots that made uplifting moral points. The new creators and executive producers, [[Rick Berman]] and [[Michael Piller]], are shooting, so to speak, for something more ambivalent, less perfect.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.nytimes.com/1993/01/07/arts/review-television-star-trek-leaps-to-the-24th-century-in-syndicated-series.html|publisher=The New York Times Company|author=John J. O'Connor|title=''Star Trek'' Leaps to the 24th Century in Syndicated Series|date=January 7, 1993|accessdate=April 26, 2010|accessdate=April 4, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; In September 1996, prior to the start of Season Four, O'Connor was not sure the series was tackling contemporary themes adequately. He wrote, &quot;Inevitably, though, there is an element of exhaustion seeping through the concept. With the [[Cold War]] over, perhaps the Roddenberry optimism seems merely naive as headlines bring news of murderous divisions between [[Serbs]] and [[Muslim]]s, [[Kurds]] and [[Turkish people|Turks]], [[Israelis]] and [[Palestinians]], [[Irish Catholic]]s and [[Protestantism in Ireland|Protestants]], and so on across an increasingly depressing globe. ''[[Star Trek]]'' offered a vision that leapt 300 years into the future. For too many people today, three years would seem a stretch.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.nytimes.com/1996/09/11/arts/when-space-seemed-a-whole-lot-bigger.html?scp=43&amp;sq=Star%20Trek:%20Deep%20Space%20Nine&amp;st=Search|publisher=The New York Times Company|author=John J. O'Connor|title=Critic's Notebook: When Space Seemed a Whole Lot Bigger|date=September 11, 1996|accessdate=April 26, 2010|accessdate=April 4, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Cynthia Littleton, writing for ''[[Variety (magazine)|Variety]]'' in 1998, summarized the ratings the series was receiving at the end of its sixth season: &quot;''Deep Space Nine'' may not go out on as high a [[Nielsen ratings|Nielsen]] note as ''[[Star Trek: The Next Generation|Next Generation]]'', which wrapped a hugely successful run in 1994, but ''DS9'' is hardly floundering. The show, which bowed in January 1993, consistently ranks among the top three [[Broadcast syndication#First-run syndication in the U.S.|first-run syndication]] hours in household and demographic ratings.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.variety.com/article/VR1117479765|publisher=Variety.com|author=Cynthia Littleton|title=&quot;Deep Space&quot; on final ''Trek''|date=August 24, 1998|accessdate=April 26, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In a 1999 edition of the Australian science-fiction magazine ''Frontier'', Anthony Leong suggested that ''Deep Space Nine'' had not initially been envisaged to include a war [[story arc]] from the beginning. He demonstrated a preference for the manner in which the plot of ''[[Babylon 5]]'' had been devised, while acknowledging how the ''Deep Space Nine'' writers had developed a continuing plotline: &quot;... it is rare for a series creator to envision how the series will develop over time. Furthermore, the creative process in dramatic television writing tends to be organic, as events in the series will unfold based on the events that preceded it. For example, were the wars with the [[Klingon]]s and the [[Dominion (Star Trek)|Dominion]] on ''Deep Space Nine'' foreseen by its creators back in the first season? Of course not ... these events developed over time through the input of its writing staff.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|last=Leong|first=Anthony|title=''Babylon 5'': Triumph and Tragedy in Three Acts|journal=Frontier: the Australian Science-Fiction Media Magazine|issue=15|publisher=K &amp; J Publishing|location=Carlton South, Victoria, Australia|date=1999-04|url=http://www.mediacircus.net/babylon5.html|issn=1326-8686|accessdate=April 4, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In 2008, Nader Elhefnawy, contributor to [[The Internet Review of Science Fiction]], asserted that, while less appreciated than other science-fiction series of the 1990s, ''Deep Space Nine'' had developed an interesting cast of characters, &quot;thanks to the Dominion War, much of the richest and most exciting drama in the ''Star Trek'' franchise's history.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|url=http://www.irosf.com/q/zine/article/10421|publisher=Bluejack|author=Nader Elhefnawy|editor=Stacey Janssen|title=The Golden Age of Science Fiction Television: Looking Back at SFTV During the Long 1990s|journal=The Internet Review of Science-Fiction|date=June 2008|accessdate=May 9, 2010}}{{dead link|date=April 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Owen Williams, writing for ''[[Empire (magazine)|Empire]]'' magazine, opines that ''Star Trek'' as a whole has been slow to adapt and develop to new trends, while singling out ''Deep Space Nine'' for special mention: &quot;... arguably even the ace ''DS9'' only got good in response to ''Babylon 5'' ...&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|url=http://www.empireonline.com/News/story.asp?nid=25848|publisher=Bauer Consumer Media|author=Owen Williams|editor=Nick de Semlyen|title=''Star Trek 2'' on ''Battlestar'' Territory? Abrams and Orci Talk Allegory|journal=Empire|date=September 17, 2009|accessdate=April 4, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; Adam Smith, chief features writer for ''Empire'' commented in a 2009 article that, &quot;It's hard to choose the best episodes of ''DS9'' without mentioning the stories involving the Dominion War.&quot; He reported &quot;[[The Search (Star Trek: Deep Space Nine)|The Search]]&quot;, &quot;[[In the Pale Moonlight]]&quot; and &quot;[[Far Beyond the Stars]]&quot; as the features staff's favorite episodes for their portrayal of darker themes and creating a change in direction.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|url=http://www.empireonline.com/features/best-and-worst-star-trek-episodes/3.asp|publisher=Bauer Consumer Media|author=Adam Smith|editor=Dan Jolin|title=''Star Trek'': The Best and Worst Episodes|journal=Empire|date=September 17, 2009|accessdate=April 4, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

''Star Trek: Deep Space Nine'' was nominated at the [[Academy of Science Fiction, Fantasy &amp; Horror Films]] for a [[Saturn Award]], from 1997 to 2000, in the field of Best Genre Cable or Syndicated Series. It was nominated in technical and artistic categories at the [[Emmys]] in each season. [[Cinescape]] columnist Andrew Hershberger remarked in 2003 on the lack of critical success for science-fiction television: &quot;Nobody cool would dare vote for a sci-fi show [for Outstanding Drama Series] that didn't have [Stanley] [[Stanley Kubrick|Kubrick]] or [[Chris Carter (screenwriter)|Chris Carter]]'s name attached to it ... If ''Deep Space Nine'' was involved, you'd hear some real complaining on this end.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.trektoday.com/articles/trekking_to_the_emmys.shtml|publisher=Trek Nation|author=Caillan Davenport|title=Trekking to the Emmys|date=200-07-16|accessdate=April 4, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Academic perspectives===
Academics have noted how the Dominion War plotlines have explored the human psyche as much as outer space. Lincoln Geraghty praises the ending to the [[story arc]] and ''[[Star Trek: Deep Space Nine]]'' as a series, and believes this is indicative of how the series manipulates the ''[[Star Trek]]'' ethos, identifying a theme of ambiguity as part of its continuing narrative.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|publisher=I.B. Tauris|first1=Lincoln|last1=Geraghty|title=Living with Star Trek: American Culture and the Star Trek Universe|isbn=978-1845112653|page=262|date=February 30, 2007|accessdate=May 16, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; Karin Blair, writing in 1997 at the time of Season Five, felt that the series was reflecting trends for American culture to re-consider its place in the global community.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|publisher=|author=Karin Blair|editor=Dan Jolin|title=Star Trek Old and New: From the Alien Embodied to the Alien Imagined|year=1997}}&lt;/ref&gt; Social theorist Michele Barrett comments on the &quot;declining faith in [[rationalism]] that haunts ''Deep Space Nine''&quot; in her book ''Star Trek: The Human Frontier''.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|publisher=Routledge|first1=Michele|last1=Barrett|first2=Duncan|last2=Barrett|title=Star Trek: The Human Frontier|isbn=0415929822|date=December 1, 2001|accessdate=May 16, 2010}} Back cover.&lt;/ref&gt;

In contrast, Robert Jewett and [[John Shelton Lawrence]], authors of ''[[The Myth of the American Superhero]]'', argue that the Dominion War plotlines in ''Deep Space Nine'' continue ''Star Trek''&lt;nowiki&gt;'&lt;/nowiki&gt;s portrayal of &quot;humanistic militarism&quot;, in that conflict is justified for the sake of humanity.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|publisher=William B Eerdmans Publishing Co|first1=Robert|last1=Jewett|first2=John|last2=Lawrence|title=The Myth of the American Superhero|isbn=978-0802849113|page=245|date=September 20, 2002|accessdate=May 16, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; Criticism is levelled at [[Paramount Television|Paramount]]'s tie-in merchandising, in particular the slogan for the computer game ''[[Star Trek: Deep Space Nine: Dominion Wars|Deep Space Nine: Dominion Wars]]'', which is considered to emphasize the combat element at the expense of other themes.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|publisher=William B Eerdmans Publishing Co|first1=Robert|last1=Jewett|first2=John|last2=Lawrence|title=The Myth of the American Superhero|isbn=978-0802849113|page=262|date=September 20, 2002|accessdate=May 16, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;

While television commentators and fans have noted associations with the [[Yugoslav Wars]] in the 1990s, some academics have noted parallels between the portrayal of the Dominion War and other historical conflicts. Michele Barrett identifies a number of themes relating to [[World War I]] in ''Star Trek'', especially &quot;in the bleak and costly alliances and endless casualty sheets that characterize the protracted Dominion War in ''DS9''.&quot;&lt;ref name=HumanFrontierp66p72&gt;{{cite book|publisher=Routledge|first1=Michele|last1=Barrett|first2=Duncan|last2=Barrett|title=Star Trek: The Human Frontier|isbn=0415929822|date=December 1, 2001|pages=66, 72|accessdate=May 16, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Spin-off media==
A number of novels, novelizations and short-story collections have been written to chronicle events of the Dominion War outside of [[Canon (fiction)|canon]]:
* ''[[Behind Enemy Lines (Star Trek)|Behind Enemy Lines]]'' by [[John Vornholt]]&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|author=John Vornholt|title=Behind Enemy Lines: The Dominion War #1|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=L-9NLlBhBxMC|accessdate=April 4, 2011|date=July 1, 1999|publisher=Simon and Schuster|isbn=9780671041045}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* ''A Call to Arms'' by [[Keith R. A. DeCandido]]
* ''Tunnel Through the Stars'' by John Vornholt&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|author=John Vornholt|title=Tunnel Through The Stars: The Dominion War #3|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=8mdeYdF4asEC|accessdate=April 4, 2011|date=July 1, 1999|publisher=Simon and Schuster|isbn=9780671041069}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* ''Sacrifice of Angels'' by [[Diane Carey]]&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|author=Diane Carey|title=Sacrifice Of Angels: The Dominion War #4|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=8ZNwHW-La04C|accessdate=April 4, 2011|date=July 1, 1999|publisher=Simon and Schuster|isbn=9780671041076}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* ''Tales of the Dominion War'' edited by Keith R. A. DeCandido&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|author=Keith R. A. DeCandido|title=Tales of the Dominion War|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=ynAOelFpNs8C|accessdate=April 4, 2011|date=September 1, 2004|publisher=Simon and Schuster|isbn=9781416503644}}&lt;/ref&gt;

''[[Star Trek: Deep Space Nine: Dominion Wars|Deep Space Nine: Dominion Wars]]'' is a real-time tactics computer game based on the depictions of the Dominion War published by [[Simon &amp; Schuster Interactive]] in 2001.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://uk.gamespot.com/pc/strategy/startrekdeepspacendw/review.html?om_act=convert&amp;om_clk=tab|title=''Star Trek: Dominion Wars'' Review|accessdate=April 4, 2011|year=1993|work=GameSpot UK}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==See also==
{{Portal|Star Trek}}
* [[Bajoran]]
* [[Bajoran Wormhole]]
* [[Changeling (Star Trek)|Changeling]]
* [[Dominion (Star Trek)|Dominion]]
* [[Jem'Hadar]]
* [[Vorta]]

==References==
{{reflist|colwidth=30em}}

==External links==
{{Memoryalpha}}
* {{imdb title|0106145|Star Trek: Deep Space Nine}}

{{Star Trek DS9}}
{{Star Trek}}

[[Category:Star Trek: Deep Space Nine]]
[[Category:Star Trek wars and battles]]

[[ko:도미니언 전쟁 (스타 트렉)]]
[[it:Guerra del Dominio]]
[[ja:ドミニオン戦争]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
