<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="20803008" ns="0" title="Don Tallon with the Australian cricket team in England in 1948"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Infobox cricketer tour biography
|          playername = Don Tallon
|               image = DonTallon.jpg
|             country = Australia
|            fullname = Donald Tallon
|            nickname = Deafy
|          dayofbirth = 17
|        monthofbirth = 2
|         yearofbirth = 1916
|        placeofbirth = [[Bundaberg, Queensland|Bundaberg]], [[Queensland]]
|      countryofbirth = [[Australia]]
|          dayofdeath = 7
|        monthofdeath = 9
|         yearofdeath = 1984
|        placeofdeath = Bundaberg
|      countryofdeath = Australia
|            heightft =
|          heightinch =
|             heightm = 1.8
|             batting = Right-hand batsman
|             bowling = Right-arm [[leg spin]]
|                role = [[Wicket-keeper]]
|       international = true
|       testdebutdate = 10 June
|       testdebutyear = 1948
|    testdebutagainst = England
|        lasttestdate = 14 August
|        lasttestyear = 1948
|     lasttestagainst = England
|          deliveries = balls
|             columns = 2
|             column1 = [[Test cricket|Tests]]
|            matches1 = 4
|               runs1 = 112
|            bat avg1 = 28.00
|           100s/50s1 = &amp;ndash;/1
|          top score1 = 53
|         deliveries1 = &amp;ndash;
|            wickets1 = &amp;ndash;
|           bowl avg1 = &amp;ndash;
|            fivefor1 = &amp;ndash;
|             tenfor1 = &amp;ndash;
|       best bowling1 = &amp;ndash;
|  catches/stumpings1 = 12/0
|             column2 = [[First-class cricket|First-class]]
|            matches2 = 14
|               runs2 = 283
|            bat avg2 = 25.72
|           100s/50s2 = 0/2
|          top score2 = 53
|         deliveries2 = &amp;ndash;
|            wickets2 = &amp;ndash;
|           bowl avg2 = &amp;ndash;
|            fivefor2 = &amp;ndash;
|             tenfor2 = &amp;ndash;
|       best bowling2 = &amp;ndash;
|  catches/stumpings2 = 29/14
|                date=  12 December
|                year = 2007
|              source =
}}

[[Don Tallon]] was a key member of [[Donald Bradman]]'s famous [[Australian cricket team in England in 1948|Australian cricket team tour of England in 1948]], in which Australia was undefeated in their 34 matches. This unprecedented feat by a Test side touring England earned them the sobriquet ''The Invincibles''.

The team's first-choice [[wicket-keeper]] ahead of [[Ron Saggers]], Tallon played in four of the five Tests, missing the Fourth Test due to injury. Despite being the preferred gloveman, Tallon conceded [[bye (cricket)|byes]] at a higher rate than Saggers during the tour.

Bradman rotated the two glovemen during the tour, and Tallon played in 14 of the 31 first-class matches, taking 29 catches and 14 stumpings. Tallon's catch of [[Len Hutton]] in the Fifth Test at [[The Oval]] was described as [[Wisden]] as the best of the year. He also took a difficult catch to remove [[George Emmett]] in the Third Test at [[Old Trafford (cricket ground)|Old Trafford]], catching a ball that flew to his feet at [[yorker]] length. However, Tallon also had some mishaps, with finger injuries inflicted by failing to catch the ball correctly. Tallon had few opportunities with the bat, scoring 283 runs at a [[batting average]] of 25.72 in 13 first-class innings, including two fifties. During the Test, Tallon scored 112 runs at 28.00, including a 53 in the Second Test that saw Australia recover to a first innings of 350 after a [[batting order (cricket)|middle-order]] slump had seen England take the upper hand. He took 12 catches in the Tests.

In recognition of his performances, Tallon was named as one of the five [[Wisden Cricketers of the Year]] in 1949.

==Background==
Tallon's form as Australia's wicket-keeper since [[World War II]] saw him selected for the 1948 Ashes tour as part of the side that would become known to cricket history as the ''[[Australian cricket team in England in 1948|Invincibles]]''. Tallon was the first-choice wicket-keeper, with Saggers as his deputy.&lt;ref&gt;Pollard, p. 6.&lt;/ref&gt; Having spent the majority of his life in sunny Queensland and growing up in tropical Bundaberg, the cold English climate initially caught Tallon off guard. He did not wet his inner gloves as was his custom due to the temperature.&lt;ref name=&quot;p196&quot;&gt;Perry (2001), p. 196.&lt;/ref&gt; As England agreed to make a [[cricket_ball#Condition_of_a_cricket_ball|new ball]] available every 55 [[Over (cricket)|overs]], this meant that the ball would more frequently be in a favourable state for fast bowling, since it would [[Swing bowling|swing]] more.&lt;ref name=&quot;p197&quot;&gt;Perry (2001), p. 197.&lt;/ref&gt; As a result, Australia adopted a pace-oriented strategy and [[Ian Johnson (cricketer)|Ian Johnson]] was the only spinner regularly used in the Test matches. [[Colin McCool]] was not to play a Test on the tour, depriving Tallon of an opportunity to show his stumping abilities standing up at the [[stump (cricket)|stump]]s to his Queensland team-mate in the Tests.&lt;ref&gt;Perry (2001), pp. 197&amp;ndash;198.&lt;/ref&gt;

==Early tour==
Australia traditionally fielded its first-choice team in the tour opener, which was customarily against [[Worcestershire County Cricket Club|Worcestershire]].&lt;ref name=haigh&gt;{{Cite news| title=Gentrifying the game| first=Gideon | last=Haigh| authorlink=Gideon Haigh| url=http://content-aus.cricinfo.com/ci/content/story/295893.html |publisher=[[Cricinfo]] |date=2007-05-26| accessdate=2007-06-01}}&lt;/ref&gt; Accordingly, Tallon was selected as the wicket-keeper for the match. The home side batted first and Tallon made his first dismissal on English soil by catching Worcestershire captain [[Allan White]] from the bowling of [[Keith Miller]]. He then stumped former England captain [[Bob Wyatt]] from McCool. In reply to the hosts' 233, Tallon was promoted to No. 6, but managed only six in a collapse of 4/38 before Australia recovered to declare at 8/462. He took a further three [[dismissal (cricket)|dismissals]] in the second innings, two of them stumpings from McCool's bowling, as Australia crushed the hosts by an innings and 17 runs. Tallon conceded 11 byes in the match.&lt;ref name=sched/&gt;&lt;ref name=o/&gt;&lt;ref name=worcs&gt;{{Cite web
|url = http://www.cricketarchive.com/Archive/Scorecards/18/18403.html
|title = Worcestershire v Australians
|publisher = [[CricketArchive]]
|accessdate = 2008-12-18}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Tallon was rested for the second tour match against [[Leicestershire County Cricket Club|Leicestershire]], which Australia won by an innings with Saggers behind the stumps.&lt;ref name=leics&gt;{{Cite web
|url = http://www.cricketarchive.com/Archive/Scorecards/18/18406.html
|title = Leicestershire v Australians
|publisher = [[CricketArchive]]
|accessdate = 2008-12-18}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Tallon played a key role in Australia's victory in the next match against [[Yorkshire County Cricket Club|Yorkshire]], on a [[sticky wicket|damp pitch]] that suited slower bowling.&lt;ref name=o/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Fingleton, pp. 53&amp;ndash;55.&lt;/ref&gt; He came in at 7/86 and made ten in the first innings to push Australia to 101 in reply to Yorkshire's 71, in which Tallon did not concede a bye.&lt;ref name=york/&gt; However, Tallon was not so tidy in the second innings, conceding 11 byes as the hosts were bowled out for 89 in their second innings. He did not make a dismissal in the match. Australia then collapsed to 6/31 in pursuit of 60 for victory when Tallon strode in. To make matters worse, [[Sam Loxton]] was injured and could not bat, so Australia only had three wickets in hand. Australia faced its first loss to an English county since 1912.&lt;ref name=york&gt;{{Cite web
|url = http://www.cricketarchive.com/Archive/Scorecards/18/18412.html
|title = Yorkshire v Australians
|publisher = [[CricketArchive]]
|accessdate = 2008-12-18}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=f55&gt;Fingleton, p. 55.&lt;/ref&gt; He survived an immediate [[leg before wicket]] appeal and then hit a shot that fell just short of a fielder. He then compiled 17 unbeaten runs as Australia scraped home by four wickets.&lt;ref name=york/&gt;&lt;ref name=f56&gt;Fingleton, p. 56.&lt;/ref&gt;

The Australians travelled to London to play [[Surrey County Cricket Club|Surrey]] at [[The Oval]]. Tallon came in with the score at 6/553, and held up his end, scoring an [[not out|unbeaten]] 50 as his partners steadily fell and Australia were bowled out at 632.&lt;ref name=surrey/&gt; Tallon had some difficulty in English conditions as he sustained a bruised right finger when he lost sight of a [[Ray Lindwall]] [[bouncer (cricket)|bouncer]] on a misty morning during the match and was hit as he put hand over his face for protection, with the ball running away for four byes.&lt;ref name=&quot;p197&quot;/&gt; Tallon took two catches in the second innings as Australia won the match by an innings, but he also conceded 24 byes in Surrey's match total of 336.&lt;ref name=surrey&gt;{{Cite web
|url = http://www.cricketarchive.com/Archive/Scorecards/18/18422.html
|title = Surrey v Australians
|publisher = [[CricketArchive]]
|accessdate = 2008-12-18}}&lt;/ref&gt;

After sustaining the bruised finger, Tallon was rested for the following three matches, which were against [[Cambridge University Cricket Club|Cambridge University]], [[Essex County Cricket Club|Essex]] and [[Oxford University Cricket Club|Oxford]].&lt;ref name=sched/&gt;&lt;ref name=o/&gt; Australia won each of the matches by an innings. Saggers filled in and scored 110 runs including a 104 not out against Essex and took five dismissals.&lt;ref name=saggers&gt;{{Cite web
|url = http://www.cricketarchive.com/cgi-bin/player_oracle_reveals_results2.cgi?playernumber=830&amp;opponentmatch=exact&amp;playername=John&amp;resulttype=All&amp;matchtype=All&amp;teammatch=exact&amp;startwicket=&amp;homeawaytype=All&amp;opponent=&amp;endwicket=&amp;wicketkeeper=&amp;searchtype=InningsList&amp;endscore=&amp;playermatch=contains&amp;branding=cricketarchive&amp;captain=&amp;endseason=1948&amp;startscore=&amp;team=&amp;startseason=1948
|title = Player Oracle RA Saggers 1948
|publisher = [[CricketArchive]]
|accessdate = 2008-12-18}}&lt;/ref&gt; Saggers conceded only 34 byes in his four tour matches, while Tallon had conceded 46 in three.&lt;sup&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#00f&quot;&gt;N-&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;{{Ref label|Saggers|1|a}}
[[Image:SaggersMcCabeTallon.jpg|left|thumb|290px|Ron Saggers (centre) pictured with [[Stan McCabe]] (left) and Tallon (right) during a country match in 1945.]]
The next match was against the [[Marylebone Cricket Club]] (MCC) at [[Lord's]]. The MCC fielded seven players who would represent England in the Tests,&lt;sup&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#00f&quot;&gt;N-&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;{{Ref label|MCC|2|a}} and were basically a full strength Test team, as were Australia, who fielded their first-choice team. It was a chance to gain a psychological advantage, and Tallon was selected despite conceding byes at a higher rate in the preceding tour matches. He made 11 batting at No. 9, including a [[six (cricket)|six]] from [[Jim Laker]] as Australia made 552.&lt;ref&gt;Fingleton, p. 73.&lt;/ref&gt; He took three catches in the first innings, having a hand in the first three wickets to fall, [[Jack Robertson]], [[Bill Edrich]] and [[Denis Compton]]. He then took two stumpings in the second innings as the [[follow on]] was enforced, but also conceded 26 byes as Australia won by an innings.&lt;ref name=sched&gt;{{Cite web|title=Matches, Australia tour of England, Apr-Sep 1948 |url=http://content-aus.cricinfo.com/invincibles/engine/series/61329.html |publisher=[[Cricinfo]] |accessdate=2008-07-16}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=o&gt;{{Cite web
|url = http://www.cricketarchive.com/cgi-bin/player_oracle_reveals_results2.cgi?playernumber=744&amp;opponentmatch=exact&amp;playername=John&amp;resulttype=All&amp;matchtype=All&amp;teammatch=exact&amp;startwicket=&amp;homeawaytype=All&amp;opponent=&amp;endwicket=&amp;wicketkeeper=&amp;searchtype=InningsList&amp;endscore=&amp;playermatch=contains&amp;branding=cricketarchive&amp;captain=&amp;endseason=1948&amp;startscore=&amp;team=&amp;startseason=1948
|title = Player Oracle D Tallon 1948
|publisher = [[CricketArchive]]
|accessdate = 2008-12-18}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=mcc/&gt; Tallon had conceded 72 byes to Saggers' 34 with both having played four matches.&lt;sup&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#00f&quot;&gt;N-&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;{{Ref label|Saggers|1|a}}

Following the match against the MCC, there were four more county fixtures before the First Test, against [[Lancashire County Cricket Club|Lancashire]], [[Nottinghamshire County Cricket Club|Nottinghamshire]], [[Hampshire County Cricket Club|Hampshire]] and [[Sussex County Cricket Club|Sussex]]. Australia drew the first two before winning the latter two by eight wickets and an innings and 325 runs respectively.&lt;ref name=sched/&gt; Tallon played in only the Nottinghamshire match,&lt;ref name=o/&gt; taking two catches in the first innings and two stumpings in each of the innings. The catches were all from Lindwall and the stumpings from [[Doug Ring]]. Tallon conceded 18 byes for the match and scored 27, being last man out at 400 after coming to the crease at 6/355.&lt;ref name=notts&gt;{{Cite web
|url = http://www.cricketarchive.com/Archive/Scorecards/18/18467.html
|title = Nottinghamshire v Australians
|publisher = [[CricketArchive]]
|accessdate = 2008-12-18}}&lt;/ref&gt; In Saggers's three matches, 36 byes were conceded and six dismissals were made.&lt;ref name=lancs&gt;{{Cite web
|url = http://www.cricketarchive.com/Archive/Scorecards/18/18458.html
|title = Lancashire v Australians
|publisher = [[CricketArchive]]
|accessdate = 2008-12-18}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=hants&gt;{{Cite web
|url = http://www.cricketarchive.com/Archive/Scorecards/18/18473.html
|title = Hampshire v Australians
|publisher = [[CricketArchive]]
|accessdate = 2008-12-18}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=sussex&gt;{{Cite web
|url = http://www.cricketarchive.com/Archive/Scorecards/18/18489.html
|title = Sussex v Australians
|publisher = [[CricketArchive]]
|accessdate = 2008-12-18}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==First Test==
{{Main|First Test, 1948 Ashes series}}
Despite averaging more byes per innings than Saggers during the warm-up matches,&lt;sup&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#00f&quot;&gt;N-&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;{{Ref label|Warm|3|ad}} Tallon was retained in the Test team.  During the First Test at [[Trent Bridge]], Tallon took four catches. In the first innings, Tallon caught [[Jim Laker]] from the bowling of [[Keith Miller]] to end England's innings of 165 after he and [[Alec Bedser]] had joined forces at 8/74.&lt;ref name=sco1/&gt;

When Australia batted, Tallon came in at 6/338 to accompany [[Lindsay Hassett]] and took 39 minutes to compile 10 before hitting a return catch to the [[left arm orthodox spin]] of [[Jack Young (cricketer)|Jack Young]].&lt;ref name=&quot;sco1&quot;/&gt; The scoring was slow during this passage of play&amp;mdash;Young delivered 11 consecutive [[over (cricket)|maiden overs]] and his 26-over spell conceded only 14 runs with Australia using [[leg theory]].&lt;ref name=&quot;report1&quot;&gt;{{Cite web|title= First Test Match England v Australia |work= [[Wisden Cricketers' Almanack]] |year=1949  |url=http://content-aus.cricinfo.com/wisdenalmanack/content/story/152894.html |accessdate=2008-07-02 |publisher=[[Wisden]]}}&lt;/ref&gt;

After Australia ended with 509 and took a 334-run lead,&lt;ref name=sco1/&gt; Tallon took two difficult catches to dismiss key batsmen at the start of England's second innings.&lt;ref name=p199/&gt; Miller removed [[Cyril Washbrook]] for one from a top-edged [[Batting (cricket)#Pull and hook|hook shot]] to Tallon.&lt;ref name=f96&gt;Fingleton, p. 96.&lt;/ref&gt; [[Bill Edrich]] was then caught behind attempting a cut from the [[off spin]] of Johnson. He did not read the [[arm ball]] that went straight on and the ball took the outside edge, leaving England at 2/39.&lt;ref name=&quot;sco1&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;report1&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=f97&gt;Fingleton, p. 97.&lt;/ref&gt; He thus helped Australia to seize the initiative by denying England a good start, but they recovered. Later, he caught [[Godfrey Evans]] for 50 from Johnson as England ended at 441. Australia reached their target of 98 with two wickets down, completing an eight-wicket victory.&lt;ref name=&quot;p199&quot;&gt;Perry, p. 199.&lt;/ref&gt; Tallon conceded five and 12 byes in the two innings respectively.&lt;ref name=sco1/&gt;

Between Tests, Australia played [[Northamptonshire County Cricket Club|Northamptonshire]] and Yorkshire, and Tallon was rested for both matches. The first was won by an innings and second was drawn.&lt;ref name=sched/&gt;&lt;ref name=o/&gt; Saggers made four and 22 and conceded 24 byes in four innings.&lt;ref name=saggers/&gt;&lt;ref name=northants&gt;{{Cite web
|url = http://www.cricketarchive.com/Archive/Scorecards/18/18514.html
|title = Northamptonshire v Australians
|publisher = [[CricketArchive]]
|accessdate = 2008-12-18}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=york2&gt;{{Cite web
|url = http://www.cricketarchive.com/Archive/Scorecards/18/18526.html
|title = Yorkshire v Australians
|publisher = [[CricketArchive]]
|accessdate = 2008-12-18}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Second Test==
{{Main|Second Test, 1948 Ashes series}}
[[Image:Don Tallon batting.jpg|thumb|left|Tallon batting in an earlier season.]]
The teams moved on to [[Lord's Cricket Ground|Lord's]] for the Second Test and Australia compiled 350 in its first innings. Tallon came to the crease with Australia at 6/225 after Hassett and [[Bill Brown (cricketer)|Bill Brown]] had gone in quick succession, joining Johnson in the middle. Johnson struggled to score, while Tallon did so freely in the last hour. After Johnson fell for four at 7/246, Lindwall then joined Tallon and the pair survived to the close of play.&lt;ref name=sco2/&gt; England were well placed when Australia ended [[List of cricket terma#S|at stumps]] on 7/258 with Tallon on 25.&lt;ref name=&quot;report2&quot;&gt;{{Cite web|title= Second Test Match England v Australia |work= [[Wisden Cricketers' Almanack]] |year=1949  |url=http://content-aus.cricinfo.com/wisdenalmanack/content/story/152895.html |publisher=[[Wisden]] |accessdate=2008-07-02}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=f110/&gt; Tallon had dominated the scoring late in day, making 25 of the 33 runs added.&lt;ref name=sco2/&gt; The crowd was optimistic about England's position and some immediately camped outside the turnstiles upon leaving the ground.&lt;ref name=f110&gt;Fingleton, p. 175.&lt;/ref&gt;

Australia's lower order batted the tourists into control on the second morning.&lt;ref name=f110/&gt; Despite the loss of Lindwall for 15 at 8/275, Tallon kept on batting in a conventional manner, supported by Johnston and [[Ernie Toshack]], who scored their highest Test scores.&lt;ref&gt;Cashman, pp. ??.&lt;/ref&gt; Both [[tail-ender]]s threw the bat at the ball, which often went in vastly different directions to where they had aimed their shots.&lt;ref name=f110/&gt; Tallon put on 45 with Johnston&amp;mdash;who scored 29&amp;mdash; before holing out for 53.&lt;ref name=&quot;sco2&quot;/&gt; Ending at 350, the Australians had regained the momentum, taking 92 runs from 66 minutes of hitting in the morning.&lt;ref name=&quot;report2&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=f110/&gt;

Tallon did not concede a bye in England's first innings of 215 and his diving was estimated to have saved around 40&amp;nbsp;runs.&lt;ref name=&quot;p199&quot;/&gt; He caught Washbrook from Lindwall to leave England at 1/17, and later caught Laker from Johnson.&lt;ref name=sco2/&gt; Tallon was not needed in the second innings; Lindwall was promoted above Tallon because Australia needed quick runs and Lindwall was a big-hitter. Australia declared at 7/460, leaving England a target of 509.&lt;ref name=sco2/&gt;

With the score at 2/65,&lt;ref name=sco2/&gt; Washbrook [[List of cricket terms#E|inside edged]] a Toshack [[full toss]] directly downwards at Tallon's ankle. Bradman described the catch as &quot;miraculous&quot; because Tallon had to reach so low, so quickly, in order to take the catch.&lt;ref name=&quot;p199&quot;/&gt; Another dive to stop a [[Batting (cricket)#Leg glance|leg glance]] resulted in a severely bruised left little finger.&lt;ref name=&quot;p200&quot;/&gt; Tallon conceded 16 byes  in the second innings, more than 8% of England's score.&lt;ref name=sco2/&gt; Australia won the Test by 409 runs,&lt;ref name=sco2/&gt; and nursing his finger, Tallon was rested for both tour matches between the Tests, which were against [[Surrey County Cricket Club|Surrey]] and [[Gloucestershire County Cricket Club|Gloucestershire]], which were won by ten wickets and an innings respectively.&lt;ref name=sched/&gt;&lt;ref name=o/&gt; In his place, Saggers scored 12, took nine dismissals and conceded 31 byes in four innings.&lt;ref name=saggers/&gt;&lt;ref name=surrey2&gt;{{Cite web
|url = http://www.cricketarchive.com/Archive/Scorecards/18/18553.html
|title = Surrey v Australians
|publisher = [[CricketArchive]]
|accessdate = 2008-12-18}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=gloucs&gt;{{Cite web
|url = http://www.cricketarchive.com/Archive/Scorecards/18/18558.html
|title = Gloucestershire v Australians
|publisher = [[CricketArchive]]
|accessdate = 2008-12-18}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Third Test==
{{Main|Third Test, 1948 Ashes series}}

The teams then played out a rain-affected draw in the Third Test match at [[Old Trafford Cricket Ground|Manchester]], where England elected to bat first.&lt;ref name=sco3/&gt; On the first day, Edrich gloved a rising Lindwall delivery and was caught by Tallon for 32, leaving England at 5/119.&lt;ref name=sco3/&gt;&lt;ref name=f171&gt;Fingleton, p. 171.&lt;/ref&gt; Compton returned at the fall of Edrich's wicket after previously leaving the ground after being bloodied in the head by a Lindwall bouncer. He batted to stumps, after being dropped one-handed on 50 by Tallon, before again being dropped on 64 late in the day by the gloveman from the bowling of Johnston.&lt;ref&gt;Fingleton, pp. 133&amp;ndash;134.&lt;/ref&gt; England closed at 7/231 with Compton on 64.&lt;ref name=sco3/&gt;

On the second morning, Tallon again dropped Compton from Johnston when the batsman was on 73.&lt;ref name=f134&gt;Fingleton, p. 134.&lt;/ref&gt; England eventually finished on 363, with Compton [[not out]] on 145. Thus Tallon's drops cost 95 runs as well as allowing Compton to hold up one end so his partners could score. Tallon also conceded seven byes.&lt;ref name=sco3/&gt;

Australia reached 3/135 when Miller and [[Arthur Morris]] departed in quick succession. With [[Sid Barnes]] [[List of cricket terms#R|retiring hurt]] because of a blow to the ribs,&lt;ref name=sco3/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;report3&quot;&gt;{{Cite web|title= Third Test Match England v Australia |work= [[Wisden Cricketers' Almanack]] |year=1949  |url=http://content-aus.cricinfo.com/wisdenalmanack/content/story/152896.html |accessdate=2008-07-02 |publisher=[[Wisden]]}}&lt;/ref&gt; Tallon came in at 5/139, effectively six wickets down and made 18 in half and hour before falling at 6/172. Australia managed to reach 221 and avoid the [[follow on]].&lt;ref name=sco3/&gt;

England batted again and Tallon dismissed [[George Emmett]] from Lindwall with a diving one-handed catch.&lt;ref name = &quot;p200&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;l103&quot;&gt;Lemmon, p. 103.&lt;/ref&gt; Lindwall pitched an [[outswinger]] on the off stump and Emmett edged it to wicket-keeper Tallon, who took it in his right hand with a dive, leaving England at 1/1.&lt;ref name=sco3/&gt;&lt;ref name=f141&gt;Fingleton, p. 141.&lt;/ref&gt; England then declared at 3/174; Tallon conceded nine byes and with more than a day was lost to rain, Tallon was not required as Australia batted out the last session for a draw.&lt;ref name=sco3/&gt;&lt;ref name=report3/&gt;

Tallon's little left finger swelled up after the Third Test and he exacerbated the injury during a tour match against [[Middlesex County Cricket Club|Middlesex]].&lt;ref name=l103/&gt; In this match, he scored 17, took two catches and a stumping in the first innings and conceded only seven byes for the entire match as Australia won by ten wickets.&lt;ref name=middlesex&gt;{{Cite web
|url = http://www.cricketarchive.com/Archive/Scorecards/18/18593.html
|title = Middlesex v Australians
|publisher = [[CricketArchive]]
|accessdate = 2008-12-18}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Fourth Test==
{{Main|Fourth Test, 1948 Ashes series}}

The left finger injury ruled him out of the Fourth Test at [[Headingley Stadium|Headingley]],&lt;ref name=&quot;l103&quot;/&gt; and he was replaced by Saggers.  Australia set a world record in successfully chasing a target of 404 to win the match by seven wickets and secure the series.&lt;ref name=sco4/&gt; Saggers leaked only six byes in 299.1 overs of glovework during the match as Australia conceded a total of 861 runs for the match.&lt;ref name=sco4/&gt; It was the lowest percentage of byes conceded in a match total by an Australian wicket-keeper for the tour (0.697%).&lt;sup&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#00f&quot;&gt;N-&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;{{Ref label|stumps|4|d}}

Tallon missed the innings victory over [[Derbyshire County Cricket Club|Derbyshire]],&lt;ref name=sched/&gt;&lt;ref name=o/&gt;&lt;ref name=derby&gt;{{Cite web
|url = http://www.cricketarchive.com/Archive/Scorecards/18/18616.html
|title = Derbyshire v Australians
|publisher = [[CricketArchive]]
|accessdate = 2008-12-18}}&lt;/ref&gt; before returning against [[Glamorgan County Cricket Club|Glamorgan]]. In his first match back from injury, Tallon took a catch and two stumpings as the hosts were dismissed for 197, but he also conceded 19 byes. Byes made 9.64% of the match total conceded by Australia, the highest proportion by the tourists during the summer.&lt;sup&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#00f&quot;&gt;N-&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;{{Ref label|stumps|4|d}} He did not bat as rain ended the match with Australia at 3/215.&lt;ref name=o/&gt;&lt;ref name=glam&gt;{{Cite web
|url = http://www.cricketarchive.com/Archive/Scorecards/18/18619.html
|title = Glamorgan v Australians
|publisher = [[CricketArchive]]
|accessdate = 2008-12-18}}&lt;/ref&gt; He was rested for the nine-wicket win over [[Warwickshire County Cricket Club|Warwickshire]],&lt;ref name=warwick&gt;{{Cite web
|url = http://www.cricketarchive.com/Archive/Scorecards/18/18634.html
|title = Warwickshire v Australians
|publisher = [[CricketArchive]]
|accessdate = 2008-12-18}}&lt;/ref&gt; before returning for Australia's second match and second draw against [[Lancashire County Cricket Club|Lancashire]].&lt;ref name=sched/&gt;&lt;ref name=o/&gt; Tallon came in at 7/232 and scored 33, adding 63 with [[Ian Johnson (cricketer)|Ian Johnson]] to help Australia reach 321. He took two catches and two stumpings but also conceded 23 byes.&lt;ref name=lancs2&gt;{{Cite web
|url = http://www.cricketarchive.com/Archive/Scorecards/18/18639.html
|title = Lancashire v Australians
|publisher = [[CricketArchive]]
|accessdate = 2008-12-18}}&lt;/ref&gt; In the non-first-class match against [[Durham County Cricket Club|Durham]], Tallon played purely as a batsman, while Saggers kept wicket. He opened the batting, but was dismissed for one as Australia made 273 and the hosts reached 5/73 before rain ended the match.&lt;ref name=durham&gt;{{Cite web
|url = http://www.cricketarchive.com/Archive/Scorecards/18/18654.html
|title = Durham v Australians
|publisher = [[CricketArchive]]
|accessdate = 2008-12-18}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Fifth Test==
{{Main|Fifth Test, 1948 Ashes series}}

Tallon returned for the Fifth Test at [[The Oval]], where England elected to bat first on a rain-affected pitch.&lt;ref name=&quot;report5&quot;&gt;{{Cite web|title= Fifth Test Match England v Australia |work= [[Wisden Cricketers' Almanack]] |year=1949  |url=http://content-aus.cricinfo.com/wisdenalmanack/content/story/152898.html |accessdate=2008-07-02 |publisher=[[Wisden]]}}&lt;/ref&gt; Tallon caught [[Jack Crapp]] from an outside edge for a [[duck (cricket)|duck]] from the bowling of Miller, leaving England at 4/23 as play was adjourned for lunch.&lt;ref name=&quot;sco5&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;p250&quot;&gt;Perry (2005), p. 250.&lt;/ref&gt; England continued to struggle against the moving ball and were all out for 52 in the middle session. The innings ended when Tallon took an acrobatic catch to dismiss [[Len Hutton]] down the [[leg side]], catching it with his left hand. It was considered the catch of the season by ''Wisden''.&lt;ref name=&quot;p200&quot;&gt;Perry, p. 200.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;l103&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;wisden&quot;&gt;{{Cite web| title= ''Wisden'' 1949 &amp;ndash; Don Tallon |url=http://content-www.cricinfo.com/ci/content/story/154630.html| year= 1949 |accessdate=2007-05-31| publisher=[[Wisden]]}}&lt;/ref&gt; Tallon conceded six byes in the innings.&lt;ref name=sco5/&gt;

Australia batted and passed England's total on the first afternoon. Tallon came in to bat on the second day with the score at 7/332, joining opener Morris, who had already passed 150.&lt;ref name=sco5/&gt; It took a [[run out]] to remove Morris; he attempted a quick run to [[Fielding (cricket)#Fielding position names and locations|third man]] after being called through by Tallon but was not quick enough for the substitute fielder's arm,&lt;ref name=&quot;report5&quot;/&gt; leaving Australia at 8/359. Tallon, who scored 31, put on another 30 runs with [[Doug Ring]], before both were out on 389, ending Australia's innings.&lt;ref&gt;Pollard, p. 17.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;f188&quot;&gt;Fingleton, p. 188.&lt;/ref&gt; In the second innings, Tallon caught Hutton from Miller and conceded nine byes as England were dismissed for 188 and lost by an innings, sealing a 4&amp;ndash;0 series victory for Australia.&lt;ref name=sco5/&gt;

==Later tour matches==
Seven matches remained on Bradman's quest to go through a tour of England without defeat.&lt;ref name=sched/&gt; Tallon was rested for three consecutive matches against [[Kent County Cricket Club|Kent]],&lt;ref name=kent&gt;{{Cite web
|url = http://www.cricketarchive.com/Archive/Scorecards/18/18674.html
|title = Kent v Australians
|publisher = [[CricketArchive]]
|accessdate = 2007-12-26}}&lt;/ref&gt; the Gentlemen of England,&lt;ref name=gents&gt;{{Cite web
|url = http://www.cricketarchive.com/Archive/Scorecards/18/18684.html
|title = Gentlemen v Australians
|publisher = [[CricketArchive]]
|accessdate = 2007-12-26}}&lt;/ref&gt; and [[Somerset County Cricket Club|Somerset]],&lt;ref name=sched/&gt;&lt;ref name=o/&gt; all of which Australia won by an innings.&lt;ref name=sched/&gt;&lt;ref name=o/&gt; Saggers stood in and made seven dismissals and conceded 29 byes in the six innings of the three matches.&lt;ref name=kent/&gt;&lt;ref name=gents/&gt;&lt;ref name=somerset&gt;{{Cite web
|url = http://www.cricketarchive.com/Archive/Scorecards/18/18696.html
|title = Somerset v Australians
|publisher = [[CricketArchive]]
|accessdate = 2008-12-18}}&lt;/ref&gt;

He returned for the following match against the [[South of England cricket team|South of England]]. He did not bat as Australia declared at 7/522. He then took three catches and conceded 13 byes as the match was washed out when the hosts were dismissed for 298.&lt;ref name=sched/&gt;&lt;ref name=o/&gt;&lt;ref name=soe&gt;{{Cite web
|url = http://www.cricketarchive.com/Archive/Scorecards/18/18698.html
|title = South of England v Australians
|publisher = [[CricketArchive]]
|accessdate = 2008-12-18}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Australia's biggest challenge in the post-Test tour matches was against the Leveson-Gower's XI. During the last tour in 1938, this team was effectively a full-strength England outfit, but this time Bradman insisted that only six current England Test players be allowed to play for the hosts.&lt;ref name=plg/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Fingleton, pp. 207&amp;ndash;209.&lt;/ref&gt; Bradman then fielded a full-strength team,&lt;ref name=plg&gt;Perry (2005), pp. 253&amp;ndash;254.&lt;/ref&gt; with the only difference from the Fifth Test team being Johnson coming for [[Doug Ring]]. Tallon made two as Australia declared at 8/489. He conceded seven byes and did not make a dismissal as the match ended in a draw after multiple rain delays.&lt;ref name=sco5/&gt;&lt;ref name=lg&gt;{{Cite web
|url = http://www.cricketarchive.com/Archive/Scorecards/18/18706.html
|title = H.D.G. Leveson-Gower's XI v Australians
|publisher = [[CricketArchive]]
|accessdate = 2008-12-18}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The tour ended with two non-first-class matches against [[Scotland national cricket team|Scotland]]. In the first match, Tallon played as a batsman while Saggers kept wicket. Tallon scored only six in Australia's 236 and then took 0/10 in Scotland's second innings and did not take a catch in the innings victory.&lt;ref name=scot1&gt;{{Cite web
|url = http://www.cricketarchive.com/Archive/Scorecards/18/18707.html
|title = Scotland v Australians
|publisher = [[CricketArchive]]
|accessdate = 2008-12-18}}&lt;/ref&gt; In the second match in [[Aberdeen]], Tallon kept wicket, conceding 26 byes and not taking a dismissal and he was not required to bat.&lt;ref name=scot2&gt;{{Cite web
|url = http://www.cricketarchive.com/Archive/Scorecards/18/18709.html
|title = Scotland v Australians
|publisher = [[CricketArchive]]
|accessdate = 2008-12-18}}&lt;/ref&gt; When the match became safe, with Australia in an unassailable position in Scotland's second innings, Bradman allowed Tallon to dispense with his wicket-keeping pads and try his luck at bowling [[leg spin]].&lt;ref name=&quot;p201&quot;&gt;Perry, p. 201.&lt;/ref&gt; Tallon never bowled in his Test career and only rarely in first-class cricket, where he delivered 301 balls, the approximate workload of a specialist bowler in one match.&lt;ref name=&quot;ci&quot;&gt;{{Cite web|title=Players and Officials &amp;ndash; Don Tallon |url=http://content-aus.cricinfo.com/ci/content/player/7913.html |publisher=[[Cricinfo]] |accessdate=2008-01-08}}&lt;/ref&gt; Tallon took 2/15 as Australia finished the tour with another innings win.&lt;ref name=o/&gt;

==Role==
[[Image:Don Tallon graph 1948.png|300px|right|thumb|A chart showing Tallon's batting performance during the tour. The runs scored per innings are represented by the bars, with the red bars being Test innings and the pink bars being other first-class innings. The blue line is the average of the five most recent innings and the dots indicate [[not out]]s.&lt;ref name=o/&gt;]]

Tallon had had moderate success with his batting during the Test series, aggregating 114&amp;nbsp;runs at 28.50.&lt;ref name=&quot;testlist&quot;/&gt; He usually batted at No. 8,&lt;ref name=sco1/&gt;&lt;ref name=sco2/&gt;&lt;ref name=sco3/&gt;&lt;ref name=sco5/&gt; and only had four innings as Australia's batting strength was such that he did not need to bat in the second innings in any of the Tests.&lt;ref name=testlist/&gt; The Australian team strategy of primarily depending on [[fast bowling]] saw Tallon make 12 catches and no stumpings during the Tests.&lt;ref name=&quot;testlist&quot;&gt;{{Cite web
  | work =Statsguru
  | title =D Tallon &amp;ndash; Tests &amp;ndash; Innings by innings list
  | publisher =Cricinfo
  | url =http://statserver.cricket.org/guru?sdb=player;playerid=744;class=testplayer;filter=basic;team=0;opposition=0;notopposition=0;season=0;homeaway=0;continent=0;country=0;notcountry=0;groundid=0;startdefault=1941-06-08;start=1941-06-08;enddefault=1971-02-03;end=1971-02-03;tourneyid=0;finals=0;daynight=0;toss=0;scheduledovers=0;scheduleddays=0;innings=0;result=0;followon=0;seriesresult=0;captain=0;keeper=0;dnp=0;recent=;viewtype=aro_list;runslow=;runshigh=;batposition=0;dismissal=0;bowposition=0;ballslow=;ballshigh=;bpof=0;overslow=;overshigh=;conclow=;conchigh=;wicketslow=;wicketshigh=;dismissalslow=;dismissalshigh=;caughtlow=;caughthigh=;caughttype=0;stumpedlow=;stumpedhigh=;csearch=;submit=1;.cgifields=viewtype
  | accessdate = 2007-07-31 }}&lt;/ref&gt; However, Bradman gave his lead pace bowlers Miller and Lindwall more rest during the tour games to save energy for the Tests,&lt;ref name = &quot;p202&quot;/&gt; and relied more heavily on the [[off spin]] of [[Ian Johnson (cricketer)|Ian Johnson]] and the [[leg spin]] of McCool and [[Doug Ring]] in the county matches. Thus overall Tallon took 29 catches and 14 stumpings for the first-class matches during the tour. Tallon scored 283 runs at 25.72 for the season at an average higher than Saggers's 23.22.&lt;ref name=fc&gt;{{Cite web| url=http://stats.cricinfo.com/ci/engine/records/averages/batting_bowling.html?class=4;id=1070;type=tour |publisher=[[Cricinfo]] |title=Batting and bowling averages Australia tour of England, Apr-Sep 1948 &amp;ndash; First-class matches|accessdate=2008-12-10}}&lt;/ref&gt; In all his matches on tour, Tallon conceded 249 byes as Australia conceded 5331 runs, a bye percentage of 4.67%, compared to Saggers's 221 byes from 6190 runs, a percentage of 3.57%.&lt;sup&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#00f&quot;&gt;N-&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;{{Ref label|stumps|4|d}}

During the tour, Tallon had few opportunities with the bat, generally batting between No. 8 and No. 9,&lt;sup&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#00f&quot;&gt;N-&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;{{Ref label|stumps|4|d}} because Australia's frontline bowlers included the likes of [[Ray Lindwall]], [[Colin McCool]], [[Ian Johnson (cricketer)|Ian Johnson]] and [[Doug Ring]], who were all capable with the bat. Lindwall scored two Test centuries in his career, while McCool scored 18 first-class centuries a including one in Tests. Johnson and Ring both scored more than 20 fifties at first-class level.&lt;ref&gt;Cashman, pp. 152, 175, 199, 258.&lt;/ref&gt; As Australia often won by an innings, and often declared in the first innings, Tallon only had 13 innings in his 14 first-class fixtures and was not out two times as he ran out of partners.&lt;ref name=o/&gt;

Tallon's performances during the English summer saw him named by ''Wisden'' as one of its five [[Wisden Cricketers of the Year|Cricketers of the Year]].&lt;ref name=&quot;p202&quot;&gt;Perry, p. 202.&lt;/ref&gt;

==Notes==
=== Statistical notes ===
&lt;div class=&quot;references-small&quot;&gt;

&lt;span style=&quot;color:#00f;font-variant:small-caps&quot;&gt;n-[1]&lt;/span&gt;
{{note_label|Saggers|1|a}}
This statement regarding byes in the early warm-up matches can be verified by summation of the scorecards, as listed here.&lt;ref name=worcs/&gt;&lt;ref name=leics/&gt;&lt;ref name=york/&gt;&lt;ref name=surrey/&gt;&lt;ref name=essex&gt;{{Cite web
|url = http://www.cricketarchive.com/Archive/Scorecards/18/18429.html
|title = Essex v Australians
|publisher = [[CricketArchive]]
|accessdate = 2008-12-18}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=camb&gt;{{Cite web
|url = http://www.cricketarchive.com/Archive/Scorecards/18/18423.html
|title = Cambridge University v Australians
|publisher = [[CricketArchive]]
|accessdate = 2008-12-18}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=ox&gt;{{Cite web
|url = http://www.cricketarchive.com/Archive/Scorecards/18/18444.html
|title = Oxford University v Australians
|publisher = [[CricketArchive]]
|accessdate = 2008-12-18}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;span style=&quot;color:#00f;font-variant:small-caps&quot;&gt;n-[2]&lt;/span&gt;
{{note_label|MCC|2|a}}
This statement regarding the team composition can be verified by inspecting the records of the respective matches, as attached.&lt;ref name=mcc&gt;{{Cite web
|url = http://www.cricketarchive.com/Archive/Scorecards/18/18451.html
|title = MCC v Australians
|publisher = [[CricketArchive]]
|accessdate = 2008-12-18}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=sco1&gt;{{Cite web| title = 1st Test England v Australia at Nottingham Jun 10&amp;ndash;15 1948|url=http://content-aus.cricinfo.com/ci/engine/match/62685.html|publisher= [[Cricinfo]]|accessdate=2007-12-12}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=sco2&gt;{{Cite web| title = 2nd Test England v Australia at Lord's Jun 24&amp;ndash;29 1948|url=http://content-aus.cricinfo.com/ci/engine/match/62686.html|publisher= [[Cricinfo]]|accessdate=2007-12-12}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=sco3&gt;{{Cite web| title = 3rd Test England v Australia at Manchester Jul 8-13 1948|url=http://content-aus.cricinfo.com/ci/engine/match/62687.html|publisher= [[Cricinfo]]|accessdate=2007-12-12}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=sco4&gt;{{Cite web| title = 4th Test England v Australia at Leeds Jul 22&amp;ndash;27 1948|url=http://content-aus.cricinfo.com/ci/engine/match/62688.html|publisher= [[Cricinfo]]|accessdate=2007-12-12}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=sco5&gt;{{Cite web| title = 5th Test England v Australia at The Oval Aug 14&amp;ndash;18 1948|url=http://content-aus.cricinfo.com/ci/engine/match/62689.html|publisher= [[Cricinfo]]|accessdate=2007-12-12}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;span style=&quot;color:#00f;font-variant:small-caps&quot;&gt;n-[3]&lt;/span&gt;
{{note_label|Warm|3|a}}
This statement regarding byes in the warm-up matches can be verified by summation of the scorecards, as listed here.&lt;ref name=worcs/&gt;&lt;ref name=leics/&gt;&lt;ref name=york/&gt;&lt;ref name=surrey/&gt;&lt;ref name=mcc/&gt;&lt;ref name=notts/&gt;&lt;ref name=lancs/&gt;&lt;ref name=hants/&gt;&lt;ref name=sussex/&gt;&lt;ref name=essex/&gt;&lt;ref name=camb/&gt;&lt;ref name=ox/&gt;

&lt;span style=&quot;color:#00f;font-variant:small-caps&quot;&gt;n-[4]&lt;/span&gt;
{{note_label|stumps|4|d}}
This statement can be verified by consulting all of the scorecards for the matches, as listed here.&lt;ref name=worcs/&gt;&lt;ref name=leics/&gt;&lt;ref name=york/&gt;&lt;ref name=surrey/&gt;&lt;ref name=mcc/&gt;&lt;ref name=notts/&gt;&lt;ref name=lancs/&gt;&lt;ref name=hants/&gt;&lt;ref name=sussex/&gt;&lt;ref name=sco1/&gt;&lt;ref name=northants/&gt;&lt;ref name=york2/&gt;&lt;ref name=sco2/&gt;&lt;ref name=surrey2/&gt;&lt;ref name=gloucs/&gt;&lt;ref name=sco3/&gt;&lt;ref name=middlesex/&gt;&lt;ref name=sco4/&gt;&lt;ref name=derby/&gt;&lt;ref name=glam/&gt;&lt;ref name=warwick/&gt;&lt;ref name=lancs2/&gt;&lt;ref name=durham/&gt;&lt;ref name=sco5/&gt;&lt;ref name=kent/&gt;&lt;ref name=gents/&gt;&lt;ref name=somerset/&gt;&lt;ref name=soe/&gt;&lt;ref name=lg/&gt;&lt;ref name=scot1/&gt;&lt;ref name=scot2/&gt;&lt;ref name=essex/&gt;&lt;ref name=camb/&gt;&lt;ref name=ox/&gt;

===General notes===
{{Reflist|2}}

==References==
*{{Cite book|last=Arlott |first=John |authorlink=John Arlott |year=1949 |title=Gone to the test match : being primarily an account of the test series of 1948  |publisher=Longmans |location=London}}
*{{Cite book| last = Cashman, Richard; Franks, Warwick; [[Jim Maxwell (commentator)|Maxwell, Jim]]; Sainsbury, Erica; Stoddart, Brian; Weaver, Amanda; Webster, Ray | year = 1997 | title = The A&amp;ndash;Z of Australian cricketers| isbn=0-9756746-1-7|location=Melbourne, Victoria |publisher=[[Oxford University Press]]}}
*{{Cite book| last=Fingleton |first=Jack |authorlink=Jack Fingleton |title=Brightly fades the Don |year=1949 |location=London|publisher=Collins}}
* {{Cite book|first=David |last=Lemmon |title=The great wicket-keepers| year=1984 | location=London |publisher=Stanley Paul |isbn=0-09-155210-9}}
*{{Cite book|author=[[Bill O'Reilly (cricketer)|O'Reilly, W. J.]] |year=1949 |title=Cricket conquest: the story of the 1948 test tour |publisher=Werner Laurie |location=London}}
* {{Cite book|first=Roland |last=Perry| authorlink=Roland Perry| title=Bradman's best: Sir Donald Bradman's selection of the best team in cricket history|year=2001 |location=Milsons Point, New South Wales |publisher= [[Random House|Random House Australia]] |isbn=0-09184-051-1}}
*{{Cite book|last=Perry|first=Roland|authorlink=Roland Perry|title=Miller's Luck: the life and loves of Keith Miller, Australia's greatest all-rounder|year=2005|publisher=Random House|location=Milsons Point, New South Wales |isbn=9781741662221}}
*{{Cite book|first=Jack |last=Pollard |authorlink=Jack Pollard|year=1990 |location=North Ryde, New South Wales |publisher=[[Harper Collins]] |title=From Bradman to Border: Australian Cricket 1948&amp;ndash;89 |isbn=0-207-16124-0 &lt;!--0-207-15596-8 The Bradman Years 1918&amp;ndash;1948--&gt;}}
{{The Invincibles squad}}

{{Use dmy dates|date=September 2010}}

{{Good article}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Tallon, Don}}
[[Category:The Invincibles (cricket)]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
