<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="2089047" ns="0" title="U3"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{About|the computer company and design specification}}
{{Infobox company
| company_name = U3 LLC.
| company_logo = [[Image:U3logo.svg|U3 LLC Logo]]
| company_type = [[Private Company|Private]]
| company_slogan = Your digital universe in your pocket.
| foundation = 2004
| location = [[Redwood City, California]]
| industry = [[Computer industry|Computer]]
| homepage = {{url|http://u3.sandisk.com/}}
}}

'''U3''' was a joint venture between [[SanDisk]] and [[M-Systems]] &lt;ref&gt;[http://www.pcmag.com/article2/0,2817,2128799,00.asp Microsoft, SanDisk to Replace U3 Drives], PC Magazine, May 11, 2007 11.46 a.m. EST.&lt;/ref&gt;, producing a [[proprietary software|proprietary]] method of launching Windows applications from special [[USB flash drive]]s. Flash drives adhering to the U3 specification are termed &quot;'''U3 smart drives'''&quot;. 
U3 smart drives come preinstalled with the '''U3 Launchpad''', which looks similar to the [[Windows OS]] start menu and controls program installation. Applications that comply with U3 specifications are allowed to write [[Computer file|files]] or [[Windows registry|registry]] information to the host computer, but they must remove this information when the flash drive is ejected. Customizations and settings are instead stored with the application on the flash drive.

[[Microsoft]] and [[SanDisk]] created a successor called [[StartKey]].

SanDisk began phasing out support for U3 Technology in late 2009.&lt;ref&gt;[http://kb.sandisk.com/app/answers/detail/a_id/5358/kw/u3%202009/r_id/101834 SanDisk knowledge base article about end of U3 support]&lt;/ref&gt;

== U3 platform ==
=== U3 disk mounting: hardware emulation ===
A U3 flash drive presents itself to the host system as a [[USB hub]] with a CD drive and standard [[USB mass storage device class|USB mass storage device]] attached.&lt;ref name=&quot;Technet 137730&quot;&gt;[http://technet.microsoft.com/en-us/magazine/cc137730.aspx How Flash Drives and Social Engineering can Compromise Networks], ''Microsoft Technet Magazine'', January 2008.&lt;/ref&gt;
* This configuration causes Windows disk management to show two drives:
*# A read-only [[ISO 9660]] volume on an emulated CD-ROM drive with an [[autorun]] configuration to execute the U3 LaunchPad, and;
*# A standard flash drive ([[File Allocation Table|FAT]] formatted) that includes a hidden &quot;SYSTEM&quot; folder with installed applications.
* U3 compliant applications can be (optionally) preloaded by manufacturers.

=== U3 Launchpad ===
[[Image:U3launch.PNG|right|thumb|216px|U3 Launch Pad example.]]

The U3 Launchpad (LaunchU3.exe) is a [[Microsoft Windows|Windows]] program manager that is preinstalled on every U3 smart drive.&lt;ref name=&quot;kb85&quot;&gt;[https://u3.custhelp.com/cgi-bin/u3.cfg/php/enduser/std_adp.php?p_faqid=85 U3 Knowledge Base: Can I access the Documents directory on my U3 smart drive without running the U3 Launchpad?]{{Dead link|date=December 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The U3 Launchpad automatically starts at insertion of a U3 enabled device.

=== U3 applications ===
To be fully U3 compliant, an application has to be programmed to clean up its own data from the local machine. It must also be packaged in U3's special program format.  U3 applications will only run from a U3 device. U3 programs can be downloaded from the U3 website and other places. Applications include [[Opera (browser)|Opera]] and [[Skype]] and do not need to be installed on the computer.

==== APIs ====
The U3 [[application programming interface]]s (APIs) allows U3 programs lower-level access to USB flash drive, and to query the drive letter. The U3 APIs primarily allow developers who choose to use more of the power of U3 to control how their application handles things like device removal and saves data back to the drive such as configuration or documents.

=== Compatibility ===
The latest version of U3 launchpad supports [[Windows 2000]] with Service Pack 4, [[Windows XP]], [[Windows Vista]] and [[Windows 7]]. 

Data can be accessed using any OS capable of reading from USB mass storage devices, unless the U3 device is password-protected.&lt;ref group=&quot;note&quot; name=&quot;kb&quot;&gt;[http://kb.sandisk.com/app/answers/detail/a_id/232 U3 Launchpad Application], SanDisk.com. &quot;If the OS in question can normally see ordinary USB flash drives, then the U3 smart drive removable mass storage area (domain) should still be available for standard file system activities unless it is a private area protected by a password.&quot;&lt;/ref&gt;

===Issues with older versions===
Early versions of the U3 launchpad software had Vista compatibility issues (specifically the SanDisk Cruzer Titanium series with device numbers 2.17, 2.18, 2.19 and 2.20), although this problem could be eliminated by updating the launcher software.&lt;ref&gt;[http://communities.sandisk.com/sandisk/board/message?board.id=u3&amp;thread.id=237 Vista driver? Cruzers with U3], Community Forum at SanDisk.com&lt;/ref&gt; Prior to Sandisk's updated launcher software being released, Microsoft supported U3 by releasing an update to Vista (KB940199).&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.microsoft.com/downloads/details.aspx?familyid=51F0EF25-280B-4613-A600-C61224BACD1C&amp;displaylang=en Update for Windows Vista (KB940199)], microsoft.com&lt;/ref&gt;

== Developer resources ==
Information on building U3 compliant applications and the U3 [[Software Development Kit|software development kit]] are available to registered developers at the official U3 website. Individuals must register (as a company) to download the SDK, or participate in the forums.&lt;ref&gt;[https://u3.custhelp.com/cgi-bin/u3.cfg/php/enduser/std_adp.php?p_faqid=52 U3 Forum registration guidelines]{{Dead link|date=December 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; Applications that do not require installation steps in order to run can easily utilize U3 with little or no modification by taking steps to either not modify the host systems files or registry, or undoing all changes when the application terminates. A wizard which packages your distribution files and creates the special &quot;manifest&quot; file is provided.

== Removal ==
Reformatting the drive will remove some of the software (the hidden &quot;SYSTEM&quot; folder), but not all of it. The virtual CD-ROM drive cannot be removed by reformatting because it is presented to the host system as a physical device attached to a USB hub;&lt;ref name=&quot;Technet 137730&quot; /&gt; the official U3 Launchpad Removal Software was available on the U3 website and disabled the virtual CD drive device, leaving only the [[USB mass storage device class|USB mass storage device]] active on the U3 USB hub controller, at which point the remaining software can be removed by a subsequent format, performed by the removal software itself. The [http://u3.sandisk.com/launchpadremoval.htm removal tool] is available from SanDisk's website.
&lt;!-- http://www.everythingusb.com/u3.html : more info maybe
Applications without U3 that run on USB flash drives: http://www.kikizas.net/en/usbapps.html --&gt;

[http://u3-tool.sourceforge.net/ U3 tool] is another option that includes the ability to remove the virtual CD-ROM drive, as well as ways to reconfigure it to your liking.

== Benefits ==
[[File:ToshibaUSB.jpg|right|thumb|300px|A Toshiba 2&amp;nbsp;GB ''TransMemory'' Flash Drive, sold with U3 functionality pre-installed on the [[USB drive]].]]
;Portability: This software automatically attempts installation of U3 components (U3 Launchpad) on the hard disk drive and associated System Registry entries on the Host Computer.  Afterwards the U3 software can be taken with all its personalized settings to any computer running a compatible version of Microsoft Windows (though no other operating system), with no need to install the software if not already there, or to use different settings and options, the initialization Host computer requires Administrative privileges and no need for administrator access privileges on subsequent computers.{{Citation needed|date=January 2009}}
;Integration with existing Windows look and feel: Programs are run from the Launchpad, functionally similar to the Windows Start menu familiar to most users of Windows XP.
;No need of admin rights on other computers: New software can be installed to a U3 flash drive without the requirement for administrative privileges on the host computer. Note: Portable software can be used just the similar way, without the need for U3.
;Virus protection: Many U3 drives come with [[computer virus|virus protection software]].
;Data security: Most U3 drives on the market feature a security lock within the U3 Launchpad. This loads the CD partition first and can be user-configured to require a password to be entered; otherwise the data partition will not load. The drive is supposed to seal itself after a certain number of invalid password entries, requiring a reformat.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.everythingusb.com/u3.html U3 Newbie Guide&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt; Note: Wide range of 3rd party [[disk encryption software]] exist that can used to achieve similar functionality without need for U3 (such as [[FreeOTFE]], [[TrueCrypt]], [[BestCrypt]] etc).
;Emulation of a CD-Rom drive: Emulating a CD-Rom drive allows booting PCs from U3 enabled Flash Drives which do not support booting from USB flash natively.
::Using the open-source [[U3 Tool]], a bootable ISO image can be copied onto the flash memory that will be presented to the PC as a USB CD-Rom drive to boot from.

== Criticisms ==
{{Section OR|date=September 2008}}
Numerous criticisms have been made of the U3 platform. These criticisms are:
;Malware-like integration behaviour: Software comes preinstalled on USB disk and, when using stock windows settings, roots itself in the system similar to malware. U3 removal is possible, but requires complete data backup.

;Questioned use: There are already portable versions of many windows software available, [[portableapps.com|some of which]] do not require any proprietary solution to work.

;Removed user data, but not all of it: Recent files and programs had it listed.&lt;!-- Need more info --&gt;

;Freezing with certain CD writing software: There is a possibility of slowing down or freezing Windows XP Pro if certain Windows drivers that are associated with high-volume data transfers to CD writers using certain CD/DVD burning software installed (Nero v7 and Roxio DirectCD&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.u3.com/support/default.aspx#CQ1 The U3 Launchpad doesn't run. What should I do?]{{Dead link|date=December 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;)

;Proprietary format / closed platform: The U3 platform is a &quot;closed&quot; platform / proprietary format, and unavailable for developers.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.u3.com/developers/default.aspx {{Dead link|date=August 2010}} &quot;At this point we do not accept any new releases. Thank you U3.com&quot;&lt;/ref&gt; [[SanDisk]], the rightsholders for U3, ask for a 5% royalty from USB flash drive manufacturers who wish to implement the platform on their products.

;Two drive letters: As a work-around to the lack of Auto-Play for Flash drives on older versions of Windows, the U3 software creates two drive letters (one which presents itself as a CD to allow Windows' auto-play to start the launcher, and another for storing user data). Although this is the only way to implement auto-start functionality on pre-Windows XP systems, it could be considered a [[kludge]], and the extra drive letter created can be an annoyance. However, it is possible to prevent Windows from allocating a drive letter for the &quot;CD drive&quot; via the Windows &quot;Disk Management&quot; tool—as long as the user has the appropriate rights/authority to do so.

;Incompatibility with certain embedded systems: Some host systems &amp;ndash; such as photo kiosks, consumer electronics, and other [[embedded computing]] devices &amp;ndash; cannot correctly mount U3 &quot;smart drives.&quot;  The problem may arise because the emulated CD-ROM is the first drive presented to the host system.  As such, the device is detected as a CD-ROM drive or not at all.  Although some newer photo kiosks are U3 aware&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.everythingusb.com/u3c-15358.html U3 Drives Finally Get Along with Photo Kiosks]&lt;/ref&gt; and can overcome this limitation, it still exists on many platforms.

== See also ==
* [[USB flash drive]]
* [[List of portable software]]
* [[Portable application creators]]
* [[Live USB]]
* [[Live CD]]
* [[Comparison of application launchers]]
* [[Windows To Go]]

== Notes ==
{{Reflist|group=note}}

== References ==
{{Reflist|2}}

== External links ==
* {{Official|http://u3.sandisk.com/}}
* [http://www.pcmag.com/article2/0,1895,1861720,00.asp PC Magazine] reviews of the U3 Launcher, and programs (has screenshots)
* [http://www.everythingusb.com/u3.html U3 Newbie Guide]
* [http://www.u3-info.com/ U3 Community] (U3-Info: news, articles, forums, etc.)
* [http://u3-tool.sourceforge.net/ u3-tool, open source u3 managing tool]

[[Category:USB]]
[[Category:Package management systems]]
[[Category:Companies established in 2004]]
[[Category:Portable software]]
[[Category:Portable software suites]]

[[de:U3 (Standard)]]
[[es:U3]]
[[fr:Clé USB U3]]
[[it:U3 (informatica)]]
[[lt:U3]]
[[nl:U3 (computerstandaard)]]
[[ja:U3]]
[[no:U3]]
[[pl:U3]]
[[pt:U3]]
[[ru:U3]]
[[sl:U3]]
[[fi:U3-USB-muisti]]
[[sv:U3]]
[[tr:U3]]
[[uk:U3]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
