<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="20897374" ns="0" title="15 Field Ambulance"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Infobox military unit
|unit_name= 15 (Edmonton) Field Ambulance
|caption=Crest of the Canadian Forces Medical Services
|image=
|dates= 1939–present
|country= [[Canada]]
|branch= Military Personnel Command
|type= [[Canadian Forces Health Services Group]]
|role=Medical
|size=Company
|command_structure=1 Health Services Group
|garrison=  Brigadier James Curry Jefferson Building
|motto= ''Militi Succurrimus'' (We Hasten to Aid the Soldier)
|colors=
|march=Farmer's Boy
|mascot=
|battles=
|notable_commanders=
|anniversaries=
|commander1=Lieutenant-Colonel Roger Scott, CD, AdeC
|commander1_label=Commanding Officer
|commander2=Chief Warrant Officer Mark Noble, CD
|commander2_label=Regimental Sergeant Major
|commander3=Colonel, The Honourable Allan H. Wachowich, QC, LLD
|commander3_label=Honorary Colonel
|commander4=Vacant
|commander4_label=Honorary Lieutenant-Colonel
}}

'''15 (Edmonton) Field Ambulance''' (15 (Edm) Fd Amb) is a [[Canadian Forces]] [[Primary Reserve]] medical unit headquartered in [[Edmonton]] with a detachment (15 (Edmonton) Field Ambulance Detachment Calgary) in [[Calgary]]. The unit mission is to attract, train, force generate and retain high quality health service personnel to provide health service support (HSS) to 41 CBG and to augment CF domestic and international operations. An additional and important activity is to participate in activities that will raise our profile in our communities.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.army.dnd.ca/15MEDICAL_COMPANY/content_e.htm 15 Field Ambulance Homepage]&lt;/ref&gt;

==History==
15 (Edmonton) Field Ambulane's lineage originates with No. 4 Casualty Clearing Station mobilized in December 1939 as one of the medical units of the 1st Canadian Division for service overseas during the second world war. No. 4 CSS departed Halifax on 30 Jan 1940 embarked in the Empress of Britain and disembarked along the Clyde on 8 Feb 40. The unit was directed to Aldershot were it spent the next three years. The medical services of No. 4 CCS during the windter of 1941-42 were provided in a large country house that accommodated 130 patients. Patients expected to be ill for more than three or four days were transferred from a field ambulance to the CCS.

During the Dieppe raid, No. 4 CCS remained in Dorking, England. Casualties from the battle were evacuated by landing craft back to the casualty reception area at Portsmouth and No. 4 CCS handled the walking wounded.

In 1943 No.4 CCS was sent to Sicily and opented in Catania providing care for sick and injured Canadian soldiers. The unit followed the battle of the 1st Canadian Corps through Ortona to the Gustav Line, on to the Hitler Line and Northern Italy. In 1945, the unit moved to Maresilles, France and to Belgium and finally into Holland. No. 4 CCS opened with attached surgicial and transfusion units in Brackenstein, near Nijmeagon.

At war's end, No. 4 CCS returned to Canada and was re-designated No. 36 Casualty Celaraing Station in the milita. In 1954, the unit was once again re-designated No. 23 Medical Comapnay (Royal Canadian Army Medical Corps). 23 Med Coy trained to achieve the highest standards and won the Ryerson Trophy each year from 1961–1964, and 1972-1974.

In 1978 No. 23 Medical Company was once again redesignated as 15 (Edmonton) Medical Company. In 1991, 14 Medical Platoon of 14 (Calgary) Service Battalion was reassigned and became 15 (Edmonton) Medical Company Detachmet Calgary. In 2004, subsequent to the reorganization of all Canadian Forces medical and dental units into the Canadian Forces Health Services Group, the militia medical companies were re-designated and organized as Reserve field ambulances and the unit became 15 (Edmonton) Field Ambulance with its detachment 15 (Edmonton) Field Ambulance Detachment Calgary.&lt;ref&gt;Unit history, Department of National Defence, http://www.army.dnd.ca/15MEDICAL_COMPANY/history.htm&lt;/ref&gt;

==Present day==
15 (Edm) Fd Amb is a unit of 1 Health Services Group and under operational control (OPCON) of  [[41 Canadian Brigade Group]], consisting of all Alberta Army Reserve personnel.  As a Canadian Forces (CF) Primary Reserve unit, members may serve on a full or part-time basis.  Deployments are voluntary, and personnel continue to serve alongside Regular Force CF members.  The [[Edmonton]] unit is based at Brigadier James Curry Jefferson Bldg, and in [[Calgary]] at the North East Armoury. The current commanding officer (6 Oct 2007) is Lieutenant-Colonel Roger Scott of Edmonton.&lt;ref&gt;CO’s news release, www.army.dnd.ca/lfwa_hq/Documents/2008/Statement_15_FieldAmb_Starker.pdf -&lt;/ref&gt;

==Notable members==
===Past Honorary Colonels===

Colonel James Donald Johnston, CD, MD, MSc, FRCP(C) (2003–2006)

Colonel Kenneth Angus Munn, CD, QHP, MD, FRCP(C) (1993–2003)

Colonel Harald A.J. Schwarz, CD, MD, CCFP, FCFP

===Past Honorary Lieutenant-Colonels===
Lieutenant-Colonel Sandra J. Munn (2005–2011)

Lieutenant-Colonel Kenneth Angus Munn, CD, QHP, MD, FRCP(C) (1991–1993)

Lieutenant-Colonel Robert James Sinclair Gibson

Lieutenant-Colonel R.C. Bray

Lieutenant-Colonel Harald A. Schwarz, CD, MD, CCFP, FCFP

===World War II===
{{Empty section|date=January 2011}}

===Post World War II–1999===

Col. H.A.J. Schwarz KStJ CD MD

Cpl. Michael Starker - Born Jan 01, 1972 Died May 6, 2008, [[Pashmul]] Region, [[Zhari]] district (25&amp;nbsp;km west of [[Kandahar]]) [[Afghanistan]] - was both a soldier and a Calgary Emergency Medical Services paramedic.&lt;ref&gt;Calgary Sun http://www.calgarysun.com/news/alberta/2009/11/10/11702351.html&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Cpl. Michael Starker Online Tribute and Memorial Website http://www.respectance.com/Cpl_Michael_Starker/&lt;/ref&gt;

==Awards==
[[Freedom of the City]] of Edmonton and Calgary.

==Operations==
15 Field Ambulance members have deployed in many Domestic and International Operations including:

Op ATHENA (Afghanistan)

Op PODIUM (2010 Olympic Games, British Columbia)

Op ARCHER (Afghanistan)

Op PEREGRINE (2003 Brisith Columbia Forest Fires)

Op DANACA (Golan Heights)

Op PALLADIUM (Bosnia-Herzegovina)

United Nations Emergency Force (UNEF) (Egypt)

==Royal Canadian Army Cadets==
15 (Edmonton) Field Ambulance is affiliated with 2995 Med Coy RCACC, based in [[Lac La Biche]], [[Alberta]].&lt;ref&gt;Locations | Army Cadet League of Canada (Alberta), http://www.armycadetleagueab.ca/locations&lt;/ref&gt;

==References==
{{Reflist}}

==External links==
* [http://www.forces.gc.ca/health-sante/ CFMS History/Heritage Page.]
* [http://www.forces.gc.ca/health-sante/pub/hist/default-eng.asp Canadian Forces Medical Service : Introduction to its History and Heritage.]
* [http://www.k2000k2.com Troop and Family Support Awareness Fundraiser]
* [http://www.warmuseum.ca Canadian War Museum.]

{{Canadian Forces}}
{{Canadian Forces Land Force Command}}

[[Category:Canadian Forces Medical Service]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
