<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="20903684" ns="0" title="List of minor Emmerdale characters (2008)"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{DISPLAYTITLE:List of minor ''Emmerdale'' characters (2008)}}
{{Emmerdaleminor}}
The following is a '''list of minor characters''' that first appeared in the [[United Kingdom|British]] [[soap opera]] '''''[[Emmerdale]]''''' in 2008, by order of first appearance.

{{TOC limit|limit=2}}
{{-}}

==Shane Doyle==
{{Infobox soap character
|series=Emmerdale
|image=&lt;!-- Deleted image removed: [[Image:shaneyboy.jpg]]  --&gt;
|color=#99CCCC
|name=Shane Doyle
|portrayer=[[Paul McEwan (actor)|Paul McEwan]]
|years=2008
|first=4 January 2008
|last=3 December 2008
|born=1980
|death=1 December 2008
|romances=[[Jasmine Thomas]] (2008)
|occupation=[[Police officer]]
}}
'''Shane Doyle''' was a local policeman and colleague of [[Donna Windsor-Dingle]] and [[Ross Kirk]]. He appeared throughout 2008. 

Shane first appears on 4 January 2008 when he investigates [[Zak Dingle|Zak]], [[Shadrach Dingle|Shadrach]] and [[Eli Dingle]] for pretending to be police officers and scamming people. When Donna joins the police, Shane takes an immediate dislike to her due to her being related by marriage to the Dingle family. He also has resentment having been looked over for promotion several times. Shane continues to bully Donna, while appearing friendly with others. In spring 2008, Donna decides to put the past behind them and become friends with him. However, he takes this for more and tries to kiss her. Before she could tell their boss [[Charles Vaughan (Emmerdale)|Charles Vaughan]], Doyle tells him that Donna forced herself upon him. Donna choses not to file a complaint as Vaughan warns it could effect her career. 

Shane does not appear again for some months, until August when he visits Donna in hospital after a car crash. He handles the investigation into her conduct and ensures she does not receive a harsh punishment. Shane then turns his attentions to [[Jasmine Thomas]], and causes her to split from her boyfriend [[Jake Doland]] after Shane lies and tells him that he had slept with Jasmine, causing Jake to punch Shane and get himself arrested. Jasmine, a [[journalist]], starts getting close to Shane in order to get information on the McFarlanes, a local criminal family. Unbeknown to her, Shane is paid by the McFarlanes, but she believes him when he denies this. They soon start to get closer. He meanwhile blackmails Ross and Donna after finding out they are having an affair.

However, eventually Jasmine has doubts and on 2 December finds drugs and thousands of pounds in Shane's flat. When Shane returns home, Jasmine tries to leave after talking to him, but he stops her and tries to force himself upon her. Jasmine's friend, [[Debbie Dingle]], arrives and attacks Shane in an attempt to protect Jasmine, knocking him unconscious. As soon as he comes to, he attacks Debbie, so Jasmine hits him repeatedly with a chair leg, killing him. In shock, Debbie and Jasmine get Debbie's first cousin, once removed, Eli, to help them dispose of the body in a local lake. They book a plane ticket using Shane's credit card and make it appear that he had gone on holiday during his time off work. Weeks later when Shane does not return to work, an investigation starts and it comes to light that he was being paid by the McFarlanes. On Christmas Day, [[Victoria Sugden]] sees Shane's body when she falls in the frozen-over lake, but everyone believes she imagined it. Five days later, Victoria and [[Daz Eden]] go back to the lake, and Shane's body surfaces. In early January 2009, [[Ross Kirk]] is charged with his murder, however, by the end of the month, Eli is arrested and he later reveals what happened in order to avoid being charged himself. Debbie is later arrested but Jasmine runs away. Debbie is charged with murder. In early March, Jasmine returns and confesses that she killed Shane in order to clear Debbie's name. Jasmine is sentenced to four years imprisonment for manslaughter, while Debbie is jailed for six months for perverting the course of justice.

==Charlie Sellers==
{{Infobox soap character
|series=Emmerdale
|color=#99CCCC
|name=Charlie Sellers
|portrayer=Michael Keogh
|years=2008
|first=8 January 2008
|last=18 March 2008
}}
'''Charlie Sellers''' is a cellmate of [[Andy Sugden]]. He appeared in 2008.

Charlie first appears when Andy Sugden is sent to prison for the arson attack which killed his adoptive mother [[Sarah Sugden]]. He makes Andy's life a misery, and Andy attacks him after he suggests Andy's wife [[Jo Sugden|Jo]] could be having an affair without him. 

When Charlie is released, he begins harassing Jo. On 7 March, he moves into Jo and Andy's farm, threatening Jo if she tells anyone. Jo eventually works with [[Debbie Dingle]] and [[Chas Dingle]]
to get rid of him. They convince [[List of minor Emmerdale characters (2007)#Brenda McFarlane|Brenda McFarlane]] to help them. Jo convinces Charlie to steal from a club owned by the McFarlanes, a local family of criminals, with Chas helping him. The idea is that Charlie will get caught by the police while Chas escapes. However, Charlie holds the bar manager hostage at gunpoint, and both escape. Mrs. McFarlane later appears with a 'heavy' and demands the stolen money back. She tells him to leave and never return and he has no choice but to agree.
&lt;br clear=&quot;right&quot; /&gt;

==Nick Baine==
{{Infobox soap character
|series=Emmerdale
|color=#99CCCC
|name=Nick Baine
|portrayer=[[Samuel Kane|Sam Kane]]
|years=2008
|spouse=[[Carrie Baine|Carrie Nicholls]] (2008-)
|first=10 January 2008
|last=5 February 2008
|residence=[[Canada]]
}}

'''Nick Baine''' was the ex-boyfriend of [[Carrie Nicholls]]. He appeared in 2008. Sam Kane, who played Nick, is married to [[Linda Lusardi]], who played Carrie.

Nick first appears in January 2008 to offer Carrie, his former partner, a job and new life in [[Canada]]. Having grown dissatisfied with life in the village, Carrie is eager to go and start a new life. However, her daughter Scarlett does not want to leave, partly because of her relationship with [[Daz Eden]]. Carrie turns down Nick's offer, but he can not stay away and they soon resumed their relationship. On 5 February 2008, Nick and Carrie leave Emmerdale for Canada. 

They marry in August 2008 in [[Thailand]], with Carrie's daughters, [[Lexi King|Lexi]] and [[Scarlett Nicholls|Scarlett]] present.
&lt;br clear=&quot;right&quot; /&gt;

==Cindy Burton==
{{Infobox soap character
|series=Emmerdale
|color=#99CCCC
|name=Cindy Burton
|portrayer=[[Tiffany Chapman]]
|years=2008
|first=5 February 2008
|last=March 2008
|occupation=[[Actress]]
}}
'''Cindy Burton''' is an actress employed by [[Donald De Souza]]. She appeared in 2008. 

Following Donald leaving hospital after a [[Cerebral hemorrhage|brain haemorrhage]], Cindy is hired to look after him while he recovers. However, Donald hires Cindy to annoy his wife [[Nicola De Souza|Nicola]], who he knows has had an affair with [[David Metcalfe]], who flirts with Cindy himself, much to Nicola’s irritation. After a few weeks, Nicola learns the true nature of Cindy's employment. She tries her best to use Cindy in her plan to kill Donald. This includes one attempt where Cindy takes pills meant for Donald in a set-up where Cindy would have taken the blame. When Donald learns all this, he makes Nicola leave his house. Cindy, meanwhile, leaves the village as she is no longer needed by Donald and is keen to move on.
&lt;br clear=&quot;right&quot; /&gt;

==Joe Jacobs==
{{Infobox soap character
|series=Emmerdale
|color=#99CCCC
|name=Joe Jacobs
|portrayer=[[John Woodvine]]
|years=2008
|first=20 February 2008
|last=20 May 2008
|occupation=Retired Naval captain
}}

'''Joe Jacobs''' is an old friend of [[Sandy Thomas]]. He appeared in 2008.

Soon after arriving, he flirts with [[Betty Eagleton]], who Sandy had got close to. Months later he reappears when Betty and [[Pearl Ladderbanks]] try [[speed dating]] at the Woolpack. Pearl quickly gets fond of Joe but she thinks his affection is only because she has a spare ticket for a cruise she has won. Pearl chooses to take [[Lily Butterfield]] on the cruise, but Joe drops a suitcase on her foot as he thinks she is being too demanding. Pearl then chooses Joe to go with her on the cruise and he tells her how fond of her he is. When Pearl returns from the cruise without Joe, she reluctantly tells her friends that he had been kicked off the cruise for rude behaviour.
&lt;br clear=&quot;right&quot; /&gt;

==Adele Allfrey==
{{Infobox soap character 2
|series=Emmerdale
|color=#99CCCC
|name=Adele Allfrey
|portrayer=Tanya Vital
|occupation=Factory worker
|years=2008–2010
|first=11 August 2008
|last=5 October 2010
|romances=[[Andy Sugden]] (2010)
}}

'''Adele Allfrey''' was a worker at Sharma and Sharma sweet factory. She appeared from 2008 to 2010, and was played by Tanya Vital.

After [[Eric Pollard]]'s staff go on strike, He places an advert for more staff. After having an interview, Adele is given a job along with [[Leyla Harding]]. Adele gets on well with the other workers and joins them in playing practical jokes on their supervisor, [[Lexi King]]. One day, Adele does not show up for work, and Lexi tells them she had fired Adele as a warning to everyone else to keep their focus on their job. The next day, they learn Adele had actually taken leave to help her sick mother, and she soon returns to work. She loses her job in July 2009 when Eric closes the factory due to a loss in business. She then got her current job at the new sweet factory when it opened in Emmerdale in the summer of 2009.

In the summer of 2010, Adele had a brief fling with [[Andy Sugden]], but the romance was cut short when his ex-wife and Adele's friend [[Katie Sugden|Katie]] admitted sleeping with him. Katie's betrayal then prompted Adele to quit her job and leave the village.
&lt;br clear=&quot;right&quot; /&gt;

==Bonnie Drinkwater==
{{Infobox soap character
|series=Emmerdale
|color=#99CCCC
|name=Bonnie Drinkwater
|portrayer=[[Sue Jenkins]]
|years=2008
|first=25 August 2008
|last=29 August 2008
}}
'''Bonnie Drinkwater''' is a holiday friend of [[Val Pollard]]. She appeared in 2008.

She arrives in Emmerdale, having met Val in [[Cancún]], [[Mexico]], and her stories of her and Val's drunken holiday antics soon annoy Val but interest Val's husband [[Eric Pollard|Eric]], who Bonnie starts to flirt with. Val then spends more and more time with Bonnie to keep her away from Eric. After a few days, Bonnie tells Val that during the holiday, Val slept with a much younger man called Derek, a name she has tattooed on her back, although Val does not remember this. Val then feels blackmailed because if she tells Bonnie to leave the village, she fears she will tell Eric of her affair. Later that day, she gets drunk with [[Douglas Potts|Doug Potts]], whose wife had just said she wanted a [[divorce]], and she tells him to start living his life, causing him to buy a very expensive car the following day.

Val's son, [[Paul Lambert (Emmerdale)|Paul Lambert]], orders Bonnie to ring her daughter so she can leave, but later discovers that she rung the [[Speaking clock#United Kingdom|Talking Clock]]. Bonnie then confesses that she has no daughter, and is a spinster who lives in a one-bedroom flat in [[Barnsley]], and Val is her only friend. She had also made up Val sleeping with Derek. Seeing her as a pathetic, clinger-on, Paul tells her to leave the village. Shortly after she drives away in Doug's car, and then spends the night with him at the Vicarage. The following day he tries to get rid of her, but is only successful when [[Ashley Thomas]] tells her that if she is to stay at the Vicarage it will have to be in separate rooms and with no alcohol. It is later revealed Doug had contracted [[crabs]] from Bonnie.

==Danielle Hutch==
{{Infobox soap character
|series=Emmerdale
|color=#99CCCC
|name=Danielle Hutch
|portrayer=[[Nicola Stapleton]]
|years=2008, 2009
|first=23 September 2008
|last=3 March 2009 
}}

'''Danielle Hutch''' is a friend of [[Eli Dingle]]. She appeared from 2008 to 2009.

Danielle first appears in 2008 when Eli nearly runs her over on a road near Emmerdale. They previously knew each other, and had been romantically involved. She stays at the Dingles' house overnight, but Debbie soon finds her with [[cocaine]] in her bag. She is later arrested when caught by [[List of minor Emmerdale characters (2008)#Shane Doyle|PC Shane Doyle]] and taken to [[London]]. 

Danielle reappears in November 2008 when she is spotted working for the McFarlane's, a local criminal family, who paid Doyle to work for them. She warns [[Jasmine Thomas]], who is trying to do some investigative journalism, to stay away from Shane and the McFarlanes. Danielle also helps the Dingles rescue [[List of minor Emmerdale characters (2003)#Aaron Livesy|Aaron Livesy]] from the McFarlanes' house. In February 2009, Danielle arrives in the same prison wing as [[Debbie Dingle]], who has been charged with murdering Shane Doyle. When Eli visits, she explains that after helping the Dingles, the McFarlanes set her up by planting things on her. Eli persuades Danielle to have a fight with Debbie, so they both get sent to hospital. The following week, Eli and [[Marlon Dingle|Marlon]] dress up and knock out the officers guarding Debbie and Danielle. Debbie refuses to go with them, but Danielle escapes. However, the following day, the police catch her just as her bus is about to depart.

==Andrew Drake==
{{Infobox soap character
|series=Emmerdale
|color=#99CCCC
|name=Andrew Drake
|portrayer=Steven Hillman
|occupation=Police sergeant
|years=2008&amp;ndash;2009
|first=21 October 2008
|last=30 January 2009
}}

'''Sergeant Andrew Drake''' is a police officer. He appeared from 2008 to 2009.

He decides not to discipline PCs [[Donna Windsor-Dingle]] and [[List of minor Emmerdale characters (2007)#Charlotte Beecham|Charlotte Beecham]] when they break into [[List of minor Emmerdale characters (2008)#Shane Doyle|PC Shane Doyle]]'s flat when he goes missing. Shortly after is put in charge of the investigation into Doyle's disppearance by [[List of minor Emmerdale characters (2006)#Charles Vaughan|Charles Vaughan]]. This investigation soon ends when Shane's body is found on 30 December 2008. In late January, Drake tries to persuade Donna not to accept a transfer, but is unable to convince her to stay.
&lt;br clear=&quot;right&quot; /&gt;

==Mick Naylor==
{{Infobox soap character
|series=Emmerdale
|color=#99CCCC
|image1= 
|caption1= Tony Haygarth as Mick Naylor in 2009.
|name=Mick Naylor
|portrayer=[[Tony Haygarth]]
|first=3 November 2008
|last=12 June 2009
|years=2008&amp;ndash;2009
|occupation=Farm hand
|spouse=Carol Naylor
|grandchildren=[[List of recurring and minor Emmerdale characters#Lee Naylor|Lee Naylor]]
}}

'''Mick Naylor''' is a farm hand who later works in the Woolpack. He appeared from 2008 to 2009.

He first appears on 3 November 2008 when he visits Jo Sugden at Butlers Farm. He complains that her broken fence has caused cows to go onto his boss' farm. Mick then demands compensation after its discovered that [[Sam Dingle]] sold some of Mick's cows by accident. The following day, Mick returns with his grandson [[List of recurring and minor Emmerdale characters#Lee Naylor|Lee]] and they soon fix their differences. In the following weeks, Mick and Lee help Jo out on the farm following her separation from abusive husband [[Andy Sugden|Andy]]. Jo and Lee start to get on well, and in mid-December Mick warns Lee not to spend too much time flirting with her. By late December, with Lee's help, Jo has decided to sell off most of the farm and leave Emmerdale. With Lee helping her, everything goes fine until Mick turns up. Jo locks him in the barn so he cannot stop her from leaving. He is not discovered until the following morning. 

In February 2009, [[Diane Sugden]] pays Mick to help [[Andy Sugden|Andy]] out on the farm, although Andy is not keen on this. When Andy decides to leave the farm, Mick asks [[Natasha Wylde]] if he can lease the farm of her. She agrees to this on a temporary basis. However, before this can be formalised Andy changes his mind and decides to keep the farm. The following day Diane offers him a job in the Woolpack, which he accepts. In April he admits to poaching from the Home Farm estate, and setting a trap that trapped Lee's foot, causing him to be rushed to hospital. Later that month he leaves the Woolpack to start helping at the farm again, after [[Val Pollard]] asked Andy to employ as she was getting annoyed with him. In May, he becomes homeless after getting into debt with his rent. He moves into Emmerdale's B&amp;B. In June, as Andy begins to suffer a mental breakdown, he pays less and less attention to the farm. Mick, frustrated with the pointless attempts to keep Andy going, quits, and gets a job in Robblesfield. 
&lt;br clear=&quot;right&quot; /&gt;

==Lee Naylor==
{{Infobox soap character
|series=Emmerdale
|color=#99CCCC
|image1=
|name=Lee Naylor
|portrayer=[[Lewis Linford (actor)|Lewis Linford]]
|first=4 November 2008
|last=18 June 2009
|years=2008&amp;ndash;2009
|occupation=[[Gamekeeper]]
|grandparents=[[List of recurring and minor Emmerdale characters#Mick Naylor|Mick Naylor]]&lt;br&gt;Carol Naylor
|Romances=[[Katie Sugden]]
}}

'''Lee Naylor''' played by Lewis Linford is the grandson of [[List of recurring and minor Emmerdale characters#Mick Naylor|Mick Naylor]]. He appeared from 2008 to 2009.&lt;ref name=&quot;DS1&quot;&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.digitalspy.co.uk/soaps/a155116/three-emmerdale-characters-to-leave.html|title=Three 'Emmerdale' characters to leave|first=Kris|last=Green|publisher=[[Digital Spy]]|date=7 May 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Lee first appears on 4 November 2008, when he accompanies his grandfather to Butler's Farm - run by [[Jo Sugden]] - to sort out a problem over cattle. Over the following weeks, Mick and Lee help Jo out with the farm, which she is struggling to run after separating from her abusive husband [[Andy Sugden|Andy]]. Lee is a qualified gamekeeper. He and Jo get on well from the start, and when in mid-December 2008, he has to remove his shirt after fixing some plumbing, Mick warns him not to flirt with Jo too much. In late December, Lee catches Andy sabotaging the washing machine so Jo will ask him over to do the repair. They get into a fight, and Andy is thrown out. Jo decides she needs to leave the village, and Lee agrees to help her. She leaves on 22 December.

In February 2009, Lee is made Home Farm's gamekeeper by [[Natasha Wylde]]. He soon takes an interest in [[Katie Sugden]], but [[List of minor Emmerdale characters (2009)#Nathan Wylde|Nathan Wylde]] is also interested in Katie and he tries to stop him seeing her. In April, Lee is rushed to hospital after Natasha and Mark find him on the estate having got his foot caught in a poacher's trap. Mick later admits he was the poacher, and Lee is soon sacked by Nathan when Lee punches him after he taunts him about his grandfather. Soon after Nathan rehires him after Katie persuades him to do so. In May, he becomes homeless after Mick's gets into debt with the rent. After sleeping on the grounds for a few nights, he moves to Katie's house. 

Tension continues to simmer between Nathan and Lee. In mid-June Lee has a further argument with Nathan over Katie, and is sacked. This time, however, Lee does not want his job back. When Katie learns that Lee told Nathan about some of her private conversations, she orders him to move out. Lee, already planning to apply for a gamekeeper job elsewhere, packs his bags that day and leaves the village.
&lt;br clear=&quot;right&quot; /&gt;

==Gary McFarlane==
{{Infobox soap character
|series=Emmerdale
|color=#99CCCC
|name=Gary McFarlane
|portrayer=[[Colin Connor]]
|years=2008
|first=November 2008
|last=1 December 2008
|occupation=Night club owner
|relatives=[[Brenda McFarlane]]&lt;br&gt;[[Seth McFarlane]]
}}

'''Gary McFarlane''' is a night club owner. He appeared in 2008.

Gary owns the night club where [[Jasmine Thomas]] briefly works, unbeknown to him as an undercover journalist. He is a member of the criminal McFarlane family.
&lt;br clear=&quot;right&quot; /&gt;

==Pam Montclare==
{{Infobox soap character
|series=Emmerdale
|color=#99CCCC
|name=Pam Montclare
|portrayer=[[Catherine Rabett]]
|occupation=
|years=2008&amp;ndash;2009
|first=26 December 2008
|last=27 January 2009
|spouse=[[List of minor Emmerdale characters (2008)#Richard Montclare|Richard Montclare]]
|romances=[[Rodney Blackstock]]
}}

'''Pamela Montclare''' has a brief affair with [[Rodney Blackstock]]. She appeared from 2008 to 2009.

Pam arrives in Emmerdale with her husband Richard for a Boxing Day shoot at Home Farm. She and Rodney Blackstock soon get on well, and are just about to make love in Rodney's house when [[Jamie Hope]] arrives. They just about tidy themselves up before Richard arrives. They return to the village the following week for another shoot, and stay in Rodney's cottage for the first night. When her husband has gone to bed, Pam shares a kiss with Rodney before joining her husband. The following day, while Richard is on a shoot, she and Rodney sleep together. When [[Shadrach Dingle]] suggests this to Richard, he goes to the B&amp;B, and although Rodney just has time to escape, Pam cannot hide they have been together. They both then leave the village. However, Pam and Rodney continue their affair and Pam visits the village again on 27 January. They are about to go to his bedroom, when [[Paul Lambert (Emmerdale)|Paul]] and [[Diane Sugden|Diane]] arrive telling Rodney he cannot have an affair with his heart condition. Pam then quickly leaves, not wanting to be put in that situation. Rodney then explains to Paul and Diane he does not have a heart condition, it was made up by [[Val Lambert]] as a ploy to keep Paul in the village.
&lt;br clear=&quot;right&quot; /&gt;

==Richard Montclare==
{{Infobox soap character
|series=Emmerdale
|color=#99CCCC
|name=Richard Montclare
|portrayer=[[Dominic Jephcott]]
|occupation=
|years=2008&amp;ndash;2009
|first=26 December 2008
|last=8 January 2009
|spouse=[[List of minor Emmerdale characters (2008)#Pam Montclare|Pam Montclare]]
}}
'''Richard Montclare''' stays in Emmerdale for a shoot. He appeared from 2008 to 2009.

He arrives in the village with his wife Pam for a Boxing Day shoot at Home Farm. Pam and [[Rodney Blackstock]] soon get on well, and unbeknown to Richard he narrowly avoids walking in on them about to make love. They return to the village the following week for another shoot, and stay in Rodney's cottage for the first night as the B&amp;B is full. The following day Richard is on a shoot while Pam stays at the B&amp;B. When [[Shadrach Dingle]] suggests she and Rodney maybe making love, Richard rushes to the B&amp;B with his shot gun. While trying to fight past [[Jamie Hope]] to get up the stairs, Richard accidentally shoots [[Jimmy King (Emmerdale)|Jimmy King]] - who is trying to find Rodney because he has just discovered the illegal shoot - in the behind. Richard and Pam then leave the village. The following day, Richard returns when Jimmy demands thousands of pounds in compensation in return for not telling the police.
{{-}}

==Nick Henshall==
{{Infobox soap character 2
|series=Emmerdale
|color=#99CCCC
|name=Nick Henshall
|portrayer=[[Michael McKell]]
|years=2008&amp;ndash;2009, 2010&amp;ndash;2011
|first=31 December 2008
|last=17 February 2011 
|introducer=[[Anita Turner]] (2008)&lt;br /&gt;[[Gavin Blyth]] (2010)
|occupation=Detective
|wife=Alison Henshall (?-1998)
|romances=[[Katie Sugden]] (2010-2011)
|death=17 February 2011
}}
'''Detective Sergeant Nicholas &quot;Nick&quot; Henshall''', played by [[Michael McKell]], was a local police officer. He made his first appearance on 31 December 2008. He returned in 2010 and began a relationship with [[Katie Sugden]] and started a fire that killed two people. He departed on 17 February 2011 when he killed himself.

In January 2011, McKell told ''[[Inside Soap]]'' that Henshall did not intend for anyone to be hurt by the fire he started.&lt;ref name=&quot;Henshall&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.digitalspy.co.uk/soaps/s12/emmerdale/news/a302867/emmerdale-star-reveals-henshall-secrets.html|title='Emmerdale' star reveals Henshall secrets|last=Kilkelly|first=Daniel|date=9 February 2011|work=[[Digital Spy]]|publisher=[[Hachette Filipacchi UK]]|accessdate=17 February 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; The fire claimed the lives of [[Terry Woods (Emmerdale)|Terry Woods]] ([[Billy Hartman]]) and [[Viv Hope]] ([[Deena Payne]]).&lt;ref name=&quot;Henshall&quot;/&gt; McKell revealed that Henshall's wife, Alison, was killed in a fire that was intended for him. He could not rescue his wife and uses the fire at Victoria Cottage as a way to make amends.&lt;ref name=&quot;Henshall&quot;/&gt; McKell said &quot;Because he felt powerless to help, he invested his life in his career and actually became a very good cop in the process. When he set alight Katie's cottage, he only wanted to start a little fire so he could be a hero and she'd need him.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;Henshall&quot;/&gt; Henshall later become unstable and a hostage situation occurs between him and [[Katie Sugden|Katie]] ([[Sammy Winward]]).&lt;ref name=&quot;Henshall&quot;/&gt;

===Storylines===
Detective Constable Henshall is first seen when he and [[List of minor Emmerdale characters (2006)#Karen Williams|DS Karen Williams]] (Annie Fitzmaurice) investigate the murder of policeman [[#Shane Doyle|Shane Doyle]] ([[Paul McEwan]]) and they initially arrest [[Eli Dingle]] ([[Joseph Gilgun]]) for the murder and he implicates [[Debbie Dingle]] ([[Charley Webb]]) and [[Jasmine Thomas]] ([[Jenna-Louise Coleman]]) as being Shane's killers and Henshall and Williams arrest and charge Debbie with the murder. However, Jasmine later hands herself in and confesses to Henshall and Williams that she killed Shane. In February 2009, Henshall investigates the disappearance of [[List of minor Emmerdale characters (2009)#Will Wylde|Will Wylde]] ([[Oscar Lloyd]]) and in May questions [[Cain Dingle]] ([[Jeff Hordley]]) about a break-in. He is promoted to Detective Sergeant and returns in July 2010 to investigate the murder of [[Mark Wylde]] ([[Maxwell Caulfield]]). He and DC Laura Prior initially arrest [[Nathan Wylde]] ([[Lyndon Ogbourne]]), but release him without charge due to a lack of evidence. They then arrest and charge [[Ryan Lamb]] ([[James Sutton (actor)|James Sutton]]), but [[Natasha Wylde]] ([[Amanda Donohoe]]) is proven to be the killer. In November 2010, Henshall investigates the theft of two horses from Home Farm and he later buys stable manager, Katie Sugden a drink. Katie's ex-husband, [[Andy Sugden]] ([[Kelvin Fletcher]]) is not happy with Katie dating Henshall and they goad each other. In December 2010, Henshall investigates the disappearance of [[Jacob Gallagher]] (Joe Warren-Plant) and he suggests to Jacob's parents [[Alicia Gallagher|Alicia]] ([[Natalie Anderson]]) and [[Justin Gallagher|Justin]] ([[Andrew Langtree]]) that they hold a televised appeal. [[David Metcalfe]] ([[Matthew Wolfenden]]) eventually finds Jacob in a old building and rescues him, despite Henshall telling him to wait.

Katie and her housemates, [[Genesis Walker|Gennie Walker]] ([[Sian Reese-Williams]]) and [[Chas Dingle]] ([[Lucy Pargeter]]), receive prank calls and they are later burgled. Gennie tells Henshall that she thinks Andy may be responsible. On a date with Katie, Henshall mentions his dead wife, Alison. When they get back to Katie's, Henshall argues with Andy in the street and she decides to end their relationship. Later, Henshall returns with a petrol can and starts a fire at the back of Victoria Cottage. He tries to ring Katie, but she does not answer and he assumes that she has gone out. Henshall hides and watches as [[Carl King]] ([[Tom Lister]]), Andy and other residents try to put the fire out. The fire spreads and kills Terry Woods and Viv Hope when the Post Office catches alight. Henshall returns the following morning to investigate the fire with Prior and they interview both Andy and Carl. In the coming weeks, Katie and Henshall get back together. Henshall attends both Terry's funeral and Viv's memorial service at The Woolpack. Andy makes a complaint about Henshall harassing him and reveals his relationship with Katie to his colleague Prior. Henshall is then taken off the case and he blames Prior for ruining his chances of promotion. Henshall threatens Andy by holding his face over a gas cooker in his caravan. Henshall and Gennie go to Butler's Farm after [[Brenda Walker]] ([[Lesley Dunlop]]) goes to confront Andy. When they arrive, they discover that Brenda crashed her car into Andy's caravan. Henshall talks to Andy's landlords [[John Barton (Emmerdale)|John]] ([[James Thornton (actor)|James Thornton]]) and [[Moira Barton]] ([[Natalie J. Robb]]) and they agree not to press charges.

Prior warns Henshall to stay away from the case and that she knows that he withheld information from Katie and Carl's statements. On Valentine's Day, Henshall takes Katie for a meal at the B&amp;B and tells her that he is falling in love with her. Andy arrives with Alicia to watch them and Henshall demands that he leave. Henshall asks his colleague DC Darren Foster for updates on the case and Foster tells Henshall that they have CCTV footage from the shop where the phone used to make the calls to Victoria Cottage was bought from. Henshall asks Katie to come away with him and she agrees. At his home, Katie finds some newspaper clippings about his wife Alison's death. Katie asks Henshall about them and he tells her that Alison died in an arson attack on their home. Katie discovers her stolen bracelet and Henshall locks the front door and starts to barricade the house. Katie realises that he is responsible for the prank phone calls, the burglary and the fire. Henshall tells Katie that he tried to save his wife and that it was his fault she died as their home was targeted by some criminals he had arrested and imprisoned. He tells her that he wanted to make up for Alison's death and that he wanted her to need him, so he started the fire at her home in order for him mto rescue her. Henshall insists that Terry and Viv's deaths were accidental. Katie demands that he let her go, but he refuses. Henshall tells Katie that he loves her and insists that she loves him. Katie tries to escape, but Henshall stops her. Prior and Foster call round to question Henshall after discovering he is the culprit for the fire and they realise that Katie is in the house. Prior calls Katie's phone and Henshall answers and shows them Katie at the window to prove she is alive. He produces a gun and Katie begs him to not to use it and he suggests killing them both in order for them to be together. A shot is fired and Katie leaves the house. She tells Prior and Andy, who had arrived at the scene with Gennie, that Henshall had killed himself.

==References==
{{reflist}}

{{Emmerdale}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:List Of Minor Emmerdale Characters (2008)}}
[[Category:Emmerdale characters|2008]]
[[Category:Lists of minor fictional characters|Emmerdale, 2008]]
[[Category:Fictional characters introduced in 2008|*, Emmerdale]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
