<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="20913658" ns="0" title="List of minor Emmerdale characters (2004)"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{DISPLAYTITLE:List of minor ''Emmerdale'' characters (2004)}}
{{Refimprove|date=April 2010}}
{{Emmerdaleminor}}
The following is a '''list of minor characters''' that first appeared in the [[United Kingdom|British]] [[soap opera]] '''''[[Emmerdale]]''''' in 2004, by order of first appearance.

==Noah Tate==
{{Infobox soap character 2
|series=Emmerdale
|color=#99CCCC
|name=Noah Tate
|portrayer=Alfie Mortimer (2004-05)&lt;br/&gt;Jack Downham (2009 -)
|born=1 March 2004
|death=
|family=[[Tate family]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Dingle family]]
|father=[[Chris Tate]]
|mother = [[Charity Tate]]
|halfbrothers = [[Joseph Tate (Emmerdale)|Joseph Tate]] 
|halfsisters = [[Debbie Dingle]] 
|grandfathers=[[Frank Tate (Emmerdale)|Frank Tate]]&lt;br /&gt;Obadiah Dingle
|grandmothers = Jean Tate Sr.
|uncles=[[Liam Hammond]]&lt;br /&gt;[[James Tate (Emmerdale)|James Tate]]&lt;br /&gt;
|aunts = [[Zoe Tate]]
|nieces=[[Sarah Dingle|Sarah Sugden]]
|cousins = [[Jean Tate]]
|years=2004–05, 2009—
|occupation=Student
|home=Holdgate Farm|
|first=1 March 2004
|last=
|classification=Current; recurring
|spinoffs= ''Emmerdale: The Dingles - For Richer for Poorer(2010)
}}

'''Noah Tate''' (previously '''Christopher Francis Tate, Jr.''') is the son of [[Charity Tate|Charity]] and [[Chris Tate]]. He appeared from 2004 to 2005 and returned in 2009 along with his mother, Charity.

Noah is born in prison while Charity was serving a life sentence for the murder of his father, Chris, who had actually committed suicide. His paternity was doubtful as Charity had slept with her cousins, [[Cain Dingle|Cain]] and [[Marlon Dingle|Marlon]] as well as her husband, but DNA tests confirmed he was Chris's son. Charity, knowing she couldn't keep Noah with her in prison, sells him to his aunt [[Zoe Tate|Zoe]], who calls him Christopher after her brother. In return for this, Zoe tells the court that Chris framed Charity for murder and she is freed. The courts, however, do not allow Zoe to adopt Christopher, due to her current workload, other family commitments and mental illness so Charity takes him back, returning his name to Noah and leaves the village in 2005. 

In October 2009, Noah and Charity return to the village when Charity discovers that her fiance, Michael, has been having an affair with Charity's daughter, Debbie. After the wedding is called off, Noah and Charity move in with Debbie and her daughter, Sarah. Charity sends Noah to the local primary school as he is too old to go to playgroup with Sarah.
{{-}}

==Colleen King==
{{Infobox soap character 2
|series=Emmerdale
|color=#99CCCC
|name=Colleen King
|first=1 April 2004
|last=23 April 2010
|years=2004, 2005, 2010
|portrayer=Melanie Ash
|husband=[[Carl King]] (1998–2004)
|sons=[[List of minor Emmerdale characters (2004)#Thomas King|Thomas King]]
|daughters=[[List of minor Emmerdale characters (2004)#Anya King|Anya King]]
}}

'''Colleen King''', played by Melanie Ash, is the first wife of [[Carl King]], appearing in 2004, 2005 and 2010.

Colleen is [[divorce]]d from Carl, with whom she had two children [[List of minor Emmerdale characters (2004)#Thomas King|Thomas]] and [[List of minor Emmerdale characters (2004)#Anya King|Anya]]. She has custody of the children, and appears in the village briefly when they visit Carl. Colleen returned in January 2010 with Thomas and Anya as she was going somewhere and her sister would not have them so she dropped them off at Carl's. In April 2010 Colleen returned and told Carl she wanted to emigrate to Dubai and take the children with her. She left with Thomas and Anya the following day. 
&lt;br clear=&quot;right&quot; /&gt;

==Thomas King==
{{Infobox soap character
|series=Emmerdale
|color=#99CCCC
|name=Thomas King
|first=1 April 2004
|last=25 December 2010
|years=2004, 2005, 2006,&lt;br /&gt;2007, 2009, 2010
|portrayer=[[Jack Ferguson (British actor)|Jack Ferguson]]&lt;br /&gt;Connor Hill
|date of birth=1996
|parents=[[Carl King]]&lt;br /&gt;[[List of minor Emmerdale characters (2004)#Colleen King|Colleen King]]
|siblings = [[Anya King]]
|grandparents=[[Tom King (Emmerdale)|Tom King]]&lt;br /&gt;Mary King
|aunts/uncles=[[Scarlett Nicholls]]&lt;br /&gt;Unnamed aunt&lt;br/&gt;[[Jimmy King (Emmerdale)|Jimmy King]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Matthew King (Emmerdale)|Matthew King]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Max King (Emmerdale)|Max King]]&lt;br /&gt;Georgina King
|cousins=[[Angelica King]] &lt;br /&gt; [[List of minor Emmerdale characters (2011)#Elliot Windsor-King|Elliot Windsor-King]]
}}

'''Thomas King''' is the son of [[Carl King]]. He appeared in 2004, 2005, 2006, 2007, 2009 and 2010.

Named after his grandfather, [[Tom King (Emmerdale)|Tom King]], Thomas's parents separated when he was young. He first appears in 2004 when his mother tells Carl she wants a [[divorce]] and initially refuses to let him see the children. 

However, Thomas and his sister, Anya, visit their father in 2005, 2006 and June 2007. In February 2009, he and Anya visit, following Carl's engagement to [[Lexi King|Lexi Nicholls]]. Thomas is meant to attend his father's wedding but stays at home, due to [[chicken pox]]. In January 2010, Colleen arrives with the children, asking Carl to look after them as her husband has had an accident at work. They move into Mill Cottage temporarily. Thomas and Anya cause problems for [[Ashley Thomas|Ashley]] and [[Laurel Thomas]] and [[Edna Birch]]. In April 2010 Colleen returns and tells Carl she wants to emigrate to Dubai and take the children with her. She leaves with Thomas and Anya the following day.

Thomas returns along with Anya eight months later on Christmas Eve in preparation for Carl's wedding to [[Chas Dingle]] the following day. After the wedding ends in chaos with Chas jilting Carl and revealing his affair with [[Eve Jenson]], Carl takes Thomas and Anya back home to Dubai.

&lt;br clear=&quot;right&quot; /&gt;

==Anya King==
{{Infobox soap character
|series=Emmerdale
|color=#99CCCC
|name=Anya King
|years=2004, 2005, 2006, 2007, 2009, 2010
|first=1 April 2004
|last=25 December 2010
|portrayer=Ceryen Dean&lt;br /&gt;Millie Archer
|date of birth=1998
|parents=[[Carl King]]&lt;br /&gt;[[List of minor Emmerdale characters (2004)#Colleen King|Colleen King]]
|siblings = [[Tom King (Emmerdale)|Thomas King]]
|grandparents=[[Tom King (Emmerdale)|Tom King]]&lt;br /&gt;Mary King
|aunts/uncles=Georgina King&lt;br /&gt;Unnamed aunt&lt;br/&gt;[[Scarlett Nicholls]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Jimmy King (Emmerdale)|Jimmy King]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Matthew King (Emmerdale)|Matthew King]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Max King (Emmerdale)|Max King]]&lt;br /&gt;Georgina King
|cousins=[[Angelica King]] &lt;br /&gt; [[List of minor Emmerdale characters (2011)#Elliot Windsor-King|Elliot Windsor-King]]
}}

'''Andrea &quot;Anya&quot; King''' is the daughter of [[Carl King]]. She appeared in 2004, 2005, 2006, 2007, 2009 and 2010.

Anya's parents separated when she was young and she first appears in 2004 when her mother tells Carl that she wants a [[divorce]] and initially refuses to let him see the children. 

However, Anya and her brother, Thomas, visit their father in 2005, 2006 and June 2007. In February 2009, she and Thomas visit, following Carl's engagement to [[Lexi King|Lexi Nicholls]]. Anya is meant to attend her father's wedding the following month but stays at home with chicken pox. 

In January 2010, Colleen arrives with the children, asking Carl to look after them as her husband has had an accident at work. They move into Mill Cottage temporarily. In April 2010 Colleen returns and tells Carl she wants to emigrate to Dubai and take the children with her. She leaves with Anya and Thomas the following day. 

Anya returns with Thomas eight months later on Christmas Eve in preparation for Carl's wedding to [[Chas Dingle]] the following day. After the wedding ends in chaos with Chas jilting Carl and revealing his affair with [[Eve Jenson]], Carl takes Anya and Thomas back home to Dubai.

&lt;br clear=&quot;right&quot; /&gt;

==PC Mike Swirling==
{{Infobox soap character
|series=Emmerdale
|color=#99CCCC
|image1= 
|name=PC Mike Swirling
|portrayer=[[Andy Moore (actor)|Andy Moore]]
|occupation=[[Police officer]]
|first=31 May 2004
|last=
|years=2004–
|occupation=[[Police Constable]]
|parents=Elaine Swirling
|spouse=Unnamed ex wife
|siblings= Robbie&lt;br&gt;Joanne
|children=Danny Swirling&lt;br&gt;Tina Swirling
}}

'''Police Constable Mike Swirling''' is a local [[police officer]]. He has appeared since 2004. 

PC Swirling often appears in the village whenever the police are called. On 28 December 2006, Swirling appears when a fight breaks out in the street between [[Carl King]] and [[Jamie Hope]]. Jamie presses charges and Swirling arrests Carl for assault. In April 2007, he is called to the Post Office by [[Viv Hope]] when [[Belle Dingle]] steals a packet of sweets and then insults her. Whilst waiting for the police, Viv locks Belle and her mother [[Lisa Dingle|Lisa]] in the shop. When PC Swirling and a colleague arrive, they are both unsympathetic to Viv and Lisa's claims and tell them that both were acting like children. Swirling threatens to charge them with wasting police time, before leaving. Later that month he visits the village again when [[Jo Sugden|Jo Stiles]] calls the police after believing [[Billy Hopwood]] had assaulted [[Andy Sugden]]. Swirling arrests Billy and after taking a statement from Andy, he charges Billy with assault. Andy later changes his statement and Swirling releases Billy. On 3 July 2007, Swirling appears when [[Eli Dingle]] stages a fake robbery at Tug Ghyll. In August 2008, Mike appears when [[Donna Windsor-Dingle]] and [[Ross Kirk]] are nearly killed in a car chase. In July 2009, he appears when [[Rodney Blackstock]]'s car crashes into the Farm shop. He is later called to Mulberry Cottage when [[Laurel Thomas]] accuses [[Sally Spode]] of trying to kill her and kidnapping her son [[Arthur Thomas (Emmerdale)|Arthur]]. Swirling appears again on 28 January 2010 when [[Faye Lamb]] reports [[Mark Wylde]]'s disappearance and [[Natasha Wylde]] tells him about Mark's bigamy. Swirling returns on 26 February 2010 when he, Faye and Natasha are called out to the hospital to try and identify a body but it is not Mark's. Swirling appears again on 22 June 2010 at Home Farm after Mark's credit card is used to purchase some flowers which Natasha and her son [[Nathan Wylde|Nathan]] both knew were not from Mark although they did not let on about it. Swirling later appears at Butler's Farm after [[John Barton (Emmerdale)|John Barton]] reports his daughter, [[Holly Barton|Holly]]'s disappearance. Swirling appears in September again at Butler's Farm after it is burgled. Swirling and his colleague give John and his wife [[Moira Barton|Moira]] advice on not leaving windows or doors open. John tells Swirling that he suspects that Holly committed the burglary to fund her drug addiction. Moira later tracks Holly down and takes her to the police station where Swirling arrests her and she confesses to carrying out the burglary. When he asks Moira if she wants Holly to be charged she agrees but Swirling suggests she and John get Holly some counselling. Swirling appears again on 2 December 2010. He is at the police station when Moira is arrested for possession of heroin which she had been going to give to Holly. Swirling recognizes Moira and he interviews her along with the arresting officer. Swirling tells Moira she could go to prison for the offence. He offers to help Moira get a more lenient sentence if she agrees to tell him everything she knows about where the heroin came from and she does so. On 23 February 2011, Swirling visits the offices of Emmerdale haulage to inform Carl that his brother [[Jimmy King (Emmerdale)|Jimmy]]'s van has been discovered in Peterborough with bloodstains inside. On 1 March, he returns to inform Jimmy's wife [[Nicola King|Nicola]] that the blood found in the van has been positively identified as Jimmy's. The following day, Swirling returns to tell Nicola and Carl that a man fitting Jimmy's description has been located in a hospital in Nottingham. On 21 April 2011, Swirling is called to Holdgate Farm after it is burgled by [[Cain Dingle]]. Swirling takes details of the burglary from Cain's ex-girlfriend [[Charity Tate]], her current boyfriend [[Jai Sharma]], whose car Cain had stolen, and Jai's brother [[Nikhil Sharma|Nikhil]], all of whom implicate Cain as the culprit. Swirling later visits Cain at Tug Ghyll and questions him about his whereabouts. Despite [[Cameron Murray]] giving him an alibi, Swirling arrests Cain and takes him to the police station. He later visits Cain's colleague [[Ryan Lamb]], who Cain had tricked into acting as a lookout, at his home. The following morning, Swirling visits Cain in his cell at the police station and informs him that they questioned Ryan and released him and that they believed that Cain had acted alone. Swirling warns Cain that he faces a long prison sentence but Cain is defiant and taunts Swirling, saying that they have no evidence against him and that they should release him. Swirling ignores him and leaves the cell. Later Charity comes to the police station to change her statement and tells Swirling that she is longer certain that it was Cain who carried out the burglary. Swirling tells Charity that if she lets Cain get away with it then she will never be free of him but she ignores him and Swirling has no choice but to release Cain.    
&lt;br clear=&quot;right&quot; /&gt;

==Niamh O'Connor==
{{Infobox soap character
|series=Emmerdale
|color=#99CCCC
|name=Niamh O'Connor
|portrayer=Tracey Moore
|years=2004
|born=
|death=
|occupation=Charity worker
|first=11 June 2004
|last=29 December 2004
}}

'''Niamh O'Connor''' was the fiancee of [[Ethan Blake]]. She appeared in 2004.

After dating for several years, Ethan and Niamh become engaged. However, their different views of the world lead to significant differences between them. Niamh spends some time travelling, and visits Ethan during a break from travelling. When, during her visit, Ethan learns she wants to return to [[Malawi]], they decide to go their separate ways - in spite of their love for each other. Months later, Niamh returns to Emmerdale on a surprise visit. However, Ethan is out of the village at the time visiting friends and he can not be contacted. She leaves the village several days later, missing Ethan, who returns shortly afterwards.
&lt;br clear=&quot;right&quot; /&gt;

==Callum Rennie==
{{Infobox soap character
|image=
|series=Emmerdale
|color=#99CCCC
|name=Callum Rennie
|portrayer=[[Andrew Whipp]]
|born=18 April
|years=2004–2005
|occupation=Home Farm estate manager
|spouse= Unnamed Wife (deceased)
|first=23 June 2004
|last=22 September 2005
}}

'''Callum Rennie''' was Home Farm's estate manager. He appeared from 2004 to 2005.  

Callum works for [[Zoe Tate]], whom he builds up a friendship with. Callum is devoted to Zoe and eventually confides in her that he is in love with her, although he knows his feelings will never be reciprocated as Zoe is a lesbian. When Zoe leaves the village, he helps her tamper with the gas pipes and timer, and so causes an explosion when the [[King family (Emmerdale)|King family]], who had conned her out the property, arrive.
&lt;br clear=&quot;right&quot; /&gt;

==Tash Abbott==
{{Infobox soap character
|series=Emmerdale
|color=#99CCCC
|image=
|name= Tash Abbott
|portrayer=[[Sally Evans]]
|first=18 July 2004
|last= 2006
|years=2004, 2005, 2006
|born=
|death=
|occupation=
|romances=[[Simon Meredith]]
}}
'''Natasha &quot;Tash&quot; Abbott''' is the former fiancee of [[Simon Meredith]]. She appeared in 2004, 2005 and 2006.

Tash and Simon remain friends after their failed engagement.
&lt;br clear=&quot;right&quot; /&gt;

==Dean Morris==
{{Infobox soap character
|series=Emmerdale
|color=#99CCCC
|image=
|name=Dean Morris
|portrayer=[[Marc Bolton]]
|first=21 July 2004
|last=31 March 2009
|years=2004–2007, 2009
|occupation=[[Construction foreman|Foreman]]
}}

'''Dean Morris''' was an employee of the [[King family (Emmerdale)|King family]]. He appeared from 2004 to 2007 and in 2009.

Dean first appears in 2004 and works primarily as their [[chauffeur]]. He was one of the most loyal and trusted King employees. He takes [[Carl King]] around [[Romania]] following his involvement in the accidental death of [[Paul Marsden (Emmerdale)|Paul Marsden]], and is forced to lie to [[Tom King (Emmerdale)|Tom]], which upsets him, as Tom has helped him on numerous occasions. At one point, false rumours suggest he is having an affair with [[Charity Tate]]; a few weeks later, Tom dumps Charity as he believes she has slept with [[Cain Dingle]], and as Dean drives him away from the wedding, Tom apologises for doubting him. Following Tom's death on Christmas Day 2006, Dean carries his coffin at the funeral along with [[Jimmy King (Emmerdale)|Jimmy]], [[Matthew King (Emmerdale)|Matthew]] and Carl. In January 2009, he is a pallbearer at Matthew's funeral, and at the wake talks to [[Lexi Nicholls]] about his loyalty to the Kings. The following day Dean brings some of Matthew's effects from the site office to Jimmy and Carl. When they see [[Rosemary King]]'s name plate, Dean reveals to them that Matthew had dug up her body and crushed it in a rubbish truck. In February 2009, he drives a van to [[Belgium]], not knowing Jimmy and [[Nicola De Souza]] are in the back, having just slept together. The following month he attends Carl and Lexi's wedding. This was Dean's last appearance so far and he has not been seen since. 
&lt;br clear=&quot;right&quot; /&gt;

==John McNally==
{{Infobox soap character
|series=Emmerdale
|color=#99CCCC
|image1=
|name=John McNally
|portrayer=[[Steven Farebrother]]
|years=2004–2009
|first=2004
|last=3 April 2009
|occupation=[[Journalist]]
}}

'''John McNally''' was a local [[journalist]] with the ''Hotton Courier''. He has appeared since 2004.

First appearing in 2004, McNally - as he is normally known - appears whenever there is a newsworthy event in the village. In 2004, he corners [[Pearl Ladderbanks]] when her rapist son [[List of minor Emmerdale characters (2004)#Frank Bernard Hartbourne|Frank Bernard Hartbourne]] moves to the village after being released from prison. This sets off a chain of events which lead to the whole village finding out. In early 2005, he covers the disappearance of [[Shelley Williams]], and her presumed murder by [[Steph Stokes]]. When [[Eric Pollard]] stands for re-election to the local Council, McNally tries to catch him in embarrassing positions, and catches him coming out of a van half-naked with [[Val Pollard|Val Lambert]]. He also covers Steph Stokes being investigated for the murder of her brother [[Terence Turner]] and [[Tom King (Emmerdale)|Tom King]]'s murder. He hires aspiring journalist [[Jasmine Thomas]] for her village knowledge. 

An unpopular man in the village, following [[Viv Hope]]'s imprisonment he hounds [[Bob Hope (Emmerdale)|Bob]] and writes an article claiming to expose Bob's alleged crime. This causes Bob to have a break down and stage a one-man protest outside the newspaper's offices. However, during this protest John is away attending the wedding of his former wife. In November 2008, he covers the new village choir's attempts to enter a competition; and in December Jasmine demands her article about the local criminal family the McFarlane's is changed to a story about the church. 

McNally makes another appearance in April 2009, when Jasmine's grandfather [[Sandy Thomas|Sandy]] asks him to help with a campaign to overturn Jasmine's murder conviction. In spite of their close working relationship, McNally has no sympathy for her, and goes as far as to crack jokes about lesbians in prison before Sandy tells him to get out. McNally has not been seen since.
&lt;br clear=&quot;right&quot; /&gt;

==Frank Bernard Hartbourne==
{{Infobox soap character
|series=Emmerdale
|color=#99CCCC
|name=Frank Bernard Hartbourne
|portrayer=[[Rob Parry]]
|years=2004
|first=8 October 2004
|last=25 October 2004
|parents=Robbie&lt;br&gt;[[Pearl Ladderbanks]]
|children=Nadine&lt;br&gt;[[Owen Hartbourne]]
|spouse=Susan
|romances=Fay Bolton
}}

'''Frank Bernard Hartbourne''' is the son of [[Pearl Ladderbanks]]. He appeared in 2004. 

Frank Bernard - normally referred to by both names - arrives in Emmerdale having just been released from prison for [[rape|raping]] one of Pearl's neighbours, having previously been accused by a colleague but the case was dropped due to a lack of evidence. Many villagers do not take kindly to having a rapist living amongst them, and some either shun or harass him. 

When [[Donna Windsor-Dingle|Donna Windsor]] has an accident on her scooter, Frank Bernard goes to see if she is all right. Donna panics when she sees him and runs to her brother [[Scott Windsor|Scott]]. He and [[Syd Woolfe]] then set upon Frank Bernard, thinking he had harmed Donna, and leave him for dead on a roadside. Frank Bernard is later discovered by [[Rodney Blackstock]] and [[Danny Daggert]], who take him to his mother's home. He refuses to give the names of his attackers. He then decides to leave the village for his mother's sake.

The scene where Scott and Syd beat up Frank Bernard attracted 27 complaints. However, [[Ofcom]] ruled that Emmerdale were not in breach of any broadcasting codes as the scenes were edited in a careful manner.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news 
 |title = Ofcom Broadcast Bulletin
 |url = http://www.ofcom.org.uk/tv/obb/prog_cb/pcb67/issue28.pdf.
 |publisher = Ofcom
 |date = 
 |accessdate = 2005-02-14
}}&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;br clear=&quot;right&quot; /&gt;

==Solomon Dingle==
{{Infobox soap character
|series=Emmerdale
|color=#99CCCC
|name=Solomon Dingle
|portrayer=[[Paul Shane]]
|years=2004
|first=19 October 2004
|last=27 October 2004
|family=[[Dingle family]]
|aunts/uncles=[[Jedediah Dingle]]
|cousins=[[Zak Dingle]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Shadrach Dingle]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Albert Dingle]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Caleb Dingle]]&lt;br /&gt;[[List of minor Emmerdale characters (1999)#Ezra Dingle|Ezra Dingle]]&lt;br /&gt;Zebediah Dingle
}}
'''Solomon Dingle''' is [[Zak Dingle]]'s cousin. He appeared in 2004.

Solomon serves time in prison alongside Zak's son, [[Sam Dingle|Sam]]. He arrives in the village for the 10th anniversary of the Dingles being in Emmerdale. Zak and Solomon had been rivals for many years and compete for the title &quot;Dingle King&quot;, which Solomon wins by cheating. This forces Zak and his family to live in Solomon's caravan. However, Solomon soon abdicates his title to Sam, hoping to drive Zak and Sam apart. However, this did not happen and Solomon leaves the village.
&lt;br clear=&quot;right&quot; /&gt;

==Jon Dingle==
{{Infobox soap character
|series=Emmerdale
|color=#99CCCC
|name=Jon Dingle
|portrayer=Lucy Webb
|years=2004, 2006-2007
|first=20 October 2004
|last=13 July 2007
|dob=
|occupation=|
|family=[[Dingle family]]
|parents=[[Lilith Dingle]]
|aunts/uncles=[[Delilah Dingle]]
|siblings=[[Luke Dingle]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Matthew Dingle]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Mark Dingle]]
|cousins=[[Ben Dingle]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Butch Dingle]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Cain Dingle]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Sam Dingle]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Tina Dingle]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Belle Dingle]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Marlon Dingle]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Eli Dingle]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Mandy Dingle]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Chas Dingle]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Genesis Walker]]
}}
'''Jon Dingle''' is the youngest child and only daughter of [[Lilith Dingle]]. She appeared in 2004, and from 2006 to 2007.

Jon first visits Emmerdale in October 2004 for a Dingle family celebration to mark their 10th anniversary of living in the village. Her mother Lilith then leaves Jon and her brothers to live with her cousin [[Marlon Dingle]] for a month. Jon returns in 2006 when Lilith leaves her children with Marlon and his wife [[Donna Windsor-Dingle|Donna]] while she goes away to work. Days later, Lilith is arrested for armed robbery. 

Marlon tells social services that he is having difficulties looking after them, so its agreed that they will go and stay with their uncle, Tony. They are soon informed that the children have gone missing and are found in a nearby woodland. The following day, they are taken into foster care. Marlon and Donna desperately try to get the children back but first have to find suitable accommodation. This finally happens when they buy Tall Tree Cottage, and the children move in on 5 July. However, the case against their mother collapses and on 13 July 2007, she takes them to [[Ireland]], much to Donna and Marlon's distress. 
&lt;br clear=&quot;right&quot;/&gt;

==Lilith Dingle==
{{Infobox soap character
|series=Emmerdale
|color=#99CCCC
|name=Lilith Dingle
|portrayer=[[Amanda Hennessy]]
|years=2004, 2006, 2007
|first=20 October 2004
|last=13 July 2007
|family=[[Dingle family]]
|siblings=[[Delilah Dingle]]
|children=[[Luke Dingle]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Matthew Dingle]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Mark Dingle]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Jon Dingle]]
|cousins=[[Ben Dingle]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Butch Dingle]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Cain Dingle]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Sam Dingle]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Tina Dingle]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Belle Dingle]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Marlon Dingle]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Eli Dingle]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Mandy Dingle]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Chas Dingle]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Genesis Walker]]
}}

'''Lilith Dingle''' is the older sister of [[Delilah Dingle]]. She appeared in 2004, 2006 and 2007. 

Lilith first visits Emmerdale in October 2004 for a Dingle family celebration to mark their 10th anniversary of living in the village. To pursue her singing career, she then leaves her four children - named after the [[Apostles]] - with her cousin [[Marlon Dingle]] for a month before collecting them on 21 November. Lilith returns on 7 November 2006 when she leaves her four children with Marlon and his wife [[Donna Windsor-Dingle|Donna]] while she goes away to work. Days later Lilith is arrested for armed robbery. Shortly after she is arrested for armed robbery and remanded in police custody. After months on remand, Lilith stands trial on 12 July 2007, and is freed when the case collapses after a prosecution witness collapses after being intimidated by [[Eli Dingle]]. The following day she take her four children to [[Ireland]] with her, much to Donna and Marlon's distress. 
&lt;br clear=&quot;right&quot;/&gt;

==Luke Dingle==
{{Infobox soap character
|series=Emmerdale
|color=#99CCCC
|name=Luke Dingle
|portrayer=[[Dean McGonagle]]
|years=2004, 2006-2007
|first=20 October 2004
|last=13 July 2007
|dob=1994
|family=[[Dingle family]]
|parents=[[Lilith Dingle]]
|aunts/uncles=[[Delilah Dingle]]
|siblings=[[Matthew Dingle]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Mark Dingle]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Jon Dingle]]
|cousins=[[Ben Dingle]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Butch Dingle]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Cain Dingle]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Sam Dingle]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Tina Dingle]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Belle Dingle]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Marlon Dingle]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Eli Dingle]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Mandy Dingle]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Chas Dingle]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Genesis Walker]]
}}

'''Luke Dingle''' is the eldest son of [[Lilith Dingle]]. He appeared in 2004, and from 2006 to 2007.

Luke first visits Emmerdale in October 2004 for a Dingle family celebration to mark their 10th anniversary of living in the village. His mother Lilith then leaves Luke and his siblings to live with her cousin [[Marlon Dingle]] for a month. Luke returns in 2006 when Lilith leaves her children with Marlon and his wife [[Donna Windsor-Dingle|Donna]] while she goes away to work. Days later Lilith is arrested for armed robbery. On his first day at Hotten Comprehensive School, Luke gets into a fight with [[Victoria Sugden]] after she makes a remark about his mother being in custody. 

Marlon tells social services that he is having difficulties looking after them, so its agreed that they will go and stay with their uncle, Tony. They are soon informed that the children have gone missing, and are soon found in a nearby woodland. The following day they are taken into foster care. Marlon and Donna desperately try to get the children back but first have to find suitable accommodation. This finally happens when they buy Tall Tree Cottage, and the children move in with them on 5 July. However, the case against their mother collapses and on 13 July 2007 she takes them all to [[Ireland]] with her, much to Donna and Marlon's distress.
&lt;br clear=&quot;right&quot;/&gt;

==Mark Dingle==
{{Infobox soap character
|series=Emmerdale
|color=#99CCCC
|name=Mark Dingle
|portrayer=Cormac Golden (2004)&lt;br /&gt;Joe Manuel (2006-07)
|years=2004, 2006-2007
|first=20 October 2004
|last=13 July 2007
|born=21 November 1996
|family=[[Dingle family]]
|parents=[[Lilith Dingle]]
|aunts/uncles=[[Delilah Dingle]]
|siblings=[[Luke Dingle]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Matthew Dingle]] (twin)&lt;br /&gt;[[Jon Dingle]]
|cousins=[[Ben Dingle]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Butch Dingle]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Cain Dingle]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Sam Dingle]]&lt;br /&gt;Tina Dingle&lt;br /&gt;[[Belle Dingle]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Marlon Dingle]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Eli Dingle]]&lt;br /&gt;Mandy Dingle&lt;br /&gt;[[Chas Dingle]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Genesis Walker|Gennie Walker]]
}}
'''Mark Dingle''' is one of [[Lilith Dingle]]'s twin sons. He appeared in 2004, and from 2006 to 2007.

Mark first visits Emmerdale in October 2004 for a Dingle family celebration to mark their 10th anniversary of living in the village, leaving on his eighth birthday on 21 November 2004. His mother Lilith then leaves Mark and his siblings to live with her cousin [[Marlon Dingle]] for a month. Mark returns in 2006 when Lilith leaves her children with Marlon and his wife [[Donna Windsor-Dingle|Donna]] while she goes away to work. Days later Lilith is arrested for armed robbery.    
 
Marlon tells social services that he is having difficulties looking after them, so its agreed that they will go and stay with their uncle, Tony. They are soon informed that the children have gone missing, but they are soon found in a nearby woodland. The following day they are taken into foster care. Marlon and Donna desperately try to get the children back but first have to find suitable accommodation. This finally happens when they buy Tall Tree Cottage, and the children move in with them on 5 July. However, the case against their mother collapses and on 13 July 2007 she takes them all to [[Ireland]] with her, much to Donna and Marlon's distress. 
&lt;br clear=&quot;right&quot;/&gt;

==Matthew Dingle==
{{Infobox soap character
|series=Emmerdale
|color=#99CCCC
|name=Matthew Dingle
|portrayer=Mark Wanner 
|first=20 October 2004
|last=13 July 2007
|family=[[Dingle family]]
|parents=[[Lilith Dingle]]
|aunts/uncles=[[Delilah Dingle]]
|siblings=[[Luke Dingle]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Mark Dingle]] (twin)&lt;br /&gt;[[Jon Dingle]]
|born=21 November 1996
|cousins=[[Ben Dingle]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Butch Dingle]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Cain Dingle]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Sam Dingle]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Tina Dingle]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Belle Dingle]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Marlon Dingle]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Eli Dingle]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Mandy Dingle]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Chas Dingle]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Genesis Walker]]
}}
'''Matthew Dingle''' is one of [[Lilith Dingle]]'s twin sons. He appeared in 2004, and from 2006 to 2007.

Matthew first visits Emmerdale in October 2004 for a Dingle family celebration to mark their 10th anniversary of living in the village, leaving on his eighth birthday on 21 November 2004. His mother Lilith then leaves Matthew and his siblings to live with her cousin [[Marlon Dingle]] for a month. Matthew returns in 2006 when Lilith leaves her children with Marlon and his wife [[Donna Windsor-Dingle|Donna]] while she goes away to work. Days later Lilith is arrested for armed robbery. 

Marlon tells social services that he is having difficulties looking after them, so its agreed that they will go and stay with their uncle, Tony. They are soon informed that the children have gone missing and are found in a nearby woodland. The following day they are taken into foster care. Marlon and Donna desperately try to get the children back but first have to find suitable accommodation. This finally happens when they buy Tall Tree Cottage, and the children move in with them on 5 July. However, the case against their mother collapses and on 13 July 2007 she takes them all to [[Ireland]] with her, much to Donna and Marlon's distress.
&lt;br clear=&quot;right&quot;/&gt;

==Roger Dyson==
{{Infobox soap character
|series=Emmerdale
|color=#99CCCC
|name=Roger Dyson 
|portrayer=[[Malcolm Terris]]
|spouse=[[List of minor Emmerdale characters (2004)#Helen Dyson|Helen Dyson]]
|death=24 November 2004
|years=2004
|first=23 November 2004
|last=24 November 2004
}}

'''Roger Dyson''' is a close friend of [[Tom King (Emmerdale)|Tom King]]. He appeared in 2004.

Roger arrives with his wife Helen, both of whom have been friends with Tom and his late wife Mary for many years. They arrive to visit Tom and his fiancee [[Charity Tate]] several weeks before the planned wedding. Roger suffers from chest pains, which he does not take very seriously. The day after arriving, he collapses while playing golf with Tom and his sons. He is rushed to hospital but dies. Tom becomes depressed by the death of an old friend.
&lt;br clear=&quot;right&quot;/&gt;

==Helen Dyson==
{{Infobox soap character
|series=Emmerdale
|color=#99CCCC
|name=Helen Dyson 
|portrayer=Shirley Dixon
|spouse=[[List of minor Emmerdale characters (2004)#Roger Dyson|Roger Dyson]] (?-2004)
|years=2004, 2006, 2007
|first=23 November 2004
|last=17 February 2007
}}

'''Helen Dyson''' is a close friend of [[Tom King (Emmerdale)|Tom King]]. She appeared in 2004.

Helen arrives with her husband Roger, both of whom have been friends with Tom and his late wife Mary for many years.  They arrive to visit Tom and his fiancee [[Charity Tate]] several weeks before the planned wedding.  Helen sees Charity, much younger than Tom and with little taste for domestic life, as being unworthy of him.  While they are cooking a meal together, Charity makes a remark about Helen's food being a [[Myocardial infarction|heart attack]] in the making. Soon, they receive a phone call saying that Roger has died of a heart attack while playing golf, causing Helen to lash out at Charity. Helen made her last appearance at Tom's funeral in February 2007. 
&lt;br clear=&quot;right&quot;/&gt;

==Enzo Bianchi==
{{Infobox soap character
|series=Emmerdale
|color=#99CCCC
|name=Enzo Bianchi
|portrayer=Daniel D’Alessandro
|occupation=Bar owner
|years=2004
|first=30 November 2004
|last=1 December 2004
|romances=[[Paul Lambert (Emmerdale)|Paul Lambert]] (?-2004)
}}

'''Enzo Bianchi''' was [[Paul Lambert (Emmerdale)|Paul Lambert]]'s boyfriend. He appeared in 2004. 

When Paul first arrives in Emmerdale, he frequently mentions his boyfriend of several years, Enzo, with whom he ran a wine bar in [[Sorrento, Italy]]. Paul returns to Sorrento in late October 2004 to try and mend their relationship. Shortly after Paul's return, Enzo travels to Emmerdale and tells Paul he wants to end their relationship. Reluctantly Paul agrees and they finalize who gets what and Enzo returns home.
&lt;br clear=&quot;right&quot;/&gt;

==Gianni Bianchi==
{{Infobox soap character
|series=Emmerdale
|color=#99CCCC
|name=Gianni Bianchi
|portrayer=Andonis Anthony
|years=2004
|first=12 December 2004
|last=13 December 2004
}}

'''Gianni Bianchi''' was a fake boyfriend for [[Val Pollard|Val Lambert]]. He appeared in 2004.

Val alienates her sister [[Diane Sugden]] and son [[Paul Lambert (Emmerdale)|Paul]] before leaving for [[Italy]] in September 2004. When she returns in December 2004 she says it is only for a Christmas visit. She brings along her much younger boyfriend, Gianni.  She tells everyone they are going to get married, but the next day Gianni leaves. Val says he had dumped her because she was too old to have children.  However, before Gianni leaves, Val gives him money, and Paul sees them. Val is forced to admit that she had made the whole thing up in order to get sympathy. 
&lt;br clear=&quot;right&quot;/&gt;

== References ==

{{Reflist}}

[[Category:Emmerdale characters|2004]]
[[Category:Lists of minor fictional characters|Emmerdale, 2004]]
[[Category:Fictional characters introduced in 2004|*, Emmerdale]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
