<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="20926035" ns="0" title="List of minor Emmerdale characters (2003)"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{DISPLAYTITLE:List of minor ''Emmerdale'' characters (2003)}}
{{unreferenced|date=May 2009}}
{{Emmerdaleminor}}
The following is a '''list of minor characters''' that first appeared in the [[United Kingdom|British]] [[soap opera]] '''''[[Emmerdale]]''''' in 2003, by order of first appearance.

==Freda Darby==
{{Infobox soap character
|series=Emmerdale
|color=#99CCCC
|name=Freda Darby
|portrayer=[[Lyn Paul]]
|years=2003, 2005
|first=2003
|last=5 December 2005
}}
'''Freda Darby''' is an acquaintance of [[Jarvis Skelton]]. She appeared in 2003 and 2005.

After appearing briefly in 2003 whilst Jarvis was involved in a dancing competition with [[Edna Birch]], Freda returns to Emmerdale in late 2005. She offers Jarvis the chance to live in [[Spain]] with her. He accepts her offer and they leave the village on 5 December 2005.
&lt;br clear=&quot;right&quot; /&gt;


==Jean Tate==
{{Infobox soap character
|series=Emmerdale
|color=#99CCCC
|name=Jean Tate
|portrayer=[[Megan Pearson]]
|years=2003&amp;ndash;2005
|born=24 January 2003
|first=24 January 2003
|last=22 September 2005
|family=[[Tate family]]
|parents=[[Scott Windsor]]&lt;br&gt;[[Zoe Tate]]
|grandparents=[[Reg Dawson]]&lt;br&gt;[[Frank Tate (Emmerdale)|Frank Tate]]&lt;br&gt;[[Viv Hope]]&lt;br&gt;Jean Tate
|aunts/uncles=[[Donna Windsor-Dingle]]&lt;br&gt;[[Cathy Hope]]&lt;br&gt;[[Liam Hammond]]&lt;br&gt;[[Chris Tate]]&lt;br&gt;[[James Tate (Emmerdale)|James Tate]]&lt;br&gt;[[Heath Hope]] 
|cousins=[[Joseph Tate (Emmerdale)|Joseph Tate]]&lt;br&gt;[[Noah Tate]]
}}

'''Jean Tate''' is the daughter of [[Zoe Tate]] and [[Scott Windsor]]. She appeared from 2003 to 2005.

Jean is conceived during a one-night stand between Zoe Tate and Scott Windsor while Zoe, a [[lesbian]], was suffering from [[schizophrenia]]. Jean is named after Zoe's mother. Her father is unknown until Scott comes forward while Jean is in hospital following an accident when she fell off a table. Eventually, Zoe allows Scott access to Jean but then plans to leave for [[New Zealand]]. Scott takes Zoe, Jean and her cousin Joseph hostage at gunpoint. Scott's mother, [[Viv Hope]], talks him round and Zoe, Joseph and Jean leave the village. 
&lt;br clear=&quot;right&quot; /&gt;

==Rachel Whatmore==
{{Infobox soap character
|series=Emmerdale
|color=#99CCCC
|name=Rachel Whatmore
|portrayer=Zoe Lambert
|years=2003&amp;ndash;2005
|first=1 June 2003
|last=6 May 2005
|occupation=Lawyer
}}

'''Rachel Whatmore''' is the solicitor for the Tate family. She appeared from 2003 to 2005.

Rachel is first seen when representing [[Chris Tate]] in his personal matters, as she helps him to dispose of most of his money and make sure his wife [[Charity Tate]] has nothing. Unknown to Rachel, Chris is dying and plans to commit suicide and frame Charity for his murder. Zoe has to run the Tate empire after her brother's death, and she becomes close to Rachel, especially after she learns Rachel, like her, is a lesbian. In early 2004, Zoe attempts to have a romantic relationship with [[Scott Windsor]], the father of her child, but her feelings for Rachel lead to an affair. Scott's mother [[Viv Hope]] sees them and tells Scott, leading to a confrontation and Rachel ends the relationship. A year later, Zoe asks Rachel if they can try again, but Rachel is now in a new relationship.

In June 2005, Zoe faces charges for the attempted murder of Scott, but Rachel is on holiday, and her colleague Neil Depaul instead takes Zoe's case.
&lt;br clear=&quot;right&quot; /&gt;

==Eddie Hope==
{{Infobox soap character
|series=Emmerdale
|color=#99CCCC
|image1= 
|name=Eddie Hope
|portrayer=[[Nigel Betts]]
|years=2003, 2007
|first=4 September 2003
|last=25 July 2007
|siblings=[[Bob Hope (Emmerdale)|Bob Hope]]
|spouse=Moira Hope
|nieces/nephews=[[Jamie Hope]]&lt;br&gt;[[Josh Hope]]&lt;br&gt;[[Heath Hope]]&lt;br&gt;[[Dawn Woods]]&lt;br&gt;Carly Hope&lt;br&gt;[[Roxy Lockhart]]&lt;br&gt;[[Cathy Hope]]
}}

'''Edward Maurice &quot;Eddie&quot; Hope''' is the brother of [[Bob Hope (Emmerdale)|Bob Hope]]. He appeared in 2003 and 2007.

Eddie first appears in Emmerdale in late 2003. He tries to romance [[Lisa Dingle]], whose husband [[Zak Dingle|Zak]] is away in [[Chile]], but she does remain loyal to her husband. He leaves the village on 26 November. Eddie returns in February 2007 when he is the new sales manager for ''Naughty Nylons''. He offers Bob a job as a salesman, much to the annoyance of Bob's wife [[Viv Hope|Viv]]. During his time in the village he tries to win Viv from Bob, but this fails. He leaves the village in July 2007.
&lt;br clear=&quot;right&quot; /&gt;

==T.J. Woods==
{{Infobox soap character
|series=Emmerdale
|color=#99CCCC
|image1= 
|name=T.J. Woods
|portrayer=Connor Lee
|parents=[[Terry Woods (Emmerdale)|Terry Woods]]&lt;br&gt;[[Dawn Woods]]
|siblings=Thomas Carter (half)
|grandparents=[[Duke Woods]]&lt;br&gt;[[Bob Hope (Emmerdale)|Bob Hope]]&lt;br&gt;[[Jean Hope]]
|aunts/uncles=[[Jamie Hope]]&lt;br&gt;[[Josh Hope]]&lt;br&gt;Oliver Hope&lt;br&gt;[[Heath Hope]]&lt;br&gt;[[Carly Hope]]&lt;br&gt;[[Roxy Lockhart]]&lt;br&gt;Emma Hope&lt;br&gt;[[Cathy Hope]]
|years=2003-2011
|residence=Connelton View
|born=19 October 2003
|first=19 October 2003
|last=21 January 2011
}}

'''Terence &quot;Terry&quot; Woods Junior''', known as '''T.J.''', is the son of [[Terry Woods (Emmerdale)|Terry]] and [[Dawn Woods]]. He first appeared on his birth in 2003 and appeared intermittently for seven years until 2011.

T.J. is born on 19 October 2003, and when he is a few days old his father Terry has a stroke. With Dawn having to care for both Terry and TJ, their marriage comes under strain and they split up. In July 2006, after learning of Terry's relationship with her mother [[Jean Hope|Jean]], Dawn decides to leave the village and move to [[Cornwall]] with TJ. Jean talks Terry out of launching a custody battle. However, before they can leave Emmerdale, Dawn is killed in the [[Major Storylines of Emmerdale#Kings River Explosion 2006|Kings River House explosion]] on 13 July 2006. 

Jean accepts compensation for Dawn's death from the King family and decides to move to [[Morocco]], and without Terry knowing decides to take TJ with her. However, Dawn's brother [[Jamie Hope]] tells Terry and he rushes to the airport, but is too late to stop them departing. Terry then travels to Morocco and returns in January 2007 with TJ. TJ is still confused as to where his mother has gone and Terry has to explain, and they release a balloon in her memory. In April 2008, TJ contracts [[Escherichia coli|e.coli]] and is taken to hospital to recover. Later in 2008, TJ becomes a more sarcastic child and is unhappy with his father's relationship with [[Brenda Walker (Emmerdale)|Brenda Walker]], but later accepts her. 
On 13 January 2011, TJ is orphaned when Terry is killed in an arson attack. On 21 January, TJ goes to live with Jean in Morocco although he does not want to go as he thinks it is too hot in Morocco and that Moroccans wear &quot;funny hats&quot;.
&lt;br clear=&quot;right&quot; /&gt;

==Denzil Calburn==   
{{Infobox soap character
|series=Emmerdale   
|color=#99CCCC   
|name=Denzil Calburn   
|portrayer=Danny Lawrence   
|years=2003&amp;ndash;2005   
|first=15 December 2003    
|last=22 September 2005   
|occupation=[[Police officer]]
|romances=[[Chas Dingle]] (2003, 2005)
}}   
'''Police Constable Denzil Calburn''' is a [[police officer]]. He appeared intermittently for two years from 2003 to 2005.

A local constable, PC Calburn has a brief relationship with [[Chas Dingle]] after he offers to change a flat tyre for her when she breaks down on the side of the road. However, she later falls in love with [[Carl King (Emmerdale)|Carl King]]. Denzil breaks up with Chas when she repeatedly lies for her lawbreaking father, [[Shadrach Dingle]] who steals Denzil's patrol car, humiliating him. Denzil returns to give evidence at [[Zoe Tate]]'s trial for the attempted murder of [[Scott Windsor]] in September.
&lt;br clear=&quot;right&quot; /&gt;

==Gordon Livesy==
{{Infobox soap character
|series=Emmerdale
|color=#99CCCC
|name=Gordon Livesy
|portrayer=Gerard Fletcher
|years=2003, 2004, 2006, 2008
|first=24 December 2003
|last=8 December 2008
|occupation=
|spouse=[[Chas Dingle]] (?-?)&lt;br&gt;[[List of minor Emmerdale characters (2006)#Sandra Livesy|Sandra Livesy]] (?-)
|children=[[Aaron Livesy]]&lt;br&gt;Unnamed child
}}
'''Gordon Livesy''' is the former husband of [[Chas Dingle]] and the father of [[Aaron Livesy]]. He appeared in 2003, 2004, 2006 and 2008.

Gordon makes visits to Emmerdale in 2003, 2004 and 2006 when he drops off Aaron to spend time with Chas. When [[Louise Appleton]] tells him that she saw Chas hit Aaron, Gordon is angry and tells Chas that he will stop her having access to Aaron. He next appears in 2008 when Aaron is arrested after becoming a drug mule for a local crime family, the McFarlanes. Chas goes to the police station and later goes to see Gordon to find out what had been going on. Gordon tells her that he had thrown Aaron out after he hit Sandra, Gordon's second wife with whom he has a child. Aaron later asks to go back to his father's, but Gordon says they need a break from him and lets him stay with Chas. Later that night, Aaron vandalises Gordon's office, although he cannot prove it. Gordon hasn't been seen since.
&lt;br clear=&quot;right&quot; /&gt;

==References==
{{reflist}}

[[Category:Emmerdale characters|2003]]
[[Category:Lists of minor fictional characters|Emmerdale, 2003]]
[[Category:Fictional characters introduced in 2003|*, Emmerdale]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
