<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="2093711" ns="0" title="Lobo (New Mexico mascot)"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">[[File:UNM Lobo Logo.png|thumb|right| UNM Lobos logo]]

'''The Lobo''' is the official [[mascot]] of the [[University of New Mexico]].  [[Lobo]], the [[Spanish language|Spanish]] word for &quot;wolf,&quot; was suggested by George S. Bryan, a sophomore at UNM, in 1920.  

&quot;The Lobo is respected for his cunning, feared for his prowess, and is the leader of the pack,&quot; read Bryan's editorial in the Oct. 1, 1920 issue of the UNM student newspaper.  &quot;... All together now; 15 rahs for the LOBOS.&quot;

The Lobo became the official mascot of the school.  For a brief period in the 1920's, a live wolf pup appeared at every football game, but UNM administrators were forced to cease the practice when a child teased the wolf and was subsequently bitten.

''The Daily Lobo'' is the name of UNM's daily campus newspaper.

Human mascots, dubbed &quot;Lobo Louie&quot; and &quot;Lobo Lucy,&quot; currently rouse crowds at New Mexico athletic events.  During [[Fran Fraschilla]]'s short coaching tenure at UNM there was a small &quot;Baby Lobo&quot; mascot who appeared at men's basketball games but the Baby Lobo, in reality Fraschilla's son, left when Fraschilla quit the program. The Lobo was present at every Lobo home game, even those that started at 10 p.m. on a school night.

For some years in the 1980s, a popular chant among Lobo fans was, &quot;Everyone's a Lobo, Woof Woof Woof!&quot;  Coach [[Dave Bliss]] phased out the cheer shortly after his arrival in the early 1990s.  In recent years, however, the cheer has slowly started to resurface, and the UNM student section have begun using the chant more and more at Lobo sporting events.

==Statues==
There are three Lobo statues on the central campus of UNM: the first, sculpted by Michelle Middleton, is located in a grove of pine trees overlooking the intersection of Central and University at the southwest corner of campus. The second is a Lobo head emerging out of the ground located in front of Hodgin Hall. The third, sculpted by John Tatschl, is located atop a pedestal at the intersection of Stanford and Redondo and is dedicated to the UNM students and alumni who gave their lives in World War II.  This statue was formerly located in front of [[Zimmerman Field]].

==External links==
*[http://www.unm.edu/welcome/traditions/mascot.html UNM Traditions]

{{MWC Mascots}}

{{US-west-university-stub}}
[[Category:New Mexico Lobos]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
