<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="20947" ns="0" title="Adobe Flash"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">'''Adobe Flash''' (formerly '''Macromedia Flash''') is a [[multimedia]] [[Platform (computing)|platform]] used to add [[animation]], video, and [[interactivity]] to web pages. Flash is frequently used for advertisements, games and [[flash animations]] for broadcast. More recently, it has been positioned as a tool for &quot;[[Rich Internet Application]]s&quot; (&quot;RIAs&quot;).

Flash manipulates [[vector graphics|vector]] and [[raster graphics]] to provide animation of text, drawings, and still images. It supports bidirectional [[Streaming media|streaming]] of audio and video, and it can capture user input via mouse, keyboard, microphone, and camera. Flash contains an [[object-oriented language]] called [[ActionScript]] and supports automation via the Javascript Flash language (JSFL).

Flash content may be displayed on various computer systems and [[information appliance|devices]], using [[Adobe Flash Player]], which is available free of charge for common [[web browser]]s, some [[mobile phone]]s and a few other [[electronic device]]s (using [[Flash Lite]]).

Some users feel that Flash enriches their web experience, while others find the extensive use of Flash animation, particularly in advertising, intrusive and annoying, giving rise to a [[cottage industry]] that specializes in blocking Flash content. Flash has also been criticized for adversely affecting the usability of web pages.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.useit.com/alertbox/20001029.html|title=Flash: 99% Bad |accessdate=2011-01-08 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

{{See also|Adobe Flash Player}}

==History==
Flash originated with the application SmartSketch, developed by [[Jonathan Gay]]. It was published by [[FutureWave Software]], which was founded by Gay and [[Charlie Jackson (software)|Charlie Jackson]]. SmartSketch was a drawing application for pen computers running the [[PenPoint OS]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.flashmagazine.com/413.htm |title=The Flash History |accessdate=2001-06-18 |last=Waldron |first=Rick |authorlink= |coauthors= |date=2006-08-27 |work= |publisher=Flashmagazine |pages= |archiveurl= |archivedate= |quote= }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
 | last = Gay | first = Jonathan | authorlink = Jonathan Gay | title = The History of Flash
 | publisher = Adobe Systems Inc. | year = 2001
 | url = http://www.adobe.com/macromedia/events/john_gay/page02.html
 | accessdate = 2009-10-18}}&lt;/ref&gt; When PenPoint failed in the marketplace, SmartSketch was ported to Microsoft Windows and Mac OS. As the [[Internet]] became more popular, FutureWave added cell animation editing to the vector drawing capabilities of SmartSketch and released [[FutureSplash Animator]] on multiple platforms.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web| url=http://coldhardflash.com/2008/02/grandmasters-of-flash-an-interview-with-the-creators-of-flash.html | title=Grandmasters of Flash: An Interview with the Creators of Flash | accessdate=2008-02-12 | publisher=ColdHardFlash.com}}&lt;/ref&gt; FutureWave approached [[Adobe Systems]] with an offer to sell them FutureSplash in 1995, but Adobe turned them down at that time. FutureSplash was used by [[Microsoft]] in its early work with the Internet ([[MSN]]), and also by Disney Online for their subscription-based service, Disney's Daily Blast. In 1996, FutureSplash was acquired by Macromedia and released as '''Flash,''' contracting &quot;Future&quot; and &quot;Splash&quot;. Flash is currently developed and distributed by [[Adobe Systems]], as the result of their 2005 purchase of Macromedia.

===Rich Internet Applications===

'''Adobe Labs''' (previously called ''Macromedia Labs'') is a source for news and pre-release versions of emerging products and technologies from Adobe. Most innovations, such as Flash 10, [[Macromedia Flex|Flex]] 3, and [[ActionScript]] 3.0 have all been discussed and/or trialled on the site.

One area Adobe is focusing on (as of February 2009) is the deployment of [[Rich Internet Applications]] (RIAs). To this end, they released [[Adobe Integrated Runtime]] (AIR), a [[cross-platform]] [[runtime environment]] that builds rich internet applications in Adobe Flash. The output can be deployed as [[application software|desktop applications]]. It surpassed 100 million installations worldwide in February 2009.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web| url =http://blogs.adobe.com/air/2009/01/air_passes_100_million_install.html?sdid=EENCL | title = AIR passes 100 million installations | accessdate = 2009-02-03}}&lt;/ref&gt; Flash can be installed independently from Adobe's website (adobe.com) and is installed silently when Adobe Reader is installed.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web| url=http://kb2.adobe.com/cps/520/cpsid_52001.html | title = Adobe Download Manager FAQ &amp;#124; Flash Player and Reader | accessdate = 2011-01-19}}&lt;/ref&gt;{{failed verification|date=January 2011}}

Two additional components designed for large-scale implementation have been proposed by Adobe for future releases of Flash: first, the option to require an ad to be played in full before the main video piece is played; and second, the integration of [[digital rights management]] (DRM) capabilities. This way Adobe can give companies the option to link an advertisement with content and make sure that both are played and remain unchanged.&lt;ref name=&quot;BBCVideoControl&quot;&gt;{{cite news|url=http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/business/6558979.stm |title=Adobe unveils Flash video control |accessdate=2007-06-18 |author= |authorlink= |coauthors= |date=2007-04-16 |work=[[BBC News]] |publisher=BBC |pages= |archiveurl= |archivedate= |quote= }}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Open Screen Project===

On May 1, 2008, Adobe announced the ''Open Screen Project'', which hopes to provide a consistent application interface across devices such as [[personal computer]]s, [[mobile device]]s, and [[consumer electronics]].&lt;ref name=&quot;osppr&quot;&gt;{{cite web|title=Adobe and Industry Leaders Establish Open Screen Project|url=http://www.adobe.com/aboutadobe/pressroom/pressreleases/200805/050108AdobeOSP.html|accessdate=2009-02-20|date=2008-05-01}}&lt;/ref&gt; When the project was announced, several goals were outlined: the abolition of licensing fees for Adobe Flash Player and [[Adobe Integrated Runtime]], the removal of restrictions on the use of the [[Adobe Shockwave|Shockwave]] Flash (SWF) and Flash Video (FLV) [[file format]]s, the publishing of [[Application Programming Interface|application programming interfaces]] for porting Flash to new devices, and the publishing of The Flash Cast protocol and Action Message Format (AMF), which let Flash applications receive information from remote databases.&lt;ref name=&quot;osppr&quot;/&gt;

{{As of|February 2009}}, the specifications removing the restrictions on the use of SWF and FLV/F4V specs have been published.&lt;ref name=&quot;interview&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.uiresourcecenter.com/rich-internet-applications/articles/inside-the-open-screen-project.html?s=2_1 |title=Inside the Open Screen Project |first=Anup| last=Murarka|accessdate=2009-02-21}}&lt;/ref&gt; The Flash Cast protocol—now known as the Mobile Content Delivery Protocol—and AMF protocols have also been made available,&lt;ref name=&quot;interview&quot;/&gt; with AMF available as an open source implementation, [[BlazeDS]]. Work on the device porting layers is in the early stages. Adobe intends to remove the licensing fees for Flash Player and Adobe AIR for devices at their release for the Open Screen Project.

The list of mobile device providers who have joined the project includes [[Palm, Inc.|Palm]], Motorola, and Nokia,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.openscreenproject.org/partners/current_partners.html| title=Open Screen Project partners|accessdate=2009-02-20}}&lt;/ref&gt; who, together with Adobe, have announced a $10 million Open Screen Project fund.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Adobe and Nokia Announce $10 Million Open Screen Project Fund|url =http://www.adobe.com/aboutadobe/pressroom/pressreleases/200902/021609AdobeNokia.html|date=2009-02-16|accessdate=2009-02-20}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Flash for mobile platforms===

Flash Player for smart phones was made available to handset manufacturers at the end of 2009.&lt;ref name=&quot;palmpr&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.adobe.com/aboutadobe/pressroom/pressreleases/200902/021609AdobePalmOSP.html|title=Palm Latest Mobile Industry Leader to Join Open Screen Project|accessdate=2009-02-20|date=2009-02-16}}&lt;/ref&gt;. 

=== Decline ===

In [[November]] [[2011]] there were a number of announcements that demonstrated a decline in demand for [[rich internet application]] architectures, and Flash in particular&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web||url=http://www.theinfoboom.com/articles/adobe-flash-player-turfed-for-mobile-devices/|title=Adobe Flash Player Turfed for Mobile Devices |accessdate=2011-11-11}}&lt;/ref&gt;.

However, in November 2011 Adobe announced the end of Flash for mobile platforms or TV, instead focusing on [[HTML5]] for browser content and [[Adobe AIR]] for the various mobile [[List of digital distribution platforms for mobile devices|AppStores]] &lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://tideart.com/?id=4ebafb57|title=Web designers: Time to ditch Flash, Silverlight, and embrace HTML5}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.zdnet.com/blog/networking/flash-is-dead-long-live-html5/1633|title=Flash is dead. Long live HTML5 |accessdate=2011-11-12| date=2011-11-09|publisher=[[ZDNet]]}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://blogs.adobe.com/conversations/2011/11/flash-focus.html|title=Flash to Focus on PC Browsing and Mobile Apps; Adobe to More Aggressively Contribute to HTML5|accessdate=2011-11-12|date=2011-11-09|publisher=[[Adobe Systems]]|quote=''We will no longer continue to develop Flash Player in the browser to work with new mobile device configurations (chipset, browser, OS version, etc.) following the upcoming release of Flash Player 11.1 for Android and BlackBerry PlayBook''}}&lt;/ref&gt;. Pundits questioned its continued relevance even on the desktop&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=PlayBook has a Flash-filled future; RIM's worst decision to date?|url=http://www.zdnet.com/blog/perlow/without-mobile-adobe-flash-is-irrelevant/19247}}&lt;/ref&gt; and described it as &quot;the beginning of the end&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=The beginning of the end for Adobe's Flash|url=http://money.cnn.com/2011/11/10/technology/adobe_flash/|accessdate=11 November 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;. RIM announced that it would continue to develop Flash for the PlayBook.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=PlayBook has a Flash-filled future; RIM's worst decision to date?|url=http://www.zdnet.com/blog/btl/playbook-has-a-flash-filled-future-rims-worst-decision-to-date/63118|accessdate=11 November 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Format==
{{main|SWF}}
Flash files are in the ''SWF'' format, traditionally called &quot;'''S'''hock'''W'''ave '''F'''lash&quot; movies, &quot;Flash movies,&quot; or &quot;Flash applications&quot;, usually have a .swf [[file extension]], and may be used in the form of a web page plug-in, strictly &quot;played&quot; in a standalone Flash Player, or incorporated into a self-executing Projector movie (with the .exe extension in [[Microsoft Windows]]). [[Flash Video]] files&lt;ref group=&quot;spec&quot;&gt;FLV and F4V [http://www.adobe.com/devnet/flv/pdf/video_file_format_spec_v9.pdf Video File Format Specification Version 9]&lt;br /&gt;F4V is based on [[ISO base media file format]] standard:[http://standards.iso.org/ittf/PubliclyAvailableStandards/c051533_ISO_IEC_14496-12_2008.zip freely available ISO standards] , and also available via subscription [http://www.iso.org/iso/catalogue_detail?csnumber=41828]&lt;/ref&gt; have a .flv file extension and are either used from within .[[swf]] files or played through a flv-aware player, such as [[VLC media player|VLC]], or [[QuickTime]] and [[Windows Media Player]] with external [[codec]]s added.

The use of vector graphics combined with program code allows Flash files to be smaller — and thus for streams to use less [[Bandwidth (computing)|bandwidth]] — than the corresponding bitmaps or video clips. For content in a single format (such as just text, video, or audio), other alternatives may provide better performance and consume less [[central processing unit|CPU]] power than the corresponding Flash movie, for example when using transparency or making large screen updates such as photographic or text fades.

In addition to a vector-rendering engine, the Flash Player includes a virtual machine called the ActionScript Virtual Machine (AVM) for scripting interactivity at run-time, support for video, MP3-based audio, and bitmap graphics. As of Flash Player 8, it offers two video codecs: [[On2 Technologies]] [[VP6]] and [[sorenson codec|Sorenson Spark]], and run-time support for [[JPEG]], Progressive JPEG, [[Portable Network Graphics|PNG]], and [[Graphics Interchange Format|GIF]]. In the next version, Flash is slated to use a [[Just-in-time compilation|just-in-time]] compiler for the ActionScript engine.

Flash Player is a browser plugin, and cannot run within a usual e-mail client, such as [[Microsoft Outlook|Outlook]]. Instead, a link must open a browser window. A [[Gmail]] labs feature allows playback of YouTube videos linked in emails.

===Flash Video===
{{Main|Flash Video}}
Virtually all browser plugins for video are [[Gratis#Software|free of charge]] and cross-platform, including Adobe's offering of Flash Video, which was first introduced with Flash version 6. Flash Video has been a popular choice for websites due to the large [[#Installed user base|installed user base]] and programmability of Flash. In 2010, Apple [[#Criticism|publicly criticized]] Adobe Flash, including its implementation of video playback for not taking advantage of hardware acceleration, one reason Flash is not to be found on Apple's mobile devices. Soon after Apple's criticism, Adobe demoed and released a beta version of Flash 10.1, which takes advantage of GPU hardware acceleration even on a Mac. Flash 10.2 beta, released December 2010, adds hardware acceleration for the whole video rendering pipeline.

===Flash Audio===
Flash Audio is most commonly encoded in [[MP3]] or AAC ([[Advanced Audio Coding]]) however it does also support [[ADPCM]], Nellymoser ([[Nellymoser Asao Codec]]) and [[Speex]] audio codecs. Flash allows sample rates of 11, 22 and 44.1&amp;nbsp;kHz. It does not support 48&amp;nbsp;kHz audio sample rate, which is the standard TV and DVD sample rate.

On August 20, 2007, Adobe announced on its blog that with Update 3 of Flash Player 9, Flash Video will also support some parts of the [[MPEG-4]] international standards.&lt;ref name=MP4&gt;{{cite web
|url=http://www.kaourantin.net/2007/08/what-just-happened-to-video-on-web_20.html
|title=What just happened to video on the web
|publisher=Adobe
}}&lt;/ref&gt; Specifically, Flash Player will have support for video compressed in [[H.264]] (MPEG-4 Part 10), audio compressed using [[Advanced Audio Coding|AAC]] (MPEG-4 Part 3), the F4V, [[MP4]] (MPEG-4 Part 14), M4V, M4A, [[3GP]] and [[.mov|MOV]] multimedia [[Container format (digital)|container formats]], [[3GPP]] [[Timed Text]] specification (MPEG-4 Part 17), which is a standardized subtitle format and partial parsing support for the 'ilst' atom, which is the [[ID3]] equivalent [[iTunes]] uses to store [[metadata]]. [[MPEG-4 Part 2]] and [[H.263]] will not be supported in F4V file format. Adobe also announced that it will be gradually moving away from the FLV format to the standard ISO base media file format ([[MPEG-4 Part 12]]) owing to functional limits with the FLV structure when streaming H.264. The final release of the Flash Player supporting some parts of MPEG-4 standards had become available in Fall 2007.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.adobe.com/aboutadobe/pressroom/pressreleases/200708/082107FlashPlayer.html |title=Adobe Press release on MPEG-4 support in Flash Player 9 |publisher=Adobe.com |date= |accessdate=2010-12-04}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Adobe Flash Player 10.1 does not support acoustic echo cancellation, unlike the VoIP offerings of Skype and Google Voice, making this and earlier versions of Flash less suitable for group calling or meetings. Flash Player 10.3 Beta incorporates acoustic echo cancellation.

Adobe previously announced that version 11 of Adobe Flash Player would support the new royalty-free container, WebM, but for yet unclarified reasons there is no WebM support in Adobe Flash Player 11.[http://blogs.adobe.com/flashplatform/2010/05/adobe_support_for_vp8.html See announcement]

===Scripting language===
{{See|ActionScript}}

===Vendor dependence===
{{See also|Proprietary software}}

The reliance on Adobe for decoding Flash is seen as a concern by advocates of [[open standard]]s and [[free software]]. Proponents of open standards generally favor formats for which specifications are openly available and complete enough to make independent implementation straightforward. One advantage is that data stored in the format will be [[future proof]] in the presence of such specifications. Another possible advantage, as desired by proponents of free software, is having a usable implementation in free software.

Adobe's restrictions on the use of the SWF/FLV specifications have been lifted as of February 2009 (see [[#Open Screen Project|Adobe's Open Screen Project]]). However, despite efforts of projects like [[Gnash]], [[Swfdec]] and [[Lightspark]], a complete free software Flash player is yet to be seen, as of September 2011. For example, Gnash has no support for SWF v10 yet. &lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
|url=http://www.gnu.org/s/gnash/
|title=Gnash homepage
|accessdate=2011-9-4
|publisher=Gnu.org
}}&lt;/ref&gt; Notably, Gnash has been a long standing [http://www.fsf.org/campaigns/priority-projects/ high priority project] of the [[Free Software Foundation]], first noted by this article in December 2007 and ranked number one in September 2011.

Historically, notable representants of [[free software]], [[open standards]] and the [[World Wide Web]] have warned against use of Flash for the above reasons:

Founder of [[Mozilla Europe]], [[Tristan Nitot]], problematized in 2008:
&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
|url=http://news.zdnet.com/2424-3515_22-199508.html
|title=Mozilla warns of Flash and Silverlight 'agenda'
|last=Nitot|first=Tristan
|publisher=[[ZDNet]]
|date=2008-04-29
|accessdate=2011-9-4
}}&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;Companies building websites should beware of proprietary rich-media technologies like Adobe's Flash and Microsoft's Silverlight. (…) You're producing content for your users and there's someone in the middle deciding whether users should see your content.&lt;/blockquote&gt;

Representing open standards, inventor of [[Cascading Style Sheets|CSS]] and co-author of [[HTML5]], [[Håkon Wium Lie]] explained in a [[AtGoogleTalks|Google tech talk]] of 2007, entitled &quot;the &amp;lt;video&amp;gt; element&quot;, the proposal of [[Theora]] as the format for [[HTML5 video]]:&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
|url=http://video.google.com/videoplay?docid=5545573096553082541
|title=Håkon Wium Lie on the video element in HTML 5
|accessdate=2009-02-22
|publisher=Google Video
|date=2007-03-29}}&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;I believe very strongly, that we need to agree on some kind of baseline video format if [the video element] is going to succeed. Flash is today the baseline format on the web. The problem with Flash is that it's not an open standard.&lt;/blockquote&gt;

Presenting the [[free software movement]], [[Richard Stallman]] stated in a speech in 2004 that:&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://video.google.com/videoplay?docid=-1647626314188526128
|title=Richard Stallman on The free software movement and its challenges
|accessdate=2009-02-21
|date=2004-10
|publisher=Google Video
|location=Australian National University, Canberra, Australia}}&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;The use of Flash in websites is a major problem for our community.&lt;/blockquote&gt;

===Disclosure===
In October 1998, Macromedia disclosed the Flash Version 3 Specification to the world on its website. It did this in response to many new and often semi-open formats competing with SWF, such as Xara's [[Xara Flare|Flare]] and Sharp's [[Extended Vector Animation]] formats. Several developers quickly created a [[C (programming language)|C]] [[C library|library]] for producing SWF. In February 1999, the company introduced [[MorphInk]] 99, the first third-party program to create SWF files. Macromedia also hired [[Middlesoft]] to create a freely available [[development kit|developers' kit]] for the SWF file format versions 3 to 5.

Macromedia made the Flash Files specifications for versions 6 and later available only under a [[non-disclosure agreement]], but they are widely available from various sites.

In April 2006, the Flash SWF file format specification was released with details on the then newest version format (Flash 8). Although still lacking specific information on the incorporated video compression formats (On2, Sorenson Spark, etc.), this new documentation covered all the new features offered in Flash v8 including new ActionScript commands, expressive filter controls, and so on. The file format specification document is offered only to developers who agree to a license agreement that permits them to use the specifications only to develop programs that can export to the Flash file format. The license forbids the use of the specifications to create programs that can be used for playback of Flash files. The Flash 9 specification was made available under similar restrictions.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.adobe.com/licensing/developer/fileformat/faq/ |title=Adobe File Format Specification FAQ |accessdate=2007-11-15 |publisher=Adobe Systems |archiveurl = http://web.archive.org/web/20071111094129/http://www.adobe.com/licensing/developer/fileformat/faq/ &lt;!-- Bot retrieved archive --&gt; |archivedate = 2007-11-11}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In June 2009, Adobe launched the [[Open Screen Project]] ([http://www.adobe.com/openscreenproject/faq/ Adobe link]), which made the SWF specification available without restrictions. Previously, developers could not use the specification for making SWF-compatible players, but only for making SWF-exporting authoring software. The specification still omits information on codecs such as [[Sorenson codec|Sorenson Spark]], however.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web| title = Free Flash community reacts to Adobe Open Screen Project | url = http://www.openmedianow.org/?q=node/21 | accessdate = 2008-11-29 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Authoring tools==
===Adobe Flash Professional===
{{main|Adobe Flash Professional}}

The Adobe Flash Professional multimedia authoring program is used to create content for the [[Adobe Engagement Platform]], such as web applications, games and movies, and content for mobile phones and other embedded devices.

===Third-party tools===
[[Open Source]] projects like [[Ajax Animator]] and the (now defunct) [[UIRA]] aim to create a Flash development environment, complete with a graphical user environment. Alternatively, programs such as [[Vectorian Giotto]], [[swfmill]], [[SWFTools]], and [[MTASC]] provide tools to create SWF files, but do so by compiling text, actionscript or XML files into [[Flash animation]]s. It is also possible to create SWF files programmatically using the [[Ming library]], which has interfaces for [[C (Programming Language)|C]], [[PHP]], [[C++]], [[Perl]], [[Python (programming language)|Python]], and [[Ruby (programming language)|Ruby]]. [[haXe]] is an open source, high-level object-oriented programming language geared towards web-content creation that can compile Flash files.

Many [[shareware]] developers produced Flash creation tools and sold them for under US$50 between 2000 and 2002. In 2003 competition and the emergence of free Flash creation tools had driven many third-party Flash-creation tool-makers out of the market, allowing the remaining developers to raise their prices, although many of the products still cost less than US$100 and support ActionScript. As for open source tools, [[KToon]] can edit vectors and generate SWF, but its interface is very different from Macromedia's. Another, more recent example of a Flash creation tool is [[SWiSH Max]] made by an ex-employee of Macromedia. [[ToonBoom|Toon Boom]] Technologies also sells a traditional animation tool, based on Flash.

In addition, several programs create [[.swf]]-compliant files as output from their programs. Among the most famous of these are [[Screencast]] tools, which leverage the ability to do lossless compression and playback of captured screen content to produce demos, tutorials, or software simulations of programs. These programs are typically designed for use by non-programmers, and create Flash content quickly and easily, but cannot actually edit the underlying Flash code (i.e. the tweening and transforms, etc.) [[Screencam]] is perhaps the oldest screencasting authoring tool to adopt Flash as the preferred output format, having been developed since the mid-90s. The fact that screencasting programs have adopted Flash as the preferred output is testament to Flash's presence as a ubiquitous cross-platform animation file format.

Other tools focus on creating specific types of Flash content. [[Anime Studio]] is a 2D animation software package specialized for character animation that creates SWF files. [[Express Animator]] is similarly aimed specifically at animators. [[Question Writer]] publishes its quizzes to Flash file format.

Users who are not programmers or web designers will also find on-line tools that allow them to build full Flash-based websites. One of the oldest services available (1998) is [http://www.flashtogo.com/ FlashToGo]. Such companies provide a wide variety of pre-built models (templates) associated to a Content Management System that empowers users to easily build, edit and publish their websites. Other sites, that allows for greater customization and design flexibility are [[Wix.com]] and [[CirclePad]].

Adobe wrote a software package called [[Adobe LiveMotion]], designed to create interactive animation content and export it to a variety of formats, including SWF. LiveMotion went through two major releases, but failed to gain any notable user base.

In February 2003, Macromedia purchased Presedia, which had developed a Flash authoring tool that automatically converted PowerPoint files into Flash. Macromedia subsequently released the new product as Breeze, which included many new enhancements. In addition, (as of version 2) [[Apple Inc.|Apple]]'s [[Keynote (presentation software)|Keynote]] presentation software also allows users to create interactive presentations and export to SWF.

{{anchor|Installed user base}}

==User experience==
===Availability on operating systems===

;Desktop operating systems

Adobe Flash Player (software) exists for a variety of desktop operating systems, including [[Windows]], [[Mac OS 9]]/[[Mac OS X|X]], [[Linux]], [[Solaris (operating system)|Solaris]], [[HP-UX]], [[OS/2]], [[QNX]], [[BeOS]], and [[IRIX]].

Flash as a format has become widespread on the desktop market; one estimate is that 95% of PCs have it,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://statowl.com/plugin_overview.php |title=Web Browser Plugin Market Share |accessdate=2009-08-18 |publisher=StatOwl}}&lt;/ref&gt; while Adobe claims that 98 percent of U.S. web users and 99.3 percent of all Internet desktop users have installed the Flash Player,&lt;ref&gt;98%: [[NPD Group|NPD]] [http://www.macromedia.com/software/player_census/npd/ study]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Flash Player Statistics&quot;&gt;99.3%: Millward Brown survey, conducted June 2009. {{cite web|url=http://www.adobe.com/products/player_census/flashplayer/ |title=Flash Player Statistics |accessdate=2009-06-04 |author= |authorlink= |date= |year= |month= |work= |publisher=Adobe Systems |pages= |archiveurl= |archivedate= |quote= }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;turfwar&quot;&gt;{{cite journal
|last=Shankland
|first=Stephen
|title=HTML vs. Flash: Can a turf war be avoided?
|publisher=[[CNET News]]
|url=http://news.cnet.com/8301-30685_3-20000037-264.html
|date=February 3, 2010
|accessdate=December 26, 2010
}}&lt;/ref&gt; with 92 to 95% (depending on region) having the latest version.&lt;ref name=&quot;versionpenetration&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.adobe.com/products/player_census/flashplayer/version_penetration.html |title=Adobe Flash Player Version Penetration |accessdate=2009-06-04|author= |authorlink= |date= |year= |month= |work= |publisher=Adobe Systems |pages= |archiveurl= |archivedate= |quote= }}&lt;/ref&gt; Numbers vary depending on the detection scheme and research demographics.

;Mobile operating systems

Adobe Flash Player exists for a variety of mobile operating systems, including [[Android (operating system)|Android]] (since version 2.2&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|author=Posted on Tuesday, Apr 27, 2010 by Phil Nickinson|url=http://www.androidcentral.com/andy-rubin-says-flash-coming-froyo-version-android-operating-system |title=Andy Rubin says Flash is coming in Froyo version of Android operating system |publisher=Androidcentral.com |date=2010-04-27 |accessdate=2010-12-04}}&lt;/ref&gt;), [[Pocket PC]]/[[Windows CE]], [[QNX]] (e.g. on [[BlackBerry PlayBook]]), [[Symbian]], [[Palm OS]], and [[webOS]] (since version 2.0&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|author=Sascha Segan|url=http://www.pcmag.com/article2/0,2817,2371016,00.asp#fbid=tFzIWK6F9kL |title=HP WebOS 2.0 with Flash: Hands On |publisher=PCMAG.com |date=2010-10-19 |accessdate=2011-10-16}}&lt;/ref&gt;).

There is no Adobe Flash Player for iOS devices (iPhone, iPad and iPod Touch). The iPhone accounts for more than 60% of global smartphone web traffic and the iPod touch makes up more than 95% of &quot;mobile Internet device&quot; traffic{{citation needed|date=October 2011}}. This hurts Adobe's ability to market Flash as a ubiquitous mobile platform. However, Flash content can be made to run on iOS devices in a variety of ways:
* Flash content can be bundled inside an Adobe AIR app, which will then run on iOS devices. (Apple didn't allow this for a while, but they relaxed those restrictions in September 2010.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|author=Joseph Menn|url=http://www.ft.com/intl/cms/s/2/86cf0890-bc32-11df-8c02-00144feab49a.html#axzz1ay3FpLua |title=Apple relaxes app developer rules |publisher=FT.com |date=2010-09-09 |accessdate=2011-10-16}}&lt;/ref&gt;)
* On March 8, 2011, Techradar reported that Adobe provides an experimental server side tool (Wallaby) to convert Flash programs (as far as possible) to HTML5 code, thus allowing iOS devices to display the content.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|author=Gary Marshall &lt;!----&gt; |url=http://www.techradar.com/news/internet/flash-is-coming-to-the-ipad-ipad-2-and-iphone-934133 | title=Flash is coming to the iPad, iPad 2 and iPhone | publisher=techradar.com |date=2011-03-08 |accessdate=2011-03-08}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* If the content is Flash video being served by Adobe Flash Media Server 4.5, the server will translate and send the video as HTTP Dynamic Streaming or HTTP Live Streaming, both of which can be played by iOS devices.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|author=Jonny Evans|url=http://blogs.computerworld.com/18922/adobe_brings_flash_free_flash_to_apple_ipad_iphone |title=Adobe brings Flash-free-Flash to Apple iPad, iPhone |publisher=COMPUTERWORLD |date=2011-09-09 |accessdate=2011-10-16}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The mobile version of [[Internet Explorer 8]] for [[Windows Phone]] does not support Flash.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|last=Hemphill|first=Kenny|date=15 September 2011|title=Microsoft ditches Flash support in tablet version of Internet Explorer|journal=[[MacUser]]|publisher=[[Dennis Publishing]]|location=London|url=http://www.macuser.co.uk/5470-microsoft-ditches-flash-support-in-tablet-version-of-internet-explorer}}&lt;/ref&gt; The IE9 web browser on Microsoft Windows Phone 7.5 ('Mango') does not support Flash either.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|author=Sascha Segan|url=http://www.pcmag.com/article2/0,2817,2387190,00.asp#fbid=tFzIWK6F9kL |title=Microsoft Windows Phone 7.5 'Mango' |publisher=PCMAG.com |date=2010-09-27 |accessdate=2011-10-16}}&lt;/ref&gt;

On November 9, 2011, Adobe announced&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|author=Tom Loftus|url=http://blogs.wsj.com/digits/2011/11/09/tech-today-adobe-to-drop-mobile-flash-750-jobs/|title=Tech Today: Adobe to Drop Mobile Flash, 750 Jobs |publisher=WSJ |date=2011-11-09 |accessdate=2011-10-16}}&lt;/ref&gt; that it will no longer develop Flash for Mobile Platforms and is planning on developing new products with more open technologies and standards like HTML5, JavaScript and CSS3.{{failed verification|date=November 2011}}

;Other operating systems

[[Adobe Flash Lite]] is a lightweight version of Adobe Flash Player intended for mobile phones and other portable electronic devices like [[Chumby]] and [[iRiver]].

===Availability in countries under U.S. economic sanctions===
Downloading Flash is blocked in countries that are under U.S. [[economic sanction]]s (such as Syria &amp; Sudan). Users in these countries are blocked (by Adobe) from downloading Flash plug-ins for both Internet Explorer and Firefox browsers.{{Citation needed|date=November 2010}}

===Accessibility===
Using Flash tends to break conventions associated with normal HTML pages. Selecting text, scrolling,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.useit.com/alertbox/20050711.html |title=Scrolling and Scrollbars (Jakob Nielsen's Alertbox) |publisher=Useit.com |date=2005-07-11 |accessdate=2010-12-04}}&lt;/ref&gt; form control and right-clicking act differently than with a regular HTML webpage. Many such interface unexpectancies are fixable by the designer. Usability expert [[Jakob Nielsen (usability consultant)|Jakob Nielsen]] published an Alertbox in 2000 entitled, ''Flash: 99% Bad'', which listed issues like these.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.useit.com/alertbox/20001029.html|title=Flash: 99% Bad|last=Nielsen|first=Jakob|date=2000-10-29 |accessdate=2009-02-21}}&lt;/ref&gt; Some problems have been at least partially fixed since Nielsen's complaints:
* Text size can be controlled using full page zoom, found in many modern browsers.
* It has been possible for authors to include alternative text in Flash since Flash Player 6. This [[Accessibility#Telecommunications and IT access|accessibility]] feature is compatible only with certain [[screen readers]] and only under Windows.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.skillsforaccess.org.uk/howto.php?id=101 |title=Provide text equivalents for graphics - in Flash |accessdate=2007-06-18 |author= |authorlink= |coauthors= |date= |year= |month= |work=Skills for Access – How To |publisher= |pages= |archiveurl= |archivedate= |quote= }}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Performance===
* Any Flash player must be able to animate on top of video renderings, which makes [[Hardware acceleration|hardware accelerated]] video rendering at least not as straightforward as with a purpose-built [[Media player (application software)|multimedia player]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://blogs.adobe.com/penguin.swf/2010/01/solving_different_problems.html Solving Different Problems « Penguin.SWF]. Blogs.adobe.com. Retrieved on 2010-11-09.&lt;/ref&gt; Therefore, even when only displaying video, Flash players are more resource-intensive than dedicated video player software.
* Comparisons have shown Adobe Flash Player to perform better on [[Windows]] than [[Mac OS X]] and [[Linux]] with the same hardware.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://arstechnica.com/software/news/2008/10/benchmarking-flash-player-10.ars|title=Flash benchmarks on different operating systems}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last=Paul |first=Ryan |url=http://arstechnica.com/media/news/2009/10/hands-on-hulu-desktop-for-linux-beta-a-big-resource-hog.ars |title=Hands-on: Hulu Desktop for Linux beta a big resource hog |publisher=Arstechnica.com |date=2009-10-16 |accessdate=2010-12-04}}&lt;/ref&gt; However, the 10.1 update significantly improved performance for Mac OS X.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.timo-ernst.net/2010/05/flash-player-10-1-performance-explosion/|title=Flash 10.1: Performance improvements for Mac OS X}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Flash blocking in web browsers===

[[File:Noflash.png|thumb|Some websites rely heavily on Flash and become unusable without Flash Player, or with Flash blocked]]

Flash content is usually embedded using the &lt;code&gt;object&lt;/code&gt; or &lt;code&gt;embed&lt;/code&gt; [[HTML element]]&lt;ref&gt;http://validator.w3.org/docs/help.html#faq-flash&lt;/ref&gt; Software that does not support either of these elements, and users who cannot or will not install a plugin, will see the replacement text if this is supplied by the web page.

Some web browsers default to not play Flash content before the user clicks on it, e.g. [[Konqueror]], [[K-Meleon]]. Equivalent &quot;Flash blocker&quot; extensions also exist for many popular browsers: Firefox has [[Flashblock]] and [[NoScript]], and Opera versions since 10.5 feature native Flash blocking. Opera Turbo requires the user to click to play Flash content. Internet Explorer has Foxie, which contains a number of features, one of them also named Flashblock. WebKit-based browsers under Mac OS X, such as Apple's Safari, have ClickToFlash.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://hoyois.github.com/safariextensions/clicktoplugin/|title=ClickToFlash|accessdate=2011-07-27}}&lt;/ref&gt;

{{anchor|Security}}

==Flash client security==
Flash's security record&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.adobe.com/support/security/#flashplayer|title=Security bulletins and advisories|accessdate=2010-03-27}}&lt;/ref&gt; has caused several security experts to recommend to either not install Flash or to block it.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://news.cnet.com/8301-27080_3-10396326-245.html|title=Expert says Adobe Flash policy is risky|date=2009-11-12|accessdate=2010-03-27}}&lt;/ref&gt; The [[United States Computer Emergency Readiness Team|US-CERT]] recommends to block Flash using [[NoScript]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.us-cert.gov/reading_room/securing_browser/|title=Securing Your Web Browser|accessdate=2010-03-27}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Charlie Miller (security researcher)|Charlie Miller]] recommended &quot;not to install Flash&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.oneitsecurity.it/01/03/2010/interview-with-charlie-miller-pwn2own/|title=Pwn2Own 2010: interview with Charlie Miller|date=2010-03-01|accessdate=2010-03-27}}&lt;/ref&gt; at the [[computer security conference]] [[CanSecWest]]. As of October 31, 2010, The Flash Player has over 100 [[Common Vulnerabilities and Exposures|CVE]] entries,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.securityfocus.com/cgi-bin/index.cgi?o=0&amp;l=100&amp;c=12&amp;op=display_list&amp;vendor=Adobe&amp;title=Flash%20Player|title=SecurityFocus search results for Adobe Flash Player Vulnerabilities|accessdate=2010-10-31}}&lt;/ref&gt; 65 of which have been ranked with a high severity (leading to [[arbitrary code execution]]), and 40 ranked medium. In February 2010, Adobe officially apologized&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://blogs.adobe.com/emmy/archives/2010/02/flash_bug_repor.html|title=Flash Bug Report|date=2010-02-06|accessdate=2010-03-27}} {{Dead link|date=September 2010|bot=H3llBot}}&lt;/ref&gt; for not fixing a known vulnerability for over 1 year. In June 2010 Adobe announced a &quot;critical vulnerability&quot; in recent versions, saying there are reports that this vulnerability is being actively exploited in the wild against both Adobe Flash Player, and Adobe Reader and Acrobat.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.adobe.com/support/security/advisories/apsa10-01.html|publisher=[[Adobe Systems]]|title=Security Advisory for Flash Player, Adobe Reader and Acrobat |accessdate=2010-06-08}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|url=http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/technology/10257411.stm|title=Adobe acknowledges critical security flaw in software|publisher=[[BBC News Online]]|date=June 7, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; Later, in October 2010, Adobe announced&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.adobe.com/support/security/advisories/apsa10-05.html|publisher=[[Adobe Systems]]|title=Security Advisory for Adobe Flash Player, Adobe Reader and Acrobat|accessdate=2010-10-31}}&lt;/ref&gt; another critical vulnerability, this time also affecting [[Android (operating system)|Android]]-based mobile devices. Android users have been recommended to disable Flash or make it only on demand.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.mobilecrunch.com/2010/10/29/flash-vulnerability-revealed-for-android-fix-coming-november-9th/|publisher=[[MobileCrunch]]|title=Flash vulnerability revealed for Android, fix coming November 9th|accessdate=2010-10-31}}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Symantec]]'s Internet Security Threat Report&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www4.symantec.com/Vrt/wl?tu_id=SUKX1271711282503126202|title=Internet Security Threat Report: Volume XV: April 2010|publisher=Symantec|pages=37, 40, 42|date=April 2010|accessdate=2010-05-09}}&lt;/ref&gt; states that a [[remote code execution]] in [[Adobe Reader]] and Flash Player&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.securityfocus.com/bid/35759|title=Adobe Acrobat, Reader, and Flash Player Remote Code Execution Vulnerability|date=2009-10-15|accessdate=2010-05-09}}&lt;/ref&gt; was the second most attacked vulnerability in 2009. The same report also recommends to employ browser add-ons wherever possible to disable Adobe Flash Player when visiting untrusted sites. [[McAfee]] predicted that Adobe software, especially Reader and Flash, would be primary target for attacks in 2010.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://mcafee.com/us/local_content/reports/7985rpt_labs_threat-predict_0110_fnl_lores.pdf|title=2010 Threat Predictions|publisher= McAfee Labs|page=2|date=December 2009|accessdate=2010-05-09}}&lt;/ref&gt; Adobe applications had become, at least at some point, the most popular client-software targets for attackers during the last quarter of 2009.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://mcafee.com/us/local_content/reports/threats_2009Q4_final.pdf|title=McAfee Threats Report: Fourth Quarter 2009|publisher=McAfee Avert Labs|page=16|date=February 2010|accessdate=2010-05-09}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Local Shared Objects (“Flash cookies”)===
{{Main|Local Shared Object}}
Like the [[HTTP cookie]], a [[flash cookie]] (also known as a “[[Local Shared Object]]”) can be used to save application data. Flash cookies are not shared across [[Domain name|domains]]. An August 2009 study by the [[Social Science Research Network]] found that 50% of websites using Flash were also employing flash cookies, yet privacy policies rarely disclosed them, and user controls for privacy preferences were lacking.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://papers.ssrn.com/sol3/papers.cfm?abstract_id=1446862|title=Soltani, Ashkan, Canty, Shannon, Mayo, Quentin, Thomas, Lauren and Hoofnagle, Chris Jay: Flash Cookies and Privacy|date=2009-08-10 |accessdate=2009-08-18}}&lt;/ref&gt; Most browsers' cache and history suppress or delete functions do not affect Flash Player's writing Local Shared Objects to its own cache, and the user community is much less aware of the existence and function of Flash cookies than HTTP cookies.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://epic.org/privacy/cookies/flash.html|title=Local Shared Objects -- &quot;Flash Cookies&quot;|publisher=Electronic Privacy Information Center|date=2005-07-21|accessdate=2010-03-08}}&lt;/ref&gt; Thus, users having deleted HTTP cookies and purged browser history files and caches may believe that they have purged all tracking data from their computers when in fact Flash browsing history remains. Adobe's own Flash [http://www.macromedia.com/support/documentation/en/flashplayer/help/settings_manager07.html Website Storage Settings panel], a submenu of Adobe's Flash [http://www.macromedia.com/support/documentation/en/flashplayer/help/settings_manager.html Settings Manager web application], and other [[Local Shared Object#Editors and toolkits|editors and toolkits]] can manage settings for and delete Flash Local Shared Objects.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://kb2.adobe.com/cps/526/52697ee8.html|title=How to manage and disable Local Shared Objects|publisher=Adobe Systems Inc.|date=2005-09-09|accessdate=2010-03-08}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==64-bit support==
64-bit support of Adobe Flash Player was reintroduced in version 11, released October 4, 2011. 32-bit and 64-bit versions for [[Microsoft Windows|Windows]], [[MacOS X|Mac]] and [[Linux]] are released in sync. Other prominent features of the release include hardware acceleration through the Stage3D API.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.phoronix.com/scan.php?page=news_item&amp;px=OTk2Mg |title=Flash Player 11 commented by Phoronix |publisher=Phoronix |date=2011-10-04 |accessdate=2011-10-05}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The first experimental release of 64-bit builds of Adobe Flash Player was for the Linux platform,&lt;ref name=&quot;Linux 64&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url=http://weblogs.macromedia.com/emmy/archives/2008/11/swf_10_spec_available_and_flash_player_alpha_for_64-bit_linux_on_labs.html |title=SWF 10 spec available AND Flash Player alpha for 64-bit Linux on Labs |last=Huang |first=Emmy |publisher=Adobe Systems |date=2008-11-17}}&lt;/ref&gt; on November 11, 2008.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://blogs.adobe.com/penguin.swf/2008/11/ |title=Now Supporting 16 Exabytes |author=Mike Melanson |work=Penguin.SWF Blog |date=2008-11-17 |accessdate=2010-11-09}}&lt;/ref&gt;
The project was closed temporarily on June 15, 2010,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://arstechnica.com/open-source/news/2010/06/64-bit-flash-for-linux-dropped-as-adobe-preps-next-version.ars |title=64-bit Flash for Linux dropped as Adobe preps next version |author=Paul Ryan |date=2010-06-15 |work=Ars Technica |publisher=Condé Nast Digital |accessdate=2010-11-09}}&lt;/ref&gt; while Adobe was preparing for the preview release on September 15, 2010.

The official 32-bit player is still distributed in some 64-bit Linux distributions e.g. [[openSUSE]], older versions of [[Ubuntu (operating system)|Ubuntu]] etc., of which some users have reported problems with the 32-bit player on some websites.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://adammichaelroach.com/blog/110309-installing-adobe-flash-64-bit-ubuntu-910-karmic-koala |title=Installing Adobe Flash 64 bit in Ubuntu 9.10 Karmic Koala |author=Adam Michael Roach |publisher=Adam Michael Roach |date=2009-11-03 |accessdate=2010-12-04}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://nocturn.vsbnet.be/content/flash-problems-64-bit-linux |title=Flash problems on 64-bit Linux |author=Guy Van Sanden |work=Guy Van Sanden's Home |date=2009-11-15  |accessdate=2010-11-09}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.mat-wright.com/2010/02/flash-player-10-for-64-bit-linux.html |title=Flash Player 10 for 64 bit Linux |author=Mat Wright |work=Mat Wright' Blog |date=2010-02-27 |accessdate=2010-11-09}}&lt;/ref&gt; Affected users can install the 64-bit player manually&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://nxadm.wordpress.com/2009/04/26/install-64-bit-adobe-flash-player-on-ubuntu-904/ |title=Install 64-bit Adobe Flash Player on Ubuntu (updated to 11.04) |work=nxadm.wordpress.com |date=2009-04-26 |accessdate=2011-08-16}}&lt;/ref&gt; or through a special repository.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=https://launchpad.net/~sevenmachines/+archive/flash |title=Adobe Flash PPA for Ubuntu |work=SevenMachines |publisher=Canonical Ltd. |accessdate=2011-08-16}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Alternatives ==
{{main|Comparison of HTML5 and Flash}}
{{main|Rich Internet application}}
{{empty section|date=September 2011}}

==See also==
;Adobe Flash
* [[SWF]] file format, the files generated by the Flash application and played by Flash Player.
* [[ActionScript]]
* [[ActionScript code protection]]
* [[Adobe Flash Player]], the runtime that executes and plays back Flash movies.
* [[Adobe Flash Lite]], a lightweight version of Flash Player for devices that lack the resources to run regular Flash movies such as mobile phones, some laptop computers and other portable devices.
* [[List of 2D animation software]]
* [[Flash Video]]
* [[Flash emulator]]
* [[Saffron Type System]], the [[Anti-aliasing|anti-aliased]] text-rendering engine used in version 8 onwards.
* [[Local Shared Object]]
* [[SWFObject]], a JavaScript library used to embed Flash content into webpages.
* [[Flash CMS]], content management for Flash content.
;Other
* [[Gnash]]
* [[HTML5 video]]
* [[Microsoft Silverlight]]
* [[JavaFX]]
* [[OpenLaszlo]]
* [[Synfig]]
* [[Lightspark]]

==Footnotes==
{{Reflist|group=&quot;spec&quot;}}

==References==
{{Reflist|colwidth=30em}}

==External links==
&lt;!--======================== {{No more links}} ============================
 | PLEASE BE CAUTIOUS IN ADDING MORE LINKS TO THIS ARTICLE. Wikipedia |
 | is not a collection of links nor should it be used for advertising. |
 | |
 | Excessive or inappropriate links WILL BE DELETED. |
 | See [[Wikipedia:External links]] &amp; [[Wikipedia:Spam]] for details. |
 | |
 | If there are already plentiful links, please propose additions or |
 | replacements on this article's discussion page, or submit your link |
 | to the relevant category at the Open Directory Project (dmoz.org) |
 | and link back to that category using the {{dmoz}} template. |
 ======================= {{No more links}} =============================--&gt;
* [http://blogs.adobe.com/flashplatform/ Adobe Flash Platform Blog] - official news channel about Adobe Flash
* [http://www.adobe.com/products/flash/ Adobe Flash for MS WinXP/Vista and Mac OS X]
* [http://kb2.adobe.com/cps/406/kb406791.html Flash plug-in for MS Windows 9x / Macintosh OSX 10.1-10.3 / Red Hat Enterprise Linux 3 and 4]
* [http://wiki.benjaminwolsey.de/FLA_Format FLA format specification]
* [http://www.adobe.com/software/flash/about/ Detect if Flash Player is installed]
;Communities:
* [http://forums.adobe.com/community/flash Adobe's Flash Forum]
* [http://www.flexflashforum.com FlexFlashForum.com - Flash Forum]
* [http://www.actionscript.org Actionscript.org - Community Resource / Tutorials]
* [http://www.flashcomponents.net/community/ Flash Forum / Questions and Answers]

{{Animation editors}}
{{Adobe Flash}}
{{AdobeCS}}
{{Adobe eLearning Suite}}
{{Adobe Systems}}
{{Rich Internet applications}}

[[Category:Animation software]]
[[Category:Cross-platform software]]
[[Category:C++ software]]
[[Category:Graphics file formats]]
[[Category:Mac OS software]]
[[Category:Mac OS X software]]
[[Category:Macromedia software|Flash]]
[[Category:Adobe software|Flash]]
[[Category:Adobe Creative Suite|Flash]]
[[Category:Vector graphics editors]]
[[Category:Web development software]]
[[Category:Adobe Flash| ]]
[[Category:2D animation software]]
[[Category:American inventions]]
[[Category:Windows software]]
[[Category:1996 software]]

[[ar:أدوبي فلاش]]
[[az:Adobe Flash]]
[[bn:অ্যাডোবি ফ্ল্যাশ]]
[[zh-min-nan:Macromedia Flash]]
[[bg:Adobe Flash]]
[[ca:Adobe Flash]]
[[cs:Adobe Flash]]
[[da:Adobe Flash]]
[[de:Adobe Flash]]
[[et:Flash]]
[[es:Adobe Flash Professional]]
[[eu:Adobe Flash]]
[[fa:ادوبی فلش]]
[[fr:Adobe Flash]]
[[gl:Adobe Flash]]
[[gu:એડોબ ફ્લેશ]]
[[ko:어도비 플래시]]
[[hi:ऍडोब फ्लैश]]
[[id:Adobe Flash]]
[[is:Adobe Flash]]
[[it:Adobe Flash]]
[[he:אדובי פלאש]]
[[kn:ಅಡೋಬ್ ಫ್ಲ್ಯಾಶ್]]
[[ka:Adobe Flash]]
[[lt:Adobe Flash]]
[[hu:Adobe Flash]]
[[mk:Adobe Flash]]
[[mr:अ‍ॅडोबे फ्लॅश]]
[[ms:Adobe Flash]]
[[nl:Adobe Flash]]
[[ja:Adobe Flash]]
[[no:Adobe Flash]]
[[pl:Adobe Flash]]
[[pt:Adobe Flash]]
[[ro:Adobe Flash]]
[[ru:Adobe Flash]]
[[si:ෆ්ලෑෂ් (මෘදුකාංගය)]]
[[simple:Adobe Flash]]
[[fi:Adobe Flash]]
[[sv:Adobe Flash]]
[[ta:அடோப் ஃப்ளாஷ்]]
[[th:อะโดบี แฟลช]]
[[tr:Adobe Flash]]
[[uk:Adobe Flash]]
[[vi:Adobe Flash]]
[[diq:Adobe Flash]]
[[zh:Adobe Flash]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
