<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="20952693" ns="0" title="IOS jailbreaking"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{lowercase title}}
'''iOS jailbreaking''', or simply '''jailbreaking''', is the process of removing the limitations imposed by [[Apple Inc.|Apple]] on devices running the [[iOS]] [[operating system]] through use of custom [[Kernel (computing)|kernels]]. Such devices include the [[iPhone]], [[iPod Touch]], [[iPad]], and [[Apple TV|2nd Gen Apple TV]]. Jailbreaking allows users to gain [[root access]] to the operating system, allowing iOS users to download additional applications, extensions, and themes that are unavailable through the official [[Apple App Store]]. A jailbroken [[iPhone]], [[iPod Touch]], or [[iPad]] running [[iOS (Apple)|iOS]] can still use the App Store, [[iTunes]], and other normal functions, such as making telephone calls. 

Unlike [[Rooting (Android OS)|rooting]] an Android device, jailbreaking is necessary if the user intends to run software not authorized by Apple. A tethered jailbreak requires that the device be connected to a computer each time it needs to be booted; an untethered jailbreak allows the device to be powered without computer assistance. Under the [[Digital Millennium Copyright Act]], jailbreaking Apple devices is legal in the United States, although Apple has announced that the practice &quot;can void the warranty&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.cultofmac.com/apples-official-response-to-dmca-jailbreak-exemption-it-voids-your-warranty/52463 |title=Apple’s Official Response To DMCA Jailbreak Exemption: It Voids Your Warranty |author= Leander Kahney |date= July 26, 2010 |publisher= Cult Of Mac |accessdate= October 26, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Reasons for jailbreaking==
[[File:Cydia Tweaks section.png|thumb|Cydia displaying a list of software available for jailbroken devices.]]
One of the main reasons for jailbreaking is to expand the feature set limited by Apple and its App Store. Most jailbreaking tools automatically install [[Cydia]], an application for finding and installing software for jailbroken iOS devices.&lt;ref name=&quot;ars&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url= http://arstechnica.com/apple/news/2010/12/iphone-jailbreaker-set-to-bring-cydia-to-mac-os-x.ars |title= iPhone jailbreaker set to bring Cydia to Mac OS X |author= Chris Foresman |date= December 13, 2010 |work= Infinite Loop |publisher= Ars Technica |accessdate=August 2, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; Since software programs available through Cydia do not have to fit App Store guidelines, many of them are not typical self-contained apps but instead are extensions and customizations for iOS and other apps.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url= http://lifehacker.com/5781437/how-to-get-the-most-out-of-your-jailbroken-ios-device |title= How to Get the Most Out of Your Jailbroken iOS Device |author= Adam Dachis |date= March 14, 2011 |work= |publisher= Lifehacker |accessdate=August 2, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Some users look to software outside the App Store to express opposition to [[Apple Inc.|Apple's]] censorship of content through the [[Approval of iOS apps|app approval process]]: in early 2010, Apple banned an app submitted by Pulitzer Prize-winning cartoonist, [[Mark Fiore]], because it &quot;ridiculed public figures&quot;, in violation of Section 3.3.14 of the iPhone Developer Program License Agreement. Apple later called Fiore and asked him to resubmit his app for approval.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url= http://www.wired.com/epicenter/2010/04/apple-bans-satire/ |title= Apple App Store Bans Pulitzer-Winning Satirist for Satire |author= Ryan Singel |date= April 15, 2010 |accessdate= February 12, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; In late 2010, Apple banned the use of apps that allowed users to donate money to non-profit organization and charities.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |url= http://www.nytimes.com/2010/12/09/technology/09charity.html |title= Donations Ban on iPhone Apps Irritates Nonprofits |date= 2010-12-08 |accessdate= 2011-02-12 |work=The New York Times |first=Stephanie |last=Strom}}&lt;/ref&gt; Apple also banned the controversial [[WikiLeaks]] app, stating it &quot;violated their developer guidelines&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |url= http://bits.blogs.nytimes.com/2010/12/21/why-apple-removed-wikileaks-app-from-its-store/|title= Why Apple Removed a WikiLeaks App From Its Store |date= 2010-12-21 |accessdate= 2011-02-12 |work=The New York Times |first=Miguel |last=Helft}}&lt;/ref&gt; As the list of banned apps continues to grow, some users have found jailbreaking to be a viable alternative to Apple’s [[censorship]] of content.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url= http://abcnews.go.com/Technology/AheadoftheCurve/story?id=7415443&amp;page=1|title= Banned by Apple: 9 iPhone App Rejects |author= Ki Mae Heussner |date= 2010-04-24 |accessdate= 2011-02-12}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Installing unapproved software has the potential to affect battery life and system stability, especially if the software is poorly optimized or if the software runs resource-draining services (such as 3G or WiFi).&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url= http://www.businessinsider.com/reasons-not-to-jailbreak-iphone-2011-5 |title= The Truth About Jailbreaking Your iPhone: The 5 Biggest Drawbacks |author= Ellis Hamburger |date= May 3, 2011 |work= SAI: Tools |publisher= Business Insider |accessdate=October 26, 2011 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url= http://lifehacker.com/5799007/why-you-should-not-jailbreak-your-iphone-ipod-touch-or-ipad |title= Four Reasons Not to Jailbreak Your iPhone, iPod touch, or iPad |author= Adam Dachis |date= May 5, 2011 |work= |publisher= Lifehacker |accessdate=October 26, 2011 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url= http://www.pcworld.com/article/202441/5_reasons_to_jailbreak_your_iphone_and_5_reasons_not.html |title= 5 Reasons to Jailbreak Your iPhone - and 5 Reasons Not |author= Brennon Slattery |date= August 3, 2010 |work= Today @ PCWorld |publisher= PCWorld |accessdate=October 26, 2011 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Security==
The first [[iPhone]] [[Computer worm|worm]], iKee, appeared in early November 2009, created by 21-year-old [[Australia]]n [[technical and further education|technical college]] student Ashley Towns of [[Wollongong, New South Wales|Wollongong]]. He told Australian media that he created the worm to raise awareness of security issues; jailbreaking allows users to install a [[Secure Shell|SSH]] service, which is often left in a ''de facto'' unsecure state.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |title= Australian admits creating first iPhone virus |author= Brigid Andersen |url= http://www.abc.net.au/news/2009-11-09/australian-admits-creating-first-iphone-virus/1135474 |newspaper= [[ABC Online]] |date= November 9, 2009 |accessdate=October 26, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; In the same month, [[F-Secure]] reported on a new malicious worm compromising bank transactions from jailbroken phones in the [[Netherlands]], similarly affecting devices where the owner had installed SSH without changing the default password.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|url=http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/technology/8373739.stm |title=New iPhone worm can act like botnet say experts |publisher=BBC News |date=2009-11-23 |accessdate=2010-04-10}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.f-secure.com/weblog/archives/00001822.html |title=Malicious iPhone Worm |work= News from the Lab |publisher=F-secure |author= Mikko |date=2009-11-22 |accessdate=2010-04-10}}&lt;/ref&gt;

On July 15, 2011, Apple released a new version of iOS that closed the exploit used in [[JailbreakMe]] 3.0. The German [[Federal Office for Information Security]] had reported that the &quot;critical weakness&quot; uncovered by JailbreakMe meant that iOS users could potentially have their information stolen or unwittingly download [[malware]] by clicking on maliciously-crafted [[PDF]] files.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.news-record.com/content/2011/07/08/article/security_holes_discovered_in_iphones_ipads|title=Security holes discovered in iPhones, iPads|last=Robertson|first=Jordan|work=[[News &amp; Record]]|agency=[[Associated Press]]|date=2011-07-08|accessdate=2011-07-09}}&lt;/ref&gt; Before Apple released a fix for this security hole, jailbreak users had access to a fix published by the developer of JailbreakMe.

==United States legal issues==
In response to a request by the [[Electronic Frontier Foundation]], the [[United States Copyright Office|U.S. Copyright Office]] explicitly recognized an exemption to the DMCA to permit jailbreaking in order to allow iPhone owners to use their phones with applications that are not available from Apple's store, and to unlock their iPhones for use with unapproved carriers.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.copyright.gov/1201/ |title=Copyright office provides exemption to DMCA |publisher=[[United States Copyright Office]] |date=2009-02-12 |accessdate=2009-07-17}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url= http://news.cnet.com/8301-13578_3-20011661-38.html |title= Feds say mobile-phone jailbreaking is OK |author= Declan McCullagh |date= July 26, 2010 |work= Politics and Law |publisher= CNET |accessdate=October 26, 2011 }}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Apple Inc.|Apple]] had previously filed comments opposing this exemption and indicated that they did consider jailbreaking to be a violation of copyright (and by implication prosecutable under the DMCA). Apple's request to define copyright law to include jailbreaking as a violation was denied as part of the 2009 DMCA rulemaking. In their ruling, the Library of Congress affirmed on July 26, 2010 that jailbreaking is exempt from DMCA rules with respect to circumventing digital locks.  This exemption must be reviewed and renewed every three years or else it will expire.

[[Tim Wu]], a professor at [[Columbia Law School]], argued that jailbreaking is &quot;legal, ethical, and just plain fun.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url= http://www.slate.com/id/2175304/ |title= The iPhone Freedom Fighters |author= Tim Wu |date= October 4, 2007 |work= Technology |publisher= Slate |accessdate=October 26, 2011 }}&lt;/ref&gt; Wu cited an explicit exemption issued by the [[Library of Congress]] in 2006 for personal unlocking, which notes that locks &quot;are used by wireless carriers to limit the ability of subscribers to switch to other carriers, a business decision that has nothing whatsoever to do with the interests protected by copyright&quot; and thus do not implicate the DMCA.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.copyright.gov/fedreg/2006/71fr68472.pdf |title=Federal Register: Exemption to Prohibition on Circumvention of Copyright Protection Systems for |format=PDF |date= |accessdate=2010-09-11}}&lt;/ref&gt; Wu did not claim that this exemption applies to those who help others unlock a device or &quot;traffic&quot; in software to do so. As of July 26, 2010, the U.S. Copyright Office has approved exemptions to the DMCA that allow iPhone users to jailbreak their devices legally.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |author=David Goldman |url=http://money.cnn.com/2010/07/26/technology/iphone_jailbreaking/ |title= Jailbreaking iPhone apps is now legal |publisher= CNN Money |date=2010-07-26 |accessdate=2010-09-11}}&lt;/ref&gt; These exemptions also allow phone users to unlock their phone in order to switch carriers. It is still possible Apple may employ technical countermeasures to prevent jailbreaking or prevent jailbroken phones from functioning, but they will not be able to sue users who jailbreak.&lt;ref name=&quot;otm&quot; /&gt;  It is also unclear whether it is legal to traffic in the tools used to make jailbreaking easy.&lt;ref name=&quot;otm&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.onthemedia.org/transcripts/2010/07/30/03 |title=Transcript of &quot;Jailbreak?&quot; (July 30, 2010) |publisher=On The Media |date=2010-07-30 |accessdate=2010-09-11}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==History of iOS jailbreaking tools ==
''For a chronological list of jailbreak history, see [[History of iOS jailbreaking]].''

Many different developers and developer teams have produced free jailbreaking tools, collectively able to jailbreak almost all iOS devices on most versions of iOS.

A few days after the original iPhone became available in July 2007, developers released the first jailbreaking tool for it,&lt;ref name=&quot;ricker2007&quot;&gt;{{cite web|last=Ricker |first=Thomas |url=http://www.engadget.com/2007/07/10/iphone-hackers-we-have-owned-the-filesystem/ |title=iPhone Hackers: &quot;we have owned the filesystem&quot; |publisher=[[Engadget]] |date=2007-07-10 |accessdate=2009-07-17}}&lt;/ref&gt; and soon a jailbreak-only game app became available.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last=Topolsky |first=Joshua |url=http://www.engadget.com/2007/08/06/first-third-party-game-app-appears-for-iphone/ |title=First third-party &quot;game&quot; app appears for iPhone |publisher=[[Engadget]] |date=2007-08-06 |accessdate=2009-07-17}}&lt;/ref&gt; In October 2007, [[JailbreakMe]] 1.0 (also called &quot;AppSnapp&quot;) allowed people to jailbreak iPhone OS 1.1.1 on both the iPhone and iPod touch,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last=Wilson |first=Ben |url=http://reviews.cnet.com/8301-19512_7-10115200-233.html |title=Official iPhone 1.1.1 jailbreak released with easy-to-follow instructions; does not require TIFF exploit |publisher=[[CNET.com]] |date=2007-10-10 |accessdate=2009-11-10}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.pcworld.com/article/139061/hacker_software_can_install_unauthorized_software_on_iphones.html |title=Hacker Software Can Install Unauthorized Software on iPhones |date=October 29, 2007 |author= Gregg Keizer |publisher=PCWorld |accessdate=August 25, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; and it included [[Installer.app]] as a way to get software for the jailbroken device.

The [[iPhone Dev Team]] has released free desktop-based jailbreaking tools for versions of iOS from 2.0 to 5.0.1 on most devices. They released a version of [[PwnageTool]] in July 2008 to jailbreak the new iPhone 3G on iOS 2.0 as well as the iPod touch,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url= http://www.wired.com/gadgetlab/2008/07/pwnage-20-relea/ |title= Pwnage 2.0 Released: Gadget Lab Jailbreaks iPod Touch |author= Charlie Sorrel |date= July 21, 2008 |work= Gadget Lab |publisher= Wired |accessdate=November 2, 2011 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;iphone3g-pwnage&quot;/&gt; newly including [[Cydia]] as the primary third-party installer for jailbroken software&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url= http://www.tuaw.com/2008/07/20/first-look-pwnage-for-2-0/ |title= First Look: Pwnage for 2.0 |author= Erica Sadun |date= July 20, 2008 |work= |publisher= TUAW |accessdate=November 1, 2011 }}&lt;/ref&gt; (PwnageTool continues to be maintained for more recent releases of iOS up to 4.3.3).&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url= http://blog.iphone-dev.org/post/5239805497/tic-tac-toe |title= Tic tac toe... |author= Dev Team |date= May 2011 |work= |publisher= Dev Team Blog |accessdate=November 2, 2011 }}&lt;/ref&gt; The iPhone Dev Team released QuickPWN to jailbreak iOS 2.2 on iPhone and iPod touch, also including options to enable functionality that was possible but disabled by Apple on certain devices.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url= http://www.wired.com/gadgetlab/2008/11/quickpwn-adds-s/ |title= QuickPWN Adds Street View to iPod Touch |author= Charlie Sorrel |date= November 25, 2008 |work= Gadget Lab |publisher= Wired |accessdate=November 2, 2011 }}&lt;/ref&gt; After Apple released iOS 3.0, the Dev Team published redsn0w as a simple jailbreaking tool usable on Mac and Windows, and also updated PwnageTool (now primarily intended for expert users making custom firmware, and only for Mac).&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url= http://www.readwriteweb.com/archives/how_to_jailbreak_your_iphone_to_os_30.php |title= How to Jailbreak your iPhone to OS 3.0 |author= Sarah Perez |date= June 23, 2009 |work= |publisher= ReadWriteWeb |accessdate=November 2, 2011 }}&lt;/ref&gt; They continue to maintain redsn0w for jailbreaking most versions of iOS 4 and for iOS 5.0 on most devices except the iPad 2 and iPhone 4S.&lt;ref name=&quot;ios5-redsn0w&quot;/&gt;

[[George Hotz]], who had developed the first iPhone unlock, released a jailbreaking tool for the iPhone 3GS on iOS 3.0 called [[purplera1n]],&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url= http://news.cnet.com/8301-17938_105-10279029-1.html |title= iPhone 3GS jailbreak, 'purplera1n,' hits Web |author= Leslie Katz |date= July 3, 2009 |work= Crave |publisher= CNet |accessdate=November 2, 2011 }}&lt;/ref&gt; and [[blackra1n]] for iOS version 3.1.2 on the iPod touch 3rd generation and other devices.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url= http://www.wired.com/gadgetlab/2009/11/blackra1n-plus-blacksn0w-unlock-any-iphone-in-seconds |title= BlackRa1n Plus Blacksn0w: Unlock Any iPhone in Seconds |author= Charlie Sorrel |date= November 5, 2009 |work= Gadget Lab |publisher= Wired |accessdate=November 2, 2011 }}&lt;/ref&gt; In October 2010 he released limera1n, a low-level [[boot ROM]] exploit that permanently works to jailbreak the iPhone 4 and is used as part of tools including redsn0w.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url= http://www.engadget.com/2011/06/07/ios-5-jailbroken/ |title= iOS 5 jailbroken |author= Thomas Ricker |date= June 7 2011 |work= |publisher= Engadget |accessdate=October 26, 2011 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

comex has released multiple jailbreaks for iOS devices, beginning in May 2010 with the [[Spirit (iOS jailbreak)|Spirit]] jailbreak for iOS version 3.1.2 on devices including the iPad for the first time.&lt;ref name=&quot;spirit-register&quot;/&gt; In August 2010, comex released [[JailbreakMe]] 2.0, a web-based tool that was was the first to jailbreak the iPhone 4 (on iOS 4.0.1).&lt;ref name=&quot;jailbreakme-iphone4&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.engadget.com/2010/08/01/official-iphone-4-jailbreak-hits-from-iphone-dev-team/ |title=Official: iPhone 4 jailbreak hits from iPhone Dev Team (updated with video) |publisher=Engadget |date= August 1, 2010 |author=  Sean Hollister |accessdate=September 11, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; In July 2011, comex released JailbreakMe 3.0, a web-based tool for jailbreaking all devices on certain versions of iOS 4.3, including the iPad 2 for the first time (on iOS 4.3.3).&lt;ref name=&quot;jailbreakme-ipad2&quot;/&gt; He was hired by Apple as an intern in August 2011.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url= http://www.forbes.com/sites/andygreenberg/2011/08/26/apple-hacker-extraordinaire-comex-takes-an-internship-at-apple/ |title= Apple Hacker Extraordinaire Comex Takes An Internship At Apple |author= Andy Greenberg |date= August 26, 2011 |work= |publisher= Forbes |accessdate=November 2, 2011 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

Chronic Dev Team initially released [[greenpois0n]] in October 2010, a desktop-based tool for jailbreaking iOS 4.1&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url= http://www.pcmag.com/article2/0,2817,2370522,00.asp#fbid=d7I6xbRm1XV |title= iPhone Hackers Square Off With Competing iOS 4 Jailbreaks |author= David Murphy |date= October 9, 2010 |work= |publisher= PCMag |accessdate=November 2, 2011 }}&lt;/ref&gt; and later iOS 4.2.1&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url= http://www.wired.com/gadgetlab/2011/02/untethered-ios-4-2-1-jailbreak-live/ |title= Untethered iOS 4.2.1 Jailbreak Live |author= Charlie Sorrel |date= February 4, 2011 |work= Gadget Lab |publisher= Wired |accessdate=November 2, 2011 }}&lt;/ref&gt; on most devices including the Apple TV,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url= http://www.pcworld.com/article/208388/oh_hai_apple_tv_officially_hacked.html |title= Oh Hai! Apple TV Officially Hacked |author= Elizabeth Fish |date= October 20, 2010 |work= Geek Tech |publisher= PCWorld |accessdate=November 2, 2011 }}&lt;/ref&gt; as well as iOS 4.2.6 on CDMA (Verizon) iPhones.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url= http://www.pcworld.com/article/218932/verizon_iphone_now_available_for_jailbreaking.html |title= Verizon iPhone Now Available for Jailbreaking |author= Blair Hanley Frank |date= February 7, 2011 |work= Geek Tech |publisher= PCWorld |accessdate=November 2, 2011 }}&lt;/ref&gt;           
===List of first jailbreaks===

&lt;!--Do NOT put a device or OS on this list without a reliable source (e.g. CNN); the jailbreak developer is not considered reliable by Wikipeida standards!--&gt;
{| class=&quot;wikitable&quot; style=&quot;width:70%;&quot;
|-
!Device/OS
!Release date
!Date of first jailbreak
!Tool
!Developer
|-
|[[iPhone (original)|iPhone]]/[[iOS]] 1.0
|June 29, 2007
|July 10, 2007&lt;ref name=&quot;ricker2007&quot;/&gt;
|
|Ziphone
|-
|[[iPhone 3G]]/iOS 2.0
|July 11, 2008
|July 20, 2008&lt;ref name=&quot;iphone3g-pwnage&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url= http://tech.fortune.cnn.com/2008/07/20/dubious-achievement-hackers-jailbreak-the-iphone-3g/ |title= Dubious achievement: Hackers 'jailbreak' the iPhone 3G |author= Philip Elmer-DeWitt |date= July 20, 2008 |work= Apple 2.0 |publisher= CNN Money |accessdate=October 26, 2011 }}&lt;/ref&gt;
|PwnageTool
|[[iPhone Dev Team]]
|-
|iOS 3.0
|March 17, 2009
|June 19, 2009&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url= http://www.engadget.com/2009/06/20/pwnage-tool-for-iphone-os-3-0-now-live-ultrasn0w-still-on-stand/ |title= Pwnage Tool for iPhone OS 3.0 now live, ultrasn0w still on standby |author= Ross Miller |date= June 20, 2009 |work= |publisher= Engadget |accessdate=October 26, 2011 }}&lt;/ref&gt;
|PwnageTool
|iPhone Dev Team
|-
|[[iPhone 3GS]]
|June 19, 2009
|July 3, 2009&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url= http://www.washingtonpost.com/wp-dyn/content/article/2009/07/03/AR2009070300691.html |title= First iPhone 3GS Jailbreak Hits The Web |author= Daniel Brusilovsky |date= July 3, 2009 |work= TechCrunch |publisher= The Washington Post |accessdate=October 26, 2011 }}&lt;/ref&gt;
|purplera1n
|George Hotz
|-
|[[iPad]]
|April 30, 2010
|May 3, 2010&lt;ref name=&quot;spirit-register&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url= http://www.theregister.co.uk/2010/05/03/ipad_jailbreak/ |title= Hackers release jailbreak for iPad and newer iPhones |author= Dan Goodin |date= May 3, 2010 |work= |publisher= The Register |accessdate=October 26, 2011 }}&lt;/ref&gt;
|Spirit
|comex
|-
|iOS 4.0
|June 21, 2010
|June 21–23, 2010&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url= http://www.pcworld.com/article/199713/does_jailbreaking_still_make_sense_with_ios_40.html |title= Does Jailbreaking Still Make Sense with iOS 4.0? |author= Mike Keller |date= June 23, 2010 |work= Geek Tech |publisher= PCWorld |accessdate=October 26, 2011 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url= http://gizmodo.com/5558277/ios-4-jailbroken-within-a-day-of-first-release |title= iOS 4 Jailbroken Within a Day of First Release |author= John Herrman |date= June 8, 2010 |work= |publisher= Gizmodo |accessdate=November 2, 2011 }}&lt;/ref&gt;
|PwnageTool
|iPhone Dev Team
|-
|[[iPhone 4]]
|June 24, 2010
|August 1, 2010&lt;ref name=&quot;jailbreakme-iphone4&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url= http://articles.cnn.com/2010-08-02/tech/jailbreak.iphone.4_1_iphone-4-ios-4-1-jailbreak-apple-app-store?_s=PM:TECH |title= First iPhone 4 'jailbreak' posted online |author= John D. Sutter |date= August 2, 2010 |work= CNN Tech |publisher= CNN |accessdate=October 26, 2011 }}&lt;/ref&gt;
|JailbreakMe 2.0
|comex
|-
|[[iPad 2]]
|March 11, 2011
|July 5, 2011&lt;ref name=&quot;jailbreakme-ipad2&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url= http://news.cnet.com/8301-17938_105-20077154-1/app-enables-ipad-2-jailbreak-from-your-browser/ |title= App enables iPad 2 jailbreak from your browser |author= Eric Mack |date= July 6, 2011 |work= Crave |publisher= CNET |accessdate=October 26, 2011 }}&lt;/ref&gt;
|JailbreakMe 3.0
|comex
|-
|iOS 5.0
|October 12, 2011
|October 13, 2011&lt;ref name=&quot;ios5-redsn0w&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url= http://www.pcworld.com/article/241877/ios_5_jailbreak_is_already_here_geeks_not_surprised.html |title= iOS 5 Jailbreak Is Already Here; Geeks Not Surprised |author= Elizabeth Fish |date= October 13, 2011 |work= Geek Tech |publisher= PCWorld |accessdate=October 26, 2011 }}&lt;/ref&gt;
|redsn0w
|iPhone Dev Team
|}

=== Details of recent releases of jailbreaking tools=== 

{| class=&quot;wikitable sortable collapsible&quot;
|-
! Software Name
! Release Date
! scope=&quot;col&quot; style=&quot;width:120px;&quot;| Hardware 
! scope=&quot;col&quot; style=&quot;width:100px;&quot;| Firmware
! Untethered?
! Notes
! Publisher
|-
| [[JailbreakMe|JailbreakMe 3.0]]&lt;ref name=&quot;jailbreakme-informationweek&quot;&gt;{{cite news |title=Apple iOS Zero-Day PDF Vulnerability Exposed |author= Mathew J. Schwartz |url= http://www.informationweek.com/news/231001147 |newspaper= InformationWeek |date= July 7, 2011 |accessdate=October 23, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;
| July 5, 2011&lt;ref name=&quot;jailbreakme-informationweek&quot;/&gt;
|{{flatlist|
*[[iPhone 3GS]]
*[[iPhone 4]] GSM/CDMA
*[[iPod Touch]]
*[[iPad]]
*[[iPad 2]]
}}&lt;ref name=&quot;jailbreakme-informationweek&quot;/&gt;
| {{nowrap|4.2.6–4.2.8}}&lt;br&gt;{{nowrap|4.3–4.3.3}}&lt;ref name=&quot;jailbreakme-informationweek&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref group=&quot;notes&quot; name=&quot;cdma&quot;&gt;The [[Verizon]] CDMA iPhone 4 ran on iOS 4.2.5 to 4.2.10, with incremental updates being bugfixes that were simultaneously applied from 4.3.1 to 4.3.5.&lt;/ref&gt;
| {{yes}}&lt;ref name=&quot;jailbreakme-informationweek&quot;/&gt;
| Uses a flaw in [[Portable Document Format|PDF]] file rendering in Mobile [[Safari (web browser)|Safari]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url= http://labs.eweek.com/archives/apple-fixes-latest-ios-exploit |title= Apple Fixes Latest iOS Exploit |author= P. J. Connolly |date= July 15, 2011 |work= eWEEK Labs |publisher= eWEEK |accessdate=October 23, 2011 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url= http://esec-lab.sogeti.com/post/Analysis-of-the-jailbreakme-v3-font-exploit |title= Analysis of the jailbreakme v3 font exploit |author= jean |date= July 18, 2011 |work= |publisher= Sogeti ESEC Lab |accessdate=October 23, 2011 }}&lt;/ref&gt;
| comex&lt;ref name=&quot;jailbreakme-informationweek&quot;/&gt;
|-
|seas0npass&lt;ref name=&quot;geektech-howto&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url= http://www.pcworld.com/article/238653/jailbreaking_101_which_tool_to_use_to_hack_your_idevice.html |title= Jailbreaking 101: Which Tool to Use to Hack Your iDevice |author= Mike Keller |date= August 23, 2011 |work= Geek Tech |publisher= PCWorld |accessdate=October 23, 2011 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;seasonpass43&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url= http://blog.firecore.com/5180 |title= Seas0nPass Updated for AppleTV 4.3 |author= james |date= october 18, 2011 |work= |publisher= Firecore |accessdate=October 23, 2011 }}&lt;/ref&gt;
|''c.'' October 18, 2011&lt;ref name=&quot;geektech-howto&quot; /&gt;
|2nd generation [[Apple TV]]&lt;ref name=&quot;geektech-howto&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;seasonpass43&quot;/&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
| 4.3&lt;ref name=&quot;geektech-howto&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;seasonpass43&quot;/&gt;
| {{yes}}&lt;ref name=&quot;geektech-howto&quot;/&gt;
|
|Firecore&lt;ref name=&quot;seasonpass43&quot;/&gt;
|-
|[[redsn0w]] 0.9.9 beta 8&lt;ref name=&quot;howto-ios5&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url= http://www.pcworld.com/article/242116/how_to_jailbreak_your_ios_5_device.html |title= How to Jailbreak Your iOS 5 Device |author= Sarah Jacobsson Purewal |date= October 18, 2011 |work= Phones |publisher= PCWorld |accessdate=October 23, 2011 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;devteam-redsn0wbeta&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url= http://blog.iphone-dev.org/redsn0w-iOS5 |title= redsn0w iOS5beta |author= Dev Team |date= |work= |publisher= Dev Team Blog |accessdate=October 23, 2011 }}&lt;/ref&gt;
| ''c.'' November 3, 2011&lt;ref name=&quot;howto-ios5&quot; /&gt;
|{{flatlist|
*[[iPhone 3GS]]
*[[iPhone 4]] GSM/CDMA
*[[iPod Touch]]
*[[iPad]]
}}&lt;ref name=&quot;howto-ios5&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;devteam-redsn0wbeta&quot;/&gt;
| 4.1–5.0.1
| {{Depends|Untethered: 4.1–4.3.3, 4.2.6–4.2.8&lt;br&gt;
Tethered: 4.2.9–4.2.10, 4.3.4–4.3.5, 5.0-5.0.1&lt;ref name=&quot;devteam-redsn0wbeta&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;cdma&quot; group=&quot;notes&quot; /&gt;}}
| Jailbreak for old-bootrom iPhone 3GS models are untethered on all versions, because of the use of 24kpwn, which exists only in the MB models of the iPod touch 2G and iPhone 3GS old boot-rom.&lt;ref name=&quot;devteam-redsn0wbeta&quot;/&gt;
| |[[iPhone Dev Team]]&lt;ref name=&quot;howto-ios5&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;devteam-redsn0wbeta&quot;/&gt;
|}

==See also==
*[[Hacking of consumer electronics]]
*[[iOS version history]]
*[[Privilege escalation]]
*[[Rooting (Android OS)]]

==Notes==
{{Reflist|group=notes}}

==References==
{{Reflist|2}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Ios Jailbreaking}}
&lt;!-- categories --&gt;
[[Category:IPhone|Jailbreaking]]
[[Category:IOS (Apple)|Jailbreaking]]

[[als:Jailbreak]]
[[ar:كسر آي أو إس]]
[[cs:Jailbreak]]
[[de:Jailbreak (iOS)]]
[[es:Jailbreak (iOS)]]
[[fa:شکستن زندان آیفون]]
[[fr:Jailbreak d'iOS]]
[[ko:IOS 탈옥]]
[[id:IOS jailbreaking]]
[[it:Jailbreak (informatica)]]
[[he:פריצת iOS]]
[[nl:Jailbreak (iOS)]]
[[ja:Jailbreak]]
[[no:Jailbreak (iOS)]]
[[pt:Jailbreak (iPhone OS)]]
[[ro:Jailbreak (iOS)]]
[[ru:Jailbreak]]
[[sk:Jailbreak (iPhone OS)]]
[[sv:Jailbreak_iOS]]
[[uk:Jailbreak]]
[[zh:IOS越狱]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
