<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="209828" ns="0" title="Air America (airline)"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Refimprove|date=February 2009}}
[[File:Air-America--Bell-205-helicopter-at-Hmong-FSB.jpg|thumb|right|300px|'''Air America''' [[Bell 205]] helicopter leaving a [[Hmong people|Hmong]] [[fire support base]] in the Laotian [[Plain of Jars]], circa 1969]]
{{Infobox airline
| airline          = Air America
| image            =
| image_size       =
| alt              =
| IATA             = AAM
| ICAO             = AAM
| callsign         = AIR AMERICA
| founded          = 1950
| commenced        =
| ceased           = 1976
| aoc              =
| bases            =
| hubs             = [[Marana Army Air Field]]&lt;br&gt;&lt;small&gt;([[Tucson]])&lt;/small&gt;
| secondary_hubs   =
| focus_cities     =
| frequent_flyer   =
| lounge           =
| alliance         =
| subsidiaries     =
| fleet_size       = 80+
| destinations     = 2
| company_slogan   =
| parent           = [[Pacific Corporation|American Airdale Corporation]]
| headquarters     = [[Washington, D.C.]]
| key_people       =
| website          =
}}

[[File:AirAmericaPilotCap.jpg|thumb|right|Air America Pilots Cap]]
'''Air America''' was an American passenger and cargo airline established in 1950 and covertly owned and operated by the [[Central Intelligence Agency]]'s (CIA) [[Special Activities Division]] from 1950 to 1976. It supplied and supported [[United States]] [[covert operations]] in [[Southeast Asia]] during the [[Vietnam War]].

==Organization==
In August 1950, the CIA secretly purchased the assets of [[Civil Air Transport]] (CAT), an airline that had been started in China in 1946 by Gen. [[Claire Lee Chennault]] (of [[Flying Tigers]] fame) and Whiting Willauer.&lt;ref name=&quot;air-america.org&quot;/&gt;

In 1951, the parent company of Air America's forerunner, Civil Air Transport (CAT), was reorganized. The owner, Chennault, was approached by the CIA, who bought out the company through a [[holding company]], the [[Pacific Corporation|American Airdale Corporation]]. Under this agreement, CAT was allowed to keep its initials and the company was reorganized as Civil Air Transport, Inc.

On 7 October 1957, American Airdale was reorganized to add another layer of obfuscation to its ownership. The new [[Pacific Corporation]] became a holding company for Air Asia Company ([[Air Asia (Republic of China)|Air Asia (Taiwan)]]), Ltd; Air America, Inc; Civil Air Transport, Inc; [[Southern Air Transport]]; [[Intermountain Airlines|Intermountain Aviation]]; Bird and Sons (known as [[BirdAir]]); and Robinson Brothers. CAT attempted to change its name to Air America at the same time, but objections from [[Air France]] and [[American Airlines]] delayed the name change for two years.

Air America's slogan was &quot;Anything, Anywhere, Anytime, Professionally&quot;. Air America aircraft, including the [[de Havilland Canada DHC-4 Caribou]] and Fairchild [[C-123 Provider]], flew many types of cargo to countries such as the [[Republic of Vietnam]], the [[Kingdom of Laos]], and [[Cambodia]]. It operated from bases in those countries and also from bases in [[Thailand]] and as far afield as [[Taiwan]] and [[Japan]]. It also on occasion flew top-secret missions into [[Burma]] and the [[People's Republic of China]].

[[File:Helio U-10D Air America Laos 1970.jpg|thumb|right|Air America U-10D [[Helio Courier]] aircraft in [[Laos]] on a [[covert]] mountaintop landing strip (LS) &quot;Lima site&quot;.]]
Air America's headquarters moved several times during its existence, 808 17th St. NW, (1964), 801 World Center Bldg, (late 1964), 815 Connecticut Ave NW, (July 1968), and 1725 K Street NW, (1972), all in Washington, DC. Marana, Arizona was the principal continental United States maintenance base for Air America of which was located at [[Pinal Airpark]].

==Operations during the Vietnam War (Second Indochina War)==
From 1959 to 1962 the airline provided direct and indirect support to CIA Operations &quot;Ambidextrous&quot;, &quot;Hotfoot&quot;, and &quot;[[Operation White Star|White Star]]&quot;, which trained the regular Royal Laotian armed forces. After 1962 a similar operation known as ''[[Project 404]]'' fielded numerous U.S. Army [[attaché]]s (ARMA) and [[air attaché]]s (AIRA) to the U.S. [[embassy]] in [[Vientiane]].

From 1962 to 1975, Air America inserted and extracted U.S. personnel, provided logistical support to the [[Royal Lao Army]], [[Hmong people|Hmong]] army under command of [[Royal Lao Army]] [[Major General]] [[Vang Pao]], and combatant Thai &quot;volunteer&quot; forces, transported refugees, and flew photo reconnaissance missions that provided valuable intelligence on [[Viet Cong|NLF]] activities. Its civilian-marked craft were frequently used, under the control of the [[Seventh/Thirteenth United States Air Force|Seventh/Thirteenth Air Force]] to launch search and rescue missions for U.S. pilots downed throughout Southeast Asia. Air America pilots were the only known private U.S. corporate employees to operate non-[[Federal Aviation Administration]]-certified military aircraft in a combat role, although many of them were actually military personnel who had been transferred to the airline.

By the summer of 1970, the airline had some two dozen twin-engine transport aircraft, another two dozen [[STOL|short-take off-and-landing aircraft]], and 30 helicopters dedicated to operations in Burma, Cambodia, Thailand, and Laos. There were more than 300 pilots, copilots, flight mechanics, and airfreight specialists based in Laos and Thailand. During 1970, Air America delivered 46 million pounds (21,000 metric tons) of food in Laos. Helicopter flight time reached more than 4,000 hours a month in the same year.

[[File:Air America Pilatus PC-6 in flight.jpg|thumb|An Air America [[Pilatus PC-6 Porter]].]]

Air America flew civilians, diplomats, spies, refugees, commandos, sabotage teams, doctors, war casualties, drug enforcement officers, drugs, and even visiting VIPs like [[Richard Nixon]] all over Southeast Asia. Its non-human passengers were even more bizarre on occasion; part of the CIA's support operations in Laos, for instance, involved logistical support for local tribes fighting the North Vietnamese forces and the [[Pathet Lao]], their local opponents. [[Forced draft urbanization]] policies, such as the widespread application of [[Agent Orange]] to Vietnamese farmland created a disruption in local food production, so thousands of tons of food had to be flown in, including live chickens, pigs, water buffalo and cattle. On top of the food drops (known as 'rice drops') came the logistical demands for the war itself, and Air America pilots flew thousands of flights transporting and air-dropping ammunition and weapons (referred to as &quot;hard rice&quot;) to friendly forces.

When the [[North Vietnamese Army]] overran South Vietnam in 1975, Air America helicopters participated in [[Operation Frequent Wind]] evacuating both US civilians and South Vietnamese people associated with the regime from [[Saigon]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.historynet.com/air-america-played-a-crucial-part-of-the-emergency-helicopter-evacuation-of-saigon.htm |title=Air America: Played a Crucial Part of the Emergency Helicopter and Fixed Wing Evacuation of Saigon |publisher=History Net |date= |accessdate=2011-04-29}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.air-america.org/Articles/Fall_of_Saigon.shtml#adams |title=Air America Association - Articles |publisher=Air-america.org |date= |accessdate=2011-04-29}}&lt;/ref&gt; The iconic photograph depicting the final evacuation from the &quot;U.S. Embassy&quot; by Dutch photographer [[Hubert van Es]] was actually an Air America helicopter taking people off of an apartment at [[22 Gia Long Street]] building used by [[USAID]] and CIA employees.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.mishalov.com/Vietnam_finalescape.html&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|date=April 23, 2000|url=http://www.nytimes.com/2000/04/23/weekinreview/the-world-getting-it-wrong-in-a-photo.html?pagewanted=1|title=Getting it wrong in a photo|publisher=New York Times|first1=Fox|last1=Butterfield|first2=Kari|last2=Haskell|accessdate=2010-04-23}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Alleged Drug Smuggling===
Air America allegedly transported [[opium]] and [[heroin]] on behalf of [[Hmong people|Hmong]] leader [[Vang Pao]]. This allegation has been supported by former Laos CIA paramilitary [[Anthony Poshepny]] (aka Tony Poe), former Air America pilots, and other people involved in the war.&lt;ref&gt;http://infocollective.org/mccoyabstract.html&lt;!-- Alfred W was Bot generated title --&gt;&lt;/ref&gt;

[[University of Georgia]] historian William M. Leary claims that this was done without the airline employees' direct knowledge (except for those employees that said they did know about it), and that the airline itself did not trade in drugs (only transported them).&lt;ref name=&quot;air-america.org&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.air-america.org/About/History.shtml |title=History of CAT/Air America |publisher=Air-america.org |date= |accessdate=2011-04-29}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Curtis Peebles]] denies the allegation, citing Leary's study as evidence.&lt;ref&gt;Peebles, Curtiss. Twilight Warriors: Covert Air Operations Against the USSR, pp.254-255&lt;/ref&gt;

==After the war==
After pulling out of South Vietnam in 1975, there was an attempt to keep a company presence in Thailand; after this fell through, Air America officially disbanded on June 30, 1976, and was later purchased by [[Evergreen International Airlines]], which continues to provide support for U.S. covert operations.&lt;ref name=&quot;air-america.org&quot;/&gt;

==Airfleet==
During its existence Air America operated a diverse fleet of aircraft, the majority of which were [[STOL]] capable.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.vietnam.ttu.edu/airamerica/best/AirAmerica.htm |title=Air America Inc |publisher=Vietnam.ttu.edu |date=1976-04-01 |accessdate=2011-04-29}}&lt;/ref&gt; There was &quot;fluidity&quot; of aircraft between some companies like Air America, [[Boun Oum Airways|BAA]], [[Continental Air Services, Inc|CASI]] and the USAF. It was not uncommon for USAF and US Army aviation units to loan aircraft to Air America for specific missions. Air America tended to register its aircraft in Taiwan, operating in Laos without the B- nationality prefix. Ex US military aircraft were often used with the &quot;last three&quot; digits of the military serial as a civil marking, sometimes with a B- prefix. The first two transports of Air America arrived in Vientiane, Laos on 23 August 1959. The Air America operations at Udorn, Thailand were closed down on 30 June 1974. Air America's operating authority was cancelled by the CAB on 31 January 1974.

===Fixed wing===
* [[Beech 18]] ex-military C-45 Expediters
** Volpar Beech 18&amp;nbsp;&amp;ndash; [[Volpar]] converted 14 aircraft to [[turboprop]] power with [[Garrett AiResearch TPE-331]] engines; modified aircraft were called '''Volpar Turbo Beeches''' and also had a further increase in MTOW to {{convert|10286|lb|abbr=on}}.&lt;ref name=&quot;AA&quot;&gt;[http://www.utdallas.edu/library/collections/speccoll/Leeker/vtb.pdf &quot;Air America: Beech/Volpar Turbo Beech 18&quot;.] University of Texas at Dallas, 2006. Retrieved: 12 August 2008.&lt;/ref&gt; They were called Volpars in Air America service &lt;ref&gt;P.31 Wings of Air America, A Photo History by Terry Love&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[Beech Baron]]
* [[Beechcraft Model 18|Twin Beechcraft]]
* [[Boeing 727]]-92C
* [[PBY Catalina|Consolidated PBY-5A Catalina]]
* [[Curtiss C-46]]
* [[de Havilland Dragon Rapide|De Havilland DH.89A Dragon Rapide]]
* [[De Havilland Canada DHC-2 Beaver]]
* [[de Havilland Canada DHC-4 Caribou]]
* [[De Havilland Canada DHC-6 Twin Otter]] 300
* [[Dornier Do 28|Dornier Do28 Skyservant]]
* [[Douglas B-26 Invader]]&amp;nbsp;&amp;ndash; [[On Mark Engineering|On Mark]] [[On Mark Marksman|Marksman]] conversion
* [[C-47 Skytrain|Douglas C-47]]
* [[Douglas DC-4]]
* [[Douglas DC-6]]A/B
* [[C-119 Flying Boxcar|Fairchild C-119 Flying Boxcar]]
* [[C-123 Provider|Fairchild C-123B And K Provider]]
* [[Helio Courier]] and Super Courier
* [[Helio Twin Courier]]
* [[Lockheed Constellation|Lockheed L.1049H Constellation]]
* [[C-130 Hercules|Lockheed C-130A/E Hercules]]
* [[Pilatus PC-6|Pilatus Turbo-Porter]] includes [[Fairchild Hiller]] version
* [[Piper Apache]]

===Helicopters===
* [[Bell 47]]
* [[Bell 204]]B
* [[Bell 205]]
* [[CH-47 Chinook|Boeing-Vertol CH-47C Chinook]]
* [[MD Helicopters MD 500|Hughes 500D]]
* [[OH-6 Cayuse|OH-6A Cayuse]]
* [[Sikorsky S-55|Sikorsky S-55/H-19]]
* [[Sikorsky S-58]]T
* [[CH-54 Tarhe|Sikorsky CH-54 Skycrane]]
* [[Sikorsky H-34]]

==Air Asia==
{{main|Air Asia (Republic of China)}}
Air Asia was a wholly owned subsidiary of Air America which provided technical, management and equipment services for [[Civil Air Transport]] of Formosa. Air Asia was headquartered in Taipei and its main facilities were in [[Tainan, Taiwan]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.vietnam.ttu.edu/AirAmerica/Best/AirAmerica.htm |title=Air America Inc |publisher=Vietnam.ttu.edu |date=1976-04-01 |accessdate=2011-04-29}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Accidents and incidents==
*On 16 January 1969, [[Douglas C-47 Skytrain|Douglas C-47A]] 949 crashed in the [[Hai Van Pass]], {{convert|18|mi|km}} south of [[Huế]], [[South Vietnam]]. The aircraft was on a domestic cargo flight from [[Phu Bai International Airport]] to [[Da Nang International Airport]]. All 12 passengers and crew were killed.&lt;ref name=ASN160169&gt;{{cite web|url=http://aviation-safety.net/database/record.php?id=19690116-0 |title=949 Accident Description |publisher=Aviation Safety Network |accessdate=23 January 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*On 29 December 1973, [[Douglas C-53]]D EM-3 overran the runway on landing at [[Dalat Airport]], South Vietnam. The aircraft was substantially damaged and was not salvaged due to the presence of [[land mine]]s in the area. It was operating a non-scheduled passenger flight. All nine people on board survived.&lt;ref name=ASN291273&gt;{{cite web|url=http://aviation-safety.net/database/record.php?id=19731229-1|title=Accident description|publisher=Aviation Safety Network|accessdate=26 August 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*On 29 April 1975, Douglas VC-47A 084 crashed on landing at [[U-Tapao Royal Thai Navy Airfield]], [[Sattahip]], [[Thailand]]. The aircraft was on a flight from [[Tan Son Nhat International Airport]], [[Saigon]], [[Vietnam]].&lt;ref name=ASN290475&gt;{{cite web|url=http://aviation-safety.net/database/record.php?id=19750429-0|title=084 Accident description|publisher=Aviation Safety Network|accessdate=21 August 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==See also==
*[[Air America (film)]]
*1st [[American Volunteer Group]], a World War II unit known as &quot;The [[Flying Tigers]]&quot;
*[[Battle of Lima Site 85]]
*[[Raytheon Intelligence and Information Systems]] E-Systems
*[[Eugene DeBruin]]
*[[Front organization]]
*[[North Vietnamese invasion of Laos]]
*[[Shell corporation]]

==References==
{{Reflist|30em}}

==Further reading==
{{refbegin}}
* Cockburn, Alexander &amp; St. Clair, Jeffrey. ''Whiteout: The CIA, Drugs and the Press''. (Verso, 1998) ISBN 1859842585
* Conboy, Kenneth &amp; Morrison, James. ''Shadow War: The CIA's Secret War in Laos''. Boulder CO: Paladin Press, 1995.
* Dale Scott, Peter. ''Drugs, Oil, and War: The United States in Afghanistan, Columbia and Indochina'' (Rowman and Littlefield, 2003) ISBN 0742525228
* Leary, William M. ''Perilous Missions: Civil Air Transport and CIA Covert Operations in Asia''. (The University of Alabama Press, 1984) ISBN 081730164X
* Love, Terry. ''Wings of Air America: A Photo History'' (Schiffer Publishing Ltd., 1998) ISBN 0764306197
* Parker, James E. Jr. ''Covert Ops: The CIA's Secret War in Laos'' (St Martin’s Press, 1995) ISBN 0312963408
* Robbins, Christopher. ''Air America'' (Corgi, 1988) ISBN 055212821X
** Air America: The Story of the CIA's Secret Airlines by Christopher Robbins (Hardcover – Jan 1, 1978)
** Air America: From WWII to Vietnam: The Explosive True Story of the Cia's Secret Airline by Christopher Robbins (Paperback – Jan 15, 1988)
** Air America: The True Story of the C.I.A.'s Mercenary Fliers in Covert Operations from Pre-war China to Present Day Nicaragua by Christopher Robbins – Jan 1991) Corgi; New Ed edition (January 1991) ISBN 0552137227 ISBN 978-0552137225
** Air America From World War II to Vietnam by Christopher Robbins (Paperback – 2003)
* Robbins, Christopher. ''The Ravens: Pilots of the Secret War of Laos'' (Asia Books Co., 2000) ISBN 9748303411
* ''Vietnam'' Magazine, August 2006
{{refend}}

==External links==
*[https://www.cia.gov/csi/studies/vol50no4/html_files/prisnors.html#_ftnref24 CIA CAT activity elsewhere in the Asian theater is discussed] in the context of Agency officers [[John T. Downey]] and Richard Fecteau, shot down and imprisoned in China in 1952&amp;ndash;1973.
*[http://www.air-america.org Air America Association web site]
*[http://www.vietnam.ttu.edu/virtualarchive/redirects/air.htm Online Materials about Air America in the Vietnam Archive at Texas Tech]
*[http://www.specialforcesroh.com/browse.php?mode=viewc&amp;catid=58 Special Forces Roll of Honour – Air America]
*[http://www.dcothai.com/product_info.php?products_id=382 Robbins, Christopher. ''Air America'']{{Dead link|date=September 2011}}
*[http://www.dcothai.com/product_info.php?products_id=362 Robbins, Christopher. ''The Ravens, Pilots of the Secret War in Laos'']{{Dead link|date=September 2011}}
*[http://www.utdallas.edu/library/collections/speccoll/Leeker/thelio.pdf Air America: Helio H-500 Twin Couriers]
{{Airlines of the United States}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Air America (Airline)}}
[[Category:Airlines established in 1950]]
[[Category:Airlines disestablished in 1976]]
[[Category:Central Intelligence Agency front organizations]]
[[Category:Defunct airlines of the United States]]
[[Category:Helicopter airlines]]
[[Category:Vietnam War]]

[[cs:Air America]]
[[de:Air America]]
[[eo:Air America]]
[[fr:Air America]]
[[it:Air America]]
[[hu:Air America]]
[[nl:Air America (luchtvaartmaatschappij)]]
[[ja:エア・アメリカ]]
[[no:Air America]]
[[pl:Air America]]
[[fi:Air America]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
