<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="21005065" ns="0" title="List of The Bill characters (E-L)"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Inappropriate tone|article|date=April 2009}}
{{In-universe|article|date=October 2009}}
{{DISPLAYTITLE:List of ''The Bill'' characters (E-L)}}
This is a '''list of characters''' from the [[police drama]] ''[[The Bill]]'' ordered alphabetically by character surname. For a full list of characters ordered by rank, see [[list of The Bill characters|list of ''The Bill'' characters]]. The [[Character (arts)|characters]] are all [[police officers]] or civilian staff at the fictional [[Sun Hill (The Bill)|Sun Hill]] [[police station]] in [[London]].

{{The Bill character biographies toc}}

==E==
===Francis “Taffy″ Edwards===
{{Infobox character
| name       = '''Francis Morgan Edwards'''
| first      = Woodentop (16/08/1983)
| last       = I Thought You'd Gone (11/01/1990)
| occupation = Police Officer
| title      = Police Constable
| portrayer  = [[Colin Blumenau]]
}}

PC Francis Edwards - 'Taffy' to his friends - was known as the 'thin streak of Welsh misery'. A quiet country boy who hailed from a poor farming family near Bangor, he sometimes struggled to adapt to city life. Edwards was extremely lazy, often thinking up ingenious ways to avoid having to do serious work - but he had an infectious charm and was popular amongst the relief. He would also wade in with the team when needed. Edwards is probably best remembered for when he got hopelessly drunk on his stag night and ended up stripped naked and abandoned in the street by his mates from Sun Hill - much to the annoyance of Mary, his Welsh bride-to-be. After brushes with pigs, chickens and assorted oddballs, he asked for a transfer back to Wales. His final day convinced him he had made the right decision: Brownlow didn't seem to know who he was and Conway thought he'd already left. In the end he decided to give his own leaving party a miss and headed home alone. He returned for Ken Melvin's funeral later that year. 
  
*Note: 'Taffy' was originally referred to as PC Morgan in the 'Woodentop' storyboard episode. 
{{-}}

==F==
===Will Fletcher===
{{Infobox character
| name       = Will Fletcher
| first      = Episode 371 (14/12/2005)
| last       = Be a Man (7/1/2010)
| occupation = Police Officer
| title      = Detective Constable/Sergeant 
| portrayer  = [[Gary Lucy]]
}}
Will is played by [[Gary Lucy]]. Will grew up in [[Hemel Hempstead]] with his parents and sister.  He was inspired to join the police by a friend of his father's, who was an Area Car driver in the police force and often told him about his work.

Like most others at Sun Hill, he did his training at Hendon. It is not clear where he served his probationary period or indeed how long he has been in the force, but he previously served at Hemel Hempstead and he was later transferred to Sun Hill. 

He is a fan of cars and motorcycles which we found out on his first day when he drove to work no-handed while trying to read a map—in his spare time, he enjoys boxing. When he was injured, he was unable to compete in a boxing tournament with PC [[Dan Casper]],which was something Gina set up. However, he stood in his friend's corner for every match and tried to convince Dan to tell Inspector [[Gina Gold]] about his steroid abuse.

He later began a relationship with PC Honey Harman, but they split up after he refused to go on holiday with her in [[Tenerife]]. but Honey was later shot and killed after being held captive by drug barons. Will was devastated initially, having been one of the first on the scene when Honey's body was discovered, but later came to terms with her death.He became close friends with Dan, and the two were frequently seen paired on the beat together until Dan resigned. Since then he has been paired with PC [[Roger Valentine]], PC [[Benjamin Gayle]] and PC [[Tony Stamp]] among others. He showed strong feelings for colleague PC [[Emma Keane]] and was violently opposed to her marriage to lawyer Matt Hinckley. Despite being beaten up on Emma's wedding day after she revealed to Matt that she slept with Will and being able to prove that Matt was behind the attack, he turned up at the wedding to wish them well. Later, will helped Emma to uncover the truth about Matt's old girlfriend- who supposedly died a few years earlier- and found that she was actually alive and was only just recovering from a nervous break down after having a miscarriage.

Will transferred to CID in August 2008, after his police work impressed [[Neil Manson|DI Manson]]. He was the first uniformed officer to transfer to CID since DC [[Gary Best]]. In July 2009, Will made the move from T/DC to a fully-fledged DC. 

Will has left Sun Hill on 7 January 2010 to be transferred and promoted as Sergeant at another station.
{{-}}

===Rosie Fox===
{{Infobox character
| name       = Rosie Fox
| first      = Deep End (25/08/1998)
| last       = The Trial Of Eddie Santini (02/04/2000)
| occupation = Police Officer
| title      = Police Constable/Detective Sergeant
| portrayer  = [[Caroline Catz]]
}}
PC Rosie Fox first appeared in the episode Deep End. She was immediately the subject of unwanted attention from PC Eddie Santini, who had been assigned to an undercover investigation with her, culminating in Santini nearly raping Fox in the locker room. Subsequently Santini spread lies about her around the station and conducted a campaign of bullying and intimidation, forcing her to request a transfer away from Sun Hill. 

Now promoted to Detective Sergeant, Rosie returned to Sun Hill to investigate the murder of Santini's ex-girlfriend Jessica Orton. She suspected Santini himself of the crime and eventually linked him to it when he was found in possession of the keys to Orton's house. She arrested him for murder. 

Rosie returned again for Santini's manslaughter trial, but was murdered in her hotel room before she could testify against him as part of the elimination of key witnesses by a major crime lord awaiting trial.

===Suzanne Ford===
{{Infobox character
| name       = Suzanne Ford
| first      = Runaround (13/09/1988)
| last       = Balls in the Air (07/11/1991)
| occupation = Police Officer
| title      = Police Constable
| portrayer  = [[Vikki Gee-Dare]]
}}
Caring WPC Suzanne Ford was described as 'the ideal WPC'. She considered becoming a nurse before eventually joining the Metropolitan Police and saw her policing role as essentially one of serving the community rather than catching crooks. She was a natural police officer - 'one of the boys' who always seemed to get sent out on raids - but above all a caring woman. She also had a special ability - sign language, as she had a profoundly deaf sister. She used this skill on one occasion when questioning a deaf suspect. Suzanne left Sun Hill in 1991.

===Robin Frank===
{{Infobox character
| name       = Robin Frank
| first      = Funny Ol' Business - Cops And Robbers (16/10/1984)
| last       = Traffic (11/07/1989)
| occupation = Police Officer
| title      = Police Constable
| portrayer  = [[Ashley Gunstock]]
}}
PC Robin Frank was a steady, reliable type, known for his commitment and integrity. From Bethnal Green in the East End, he was easy going, with a naturally friendly manner and ready smile. He was the son of a schoolteacher and worked in office jobs before joining the Met. Married to Angela, a nurse, Frank was a trained area car driver. Members of the public found him thoughtful and straightforward in his dealings, and the relief knew that he always could be depended on - even if he winged at the more mundane aspects of the job. 

He suffered the trauma of being shot by a robber who had taken a woman hostage in a block of flats in 1985. Recuperating, Frank spent much of his time at the CAD desk and working as the station's crime prevention officer. He left Sun Hill in 1989.

===Christine Frazer===
{{Infobox character
| name       = Inspector Christine Frazer
| first      = Light Duties (19/07/1988)
| last       = I Thought You'd Gone (11/01/1990)
| occupation = Police Officer
| title      = Duty Inspector
| portrayer  = [[Barbara Thorn]]
}}
Christine serves at Sun Hill for a year and a half, replacing Inspector Kite. She is the station's first senior female officer, and one of the very few high-ranking females in the Metropolitan Police. Throughout her time at Sun Hill, this caused much friction between the force, particularly the young male PCs whom she often rubbed the wrong way, and eventually created a foe in Chief Inspector Derek Conway, whose initial respect and support for her waned considerably towards the end of her tenure. Elsewhere in the station, she was held in high regard, particularly by Sergeants Alec Peters and Tom Penny, who also found her particularly attractive. Bob Cryer warmed to her eventually but occasionally found cause to criticise her performance, given her tendency to lean towards &quot;modern&quot; methods of policing, rather than Cryer's own tried and tested traditional means.

She shared past history with DI Frank Burnside, who tried to rekindle romance when he was posted to Sun Hill, and was a target for DS Ted Roach's affections. Christine was not interested in a relationship but conceded to have a drink with Roach - gossip later turned this into a full-blown affair and Conway warned Roach to break it off or face immediate transfer. She was also perhaps the only officer at Sun Hill to have known of Burnside's true history in the force (most believed him bent over the years), before ousting his undercover involvement in Operation Countryman to gossiping Sergeants Cryer, Penny and Peters, thus explaining his apparent crooked ways. Burnside was particularly ungrateful afterwards. 

In late 1989 Christine became the first female inspector to take the Met's riot training course, and during the ensuing mayhem &quot;froze&quot; as her team came under heavy attack, exposing them to serious danger. She quickly overcame the fear and successfully completed the course, but couldn't stop the training supervisor from reporting her bungle to Chief Superintendent Brownlow. 

This, along with continued pressure on her to perform above and beyond to prove herself in the rank as a woman, culminated in a bad appraisal from Conway which ultimately Brownlow agreed with during a heated meeting, and he refused to recommend her for promotion. Instead he suggested she continue at Sun Hill for another year in her present rank. Christine reluctantly refuses, instead taking extended leave to write a thesis about discrimination in the force, specifically sexism. She does not return to Sun Hill following this period and presumably resigns from the Met. during her leave.
{{-}}

===Delia French===
{{Infobox character
| name       = Delia French
| first      = Don’t Like Mondays (25/07/1989)
| last       = Acting Detective (26/03/1992)
| occupation = Police Officer
| title      = Police Constable
| portrayer  = [[Natasha Williams]]
}}
Once in charge of the station typing pool, Jamaican-born Delia French left to take a clerical job in the city before returning to Sun Hill in 1990 as a probationary WPC. Delia was a feisty addition to the ranks of Sun Hill - she had no qualms in berating members of CID for the poor quality of interview transcripts, and also was a bit of a gossip - taking great interest in the business affairs of every officer in the station. She could be tough when she wanted to, and was by no means a push-over. Delia also had a razor sharp wit and was not afraid to use it. But her infectious enthusiasm soon broke down barriers and made her friends in the station. 

Delia went undercover for Burnside on one occasion when a woman who collapsed at an airport was found carrying drugs in her stomach. She took the woman's place and successfully led CID to the dealer. She left Sun Hill shortly after the operation.

==G==
===Roy Galloway===
{{Infobox character
| name       = Roy Galloway
| first      = Woodentop (16/08/1983)
| last       = Not Without Cause (07/12/1987)
| occupation = Police Officer
| title      = Detective Inspector
| portrayer  = [[Robert Pugh]] ''(Pilot)''&lt;br&gt;[[John Salthouse]] ''(series)''
}}
Roy Galloway prides himself on being one of the youngest Inspectors in the [[Metropolitan Police]]. An impulsive man, he is a thief taker in the classic mould, always seeming to be playing a game of good old fashioned cops and robbers. Nobody is above suspicion for Galloway. Even when fencing information from one of his snouts, he always takes what they say with a grain of salt.

Although he sometimes shows a wisdom of years beyond his own age, Galloway is also every bit as fiery as his red-coloured hair suggests. When frustrated, he will not hesitate to take those frustrations out on colleagues. This places him in many tricky situations with his immediate subordinate, DS [[Ted Roach]], who wants Galloway's job. At one point, [[June Ackland]] considers resigning after Galloway blames her for his own troubles. Only the timely intervention of Sergeant [[Bob Cryer (The Bill)|Bob Cryer]] stops the situation from escalating out of control.

He is married, with one daughter. The pressures of his job lead to him spending less and less time with them, however. Eventually he goes through a bitter divorce, which he takes hard. Characteristically, this only leads to him throwing himself even further into his work.

Over time, he mellows to the point where he is even willing to step in defence of Bob Cryer after he accidentally runs into a pensioner in a car during a wet, night-time call out. The two men share a strong long-time bond, but rarely has Galloway been so proactive in helping his uniform colleagues.

After three years in [[Sun Hill (The Bill)|Sun Hill]], Galloway decides to leave. The exact reasons for his departure are kept vague and confidential, but it comes as a shock to some and a relief to others.
{{-}}

===George Garfield===
{{Infobox character
| name       = George Garfield
| first      = Only a Little Bit of Thieving (02/05/1989)
| last       = Love and War part II (14/10/1999)
| occupation = Police Officer
| title      = Police Constable
| portrayer  = [[Huw Higginson]]
}}
You could call PC George 'Ears' Garfield uncomplicated, or you could be honest and call him a bit thick. Though he was no use helping you finish your crossword, he was a bloke you could rely on when the thumping and kicking started. Subtlety may have been lost on him, but he could do the job and he liked doing it, more and more. 

Londoner George joined the Met. at nineteen because it was steady employment and he’d not had much luck with other jobs he’d tried since leaving school. But he didn’t much like the leafy suburb of Teddington, to which he was sent – too dull – and used his excess energy in the boxing ring. He reached ABA quarter finals standard. He was a pretty fair snooker player, too. 

After repeated requests for a posting to a busier manor, he was transferred to Sun Hill early in 1989. He got on with most of the people there. Stamp was a good mate. He had run-ins with Dave Quinnan and Steve Loxton, both of whom could be a bit aggressive if rubbed up the wrong way. Unlike them, Garfield could control his temper, although occasionally he could be something of a bull in a china shop, charging in wildly before he had properly thought out the repercussions of his actions. He could also bear a grudge with the best of them. 

But as the relief’s Federation rep. George was a steady, reliable type, known for his loyalty and integrity. He took pride in his work and his best quality was his commitment to colleagues. He tried hard to never let anybody down, by acting as a trouble shooter for the team - and served well in the role as he always had his colleague's best interests at heart. But, like so many others, he had been taken under the wing of Bob Cryer more than once. He needed a calm father figure to advise him when everything seemed to be going wrong for him and it seemed that his second name was Gullible. 

He had money troubles before the night of the party for his twenty-fifth birthday, but they got worse after it. He’d hired a room only to have Quinnan and Jim Carver wreck it by fighting over a girl. Garfield had to pay for the repairs, which meant he had to return the flash XR3 convertible car he’d just started buying on installments, against the advice of his bank manager. Lending the key of his section-house room to Loxton – who was spotted nipping up the stairs with a nurse, against the rules – was another black mark against his name. But his colleagues were on his side when Matthew Boyden let him down – nipping off to see one of his women friends and leaving him to be beaten up by the villain they were supposed to be trailing. Garfield was knocked down and concussed. There were bets on if and when Garfield might get his own back. They were safe bets. Boyden leaned about Garfield’s right hook – the hard way. 

Over the years, young women seemed to be immune to the Garfield charm. There was some chance he was getting something together with a WPC whom he invited for a pizza, then there was that journalist from the Sun Hill Chronicle. In the end, George’s love life proved to be the end for his stint at Sun Hill. A rather messy love triangle involving himself, Dave Quinnan and nurse Jenny Delaney ensured George was not at Sun Hill station for much longer. He left the force on a voyage of self-discovery, briefly returning a couple of months later to settle his differences with Dave at his wedding.

===Benjamin Gayle===
{{Infobox character
| name       = Benjamin Gayle
| first      = ''Cracking Under Pressure'' (27/09/2007)
| last       = (31/8/2010)
| occupation = Police Officer
| title      = Police Constable
| portrayer  = [[Micah Balfour]]
}}
Benjamin arrived in September 2007 and is played by [[Micah Balfour]]. On his first day he was cornered in a woodland by 3 gang members and fought them all off giving one of them a broken collar bone.  He has an uneven temper: he once broke a man's nose because he didn't like the way that the man treated his son and almost lost his job as a result.
{{-}}

===Arun Ghir===
{{Infobox character 
| name       = Arun Ghir
| first      = New Blood (12/06/2008)
| ic         = [[IC2]]
| last       = Decision Time (19/03/2009)
| occupation = [[Police Officer]]
| title      = [[Constable|PC]]
| portrayer  = [[Abhin Galeya]]
}}
He joined Sun Hill on 12 June 2008 as a Police Constable along with Leon Taylor &amp; Millie Brown. 

PC Arun Ghir had a troubled past, joining the police on the day his father was attacked by racist thugs after he'd politely asked them to get away from his car. Arun saw this as his chance to put things right, though it didn't always go to plan given his fiery temper and high enthusiasm.

Arun was committed and dedicated to the job, wanting to put right any wrongs for everybody, however small they may be – adamant that he helped to make the streets safer. He did have a tendency to think a bit too highly and took himself too seriously at times, frequently speaking before thinking through what the consequences could be, but still managed to come across as sincere, with a certain amount of naive charm.
As dedicated as he was, his maverick streak meant he can be unpredictable and not always straight down the line – it all depends what the end result was. Arun was suspended from duty by Smithy after attempting to help an illegal immigrant escape detection with her son. After some time away from the job, Arun decided that he was not cut out for the MET and resigned.

===Craig Gilmore===
{{Infobox character
| name       = Craig Gilmore
| first      = Tour Of Duty (10/04/2001)
| last       = Episode # 088 (06/02/2003)
| occupation = Police Officer
| title      = Sergeant
| portrayer  = [[Hywel Simons]]
}}
Gilmore is recruited to replace his predecessor, [[Bob Cryer (The Bill)|Bob Cryer]]. In many ways he is the exact opposite of his predecessor. Whereas Cryer is modest, experienced and respected, Gilmore has been fast-tracked to promotion, has been a sergeant for less than a year and is considered by his colleagues to be arrogant. He is the first openly gay sergeant in the show's history. He left [[Sun Hill (The Bill)|Sun Hill]] after receiving a severe beating and having a relationship with PC [[Luke Ashton]], a [[The closet|closeted]] [[homosexual]], who was married to PC [[Kerry Young]] at the time.
{{-}}

===Danny Glaze===
{{Infobox character
| name       = Danny Glaze
| first      = Makeover (11/05/99)
| last       = Episode 155(08/10/03)
| occupation = Police Officer
| title      = Detective Constable
| portrayer  = [[Karl Collins]]
}}
A local Londoner, Glaze is streetwise and has a good sense of humour. He comes to Sun Hill after meeting Liz Rawton in a training course and was persuaded to join her in CID.  His [[Afro]] hairstyle made his presence distinctive.

Glaze later gets caught up in the scandal surrounding Des Taviner, when he finds out that Des planted evidence in accused murderer Jeff Simpson's residence. He reluctantly covers for him because he knew Simpson was guilty but later his conscience begins getting the better of him. Simpson claims he was set up and former Sun Hill officer Sally Johnson investigates the case. Glaze eventually reveals the truth, but to avoid prosecution he keeps £20,000, which he came across during a robbery case and flees to South Africa and is never heard of again.
{{-}}

===Gina Gold===
{{Infobox character
| name       = Inspector Gina Gold
| first      = Episode # 021 27 June 2002
| last       = An Honour To Serve- Part 2 2 October 2008
| occupation = Police Officer
| title       = Inspector
| spouse     = None
| portrayer  = [[Roberta Taylor]]
}}
Gina Gold first appeared on ''The Bill'' on 27 June 2002, shortly after the events of the fire. Gina already knew Superintendent Okaro at the time because they were old flames in the 80's. When Okaro left due to the promotion to Borough Commander he and Gina still remained very good friends. Gina was known for her 'iron fist'- mainly due to the fact she loved boxing in her spare time, which led PC [[Emma Keane]] to make a bullying allegation against her. Consequently, she left on leave, but soon returned. Gina was one of the well known members of the Bill crew, having been on the programme for many years. Gina worked closely with Sergeant [[Dale Smith (The Bill)|Dale Smith]], who was one of her closest friends at the station and was one of the only ones who, early in her time on the drama, she told about having cancer. In the episode &quot;The Calling&quot; Smithy told Sgt Stone that he went for a drink with Gina which means she still keeps in touch with Smithy.Gina was shown in 098 that she was a secondary area car driver

===Arrival at Sun Hill===
Although it was never mentioned which station Gina had transferred from, it was stated that she had a reputation for being a bit of a dragon.She started on the 27th of June 2002 and on arrival at her new rather shabby looking office, (which gained a scoff from the Inspector as she walked in) she quickly stashed away her bottle of whiskey and her ashtray, turning her nose up at the 'No Smoking' sign on the wall.

She soon earned the respect of the relief but still didn't fear mincing her words. One of her first big storylines which gained a lot more of respect from the relief, occurred in December 2002. Whislt out one evening at linedancing, Gina ran into a fight between two boys; one of the lads was Tommy Renolds. When she took Tommy home she realised that she used to be friends with his mum Beverly at school and her older cousin Maralyn. It transpired that Maralyn had contributed to Gina's brother being convicted of murder. He committed suicide in Prison and Gina blamed Maralyn for his death. It ended in a dramatic show-down where Maralyn ended up being shot dead, not before having a dig at Gina's infertility. Her ex Adam Okaro (and Superintendent) heard the announcement and quizzed Gina about it after, leading to her admission that that was the reason she had left him 15 years earlier.

===Friendship with Smithy===
Sergeant Dale 'Smithy' Smith arrived back in early 2003. Instantly seeing potential in his hot headed ways she worked hard at helping him to keep his personal feelings separate from the job, and earning him respect from the team.

Their friendship was sealed shortly after his arrival when the two went for a drink in a local pub. They ended up having a drinking contest

 

On Gina's departure, she and Smithy shared an emotional moment when, after saying that she would be missed, he said, &quot;Goodnight, Ma'am. Gina replied tearfully, &quot;Goodnight, Sergeant&quot;, before looking tearfully around her office.
{{-}}

===Beth Green===
{{Infobox character
| name        =Beth Green
| series      =[[The Bill]]
| first       =Baby Trade 16 May 2007
| last        =Leap Of Faith- Part 2 18 March 2009
| portrayer   =[[Louisa Lytton]] 
| gender      =[[Female]] 
| occupation  =[[Police Officer]]
| title       =[[Police Constable]] 
| nationality =English 
}}
On Beth's first day on the beat, she is paired with PC [[Emma Keane]]. As they investigate a break-in at a house, Beth's nerves get the better of her. As a suspect is being restrained with CS spray, she sprays not only the suspect in the eyes but also Emma. Beth reveals that on a previous occasion she had accidentally sprayed herself by spraying a CS can backwards. She is more successful later on in using her CS spray, this time to stop a fleeing suspect.

Although Beth gets on well with some of her colleagues, particularly PC [[Dan Casper]], who is impressed by her attention to detail and her memory, there are still a few who have doubts about their latest recruit. Emma draws attention to her girlish appearance and nicknames her 'Little Miss Daisy Chain'. PC [[Will Fletcher]] is irritated that Beth is attracted to him.

In one episode, she is hit on the head with a bottle by an escaped convict and knocked out. She is also hit with a rake, knocking her unconscious, and left tied up in a hospital cupboard by the escaped Larry Franks. In another episode (Crash Test) she was almost sprayed in the face with Acid.

In episode 530 (Crash Test), Beth goes undercover to aid [[Terry Perkins]]'s investigation of a notorious loan shark. Beth's cover is Terry's drug addicted daughter seeking money to pay back her dealer.

On Thursday March 12, 2009 in the episode 'Leap of Faith', Beth reveals to PC Tony Stamp that she has applied for a job in witness protection. Before she can say anything else the two officers spot a woman called Molly Anderson standing on the edge of a bridge. As Beth tries to talk her down, Mel and Nate arrive. When Molly jumps into the water, Nate dives in after her. After a stressful day Beth heads back to the station and finds a letter from [[witness protection]]. She is accepted for Witness Protection and leaves at the end of the second part of the episode.  
{{-}}

===Alistair Greig===
{{Infobox character
| name       = Alistair Greig
| first      = Getting It Right (03/01/1989)
| last       = Cooking (28/07/1998)
| occupation = Police Officer
| title      = Detective Sergeant
| portrayer  = [[Andrew Mackintosh]]
}}
DS Alistair Greig joined Sun Hill CID after a stint in the Vice Squad.  He was a member of the Metropolitan Police band, playing the clarinet and was initially of a breezy disposition.  A few months of working for [[Frank Burnside|Burnside]] knocked this early chirpiness out of him and though he became outwardly stoical, Alistair retained a sharp, dry sense of humour.

An intellectual and prone to being a little aloof, Greig was generally recognised and respected as a hardworking and dedicated detective, but remained peripheral to the CID “family”.  There was a sense that he preferred to keep even those colleagues with who he was on good terms, at arm's length.  He certainly had little time for the frivolous, the self-serving and the outright rule breakers - that went for both fellow officers and criminals.

Greig was put in charge of implementing the Met's anti-burglary initiative, Bumblebee, at Sun Hill, leading a team which included [[Dave Quinnan]] and [[Suzi Croft]].  Unlike most of CID, Greig offered Suzi thoughtful guidance, particularly through the early part of her career and there were occasional hints that Alistair was quite protective of his tutee.

Despite appearances, Greig was ambitious and it rankled that he was passed over for DI on more than one occasion.  He considered a move away from Sun Hill after DCI Meadows chose [[Chris Deakin|Deakin]] to replace [[Sally Johnson]].  However, Meadows dissuaded him from doing so, giving his assurance that Greig was a valued officer and was next in line.

In hindsight, perhaps Greig should have followed his initial instincts.  Like [[Jim Carver]], he found himself a victim of the controversial tenure policy in place at the time.  He appealed but was unsuccessful.  A plea by Meadows to Brownlow also failed.  Rather than take what he saw as a pointless (and humiliating) option to go back into uniform, Greig transferred to another station.{{-}}

==H==
===Vicky Hagen===
{{Infobox character
| name       = Vicky Hagen
| first      = Big Brother (07/05/1998)
| last       = Sacrifice (26/10/2001)
| occupation = Police Officer
| title      = Police Constable
| portrayer  = [[Samantha Robson]]
}}
Vicky serves at Sun Hill three years. At one point she dates Matthew Boyden and ends up getting involved in the problems he has with his daughter. She leaves after a series of unfortunate incidents culminating in a one-night stand that she picks up, who commits suicide in Polly Page's bath (she was sharing with Page after Boyden kicked her out). She was known as a bit of an 'old woofer'. Vicky transfers out of the Met to another force.
{{-}}

===Harry Haines===
{{Infobox character
| name       = Harry Haines
| first      = Bad Reaction (10/09/1993)
| last       = Nothing Ventured (31/12/1993)
| occupation = Police Officer
| title      = Detective Inspector
| portrayer  = [[Gary Whelan]]
}}
He serves at Sun Hill for a total of three months. Harry, who used to be part of the Drug Squad is forcibly transferred to Sun Hill CID. However, it only takes him three months to get his transfer back to the Drug Squad. He later returns to Sun Hill briefly to help DCI Jack Meadows with an ongoing drugs operation.
{{-}}

===Lewis Hardy===
{{Infobox character
| name        =Lewis Hardy
| series      =[[The Bill]]
| first       = Episode # 380 (11/01/06)      
| last        = Death Or Glory (19/07/07) 
| portrayer   =[[Aml Ameen]] 
| gender      =Male 
| occupation  =Police Officer
| title       =Police Constable 
| relatives    = Dominic (cousin)
| religion    = none
| nationality = english
}}
Lewis started at [[Sun Hill (The Bill)|Sun Hill]] with fellow PC [[Emma Keane]], who had a privileged upbringing. Lewis was a working class black who had spent most of his teenage life on the streets with a small gang in Hackney. Lewis was arrested numerous times, finally, for a drug offence of which he was innocent. He was taken under the wing of one of the officers who supported and inspired him to join the Metropolitan Police Force.

Lewis was smart with sharp wit who was encouraged by his teachers to go to University. After realising the amount of debt he would get into, he decided to apply to [[Hendon Police College|Hendon]] with the support of the officer from his local station. Lewis may not have always seen eye to eye with some of the older members of the relief, but his personality always shone through. It was difficult to hold a grudge against him. He left [[Sun Hill (The Bill)|Sun Hill]] after a harrowing but successful undercover operation infiltrating the Skens gang of which his cousin was a member. Whilst in hospital after being shot he was offered a transfer to [[Operation Trident (Metropolitan Police)|Operation Trident]] which he quickly snapped up.
{{-}}

===Sam Harker===
{{Infobox character
| name       = Sam Harker
| first      = Things That Go Bump in the Night (30/12/1997)
| last       = Episode 010 (18/04/2002)
| occupation = Police Officer
| title      = Police Constable
| portrayer  = [[Matthew Crompton]]
}}
Sam served at [[Sun Hill (The Bill)|Sun Hill]] five years.PC Sam Harker is a no-nonsense copper was 26, single, born in St Helens, Liverpool. He transferred to Sun Hill from Heathrow police because he wanted to broaden his experience with a spell at an East End [[police station|nick]]. Harker relished his job. He always knew what he would do with his life, coming from a long line of policemen - his father was a [[police man|copper]] in [[Liverpool]], as was his elder brother. As far as he was concerned, it beat working for a living! He was easy going, with a naturally friendly manner and a ready smile and was not easily fazed. Members of the public found him thoughtful and straightforward in his dealings, and locally he became a popular and respected uniform beat bobby. He also had the sense to leave the troubles of policing at work with his uniform at the end of the shift, and found it easy to relax with his mates and a beer.

Tragically, Sam died in hospital after being critically injured in an explosion at Sun Hill after race riots got out of hand

{{-}}

===Susan Harling===
{{Infobox character
| name       = Susan Harling
| first     =In the Cold (26/10/1989) (Referred to as &quot;Harding&quot;)
| last       = Under the Doctor (04/08/1995)
| occupation = Doctor and [[Force Medical Examiner|Forensic Medical Examiner]] (FME)
| title      = Doctor
| portrayer  = [[Gillian McCutcheon]]
}}
Dr Susan Harling was a mature doctor with a straightforward manner. She served as an [[Force Medical Examiner|FME]] for Sun Hill for some time, and so was used to the hurly-burly of day-to-day life in a police station.
{{-}}

===Honey Harman===
{{Infobox character
| colour     = 
| name       = Honey Louise Harman
| first      = Episode 098
| last       = Episode 478 
| occupation = Police Officer
| title      = Police Constable 
| spouse     = Scott Burnett
| portrayer  = [[Kim Tiddy]]

}}
PC Honey Harman was born and raised in [[Ilford]], [[Essex]]. She always excelled in sport at school but did rather poorly in academic studies. As a young adult, she worked as a [[fitness instructor]] and [[personal trainer]]. She eventually became bored of working in [[gyms]] and decided that she wanted to help people and also to work in a physically demanding job, so she joined the [[police]]. 

Honey was kind-hearted and always wanted to see the best in people; she also believed strongly in first impressions. Although she may not have been the most academically gifted officer the station has seen, her instinct and physical ability never let her down. A [[vegetarian]] who declared her body to be a temple, Honey was physically fearless and never doubted her own abilities. She was willing to put herself in dangerous situations because she knew that she was capable of, at least physically, dealing with anything. Her [[judo]] skills came in more than handy when she got herself into sticky situations whilst chasing suspects. Paperwork was another story - she hated it with a passion and would do anything to avoid the mounting pile on her desk! 

Having no awareness of her own attractiveness, Honey was perhaps initially unintentionally inappropriate with some of the men on the relief. Her love life was never plain sailing; Honey split from her [[Association football|footballer]] [[fiancé]] Fletch after she discovered he was cheating on her.

On 28 April 2005, she married Scott William Burnett. who Unknown to her, he had murdered his wife Karen whose case was under investigation. Scott takes Honey to an isolated seaside cottage in Kent. In conversation, it slips out that he killed his wife. He takes the battery out from his phone so the police can't track him down, but Honey secretly puts it back in. Discovering this, he realised that she betrayed him and the police would be there soon. He stormed out and disappeared beneath the waves. Honey rushed after him and managed to resuscitate him but he was facing a life in jail without the woman he loved, he wished she had not bothered.

Following her kidnapping by a [[Colombian people|Colombian]] drugs gang, Honey attempted to arrest drugs dealer Kristen Shaw, 'for kidnapping a police officer and accessory to murder'. In the ensuing struggle, a gun was accidentally let off, fatally wounding Honey. After Honey died, a shocked Kristen said to her bent policeman boyfriend, [[Zain Nadir]], ''&quot;I...I didn't mean to - she's dead, and it's all my fault, but she was trying to take you away from me...&quot;''
{{-}}

===Donna Harris===
{{Infobox character
| name       = Donna Harris
| first      = Discretion (19/11/1991)
| last       = Confession (27/02/1996)
| occupation = Police Officer
| title      = Police Constable
| portrayer  = [[Louise Harrison]]
}}
Donna served at [[Sun Hill (The Bill)|Sun Hill]] for five years. She came shortly after Sgt [[Matt Boyden]] arrived at the station. Her role at Sun Hill as collator was effectively made redundant by the introduction of a new computer system used by the police force and she resigned.
{{-}}

===Lorna Hart===
{{Infobox character
| name       = Lorna Hart
| first      = Inner Demons
| last       = Moving Target: Part 3
| occupation = Police Civiilan Staff
| title      = Crime Scene Examnier 
| portrayer  = [[Siobhan Redmond]]
}}
Lorna joined Sunhill as a crime scene examiner. She gained a close relationship to [[DS Stuart Turner]] and worked on the case of murdered model Cindy Statham. After her photographer, [[Rachel Inns]] kidnapped and held [[DC Jo Masters]] for discovering she was the murderer, she threatened to shoot her, CO19 stormed the factory and Jo talked her out of it. She was then replaced by CSE Eddie Olosunje.
{{-}}

===Malcolm Haynes===
{{Infobox character
| name       = Malcolm Haynes
| first      = Light Duties (19/07/1988)
| last       = Pressure (22/08/1989)
| occupation = Police Officer
| title      = Police Constable
| portrayer  = [[Eamonn Walker]]
}}
When ''The Bill'' was changed to a twice weekly half hour programme in 1988, the regular cast was expanded to include some new characters. Amongst the newcomers were PC Malcom Haynes, who makes his debut in the first half hour episode, &quot;Light Duties&quot;. It is clear from dialogue in the episode, that Haynes has only just arrived at [[Sun Hill (The Bill)|Sun Hill]]. Without much tact, old fashioned sergeant, [[Alec Peters]], asks Haynes if he is settling in well and Haynes surmises that he only asked this because he is black. In fact, Haynes quickly establishes a good working relationship with his fellow officers and in particular the maverick PC [[Pete Ramsey]]. Haynes has been a Police Officer for some years including around the time of the Brixton riots. When Pete Ramsey is shot during a bank raid, Haynes changes, becoming argumentative with both members of the public and PC Edwards, who never liked Ramsey. Thirteen months after his arrival, Haynes suddenly disappears from Sun Hill. It is presumed he has decided to transfer to another station as he could no longer work at the station. Haynes appears in the title sequence during his year in the programme, suggesting that he is designated as one of the main characters.
{{-}}

===Ben Hayward===
{{Infobox character
| name       = Ben Hayward
| first      = First Impressions Part I (19/09/2000)
| last       = Episode 008 (16/04/2002)
| occupation = Police Officer
| title      = Police Constable
| portrayer  = [[Ben Peyton]]
}}
Ben serves at [[Sun Hill (The Bill)|Sun Hill]] for two years. He dies in [[the Sun Hill Fire]] caused by the race riots.
{{-}}

===John Heaton===
{{Infobox character
| name       = Superintendent John Heaton
| first      = Episode 421 (June 22nd 2006)
| last       = 23rd July 2009
| occupation = Superintendent, Crime Scene Examiner
| Spouses    = Rhiannon Heaton
| Children   = Charlie &lt;br&gt; (adoptive daughter, with Rhiannon)
| portrayer  = [[Daniel Flynn (actor)|Daniel Flynn]]
}}
Heaton became Superintendent at Sun Hill in June 2006, having previously been a Detective Chief Inspector.  He is very much a 'hands-on' officer, leading several raids. 

He is married to Rhiannon Heaton; they have an adopted child, Charlie. 

In [[2006]] he had an affair with DAC Georgia Hobbs, but ended the relationship when he found out that DAC Hobbs had pushed to get Sun Hill closed as she had promised the land to a developer.  After taping a conversation where she admitted her role to Heaton he turned both her and the evidence over to the [[Directorate of Professional Standards]]. Heaton also had an affair with Mickey Webb's girlfriend Mia Perry 

In [[2007]] John's old enemy and former colleague in the police, Ray Moore, a gangster and club owner, arrives in Sun Hill from Manchester. Knowing how ruthless Moore can be, Heaton sends Rhiannon and Charlie to Bristol for safety.

In [[2009]] John Heaton ([[Daniel Flynn (actor)|Daniel Flynn]]) reaches the toughest point of his career when he discovers that a man he sent down for murder 20 years ago was innocent, and that he let a serial killer go undetected. While Sun Hill’s finest struggle to keep faith in the boss that they thought was invincible, John must rebuild his confidence – and his reputation. He is determined to right the wrongs, win back the respect of his colleagues and ensure that justice is finally served.

John Heaton was DC [[Grace Dasari]]'s DCI at her previous job, and knew PC [[Diane Noble]] previously, through her ex-husband.

In an episode aired on Wednesday July 15, Heaton announced that he is leaving Sun Hill to join a people trafficking unit. Heaton left, and took [[Rachel Weston (The Bill)|Inspector Weston]], [[Stuart Turner (The Bill)|DS Turner]] and [[Kezia Walker|DC Walker]] with him to his new station. As a result [[Jack Meadows (The Bill)|DCI Meadows]] was promoted to Superintendent, [[Dale Smith (The Bill)|Sergeant Smith]] was promoted to Inspector, [[Stevie Moss|DC Moss]] is expected to be promoted to [[Sergeant|DS]], and [[Will Fletcher|T/DC Fletcher]] is expected to become a fully fledged [[Constable|DC]].

===Yvonne Hemmingway===
{{Infobox character
| name       = PC Yvonne Hemmingway
| first      = Episode 156 (09/10/2003)
| last       = Episode 459 (15/11/2006)
| occupation = Police Officer
| title      = Police Constable 
| portrayer  = [[Michele Austin]]
}}
Yvonne serves at [[Sun Hill (The Bill)|Sun Hill]] for three years. Yvonne is a skilled area car driver and serves as Acting Sergeant twice; once while [[June Ackland]] is on her honeymoon and the other time when [[Dale Smith (The Bill)|Sergeant Dale Smith]] is wrongly imprisoned for murder. Yvonne's career almost comes to an end when she faces criminal charges due to the death of a young man she was trying to arrest after she struck him with her [[ASP]]. An inquiry is held, and she is acquitted of all charges when it is ruled she acted in self-defence.

Yvonne later leaves Sun Hill to become a Sergeant at another station working with young offenders.&lt;ref name=&quot;billbios&quot;&gt;[http://thebillbios.co.uk/hemmingway.htm PC Yvonne Hemmingway], The Bill Biographies&lt;/ref&gt;
{{-}}

===Matt Hinckley===
{{Infobox character
| name         = Senior Crown Prosecutor (SCP) Matt Hinckley
| first        = Episode #410 (27/4/06)
| last         = ''Day of Reckoning'' (03/5/07)
| occupation   = Solicitor
| Title        = Senior Crown Prosecutor
| spouse       = [[Emma Keane]]
| portrayer    = [[Mark Dexter]]
}}
After dating Emma Keane for a while, Matt marries her. The night before the wedding she opens up to Matt and tells him about the brief affair she had with Will Fletcher.

Matt gets his friends to beat up Will but the next day Will gives Matt a well-deserved punch and they both drop the charges made against each other. Matt later attempts to murder Emma after she threatens to leave him after she discovers that his ex-girlfriend is alive, after he told her she was dead. Emma turns to alcohol and begins drinking. After a short fight, she hits him over the head with the bottle. Emma is arrested but later she is proved innocent and Matt is arrested for the attempted murder of his wife.
{{-}}

===Reg Hollis===
{{Infobox character
| name         = Reginald Percival Hollis
| first      = 16 October 1984
| last       = 12 March 2008 
| occupation = [[Police Officer]]
| title      = [[Police Constable]]
| portrayer  = [[Jeff Stewart (actor)|Jeff Stewart]]
}}
[[Taffy Edwards]] was originally going to have the Reg Hollis persona but the producers of ''The Bill'' changed their minds at the last minute and decided to give the whiney voice, silly jokes and odd ways to Reg in the second series.{{Citation needed|date=June 2007}} Reg is officially introduced in &quot;[[Funny Ol' Business - Cops and Robbers]]&quot;, and is gradually perceived in the series as a loner; the unpopular oddball of the [[Watch system|relief]], who spends most of his time carrying out light duties such as serving as the station's collator and Federation representative. Reg however tires of being behind a desk and requests to be assigned on foot patrols. He proves to be a capable officer, on one of his early outings from the station he charges into a hostage situation and disarms a potentially dangerous gunman.&lt;ref name=&quot;billbios&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://thebillbios.co.uk/hollis.htm|title=PC Reg Hollis|publisher=The Bill Biographies|accessdate=2007-08-18}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Reg is a loner for most of his time at Sun Hill; however, an unlikely friendship-buddy pairing with [[Des Taviner]] changes him, and gives him more social confidence.&lt;ref name=&quot;billbios&quot;/&gt; Upon Des's arrival at Sun Hill, Des and Reg are paired up in the area car, which sees the beginning of a friendship that provides some of character's most memorable moments. It is truly a turning point when Reg, who was always so uptight, accompanies Des when he skips work to take a trip in the area car across the UK, attempting to convince Reg to propose to his Asian girlfriend. Des is well known for referring to Reg as &quot;Reggie Babe&quot; in his [[Scouse accent]]; Des being the only person to call him this.

After it is discovered that Des is responsible for [[The Sun Hill Fire (2002)]], which killed many of the officers, he goes on the run for a short while, and at one point he contacts Reg to apologise for everything. Reg responds telling him that he is a coward, and it should be the families of those he killed he should have been apologising to. Minutes later, armed police have Des surrounded, and Reg arrests him. Later on that afternoon, Des is beaten to death in his cell by a manic depressive, ending his relationship with Reg on bad terms.

In a spin-off episode aired on ITV2 shortly after Des's death, Reg receives a video tape that Des made immediately prior to going on the run. It's Des's last attempt to apologise to Reg for dragging him into the mess, and the episode includes clips from their partnership over the years.  The episode ends with Des reflecting on the irony of going on the run funded by fifty pound notes, and Reg, as he finishes his drink, forgiving Des's memory.

Reg began a relationship with [[Marilyn Chambers (The Bill)|Marilyn Chambers]], Sun Hill's Front Desk Officer at the time. After dating for a few months, Reg plans to propose to her at the railway station where he had taken her on their first date, where Reg discovered she was actually interested in his hobby of trainspotting. While Reg is waiting at the railway station for Marilyn to arrive she is killed in [[The Sun Hill Fire (2005)]].&lt;ref name=&quot;billbios&quot;/&gt; Reg is deeply upset by her death, and he finds her replacement very hard to swallow while he is grieving.

Reg's position has recently been threatened by Superintendent [[John Heaton (The Bill)|John Heaton]]. [[Tony Stamp]] urges him to change his approach to policing. Reg, however, refuses to compromise on his principles and says, &quot;if Superintendent Heaton's idea of running an efficient nick is to get rid of anyone over 30, I'm not sure I want to work for him&quot;. Heaton has recently started to realise how much respect and loyalty Reg receives from his colleagues. Following [[June Ackland]]'s departure, Reg considers tendering his resignation; however Tony is able to convince him not to.

Reg resigned from the force following [[Emma Keane]]'s death in the terrorist bombs in Sun Hill in May 2008.{{-}}

===Kerry Holmes===
{{Infobox character
| name       = Kerry Holmes
| first      = &quot;The Cross&quot; (Tue 20/10/98)
| last       = &quot;All Fall Down Part 2&quot; (Tue 31/10/00)
| occupation = Police Officer
| title      = Detective  Constable
| portrayer  = [[Joy Brook]]
}}
Kerry Holmes was caught up in the [[Don Beech Scandal]] and was so disgusted by the inference she was involved in his corrupt activities that she requested an immediate transfer away from Sun Hill.
{{-}}

===Phil Hunter===
{{Infobox character
| name       = Philip &quot;Phil&quot; Hunter
| first      = Episode 029 
(25 July 2002)
| last       = &quot;Collateral Damage&quot; 
(17 October 2007)
| occupation = [[Police Officer]]
| title      = [[Detective Sergeant]]
| family     = Lynn Hunter &lt;br&gt; (mother) &lt;br&gt; Steve Hunter &lt;br&gt; (brother)
| spouse     = Cindy Hunter 
| children   = Madison &lt;br&gt; (daughter, with Christine) &lt;br&gt; Alfie &lt;br&gt; (son, with Kate)
| portrayer  = [[Scott Maslen]]
}}
Scott Maslen's character was involved in many storylines from travelling to [[Romania]] with fellow DS [[Samantha Nixon|Sam Nixon]], to his relationship with DS [[Debbie McAllister]] while married to his wife, Cindy. He has two children; Madison ''(w/ Christine Weaver)'' and Alfie ''(w/ Kate Maltby)'', each by a different mother. His wife, Cindy, found out about both of Phil's children afterwards but she still continued IVF treatment with Phil so they could have a baby. They were not successful.

Sam and Phil embarked on a secret relationship when they returned from Romania, having slept together in a backstreet B&amp;B after getting shot at in a drive-by shooting. Sam broke off the relationship not much later, and they went back to being just friends.

Phil developed a rivalry with DS [[Stuart Turner (The Bill)|Stuart Turner]], both for results at work and for [[Samantha Nixon|Sam Nixon]]'s affections. He also clashed with his younger brother, PC Steve Hunter, who was posted at Sun Hill.
Scott Maslen, who portrayed Phil, left The Bill in Autumn 2007 to play [[Jack Branning]] in BBC1 soap [[EastEnders]].
{{-}}

===Steve Hunter===
{{Infobox character
| name       = Steve Hunter
| first      = Episode 224
| last       = Episode 405
| rank       = Police Constable
| family     = Lynn Hunter &lt;br&gt; (mother) &lt;br&gt; [[Phil Hunter]] &lt;br&gt; (brother) &lt;br&gt; Madison &lt;br&gt; (niece) &lt;br&gt; Alfie Luke Maltby &lt;br&gt; (nephew)
| portrayer  = [[James Lloyd]]
}}
Steve Hunter arrived at Sun Hill Police Station as a probationer, much to the disdain of his brother DS [[Phil Hunter]], who was mortified at the thought of his eager younger sibling being around the place all of the time. In fact, any chance he got, Phil tried to get Steve transferred out of the station.

Steve was naïve and likeable, yet slightly awkward and a dreamer. He clearly idolised his brother, but when he realised that he couldn't meet Phil's high expectations of him, he decided to transfer to Derby.
{{-}}

==I==
===Rachel Inns===
{{Infobox character
| name       = Rachel Inns
| first      = ''A Model Murder Part 1'' (27/06/07)
| last       = ''Caught by the Killer'' (2/08/07)
| occupation = Crime Scene Photographer
| portrayer  = [[Amanda Abbington]]
}}
Rachel is a photographer at [[Sun Hill (The Bill)|Sun Hill]] who is responsible for photographing crime scenes and evidence.

Rachel first appears working on the murder of supermodel Cindy Statham, who she went to school with. It is later discovered by DC [[Jo Masters]] that Rachel killed Cindy because she was the one who encouraged Cindy to become a model but was never acknowledged for it. Before Jo can arrest her she kidnaps her and attempts to kill her, but is arrested by [[CO19]] before she can succeed.
{{-}}

==J==
===Mike Jarvis===
{{Infobox character
| name       = Mike Jarvis
| last       = Volcano (08/05/1998)
| occupation = Police Officer
| title      = Police Constable
| portrayer  = [[Stephen Beckett]]
}}
Mike serves at Sun Hill for five years and then, after being on a temporary detachment to the Diplomatic Protection Group he transfers to the department permanently.
{{-}}

===Amber Johannsen===
{{Infobox character
| name       = Amber Johannsen
| first      = Episode 264 (01/12/2004)
| last       = Episode 377 (29/12/2005)
| occupation = Police Officer
| title      = Police Constable
| portrayer  = [[Myfanwy Waring]]
}}
Tempestuous PC Amber Johannsen was feisty, gutsy and focused. 
She was born into a lower class family but had her sights on the high life; she was looking for a provider. In the mean time, being a police officer offered a stable income, good holidays and - best of all - an opportunity to take advantage of her role in society - oh; and there was a great uniform too. She decided to join the police after briefly dating a copper. 

Amber's roots were very modest; her father was a taxi driver and her mum a beauty therapist. Beneath the happy smile, Amber was manipulative and self-obsessed. She liked to get what she wanted and didn't care who she hurt in the process. In many ways, the designer labels she wore showed her determination to get a better life for herself - and make it a far distance from her working-class background. Until she achieved her goal in society, Amber amused herself by toying with the likes of Steve Hunter. The two things that excited her most were shopping and sex and she was practically addicted to both. She was beautiful and knew it and took every opportunity to flirt and break hearts - whether it was men or women! 

Amber wanted the finer things in life and everyone at the station knew that as soon as she found a man to fund it, she'd ditch her uniform quicker than she could manage to read a criminal their rights. This attitude certainly didn't endear her to her colleagues, some of whom made no secret of their dislike for her. Inspector Gold eventually tired of her questionable commitment to the job and prompted her resignation from the Force. 

{{-}}

===Sally Johnson===
{{Infobox character
| name       = Sally Johnson
| first      = Second Sight (06/01/1994)
| last       = Done Is Done (27/01/1995)
| occupation = Police Officer (1994-1995)
&lt;br /&gt; Private Investigator (current)
| title      = Detective Inspector (1994-1995)
| portrayer  = [[Jaye Griffiths]]
}}
Bright-eyed DI Sally ‘Magic’ Johnson believed she was God’s gift to policing, and she may have turned out to be just that if her interpretation of means-to-an-end had tallied with the Met’s. You could never have accused her of lacking in self-belief. Having risen through the ranks at an alarming pace to become a DS at Stafford Row, she was ready to tackle whatever another promotion and Sun Hill could throw at her by way of racist, sexist remarks. If she couldn’t deal with it, she wouldn’t have got where she was. Johnson had always been aware that her colour and education were an advantage within the force, and that they had led to her promotion in the climate of positive discrimination rather than on her real ability to do the job. This didn't mean that she was incompetent, but like a lot of the fast track promotions, she lacked a lot of basic ground experience. She put in the hours and got her hands dirty, but always found it difficult to accept that she was the Guvn'or now, and not one of the lads. And if there was an inner core of loneliness beneath the ambitious exterior, she took care to keep it hidden. 

Johnson grew up in London, and it was soon clear to her West Indian family that she had brains. They were somewhat surprised when after university she chose to use them in the police force, but she rose through the ranks very quickly and loved going to work, loved being in control of others and, above all, loved catching thieves. Johnson charged along the corridors with her subordinates trying to keep up. Her easy manner won her friends and took the starch out of some of the senior officers. But on occasions her know-it-all air could be irritating. The word ‘delegate’ was not in her vocabulary – she enjoyed the work on the streets and in the interview room too much for that. 

She may not have shown great wisdom in the detectives she had chosen to favour – making Pearce her pet at the start was perhaps a mistake, and she'd been clumsy in her treatment of Ackland, whose years of experience she undervalued. Johnson's unshakeable faith in her own abilities irritated a number of more experienced officers at the station and her confidence took a long overdue knock when she was subjected to a private prosecution for manslaughter following the raid of a crack dealer's house. Up till then she had been completely comfortable with her power. From then on she had moments of doubt. As her methods came under increasing scrutiny, it was clear that her days at Sun Hill were numbered - and when she was offered a desk job attachment monitoring overtime, she realised she had no choice but to take it. 

Johnson eventually left the Met. to become a private investigator. She returned to Sun Hill in 2003 to investigate claims of a fit up in the Simpson murder case. 

{{-}}

==K==
===Brandon Kane===
{{Infobox character
| name       = Brandon Kane
| first      = Episode 022 (02/07/02)  
| last       = Episode 184 (15/01/04)
| occupation = Police Officer
| title      = Detective Constable
| spouse     = Tanya Kane &lt;br&gt; (died)
| children   = Zoe Kane &lt;br&gt; (daughter, with Tanya) &lt;br&gt; Jordan Kane &lt;br&gt; (son, with Tanya)
| portrayer  = [[Pal Aron]]
}}

Divorced and subsequently widowed, 30-year-old Brandon Kane came from a small Asian Leicester family. He was not a practising Hindu and although his parents were, they were fairly liberal about his decision to leave his faith at home. Only his vegetarianism gave away any sign of a religious background. Brandon grew up in a happy atmosphere with his older sister Mira whom he adored, eventually following in her footsteps by training to be an accountant where he met his ex-wife, Tanya, with whom he had 2 children. When their marriage began to crumble, he took time to consider his options in life. After the divorce he decided to give up his job to go into the police service. It was not exactly a 'calling' for Brandon - it just seemed a natural step to take. Somewhat to his surprise he was good at the profession, and began to enjoy the lifestyle it brought him. 

Kane spent three years as a PC at another station, and had been noticed early on by the CID officers where he was based as a bright, meticulous officer, with the potential to be a very good detective. This coupled with a twinkle in the eye and a sense of humour as dry as the Sahara desert, made him a very popular. Brandon hated to be idle - he always wanted to be up and off doing something; and when he was forced to remain in one place he seemed restless. When he made mistakes in the station and out on a case they tended to stem from his impulsive nature that occasionally made him speak before thinking and act before determining the consequences. After a spell in Sun Hill's Community Safety Unit as a TDC, Brandon transferred to CID as a full-fledged DC following his completion of the trainee investigator course. 

Brandon was a very friendly man, however there were those who he did not get on with, particularly [[DS Debbie McAllister]], whose guts he absolutely hated. This stemmed from when Tanya died, and Debbie pounced on Brandon as prime suspect in her tragic fall. Brandon almost came close to hitting Debbie and argued with her violently, telling her that &quot;we both know you're hanging on in CID by your fingertips&quot; and accused her of trying to score brownie points with [[DCI Jack Meadows]]. He told her she was disgusting and that she made him sick. However, Debbie fought back, saying as Tanya's ex-husband he had no rights and she had every right to gain access to Tanya. However, she knew she'd lost the battle.

Brandon's final days at Sun Hill were spent in turmoil. After being taken hostage by PC Cathy Bradford he realised the people he wanted to protect most were his children. True to his genuine good nature, Brandon left the force to be with them.

{{-}}

===Leela Kapoor===
{{Infobox character
| name       = Leela Kapoor
| first      = Episode 268 (15/12/2004)
| last       = ''Dead and Buried'' (26/09/2007)
| occupation = Police Officer
| title      = Police Constable (PC)
| portrayer  = [[Seema Bowri]]
}}
PC Leela Kapoor had been in the Metropolitan Police for seven years before coming to Sun Hill. She may have been spiky and defensive, but she was also warm with a wicked sense of humour. She served her probation at Barton Street, and prior to joining Sun Hill, saw two of her colleagues assaulting a witness. Leela being Leela, at the forefront of justice and wanting to do the right thing, reported her peers. Life subsequently became rather difficult for her as she was seen as a grass, so she opted for a transfer to another nick. 

Leela was second generation British Hindu; at home she spoke Hindi but also had Punjabi and Urdu under her belt. Although Leela's home life was happy, she was exposed to the bigotry of society at an early age. Whilst she was fairly protected from racism by her family and circle of friends, her personal circumstances meant she experienced prejudice of a different kind, when her uncle, a high profile businessman, was accused of embezzlement. Leela's family had to fight a long, public, legal battle to clear her uncle's and the family's name. The Police's handling of the case, and some officer's ignorance when dealing with her family, all contributed to Leela's decision to become a police officer. 

Leela was not for wearing her ethnicity on her forehead - she just got on with it and celebrated the fact that she was different. One thing she couldn't stand, however, was being used as a token ethnic officer in the PC initiatives being pedalled by management. Leela was never one to take the easy option, out to prove she could do whatever she put her mind to. She was uncompromising and had a strong moral code, but could at times be quite guarded. If you were fortunate enough or cared enough to get to know the real Leela, you found a warm, caring, and sensitive woman. However, Leela was a tough nut to crack and she had a tendency to withdraw into herself if she felt vulnerable. For this, people perceived her to be difficult and cold, unless they were prepared to dig a little deeper. 

Leela left Sun Hill after receiving an offer to transfer to the Foreign Office. Little did she know that the position had been orchestrated by Sgt. Stone, who had tired of Leela playing everything by the book in her position as station's Fed Rep, and wanted shot of her. In the next episode (Media Frenzy [# 542] (27/09/07) she was replaced by PC Benjamin Gayle                                

{{-}}

===Debbie Keane===
{{Infobox character
| name        = Debbie Keane
| first       = New Moves (07/03/1995) 
| last        = Taking Sides (22/09/1998) 
| portrayer   = [[Andrea Mason (actress)|Andrea Mason]] 
| nickname    =Debs 
| gender      =Female 
| occupation  =Police Officer
| title       =Police Constable 
}}
Debbie Keane was played by [[Andrea Mason (actress)|Andrea Mason]] from 1995 to 1998. She joined Sun Hill at the same time as fellow Hendon classmate, [[Nick Slater]]. She was generally regarded as the more promising of the two recruits, impressing her superiors with her mature and friendly manner.  Her background as an [[Outward Bound]] instructor allowed her to cope easily with the physical demands of on-the-beat police work.&lt;ref&gt;Tibballs, G., (2003), pp. 143-144&lt;/ref&gt;
{{-}}

===Emma Keane===
{{Infobox character
| name       = Police Constable Emma Keane
| first      = Episode # 380     (January 11th  2006)
| last       = Frontline: Shockwave (May 1st 2008)
| occupation = Police Officer
| title      = Police Constable 
| spouse     = [[Matt Hinckley]] (divorced)
| portrayer  = [[Melanie Gutteridge]]
}} 
Emma graduated from University. From a middle-class background, she is the daughter of DCI Frank Keane from the Department of Professional Standards, but is determined to prove that she earned her position in the police force on merit rather than nepotism. Emma came across as smart and fun-loving. After graduating from University, Emma trained at Hendon for five weeks before being posted to Sun Hill, and completed her training there, recently graduating from her probationary period.

After being involved in an incident where a fellow policeman was killed, Emma was convinced that Inspector Gina Gold was bullying her. She made a formal complaint but it was not until they worked together on a rape case that she realised Gina was not really bullying her and tried to withdraw the complaint. Unfortunately, she goes to see the superintendent and he tells her his hands are tied on the matter but the complaint was later withdrawn.

While dating CPS solicitor [[Matt Hinckley]], Emma had a one-night stand with [[Will Fletcher]], Emma later agreed to marry Matt out of guilt for cheating on him. However, the night before her wedding, she opened up to Matt and told him about the brief affair. Matt got his friends to beat up Will but during the course of the next day Will punched Matt and they agree not to press charges against each other. Emma and Matt get married and both go back at work after their honeymoon. Shortly after the wedding, Matt reveals that he wants to start a family with Emma fairly soon but she does not feel ready.

Later, when Emma finds out that Matt lied to her about his ex-girlfriend being dead, she confronts him with evidence that she is still alive. The two have an argument and Matt attempts to strangle her. She hit him on the head with a Vodka bottle, which is just within reach. Matt later claimed that Emma tried to kill him but was arrested, following an investigation into the incident. After the incident, Emma grew closer to Will.

Emma was killed when she attempted to evacuate a building she suspected was threatened by a terrorist attack. In the absence of her sergeant, [[Callum Stone]], Emma was forced to attempt the evacuation alone, until a bomb went off with Emma inside. When Stone arrived, he attempted frantically to revive the PC, but to no avail. Stone is racked with guilt at Emma's death, and that he may have been able to do something about it, had he been where he should have. He later took his frustration out on Sergeant [[Dale Smith (The Bill)|Smith]], and the two sergeants are pulled apart by a furious Inspector [[Gina Gold|Gold]]. It became clear that the actions of one police officer can have far-reaching effects on the rest of the team, and it's hard to imagine how life at Sun Hill can ever get back to normal. [http://www.billfans.com/dcboard.php?az=show_topic&amp;forum=120&amp;topic_id=8711&amp;mesg_id=8711&amp;page=]

PC Keane was replaced by PC [[Millie Brown]] in June 2008. [[Millie Brown|Millie]] arrived with [[Reg Hollis]]'s replacement PC [[Arun Ghir]] and a new transfer PC [[Leon Taylor (The Bill)|Leon Taylor]].
{{-}}

===Jane Kendall===
{{Infobox character
| name       = Jane Kendall
| first      = 
| last       = 
| occupation = Police Officer
| title      = Sergeant
| portrayer  = 
}}
Sergeant Jane Kendall served as Chief Inspector Conway's right-hand lady in the Community Liaison Office. Born into an RAF family, Jane joined the police force at 17 and had been a sergeant for four years when she transferred to Sun Hill. She was a tirelessly committed officer and completely dedicated to her job. She saw her policing role as essentially one of serving the community rather than catching crooks. Caring and compassionate, her generous heart was easily touched by a hard-luck story, which sometimes led to other officers accusing her of being too soft on criminals. But her instinctive perception and sympathy meant she could communicate easily with people from all walks of life. An active sportswoman, she was not afraid to be disliked and pull rank in order to get the best performance from those around her. Conway came to rely on her intuition and the two shared a good working relationship, based on mutual respect. After a 9 month stint in the CLO, she left later that year. 

{{-}}

===Gabriel Kent===
{{Main|Gabriel Kent}}
{{Infobox character
| name       = Gabriel Kent (Real name David Kent)
| first      = Episode 126 (02/07/2003)
| last       = Episode 353 (06/10/2005)
| occupation = Police Officer
| title      = Police Constable
| portrayer  = [[Todd Carty]]
}}
P.C. Gabriel Kent was one of the most corrupt and deranged police officers ever to work at Sun Hill. 

On the outside, he appeared to be a respectable police officer, but he was just as quick to exploit trust as he was to gain it. Before joining the Metropolitan Police, Kent spent sixteen years in the Royal Navy. He was not highly regarded by other sailors and was thought of as a bully with a short temper. 

Kent only joined the Met to get revenge on Sgt. June Ackland for one reason and one reason only; June had given birth to a boy and put the baby up for adoption. Kent's parents adopted June's son and gave him all the praise, making their own son extremely bitter and jealous. To put his wicked plan into action, Kent stole his brother's ID and qualifications and arrived at Sun Hill as Gabriel Kent, as he had form for assault - a conviction that would've prevented him from joining the Force. He arrived to seek revenge on June, but the mode of his insanity grew and grew as he demolished both members of the public and his colleagues when he committed crimes of fraud, perjury, pretend incest, conspiracy to pervert the course of justice, conspiracy to murder, rape and murder. 

Throughout his time at Sun Hill, Kent evolved from a bullying bigot into an ultimately evil serial killer, by murdering PC Kerry Young, the Sun Hill Sniper and leaving Andrea Dunbar to die in the Sun Hill Fire 2005

{{-}}

===Brian Kite===
{{Infobox character
| name       = Inspector Brian Kite
| first      = The New Order Of Things (21/09/1987)
| last       = Not Without Cause (07/12/1987)
| occupation = Police Officer
| title      = Police Inspector
| portrayer  = [[Simon Slater]]
}}
An unpopular recruit to the Sun Hill ranks, Inspector Brian Kite kept an eagle eye on his relief. He considered himself the modern face of policing: rule bound, PACE-quoting, politically correct, making all the right moves. But really he was pedantic, officious and uncompassionate. Choosing to rule by fear, none were too upset when his stay at the station turned out only to be for a couple of months. 

{{-}}

===Nickolas &quot;Nick&quot; Klein===
{{Infobox character
| name       = Nick Klein
| first      = Integrity part I (16/09/1999)
| last       = Episode 206 (08/04/2004)
| occupation = Police Officer
| title      = Police Constable
| portrayer  = [[René Zagger]]
}}
Nick Klein, aged 28, had three or four years' experience in the job before transferring to Sun Hill from west London. He was already familiar with the area - partly because he's an EastEnders himself, and partly because his off duty passion (dance music) had led to him becoming fairly well established as a DJ at one of Sun Hill's local clubs. DJ-ing was something he just about managed to fit in alongside his policing, mostly at weekends. Through his acquaintance with the club scene, Klein also met a girlfriend, who was the principal reason he asked for a transfer. 

Klein was a quick, likeable, clever officer - confident, versatile, naturally entrepreneurial, so he tended to play somewhat by his own rules. He had a good sense of humour, and a sharp East End wit - he was rarely stuck for a smart answer. In many ways Klein was simply a straight up East End lad, dealing in the odd bargain and happy on the odd Saturday afternoons when he could get to White Hart Lane with his mates. Klein was also essentially pragmatic - a relativist, who could usually see various sides to any argument. 

Alongside many of his colleagues he sometimes seemed to have a breezy, almost nonchalant attitude to his work. Perhaps this was because he'd done a fair amount before - e.g. travelling - and for him being a police officer was not a vocation or probably even a lifelong career. It was a different and challenging job for the time being: a chance to see things from the other side. 

Klein thought he had it all worked out in coming to Sun Hill - the girlfriend, the club, the DJ-ing. He was rapidly involved in a tricky undercover operation to expose a racist officer at Barton Street however, as a result of which he lost his girlfriend and got a nasty scare when he was almost caught buying grass (something he'd been a little too relaxed about). He moved back into the Section House for a while and then went and stayed at home with his parents. Unfortunately Klein's little forays into buying grass morphed themselves into a nasty crack habit. Supt. Okaro allowed him into the rehab programme and gave him the chance to rejoin the officers at Sun Hill - but it proved to be a while before he won back the complete trust of his colleagues. 

In the end Nick hung up his uniform when he became a vital witness to a shooting; he went deep into Witness Protection until criminal Dennis Weaver could be brought to justice.

{{-}}

===Kirsty Knight===
{{Infobox character
| name       = Kirsty Knight
| first      = Crossing the line (18/02/2010)
| last       = 
| occupation = Police Officer
| spouse     = 
| title      = Police Constable 
(Specialty: Area Car Driver)
| portrayer  = Sarah Manners 
}}
P.C. Kirsty Knight is Sun Hill's ambitious New Area Car Driver chosen by Sergeant Jo Masters. Kirsty arrived at a bad time and so got herself caught up in the Morale problem, due to Sergeant Callum Stone's suspension by Borough Commander Lisa Kennedy.
{{-}}

===Terry Knowles===
{{Infobox character
| name       = Special Constable Terry Knowles
| first      = Special Attention (18/12/01)
| last       = Loaded (03/01/02)
| occupation = Police Officer
| spouse     = Dani Knowles
| children   = One son (with Dani)
| Call Sign  = 1859
| title      = Special Constable
| portrayer  = [[Alex Avery (actor)|Alex Avery]]
}}
He was a double-glazing salesman in normal life and served as a volunteer special constable. In his short time at Sun Hill, Terry became good friends with Des Taviner and fell out with Tony Stamp (who he called Moany Tony). His Sergeant was Gilmore. Terry was killed, while on duty, by a woman whom he had stopped for a traffic offence (officially), though he was actually trying to get her phone number so he could ask her on a date. After his death and according to the local news he had split from his wife, Dani and had one son. He also had one sister and two nieces.
{{-}}
lisa kennedy

Area Commander for the Borough of Canley. Commander Kennedy was first on hand at Sun Hill Police Station when Sergeant Callum Stone was seen on video footage to be assaulting someone whilst trying to help a victim of crime, during a disturbance outside a Nightclub. She offered Superintendent Jack Meadows any support procedurely during this investigation into Sergeant Stones' actions, whilst also taking the liberty to looking over their figures, getting involved in offering further advice during a Murder investigation and to help Inspector Dale Smith and Sergeant Jo Masters increase morale with the troops that had dropped dramitcally when Sergeant Stone was &quot;shafted&quot;.

==L==
===Stuart Lamont===
{{Infobox character
| name       = Stuart Lamont
| Current Status     = Active (Background) 
| last       = 
| occupation = Police Officer
| title      = Sergeant
&lt;br /&gt; former PC
Specialty: Custody
| portrayer  = Steve Morley
}}

{{-}}

===Duncan Lennox===
{{Infobox character
| name       = Duncan Lennox
| first      = The Fat Lady Sings (27/11/98)
| last       = Episode 077 (02/01/03)
| occupation = Police Officer
| title      = Detective Constable
| portrayer  = [[George Rossi]]
}}
Duncan comes to Sun Hill from [[Epsom]] prison and his motives for wanting a transfer to the [[East End]] are at first a mystery to his new colleagues in [[Criminal Investigation Department|CID]]. A bulky Glaswegian with an ironic sense of humour, he quickly makes his presence felt, particularly with the women in the station, whom he treats with a combination of appreciative chivalry and old-fashioned sexism. Duncan manages to combine an air of profound laziness with sudden bursts of enthusiasm If he senses the chance of a good arrest, he pursues a case with dogged determination. 

There is nothing he enjoys more than arresting a villain, and he thoroughly annoys his victims by treating them with immense affability. Thirty-nine years old, with twenty-one years' service behind him, Duncan can be irritatingly smug about his experience of the job, an inveterate tease and, when roused, witheringly accurate in his put-downs, but his ready wit wins him friends and allies in the station. He is not as impulsive as some and often acts as the middle-man preferring to see both sides of an argument. 

The chink in his armour is his wife, Shona, who he treats with a healthy degree of respect and secretly adores, until she has an affair and leaves him. Shona is a highflying career woman, working for one of the larger financial institutions, and it is her salary rather than Duncan's that pays for their Docklands Riverside apartment. When Shona says jump, Duncan's only question is how high, a fact that his colleagues come to understand when they realise that it is her job that dictated the move to Sun Hill. Duncan is beginning a life on his own and slowly beginning to realise that he is up for standing on his own two feet. 

One step ahead of the game, Duncan decides to move onwards and upwards, becoming part of the [[Murder Investigation Team]]. One of his first assignments brings him back to Sun Hill to investigate the Sun Hill [[serial killer]].
{{-}}

===Alfred &quot;Tosh&quot; Lines===
{{Infobox character
| name       = Alfred Lines
| first      = Stop and Search (27/10/88)
| last       = A People Person (09/06/98)
| occupation = Police Detective
| title      = Detective Constable
| portrayer  = [[Kevin Lloyd]]
}}
often off to see a snout, or the odd pint with jim carver 

Tosh served for a decade at Sun Hill and he then took a position in the Coroner's Office.
{{-}}

===Dave Litten===
{{Infobox character
| name       = Dave Litten
| first      = Woodentop (16/08/1983)
| last       = The Sweet Smell of Failure (22/01/1985)
| occupation = Police Officer
| title      = Police Constable
| portrayer  = [[Gary Olsen]]
}}
Ambitious to join CID, PC Dave Litten took every opportunity to try and impress Roy Galloway. He was quite bigoted in his views and preferred a firm policing style rather than the 'social worker' approach of his colleagues. Litten's eagerness was often misplaced and when he attempted to score Brownie points by taking information on a series of armed robberies directly to Galloway, he was reprimanded by both the DI and Bob Cryer. Eventually a successful board led to him being temporarily seconded to CID, whereupon he began lording it over his old mates in Uniform. There was a vague spark of romantic interest between Litten and June Ackland, although it was never clear whether anything happened between them. 

Litten was eventually accepted on the trainee investigator course and later returned for Brownlow's clerk's retirement party in 1986. 
{{-}}

===Steve Loxton===
{{Infobox character
| name       = Steve Loxton
| first      = Police Powers (12/06/1990)
| last       = No Trace (14/11/1997)
| occupation = Police Officer
| title      = Police Constable 
Speciality = Area Car Driver)
| portrayer  = [[Tom Butcher]]
}}
When PC Steve Loxton came to Sun Hill from his home in Manchester, he was full of himself, confident that he could do anything the job required. At that time - when there was a recruitment drive on - to have the guts and the gift of the gab was more than enough. Loxton had more - brains, ambition and a soldier's toughness. Many of his colleagues soon thought of him as loathsome Loxton. He seemed to have no patience with people on the streets. Whether they were villains or victims, he seemed to think they had brought their troubles on themselves; they were probably to blame. If they happened to be black, they were certainly to blame. 

Loxton joined the Army when he first left school. He liked the structure, the discipline, feeling he was part of a group - get apart from ordinary people, a group with special powers. But the Army was claustrophobic. He left at the end of his contract to join the police where he felt he'd have the status but also the independence. His wife preferred it, too, although Loxton didn't talk about her. He was so tightly buttoned up about his private life, neither Tony Stamp nor Dave Quinnan nor any of the others who spent hours with him dared to ask. 

Loxton was not mad on macho heroic acts. When a suicidal man jumped into a river, he thought carefully about jumping in after him. He'd done that before and nearly drowned himself. Persistent and practical, Loxton worked hard and got results; that was why even Andrew Monroe had time for him. He took pride in being an excellent Area Car driver. He took pride in wearing the uniform, which was always clean and neat. His aim was to become a firearms officer, but after taking the Lippett's Hill course he changed his mind. Did he discover that he didn't, after all, have the killer instinct or did he reason that with a gun he would be asking to be put in dangerous situations - and only mugs do that? 

Loxton performed an illegal search of an off-duty black police officer, after which he was seriously reprimanded. Disillusioned with the job and the limits of modern-day policing, he left the force, not before fitting up a bent solicitor. Returning for Dave Quinnan's wedding in 1999, he admitted that in hindsight it was the worst mistake of his life.
{{-}}

===Abe &quot;Snowball&quot; Lyttleton===
{{Infobox character
| name       = Abe Lyttleton
| first      = Snouts and Red Herrings (11/11/1985)
| last       = The Chief Superintendent’s Party (10/02/1986)
| occupation = Police Officer
| title      = Police Constable
| portrayer  = [[Ronnie Cush]]
}}
Sun Hill was PC Abe Lyttleton's third posting in three and a half years. Senior officers attributed it to the difficulty of being a &quot;minority within a minority&quot; and indeed they were right - Lyttleton was Sun Hill's first black policeman and he had a lot of eyes on him. The relief were openly welcoming, but he was given a hard time by fellow newcomer Pete Muswell who believed the inclusion of ethnic minorities in the Met was a mistake, and promptly christened him 'Snowball'. Lyttleton rose above Muswell's repeated racist taunts and proved such a capable officer that he even won his tormentor's grudging respect. Lyttleton didn't last long at Sun Hill however, transferring only after a 3 month stint. 

Abe suffers from [[Vertigo (medical)|vertigo]], as revealed in an episode where he is forced to go onto a roof and arrest a man who is throwing tiles onto the street.
{{-}}

==References==
{{reflist|2}}

===General References===
* {{cite book |title=The Bill: The Inside Story: Behind the Scenes of Britain's Top Police Drama |publisher=HarperCollins, London |year=1999 |isbn=978-0-00-257137-1 |author=Silver, Rachel}}
* [http://www.thebillbios.co.uk The Bill Bios]
* [http://www.thebill.co.uk The Bill Official Site]
* {{cite book |title=The Bill: The Complete Lowdown on 20 Years at Sun Hill|publisher=ABC Books, Sydney |year=2003 |isbn=0-7333-1330-2 |author=Tibballs, Geoff}}

{{The Bill}}

[[Category:Lists of The Bill characters]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
