<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="21024227" ns="0" title="List of Hollyoaks characters (2005)"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{DISPLAYTITLE:List of ''Hollyoaks'' characters (2005)}}
{{HOMinor}}
The following is a list of minor characters that first appeared in the [[Channel 4]] [[soap opera]] ''[[Hollyoaks]]'' in [[2005]], by order of first appearance.
{{TOC limit|limit=2}}

==Stephen &quot;Macki&quot; Mackintosh==
{{Infobox soap character 2
|series= Hollyoaks
|name = Stephen Mackintosh
|portrayer = Paul Holowaty
|first = 2 May 2005
|last = 18 August 2005
|died = 18 August 2005
|years = 2005
|occupation = [[Student]]
}}

'''Stephen &quot;Macki&quot; Mackintosh ''' was a friend of [[Justin Burton]]. The two met when Justin was troubled and began buying [[marijuana]] off Macki. Soon Justin was forced to go to boot camp and sorted out his life. When Justin returned to town, Macki frequently distracted Jusin and wanted him to come back to his old ways. However, Justin wanted to avoid Macki and hang around with his stepbrother [[Ali Taylor]] and friend [[Nicole Owen]]. An embittered Macki made Ali's life a misery by calling him &quot;monkey boy&quot; and other racist taunts, and he framed Justin for a fire started in the science lab at the school. However, after finding evidence against Macki, Justin managed to get him expelled.

Both Ali and Justin thought their troubles were over, until next term as Macki returned to school and wanted revenge. The bullying got worse and both Ali and Justin were beaten up by Macki and his friends.  Ali eventually had enough of the bullying and went after him with a knife that his father, Richard, had confiscated from Justin (who got the knife to defend himself against Macki).  When Ali found Macki, Macki challenged him to a one-on-one fight and led him to a quiet spot; whilst Ali's back was turned, Macki picked up a brick.

Justin, who had realised the knife was missing, found Ali just in time to see Macki with the brick. He called out to Ali, who then turned around and stabbed Macki.  Ali dropped the knife and Justin told him he'd sort it all out and told Ali to go home.  Ali then ran out into the road and was hit by a car. Justin hid the knife in the hospital toilets. Meanwhile, both Macki and Ali died of their injuries. A few days later, Justin went back for the knife but the police had already found it and were waiting for Justin to show up. Justin was then arrested for Macki's murder but was later found not guilty.
{{-}}

==Charles Hayton==
{{Infobox soap character 2
|series= Hollyoaks
|name = Charles Hayton
|portrayer = Kevin McGowan
|years = 2005–06
|first = July 2005
|last = March 2006
|death = 2006
|wife= [[Margaret Hayton]]
|daughters= [[Becca Dean]]&lt;br&gt;[[Nancy Dean]]
|grandsons= [[Charlie Dean]]
}}

'''Charles Hayton''' was the father of [[Becca Dean|Becca]] and [[Nancy Hayton]]. Charles and his wife Margaret were wealthy and seen as snobbish by Jake and his family. When Charles first met Jake, he was in garden clothes, and Jake, assuming he was the gardener, proceeded to tell him all about how humourless and stuck up Charles was. Frankie, Craig, and Steph dropped in for an unplanned visit, and a drunk Frankie told the Haytons all about Jake's affair and his giving a Sexually Transmitted Infection to Becca. The families also clashed over wedding preparations and cost. In spite of this turmoil, Charles and Margaret attended their daughter's wedding and wished her well.

Charles had a heart attack in early 2006 and Becca went to visit him during his recuperation. During another visit a few months later, she was in the midst of an affair with Justin Burton and wasn't actually there when her father suddenly died.
{{-}}

==Margaret Hayton==
{{Infobox soap character 2
|series= Hollyoaks
|name = Margaret Hayton
|portrayer = Darryl Fishwick
|years = 2005, 2006, 2007
|first = 2005
|last = August 2007
|home=[[Canada]]
|husband= [[Charles Hayton]]
|daughters= [[Becca Dean]]&lt;br&gt;[[Nancy Dean]]
|grandsons= [[Charlie Dean]]
|}}

'''Margaret Hayton''' is the mother of [[Becca Dean|Becca]] and [[Nancy Hayton]]. Margaret and her husband Charles were wealthy and had some reservations about Becca's relationship with [[Jake Dean]], but attended their wedding. Charles suffered from a heart attack the next year, and died a few months later. Margaret returned in October 2006 when she learned Becca was engaged to schoolboy [[Justin Burton]]. Margaret was extremely apprehensive about the relationship, along with Nancy's relationship with tattoo artist Foz, but went along with what her daughters wanted. Over the course of the next year, Becca gave birth to Charlie, who was thought to be Jake's son, was sent to prison and stabbed to death. When Margaret returned the next summer, she was surprised to see Nancy, who was raising Charlie, had taken up with Jake. She wanted to take Charlie to raise for herself, but Jake and Nancy refused. Margaret told Nancy she would never be as good as Becca, no matter how much she tried.

{{-}}

==Bill Ashworth==
{{Infobox soap character 2
|series= Hollyoaks
|name = Bill Ashworth
|portrayer = John Jardine
|years= 2005–06, 2007
|first =2005
|last = February 2007
|family= [[Ashworth family|Ashworth]]
|sons= [[Neville Ashworth]]&lt;br&gt;[[Noel Ashworth]]
|granddaughters=[[Hannah Ashworth]]&lt;br&gt;[[Beth Clement]]
|grandsons=[[Rhys Ashworth]]&lt;br&gt;[[Josh Ashworth]]
}}

'''Bill Ashworth''' was the father of [[Noel Ashworth|Noel]] and [[Neville Ashworth]]. He was a retired bus driver and army veteran but despite his leaning towards military precision in all things, he never lost his sense of fun. With an eye for the ladies, he was not ready to settle into old age. Bill was a gambler and ran a book on any subject. He lived at an nursing home and often visited his family during Christmas holidays. However, when his best friend at the home died, Bill felt lonely and wanted to move in with his family. It was left up to his grandson [[Josh Ashworth|Josh]] and his maternal cousin [[Jamie &quot;Fletch&quot; Fletcher]] to help Bill out of the nursing home and moved him into the Ashworth's house. With much dispute between [[Suzanne Ashworth|Suzanne]] and Neville, they decided to let Bill stay after the children received a pay off from Bill in convincing their parents to let him stay. Often Bill made a mess around the house, which left Suzanne frustrated but Bill decided to give something back to the family in exchange for letting him stay. When Neville was sacked from his job, Bill gave him his inheritance which helped Neville to buy Drive and Buy. Also, the children received their inheritance as well, which was tied up into the family business.

Bill was last seen in February 2007, at Hannah's 18th birthday party. He was last mentioned in August 2007, when Hannah called him to ask if Neville had done anything bad when he was a teenager.
{{-}}

==Rory==
{{Infobox soap character 2
|series= Hollyoaks
|name = Rory
|portrayer = Alex McGettigan
|years=2005
|first =July 2005
|last = September 2005
|brothers = Connor
}}

'''Rory''' was an [[Irish Traveller]] whose caravan briefly set up a home in Chester near [[Tony Hutchinson]]'s restaurant, Il Gnosh. Tony was furious at them for being what he saw as low class and driving down his business. He clashed with Rory and his brother Connor, as well as their dog Sheba. Rory also had a brief flirtation with [[Zara Morgan]]. He confided in her that he and Connor were staying because their mother was battling cancer in a local hospital. When Zara told this to Tony's wife Mandy, and Rory helped stop a robbery at Il Gnosh, Tony mended fences, somewhat, with Rory. Conor and Rory's mother's cancer went into remission and she asked to return to Ireland, which they did.
{{-}}

==Connor==
{{Infobox soap character 2
|series= Hollyoaks
|name = Connor
|portrayer = Danann Breathnach
|years=2005
|first =July 2005
|last = September 2005
|brothers =Rory
}}

'''Connor''' was Rory's younger brother. He punched Tony when Tony threatened Rory. He also befriended [[Nicole Owen]] and kissed her on her birthday, much to her mother's displeasure. Nicole wanted to have her first time with Connor, but Connor realised she wasn't ready for sex. He was willing to try, but she ran out of the flat in shame. The next day, she wanted to start over, but he told her he was moving back to Ireland with his brother and mother. Just before he left, he kissed Nicole and told her he'd always love her.
{{-}}

==Freddy Watson==
{{Infobox soap character 2
|series= Hollyoaks
|name = Freddy Watson
|portrayer = Greg Kelly
|years=2005–06
|first = 2005
|last = 2006
}}

'''Freddy Watson''' studied English literature at HCC and was an animal rights campaigner. He arrived in 2005 and had a less than secret admirer in [[Zara Morgan]], an avid protester against anything and everything. She didn't realise he was using her to get revenge against HCC for animal rights.

Freddy also conspired with [[Chris Fenwick|Chris]] to depose [[Lee Hunter (Hollyoaks)|Lee Hunter]] from his presidency, but this backfired when Zara told the student council about the plot, and Freddy's involvement with the HCC Media Lab Fire in December 2005.

Freddy was not seen again, but it would appear that along with Zara and Lee, he and Chris were kicked out of HCC.
{{-}}

==Presley Dean==
{{Infobox soap character 2
|series= Hollyoaks
|name = Presley Dean
|years=2005
|first = 2005
|last = 2005
|born = July 2005
|father= [[Johnno Dean]]
|mother= Michelle Dean
|halfbrothers= [[Jake Dean]]&lt;br&gt;[[Craig Dean]]
|halfsisters= [[Steph Dean]]&lt;br&gt;[[Debbie Dean]]
}}
'''Presley Dean''' is the illegitimate son of married [[Johnno Dean|Johnno]] and a 19 year old named Michelle. His father briefly walked out of the family home to be with his first wife [[Frankie Osborne]] and his kids, but returned after they were disgusted with his behaviour. Johnno and Michelle married shortly afterwards when Johnno's divorce from Frankie was finalised.
{{-}}

==Chris Fenwick==
{{Infobox soap character 2
|series= Hollyoaks
|name = Christopher Fenwick
|portrayer = Chris Grierson
|years= 2005
|occupation= Newspaper editor
}}
'''Christopher &quot;Chris&quot; Fenwick''' is the former head of the entertainment committee and editor of the newspaper at Hollyoaks Community College, losing his position to [[Lee Hunter (Hollyoaks)|Lee Hunter]] in an election.  Chris pretended not to care about losing and asked if he could be Lee's [[vice president]].

Little did Lee know that Chris was manipulating him into spending more money than what was in the college funds.  Lee's friend [[David &quot;Bombhead&quot; Burke]] found out what Chris was doing but when he tried to tell Lee, Lee wouldn't believe him.

Chris then told Lee about the missing money and blamed Bombhead, which caused Lee and Bombhead to have a massive falling out.  Chris then conspired with [[List of minor and recurring characters from Hollyoaks#Freddy Watson|Freddy Watson]], who set fire to the HCC's media lab for an [[animal rights]] demonstration and tried to pin the fire on Lee.  But Lee's friend and Freddy's girlfriend [[Zara Morgan]] told people what had really happened and the truth finally came out.  Lee punched Chris saying, &quot;This is for Bombhead&quot;.

It appears that Chris was kicked out of college along with Freddy, Zara and Lee.

{{-}}

==Ally Harrison==
{{Infobox soap character 2
|series= Hollyoaks
|name = Ally Harrison
|portrayer = Louise Howells
|years=2005
|first = August 2005
|last = September 2005
|brothers = Alex Harrison
}}
'''Ally Harrison''' was a girl  Lisa Hunter met while they were both trying to get the same item exchanged. They bonded over boyfriend troubles. Ally invited Lisa and Ben Davies to lunch, where they met Alex. Lisa and Ben assumed he was another of Ally's boyfriends, due to their close bond and the fact that they lived together, but they were actually brother and sister. Ben began to suspect Ally was trying to seduce Lisa. The foursome partied during ''[[Hollyoaks: Crossing The Line]]'', and Ben worried Alex and Ally would want more than just friendship, but nothing came of it. Ben and Lisa temporarily stayed at Ally's new flat when they had nowhere else to go. Ally's further adventures were chronicled in ''[[Hollyoaks: Let Loose]]''.
{{-}}

==Karen Taylor==
{{Infobox soap character 2
|series= Hollyoaks
|name = Karen Taylor
|portrayer = Suzette Llewellyn
|appeared = 6 September 2005
|husband = [[Richard Taylor (Hollyoaks)|Richard Taylor]]
|daughters= [[Darlene Taylor]]&lt;br&gt;Georgina Taylor
|sons=[[Ali Taylor]]&lt;br&gt;Ethan Taylor
}}

'''Karen Taylor'''  was married to [[Richard Taylor (Hollyoaks)|Richard]], a marriage which produced [[Ali Taylor|Ali]], [[Darlene Taylor|Darlene]], and two younger children, Ethan and Georgina. Their marriage broke up due to his affair with Liz Burton. Ali was run over after fleeing from the scene of Macki's stabbing, and Karen attended his funeral. [[Justin Burton|Justin]], who had been arrested for the murder, unexpectedly showed up; during an argument with Karen, he told everyone what Ali had done. Karen refused to believe him and returned home.
{{-}}

==Grace Hutchinson==
{{Infobox soap character 2
|series= Hollyoaks
|name=Grace Hutchinson
|portrayer=Various
|years=2005–06
|first= October 2005
|last= 11 May 2006
|born = October 2005
|death= 12 May 2006
|father= [[Tony Hutchinson]]
|mother=[[Mandy Hutchinson]]
|halfbrothers= [[Harry Thompson (Hollyoaks)|Harry Thompson]]
|halfsisters= Ella Richardson
|uncles= [[Dominic Reilly]]&lt;br&gt; [[Tom Cunningham]]&lt;br&gt; [[Lewis Richardson (Hollyoaks)|Lewis Richardson]]
|grandmothers= Vicky Hutchinson&lt;br&gt; [[Helen Cunningham]]
|grandfathers= Brian Hutchinson&lt;br&gt;[[Dennis Richardson (Hollyoaks)|Dennis Richardson]]
}}

'''Grace Antonia Helen Hutchinson''' was born in October 2005, two months early, to [[Tony Hutchinson|Tony]] and [[Mandy Richardson|Mandy Hutchinson]] Grace was originally going to be called Antonia but Mandy was not keen. Antonia was then made her middle name. Mandy suffered [[post-natal depression]] for a while. But after she spent a while in intensive care, Mandy made friends with a woman who had a premature baby called Daisy. Daisy died and Mandy grew to love Grace in fear of losing her. Grace was christened, where [[Becca Dean]] became her godmother, while [[Max Cunningham|Max]], [[Sam &quot;OB&quot; O'Brien|OB]] and [[Dom Reilly|Dom]] became godfathers. On 12 May 2006, aged seven months old, Grace was found dead from suspected [[Sudden infant death syndrome|SIDS]], on a night [[Hannah Ashworth]] and [[Nancy Hayton]] were babysitting, which left the girls traumatised, after thinking it was their fault. Soon after Grace's death, Mandy left Hollyoaks in the hope of moving on and subsequently left a heart-broken Tony behind, after he had told her that it was all her fault that their daughter died that night.

Following her death, Grace has been mentioned several times. Tony and [[Jacqui McQueen]] miscarried a baby in 2007, thus reminding Tony of Grace. Mandy met another man and gave birth to a girl named Ella.
{{-}}

==Wayne Tunnicliffe==
{{Infobox soap character 2
|series= Hollyoaks
|name = Wayne Tunnicliffe
|portrayer = [[Joe Marsden]]
|years=2005, 2006, 2007
|first = 2005
|last =  October 2007
}}

'''Wayne Tunnicliffe''' first appeared as one of [[Ste Hay]]'s friends. Ste was interested in [[Amy Barnes]], while Wayne dated [[Michaela McQueen]]. Wayne was only interested in her because she was &quot;easy&quot; and after a few months he dumped her via text message.

Wayne and Ste befriended [[Josh Ashworth]] and his cousin Fletch to get close to Josh's sister [[Hannah Ashworth]] (they gave up because Hannah was always out with friends). A nastier moment arrived when Ste and Wayne began bullying [[Nicole Owen]] after her brother Sam blew up the Dog in the Pond. They eventually pretended to care about her, taking her to the woods, getting her drunk, and planning to rape her. She threw herself on the ground, sobbing and telling them to get on with it, and they left her alone.

Ste was sent to a juvenile detention facility for his part in a joyride which sent Amy to hospital. Wayne was next seen in spring 2007, hanging out with [[Sonny Valentine]]. Wayne soon discovered that his ex, Michaela, fancied Sonny so he mentioned it to Sonny, not knowing that he and Michaela were secretly going out. Wayne made fun of Michaela to Sonny behind her back and Sonny went along with it to keep their relationship a secret, but when Wayne went too far insulting Michaela, Sonny stood up to him and told him that he and Michaela were dating. Wayne also taunted her about her gay brother, [[John Paul McQueen]], only for John Paul to grab him and threaten him into leaving Michaela alone.

Wayne began selling his little brother's [[ADD]] medication at school. [[Nancy Hayton]], who needed pills to cope with her hectic life, began buying them. When Wayne ran out of medication, she lost her temper. Wayne promised her he would get more and he tried to ask Nancy out. Wayne got cinema tickets but Nancy ripped them up, enraged that Wayne would not get the drugs in time for her next exams.

Wayne was last seen at a house party thrown by Amy and Michaela. Wayne stole food and CDs and when Amy caught him in baby Leah's room, a drunk Wayne grabbed Leah as a hostage. Wayne's former mate Ste grabbed the baby and punched Wayne before throwing all the partygoers out of the house.
{{-}}

==Other characters==
'''Mike''' ([[Bryan Lawrence]], 19 April 2005)
: A plumber who fixed the plumbing [[Steph Dean]] broke in her family flat. They did not have the money to pay him, so Steph arranged a date for Mike and her mother [[Frankie Dean|Frankie]]. Mike turned out to be a nice man, but Frankie got drunk to combat her nerves and threw up in his lap when he tried to kiss her.

'''Robin Whittle''' ([[Phil Corbett]], 18 May 2005)
: [[Craig Dean]]'s business teacher, who took a very hard line with him over his plans for the future. To Craig's horror, Robin went out with Frankie after they met in the supermarket. Craig asked her to drop him, but Frankie refused. Only when Robin criticised Craig's abilities and put down single-parent families did Frankie tell him to leave.

'''Nathan Haywood''' (Robert Norbury)
: A friend of [[Justin Burton]] and [[Ali Taylor]]. When he first appeared, Justin and Ali were jealous of him, mainly due to his football skills and wealth. Despite their jealousy, Ali and Justin became friends with Nathan. Nathan disappeared from ''Hollyoaks'' in order to make Justin and Ali's bullying storyline their priority.{{citation}}

'''Police Officer''' (Loveday Smith, 6 September 2005)
: The police officer interviewed Steph after she accidentally stopped a thief.

'''Aphrodite''' (Jessica Frain, September 2005)
: Aphrodite was a snake charmer who appeared at Lee Hunter's house party during ''[[Hollyoaks: Crossing The Line]]''. Lee fell head over heels for the curvaceous blonde, not realising his rival Chris Fenwick had set him up with a transvestite. Lee was horrified upon learning the truth. Aphrodite returned to his house a few days later to pick up her snake, Pete.

'''Inspector Blake''' (James Nickerson, July 2005)
: Dealt with [[Mel Burton|Mel]] after she was arrested for drunkenly breaking into her old home and resisting arrest. A few weeks later, he arrested her mother Liz for her one-woman protest against the Travellers.

'''Vicar''' (John Elkington, July to August 2005)
: He tried to persuade Becca Hayton and Jake Dean to wait another year to get married, but Jake's impassioned plea convinced him of the relationship. Frankie and Jack Osborne decided on a double wedding with her son Jake and his fiance. In order to get the vicar's permission, Frankie's son Craig lied that Frankie had a terminal illness. He and Jack found out the truth at the reception, and jokingly convinced her the wedding was invalid.

'''D.S. Simpson''' ([[Chuk Iwuji]], August 2005)
: Investigated the fatal stabbing of Stephen &quot;Macki&quot; Mackintosh.

'''Edward Johnson''' (Paul Kynman, 9 August 2005)
: A man who was mentioned by Bombhead's late mother in a letter. While searching for Edward, Bombhead tracked him down at the circus, Edward insisted he'd only had a short fling with his mother which took place before Bombhead's conception.

'''Damien''' (Richard Cadman, 29 August 2005)
: Damien and his friends got into an argument with [[Sam Owen|Sam]] and [[Andy Holt|Andy]] in the SU Bar. They waited for Sam outside the bar, but Andy ran them off by setting off a police siren.

'''Alex Harrison''' (Alister Southey, September 2005)
: The brother of Ally Harrison. His further adventures were chronicled in ''[[Hollyoaks: Let Loose]]''.
{{-}}

==External links==

{{Hollyoaks}}
{{Hollyoaks characters}}

{{Use dmy dates|date=October 2010}}
[[Category:Fictional characters introduced in 2005|*, Hollyoaks]]
[[Category:Hollyoaks characters|*, 2005]]
[[Category:Lists of minor fictional characters|Hollyoaks, 2005]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
