<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="210568" ns="0" title="Joe Hill"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Other people}}
{{Infobox person
| name   = Joe Hill
| image     = Joe hill002.jpg
| image_size     = 180px
| caption  =
|birth_name=Joel Emmanuel Hägglund
| birth_date  = {{birth date|1879|10|7|mf=y}}
| birth_place = [[Gävle]], [[Sweden]]
| death_date  = {{death date and age|1915|11|19|1879|10|7|mf=y}}
| death_place = [[Utah]], [[United States]]
|death_cause=[[firing squad]]
|residence=
|nationality=
|other_names=Joseph Hillström
|known_for=
| occupation     = [[labor union|labor]] [[activist]], [[songwriter]], and member of the [[Industrial Workers of the World]]
| spouse         =
| parents        =
| children       =
|relatives=
|website=
|footnotes=
}}

'''Joe Hill''', born '''Joel Emmanuel Hägglund''' in Gävle (Sweden), and also known as '''Joseph Hillström''' (October 7, 1879&lt;ref name=&quot;joehillorg&quot;&gt;[http://www.joehill.org/ Joehill.org]&lt;/ref&gt; – November 19, 1915) was a [[Swedish American|Swedish-American]] [[labor activist]], songwriter, and member of the [[Industrial Workers of the World]] (IWW, also known as the &quot;Wobblies&quot;).&lt;ref&gt;William M. Adler, The Man Who Never Died, The Life, Times, and Legacy of Joe Hill, American Labor Icon, Bloomsbury USA, 2011, pages 92-94, 121&lt;/ref&gt; A native [[Swedish language|Swedish speaker]], he learned English during the early 1900s, while working various jobs from [[New York]] to [[San Francisco]].&lt;ref&gt;William M. Adler, The Man Who Never Died:  The Life, Times, and Legacy of Joe Hill, American Labor Icon, Bloomsbury USA, New York, pages 115-119&lt;/ref&gt; Hill, as an immigrant worker frequently facing unemployment and underemployment, became a popular song writer and cartoonist for the radical union. His most famous songs include &quot;[[The Preacher and the Slave]]&quot;, &quot;[[The Tramp (song)|The Tramp]]&quot;, &quot;[[There is Power in a Union]]&quot;, &quot;[[The Rebel Girl (song)|The Rebel Girl]]&quot;, and &quot;[[Casey Jones—the Union Scab]]&quot;, which generally express the harsh but combative life of itinerant workers, and the perceived necessity of organizing to improve conditions for working people.&lt;ref&gt;William M. Adler, The Man Who Never Died, The Life, Times, and Legacy of Joe Hill, American Labor Icon, Bloomsbury USA, 2011, pages 12-13, 206&lt;/ref&gt; 

In 1914, John G. Morrison, a Salt Lake City area grocer and former policeman, and his son were shot and killed by two men.&lt;ref&gt;William M. Adler, The Man Who Never Died, The Life, Times, and Legacy of Joe Hill, American Labor Icon, Bloomsbury USA, 2011, pages 44-52&lt;/ref&gt; The same evening, Hill arrived at a doctor's office with a gunshot wound, and briefly mentioned a fight over a woman. Yet Hill was reluctant to explain further, and he was later accused of the grocery store murders on the basis of his injury. Hill was convicted of the murders in a controversial trial. Following an unsuccessful appeal, political debates, and international calls for clemency from high profile people and workers' organizations, Hill was executed in November, 1915. After his death, he was memorialized by several [[folksong|folk songs]]. His life and death have inspired books and poetry.

Joe Hill's frequently speculated upon love relationship remained mostly conjecture for nearly a century. A biography published in 2011, said to expand our knowledge of the Joe Hill case &quot;in really dramatic ways,&quot; reveals new information about Hill's ostensible alibi, which was never introduced at his trial.&lt;ref&gt;Steven Greenhouse (quoting John R. Sillito, retired archivist at Weber State University in Ogden, Utah), The New York Times, &quot;Examining a Labor Hero’s Death&quot;, August 27, 2011, page A10&lt;/ref&gt; According to the biography, Joe Hill and his friend and fellow countryman, Otto Appelquist, were rivals for the attention of twenty year old Hilda Erickson, a member of the family with whom the two men were lodging. In a recently discovered letter, Erickson confirmed her relationship with the two men, and the rivalry between them. The letter indicates that when she first discovered Hill was injured, he explained to her that Appelquist had shot him, apparently due to jealousy.&lt;ref&gt;William M. Adler, The Man Who Never Died, The Life, Times, and Legacy of Joe Hill, American Labor Icon, Bloomsbury USA, 2011, pages 294-297&lt;/ref&gt;

== Early life ==
Hill was born 1879 in [[Gävle]], a city in the province of [[Gästrikland]], [[Sweden]]. He was the third child in a family of nine, where three children died young. His father, Olof, worked as a conductor at Gefle Dala Järnväg, a railroad company. Olof died at the age of 41, and his death meant economic disaster for the family. His mother Margareta Catharina did however succeed in keeping the family together until she died in 1902.

Joe Hill's house still stands in [[Gävle]] at the address Nedre Bergsgatan 28, in ''Gamla Stan'', the Old City. {{As of | 2011}} it houses a museum called ''Joe Hill-gården''. 

In 1902, when about 23, Joe Hill and his brother Paul emigrated to the United States. Hill became a migrant laborer, moving from [[New York City]] to [[Cleveland, Ohio]], and eventually to the west coast. He was in [[San Francisco, California]], at the time of the [[1906 San Francisco earthquake|1906 earthquake]].

==IWW==
Hill joined the [[Industrial Workers of the World]] (IWW) or Wobblies around 1910, when working on the docks in [[San Pedro, California]]. In late 1910 he wrote a letter to the IWW newspaper ''[[Industrial Worker]]'', identifying himself as a member of the IWW local chapter in [[Portland, Oregon]].
Hill rose in the IWW organization and traveled widely, organizing workers under the IWW banner, writing political songs and satirical poems, and making speeches.  His songs frequently appropriated familiar melodies from songs of his time.  He coined the phrase &quot;[[wiktionary:pie in the sky|pie in the sky]]&quot;, which appeared in his song &quot;[[The Preacher and the Slave]]&quot; (a [[parody]] of the [[hymn]] &quot;[[In the Sweet By-and-By]]&quot;). Other notable songs written by Hill include &quot;[[The Tramp (song)|The Tramp]]&quot;, &quot;[[There is Power in a Union]]&quot;, &quot;[[The Rebel Girl (song)|The Rebel Girl]]&quot;, and &quot;[[Casey Jones—the Union Scab]]&quot;.

== Trial ==
As an [[Hobo|itinerant worker]], Hill moved around the west, hopping freight trains, going from job to job. Early 1914 found him working as a laborer at the Silver King Mine in [[Park City, Utah]], not far from [[Salt Lake City, Utah|Salt Lake City]].

On January 10, 1914, John G. Morrison and his son Arling were killed in their Salt Lake City butcher store by two armed intruders masked in red [[bandanna]]s. The police first thought it was a crime of revenge, for nothing had been stolen and the elder Morrison had been a police officer, possibly creating many enemies.  On the same evening, Joe Hill appeared on the doorstep of a local doctor, bearing a bullet wound.  Hill said that he had been shot in an argument over a woman, whom he refused to name. The doctor reported that Hill was armed with a [[pistol]].  Considering Morrison's past as a police officer, several men he had arrested were at first considered suspects; 12 people were arrested in the case before Hill was arrested and charged with the murder. A red bandanna was found in Hill's room. The pistol purported to be in Hill's possession at the doctor's office was not found.  Hill resolutely denied that he was involved in the robbery and killing of Morrison. He said that when he was shot, his hands were over his head, and the bullet hole in his coat — four inches below the bullet wound in his back — seemed to support this claim. Hill did not testify at his trial, but his lawyers pointed out that four other people were treated for bullet wounds in Salt Lake City that same night, and that the lack of robbery and Hill's unfamiliarity with Morrison left him with no motive.&lt;ref name=BBC&gt;BBC.co.uk, [http://www.bbc.co.uk/dna/h2g2/A676361 &quot;Joe Hill: Murderer or Martyr?&quot;] February 19, 2002.&lt;/ref&gt;

The prosecution, for its part, produced a dozen eyewitnesses who said that the killer resembled Hill, including 13-year-old Merlin Morrison, the victims' son and brother, who said &quot;That's not him at all&quot; upon first seeing Hill, but later identified him as the murderer. The jury took just a few hours to find him guilty of murder.&lt;ref name=BBC/&gt;

An appeal to the [[Utah Supreme Court]] was unsuccessful. [[Orrin N. Hilton]], the lawyer representing Hill during the appeal, declared: &quot;The main thing the state had on Hill was that he was an IWW and therefore sure to be guilty. Hill tried to keep the IWW out of [the trial]... but the press fastened it upon him.&quot;&lt;ref name=BBC/&gt;

[[Image:The Rebel Girl cover.jpg|right|thumb|280px|Hill was the author of numerous labor songs, including &quot;The Rebel Girl,&quot; inspired by IWW activist [[Elizabeth Gurley Flynn]].]]
In a letter to the court, Hill continued to deny that the state had a right to inquire into the origins of his wound, leaving little doubt that the judges would affirm the conviction. Chief Justice Daniel Straup wrote that his unexplained wound was &quot;a distinguishing mark,&quot; and that &quot;the defendant may not avoid the natural and reasonable inferences of remaining silent.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.kued.org/productions/joehill/about/script3.html Chief Justice Daniel N. Straup]&lt;/ref&gt;
In an article for the [[socialist]] newspaper ''[[Appeal to Reason (newspaper)|Appeal to Reason]]'', Hill wrote: &quot;Owing to the prominence of Mr Morrison, there had to be a 'goat' [scapegoat] and the undersigned being, as they thought, a friendless tramp, a Swede, and worst of all, an IWW, had no right to live anyway, and was therefore duly selected to be 'the goat'.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Joe Hill, ''Appeal to Reason'', August 15, 1915; cited in &quot;Joe Hill: Murderer or Martyr?&quot;&lt;/ref&gt;

The case turned into a major media event. President [[Woodrow Wilson]], the blind and deaf author [[Helen Keller]], and people in Sweden all became involved in a bid for clemency. It generated international union attention, and critics charged that the trial and conviction were unfair.  
In a new biography published in 2011, William M. Adler concludes that Hill was probably innocent of murder (he advances another candidate as the perpetrator), but also suggests that Hill came to see himself as worth more to the labor movement as a dead martyr than he was alive, and that this understanding may have influenced his decisions not to testify at the trial and subsequently to spurn all chances of a pardon.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news| url=http://www.economist.com/node/21525352| title=Songwriter shot dead| work=The Economist| date= August 6, 2011.}}&lt;/ref&gt; He reports that evidence pointed to early police suspect [[Magnus Olson|Frank Z. Wilson]] and also discovered a letter from the woman Hill was involved with, Hilda Erickson, who wrote that Hill had told her he had been shot by her former fiance.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news| url=http://www.nytimes.com/2011/08/27/us/27hill.html| title=Examining a Labor Hero’s Death| work=The New York Times| author= Steven Greenhouse| date= August 26, 2011|page=A10}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Execution ==
Hill was executed by [[firing squad]] on November 19, 1915, and his last word was &quot;Fire!&quot; 

That same day, a dynamite bomb was discovered at the Tarrytown estate of [[John D. Archbold]], President of the Standard Oil Company.  Police theorized the bomb was planted by [[anarchist]]s and [[I.W.W.]] radicals as a protest against Hill's execution. The bomb was discovered by a gardener, who found four sticks of dynamite, weighing a pound each, half hidden in a rut in a driveway fifty feet from the front entrance of the residence. The dynamite sticks were bound together by a length of wire, fitted with percussion caps, and wrapped with a piece of paper matching the color of the driveway, a path used by Archbold in going to or from his home by automobile.  The bomb was later defused by police.&lt;ref&gt;''New York Times'', &quot;Dynamite Bomb For J.D. Archbold,&quot; 22 November 1915.&lt;/ref&gt;

Just prior to his execution, Hill had written to [[Bill Haywood]], an IWW leader, saying, &quot;Goodbye Bill. I die like a true blue rebel. Don't waste any time in mourning. Organize... Could you arrange to have my body hauled to the state line to be buried? I don't want to be found dead in Utah.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.bbc.co.uk/dna/h2g2/A676361 BBC - h2g2 - Joe Hill - Murderer or Martyr?&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Zinn,Howard ''A People's History of the United States'' page 335.&lt;/ref&gt;

His last will, which was eventually set to music by Ethel Raim, founder of the group [[The Pennywhistlers]], reads:&lt;ref&gt;[[Wikimedia:Image:Joe Hill will.pdf|Scanned copy Joe Hill's will]]&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;poem&gt;''My will is easy to decide,
''For there is nothing to divide.
''My kin don't need to fuss and moan,
''&quot;Moss does not cling to a rolling stone.&quot;

''My body? Oh, if I could choose
''I would to ashes it reduce,
''And let the merry breezes blow,
''My dust to where some flowers grow.

''Perhaps some fading flower then
''Would come to life and bloom again.
''This is my Last and final Will.
''Good Luck to All of you,
''Joe Hill&lt;/poem&gt;

==Aftermath==

Hill's body was sent to [[Chicago]] where it was cremated. His ashes were placed into 600 small envelopes and according to Wobbly folklore, sent around the world and released to the winds on May Day 1916. However it was not until the first anniversary of his death (November 19, 1916) that delegates attending the Tenth Convention of the IWW in Chicago received envelopes.&lt;ref&gt;''New York Times'', 20 November 1916.&lt;/ref&gt; The rest of the 600 envelopes were sent to IWW Locals, Wobblies and sympathizers around the world on January 3, 1917.&lt;ref&gt;Davidson, J. (2011). ''[http://libcom.org/history/remains-be-seen-tracing-joe-hills-ashes-new-zealand Remains to be Seen: Tracing Joe Hill's ashes in New Zealand]'', Rebel Press, ISBN 978-0-473-18927-3&lt;/ref&gt;

In 1988 it was discovered that an envelope had been seized by the [[United States Postal Service]] in 1917 because of its &quot;[[subversive]] potential&quot;. The envelope, with a photo affixed, captioned, &quot;Joe Hill murdered by the [[capitalist]] class, Nov. 19, 1915,&quot; as well as its contents, was deposited at the [[National Archives and Records Administration|National Archives]]. A story appeared in the [[United Auto Workers]]' magazine ''Solidarity'' and a small item followed it in ''[[The New Yorker]]'' Magazine. Members of the IWW in Chicago quickly laid claim to the contents of the envelope.

After some negotiations, the last of Hill's ashes (but not the envelope that contained them) was turned over to the IWW in 1988. The weekly ''[[In These Times]]'' ran notice of the ashes and invited readers to suggest what should be done with them. Suggestions varied from enshrining them at the [[AFL-CIO]] headquarters in Washington, DC to [[Abbie Hoffman]]'s suggestion that they be eaten by today's &quot;Joe Hills&quot; like [[Billy Bragg]] and [[Michelle Shocked]]. Bragg did indeed swallow a small bit of the ashes and still carries Shocked's share for the eventual completion of Hoffman's last prank.&lt;ref&gt;Jeff Ditz, &quot;Fifth Estate&quot;, 2005&lt;/ref&gt; The majority of the ashes were cast to the wind in the US, [[Canada]], [[Sweden]], [[Australia]], and [[Nicaragua]]. The ashes sent to Sweden were only partly cast to the wind. The main part was interred in the wall of a union office in [[Landskrona]], a minor city in the south of the country, with a plaque commemorating Hill. That room is now the reading room of the local city library.

One small packet of ashes was scattered at a 1989 ceremony which unveiled a monument to IWW coal miners buried in [[Lafayette, Colorado|Lafayette]], [[Colorado]]. Six unarmed strikers were machine-gunned by [[Colorado]] [[state police]] in 1927 in the [[Columbine Mine Massacre]]. Until 1989 the graves of five of these men were unmarked. Another famous Wobbly, [[Carlos Cortez]], scattered Joe Hill's ashes on the graves at the commemoration.&lt;ref&gt;Denver Post, June 11, 1989&lt;/ref&gt;

To commemorate the 50th anniversary of the execution of Joe Hill, Philip S. Foner published a book, ''The Case of Joe Hill'', about the trial and subsequent events, which concludes that the case was a [[miscarriage of justice]].&lt;ref&gt;Foner, P. (1965). ''The Case of Joe Hill'', New York: International Publishers Co., inc.  ISBN 0-7178-022-9&lt;/ref&gt;

== Influence and tributes ==
*Hill was memorialized in a tribute [[poetry|poem]] written about him c. 1930 by [[Alfred Hayes (writer)|Alfred Hayes]] titled &quot;I Dreamed I Saw Joe Hill Last Night&quot;, sometimes referred to simply as &quot;Joe Hill&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;Hampton, W: ''Guerrilla Minstrels''. Tennessee&lt;/ref&gt; Hayes's lyrics were turned into a song in 1936 by [[Earl Robinson]].

*[[Paul Robeson]] and [[Pete Seeger]] often performed this song and are associated with it, along with [[Ireland|Irish]] folk group [[The Dubliners]]. [[Joan Baez]]'s [[Woodstock festival|Woodstock]] performance of &quot;Joe Hill&quot; in 1969 is one of the best known recordings. She also recorded the song numerous times, including a live version on her 2005 album ''Bowery Songs''. [[Scott Walker (singer)|Scott Walker]] recorded a version for his album ''[[The Moviegoer (album)|The Moviegoer]]''.

*The [[Sweden|Swedish]] [[socialist]] leader [[Ture Nerman]] (1886–1969) wrote a biography of Joe Hill. For the project, Nerman did the first serious research about Hill's life story, including finding and interviewing Hill's family members in Sweden. Nerman, who was a poet himself, also translated most of Hill's songs into Swedish.

*[[Ralph Chaplin]] wrote a tribute poem/song called &quot;Joe Hill&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Joyce L. Kornbluh, ''Rebel Voices'', pp. 155-156.&lt;/ref&gt; and referred to him in his song &quot;Red November, Black November.&quot;

*[[Phil Ochs]] wrote and recorded a different, original song called &quot;Joe Hill&quot;,&lt;ref&gt;[http://web.cecs.pdx.edu/~trent/ochs/lyrics/joe-hill.html ''Joe Hill&quot; song by Phil Ochs]&lt;/ref&gt; using a traditional melody found in the song &quot;[[John Hardy (song)|John Hardy]]&quot;, which tells a much more detailed story of Joe Hill's life and death, and includes the lines that have since been associated with Ochs' own life and death, &quot;It's the life of a rebel that he chose to live; It's the death of a rebel that he died&quot;. Ochs' song concludes with Hill's words, &quot;This is my last and final will; Good luck to all of you, Joe Hill, Good luck to all of you.&quot;

* Singer/songwriter [[Josh Joplin]] wrote and recorded a song entitled ''Joseph Hillstrom 1879-1915'' as a tribute to Joe Hill for the self-titled debut album of his band, [[Among The Oak &amp; Ash]].

*[[Frank Tovey]] sings about Joe Hill in his song 'Joe Hill' from the 1989 album ''Tyranny and the Hired Hand''. In this song he uses some of the words from the Alfred Hayes poem.

*[[Bob Dylan]] claims that Hill's story was one of his inspirations to begin writing his own songs.{{Citation needed|date=December 2008}} His song &quot;I dreamed I Saw St. Augustine&quot; is loosely based around the story and Robinson's version.

*[[Chumbawamba]]'s song about Joe Hill, &quot;By and By&quot;, appears on the 2005 album ''[[A Singsong and a Scrap]]''. It incorporates the first stanza of Alfred Hayes' poem.

*In 1990, [[Smithsonian Folkways]] released ''Don't Mourn — Organize!: Songs of Labor Songwriter Joe Hill''. This compilation featured the likes of &quot;Haywire Mac&quot; McClintock and Cisco Houston performing his songs as well as narrative interludes from [[Utah Phillips]], [[Elizabeth Gurley Flynn]], and others.

*[[Wallace Stegner]] published a fictional biography called ''Joe Hill'' in 1950.

*Authors [[Stephen King|Stephen]] and [[Tabitha King]] named their second child, [[Joe Hill (writer)|Joseph Hillstrom King]], after Joe Hill.

*Gibbs M. Smith wrote a biography &quot;Joe Hill&quot;, which was later turned into the 1971 movie [[Joe Hill (film)|''Joe Hill'']] also known as [[The Ballad of Joe Hill (film)|''The Ballad of Joe Hill'']] directed by [[Bo Widerberg]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://swedish.imdb.com/title/tt0067276/ ''The Ballad of Joe Hill'' (film)]&lt;/ref&gt;

*A chapter of [[John Dos Passos]]'s novel [[U.S.A. trilogy|''1919'']] is a stylized biography of Joe Hill.

*Robert Hunter wrote the opening verse about Joe Hill for the song &quot;Down the Road&quot; which he wrote for [[Mickey Hart]]'s ''Mystery Box''.

*[[The Nightwatchman]] (a.k.a. [[Tom Morello]], guitarist of [[Rage Against the Machine]] and [[Audioslave]]) refers to Joe Hill in his song &quot;The Union Song&quot;.

*For [[Rage Against the Machine]]'s second Album, ''Evil Empire'', a suggested reading list was included. Included is the biography ''Joe Hill'' written by Gibbs M. Smith.

*Joe Hill's name is invoked in [[Steve Earle]]'s song, &quot;Christmas in Washington.&quot;

*Joe Hill is referred to in [[Justin Townes Earle]]'s song, &quot;They killed John Henry.&quot; ([[Justin Townes Earle]] is the son of [[Steve Earle]].) Townes Earle sings &quot;Joe Hill he worked any job he could find, he'd rake your leaves or pick your vines. They killed Joe Hill, put a bullet to his name, but that bullet made a martyr of the slain&quot;.

*The Swedish punk rock band [[Randy (band)|Randy]] refers to Joe Hill and the organization [[Industrial Workers of the World]] in a song called &quot;If We Unite&quot; on their album ''[[The Human Atom Bombs]]'' from 2001.

*[[Kev Carmody]]'s piece &quot;Comrade Jesus Christ&quot;, includes the line &quot;he'd fight with Joe Hill&quot;. Hill is also referred to in his song &quot;Cannot Buy My Soul&quot;.

*In his book ''An Undividable Glow'' ,&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.fcunitedbook.co.uk/ ''An Undividable Glow'' book by Robert Brady]&lt;/ref&gt; Robert Brady speaks about an area of Manchester, England as Cheetham &quot;Joe&quot; Hill.

*Seattle composer and bandleader [[Wayne Horvitz]] created  a musical tribute for Joe Hill in 2008. ''Joe Hill: 16 Actions for Orchestra, Voice and Soloist'', which premiered at Meany Hall in Seattle, features the Northwest Sinfonia and guest soloists [[Bill Frisell]], [[Robin Holcomb]], [[Danny Barnes]], and Rinde Eckert.

*&quot;Calling Joe Hill&quot; by Ray Hearne is frequently performed by [[Roy Bailey (folk singer)|Roy Bailey]], a British socialist folk singer.

*In 1995 the first &quot;Raise Your Banners&quot; festival of political song was held in [[Sheffield]], inspired by the 80th anniversary of the death of Joe Hill. Sheffield Socialist choir which was formed in 1988 organised the event and performed an arrangement by Nigel Wright of the Earl Robinson song about Joe Hill. Since then the festival has been held roughly every two years, being held in Bradford in November 2007 and 2009.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.raiseyourbanners.org Raise Your Banners site]&lt;/ref&gt;

*Pennsylvania based hardcore band [[Wisdom In Chains]] ended their album ''Everything You Know'' with a young voice reading &quot;Joe Hill's Last Will&quot;.

*[[Otis Gibbs]] made the ''Joe Hill's Ashes'' album in 2010

*Hill's last will is the lyrics to a song entitled ''Good Evening Mr. Q'', appearing in the 2002 album ''Memoirs'' by the Norwegian group [[The 3rd and the Mortal]].

*&quot;Joe Hill's Last Will&quot; is the concluding track on the CD ''Bittersweet Sixteen'' by the Irish-American rock band [[Black 47]]. In the song, lead singer [[Larry Kirwan]] sings the will ''[[a cappella]]''.

*In 1980 [[Posten AB]], the Swedish postal service, issued a Joe Hill postage stamp.  Red on a white background with the lyrics in English &quot;We'll have freedom, love and health/When the grand red flag is flying, In the Workers' Commonwealth.&quot;  The stamp cost [[Swedish krona|SKr]] 1,70 which was the amount for airmail to the United States.{{Citation needed|date=June 2011}}

== References ==
{{reflist|2}}

==Recording of songs==
Cover album of his songs:
*[[Joe Glazer]], ''Songs of Joe Hill,'' [[Smithsonian Folkways]], 1954

== Additional reading ==
*{{cite book| url=http://books.google.com/books?id=wjAMGpqVQA4C&amp;pg=PT33&amp;lpg=PT33&amp;dq=Qw&amp;hl=en&amp;ei=syJZTsDfD5CFsgKW7LWhDA&amp;sa=X&amp;oi=book_result&amp;ct=result&amp;resnum=9&amp;ved=0CGwQ6AEwCA#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false| last=Adler| first=William M.| title=The Man Who Never Died: The Life, Times, and Legacy of Joe Hill, American Labor Icon| publisher=Bloomsbury Publishing | isbn= 9781608192854 }}
*{{cite journal
| last        = Chaplin
| first       = Ralph
| authorlink  = Ralph Chaplin
| date        =
| year        = 1923
| month       = November
| title       = Joe Hill, a Biography
| journal     = [[The Industrial Pioneer]]
| volume      =
| issue       =
| series      =
| pages       = 23–26
| publisher   = General Executive Board, Industrial Workers of the World
| location    = Chicago
| issn        =
| pmid        =
| pmc         =
| doi         =
| bibcode     =
| oclc        =
| id          =
| url         =
| language    =
| format      =
| accessdate  =
| laysummary  =
| laysource   =
| laydate     =
| quote       =
}}
*&quot;The Man Who Never Died,&quot; A Play about Joe Hill, with Notes on Joe Hill and His Times, by [[Barrie Stavis]], New York: Haven Press, 1954. The &quot;notes&quot; are actually a carefully researched, 116 page history of the period, with detailed analysis of the trial of Joe Hill; the notes include photographs of people, events, and documents. The play was produced in New York City off-broadway at the Jan Hus Play House in 1958. The revised play and compressed notes were published in a second version of this book under the same title, published at Cranbury NJ: A.S. Barnes, 1972.
* Davidson, Jared (2011). ''Remains to be Seen: Tracing Joe Hill's ashes in New Zealand''. Wellington: Rebel Press, 2011. ISBN 978-0-473-18927-3
*''Fellow Workers.'' Philips, Utah and Difranco, Ani. Righteous Babe Records, NY, 1999.
*''Joe Hill: IWW Songwriter''. Nolan, Dead &amp; Thompson, Fred. Kersplebedeb. Montreal.
*''Joe Hill—The Man and the Myth''. [[Gibbs Smith]].
*''We Shall Be All: A History of the IWW''.  Melvyn Dubrosky.
*''Where the Fraser River Flows: the IWW in BC''. Mark Leier.
*''Wobblies! A Graphic History of the Industrial Workers of the World.'' Buhle, Paul and Schulman, Nicole, eds.  Verso, NY, 2005.
*''Union Song'' by [[The Nightwatchman]]
*{{cite book
|last= Rosemont
|first= Franklin
|author-link= Franklin Rosemont
|title= Joe Hill: The IWW &amp; the making of a revolutionary workingclass counterculture
|url=
|format=
|accessdate=
|edition=
|year= 2002
|publisher= Charles H. Kerr
|location= Chicago
|isbn= 088286-264-2
|oclc=
|doi=
|bibcode=
|id=
|page=
|pages=
|nopp=
|chapter=
|chapterurl=
|quote=
}}

*{{cite book
 | first = Howard
 | last = Zinn
 | authorlink = Howard Zinn
 | year = 2001
 | month = September
 | title = A People's History of the United States
 | edition = Revised and Updated
 | publisher = HarperCollins Publishers
 | location = New York, NY
 | isbn = 0-06-093731-9 }}

==External links ==
{{Portal box|Organized labour}}
{{wikiquote}}
{{Wikisource author}}
*[http://www.joehill.org/ The Joe Hill Project - University of Utah]
*[http://www.kued.org/productions/joehill/ Site at KUED7 about the PBS Joe Hill documentary from 2000]
*[http://www.folkarchive.de/hill.html The Songs of Joe Hill] at FolkArchive.de
*[http://www.politicalfolkmusic.org/songbook.html/#jhill Lyrics, sheet music, and audio files]{{dead link|date=September 2011}} at politicalfolkmusic.org

{{Persondata
|NAME=Joe Hill
|ALTERNATIVE NAMES=Joel Emmanuel Hägglund
|SHORT DESCRIPTION=labor activist
|DATE OF BIRTH=October 7, 1879
|PLACE OF BIRTH=[[Gävle]] [[Sweden]]
|DATE OF DEATH=November 15, 1915
|PLACE OF DEATH=[[Utah]]
}}
{{DEFAULTSORT:Hill, Joe}}
[[Category:1879 births]]
[[Category:1915 deaths]]
[[Category:People from Gävle]]
[[Category:American folklore]]
[[Category:Hoboes]]
[[Category:Industrial Workers of the World leaders]]
[[Category:American labor unionists]]
[[Category:American people of Swedish descent]]
[[Category:History of Utah]]
[[Category:People executed for murder]]
[[Category:People executed by firing squad]]
[[Category:Joan Baez songs]]
[[Category:20th-century executions by the United States]]
[[Category:People executed by Utah]]
[[Category:Executed American people]]
[[Category:Swedish people executed abroad]]
[[Category:Deaths by firearm in Utah]]
[[Category:People convicted of murder by Utah]]
[[Category:Swedish emigrants to the United States]]

{{Link GA|no}}
[[ca:Joe Hill]]
[[da:Joe Hill]]
[[de:Joe Hill]]
[[es:Joe Hill]]
[[eo:Joe Hill]]
[[fa:جو هیل]]
[[fr:Joe Hill (chanteur)]]
[[it:Joe Hill]]
[[hu:Joe Hill]]
[[no:Joe Hill]]
[[nn:Joe Hill]]
[[pl:Joe Hill]]
[[pt:Joe Hill]]
[[ro:Joe Hill]]
[[ru:Джо Хилл]]
[[fi:Joe Hill]]
[[sv:Joe Hill]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
