<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="21099419" ns="0" title="List of Hollyoaks characters (1997)"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{DISPLAYTITLE:List of ''Hollyoaks'' characters (1997)}}
{{HOMinor}}
The following is a list of characters that first appeared in the [[Channel 4]] [[soap opera]] ''[[Hollyoaks]]'' in [[1997]], by order of first appearance.

==Lewis Richardson==
{{Infobox soap character 2
|series= Hollyoaks
|name=Lewis Richardson
|portrayer=[[Ben Hull]]
|creator=[[Phil Redmond]]
|years=1997–2001
|first=1997
|last=2001
|death=October 2001
|father=[[Dennis Richardson (Hollyoaks)|Dennis Richardson]]
|mother=[[Helen Cunningham]]
|sisters=[[Mandy Richardson]]
|halfbrothers=[[Tom Cunningham]]
|nieces=[[Grace Hutchinson]]&lt;br&gt;Ella Richardson
|spinoffs = ''[[Hollyoaks: Movin' On]]'' (2001)
}}

'''Lewis Richardson''' was the older brother of [[Mandy Richardson]] and son of [[Helen Cunningham]] from her first marriage.

Lewis first arrived in Hollyoaks as part of the Richardson family, and was protective over his sister Mandy after the pair used to receive abuse from their father Dennis. Lewis moved in to a flat above the Video Shop with his friends [[Jude Cunningham|Jude]] and [[Dawn Cunningham]]. Lewis than briefly dated Jude but ended it with her after discovering from Benny about Jude’s criminal activities. Shocking news came for Lewis when he discovered that his sister Mandy has gone missing and Lewis and his father began to search for her. Lewis began to panic with the possibility that Mandy had committed suicide, but fortunately, Lewis found Mandy alive in a hospital, and rushed to her bedside. Lewis was devastated when Mandy confessed that their father [[Dennis Richardson (Hollyoaks)|Dennis]] had raped her. Lewis supported Mandy, as the pair reported the incident to the police and Dennis was arrested. Lewis took care of Mandy and helped her through her trial, as their father was found guilty and was sentence for seven years.

Lewis than began to have an affair with [[Ruth Osborne]], but they kept it a secret, but it lasted a while when Ruth confessed that she slept with [[Luke Morgan]] and Lewis dumped her. [[Beth Morgan (Hollyoaks)|Beth Morgan]] arrived in Hollyoaks, and Lewis immediately got together with her, but realised Beth was too young for him and he split up with her. Lewis was shocked to discover a pregnancy test kit and assumed it was Mandy's, but it turned out to be his mother [[Helen Cunningham|Helen]]'s, as she revealed she was pregnant with [[Gordon Cunningham]]s child. With Lewis's mother getting married to Gordon, soon Lewis realised that he still had feelings for Ruth and the pair got back together. Lewis was than hailed a hero after rescuing [[Lucy Benson]], with [[Tony Hutchinson]] and Ruth from [[Rob Hawthorne (Hollyoaks)|Rob Hawthorne]]. Lewis than went into business with best friend [[Rory &quot;Finn&quot; Finnigan]], as the pair opened up night-club The Loft. He then started to get friendly with a local club owner Lorraine Wilson, and Lewis started to gamble in her casino. Lewis's life was turned upside down, when he heard that Ruth had an abortion of his baby, and he ended up hitting her.  Lewis started to borrow money off Lorraine, soon he ended up in debt and Lorraine offered Lewis the chance of wiping out his debt, if he sleeps with her. Ruth than discovered Lewis's debts and his stealing, and ended up hitting him and in a rage he hit her back. Lewis and Ruth broke up, and Helen began to get suspicious of Lewis's gambling problems which continued to spiral and, in a moment of madness, he almost hit his own mother. Lewis decided to clear his head out and went to [[Ireland]] and returned as a new man with flash clothes. However, a loan shark came after Lewis, because he took a loan out in Ireland using the name of Ruth's dead husband [[Kurt Benson]]. Lewis was told that the loan must be repaid within thirty days. In order to pay off his debt, Lewis slept with [[Geri Hudson]], and stole the money that she made from a charity event. Soon, Ruth discovered Lewis's debts and persuaded Tony to buy Lewis out of The Loft, thus severing all links with him.

In the late night series ''[[Hollyoaks: Movin' On]]'', Lewis tried to persuade Ruth to get back with him, but Ruth got angry when she discovered that Lewis used Kurt’s name for his debts. Lewis than went to Ruth’s flat and tried to force himself on her, and Ruth told him that he was just like his father, which encouraged Lewis to beat her up bad and left Ruth for dead. Lewis felt guilty for what he had done so he took an overdose of pills and later died in hospital. With early influences of his fathers violence towards his family, Lewis never wanted to be anything like his father, but towards the end he realised that he's just like him and couldn't do anything about it. Lewis left a devastated mother behind and a sister who found it hard to understand how the person who had protected her against their father could ever hurt another woman.

On his character's decision to commit suicide Ben Hull said &quot;Lewis's greatest fear was that one day he would become like his father, alcoholic and abusive - and he has.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title=TV PREVIEW; Ben and gone Hollyoaks suicide was 'hardest role'.|url=http://www.thefreelibrary.com/TV+PREVIEW%3b+Ben+and+gone+Hollyoaks+suicide+was+'hardest+role'.-a078946029|accessdate=3 September 2011|newspaper=[[Sunday Mail (Scotland)]]|date=7 October 2001}}&lt;/ref&gt; The [[Daily Record (Scotland)|Daily Record]] initially described him as a &quot;nice bloke&quot; but later commented on Lewis saying &quot;He's just turned from one of the most easy-going blokes around into a woman-beater. Yep, when he finds out Ruth has aborted the baby, he hits her. Not a good move at all. It might be Ruth, but we can't condone this, can we? I'd smash both their heads together, the rotten pair.&quot; and described the storyline as a cracker.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=FILM of the week.|url=http://www.thefreelibrary.com/FILM+of+the+week.-a060428177| work=[[Daily Record (Scotland){{!}}Daily Record]]|publisher=[[Trinity Mirror]]|date=20 February 1999|accessdate=5 September 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |last=Merle |first=Brown|title=Soap watch; Susannah does the rounds with Darren |url=http://www.thefreelibrary.com/Soap+watch%3b+Susannah+does+the+rounds+with+Darren.-a062477826| work=[[Daily Record (Scotland){{!}}Daily Record]]|publisher=[[Trinity Mirror]]|date=3 June 2000|accessdate=26 August 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;  The [[Sunday Mercury]] described him as a &quot;wheeler-dealer&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title=Hollyoaks stars who turn into neighbours.|url=http://www.thefreelibrary.com/Hollyoaks+stars+who+turn+into+neighbours.-a060743324|accessdate=2 September 2011|newspaper=[[Sunday Mercury]]|date=8 November 1998}}&lt;/ref&gt; He was nominated for Best villain in 2002 at the [[British Soap Awards]]..&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last=Welsh|first=Dingle|title=British Soap Awards 2002: Nominations|url=http://www.digitalspy.co.uk/tv/feature/a7412/british-soap-awards-2002-nominations.html|work=[[Digital Spy]]|publisher=[[Hachette Filipacchi]]|date=16 May 2002|accessdate=20 September 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

{{-}}

==Jill Patrick==
{{Infobox soap character 2
|series= Hollyoaks
|name=Jill Patrick
|portrayer=Lynda Rooke
|creator=[[Phil Redmond]]
|years=1997–2000
|first=1997
|last=2000
|death=2000
|occupation= Barmaid
|family=
|husband= [[Jack Osborne]] 
|daughters= [[Gina Patrick]]&lt;br&gt; [[Katie Patrick]]
|sons= [[Sol Patrick]]
}}

'''Jill Osborne''' (previously '''Patrick''') is a [[fictional character]] from the long-running [[Channel 4]] [[soap opera]] ''[[Hollyoaks]]'', played by Lynda Rooke. She first appeared in 1997 and left in 2000. She appears as a new barmaid and arrives with her children [[Kate Patrick|Kate]], [[Gina Patrick|Gina]] and [[Sol Patrick|Sol]]. She and [[Jack Osborne]], her boss, soon begin a relationship, eventually getting married. The marriage goes well, despite a feud between the Patrick children and the Osborne children. Sol and Gina discover that they are not Jill's biological children. Gina goes missing and Sol and Jill go looking for her in a car he has stolen. He crashs it, almost killing Jill. He spends time in a [[Her Majesty's Young Offender Institution|Young Offenders Institute]], and eventually forgives Jill for hiding the truth from him for so long. Jill is devastated to find out she has a brain tumour and later informs her family. She makes Jack agree to look after her children when she dies. Jill later dies and Jack keeps his promise and cares for her children, helping Sol flee from the police abroad. Gina later leaves ''Hollyoaks'' to live in China and work at an orphanage to make her mother proud. The ''[[Daily Record (Scotland)|Daily Record]]'' commented on the character's death saying &quot;When there's a problem with a character in Hollyoaks, they just kill them off.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title=Television: Soap watch; Fight to death in Hollyoaks.|url=http://www.thefreelibrary.com/Television%3a+Soap+watch%3b+Fight+to+death+in+Hollyoaks.-a071440733|accessdate=5 September 2011|newspaper=[[Daily Record (Scotland)]]|date=10 March 2001}}&lt;/ref&gt; 
{{-}}

==References==
{{reflist}}

==External links==
{{Hollyoaks}}
{{Hollyoaks characters}}

[[Category:Fictional characters introduced in 1997|*, Hollyoaks]]
[[Category:Hollyoaks characters|*, 1997]]
[[Category:Lists of minor fictional characters|Hollyoaks, 1997]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
