<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="21117728" ns="0" title="Attack on Galle Harbour"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Infobox Military Conflict
|conflict=Attack on Galle Harbour
|partof=the [[Sri Lankan civil war]]
|image=
|caption= 
|date=October 18, 2006
|place=[[Galle]], [[Sri Lanka]]
|casus=
|territory=
|result=Disputed 
|combatant1=[[Image:Coat of arms of Sri Lanka.svg|18px]] [[Sri Lanka Navy]]
|combatant2= 
|commander1= Commodore [[Manil Mendis]]
|commander2=Unknown
|strength1=Unknown 
|strength2=15 in 5 boats
|casualties1=3 Naval vessels damaged 1 sailor and 1 civilian killed, 12 sailors, 14 civilians wounded (according to the Sri Lanka Navy)&lt;ref name=&quot;guardian&quot;&gt;{{cite news |first= |last= |title=Rebel suicide blasts hit Sri Lankan resort|url=http://www.guardian.co.uk/world/2006/oct/18/travelnews.srilanka|work=[[The Guardian]]|date=2006-10-19|accessdate=2009-01-17}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;br&gt;
3 Naval gun boats destroyed (according to the South Asia Analysis Group) &lt;ref name = SAAG&gt;{{cite news |first= |last= |title=WHY LTTE ATTACKED GALLE NAVAL BASE AND HARBOUR?|url=http://www.southasiaanalysis.org/%5Cpapers20%5Cpaper1997.html|work=SouthAsiaAnalysisGroup|date=2006-10-19|accessdate=2009-01-16}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|casualties2= 5 boats (3 exploded), 9+ killed (according to the SL Military)&lt;ref name=&quot;guardian&quot;/&gt;
|notes=
}} 
{{Campaignbox Sri Lankan Civil War}}
'''Attack on Galle Harbour''' &lt;ref name=&quot;BBC&quot;&gt;{{cite news |first= |last= |title=Port hit in S Lanka tourist city|url=http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/south_asia/6061184.stm|work=BBC|date=2006-10-18|accessdate=2009-01-16}}&lt;/ref&gt;
was a [[suicide attack]]&lt;ref name=&quot;guardian&quot;/&gt; carried out by fifteen [[Sea Tigers]] of the [[Liberation Tigers of Tamil Eelam]] (LTTE) on the commercial [[Galle|Galle harbour]] and [[Sri Lanka Navy]] [[Naval base|base]] SLNS ''Dakshina'' in the tourist town of [[Galle]] in southern [[Sri Lanka]]&lt;ref name=&quot;guardian&quot;/&gt;. 

==Attack==
The Navy claimed that at 7.45 a.m. on the October 18, 2006,  five &quot;sea tiger&quot; suicide boats, disguised as fishing boats, the Navy destroyed three suicide boats and the other two approached the Galle harbour and detonated at the entrance. One sailor was killed and 11 were injured. One sailor is missing in action.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.hindu.com/2006/10/19/stories/2006101915420100.htm LTTE attack on Galle repulsed ]&lt;/ref&gt;

The pro-rebel ''TamilNet'' claimed that a 15-member team entered Dakshina in five vessels and attacked four Sri Lankan naval vessels and installations. At least three explosive-laden attack vessels attacked naval crafts, including a tsunami damaged sub chaser and destroyed a Fast Attack Craft and two water jet inshore patrol vessels anchored in the port base. However these have not been substantiated or excepted by the Sri Lankan defence ministry.

There are no [[Sea Tigers|Sea Tiger]] bases close by, it is believed attackers must have travelled a long distance to get to [[Galle]]. Some of the attackers died in the attack, while others escaped into the town - their fate is unknown while the navy carried out search operations.

The defence ministry said two people had been killed, one of them a sailor. At least 26 others, civilians among them, had been wounded, a statement said. &lt;ref name=&quot;BBC&quot;/&gt;

==Aftermath==
The Sri Lankan government respond with airstriks in to rebel territory. A Riot began in the Galle, but was stopped when the police imposed a curfew in the area. [[Commodore (rank)|Commodore]] Manil Mendis, Commander of the Southern Naval Area was Court-martial and found guilty of two counts for not taking adequate precautions and counter-measures relating to the incident.&lt;ref&gt;[http://sundaytimes.lk/070128/News/120news.html Court-martial of Southern Naval Area Commander ]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://sundaytimes.lk/070225/News/116news.html Court Martialled Navy officer to appeal]&lt;/ref&gt;

==See also==
* [[Galle]]

==References==
{{Reflist}}

{{coord missing|Sri Lanka}}

[[Category:Eelam War IV]]
[[Category:Naval battles involving Sri Lanka]]
[[Category:History of Sri Lanka]]
[[Category:2006 in Sri Lanka]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
