<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="2114809" ns="0" title="Reno High School"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Infobox school
| coordinates = {{Coord|39.517464|-119.828081}}
| image= [[File:RHS Logo.jpg|thumb|Unofficial Reno High Logo]]
| image_caption = RHS logo
| imagesize =
| name=  Reno High School
| native_name=
| latin_name=
| motto =
| established =  1879
| type =   [[Public school (government funded)|Public]] [[Secondary school|secondary]]
| endowment =
| staff =
| faculty =
| Head teacher =
| schoolmaster =
| principal = Principal Robert Sullivan
| enrollment = 1750 (2009-10)
| students =
| city =  Reno
| state = Nevada
| country =  United States
| free_label =  Campus surroundings
| free  =   Suburban
| colors =  Red and blue
| mascot =   Huskies
| affiliations =
| information =
| website =  http://www.rhshuskies.com
| footnotes =
}}

'''Reno High School''' (RHS) is a public [[secondary school]] in [[Reno, Nevada]] that is a part of the [[Washoe County School District]]. The school mascot is the Husky, and the school's colors are red and blue. Their teams are known as the &quot;Reno Huskies.&quot;

==History==
Reno High was the first high school in Reno, which is celebrated by its well-known motto: &quot;Reno High-- older than Reno&quot;. High school students in Reno were originally taught in the basement of a building on the corner of First and Virginia streets, on the future site of the [[Mapes Hotel]].  In 1869 students were moved to a one-room school, and in 1879, due to Reno's expanding population, a larger high school, called &quot;Central School,&quot; built near Arlington and Fourth Streets.  This school was commonly referred to as &quot;Reno High School&quot; and 1879 is the generally accepted date of the school's founding.  In 1910 a fire in the chemistry lab destroyed the school's main building.  The school was rebuilt in downtown Reno in 1912, at a site now occupied by the Old Sundowner Casino.{{Citation needed|date=September 2007}}  The architecture of the 1912 campus closely resembled that of present-day Mt. Rose elementary school at Lander Street and La Rue Avenue, and McKinley School on Riverside Drive.

In 1951, Reno High moved to its current location on Booth and Foster streets, south of the [[Truckee River]] and [[Idlewild Park]]. The {{convert|71|acre|abbr=on}} campus is less than {{convert|200|yd|abbr=on}} from the Truckee River.

==Campus==
Reno High has a large campus at the corner of Booth Street and Foster Drive in the city's older southwest neighborhood district. Reno High occupies a two-story brick building with architecture that is unique among Washoe County schools. The Reno High campus is within {{convert|200|yd}} of the Truckee River, which receives its water flow from alpine Lake Tahoe.

Reno High boasts {{convert|71|acre|abbr=on}} of campus space, large green areas, a unique student quad, modern football/baseball/tennis and track and field facilities,the large Kahl Fieldhouse, and many tennis courts.  A distinctive red arch brick structure adorns its main entrance, which sits behind a circular driveway that has a large newly renovated {{convert|50|ft|abbr=on}} tall brick &quot;R&quot; on the grass in the center. The halls covered with yellow tile, are designated &quot;R,&quot; &quot;E,&quot; &quot;N,&quot; &quot;O,&quot; and &quot;HI,&quot; which gives the school's corridors a room-numbering scheme.  In the past several years blue awnings have been added to shade south sun-facing classrooms.  In testament to a long history and generations of former students, Reno High is unusual among high schools in having an alumni center building on the Reno High campus.  The large round brick building was completed in January 2000, and houses a large collection of yearbooks, memorabilia, and school artifacts, including the 1879 school class bell.

The Link Piazzo Alumni Center is open most Saturdays from 10:00 a.m. to 1:00 p.m., and for special events, and the amount of unique RHS school exhibits continues to grow as the Alumni Center becomes better known in the state of Nevada. The RHS principal is Mr. Robert Sullivan. Reno High does well academically, and was ranked in the top 400 high schools nationally in 2004, 2005, 2006, 2007 and 2008 by [[Time Magazine]].{{Citation needed|date=March 2008}}

==Extracurricular activities==
===Athletics===
Reno has won numerous state championships this decade. The boys' cross country team has been most dominant, winning 11 state championships (5 on them being consecutive).  The girls' basketball team won the State Championship in 2001.  The football team won the state title in 2003, the baseball team won in 2004 and the boys basketball team won the championship in 2006, knocking off North Las Vegas' Rancho High School.  The Huskies compete in the [[Sierra League (Nevada)|Sierra League]] of the [[Northern Nevada 4A Region]], which is the large-school level. Since 2003, the Reno High boys' sports varsity teams have won
Nevada state championships in football, basketball, baseball, track and field,
swimming, diving, and snow skiing. On Friday, February 22, 2008, the Reno Huskies defeated Cheyenne High of Las Vegas 76 to 72 for their second state basketball championship in the past three seasons. The Huskies have won at least one state championship in 7 different sports, in every year from 2002 to 2008.  Men's soccer at Reno High School has been a sport with controversy and some students  feel soccer has been notorious for the lack of acknowledgment it receives from the school's athletic department.

*Reno's school fight song is &quot;The Red and the Blue.&quot;{{Citation needed|date=February 2007}}
With the goal before you,
Red and the Blue,
now all together, smash
them and go through.
Rah! Rah! Rah!

Against the men from Reno
fight must they show.
Three cheers for Reno-
the Red and Blue.
Red and Blue!
Reno! Huskies! Raaaaah! Oy!

*Reno High football kicker placekicker [[Dirk Borgognone]] set the world record for the longest high school football [[Field goal (football)|field goal]] in 1986. The field goal is the second-longest in all of organized football at any level, just short of [[Ove Johansson]]'s 69-yarder in 1976, for NAIA school Abilene Christian.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.nflhs.com/news/features/Legends_DirkBorgognone%20_11282005_lcb.asp NFLHS.COM - Legends of HS Football: Dirk Borgognone&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;
*Reno High cross country runner Marie(Mel) Lawrence holds the U.S. high school record in the 2,000 m and 3,000 m steeplechase.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.eliterunning.com/features/38/ EliteRunning.com | Interview with Marie Lawrence&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;

===Speech &amp; Debate===
*Reno High School has a large and successful speech and debate team.  The team placed first in the Sagebrush District (covering Northern Nevada) every year from 1996 to 2010 and won Nevada state championships in 2000, 2006 and 2007.  The Reno High School Speech and Debate Team participates in the following events: Lincoln Douglass, Policy, Public Forum, Congress, Dramatic Interpretation, Humorous Interpretation, Original Oratory, Impromptu, Story Telling, Foreign Extemporaneous, and Domestic Extemporaneous.  The current teacher of the class, and coach of the team is Ms. Christy Briggs.  The team also puts on an annual Night of Comedy and Drama in the school theater.  The team also hosts a tournament at Reno High School every year.  The participants of this tournament are teams from the Sagebrush District.  The team sends members to the National Debate tournament yearly, where many often do well.

===Bands===
*Marching Band
*Wind Ensemble
*Jazz Band
*Concert Band
*Pep Band
*Winter Percussion
*Guard

The Reno High School Band program is currently directed by Mr. Timothy Wood and can be found at http://renohsband.org/. The program is successful in yearly festivals and competitions. The band also has many members who participate in outside of school activities like Honor Band, RYJO, RPYO, Solo and Ensemble, and the Nevada all-state convention.

===Performing Arts===
The Reno High School Theater Program, known as the Booth Street Players, presents 3 to 4 shows a year along with out side school community performances. The Fall production is a play and The Spring production is a musical. Past shows have included ''Little Shop of Horrors'', ''Our Town'', ''Grease'', ''The Boy Friend'', and ''Pippin'' (the last of which included students trained in silk aerial acrobatics).

===Publications===
*''Re-Wa-Ne'' &amp;mdash; school yearbook (the name is a [[portmanteau]] of &quot;REno WAshoe NEvada&quot;){{Citation needed|date=October 2007}}

*''The Red &amp; Blue'' &amp;mdash; monthly school newspaper (Nevada's first high school newspaper){{Citation needed|date=October 2007}}

*''The Mirror'' &amp;mdash; school literary magazine (publicaten ceased in 2008)

===Junior Reserve Officers' Training Corps===
* The Junior Reserve Officers' Training Corps (JROTC) program at Reno High School is one of the oldest in the nation, founded in 1919 after the passage of the [[National Defense Act of 1916]].{{Citation needed|date=October 2007}}

* The current instructors are Sergeant Major (Ret) Ronald Rillon, Sergeant Major (Ret) Rick Camacho, and Lieutenant Colonel (Ret) Scott Maryott.&lt;ref&gt;[http://renohighrotc.tripod.com/index.html Reno High JROTC Leadership Program&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;

==Notable alumni==
*[[Walter S. Baring, Jr.]] ('29), former congressman (D-NV)
*[[Josh Barrett]] ('03) - [[NFL]] professional American football player, with the [[Denver Broncos]]
*[[Shawn Boskie]] ('86) - former major league baseball pitcher
*[[Frederic Joseph DeLongchamps]] (1900) - architect
*[[Frank Fahrenkopf]] ('57)- political adviser to President Reagan,former chairman of the [[Republican National Party]]
*[[Ray Handley]] ('62)- former professional American football player and [[NFL]] coach
*[[Pat McCarran|Patrick Anthony McCarran]] (1897) - former United States senator (D-NV)
*[[Link Piazzo]] ('37) - Philanthropist
*[[John Savage (baseball)|John Savage]], [[UCLA Bruins baseball]] head coach&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.uclabruins.com/sports/m-basebl/mtt/savage_john00.html #22 John Savage], ''UCLABruins.com'', 2010&lt;/ref&gt;
*[[Dawn Wells]] ('56) - actress,who starred in [[Gilligan's Island]] as [[Mary Ann]]
*[[Sean &quot;Hollywood&quot; Hamilton]] (Freshman only) - National Radio Personality

==References==
{{reflist}}

==External links==
*[http://www.rhshuskies.com/ Official school site]
*[http://www.renohighalum.com/ Alumni association] (Alumni Center Web page)
*[http://www.washoe.k12.nv.us/ Washoe County School District]

[[Category:High schools in Reno, Nevada]]
[[Category:Reno High School alumni| ]]
[[Category:Educational institutions established in 1879]]
[[Category:Washoe County School District]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
