<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="21154656" ns="0" title="Daniel Dantas"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">[[Image:Daniel Dantas.jpg|thumb|Daniel Valente Dantas.]]
'''Daniel Valente Dantas''' is a [[Brazil]]ian [[banker]] and financier, founder of [[Opportunity Asset Management]] in 1994. Opportunity Group lead an international private sector partnership that bought up a large chunk of the Brazilian telecoms sector in 1997, when this sector was privatized.&lt;ref name=&quot;Reuters&quot;&gt;{{cite web | url = http://www.reuters.com/article/2008/12/02/brazil-banker-sentence-idUSN0225856520081202 | title = Prominent Brazil financier gets 10 years in prison | publisher = Reuters | date = December 2, 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt; On December 2, 2008 Daniel Dantas was convicted of  an attempt to bribe police officers; this is related to a police investigation into [[money laundering]]. He has appealed against his conviction.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url = http://www.economist.com/world/americas/displaystory.cfm?story_id=12725169 | title = Fall of an opportunist | publisher = The Economist | date = December 4, 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Dantas was arrested twice by [[Protógenes Queiroz]], police officer who investigated Daniel Dantas on ''Satiagraha Operation'', in early July 2008, but each time released almost immediately. The President of the [[Supreme Federal Court (Brazil)|Supreme Court]] [[Gilmar Mendes]] gave Dantas two [[habeas corpus]] in less than two days.

Daniel Dantas was finally convicted to ten years imprisonment in December 2008 for attempting to bribe a police officer.&lt;ref name=&quot;Reuters&quot;/&gt;

National Council of Justice: Conduct of Judge De Sanctis in Satyagraha is incompatible with a judge’s behavior and with the due process.
On June 7th, 2011 the National Council of Justice (CNJ) unanimously recognized that Judge Fausto de Sanctis, at the time the head judge of the 6th Criminal Court of São Paulo, intentionally disobeyed the orders of the Federal Supreme Court (STF), when he ordered the detention of Daniel Dantas in Operation Satyagraha. 
The judges of the CNJ followed the vote of reporting Judge Morgana Richa, who determined that De Sanctis’s conduct is incompatible with that of a judge, and that he would only escape proper punishment through the lack of a legal provision. 

STF voids Satyagraha for irregularities.
Also on the 7th June 2011, the Higher Court of Justice (STJ) accepted the opinion of the Federal Public Prosecutor’s Office and voided the criminal action originating from Operation Satyagraha, for its irregularities. 
According to the President of the 5th Bench of the Higher Court of Justice, Jorge Mussi, “the involvement of ABIN (Brazilian Intelligence Agency) was demonstrated in a document in which the Federal Police ordered the internal investigation of irregularities in the operation”. 
The scheme of informal investigation set up in Satyagraha represents, for Mussi, “a model of investigation more suited to the secret police, beyond the most basic rules of the Democratic State of Law”. 

== Operation Satyagraha ==
In July 2008, several [[TrueCrypt]]-secured hard drives were seized from Daniel Dantas, who was suspected of financial crimes. The Brazilian National Institute of Criminology (INC) tried for five months (without success) to obtain access to TrueCrypt-protected disks owned by the banker, after which they enlisted the help of the [[FBI]]. The FBI used [[dictionary attack]]s against Dantas' disks for over 12 months, but were still unable to decrypt them.&lt;ref name=&quot;Dantas&quot;&gt;{{cite web | first = John | last = Leyden | title = Brazilian banker's crypto baffles FBI | url = http://www.theregister.co.uk/2010/06/28/brazil_banker_crypto_lock_out/ | publisher = The Register | date = June 28, 2010 | accessdate = August 13, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==References==
{{Reflist}}

{{Persondata &lt;!-- Metadata: see [[Wikipedia:Persondata]]. --&gt;
| NAME              = Dantas, Daniel
| ALTERNATIVE NAMES =
| SHORT DESCRIPTION =
| DATE OF BIRTH     =
| PLACE OF BIRTH    =
| DATE OF DEATH     =
| PLACE OF DEATH    =
}}
{{DEFAULTSORT:Dantas, Daniel}}
[[Category:Brazilian bankers]]
[[Category:Living people]]


{{Brazil-business-bio-stub}}

[[es:Daniel Dantas]]
[[it:Daniel Dantas]]
[[pt:Daniel Dantas (banqueiro)]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
