<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="211843" ns="0" title="Culture of Israel"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">[[Image:HoraIsraeliDance.jpg|right|thumb|250px|Dancing the [[Hora (dance)|Hora]], 1948]]
[[File:Jerusalem Theater night.jpg|thumb|200px|[[Jerusalem Theater]] at night]]
[[File:Judaica.jpg|200px|thumb|Jewish ritual objects]]
The '''culture of Israel''' developed long before the [[Declaration of Independence (Israel)|foundation of]] the [[State of Israel]] in [[1948]] and combines the heritage of secular and religious lives. Much of the diversity in Israel's culture comes from the diversity of its population. Originating in the levant and around the world, [[Aliyah|immigrants]] arrived with diverse cultural backgrounds and contributed to the development of Israeli culture, which follows cultural trends and changes across the globe. Israeli culture also reflects [[Jewish history]] in the diaspora, especially the ideology of the [[Zionist]] movement beginning in the late nineteenth century.

Israeli traditions are rooted in a synthesis of ethnic and religious Hebrew Israelite traditions, and Israeli artists continually push the boundaries of their art forms. Through their work, Israel's artists provoke self-reflective and communal examination and inspire social change, while expressing the beauty of the people and the land of Israel.&lt;ref&gt;[http://london.mfa.gov.il/mfm/web/main/document.asp?SubjectID=13625&amp;MissionID=34&amp;LanguageID=0&amp;StatusID=0&amp;DocumentID=-1 Cultural Affairs: Introduction] by the Cultural Affairs Department at the Embassy of Israel in London&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Zionism]] is partly based on [[religious tradition]]. It links the [[Jew]]ish people to the [[Land of Israel]] where the concept of Jewish nationhood first evolved between 1200 BCE and 70 CE (end of the [[Second Temple]] era). However, modern Zionism evolved as mainly secular.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.zagraevsky.com/jews_english.htm Dr. Sergey Zagraevsky. The Past, the Present and the Future of the Jewish nation]&lt;/ref&gt; It mostly began as a response to the widespread [[antisemitism]] toward European Judaism. It constituted a branch of the broader phenomenon of modern nationalism. Though Zionist groups were first competing with other Jewish political movements, Zionism became an equivalent to political [[Judaism]] during and after the [[Holocaust]].

==Overview==
Israeli culture is heterogeneous and dynamic. With a diverse population of immigrants from five continents and more than 100 countries, and significant subcultures like the Palestinians, the Russians, and the Orthodox, each with its own newspapers and cultural networks, Israeli culture is extremely varied. [[Tel Aviv]] is considered the hub of secular culture, although many leading cultural institutions are located in [[Jerusalem]].  The [[Israel Philharmonic Orchestra]] plays at venues throughout the country and abroad. The [[Israel Broadcasting Authority]] has a symphony orchestra that performs in Israel and around the world, and almost every city has its own orchestras, many of the musicians hailing from the former [[Soviet Union]]. Israeli dance companies, among them the [[Batsheva Dance Company|Batsheva]] and [[Bat Dor]], are highly acclaimed in the dance world. Theater is also an important facet of the culture of Israel. The national theater, [[Habima Theatre|Habima]] was established in 1917. Other theater companies include the [[Cameri Theater]], [[Beit Lessin Theater]], [[Gesher Theater]] (which performs in Hebrew and Russian), [[Haifa Theater]] and [[Beersheba Theater]]. 

[[Safed]], [[Jaffa]] and [[Ein Hod]] are home to artist colonies. Major art museums operate in  [[Tel Aviv]], [[Herzliya]] and [[Jerusalem]], as well as in many towns and kibbutzim. Jerusalem's [[Israel Museum]] has a special pavilion showcasing the [[Dead Sea scrolls]] and a large collection of Jewish religious art, Israeli art, sculptures and Old Masters paintings. Newspapers appear in dozens of languages, and every city and town publishes a local newsletter.

==Hebrew language ==
[[File:Ulpan 1955.jpg|thumb|250px|Ulpan in [[Dimona]], 1955]]
As new immigrants arrived, Hebrew language instruction was of utmost importance.  [[Eliezer Ben-Yehuda]], who founded the Hebrew Language Committee, coined thousands of new words and concepts based on Biblical, Talmudic and other sources, to cope with the needs and demands of life in the 20th century. Learning Hebrew became a national goal, employing the slogan &quot;Yehudi, daber ivrit&quot; (&quot;Jew - speak Hebrew&quot;). Special schools for Hebrew language learning, ''[[ulpan]]im'',  were set up all over the country.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.jewishvirtuallibrary.org/jsource/Society_&amp;_Culture/culture1.html Culture in Israel]&lt;/ref&gt;

==Cultural influences ==
The development of Israeli culture was very much influenced by [[aliyah]] or immigration waves and by [[Jews]] in the Holy Land. The Jewish pioneers who came to the Holy Land hailed from many countries and brought with them the cultures of their lands. [[Russian culture]] had an undeniable impact on the arts in Israel. [[Habima Theatre]] brought its Russian and [[Yiddish]] roots to the country.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.jafi.org.il/education/culture/onisraeli/14-west.html On Israeli culture]&lt;/ref&gt;  Local Arab culture had an influence on dance, language and mannerisms. British culture was introduced during the period of the [[British Mandate of Palestine]]. German culture left its mark on the [[architecture of Israel]], with many buildings in [[Tel Aviv]] and other cities inspired by the [[Bauhaus]] movement.

Especially celebrated are works from the 1950s and the 1960s when art in [[modern Hebrew]] was created, in contrast to the poetry written previously, like that of [[Nathan Alterman]], [[Avraham Shlonsky]], and [[Leah Goldberg]], or the literary style of one of the greatest Hebrew authors, [[Shmuel Yosef Agnon|S. Y. Agnon]]. The central figures of the modern poetry of the first decades were [[Yehuda Amichai]], [[Nathan Zach]] and [[David Avidan]]. In the field of literature, most notable were [[Moshe Shamir]] and [[Aharon Megged]] along with [[Amos Oz]], [[A. B. Yehoshua]], [[Meir Shalev]], and many more.
[[File:Diván Este-Oeste 2005.jpg|thumb|right|left|280px|Daniel Barenboim conducting the [[West-Eastern Divan]], a project bringing together Israeli and Arab musicians]]
After the founding of the state in 1948, immigrants rushed to Israel from many different countries, but their influence on the Israeli culture happened only gradually and relatively. In the 1950s, the prominent effects on Israel were the cultures of England, France, and the United States. Since the early 1960s and more prominently in the 1970s, additional dominant effects began to appear. In theater, the Russian dominancy began to weaken gradually and other effects began to permeate such as the European theater of [[Bertolt Brecht]]. In music, in spite of the continuance of the French effect they began to weaken. Instead, a wide variety of effects, such as British popular music (and in particular [[The Beatles]]), Greek music, and a more updated Russian culture influenced Israeli culture.

The culture of the [[Mizrahi Jews|Jewish refugees from the Arab states]] has had a considerable impact on music and film. The comedy troupe [[HaGashash HaHiver]] and [[bourekas]] films offered a satiric look at Mizrahi mannerisms and perceived predominance of Ashkenazi culture.  In popular music, the main influences were from [[UK|Britain]], Europe, and South America; in addition to those, Turkish, Greek, and Arab music gradually became more important. Since the inauguration  of [[Israel]]i [[commercial broadcasting|commercial]] television, high-quality local drama developed, adding another dimension to Israel Television, which had previously relied on imported series from England and the United States.

==Melting pot approach==
The first Israeli prime minister, David Ben Gurion, led a trend to blend the many immigrants who arrived at the first years of the state from Europe, North Africa, and Asia into one melting pot that will not differentiate between the older residents of the country and the new immigrants. The original purpose was to unite the immigrants with the veteran Israelis for the creation of a common Israeli culture in order to build a new nation in the new country.

The two central tools that were destined for this effect were the [[Israel Defense Forces]] and the [[education]] system.  Israel Defense Forces—by the means of its transformation to the army of the nation which would constitute a common ground between all civilians of the country wherever they are. The education system—firstly in the method of unitary education, following the cancellation of the method of the currents in education and uniting the education system under the education laws, in order that different students from different sectors would study together at the same schools. In a gradual process the Israeli society became more [[Pluralism (political philosophy)|pluralistic]] and the melting pot declined with the years.

Some critics of the melting pot consider it to have been a necessity in the first years of the state in order to build a mutual society, but now claim that there is no longer a need for it.  They instead see a need for Israeli society to enable the people to express the differences and the exclusiveness of every stream and sector. Others, mainly [[Mizrahi Jews]] and [[Sh'erit ha-Pletah|Holocaust survivors]] from Europe, criticized the early melting pot process. According to them, they were forced to give up or conceal their original [[Cultural heritage|heritage]] and [[culture]], which they brought from their homelands, and to adopt a new &quot;[[Sabra (person)|Sabra]]&quot; culture. This has been articulated by the Anglo-Jewish writer [[Emanuel Litvinoff]] who lamented the denigration of the Yiddish language and objected to a Zionist 'chauvinism.'

==Literature ==
[[File:David Grossman 2.jpg|thumb|150px|Israeli author [[David Grossman]]]]
The first works of Hebrew literature in Israel were written by immigrant authors rooted in the world and traditions of European Jewry. Yosef Haim Brenner (1881–1921) and Shmuel Yosef Agnon (1888–1970), are considered by many to be the fathers of modern Hebrew literature.&lt;ref name=&quot;focusmm.com&quot;&gt;[http://www.focusmm.com/israel/is_la_01.htm Focus on Israel: Language and Literature in Israel]&lt;/ref&gt;
Brenner, torn between hope and despair, struggled with the reality of the Zionist enterprise in the Land of Israel. Agnon, Brenner's contemporary, fused his knowledge of Jewish heritage with the influence of 19th and early 20th century European literature. He produced fiction dealing with the disintegration of traditional ways of life, loss of faith and the subsequent loss of identity. In 1966, Agnon was co-recipient of the Nobel Prize for Literature.&lt;ref name=&quot;focusmm.com&quot;/&gt;
Native-born writers who published their work in the 1940s and 1950s, often called the &quot;War of Independence generation,&quot; brought a sabra mentality and culture to their writing. S. Yizhar, Moshe Shamir, Hanoch Bartov and Benjamin Tammuz vacillated between individualism and commitment to society and state. In the early 1960s, A.B. Yehoshua, Amos Oz, and Yaakov Shabtai broke away from ideologies to focus on the world of the individual, experimenting with narrative forms and writing styles such as psychological realism, allegory and symbolism. Since the 1980s and early 1990s, Hebrew literature has been widely translated and several Israeli writers have achieved ohya international recognition.&lt;ref name=&quot;focusmm.com&quot;/&gt;

==Visual arts==
[[File:Shrine of the Book.jpg|thumb|200px|[[Shrine of the Book]], [[Israel Museum]], [[Jerusalem]]]]
From the beginning of the 20th century, visual arts in Israel have shown a creative orientation influenced by the encounter between East and West, as well as by the land itself and its development, the character of the cities, and stylistic trends emanating from art centers abroad. In painting, sculpture, photography, and other art forms, the country's varied landscape is the protagonist: the hill terraces and ridges produce special dynamics of line and shape; the foothills of the Negev, the prevailing grayish-green vegetation and the clear luminous light result in distinctive color effects; and the sea and sand affect surfaces. On the whole, local landscapes, concerns, and politics lie at the center of Israeli art and ensure its uniqueness.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.facebook.com/IsraelCulture?v=app_10467688569 '''CultureIL'''- Art - Everything about Israeli Culture and more]&lt;/ref&gt;

The earliest Israeli art movement was the [[Bezalel school]] of the Ottoman and early Mandate period in which artists portrayed both Biblical and Zionist subjects in a style influenced by the European jugendstil (or art nouveau) movement, symbolism, and traditional Persian and Syrian artistry. Israel has a lively gallery scene with galleries ranging form Tel Aviv's contemporary [[Raw Art Gallery]] to Jerusalem's more representational [[Mayanot Gallery]].
==Music==
[[File:Israel Philharmonic Orchestra.jpg|thumb|200px|Israel Philharmonic Orchestra, 2006]]
{{Main|Music of Israel}}
Classical music in Israel has been vibrant since the 1930s when hundreds of music teachers and students, composers, instrumentalists and singers, as well as thousands of music lovers, streamed into the country, driven by the threat of Nazism in Europe. The founding of The Palestine Philharmonic Orchestra (today the Israel Philharmonic Orchestra) 1936, marked the beginning of Israel's classical music scene. In the early 1980s, the New Israeli Opera began staging productions, reviving public enthusiasm for operatic works. The Russian immigration in the 1990s boosted the classical music arena both with new talents and music lovers. The contemporary music scene in Israel is hugely varied, dynamic and eclectic. It spans across all spectrums of musical genres and often fuses many musicals influences ranging from Ethiopian, Middle-Eastern soul, rock, jazz, hip hop, electronic, Arabic, pop and mainstream. Israeli music is versatile and combines elements of both western and eastern music. It tends to be very eclectic and contains a wide variety of influences from the [[Diaspora]] and more modern cultural importation: [[Hassidic]] songs, Asian and Arab pop (especially by Yemenite singers), and [[hip hop music|Israeli hip hop]] or [[heavy metal music|heavy metal]]. Israel is also home to several world-class classical music ensembles such as the [[Israel Philharmonic]] and the [[New Israeli Opera]]. Also popular are various forms of electronic music, including trance, hard-trance, and goa-trance. Notable artists from Israel popular in this field are limited but include the psychedelic trance duo [[Infected Mushroom]].

==Dance==
[[Image:Batsheva Dance Company by David Shankbone.jpg|thumb|150px|[[Batsheva Dance Company]]  co-founded by [[Martha Graham]] and [[Baroness Batsheva De Rothschild]] in 1964]]
Traditional folk dances of Israel include the [[Hora]] and [[Yemenite dance]]. [[Israeli folk dancing]] today is choreographed for recreational and performance dance groups. 

[[Modern dance]] in Israel has won international acclaim. Israeli choreographers, among them  [[Ohad Naharin]] and [[Barak Marshall]] are considered among the most versatile and original international creators working today. Notable Israeli dance companies include the [[Batsheva Dance Company]] and the [[Kibbutz Contemporary Dance Company]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.mfa.gov.il/MFA/MFAArchive/2000_2009/2000/7/Israeli%20Dance%201995-1998 Israeli Dance]&lt;/ref&gt; People come from all over Israel and many other nations for the annual dance festival in [[Karmiel]], held in July. First held in 1988, the Karmiel Dance Festival is the largest celebration of dance in Israel, featuring three or four days and nights of dancing with 5,000 or more dancers and a quarter of a million spectators in the capital of the [[Galilee]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url=http://www.galilee.gov.il/Galil_Eng/Templates/ShowPage.asp?TMID=84&amp;FID=432 | title=Galilee - Culture | publisher=Galilee Development Authority | accessdate=2007-08-06}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url=http://www.dancefest.karmiel.israel.net/ | title=Karmiel Dance Festival | publisher=ACTCOM-Active Communication Ltd. | accessdate=2007-08-06}}&lt;/ref&gt; Begun as an Israeli folk dance event, the festivities now include performances, workshops, and open dance sessions for a variety of dance forms and nationalities.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url=http://www.karmielfestival.co.il/index.php | title=Karmiel Dance Festival | publisher=Karmiel Dance Festival | accessdate=2007-08-06}}&lt;/ref&gt; Choreographer Yonatan Karmon created the Karmiel Dance Festival to continue the tradition of [[Gurit Kadman]]'s [[Dalia, Israel|Dalia]] Festival of Israeli dance, which ended in the 1960s.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.forward.com/articles/in-israel-still-dancing-after-all-these-years/ |title=In Israel, Still Dancing After All These Years |publisher=Forward Association, inc. |date=2004-04-16 |accessdate=2007-08-23 |archiveurl = http://web.archive.org/web/20070929125546/http://www.forward.com/articles/in-israel-still-dancing-after-all-these-years/  |archivedate = 2007-09-29}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.phantomranch.net/folkdanc/teachers/kadman_g.htm |title=Gurit Kadman |publisher=PhantomRanch.net |accessdate=2007-08-06}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Famous companies and choreographers from all over the world have come to Israel to perform and give master classes.  In July 2010, [[Mikhail Baryshnikov]] came to perform in Israel.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.danceinisrael.com/2010/06/mikhail-baryshnikov-and-ana-laguna-to-perform-in-israel/ Mikhail Baryshnikov and Ana Laguna to Perform in Israel]&lt;/ref&gt;

==Theater==
[[File:Habima2.jpg|thumb|250px|Habimah theater]]
The emergence of Hebrew theatre predated the state by nearly 50 years. The first amateur Hebrew theatre group was active in Palestine from 1904-1914. The first professional Hebrew theatre, Habimah, was founded in Moscow in 1917 and moved to Palestine in 1931, where it became the country's national theater.&lt;ref name=&quot;myjewishlearning.com&quot;&gt;[http://www.myjewishlearning.com/culture/2/Theatre_and_Dance/Theatre/Israel.shtml Israeli Theatre: A culmination of foreign and native influences]&lt;/ref&gt; The Ohel Theatre was founded in 1925 as a workers' theatre that explored socialist and biblical themes. The first Hebrew plays revolved around pioneering.  

After 1948, two major motifs were the Holocaust and the Arab-Israeli conflict. Moshe Shamir's ''He Walked in the Fields'' in 1949 was the first produced by a sabra writing about sabras in idiomatic and contemporary Hebrew. In the 1950s, dramatists portrayed the gap between pre-state dreams and disillusionment. Other plays pitted  native Israelis against Holocaust survivors.&lt;ref name=&quot;myjewishlearning.com&quot;/&gt; Beginning in the 1960s, [[Hanoch Levin]] wrote 56 plays and political satires. During the 1970s, Israeli theatre became more critical, highlighting extreme images of Israeli identity, such as the muscleman versus the spiritual Jew. In the 1980s, Yehoshua Sobol explored Israeli-Jewish identity issues. Today, Israeli theatre is extremely diverse in content and style, and half of all plays are local productions.&lt;ref name=&quot;myjewishlearning.com&quot;/&gt;

==Cinema==
[[File:Doron Cinema Center in Tel Aviv.jpg|thumb|The Doron Cinema Center in [[Tel Aviv]]]]
{{Main|Cinema of Israel}}
Filmmaking in Israel has undergone major developments since its inception in the 1950s. The first features produced and directed by Israelis such as &quot;Hill 24 Does Not Answer,&quot; and &quot;They Were Ten,&quot; tended, like Israeli literature of the period, to be cast in the heroic mold. Some recent films remain deeply rooted in the Israeli experience, dealing with such subjects as Holocaust survivors and their children (Gila Almagor's &quot;The Summer of Aviya&quot; and its sequel, &quot;Under the Domim Tree&quot;) and the travails of new immigrants (&quot;Sh'hur&quot;, directed by Hannah Azoulai and Shmuel Hasfari, &quot;late Marriage&quot; directed by Dover Koshashvili). Others reflect a more predominant trend towards the present Israeli reality, whether dealing with the Israel-Arab and the Jews-Arabs confrontations (Eran Riklis's &quot;The Lemon Tree&quot;, Scandar Copti and Yaron Shani's &quot;Ajami&quot;), the military aspects in the Israelis life (Joseph Cedar's &quot;Beaufort&quot;, Samuel Maoz's &quot;Lebanon&quot;, Eytan Fox 's &quot;Yossi and Jagger&quot;) or set in the context of universalist, somewhat alienated and hedonistic society (Eytan Fox's &quot;A Siren's Song&quot; and &quot;The Bobble&quot;, Ayelet Menahemi and Nirit Yaron's &quot;Tel Aviv Stories&quot;). The Israeli film industry continues to gain worldwide recognition through International awards nominations. For three years consecutively Israeli films have been nominated for an Academy Award, namely, &quot;Beaufort&quot; (2008), &quot;Waltz with Bashir&quot; (2009) and &quot;Ajami&quot; (2010).

==Cuisine==
[[File:Hummuswithpinenuts.jpg|thumb|200px|Hummus garnished with pine nuts]]
The heterogeneous nature of culture in Israel is also manifested in [[Israeli cuisine]], a diverse combination of local ingredients and dishes and immigrant dishes from around the world. Since the establishment of the State of Israel in 1948, and particularly since the late 1970s, an Israeli [[fusion cuisine]] has developed with the adoption and continued adaption of elements of various Jewish styles of cuisine including [[Mizrahi]], [[Sephardic]], [[Yemenite Jews|Yemeni Jewish]] and [[Ashkenazi]]&lt;ref name=region&gt;[http://www.nytimes.com/1994/07/20/garden/a-region-s-tastes-commingle-in-israel.html?pagewanted=all A region's tastes commingle]&lt;/ref&gt; and many foods traditionally eaten in the Middle East.&lt;ref name=Roden2&gt;Roden, ''The Book of Jewish Food'', pp 202-207&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=Gur&gt;Gur,''The Book of New Israeli Food''&lt;/ref&gt;
==Fashion==
Israel has become an international center of fashion and design.&lt;ref name=&quot;T+L1&quot;&gt;[http://www.travelandleisure.com/articles/newsflash-whats-new-in-tel-aviv What’s New in Tel Aviv], by David Kaufman, March 2008.&lt;/ref&gt; Tel Aviv has been called the “next hot destination” for fashion.&lt;ref name=&quot;JewishWeek&quot;&gt;[http://www.thejewishweek.com/viewArticle/c277_a14292/Special_Sections/Israel_Travel.html Promoting Israel in a Downturn], David Saranga, 17 December 2008&lt;/ref&gt; Israeli designers, such as swimwear company [[Gottex]] show their collections at leading fashion shows, including New York’s [[Bryant Park]] fashion show.&lt;ref name=&quot;TimeOut&quot;&gt;[http://www3.timeoutny.com/newyork/tonyblog/2008/09/fashion-week-gottex/ Fashion Week: Gottex], 9 September 2008.&lt;/ref&gt; In 2011, Tel Aviv hosted its first [[Fashion Week]] since the 1980s, with [[Italy|Italian]] designer [[Roberto Cavalli]] as a guest of honor.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last=Merle Ginsberg|title=Roberto Cavalli Shows Spring 2012 Collection at First Ever Tel Aviv Fashion Week|url=http://www.hollywoodreporter.com/fash-track/roberto-cavalli-spring-2012-tel-aviv-fashion-week-264432|accessdate=21 November 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Sports==
[[File:Galfridman.jpg|thumb|180px|[[Gal Fridman]], winner of Israel's first Olympic gold medal]]
[[Image:Israel 1970.jpg|thumb|right|200px|Israel at the [[1970 FIFA World Cup|1970 World Cup]]]]
{{main|Sport in Israel}}
[[Sports]] and [[Physical fitness|Fitness]] are important in Jewish culture. Athletic prowess, which was prized by the [[Ancient Greeks]], was looked down upon as an unwelcome intrusion of [[Hellenistic]] values. [[Maimonides]], who was both a [[Rabbi]] and a [[Physician]], emphasized the importance of regular Exercise in preventing illness on the authority of [[Hippocrates]] and [[Galen]]. This approach reiceved a boost in the 19th century from the Physical culture campaign of [[Max Nordau]], and in the early 20th century when the [[Chief Rabbi]] of [[Palestine]], [[Abraham Isaac Kook]], declared that the body serves the soul, and only a Healthy body can ensure a Healthy soul. 

The [[Maccabiah Games]], an Olympic-style event for Jewish athletes and Israeli athletes, was inaugurated in the 1930s, and has been held every 4 years since then. In 1964, [[Israel]] hosted and won the [[AFC Asian Cup]]; in 1970, the [[Israel national football team]] managed to qualify to the [[FIFA World Cup]], which is still considered the biggest achievement in Israeli Football.

Israel was excluded from the [[1978 Asian Games]] due to [[Arab]] pressure on the organizers. The exclusion left Israel in limbo and it ceased competing in Asian competitions. In 1994, [[UEFA]] agreed to admit Israel and all Israeli sporting organizations now compete in [[Europe]].

[[Association football|Football]] (soccer) and [[basketball]] are the most popular sports in Israel. The [[Israeli Premier League]] is the country's [[Premier Soccer League]], and [[Ligat ha'Al (basketball)|Ligat ha'Al]] is the premier basketball league. [[Maccabi Haifa F.C.|Maccabi Haifa]], [[Maccabi Tel Aviv F.C.|Maccabi Tel Aviv]], [[Hapoel Tel Aviv F.C.|Hapoel Tel Aviv]] and [[Beitar Jerusalem F.C.|Beitar Jerusalem]] are the largest sports clubs. Maccabi Tel Aviv, Maccabi Haifa, and Hapoel Tel Aviv have competed in the [[UEFA Champions League]] and Hapoel Tel Aviv reached the Quarterfinal in the [[UEFA Cup]]. [[Maccabi Tel Aviv B.C.]] has won the [[European Championship]] in Basketball 5 times. Israeli Tennis champion [[Shahar Pe'er]] peeked 11th at the WTA rank list, a national record.

[[Beersheba]] has become a national [[chess]] center; thanks to Soviet immigration, it is home to the largest number of [[Chess grandmaster]]s of any city in the world. The city hosted the [[World Team Chess Championship]] in 2005, and Chess is taught in the city's kindergartens. The Israeli Chess team won the silver medal at the [[2008 Chess Olympiad]], and the bronze medal at the [[39th Chess Olympiad|2010 Chess Olympiad]]. Israeli grandmaster [[Boris Gelfand]] is the current [[Chess World Cup]] holder. 

To date, Israel has won seven Olympic medals since its first win in [[1992 Summer Olympics|1992]], including a gold medal in [[Windsurfing]] at the [[2004 Summer Olympics]]. Israel has won over 100 gold medals in the [[Paralympic Games]] and is ranked about 15th in the [[All-time Paralympic Games medal table]]. The [[1968 Summer Paralympics]] were hosted by Israel.

==Outdoor and vacation culture==
[[File:AlmoganS.jpg|thumb|250px|[[Kibbutz]] Almog guesthouse]]
Camping and hiking are an integral part of Israeli culture. National parks and nature reserves across Israel register some 6.5 million visits a year.&lt;ref name=&quot;webcache.googleusercontent.com&quot;&gt;[http://webcache.googleusercontent.com/search?q=cache:Ea2eu1RmQrAJ:www.mfa.gov.il/MFA/Facts%2BAbout%2BIsrael/Looking%2Bat%2BIsrael/Looking%2Bat%2BIsrael-%2BCulture%2Band%2BLeisure.htm+hiking+culture+in+israel&amp;cd=30&amp;hl=en&amp;ct=clnk Letter from Israel: Culture and Leisure]&lt;/ref&gt; Schools and youth groups are taken on annual hiking trips throughout the country, raising children with an affinity for hiking and other outdoor activities. Consequently, many young Israelis take several months to a year off to travel the world, primarily to hike and experience the outdoors in remote, mountainous areas, like Nepal, India, New Zealand, Chile, and Peru.

Along the {{convert|190|km|mi}} of the Israeli Mediterranean coast, two thirds are accessible to bathing activities. Isrel has 100 surf bathing beaches guarded by professional lifeguards.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.jstor.org/pss/30138414 Beach Safety Management]&lt;/ref&gt; [[Matkot]] is a popular paddle ball game similar to [[beach tennis]], often referred to as the country's national sport.&lt;ref name=&quot;Fogelman&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.haaretz.com/hasen/spages/1099549.html |title=Beach Paddle Battle |last=Fogelman |first=Shay |work=Haaretz |date=2009-07-12}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Wedding customs==
[[File:IsraeliWedding.jpg|right|thumb|150px|Traditional Eastern (Mizrahi) Israeli Jewish Wedding]]
All marriages between Jews in Israel are registered with the [[Chief Rabbinate]] and the ceremony follows Orthodox [[halakha|Jewish practice]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://judaism.about.com/od/weddings/a/all_marriage.htm All about Marriage and Weddings in Judaism]&lt;/ref&gt; As civil ceremonies are not performed in Israel,&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.jta.org/news/article/2011/11/21/3090383/israelis-seeking-alternatives-to-traditional-wedding-ceremonies Israelis seeking alternatives to traditional wedding ceremonies]&lt;/ref&gt; a growing number of secular couples circumvent this by traveling to nearby locations such as Cyprus.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.ynetnews.com/articles/0,7340,L-3045322,00.html Israelis turn to secular weddingsad]&lt;/ref&gt; While most Jews in Israel have adopted Western styles in dress,  traditional clothing and jewelry is sometimes brought out for pre-wedding rituals in the Mizrahi and Yemenite community, such as the [[henna]] ceremony.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.jewishvirtuallibrary.org/jsource/vjw/Yemen.html The Virtual Jewish History Tour:Yemen]&lt;/ref&gt;

==Museums==
{{Main|List of museums in Israel}}
With over 200 museums, Israel has the highest number of museums per capita in the world, with millions of visitors annually.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url=http://www.israeliconsulatela.org/culture/Science.asp | title=Science &amp; Technology | publisher=Consulate General of Israel in Los Angeles | accessdate=2007-05-26 |archiveurl = http://web.archive.org/web/20070416111417/http://www.israeliconsulatela.org/culture/Science.asp  |archivedate = 2007-04-16}}&lt;/ref&gt;
==See also==
* [[List of Israeli musical artists]]
* [[List of Israeli visual artists]]
* [[List of Hebrew language poets]]
* [[List of Hebrew language authors]]
* [[List of Israeli actors]]
* [[List of Hebrew language playwrights]]
* [[Science and technology in Israel]]
* [[Religion in Israel]]
* [[Israeli cuisine]]
* [[Jewish ethnic divisions]]

==References==
{{reflist}}

==External links==
* [http://www.culture.org.il/directory/introduction.asp Israel Arts Directory]
* [http://www.acum.org.il/jsp/index_e.jsp ACUM - Society of Authors, Composers and Music Publishers in Israel]
* [http://www.ilmuseums.com/ Museums in Israel]
* [http://www.ithl.org.il/ The Institute for the Translation of Hebrew Literature]
* [http://imi.org.il/site/about.asp Israel Music Institute]
* [http://www.ynetnews.com/home/0,7340,L-3086,00.html Israeli Culture Ynetnews]
* [http://acheret.co.il/en/?cmd=articles.302 Jewish and Israeli Culture], [http://acheret.co.il/en Eretz Acheret] Magazine

{{DEFAULTSORT:Culture Of Israel}}
[[Category:Israeli culture| ]]

[[da:Israels kultur]]
[[de:Israelische Kultur]]
[[es:Cultura de Israel]]
[[id:Budaya Israel]]
[[he:תרבות ישראלית]]
[[lad:Kultura en Yisrael]]
[[no:Israels kultur]]
[[pl:Kultura Izraela]]
[[pt:Cultura de Israel]]
[[ru:Культура Израиля]]
[[sq:Kultura në Izrael]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
