<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="211917" ns="0" title="University of California, Santa Barbara"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Infobox University
| name            = University of California,&lt;br&gt;Santa Barbara
| motto           = ''Fiat lux'' ([[Latin]])
| mottoeng        = [[Let there be light]]
| image_name      = Ucsb seal.svg
| image_size      = 180px
| caption         = Seal of the&lt;br&gt;University of California, Santa Barbara
| established     = 1891 (Anna Blake School);&lt;br&gt;Joined the UC in 1944
| type            = [[Public university|Public]]&lt;br/&gt; [[Space grant colleges|Space Grant]]
| calendar        = Quarter
| endowment       = [[United States Dollar|US $]]178.1 [[1000000 (number)|million]] (March 31, 2010) &lt;ref&gt;[http://www.ucop.edu/treasurer/foundation/foundation.pdf UC Annual Endowment Report] ''Office of the Treasurer of The Regents'.' Retrieved March 31, 2010.&lt;/ref&gt;
| staff           =
| faculty         = 1,086&lt;ref&gt;http://www.ucsb.edu/campus/campus-intro.shtml&lt;/ref&gt;
| nobel_laureates = 6
| chancellor      = [[Henry T. Yang]]
| undergrad       = 19,800
| postgrad        = 3,050
| doctoral        =
| city            = [[Santa Barbara, California|Santa Barbara]]
| state           = [[California]]
| country         = USA{{flagicon|USA}}{{flagicon|California}}
| campus          = [[Suburban]], {{convert|1055|acre|ha}}
| former_names    = Anna Blake School (1891-1909)&lt;br&gt;Santa Barbara State Normal School (1909–21)&lt;br&gt;Santa Barbara State College (1921–44)&lt;br&gt;Santa Barbara College of the University of California (1944-58)
| colors          = Pacific [[Azure (heraldry)|Blue]] and Gaucho [[Or (heraldry)|Gold]] {{color box|#000099}}{{color box|#FFCC00}}
| nickname        = [[Gaucho]]s
| athletics       = [[National Collegiate Athletic Association|NCAA]] [[Division I (NCAA)|Division I]]&lt;br&gt;[[UCSB Gauchos]]
| affiliations    = [[University of California]]&lt;br/&gt; [[Big West Conference]]
| free_label      = Newspaper
| free            = [[The Bottom Line]]&lt;br/&gt; [[The Daily Nexus]]
| website         = [http://www.ucsb.edu ucsb.edu]
| logo            = [[Image:UCSB logo.png|220px]]
}}

The '''University of California, Santa Barbara''', commonly known as '''UCSB''' or '''UC Santa Barbara''', is a [[public university|public]] research university and one of the 10 general campuses of the [[University of California]] system. The main campus is located on a {{convert|1022|acre|ha|adj=on}} site in [[Goleta, California]], {{convert|8|mi|km}} from [[Santa Barbara, California|Santa Barbara]] and {{convert|100|mi|km}} northwest of Los Angeles. Founded in 1891 as an independent teachers' college, UCSB joined the University of California system in 1944 and is the third-oldest general-education campus in the system.

UCSB is a comprehensive doctoral university and is organized into five colleges offering 87 undergraduate degrees and 55 graduate degrees. The campus is the 5th-largest in the UC system by enrollment with 19,800 undergraduate and 3,050 graduate students. The university granted 5,442 bachelors, 576 masters, and 310 Ph.D. degrees in 2006–2007.&lt;ref name=&quot;Portrait&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://bap.ucsb.edu/IR/UCSB_Portrait.pdf |format=PDF|title=UCSB Portrait |publisher=University of California, Santa Barbara |accessdate=October 16, 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt; In 2010, UCSB was ranked 39th among &quot;National Universities&quot; by [[U.S. News &amp; World Report]],&lt;ref name=&quot;US News&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://colleges.usnews.rankingsandreviews.com/best-colleges/santa-barbara-ca/ucsb-1320|title=America's Best Colleges 2008: National Universities: Top Schools |publisher=U.S. News &amp; World Report |accessdate=August 17, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;  and 29th worldwide by the [[Times Higher Education World University Rankings]]&lt;ref name=autogenerated1&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.timeshighereducation.co.uk/world-university-rankings/2010-2011/top-200.html |title=Top 200 – The Times Higher Education World University Rankings 2010–2011 |publisher=Timeshighereducation.co.uk |date= |accessdate=January 22, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;.  The [[Academic Ranking of World Universities]] ranked UCSB 33rd overall,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.shanghairanking.com/ARWU2011.html |title=Academic Ranking of World Universities - 2011 |publisher=ShanghaiRanking.com |date= |accessdate=November 11, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; 18th in Sciences, and 15th in Engineering. In 2011, UCSB was ranked 118th internationally in the [[QS World University Rankings]] &lt;ref name=&quot;topuniversities&quot;&gt;http://www.topuniversities.com/university-rankings/world-university-rankings/2011?page=2&lt;/ref&gt;.

UC Santa Barbara is a &quot;very high activity&quot; research university and spent $191.2 million on research expenditures in the 2007 fiscal year, 97th-largest in the United States.&lt;ref name=&quot;NSF R&amp;D&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.nsf.gov/statistics/profiles/ranking.cfm?ess=1&amp;sort=a |title=2005 Institution rankings |publisher=National Science Foundation |accessdate=October 15, 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt; UCSB houses twelve national research centers,&lt;ref name=&quot;ucsb.edu&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.ucsb.edu/pop/ |title=UCSB Points of Pride |publisher=Ucsb.edu |date= |accessdate=January 22, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; including the renowned [[Kavli Institute for Theoretical Physics]].&lt;ref&gt;http://www.kitp.ucsb.edu/&lt;/ref&gt; UCSB faculty includes five [[Nobel Prize]] laureates, one [[Fields Medal]]ist, 29 members of the [[United States National Academy of Sciences|National Academy of Sciences]], 27 members of the [[National Academy of Engineering]], and 23 members of the [[American Academy of Arts and Sciences]]. UCSB was elected to the [[Association of American Universities]] in 1995. UCSB was the #3 host on the [[ARPAnet]].

The [[UC Santa Barbara Gauchos]] compete in the [[NCAA]] [[Division I (NCAA)|Division I]] [[Big West Conference]]. The Gauchos have won NCAA national championships in men's soccer and men's water polo.

==History==
UCSB traces its origins back to the Anna Blake School which was founded in 1891 and offered training in home economics and industrial arts.&lt;ref&gt;University of California, Santa Barbara, 1975–76 General Catalog Issue, page 1&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;http://www.sbsdk12.org/schools/history/SBCC-UCSB.shtml&lt;/ref&gt; The Anna Blake School was taken over by the state in 1909 and became the Santa Barbara State Normal School. In 1921, a liberal arts program was authorized and the school was renamed again to [[California State University#Former campuses|Santa Barbara State College]]. Intense lobbying by an interest group in the City of Santa Barbara, led by [[Thomas Storke]] and Pearl Chase, persuaded the State Legislature, Governor [[Earl Warren]], and the [[Regents of the University of California]] to move the State College over to the more research-oriented University of California system in 1944. The State College system sued to stop the takeover, but the Governor did not support the suit. A state initiative was passed, however, to stop subsequent conversions of State Colleges to University of California campuses.&lt;ref name=&quot;stadtman&quot;&gt;{{cite book |author=Stadtman, Verne |title=The University of California, 1868–1968, page 346|publisher=McGraw-Hill |location=|year=1970 |page=594 |oclc= |doi=}}&lt;/ref&gt; From 1944 to 1958 the school was known as Santa Barbara College of the University of California, before taking on its current name. 

Originally, the Regents envisioned a small, several thousand-student liberal arts college, a so-called &quot;[[Williams College]] of the West&quot;, at Santa Barbara. Chronologically, UCSB is the third general-education campus of the University of California, after Berkeley and UCLA (the only other state campus to have been acquired by the UC system). The original campus the Regents acquired in Santa Barbara was located on only {{convert|100|acre|ha}} of largely unusable land on a seaside mesa. The availability of a {{convert|400|acre|ha|sing=on}} portion of the land used as [[Marine Corps Air Station Santa Barbara]] until 1946 on another seaside mesa in [[Goleta, California|Goleta]], which the Regents could acquire for free from the federal government, led to that site becoming the Santa Barbara campus in 1949. Originally, only 3000–3500 students were anticipated, but the post WWII [[baby boom]] led to the designation of general campus in 1958, along with a name change from &quot;Santa Barbara College&quot; to &quot;University of California, Santa Barbara,&quot; and the discontinuation of the industrial arts program for which the State college was famous. A [[Chancellor (education)|Chancellor]], Samuel B. Gould, was appointed in 1959. All of this change was done in accordance with the [[California Master Plan for Higher Education]].

In 1959, UCSB Professor Douwe Stuurman hosted the English writer [[Aldous Huxley]] as the university's first visiting professor.&lt;ref name=&quot;The 50th Anniversary of Aldous Huxley’s UCSB Lecture Series&quot;&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.independent.com/news/2009/mar/24/50th-anniversary-aldous-huxleys-ucsb-lecture-serie/ |title=The 50th Anniversary of Aldous Huxley's UCSB Lecture Series |accessdate=May 24, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; Huxley delivered a lectures series called &quot;The Human Situation&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.amazon.com/Human-Situation-Lectures-Given-Barbara/dp/0701121432&lt;/ref&gt;

In the late 1960s and early 1970s UCSB became nationally known as a hotbed of anti-Vietnam War activity.  Events during the era included a bombing at the school's faculty club in 1969, which killed the caretaker, Dover Sharp, and the spring 1970 burning of the [[Bank of America]] branch building in the student community of [[Isla Vista]],  during which time one male student, Kevin Moran, was shot and killed.  UCSB's anti-Vietnam activity impelled then Governor [[Ronald Reagan]] to impose a [[curfew]] and order  the [[California National Guard|National Guard]] to enforce it.  Weapon-carrying guardsmen were a common sight on campus and in Isla Vista during this time.  

In 1995, UCSB was elected to the [[Association of American Universities]], an organization of leading research universities, with a membership consisting of 59 universities in the [[United States]] (both [[State university system (United States)|public]] and [[private university|private]]) and two universities in [[Canada]].

===Provosts and Chancellors===

*1944–1946 [[Clarence L. Phelps]] 
*1946–1955 [[J. Harold Williams]] 
*1955–1955 [[Clark G. Kuebler]] 
*1956–1956 [[John C. Snidecor]] 
*1956–1959 [[Elmer Noble]] 
*1959–1962 [[Samuel B. Gould]]
*1962–1977 [[Vernon Cheadle]] 
*1977–1986 [[Robert Huttenback]] 
*1986–1987 [[Daniel G. Aldrich]]
*1987–1994 [[Barbara Uehling]] 
*1994–present [[Henry T. Yang]] 

[[California State University#Former campuses|Santa Barbara State College]] was under the supervision of a [[President]], but in 1944, when it became a campus of the [[University of California]], the title of the chief executive was changed to [[Provost (education)|Provost]]. In September 1958, the [[Regents of the University of California]] established Santa Barbara as a general University campus and at the official title of the chief executive was changed to [[Chancellor]]. UCSB's first Provost was thus [[Clarence L. Phelps]], while UCSB's first Chancellor was [[Samuel B. Gould]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://sunsite.berkeley.edu/~ucalhist/general_history/campuses/ucsb/officers.html |title=University of California History Digital Archives |publisher=Sunsite.berkeley.edu |date= |accessdate=January 22, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Campus==
[[Image:Ucsbuniversitycenterandstorketower.jpg|thumb|right|300px|The [[Storke Tower]] and the University Center in front of the UCSB Lagoon.]]
[[Image:UCSB 06.JPG|thumb|right|300px|A view over the school's lagoon to one of the Channel Islands]]
UCSB is located on cliffs directly above the Pacific Ocean. UCSB's campus is completely autonomous from local government and has not been annexed by the city of [[Santa Barbara, California|Santa Barbara]] and thus is not part of the city.&lt;ref name=&quot;annex&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://facm.ucsb.edu/planning/ellwood-devereux/documents/2006_NW_Campus_LRDPA/UCSB%20_90%20LRDP%20text%20with%20_06%20N%20and%20W%20Campus%20Amend.pdf|title=UCSB Long Range Development Plan – 1990|accessdate=September 16, 2007|publisher=University of California, Santa Barbara|year=1990|author=University of California, Santa Barbara|work=Page 16|format=PDF |archiveurl = http://web.archive.org/web/20070629112004/http://facm.ucsb.edu/planning/ellwood-devereux/documents/2006_NW_Campus_LRDPA/UCSB+_90+LRDP+text+with+_06+N+and+W+Campus+Amend.pdf &lt;!-- Bot retrieved archive --&gt; |archivedate = June 29, 2007}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;ellwood&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://facilities.ucsb.edu/planning/ellwood-devereux/documents/ucsb_lrdp.asp|title=Open Space Habitat Management Plan for the Ellwood-Devereux Coast: Reports and Documents|accessdate=September 16, 2007|publisher=University Of California Santa Barbara|year=1990|author=University Of California Santa Barbara |archiveurl = http://web.archive.org/web/20070811154530/http://facilities.ucsb.edu/planning/ellwood-devereux/documents/ucsb_lrdp.asp &lt;!-- Bot retrieved archive --&gt; |archivedate = August 11, 2007}}&lt;/ref&gt; While it appears closer to the recently formed city of [[Goleta, California|Goleta]], a parcel of the City of Santa Barbara that forms a strip of &quot;city&quot; through the ocean to the Santa Barbara airport, runs through the west entrance to the university campus. Although UCSB has a Santa Barbara mailing address, as do other unincorporated areas around the city, only this entry parcel is in the Santa Barbara city limits. Like all other UC and CSU campuses, it is self-governing and cannot be incorporated into either city. The campus is divided into four parts: Main (East) Campus {{convert|708|acre|ha}} that houses all academic units plus the majority of undergraduate housing, Storke Campus, West Campus and North Campus. The campuses surround the community of [[Isla Vista, California|Isla Vista]].

UCSB is one of a few universities in the United States with its own beach. The campus, bordered on three sides by the Pacific Ocean, has miles of coastline as well as its own lagoon. The campus has numerous walking and bicycle paths across campus, around the lagoon and along the beach.

Much of the campus' early architecture was designed by famed architect [[William Pereira]] and his partner [[Charles Luckman]], and made heavy use of custom tinted and patterned concrete block. This design element was carried over into many of the school's subsequent buildings.

The [[Lagoon]] is a large body of water adjacent to the coastline, between San Rafael and San Miguel Residence Halls. It was created from a former tidal salt marsh flat and is fed by a combination of run-off and ocean water used by the Marine Science Building's aquatic life tanks; thus, it is a unique combination of fresh and salt water. Many of the older campus buildings are being replaced with newer, more modern facilities. The [[UCSB Libraries]], consisting of the Davidson Library and the Arts Library, hold more than 3 million bound volumes&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.independent.com/news/2010/nov/09/uscb-library-celebrates-3-millionth-book/ |title=The Santa Barbara Independent UCSB Library Celebrates 3 Millionth Book |publisher=Independent.com |date=November 9, 2010 |accessdate=January 22, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; and millions of [[microform]]s, government documents, manuscripts, maps, satellite and aerial images, sound recordings, and other materials. The 24 Hour Study Room, formerly known as the RBR (Reserved Book Room), is adjacent to the Davidson Library, which is located in the middle of the UCSB campus.

Campbell Hall is the university's largest lecture hall with 862 seats. It is also the main venue for the UCSB Arts and Lectures series, which presents special performances, films, and lectures for the UCSB campus and Santa Barbara community.

[[Storke Tower]], completed in 1969, is the tallest building in [[Santa Barbara County]]. It can be seen from most places on campus, and it overlooks Storke Plaza. It is home to a five-octave, 61-bell [[carillon]]. [[KCSB 91.9FM Santa Barbara|KCSB 91.9]] and the ''[[Daily Nexus]]'' have headquarters beneath Storke Tower.

The UCSB Family Vacation Center founded in 1969, is a summer family camp located on campus that draws over 2,000 guests each summer. The staff of over 50 includes many UCSB students who have been extensively trained as camp counselors.
===Layout===
The university (itself termed a &quot;campus&quot; of the University of California) is divided into two physical campuses, a West Campus and East Campus. The vast majority of university facilities, including all lecture halls and laboratories, are in the East Campus. The two campuses are connected by a large strip (known as the North and Storke Campuses) to the north which contain university housing and athletic fields. Thus, the university surrounds Isla Vista on three sides.

West Campus, aside from a few buildings dedicated to faculty housing, has largely been leased out to private organizations, and includes a school for the mentally disabled and a large nature preserve. The largest sand dunes on the south-facing coast of the Santa Barbara Channel are located here.

The East Campus centers around two [[Quadrangle (architecture)|quadrangle]]s, separated from each other by the main library and bus circle, and the life sciences buildings. Along the western quad are Storke Plaza and buildings housing the various arts, social sciences, and humanities departments. The Student Resource Building and the Events Center are also located along this quad. Surrounding the wider, park-like eastern quad are buildings housing the physical sciences departments and the College of Engineering. Directly to the south of, but not adjacent to, the eastern quad are the life sciences and psychology departments, as well as most of the on-campus housing. The southernmost section of the campus is dominated by the lagoon. The peninsula extending from the beach into the lagoon contains an elaborate labyrinth.

===Bicycles===
Along with [[University of California, Davis|UC Davis]], UCSB is known for its extensive biking system. Bicycles [[Segregated_cycle_facilities#Bikeways_that_use_independent_rights-of-way|have exclusive right of way]] on paths throughout East Campus. [[Bicycle stand]]s and [[bicycle locker|lockers]] are ubiquitous.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.as.ucsb.edu/bikes/AS_BIKESMap_2010.pdf&lt;/ref&gt; UCSB is unique among bicycle-heavy areas in that most travel is done within a small radius.&lt;ref&gt;http://police.ucsb.edu/Web/CSO/BicycleProgram.html&lt;/ref&gt;

==Organization==

Santa Barbara is one of the ten major campuses affiliated with the [[University of California]]. The University of California is governed by a 26-member [[Board of Regents]], 18 of which are appointed by the [[Governor of California]] to 12-year terms, 7 serving as ''[[ex officio]]'' members, and a single student regent.&lt;ref name=&quot;Governance&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.universityofcalifornia.edu/aboutuc/governance.html |title=About UC - Shared Governance |publisher=The University of California |accessdate=2008-11-30}}&lt;/ref&gt; The position of Chancellor was created in 1952 to lead individual campuses. The Board of Regents appointed [[Henry T. Yang]] to be the 5th Chancellor of the university in 1994.&lt;ref&gt;http://chancellor.ucsb.edu/about/&lt;/ref&gt;

===Colleges and schools===

*[[College of Creative Studies]]
*[[UCSB College of Engineering|College of Engineering]]
*[[UCSB College of Letters &amp; Science|College of Letters &amp; Science]]
*[[Bren School of Environmental Science &amp; Management]]
*[[Gevirtz Graduate School of Education]]

UC Santa Barbara has three colleges: the [[UCSB College of Letters &amp; Science|College of Letters &amp; Science]], the [[UCSB College of Engineering|College of Engineering]], and the [[College of Creative Studies]]. The College of Creative Studies offers students an alternative approach to education by supporting advanced, independent work in the arts, mathematics, and sciences. The campus also has two professional schools, the [[Bren School of Environmental Science &amp; Management]], located in [[Bren Hall]], and the [[Gevirtz Graduate School of Education]].

===Academic year===
The university runs on a [[academic quarter (year division)|quarter system]]. There are three terms in the normal academic year: fall, winter, and spring, as well as a summer term. At the beginning of each term, there are one to three days of Pre-instructional Activities, where faculty meet to discuss instructional plans. During this period, students acquaint themselves to the campus and have the opportunity to take placement tests. At the end of each term, one week is devoted to final exams and special academic activities. There are 146 days of instruction, with a minimum of 48 per term.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.registrar.ucsb.edu/cal2012.htm|title=Approved Academic Calendar for 2011-2012|publisher=UCSB Office of the Registrar|accessdate=14 May 2011|date=15 September 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Academics==
UC Santa Barbara is a large, comprehensive, primarily residential doctoral university.&lt;ref name=&quot;Carnegie&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://classifications.carnegiefoundation.org/lookup_listings/view_institution.php?unit_id=110705&amp;start_page=institution.php&amp;clq={%22ipug2005_ids%22%3A%22%22%2C%22ipgrad2005_ids%22%3A%22%22%2C%22enrprofile2005_ids%22%3A%22%22%2C%22ugprfile2005_ids%22%3A%22%22%2C%22sizeset2005_ids%22%3A%22%22%2C%22basic2005_ids%22%3A%22%22%2C%22eng2005_ids%22%3A%22%22%2C%22search_string%22%3A%22University+of+California+Santa+Barbara%22%2C%22first_letter%22%3A%22%22%2C%22level%22%3A%22%22%2C%22control%22%3A%22%22%2C%22accred%22%3A%22%22%2C%22state%22%3A%22%22%2C%22region%22%3A%22%22%2C%22urbanicity%22%3A%22%22%2C%22womens%22%3A%22%22%2C%22hbcu%22%3A%22%22%2C%22hsi%22%3A%22%22%2C%22tribal%22%3A%22%22%2C%22msi%22%3A%22%22%2C%22landgrant%22%3A%22%22%2C%22coplac%22%3A%22%22%2C%22urban%22%3A%22%22} |title=Institutions – University of California – Santa Barbara |publisher=The Carnegie Foundation for the Advancement of Teaching |accessdate=February 1, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; The full-time, four-year undergraduate program comprises the majority of enrollments and has an arts &amp; sciences focus with high graduate co-existence.&lt;ref name=&quot;Carnegie&quot;/&gt; UCSB is organized into five colleges offering 87 undergraduate degrees and 55 graduate degrees. The campus is the 5th-largest in the UC system by enrollment with 18,429 undergraduate and 2,981 graduate students. The university granted 5,442 bachelor's, 576 master's, and 310 Ph.D. degrees in 2006–2007.&lt;ref name=&quot;Portrait&quot;/&gt;

===Research activity===
From 2005–2009, UCSB was ranked fourth in terms of relative citation impact in the U.S. (behind [[MIT]], [[Caltech]], and [[Princeton University]]) according to [[Thomson Reuters]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.independent.com/news/2010/dec/09/ucsb-among-top-universities-research-citations/ |title=The Santa Barbara Independent UCSB Among Top Universities in Research Citations |publisher=Independent.com |date=December 9, 2010 |accessdate=January 22, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.ia.ucsb.edu/pa/display.aspx?pkey=2385 |title=UCSB Press Release: &quot;UCSB Among Top Universities in the U.S. in High-Quality Research Citations &quot; |publisher=Ia.ucsb.edu |date=December 9, 2010 |accessdate=January 22, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

UCSB hosts 12 National Research Centers, including the [[Kavli Institute for Theoretical Physics]], the [[National Center for Ecological Analysis and Synthesis]], the [[Southern California Earthquake Center]], and the [[California Nanosystems Institute]]. Eight of these centers are supported by the National Science Foundation.&lt;ref name=&quot;ucsb.edu&quot;/&gt; UCSB is also home to [[Microsoft Station Q]], a research group working on [[topological quantum computer|topological quantum computing]] where American mathematician and [[Fields Medal]]ist [[Michael Freedman]] is the director.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://stationq.ucsb.edu/index.html |title=Microsoft Station Q |publisher=Stationq.ucsb.edu |date= |accessdate=January 22, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Teaching and degrees===
The focus of the University of California is on research.&lt;ref name=&quot;Carnegie&quot;/&gt; Like all University of California campuses, UCSB focuses on academic development instead of vocational learning. Undergraduate teaching is centered on lectures, with larger lecture classes having sections. Sections may be tutorial style, or they may be set up as seminars or discussions. For undergraduates, UCSB confers both [[Bachelor of Arts|B.A.]] and [[Bachelor of Science|B.S.]] degrees. Music majors may pursue a [[Bachelor of Music]] degree. Graduate teaching involves seminar style classes and an emphasis on research and further study. UCSB confers [[Master of Arts (postgraduate)|M.A.]], [[Master of Science|M.S.]], and [[Doctor of Philosophy|Ph.D.]] degrees. Those studying music may pursue a [[Master of Music|M.M.]] or [[Doctor of Musical Arts|D.M.A.]] degree. Students pursuing a career in education may receive a [[Master of Education|M.Ed.]] or [[Doctor of Education|Ed.D.]] degree.

===Rankings===

{{Infobox US university ranking
| ARWU_W = 33
| ARWU_N = 25
| Forbes = 
| QS_W = 118
| THES_W = 35
| THES_N = 24
| USNWR_NU = 42
| USNWR_LA =  
| Wamo_NU = 13
| Wamo_LA =
}}

The [[Times Higher Education World University Rankings]] ranked UCSB 35th worldwide in 2011, 24th in the U.S.&lt;ref name=autogenerated1 /&gt; while the [[Academic Ranking of World Universities]] ranked UCSB 33rd, 25th in the nation.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.shanghairanking.com/ARWU2011.html |title=Academic Ranking of World Universities - 2011 |publisher=ShanghaiRanking.com |date= |accessdate=November 11, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;
Among U.S. universities, UCSB is considered a &quot;[[public Ivy]]&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;edportal&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.amazon.com/gp/reader/006093459X/|title=The Public Ivies|accessdate=February 10, 2009|publisher=Collins|year=2001|author=Howard Greene, M.A., M.Ed. and Matthew Greene, Ph. D}}&lt;/ref&gt; ''Newsweek'' named UCSB one of &quot;America’s 25 Hottest Colleges of 2005&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;release&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.ia.ucsb.edu/pa/display.aspx?pkey=1177|title=UCSB Again Named One of 'Hottest Colleges'|accessdate=September 16, 2007|publisher=University of California, Santa Barbara|year=2004|author=University of California, Santa Barbara News Release}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The Global Research Report: United States published by Thomson Reuters in November 2010 rated UCSB's research 4th nationally in citation impact. &lt;ref&gt; {{cite web | url=http://researchanalytics.thomsonreuters.com/m/pdfs/globalresearchreport-usa.pdf | title= Global Research Report: United States| accessdate = November 11, 2011 | publisher = Thomson Reuters | author = Thomson Reuters Research Analytics}}&lt;/ref&gt;

According to the [[US News &amp; World Report]] for 2012, UCSB is ranked 42nd among national universities and 10th among public universities. [[US News &amp; World Report]] also ranked UCSB's graduate program in Materials Engineering 4th,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://grad-schools.usnews.rankingsandreviews.com/grad/eng/mater |title=Materials – Best Engineering Schools – Graduate Schools – Education – US News |publisher=Grad-schools.usnews.rankingsandreviews.com |date=April 15, 2010 |accessdate=January 22, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; the graduate Physics program 10th,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://grad-schools.usnews.rankingsandreviews.com/grad/phy/search |title=Rankings – Physics – Graduate Schools – Education – US News |publisher=Grad-schools.usnews.rankingsandreviews.com |date=April 15, 2010 |accessdate=January 22, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; including the 3rd best program for Condensed Matter Physics,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://grad-schools.usnews.rankingsandreviews.com/best-graduate-schools/top-physics-schools/condensed-matter |title=Condensed Matter – Physics – Graduate Schools – Education – US News |publisher=Grad-schools.usnews.rankingsandreviews.com |date=April 15, 2010 |accessdate=January 22, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; and the program for Elementary Particles/Field/String Theory 8th.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://grad-schools.usnews.rankingsandreviews.com/best-graduate-schools/top-physics-schools/string-theory |title=Elementary Particles / Field / String Theory – Physics – Graduate Schools – Education – US News |publisher=Grad-schools.usnews.rankingsandreviews.com |date=April 15, 2010 |accessdate=January 22, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;  In terms of the social sciences, UCSB's graduate program in Sociology is ranked 2nd for research in sex and gender &lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://grad-schools.usnews.rankingsandreviews.com/best-graduate-schools/top-sociology-schools/sex-gender-sociology |title=Sex and Gender – Sociology – Graduate Schools – Education – US News |publisher=Grad-schools.usnews.rankingsandreviews.com |date=April 15, 2010 |accessdate=January 22, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; and 7th for sociology of culture,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://grad-schools.usnews.rankingsandreviews.com/best-graduate-schools/top-sociology-schools/sociology-of-culture |title=Sociology of Culture – Sociology – Graduate Schools – Education – US News |publisher=Grad-schools.usnews.rankingsandreviews.com |date=April 15, 2010 |accessdate=January 22, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; and the History department is ranked 10th for women's history.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://grad-schools.usnews.rankingsandreviews.com/best-graduate-schools/top-history-schools/womens-history |title=Women's History – History – Graduate Schools – Education – US News |publisher=Grad-schools.usnews.rankingsandreviews.com |date=April 15, 2010 |accessdate=January 22, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[The Washington Monthly]] named UCSB as the 11th best national university in 2010.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.washingtonmonthly.com/college_guide/rankings_2010/national_university_rank.php |title=National University Rankings 2010 |publisher=Washington Monthly |date= |accessdate=January 22, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; In 2011 [[QS World University Rankings]]&lt;ref name=&quot;topuniversities&quot; /&gt; ranked UCSB 118th in the world.
UCSB was also ranked #59 of the &quot;Top 100 Global Universities&quot; by Newsweek Magazine in 2006.&lt;ref name=&quot;nweek&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.msnbc.msn.com/id/14321230/site/newsweek|title=The Complete List: The Top 100 Global Universities|accessdate=September 16, 2007|publisher=Newsweek|year=2006|author=MSNBC |archiveurl = http://web.archive.org/web/20070911054615/http://www.msnbc.msn.com/id/14321230/site/newsweek &lt;!-- Bot retrieved archive --&gt; |archivedate = September 11, 2007}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Among US university economics programs, in 2010 UCSB was ranked the 6th for experimental economics, 3rd for environmental economics, and 12th for cognitive and behavioral economics by RePEc.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://ideas.repec.org/top/top.env.html |title=Field Rankings at IDEAS: Environmental Economics |publisher=Ideas.repec.org |date= |accessdate=January 22, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.econ.ucsb.edu/rankings.html |title=UCSB Economics &amp;#124; UCSB Ranked Third in Nation for Environmental Economics and Sixth in Experimental Economics |publisher=Econ.ucsb.edu |date= |accessdate=January 22, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Student activities and traditions==
[[Image:Storke Tower, UCSB.jpg|thumb|[[Storke Tower]]]]
{{See also|List of fraternities and sororities at University of California, Santa Barbara}}

{| class=&quot;wikitable sortable&quot;  style=&quot;width:390px; float:left;&quot;
|| '''Ethnicity, 2010'''&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | title= 2010–1 Campus Profile | url=http://bap.ucsb.edu/IR/campusprofile/cp2010.pdf | publisher= UCSB Institutional Research and Planning |accessdate=September 14, 2011|format=PDF}}&lt;/ref&gt; ||'''Under-graduates''' || '''Graduate students'''
|-
|[[White American|White]]
| 55.3
| 47.3%
|-
|[[Hispanic]] or [[Chicano]]
| 22.5%
| 7.8%
|-
|[[Asian American]] or [[Pacific Islander]]
| 17.2%
| 7.1%
|-
|[[African American]]
| 3.5%
| 1.7%
|-
|[[Indian American]] or [[Pakistani American]]
| 1.3%
| 1.4%
|-
|[[Indigenous peoples of the Americas|Native Americans]]
| 0.9%
| 0.4%
|-
|Other
| 1%
| 3.4%
|-
|Unknown (U.S. residents)
| 4.9%
| 12.6%
|-
|International
| 1.5%
| 18.3%
|-
|'''Total'''
| '''''100%'''''
| '''''100%'''''
|}

===Social===
UCSB is a politically active campus. For the 2008 presidential election, UCSB won a national college competition for student voter registration by registering 10857 voters, or 51.5% of the student population.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.dailynexus.com/2008-11-17/ucsb-wins-death-cab-for-cutie-concert/ |title=UCSB Wins Death Cab for Cutie Concert |publisher=The Daily Nexus |date=January 1, 1970 |accessdate=January 22, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;  The UCSB Campus Democrats are one of the most active organizations on campus. Over the years, other political parties and organizations have also been known to be active on campus, such as the Environmental Affairs Board, [[Green Party (United States)|Green Party]], [[Libertarian Party (United States)|Libertarians]], [[NORML]], and the Queer Student Union.{{Citation needed|date=February 2007}} Several presidential and vice presidential candidates have visited the campus in recent years, including [[Hillary Clinton]], [[John B. Anderson]] and [[Peter Camejo]]. The campus has also seen a resurgence of anti-war sentiment among students. 

There are a variety of on campus centers offering social, recreational, religious, and preprofessional activities for students. The UCSB Multicultural Center puts on numerous activities every year to support students of color and promote awareness of diversity issues on campus. Other organizations and centers include the ''[[Daily Nexus]]'', the campus newspaper, the La Cumbre Yearbook, the school radio station, [[KCSB 91.9FM Santa Barbara|KCSB 91.9]], ''The Bottom Line'', an alternative weekly newspaper, and the Gaucho Free Press, the campus's conservative magazine. The UCSB Recreation Center also hosts a variety of activities, from Adventure Programs to [[ballroom dancing]] classes.
Further UCSB Hillel offers a space for UCSB's large Jewish population and a place for Jewish students to come together in a unique building in Isla Vista.
Students socialize at the [[UCSB Arbor|Arbor]], the [[UCSB UCen|UCen]], the Coral Tree Cafe the Courtyard Cafe and for a special lunch, the Faculty Club.

UCSB is also known for its annual free music festival, [[Extravaganza (Music Festival)|Extravaganza]]. It is held at Harder Stadium in the spring and generally attracts around 8,000 people. Past performers have included [[Nas]], [[T.I.]], [[E-40]], [[Sublime (band)|Sublime]], [[Run-D.M.C.]], [[The Pharcyde]], [[Social Distortion]], [[Jack Johnson (musician)|Jack Johnson]], and [[Drake (entertainer)|Drake]] amongst many others.
{{clear}}

===Housing===
[[Image:San Nicolas, UCSB.jpg|thumb|right|San Nicolas residence hall.  As of September 2008, six of the on-campus residence halls are named after the islands in the nearby [[Channel Islands of California|Channel Islands]] chain.]]
[[Image:De La Guerra dining common, UCSB.jpg|thumb|right|De La Guerra dining commons]]

There are 8 [[residence halls]] at UCSB, seven of which are located at the Main campus, and one of which, Santa Catalina Dorms (Formerly known as Francisco Torres or FT), is located near the entrance to West campus north of [[Isla Vista]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.housing.ucsb.edu/hchoices/reshalls-descriptions.htm ]{{dead link|date=January 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Santa Catalina has, not only its own dining commons, Portola Dining Commons, but it has a heated swimming pool, two lounges, numerous study rooms, 2 Recreational Rooms, a gym, as well as tennis courts and an expansive lawn. Because Santa Catalina is nearly {{convert|1|mi|km|abbr=on}}. off-campus it has its own Campus police station as well as housing offices and Res-Net support center.

The Main Campus residence halls are found in two different locations. On the east end of campus are the residence halls named after five of the [[Channel Islands of California|Channel Islands]]: [[Santa Rosa Island, California|Santa Rosa]], [[Santa Cruz Island|Santa Cruz]], [[Anacapa Island|Anacapa]], [[San Miguel Island|San Miguel]] and [[San Nicolas Island|San Nicolas]]. There are two dining commons located near the Channel Islands residence halls. The Ortega Dining Commons is located between San Miguel and the University Center [[UCSB UCen|(UCen)]], and the De La Guerra Dining Commons (better known as DLG) is located between Santa Rosa, Santa Cruz, and San Nicolas.

The two other residence halls, San Rafael and [[Manzanita Village]], are located on the west side of campus and primarily house continuing and transfer students. The Carrillo Dining Commons is located in [[Manzanita Village]], right next to San Rafael Hall. Manzanita Village was completed in 2002, and is the newest residence hall on campus.

In addition the University also has four housing complexes for Graduate students and their families: the recently completed San Clemente Villages for single graduate students, Santa Ynez Apartments, El Dorado Apartments, Westgate Apartments, and family student housing: West Campus Apartments and the Storke Apartment complexes. There is also Faculty Housing at the West Campus Point and new construction underway at the North Campus.

Students may also choose to rent housing in the bordering community of Isla Vista. An estimated average for rent costs is $500–$800 US/month to share a bedroom, and includes trash pickup and water utilities. Low-cost housing is limited, with the cheapest source being the [[Santa Barbara Student Housing Cooperative]].

Other sources of housing include the Greek System, and outlying communities (i.e. Goleta, Santa Barbara, Isla Vista, Montecito). Many students live in Isla Vista, which is immediately adjacent to campus. Isla Vista since the early 1960s has a reputation of being a party environment. UCSB is also affiliated with the [[Santa Barbara Student Housing Cooperative]] in Isla Vista, which seeks to provide low rent co-op housing regardless of gender, race, social, political, or religious affiliation, and thereby influencing the community to eliminate prejudice and discrimination in the community.

===Services===
There are a number of academic resources offered by the university, including a [[writing center]], open [[computer lab]]s, a [[machining|machine shop]], and drop-in academic advising.

A large Recreation Center provides classes and facilities for students and faculty. The Center has [[swimming pool]]s, [[racquetball]] courts, a rock wall, and exercise machines. The University Center has facilities for meetings and presentations, and also contains a bookstore, restaurants and a cashier.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.sa.ucsb.edu/ sa.ucsb.edu]&lt;/ref&gt;

UCSB has a health clinic. Students with ailments or seeking medical assistance may consult a physician at the clinic. The clinic also offers basic health care and provides emergency medicine and contraceptives. The university is the only UC campus with its own Paramedic Rescue Unit. It is staffed by full-time professional paramedics and part-time undergraduate [[Emergency medical technician|EMT]]s.

SexInfo, which was started in 1976 by Professors John and Janice Baldwin, is run by students doing advanced course work and research on [[Sexology|sexuality]] through UCSB's [[Sociology]] Department. The site is dedicated to providing accurate information about sexuality in a way that is both informative and personal. SexInfo answers questions sent in by readers from all over the world, as well as regularly updates and posts articles on various topics related to human sexuality. This program helps students getting their degree in psychology.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news | last=Snedden |first=Megan | title= A.S. Allocates Funds For Sex Ed, Foreign Affairs, Chilla Vista | url=http://www.dailynexus.com/article.php?a=12536 | date= November 14, 2006 | publisher=Daily Nexus | accessdate= November 17, 2007}} {{Dead link|date=September 2010|bot=H3llBot}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Athletics==
{{main|UC Santa Barbara Gauchos}}
The mascot of UCSB is the [[Gaucho]] and the school colors are blue and gold. UCSB's sports teams compete in the [[Big West Conference]], with the exception of the men's water polo, men's and women's swimming, and the men's volleyball teams, which are in the [[Mountain Pacific Sports Federation]]. Santa Barbara is best known for its women's [[basketball]] and [[UCSB soccer|men's soccer]] teams. In 2006, UCSB won their first NCAA Men's Soccer title and its second overall NCAA championship (1979 water polo) in school history.&lt;ref name=&quot;ncaas&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.ncaasports.com/soccer/mens/recaps/d1_1203_517049/2006|title=UC Santa Barbara 2, UCLA 1|accessdate=September 16, 2007|publisher=NCAA sports.com|year=2006|author=NCAA sports.com}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;
{{Cite news
|url=http://www.nytimes.com/2006/12/04/sports/soccer/04soccer.html
|title=Santa Barbara Rides Its Revival All the Way to the Championship
|newspaper=[[The New York Times]]
|accessdate=January 29, 2008
|last=Eligon
|first=John
|date=December 4, 2006
|postscript=&lt;!--None--&gt;
}}
&lt;/ref&gt;
[[Image:NewUCSBLogo.png|thumb|left|250px]]
While there are some 400 students in ICA, there are over 700 in Club Sports Teams including: [[Alpine skiing|Alpine Racing]], [[Cycling]], [[Fencing]], [[Field Hockey]], [[UC Santa Barbara Gauchos men's lacrosse|Lacrosse]], [[Roller Hockey]], [[Rugby union|Rugby]], [[Sailing]], [[Soccer]], [[Triathlon]], [[Ultimate Frisbee]], [[Water Ski]] and [[Rowing (sport)|Rowing]]. Many of these teams are highly regarded and compete against Intercollegiate teams from across the US. For example [[Rowing (sport)|Rowing]] has produced several national team members including Nine-time National Rowing Team member Amy Fuller, winner of several [[Olympic Games|Olympic]] and World Championship medals and currently head of the [[UCLA]] Rowing Program. The UCSB Cycling Team has also produced several national team members, Olympians, and members of numerous US and international professional teams.

Many other hundreds of students participate in a large Intramural program consisting of Badminton, Basketball, Bowling, Flag Football, Golf, Floor Hockey, Indoor and Outdoor Soccer, Racquetball, Squash, Running, Softball, Tennis, Table Tennis, Ultimate Frisbee, Volleyball, Inner tube water polo, and Kickball.

One non-sanctioned sport also draws many students to UCSB: surfing.  The on-campus beaches include a number of decent surfing sites, including &quot;Poles,&quot; &quot;Campus Point,&quot; &quot;Depressions&quot; and &quot;Sands&quot; and &quot;Devereaux Point&quot; on the west campus.  Because Campus Beach actually faces South and East, and is shielded by the Santa Barbara Channel Islands, the surf is usually quite small.  However, a large North or West swell can wrap in to create great waves which are typically very clean and good for surfing. UCSB has a surf team that competes in NSSA (National Scholastic Surfing Association) competitions, and is generally considered one of the best in the nation. They continued their reputation by winning a record 14th National Title at the college level in 2010's finals.

==People==
{{main|List of University of California, Santa Barbara people}}

===Student body===
''[[The Princeton Review]]'' rates the University of California, Santa Barbara with an Admission Selectivity of 95 out of 99 points.{{Citation needed|date=November 2007}} Admissions is classified as &quot;Most Selective&quot; by [[U.S. News &amp; World Report]]. The admitted students for Fall 2010 had an average [[SAT]] score of 1905 and an average high school GPA of 4.10, while the enrolled students for Fall 2010 had an average SAT score of 1817 and an average high school GPA of 3.92.&lt;ref name=&quot;glance&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.admissions.ucsb.edu/quickfacts.asp|title=UCSB Admissions|accessdate=April 15, 2011|publisher=University of California, Santa Barbara|year=2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; The application fee is $60. Applications can be completed on the Internet. 25% of admitted students receive federal [[Pell grant]]s.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news | title=Economic Diversity Among All National Universities | url=http://colleges.usnews.rankingsandreviews.com/usnews/edu/college/rankings/brief/natudoc_ecodiv_brief.php | newspaper=[[U.S. News &amp; World Report]]| accessdate= August 10, 2007 | postscript=&lt;!--None--&gt;}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Notable faculty===

The faculty of UCSB have received five [[Nobel Prize]]s since 1998, for landmark research in [[chemistry]], [[physics]], and [[economics]],&lt;ref name=&quot;nobel1&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://nobelprize.org/nobel_prizes/economics/laureates/2004/|title=The Sveriges Riksbank Prize in Economic Sciences in Memory of Alfred Nobel 2004|accessdate=September 16, 2007|publisher=The Nobel Foundation|year=2007|author=The Nobel Foundation}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;nobel2&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://nobelprize.org/nobel_prizes/physics/laureates/2004/|title=The Nobel Prize in Physics 2004|accessdate=September 16, 2007|publisher=The Nobel Foundation|year=2007|author=The Nobel Foundation}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;nobel3&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://nobelprize.org/nobel_prizes/chemistry/laureates/2000/heeger-autobio.html|title=Alan Heeger: The Nobel Prize in Chemistry 2000|accessdate=September 16, 2007|publisher=The Nobel Foundation|year=2007|author=The Nobel Foundation}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;nobel4&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://nobelprize.org/nobel_prizes/physics/laureates/2000/kroemer-autobio.html|title=Herbert Kroemer: The Nobel Prize in Physics 2000|accessdate=September 16, 2007|publisher=The Nobel Foundation|year=2007|author=The Nobel Foundation}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;nobel5&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://nobelprize.org/nobel_prizes/chemistry/laureates/1998/kohn-autobio.html|title=Walter Kohn: The Nobel Prize in Chemistry 1998|accessdate=September 16, 2007|publisher=The Nobel Foundation|year=2007|author=The Nobel Foundation}}&lt;/ref&gt; as well as a [[Fields Medal]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://stationq.cnsi.ucsb.edu/~freedman/ |title=Michael Freedman @ Microsoft Station Q |publisher=Stationq.ucsb.edu |date= |accessdate=January 22, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; In addition, there are 25 members of the [[United States National Academy of Sciences|National Academy of Sciences]],&lt;ref name=&quot;memb&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.nasonline.org/site/Dir/2110534239?pg=rslts|title=UCSB Membership list|accessdate=September 16, 2007|publisher=National Academy of Sciences|year=2007|author=National Academy of Sciences}}&lt;/ref&gt; 24 members of the [[National Academy of Engineering]],&lt;ref name=&quot;naoe&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.nae.edu/nae/naepub.nsf/Members%20By%20Parent%20InstitutionU?OpenView&amp;Start=1&amp;Count=30&amp;Expand=20#20|title=National Academy of Engineering Member Directory&amp;nbsp;— UCSB|accessdate=September 16, 2007|publisher=National Academy of Engineering|year=2007|author=National Academy of Engineering}}&lt;/ref&gt; and 21 members of the [[American Academy of Arts and Sciences|Academy of Arts and Sciences]] on the faculty.&lt;ref name=&quot;aaas&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.amacad.org/news/new2005.aspx|title=Academy Elects 225th Class of Fellows and Foreign Honorary Members|accessdate=September 16, 2007|publisher=The American Academy of Arts and Sciences|year=2005|author=The American Academy of Arts and Sciences}}&lt;/ref&gt;

*[[David Awschalom]], 2005 [[Buckley Prize]] winner and Director of [[California NanoSystems Institute]]
*[[Walter Capps|Walter Holden Capps]] (1934–1997)&amp;nbsp;— also known as Walter H. Capps&amp;nbsp;— Democrat. Religious Studies professor. U.S. Representative from California 22nd District, 1997; (defeated, 1994) died in office 1997
*[[Glen Culler]], Professor of [[Electrical Engineering]], principal investigator for UCSB ARPAnet
*[[Michael Freedman]], 1986 [[Fields Medal]]ist and director of [http://stationq.ucsb.edu/ Microsoft Station Q]
*[[Kip Fulbeck]], Professor of Art, author, and artist exploring [[Hapa]] identity
*[[Michael Gazzaniga]], Director of the SAGE Center for the Study of the Mind and Professor of [[Psychology]], leading researcher in the field of [[cognitive neuroscience]]
*[[Michael Frank Goodchild]], Professor of [[Geography]], winner of the 2007 [[Lauréat Prix International de Géographie Vautrin Lud]]
*[[David J. Gross]], Director of the [[Kavli Institute for Theoretical Physics]] and 2004 Nobel Laureate in [[Physics]]&lt;ref name=&quot;bio3&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.kitp.ucsb.edu/community/ITPBios/David.html|title=David J. Gross Biography|accessdate=September 16, 2007|publisher=University of California, Santa Barbara|year=2007|author=University of California, Santa Barbara}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*[[Alan J. Heeger]], Professor of [[Physics]] and of [[Materials]] and 2000 Nobel Laureate in [[Chemistry]]&lt;ref name=&quot;bio4&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.ipos.ucsb.edu/ajh.html|title=Alan J. Heeger Biography|accessdate=September 16, 2007|publisher=University of California, Santa Barbara|year=2007|author=University of California, Santa Barbara}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*[[Immanuel C.Y. Hsu]], [[sinologist]] and Emeritus Professor of [[History]]
*[[Jacob Israelachvili]], Professor of [[Chemical Engineering]] and [[Materials]], Elected Fellow of the [[Royal Society of London]], 1988{{Citation needed|date=April 2009}}
*[[Charles Kolstad]], Chair of the Economics Department and Professor of Environmental Economics
*[[Walter Kohn]], Founding director, Kavli Institute for Theoretical Physics, Research Professor of Physics and 1998 Nobel Laureate in Chemistry&lt;ref name=&quot;bio6&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.chem.ucsb.edu/people/faculty/kohn/index.shtml|title=Walter Kohn Biography|accessdate=September 16, 2007|publisher=University of California, Santa Barbara|year=2007|author=University of California, Santa Barbara}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*[[Herbert Kroemer]], Professor of [[Electrical and Computer Engineering]] and of Materials and 2000 Nobel Laureate in Physics&lt;ref name=&quot;bio5&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.ece.ucsb.edu/Faculty/Kroemer/default.html|title=Herbert Kroemer Biography|accessdate=September 16, 2007|publisher=University of California, Santa Barbara|year=2007|author=University of California, Santa Barbara}} {{Dead link|date=September 2010|bot=H3llBot}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*[[Finn E. Kydland]], Professor of [[Economics]] and 2004 Nobel Laureate in Economics&lt;ref name=&quot;bio2&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.econ.ucsb.edu/cgi-bin/faculty.cgi?f=kydland|title=Finn E. Kydland Biography|accessdate=September 16, 2007|publisher=University of California, Santa Barbara|year=2007|author=University of California, Santa Barbara}} {{Dead link|date=September 2010|bot=H3llBot}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*[[L. Gary Leal]], Warren &amp; Katharine Schlinger Professor of Chemical Engineering&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.chemengr.ucsb.edu/people/faculty_d.php?id=17 |title=UCSB – Chemical Engineering – People – L. Gary Leal |publisher=Chemengr.ucsb.edu |date= |accessdate=January 22, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*[[Bruce H. Lipshutz]], Professor of [[Chemistry]] and [[Biochemistry]]
*[[Harold Lewis]], [[Emeritus]] Professor of [[Physics]] and former department chairman
*[[William W. Murdoch]], Charles A. Storke II professor of [[population ecology]], recipient of the 1990 Robert H. [[MacArthur Award]], and [[American Academy of Arts and Sciences|AAAS]] Fellow known for his research in population regulation, biological control, and predator-prey relationships&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.lifesci.ucsb.edu/eemb/faculty/murdoch/murdoch_cv.pdf|format=PDF|title=Murdoch's UCSB Faculty Page| accessdate=December 8, 2008|publisher=www.lifesci.ucsb.edu}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*[[Shuji Nakamura]], Japanese inventor of the bright green, white and blue [[Gallium nitride|GaN]] [[Light-emitting diode|LED]]s and a blue laser. Recipient of the Millennium Technology Prize from the Finnish government in 2006&lt;ref name=&quot;bio7&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.materials.ucsb.edu/LINKS/PROFnakamura/|title=Shuji Nakamura Biography|accessdate=September 16, 2007|publisher=University of California, Santa Barbara|year=2007|author=University of California, Santa Barbara}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*[[John Nathan]], Takashima Professor of Japanese Cultural Studies and Emmy-award winning director of several documentaries{{Citation needed|date=May 2009}}
*[[Galen D. Stucky]], E. Khashoggi Industries, LLC Professor in Letters and Science, Professor of [[Chemistry]] and [[Biochemistry]], [[Materials]] Departments&lt;ref name=&quot;bio8&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.chem.ucsb.edu/people/faculty/stucky/index.shtml|title=Galen D. Stucky Biography|accessdate=February 22, 2008|publisher=University of California, Santa Barbara|year=2008|author=University of California, Santa Barbara}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*[[James Thomson (cell biologist)|James A. Thomson]], Adjunct Professor – Molecular, Cellular &amp; Developmental Biology, &quot;father of stem-cell research&quot;&lt;ref&gt;http://independent.com/news/2007/apr/20/ucsb-snags-father-stem-cell-research/&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;gallery perrow=&quot;5&quot;&gt;
Image:WalterKohnGraz21042006 1.jpg|[[Walter Kohn]], Nobel Prize in Chemistry (1998) for the contributions to the understandings of the electronic properties of materials
Image:David Gross cropped.JPG|[[David Gross]], Nobel Prize in Physics (2004) for the discovery of [[asymptotic freedom]]
Image:Kydland.jpg|[[Finn Kydland]], Nobel Prize in Economics (2004) for the contributions to dynamic [[macroeconomics]]
Image:Michael Freedman 2010.jpg|[[Michael Freedman]], Fields Medal (1986) for his work on the [[Poincaré conjecture]]
&lt;/gallery&gt;

===Notable alumni===


*[[Joseph M. Acaba]] — 1990 Astronaut on the [[STS-119]] Space Shuttle
*[[R.J.Q. Adams]] — 1972 Ph.D., historian
*[[Richard Anderson (basketball)|Richard Anderson]] — 1982, Former NBA basketball player
*[[Steve Aoki]] — Founder and owner of [[Dim Mak Records]] and [[electro house]] [[producer (music)|producer]] and [[DJ]]
*[[Brandon Baker]] — Actor
*[[Robert Ballard]] — 1965, Oceanographer, Discovered Titanic wreckage.
*[[David Boynton]] — 1967, Hawaiian naturalist, educator, photographer
*[[Benjamin Bratt]] — 1986, actor&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.ucsbalum.com/alum_dir_plus/notable/arts.html ]{{dead link|date=January 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*[[Lois Capps]] — 1990, M.A.,&lt;ref&gt;[http://bioguide.congress.gov/scripts/biodisplay.pl?index=c001036 CAPPS, Lois – Biographical Information], Biographical Directory of the United States Congress.&lt;/ref&gt; Congresswoman (D-Santa Barbara)
*[[Leroy Chiao]] — 1985 (masters), 1987 (doctorate), NASA astronaut, American engineer
*[[Steve Czaban]] - National Sports Radio Talk Show Host 
*[[Michael Douglas]] — 1968, [[Academy Award]] winning Actor and Producer, honorary Alumni Association President
*[[Josh Elliott]] — ESPN sports commentator
*[[Larry J. Estrada]] - 1968, Professor and  former mayor of [[Fort Collins, Colorado]]
*[[Alexei Filippenko]] — American astrophysicist and professor of astronomy at  UC Berkeley
*[[Morgan J. Freeman]] — 1992 (film studies), film director
*[[Carol Greider]] — 1983, B.A., awarded the 2009 Nobel Prize for Physiology or Medicine.
*[[Mike Hebert]] — 1966, University of Minnesota volleyball coach, former [[United States women's national volleyball team|U.S. National Team]] coach
*[[Jeffrey O. Henley]] — 1966, B.A., Economics, Chairman of Oracle Corporation
*[[Conner Henry]] — 1986, Former NBA basketball player (Rockets, Celtics, Bucks, Kings)
*[[Don Hertzfeldt]] — 1998, [[Academy Award]] nominated filmmaker
*[[Jared Huffman]] — California State Assemblyman
*[[Jack Johnson (musician)|Jack Johnson]] — 1997, Musician
*[[Jenna Lee]] — Fox News Anchor
*[[Harvey Levin]] — Attorney and host for ''The People's Court'', founder of ''[[TMZ.com|TMZ]]''
*[[Jason Lezak]] — 1999, U.S. Olympic Gold Medalist – Swimming
*[[Tony Lochhead]] — 2004, soccer player for New Zealand , played in the 2010 World Cup
*[[Jakob Lothe]] — 1977, famous Norwegian expert at comparative literature. Has since worked at [[Harvard University]] and [[University of Oxford]]
*[[Jasun Martz]] — Award-winning musician recorded with Michael Jackson, toured with Frank Zappa, arranged Starship's #1 hit, We Built This City
*[[Lon McEachern]] ESPN Sports Broadcaster, most notable for hand-by-hand commentary on the [[World Series of Poker]]
*[[Howard McGillin]] —  Tony-nominated stage, screen and television actor
*[[Jason Narvy]] — Actor
*[[Aaron D. O'Connell]] — Creator of the world's first [[quantum machine]]
*[[Peggy Oki]] — Surfer, painter, and environmental activist best known for being the only woman to skate as part of [[Z-Boys]]
*[[Gwyneth Paltrow]] — [[Academy Award]] winning Actress (attended, but did not graduate)
*[[George Perry (neuroscientist)|George Perry]] — B.A., Zoology, Dean at the [[University of Texas at San Antonio]] and leading Alzheimer´s disease researcher
*[[Ken Rinaldo]] —1958 (New Media Artist), professor
*[[Todd Rogers]] — 1996, U.S. Olympic Gold Medalist — Beach Volleyball
*[[Jim Rome]] — 1986, ESPN sports commentator, host of ESPN show ''Jim Rome is Burning''
*[[Robin Sax]] — 1993, author, legal analyst, commentator, former prosecutor
*[[Skip Schumaker]] — 2nd basemen for the [[St. Louis Cardinals]]
*[[Brian Shaw]] — Former NBA basketball player (Celtics, Magic, Heat, Lakers) and Lakers assistant coach
*[[Bob Sipchen]] 1976, Pulitzer Prize winning journalist, author (Baby Insane and the Buddha) and Communications Director, Sierra Club
*[[L. J. Smith (author)|L. J. Smith]] - 1987, young-adult literature writer
*[[Mark Andrew Smith]] — Graphic Novelist
*[[Ryan Spilborghs]] — Outfielder for the [[Colorado Rockies]]
*[[Charissa Thompson]] — Reporter for [[Fox Sports (USA)|Fox Sports]] and [[Big Ten Network]]
*[[Brian Townsend]] — Professional Poker Player and co-owner of [[CardRunners]]
*[[Knut Vollebæk]] — Former [[Foreign minister of Norway]]
*[[Joseph C. Wilson]] — Former U.S. diplomat
*[[Michael Young (baseball)|Michael Young]] — Perennial all star major league shortstop/third baseman for Texas Rangers
*[[Barry Zito]] — MLB pitcher for the San Francisco Giants; 2002 AL Cy Young Winner (Oakland Athletics)
*[[Julia Roberts]] — Actress 

&lt;gallery perrow=&quot;5&quot;&gt;

Image:Carol Greider 2009-01.JPG|[[Carol Greider]], Nobel Prize in Physiology or Medicine (2009)
Image:Michael Douglas Navy3.jpg|[[Michael Douglas]], Academy Award winning actor
Image:Bonnaroo08 jackjohnson2 lg.jpg|[[Jack Johnson (musician)|Jack Johnson]], Musician
Image:Robert Ballard.jpg|[[Robert Ballard]], Oceanographer, discovered the [[RMS Titanic]]
&lt;/gallery&gt;

==See also==
*[[List of Nobel laureates affiliated with the University of California, Santa Barbara]]
*[[University of California]]

==References==
{{Reflist|colwidth=30em}}

==External links==
{{Portal box|California|University}}
{{commons category|University of California, Santa Barbara|UCSB}}
*[http://www.ucsb.edu/ Official website]

{{coord|34.41254|-119.84813|display=title|type:edu}}

{{UCSB}}
{{University of California}}
{{Association of American Universities}}
{{Universities Research Association}}
{{APRU}}
{{Santa Barbara County Colleges and Universities}}
{{Public Ivy}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:California, Santa Barbara, University Of}}
[[Category:University of California]]
[[Category:University of California, Santa Barbara]]
[[Category:Association of American Universities]]
[[Category:Association of Public and Land-Grant Universities]]
[[Category:Educational institutions established in 1909]]
[[Category:Schools accredited by the Western Association of Schools and Colleges]]
[[Category:Visitor attractions in Santa Barbara, California]]
[[Category:Universities and colleges in Santa Barbara County, California]]

[[bg:Калифорнийски университет, Санта Барбара]]
[[ca:Universitat de Califòrnia, Santa Barbara]]
[[cs:University of California, Santa Barbara]]
[[da:University of California, Santa Barbara]]
[[de:University of California, Santa Barbara]]
[[es:Universidad de California en Santa Bárbara]]
[[fa:دانشگاه کالیفرنیا، سانتا باربارا]]
[[fr:Université de Californie à Santa Barbara]]
[[ko:캘리포니아 대학교 샌타바버라]]
[[hi:कैलिफोर्निया विश्वविद्यालय, सांता बारबरा]]
[[is:Kaliforníuháskóli í Santa Barbara]]
[[it:Università della California, Santa Barbara]]
[[ja:カリフォルニア大学サンタバーバラ校]]
[[no:University of California, Santa Barbara]]
[[pnb:یونیورسٹی آف کیلیوفورنیا سانٹا باربرا]]
[[pt:Universidade da Califórnia em Santa Bárbara]]
[[ru:Калифорнийский университет в Санта-Барбаре]]
[[simple:University of California, Santa Barbara]]
[[sh:University of California, Santa Barbara]]
[[fi:Kalifornian yliopisto (Santa Barbara)]]
[[sv:University of California, Santa Barbara]]
[[zh:聖塔芭芭拉加利福尼亞大學]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
