<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="21208262" ns="0" title="Western culture"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Original research|date=May 2009}}
{{two other uses||this article's equivalent regarding the East|Eastern culture|the Henry Cow album of the same name|Western Culture (album)}}
{{pp-move-indef}}
[[File:Da Vinci Vitruve Luc Viatour.jpg|thumb|200px|[[Leonardo da Vinci]]'s ''[[Vitruvian Man]]''. A symbol of the importance of [[humanism]] and [[empiricism]] in Western culture since the [[Renaissance]]]]
[[File:Platon-2b.jpg|thumb|200px|[[Plato]] along with [[Socrates]] and [[Aristotle]] were founding members of [[Western philosophy]].]]

'''Western culture''', sometimes equated with '''Western civilization''' or '''European civilization''', refers to [[culture]]s of [[Europe]]an origin and is used very broadly to refer to a [[Cultural heritage|heritage]] of [[social norms]], [[ethics|ethical values]], [[tradition|traditional customs]], [[religion|religious]] beliefs, [[political system]]s, and specific [[Cultural artifact|artifacts]] and [[technology|technologies]]. 

Western culture stems from two sources: the [[Classics|Classical Period]] of the the [[Graeco-Roman|Graeco-Roman era]] and the influence of [[Christianity]].  The artistic, philosophic, literary, and [[Western law|legal]] themes and traditions; the heritages of especially [[Latin Europe|Latin]], [[Celts|Celtic]], [[Germanic peoples|Germanic]], and [[Hellenistic civilization|Hellenic]] ethnic or linguistic groups; as well as a tradition of [[rationalism]] in various spheres of life, developed by [[Hellenistic philosophy]], [[Scholasticism]], [[Humanism]]s, the [[Scientific Revolution]] and [[Age of Enlightenment|Enlightenment]]; and including, in [[political thought]], widespread [[debate|rational arguments]] in favour of [[freethought]], [[human rights]], [[Egalitarianism|equality]] and [[democracy|democratic]].{{Citation needed|date=September 2009}} &lt;!-- for all the proceeding principles --&gt;

The term has come to apply to countries whose [[history]] is strongly marked by European immigration or settlement, such as [[the Americas]], and [[Australasia]], and is not restricted to Western Europe.

Historical records of western culture in its European geographical range begin with [[Ancient Greece]], and then [[Ancient Rome]], Christianization during the European [[Middle Ages]], and reform and modernization starting by [[Renaissance]], and globalized by successive [[Colonial empire|European empires]] that spread the European ways of life and education between the sixteenth and twentieth centuries. European Culture developed with a complex range of philosophy, medieval scholasticism and mysticism, Christian and secular humanism. Rational thinking developed through a long age of change and formation with the experiments of enlightenment, naturalism, romanticism, science, democracy, and socialism. With its global connection, European culture grew with an all-inclusive urge to adopt, adapt, and ultimately influence other trends of culture.

Some tendencies that have come to define modern Western [[societies]] are the existence of [[political pluralism]], prominent [[subcultures]] or [[counterculture]]s (such as [[New Age]] movements), and increasing cultural [[syncretism]] resulting from [[globalization]] and [[human migration]].

==Terminology==
{{See|Western world}}
[[File:GodfreyKneller-IsaacNewton-1689.jpg|thumb|[[Isaac Newton]] discovered [[universal gravitation]] and [[Newton's laws of motion|the laws of motion]].]]

The Greeks contrasted themselves to their [[Ancient Anatolia|Eastern neighbors]], such as the [[Troy|Trojans]] in ''[[Iliad]]'', setting an example for later contrasts between east and west. In the [[Middle Ages]], [[Islam]] in the [[Near East]] provided a contrast to the West though it had been [[Hellenization|Hellenized]] since the time of [[Alexander the Great]], and had been ruled by Rome and Constantinople and part of &quot;[[Christendom]]&quot;. 

In the later 20th to early 21st century, with the advent of increasing [[globalism]], it has become more difficult to determine which individuals fit into which category, and the East–West contrast is sometimes criticized as [[relativism|relativistic]] and arbitrary.&lt;ref&gt;[[Yin Cheong Cheng]], ''New Paradigm for Re-engineering Education''. Page 369&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[[Ainslee Thomas Embree]], [[Carol Gluck]], ''Asia in Western and World History: A Guide for Teaching''. Page xvi&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[[Kwang-Sae Lee]], ''East and West: Fusion of Horizons''&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Globalism]] has, especially since the end of the [[cold war]], spread western ideas so widely that almost all modern countries or cultures are to some extent influenced by aspects of western culture which they have absorbed. Recent stereotyped Western views of &quot;the West&quot; have been labelled ''[[Occidentalism]]'', paralleling [[Orientalism]], the term for the 19th century stereotyped views of &quot;the East&quot;.

Geographically, &quot;[[Western world|The West]]&quot; today would normally be said to include [[Western Europe]] as well as certain territories belonging to the [[Anglosphere]], the [[Hispanidad]], the [[Lusosphere|Lusofonia]] or the [[Francophonie]].

==History==
{{further|[[History of Western civilization]]}}
{{histphil}}
Western culture is neither [[homogeneous]] nor unchanging. As with all other cultures it has evolved and gradually changed over time. All generalities about it have their exceptions at some time and place. The organisation and tactics of the Greek [[Hoplites]] differed in many ways from the [[Roman legion]]s. The ''[[polis]]'' of the Greeks is not the same as the American [[superpower]] of the 21st century. The [[Gladiator|gladiatorial games]] of the [[Roman Empire]] are not identical to present-day [[football]]. The art of [[Erotic art in Pompeii and Herculaneum|Pompeii]] is not the art of [[Hollywood]]. Nevertheless, it is possible to follow the evolution and history of the West, and appreciate its similarities and differences, its borrowings from, and contributions to, other cultures of [[human]]ity.

Concepts of what is ''the West'' arose out of legacies of the [[Western Roman Empire]] and the [[Eastern Roman Empire]]. Later, ideas of the west were formed by the concepts of [[Christendom]] and the [[Holy Roman Empire]]. What we think of as Western thought today is generally defined as [[Greco-Roman]] and [[Judeo-Christian]] culture, and includes the ideals of [[the Renaissance]] and the [[Age of Enlightenment|Enlightenment]].

===The Classical West===
[[Image:Aleksander-d-store.jpg|thumb|left|[[Alexander the Great]]]]
[[File:Colosseum-exterior-2007.JPG|thumb|The [[Colosseum]] in [[Rome]]]]
The Classical West was Greco-Roman/Celtic/Germanic Europe.

In [[Homer|Homeric literature]], and right up until the time of [[Alexander the Great]], for example in the accounts of the [[Persian Wars]] of [[Greeks]] against [[Persia]]ns by [[Herodotus]], we see the [[paradigm]] of a contrast between the West and East.

Nevertheless the Greeks felt they were the most civilized and saw themselves (in the formulation of [[Aristotle]]) as something between the wild [[barbarians]] of most of Europe and the soft, slavish Easterners. Ancient Greek [[scientific method|science]], [[philosophy]], [[democracy]], [[classical architecture|architecture]], [[classical literature|literature]], and [[art]] provided a foundation embraced and built upon by the [[Roman Empire]] as it swept up Europe, including the [[Ancient Greece|Hellenic World]] in its conquests in the 1st century BC. In the meantime however, Greece, under Alexander, had become a capital of the East, and part of an [[empire]]. The idea that the later [[Eastern Orthodox Church|Orthodox]] or [[Eastern Christian]] cultural descendants of the Greek-speaking Eastern Roman empire, are a happy mean between Eastern slavishness and Western barbarism is promoted to this day, for example in Russia, creating a zone which is both Eastern and Western depending upon the context of discussion.

For about five hundred years, the Roman Empire maintained the [[Greek East]] and consolidated a Latin West, but an East-West division remained, reflected in many cultural norms of the two areas, including language. Although Rome, like Greece, was no longer democratic, the idea of democracy remained a part of the education of citizens, as if the emperors were a temporary emergency measure.

Eventually the empire came to be increasingly officially split into a Western and Eastern part, reviving old ideas of a contrast between an advanced East, and a rugged West. In the Roman world one could speak of three main directions; North (Celtic tribes and Parthians), the East (lux ex oriente), and finally South which implied danger, historically via the Punic wars (Quid novi ex Africa?) The West was peaceful – it contained only the Mediterranean.

With the rise of Christianity in the midst of the Roman world, much of Rome's tradition and culture were absorbed by the new religion, and transformed into something new, which would serve as the basis for the development of Western civilization after the fall of Rome. Also, Roman [[culture]] mixed with the pre-existing [[Celts|Celtic]], [[Germanic peoples|Germanic]] and [[Slavic peoples|Slavic]] cultures, which slowly became integrated into Western culture starting, mainly, with their acceptance of Christianity.

===The Medieval West===
[[File:Image-Charlemagne-by-Durer.jpg|thumb|right|right|[[Charlemagne]]]]
[[Image:1099jerusalem.jpg|thumb|right|[[Christendom]] and the [[Crusades]]]]
[[Image:Eertvelt, Santa Maria.jpg|thumb|left|The [[Age of Discovery|discovery of the New World]] by [[Christoper Columbus]]]]

The Medieval West was at its broadest the same as [[Christendom]], including both the &quot;Latin&quot; or &quot;Frankish&quot; West, and the Orthodox Eastern part, where Greek remained the language of empire. After the crowning of [[Charlemagne]], Charlemagne's part of Europe was referred to by its neighbors in Byzantium and the Muslim world as &quot;Frankish&quot;.

After the [[fall of Rome]] much of Greco-Roman art, literature, science and even technology were all but lost in the western part of the old empire, centered around [[Italy]], and [[Gaul]] ([[France]]). However, this would become the centre of a new West. Europe fell into political anarchy, with many warring kingdoms and principalities. Under the Frankish kings, it eventually reunified and evolved into [[feudalism]]. [[Charlemagne]] was crowned [[Holy Roman Emperor|Emperor of the Romans]] by the Pope in 800. His reign is associated with the [[Carolingian Renaissance]], a revival of art, religion, and culture through the medium of the [[Catholic Church]]. Through his foreign conquests and internal reforms, Charlemagne helped define both Western Europe and the Middle Ages. He is numbered as Charles I in the regnal lists of France, Germany (where he is known as Karl der Große), and the [[Holy Roman Empire]]. The re-establishment of a Western &quot;Roman&quot; imperium challenged the status of the [[Eastern Roman Emperor]] in [[Constantinople]] and strained relations between Eastern and Western Europe.

Much of the basis of the post-Roman cultural world had been set before the fall of the Empire, mainly through the integrating and reshaping of Roman ideas through Christian thought. The Greek and Roman [[Religion in ancient Rome|paganism]] had been completely replaced by [[Christianity]] around the 4th and 5th centuries, since it became the official State religion following the baptism of emperor [[Constantine I]]. [[Roman Catholic]] Christianity and the [[Nicene Creed]] served as a unifying force in [[Western Europe]], and in some respects replaced or competed with the secular authorities. Art and literature, law, education, and politics were preserved in the teachings of the Church, in an environment that, otherwise, would have probably seen their loss. The [[Roman Catholic Church|Church]] founded many [[cathedrals]], [[university|universities]], [[Monastery|monasteries]] and [[Seminary|seminaries]], some of which continue to exist today. In the [[Medieval]] period, the route to power for many men was in the Church.

In a broader sense, the [[Middle Ages]], with its fertile encounter between Greek [[reasoning]] and [[Levant]]ine [[monotheism]] was not confined to the West but also stretched into the old East, in what was to become the [[Muslim world|Islamic world]]. The philosophy and science of Classical Greece was largely forgotten in Western and Northern Europe after the collapse of the [[Western Roman Empire]], other than in isolated monastic enclaves (notably in Ireland, which had become Christian but which was never conquered by Rome).&lt;ref&gt;&quot;How The Irish Saved Civilisation&quot;, by Thomas Cahill, 1995&lt;/ref&gt; Although the Eastern [[Emperor Justinian]] (the last Emperor to speak Latin as a first tongue) closed [[the Academy]] in AD 529 (a date that is often cited as the end of Antiquity), the learning of [[Classical Antiquity]] was better preserved in the [[Byzantine]] [[Eastern Roman Empire]], whose capital at [[Constantinople]] stood for another millennium, before being captured by the [[Ottoman Turks]]. Justinian's [[Corpus Juris Civilis]] Roman civil law code was preserved in the East and Constantinople maintained trade and intermittent political control over outposts such as [[Venice]] in the West for centuries. Classical Greek learning was also subsumed, preserved and elaborated in the rising Islamic world, which gradually supplanted Roman-Byzantine control over the Mediterranean, Middle East, North Africa, Iberia and even Greece itself - becoming a dominant cultural-political force in those regions. Thus, from the margins of the Roman world much of the learning of classical antiquity was slowly reintroduced to Western Europe in the centuries following the collapse of the [[Western Roman Empire]]. Irish missionaries such as [[St Columba]] propagated Christianity and Latin learning in Western Europe during the [[Early Medieval Period]] and Byzantine Greeks and Islamic Arabs reintroduced texts from Antiquity to Western Europe during the [[Late Middle Ages]] and [[Renaissance of the 12th century]].

The rediscovery of the [[Roman law|Justinian Code]] in Western Europe early in the 10th century rekindled a passion for the discipline of law, which crossed many of the re-forming boundaries between East and West. Eventually, it was only in the [[Catholic]] or [[Franks|Frankish]] west, that [[Roman law]] became the foundation on which all legal concepts and systems were based. Its influence can be traced to this day in all Western legal systems (although in different manners and to different extents in the [[common law|common]] (England) and the [[civil law (legal system)|civil]] (continental European) legal traditions). The study of [[canon law]], the legal system of the Catholic Church, fused with that of Roman law to form the basis of the refounding of Western legal scholarship. The ideas of [[civil rights]], [[social equality|equality]] before the [[law]], [[equality of women]], [[procedural justice]], and [[democracy]] as the ideal form of [[society]] were principles which formed the basis of modern Western culture.

The West actively encouraged the spreading of [[Christianity]], which was inexorably linked to the spread of Western culture.  Owing to the influence of [[Muslim culture|Islamic culture]] and [[Islamic Golden Age|Islamic civilization]] — a culture that had preserved some of the knowledge of ancient [[Mesopotamia]], [[Ancient Egypt|Egypt]], [[Science and technology in ancient India|India]], [[Persian Empire|Persia]], [[Ancient Greece|Greece]], and [[Roman Empire|Rome]]— in [[Al-Andalus|Islamic Spain]] and [[History of Islam in southern Italy|southern Italy]], and in the [[Levant]] during the [[Crusades]], Western Europeans translated many [[Latin translations of the 12th century|Arabic texts into Latin]] during the Middle Ages. Later, with the [[fall of Constantinople]] and the [[Byzantine-Ottoman wars|Ottoman conquest of the Byzantine Empire]], followed by a massive exodus of Greek Christian priests and [[Greek scholars in the Renaissance|scholars]] to Italian towns like [[Venice]], bringing with them as many scripts from the Byzantine archives as they could, scholars' interest for the [[Greek language]] and classic works, topics and lost files was revived. Both the Greek and Arabic influences eventually led to the beginnings of the [[Renaissance]]. From the late 15th century to the 17th century, Western culture began to spread to other parts of the world by intrepid explorers and missionaries during the [[Age of Discovery]], followed by [[Imperialism|imperialists]] from the 17th century to the early 20th century.
{{-}}

===The Modern Era===
[[Image:Constitution_of_the_United_States,_page_1.jpg|thumb|150px|left|upright|The [[U.S. Constitution]]]]
[[File:Zeche Mittelfeld Ilmenau.jpg|thumb|right|upright|The [[Industrial Revolution]]]]
[[File:World 1910.jpg|thumb|right|upright|Western empires in 1910]]

Coming into the [[modern era]], the historical understanding of the East-West contrast - as the opposition of [[Christendom]] to its geographical neighbors - began to weaken. As religion became less important, and Europeans came into increasing contact with far away peoples, the old concept of Western Culture began a slow evolution towards what it is today. The [[Early Modern]] &quot;[[Age of Discovery]]&quot; in the 15th, 16th and 17th centuries faded into the &quot;[[Age of Enlightenment]]&quot; continuing into the 18th, both characterized by the military advantages coming to [[Europe]]ans from their development of [[firearms]] and other [[military technology|military technologies]]. The &quot;[[Great Divergence]]&quot; became more pronounced, making the West the bearer of [[science]] and the accompanying revolutions of [[technology]] and [[industrialisation]]. Western political thinking also, eventually spread in many forms around the world. With the early 19th century &quot;[[Age of Revolution]]&quot; the West entered a period of [[World empire]]s, massive economic and technological advance, and bloody international conflicts continuing into the 20th century.

As Europe discovered the wider world, old concepts adapted. The Islamic world which had formerly been considered &quot;the [[Orient]]&quot; (&quot;the East&quot;) more specifically became the &quot;[[Near East]]&quot; as the interests of the European powers for the first time interfered with [[Qing China]] and [[Meiji period|Meiji Japan]] in the 19th century.&lt;ref name=&quot;davison&quot;&gt;{{Cite journal |author=Davidson, Roderic H. |title=Where is the Middle East? |journal=Foreign Affairs |volume=38 |issue=4 |pages=665–675 |year=1960 |doi=10.2307/20029452 |postscript=. |jstor=20029452 |ref=harv}}&lt;/ref&gt; Thus, the [[First Sino-Japanese War|Sino-Japanese War]] in 1894–1895 occurred in the &quot;[[Far East]]&quot;, while the troubles surrounding the [[decline of the Ottoman Empire]] simultaneously occurred in the &quot;Near East&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;British archaeologist [[David George Hogarth|D.G. Hogarth]] published ''The Nearer East'' in 1902, which helped to define the term and its extent, including [[Albania]], [[Montenegro]], southern [[Serbia]] and [[Bulgaria]], [[Greece]], [[Egypt]], all the [[Ottoman Empire|Ottoman]] lands, the entire [[Arabian Peninsula]], and western parts of [[Iran]].&lt;/ref&gt; The &quot;[[Middle East]]&quot; in the mid-19th century included the territory east of the Ottoman empire but West of China, i.e. [[Greater Persia]] and [[Greater India]], but is now used synonymously with &quot;Near East&quot; in most languages.

===Religion In Modern Western Culture===
Religion in the meantime has waned considerably in Western Europe, where many are [[agnostic]] or [[atheist]]. Nearly half of the populations of the [[United Kingdom]] (44-54%), [[Germany]] (41-49%), [[France]] (43-54%) and the [[Netherlands]] (39-44%) are non-theist. However, religious belief in the United States is very strong, about 75-85% of the population,&lt;ref&gt;Zuckerman, P. 2005. [http://www.pitzer.edu/academics/faculty/zuckerman/atheism.html &quot;Atheism: Contemporary Rates and Patterns&quot;] Pitzer College. Retrieved: 2006-06-21.&lt;/ref&gt; as also happens in most of Latin America.

==Widespread influence==
[[File:Whitehouse north.jpg|left|thumb|The architecture of the [[White House]] deliberately recalls ancient Greek temples.]]
Elements of Western culture have had a very influential effect on other cultures worldwide. People of many cultures, both Western and non-Western, equate ''modernization'' (adoption of technological progress) with ''[[westernization]]'' (adoption of Western culture). Some members{{Who|date=June 2010}} of the non-Western world, such as M. K. Gandhi, have suggested that the link between technological progress and certain harmful Western values provides a reason why much of &quot;modernity&quot; should be rejected as being incompatible with their vision and the values of their societies. These types of argument referring to [[imperialism]] and stressing the importance of [[Freedom (philosophy)|freedom]] from it and the [[relativism|relativist]] argument that different cultural norms should be treated equally, are also present in Western philosophy.


{{-}}

==Music, art, story-telling and architecture==
[[File:Vatican City at Large.jpg|thumb|right|upright|[[Saint Peter's Basilica]]]]
[[File:First Folio.jpg|thumb|upright|left|[[Western literature]]. [[William Shakespeare]]'s ''[[First Folio]]'' pictured]]
[[File:Mona_Lisa,_by_Leonardo_da_Vinci,_from_C2RMF_retouched.jpg|thumb|right|upright|[[Western Art]]. The ''[[Mona Lisa]]'' pictured]]
[[File:Swanlake001.jpg|thumb|left|upright|[[Classical music]], [[opera]] and [[ballet]]. ''[[Swan lake]]'' pictured]]
[[File:Sears Tower ss.jpg|thumb|upright|left|[[Skyscrapers]]. [[Willis Tower]] pictured]]
[[File:Sydney Opera House - Dec 2008.jpg|thumb|upright|[[Sydney Opera House]].]]

Some cultural and artistic modalities are also characteristically Western in origin and form. While dance, music, visual art, story-telling, and architecture are human universals, they are expressed in the West in certain characteristic ways.

The [[symphony]], [[concerto]], [[sonata]], [[opera]] and [[oratorio]] have their origins in Italy. Many important musical instruments used by cultures all over the world were also developed in the West; among them are the [[violin]], [[piano]], [[pipe organ]], [[saxophone]], [[trombone]], [[clarinet]], and the [[theremin]].  The solo [[piano]], [[symphony orchestra]] and the [[string quartet]] are also important performing musical forms.

The [[ballet]] is a distinctively Western form of performance dance.&lt;ref&gt;Barzun, p 329&lt;/ref&gt; The [[ballroom dance]] is an important Western variety of dance for the elite. The [[polka]], the [[square dance]], and the Irish [[step dance]] are very well known Western forms of [[folk dance]].

Historically, the main forms of western music are European [[Folk music|folk]], [[choral]], [[classical music|classical]], [[Country music|country]], [[rock and roll]], [[Hip hop music|hip-hop]], and [[electronica]].

While epic literary works in verse such as the [[Mahabarata]] and Homer's [[Iliad]] are ancient and occurred worldwide, the [[novel]] as a distinct form of story telling only arose in the West &lt;ref&gt;Barzun, p. 380&lt;/ref&gt; in the period 1200 to 1750. Photography and the motion picture as a technology and as the basis for entirely new art forms were also developed first in the West.  The [[soap opera]], a popular culture dramatic form originated in the United States first on radio in the 1930s, then a couple of decades later on television.  The [[music video]] was also developed in the West in the middle of the twentieth century.

Important western architectural motifs include the [[Doric order|Doric]], [[Corinthian order|Corinthian]], and [[Ionic order|Ionic]] columns, and the [[Romanesque architecture|Romanesque]], [[Gothic architecture|Gothic]], [[Baroque]], and [[Victorian architecture|Victorian]] styles are still widely recognised, and used even today, in the West. Much of Western architecture emphasizes repetition of simple motifs, straight lines and expansive, undecorated planes. A modern ubiquitous architectural form that emphasizes this characteristic is the [[skyscraper]], first developed in New York and Chicago.

[[Oil painting]] is said to have originated by [[Jan van Eyck]], and [[perspective (graphical)|perspective]] drawings and paintings had their earliest practitioners in Florence.&lt;ref&gt;Barzun, p 73&lt;/ref&gt; In art, the [[Celtic knot]] is a very distinctive Western repeated motif. Depictions of the [[nude]] human male and female in photography, painting and sculpture are frequently considered to have special artistic merit. Realistic [[portrait]]ure is especially valued. In Western dance, music, plays and other arts, the performers are only very infrequently masked. There are essentially no taboos against depicting God, or other religious figures, in a representational fashion.

Many forms of [[popular music]] have been derived from [[African-Americans]], and their innovations of [[jazz]] and [[blues]] serve as the basis from which much of modern popular music was derived. [[Folklore]] [[folk music|and music]] during 20th and 19th centuries, initially by themselves, but later played and further developed together with White &amp; Black [[USA|American]]s, [[UK|British people]], and Westerners in general. These include [[jazz]], [[blues]] and [[rock music]] (that in a wider sense include the [[rock and roll]] and [[Heavy metal music|heavy metal]] genres), [[rhythm and blues]], [[funk]], [[Hip-Hop]], [[techno]] as well as the [[ska]] and [[reggae]] genres from [[Jamaica]]. Several other related or derived styles were developed and introduced by western [[pop culture]] such as [[Pop music|pop]], [[Heavy metal music|metal]] and [[dance music]].
Caribbean Hispanic music, such as [[Merengue (music)|merengue]], [[Bachata (music)|bachata]], [[Salsa music|salsa]], and more recently [[reggaeton]], from such countries as the Dominican Republic, Puerto Rico, Trinidad, Cuba, and Panama has been strongly influenced by African rhythms and melodies. Haiti's [[Compas music|compas]] is a genre of music that draws influence and is thus similar to its Caribbean Hispanic counterparts, with an element of jazz and modern sound as well.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|author=Dr. Christopher Washburne |publisher=University of Salsa |title=Clave: The African Roots of Salsa |accessdate=2006-05-23 |url=http://www.planetsalsa.com/university_of_salsa/clave/clave_roots.htm}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|publisher=Caravan Music |title=Guide to Latin Music |url=http://www.caravanmusic.com/GuideLatinMusic.htm |accessdate=2006-05-23}}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:Tango-Show-Buenos-Aires-01.jpg|thumb|right|200px|A couple dances the [[Culture of Argentina|Argentine]] [[Tango (dance)|Tango]].]]

Other well-known musical genres include the music played by [[Mariachi|Mexican mariachis]], the [[Argentine tango|Argentine]] and [[Uruguayan tango|Uruguayan]] [[tango music|tango]], North American [[jazz]] and Brazilian [[bossa nova]].

[[File:Guadalajara mariachis.jpg|thumb|left|200px|Mexican Mariachi joining three well-known western instruments: violins, guitars and trumpets]]

{{-}}

==Sport==
[[Image:Bull-leaping.jpg|thumb|left|The [[Bull-Leaping Fresco]] from the Great Palace at [[Knossos]], [[Crete]]. Sport has been an important part of Western cultural expression since [[Classical Antiquity]].]]
[[File:Donald Bradman australian cricket player pic.JPG|thumb|upright|Sir [[Don Bradman]], one of the great exponents of the game of [[cricket]].]]
[[File:Baron Pierre de Coubertin.jpg|thumb|upright|left|Baron [[Pierre de Coubertin]], founder of the [[International Olympic Committee]], and considered father of the modern [[Olympic Games]].]]
[[Image:World Cup 2006 German fans at Bochum.jpg|thumb|upright|[[German flag]]s waving at the [[2006 Football World Cup]].]]

Since [[Classical Antiquity]], sport has been an important facet of Western cultural expression. A wide range of sports were already established by the time of [[Ancient Greece]] and the military culture and the development of sports in Greece influenced one another considerably. Sports became such a prominent part of their culture that the Greeks created the [[Olympic Games]], which in ancient times were held every four years in a small village in the [[Peloponnese|Peloponnesus]] called [[Olympia, Greece|Olympia]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url= http://www.olympic.org/uk/games/ancient/index_uk.asp| title= Ancient Olympic Games}}&lt;/ref&gt; Baron [[Pierre de Coubertin]], a Frenchman, instigated the modern revival of the Olympic movement.&lt;ref name=&quot;H5&quot;&gt;Hill, p. 5&lt;/ref&gt; The first modern Olympics were held at [[1896 Summer Olympics|Athens in 1896]].

The Romans built immense structures such as the [[Colisseum]] in Rome to house their festivals of sport. The Romans exhibited a passion for [[blood sports]], as in the infamous [[Gladiator]]ial battles which pitted contestants against one another in a fight to the death. The Olympic Games revived many of the sports of [[Classical Antiquity]] - such as [[Graeco-Roman wrestling]], [[discus]] and [[javelin]].

The sport of [[Bullfighting]] is a traditional spectacle of Spain, Portugal, southern France and some Latin American countries which traces its roots to prehistoric [[bull worship]] and [[animal sacrifice|sacrifice]] and is often linked to [[Roman Empire|Rome]], where many human-versus-animal events were held. Bullfighting spread from Spain to its Central and South American colonies, and in the 19th century to France, where it developed into a distinctive form in its own right.

[[Jousting]] and hunting were popular sports in the Western Europe of the [[Middle Ages]], and the aristocratic classes of Europe developed passions for leisure activities. A great number of the popular global sports were first developed or codified in Europe. The modern game of [[golf]]  originated in Scotland, where the first written record of golf is [[James II of Scotland|James II]]'s banning of the game in 1457, as an unwelcome distraction to learning [[archery]].&lt;ref&gt;http://www.golf-information.info/history-of-golf.html History Of Golf&lt;/ref&gt; The [[Industrial Revolution]] which began in Britain in the 18th Century brought increased leisure time, leading to more time for citizens to attend and follow spectator sports, greater participation in athletic activities, and increased accessibility. These trends continued with the advent of mass media and global communication. The bat and ball sport of [[cricket]] was first played in England during the 16th century and was exported around the globe via the [[British Empire]]. A number of popular modern sports were devised or codified in Britain during the 19th Century and obtained global prominence - these include [[Ping Pong]],&lt;ref name=H2&gt;{{Harvnb |Hodges|1993| p=2}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Letts&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url=http://tabletennis.about.com/od/beginnersguide/a/history_of_tt.htm |title=A Brief History of Table Tennis/Ping-Pong|first=Greg |last=Letts  |work=About.com |publisher=The New York Times Company |accessdate=29 August 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; modern [[tennis]],&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.historyoftennis.net/history_of_tennis.html]&quot;&lt;/ref&gt; [[Association Football]], [[Netball]] and [[Rugby football|Rugby]].

Football (also known as [[soccer]]) remains hugely popular in Europe but has grown from its origins to be known as the &quot;world game&quot;. Similarly, sports such as cricket, rugby and netball were exported around the world, particularly among countries in the [[Commonwealth of Nations]], thus [[India]] and [[Australia]] are among the strongest cricketing nations, while victory in the [[Rugby World Cup]] has been shared among the Western Nations of New Zealand, Australia, South Africa and England.

[[Australian Rules Football]], an Australian variation of football with similarities to [[Gaelic football]] and [[Rugby football|rugby]] evolved in the British [[colony of Victoria]] in the mid-19th century. The United States also developed unique variations of English sports. English migrants took antecedents of [[baseball]] to America during the colonial period. The history of [[American football]] can be traced to early versions of [[rugby football]] and [[association football]]. Many games known as &quot;football&quot; were being played at colleges and universities in the United States in the first half of the 19th century&lt;ref name=histfoot&gt;{{Cite web| title = What it was was Football! | work = Georgetown Magazine | publisher = [[Georgetown University]] Library Special Collections | url = http://www.library.georgetown.edu/special-collections/archives/essays/football | accessdate = 20010-02-07}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=Completerugby&gt;Bath, Richard (ed.) ''The Complete Book of Rugby'' (Seven Oaks Ltd, 1997 ISBN 1 86200 013 1) p77&lt;/ref&gt; American football resulted from several major divergences from rugby, most notably the rule changes instituted by [[Walter Camp]], the &quot;Father of American Football&quot;.  [[Basketball]] was invented in 1891 by [[James Naismith]], a Canadian physical education instructor working in Springfield, Massachusetts in the [[United States]]. From these American origins, basketball has grown to be one of the great international participation sports.

Professionalism in sport in the West became prevalent during the 20th Century, further adding to the increase in sport's popularity, as sports fans began following the exploits of professional athletes through radio, television, and the internet—all while enjoying the exercise and competition associated with amateur participation in sports.

==Scientific and technological inventions and discoveries==
[[Image:Ba b747-400 g-bnle arp.jpg|thumb|175px|right|upright|[[Aircraft]] and [[Spaceflight|Space Travel]]]]
[[Image:Compact-Fluorescent-Bulb.jpg|thumb|175px|left|upright|[[Electricity]]]]
[[Image:Columbia Supercomputer - NASA Advanced Supercomputing Facility.jpg|thumb|175px|right|upright|[[Computers]]]]
[[Image:DNA orbit animated.gif|thumb|175px|left|upright|[[Evolution]] and [[genetics]]]]
[[Image:Operation Upshot-Knothole - Badger 001.jpg|thumb|175px|right|[[Nuclear power|Nuclear energy]] and [[Nuclear weapon|weapons]]]]
[[Image:Fibreoptic.jpg|thumb|175px|left|[[Telecommunication|Mass Communications]] and the [[Internet]]]]
[[Image:Einstein1921 by F Schmutzer 4.jpg|thumb|175px|right|[[Albert Einstein]], Physicist]]
[[Image:Mariecurie.jpg|thumb|175px|right|[[Maria Skłodowska-Curie]], Physicist–Chemist]]

A feature of Western culture is its focus on science and technology, and its ability to generate new processes, materials and material artifacts.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book| last=Holmes| first=Richard| title=The Age of Wonder:  How the Romantic Generation Discovered the Beauty and Terror of Science| publisher=Pantheon Books| place=New York | year=2008 |isbn=978-0-375-42222-5| ref=harv| postscript=&lt;!-- Bot inserted parameter. Either remove it; or change its value to &quot;.&quot; for the cite to end in a &quot;.&quot;, as necessary. --&gt;{{inconsistent citations}} }}&lt;/ref&gt;


It was the West that first developed steam power and adapted its use into factories, and for the generation of electrical power.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book| last=Jonnes| first=Jill| title=Empires of Light:  Edison, Tesla, Westinghouse and the Race to Electrify the World | publisher=Norton| place=New York | year=1997 |isbn=0-393-04124-7| ref=harv| postscript=&lt;!-- Bot inserted parameter. Either remove it; or change its value to &quot;.&quot; for the cite to end in a &quot;.&quot;, as necessary. --&gt;{{inconsistent citations}} }}&lt;/ref&gt; The electrical [[Electric motor|motor]], [[Electrical generator|dynamo]], [[transformer]], and electric light, and indeed most of the familiar electrical appliances, were inventions of the West. The [[Four-stroke cycle|Otto]] and the [[Diesel engine|Diesel]] internal combustion engines are products whose genesis and early development were in the West. [[Nuclear power]] stations are derived from the first [[atomic pile]] constructed in Chicago in 1942.

Communication devices and systems including the telegraph, the [[telephone]], radio, television, communication and [[Satellite navigation system|navigation satellites]], [[mobile phone]], and the [[Internet]] were all invented by Westerners.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book| last=Riordan| first=Michael| title=Crystal Fire:  The Birth of the Information Age | publisher=Random House| place=New York | year=2003 |isbn=0-375-50739-6| ref=harv| postscript=&lt;!-- Bot inserted parameter. Either remove it; or change its value to &quot;.&quot; for the cite to end in a &quot;.&quot;, as necessary. --&gt;{{inconsistent citations}} }}&lt;/ref&gt;  The pencil, ballpoint pen, [[Cathode ray tube|CRT]], [[LCD]], [[LED]], photograph, photocopier, [[laser printer]], [[ink jet printer]], [[plasma display]] screen and [[world wide web]] were also invented in the West.

Ubiquitous materials including [[concrete]], aluminum, clear [[glass]], [[synthetic rubber]], [[synthetic diamond]] and the plastics [[polyethylene]], [[polypropylene]], [[PVC]] and [[polystyrene]] were invented in the West. Iron and steel ships, bridges and skyscrapers first appeared in the West. [[Nitrogen fixation]] and [[petrochemicals]] were invented by Westerners.  Most of the [[Chemical element|elements]], were discovered and named in the West, as well as the contemporary [[Bohr model|atomic theories]] to explain them.

The [[transistor]], [[integrated circuit]], memory chip, and computer were all first seen in the West. The [[Longitude by chronometer|ship's chronometer]], the [[screw propeller]], the [[locomotive]], [[bicycle]], [[automobile]], and aeroplane were all invented in the West.  Eyeglasses, the telescope, the microscope and [[electron microscope]], all the varieties of [[chromatography]], [[Protein sequencing|protein]] and [[DNA sequencing]], [[computerized tomography|computerised tomography]], [[Nuclear magnetic resonance|NMR]], [[x-rays]], and light, ultraviolet and infrared [[spectroscopy]], were all first developed and applied in Western laboratories, hospitals and factories.

In medicine, [[vaccination]], [[anesthesia]], and all the pure [[antibiotics]] were created in the West. The method of preventing [[Rh disease]], the treatment of [[diabetes]], and the [[germ theory]] of disease were discovered by Westerners. The eradication of that ancient scourge, [[smallpox]], was led by a Westerner, [[Donald Henderson]]. [[Radiography]], [[Computed tomography]], [[Positron emission tomography]] and [[Medical ultrasonography]] are important diagnostic tools developed in the West.  Other important diagnostic tools of [[clinical chemistry]] including the methods of [[spectrophotometry]], [[electrophoresis]] and [[immunoassay]] were first devised by Westerners. So were the [[stethoscope]], [[electrocardiograph]], and the [[endoscope]]. [[Vitamins]], [[hormonal contraception]], [[hormones]], [[insulin]], [[Beta blocker]]s and [[ACE inhibitors]], along with a host of other medically proven drugs were first utilised to treat disease in the West. The [[double-blind]] study and [[evidence-based medicine]] are critical scientific techniques widely used in the West for medical purposes.

In mathematics, [[calculus]], [[statistics]], [[mathematical logic|logic]], [[Vector (geometric)|vector]], [[tensor]] and [[complex analysis]], [[group theory]] and [[topology]] were developed by Westerners. In biology, [[evolution]], [[chromosomes]], [[DNA]], [[genetics]] and the methods of [[molecular biology]] are creatures of the West.  In physics, the science of [[mechanics]] and [[quantum mechanics]], [[theory of relativity|relativity]], [[thermodynamics]], and [[statistical mechanics]] were all developed by Westerners. The discoveries and inventions by Westerners in [[electromagnetism]] include [[Coulomb's law]] (1785), the first [[Battery (electricity)|battery]] (1800), the unity of electricity and magnetism (1820), [[Biot–Savart law]] (1820), [[Ohm's Law]] (1827), and the [[Maxwell's equations]] (1871). The [[atom]], [[Atomic nucleus|nucleus]], [[electron]], [[neutron]] and [[proton]] were all unveiled by Westerners.

In finance, [[Double-entry bookkeeping system|double entry bookkeeping]], the [[limited liability company]], [[life insurance]], and the [[charge card]] were all first used in the West.

Westerners are also known for their explorations of the globe and space. The first expedition to [[Ferdinand Magellan|circumnavigate the Earth]] (1522) was by Westerners, as well as the first to set foot on the [[South Pole]] (1911), and the first human to [[Apollo 11|land on the moon]] (1969). The [[Mars Exploration Rovers|landing of robots on Mars]] (2004) and on an [[NEAR Shoemaker|asteroid]] (2001), and the [[Voyager 2|Voyager]] explorations of the outer planets ([[Uranus]] in 1986 and [[Neptune]] in 1989) were all achievements of Westerners.

Human rights development in two recent centuries enabled women and disadvantaged people to obtain education and use their intellectual potential. One of them is double Noble prize winner [[Maria Skłodowska-Curie]] (Poland) famous for her pioneering research on radioactivity, techniques for isolating radioactive isotopes, and the discovery of two elements, polonium and radium. In 1932 she founded a Radium Institute (now the Maria Skłodowska–Curie Institute of Oncology) in her home city, Warsaw.

==Themes and traditions==
[[File:Susquehanna steam electric station.jpg|thumb|right|upright|[[Power stations]] and [[factories]]]]
[[File:Mercedes-Benz SLR McLaren 2 cropped.jpg|thumb|right|upright|[[Automobiles]] and [[trains]]]]
[[File:Olympic flame at opening ceremony.jpg|thumb|right|upright|Codified [[sports]]. [[2004 Athens Olympics]] pictured.]]

Western culture has developed many themes and traditions, the most significant of which are:

* Greco-Latin classic letters, arts, architecture, philosophical and cultural tradition, that include the influence of  preeminent authors such as [[Plato]], [[Aristotle]], [[Homer]], [[Herodotus]], and [[Marcus Tullius Cicero|Cicero]], as well as a long [[Greek mythology|mythologic tradition]]
* A tradition of the importance of [[the rule of law]] which has its roots in [[Ancient Greece]].
* The [[Catholicism|Catholic]] and [[Protestantism|Protestant]] [[Christian]] cultural tradition and [[ethics|ethic]].
* [[Secular humanism]], [[rationalism]] and [[Age of Enlightenment|Enlightenment thought]], as opposed to traditionally preeminent [[Catholicism]] and [[Protestant Christianity]], religious and moral doctrines in lifestyle. Though such opposition has not fully ended, it set the basis for a new critical attitude and open questioning of religion, favouring [[freethinking]] and questioning of the church as an authority, which resulted in open-minded and reformist ideals inside, such as [[liberation theology]], which partly adopted these currents, and secular and political tendencies such as [[laicism]], [[agnosticism]], [[materialism]] and [[atheism]].
* Widespread usage of terms and specific vocabulary borrowed, based or derived from [[Greek and Latin roots]] or [[etymologies]] for almost any field of arts, science and human knowledge, becoming easily understandable and common to almost any European language, and being a source for inventing internationalized [[neologisms]] for nearly any purpose. It is not rare for full loan Latin phrases or expressions, such as ''in situ'', ''habeas corpus'' or ''tempus fugit'', to be in usage, many of them giving name to artistic or literary concepts or currents. The usage of such roots and phrases is standardized in giving official scientific names for biological [[species]] (such as ''[[Homo sapiens]]'' or ''[[Tyrannosaurus|Tyrannosaurus rex]]''). This shows a reverence for these languages, called [[classicism]].
* Generalized usage of some form of the [[Latin alphabet|Latin]] or [[Greek alphabet]]. The latter includes the standard cases of [[Greece]] and other derived forms, such as [[Cyrillic alphabet|Cyrillic]], the case of those Slavic Eastern countries of [[Eastern Christianity|Christian Orthodox]] tradition, historically under the [[Byzantine Empire|Byzantine]] and later [[Russia]]n [[czarist]] or [[Soviet Union|Soviet]] area of influence. Other variants of it are encountered for [[Gothic alphabet|Gothic]] and [[Coptic alphabet]]s, that historically substituted older scripts, such as [[Runic]], and [[Demotic (Egyptian)|Demotic]] or [[Hieroglyphic]] systems.
* [[Scholasticism]].
* [[Renaissance]] arts and letters.
* [[Natural law]], [[human rights]], [[constitutionalism]], [[parliamentarism]] (or [[presidentialism]]) and formal [[liberal democracy]] in recent times — prior to the 19th century, most Western governments were still monarchies.
* A large influence, in [[modern history|modern times]], of many of the ideals and values developed and inherited from [[Romanticism]]
* Several [[subculture]]s (sometimes deriving into urban tribes) and [[Counterculture|countercultural]] movements, such as [[Hippie|hippie lifestyle]] or [[New Age]], that have left several influences on contemporary mainstream or subcultural tendencies (some of them, especially in the mainstream, can become merely [[Aesthetics|aesthetic]]).

==See also==
{{Portalbox|Culture|Europe}}
*[[Eastern culture]]
*[[History of western civilization]]
*[[Western World]]
*[[Westernisation]]
*[[Western religion]]
*[[Western philosophy]]
*[[Globalization]]
*[[The Enlightenment]]
*[[Industrial Revolution]]
*[[Culture during the Cold War]]
'''Books:'''
*''[[Death of the West]]''
*''[[Death, Desire and Loss in Western Culture]]'' by [[Jonathan Dollimore]]

== Maps ==
&lt;gallery&gt;
File:Latin alphabet world distribution.svg|[[Latin alphabet]] world distribution. The dark green areas shows the countries where this alphabet is the sole main script. The light green shows the countries where the alphabet co-exists with other scripts

Image:LegalSystemsOfTheWorldMap.png|[[Legal Systems of the World]]
{{legend|#4ac|Civil law}}
{{legend|#c76|[[Common law]]}}
{{legend|#975|Bijuridical (civil and common law)}}
{{legend|#363|[[Customary law]]}}
{{legend|#fb3|[[Fiqh]]}}

File:Major religions distribution.png|Religions of the world, mapped by distribution.

File:Religion in the world.PNG|Map showing relative degree of religiosity by country. Based on a 2006-2008 worldwide survey by Gallup.

File:Human Language Families (wikicolors).png|Human language families
&lt;/gallery&gt;

==Notes==
{{Reflist|1}}

==References==
*Sailen Debnath, &quot;Secularism: Western and Indian,&quot;, ISBN 9788126913664, Atlantic Publishers, New Delhi
* Jones, Prudence and Pennick, Nigel ''A History of Pagan Europe'' Barnes &amp; Noble (1995) ISBN 0-7607-1210-7.
*{{Cite book|last= Ankerl |first= Guy |title= Global communication without universal civilization |origyear= 2000 |series= INU societal research |volume= Vol.1: Coexisting contemporary civilizations : Arabo-Muslim, Bharati, Chinese, and Western |publisher= INU Press |location= Geneva |isbn= 2-88155-004-5 |pages=|year= 2000|ref= harv|postscript= &lt;!-- Bot inserted parameter. Either remove it; or change its value to &quot;.&quot; for the cite to end in a &quot;.&quot;, as necessary. --&gt;{{inconsistent citations}} }}
* Barzun, Jacques ''From Dawn to Decadence: 500 Years of Western Cultural Life 1500 to the Present'' HarperCollins (2000) ISBN 0-06-017586-9.
* Merriman, John ''Modern Europe: From the Renaissance to the Present'' W. W. Norton (1996) ISBN 0-393-96885-5.
* Derry, T. K. and Williams, Trevor I. ''A Short History of Technology: From the Earliest Times to A.D. 1900'' Dover (1960) ISBN 0-486-27472-1.
*Eduardo Duran, Bonnie Dyran ''[http://books.google.com/books?id=qgVoY7mypa4C Native American Postcolonial Psychology]'' 1995 Albany: State University of New York Press ISBN 0791423530
* McClellan, James E. III and Dorn, Harold ''Science and Technology in World History'' Johns Hopkins University Press (1999) ISBN 0-8018-5869-0
* Stein, Ralph ''The Great Inventions'' Playboy Press (1976) ISBN 0-87223-444-4.
* Asimov, Isaac ''Asimov's Biographical Encyclopedia of Science and Technology: The Lives &amp; Achievements of 1510 Great Scientists from Ancient Times to the Present'' Revised second edition, Doubleday (1982) ISBN 0-385-17771-2.
* [[Ludwig Pastor|Pastor, Ludwig von]], ''History of the Popes from the Close of the Middle Ages; Drawn from the [[Vatican Secret Archives|Secret Archives of the Vatican]] and other original sources'', 40 vols. St. Louis, B. Herder (1898ff.)
* [[James Joseph Walsh|Walsh, James Joseph]], ''The Popes and Science; the History of the Papal Relations to Science During the Middle Ages and Down to Our Own Time'', Fordam University Press, 1908, reprinted 2003, Kessinger Publishing. ISBN 0-7661-3646-9  Reviews: [http://books.google.com/books?vid=02tZKPD5CJrIa31EgK&amp;id=G57Y1rlQVP0C&amp;pg=PT2&amp;lpg=PT2&amp;dq=%22the+popes+and+science%22 P.462] [http://www.pubmedcentral.nih.gov/articlerender.fcgi?artid=1407075]
*[Ankerl, Guy] (2000) :Coexisting Civilizations: Arabo-Muslim, Bharati, Chinese, and Western. INUPRESS, Geneva,119-244. ISBN 2-88155-004-5
*Duchesne, Ricardo (2011): ''[http://www.brill.nl/downloads/ToC-Duchesne-SCSS-28.pdf The Uniqueness of Western Civilization]'', Studies in Critical Social Sciences, Vol. 28, Leiden and Boston: Brill, ISBN 978-90-04-19248-5
*[[Victor Davis Hanson|Hanson, Victor Davis]]; Heath, John (2001): ''Who Killed Homer: The Demise of Classical Education and the Recovery of Greek Wisdom'', Encounter Books
*Stearns, P.N. (2003): ''Western Civilization in World History'', Routledge, New York
*[[Bruce Thornton|Thornton, Bruce]] (2002): ''Greek Ways: How the Greeks Created Western Civilization'',  Encounter Books

{{Western culture}}
{{Use dmy dates|date=March 2011}}

{{Commons category|Western culture}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Western Culture}}
[[Category:Western culture| ]]
[[Category:Classical studies]]
[[Category:Cultural anthropology]]
[[Category:Sociology]]

[[ar:الحضارة الغربية]]
[[bo:ནུབ་ཕྱོགས་རྒྱལ་ཁབ་ཀྱི་རིག་གནས།]]
[[ca:Cultura occidental]]
[[cs:Západní kultura]]
[[el:Δυτικός πολιτισμός]]
[[fr:Civilisation occidentale]]
[[ko:서양 문화]]
[[hi:पश्चिमी संस्कृति]]
[[hr:Zapadna kultura]]
[[id:Budaya Barat]]
[[he:תרבות המערב]]
[[it:Civiltà occidentale]]
[[kn:ಪಾಶ್ಚಾತ್ಯ ಸಂಸ್ಕೃತಿ]]
[[ms:Kebudayaan Barat]]
[[nl:Westerse cultuur]]
[[ja:西洋文明]]
[[pl:Cywilizacja łacińska]]
[[pt:Cultura ocidental]]
[[sh:Zapadna kultura]]
[[fi:Länsimainen kulttuuri]]
[[sv:Västerländsk kultur]]
[[te:పాశ్చాత్య సంస్కృతి]]
[[yi:מערב וועלט]]
[[zh:西方文化]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
