<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="212177" ns="0" title="ITV1"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{About|the brand name used for the ITV Network in the English regions, Wales, Southern Scotland, Isle of Man and Channel Islands|the brand name used in Central and Northern Scotland|STV (TV network)|the brand name used in Northern Ireland|UTV|the variation used in the Channel Islands|Channel Television}}
{{Infobox television channel
| name              = ITV1
| logofile          = ITV1.svg 
| logosize          = 200px
| logocaption       = 
| logo2             =
| launch            = 28 October 2002 
| closed date       = 
| picture format    = [[576i]] ([[SDTV]]);&lt;br&gt;[[1080i]] ([[HDTV]])
| share             = '''ITV Network:'''&lt;br&gt;16.0%&lt;br&gt;0.7% (+1)&lt;br&gt;1.0% (HD)&lt;br&gt;
| share as of       = October 2011
| share source      = [http://www.barb.co.uk/report/monthlyViewing?_s=4 BARB]
| network           = [[ITV]]
| owner             = [[ITV plc]]
| parent            =
| key people        =
| slogan            = &quot;The Brighter Side&quot;
| motto             = 
| country           = United Kingdom
| language          = [[English language|English]]
| broadcast area    = [[English regions]],&lt;br /&gt; [[Scotland|Southern Scotland]],&lt;br /&gt; [[Wales]],&lt;br /&gt; [[Isle of Man]], &lt;br /&gt; and the &lt;br /&gt; [[Channel Islands]]
| affiliates        = 
| headquarters      = [[London]], [[England]]
| former names      = 
| replaced names    = [[Anglia Television|Anglia]], [[Border Television|Border]], [[Carlton Television|Carlton]], [[Central Independent Television|Central]], [[Channel Television|Channel]], [[Granada Television|Granada]], [[ITV Wales &amp; West|HTV]], [[London Weekend Television|LWT]], [[Meridian Broadcasting|Meridian]], [[Tyne Tees Television|Tyne Tees]], [[Westcountry Television|Westcountry]] and [[Yorkshire Television|Yorkshire]]&lt;br /&gt;(on 28 October 2002)
| replaced by names = 
| sister names      = [[ITV1 HD]]&lt;br&gt;[[ITV2]]/[[ITV2#ITV2 HD|ITV2 HD]]&lt;br&gt;[[ITV3]]/[[ITV3#ITV3 HD|ITV3 HD]]&lt;br&gt;[[ITV4]]/[[ITV4#ITV4 HD|ITV4 HD]]&lt;br&gt;[[CITV]]
| timeshift names   = ITV1+1
| web               = {{url|itv.com/itv1}}
| terr serv 1       = [[Analogue terrestrial television in the United Kingdom|Analogue]]
| terr chan 1       = Channel 3&lt;br&gt;&lt;small&gt;(Phased out nationwide by 2012)&lt;/small&gt;
| terr serv 2       = [[Freeview (UK)|Freeview]]
| terr chan 2       = Channel 3&lt;br&gt;Channel 33 (+1)&lt;br&gt;Channel 51 (HD)
| sat serv 1        = [[Freesat]]
| sat chan 1        = Channel 103&lt;br&gt;Channel 112 (+1)&lt;br /&gt;Channel 119 (HD)&lt;br&gt;Channel 997 ([[Audio description|AD]]) &lt;small&gt;(ITV1 London)&lt;/small&gt;
| sat serv 2        = [[Sky (UK &amp; Ireland)|Sky]]
| sat chan 2        = Channel 103 &lt;br&gt;Channel 114 (+1)&lt;br /&gt;Channel 178 (HD)&lt;/small&gt;&lt;br&gt;Channel 993 (AD) &lt;small&gt;(ITV1 London)&lt;/small&gt;
| sat serv 3        = [[Astra 2D]]|
| sat chan 3        = 10758V 22000 5/6 &lt;br /&gt;10832H 22000 5/6 (HD)
| cable serv 1      = [[Virgin Media]]
| cable chan 1      = Channel 103&lt;br&gt;Channel 114 (+1)&lt;br /&gt;Channel 113 (HD)&lt;br&gt;Channel 853 (AD) &lt;small&gt;(ITV1 London)&lt;/small&gt;
| cable serv 2      = [[Smallworld Cable]]
| cable chan 2      = Channel 103&lt;br&gt;Channel 126 (+1)&lt;br&gt;Channel 107 (HD)
| cable serv 3      = [[Naxoo]]&lt;br&gt;&lt;small&gt;(Switzerland)&lt;/small&gt;
| cable chan 3      = Channel 217 &lt;small&gt;(ITV1 London)&lt;/small&gt;
| cable serv 4      = [[UPC Cablecom]]&lt;br&gt;&lt;small&gt;(Switzerland)&lt;/small&gt;
| cable chan 4      = Channel 159/175 &lt;small&gt;(ITV1 London)&lt;/small&gt;
| cable serv 5      = UPC [[Poland]]
| cable chan 6      = Channel 853 &lt;small&gt;(ITV1 London)&lt;/small&gt;
| iptv serv 1       = [[Freewire]]
| iptv chan 1       = Channel 103
| iptv serv 2       = [[TalkTalk TV]]
| iptv chan 2       = Channel 3&lt;br&gt;Channels 971-985 &lt;small&gt;(ITV1 regions)&lt;/small&gt;
| online serv 1     = [[itv.com]]
| online chan 1     = [http://www.itv.com/itv1 Watch live]&lt;br&gt;&lt;small&gt;(ITV1 London, UK only)&lt;/small&gt;
| online serv 2     = [[TVCatchup]]
| online chan 2     = [http://www.tvcatchup.com/watch.html?c=3 Watch live]&lt;br&gt;&lt;small&gt;(ITV1 London, UK only)&lt;/small&gt;&lt;br&gt;[http://www.tvcatchup.com/watch.html?c=64 Watch live]&lt;br&gt;&lt;small&gt;(ITV1+1, UK only)&lt;/small&gt;
| online serv 3     = [[ITV Player]]
| online chan 3     = [http://www.itv.com/itvplayer/ Catch up]
}}
'''ITV1''' is a generic brand that is used by twelve franchises of the [[United Kingdom|British]] [[ITV]] [[television network|Network]] in the [[English regions]], [[Wales]], southern [[Scotland]] ([[Dumfries and Galloway|Dumfries &amp; Galloway]] and [[Scottish Borders|the Scottish Borders]]), the [[Isle of Man]] and the Bailiwicks of [[Jersey]] and [[Guernsey]]. The ITV1 brand was introduced by [[Carlton Communications|Carlton]] and [[Granada (company)|Granada]] in 2001, alongside the regional identities of their eleven regional companies. ITV1 replaced these regional brands completely in October 2002, before Granada and Carlton merged to form ITV plc in 2004. The brand is also used by the non-ITV plc owned [[Channel Television]]. The ITV1 brand, however, should be distinguished from the UK-wide [[ITV]], of which ITV1 forms a large proportion.

ITV1 and its predecessor channels (collectively known simply as ITV from 1955 to 2001, and always treated as a single channel for ratings purposes), have contended with [[BBC One]] for the status of the UK's most watched television channel since the 1950s. However in line with other terrestrial channels, ITV1's audience share has fallen in the era of multi-channel television.

==History==
{{Main|History of ITV}}
Following the creation of the Television Act in 1954, the establishment of a commercial television service in the UK began.

The &quot;Independent Television&quot; service was made up of regions, with each region run by different companies. The three largest regions (London, the Midlands and the North of England) were subdivided into weekday and weekend services, with a different company running each. ITV existed in a region-heavy form from its inception to the 2000s, although the switch was gradual.

ITV1 became the generic on-screen brand name used by the twelve franchises of the [[ITV]] Network in the United Kingdom. The brand was introduced in 2001 by [[Carlton Communications|Carlton]]- and [[Granada Ltd.|Granada]]-owned franchises, initially used alongside the local regional name. However, it became the sole on-air identity in 2002 when the two companies decided to create a single unified playout of the channel, with regional references only used prior to regional programming. Carlton and Granada went on to [[merger|merge]] in 2004, creating [[ITV plc]] which now owns eleven of the fifteen regional ITV licences. 

The ITV1 name was only used in England, Wales, [[Scotland|Southern Scotland]] and [[Isle of Man]] until [[Channel Television]] adopted the name in January 2006, bringing it to the [[Channel Islands]]. It should be noted, however, that as national continuity is often used on Channel Television, ITV1 national branding had been seen on the station for several years previously.

The franchises that use the ITV1 brand are [[Anglia Television]], [[Border Television]], [[Carlton Television]], [[Central Independent Television]], [[Channel Television]], [[Granada Television]], [[HTV]], [[London Weekend Television]], [[Meridian Broadcasting]], [[Tyne Tees Television]], [[Westcountry Television]] and [[Yorkshire Television]]. 

[[HTV]] is the only exception using the name ''ITV1 Wales'' at all times for the Welsh part of its broadcast area, as it has a higher regional commitment, although recently the ''ITV1 Wales'' name is only used on Breakbumpers and regionally advertised programmes. Non ITV plc-owned franchises on the network generally do not refer to the ITV1 name.

The companies which represent ITV1 produce programming under the [[Granada Productions|ITV Studios]] and Granada brands.

==Corporate unification==
[[Image:ITV share of viewing 1992-2007.png|thumb|left|200px|ITV1 share of viewing 1992-2007 BARB figures]]
[[Image:Itvplc formation.png|200px|thumb|left|Flow diagram displaying consolidation of ITV franchises into ITV plc]]

ITV1 was formed by the unification of eleven of the ITV licences. The [[Broadcasting Act 1990]] changed many of the rules regulating the ITV Network, which most notably relaxed franchise ownership and hours of production. However as far back as 1974, Yorkshire Television and its [[North East England|North East]] neighbour, Tyne Tees Television, formally created [[Trident Television]], a merged entity of the two companies. By 1981 due to regulation, the company was forced to de-merge, however they resumed their alliance in 1993 as [[Yorkshire-Tyne Tees Television]], which therefore owned the two franchises and integrated the two company's assets more than its predecessor.
 
However, the intense race to own more of the ITV Network began in 1994 when [[Carlton Communications]], the owner of London weekday broadcaster [[Carlton Television]], took control of [[Central Independent Television]] in the [[English Midlands|Midlands]]. Literally days afterwards, [[Granada Ltd.|Granada plc]], owner of [[Granada Television]] of the [[North West England|North West]] purchased [[London Weekend Television]]. [[Meridian Broadcasting|Meridian's]] owner, [[Mills and Allen International]], then went on to purchase [[Anglia Television]] in the same year, before merging to become [[United News and Media]] (UNM) in 1995. UNM then went on to purchase Wales and [[West of England|West]] broadcaster, [[HTV]] in 1996, while Carlton purchased [[Westcountry Television]] later that year. Granada then agreed a deal to take over [[Yorkshire-Tyne Tees Television]] in 1997, giving the broadcaster access to both [[Yorkshire]] and [[North East of England|North East]] franchises. 

There was no movement in the take-over of franchises until 2000 when [[Border Television]] and all of its [[radio]] assets were sold to [[Capital Radio Group]], who consequently sold the television broadcasting arm to Granada Media Group. Granada then went on to purchase all of UNM's television interests (including its ITV franchises), which brought [[Meridian Broadcasting|Meridian]], [[Anglia Television|Anglia]] and [[HTV]] into its power, however due to regulation Granada was forced to sell HTV to Carlton. By this time, all of the franchises in England and Wales were owned by either Carlton or Granada.

In 2004, [[Granada plc]] officially merged with [[Carlton Communications]], creating [[ITV plc]], although it was a takeover by Granada in effect.

===Regional variations===
ITV1 consists of eleven franchises in England and Wales which broadcast regional news and other local programming to its area. Many franchise areas in England previously had sub-regions providing separate regional news bulletins. For example, the Anglia region was divided into West and East. This arrangement came to an end in February 2009 when ITV implemented plans to save the company £40m a year on the amount it spent making local news.

Since 27 October 2002, all ITV plc-owned franchises, regional programming is either preceded or plugged by an oral regional announcement, in the format ITV1 ''regional brand'', e.g. ITV1 Granada. In English regions, up until 13 November 2006, regional names were also superimposed (post-production) on these idents below the ITV1 logo, however this practice has since ceased. ITV Wales remains unaffected and still continues to use dual-branding across all of its on-screen presentation. Despite the lack of regional names on screen, the regional name is usually spoken by the [[continuity announcer|announcer]] prior to local programmes. After ITV's unification in 2002, the two London franchises, [[Carlton Television]] and [[London Weekend Television]] were [[merger|merged]] into a single entity, [[ITV London]], while the Wales and West franchise lost its official identity and instead was substituted with ITV Wales and ITV West on-air, with no reference linking the two together.

Although Channel Television have adopted the ITV1 brand on-air, announcements are still referred to &quot;Channel Television&quot;. Channel Television is the only franchise not owned by ITV plc to use the brand.

Areas with full ITV1 branding and continuity:

{| class=&quot;wikitable&quot;
|-
!Broadcast area
!Pre-ITV1 branding
!Post-ITV1 branding
|-
|English-Scottish border/Isle of Man||[[Border Television|Border]]||ITV1
|-
|North East England||[[Tyne Tees Television|Tyne Tees]]||ITV1
|-
|Yorkshire and Lincolnshire||[[Yorkshire Television|Yorkshire]]||ITV1
|-
|North West England||[[Granada Television|Granada]]||ITV1
|-
|Wales||[[HTV|HTV Wales]]||ITV1 Wales
|-
|West of England||[[HTV|HTV West]]||ITV1
|-
|The Midlands||[[Central Independent Television|Central]]||ITV1
|-
|East of England||[[Anglia Television|Anglia]]||ITV1
|-
|London (weekdays)||[[Carlton Television|Carlton]]||ITV1
|-
|London (weekends)||[[London Weekend Television|LWT]]||ITV1
|-
|South and South East England||[[Meridian Broadcasting|Meridian]]||ITV1
|-
|South West England||[[Westcountry Television|Westcountry]]||ITV1
|}
In the English regions, the channel has been known since 2006 as ITV1 at all times. Regional references no longer appear before any programming at all in these areas.

* The ''ITV1 Wales'' name is not used overnight.

Areas without full ITV1 branding and continuity:

{| class=&quot;wikitable&quot;
|-
!Broadcast area
!Present Branding
!Former Branding
|-
|Channel Islands||ITV1 ([[Channel Television]])||[[Channel Television]]**
|-
|Northern Ireland||[[UTV]]||Ulster Television***
|-
|Northern Scotland||[[STV (TV network)|STV (North)]]||[[Grampian Television]]
|-
|Central Scotland||[[STV (TV network)|STV (Central)]]||[[Scottish Television]]
|}
&lt;small&gt;**Channel Television use the ITV1 logo on all idents, promotions, ECPs, etc.&lt;/small&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;small&gt;***UTV uses the ITV1 branding between the end of the teleshopping strand at around 2.30am until the end of [[ITV Breakfast]]. UTV Branding is used from 9:25am–2:30am daily.&lt;/small&gt;

===Proposed regional changes===
In June 2007, ITV plc executive chairman [[Michael Grade]] hinted at a possible re-structure of the ITV regional layout, stating the existence of smaller regional services &quot;no longer makes sense&quot; relative to the regional audience they serve.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news 
  | title = Grade hints at ITV region restructure
  | publisher = [[Digital Spy]]
  | date = 12 September 2007
  | url = http://www.digitalspy.co.uk/broadcasting/a63355/grade-hints-at-itv-region-restructure.html
  | accessdate = 2007-09-12}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The plan was confirmed in September 2007, reducing the number of regional news programmes from 17 to just 9, saving around £35 to £40 million each year, and affecting every ITV plc regional company with the exception of [[ITV London]], [[HTV|ITV Wales]] and [[Granada Television|ITV Granada]]. These changes were implemented in early 2009. All sub-regional news programmes ceased, [[Border Television|ITV Border]]'s ''[[Lookaround]]'' programme was merged with [[Tyne Tees Television|ITV Tyne Tees]]' ''[[North East Tonight]]'' programme, [[Westcountry Television|ITV Westcountry]]'s ''[[Westcountry Live]]'' merged with [[HTV|ITV West]]'s ''[[The West Tonight]]'' programme, and [[Meridian Broadcasting|ITV Meridian]]'s ''[[Meridian Tonight]]'' south and south east editions merged with [[ITV Thames Valley]]'s ''[[Thames Valley Tonight]]''.

Pre-recorded sub-regional opt-outs are included in most of these new regions - a practice that has been used by [[Westcountry Television|Westcountry]] since their launch in 1993. Future job losses are currently unknown.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news 
  | title = ITV to merge regional newsrooms
  | publisher = BBC News
  | date = 12 September 2007
  | url = http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/business/6991206.stm
  | accessdate = 2007-09-12}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Branding==
{{Main|History of ITV television idents}}
From the founding of the ITV Network in 1955, it was known nationally as Independent Television (later ITV) and locally by the regional branding of the local ITV franchise operator.  

In 1989, the ITV Association set out a generic presentation package with a new &quot;ITV&quot; logo, which included [[Station identification|idents]], promotions and general on and off air design, and an edit of this package was designed for each franchise holder. The dual branded idents included a large &quot;ITV&quot; logo, in which the &quot;V&quot; contained part of the franchise's logo, and written below the logo in a grey capitalised font was the name of the regional broadcaster. However, only half of the regional broadcasters opted to use the package, which had completely failed by 1997.  

In 1999, another second common presentation package (once again using dual-branding with the ITV name) was launched, under the theme, &quot;TV From The Heart&quot;. Like the 1989 attempt, a version was created for every franchise holder, however it was only taken by nine of the fifteen ITV broadcasters, two of which resorted to other designs, being [[London Weekend Television]], which actually used the look for a year but then adopted a more original look (claiming it &quot;wasn't exciting enough&quot;), and [[HTV]] which adopted Carlton's identity when it was purchased by the company in 2001. Carlton, owner of three ITV licences at the time, did not adopt the generic look and instead used another package designed by [[Lambie-Nairn]], which again followed the &quot;TV from the Heart&quot; theme, however with more emphasis on the Carlton corporate identity. 

By 2001, all eleven franchises of England and Wales were owned by either [[Granada plc]] or [[Carlton Communications]], and a new common name, '''ITV1''', was launched on 11 August 2001 to coincide with digital channel [[ITV2]]. The existing &quot;Hearts&quot; idents were simply re-edited.

However from 28 October 2002, in England, the Scottish/English Border and Isle of Man (where all the franchises are owned by [[ITV plc]]), the station dropped regional branding and identification before most programming and adopted a unified national branding of ITV1. In Wales, although the [[HTV]] name has been dropped, some regional identification remains in the form of [[HTV|ITV1 Wales]]. At this time all regional continuity announcers were replaced with a single team of six national continuity announcers. Since the re-brand of 2006, that team has been reduced to just four.

===ITV Day===
In 2005, ITV plc introduced a new channel branding called [[ITV Day]] , used to identify ITV1 between 9.25am and 5.00pm. ITV Day was treated as a separate entity to ITV1 and featured its own presentation set focusing using the colours of red, orange and yellow and featured scenes of typical &quot;daytime&quot; activities. Promotions were used in a similar format to ITV1, and all daytime programmes advertised within ITV1 hours were branded with the ITV Day logo. A similar &quot;UTV Day&quot; branding was adopted in Northern Ireland.

===ITV1 (2006–present)===
In January 2006, the channel adopted a new on-air look to coincide with the launch of [[ITV4]], designed mainly to improve cross-channel promotion across ITV's multichannel presence. The new logo brought ITV1, [[ITV2]] and [[ITV3]] in line with [[ITV4]]'s, and had been observed on various billboard ads in the UK when the new identity was first used on-screen on 16 January 2006. The overhaul also put an end to the former ITV Day brand, which was axed in favour of a full-time ITV1 identity.

On 13 November 2006, a new set of idents replaced the previous set which debuted in January, the theme being &quot;alive with colour&quot;. The initial set consisted of 'Beach', 'Bike', 'Lake' and 'Market'; 'Basketball' and 'Pavement Art' were added later in the year. They were created by [[Blink Productions]] for [[ITV]], unlike the old idents which were masterminded by [[Red Bee Media]]. The logo remained the same in essence; only the 'itv' lettering was inverted from its previous white state to black, to allow it to stand out against the yellow more.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news 
  | title = ITV1 rolls out more idents
  | publisher = Guardian
  | date = 13 November 2006
  | url = http://media.guardian.co.uk/broadcast/story/0,,1945157,00.org
  | accessdate = 2006-06-06
| location=London
| first=Jason
| last=Deans}}&lt;/ref&gt;

On 3 September 2007, four more idents where added to the set, featuring 'Bubbles', 'Fountains', 'Garden' and 'Buildings', and as of 19 September 2009, all now have 'the brighter side' on their breakbumpers. On 9 April 2010, four more idents where added to the set, 'Lanterns', 'Sunflowers', 'Snakes and Ladders' and 'Dodgems', featuring an updated ITV1 logo as seen on [[ITV1 HD]].

In September 2009 [[ITV plc]] announced that ITV1 +1, a one hour time-shift version of ITV1, would launch in October 2009 from 10.25 am to 7 am daily. The hours covered by [[GMTV]] from 7 am to 10.25 am will not originally have been included in the relay.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news 
  | title = ITV1+1 to launch in October
  | publisher = Marketing Magazine
  | date = 2 September 2009
  | url = http://www.marketingmagazine.co.uk/news/931190/ITV1+1-launch-October/
  | accessdate = 2009-09-05}}&lt;/ref&gt; The channel launched on 11 January 2011.

==Notable programming==
{{main|List of television programmes broadcast by ITV}}
{{col-begin}}
{{col-2}}

===Daytime programming===
*''[[Daybreak (ITV)|Daybreak]]''
*''[[Lorraine (TV programme)|Lorraine]]''
*''[[The Jeremy Kyle Show]]''
*''[[This Morning (TV series)|This Morning]]''
*''[[Loose Women]]''
*''[[ITV News at 1:30]]''
*''[[60 Minute Makeover]]''
*''[[House Gift]]''
*''[[Dickinson's Real Deal]]''
*''[[The Alan Titchmarsh Show]]''
*''[[Midsomer Murders]]''
*''[[The Chase (game show)|The Chase]]''
*''[[Britain's Best Dish]]''
*''Dinner Date''
*''[[ITV News|ITV Regional News]]''

{{col-2}}

===Primetime programming===
*''[[ITV News at 6:30]]
*''[[Emmerdale]]''
*''[[Coronation Street]]''
*''[[Tonight (TV series)|Tonight]]''
*''[[Countrywise]]''
*''[[I'm a Celebrity...Get Me Out of Here! (UK TV series)|I'm a Celebrity...Get Me Out of Here!]]''
*''[[Paul O'Grady Live]]''
*''Documentaries''
*''Drama Premieres''
*''[[ITV News at Ten]]''
{{col-end}}

{{col-begin}}
{{col-2}}

===Weekend programming===
*''[[You've Been Framed]]''
*''[[Harry Hill's TV Burp]]''
*''[[Sing If You Can]]''
*''[[Odd One In]]''
*''[[Britain's Got Talent]]''
*''[[Penn &amp; Teller: Fool Us]]''
*''[[Piers Morgan's Life Stories]]''
*''[[The X Factor (UK)|The X Factor]]''
*''[[The Cube (game show)|The Cube]]''
*''[[The Royal]]''
*''[[Dancing on Ice]]''
*''[[Wild at Heart (TV series)|Wild at Heart]]''
*''[[Popstar to Operastar]]''
*''Drama Premieres''
*''[[ITV News (weekend bulletins)|ITV News]]''

{{col-2}}

===Nighttime programming===
*''Movies''
*''Primetime repeats''
*''[[The Zone (ITV)|The Zone]]''
*''[[The Jeremy Kyle Show]]''
*''[[Crossing Jordan]]''
*''[[In Plain Sight]]''
*''[[Swingtown]]''
*''[[ITV Nightscreen]]''
*''[[ITV News at 5:30]]''
{{col-end}}

==Spin-off channels==
===ITV1 HD===
{{main|ITV1 HD}}
A [[high definition television|high-definition]] simulcast of ITV1, '''[[ITV1 HD]]''', debuted on 2 December 2009 with the technical launch of the [[Freeview HD]] service. The channel has its roots in '''ITV HD''', which began as a trial service in 2006 on a low-power digital terrestrial ([[DVB-T]]) channel from London's [[Crystal Palace transmitting station]], and on [[Telewest]] [[V+|TV Drive]] cable service. The channel was revived on 7 June 2008 in time for the [[UEFA Euro 2008]] football tournament, this time exclusively available on the [[Freesat]] [[digital satellite]] service &lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web |url=http://www.digitalspy.co.uk/digitaltv/a95312/confirmed-itv-hd-is-freesat-exclusive.html |title=Confirmed: ITV HD is Freesat exclusive |publisher=Digital Spy |date=2008-05-06 |accessdate=2008-05-06}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |url=http://www.digitalspy.co.uk/digitaltv/a75516/hd-version-of-itv1-to-launch-next-spring.html|title=HD version of ITV to launch next Spring|publisher=Digital Spy|date=12 September 2007|accessdate=2007-09-12}}&lt;/ref&gt; With its debut on [[Freeview (UK)#Freeview HD|Freeview HD]], the channel was re-branded as '''ITV1 HD''' in December 2009.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://blog.wotsat.com/page/whatsat?entry=itv_hd_will_relaunch_for|title=ITV HD will relaunch for Freeview HD|publisher=What Satellite &amp; Digital TV|date=2009-08-07}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===ITV1 +1===
{{update|date=January 2011}}
On 1 September 2009 it was announced that ITV1 would get a one-hour timeshift on digital satellite and Virgin Media, on 1 October 2009, subject to the Competition Commission's ruling on the contract rights renewal system.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.agbnielsen.co.uk/agb/files/ClientServices/New%20BARB%20Channels/Implementation%20-%20ITV1+1.doc|title=Implementation - ITV1+1|publisher=AGB Nielsen Media Research|date=2009-09-01}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://mediatel.co.uk/microsite/agb-nielsen/2009/09/03/itv-to-wait-for-crr-ruling-before-launching-1-channel/|title=ITV to wait for CRR ruling before launching +1 channel|publisher=AGB Nielsen Media Research|date=2009-09-03}}&lt;/ref&gt; However on 18 September 2009, it was announced that ITV1 +1 has been postponed until further notice.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.digitalspy.co.uk/broadcasting/a178002/itv-postpones-itv11-launch.html|title=ITV postpones ITV1+1 launch|date=18 September 2009|publisher=Digital Spy}}&lt;/ref&gt; Prior to this announcement, EPG data for the service had appeared on satellite.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.digitalspy.co.uk/digitaltv/a177893/itv11-data-appears-on-skys-epg.html|title=ITV1+1 data appears on Sky's EPG|date=17 September 2009|publisher=Digital Spy}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The Competition Commission delayed the final decision in its review of ITV's Contract Rights Renewal undertakings to the end of February 2010 because it had to consider the &quot;significant&quot; submissions it has received.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.brandrepublic.com/News/971284/CRR-decision-put-back-commission-chews-submissions/|title=CRR decision put back as commission chews on submissions|publisher=Brand Republic|date=2009-12-02}}&lt;/ref&gt;

On 19 January 2010, the Competition Commission delivered its provisional findings, ruling that audiences for both ITV1 +1 and ITV1 HD will be accredited to ITV1's commercial impacts.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.mediaweek.co.uk/news/978157/ITV-given-greenlight-+1-HD-channels-CRR/|title=ITV given green light for +1 and HD channels under CRR|publisher=Media Week|date=2010-01-19}}&lt;/ref&gt; The Competition Commission recognised that the broadcaster had been deterred from launching new ways of delivering ITV1, because of the way media buying is currently conducted under the established contracts rights renewal (CRR) mechanism. However, the regulator rejected ITV's proposed removal of large elements of the &quot;outdated&quot; CRR Undertakings while maintaining an obligation on ITV to offer ITV1 airtime on &quot;fair and reasonable&quot; terms. The Competition Commission announced that such a change would leave the process too open to interpretation and that they were &quot;not likely to be either practicable or effective in addressing the adverse effects of the merger&quot;.

On 12 May 2010, the Competition Commission stood by its provisional decision to retain the contracts rights renewal system – but it added that the mechanism should be dropped at some point and that the entire UK TV ad sales market needs a review.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.guardian.co.uk/media/2010/may/12/itv-crr-ad-rules-say|title=ITV's CRR ad rules stay – for now|publisher=The Guardian|date=2010-05-12 | location=London | first=Mark | last=Sweney}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.competition-commission.org.uk/press_rel/2010/may/ITV_CRR_press_release_final_report.pdf|title=CC publishes final decision on UBLISHES |publisher=Competition Commission|date=2010-05-12}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.itvplc.com/media/newsrelease/?id=33696|title=ITV Statement In Response To The Competition Commission’s Final Decision On Contract Rights Renewal (CRR)|publisher=ITV plc|date=2010-05-12}}&lt;/ref&gt; &quot;ITV1 remains a 'must have' for certain advertisers and certain types of campaign,&quot; said the chairman of the CRR review group at the Competition Commission, Diana Guy. &quot;Despite all the changes in this market, no other channel or medium can come close to matching the size of audience that ITV regularly provides. So the essential reason for the CRR undertakings remains: to protect advertisers and other commercial broadcasters.&quot; The ITV chief executive, Adam Crozier, said that the ruling was &quot;out of touch and damaging for the interests of creative Britain&quot;. He added that it was &quot;unlikely&quot; that ITV would look to seek a judicial review but that ITV would redouble its lobbying campaign for a liberalisation of regulation and &quot;urgent modernisation&quot; of competition law. But the commission said there was &quot;virtual unanimity&quot; among advertisers, media agencies, commercial broadcasters and trade bodies that CRR should be kept &quot;in some form&quot;. The commission confirmed that the CRR remedy should be broadened to include ITV+1 and ITV's high definition channels.

On 27 July 2010, the [[House Of Lords]] confirmed plans to launch an inquiry into the television advertising market, which will &quot;pay particular attention&quot; to the CRR mechanism.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.digitalspy.co.uk/broadcasting/news/a251914/lords-to-review-itv1s-crr-mechanism.html?rss|title=Lords to review ITV1's CRR mechanism|publisher=Digital Spy|date=2010-07-28}}&lt;/ref&gt; The Lords committee will investigate the declining revenues that commercial broadcasters gain from the sale of advertising across their networks. The members will also consider possible changes to current ad market regulation, including the CRR system, product placement rules and the scheduling and sale of advertising. The committee wants to hear evidence on the current levels of regulation and what impact a relaxation of the rules could have on the commercial broadcasting sector. Interested parties must submit written evidence to the inquiry by September 24, with oral evidence to be heard in October. A written report is expected to follow in late 2010 or early 2011.

On 3 August 2010, ITV plc announced the launch of ITV1 +1 would take place in Q1 2011,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.itv.com/presscentre/pressreleases/programmepressreleases/itvplc2010interimresults/default.html|title=ITV plc 2010 Interim Results &amp; Sky deal|publisher=ITV plc|date=3 August 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; with [[Broadcasters' Audience Research Board|BARB]] later reporting that the channel would be launched on 11 January 2011.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.digitalspy.co.uk/broadcasting/news/a293215/itv11-sets-january-launch-date.html|title=ITV1+1 sets January launch date|publisher=Digital Spy|date=14 December 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; In December 2010 full testing of all six regions began on satellite.

ITV1 +1 was launched on 11 January 2011 on Freesat channel 112, Freeview channel 33, Sky channel 131 and Virgin Media channel 114.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.digitalspy.co.uk/broadcasting/news/a297309/itv11-to-launch-tonight.html|title=ITV1+1 to launch tonight|date=11 January 2011|publisher=Digital Spy}}&lt;/ref&gt; ITV1 broadcasts 22 different editions of digital satellite, but the timeshifted service only transmits six macro regional variants:&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.digitalspy.co.uk/broadcasting/a175012/itv-to-launch-itv11-channel.html|title=ITV to launch ITV1+1 channel|date=1 September 2009|publisher=Digital Spy}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* London
* South East Macro (encompassing Meridian and Anglia)
* West Macro (encompassing Wales &amp; West and Westcountry)
* Central
* Yorkshire/Tyne Tees Macro (encompassing Yorkshire and Tyne Tees)
* Granada/Border Macro (encompassing Granada and Border)

==See also==
* [[British Touring Car Championship#Television coverage|British Touring Car Championship]]
* [[List of ITV journalists and newsreaders]]

==References==
{{Reflist|2}}

==External links==
{{col-begin}}
{{col-2}}
*{{itv.com|id=itv1|title=ITV1}}
*{{YouTube|user = itv1|ITV1}}
{{col-2}}
*{{Facebook user|itv1|name=ITV1}}
*{{Twitter|ITV1|ITV1}}
{{col-end}}

{{ITV}}
{{Media in the United Kingdom|television}}
{{DEFAULTSORT:Itv1}}
[[Category:ITV]]
[[Category:Television channels in the United Kingdom]]

[[cy:ITV1]]
[[es:ITV1]]
[[fr:ITV1]]
[[gl:ITV1]]
[[id:ITV1]]
[[nl:ITV1]]
[[ja:ITV1]]
[[pl:ITV1]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
