<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="21210322" ns="0" title="Florida International University Robert Stempel College of Public Health and Social Work"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Infobox_University 
|name           = FIU Robert Stempel College of Public Health and Social Work
|image          = &lt;!-- Do NOT place a non-free image here without complying with WP:NFCC #10c --&gt;
|established    = 2006
|type           = [[Public university|Public]]
|city           = [[Miami]]
|state          = [[Florida]]
|country        = [[United States|USA]]
|faculty        = 
|students       = 1,652 (Fall 2009)&lt;ref&gt;http://w3.fiu.edu/irdata/portal/di.htm&lt;/ref&gt;
|dean           = Michele Ciccazzo
|website        = [http://cphsw.fiu.edu cphsw.fiu.edu]
}}

The '''Robert Stempel College of Public Health and Social Work''' at [[Florida International University]], located in [[Miami, Florida]] in the [[United States]] is one of the university's 26 schools and colleges, composed of the Robert Stempel School of Public health and the School of Social Work. The dean of the college is Michele Ciccazzo.  The school was originally founded by the now defunct College of Health and Urban Affairs of Florida International University, honoring faculty member Robert R. Stempel. Stempel joined the faculty in the Department of Public Health in 1991 and was promoted to associate professor with tenure in 1995. He was responsible for developing most of the courses in the Master of Public Health epidemiology track and was well known and respected for his graduate-level courses on AIDS Epidemiology, Behavioral Epidemiology, and International Public Health.

==Robert Stempel School of Public Health==
The initial strategic plan for the SSPH was drafted by a Strategic Planning Committee, using the results of a SWOT (strengths, weaknesses, opportunities, and threats) analysis conducted in a faculty retreat in 2004. The committee was composed of Department Chairs, a representative from the Executive Dean’s office, Associate Deans, and a graduate student representative. The plan was approved by faculty in January 2005, following a review by the External Advisory Committee. The initial plan guided us through our accreditation site visit in October 2006. Another Strategic Planning Committee revised the plan with a view toward 5–10 years in the future.  The School was created with $1 million gifts from the Starr Foundation and the Stempel Foundation. The $2 million total will receive a 75 percent match from the state to create the Robert Stempel Foundation to support activities in the new School. On 2008, the RSSPH joined the School of Social Work, previously part of the College of Social Work, Criminal Justice and Public Affairs of Florida International University to form the new college.&lt;ref&gt;[http://ssph.fiu.edu/about.html About Robert Stempel]&lt;/ref&gt;

===Accreditation===
The Stempel School of Public Health (SSPH) is accredited by The [[Council on Education for Public Health]] (CEPH) for a five-year term, the maximum for a new school of [[public health]], through 2012. FIU joins the ranks of 38 other accredited schools of public health to assure the public of a competent public health workforce. The [[Dietetics]] and [[Nutrition]] programs are accredited by the [[Commission on Education for Dietetics Education]] (CADE).

==School of Social Work==
The Social Work Program was established in 1972, when the University began offering academic programs. The School offers undergraduate and graduate programs leading to the Bachelors (BSSW) and Masters (MSW) and Doctor of Philosophy (Ph.D.) degrees in Social Work. The BSSW program was one of the first degree program offerings in the University and has been accredited since July, 1974, by the Council on Social Work Education (CSWE). The MSW degree program has been offered since August, 1981 and received full accreditation status from CSWE in April, 1986. The School is located on the University Park Campus.&lt;ref&gt;[http://ssph.fiu.edu/social_work/message.html Welcome Message by Paul Stuart - Director of the School of Social Work]&lt;/ref&gt;

== Facilities ==
[[Image:FIU HLS.JPG|right|thumb|150px|Academic Health Center Building 1 and 2 house the Robert Stempel College of Public Health and Social Work.]]

The Robert Stempel College of Public Health and Social Work Office of the Dean and most departments are housed in the Academic Health Center Buildings 1 and 2. Both the college's administrative and academic resources are located here. The School of Social Work is located in the Green Library Building's 4th floor.

== References ==

&lt;references/&gt;

== External links ==
* [http://cphsw.fiu.edu Robert Stempel College of Public Health and Social Work]
* [http://www.fiu.edu Florida International University]

{{Florida International University}}
{{coord missing|Florida}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Florida International University Robert Stempel College Of Public Health And Social Work}}
[[Category:Florida International University]]
[[Category:Educational institutions established in 2006]]
[[Category:Schools of public health in the United States]]
[[Category:Schools of social work]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
