<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="212357" ns="0" title="Media coverage of the Iraq War"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{POV|date=November 2009}}
[[Image:GeraldoCHCI.jpg|thumb|right| Journalist Geraldo Rivera who while with the 101st Airborne Division during war with Iraq in 2003 began to disclose an upcoming operation drawing a map in the sand for his audience.]]
The [[2003 invasion of Iraq]] involved unprecedented media coverage{{Citation needed|date=April 2008}}. The coverage itself became a source of controversy, as media outlets were accused of bias, reporters were casualties of both Iraqi and American gunfire, and claims of [[censorship]] and [[propaganda]] became widespread.

==U.S. mainstream media coverage==
{{multiple|section=y|synthesis=September 2011|original research=September 2011}}
&lt;div style=&quot;float:right&quot;&gt;
&lt;gallery&gt;
&lt;!-- Deleted image removed: Image:IraqWarCoverage-FNC.jpg|[[Fox News Channel|Fox News]] simulcasts [[Sky News]] reporter David Bowden's interview with a [[United States Army|U.S. Army]] sergeant following a firefight near [[Umm Qasr]]. &lt;small&gt;(March 23, 2003, 09:35 UTC)&lt;/small&gt; --&gt;
&lt;!-- Deleted image removed: Image:IraqWarCoverage-MSNBC.jpg|[[MSNBC]] discusses the various appearances of Iraqi President [[Saddam Hussein]] on television and speculates on his fate. &lt;small&gt;(March 24, 2003, 08:41 UTC)&lt;/small&gt; --&gt;
&lt;/gallery&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

The most popular cable network in the United States for news on the war was [[Fox News]],&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.stateofthenewsmedia.org/2005/narrative_cabletv_audience.asp?cat=3&amp;media=5 Cable TV: audience], stateofthenewsmedia.org&lt;/ref&gt; some of whose commentators and anchors made pro-war comments{{Citation needed|date=June 2007}} or disparaged detractors of the war, such as calling them &quot;the great unwashed&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.commondreams.org/headlines03/0416-06.htm Cable's War Coverage Suggests a New 'Fox Effect' on Television] by  Jim Rutenberg, commondreams.org&lt;/ref&gt; Fox News is owned by [[Rupert Murdoch]], a strong supporter of the war.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.guardian.co.uk/Iraq/Story/0,2763,897015,00.html Their master's voice], ''[[The Guardian]]''&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.msnbc.msn.com/id/19558317/ Inside the world of Rupert Murdoch], [[MSNBC]]&lt;/ref&gt; On-screen during all live war coverage by Fox News was a waving flag animation in the upper left corner and the headline &quot;Operation Iraqi Freedom&quot; along the bottom.{{Citation needed|date=June 2007}} The network has shown the American flag animation in the upper-left corner since the [[September 11, 2001 terrorist attacks]].{{Citation needed|date=June 2007}} Fox News' pro-war commentary stood in contrast to many U.S. newspapers' editorial pages, which were much more hesitant about going to war.{{Citation needed|date=June 2007}}

Anti-war celebrities appearing frequently on news networks included actors [[Tim Robbins]], [[Mike Farrell]], [[Janeane Garofalo]], [[Martin Sheen]], [[Susan Sarandon]] and director [[Michael Moore]].{{Citation needed|date=June 2007}} Most of these celebrities were able to make anti-war comments in the media and receive little public criticism. However, in a widely publicized story, the [[country music]] [[musical band|band]] [[Dixie Chicks]] ignited boycotts and record burnings in the [[United States|U.S.]] for their negative remarks about President Bush in a concert in [[London]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://edition.cnn.com/2003/SHOWBIZ/Music/03/14/dixie.chicks.apology/|title=Dixie Chicks singer apologizes for Bush comment|accessdate=2007-06-10 | work=CNN | date=March 13, 2003}}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[MSNBC]] also brought the American flag back on screen and regularly ran a tribute called &quot;America's Bravest&quot; which showed photographs sent by family members of troops deployed in Iraq.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news 
| accessdate=2008-01-21
| title=Who won the US media war?
| url=http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/world/americas/2959833.stm
| publisher=BBC
| date=2003-04-18
| first=Steve
| last=Schifferes
}}&lt;/ref&gt; MSNBC also fired liberal [[Phil Donahue]], a critic of Bush's Iraq policy,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news
| accessdate=2008-01-21
| title=The marketing plan for war
| url=http://seattletimes.nwsource.com/html/movies/2004118752_war11.html
| date=2008-01-11
| publisher=Seattle Times
| first=Jeff
| last=Shannon
}}&lt;/ref&gt; a month before the invasion began and replaced his show with Iraq war coverage hosted by [[Keith Olbermann]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
| date=2006-04-03
| accessdate=2008-01-22
| url=http://mediamatters.org/items/200604030009
| title=Olbermann marked third anniversary by devoting segment to &quot;O'Rivalry...
}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web 
| date=2006-10-03
| accessdate=2008-01-22
| url=http://www.commondreams.org/views06/1003-36.htm
| title=Is Olbermann on Thin Ice? 
}}&lt;/ref&gt; Shortly after Donahue's firing, MSNBC hired [[Michael Savage (commentator)|Michael Savage]], a controversial conservative radio talk show host for a Saturday afternoon show.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
| accessdate=2008-01-21
| url=http://www.sptimes.com/2003/03/07/Columns/MSNBC_shouldn_t_give_.shtml
| title=MSNBC shouldn't give voice to Savage
| date=2003-03-07
}}&lt;/ref&gt; Although Donahue's show had lower ratings than several shows on other networks, and most reports on its cancellation blamed poor ratings, it was the highest-rated program on MSNBC's struggling primetime lineup at the time of its cancellation.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web 
| accessdate=2008-01-21
| url=http://www.fair.org/index.php?page=2707
| title=Too Many Liberals?
| date=2005-10-27
}}&lt;/ref&gt; During February &quot;sweeps&quot;, Donahue's show averaged 446,000 viewers, compared to rival [[Connie Chung]]'s 985,000 on [[CNN]] and [[Bill O'Reilly (commentator)|Bill O'Reilly's]] 2.7 million on Fox News, according to Nielsen Media Research.{{Citation needed|date=June 2007}}

Comparing viewership from prewar to post war, MSNBC saw a 357% jump in ratings, while CNN went up 305%, and Fox News climbed 239%, according to Nielsen numbers.{{Citation needed|date=June 2007}}  In overall numbers, Fox News was number one, followed by CNN, and then MSNBC.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web 
| accessdate=2008-01-21
| url=http://www.marketwatch.com/News/Story/Story.aspx?guid=%7B5531CCF2-D364-441A-90FA-027EC0955801%7D&amp;source=blq%2Fyhoo&amp;dist=yhoo&amp;siteid=yhoo
| date=2003-03-21
| title=Fox tops CNN, MSNBC in war TV ratings 
}}&lt;/ref&gt; It was a major success for Fox News, as many had believed CNN would reclaim the top spot, since it established itself with coverage from the 1990-1991 Gulf War.

In separate incidents, at least three different Western reporters were fired or disciplined due to their actions in covering the war. [[Peter Arnett]], an [[NBC]] and [[National Geographic]] correspondent, was fired for giving an interview with Iraqi officials in which he questioned the United States' role and saying the &quot;first war plan had failed.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news 
| accessdate=2008-01-21
| publisher=CNN
| url=http://www.cnn.com/2003/WORLD/meast/03/31/sprj.irq.arnett/
| title=Just fired, Peter Arnett hired by British paper
| date=2003-04-01
}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Brian Walski]] of the ''[[Los Angeles Times]]'' was fired on March 31 for altering a photo of a U.S. soldier warning Iraqi civilians to take cover from an Iraqi aerial bombing.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news
| accessdate=2008-01-21
| publisher=Washington Post
| url=http://www.washingtonpost.com/wp-srv/photo/essays/vanRiper/030409.htm
| title=Manipulating Truth, Losing Credibility 
}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Geraldo Rivera]] left Iraq after drawing a crude map in the sand during a live broadcast on Fox News, which raised concerns at the Pentagon that he was possibly revealing vital troop movements on air.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news
| accessdate=2008-01-21
| url=http://www.guardian.co.uk/media/2003/mar/31/Iraqandthemedia.broadcasting1
| title=Rivera gets army boot out of Iraq
| date=2003-03-21
| publisher=The Guardian
| location=London
| first=Jason
| last=Deans}}&lt;/ref&gt;

One study has compared the number of insurgent attacks in Iraq to the number of &quot;anti-resolve&quot; statements in the US media, the release of public opinion polls, and geographic variations in access to international media by Iraqis.  The purpose was to determine if insurgents responded to information on &quot;casualty sensitivity.&quot;  The researchers found that insurgent attacks spiked by 5 to 10% after increases in the number of negative reports of the war in the media.  The authors identified this as an &quot;emboldenment effect&quot; and concluded &quot;insurgent groups respond rationally to expected probability of US withdrawal.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Radha Iyengar and Jonathan Monten, [http://www.nber.org/papers/w13839 &quot;Is There an &quot;Emboldenment&quot; Effect? Evidence from the Insurgency in Iraq,&quot;] [[National Bureau of Economic Research]] Working Paper No. 13839, March 2008 (free version at [http://people.rwj.harvard.edu/~riyengar/insurgency.pdf &quot;Is There an “Emboldenment” Effect? Evidence from the Insurgency in Iraq&quot;])&lt;/ref&gt;

===Criticisms of pro-invasion bias===
[[Image:Iraq War Media Sources Opinion Percentage.svg|300px|thumb|A study found that in the lead up to the Iraq War, most sources were overwhelmingly in favor of the invasion.]]

A [[University of Maryland, College Park|University of Maryland]] study on American public opinion found that:
*Fifty-seven percent of mainstream media viewers believed the falsity that Iraq gave substantial support to Al-Qaeda, or was directly involved in the [[September 11 attacks]] (48% after invasion).
*Sixty-nine percent believed the falsity that Saddam Hussein was personally involved in the [[September 11 attacks]].
*Twenty-two percent believed the falsity that weapons of mass destruction had been found in Iraq. (Twenty-one percent believed that chem/bio weapons had actually been used against U.S. soldiers in Iraq during 2003)
*In the composite analysis of the PIPA study, 80% of Fox News watchers had one or more of these misperceptions, in contrast to 71% for [[CBS]] and 27% who tuned to [[NPR]]/[[Public Broadcasting Service|PBS]].&lt;ref&gt;&quot;Misperceptions, Media, and the Iraq War.&quot; The PIPA/Knowledge Networks Poll The American Public On International Issues. Available at: [http://65.109.167.118/pipa/pdf/oct03/IraqMedia_Oct03_rpt.pdf] See also: [http://www.worldpublicopinion.org/pipa/articles/international_security_bt/102.php?nid=&amp;id=&amp;pnt=102&amp;lb=brusc]&lt;/ref&gt;

In 2003, a study released by [[Fairness and Accuracy In Reporting]] stated the network news disproportionately focused on pro-war sources and left out many [[anti-war]] sources. According to the study, 64% of total sources were in favor of the Iraq War while total anti-war sources made up 10% of the media (only 3% of US sources were anti-war). The study stated that &quot;viewers were more than six times as likely to see a pro-war source as one who was anti-war; with U.S. guests alone, the ratio increases to 25 to 1.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |author=Steve Rendall and Tara Broughel|year=2003 |title=Amplifying Officials, Squelching Dissent |journal=Extra!|publisher=[[Fairness and Accuracy In Reporting]] |url=http://www.fair.org/index.php?page=1145 |accessdate=}}&lt;/ref&gt;

FAIR also conducted a similar study in February 2004. According to the study, which took place during October 2003, current or former government or military officials accounted for 76 percent of all 319 sources for news stories about Iraq which aired on network news channels.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.fair.org/index.php?page=1167 |title=If News From Iraq Is Bad, It's Coming From U.S. Officials |publisher=Fair.org |first=Jon |last=Whiten |month=February | year=2004 |accessdate=2007-03-28}}&lt;/ref&gt;

After the invasion, the editors of the ''New York Times'' apologized for its coverage of Hussein's alleged weapons programs, acknowledging that &quot;we wish we had been more aggressive in re-examining the claims (related to Iraqi weapons programs) as new evidence emerged — or failed to emerge.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.nytimes.com/2004/05/26/international/middleeast/26FTE_NOTE.html?ex=1400990400&amp;en=94c17fcffad92ca9&amp;ei=5007&amp;partner=USERLAND &quot;The Times and Iraq.&quot;] ''The New York Times,'' May 26, 2004. Retrieved on April 11, 2007. See also Michael Massing in ''The New York Review of Books'' Volume 51, Number 3 · February 26, 2004&lt;/ref&gt;

During the invasion, critics argued that the mainstream media unduly focused on optimistic events, such as the toppling of a Saddam Hussein statue in [[Firdos Square]], which was staged with the help of the U.S. military forces, thus downplaying more negative news developments.&lt;ref&gt;[http://newstandardnews.net/content/?action=show_item&amp;itemid=641 Army report confirms Psy-ops staged Saddam statue toppling - The NewStandard&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;
In particular, the mainstream media has been criticized for underreporting news about Iraqi civilian casualties, which are estimated to be anywhere between 100,000 and 650,000.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.thelancet.com/webfiles/images/journals/lancet/s0140673606694919.pdf]{{Dead link|date=December 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt;

As the security situation in Iraq has worsened since the invasion, many journalists have found it increasingly difficult to report from Iraq without jeopardizing their lives. Some media outlets, unable to afford the cost of additional security, have even abandoned their bureaus in Baghdad. This trend has forced journalists to depend even more heavily on U.S. military sources, which has led some critics to call into question the impartiality of their reports on events such as the [[Iraqi elections]].&lt;ref&gt;Schell, Orville. &quot;Baghdad: The Besieged Press.&quot; New York Review of Books, April 6, 2006. Retrieved from [http://www.globalpolicy.org/security/issues/iraq/media/2006/0406besieged.htm Global Policy Forum] on April 11, 2007.&lt;/ref&gt;

A post-2008 election poll by [[FactCheck.org]] found that 48% of Americans believe Hussein played a role in the 9/11 attacks; the group concluded that &quot;voters, once deceived, tend to stay that way despite all evidence.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.factcheck.org/specialreports/our_disinformed_electorate.html Our Disinformed Electorate]. By Kathleen Hall Jamieson and Brooks Jackson. [[FactCheck.org]] Published December 12, 2008.&lt;/ref&gt;

===Allegations of Propaganda===
{{main|Propaganda model}}

[[Image:Kofi Annan.jpg|180px|right|thumb|[[Kofi Annan]] and [[Richard Perle]] have said the [[Iraq War]] is illegal,&lt;ref&gt;[http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/3661134.stm Iraq war illegal, says Annan]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.guardian.co.uk/uk/2003/nov/20/usa.iraq1 War critics astonished as US hawk admits invasion was illegal]&lt;/ref&gt; but this was never mentioned in the US media aside from the Fox News Channel, MSNBC, and CNN.]]

Media critics such as [[Noam Chomsky]], have alleged that the media acted as [[propaganda]] for not questioning the [[legality of the Iraq war]] and thus, took on the fundamental assumptions given by the government.&lt;ref&gt;[http://video.google.com/videoplay?docid=-4495142117559144505# Illegal but Legitimate: a Dubious Doctrine for the Times.] University of Washington. April 20, 2005.&lt;/ref&gt; This is despite overwhelming public opinion in favor of only invading Iraq with UN authorization.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.gallup.com/poll/7195/support-invasion-iraq-remains-contingent-un-approval.aspx Support for Invasion of Iraq Remains Contingent on U.N. Approval]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://books.google.com/books?id=OAg68_PMDwAC&amp;printsec=frontcover&amp;dq=foreign+policy+disconnect&amp;hl=en&amp;ei=jMrITb-YIaffiALu97iLBQ&amp;sa=X&amp;oi=book_result&amp;ct=result&amp;resnum=1&amp;ved=0CDEQ6AEwAA#v=onepage&amp;q=65%20percent%20%22the%20U.S.%20should%20only%20invade%20Iraq%20with%20UN%20approval%20and%20the%20support%20of%20its%20allies%22&amp;f=false ''The Foreign Policy Disconnect''], pg 109&lt;/ref&gt;

In a 2010 interview, Chomsky compared media coverage of the [[Afghan War documents leak|Afghan War Diaries]] released by [[Wikileaks]] and lack of media coverage to a study of [[Fallujah during the Iraq War#Health Effects|severe health problems in Fallujah]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=WHfYtvYRgdk Chomsky on the WikiLeaks' Coverage in the Press]&lt;/ref&gt; While there was ample coverage of Wikileaks there was no American coverage of the Fallujah study,&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.medialens.org/index.php?option=com_content&amp;view=article&amp;id=5:beyond-hiroshima-the-non-reporting-of-fallujahs-cancer-catastrophe&amp;catid=1:alerts&amp;Itemid=34 BEYOND HIROSHIMA - THE NON-REPORTING OF FALLUJAH'S CANCER CATASTROPHE]&lt;/ref&gt; in which the health situation in Fallujah was described by the British media as &quot;worse than Hiroshima&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.independent.co.uk/news/world/middle-east/toxic-legacy-of-us-assault-on-fallujah-worse-than-hiroshima-2034065.html Toxic legacy of US assault on Fallujah 'worse than Hiroshima']&gt;&lt;/ref&gt;  

Chomsky also asserts that the media accurately covered events such as the [[Second Battle of Fallujah|Battle of Fallujah]] but because of an ideological bias, it acts as pro-government propaganda. In describing coverage of raid on Fallujah General Hospital he states that ''[[The New York Times]]'', &quot;accurately recorded the battle of Fallujah but it was celebrated...it was celebration of ongoing war crimes&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news
|title=Chomsky: US won’t acknowledge Iraq war crimes
|author=Saba Hamedy
|url=http://dailyfreepress.com/2010/09/19/chomsky-us-wont-acknowledge-iraq-war-crimes/
|newspaper=The Daily Free Press
|date=19 September 2010
|accessdate=6 January 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; The article in question was &quot;[http://www.nytimes.com/2004/11/08/international/middleeast/08hospital.html Early Target of Offensive Is a Hospital]&quot;.

===Pentagon military analyst group===

{{See also|Pentagon military analyst program}}

An investigation by the ''New York Times'' discovered that top [[The Pentagon|Pentagon]] officials met with news analysts where they gave the analysts 'special information' and then tried to convince them to speak favorably about the Iraq war.&lt;ref name=&quot;autogenerated1&quot;&gt;{{cite news| url=http://www.nytimes.com/2008/04/20/washington/20generals.html?ref=washington | work=The New York Times | title=Behind TV Analysts, Pentagon's Hidden Hand | first=David | last=Barstow | date=April 20, 2008 | accessdate=May 12, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; The discovery was based on 8000 pages of secret information that had been revealed to The New York Times through a lawsuit under the Freedom of Information Act. The article states that top Pentagon officials would invite news analysts to secret meetings, and urge the analysts to speak positively of the war. Often, the US would give &quot;classified information,&quot; trips, and contracts to the news analysts.&lt;ref name=&quot;autogenerated1&quot; /&gt;

==U.S. independent media coverage==
The [[Media Workers Against the War]] and the [[Indymedia]] network, among many other independent networks including many journalists from the invading countries, provided reports in a way difficult to control by any government, corporation or political party. In the United States [[Democracy Now]], hosted by
[[Amy Goodman]] has been critical of the reasons for the 2003 invasion
and the alleged crimes committed by the US authorities in Iraq.

Australian [[war artist]] [[George Gittoes]] collected independent interviews with soldiers while producing his documentary [[Soundtrack To War]].

The war in Iraq provided the first time in history that military on the front lines were able to provide direct, uncensored reportage themselves, thanks to [[blog]]ging software and the reach of the [[internet]]. Dozens of such reporting sites, known as [[Warblog|soldier blogs]] or milblogs, were started during the war.

==Non-U.S. media coverage==
Non-U.S. coverage sometimes differed strongly in tone and content from U.S. media coverage.

In some countries television journalists' behavior differed significantly during the conflict compared to Gulf War conflicts{{Citation needed|date=February 2010}}. [[Jean-Marie Charon]] said most journalists were more cautious, often using the conditional form and rigorously citing sources.

The crew of the [[HMS Ark Royal (R07)|HMS ''Ark Royal'']], Britain's flagship naval vessel, demanded that the BBC be turned off on the ship because of what they saw as a clear anti-Coalition or &quot;pro-Iraq&quot; bias. One BBC correspondent had been embedded on the ship, but the crew said they had no complaints of his reporting specifically. The sailors on board the ship claimed that the BBC gave more credit to Iraqi reports than information coming from British or Allied sources, often questioning and refusing to believe reports coming from Coalition sources while reporting Iraqi claims of civilian casualties without independent verification. The ship's news feed was replaced with [[Sky News]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.ananova.com/news/story/sm_768569.html?menu=news.wariniraq]&lt;/ref&gt; Ironically, it later emerged from a study conducted by Professor Justin Lewis of the School of Journalism at Cardiff University that the BBC was the most pro-war of British networks,&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.wsws.org/articles/2003/jul2003/bbc-j10.shtml BBC was most pro-war of British networks&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt; a finding confirmed in a separate study by the German newspaper ''Frankfurter Allgemeine Zeitung''.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.wsws.org/articles/2003/may2003/med-m02.shtml Media bosses admit pro-war bias in coverage of Iraq&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;

Arab media outfit [[Al Jazeera]] broadcast many scenes of civilian casualties, usually referring to them as &quot;martyrs&quot;, press conferences with Iraqi officials claiming to be winning the war, and of American and British [[POW]]s which U.S. media refused to run{{Citation needed|date=February 2010}}. Most Arab networks also downplayed the scenes of Iraqi citizens cheering coalition forces entering their towns{{Citation needed|date=February 2010}}. Arab networks consistently referred to U.S. and British forces as &quot;invading forces,&quot;{{Citation needed|date=February 2010}} while Western media referred to them as &quot;coalition forces.&quot;

The war in Iraq saw [[Abu Dhabi TV]] mature into a credible Al-Jazeera rival. However, the war did not benefit [[Al-Arabiya]], the newest of Arabic news networks. Created by the audio-visual group saoudien [[Middle East Broadcasting Center|MBC]] to compete with Al-Jazeera (whose tone often displeases Arab leaders), Al-Arabiya was launched on February 19, 2003.

==Iraqi media coverage==
According to reports from three separate media watchdog groups, the Iraqi media was under tight state control prior to the invasion. Saddam Hussein's eldest son, Uday, oversaw as many as a dozen newspapers, sat on several important editorial boards, and ran the most popular television station, Youth TV.&lt;ref&gt;Tabor, Kimberly. [http://www.pbs.org/frontlineworld/stories/iraq/press.html &quot;The Press in Iraq.&quot;] ''PBS.org'', November, 2002. Retrieved April 11, 2007.&lt;/ref&gt; In a 2001 report, the French-based [http://www.cpj.org/ Committee to Protect Journalists] wrote that Saddam Hussein's government maintained a &quot;stranglehold&quot; on Iraqi media outlets, and that &quot;insulting the president or other government authorities is punishable by death.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.cpj.org/attacks01/pages_att01/attacks01.html|title=Attacks on the Press in 2001|publisher=Committee to Protect Journalists|accessdate=2007-04-15 |archiveurl = http://web.archive.org/web/20070406232226/http://www.cpj.org/attacks01/pages_att01/attacks01.html |archivedate = April 6, 2007}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In the wake of the invasion, the Iraqi media establishment changed drastically. Hundreds of newspapers, television stations, and radio stations sprouted both inside and outside of the country. Many of these new media outlets were closely linked with religious or political organizations, and closely reflected the interests of their backers. Some observers have suggested that this has contributed to increased sectarianism in the country.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|last=Metcalf|first=Steve|url=http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/world/middle_east/4884246.stm|title=Analysis: Iraq's media three years on|work=BBCNews.com|date=2006-04-06|accessdate=2007-04-11}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The burgeoning Iraqi media market has also proven subject to manipulation by the United States government. In November 2005, the [[Los Angeles Times]] reported on a secret Pentagon program to pay Iraqi media outlets to publish articles favorable of the U.S. invasion and occupation. This initiative relied on U.S.-based subcontractors such as the [[Lincoln Group]] to write and place stories with headlines such as &quot;Iraqis Insist on Living Despite Terrorism&quot; and &quot;More Money Goes to Iraq's Development.&quot; According to anonymous sources within the U.S. government, Army Lt. Gen. John R. Vines oversees the program.&lt;ref&gt;Gerth, Jeff and Scott Shane.
[http://www.nytimes.com/2005/12/01/politics/01propaganda.html?ex=1291093200&amp;en=15a816ad2c204281&amp;ei=5088&amp;partner=rssnyt&amp;emc=rss &quot;U.S. Is Said to Pay to Plant Articles in Iraq Papers.&quot;] ''The New York Times'', December 1, 2005. Retrieved April 11, 2007.&lt;/ref&gt; In March 2006, General George Casey, the Army's second in command, indicated that this practice, which did not &quot;violate U.S. law or Pentagon guidelines,&quot; would continue.&lt;ref&gt;Shanker, Thom. [http://travel2.nytimes.com/2006/03/22/politics/22lincoln.html THE STRUGGLE FOR IRAQ: THE IMAGE CAMPAIGN; No Breach Is Seen in Planting U.S. Propaganda in Iraq Media&quot;] ''The New York Times''. March 22, 2006. Retrieved April 6, 2008.&lt;/ref&gt;

==&quot;Embedded&quot; reporters==
Around 600 journalists were &quot;[[Embedded journalist|embedded]]&quot; with military units, 80% being [[United Kingdom|British]] or [[United States|American]]. [[The Pentagon]] established the policy of &quot;embedding&quot; reporters with military units.

[[Robert Entman]], professor of communication at the [[George Washington University]] and critic of mainstream media for decades, indicated it was a very wise tactic from the Pentagon. He mentioned there were more chances for the journalists to make favorable reports whilst in Iraq with British and American soldiers than if they had been asking questions in Washington. Entman indicated there is a natural cultural bias of American journalists in favor of military troops of their own country and that journalists do like to satisfy the government upon which they rely for information, as well as the public on whom they depend commercially. Entman also mentioned the high number of retired generals making comments on TV, pointing out these could not be considered independent experts as they were still paid by the government. He claims the [[British Broadcasting Corporation]] was much more neutral and informative on cultural and historical background than most American television reports.

The Ministry of Defense explained &quot;maintaining morale as well as information dominance will rank as important as physical protection&quot;. An MoD-commissioned commercial analysis of the print output produced by embeds shows that 90% of their reporting was either &quot;positive or neutral.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news| url=http://media.guardian.co.uk/iraqandthemedia/story/0,12823,1118405,00.html | work=The Guardian | location=London | title=The domination effect | date=January 8, 2004 | accessdate=May 12, 2010 | first=David | last=Miller}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Firdos Square Controversy==
{{main|Firdos Square statue destruction}}
[[Image:SaddamStatue.jpg|thumb|The famous April 2003 toppling of [[Saddam Hussein]]’s statue in [[Firdos Square]] in [[Baghdad]] shortly after the [[Iraq War]] invasion.]]
On April 9, 2003, a large statue of [[Saddam Hussein]] in Baghdad's [[Firdos Square]], directly in front of the [[Palestine Hotel]] where the world's journalists had been quartered, was toppled by a U.S. M88 tank recovery vehicle surrounded by dozens of celebrating Iraqis, who had been attempting to pull down the statue earlier with little success. One such futile attempt by sledgehammer wielding weightlifter [[Kadhem Sharif]] particularly caught media attention.&lt;ref name=&quot;FamousPictures&quot;&gt;{{cite web | year = 2007 | url = http://www.famouspictures.org/mag/index.php?title=Fall_of_Saddam_Hussein%27s_Statue| title = Famous Pictures Magazine - Fall of Saddam Hussein's Statue| publisher = Famous Pictures Magazine| accessdate = 2007-07-16 | last=Lucas, Dean }}&lt;/ref&gt;  Eventually the M88 was able to topple the statue which was jumped upon by Iraqi citizens who then decapitated the head of the statue and dragged it through the streets of the city hitting it with their shoes. The destruction of the statue was shown live on cable news networks as it happened and made the front pages of newspapers and covers of magazines all over the world - symbolizing the fall of the Hussein government. The images of the statue falling came as a shock to many Arab viewers, who had thought that Iraq was winning the war.&lt;ref&gt;[http://weekly.ahram.org.eg/2003/634/eg8.htm Al-Ahram Weekly | Egypt | Shocked, awed and saddened&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;

Before the statue was toppled, [[Corporal#United States Marine Corps|Marine Corporal]] Edward Chin of the [[3rd battalion 4th Marines regiment]] climbed the ladder and placed an American flag over the statue's face.&lt;ref name=&quot;FamousPictures&quot;/&gt; An Iraqi flag was then placed over the statue. The event was widely publicized, but allegations that it had been staged were soon published. One picture from the event, published in the ''[[London Evening Standard]]'', was allegedly doctored to make the crowd appear larger.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.thememoryhole.org/media/evening-standard-crowd.htm The Memory Hole &gt; Doctored Photo from London Evening Standard&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;  A report by the ''[[Los Angeles Times]]'' stated it was an unnamed Marine colonel, not Iraqi civilians who had decided to topple the statue; and that a quick-thinking Army psychological operations team then used loudspeakers to encourage Iraqi civilians to assist and made it all appear spontaneous and Iraqi-inspired.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.commondreams.org/headlines04/0703-02.htm Army Stage-Managed Fall of Hussein Statue&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt; According to Tim Brown at Globalsecurity.org: &quot;It was not completely stage-managed from Washington, DC but it was not exactly a spontaneous Iraqi operation.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;http://web.archive.org/web/20041207142542/http://www.wjla.com/news/stories/0704/161032.html&lt;/ref&gt; 

The 2004 film ''[[Control Room (film)|Control Room]]'' deals with the incident in depth and indicated that the overall impression of Al Jazeera reporters was that it was staged. The Marines present at the time, [[3rd Battalion 4th Marines]], maintain that the scene was not staged other than the assistance they provided.&lt;ref&gt;Coughlin, GySgt Jack and Kuhlman, Capt. Casey with Davis, Donald A., ''Shooter: The Autobiography of the Top-Ranked Marine Sniper'', St. Martins, hardback edition - 2005, paperback edition - 2006.&lt;/ref&gt;

==Coverage of U.S. casualties==
Media coverage of U.S. military casualties has been met by Bush administration efforts to downplay reports about soldiers' deaths throughout the invasion. Unlike the Vietnam War, when the media regularly published photographs of flag-draped coffins of American military personnel killed in action, the Bush administration prohibited the release of such photographs during the Iraq invasion. This ban was instituted in 2000 by the Clinton administration, and mirrors a similar ban put in place during the [[Gulf War]],&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news| url=http://www.cbsnews.com/stories/2004/04/23/iraq/main613301.shtml | work=CBS News | title=Pentagon: Families Want Photo Ban | date=April 23, 2004}}&lt;/ref&gt; though it appears to have been enforced less tightly during previous military operations.

According to [[United States Senator|Senator]] [[Patrick Leahy]], the administration also scheduled the return of wounded soldiers to [[Dover Air Force Base]] for after midnight so that the press would not see them.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|last=Buncombe|first=Andrew|url=http://news.independent.co.uk/world/middle_east/article78272.ece|title=The hidden cost of Bush's war|work=The Independent|date=2003-11-14|accessdate=2007-04-15 | location=London}}&lt;/ref&gt; This practice was documented by both the [[Drudge Report]] and [[Salon.com]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://archive.salon.com/news/feature/2005/03/08/night_flights/ The invisible wounded | Salon News&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;  A number of Dover photographs were eventually released in response to a Freedom of Information request filed by blogger [[Russ Kick]].

Media coverage related to casualty milestones, such as the 1000th, 2000th, and 3000th U.S. soldier killed, have consistently sparked controversy among supporters and defenders of the invasion. On September 7, 2004 the US recorded its 1,000th casualty of the war, when four servicemen died that day (three in one incident, one in another). Presidential candidate [[John Kerry]] called it a &quot;tragic milestone.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news| url=http://www.cnn.com/2004/WORLD/meast/09/07/iraq.main/ | work=CNN}} {{Dead link|date=August 2010|bot=RjwilmsiBot}}&lt;/ref&gt; Defense Secretary [[Donald Rumsfeld]] argued the 1000th milestone was passed long ago in the [[War on Terrorism]], with the loss of life on September 11, 2001 being in the thousands, and going on the offensive against terrorism &quot;has its cost.&quot;

{{wikinews|Pentagon announces 2,000th U.S. military death}}
On October 25, 2005 the [[United States Department of Defense|Department of Defense]] announced the 2,000th U.S. death from the war as [[George Alexander (US Army soldier)|Staff Sergeant George T. Alexander Jr.]], who was killed when a roadside bomb detonated near his [[M2 Bradley]] in the city of [[Samarra]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news| url=http://www.cnn.com/2005/WORLD/meast/10/25/iraq.main/index.html | work=CNN}} {{Dead link|date=August 2010|bot=RjwilmsiBot}}&lt;/ref&gt; In response, Senators including [[Dick Durbin]] made statements opposing the war, and activists held six hundred [[Protests against the 2003 Iraq war|anti-war protests]] and candlelight [[vigil]]s across the United States.&lt;ref&gt;http://web.archive.org/web/20070927204305/http://www.suburbanchicagonews.com/beaconnews/top/2_1_AU27_VIGIL_S1.htm&lt;/ref&gt;
In contrast, [[the Pentagon]] downplayed the death — Lt. Col. [[Steven Boylan]], chief spokesman for the U.S. military in Iraq, told the Associated Press that &quot;the 2,000 service members killed in Iraq supporting Operation Iraqi Freedom is not a milestone. It is an artificial mark on the wall set by individuals or groups with specific agendas and ulterior motives.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.usatoday.com/news/world/iraq/2005-10-25-military-casualties_x.htm|title=U.S. military death toll in Iraq hits 2,000|work=AP|publisher=USA Today|date=2005-10-25|accessdate=2007-04-11}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.usatoday.com/news/world/iraq/2005-10-25-military-casualties_x.htm|title=www.usatoday.com/news/world/iraq/2005-10-25-military-casualties_x.htm|title=&quot;U.S. military death toll in Iraq hits 2,000.&quot;] ''USA Today,'' October 25, 2005. Retrieved on April 11, 2007|last=Press|first=Associated|accessdate=2007-04-15 | date=October 26, 2005}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news| url=http://www.usatoday.com/news/world/iraq/2005-10-25-military-casualties_x.htm | work=USA Today | title=U.S. military death toll in Iraq hits 2,000 | date=October 26, 2005 | accessdate=May 12, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The U.S. death toll reached 3,000 on December 31, 2006 when [[Texas]] soldier Spc. [[Dustin R. Donica]] was killed in Baghdad, near the office of [[Saleh al-Mutlaq]], a [[Sunni]] [[Arab]] politician and leader of the [[Iraqi National Dialogue Front]].&lt;ref&gt;&quot;Hurst, Steven R. [http://abcnews.go.com/International/wireStory?id=2763716 U.S. Death Toll in Iraq Surpasses 3,000].&quot; ''ABCNews.com'', January 1, 2007. Retrieved on January 8, 2007.&lt;/ref&gt; The milestone came just one day after the [[execution of Saddam Hussein]] and just as the [[George W. Bush administration|Bush Administration]] was revising its wartime strategy.

===Ban lifted===

Soon after taking office in January 2009, President [[Barack Obama]] asked Defense Secretary [[Robert Gates]] to review the ban on media coverage of coffins. In February Gates announced that the ban would be lifted, and permission for coverage of individual soldiers would be at the discretion of their next of kin.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news | title=Ban lifted, media witness solemn return of fallen service member | url=http://edition.cnn.com/2009/POLITICS/04/06/photo.ban.lifted/ | publisher=CNN | date=6 April 2009 | accessdate=2009-04-16 |last=Mount |first=Mike}}&lt;/ref&gt; On 5 April the return of Phillip Myers, an Air Force Staff Sergeant killed in Afghanistan the day before, became the first return of a US serviceman's remains to receive media coverage since the instatement of the original ban in 1991.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news | title=US war dead media blackout lifted  | url=http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/world/americas/7986203.stm | publisher=BBC News | date=6 April 2009 | accessdate=2009-04-16}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Attack on Al Jazeera==
On April 8, 2003, U.S. aircraft bombed the Baghdad bureau of Qatar satellite TV station [[Al Jazeera]] killing a journalist and wounding another despite the U.S. being informed of the office's precise coordinates prior to the incident. An Al Jazeera correspondent said that very clear, yellow signs reading &quot;Press&quot; covered the building from all sides and on the roof.&lt;ref&gt;[http://islamicsydney.com/printable.php?id=896 U.S. Missiles Hit Al-Jazeera Office - IslamicSydney.com&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt; A U.S. Central Command spokesman said that the station &quot;was not and never had been a target.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/middle_east/2927527.stm|title=Al-Jazeera 'hit by missile'|accessdate=2007-09-28 | work=BBC News | date=April 8, 2003}} BBC News&lt;/ref&gt; The U.S. government had repeatedly criticized Al Jazeera as &quot;endangering the lives of American troops.&quot;

The attack had drawn particular criticism because the [[Kabul]] office of Al Jazeera had been bombed in the [[War in Afghanistan (2001–present)|U.S. invasion of Afghanistan]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.csmonitor.com/2005/1123/dailyUpdate.html British paper: Bush wanted to bomb Al Jazeera | csmonitor.com&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;

On 2 April 2003, in a speech given in [[New York City]], [[British Home Secretary]] [[David Blunkett]] commented on what he believed to be sympathetic and corrupt reporting of Iraq by Arab news sources. He told the audience that &quot;It's hard to get the true facts if the reporters of Al Jazeera are actually linked into, and are only there because they are provided with facilities and support from, the régime.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.weeklystandard.com/Content/Public/Articles/000/000/002/605fgcob.asp?pg=2 Saddam's Cash&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt; His speech came only hours before Al Jazeera was ejected from Baghdad by the US occupation.

A top secret memo leaked by a British civil servant and a parliamentary researcher detailed a lengthy conversation on April 16, 2004 between Prime Minister Blair and President Bush, in which Bush according to British media allegedly proposed bombing the Qatar central office of Al Jazeera.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.mirror.co.uk/news/tm_objectid=16397937&amp;method=full&amp;siteid=94762&amp;headline=exclusive--bush-plot-to-bomb-his-arab-ally-name_page.html&lt;/ref&gt; House press secretary, Scott McClellan, describing it as &quot;outlandish&quot; said, &quot;Any such notion that we would engage in that kind of activity is just absurd.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.msnbc.msn.com/id/10269701/site/newsweek/from/RL.5/ Newsweek National News | Newsweek.com&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt; A UK government official suggested that the Bush threat had been &quot;humorous, not serious.&quot; Another source said Bush was &quot;deadly serious.&quot; The UK government refuses to publish the memo and two civil servants have been charged with violating Britain's Official Secrets Act for allegedly disclosing the document.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news| url=http://www.washingtonpost.com/wp-dyn/content/article/2005/11/22/AR2005112201784.html | work=The Washington Post | title=Paper Says Bush Talked of Bombing Arab TV Network | first1=Kevin | last1=Sullivan | first2=Walter | last2=Pincus | date=November 23, 2005 | accessdate=May 12, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; For a fuller discussion, see [[Al Jazeera bombing memo]].

==Attack on Palestine Hotel==
On the same day as the destruction of the Baghdad bureau of [[Al Jazeera]], a U.S. tank fired a [[High explosive anti-tank|HEAT]] round at what the U.S. military later claimed was a suspected Iraqi forward artillery observer. Due to what the U.S. states was a communications error, the tank mistakenly fired at the Palestine Hotel, where approximately 100 international reporters in Baghdad were based, instead of the correct building, killing two journalists, Taras Protsyuk of Reuters and Jose Cousa of the Spanish network Telecinco&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news| url=http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/middle_east/2928153.stm | work=BBC News | title=Foreign media suffer Baghdad losses | date=April 8, 2003 | accessdate=May 12, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; and wounding three other correspondents.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.fair.org/index.php?page=1843 Is Killing Part of Pentagon Press Policy?&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Zucchino, ''Thunder Run'', 2004&lt;/ref&gt;

After interviewing &quot;about a dozen reporters who were at the scene, including two embedded journalists who monitored the military radio traffic before and after the shelling occurred&quot; the [[Committee to Protect Journalists]] said the facts suggested &quot;that attack on the journalists, while not deliberate, was avoidable.&quot; The Committee to Protect Journalists went on to say that &quot;Pentagon officials, as well as commanders on the ground in Baghdad, knew that the Palestine Hotel was full of international journalists and were intent on not hitting it&quot;. It is not clear that orders not to fire upon the hotel had actually made it to the tank level.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.cpj.org/Briefings/2003/palestine_hotel/palestine_hotel.html Permission to Fire? - Reports - Committee to Protect Journalists&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt; [[Reporters Without Borders]] demanded proof from Donald Rumsfeld that incidents &quot;were not deliberate attempts to dissuade the media from reporting.&quot; [[Amnesty International]] demanded independent investigation.
:''see [[April 8, 2003 journalist deaths by U.S. fire]] for more detail.''

==Journalist casualties==
There have been a number of journalist casualties during the invasion, including fourteen deaths (some not directly war-related). [[Michael Kelly (editor)|Michael Kelly]], an influential neoconservative reporter, columnist, and editor died in a [[Humvee]] accident on April 3. NBC's [[David Bloom]] died of a blood clot on April 6. Both Kelly and Bloom were embedded with the [[United States Army|U.S. Army's]] [[U.S. 3d Infantry Division|3rd Infantry Division]]. [[ITN]] reporter [[Terry Lloyd]] was killed by US forces near [[Basra]] on March 22, 2003.

==Critical Journalists==
Journalist [[Peter Arnett]] was fired by [[MSNBC]] and [[National Geographic]] after he declared in an interview with the Iraqi information ministry that he believed the U.S. strategy of &quot;[[shock and awe]]&quot; had failed. He also went on to tell Iraqi State TV that he had told &quot;Americans about the determination of the Iraqi forces, the determination of the government, and the willingness to fight for their country,&quot; and that reports from Baghdad about civilian deaths had helped antiwar protesters undermine the Bush administration's strategy. The interview was given 10 days before the fall of Baghdad.

==References==
{{reflist|2}}

==External links==
* [http://www.nytimes.com/2003/04/16/international/worldspecial/16FOX.html Cable's War Coverage Suggests a New 'Fox Effect' on Television], ''The New York Times'', April 16, 2003
* [http://www.cjonline.com/stories/042403/bre_landonlec.shtml MSNBC's Banfield: Media filtered realities of war], ''Topeka Capitol-Journal'', Matt Moline, April 24, 2003
* [http://web.archive.org/web/20050201012646/http://www.latimes.com/entertainment/printedition/calendar/la-war-howard25apr25214426,1,4381680.column The independence of CNN; the legacy of NBC's Bloom], Howard Rosenberg, ''Los Angeles Times'', April 25, 2003
*[http://www.prospect.org/weblog/archives/2003/02/index.html#000743 Why Phil Got Killed], TAPPED, February 27, 2003
* [http://www.fair.org/international/iraq.html Archive of well-documented media criticism of Iraqi war coverage], Provided by the national media watch group, FAIR.
* [http://www.ithaca.edu/rhp/media_iraq/ Selection of links and resources on media coverage of the war in Iraq], Provided by The Roy H. Park School of Communications at Ithaca College.
* [http://video.google.com/videoplay?docid=-6840473009639653689# Independent Media in a Time of War], Documentary on the media coverage of the invasion.
* Faulk, Kent. ''[http://www.al.com/news/birminghamnews/index.ssf?/base/news/113040497267990.xml&amp;coll=2 &quot;Soldier fought to make difference&quot;]'', The [[Birmingham News]]. October 27, 2005. Retrieved October 30, 2005.
* Salles, Andre. ''[http://web.archive.org/web/20070927204305/http://www.suburbanchicagonews.com/beaconnews/top/2_1_AU27_VIGIL_S1.htm &quot;Vigil notes 2000 U.S. war dead&quot;]'', The Beacon News. October 27, 2005. Retrieved October 27, 2005.
* Cannon, Jason. ''[http://www.clantonadvertiser.com/articles/2005/10/26/news/a-news.txt &quot;Roadside bomb kills Clanton soldier&quot;]{{Dead link|date=December 2008}}'', The Clanton Advertiser. October 26, 2005. Retrieved October 26, 2005.
* Parsons, Claudia &amp; Quinn, Andrew. ''[http://today.reuters.com/news/newsArticle.aspx?type=worldNews&amp;storyID=2005-10-25T194546Z_01_YUE544037_RTRUKOC_0_US-IRAQ.xml &quot;US military death toll in Iraq reaches 2,000&quot;]{{Dead link|date=December 2008}}'', [[Reuters]]. October 25, 2005. Retrieved October 26, 2005.
* ''[http://www.defenselink.mil/releases/2005/nr20051025-4982.html &quot;DoD Identifies Army Casualty&quot;]'', [[United States Department of Defense]]. October 25, 2005. Retrieved October 29, 2005.
* [http://web.archive.org/web/20070605105057/http://www.pipa.org/OnlineReports/Iraq/Media_10_02_03_Report.pdf Misperceptions, The Media, and The Iraq War], PIPA. October 2, 2003.

[[Category:Media coverage and representation]]
[[Category:Iraq War and the media|Media coverage]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
