<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="21244171" ns="0" title="Gentry"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{About|the social concept of gentry}}
[[Image:Cleric-Knight-Workman.jpg|250px|right||thumb|Cleric, Knight, and Peasant archetypes represent the virtues of [[prudence]], [[fortitude]] and [[Temperance (virtue)|temperance]]. In [[Classical antiquity]] and [[Christendom]], prudence and fortitude were seen as the main virtues that should govern society. (See also [[Cardinal virtues]], [[Junzi]].)]]

'''Gentry''' (origin [[Old French]] ''genterie'', from ''gentil'', &quot;high-born, noble&quot;) denotes &quot;well-born and well-bred people&quot; of high [[social class]], especially in the past.&lt;ref&gt;[http://dictionary.cambridge.org/define.asp?key=32548&amp;dict=CALD Cambridge Advanced Learner's Dictionary]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.askoxford.com:80/concise_oed/gentry?view=ukCompact Oxford English Dictionary]&lt;/ref&gt;

''Gentry'', in its widest connotation, refers to people of good social position connected to [[landed estate]]s (see [[Manorialism]]), including various ranks of nobility, clerical upper crust and &quot;gentle&quot; families of long descent who never obtained official right to bear a [[coat of arms]].

In England, the term often refers to the social class of the [[landed aristocracy]] or to the minor [[aristocracy]] (see [[landed gentry]]) whose income derives from their large landholdings&lt;ref&gt;''Webster's New Universal Unabridged Dictionary'', 1996, p.798.&lt;/ref&gt; and thus designates the more narrow definition.  The idea of ''gentry'' in the continental sense of &quot;[[nobility|noblesse]]&quot; is extinct in England, despite the efforts of enthusiasts to revive it (see A.C. Fox-Davies, ''Armorial Families'', Edinburgh, 1895; ''The Right to Bear Arms'', 1900). Though the untitled nobility in England are normally termed ''gentry'' the older sense of &quot;nobility&quot; is that of a quality identical with gentry. Arms sex legally ensigns of nobility, that is, gentility.

The fundamental social cleavage in most parts of Europe in the Middle Ages was between the &quot;nobiles&quot;, i.e. the tenants in chivalry, whether counts, barons, knights, esquires or [[franklin (class)|franklins]], and the &quot;ignobiles&quot;, i.e. the villeins, citizens and burgesses; and between the most powerful noble and the humblest franklin there was, until the 15th century, no &quot;separate class of gentlemen&quot;.
The division into nobles and ignobles in smaller regions of Europe in the [[Middle Ages]], such as Sweden (including the province of [[Finland]]), was less exact due to a more rudimentary feudal order. As such, the difference in the late Middle Ages between the medieval Swedish nobility and the wealthier strata of the peasantry was small. After the [[Reformation]], intermingling between the noble class and the often hereditary clerical upper class became a distinctive feature in several [[Nordic countries]].

The adjective ''[[Patrician (post-Roman Europe)|patrician]]'' (&quot;of or like a person of high social rank&quot;)&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://dictionary.cambridge.org/search/british/?q=patrician|title=Patrician|publisher=dictionary.cambridge.org}}&lt;/ref&gt; describes most closely members of the governing elites found within metropolitan areas such as the medieval [[City-state|free cities]] of Italy ([[Venice]], [[Genoa]]), [[Free imperial city|free imperial cities]] of [[Germany]] and [[Switzerland]] and the areas of the [[Hanseatic League]], which, by virtue of their urban milieu, differed from the gentry. Still, many urban patricians, e.g., in Venice, had rural residences in the countryside (e.g., [[Veneto]]). Following the admired example of the [[Patrician (ancient Rome)|Roman patrician]], the Venetian patrician reverted, especially in the [[Renaissance]], to a life more focused on his rural estate.

== Historical definition ==
===Indo-European caste systems===
{{Main|Caste}}  [[Image:Three kings or three gods.jpg|thumbg|200px|left|thumb|This part of a 12th-century Swedish tapestry has been interpreted to show, from left to right, the one-eyed [[Odin]], the hammer-wielding [[Thor]] and [[Freyr]] holding up an ear of corn. This [[Triple deities|triad]] corresponds closely to the trifunctional division: Odin is the patron of priests and magicians, Thor of warriors, and Freyr of fertility and farming.&lt;ref&gt;Leiren, Terje I. (1999). ''From Pagan to Christian: The Story in the 12th-Century Tapestry of the Skog Church''. Published online: http://faculty.washington.edu/leiren/vikings2.html&lt;/ref&gt;]]
The [[Proto-Indo-Europeans|Indo-Europeans]] who settled Europe, Western Asia and the Indian Subcontinent conceived their societies to be ordered (not divided) in a tripartite fashion, the three parts being castes.&lt;ref&gt;Mallory, J.P. ''In search of the Indo-Europeans'' Thames &amp; Hudson (1991) p131&lt;/ref&gt; Castes came to be further divided, perhaps as a result of greater specialisation.

The &quot;classic&quot; formulation of the caste system as largely described by [[Georges Dumézil]] was that of a priestly or religiously occupied caste, a warrior caste, and a worker caste.
[[Georges Dumézil|Dumézil]] divided the [[Proto-Indo-European society|Proto-Indo-Europeans]] into three categories: [[sovereignty]], [[military]], and productivity (see [[Trifunctional hypothesis]]). He further subdivided [[sovereignty]] into two distinct and complementary sub-parts. One part was formal, juridical, and priestly, but rooted in this world. The other was powerful, unpredictable, and also priestly, but rooted in the &quot;other&quot;, the supernatural and spiritual world. The second main division was connected with the use of force, the [[military]], and war. Finally, there was a third group, ruled by the other two, whose role was productivity: herding, farming, and [[crafts]].

This caste system can be seen to be that which flourished on the Indian Subcontinent and amongst the Italic peoples.

Examples of the Indo-European Castes:

*'''Indo-Iranian''' - [[Brahmin]]/Athravan, [[Kshatriyas]]/Rathaestar, [[Vaishyas]]
*'''Roman''' - [[Flamen|Flamines]], [[Milites]], [[Quirites]]
*'''Celtic''' - [[Druid]]s, [[Equites]], [[Plebs|Plebes]] (according to [[Julius Caesar]])
*'''Anglo-Saxon''' - Gebedmen (prayer-men), Fyrdmen (army-men), Weorcmen (workmen) (according to [[Alfred the Great]])
*'''Slavic ''' - Volkhvs, Voin, Krestyanin/Smerd
*'''Nordic''' - [[Earl]], [[Churl]], [[Thrall]] (according to the [[Poetic Edda|Lay of Rig]])
*'''Greece (Attica)''' - [[Eupatridae]], [[Geomori]], [[Demiurge|Demiurgi]]
*'''Greece (Sparta)''' - [[Spartiate|Homoioi]], [[Perioeci]], [[Helots]]

Kings were born out of the warrior or noble class.

====End of caste system and replacement by class system====
{{Main|Class society}}
[[File:Organisation féodale.svg|350px|right||thumb|The feudal social structure in three orders: those who pray (''oratores''), fight (''bellatores'') and work (''laboratores'')]]
The revolutions in British America and France and then elsewhere directly challenged Indo-European culture and swept away the native caste system and replaced it with a system based on class, but it is noticeable that in many countries, the class system then followed a tripartite division like the caste system: for example, the upper, middle and lower class used in Britain and the ''Dreiklassen'' system in Germany.

===Two principal estates of the realm ===

The gentry is formed on the bases of the medieval societies' two higher estates of the realm, [[nobility]] and [[clergy]], both exempted from tax. Subsequent &quot;gentle&quot; families of long descent who never obtained official rights to bear a coat of arms were also admitted to the rural upper-class society: the gentry.

'''The three estates'''

The widespread three estates order was particularly characteristic of France:

* First estate included the group of all clergy, that is, members of the higher clergy and the lower clergy.
* Second estate has been encapsulated by the nobility. Here too, it did not matter whether they came from a lower or higher nobility or if they were impoverished members.
* Third estate included all nominally free citizens; in some places, free peasants.

At the top of the pyramid were the princes and estates of the king or emperor, or with the clergy, the bishops and the pope.

The feudal system was, for the people of the Middle Ages and early modern period, fitted into a God-given order. The nobility and the third estate were born into their class, and change in social position was slow, if possible at all. Wealth had little influence on what estate one belonged to. The exception was the Medieval Church, which was the only institution where competent men (and women) of merit could reach, in one lifetime, the highest positions in society.

The first estate comprised the entire clergy, traditionally divided into &quot;higher&quot; and &quot;lower&quot; clergy. Although there was no formal demarcation between the two categories, the upper clergy were, effectively, clerical nobility, from the families of the second estate or as in the case of [[Cardinal Wolsey]], from more humble backgrounds.

The second estate was the nobility. Being wealthy or influential did not automatically make one a noble, and not all nobles were wealthy and influential (aristocratic families have lost their fortunes in various ways, and the concept of the &quot;poor nobleman&quot; is almost as old as nobility itself). Countries without a feudal tradition did not have a nobility as such.[[File:Mittelalterliches Ständebild 15. Jahrhundert.png|left||thumb|Estates of the realm as an expression of the traditional [[social stratification]] in the [[Occident]]]]
The nobility of a person might be either inherited or earned. Nobility in its most general and strict sense is an acknowledged preeminence that is hereditary:  legitimate descendants (or all male descendants, in some societies) of nobles are nobles, unless explicitly stripped of the privilege. The terms ''aristocrat'' and ''aristocracy'' are a less formal means to refer to persons belonging to this social milieu.

Historically in some cultures, members of an upper class often did not have to work for a living, as they were supported by earned or inherited investments (often real estate), although members of the upper class may have had less actual money than merchants. Upper-class status commonly derived from the social position of one's family and not from one's own achievements or wealth. Much of the population that comprised the upper class consisted of aristocrats, ruling families, titled people, and religious hierarchs. These people were usually born into their status, and historically, there was not much movement across class boundaries. This is to say that it was much harder for an individual to move up in class simply because of the structure of society.

In many countries, the term ''upper class'' was intimately associated with hereditary land ownership and titles. Political power was often in the hands of the landowners in many pre-industrial societies (which was one of the causes of the French Revolution), despite there being no legal barriers to land ownership for other social classes. Power began to shift from upper-class landed families to the general population in the early modern age, leading to marital alliances between the two groups, providing the foundation for the modern upper classes in the West. Upper-class landowners in Europe were often also members of the titled nobility, though not necessarily: the prevalence of titles of nobility varied widely from country to country. Some upper classes were almost entirely untitled, for example, the Szlachta of the Polish-Lithuanian Commonwealth.

Before the Age of [[Absolutism (European history)|Absolutism]], institutions, such as the church, legislatures, or social elites,&lt;ref&gt;{{ cite web|url=http://www2.sunysuffolk.edu/westn/absolutism.html|title=French Absolutism |accessdate=2007-09-29|work=SUNY Suffolk history department}}&lt;/ref&gt; restrained monarchical power. Absolutism was characterized by the ending of feudal partitioning, consolidation of power with the monarch, rise of state, rise of professional standing armies, professional bureaucracies, the codification of state laws, and the rise of ideologies that justify the absolutist monarchy. Hence, Absolutism was made possible by new innovations and characterized as a phenomenon of [[Early Modern Europe]], rather than that of the Middle Ages, where the clergy and nobility counterbalanced as a result of mutual rivalry.

==Gentries ==
=== Europe ===
==== German ====
{{Main|German nobility}}

In Germany, nobility and titles pertaining to it were bestowed on a person by higher sovereigns and then passed down through legitimate children of a nobleman. Alternatively, unlike men, women could legally become members of nobility by marrying a noble, although they could not pass it on. Nobility and titles (except for most reigning titles) were always inherited equally by all legitimate descendants of a nobleman.

''Divisions of nobility in Germany''

* ''[[Uradel]]'' (ancient nobility): Nobility that dates back to at least the 16th century. This contrasts with:

* ''[[Briefadel]]'' (patent nobility): Nobility by letters patent. The first known such document is from September 30, 1360, for Wyker Frosch in Mainz.

* ''[[Hochadel]]'' (high nobility): Nobility that was sovereign or had a high degree of sovereignty. This contrasts with:

* ''[[Niederer Adel]]'' (lower nobility): Nobility that had a lower degree of sovereignty.

'''[[Edler]]''' (Edler von) was, until 1919, the lowest title of [[nobility]] in [[Austria-Hungary]] and Germany, just beneath a [[Ritter]], but above nobles without title, who used only the preposition ''von'' before their surname. It was mostly given to civil servants and military officers, as well as those upon whom the second rank of an [[Order (decoration)|Order]] had been conferred. Women were styled '''Edle''' (Edle von).

Originally, from the Middle Ages, under the [[feudal system]] (in Europe and elsewhere), the nobility were generally those who held a [[fief]], often in the form of heritable land worked by [[vassals]].

'''[[Ritter]]''' ([[German language|German]] for &quot;[[knight]]&quot;) is a designation used as a [[title]] of [[nobility]] in German-speaking areas. Traditionally, it denotes the second lowest rank within the nobility, standing above [[Edler]] and below [[Freiherr]]. For its historical association with warfare and the [[landed gentry]] in the [[Middle Ages]], it can be considered roughly equal to the titles of &quot;[[Knight]]&quot; or &quot;[[Baronet]]&quot;. As with most [[title]]s and designations within the [[nobility]] in German-speaking areas, the rank was normally hereditary and would generally be used together with the designation of '''von''' before a family name.

In the [[Austrian Empire]], the title of &quot;Ritter von&quot; would be bestowed upon citizens who deserved more than the plain &quot;von&quot;.

In German, the meaning of ''Ritter'' is &quot;rider&quot;, and likewise for the [[Dutch language|Dutch]] and [[North Germanic languages|Scandinavian]] title ''ridder''. These words are cognates derived from Germanic ''rīdan'', &quot;to ride&quot;, from Proto-Indo-European ''reidh-''.&lt;ref&gt;See [http://www.bartleby.com/61/roots/IE429.html reidh-] from American Heritage Dictionary's Index of Indo-European Roots.&lt;/ref&gt;

'''[[Junker]]''' in [[German language|German]] means &quot;country squire&quot; and is probably derived from the German words ''Junger Herr'' (English: &quot;young lord&quot;). As part of the nobility, many ''Junker'' families have particles like ''[[von]]'' or ''[[Nobility particle|zu]]'' before their family names. In the [[Middle Ages]], a ''Junker'' was simply a lesser noble, often poor and politically insignificant. Over the centuries, they rose from mercenary captains to influential commanders and landowners in the 19th century, especially in the [[Kingdom of Prussia]].

Being the bulwark of [[House of Hohenzollern|Hohenzollern]] Prussia, the ''Junkers'' controlled the [[Prussian Army]], led in [[Politics|political influence]] and [[social status]], and owned immense [[Estate (house)|estates]], especially in the north-eastern half of Germany ([[Province of Brandenburg|Brandenburg]], [[Mecklenburg]], [[Province of Pomerania (1815–1945)|Pomerania]], [[Province of East Prussia|East Prussia]], [[Province of Saxony|Saxony]] and [[Province of Silesia|Silesia]]).&lt;ref&gt;Frederic Austin Ogg, ''The governments of Europe'' (1920), Macmillan, p. 681&lt;/ref&gt;[[File:Bismarck pickelhaube.jpg|100px|left|thumb|[[Otto von Bismarck]] wearing a [[cuirassier]] officer's metal ''[[Pickelhaube]]'']][[Image:Parade 1894.JPG|thumb|right|200px|[[German Emperor]] [[William II, German Emperor|William II]] reviews Prussian troops, by [[Carl Röchling]].]]
They dominated all the higher civil offices and officer corps. Supporting [[monarchism]] and military traditions, they were often [[reactionary]] and protectionist; they were often anti-[[Liberalism|liberal]], siding with the conservative monarchist forces during the [[Revolutions of 1848 in the German states|1848 Revolution]]. Their political interests were served by the [[German Conservative Party]] in the [[Reichstag (German Empire)|Reichstag]] and the extraparliamentary [[Agrarian League]]. This political class held tremendous power over the industrial classes and the government. When Chancellor [[Leo von Caprivi|Caprivi]] reduced the protective duties on imports of grain, these landed magnates demanded and obtained his dismissal; and in 1902, they brought about a restoration of such duties on foodstuffs as would keep the prices of their own products at a high level.

As landed aristocrats, the ''Junkers'' owned most of the arable land in the Prussian and eastern German states. This was in contrast to the Catholic southern states, such as [[Bavaria]], [[Württemberg]] or [[Baden]], where land was owned by small farms, or the mixed agriculture of the western states, such as [[Hesse]] or [[Westphalia]]. This gave the ''Junkers'' a virtual monopoly on all agriculture in the German states east of the [[Elbe|River Elbe]].

The German statesman [[Otto von Bismarck]] was a noted ''Junker'', as were [[President of Germany#Weimar_Republic|President]] [[Paul von Hindenburg]] and ''[[Generalfeldmarschall]]'' [[Gerd von Rundstedt]].

==== Dutch ====

'''[[Ridder (title)|Ridder]]''' ([[Dutch (language)|Dutch]] &quot;[[knight]]&quot;) is a noble title in the Netherlands and Belgium.  The collective term for its holders in a certain locality is the '''Ridderschap''' (e.g. Ridderschap van Holland, Ridderschap van Friesland, etc.).  In the Netherlands and Belgium, no female equivalent exists.  It is placed between the first name(s) and the family name (as ''ridder'', not ''Ridder'', as in Dutch, titles are written in lower case, which in this case also avoids confusion between the family name and the title).

The title ''Ridder'' descends in two ways: &quot;op allen&quot; (to all - i.e., every descendant, male or female, in the male line, is entitled to the title) and &quot;met het recht op eerstgeboorte&quot; (with the right of the first-born - i.e., descent by [[Salic law]], i.e., the eldest male descendant of the title's first bearer may take the title, but not the others).

'''[[Jonkheer]]''', or '''Jonkvrouw''', is literally translated as &quot;young [[lord]]&quot; or &quot;young [[lady]]&quot;, or &quot;[[esquire]]&quot;. In medieval times, such a person was a young and unmarried son or daughter of a high-ranking knight or nobleman. Many noble families could not support all their sons to become a knight because of the expensive equipment. So the eldest son of a knight was a young lord, and his brothers remained as esquires.
However, in the low countries (and other parts of continental Europe), only the head of most noble families did and does carry a title and inheritability of it is via the male lineage. This resulted, therefore, that most of the nobility was and is nowadays untitled in the Netherlands and Belgium. ''Jonkheer'', and its female equivalent ''jonkvrouw'', developed quite early into a different but general meaning, i.e., an honorific to show that someone does belong to the nobility, but does not possess a title. The abbreviation ''jhr.'', or ''jkvr.'' for women, is placed in front of the name (preceding academic, but not state titles).

&lt;center&gt;&lt;gallery perrow=&quot;4&quot;&gt;
File:Jonkheer J. van Eyck (Componist).jpg|Jonkheer [[Jacob van Eyck]]
File:Jonkheer Lodewijk de Boisot (Cornelis Visscher, 1649).jpg|Jhr. Lodewijk de Boisot
File:Theodorus Frederik van Capellen.jpg|Jhr. [[Theodorus Frederik van Capellen]] (1762-1824)
File:Jan Willem Jassens door Pieneman.jpg|Jhr. [[Jan Willem Janssens]]
File:Dirk de Graeff van Polsbroek.jpg|Jhr. [[Dirk de Graeff van Polsbroek]]
File:Beerenbrouck.jpg|Jhr. [[Charles Ruijs de Beerenbrouck]]
File:J. Veth Alexander Frederik de Savornin Lohman.jpg|Jhr. [[Alexander de Savornin Lohman]]
File:Guilherme Alexandre, príncipe de Orange.jpg|[[Willem-Alexander, Prince of Orange|Willem-Alexander der Nederlanden]], Jonkheer van Amsberg
 &lt;/gallery&gt;&lt;/center&gt;

==== British ====
{{Main|British nobility|landed gentry}}

The British upper classes consist of two entities, the [[peerage]] and [[landed gentry]]; any male member of either may regard himself as a gentleman, in a special sense mutually understood between hereditary members of the class, which will often exclude life peers. In the British peerage, only the senior family member (typically the oldest son) inherits a substantive title (duke, marquess, earl, viscount, baron); these are referred to as peers or lords. The rest of the nobility is referred as landed gentry (abbreviation, gentry), and with the exceptions of the [[baronet]], which is a title akin to a hereditary knighthood; those that are knighted (for life), being called Sir X Y; [[Baron#Scotland|Scottish barons]], who bear the designation Baron of X after their name;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.lyon-court.com/lordlyon/536.html |title=The Court of the Lord Lyon web site |accessdate=2010-06-22}}&lt;/ref&gt; and [[Laird|Scottish lairds]], whose names include a description of their lands in the form of a [[territorial designation]],&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.debretts.com/forms-of-address/titles/scottish--and-irish-titles/chief,-chieftain,-laird.aspx |title=Debrett's Forms of Address (Lairds) |accessdate=2010-07-18}}&lt;/ref&gt; they bear no titles apart from the qualifications of esquire or gentleman (which are ranks recognised in law, although now without any legal consequence).

The term ''landed gentry'', although originally used to mean nobility, came to be used of the lesser nobility in England around 1540.  Once identical, eventually these terms became complementary, in the sense that their definitions began to fill in parts of what the other lacked. The term ''gentry'' by itself as commonly used by historians, so [[Peter Coss]] argues, is a construct that historians have applied loosely to rather different societies. Any particular model may not fit a specific society, yet a single definition nevertheless remains desirable.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.history.ac.uk/reviews/review/402 Michael Hicks, review of The Origins of the English Gentry, (review no. 402)]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://assets.cambridge.org/97805210/21005/frontmatter/9780521021005_frontmatter.pdf Cambridge University Press 0521021006 - The Origins of the English Gentry Peter Coss]&lt;/ref&gt;

Titles, while often considered central to the upper class, are not strictly so. Both Captain [[Mark Phillips]] and Vice Admiral [[Timothy Laurence]], the respective first and second husbands of HRH The [[Anne, Princess Royal|Princess Anne]], lacked any rank of [[peerage]], yet could scarcely be considered anything other than upper class. The same is true of [[Francis Fulford (born 1953)|Francis Fulford]], who was memorably featured in a [[Channel 4]] documentary and whose family has owned estates in [[Devon]] for over 800 years. In fact, the Fulfords represent the group that makes up the largest component of the upper class: the [[landed gentry]].

'''[[Landed gentry]]''' is a traditional British [[social class]] consisting of [[gentlemen]] in the original sense; that is, those who owned land in the form of [[country estate]]s to such an extent that they were not required to actively work, except in an administrative capacity on their own lands. The estates were often (but not always) made up of [[tenant farm|tenanted farms]], in which case the gentleman could live entirely off [[renting|rent]] income.

''[[Burke's Landed Gentry]]''

In the 18th and 19th centuries, the names and families of those with titles (specifically [[peers]] and [[baronets]], less often including those with the non-hereditary title of [[knight]]) were often listed in books or manuals known as &quot;Peerages&quot;, &quot;Baronetages&quot;, or combinations of these categories, such as the &quot;Peerage, Baronetage, Knightage, and Companionage&quot;. As well as listing genealogical information, these books often also included details of a given family right to a [[coat of arms]]. [[Jane Austen]], who was herself a member of the gentry, shrewdly summarised the appeal of these works, which was particularly strong for those included in them, in the opening words of her novel ''[[Persuasion (novel)|Persuasion]]'' (1818):

:&quot;Sir Walter Elliot, of Kellynch Hall, in Somersetshire, was a man who, for his own amusement, never took up any book but the Baronetage; there he found occupation for an idle hour, and consolation in a distressed one; there his faculties were roused into admiration and respect, by contemplating the limited remnant of the earliest patents; there any unwelcome sensations, arising from domestic affairs changed naturally into pity and contempt as he turned over the almost endless creations of the last century; and there, if every other leaf were powerless, he could read his own history with an interest which never failed.&quot;

'''[[Esquire]]''' (abbreviated '''Esq.''') is a term of British origin (ultimately from Latin ''scutarius'', in the sense of shield bearer, via Old French ''esquier''), referring only to males, and used to denote a high but indeterminate social status.

The most common occurrence of term ''Esquire'' today is the conferral as the suffix ''Esq.'' in order to pay an informal compliment to a male recipient by way of implying [[gentle birth]]. Today, there remain respected protocols, especially in the US, for identifying those to whom it is thought most proper that the suffix should be given in very formal or in official circumstances. The social rank of Esquire is that above [[gentlemen]]. Nineteenth-century tables of precedences further distinguished between ''esquires by birth'' and ''esquires by office'' (and likewise for ''gentlemen'').{{Citation needed|date=July 2007}}.

According to one typical definition,&lt;ref&gt;Burn, Richard; Chitty, J; Black, Philip (1975, reprint of the 1831 edition) ''The Justice of the Peace and Parish Officer'', pages 884–885; see also [http://books.google.com/books?id=GI0DAAAAQAAJ books.google.com], pages 540–541&lt;/ref&gt; esquires in English law included:

*The eldest sons of [[knight]]s, and their eldest sons in perpetual succession
*The eldest sons of younger sons of [[Peerage|peer]]s, and their eldest sons in perpetual succession (children of peers already had higher precedence)
*Esquires created by [[letters patent]] or other investiture, and their eldest sons
*Esquires by virtue of their offices, as [[Justice of the Peace|Justices of the Peace]] and others who bear any office of trust under the [[The Crown|Crown]]
*Esquires of knights constituted at their investiture
*Foreign noblemen
*Persons who are so styled under the [[Royal sign-manual|Royal sign manual]] (officers of the [[British Armed Forces|Armed Forces]] of or above the rank of [[Captain (land)|Captain]] in the [[British Army|Army]] or its equivalent)
*[[Barrister]]s (but not [[Solicitor]]s)

A slightly later source&lt;ref name=boutell&gt;Boutell, Charles (1899) ''English Heraldry'', page 120; see also [http://books.google.com/books?id=47Qtu3tkmFsC books.google.com], page 120&lt;/ref&gt; defines the term as
{{quote|''Esquire'' — A rank next below that of Knight.  Besides those Esquires who are personal attendants of Knights of Orders of Knighthood, this title is held by all attendants on the person of the Sovereign, and all persons holding the Sovereign's commission being of military rank not below Captain; also, by general concession, by Barristers at Law, Masters of Arts and Bachelors of Law and Physic.}}

In the post-mediaeval world, the title of ''esquire'' came to belong to all men of the higher [[landed gentry]]; an esquire ranked socially above a [[gentleman]] but below a [[knight]]. In the modern world, where all men are assumed to be gentlemen, the term has correspondingly often been extended (albeit only in very formal writing) to all men without any higher title. It is used post-nominally, usually in abbreviated form: &quot;Thomas Smith, Esq.&quot;, for example.

The linguistic and social development of ''squire'' is paralleled by that of the [[German language|German]] ''[[junker]]'', which originally meant &quot;young lord&quot; and denoted the poorer and unimportant part of the aristocracy, but &quot;went up in the world&quot; in much the same time as ''squire'' did in England.

'''[[Knight]]''', from [[Old English]] ''cniht'' (&quot;boy&quot; or &quot;servant&quot;),&lt;ref name=&quot;Etymo&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.etymonline.com/index.php?l=k&amp;p=3 |title=Knight |work=Online Etymology Dictionary |accessdate=2009-04-07}}&lt;/ref&gt; is a [[cognate]] of the [[German language|German]] word ''Knecht'' (&quot;laborer&quot; or &quot;servant&quot;).&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://dict.leo.org/ende?lp=ende&amp;p=KO6ek.&amp;search=Knecht |title=Knecht |work=LEO German-English dictionary |accessdate=2009-04-07}}&lt;/ref&gt; A knight can be either a medieval tenant giving military service as a mounted man-at-arms to a feudal landholder, or a medieval gentleman-soldier, usually high-born, raised by a sovereign to privileged military status after training as a page and squire (contemporary reference, see [[British honours system]]).  

In the century or so following Charlemagne's death, his newly empowered warrior class grew stronger still, and [[Charles the Bald]] declared their fiefs to be hereditary. The period of chaos in the 9th and 10th centuries, between the fall of the Carolingian central authority and the rise of separate Western and Eastern Frankish kingdoms (later to become France and Germany respectively), only entrenched this newly landed warrior class. This was because governing power, and defense against [[Viking]], [[Hungarian people|Magyar]] and [[Saracen]] attack, became an essentially local affair that revolved around these new hereditary local [[lord]]s and their ''[[demesne]]s''. The resulting hereditary, landed class of mounted elite warriors, the knights, were increasingly seen as the only true soldiers of Europe, hence the exclusive use of ''miles'' (Latin, &quot;soldier&quot;) for them.

All nobles of military age were generally considered as knights; knighthood still had to be earned through some exploit involving the use of arms. The general route for a son of a nobleman would be to first serve as page, then as squire, before being knighted.

In formal protocol, '''''[[Sir]]''''' is the correct [[Style (manner of address)|styling]] for a [[knight]] or a [[baronet]] (the UK nobiliary rank just below all [[Peerage|peers of the realm]]), used with (one of) the knight's [[given name]](s) or full name, but not with the [[Family name|surname]] alone.  The equivalent for a woman is [[Dame (title)|Dame]], that is, for one who holds the title in her own right; for such women, the title ''Dame'' is used as ''Sir'' for a man, that is, never before the surname on its own. This usage was devised in 1917, derived from the practice, up to the 17th century (and still also in legal proceedings), for the wife of a knight. The wife of a knight or baronet now, however, is styled &quot;[[Lady]] [Surname]&quot;.

Until the 17th century, it was also a title of priests (the related word ''[[monsignor]]'', from French ''monseigneur'', is still used for Catholic prelates). In [[Icelandic language|Icelandic]], the cognate word ''séra'' is used exclusively to address a priest, together with his first name: a priest named Jón Jónsson would be addressed as ''séra Jón'' and referred to as ''presturinn séra Jón Jónsson'' (&quot;the priest, ''séra'' Jón Jónsson&quot;).

The '''[[Peerage]]''' is a system of [[titles]] in the United Kingdom, which represents the upper ranks of [[British nobility]] and is part of the [[British honours system]]. The term is used both collectively to refer to the entire body of titles, and individually to refer to a specific title. All modern British honours, including peerage dignities, are created directly by the [[Monarchy of the United Kingdom|British monarch]], taking effect when [[letters patent]] are affixed with the [[Great Seal of the Realm]].  The Sovereign is considered the [[fount of honour]], and as &quot;the fountain and source of all dignities cannot hold a dignity from himself&quot;,&lt;ref&gt;Opinion of the House of Lords in the ''[[Buckhurst Peerage Case]]''&lt;/ref&gt; cannot hold a peerage.

The modern peerage system is a vestige of the custom of English kings in the 12th and 13th centuries in summoning wealthy individuals (along with church officials and elected representatives for commoners) to form a Parliament.  The economic system at the time was [[manorialism]] (or [[feudalism]]), and the burden or privilege of being summoned to Parliament was related to the amount of land one controlled (a &quot;barony&quot;).  In the late 14th century, this right (or &quot;title&quot;) began to be granted by decree, and titles also became inherited with the rest of an estate under the system of [[primogeniture]].  Non-hereditary positions began to be created again in 1867 for Law Lords, and 1958 generally.

* The [[Peerage of England]] — all titles created by the Kings and Queens of England before the [[Act of Union 1707|Act of Union]] in 1707.
* The [[Peerage of Scotland]] — all titles created by the Kings and Queens of [[Scotland]] before 1707.
* The [[Peerage of Ireland]] — titles created for the [[Kingdom of Ireland]] before the [[Act of Union 1800|Act of Union]] of 1801, and some titles created later.
* The [[Peerage of Great Britain]] — titles created for the Kingdom of Great Britain between 1707 and 1801.
* The [[Peerage of the United Kingdom]] — most titles created since 1801.

Peers are of five ranks, in descending order of hierarchy:
* [[Duke]] comes from the [[Latin]] ''dux'', leader. Created in 1337.&lt;ref name=&quot;cftech&quot;&gt;[http://www.cftech.com/BrainBank/OTHERREFERENCE/FORMSOFADDRESS/OrdBritPeer.html CFtech.ncom]&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[Marquess]] comes from the French ''marquis'', which is a derivative of ''marche'', or march.  This is a reference to the borders (&quot;[[marches]]&quot;) between England, Scotland and Wales, a relationship more evident in the feminine form: Marchioness. Created in 1385.&lt;ref name=&quot;cftech&quot; /&gt;
* [[Earl]] comes from the [[Old English]] or Anglo-Saxon ''eorl'', a military leader. The meaning may have been affected by the [[Old Norse]] ''jarl'', meaning free-born warrior or nobleman, during the [[Danelaw]], thus giving rise to the modern sense. Since there was no feminine Old English or Old Norse equivalent for the term, &quot;Countess&quot; is used (an Earl is analogous to the [[Continental Europe|Continental]] ''[[count]]''), from the Latin ''comes''.  Created circa 800–1000.&lt;ref name=&quot;cftech&quot; /&gt;
* [[Viscount]] comes from the Latin ''vicecomes'', vice-count. Created in 1440.&lt;ref name=&quot;cftech&quot; /&gt;
* [[Baron]] comes from the Old Germanic ''baro'', freeman. Created in 1066.&lt;ref name=&quot;cftech&quot; /&gt;

'''Portrait gallery of British Gentry'''
The portraits (below) are an illustration of people and surnames from the gentry.

&lt;center&gt;&lt;gallery perrow=&quot;6&quot;&gt;
File:Elizabeth de Clare.jpg|[[Elizabeth de Clare]]
File:Bishop William Smyth.jpg|[[William Smyth|His Lordship Bishop William Smyth]]
File:Lady Margaret Beaufort.jpg|[[Lady Margaret Beaufort]]
File:Unknown woman, formerly known as Margaret Pole, Countess of Salisbury from NPG retouched.jpg|[[Margaret Pole, 8th Countess of Salisbury]] 
File:Walter Devereux, 1st Earl of Essex from NPG.jpg|[[Walter Devereux, 1st Earl of Essex]] 
File:PhilipHowardEarlOfArundel.jpg|[[Philip Howard, 20th Earl of Arundel]]
File:Wenceslas Hollar - William Dugdale (State 5) cropped.jpg|[[William Dugdale]]
File:Sir Jonathan Trelawny, 3rd Bt by Sir Godfrey Kneller, Bt.jpg|[[Sir Jonathan Trelawny, 3rd Baronet|His Lordship Bishop Jonathan Trelawny]] 
File:GeorgeChurchill.jpg|[[George Churchill (Royal Navy officer)|George Churchill]] 
File:John Erskine.jpeg|[[John Erskine, 22nd Earl of Mar]]
File:Benedict Calvert.jpg|[[Benedict Calvert, 4th Baron Baltimore]] 
File:Thomas Forster.gif|[[Thomas Forster]] [[Esquire|Esq.]]
File:Rev Nicolas Tindal - portrait.jpg|[[Nicolas Tindal|The Reverend Nicolas Tindal]]
File:Gen james oglethorpe.jpg|[[James Oglethorpe]]
File:Sirjohnacton.jpg|[[Sir John Acton, 6th Baronet]]
File:Lady Elizabeth Hamilton (1753–1797), Countess of Derby.jpg|Lady Elizabeth Hamilton, Countess of Derby
File:William Windham by Sir Joshua Reynolds.jpg|[[William Windham]] 
File:Lord Robert William Manners by William Salter.jpg|[[Lord Robert Manners (major-general)]]
File:Charles Gordon-Lennox, 5th Duke of Richmond and Lennox 1824.jpg|[[Charles Gordon-Lennox, 5th Duke of Richmond and Lennox]]
File:Rowland Egerton-Warburton.jpg|[[Rowland Egerton-Warburton]]
File:7thDukeOfDevonshire.jpg|[[William Cavendish, 7th Duke of Devonshire]]
File:Sir William Molesworth, 8th Bt by Sir John Watson-Gordon.jpg|[[Sir William Molesworth, 8th Baronet]]
File:Lady Jane Erskine.jpg|[[The Honourable]] [[James Henry Callander|Jane Plumer Erskine]] 
File:Robert Arthur Talbot Gascoyne-Cecil, 3rd Marquess of Salisbury by George Frederic Watts.jpg|[[Robert Cecil, 3rd Marquess of Salisbury]]
File:John Roddam Spencer Stanhope.jpg|[[John Roddam Spencer Stanhope]]
File:24thBarondeRos.jpg|[[Dudley FitzGerald-de Ros, 24th Baron de Ros]]
File:CRMarkham25.jpg|[[Sir]] [[Clements Markham]]
File:Lorne.jpg|[[John Campbell, 9th Duke of Argyll]]   
File:Charles E Marfleet Battle.gif|Charles E Marfleet Battle, [[Squire]] of [[Somerton Castle]] and Boothby Graffoe
File:Laszlo - Winifred Anna Cavendish-Bentinck (née Dallas-Yorke), 6th Duchess of Portland, 1912.jpg|[[Winifred Cavendish-Bentinck, Duchess of Portland]]
File:Simon Joseph Fraser, 14th Lord Lovat.jpg|[[Simon Fraser, 14th Lord Lovat]]
File:General Carter-Campbell.png|[[George Carter-Campbell]] 
File:Lady Margaret Sackville.jpg|[[Lady Margaret Sackville]]
File:Edward George Villiers Stanley, 17th Earl of Derby by Sir William Orpen.jpg|[[Edward Stanley, 17th Earl of Derby]]
File:Thomas Innes of Learney.jpg|[[Thomas Innes of Learney]]
File:The 7th Marquess of Cholmondeley Allan Warren.jpg|[[David Cholmondeley, 7th Marquess of Cholmondeley]] 
&lt;/gallery&gt;&lt;/center&gt;

====Swedish (and Finnish)====
{{Main|Swedish nobility}}

The Swedish nobility ''([[Adeln]])'' were historically a legally privileged [[Social class|class]] in Sweden, part of the so-called ''[[frälse]]'' (a classification defined by tax exemptions and representation in the [[Diet (assembly)|diet]] that also applied to [[clergy]]).

Generally, the nobility grew from wealthier or more powerful members of the peasantry, those who were capable of assigning work or wealth to provide the requisite cavalrymen. In Sweden, there never existed outright [[serfdom]]. Hence, nobility was basically a class of well-off citizens, not owners of other human beings. In the Middle Ages and much of the modern age, nobles and other wealthy men were landowners, as well as lords of [[villein]]s and servants. Members of the nobility utilized their economic power and sometimes also other powers to have small-farm owners sell their lands to manor lords, so landowning centralized gradually more in the hands of the noble class.

There was a special group of petty nobility, the so-called ''[[knap]]adel'', derived from the last centuries of the Middle Ages, who generally were not able to produce a royal letter of ennoblement to support their status. Regarding certain districts where there existed a disproportionally high number of such families, their introduction to the House of Nobility was often denied. However, in most cases, such petty noble families were ultimately registered as nobles (the concept of &quot;ancient nobility&quot; was a loose one, in many cases demonstrated only by privileges enjoyed for a long time, for example in taxation or holding offices). Thus, quite many families confirmed in their nobility in the 17th century were presumably actually without any original royal ennoblement, but only became frälse by decisions of past royal bailiffs of castles and such.

At the head of the Swedish clergy stood the Archbishop of Uppsala since 1164. The clergy encompassed almost all the educated men of the day and furthermore was strengthened by considerable wealth, and thus it came naturally to play a significant political role. Until the Reformation, the clergy was the first estate but was relegated to the secular estate in the Protestant North Europe. Clerical (pastor) Families is a concept in genealogy to characterize some families in the Swedish Church after the Reformation, in which members of the family had served for generations in the Swedish Church either as active clergy in the Church, educational institutions or in the civil service.

''Divisions of nobility in Sweden''

Swedish nobility is organized into three classes according to a scheme introduced in ''riddarhusordningen'' ([[Rules of order|Standing orders]] of the House of Knights), 1626
* [[Count]]s (''greve'') and [[baron]]s (''[[friherre]]'', &quot;baron&quot;) in the ''Class of Lords'' ({{lang-sv|Herreklassen}}) (these two titles were introduced in 1561 by [[Erik XIV]]),
* the ''Class of Knights'' ({{lang-sv|Riddarklassen}}), untitled descendants of [[Privy Council of Sweden|Swedish Privy Councillors]], and
* the ''Class of [[Esquire]]s'' ({{lang-sv|Svenneklassen}}), other untitled nobles.
The last two classes contain the so-called ''untitled [[nobility]]'' ({{lang-sv|obetitlad adel}}). The division into classes has roots in the [[Middle Ages]] when the nobility ''frälse'' was divided into lords in the Privy Council, knights and esquires.

'''Surnames'''

Surnames in Sweden can be traced to the 15th century, when they were first used by the Gentry (Frälse), i.e., priests and nobles. The names of these were usually in Swedish, Latin, German or Greek.

The adoption of Latin names was first used by the Catholic clergy in the 15th century. The given name was preceded by Herr (Sir), such as Herr Lars, Herr Olof, Herr Hans, followed by a Latinized form of patronymic names, e.g., Lars Petersson Latinized as Laurentius Petri. Starting form the time of the Reformation, the Latinized form of their birthplace ([[Laurentius Petri Gothus]], from Östergötland) became a common naming practice for the clergy.  The Swedish family [[Benzelius family|Benzelius]] was derived from Bentseby (Bentse village) in [[Luleå]], the birthplace of [[Erik Benzelius the Elder|Ericus Henrici Benzelius Bothniensis]], who was the first to adopt the family name. The [[Retzius]] surname was from Lake Ressen, near the Odensvi parish vicarage in [[Västervik Municipality|Västervik]]. Later merchants and other social groups discarded the formerly used family names (such as patronymic surnames) and adopted high-sounding Latin surnames, which conjured an image of an old family pedigree.

Another subsequent practice was the use of the Greek language with the ending of ''ander'', the Greek word for man (e.g., [[Julius Micrander|Micrander]], [[Karl Fredrik Mennander|Mennander]]). The use of surnames was still quite uncommon in the 17th century among the nobility and the educated class. Furthermore, the concept of hereditary surnames was also limited to a few families.

When a family was ennobled, it was usually given a name—just as lordships of England and other Western European countries. In the 17th and 18th centuries, the surname was only rarely the original family name of the ennobled; usually, a more imposing new name was chosen. This was a period which produced a myriad of two-word Swedish-language family names for the nobility (very favored prefixes were Adler, &quot;eagle&quot;; Ehren - &quot;ära&quot;, &quot;honor&quot;; Silfver, &quot;silver&quot;; and Gyllen, &quot;golden&quot;). The regular difference with Britain was that it became the new surname of the whole house, and the old surname was dropped altogether. The [[ennoblement]] (in 1632) of Peder Joenson is a case in point, where the use the old surname was discontinued, and thus, after the ennoblement, &quot;Peder Gyllensvärd&quot; came in to use. An illustration of the old name having an addition to it can be seen in the ennoblement of the brothers Johan Henrik Lang and Lars Adam Lang (in 1772) taking the surname Langenskjöld.

Usually, the descendants of a bishop where ennobled, but not the bishop himself or any other member of the clergy. This was due to the fact that clergy represented the clerical estate and hence would have no use of nobility. The medieval tradition continued in Catholic countries, which meant that the clergy was the first estate, and noblemen who took orders should not in principle use their own family coat of arms.

'''Portrait gallery of Swedish (Finnish) Gentry'''
The portraits (below) are an illustration of people and surnames from the gentry.

&lt;center&gt;&lt;gallery perrow=&quot;5&quot;&gt;
File:Clfleming 2.jpg|[[Clas Fleming (admiral)]]
File:Johan Gyllenstierna.png|[[Johan Gyllenstierna]]
File:Nils Bielke porträtterad av David Richter dy.jpg|Count [[Nils Bielke]]
File:Jacob De la Gardie 1606.jpg|Count [[Jacob De la Gardie]]
File:Göran Silfverhielm.jpg|[[Göran Silfverhielm]]
File:Anders Celsius.jpg|[[Anders Celsius]]
File:Evadelagardie.gif|Countess [[Eva Ekeblad]] 
File:Augustin Ehrensvard.jpg|Count [[Augustin Ehrensvard]]
File:Carl Jesper Benzelius.JPG|The Right Reverend [[Carl Jesper Benzelius]]
File:Johan Henrik Hastesko.jpg|[[Johan Henrik Hästesko]]
File:Jacob Magnus Sprengtporten.jpg|[[Jacob Magnus Sprengtporten]]
File:JohanGabrielOxenstierna.jpg|Count [[Johan Gabriel Oxenstierna]]
File:Porträtt föreställande Sophie Piper, målning av Carl Fredrik von Breda.jpg|Countess [[Sophie Piper]]
File:Armfelt.png|Count [[Gustaf Mauritz Armfelt]]
File:Carl Gustaf von Brinkman 1835.jpg|[[Carl Gustaf von Brinkman]]
File:Malla Silfverstolpe 1843.jpg|[[Malla Silfverstolpe]] 
File:MagnusBrahe.jpg|[[Magnus Brahe (1790–1844)|Magnus Brahe]] 
File:Jacquette Löwenhielm 1824.jpg|Countess [[Jaquette Löwenhielm]]
File:Adolf Erik Nordenskiöld by Axel Jungstedt 1902.jpg|Baron [[Adolf Erik Nordenskiöld]] 
File:Swedish Reichsmarschall Fredrik von Essen.jpg|Baron [[Fredrik von Essen]]
 &lt;/gallery&gt;&lt;/center&gt;

'''Grand Principality of Finland'''
[[Image:GustafHorn.jpg|100px|left|thumb|Finnish 17th-century nobleman [[Gustaf Horn]]]]
[[Image:Johannes Gezelius vanhempi.jpg|100px|left|thumb|Finnish 17th-century clergyman [[Johannes Gezelius]] the elder]]

Areas of modern-day Finland were integrated into the Swedish realm in the 13th century, at a time when that realm was still in the process of being formed. The formal nobility in Finland dates back to 1280 when it was agreed in the entire Swedish realm by the [[Decree of Alsnö]] that magnates who could afford to contribute to the cavalry with heavily equipped soldiers were to be exempted from tax, at least from ordinary land taxes, as the clergy already had been. The archaic term for nobility, ''frälse'', also includes the clergy when referring to their exemption from tax.

At the time of [[Late Middle Ages]], Latin was still the language of instruction from the secondary school upwards and in use among the educated class and priests. As Finland was part of Sweden for 500 years, [[Swedish language|Swedish]] was the language of the nobility, administration and education. Hence the two highest [[estates of the realm]], i.e. [[Nobility|nobles]] and [[clergy|priests]], had Swedish as the language of the gentry. In the two minor estates, [[Bourgeoisie|burghers]] and [[peasant]]s, Swedish also held sway, but in a more varying degree depending on regional differences.

In the Middle Ages, celibacy in the [[Catholic Church]] was a natural barrier to the formation of an hereditary priestly class. After compulsory celibacy was abolished in Sweden during the [[Protestant Reformation|Reformation]], the formation of an hereditary priestly class became possible, whereby wealth and clerical positions were frequently inheritable. Hence the bishops and the vicars, who formed the clerical upper class, would frequently have [[Manorialism|manors]] similar to those of the nobility. Hence continued the medieval Church legacy of the intermingling between noble class and clerical upper class and the intermarriage as the distinctive element in several Nordic countries after the Reformation. As a result, the gentry in Finland was constituted by nobles, clerical and some burgher families.

Among the nobility, a very large proportion of the families arrived directly from Sweden, but a significant amount had foreign origins (predominantly [[Germans|German]])&lt;ref&gt;Haggren &amp; Jansson, 2005. New light on the colonization of Nyland, [http://www.ennenjanyt.net/4-04/haggren.pdf ennenjanyt.net] &quot;Nyland has always been characterized as an area of medieval colonization conducted by the Swedes. Previously this colonization has been seen as an immigration of independent peasants. As a new result a significant noble impact has been verified both in the colonization activity itself and the establishing of parish churches as well&quot;.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Kari Tarkiainen, Sveriges Österland, från forntiden till Gustav Vasa, 2008, &quot;Frälseståndets ursprung var till två tredjedel svenskt, till en tredjedel tyskt. Någon social rörelse som skulle ha fört kristnade finnar uppåt till dessa poster fanns inte, då jordegendomen inte var ett vilkor för en ledande ställning inom förvaltning, rättskipning och skatteadministration&quot;.&lt;/ref&gt; but their descendants normally adopted Swedish as their first language. The clergy in the earlier part of the formation of the [[Lutheran Church]] (in its [[High Church Lutheranism|High Church]] form) was constituted most often of the wealthier strata of the peasantry with the closely linked medieval [[Finnish nobility]] and the rising burgher class in the expanding cities. Their descendants usually adopted Swedish as their first language, but, as the Church required fluency in Finnish from clergymen serving in predominantly or totally Finnish-speaking parishes (most of the country), they tended to maintain a high degree of functional bilingualism. In the Middle Ages, commerce in the Swedish realm, including Finland, was dominated by German [[merchants]] who immigrated in large numbers to the cities and towns of Sweden and Finland. As a result, the wealthier burghers in Sweden (and in Finnish cities such as [[Åbo]] and [[Vyborg]]) during the late Middle Ages tended to be of German origin. In the 19th century, a new wave of immigration came from German-speaking countries predominantly connected to commercial activities, which has to date formed a notable part of the Swedish-speaking grand bourgeoisie in Finland.

The lowest, non-titled level of hereditary nobility was &quot;adelsman&quot; (i.e., &quot;noble&quot;). The untitled nobility was basically a rank without a fief. In practice, however, the majority of noble houses were fief holders until the late 19th century.

In contrast to the United Kingdom and the [[Benelux]] countries, it has been impossible to grant hereditary [[title of nobility|titles]] or honours since 1917. The last baron created was [[August Langhoff]] in 1912; he was [[Finnish Minister Secretary of State]].

====Hungarian====
{{Main|Nobility in the Kingdom of Hungary}}
'''Nobility in the Kingdom of Hungary'''

The origin of the [[nobility]] in the [[Kingdom of Hungary]] can be traced back to the &quot;men distinguished by birth and dignity&quot; (''maiores natu et dignitate'') mentioned in the charters of the first kings. They descended partly from the leaders of the [[Magyar tribes]] and [[clan]]s and partly from the immigrant (mainly [[Germans|German]], [[Italians|Italian]] and [[French people|French]]) knights who settled in the kingdom in the course of the 10th-12th centuries.[[Image:Castle in Nadasel (Cluj County, Romania).JPG|thumb|right|200px|A little noble (gentry) manor house in [[Nădăşelu, Cluj|Magyarnádas]] (today, Nădăşelu in Romania)]] By the 13th century, the [[Royal servant (Kingdom of Hungary)|royal servants]] (''servientes regis''), who mainly descended from the wealthier freemen (''liberi''), managed to ensure their liberties and their privileges were confirmed in the [[Golden Bull of 1222|Golden Bull]] issued by King [[Andrew II of Hungary]] in 1222. Several families of the [[Royal castle's serf (Kingdom of Hungary)|soldiers of the royal fortresses]] (''iobagio castri'') could also strengthen their liberties, and they received the status of the &quot;true nobles of the realm&quot; (''veri nobiles regni'') by the end of the 13th century, although most of them lost their liberties and became subordinate to private-castle holders. Many leaders of the mainly [[Slavic peoples|Slavic]], [[Germans|German]] and [[Romanians|Romanian]] colonists who immigrated to the kingdom during the 11th-15th centuries also merged into the nobility. Moreover, the kings had the authority to reward [[commoners]] with nobility, and thenceforward, they enjoyed all the liberties of other nobles.

From the 14th century, the idea of &quot;one and the same liberty&quot; (''una eademque libertas'') appeared in the [[public law]] of the kingdom; the idea suggested that all the nobles enjoyed the same privileges independently of their offices, birth or wealth. Moreover, [[public law]] also recognized the existence of some groups of the &quot;[[Conditional nobility (Kingdom of Hungary)|conditional nobility]]&quot; (''conditionarius'') whose privileges were limited; ''e.g.'', the &quot;[[Nobles of the Church (Kingdom of Hungary)|nobles of the Church]]&quot; (''nobilis ecclesiæ'') were burdened with defined services to be provided to certain [[prelate]]s. In some cases, not individuals but a group of people was granted a legal status similar to that of the nobility; ''e.g.'', the [[Hajduk#Hungary|Hajdú]] people enjoyed the privileges of the nobility not as individuals but as a community.

==== Spanish ====
{{Main|Spanish nobility}}

Spanish nobles are classified either as ''Grandes de España'' (also called in English ''[[grandee]]s''), or as titled nobles. Formerly, grandees were divided into the first, second and third classes, but now, all grandees enjoy the same privileges. Lower nobility held titles such as [[Hidalgo (Spanish nobility)|hidalgo]], [[infanzon]] (Aragonese equivalent to hidalgo), and [[escudero]] (esquire), but these do not correspond to [[baron]], a title unknown to Spanish nobility but in Catalonia. Hidalgo (plural: hijosdalgo) was the most common one, all the people of [[Biscay]] having been granted that noble title. All titled and untitled nobles are considered hidalgos.

''' Grandee''' (Grandeza de España)

The dignity of grandee (&quot;grand one&quot;) was apparently originally assumed by the most important nobles. Being a grandee formerly implied certain privileges, notably that of the ancient uses of remaining covered or seated in the presence of royalty.

'''Hidalgo'''
{{Main|Hidalgo (Spanish nobility)}}
[[File:Don Quijote and Sancho Panza.jpg|150px|thumb|right|[[Gustave Doré]]: [[Don Quixote|Don Quixote of La Mancha and Sancho Panza]], 1863]]
An '''hidalgo''' or '''fidalgo''' is a member of the Spanish [[nobility]]. In popular usage, it has come to mean the non-titled nobility. Hidalgos were exempt from paying [[tax]]es, but did not necessarily own [[real property]].

Since at least the 12th century, the phrase ''fijo dalgo'' (often literally translated as &quot;son of something&quot;), or its common contraction, ''fidalgo'', was used in the [[Kingdom of Castile|Kingdoms of Castile]] and [[Kingdom of Portugal|Portugal]] to refer to the [[nobility]]. In Portugal, the [[cognate (etymology)|cognate]] remained ''[[fidalgo]]'', although these &quot;nobles&quot; had a somewhat different status from the Spanish hidalgos. In the [[Kingdom of Aragon]] the counterpart of the Castilian hidalgos were called ''infanzones'' (singular: ''infanzón''). With the changes in Spanish pronunciation that occurred in the late Middle Ages, the [[Voiceless labiodental fricative|[f]]] became silent, giving rise to the modern pronunciation and spelling, ''hidalgo''.&lt;ref&gt;[[Joan Coromines|Corominas, Joan]] and José A Pascual (1981). &quot;Hijo&quot; in ''Diccionario crítico etimológico castellano e hispánico'', Vol. G-Ma (3). Madrid: Editorial Gredos, 359-360. ISBN 84-249-1362-0&lt;/ref&gt; (See [[History of the Spanish language]].)

The term is a [[calque]] of the [[Arabic influence on the Spanish language|Arabic]] expressions which used ''ibn'' (&quot;son&quot;) or ''bint'' (&quot;daughter&quot;) and an noun to describe someone. Although the word ''algo'' generally means &quot;something&quot;, in this expression, the word specifically denotes &quot;riches&quot; or &quot;wealth&quot;; therefore, it was originally a [[synonym]] of &quot;noble&quot; or ''ricohombre'' (literally a &quot;rich man&quot;) in the Spanish of the period.

In literature, the hidalgo is usually portrayed as a noble who has lost nearly all of his family's wealth but still held on to the privileges and honours of the nobility. The prototypical fictional hidalgo is [[Don Quixote (ballet)|Don Quixote]], who was given the [[sobriquet]] &quot;the Ingenious Hidalgo&quot; by his creator, [[Miguel de Cervantes]]. In the novel, Cervantes has Don Quixote satirically present himself as an ''hidalgo de sangre'' and aspire to live the life of a [[knight-errant]] despite the fact that his economic position does not allow him to truly do so.&lt;ref&gt;{{Citation |last= Rey Hazas |first= Antonio |title= El ''Quijote'' y la picaresca: la figura del hidalgo en el nacimiento de la novela moderna |journal= Edad de Oro |volume= 15 |pages=141–160 |url= http://cvc.cervantes.es/obref/quijote_antologia/hazas.htm |language= Spanish |accessdate=2009-06-02}}&lt;/ref&gt; Don Quixote's possessions allowed to him a meager life devoted to his reading [[Obsessive-compulsive disorder|obsession]], yet his concept of honour led him to emulate the knights-errant.

==== Polish====
'''Szlachta'''
{{Main|Szlachta}}

The Polish term ''szlachta'' designates the formalized, hereditary noble class. In official Latin documents, the old [[Polish-Lithuanian Commonwealth|Commonwealth]] hereditary szlachta is referred to as ''nobilitas'' and is equivalent to the English nobility.

The Polish nobility probably derived from a Slavic warrior class, forming a distinct element within the ancient Polonic tribal groupings. This is uncertain, however, as there is little surviving documentation on the early history of Poland, or of the movements of the Slavonic people into what became the territory so designated. The szlachta themselves claimed descent from the Sarmatians (see paragraph 2.2 below) who came to Europe in the 5th century C.E. Around the 14th century, there was little difference between knights and the szlachta in Poland, apart from legal and economic. Members of the szlachta had the personal obligation to defend the country (''pospolite ruszenie''), thereby becoming the kingdom's privileged social class.

All children of the Polish nobility inherited their noble status from a noble mother and father. Any individual could attain ennoblement (''{{lang|pl|nobilitacja}}'') for special services to the state. A foreign noble might be naturalised as a Polish noble (Polish: ''indygenat'') by the Polish king (later, from 1641, only by a [[general sejm]]).
[[File:Ubior Szlachty.jpg|400px|thumb|right|Polish noblemen, early 17th century]]

In theory at least, all Polish noblemen were social equals. Also in theory, they were legal peers. Those who held &quot;real power&quot; dignities were more privileged but these dignities were not hereditary. Those who held honorary dignities were higher in &quot;ritual&quot; hierarchy, but these dignities were also granted for a lifetime. Some tenancies became hereditary and went with both privilege and titles. Nobles who were not direct barons of the Crown but held land from other lords were only peers &quot;de iure&quot;. The poorest enjoyed the same rights as the wealthiest magnate. The exceptions were a few symbolically privileged families such as the Radziwiłł, Lubomirski and [[Czartoryski]], who sported honorary aristocratic titles recognized in Poland or received from foreign courts, such as &quot;[[Prince]]&quot; or &quot;[[Count]]&quot;. (See also [[The Princely Houses of Poland]].) All other szlachta simply addressed each other by their given name or as &quot;Sir Brother&quot; (''Panie bracie'') or the feminine equivalent. The other forms of address would be &quot;Illustrious and Magnificent Lord&quot;, &quot;Magnificent Lord&quot;, &quot;Generous Lord&quot; or &quot;Noble Lord&quot; (in decreasing order), or simply &quot;His/Her Grace Lord/Lady&quot;.

According to their financial standing, the nobility were in common speech divided into:
* magnates: the wealthiest class; owners of vast lands, towns, many villages, thousands of peasants
* [[middle nobility]] (''średnia szlachta''): owners of one or more villages, often having some official titles or Envoys from the local Land Assemblies to the General Assembly,
* [[petty nobility]] (''drobna szlachta''): owners of a part of a village or owning no land at all, often referred to by a variety of colourful Polish terms such as:
**''szaraczkowa'' - &quot;grey nobility&quot;, from their grey, [[wool]]len, uncoloured [[żupan]]s
**''okoliczna'' - &quot;local nobility&quot;, similar to ''zaściankowa''
**''zagrodowa'' - from ''zagroda'', a farm, often little different from a peasant's dwelling
**''zagonowa'' - from ''zagon'', a small unit of land measure, &quot;hide nobility&quot;
**''cząstkowa'' - &quot;partial&quot;, owners of only part of a single village
**''panek'' - little ''pan'' (i.e. lordling), term used in [[Kashubia|Kaszuby]], the Kashubian region, also one of the legal terms for legally separated lower nobility in late medieval and early modern Poland
**''hreczkosiej'' - &quot;[[buckwheat]] sowers&quot; &lt;!--more or less--&gt; - those who had to work their fields themselves
**''zaściankowa'' - from ''zaścianek'', a name for plural nobility settlement, &quot;neighbourhood nobility&quot;; just like ''hreczkosiej'', ''zaściankowa'' nobility would have no peasants
**''brukowa'' - &quot;[[Cobblestone|cobble]] nobility&quot;, for those living in towns like townsfolk
**''gołota'' - &quot;naked nobility&quot;, i.e., the landless. ''Gołota'' szlachta would be considered the 'lowest of the high'.

'''The rise of the aristocrat magnate'''

For many centuries, wealthy and powerful members of the szlachta sought to gain legal privileges over their peers. Few szlachta were wealthy enough to be known as magnates (''karmazyni'' — the &quot;[[Crimson]]s&quot;, from the crimson colour of their boots). A proper magnate should have been able to trace noble ancestors back for many generations and owned at least 20 villages or [[folwark|estate]]s. He should also have held a major [[offices in Polish-Lithuanian Commonwealth|office in the Commonwealth]].

Some historians estimate the number of magnates as 1% of the number of szlachta. Out of approximately one million szlachta, tens of thousands of families, only 200-300 persons could be classed as great magnates with country-wide possessions and influence, and 30-40 of them could be viewed as those with significant impact on Poland's politics.

&lt;center&gt;&lt;gallery perrow=&quot;5&quot;&gt;
File:Barbara Kolanka.jpg|[[Barbara Kola]]
File:Andrzej Frycz Modrzewski.JPG|[[Andrzej Frycz Modrzewski]]
File:Stanisław Hozjusz.PNG|[[Stanislaus Hosius]] 
File:Jan Tarnowski (Hetman).jpg|[[Jan Tarnowski]]
File:POL Marek Sobieski.jpg|[[Marek Sobieski]]
File:Franciszek Maksymilian Ossolinski (1676-1756).jpg|[[Franciszek Maksymilian Ossoliński]]
File:Karol Ferdynand Waza.jpg|[[Karol Ferdynand Vasa]]
File:Elżbieta Sieniawska.jpg|[[Elżbieta Sieniawska]]
File:Kazimierz Pułaski.PNG|[[Casimir Pulaski]] 
File:Michał Kazimierz Ogiński.PNG|[[Michał Kazimierz Ogiński]] 
File:Hugon Kołłątaj.PNG|[[Hugo Kołłątaj]]
File:Radziwill.GIF|[[Antoni Radziwiłł]]
File:Paweł Edmund Strzelecki.jpg|[[Paweł Edmund Strzelecki]]
File:Jan Leon Kozietulski.PNG|[[Jan Kozietulski]]
File:Delfina Potocka 4.jpg|[[Delfina Potocka]]
File:August Franciszek Maria Anna Józef Kajetan Czartoryski Muñoz, duque de Vista Alegre.jpg|[[August Czartoryski|August Franciszek Maria Anna Józef Kajetan Czartoryski, Duke of Vista Alegre]]
File:Antoni Patek.jpg|[[Antoni Patek]]
File:Jan Puzyna.jpg|[[Jan Puzyna de Kosielsko]]
File:Jozef Pilsudski.jpg|[[Józef Piłsudski]]
File:Czeslaw Milosz, 1986.jpg|[[Czeslaw Milosz]]
&lt;/gallery&gt;&lt;/center&gt;

==== Baltic ====
{{Main|Baltic nobility|Baltic Germans|Lithuanian nobility|Szlachta|Terra Mariana|Danish Estonia|Swedish Livonia|Swedish Estonia|Baltic governorates|Baltic states}}
[[File:Baltic coat of arms.svg|thumb|right|110px|Coat of arms of Terra Mariana (Land of [[St. Mary]]), which was the official name&lt;ref name=&quot;EA&quot;&gt;{{cite encyclopedia | year =1967  | title =Terra Mariana | encyclopedia =The Encyclopedia Americana | publisher =Americana Corp  | location =  | id = |url=http://books.google.com/books?id=jsJWAAAAMAAJ&amp;q=%22Livonia.+Under+its+official+name,+Terra+Mariana%22&amp;dq=%22Livonia.+Under+its+official+name,+Terra+Mariana%22&amp;ei=HV4aSbrgEYOUMojX-acE&amp;pgis=1}}&lt;/ref&gt; for [[Medieval]] [[Livonia]]&lt;ref&gt;[http://books.google.com/books?client=firefox-a&amp;um=1&amp;q=%22Medieval+Livonia%22&amp;btnG=Search+Books Medieval Livonia @ google books]&lt;/ref&gt; or Old Livonia&lt;ref&gt;referred to by historians as Medieval Livonia or Old Livonia [http://books.google.com/books?client=firefox-a&amp;um=1&amp;q=%22Old+Livonia%22&amp;btnG=Search+Books Old Livonia @ google books] to distinguish it from the rump-[[Livonia]] ([[Duchy of Livonia]]) and the [[Livonian Governorate]] that was formed from part of its territories after its breakup.&lt;/ref&gt;]]
[[Image:COA of Gediminaičiai dynasty Lithuania.png|thumb|right|110px|Columns of [[Gediminas]], among the first symbols of Lithuania and used as a part of [[heraldry|heraldic]] signs of leading the aristocracy]]

The '''Baltic nobility''' in Latvia and Estonia has existed continuously since the medieval days of [[Terra Mariana]], which was formed in the aftermath of the [[Livonian Crusade]] in the territories comprising present-day [[Estonia]] and [[Latvia]]. Most of the nobles in [[Livonia]]  were [[Baltic German]]s, but [[Poland|Poles]] and [[Sweden|Swedes]] joined as well, and [[Russia]]ns later under the [[Russian empire]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://personen.digitale-sammlungen.de/baltlex/Band_bsb00000445.html Carl Arvid von Klingspor’s ''Baltisches Wappenbuch. Wappen sämmtlicher, den Ritterschaften von Livland, Estland, Kurland und Oesel zugehöriger Adelsgeschlechter'' (Stockholm 1882)]&lt;/ref&gt;

The Baltic nobility of Livonia was a source of officers and other servants to Swedish and Polish kings in the 16th and particularly 17th centuries, when [[Couronia]]n, [[Swedish Estonia|Estonia]]n, [[Livonia]]n and [[Oesel]]ian lands belonged to them. Russian emperors used Baltic nobles in government.

They were organized in the [[:de:Estländische Ritterschaft|Estonian Noble Corporation]] in [[Reval]], Couronian Noble Corporation in [[Mitau]], and Livonian Noble Corporation in [[Riga]].

It should be noted that in the course of their 700-year history, Baltic German families often had not only ethnic German roots, but also mixed with peoples of non-German origin, such as native Estonians, Livonians and Latvians, as well as with Danes, Swedes, English, Scots, Poles, Dutch, and Hungarians.

In those cases where intermarriage occurred, the other ethnic group usually assimilated into the German culture and adopted the German language and customs, which often included &quot;Germanizing&quot; their names and surnames. They were then considered Baltic Germans as well. (See also: [[Ethnogenesis]].)

In the Imperial census of 1897, 98,573 Germans (7.58% of total population) lived in the [[Governorate of Livonia]], 51,017 (7.57%) in the [[Governorate of Curonia]], and 16,037 (3.89%) in the [[Governorate of Estonia]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://demoscope.ru/weekly/ssp/rus_lan_97.php?reg=49 Language Statistics of 1897] {{ru icon}}&lt;/ref&gt;   

The Lithuanian gentry consisted mainly of [[Lithuanians]], but due to strong ties to Poland, had been culturally Polonized. After the [[Union of Lublin]] in 1569, they became less distinguishable from Polish ''[[szlachta]]'', although preserved [[Lithuania]]n national awareness.

The Lithuanian nobility was historically a legally privileged class in the [[Grand Duchy of Lithuania]], from the historical regions of [[Lithuania Proper]] and [[Samogitia]], and in some cases [[Ruthenia]]n noble families.  Families were primarily granted [[privileges]] for their military service to the Grand Duchy. 

The Church had been from the beginning the foundation of the learned society in the Baltic region. It was not only the religious, but also the social and political aspects of which were intervowen in the life of the Church in the Middle Ages. A noticeable part of the clergy were recruited from the local inhabitants, and the celibacy of clergy constrained the rise of structure-based inheritable privileges in the Church.
The Protestant Reformation brought about great change in the Baltic Region of Europe. The Church in Lithuania remained Catholic, but a large part of Livonia came under the sway of the Reformation. The first to accept the ideas of the Reformation where the merchants of [[Riga]] and [[Reval]], which subsequently functioned as the centers of the Reformation. The Lutheran Church in the Baltics did not come to have the institutional importance or independence its counterpart had in the Nordic countries. Up until the 20th century, the Lutheran Church was dominated by the German segment of the population. The clergy were mostly constituted of German-speaking inhabitance or had often come from Germany.  Financially, the clergy where tied to the Baltic German nobilities' estates, which provided revunues. All this added to the notion of the Lutheran Church by the ethnic majority of Estonians and Latvians as Baltic German and not their own. Following the independence of Latvia and Estonia, the refounded national churches took steps to distance itself from its Baltic German association and emphasize Estonian and Latvian aspects.

'''Noble titles in Estonia and Livonia'''

*Duke (only one)- [[Schleswig-Holstein-Sonderburg-Beck]], Ex. [[Peter August, Duke of Schleswig-Holstein-Sonderburg-Beck]]
*Fürst (usually translated into English as [[Prince]] )- Ex. [[Barclay de Tolly]]. Fürst [[Michael Andreas Barclay de Tolly]]
*Marquis (only one)- Ex. [[Paulucci]], Marquis [[Philip Osipovich Paulucci]]
*Count- Ex. [[Anrep family|Anrep-Elmpt]], Count [[Joseph Carl von Anrep]]
*Baron (or the corresponding title of [[Freiherr]] )- Ex. [[von Buddenbrock]], Baron [[Henrik Magnus von Buddenbrock]]

'''Baltic German gentry from Curonia, Estonia and Livonia'''

&lt;center&gt;&lt;gallery perrow=&quot;6&quot;&gt;
File:Albert of Riga.JPG|[[Bishop of Riga]] [[Albert of Riga|Albrecht von Buxthoeven]]
File:Wrangel Herman-Ugglan.jpg|[[Herman Wrangel]] 
File:Jacob De la Gardie 1606.jpg|[[Jacob De la Gardie]] 
File:Johannes Gezelius nuorempi.png|[[Johannes Gezelius the younger]]
File:OttoWilhelmvonFersen.jpg|[[Otto Wilhelm von Fersen]]
File:ElisabethSophieBrandKur.JPG|[[Margravine Elisabeth Sophie of Brandenburg]]
File:Laudon.jpg|[[Baron Ernst Gideon von Laudon|Ernst Gideon von Laudon]]
File:Palen P A.jpg|[[Peter Ludwig von der Pahlen]]
File:Jacob Sievers by Joseph Grassi.JPG|[[Jacob Sievers]]
File:JMRLenz rotate.jpg|[[Jakob Michael Reinhold Lenz]]
File:Kruzenshtern I F.jpg| [[Adam Johann von Krusenstern]]
File:Barclay de Tolly portrait copy in XIX.jpg| [[Michael Andreas Barclay de Tolly]]
File:Fabian Wilhelm von Osten-Sacken.jpg|[[Fabian Gottlieb von Osten-Sacken]]
File:Dorothea von Lieven.jpg|[[Dorothea Lieven]]
File:Anton Graff Bildnis Elisa von der Recke 1797.jpg|[[Elisa von der Recke]]
File:Balthasar Campenhausen.jpg|[[Balthasar von Campenhausen|Balthasar Balthasarovich Campenhausen]]
File:Otto von Kotzebue.jpg|[[Otto von Kotzebue]]
File:Baer Karl von 1792-1876.jpg|[[Karl Ernst von Baer]]
File:Johann Friedrich von Eschscholtz.gif|[[Johann Friedrich Eschscholtz]]
File:Struve O.jpg|[[Otto Wilhelm von Struve]] 
File:Dorothea von Medem young.jpg|[[Dorothea von Medem]]
File:Alexander von Bunge.jpg|[[Alexander Bunge]]
File:Kieseritzky.jpg|[[Lionel Kieseritzky]]
File:Otto-magnus-1786.jpg|[[Otto Magnus von Stackelberg (archaeologist)]]
File:AlexanderGrafKeyserling.jpg|[[Alexander Keyserling]]
File:Rennenkampf.jpg|[[Paul von Rennenkampf]]
File:Peter Clodt von Jürgensburg.jpg|[[Peter Clodt von Jürgensburg]]
File:Friedrich Bidder.jpg|[[Friedrich Bidder]]
File:Eduard Toll.jpg|[[Eduard Toll]]
File:Alexander von Oettingen.jpg|[[Alexander von Oettingen]]
File:Paul von Tiesenhausen.jpg|Paul von [[Tiesenhausen]]
File:De Kolong.jpg|[[Jean Alexander Heinrich Clapier de Colongue]]
File:Uex photo full.jpg|[[Jakob von Uexküll]]
File:Ungern-sternberg r.jpg|[[Roman Ungern von Sternberg|Roman von Ungern-Sternberg]]
File:Evgenij Miller.jpg|[[Evgeny Miller]]
File:Patriarch Alexey II of Russia.jpg|[[Alexy II of Moscow]]
&lt;/gallery&gt;&lt;/center&gt;

==== Holy Roman Empire - Austrian Empire ====
'''Western Ukrainian Clergy'''
{{Main|Western Ukrainian Clergy}}
[[File:Bishop consecration Hajdudorog 1913.JPG|thumb|right|200px|Clergy from the Greek Catholic Church in a procession]]

The '''Western Ukrainian Clergy''' of the [[Ukrainian Greek Catholic Church]] were a hereditary tight-knit social caste that dominated western Ukrainian society from the late eighteenth until the mid-20th centuries, following the reforms instituted by [[Joseph II, Holy Roman Emperor|Joseph II, Emperor of Austria]]. Because, like their [[Orthodox Church|Orthodox]] brethren, Ukrainian Catholic priests could marry, they were able to establish &quot;priestly dynasties&quot;, often associated with specific regions, for many generations. Numbering approximately 2,000-2,500 by the 19th century, priestly families tended to marry within their group, constituting a tight-knit hereditary caste.&lt;ref name = &quot;Subtleny&quot;&gt;Orest Subtelny. (1988). ''Ukraine: A History.'' Toronto: University of Toronto Press, pp.214-219.&lt;/ref&gt; In the absence of a significant native nobility and enjoying a virtual monopoly on education and wealth within western Ukrainian society, the clergy came to form that group's native aristocracy. The clergy adopted Austria's role for them as bringers of culture and education to the Ukrainian countryside. Most Ukrainian social and political movements in Austrian-controlled territory emerged or were highly influenced by the clergy themselves or by their children. This influence was so great that western Ukrainians were accused of wanting to create a theocracy in western Ukraine by their Polish rivals.&lt;ref&gt;Himka, John Paul.  (1999). ''Religion and Nationality in Western Ukraine.'' McGill-Queen's University Press: Montreal and Kingston. Pg. 10&lt;/ref&gt; The central role played by the Ukrainian clergy or their children in western Ukrainian society would weaken somewhat at the end of the 19th century but would continue until the mid-20th century.

===North America===
====United States of America ====
'''Colonial families of the United States'''
{{Main|First Families of Virginia|Colonial families of Maryland|Colonial families of the United States }}

[[File:Mtvernon1.jpg|thumb|right|[[Mount Vernon]], [[Virginia]], was the [[plantation#Other types of plantation|plantation]] home of George Washington.]]
[[File:Washington 1787-1790.jpg|100px|thumb|left|[[George Washington]]]]
[[File:T Jefferson by Charles Willson Peale 1791 2.jpg|100px|thumb|left|[[Thomas Jefferson]]]][[Image:monticello.jpg|thumb|alt=Jefferson's home, Monticello|[[Monticello]], in Virginia, was the estate of Thomas Jefferson.]]

The [[Thirteen Colonies|Colonial American]] use of ''gentry'' followed the British usage (i.e., [[landed gentry]]); before the independence of the United States, [[Southern United States|Southern]] [[plantation]] owners were often the younger sons of British landowners, who perpetuated the British system in rural Virginia and Charleston, South Carolina, by employing [[tenant farmers]], [[indentured servants]], and [[chattel]] [[slavery|slaves]]. In the [[Northeastern United States]], the gentry included (colonial and British) offshoot families who established the city of Boston, Massachusetts, and Harvard and Yale colleges.

The families of Virginia (see [[First Families of Virginia]], [[Colonial families of Maryland]]) formed the Virginia gentry class as the old guard of plantation owners in United States.
As General [[Robert E. Lee]]'s paternal ancestors were among the earliest settlers in Virginia, his family was considered among the oldest of the Virginia [[Gentleman#Robert_E._Lee|gentry class]].

The concept of the [[gentleman farmer]] as a man who farms mainly for pleasure rather than for profit was not only a model for the Southern gentry, but very much an ideal befitting some of founding fathers of America, such as Thomas Jefferson and George Washington. Thomas Jefferson, the patron of American agrarianism, wrote in his ''Notes on Virginia'' (1785), &quot;Those who labor in the earth are the chosen people of God, if He ever had a chosen people, whose breasts He has made His peculiar deposit for substantial and genuine virtue.&quot;

George Washington resumed himself the life of a gentleman farmer at his Mount Vernon estate in Virginia following his resignation as commander in chief of the army in December 1783. Washington lived an aristocratic lifestyle—fox hunting was a favorite leisure activity. Like most Virginia planters, he imported luxuries and other goods from England and paid for them by exporting his tobacco crop. Extravagant spending and the unpredictability of the tobacco market meant that many Virginia planters of Washington's day were losing money.

The American gentry, even in cases where the family never had obtained official rights to bear a coat of arms in history, bore all the same hallmarks of traditional elite as in the old continent.

'''The first Families of Virginia and Maryland'''

[[File:Gmetching.gif|100px|thumb|left|[[George Mason IV]]]]
[[File:Gunston-Hall-front.jpg|thumb|right|180px|[[Gunston Hall]] was the home of the United States Founding Father [[George Mason|George Mason IV]].]]
[[File:JohnCarrollGilbertStuart.jpg|100px|thumb|left|John_Carroll_(bishop)|[[John Carroll (bishop)|Bishop John Carroll]]]][[File:Mount Clare, Bayard &amp; South Monroe Streets, Carroll Park (Baltimore, Independent City, Maryland).jpg|thumb|right|180px|[[Mount Clare (Maryland)|Mount Clare]], one of the Carroll family residences]]
[[File:Robert Edward Lee.jpg|100px|thumb|left|[[General Robert E. Lee|Robert E. Lee]]]]
[[Image:Arlington House pre-1861.jpg|thumb|right|190px|Robert E. Lee's [[Arlington House, The Robert E. Lee Memorial|Arlington estate]]]]

First Families of Virginia originated with colonists from England who primarily settled at [[Jamestown, Virginia|Jamestown]] and along the [[James River (Virginia)|James River]] and other navigable waters in the [[Colony of Virginia]] during the 17th century. As there was a propensity to marry within their narrow social scope for many generations, many descendants bear surnames which became common in the growing colony.

Many of the original English colonists considered members of the First Families of Virginia migrated to the [[Colony of Virginia]] during the [[English Civil War]] and [[English Interregnum]] period (1642–1660). Royalists left England on the accession to power of Oliver Cromwell and his Parliament. Because most of Virginia's leading families recognized [[Charles II of England|Charles II]] as King following the execution of [[Charles I of England|Charles I]] in 1649, Charles II is reputed to have called Virginia his &quot;Old Dominion&quot;, a nickname that endures today. The affinity of many early aristocratic Virginia settlers for the Crown led to the term &quot;distressed Cavaliers&quot;, often applied to the Virginia oligarchy. Many Cavaliers who served under King Charles I fled to Virginia. Thus, it came to be that FFVs often refer to Virginia as &quot;Cavalier Country&quot;. These men were offered rewards of land, etc., by King Charles II, but they had settled Virginia and so remained in Virginia.

Most of such early settlers in Virginia were so-called &quot;Second Sons&quot;.  [[Primogeniture]] favored the first sons' inheriting lands and titles in England. Virginia evolved in a society of second or third sons of English aristocracy who inherited [[land grant]]s or land in Virginia. They formed part of the southern elite in America.

Many of the great Virginia dynasties traced their roots to families like the [[Lee family|Lees]] and the Fitzhughs, who traced lineage to England's county families and baronial legacies. But not all: even the most humble Virginia immigrants aspired to the English manorial trappings of their betters. Virginia history is not the sole province of English aristocrats. Such families as the Shackelfords, who gave their name to a Virginia hamlet, rose from modest beginnings in Hampshire to a place in the Virginia firmament based on hard work and smart marriages. At the same time, other once-great families were decimated not only by the [[English Civil War]], but also by the enormous power of the London merchants to whom they were in debt and who could move markets with the stroke of a pen.

The Colonial families of Maryland were the leading families in the [[Province of Maryland]]. Several also had interests in the [[Colony of Virginia]], and the two are sometimes referred to as the [[Chesapeake Colonies]]. Many of the early settlers came from the [[West Midlands (region)|West Midlands]] in England, although the Maryland families were composed of a variety of European nationalities, e.g., French, Irish, Welsh, Scottish, and Swedish, in addition to English.

The Carroll family is an example a prominent political family from Maryland, of Irish descent and origin in the ancient kingdom of Éile, commonly anglicized Ely, as a branch of the ruling O'Carroll family. Another is the Mason family of Virginia, who descended from the progenitor of the Mason family, [[George Mason I]], a [[Cavalier]] member of the [[Parliament of England]] born in Worcestershire, England.

[[Charles I of England]] granted the province [[County palatine|palatinate]] status under [[Cecilius Calvert, 2nd Baron Baltimore]]. The foundational charter created an aristocracy of [[lords of the manor]] for Maryland. Maryland was uniquely created as a colony for [[Catholic church|Catholic]] aristocracy and [[landed gentry]], but [[Anglicanism]] eventually came to dominate, partly through influence from neighboring Virginia.

==Church==
[[Image:Philo mediev.jpg|thumb|300px|right|Teaching at Paris, in a late 14th-century ''[[Grandes Chroniques de France]]'': the [[tonsure]]d students sit on the floor]]

[[Decline of the Roman Empire|Roman]]  authority in the West completely collapsed, and the western provinces soon became a patchwork of Germanic kingdoms. However, the city of Rome, under the guidance of the [[Catholic Church]], still remained a centre of learning and did much to preserve classic Roman thought in Western Europe.&lt;ref&gt;[[History of Europe#Decline of the Roman Empire|History of Europe]]&lt;/ref&gt;

The only universal European institution was the [[Catholic Church]], and even there, a fragmentation of authority was the rule; all the power within the [[church hierarchy]] was in the hands of the local bishops and finally the [[Primacy of the Roman Pontiff|Bishop of Rome]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.mnsu.edu/emuseum/history/middleages/church.html MNSU.edu]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://csis.pace.edu/grendel/projs2c/middle.html CSIS.pace.edu]&lt;/ref&gt; The clergy encompassed almost all of the time's educated men and was furthermore strengthen by considerable wealth, and thus, it came naturally to play a significant political role.

; Education

During the Early Middle Ages, the monasteries of the [[Roman Catholic Church|Catholic Church]] were the centres of education and literacy, preserving the Church's selection from Latin learning and maintaining the art of writing. Medieval universities had been run for centuries as [[Christianity|Christian]] [[bishop|episcopal]] or [[monastery|monastic]] schools (''scholae monasticae''), in which [[monk]]s and [[nun]]s taught classes; evidence of these immediate forerunners dates back to the 6th century AD.&lt;ref&gt;Riché, Pierre (1978): &quot;Education and Culture in the Barbarian West: From the Sixth through the Eighth Century&quot;, Columbia: University of South Carolina Press, ISBN 0-87249-376-8, pp. 126-7, 282-98&lt;/ref&gt;

With the increasing growth and urbanization of European society during the 12th and 13th centuries, a demand grew for professional [[clergy]]. Before the 12th century, the intellectual life of Western Europe had been largely relegated to [[monastery|monasteries]], which were mostly concerned with performing the [[liturgy]] and prayer; relatively few monasteries could boast true intellectuals.[[File:Rogier van der Weyden- Seven Sacraments Altarpiece - Baptism, Confirmation, and Penance; detail, left wing.JPG|thumb|300px|Detail from the ''[[Seven Sacraments Altarpiece]]'' - Baptism, Confirmation, Penance; detail, left wing (ca. 1445-1450) by [[Rogier van der Weyden]].]] Following the [[Gregorian Reform]]'s emphasis on canon law and the study of the [[sacrament]]s, bishops formed [[cathedral school]]s to train the clergy in [[Canon law (Catholic Church)|Canon law]], but also in the more secular aspects of religious administration, including logic and disputation for use in preaching and theological discussion, and accounting to control finances more effectively. Learning became essential to advancing in the ecclesiastical hierarchy, and teachers also gained prestige.

Modern systems of education in Europe derive their origins from the schools of the [[High Middle Ages]]. Most schools during this era were founded upon religious principles with the primary purpose of training the clergy. Many of the earliest universities, such as the [[University of Paris]] founded in 1160, had a [[Christianity|Christian]] basis. In addition to this, a number of [[secular]] universities existed, such as the [[University of Bologna]], founded in 1088. Free education for the poor was officially mandated by the Church at the [[Third Lateran Council]] (1179), which decreed that every cathedral must assign a master to teach boys too poor to pay the regular fee; parishes and monasteries also established free schools teaching at least basic literary skills. With few exceptions, priests and brothers taught locally, and their salaries were frequently subsidized by towns. Private, independent schools reappeared in medieval Europe during this time, but they, too, were religious in nature and mission.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;All schools are public&quot;, Jason Bofetti [http://www.frinstitute.org/allschools1.html FRinstitute.org]&lt;/ref&gt;

By the 13th century, almost half of the highest offices in the Church were occupied by degreed masters ([[abbot]]s, [[archbishop]]s, [[cardinal (Catholicism)|cardinals]]), and over one-third of the second-highest offices were occupied by masters. In addition, some of the greatest theologians of the [[High Middle Ages]], [[Thomas Aquinas]] and [[Robert Grosseteste]], were products of the medieval university.

; Social Rituals

Social rituals have formed a part of human [[culture]] for tens of thousands of years.  Anthropologists see social rituals as one of many [[cultural universals]].

The Christian clergy has traditionally officiated over of acts worship, reverence, rituals and ceremonies. The basic social function it has served as, has been the expressing, fixing and reinforcing of shared values and beliefs of a society. Among these central traditions have been  [[baptism]], [[Confirmation (Catholic Church)|Confirmation]], [[Sacrament of Penance (Catholic Church)|Penance]], [[Anointing of the Sick]], [[Holy Orders]], marriage, the [[Mass]] or the [[Divine Service (Lutheran)|Divine Service]], and [[coronation]]s.

&lt;center&gt;&lt;gallery perrow=&quot;6&quot;&gt;
File:Baptism Sainte-Chapelle MNMA Cl23717.jpg|Scene of baptism. [[Stained glass]], Paris, last quarter of the 12th century. From the [[Sainte-Chapelle]] of Paris.
File:LutheranClergy.JPG|This Lutheran [[pastor]] is confirming the youth of his congregation after instructing them in ''[[Luther's Small Catechism]]''.
File:Confirmation VanderWeyden.png|A bishop administering [[Confirmation]]. [[Rogier van der Weyden]], ''[[Sacraments of the Catholic Church|The Seven Sacraments]]'', 15th century.
File:Tridentine mass.jpg|Celebreation of the [[Mass (liturgy)|Mass]]
File:Dagmar es Alekszandr eskuvoje detail.jpg|Wedding of [[Maria Feodorovna (Dagmar of Denmark)]] and [[Alexander III of Russia]]
File:Extreme Unction Rogier Van der Weyden.jpg|&quot;Extreme Unction&quot;, part of ''The Seven Sacraments'' (1445)
File:1962 consecration of William Evan Sanders - Bishop of Tennessee.jpg|Consecration of William Evan Sanders as [[Episcopal Church (United States)|Episcopal]] Bishop Coadjutor of [[Tennessee]], [[St. Mary's Episcopal Cathedral in Memphis]] 
File:Sluby Jana Kazimierza.jpg|''[[Lwów Oath]]'' by [[Jan Matejko]]. The essence of a divine [[oath]] is an invocation of divine agency to be a guarantor of the oath taker's own honesty and integrity in the matter under question.
Image:Исповедь берн собор.jpg|A penitent confessing his sins in the former [[Latin rite|Latin rite Catholic]], now [[Ukrainian Greek Catholic Church|Ukrainian Byzantine Rite Greek-Catholic church]] of the Bernhardines in [[Lviv]], [[Ukraine]]
File:1 Sanok, Blessing of the holy water at San River.JPG|[[Orthodox Church|Eastern Orthodox]] priests performing the [[Holy water in Eastern Christianity|Great Blessing of Waters at Theophany]]. Sanok.
File:Richthofen funeral.jpg|Funeral of [[Manfred von Richthofen]], Bertangles Cemetery, France, 22 April 1918, Reverend George H. Marshall
File:Priestly ordination.jpg|At priestly [[ordination]], the Catholic [[bishop]] imposes hands upon the [[deacon]] for ordination to the [[priesthood]].
&lt;/gallery&gt;&lt;/center&gt;

; Coronation

In the past, concepts of royalty, coronation and deity were often inexorably linked.  In some ancient cultures, rulers were considered to be divine or partially divine: the [[Ancient Egypt|Egyptian]] [[Pharaoh]] was believed to be the son of [[Ra]], the sun god, while in Japan, the [[Emperor of Japan|Emperor]] was believed to be a descendant of [[Amaterasu]], the sun goddess.  [[Ancient Rome|Rome]] promulgated the practice of [[emperor worship]]; in [[Medieval Europe]], monarchs claimed to have a [[Divine Right of Kings|divine right]] to rule.

The European coronation ceremonies of the Middle Ages were essentially a combination of the Christian rite of [[anointing]] with additional elements.  In some European countries prior to the adoption of Christianity, the ruler upon his election was raised on a [[shield]] and, while standing upon it, was borne on the shoulders of several chief men of the nation (or tribe) in a procession around his assembled subjects. Following Europe's conversion to Christianity, crowning ceremonies became more and more ornate, depending on the country in question, and their Christian elements—especially anointing—became the paramount concern.&lt;ref name=&quot;britannica1&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.1911encyclopedia.org/Coronation|title=Coronation|year=1911|publisher=Encyclopædia Britannica|accessdate=2008-09-25}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;catholic2&quot;&gt;{{CathEncy|wstitle=Coronation|last=Thurston|first=Herbert}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The [[coronation]] of the '''[[Holy Roman Emperor]]''' refers to a ceremony in which the ruler of Europe's then-largest political entity received the [[Imperial Regalia]] at the hands of the [[Pope]], symbolizing the pope's alleged right to crown [[Christian]] sovereigns and the emperor's role as protector of the [[Roman Catholic Church]]. The [[Holy Roman Empire]] was last established in 962&amp;nbsp;AD under [[Otto the Great]], though Otto was not the first Western sovereign to have been crowned ''[[Imperator]]'' ''[[Augustus]]'' by the [[Pope]].  [[Charlemagne]] was crowned as Emperor by [[Pope Leo III]] on 25 December 800, but his dominions were divided between his heirs, with the eastern portions ultimately reunited under Otto I.

Anointing a king was equivalent to crowning him; in fact, in Israel, a crown was not required ({{bibleverse|1|Samuel|16:13|KJV}}; {{bibleverse|2|Samuel|2:4|KJV}}, etc.). Thus, [[David]] was anointed as king by the prophet [[Samuel (Bible)|Samuel]]:

Then Samuel took the horn of oil, and anointed him in the midst of his brethren: and the Spirit of the Lord came upon David from that day forward. So Samuel rose up, and went to Ramah.&amp;mdash;{{bibleverse|1|Samuel|16:13|KJV}}.

&lt;center&gt;&lt;gallery perrow=&quot;6&quot;&gt;
File:Pepin le Bref.jpg|Coronation of [[Pepin the Short]]
File:Karel Leo.jpg|The coronation of [[Charlemagne]] by [[Pope Leo III]]
File:Lvisrdce korunovace 1189.jpg|[[Richard I of England]] crowned king.
File:Ludvik6 korunovace.jpg|[[Louis VI of France]] was crowned on 3 August 1108 in the cathedral of [[Orléans]] by [[Daimbert, Archbishop of Sens]].
File:JanBrienne.jpg|Coronation of [[Maria of Montferrat]] and [[John of Brienne]], [[King of Jerusalem]] and [[Latin Emperor of Constantinople]]
File:Bela4 korunovace.jpg| The coronation of [[Béla IV]], [[King of Hungary]]
File:Coelestin V.jpg|Coronation of Pope [[Celestine V]]
File:Charles-vii-courronement- Panthéon III.jpg|The coronation of [[Charles VII of France]] in the [[Panthéon, Paris|Panthéon de Paris]]
File:Koronacja Jana Kazimierza.JPG|Coronation of [[John II Casimir Vasa]]
File:Preussen 1701 Königsberg.jpg|[[Frederick II of Prussia]] being anointed by two Protestant bishops after his coronation at [[Königsberg]] in 1701
File:SerovV MiropomazanNikolAlek.jpg|Anointing of Tsar [[Nicholas II of Russia]] during his coronation in 1896
File:The Anointing of Queen Alexandra at the Coronation of Edward VII.JPG|The anointing of [[Alexandra of Denmark|Queen Alexandr]]a at the coronation of [[Edward VII]]
&lt;/gallery&gt;&lt;/center&gt;

; Clergy - Priests and Pastors

The [[Catholic Church|Catholic]],  [[Eastern Orthodox Church|Eastern Orthodox]], [[Anglicanism|Anglican]] and the [[Church of Sweden]] (including former dominions of the [[Swedish Empire]]: [[History of Finland|Finland]], [[Swedish Estonia|Estonia]] and [[Swedish Livonia|Livonia]]) have applied the formal, church-based leadership or an [[Ordination|ordained]] clergy in matters of either the church or broader political and sociocultural import.

Until the reformation, the clergy was the first estate but was relegated to the secular estate in the Protestant [[Northern Europe]]. Clerical (pastor) Families is a concept in genealogy to characterize some families in the Swedish Church after the reformation, in which members of the family had served for generations in the Swedish Church either as active clergy in the Church, educational institutions or in the civil service.

After compulsory celibacy was abolished in Sweden during the Reformation, the formation of an hereditary priestly class became possible, whereby wealth and clerical positions were frequently inheritable. Hence the bishops and the vicars, who formed the clerical upper class, would frequently have manors similar to those of the nobility.

Historically, Sweden, including the former Swedish province of Finland, has had a more elaborate form of liturgy, which preserved more than other Nordic countries links to the Medieval Catholic tradition. In Germany, the high church movement is much smaller than in Sweden. Because of several unions between [[Lutheran]] and [[Reformed]] churches since the [[Prussian Union (Evangelical Christian Church)|Prussian Union]], resulting in the simple spread of Calvinist concepts from the Reformed Churches by &quot;osmosis&quot;, Lutheranism has often taken on a Reformed context.

&lt;center&gt;&lt;gallery perrow=&quot;6&quot;&gt;
File:Philippus Rovenius.jpg|[[Ecclesiastical Addresses|The Very Reverend]] [[Philippus Rovenius]], Dutch apostolic vicar
File:SirGeorgeFlemingBt2.jpg|[[Sir George Fleming, 2nd Baronet]], British churchman
File:The Seven Bishops Committed to the Tower in 1688 by John Smith.jpg|The [[Seven Bishops]] of the Church of England
File:Gedenkbild Erste Deutsche Bischofskonferenz Wuerzburg 1848.jpg|[[Prelate]]s at the [[German Bishops' Conference]] in Wuerzburg, 1848
File:Gilbert White.jpg|The Reverend [[Gilbert White]], [[Anglican]] priest and a pioneering [[naturalist]] and [[ornithologist]]
File:Hans Ridderstedt.jpg|The Reverend [[Hans G. Ridderstedt]] (1919-2007), Assistant Vicar at [[Stockholm Cathedral]]
&lt;/gallery&gt;&lt;/center&gt;

; Ecclestical residences

A '''rectory''' is the residence, or former residence, of a [[rector]], most often a [[Christian]] cleric, but in some cases, an academic rector or other person with that title. Many former rectories may still be referred to locally as a rectory once a church or religious organisation has vacated the property.

''Bishop's Palace'' refers to the official residence of any bishop. Often the most grand ecclestical palaces were built by [[Prince-Bishop]]s.

&lt;center&gt;&lt;gallery perrow=&quot;5&quot;&gt;
File:Old Vicarage at Kintbury - geograph.org.uk - 61755.jpg|Vicarage at Kintbury. The grand former vicarage adjacent to the [[Kennet and Avon Canal]]
File:Pfarrhaus Ilmenau.JPG|A rectory in [[Thuringia]], Germany
File:Knole, Sevenoaks in Kent - March 2009.jpg|[[Knole House]] built by [[Thomas Bourchier (bishop)|Thomas Bourchier]], [[Archbishop of Canterbury]], between 1456 and 1486
File:Rectory Liminka 2006 07 26.JPG|The rectory of [[Liminka]], [[Finland]]
File:Primate's Palace in Bratislava at 2009 summer.jpg|[[Primate's Palace]] in [[Bratislava]]
&lt;/gallery&gt;&lt;/center&gt;

== Values and traditions associated with the gentry ==
===Military and clerical tradition of the gentry ===
Historically, the nobles in Europe became soldiers. Actually, the aristocracy in Europe can trace their origins to military leaders from the migration period and the Middle Ages. For many years, the British Army, together with the Church, was seen as the ideal career for the younger sons of the aristocracy, those who would not inherit their fathers' titles or estates. Although now much diminished, the practice has not totally disappeared, the slang term ''Rupert'' being used to describe such blue-blooded, usually British public-school-educated, officers. Such practices are not unique to the British either geographically or historically.
As a very practical form of displaying patriotism, it has been at times &quot;fashionable&quot; for &quot;gentlemen&quot; to participate in the military, usually the militia, to fulfill societal expectations. It has been said that the title &quot;Colonel&quot; was the ultimate fashion accessory for a Southern gentleman.

=== Superiority of the fighting man ===
The fundamental idea of gentry, symbolised in this grant of coat-armour, had come to be that of the essential superiority of the fighting man; and, as Selden points out (page 707), the fiction was usually maintained in the granting of arms &quot;to an ennobled person though of the long Robe wherein he hath little use of them as they mean a shield.&quot;
At the last, the wearing of a sword on all occasions was the outward and visible sign of a &quot;gentleman&quot;; the custom survives in the sword worn with &quot;court dress&quot;.

A suggestion that a gentleman must have a coat of arms was vigorously advanced by certain 19th- and 20th-century heraldists, notably Arthur Charles Fox-Davies in England and Thomas Innes of Learney in Scotland, but the suggestion is discredited by an examination, in England, of the records of the High Court of Chivalry and, in Scotland, by a judgment of the Court of Session (per Lord Mackay in Maclean of Ardgour v. Maclean [1941] SC 613 at 650). The significance of a right to a coat of arms was that it was definitive proof of the status of gentleman, but it recognised rather than conferred such a status, and the status could be and frequently was accepted without a right to a coat of arms.

=== Chivalry ===
[[File:Meister der Manessischen Liederhandschrift 001.jpg|200px|right|thumb|A knight being armed.]]
{{Main|Chivalry}}

''Chivalry''&lt;ref&gt;Etymology: English from 1292, loans from [[French language|French]] ''chevalerie'' &quot;[[knighthood]]&quot;, from ''chevalier'' &quot;knight&quot; from [[Medieval Latin]] ''caballarius'' &quot;horseman&quot;; ''[[cavalry]]'' is from the [[Middle French]] form of the same word.&lt;/ref&gt; is a term related to the [[medieval]] institution of [[knighthood]]. It is usually associated with ideals of [[knightly virtues]], [[honour|honor]] and [[courtly love]]. The word is derived from the [[French language|French]] word ''chevalerie'', itself derived from ''chevalier'', which means &quot;knight&quot;, derived from ''cheval'', &quot;horse&quot; (indicating one who rides a horse).

Christianity had a modifying influence on the virtues of chivalry. The [[Peace and Truce of God]] in the 10th century was one such example, with limits placed on knights to protect and honor the weaker members of society and also help the church maintain peace. At the same time, the church became more tolerant of war in the defense of faith, espousing theories of the [[just war]], and [[liturgies]] were introduced which blessed a knight's sword, and a bath of chivalric purification. In the 11th century, the concept of a &quot;knight of Christ&quot; (''miles Christi'') gained currency in France, Spain and Italy.&lt;ref name=sweeney&gt;[[James Ross Sweeney]] (1983). &quot;Chivalry&quot;, in ''[[The Dictionary of the Middle Ages]]'', Volume III.&lt;/ref&gt;  These concepts of &quot;religious chivalry&quot; were further elaborated in the era of the [[Crusades]], with the Crusades themselves often being seen as chivalrous enterprises.&lt;ref name=sweeney/&gt; Their ideas of chivalry were also further influenced by [[Saladin]], who was viewed as a chivalrous knight by medieval Christian writers.

The relationship between knights and the nobility varied based on region. In France, being dubbed a knight also bestowed noble status. In Germany and the Low Countries, knights and the nobility were distinctly different classes. In England, the relations between knights, nobles and land-owning landed gentry were complex.

In the later Middle Ages, wealthy merchants strove to adopt chivalric attitudes - the sons of the bourgeoisie were educated at aristocratic courts, where they were trained in the manners of the knightly class.&lt;ref name=sweeney/&gt; This was a democratization of chivalry, leading to a new genre called the [[courtesy book]], which were guides to the behavior of &quot;gentlemen&quot;. Thus, the post-medieval gentlemanly code of the value of a man's honor, respect for women, and a concern for those less fortunate, is directly derived from earlier ideals of chivalry and historical forces which created it.&lt;ref name=sweeney/&gt;

When examining [[medieval literature]], chivalry can be classified into three basic but overlapping areas:
# Duties to countrymen and fellow Christians: this contains virtues such as mercy, courage, valor, fairness, protection of the weak and the poor, and in the servant-hood of the knight to his lord. This also brings with it the idea of being willing to give one's life for another's; whether he would be giving his life for a poor man or his lord.
# Duties to God: this would contain being faithful to God, protecting the innocent, being faithful to the church, being the champion of good against evil, being generous and obeying God above the feudal lord.
# Duties to women: this is probably the most familiar aspect of chivalry. This would contain what is often called [[courtly love]], the idea that the knight is to serve a lady, and after her all other ladies. Most especially in this category is a general gentleness and graciousness to all women.
These three areas obviously overlap quite frequently in chivalry and are often indistinguishable.

Different weight given to different areas produced different strands of chivalry:
#warrior chivalry, in which a knight's chief duty is to his lord, as exemplified by Sir [[Gawain]] in ''[[Sir Gawain and the Green Knight]]'' and ''[[The Wedding of Sir Gawain and Dame Ragnelle]]''
#religious chivalry, in which a knight's chief duty is to protect the innocent and serve God, as exemplified by Sir [[Galahad]] or Sir [[Percival]] in the [[Holy Grail|Grail legends]]
#courtly love chivalry, in which a knight's chief duty is to his own lady, and after her, all ladies, as exemplified by Sir [[Lancelot]] in his love for Queen [[Guinevere]] or Sir [[Tristan]] in his love for [[Iseult]]

One particular similarity between all three of these categories is honor. Honor is the foundational and guiding principle of chivalry. Thus, for the knight, honor would be one of the guides of action.

=== Gentleman ===
[[File:English Gentleman.jpg|180px|right|thumb|A page from Brathwait's book that displays the qualities associated with being a gentleman]]
{{Main|Gentleman}}

The term '''gentleman''' (from [[Latin]] ''gentilis'', belonging to a race or ''gens'', and  &quot;man&quot;, [[cognate]] with the [[French language|French]] word ''gentilhomme'', the Spanish ''hombre gentil'' and the [[Italian language|Italian]] ''gentil uomo'' or ''gentiluomo''), in its original and strict signification, denoted a man of good family, analogous to the Latin ''generosus'' (its invariable translation in English-Latin documents). In this sense the word equates with the French ''gentilhomme'' (&quot;nobleman&quot;), which was in Great Britain long confined to the [[peerage]]. The term ''gentry'' (from the Old French ''genterise'' for ''gentelise'') has much of the social-class significance of the French ''noblesse'' or of the [[German language|German]] ''Adel'', but without the strict technical requirements of those traditions (such as [[quarters of nobility]]). This was what the rebels under [[John Ball (priest)|John Ball]] in the 14th century meant when they repeated:

{{quote|When [[Adam and Eve|Adam]] delft and [[Adam and Eve|Eve]] span,&lt;br /&gt;Who was then the Gentleman?&lt;sup&gt;[[John Ball (priest)#Footnotes|[1]]]&lt;/sup&gt;}}

To a degree, ''gentleman'' signified a man with an income derived from property, a legacy or some other source and was thus independently wealthy and did not need to work.

'''Confucianism'''

The [[East Asia|Far East]] also held similar ideas to the West of what a gentleman is, which are based on [[Confucianism|Confucian]] principles. The term ''[[Junzi|Jūnzǐ]]'' (君子) is a term crucial to classical Confucianism. Literally meaning &quot;son of a ruler&quot;, &quot;prince&quot; or &quot;noble&quot;, the ideal of a &quot;gentleman&quot;, &quot;proper man&quot;, &quot;exemplary person&quot;, or &quot;perfect man&quot; is that for which Confucianism exhorts all people to strive. A succinct description of the &quot;perfect man&quot; is one who &quot;combine[s] the qualities of saint, scholar, and gentleman&quot; ([[Catholic Encyclopedia|CE]]). (In modern times, the masculine bias in Confucianism may have weakened, but the same term is still used; the masculine translation in English is also traditional and still frequently used.) A hereditary elitism was bound up with the concept, and gentlemen were expected to act as moral guides to the rest of society. They were to:
* cultivate themselves morally;
* participate in the correct performance of ritual;
* show filial piety and loyalty where these are due; and
* cultivate humaneness.

The opposite of the ''Jūnzǐ'' was the ''Xiǎorén'' (小人), literally &quot;small person&quot; or &quot;petty person&quot;. Like English &quot;small&quot;, the word in this context in Chinese can mean petty in mind and heart, narrowly self-interested, greedy, superficial, and materialistic.

=== Noblesse oblige ===
The idea of ''[[Noblesse oblige]]'', &quot;nobility obliges&quot;, among gentry is, as the ''[[Oxford English Dictionary]]'' expresses, that the term &quot;suggests noble ancestry constrains to honourable behavior; privilege entails to responsibility&quot;. Being a noble meant that one had responsibilities to lead, manage and so on. One was not to simply spend one's time in idle pursuits.

'''General [[Robert E. Lee]]'s definition speaks only to conduct.'''
:The forbearing use of power does not only form a touchstone, but the manner in which an individual enjoys certain advantages over others is a test of a true gentleman.

:The power which the strong have over the weak, the employer over the employed, the educated over the unlettered, the experienced over the confiding, even the clever over the silly — the forbearing or inoffensive use of all this power or authority, or a total abstinence from it when the case admits it, will show the gentleman in a plain light.

:The gentleman does not needlessly and unnecessarily remind an offender of a wrong he may have committed against him. He can not only forgive, he can forget; and he strives for that nobleness of self and mildness of character which impart sufficient strength to let the past be but the past. A true man of honor feels humbled himself when he cannot help humbling others.&lt;ref&gt;[http://xroads.virginia.edu/~CAP/LEE/gentdef.html &quot;Definition of a Gentleman&quot;], a memorandum found in Lee's papers after his death, as quoted in ''Lee the American'' (1912) by Gamaliel Bradford, p. 233&lt;/ref&gt;

== Heraldry ==
'''Coat of arms'''
{{Main|Coat of arms}}

A coat of arms is a heraldic device dating to the 12th century in Europe. It was originally a cloth tunic worn over or in place of armour to establish identity in battle.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.britannica.com/EBchecked/topic/35518/coat-of-arms Britannica Online Encyclopedia]&lt;/ref&gt; The coat of arms is drawn with heraldic rules for a person, family or organization. Family coats of arms where originally derived from personal ones, which then became extended in time to the whole family. In Scotland, family coats of arms are still personal ones and are mainly used by the head of the family.
&lt;center&gt;&lt;gallery perrow=&quot;4&quot;&gt;
File:Hyghalmen Roll Late 1400s.jpg|The German [[Hyghalmen Roll]] from the late fifteenth century
File:Robert Glover Pedigree de Euro.jpg|Pedigree of the De Euro family, of [[Northumberland]], barons of [[Duke of Northumberland|Warkworth]] and Clavering, by [[Robert Glover (officer of arms)|Robert Glover]]
File:Brockhaus and Efron Encyclopedic Dictionary b15 462-1.jpg|Illustration from ''[[Brockhaus and Efron Encyclopedic Dictionary]]'' (1890—1907)
File:Brockhaus and Efron Encyclopedic Dictionary 243.jpg|''Brockhaus and Efron Encyclopedic Dictionary'' (1890—1907)
 &lt;/gallery&gt;&lt;/center&gt;

=== Ecclesiastical heraldry ===
{{Main|Ecclesiastical heraldry}}

Ecclesiastical heraldry is the tradition of [[heraldry]] developed by [[Christianity|Christian]] [[clergy]]. Initially used to mark documents, [[ecclesiology|ecclesiastical]] heraldry evolved as a system for identifying people and [[diocese]]s. It is most formalized within the [[Catholic Church]], where most [[bishop]]s, including the [[pope]], have a personal [[coat of arms]]. Clergy in [[Anglicanism|Anglican]], [[Lutheranism|Lutheran]], [[Eastern Catholic Churches|Eastern Catholic]], and [[Eastern Christianity|Orthodox churches]] follow similar customs.

&lt;center&gt;&lt;gallery perrow=&quot;6&quot;&gt;
File:Franz von Sales Bischofswappen.jpg|Coat of arms of [[Francis de Sales]], [[Diocese of Lausanne, Geneva and Fribourg#Geneva|Bishop of Geneva]], displayed on an oval shield with both mitre and galero above, and motto below
File:Slipyj herb.jpg|Arms of Cardinal [[Josyf Slipyj]], [[major archbishop]] of the [[Ukrainian Greek Catholic Church]], with [[mantling]]
File:Luth-Uppsala-Arms.png|[[Archbishop of Uppsala|Archbishop of Uppsala's]] coat of arms
File:TeutonicCoA PioM.svg|Coat of arms of the [[Teutonic Knights|Order of the Teutonic Knights of St. Mary's Hospital in Jerusalem]]
File:COAanglicanmarried.gif|Arms of an Anglican bishop marshalled with those of the diocese (left shield) and spouse (right shield)
File:Franz Christoph von Hutten Wappen.jpg|[[:de:Franz Christoph von Hutten|Franz Christoph von Hutten's]] coat of arms from the 18th century with mitre, staff, and sword
&lt;/gallery&gt;&lt;/center&gt;

===East Asia===
====Four occupations (East Asia)====
{{Main|Four occupations (East Asia)}}

The '''four divisions of society''' refers to the [[Four occupations (China)|model of society in ancient China]] and was a [[meritocratic]] [[social class]] system in China and other subsequently influenced [[Confucian]] societies. The four castes—gentry, farmers, artisans and merchants—are combined to form the term '''Shìnónggōngshāng''' (士農工商).

'''Gentry'''
(士) This means different things in different countries.

In China, Korea, and Vietnam, this meant that the Confucian scholar gentry that would - for the most part - make up most of the bureaucracy. This caste would comprise both the more-or-less hereditary aristocracy as well as the meritocratic scholars that rise through the rank by public service and, later, by imperial exams.

In Japan, this caste essentially equates to the [[samurai]] class. In the [[Edo period]], with the creation of the [[Han (country subdivision)|Domains (''han'')]] under the rule of [[Toyotomi Hideyoshi]], all land was confiscated and reissued as fiefdoms to the [[daimyo]]. The small lords, the {{nihongo|samurai|武士|bushi|}}, were ordered either to give up their swords and rights and remain on their lands as peasants or to move to the castle cities to become paid retainers of the daimyo. Only a few samurai were allowed to remain in the countryside; the {{Nihongo|landed samurai|郷士|gōshi}}. Some 5% of the population were samurai. Only the samurai could have proper surnames, which after the [[Meiji Restoration]], became compulsory to all inhabitants (see [[Japanese name]]).

'''Farmers'''

(農) In a largely agrarian society, the farmers occupy a high position in Chinese, Japanese, Korean, and Vietnamese society, at least in theory. Some sources, such as [[Xunzi]], list them before the gentry, based on the [[Confucian]] view that they directly contributed to the welfare of the state. In China, the farmer lifestyle is also closely linked with the ideals of Confucian gentlemen, and aging scholars and bureaucrats often retire to a life of farming—again, at least in theory.

====Hierarchical structure of Feudal Japan====
[[File:Social stratification in feudal Japan (12th - 19th century).gif|thumb|left|200px|Social stratification in feudal Japan (12th - 19th century)]]
{{Main|Hierarchical structure of Feudal Japan}}
[[File:Matsue daimyo c1850s.jpg|thumb|right|200px|Matsue daimyo (c. 1850s)]][[File:Group of 4 samurai.jpg|thumb|right|200px|Group of four samurai]]
There were two leading classes, i.e. the gentry, in the time of '''Feudal Japan''': the Daimyo and the Samurai. The Confucian ideals in the Japanese culture emphasized the importance of productive members of society, so farmers and fishermen were considered of a higher status then merchants.

'''Daimyo'''
{{Main|Daimyo}}

{{nihongo| Daimyo |大名|Daimyō|{{Audio|ja-daimyo.ogg|Pronunciation}}}}  is a generic term referring to the powerful territorial lords&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=FiHJX2FRg6sC&amp;pg=PA291&amp;dq=%22territorial+lord%22#v=onepage&amp;q=%22territorial%20lord%22&amp;f=false|page=291|title=An Introduction to the History of Japan |first= Hara |last=Katsuro |publisher= BiblioBazaar, LLC|year= 2009 |isbn= 1110787855}}&lt;/ref&gt; in premodern Japan who ruled most of the country from their vast, hereditary land holdings. In the term, {{nihongo|''dai''|大}} literally means &quot;large&quot;, and ''myō'' stands for {{nihongo3||名田|myōden}}, meaning private land.&lt;ref&gt;Kodansha Encyclopedia of Japan, entry for &quot;daimyō&quot;&lt;/ref&gt;

They were the most powerful [[feudalism|feudal]] rulers from the 10th century to the early 19th century in [[History of Japan|Japan]] following the [[Shogun]].

From the ''[[shugo]]'' of the [[Muromachi period]] through the ''[[Sengoku period|Sengoku]]'' to the daimyo of the [[Edo period]], the rank had a long and varied history.

The term ''daimyo'' is also sometimes used to refer to the leading figures of such clans, also called &quot;[[lord]]&quot;. It was usually, though not exclusively, from these warlords that a [[shogun]] arose or a [[regent]] was chosen.

'''After the Meiji Restoration'''

In 1869, the year after the [[Meiji Restoration]], the daimyo, together with the ''[[kuge]]'', formed a new aristocracy, the ''[[kazoku]]''. In 1871, the [[Abolition of the han system|han were abolished]], and [[Prefectures of Japan|prefectures]] were established, thus effectively ending the daimyo era in Japan. In the wake of this change, many daimyo remained in control of their lands, being appointed as prefectural governors; however, they were soon relieved of this duty and called en masse to Tokyo, thereby cutting off any independent base of power from which to potentially rebel. Despite this, members of former daimyo families remained prominent in government and society and, in some cases, continue to remain prominent to the present day. (For example, [[Morihiro Hosokawa]], the former prime minister, is a descendant of the daimyo of [[Kumamoto]], but these cases are very few now.)

'''Samurai'''
{{Main|Samurai}}
{{Nihongo|Samurai|[[wikt:侍|侍]]&lt;!--&quot;武士&quot; is pronounced &quot;Bushi&quot; or, occasionally, &quot;mononofu&quot;--&gt;}} is the term for the military nobility of [[Pre-industrial society|pre-industrial]] Japan. According to translator [[William Scott Wilson]]: &quot;In Chinese, the character 侍 was originally a verb meaning to wait upon or accompany a person in the upper ranks of society, and this is also true of the original term in Japanese, [[wiktionary:侍う#Etymology 2|saburau]]. In both countries the terms were nominalized to mean 'those who serve in close attendance to the nobility', the pronunciation in Japanese changing to [[wiktionary:侍#Etymology 1|saburai]].&quot; According to Wilson, an early reference to the word ''samurai'' appears in the ''[[Kokin Wakashū]]'' (905-914), the first imperial anthology of poems, completed in the first part of the 9th century.

By the end of the 12th century, ''samurai'' became almost entirely synonymous with ''bushi'' (武士), and the word was closely associated with the middle and upper echelons of the warrior class. The samurai followed a set of written rules called the [[Bushidō]]. They numbered less than 10% of Japan's population.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;[http://www.britannica.com/EBchecked/topic/520850/samurai Samurai (Japanese warrior)]&quot;. Encyclopædia Britannica.&lt;/ref&gt; Samurai teachings can still be found today in modern-day society with the martial art [[Kendō]], meaning &quot;the way of the sword&quot;.

As ''de facto'' aristocrats for centuries, samurai developed their own cultures that influenced Japanese culture as a whole. The culture associated with the samurai such as the tea ceremony, monochrome ink painting, rock gardens and poetry were adopted by warrior patrons throughout the years 1200-1600. These practices were adapted from the Chinese arts. Zen monks introduced them to Japan, and they were allowed to flourish due to the interest of powerful warrior elites. Muso Soseki (1275–1351) was a Zen monk who was advisor to both Emperor Go-Daigo and General Ashikaga Takauji (1304–58). Muso as well as other monks acted as political and cultural diplomats between Japan and China. Muso was particularly well known for his garden design. Another Ashikaga patron of the arts was Yoshimasa. His cultural advisor, the Zen monk Zeami, introduced tea ceremony to him. Previously, tea had been used primarily for Buddhist monks to stay awake during meditation.&lt;ref&gt;Mason, RHP and JG Caiger &quot;A History of Japan&quot; 1997&lt;/ref&gt;

In general, samurai, aristocrats, and priests had a very high literacy rate in Kanji.
&quot;The Nobles send their sons to monasteries to be educated as soon as they are 8 years old, and they remain there until they are 19 or 20, learning reading, writing and religion; as soon as they come out, they marry and apply themselves to politics.&quot;

[[Emperor Meiji]] abolished the samurai's right to be the only armed force in favor of a more modern, Western-style, conscripted army in 1873. Samurai became ''Shizoku'' ({{lang|ja|士族}}), who retained some of their salaries, but the right to wear a katana in public was eventually abolished along with the right to [[execution|execute]] commoners who paid them disrespect.

In defining how a modern Japan should be, members of the Meiji government decided to follow in the footsteps of the United Kingdom and Germany, basing the country on the concept of ''[[noblesse oblige]]''. Samurai were not to be a political force under the new order.

The difference between the Japanese and European feudal systems was that European feudalism was grounded in [[Roman law|Roman legal structure]], while Japan feudalism had Chinese [[Confucianism|Confucian morality]] as its basis.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.psych.ualberta.ca/~msnyder/Academic/japvseur.html Snyder, M.R. (October 1994) Japanese vs. European Feudalism. Guest lecturer at Alberta Vocational College]&lt;/ref&gt;

{{nihongo|'''Bushidō'''|[[wiktionary:武士道|武士道]]}}, meaning &quot;Way of the Warrior&quot;, is a name in common usage since the late 19th century which is used to describe a uniquely [[Japan]]ese [[code of conduct]] adhered to by [[samurai]] since time immemorial. This code is said to have emphasized virtues such as [[loyalty]], honor, obedience, duty, [[filial piety]], and self-sacrifice.

The ''[[Kojiki]]'' is Japan's oldest extant book. Written in 712, it contains passages about legendary prince [[Yamato Takeru]] and provides an early indication of the values and literary self-image of the Bushidō ideal.

''Seven virtues of Bushidō'' 
{{main|Virtue}}

The Bushidō code is typified by seven virtues:
*{{Nihongo|[[wiktionary:rectitude|Rectitude]]|[[wiktionary:義|義]]|gi}}
*{{Nihongo|[[wiktionary:courage|Courage]]|[[wiktionary:勇|勇]]|yū}}
*{{Nihongo|[[wiktionary:benevolence|Benevolence]]|[[wiktionary:仁|仁]]|jin}}
*{{Nihongo|[[wiktionary:respect|Respect]]|[[wiktionary:礼|礼]]|rei}}
*{{Nihongo|[[wiktionary:honesty|Honesty]]|[[wiktionary:誠|誠]]|makoto}}
*{{Nihongo|[[wiktionary:honor|Honor]]|[[wiktionary:名誉|名誉]]|meiyo}}
*{{Nihongo|[[wiktionary:loyalty|Loyalty]]|[[wiktionary:忠義|忠義]]|chūgi}}

''Associated virtues''
*{{Nihongo|[[Filial piety]]|[[wiktionary:孝|孝]]|kō}}
*{{Nihongo|[[Wisdom]]|[[wiktionary:智|智]]|chi}}
*{{Nihongo|[[Care for the aged]]|[[wiktionary:悌|悌]]|tei}}

'''Kazoku (Meiji Restoration)'''

The {{nihongo| Kazoku |華族||lit. &quot;exalted families&quot;}} was the hereditary [[peerage]] of the [[Empire of Japan]] that existed between 1869 and 1947.

Under the Peerage Act of 7 July 1884, pushed through by [[Itō Hirobumi]] after visiting Europe, the Meiji government expanded the hereditary peerage with the award of ''kazoku'' status to persons regarded as having performed outstanding services to the nation. The government also divided the ''kazoku'' into five ranks explicitly based on the [[British peerage]], but with titles deriving from the ancient [[Chinese nobility]]:

# {{nihongo|[[Prince]] or [[Duke]]|公爵|kōshaku}}
# {{nihongo|[[Marquess]]|侯爵|kōshaku}}
# {{nihongo|[[Earl]] or [[Count]]|伯爵|hakushaku}}
# {{nihongo|[[Viscount]]|子爵|shishaku}}
# {{nihongo|[[Baron]]|男爵|danshaku}}

&lt;center&gt;&lt;gallery perrow=&quot;4&quot;&gt;
File:Ehon-Shahobukuro Kamakura Gongoro.jpg|Samurai [[Kamakura Gongorō Kagemasa]]
File:Fujiwara no Teika.jpg|[[Fujiwara no Teika]] was a Japanese poet, calligrapher, and novelist.
File:Hyakuninisshu 087.jpg|[[Jakuren|Fujiwara no Sadanaga]], Japanese Buddhist priest and poet
File:Minamoto no Yoritomo.jpg|[[Minamoto no Yoritomo]], founder and the first shogun of the Kamakura Shogunate of Japan
File:Baba Nobufusa.jpg|Samurai [[Baba Nobuharu]]
File:Ikoma Chikamasa.jpg|Daimyo [[Ikoma Chikamasa]]
File:MakinoTadayuki.jpg|Daimyo [[Makino Tadayuki]] 
File:AraiIkunosuke.jpg|Samurai [[Arai Ikunosuke]], Navy Minister of the [[Republic of Ezo]]
&lt;/gallery&gt;&lt;/center&gt;

====Korea====
{{Main|Korean nobility|Yangban|korean ruling class}}

'''Korean monarchy and native nobility''' existed in [[Korea]] until the end of the [[Korea under Japanese rule|Japanese occupation]]. (In Imperial Japan, Korean nobles continued to hold noble titles.) The system is roughly the same as that of the [[Chinese nobility]]. It included ''che'', ''wang'' and ''kun''.

As the [[Jesuits]] and other monastical orders did during Europe's [[Dark Ages (historiography)|Dark Ages]], the Buddhist monks became the purveyors and guardians of Korea's literary traditions while documenting Korea's written history and legacies from the [[Silla]] period to the end of the [[Goryeo]] dynasty. Korean Buddhist monks also developed and used the first movable metal type printing presses in history—some 500 years before [[Johannes Gutenberg|Gutenberg]]—to print ancient Buddhist texts. Buddhist monks also engaged in record keeping, food storage and distribution, as well as the ability to exercise power by influencing the Goryeo royal court.

=== Gentry noun ===
&quot;Posing as a member of the gentry upper classes, privileged classes, elite, high society, haut monde, smart set; establishment, aristocracy; informal upper crust, top drawer.&quot; (''The New Oxford American Dictionary'' (NOAD), Second Edition)

==See also==
{{Col-begin}}
{{Col-1-of-3}}
* [[Aristocracy (class)]]
* [[Estates of the realm]]
* [[Feudalism]]
* [[Gentleman farmer]]
* [[Gentlewoman]]
* [[Hochwohlgeboren]]
* [[Junzi]]
* [[Landed gentry]]
* [[Landed property]]
* [[Manorialism]]

{{Col-2-of-3}}
* [[Patrician (ancient Rome)]]
* [[Patrician (post-Roman Europe)]]
* [[Old Money]]
* [[Peerage]]
** [[Burke's Landed Gentry]]
** [[Burke's Peerage]]
** [[Debrett's Peerage]]
* [[Polish landed gentry]]
* [[Magnate]]
* [[Szlachta]]
{{Col-3-of-3}}

* ''[[Redorer son blason]]''
* [[Ecclesiastical Addresses]]
* [[Forms of address in the United Kingdom]]
* [[Royal and noble ranks]]
* [[Royal and noble styles]]
* [[Style (manner of address)]]
* [[Social environment]]
* [[Status–income disequilibrium]]
* [[Honour]]
* [[Symbolic capital]]

{{col-end}}

== Notes ==
&lt;references/&gt;

== References ==
* John Burke family ''et al.'', ''Burke's Landed Gentry'' (genealogy book). United Kingdom (1826, 1898).
* [[Peter Coss]], ''The Origins of the English Gentry''. Past and Present Publications. Cambridge, Cambridge University Press (2003). ISBN 0-521-82673-X

{{Socialclass}}

[[Category:Social classes]]

[[cs:Džentry]]
[[de:Gentry]]
[[es:Gentry]]
[[fr:Gentry]]
[[ko:젠트리]]
[[it:Gentry (classe sociale)]]
[[hu:Dzsentri]]
[[nl:Landadel]]
[[ja:ジェントリ]]
[[pl:Gentry]]
[[pt:Nobreza rural]]
[[ru:Джентри]]
[[simple:Gentry]]
[[sh:Džentrija]]
[[uk:Джентрі]]
[[zh:绅士]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
