<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="212818" ns="0" title="Eating"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Redirect|Eat|other uses of &quot;eat&quot;, or &quot;EAT&quot; as an abbreviation or acronym|EAT (disambiguation)}}
{{redirect|Feeding}}
{{Meals}}
[[Image:20051129-MelbMeetup-Dining.JPG|thumb|right|250px|In human societies, eating is often a social occasion.]]
[[Image:Lunch Iraq.jpg|thumb|right|250px|Marines having lunch with Iraqi soldiers during Operation Iraqi Freedom.]]
'''Eating''' is the [[ingestion]] of [[food]] to provide for all [[organism]]s their [[nutrition]]al needs, particularly for [[food energy|energy]] and [[growth]]. Animals and other [[heterotroph]]s must eat in order to survive: [[carnivore]]s eat other animals, [[herbivore]]s eat plants, [[omnivore]]s consume a mixture of both plant and animal matter, and [[detritivores]] eat [[detritus]]. Fungi digest organic matter outside of their bodies as opposed to animals that digest their food inside their bodies. For humans, eating is an [[Activities of daily living|activity of daily living]].
==Eating practices among humans==
Many homes have a kitchen room or outside (in the tropics) kitchen area devoted to preparation of meals and food, and may have a [[dining room]], [[dining hall]], or another designated area for eating. Some trains have a [[dining car]]. Dishware, silverware, [[drinkware]], and [[cookware]] come in a wide array of forms and sizes. Most societies also have [[restaurant]]s, [[food court]]s, and/or [[street food|food vendors]], so that people may eat when away from home, when lacking time to prepare food, or as a social occasion ([[dining club]]).&lt;ref&gt;John Raulston Saul (1995), &quot;The Doubter's Companion&quot;, 155&lt;/ref&gt; At their highest level of sophistication, these places become &quot;theatrical spectacles of global [[cosmopolitanism]] and [[myth]].&quot;&lt;ref&gt;David Grazian (2008), &quot;On the Make: The Hustle of Urban Nightlife&quot;, 32&lt;/ref&gt; At [[picnic]]s, [[potluck]]s, and [[food festival]]s, eating is in fact the primary purpose of a social gathering. At many social events, food and beverages are made available to attendees.

People usually have two or three meals a day regularly. Snacks of smaller amounts may be consumed between meals. Some propose not snacking, yet advocate three meals a day (of 600 kcal per meal) with four to six hours between.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.bcminfo.be Eating recommendations by BCM]&lt;/ref&gt; Having three well-balanced meals (thus 1/2 of the plate with vegetables,&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.hsph.harvard.edu/nutritionsource/what-should-you-eat/vegetables-and-fruits/ Half of plate to be filled with vegetables, according to Harvard School of Public Health]&lt;/ref&gt; 1/4 protein food as meat, ... and 1/4 carbohydrates as pasta, rice, ...) will then account to some 1800–2000 kcal; which is the average requirement for a regular person.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.iloveindia.com/nutrition/food-facts/calorie-requirement-of-body.html Calorie requirements for regular person estimated at 2000 kcal]&lt;/ref&gt;

The issue of [[healthy eating]] has long been an important concern to individuals and cultures. Among other practices, [[fasting]], [[dieting]], and [[vegetarianism]] are all techniques employed by individuals and encouraged by societies to increase longevity and health.{{Citation needed|date=January 2009}} Some religions promote vegetarianism, considering it wrong to consume animals. Leading nutritionists believe that instead of indulging oneself in three large meals each day, it is much healthier and easier on the metabolism to eat five smaller meals each day (e.g. better digestion, easier on the lower intestine to deposit wastes; whereas larger meals are tougher on the digestive tract and may call for the use of [[laxatives]]){{Citation needed|date=January 2008}}. However, psychiatrists with Yale Medical School have found that people who suffer from Binge Eating Disorder (BED) and consume three meals per day weigh less than those who have meals that are more frequent. Eating can also be a way of making money (see [[competitive eating]]).

===Eating positions===
{{expand section|Additional information regarding Far East, Europe and America|date=September 2011}}
Eating positions vary according to the different regions of the world where many cultures influence the way people eat their meals.
In most of the Middle Eastern countries eating while sitting on the floor is considered the most common way to eat and it's believed to be healthier than eating while sitting to a table.{{Citation needed|date=April 2011}}

===Emotional eating===
[[Emotional eating]] is “the tendency to eat in response to negative emotions”.&lt;ref&gt;Eldredge, K. L., &amp; Agras, W. S. (1994). Weight and Shape Overconcern and Emotional Eating in Binge Eating Disorder. ''International Journal of Eating Disorders, 19'' (1), 73-82.&lt;/ref&gt; Empirical studies have indicated that anxiety leads to decreased food consumption in people with normal weight and increased food consumption in the obese.&lt;ref&gt;McKenna, R. J. (1972). Some Effects of Anxiety Level and Food Cues on the Eating Behavior of Obese and Normal Subjects: A Comparison of Schachterian and Psychosomatic Conceptions. ''Journal of Personality and Social Psychology, 22'' (3), 311-319.&lt;/ref&gt;

Many laboratory studies showed that overweight individuals are more emotionally reactive and are more likely to overeat when distressed than people of normal weight. Furthermore, it was consistently found that obese individuals experience negative emotions more frequently and more intensively than do normal weight persons.&lt;ref name=&quot;Lowe&quot;&gt;Lowe, M. R., &amp; Fisher, E. B. Jr. (1983). Emotional Reactivity, Emotional Eating, and Obesity: A Naturalistic Study. ''Journal of Behavioral Medicine, 6'' (2), 135-149.&lt;/ref&gt;

The naturalistic study of Lowe and Fisher compared the emotional reactivity and emotional eating of normal and overweight female college students. The study confirmed the tendency of obese individuals to overeat, but these findings applied only to snacks, not to meals. That means that obese individuals did not tend to eat more while having meals – rather, the amount of snacks they ate between meals was greater. One possible explanation that Lowe and Fisher suggest is that obese individuals often eat their meals with others and do not eat more than average due to the reduction of distress because of the presence of other people. Another possible explanation would be that obese individuals do not eat more than the others while having meals due to social desirability. Conversely, snacks are usually eaten alone.&lt;ref name=&quot;Lowe&quot;/&gt;

===Satiety and human metabolism===
{{See|Hunger#Biological mechanisms}}
The control of food intake is a physiologically complex, motivated behavioral system. Hormones such as [[cholecystokinin]], [[bombesin]], [[neurotensin]], [[anorectic|anorectin]], [[calcitonin]], [[enterostatin]], [[leptin]] and [[corticotropin-releasing hormone]] have all been shown to suppress food intake.&lt;ref&gt;Geiselman, P.J. (1996). Control of food intake. A physiologically complex, motivated behavioral system. Endocrinol Metab Clin North Am. 1996 Dec;25(4):815-29.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/entrez/dispomim.cgi?id=164160&amp;rn=1&lt;/ref&gt;

==Disorders==
{{main|Eating disorder}}

Physiologically, eating is generally triggered by [[hunger]], but there are numerous physical and psychological conditions that can affect [[appetite]] and disrupt normal eating patterns. These include [[clinical depression|depression]], food [[allergy|allergies]], ingestion of certain chemicals, [[bulimia]], [[anorexia nervosa]], [[pituitary gland]] malfunction and other [[endocrine]] problems, and numerous other [[illness]]es and [[eating disorder]]s.

A chronic lack of [[nutrition|nutritious]] food can cause various illnesses, and will eventually lead to [[starvation]]. When this happens in a locality on a massive scale, it is considered a [[famine]].

If eating and [[drinking]] is not possible, as is often the case when recovering from [[surgery]], alternatives are [[Route of administration#Enteral|enteral]] nutrition and [[parenteral nutrition]].{{Citation needed|date=April 2011}}

==See also==
{{Wiktionary}}
* [[Aphagia]]
* [[Chewing]]
* [[Competitive eating]]
* [[Crop]]
* [[Dietary supplement]]
* [[Dieting]]
* [[Dining in]], formal military ceremony
* [[Energy crop]]
* [[Forced feeding]]
* [[Swallowing]]

==References==
{{reflist}}

==External Links==
{{wikiquote}}
* [http://ec.europa.eu/health-eu/my_lifestyle/nutrition/index_en.htm Health-EU Portal - Nutrition]

{{Activities of daily living}}
[[Category:Physiology]]
[[Category:Food and drink]]
[[Category:Human body positions]]

[[ca:Alimentació]]
[[es:Alimentación]]
[[fa:خوردن]]
[[fr:Alimentation]]
[[gl:Alimentación]]
[[ko:먹기]]
[[id:Makan]]
[[it:Alimentazione (nutrizione)]]
[[he:אכילה]]
[[kn:ತಿನ್ನುವಿಕೆ]]
[[lt:Mityba]]
[[ms:Makan]]
[[nl:Eten]]
[[ne:खानु]]
[[pl:Odżywianie]]
[[pt:Alimentação]]
[[simple:Eating]]
[[fi:Syöminen]]
[[sv:Ätande]]
[[tl:Pagkain (gawain)]]
[[ta:உண்ணுதல்]]
[[te:తినడం]]
[[th:การรับประทานอาหาร]]
[[vi:Ăn]]
[[wuu:喫]]
[[yi:עסן]]
[[zh-yue:食嘢]]
[[zh:進食]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
