<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="21291384" ns="0" title="Windows 1.0"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{refimprove|date=August 2011}}
{{Use dmy dates|date=August 2010}}
{{Infobox OS version
|name=Windows 1.0
|family=Microsoft Windows
|logo=Windows 1.0 logo.svg
|screenshot=Windows1.0.png
|caption=Screenshot of Windows 1.01
|developer=Microsoft
|website=
|source_model=[[Closed source software|Closed source]]
|license=[[Commercial software]]
|kernel_type=
|preceded_by=
|succeeded_by=[[Windows 2.0]]
|first_release_date={{Start date and age|1985|November|20|df=yes|date=August 2011}}
|first_release_url=http://support.microsoft.com/kb/32905
|release_version=1.04
|release_date={{Start date and age|1987|April}}
|release_url=http://support.microsoft.com/kb/32905
|preview_version=
|preview_date=
|preview_url=
|support_status=Mainstream support ended on {{Start date and age|2001|December|31|df=yes}}. Did not have extended support.&lt;ref name=&quot;obsolete-prod&quot; /&gt;
|Working-status=Historic
|date=January 2009 &lt;!-- approximate date of template insertion for dating hidden maintenance categories --&gt;
}}

'''Windows 1.0''' is a [[16-bit]] graphical [[operating environment]], developed by Microsoft and released on 20 November 1985.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|author=Chaitanya Sareen|title=The Windows 7 Taskbar|url= http://blogs.msdn.com/e7/archive/2008/11/20/happy-anniversary-windows-on-the-evolution-of-the-taskbar.aspx|publisher=Microsoft|date=20 November 2008|accessdate=4 September 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt; It was Microsoft's first attempt to implement a [[Computer multitasking|multi-tasking]] [[graphical user interface]]-based operating environment on the [[personal computer|PC]] platform. Windows 1.0 was the first version of Windows launched. It was succeeded by [[Windows 2.0]] and support was discontinued on 31 December 2001.

==History==
Windows 1.0 was first released on 20 November 1985. Version 1.02, released in May 1986, was international and was available in several{{Which?|date=August 2011}} European languages. Version 1.03, released in August 1986 included enhancements that made it consistent with the international release. It included drivers for European keyboards and additional screen and printer drivers. Version 1.04, released in April 1987, added support for the [[VGA]] graphics adapters of the new [[IBM Personal System/2|IBM PS/2]] computers.{{Citation needed|date=December 2010}} At the same time, Microsoft and IBM announced the introduction of [[OS/2]] and its graphical OS/2 [[Presentation Manager]], which were supposed to ultimately replace ''both'' [[MS-DOS]] and Windows.&lt;ref&gt;http://windows.microsoft.com/en-US/windows/history&lt;/ref&gt;

In November 1987, Windows 1.0 was succeeded by [[Windows 2.0]]. Microsoft supported Windows 1.0 for sixteen years, until 31 December 2001.&lt;ref name=&quot;obsolete-prod&quot;&gt;{{Cite web
  |url = http://support.microsoft.com/gp/lifeobsoleteproducts
  |title = Obsolete Products
  |work = Microsoft Support
  |publisher = Microsoft Corporation
  |date = 25 July 2011
  |accessdate = 21 August 2011
}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Competition===
The history of Windows dates back to September 1981, when the project named &quot;Interface Manager&quot; was started. It was first presented to the public on 10 November 1983, renamed to &quot;Microsoft Windows&quot;; the two years of delay before release led to charges that it was &quot;[[vaporware]]&quot;. The initially announced version of Windows had features so much resembling the Macintosh interface that Microsoft had to change many of them: overlapping windows, although supported by the GUI engine, weren't allowed for exactly this reason. The announcement of Windows' imminent arrival in 1985 probably did not help the sales of [[VisiCorp]]'s [[VisiOn]] environment which debuted at the same time. However, even when finally released, Windows 1.0 aroused little interest.

Another GUI for the PC platform at the time was [[Graphical Environment Manager|GEM]]. It used more aspects from the [[Apple Macintosh|Macintosh]] [[GUI]], for example the [[Recycle bin (computing)|trash can]] concept (which Microsoft would later employ in future Windows releases) and more generally the desktop interaction. GEM was eventually used as the standard GUI for the [[Atari]]'s [[Atari ST|ST]] range of [[68k]]-based computers, which were sometimes referred to as [[Jackintosh]]es (the company being run by [[Jack Tramiel]]). GEM was also included in the Amstrad PC1512, probably the first 8086 based PC targeted at the home consumer and sold alongside TV's and washing machines at appliance stores. GEM's resemblance to the Mac OS later caused legal trouble for the manufacturer, [[Digital Research]], who was obliged to seriously cripple the desktop's appearance and functionality (applications were not affected).

GEM was relying on multitasking of the OS under it (non-existing in DOS on that time), so users had to close one program in order to run another one. Collections of related programs, like GEM Draw, had confusing File menu items like ''Close (to Edit)'' to facilitate switching.

An alternative multitasker released shortly before was [[Quarterdeck Office Systems|Quarterdeck]]'s [[DESQview]], modeled after but more memory-economical and versatile than [[IBM]]'s failed [[TopView]] from 1984. It did not have graphical capabilities initially, but is able to multitask DOS applications in windows as long as they are well-behaved or have a specially written &quot;loader&quot; to fix them on the fly.

Windows 1.0 market share grew very slowly. Early Windows versions of [[Microsoft Excel]] and other Windows applications were bundled with a runtime version of Windows, presumably to both increase sales of the applications and allow users to &quot;test drive&quot; Windows at no additional cost.

The Macintosh remained the platform of choice especially for high-end graphics and [[desktop publishing]] (DTP). Although [[Aldus PageMaker]] shipped in January 1987 with a Windows executable, it remained a curiosity due to poor support relative to the Mac version, and a steep $795 price tag.

Other shell programs for MS-DOS include [[Norton Commander]], [[PC Tools (Central Point Software)|PC Tools]], [[XTree]]. [[DOS Shell]], and DOS Menu (in MS-DOS version 4.0). These applications attempted to be organizational and menu-driven tools, and did not try at all to be a 'desktop' shell.

==Features==
Windows 1.0 offers limited multitasking of existing MS-DOS programs and concentrates on creating an interaction [[paradigm]] (cf. [[Message loop in Microsoft Windows|message loop]]), an execution model and a stable [[Application programming interface|API]] for [[native mode|native]] programs for the future. Due to Microsoft's extensive support for [[backward compatibility]], it is not only possible to execute Windows 1.0 [[executable|binary]] programs on current versions of Windows to a large extent, but also to recompile their [[source code]] into an equally functional &quot;modern&quot; application with just limited modifications.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|author=Nathan Lineback|title=Misc. Windows Screen Shots|url=http://toastytech.com/guis/misc.html|work=Graphical User Interface Gallery |date=October 2007|accessdate=4 September 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Windows 1.0 is often regarded as a &quot;[[Front-end and back-end|front-end]] to the [[MS-DOS]] [[operating system]]&quot;, a description which has also been applied to subsequent versions of Windows. Windows 1.0 is an MS-DOS program. Windows 1.0 programs can call MS-DOS functions, and GUI programs are run from [[.exe]] files just like MS-DOS programs. However, Windows .exe files had their own &quot;new executable&quot; (NE) file format, which only Windows could process and which, for example, allowed demand-loading of code and data. Applications were supposed to handle memory only through Windows' own memory management system, which implemented a software-based [[virtual memory]] scheme allowing for applications larger than available [[Random access memory|RAM]].

Because graphics support in MS-DOS is extremely limited, MS-DOS applications have to go to the ''bare hardware'' (or sometimes just to the [[BIOS]]) to get work done. Therefore, Windows 1.0 included original [[device driver]]s for video cards, a mouse, keyboards, printers and serial communications, and applications were supposed to only invoke APIs built upon these drivers. However, this extended to other APIs such as file system management functions. In this sense, Windows 1.0 was designed to be extended into a full-fledged operating system, rather than being just a graphics environment used by applications. Indeed, Windows 1.0 is a &quot;DOS front-end&quot; and cannot operate without a DOS environment (it uses, for example, the file-handling functions provided by DOS.) The level of replacement increases in subsequent versions.

The system requirements for Windows 1.01 constituted [[Color Graphics Adapter|CGA]]/[[Hercules Graphics Card|HGC]]/[[Enhanced Graphics Adapter|EGA]] (listed as &quot;Monochrome or color monitor&quot;), MS-DOS 2.0, 256&amp;nbsp;kB of memory or greater, and two double-sided disk drives or a hard drive.&lt;ref&gt;http://support.microsoft.com/kb/32905&lt;/ref&gt;

Windows 1.0 runs a [[operating system shell|shell]] program known as MS-DOS Executive. Other supplied programs are [[Microsoft Calculator|Calculator]], [[Microsoft Calendar|Calendar]], [[Cardfile]], [[Clipboard (software)#Microsoft Windows|Clipboard]] viewer, Clock, [[Notepad (Windows)|Notepad]], [[Microsoft Paint|Paint]], [[Reversi]], [[Terminal emulator|Terminal]], and [[Windows Write|Write]].

Windows 1.0 does not allow overlapping windows. Instead all windows are ''[[tiling window manager|tiled]]''. Only dialog boxes can appear over other windows.

Windows 1.0 [[executables]], while having a similar .exe [[filename extension|extension]] and initial file header similar to [[MS-DOS]] programs, do not contain the so-called ''MS-DOS stub'' which prints the &quot;This program requires Microsoft Windows&quot; message and exits when the program is run outside of Windows. Instead, the exe file header has a newer C programming model specifying more memory and makes DOS reject the executable with a &quot;program too large to fit in memory&quot; error message.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.freeinfosociety.com/media/pdf/2801.pdf&lt;/ref&gt; &lt;!-- this info irrelevant to Windows article: When I run Windows 1.02 programs in Dosbox 0.74, I get a &quot;This program requires Microsoft Windows&quot; message. The only difference between the Windows 2 and Windows 3 DOS stub seems to be that the message doesn't end with a full stop. Maybe the &quot;program too large to fit in memory&quot; message appears under certain versions of MS-DOS with certain hardware configurations, though.--&gt;

From the beginning, Windows was intended to multitask programs (although this originally only applied to native applications and for many versions the multitasking was [[co-operative multitasking|co-operative]], rather than preemptive).

Pre-release versions had menus at the bottom of windows, as it was used in Microsoft applications, such as Word and Multiplan of that era; however, this was changed before the first release.

==See also==
{{Portal|Microsoft}}
*[[Comparison of file managers]]
*[[VM/386]]
{{-}}

==References==
{{Reflist}}

==External links==
*[http://uk.youtube.com/watch?v=ItuymzxNUYM Demo of Windows 1.04 running on an original IBM XT]
*[http://toastytech.com/guis/win1983.html A good look at Windows 1.0]

{{Microsoft Windows family}}

[[Category:1985 software]]
[[Category:Discontinued versions of Microsoft Windows]]

{{Link GA|de}}

[[ar:ويندوز 1.0]]
[[az:Windows 1.0]]
[[be:Microsoft Windows 1.0]]
[[be-x-old:Windows 1.0]]
[[bg:Windows 1.0]]
[[ca:Microsoft Windows 1.0]]
[[cs:Windows 1.0]]
[[da:Microsoft Windows 1.0]]
[[de:Microsoft Windows 1.0]]
[[et:Windows 1.0]]
[[el:Windows 1.0]]
[[es:Windows 1.0]]
[[fr:Microsoft Windows 1.0]]
[[gl:Windows 1.0]]
[[ko:윈도 1.0]]
[[hy:Վինդոուզ 1.0]]
[[hr:Windows 1.0]]
[[id:Windows 1.0]]
[[is:Windows 1.0]]
[[it:Windows 1.0]]
[[jv:Windows 1.0]]
[[ka:Windows 1.0]]
[[lt:Windows 1.0]]
[[hu:Windows 1.0]]
[[mr:विंडोज १.०]]
[[nl:Windows 1.0]]
[[ja:Microsoft Windows 1.0]]
[[no:Windows 1.0]]
[[nn:Windows 1.0]]
[[uz:Windows 1.0]]
[[pl:Microsoft Windows 1.x]]
[[pt:Windows 1.x]]
[[ro:Windows 1.0]]
[[ru:Windows 1.0]]
[[si:වින්ඩෝස් 1.0]]
[[simple:Windows 1.0]]
[[sk:Windows 1.0]]
[[sl:Windows 1.0]]
[[fi:Windows 1.0]]
[[sv:Windows 1.0]]
[[tl:Windows 1.0x]]
[[ta:விண்டோஸ் 1.0]]
[[th:วินโดวส์ 1.0]]
[[tr:Windows 1.0]]
[[uk:Windows 1.0]]
[[zh:Windows 1.0]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
