<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="21304364" ns="0" title="DOS"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{About|the family of operating systems for IBM PC-compatible computers}}

[[Image:FreeDOS Beta 9 pre-release5 (command line interface) on Bochs sshot20040912.png|right|thumb|256px|[[FreeDOS]] screenshot showing the command line interface, directory structure and version information.]]
'''DOS''', short for &quot;Disk Operating System&quot;,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Murdock|first=Everett|title=DOS the Easy Way|publisher=EasyWay Downloadable Books|year=1988|isbn=0923178007}}&lt;/ref&gt; is an [[acronym]] for several closely related [[operating system]]s that dominated the [[IBM PC compatible]] market between 1981 and 1995, or until about 2000 if one includes the partially DOS-based [[Microsoft Windows]] versions [[Windows 95|95]], [[Windows 98|98]], and [[Windows Me|Millennium Edition]].

Related systems include [[MS-DOS]], [[PC-DOS]], [[DR-DOS]], [[FreeDOS]], [[PTS-DOS]], [[ROM-DOS]], [[Novell DOS]], [[OpenDOS]] and several others.

In spite of the common usage, none of these systems were simply named &quot;DOS&quot; (a name given only to an unrelated [[DOS/360 and successors|IBM mainframe operating system]] in the 1960s). A number of unrelated, non-[[x86]] microcomputer disk operating systems had &quot;DOS&quot; in their name, and are often referred to simply as &quot;DOS&quot; when discussing machines that use them (e.g. [[AmigaDOS]], [[AMSDOS]], [[ANDOS]], [[Apple DOS]], [[Atari DOS]], [[Commodore DOS]], [[CSI-DOS]], [[ProDOS]], and [[TRS-DOS]]). While providing many of the same [[operating system]] functions for their respective computer systems, programs running under any one of these operating systems would not run under others.

==Design==

All MS-DOS-type operating systems run on machines with the [[Intel]] [[x86]] or compatible [[CPU]]s, mainly the [[IBM PC]] and [[IBM PC compatible|compatibles]]. Machine-dependent versions of MS-DOS were produced for many non-IBM-compatible [[x86]]-based machines, with variations from relabelling of the [[Microsoft]] distribution under the manufacturer's name, to versions specifically designed to work with non-IBM-PC-compatible hardware. For as long as application programs used DOS APIs instead of direct hardware access, they could thereby also run on non-IBM-PC compatible machines.
In 1985, Digital Research also had a version of [[Concurrent DOS 68K]] for use on Motorola 68000 CPUs, and the original [[FreeDOS]] kernel [[DOS-C]] derived from [[DOS/NT]], also for Motorola CPUs, in the early 1990s. While these systems resembled the DOS architecture, applications were not binary compatible due to the incompatible instruction sets of these non-x86-CPUs. However, applications written in high-level languages could be ported easily.

DOS is a single-user, single-task operating system with basic [[kernel (computer science)|kernel]] functions that are [[reentrant (subroutine)|non-reentrant]]: only one program at a time can use them. There is an exception with [[Terminate and Stay Resident]] (TSR) programs, and some TSRs can allow [[Computer multitasking|multitasking]]. However, there is still a problem with the non-reentrant kernel: once a process calls a service inside of operating system kernel ([[system call]]), it must not be interrupted with another process calling system call, until the first call is finished.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=CHAPTER EIGHTEEN: RESIDENT PROGRAMS (Part 3)|url=http://oopweb.com/Assembly/Documents/ArtOfAssembly/Volume/Chapter_18/CH18-3.html|accessdate=2008-09-02|work=The Art of Assembly Language Programming|last=Hyde|first=Randall|date=1996-09-30}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The DOS kernel provides [[MS-DOS API|various functions for programs]] (an ''application program interface''), like displaying characters on-screen, reading a character from the keyboard, accessing disk files and more.

DOS by default provides a primitive ability for [[shell script]]ing, via ''batch files'' (with the [[filename extension]] '''.BAT'''). These are text files that can be created in any text editor. They are executed in the same fashion as compiled programs, and run each line of the batch file as a command. Batch files can also make use of several internal commands, such as [[GOTO]] and [[Conditional (programming)|conditional statements]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.computerhope.com/batch.htm|title=Batch File Help|accessdate=2008-09-10|publisher=computerhope.com}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[GOSUB]] and simple arithmetic is supported with the DR&amp;nbsp;DOS COMMAND.COM as well as some with third-party shells like [[4DOS]], but can also be faked via strange workarounds; however, no real form of programming is usually enabled.

The operating system offers a [[hardware abstraction layer]] that allows development of character-based applications, but not for accessing most of the [[computer hardware|hardware]], such as [[Video card|graphics card]]s, [[computer printer|printer]]s, or [[computer mouse|mice]]. This required programmers to access the hardware directly, usually resulting in each application having its own set of [[device driver]]s for each hardware peripheral. Hardware manufacturers would release specifications to ensure device drivers for popular applications were available.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.zingtech.com/features/gamedev/gnewprog.htm|title=ZINGTECH - Guide to the New Game Programmer|accessdate=2008-09-02|last=Matczynski|first=Michael}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Drive naming scheme===
{{Main|Drive letter assignment}}
In DOS, drives are referred to by identifying letters. Standard practice is to reserve &quot;A&quot; and &quot;B&quot; for [[floppy drives]]. On systems with only one floppy drive DOS assigns both letters to the drive, prompting the user to swap disks as programs alternate access between them. This facilitates copying from floppy to floppy or having a program run from one floppy while accessing its data on another. [[Hard drives]] were originally assigned the letters &quot;C&quot; and &quot;D&quot;. DOS could only support one active partition per drive. As support for more hard drives became available, this developed into first assigning a drive letter to each drive's active [[primary partition]], then making a second pass over the drives to allocate letters to logical drives in the [[extended partition]], then a third pass to give any other non-active [[primary partition]]s their names (where such additional partitions existed and contained a DOS-supported file system.) Lastly, DOS allocates letters for [[optical disc drive]]s, [[RAM disk]]s, and other hardware. Letter assignments usually occur in the order the drivers are loaded, but the drivers can instruct DOS to assign a different letter; drivers for network drives, for example, typically assign letters nearer the end of the alphabet.&lt;ref name=&quot;driveletter&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.storagereview.com/guide/partLetter.html|title=Drive Letter Assignment and Choosing Primary vs. Logical Partitions|work=The PC Guide|date=2007-05-17|accessdate=2008-09-02}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Because DOS applications use these drive letters directly (unlike the /dev directory in [[Unix-like]] systems), they can be disrupted by adding new hardware that needs a drive letter. An example is the addition of a new hard drive having a primary partition where a pre-existing hard drive contains logical drives in extended partitions; the new drive will be assigned a letter that was previously assigned to one of the extended partition logical drives. Moreover, even adding a new hard drive having only logical drives in an extended partition would still disrupt the letters of RAM disks and optical drives.
This problem persisted through Microsoft's DOS-based 9x versions of Windows until they were replaced by versions based on the NT line, which preserves the letters of existing drives until the user changes them.&lt;ref name=&quot;driveletter&quot; /&gt;
Under DOS, this problem can be worked around by defining a SUBST drive and installing the DOS program into this logical drive. The assignment of this drive would then be changed in a batchjob whenever the application starts. Under some versions of [[Concurrent DOS]], as well as under [[Multiuser DOS]], System Manager and [[REAL/32]], the reserved drive letter L: will automatically be assigned to the corresponding [[load drive]] whenever an application starts.

===Reserved device names===
{{Main|Device file}}
There are reserved device names in DOS that cannot be used as filenames regardless of extension; these are used to send application output to hardware peripherals. These restrictions also affect several Windows versions, in some cases causing crashes and security vulnerabilities.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.juniper.net/security/auto/vulnerabilities/vuln1043.html|title=Microsoft Windows MS-DOS Device Name DoS Vulnerability|accessdate=2008-09-02}}&lt;/ref&gt;

A partial list of these reserved names is: &lt;code&gt;NUL:&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;CON:&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;AUX:&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;PRN:&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;COM1:&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;COM2:&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;COM3:&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;COM4:&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;LPT1:&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;LPT2:&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;LPT3:&lt;/code&gt;,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.pcmag.com/encyclopedia_term/0,2542,t=DOS+device+names&amp;i=41766,00.asp|title=DOS device names definition|publisher=PC Magazine|accessdate=2008-09-02}}&lt;/ref&gt; and sometimes &lt;code&gt;LPT4:&lt;/code&gt; as well.&lt;!-- for example with DR-DOS 7.02 --&gt; &lt;code&gt;AUX:&lt;/code&gt; typically defaults to &lt;code&gt;COM1:&lt;/code&gt;, and &lt;code&gt;PRN:&lt;/code&gt; to &lt;code&gt;LPT1:&lt;/code&gt;, but these defaults can be changed on some systems.&lt;!-- for example under Concurrent DOS, Multuser DOS or DR-DOS 7.02+ --&gt;

Colons are not necessary in some cases, for example:
&lt;source lang=&quot;dos&quot;&gt;
echo This does nothing &gt; nul
&lt;/source&gt;

It is still possible to create files or directories using these reserved device names, such as through direct editing of directory data structures in disk sectors. Such naming, such as starting a file name with a space, has sometimes been used by viruses or hacking programs to obscure files from users who do not know how to access these locations.

===Boot sequence===

* The [[bootstrap loader]] on PC-compatible computers ([[Master boot record|MBR]] or [[boot sector]]) is located at [[track0|track zero]], the first sector on a disk. The [[BIOS|ROM-BIOS]] will load this sector into memory at address 0000h:7C00h, and check for a signature &quot;55h AAh&quot; at position 01FEh. If found, the sector is considered to be valid and executed, if not, the ROM-BIOS will try the next physical disk in the row.
*If the loaded sector happens to be a MBR, its code will scan the partition table, which is located within this sector, for an active partition (bit7=1 at pos 01BEh+10h*n), and, if found, load the first sector of the corresponding partition into memory in the similar fashion as it had been loaded by the ROM-BIOS itself.
* The boot sector code loads the start of the DOS-[[BIOS]], which is located in the file [[IO.SYS]] on MS-DOS systems, into segment 0000h:0600h&lt;ref name=&quot;pagetable-165&quot;&gt;{{cite web|title=Reverse-Engineering DOS 1.0 &amp;#8211; Part 1: The Boot Sector &amp;laquo; pagetable.com|url=http://www.pagetable.com/?p=165}} 090912 pagetable.com&lt;/ref&gt; In some cases the boot sector instead relocates itself into 0000h:0600h and loads the partition boot code into 0000h:7C00h and executes it.&lt;ref name=&quot;dewassoc_com-master_boot_record&quot;&gt;{{cite web|title=The Master Boot Record (MBR) and What it Does|url=http://www.dewassoc.com/kbase/hard_drives/master_boot_record.htm}} 090912 dewassoc.com&lt;/ref&gt; The boot sector will then pass execution to the loaded portion.
* The loaded portion of the DOS-BIOS will then load the remainder of itself into memory. The DOS-BIOS will then load the DOS kernel, located in [[MSDOS.SYS]] on MS-DOS systems, into memory as well. In Windows 9x, the DOS-BIOS and kernel are combined into IO.SYS, and MSDOS.SYS is used as a text configuration file.
* The DOS-BIOS then loads the [[CONFIG.SYS|\CONFIG.SYS]] file to [[Parsing#Programming languages|parse]] configuration parameters. The &lt;tt&gt;SHELL&lt;/tt&gt; variable specifies the location of the [[shell (computing)|shell]] which defaults to [[COMMAND.COM|\COMMAND.COM]].
* The shell is loaded and executed.
* The startup batch file [[AUTOEXEC.BAT]] is then run by the shell.&lt;ref name=&quot;evergreen_edu-config-sys&quot;&gt;{{cite web|title=CONFIG.SYS Commands|url=http://academic.evergreen.edu/projects/biophysics/technotes/program/config-sys.txt}} 090913 academic.evergreen.edu&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.pcguide.com/ref/hdd/file/structBoot-c.html|title=The DOS Boot Process|work=The PC Guide|last=Kozierok|first=Charles|year=2001|accessdate=2008-09-02}}&lt;/ref&gt; DR-DOS COMMAND.COM and 4DOS allow for the specification of the startup batch file through a parameter in the &lt;tt&gt;SHELL&lt;/tt&gt; statement.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.drdos.net/documentation/usergeng/09ugch9.htm|title=DR-DOS 7.02 User Guide chapter 9|publisher=Caldera Systems|year=1998|accessdate=2009-09-15}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;DRDOS6&quot;&gt;{{cite book|title=DR DOS 6.0 User Guide|publisher=Digital Research|year=1991|pages=320–324}}&lt;/ref&gt;{{Rp|392}}

The DOS-BIOS and kernel files loaded by the boot sector must be [[Fragmentation (computer)|contiguous]] and be the first two [[File Allocation Table#Directory table|directory entries]].&lt;ref name=&quot;wustl_edu-misc&quot;&gt;{{cite web|title=misc.txt|url=http://www.arl.wustl.edu/~lockwood/class/cse306-s04/resources/helppc/misc.txt.html}} 090912 arl.wustl.edu&lt;/ref&gt; As such, removing and adding this file is likely to render the media unbootable. It is, however, possible to replace the shell at will, a method that can be used to start the execution of dedicated applications faster.
This limitation does not apply to any version of DR&amp;nbsp;DOS, where the system files can be located anywhere in the root directory and do not need to be contiguous. Therefore, system files can be simply copied to a disk provided that the boot sector is DR&amp;nbsp;DOS compatible already. This works because the DR DOS boot sector mounts the FAT filesystem, locates the DOS-BIOS and loads the whole file into memory.

In variation from MS-DOS, the DOS-BIOS and kernel files have different names in some DOS versions, for example, in PC-DOS as well as in DR-DOS 5.0 (and higher) they are named [[IBMBIO.COM]] instead of [[IO.SYS]] and [[IBMDOS.COM]] in place of [[MSDOS.SYS]]. Older versions of DR DOS used DRBIOS.SYS and DRBDOS.SYS instead. On systems designed for PC-DOS v1.10 the signature 55h AAh at position 01FEh is not checked. {{Citation needed|date=September 2010}}

==Origins==

[[IBM]] PC-DOS (and the separately sold MS-DOS) and its predecessor, [[86-DOS]], were loosely inspired by [[Digital Research]]'s [[CP/M]], which was the dominant disk operating system for 8-bit [[Intel 8080]] and [[Zilog]] [[Zilog Z-80|Z80]] based microcomputers. PC-DOS ran on 8088-family processors. 

When IBM introduced the IBM PC, built with the [[Intel 8088]] microprocessor, they needed an operating system. Seeking an 8088-compatible build of CP/M, IBM initially approached Microsoft CEO [[Bill Gates]] (possibly believing that Microsoft owned CP/M due to the Microsoft [[Z-80 SoftCard]], which allowed CP/M to run on an [[Apple II]]&lt;ref name=&quot;rolander&quot;&gt;{{cite interview|url=http://www.podtech.net/scobleshow/technology/1593/the-rest-of-the-story-how-bill-gates-beat-gary-kildall-in-os-war-part-1 |title=The rest of the story: How Bill Gates beat Gary Kildall in OS war, Part 1|last=Rolander|first=Tom|interview=Robert Scoble|show=The Scoble Show}}&lt;/ref&gt;). IBM was sent to Digital Research, and a meeting was set up. However, the initial negotiations for the use of CP/M broke down&amp;mdash;Digital Research wished to sell CP/M on a royalty basis, while IBM sought a single license, and to change the name to &quot;PC DOS&quot;. DR founder [[Gary Kildall]] refused, and IBM withdrew.&lt;ref name=&quot;rolander&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|title=Just Say No to Microsoft|url=http://books.google.co.uk/books?id=I0RB1Xxp-KAC&amp;pg=PA11&amp;lpg=PA11&amp;dq=ibm+cp/m+licensing&amp;source=web&amp;ots=dryptL9LAW&amp;sig=KJqNIT1r_-yVcpe0fa0p9RI1BW4&amp;hl=en&amp;sa=X&amp;oi=book_result&amp;resnum=10&amp;ct=result#PPA9,M1|last=Bove|first=Tony|publisher=No Starch Press|year=2005|pages=9–11|isbn=159327064X}}&lt;/ref&gt;

IBM again approached Bill Gates. Gates in turn approached [[Seattle Computer Products]]. There, programmer [[Tim Paterson]] had developed a variant of [[CP/M-80]], intended as an internal product for testing SCP's new [[16-bit]] [[Intel 8086]] [[Central processing unit|CPU]] card for the [[S-100 bus]]. The system was initially named &quot;QDOS&quot; (Quick and Dirty Operating System), before being made commercially available as [[86-DOS]]. Microsoft purchased 86-DOS, allegedly for $50,000. This became Microsoft Disk Operating System, MS-DOS, introduced in 1981.&lt;ref name=&quot;mshist&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://inventors.about.com/library/weekly/aa033099.htm|title=The Unusual History of MS-DOS The Microsoft Operating System|accessdate=2008-09-02|last=Bellis|first=Mary}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Microsoft also licensed their system to multiple computer companies, who supplied MS-DOS for their own hardware, sometimes under their own names. Microsoft later required the use of the MS-DOS name, with the exception of the IBM variant. IBM continued to develop their version, [[PC-DOS|PC DOS]], for the IBM PC.&lt;ref name=&quot;mshist&quot; /&gt; Digital Research became aware that an operating system similar to CP/M was being sold by IBM (under the same name that IBM insisted upon for CP/M), and threatened legal action. IBM responded by offering an agreement: they would give PC consumers a choice of PC DOS or [[CP/M-86]], Kildall's 8086 version. Side-by-side, CP/M cost almost $200 more than PC DOS, and sales were low. CP/M faded, with MS-DOS and PC DOS becoming the marketed operating system for PCs and PC compatibles.&lt;ref name=&quot;rolander&quot; /&gt;

Digital Research attempted to regain the market lost from CP/M-86; initially with [[Concurrent DOS]], [[FlexOS]] and [[DOS Plus]] (both compatible with both MS-DOS and CP/M-86 software), later with [[Multiuser DOS]] (compatible with both MS-DOS and CP/M-86 software) and [[DR-DOS]] (compatible with MS-DOS software). Digital Research was bought by [[Novell]], and DR DOS became [[Novell DOS]] 7; later, it was part of [[Caldera (company)|Caldera]] (under the names [[OpenDOS]] and DR-DOS 7.02/7.03), [[Lineo]], and [[DeviceLogics]].

Microsoft and IBM later had a series of disagreements over two successor operating systems to DOS - Microsoft's Windows and IBM's [[OS/2]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0CE0D81339F934A15754C0A967958260|title=Microsoft Widens Its Split With I.B.M. Over Software|last=Pollack|first=Andrew|accessdate=2008-09-02|date=1991-07-27|publisher=New York Times}}&lt;/ref&gt; They split development of their DOS systems as a result.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=990DEEDD1630F93BA15756C0A96F958260|title=I.B.M. Executive Describes Price Pressure by Microsoft|last=Brinkley|first=Joel|date=1999-05-28|publisher=New York Times|accessdate=2008-09-02}}&lt;/ref&gt; MS-DOS was partially transformed into Windows; the last version of PC DOS was PC DOS 7.10,&lt;!-- a successor to PC DOS 2000, which was PC DOS 7.0 revision 1 --&gt; released in 2003.

The [[FreeDOS]] project began 26 June 1994, when Microsoft announced it would no longer sell or support MS-DOS. [[Jim Hall (programmer)|Jim Hall]] then posted a manifesto proposing the development of an open-source replacement. Within a few weeks, other programmers including Pat Villani and Tim Norman joined the project. A kernel, the command.com command line interpreter (shell) and core utilities were created by pooling code they had written or found available. There were several official pre-release distributions of FreeDOS before the FreeDOS 1.0 distribution was released on 3 September 2006.  Made available under the [[GNU General Public License]] (GPL), FreeDOS does not require license fees or royalties.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.linuxdevices.com/articles/AT3952799051.html|title=The past, present, and future of the FreeDOS Project|date=2002-03-25|accessdate=2008-06-14|author=Jim Hall}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web| url=http://www.freedos.org/freedos/about/| date=September 23, 2006| title=History of FreeDOS|first=Jim| last=Hall| publisher=freedos.org| accessdate=2007-05-28}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Decline==
{{Main|History of Microsoft Windows}}
Early versions of [[Microsoft Windows]] were an application that ran on top of a separate version of DOS.&lt;ref name=&quot;emulate&quot;/&gt; By the early 1990s, Windows saw heavy use on new DOS systems. With [[Windows 3.1x|MS-Windows for Workgroups 3.11]], DOS was almost reduced to the role of a boot loader for the Windows kernel; in 1995, [[Windows 95|MS-Windows 95]] was bundled as a standalone operating system that did not require a separate DOS license. With Windows 95 (and Windows 98 and Me, that followed it), the MS-DOS kernel remained, but with Windows as the system's graphical shell. With Windows 95 and 98, but not ME, the MS-DOS component could be run without starting Windows.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.smartcomputing.com/Editorial/article.asp?article=articles/archive/95win/95win21/95win21.asp&amp;guid=|title=Finding The DOS In Windows 95|work=Smart Computing|month=March | year=1996|accessdate=2008-07-12}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;http://support.microsoft.com/kb/138996&lt;/ref&gt; With DOS no longer required to use Windows, the majority of PC users stopped using it directly.

==Continued use==
Currently available DOS systems are [[FreeDOS]], [[DR-DOS]] (and Enhanced DR-DOS), [[ROM-DOS]], [[PTS-DOS]], [[RxDOS]], [[Multiuser DOS]],&lt;ref&gt;http://www.conctrls.com/CCInews.html&lt;/ref&gt; [[REAL/32]], and others.  Some computer manufacturers, including [[Dell]] and [[HP]], sell computers with FreeDOS as the [[Original equipment manufacturer|OEM]] operating system.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.freedos.org/jhall/|title=Jim Hall|date=2007-07-13|accessdate=2008-06-12|last=Hall|first=Jim}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.dell.com/content/topics/segtopic.aspx/e510_nseries?c=us&amp;cs=19&amp;l=en&amp;s=dhs|title=Dell PCs Featuring FreeDOS|accessdate=2008-06-14}}&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;!-- Perhaps the following should be moved to a separate article? --&gt;
[[NX-DOS]] is currently under development. It is 16-bit, real-time, networkable, bootable from a floppy, and has an incomplete USB driver. It dates back to 1992 as a personal project, and was released as [[GPL]] in 2005.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.linuxdevices.com/news/NS9509696845.html|title=GPL'd DOS workalike adds features|date=2007-04-01|accessdate=2008-06-01}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Embedding===
DOS' structure of accessing hardware directly makes it ideal for use in embedded devices. The final versions of DR-DOS are still aimed at this market.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.drdos.com/products/drdos703.htm|title=DR DOS Embedded DOS|accessdate=2008-09-26}}&lt;/ref&gt; ROM-DOS was used as the embedded system on the [[Canon PowerShot Pro]] 70.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://findarticles.com/p/articles/mi_m0EIN/is_1999_Feb_23/ai_53930374|title=Datalight DOS Selected for Canon's New Line of Digital Still Cameras|publisher=Business Wire|date=1999-08-24|accessdate=2008-09-26}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Emulation===
[[Image:DOSBox screenshot.png|thumb|right|250px|DOSBox running on Windows Vista]]
Under [[Linux]], it is also possible to run copies of DOS and many of its clones under ''[[DOSEMU]]'', a Linux-native [[virtual machine]] for running DOS programs at near native speed.  There are a number of other [[emulator]]s for running DOS under various versions of UNIX, even on non-[[x86]] platforms, such as [[DOSBox]].&lt;ref name=&quot;DOSBox&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.dosemu.org/|title=DOSEMU Home|date=2007-05-05|accessdate=2008-07-03|author=}}&lt;/ref&gt;

DOS emulators are gaining popularity among [[Windows XP]] and [[Windows Vista]] users, due to these systems being very incompatible with pure DOS. They can be used to run games or other DOS software. One of the best-known is [[DOSBox]], designed for legacy gaming (e.g. [[King's Quest]], [[Doom (video game)|Doom]]) on modern operating systems.&lt;ref name=&quot;emulate&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://apcmag.com/how_to_coax_retro_dos_games_to_play_on_vista.htm|title=HOW TO: Coax retro DOS games to play on Vista|date=2006-10-13|accessdate=2008-07-03|author=James Bannan}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;DOSBox&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.dosbox.com/information.php|title=DOSBox Information|accessdate=2008-05-18}}&lt;/ref&gt;

It is possible to run DOS applications in a copy of a DOS operating system on a [[:Category:x86 emulators|PC emulator]], allowing better compatibility than DOS emulators where the emulation of the DOS operating environment is imperfect.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.winvistatips.com/dos-games-on-vista-a102.php|title=DOS Games on Vista|date=2008-03-11|accessdate=2008-09-02}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===With Microsoft Windows===
[[Image:Command prompt on windows vista.png|thumb|left|250px|[[CMD.EXE]], the DOS-styled command prompt used in [[Windows NT|Microsoft-NT]]-based Windows.]]
True 32-bit versions of Windows, starting with NT and including 2000, XP, and Vista, are not based on DOS. These include the [[Virtual DOS machine|NT Virtual DOS Machine]] (NTVDM), which runs a modified version of MS-DOS 5 in a virtual machine. While DOS-based versions used the traditional [[COMMAND.COM]] for a [[command line interface]], [[Windows NT|MS-Windows NT]] and its derivatives use [[CMD.EXE]], a descendant of OS/2's command interpreter which recognizes many DOS commands (although COMMAND.COM is still called and used when DOS .EXE files are run).{{Clear}}

===64-bit Windows Versions===
[[Windows XP x64]], Windows Vista x64 and Windows 7 x64 editions do not contain the NTVDM and cannot run 16-bit DOS applications directly. COMMAND.COM is missing and the only way to run a DOS application under these versions of Windows is by using an emulator.

==Versions==
{{see|Comparison of x86 DOS operating systems|Timeline of x86 DOS operating systems}}

==Software==
{{See|:Category:DOS software}}
[[Image:Arachne VESA Mode.png|thumb|right|250px|Arachne web browser]]

DOS was the dominant PC-Compatible platform and many notable programs were written for it. These included:

*'''[[Lotus 1-2-3]]'''; a protected mode [[spreadsheet]] program that saw heavy use in corporate markets and has been credited with the success of the IBM PC&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.crn.com/it-channel/18818026|last=Darrow|first=Barbara|title=Whatever Happened To Lotus 1-2-3?|date=1 February 2002|accessdate=2008-07-12}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*'''[[WordPerfect]]'''; a [[word processor]] that is currently produced for the [[Microsoft Windows|Windows]] platform
*'''[[dBase]]'''; one of the earliest [[database]] programs
*'''[[Harvard Graphics]]'''; one of the earliest [[presentation]] for overhead designing and hand-outs computer aid
*'''[[Telix]]'''; a [[modem]] communication program
*'''[[Arachne (web browser)|Arachne]]'''; a 16-bit graphical DOS [[web browser]]
*'''[[DJGPP]]''', the 32-bit DPMI DOS port of [[GNU Compiler Collection|gcc]]
*'''[[4DOS]]''', a much improved replacement [[shell (computing)|shell]]
*[[Borland]]'s [[integrated development environment]], which included [[Turbo Pascal]], [[Turbo BASIC]], [[Turbo C]], and [[Turbo Assembler]]
*[[Bulletin board systems|BBS]] hosting software [[PCBoard]], [[RemoteAccess]], [[Spitfire (BBS)|Spitfire]], [[Maximus (BBS)|Maximus]], [[McBBS]], and [[TAG (BBS)|TAG]]
*[[BASIC]]-language interpreters [[BASICA]] and [[GW-BASIC]]
*Numerous [[first-person shooter]] games: [[Wolfenstein 3D]], a joint venture between [[id Software]] and Apogee Software (later [[3D Realms]]); id Software's [[Doom (video game)|Doom]] and [[Quake (video game)|Quake]]; and 3D Realms' [[Duke Nukem 3D]], [[Shadow Warrior]], and [[Rise of the Triad]]. The first two 3D Realms' titles were built with the DOS-based [[Build engine]], written by [[Ken Silverman]] and used for numerous DOS FPS games. R.O.T.T. (among others) was based upon a heavily-modified Wolfenstein 3D.

==Ease of use==
===User interface===
{{See also|List of DOS commands}}
[[File:DirectoryListing1.png|300px|thumb|right|Screenshot of a Windows command shell listing the files in a directory]]
DOS systems utilize a [[command line interface]]. Programs are started by entering their filename at the command prompt. DOS systems include several programs as system utilities, and provides additional commands that don't correspond to programs (''internal commands'').&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|title=DOS the Easy Way|last=Murdock|first=Everett|pages=7–12|publisher=EasyWay Downloadable Books|isbn=0923178023}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In an attempt to provide a more user-friendly environment, numerous software manufacturers wrote [[file manager|file management programs]] that provided users with menu- and/or icon-based interfaces. Microsoft Windows is a notable example, eventually resulting in [[Windows 9x|Microsoft Windows 9x]] becoming a self-contained program loader, and replacing DOS as the most-used PC-compatible program loader. [[Text user interface]] programs included [[Norton Commander]], [[Dos Navigator]], [[Volkov Commander]], Quarterdesk [[DESQview]], and [[SideKick]]. [[Graphical user interface]] programs included Digital Research's [[Graphical Environment Manager]] (originally written for CP/M) and [[GEOS (16-bit operating system)|GEOS]].

Eventually, the manufacturers of major DOS systems began to include their own environment managers. MS-DOS/IBM DOS 4 included [[DOS Shell]];&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|title=DOS the Easy Way|last=Murdock|first=Everett|pages=71|publisher=EasyWay Downloadable Books|isbn=0923178023|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=vrsSflB2o5sC}}&lt;/ref&gt; DR DOS 5.0, released the next year, included [[ViewMAX]], based upon GEM.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|title=Dvorak's Guide to DOS and PC Performance|last=Dvorak|first=John|coauthors=Nick Anis|pages=442–444|publisher=Osborne McGraw-Hill|year=1991}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Multitasking===
By its original design, MS-DOS and PC DOS were single task operating systems, but Digital Research's [[Concurrent DOS]] 3.1, based on their [[Concurrent CP/M-86]] operating system, introduced DOS multi-user and multi-tasking capabilities in March 1984. This system later evolved into [[FlexOS]], [[Multiuser DOS]], System Manager and [[REAL/32]].

MS-DOS and PC DOS 5.0 introduced [[task switching]] via [[DOSSHELL]] in June 1991,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|title=DOS the Easy Way|last=Murdock|first=Everett|pages=83|publisher=EasyWay Downloadable Books|isbn=0923178023}}&lt;/ref&gt; and DR DOS 6.0 with TASKMAX, optionally aided by [[ViewMAX]], in September 1991.&lt;ref name=&quot;DRDOS6&quot; /&gt;{{Rp|320–324}}

MS-DOS and PC DOS never had a [[Computer multitasking|multitasking]] capability;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|title=Sams Teach Yourself Windows XP Computer Basics All in One|pages=445|publisher=Sams Publishing|year=2003|last=Perry|first=Greg|coauthors=Jill Freeze|url=http://books.google.co.uk/books?id=FptQSQs0skEC&amp;pg=PA445&amp;dq=ms-dos+multitasking&amp;sig=ACfU3U1yCLlNTSiGByW9TJOZJqmPENSdkQ|isbn=0672325357}}&lt;/ref&gt; whereas pre-emptive multitasking in virtual DOS machines was introduced into the DR&amp;nbsp;DOS line of products with [[Novell DOS]] 7 in December 1993 with EMM386 /MULTI and TASKMGR.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Chapter 13 Multitasking and Task Switching|work=Caldera DR-DOS 7.02 User Guide|publisher=Caldera Systems|year=1998|accessdate=2008-09-12|url=http://www.drdos.net/documentation/usergeng/13ugch13.htm}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Programs such as VMIX or [[DESQView]] could multitask even on an 8088, which did not have hardware support for multitasking due to its lack of [[protected mode]].

==Limitations==
Several limitations plague the DOS architecture. The original 8088 microprocessor could only address 1 [[megabyte]] of physical [[Random-access memory|RAM]]. With additional hardware devices being mapped into this range, the highest amount of available memory was 640 [[kilobyte]]s, known as [[conventional memory]]. Due to DOS's structure, this was assumed to be the maximum, and DOS could not address more than this. An early workaround was [[expanded memory]]; later, [[extended memory]] was developed with the [[80286]]. While these provided usable memory to applications, they still had to start in conventional memory, thereby using part of the existing 640&amp;nbsp;KB. Newer version of DOS starting with 5.0 could relocate parts of itself as well as device drivers into previously unused areas in the adapter range between 640 KB and 1 MB ([[upper memory]]) and the HMA ([[high memory area]]), thereby freeing up more conventional memory for DOS programs to run within the first 640 KB of the system. With [[DOS Protected Mode Services|DPMS]], it was possible to load and execute drivers in extended memory, leaving only a stub in conventional memory as an interface with the DOS system. With the [[80386]] microprocessor's redesigned [[protected mode]],&lt;!--existed in the 286 but not widely deployed; see article--&gt; [[DOS extender]]s and the [[DOS Protected Mode Interface]] were able to provide additional memory to extended DOS applications running in protected mode.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |url=http://findarticles.com/p/articles/mi_m0SMG/is_n6_v10/ai_8528224|title=DOS: still thriving after all these years|accessdate=2008-07-10|work=Software Magazine|publisher=Findarticles.com|month=May | year=1990 | first=Paul | last=Korzeniowski}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Duncan|first=Ray|title=Extending DOS: A Programmer's Guide to Protected-Mode DOS|year=1991|edition=2|publisher=Addison-Wesley|isbn=0201567989}}&lt;/ref&gt; The XMS drivers in many versions of DOS have a limit of 64 MB,&lt;ref&gt;[http://toogam.bespin.org/newcomp/ramlimit.htm Physical RAM limit for DOS.]&lt;/ref&gt; but this limit is not in the underlying architecture, but in specific implementations. Using third-party XMS drivers, extended DOS applications can take advantage of up to theoretical 4 GB of memory.

DOS also has an upper limit to the size of [[hard disk]] partitions. This has two causes. First, many DOS-type systems never had support for any [[file system]] newer than [[FAT16]], which, by design, does not allow partitions larger than 2 [[gigabyte]]s.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Mueller|first=Scott|title=Upgrading and Repairing PCs|year=2003|page=812|publisher=Que Publishing|isbn=0789729741}}&lt;/ref&gt; Additionally, DOS accesses the hard disk by calling [[INT 13|Interrupt 13h]]. Older version of DOS utilized the [[cylinder-head-sector]] (CHS) system of mapping the disk. Under this system, only the first 8.4 GB or 7.84 GiB&lt;ref&gt;8,422,686,720 bytes or 1,024 cylinders × 255 heads per cylinder × 63 sectors per head × 512 bytes per sector&lt;/ref&gt; are visible to the operating system.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.storagereview.com/guide2000/ref/hdd/bios/sizeGB8.html|title=The Int 13h Interface|accessdate=2008-07-10|work=The PC Guide|publisher=storagereview.com}}&lt;/ref&gt;  Newer versions of DOS also deploy [[Logical block addressing|LBA]]-access through Interrupt 13h. Thereby, they can address hard disks up to 128 GB in size. Newer versions of DOS also support the [[FAT32]] file system (in addition to [[FAT12]] and FAT16) to allow for partitions larger than 2 GB.

Filenames in the FAT filesystem can not be longer than eight characters, and the [[filename extension]] cannot be longer than three. The [[VFAT]] extension, introduced with Windows 95, however, allows to store them in hidden directory entries on FAT12, FAT16 or FAT32 volumes.

Using the traditional DOS APIs, the maximum file size remains limited to 4 GB, but 3rd-party extensions such as FAT+ exist to work around this problem.

== See also ==
* [[COMMAND.COM]], the command line interpreter for DOS and [[Windows 9x|MS-Windows 9x]]
* [[MS-DOS API]]
* [[VGA compatible text mode]], the base of DOS’s TUI on IBM PC compatibles
* [[Timeline of x86 DOS operating systems]]

==References==
{{Reflist|3}}
;Notes
{{Refbegin}}
*   IBM Corp., IBM, (January 1984). “IBM DOS Release 2.10 Cloth bound retail hard board box”. 1st edition. IBM Corp. Item Number. 6183946
*   IBM Corp., IBM, (January 1984). “Disk Operating System User's guide (DOS Release 2.10)”. 1st edition. Microsoft Corp. (100 pages including colour illustrations) Item Number. 6183947
*   IBM Corp., IBM, (January 1984). “Disk Operating System Manual (DOS Release 2.10)”. 1st edition. Microsoft Corp. (574 looseleaf pages in 3 ring folder) Item No. 6183940
*   IBM Corp., IBM, (May 1984). “BASIC HANDBOOK General Programming Information (BASIC Release 3.0)”. 3rd edition. IBM Corp. (127 pages) Item Number 6361129
*   IBM Corp., IBM, (May 1984). “BASIC Reference (BASIC Release 3.0)”. 3rd edition. IBM Corp. Item Number 6361134
{{Refend}}

==External links==
*[http://www.nukesoft.co.uk/msdos/ ''MS-DOS Reference''] &amp;mdash; [[MS-DOS]] commands; many also apply to other DOSes on the [[PC compatible|PC]] platform.
*[http://web.archive.org/web/20071028074338/http://oldfiles.org.uk/powerload/timeline.htm Timeline of DOS and Windows versions]
*[http://www.ii.pw.edu.pl/~borkowsm/dos.htm DOS - where hardware is the only limit]

{{DEFAULTSORT:Dos}}
[[Category:DOS on IBM PC compatibles|*DOS]]
[[Category:Disk operating systems]]
[[Category:American inventions]]

[[af:DOS (bedryfstelsel)]]
[[ar:دوس]]
[[bs:DOS]]
[[bg:DOS]]
[[cs:DOS]]
[[de:Disk Operating System]]
[[et:Ketta-opsüsteem]]
[[es:DOS]]
[[eu:DOS]]
[[fa:ام‌اس-داس]]
[[fr:DOS]]
[[gl:DOS]]
[[ko:도스]]
[[hi:डॉस]]
[[hr:DOS]]
[[id:DOS]]
[[it:DOS]]
[[he:DOS]]
[[kn:DOS (ಡಾಸ್‌)]]
[[ka:DOS]]
[[lv:DOS]]
[[lt:DOS]]
[[ml:DOS]]
[[hu:DOS]]
[[nl:DOS (besturingssysteem)]]
[[ne:डस]]
[[ja:DOS (OS)]]
[[no:DOS]]
[[nn:DOS]]
[[pl:DOS]]
[[pt:DOS]]
[[ro:DOS]]
[[ru:DOS]]
[[simple:DOS]]
[[sk:DOS]]
[[sl:DOS]]
[[sr:DOS (оперативни систем)]]
[[fi:DOS]]
[[sv:DOS]]
[[ta:டாஸ்]]
[[th:ดอส (ระบบปฏิบัติการ)]]
[[tr:DOS]]
[[uk:DOS]]
[[ur:قرص اشتغالی نظام]]
[[bat-smg:DOS]]
[[zh:DOS]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
