<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><redirects><r from="Online money" to="Electronic commerce" /></redirects><pages><page pageid="9611" ns="0" title="Electronic commerce"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{ecommerce}}
'''Electronic commerce''', commonly known as '''e-commerce''', '''eCommerce''' or '''e-comm''', refers to the buying and selling of [[product (business)|product]]s or [[Service (economics)|service]]s over electronic systems such as the Internet and other [[computer network]]s. However, the term may refer to more than just buying and selling products online. It also includes the entire online process of developing, marketing, selling, delivering, servicing and paying for products and services. The amount of trade conducted electronically has grown extraordinarily with  widespread Internet usage. The use of commerce is conducted in this way, spurring and drawing on innovations in [[electronic funds transfer]], [[supply chain management]], [[Internet marketing]], [[online transaction processing]], [[electronic data interchange]] (EDI), [[inventory management]] systems, and automated data collection systems. Modern electronic commerce typically uses the [[World Wide Web]] at least at one point in the transaction's life-cycle, although it may encompass a wider range of technologies such as [[e-mail]], mobile devices and telephones as well.

A large percentage of electronic commerce is conducted entirely in electronic form for [[virtual]] items such as access to premium content on a website, but mostly electronic commerce involves the transportation of physical items in some way. Online retailers are sometimes known as [[e-tailer]]s and online retail is sometimes known as '''e-tail'''. Almost all big retailers are now electronically present on the [[World Wide Web]].

Electronic commerce that takes place between businesses is referred to as [[business-to-business]] or B2B. B2B can be open to all interested parties (e.g. [[commodity exchange]]) or limited to specific, pre-qualified participants ([[private electronic market]]). Electronic commerce that takes place between businesses and consumers, on the other hand, is referred to as [[business-to-consumer]] or [[B2C]]. This is the type of electronic commerce conducted by companies such as [[Amazon.com]]. [[Online shopping]] is a form of electronic commerce where the buyer is directly online to the seller's computer usually via the internet. There is often no intermediary service involved, and the sale or purchase transaction is completed electronically and interactively in real-time. However in some cases, an intermediary may be present in a sale or purchase transaction, or handling recurring or one-time purchase transactions for online games.

Electronic commerce is generally considered to be the sales aspect of [[e-business]]. It also consists of the exchange of data to facilitate the financing and payment aspects of business transactions.

==History==
===Early development===
Originally, electronic commerce was identified as the facilitation of commercial transactions electronically, using technology such as [[Electronic Data Interchange|Electronic Data Interchange (EDI)]] and [[Electronic funds transfer|Electronic Funds Transfer (EFT)]]. These were both introduced in the late 1970s, allowing businesses to send commercial documents like purchase orders or invoices electronically. The growth and acceptance of credit cards, automated teller machines (ATM) and telephone banking in the 1980s were also forms of electronic commerce. Another form of e-commerce was the airline reservation system typified by Sabre in the USA and Travicom in the UK.

From the 1990s onwards, electronic commerce would additionally include [[enterprise resource planning]]  systems (ERP), [[data mining]] and [[data warehousing]].

In 1990, [[Tim Berners-Lee]] invented the [[WorldWideWeb]] [[web browser]] and transformed an academic telecommunication network into a worldwide everyman everyday communication system called internet/www. Commercial enterprise on the [[Internet]] was strictly prohibited by NSF until 1995.&lt;ref&gt;[[Kevin Kelly (editor)|Kevin Kelly]]: [http://www.wired.com/wired/archive/13.08/tech.html?pg=2 We Are the Web] [[Wired magazine]], Issue 13.08, August 2005&lt;/ref&gt; Although the Internet became popular worldwide around 1994 with the adoption of [[Mosaic (web browser)|Mosaic]] web browser, it took about five years to introduce security protocols and [[DSL]] allowing continual connection to the Internet. By the end of 2000, many European and American business companies offered their services through the [[World Wide Web]]. Since then people began to associate a word &quot;[[ecommerce]]&quot; with the ability of purchasing various goods through the Internet using secure protocols and electronic payment services.

===Timeline===
* 1979: [[Michael Aldrich]] invented [[online shopping]]&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book | last1 = Tkacz | first1 = Ewaryst | last2 = Kapczynski | first2 = Adrian | title = Internet - Technical Development and Applications | publisher = Springer | year = 2009 | page = 255 | url = http://books.google.com/books?id=a9_NJIBC87gC&amp;dq | accessdate = 2011-03-28 | isbn = 978-3642050183 | quote = The first pilot system was installing in Tesco in the UK (first demonstrated in 1979 by Michael Aldrich).}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* 1981: [[Thomson Holidays]], UK is first B2B online shopping{{Citation needed|date=November 2010}}
* 1982: [[Minitel]] was introduced nationwide in [[France]] by [[France Telecom]] and used for online ordering.
* 1984: [[Gateshead]] SIS/[[Tesco]] is first B2C online shopping and Mrs Snowball, 72, is the first online home shopper{{Citation needed|date=November 2010}}
* 1985: [[Nissan]] UK sells cars and finance with credit checking to customers online from dealers' lots.{{Citation needed|date=November 2010}}
* 1987: [[Swreg]] begins to provide software and shareware authors means to sell their products online through an electronic [[Merchant account]].{{Citation needed|date=November 2010}}
* 1990: [[Tim Berners-Lee]] writes the first web browser, [[WorldWideWeb]], using a [[NeXTSTEP|NeXT]] computer.
* 1992: Terry Brownell launches first fully graphical, iconic navigated [[Bulletin board system]] online shopping using [[RoboBOARD/FX]].
* 1994: [[Netscape Communications Corporation|Netscape]] releases the Navigator browser in October under the code name [[Mozilla]]. [[Pizza Hut]] offers online ordering on its Web page. The first online bank opens. Attempts to offer flower delivery and magazine subscriptions online. [[Pornographic|Adult]] materials also become commercially available, as do cars and bikes.  [[Netscape Navigator|Netscape]] 1.0 is introduced in late 1994 [[Secure Sockets Layer|SSL]] encryption that made transactions secure.
* 1995: Jeff Bezos launches [[Amazon.com]] and the first commercial-free 24 hour, internet-only radio stations, Radio HK and [[NetRadio]] start broadcasting. [[Dell, Inc.|Dell]] and [[Cisco Systems|Cisco]] begin to aggressively use Internet for commercial transactions. [[eBay]] is founded by computer programmer Pierre Omidyar as AuctionWeb.
* 1998: [[Electronic stamp|Electronic postal stamps]] can be purchased and downloaded for printing from the Web.
* 1998: [[Alibaba Group]] is established in China. And it leverage China's B2B and C2C, B2C([[Taobao]]) market by its Authentication System.
* 1999: [[Business.com]] sold for US $7.5 million to eCompanies, which was purchased in 1997 for US $149,000. The peer-to-peer filesharing software [[Napster]] launches. [[ATG Stores]] launches to sell decorative items for the home online.
* 2000: The [[dot-com bust]].
* 2001: [[Alibaba Group|Alibaba.com]] achieved profitability in December 2001.
* 2002: [[eBay]] acquires [[PayPal]] for $1.5 billion.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web| url=http://investor.ebay.com/releasedetail.cfm?ReleaseID=84142|title=eBay acquires PayPal |publisher= eBay}}&lt;/ref&gt; Niche retail companies [[Wayfair]] and [[NetShops]] are founded with the concept of selling products through several targeted domains, rather than a central portal.
* 2003: [[Amazon.com]] posts first yearly profit.
* 2004: [[DHgate.com]], China's first online b2b transaction platform, is established, forcing other b2b sites to move away from the &quot;yellow pages&quot; model.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.zwgl.com.cn/article_info.asp?nid=4243|title=Diane Wang: Rounding up the &quot;Ant&quot; Heroes|publisher= Sino Foreign Management|accessdate=2011-09-03}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* 2007: [[Business.com]] acquired by [[R.H. Donnelley]] for $345 million.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://domainnamewire.com/2007/07/26/rh-donnelley-acquires-businesscom-for-345m/ |title=R.H. Donnelley Acquires Business.com for $345M |publisher=Domain Name Wire |date= |accessdate=2011-09-04}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* 2009: [[Zappos.com]] acquired by [[Amazon.com]] for $928 million.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web| url=http://techcrunch.com/2009/07/22/amazon-buys-zappos/|title=Press Release |publisher= TechCrunch}}&lt;/ref&gt; Retail Convergence, operator of private sale website RueLaLa.com, acquired by [[GSI Commerce]] for $180 million, plus up to $170 million in earn-out payments based on performance through 2012.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news| url=http://www.reuters.com/article/idUSBNG53538820091027/|title=Press Release |publisher= Reuters | date=October 27, 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* 2010: [[Groupon]] reportedly rejects a $6 billion offer from [[Google]]. Instead, the group buying websites plans to go ahead with an IPO in mid-2011.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web| url=http://www.msnbc.msn.com/id/40499923/ns/business-us_business/|title=Press Release |publisher=MSNBC}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* 2011: Online payment and recurring billing services provider [[Vindicia]], developer of the [[Cashbox|CashBox]] SaaS billing solution, is named the 20th fastest growing company in Silicon Valley. &lt;ref&gt;{{cite web| url=http://www.marketwatch.com/story/vindicia-named-a-fastest-growing-private-company-in-silicon-valley-for-third-consecutive-year-2011-10-14|title=Press Release |publisher=MarketWatch}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* 2011: US eCommerce and Online Retail sales projected to reach $197 billion, an increase of 12 percent over 2010.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web| url=http://www.fortune3.com/blog/2011/01/ecommerce-sales-2011/|title=Forecast of eCommerce Sales in 2011 and Beyond|publisher= Forrester Research, Inc.}}&lt;/ref&gt; Quidsi.com, parent company of [[Diapers.com]], acquired by [[Amazon.com]] for $500 million in cash plus $45 million in debt and other obligations.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web| url=http://www.marketwatch.com/story/amazon-buys-diaperscom-parent-in-545-mln-deal-2010-11-08/|title=Press Release|publisher= MarketWatch}}&lt;/ref&gt;  [[GSI Commerce]], a company specializing in creating, developing and running online shopping sites for [[brick and mortar business]]es, acquired by [[eBay]] for $2.4 billion.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web| url=http://techcrunch.com/2011/03/28/ebay-to-acquire-gsi-commerce-for-2-4-billion//|title=Press Release|publisher= TechCrunch}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Business applications==
[[File:Automated online assistant.png|thumb|200px|An example of an [[automated online assistant]] on a merchandising website.]]
Some common applications related to electronic commerce are the following:
* [[Document automation]] in [[supply chain]] and [[logistics]]
* Domestic and international [[payment system]]s
* [[Enterprise content management]]
* [[Group buying]]
* [[Automated online assistant]]s
* [[Instant messaging]]
* [[Newsgroups]]
* [[Online shopping]] and order tracking
* [[Online banking]]
* [[Online office suite]]s
* [[Shopping cart software]]
* [[Teleconferencing]]
* [[Electronic ticket]]s

==Governmental regulation==
{{globalize|United States|date=March 2011}}
In the United States, some electronic commerce activities are regulated by the [[Federal Trade Commission]] (FTC).  These activities include the use of commercial e-mails, online advertising and consumer [[privacy]].  The [[CAN-SPAM Act of 2003]] establishes national standards for direct marketing over e-mail. The [[Federal Trade Commission Act]] regulates all forms of advertising, including online advertising, and states that advertising must be truthful and non-deceptive.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web| url= http://www.ftc.gov/bcp/conline/pubs/buspubs/ruleroad.shtm |title= Advertising and Marketing on the Internet: Rules of the Road |publisher= [[Federal Trade Commission]]}}&lt;/ref&gt; Using its authority under Section 5 of the FTC Act, which prohibits unfair or deceptive practices, the FTC has brought a number of cases to enforce the promises in corporate privacy statements, including promises about the security of consumers’ personal information.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web| url= http://www.ftc.gov/privacy/privacyinitiatives/promises.html |title= Enforcing Privacy Promises: Section 5 of the FTC Act |publisher= [[Federal Trade Commission]]}}&lt;/ref&gt; As result, any corporate privacy policy related to e-commerce activity may be subject to enforcement by the FTC.

The Ryan Haight Online Pharmacy Consumer Protection Act of 2008, which came into law in 2008, amends the [[Controlled Substances Act]] to address [[Online pharmacy|online pharmacies]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web| url= http://www.govtrack.us/congress/bill.xpd?bill=h110-6353&amp;tab=summary |title= H.R. 6353: Ryan Haight Online Pharmacy Consumer Protection Act of 2008 |publisher= [[Govtrack]]}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Forms==
Contemporary electronic commerce involves everything from ordering &quot;digital&quot; content for immediate online consumption, to ordering conventional goods and services, to &quot;meta&quot; services to facilitate other types of electronic commerce.

On the institutional level, big corporations and financial institutions use the internet to exchange financial data to facilitate domestic and international business. Data integrity and security are very hot and pressing issues for electronic commerce.

==Global trends==
Business models across the world also continue to change drastically with the advent of eCommerce and this change is not just restricted to USA. Other countries are also contributing to the growth of eCommerce. For example, the United Kingdom  has the biggest e-commerce market in the world when measured by the amount spent per capita, even higher than the USA. The [[internet economy]] in UK is likely to grow by 10% between 2010 to 2015. This has led to changing dynamics for the advertising industry&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web| url=http://www.guardian.co.uk/technology/2010/oct/28/net-worth-100bn-uk/|title=news|publisher=Guardian.co.uk}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Amongst emerging economies, China's eCommerce presence continues to expand. With 384 million internet users,China's online shopping sales rose to $36.6 billion in 2009 and one of the reasons behind the huge growth has been the improved trust level for shoppers. The Chinese retailers have been able to help consumers feel more comfortable shopping online.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news| url=http://www.forbes.com/2010/01/18/china-internet-commerce-markets-equities-alibaba.html/|title= China's migration to eCommerce|newspaper=Forbes.com|date=January 18, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; E-Commerce has become an important tool for businesses worldwide not only to sell to customers but also to engage them.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |last1=Eisingerich |first1=Andreas B. |last2=Kretschmer |first2=Tobias |year=2008 |title=In E-Commerce, More is More |journal=Harvard Business Review |volume=86 (March) |pages=20–21 |url=http://hbr.org/2008/03/in-e-commerce-more-is-more/ar/1  }}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Impact on markets and retailers==
Economists have theorized that e-commerce ought to lead to intensified price [[competition (economics)|competition]], as it increases consumers' ability to gather information about products and prices. Research by four economists at the University of Chicago has found that the growth of online shopping has also affected industry structure in two areas that have seen significant growth in e-commerce, [[book selling|bookshops]] and [[travel agencies]]. Generally, larger firms have grown at the expense of smaller ones, as they are able to use [[economies of scale]] and offer lower prices. The lone exception to this pattern has been the very smallest category of bookseller, shops with between one and four employees, which appear to have withstood the trend.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title=Economics focus: The click and the dead|url=http://www.economist.com/node/16478931|newspaper=The Economist|date=July 3–9, 2010|page=78}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Distribution channels==
E-commerce has grown in importance as companies have adopted Pure-Click and [[Bricks and clicks|Brick and Click]] channel systems. We can distinguish between pure-click and brick and click channel system adopted by companies.

* Pure-Click companies are those that have launched a website without any previous existence as a firm. It is imperative that such companies must set up and operate their e-commerce websites very carefully. Customer service is of paramount importance.
* Brick and Click companies are those existing companies that have added an online site for e-commerce. Initially, Brick and Click companies were skeptical whether or not to add an online e-commerce channel for fear that selling their products might produce channel conflict with their off-line retailers, agents, or their own stores. However, they eventually added internet to their distribution channel portfolio after seeing how much business their online competitors were generating.

==See also==
{{div col|colwidth=20em}}
*[[Comparison of shopping cart software]]
*[[Digital economy]]
*[[Dot-com company]]
*[[e-Government]]
*[[Electronic money]]
*[[List of free and open source eCommerce software]]
*[[Multichannel ecommerce]]
*[[Non-store retailing]]
*[[Online marketplace]]
*[[Paid content]]
*[[Virtual economy]]
{{div col end}}

==Notes==
{{Reflist|30em}}

==References==
{{Refbegin|30em}}
* {{cite book
 | last = Chaudhury | first = Abijit
 | coauthors = Jean-Pierre Kuilboer
 | year = 2002
 | title = [[e-Business]] and e-Commerce Infrastructure
 | publisher = McGraw-Hill
 | isbn = 0-07-247875-6
 }}
*{{Cite journal
  | last1 = Frieden| first1 = Jonathan D.
  | author1-link = Jonathan D. Frieden
  | last2 = Roche| first2 = Sean Patrick
  | author2-link = Sean Patrick Roche
  | title = E-Commerce: Legal Issues of the Online Retailer in Virginia
  | journal = Richmond Journal of Law &amp; Technology
  | volume = 13
  | issue = 2
  | date = 2006-12-19
  | url = http://law.richmond.edu/jolt/v13i2/article5.pdf|format=PDF
  | postscript = &lt;!--None--&gt;}}
*{{Cite journal
  | last1 = Graham| first1 = Mark
  | title =  Warped Geographies of Development: The Internet and Theories of Economic Development
  | journal = Geography Compass
  | volume = 2
  | issue = 3
  | year = 2008
  | url = http://geospace.co.uk/files/compass.pdf|format=PDF
  | doi = 10.1111/j.1749-8198.2008.00093.x
  | page = 771
  | postscript = &lt;!--None--&gt;}}
* [http://www.usatoday.com/tech/news/2003-12-22-shoppers_x.htm Kessler, M. (2003). More shoppers proceed to checkout online. Retrieved January 13, 2004]
* {{cite book
 | last = Nissanoff | first = Daniel
 | year = 2006
 | title = '''FutureShop''': How the New Auction Culture Will Revolutionize the Way We Buy, Sell and Get the Things We Really Want
 | publisher = The Penguin Press
 | isbn = 1-59420-077-7
 | edition = Hardcover
 | pages = 246 pages
 }}
* {{cite book
 | last = Seybold | first = Pat
 | year = 2001
 | title = Customers.com
 | publisher = Crown Business Books (Random House)
 | isbn = 0-609-60772-3
 }}
* {{cite book
 | last = Miller | first = Roger
 | year = 2002
 | title = The Legal and E-Commerce Environment Today
 | publisher = Thomson Learning
 | isbn = 0-324-06188-9
 | edition = Hardcover
 | pages = 741 pages
 }}
* {{cite book
 | last = Kotler | first = Philip
 | year = 2009
 | title = Marketing Management
 | publisher = Pearson:Prentice-Hall
 | isbn = 978-81-317-1683-0
 }}
{{Refend}}

==External links==
&lt;!-- This is ''not'' the place to advertise your website. --&gt;
{{wikibooks|The Information Age}}
{{wikibooks-inline|E-Commerce and E-Business}}
*[http://business.gov/guides/e-commerce/ US Small Business Guide to E-Commerce Laws and Regulations]

{{DEFAULTSORT:Electronic Commerce}}
[[Category:Electronic commerce| ]]
[[Category:Information technology management]]
[[Category:Marketing]]
[[Category:Web applications]]
[[Category:Web development]]

[[ar:تجارة إلكترونية]]
[[az:Elektron ticarət]]
[[bg:Електронна търговия]]
[[cs:Elektronické obchodování]]
[[da:E-handel]]
[[de:Elektronischer Handel]]
[[et:E-kaubandus]]
[[el:Ηλεκτρονικό εμπόριο]]
[[es:Comercio electrónico]]
[[eu:Merkataritza elektroniko]]
[[fa:تجارت الکترونیک]]
[[fr:Commerce électronique]]
[[ko:전자 상업]]
[[hr:E-trgovina]]
[[id:Perdagangan elektronik]]
[[it:Commercio elettronico]]
[[he:מסחר אלקטרוני]]
[[kn:ಇ-ಕಾಮರ್ಸ್]]
[[lv:Elektroniskā komercija]]
[[lb:E-Commerce]]
[[lt:Elektroninė komercija]]
[[hu:E-kereskedelem]]
[[mk:Електронска трговија]]
[[mr:इलेक्ट्रॉनिक वाणिज्य]]
[[ms:Perdagangan elektronik]]
[[nl:Electronic commerce]]
[[ja:電子商取引]]
[[uz:Elektron tijorat]]
[[km:E-commerce]]
[[pl:Handel elektroniczny]]
[[pt:Comércio eletrônico]]
[[ro:Comerț electronic]]
[[ru:Электронная коммерция]]
[[sq:Biznesi elektronik]]
[[simple:Electronic commerce]]
[[sk:E-commerce]]
[[sl:Elektronsko poslovanje]]
[[sv:E-handel]]
[[ta:இலத்திரனியல் வர்த்தகம்]]
[[th:การพาณิชย์อิเล็กทรอนิกส์]]
[[tr:Elektronik ticaret]]
[[uk:Електронна комерція]]
[[vi:Thương mại điện tử]]
[[zh-yue:網上買賣]]
[[zh:电子商务]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
