<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="21383107" ns="0" title="List of Coronation Street characters (2005)"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{DISPLAYTITLE:List of ''Coronation Street'' characters (2005)}}
{{CSMinor}}
{{-}}

==Jessie Jackson==
{{Infobox soap character 2
|series=[[Coronation Street]]
|name=Jessie Jackson|
portrayer=Nailah Cumberbatch|
| years 2005-2006
| first = 28 February 2005
| last=27 January 2006|
occupation=[[Stewardess]]|
cousins=[[Joanne Jackson (Coronation Street)|Joanne Jackson]]|
}}

'''Jessie Jackson''' is played by actress Nailah Cumberbatch. She arrives at ''Underworld'' with her &quot;twin sister&quot; [[Joanne Jackson (Coronation Street)|Joanne]] to replace departing machinist [[Sonia Marshall]] and is the more outgoing one of the two. In 2006, [[Danny Baldwin]] sacks Jessie after he catches her dancing on the tables, and she subsequently seeks employment as a stewardess and leaves the Street. Her &quot;twin sister&quot; is later revealed to be her cousin.
{{-}}

==Joanne Jackson==
{{Infobox soap character 2
| series = Coronation Street
| name = Joanne Jackson
| first = 20 April 
| years = 2005 - 2007
| last = 20 July 2007
| born = [[5th January]] [[1987]]
| cousins = [[Jessie Jackson]]
| occupation = Machinist
| portrayer = [[Zaraah Abrahams]]
}}
 
'''Joanne Jackson''' was played by the actress [[Zaraah Abrahams]]. Joanne arrived at Underworld with her &quot;twin sister&quot; [[Jessie Jackson|Jessie]] and proceeded to cause much amusement by claiming to be identical despite the obvious difference in appearance. Joanne was the shyer of the two and lacks confidence where men are concerned. Her crush, and subsequent date, with [[Nathan Harding]] came to nothing after she was left feeling stupid and embarrassed about having a make over for someone who wasn't really interested in her.

Following his nasty break up with [[Leanne Battersby]], [[Jamie Baldwin]] was keen to ask Joanne out on a date. After a disastrous date the two realised that they did enjoy each others company and shared a kiss. This was followed by the promise to see each other again (unfortunately this was ruined by Jamie's problems with his alcoholic mother, [[Carol Baldwin|Carol]] and they decided against starting a new romance so soon after his break up with Leanne). She was also gutted when Jessie was sacked from Underworld and left to become an air hostess. When [[Kelly Crabtree]] took Joanne under her wing, Kelly's obsessed &quot;friend&quot; [[Becky Grainger]] threatened her, scaring Joanne half to death. When Kelly was set up for stealing at the factory by unhinged Becky, Joanne was the only person who believed Kelly was innocent and was instrumental in convincing the other factory workers that it was Becky, not Kelly who was to blame. For most of 2006, Joanne dated [[Adam Barlow]]. However, she kissed her new factory boss, [[Liam Connor]] (who, incidentally, Adam sold his half of the factory to) and had a fling with him, despite Kelly being sure that Liam fancied her, she soon dumped Adam with a [[short message service|text message]]. In April 2007 she revealed to [[Hayley Cropper]] that she was an illegal immigrant, brought over from [[Liberia]] at the age of 8, and that her &quot;twin sister&quot; is in fact her cousin, and was soon arrested as immigration officers raided the Factory. In June 2007, Joanne was released from [[Immigration]] Detention and resumed her job at underworld for around two weeks, until [[Carla Connor]], the majority owner of underworld, fired her claiming that the factory is over-staffed and that Joanne was the most recent employee, regardless of the fact she had worked at the factory for over three years previously. Joanne later [[blackmail]]ed [[Carla Connor|Carla]] and [[Liam Connor|Liam]] by threatening to take them to a tribunal for unfair dismissal and sexual harassment.


==Jean Harris==
{{Infobox soap character 2      
|series=[[Coronation Street]]   
|name= Jean Harris
|portrayer= Sue Wallace
|first = 21 March 2005
|last = 25 March 2005
|classification = Former; guest
|introducer = 
|years = 2005
|sons = [[Tommy Harris (Coronation Street)|Tommy Harris]]
|granddaughters = [[Katy Harris]]
|grandsons = [[Craig Harris (Coronation Street)|Craig Harris]]
}}       
'''Jean Harris''' is the mother of Tommy Harris. Jean arrives to attend Tommy's funeral in 2005 and is angered to discover that he is being buried as opposed to his wishes of being cremated.

{{-}}

==Nathan Harding==
{{Infobox soap character 2
|series=[[Coronation Street]]
|name= Nathan Harding|
portrayer=[[Ray Fearon]]|
occupation= [[Mechanic]]|
first =1 April 2005 |
last = 19 July 2006|
romances = [[Tracy Barlow]] (2005)&lt;br&gt;[[Frankie Baldwin]] (2006)|
}}

'''Nathan Harding''' is played by [[Ray Fearon]]. He first appears in 2005 when [[Kevin Webster]] is looking for a new mechanic, following the death of [[Tommy Harris (soap character)|Tommy Harris]]. Nathan leaves the job after breaking up with his girlfriend [[Frankie Baldwin]] largely to do with the fact her ex-husband, [[Danny Baldwin|Danny]] is still in the picture. In his final scene he punches Danny as he leaves the cobbles. He had previously romanced factory machinist [[Joanne Jackson (Coronation Street)|Joanne Jackson]] as well as [[Tracy Barlow]], while he also enjoyed a brief flirtation with hairdresser [[Maria Sutherland]] in the Rovers. His fiery temperament is revealed when he almost blinds [[Ashley Peacock]] when they argue over their women while giving him boxing lessons.
{{-}}

==Louise Hazel==
{{Infobox soap character 2
| series     = [[Coronation Street]]
| name       = Louise Hazel
| first      = 1 April 2005
| last       = 12 June 2005
| residence  = [[Ireland]]
| romances   = [[Steve McDonald (Coronation Street)|Steve McDonald]] (2005)
| portrayer  = [[Nora Jane Noone]]
}}

'''Louise Hazel''' meets [[Steve McDonald (Coronation Street)|Steve McDonald]] on the Red Rec. He is immediately attracted to her and when she says she's going into town he organises a free taxi. Steve is delighted the taxi driver gives him a note from Louise with her phone number on it. On 3 April 2005, Louise enjoys a drink with Steve, much to the indignation of his ex [[Tracy Barlow]]. Louise is unfazed by Tracy and tells her to move on and leave her and Steve alone. Steve keeps Louise waiting in the pub while he comforts Tracy following the sudden death of her father [[Ray Langton]]. When he finally arrives at the Rovers and convinces Louise to go home with him and the couple then sleep together. On 13 April 2005, Louise shares a sad farewell with Steve as she has to return to Ireland. Louise returns to the Street on 12 June 2005, as she is visiting relatives and calls to Steve, who is delighted. However, Tracy threatens Louise telling her to leave Steve alone.
{{-}}

== Keith Appleyard ==
{{Infobox soap character 2
|series=[[Coronation Street]]
|name = Keith Appleyard
|portrayer =[[Ian Redford (actor)|Ian Redford]]
|born=
|first=4 April 2005
|last=30 July 2006
|home = [[Bournemouth]]
|years = 2005-06
|occupation=Paper deliverer/Taxidermist
| daughters = [[Angela Harris (Coronation Street)|Angela Harris]]
| grandsons  = [[Craig Harris (Coronation Street)|Craig Harris]]
| granddaughters = [[Katy Harris]]
}}

'''Keith Appleyard''' is played by [[Ian Redford (actor)|Ian Redford]]. Keith is [[Angela Harris (Coronation Street)|Angela Harris]]'s father. When she and her family live in Sheffield, she witnesses a murder. Keith persuades Angela to tell the truth and testify at the trial, which results in their move to Weatherfield under the [[witness protection]] scheme. They are also given a new name - Nelson - but don't use it for long. 

Keith first appears in 2005 to help Angela after her husband [[Tommy Harris (Coronation Street)|Tommy]] dies. He stays to look after his grandchildren [[Katy Harris|Katy]] and [[Craig Harris (Coronation Street character)|Craig]] after Angela is arrested for Tommy's murder. Katy (the real killer) commits suicide, unable to handle the guilt, and Angela is imprisoned for helping Katy cover up the crime. Keith stays with Craig in Coronation Street, rather than insist Craig join him in Sheffield, feeling Craig has suffered enough - plus, Weatherfield is closer than Sheffield to where Angela is in prison.

After moving in, Keith dates hairdresser [[Audrey Roberts]], who is his opposite in many ways. Keith is always watching the pennies and takes on a paper round to earn some extra money. His hobbies include [[taxidermy]].

Keith is widowed, his wife having died between 2003 and 2005. Angela telephones her mother on [[Christmas Day]] 2002, and visits her in September 2003, but she has died by the time Keith arrives in 2005.

After he and Audrey end things as they are so different, Keith became enemies with builder [[Charlie Stubbs]]. Charlie bills Keith for repairing the leak on the roof but Keith refuses to pay the bill, feeling Charlie has overcharged. In revenge, Charlie removes the roof tiles, insisting he will replace them when Keith pays his bill. Keith rings the police but the police say they can't help as it isn't a police matter. Keith is delighted to see Charlie replacing the tiles, thinking that he has won, until Charlie reveals that he is his new landlord. Keith is horrified and says that the landlord would have told him but Charlie says that he asked the former landlord to let him do that. Charlie's girlfriend, [[Tracy Barlow]], is delighted. She thinks, when Charlie tells Keith and Craig that he wants them out, that he intends to live there. 

Keith decides that he and Craig will move to [[Sheffield]] but Craig doesn't want to leave Coronation Street as his girlfriend, [[Rosie Webster|Rosie]], lives there too. Initially Keith agrees to stay but after an angina attack, he is told by the doctor that it is a warning and things have to change. Keith tells Craig that they are moving to [[Bournemouth]] with Keith's sister, Marjorie.
Craig is determined that he won't leave the street but Keith and Rosie's mother [[Sally Webster|Sally]] persuade him and they leave.
 
Keith later returns to the Street when Craig runs away from Bournemouth and refuses to return there.
{{-}}

==Mr. Wong==
{{Infobox soap character 2
| series     = [[Coronation Street]]
| name       = Mr. Wong
| first      = 6 May 2005
| last       = 23 December 2005
| years      = 2005
| occupation = Former chip shop owner
| portrayer  = [[Daryl Kwan]]
}}
'''Mr. Wong''' is the owner of the chip shop on Rosamund Street, who hires [[Cilla Brown]] and [[Yana Lumb]] to work for him. He speaks very limited English and is frequently seen arguing with Cilla.
{{-}}

==Diggory Compton==
{{Infobox soap character 2
| series = [[Coronation Street]]
| name = Diggory Compton
| image = 
| caption = 
| first = 9 May 2005
| last = 17 July 2006
| years = 2005–06
| creator = Sue Pritchard
| born = {{Birth date and age|1940|3|12|df=y}}
| death = 
| classification = [[List of past Coronation Street characters#C|Former; regular]]
| sisters = [[Pam Hobsworth]]
| daughters = [[Molly Compton|Molly Dobbs]]
| grandsons = [[Jack Dobbs]]
| occupation = [[Baker]]
| portrayer = [[Eric Potts]]
}}
'''Diggory Compton''' is played by [[Eric Potts]].

When he arrives in Weatherfield with his daughter [[Molly Dobbs|Molly]], Diggory opens the local bakery shop at the end of the street. He tries wooing [[Liz McDonald]] by inviting her to a Christmas dinner party, however she ended up meeting her future husband, drummer [[Vernon Tomlin]] at the event. During his time in [[Weatherfield]], Diggory befriends [[Mike Baldwin (Coronation Street)|Mike Baldwin]]. Diggory leaves Weatherfield in July 2006 after his business fails.

Molly visits him in 2008 after falling out with her fiance [[Tyrone Dobbs]]. On 5 January 2009, Molly receives a call from the hospital that Diggory's appendix has burst. Several days later, it is revealed Diggory will recover but he will ultimately miss Molly and Tyrone's wedding due to being hospitalised for a week.

In December 2010, Diggory is informed by telephone that Molly has died in the tram crash caused by an explosion at the Joinery Bar. Diggory's sister [[Pam Hobsworth]] tells Molly's former lover [[Kevin Webster]] the heartbreak of having to inform Diggory of his daughter's death saying she is wondering what words to use to break the news to him. Diggory is not seen at Molly's funeral as he is reportedly too ill to attend.
{{-}}

==Yana Lumb==
{{Infobox soap character 2
| series     = [[Coronation Street]]
| name       = Yana Lumb
| years= 2005, 2006, 2007
| first      = 11 May 2005
| last       = 16 July 2007
| occupation = Former chip shop worker
| romances   = [[Les Battersby-Brown]]
| siblings   = Mr. Lumb
| portrayer  = [[Jayne Bickerton]]
}}
'''Yana Lumb''' is [[Cilla Battersby-Brown]]'s best friend and in a way is usually involved in Cilla's scams and plots. Yana works with Cilla in Wong's chip shop on Rosamund Street until its closure in 2007. 

Yana ends up going on Cilla's honeymoon with her instead of Cilla's husband [[Les Battersby-Brown]], who is in trouble with Cilla for trashing all the wedding presents at the reception.

Yana takes pity on Les in late November 2006, when he reveals his suspicions of Cilla having an affair. Yana is shocked that Cilla won't confide in her and feels sorry for a miserable Les, they become more and more attracted to each other and eventually can't resist each other. Yana engages in an affair with Les and sleeps with him in the living room, only to be seen by Cilla's son, [[Chesney Battersby-Brown]].  Cilla soon finds out about the affair, and pretends she has cancer. She forces Yana and Les to sit in a bathtub of mushy peas on Christmas Eve to raise money for Cilla's holiday fund to [[Florida]]. Before she leaves, she revealed the truth.

Returning in December, Cilla slaps Yana but forgives her. Her last appearance is in July 2007 when she and Cilla are both fired from the takeaway.
{{-}}

==Carol Baldwin==
{{Infobox soap character 2
|series=[[Coronation Street]]
|name=Carol Baldwin
|portrayer=Lynne Pearson
|years=2005–06
|first= 15 May 2005
|last= 15 January 2006
|home = [[Birmingham]]
|husband = [[Danny Baldwin]] (1979–86)
|sons =[[Jamie Baldwin]]
|romances = [[Eric Talford]] (2005)
}}
'''Carol Baldwin''' (née '''Saunders''') was played by Lynne Pearson.

Carol is the first wife of [[Danny Baldwin|Danny]], and the mother of [[Jamie Baldwin|Jamie]]. While she is still married to Danny, he is sleeping with her son's babysitter [[Frankie Baldwin|Frankie]]. Carol is oblivious to this, as she completely trusted Frankie; she only finds out when Danny leaves her to marry Frankie, taking Jamie with him.

Jamie doesn't see Carol for many years; he is raised by Danny and Frankie. In 2005, he tracks down Carol to [[Birmingham]] and decides to pay her a visit. It soon becomes clear that past events have affected Carol's life very badly; she has never re-married, is living in a run down flat, and is an [[alcoholic]] with no job or money. Jamie becomes very concerned for his mother and visits her many times in Birmingham; she appears in [[Weatherfield]] for the first time for Jamie's 25th birthday party, much to the horror of her ex-husband, Danny, and his wife, Frankie.

Carol appears regularly for months, and when Danny begins an affair with his girlfriend, [[Leanne Battersby|Leanne]], Carol was the one who tells Jamie.

When Frankie and Danny split up, Carol moves in with them to be closer to Jamie and he makes her promise to give up alcohol. However, in January 2006, Jamie and Frankie throw Carol out when she accuses them of sleeping together (which is somewhat prophetic, as later that year Jamie and Frankie pursue an affair), and her drinking continues. 

In 2007, it becomes apparent that Carol has ditched the drink, and is now engaged. On September 25, 2007, Jamie and his ex-girlfriend, [[Violet Wilson]], attend Carol's wedding.
{{-}}

==Lloyd Mullaney==
{{Main|Lloyd Mullaney}}

==Viv Baldwin==
{{Infobox soap character 2
|series=[[Coronation Street]]
| name = Viv Baldwin
| first = 29 July 2005
| last = 18 December 2006 
| home = [[London]]
| classification = Former; recurring
| years= 2005, 2006
| sons  = [[Danny Baldwin]]
| romances = [[Mike Baldwin (Coronation Street)|Mike Baldwin]] (1961)
| husband = Harry Baldwin (?-2005) 
| grandsons = [[Jamie Baldwin]]&lt;br&gt;[[Warren Baldwin]] 
| occupation = [[Retired]]
| portrayer = [[Patricia Brake]]
}}

'''Vivian &quot;Viv&quot; Baldwin''' is the mother of [[Danny Baldwin]]. She is first seen on the street in July 2005, following her husband Harry's death and later revealing to her brother-in-law [[Mike Baldwin (Coronation Street)|Mike]] that he is in fact Danny's biological father, not Harry.

Viv makes a reappearance in Weatherfield at Christmas 2005, when the family go out to Christmas dinner.

In December 2006, she returns enquiring about her son's disappearance, only to find out the truth about her grandson [[Jamie Baldwin|Jamie]]'s affair with his former stepmother [[Frankie Baldwin]]. After finding this, Viv storms back home to [[London]]. 
{{-}}

==Phil Nail==
{{Infobox soap character 2
|series=[[Coronation Street]]
| name = Phil Nail
| portrayer = [[Clive Russell]]
| first = 15 August 2005
| last = 27 March 2006
| born =
| occupation = [[Reflexologist]]
| romances = [[Gail Platt]]
}}

'''Philip &quot;Phil&quot; Nail''', is played by Scottish actor [[Clive Russell]],&lt;ref&gt;http://www.sundaymail.co.uk/news/tm_objectid=16559264&amp;method=full&amp;siteid=64736&amp;headline=after-20-years-in-the-business-corrie-s-given-me-street-cred--name_page.html&lt;/ref&gt; Phil is a [[reflexologist]], and works at the Medical Centre on [[Rosamund Street]] as a reflexologist. He quickly begins a relationship with receptionist [[Gail Platt]]. 

Phil is very interested in the Platt family's experience with [[Richard Hillman]] because he is undertaking a Criminology course. Gail trusts Phil; she even allows him to record interviews with her children about their experiences with Richard.

Gail's son [[David Platt (Coronation Street)|David Platt]] does not like Phil; in fact, he despises him knowing that Phil is only wanting to know about Richard Hillman and that he doesn't care about Gail's children. He even begins a campaign to stop the relationship between Phil and his mother. One such example is when Phil's hand is badly injured when David intentionally slams it with a car bootlid. Another is where Phil pins David up against a wall and threatens him. David has become unhappy ever since his father [[Martin Platt|Martin]] has left and he does not like another man in the house telling him what to do, as that is his dad's job.

Eventually Phil leaves the street after Gail discovers that Phil attacked David.

Phil is a suspect when Gail began receiving a series of hoax letters claiming to be from the deceased Richard in 2006. The culprit is later revealed to have been David.
{{-}}

==Zack==
{{Infobox soap character 2
|series=[[Coronation Street]]
| name = Zack
| first = 22 August 2005
| last = 21 September 2005 
| occupation = [[Psychiatrist]]
| portrayer = [[Ralph Ineson]]
}}

'''Zack''' is a psychiatrist who treats [[Shelley Unwin]] when her anxiety overtakes so much of her life that she is rarely able to leave her own room. Zack helps Shelley slowly go back to the outside world, but Shelley's boyfriend [[Charlie Stubbs]] resents Zack's efforts to help, and eventually convinces Shelley to stop seeing him. Shelley progresses far enough that she manages to dump Charlie moments before she is to become his wife. After getting away from Charlie, she calls Zack to tell him the news. He says that he is proud of her, and both agree to continue therapy until she is fully recovered.
{{-}}

==Molly Dobbs==
{{Main|Molly Dobbs}}

==Ronnie Clayton==
{{Infobox soap character 2
|series=[[Coronation Street]]
|image=  
|caption= Ronnie Clayton as she appeared in 2006.
|years=2005-06
|first=3 October 2005
|last=11 June 2006
|name = Veronica Clayton
|portrayer = [[Emma Stansfield]]
|born =
|home = Prison
|occupation = [[Taxicab driver]]
|husband = Jimmy Clayton
}}

'''Veronica &quot;Ronnie&quot; Clayton''' is played by [[Emma Stansfield]]. Ronnie, as she likes to be known, first appears on the show in late October 2005. She is formerly married to [[gangster]] Jimmy Clayton and works for his cab firm. In an attempt to escape his [[bullying]] nature, she leaves him and starts working under [[Steve McDonald (Coronation Street character)|Steve McDonald]] at ''Streetcars''. Steve and Ronnie start a relationship, but Ronnie's presence puts the entire Streetcars workforce under risk from the vengeful Jimmy. Ronnie refuses to back down and go back to him, with Steve supporting her.

Jimmy is eventually able to trick Ronnie into driving out to a deserted farm. He holds her at gunpoint, and she agrees to give their marriage another try when he nearly kills her and Steve. [[Lloyd Mullaney]] rescues them, but Ronnie is then distant with Steve since the ordeal. She moves out of his house and into a flat of her own to show her independence.

On 31 May 2006, after having a row with Steve, Ronnie calls Steve on her mobile phone whilst driving, and not concentrating on the road, runs over an elderly man and kills him. Instead of calling an ambulance, Ronnie drives away. The next day Ronnie sees in the paper the news about the dead man and feels even more guilty. She tries to blame Steve for the accident, but is eventually caught and arrested.

[[Sarah Manners]] was originally offered the part of Ronnie, but turned it down because of her other work offers. Emma Stansfield was only contracted until Christmas 2005, but had her contract extended for another 12 months because her character initially proved popular. She was then axed by new producer [[Steve Frost]].
{{-}}

==Amber Kalirai==
{{Main|Amber Kalirai}}

==Ravinder Kalirai==
{{Infobox soap character 2
| name = Ravinder Kalirai
| series=[[Coronation Street]]
| portrayer= [[Mina Anwar]]
| first = 9 November 2005
| last = 26 May 2006
| years = 2005-06 
| classification = Former; recurring
| home = [[Finland]]
| daughters = [[Amber Kalirai]]
| romances  = [[Dev Alahan]] (1990)&lt;br&gt;Martin Bellingham (2003&amp;mdash;)
 }}
'''Ravinder Kalirai''' is the mother of [[Amber Kalirai]], who first appears in 2005 and tells her the truth about her father [[Dev Alahan]]. During the summer of 2006, Ravinder meets a new man and decides relocate to [[Finland]] with him. After falling out with Dev, Amber goes to stay with Ravinder for several weeks in November 2008.
{{-}}

==Billy Brown==
{{Infobox soap character 2
|series=[[Coronation Street]]|
name=Billy Brown|
portrayer=Jay Martin|
appeared= 31 October  2005|
years = 2005 |
mother=[[Cilla Battersby-Brown]]|
halfsisters= [[Fiz Brown]]&lt;br&gt;Unnamed|
halfbrothers=[[Chesney Battersby-Brown]]|
nieces = [[Hope Stape]]|
classification = Former; guest|
occupation=Soldier
}}
'''William &quot;Billy&quot; Brown ''' is the eldest son of [[Cilla Battersby-Brown]], who attends her wedding to [[Les Battersby]] on 31 October 2005 and informs his mother that he is joining the army. Billy is more recently mentioned when younger brother [[Chesney Battersby-Brown|Chesney]] runs away from home to visit him in 2009.
{{-}}

==Nicolette Seddon==
{{Infobox soap character 2
|series=[[Coronation Street]]|
name=Nicolette Seddon|
portrayer=Natalie Richards|
first= 28 November 2005|
last= 5 December 2005|
born= 1990
| father = Paul Seddon
| mother = Suzanne Seddon
| cousins = [[Sally Webster]] (once removed)&lt;br&gt;[[Gina Seddon]] (once removed)
| uncles = Eddie Seddon (great)
| classification = Former; guest
}}
'''Nicolette Seddon''' is the daughter of [[Sally Webster]]'s cousin, Paul. This is revealed when Sally's daughter [[Sophie Webster|Sophie]] brings her home one day as a new friend and they mention they had traced their family trees and discovered they were related. Sally sees Nicolette as a bad influence on Sophie and later visits Nicolette's house - when she discovers that Nicolette's father is successful and wealthy, much to her chagrin. After a heated exchange with her parents, Sally decides not to keep in touch with that branch of the Seddon family tree.
{{-}}

==Vernon Tomlin==
{{Main|Vernon Tomlin}}

==Eric Talford==
{{Infobox soap character 2
|series=[[Coronation Street]]|
name=Eric Talford|
portrayer=[[Tony Slattery]]|
first= 11 December 2005|
last= 19 February 2006|
occupation=Bookmaker|
romances = [[Carol Baldwin]] (2005)|
}}
'''Eric Talford''' is the owner of the bookies on Rosamund Street who first appears in December 2005 and becomes the boss and love interest of [[Carol Baldwin]]. 
{{-}}

==Freda Burgess==
{{Infobox soap character 2
|series=[[Coronation Street]]|
name=Freda Burgess|
portrayer=Ali Briggs|
|image=
| years = 2005, 2006, 2009–10
| first=8 August 2005
| last=11 January 2010
| occupation=
| uncles=[[Ernest Bishop]]
}}
'''Freda Burgess''' is the deaf niece of the late Ernest Bishop. In August 2005, Freda came to visit her aunt Emily, but got a frosty reception from Emily's lodger Norris Cole, who thought she had only come for money from Emily but was impressed with her ability to lip-read. Freda helped Emily when she fell down the stairs and sprained her ankle, but left Coronation Street when she had had enough of Norris and the way he was treating her.

In March 2006, Freda visited to support Emily, who had just found out that her friend Ed Jackson was the man who shot Ernie dead in 1978. Emily was suffering a crisis of faith as she couldn't bring herself to forgive Ed or go to church, where she would have to face Ed as well as God.

In July 2009, Freda arrived back on the Street. She revealed to Emily that she was engaged, but her fiancée was in prison. She took a dislike to Emily's new friend Ramsay Clegg (Norris' half-brother) because she found him annoying - he was always too eager to please. Norris was thrilled, as he disliked his brother as well and felt they both had something in common. After staying a few days, Freda left again.

Freda turned up again in November after losing her job. She revealed to Emily that the woman she was working for was horrible to her, so she got her revenge by stealing her prosthetic leg. Emily didn't like this and said it was theft. However, Graeme Proctor found this amusing. She then got Graeme to dispose of the leg, as it was reported in the paper and she didn't want to get caught for theft.

She started entering competitions with Norris, and they both won £1,000 pounds. They split it equally and Freda left to put the £500 pounds on a house for herself.

== References ==
&lt;references /&gt;

{{Coronation Street}}

[[Category:Coronation Street characters|#, 2005]]
[[Category:Lists of minor fictional characters|Coronation Street, 2005]]
[[Category:Fictional characters introduced in 2005|*, Coronation Street]]
[[Category:2005 in British television]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
