<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="21401715" ns="0" title="Wikiversity"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Infobox Website
| name         = Wikiversity
| logo         = [[File:Wikiversity-logo-Snorky.svg|135px|Wikiversity logo.]]
| screenshot   = [[File:Wikiversity screenshot 2008.png|250px|Detail of the Wikiversity multilingual portal main page.]]
| caption      = Screenshot of wikiversity.org home page
| url          = [http://www.wikiversity.org/ www.wikiversity.org]
| commercial   = No
| location     = [[Miami, Florida|Miami]], [[Florida]]
| type         = Educational, self study
| language     = Multilingual
| registration = Optional
| owner        = [[Wikimedia Foundation]]
| author       = Wikimedia community
| slogan       = &quot;set learning free&quot;
| alexa        = {{decrease}} 25,196 ({{as of|2011|11|2|alt=November 2011}})&lt;ref name=&quot;alexa&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url= http://www.alexa.com/siteinfo/wikiversity.org |title= Wikiversity.org Site Info | publisher= [[Alexa Internet]] |accessdate= 2011-11-02 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;!--Updated monthly by OKBot.--&gt;
| launch date  = August 15, 2006
}}

'''Wikiversity''' is a [[Wikimedia Foundation]] project,&lt;ref&gt;[http://wikimania2006.wikimedia.org/wiki/Opening_Plenary_%28transcript%29#Wikiversity_.2826:35.29 Welcome speech], Jimbo Wales, Wikimania 2006 ([http://www.supload.com/listen?s=SI0OG2vN04i audio])&lt;/ref&gt; which supports learning communities, their learning materials, and resulting activities. It differs from more structured projects such as [[Wikipedia]] in that it instead offers a series of tutorials, or courses, for the fostering of learning, rather than formal content.

== History ==

{{Expand section|date=June 2008}}
Wikiversity's [[beta software|beta]] phase officially began on August 15, 2006 with the [[v:|English language Wikiversity]]. Before it was created in [[Wikibooks]], another project by the [[Wikimedia Foundation]].

== Project details ==

Wikiversity is a center for the creation of and use of free learning materials, and the provision of [[v:Portal:Learning Projects|learning activities]]. Wikiversity is one of many wikis used in educational contexts,&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.itdl.org/Journal/Jan_07/Jan_07.pdf#page=19 &quot;Wikis and Wikipedia as a Teaching Tool&quot;] by Piotr Konieczny; International Journal of Instructional Technology and Distance Learning;January 2007, Vol. 4, No. 1.&lt;/ref&gt; as well as many initiatives that are creating free and [[open educational resources]].

The primary priorities and goals for Wikiversity are to:
*Create and host a range of free-content, multilingual learning materials/resources, for all age groups in all languages.
*Host scholarly/learning projects and communities that support these materials.&lt;ref&gt;[http://en.wikiversity.org/wiki/Wikiversity:Wikiversity_project_proposal Approved Wikiversity project proposal], Wikiversity&lt;/ref&gt;

The Wikiversity e-Learning model places emphasis on &quot;learning groups&quot; and [[Experiential learning|&quot;learning by doing&quot;]]. Wikiversity's motto and slogan is &quot;set learning free&quot;,&lt;ref&gt;[http://en.wikiversity.org/wiki/Wikiversity:Learning Wikiversity:Learning], Wikiversity&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://en.wikiversity.org/wiki/Portal:Education/Wikiversity_model Wikiversity learning model], Wikiversity&lt;/ref&gt; indicating that groups/communities of Wikiversity participants will engage in learning projects. Learning is facilitated through collaboration on projects that are detailed, outlined, summarized or results reported by editing Wikiversity pages. Wikiversity learning projects include collections of [[wiki|wiki webpages]] concerned with the exploration of a particular topic.&lt;ref&gt;[http://en.wikiversity.org/wiki/Portal:Learning_Projects Wikiversity learning projects portal], Wikiversity&lt;/ref&gt; Wikiversity participants are encouraged to express their learning goals, and the Wikiversity community collaborates to develop learning activities and projects to accommodate those goals. However, as the project is still in its early stages,&lt;ref&gt;[http://chronicle.com/free/2005/12/2005121601t.htm Wikipedia, the Free Online Encyclopedia, Ponders a New Entity: Wikiversity] by Andrea L. Foster; The Chronicle of Higher Education; December 16, 2005.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.pcworld.com/article/id,135533-pg,1/article.html Wikiversity Gains Momentum] at [[PC World (magazine)|PC World]]&lt;/ref&gt; its learning model is still in development.

Learning resources are developed by an individual or groups, either on their own initiative, or as part of a learning project.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.editlib.org/index.cfm?fuseaction=Reader.ViewAbstract&amp;paper_id=24981 &quot;One Laptop Per Teacher: Content and Curriculum for (in-service) Teacher Training&quot;] by Ian Kennedy, Delia Pass and Roxan Cadir; Proceedings of Society for Information Technology and Teacher Education International Conference 2007; pp. 2564–2569&lt;/ref&gt; Wikiversity resources include teaching aids, lesson plans, curricula, links to off-site resources, course notes, example and problem sets, computer simulations, reading lists, and other as devised by participants&amp;nbsp;– but do not include final polished  textbooks. Texts useful to others are hosted at [[Wikibooks]] for update and maintenance.&lt;ref&gt;[http://en.wikiversity.org/wiki/Wikiversity:What_Wikiversity_is_not Wikiversity:What Wikiversity is not], Wikiversity&lt;/ref&gt; Learning groups with interests in each subject area create a web of resources that form the basis of discussions and activities at Wikiversity. Learning resources can be used by  educators outside of Wikiversity for their own purposes, under the terms of the [[GFDL]] and a [[Creative Commons]] license (like [[Wikipedia]]).

== Languages ==

There are currently thirteen language Wikiversities&amp;nbsp;– Arabic, Czech, English, Finnish, French, German, Greek, Italian,  Japanese, Portuguese, Russian, Spanish, and Swedish; Wikiversity projects in other languages are being developed at the [http://beta.wikiversity.org &quot;beta&quot;] multilingual hub.

For newly established specific language Wikiversities to move out of the initial exploratory &quot;beta&quot; phase, the new Wikiversity community must establish policies governing research activities. Wikiversity may act as a repository of research carried out by the [[m:Wikimedia Research Network|Wikimedia Research Network]], or others who are involved in wiki-based, or other research. Wikiversity hosts original research in addition to secondary research, unless a specific language group decides upon no research.  It is expected that researchers will respect and update guidelines for appropriate research through a community consensus process.&lt;ref&gt;[http://beta.wikiversity.org/wiki/Wikiversity:Scope_of_research/Policy/En Scope of research on Wikiversity (in development)], Multingual Wikiversity hub&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://beta.wikiversity.org/wiki/Wikiversity:Research_guidelines/En Wikiversity research guidelines (in development)], Multilingual Wikiversity hub&lt;/ref&gt;

== See also ==

* [[Wikipedia:Wikipedia Signpost/2008-05-09/Wikiversity interview|Wikiversity interview]]
* [[OpenLearn]]&amp;nbsp;— a project of [[Open University]] to deliver free educational resources
* [[WikiEducator]]

== References ==

{{Reflist}}

== External links ==
{{External links|date=July 2011}}
{{wikinews|Wikimedia Netherlands 2007 conference held on wikis and education}}
* The [http://www.wikiversity.org/ Wikiversity multilingual portal]&amp;nbsp;– with links to all Wikiversity sites, with exception of the [[v:ar:الصفحة الرئيسية|Arabic edition]] for the time being.
* The [[v:Main Page|English language Wikiversity]] (in [[Software testing#Alpha, Beta, and Gamma testing|beta]] phase)
* &quot;[http://google.com/unclesam?q=cache:6DniVqOwftAJ:www.courts.mo.gov/file.asp%3Fid%3D3311+wikiversity&amp;hl=en&amp;ct=clnk&amp;cd=10&amp;gl=us Resources for Professional Development]&quot; Prepared for the Fall conference of the Missouri Juvenile Justice Association, October—2006, Office of State Courts Administrator, Division of Judicial Education P48.
* [http://64.233.179.104/scholar?hl=en&amp;lr=&amp;q=cache:GxPqQpQxXEUJ:jephc.com/uploads/Manuscript990221Web3.pdf+wikiversity &quot;Conference Review&quot;] by Peter Mulholland; Journal of Emergency Primary Health Care; Vol.4, Issue 4, 2006. ([http://jephc.com/uploads/Manuscript990221Web3.pdf pdf version])
* Topps, D. &quot;Sharing medical educational resources using free and open-source software.&quot; in 7th Annual WONCA Rural Health Conference&amp;nbsp;– Transforming Rural Practice Through Education. 2006. Seattle, WA, USA.
* [http://64.233.179.104/scholar?hl=en&amp;lr=&amp;q=cache:pnj7HTazn44J:www.wwmr.us/Access-VanHook.pdf+wikiversity &quot;Access to Global Learning: A Matter of Will&quot;] by Steven R. Van Hook; Education Resources Information Center; (ERIC Document No. ED492804); April 27, 2006.
* [http://64.233.179.104/scholar?hl=en&amp;lr=&amp;q=cache:_FJYBJHzugsJ:orgprints.org/10673/01/10673.pdf+wikiversity &quot;Organic Education: Nine Best Internet Tools&quot;] by John Paull.
* [http://repositories.cdlib.org/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1005&amp;context=uclastat/cts/tise &quot;Using Wiki to Promote Collaborative Learning in Statistics Education&quot;] by Dani Ben-Zvi; Technology Innovations in Statistics Education; Volume 1, Issue 1, 2007, Article 4; Page 4. ([http://jephc.com/uploads/Manuscript990221Web3.pdf pdf version])
* [http://64.233.179.104/scholar?hl=en&amp;lr=&amp;q=cache:C0VPpDZarLcJ:www.activemath.org/pubs/semantics2006.pdf+wikiversity &quot;Bootstrapping a Semantic Wiki Application for Learning Mathematics&quot;] by Claus Zinn.
* [http://64.233.179.104/scholar?hl=en&amp;lr=&amp;q=cache:_kI7zTJznCgJ:eprints.qut.edu.au/archive/00006622/01/6622.pdf+wikiversity &quot;Beyond Difference: Reconfiguring Education for the User-Led Age&quot;] by Axel Bruns; Proceedings ICE 3: Ideas, Cyberspace, Education.
* [http://64.233.179.104/scholar?hl=en&amp;lr=&amp;q=cache:876F3XE4K78J:wiki-riki.wikispaces.com/space/showimage/AERA%2BWikibook%2Bpaper%2Brevised--4th%2Bedit-q.doc+wikiversity &quot;The Challenges and Successes of Wikibookian Experts and Wikibook Novices:  Classroom and Community Collaborative Experiences&quot;] by Suthiporn Sajjapanroj, Curt Bonk, Mimi Lee and Meng-Fen Grace Lin.
* [http://www.ariadne.ac.uk/issue49/guy/ &quot;Wiki or Won't He? A Tale of Public Sector Wikis&quot;] by Marieke Guy; Ariadne, Issue 49; October 2006.
* [http://molodiez.org/artjournal_05.pdf &quot;New-Media Art Education and Its Discontents&quot;] by Trebor Scholz.

{{Wikimedia Foundation}}

[[Category:Alternative education]]
[[Category:Educational technology]]
[[Category:Virtual learning environments]]
[[Category:Wikimedia projects]]
[[Category:Online education]]
[[Category:Multilingual websites]]
[[Category:Internet properties established in 2006]]

[[af:Wikiversity]]
[[als:Wikiversity]]
[[ar:ويكي الجامعة]]
[[az:VikiVersitet]]
[[be-x-old:Віківэрсытэт]]
[[bar:Wikiversity]]
[[bg:Уикиверситет]]
[[ca:Wikiversity]]
[[cv:Викиверситет]]
[[cs:Wikiverzita]]
[[de:Wikiversity]]
[[et:Vikiülikool]]
[[es:Wikiversidad]]
[[eo:Vikiversitato]]
[[eu:Wikibertsitatea]]
[[fa:ویکی‌دانشگاه]]
[[fr:Wikiversité]]
[[ko:위키버시티]]
[[hr:Wiki-sveučilište]]
[[id:Wikiversity]]
[[it:Wikiversità]]
[[he:ויקיברסיטה]]
[[ka:ვიკივერსიტი]]
[[lt:Vikiversitetas]]
[[hu:Wikiegyetem]]
[[ml:വിക്കിവേഴ്സിറ്റി]]
[[mt:Wikiversità]]
[[ms:Wikiversity]]
[[cdo:Wiki Dâi-hŏk]]
[[nl:Wikiversity]]
[[ja:ウィキバーシティ]]
[[no:Wikiversity]]
[[pl:Wikiversity]]
[[pt:Wikiversidade]]
[[ru:Викиверситет]]
[[simple:Wikiversity]]
[[sk:Wikiversity]]
[[fi:Wikiopisto]]
[[sv:Wikiversity]]
[[th:วิกิวิทยาลัย]]
[[tr:Vikiversite]]
[[uk:Віківерситет]]
[[vi:Wikiversity]]
[[zh-yue:維基學府]]
[[zh:维基学院]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
