<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="21434966" ns="0" title="History of the bikini"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Good article}}
[[Image:ChicagoBikini1973.jpg|thumb|237px|Woman wearing bikini in [[Chicago]] (1973)]]

The '''history of the bikini''' is a checkered one. Though the [[bikini]] shocked when it appeared on French beaches in 1947, its origins date back millennia. Depictions of bikini-like garments appear at the [[Chalcolithic]] site of [[Çatalhöyük]], and two-piece bikini-like garments were worn by women for athletic purposes in [[Ancient Greece]] as far back as 1400 BC. [[Roman Empire|Roman]] mosaic artwork in [[Sicily]], dubbed &quot;Bikini Girls&quot; and dating back to the reign of [[Diocletian]] (286-305 AD) gained significant archeological renown, and Roman statues of [[Aphrodite|Venus]] in a bikini were found elsewhere. In the modern era, the first functional two-piece swimsuit was designed in 1913 by [[Carl Jantzen]]. Australian swimmer-performer [[Annette Kellerman]] was arrested in 1907 for wearing a two-piece. Later it was made popular by [[pin-up girl]]s like swimmer-actress [[Esther Williams]], and actresses [[Ava Gardner]], [[Rita Hayworth]], and [[Lana Turner]].

The modern bikini was invented by [[France|French]] engineer [[Louis Réard]] in 1946. He named it after [[Bikini Atoll]] in the Pacific, the site of an [[Operation Crossroads|atomic bomb test]] on July 1, 1946. Réard hoped that the burst of excitement it caused would be as explosive as an atomic bomb. Since his contemporary [[Jacques Heim]] had called his bikini precursor the ''Atome'' in view of its size, Réard claimed to have &quot;split the ''Atome''&quot; to make it even smaller. His innovation was to expose the navel, which was not done in earlier two-piece bathing costumes. Though a moderate hit in France, it was not well accepted in other parts of the world. The [[Miss World]] contest in UK, the [[United States Motion Picture Production Code of 1930|Hays production code]] in the US, and the [[Roman Catholicism by country|Catholic countries]] banned the costume. But, the advent of bikinis in popular media, including [[Ursula Andress]]'s [[White bikini of Ursula Andress|white bikini]] in ''[[Dr. No (film)|Dr. No.]]'', [[Brian Hyland]]'s song &quot;[[Itsy Bitsy Teenie Weenie Yellow Polka Dot Bikini]]&quot;, and the [[Sports Illustrated Swimsuit Issue]], eventually gained social acceptance for the bikini. By the early 2000s, bikinis had become a US$811 million business annually, and boosted spin-off services like [[bikini waxing]] and the [[sun tanning]] industries. Further variants were added to the bikini family of beachwears and bathing costumes, contributing to the popular lexicon a variety of ''-kini''s and ''-ini''s.

==In antiquity==
[[File:Romanbikini.gif|thumb|275px|Leather [[Thong (clothing)|thong]] bottom from the time of [[Roman Britain]]]]
{{see also|Clothing in ancient Rome}}

In the [[Chalcolithic]] era around 5600 BC, the mother-goddess of [[Çatalhöyük]], a large ancient settlement in southern [[Anatolia]], was depicted astride two leopards wearing a costume somewhat like a bikini.&lt;ref name=PKumar&gt;Prithvi Kumar Agrawala, ''Goddessess in Ancient India'', page 12, Abhinav Publications, 1984, ISBN 0-391-02960-6&lt;/ref&gt; Two-piece garments worn by women for athletic purposes are depicted on Greek [[urn]]s and paintings dating back to 1400 BC.&lt;ref name=IndeR&gt;{{cite news |first=Rupert |last=Cornwell |coauthors=John Lichfield |title= Boom and Bust: The nuclear age and the bikini age |url=http://www.independent.co.uk/news/science/boom-and-bust-the-nuclear-age-and-the-bikini-age-404390.html |work= |publisher=''[[The Independent]]'' |date=17 June 2006 |accessdate=30 September 2008 }}&lt;/ref&gt; Active women of ancient Greece wore a [[bandeau|breastband]] called a ''mastodeton'' or an ''apodesmos'', which continued to be used as an undergarment in the [[Middle Ages]].&lt;ref&gt;Stephanie Pedersen, ''Bra'', page 8, David &amp; Charles, 2004, ISBN 0-7153-2067-X&lt;/ref&gt; While men in ancient Greece abandoned the ''perizoma'', partly high-cut [[briefs]] and partly loincloth, women performers and acrobats continued to wear it.&lt;ref&gt;Larissa Bonfante, ''Etruscan Dress'', page 21, JHU Press, 2003, ISBN 0-8018-7413-0&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:PiazzaArmerina-Mosaik-Bikini.jpg|thumb|left|200px|One of the earliest visual documentations of a bikini, from the Ancient Roman [[Villa Romana del Casale]]]]

Artwork dating back to the [[Diocletianic Persecution|Diocletian period]] (286-305 AD) in [[Villa Romana del Casale]], [[Sicily]], excavated by [[Gino Vinicio Gentile]] in 1950-60, depicts women in garments resembling bikinis in [[mosaic]]s on the floor.&lt;ref name=BBCW/&gt;&lt;ref name=VilCas&gt;[http://www.valdinoto.com/english/villa_romana_del_casale.htm Villa Romana del Casale], Val di Noto&lt;/ref&gt; The images of ten women, dubbed the &quot;Bikini Girls&quot;,&lt;ref&gt;Allen Guttmann, ''Women's Sports: A History'', page 38, Columbia University Press, 1991, ISBN 0-231-06957-X&lt;/ref&gt; exercising in clothing that would pass as bikinis today, are the most replicated mosaic among the 37 million colored tiles at the site.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.worldheritagesite.org/sites/villaromanadelcasale.html Villa Romana del Casale], World Heritage Sites&lt;/ref&gt; In the artwork &quot;Coronation of the Winner&quot; done in floor mosaic in the Chamber of the Ten Maidens (''Sala delle Dieci Ragazze'' in Italian&lt;ref&gt;Darwin Porter &amp; Danforth Prince, ''Frommer's Sicily‎'', page 272, Frommer's, 2007, ISBN 0-470-10056-7&lt;/ref&gt;) the bikini girls are depicted weight-lifting, discus throwing, and running. Some activities depicted have been described as dancing,&lt;ref&gt;Allen Guttmann, ''The Erotic in Sports'', page 31, Columbia University Press, 1996, ISBN 0-231-10556-8&lt;/ref&gt; as their bodies resemble dancers rather than athletes.&lt;ref&gt;Liz James, ''Women, Men, and Eunuchs'', page 126, Routledge, 1997, ISBN 0-415-14686-0&lt;/ref&gt; Coronation in the title of the mosaic comes from a woman in a [[toga]] with a crown in her hand and one of the maidens holding a palm frond.&lt;ref name=VilCas/&gt; Some academics maintain that the nearby image of [[Eros]], the primordial god of lust, love, and intercourse, was added later, demonstrating the owner's predilections and strengthening the association of the bikini with the erotic.&lt;ref&gt;Paul MacKendrick, ''The Mute Stones Speak'', page 433, Norton, 1984, ISBN 0-393-30119-2&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Neil Christie, ''From Constantine to Charlemagne'', page 431, Ashgate Publishing, Ltd., 2006, ISBN 1-85928-421-3&lt;/ref&gt; Similar mosaics have been discovered in [[Tellaro]] in northern Italy and [[Patti, Sicily|Patti]], another part of Sicily.&lt;ref&gt;Philippe Ariès, Paul Veyne, Georges Duby &amp; Arthur Goldhammer, ''A History of Private Life'', page 651, Harvard University Press, 1992, ISBN 0-674-39974-9&lt;/ref&gt; Prostitution, skimpy clothes and athletic bodies were related in ancient Rome, as images were found of female sex workers exercising with [[dumbbell]]s/[[Clapper (musical instrument)|clappers]] and other equipment wearing costumes similar to the Bikini Girls.&lt;ref&gt;Nils Johan Ringdal &amp; Richard Daly, ''Love for Sale'', page 151, Grove Press, 2005, ISBN 0-8021-4184-6&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Charles Seltman]], a fellow of [[Queens' College, Cambridge]], curator of the Archaeology Museum there and an editor of ''The Cambridge Ancient History'', illustrated a chapter titled &quot;The new woman&quot; in his book ''Women in Antiquity'' with a 1950s model wearing an identical bikini against the 4th-century mosaics from [[Piazza Armerina]] as part of a sisterhood between the bikini-clad female athletes of ancient Greco-Romans and modern woman. A photograph of the mosaic was used by [[Sarah Pomeroy]], Professor of Classics at [[Hunter College]] and the [[CUNY Graduate Center|Graduate Center, City University of New York]], in the 1994 British edition of her book ''Goddesses, Whores, Wives and Slaves'' to emphasize a similar identification.&lt;ref&gt;Janet Huskinson, ''Experiencing Rome'', pages 162-163, Routledge, 2000, ISBN 0-415-21284-7&lt;/ref&gt; According to archeologist [[George M.A. Hanfmann]] the bikini girls made the learned observers realize &quot;how modern the ancients were&quot;.&lt;ref name=hanfmann&gt;George Maxim Anossov Hanfmann, ''Roman Art: A Modern Survey of the Art of Imperial Rome'', page XXV, New York Graphic Society, 1964, ASIN B001826ZJO&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:Venus in Bikini.jpg|thumb|200px|[[Venus]] in bikini from the [[house of Julia Felix]], [[Pompeii]]]]

In ancient [[Roman Empire|Rome]], the bikini-style bottom, a wrapped [[loincloth]] of cloth or leather, was called a ''subligar'' or ''[[subligaculum]]'' (&quot;little binding underneath&quot;), while a band of cloth or leather to support the breasts was called ''strophium'' or ''mamillare''.&lt;ref&gt;Barbara F. McManus, [http://www.vroma.org/~bmcmanus/clothing.html Roman Clothing], The College of New Rochelle, 2003&lt;/ref&gt; The exercising bikini girls from Piazza Armenia wear ''subligaria'', scanty briefs made as a dainty version of a man's ''perizoma'', and a ''strophium'' band about the breasts, often referred to in literature as just ''fascia'', which can mean any kind of bandage. Observation of artifacts and [[Experimental archaeology|experiments]] shows bands had to be wrapped several times around the breasts, largely to flatten them in a style popular with [[flapper]]s in the 1920s.&lt;ref name=RomCost&gt;Judith Lynn Sebesta &amp;, Larissa Bonfante, ''The World of Roman Costume'', pages 234-235, Wisconsin Press, 1994, ISBN 0-299-13854-2&lt;/ref&gt; These Greco-Roman [[Bandeau|breastband]]s may have flattened big breasts and padded small breasts to look bigger. Evidence suggests regular use.&lt;ref name=LizCle&gt;Liza Cleland, Glenys Davies &amp; Lloyd Llewellyn-Jones, ''Greek and Roman Dress from A to Z'', Routledge, 2007, ISBN 0-415-22661-9&lt;/ref&gt; The &quot;bikini girls&quot; from Piazza Armenia, some of whom sport the braless look of the late 20th century, do not depict any propensity of such popularity in style.&lt;ref name=RomCost/&gt; One bottom, made of leather, from [[Roman Britain]] was displayed at the [[Museum of London]] in 1998.&lt;ref name=AlWer&gt;Alex Werner, &quot;[http://www.highbeam.com/doc/1G1-54879248.html Bodies at the Museum of London]&quot;, ''[[History Today]]'', 1998-11-01&lt;/ref&gt; There has been no evidence that these bikinis were for swimming or [[Sun tanning|sun-bathing]].&lt;ref&gt;Liza Cleland, Glenys Davies &amp; Lloyd Llewellyn-Jones, ''Greek and Roman Dress from A to Z'', page 19, Routledge, 2007, ISBN 0-415-22661-9&lt;/ref&gt;

Finds especially in [[Pompeii]] show the Roman goddess [[Venus]] wearing a bikini. A statue of Venus in a bikini was found in a cupboard in the southwest corner in Casa della Venere, others were found in the front hall.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.stoa.org/gallery/allison Pompeian Households], [http://www.stoa.org/gallery/albums.php Stoa Image Gallery], [http://www.stoa.org/ The Stoa Consortium]&lt;/ref&gt; A statue of Venus was recovered from the ''[[tablinum]]'' of the [[house of Julia Felix]],&lt;ref&gt;Mary Beard &amp; John Henderson, ''Classical Art'', page 116, Oxford University Press, 2001, ISBN 0-19-284237-4&lt;/ref&gt; and another from an [[Atrium (architecture)|atrium]] in the garden at [[House of Loreius Tiburtinus|Via Dell'Abbondanza]].&lt;ref&gt;Elisabeth B. MacDougall, Wilhelmina Mary Feemster Jashemski &amp; Dumbarton Oaks, ''Ancient Roman Gardens'', page 38, Dumbarton Oaks, 1979, ISBN 0-88402-100-9&lt;/ref&gt; [[Naples National Archaeological Museum]], which opened its limited viewing gallery of more explicit exhibits in 2000, also exhibits a &quot;Venus in Bikini&quot;.&lt;ref name=BBCS&gt;David Willey, &quot;[http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/low/europe/715697.stm Pompeii's erotic art goes on show]&quot;, BBC News, 2000-04-16&lt;/ref&gt; The museum's exhibits include female statues wearing see-through gold [[Lamé (fabric)|lamé]] [[brassiere]], [[Basque (clothing)|basque]] and [[knickers]].&lt;ref&gt;Roderick Conway Morris, &quot;[http://www.highbeam.com/doc/1P1-15178904.html The Chaos and Color of the Ancient World]&quot;, ''International Herald Tribune'', page 1, 1998-06-27&lt;/ref&gt; The [[List of monarchs of Naples|Kings of Naples]] discovered these Pompeii artifacts, including the one meter tall, almost unclothed statue of Venus painted in gold leaf with something like a modern bikini. They found them so shocking that for long periods the secret chamber was opened only to &quot;mature persons of secure morals&quot;. Even after the doors were opened, only 20 visitors were to be admitted at a time, and children under 12 were not allowed into the new part of the museum without their parents' or a teacher's permission.&lt;ref name=BBCS/&gt;

There are references to bikinis in ancient literature as well. [[Ovid]], the writer ranked alongside [[Virgil]] and [[Horace]] as one of the three canonical poets of [[Latin literature]], suggests the breastband or long strip of cloth wrapped around the breasts and tucked in the ends, is a good place to hide love-letters.&lt;ref name=LizCle/&gt; [[Martial]], a [[Latin]] poet from [[Hispania]] who published between AD 86 and 103, satirized a female athlete he named Philaenis, who played ball in a bikini-like garb quite bluntly, making her drink, gorge and vomit in abundance and hinting at her [[lesbian]]ism.&lt;ref&gt;Louis Crompton, '' Homosexuality &amp; Civilization'', page 98, Harvard University Press, 2006, ISBN 0-674-02233-5&lt;/ref&gt; In an [[epigram]] on [[Chione (daughter of Daedalion)|Chione]], Martial strangely mentions a sex worker who went to the [[Roman Baths (Bath)|bathhouse]] in a bikini, while it was more natural to go unclothed.&lt;ref&gt;Martial, Lindsay Watson &amp; Patricia A. Watson, ''Select Epigrams'', page 189, Cambridge University Press, 2003, ISBN 0-521-55539-6&lt;/ref&gt; Reportedly [[Theodora (6th century)|Theodora]], the 6th century empress of the [[Byzantine Empire]] wore a bikini when she appeared as an actress before she captured the heart of emperor [[Justinian I]].&lt;ref name=hanfmann/&gt;

[[File:Hietaniemi 1929.jpg|thumb|left|215px|Woman wearing early two-piece [[swimwear]] in [[Hietaniemi beach]] near [[Helsinki]], Finland in 1929]]
[[File:Yvonne DeCarlo.jpg|thumb|left|215px|Pin-up photo of [[Yvonne DeCarlo]] wearing a two-piece bathing suit in the June 9, 1944 issue of [[Yank, the Army Weekly]]]]

==19th century to 1930s: Precursors==
{{see also|Swimsuit|Beachwear}}

The modern bikini has had a checkered history. The first domestic swimsuit for &quot;decency&quot; appeared in 1830. Featuring red and white horizontal stripes from ankle to wrist, it was nicknamed the &quot;prison suit&quot;.&lt;ref name=notting&gt;David Sandhu, &quot;[http://www.telegraph.co.uk/travel/sunandsea/728059/Nottingham-Bathed-in-nostalgia.html Nottingham: Bathed in nostalgia]&quot;, ''The Telegraph'' (UK), 2003-08-04&lt;/ref&gt; In 1907, Australian swimmer and performer [[Annette Kellerman]] was arrested on a [[Boston]] beach for wearing a form-fitting one-piece although it became accepted swimsuit attire for women by 1910.&lt;ref&gt;Liz Conor, ''The spectacular modern woman: feminine visibility in the 1920s‎'', page 152, Indiana University Press, 2004, ISBN 0-253-34391-7&lt;/ref&gt; Pictures of her were produced as evidence in the ''[[Esquire (magazine)|Esquire magazine]]'' versus [[United States Postmaster General]] legal battle over indecency in 1943.&lt;ref&gt;Jean Preer, &quot;[http://www.archives.gov/publications/prologue/1990/spring/esquire-v-walker-3.html The Postmaster General and ''The Magazine for Men'']&quot;, ''Prologue Magazine'', page 3, Spring 1990, Vol. 23, No. 1, U.S. National Archives and Records Administration&lt;/ref&gt; In 1913, inspired by the introduction of females into Olympic swimming, the designer [[Carl Jantzen]] made the first functional two-piece swimwear, a close-fitting one-piece with shorts on the bottom and short sleeves on top.&lt;ref name=heritage&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.americanheritage.com/articles/web/20060705-bikini-swimming-suit-louis-reard-micheline-bernardini-paris-brigitte-bardot.shtml|accessdate=13 November 2007|publisher=American Heritage Inc.|title=60 Years of Bikinis|author=Hoover, Elizabeth D.|date=5 July 2006}}&lt;/ref&gt; Silent films such as ''[[The Water Nymph]]'' (1912) saw [[Mabel Normand]] in revealing attire, and this was followed by the daringly dressed [[Sennett Bathing Beauties]] (1915–1929).  The first annual bathing-suit day at New York's [[Madison Square Garden]] in 1916 was a landmark.&lt;ref&gt;Jean Preer, &quot;[http://www.archives.gov/publications/prologue/1990/spring/esquire-v-walker-1.html The Postmaster General and &quot;The Magazine for Men]&quot;''Prologue Magazine'', page 1, Spring 1990, Vol. 23, No. 1, U.S. National Archives and Records Administration&lt;/ref&gt; The swimsuit apron, a design for early swimwear, disappeared by 1918, leaving a tunic covering the shorts.&lt;ref name=carnival/&gt;

[[File:Annette Kellerman.jpg|thumb|200px|[[Annette Kellerman]] in the form-fitting one-piece [[Maillot|tank suit]] that troubled the law]]

By the 1930s, necklines plunged at the back, sleeves disappeared and sides were cut away. Hollywood endorsed the new glamour with films such as ''[[Neptune's Daughter (1949 film)|Neptune's Daughter]]'' in which [[Esther Williams]] wore provocatively named costumes such as &quot;Double Entendre&quot; and &quot;Honey Child&quot;.&lt;ref name=notting/&gt; Williams also portrayed Kellerman in the 1952 film ''[[Million Dollar Mermaid]]'' (titled as ''The One Piece Bathing Suit'' in UK).&lt;ref&gt;Steven Anzovin &amp; Janet Podell, ''Famous First Facts'', page 51, H.W. Wilson, 2000, ISBN 0-8242-0958-3&lt;/ref&gt; American designer [[Adele Simpson]], a [[Coty Award|Coty American Fashion Critics' Awards]] winner (1947) and a notable alumna of the New York art school [[Pratt Institute]], who believed clothes must be comfortable and practical designed a large part of her wardrobe which included mostly one-piece suits that were considered fashionable even in early 1980s.&lt;ref&gt;Gayle Kimball, ''Women's Culture: The Women's Renaissance of the Seventies'', page 141, Scarecrow Press, 1981, ISBN 0-8108-1455-2&lt;/ref&gt; This was when [[Cole of California]] started marketing revealing prohibition suits and [[Catalina Swimwear]] introduced almost bare-back designs.&lt;ref&gt;Kathleen Morgan Drowne &amp; Patrick Huber, ''The 1920's'', page 104, Greenwood Publishing Group, 2004, ISBN 0-313-32013-6&lt;/ref&gt;

With new materials like [[lastex]] and [[nylon]], by 1934 the swimsuit started hugging the body and had shoulder straps to lower for tanning.&lt;ref name=carnival&gt;[http://www.carnaval.com/bikini/#In%20Brazil History of the Bikini], Carnival&lt;/ref&gt; [[Burlesque]] and [[vaudeville]] performers wore two-piece outfits in the 1920s, films of holidaymakers in Germany in the 1930s show women wearing two-piece suits,&lt;ref name=metm/&gt; and in 1932 French designer [[Madeleine Vionnet]] offered an exposed midriff in an evening gown. They were seen a year later in ''[[Gold Diggers of 1933]]''. The [[Busby Berkeley]] film ''[[Footlight Parade]]'' of 1932 showcases [[water ballet|aquachoreography]] that featured bikinis.  [[Dorothy Lamour]]'s ''[[The Hurricane (1937 film)|The Hurricane]]'' (1937) also showed two-piece bathing suits.&lt;ref name=metm&gt;[http://www.metmuseum.org/toah/hd/biki/hd_biki.htm The Bikini], [[Metropolitan Museum of Art]]&lt;/ref&gt; In 1935 American designer [[Claire McCardell]] cut out the side panels of a [[maillot]]-style bathing suit, the bikini's forerunner.&lt;ref&gt;Samantha Critchell, &quot;[http://www.signonsandiego.com/uniontrib/20060528/news_1c28bikini.html Little wonder that bikinis have fit in almost from the start]&quot;, ''[[The San Diego Union-Tribune]]'', 2006-05-28&lt;/ref&gt; A woman's cotton sun-top of 1939, printed with palm trees, provides a good example here.&lt;ref name=notting/&gt; 

[[File:Esther Williams 2.jpg|thumb|200px|Pin-up photo of [[Esther Williams]] wearing a conservative two-piece in the October 12, 1945 issue of Yank, the Army Weekly]]

Two-piece swimsuits without the usual [[skirt panel]] and other superfluous material started appearing in the US when the government ordered a 10% reduction in fabric used in woman's swimwear in 1943 as wartime rationing.&lt;ref name=HistC&gt;[http://www.history.com/this-day-in-history.do?action=VideoArticle&amp;id=6949 Bikini Introduced], This Day in History, ''[[History Channel]]''&lt;/ref&gt; By that time, two-piece swimsuits were frequent on American beaches. The July 9, 1945, ''[[Life (magazine)|Life]]'' shows women in Paris wearing similar items. [[Hollywood]] stars like Ava Gardner, [[Rita Hayworth]] and [[Lana Turner]] tried similar swimwear or [[beachwear]].&lt;ref name=ArtCent&gt;James Kitchling, &quot;[http://www.articles-central.info/Art/22681/48/Short-History-of-Bikinis-and-Swimsuits.html Short History of Bikinis and Swimsuits]&quot;, Articles Central, 2008-08-02&lt;/ref&gt; [[Pin-up girl|Pin ups]] of Hayworth and [[Esther Williams]] in the costume were widely distributed.&lt;ref name=heritage/&gt; The most provocative swimsuit was the 1946 Moonlight Buoy, a bottom and a top of material that weighed only eight ounces. What made the Moonlight Buoy distinctive was a large [[Cork (material)|cork]] [[buckle]] attached to the bottoms, which made it possible to tie the top to the cork buckle and splash around [[Naturism|''au naturel'']] while keeping both parts of the suit afloat. ''[[Life (magazine)|Life]]'' magazine had a photo essay on the Moonlight Buoy and wrote, &quot;The name of the suit, of course, suggests the nocturnal conditions under which nude swimming is most agreeable.&quot;&lt;ref name=WOJSI/&gt; 

Swimwear of the 1940s, 50s and early 60s followed the [[Silhouette#Fashion and fitness|silhouette]] mostly from early 1930s. Keeping in line with the ultra-feminine look dominated by [[Christian Dior SA|Dior]], it evolved into a dress with cinched waists and constructed bustlines, accessorized with earrings, bracelets, hats, scarves, sunglasses, hand bags and cover-ups.&lt;ref name=asseen&gt;Daniel Delis Hill, ''As Seen in Vogue'', page 63, Texas Tech University Press, 2007, ISBN 0-89672-616-9&lt;/ref&gt; Many of these pre-bikinis had fancy names like Double Entendre, Honey Child (to maximize [[Breast|small bosoms]]), Shipshape (to minimize [[Breast|large bosoms]]), Diamond Lil (trimmed with [[rhinestone]]s and [[lace]]), Swimming In Mink (trimmed with [[Fur clothing|fur]] across the [[bodice]]) and Spearfisherman (heavy [[poplin]] with a [[rope belt]] for carrying a knife), Beau Catcher, Leading Lady, Pretty Foxy, Side Issue, Forecast, and Fabulous Fit.&lt;ref name=WOJSI&gt;William Oscar Johnson , &quot;[http://vault.sportsillustrated.cnn.com/vault/article/magazine/MAG1068171/3/index.htm In The Swim]&quot;, ''Sports Illustrated'', 1989-02-07&lt;/ref&gt; According to ''[[Vogue (magazine)|Vogue]]'' the swimwear had become more of &quot;state of dress, not undress&quot; by mid 1950s.&lt;ref name=asseen/&gt; But, to a bikini, size makes all the difference.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.iol.co.za/index.php?click_id=29&amp;art_id=qw1151560801728A141&amp;set_id=1 Bikinis still abreast of fashion], IOL News&lt;/ref&gt; Pin-up queen and [[Hollywood]] star Williams, who also was an [[Amateur Athletic Union]] champion in the 100 meter [[Freestyle swimming|freestyle]] (1939)&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.novelguide.com/a/discover/adec_0001_0004_0/adec_0001_0004_0_01367.html THE 1930s: Sports: Overview], Novel Guide&lt;/ref&gt; and an [[Swimming at the Summer Olympics|Olympics swimming]] finalist (1940),&lt;ref&gt;[http://everything2.com/e2node/Esther%2520Williams Esther Williams], Everything2&lt;/ref&gt; commented, &quot;A bikini is a thoughtless act.&quot;&lt;ref name=heritage/&gt; Popularity of the charms of Williams were to vanish along with pre-bikinis with fancy names over the next few decades.&lt;ref&gt;Charles Sprawson, ''Haunts of the Black Masseur: The Swimmer as Hero'', page 267, Pantheon Books, 1992, ISBN 0-679-42051-7&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:MichelineBernardini.jpg|thumb|right|200px|[[Micheline Bernardini]] modeling one of the first modern bikinis]]

==1940s to 1950s: Introduction and resistance==
{{see also|Indecent exposure}}

The modern bikini was introduced by French engineer [[Louis Réard]] and separately by fashion designer [[Jacques Heim]] in Paris in 1946. Réard was a car engineer but by 1946 he was running his mother's lingerie boutique near [[Folies Bergère|Les Folies Bergère]] in Paris.&lt;ref name=TimA&gt;Adam Sage, &quot;[http://www.timesonline.co.uk/tol/news/world/europe/article705414.ece Happy birthday: the 'shocking and immoral' bikini hits 60]&quot;, ''[[The Times]]'', 2006-04-16&lt;/ref&gt; Heim was working on a new kind of beach costume. It comprised two pieces, the bottom large enough to cover its wearer's navel. In May 1946, he advertised it as the world's &quot;smallest bathing suit&quot;. Réard sliced the top off the bottoms and advertised it as &quot;smaller than the smallest swimsuit&quot;.&lt;ref name=Guard&gt;Paula Cocozza, &quot;[http://www.guardian.co.uk/travel/2006/jun/10/sttropez.filminspiredtravel.france.culturaltrips?gusrc=rss&amp;feed=travel A little piece of history]&quot;, ''[[The Guardian]]'', 2006-06-10&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=Lil&gt;[http://www.lilith-ezine.com/articles/2006/The-Bikini.html The Bikini Turns 60], 1946 to 2006: 60 Years of Bikini Bathing Beauties, ''Lilith E-Zine''&lt;/ref&gt; The idea struck him when he saw women rolling up their beachwear to get a better tan.&lt;ref name=BBCW&gt;Kathryn Westcott, &quot;[http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/in_depth/5130460.stm The Bikini: Not a brief affair]&quot;, BBC News, 2006-06-05&lt;/ref&gt; 

Réard could not find a model to wear his design. He ended up hiring [[Micheline Bernardini]], a [[Striptease|nude dancer]] from the Casino de Paris.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url = http://www.bikiniscience.com/chronology/1945-1950_SS/LR4601_S/LR4601.html | title = Michele Bernadini: The First Bikini | first = Judson | last = Rosebush | work = Bikini Science | date = | accessdate = 19 September 2007 }}&lt;/ref&gt; That bikini, a string bikini with a [[g-string]] back of {{convert|30|sqin|cm2|0}} of cloth with newspaper type print, was introduced on July 5 at Piscine Molitor, a public pool in Paris. The bikini was a hit, especially among men, and Bernardini received 50,000 letters.&lt;ref name=heritage/&gt;&lt;ref name=HistC/&gt; Heim's design was the first worn on the beach, but the design was given its name by Réard.&lt;ref name=BBCW/&gt; Reard's business soared. In advertisements he kept the bikini alive by declaring that a two-piece wasn't a genuine bikini &quot;unless it could be pulled through a wedding ring.&quot;&lt;ref name=HistC/&gt; French newspaper ''[[Le Figaro]]'' wrote, &quot;People were craving the simple pleasures of the sea and the sun. For women, wearing a bikini signaled a kind of second liberation. There was really nothing sexual about this. It was instead a celebration of freedom and a return to the joys in life.&quot;&lt;ref name=heritage/&gt;

[[File:Bundesarchiv Bild 183-65046-0002, Badrina, Studentin beim Arbeitseinsatz.jpg|thumb|left|200px|A [[International Union of Socialist Youth|first socialist camp]] student wearing a bikini in [[Leipzig]], [[Germany]], 1959]]

But sales did not pick up around the world as women stuck to traditional two-piece swimsuits. Réard went back to designing orthodox knickers to sell in his mother’s shop.&lt;ref name=TimA/&gt; Actresses in movies like ''[[My Favorite Brunette]]'' (1947) and the model on a 1948 cover of ''LIFE'' were shown in traditional two-piece swimwear, not the bikini. In 1950, ''[[Time (magazine)|Time]]'' magazine interviewed American swimsuit mogul Fred Cole, owner of [[Cole of California]], and reported that he had &quot;little but scorn for France’s famed Bikinis,&quot; because they were designed for &quot;diminutive Gallic women&quot;. &quot;French girls have short legs,&quot; he explained, &quot;Swimsuits have to be hiked up at the sides to make their legs look longer.&quot; One writer described it as a &quot;two-piece bathing suit which reveals everything about a girl except for her mother's maiden name.&quot;&lt;ref name=heritage/&gt; According to Kevin Jones, curator and fashion historian at the [[Fashion Institute of Design &amp; Merchandising]], &quot;Réard was ahead of his time by about 15 to 20 years. Only women in the vanguard, mostly upper-class European women embraced it, just like the upper-class European women who first cast off their corsets after [[World War I]].&quot;&lt;ref name=SFC&gt;Sylvia Rubin, &quot;[http://www.sfgate.com/cgi-bin/article.cgi?file=/c/a/2006/07/02/BIKINI.TMP&amp;type=printable Fashion shocker of '46: the naked belly button]&quot;, ''[[San Francisco Chronicle]]'', 2006-07-02&lt;/ref&gt; Australian designer [[Paula Straford]] introduced the bikini to [[Gold Coast, Queensland|Gold Coast]] in 1952. 

Despite the controversy, some in France admired &quot;naughty girls who decorate our sun-drenched beaches&quot;.&lt;ref name=craik&gt;Jennifer Craik, ''The Face of Fashion'', page 148, Routledge, 1993, ISBN 0-415-05262-9&lt;/ref&gt; [[Brigitte Bardot]], photographed wearing similar garments on beaches during the [[Cannes Film Festival|Film Festival]] (1953) helped popularize the bikini in Europe in the 1950s and created a market in the US.&lt;ref name=ArtCent/&gt; Photographs of Bardot in a bikini, according to ''The Guardian'', turned [[Saint-Tropez]] into the bikini capital of the world.&lt;ref name=Guard/&gt; The [[Cannes Film Festival]], held on the French Riviera each May, remains as a reminder of the days when a starlet was as big as her swimsuit was brief. [[Esther Williams]], [[Betty Grable]], [[Marilyn Monroe]] and [[Brigitte Bardot]] all used the swimsuit as a career prop to their sex appeal,&lt;ref name=menkes&gt;Suzy Menkes, &quot;[http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0CE7D81430F93BA25754C0A965958260&amp;sec=&amp;spon=&amp;pagewanted=2 Runways: Remembrance of Thongs Past]&quot;, ''The New York Times'', 1993-07-18&lt;/ref&gt; with Bardot identified as the original Cannes bathing beauty.&lt;ref&gt;Cari Beauchamp &amp; Henri Béhar, '' Hollywood on the Riviera: The Inside Story of the Cannes Film Festival‎'', page 165, W. Morrow and Co., 1992, ISBN 0-688-11007-X&lt;/ref&gt; Cannes played a crucial role in the career of Brigitte Bardot, who in turn played a crucial role in promoting the Festival, largely by starting the trend of being photographed in a bikini at her first appearance at the festival.&lt;ref&gt;Vanessa R. Schwartz, '' It's So French!: Hollywood, Paris, and the Making of Cosmopolitan Film Culture‎'', page 79, University of Chicago Press, 2007, ISBN 0-226-74243-1&lt;/ref&gt; As late as in 1959, [[Anne Cole]], a US swimsuit designer and daughter of Fred Cole, said about a Bardot bikini, &quot;It's nothing more than a G-string. It's at the razor's edge of decency.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;James Peterson, ''The Century of Sex'', page 184, Grove Press, 1999, ISBN 0-8021-1652-3&lt;/ref&gt; ''Modern Girl Magazine'', a fashion magazine from the United States, was quoted in 1957 as saying: &quot;it is hardly necessary to waste words over the so-called bikini since it is inconceivable that any girl with tact and decency would ever wear such a thing&quot;.&lt;ref name=YorkS/&gt;

&lt;!-- Deleted image removed: [[File:Kiki Håkansson in Miss World 1951.jpg|thumb|left|225px|[[Kiki Håkansson]], the first and last [[Miss World]] to be crowned in a bikini]] --&gt;

The bikini became more accepted in parts of Europe when worn by fifties &quot;love goddess&quot; actresses such as Bardot, [[Anita Ekberg]] and [[Sophia Loren]].&lt;ref&gt;Frank A. Salamone, ''Reflections on Theory and History in Anthropology‎'', page 208, University Press of America, 2006, ISBN 0-7618-3454-0&lt;/ref&gt; But, Spain, Portugal and Italy, three countries neighboring France, banned the bikini, and it remained prohibited in many US states.&lt;ref name=ArtCent/&gt; In July 1959, the ''[[New York Post]]'' searched for bikinis around New York City and found only a couple.&lt;ref name=WOJSI/&gt; Writer [[Meredith Hall]] wrote in her memoir that till 1965 one could get a [[Summons#Citation|citation]] for wearing a bikini in [[Hampton Beach, New Hampshire]].&lt;ref&gt;Henrik Vejlgaard, ''Anatomy of a Trend'', page 94, McGraw-Hill Professional, 2008, ISBN 0-07-148870-7&lt;/ref&gt; By the end of the decade a vogue for strapless styles developed, wired or bound for firmness and fit, and a taste for bare-shouldered two-pieces called Little Sinners. But, it was the [[halterneck]] bikini that caused the most moral controversy because of its degree of exposure. So much so as bikini designs called &quot;Huba Huba&quot; and &quot;Revealation&quot; were withdrawn from fashion parades in Sydney as immodest.&lt;ref&gt;Margaret Maynard, ''Out of Line'', page 153, UNSW Press, 2001, ISBN 0-86840-515-9&lt;/ref&gt;

In 1951, the first Miss World contest, originally the ''Festival Bikini Contest'',&lt;ref&gt;Elissa Stein &amp; Lee Meriwether, ''Beauty Queen'', page 45, Chronicle Books, 2006, ISBN 0-8118-4864-7&lt;/ref&gt; was organized by [[Eric Morley]] as a mid-century advertisement for swimwear at the [[Festival of Britain]].&lt;ref&gt;Susan Dewey, ''Making Miss India Miss World''‎ page 46, Syracuse University Press, 2008, ISBN 0-8156-3176-6&lt;/ref&gt; The press welcomed the spectacle and referred to it as ''Miss World'', and Morley registered the name as a trademark.&lt;ref&gt;Keith Lovegrove, ''Pageant: The Beauty Contest‎'', page 1967, teNeues, 2002, ISBN 3-8238-5569-7&lt;/ref&gt; When, the winner [[Kiki Håkansson]] from Sweden, was crowned in a bikini, countries with religious traditions threatened to withdraw delegates. The bikinis were outlawed and [[evening gown]]s introduced instead.&lt;ref&gt;Han Shin, ''Beauty with a Purpose'', page 193, iUniverse, 2004, ISBN 0-595-30926-7&lt;/ref&gt; Håkansson remains the only Miss World crowned in a bikini,&lt;ref&gt;Keith Lovegrove, ''Pageant: The Beauty Contest'', page 1967, teNeues, 2002, ISBN 3-8238-5569-7&lt;/ref&gt; a crowning that was condemned by the [[Pope]].&lt;ref&gt;Various, ''Selvedge: The Fabric of Your Life'', page 39, Selvedge Ltd., 2005&lt;/ref&gt; Bikini was banned from beauty pageants around the world after the controversy.&lt;ref&gt;Ben Marcus and Jeff Divine, ''Surfing USA!: An Illustrated History of the Coolest Sport of All Time'', page 60, MVP Books, 2005, ISBN 9780896586901&lt;/ref&gt; Feminist groups published fliers against bikinis in the contest in 1970.&lt;ref&gt;Michelene Wandor, ''The body politic: writings from the Women's Liberation Movement in Britain, 1969-1972'', page 252, Stage 1, 1972, ISBN 9780850350142&lt;/ref&gt; The [[National Legion of Decency]] pressured Hollywood to keep bikinis from being featured in Hollywood movies.&lt;ref&gt;Frank A. Salamone, ''Popular Culture in the Fifties‎'', page 76, University Press of America, 2001, ISBN 0-7618-2103-1&lt;/ref&gt; The [[United States Motion Picture Production Code of 1930|Hays production code]] for US movies, introduced in 1930 but not strictly enforced till 1934, allowed two-piece gowns but prohibited navels on screen.&lt;ref&gt;Rachel Moseley, ''Fashioning Film Stars: Dress, Culture, Identity'', page 136, BFI, 2005, ISBN 1-84457-067-3&lt;/ref&gt; But between the introduction and enforcement of the code two [[Tarzan]] movies, ''[[Tarzan the Ape Man (1932 film)|Tarzan, the Ape Man]]'' (1932) and ''[[Tarzan and His Mate]]'' (1934), were released in which actress [[Maureen O'Sullivan]] wore skimpy bikini-like leather outfits. Film historian Bruce Goldstein described her clothes in the first film as &quot;It's a loincloth open up the side. You can see loin.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;David Hinckley, &quot;[http://nl.newsbank.com/nl-search/we/Archives?p_product=BN&amp;p_theme=bn&amp;p_action=search&amp;p_maxdocs=200&amp;p_topdoc=1&amp;p_text_direct-0=0EAF95FEC0F7FD70&amp;p_field_direct-0=document_id&amp;p_perpage=10&amp;p_sort=YMD_date:D&amp;s_trackval=GooglePM Tarzan's defenders wrap themselves in morality]&quot;, ''The Buffalo News'', 1992-04-29&lt;/ref&gt; In reaction to the introduction of the bikini in Paris, American [[:Category:Swimwear manufacturers|swimwear manufacturers]] compromised cautiously by producing their own similar design that included a [[Halterneck|halter]] and a midriff-bottom variation.&lt;ref&gt;Daniel Delis Hill, ''Advertising to the American Woman, 1900-1999'', page 162, Ohio State University Press, 2002, ISBN 0-8142-0890-8&lt;/ref&gt; The early ''bikinis'' often covered the navel but if it showed in pictures, magazines like ''[[Seventeen (magazine)|Seventeen]]'' [[airbrush]]ed it out. Navel-less women ensured the early dominance of European bikini makers over their American counterparts.&lt;ref&gt;Arthur Asa Berger, ''Reading Matter: Multidisciplinary Perspectives on Material Culture '', page 105, Transaction Publishers, 1992, ISBN 0-88738-435-8&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:Ursula Andress in bikini.jpg|thumb|200px|[[Ursula Andress]] in the iconic scene from ''[[Dr. No (film)|Dr. No]]'']]

==Since 1960s: Popularity and acceptance==
{{see also|Bikini in popular culture|Bikini variants}}

In 1962, Bond Girl [[Ursula Andress]] [[White bikini of Ursula Andress|emerged from the sea wearing a white bikini]] in ''[[Dr. No (film)|Dr. No]]''. The  scene has been named one of the most memorable of the series.&lt;ref&gt;[http://archives.cnn.com/2001/SHOWBIZ/Movies/01/12/andress.bikini/index.html Bond girl Ursula sells Dr. No bikini], [[CNN]]; Retrieved: 2008-01-14&lt;/ref&gt; [[Channel 4]] declared it the top bikini moment in film history,&lt;ref name=chan4&gt;[http://www.channel4.com/film/newsfeatures/microsites/S/sexy/index.html 100 Greatest Sexy Moments (in film)], Channel 4&lt;/ref&gt; [[Virgin Media]] puts it ninth in its top ten,&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.virginmedia.com/movies/movieextras/top10s/top-ten-movie-bikinis.php?ssid=9 Ursula Andress - Dr No - 1962], Virgin Media; Retrieved: 2008-01-14&lt;/ref&gt; and top in the [[Bond girl]]s.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.virginmedia.com/movies/galleries/bondgirls-2007.php Honey Ryder - Dr No (1962)], Virgin Media; Retrieved: 2008-01-14&lt;/ref&gt; [[The Herald (Glasgow)|''The Herald'' (Glasgow)]] put the scene as best ever on the basis of a poll.&lt;ref&gt;Damien Henderson, [http://www.theherald.co.uk/news/news/display.var.1452703.0.0.php Andress: best ever bikini scene], The Herald (Glasgow), 2007-06-07; Retrieved: 2008-01-14&lt;/ref&gt; It also helped shape the career of Ursula Andress,&lt;ref&gt;Tom Lisanti, Louis Paul; Film Fatales: Women in Espionage Films and Television, 1962-1973; pages 36-37; McFarland &amp; Company; 2002; ISBN 0-7864-1194-5&lt;/ref&gt; the look of the quintessential [[Bond movie]].&lt;ref&gt;James Chapman; Licence to Thrill: A Cultural History of the James Bond Films; page 81; Columbia University Press; 2001; ISBN 0-231-12049-4&lt;/ref&gt; According to Andress, &quot;This bikini made me into a success.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;[http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/entertainment/1113839.stm Dr No bikini for sale], [[BBC]]; Retrieved: 2008-01-03&lt;/ref&gt; That white bikini has been described as a &quot;defining moment in the sixties liberalization of screen eroticism&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;Martin Rubin; Thrillers; page 128; Cambridge University Press; 1999; ISBN 0-521-58839-1&lt;/ref&gt; Because of the shocking effect from how revealing it was at the time, she got referred to by the joke nickname &quot;Ursula Undress&quot;. According to the [[British Broadcasting Corporation]], &quot;So iconic was the look that it was repeated 40 years later by [[Halle Berry]] in the Bond movie ''[[Die Another Day]]''.&quot; In 2001, the ''Dr. No'' bikini sold at an auction for [[US$]]61,500.&lt;ref name=BBCW/&gt;

The appearance of bikinis kept increasing both on screen and off. The [[sex appeal]] prompted [[film]] and [[television]] productions, including ''[[Dr. Strangelove]]''. They include the [[surf movie]]s of the early 1960s. In 1960, [[Brian Hyland]]'s song &quot;[[Itsy Bitsy Teenie Weenie Yellow Polka Dot Bikini]]&quot; inspired a bikini-buying spree.&lt;ref&gt;James Rothaar, &quot;[http://web.archive.org/web/20071012142337rn_1/www.justluxe.com/resources/history-bikini.php Bikinis Exposed: Happy 60th Anniversary!]&quot;, JustLuxé, LuxeMont, 2004&lt;/ref&gt; By 1963, the movie ''[[Beach Party]]'', starring [[Annette Funicello]] and [[Frankie Avalon]], led a wave of films that made the bikini pop-culture symbol. In the [[sexual revolution in 1960s America]], bikinis became popular fast.&lt;ref name=BBCW/&gt; In 1965, a woman told Time it was &quot;almost square&quot; not to wear one. In 1967 the magazine wrote that &quot;65% of the young set had already gone over.&quot; ''[[Playboy]]'' first featured a bikini on its cover in 1962. The [[Sports Illustrated Swimsuit Issue]] debuted two years later. This popularity was reinforced by its appearance in movies like ''[[How to Stuff a Wild Bikini]]'' featuring Annette Funicello and ''[[One Million Years B.C]]'' featuring [[Raquel Welch]].&lt;ref name=ArtCent/&gt; Hollywood stars like Marilyn Monroe, [[Jayne Mansfield]], [[Gina Lollobrigida]] and [[Jane Russell]] helped the growing popularity further. Pin-up posters of Monroe and Mansfield and of Hayworth, Bardot and Raquel Welch contributed significantly .&lt;ref name=AgeL&gt;Lorna Edwards, &quot;[http://www.theage.com.au/articles/2006/06/02/1148956539436.html?page=fullpage#contentSwap1 You've still got it, babe], ''[[The Age]]'', 2006-06-03&lt;/ref&gt; By the end of the century, the bikini went on to become the most popular beachwear around the globe, according to French fashion historian [[Olivier Saillard]] due to &quot;the power of women, and not the power of fashion&quot;. As he explains, &quot;The emancipation of swimwear has always been linked to the emancipation of women&quot;,&lt;ref name=&quot;BBCW&quot;/&gt; though one survey tells 85% of all bikinis never touch the water.&lt;ref name=YorkS&gt;Jayne Dawson, &quot;[http://www.yorkshireeveningpost.co.uk/features/Sexy-at-60.1649828.jp Sexy at 60]&quot;, 2006-07-25&lt;/ref&gt; By the early 2000s, bikinis had become a US$811 million business annually, according to the [[NPD Group]], a consumer and retail information company.&lt;ref name=&quot;SFC&quot;/&gt; The bikini has boosted spin-off services like [[bikini wax]]ing and the sun tanning industries.&lt;ref name=AgeL/&gt;

[[File:Sharmila tagore in bikini.jpg|thumb|left|200px|[[Sharmila Tagore]] was the first [[India]]n actress to wear a bikini in 1967]]

When Mansfield and her husband [[Miklós Hargitay]] toured for stage shows, newspapers wrote that Mansfield convinced the rural population that she owned more bikinis than anyone.&lt;ref&gt;Dorothy Kilgallen, &quot;Jayne's Touring Strawhats in Bikinis&quot;, Washington Post, page B11, 1964-07-22&lt;/ref&gt; She showed a fair amount of her {{convert|40|in|mm|adj=on}} bust, as well as her midriff and legs, in the leopard-spot bikini she wore for her stage shows.&lt;ref&gt;Staff Correspondent, &quot;The bare facts at last, all those hours at the gym will pay off with spring's slightly skimpy fashions&quot;, ''Miami Herald'', page D1, 1986-03-12&lt;/ref&gt;  Kathryn Wexler of ''[[The Miami Herald]]'' wrote, &quot;In the beginning as we know it, there was Jayne Mansfield. Here she preens in leopard-print or striped bikinis, sucking in air to showcase her well noted physical assets.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Kathryn Wexler, &quot;[http://www.accessmylibrary.com/coms2/summary_0286-14911424_ITM Old-time eroticism: When bikinis really mattered]&quot;, ''Miami Herald'', 2006-04-19&lt;/ref&gt; Her [[Leopard (pattern)|leopard-skin]] bikini remains one of the earlier specimens of the fashion.&lt;ref&gt;Jennifer Steinhauer, &quot;[http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0DE0D91539F932A25756C0A961958260 In, Damned Spot!], New York Times, 1997-05-11&lt;/ref&gt; Other memorable bikini moments include Raquel Welch as the prehistoric cavegirl in the 1966 film ''[[One Million Years B.C.]]'', and [[Phoebe Cates]] in the 1982 [[teen film]] ''[[Fast Times at Ridgemont High]]''. These two bikini moments were ranked 86 and 84 in [[Channel 4]] ([[United Kingdom|UK]])'s list of the 100 Greatest Sexy Moments in Film.&lt;ref name=&quot;chan4&quot;/&gt; Raquel Welch appeared in five interjected repetitions of &quot;Raquel Welch in a fur bikini&quot; becoming the one special thing that increased the value of the film, making people want to see it again and again.&lt;ref&gt;Karín Lesnik-Oberstein, ''The Last Taboo: Women and Body Hair'', page 172, Manchester University Press, 2006, ISBN 0-7190-7500-9&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Bollywood]] actress [[Sharmila Tagore]] struck a memorable moment{{pov statement|date=August 2011}} in 1967 when she appeared in a bikini in ''[[An Evening in Paris]]'',&lt;ref&gt;Stuff Reporter, &quot;[http://www.hindu.com/mp/2006/04/03/stories/2006040301320100.htm Being Sharmila, all through life]&quot;, ''The Hindu'', 2006-04-03&lt;/ref&gt; a film mostly remembered for the first bikini appearance of an [[India]]n actress.&lt;ref&gt;Lalit Mohan Joshi &amp; Gulzar, Derek Malcolm, ''Bollywood'', page 20, Lucky Dissanayake, 2002, ISBN 0-9537032-2-3&lt;/ref&gt; She also posed in a bikini for the glossy ''[[Filmfare]]'' magazine.&lt;ref&gt;B. K. Karanjia, ''Blundering in Wonderland‎'', page 18, Vikas Publishing House, 1990, ISBN 0-7069-4961-7&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://123india.santabanta.com/cinema.asp?pid=3236 Sharmila Tagore], Showbiz Legends, SantaBanta&lt;/ref&gt; The costume shocked the conservative Indian audience,&lt;ref&gt;Various writers, ''Rashtriya Sahara'', page 28, Sahara India Mass Communication, 2002&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Manjima Bhattacharjya, &quot;[http://timesofindia.indiatimes.com/Why_the_bikini_is_badnaam/articleshow/2568307.cms Why the bikini is badnaam]&quot;, ''Times of India'', 2007-11-25&lt;/ref&gt; but it also set a trend of bikini-clad actresses carried forward by [[Parveen Babi]] (in ''[[Yeh Nazdeekiyan]]'', 1982&lt;ref name=avi&gt;Avijit Ghosh, &quot;[http://timesofindia.indiatimes.com/articleshow/1696458.cms Bollywood's unfinished revolution]&quot;, ''The Times of India'', 2006-07-02&lt;/ref&gt;), [[Zeenat Aman]] (in ''[[Heera Panna]]'' 1973; ''[[Qurbani (1980 film)|Qurbani]]'', 1980&lt;ref name=avi/&gt;) and [[Dimple Kapadia]] (in ''[[Bobby (1973 film)|Bobby]]'', 1973&lt;ref name=avi/&gt;) in the early 1970s.&lt;ref&gt;Stuff Reporter, &quot;[http://www1.timesofindia.indiatimes.com/articleshow/1655251.cms That itsy bitsy thing]&quot;, ''Times of India'', 2006-06-16&lt;/ref&gt; Wearing a bikini put her name in the Indian press as one of Bollywood's ten hottest actresses of all time,&lt;ref&gt;Subhash K Jha, &quot;[http://timesofindia.indiatimes.com/cms.dll/html/uncomp/articleshow?artid=34899626 Bollywood's 10 hottest actresses of all time], ''Times of India'', 2003-01-19&lt;/ref&gt; and was a transgression of female identity through a reversal of the state of modesty, which functions as a signifier of femininity in Bombay films.&lt;ref&gt;Sumita S. Chakravarty, ''National Identity in Indian Popular Cinema, 1947-1987‎'', page 321, University of Texas Press, 1993, ISBN 0-292-75551-1&lt;/ref&gt; But, when Tagore was the chairperson of the [[Central Board of Film Certification]], she expressed concerns about the rise of the bikini in Indian films.&lt;ref&gt;Preeti Mudliar, &quot;[http://cities.expressindia.com/fullstory.php?newsid=124512 Without Cuts]&quot;, ''Pune Newsline'', 2005-04-11&lt;/ref&gt; By that time it became usual for actors to change outfits a dozen times in a single song — starting with a [[Chiffon (fabric)|chiffon]] [[sari]] and ending up wearing a bikini.&lt;ref&gt;Stephen Alter, ''Fantasies of a Bollywood Love Thief: Inside the World of Indian Moviemaking‎'', page 7, Harcourt, 2007, ISBN 0-15-603084-5&lt;/ref&gt; In [[Nissim Ezekiel]]'s one act [[Indian English literature|Indian English]] moral play ''[[The Song of Deprivation]]'', the protagonist becomes a &quot;different woman altogether&quot; as she takes off her bikini and gets into a sari.&lt;ref&gt;Sudhakar Pandey &amp; Freya Taraporewala, ''Studies in Contemporary Indian Drama'',‎ page 84, Prestige Books in association with Indian Society for Commonwealth Studies, 1990, ISBN 81-85218-18-8&lt;/ref&gt; Cultural and literary evidence, especially in the form of [[Calypso music|calypsos]] (&quot;Whole day she jumping shamelessly/In a tiny little bikini&quot;), show that [[Indo-Caribbean]]s, people with roots in the [[Indian subcontinent]] who reside in the [[Caribbean]], were more receptive of the bikini than people of their original homeland.&lt;ref&gt;Tejaswini Niranjana, ''Mobilizing India'', pages 138-139, Duke University Press, 2006, ISBN 0-8223-3842-4&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:Pamela Anderson 2.jpg|thumb|187px|[[PETA]] used [[Pamela Anderson]] for an advertisement campaign to promote [[vegetarianism]]]]

During the 1980s and early 1990s, the one-piece made a big comeback. In France, Réard's company folded in 1988,&lt;ref name=SFC/&gt; four years after his death.&lt;ref name=IndeR/&gt; By that year the bikini made up nearly 20% of swimsuit sales, more than any other model in the US.&lt;ref name=WOJSI/&gt; As [[skin cancer]] awareness grew and a simpler aesthetic defined fashion in the 1990s, sales of the skimpy bikini decreased dramatically. The new swimwear code was epitomized by surf star [[Malia Jones]], who appeared on the June 1997 cover of ''[[Shape Magazine]]'' wearing a [[halter top]] two-piece for rough water.&lt;ref name=Lil/&gt; After the 90s, however, the bikini came back again. US market research company [[NPD Group]] reported that sales of two-piece swimsuits nationwide jumped 80% in two years.&lt;ref name=BBCW/&gt; In the 1970s and 80s, bikinis became briefer with the string bikini.&lt;ref name=asseen/&gt; According to Beth Dincuff Charleston, research associate at the Costume Institute of the Metropolitan Museum of Art, &quot;The bikini represents a social leap involving body consciousness, moral concerns, and sexual attitudes.&quot;&lt;ref name=heritage/&gt; According to Gina Bellafonte of ''[[The New York Times]]'', actresses in [[action film]]s like ''[[Charlie's Angels: Full Throttle]]'' and ''[[Blue Crush]]'' have made the two-piece &quot;the millennial equivalent of the power suit.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;heritage&quot;/&gt; [[People for the Ethical Treatment of Animals|PETA]] used celebrities like [[Pamela Anderson]], [[Traci Bingham]] and [[Alicia Mayer]] wearing a bikini made of [[Lettuce#Cultivars|iceberg-lettuce]] for an advertisement campaign to promote [[vegetarianism]].&lt;ref&gt;News desk, &quot;[http://www.iol.co.za/index.php?sf=29&amp;set_id=1&amp;click_id=29&amp;art_id=qw1124867521722B234 Nudity with a cause]&quot;, ''Independent Online'', 2005-08-24&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Alexander Villafania, &quot;[Alicia Mayer wears lettuce bikini for a cause]&quot;, ''Inquirer'', 2007-02-28&lt;/ref&gt; A protester from [[Columbia University]] used a bikini as a message board against a [[New York City]] visit by [[Iran]]ian president [[Mahmoud Ahmadinejad]]&lt;ref&gt;Karen A Arenson,&quot;[http://www.nytimes.com/2007/09/25/us/25protest.html?pagewanted=print A Campus Buzzes With Protest and Political Debate]&quot;, ''The New York Times'', 2007-09-25&lt;/ref&gt;

The &quot;''-kini'' family&quot; (as dubbed by author [[William Safire]]&lt;ref&gt;William Safire, ''No Uncertain Terms'' , page 291, Simon &amp; Schuster, 2003, ISBN 0-7432-4955-0&lt;/ref&gt;), including the &quot;''-ini'' sisters&quot; (as dubbed by designer Anne Cole&lt;ref&gt;Trish Donnally, &quot;[http://www.sfgate.com/cgi-bin/article.cgi?f=/c/a/1999/05/18/DD105172.DTL&amp;hw=CARGO+PANTS&amp;sn=088&amp;sc=171 &quot;Inis&quot; Are In]&quot;, ''San Francisco Chronicle'', 1999-05-18&lt;/ref&gt;) has grown to include a large number of subsequent variations, often with a hilarious lexicon &amp;mdash; [[string bikini]], [[monokini]] or numokini (top part missing), seekini (transparent bikini), [[tankini]] (tank top, bikini bottom), camikini ([[camisole]] top and bikini bottom), hikini, [[thong (clothing)|thong]], slingshot, minimini, teardrop, and micro.&lt;ref&gt;Barry J. Blake, ''Playing with Words: Humour in the English Language‎'', page 59, Equinox, 2007, ISBN 1-84553-330-5&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;David Diefendorf &amp; James Randi, ''Amazing... But False!: Hundreds of &quot;Facts&quot; You Thought Were True, But Aren't'', page 33, Sterling, 2007, ISBN 1-4027-3791-2&lt;/ref&gt; In just one major fashion show in 1985, there  were two-piece suits with [[Crop top|cropped tank tops]] instead of the usual skimpy bandeaux, suits that are bikinis in front and one-piece behind, [[Suspenders|suspender straps]], [[ruffle]]s, and daring, navel-baring cutouts.&lt;ref&gt;Fashion Correspondent, &quot;[http://nl.newsbank.com/nl-search/we/Archives?p_product=PI&amp;s_site=philly&amp;p_multi=PI&amp;p_theme=realcities&amp;p_action=search&amp;p_maxdocs=200&amp;p_topdoc=1&amp;p_text_direct-0=0EB29A230AE055D5&amp;p_field_direct-0=document_id&amp;p_perpage=10&amp;p_sort=YMD_date:D&amp;s_trackval=GooglePM Swimsuits take some inspiration from the past]&quot;, ''Philadelphia Inquirer'', 1985-11-10&lt;/ref&gt; To meet the fast changing tastes, some of the manufacturers have made a business out of making made-to-order bikinis in around seven minutes.&lt;ref&gt;Siobhan Morrissey, &quot;[http://nl.newsbank.com/nl-search/we/Archives?p_product=PBPB&amp;p_theme=pbpb&amp;p_action=search&amp;p_maxdocs=200&amp;p_topdoc=1&amp;p_text_direct-0=0EAF84758A18E87D&amp;p_field_direct-0=document_id&amp;p_perpage=10&amp;p_sort=YMD_date:D&amp;s_trackval=GooglePM Bikinis made in teeny-weeny time], ''Palm Beach Post'', page 1D, 1991-08-28&lt;/ref&gt; The world's most expensive bikini was designed in February 2006 by Susan Rosen. The bikini, made up of over {{convert|150|carat|g}} of flawless diamonds, was worth a massive £20 million.&lt;ref name=YorkS/&gt;

==Controversies==
===The &quot;body ideal&quot;===
In the 1960s Emily Post decreed, &quot;(A bikini) is for perfect figures only, and for the very young.&quot; In ''[[The Bikini Book]]'' by [[Kelly Killoren Bensimon]], responding to a question on who should not wear a bikini, swimwear designer [[Norma Kamali]] says, &quot;Anyone with a tummy.&quot; Since then, a number of bikini designers including [[Malia Mills]] have encouraged women of all ages and body types to take up the style. The 1970s saw the rise of the lean ideal of female body and figures like [[Cheryl Tiegs]] possessed the figure that remains in vogue today. The fitness boom of the 1980s led to one of the biggest leaps in the evolution of the bikini. According to swimwear designer Malia Mills, &quot;The leg line became superhigh, the front was superlow, and the straps were superthin.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.lilith-ezine.com/articles/2006/The-Bikini.html The Bikini turns 60! from the Lilith Gallery of Toronto]. Retrieved 9 February 2009.&lt;/ref&gt; Women's magazines used terms like &quot;Bikini Belly&quot;,&lt;ref&gt;Alex Kuczynski, &quot;[http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CEEDB1E3EF937A15755C0A9679C8B63 Looking for Health News? A Bikini Belly? There's More to Read]&quot;, ''The New York Times'', 2001-06-21&lt;/ref&gt; workout programs were launched to develop a &quot;bikini-worthy body&quot;,&lt;ref&gt;Jennifer Nicole Lee, &quot;[http://www.cbsnews.com/stories/2007/02/12/health/healthy_living/main2463528.shtml Get A Bikini-Worthy Body]&quot;, ''CBS News'', Feb. 1, 2007-02-01&lt;/ref&gt; while the tiny &quot;fitness-bikinis&quot; made of [[lycra]] were launched to cater to the hardbodied ideal.&lt;ref&gt;Stuart B. Chirls, &quot;[http://www.highbeam.com/doc/1G1-7827637.html Americans head for the water - in, on and under]&quot;, ''Daily News Herald'', 1989-07-31&lt;/ref&gt; The ideal was carried further by models like [[Elle Macpherson]], featured six times on the cover of [[Sports Illustrated Swimsuit Issue]].&lt;ref name=AgeL/&gt; In one section of the ''Bikini Book'', professional beach volleyballer [[Gabrielle Reece]], who competes in a bikini, says that &quot;confidence&quot; alone can make a bikini sexy.&lt;ref name=ArtCent/&gt; Faced with sexpot supermodels and the cult of body consciousness, a shift away from the bikini remains, offering passive resistance to the concept that &quot;if you've got it, you have to flaunt it&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;menkes&quot;/&gt;

===Cultural controversies===
In 1996, when the Miss World contest was held in [[Bangalore]], India, dozens of Indian groups opposed the event claiming that the contest degraded women by featuring them in bikinis. Social activist Subhashini Ali commented, &quot;It's not an IQ test. Neither is it a charity show. It's a beauty contest in which these things have been added on as sops.&quot; The protests were so intense that the organizers were finally compelled to shift the venue of the &quot;Swimsuit Round&quot; to [[Seychelles]].&lt;ref&gt;News Desk, [http://web.archive.org/web/20031217161734/http://www.cnn.com/WORLD/9611/23/miss.world/index.html Miss Greece now Miss World, despite pageant protests], CNN, 1996-11-23&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Anita Pratap, [http://web.archive.org/web/20030404132350/http://www.cnn.com/WORLD/9611/22/india.miss.world/index.html Indian police prepare for worst in beauty pageant clash], CNN, 1996-11-22&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Anita Pratap, [http://www.cnn.com/WORLD/9611/17/miss.world/index.html Beauty pageant in India becomes a contest of wills], CNN, 1996-11-17&lt;/ref&gt; Afghan [[Miss Earth]] 2003 contestant [[Vida Samadzai]] (born in Afghanistan, raised in USA and living in India&lt;ref name=Fida&gt;Ayesha Matthan, &quot;[http://www.hindu.com/mp/2007/12/18/stories/2007121850150600.htm Fida over Vida]&quot;, ''The Hindu'', 2007-12-18&lt;/ref&gt;) was severely condemned by the both the Afghan authority and community.&lt;ref name=Gersh&gt;Gersh Kuntzman, &quot;[http://gershkuntzman.homestead.com/files/Beauty_is_a_Beast.htm Beauty is a Beast]&quot;, ''Newsweek'', 2003-11-03&lt;/ref&gt; The [[Afghan Supreme Court]], banning such contests, said that appearing naked in beauty contests is totally un-Islamic, and is against Afghan tradition, human honour and dignity. Afghan women affairs minister, [[Habiba Sarabi]], said her semi-naked appearance &quot;is not women's freedom but in my opinion is to entertain men&quot;. Afghanistan's embassy in Washington DC declared that claims by [[Afghan American]] Samadzai to represent Afghanistan is baseless.&lt;ref&gt;News desk, &quot;[http://www.iol.co.za/index.php?click_id=126&amp;art_id=qw1067503501825B212&amp;set_id=1 Afghan Supreme Court bans beauty pageants]&quot;, ''Independent Online'', 2003-09-30&lt;/ref&gt; Samadzai, the second woman to be crowned Miss Afghanistan after [[Zohra Daoud]]'s crowing in 1972, received a number of death threats and had to be under the protection of [[FBI]] for three months.&lt;ref name=Gersh/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Farhad J. Dadyburjor, &quot;[http://www.dnaindia.com/report.asp?NewsID=1049966 I was under FBI's watch for 3 months: Miss Afghanistan]&quot;, ''Daily News and Analysis'', 2006-06-29&lt;/ref&gt; She said she was bit uncomfortable wearing the skimpy &quot;70s style red bikini&quot;, and was aware of the risks involved.&lt;ref name=Fida/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;News Desk, &quot;[http://www.accessmylibrary.com/coms2/summary_0286-19308457_ITM Miss Afghanistan says she was uncomfortable wearing bikini, goal is to help women and children back home]&quot;, ''Financial Times'', 2003-11-07&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Kimi Yoshino, &quot;[http://www.highbeam.com/doc/1P1-87832327.html Causing a stir, all because of a bikini]&quot;, ''Times New Service '', 2003-11-28&lt;/ref&gt; Bikini related [[wardrobe malfunction]]s including [[wedgie]]s, [[whale tail]]s or bikini tops falling off have also stirred controversies.&lt;ref name=AgeL/&gt; In April 2004, a bikini line with images of [[Buddha]] printed on it was withdrawn by [[Victoria's Secret]], the manufacturer, in the face of protest by followers of [[Buddhism]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.expressindia.com/news/fullstory.php?newsid=30628 Buddha bikini upsets believers], Express India (quoting [[Reuters]]), 2004-04-21&lt;/ref&gt; Buddhists were upset again when organizers of [[Miss Universe]] 2005 shot photographs of contestants in bikini in front of Buddhist religious sites.&lt;ref&gt;[http://english.people.com.cn/200505/18/eng20050518_185661.html Beauty pageant's bikini shot incurs controversy in Buddhist Thailand], People's Daily Online (Quoting [[Xinhua]]), 2005-05-18&lt;/ref&gt;

===Health aspects===
Alongside controversies about the body ideal projected by the bikini and various cultural issues, there also is a concern about excess exposure of the skin to sun and the health hazards involved.&lt;ref name=&quot;menkes&quot; /&gt;

==References==
;Notes
{{reflist|2}}

==External links==
{{commonscat|Bikinis}}
* [http://articles.latimes.com/2010/may/23/image/la-ig-0523-timeline-20100523/2 &quot;Bikini Timeline&quot;], ''[[Los Angeles Times]]''
* [http://www.bikiniscience.com/bsmain.html Bikini Science -- A Comprehensive History of the Bikini and Species of Swimwear]
* [http://www.vintagefashionguild.org/VFGSITECA/SWIMSUITS/VFG_Swim.html Cole of California and history of the bikini]

{{DEFAULTSORT:History Of The Bikini}}
[[Category:1946 introductions]]
[[Category:History of clothing]]
[[Category:Bikinis]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
