<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="2162571" ns="0" title="Donna Fiducia"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{BLP sources|date=June 2011}}
{{Infobox Person
| name        = Donna Fiducia
| image       =  
| image_size  =  
| caption     =  
| birth_name  = Donna Cara Fiducia
| birth_date  = {{birth date and age|mf=yes|1956|12|05}}
| birth_place = [[Essex County, New Jersey]], [[USA]]
| education   = [[Seton Hall University]]
| nationality = American
| occupation  = [[Media Personality]]
| spouse      = Don Neuen (engaged to)
| children    = Jeffrey, Thomas
| website     = http://www.donnafiducia.com/ and http://www.ddhorses.com/
| religion    = [[Christian]]
|residence    = [[Roopville, Georgia]]
|home_town    = [[Maplewood, New Jersey]]
}}

'''Donna Fiducia''' (born December 5, 1956) is an American media personality who worked in New York television and radio for 26 years.

Fiducia gained international recognition when she was hired by [[The Fox News Channel]], New York, NY in September 1999 as an anchor and live host.  In 2003, she was reassigned to overnight duty where she was both a long-form and news update anchorwoman.  In late 2006, she retired from The Fox News Channel and relocated to Georgia.

Prior to The Fox News Channel, she worked at Fox-owned [[WNYW]] in New York City.  In her four years at WNYW, she was a general assignment reporter for the 10 o'clock news. She also anchored ''Good Day New York'' and ''Good Day Sunday'' where she not only anchored the news but did celebrity and lifestyle interviews.

Fiducia gained national recognition as the host of ''Entertainment Watch''  on [[VH-1]], featuring entertainment news and celebrity interviews from movie stars to musicians.

She became New York's first television helicopter traffic reporter at [[WNBC-TV]] in 1995. She was also a general assignment reporter for ''Live At Five'', the 6 and 11 o'clock news and ''Weekend Today''.

Fiducia began her career at [[Shadow Traffic]] in New York. She went on to report from [[WNBC (AM)|WNBC]]  Radio's &quot;N Copter&quot; where she worked daily with [[Howard Stern]] and [[Don Imus]]. She was also the news director and morning news anchor of the famed rock radio station [[WNEW-FM]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://articles.nydailynews.com/1995-05-11/entertainment/17966447_1_howard-stern-fm-radio From Chopping Block To News Chopper]&lt;/ref&gt;

Fiducia also has done some acting in the first rap-influenced feature length movie, ''Tougher Than Leather'' with [[Run DMC]], and on the 1980 [[CBS]] television show ''[[The Equalizer]]'' in which she performed the role of a newscaster.

In 2006, she was in the movie ''Being Michael Madsen'' in which she again played the role of a reporter.

Fiducia graduated from [[Columbia High School (New Jersey)|Columbia High School]] in [[Maplewood, NJ]] in 1975, and subsequently graduated [[Magna Cum Laude]] from [[Seton Hall University]] with degrees in both Communications and Political Science.  She was active in the college's radio station, [[WSOU-FM]].  She also studied flute and piccolo during this time.

Fiducia is an avid horseback rider and has won numerous state and national championships in equestrian events as a hunter/jumper.  In addition, she is competing at barrel racing in rodeos.

Currently, Fiducia resides in Georgia where she owns, raises and trains champion warmbloods and quarterhorses on her horse farm, [[Double D Ranch]].

In 2007, she founded her own Georgia based production company, [[Donna Fiducia Productions, Inc.]] which specializes in media production, soundtrack music, voiceover talent, media training, and political campaigns marketing. She currently serves as President and CEO of the company.

In addition, Fiducia is in demand as a featured speaker, college lecturer, and as a moderator.  She is also a media coach and political adviser.
==References==
{{Reflist}}

==External links==
*[http://www.donnafiducia.com/ Donna Fiducia's Official Site]
*{{IMDb name|2289602}}

{{Persondata &lt;!-- Metadata: see [[Wikipedia:Persondata]]. --&gt;
| NAME              =Fiducia, Donna
| ALTERNATIVE NAMES =
| SHORT DESCRIPTION =
| DATE OF BIRTH     =December 5, 1956
| PLACE OF BIRTH    =[[Essex County, New Jersey]], [[USA]]
| DATE OF DEATH     =
| PLACE OF DEATH    =
}}
{{DEFAULTSORT:Fiducia, Donna}}
[[Category:American television reporters and correspondents]]
[[Category:Seton Hall University alumni]]
[[Category:1956 births]]
[[Category:Living people]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
