<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="216776" ns="0" title="Laguna (province)"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{About|the province of Laguna|the biggest lake in the Philippines|Laguna de Bay|other uses|Laguna (disambiguation){{!}}Laguna}}
{{unref|date=December 2011}}
{{Infobox province
| name                    = Province of Laguna
| native_name             = Lalawigan ng Laguna
| official_name           = 
| settlement_type         = [[Provinces of the Philippines|Province]]
| image_skyline           = 
| image_alt               = 
| image_caption           = 
| image_flag              = 
| flag_alt                = 
| image_seal              = Ph seal laguna.png
| seal_alt                = 
| image_shield            = 
| shield_alt              = 
| nickname                = &quot;Resort Capital, Detroit and Silicon Valley of the Philippines&quot;
| motto                   = '''BAGONG LAGUNA, Una sa Lahat!''' &lt;br&gt; (NEW LAGUNA, First of all!)
| image_map               = Ph locator map laguna.png
| map_alt                 = 
| map_caption             = Map of the Philippines with Laguna highlighted
| latd  =  14|latm  =  10|lats  =  |latNS  = N
| longd =  121|longm =  20|longs =  |longEW = E
| coordinates_type        = region:PH_type:adm1st_source:GNS-enwiki
| coordinates_display     = inline,title
| coordinates_footnotes   = 
| subdivision_type        = [[List of sovereign states|Country]]
| subdivision_name        = {{flag|Philippines}}
| subdivision_type1       = [[Regions of the Philippines|Region]]
| subdivision_name1       = [[CALABARZON]] (Region IV-A)
| established_title       = Founded
| established_date        = March 10, 1917
| seat_type               = Capital
| seat                    = [[Santa Cruz, Laguna|Santa Cruz]]
| government_type         = [[Province]] of the [[Philippines]]
| leader_title            = [[Governor]]
| leader_name             = [[E.R. Ejercito|Emilio Ramon Ejercito]] ([[Pwersa ng Masang Pilipino|PMP]])
| leader_party            = 
| leader_title1           = [[Vice Governor]]
| leader_name1            = Caesar Perez (Bigkis Pinoy)
| leader_party1           = 
| area_total_km2          = 1823.6
| area_rank               = 65th out of 80
| area_note               =
| population_total        = 2473530
| population_as_of        = 2007
| population_rank         = 6th out of 80
| population_density_km2  = auto
| population_density_rank = 3rd out of 80
| population_note         = 
| elevation_m             = 
| demographics_type1      = Divisions
| demographics1_footnotes = &lt;!-- for references: use &lt;ref&gt; tags --&gt;
| demographics1_title1    = [[Cities of the Philippines#Independent cities|Independent&amp;nbsp;cities]]
| demographics1_info1     = 0
| demographics1_title2    = [[Cities of the Philippines|Component cities]] 
| demographics1_info2     = 4
| demographics1_title3    = [[Municipalities of the Philippines|Municipalities]]
| demographics1_info3     = 26
| demographics1_title4    = [[Barangay]]s
| demographics1_info4     = 674
| demographics1_title5    = [[House of Representatives of the Philippines|Districts]]
| demographics1_info5     = [[Legislative districts of Laguna|1st to 4th districts of Laguna]]
| blank_name_sec1         = Spoken languages
| blank_info_sec1         = [[Tagalog language|Tagalog]], [[English language|English]]
| timezone                = [[Philippine Standard Time|PHT]]
| utc_offset              = +8
| postal_code_type        = [[List of ZIP codes in the Philippines|ZIP Code]]
| postal_code             = 4000-4033
| website                 = [http://www.laguna.gov.ph www.laguna.gov.ph]
| footnotes               = 
}}
'''Laguna''' (PSGC: [http://www.nscb.gov.ph/activestats/psgc/province.asp?provcode=043400000&amp;regName=REGION%20IV-A%20(CALABARZON) 035400000]; [[ISO 3166-2:PH|'''ISO''': PH-LAG]]) is a [[Provinces of the Philippines|province]] of the [[Philippines]] found in the [[CALABARZON]] [[Regions of the Philippines|region]] in [[Luzon]]. Its capital is [[Santa Cruz, Laguna|Santa Cruz]] and the province is located southeast of [[Metro Manila]], south of the province of [[Rizal province|Rizal]], west of [[Quezon]], north of [[Batangas]] and east of [[Cavite]]. Laguna almost completely surrounds  [[Laguna de Bay]], the largest lake in the country. The province acquired its name from the [[Spanish language|Spanish]] word ''lago'', which means ''lake'' or ''lagoon''. The city with the highest population (based on 2007 census) is [[Calamba City]], while the least poluation is the [[Famy, Laguna|Municipality of Famy]].

Laguna is notable for being the birthplace of [[Jose Rizal]], the country's national hero. Laguna is also famous among tourists for the [[Pagsanjan Falls]], the [[University of the Philippines, Los Baños|University of the Philippines]] campus and the hot spring resorts in [[Los Baños, Laguna|Los Baños]] and [[Calamba City]], on the slopes of [[Mount Makiling]], [[Pila, Laguna|Pila]] Town Plaza, Taytay Falls, [[Majayjay]], the wood carvings and ''papier mache'' created by the people of [[Paete, Laguna|Paeté]], the ''turumba'' of [[Pakil, Laguna|Pakil]], the [[Seven Lakes of San Pablo|Seven Lakes of San Pablo City]] (San Pablo City is the first city in the province) and Hidden Valley Springs in [[Calauan]].

Currently, the province has a metropolitan area namely the Laguna West Metro, as it has the cities and towns nearest the [[National Capital Region]]. Laguna West Metro consists of 3 cities ([[Binan|Biñan City]], [[Calamba City]] and [[Santa Rosa City]]) and 4 municipalities ([[Bay, Laguna|Bay]], [[Cabuyao, Laguna|Cabuyao]], [[Los Baños, Laguna|Los Baños]] and [[San Pedro, Laguna|San Pedro]]). Laguna is also considered as the richest and the most progressive province in the Philippines. 

==History==
[[File:Luisiana Catholic Church.jpg|thumb|200px|Luisiana Catholic Church]]
[[File:Church of Liliw, Facade.jpg|thumb|200px|Liliw Catholic Church]]
The Province of Laguna was named after [[Laguna de Bay]], the body of water that forms its northern boundary. Laguna de Bay, in turn, was named after the town of [[Bay, Laguna|Bay]] (''Laguna de Bay'' is Spanish which means &quot;Lake of Bay&quot;), the first provincial capital. Captain [[Juan de Salcedo]] with a band of one hundred Spanish-Mexican soldiers and many Bisayan allies conquered the province and its surrounding regions for [[Spain]] in 1571. Seven years later, two [[Franciscan]] friars started the work of Christianisation.

In 1577, the Franciscan missionaries arrived in [[Manila]], and in 1578 they started evangelizing Laguna, Morong (now [[Rizal]]), [[Tayabas Province|Tayabas]] (now [[Quezon]]) and the [[Bicol Peninsula]]. [[Juan de Plasencia]] and Diego de Oropesa were the earliest Franciscans sent to these places. From 1580, the towns of [[Bay]], Caliraya, Majayjay, Nagcarlán, [[Liliw]], [[Pila, Laguna|Pila]], [[Santa Cruz, Laguna|Santa Cruz]], [[Lumban]], Pángil and [[Siniloan]] were founded. In 1678, Fray Hernando Cabrera founded San Pablo de los Montes (now [[San Pablo City]]) and built a wooden church and convent considered as the best and finest in the province.

In 1670, [[delimitation]] of borders were made between [[Lucban]], [[Majayjay]] and [[Cavite]]. The populous town at that time was [[Bay, Laguna|Bay]], the capital of the province until 1688, when the seat of the provincial government was moved to Pagsanján, and later in 1858, to Santa Cruz. In 1754, the Province of Laguna and [[Quezon|Tayabas]] were divided, with the Malinao River separating the towns of Majayjay and Lucbán.

The province became a bloody battle ground for the Chinese during the two instances that they rose in revolt against Spain. In 1603s, the Chinese made their last stand in the mountains of San Pablo, and in 1639, they fortified themselves in the highlands of [[Cavinti]] and [[Lumban]], surrendering in [[Pagsanjan]] a year later.

The natives of Laguna proved loyal to the Spanish crown during the British invasion (1762–1764) when thousands rallied to its defense. When a detachment of British troops under Captain Thomas Backhouse entered the province in search of the silver cargo of the galleon Filipino, Francisco de San Juan of Pagsanján led a band of volunteers that fought them in several engagements in and around the town which was then the provincial capital (1688–1858). Backhouse plundered the town and burned its newly reconstructed church but San Juan succeeded in escaping with the precious hoard to Pampanga where the treasure greatly bolstered the defense effort of [[Simón de Anda y Salazar|Simón de Anda]], leader of the resistance movement. For his heroism, San Juan was made a brigade commander and alcalde mayor of Tayabas (now [[Quezon]]) province.

The people's loyalty gradually degenerated into bitter hostility. Grave abuses by the colonizers, especially those of the clergy, caused the resentment of the natives to be fanned into a rising flood of insurrection. In 1840 for instance, religious intolerance led the people of Majayjay, Nagcarlan, [[Bay]], and [[Biñan]] to join the revolt of [[Hermano Pule]] ([[Apolinario de la Cruz]]) of [[Lucban]], Tayabas.

Laguna was also exposed to the aspirations of its most famous son, [[Dr. José Rizal]], who was born in [[Calamba City]]. The persecution of the Rizal family, along with their fellow landowners toward the end of the century further aggravated the situation. In 1896, thousands of inhabitants, especially of [[Bay]], [[Los Baños, Laguna|Los Baños]], Nagcarlan, [[Magdalena, Laguna|Magdalena]], [[Santa Cruz, Laguna|Santa Cruz]], and [[Pagsanjan]] had joined the revolutionary Katipunan.

[[Image:Philippines Paete Catholic Church.JPG|thumb|right|200px|A Spanish colonial church in [[Paete]], Laguna, with the [[Sierra Madre (Philippines)|Sierra Madre]] mountain range at the background.]]
Laguna was one of the eight provinces to rise in revolt against the Spanish misrule led by Generals [[Paciano Rizal]] of [[Calamba City]], [[Severino Taino]] of [[Pagsanján]], Agueda Kahabagan of [[Calauan]], and [[Miguel Malvar]] of [[Batangas]]. The ill-equipped revolutionaries fought the well-armed enemy until on August 31, 1898, when the last Spanish garrison surrendered to the victorious patriots in Santa Cruz. The province was cleared of Spaniards. There had been only one respite, the [[Pact of Biak-na-Bato]] on December 14 to 15, 1897.

Laguna actively supported the first Philippine Republic proclaimed at [[Malolos]] on January 23, 1899. Its two delegates to the [[Malolos Congress]] were Don Higino Benítez and Don Graciano Cordero, both natives of Pagsanján.

Upon the outbreak of the Filipino-American War (1899–1901), Generals Juan Cailles and Paciano Rizal led the defense of Laguna until June 30, 1901, when surrender became inevitable. Cailles became the first Filipino Governor of Laguna under the American flag.

The Province of Laguna progressed rapidly in peace. Roads were built, schools were established, and in 1917, the Manila Railroad Company extended its line to Laguna as far as Pagsanjan.

During the [[Japanese occupation of the Philippines]] (1942–1945), Laguna was a center of Filipino resistance despite the presence of [[Makapili]] collaborators. 

The establishment of the military general headquarters and military camp bases of the Philippine Commonwealth Army and the Philippine Constabulary is a military unit organization was founded on 1942 to 1946 in the province of Laguna, and aided of the local military regular units of the Philippine Commonwealth Army 4th and 42nd Infantry Division and the Philippine Constabulary 4th Infantry Regiment. Started the engagements of the Anti-Japanese Military Operations in Southern Luzon, Mindoro and Palawan from 1942 to 1945 against the Japanese Imperial forces.

Beginning in 1945, attacks by the Filipino soldiers of the 4th, 41st, 42nd, 43rd, 45th, 46th and 47th Infantry Division of the Philippine Commonwealth Army, 4th Infantry Regiment of the Philippine Constabulary and the recognized guerrillas against Japanese forces in Laguna increased in anticipation of the Liberation of the Philippines by joint Filipino &amp; American forces.

Present-day Laguna shows a thriving economy. Peopled by 2,473,530 (2009 Population) industrious citizens and possessing a total area of 1760&amp;nbsp;km² of land, Laguna produces millions of pesos worth of coconuts, rice, sugar, citrus fruits, lanzones and other products. Tourists flock to its beauty spots, especially [[Pagsanjan Falls]], [[Calamba City]] and [[Los Baños, Laguna|Los Banos]] hotsprings, Makiling National Park, Caliraya Lake and many others. Levels of development vary. The towns near Metro Manila have become industrialized whereas the inner towns continue to engage in agricultural production or pursue agri-based industries and cottage and small-scale industries.

==Government Members (2010-2013)==
*'''Governor''': [[E. R. Ejercito|Emilio Ramon &quot;Jeorge Estregan&quot; P. Ejercito III]] ([[Pwersa ng Masang Pilipino|PMP]])
*'''Vice-Governor''': Caesar Perez (Bigkis Pinoy)

===House of Representatives===
*'''[[Legislative districts of Laguna#1st District|1st District]]''': [[Danilo Fernandez|Dr. Danilo Ramon &quot;Dan&quot; S. Fernandez]] ([[Liberal Party (Philippines)|Liberal]])
*'''[[Legislative districts of Laguna#2nd District|2nd District]]''': Atty. Justin Marc &quot;Timmy&quot; S.B. Chipeco ([[Nacionalista Party|Nacionalista]])
*'''[[Legislative districts of Laguna#3rd District|3rd District]]''': Ma. Evita &quot;Ivy&quot; R. Arago ([[Liberal Party (Philippines)|Liberal]])
*'''[[Legislative districts of Laguna#4th District|4th District]]''': Edgar &quot;Egay&quot; S. San Luis ([[Nationalist People's Coalition|NPC]])

===Board Members===
'''1st District''':
*Gabnulang &quot;Gab&quot; A. Alatiit
*Carlo M. Almoro
*Emilio &quot;Emil&quot; M. Tiongco

'''2nd District''':
*Neptali &quot;Ninoy&quot; B. Bagnes
*Neil Andrew &quot;Neil&quot; N. Nocon
*Juan &quot;Johnny&quot; M. Unico

'''3rd District''':
*[[Angelica Jones|Angelica &quot;Angelica Jones&quot; B. Alarva]]
*Reynaldo &quot;Rey&quot; D. Paras

'''4th District''':
*Joseph Kris Benjamin &quot;Benjo&quot; B. Agarao
*Benedicto Mario &quot;Bong&quot; C. Palacol, Jr.

==Economy==


*'''Natural Resources:''' Laguna is endowed with abundant natural resources. Its forests are filled with bamboo, rattan, and soft hardwood. Its wide fields and vast forests are ideal for growing rice, coconuts, vegetables, tropical fruits, orchids, and other ornamental flowers and exotic plants. The province is also rich in mineral resources such as clay, jasper and basalt glass.

There are about forty rivers in Laguna with a total area of almost 0.5 square kilometres. In the forests of Mount Makiling and in the waters of [[Laguna de Bay]] are an abundance of flora and fauna. The [[Laguna de Bay]] has an approximate area of 3800&amp;nbsp;km² broken down into 2900&amp;nbsp;km² of land and 900&amp;nbsp;km² of lake proper with 220&amp;nbsp;km shoreline.

Laguna's greatest natural resource is water. It has an estimated 300 million US gallons (1,100,000&amp;nbsp;m³) of underground water, capable of generating energy for Laguna's expanding power needs. At least seven principal water basins in the province with a total of 5,773&amp;nbsp;km² drainage area and 1,316&amp;nbsp;km² level area provide an estimated 9.238&amp;nbsp;km³ total run-off annually.

* '''Agricultural Activities:''' Crop Production, Livestock and Poultry Production, Fishing

* '''Investment Opportunities:''' Ecotourism enterprises; Convention centers; Coconut inter-cropping; Forest Trees, Cutflowers &amp; ornamentals; Fruit &amp; vegetable processing; Herbal medicines; Herbal essences; Gifts and housewares; Metalcraft (Industrial equipment, Engines, Surgical instruments, Agricultural machinery, tools); Service Facilities (Packaging, Warehousing, Trucking services, dryers); Electronics (Consumer electronics, Telecommunications, Computers &amp; peripherals, Semi-conductors); and Garments and footwear; Agriculture; Fishing; Forestry; Tourism.

* '''Financial Institutions:''' Banking institutions maintain an extensive branch network in Laguna. Commercial banks, savings and mortgage banks, private development banks, stock savings and loan associations, and rural banks operated a total of 267 branches in the province.
[[Non-bank financial institution]]s provide supplementary financial services to Laguna residents and businesses. A total of 394 offices have been set up by lending investors, pawnshops, financial companies, nonstock savings and loan associations, and investment houses with quasi-banking functions.

* '''Exports:''' US$7.0 Billion (1997) out of total Philippine exports of $25 Billion
US$1.5 billion (1996)

===Political===
Laguna is subdivided into 25 [[Philippine municipality|municipalities]] and 5 [[Cities of the Philippines|cities]].

====Cities====
{| class=&quot;wikitable&quot;
|- bgcolor=#cccccc
! colspan=1 | [[Cities of the Philippines|City]] !! Type !! District !! Population&lt;br /&gt;(2007) !! Mayors !! No. of Barangays 
|-
|[[Biñan City]]
|[[Cities of the Philippines#Income classification|1st Class City]]
|[[Legislative districts of Laguna#1st District|1st District]]
|262,735
|Marlyn Alonte-Naguiat
|24
|-
|[[Calamba City]]
|[[Cities of the Philippines#Income classification|1st Class City]]
|[[Legislative districts of Laguna#2nd District|2nd District]]
|360,281
|[[Jun Chipeco, Jr.|Joaquin M. Chipeco Jr.]]
|54
|-
|[[San Pablo City]] 
|[[Cities of the Philippines#Income classification|1st Class City]]
|[[Legislative districts of Laguna#3rd District|3rd District]] 
|237,259
|[[Vicente B. Amante]]
|80
|-
|[[Santa Rosa City]]
|[[Cities of the Philippines#Income classification|1st Class City]]
|[[Legislative districts of Laguna#1st District|1st District]]
|266,943
|Arlene Arcillas-Nazareno
|18
|-
! style=&quot;background: gray&quot; |
! style=&quot;background: gray&quot; |
! style=&quot;background: gray&quot; |
! style=&quot;background: gray&quot; |
! style=&quot;background: gray&quot; |
! style=&quot;background: gray&quot; |
|-
|[[Los Baños, Laguna|Los Baños]]{{ref|Los Baños|1}}
|Nature and Science City of the Philippines
|[[Legislative districts of Laguna#2nd District|2nd District]]    
|98,631
|Anthony Genuino
|14
|-
|[[San Pedro, Laguna|San Pedro]]{{ref|San Pedro|2}}
|Cityhood Process
|[[Legislative districts of Laguna#1st District|1st District]]
|281,808
|Calixto Cataquiz
|20
|-
|[[Cabuyao, Laguna|Cabuyao]]{{ref|Cabuyao|3}}
|Cityhood Process
|[[Legislative districts of Laguna#2nd District|2nd District]]
|205,367
|Isidro L. Hemedes, Jr.
|18
|-
|}
{{refbegin}}
:{{ref|Los Baños|1}} Los Baños is one of the Special Zones of [[Laguna, Philippines|Laguna]] and declared as Nature and Science City of the Philippines. &lt;small&gt;(considered as a municipality.)&lt;/small&gt;
:{{ref|San Pedro|2}} San Pedro is declared as the Rooster City of the Philippines and the Sampaguita Capital of the Philippines. &lt;small&gt;(considered as a municipality and under the cityhood process.)&lt;/small&gt;
:{{ref|Cabuyao|3}} Cabuyao Cityhood is already filed to the senate. &lt;small&gt;(considered as a municipality and under the cityhood process.)&lt;/small&gt;
{{refend}}

====Municipalities====
{| class=&quot;wikitable&quot;
|- bgcolor=#cccccc
! colspan=1 | [[Municipalities of the Philippines|Municipality]] !! Type !! District !! Population&lt;br /&gt;(2007) !! Mayors !! No. of Barangays
|-
|[[Alaminos, Laguna|Alaminos]]
|3rd Class
|[[Legislative districts of Laguna#3rd District|3rd District]]
|40,380
|Eladio Magampon, M.D.
|15
|-
|[[Bay, Laguna|Bay]]
|2nd Class
|[[Legislative districts of Laguna#2nd District|2nd District]]
|50,756
|Jose Ortiz Padrid
|15
|-
|[[Calauan, Laguna|Calauan]]
|3rd Class
|[[Legislative districts of Laguna#3rd District|3rd District]]
|54,248
|Felisa  L. Berris
|17
|-
|[[Cavinti, Laguna|Cavinti]]
|4th Class
|[[Legislative districts of Laguna#4th District|4th District]]
|20,469
|Florcelie Esguerra
|19
|-
|[[Famy, Laguna|Famy]]
|5th Class
|[[Legislative districts of Laguna#4th District|4th District]]
|13,577
|Renonia B. Muramatsu
|20
|-
|[[Kalayaan, Laguna|Kalayaan]]
|5th Class
|[[Legislative districts of Laguna#4th District|4th District]]
|21,203
|Teodoro Adao, Jr.
|3
|-
|[[Liliw, Laguna|Liliw]]
|4th Class
|[[Legislative districts of Laguna#3rd District|3rd District]]
|32,727
|Cesar C. Sulibit
|33
|-
|[[Luisiana, Laguna|Luisiana]]
|4th Class
|[[Legislative districts of Laguna#4th District|4th District]]
|19,255
|Manuel R. Rondilla
|23
|-
|[[Lumban, Laguna|Lumban]]
|3rd Class
|[[Legislative districts of Laguna#4th District|4th District]]
|28,443
|Wilfredo O. Paraiso
|16
|-
|[[Mabitac, Laguna|Mabitac]]
|5th Class
|[[Legislative districts of Laguna#4th District|4th District]]
|17,608
|Gerardo C. Fader
|15
|-
|[[Magdalena, Laguna|Magdalena]]
|5th Class
|[[Legislative districts of Laguna#4th District|4th District]]
|20,204
|Teresa Nieva B. Reodica
|24
|-
|[[Majayjay, Laguna|Majayjay]]
|4th Class
|[[Legislative districts of Laguna#4th District|4th District]]
|23,681
|Teofilo C. Guerra
|40
|-
|[[Nagcarlan, Laguna|Nagcarlan]]
|3rd Class
|[[Legislative districts of Laguna#3rd District|3rd District]]
|57,070
|Nelson Osuna
|52
|-
|[[Paete, Laguna|Paete]]
|4th Class
|[[Legislative districts of Laguna#4th District|4th District]]
|24,696
|Emmanuel B. Cadayona
|9
|-
|[[Pagsanjan, Laguna|Pagsanjan]]
|2nd Class
|[[Legislative districts of Laguna#4th District|4th District]]
|35,944
|Girlie Ejercito 
|16
|-
|[[Pakil, Laguna|Pakil]]
|5th Class
|[[Legislative districts of Laguna#4th District|4th District]]
|20,242
|Vipops R. Martinez
|13
|-
|[[Pangil, Laguna|Pangil]]
|4th Class
|[[Legislative districts of Laguna#4th District|4th District]]
|23,421
|Juanita C. Manzana
|8
|-
|[[Pila, Laguna|Pila]]
|4th Class
|[[Legislative districts of Laguna#4th District|4th District]]
|44,227
|Edgardo A. Ramos
|17
|-
|[[Rizal, Laguna|Rizal]]
|5th Class
|[[Legislative districts of Laguna#3rd District|3rd District]]
|15,459
|Antonino A. Aurelio
|11
|-
|--style=&quot;background:#ccccff&quot;
|[[Santa Cruz, Laguna|Santa Cruz]]
|1st Class
|[[Legislative districts of Laguna#4th District|4th District]]
|101,914
|Domingo G. Panganiban
|26
|-
|[[Santa Maria, Laguna|Santa Maria]]
|4th Class
|[[Legislative districts of Laguna#4th District|4th District]]
|26,267
|Antonio Carolino
|25
|-
|[[Siniloan, Laguna|Siniloan]]
|3rd Class
|[[Legislative districts of Laguna#4th District|4th District]]
|34,877
|Juanita Realeza-Acero
|20
|-
|[[Victoria, Laguna|Victoria]]
|4th Class
|[[Legislative districts of Laguna#3rd District|3rd District]]
|33,829
|Nonong Gonzalez
|9
|}

===Physical===

Laguna lies on the southern shores of [[Laguna de Bay]], the largest lake in the country. On the southern border of the province are [[Mt. Makiling]] and [[Mount Banahaw|Mt. Banáhaw]], both are long dormant volcanoes, but still sources of geothermal energy. Mt. Makiling is popular for the numerous hot spring resorts that are found on its slopes. [[Pagsanjan Falls]], is a popular waterfall that tumbles down a deep gorge in the hills.

The eastern portion of Laguna straddles the southernmost portions of the [[Sierra Madre (Philippines)|Sierra Madre]] mountain range.

== Climate ==
The province is relatively dry from November to April and wet during the rest of the year for a small portion near the southern boundary. The other parts, west of Santa Cruz municipality, experience a dry season from November to April and rainy season during the rest of the year. The eastern and southern most portions do not have distinct season, with rainfall more evenly distributed throughout the year.

==Major attractions==
===Historical===

[[File:Nagcarlan, Underground Cemetery.jpg|thumb|200px|Underground Cemetery]]
{| class=&quot;wikitable&quot;
|-
! City/Municipality
! Name of Landmark
! Roads from Manila
! Description
|-
| [[Calamba City]]
| Rizal Shrine
| [[South Luzon Expressway|South Luzón Tollway]] - Calamba Exit via National Road to J.P. Rizal Avenue
| The Rizal Shrine is located in [[Calamba City]] and features the home of [[José Rizal]].
|-
| [[Biñan City]]
| Alberto House
| [[SLEX|South Luzón Tollway]] - Southwoods, Carmona, and Mamplasan Exits, via [[Maharlika Highway|National Road]]
| Ancestral House of Teodora Alonzo's (Jose Rizal's mother) clan.
|-
| [[Los Baños, Laguna|Los Baños]]
| Homma-Yamashita Shrine
| [[SLEX|South Luzón Tollway]] - Calamba Exit via [[Maharlika Highway|National Road]] to Los Baños
|- 
| [[Cavinti, Laguna|Cavinti]]
| Japanese Garden
| [[SLEX|South Luzón Tollway]] - Calambâ Exit via [[Maharlika Highway|National Road]] to Famy-Cavinti Road
|-
| [[Nagcarlan, Laguna|Nagcarlán]]
| Underground Cemetery
| [[SLEX|South Luzón Tollway]] - Calamba Exit via [[Maharlika Highway|National Road]] to San Pablo-Nagcarlan Road
| 
|-
| [[Mabitac, Laguna|Mabitac]]
| The Battle of Mabitac Mural, Mabitac
| Ortigas Avenue heading to Manila East Road (Rizal)
| 
|-
| rowspan=2| [[Pila, Laguna|Pila]]
| Pila Town Plaza and Ancestral Homes
|[[SLEX|South Luzón Tollway]]- Calamba Exit via [[Maharlika Highway|National Road]] to Pila
|
|-
| Pinagbayanan Crematorium
|[[SLEX|South Luzón Tollway]]- Calamba Exit via [[Maharlika Highway|National Road]] to Pila
| The [[Philippines]]' oldest crematorium.
|-
| [[Los Baños, Laguna|Los Baños]]
| Baker Hall, UP Los Baños, 
| [[SLEX|South Luzón Tollway]] - Calamba Exit via [[Maharlika Highway|National Road]] to Los Baños
|-
| [[Santa Cruz, Laguna|Santa Cruz]]
|Emilio Jacinto Shrine Burial Site, Villa Valenzuela and Santa Cruz Town Plaza  
|[[SLEX|South Luzón Tollway]]- Calamba Exit via [[Maharlika Highway|National Road]] to Santa Cruz
|
|}

===Natural===
[[File:Ausflug Falls 1992 Manila.jpg|thumb|200px|[[Pagsanjan Falls]]]]
{| class=&quot;wikitable&quot;
|-
! City/Municipality
! Name of Landmark
! Roads from Manila
! Description
|-
|[[Pagsanjan, Laguna|Pagsanjan]]
|[[Pagsanjan Falls]]
|
| The Magdapio Falls used to be called the ''Magdapio Falls'' but have become popularly known as the [[Pagsanjan Falls]] because the trip starts in [[Pagsanjan, Laguna|Pagsanjan]]. 
|-
|[[Calamba City]] and [[Los Baños, Laguna|Los Baños]] Springs
|[[Mount Makiling]]
|[[SLEX]] - Calamba Exit via National Road to Brgy. Pansol and Bucal to National Highway of Los Baños
|
|-
|[[Calauan, Laguna|Calauan]]
|Hidden Valley Springs
|
|
|- 
|[[Los Baños, Laguna|Los Baños]]
|Crocodile Lake
|City of Springs
|
|-
|[[Nagcarlan, Laguna|Nagcarlán]]
|Eight mountains
|
|It includes Mt. Atimla, Mt. Mabilog, Mt. Nagcarlán, Mt. Malauban, Mt. Lansay, Mt. Bayaquitos, Mt. Cristóbal and Mt. Banaháw.
|-
|[[San Pablo City]]
|Seven Lakes of San Pablo
|
|It includes like Sampaloc Lake, Lake Bunot, Lake Calibato, Lake Pandin, Lake Yambo, Lake Palakpakin, and Lake Muhikap.
|-
|Botocan, [[Majayjay, Laguna|Majayjay]]
|Dalitiwan River, Taytay Falls
|
|
|- 
|[[Famy, Laguna|Famy]]
|Natural Drinking Water, Mayatba &amp; Spill Way Resort
|
|Natural Drinking Water in the middle of the town proper, near Famy Municipal Hall
|-
|[[Siniloan, Laguna|Siniloan]]
|Buruwisan Falls
|
|
|}

===Man-made===
[[File:Enchanted kingdom.jpg|thumb|200px|[[Enchanted Kingdom]]]]
[[File:The Plaza Calamba.jpg|thumb|200px|The Plaza Calamba]]
{| class=&quot;wikitable&quot;
|-
! City/Municipality
! Name
! Road from Manila
! Remarks
|-
| [[Santa Rosa City, Laguna|Santa Rosa City]]
| [[Enchanted Kingdom]]
| rowspan=10| [[SLEX]] - Calamba Exit via National Road
|-
| [[Pila, Laguna|Pila]]
| Pila Municipal Museum
|
|-
| [[Los Baños, Laguna|Los Baños]]
| [[Boy Scouts of the Philippines]] Camp, [[University of the Philippines]], Los Baños
|
|-
| [[Los Baños, Laguna|Los Baños]]
| Pook ni María Makiling
|
|-
| [[Calamba City]]
| Hot Springs, Private and Public Resorts
| [[Calamba City]] has 661 resorts, respectively. Making the city as the '''Resort Capital of the Philippines'''.
|-
| [[Calamba City]]
| The Plaza Calamba
| A park along the Calamba City Hall Complex with the tallest [[Jose Rizal]] monument. 
|- 
| [[Paete, Laguna|Paeté]]
| Paete's Woodcarvings
| 
|-
| [[Cabuyao, Laguna|Cabuyao]]
| St. Polycarp Church
| A catholic church
|-
| [[Mamatid]], [[Cabuyao, Laguna|Cabuyao]]
| Diocesan Shrine of San Vicente Ferrer
| [[SLEX]] - Cabuyao Exit via Mamatid Road
|-
| [[Majayjay, Laguna|Majayjay]]
| St. Gregory Church
| A catholic church
|-
| [[Paete, Laguna|Paeté]]
| St. James the Apostle Church
|
|-
| [[Pakil, Laguna|Pakil]]
| San Pedro de Alcantara Church
|
| also known as the Diocesan Shrine of Our Lady of Turumba 
|-
| [[San Pedro, Laguna|San Pedro]]
| Centro Pacita
|
| Commercial Center in Pacita
|-
| [[San Pedro, Laguna|San Pedro]]
| Sto. Rosario Parish Church
|
|
|-
| Landayan, [[San Pedro, Laguna|San Pedro]]
| Diocesan Shrine of Santo Sepulchre
| rowspan=11| National Road
|
|-
| [[Mabitac, Laguna|Mabitac]]
| Our Lady of Candelaria
| 
|-
| [[Biñan, Laguna|Biñán City]]
| Splash Island, San Isidro Labrador Church, Biñan City Plaza
 
|-
| [[San Pablo City, Laguna|San Pablo City]]
| St. Paul the First Hermit Cathedral

|-
| [[Santa Cruz, Laguna|Santa Cruz]]
| Immaculate Concepcion Parish Church

|-
|}


==References==
{{reflist}}

==See also==
* [[Battles of the Philippine-American War]]
* [[Laguna Lake Development Authority]]
* [[Laguna de Bay]]
* [[Mount Makiling]]
* [[University of the Philippines Los Baños]]
* [[Roman Catholic Diocese of San Pablo]]

==External links==
{{Wikinews}}
{{Commons category}}
{{Wikipedia search categories |Category =Laguna (Province) }}
*[http://www.laguna.gov.ph Official Website of the Province of Laguna]
*[http://tourism-philippines.com/laguna/ Laguna Travel Guide - Tourism Philippines]

{{Geographic Location
|Centre    = Laguna
|North     = [[Laguna de Bay]]
|Northeast = [[Quezon]]
|East      = [[Quezon]]
|Southeast = [[Quezon]]
|South     = [[Quezon]]
|Southwest = [[Batangas]]
|West      = [[Cavite]]
|Northwest = [[Metro Manila]]
|image     = Ph seal laguna.png
}}

{{Template group
|title = Articles Related to Laguna
|list = 
{{Laguna}}{{Luzon lateral}}{{CALABARZON}}{{List of Universities and College Schools in Laguna}}{{Laguna Special Zones}}{{Major Malls in Laguna}}
}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Laguna (Province)}}
[[Category:Provinces of the Philippines]]
[[Category:Laguna (province)| ]]
[[Category:Luzon]]

[[ace:Propinsi Laguna]]
[[zh-min-nan:Laguna]]
[[bcl:Laguna]]
[[ceb:Laguna]]
[[cbk-zam:Laguna (provincia)]]
[[de:Laguna (Philippinen)]]
[[es:La Laguna (Filipinas)]]
[[fa:لاگونا]]
[[fr:Laguna (Philippines)]]
[[ko:라구나 주]]
[[ilo:Laguna]]
[[id:Laguna (provinsi)]]
[[it:Provincia di Laguna]]
[[pam:Laguna]]
[[la:Laguna (provincia)]]
[[mk:Лагуна (провинција)]]
[[nl:Laguna (provincie)]]
[[ja:ラグナ州]]
[[no:Laguna]]
[[pag:Laguna (luyag)]]
[[pl:Laguna (prowincja)]]
[[pt:Laguna (Filipinas)]]
[[ru:Лагуна (провинция)]]
[[sv:Laguna (provins)]]
[[tl:Laguna]]
[[tr:Laguna (il)]]
[[vi:Laguna (tỉnh)]]
[[war:Laguna (lalawigan)]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
